<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3349042" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Schizandra chinensis Baillon is a traditional folk medicine plant that is used to treat and prevent several inflammatory diseases and cancer in 
Korea, but the underlying mechanisms involved in its anti-allergic activity are not fully understood. This study was designed to investigate mechanisms 
of anti-allergic activity of a Schizandra chinensis Baillon water extract (SCWE) in immunoglobulin E (IgE)-antigen complex-stimulated RBL2H3 
cells and to assess whether gastric and intestinal digestion affects the anti-allergic properties of SCWE. Oxidative stress is an important consequence 
of the allergic inflammatory response. The antioxidant activities of SCWE increased in a concentration-dependent manner. RBL-2H3 cells were 
sensitized with monoclonal anti-dinitrophenol (DNP) specific IgE, treated with SCWE, and challenged with the antigen DNP-human serum albumin. 
SCWE inhibited β-hexosaminidase release and expression of interleukin (IL)-4, IL-13, and tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α) mRNA and protein 
in IgE-antigen complex-stimulated RBL2H3 cells. We found that digested SCWE fully maintained its antioxidant activity and anti-allergic activity 
against the IgE-antigen complex-induced activation of RBL-2H3 cells. SCWE may be useful for preventing allergic diseases, such as asthma. Thus, 
SCWE could be used as a natural functional ingredient for allergic diseases in the food and/or pharmaceutical industries. </p>

<p>In an anaphylactic type of allergy, binding of immunoglobulin 
E (IgE) and antigen to the high affinity IgE receptor (FcεRI) 
on the surface of mast cells and basophils induces the release 
of preformed intragranular mediators [1]. Mast cells and 
basophils play important roles initiating and perpetuating the 
inflammatory responses that mediate allergic reactions by 
secreting abundant levels of proinflammatory mediators such as 
histamine and several cytokines, including interleukin-4 (IL-4), 
IL-5, IL-13, and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α [2]. Mast cell 
and basophil activation is initiated when antigens with 
surface-bound IgE bind to FcεRI on the mast cell surface and 
induce degranulation and release of cytokines [3]. The rat 
basophilic leukemia cell line RBL-2H3, which expresses FcεRI, 
is widely used to study the molecular basis of mast cell activation 
[3]. This cell line has also been used to develop anti-allergy drugs </p>

<p>that reduce allergic symptoms, including steroids that have 
anti-histamine actions and anti-inflammatory drugs that inhibit 
cytokine production [2,3]. However, the effectiveness of such 
drugs is limited by their side effects. These problems have led 
to increasing interest in traditional herbal medicines that have 
been used to treat allergic diseases. As a result, more and more 
studies examining the efficacy of natural extracts and compounds 
isolated from natural extracts to prevent and treat allergic 
disorders are being performed. 
In the last few decades in Korea, China, and Japan, Schisandra 
chinensis Baillon (Korean name: Omija; English name: Chinese 
magnolia fruit) has been used by herbalists to regulate various 
pathophysiological conditions [4]. For example, it has been used 
to treat and prevent several chronic inflammatory diseases (e.g., 
asthma), hepatitis, and cancer [5] that may be the result of 
biomolecular damage due to free radicals and reactive oxygen 
species. However, the molecular mechanism by which S. </p>

<p>* The authors contributed equally to this work. 
 § Corresponding Author: Myeon Choe, Tel. 82-33-250-8645, Fax. 82-33-250-7451, Email. mchoe@kangwon.ac.kr 
Received: July 27, 2011, Revised: January 4, 2012, Accepted: February 1, 2012 
ⓒ2012 The Korean Nutrition Society and the Korean Society of Community Nutrition 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>Beneficial effects of a Schizandra chinensis Baillon </p>

<p>chinensis Baillon counters antigen-mediated allergic diseases is 
not yet understood. 
To elucidate this mechanism, we generated a S. chinensis 
Baillon water extract (SCWE) and tested its ability to inhibit 
degranulation (release of β-hexosaminidase) and allergy-related 
cytokine generation (IL-4, IL-13, and TNF-α) in RBL-2H3 cells 
stimulated with the dinitrophenyl (DNP)-specific IgE-antigen 
complex. We also determined whether gastric and intestinal digestion 
affects the anti-allergic effect of SCWE against the IgE-antigen 
complex-induced activation of RBL-2H3 cells. Oxidative stress 
is an important consequence of the inflammatory response in 
allergic diseases [6]. Thus, we also measured the antioxidant 
properties of SCWE and digested SCWE (DSCWE). </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>The following materials were purchased from the indicated 
commercial sources: PowerScript reverse transcriptase (Clontech, 
Palo Alto, CA, USA), oligo(dT) 
15 primers (Promega, Madison, </p>

<p>WI, USA), GoTaq® Green Master Mix (Promega), rat TNF-α 
ELISA kit (eBioscience, San Diego, CA, USA), ECL chemi-
luminescence kit (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA), anti-
IL-4 (mouse monoclonal antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, 
Santa Cruz, CA, USA), and anti-IL-13 (mouse monoclonal 
antibody; Santa Cruz Biotechnology). Folin-Ciocalteu reagent, 
caffeic acid, monoclonal anti-DNP IgE, DNP-conjugated human 
serum albumin (DNP-HSA), and all other reagents used were 
purchased from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO, USA). </p>

<p>Preparation of the SCWE </p>

<p>S. chinensis Baillon (fruits of Omija) was purchased from an 
herbal shop in Chuncheon-si, and was cleaned, dried and ground 
to fine power before being extracted three times with 10.7 
volumes of distilled water in a 60℃ shaking incubator for 24 
h. The extract was centrifuged, and the supernatant was filtered 
under vacuum, concentrated in a rotary evaporator, and 
lyophilized. </p>

<p>Preparation of simulated gastric and intestinal juice </p>

<p>The simulated gastric and intestinal juices were prepared as 
follows. Gastric fluid consisted of 2.0 g NaCl and 3.2 g pepsin 
dissolved in 900 mL water. The pH was adjusted to 1.2 and 
distilled water was added to make 1,000 mL. The pH of the 
gastric fluid was pH 1.2. The intestinal fluid consisted of 6.8 
g KH2PO4 and 10.0 g pancreatin in 700 mL water containing 
190 mL of 0.2 N NaOH. The pH was adjusted to 7.5 and distilled 
water was added to make 1,000 mL [7]. </p>

<p>Preparation of the DSCWE </p>

<p>The digested sample solution was prepared by the methods 
of Shon et al. [7] and Ryu et al. [8]. Lyophilized SCWE (1.0 
g) was placed in 250 mL gastric fluid and the mixture was 
incubated in a 37℃ shaking incubator for 1 h. The mixture was 
adjusted to pH 7.5 with 0.2 N NaOH before 1 L intestinal juice 
was added. Thus, the volumetric ratio of gastric fluid to intestinal 
fluid was 1:4. The mixture was incubated in a 37℃ shaking 
incubator for 6 h. The DSCWE was then placed at 100℃ in 
a water bath for 5 min and subsequently put on ice. The DSCWE 
was then centrifuged, and the supernatant was filtered under 
vacuum, concentrated in a rotary evaporator, and lyophilized. </p>

<p>Determination of total phenolic levels </p>

<p>The concentration of phenolics in SCWE and DSCWE was 
determined by a slight modification of the Folin and Denis 
method [9]. Five mL of SCWE or DSCWE (0, 100, 250, 500, 
and 1,000 μg/mL) was mixed with 0.5 mL of Folin-Ciocalteau 
phenol reagent. After 3 min, 1 mL of saturated Na2CO3 solution 
was added to the mixture. The reaction was kept in the dark 
for 1 h, and the absorbance of the mixture was measured at 700 
nm. A standard curve was prepared with gallic acid [10]. The 
total phenol content of the extract was estimated by comparison 
with the standard curve. </p>

<p>DPPH radical scavenging activity </p>

<p>DPPH radical scavenging activity of the SCWE and DSCWE 
was measured according to the procedure described by Choi et 
al. [11] with slight modifications. Different concentrations (0, 
100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) of SCWE, DSCWE, or vitamin 
C (180 μL) were mixed with 120 μL of an ethanol solution 
containing the DPPH radical (1.5 × 10 
-4 M). The mixture was </p>

<p>shaken vigorously and allowed to stand in the dark at room 
temperature for 30 min. Reduction of the DPPH radicals was 
measured by an enzyme linked immunoassay (ELISA) reader 
(VERSA max microplate reader, Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, 
CA, USA) at 517 nm. Radical scavenging activity was measured 
as the decrease in DPPH absorbance, and the inhibition 
percentage was calculated using the following equation: </p>

<p>Scavenging activity (%) = (1-Asample(517nm)/Acontrol (517nm)) × 100 </p>

<p>Cell culture and cell viability assay </p>

<p>RBL-2H3 cells were obtained from the Korean Cell Line Bank 
(Seoul, Korea) and grown in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's 
medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 1% 
penicillin and streptomycin (PEST) at 37℃ in a humidified 
incubator (5% CO2, 95% air). Cell viability was determined using 
the MTT [3-(3,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium 
bromide] assay according to the method of Chang et al. [4]. </p>

<p>Mi Ja Chung et al. </p>



<p>Gene </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>Primer 
Sequence </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Cycle </p>

<p>Annealing 
Temp. 
(℃) </p>

<p>TNF-α Forward CGGAATTCGGCTCCCTCTCATCAGTTC 
36 
60 </p>

<p>Reverse GCTCTAGACCCTTGAAGAGAACCTGGG </p>

<p>IL-2 
Forward CTGTGTTGCACTGACGCTTGTC 
38 
60 </p>

<p>Reverse CTGAGTCATTGTTGAGATGATGC </p>

<p>IL-4 
Forward ACCTTGCTGTCACCCTGTTC 
22 
60 </p>

<p>Reverse TTGTGAGCGTGGACTCATTC </p>

<p>IL-13 
Forward GCTCTCGCTTGCCTTGGTGGTC 
25 
60 </p>

<p>Reverse CATCCGAGGCCTTTTGGTTAGAG </p>

<p>GAPDH Forward ACCACAGTCCATGCCATCAC 
30 
55 </p>

<p>Reverse TCCACCACCCTGTTGCTGTA 
1) TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; IL-2, interleukin-2; IL-4, interleukin-4; IL-13, 
interleukin-13; GAPDH, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase 
2) Primers are shown 5 
3. Each cycle consisted of denaturation at 94℃ for 4 
min, annealing at each temperature for 30 s, and extension at 72℃ for 5 min. </p>

<p>Table 1. Polymerase chain reaction primer sequences and thermocycling 
parameters </p>

<p>Briefly, RBL-2H3 cells were seeded on 96-well plates. After 
growth in DMEM containing 10% FBS and 1% PEST at 37℃ 
for 24 h, various concentration (0, 100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μ 
g/mL) of SCWE or DSCWE were added to 96-well plates, and 
the RBL-2H3 cells were incubated for 24 h. MTT (5 mg/mL) 
was added to each culture well (one tenth of the original culture 
volume). After incubating for another 4 h, the precipitate formed 
was then dissolved in DMSO during shaking for 30 min. The 
extent of the reduction of MTT was quantified by measuring 
the absorbance at 570 nm in a microplate reader. The density 
of formazan formed in control cells was considered 100% viability. </p>

<p>β-hexosaminidase release assay </p>

<p>The β-hexosaminidase release assay was performed as 
described previously [3] with slight modifications. RBL-2H3 
cells (2 × 10 
5 cells) in 24-well plates were preincubated with 0.5 
μg/mL anti-DNP IgE for 12 h. The cells were then washed with 
Siraganian buffer (pH 7.2, 119 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 0.4 mM 
MgCl2, 25 mM PIPES), incubated in Siraganian buffer containing 
5.6 mM CaCl2 and 0.1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) for an 
additional 10 min, and exposed to 1 mL of 0, 100, 250, 500 
and 1,000 μg/mL SCWE for 30 min. Thereafter, the cells were 
stimulated for 2 h with DNP-HSA (10 μg/mL), which activates 
RBL-2H3 cells into producing allergic reactions. The supernatant 
(20 μL) was mixed with an equal volume (20 μL) of substrate 
solution (2 mM p-nitrophenyl-N-acetyl-β-D-glucosaminide in 0.1 
M sodium citrate buffer, pH 1.5), and the mixture was incubated 
for 1 h at 37℃. The reaction was terminated by adding 200 
μL of stopping buffer (0.1 M Na2CO3/NaHCO3, pH 10.0). The 
absorbance at 405 nm was measured with a microplate reader. 
The SCWE or DSCWE-mediated inhibition of β-hexosaminidase 
release was expressed as the inhibition percentage and was 
calculated using the following formula: </p>

<p>Inhibition (%) = [1-T (405 nm)/C (405 nm)] × 100 </p>

<p>where C is IgE (+) + DNP-HSA (+) + test sample (-) and T is 
IgE (+) + DNP-HSA (+) + test sample (+). </p>

<p>Measurement of TNF-α production by ELISA </p>

<p>RBL-2H3 cells (2 × 10 
5 cells) were primed with anti-DNP IgE </p>

<p>(0.5 μg/mL) for 12 h and treated with SCWE or DSCWE (0, 
100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) for 30 min. The cells were 
then washed with Siraganian buffer and incubated in Siraganian 
buffer containing 5.6 mM CaCl2 and 0.1% BSA. The cells were 
stimulated with DNP-HSA (1 μg/mL) for 2 h. The cells were 
used for reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-
PCR) and Western blot analyses. 
The supernatants (100 μL per well) of these cells were then 
transferred to 96-well ELISA plates and TNF-α concentrations 
were determined using a rat TNF-α ELISA kit (eBioscience, San </p>

<p>Diego, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
The ability of SCWE or DSCWE to inhibit TNF-α production 
was calculated relative to the TNF-α production associated when 
vehicle rather than SCWE or DSCWE was used. </p>

<p>RNA extraction and RT-PCR analysis of cytokine mRNA 
production </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, 
Carlsbad CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
The RNAs were then reverse-transcribed using a Superscript II 
kit (Invitrogen) with the oligo(dT)15 primer according to the 
manufacturer's recommendations. The PCR was performed with 
a GoTaq® Green Master Mix PCR kit (Promega) in 20 μL of 
total reaction mixture containing 1 μL of the RT-reaction mixture 
and 0.5 μL of each primer (forward and reverse, 15 μM). The 
PCR primers sets and the thermocycling parameters used are 
listed in Table 1. The PCR samples were analyzed electroph-
oretically on a 1.2% agarose gel containing 0.2 mg/mL ethidium 
bromide at 90 V for 1 h. The bands were visualized under UV 
light. GAPDH transcripts served as internal controls. mRNA band 
density was quantified using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SigmaGel</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Jandel Scientific</rs>, 
San Rafael, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Western blot analysis of IL-4 and IL-13 protein production </p>

<p>Western blotting was used to analyze IL-4 and IL-13 protein 
expression. The treated cells were lysed in lysis buffer containing 
0.1 M EDTA, 0.1 mM NaCl, 0.1% Triton X-100, and protease 
inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich). The protein content of the 
whole cell lysate was measured with a Bio-Rad Protein Assay 
kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). Whole cell lysates 
were separated by 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide 
gel electrophoresis and electroblotted onto polyvinylidene difluoride 
membranes (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, UK). After bloc-
king, the membranes were incubated first with mouse anti-rat </p>



<p>Beneficial effects of a Schizandra chinensis Baillon </p>

<p>(A) 
(B) 
(C) </p>

<p>(D) 
(E) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. RBL-2H3 cell toxicity to the Schisandra chinensis water extract (SCWE) and digested SCWE (DSCWE) and their antioxidant effects in a cell-free system. 
A and B, Cytotoxicity. After a 24 h treatment with various SCWE or DSCWE concentrations (0, 100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL), RBL-2H3 cell viability was determined 
by the MTT assay. C and D, Total phenol content. The Folin-Ciocalteu method was used. E, DPPH radical scavenging activity. Various concentrations of SCWE or DSCWE 
(0, 100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) were mixed with the DPPH solution and incubated at 37℃, and the absorbance change at 517 nm was then determined. The reference 
compound was ascorbic acid. Means with different letters (a-e) differ significantly from each other (P &lt; 0.05), as determined by Duncan's multiple range test (n = 4). Cell viability 
results were not significantly different (P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>IL-4 or mouse anti-rat IL-13 antibody (1:500) and then with 
horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG secondary 
antibody. The immunoreactive proteins were visualized using the 
ECL Western Blot Detection System (GE Healthcare) and the 
protein band densities were quantified using <rs type="software">SigmaGel</rs> software. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data are expressed as means ± standard deviation, and are the 
average values of three to five values per experiment. Analyses 
were performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 10.0</rs> (SPSS, 
Chicago, IL, USA). The experiments were repeated at least twice 
to confirm the results. Analysis of variance was conducted, and 
Duncan's multiple-range tests were used to determine significant 
differences between groups. The level of statistical significance 
was set to P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>RBL-2H3 cell cytotoxicity of SCWE and DSCWE, and their 
antioxidant properties in a cell-free system </p>

<p>The SCWE yield was 15.9 ± 1.6%. It is important that it 
maintains its biological activity after passing through the human </p>

<p>digestive tract for SCWE to have an effect on human health. 
Consequently, SCWE that was digested with simulated gastric 
and intestinal juices was prepared (named DSCWE). To 
investigate the effect of SCWE and DSCWE on cell viability, 
RBL-2H3 cells were exposed for 24 h to various concentrations 
of SCWE or DSCWE ranging from 0 to 1,000 μg/mL. As shown 
in Fig. 1A and 1B, RBL-2H3 cell viability was not affected by 
any of the SCWE or DSCWE concentrations. 
To determine SCWE and DSCWE antioxidant activity, the total 
phenolics levels and DPPH radical scavenging activities of 
various concentrations of SCWE and DSCWE (0, 100, 250, 500, 
and 1,000 μg/mL) were determined (Fig. 1C-E). Total phenolic 
levels and DPPH radical scavenging activities of SCWE and 
DSCWE increased in a dose-dependent manner. Although 
DSCWE did not differ significantly from SCWE in total phenolic 
levels or DPPH radical scavenging activity, both had lower DPPH 
radical scavenging activity than that of ascorbic acid (Fig. 1E). 
The phenolic content of SCWE correlated significantly with its 
antioxidant capacity (r = 0.94, P &lt; 0.0001). </p>

<p>Ability of SCWE and DSCWE to inhibit β-hexosaminidase </p>

<p>release of IgE-antigen complex-stimulated RBL-2H3 cells </p>

<p>To investigate the ability of SCWE and DSCWE to inhibit 
degranulation, we primed RBL-2H3 cells with anti-DNP IgE, </p>

<p>Mi Ja Chung et al. </p>



<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effect of Schisandra chinensis water extract (SCWE) and digested 
SCWE (DSCWE) on β-hexosaminidase release in RBL-2H3 cells stimulated by 
the anti-DNP IgE-antigen (DNP-HSA) complex. RBL-2H3 cells (2 × 10 
5 cells) in 
24-well plates were preincubated with 0.5 μg/mL anti-DNP IgE for 12 h, washed 
with Siraganian buffer, incubated in Siraganian buffer containing 5.6 mM CaCl2 and 
0.1% BSA for 10 min, and then treated with 1 mL of SCWE or DSCWE (0, 100, 
250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) for 30 min. Cells were stimulated for 2 h with 
DNP-HSA (10 μg/mL) to activate the cells and evoke an allergic reaction. β 
-hexosaminidase secretion into the supernatant was then measured. Means with 
different letters (a-f) differ significantly from each other (P &lt; 0.05), as determined by 
Duncan's multiple range test (n = 4). control, C. </p>

<p>(A) 
(B) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effects of Schisandra chinensis water extract (SCWE) and digested SCWE (DSCWE) on the expression of interleukin (IL)-4, IL-13 and tumor necrosis factor 
(TNF)-α mRNA in RBL-2H3 cells stimulated with the IgE-antigen (DNP-HSA) complex. RBL-2H3 cells were preincubated with anti-DNP IgE (0.5 μg/mL) for 12 h, treated 
with various concentration (0, 100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) of SCWE or DSCWE for 30 min, and stimulated with DNP-HSA (1 μg/mL) for 2 h. The cells were then 
washed, lysed, and subjected to reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). The IL-4, IL-13, and TNF-α mRNA levels in each sample were normalized to 
GAPDH levels. mRNA band density was quantified using <rs type="software">SigmaGel</rs> software, and the group data were averaged and plotted. Means for each gene with different letters 
(a-e) differ significantly from each other (P &lt; 0.05), as determined by Duncan's multiple range test (n = 4). Control, C. </p>

<p>treated them with SCWE or DSCWE, stimulated them with 
DNP-HSA, and measured β-hexosamididase release. Stimulation 
with the IgE-antigen complex induced the release of β 
-hexosaminidase, which was significantly inhibited by SCWE 
and DSCWE (100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) (Fig. 2A and </p>

<p>2B). Inhibition of the β-hexosaminidase release by SCWE was 
not significantly different from that in DSCWE-treated cells. </p>

<p>Ability of SCWE and DSCWE to inhibit cytokine production of 
activated RBL-2H3 cells </p>

<p>IL-4, IL-13, and TNF-α play important roles in allergic diseases 
[3]. Therefore, we determined whether SCWE and DSCWE could 
inhibit IL-4, IL-13 and TNF-α mRNA expression in RBL-2H3 
cells stimulated by the IgE-antigen complex (Fig. 3A and 3B). 
The IgE-antigen complex increased the accumulation of IL-4, 
IL-13, and TNF-α mRNA in RBL-2H3 cells, and this effect was 
significantly suppressed by treatment with SCWE or DSCWE 
(Fig. 3A and 3B). For example, treatment with 500 μg/mL SCWE 
suppressed the IgE-antigen complex-induced expression of IL-4 
and IL-13 mRNA by 8.3-and 2.8-fold, respectively compared 
to those in untreated cells (Fig. 3A). Moreover, treatment with 
500 μg/mL DSCWE reduced the IL-4 and IL-13 mRNA levels 
by 3.5-and 1.6-fold, respectively. Additionally, treatment with 
500 μg/mL SCWE and DSCWE inhibited TNF-α mRNA 
expression by 50.0-and 2.3-fold, respectively. SCWE inhibited 
IL-4 and TNF-α mRNA production slightly more potently than 
that of DSCWE (Fig. 3A and 3B). 
We also investigated the effect of SCWE or DSCWE treatment 
on IgE-antigen complex-induced IL-4, IL-13, and TNF-α protein 
production by Western blot analysis (IL-4 and IL-13) and ELISA 
(TNF-α). The Western blot results were analyzed using <rs type="software">SigmaGel</rs> 
software (Figs. 4B, 4C, 5B and 5C). The data showed that 
stimulating with the IgE-antigen complex increased IL-4, IL-13, 
and TNF-α protein levels in RBL-2H3 cells, and that treatment 
with 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL SCWE reduced IL-4 and IL-13 
protein levels (Fig. 4A-C). DSCWE at 500 and 1,000 μg/mL 
also reduced IL-4 and IL-13 protein levels (Fig. 5A-C). The 
inhibitory effect of SCWE was slightly more potent than that 
of DSCWE (Figs. 4A-5C). Moreover, SCWE or DSCWE 
treatment (100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) led to a reduction 
in TNF-α protein levels, compared with that of untreated IgE-
antigen complex-stimulated RBL-2H3 cells (Fig. 6A and 6B). </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) 
(C) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effects of Schisandra chinensis water extract (SCWE) on interleukin (IL)-4 and IL-13 protein production in RBL-2H3 cells stimulated with the IgE-antigen 
(DNP-HSA) complex. The cells were primed with anti-DNP IgE (0.5 μg/mL) for 12 h, treated with various concentrations (0, 100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) of SCWE 
for 30 min, stimulated with DNP-HSA (1 μg/mL) for 2 h, washed, lysed, and subjected to Western blot analysis. IL-4 and IL-13 protein levels in each sample were normalized 
to α-tubulin levels. Protein band density was quantified using <rs type="software">SigmaGel</rs> software, and the group data were averaged and plotted. Means for each protein with different 
letters (a-f) differ significantly from each other (P &lt; 0.05), as determined by Duncan's multiple range test (n = 4). Control, C. </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) 
(C) </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Effects of digested Schisandra chinensis water extract (DSCWE) on interleukin (IL)-4 and IL-13 protein production in RBL-2H3 cells stimulated with the 
IgE-antigen (DNP-HSA) complex. The cells were primed with anti-DNP IgE (0.5 μg/mL) for 12 h, treated with various concentrations (0, 100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) 
of DSCWE for 30 min, stimulated with DNP-HSA (1 μg/mL) for 2 h, washed, lysed, and subjected to Western blot analysis. IL-4 and IL-13 protein levels in each sample 
were normalized to α-tubulin levels. Protein band density was quantified using SigmaGel software, and the group data were averaged and plotted. Means for each protein 
with different letters (a-d) differ significantly from each other (P &lt; 0.05), as determined by Duncan's multiple range test (n = 4). Control, C. </p>

<p>102 </p>

<p>Beneficial effects of a Schizandra chinensis Baillon </p>

<p>Mi Ja Chung et al. </p>



<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Effects of Schisandra chinensis water extract (SCWE) and digested 
SCWE (DSCWE) on the tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α protein production in 
RBL-2H3 cells stimulated with the IgE-antigen (DNP-HSA) complex. RBL-2H3 
cells were preincubated with anti-DNP IgE (0.5 μg/mL) for 12 h, treated with various 
concentrations (0, 100, 250, 500, and 1,000 μg/mL) of SCWE or DSCWE for 30 
min, and stimulated with DNP-HSA (1 μg/mL) for 2 h. The supernatant was subjected 
to enzyme-linked immunoabsorbent assay (ELISA). Means with different letters (a-e) differ 
significantly from each other (P &lt; 0.05), as determined by Duncan's multiple range test 
(n = 4). Control, C. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Mast cells and basophils play central roles in the immediate 
allergic reactions that are mediated by IgE and antigens [2]. 
These Th2-type reactions are precipitated when specific IgE 
receptors on the surface of mast cells or basophils bind multi-
valent allergens with surface-bound IgE. This, in turn, leads to 
the release of inflammatory mediators such as histamine and β 
-hexosaminidase, and cytokines such as IL-4, IL-13, and TNF-α 
[2]. 
Rat basophilic leukemia RBL-2H3 cells are mucosal mast 
cell-type cells and are frequently used to study the anti-allergenic 
activity of natural extracts [12,13]. When RBL-2H3 cells are 
primed with DNP-IgE, stimulation with antigen (DNP-HSA) 
induces them to rapidly degranulate and produce Th2 cytokines, 
including IL-4 and IL-13 [14]. As these responses closely mimic 
what occurs during the immediate allergic response, we selected 
the RBL-2H3 cell line, and IgE-antigen (DNP-HSA) complex-
stimulated RBL-2H3 cells were used as the allergic cell model 
for our study. 
S. chinensis Baillon is used as a medicinal plant in Asia [4]. 
In this study, we generated SCWE to examine its ability to </p>

<p>suppress the IgE-antigen complex-induced allergic activation of 
RBL-2H3 cells. SCWE contains polyphenol compounds and it 
may provide protection against an allergic response. When 
phenolic compounds are consumed in the diet, the stomach 
enhances the release of phenolic compounds in natural extracts 
[15]. Phenolic compounds are absorbed from the stomach in a 
free form [16,17] and are extensively metabolized in the stomach 
and intestines [15]. Flavonoids, the main category of polyphenols, 
are absorbed from the small intestine. Subsequently, flavonoids 
are methylated, sulfated or glucuronidated as conjugates [18]. 
Anthocyanins are very sensitive to pH and are relatively unstable; 
thus, the color changed under different pH conditions (red in 
the acidic condition and purple in the neural condition). Glycosidic 
anthocyanins are abundant at low pH but anthocyanidins 
(aglycone) are exhibited in mildly acidic conditions [18]. Thus, 
some biological activities of phenolic compounds may be altered 
by changes in the stomach due to the acidic and neutral 
environments of the stomach and intestines, respectively. It is 
thus necessary to analyze the biological properties of their 
digestion products. It is unknown whether digested DSCWE 
retains its biological activity. We subjected SCWE to digestion 
using a simulated human digestive system to determine whether 
digestion affects the functional properties of SCWE. Simulated 
saliva and gastric juices as a model system has been used in 
previous studies [7,8], so we chose the same model system to 
test the effect of artificial digestive juice on antioxidant and 
anti-allergic activities of SCWE. We found that DSCWE fully 
maintained antioxidant and anti-allergic activities compared with 
those of SCWE as assessed by total phenolics levels, DPPH 
radical scavenging activity, β-hexosaminidase release, and 
measurements of allergy-related cytokine (IL-4, IL-13, and TNF-
α) production. Our results suggest that the antioxidant and 
anti-allergic compounds in SCWE were not inactivated by gastric 
acid and intestinal juices. 
Oxidative stress is an important consequence of the inflam-
matory response in allergic diseases, and oxidative stress is 
associated with a decrease in antioxidant activity in the 
respiratory tract [6]. Thus, we first examined the antioxidant 
activities of SCWE and DSCWE and the effect of both prepara-
tions on the secretion of β-hexosaminidase in IgE-antigen 
complex-stimulated RBL-2H3 cells. These two cellular properties 
may be mechanistically related, because allergic inflammation 
is believed to be driven by the reactive oxygen species (ROS) 
that are generated by macrophages, neutrophils, and mast cells 
in response to various factors. These ROS may then promote 
degranulation of mast cells, which can be determined by measur-
ing the release of β-hexosaminidase, which is the granule marker 
of mast cells [3]. These observations suggest that compounds 
with antioxidant properties may be able to inhibit the mast cell 
degranulation that occurs during an allergic reaction. Many plants 
contain pharmacological compounds with antioxidant properties 
[19]. That such antioxidant plant compounds could have 
anti-allergy capability is supported by two recent studies showing </p>



<p>Beneficial effects of a Schizandra chinensis Baillon </p>

<p>that polyphenolic compounds from tea and coffee inhibit 
degranulation and histamine release from mast cells [12,20]. In 
our study, measurements of the total polyphenol levels and 
antioxidant activity of SCWE and DSCWE revealed that both 
increased in a concentration-dependent manner. This is consistent 
with a study showing that the total phenol content of fruit and 
plant extracts correlates well with their antioxidant capacities 
[21]. Notably, SCWE and DSCWE also markedly inhibited the 
increase in β-hexosaminidase release in IgE-antigen complex-
stimulated RBL-2H3 cells. Thus, the antioxidant activity of the 
polyphenolic compounds in SCWE may be responsible for the 
ability of SCWE to inhibit β-hexosaminidase release. 
We also examined the effects of SCWE and DSCWE on 
cytokine production of in IgE-antigen complex-stimulated RBL-
2H3 cells. It is known that various cytokines, including the 
proinflammatory cytokine TNF-α and the Th2 cytokines such 
as IL-4, IL-5, and IL-13, play critical roles in allergic 
inflammation [2,22]. IL-4 is essential for IgE production [23] 
and promotes the switch from naive T cells to allergic type Th2 
cells [24]. IL-13 affects many processes that contribute to an 
asthmatic phenotype, including inflammation, fibrosis, and mucus 
production. As a result, a number of experimental approaches 
have sought to neutralize the production of IL-13 as a novel 
therapeutic strategy for allergic asthma [25,26]. TNF-α is a potent 
inflammatory mediator that is mainly produced by activated 
various cell types in response to allergic pulmonary inflammation, 
including mast cells, macrophages, basophils, neutrophils, 
eosinophils, and epithelial cells. TNF-α is also synthesized and 
secreted by mast cells and basophils as a result of IgE and antigen 
challenge [27]. We found that SCWE and DSCWE inhibited 
upregulation of TNF-α, IL-4, and IL-13 mRNA and protein in 
IgE-antigen complex-stimulated RBL-2H3 cells. These results are 
consistent with the finding that anti-allergenic compounds such 
as thunberginol B and luteolin inhibit upregulation of TNF-α, 
IL-2, IL-4 and IL-13 mRNA after RBL-2H3 cells are stimulated 
with DNP-BSA [2]. We found that TNF-α protein levels did not 
decrease in a dose-dependent manner after SCWE or DSCWE 
treatment compared to that in untreated control cells, suggesting 
that TNF-α, a potent proinflammatory cytokine with immunore-
gulatory activities, responded strongly at low concentrations of 
SCWE or DSCWE. Quan et al. [28] reported that allergy-related 
cytokines such as IL-4 and IL-13 do not change in a dose-
dependent manner following treatment with anti-allergic extract 
(Saururus chinensis ethanol extract) and that IL-4 and IL-13 
levels decreased significantly at a doses of 10 and 100 mg/kg 
S. chinensis ethanol extract with similar levels. It is possible that 
some types of anti-allergic extracts and anti-allergy drugs may 
dose-dependently decrease allergy-related cytokines levels, whereas 
others may not. 
In conclusion, we found that SCWE inhibited degranulation, 
transcription, and translation of allergy-related cytokines in 
IgE-antigen complex-stimulated RBL-2H3 cells, and that gastric 
and intestinal digestion did not significantly alter these properties. </p>

<p>These results suggest that SCWE may be protective against 
allergic diseases by antigen-induced activation and that SCWE 
could be a beneficial food ingredient for preventing inflammatory 
diseases, such as allergic asthma. The artificial digestion system 
may use a useful model during the search for a therapeutic 
candidate against antigen-mediated allergic diseases before experi-
mentation on animals or/and humans. </p>



</text></tei>