<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3177208" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Polyadenylation of mRNA in human mitochondria 
is crucial for gene expression and perturbation 
of poly(A) tail length has been linked to a human 
neurodegenerative disease. Here we show that 
2 0 -phosphodiesterase (2 0 -PDE), (hereafter PDE12), 
is a mitochondrial protein that specifically removes 
poly(A) extensions from mitochondrial mRNAs 
both in vitro and in mitochondria of cultured cells. 
In eukaryotes, poly(A) tails generally stabilize 
mature mRNAs, whereas in bacteria they increase 
mRNA turnover. In human mitochondria, the 
effects of increased PDE12 expression were tran-
script dependent. An excess of PDE12 led to an 
increase in the level of three mt-mRNAs (ND1, ND2 
and CytB) and two (CO1 and CO2) were less 
abundant than in mitochondria of control cells and 
there was no appreciable effect on the steady-state 
level of the remainder of the mitochondrial tran-
scripts. The alterations in poly(A) tail length accom-
panying 
elevated 
PDE12 
expression 
were 
associated with severe inhibition of mitochondrial 
protein synthesis, and consequently respiratory in-
competence. Therefore, we propose that mRNA 
poly(A) tails are important in regulating protein syn-
thesis in human mitochondria, as it is the case for 
nuclear-encoded eukaryotic mRNA. </p>

<p>Mitochondria are vital organelles as they provide energy 
to the cell via the process of oxidative phosphorylation 
(OXPHOS). The 16.6 kb circular human mitochondrial 
genome (mtDNA) encodes 2 rRNAs, 22 tRNAs and 
13 essential protein components of the OXPHOS 
complexes (1). The remaining proteins of the mitochon-
drial proteome (&gt;99%), including all factors necessary for 
the maintenance and expression of mtDNA, are encoded 
by the nucleus. Both mtDNA strands (termed H and L) 
are almost entirely transcribed from the promoters located </p>

<p>in the control non-coding region. Resulting polycistronic 
RNA molecules are then processed to produce mRNAs, 
rRNAs and tRNAs (2). Human mitochondrial mRNAs 
(mt-mRNAs) released by this processing do not contain 
introns and lack any cap or modification at the 5 0 -end; 
however, they do have $50 adenosine residues added at 
the 3 0 -terminus by a dedicated mitochondrial poly(A) 
polymerase (3,4). Seven of the 13 open reading frames 
(ORFs) require polyadenylation to create a translation 
stop codon (5). 
Regulation of human mitochondrial RNA (mt-RNA) 
surveillance and turnover has not been well characterized 
thus far (6,7); also the regulatory mechanisms that control 
mitochondrial translation are poorly understood (8). 
In many systems, RNA polyadenylation plays an import-
ant role both in controlling mRNA stability and in 
modulating translation (9). The human mitochondrial 
poly(A) polymerase (hmtPAP) responsible for the synthe-
sis of the mitochondrial poly(A) extensions has been 
identified (3,4), however, inactivation of this enzyme did 
not yield a clear answer to the role of poly(A) extensions 
in the stability of mt-RNAs. The siRNA-mediated 
knockdown of hmtPAP led to shortening of mitochon-
drial 3 0 -poly(A) extensions, but this either did not affect 
the stability (3) or resulted in decreased steady-state levels 
of some mt-mRNAs (4,10). Furthermore, analysis of the 
ATP6/8 mt-mRNA (RNA14) harbouring a microdeletion 
in the translation stop codon in a patient-derived cell line 
showed that this message has shortened poly(A) tails and 
is less stable, consistent with the poly(A) tail stabilizing 
the ATP6/8 mRNA (11). Another approach based 
upon mitochondrial targeting of a poly(A)-specific 3 0 -
exoribonuclease PARN led to efficient RNA 
deadenylation; however, this had a variable effect on 
mt-mRNA steady-state levels, increasing or decreasing 
particular mRNAs with no effect on others (12). 
Another previous study showed that a fraction of the 
mt-RNA is truncated and internally polyadenylated, con-
sistent with the possibility that a poly(A)-dependent deg-
radation pathway exists in human mitochondria (13). 
Also, oligoadenylation at the 3 0 -termini has been sug-
gested to precede the addition of long poly(A) tails, 
(14,15), but to date no enzyme responsible for the </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +0044 1223 252750; Fax: +0044 1223 252755; Email: michal.minczuk@mrc-mbu.cam.ac.uk </p>

<p>7750-7763 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 
Published online 11 June 2011 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr470 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>synthesis of oligo(A) extensions has been identified. By 
analogy with the role of RNA polyadenylation in the 
cytosol of eukaryotes, poly(A) tails may also play a role 
in modulating mitochondrial translation. However, this 
potential function has received very little attention thus 
far (12). 
Deadenylase enzymes ensure changes of the lengths 
of mRNA poly(A) in order to regulate mRNA stability 
and therefore protein production. All known human 
deadenylases belong to two enzyme families classified on 
the basis of conserved nuclease motifs (16): (i) the DEDD 
family, e.g. POP2, PARN and PAN2 deadenylases and (ii) 
the ribonucleases of the exonuclease/endonuclease/phos-
phatase (EEP) family, e.g. CCR4 (CNOT6), Nocturnin 
and ANGEL (16). All human deadenylases characterized 
thus far have been localized either to the cytosol or the 
nucleus (or found to shuttle between these two compart-
ments). Therefore, the mechanism of regulation of mRNA 
poly(A) tail length in mitochondria was not known. 
We studied PDE12 because it shares sequence hom-
ology with known RNA deadenylases and in silico 
analysis predicted its a mitochondrial localization. 
PDE12 is an exoribonuclease with a preference for 
homo-adenine oligonucleotides, and removes poly(A) tail 
extensions from mt-mRNAs in vitro and in mitochondria 
of cells in culture. Deadenylation altered the steady-state 
level of some, but not other, mitochondrial mRNAs, 
which may explain earlier contradictory results of the 
effect of mitochondrial poly(A) tails on controlling 
mt-mRNA stability. We also show that deadenylation of 
mt-mRNA led to a marked inhibition of mitochondrial 
protein synthesis, suggesting that poly(A) tails modulate 
translation in mitochondria. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Plasmids </p>

<p>In order to construct the pcDNA5-PDE12.Strep2.Flag 
plasmid used to generate an inducible Flp-In T-Rex TM 
human embryonic kidney 293 T (HEK293T) cell line, 
two oligonucleotides encoding an AgeI restriction site, 
Flag and Strep2 epitope tags were annealed and cloned 
into XbaI (5 0 ) and ApaI (3 0 ) restriction sites of pcDNA5/ 
FRT/TO (Invitrogen). The resulting plasmid was named 
pcDNA5-FST2. The cDNA-encoding PDE12 (IMAGE 
clone: 4823249) was then modified by PCR to introduce 
unique KpnI (5 0 ) and AgeI (3 0 ) sites and the resulting 
fragment was cloned into pcDNA5-FST2 using the 
above restriction sites. The E351A catalytic mutant was 
generated using PCR-based mutagenesis and the resulting 
cDNA was cloned into pcDNA5-FST2 as above. For 
transfection of mammalian cells plasmid, DNA was 
purified using a Qiafilter MidiPrep Kit (Qiagen). </p>

<p>Maintenance, transfection and growth analysis of 
mammalian cell lines </p>

<p>Human 143B osteosarcoma (HOS) cells that are routinely 
used by us for immunofluorescence localization of mito-
chondrial proteins were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified 
Eagle Medium (DMEM) containing 2 mM L-glutamine </p>

<p>(Invitrogen) with 10% FBS (PAA Laboratories). For 
immunofluorescence experiments, HOS cells were 
electroporated with pcDNA5-PDE12.Strep2.Flag using 
Cell Line Nucleofector (Lonza) and buffer kit V (Lonza) 
applying programme I-13. 
The Flp-In T-Rex TM HEK293T cell line (Invitrogen), 
which allows for the generation of stable, doxycycline-
inducible expression of transgenes by FLP recombinase-
mediated integration was used to express PDE12 
.Strep2.Flag and the E351A catalytic mutant. HEK293T 
cells were grown in DMEM containing 2 mM L-glutamine 
(Invitrogen), 10% tetracycline free FCS (Autogen 
Bioclear) and supplemented with 100 mg/ml Zeocin 
(Invivogen) and 15 mg/ml Blasticidin (Invivogen). 
Twenty-four hours prior to transfection cells were split to 
10 cm plates, grown to 80-90% confluence and transfected 
using Cell Line Nucleofector (Lonza), buffer kit V (Lonza) 
applying programme A-23. Twenty-four hours after trans-
fection, the selective antibiotics hygromycin (100 mg/ml, 
Invivogen) and blasticidin (15 mg/ml) were added and the 
selective medium was replaced every 3-4 days. For growth 
on respiratory substrates, the medium contained 
glucose-free DMEM (Gibco), 0.9 mg/ml galactose, 1 mM 
sodium pyruvate, 10% (v/v) FCS and 2 mM L-glutamine. 
For growth measurements cells were plated in six-well 
plates and grown with 50 ng/ml of doxycycline in galact-
ose or glucose containing medium. Cells were harvested 
from replicate plates on alternate days and total cell 
counts made using a Neubauer haemocytometer. </p>

<p>Immunodetection of proteins </p>

<p>The immunofluorescence localization of proteins in 
fixed HOS cells were performed as described previously 
(17). The following antibodies were used: anti-Flag IgG 
(Sigma, 1:200), FITC-conjugated anti-mouse IgG (Sigma, 
1:200). Immunofluorescence images were captured using a 
Zeiss LSM 510 META confocal microscope. 
For immunoblot analysis, equal amounts of proteins 
corresponding to total cell lysates or protein fractions 
were subjected to SDS-PAGE, semi-dry transferred to 
nitrocellulose membranes, blocked in 5% non-fat milk 
(Marvel) in PBS for 1 h and incubated with specific 
primary antibodies in 5% non-fat milk in PBS for 1 h 
or overnight. The blots were further incubated with 
HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies in 5% non-fat 
milk in PBS for 1 h and visualized using ECL + 
(Amersham). 
The primary antibodies used were: rabbit anti-PDE12 
(Abcam, 1:1000), mouse anti-FLAG IgG (Sigma, 1:5000), 
rabbit anti-b-actin IgG (1:7000, Sigma), mouse anti-CO2 
IgG (1:5000, Abcam), rabbit anti-TFAM IgG (kindly 
donated by Professor Rudolf Wiesner, University of 
Cologne, 1:4000), mouse anti-GAPDH IgG (Abcam, 
1:10 000), mouse anti-Complex I subunit NDUFB8 
(MitoSciences, 1:2000), mouse anti-Complex II subunit 
30 kDa (MitoSciences, 1:2000), mouse anti-Complex 
III subunit Core 2 (MitoSciences, 1:2000), rabbit 
anti-VDAC-1 IgG (Abcam, 1:5000), mouse anti-DAP3 
IgG (Abcam, 1:1000) and goat anti-MRPL3 (Abcam, 
1:1000). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7751 </p>

<p>Secondary antibodies were: anti-rabbit IgG-HRP 
(Promega, 1:2000), anti-mouse IgG-HRP (Promega, 
1:2000) and anti-goat IgG-HRP (Sigma, 1:1000). </p>

<p>Protein purification </p>

<p>Mitochondria derived from HEK293T cells expressing 
PDE12.Strep2.Flag or the E351A catalytic mutant were 
isolated as described previously (18) and resuspended to 
8 mg protein/ml in 40 mM HEPES (pH 7.6), 10 mM 
EDTA, 4 mM DTT, 0.4 mM PMSF, 300 mM NaCl and 
protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche). Next, the 
mitochondria were lysed by mixing with an equal 
volume of 0.8% dodecylmaltoside (DDM) in water, on a 
roller at 4 C for 30 min. The lysate was centrifuged at 
1600 g max for 10 min to remove insoluble debris and the 
supernatant was loaded onto a gravity flow Strep-Tactin 
column (IBA) and the flow-through re-loaded twice. The 
column was washed sequentially with five column volumes 
(CV) of washing buffer containing 20 mM HEPES 
(pH 7.6), 1 mM EDTA, 2 mM DTT, 0.2 mM PMSF, 
150 mM NaCl, 0.05% DDM, protease inhibitors 
(Roche) and eluted six times with 0.5 CV elution buffer 
(washing buffer plus 10 mM desthiobiotin). Peak fractions 
containing PDE12.Strep2.Flag were concentrated using 
Vivaspin 2 Centrifugal Concentrators (Sartorius stedim), 
supplemented with glycerol to 20% and stored at À80 C. 
In order to assess the purity and identity of the 
Strep-Tactin purified proteins, the preparations were 
separated by SDS-PAGE, Coomassie stained and 
protein bands were excised from gels and identified by 
mass spectrometry. </p>

<p>Nuclease assays </p>

<p>The reaction substrates were prepared by: (i) 5 0 -end-
labelling of RNA or DNA oligonucleotides with T4 
Polynucleotide Kinase (New England Biolabs) according 
to the manufacturer's instructions; (ii) in vitro run off tran-
scription of PCR-generated templates [encompassing T7 
promoter (5 0 ) and 50 adenine nucleotides where appropri-
ate (3 0 )] using MAXIscript Õ T7 Kit (Ambion) in the 
presence of 0.825 mM a-32 P UTP (3000 Ci/mmol, Perkin 
Elmer] according to the manufacturer's instructions; or 
(iii) ligating the 3 0 -end of RNA oligonuclotides with radio-
active pCp (PerkinElmer) using T4 RNA ligase (New 
England Biolabs). 
The reaction mixture of 20 ml containing 5 pmoles of the 
substrate, 50 mM HEPES (pH 8.0), 10 mM MgCl 2 , 
0.5 mM DTT, 100 mg/ml BSA, 4 U of RNasin (Promega) 
and 8.5 pmols of PDE12 or E351A catalytic mutant were 
incubated at 37 C for the indicated time. The samples 
were analysed on 5-10% urea polyacrylamide gels in 1Â 
glycerol tolerant buffer (GTB) containing 90 mM Tris-
base, 30 mM Taurine and 0.5 mM EDTA. </p>

<p>Analysis of mitochondrial poly(A) by circular reverse 
transcription-PCR assay </p>

<p>Circular reverse transcription PCR (cRT-PCR) labelling 
and sequencing were used to determine both 5 0 -and 
3 0 -ends of mt-RNA as described in Tomecki et al. (3) 
with minor modiEcations. Briefly, 2.5 mg of total RNA </p>

<p>was circularized with T4 RNA ligase (New England 
Biolabs) in the presence of DNAse I (Roche) followed 
by phenol-chloroform extraction and ethanol precipi-
tation. Reverse transcription was carried out using 
Omniscript Reverse Transcriptase (Qiagen) with a 
gene-specific reverse primer, generally termed R1. Newly 
synthesized cDNA was used as a template for a PCR 
reaction, primed with R1 primer and a forward primer, 
F1. The region amplified contained the junction of the 5 0 -
and 3 0 -extremities. A second round of PCR with the 
nested reverse primer, R2, and forward primer, F2, was 
applied. Products were cloned into pCR Õ II-TOPO vector 
(TOPO TA Cloning Kit, Invitrogen) and sequenced. 
For CO2 analysis the following primers were used: </p>

<p>F1: GGTATACTACGGTCAATG, 
R1: GTTCAGACGGTTTCTATTTC, 
F2: TATAGCACCCCCTCTACCCC, 
R2: GTAGACCTACTTGCGCTGCAT and 
F2: TATAGCACCCCCTCTACCCC. </p>

<p>ND1 analysis: </p>

<p>F1: TAAACACCCTCACCACTACA, 
R1: GCCTAGAATTTTTCGTTCGG, 
F2: TACAATCTCCAGCATTCCC and 
R2: AGGAGTAGGAGGTTGGCCAT. </p>

<p>RNA isolation and northern blotting </p>

<p>Total RNA from HEK293T cells was isolated using Trizol 
(Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
For northern blots, RNA was resolved on 1% agarose 
gels containing 0.7 M formaldehyde in 1Â MOPS buffer, 
transferred to a nylon membrane in 2Â SSC and 
hybridized with radioactively labelled PCR fragments cor-
responding to appropriate regions of mtDNA. </p>

<p>Measurement of mitochondrial respiration and membrane 
potential </p>

<p>HEK293T cells expressing PDE12 were seeded at 
3 Â 10 4 cells/well in 200 ml growth medium in XF 24-well 
cell culture microplates (Seahorse Bioscience) and 
incubated at 37 C in 5% CO 2 for 36-40 h. One hour 
before the assay growth medium was removed and 
replaced with assay medium (low buffered DMEM, 
10 mM L-glutamine, 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 2 mM 
glucose), with one rinse with assay medium, and left to 
stabilize in a 37 C non-CO 2 incubator. Analysis was per-
formed in quadruplicates using XF24 Extracellular Flux 
Analyzer (Seahorse Bioscience). The wells containing cells 
were sequentially injected with 20 mM 2-deoxyglucose 
(2-DG) to inhibit glycolysis, 100 nM oligomycin to 
inhibit ATP synthase, 500-1000 nM carbonylcyanide-4-
trifluorometho-xyphenylhydrazone (FCCP) to uncouple 
the respiratory chain and 200 nM rotenone to inhibit 
complex I. Oxygen consumption rate (OCR) was 
measured for each well every 5 min before and after each 
injection. Test compounds: 2-DG, oligomycin, FCCP and 
rotenone were obtained from Sigma. </p>



<p>For membrane potential measurements, 4 Â 10 5 cells 
were stained with 100 nM tetramethylrhodamine ethyl 
ester (TMRE) (Invitrogen) in PBS for 1 h at 37 C, 
trypsinized, resuspended in PBS and analysed by BD 
LSRII flow cytometer. Debris and apoptotic cells were 
excluded from the analyses using Forward and Side 
Scatter gate. Acquired data were analysed by <rs id="software-1" type="software">FlowJo</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Tree Star, Inc.</rs>.). Experiments were performed 
for three independent transgene inductions with triplicate 
measurements based on 20 000 events. </p>

<p>35 S-methionine metabolic labelling of mitochondrial 
proteins </p>

<p>Stably transfected HEK293T cells expressing PDE12 (or 
E351A) were induced with doxycycline (50 ng/ml) for 2 or 
4 days prior to 35 S labelling. Growth medium was replaced 
with methionine/cysteine-free DMEM (Sigma) supple-
mented with 2 mM L-glutamine, 48 mg/ml cysteine and 
50 mg/ml uridine. The cells were incubated for 2 Â 10 min 
in this medium and then transfered into fresh methionine/ 
cysteine-free DMEM medium containing 10% (v/v) 
dialysed FCS and emetine dihydrochloride (100 mg/ml). 
Cells were incubated for 10 min before addition of 
120 mCi/ml of [ 35 S]-methionine. Labelling was performed 
for 15 min and the cells were washed twice with standard 
growth medium. Protein samples (30 mg) were separated by 
4-12% SDS-PAGE and products visualized and quantified 
with a PhosphorImager system with <rs id="software-2" type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Molecular Dynamics, GE Healthcare</rs>). </p>

<p>Analysis of mitochondrial ribosome profile on density 
gradients </p>

<p>Total cell lysates (0.7 mg) were loaded on a linear sucrose 
gradient [2 ml 10-30% (v/v)] in 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.2), 
10 mM Mg(OAc) 2 , 80 mM NH 4 Cl, 0.1 M KCl, 1 mM 
PMSF and centrifuged for 2 h 15 min at 100 000 g max at 
4 C (39 000 rpm, Beckman Coulter TLS-55 rotor). Twenty 
fractions (100 ml) were collected and 10 ml aliquots were 
analysed directly by western blotting. </p>

<p>Other procedures </p>

<p>Other procedures including assessing mtDNA copy 
number by quantitative PCR and the ribonuclease protec-
tion assay (RPA) are described in Supplementary Data. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In silico characterization and mitochondrial localization 
of PDE12 </p>

<p>The previously identified 2 0 -PDE protein (19), hereafter 
PDE12, contains the domain characteristics of the endo-
nuclease/exonuclease/phosphatase (EEP) family of 
proteins (PFAM: PF03372). In order to examine the 
genetic divergence of human PDE12 and other human 
proteins with the PF03372 domain we built a classification 
tree (Figure 1A). The analysis revealed that human 
PDE12 belongs to a subgroup that contains all established 
and putative human deadenylases from the EEP family 
(Figure 1A, red) as described by Goldstrohm and </p>

<p>Wickens (16). Human PDE12 shares the same general 
domain architecture (Figure 1B) and all key catalytic 
residues with other EEP deadenylases (Supplementary 
Figure S1). Furthermore, 3D homology modelling of the 
PDE12 active site based on the crystal structure of the 
poly(A)-specific ribonuclease CNOT6L (20) indicated a 
similar arrangement of the key catalytic residues (Figure 
1C and D). 
Several computer programmes that scan the N-terminal 
region of proteins for the presence of a putative mitochon-
drial targeting sequence (MTS) returned a high probabil-
ity of a MTS in PDE12 (MultiLoc -98.0%, MitoProt II 
-94%, Predotar -81%, TargetP -77% and PSORT -
75%). Moreover, PDE12 is listed in the compendium 
of predicted mitochondrial proteins ['Mitocarta', (21)] 
constructed on the basis of subtractive proteomics 
of mitochondria from different tissues, mRNA 
co-expression, transcriptional induction during mitochon-
drial proliferation, homology studies and more. Therefore, 
PDE12 represented a strong candidate for a mitochondrial 
poly(A)-specific ribonuclease. 
Indeed, while our manuscript was in preparation, 
Poulsen et al. (22) reported that a His-tagged version of 
PDE12 (2 0 -PDE) is localized in the mitochondrial matrix 
of HeLa cells (as shown by immunofluorescence, in vitro 
import of 35 S-labelled recombinant protein and mass 
spectrometry of mitochondrial fractions). Transiently 
expressed PDE12 with Flag and Strep2 tags also 
co-localizes with mitochondria, in HOS cells 
(Figure 2A), and endogenous PDE12 co-fractionates 
with the well-characterized mitochondrial matrix protein 
TFAM and the mitochondrial inner membrane CO2 
(Figure 2B). Therefore, it is now established by two 
laboratories, using four different techniques, that the 
PDE12 protein is present inside the mitochondria of 
human cells. </p>

<p>PDE12 has deadenylase activity in vitro </p>

<p>Since PDE12 contains a domain similar to deadenylases 
(Figure 1), we tested PDE12 for sequence-specific nuclease 
activity. We generated a point mutation in a putative 
magnesium-binding residue by substituting glutamate 
at position 351 with alanine (E351A, Figure 1C, cyan). 
A point mutation in the analogous residue severely 
compromised the activity of other EEP deadenylases 
(20,23). 
In order to purify the enzymes for biochemical studies, a 
Flag-and Strep2-tagged version of the PDE12 wild-type 
and the E351A mutant were introduced into HEK293T 
cells. The mitochondrial localization of the overexpressed 
wild-type PDE12 and the E351A mutant in HEK293T 
cells was confirmed by fractionation after induction of 
the transgenes for 48 h with 50 ng/ml of doxycycline. 
Both proteins were concentrated in the mitochondrial 
fraction (Supplementary Figure S2A). The enzymes were 
purified from mitochondria of HEK293T cells on a 
streptavidin-coated matrix (see 'Material and Methods' 
section). SDS-PAGE analysis demonstrated a substantial 
enrichment of the tagged proteins (Supplementary Figure </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7753 </p>

<p>S2B) and their identities were confirmed by mass spec-
trometry (data not shown). 
First, we compared the hydrolytic activity of PDE12 
and the E351A mutant using 25 nt-long, homopolymeric 
RNA (A 25 ) or DNA (dA 25 ) substrates, labelled at their 
5 0 -ends. We observed a time-dependent degradation of 
the RNA with wild-type, but not E351A mutant, 
PDE12; neither protein had any effect on DNA (Figure 
3A). The degradation of the 5 0 -end-labelled A 25 substrate 
resulted in a progressive and sequential appearance of 
RNA fragments of lower molecular mass suggesting that 
the enzyme hydrolyses RNA in the 3 0 !5 0 direction. The 
addition of a phosphate group at the 3 0 -end of RNA 
(substrate A 25 pCp) completely inhibited RNA degrad-
ation, whereas the analogous RNA substrate with a 
3 0 -hydroxyl group (A 25 pC-OH) was efficiently degraded 
by the wild-type enzyme (Figure 3A). These results 
suggest that PDE12 displays specificity for RNA 3 0 -ends 
containing a free hydroxyl group, and does not possess 
5 0 !3 0 exoribonucleolytic or endoribonucleolytic activity. 
Next, we studied the specificity of PDE12 by comparing 
the time-dependent hydrolytic activity of PDE12 on </p>

<p>25 nt-long homopolymeric RNA substrates i.e. A 25 , C 25 , 
G 25 or U 25 (Figure 3B). PDE12 preferred A 25 and U 25 as 
substrates, whereas C 25 and in particular G 25 were poorly 
degraded. The specificity of PDE12 towards poly(A) tails 
was further characterized on RNA substrates containing: 
(i) a 111 nt-long 3 0 -portion of the ND1 human mitochon-
drial gene (3 0 ND1) or (ii) the same 3 0 -portion of ND1 
containing a 50 nt poly(A) tail (3 0 ND1-A 50 ). Analogous 
substrates containing a 111 nt-long 3 0 -portion of the 
CO2 human mitochondrial gene (3 0 CO2 and 3 0 CO2-A 50 , 
respectively) were also tested. Incubation of recombinant 
PDE12, but not the E351A mutant, with the 
polyadenylated substrates (3 0 ND1-A 50 or 3 0 CO2-A 50 ) for 
30 min resulted in a size change consistent with the 
removal of the poly(A) tail (Figure 3C, compare lanes 4 
and 5 or 10 and 11). Of note, the enzyme trimmed both 
substrates $6-8 nt beyond the poly(A) tail into the body 
of the message (Figure 3C, compare lanes 1 and 5 or lanes 
7 and 11). Incubation of the enzyme with the poly(A)-less 
substrates (3 0 ND1 or 3 0 CO2) resulted in shortening of the 
message only by $6-8 nt (Figure 3C, compare lanes 1 and 
2 or lanes 7 and 8). Taken together, our results (Figure 3) </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Figure 1. Computational analysis of PDE12. (A) The unrooted classification tree of human EEP proteins. The sequences of the catalytic domain of 
all human proteins of the EEP family (PF03372) were extracted from the Pfam database (see Supplementary Table S1 for details) and aligned using 
ClustalW2. Five major subgroups identified are indicated on the tree: inositol phosphatases (orange), Sphingomyelin phosphodiesterases (grey), 
Endo-and exonucleases (green), DNase I-like proteins (blue) and Deadenylases (red). (B) Domain architecture of confirmed and putative human 
deadenylases of the EEP family. Functional domains of human proteins of the 'Deadenylases' subgroup identified in (A) are schematically repre-
sented. The position of the EEP domain is represented in each protein by a red box containing the percentage of identity between this domain and 
that of PDE12. (C and D) Comparison of the active site structure of PDE12 and other EEP deadenylases. The active site structural motif of PDE12 
(C) predicted based on the known crystal structure of the homologous EEP deadenylase CNOT6L (D) using the 3D-Jury algorithm (42) was 
modelled using the <rs id="software-3" type="software">MODELLER</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">9v1</rs> software (43). </p>



<p>indicate that PDE12 can operate as an RNase with speci-
ficity for poly(A) tails. </p>

<p>PDE12 transgene expression alters the length of RNA 
poly(A) tails in mitochondria </p>

<p>Based on the in vitro data (Figure 3), a high dose of 
PDE12 in mitochondria is predicted to shorten poly(A) 
tails. In order to determine the effect of PDE12 on 
RNA poly(A) tail length of mitochondrial transcripts, re-
combinant PDE12 or the E351A catalytic mutant was ex-
pressed in HEK293T cells. Both proteins were equally 
stable in human mitochondria (Figure 4A). In order to 
map the exact changes in mt-RNA species, total RNA 
was isolated parental HEK293T cells. The length and 
sequence of mitochondrial transcripts ND1 and CO2 
were analysed after PCR amplification, circularization, 
reverse transcription and cloning (cRT-PCR). All mito-
chondrial transcripts analyzed preserved the normal 
5 0 -end, but in approximately half of the CO2 transcripts 
the length of the poly(A) tail was reduced to 40 adenines 
or less (48 and 54% for 2 and 4 days of PDE12 
overexpression, respectively); all of the ND1 transcripts 
had poly(A) tails shorter than 40 adenines after 2 or 4 
days of PDE12 overexpression (Figure 4B and 
Supplementary Table S2). In $8 and 41% of the CO2 
and ND1 transcripts, respectively, the poly(A) tail was </p>

<p>lost completely 4 days after PDE12 induction. Similarly 
to the data obtained in vitro (Figure 3C), RNA truncation 
of the ND1 and CO2 transcripts by PDE12 did not stop at 
the beginning of the poly(A) tract, but continued for up to 
8 nt, into the 3 0 -termini of the transcripts (Supplementary 
Table S2). Some of the truncated ND1 transcripts were 
re-adenylated (Supplementary Table S2). Mitochondrial 
transcripts of cells overexpressing the E351A catalytic 
mutant were indistinguishable from those of control cells 
(Figure 4B). These data indicate that PDE12 can degrade 
poly(A) tails in human mitochondria. </p>

<p>Removal of poly(A) tails by PDE12 has different 
effects on the stability of the various 
mitochondrial transcripts </p>

<p>Because there is currently no consensus as to the role 
of poly(A) tails in the regulation of mitochondrial 
transcript stability, we studied the effects of elevated mito-
chondrial PDE12 expression (deadenylase activity) on the 
steady-state levels of all 11 mt-mRNAs by northern blot 
analysis. Induction of expression of the PDE12 transgene 
resulted in a size reduction of mt-mRNAs consistent with 
the removal of the poly(A) from the mitochondrial tran-
scripts (Figure 4C). Deadenylation had transcript-specific 
effects on the stability of individual mt-RNAs. After 4 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>e 
g 
r 
e 
M 
a 
i 
r 
d 
n 
o 
h 
c 
o 
t 
i 
M 
g 
a 
l 
F 
. 
2 
p 
e 
r 
t 
S 
. 
2 
1 
E 
D 
P </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>TFAM </p>

<p>T 
C Mitochondria 
Proteinase K </p>

<p>Fraction </p>

<p>Triton X </p>

<p>-
-
-
+ 
+ 
-
-
-
-
+ 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>PDE12 </p>

<p>CO2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Mitochondrial localization of PDE12. (A) The intra-cellular localization of PDE12 by immunofluorescence. The cDNA encoding the 
Strep2-and Flag-tagged variant of PDE12 was transiently transfected into HOS cells, the protein product was detected by anti-Flag antibody and 
visualized by secondary antibodies conjugated with FITC (green). Mitochondria were stained with MitoTracker Red CMXRos (red). Co-localization 
of the green and red signal appears yellow on digitally overlaid images (Merge). (B) Location of PDE12 in subcellular fractions. The HOS cells were 
fractionated into cytosol (C, lane 2) and mitochondria (lanes 3-5) as described 'Material and Methods' section. The mitochondrial fraction was 
treated with 25 mg/ml proteinase K in the absence (lane 4) or presence of 1% Triton X-100 (lane 5). 'T' denotes the total cell lysate. The protein 
fractions were analysed by western blotting using antibodies to endogenous PDE12. The location of PDE12 was compared with that of the following 
marker proteins: TFAM (mitochondrial matrix), CO2 (mitochondrial inner membrane) and GAPDH (cytosol). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7755 </p>

<p>days of PDE12 induction, the steady-state levels of ND1 
and ND2 mRNAs had doubled, ND3 and CytB mRNAs 
were one-third higher, whereas the levels of CO1 and 
CO2 had halved, compared to those of uninduced cells 
(Figure 4D). There was little change in the steady-state 
levels of the remaining mt-RNAs: 12 S-rRNA, 
16 S-rRNA, ND4, ND5, ND6, CO3 and ATP6/8 
mRNAs were within 15% of the starting level, after 4 
days of PDE12 induction (Figure 4D). Overexpression 
of the E351A catalytic mutant did not affect the 
steady-state level of mt-RNAs (data not shown) consistent 
with the retention of poly(A) tails (Figure 4B). Although 
PDE12 has no detectable deoxyribonuclease activity 
(Figure 3A), it might perturb mtDNA metabolism in 
some way. However, mtDNA copy number was un-
changed in cells expressing PDE12 (Figure 4E). </p>

<p>Elevated levels of PDE12 compromise OXPHOS 
function </p>

<p>Mitochondrial ATP production and OXPHOS were 
analysed in cells-expressing PDE12, or the E351A 
mutant, to investigate the consequences of the increased 
deadenylase activity on mitochondrial function. Induction 
of PDE12, but not E351A, resulted in greater acidification 
of growth media (Supplementary Figure S3), suggesting 
that elevated expression of PDE12 results in increased 
dependence on glycolytic as oppose to mitochondrial 
ATP production. Furthermore, PDE12 transgene express-
ing cells had a reduced growth rate when cultured in 
medium containing 25 mM glucose (generation times: 
PDE12 = 1.42 ± 0.06, HEK293T = 1.27 ± 0.03 and 
E351A = 1.30 ± 0.03 days) and the growth impair-
ment was accentuated when the cells' reliance on mito-
chondrial ATP production was increased by culturing 
them in medium containing galactose as the sole carbon 
source 
(generation 
times: 
PDE12 = 2.17 ± 0.13, 
HEK293T = 1.51 ± 0.04 and E351A = 1.48 ± 0.03 days) 
(Figure 5A). Overexpression of PDE12 for 4 days 
also resulted in a 35% decrease in mitochondrial </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 3. Enzymatic activity of PDE12. (A) 3 0 !5 0 exoribonucleolytic 
activity of PDE12. 8.5 pmoles of PDE12.Strep2.Flag or the E351A 
catalytic mutant purified from human mitochondria were incubated 
with 5 pmols of radioactively labelled 25 nt-long homopolymeric </p>

<p>adenosine RNA (A 25 ), 25 nt-long homopolymeric adenosine DNA 
(dA 25 ), 25 nt-long homopolymeric adenosine RNA labelled on the 
3 0 -end with pCp (A 25 pCp) or 25 nt-long homopolymeric adenosine 
RNA with cytosine ribonucleotide at the 3 0 -end (A 25 pC-OH) for the 
indicated time. The products were separated on a 10% urea polyacryl-
amide gel and subjected to autoradiography. (B) Sequence specificity of 
PDE12. 8.5 pmoles of PDE12.Strep2.Flag or the E351A catalytic 
mutant were incubated with 5 pmoles of radioactively labelled 
25 nt-long homopolymeric RNAs consisting of adenine (A 25 ), cytosine 
(C 25 ), guanine (G 25 ) or uridine (U 25 ) nucleotides for the indicated time. 
The products were separated on a 10% urea polyacrylamide gel and 
subjected to autoradiography. (C) Deadenylase activity of PDE12 on 
synthetic mt-RNA substrates. About 8.5 pmols of PDE12.Strep2.Flag 
or the E351A catalytic mutant were incubated with synthetic transcripts 
produced by run-off T7 transcription in the presence of radioactive 
UTP. The following RNAs were tested: 111 nt-long 3 0 -region of the 
ND1 ORF (3 0 ND1, lanes 1-3), 111 nt-long 3 0 -part of the ND1 ORF 
containing a 50 nt poly(A) tail (3 0 ND1-A 50 , lanes 4-6), 111-nt long 
3 0 -part of the CO2 ORF (3 0 CO2, lanes 7-9) or 111 nt-long 3 0 -part of 
the CO2 ORF containing a 50-nt poly(A) tail (3 0 CO2-A 50 , lanes 10-12). 
The products were separated on a 5% urea polyacrylamide gel and 
subjected to autoradiography. </p>



<p>membrane potential (Figure 5B). Finally, we analyzed 
steady-state levels of respiratory chain subunits, as 
OXPHOS dysfunction is usually associated with 
aberrant assembly or instability of mitochondrial respira-
tory complexes. PDE12 overexpression for 4 or 6 days 
markedly reduced the abundance of components of 
complex I and subunits of complex IV (Figure 5C). 
The observed perturbations in the respiratory 
complexes in PDE12 overexpressing cells were additional-
ly reflected by cellular oxygen consumption rates 
(OCR) that were reduced by $50% of the level of 
controls (Figure 5D). The above results suggest that 
overexpression of PDE12 causes a severe defect in oxida-
tive metabolism. </p>

<p>PDE12 transgene overexpression inhibits mitochondrial 
translation and alters mitoribosomal profile </p>

<p>In order to determine whether the OXPHOS defect in cells 
overexpressing PDE12 is a consequence of impaired mito-
chondrial protein synthesis, we labelled the de novo 
synthesized mitochondrially encoded subunits of the 
electron transport chain with radioactive methionine. 
After the inhibition of cytosolic translation, the incorpor-
ation of 35 S-Met into mitochondrial proteins was analysed 
over a time course of 4 days in HEK293T cells 
overexpressing PDE12 or the E351A catalytic mutant 
(Figure 6A). Translation of all mitochondrially encoded 
respiratory chain subunits was compromised upon the in-
duction of PDE12 overexpression and the incorporation </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Figure 4. Mitochondrial transcripts in cells overexpressing PDE12. (A) Inducible expression of PDE12 and the E351A catalytic mutant in HEK293T 
cells. Western blot illustrating a time course of expression of PDE12.Strep2.Flag or the E351A mutant induced with 50 ng/ml doxycycline. The 
PDE12 protein was detected using anti-Flag antibody; anti-VDAC-1 antibodies were used as a mitochondrial loading control. (B) Analysis of the 
poly(A) tail length of mitochondrial transcripts upon PDE12 induction. Mitochondrial ND1 or CO2 mRNAs were analysed by cRT-PCR and 
sequencing as described in 'Materials and Methods' section. Each data point represents a single clone analysed for the HEK293T parental cells 
(triangle), wild-type PDE12 (circle) and the E351A mutant (square). The length of poly(A) extensions are given on the Y-axis (note that the values 
below zero indicate transcripts that were truncated beyond the processing/polyadenylation site). Doxycycline induction times are given on the X-axis. 
The horizontal lines represent average lengths of poly(A) tails. (C) Northern blots of mitochondrial transcripts upon overexpression of PDE12. Total 
RNA from parental HEK293T cells (H), uninduced cells (0 days) and cells expressing PDE12 for 2 or 4 days (induced with 50 ng/ml doxycycline) 
from two independent experiments ('expt. 1 0 and 'expt. 2 0 ) were analysed by northern blots using probes specific for all mitochondrial transcripts. 
Nuclear-encoded 28 S rRNA was used as a loading control. (D) Quantification of steady-state levels of mitochondrial transcripts in cells 
overexpressing PDE12. The values of the relative RNA levels (mt-RNA/28 S rRNA) were obtained by quantifying PhosphorImager scans of 
northern blots using <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software and normalized for the values obtained from uninduced cells. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, ***P &lt; 0.001; 
n = 3, Error bars = 1 SD. (E) mtDNA copy number in cells overexpressing PDE12. Comparative Q-PCR of the mitochondrial CytB gene and 
single copy nuclear gene (APP) was used with total DNA isolated from cells overexpressing PDE12 for the indicated time. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, 
***P &lt; 0.001; n = 3, Error bars = 1 SD. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7757 </p>

<p>of 35 S-Met was $15% of those in uninduced cells 
(Figure 6B). Overexpression of the E351A mutant did 
not have any appreciable effect upon mitochondrial 
protein synthesis (Figure 6B). Next, we carried out 
gradient sedimentation analyses of cell extracts from 
cells overexpressing PDE12 for 4 days and control cells 
in order to investigate the integrity of the mitochondrial 
ribosome (Figure 6C). In this method, we detected the 28 S 
(small) and 39 S (large) subunits by western blotting of 
gradient fractions. We used DAP3/MRPS29 as a marker 
for the 28 S ribosomal subunit and MRPL3 as a marker 
for the 39 S subunit. The analyses of sedimentation of 
mitoribosomal subunits upon overexpression of PDE12 
revealed: (i) deficiency of assembled 28 S mitoribosomal 
subunits as compared to the control and (ii) anomalous 
sedimentation of the 39 S subunits that was shifted 
towards slower migrating species (Figure 6C). These 
changes in mitoribosomes were not due to any alteration </p>

<p>in the length of the mitochondrial rRNAs, based on 
RNase protection assays of 12 S and 16 S rRNA 
(Supplementary Figure S4A-B). Nor was the steady-state 
level or length of 7 mt-tRNAs (Ser-UCN, Leu-UUR, Thr, 
Gln, Pro, Lys and Phe) affected by elevated PDE12 ex-
pression (Supplementary Figure S4C-D). However, in the 
case of tRNASer-AGY the steady-state level of the 
full-length molecule was $60% of the control value after 
4 days of PDE12 overexpression and a species of lower 
molecular mass was detected. A similar truncated form of 
tRNASer-AGY, albeit of much lower abundance, was 
observed in control cells (Supplementary Figure S4C). 
Mutant tRNA levels considerably &gt;50% are needed to 
produce a mitochondrial translation defect (24) and 
so the observed inhibition of mitochondrial translation 
is most likely attributable to the shortening of the 
mt-RNA poly(A) tails, owing to mitochondrial ribosome 
instability and/or impaired assembly. </p>

<p>A 
C </p>

<p>D 
B </p>

<p>Figure 5. Respiratory chain function upon PDE12 overexpression. (A) Growth of cells overexpressing PDE12 on galactose and glucose media. 
Growth curves of parental HEK293 cells or transfectants-expressing PDE12 or the E351A mutant in galactose or glucose (inset) media and induced 
for the indicated time. (B) Mitochondrial membrane potential in cells overexpressing PDE12. Mitochondrial membrane potential was assessed by a 
quantitative FACS analysis of TMRE intensity. Twenty thousand cells stained with TMRE were analysed for each sample. The percentages of 
TMRE intensity were normalized to that of HEK293T cells (=100%). The mtDNA-less HEK293T cells were used as a negative control. **P &lt; 0.01, 
***P &lt; 0.001; two-tailed Student's t-test; n = 3, Error bars = 1 SD. (C) Steady-state level of the OXPHOS subunits in cells overexpressing PDE12. 
Steady-state protein level of subunits of respiratory chain complexes in uninduced control cells or cells overexpressing PDE12 or its catalytic mutant 
(E351A) for the indicated time were analysed by western blot. b-Actin was used as a loading control. (D) OCR in cells overexpressing PDE12. OCR 
measured in an extracellular flux Seahorse instrument in a quadruplicate population of control uninduced or cells overexpressing PDE12 or its 
catalytic mutant (E351A) for 4 days. The wells containing cells were sequentially injected with 20 mM 2-DG to inhibit glycolysis, 100 nM oligomycin 
to inhibit ATP synthase, 1 mM FCCP to uncouple the respiratory chain and 200 nM rotenone to inhibit complex I.** P &lt; 0.01; two-tailed Student's 
t-test; n = 3, Error bars = 1 SD. </p>

<p>7758 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>39S 
28S </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>39S 
28S </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>2 
4 
0 </p>

<p>PDE12 </p>

<p>2 
4 
0 </p>

<p>E351A </p>

<p>ND5 </p>

<p>CO1 
ND4 </p>

<p>CO3 
CO2 
ATP6 </p>

<p>ND2 
ND1 </p>

<p>CYTB </p>

<p>ND3 </p>

<p>ND4L 
ATP8 </p>

<p>PDE12 
E351A </p>

<p>-28S (DAP3) 
-39S (MRPL3) </p>

<p>control </p>

<p>PDE12 </p>

<p>-28S (DAP3) 
-39S (MRPL3) </p>

<p>incorporation of S-Met (a.u.) </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>protein level </p>

<p>[% of total signal] </p>

<p>protein level </p>

<p>[% of total signal] </p>

<p>) 
% 
0 
3 
( 
M 
O 
T 
T 
O 
B 
) 
% 
0 
1 
( 
P 
O 
T </p>

<p>) 
% 
0 
3 
( 
M 
O 
T 
T 
O 
B 
) 
% 
0 
1 
( 
P 
O 
T </p>

<p>induction 
[days] </p>

<p>ND6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
0 
2 
4 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>Coomassie 
gel stain </p>

<p>Figure 6. Mitochondrial translation in cells overexpressing PDE12. (A) Products of mitochondrial translation were labelled with 35 S 36methionine 
for 15 min after expression of PDE12 or the E351A catalytic mutant in HEK293T cells for 2 or 4 days as described in 'Materials and Methods' 
section. Mitochondrial proteins were separated by a 4-12% gradient SDS-PAGE and visualized by autoradiography. To validate equal protein 
loading, a small section of the gel was stained with Coomassie. (B) Radiolabelled products of mitochondrial translation as in (A) were quantified 
using <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software following exposure to a PhosphorImager cassette. ***P &lt; 0.001; two-tailed Student's t-test; n = 4, Error bars = 1 SD. (C) 
Mitochondrial ribosome profile in cells overexpressing PDE12. Cell lysates of HEK293T cells overexpressing PDE12 for 4 days or control cells were 
separated on a 10-30% (v:v) isokinetic sucrose gradient. Fractions obtained for control and PDE12 overexpressing cells were analysed by western 
blot simultaneously with antibodies to MRPL3 (39 S mitoribosomal subunit) and DAP3 (28 S mitoribosomal subunit). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7759 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this work, we show that the EEP family protein PDE12 
is the human mitochondrial poly(A)-specific exoribo-
nuclease. Previously, it has been suggested that human 
polynucleotide phosphorylase (PNPase), which has a 
phosphorolytic 3 0 !5 0 exoribonuclease and a poly(A) 
polymerase activity, might be responsible for poly(A) 
removal in mitochondria (14). However, hPNPase has 
been localized to the mitochondrial inter-membrane 
space, rather than the matrix where mt-RNA resides, 
and a role in processing of mitochondrial transcripts has 
been suggested, most likely by indirect means (15,25). As 
there is no published data on the presence of other 
enzymes from the DEDD of EEP family in human 
mitochondria, therefore, PDE12 is the first recognized 
human mt-RNA deadenylase. </p>

<p>PDE12 as a mitochondrial deadenylase </p>

<p>In the present study, we show that human PDE12 
degrades poly(A) tails in vitro and that elevated expression 
of PDE12 results in shortening of poly(A) tails of certain 
mt-mRNAs in human cultured cells. The previous classi-
fication of PDE12 (2 0 -PDE) as an EEP-type deadenylase 
by Goldstrohm and Wickens (16) was circumstantial; 
PDE12 was reported to cleave phosphodiester bonds in 
short oligo(A) substrates when the 5 0 -phosphates of each 
adenosine are covalently linked between either the 2 0 -or 
3 0 -hydroxyl positions (19). Until recently, the only sug-
gested biological role of PDE12 has been the degradation 
of 2 0 -5 0 -linked oligo(A) in the RNase L innate immune 
response system and its cellular localization had not 
been studied (19). While our manuscript was in prepar-
ation, Poulsen et al. (22) reported the mitochondrial local-
ization of PDE12 and confirmed that recombinant PDE12 
produced in Escherichia coli is capable of degrading 
3 0 -5 0 -linked RNA. Relatively short RNA substrates were 
used containing either (i) a 20-residue generic unstructured 
RNA sequence followed by 10 adenosine or cytosine 
residues or (ii) an RNA consisting of an 8 bp strong 
stem-loop structure followed by 10 adenosine residues. 
Longer incubation of the recombinant enzyme that 
lacked the predicted MTS with all three RNA substrates 
resulted in degradation into small fragments of 4-11 nt in 
size with comparable efficiency for all three substrates 
(22). In contrast, our studies of the biochemical properties 
of PDE12 isolated from human mitochondria show that 
PDE12 efficiently degrades poly(A) and poly(U), whereas 
poly(C) and poly(G) are not preferred substrates. Thus, 
PDE12 shares the same preference for poly(A) or poly(U) 
substrates as cytoplasmic deadenylases, such as PARN 
(26) and POP2 (27). Furthermore, we found that PDE12 
isolated from mitochondria exhibits strong specificity to 
poly(A) when relatively long substrates containing a 
fragment of endogenous human mitochondrial sequence 
(over 100 nt of the 3 0 -end of ND1 or CO2) and poly(A) 
tails of 50 nt (close to the physiological length of the tails 
in mt-mRNAs) were used. The enzyme degraded max-
imally eight residues beyond the mRNA-poly(A) tail 
boundary. Eight nucleotides was also the maximum 
number of bases removed beyond the poly(A) tail of </p>

<p>mt-mRNAs isolated from cells overexpressing PDE12. 
Therefore, human PDE12 has characteristics typical of a 
number of deadenylases: PARN, CCR4 and CAF1 
(23,28). Moreover, as no RNA was truncated beyond 
the À8 position, PDE12 is not likely to be responsible 
for a general mt-RNA decay, as previously suggested 
(22). The discrepancy between the activity of PDE12 on 
RNA reported by Poulsen et al. (22) and in the current 
study could be owing to: (i) the molar ratio of the enzyme 
to RNA (100:1 and 1.7:1, respectively); (ii) the source of 
the purified enzyme (E. coli and human mitochondria, re-
spectively); or (iii) the use of RNA substrates containing 
arbitrary rather then natural mitochondrial sequences (see 
above). 
The poly(U)-degrading property of PDE12 (Figure 3B) 
could be of biological significance, as the presence of 
poly(U) tails in human mt-RNA has been reported 
recently (15,29,30). Interestingly, the polyuridinylated 
RNA identified in these cases contained unprocessed 
upstream or downstream tRNA genes in addition to a 
protein-coding region, and therefore might represent 
products of improper processing of the polycistronic pre-
cursor. This suggests that poly(U) tails play a role in the 
degradation of mt-RNA, and that PDE12 might contrib-
ute to this process. 
PDE12 has been suggested to play a role in 
2 0 -5 0 -adenylate catabolism in the RNaseL innate immune 
response system. As all components of this pathway are 
localized in the cytosol, it is difficult to explain the previ-
ously postulated role of PDE12 in the context of its mito-
chondrial localization. It is possible, however, that an 
alternatively localized form of the enzyme exists, which 
is involved in the regulation of the RNaseL pathway, as 
suggested previously (22). Of note, degradation of both 
2 0 -5 0 -and 3 0 -5 0 -linked oligoriboadenylates has been 
reported previously for other poly(A)-specific exoribo-
nucleases (31,32) and might therefore represent a 
common property of this class of enzyme. </p>

<p>Mitochondrial poly(A) tails and RNA stability </p>

<p>Polyadenylation plays an important role in regulating 
mRNA stability in many systems [see 'Introduction' 
section and ref. (7)]. The role of mitochondrial poly(A) 
tails in controlling the stability of mRNA has been 
debated. Different approaches have been undertaken to 
address this issue in human mitochondria: (i) prevention 
of the synthesis of mitochondrial poly(A) by depleting 
hmtPAP levels with siRNA (3,4,10) or (ii) trimming 
poly(A) tails by targeting the cytosolic poly(A)-specific 
nuclease PARN to mitochondria (12). Independent 
studies of hmtPAP gene silencing reached quite different 
conclusions as shortening of poly(A) tails did not affect 
the stability of the analysed mitochondrial transcripts 
(ND3, CO3 and ATP6/8) in one study (3), whereas 
others found that the abundance of several mitochondrial 
transcripts decreased in response to hmtPAP siRNA 
(4,10). It should be stressed, however, that siRNA-
induced downregulation of hmtPAP might not have 
been complete and also the existence of a second 
polyadenylating enzyme has been postulated (33,34) that </p>



<p>would additionally complicate the interpretation of the 
results of the downregulation of hmtPAP by siRNA. On 
the other hand, mitochondrial targeting of PARN com-
pletely removed the 3 0 -poly(A) extensions of mt-RNAs 
(12). This had a variable effect on mt-mRNA steady-state 
levels, increasing some (ND1, ND2 and ND5) and 
decreasing others (CO1, CO2 and ATP6/8), whilst still 
others were little changed (ND4/4 L and ND3). 
Deadenylation of mitochondrial transcripts as a result of 
overexpression of PDE12 had a very similar effect on the 
steady-state levels of the above transcripts (Figure 4D). 
Thus, in both studies removing poly(A) tails from 
mt-mRNAs destabilized CO1 and CO2, whereas poly(A) 
addition promotes turnover of ND1 and ND2 mRNAs in 
human mitochondria, as previously proposed (15,33). 
Therefore, there is no universal role of mitochondrial 
poly(A) tails in regulation of the RNA stability, and two 
classes of poly(A) tails might exist in mitochondria that 
have opposite regulatory functions i.e. either stabilization 
or destabilization. If stable and degradation inducing 
poly(A) tails exist in mitochondria, how do animal 
mitochondria differentiate between them? Our data show 
that the efficiency of degrading of the poly(A) tails by 
PDE12 in vitro is different for certain transcripts, e.g. 
PDE12 deadenylates ND1 more efficiently than CO2 
in vitro (Figure 3C), and in cells (Figure 4B). This might 
suggest the presence of RNA 3 0 -end cis-regulatory 
elements that modulate the deadenylating activity of 
PDE12. Perhaps, the structure of the 3 0 -end of the CO2 
mRNA partially protects the transcript from 
deadenylation, which is particularly intriguing in light of 
the fact that the CO2 messenger becomes unstable upon 
removal of the poly(A) tail. In summary, our data confirm 
a previous suggestion (6,35) that polyadenylation itself is 
not sufficient to direct mt-RNA for degradation or to sta-
bilise mitochondrial transcripts and that the regulation of 
RNA turnover must depend on additional, yet to be 
identified, factors. </p>

<p>PDE12 as a regulator of mitochondrial translation </p>

<p>Our data show that PDE12 is important for regulating 
translation efficiency in human mitochondria. The 
overexpression of PDE12 resulted in decreased translation 
rates for all mitochondrial proteins (Figure 6) despite 
the fact that the steady-state levels of the majority of 
transcripts were not changed or were up-regulated 
(Figure 4D). There was an $50% reduction in the 
steady-state levels of only two transcripts-CO1 and 
CO2. However, it is unlikely that the down-regulation of 
these individual transcripts could have caused the general 
inhibition of mitochondrial translation, as published data 
indicates that a comparable reduction in the steady-state 
levels of two or more human mitochondrial transcripts 
does not lead to a global translational defect affecting 
all mtDNA-encoded proteins (36). The effect on mito-
chondrial protein synthesis is likely to result from the 
removal of poly(A) tails by the exoribonucleolytic 
activity of PDE12, rather then from a direct interaction 
of the enzyme with the mitochondrial translation machin-
ery (e.g. ribosomes or translation factors) or from an </p>

<p>indirect effect related to a defect in cell growth. This is 
supported by the lack of co-sedimentation of PDE12 with 
mitoribosomes in sucrose gradient experiments or the lack 
of interaction with mitoribosomal proteins in pull-down 
experiments (data not shown). Also, conditions that 
increase cells' reliance on mitochondrial ATP production 
exacerbated the observed growth phenotype (Figure 5A). 
No alterations were observed in the abundance of compo-
nents of complex II (containing only nuclearly encoded 
and cytoplasmically translated subunits) nor other cyto-
plasmic proteins (b-actin or GAPDH) suggesting a specif-
ically mitochondrial, rather than cytoplasmic, effect in 
cells overexpressing PDE12. Here, again our findings are 
concordant with another study in which mt-mRNA 
poly(A) tails were removed by mitochondrial targeting 
of the cytosolic deadenylase PARN or coated by 
mitochondrially targeted human cytosolic poly(A)-
binding protein, PABPC1 (12), both of which resulted in 
marked inhibition of mitochondrial translation. 
We excluded the possibility that mitochondrial transla-
tion is inhibited as a consequence of the partial degrad-
ation of mt-rRNAs by PDE12 causing instability or 
impeding the assembly of mitoribosomes. This is in agree-
ment with the observation that the 3 0 -termini of 
mt-rRNAs normally do not have &gt;1-2 nt adenine nucleo-
tides (3) and therefore might not present good substrates 
for PDE12 deadenylation. Also, we did not observe a 
marked change in the steady-state levels of the majority 
of mt-tRNAs analysed. Only tRNA-SerAGY-the 
unusual mt-tRNA, which does not fold into cloverleaf 
structure (37)-was downregulated by $40% and a 
shorter species was observed for this mt-tRNA. This 
change is unlikely to account for the dramatic (almost 
90%) translation inhibition observed after PDE12 over-
expression. As the truncated product of tRNASer-AGY 
was also observed in control cells, it might represent a 
relatively stable decay intermediate, which is more 
abundant in cells with inhibited mitochondrial translation, 
rather then a PDE12 degradation product. 
Translation is principally controlled at the initiation 
stage (rather than elongation or termination), allowing 
for rapid, reversible and spatial regulation of cellular con-
centrations of proteins. Nuclear-encoded eukaryotic tran-
scripts are polyadenylated by the nuclear polyadenylation 
machinery. Once the mRNA is transported to the cyto-
plasm, poly(A) not only stabilize RNA, but also promotes 
translation initiation. Eukaryotic cytoplasmic initiation 
factors recognize the 5 0 -mRNA m 7 G cap structure and 
the 3 0 -poly(A) tail via poly(A)-binding protein leading to 
circularization of the mRNA, which is necessary for trans-
lation initiation (38). The architecture of the mitochon-
drial translation initiation machinery resembles the one 
found in bacteria (8), and both bacterial and mitochon-
drial mt-mRNAs lack the 5 0 -end cap structure. However, 
mature bacterial messengers do not contain poly(A) tails 
as polyadenylation consistently promotes mRNA degrad-
ation in prokaryotes. If, by analogy to Eukaryota, mito-
chondrial poly(A) tails play a role in translation initiation 
their removal might primarily affect the stability of the 
28 S small ribosomal subunit as this subunit binds 
mRNA prior to assembly of the 55 S mitoribosome (39). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7761 </p>

<p>This would be consistent with the results of our analysis of 
mitoribosomal sedimentation on isokinetic density gradi-
ents that shows the steady-state level of the 28 S subunit 
was notably lower in cells, in which mt-mRNAs were 
deadenylated by PDE12 overexpression. 
The exonucleolytic activity of PDE12 can extend several 
nucleotides beyond the processing/polyadenylation site 
(Figures 3C and 4B). This observation brings about an 
alternative explanation of how polyadenylation could in-
fluence mitochondrial translation. For 7 of 13 mitochon-
drial ORFs (ND1, ND2 ND3, ND4, CytB, CO3 and 
ATP6) removal of several terminal ribonucleotides (e.g. 
eight as seen for the ND1 mRNA) would result in trun-
cation of a translation stop codon and at least two 
protein-coding triplets. This might be sufficient to inhibit 
translation owing to mitoribosome stalling. Studies of 
bacterial and eukaryotic systems have identified several 
mechanisms of regulatory stalling of ribosomes that 
inhibits protein synthesis (40,41). However, the remaining 
six mitochondrial transcripts, ND4L, ND5, ND6, CO1, 
CO2 and ATP8, contain 3 0 -UTRs prior to poly(A) exten-
sion that are long enough to ensure the presence of an 
entire ORF, even after the removal of 8 nt. Nonetheless, 
notably lowered steady-state levels of deadenylated 
mRNAs-encoding CO1, CO2 and ATP6/8 were 
observed in our experiments (Figure 4C) and have been 
reported previously by others (4,10,12). Therefore, the 
deadenylation-mediated inhibition of mitochondrial trans-
lation could depend on two simultaneous events: removal 
of the last 2-3 codons from the 3 0 -ends causing ribosome 
stalling and destabilization of mRNAs containing 
3 0 -UTRs. 
In summary, our study identifies PDE12 as an RNase 
that is directly involved in the regulation of mRNA 
poly(A) tail lengths in mitochondria. Our results also 
underscore the importance of poly(A) tails in modulation 
of mitochondrial gene expression and suggest that in 
addition to being required for completing the termination 
codon of seven mitochondrial ORFs, they also play a role 
in mitochondrial protein synthesis. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to thank Ian Holt for stimulating discus-
sions and help with the manuscript. We are also grateful 
to Marcin Pekalski for his help with the FACS analysis. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Medical Research 
Council. Funding for open access charge: MRC. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7763 </p>

</text></tei>