<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3220261" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the 
terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-
Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Purpose: To investigate the effects of music therapy on depressive mood and anx-
iety in post-stroke patients and evaluate satisfaction levels of patients and caregiv-
ers. Materials and Methods: Eighteen post-stroke patients, within six months of 
onset and mini mental status examination score of over 20, participated in this study. 
Patients were divided into music and control groups. The experimental group partic-
ipated in the music therapy program for four weeks. Psychological status was 
evaluated with the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI) and Beck Depression Inventory 
(BDI) before and after music therapy. Satisfaction with music therapy was evaluat-
ed by a questionnaire. Results: BAI and BDI scores showed a greater decrease in 
the music group than the control group after music therapy, but only the decrease 
of BDI scores were statistically significant (p=0.048). Music therapy satisfaction 
in patients and caregivers was affirmative. Conclusion: Music therapy has a posi-
tive effect on mood in post-stroke patients and may be beneficial for mood im-
provement with stroke. These results are encouraging, but further studies are need-
ed in this field. </p>

<p>Music therapy appears to affect physiological phenomena such as blood pressure, 
heartbeat, respiration, and mydriasis as well as emotional aspects such as mood 
and feelings. 1 Clinical studies in adults also demonstrated correlations between the 
physiological and emotional stimulation effects of music. 2 Clair found that music 
induced adjustment of respiratory rhythm, relaxation of muscular stiffness, de-
crease of heart rate and blood pressure by formation of a comfortable atmosphere, 
and alleviation of tension by increased alpha waves in the brain, and bright showed 
significant effects of music on the reduction of depression and anxiety indices in 
patients with respiratory diseases, rehabilitation, and cranial nerve diseases. 
Post-stroke depression is reported to be present in 32.9-35.9% of stroke patients, 
which is significantly higher than the prevalence of depression in the general pop-
ulation (10%). 3,4 Post-stroke depression is known to be related to cognitive dys-</p>

<p>Dong Soo Kim, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 52 Number 6 November 2011 </p>



<p>cordance with the physical strength and individual charac-
teristics of patients. The session consisted of a hello song 
and sharing of events in their lives (5 minutes); planned mu-
sical activities (30 minutes) including respiration and pho-
nation, improvised play, hand bell play, singing, songwrit-
ing, and expression in tune with music; and sharing of 
feelings and a goodbye song (5 minutes). Keyboards, hand 
bells, percussion instruments, flutes, and other tools such as 
picture cards, flowers, and fruit scents were used in accor-
dance with the planned activities. Patients were encouraged 
to improvise depending on their feelings and sing children's 
and folk songs. 
The Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) and Beck Anxiety 
Inventory (BAI) tests were performed for the music and 
control groups before and after treatment to determine the 
effect of music therapy on psychological status. A question-
naire was conducted on the change in psychological status 
after treatment and satisfaction level in patients who re-
ceived music therapy and their caregivers. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
Group differences in age, MMSE and pretest BAI/BDI score 
between groups were tested by t-test. In addition, differences 
in BDI and BAI between before and after treatment were an-
alyzed with paired t-test. The level of statistically significance 
was set at p&lt;0.05. All data were entered into the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical 
Program for Social Sciences</rs> (SPSS ® , <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>
The average age of the music group was 51.7±13.5 years. 
Eight of nine patients were males with a mean MMSE of 
27.1±2.0. The average age of the control group was 47.3± 
11.7 years, and all the patients were male with a mean 
MMSE of 25.4±2.9. There were no significant differences 
in age and MMSE between the two groups. There were 
four patients in music therapy group who took antidepres-
sants, and three patients in control group, with a ratio of 
44% and 33%. The etiology of stroke was divided by hem-
orrhage and infarction. In music therapy group, three of 
nine patients' etiology was hemorrhage, and the other six 
patients' was infarction. In control group, five patients' eti-
ology was hemorrhage, and the other four patients' etiology 
was infarction. 
The mean BAI and BDI scores of the music group before 
music therapy were 9.2 and 14.8 and those of the control </p>

<p>function and can have a negative influence on recovery of 
daily living (ADL) activities or be in close relationship to 
death. 5-8 Early diagnosis and treatment of post-stroke depres-
sion can have a major effect on the final outcome. 9 Major 
goals of treatment are to reduce depressive symptoms, im-
prove mood and quality of life, and reduce the risk of medi-
cal complications as well as the relapse of post-stroke depres-
sion. However, antidepressants are generally not indicated in 
mild forms because the balance of benefit and risk is not 
satisfactory in stroke patients. 10 
The frequency of anxiety after stroke varies from study 
to study ranging from 21% to 28%, 11-13 and prevalence and 
severity of anxiety symptoms are comparable to depression 
symptoms. Anxiety is found to have a relationship with 
quality of life in post-stroke patients. 14 
There are few studies with music therapy on mood in 
post-stroke patients, although music therapy has been used 
in rehabilitation to stimulate brain functions involved in 
emotion, cognition, speech and sensory perceptions. 15 
The goals of this study are to investigate the effects of 
music therapy on the mood of stroke patients and evaluate 
satisfaction levels of patients and caregivers after therapy. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>
Subjects in this study included 18 post-stroke patients, within 
six months of onset and mini mental status examination 
(MMSE) score of over 20, who were admitted to the Depart-
ment of Rehabilitation Medicine of Gangnam Severance 
Hospital. All patients were receiving comprehensive reha-
bilitation treatment including physiotherapy, occupational 
therapy, or speech therapy. And all patients received regular 
counseling by licensed psychotherapist. The music group 
consisted of nine patients who volunteered for music thera-
py. We selected nine patients as a control group who were 
matched for age and MMSE score to patients in the experi-
mental group. Both groups received the same comprehen-
sive rehabilitation therapy. Nine patients in the music group 
underwent a total of eight music therapy sessions twice a 
week for four weeks while nine patients in the control group 
did not receive music therapy. Exclusion criteria were cur-
rent alcohol or substance abuse and primary psychiatry di-
agnosis before stroke. The study was approved by local eth-
ical committee. 
The music therapy program in this study followed the 
40-minute music therapy format and was carried out in ac-</p>

<p>Effects of Music Therapy on Mood in Stroke Patients </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 52 Number 6 November 2011 </p>



<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Standardized music therapy is currently being used as a 
new treatment for various diseases. It is known that it im-
proves communication, linguistic development, emotional 
response, and behavioral adjustment in patients with au-
tism, 16 and improvement in the sound field, mood, and ac-
centuation method was observed in patients with traumatic 
brain injury. 17 Moreover, it has been reported that music ther-
apy significantly decreased anxiety and blood pressure in pa-
tients who underwent transurethral resection of the prostate. 18 
According to Buffum, et al., 19 music therapy could reduce 
anxiety in patients who were about to undergo angiography. 
In Lee, et al.'s 20 study, music therapy reduced anxiety in pa-
tients who received mechanical ventilation respiration. 
We investigated the effects of music therapy on psycho-
logical status in stroke patients. Both the BAI and BDI 
scores decreased in stroke patients after music therapy, al-
though only the decrease in BDI score was statistically sig-
nificant. These findings are similar to previous studies 
showing that music therapy is effective for depression. 21,22 
According to Rudin, et al., 23 music therapy allowed patients </p>

<p>group were 9.2 and 10.9, respectively. There was no statis-
tical difference between the two groups. BAI score after 
music therapy decreased in five patients in the music group 
and three patients in the control group. The BDI score de-
creased in six patients in the music group and four patients 
in the control group. The BDI score after music therapy de-
creased by average 2.3 points in the music group and in-
creased by average 0.2 points in the control group. The 
change in BDI score was statistically significant in the mu-
sic group (p=0.048), but not in the control group (Table 1). 
The BAI score after music therapy decreased by average 
0.2 points in the music group, but did not change in the con-
trol group. The changes in the music and control group 
were not statistically significant (Table 1). 
In the questionnaire for patients who received music thera-
py and their caregivers, the percentages of patients and care-
givers who answered that there was a positive psychological 
change after music therapy were 77.8% and 66.7%, respec-
tively. The percentages of patients and caregivers who an-
swered that music therapy inspired motivation and actually 
helped rehabilitation treatment, and that they would active-
ly recommend the music therapy to others were 66.7% and 
55.6% respectively. </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of BDI and BAI before and after Music Therapy </p>

<p>Case No. 
Sex 
Age 
MMSE 
BAI 
BDI 
Pre. 
Post. 
Pre. 
Post. 
Music group 
1 
M 
68 
29 
14 
13 
7 
7 
2 
M 
32 
29 
3 
2 
9 
6 
3 
M 
69 
28 
12 
13 
8 
9 
4 
M 
44 
28 
10 
9 
26 
20 
5 
M 
51 
26 
11 
14 
19 
16 
6 
F 
55 
28 
3 
3 
16 
11 
7 
M 
64 
25 
9 
7 
21 
15 
8 
M 
36 
23 
8 
9 
13 
15 
9 
M 
46 
28 
13 
11 
14 
13 
Mean±SD 
9.2±4.0 
9.0±4.3 
14.8±6.4 12.4±4.6* 
Control group 
10 
M 
59 
27 
13 
14 
10 
11 
11 
M 
25 
26 
16 
12 
14 
10 
12 
M 
42 
22 
5 
8 
10 
16 
13 
M 
58 
28 
6 
7 
9 
13 
14 
M 
57 
25 
12 
10 
11 
10 
15 
M 
38 
29 
10 
10 
16 
12 
16 
M 
58 
23 
7 
7 
8 
9 
17 
M 
45 
21 
4 
6 
10 
12 
18 
M 
44 
28 
10 
9 
10 
9 
Mean±SD 
9.2±4.0 
9.2±2.6 
10.9±2.5 
11.1±2.5 </p>

<p>BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; BAI, Beck Anxiety Inventory; MMSE, mini mental status examination; SD, standard deviation. 
The decrease in BDI scores was statistically significant. 
*p=0.048. </p>

<p>Dong Soo Kim, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 52 Number 6 November 2011 </p>



<p>music therapy stopped. Thirdly, the effect of medications 
such as antidepressants or sedatives was not considered. 
According to Dafer, et al., 28 early diagnosis and success-
ful intervention of post-stroke depression may improve 
clinical outcome and should be considered as a key to bet-
ter stroke care. In this regard, our research is a leading study 
on the effects of music therapy on mood, which may result in 
functional improvement by giving emotional support for 
stroke patients hospitalized in a rehabilitation unit. In the 
questionnaire for patients and caregivers, many subjects an-
swered that they were satisfied with music therapy and that it 
helped their rehabilitation. We found that further quantita-
tive research into the effects of music therapy on rehabilita-
tion treatment is necessary. 
This study demonstrated that music therapy can reduce 
depressed mood or have positive effects on mood in post-
stroke patients. Music therapy can inspire motivation for re-
habilitation treatment and contribute to improvement in 
daily living functions and functional level. In the future, ad-
ditional studies are needed on the effects of music therapy 
on ADL and functional level. </p>



<p>to calmly undergo examinations by reducing stress and act-
ing as painkiller during endoscopy. Furthermore, Koch, et 
al. 24 insisted that music therapy in patients who are awake 
during surgery decreased the dose of anesthetics and seda-
tives required compared to patients who did not receive 
music therapy. As shown by these studies, music therapy 
decreases depression and anxiety and is being used effec-
tively in various operations and treatments. In our study, 
distribution of BAI score in music therapy group represents 
minimal and mild level of anxiety, whether distribution of 
BDI score represents minimal to severe level of depres-
sion. 25 This differences in distribution of BAI and BDI score 
could result in only subtle improvement in BAI. 
One major advantage of music therapy is that it has a low 
possibility of side effects because it is noninvasive and does 
not use drugs. In a study on the mechanism of music thera-
py, Koelsch, et al. 26 reported that unpleasant music showed 
activation of the limbic and paralimbic systems through 
functional MRI, which are known as the center of feelings, 
but pleasant music stimulated the inferior frontal gyrus and 
Rolandic operculum which reflect working memory. These 
results show that music therapy can intervene in feelings 
through the stimulation and non-stimulation of these struc-
tures, and we believe music can enhance functional abilities 
by inspiring motivation for rehabilitation treatment through 
the improvement of depression and anxiety. 
Previous studies were just listening to music from re-
cords and had no standardized form or patient participating 
music therapy. However, our study used the 40-minute pa-
tient performing treatment method. This study is highly sig-
nificant, because this is the first to intervene the mood of 
stroke patients using music therapy, which is still virtually 
unknown in clinical field. 
Previous studies found significant differences in BDI 
scores between the control group and depression group. 27 
Similarly, significant differences in BAI scores were also 
observed between the control group and group of patients 
with anxiety or affective disorders, 25 strongly suggesting 
that lower scores of BDI or BAI indicate lower incidences 
of depression or anxiety. 
There are some limitations in this study. Firstly, the num-
ber of patients included was small, and we didn't match the 
lesion site and severity of patients' disease and function. 
And the music therapy group was consisted of volunteers, 
therefore, the study was not blinded. Placebo effect cannot 
be ruled out in the music therapy group. Secondly, we didn't 
evaluate whether the treatment effect persisted even after </p>

<p>Effects of Music Therapy on Mood in Stroke Patients </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 52 Number 6 November 2011 </p>





</text></tei>