<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3246293" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Electronic data capture of case report forms, demographic, neuropsychiatric, or clinical 
assessments, can vary from scanning hand-written forms into databases to fully elec-
tronic systems. Web-based forms can be extremely useful for self-assessment; however, 
in the case of neuropsychiatric assessments, self-assessment is often not an option. The 
clinician often must be the person either summarizing or making their best judgment about 
the subject's response in order to complete an assessment, and having the clinician turn 
away to type into a web browser may be disruptive to the flow of the interview. The Mind 
Research Network has developed a prototype for a software tool for the real-time acquisi-
tion and validation of clinical assessments in remote environments. We have developed the 
clinical assessment and remote administration tablet on a Microsoft Windows PC tablet 
system, which has been adapted to interact with various data models already in use in 
several large-scale databases of neuroimaging studies in clinical populations. The tablet 
has been used successfully to collect and administer clinical assessments in several large-
scale studies, so that the correct clinical measures are integrated with the correct imaging 
and other data. It has proven to be incredibly valuable in confirming that data collection 
across multiple research groups is performed similarly, quickly, and with accountability for 
incomplete datasets. We present the overall architecture and an evaluation of its use. </p>

<p>Mental health research conducted on human subjects involves a 
rich set of clinical, neuropsychological, and sociodemographic 
assessments. Traditionally, these assessments which result from 
face to face interactions between the researcher and the study par-
ticipant are recorded on paper. The paper forms are then passed 
at a later date to separate data-entry operators, who either scan 
the documents as graphics or use a combination of automatic text 
recognition and manual methods to enter the needed values into 
a database. This time-consuming transcription process can be a 
source of both delays and random error in large studies (Welker, 
2007; Babre, 2011). 
The process of transferring paper forms to electronic data can 
be cumbersome, confusing, and error-prone. Errors may slip past 
data-entry operators, who are not trained as raters and may not 
recognize that data is in fact illogical or missing, and the problem-
atic data may only be discovered by data-entry operators months 
or longer after the assessment is performed. Clinical trials orga-
nizations implement continuing oversight processes with regular 
audits of the paper forms, to ensure that data are being col-
lected correctly; effective, source data verification (SDV) creates 
an incredible cost in personnel time both on the part of the local 
research team and the study as a whole. Large-scale research stud-
ies without that level of personnel hours to invest in auditing or 
SDV can find that subjects may be excluded from analysis for 
an extended period of time due to incomplete data. In extreme </p>

<p>cases, some subjects' data, so costly to collect, may be entirely 
lost to analysis. In studies where it is difficult to find a suf-
ficient number of qualified subjects, exclusion of subjects may 
compromise the research. These problems can become even more 
pronounced in multi-site research protocols that use paper-based 
assessments and centralized data-entry operations (Vessey et al., 
2003). Automated methods are needed to ensure that data are 
complete. 
Electronic data capture (EDC) promises a solution: The data 
are collected electronically and can be validated at the time of 
collection, confirming logical errors or notational problems, and 
ensuring that the required forms are complete. EDC can alleviate 
the need for time-consuming audits, since each subject's data can 
be electronically audited, in a sense, at the time of collection (Kahn 
et al., 2007; Carvalho et al., 2011). The overall progress of a study 
can be monitored more closely during its actual execution and 
incomplete data identified promptly, through the integration of 
EDC methods with data management systems which track subject 
enrollment and other progress. 
Web-based forms for EDC such as those developed by <rs type="software">REDCap</rs> 
(Harris et al., 2009) are extremely useful for either clinician-or 
self-assessment, allowing the subjects to answer the questions on 
their own time in the comfort of their own home over the inter-
net, and the answers can be collated without the introduction of an 
extra transcription step. However, self-assessment may not be an 
option in some situations. In the case of psychiatric assessments, </p>

<p>Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>December 2011 | Volume 5 | Article 31 | 1 </p>

<p>Turner et al. </p>

<p>EDC in <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> </p>

<p>the clinician researcher often must be the person either summariz-
ing or making their best judgment about the subject's response in 
order to complete an assessment, as in conducting the Structured 
Clinical Interview for Diagnosis (Spitzer et al., 1992) or reporting 
the level of consciousness in a neurological assessment of a near-
comatose patient, for example. Interviewers cannot maintain eye 
contact or a comfortable interaction when there is a computer 
monitor between them, which is problematic in various studies; 
having the clinician turn away to type into a web browser may 
be disruptive to assessing body language cues or the flow of the 
interview. 
Electronic data capture methods for research that occurs in 
a medical institution to integrate health records with research 
records (El Fadly et al., 2011) can depend on internet access during 
data collection and integration. EDC methods are also needed for 
studies that need to be performed at locations without internet 
access, remote rural areas, prisons, or mental health facilities that 
do not provide computing resources and may even block internet 
access. These problems make traditional web and desktop software 
impractical for many studies, which in turn keeps these more dis-
tributed clinical studies tethered to paper forms. REDCap is one 
of the few to address this, with a "<rs type="software">REDCap Mobile</rs>" version which 
allows researchers in these situations to have encrypted laptops 
with a push-pull relationship to the centralized REDCap database 
to allow data collection while off-line (Borlawsky et al., 2011). 
A list of current EDC packages are listed in Table 1, with their 
published characteristics. Current web-based EDC solutions suf-
fer from two primary disadvantages, as can be seen: The first is 
the need to have internet access in order to function, which makes 
them unusable in remote situations such as those noted above, with 
the exception of <rs type="software">REDCap</rs>. The second is that many of them are 
integrated into select data management systems. To use a specific 
EDC system one must also use a specific database and presumably 
port any pre-existing data into it. This is less attractive when the 
research group has a mature data management system in place for 
their neuroimaging data, and is looking to add EDC for clinical 
assessments. 
The solution is a system that combines the automated data 
capture of web-based self-assessment with the dynamics of a clin-
ician's expertise and needs, and the abilities to work off-line until </p>

<p>interface with an arbitrary database is needed. The Mind Research 
Network (MRN) has developed a software tool for the real-time 
acquisition and validation of clinical assessments in remote envi-
ronments: <rs type="software">The clinical assessment and remote administration 
tablet (CARAT</rs>). We have developed this tool on a Microsoft Win-
dows PC tablet system, and it has been used successfully to collect 
and administer clinical assessments in several large-scale studies. 
It has proven to be incredibly valuable in confirming that data 
collection across multiple research groups is performed similarly, 
quickly, and with accountability for incomplete datasets. Here we 
present its specifications and current availability, focusing on its 
use in conjunction with the Functional Biomedical Informatics 
Research Network (FBIRN) multi-site neuroimaging studies in 
schizophrenia, and the FBIRN Human Imaging Databases (Keator 
et al., 2008); and in conjunction with the MRN data manage-
ment system (Bockholt et al., 2010; Scott et al., 2011), a centralized 
institutional level system managing multiple federated studies 
simultaneously. It has also been applied within an <rs type="software">OpenClinica</rs> 1 
data management system (Bockholt et al., in preparation). </p>

<p><rs type="software">CARAT</rs> SPECIFICATIONS </p>

<p>The current application approached the problem of real-time 
clinical assessment entry and quality control with the following 
specifications: </p>

<p>1. Tablet hardware with convertible keyboard: Interviewers had to 
be able to hold a tablet on their laps, maintain eye contact with 
the subject, and enter data or make notes using the touch screen. 
Tablets offer a form factor uniquely suitable to an assessment 
interview. They are slim, easily carried, and shaped similarly to 
a sheet of paper or a notepad, allowing them to be held without 
attracting attention during an assessment. Touch screens allow 
for a rater to quickly select answers to questions with multiple 
choice options, and a touch keyboard is available for free-form 
questions and annotations. 
2. Internet-independence for most functions: Users needed to be 
able to work remotely, entering case report forms (CRF) data </p>

<p>1 http://community.openclinica.org </p>

<p>Table 1 | Electronic data capture systems available for clinical data capture and transmission to a database. </p>

<p>Free Open </p>

<p>source </p>

<p>Internet </p>

<p>independent </p>

<p>Database independent 
CRF </p>

<p>library </p>

<p>CRF </p>

<p>design </p>

<p>Data </p>

<p>validation </p>

<p><rs id="software-8" type="software">OpenClinica</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="url">www.openclinica.org</rs> 
Yes 
Yes 
No 
No 
Yes 
Limited* Yes </p>

<p><rs id="software-9" type="software">Clinovo ClinCapture</rs> <rs corresp="#software-9" type="url">www.clinovo.com</rs> 
Yes 
Yes 
No 
No, but it supports several databases No 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p><rs id="software-10" type="software">Study Manager Evolve</rs> <rs corresp="#software-10" type="url">clinicalsoftware.net</rs> No 
No 
No 
No 
No 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p><rs id="software-11" type="software">REDCap</rs> <rs corresp="#software-11" type="url">project-redcap.org</rs> 
Yes 
Yes 
Somewhat 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p><rs id="software-12" type="software">eCaseLink</rs> <rs corresp="#software-12" type="url">http://www.dsg-us.com/</rs>/ </p>

<p><rs type="software">eCaseLinkEDC.aspx</rs> </p>

<p>No 
No 
No 
No, but it supports several databases Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p><rs id="software-14" type="software">Medidata Rave</rs> <rs corresp="#software-14" type="url">http://www.mdsol.com/</rs>/ </p>

<p><rs type="software">products/rave_capture.htm</rs> </p>

<p>No 
No 
No 
Yes 
Unknown Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>CARAT 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>*Uses an excel template method. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>December 2011 | Volume 5 | Article 31 | 2 </p>

<p>Turner et al. </p>

<p>EDC in CARAT </p>

<p>and saving it to a central repository when the internet became 
available. 
3. Potential for interaction with arbitrary database platforms and 
schemas: From the beginning, the software needed to be able to 
both submit to and receive data from several different databases 
as used by several investigators. 
4. Real-Time Data Quality Validation: Data had to be checked as 
it was entered into each CRF for each interview or assessment. 
5. Generic engine useful for any assessment and arbitrary visit-
based groupings of assessments: The CRF metadata, including 
the questions, possible answers, data validation and required 
field information, and identifiers for upload to the database, 
had to be easily understood and expandable. CRFs may be 
changed after the study begins, or modified from one study to 
another. CRFs must be able to be grouped for initial screening 
visits and follow-up visits to follow the flow of a study protocol. </p>

<p><rs type="software">CARAT</rs> IMPLEMENTATION </p>

<p>The overall flow of information when using CARAT is shown in 
Figure 1. Clinical study setup (upper half of the figure) requires 
CRF form layout on the tablet, as well as arranging the CRFs into 
visits for each study; the data collection steps (lower half) use 
the XML representations to send the subject's responses via the 
web service back to the database. The data collection steps from 
Figure 1 are expanded in the workflow shown in Figure 2. These 
are discussed below. </p>

<p>Tablet hardware. The current version of CARAT is built in C#. 
Net and designed to run on Windows XP Tablet Edition. It also 
runs successfully on Windows 7 desktops, laptops, and slate 
tablets. </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 | The flow of information for study setup and data collection 
using CARAT. The currently usable databases are the FBIRN human 
imaging database (HID) and the MRN medical imaging computer 
information system (MICIS), but others can be modeled in the web service. 
The study definition portion determines which CRFs are required in what 
layout for which visits and subject types within the study. The CRF XML 
layout captures how the questions should be presented on the tablet and 
the validation steps required. Following the administration of the 
assessments, the subject's responses are sent via the web service back to 
the available database. </p>

<p>Internet-independence. CARAT does not require an Internet or 
database connection for the entry of new clinical data. In the 
workflow shown in Figure 2, once the CRF information has 
been created during study setup, the data collection steps that 
follow, the subject interviews and data validation, data cor-
rection, and inclusion of any additional annotations, can be 
completed without any database connectivity. When network 
access is available, the submission process can be completed: 
The completed assessments that have passed data quality vali-
dation are exported, and can be inserted into a central database 
via the web service module shown in Figure 1. </p>

<p>Linking to other databases. To ensure database platform and 
schema independence, this step is performed by a SOAP web 
service that is individually customized by a software engineer 
associated with the required database platform. This web ser-
vice need be written only once per database schema and then 
applied to all studies that are stored using the same database 
schema. Modification for communication with FBIRN Human 
Imaging Database (FBIRN HID) 2 led to the addition of the 
ability to export assessments in different XML formats. As 
shown in Figure 1, <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> can export the subject's data using 
the XML-based Clinical Experiment Data Exchange (XCEDE) 
schema, which the FBIRN HID uses to import data 3 . </p>

<p>Real-time data validation. The validation steps can be set per 
question per assessment, and can be changed for different vis-
its within a study if needed. They include checking required 
fields for completion, data type (e.g., numeric, character string, 
or date), bounds-checking (e.g., systolic blood pressure is a 
number between 0 and 300), and question dependencies (e.g., 
Question 2 "How many cigarets do you smoke a day?" does 
not need to be answered if the answer to Question 1 "Do you 
smoke?" is NO). <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> provides some complex controls like 
tree selects, and repeating groups of fields, as one might use for 
a medication or drug history. During an interview, the rater is 
notified immediately when a required field is skipped or data 
entered does not meet quality criteria, but the software does 
not require the rater to fix the data immediately. This allows 
the rater to complete the interview smoothly and fix data issues 
at a later time if necessary. CRFs that do not pass data quality 
validation may be stored on the rater's tablet and edited at any 
time, but they may not be submitted to the database until all 
issues are resolved. Examples are shown in Figures 4 and 6. </p>

<p>Generic CRF specifications. The CRF questions, possible 
answers, data validation and required field information, and 
identifiers for upload to the database, are stored in XML spec-
ification files, created from the database specifications of the 
CRF questions. The XML file also specifies traditional GUI ele-
ments, such as radio buttons and drop-down list boxes, and 
their location on the screen. Data-entry screens may then be 
created dynamically for any assessment the rater needs to use. 
The general data model is shown in Figure 3: A subject has an 
ID and a type or group assignment; a study may have multiple 
visits with varying assessments, and may be a multi-site study. </p>

<p>2 www.birncommunity.org 
3 www.xcede.org </p>

<p>Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>December 2011 | Volume 5 | Article 31 | 3 </p>

<p>Turner et al. </p>

<p>EDC in CARAT </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 | The workflow for <rs type="software">CARAT</rs>, expanding on the data collection parts of Figure 1. Following study setup, data collection can proceed through the 
needed steps of interviews, validation, correction, addition of other notes or annotations, and final submission. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 | The data model for <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> is lightweight, combining an 
individual's responses with their study-specific information and 
response validation prior to inserting the information in the database. 
The upper row indicates those parts of the model that draw from study setup, </p>

<p>while the lower row indicates the parts that are populated during data 
collection. The solid bulleted connections indicate a many-to-one relationship: 
a single CRF pulls from many questions, and a completed assessment 
includes several responses. </p>

<p>The CRF is linked to many questions, each of which contains 
the question text and the validation rules for the answers. The 
CRF, in combination with information regarding the visit and 
study, forms an assessment for that study and visit. The subject's 
responses for that assessment are tagged with the information 
about which question it came from on the CRF, as well as the 
subject, study, and visit information. </p>

<p>Both Figures 4 and 5 show data-entry screens dynamically gen-
erated from XML layout specification files. This provides flexi-
bility and frees the researchers from the management of separate 
software packages to handle different clinical assessments. 
A user-friendly method of creating electronic forms is required, 
to allow for rapid prototyping of new assessments for a study, and 
flexibility in re-use of forms. Clinicians may find that they habit-
ually rearrange the order of questions on an assessment from the </p>

<p>paper form during an interview, for example; electronic forms can 
allow this kind of rearrangement to be done to allow for a more 
natural interviewing environment. Questions that are not required 
based on the current interviewee's answers may be automatically 
and dynamically hidden. Medication categories are included so 
that drug names can be selected rather than re-typed each time 
they are used. 
In <rs type="software">CARAT</rs>, XML layout specifications for CRFs are created using 
a graphic tool that uses the SOAP web service to pull the question 
metadata from the study protocols already in the database. The 
layout tool is designed for raters or other study staff to use to 
create detailed layouts, including GUI elements and data valida-
tion, with a minimum of technical expertise. Questions may be 
dragged and dropped into a GUI form and then modified as nec-
essary. If metadata about a particular CRF question does not exist 
in a database, the metadata can be provided directly in the layout </p>

<p>Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>December 2011 | Volume 5 | Article 31 | 4 </p>

<p>Turner et al. </p>

<p>EDC in CARAT </p>

<p>FIGURE 4 | An example of a questionnaire on <rs type="software">CARAT</rs>, 
demonstrating: (1) Annotations may be stored for any question by 
clicking the pencil icon (the pencil icon then displays in green). (2) 
Data types and reasonable responses are enforced, with error 
messages available to clarify. (3) Navigation through a form can be done </p>

<p>using either the navigation tree or the buttons on the lower right corner. 
(4) Conditional skipping of questions: Here, since the participant 
answered "Yes" about English being their primary language, the 
follow-up question is not required. (5) Required fields are marked with a 
red icon. </p>

<p>FIGURE 5 | Example question with a drop-down menu and extended text. </p>

<p>tool. The layout is then exported as an XML CRF specification to 
be included in <rs type="software">CARAT</rs>. </p>

<p><rs type="software">CARAT</rs> USER INTERFACE </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> software has spent the last almost 3 years in long-
term piloting with multiple studies. During this time, it has 
been through three rounds of enhancement in response to user </p>

<p>feedback. User needs led to extensive expansion of the options 
for assessment appearance, keyboard shortcuts for studies that 
made more use of the keyboard, expansion of user preferences so 
that default behavior better matches specific study needs, allowing 
sorting and re-ordering of assessments on the fly, creating missing 
data explanation fields, turning pen use on and off as needed, and 
various other usability changes. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>December 2011 | Volume 5 | Article 31 | 5 </p>

<p>Turner et al. </p>

<p>EDC in CARAT </p>

<p>FIGURE 6 | Example of error messages to identify which questions the error occurred on, what the error was, and what page of the assessment it 
occurred on. </p>

<p>Figure 4 demonstrates some of the user interface features of 
the prototype. The prototype provides a wide variety of data-
entry methods from simple free text entry to methods of multiple 
choice that may be selected by a mouse click or a pen tap. Sup-
ported forms of data-entry include: Radio Buttons (displayed in 
Figure 4), Checkboxes, Date Selector, Extended Text Drop-Down 
Combo Box (displayed in Figure 5), Free Text Entry, and Tree 
Menus. Free text annotations may be stored for any question by 
clicking the pencil icon or tapping it with the tablet stylus. 
Navigation of lengthy CRFs on paper is often not linear; clini-
cians may skip back and forth as the flow of the interview require. 
To recreate this in <rs type="software">CARAT</rs>, users may navigate through the CRF 
pages using the arrow buttons in the lower right-hand corner, or 
they may go to a specific page using the navigation tree. 
Questions may be skipped based on the answers to other ques-
tions. For example, one question may record if the subject ever 
received a specific diagnosis. If the answer is no, then the sub-
sequent question about the diagnosis is non-applicable and is 
skipped. 
The validation of data types and reasonable responses are 
enforced using regular expressions. If, for example, text is entered 
in a field expecting an integer or an out-of-range response is 
entered, or if a required response is missing, the user is imme-
diately notified with a red exclamation icon. If the cursor hovers 
over the icon, then a specific error message is displayed. 
When Complete or Review buttons at the top of the form are 
clicked, the prototype validates all questions in the CRF and dis-
plays a list of errors for the user to address, as shown in Figure 6. 
Clicking or tapping the error listing takes the user to the question 
that needs to be addressed. CRFs may be edited and saved with 
known errors, but they may not be submitted to the database until 
all errors are addressed. The <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> interface includes the ability 
to create an exception, explaining how the data were not able to be 
collected, if this is the case. This method ensures that an error does 
not obstruct an interview, but that all issues are addressed before 
the data appears in the database. </p>

<p>EVALUATION OF <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> </p>

<p>This prototype has been in long-term pilot with multiple groups, 
of which we will describe two examples: Psychopathy Research 
under Dr. Kent Kiehl located at the MRN and FBIRN (Keator et 
al., 2008; Potkin et al., 2009), a collaboration featuring more than 
10 distributed sites. These groups use different database schemas 
and have different data collection needs. These projects have been </p>

<p>instrumental in gathering user feedback as well as demonstrat-
ing the usefulness of the software in real assessment gathering 
conditions. We have recently added a self-assessment mode to 
allow the same <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> system to be used in computer labs for 
self-assessments. 
The psychopathy research team currently conducts five related 
studies. The team has been using the tablet application for longi-
tudinal acquisition of clinical and sociodemographic assessments 
on an incarcerated adult psychopathy population since January 
2009 (Ermer and Kiehl, 2010; Harenski and Kiehl, 2010; Harenski 
et al., 2010). The tablet product is ideal in a prison setting, since 
network desktop PC clients are typically disallowed and internet 
access is not available. Among the assessments in use are sev-
eral standard questionnaires, personality checklists, and symptom 
severity indices, which use a broad range of question types and 
answers. Some of them have been modified for specific study 
needs; they are implemented with type-checking (dates, strings, 
numbers) and range-checking where relevant. Assessment data is 
entered in the MRN database, as part of the COINS system (Scott 
et al., this issue). The vast majority of CRFs for the psychopathy 
research studies are now entered via tablet. 
Because the Kiehl psychopathy team phased the tablet entry 
into ongoing studies that had been using manual transcription 
and dual-entry, it is possible to compare the old method to the 
new method to evaluate the effects. For example, as of this writ-
ing, 15,393 assessments were entered manually from paper forms 
into the MRN's database. The average time between the assess-
ment interview and the time the data were verified as complete 
in the database was 232 days. In contrast, 5,567 assessments have 
been entered using the tablet prototype, and the average time 
between interview and complete data in the database is 3 days. 
This trend indicates that assessment data can be made avail-
able for analysis very quickly after it is gathered, and results 
may be available more than 7 months earlier than they would be 
otherwise. 
The FBIRN community has used the tablet application as its 
primary method of assessment gathering for its Phase III schiz-
ophrenia study since January 2009. These assessments are con-
ducted with schizophrenic and normal control participants across 
eight different data collection sites. For this project, we added 
functionality to the current prototype application to support data 
exchange using the XCEDE standard (Keator et al., 2006, 2009). 
Completed CRFs for FBIRN are uploaded to distributed instances 
of the Human Imaging Database, one at each data collection site. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>December 2011 | Volume 5 | Article 31 | 6 </p>

<p>Turner et al. </p>

<p>EDC in CARAT </p>

<p>Similarly in FBIRN as in the psychopathy research, two large-
scale studies have been performed that can be compared. The 
Phase II dataset (Potkin and Ford, 2009; Potkin et al., 2009) was col-
lected using the dual-entry method, including requiring manual 
double entry of the transcribed data to minimize errors. As project 
manager of the FBIRN at the time, Dr. Turner was very aware of the 
delays and errors in clinical data availability due to the dual-entry 
method, and the final data aggregation across assessments ranged 
from 100% available (for simple measures such as age and gender) 
to only 70% available or less (for more detailed questions regard-
ing duration of illness or the full list and dosing information for 
current medications, for example). This was highly problematic in 
the full analysis of the final study. In the next multi-site study, the 
currently ongoing Phase III study, the clinical tablet is being used in 
all eight data collection sites, of which MRN is one. In conjunction 
with the multi-database querying allowed by the HID infrastruc-
ture, this allows regular confirmation of which subjects have been 
enrolled, screened, scanned, and have their clinical data complete -
rather than simply asking the data collection teams for their assur-
ances, electronic audits are being performed automatically and 
reviewed by the whole FBIRN regularly. As of this writing, over 300 
subjects have been enrolled, with some sites showing 100% com-
plete clinical assessments and others very close to that. This allows 
immediate accountability for incomplete data, and the ability to 
correct it rapidly to increase the proportion of usable datasets. </p>

<p>CAVEATS </p>

<p>With the exception of the upload of completed CRFs to a data-
base, all major functions on <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> are available without internet 
or network access. Asynchronous updates, however, can lead to 
duplicate or existing data in the centralized data management sys-
tem, which must not be overwritten. REDCap has developed an 
elegant system to manage these issues (Borlawsky et al., 2011); 
<rs type="software">CARAT</rs> handles those problems to some extent, though not as 
completely. At this point, the MICIS and BIRN web services will 
check against the subject ID, assessment, study, and visit to see if 
duplicate data already exists in the database. We are working to 
make the generic web service more flexible and secure for these 
issues while maintaining its agnostic approach to database schema 
Clinical assessment and remote administration tablet was 
designed and implemented on a Windows system. Convertible 
tablets, for which Windows was the dominant operating system, 
are being overwhelmed by the new popularity of slate tablets. Slates 
tend to run Android or iOS, as well as Windows; <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> is being 
re-factored to be platform-independent, to take advantage of these 
new options. 
A challenge specific to multi-site studies is the need to have 
all users have the same implementation of <rs type="software">CARAT</rs>, the same 
forms and layouts. For studies which decide on their protocol 
and never vary from it, it is not a challenge to set up one instan-
tiation of <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> and disseminate it to all the participating sites. 
Many clinical and research studies, however, find that they need 
new or revised CRFs over the course of a study; confirming all 
sites are using the same version has been a challenge for <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> 
in multi-site studies. Future versions of <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> will implement 
automatic update detection, so that all sites are running with the 
latest version for a given study whenever they have internet access. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Electronic data capture of the assessments and interviews associ-
ated with clinical neuroimaging studies have been used in many 
studies, and the <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> system which we present has been tested 
in a wide range of study situations. The needs which EDC sys-
tems commonly address include using a web interface to transmit 
data directly into a database, usually over the internet so that only 
a browser is needed for the user. The ability to handle complex 
forms, multiple types of questions, conditional branching, and 
constraint checking is also needed for an adequate system (Harris 
et al., 2009). Unique needs for many research programs include the 
ability to use a tablet system rather than a desktop or laptop, and 
to work where the internet is not available, without giving up the 
ability to capture the data and transmit it directly to a study data-
base. The demands of neuroimaging studies includes the ability 
to identify the subject's imaging data with their clinical and other 
data, preferably within a centralized multi-modal data repository. 
The first advantage of <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> is that it was designed to work on 
a tablet, mimicking natural interviewing style. The use of the stylus 
on the tablet screen has been popular with researchers who prefer 
the pen and paper approach. <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> also includes the ability to 
handle constraint checking and complex conditional branching, 
similar to what <rs type="software">REDCap</rs> provides. Data validation supports regu-
lar expressions, so error detection can become extremely detailed. 
Responses can be validated not just by data type (date, number, 
character string, etc.) but by complex ranges of these in almost any 
combination. <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> at the moment does not implement the abil-
ity to reference multiple questions in a single validation rule, how-
ever; it can require the response field be filled in according to highly 
complex string-formation rules combining letters and numbers, 
but we can't say that the response must be less the answer to the pre-
vious question plus 100, for example. That has not been a common 
request from users, though it could be implemented if needed. 
An appropriate EDC solution must also provide a high degree of 
CRF customization to accommodate the almost constant stream of 
new assessments, and modifications to existing assessments, which 
comes with many research programs. The CRFs and other assess-
ment forms must be extremely customizable, allowing for entry of 
common, rare, and unique study-specific assessments. It should be 
modifiable by the research team that is collecting and/or managing 
the data, rather than depending on the original software develop-
ers -ease of use in the <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> layout system is currently a focus of 
ongoing development. Ideally, for non-copyright material, a repos-
itory of assessments should be available, built from studies already 
using <rs type="software">CARAT</rs>, so that the forms for a new study can be set up 
quickly and re-use existing forms automatically whenever possible, 
similar to the system implemented in (El Fadly et al., 2011). 
Data-gathering software appropriate to the specific needs of 
clinical research interviews is unlikely to be widely adopted if it 
cannot conform to the data storage solutions already employed at 
mature research sites. It may or may not be possible to integrate 
data from independent software packages that employ their own 
distinct database schemas. The software must be able to plug 
into the existing frameworks already in use by mature research 
programs. It must have a mechanism to communicate with exist-
ing databases and schemas, be they off-the-shelf like <rs type="software">OpenClinica</rs> 
or custom solutions such as <rs type="software">REDCap</rs>. CARAT has the flexibility </p>

<p>Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>December 2011 | Volume 5 | Article 31 | 7 </p>

<p>Turner et al. </p>

<p>EDC in CARAT </p>

<p>to interact with arbitrary databases, rather than a single propri-
etary database specialized for clinical assessments, thus allowing 
the ability of combining clinical and imaging data within a single 
repository. 
Franklin et al. (2011) reviewed several common EDC systems 
within their needs for small-scale clinical trials; their list of val-
ued features overlapped with the <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> specifications to some 
extent. Their list included availability of training materials, the 
presence of site and user roles and permissions, ease of designing 
CRFs including error detection, the ability to create a visit sched-
ule for data-entry, and the ease in importing or exporting data in a 
standards-compliant way. <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> provides training materials for 
the user interface, and the developers' manual for the web interface 
is in development. The fact that <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> is built to work with both 
MICIS and HID and to be expandable to other database system 
means many of the security issues and permissions are considered 
the purview of the database, however, rather than the data col-
lection system. <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> can validate that the rater's username and 
password is a valid rater for the study, and that the subject ID being 
used is for a subject who is enrolled in the study. Other levels of 
permission that are not related to collecting assessment data are 
not within the scope of <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> at this time. </p>

<p>Clinical assessment and remote administration tablet is orga-
nized around the idea of visit schedules, which are part of the 
fundamentals of the tablet interface. The grouping of assessments 
that need to be done at baseline screening and subsequent visits 
throughout a study protocol are defined in the primary con-
figuration file and are required. Each assessment or group of 
assessments for an individual subject, can be exported as XML 
as described above; data import and export from the database 
repository, whether in text or comma separated values or other 
formats, is again, a choice for that data management system. </p>

<p>AVAILABILITY </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">CARAT</rs> software is available from www.nitric.org, under mul-
tiple licenses. For the research community with free re-use, it is 
available under the GNU General Public License (GPL). If the 
software is to be used with a commercial interest, other licenses 
can be negotiated. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by funding from the National Institutes 
of Health as part of the FBIRN project (U24 RR021992, S. G. 
Potkin PI), by 1R01EB006841 (Vince D. Calhoun), and from the 
Department of Energy, DE-FG02-08ER64581. </p>



<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The 
authors declare that the research was 
conducted in the absence of any 
commercial or financial relationships 
that could be construed as a potential 
conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Received: 14 September 2011; paper 
pending published: 08 October 2011; 
accepted: 21 November 2011; published 
online: 27 December 2011. 
Citation: Turner JA, Lane SR, Bockholt 
HJ and Calhoun VD (2011) The clin-
ical assessment and remote administra-
tion tablet. Front. Neuroinform. 5:31. doi: 
10.3389/fninf.2011.00031 
Copyright © 2011 Turner , Lane, Bock-
holt and Calhoun. This is an open-
access article distributed under the terms 
of the Creative Commons Attribution 
Non Commercial License, which per-
mits noncommercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in other forums, pro-
vided the original authors and source are 
credited. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Neuroinformatics 
www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>December 2011 | Volume 5 | Article 31 | 8 </p>

</text></tei>