<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3835222" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Methods and Results--We first studied MIF level in plasma and the myocardium in mice and determined infarct size. MI for 15 
or 60 minutes resulted in 2.5-fold increase over control values in plasma MIF levels while MIF content in the ischemic 
myocardium reduced by 50% and plasma MIF levels correlated with myocardium-at-risk and infarct size at both time-points 
(P&lt;0.01). In patients with STEMI, we obtained admission plasma samples and measured MIF, conventional troponins (TnI, TnT), 
high sensitive TnI (hsTnI), creatine kinase (CK), CK-MB, and myoglobin. Infarct size was assessed by cardiac magnetic resonance 
(CMR) imaging. Patients with chronic stable angina and healthy volunteers were studied as controls. Of 374 STEMI patients, 68% 
had elevated admission MIF levels above the highest value in healthy controls (&gt;41.6 ng/mL), a proportion similar to hsTnI (75%) 
and TnI (50%), but greater than other biomarkers studied (20% to 31%, all P&lt;0.05 versus MIF). Only admission MIF levels 
correlated with CMR-derived infarct size, ventricular volumes and ejection fraction (n=42, r=0.46 to 0.77, all P&lt;0.01) at 3 day 
and 3 months post-MI. </p>

<p>Conclusion--Plasma MIF levels are elevated in a high proportion of STEMI patients at the first obtainable sample and these levels 
are predictive of final infarct size and the extent of cardiac remodeling. ( J Am Heart Assoc. 2013;2:e000226 doi: 10.1161/ 
JAHA.113.000226) </p>

<p>Key Words: infarct size • macrophage migration inhibitory factor • myocardial infarction </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he use of plasma biomarkers has become central to the 
diagnosis and management of acute coronary syn-
dromes and exclusion of myocardial necrosis. 
1 Specifically, </p>

<p>the diagnostic value of troponin I or T (TnI or TnT) elevation 
among patients with myocardial infarction (MI) is well 
established. 
2,3 Long-term mortality and morbidity following </p>

<p>MI are largely determined by infarct size, and the extent of left 
ventricular (LV) dysfunction. 
4,5 Primary percutaneous coro-</p>

<p>nary intervention (PCI) is now the established standard of 
treatment for patients with ST-elevation MI (STEMI) 
6,7 to limit </p>

<p>infarct size and mortality. 
8 Improvement in the early diagnosis </p>

<p>of MI has the potential to critically affect global health-service 
delivery. 
9 Moreover, given its prognostic impact, early accu-</p>

<p>rate prediction of infarct size, currently only possible after 36 
to 48 hours of STEMI with either peak or cumulative release 
of troponins or creatine kinase (CK) or with imaging, in 
patients with MI would be advantageous in tailoring prompt 
treatment, particularly in complex patients, or where local 
healthcare resources are limited. 
In addition to the electrocardiogram, measurement of 
circulating levels of cardiac biomarkers is routinely used for 
the early detection of myocardial necrosis. Several biomar-
kers are known to increase within the first 12 hours after </p>

<p>From the Departments of Cardiovascular Medicine (W.C., S.J.D., A.J.T., A.M.D.) 
and Pathology (H.G.S.), Alfred Hospital, Melbourne, Australia; Baker IDI Heart 
and Diabetes Institute, Melbourne, Australia (X.-M.G., X.-J.D. D.A.W., R.-F.B., 
Y.L., F.F., A.M.D.); The Third Hospital, Peking University, Beijing, China (X.-Y.W., 
H.-Y.Y., Y.-Y.Z., W.G.); Departments of Medicine (S.J.D., A.J.T., X.-J.D., A.M.D.) 
and Surgery (X.-M.G.), Central Clinical School, Monash University, Melbourne, 
Australia. </p>

<p>*Drs Chan, White, and Wang contributed equally to this work. 
 † Drs W. Gao, X.-M. Gao, and Dart contributed equally to the work. </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Anthony M. Dart, FRACP, DPhil, Heart Centre, the Alfred 
Hospital, Heart Centre, the Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, 
Victoria 3004, Australia. E-mail: a.dart@alfred.org.au. </p>

<p>Received March 30, 2013; accepted September 6, 2013. 
ª 2013 The Authors. Published on behalf of the American Heart Association, 
Inc., by Wiley Blackwell. This is an open access article under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, 
distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>acute MI, including CK, troponins, and myoglobin. </p>

<p>10-12   Current routine laboratory troponin assay cannot definitively 
exclude acute MI on the basis of normal levels until at least 6 
to 12 hours after symptom onset as the rise in plasma 
troponin can be delayed. 
1,13 CK and myoglobin levels have </p>

<p>been claimed to rise earlier after the onset of MI than 
troponins, albeit neither are cardiac-specific. 
1 High-sensitive </p>

<p>assays of troponins (hsTn) have significantly improved the 
sensitivity for early diagnosis of acute MI. 
12,14,15 However, </p>

<p>information on infarct size still requires serial measurements 
of biomarkers over the first 36 to 48 hours or with myocardial 
imaging techniques such as cardiac magnetic resonance 
during the first week post-STEMI. 
Experimental studies have revealed a critical role for the 
inflammatory cytokine macrophage migration inhibitory factor 
(MIF) involved in the early response to acute ischemic 
stress and the ongoing inflammatory response following acute 
MI. 
16-19 MIF is widely expressed and is present in cardio-</p>

<p>myocytes in a preformed state. 
20 Previous clinical studies </p>

<p>have reported elevated MIF plasma levels detected as early as 
4 to 6 hours after acute MI, 
21,22 which remained elevated up </p>

<p>to 2 weeks post-MI. 
23 Although these clinical and experimen-</p>

<p>tal studies have indicated a close association between 
MIF and acute MI, to what extent very early circulating MIF 
levels correlate with the onset and extent of myocardial 
necrosis (ie, infarct size) has not been established. 
In the current study, we performed experimental and 
clinical studies to examine our hypothesis that plasma MIF is 
elevated early after acute MI due to cardiac release and that 
MIF levels in the first obtainable plasma samples may predict 
infarct size. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Experiments on Mice With Acute Myocardial 
Infarction </p>

<p>A mouse model of MI was used to define changes in plasma MIF 
and its source during the acute phase of MI. Furthermore, we 
determined the relationship between plasma MIF levels and 
the size of myocardium-at-risk and infarct myocardium. TnI was 
similarly studied for comparison with MIF. </p>

<p>Animals and surgery </p>

<p>All animal procedures were approved by a local Animal Ethics 
Committee and in accordance with guidelines set out in the 
Australian Code of Practice for the Care and Use of Animals 
for Scientific Purposes (7th Ed). Male C57Bl/6 mice at 
12 weeks of age were subjected to open-chest surgery for 
coronary artery occlusion (CAO) for a period of 15 or 
60 minutes, respectively (n=19 per group) or for sham 
procedure (n=6 per group) as we previously described. </p>

<p>24   Quantification of the myocardium-at-risk and infarct 
myocardium </p>

<p>Myocardium-at-risk and infarct myocardium were identified as 
described previously with minor modifications. 
16,25 Briefly, </p>

<p>after cannulation of the ascending aorta, 5% Evans blue was 
injected into coronary arteries to stain nonischemic myocar-
dium. The LV was then harvested and sectioned into 5 to 7 
slices at a thickness of 0.7 mm from the apex to the base 
and then incubated in 1.5% triphenyltetrazolium chloride (TTC 
in PBS, 30 minutes at 37°C). The nonischemic zone (blue 
area), myocardium-at-risk (nonstained area by Evans blue), 
and infarct zone (nonstained area by TTC) were outlined and 
areas quantified digitally using <rs type="software">Image J</rs> software. Since LV 
sections were at an equal thickness of 0.7 mm, volumes of 
myocardium-at-risk and infarct myocardium were also calcu-
lated by multiplying differently stained areas of each LV 
section with 0.7 mm, and expressed as mm 
3 per heart. The </p>

<p>size of infarct or myocardium-at-risk was expressed asper-
centage of the LV. </p>

<p>Plasma and tissue preparation and assays 
of MIF and TnI </p>

<p>At the end of the ischemic period, blood was collected by 
cardiac puncture using heparin as an anticoagulant. Plasma 
was prepared and stored at À80°C until assay. In 2 
subgroups of mice with CAO for 15 or 60 minutes, blood 
and hearts were collected. Under a dissecting microscope, 
the myocardium-at-risk and nonischemic LV tissues were 
carefully separated based on the pale color of the former 
and snap frozen. Tissue of 20 to 40 mg was homogenized 
and proteins extracted. Protein concentration was measured 
using Bradford assay. 
16 MIF levels in mouse plasma (n=19 </p>

<p>per group) and the myocardium (n=6 to 8 per group) were 
measured by Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) 
in duplicates using a commercial mouse MIF kit (USCN Life 
Science &amp; Technology Co) according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. The cardiac TnI assay (n=19 per group) was 
performed at the Alfred Hospital Pathology service using 
Chemiluminescent Microparticle Immunoassay (CMIA) on 
the Abbott Architect ci16200 (Abbott Laboratories). </p>

<p>Determination of cardiac MIF release by 
immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Effect of myocardial ischemia on the cardiac MIF content 
was further examined by immunohistochemistry on fresh-
frozen LV sections from mice with sham-operation, 15 or 
60 minutes CAO (n=2 to 3 per group). We used rabbit 
antimouse primary anti-MIF antibody (1:2000, Invitrogen) and 
the secondary antibody was a biotinylated antirabbit IgG 
(1:200, Vector Laboratories). Antigen was visualized using 
3,3 
0 -Diaminobenzidine tetrahydrochloride (DAB). </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Clinical Studies on Patients With Acute STEMI </p>

<p>Retrospective study (Beijing patient cohort) </p>

<p>This study was approved by the Human Ethics Committee, 
Peking University Health Science Centre and all participants 
provided written informed consent. We recruited consecutive 
patients with STEMI over 18 years of age who attended the 
Department of Cardiology, Third Hospital of Peking University 
during the period of 2008-2010. Patients with a diagnosis of 
STEMI (chest pain ≥30 minutes in duration, and electrocar-
diographic changes of new ischemia: ST elevation at the J 
point ≥0.1 mV in 2 contiguous leads) who underwent initial 
admission blood sampling within 6 hours after the onset of 
chest pain prior to any reperfusion interventions were eligible 
for inclusion. Patients having 1 or more of the following 
criteria were excluded: suspected or known previous MI in the 
same coronary artery territory as the current STEMI, rescue 
angioplasty, cardiogenic shock (systolic blood pressure 
&lt;90 mm Hg), or renal failure (estimated glomerular filtration 
rate ≤30 mL/min). A total of 332 patients with STEMI 
meeting these inclusion and exclusion criteria were included 
in this report. We also recruited 58 healthy consecutive 
volunteers who had no evidence of cardiovascular and other 
systemic disease as determined on history, physical exami-
nation, and electrocardiogram from the Risk Assessment 
Clinic, the Third Hospital, and 26 patients with chronic stable 
angina who had evidence of coronary artery disease (CAD) 
verified by chart review (prior coronary angiograms or history 
of MI) and by their treating physicians and in whom there had 
not been any recent deterioration of anginal symptoms or 
CCS (Canadian Cardiovascular Society) class within the 
previous 6 months. Plasma samples were used for assay of 
MIF, TnT, CK-MB, and other routine laboratory analyses (see 
below). We included both a healthy control group and patients 
with chronic stable angina in order to investigate differences 
in not only MIF but also each of the other biomarkers of 
cardiomyocyte necrosis in each of the groups. This would 
serve to provide evidence for changes in MIF or other 
biomarker status according to different health states and 
clinical presentation. Compared to an apparently healthy 
phenotype, those patients with documented CAD might be 
expected to exhibit a different biomarker profile. Thus, it 
would be important to have baseline knowledge of different 
biomarker profiles when comparing against patients with 
STEMI. </p>

<p>Prospective study (Melbourne patient cohort) </p>

<p>This study was approved by the local hospital Human 
Research Ethics Committee in accordance with National 
Health and Medical Research Council's (NHMRC) National 
Statement on Ethical Conduct in Research Involving 
Humans and carried out at the Alfred Hospital between </p>

<p>August 2008 and December 2010. All patients provided 
written informed consent. Admission plasma sampling was 
obtained prior to primary PCI for assay of MIF, TnI, hsTnI, 
CK, myoglobin, and high sensitive C-reactive protein 
(hsCRP). Plasma samples were then obtained every 6 hours 
for 48 hours for assay of CK and TnI to determine peak 
values and area under curve (AUC) determined by planime-
try. 
26 hsCRP at 48 hours post-MI was also analyzed. A total </p>

<p>of 42 STEMI patients were recruited and all underwent 
primary PCI as per routine practice. Nine chronic stable 
angina patients and 50 healthy volunteers were recruited 
following the same standards as described in Beijing cohort 
during routine outpatient visits. </p>

<p>MIF ELISA </p>

<p>In both clinical studies, plasma MIF was measured in 
duplicates using Quantikine MIF ELISA kits (R&amp;D Systems) 
according to manufacturer's specifications at the core 
laboratories in Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute and in 
Cardiovascular Research Institute, Beijing University. The 
coefficient of variation for intra-and interassay variation was 
2.2% and 3.6%, respectively. The highest value obtained from 
healthy control participants was used as the upper reference 
cut-off value. This was 32.9 ng/mL in the Beijing cohort and 
41.6 ng/mL in the Melbourne cohort. The first obtainable 
blood/plasma sample post-admission was defined as the 
admission sample in both centers. </p>

<p>Routine laboratory analyses </p>

<p>All routine laboratory assays including full blood examination 
and renal function were performed using commercially 
available automated platform. Fourth generation TnT and 
CK-MB were measured using a Roche Cobas E601 Immunol-
ogy Analyzer (Diamond Diagnostics) at the Clinical Chemistry 
Service of the Third Hospital, Beijing University. hsTnI, TnI, CK, 
and hsCRP were measured using Abbott Architect ci16200 
(Abbott Laboratories) at the Alfred Hospital Pathology by 
laboratory technicians blinded to patient details. In the 
Melbourne cohort, myoglobin was measured in whole blood 
using a fluorescence immunoassay (Triage Cardiac Panel, 
Biosite Diagnostics). 
11 Based on manufacturers' recommen-</p>

<p>dation or literature, the upper reference limits for biomarkers 
studied were set as follows: for the Beijing cohort, CK-MB 24 
U/L and TnT 0.03 lg/L; 
9 for the Melbourne cohort: CK 200 </p>

<p>U/L, TnI 0.03 lg/L, 
9 hsTnI 0.03 lg/L, 
27 and myoglobin </p>

<p>200 lg/L. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Cardiac resonance magnetic imaging for infarct size 
and LV volumes and function </p>

<p>Cardiac resonance magnetic (CMR) examination post-MI was 
completed in all 42 patients of the Melbourne cohort at day 3 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>and in 36 patients at 3 months using a clinical 1.5-T CMR 
scanner (Sigma HDx 1.5-T, GE Healthcare) following the 
method previously described. 
26,28 Briefly, LV function was </p>

<p>assessed by a standard steady state free precession 
technique called Fast Imaging Employing Steady State 
Acquisition (FIESTA). LV ejection fraction (LVEF) was calcu-
lated by volumetric analysis from a contiguous short axis 
FIESTA stack covering the LV and right ventricle using the 
summation of disc method 
29 by 2 cardiologists. For determi-</p>

<p>nation of myocardium-at-risk, LV short-axis slices covering the 
whole LV using a T2-weighted triple-inversion recovery breath-
hold fast spinecho pulse sequence were obtained using a 
body coil. Myocardium-at-risk was quantified by manual 
delineation of myocardium with bright signal intensity 2 SD 
above the mean signal obtained in the remote, noninfarct 
myocardium and multiplying the slice thickness and the 
myocardial density of 1.05 g/mL, expressed as a percentage 
of LV mass. Late enhancement images covering the whole LV 
were acquired %15 minutes after intravenous administration 
of a bolus of gadolinium-diethylene triamine penta-acetic acid 
(DTPA) to identify regional necrosis/fibrosis for infarct size 
quantification using an inversion recovery gradient echo 
technique. The area of hyperenhanced myocardium (bounded 
by endocardial and epicardial contours) on each of the short-
axis slice was manually traced then multiplied by the slice 
thickness and the myocardial density of 1.05 g/mL to obtain 
the infarct mass, and expressed as a percentage of LV mass 
(infarct size). 
30 All analyses were performed offline on </p>

<p>dedicated workstations running <rs id="software-1" type="software">AW SDC</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.4</rs> and <rs id="software-2" type="software">IDL</rs> version 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">6.3</rs> with <rs id="software-3" type="software">ReportCARD</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">3.6</rs> by fully blinded observers 
with excellent reproducibility (r=0.98) for infarct size assess-
ment. </p>

<p>26,29 </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>For the animal studies, results are presented as meanAESEM. 
For clinical studies, categorical data are presented as 
numbers and percentages. Continuous data are presented 
as meanAESD. All continuous variables were subjected to 
D'Agostino &amp; Pearson omnibus or the 1-sample Kolmogorov-
Smirnov normality test. If variables failed to pass the test, 
nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis test was used to detect 
significance among groups with Dunns post-hoc test, and 
Spearman correlation was performed to detect the correla-
tion between parameters. If variables passed the test, 
Pearson correlation or standard linear regression was 
performed to detect the correlation and continuous vari-
ables were compared with either unpaired Student's t test or 
1-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Newman-Keuls 
post-hoc test. When multiple independent terms were 
included in regression analyses, stepped entry and removal 
was used with p for inclusion (PIN) and p for removal (POUT) </p>

<p>set at 0.05 and 0.1, respectively. P&lt;0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. All data analyses were performed 
with <rs id="software-4" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">16</rs> or <rs id="software-5" type="software">Graphpad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">5.0</rs>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Experimental Findings From the Mouse Model of 
MI </p>

<p>Rapid myocardial MIF release following MI and 
correlation between plasma MIF levels and the extent 
of myocardial injury </p>

<p>First, we observed a 2.5-fold increase in plasma MIF level in 
mice subjected to CAO for 15 or 60 minutes (Figure 1A). We 
then studied whether the early rise of circulating MIF was 
cardiac in origin. Indeed, we found %50% reduction relative to 
the respective sham values in MIF content of the jeopardized 
myocardium at both time-points studied (Figure 1A, both 
P&lt;0.05). MIF content in the noninfarct myocardium collected 
at 1 hour after MI showed no change (data not shown). Rapid 
loss of MIF from the ischemic myocardium was also indicated 
by immunohistochemistry for MIF in LV tissues of mice with 
CAO for 15 or 60 minutes (Figure 1B). Plasma TnI levels were 
modestly elevated at 15 minutes but robustly elevated after a 
60-minute period of CAO (Figure 1A). 
Myocardial necrosis, determined by TTC staining, was 
evident in LVs within a 60-minute period of CAO but not from 
those with CAO for 15 minutes (Figure 1C). Plasma MIF levels 
measured at either 15 or 60 minutes positively correlated 
with the size of infarct and myocardium-at-risk (Figure 1D), 
while plasma TnI at either 15 or 60 minutes post-MI showed 
no correlation with the size of infarct or myocardium-at-risk 
(Figure 1D). </p>

<p>Findings From Clinical Studies </p>

<p>Baseline clinical data and clinical characteristics of 
STEMI patients </p>

<p>The baseline clinical characteristics of both patient cohorts 
are presented in Table 1. In both cohorts, a higher proportion 
of STEMI patients were male and smokers compared to 
healthy controls. The prevalence of smoking, hypertension, 
diabetes, dyslipidemia, and family history of CAD was 
significantly higher in STEMI and chronic stable angina 
patients than that in healthy controls. Patients with chronic 
stable angina had the largest body mass index in the Beijing 
cohort, and were significantly older than the other 2 groups in 
the Melbourne cohort. The clinical and procedural character-
istics of the STEMI patients are summarized in Table 2. The 
mean values of MIF, TnT, and CK-MB at admission, were 
higher than their respective upper reference limits in the </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Beijing cohort. For the Melbourne cohort, admission mean 
levels of MIF, TnI, hsTnI, and myoglobin, except CK, were 
above their respective upper reference limits. In the Beijing 
STEMI cohort, patients with admission MIF value above 
32.9 ng/mL were older, more likely to be male, and had a 
higher BMI (all P&lt;0.05) than those whose MIF values were 
below 32.9 ng/mL. The Melbourne cohort showed the same 
trend with respect to age and male gender, but differences 
did not reach statistical significance. The median symptom-
to-blood sampling time was 216AE83 minutes and </p>

<p>211AE75 minutes in the Beijing and the Melbourne cohorts, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Early elevation of plasma MIF levels in patients with 
STEMI </p>

<p>The distribution of plasma MIF and other biomarkers from the 
admission blood samples in patients with STEMI are shown in 
Figure 2. In the Beijing cohort, 67.5% of patients exhibited 
plasma MIF levels above the upper reference limit (32.9 ng/mL) 
of healthy controls (Figure 2A), a proportion significantly higher </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Tn I (plasma), µg/L 
MAR, % of LV </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 
150 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Tn I (plasma), µg/L 
Infarct size, % of LV </p>

<p>0 
500 
1000 
1500 
2000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>MIF (plasma), pg/ml 
MAR, % of LV </p>

<p>200 400 600 800 1000 1200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>MIF (plasma), pg/ml 
Infarct size, % of LV </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>SH 15min 60min </p>

<p>MIF (plasma), pg/ml </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>SH 15min 60min </p>

<p>MIF (LV), ng/mg protein </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>SH 15min 60min </p>

<p>Tn I (plasma), </p>

<p>µg/L </p>

<p>15 min CAO </p>

<p>r=0.616 
P=0.005 </p>

<p>r=0.328 
P=0.170 </p>

<p>r=0.719 
P=0.0005 </p>

<p>r=0.419 
P=0.074 </p>

<p>60 min CAO </p>

<p>A 
C </p>

<p>B 
D </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*  † </p>

<p>15 min CAO 60 min CAO </p>

<p>Sham </p>

<p>15' ischemia </p>

<p>60' ischemia </p>

<p>Figure 1. Changes in mouse plasma and cardiac macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) following coronary artery occlusion (CAO) and </p>

<p>correlation of plasma MIF levels with size of ischemic or infarct myocardium at 15 and 60 minutes of CAO. A, Rapid elevation of plasma MIF 
together with reduction in myocardial MIF at 15-and 60-minute periods of CAO. In contrast, plasma levels of troponin I (TnI) increased modestly 
at 15 minutes but markedly at 60 minutes, when myocardial necrosis developed. n=19 per CAO group, n=6 for sham-operated group, n=6 to 8 
per group for myocardial MIF measurement. One-way ANOVA with Newman-Keuls post hoc test was used to detect significance between groups. 
*P&lt;0.01 vs sham-operated control (SH). 
 † P&lt;0.01 vs 15 minutes CAO. B, Representative immunohistochemical staining for MIF (brown color) in 
the myocardium from mice subjected to sham-operation or with CAO for 15 and 60 minutes, respectively, showing a reduction of MIF density. 
n=2 to 3 per group. C, Representative left ventricular (LV) sections from mice subjected to CAO for 15 or 60 minutes. LV sections were dual 
stained to identify ischemic but viable (pink) myocardium and necrotic (pale) myocardium, dark blue stained areas denote normal perfused areas. 
D, Pearson correlation was performed to detect correlation between plasma levels of MIF or TnI and the size of myocardium-at-risk (MAR) or 
infarct size determined by serial LV sections with dual staining, as shown in (C). n=19 per group. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>than that of plasma CK-MB (30.6%, Figure 2C), or TnT (24%, 
individual data not shown, all P&lt;0.05 versus MIF). In the 
Melbourne cohort, 71.4% of patients with STEMI had 
elevated admission MIF level above the upper reference limit 
(41.6 ng/mL, Figure 2B), a figure similar to hsTnI (75%) or TnI 
(50%, P=0.073, individual data not shown), but significantly 
higher than that of CK (19.5%) and myoglobin (26.8%, both 
P&lt;0.05 versus MIF, Figure 2D through 2F). </p>

<p>Admission MIF levels correlated with infarct size, 
myocardium at risk, LV remodeling and dysfunction </p>

<p>The relationship between admission MIF levels and infarct size 
and LV remodeling and function was further evaluated in the 
prospective study conducted in Melbourne. Admission plasma 
MIF levels correlated significantly with CMR-derived infarct 
size at day-3 post-MI whereas other biomarkers measured did 
not (Figure 3). Moreover, admission MIF levels also correlated 
with peak level and AUC for TnI (r=0.669 and 0.678, both 
P&lt;0.001) and CK (r=0.513 and 0.695, both P&lt;0.001). Day-3 
infarct size closely correlated with peak level and AUC for CK 
(r=0.589 and 0.775, both P&lt;0.001) and TnI (r=0.660 and 
0.859, both P&lt;0.001) as well, suggesting that MIF is a reliable 
marker for infarct size prediction. Importantly, admission MIF 
levels also correlated with myocardium-at-risk at day 3 
(Figure 4A) and chronic infarct size 3 months post-MI 
(Figure 4B). Furthermore, standard multiple regression analy-
sis revealed that among the 5 admission biomarkers tested 
(eg, MIF, hsTnI, CK, myoglobin, and hsCRP) only MIF emerged 
as a significant independent predictor of both day 3 and 
3 months infarct size (data not shown). Notably, admission 
MIF levels also exhibited a significant relationship with CMR-
derived LV end-diastolic and end-systolic volume indexed </p>

<p>(LVEDVI, LVESVI) and LVEF determined at 3 days and 3 
months post-MI (all P&lt;0.01, Figure 4). All significant associ-
ations reported for admission MIF were still present and 
essentially unchanged when examined in regression analyses, 
which also included age, gender, and body mass index in 
addition to admission MIF as independent variables. In these 
analyses, age was significantly related to LVEF (r=0.048) and 
body mass index to LVEDVI (r=0.037) at day-3 post-MI, but 
there were no other significant associations with age, gender, 
or body mass index. 
hsCRP assay was also performed in patients with STEMI 
(the Melbourne cohort). Plasma hsCRP levels were unchanged 
at admission but increased by 10-fold at 48 hours post-MI. 
Furthermore, admission hsCRP levels neither correlated with 
admission MIF levels nor with infarct size measured by CMR 
at 3 days (Figure 5), while hsCRP levels at 48 hours post-MI 
significantly correlated with admission MIF levels and day-3 
infarct size (all P&lt;0.05, Figure 5). However, there were no 
significant associations involving hsCRP at 48 hours post-MI 
when these were examined using log e transformed hsCRP 
values in regression analyses which also included age, gender, 
and body mass index. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Three important findings have been made in the present 
study. First, we demonstrated in the mouse MI model that 
there was a rapid increase in circulating MIF, which occurred 
earlier than that of TnI and was accompanied by a reciprocal 
reduction in myocardial MIF content suggesting release of MIF 
from the ischemic myocardium into circulation. Elevated 
plasma MIF levels correlated with the mass of ischemic and </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline Characteristics of Study Participants </p>

<p>Beijing Cohort 
Melbourne Cohort </p>

<p>Healthy Control 
CSA 
STEMI 
Healthy Control 
CSA 
STEMI </p>

<p>Number 
58 
26 
332 
50 
9 
42 </p>

<p>Age, y 
54.0AE10.0 
64.8AE9.4* 
60.7AE12.9* 
57.8AE10.9 
73.7AE5.1* 
59.6AE10.9 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Male gender, % 
62 
58 
82* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>52 
80* 
76* </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>22.5AE2.5 
32.0AE11.5* 
25.2AE3.0 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>25.3AE4.1 
28.6AE3.8 
27.7AE5.4 </p>

<p>Current smoking, % 
8 
42* 
72* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>10 
22 
45* </p>

<p>Hypertension, % 
-
73* 
54* 
-
44* 
38* </p>

<p>Diabetes, % 
-
35* 
25* 
-
33* 
14* </p>

<p>Dyslipidemia, % 
-
46* 
30* 
-
44* 
33* </p>

<p>Family history of CAD, % 
-
42* 
21* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>22 
55* 
45* </p>

<p>Values are expressed as meanAESD or percentage. BMI indicates body mass index; CAD, coronary artery disease; CSA, chronic stable angina; STEMI, ST-segment elevation myocardial 
infarction. 
*P&lt;0.05 vs healthy control. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs CSA. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>infarcted myocardium. Second, elevation of plasma MIF was 
observed in 68% of patients with STEMI at the earliest 
available samples after admission, and this proportion was 
similar to hsTnI or TnI, but significantly higher than other 
conventional cardiac biomarkers measured (19% to 30%) at 
the same time. Third, in patients with STEMI, admission levels 
of MIF, but not other biomarkers, correlated positively with 
infarct size and LV chamber size, and negatively with LVEF 
measured both acutely (day 3) and at 3 months. Our 
experimental and clinical findings indicate that a single MIF 
assay at admission could be a useful biomarker for early 
prediction of final infarct size and might have utility in the 
early detection of myocardial necrosis. 
Previous clinical studies reported an increase in plasma 
MIF levels in patients with acute MI 4 to 6 hours after 
admission, 
22 which remained elevated over the next </p>

<p>2 weeks. 
21 However, it remains unclear if MIF circulating </p>

<p>levels might be detectable earlier than 4 to 6 hours after </p>

<p>symptom onset in patients with acute MI (STEMI). Our 
findings from mice and patients with acute MI demonstrated a 
much earlier elevation of plasma MIF levels than previously 
reported. In mice, a brief period of ischemia (15 minutes) 
induced a significant increase in circulating MIF level. 
Specifically, admission plasma MIF levels determined at a 
median of 216 minutes (Beijing cohort) or 211 minutes 
(Melbourne cohort) of symptom-to-sampling time were 
already elevated in 68% to 71% of patients with STEMI 
compared to 19% to 50% for other biomarkers studied with 
the exception of hsTnI (75%). Although release of MIF by 
cardiac tissue or cardiomyocytes has been reported in in vitro 
settings of hypoxia, ischemia or oxidative stress, 
18,21 our in </p>

<p>vivo animal model further documented the cardiac source of 
circulating MIF manifested by reciprocal changes in plasma 
MIF levels and in the ischemic myocardium. A reduction of 
MIF density in the ischemic myocardium was observed by 
immunohistochemistry. </p>

<p>Table 2. Baseline Clinical and Procedural Characteristics in STEMI Patients </p>

<p>Beijing Cohort 
Melbourne Cohort 
P Value </p>

<p>Number 
332 
42 
-</p>

<p>Heart rate, beats/min 
76AE16 
73AE16 
0.25 </p>

<p>Systolic blood pressure, mm Hg 
137AE27 
122AE23 
0.0006 </p>

<p>Diastolic blood pressure, mm Hg 
79AE18 
77AE14 
0.49 </p>

<p>Serum creatine, lmol/L 
88AE28 
85AE25 
0.51 </p>

<p>Symptom-to-sampling, min 
216AE83 
211AE75 
0.983 </p>

<p>Admission MIF, ng/mL 
55AE40 
66AE36 
0.091 </p>

<p>Admission troponins, lg/L 
0.08AE0.26 (TnT) 
0.10AE0.21 (TnI) 
0.63 </p>

<p>Admission hsTnI, lg/L 
-
0.38AE0.19 
-</p>

<p>Admission CK, U/L 
-
133AE111 
-</p>

<p>Admission CK-MB, U/L 
31AE51 
-
-</p>

<p>Admission myoglobin, lg/L 
-
367AE913 
-</p>

<p>Pre-PCI medication, n (%) </p>

<p>Aspirin 
100% 
100% 
-</p>

<p>Clopidogrel 
5% 
54% 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>b-blocker 
0 
2% 
0.219 </p>

<p>ACEi/ARB 
0 
27% 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Statin 
28.6% 
10% 
0.014 </p>

<p>Infarct-related artery </p>

<p>Left anterior descending artery, n (%) 
49% 
37% 
0.24 </p>

<p>Right coronary artery, n (%) 
35% 
39% 
0.82 </p>

<p>Left circumflex artery, n (%) 
15% 
24% 
0.22 </p>

<p>Number of stenosed vessels 
2.1AE0.88 
1.7AE0.8 
0.005 </p>

<p>Stent type BMS/DES, %/ 
3/97 
67/33 
-</p>

<p>Values are expressed as meanAESD, percentage or exact number. ACEi indicates angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor; ARB, angiotensin receptor blocker; BMS, bare-metal stent; 
CK, creatine kinase; DES, drug-eluting stent; hsTnI, high sensitive troponin I; MIF, macrophage migration inhibitory factor; PCI, percutaneous coronary intervention; STEMI, ST-segment 
elevation myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>There are several reasons why a biomarker that could 
predict final infarct size might be desirable in the clinical 
management of patients presenting with STEMI. Early 
changes in circulating levels of this biomarker would facilitate 
decision-making about the timeliness of reperfusion, partic-
ularly in regions of the world where healthcare resources are 
limited. It would also facilitate appropriate resource allocation 
for specific patients who are likely to need more intensive 
medical attention. Currently available biomarkers require 
serial assays to determine peak values and/or AUC for 
infarct size quantification. In contrast, MIF levels obtained </p>

<p>from our experimental mouse MI model, correlated with 
ischemic and infarct mass at 15 and 60 minutes post-CAO, 
whereas TnI assay showed no such correlation, Similarly, in 
our clinical studies, while there was no predictive value for 
infarct size by CK, hsTnI, TnI, and myoglobin, at the time of 
hospital presentation, an impressive correlation between a 
single admission MIF level and infarct size determined by 
CMR either acutely or at 3 months was observed. These 
findings raise the prospect that MIF may prove to be useful in 
the clinical setting, especially in the emergency department or 
coronary care unit. Release of conventional biomarkers from </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>Myoglobin (adm.), </p>

<p>µg/L </p>

<p>26.8% &gt;200 µg/L </p>

<p>STEMI </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>CK (adm.), U/L </p>

<p>19.5% &gt;200 U/L </p>

<p>STEMI </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>STEMI </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>CK-MB (adm.), U/L </p>

<p>30.6% &gt;24 U/L </p>

<p>µ </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 
4 
6 
8 </p>

<p>hsTn I (adm.), </p>

<p>µg/L </p>

<p>STEMI </p>

<p>75% &gt;0.03 µg/L </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>P&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>67.5% &gt;32.9 ng/ml </p>

<p>Control 
CSA 
STEMI </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>MIF (adm.), ng/ml </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Control 
CSA 
STEMI </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>MIF (adm.), ng/ml </p>

<p>71.4% &gt;41.6 ng/ml </p>

<p>P&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Admission plasma levels of macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) and other biomarkers in patients with ST-elevation </p>

<p>myocardial infarction (STEMI) and chronic stable angina (CSA), and healthy controls. Broken lines denote upper reference normal limit for 
respective biomarker. A and C, Data from the Beijing cohort. n=58, 26, 332 for control, CSA, and STEMI, respectively. B, D, E, F, Data from the 
Melbourne cohort. n=50, 9, 42 for control, CSA, and STEMI, respectively. One-way ANOVA with Newman-Keuls post hoc test was used to detect 
significance between groups in both cohorts. ANOVA indicates analysis of variance; CK, creatine kinase; hsTnI, high sensitive troponin I. </p>

<p>µ </p>

<p>0 
2000 
4000 
6000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>myoglobin (adm.), µg/L 
Infarct size (d3), % 
r=-0.089 
P=0.586 </p>

<p>0 
300 
600 
900 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>CK (adm.), U/L 
Infarct size (d3), % </p>

<p>r=-0.240 
P=0.136 </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 150 200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>MIF (adm.), ng/ml 
Infarct size (d3), % 
r=0.772 
P&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.5 
1.0 
1.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>hsTnI (adm.), µg/L 
Infarct size (d3), % </p>

<p>r=-0.091 
p=0.578 </p>

<p>µ </p>

<p>Figure 3. Admission (adm.) macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) levels, but not other cardiac biomarkers, for example, high sensitive </p>

<p>troponin I (hsTnI), creatine kinase (CK), and myoglobin, correlated with cardiac magnetic resonance-derived infarct size determined at day 3 (d3) 
after acute ST-elevation myocardial infarction. Data were from the Melbourne cohort. Pearson correlation for MIF and Spearman correlation for 
other biomarkers were performed to detect a correlation with infarct size. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>cardiomyocytes is known to require degradation of sarcomere 
contractile proteins (such as troponins) and membrane 
disintegration with leakage of cytosolic enzymes (such as 
CK), 
12 and therefore a significant delay relative to that of MIF </p>

<p>is required for adequate detection. Our observation that both 
peak and cumulative release of CK and TnI following PCI 
appear to be strong predictors of infarct size is consistent 
with the literature. 
31-33 However, this information would not </p>

<p>be available at least for another 24 to 36 hours for peak levels 
and 48 hours for AUC. 
1 Currently, no admission biomarkers </p>

<p>appear to be able to predict final infarct size when used within 
the first hours of onset of symptoms. The current study 
indicates that plasma MIF levels may offer such potential. 
As MIF is a proinflammatory cytokine, 
34 and acute MI is </p>

<p>associated with a systemic and regional inflammatory 
responses, the question raised as to whether the rise in MIF 
also reflect a state of inflammation. A recent study reported 
that the plasma level of CRP at 2 days after acute MI 
correlated with an inflammatory marker, interleukin-6, and 
infarct size. 
35 We therefore elected to study the relationship </p>

<p>between MIF and a surrogate marker of inflammation, hsCRP, 
in the Melbourne Cohort. Unlike MIF, plasma hsCRP level was 
not elevated at the time of admission but increased at 
48 hours after STEMI and only hsCRP levels at 48 hours 
correlated with admission MIF levels and with day-3 infarct 
size, similar to the previous report. 
35 The lack of a correlation </p>

<p>between admission MIF and hsCRP levels suggests that a 
rapid release of cardiac MIF is a supra-acute reaction to the 
ischemic insult. However, it is possible that the subsequent 
sustained rise of circulating MIF reported previously 
22,23 may </p>

<p>be related to a systemic inflammation and this requires a 
further investigation. 
Interestingly, plasma levels of MIF were already signifi-
cantly increased in mice undergoing CAO within 15 minutes 
when myocardial necrosis was not yet evident. Plasma MIF in 
mice correlated with the extent of the ischemic myocardium. 
This observation implies that MIF is also released from 
ischemic-but-viable myocardium following severe ischemic 
stress. Although plasma TnI was also elevated at this time-
point, there was no correlation between TnI level and size of 
myocardium-at-risk. Similarly, both admission MIF and hsTnI 
levels were elevated in STEMI patients, but only MIF levels 
closely correlated with CMR-derived size of myocardium-at-
risk. These results suggest a predictive value of early 
circulating MIF levels with the extent of ischemic myocardium. 
Therefore, we propose that MIF may represent a new class of 
biomarker that is released by the myocardium upon acute 
ischemic insult but without the necessity for tissue necrosis. 
Furthermore, the predictive value of admission MIF levels was 
not only limited to acute and final infarct size, but was also 
associated with parameters of cardiac remodeling and 
dysfunction. CMR imaging performed in STEMI patients in </p>

<p>0 
50 100 150 200 250 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>LVEF (d3), % </p>

<p>0 
50 100 150 200 250 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>MIF (adm.), ng/ml 
LVESVI (3mo), ml/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
50 100 150 200 250 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>LVESVI (d3), ml/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
50 100 150 200 250 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>MIF (adm.), ng/ml 
LVEDVI (3mo), ml/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
50 100 150 200 250 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>LVEDVI (d3), ml/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r=0.583 
P=0.0002 </p>

<p>r=0.477 
P=0.003 </p>

<p>r=0.455 
P=0.003 </p>

<p>r=0.650 
P&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>r=0.473 
P=0.0015 </p>

<p>0 
50 100 150 200 250 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>MIF (adm.), ng/ml 
Infarct size (3mo), % </p>

<p>r=0.726 
P&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>0 
50 100 150 200 250 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>MIF (adm.), ng/ml 
LVEF (3mo), % </p>

<p>r=0.627 
P&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 150 200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>r=0.426 
P=0.007 
MAR (d3), % </p>

<p>Figure 4. Admission (adm.) macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) levels correlated with cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR)-derived size </p>

<p>of myocardium-at-risk (MAR), infarct size, left ventricular (LV) indexed end-diastolic or end-systolic volumes (LVEDVI, LVESVI) and LV ejection 
fraction (LVEF) measured at day 3 (d3) and 3-month (3 mo) after acute ST-elevation myocardial infarction (MI). Data were from the Melbourne 
cohort, n=42 for day 3 and n=36 for 3 months post-MI. Standard linear logistic regression between admission MIF levels and CMR-derived 
parameters was performed. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>the Melbourne cohort demonstrated a strong correlation 
between admission MIF levels and LV volume index or LVEF 
measured by CMR acutely and chronically. </p>

<p>Limitations and Future Direction </p>

<p>First, in our current study only STEMI patients were 
investigated. Our hypothesis was that elevation in plasma 
MIF early after acute MI might be predictive of infarct size. 
Thus, inclusion of only STEMI patients was by study design. 
However, we demonstrated that the very early rise in plasma 
MIF levels is most likely due to release of preformed 
cardiomyocyte stores providing a plausible biologic explana-
tion that closely couples the early release of MIF, which might 
be of use in early detection of myocardial necrosis, with 
infarct size insofar as reflecting the magnitude of overall 
myocardial injury or necrosis that is subsequently quantified 
by cardiac magnetic resonance imaging. The possibility that 
MIF might be of utility in the early detection of myocardial 
necrosis needs to be investigated in future studies in patients 
who present with non-ST elevation acute coronary syndrome, </p>

<p>including unstable angina, to properly assess the diagnostic 
performance of MIF against other biomarkers. Second, our 
study was not designed to specifically compare the diagnostic 
performance of MIF versus established biomarkers. We 
acknowledge that hsTns, which have a lower limit of detection 
with higher sensitivity for early diagnosis than conventional 
troponin assays, need to be compared against MIF in future 
studies. While the diagnostic performance of hsTn in 
detecting myocardial necrosis is excellent with superior 
sensitivity and precision over conventional troponin assays, 
there are still well recognized challenges and limitations in 
adopting and implementing the use of hsTn in early diagnosis 
of acute MI. 
36 For example, the appropriate reference (99th </p>

<p>percentile) value to use clinically is different for men versus 
women (a situation that might be similar to observed 
differences in MIF levels between men and women and also 
with increasing age); solitary elevations of hsTn values (&gt;99th 
percentile) is thought to be inadequate for clinical decision 
making and serial changes in hsTn values will still be required 
to determine acute myocardial injury. Thus, each biomarker 
has advantages and limitations depending on the pretest </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>hsCRP (adm.), mg/L 
Infarct size (d3), % </p>

<p>CTL 
CSA Adm. MI 48h MI </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>hsCRP, mg/L </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>hsCRP (adm.), mg/L 
MIF (adm.) ng/ml </p>

<p>0 
100 200 300 400 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>hsCRP (48h), mg/L 
Infarct size (d3), % </p>

<p>0 
100 200 300 400 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>hsCRP (48h), mg/L 
MIF (adm.) ng/ml </p>

<p>r=-0.118 
P=0.458 </p>

<p>r=-0.022 
P=0.896 </p>

<p>r=0.487 
P=0.0012 
r=0.321 
P=0.040 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Figure 5. Plasma levels of high sensitive C-reactive protein (hsCRP) in healthy controls (CTL) and in patients with chronic stable angina (CSA) or </p>

<p>with ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI), and correlation between hsCRP and migration inhibitory factor (MIF) or cardiac magnetic 
resonance imaging-derived infarct size at 3 days post-MI. Plasma hsCRP was not elevated at admission (adm.) but was increased after 48 hours 
post-MI. Admission hsCRP correlated neither with admission MIF levels nor day 3 infarct size. However, plasma hsCRP at 48 hours post-MI 
correlated with admission MIF levels and infarct size. n=10, 9, 42 for healthy controls, CSA, and MI (both admission and 48 hours post-MI) 
groups, respectively. *P&lt;0.01 vs other groups. Nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis test was used to detect significance in hsCRP between groups with 
Dunns post-hoc test. Spearman correlation was performed for correlation between MIF, hsCRP, or infarct size. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>probability of myocardial injury and the specific assays used. 
In our study we did not use the MIF 99th percentile to define 
our upper reference limit but rather the highest value of 
healthy control participants. Although our study, to our 
knowledge, is the first study to publish the distribution of MIF 
levels in the largest sample of normal controls, the sample 
size of 50 (Melbourne cohort) and 58 (Beijing cohort) remains 
relatively small. We plan to undertake future studies involving 
larger numbers of normal controls in order to define the 99th 
MIF percentile. Third, MIF is not cardiac-specific, however, 
rapid rise of circulating MIF levels within a short time-window 
during the early phase post-MI period strongly supports a 
cardiac origin. Finally, we excluded patients with a prior 
infarct in order to minimize any confounding related to the 
interpretation of biomarker levels with myocardium-at-risk and 
infarct size. Patients with prior infarction are known to have a 
smaller myocardium-at-risk. Therefore, by only including 
patients without prior infarct, we believe this to be a more 
appropriate study design in our evaluation of the relationship 
between biomarkers (MIF) with myocardium-at-risk and infarct 
size. In addition, it is possible that patients with prior MI who 
present with their current MI might have a smaller rise in MIF 
levels as would be predicted by the size of MI imaged on CMR, 
which is a composite of old and new MI. Thus, by including only 
patients without prior MI this confounding effect could be 
minimized. 
In conclusion, we demonstrate that plasma MIF levels were 
elevated in the majority of STEMI patients at the first obtainable 
sample post-admission, which predicted acute and final infarct 
size and also post-MI cardiac remodeling and dysfunction while 
other biomarkers, such as hsTnI, conventional TnI and TnT, CK, 
myoglobin and hsCRP, did not. This early rise in MIF levels may 
have significant implications for prognostication, patient man-
agement, and healthcare utilization. </p>

<p>Sources of Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by a project grant (ID 472628) to 
Dr Gao and a program grant (ID 472600) from the National 
Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) of Australia. 
Dr Chan is supported by NHMRC Early Career Fellowship (Neil 
Hamilton Fairley-Clinical Overseas Fellowship, APP1052960). 
Dr White is supported by Australian National Heart Foundation 
PhD Scholarship (PB 10M 5481). Drs Dart and Taylor were 
funded by a NHMRC Program Grant (ID 472600). Drs Dart and 
Du are NHMRC research fellows. This study was also funded 
in part by the Victorian Government's Operational Infrastruc-
ture Support Program. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>None. </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.113.000226 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>MIF Predicts Infarct Size 
Chan et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

</text></tei>