<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3724279" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background In the evaluation of childhood obesity interventions, few researchers 
undertake a rigorous feasibility stage in which the design and procedures of the 
evaluation process are examined. Consequently, phase III studies often demonstrate 
methodological weaknesses. 
Purpose Our aim was to conduct a feasibility trial of the evaluation of WATCH IT, a 
community obesity intervention for children and adolescents. We sought to deter-
mine an achievable recruitment rate; acceptability of randomisation, assessment 
procedures, and dropout rate; optimal outcome measures for the definitive trial; 
and a robust sample size calculation. 
Method Our goal was to recruit 70 participants over 6 months, randomise them to 
intervention or control group, and retain participation for 12 months. Assessments 
were taken prior to randomisation and after 6 and 12 months. Procedures mir-
rored those intended for a full-scale trial, but multiple measures of similar outcomes 
were included as a means to determine those most appropriate for future research. 
Acceptability of the research and impact of the research on the programme were 
ascertained through interviewing participants and staff. 
Results We recruited 70 participants and found that randomisation and data col-
lection procedures were acceptable. Self-referral ( via media promotion) was more 
effective than professional referral. Blinding of assessors was sustained to a reason-
able degree, and optimal outcome measures for a full-scale trial were identified. Esti-
mated sample size was significantly greater than sample sized reported in published 
trials. There was some negative impact on the existing programme as a result of the 
research, a lesson for designers of future trials. 
Limitations We successfully recruited socially disadvantaged families, but the major-
ity of families were of White British nationality. The composition of the participants 
was an added valuable lesson, suggesting that recruitment strategies to obtain a 
more heterogeneous ethnic sample warrant consideration in future research. 
Conclusions This study provided us with confidence that we can run a phase III 
multi-centre trial to test the effectiveness of WATCH IT. Importantly, it was invalu-
able in informing the design not only of that trial but also of future evaluations of 
childhood obesity treatment interventions. Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755-764. The need to intervene to reduce the high prevalence 
of childhood obesity has prompted policy makers and 
researchers to identify effective options for its treat-
ment. There remains an uncertainty in the research 
literature as to the best treatment approach, and there 
is still a lack of well-designed, robust trials that evalu-
ate the effectiveness of interventions [1]. In the most 
recent Cochrane review for treatment interventions, 
there was some agreement that multi-component life-
style interventions were optimal [1], but there were 
only a limited number of high-quality studies and few 
met the criteria for inclusion in the meta-analysis. 
Most of the 64 identified studies demonstrated meth-
odological weakness in one or more areas, including 
inadequate group allocation, lack of blinding, and 
poorly reported follow-up and dropout rates. Thus, in 
their bid to find answers, researchers must conduct 
rigorous evaluations of such complex interventions as 
set out in the UK Medical Research Council (MRC) 
framework for complex interventions [2]. Within this 
model, feasibility trials are emphasised as essential to 
examine the viability of conducting definitive trials 
and to ensure that necessary refinements can be made 
to interventions and study procedures. Such protocols 
should mirror the procedures intended in the full trial 
[2], enabling researchers to identify and rectify short-
comings, determine appropriate outcome measures, 
and calculate an appropriate sample size. 
WATCH IT is a programme for obese children 
and adolescents, set up in 2002 and delivered in a 
community setting. It was formally piloted in an 
uncontrolled study in 2004 [3-6], showing proof of 
concept and leading to funding to conduct a feasi-
bility randomised controlled trial (RCT) to support 
development of a full-scale multi-centre trial to test 
its effectiveness. The programme was developed in 
Leeds, has been extended to Birmingham, and is 
now included in the UK Department of Health's 
National Framework for Weight Management 
Services [7]. In this study, we aimed to conduct pre-
liminary work needed to inform the design and 
conduct of a multi-centre trial and to identify and 
rectify any shortcomings. We sought to determine 
the best way to recruit young people at an achieva-
ble recruitment rate, estimate loss to follow-up, 
determine the acceptability of randomisation and 
assessment procedures, assess blinding integrity, 
determine optimal primary and secondary outcome 
measures, and calculate a robust sample size. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Design </p>

<p>With the ultimate goal of conducting a future large 
multi-centre individually RCT, a feasibility study </p>

<p>was developed to test this design in one centre. An 
assessor-blinded randomised controlled feasibility 
trial was performed in which participants were allo-
cated to WATCH IT or to a waiting list control group 
for 12 months. The trial was designed to address the 
specific objectives relating to study design for a full 
trial and not to determine effectiveness. Data were 
collected at baseline, 6, and 12 months. </p>

<p>Intervention </p>

<p>Full details of the WATCH IT intervention are 
described elsewhere [6]. In short, WATCH IT is a pro-
gramme for obese children and adolescents, deliv-
ered in the community setting by non-professional 
health trainers. Obesity is most prevalent in the 
socially disadvantaged, who are notoriously most 
difficult to reach and treat. Thus, WATCH IT was 
purposely located within socially disadvantaged 
areas of Leeds. Use of health trainers, rather than 
medical professionals, is part of an National Health 
Service (NHS) initiative to include a cost-effective 
addition to services aimed at tackling inequalities in 
health and targeting resources on individuals and 
areas in greatest need. WATCH IT health trainers are 
appointed for their personal qualities and commu-
nication skills. They do not have to have any formal 
health qualifications, but they receive 2 weeks of 
training in the intervention delivery and have 
ongoing support and supervision from a team leader 
(an educationalist), a children's nurse, dietician, 
psychologist, and a paediatrician. The WATCH IT 
programme takes a motivation-enhancing, solu-
tion-focussed approach and is embedded within 
Primary Care Trust Services in Leeds. The core pro-
gramme length is 4 months, after which families 
can opt to continue for a further 4 or 8 months. 
Child and parent/carer receive weekly individual 
appointments structured on the Healthy Eating 
Lifestyle Programme [6] and group physical activity 
sessions. Individual weekly appointments are pro-
vided for young people and their parents, allowing 
any emotional or social issues that may be affecting 
the young person's ability to achieve healthy behav-
iours also to be addressed. </p>

<p>Recruitment and consent </p>

<p>In order to determine whether we could recruit the 
desired number of participants and ascertain which 
recruitment methods were most successful, the 
number of enquiries and the consent rate were ana-
lysed. We sought to recruit 70 children over a 
6-month period beginning September 2006. This 
target was chosen pragmatically based on participa-
tion in the programme in previous years. Obese chil-
dren and adolescents considered for enrolment were </p>

<p>Feasibility RCT for WATCH IT 757 </p>

<p>http://ctj.sagepub.com 
Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755 -764 </p>

<p>aged 8-16 years and had a body mass index (BMI) &gt; 
98th percentile value and a parent or carer with flu-
ent spoken English. Children with a medical cause 
for obesity, severe learning difficulties, significant 
medical or psychiatric problems, or siblings already 
enrolled as participants were excluded. Candidate 
participants were recruited through health profes-
sionals or self-referral; publicity was amplified dur-
ing the recruitment period through media coverage. 
In addition, the WATCH IT database was searched 
for children who had been referred previously or 
enquired about the programme but had not taken 
part. During the study period, only families agreeing 
to be part of the research were able to enrol in the 
WATCH IT treatment programme. 
After informed consent (parental consent and 
child assent) and baseline assessment, participants 
were randomised to either WATCH IT or a waiting 
list control for 12 months using a remote automated 
telephone randomisation system. Randomisation 
was stratified by BMI standard deviation score (SDS; 
≤3.0 vs. &gt;3.0), age (≤12 years vs. &gt;12 years), gender, 
and maternal level of education (less than General 
Certificate of Secondary Education (GCSE) or equiv-
alent (attainment reached at the age of 16 years) vs. 
higher). Full ethical approval was obtained from the 
Leeds West NHS Research Ethics Committee. </p>

<p>Acceptability of randomisation and assessment procedures </p>

<p>Acceptability of randomisation and procedures was 
determined by measuring loss to follow-up and by 
exploring children's and parents' views about their 
participation in the research. Ten percent of trial 
participants (including families who had withdrawn 
from the intervention) were randomly selected to 
answer structured questions at the 12-month assess-
ment to ascertain their views on the randomisation 
procedure and outcome measures. Open response 
questions were used to get a general overview of 
acceptability (e.g., what has been your overall expe-
rience of the WATCH IT assessments? Please try to 
think about both positive and negative things); 
prompts were provided (e.g., what about the way 
that it was set up, so that you had a 50/50 chance of 
starting WATCH IT straight away, or going onto a 
waiting list?). Focussed questions concerning the 
assessments also were asked (e.g., do you have any 
comments about some of the types of tests and 
assessments that you or your child were asked to do 
during each visit?) with prompts (what about the 
blood tests that your child had? How about the 
questionnaires; you or your child?). Parents and 
children were interviewed separately; thus, a total 
of 14 interviews were conducted. Detailed contem-
poraneous notes were taken and transcribed at the 
end of the study by the project manager (M.B.). </p>

<p>Blinding </p>

<p>Baseline assessments were performed before ran-
domisation to avoid bias. Follow-up assessments 
performed after randomisation were conducted by 
assessors who were blinded to the treatment alloca-
tion for each family. A letter was mailed to partici-
pants prior to each assessment appointment 
explaining the need and importance of concealing 
their group allocations during assessments. In order 
to explore how effective our blinding strategy was, 
we asked our assessors to try to guess the treatment 
allocation of each family at the end of each assess-
ment. They were also asked to make a note of the 
point at which they thought that they had guessed 
the treatment allocation and whether the child or 
parent revealed the group identity. </p>

<p>Determination of primary outcome measure for the 
definitive trial </p>

<p>We examined the relationship between BMI, waist 
circumference, and bioimpedance (BIA) with dual 
energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) to determine 
the ability of these measures to predict change in 
adiposity as measured by DXA, so that the most fea-
sible and accurate measure could be included in 
future studies. Trained researchers measured weight, 
height, waist circumference, and BIA (HYDRA ECF-
ICF model 4200; Xitron technologies, San Diego, 
CA) and performed a DXA (Lunar Prodigy; GE 
Medical Systems, Madison, WI) scan at baseline and 
6 and 12 months. Height was measured to within 
0.1 cm using a wall-mounted Seca stadiometer 
(Vogel and Halke, Hamburg, Germany). To ensure 
consistency, two measurements were taken, and an 
average was used. Whenever they differed by &gt;0.5 
cm, a third measurement was taken, and an average 
of the closest two was used. Weight was measured 
in light clothing with no shoes (to within 0.1 kg) 
using a calibrated Seca digital weighing scale (Vogel 
and Halke). Waist was measured twice at 4 cm above 
the umbilicus. Whenever measurements were &gt;1.0 
cm apart, a third measurement was taken, and an 
average of the closest two was used. </p>

<p>Selection of secondary outcome measures for the 
definitive trial. </p>

<p>The following measurements were taken in the chil-
dren at baseline, 6, and 12 months to determine the 
feasibility and acceptability of their inclusion for a 
large multi-centre trial rather than treatment effect: 
2-h oral glucose tolerance, lipid level, liver function 
assay, blood pressure, fitness (step test), and physi-
cal activity over a 7-day period measured by acceler-
ometry (Actigraph ™ ). In addition, parental height </p>

<p>758 </p>

<p>M Bryant et al. </p>

<p>Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755 -764 
http://ctj.sagepub.com </p>

<p>and weight were measured. The time points of 6 
and 12 months (rather than at completion of the 
WATCH IT programme's four monthly stages) were 
chosen for reasons of cost and to allow comparison 
with other trials. Questionnaires included the 
WATCH IT Diet questionnaire and Home Food 
Availability checklist (two questionnaires designed 
specifically to examine foods aligned to the dietary 
goals promoted as part of the intervention), Dutch 
Eating Behaviour Questionnaire [8], Physical 
Activity Questionnaire for Children (PAC-Q) [9], 
Robinson School-Based Sedentary Behaviour 
Questionnaire [10], Paediatric Quality of Life 
(PedsQoL) [11], Strengths and Difficulties 
Questionnaire (SDQ) [12], and the Harter Scale of 
Perceived Social and Cognitive Competence [13]. 
These measures were chosen because they address 
key components of the intervention (i.e., diet, eat-
ing behaviour, physical activity, sedentary behav-
iour, and psychological well-being). Multiple 
measures of similar constructs were administered 
where possible (e.g., psychological well-being) to 
determine which measure to include in the defini-
tive trial according to feasibility, acceptability, and 
sensitivity. </p>

<p>Sample size estimation for full trial </p>

<p>Percent body fat from DXA was used as the primary 
outcome to estimate sample size for a multi-centre 
trial. We examined the variability of DXA measure-
ments and estimated the difference between control 
and intervention measurements over time, as these 
were unavailable from other studies. The study also 
provided a more accurate estimate of the likely 
eventual dropout rate in a larger trial. </p>

<p>Identification of shortcomings </p>

<p>Issues related to the research were monitored 
throughout the study period in order to identify 
and rectify any emerging shortcomings that were 
not previously considered in the study protocol. 
The project manager maintained a constant dia-
logue with the data collection staff, clinical staff, 
and study participants throughout the study 
period. In addition, clinical staff were asked to 
report the impact of the research on the WATCH 
IT programme at regular steering committee 
meetings. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>Feasibility studies are not designed to detect a treat-
ment effect and analysis should be mainly descrip-
tive or concentrate on confidence interval (CI) </p>

<p>estimation [14]. Data (mean, CIs) are presented 
below for interest even though the study was not 
powered to detect an effect of the intervention. 
Questionnaire feasibility was determined via partici-
pant acceptability, mean duration for completion 
(minutes), and standardised response means (SRM), 
a measure of the sensitivity of each questionnaire to 
detect change. SRM was calculated as mean change 
in scores or values divided by the standard deviation 
in change scores [15]. The SRM provides the relative 
magnitude of mean change compared with the var-
iability of change, with higher SRM values indicat-
ing greater sensitivity. BMI and waist circumference 
measurements were converted to SDSs using UK 
1990 growth references [16]. For selection of a pri-
mary outcome for the multi-centre trial (based on 
the ability of BMI, waist circumference, and BIA to 
predict DXA), multiple linear regression modelling 
was used, starting with a full model and using back-
wards selection, to identify which variables were 
predictors of DXA fat mass after adjusting for age 
and gender. Model assumptions were checked (nor-
mally distributed residuals and constant variance) 
and, when necessary, variables were log transformed 
to improve model fit. The models that best predicted 
baseline DXA (those with the most significant pre-
dictors and the highest R 2 value) were then applied 
separately to the 6-and 12-month DXA results in 
order to see how well the models predicted fat mass. 
Analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> software (ver-
sion 9.1; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Inc., Cary, NC). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>Characteristics of participants at baseline are shown 
in Table 1. Mean BMI SDS was greater in the control 
group, and there were more severely obese partici-
pants assigned to this group (BMI SDS ≥ 3.5). The 
majority of families were Caucasian and economi-
cally disadvantaged. Just more than 50% had an 
annual household income below £15,000, with 
14% earning less than £5000 per year. The majority 
of mothers were not educated beyond GCSE or 
equivalent. </p>

<p>Recruitment and consent </p>

<p>Ninety-six children were newly referred during the 
study recruitment period from September 2006 to 
March 2007. Sixty-three (66%) of these children 
were recruited and consented to the trial from these 
de novo referrals. A further seven families were 
recruited by identifying and contacting 84 families 
who had been referred to WATCH IT previously but 
had not responded to correspondence from the </p>

<p>Feasibility RCT for WATCH IT 759 </p>

<p>http://ctj.sagepub.com 
Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755 -764 </p>

<p>clinical staff and who had not joined the pro-
gramme. We therefore attained our target of 70 par-
ticipants randomised in a 7-month time frame, that 
is, 39% of 180 contacts or referrals. Thirty partici-
pants (31%) were professionally referred and 66 
(69%) were self-referred. More self-referred families 
consented to participate in the research than profes-
sionally referred families (55% and 29%, respec-
tively). The most effective form of promotion was 
television compared with methods such as newspa-
per, poster, radio, and email advertisements, with 
television accounting for 41% of referrals. General 
practitioners made 79% of professional referrals; the 
remainder were from school nurses and other pro-
fessionals. </p>

<p>Acceptability of randomisation and 
assessment procedures </p>

<p>Figure 1 shows the flow of participants through the 
study, including those lost to follow-up. Only 22 eli-
gible referrals that could be contacted declined to 
take part. Of these, one refusal was due to the research 
process (i.e., the possibility of taking the child out of 
school for the research assessments); one was due to </p>

<p>a family bereavement; and the remainder were not 
interested in attending the WATCH IT programme. 
Of the 10% of families who were randomly 
selected to provide feedback at the end of the study, 
all except one parent reported a positive experience. 
Parents allocated to the control arm reported that 
they were disappointed that they had to wait but 
said they would do so again for the well-being of 
their child. Despite individual consent provided at 
the start of the study, one parent voiced ethical con-
cerns about the randomisation procedure. The 
majority of parents said that the assessments were 
interesting and that they were happy to be occupied 
completing questionnaires while their child was 
engaged in assessments. Children and adolescents 
were also positive about the assessments and enjoyed 
doing some of the tests; most stated that the base-
line blood test was the worst part of participation. 
When asked about individual components, few neg-
ative comments were made by parents. Many noted 
that they did not like their child having a blood test 
but understood the necessity. One parent com-
plained that the child was asked to attend on a 
school morning, resulting in the need to reschedule 
appointments to holiday periods. We also asked the 
children and adolescents about their understanding 
of the randomisation procedure and all responded 
that they understood and that they did not mind 
the risk of having to wait for 12 months. </p>

<p>Blinding </p>

<p>Assessors recorded estimations of participant group 
allocation for 86 assessments. Overall, they assumed 
that the majority of assessments were with control 
participants and correctly guessed the group alloca-
tion for 76% of 6-month assessments and 51% of 
12-month assessments. Six participants inadvert-
ently revealed their group allocation at 6 months 
(four from the intervention group) and five did so 
during the 12-month assessment (one from the 
intervention group). Of those who accidentally 
revealed their group allocation at 6 months, alloca-
tions were guessed correctly for three participants at 
12 months. The most common point at which the 
assessor guessed the group allocation was during the 
fitness test, which was the final test. This test is also 
administered as part of the WATCH IT programme. </p>

<p>Determination of primary outcome 
measure for the multi-centre trial </p>

<p>Results indicate that BMI (r = 0.93; 95% CI 0.88, 
0.95; p &lt; 0.0001), waist circumference (r = 0.83; 95% 
CI 0.73, 0.89; p &lt; 0.0001), and BIA (r = 0.94; 95% CI 
0.92, 0.97; p &lt; 0.0001) strongly correlated with DXA </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline participant characteristics </p>

<p>Intervention 
(N = 35) 
Control 
(N = 35) </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD </p>

<p>Child age (years) 
11.5 
1.8 
11.3 
2.2 
Guardian age (years) 
40.5 
10.2 
39.5 
6.7 
Child BMI SDS 
2.86 
0.45 
3.11 
0.47 </p>

<p>N 
% 
N 
% </p>

<p>Gender -boys 
13 
37 
12 
34 
Gender -female carer 
31 
89 
34 
97 
Highest level of maternal education 
None 
6 
17 
5 
14 
GCSE or equivalent a 
15 
43 
17 
49 
A-level or equivalent a 
5 
14 
6 
17 
Degree or higher 
9 
26 
7 
20 
Child ethnicity 
White 
32 
91 
29 
83 
South Asian 
0 
0 
3 
9 
Black 
1 
3 
2 
6 
Mixed ethnicity 
1 
3 
1 
3 
Annual household income 
Less than £5000 
3 
9 
5 
14 
£5000-£14,999 
14 
40 
13 
37 
£15,000-£35,000 
11 
31 
11 
35 
More than £35,000 
7 
20 
6 
17 </p>

<p>a General Certificate of Secondary Education (GCSE) and A-levels are 
national examinations taken at the age of 16 and 18 years, respectively. </p>

<p>760 </p>

<p>M Bryant et al. </p>

<p>Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755 -764 
http://ctj.sagepub.com </p>

<p>results, with a lower (but moderate) correlation of 
DXA measurements with BMI SDS (r = 0.55; 95% CI 
0.35, 0.7; p &lt; 0.0001) and waist circumference SDS (r 
= 0.62; 95% CI 0.45, 0.75; p &lt; 0.0001). Results were 
similar for cross-sectional and longitudinal analy-
ses, with BIA consistently demonstrating the strong-
est relationship with DXA and greatest ability to 
predict future adiposity as measured by DXA. </p>

<p>Selection of secondary outcome measures 
for the multi-centre trial </p>

<p>No negative comments were made during feedback 
interviews for any individual assessment. However, 
data collection staff reported that children often com-
plained or exhibited apathy during completion of 
the Harter scale and the WATCH IT diet question-
naire, which took longer to complete than the other </p>

<p>questionnaires (Table 2). The Harter scale took twice 
as long to complete as the other psychological meas-
ures, including the SDQ and the PedsQoL. The 
WATCH IT diet questionnaire had many questions 
asking about foods and drinks throughout the day, 
with five simple summary questions aimed at estimat-
ing consumption of some key items over the whole 
day. On examination, there was a moderate correlation 
between the summary questions and the sum of the 
detailed individual items (R 2 range 0.5-0.7; p &lt; 0.001), 
indicating that it would be possible and desirable to 
change the format to focus on the summary questions. 
SRMs were calculated to estimate the sensitivity of 
each questionnaire to detect change. While insufficient 
data were available to determine a clinically sufficient 
SRM for each of the tools, we were able to make com-
parisons between questionnaires. Comparisons were 
especially important for psychological questionnaires 
in which more than one outcome was measured. SRM </p>

<p>Baseline assessment 
n=70 
(n=7 from existing 
database, n= 63 from 
new referrals) </p>

<p>Referred during study 
period n=96 
On existing WATCH IT 
referral database but 
had not participated in 
programme 
n=84 </p>

<p>Enrolment </p>

<p>Ineligible n= 37 
Could not contact n=51 
Declined participation 
n=22 </p>

<p>Consented n=70 </p>

<p>Randomisation </p>

<p>Control 
n=35 
Intervention 
n=35 </p>

<p>6-month assessment 
n=30 (86%) 
Loss to follow-up 
n=5 </p>

<p>6-month assessment 
n=26 (74%) 
Loss to follow-up 
n=9 </p>

<p>Follow-up </p>

<p>12-month assessment 
n=27 (77%) 
Loss to follow-up 
n=8 </p>

<p>12-month assessment 
n=26 (74%) 
Loss to follow-up 
n=9 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flow of participants in the feasibility trial of WATCH IT. </p>

<p>Feasibility RCT for WATCH IT 761 </p>

<p>http://ctj.sagepub.com 
Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755 -764 </p>

<p>values for change between baseline and 12 months for 
the psychological well-being scales are shown in Table 2, 
with the PedsQoL demonstrating the greatest sensitivity. 
Thus, overall, the PedsQoL was considered the most fea-
sible psychological well-being questionnaire, with a rela-
tively low time for completion and the greatest sensitivity. 
Valid accelerometer data in which there was at 
least 500 min of recording for at least 3 days [17] 
were recorded for 51, 27, and 28 children at base-
line, 6, and 12 months, respectively, translating to 
73% (51/70), 48% (27/56), and 53% (28/53) of com-
plete accelerometry data for those participants who 
remained in the trial. </p>

<p>Sample size estimation for full-scale trial </p>

<p>To calculate the target sample size, we assumed that 
the primary outcome variable for the full-scale trial 
will be percent body fat at 12 months based on DXA 
measurement. A standard deviation of 2.3 in change 
in percent body fat was observed in the feasibility 
study. In the absence of clinical information regard-
ing what constitutes a clinically important differ-
ence in change in percent body fat, we assumed that 
a difference of 0.75 is important, which translates to 
a standardised effect size of 0.326, usually consid-
ered moderate. Thus, 199 participants per group 
would be required to provide 90% power at the 5% 
significance level. However, as the sample size cal-
culations should account for the natural clustering 
of outcomes by trainer (we estimated sample cluster 
size to be at most 16 children in the full-scale trial), 
the sample size was inflated by a design effect of 
1.75 (assuming an intraclass correlation coefficient 
(ICC) of 0.05) to yield a revised total sample size of 
69 participants. Allowing for 25% loss to follow-up 
(as observed in the feasibility study), we estimated </p>

<p>that the multi-centre trial would require 930 par-
ticipants to provide a definitive indication of clini-
cal effectiveness and to allow a moderate effect size 
to be detected in other outcomes. </p>

<p>Identification of shortcomings </p>

<p>The research process was found to impact nega-
tively on the WATCH IT programme in a number of 
ways. Attendance data for the programme were 
comparable with those of the pilot study [6], with 
74% (n = 26) completing the core 4-month phase, 
and 63% (n = 22) and 46% (n = 16) opting to con-
tinue for a further 4 or 8 months, respectively. In 
order to maximise participation in the feasibility 
study, entry into WATCH IT was only via the trial 
during the study period and usual enrolment was 
halted immediately prior to its start. As a result of 
randomisation of families to the waiting list, the 
programme ran at reduced capacity. Health trainers 
reported a disruption to group sessions (especially 
physical activity sessions), in which they believed 
that the children were less motivated. The health 
trainers also complained that the requirement to 
adhere to protocol constrained them and prevented 
them from working in a more flexible manner to suit 
the individual needs of children. Another major influ-
ence of the research was that at the end of the trial, 
capacity had to double to allow the waiting list con-
trol participants immediate access to the programme 
as they had been guaranteed during recruitment. </p>

<p>Change in BMI and adiposity </p>

<p>The trial was not powered to demonstrate effective-
ness of the intervention with only 35 children per </p>

<p>Table 2. Questionnaire feasibility </p>

<p>Domains 
Administration duration, minutes (range) 
SRM a </p>

<p>Harter Scale [13] 
Self-esteem 
9.1 (1-29) 
0.01 
PedsQoL 
Social functioning 
Child 
3.5 (1-15) 
0.55 
Parent 
-b 
0.36 
SDQ [12] 
Behavioural screening 
Child 
4.3 (1-14) 
−0.37 
Parent 
-b 
−0.51 
DEBQ [8] 
Eating behaviour 
6.3 (1-23) 
0.33 
WATCH IT c diet 
Dietary intake 
12.5 (1-43) 
NA d 
PAC-Q [9] 
Physical activity 
9.1 (1-45) 
0.14 
Robinson screen time 
Duration and frequency of screen time 
10.2 (1-33) 
0.13 </p>

<p>a Standardised response mean (SRM; sensitivity, calculated by mean change divided by the standard deviation in change scores [15]). 
b Parent completion was not timed. 
c Developed specifically for WATCH IT. 
d Questionnaire does not generate a single score. </p>

<p>762 </p>

<p>M Bryant et al. </p>

<p>Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755 -764 
http://ctj.sagepub.com </p>

<p>treatment arm. Mean change in BMI SDS was 0.03 
(95% CI −0.05, 0.11) in the intervention group and 
−0.03 (95% CI −0.12, 0.06) in the control group. 
Change in percent body fat was 1.40 (95% CI 0.31, 
2.38) for the intervention group and 0.20 (95% CI 
−1.41, 1.72) for the control group. Mean change in 
waist circumference SDS was −0.08 (95% CI −0.24, 
0.07) in the intervention group and −0.03 (95% CI 
−0.16, 0.11) in the control group. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The findings from our feasibility trial can be used to 
inform the design and conduct of trials in child-
hood obesity research. We were able to recruit the 
desired number of participants within a desirable 
time frame and showed acceptable loss to follow-up 
for the research that was comparable with other sim-
ilar research protocols [1]. Furthermore, our recruit-
ment strategy resulted in adequate numbers of 
children from socially disadvantaged families, a 
group that are more likely to be obese, yet can be 
difficult to access and recruit into research. However, 
the majority of families were of White British nation-
ality; we therefore learnt that recruitment of a more 
heterogeneous ethnic sample warrants considera-
tion in future research. The research methodology 
was acceptable to participants, and the recruitment 
strategies were successful. However, returning to an 
old database to recruit families who had been 
referred previously to an ongoing programme but 
had failed to participate in it was not productive. 
Implementation of the feasibility trial has ena-
bled us to develop a robust protocol for a definitive 
multi-centre trial. However, since the feasibility trial 
was only conducted at one centre, we recognise that 
there may be other feasibility issues with multiple 
centres that were not measurable or observed at a 
single centre. Key findings did not necessarily form 
part of the formal hypotheses of the trial. However, 
the feasibility trial enables us to address issues that 
were not been considered prior to the conduct of 
large multi-centre trials. Potential shortcomings, 
related to pragmatic issues associated with data col-
lection, were identified. For example, initiation of 
an intervention was dependent upon the needs and 
availability of both the family and the programme, 
and the actual intervention start date could not 
always immediately follow baseline assessment. 
Thus, baseline measurements may have changed 
prior to the actual start of the intervention. Designers 
of future protocols should consider adopting a flex-
ible start date for the intervention. Similarly, follow-
up assessments may not be made exactly as specified 
in the research timeline because of holidays or sick-
ness. Other key lessons for the design of an evalua-
tion of a complex intervention in obese children are </p>

<p>that blinding of assessors is important to reduce 
bias; automated electronic randomisation improves 
efficiency and separates responsibility from the 
researcher; children should be interviewed without 
their parents; and careful consideration should be 
placed on the ordering of assessments. We discov-
ered that assessment blinding was most likely to 
become compromised during a test that also was 
administered as part of the intervention programme. 
Thus, future study designs should ensure tests which 
can reveal group allocation (i.e., those most likely to 
stimulate conversation related to the intervention) 
should be administered late in the assessment. Our 
initial protocol did not consider interviewing chil-
dren separately from their parents. It soon became 
apparent, however, that separation would be neces-
sary in order to get responses to questionnaires 
directly from the child, rather than via the parent. 
In the first two interviews, it was obvious that par-
ents found it difficult to avoid answering the ques-
tions for their children. 
Retention strategies were not formalised within 
the protocol, but we had an acceptable level of 
dropout (24% withdrawal overall). On reflection, 
we believe that establishing a good rapport with 
both children and their parents was essential, along 
with providing full details of the level of involve-
ment required as part of participation in both the 
intervention and research. Recruitment and con-
sent occurred within a clinical setting and was con-
ducted by a childhood obesity expert, helping to 
formalise the value and prestige of participation. 
The feasibility trial also provided an excellent 
test bed for potential outcome measures for a defin-
itive trial. We used DXA to measure fat mass as a 
primary outcome, which incurred a cost of £14,700. 
We estimated that its use in the definitive trial 
(based on the suggested sample size of 930) would 
cost £195,300. Financial constraints and availability 
of a DXA apparatus therefore may preclude it use. 
Since DXA data were well correlated with BMI, BIA, 
and waist circumference, which primary outcome 
to use may be a pragmatic choice. Secondary out-
comes in childhood obesity research are notoriously 
difficult to measure. Self-report methods often are 
biased systematically and objective measures are 
usually expensive and often infeasible. There is a 
lack of consistency in the use of outcome measures, 
in part, due to a lack of valid tools. Importantly, 
through this work, we have confirmed that more 
research is required to have confidence in the sec-
ondary outcome measures. While we found the 
measures to be feasible, we believe that more 
research is necessary to ascertain the validity and 
reliability of outcomes within a paediatric obese 
population. The UK National Obesity Observatory 
has published a standard evaluation framework to 
guide proficient research for assessing childhood </p>

<p>Feasibility RCT for WATCH IT 763 </p>

<p>http://ctj.sagepub.com 
Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755 -764 </p>

<p>obesity interventions, but it is evident that one of 
the greatest barriers at present is the lack of valid 
and reliable outcome measures [18]. 
Accelerometry is accepted as a useful and objec-
tive method to measure habitual physical activity 
[19-21]. However, in a community-based paediatric 
sample, we had many monitors that were returned 
without valid data. Using relatively relaxed criteria 
for data quality of at least 500 min of recording for 
at least 3 days [17], we received only 53% of acceler-
ometers with valid data at 12 months. Given the 
high degree of resources required from researchers 
and participants to collect accelerometry data, 
future researchers with this type of population 
should consider carefully whether their collection is 
cost-effective. Lower criteria might have to be 
accepted; for example, rather than choosing a pre-
defined inclusion criterion (e.g., minimum of 10 h a 
day), Alhassan et al. [22] calculated the number of 
minutes required to obtain a correlation coefficient 
of 0.80 for the average count per minute of ran-
domly selected blocks of 30 min correlated with 
average counts for the full day. 
Importantly, this feasibility trial enabled us to 
estimate sample size for a future multi-centre RCT. 
Based on our calculations, we estimated that 930 
children would be required to detect a statistically 
significant moderate difference between the inter-
vention and control group, a larger sample size than 
those of studies in the recent Cochrane report on 
interventions for treating obesity in children [1], in 
which, out of 64 trials reported, the average number 
of randomised participants was 85 with a range of 
16-539 participants. Because of expected clustering 
by trainer, we inflated the nominal sample size by 
assuming an ICC of 0.05. Sample size was calculated 
assuming individual level randomisation, in addi-
tion to the inflation factor. Data from the feasibility 
study enabled us to realistically estimate variation, in 
addition to likely intraclass correlation of outcomes. 
Assessing the influence of interventions according 
to efficacy (i.e., assessment in people who received 
the assigned intervention and adhered to the proto-
col) and effectiveness (i.e., assessment in all people 
assigned to the intervention, regardless of protocol 
adherence) [23] is challenging since the difference 
between efficacy and effectiveness is not clear in the 
evaluation of complex interventions and they may 
not be mutually distinct. Rather, owing to the com-
plexities of behavioural change interventions, they 
may be viewed as a continuum. For example, we are 
confident that our study design meets scientific rig-
our in terms of optimising independence of the treat-
ment effect via implementation of carefully allocated 
active and control conditions, appropriately strati-
fied randomisation, use of standardised treatment 
and evaluation protocols, generation of a homogene-
ous comparison group, and optimal blinding. </p>

<p>Demonstration of such study characteristics lends 
itself to provision of evidence of efficacy. However, 
the nature of the intervention and its delivery within 
the NHS results in uncertainty of the level of adher-
ence to the interventions regardless of provider fidel-
ity to the intervention. Because it is not possible to 
consider all potential confounding factors within a 
community-based intervention for which partici-
pants are expected to make lifestyle changes, efficacy 
cannot be guaranteed. Ultimately, the WATCH IT 
programme aims to provide services across the UK. 
Thus, it is imperative that it demonstrate effective-
ness (rather than efficacy) under 'real-world' condi-
tions or in 'natural' settings [24]. Furthermore, it has 
been argued that trials demonstrating efficacy are 
not essential before effectiveness trials are conducted, 
provided that the effectiveness trial meets all of the 
standards of efficacy trials. 
The feasibility trial allowed us to identify the 
impact of research on the normal operation of the 
intervention programme. With initiation of the fea-
sibility study, the programme initially was con-
strained to operate at lower than usual capacity due 
to randomisation. It then had to increase capacity 
at the end of the trial to allow entry of the waiting 
list control group participants. Recognition of these 
issues has informed the design of future trials, which 
must address the impact of randomisation on pro-
grammes during the trials and at their conclusion. 
Surprisingly, we also discovered through the health 
trainers that families who had started WATCH IT 
before the trial and were not involved in the research 
(but who were integrated with the trial participants) 
were disappointed that their clinical assessment 
lacked the depth that was given in the trial assess-
ments. Such information has enabled us to consider 
the importance of working with the service provid-
ers and service users in the design of future trials; it 
is possible that future trials will be conducted only 
in areas where there is no established service. A con-
stant dialogue was maintained with the service pro-
viders throughout the study period to help the 
researchers to understand the impact of the study 
on the intervention. In addition, we elicited formal 
feedback from at least one service provider during 
regular steering committee meetings. While this 
feedback ensured that we met the feasibility study 
objectives, we recommend continued service pro-
vider involvement in the design of future RCTs in 
order to gain greater understanding of the processes 
involved in generating a behavioural change. 
To conclude, this feasibility trial has been invalu-
able in informing the design of future research for 
WATCH IT, and importantly, it has emphasised the 
necessity for any childhood obesity intervention 
research to follow guidelines for the evaluation of 
complex interventions. We hope that lessons learned 
from the conduct of our feasibility RCT will help </p>

<p>764 </p>

<p>M Bryant et al. </p>

<p>Clinical Trials 2011; 8: 755 -764 
http://ctj.sagepub.com </p>

<p>future researchers. However, we recommend that all 
researchers evaluating the effect of obesity interven-
tions conduct an exploratory feasibility or pilot study 
prior to designing definitive trials of effectiveness. 
Feasibility testing of obesity interventions is com-
mon in the literature, but there remains a lack of 
studies that test the feasibility of conducting the 
research. Those that do provide valuable assistance to 
future researchers [25] but cannot substitute the con-
duct of feasibility trials related to the evaluation of 
specific interventions. Our results have highlighted 
the appropriateness of following a cyclical sequence 
of research pathways, as suggested by the MRC [2], so 
that additional formative research can be considered 
prior to large-scale testing if necessary. In doing so, 
researchers and clinical staff can avoid wasting time 
and/or resources on running definitive trials before 
they are 100% confident in both the research and the 
intervention. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This research was supported by the Wellcome Trust 
Ltd. (078174/Z05/Z). ISRCTN registration number: 
ISRCTN95431788. </p>



</text></tei>