<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3252618" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background The India AIDS Initiative (Avahan) project is 
involved in rapid scale-up of HIV-prevention interventions 
in high-risk populations. This study examines the cost 
variation of 107 non-governmental organisations (NGOs) 
implementing targeted interventions, over the start up 
(defined as period from project inception until services to 
the key population commenced) and first 2 years of 
intervention. 
Methods The Avahan interventions for female and male 
sex workers and their clients, in 62 districts of four 
southern states were costed for the financial years 
2004/2005 and 2005/2006 using standard costing 
techniques. Data sources include financial and economic 
costs from the lead implementing partners (LPs) and 
subcontracted local implementing NGOs retrospectively 
and prospectively collected from a provider perspective. 
Ingredients and step-down allocation processes were 
used. Outcomes were measured using routinely 
collected project data. The average costs were 
estimated and a regression analysis carried out to 
explore causes of cost variation. Costs were calculated 
in US$ 2006. 
Results The total number of registered people was 
134 391 at the end of 2 years, and 124 669 had used STI 
services during that period. The median average cost of 
Avahan programme for this period was $76 per person 
registered with the project. Sixty-one per cent of the cost 
variation could be explained by scale (positive 
association), number of NGOs per district (negative), 
number of LPs in the state (negative) and project maturity 
(positive) (p&lt;0.0001). 
Conclusions During rapid scale-up in the initial phase of 
the Avahan programme, a significant reduction in 
average costs was observed. As full scale-up had not yet 
been achieved, the average cost at scale is yet to be 
realised and the extent of the impact of scale on costs 
yet to be captured. Scale effects are important to 
quantify for planning resource requirements of large-
scale interventions. The average cost after 2 years is 
within the range of global scale-up costs estimates and 
other studies in India. </p>

<p>The Avahan programme is a unique large-scale HIV 
prevention programme supported by the Bill and 
Melinda Gates Foundation. It works with local 
implementing non-governmental organisations 
(NGOs) supported through lead implementing part-</p>

<p>ners (LPs) at the state level to deliver prevention 
activities for high-risk and bridge populations in 
India. 
1 The programme is focused on four Southern 
States (Andhra Pradesh, Karnataka, Tamil Nadu, 
Maharashtra) and the two north-eastern states of 
Manipur and Nagaland. An integral part of the 
programme is its evaluation, designed to provide 
lessons on the roll-out of large-scale national 
programmes. 
2 The multilevel analysis includes a cost-
effectiveness analysis of the programme. This will 
provide new insight into the overall costs of large-
scale national programme roll out, their cost struc-
tures, factors that influence costs and the cost-effec-
tiveness of reaching high-risk and bridge populations. 
Costs of HIV-prevention efforts are poorly under-
stood, thus limiting the ability to plan and forecast 
costs for implementation. 
3e8 Previous cost studies of 
India National AIDS Control Programme (NACP) 
NGO projects focus on the NGO level and have a 
1-year time frame, excluding costs of funding 
partners 
9e15 (and National AIDS Control Organisa-
tion's Revised Costing Guidelines for Targeted Inter-
ventions working with HRGs under NACPIII. 2009. 
http://www.nacoonline.org/Divisions/Finance_Divi-
sion/Revised_costing_guidelines_for_Targeted_Inter-
ventions_working_with_HRGs_under_NACP-III/). 
Only two studies examine the causes of cost 
variation. 
14 16 Factors that might influence costs 
include scale, the typology of the target population, 
the difference in LP, the age of the intervention, 
geographical location and other contextual 
factors. 
13 17 18 A review of empirical and econo-
metric evidence of costs found that targeted 
prevention activities among sex workers demon-
strated scale effects, with 38e88% of cost variation 
attributed to scale. </p>

<p>5   There are a limited number of peer-reviewed 
studies on the costs of HIV prevention services in 
Asia. The Avahan programme provides a unique 
opportunity to fill this gap in the evidence by 
prospectively measuring the costs of a large-scale 
programme and incorporating all levels of the 
delivery system and the start up activities. This 
paper explores the cost of Avahan activities during 
the first 2 years of its activity (financial years 2004/ 
2005 and 2005/2006) as it moves from start-up to 
rapid scale-up. It documents the costs of imple-
mentation of HIV prevention for female sex 
workers (FSWs), men who have sex with men 
(MSM) and transgenders (TGs) in 62 districts of the 
four Southern states where Avahan was </p>

<p>1 Department of Public Health 
and Policy, London School of 
Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, 
London, UK 
2 St John's Research 
Institute, Bangalore, India 
3 Karnataka Health Promotion 
Trust, Bangalore, India 
4 Population Health Research 
Unit, Centre hospitalier affilié 
universitaire de Québec, Canada </p>

<p>Correspondence to 
Dr Sudha Chandrashekar, No 
206, 15th B Cross, West of 
Chord Road, Mahalaxmipuram, 
Bangalore 560086, Karnataka, 
India; sudhashreec@yahoo.co.in </p>

<p>Accepted 3 December 2009 </p>

<p>This paper is freely available 
online under the BMJ Journals 
unlocked scheme, see http://sti. 
bmj.com/site/about/unlocked. 
xhtml </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 1):i89ei94. doi:10.1136/sti.2009.038547 
i89 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>operational, calculates the cost per person registered and the cost 
per STI (sexually transmitted infection) clinic visit and analyses 
the causes of cost variation across the NGO projects. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Programme description </p>

<p>Avahan started in late 2003/early 2004 and is a focused 
prevention program, reaching the high-risk groups and bridge 
populations, in geographical locations most affected. The 
Avahan programme is delivered by grassroots NGOs supported 
by state-level LPs who are large Indian or international NGOs. 
The LPs subcontracted local implementing NGOs and provided 
technical and management support to the NGOs. The package 
of prevention interventions address proximate determinants of 
risk through outreach, behaviour-change communication on safe 
sex (BCC), free or socially marketed condom distribution, needle 
and syringe exchange (for injecting-drug use) and treatment of 
STIs as well as distal determinants (stigma, violence, the legal 
environment, medical infrastructure, mobility and migration, 
and gender) through structural interventions and community 
mobilisation. 
1 Within 4 years, the programme had scaled up to 
reach 226 855 high-risk group individuals monthly. </p>

<p>19   Sample </p>

<p>Over the 2-year period of analysis (2004/2005 and 2005/2006), 107 
NGO projects were functioning in the 62 districts operational at 
the time (see table 1), providing intervention services for FSWs 
(38), MSM/TG (9) and mixed populations (60). Cost data were 
collected from each district and from six LPs in four states. 
Fifteen districts in the first year and 11 in the second, covering 38 
NGO projects, were selected for detailed costing (see table 1). In 
the remaining districts, a more general costing based on routine 
data was carried out. 
2 The detailed costing enabled a better 
understanding of economic costs, how costs and cost structures 
change with scaling up and an activitywise costing. The sites 
were selected in consultation with the LPs to best represent the 
different level of activities across the NGOs. Costs of the external 
programme evaluation and research studies are not included. </p>

<p>Methodological approach </p>

<p>An ingredients approach was used to consider full financial and 
economic costs from the provider perspective based on the 
UNAIDS 'Costing Guidelines for HIV Prevention Strategies' and 
as recommended by the Asian Development Bank. 
20 21 Financial 
costs represent actual expenditure on goods and services 
purchased. Economic costs include the estimated value of all 
inputs including donated or subsidised goods and services. Costs </p>

<p>were classified as recurrent or capital. Additionally, classifications 
by activity at the level of the local implementing NGO (ie, 
capacity building, BCC, STI services, condom promotion, 
community mobilisation, monitoring, planning and coordina-
tion, start-up activities, enabling environment and others) and 
organisational level (eg, NGO, district, state) were carried out. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>Cost data were obtained from the financial records used for 
routine financial and management reporting of the NGOs, LPs 
and foundation office in Delhi, as well as staff records and 
interviews with staff. For the detailed costing sites, details of 
donated goods and services were collected from the project. The 
economic costs of these items were valued at market prices 
obtained from local shops and interviews with project staff. 
Process output and outcome data were extracted from the 
management information system (MIS) of the project and 
project reports. All data were entered into a specifically designed 
<rs type="software">MS Excel</rs> workbook. </p>

<p>Recurrent costs </p>

<p>Personnel costs included salaries and expenses of all staff 
including peer educators, volunteers and shared resource 
personnel. The peer educator time was valued at the honorarium 
paid, except where peers were not paid. In the latter case and for 
other volunteers, their cost was valued based on time spent on 
the project and the value of their time, estimated as per their 
average earnings or, if unemployed, the corresponding payment 
to peers in NACP targeted interventions. 
All expenses related to project building and operating 
expenses, travel and monitoring were obtained from project 
accounts. In three of the states, the cost of STI supplies was 
taken from expenditure records obtained from the LP or NGO 
where they were held. In one state, STI provision was 
contracted out to an agency, and so supply costs were obtained 
directly from the agency. Condom costs were calculated using 
the number of free condoms distributed (supplied by the 
primary health centre or government hospitals) and the price of 
the lowest cost alternative in the market, that is, subsidised 
socially marketed condoms. Indirect costs included project-
management administration and overhead costs at the NGO and 
LP level, and were obtained from expenditure statements. </p>

<p>Capital costs </p>

<p>In the financial costing, capital costs (including training and 
start up inputs) were annualised using straight-line economic 
depreciation, in which the total cost of the good is divided by 
the working life of that item. Economic costs were annualised 
using a discount rate of 10%, reflecting the long-term interest 
rates in India. A standard discount rate of 3% was then used in 
a sensitivity analysis. 
22 23 Capital equipment was assumed to 
have a life of between 5 and 10 years, depending on the item. 
Start-up and training costs were annualised over the lifetime of 
the project (assumed to be 5 years). The start-up period was 
defined as from project inception until the start of services to the 
key population and project output reporting commenced. 
Recurrent costs in the start-up period were treated as capital 
costs and annualised. Start-up period capital costs were allocated 
to the start-up period based on percentage months of start-up. 
Rent for project offices was included as a capital item. </p>

<p>Calculation of total and average costs </p>

<p>Both economic and financial costs were obtained from detailed 
costing sites. Where only financial cost data were available at the </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary of districts included in the cost analysis of Avahan 
for first 2 years of activity </p>

<p>State lead 
partner </p>

<p>No of districts (number 
of non-governmental 
organisations) costed 
in year 1 </p>

<p>No of districts (number 
of non-governmental 
organisations) costed 
in year 2 </p>

<p>Full 
sample </p>

<p>Detailed 
costing </p>

<p>Full 
sample </p>

<p>Detailed 
costing </p>

<p>Tamil Nadu 
12 (24) 
e 
12 (25) 
2 (7) 
Karnataka 
15 (15) 
15 (15) 
16 (17) 
3 (4) 
Maharashtra 1 
e 
e 
11 (12) 
2 (2) 
Maharashtra 2 
e 
e 
2 (14) 
1 (5) 
Andhra Pradesh 1 
8 (10) 
e 
8 (10) 
1 (1) 
Andhra Pradesh 2 
9 (21) 
e 
13 (29) 
2 (4) 
All Avahan 
44 (70) 
15 (15) 
62 (107) 
11 (23) </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 1):i89ei94. doi:10.1136/sti.2009.038547 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>general cost sites, these were inflated by the average percentage 
difference between financial and economic costs at the detailed 
sites to obtain estimates of economic costs. Unless directly 
allocable, the LP level costs were allocated to each NGO 
according to the percentage of the total LP target population the 
NGO covered. Only financial costs were available for the Bill &amp; 
Melinda Gates Foundation India office and the capacity devel-
opment partners. These costs were allocated equally to each of 
the LPs. Given this and to ensure comparability with other 
studies that do not include central costs, these costs are reported 
separately. 
The total costs of the Avahan programme were calculated by 
summing up the total capital and recurrent costs at all levels of the 
intervention (NGO, LP). Average costs were obtained by dividing 
total costs by the relevant output indicators to obtain estimates of 
the cost per person registered and cost per person accessing STI 
services. Scale, in the economic sense, reflects the extent or level of 
activity at which an intervention is operating. 
13 In the Avahan 
programme, this is defined as utilisation coverage. 
19 As the MIS 
was not functioning in all NGOs until 2006, the LPs were 
consulted to select measures of utilisation. People were registered 
with a project only once they had developed a rapport with the 
project sufficient to obtain personal details, including client 
volume and sex-work history. This enables peer educators to 
actively pursue the provision of services to these individuals. As 
a result, this was used alongside people receiving STI services. 
However, due to the early stage of development of the MIS, 
average costs were therefore not available for all NGOs. 
Costs were adjusted for inflation using the average consumer 
price index for the year. 
24 All costs are presented in constant INR 
(2006) and converted to US dollars using (1 US $¼44.3) (http:// 
www.oanda.com). </p>

<p>Activity costing </p>

<p>In order to allocate the time between activities, the time that 
each individual spent on the project was assessed using time-
sheets provided to the relevant staff at the detailed costing sites 
and completed over 1 week. The project specific personnel costs 
were allocated using the percentage of time spent on various 
activities. General staff time was allocated equally across all the 
activities. From these allocations, a total activitywise recurrent 
personnel cost was calculated. Directly allocable recurrent and 
capital costs such as training costs, STI services, BCC costs were 
allocated to the specific activity. Non-allocable costs such as rent, 
building operating and maintenance, and travel costs were allo-
cated among activities using the personnel cost percentage. The 
average activitywise allocations obtained at the detailed costing 
sites were used to allocate costs at the general costing sites. </p>

<p>Analysis of variation in average costs </p>

<p>Multivariate linear regression analysis was used to give an initial 
insight into the causes of the variation in average cost between 
local implementing NGOs. The analysis explored the relation-
ship of cost per person registered with scale, high-risk group 
(MSM/TG or FSW), age of intervention, number of Avahan 
NGOs in the district, whether the NGO was in a metropolitan 
area, number of LPs in the state and by LPs by adding each 
variable progressively into the model. The regression was carried 
out using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS</rs>, Chicago). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>At the end of the 2-year period, the Avahan interventions in the 
four Southern states were being implemented in 62 districts by </p>

<p>107 NGOs. The median start up time for the programme was 
3 months (range 0e6 months). The programme had 134 391 
people registered, and utilisation at the NGO level varied from 37 
to 6315 people registered (n¼93). The total cost of the 
programme was US$16 759 189 (see table 2). Table 2 shows that 
personnel costs were 40.4%, and STI supply costs were 8.0% of 
total costs. Travel costs and training costs constituted 7.7% each 
and indirect expenses 3.4% of the total, respectively. The 
economic costs were 6% higher than the financial costs. When 
using a 3% discount rate, the total costs fall to US$16.6 million. 
The analysis found that US$8.7 million were incurred at the LP 
level and US$12.9 million (financial costs) by the foundation 
office in Delhi and capacity development partners. 
Table 3 shows the composition of the overall costs by activity. 
The major activities were STI service costs (27% of total costs), 
BCC costs (15%) and condom promotion costs (11%). These 
were followed by capacity building costs (9.3%) and enabling 
environment costs, constituting 8.9%. Start-up costs were 4.7% 
of the overall costs. 
The median cost per person registered was US$76 (see table 2). 
The cost per person registered ranged from US$18 to US$616 
across the NGOs (see table 2, figure 1). The median cost per STI 
clinic visit was US$117 with a mean cost of US$134 (range US 
$37e411). With a 3% discount rate, the median costs per person 
registered and per STI clinic visit were US$75 and US$112, 
respectively. 
The regression of cost per person registered with scale showed 
that scale was significantly associated with decreasing average 
costs (adjusted R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>¼À0.248, p¼0.0001). When all variables were 
included in the model (adjusted R 
2 ¼0.605, p&lt;0.001), the factors 
found to be significantly associated with average costs were scale 
(b¼À0.604, p&lt;0.001), age of the intervention (0.376, p&lt;0.001), 
number of Avahan NGOs in the district (À0.425, p&lt;0.001) and 
number of LPs in the state (either one or two) (À0.227, p¼0.012). 
The other variables did not have a significant effect, but their 
inclusion increased the explained variation. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This paper presents the results of the cost analysis of the 
first 2 years of Avahan's implementation and examines causes 
of average cost variation over the sampled sites for this period. 
The total cost of the programme was US$16.8 million, with 
personnel comprising nearly 40% of the total. Costs rose from 
US$4.5 million to US$12.2 million in year 2, an increase of US 
$7.7 million, as NGOs started up and moved from start-up to 
focus on increasing the intensity and quality of coverage. The 
activities addressing proximate determinants of risk comprised 
53% of total costs, whereas those addressing distal determi-
nants of risk made up 14.6% of costs. The 8.6% of costs 
attributable to enabling environment activities is in the range 
recommended by the AIDS commission report 2008. 
25 Capacity 
building and monitoring were also shown to be an important 
component of costs (9.3% and 8.1%, respectively). This activi-
tywise analysis is unique in the costing of HIV prevention for 
high-risk groups in India and provides new insight into cost 
structures. </p>

<p>10 12 13   A number of earlier studies have examined the costs of 
targeted interventions in India. 
10 12 13 26 The district-level-only 
average costs of Avahan range from US$11 to US$95 (US 
$10e124 with a 3% discount rate), and are closer in value to these 
studies (see table 4). They also coincide with the range of US 
$16e50 used for global scale-up estimates for different regions. </p>

<p>27   LP level costs were found to be approximately half the total costs. </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 1):i89ei94. doi:10.1136/sti.2009.038547 
i91 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>These costs include both the technical and management support 
activities required in the early stages of the scale-up and supplies 
such as condoms, STI drugs and supply of educational materials. 
These project supplies distributed directly to the NGO level 
amount to 7% of total LP costs. 
Further costs were incurred beyond the NGOs and LP organ-
isational levels at the foundation office. These amounted to US 
$12.9 million, 70% of which was spent on capacity development 
through pan-Avahan capacity development partners. Approxi-
mately 14% of total financial costs are foundation staff costs. 
These transaction costs inherent in the contracting out and 
subsequent management are rarely reported. One study of 
a large-scale nutrition programmes in Madagascar and Senegal 
found contracting costs to be between 13% and 17% of total 
costs. 
28 Similarly, Guinness (2006) estimated that the costs 
incurred by the State AIDS Control Societies and other state-</p>

<p>level agencies responsible for management of NGO contracts in 
the delivery of HIV prevention services in India were between 
11% and 17% of total costs. 
29 In the case of the Avahan costs 
presented here, the relatively high portion of costs at the central 
and LP level need to be seen in the context of a large-scale 
programme in its first 2 years. These early years require a high 
level of technical and management inputs to ensure quality and 
consistency of services and supplies and to develop management 
systems while scaling up. 
The cost per person registered varies across the NGOs. 
Economic theory on costs and empirical literature on costs of HIV 
prevention strategies show that scale is a major cause of this 
variation so that average cost falls as scale increases, at least in 
the short run. 
5 10 13 30 Figure 1 supports this hypothesis, and the 
regression found scale to be responsible for 24% of the cost varia-
tion. The figure indicates that as each NGO intervention is scaled </p>

<p>Table 2 Total costs by input, outputs and average costs of the Avahan programme for the first 2 years of activity (2004/2005 and 2005/2006), US$ 
2006 prices </p>

<p>Total costs (NGO and LP levels) by input 
Financial (US$) </p>

<p>Economic 
(US$) 
Percentage of total economic cost </p>

<p>Capital costs 
Rent 
710436 
721443 
4.3 
Equipment 
233911 
327933 
2.0 
Furniture and fixtures 
89731 
137115 
0.8 
Vehicle 
88008 
131995 
0.8 
Training (start-up) 
33821 
40929 
0.2 
Insurance and deposits 
28652 
35521 
0.2 
Start up 
626351 
728065 
4.3 
Subtotal 
1810910 
2123000 
12.7 
Recurrent costs 
Personnel 
6624189 
6770706 
40.4 
Travel 
1286108 
1286141 
7.7 
Building operating and maintenance 
952567 
949977 
5.7 
STI supplies 
1342251 
1343331 
8.0 
Monitoring 
931288 
930936 
5.6 
Information education communication 
867658 
872300 
5.2 
Training recurrent 
1283786 
1290585 
7.7 
Condom supplies 
120132 
627755 
3.7 
Indirect expenses 
560467 
564456 
3.4 
Subtotal 
13968446 
14636189 
87.3 
Total 
15779356 
16759189 
100.0 
Total costs by organisational level 
US$ 
Percentage of total 
NGO level 
8030991 
28.0 
Lead implementing partner level 
8728198 
30.4 
Avahan Delhi office costs* 
3944959 
13.7 
Capacity building partner costs* 
9006456 
31.3 
All level costs* 
28730771 
Outputs of the programme 
Total number of people registeredy 
134391 
Total number of people receiving STI servicesz 
124669 
Average costs 
Mean 
Median 
Range 
Total cost per NGO at the NGO level (US$) 
153646 
128192 
20287 to 532112 
People registered at the NGO levely 
1908 
1930 
37 to 6315 
Cost per person registered (US$)y 
166 
76 
18 to 650 
People receiving STI services at the NGO levelz 
1955 
1950 
7 to 8004 
Cost per person receiving STI services (US$)z 
134 
117 
37 to 411 
Sensitivity analysis (discount rate[3%) 
Total economic cost US$ 
16605094 
Total cost per NGO at the NGO level (US$) 
153650 
124269 
20008 to 541692 
Cost per person registered (US$)y 
163 
75 
18 to 616 
Cost per person receiving STI services (US$)z 
79 
112 
22 to 411 </p>

<p>*Financial costs only. 
yNo of non-governmental organisations (NGOs)¼93. 
zNo of NGOs¼96. </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 1):i89ei94. doi:10.1136/sti.2009.038547 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>up, the average cost for that intervention will fall until about 2000 
people are registered, above which there is less variation in the 
average cost. This implies that in moving to scale, total costs will 
initially increase rapidly, but as scale is reached the rate of increase 
in total costs will begin to fall. The regression also found that age, 
number of Avahan NGOs in the district and number of LPs in the 
state have an impact on costs. Age is positively associated with 
average cost, and the number of NGOs and number or LPs in the </p>

<p>state are negatively associated with average cost. As all imple-
mentation NGOs were local, it was not possible to test for the 
impact of an international NGO on average costs. However, 
without a random sample and the skewed nature of the data, 
econometric estimation of a cost function will be required to 
further explore the impact of these factors. 
As with other studies of unit cost, the average cost per person 
registered cannot capture the quality of the intervention. In </p>

<p>Table 3 Total cost by activity at the state level (non-governmental organisation and lead implementing partner costs), 2004/2005 and 2005/2006, US$ 
2006 prices </p>

<p>Financial cost (US$) 
Economic cost (10%) (US$) 
Percentage of total economic cost </p>

<p>Capacity building 
1484920 
1558215 
9.3 
Behaviour-change communication* 
2693357 
2552033 
15.2 
STI services 
4766458 
4534406 
27.1 
Condom promotiony 
1045264 
1856335 
11.1 
Community mobilisationz 
938975 
1003254 
6.0 
Monitoring 
867696 
1350681 
8.1 
Planning and coordination 
1270790 
1097431 
6.5 
Start-up activitiesx 
817712 
786120 
4.7 
Enabling environment{ 
1328141 
1498584 
8.9 
Others 
566044 
522130 
3.1 
Grand total 
15779356 
16759189 
100.0 </p>

<p>*Behaviour-change communication includes outreach activities including peer educator remuneration. 
yCondom promotion includes establishment of condom outlets, condom campaigns, condom demonstrations, condom supplies and lubricants. 
zCommunity mobilisation includes all drop in centre activities, special events, self-help group formation and welfare activities for the key population. 
xStart-up activities includes recruitment, training, mapping, office set-up and all expenses until the start of implementation. 
{Enabling environment includes advocacy, sensitisation of stakeholders, crisis management and creation of mass awareness. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Average costs by scale (cost 
per person registered), 2004e2006 (US 
$ 2006 prices). </p>

<p>Table 4 Comparison of costs of HIV prevention for female sex workers in India </p>

<p>Cost 
study </p>

<p>Cost per sex 
worker reached </p>

<p>Cost per sex 
worker treated </p>

<p>No of 
interventions 
Scale 
Nature of costs </p>

<p>Avahan 
53 (10 to 124) 
78.7 (10 to 292) 
107 
37 to 6315 
Full economic costing, implementation 
and support levels; 1st 2 years* </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>19.21 (10 to 51 
62.5 (13.9 to 141.2) 
17 
250 to 2008 
Full economic costing, implementation 
level; mature NGO projects </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>31.65 (21.5 to 57.2) 
16.6 (5.1 to 55.7) 
14 
1109 to 5721 
Full economic costing, implementation 
level, mature NGO projects </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>56.5 
NA 
1 
2342 
Full economic costing, implementation 
level; first 51 months of project </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>13.66 (4.58 to 28.2) 
NA 
15 
803 to 6379 
Full economic costing, implementation 
level, mature NGO projects 
NACOy 
34.2 to 50.88 
NA 
NA 
400 to 1000 
Annual financial cost </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>31.02 
NA 
NA 
1000 
Annual financial cost </p>

<p>*Lead implementing partner costs excluded, 3% discount rate. 
yNational AIDS Control Organisation's Revised Costing Guidelines for Targeted Interventions working with HRGs under NACPIII. 2009. http://www.nacoonline.org/Divisions/Finance_Division/ 
Revised_costing_guidelines_for_Targeted_Interventions_working_with_HRGs_under_NACP-III/ 
NGO, non-governmental organisation. </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 1):i89ei94. doi:10.1136/sti.2009.038547 
i93 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>addition, although the person registered does capture only those 
target group members that have had repeated contact with the 
projects, this may be subject to some variation across the NGOs. 
However, the standardised MIS used and the uniform capacity 
development that staff undergo across the NGOs should minimise 
this variation. The use of registration data may also have under-
estimated utilisation. In the early years, there was reluctance by 
some outreach teams to collect registration data due to the 
concern of scaring the target group. In contrast, in a minority of 
cases, registration data were not available for the first year of 
analysis, and people contacted was used as a proxy, so that 
utilisation numbers have been inflated. A final limitation lies in the 
standard issues of bias in self-reporting for the timesheets. The 
extent of the bias is unknown but is believed to be limited. 
Kumaranayake, in her review, observed that there are very few 
empirical cost data collected alongside programming as it 
expands. 
5 In the Avahan evaluation, prospective data are being 
collected to monitor costs and document service delivery. This 
prospective data collection provides for greater reliability in the 
cost estimates than any of the previous studies in which costs 
have been collected retrospectively. At the end of this period of 
analysis, the Avahan programme had reached less than 50% of 
the estimated population through monthly outreach. 
19 By 
December 2008, 75% of the estimated target population was 
being reached monthly. 
19 Estimating the resource requirements 
for this further scaling up, and the implications for scaling up in 
the government programme, requires further modelling of the 
costs. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>In this paper, we have presented the early results of the cost 
analysis of the first 2 years of the Avahan project. Once the full 
4 years of data have been collected, it will be possible to explore 
further how costs change as the programme scales up coverage, 
intensity, quality and scope of services. These first results from the 
programme show that during rapid scale-up of targeted HIV 
preventions, a significant reduction in average costs is apparent. 
These scale effects are therefore important to quantify for plan-
ning future resource requirements of large-scale interventions. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements Our sincere gratitude to all the project staff, peer educators, 
volunteers and community members who participated in the study. </p>

<p>Contributors SC contributed to the design, data collection, analysis and interpretation, 
and prepared the first draft of the paper. LK contributed to the design, analysis and 
interpretation. LG contributed in the interpretation of the data and manuscript 
preparation. PV contributed to manuscript preparation. BR and GY assisted in the data 
collection, data entry, preliminary data analysis and generation of tables. MA was the 
principal investigator of the main study and contributed to the design of the study. </p>

<p>Funding This research was funded by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation. </p>

<p>Conflict of interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Ethics approval was provided by the Health Monitoring and Steering 
Committee in India and the Centre Hospital Affiliare ethics board in Canada. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>



<p>Key messages </p>

<p>&lt; Unique costing of a large-scale HIV prevention programme for 
vulnerable groups with multiple national and international 
implementing partners in South Asia. 
&lt; After 2 years, the total economic cost was 16.9 million; the 
cost per person registered was $76, ranging from $18 to $650 
across the NGO service delivery partners. 
&lt; The average cost variation was largely explained by scale, 
number of NGOs per district, number of LPs in the state and 
project age. </p>

<p>i94 
Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 1):i89ei94. doi:10.1136/sti.2009.038547 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

</text></tei>