<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3762194" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The ectodermal neural cortex (ENC) gene family, whose members are implicated in neurogenesis, is part of the kelch repeat super-
family. To date, ENC genes have been identified only in osteichthyans, although other kelch repeat-containing genes are prevalent 
throughout bilaterians. The lack of elaborate molecular phylogenetic analysis with exhaustive taxon sampling has obscured the 
possible link of the establishment of this gene family with vertebrate novelties. In this study, we identified ENC homologs in diverse 
vertebrates by means of database mining and polymerase chain reaction screens. Our analysis revealed that the ENC3 ortholog was 
lost in the basal eutherian lineage through single-gene deletion and that the triplication between ENC1, -2, and -3 occurred early in 
vertebrate evolution. Including our original data on the catshark and the zebrafish, our comparison revealed high conservation of the 
pleiotropic expression pattern of ENC1 and shuffling of expression domains between ENC1, -2, and -3. Compared with many other 
gene families including developmental key regulators, the ENC gene family is unique in that conventional molecular phylogenetic 
inference could identify no obvious invertebrate ortholog. This suggests a composite nature of the vertebrate-specific gene repertoire, 
consisting not only of de novo genes introduced at the vertebrate origin but also of long-standing genes with no apparent invertebrate 
orthologs. Some of the latter, including the ENC gene family, may be too rapidly evolving to provide sufficient phylogenetic signals 
marking orthology to their invertebrate counterparts. Such gene families that experienced saltatory evolution likely remain to be 
explored and might also have contributed to phenotypic evolution of vertebrates. </p>

<p>The first vertebrates emerged more than 500 Ma (Shu et al. 
1999; Hedges 2009), and this was paralleled by embryonic 
novelties, such as the neural crest mainly contributing to cra-
niofacial morphogenesis. The genetic basis underlying these 
morphological novelties is not fully understood, but increasing 
sequence data is providing clues to these questions. In partic-
ular, recent genome-wide analyses provided convincing 
evidence of two rounds (2R) of whole-genome duplication 
(WGD) early in vertebrate evolution (Lundin 1993; Holland 
et al. 1994; Sidow 1996; Dehal and Boore 2005; Putnam </p>

<p>et al. 2008). As a result, the common pattern obtained in 
phylogenetic analyses of typical gene families is a "four-to-
one" relationship in which maximally four vertebrate paralogs 
are co-orthologs of a single invertebrate proto-ortholog. 
Among vertebrate lineages, the teleost fishes are character-
ized by their further derived genomes because of a third round 
of WGD, the so-called teleost-specific genome duplication 
(TSGD; Amores et al. 1998; Wittbrodt et al. 1998; reviewed 
in Meyer and Van de Peer 2005). Postduplication processes, 
such as neo-or subfunctionalization, based on the initially 
redundant set of genes, utilized this initial abundance of </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits 
non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>



<p>genetic raw material for further diversification (Ohno 1970; 
Force et al. 1999). The redundancy introduced by the 
2R-WGD might thus have triggered vertebrate novelties, 
such as a well-organized brain compartment (Manning and 
Scheeff 2010). 
In addition to the surplus of genomic elements resulting 
from the 2R-WGD, de novo genes (also often referred to as 
taxonomically restricted genes or new genes; Khalturin et al. 
2009) introduced at the vertebrate origin could have contrib-
uted to the vertebrate-specific gene repertoire. A study focus-
ing on genome-wide information of the sea lamprey 
(Petromyzon marinus), an outgroup to jawed vertebrates, 
revealed 224 protein-coding genes that are unique to verte-
brates (Smith et al. 2013). The target of this study, ectodermal 
neural cortex (ENC) genes, has been identified only in verte-
brates, but they share the conserved BTB/POZ domain and 
kelch repeats with the rest of the BTB/POZ-kelch repeat 
superfamily members. The fact that kelch repeat-containing 
genes are present throughout bilaterians implies that a proto-
ENC gene dates back to the last common ancestor of proto-
stomes and deuterostomes (Prag and Adams 2003). The kelch 
repeat superfamily to which the ENC genes belong is charac-
terized by four to seven tandem repeats of~50 amino acid 
motif in a peptide (Bork and Doolittle 1994; Adams et al. 
2000). Amino acid sequences between motifs are weakly con-
served, except for a few key residues (fig. 1A). This low level of 
conservation in amino acid sequences impeded a reliable 
survey of the complete superfamily (Adams et al. 2000). 
Despite the divergent amino acid sequence, they all presum-
ably form antiparallel b-sheets that together assemble a b-
propeller (Adams et al. 2000). The structural subgroup of 
the kelch repeat superfamily to which ENC genes belong is 
additionally characterized by an N-terminal BTB/POZ (Broad-
Complex, Tramtrack, and Bric-a-brac/Poxvirus and Zinc-finger) 
domain of approximately 120 amino acids (Godt et al. 1993; 
Bardwell and Treisman 1994). This domain is responsible for 
protein-protein interactions and allows this class of proteins to 
dimerize (Bardwell and Treisman 1994; Albagli et al. 1995). 
Proteins encoded by members of the kelch repeat superfamily 
are implicated in diverse biological processes, and their cellular 
localizations differ between intracellular compartments, cell 
surface, and extracellular milieu. Products of several members 
of this superfamily, including ENC1, have been shown to as-
sociate with actin cytoskeleton (Xue and Cooley 1993; 
Hernandez et al. 1997). 
Li et al. (2007) identified ENC1, among others, as suitable 
phylogenetic marker because it is qualified by the presence of 
one single coding exon, which facilitates polymerase chain 
reaction (PCR) amplification with genomic DNA (gDNA). 
ENC1 as a phylogenetic marker has been employed in numer-
ous phylogenetic studies of actinopterygian fish (e.g., 
notothenioid fishes [Matschiner et al. 2011], sticklebacks 
[Kawahara et al. 2009], and ray-finned fishes [Li et al. </p>

<p>2008]) as well as reptiles (iguanian lizards [Townsend et al. 
2011] and other squamates [Wiens et al. 2010]). 
Hernandez et al. (1997) reported for the first time devel-
opmental roles of an ENC gene, namely those of ENC1 in the 
nervous system of mouse. ENC1 is expressed in a dynamic 
manner from early gastrulation on throughout neural devel-
opment and persists in the adult nervous system (Hernandez 
et al. 1997). A study on various human cell lines suggested 
that ENC1 is involved in the differentiation of neural crest cells 
and is down-regulated in neuroblastoma tumors (Hernandez 
et al. 1998). Interestingly, an antisense transcript of its first 
exon, ENC1-AS, is linked to a certain type of leukemia 
(Hammarsund et al. 2004). 
Except for mammalian ENC1, only sparse information on 
the developmental roles of the ENC gene family is available. 
The expression patterns of chicken ENC1 in the developing 
telencephalon were characterized in great detail and resemble 
the dynamic pattern in mouse (Garcia-Calero and Puelles 
2009). Expression patterns of the full set of ENC genes 
(ENC1, -2, and -3) have been investigated only in one species, 
the amphibian Xenopus laevis (Haigo et al. 2003). The only 
expression data of ENC genes outside tetrapods are reports of 
enc3 in developing zebrafish (Kudoh et al. 2001; Thisse B and 
Thisse C 2004; Thisse C and Thisse B 2005; Bradford et al. 
2011; available on the ZFIN database: http://zfin.org/, last 
accessed July 24, 2013; Qian et al. 2013). 
In this study, our exhaustive gene and taxon sampling 
revealed the diversification pattern of the ENC gene family 
in a higher resolution. Conserved synteny between genomic 
regions containing ENC1, -2, and -3 suggested the triplication 
through 2R-WGDs early in vertebrate evolution. Of those, the 
ENC3 ortholog was shown to have been lost in the eutherian 
lineage. We also provide the first report of expression patterns 
of nontetrapod ENC1 in a catshark and of the complete set of 
enc genes (enc1, -2, and -3) in zebrafish. Overall, molecular 
and regulatory evolution of the ENC genes within vertebrates 
conform to typical patterns hitherto observed for many other 
gene families including developmental regulatory genes, 
except for one aspect: Conventional molecular phylogenetic 
methods could not identify the invertebrate orthologs of ENC 
genes. Because the ENC gene family is one of the numerous 
subfamilies in the kelch repeat superfamily widely possessed 
by bilaterians, nonidentification of this long-standing gene in 
invertebrate indicates unique evolutionary trajectory of the 
ENC gene family. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Collection and Staging of Catshark Embryos </p>

<p>Eggs of the small-spotted catshark Scyliorhinus canicula were 
harvested by staffs of the Sea Life Centre Konstanz and incu-
bated in separate containers at 18 
C in oxygenated water 
until they reached required stages. Embryos were dissected in </p>

<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>1486 Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>

<p>FIG. 1.-Comparison of the amino acid sequence of the kelch repeat of selected ENC proteins and phylogenetic relationships within the ENC gene 
family. (A) The six units of the kelch repeat of all three chicken ENC proteins (ENC1, -2, and -3), the small-spotted catshark ENC1 protein, and all three 
cyclostome ENC proteins (Eptatretus burgeri ENC-A, Petromyzon marinus ENC-A, and -B) are aligned. Note that the P. marinus ENC-A protein is partial. </p>

<p>Evolution of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>



<p>(continued) </p>

<p>phosphate-buffered saline solution and staged according to 
Ballard et al. (1993). Animals that were subjected to in situ 
hybridizations were fixed for 12 h at 4 
C in either Serra's 
fixative or 4% paraformaldehyde. Additionally, staged 
and fixed S. canicula embryos were provided by the 
Biological Marine Resources facility of Roscoff Marine 
Station in France. </p>

<p>Polymerase Chain Reaction </p>

<p>gDNA extracted from red blood cells of the horn shark 
Heterodontus francisci and the lemon shark Negaprion brevir-
ostris was gifted by Yuko Ohta. Total RNA was extracted using 
TRIzol (Invitrogen) from a zebrafish at 25 h post-fertilization 
(hpf), an adult Florida gar Lepisosteus platyrhincus and a 
S. canicula embryo at stage 33. Total RNA of the inshore hag-
fish Eptatretus burgeri was gifted by Kinya G. Ota and Shigeru 
Kuratani. These total RNAs were reverse transcribed into 
cDNA using SuperScript III (Invitrogen), following the instruc-
tions of the 3 
0 -RACE System (Invitrogen). 
gDNAs of H. francisci and N. brevirostris, and cDNAs of 
L. platyrhincus and S. canicula were used as templates for 
degenerate PCRs using forward oligonucleotide primers that 
were designed based on amino acid stretches shared among 
ENC1, -2, and -3 sequences of diverse vertebrates. Forward 
primer sequences were 5 
0 -GCA TGC WSN MGN TAY TTY 
GAR GC-3 
0 for the first, and 5 
0 -TGC CAN MGN TAY TTY 
GAR GCN ATG TT-3 
0 for the nested reaction, and reverse 
primer sequences were 5 
0 -TG TGC NCC RAA RTA NCC 
NCC NAC-3 
0 for the first, and 5 
0 -TGC TCC RAA RTA NCC 
NCC NAC NAC-3 
0 for the nested reaction. The 5 
0 -ends of 
S. canicula ENC1 and ENC3 transcripts were obtained using 
the GeneRacer Kit (Invitrogen). These cDNA fragments were 
used as templates for riboprobes used in in situ hybridizations. 
In addition, the entire 3 
0 -untranslated region (UTR) plus sub-
stantial parts of the coding regions of zebrafish enc1, -2, -3, 
and egr2b (krox20) cDNAs were cloned to prepare riboprobes. 
Gene-specific primers for these PCRs were designed based on 
publicly available sequences (ENSDART00000062855 for 
egr2b, see supplementary table S1, Supplementary Material 
online, for zebrafish accession IDs). A 249-base pair fragment </p>

<p>of E. burgeri ENC-A was identified by performing a TBlastN 
search in a hagfish EST archive (http://transcriptome.cdb.riken. 
go.jp/vtcap/, last accessed July 24, 2013; Takechi et al. 2011) 
using human ENC1 peptide sequence as query. Based on this 
sequence, gene-specific primers were designed, and the 5 
0 -
part of the coding region plus 5 
0 -UTR of E. burgeri ENC-A was 
obtained using the GeneRacer Kit (Invitrogen). Assembled full-
length S. canicula ENC1 and ENC3 cDNA sequences and the 
obtained fragments of E. burgeri ENC-A, H. francisci ENC1 and 
ENC3, N. brevirostris ENC3, and L. platyrhincus ENC2 are de-
posited in EMBL under accession numbers HE981756, 
HE981757, HE981759, HE981760, and HE981762-
HE981764. 
Because the chicken ENC3 gene sequence was incomplete 
with a stretch of "N"s in the open reading frame (ORF) of 
ENSGALG00000024263 (Ensembl genome database: http:// 
www.ensembl.org, last accessed July 24, 2013; release 64; 
Hubbard et al. 2009), we performed a reverse transcriptase 
(RT)-PCR with gene-specific primers and sequenced the miss-
ing part. By aligning the overlapping regions of the deduced 
protein sequences of the newly obtained fragment and the 
incomplete sequence in Ensembl, we detected an amino acid 
substitution. The comparison with other vertebrate ENC pro-
teins clearly showed that this is a highly conserved residue 
(asparagine). Therefore, we assume that the lysine residue 
of the Ensembl chicken ENC3 protein was caused by a se-
quencing error, which is also plausible with respect to the 
stretch of "N"s. The curated cDNA fragment is deposited in 
EMBL under accession number HE981758. </p>

<p>Retrieval of Sequences from Public Databases </p>

<p>Sequences of ENC homologs were retrieved from the Ensembl 
genome database and National Center for Biotechnology 
Information (NCBI) Protein database, by performing BlastP 
searches (Altschul et al. 1997) using human ENC1 as query. 
An optimal multiple alignment of the retrieved ENC amino 
acid sequences including the query sequence was constructed 
(fig. 1B) using the alignment editor XCED in which the <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> 
program is implemented (Katoh et al. 2005). Similarly, a 
second alignment including human, zebrafish, Drosophila </p>

<p>FIG. 1.-Continued 
The diagnostic amino acid residues, namely a diglycine followed by a tyrosine, six nonconserved amino acids, and a tryptophan residue are highlighted with 
gray background. This pattern is disrupted in the first kelch repeat of all three cyclostome proteins where the first glycine ("G") is replaced by an alanine 
residue ("A"). Another nonconserved site is a phenylalanine ("F") instead of a tyrosine ("Y") in the fourth kelch repeat of the chicken ENC3 protein. Because 
of similar physiochemical properties, these substitutions do not necessarily prevent the characteristic folding of the mature protein and thus its cellular 
function. Interestingly, the first kelch repeat of all vertebrate ENC proteins lacks the tryptophan residue and thus does not show the described motif. (B) A 
phylogenetic tree of the three ENC subgroups of jawed vertebrates, three cyclostome homologs, and the Branchiostoma floridae gene "XP_002612442" as 
outgroup is shown. Support values are shown for each node in order, bootstrap probabilities in the ML tree inference, and Bayesian posterior probabilities. 
Analysis is based on 311 amino acids, and the JTT + I + F + À 4 model was assumed (shape parameter of gamma distribution a ¼ 0.66). Red arrows denote 
sequences that are newly reported in this study. For accession IDs of amino acid sequences used in this analysis, see supplementary table S3, Supplementary 
Material online. </p>

<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>melanogaster, Ciona intestinalis, and C. savignyi amino acid 
sequences belonging to the KLHL superfamily was con-
structed (supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary Material 
online; for a list of sequences used in this study, see supple-
mentary table S1, Supplementary Material online). 
Sea lamprey P. marinus ENC-A was predicted in 
the AUGUSTUS web server (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://bioinf.uni-greifswald.de/webaugustus/prediction/create</rs>, last accessed July 24, 2013) 
with its species-specific parameters on the supercontig22564 
in the version 3 assembly of the genome sequencing project 
(PMAR3.0). An ORF of the gene designated P. marinus ENC-A 
was curated (for sequence see supplementary table S2, 
Supplementary Material online). A truncated fragment of 
this gene is also present in Ensembl release 64 
(ENSPMAG00000008371). The second lamprey ENC gene 
(ENC-B) 
is 
available 
in 
Ensembl 
version 
64 
(ENSPMAG00000000574). Because of unresolved orthology 
of these lamprey ENC genes to gnathostome ENC1-3, we 
refer to them as PmENC-A and PmENC-B. 
To search for ENC orthologs in sequenced invertebrate 
genomes, we explored public databases. Predicted peptide 
sequences of Nematostella vectensis, Trichoplax adherens, 
Helobdella robusta, Capitella teleta, Lottia gigantea, Daphnia 
pulex, Branchiostoma floridae (all accessible at the DOE 
Joint Genome Institute: http://www.jgi.doe.gov/, last accessed 
July 24, 2013) and of Schistosoma mansoni (ftp://ftp.sanger. 
ac.uk/pub/pathogens/Schistosoma/mansoni/genome/gene_ 
predictions/, last accessed July 24, 2013) were downloaded, 
and local Blast searches using human ENC1 protein as query 
were performed. Invertebrate sequences with high similarity 
scores were included in the phylogenetic analysis (fig. 2). </p>

<p>Molecular Phylogenetic Analysis </p>

<p>In phylogenetic analyses, we employed <rs id="software-2" type="software">PhyML</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.0</rs> (Guindon 
et al. 2010) for maximum-likelihood (ML) tree inference and 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">MrBayes</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">3.1</rs> (Huelsenbeck and Ronquist 2001) for Bayesian 
method. For the ML analyses including large data sets (fig. 2 
and supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary Material online), 
we used <rs type="software">RAxML</rs> (Stamatakis 2006), because this software 
tends to outperform PhyML under these conditions 
(Guindon et al. 2010). Optimal amino acid substitution 
models were determined by <rs type="software">ProtTest</rs> (Abascal et al. 2005). 
To identify invertebrate orthologs of ENC genes and to inves-
tigate the phylogenetic relationships within the ENC gene 
family, a data set that contained relevant representatives of 
each major vertebrate class for each ENC subtype was created 
(fig. 1B; see supplementary table S3, Supplementary Material 
online). We rooted the tree with the most closely related in-
vertebrate protein, B. floridae XP_002612442 (see below and 
fig. 2). Similarly, we constructed a molecular phylogeny of the 
complete KLHL superfamily (supplementary fig. S1, 
Supplementary Material online). Based on these inferred rela-
tionships, several invertebrate sequences that are closely </p>

<p>related to the ENC gene family were selected and 
phylogenetically analyzed for putative orthology to the ENC 
gene family (fig. 2). </p>

<p>In Situ Hybridization and Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>The aforementioned 5 
0 -and 3 
0 -cDNA fragments of S. canicula 
ENC1 were used as templates for riboprobes used in in situ hy-
bridizations. Paraffin-embedded section in situ hybridizations 
using S. canicula embryos were performed as described pre-
viously (Kuraku et al. 2005), with the modification that the 
acetylation step and the proteinase K treatment were skipped. 
Whole-mount in situ hybridizations on catshark embryos were 
performed according to a protocol originally developed for 
snake and lizard embryos (Di-PoE N, personal communication). 
Zebrafish standard whole-mount in situ hybridizations and 
double in situ hybridizations using the enc1 riboprobes labeled 
with digoxigenin-UTP and the egr2b riboprobes labeled with 
Fluorescein (Roche Applied Science, Mannheim, Germany) 
were performed as described previously (Begemann et al. 
2001; Manousaki et al. 2011). In double in situ staining, 
enc1 transcripts were detected using nitro blue tetrazolium/ 
5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl-phosphate (BCIP) and egrb2 tran-
scripts by a p-Iodonitrotetrazolium/BCIP-based detection. 
Stained embryos were examined with a Zeiss Axiophot micro-
scope. Immunohistochemistry on whole-mount S. canicula 
embryos was performed as described previously (Kuratani 
and Eichele 1993) with minor modifications. Monoclonal 
anti-acetylated tubulin antibody (Sigma T7451) was used to 
detect developing axons. As secondary antibody, AlexaFluor 
568 goat anti-mouse IgG (H + L, Invitrogen A-11004) was ap-
plied, and the signal was detected using fluorescence micros-
copy (Leica). Images were processed with <rs type="software">Zeiss Axiovision</rs> and 
<rs type="software">Adobe Photoshop</rs> software. </p>

<p>Identification of Conserved Synteny </p>

<p>To analyze the mode of the putative loss of ENC3 in euthe-
rians, we downloaded a list of Ensembl IDs of 79 genes har-
bored in the 1-Mb genomic region flanking ENC3 in chicken, 
together with IDs of human orthologs of those genes via the 
<rs type="software">BioMart</rs> interface. Human orthologs on chromosome 19 were 
plotted against the corresponding chicken chromosomal 
region (fig. 3). 
We analyzed the genomic regions up to 10 Mb flanking the 
three chicken ENC genes to search for conserved intragenomic 
synteny as instructed by Kuraku and Meyer (2012). Using the 
Ensembl "Gene Tree," we selected only pairs, triplets, or quar-
tets of paralogous genes that show a gene duplication pattern 
in accordance with the 2R-WGD (Dehal and Boore 2005). The 
conserved synteny is depicted in figure 4. </p>

<p>Evolution of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>



<p>FIG. 2.-Phylogenetic tree of vertebrate ENC-related genes of the kelch repeat superfamily and its invertebrate homologs. This tree is based on an 
alignment of 334 amino acids and was inferred with the ML method assuming the LG + I + F + À 4 model (a ¼ 1.67). Support values at nodes are shown in 
order, bootstrap probabilities in the ML analysis, and Bayesian posterior probabilities. Vertebrate species are color coded in blue, invertebrate deuterostomes 
in green, and other invertebrates in purple. On the basis of a large-scale phylogenetic analysis encompassing the entire kelch repeat superfamily (supple-
mentary fig. S1, Supplementary Material online), we selected several sequences that are phylogenetically close to the ENC gene family. This selected set of 
genes was combined with a set of invertebrate homologs that was analyzed for putative orthology to the ENC gene family. Note that the clustering of the 
Branchiostoma floridae gene "XP_002612442" to the group of ENC genes was only weakly supported by the ML analysis (bootstrap value of 37) and not 
supported by the Bayesian tree inference. </p>

<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>Results </p>

<p>Identification of ENC Genes in Diverse Nontetrapod 
Species </p>

<p>By means of RT-PCR, the full-length cDNA of S. canicula ENC1 
and ENC3, including 5 
0 -and 3 
0 -UTRs, and fragments of E. 
burgeri ENC-A were sequenced. PCRs using gDNA identified 
fragments of H. francisci ENC1 and ENC3, N. brevirostris ENC3, 
and L. platyrhincus ENC2. The inclusion of these genes into the 
ENC gene family was suggested in BlastX searches in the NCBI 
nonredundant protein sequence database (nr). These BlastX 
searches failed to identify any ENC3 orthologs in all available 
eutherians. An alignment of the deduced amino acid 
sequences with proteins downloaded from public databases 
was constructed. The amino acid sequence alignment 
revealed a high level of conservation especially in the diagnos-
tic residues described previously (fig. 1A; Adams et al. 2000). 
Each unit of the kelch repeat is characterized by a diglycine 
followed by a tyrosine, six nonconserved amino acids, and a 
tryptophan residue (fig. 1A). This pattern is disrupted in the 
first unit of the kelch repeat of all three cyclostome ENC genes 
with the first glycine residue replaced by an alanine residue. 
However, the similar physiochemical property of alanine and 
glycine theoretically most likely allows this first repeat to be still 
functional. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic Relationships within Vertebrate ENC </p>

<p>Our sequence data set included selected gnathostome ENC 
genes and deduced amino acid sequences of the three newly 
isolated cyclostome ENC genes. Unexpectedly, a protein of a 
plant, Ipomoea trifida (EU366607 in GenBank), was placed 
inside the group of teleost ENC1 genes and was found to 
cluster with stickleback ENC1 (bootstrap support in the ML 
analysis, 79; data not shown). This placement is in stark con-
trast to the generally accepted species phylogeny, and there-
fore we conclude that a contamination of a teleost sequence 
is the most likely explanation. On the basis of our molecular 
phylogenetic analysis, we suggest the new gene names enc3 
for the formerly called enc1l gene in zebrafish, and Xenc-1 
and Xenc-3 for the Xenopus genes previously referred to as 
Xenc-3 and Xenc-1, respectively (fig. 1B). </p>

<p>FIG. 3.-Gene location correspondence between ENC3-containing 
genomic region in chicken and its orthologous region in the human 
genome. Magnifications of the indicated regions of chicken chromosome 
28 (left) and human chromosome 19 (right) are shown in the middle; </p>

<p>FIG. 3.-Continued 
1-Mb regions flanking chicken ENC3 (shown in bold) were selected, and 
gray diagonal lines indicate gene-by-gene orthology between chicken and 
human. It should be noted that human chromosome 19 is shown in in-
verted orientation relative to chicken chromosome 28. Human orthologs 
of the chicken ENC3-neighboring genes, but not ENC3 itself, are concen-
trated in two distinct regions. The high level of conserved synteny between 
the chicken ENC3-containing chromosomal region and the human chro-
mosome 19 suggests a small-scale secondary gene loss of ENC3 in the 
lineage leading to eutherians. chr, chromosome; Mb, mega base pairs. </p>

<p>Evolution of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>



<p>FIG. 4.-Intragenomic conserved synteny between ENC-containing regions in chicken. (A) Overview of the chromosomal location of the three chicken 
ENC genes (red bars). At the longest, 10-Mb regions flanking the ENC genes were analyzed and are shown in black. The entire region containing paralogs </p>

<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>1492 Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>

<p>(continued) </p>

<p>The heuristically inferred ML tree (fig. 1B) shows a tight 
clustering within the three individual subgroups of gnathos-
tome ENC genes (ENC1, -2, and -3). Monophyly of gnathos-
tome sequences for ENC1 (89/0.81), ENC2 (88/1.00), and 
ENC3 (95/1.00) is inferred (all support values are shown in 
order, bootstrap probabilities in the ML analysis and 
Bayesian posterior probabilities; fig. 1B). The three cyclostome 
ENC genes form an independent group (48/0.65; fig. 1B). The 
high support (97/1.00) for the clustering of the sea lamprey P. 
marinus ENC-A with inshore hagfish E. burgeri ENC-A implies 
their orthology (fig. 1B). The relationship between this cyclo-
stome gene cluster to the three gnathostome ENC subgroups 
was not unambiguously inferred. The ML tree suggests a 
closer relationship of gnathostome ENC1 and -3 genes (boot-
strap support for their clustering, 27; fig. 1B) to cyclostome 
ENC genes (bootstrap support, 27; fig. 1B) than to gnathos-
tome ENC2 genes. The topology of the Bayesian analysis in-
ferred a clustering of gnathostome ENC2 and -3 subgroups 
(posterior probability for their clustering, 0.99; fig. 1B) but did 
not resolve the trichotomy between this cluster, the ENC1 
subgroup, and the group of cyclostome genes. This uncer-
tainty of the phylogenetic position of cyclostome ENC genes 
demands alternative approaches such as synteny analysis (see 
below). The exact timings of duplications of the entire geno-
mic region, and thus the ENC gene family, can be pinned 
down by analyzing the phylogenetic trajectories of neighbor-
ing gene families. </p>

<p>Is There an Invertebrate Ortholog of the ENC Gene? </p>

<p>A comprehensive phylogenetic tree was inferred to investigate 
the relationships of the ENC group of genes to the rest of the 
KLHL superfamily. This phylogenetic analysis resulted in a close 
relationship between the vertebrate ENC genes to other genes 
in the KLHL superfamily, for example, KLHL29 and KLHL30 
(supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary Material online). The 
vast number of sequences was reduced to a data set including 
only human, zebrafish, D. melanogaster, C. intestinalis, and 
C. savignyi genes, and a phylogenetic tree was inferred. Based 
on this comprehensive phylogenetic tree, a subset containing 
the ENC gene family was selected for further analysis. 
Sequences of diverse invertebrates were added to this reduced 
data set, and their position in the tree relative to the ENC 
gene family was examined (fig. 2). One B. floridae gene 
(XP_002612442 in NCBI) was placed close to the ENC 
group of proteins in the ML analysis (fig. 2). However, this 
clustering was only weakly supported (bootstrap probability, </p>

<p>37) and was not supported by the Bayesian tree inference 
(fig. 2). Additionally, a BlastP search of the B. floridae candi-
date protein sequence in vertebrates (nonredundant protein 
sequences in NCBI) revealed its highest similarity to kelch-like 
protein 24 (KLHL24) instead of the ENC genes. The scaffold57 
in the B. floridae genome assembly (version 1) harboring this 
B. floridae gene does not contain any orthologs of the genes 
surrounding ENC genes in the chicken genome (supplemen-
tary table S4, Supplementary Material online). Taken together, 
our analyses did not particularly support the orthology of this 
B. floridae gene (XP_002612442) to the vertebrate ENC 
genes. </p>

<p>Scale of the Putative Loss of the ENC3 Gene </p>

<p>Our molecular phylogenetic analysis suggested the absence of 
the ENC3 ortholog in eutherians and possibly in lepidosaurs 
(fig. 1B). Because of sparse sequence information in the lepi-
dosaurian lineage (genome-wide information only exists for 
the green anole and the Burmese python [Castoe et al. 2011]), 
the absence of ENC3 in this taxon is highly speculative at this 
time point. The absence of ENC3 in eutherians was confirmed 
by exhaustive TBlastN searches in eutherian genome assem-
blies using nonmammalian ENC3 peptide sequences as 
queries. We aimed to determine whether this absence is 
best explained by a single-gene loss or a large-scale deletion 
involving substantial parts of the chromosome or even the 
whole chromosome. For this purpose, we examined whether 
gene orders are conserved between chicken chromosome 28 
containing ENC3 and their orthologs in the human genome. In 
the region flanking ENC3 (1 Mb both up-and downstream), 
we identified 62 chicken protein-coding genes that possess 
orthologs in the human genome, and 58 of these are located 
on human chromosome 19. More precisely, they are concen-
trated in two distinct regions (fig. 3). This dense gene-by-gene 
orthology between these two chromosomes strongly suggests 
that they are derived from the same ancestral chromosome. 
Despite several rearrangements, the gene order is well con-
served (fig. 3). Thus, a large-scale loss event in the lineage 
leading to eutherians is not supported. It is more likely that 
the ENC3 gene was lost in this lineage in a single-gene dele-
tion that did not affect the surrounding genes. 
We also attempted to determine the scale of the putative 
ENC3 loss in lepidosaurs by performing the corresponding 
analysis between the chicken genomic region containing 
ENC3 and the orthologous genomic region in the green 
anole, Anolis carolinensis. However, the orthologs of the </p>

<p>FIG. 4.-Continued 
of ENC-flanking genes is shown for chromosomes that lack an ENC gene, namely chromosomes 8 and 25. (B) Gene-by-gene paralogies among the 
quadruplicated genomic regions are highlighted with diagonal lines: gray lines for two paralogs and blue lines for three paralogs. Note that the fourth 
chromosome of the ancestral quartet was split into two chromosomes (chromosomes 8 and 25). The fourth ENC gene presumably got lost during evolution 
but was originally located on an ancestral genomic region from which both chromosome 8 or 25 are derived. chr., chromosome; Mb, mega base pairs. </p>

<p>Evolution of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>



<p>chicken ENC3-neighboring genes were identified on unas-
sembled small contigs. Thus, the current assembly of the 
A. carolinensis genome does not allow us to draw any con-
clusions about the scale of the putative loss of ENC3. </p>

<p>Did ENC1, -2, and -3 Arise through the 2R-WGD? </p>

<p>In addition to the molecular phylogenetic analysis, we ad-
dressed the question of the timing of the ENC gene family 
diversification by investigating the conserved gene order be-
tween chicken genomic regions containing ENC1, -2, and -3. 
The chicken genome was selected for this purpose because it 
still retains the ENC3 ortholog (unlike eutherians), and it 
experienced no additional genome duplication (unlike tele-
osts). The comparisons between the three genomic regions 
revealed 47 flanking gene families whose pattern of diversifi-
cation matches the expected 2R-WGD pattern (fig. 4). 
Additionally, the hypothetical fourth chromosome of the initial 
2R-WGD quartet was identified: 15 gene families feature one 
of the 2R-WGD quartets on chromosome 8 or 25 (fig. 4). The 
identification of these two chromosomes is not surprising 
because genome-wide synteny analyses between human 
and chicken revealed that chicken chromosomes 8 and 25 
are orthologous to human chromosome 1 (International 
Chicken Genome Sequencing Consortium 2004; Voss et al. 
2011). This is best explained by chromosome fission in the 
lineage leading to chicken that gave rise to chromosomes 8 
and 25. </p>

<p>Embryonic Expression Patterns of Catshark ENC1 and 
Zebrafish ENC1, -2, and -3 </p>

<p>Here, we report the expression patterns of the ENC1 gene in 
the small-spotted catshark and enc1, -2, and -3 in zebrafish. 
We performed in situ hybridizations on histological samples of 
embryos of the small-spotted catshark and whole-mount in 
situ hybridizations on developing zebrafish. Both 5 
0 -and 
3 
0 -riboprobes for the catshark ENC1 gene (see Materials and 
Methods) yielded the same result, and the expression patterns 
shown in figure 5 were obtained using riboprobes prepared 
with the 3 
0 -end cDNAs. Our analysis on catshark embryos at 
intermediate (stages 26.5-28) and late stages (stages 30-35) 
of development did not detect any significant expression 
signal outside the central nervous system (fig. 5). The upregu-
lation was first detected in embryos at stage 26.5, when the 
expression signal was the most intensified in the corpus cere-
belli, the hypothalamus (particularly in the nucleus lobi later-
alis), the hindbrain, and a putative sensory patch of the otic 
vesicle (fig. 5B-E). At stage 30, ENC1 is expressed in the 
superficial region of the cerebellum, midbrain, and telenceph-
alon (fig. 5G and H). The expression in the telencephalon was 
primarily restricted to the primordial plexiform layer. ENC1 is 
expressed in the developing nucleus in the hypothalamus 
(nucleus lobi lateralis) but not in the neurohypophysis. At 
stage 33, ENC1 is strongly expressed in a specific layer of </p>

<p>the optic tectum (dorsal part of the midbrain), pallium 
(dorsal part of the telencephalon), and a specific part of the 
diencephalon (presumably prosomere 2; fig. 5J-L). From this 
stage on it is evident that ENC1 transcripts in the telenceph-
alon are restricted to the pallium and absent from the sub-
pallium (ventral part of the telencephalon). At stage 35, ENC1 
is expressed in the dorsal side of the telencephalon (pars 
superficialis anterior, pars superficialis aposteric, and area peri-
ventricularis pallialis) and the choroid plexus, which is the only 
nonneural expression domain of this gene (fig. 5M and N). 
The expression patterns of the three zebrafish enc genes 
shown in figure 6 were obtained with riboprobes spanning 
the 3 
0 -UTR and substantial parts of the coding region. We 
found significant expression of all three zebrafish enc genes 
(enc1, -2, and -3) in developmental stages ranging from 12 to 
24 hpf (fig. 6). At early stages of development (14 and 16 hpf; 
fig. 6A, B, and E), enc1 transcripts are localized in ventral parts 
of the forebrain, optic vesicle, distinct parts of the hindbrain, 
newly formed somites, and the tail bud. The enc1 expression 
in the outgrowing tail bud is found in a broad domain of 
mesenchyme (fig. 6A''). Double stainings with egr2b, a 
marker gene for rhombomeres 3 and 5, revealed that both 
signals overlap in the hindbrain region. Thus, the enc1 expres-
sion in the hindbrain is also restricted to rhombomeres 3 and 5 
(fig. 6C and D). At later developmental stages (24 hpf, fig. 6F 
and G), the expression of enc1 in the brain persists but does 
not extend to the anterior most part of the brain. The tail bud 
expression is reduced to a small domain of the tip of the tail 
(fig. 6F). We detected the expression of enc2 at 12 hpf in 
anterior parts of the developing brain, distinct parts of the 
hindbrain, the midline of the posterior trunk, and the tail 
bud (fig. 6H and I). The expression domain in the hindbrain 
strongly resembles the expression of enc1 and is most likely 
also localized in the rhombomeres 3 and 5 (fig. 6H' and I). At 
24 hpf, enc2 transcripts are found in the entire anterior part of 
the central nervous system and a weak expression signal was 
detected in the tail bud (fig. 6J). Expression signals of enc3 at 
16 hpf were found in the tail bud and a specific part of the 
hindbrain (fig. 6K). A dorsal view revealed that the expression 
in the hindbrain is localized in two lateral structures (fig. 6L). At 
24 hpf, expression signal of enc3 is restricted to specific parts 
of the hindbrain (fig. 6M). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The ENC Gene Repertoire in Vertebrates </p>

<p>Our survey in public databases (including databases derived 
from individual genome sequencing projects), as well as PCR 
screens, revealed the presence of three ENC subgroups (ENC1, 
-2, and -3) in jawed vertebrates, two ENC genes in the sea 
lamprey (ENC-A and -B), and one in a hagfish (ENC-A). An 
alignment of deduced amino acid sequences of ENC genes 
revealed a high level of conservation of some key residues </p>

<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>FIG. 5.-Expression patterns of Scyliorhinus canicula ENC1 between developmental stages 26 and 35. Panels labeled with letters followed by an 
apostrophe (') are magnifications of the corresponding overview picture. (A, F, I) Immunohistochemistry stainings of the neural system (i.e., acetylated 
tubulin) of S. canicula embryos at different developmental stages show overviews of head morphologies. B-E, G, H, and J-N are in situ hybridizations on 
transverse sections at the levels indicated in A, F, and I. (B-B'') Expression signal in the corpus cerebelli (cocb) and two distinct regions of the diencephalon (di, 
arrowheads) are shown. (C-C'') ENC1 transcripts are detected in the hindbrain (hb) and the presumptive nucleus lobi lateralis (nlobl) that is part of the 
hypothalamus (hpt, arrow). (D, D') Parts of the hindbrain and the anterodorsal lateral line ganglion (allg) are expressing ENC1. (E, E') Expression signals in the 
hindbrain are maintained at this level, and expression in a putative sensory patch of the otic vesicle (ov) is detected. (G, G') ENC1 is expressed in the outermost 
layer of the midbrain (mb). (H-H'') ENC1 transcripts are located in the corpus cerebelli, the midbrain, and the primordial plexiform layer of the telencephalon 
(tel). (J-J'') ENC1 transcripts are localized in one specific layer of the optic tectum (ot) and specific regions of the pallium (p). No expression signal was detected </p>

<p>Evolution of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>



<p>(continued) </p>

<p>(fig. 1A). Therefore, we assume that the structure of ENC 
proteins is conserved among vertebrates. 
Our phylogenetic analysis clearly supported the individual 
clusters of three distinct gnathostome ENC subgroups, namely 
ENC1, -2, and -3 (fig. 1B). These three subgroups show uni-
form rates of evolution indicated by comparable branch 
lengths. Interestingly, we do not detect any additional gene 
in teleost fish generated in the TSGD (Meyer and Van de Peer 
2005). This observation can be best explained through a sec-
ondary gene loss of one ENC paralog derived from this third 
round of WGD before the radiation of teleosts. It is also 
noteworthy that we did not find any ENC2 gene in multiple 
chondrichthyan species. Further sequence data of this taxon 
are needed to confirm a possible loss of chondrichthyan ENC2. </p>

<p>Origin of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>The ENC gene family is a member of the kelch repeat super-
family (supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary Material online) 
and shares the conserved BTB/POZ domain and the kelch 
repeats with other members (fig. 1A). Our database mining 
and molecular phylogenetic analysis did not identify any ap-
parent ENC ortholog in invertebrates (fig. 2; supplementary 
table S4, Supplementary Material online). One possible expla-
nation for the alleged absence of invertebrate ENC orthologs 
might be that they were secondarily lost in invertebrates. 
However, this assumption would require multiple indepen-
dent gene losses in diverse invertebrate lineages. 
Alternatively, this absence can be explained by an elevated 
evolutionary rate of the ENC gene in the lineage leading to 
vertebrates erasing significant phylogenetic signals from their 
sequences (fig. 7). In molecular phylogenies of many gene 
families, the branch of the lineage leading to vertebrate 
genes tends to be elongated for the evolutionary time that 
elapsed for that period. However, the rate of sequence evo-
lution could still be in the range of sufficient gradualism to 
allow identification of orthology. In contrast, the evolutionary 
rate of the ENC gene family might have been beyond gradu-
alism, resulting in saltatory sequence change. As a conse-
quence, orthology of vertebrate ENC genes to their 
counterparts in invertebrates might be no longer traceable 
with conventional phylogenetic methods based on overall 
sequence similarity. 
We used the B. floridae gene "XP_002612442" to root the 
tree, although it has not been revealed to be orthologous to 
vertebrate ENC genes (fig. 1B). However, the placement of a </p>

<p>root to the tree allowed us to address the question about the 
relationship between cyclostome and gnathostome ENC 
genes. In this study, we identified three ENC homologs of 
cyclostomes (hagfish and lamprey) that occupy a key phylo-
genetic position in addressing early vertebrate evolution. In 
our phylogenetic analysis, the position of the cyclostome 
ENC genes remains poorly resolved, and no clear orthology 
to any gnathostome ENC subgroup was confidently suggested 
(fig. 1B). Depending on the method we applied, alternative 
scenarios are conceivable, regarding the diversification pattern 
within the ENC gene family. This unreliability of the molecular 
phylogeny is enhanced by unclear timing of WGDs (Kuraku 
et al. 2009). One scenario in which the three jawed vertebrate 
ENC subgroups originated through gnathostome-specific 
gene duplications would result in a clustering of all gnathos-
tome ENC genes with the exclusion of cyclostome ENC genes. 
Our data do not suggest this scenario (fig. 1B). A second pos-
sibility based on the 2R-WGD is that the group of cyclostome 
ENC genes is orthologous to one particular gnathostome ENC 
subgroup. We did not observe any marked affinity of cyclo-
stome ENC genes to a single gnathostome ENC subgroup. The 
third possible scenario based on the 2R-WGD is that cyclo-
stomes are the only vertebrate group retaining the fourth ENC 
subtype, the hypothetical ENC4 gene. This scenario would 
result in a tree topology inferred by the ML method 
(fig. 1B), if not only the expected ((A,B),(C,D)) but also a 
(A,(B,(C,D))) topology is admitted as evidence for a 1-2-4 pat-
tern. Also, the phylogeny inferred by the Bayesian method 
suggests this scenario (fig. 1B). Thus, our phylogenetic analysis 
suggests that cyclostome ENC genes are remnants of the 
fourth ENC subtype that is absent from gnathostome 
genomes (fig. 7). All scenarios imply an additional cyclo-
stome-specific duplication of the ancestral ENC4 gene result-
ing in E. burgeri ENC-A, P. marinus ENC-A and ENC-B followed 
by a secondary gene loss or nonidentification of the ENC-B 
gene in hagfish (fig. 7). It was previously proposed that fre-
quent clustering of cyclostome sequences in molecular phylo-
genetic trees might be caused by a systematic artifact resulting 
from their unique sequence properties (Qiu et al. 2011). More 
sequence data of cyclostomes could potentially provide a 
higher resolution of the ENC gene phylogeny. </p>

<p>Putative ENC3 Gene Loss in the Eutherian Lineage </p>

<p>Our molecular phylogenetic analysis suggested the absence of 
ENC3 genes in eutherians and possibly in lepidosaurs (fig. 1B). </p>

<p>FIG. 5.-Continued 
in the epiphysis (epi). (K-K'') Low levels of expression were detected in the corpus cerebelli, whereas strong expression signal was evident in a specific area of 
the diencephalon, the prosomere 2 (di p2). (L, L') The ENC1 expression continues more caudally in the hindbrain. (M) The rostral-most part of the pallium, the 
pars superficialis anterior of the dorsal pallium (pdsa), and the area periventricularis pallialis (app) show ENC1 expression, whereas it is absent from the 
subpallium (sp). (N) The only nonneural expression domain of ENC1 is the choroid plexus (chp). asb, area superficialis basalis; ed, endolymphatic duct; ob, 
olfactory bulb; oe, olfactory epithilium; str, stratum; teg: midbrain tegmentum. Scale bars: 0.5 mm in B-E, G, H, and J-N; 100 mm in all magnifications. 
Smeets et al. 1983 was referred for the morphological identification. </p>

<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>FIG. 6.-Expression patterns of enc1, -2, and -3 in zebrafish embryos. In situ hybridizations of enc1 (A, B, and E-G), enc2 (H-J), and enc3 (K-M). 
Expression patterns are shown at 12 hpf (H, I), 14 hpf (A, B), 16 hpf (C-E, K, L), and 24 hpf (F, G, J, M). Panels labeled with letters followed by an apostrophe 
(') are magnifications of the corresponding overview picture. (A-A'', B) Lateral views of enc1 expression reveals signals in ventral parts of the forebrain 
(arrow), the optic vesicle (opt), distinct parts of the hindbrain (arrowheads), somites (s), and the tail bud (tb) at 14 hpf. (C, D) Lateral view of a double staining </p>

<p>Evolution of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>



<p>(continued) </p>

<p>The secondary loss of the ENC3 gene in the lepidosaur lineage 
cannot be inferred with high confidence because of sparse 
sequence information in this lineage. Our attempt to trace 
conserved synteny between the chicken ENC3-containing 
genomic region and the green anole genome failed because 
of insufficient assembly continuity of the latter genome. In 
contrast, a considerably large number of eutherian genomes 
have been sequenced, and this speaks in favor of a secondary 
gene loss instead of incomplete genome sequencing. Other 
examples of genes that are absent from mammalian 
genomes, and therefore remained unidentified until recently, 
include the Bmp16 gene (Feiner et al. 2009), the Edn4 gene 
(Braasch et al. 2009), the Pdx2 gene (Mulley and Holland 
2010), and the Hox14 gene (Powers and Amemiya 2004). 
To address whether the presumed absence of ENC3 in this 
lineage was caused by a small-scale secondary loss or rather a 
large-scale deletion, we searched for conserved synteny be-
tween the chicken chromosomal region containing ENC and 
the human genome. We identified an array of orthologous 
genes shared between chicken chromosome 28 and human 
chromosome 19 (fig. 3), as previously suggested by macro-
synteny data (International Chicken Genome Sequencing 
Consortium 2004). The fact that orthologs of chicken ENC3-
neighboring genes are present in the human genome 
suggests a single-gene loss of ENC3 in the common ancestor 
of eutherians. It is interesting to investigate in future work 
what impact the loss of the ENC3 ortholog had on associated 
pathways and to what extent ENC1 and -2 might have possi-
bly compensated the roles of ENC3. </p>

<p>Expansion of the ENC Gene Family in 2R-WGD </p>

<p>By performing intragenomic comparison in chicken, we iden-
tified a quartet of chromosomes containing ENC1, -2, and -3 
and the region that presumably erstwhile harbored the 
putative fourth paralog (fig. 4). The patterns and timings of 
duplications in neighboring gene families lend support to the 
hypothesis that ENC1, -2, and -3 are derived from the 
2R-WGD early in vertebrate evolution (Dehal and Boore 
2005; Kasahara 2007; Putnam et al. 2008). The precise 
timing of the 2R-WGD was revealed to be after the split of 
the invertebrate lineages but before the divergence between 
cyclostomes and gnathostomes (Kuraku et al. 2009). </p>

<p>Quartets of chromosomes showing conserved synteny 
have been used as evidence of the 2R-WGD (Lundin 1993; 
Holland et al. 1994; Sidow 1996; Spring 1997). It was previ-
ously shown that chicken chromosomes 8, 10, 17, 28, W, and 
Z were derived from one single chromosome in the hypothet-
ical karyotype of the vertebrate ancestor (Nakatani et al. 
2007). This set of corresponding chromosomes after the 
2R-WGD does not form a quartet but a sextet, possibly </p>

<p>FIG. 6.-Continued 
of enc1 and egr2b in a 16 hpf embryo shows overlapping signal in rhombomeres 3 (r3) and 5 (r5). (E-E'') Dorsal view of an embryo at 16 hpf reveals enc1 
expression in r3 and r5, the tail bud, and additional signal in newly formed somites. (F) Lateral view of expression signal of enc1 in a 24 hpf embryo shows 
persistence of transcripts in distinct, anterior parts of the brain, and the tail bud. (G) Dorsal view of a 24 hpf embryo indicates that enc1 expression is 
concentrated in the central nervous system. (H, H') Lateral view of a 12 hpf embryo shows expression in anterior parts of the developing brain (arrow), 
presumptive r3 and r5, and the tail bud. (I) Dorsal view of the embryo in H reveals additional expression of enc2 along the posterior midline. (J) Dorsal view of 
a 24 hpf embryo shows enc2 expression in the developing brain and weak expression signal in the tail bud. (K, K') Lateral and dorsal views of enc3 expression 
signals in a 16 hpf embryo reveals expression in the tail bud and a distinct area of the developing hindbrain (arrowhead). (L) Dorsal view of embryo in K 
indicates that the hindbrain signal appears in a paired structure. (M, M') Dorsal view at 24 hpf shows enc3 expression in lateral parts of the hindbrain. </p>

<p>FIG. 7.-Scenario describing the diversification of the ENC gene 
family. This schematic gene tree illustrates the saltatory evolution of the 
ENC gene family in the lineage leading to vertebrates. At the base of 
vertebrate radiation, the ancestral ENC gene was quadruplicated in the 
2R-WGD giving rise to ENC1-3 as well as the fourth duplicate hypothet-
ically designated ENC4. No obvious cyclostome ortholog of gnathostome 
ENC1-3 was identified to date, which is best explained by their secondary 
losses in the cyclostome lineage. The hypothetical ENC4 gene presumably 
was secondarily lost in the lineage leading to gnathostomes and duplicated 
in cyclostomes giving rise to ENC-A and -B followed by presumed gene loss 
of ENC-B in hagfish. This hypothetical scheme is deduced from the phy-
logenetic trees shown in figures 1B and 2. Red crosses indicate inferred 
secondary gene losses, and question marks indicate uncertainty of the loss 
because of incomplete sequence information. </p>

<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>because of chromosome fission after the first round of dupli-
cation (Nakatani et al. 2007). Our analysis focusing only on 
parts of the chromosomes harboring ENC genes identified the 
same set of chromosomes with the exception of chromosome 
25, instead of W and 17 (fig. 4). More precisely, our analysis 
suggested that chromosomes 25 and 8 are derived from one 
proto-chromosome separated by fission (fig. 4). The incongru-
ence is best explained by different resolution of our study 
compared with that of Nakatani et al. (2007). Although we 
focused on a 20-Mb region flanking the ENC genes, the pre-
vious study employed fewer markers in the genomic region of 
our interest (Nakatani et al. 2007). This is why our study pro-
vided a higher resolution to detect microlevel genomic rear-
rangements relevant for ENC gene family evolution (fig. 4). </p>

<p>Conserved Role of ENC Genes in Brain Patterning </p>

<p>Chondrichthyans occupy a key phylogenetic position serving 
as outgroup to osteichthyans (including teleosts and tetra-
pods). Comparisons of features between chondrichthyans 
and osteichthyans allow us to reconstruct the ancestral state 
of jawed vertebrates. Our study advances the knowledge on 
both of these major gnathostome lineages by providing the 
first report of ENC1 expression patterns in a chondrichthyan 
and expression profiles of all three enc genes in a teleost. 
Expression analysis of the full set of ENC genes in a single 
species was hitherto only performed in the amphibian 
X. laevis (Haigo et al. 2003). Detailed cross-species compari-
sons need to be drawn with caution, and only homologous 
structures of corresponding developmental stages can pro-
vide meaningful insights into the evolution of expression pat-
terns and their regulation. In this respect, the expression 
patterns we obtained in the small-spotted catshark S. canicula 
and the zebrafish are difficult to compare to Xenc-1 to -3 
because Haigo et al. (2003) mainly focused on earlier devel-
opmental stages of X. laevis. In addition, the literature does 
not contain any detailed description of Xenc expression do-
mains in the developing brain as Garcia-Calero and Puelles 
(2009) and Hernandez et al. (1997) published for chicken 
(only telencephalon) and mouse ENC1, respectively. The 
ENC1 expression in the catshark prosencephalon (primordial 
plexiform layer of telencephalon and specific parts of the 
pallium; see fig. 5) has also been described for chicken 
(Garcia-Calero and Puelles 2009) and mouse (Hernandez 
et al. 1997). In addition, ENC1 is expressed in diencephalon 
(hypothalamus and prosomere 2 of the diencephalon), mes-
encephalon (optic tectum), and rhombencephalon (corpus 
cerebelli and its caudal extension to the neural tube) of cat-
shark (fig. 5) and mouse (Hernandez et al. 1997). This sug-
gests that the roles of ENC1 in brain patterning were already 
established in the last common ancestor of chondrichthyans 
and osteichthyans. Although deep homology between all 
bilaterian brains has been suggested (reviewed in Hirth 
2010; see also Northcutt 2012 and references therein; </p>

<p>Strausfeld and Hirth 2013), integrative centers such as the 
telencephalon have not been identified in nonvertebrate 
chordates (Wicht and Lacalli 2005; see also Pani et al. 
2012). Thus, well-organized brain structures based on the 
expansion of the neural tube should be regarded as a verte-
brate novelty. Its origin in the earliest phase of vertebrate 
evolution coincides with the establishment of the ENC gene 
family involved in brain patterning. It is intriguing to corrob-
orate if the emergence of this gene family contributed to the 
vertebrate novelty of the tripartite brain. 
We also identified differences in expression patterns sug-
gesting lineage-specific changes in developmental programs. 
ENC1 expression in presomitic mesoderm, the only expression 
domain outside the nervous system, and dorsal root ganglia of 
mouse embryos (Hernandez et al. 1997) have not been ob-
served in zebrafish (fig. 6A-G) and Xenopus (Haigo et al. 
2003). Vice versa, expression signals of ENC1 in the tail bud 
of zebrafish (fig. 6A-F) and somites of zebrafish (fig. 6A-E) 
and Xenopus (Haigo et al. 2003) are absent from the devel-
oping mouse (Hernandez et al. 1997). Thus, these expression 
domains of ENC1 were secondarily modified in the respective 
lineages. We identified a nonneural expression of ENC1 in the 
choroid plexus of a catshark embryo at stage 35 (fig. 7N) that 
has not been identified in any other species to date. The cho-
roid plexus potentially is an ancestral jawed vertebrate ENC1 
expression domain that was lost in the lineage leading to 
osteichthyans or, more parsimoniously, represents an autapo-
morphic feature of chondrichthyans. The ENC1 expression in 
the optic vesicle is shared between zebrafish (fig. 6A and B), 
Xenopus, and mouse but is not observed in catshark embryos 
(fig. 5) and presumably has been established in the common 
ancestor of osteichthyans. 
Within osteichthyans, expression data of ENC2 and -3 
genes as well as ENC1 allow inferences of possible shuffling 
of expression domains. Previously, the full set of ENC1, -2, 
and -3 genes has been investigated in X. laevis (Haigo et al. 
2003), and enc3 expression was analyzed in the zebrafish 
Danio rerio (Bradford et al. 2011; Qian et al. 2013). Our 
study describing expression patterns of zebrafish enc1, -2, 
and -3 combined with a reliable orthology assignment (fig. 
1B) allows a solid reconstruction of the evolution of expres-
sion domains within osteichthyans. During tailbud stages, all 
three Xenopus ENC genes are expressed in the neural tube 
and the otic vesicle, and only ENC1 is expressed in the tail 
bud. In addition, each gene possesses specific expression do-
mains, such as the dorsal fin, the cement gland, and the 
pronephric anlage for ENC1 (Xenc-3), ENC2, and ENC3 
(Xenc-1), respectively. In comparable stages of zebrafish 
(~16 hpf), all three enc genes are commonly expressed in 
the tail bud and the developing brain (fig. 6). Each zebrafish 
enc gene also has specific expression domains such as so-
mites, midline expression (presumably corresponding to the 
neural tube), and specific parts of the hindbrain for enc1, -2, 
and -3, respectively (fig. 6A, I, and K). The comparison of the </p>

<p>Evolution of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>



<p>overlap between expression domains of individual ENC genes 
between zebrafish and Xenopus reveals that most likely a 
different set of genes retained the ancestral expression do-
mains: only Xenopus ENC1, but all three zebrafish enc genes 
retained expression in the tail bud (fig. 6A, H, and K), and 
Xenopus ENC1 and -2, but only zebrafish enc1 retained the 
somite-specific expression domain (fig. 6A). The ENC1 gene is 
expressed in a more pleiotropic manner than its sister genes 
ENC2 and ENC3 in zebrafish (fig. 6) and Xenopus (Haigo et al. 
2003), suggesting its prevalent role in the developing nervous 
system. The expression of enc1 and -2 in the rhombomeres 3 
and 5 that we observed in zebrafish is absent from Xenopus 
(Haigo et al. 2003). However, the catshark ENC1 gene also 
showed expression in the hindbrain (fig. 5B-E and L). Thus, 
the role of ENC1 in the developing hindbrain might be con-
served between chondrichthyans and teleosts. Our compari-
son suggests a shuffling of expression domains among ENC1, 
-2, and -3 in osteichthyans. However, without expression 
data of ENC2 and -3 in a more basal lineage, for example, 
chondrichthyans, we cannot decide whether losses or gains in 
the lineages leading to osteichthyans or actinopterygians 
caused these differences in expression profiles. An intriguing 
question about possible shuffling of ENC expression domains 
also within tetrapods is currently elusive because of missing 
ENC2 expression data in mammals and the presumed ab-
sence of ENC3 in eutherians. Our expression analysis in the 
small-spotted catshark S. canicula suggests conserved devel-
opmental roles of ENC1 in brain patterning during jawed 
vertebrate evolution. The comparison of the expression pro-
files we gained for zebrafish enc1, -2, and -3 genes revealed a 
differential loss of ancestral expression domains between 2R-
derived paralogs. </p>

<p>Perspectives </p>

<p>It is usually the case that we can identify invertebrate ortho-
logs of vertebrate gene families even though they experi-
enced secondary events such as WGDs in the vertebrate 
lineage. Many of such genes are additional copies of existing 
genes derived from the WGDs. Otherwise, some genes arose 
de novo at the base of vertebrate evolution. Interestingly, the 
ENC family does not belong to these categories, possibly 
because of the saltatory evolution of the ancestral ENC 
gene early in the vertebrate lineage. This unique feature 
was masked for a long time by a lack of whole-genome 
sequences of invertebrates. To our knowledge, Satb1/2 
genes (Nechanitzky et al. 2012) in the homeobox-containing 
gene family belong to this category (Burglin and Cassata 
2002; Zhong et al. 2008). Our finding renders an insightful 
theme for future genome-wide studies to reveal more long-
standing genes that experienced saltatory evolution at the 
emergence of vertebrates and examine their contribution to 
phenotypic characters unique to vertebrates. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Supplementary tables S1-S4 and figure S1 are available at 
Genome Biology and Evolution online (http://www.gbe. 
oxfordjournals.org/). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Young Scholar Fund of the 
University of Konstanz and the research grant (KU2669/1-1) 
from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) to S.K., 
by the University of Konstanz to A.M., and by the 
International Max-Planck Research School (IMPRS) for 
Organismal Biology to N.F. S.M. was supported by the 
EVOLAX ANR grant (number ANR-09-BLAN-026201) and 
by Ré gion Bretagne (EVOVERT, grant number 049755). 
The authors thank Ursula Topel, Adina J. Renz, and Elke 
Hespeler for technical support in cDNA cloning and in situ 
hybridization, Dominique Leo for supplying zebrafish em-
bryos, and Sven Tschall, Holger Kraus, and Alexander 
Dressel from the Sea Life Centre Konstanz for providing cat-
shark embryos. A data set of predicted genes of the lamprey 
whole-genome sequence was produced by Falk Hildebrand. 
They are also grateful to Kinya G. Ota and Shigeru Kuratani 
for providing total RNA of the inshore hagfish and Yuko 
Ohta for providing gDNA of the horn shark and the lemon 
shark. Their gratitude extends to two anonymous reviewers 
for their constructive suggestions. </p>



<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>





<p>Evolution of the ENC Gene Family </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>





<p>Feiner et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>1502 Genome Biol. Evol. 5(8):1485-1502. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt104 Advance Access publication July 10, 2013 </p>

</text></tei>