<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3318181" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Sentinel lymph node biopsy (SLNB) has reduced, but not 
eliminated, surgical complications in those patients who avoid 
axillary lymph node dissection (ALND). The incidence of 
lymphedema after ALND has ranged from 6% to 30% [1-3]. 
However, recent short term studies demonstrated that lymph-
edema develops in 2-7% of patients with SLNB alone [4-6]. 
Recently, two articles regarding the preservation of arm 
nodes in breast cancer patients during ALND or SLNB were </p>

<p>published. Both authors concluded that the axillary reverse 
mapping (ARM) technique is feasible and the detection rate 
of blue lymphatics and/or nodes is 61-71% [7,8]. 
The ARM procedure is based on the hypothesis that the 
lymphatics from the arm are not involved in metastasis of 
breast cancer. However, several recent articles reported that the 
sentinel node was the same as the arm node in a small number 
of patients [9,10]. Another problem is that the identification 
rate of the arm node by blue dye is relatively low compared to 
the identification rate of the sentinel lymph node (SLN) [7,8]. 
The last issue is that the arm node may be involved with meta-
static foci in patients with axillary lymph node metastasis [10,11]. 
In our preliminary study, we confirmed that the arm node 
can be involved in metastasis from breast cancer through the 
common lymphatic channel; however, in non-concordant 
cases, the arm node can be safely preserved except for patients 
with high N stage [10]. But the location of the arm node and 
the practical efficacy after arm node preserving surgery 
remained uncertain. </p>

<p>The Efficacy of Arm Node Preserving Surgery Using Axillary Reverse 
Mapping for Preventing Lymphedema in Patients with Breast Cancer </p>

<p>Jung Woo Han, Yu Jeong Seo, Jung Eun Choi, Su Hwan Kang, Young Kyung Bae </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Soo Jung Lee </p>

<p>Departments of Surgery and </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Pathology, Yeungnam University College of Medicine, Daegu, Korea </p>

<p>O R I GINAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>J Breast Cancer 2012 March; 15(1): 91-97 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2012.15.1.91 </p>

<p>Purpose: The axillary reverse mapping (ARM) technique to iden-
tify and preserve arm nodes during sentinel lymph node biopsy 
(SLNB) or axillary lymph node dissection (ALND) was developed 
to prevent lymphedema. The purpose of this study was to inves-
tigate the location and metastatic rate of the arm node, and to 
evaluate the short term incidence of lymphedema after arm node 
preserving surgery. Methods: From January 2009 to October 
2010, 97 breast cancer patients who underwent ARM were 
included. Blue-dye (2.5 mL) was injected into the ipsilateral 
upper-inner arm. At least 20 minutes after injection, SLNB or 
ALND was performed and blue-stained arm nodes and/or 
lymphatics were identified. Patients were divided into two groups, 
an arm node preserved group (70 patients had ALND, 10 patients 
had SLNB) and an unpreserved group (13 patients had ALND, 4 
patients had SLNB). The difference in arm circumference between 
preoperative and postoperative time points was checked in both 
groups. Results: The mean number of identified blue stained arm </p>

<p>nodes was 1.4± 0.6. In the majority of patients (92%), arm nodes 
were located between the lower level of the axillary vein and just 
below the second intercostobrachial nerve. In the arm node 
unpreserved group, 2 patients had metastasis in their arm node. 
Among ALND patients, in the arm node preserved group, the 
difference in arm circumference between preoperative and post-
operative time points in ipsilateral and contralateral arms was 
0.27 cm and 0.07 cm, respectively, whereas it was 0.47 cm and 
-0.03 cm in the unpreserved group; one case of lymphedema 
was found after 6 months. No difference was found between arm 
node preserved and unpreserved group among SLNB patients. 
Conclusion: Arm node preserving was possible in all breast cancer 
patients with identifiable arm nodes, during ALND or SLNB, 
except for those with high surgical N stage, and lymphedema 
did not develop in patients with arm node preserving surgery. </p>

<p>Key Words: Arm, Breast neoplasms, Lymphedema, Sentinel lymph node biopsy </p>

<p>Correspondence: Soo Jung Lee 
Department of Surgery, Yeungnam University College of Medicine, 
170 Hyeonchung-ro, Nam-gu, Daegu 705-717, Korea 
Tel: +82-53-620-3587, Fax: +82-53-624-1213 
E-mail: crystallee@med.yu.ac.kr </p>

<p>This work was supported by the 2011 Yeungnam University research grants. </p>

<p>This article was presented in 2011 Annual meeting of Korea Breast Cancer 
Society and 2011 San Antonio Breast Cancer Symposium. </p>

<p>Received: July 5, 2011 Accepted: January 30, 2012 </p>

<p>J ournal of 
Breast 
Cancer </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>
JungWooHan,etal. </p>

<p>http://ejbc.kr 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2012.15.1.91 </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to investigate the location of the 
arm node and the metastatic rate of the arm node, and to 
evaluate the short term incidence of lymphedema after arm 
node preserving surgery. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Patients 
From January 2009 to October 2010, a study was performed 
using ARM with combined isotope and blue dye identifica-
tion at Yeungnam University Hospital. If a metastatic sentinel 
node was identified, ALND was performed. During this period, 
in the first 3 months, patients who received SLNB only or 
ALND followed by SLNB were included. Thereafter, patients 
who received ALND followed by SLNB were included. Patients 
whose arm nodes were not identified and who had bilateral 
breast cancer were excluded. Therefore, a total of 97 patients 
with clinically determined N0-N2 breast cancers were included. </p>

<p>SLNB procedure 
For SLNB procedures, patients were injected with 0.5-1 
mCi of </p>

<p>99m </p>

<p>Tc-human serum albumin (HSA) or </p>

<p>99m </p>

<p>Tc-phytate 
diluted with 0.1-0.2 mL of normal saline at the subareolar 
plexus, 30 minutes to 3 hours prior to surgery. After injection, 
lymphangiography was performed to identify the number 
and the location of SLNs. Before incision, radioactivity counts 
of the injection site, axilla and background were recorded 
using a hand-held gamma probe (Neoprobe, Dublin, USA) 
and hot SLN were defined by radioactivity &gt; 10% higher than 
background. </p>

<p>Axillary reverse mapping 
After general anesthesia, 2.5-3.0 mL of blue dye (methylene-
blue) was injected subcutaneously in the medial intermuscu-
lar groove of the ipsilateral upper arm using a 22-gauge injec-
tion needle. After injection, the arm was elevated above the 
heart level and massaged for 5 minutes to facilitate lymphatic 
drainage. After at least 20 minutes, SLNB or ALND was per-
formed in the usual manner. We noted blue nodes and/or 
blue lymphatics during dissection through the axillary fascia. 
To find the arm node, the first important step was the identifi-
cation of the second intercostobrachial nerve (Figure 1). 
When an arm node looked suspicious for metastasis because 
of its size or hardness, it was concordant with the SLN, or it 
was juxtaposed to a SLN that could not be separated from the 
SLN, the arm node was removed. When the decision as to 
whether to preserve the arm node or not was difficult, fine 
needle aspiration or frozen biopsy of a partial resection of the 
suspicious arm node was performed. Cross-over meant that </p>

<p>the SLN and the arm lymph node have common lymphatic 
channels. </p>

<p>Arm circumference measurement 
Arm circumference was measured at 10 cm proximal to the 
medial epicondyle before surgery and every 3 months after sur-
gery. We did a comparison between arm circumference change 
at the last follow-up point of the ipsilateral upper-extremity 
and contralateral upper-extremity circumference in each group. 
A comparison between arm circumference in the ipsilateral 
upper-extremity of the arm node preserved group and unpre-
served group was made, too. These changes in ipsilateral upper-
extremity circumference, corrected for any change in the con-
tralateral upper-extremity, were calculated using the following 
formula, which was introduced by McLaughlin et al. [12]. We 
defined lymphedema as measurement changes of &gt; 2 cm dur-
ing the follow-up period. </p>

<p>Pathologic measurement of the arm node or SLN 
Resected hot or blue lymph nodes that were &gt; 5 mm in size 
were sectioned at 2-mm intervals along the long axis, and those 
nodes &lt; 5 mm in size were sectioned at the largest diameter. 
Routine hematoxylin and eosin staining was done. The diag-
nostic criterion for lymph node metastasis was a cluster of 
&gt; 0.2 mm in size in the lymph node according to the 6th Amer-
ican Joint Committee on Cancer. </p>

<p>Data collection and analysis 
Data on arm circumference of the ipsilateral upper arm, the </p>

<p>Axillary vein </p>

<p>2nd intercostobrachial 
nerve </p>

<p>Arm node </p>

<p>Thoracodorsal 
vessel </p>

<p>Figure 1. Arm node. The arm node is usually located between the lower 
level of axillary vein and above or at the level of the second intercosto-
brachial nerve. </p>

<p>TheEfficacyofAxillaryReverseMappinginBreastCancerPatients </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2012.15.1.91 
http://ejbc.kr </p>

<p>location of the arm node, the crossover rate of the arm node, 
and the metastatic rate of the arm node were collected from 
all patients. All analyses were done in SPSS for Windows ver-
sion 17.0 (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, USA). The effect of arm node 
preserving surgery on lymphedema was analyzed by paired 
t-test (in a comparison between arm circumference changes 
at the last follow-up point of the ipsilateral upper-extremity 
and contralateral upper-extremity circumference in each group) 
and by an independent t-test (in a comparison between arm 
circumference in the ipsilateral upper-extremity of the arm 
node preserved group and unpreserved group). A p-value 
&lt; 0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Clinicopathologic characteristics of patients 
From January 2009 to October 2010, 97 patients with clini-
cally determined N0-N2 breast cancers were studied. The mean 
age of the study population was 46.2± 10.4 years (range, 22-77 
years) and the mean body mass index was 23.2 ± 3.5 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(range, 16.2-32.9 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). SLNB was done in all patients and 
ALND was done in 83 patients (85.6%). Stained arm lymph 
nodes were removed in 17 patients (17.5%): 4 patients in the 
SLNB only group and 13 patients in the ALND group. There 
were no significant differences in the mean tumor size, N 
stage, operative procedure, the number of removed lymph 
nodes, or follow-up periods between the arm lymph node 
preserved group and the unpreserved group (Table 1). </p>

<p>Axillary reverse mapping 
The mean number of identified blue stained arm nodes was 
1.4± 0.6 (range, 1-4). Average time to detection for arm nodes 
was 19.2± 13.5 minutes. The location of the arm node was the 
inferolateral side of axillary and thoracodorsal vessels in 57 
patients (58.76%), the inferomedial side in 37 patients (38.14%), 
the superolateral side in 2 patients (2.06%), and the superome-
dial side in 1 patient (1.04%) (Table 2, Figure 2). Arm nodes 
were located between the lower level of the axillary vein and just 
below the second intercostobrachial nerve in the majority of 
our patients (92%). Metastatic arm nodes were found in infero-
medial and inferolateral sides, and the arm node of the patient 
who developed lymphedema was found in the inferomedial side 
(Table 2). Among ALND patients, a stained arm lymph node 
was preserved in 70 patients and removed in 13 patients. Among 
SLNB only patients, a stained arm lymph node was preserved 
in 10 patients and removed in 4 patients. Seven patients had high 
radioactivity in the blue arm lymph node, so a cross-over node 
was identified in 7 of 97 cases (7.2%). Arm nodes were removed 
in 17 patients because of adhesion with SLNs (1 case), grossly </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of patients </p>

<p>Arm lymph node </p>

<p>SLNB (n= 14) 
ALND (n= 83) </p>

<p>Preserved (n= 10) 
No. (%) </p>

<p>Not preserved (n= 4) 
No. (%) 
p-value 
Preserved (n= 70) 
No. (%) </p>

<p>Not preserved (n= 13) 
No. (%) 
p-value </p>

<p>Age (yr)* 
49.2± 6.6 
48.7± 6.2 
0.909 
45.1± 11.2 
49.4± 7.2 
0.188 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>)* 
22.9± 2.7 
22.1± 2.6 
0.957 
23.2± 3.7 
23.1± 3.3 
0.926 
Surgery 
0.134 
0.980 
Mastectomy 
4 (40.4) 
0 (0.0) 
31 (44.3) 
9 (62.2) 
BCS 
6 (60.0) 
4 (100.0) 
39 (55.7) 
4 (30.8) 
Radiation therapy 
0.134 
0.883 
Yes 
6 (60.0) 
4 (100.0) 
47 (67.1) 
9 (69.2) 
No 
4 (40.0) 
0 (0.0) 
23 (32.9) 
4 (30.8) 
Tumor size (cm) 
1.9± 0.9 
1.6± 0.5 
0.577 
2.4± 1.4 
2.9± 1.7 
0.194 
N stage 
NA 
0.082 
N 0 
10 (100.0) 
4 (100.0) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
N 1 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
50 (71.4) 
7 (53.8) 
N 2 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
20 (28.6) 
5 (38.4) 
N 3 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (7.8) 
No. of Removed LN* 
6.0± 3.0 
4.3± 0.9 
0.134 
20.5± 7.1 
24.3± 7.0 
0.083 
Follow-up (mo)* 
12.0± 4.9 
18.0± 6.928 
0.089 
11.1± 3.9 
12.0± 5.1 
0.131 </p>

<p>SLNB = sentinel lymph node biopsy; ALND = axillary lymph node dissection; BMI = body mass index; BCS = breast conserving surgery; NA = not available; 
LN= lymph node. 
*Mean± SD. </p>

<p>Table 2. Location of arm node, metastatic rate and lymphedema </p>

<p>Location of arm node 
Patients 
No. (%) </p>

<p>No. of 
Metastasis </p>

<p>No. of 
Lymphedema </p>

<p>A. Inferolateral 
57 (58.79) 
1 
0 
B. Inferomedial 
37 (38.14) 
1 
1 
C. Superolateral 
2 (2.06) 
0 
0 
D. Superomedial 
1 (1.04) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>
JungWooHan,etal. </p>

<p>http://ejbc.kr 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2012.15.1.91 </p>

<p>enlarged arm nodes (5 cases), high surgical N stage (4 cases), 
and common lymphatic channel (7 cases). 
Two patients had metastasis in the arm node. The first pa-
tient had a common lymphatic channel between the arm node 
and the SLN. She had stage IIIA (T3, N2, M0) breast cancer; 
the histologic grade was 3 with lymphatic invasions and triple 
negative markers (estrogen receptor [ER] negative, progester-
one receptor [PR] negative, human epidermal growth factor 2 
[HER2] negative). The metastatic arm node of the second 
patient was not a common lymphatic channel, but rather an 
extranodal extension with N3 metastasis. She had stage IIIC 
(T1, N3, M0); the histologic grade was 3 with lymphovascular 
invasion, and markers for ER, PR, and HER2 were all negative. 
The arm node of this patient was removed and she had lymph-
edema after 6 months. </p>

<p>Changes in arm circumference 
The mean follow-up period was 9.6± 4.3 months (range, 3-
24 months): 8.8 months in the ALND group and 13.7 months 
in the SLNB only group. When comparing between arm </p>

<p>circumference changes at the last follow-up point of the ipsi-
lateral upper-extremity and the contralateral upper-extremity 
circumference, among the ALND group, the change in arm 
circumference of the ipsilateral upper-extremity after surgery 
was 0.27 ± 1.19 cm in the arm lymph node preserved group 
and 0.47± 0.85 cm in the unpreserved group. In the SLNB only 
group, the change in arm circumference after surgery was 
0.21 ± 1.31 cm in the arm lymph node preserved group and 
0.20 ± 0.46 cm in the unpreserved group (Table 3). When 
comparing between arm circumferences in ipsilateral upper-
extremity of the arm node preserved group and unpreserved 
group, in the SLNB group and ALND group, there was no 
significant difference. But in the ALND group, the arm circum-
ference changes of the arm node unpreserved group were big-
ger than that of the preserved group (0.51± 1.07 vs. 0.20± 0.83, 
p= 0.081) (Table 4). There were no lymphedema cases among 
the arm node preserved cases (70 cases), but one lymphedema 
developed in the unpreserved cases (7.7%), as stated above. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The ARM procedure was first introduced by Thompson et 
al. [7] and Nos et al. [8] in attempts to identify a separate drain-
age pathway of arm lymphatics from the sentinel lymphatic 
pathway to reduce the incidence of lymphedema by preserving 
the arm lymphatic pathways. The technique of arm node pres-</p>

<p>Table 3. Changes in arm circumference in each group </p>

<p>Arm node 
No. 
Circumference change 
Lymphedema 
Ipsilateral (cm)* 
p-value 
Contralateral (cm)* 
p-value </p>

<p>SLNB 
Removed 
4 
0.20± 0.46 
0.456 
0.02± 0.73 
0.950 
No 
Preserved 
10 
0.21± 1.31 
0.625 
0.39± 1.17 
0.321 
No 
ALND 
Removed 
13 
0.47± 0.85 
0.067 
-0.03± 1.20 
0.910 
1 case 
Preserved 
70 
0.27± 1.19 
0.057 
0.07± 0.86 
0.477 
No </p>

<p>SLNB= sentinel lymph node biopsy; ALND= axillary lymph node dissection. 
*Mean± SD. </p>

<p>2nd intercostobrachial nerve </p>

<p>Thoracodorsal vessel </p>

<p>Axillary vein 
A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Figure 2. Location of arm node. According to the axillary vein and tho-
racodorsal vessels, we divided the region into four quadrants. </p>

<p>Table 4. Changes in arm circumference between in the arm node pre-
served group and unpreserved group </p>

<p>Arm node 
No. 
Circumference change </p>

<p>L (cm)* 
p-value </p>

<p>SLNB 
Removed 
4 
0.17± 0.42 
0.982 
Preserved 
10 
0.18± 0.35 
ALND 
Removed 
13 
0.51± 1.07 
0.081 
Preserved 
70 
0.20± 0.83 </p>

<p>SLNB = sentinel lymph node biopsy; ALND = axillary lymph node dissection; 
L = (If/u -Ib) -(Cf/u -Cb); I = ipsilateral upper-extremity circumference; 
C= contralateral upper-extremity circumference; f/u= follow-up; b= baseline (or 
preoperative). 
*Mean± SD. </p>

<p>TheEfficacyofAxillaryReverseMappinginBreastCancerPatients </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2012.15.1.91 
http://ejbc.kr </p>

<p>ervation was based on the concept that the arm lymphatic 
pathway does not communicate with the sentinel lymphatic 
pathway. Since then, various reports have been introduced 
[8,11,13-16], but there are some key issues that need to be 
resolved in arm node preservation. First, the rate of arm node 
identification by blue dye staining is somewhat insufficient. 
Second, there are reports of metastasis in arm lymph nodes or 
in the lymphatic pathway. This raises problems regarding the 
safety of arm node preservation surgery. Third, common lym-
phatic channels are found between SLNs and arm lymph 
nodes. When a common channel exists, even SLNB can cause 
lymphedema. Fourth, the stained blue arm node may be juxta-
posed to the metastatic lymph node, which could result in dir-
ect invasion of the carcinoma and make it difficult to save the 
arm node. 
With the use of blue dye in arm lymph node detection, the 
detection rate has been 61-78.3% [7,8,13,16-18]. This low 
detection rate is associated with a short interval between dye 
injection and surgery, and a deeper location of the arm node 
than the SLN, which makes it hard to identify the arm node 
in the surgical field, and a lower detection rate of blue dye 
compared with radioisotope. In recent reports, the use of radio-
isotopes or fluorescence has increased the detection rate to 88-
100% [9,11,14]. 
In our preliminary study, the identification rate of arm nodes 
was 78%. In this study, the identification rate of arm nodes was 
not included in the original design of this study and not inves-
tigated because of the possibility of causing lymphatic injury 
by dissection beyond the SLNB field while searching for the 
arm node. We included only patients whose arm node was 
identified. Therefore, patients who had ALND were more 
frequently included than those who had only SLNB. Average 
time to detection for the arm node was 19.2 ± 13.5 minutes. 
During the operation, about 10 minutes after blue dye injec-
tion, we could find hardly any blue-stained arm nodes. When 
injected intravenously, the plasma half-life of methylene-blue 
dye has been reported as 5-6.5 hours [19,20]. However, the 
pharmacokinetics of methylene-blue dye in the lymphatic 
system and lymph nodes has not been well studied. In our 
study, although time to detection for the arm node was &gt; 40 
minutes in some cases, it did not seem to affect washing out of 
blue dye. Further studies are needed for determination of op-
timal time to detection of arm nodes. 
Metastasis of the arm node develops in 0-43% of patients 
[7,10,11,13,14]. Thompson et al. [7] and Nos et al. [8] reported 
that none of the arm nodes contained metastasis in the initial 
study. Later, Nos et al. [11] reported that ARM nodes showed 
metastatic involvement in 3 of 21 patients with N1-3 (14%). 
Similarly, in a study by Noguchi et al. [14], the metastatic rate </p>

<p>for arm nodes was 3 of 7 patients (43%) with a clinically posi-
tive node or positive SLN, and all were pN3. According to the 
study of Bedrosian et al. [13], the metastatic rate of arm nodes 
was 18%, including patients who received neoadjuvant che-
motherapy. When we summarized these results, arm node 
preserving surgery was contraindicated in patients who had a 
high N stage (N3). 
In our study, two patients had metastasis in arm lymph nodes. 
Possible explanations for such metastasis in an arm lymph 
node are a common lymphatic pathway, lymphatic intercon-
nections or direct invasion from juxtaposed sites of metasta-
sis. So, locally advanced breast cancer and N3 lymphatic inva-
sion should be contraindications for ARM and arm node pre-
serving procedures. In our cases, one patient had a common 
lymphatic pathway and the other patient had extensive nodal 
metastasis with N3 disease without common lymphatic path-
ways, suggesting direct invasion or lymphatic interconnec-
tions from metastatic nodes. 
In a recent article, the cross-over rate was 2.8-21%, depend-
ing on the methods, and included patients' characteristics [9, 
10,14,18]. Indeed, if a cross-over node was identified among 
SLNs, their preservation could be impossible. So when a cross-
over node is removed at SLNB, lymphedema could occur even 
after SLNB. In our study, the cross-over rate between arm and 
SLNs was 7.2%; a few previous reports have identified cross-
over rates of 13.3% and 18.9% [9,10]. 
All arm nodes cannot be preserved. When a surgeon sus-
pects that the arm node may involve metastasis in an opera-
tion field, preservation of the arm nodes mainly depends on 
the surgeon's experience. So we used fine needle aspiration or 
frozen biopsy of partial resection of suspicious arm nodes dur-
ing the operation. The number of patients from whom arm 
nodes were removed was 17; 7 patients had common lym-
phatic pathways with SLNs, 4 patients had grossly enlarged 
arm nodes, 4 patients had high surgical N stage, 1 patient had 
adhesions with a SLN, and 1 patient had a metastatic arm 
node on frozen biopsy. 
Boneti et al. [21] demonstrated 5 anatomic variations in arm 
drainage including the traditional teaching of lymphatics from 
the arm running juxtaposed to the axillary vein either above 
or below, slung low in the axilla, lateral apron, or medial apron 
(lateral and medial aprons usual consist of multiple blue nodes), 
or an entwined cord of lymphatics. The arm node was local-
ized in the lateral pillar of the axilla, and it was always found 
above or at the level of the second intercostobrachial nerve 
[11]. In our study, 97% of nodes were located between the 
lower level of the axillary vein and the second intercostobra-
chial nerve. To identify the arm node, an important landmark 
in the operative field is the axillary vein and the second inter-</p>



<p>
JungWooHan,etal. </p>

<p> 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4048/jbc.2012.15.1.91 </p>

<p>costobrachial nerve. The metastatic arm nodes were found in 
the inferomedial and inferolateral sides, one by each side, and 
the arm node of the patient who developed lymphedema was 
found in the inferomedial side. If more patients were included, 
statistical analysis would be possible, and the relationship 
between the location and metastasis of arm nodes would be 
identified. 
Boneti et al. [18] reported that there were no cases of lymph-
edema in those who had an arm node preserved at 6 months 
follow-up. In 51 patients with arm node preserving surgery, 
the incidence of lymphedema in those who had an arm node 
resected was 2 of 15 patients (13%). Casabona et al. [16] simi-
larly reported that there was no lymphedema at 9 months 
follow-up in 72 patients with arm node preserving surgery. In 
our study, average follow-up periods were 9.4 months. Of course, 
in the arm node preserved group, there was no lymphedema. 
For assessment of lymphedema, there are many methods 
such as measurement of arm circumference, water displace-
ment, self-assessment, bioimpedance spectroscopy and perom-
etry [12,22-26]. Measurement of arm circumference, used in 
our study, is simple and inexpensive, so it is routinely used in 
many studies as the method. In the ALND group, the absolute 
change in arm circumference before and after the operation 
was 0.27 ± 1.19 cm in the arm lymph node preserved group 
and 0.47 ± 0.85 cm in the unpreserved group; the difference 
was not statistically significant. However, the arm lymph node 
preserved group showed a tendency towards less change in arm 
circumference than the unpreserved group. When making com-
parisons between arm circumferences in the ipsilateral upper-
extremity of the arm node preserved group and unpreserved 
group, according to the formula introduced by McLaughlin et 
al. [12], there was no significant difference. But in the ALND 
group, the arm circumferences changes of the arm node unpre-
served group were bigger than the preserved group (0.51± 1.07 
vs. 0.20± 0.83, p= 0.081). There were no cases of lymphedema 
in 70 patients in whom the arm node was preserved during 
ALND, but there was 1 case of lymphedema in 13 patients in 
whom the arm node was resected during ALND. To verify the 
efficacy of arm lymph node preservation in preventing lymph-
edema, more patients should be included and longer follow-up 
periods are needed. We defined lymphedema as a measurement 
change of &gt; 2 cm during the follow-up period, but, self-assessed 
symptoms are also important. Although measurement change 
was less than 2 cm, if the patient feels discomforts, she may 
have lymphedema. In a future study, we should check patient's 
subjective symptoms. There was no significant change in arm 
circumference in the SLNB only group, and it was difficult to 
determine the efficacy of arm lymph node preservation because 
of the small number of patients. There was no axillary recur-</p>

<p>rence during the follow-up period in patients who underwent 
arm node preserving surgery. But, oncologic safety should be 
observed, always. Further studies about actual regional recur-
rence in preserved arm nodes are needed. In practical terms, 
arm node preserving surgery gives no advantage to patients 
with a cross-over node or N0, but does benefit patients with 
N1 and N2. Standard SLNB is not indicated in patients with 
N1 or N2, but SLNB should be done to preserve the arm nodes 
in these patients. 
In conclusion, arm node preserving surgery may prevent 
lymphedema in SLNB and/or ALND in patients with clinically 
determined N1 or N2 breast cancer. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </p>



<p>TheEfficacyofAxillaryReverseMappinginBreastCancerPatients </p>





</text></tei>