<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3060514" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Free fatty acid receptor 2 (FFA2; GPR43) is a G protein-cou-
pled seven-transmembrane receptor for short-chain fatty acids 
(SCFAs) that is implicated in inflammatory and metabolic dis-
orders. The SCFA propionate has close to optimal ligand effi-
ciency for FFA2 and can hence be considered as highly potent 
given its size. Propionate, however, does not discriminate 
between FFA2 and the closely related receptor FFA3 (GPR41). 
To identify FFA2-selective ligands and understand the molecu-
lar basis for FFA2 selectivity, a targeted library of small carbox-
ylic acids was examined using holistic, label-free dynamic mass 
redistribution technology for primary screening and the recep-
tor-proximal G protein [ 
35 S]guanosine 5-(3-O-thio)triphos-
phate activation, inositol phosphate, and cAMP accumulation 
assays for hit confirmation. Structure-activity relationship anal-
ysis allowed formulation of a general rule to predict selectivity 
for small carboxylic acids at the orthosteric binding site where 
ligands with substituted sp </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>-hybridized ␣-carbons preferen-
tially activate FFA3, whereas ligands with sp 
2 -or sp-hybridized 
␣-carbons prefer FFA2. The orthosteric binding mode was ver-
ified by site-directed mutagenesis: replacement of orthosteric 
site arginine residues by alanine in FFA2 prevented ligand bind-
ing, and molecular modeling predicted the detailed mode of 
binding. Based on this, selective mutation of three residues to 
their non-conserved counterparts in FFA3 was sufficient to 
transfer FFA3 selectivity to FFA2. Thus, selective activation of </p>

<p>FFA2 via the orthosteric site is achievable with rather small 
ligands, a finding with significant implications for the rational 
design of therapeutic compounds selectively targeting the SCFA 
receptors. </p>

<p>The seven-transmembrane G protein-coupled receptor 
FFA2, 
6 previously named GPR43, is expressed primarily on 
neutrophils, eosinophils, and other immune cells and responds 
to short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) (1), which are produced in 
high concentrations by microbial fermentation in the colon (2). 
The receptor plays a critical role in neutrophil recruitment dur-
ing intestinal inflammation (3), and FFA2-deficient mice show 
exacerbated or unresolved inflammation in colitis, arthritis, 
and asthma models, indicating that FFA2 can provide a molec-
ular link between fermentable dietary fiber and its beneficial 
effects on colitis and inflammation (4). These studies suggest 
that FFA2 is important in the regulation of intestinal inflamma-
tion and that the receptor might represent a new drug target for 
the treatment of inflammatory bowel disease. The receptor is 
also believed to play a role in energy homeostasis and appetite 
regulation (5). Further studies, however, are necessary to firmly 
establish these novel links, and such studies will depend criti-
cally on the availability of selective agonists and antagonists for 
the receptor. 
FFA2 and the closely related receptor FFA3 (GPR41) respond 
to SCFAs at high micromolar and millimolar concentrations 
with propionate being the most potent agonist for both recep-
tors (6 -8). Together with the medium-and long-chain free 
fatty acid receptor FFA1 (GPR40), the receptors form a subfam-
ily capable of sensing free fatty acids in concentrations corre-
sponding to elevated physiological levels (1, 9). Although the 
molar potency of the SCFAs on FFA2 and FFA3 must be 
regarded as low, the compounds are also very small. Ligand </p>

<p>6 The abbreviations used are: FFA2, free fatty acid receptor 2; FFA3, free fatty 
acid receptor 3; FFA1, free fatty acid receptor 1; SCFA, short-chain fatty 
acid; SCA, small carboxylic acid; GTP␥S, guanosine 5Ј-(3-O-thio)triphos-
phate; LE, ligand efficiency; SAR, structure-activity relationship; eYFP, 
enhanced yellow fluorescent protein; DMR, dynamic mass redistribution; 
GPCR, G protein-coupled receptor; IP 1 , inositol monophosphate; hFFA2, 
human FFA2; hFFA3, human FFA3; ECL2, extracellular loop 2. </p>

<p>efficiency (LE) is a recently introduced concept that assists lead 
selection by calculating binding energy per non-hydrogen atom 
as smaller, potent leads increase the likelihood of generating 
drug candidates with appropriate pharmacokinetic character-
istics (10, 11). LE has become popular in evaluation of early 
leads and is especially widespread in fragment-based drug dis-
covery where such small ligands are grown or assembled to 
larger and more potent leads (12, 13). Analysis of successful 
drugs has suggested that an LE of ⌬g Ͻ Ϫ0.3 kcal mol 
Ϫ1 per 
non-hydrogen atom is desirable, and empirical analysis has 
concluded that the maximal free energy contribution per heavy 
atom for non-metal ligands is around Ϫ1.5 kcal mol 
Ϫ1 per non-
hydrogen atom (14). Notably, acetate (C2) and propionate (C3) 
already have ligand efficiencies close to this value at FFA2 and 
FFA3 and can therefore be regarded as highly potent for their 
size (Table 1). Thus, it is unrealistic to expect that the potency 
of the SCFAs can be increased without at the same time con-
siderably increasing the size of the compounds. It is unclear, 
however, whether the orthosteric binding site can accommo-
date significantly larger ligands. A detailed understanding of 
the interactions of the SCFAs in the orthosteric binding site is 
expected to indicate the prospects for this strategy and to assist 
the rational design of larger, more potent and selective modu-
lators of FFA2 and FFA3. 
Previous structure-activity relationship (SAR) studies have 
found FFA2 to exhibit a preference for smaller SCFAs than does 
FFA3 with a rank order of potency of acetate (C2) ϳ propionate 
(C3) Ͼ butyrate (C4) Ͼ valerate (C5) ϳ formate (C1) for FFA2 
and C3 ϳ C4 ϳ C5 Ͼ C2 Ͼ caproate (C6) for FFA3 (15). A series 
of FFA2-selective allosteric agonists that exhibit positive coop-
erativity with SCFAs has also been disclosed (16, 17). Although 
these compounds certainly represent useful tools for further 
pharmacological studies of FFA2, because they bind to a site or 
sites distinct from the orthosteric binding pocket, it is possible 
that they may generate signals that are not identical to those 
triggered by SCFAs. The moderate solubility and metabolic lia-
bility of these allosteric compounds furthermore represent a 
limitation to their use (17). In the present study, we explored 
the potential of small carboxylic acids (SCAs) as pharmacolog-
ical tools and further investigated their interaction with the 
orthosteric binding site. To date, only a small number of satu-
rated straight and branched SCAs have been investigated as 
ligands at these receptors. Here we report the results from 
structure-activity investigations of an expanded set of SCAs, 
including carboxylic acids with additional branched, unsatu-
rated, and cyclic tails. The studies led to the identification of 
selective orthosteric ligands for both FFA2 and FFA3 and to the 
elucidation of a general rule to predict the FFA2/FFA3 selectiv-
ity of SCAs. Furthermore, this rule was validated by molecular 
modeling and site-directed mutagenesis at FFA2, resulting in 
the reversal of selectivity between FFA2 and FFA3 ligands at the 
mutated receptor. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Materials-Materials for cell culture were purchased from 
Invitrogen. Cell culture-compatible Epic biosensor micro-
plates and compound source plates were from Corning Inc. 
Restriction endonucleases and modifying enzymes were </p>

<p>from New England Biolabs, and all other laboratory reagents 
were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich unless otherwise speci-
fied. The radiochemical [ 
35 S]GTP␥S was from PerkinElmer 
Life Sciences. 
Formic acid (C1), acetic acid (C2), propionic acid (C3), 
butyric acid (C4), valeric acid (C5), methylthioacetic acid (1), 
3-methylbutyric acid (2), pivalic acid (3), 2-methylbutyric 
acid (4), cyclopropylcarboxylic acid (5), cyclobutylcarboxylic acid 
(6), 1-methylcyclopropanecarboxylic acid (7), vinylacetic acid 
(9), 3-pentenoic acid (12), acrylic acid (13), propiolic acid (14), 
2-butynoic acid (15), trans-crotonic acid (16), 2-methylacrylic 
acid (18), 3-methylcrotonic acid (19), trans-2-methylcrotonic 
acid (20), cyclopent-1-enecarboxylic acid (22), trifluoroace-
tic acid (23), 3-bromopropionic acid (24), (Ϯ)-2-methylcyclo-
propanecarboxylic acid (25; 1:4 mixture of diastereomers), 
1-cyanocyclopropanecarboxylic acid (26), pyruvic acid (27), 
and (Ϯ)-2-phenylpropionic acid (28) were purchased from Sig-
ma-Aldrich. Angelic acid (21) was purchased from ABCR 
(Karlsruhe, Germany). Cyclopropylacetic acid (8) was pur-
chased from Alfa Aesar. 3-Butynoic acid (10), 3-pentynoic acid 
(11), and cis-crotonic acid (17) were synthesized as described in 
the supplemental methods. The identity and purity of all com-
pounds were confirmed by 
1 H and 
13 C NMR. 
Plasmid Construction-The Flp recombinase-mediated ho-
mologous recombination system (Flp-In 
TM T-REx 
TM , Invitro-
gen) was used to generate cell lines stably expressing human 
FFA2 and FFA3 in a doxycycline-dependent manner. The cod-
ing sequences of FFA2 and FFA3 were subcloned from 
pcDNA3.1 (Invitrogen) into the inducible expression vector 
pcDNA5/FRT/TO (Invitrogen) via 5Ј HindIII and 3Ј XhoI. 
Veracity of the constructs was confirmed by restriction endo-
nuclease digestion. Cloning and generation of enhanced yellow 
fluorescent protein-tagged versions of human FFA2 and FFA3 
(FFA2-eYFP and FFA3-eYFP) and various binding mutants 
have been described elsewhere (18). 
Cell Culture and Generation of Stable Flp-In T-REx HEK293 
Cells-Flp-In T-REx cells were maintained in high glucose Dul-
becco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) supplemented with 
10% (v/v) fetal bovine serum, 1% penicillin/streptomycin mix-
ture, and 15 g/ml blasticidin at 37°C and 5% CO 2 in a humid-
ified atmosphere. 
To generate Flp-In T-REx 293 cells able to inducibly express 
a receptor of interest, the cells were transfected with a 1:9 mix-
ture of the desired receptor cDNA in pcDNA5/FRT/TO vector 
and the pOG44 vector (Invitrogen's expression vector for Flp 
recombinase) using a calcium phosphate DNA precipitation 
method according to the manufacturer's instructions. After 
48 h, the medium was changed to medium supplemented with 
100 g/ml hygromycin B (InvivoGen, Toulouse, France) to ini-
tiate selection of stably transfected cells. Expression of the 
appropriate construct from the Flp-In locus was induced by 
treatment with 1 g/ml doxycycline (Sigma) for 16 h. 
Dynamic Mass Redistribution (DMR) Assays (Corning Epic 
Biosensor)-DMR assays were performed on a beta version of 
the Corning Epic biosensor. A description and validation of this 
method is detailed in Schröder et al. (19). Briefly, cells were 
grown in Epic microplates, which are equipped with a resonant 
wave guide grating biosensor. GPCR signaling-induced mass </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>

<p>MARCH 25, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 10629 </p>

<p>redistribution, due to relocation of cellular constituents, leads 
to a change of the optical density in cells. This phenomenon can 
be detected by passing polarized broadband light through the 
bottom portion of cells and measuring changes in wavelength 
of the outgoing light. The wavelength shift (in picometers) is 
directly proportional to the amount of DMR. 
For Epic assays, HEK Flp-In T-REx cells were seeded onto 
fibronectin-coated 384-well Epic sensor microplates at a den-
sity of 15,000 cells/well to obtain confluent monolayers. After 
cultivation for 20 -24 h (at 37°C and 5% CO 2 ) cells were washed 
with Hanks' balanced salt solution containing 20 mM HEPES 
and kept for 1 h at 28°C in the Epic reader to allow for temper-
ature equilibration. The sensor plate was then scanned to 
obtain a base-line optical signature. Finally, compound solu-
tions were transferred into the sensor plate with an integrated 
liquid handling device, and cell responses were recorded con-
tinuously for at least 3600 s. All data were normalized to the 
responses induced by 300 M propionic acid, which were set to 
100%. 
[ </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S]GTP␥S G Protein Activation Assays-Membranes ex-
pressing wild type or mutant versions of human FFA2-eYFP or 
FFA3-eYFP were prepared from stable cell lines using 
0.5 g/ml doxycycline (24 h) as described elsewhere (20). 
[ 
35 S]GTP␥S binding assays were performed essentially as 
described (20). Briefly, 5 g of cell membranes were preincu-
bated for 15 min at 25°C in assay buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 
7.4, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 M GDP, 0.5% 
fatty acid-free BSA) containing the indicated concentrations 
of ligands. Binding was initiated by addition of 50 nCi of 
[ 
35 S]GTP␥S to each tube, and the reaction was terminated after 
1-h incubation by rapid filtration through GF/C glass filters 
using a 24-well Brandel cell harvester (Alpha Biotech, Glasgow, 
UK). Unbound radioligand was washed from filters by three 
washes with ice-cold wash buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 10 
mM MgCl 2 ), and [ 
35 S]GTP␥S binding was determined by liquid 
scintillation spectrometry. Membrane expression of each re-
ceptor was assessed by measurement of enhanced yellow fluo-
rescent protein (eYFP) using a PHERAstar FS microplate 
reader (excitation, 485 nm; emission, 520 nm; BMG Labtech, 
Offenburg, Germany). 
cAMP Accumulation Assays-Inhibition of forskolin-stimu-
lated cAMP accumulation in FFA3 cells was monitored with 
the MithrasLB 940 multimode reader (Berthold Technologies, 
Bad Wildbad, Germany) using the HTRF-cAMP dynamic kit 
(CIS Bio International, Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex, France) accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions. For the assay, cells were 
resuspended in assay buffer (Hanks' balanced salt solution, 20 
mM HEPES, 1 mM 3-isobutyl-1-methylxanthine) and trans-
ferred to 384-well small volume microplates (Greiner Bio-One, 
Frickenhausen, Germany) at a density of 50,000 cells/well. 
Plates were incubated for 30 min at 37°C before compounds 
were added in the presence of 5 M forskolin. After further 
incubation for 30 min at 37°C, the reactions were stopped by 
adding 1.25% Triton X-100 containing HTRF reagents. Plates 
were then incubated for 60 min at room temperature, and time-
resolved FRET signals were measured after excitation at 320 
nm. Both the emission signal from the europium cryptate-la-
beled anti-cAMP antibody (620 nm) and the FRET signal </p>

<p>resulting from the labeled cAMP-d2 (665 nm) were recorded. 
Results were calculated from the 665/620 nm ratio and ex-
pressed as ⌬F (⌬F % ϭ ((Standard or sample ratio Ϫ Ratio neg )/ 
Ratio neg ) ϫ 100). All data were normalized to the functional 
response obtained with 300 M propionic acid. 
Inositol Monophosphate (IP 1 ) Accumulation Assays-The 
HTRF-IP One kit (CIS Bio International) was used for mea-
suring IP 1 production in cells expressing FFA2. In a 384-well for-
mat, the cell suspension was dispensed at 100,000 cells/7 
l/well. After 20-min incubation at 37°C, 7 l of stimulation 
buffer (Hanks' balanced salt solution, 10 mM HEPES, 50 mM 
LiCl) containing various concentrations of ligand were added. 
After further incubation at 37°C for 30 min, 3 l of IP 1 -d 2 
conjugate followed by 3 l of europium cryptate-labeled anti-
IP 1 antibody were added. Time-resolved fluorescence at 620 
and 665 nm was measured with the Mithras LB 940 multimode 
reader after incubation at room temperature for 60 min, and the 
ratios of the signals expressed as ⌬F were calculated as 
described above. Data were normalized to the IP 1 response 
obtained with 300 M propionic acid. 
Molecular Modeling and Ligand Docking-Homology mod-
eling of hFFA2 and hFFA3 receptors using the ␤ 2 -adrenergic 
receptor (Protein Data Bank code 2RH1) as a template was con-
ducted using <rs id="software-3" type="software">MOE</rs> software (Molecular Operating Environ-
ment, <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-date">2009</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Chemical Computing Group, Inc.</rs>., Montreal, 
Quebec, Canada) with a default homology modeling protocol. 
Selection of homology models was based on the location of 
extracellular loop 2 (ECL2). Only models where ECL2 was 
located relatively similarly to the available crystal structures of 
the ligand-bound GPCRs were considered for docking. Thus, 
ECL2 conformations that prevented entrance to the putative 
binding cavity were excluded for the next steps. The available 
model of FFA1 (21), with the side-chain conformers optimized 
according to mutagenesis data for HisVI:16/4.56, ArgV:05/ 
5.39, HisVI:20/6.55, and ArgVII:02/7.35, was used to optimize 
the rough homology models of hFFA2 and hFFA3 obtained. 
Docking of SCAs into these models and those containing pro-
posed mutants was performed using the Glide module of 
<rs type="software">Schrödinger</rs> software (22). The Glide docking box included the 
cavity between transmembrane helices 3, 5, and 6 involving 
residues at positions V:05/5.39, VII:02/7.35, and VI:20/6.55, 
which we have shown to be crucial for anchoring the carboxyl 
group of fatty acids (18). The Glide default settings with the 
extraprecision scoring option were used for docking. Images 
were prepared using the Maestro 8.5 interface (23). 
Data Analysis-All data were quantified, grouped, and ana-
lyzed using <rs id="software-5" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">5.02</rs> and are expressed as mean Ϯ 
S.E. Data were fit to both three-parameter (fixed Hill slope) and 
four-parameter non-linear regression isotherms. The three-pa-
rameter curve fit was statistically appropriate in all cases. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characterization of Assays for Primary and Secondary 
Screening-FFA2 and FFA3 clearly mediate distinct physiolog-
ical and pathological outcomes (1), yet the absence of selective 
ligands for these receptors has hampered further pharmacolog-
ical studies of their individual functions. Both receptors couple 
to the Pertussis toxin-sensitive G␣ i/o family of G proteins, </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 • MARCH 25, 2011 </p>

<p>whereas FFA2 additionally couples to the G␣ q/11 family (6 -8, 
18). To avoid any potential bias in our assay results due to func-
tional selectivity of tested ligands, we used the holistic, label-
free Epic DMR assay, which monitors integrated traffic in the 
cell in real time without the need for epitope tagging or specific 
receptor probes (19, 24). Previously, we have demonstrated that 
DMR is a powerful assay platform for discerning the individual 
pathways activated by different GPCRs from all four G protein 
classes (G␣ i/o , G␣ s , G␣ q/11 , and G␣ 12/13 ) and is therefore unbi-
ased yet also pathway-sensitive (19). Thus, we initially tested 
the standard straight-chain orthosteric FFA2/FFA3 agonists, 
formate (C1), acetate (C2), propionate (C3), butyrate (C4), and 
valerate (C5), using the Epic DMR assay and compared these 
results with those obtained with the traditional [ 
35 S]GTP␥S 
binding assay, which measures predominantly G␣ i/o G protein 
activation (and hence is appropriate for both FFA2 and FFA3 
signaling). In addition, second messenger accumulation in 
whole cells was examined using IP 1 assays for FFA2 and cAMP 
accumulation assays for FFA3. 
Stimulation of Flp-In T-REx 293 cells stably transfected to 
express human FFA2 on demand resulted in positive deflec-
tions in DMR in a concentration-dependent manner (Fig. 1A), </p>

<p>the peaks of which can be converted into log concentration-
response curves to determine potency and efficacy for each 
agonist (Fig. 1C, red symbols, and Table 1). Notably, the DMR 
traces obtained for the same ligands at FFA2 (Fig. 1A) or FFA3 
(Fig. 1B) were qualitatively different, indicating the involve-
ment of non-identical signaling pathways and corroborating 
previous studies using traditional second messenger assays 
(6 -8, 18, 20). Millimolar activity of formate (C1) on FFA2 was 
confirmed (7), but no activity was observed on FFA3 at up to 10 
mM. In accordance with previous results, acetate (C2) was more 
than an order of magnitude more potent on FFA2, whereas 
propionate (C3) was the most potent SCFA and equipotent at 
each receptor (Fig. 1C and Table 1). Butyrate (C4) and valerate 
(C5) exhibited modest selectivity for FFA3 and in the case of 
valerate with lower efficacy than C3 also in agreement with 
other reports (6, 7). 
Examination of each of C1-C5 in traditional assays of recep-
tor activation resulted in a similar pattern of selectivity (Fig. 1, D 
and E, and Table 1), although as expected for signals with dif-
ferent levels of amplification and for comparisons between 
intact cells and cell membrane assays, absolute values of 
potency varied somewhat. Despite this, C1 and C2 had marked </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Short-chain fatty acid responses at FFA2 and FFA3 receptors. Signaling in response to the SCFAs formate (C1), acetate (C2), propionate (C3), 
butyrate (C4), and valerate (C5) in Flp-In T-REx 293 cells stably expressing either human FFA2 or FFA3 was assessed by measuring DMR in a Corning Epic 
biosensor. A and B, wavelength shift in picometers (pm) over time (seconds) was assessed upon stimulation with increasing concentrations of ligand as 
indicated at FFA2 (A) and FFA3 (B). Shown are representative traces from a single experiment representative of three separate experiments. C, concentration-
response curves were constructed from the maximum (max) wavelength shift per concentration normalized to C3 at the corresponding receptor, thereby 
allowing comparison of ligand selectivity at FFA2 (red circles) versus FFA3 (blue squares). Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. D, concentration-response curves were also 
generated using the [ 
35 S]GTP␥S binding assay to enable comparison of receptor selectivity using DMR with a more traditional GPCR readout. Data are mean Ϯ 
S.E., n ϭ 3. E, comparison of concentration-response curves from cAMP (FFA3) and IP 1 (FFA2) second messenger assays. Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>

<p>MARCH 25, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 10631 </p>

<p>selectivity for FFA2 over FFA3 (⌬pEC 50 of Ͼ1.8 and Ͼ1.3 for 
C1 and C2, respectively, where positive ⌬pEC 50 indicates selec-
tivity for FFA2 and a negative number represents FFA3 selec-
tivity). LEs were calculated using an average of the experimen-
tally determined pEC 50 values and indicate that C2 and C3 do 
indeed have LE values close to the maximal value (Table 1). 
Selection and Evaluation of Compounds-SCAs with lipo-
philic hydrocarbon tails consisting of four or fewer carbon 
atoms, including cyclic and unsaturated compounds with well 
defined three-dimensional structure, were selected to thor-
oughly explore the binding site of FFA2. We screened these 
SCAs at a single concentration of 300 M using the Epic DMR 
(Fig. 2). None of the noted chemicals produced significant 
DMR responses in native HEK 293 cells lacking expression of 
either FFA2 or FFA3 (Fig. 2A). A large proportion of the SCAs 
tested displayed activity, however, at either or both FFA2 (Fig. </p>

<p>2B) and FFA3 (Fig. 2C). SCAs with polar substituents, like 26 
and 27, or larger structures, like 28, were close to inactive on 
both receptors. Ligands that generated negative DMR signals 
were not pursued further, whereas the majority of the active 
compounds were then further explored with both full concen-
tration-response curves in the DMR assay and at [ 
35 S]GTP␥S 
binding and appropriate second messenger pathways (Table 1 
and below) after being subdivided into groups based upon their 
structure to enable SAR investigation. 
Branched and Cyclic Compounds-Receptor selectivity and 
SAR were examined with branched and cyclic SCAs using the 
Epic DMR assay (Fig. 3A) and conventional signaling assays 
(Table 1 and Fig. 3B). Isobutyrate, isovalerate (2), and pivalate 
(3), representing bulkier methyl-substituted analogs of propio-
nate and butyrate, have previously been reported to be at least 
an order of magnitude more selective for FFA3 over FFA2 (7). </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Agonist activities of small carboxylic acids on hFFA2 and hFFA3, calculated ligand efficiencies, and average selectivities </p>

<p>Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n Յ 3. </p>

<p>a DMR assay using the Corning Epic biosensor. 
b LE is calculated by the formula Ϫ⌬g ϭ Ϫ⌬G/N non-hydrogen atoms where Ϫ⌬G ϭ RTln(K D ) presuming that K D Ϸ EC 50 . The average of pEC 50 values from at least two differ-
ent assays was used in the calculation. Values are given as kcal mol 
Ϫ1 atom </p>

<p>Ϫ1 </p>

<p>. 
c Selectivity (calculated by ⌬pEC 50 ϭ pEC 50,FFA2 Ϫ pEC 50,FFA3 ) is based on the average pEC 50 values of the available assays. 
d n.a., not assessed. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 • MARCH 25, 2011 </p>

<p>We also found these ligands to be selective for FFA3 over FFA2 
(⌬pEC 50 ϽϪ0.4 for 2 and ϽϪ0.7 for 3; Fig. 3, A and B, and 
Table 1), and this relationship extended to sec-valerate (4; 
⌬pEC 50 ϽϪ0.7; Fig. 3, A and B). Interestingly, although selec-
tive for FFA3, both 2 and 4 were poorly efficacious at this recep-
tor in the DMR assay, an observation that was consistent at the 
other signaling assays for 4 but not 2. Cyclopropylcarboxylate 
(5), a somewhat bulkier analog of C3, exhibited moderate selectiv-
ity for FFA3, which was maintained upon replacing the cyclopro-
pyl with cyclobutyl (6). The bulky cyclopropyl analog (7) was equi-</p>

<p>potent with C3 on FFA3 and was ϳ30-fold selective for FFA3 over 
FFA2. A similar selectivity was observed for the cyclopropyl analog 
8. In each instance these ligands displayed close to full agonism at 
FFA3 (Fig. 3, A and B, and Table 1). Based upon these findings, 
branched and cyclic SCAs appear to be selective for FFA3 over 
FFA2 at a variety of signaling readouts. 
Non-conjugated Unsaturated Compounds-Introduction of 
a terminal double bond in C4 (9) resulted in preserved FFA3 
activity and slightly increased selectivity over FFA2 compared 
with C4 (⌬pEC 50 Ϫ0.7; Fig. 3, A and B, and Table 1), whereas </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Screening of small carboxylic acids using DMR. Cells either lacking both FFA2 and FFA3 (HEK293 cells; A) or expressing FFA2 (B) or FFA3 (C) were 
stimulated with a 300 M concentration of individual SCAs or positive controls (SCFAs C1, C2, C3, and C5) and DMR-monitored over a 60-min period. B, panel 
i, DMR traces for SCAs over time at FFA2. B, panel ii, maximum (max) wavelength shift (pm) achieved at FFA2 during the length of the assay for each SCA in 
triplicate. C, DMR traces (panel i) and maximum wavelength shift (panel ii) for the FFA3 counterscreen. Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>

<p>MARCH 25, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 10633 </p>

<p>introduction of a terminal alkyne (10), which produces a con-
strained and distinctly shaped C4 analog, resulted in an order of 
magnitude lower activity on both receptors while maintaining 
selectivity for FFA3 (⌬pEC 50 Ͻ Ϫ0.4; Fig. 3, A and B). The poor 
potency of 10 resulted in loss of signal in the [ 
35 S]GTP␥S bind-
ing assay (Table 1). Greatest selectivity for FFA3 in the Epic 
DMR and second messenger assays was achieved with the rigid-
ified unsaturated analog 12 (⌬pEC 50 ϭ Ϫ1.4; Fig. 3, A and B). 
Interestingly, 12 displayed higher efficacy on FFA3 in the </p>

<p>receptor-proximal [ 
35 S]GTP␥S assay, yet the potency of 12 at 
each receptor was equivalent (Table 1). Regardless, compound 
12 is also instructive because it demonstrates that a rigidly 
extended C 4 tail can be contained within the binding sites of 
both receptors. 
Conjugated Unsaturated Compounds-Acrylate (13) repre-
sents a narrower analog of propionate and exists preferentially 
in a flat conformation because of the conjugation between the 
alkene and the carboxylic acid. This compound was a full ago-</p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Structure-activity relationships of branched, cyclic, and non-conjugated unsaturated SCAs at FFA2 and FFA3. A, DMR maximum (max) 
response (pm) concentration-response curves to branched/cyclic (panels i-vi) and non-conjugated unsaturated (panels vii-ix) SCAs (chemical structures are 
inset) were generated in cells stably expressing either FFA2 (circles) or FFA3 (squares). Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. B, concentration-response curves of the same 
chemical series in IP 1 (FFA2) and cAMP (FFA3) assays. Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 • MARCH 25, 2011 </p>

<p>nist at both FFA2 and FFA3 but was moderately selective for 
FFA2 (⌬pEC 50 ϭ 0.7; Fig. 4, A and B). Introduction of a triple 
bond with propargylate (14) resulted in a ligand markedly more 
selective for FFA2 (⌬pEC 50 Ͼ 1.3; Fig. 4, A and B, and Table 1) 
with little to no activity observed in either the Epic DMR assay 
or second messenger assays for FFA3. For FFA2, methyl substi-
tutions were accommodated at all positions on acrylate (16-20) 
(Fig. 4, A and B, and Table 1). In contrast, FFA3 was far less 
tolerant to conjugated unsaturated compounds. Of the ligands 
tested, trans-3-methyl (16), cis-3-methyl (17), and 2-methyl 
(18) substitutions were moderately active with reduced efficacy 
and, for 17, reduced potency in both the DMR and signaling 
assays (⌬pEC 50 ϭ 0.6). The terminally dimethyl-substituted 19 
maintained the selectivity of 17, whereas 2,3-cis-dimethylacry-
late (20) and 2,3-trans-dimethylacrylate (21) both exhibited 
Ͼ Ͼ100-fold selectivity for FFA2 (Fig. 4, A and B, and Table 1). 
The conjugated cyclopentene analog 22 exhibited activity with 
low efficacy on FFA2 but again Ͼ Ͼ100-fold selectivity over 
FFA3 (Table 1). Thus, the series of conjugated unsaturated 
SCAs preferentially activated the FFA2 receptor, and this was 
achieved without substantial loss of LE. 
General Rule for SCA Selectivity at FFA2 and FFA3 and 
Molecular Modeling of Binding Pocket-Close inspection of the 
SAR data described above led us to hypothesize a general rule </p>

<p>governing SCA selectivity at FFA2 and FFA3. Overall, we found 
that C1, C2, and all conjugated unsaturated carboxylic acids 
exhibited substantial selectivity for FFA2, whereas the remain-
ing compounds exhibited selectivity for FFA3. Thus, we pro-
pose that ligands with sp 
2 -or sp-hybridized ␣-carbon preferen-
tially activate FFA2, whereas FFA3-selective ligands contain a 
substituted sp 
3 -hybridized ␣-carbon. Furthermore, this rela-
tionship indicates that the binding pockets of FFA2 and FFA3 
must be subtly different despite both receptors requiring the 
same four basic amino acids for SCFA binding (18). 
To examine the molecular determinants of SCA ligand selec-
tivity, we docked the FFA2-selective compound 20 (Fig. 5A) 
and FFA3-selective compound 7 (Fig. 5B) into our molecular 
models of the receptors. Because 12 also showed receptor-spe-
cific effects, albeit on efficacy rather than potency in the 
[ 
35 S]GTP␥S assay, we also modeled 12 at FFA3 (Fig. 5C). We 
have previously demonstrated that SCFA binding requires two 
conserved arginine residues in both FFA2 and FFA3, ArgV:05/ 
5.39 and ArgVII:08/7.35 (numbered according to the systems of 
Schwartz and Baldwin (25, 41, 42) and Ballesteros and Wein-
stein (26)), which are presumed to act as anchoring residues for 
the carboxylic acid on SCFAs (18). As expected, the carboxyl 
group of each of the ligands is coordinating these arginines 
in the models, and the ligands are placed in the cavity com-</p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Structure-activity relationships of conjugated unsaturated SCAs at FFA2 and FFA3. A, panels i-viii, DMR maximum response (pm) concentra-
tion-response curves to conjugated unsaturated SCAs were generated for either FFA2 (circles) or FFA3 (squares). Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. B, panels i-viii, 
concentration-response curves of the same chemical series in IP 1 (FFA2) and cAMP (FFA3) assays. Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>

<p>MARCH 25, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 10635 </p>

<p>prising transmembrane helices 3, 5, and 6 (Fig. 5, A and B). In 
particular, the SCA is surrounded by Tyr 
90 (III:09/3.33), 
Glu 
166 (ECL2), Phe 
168 (ECL2), Leu 
183 (V:08/5.42), Cys 
184 (V:09/ 
5.43), Tyr 
238 (VI:16/6.51), and His 
242 (VI:20/6.55) in hFFA2 and 
by Phe 
96 (III:09/3.33), Leu 
171 (ECL2), Phe 
173 (ECL2), Met 
188 (V: 
08/5.42), Ala 
189 (V:09/5.43), Tyr 
241 (VI:16/6.51), and His 
245 (VI: 
20/6.55) in hFFA3. We noted that the non-conserved residues 
closest to the aliphatic moiety are residues at positions III:09/ 
3.33, V:08/5.42, and V:09/5.43 and Glu 
166 /Leu 
171 in ECL2. The 
aromatic residues at position III:09/3.33 form hydrophobic 
interactions with the ligand; the tyrosine OH group at this posi-
tion in FFA2 is predicted to interact with the carboxyl group of 
20. It is unlikely that this hydrogen-bond is crucial for binding, 
however, because the conserved positively charged arginines 
already anchor this group; thus, this residue is not thought to 
contribute to ligand selectivity. Of the remaining non-con-
served residues within the predicted binding pocket, amino 
acids at positions 5.42 and 5.43 are likely to provide hydropho-
bic interactions with the aliphatic moiety of the SCAs. 
Glu 
166 (ECL2) of FFA2 forms a salt bridge with Arg 
255 (VII:08/ 
7.35), thereby coordinating the position of Arg 
255 , whereas 
Leu 
171 (ECL2) of FFA3 has hydrophobic interactions with 
ligands 7 and 12 (Fig. 5C). Because our SAR data indicated that 
FFA3 preferred larger saturated or alicyclic moieties within the 
SCAs compared with FFA2, which preferred flat unsaturated 
moieties, we calculated the volume of the orthosteric binding 
sites. In accordance with our SAR studies, we found that the 
modeled binding site volume of FFA3 (105 Å 
3 ) is more than 
double the volume of FFA2 (41 Å </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>). This difference may be due 
to the presence of the non-conserved residues discussed earlier 
as well as different residue packing caused by overall sequence 
differences between the receptors. To verify that our models 
and, therefore, our binding pocket hypotheses were predictive, 
we next examined signaling at a series of orthosteric binding 
site mutants. 
Small Carboxylic Acids Bind to Orthosteric Binding Sites of 
FFA2 and FFA3-We have previously demonstrated that SCFA 
binding requires the two conserved arginine residues described 
above (18). To establish whether the selective SCAs are also 
accommodated within the orthosteric sites of FFA2 and FFA3, 
respectively, and to confirm positioning of ligands 20, 7, and 12 
in our molecular models, we examined the effect of these 
ligands in [ 
35 S]GTP␥S binding assays following mutation of 
either ArgV:05/5.39 or ArgVII:08/7.35 in FFA2 and FFA3. 
Membranes were isolated from Flp-In T-REx 293 cells stably 
expressing hFFA2 R180A(V:05/5.39)-eYFP, hFFA2 R255A(VII: 
08/7.35)-eYFP, hFFA3 R185A(V:05/5.39)-eYFP, or hFFA3 
R258A(VII:08/7.35)-eYFP in an inducible manner (18). For 20, 
stimulation of wild type FFA2-eYFP but not hFFA2 R180A(V: 
05/5.39)-eYFP or hFFA2 R255A(VII:08/7.35)eYFP membranes 
resulted in [ 
35 S]GTP␥S incorporation (pEC 50 ϭ 4.17 Ϯ 0.09; 
Fig. 6A), whereas no activity was observed at any of the forms </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Molecular models of selective SCAs in orthosteric binding 
sites of FFA2 and FFA3. A, molecular model of compound 20 in the puta-
tive FFA2 orthosteric binding site. B, compound 7 in FFA3 binding site. </p>

<p>C, compound 12 in FFA3 binding site. Ligand is represented by yellow 
sticks, side chains of the residues forming the binding site only are shown 
in green, and the backbone of the receptor is in ribbon style. The GPCR 
residue notations of Schwartz and Baldwin (25, 41, 42) and Ballesteros and 
Weinstein (26) are shown in parentheses. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 • MARCH 25, 2011 </p>

<p>of FFA3 (Fig. 6B). Both arginine residues were also required for 
activity of ligand 7 as mutation of either ArgV:05/5.39 or 
ArgVII:08/7.35 prevented signal transduction at both FFA3 
(pEC 50 ϭ 3.74 Ϯ 0.08 for wild type; Fig. 6C) and also FFA2 
where it is a weak partial agonist (pEC 50 ϭ 3.05 Ϯ 0.09 for wild 
type; Fig. 6D). Thus, it is clear that the carboxylic acid head 
groups of the SCAs described here are also coordinating with 
the positively charged arginines in the orthosteric binding site. 
Examination of SCA Binding Pocket at FFA2-To interrogate 
the putative mode of binding of FFA2-selective ligands, we 
replaced three non-conserved residues lining the FFA2 binding 
site with the corresponding residues in FFA3. By making such a 
triple mutant receptor, we aimed to change the architecture of 
the binding pocket to more closely resemble that of FFA3 and, if 
our hypotheses were correct, change the selectivity of ligands 
acting at this receptor. Thus, the FFA2 residues Glu </p>

<p>166 </p>

<p>(ECL2), 
Leu 
183 (V:08/5.42), and Cys 
184 (V:09/5.43) were substituted by 
the corresponding FFA3 residues Leu, Met, and Ala, respec-
tively (hereafter referred to as "FFA2 triple") within the context 
of hFFA2-eYFP (Fig. 7, A and B). Compounds 7 and 12 were 
subsequently docked in the model of FFA2 triple, indicating 
that mutation of these residues was consistent with facilitating 
FFA3 ligand binding. We again calculated the volume of the 
ligand binding site (this time at FFA2 triple) and found that 
exchange of the FFA3 residues within FFA2 increased the vol-
ume of the orthosteric site (50 Å 
3 ), favoring accommodation of 
the bulkier 7 (Fig. 7A) and 12 (Fig. 7B), which are now located 
deeper within the pocket. Thus, to examine whether the triple 
mutant could lead to reversal of ligand selectivity at FFA2, a 
stable inducible Flp-In T-REx 293 cell line was established. 
FFA2 triple expression was assessed using eYFP fluorescence as 
a surrogate parameter and found to be at a level similar to wild </p>

<p>type hFFA2-eYFP and not significantly different from wild type 
hFFA3-eYFP (Fig. 7C). 
As noted earlier, propionate is equipotent at FFA2 and FFA3 
in the [ 
35 S]GTP␥S assay (Fig. 7D). Propionate potency at FFA2 
triple was identical to wild type FFA2 and FFA3 (Fig. 7D), indi-
cating that these modifications to the orthosteric binding site of 
FFA2 did not cause gross changes in receptor conformation. 
Consistent with the Epic DMR assay data in Fig. 4A, 20 was 
selective for FFA2 because it was inactive at FFA3 (Fig. 7E). 
Critically, however, activity of 20 at FFA2 triple was markedly 
impaired, suggesting that the binding pocket could no longer 
effectively accommodate or be activated by this sp 
2 ligand (Fig. 
7E). Because of their differing effects on selectivity and efficacy 
in the [ 
35 S]GTP␥S assay, we also examined both 7 and 12 at the 
FFA2 triple chimera. The highly selective and bulky compound 
7 displayed Ͼ100-fold selectivity for FFA3 over FFA2 (pEC 50 ϭ 
3.76 Ϯ 0.26 at FFA3 and pEC 50 ϭ 1.65 Ϯ 0.17 at FFA2; Fig. 7F). 
Mutation within the FFA2 orthosteric binding pocket was able 
to rescue 7 function at FFA2 as this ligand displayed equivalent 
potency at FFA2 triple and the FFA3 receptor (pEC 50 ϭ 3.80 Ϯ 
0.12) (Fig. 7F), although full agonism was not achieved. Con-
versely, although ligand 12 was highly selective for FFA3 in the 
DMR and second messenger assays (Fig. 3 and Table 1), in the 
[ 
35 S]GTP␥S assay, it was equipotent at the wild type receptors 
but differed in the magnitude of signal effect. Interestingly, this 
poor efficacy at FFA2 wild type was completely reversed at 
FFA2 triple with maximum activation even exceeding that of 
wild type FFA3 (Fig. 7G). Thus, guided by developing a chemi-
cal rule for predicting specific activation of SCFA receptors and 
in conjunction with molecular modeling and site-directed 
mutagenesis, we were able to transfer FFA3 selectivity to FFA2. </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. Activity of selective SCAs at FFA2 and FFA3 orthosteric binding mutants. A and B, the FFA2-selective SCA 20 was assessed in the [ 
35 S]GTP␥S 
binding assay at wild type (WT) FFA2-eYFP (A) or WT FFA3-eYFP (B) and the corresponding orthosteric binding site mutants R(V:05/5.39)A and R(VII:08/7.35)A 
(amino acid and sequence number for each receptor construct is indicated in the key). C and D, the same orthosteric binding site mutants were assayed in 
response to the FFA3-selective SCA, 7. Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>

<p>MARCH 25, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 10637 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>SCFAs are the endogenous ligands for both of the closely 
related receptors FFA2 and FFA3, acting with similar potency 
for all but the very shortest chain length SCFAs, C1 and C2 (1). 
The physiological roles of the two receptors have largely been 
based on studies with knock-out mice. The expression of FFA2, 
however, was recently found to be reduced in FFA3 knock-out 
mice, making it difficult to draw clear conclusions from these 
studies (27). Limited endogenous ligand selectivity, the low 
potency of these ligands, and the absence of selective </p>

<p>orthosteric compounds are therefore currently major obstacles 
to the exploration of the physiological and pathological roles of 
these receptors both in vitro and in vivo (15). In the present 
study, we sought to address this issue by examining the molec-
ular determinants of ligand selectivity at FFA2. By screening a 
targeted library of SCAs at FFA2 and counterscreening at FFA3 
using the holistic Epic DMR biosensor assay, we discovered a 
series of ligands with selectivity for either receptor. SAR analysis of 
the screening hits in combination with molecular modeling and 
site-directed mutagenesis enabled formulation of a general chem-</p>

<p>FIGURE 7. Triple mutation within FFA2 orthosteric binding site confers FFA3 ligand selectivity to resulting receptor chimera. A and B, molecular model 
of the hFFA2 E166L(ECL2)/L183M(V:08/5.42)/C184A(V:09/5.43)-eYFP chimeric receptor, FFA2 triple, showing docking of 7 (A) and 12 (B). C, expression of each 
receptor was established by eYFP fluorescence where HEK293 autofluorescence was used as a negative control. RLU, relative light units. D-G, [ 
35 S]GTP␥S 
binding was assessed for non-selective (C3; D), FFA2-selective (20; E), and FFA3-selective (7 and 12; F and G, respectively) SCAs at FFA2 triple. Responses were 
compared with WT FFA2 and FFA3 in each experiment. Data are mean Ϯ S.E., n ϭ 3. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 • MARCH 25, 2011 </p>

<p>ical rule to predict receptor preference of SCAs. Three amino acids 
were identified as critical for selective orthosteric activation of 
FFA2, and transfer of these residues to the binding pocket of FFA3 
was sufficient to confer FFA3 ligand selectivity to the FFA2 recep-
tor. Our findings therefore provide the first description of the 
determinants of selective orthosteric activation for FFA2. 
Propionate is the most potent SCFA at both FFA2 and FFA3 
and displays close to maximal LE for both these receptors; i.e. it 
is highly potent based on its size. Although increased potency 
requires larger ligands, here we demonstrate that development 
of small but selective ligands is indeed feasible. In fact, 20 and 
21 represent two notable examples as they are both selective 
and potent given their size. These two ligands are expected to 
be instrumental for the design of novel selective orthosteric 
FFA2 activators. A multifaceted program combining the vali-
dated molecular model of FFA2 described herein with frag-
ment-based drug discovery may facilitate the identification of 
ligands with enhanced potency either by "growing" the ligands 
stepwise or by linking the SCAs to fragments docked at acces-
sible positions within the receptor (13). In recent times, a series 
of receptors have been shown to be activated by endogenous 
small molecule ligands that are more traditionally considered as 
products of intermediary metabolism (28 -31). All of these 
ligands have modest potency at their target receptors, and the 
concepts elucidated and discussed here may have general value 
in the identification of selective and more potent orthosteric 
agonists. This is particularly relevant as the potential therapeu-
tic implications of many of these receptors, e.g. GPR109A, 
clearly define a need to develop potent and selective agonists 
rather than antagonists (32, 33). 
A well defined shape was a criterion for selection of screening 
compounds to facilitate SAR analysis and modeling. Apart from 
C5, they only have zero to two rotatable bonds (defined as the 
number of non-cyclic single bonds where rotation leads to a 
change in the position of non-hydrogen atoms relative to the 
remaining molecule; e.g. 14 has zero rotatable bonds). These 
ligands adopt a very limited number of possible conformations 
and are therefore ideally suited for modeling and docking stud-
ies at the FFA2 binding site. Indeed, evidence of the accuracy of 
our FFA2 model and SCA docking is provided by the fact that 
we were able to identify the anchoring arginines for the carbox-
ylic acid group in transmembrane domain V and transmem-
brane domain VII and transfer ligand selectivity between FFA2 
and FFA3 by exchanging just three key amino acids. Very few 
examples of such a transfer of ligand selectivity between GPCR 
binding sites have been described. A notable example is the 
transfer of the binding of AMD3100 from CXCR4 to CXCR3 
achieved by a double mutation and the presence of two essential 
aspartates conserved in both receptors (34). 
It is well known from a number of studies that receptor phar-
macology may vary depending on the cellular context and the 
signaling end point under investigation (35-38). The SCFA 
receptors examined herein are known to engage with G␣ i/o 
family proteins (FFA3) or with both G␣ i/o and G␣ q/11 (FFA2). 
This implies that, at least for FFA2, ligands may be identified 
with preference for individual signaling pathways. To rule out 
the possibility that so-called biased ligands may escape detec-
tion when using a single functional end point assay, one can </p>

<p>either gather biological information by testing compounds in 
several parallel assays or rather use one of the novel, label-free 
assay technologies that capture whole cell responses in a man-
ner comparable with tissue bioassays (24, 39, 40). The latter 
may also have the advantage that ligand activity will reflect an 
integrated response of a living cell rather than a readout deter-
mined in isolation and underappreciative of intertwined signal-
ing networks that overlap in time and space. In our study, we 
took advantage of the Corning Epic biosensor, which translates 
receptor activation into real time optical traces in a pathway-
unbiased yet pathway-sensitive manner (19) and chose this 
method for primary screening. Hit confirmation was per-
formed with classical biochemical ([ 
35 S]GTP␥S) or second 
messenger (cAMP and IP 1 ) assays as validation. The majority of 
hits identified using the holistic approach were also confirmed 
in the classical assays. However, we also noted the existence of 
compounds such as 10 with activity in the Epic but complete 
inactivity in [ 
35 S]GTP␥S binding assays. Lack of [ 
35 S]GTP␥S 
incorporation induced by 10 at FFA2 might be explained by its 
inability to engage G␣ i/o signaling; however, inactivity at FFA3 
of 10 is hard to rationalize given that activity was also detected 
in parallel cAMP inhibition assays. Hence, it is possible that the 
receptor-proximal [ 
35 S]GTP␥S binding assay is simply not sen-
sitive enough to identify activators with poor potency and effi-
cacy because this is likely to be linked closely to receptor occu-
pancy, whereas more distal signals, such as those measured in 
the DMR assay, often provide substantial amplification and 
receptor reserve (39). In contrast, 2 was hardly active in DMR 
assays on either receptor but appeared to be a high efficacy 
agonist in GTP␥S binding. As DMR is an integrated signal, the 
absence of positive DMR for 2 may reflect additional but oppos-
ing cellular events triggered by this compound. Overall, these 
data demonstrate the strength of combining traditional end 
point with novel holistic assays to unravel mechanistic differ-
ences of compounds that would remain unexplored when using 
either method in isolation. 
It is interesting that introduction of an alkene or alkyne con-
jugated with the carboxylic acid in the SCAs consistently 
reversed FFA receptor selectivity and that FFA2 was able to 
accommodate and respond to larger compounds provided that 
they contained this conjugated unsaturation. Acrylate (13) is 
the parent compound of most of these and has agonist activity 
comparable with C3 yet preferentially activates FFA2 over 
FFA3. All substituted acrylates (16-22) were FFA2 agonists and 
showed preference or in most cases significant selectivity for 
FFA2 over FFA3. These results indicate that the binding pocket 
of FFA2 has a narrow shape, and steric restrictions apply in the 
area around the ␣-carbon atoms of the SCFAs. The preferred 
planar structure around the carboxylic acid due to conjugation 
is likely to be a significant factor in FFA2 selectivity. These 
observations have led to the identification of a general rule to 
predict FFA2 versus FFA3 selectivity of small (Ͻ6 carbon 
atoms) carboxylic acids with lipophilic tails: compounds carry-
ing an sp 
2 -or sp-hybridized ␣-carbon will be FFA2-selective, 
whereas compounds carrying a substituted sp 
3 -hybridized 
␣-carbon will be FFA3-selective. The rule has proven highly 
predictive, and we have yet to observe any exceptions. </p>

<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>

<p>MARCH 25, 2011 • VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 10639 </p>

<p>In summary, the first series of molecular tools selectively 
activating FFA2 via the orthosteric binding site was provided, 
and many of these ligands showed close to optimal ligand effi-
ciencies. Hence, it is possible to achieve selective activation of 
FFA2 versus FFA3 with rather small ligands. Such ligands will 
undoubtedly be useful to further explore the mechanism of 
activation of FFA2 in more detail or its signaling characteristics 
in vitro even in cells coexpressing the related FFA3. Future 
studies are needed to unravel whether selectivity can be main-
tained within molecules that are gradually increased in size to 
also achieve a gain of potency that will be a prerequisite to 
explore the role of FFA2 in vivo. Nevertheless, our results pro-
vide, for the first time, a molecular explanation for selective 
orthosteric activation of FFA2 by highlighting previously 
unrecognized determinants of selectivity within the orthosteric 
binding site. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment-We thank Ulrike Rick for expert technical 
assistance. </p>



<p>Selective Orthosteric FFA2 Agonists </p>



<p>VOLUME 286 • NUMBER 12 • MARCH 25, 2011 </p>

</text></tei>