<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3982819" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis invokes 
a number of physiological changes that enhance adaptation 
of the individual in the face of acute stresses [26]. Prosta-
glandins (PGs) are bioactive lipids derived from arachidonic 
acid by the sequential actions of phospholipase A, cyclooxy-
genase (COX) and specific PG synthases [6]. COX exists 
as the isozymes COX-1, which is constitutively expressed, 
and COX-2, which is usually expressed at low basal levels 
and rapidly induced in response to various stimuli [13, 24]. 
COX [7, 9, 31] and microsomal prostaglandin E synthase-1 
(mPGES-1), a terminal PGE2 synthase [7, 8], are involved 
in the activation of the HPA axis. We have previously dem-
onstrated that selective COX-2 inhibitor NS398 attenuated 
the increase in serum corticosterone levels at 30 and 120 min 
after lipopolysaccharide (LPS) and restraint stress stimuli. 
On the other hand, this inhibitory effect of COX-2 inhibi-
tor was not discernible on the 2-deoxy-D-glucose (2DG)-
injected animals. These results suggest that activation of the 
HPA axis is at least partially dependent on COX-2-related 
signaling under infectious and restraint stresses, but less de-
pendent on it under hypoglycemic stress [15]. However, the 
mechanisms underlying a stress-specific relevance between 
COX-2-related signaling and activation of the HPA axis re-
main to be elucidated. </p>

<p>Y. MA, T. MATSUWAKI, K. YAMANOUCHI AND M. NISHIHARA </p>

<p>
namely infectious (LPS; Sigma, St. Louis, MO, U.S.A.; 100 
µg/kg BW, ip), hypoglycemic (2DG; Sigma; 400 mg/kg BW, 
ip) or restraint (1 hr) stresses were applied to rats. Animals 
were divided into 2 groups and given a selective COX-2 in-
hibitor (NS-398; Cayman Chemical, Ann Arbor, MI, U.S.A.; 
10 mg/kg BW, ip) or vehicle (DMSO; Sigma) 30 min before 
stress application. Just before stress application (0 min) and 
30 and 120 min after the start of stress application, animals 
were decapitated, and the whole brain was removed and 
fixed in cold 4% paraformaldehyde in phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS; 0.02 M, pH 7.2). 
Immunohistochemistry for c-Fos: Brains were further 
fixed for 48 hr at 4°C in the fixative paraformaldehyde 
solution and then submerged in 10% sucrose solution over-
night, 20% sucrose solution for 24 hr and 30% sucrose for 
48 hr until the brain completely sank. Brain sections of 30 
µm thickness were cut using a cryostat (Microm HM550, 
Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, U.S.A.) and collected 
serially in 24-well plates containing PBS (0.02 M, pH 7.2). 
One out of every eight slices was used for immunostaining 
for c-Fos protein. Free-floating sections were rinsed with 
PBS for 10 min three times. Sections were then incubated 
with 0.3% H 2 O 2 in PBS for 30 min at room temperature 
and rinsed with PBS for 10 min three times. Thereafter, sec-
tions were incubated in blocking solution (Block Ace, Snow 
Brand Milk Products Co., Sapporo, Japan) for 2 hr. Tissue 
sections were incubated in rabbit anti-Fos primary antibody 
(1:5,000 dilution with 0.02 M PBS containing 1% BSA and 
0.3% Triton X-100; Ab-5, Oncogene Research Product, Cal-
biochem, MA, U.S.A.) at 4°C for 60 hr, washed three times 
with 0.02 M PBS containing 0.03% Triton X-100 (0.03% 
PBST), and then, the sections were incubated with the 
biotinylated goat-anti-rabbit secondary antibody IgG (1:800 
dilution with 0.02 M PBS containing 0.3% Triton X-100; 
Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, U.S.A.) at room tem-
perature for 2 hr. Sections were then rinsed three times with 
0.03% PBST and incubated at room temperature for a further 
2 hr with an avidin-biotin-horseradish peroxidase complex 
solution (Vectastain ABC Kit, Vector Laboratories). Finally, 
sections were treated for approximately 1.5 min in 0.5 mg/ 
ml diaminobenzidine tetrahydrochloride (Sigma,; dissolved 
in 0.02 M PBS with 0.01% hydrogen peroxide and 0.25% 
nickel chloride). The sections were mounted on slides, air 
dried, dehydrated in ethanol solutions and xylene, and cov-
erslipped. 
Quantification of c-Fos immunoreactive cells: Brain 
regions were identified using the rat brain in stereotaxic 
coordinates [19]. The number of c-Fos-immunoreactive (IR) 
cells in the PVN and SON was counted using an Olympus 
Optical System (BX-51, Olympus Optical Co., Tokyo, Ja-
pan), and the digitized images were analyzed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">IPLab</rs> 
image analyzing software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Scanalytics Corp.</rs>., Fairfax, VA, 
U.S.A.). A threshold was set to delineate c-Fos-positive 
stained nuclei from background, and only cells above the 
threshold were included. Up to four sections per animal for 
each region were quantified bilaterally and then averaged. 
Statistical analyses: All statistical analyses were per-
formed in <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">11.5 Version</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, </p>

<p>U.S.A.). Data were analyzed with two-way analysis of vari-
ance (ANOVA), followed by Tukey's test. Differences at 
P&lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Induction of c-Fos expression in the brain under stress 
conditions: In order to determine the brain regions respond-
ing to acute stress stimuli, immunostaining for c-Fos protein 
in the forebrain was performed. Before the application of 
stresses (0 min), almost no c-Fos-immunoreactive (IR) cells 
were observed, while few scattered c-Fos-IR cells were seen 
in the paraventricular nucleus (PVN) and the supraoptic 
nucleus (SON). As shown in Figs. 1-3, stress stimuli in-
duced c-Fos immunoreactivity in many brain regions. After 
30 min of stress stimuli, there was a small increase in the 
number of c-Fos-IR cells in the PVN, SON, ventromedial 
hypothalamic nucleus (VMH) and piriform cortex (Pir) in 
the LPS and restraint stress models, while an increase in c-
Fos-IR cell number was found in the PVN, SON and lateral 
hypothalamic area (LHA) in the 2DG stress model. Strong 
increases in c-Fos-IR cells were observed in the PVN and 
SON at 120 min after the application of all the three differ-
ent acute stresses. Considerable increases in c-Fos-IR cell 
number were also seen in other brain regions, including the 
central amygdaloid nucleus, medial amygdaloid nucleus, 
arcuate nucleus, dentate gyrus and Pir. In addition, LPS and 
restraint stresses increased c-Fos-IR cells in the VMH, while 
2DG injection increased those in the LHA at 120 min as well 
as 30 min. These results suggest that the two hypothalamic 
regions, the PVN and SON, have similar expression patterns 
of neuronal activation in response to all three different acute 
stresses applied in this study and that the VMH is sensitive 
to LPS and restraint stresses, while the LHA is sensitive to 
hypoglycemic stress. 
Effects of COX-2 inhibitor on the expression of c-Fos in 
the PVN and SON: To investigate the involvement of COX-
2-related signaling in activation of the HPA axis responding 
to the acute stress stimuli, we evaluated the effect of COX-2 
selective inhibitor NS-398 on the number of c-Fos-IR cells in 
the PVN and SON under the three different acute stress con-
ditions. c-Fos expression in the PVN is shown in Figs. 4-6, 
and that in the SON is illustrated in Figs. 7-9. Quantitative 
analysis showed that the interaction of time and treatment 
significantly affected the number of c-Fos-IR cells in both the 
PVN [LPS, (F(2,24)=8.606, P&lt;0.01); 2DG, (F(2,24)=9.865, 
P&lt;0.001); restraint, (F(2,24)=6.938, P&lt;0.01)] and SON 
[LPS, (F(2,24)=94.371, P&lt;0.001; restraint, F(2,24)=6.522, 
P&lt;0.01)], except for 2DG (F(2,24)=0.231, P&gt;0.05). In the 
PVN of vehicle-injected animals, the numbers of c-Fos-IR 
cells at 120 min after stress stimuli were significantly larger 
than those of other 2 time points under all three acute stress 
conditions. There was no significant difference between 
the numbers of c-Fos-IR cells in the PVN in vehicle-and 
NS-398-treated rats at any time points under three different 
stress conditions. These results suggest that all three acute 
stress conditions induce the neuronal activation in the PVN 
and COX-2-related signaling does not affect the total num-</p>

<p>COX-2-RELATED NEURAL ACTIVITY UNDER STRESSES </p>



<p>ber of neurons activated in this nucleus. 
On the other hand, the number of c-Fos-IR cells in the 
SON of vehicle-injected animals was significantly larger at 
30 min compared with that at 0 min only in 2DG-injected 
animals, but not in LPS-injected or restraint-stressed ones. 
The number of c-Fos-IR cells in the SON at 120 min was 
significantly larger than those of other 2 time points under 
all three acute stress conditions. Treatment with NS-398 
significantly increased the number of c-Fos-IR cells at 30 </p>

<p>min, but not at 0 and 120 min, under both LPS and restraint 
stresses, while the effect of NS-398 was not discernible 
under 2DG stress at any time points. These results suggest 
that all the three different acute stresses induce the neuronal 
activation of the SON, on which COX-2-related signaling 
has a negative effect at least at 30 min under infectious and 
restraint stress conditions, but not under hypoglycemic stress 
condition. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Immunohistochemical staining for c-Fos protein in the brain 0, 30 and 120 min after LPS injection (100 
µg/kg BW, ip). Representative photomicrographs of c-Fos-immunoreactive cells in the paraventricular nucleus 
(PVN, A-C), supraoptic nucleus (SON, D-F), central amygdaloid nucleus (CeAD, G-I), medial amygdaloid 
nucleus (MeAD, J-L), ventromedial hypothalamic nucleus (VMH, M-O), arcuate nucleus (Arc, P-R), dentate 
gyrus (DG, S-U) and piriform cortex (Pir, V-X). Scale bars: 100 µm. </p>

<p>Y. MA, T. MATSUWAKI, K. YAMANOUCHI AND M. NISHIHARA </p>

<p>
DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The present study showed that all the three acute stresses 
applied, namely infectious, hypoglycemic and restraint 
stresses, induced neuronal activation in some restricted pop-
ulations of neurons in the brain, especially in the PVN and 
SON. In addition, activation of the SON was significantly 
enhanced by COX-2 inhibitor under the infectious and 
restraint stress conditions, but not under the hypoglycemic </p>

<p>stress condition. These results appear to have some relation-
ship with the data of our previous study, which suggests that 
activation of the HPA axis is dependent on COX-2-related 
signaling under infectious and restraint stresses, but less 
dependent on it under hypoglycemic stress [15]. 
In the parvocellular region of the PVN, there is a popula-
tion of neuropeptide-secretory neurons synthesizing cortico-
trophin-releasing hormone (CRH) or both CRH and arginine 
vasopressin (AVP) [3, 27], while AVP and oxytocin (OXT) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Immunohistochemical staining for c-Fos protein in the brain 0, 30 and 120 min after 2DG injection (400 
mg/kg BW, ip). Representative photomicrographs of c-Fos-immunoreactive cells in the paraventricular nucleus 
(PVN, A-C), supraoptic nucleus (SON, D-F), central amygdaloid nucleus (CeAD, G-I), medial amygdaloid 
nucleus (MeAD, J-L), lateral hypothalamic area (LHA, M-O), arcuate nucleus (Arc, P-R), dentate gyrus (DG, 
S-U) and piriform cortex (Pir, V-X). Scale bars: 100 µm. </p>

<p>COX-2-RELATED NEURAL ACTIVITY UNDER STRESSES </p>



<p>neurons are mainly located in the magnocellular regions of 
the PVN and SON [11, 12]. A previous research showed that 
acute stresses increased c-Fos-IR cells, which were mainly 
colocalized with CRH-IR perikarya in the PVN [20]. In ad-
dition, c-Fos-IR nuclei were also increased in both AVP-and 
OXT-containing neurons of the PVN and SON after acute 
stresses [16, 20, 32]. The present study demonstrated that 
many regions of the brain respond to acute stresses and es-
pecially, the PVN and SON have similar expression patterns </p>

<p>of neuronal activation in response to three different acute 
stresses, which are consistent with these previous reports. 
It is well known that CRH and AVP play a key role in 
mediating activation of the HPA axis [18, 21], while some 
researches suggested that intracerebroventricular infusion of 
OXT suppresses stress-induced activation of the HPA axis 
[28, 29]. In the present study, there was no significant dif-
ference between the number of c-Fos-IR cells in the PVN 
between vehicle-injected and NS-398-treated animals at any </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Immunohistochemical staining for c-Fos protein in the brain 0, 30 and 120 min after restraint stress (1 
hr). Representative photomicrographs of c-Fos-immunoreactive (c-Fos-IR) cells in the paraventricular nucleus 
(PVN, A-C), supraoptic nucleus (SON, D-F), central amygdaloid nucleus (CeAD, G-I), medial amygdaloid 
nucleus (MeAD, J-L), ventromedial hypothalamic nucleus (VMH, M-O), arcuate nucleus (Arc, P-R), dentate 
gyrus (DG, S-U) and piriform cortex (Pir, V-X). Scale bars: 100 µm. </p>

<p>Y. MA, T. MATSUWAKI, K. YAMANOUCHI AND M. NISHIHARA </p>

<p>
time points under three different acute stress conditions, 
suggesting that COX-2-related signaling is not directly 
involved in stress responses in the PVN. This is consistent 
with a previous report showing that COX-2-or mPGES-
1-deficient mice did not show any attenuation of the c-Fos 
expression in the PVN after LPS administration [7], though 
the other research group reported that LPS strongly reduced 
the number of c-Fos positive nuclei in the PVN in mPGES-
1-deficient mice [4]. As to the SON, on the other hand, the 
numbers of c-Fos-IR cells in NS-398-treated animals were 
significantly higher than those in vehicle-injected animals at </p>

<p>30 min under LPS and restraint stresses, but not under 2DG 
stress condition. Lacroix et al. [14] reported that injection 
of PGE2 induced c-Fos expression in the PVN and SON. 
In the parvocellular division of the PVN, c-Fos was mainly 
expressed in CRH-and OXT-IR neurons and very rarely 
expressed in AVP-IR neurons, while in the magnocellular 
part of the PVN and SON, c-Fos was mainly colocalized 
in OXT-IR neurons and some expression was also detected 
in AVP-IR neurons. It is therefore likely that, in the pres-
ent study, c-Fos-IR neurons in the PVN are mainly CRH 
and OXT neurons, and those in the SON are mainly OXT 
neurons. Taken together, it is suggested that, in the SON, </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effect of COX-2 selective inhibitor NS-398 on the ex-
pression of c-Fos protein in the paraventricular nucleus (PVN) 
after LPS injection. Vehicle (A-C) or COX-2 selective inhibi-
tor NS-398 (10 mg/kg BW, ip, D-F) was injected to male rats 
30 min before applying LPS (100 µg/kg BW, ip). Scale bars: 
100 µm. Quantification of the number of c-Fos-IR cells in the 
PVN of vehicle-treated (closed column) or NS-398-treated 
(open column) rats after an injection of LPS (G). Each column 
with a vertical bar represents the mean ± SEM (n=5). Values 
with different letters are significantly different (P&lt;0.05, two-
way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test). </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Effect of COX-2 selective inhibitor NS-398 on the ex-
pression of c-Fos protein in the paraventricular nucleus (PVN) 
after 2DG injection. Vehicle (A-C) or COX-2 selective inhibi-
tor NS-398 (10 mg/kg BW, ip, D-F) was injected to male rats 
30 min before applying 2DG (400 mg/kg BW, ip). Scale bars: 
100 µm. Quantification of the number of c-Fos-IR cells in the 
PVN of vehicle-treated (closed column) or NS-398-treated 
(open column) rats after an injection of 2DG (G). Each column 
with a vertical bar represents the mean ± SEM (n=5). Values 
with different letters are significantly different (P&lt;0.05, two-
way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test). </p>

<p>COX-2-RELATED NEURAL ACTIVITY UNDER STRESSES </p>



<p>NS-398 increased the number of OXT neurons expressing c-
Fos and thereby decreased serum corticosterone levels under 
infectious and restraint stress conditions as observed in our 
previous study [15]. This may at least partially account for 
the differences in COX-2-dependency of the activation of 
the HPA axis among stresses. 
Interestingly, in the present study, infectious and restraint 
stresses increased c-Fos expression levels in the VMH, while 
hypoglycemic stress increased those in the LHA, which are 
consistent with previous researches reported separately [1, 
2, 10, 22]. Bilateral electrolytic lesions of the VMH or LHA </p>

<p>were reported to inhibit corticosteroid feedback or extin-
guish the role of serotonin (5-HT) on activity in the HPA axis 
[25]. In addition, involvement of the VMH and LHA in the 
regulation of energy metabolism has been well documented 
[30]. The VMH and the LHA have been regarded as the 
'satiety center' and 'hunger center', respectively [23]. Infec-
tious stress is known to induce anorexic symptoms, in which 
condition the satiety center should be activated, while 2DG 
as an inhibitor of glucose uptake would stimulate the hunger 
center. Taken together, these results suggest that infectious 
and restraint stresses or hypoglycemic stress differently acti-</p>

<p>Fig. 6. Effect of COX-2 selective inhibitor NS-398 on the 
expression of c-Fos protein in the paraventricular nucleus 
(PVN) after restraint stress. Vehicle (A-C) or COX-2 selec-
tive inhibitor NS-398 (10 mg/kg BW, ip, D-F) was injected 
to male intact rats 30 min before applying restraint (1 hr) 
stress. Scale bars: 100 µm. Quantification of the number of 
c-Fos-IR cells in the PVN of vehicle-treated (closed column) 
or NS-398-treated (open column) rats after restraint stress. 
Each column with a vertical bar represents the mean ± SEM 
(n=5). Values with different letters are significantly different 
(P&lt;0.05, two-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test). </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Effect of COX-2 selective inhibitor NS-398 on the 
expression of c-Fos protein in the supraoptic nucleus (SON) 
after LPS injection. Vehicle (A-C) or COX-2 selective in-
hibitor NS-398 (10 mg/kg BW, ip, D-F) was injected to male 
intact rats 30 min before applying LPS (100 µg/kg BW, ip). 
Scale bars: 100 µm. Quantification of the number of c-Fos-IR 
cells in the SON of vehicle-treated (closed column) or NS-
398-treated (open column) rats after an injection of LPS (G). 
Each column with a vertical bar represents the mean ± SEM 
(n=5). Values with different letters are significantly different 
(P&lt;0.05, two-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's test). </p>

<p>Y. MA, T. MATSUWAKI, K. YAMANOUCHI AND M. NISHIHARA </p>

<p>
vates neurons in the VMH or LHA mediating the regulation 
of not only the HPA axis activity but also food intake. 
In conclusion, the present study demonstrated that many 
regions of the brain, especially the PVN and SON, respond 
to acute stresses and work as common mediators that gen-
erate potent autonomic and neuroendocrine responses. In 
addition, it is also suggested that COX-2-related signaling 
decreases neuronal activity in the SON under infectious 
and restraint, but not hypoglycemic, stresses, which may be 
involved in the suppression of the HPA axis. This difference 
in the role of COX-2-related signaling in inhibiting SON </p>

<p>neurons among stresses may at least partially account for the 
difference in the role of COX-2-related signaling in activat-
ing the HPA axis among stresses observed in our previous 
study [15]. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENT. This work was supported in part by 
JSPS KAKENHI Grant Number 23228004 and 22780260. </p>



<p>COX-2-RELATED NEURAL ACTIVITY UNDER STRESSES </p>





</text></tei>