<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3256755" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The t(10;11)(p13;q14) translocation results in the fusion of the 
CALM (clathrin assembly lymphoid myeloid leukemia protein) 
and AF10 genes. This translocation is observed in acute 
myeloblastic leukemia (AML M6), acute lymphoblastic leukemia 
(ALL) and malignant lymphoma. Using a yeast two-hybrid 
screen, the four and a half LIM domain protein 2 (FHL2) was 
identified as a CALM interacting protein. Recently, high 
expression of FHL2 in breast, gastric, colon, lung as well as 
in prostate cancer was shown to be associated with an adverse 
prognosis. The interaction between CALM and FHL2 was 
confirmed by glutathione S-transferase-pulldown assay and 
co-immunoprecipitation experiments. The FHL2 interaction 
domain of CALM was mapped to amino acids 294-335 of 
CALM. The transcriptional activation capacity of FHL2 was 
reduced by CALM, but not by CALM/AF10, which suggests that 
regulation of FHL2 by CALM might be disturbed in CALM/AF10-
positive leukemia. Extremely high expression of FHL2 was seen 
in acute erythroid leukemia (AML M6). FHL2 was also highly 
expressed in chronic myeloid leukemia and in AML with 
complex aberrant karyotype. These results suggest that FHL2 
may play an important role in leukemogenesis, especially in the 
case of AML M6. 
Chromosomal translocations play a crucial role in the develop-
ment of many types of leukemia, lymphomas, sarcomas and 
solid tumors. 
1 In translocations, normal gene function can be 
altered in two different ways: either by the formation of fusion 
genes or by transcriptional deregulation of genes adjacent to the 
breakpoints. 
2 The t(10;11)(p12;q14) translocation results in the 
fusion of CALM (clathrin assembly lymphoid myeloid leukemia 
protein) on chromosome 11 band q14 with AF10 (MLLT10) on 
chromosome 10 band p12. 
3 The CALM/AF10 fusion is observed 
in acute myeloid leukemia (AML), acute lymphoblastic leuke-
mia (ALL) and malignant lymphoma, and has a poor prognosis </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>(Figure 1a). 
The AF10 gene was first identified as the fusion partner of MLL 
in AML patients carrying a t(10;11)(p12;q23) translocation. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>AF10 codes for a 1027-amino-acid-long putative zinc-finger 
transcription factor. The Drosophila homolog of AF10, alhambra, </p>

<p>has been suggested to play a role in heterochromatin-mediated 
transcriptional silencing. 
7 We could recently show that AF10 
interacts with Ikaros, an important regulator of lymphoid 
development, and that CALM/AF10 influences the subcellular 
localization of Ikaros. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>The CALM gene is located on chromosomes 11 band q14 and 
encodes a 652-amino-acid-long protein. CALM is ubiquitously 
expressed and homologous to the neuron-specific clathrin 
assembly protein AP180. 
9 CALM is mainly located in the 
cytoplasm and along the membrane in clathrin-coated pits. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>CALM does also shuttle between the cytoplasm and the nucleus, 
permitting CALM and the nucleolar protein CATS to interact. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>CALM promotes the assembly of clathrin into clathrin cages 
and takes part in the initial stage of clathrin-coated pit formation 
and invagination together with clathrin, AP-2 and PtdIns(4,5) 
P 2 . 
9,11-13 Both overexpression and downregulation of CALM 
have been shown to inhibit clathrin-mediated endocytosis and 
impair the trafficking of receptors between the trans-Golgi 
network and endosomes. 
9,12 Interestingly, point mutations in the 
mouse CALM homolog Picalm were shown to cause abnorm-
alities in hematopoiesis, iron metabolism and bone growth. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>The CALM/AF10 fusion protein has been shown to be strongly 
leukemogenic. It causes an aggressive acute leukemia in a 
murine bone marrow transplantation model 
15 and leads to the 
development of acute leukemia in a transgenic mouse model 
after a median latency of about 12 months. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>To study the function of CALM and the CALM/AF10 protein, 
we searched for protein interaction partners of CALM using a 
yeast two-hybrid (Y2H) approach. The four and a half LIM 
domain protein 2 (FHL2) was identified as one of several CALM 
interacting partners. FHL2 has been shown to be involved in 
several important cellular processes like transcriptional regula-
tion, DNA replication and signal-transduction pathways. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>FHL2 plays an important role in Wnt signaling. 
18,19 Recently, 
high expression of FHL2 has been associated with adverse 
prognosis in breast and prostate cancer, 
20-22 and high expres-
sion of FHL2 is found in ovarian and gastrointestinal cancer. </p>

<p>23,24 </p>

<p>In this study, we show that FHL2 interacts with CALM and that it 
is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia (AML M6), 
suggesting an important role for FHL2 in leukemogenesis, 
especially in the development of erythroleukemia. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plasmid construction </p>

<p>The bait plasmids for the Y2H screen were constructed by 
inserting the full-length CALM cDNA, as well as the CALM 
deletion mutants in frame into pGBKT7 vector (Clontech, 
Heidelberg, Germany), to be expressed as GAL4-DBD fusion 
proteins. The following fragments of CALM were cloned in </p>

<p>Received 13 July 2011; accepted 12 August 2011 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Professor SK Bohlander, Department of Medicine III, 
University of Munich Hospital Grosshadern, University of Munich, 
Marchioninistr. 15, Klinikum Grosshadern, Bavaria, Munich 81377, 
Germany. 
E-mail: bohlander@helmholtz-muenchen.de </p>

<p>Citation: Blood Cancer Journal (2011) 1, e42; doi:10.1038/bcj.2011.40 
&amp; 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 2044-5385/11 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/bcj </p>

<p>frame with the GAL4-DBD (aa 1-147) into the yeast expression 
vector pGBKT7: (1) CALM (1-408); (2) CALM (1-294); (3) CALM 
(1-335); (4) CALM (1-221); and (5) CALM (1-105). For mapping 
the CALM interaction domain of FHL2, the following FHL2 
fragments were cloned in frame into the pGBKT7 vector: (1) LIM 
domains </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 -3; (2) LIM domains </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 -2; (3) LIM domains </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 -1; and (4) 
LIM domain </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 , all PCR amplified using the following forward 
primer: 5 
0 -ATTACCATGGATGGCTGGCATTTTGACTTTGGG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>and the following backward primers: LIM </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 (5 
0 -CGGGATCCCTG </p>

<p>ACGAACAGGGTCTCAAAGCACAC-3 
0 ), LIM </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 -1 (5 
0 -CGGGAT </p>

<p>CCCGCATTCCTGGCACTTGGATGAG-3 
0 ), LIM </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 -2 (5 
0 -CGGGA </p>

<p>TCCCTGACGCACT-GCATGGCATGTTG-3 
0 ) and LIM </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 -3 (5 
0 -CG 
GGATCCCTGACCCAGCACACTTCTTGG-CATAC-3 
0 ). 
For the GST-pulldown assay, the GST-Flirt 1 (full-length FHL2) 
construct was used (a gift from Dr Judith Mü ller, Freiburg, 
Germany). The FLAG-FHL2 construct for co-immunoprecipita-
tion was provided by Dr Paul Riley (London, UK). Dr Judith 
Mü ller (Freiburg) provided the GAL4-DBD-FHL2 construct for 
the luciferase assay. The pGAL4-DBD-CALM/AF10 plasmid was 
constructed by inserting the full-length CALM/AF10 open 
reading frame, fused to GAL4-DBD (aa 1-47), into pcDNA3. 
Plasmids expressing YFP-FHL2 fusion protein was constructed in 
the pEYFP-C1 vector (Clontech). </p>

<p>Y2H screen </p>

<p>A co-transformation of the yeast strain AH109 (Clontech), using 
the lithium-acetate procedure, was performed with the pGBKT7-
CALM (1-408) bait plasmid and a thymus library cloned into 
pACT2 (Clontech). The resulting colonies were plated on 
selective plates lacking histidine, adenine, leucine and trypto-
phan, and colonies exhibiting a positive b-galactosidase 
reaction were selected for further analysis. </p>

<p>Mapping of interacting domains </p>

<p>The interaction domain mapping was performed by co-
transformation of the CALM deletion mutants and pACT-FHL2 </p>

<p>prey plasmid into yeast strain AH109. Growth was assayed on 
selective plates lacking tryptophan and leucine (-W, -L: 
transformation control) and interaction was scored on plates 
lacking histidine, adenine, leucine and tryptophan (-H, -A, -L, 
-W: interaction assay). </p>

<p>Transfection of mammalian cells and preparation of 
cytoplasmic extracts </p>

<p>A total of 1 Â 10 
6 HEK293T cells grown in 100 mm Petri dishes 
were transiently transfected with 8 mg of plasmid DNA and 12 mg 
polyethyleneimine (Sigma-Aldrich, Steinheim, Germany). After 
24 h, the cells were harvested and nuclear extract was prepared 
using 400 ml hypotonic buffer (10 mM HEPES (pH 7.5), 1.5 mm 
MgCl 2 , 10 mM NaCl, 0.5 mM dithiothreitol, 4 ml protease inhi-
bitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich)) as lysis buffer for cytoplasmic 
extracts. Cytoplasmic extracts were then used freshly for 
immunoprecipitation experiments. </p>

<p>GST-pulldown </p>

<p>The GST-Flirt 1 (full-length FHL2) was expressed in the Esche-
richia coli strain XL1 blue (Agilent Technologies, Bö blingen, 
Germany) and purified from bacterial proteins by incubation 
with glutathione Sepharose 4B beads (GE Healthcare Bio-
Sciences, Munich, Germany). The CALM protein was obtained 
from the in vitro TNT translation (Promega, Mannheim, 
Germany) of the pGBKT7-CALM (aa 1-408) in the presence 
of </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S-methionine. A measure of 20 ml of the </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S-labeled 
CALM lysate was incubated with 10 ml of Sepharose-bound 
GST fusion protein or Sepharose-bound GST as control in 
100 ml binding buffer (100 mM NaCl, 25 mM Tris (pH 7.5), 0.1% 
NP-40). After incubation, the beads were washed five times 
with the binding buffer and subsequently boiled and separated 
on a 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electro-
phoresis (SDS-PAGE) gel. The CALM protein was then detected 
by autoradiography. </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>A measure of 200 ml of freshly prepared cytoplasmic extract 
from HEK293T cells, co-transfected with pcDNA-FLAG-FHL2 
and YFP-CALM, was used for the immunoprecipitation experi-
ment. The cytoplasmic extract was incubated in 200 ml protein 
binding buffer (Dulbecco's phosphate-buffered saline (DPBS), 
0.1% NP-40) together with 15 ml GFP-binder beads. The reaction 
was incubated for 30 min at 4 1C on a rotating platform, 
whereafter the beads were washed extensively with the binding 
buffer. The beads were then resuspended in SDS sample buffer, 
boiled and separated on a 12% SDS-PAGE gel. Subsequent 
western blot analysis was carried out with a monoclonal rabbit 
anti-GFP antibody (Life Technologies, Darmstadt, Germany), to 
detect the precipitated YFP-CALM and YFP, and the monoclonal 
mouse anti-FLAG M2 antibody (Sigma-Aldrich) to detect the 
co-immunoprecipitated FHL2. </p>

<p>Immunoblotting analysis </p>

<p>Immunocomplexes and cellular lysates were electrophoresed on 
10-12% SDS-PAGE gel and transferred to PVDF membrane 
(Hybond P; GE Healthcare). The membranes were blocked for 
1 h with 5% non-fat dried milk at room temperature and probed 
with the described primary antibodies, followed by secondary 
antibodies conjugated to horseradish peroxidase. Proteins were 
detected with an enhanced chemiluminescence reagent (ECL; 
GE Healthcare). </p>

<p>Figure 1 (a) Structure of AF10, AF10/CALM, CALM/AF10 and CALM. 
BP: breakpoint; PHD: plant homeo domain; ePHD: extended plant 
homeo domain; OM/LZ: octapeptide/leucine zipper; ANTH: AP180 
N-terminal homology domain; CID: CATS interaction domain. The BP 
in AF10 and CALM is indicated by arrows. (b) Structure of the FHL2 
protein. FHL2 is composed of four and a half LIM domains. </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>Immunostaining and confocal laser scanning 
fluorescence microscopy </p>

<p>For localization studies, U2OS (bone sarcoma) cells were grown 
on coverslips and co-transfected with FLAG-FHL2 and YFP-
CALM or FLAG-CALM/A10 and YFP-FHL2. After 24 h, the cells 
were fixed for 10 min with PBS 2% paraformaldehyde, and then 
permeabilized with PBS 0.1% Triton X-100 for 10 min and 
blocked with PBS 10% fetal calf serum for 1 h. Coverslips were 
incubated with monoclonal mouse anti-FLAG M2 antibody 
(Sigma-Aldrich). After extensive washing with PBS 0.1% Tween, 
the coverslips were incubated with secondary Cy3-conjugated 
antibody for 1 h in room temperature. After further washing, step 
cells were stained with 4 
0 ,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole for 2 min 
and then mounted with Cytomation medium (Dako, Hamburg, 
Germany). The preparations were analyzed with a confocal 
fluorescence laser scanning system (TCS-SP2 scanning system 
and DM IRB inverted microscope; Leica, Solms, Germany). </p>

<p>Reporter gene assays </p>

<p>A total of 5 Â 10 
4 HEK293T cells were seeded in 24-well plates 
and co-transfected with 100 ng GAL4 SV40 minimal promoter 
reporter plasmid, 
10 20 ng of p-RL co-reporter vector (Promega), 
200 ng of GAL4-DBD-FHL2-or GAL4-DBD-only expression 
plasmids, 100-400 ng of YFP-CALM and YFP-CALM/AF10, 
respectively, and as a control the pEYFP-C1 (Clontech) only. 
For the CALM/AF10 experiment, the cells were co-transfected 
with 100 ng GAL4 SV40 minimal promoter reporter plasmid, 
20 ng of p-RL co-reporter vector (Promega), 100 ng GAL4-DBD-
CALM/AF10 or GAL4-DBD empty expression plasmid, 100 ng 
pcDNA-FLAG-FHL2 and empty pcDNA vector. The cells were 
harvested after 24 h and assayed for firefly and Renilla luciferase 
activities using the Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System 
(Promega). The Renilla luciferase activity measurements were 
used for normalization. Experiments were carried out four times 
and the samples were measured three times. </p>

<p>Expression analysis of FHL2 in leukemic samples </p>

<p>For the first set of expression analysis, patient bone marrow 
samples were hybridized to Affymetrix HG-U133A and HG-
U133B chips as described previously. 
25 The HG-U133A, HG-
U133B and HG-U133plus2 CEL files were first normalized 
separately using robust multi-array normalization and then 
combined into one matrix and normalized altogether using an 
empirical Bayes method as described previously. 
26 The normal-
ized expression data were analyzed with the <rs type="software">R software 
package</rs>. 
27 The expression signal intensities are given on a 
logarithmic scale 
For the second analysis, 308 expression profiles from AML 
leukemia patients were analyzed on Affymetrix HG-U133A, 
HG-U133B and HG-U133plus2 chips. The data were depicted 
as boxplot. The Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney test was used to 
calculate the statistical significance. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>qPCR was used to determine the mRNA expression levels of 
FHL2 in patients with AML M6, normal and complex 
karyotypes. The endogenous control RPL10A was selected from 
the microarray data. Individual qPCR reactions were set up in 
triplicates in 96-well plates and were carried out in 10 ml 
reactions with TaqMan Gene Expression Assay according to the 
manufacturer's protocol (Life Technologies). In all, 100 ng of 
patient cDNA was used for each reaction. The plates were run </p>

<p>and analyzed on an ABI PRISM 7900HT Sequence Detection 
System (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">SDS 2.1</rs>; Applied Biosystems) according to the 
manufacturer's protocol (Applied Biosystems). The 2 </p>

<p>ÀDDCT </p>

<p>relative quantification method was used to analyze the qPCR 
experiment. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Identification of FHL2 as a CALM interacting protein </p>

<p>To identify interaction partners of the CALM protein, the 
N-terminal 408 amino acids of CALM were used as a bait to 
perform a Y2H screen of a human thymus cDNA library. The 
N-terminal 408 amino acids of CALM are contained within the 
CALM/AF10 fusion protein and do not show any transcriptional 
activation properties in yeast. 
10 Under high stringency screening 
conditions of 1 Â 10 
6 primary transformants, six clones were 
identified that grew in the absence of histidine and adenine and 
were b-galactosidase positive. These six clones encoded five 
different proteins. One of these clones contained the complete 
open reading frame of FHL2 (Figure 1b). FHL2 encodes for a 
279-amino-acid-long protein with four and a half LIM (Lin11, 
Isl-1, Mec-3) domains, reported to be overexpressed in several 
different cancer types. </p>

<p>CALM interacts with FHL2 in vitro </p>

<p>To confirm the interaction between CALM and FHL2 in vitro, a 
glutathione S-transferase (GST)-pulldown assay was performed. 
FHL2 was expressed as a GST fusion protein in bacteria and 
immobilized on glutathione beads. The beads were then incu-
bated with 
35 S-methionine-labeled CALM protein (aa 1-408). 
FHL2, but not GST alone, retained the radiolabeled CALM 
protein (Figure 2a). These results indicate a direct physical 
interaction between CALM and FHL2. </p>

<p>CALM interacts with FHL2 in vivo </p>

<p>The in vivo interaction between CALM and FHL2 was confirmed 
by co-immunoprecipitation experiments. After transient trans-
fection of FLAG-FHL2-and YFP-CALM-expressing plasmids in 
HEK293T cells, and immunoprecipitation of YFP-CALM using 
GFP-binder beads, 
29 the co-precipitated FHL2 protein could be 
detected with anti-FLAG antibodies (Figure 2b). We were also 
able to co-precipitate small amounts of overexpressed FHL2 by 
immunoprecipitation of endogenous CALM in HEK293T cells 
(Supplementary Figure S1). </p>

<p>Mapping of the FHL2 interacting domains of CALM </p>

<p>To map the minimal FHL2 interaction domain of CALM, yeast 
cells were co-transformed with several CALM deletion mutants 
fused to the GAL4-DNA-binding domain (DBD) and the FHL2 
prey clone (Figure 3a). Only transformants with CALM mutants 
containing amino acids 294-335 grew on selective plates 
indicating protein-protein interaction (Figure 3b). These results 
show that amino acids 294-335 of CALM are required for its 
interaction with FHL2. </p>

<p>Mapping of the CALM interacting domains of FHL2 </p>

<p>To map the minimal CALM interaction domain of FHL2, yeast 
cells were co-transformed with several FHL2 deletion mutants 
fused to GAL4-DBD and with a CALM prey clone, obtained in 
the Y2H screening using the CALM bait (Figure 3c). Only 
transformants with full-length FHL2 grew on selective plates </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>indicating protein-protein interaction (Figure 3c). These results 
show that amino acids 206-279 of FHL2 are required for its 
interaction with CALM. </p>

<p>CALM/AF10 alters the subcellular localization of FHL2 </p>

<p>To learn more about the interaction between CALM and FHL2, 
colocalization experiments were performed. YFP-CALM, YFP-
CALM/AF10 and YFP-FHL2 were transiently expressed in the 
osteosarcoma cell line U2OS (Figures 4a-i). YFP-CALM is 
localized mainly in the cytoplasm (Figures 4a and b), as is YFP-
CALM/AF10 (Figures 4d and e). In contrast to YFP-CALM, the 
CALM/AF10 protein is enriched in speckles in the cytoplasm 
(Figure 4e). These cytoplasmic speckles might be CALM/AF10 
protein inclusions in clathrin-coated pits due to disturbed 
endocytosis or because of an altered solubility of the CALM/ 
AF10 protein. YFP-FHL2 is expressed in both the cytoplasm and 
the nucleus (Figures 4g and h). When FLAG-FHL2 was co-
expressed with YFP-CALM, the distribution of YFP-CALM 
changed with more YFP-CALM found in the nucleus (compare 
Figures 4b and k). However, the distribution of FHL2 did not 
change noticeably upon co-expression of YFP-CALM (compare 
Figures 4h and l). There was also colocalization of YFP-CALM 
and FLAG-FHL2 in the nucleus and especially in the cytoplasm 
(Figures 4j-m), as it can be visualized in line scan images in </p>

<p>Figure 5a. When FLAG-FHL2 was co-expressed with YFP-
CALM/AF10 (Figures 4n-q), the subcellular localization of YFP-
CALM/AF10 did not change markedly (compare Figures 4e and 
o), but there were pronounced changes in the cytoplasmic 
localization of FLAG-FHL2 (compare Figures 4h and p), which 
colocalized with YFP-CALM/AF10 in distinct cytoplasmic 
speckles (Figures 4n-q). The colocalization of FLAG-FHL2 and 
YFP-CALM/AF10 was also clearly visible in the line scans of the 
confocal images (Figure 5b). The same pattern of colocalization 
of CALM/AF10 and FHL2 was also observed when a FLAG-
tagged CALM/AF10 and YFP-FHL2 fusion protein were co-
expressed (Figures 4r-u and 5c). </p>

<p>CALM reduces the transcriptional activation of FHL2 </p>

<p>Since FHL2 is known to act as an activator of transcription in 
reporter gene assays when fused to a GAL4-DBD (GAL4-DBD-
FHL2), 
30 we tested the influence of CALM and CALM/AF10 on 
FHL2-mediated transcriptional activation using a GAL4-UAS 
minimal SV40 promoter luciferase reporter construct (GAL4luc) 
in transiently transfected HEK293T cells. Expression of GAL4-
DBD-FHL2 resulted in a 40-fold activation of the reporter gene. 
Co-expression of YFP-CALM and GAL4-DBD-FHL2 reduced the 
FHL2-mediated activation from approximately 40-to 20-fold 
(Figure 6a). However, co-expression of YFP-CALM/AF10 had no 
effect on FHL2-mediated activation (Figure 6b). One explana-
tion for this result could be the fact that the AF10 portion of 
CALM/AF10 contains an activating domain (see Figure 6c) that 
over-rides the repressive effects seen with YFP-CALM. Interest-
ingly, when CALM/AF10 was expressed as a GAL4-DBD fusion 
(GAL4-DBD-CALM/AF10), a strong transcriptional activation of 
about 50-fold over background of the reporter gene was seen 
(Figure 6c). Co-expression of FLAG-FHL2 led to a threefold 
reduction of the CALM/AF10-mediated activation (Figure 6c). </p>

<p>FHL2 is highly expressed in AML M6 and is a marker for 
erythroleukemia </p>

<p>To obtain an overview of FHL2 expression levels in leukemia 
cells, we analyzed the expression of FHL2 in bone marrow 
samples from 129 leukemia patients and 10 normal bone 
marrows using Affymetrix expression chips. High expression of 
FHL2 was observed in AML samples with complex aberrant 
karyotypes and in chronic myeloid leukemia (CML) patient 
samples. The expression levels of FHL2 were relatively low in all 
the other subgroups examined, including CALM/AF10-positive 
leukemias (Figure 7). The higher expression levels of FHL2 in 
CML patients and AML patients with complex aberrant 
karyotypes did not reach statistical significance at the 0.05 
level, but suggested a trend, which was then examined in a 
larger group of AML patients. 
The second analysis was performed with a total of 308 
leukemia patient samples using Affymetrix expression chips that 
were divided into three groups. Group 1 consisted of 167 AML 
patients with normal karyotypes and excluding any samples 
with erythroleukemia (AML-M6). Group 2 was composed of 115 
AML patients with complex aberrant karyotypes, which 
included 46 patients with monosomy 5 or 5q deletions 
(subgroup 'À5/5qÀ'), seven patients with monosomy 7 or 7q 
deletions (subgroup 'À7/7qÀ'), 47 patients with aberrations of 
both chromosomes 5 and 7 (subgroup '5 þ 7') and 15 patients 
with no aberration of either chromosome 5 or 7 (subgroup 
'neither'). Group 3 contained 26 patients with AML M6. This 
second analysis clearly showed that FHL2 is significantly higher 
expressed in AML M6 patients than in patients with normal </p>

<p>Figure 2 (a) GST-pulldown experiment: bead-bound GST-FHL2 was 
incubated with 
35 S-labeled CALM (1-408), and the beads were 
washed and analyzed by SDS-PAGE. Only GST-FLH2 (lane 3), but not 
GST alone (lane 2), is able to retain </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>S-labeled-CALM (1-408). (b) Co-
immunoprecipitation (co-IP) of FLAG-FHL2 and YFP-CALM. HEK293T 
cells were transiently co-transfected with plasmids expressing FLAG-
FHL2 and YFP-CALM or FLAG-FHL2 and YFP. In lanes 1 and 3, 10% 
of the protein extract that was used for each co-IP reaction is loaded. 
GFP-binder beads were used for the precipitation, and only YFP-CALM 
(lane 2), but not YFP alone (lane 4), is able to precipitate FLAG-FHL2. </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>Figure 3 (a) FHL2 prey clone: alignment of the FHL2 prey clone with FHL2 (GAL4AD-FHL2). UTR: untranslated region; ORF: open reading 
frame; AD: activation domain; nt: nucleotide. Numbers above the diagrams refer to amino acids, and that below refer to nucleotides. (b) Mapping 
of the FHL2 interaction domain of CALM. A series of CALM deletion mutants was expressed as bait proteins in yeast together with the FHL2 prey 
protein (GAL4AD-FHL2). Dilutions of the transformants were spotted on yeast synthetic drop-out medium lacking tryptophan and leucine (-W/-L) 
to control for double transformant status or lacking tryptophan, leucine, histidine and adenine (-H/-A/-L/-W) to assay the activation of the reporter 
genes. Only the yeast clones with the CALM mutants CALM (1-408) and CALM (1-335) grow on the -H/-A/-L/-W plates, indicating that amino 
acids 294-335 of CALM are necessary for its interaction with FHL2. (c) Mapping of the CALM interaction domain of FHL2. Structure of CALM prey 
clone obtained from the yeast two-hybrid assay, GAL4 AD-CALM. AD: activation domain. A series of FHL2 deletion mutants was expressed as bait 
proteins in yeast together with the CALM prey protein (GAL4AD-CALM). Yeast double transformants were streaked on yeast synthetic drop-out 
medium lacking tryptophan and leucine (-W/-L) to control for double transformant status or on SD plates lacking tryptophan, leucine, histidine 
and adenine (-H/-A/-L/-W) to assay the activation of the reporter genes. Only the yeast clones with the full-length FHL2 (clone (1)) grow on the 
-H/-A/-L/-W plates, indicating that amino acids 206-279 of FHL2 are required for interaction with CALM. </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>Figure 4 Subcellular localization of FHL2, CALM and CALM/AF10. Confocal images of U2OS cells transiently transfected with plasmids 
expressing the proteins indicated on the left-hand side. Channels are indicated above the images (4 
0 ,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole, YFP, Cy3 and 
merged). For a detailed explanation of this figure, see the Results section. </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>karyotype or in the patients with complex aberrant karyotypes 
(P-value ¼ 5.256 Â 10 
À13 and ¼ 7.543 Â 10 
À7 , respectively) 
(Figure 8). There were no significant differences in the level of 
FHL2 expression between the different subgroups of patients 
with complex aberrant karyotypes (data not shown). </p>

<p>High expression of FHL2 mRNA transcript in patients 
with AML M6 </p>

<p>To confirm the results obtained from the microarray experiment, 
a quantitative real-time-polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) was 
performed on 45 patient samples. The 45 patients were divided 
into three groups: patients with AML M6 (n ¼ 15), patients with 
complex karyotype (n ¼ 15) and AML patients with normal 
karyotype (n ¼ 15). The qPCR revealed that the mRNA expres-
sion of FHL2 in patients with AML M6 was significantly higher 
than that in patients with complex karyotype (P-value: 0.000 
with (2369, 5379) 95% confidence interval) or normal 
karyotype (P-value: 0.000 (2064, 5156) with 95% confidence 
interval). No significant difference was detected between the 
mRNA expression of FHL2 in patients with complex karyotype 
or normal karyotype (P-value: 0.685 (À0.906, 0.378) with 95% 
confidence interval) (Figure 9). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The CALM/AF10 fusion is found in myeloid and lymphoid 
lineage acute leukemias. In contrast to many other leukemia-</p>

<p>associated fusion genes (for example, AML1/ETO), expression of 
CALM/AF10 leads to the development of an acute leukemia with 
a latency of only 9 weeks in a murine bone marrow 
transplantation model. 
15 One of the critical domains in the 
CALM/AF10 fusion protein that is required for malignant 
transformation is the octapeptide/leucine zipper domain in the 
AF10 portion of the fusion, which interacts with the histone 
methytransferase DOT1L. 
31 The octapeptide/leucine zipper 
domain is also critical for the transformation potential of MLL/ 
AF10 fusion. 
32 However, much less is known about the domains 
in CALM that contribute to the transforming potential of the 
CALM/AF10. We therefore used a Y2H approach to identify 
CALM protein interactors. 
Using the N-terminal 408 amino acids of CALM as bait, a 
member of the FHL subfamily of LIM-only proteins, FHL2, was 
identified as a protein interactor of CALM. FHL2 interacts with 
proteins belonging to different functional classes, including 
nuclear receptors, structural proteins, transcription factors and 
cofactors, splicing factors, DNA replication and repair enzymes, 
metabolic enzymes and signal transducers. </p>

<p>17,30,33-38 </p>

<p>The FHL2 interacting domain in CALM was mapped to amino 
acids 294-335 of CALM. The N-terminal domain (aa 22-138) of 
CALM contains the ANTH domain, which specifically binds to 
lipids (PtdIns(4,5)P 2 ) in the plasma membrane. 
11,39-41 The three-
dimensional structure of the N-terminal 280 amino acids of 
CALM has been solved and consists of 10 a-helices, which 
aggregate to form a globular protein. 
11 The C-terminal half of 
CALM, on the other hand, has most likely a poorly ordered 
structure that contains multiple short protein interaction motifs, </p>

<p>Figure 5 Line scans of the confocal images m, q and u from Figure 5 to demonstrate colocalization of (a) FLAG-FHL2 with YFP-CALM; (b) FLAG-
FHL2 with YFP-CALM/AF10; and (c) YFP-FHL2 with FLAG-CALM/AF10. </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>functioning like a flexible 'fishing line'. 
42 This composition of 
CALM permits the establishment of interactions during clathrin-
coated pit assembly. 
40 Interestingly, FHL2 binds to b-integrin, </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>which together with clathrin, a major binding partner of CALM, 
has been shown to be involved in endocytosis. 
9,44 Taken 
together, these data suggest a role for the CALM-FHL2 
interaction in the complex interaction network in endocytosis. 
The notion that FHL2 and CALM may act together in the 
cytoplasm in the endocytic machinery is supported by the fact 
that the expression of YFP-CALM and FLAG-FHL2 in U2OS cells 
result in colocalization of both proteins in the cytoplasm and at 
the cell membrane. In addition, CALM and FHL2 also 
colocalized in the nucleus of the U2OS cells, suggesting a </p>

<p>nuclear function for these proteins. FHL2 has previously been 
shown to be localized to both the nucleus and cytoplasm. </p>

<p>45-47 </p>

<p>Our immunofluorescence experiments with YFP-tagged FHL2 
and FLAG-tagged CALM/AF10 showed that CALM/AF10 was 
located mainly in the cytoplasm, while the FLAG-tagged FHL2 
was predominantly seen in the nucleus. Interestingly, a minor 
fraction of the FHL2 also colocalized with CALM/AF10 in 
distinct spots in the cytoplasm and there was a pronounced 
change in the distribution pattern of the cytoplasmic FHL2 when 
CALM/AF10 was co-expressed with FHL2 colocalizing with 
CALM/AF10 in distinct speckles in the cytoplasm. We suggest 
that these speckles might be inclusions of CALM/AF10 into 
clathrin-coated pits due to CALM/AF10-induced aberrant 
endocytosis. CALM/AF10 may tether its interaction partners 
into these endocytic vesicles and thereby disturb their physio-
logical function. 
FHL2 interacts with transcription factors like SKI and the 
promyelocytic leukemia zinc-finger protein (PLZF). PLZF has 
been shown to be a transcriptional repressor with a role in the 
control of cellular proliferation and Hox gene regulation, </p>

<p>48,49 </p>

<p>and FHL2 has been shown to enhance PLZF-mediated repres-
sion. 
50 PLZF is involved in the PLZF/RARa translocation found 
in patients with acute promyelocytic leukemia. 
51 Through the 
interaction with PLZF, FHL2 may mediate the activation of Hox 
genes by CALM/AF10, which was previously observed in patient 
samples and murine models. 
31,52 Interestingly, the FHL2 
interactors FOXO1 and SIRT1 
37 link FHL2 to the histone 
methyltransferase DOT1L, which interacts with AF10 and 
CALM/AF10 and methylates histone H3 at lysine 79. CALM-
AF10-positive patient samples and cell lines show marked 
histone H3 K79 hypomethylation. 
53 Therefore, CALM/AF10 may 
strongly influence the levels of H3K79 methylation by interact-
ing with both FHL2 and DOT1L; however, it will be very 
challenging to understand the complex interplay between these 
multiple interacting proteins involved in the regulation of 
histone marks. The SKI-FHL2 interaction potentiates the 
function of b-catenin in melanoma cells, inducing proliferation, 
cell cycle alterations and tumor progression. 
54 FHL2 is also a 
crucial member of the transmembrane glycoprotein EpCAM's 
signaling complex, which regulates transcription in the nucleus 
through its association with components of the Wnt signaling 
pathway, like b-catenin and Lef1. </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>Figure 6 (a) CALM inhibits FHL2-dependent activation of transcrip-
tion. HEK293T cells were transiently transfected with plasmids 
expressing GAL4DBD, GAL4DBD-FHL2 and YFP-CALM, a luciferase 
reporter plasmid and a Renilla luciferase control plasmid as indicated. 
The bars indicate fold activation of luciferase activity compared to 
GALDBD. Four independent experiments with three measurements 
per sample were performed. The error bars represent standard 
deviations. The firefly luciferase values were normalized to the Renilla 
luciferase values. (b) CALM/AF10 does not inhibit FHL2-dependent 
activation of transcription. HEK293T cells were transiently transfected 
with plasmids expressing GAL4DBD, GAL4DBD-FHL2 and YFP-
CALM/CAF10 and a luciferase reporter plasmid as indicated. Co-
transfection of YFP-CALM/AF10 did not have a significant influence on 
the transcriptional activation mediated by GAL4DBD-FHL2. (c) FHL2 
inhibits CALM/AF10-dependent activation of transcription. HEK293T 
cells were transiently transfected with plasmids expressing GAL4DBD, 
GAL4DBD-CALM/AF10, YFP-CALM/AF10 and a luciferase reporter 
plasmid as indicated. In this setting, GAL4DBD-CALM/AF10 is a 
strong transcriptional activator. A threefold reduction of the 
GAL4DBD-CALM/AF10-mediated transcriptional activation is ob-
served when FLAG-FHL2 is co-expressed. Three independent experi-
ments were performed and measured in duplicate. </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>In reporter gene assay, FHL2 functions as a transcriptional 
activator when fused to the GAL4-DBD. 
30 We could show that 
co-expression of CALM significantly disturbed the transcrip-
tional activation induced by FHL2. Since the FHL2 interaction 
domain of CALM is present in the leukemogenic CALM/AF10 
fusion protein, we also tested whether CALM/AF10 would 
influence the transcriptional activation function of GAL4-DBD-
FHL2. Interestingly, this was not the case. The transcriptional 
activation mediated by FHL2 was inhibited by CALM, but not by 
CALM/AF10, suggesting that the CALM/AF10 fusion protein 
might interfere with a physiological negative regulatory role of 
CALM on the function of FHL2. In other words, CALM/AF10 
might change the function of FHL2 and this could be an 
important mechanism in CALM/AF10-induced leukemia. In 
particular, the loss of FHL2 inhibition by CALM may potentiate 
the enhanced proliferation of myeloid progenitors that was 
observed upon forced expression of FHL2 in murine bone 
marrow cells. </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>One of the characteristics of AML with complex aberrant 
karyotypes is the frequent loss of chromosome 5 as well as a 
high incidence of TP53 deletions and/or mutations, resulting in 
an overall unfavorable prognosis. 
57 Interestingly, Qian et al. </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>showed that therapy-related myelodysplastic syndrome and 
AML characterized by a loss of a whole chromosome 5 or a 
deletion of the long arm of chromosome 5 (À5/del(5q)) showed 
elevated FHL2 expression levels. Another characteristic of AML 
with complex aberrant karyotypes is the frequent loss of 
chromosome 7 that is also associated with adverse prognosis. </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>Figure 8 Expression of FHL2 in samples from patients with AML with 
complex aberrant karyotypes, AML M6 and AML with normal 
karyotypes. FHL2 microarray expression levels from 308 AML. Group 
1 consists of 167 AML patients with normal karyotypes of all FAB 
subtypes, except M6, group 2 consists of 115 samples from patients 
with AML with complex aberrant karyotypes, and group 3 contains 26 
samples from patients with AML M6. FHL2 is significantly higher 
expressed in patients with AML M6 than in AML patients with a 
normal karyotype or in patients with complex aberrant karyotypes 
(P ¼ 2.2 Â 10 
À16 and P ¼ 9.967 Â 10 </p>

<p>À10 </p>

<p>, respectively). A significant 
difference in the expression of FHL2 was found between AML patients 
with normal karyotype and patients with AML complex karyotype with 
a P-value ¼ 1.04 Â 10 </p>

<p>À12 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Figure 9 FHL2 is highly expressed in patients with AML M6 
karyotype. FHL2 expression was determined using qRT-PCR in 45 
AML patient samples. High expression of FHL2 was observed in 
patients with AML M6 in comparison to patients with complex or 
normal karyotype (P-value: 0.000). No statistical significance was 
discovered between AML patients with complex karyotype and 
patients with normal karyotype (P-value: 0.685). The data are 
presented as fold change in gene expression compared to the gene 
expression of AML patients with normal karyotype. </p>

<p>Figure 7 Expression of FHL2 in leukemia patient samples. FHL2 is 
expressed at higher levels in CML and AML with complex aberrant 
karyotype. A microarray analysis was performed on 129 patient 
samples and 10 normal bone marrow (nBM) samples. The boxplots 
depict the expression levels of FHL2 in nBM, CML, CALM/AF10-
positive leukemias, in seven different AML subtypes (AML_nk: AML 
with normal karyotype; AML_comp: AML with complex aberrant 
karyotype; AML_MLL: AML with an MLL rearrangement; AML_M4: 
AML with CBFB/MYH11 fusion; AML_M3: acute promyelocytic 
leukemia with a PML/RARA fusion; AML_M2: AML with an AML1/ 
ETO fusion; AML_FLT3: AML with normal karyotype and with an fms-
like tyrosine kinase receptor-3 (FLT3) internal tandem duplication), 
and four ALL subtypes (ALL_Ph: ALL with BCR/ABL fusion; ALL-MLL: 
ALL with an MLL rearrangement; ALL_BA: c-ALL: (common ALL) and 
ALL: pro-B-ALL). Each group is composed of 10 patient samples, 
except the ALL-MLL patient group, which contains 9 samples. 
Expression intensities are depicted on a logarithmic scale. The median 
of the distribution is indicated by a bar. The box presents 50% of the 
expression values in that group and is called the interquartile range 
(IQR). An expression value is considered an outlier when it lies more 
than 1.5 IQR lower or higher than the first or third quartile, respectively. 
Outliers are represented as circles. The smallest and largest values that 
are not outliers are indicated by a vertical tic mark or 'whisker', which is 
connected to the box via a horizontal line. If the notches of the boxes 
do not overlap between two groups, there is evidence that the medians 
are significantly different between the groups. </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

<p>We also observed high expression levels of FHL2 in patients 
with complex aberrant karyotype and with CML. Although 
analyzing the expression levels of FHL2 in patients with 
monosomy 5 or del(5)(q), five patients with very high FHL2 
expression levels were noted (data not shown). Three of these 
outliers had erythroleukemia (AML M6) and two had AML M4. 
When we performed a new analysis using the FHL2 expression 
data from all available M6 patient samples, a significantly higher 
FHL2 expression in patients with AML M6 was discovered. 
Erythroid leukemia has a poor prognosis. 
59 These results are in 
line with reports that high expression levels of FHL2 in breast 
and prostate cancer have recently been shown to be associated 
with an adverse prognosis. 
20-22 Interestingly, we could recently 
show that the expression levels of another member of the FHL 
family, namely FHL1, correlated closely with a poor prognosis 
in cytogenetically normal AML. 
25 Early erythroid cells are 
characterized by an increased expression of FHL2 (GNF 
Expression Atlas 2 Data from U133A and GNF1H Chips; 
http://www.genome.ucsc.edu). Thus, the observed overexpres-
sion of FHL2 could be only a marker of the erythroid lineage. 
Additional experiments are required to determine the causes 
and/or consequences of elevated FHL2 expression levels in 
erythroid leukemia. 
Our results, combined with previous reports of FHL2 being 
associated with adverse prognosis in different cancers as well as 
acting on the cell cycle program, thus regulating cell prolifera-
tion 
46 and cell differentiation, 
60 suggest that there might be a 
common oncogenic pathway in the development and progres-
sion of leukemogenesis as well as in tumorigenesis. However, 
more studies will be required to understand the role of the 
CALM-FHL2 interaction in leukemogenesis and especially its 
role in erythroleukemia. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Dr Judith Mü ller for providing the GST-FHL2 and GAL4-
DBD-FHL2 constructs and Dr Paul Riley for the FLAG-FHL2 
construct. This work was funded by a grant from the German 
Ministry of Research and Education (BMBF; 01GS0876) to SKB, a 
grant to the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft to SKB (SFB 684, 
A6) and by a scholarship from the Deutsche Jose-Carreras-
Leukämie-Stiftung to PAG. </p>



<p> 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>



<p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-No Derivative Works 
3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on Blood Cancer Journal website (http://www.nature.com/bcj) </p>

<p>FHL2 interacts with CALM and is highly expressed in acute erythroid leukemia 
Z Pašaliae et al </p>



<p>Blood Cancer Journal </p>

</text></tei>