<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3488743" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: To date, there are no data available </p>

<p>concerning the impact of iron therapy on the long-term 
well-being and health-related quality of life (HRQoL) in 
pregnancy. </p>

<p>Objective: To assess the long-term effect of iron </p>

<p>therapy on HRQoL in pregnancy. </p>

<p>of an earlier 
randomised open-label clinical trial of intravenous and 
oral iron versus oral iron for pregnancy-related iron 
deficiency anaemia. We used a modified version of the 
SF-36 questionnaire together with the original 
prospective HRQoL data collected during and after 
pregnancy. </p>

<p>Participants and interventions: Of the original </p>

<p>evaluable 183 pregnant Caucasian women randomised 
to receive oral iron or a single intravenous iron 
polymaltose infusion followed by oral iron maintenance, 
126 women completed the follow-up HRQoL study. </p>

<p>Methods: The participants were followed up 4 weeks </p>

<p>after treatment, predelivery and postdelivery for a 
median period of 32 months (range, 26-42) with a well-
being and HRQoL questionnaire using a modified SF-36 
QoL-survey and child growth charts as set by the 
Australasian Paediatric Endocrine Group (APEG). </p>

<p>Results: Patients who received intravenous iron </p>

<p>demonstrated significantly higher haemoglobin and 
serum ferritin levels ( p&lt;0.001). There were strong 
associations between iron status and a number of the 
HRQoL parameters, with improved general health 
( p&lt;0.001), improved vitality ( physical energy) 
( p&lt;0.001), less psychological downheartedness 
( p=0.005), less clinical depression ( p=0.003) and 
overall improved mental health ( p&lt;0.001). The duration 
of breastfeeding was longer ( p=0.046) in the 
intravenous iron group. The babies born in both groups 
recorded similarly on APEG growth chart assessments. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Our data suggest that HRQoL is </p>

<p>improved until after pregnancy in anaemic pregnant 
women by repletion of their iron stores during 
pregnancy. About 80% of the intravenous iron group 
showed a maintained normal ferritin until delivery with 
long-term benefits. Further studies to confirm these 
findings are warranted. </p>

<p>ARTICLE SUMMARY </p>

<p>Article focus </p>

<p>▪ Health-related quality-of-life (HRQoL) assess-
ment during and after pregnancy in 126 women 
with iron deficiency who received either a single 
infusion of intravenous iron polymaltose followed 
by oral iron maintenance or oral iron only. 
▪ Study of postnatal depression and its association 
with treatment arms and iron status. 
▪ Assessment of breastfeeding duration and correl-
ation to mothers' iron status. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ HRQoL during and after pregnancy is improved 
significantly in anaemic pregnant women by 
repletion of their iron stores during pregnancy. 
▪ About 80% of the intravenous iron group 
showed a maintained normal ferritin until deliv-
ery with long-term benefits such as prolongation 
of the breastfeeding period and less postnatal 
clinical depression. 
▪ There were strong associations between iron 
status and a number of the HRQoL scales with 
improved general health (p=0.021), improved 
physical energy ( p=0.016), less psychological 
downheartedness ( p=0.005), less clinical depres-
sion ( p=0.003) and an overall improved mental 
component scale ( p&lt;0.001). The duration of 
breastfeeding was longer ( p=0.046) in women 
who had received intravenous iron. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This study reports a novel finding in terms of a 
correlation between both postnatal depression 
and the breastfeeding period with iron status. 
▪ There are limited data available concerning the 
quality of life during and after pregnancy, which 
makes the scientific input of the current study 
important. 
▪ Limitations of our study include that the modi-
fied questionnaire was in part a retrospective 
HRQoL evaluation, and this should ideally have 
been prospectively conducted. 
▪ Another limitation is the relatively small number 
of women studied. </p>

<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. 3 10 11   In the past, intravenous iron was associated with 
undesirable and sometimes serious side effects that 
limited its use. 
12 Recently, new type II iron complexes 
have been developed with the potential to reverse iron 
deficiency with less side effects than their predeces-
sors. 
12-14 Despite increasing evidence for the safety of the 
newer preparations in both pregnant and general popula-
tions, intravenous iron continues to be underutilised. </p>

<p>15   Earlier, we reported on a randomised controlled trial 
(PMID: 20546462) of intravenous followed by oral iron 
therapy versus oral iron therapy only for moderate IDA in 
pregnancy. 
14 The results of the earlier analysis showed that 
intravenous iron polymaltose was associated with greater 
improvements in haemoglobin (Hb) levels and iron stores 
compared to oral iron alone in pregnancy-related IDA. </p>

<p>14   Here, we report the results of a follow-up assessment of the 
same cohort of patients. We studied the effects of both 
treatment types on the perceived health-related quality of 
life (HRQoL) as measured by a modified SF-36 question-
naire. The effect of iron therapy on breastfeeding rates 
and on the general well-being of the babies born to these 
women was measured by child growth charts set by the 
Australasian Paediatric Endocrine Group (APEG). </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS 
Rationale and objectives 
An initial prospective randomised controlled trial was 
conducted between March 2007 and January 2009 at the 
Launceston General Hospital (LGH), a tertiary referral 
centre for Northern Tasmania, Australia. The initial study 
assessed Hb and serum ferritin levels after intravenous 
followed by oral iron therapy versus oral iron therapy 
only. The current study constitutes a follow-up on the 
earlier one and took place between January 2010 and 
January 2011 and focused on HRQoL, breastfeeding dur-
ation and child health. Informed consent was obtained 
from all participants in accordance with the Declaration </p>

<p>of Helsinki. The original and the follow-up studies were 
approved by the Tasmanian Human Research Ethics 
Committee and registered in the Australian New Zealand 
Clinical Trials Registry (http://www.ANZCTR.org.au/ 
ACTRN12609000177257.aspx) and the WHO Clinical 
Trials Registry (http://www.who.int/trialsearch/trial. 
aspx? trialid=ACTRN12609000596202). 
In the original study, we prospectively assessed HRQoL 
at baseline prior to treatment in the second trimester, 
4 weeks after the initiation of treatment, in the third tri-
mester before delivery, and at 6-8 weeks postdelivery. In 
the follow-up study, an HRQoL questionnaire was com-
pleted that incorporated the original questionnaire plus 
additional parameters such as the length of the breast-
feeding period and occurrence of postnatal depression 
as well as child growth data. This was performed at a 
median of 32 months postintervention in order to assess 
the long-term effects of both treatment types on 
mothers' HRQoL in relation to data from the earlier 
study. This questionnaire, although completed prospect-
ively, had a retrospective component that asked the par-
ticipating mothers the same questions again that they 
had previously answered prospectively. These data were 
compared with the mothers' original prospective QoL 
data for validation purposes. </p>

<p>Participants 
Pregnant women aged 18 years or above who presented 
to the LGH with IDA between 2007 and 2009 were 
invited to participate. In the original study (figure 1), 
196 Caucasian pregnant women aged 18 years or above 
were identified who had moderate IDA, defined as Hb 
≤115 g/l (reference range (RR) 120-160 g/l), and low 
iron stores, based on serum ferritin levels &lt;30 µg/l (RR 
30-440 µg/l). 
Of the original evaluable 183 pregnant Caucasian 
women randomised to receive oral iron or a single intra-
venous iron polymaltose infusion, 126 women completed 
the QoL follow-up study (table 1). The median age was 
29 years at enrolment (range, 21-43); and the median 
follow-up period was 32 months (range, 26-42) with an 
average follow-up period of 36 months postdelivery. </p>

<p>Randomisation and interventions 
Informed consent was obtained from all patients. 
Treatment arms were allocated in blocks of 10 by 
computer-generated random assignment, and allocation 
was done by concealed envelopes. This was done by the 
LGH pharmacy department in order to avoid possible 
bias. The oral-only treatment arm comprised iron sul-
phate 250 mg tablets once daily, (elemental iron 80 mg, 
Abbott, Australasia Pty Ltd) to be taken daily within 
2 days after booking until delivery. The intravenous arm 
required a single intravenous infusion of iron polymal-
tose (Ferrosig, Sigma Pharmaceuticals, Sydney, NSW, 
Australia) within 1 week after first antenatal visit fol-
lowed by oral iron identical to the other arm. 
Pre-enrolment, there were no significant differences in </p>



<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000998 </p>

<p>Quality of life in pregnancy </p>

<p>the dietary iron intake or supplement intake between 
the two groups based on a specially designed question-
naire addressing these issues. 
14 Patients assigned to intra-
venous iron polymaltose received a 100 mg test dose 
dissolved in 50-100 ml normal saline infused over 
30 min. Clinical observation and vital signs were assessed </p>

<p>initially and every 15 min from the start of the infusion. 
After the test-dose was tolerated, the remainder of the 
iron polymaltose dose was infused. The total dose of 
intravenous iron polymaltose was calculated according to 
the patients' body weight at their first antenatal visit and 
entry Hb level according to the product guidelines; iron </p>

<p>Figure 1 Patients flow chart. *Fourteen patients were admitted late in labour, and no blood samples were taken before delivery. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>The primary hypothesis examined the change in haemoglobin levels between the time of booking and immediately prior to 
delivery; an 'intention-to-treat' analysis was performed according to original randomisation group on those patients who had blood 
samples taken before delivery, whether or not the treatment was completed as per the protocol. 
 ‡ Twenty-one patients withdrew 
from the trial treatments, and all but one of these patients agreed to continued collection of haematological and other trial data; 
eight patients gave no reason for withdrawal. 
 § Five patients did not complete the intended treatments, but did not choose to 
withdraw themselves; three patients in the oral iron group were treated with intravenous iron when their haemoglobin was judged 
not to have responded adequately to oral iron, while one patient was unable to attend for intravenous iron treatment. </p>

<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000998 </p>



<p>Quality of life in pregnancy </p>

<p>dose in mg (50 mg/1 ml)=body weight (maximum 90) 
in kg×[target Hb (120 g/l)−actual Hb (in g/l)×constant 
factor (0.24)+iron depot (500)]. </p>

<p>14   Outcome measurement 
Two HRQoL questionnaires were administered during 
the initial and follow-up studies. First, a clinical question-
naire was completed prospectively by trained midwives at 
4 weeks after initiation of treatment, at 28 and 34 weeks 
gestation, and then 6-8 weeks postdelivery. This ques-
tionnaire assessed four aspects: energy levels, activity, tol-
erance and side effects of the treatment. This was used 
to guide individual patient clinical decision-making as 
well as to provide a safety audit of the trial treatments. </p>

<p>14   Second, a prospective/retrospective survey was con-
ducted between June and October 2010 by trained 
research personnel via phone interview using a modified 
version of the SF-36 HRQoL questionnaire, similar to a 
version published previously. 
16 17 Additional modifica-
tions for this study included: (1) use of eleven of the 36 
questions (table 2) and (2) the women were asked to 
recall their response to each of the questions at four 
timepoints; pretrial prior to commencement of iron 
therapy during the pregnancy, 4 weeks after the start of 
iron therapy, 1 week after delivery and the last 4 weeks 
prior to the telephone questionnaire contact (table 2). 
This was compared in a retrospective manner to the 
same questions answered earlier prospectively by the 
participants at these different timepoints. In order to val-
idate the retrospective use of the modified SF-36 </p>

<p>questionnaire to assess the women's HRQoL during and 
after pregnancy, we estimated the associations of the 
physical activity component of the prospective monitor-
ing questionnaire following entry into the trial with the 
Physical Component Scale values of the modified SF-36 
at each of the timepoints. We hypothesised that the asso-
ciation would be greatest at 4 weeks after enrolment 
compared to trial entry, time of delivery or at the time 
of questionnaire completion. In addition, data concern-
ing breastfeeding and the health of the child were col-
lected from the baby's growth booklet. This included 
breastfeeding duration, baby gender, age, weight and 
previous hospitalisation, if any, in addition to the baby's 
sleep quality since birth and specific growth data for the 
children as set by the APEG. Hb and ferritin levels for 
participants at delivery were available for all participants; 
however, no further testing was performed during the 
follow-up. The principal investigators, including the stat-
istician, evaluated the questionnaire results data. </p>

<p>Statistical methods 
The HRQoL scores that form the raw data for this analysis 
are rank-order in nature. Means and SDs of the scores 
were estimated using generalised estimating equations 
for illustrative purposes only. Physical and mental com-
posite scores were calculated in the modified SF-36 
according to the SF-12 scoring guidelines. 
16 17 Group 
comparison and covariate effect size calculation, OR 
(with 95% CIs and p values) were estimated using 
repeated measures of ordinal logistic regression, with cov-
ariates selected for inclusion by backward stepwise regres-
sion ( p-value for exclusion 0.22) from maternal age, Hb, 
ferritin, Socio-Economic Indexes for Areas ( based on 
the Collector District of residence of mothers), quality of 
sleep, use and duration of breastfeeding, hospitalisation 
of the baby, baby gender and mode of delivery. This 
included randomisation group covariate interactions in 
the starting model with exclusion of those interactions 
using the above criteria. When iron status was selected 
for inclusion in the model, the association between iron 
status (ferritin) and HRQoL was reported independently 
of the trial treatment group. p Values were corrected for 
multiple comparisons where necessary by the Holm 
method. The effect of intravenous iron versus oral iron 
on time of cessation of breastfeeding was compared by 
estimation of the HR with 95% CIs and p values by Cox 
proportional hazards regression adjusted for covariates 
selected for inclusion by backward stepwise regression 
( p-value for exclusion 0.22). The time to cessation of 
breast-feeding was taken from the subject's baby growth 
booklet for all participants. Neonatal growth in the treat-
ment groups was compared by multivariate third-order 
polynomial regression as an approximation to APEG 
growth assessment. The iron status variables used in the 
multivariate regression models were selected by stepwise 
regression. All HRQoL statistical analyses were performed 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata SE</rs> for Windows V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">11.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp</rs>, College 
Station, Texas, USA). </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Intravenous iron 
group </p>

<p>Oral iron 
group </p>

<p>Number of patients 
64 
62 
Vaginal delivery 
45 
46 
Caesarean section 
19 
16 
Median age (years) 
28 (range; 
21-43) </p>

<p>28.5 (range; 
22-42) 
Mean age (years) 
27.5 
28 
Median time between 
trial intervention and 
delivery (months) </p>

<p>2.7 (range; 
2.6-6) </p>

<p>2.8 (range; 
2.2-5.3) </p>

<p>Median time of 
follow-up (months) </p>

<p>28 
29 </p>

<p>Baby birth weight (g) 
Median 3523 
(range; 
1315-4920) </p>

<p>Median 3480 
(range; 
1330-4928) 
Median initial Hb (g/l) 
105 
108 
Median Hb after 
intervention and prior 
to delivery (g/l) </p>

<p>128 
118 </p>

<p>Median Hb 
postdelivery (g/l) </p>

<p>118 (range; 
86-146) </p>

<p>112 (range; 
78-137) 
Blood transfusion 
requirement </p>

<p>None 
Two patients </p>

<p>Hb, haemoglobin. </p>



<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000998 </p>

<p>Quality of life in pregnancy </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Of the original 196 patients randomised to receive the 
trial medications (98 intravenous plus oral iron; 98 oral 
iron only), 183 patients completed the trial by collection 
of blood for iron status at the time of delivery. Data of </p>

<p>HRQoL were collected from 126 of the 183 women who 
completed the original trial, representing 69% of the ori-
ginal cohort, while 57 (31%) of the 183 patients had 
moved away, were uncontactable or did not respond to 
follow-up requests (see figure 1 for description of patient </p>

<p>Table 2 Comparison of the questions in the SF-36 and the abbreviated health-related quality-of-life (HRQoL) questionnaire 
used in this study </p>

<p>Questionnaires* 
Original SF-36 
Modified short-HRQoL 
Time specified for subject response 
Either in at the time of analysis 
or in past 4 weeks </p>

<p>Evaluated at four time periods: before 
treatment; after 4 weeks of treatment; after 
delivery; and during the past 4 weeks 
before interview 
Question: stem and detailed item † 
Question number and response 
options </p>

<p>Question number and response options </p>

<p>In general, would you say your health is 
Q1: Excellent; Very good; Good; 
Fair; Poor </p>

<p>Q1: Excellent; Very good; Good; Fair; 
Poor 
The following questions are about activities 
you might do during a typical day. Does your 
health now limit you in these activities? If so, 
how much? </p>

<p>Yes, limited a lot; Yes, limited a 
little; No, not limited at all </p>

<p>Yes, limited a lot; Yes, limited a little; No, 
not limited at all </p>

<p>Moderate activities, such as moving a table, 
pushing a vacuum cleaner, bowling, or 
playing golf </p>

<p>Q3b 
Q2a </p>

<p>Climbing several flights of stairs 
Q3d 
Q2b 
During the past 4 weeks, how much of the 
time have you had any of the following 
problems with your work or other regular 
daily activities as a result of your physical 
health? </p>

<p>All of the time; Most of the time; 
Some of the time; A little of the 
time; None of the time </p>

<p>All of the time; Most of the time; Some of 
the time; A little of the time; None of the 
time </p>

<p>Accomplished less than you would like 
Q4b 
Q3a 
Were limited in the kind of work or other 
activities </p>

<p>Q4c 
Q3b </p>

<p>During the past 4 weeks, how much of the 
time have you had any of the following 
problems with your work or other regular 
daily activities as a result of any emotional 
problems (such as feeling depressed or 
anxious)? </p>

<p>All of the time; Most of the time; 
Some of the time; A little of the 
time; None of the time </p>

<p>All of the time; Most of the time; Some of 
the time; A little of the time; None of the 
time </p>

<p>Accomplished less than you would like 
Q5b 
Q6a 
Did work or other activities less carefully than 
usual </p>

<p>Q5c 
Q6b </p>

<p>Have you felt calm and peaceful? 
Q9d 
Q4a 
Did you have a lot of energy? 
Q9e 
Q4b 
Have you felt downhearted and depressed? 
Q9f 
Q4c 
Have you been diagnosed with or treated for 
depression or postnatal depression since the 
birth of your baby? </p>

<p>Not included 
Q4d: Diagnosed: Yes/No; Treated: Yes/No </p>

<p>During the past 4 weeks, how much of the 
time has your physical health or emotional 
problems interfered with your social activities 
(like visiting friends, relatives, etc)? </p>

<p>Q10: All of the time; Most of the 
time; Some of the time; A little of 
the time; None of the time </p>

<p>Q5: All of the time; Most of the time; Some 
of the time; A little of the time; None of the 
time </p>

<p>During the past 4 weeks, how much did pain 
interfere with your normal work (including 
both work outside the home and 
housework)? </p>

<p>Q8: Not at all; A little bit; 
Moderately; Quite a bit; 
Extremely </p>

<p>Not included </p>

<p>*Not all of the original SF-36 questions are included in this list. All the questions shown in this list, except for the last original SF-36 question 
about pain, were included in the questionnaire administered in this study. Where the questionnaire response was the same this is indicated, 
and where the response differed from the original SF-36 wording the new responses were shown. The order in which the questions (eg, Q1 
as first question, or Q5b as question subset 5 s question) were administered in the original and modified questionnaires is shown. 
 †Questions: Q1, Q2, etc denotes question numbers. </p>

<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000998 </p>



<p>Quality of life in pregnancy </p>

<p>flow). The median age of the patients included in the 
follow-up study was 29 years at enrolment (range, 21-43) 
and the median follow-up was 32 months (range, 26-42) 
postdelivery. There were no significant differences in 
demographic or iron status measurements between any of 
the groups of women recruited to the trial. All participants 
were Caucasians. 
As reported in the original study, 
14 at delivery the propor-
tion of women with lower than normal ferritin levels was 53 
of 67 (79%) for women with analysable iron status mea-
surements who were treated with oral iron as compared to 
3 of 66 (4.5%) for women who received intravenous iron 
(Fisher's exact p&lt;0.001). The pretreatment mean serum 
ferritin levels were low in both groups at 17 µg/l. However, 
the serum ferritin of those in the intravenous iron group 
increased markedly within 4 weeks of the intravenous 
therapy with a mean level of 222 µg/l; 95% CI 194 to 
249 µg/l (p&lt;0.001). This substantial improvement was 
maintained after delivery with a mean level of 108 µg/l; 
95% CI 43 to 209 µg/l (p&lt;0.001). 
14 On the other hand, 
ferritin levels did not show a significant increase in the oral 
iron group through pregnancy and after delivery. 
Furthermore, the percentage of women at delivery with Hb 
levels &lt;116 g/l was 29% (25 of 85) in the oral iron group 
versus 16% (14 of 87) in the intravenous iron group 
(p=0.04) incidence rate ratio 0.55 (95% CI 0.31 to 0.98; 
p=0.043). After delivery, the mean Hb levels declined to </p>

<p>111.6 g/l (SD 14.2) in the oral iron versus 115.5 g/l (SD 
10.8) in the intravenous iron group. This showed a continu-
ing favourable effect of intravenous iron therapy (95% CI 
2.5 to 9.1; p=0.004) despite the loss of blood at delivery. </p>

<p>14   There were no significant differences in the birth 
weights of the babies in the two treatment groups, with 
an average birth weight of 3.42 kg in both groups with a 
difference of 0.03 kg ( p=0.77). There were also no dif-
ferences in the gestational age at delivery in both treat-
ment groups with a mean of 39.1 weeks in the oral iron 
versus 38.9 weeks in the intravenous iron group, with 
only a slight difference of 0.2 weeks ( p=0.74). There 
were no significant differences in placental cord Hb or 
ferritin levels in both treatment groups. The mean cord 
Hb was 165 g/l (SD 9.6) in the oral iron group versus 
157 g/l (SD 14.1) in the intravenous iron group (differ-
ence −7; 95% CI −18 to 3; p=0.17). The ferritin levels 
were 142 µg/l (SD 86) and 185 µg/l (SD 101), respect-
ively, (difference 43; 95% CI −59 to 145; p=0.41). 
The HRQoL Physical Component Scale (difference 
10.3; 95% CI 3.3 to 17.2; p=0.27; OR 2.39; 95% CI 1.32 to 
4.32; p=0.004) and general health (difference 15.1; 95% 
CI 6.0 to 24.2; p=0.31; OR 3.14; 95% CI 1.57 to 6.26; 
p=0.001) responses were improved in the intravenous 
compared to the oral iron group, but these differences 
became less apparent at subsequent assessment time-
points (figure 2A,B). Furthermore, there were strong </p>

<p>Figure 2 (A and B) Comparison of physical component scale of health-related quality-of-life (HRQoL) scores in the intravenous 
plus oral iron versus the oral iron group, and separate association with iron status.  †Comparison of the effect of intravenous plus 
oral iron versus oral iron on physical (A) and mental (B) components of the HRQoL scores at different time periods (before 
starting iron, 4 weeks after starting iron, at delivery and when the mother responded to questionnaire), estimated using ordinal 
logistic regression adjusted for significant demographic confounders but not including iron status, corrected for repeated 
measures and multiple comparisons (Holm method). *The effect of iron status on physical component and mental component 
scores was estimated separately without including treatment group in the analysis. The timepoint 'Later' is referring to the 
postdelivery follow-up assessment. </p>



<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000998 </p>

<p>Quality of life in pregnancy </p>

<p>associations between the level of iron status, independent 
of how that iron status was achieved, and a number of the 
HRQoL scales (figure 2): notably improved general 
health (slope (1 SD log-ferritin) 10.0; 7.2-12.7; p&lt;0.001; 
OR 1.49; 95% CI 1.09 to 2.03; p=0.021), improved vitality 
(slope (1 SD log-ferritin) 10.0; 7.3-12.8; p&lt;0.001; OR 
2.09; 95% CI 1.66 to 2.62; p&lt;0.001), less psychological 
downheartedness ((1 SD Hb ) OR 1.57; 95% CI 1.14 to 
2.15; p=0.005), less clinical depression ((1 SD log.-
ferritin) OR 2.05; 95% CI 1.27 to 3.32; p=0.003) and 
overall improved mental component scale (slope (1 SD 
Hb ) 3.8; 2.5-5.0; p&lt;0.001; OR 1.71; 95% CI 1.39 to 2.10; 
p&lt;0.001) (Psychological Downheartedness and Clinical 
Depression analysis used raw scores rather than 100-point 
scales). 
There was an increased duration of breastfeeding (HR 
for cessation was 0.70; 95% CI 0.50 to 0.99; p=0.046) in 
women in the intravenous iron group (figure 3), where 
higher maternal age was associated with longer breast-
feeding (HR 0.76; 95% CI 1.00 to 1.52; p=0.006, table 3). 
Earlier cessation of breastfeeding was associated with 
downheartedness (HR 1.23; 95% CI 1.00 to 1.52; p=0.06). 
There was no difference between the oral iron or intra-
venous plus oral iron groups in the weight of the baby at 
birth ( p=0.64), and no difference in the rate of weight 
gain ( p=0.90). 
The correlation between the prospective physical 
symptom questions index from the clinical monitoring 
questionnaire and the Physical Component Scale of the 
retrospective HRQoL for the four time periods is shown 
in table 4. There was a significant association between the 
physical symptom questions index at 4 weeks after trial 
entry and each of the HRQoL recall timepoints, and the 
correlation was strongest for the 4 weeks recall (OR 3.18; 
95% CI 2.14 to 4.74; p&lt;0.001). 
Another finding of our study was an association 
between male gender babies and an unfavourable mental 
health component outcome for participant women 
across the two groups. Of the seven component </p>

<p>questions, two showed a significant association, with 
women who had male babies less likely to be calm and 
peaceful (OR=0.55, 95% CI 0.32-0.97, p=0.039). There 
were no statistical differences in terms of HRQoL assess-
ment regarding the method of delivery between women 
who delivered normally and those who had caesarean 
section. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Prior to our study, there were no data available concern-
ing the effects of either intravenous or oral iron supple-
mentation for anaemia on postdelivery psychological and 
physical welfare of mothers, the quality of the bonding to 
the baby and the rate of developmental progress of the 
baby. We are reporting on 126 patients in a follow-up 
study of the effect of intravenous iron versus oral iron 
therapy on HRQoL during and after pregnancy. Our 
study demonstrates that there was an improvement in the 
self-assessed feeling of general health in both treatment 
groups from the prelabour period to all subsequent 
periods. Although the improvement was significantly 
greater during pregnancy in the intravenous iron group 
4 weeks after commencement of trial treatment 
( p=0.001), the difference persisted in the subsequent 
measurement periods at a lesser magnitude that did not 
achieve statistical significance. 
Regardless of treatment and regardless of which 
period was being considered, higher Hb and higher fer-
ritin levels were associated with better baby sleep quality, 
a longer period of breastfeeding and a higher level of 
mothers' general health. 
The modified HRQoL questionnaire used in our study 
includes many useful and relevant aspects regarding 
general health, daily activities, levels of energy and </p>

<p>Figure 3 Effect of IV plus oral iron versus oral iron on rate of 
cessation of breastfeeding. </p>

<p>Table 3 Effect of intravenous iron versus oral iron on rate 
of cessation of breast feeding </p>

<p>HR* 
95% CI 
p Value </p>

<p>Intravenous plus oral 
0.70 
(0.50 to 0.99) 
0.046 
Maternal age 
0.76 
(0.63 to 0.92) 
0.006 
Downheartedness 
1.23 
(1.00 to 1.52) 
0.055 
Current alcohol intake 
1.34 
(0.88 to 2.03) 
0.18 
Mode of delivery: 
NVD 
1.00 
LSCS 
1.24 
(0.84 to 1.82) 
0.29 
Forceps 
1.39 
(0.85 to 2.27) 
0.19 </p>

<p>*The likelihood of cessation of breast feeding in the intravenous 
plus oral iron group was compared with that of the oral iron only 
group: estimated using Cox proportional hazards regression 
corrected for repeated-measures and adjusted for the covariates 
shown, expressed as hazards ratios (95% CIs; p values). 
Covariates included in the final multivariate model were selected 
by stepwise regression. The standardised normal transformation 
of maternal age was used ((mother's age−group mean age)/group 
SD of age): mean age 28.1±5.6 years. HR less than 1.00 
indicates a slower rate of cessation of breastfeeding, while an HR 
greater than 1.00 indicates a faster rate of ceasing breastfeeding. 
NVD, normal vaginal delivery; LSCS, lower segment caesarean 
section. </p>

<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000998 </p>



<p>Quality of life in pregnancy </p>

<p>depression. There was a substantial improvement of iron 
status in women who received intravenous iron com-
pared to oral iron as demonstrated during the trial ana-
lysis ( p&lt;0.001). Limitations of our study include the 
modified questionnaire being in part a retrospective 
HRQoL evaluation that should ideally have been con-
ducted within a shorter period of time. However, a cor-
relation to a prospective evaluation of the studied 
subjects has been made in our study in order to over-
come a possible recall bias. Therefore, we were able to 
minimise the number of retrospective questions, since 
the women were asked to recall their responses to each 
question at four different timepoints. The full SF-36 was 
impractical and may have been judged to be an exces-
sive burden on the women. Thus, we attempted to 
provide a retrospective form of validation by showing 
that the clinical HRQoL questions in the physical 
domain, recorded prospectively at week 4 after trial, 
were most strongly associated with the Physical 
Component Scales of the recall of modified SF-36 at 
week 4 compared to the other timepoints. This indicates 
that the retrospective methodology was able to provide 
an acceptable degree of accuracy in the differentiation 
of HRQoL levels at different timepoints despite the con-
cerns that may have arisen with this issue. The assump-
tion being made is that the way those patients judge 
their physical and mental condition will be relatively 
stable over time, 
18 an assumption with which we agree 
may occur in patients with chronic diseases. However, 
this assumption may not hold for women during and 
after pregnancy. The expectations by the woman about 
how she should be feeling at the different stages of preg-
nancy, around the time of delivery, and when she is 
caring for one or more young infant or child may differ 
substantially at those different timepoints. At least in our 
analysis, the judgement the woman is making about how 
to answer the questions is likely to be the same for each 
timepoint, since she had made that judgement at one 
point in time: the repeated measures analysis compares 
each woman with herself, thus substantially reducing the 
impact of variation between women in this judgement. </p>

<p>Thus, for the purpose of generating a hypothesis con-
cerning iron status and quality of life, we believe that 
our methodology has been adequate. Another limitation 
of our study is the relatively small number of women 
studied. Nevertheless, prior to our study there was a lack 
of research that addressed HRQoL during and after 
pregnancy, and particularly the association between iron 
status and postnatal clinical depression as well as breast-
feeding duration in our cohort of patients provides a 
novel finding and a basis for further research. 
An incidental finding of our study was a trend for 
unfavourable mental health component outcomes for 
women with male babies. There is only a single report in 
the literature that addressed this issue and reported 
similar findings. 
19 Perhaps this may be explained with 
the observation that male babies are usually more active, 
and this may be associated with postnatal depression. </p>

<p>19   However, due to lack of more detailed data, this issue 
should be addressed separately and studied in future 
research. 
Owing to paucity of data regarding HRQoL during 
and after pregnancy, there are only limited data avail-
able from other studies. Jansen et al 
20 studied the effect 
of delivery and postpartum changes on the HRQoL. A 
cohort of 141 pregnant women were included in that 
study. HRQoL questionnaires were measuring the imme-
diate effect of delivery on the quality of life. The 
HRQoL questionnaires were conducted less than 1 day 
after vaginal delivery and less than 2 days after delivery 
by caesarean section and compared to 3-6 weeks postde-
livery for both groups. 
20 The study focused on patients' 
HRQoL recovery after both delivery interventions. In 
that study, 
20 the different timepoints of completion of 
the questionnaire (immediately postdelivery and 3-6 
weeks thereafter) may not necessarily reflect the HRQoL 
during pregnancy and subsequently after the post-
partum period. Furthermore, the immediate question-
naire after delivery and at 3-6 weeks time in the 
postpartum period may have been influenced, at least in 
theory, by the event of delivery, in particular when com-
plications occurred, as well as by the possible emotional </p>

<p>Table 4 Correlation between the physical symptom questions* from the prospective clinical monitoring questionnaire and the 
Physical Component Scale of the retrospective health-related quality of life (HRQoL) for the four time periods </p>

<p>Time 
Slope (SD) † 
OR ‡ 
95% CI 
p Value 
OR § 
95% CI 
p Value </p>

<p>Pretrial 
2.67 (13.0) † 
1.46 
(1.01 to 2.11) 
0.043 
1.00 
4 weeks 
8.07 (18.6) 
3.18 
(2.11 to 4.80) 
&lt;0.001 
2.18 
(1.44 to 3.28) 
&lt;0.001 
Delivery 
4.91 (12.2) 
2.14 
(1.37 to 3.35) 
&lt;0.001 
1.46 
(0.94 to 2.29) 
0.10 
Postdelivery 
4.31 (14.1) 
1.98 
(1.28 to 3.08) 
&lt;0.001 
1.36 
(0.88 to 2.10) 
0.17 </p>

<p>*The scores for four questions were combined as a single index: Do you have energy? Do you feel fatigued or sleepy? Do you feel 
light-headed (dizzy)? Do you feel short of breath? Responses: Not at all; A little of the time; Sometimes; Most of the time; Always. 
 †The slope (SD) of the association between the physical symptom questions from the clinical monitoring questionnaire and the Physical 
Component Scale of the HRQoL for the four time periods was estimated by repeated measures general linear modelling for illustrative 
purposes only (mean index score at pretrial was 74.3 of 100). 
 ‡The strength of the absolute association at each timepoint was compared to the pretrial timepoint and was estimated using repeated 
measures ordered logistic regression and expressed as OR (95% CIs; p values). 
 §The strength of the relative association at the other timepoints was compared to the pretrial timepoint and was estimated using repeated 
measures ordered logistic regression and expressed as OR (95% CIs; p values). </p>



<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000998 </p>

<p>Quality of life in pregnancy </p>

<p>and hormonal fluctuations during this period. It is 
worthwhile to note that the same study did not show any 
association between Hb and QoL; however, it did not 
investigate a possible effect of iron status on perceived 
HRQoL in conjunction with breastfeeding. This high-
lights our novel finding of the correlation between iron 
status and improved HRQoL during and after 
pregnancy. 
In summary, we found a significant improvement in 
the general health of women who received intravenous 
iron ( p&lt;0.001), but this effect was found prominently 
4 weeks after the intravenous iron treatment. The dur-
ation of breast-feeding was longer ( p=0.04) in those 
women who had received intravenous iron. Women with 
better iron status were less downhearted ( p=0.005) and 
less likely to develop postnatal clinical depression 
( p=0.003). 
Our results indicate that it is worthwhile considering 
Hb and iron status as a surrogate marker for assessment 
of women's well-being, not only during pregnancy, but 
also during the postnatal period. 
Further studies are warranted to confirm and extend 
our findings, and to determine outcomes in different 
populations with IDA in order to improve the estimates 
of the magnitude of the benefits of intravenous iron for 
the management of IDA. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Medicine and Clinical Haematology, Launceston General 
Hospital, Launceston, Tasmania, Australia </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Clinical School of Medicine, University of Tasmania, Launceston, Tasmania, 
Australia </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>School of Human Life Sciences, University of Tasmania, Launceston, 
Tasmania, Australia </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Launceston General Hospital, 
Launceston,Tasmania, Australia </p>

<p>Acknowledgements This research received a grant from the Clifford Craig 
Medical Research Trust, Launceston, Tasmania, Australia. The authors thank 
Professor Matthias Maiwald (KK Women's and Children's Hospital, Singapore) 
for helpful comments on the manuscript. The authors acknowledge the 
midwives and the Pharmacy Department at the Launceston General Hospital 
for their help in conducting the trial. </p>

<p>Contributors AAK is the principal investigator of the study who organised and 
coordinated all aspects of the research including all steps of the manuscript 
preparation. He is responsible for the study concept, design, recruitment of 
patients, writing, reviewing, editing and approving the manuscript in its final 
form as well as all aspects of the research. AD, KO, IR and MB contributed to 
study design, analysis and interpretation of data, and revised the manuscript. 
RC, JBB, JS and NB conducted the interviews with patients, collected the 
data, drafted the article and finally approved the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding Clifford Craig Medical Research Trust is a local community 
organisation in Tasmania, Australia that supports medical research by </p>

<p>providing monetary funds without interference in the research design or 
outcome. Clifford Craig Medical Trust Fund has no influence in the study 
design; subject, methods, data collection, analysis, interpretation of data; 
writing the research report or the decision to submit the manuscript for 
publication. The grant was used to support the research assistants. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The trial was approved by the state-wide Tasmanian Human 
Research Ethics Committee, Tasmania, Australia. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement There are no additional data available. </p>



<p>Khalafallah AA, Dennis AE, Ogden K, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000998. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000998 </p>



<p>Quality of life in pregnancy </p>

</text></tei>