<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3302911" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Study Design: Retrospective study. 
Purpose: To assess the feasibility and limitations of fracture risk assessment tool (FRAX) for osteoporotic vertebral fractures 
in the Korean population. 
Overview of Literature: The FRAX algorithm is country specific and uses clinical risk factor data to calculate an individual 
patient' s 10-year probability of hip fracture and 10-year probability of major osteoporotic fracture. However, it has not been 
adequately investigated for Korean. 
Methods: One hundred ninety four patients who had all risk factor data for the calculation of FRAX were divided into two 
groups depending on the existence of vertebral fractures: the fracture group was comprised of 88 patients and the non-
facture group comprised of 105 patients. We analyzed prediction of the fracture by applying respectively the Korean, Japanese, 
USA and UK model, and compared their FRAX results by calculating lumbar bone mineral density (BMD) instead of femoral 
neck BMD. 
Results: The prediction of vertebral fracture using FRAX was 10.9 ± 6.2% in the fracture group, 9.5 ± 5.5% of the non-
fracture group in the Korean model (p = 0.108); 17.9 ± 10.2% in the fracture group, 14.6 ± 9.0% in the non-fracture group 
in the Japanese model (p = 0.017). Only the Japanese model exhibited significant difference in vertebral fracture risk. The 
prediction of vertebral fracture using lumbar BMD instead of femoral neck BMD was 19.5 ± 12.1% in the fracture group, 
16.0 ± 10.3% in the non-fracture group in the Korean model ( p = 0.029). All models had statistically significant differences 
for the prediction of osteoporotic vertebral fracture. 
Conclusions: The 10-year probability of osteoporotic vertebral fracture had underestimation of the risk considering treatment 
eligibility based on the National Osteoporosis Foundation guidelines. BMD that accurately reflects the contribution of each 
result to fracture risk should be preferred for the prediction of fracture using FRAX, when lumbar spine and hi p BMD 
measurements are both performed for clinical purposes in Korean. </p>

<p>Osteoporotic fractures are common in the aging 
population and are associated with high morbidity, 
mortality, and loss of independence [1]. The World 
Health Organization (WHO) proposed the definition of </p>

<p>osteoporosis as bone mineral density (BMD) obtained 
using dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) that lies 2.5 
standard deviations (SD) or more below the mean value of 
young health women (T-score ≤ -2.5 SD). This definition 
has been accepted by most regulatory agencies globally 
and is being used as a cut-off to limit treatment access </p>

<p>FRAX for Prediction of Osteoporotic Vertebral Fractures / 23 </p>

<p>[2]. Although low BMD is a strong predictor of future 
fracture risks, other factors are also important. BMD alone 
is inadequate to identify individuals at risk for fracture [3]. 
Many people with fracture experience osteopenia rather 
than osteoporosis. Multiple risk factors define the unique 
risk profile for an individual. Family history of osteoporosis, 
personal history of fragility fracture as an adult, low body 
weight, and cigarette smoking are frequently mentioned for 
consideration in deciding whom to treat [4]. 
In 2008, the WHO Metabolic Disease Group focused 
on developing a fracture risk assessment tool (FRAX) 
using clinical risk factors based on femoral neck BMD 
to enhance fracture prediction. The FRAX algorithm is 
country specific and uses clinical risk factor data, with or 
without consideration of femoral neck BMD measurement, 
to calculate an individual patient's 10-year probability of 
hip fracture and 10-year probability of major osteoporotic 
fracture [5]. In addition, the National Osteoporosis 
Foundation (NOF) guidelines for treatment eligibility was 
changed to incorporate fracture history, BMD and 10-year 
fracture probability [6]. 
These new concepts are valuable as they include 
various clinical factors for the prediction of fracture risk. 
However, the WHO selected the femoral neck as the 
reference site for BMD, and fracture risk assessment based 
on large epidemiologic studies that have demonstrated 
its performance in fracture prediction, particularly for the 
assessment of hip fracture risk [7,8]. When BMD is included 
in FRAX calculations, femoral neck measurement must be 
used. Another BMD measurement sites can also be used for 
fracture risk assessment and for osteoporosis diagnosis [9], 
but they are not currently a component of FRAX. In Korea, 
BMD of the lumbar spine is being widely used clinically 
because the physical size of elderly Koreans is less than that 
of Westerners, giving rise to a view based on little evidence 
that the reproducibility of BMD measurements at the 
femoral neck would be poorer than that in the lumbar spine. 
The objective of this study was to assess the feasibility 
and limitations of FRAX for the risk assessment of 
osteoporotic vertebral fracture in Koreans, by comparing 
with prediction of osteoporotic vertebral fracture using 
FRAX tool by applying the Korean, Japanese, USA and UK 
models. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This was a retrospective study consisted of 194 patients </p>

<p>who underwent BMD measurement of both the lumbar 
spine and femoral neck, and possessed risk factors data 
for FRAX calculation from January 2008 to December 
2009. We divided patients into two groups, depending 
on existence of vertebral fracture: the fracture group 
was comprised of 88 patients and the non-facture group 
comprised of 106 patients. Fractures and other medical 
diagnoses were assessed through a combination of hospital 
discharge records (diagnoses and procedures coded using 
the KCD-5) and radiographs. 
The risk factors included age, height, body weight, 
previous fragility fracture as an adult, family history of 
osteoporosis (parent with hip fracture), current smoking, 
corticosteroid use, rheumatoid arthritis, secondary 
osteoporosis (e.g., type 1 diabetes, osteogenesis imperfecta 
in adults, untreated long-standing hypothyroidism and 
hypogonadism or premature menopause), and alcohol 
intake of more than 3 units daily. Prior fragility fracture 
was defined as a major osteoporotic fracture prior to BMD 
testing. A diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis was taken 
from clinic visits and/or hospitalizations with a relevant 
KCD-5 code in a 3-year period prior to BMD evaluation. 
Prolonged corticosteroid use was defined as over 90 days of 
medication dispended in the year prior to BMD evaluation, 
at a mean prednisolone-equivalent dose of 7.5 mg per 
day or greater. Weight and height were recorded at the 
time of DXA evaluation. This study was approved by the 
Institutional Review Board. 
The mean age of patients was 70.2 years (range, 21 to 
91 years); the mean age of the fracture group was 71.8 
years (range, 21 to 88 years) and the mean age of the non-
fracture group was 69 years (range, 41 to 91 years). Total 
male-female ratio was 25 vs. 169, male-female ratio of the 
fracture group was 17 vs. 71, male-female ratio of the non-
fracture group was 8 vs. 98, respectively. The fracture group 
had 13 cases of previous vertebral fracture and 10 cases 
of other previous fractures. The non-fracture group had 1 
case of previous vertebral fracture, 2 cases of previous hip 
fracture and 17 cases of other previous facture (Table 1). 
The 10-year probability of hip and major osteoporotic 
fractures were compared to the results of FRAX applied to 
the Korean, Japanese, USA and UK models by the WHO 
Collaborating Centre with femoral neck BMD. We analyzed 
the results of FRAX by calculating lumbar BMD instead of 
femoral neck BMD. It was hypothesized that the difference 
between the lumbar spine and the femoral neck T-scores 
would provide an indication of whether fracture risk was </p>

<p>24 / ASJ: Vol. 6, No. 1, 2012 </p>

<p>higher or lower than the risk predicted from the femoral 
neck alone. DXA scans were performed and analyzed in 
accordance with the manufacturer's recommendations 
(Explorer, Hologic Co., Bedford, MA, USA). Hip T-scores 
(number of SDs above or below young adult mean BMD) 
were calculated from Japanese reference values. No 
comparable international reference standard exists for 
the lumbar spine, and T-scores were calculated using the 
manufacturer's Japanese female reference values. Vertebral 
levels affected by artifacts were excluded by experienced 
physicians using conventional criteria [10]. 
All results are expressed as mean ± SD unless otherwise 
stated. We performed risk factor analysis for vertebral 
fracture using logistic regression model. Group comparisons 
for BMD were conducted with the Student t-test. FRAX </p>

<p>prediction of vertebral fracture and hip fracture using 
femoral neck BMD in the Korean, Japanese, USA and UK 
models were assessed using the ANOVA methods. FRAX 
prediction of vertebral fracture using lumbar spine BMD in 
the Korean, Japanese, USA and UK models were assessed 
using the ANOVA methods. Each result was analyzed using 
the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 12.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) and a p &lt; 
0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The lumbar BMD (odds ratio [OR], 0.578; p = 0.001), 
smoking (OR, 14.820; p = 0.001), body weight (OR, 0.943; 
p = 0.008), corticosteroids use (OR, 19.972; p = 0.029) were 
significantly associated with osteoporotic vertebral fracture. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The 10-years probability of hip fracture by Korean, Japanese, USA and UK models of fracture risk 
assessment tool (FRAX) using femoral neck bone mineral density in both groups. </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of the 194 participants </p>

<p>Non-fracture group 
Fracture group 
Total </p>

<p>Sex (male/female) 
8/98 
17/71 
25/169 </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
69 
71.8 
70.2 </p>

<p>Height (cm) 
158.5 
158.5 
158.5 </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
55.97 
54.03 
55.67 
Previous fracture history 
(vertebral fracture/hip fracture/others/non) 
1/2/17/86 
13/0/10/66 
14/2/27/152 </p>

<p>Parents fracture history (yes/no) 
8/98 
1/87 
9/185 </p>

<p>Smoking: current (yes/no) 
3/103 
12/76 
15/179 </p>

<p>Alcohol: &gt;3 units daily (yes/no) 
2/104 
5/83 
7/187 </p>

<p>Glucocorticoid 
1 
8 
9 </p>

<p>Rhematoid arthritis 
5 
2 
7 </p>

<p>Secondary osteoporosis 
6 
7 
13 </p>

<p>Femoral neck T-score 
-2.2 
-2.6 
-2.4 </p>

<p>Lumbar spine T-score 
-3.06 
-3.6 
-3.3 </p>

<p>FRAX for Prediction of Osteoporotic Vertebral Fractures / 25 </p>

<p>The mean femoral neck BMD was -2.5 ± 0.9 in the fracture 
group, and -2.2 ± 0.7 in the non-fracture group (p = 0.005). 
The mean lumbar BMD was -3.6 ± 1.1 in the fracture 
group, and -3.0 ± 0.9 in the non-fracture group (p = 0.001). 
The prediction of hip fracture using FRAX was 5.4 ± 4.2% 
in the fracture group, 4.0 ± 4.2% in the non-fracture group 
in the Korean model (p = 0.022); 7.2 ± 6.2% in the fracture 
group, 5.0 ± 6.0% in the non-fracture group in the Japanese 
model (p = 0.013); 7.7 ± 6.1% in the fracture group, 5.7 
± 7.2% in the non-fracture group in the USA model (p = 
0.041); 7.3 ± 5.5% in the fracture group, 5.3 ± 5.6% in the 
non-fracture group in the UK model (p = 0.014) (Fig. 1). 
However, the prediction of vertebral fracture using FRAX 
was 10.9 ± 6.2% in the fracture group, 9.5 ± 5.5% in the 
non-fracture group in the Korean model (p = 0.108); 17.9 ± 
10.2% in the fracture group, 14.6 ± 9.0% in the non-fracture 
group in Japanese model (p = 0.017); 18.7 ± 9.5% in the </p>

<p>fracture group, 17.0 ± 10.4% in the non-fracture group in 
USA model (p = 0.232); 16.4 ± 8.5% in the fracture group, 
14.5 ± 8.0% in the non-fracture group in UK model (p = 
0.110) (Fig. 2). In contrast to the prediction of hip fracture, 
the risk of vertebral fracture was underestimated considering 
the eligibility of osteoporosis treatment, particularly with 
the Korean model. 
The prediction of vertebral fracture using lumbar BMD 
instead of femoral neck BMD was 19.5 ± 12.1% in the 
fracture group, 16.0 ± 10.3% in the non-fracture group 
in the Korean model (p = 0.029). All models exhibited 
statistically significant differences for the prediction of 
osteoporotic vertebral fracture (Fig. 3). Lumbar BMD offers 
better prediction of vertebral fracture risk than femoral neck 
BMD when considering treatment eligibility based on the 
NOF guidelines. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The 10-years probability of vertebral fracture by the Korean, Japanese, USA and UK model of fracture 
risk assessment tool (FRAX) using lumbar spine bone mineral density in both groups. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The 10-years probability of vertebral fracture by the Korean, Japanese, USA and UK models of 
fracture risk assessment tool (FRAX) using femoral neck bone mineral density in both groups. In contrast to 
the prediction of hip fracture, the risk of vertebral fracture was underestimated considering the eligibility of 
osteoporosis treatment, particularly the Korean model. </p>

<p>26 / ASJ: Vol. 6, No. 1, 2012 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The FRAX established by WHO was developed by 
incorporating the major risk factors of osteoporotic fracture 
based on the results of 9 cohort studies, and calculating 
the interaction between femoral neck BMD and each 
major risk factor [11]. These cohort studies included about 
60,000 people. There were 5,563 fractures during research, 
including 978 hip fractures. The effect of each fracture 
risk factor was analyzed by using the Poisson regression 
model. The FRAX was based on the relative risk of major 
osteoporotic fractures calculated between each clinical risk 
factor. The positive aspects of FRAX include conversion 
of relative risk into absolute or real risk, including various 
risk factors, unlike DXA using BMD as threshold for 
osteoporosis medical intervention. The risk factors in 
FRAX include age, body mass index, previous fracture or 
fragility as an adult, family history of osteoporosis (parent 
with hip fracture), current smoking, corticosteroid use, 
rheumatoid arthritis, secondary osteoporosis and alcohol 
intake more than 3 units daily. However, it is important 
to define the intervention and assessment thresholds of 
fracture frequency, mortality, cost of treatment and efficacy 
of treatment on a country-by-country basis [12]. Also, 
the lumbar spine BMD is not currently part of the FRAX 
formulation but is being widely used in clinical practice and 
this creates confusion when there is spine-hip discordance 
[13]. Therefore, we analyzed the difference between the 
Korean model and the others, and the results between 
lumbar BMD and femoral neck BMD. 
The new NOF guidelines recommended that medical 
therapy be considered in postmenopausal women and men 
aged 50 years and above, who met any of the following 
criteria: 1) sustained a self-reported hip or spine fracture 
after age 20 years; 2) had a femoral neck or spine BMD 
T-score ≤ -2.5; 3) had a femoral neck T-score between -1 
and -2.5 SD, with a 10-year hip fracture probability ≥ 3% or 
major fracture (humerus, forearm, hip or clinical vertebral 
fracture) probability ≥ 20% [6]. The new NOF guidelines 
are difficult to apply in all countries. The guidelines are 
based on cost-effectiveness that produce 35% prevention 
rate for 5 years according to frequency, mortality and 
morbidity in the USA [14]. However, the incidence of 
vertebral fractures in the prospective cohorts was higher 
than that predicted by FRAX, showing a limitation of 
FRAX in clinical application. Fujiwara et al. [15] reported 
the absolute risk for major osteoporotic fractures was </p>

<p>underestimated in the Japanese population, compared to 
Caucasians. As such, they recommended modification of the 
treatment threshold from 20% to 10% [15]. Recently, the 
Japanese committee recommended a cut-off value of 15% 
on FRAX as treatment threshold for major osteoporotic 
fractures in osteopenic patients [16]. Therefore, direct 
application of the NOF guidelines in Korea is inappropriate, 
and the guideline should be adjusted according to the socio-
economic model of each country. In our study, vertebral 
fracture risks using FRAX was underestimated in the 
vertebral fracture group as 10.9% (Fig. 2), as to the results 
the guideline of treatment should changed to 10-15%. 
Lumbar spine BMD is routinely performed in clinical 
practice both for baseline risk assessment and for monitering 
purposes. However, the WHO selected the femoral neck as 
the reference site for BMD [17,18]. When BMD is included 
in the FRAX calculation, femoral neck measurement 
must be used. Kanis et al. [19] presented that there were 
significant correlation between bone mineral measurements 
made at one site compared with another, but this correlation 
was decreased as increasing bone loss by aging. Woodson 
[20] found 38% of the time minor discordance and 3% 
of the time major discordance in analyzing 2,547 cases 
of lumbar and femoral neck BMD. Feyerabend and Lear 
[21] reported that only 50% of patient has matched results 
between lumbar and femoral neck BMD. When confronted 
with highly discordant results such as lumbar spine worse 
than femoral neck, clinicians are in a quandary about how 
this should be integrated into the decision-making process. 
Under some guidelines such as those from the NOF, 
treatment would be recommended for lumbar spine T-score 
in the osteoporotic range regardless of the estimated risk 
[22]. Where lumbar spine and hip BMD measurements are 
both performed for clinical purposes, BMD that accurately 
reflects the contribution of each result to fracture risk 
should be clearly preferred. Other limitation of FRAX 
was that the patients who had previous vertebral fracture 
can not be predicted the increased fracture risk. In case of 
asymptomatic vertebral fracture, the body mass index was 
increased as height was decreased, the risk of vertebral 
fracture may be lower estimated. The bone loss was begun 
in lumbar vertebra initially in almost menopausal women 
because lumbar vertebra had relatively more trabecular 
bone [23]. So the T-score of lumbar BMD was lower than 
the T-score of femoral neck BMD. Therefore low energy 
osteoporotic fracture was more frequent in thoracolumbar 
vertebra. In this study lumbar BMD was lower than </p>

<p>FRAX for Prediction of Osteoporotic Vertebral Fractures / 27 </p>

<p>femoral BMD. On comparison with FRAX model between 
lumbar BMD and femoral neck BMD, vertebral fracture 
probability using lumbar BMD was increased especially 
in Korean model. The results revealed that lumbar BMD 
was more suitable than femoral neck BMD for assessment 
of osteoporotic vertebral fracture using FRAX. This study 
was limited by selection bias. Patients were recruited at 
one center and the nature of this study was retrospective 
and not prospective, performed after assessment of fracture 
risk using FRAX, calculation of major osteoporotic 
fracture as risk of vertebral fracture, and the potential for 
interactions between lumbar spine BMD and other risk 
factors, including relatively small number of men. Further 
investigations are needed to clarify the cut-off thresholds 
of vertebral fractures, and the application of lumbar spine 
BMD for FRAX calculation by appropriate assessment of 
vertebral fracture probability using FRAX in a large cohort 
study. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The 10-year probability of osteoporotic vertebral fracture 
had underestimation of the risk considering treatment 
eligibility based on the NOF guidelines. Treatment 
guidelines with reference to FRAX prediction of major 
osteoporotic fractures should be adjusted to 10-15%, and 
BMD that accurately reflects the contribution of each result 
on fracture risk should be preferred for the prediction of 
fracture using FRAX when lumbar spine and hip BMD 
measurements are both performed for clinical purposes in 
Korean. </p>



</text></tei>