<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3230829" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The Health Protection Agency recorded 49 880 
laboratory-confirmed cases of infectious intestinal 
disease (IID) due to Campylobacter and 9885 cases of </p>

<p>non-typhoidal salmonellosis in England and Wales 
in 2008 </p>

<p>1 2   ; rotavirus and norovirus accounted for 
13 935 and 6828 reports, respectively. 
3 4 Most IID is 
self-limiting, requiring no clinical intervention, but 
commonly causes high levels of healthcare usage 
and absenteeism. 
5 Organisms such as verocyto-
toxin-producing Escherichia coli (VTEC) and 
Campylobacter are also associated with long-term, </p>

<p>&lt; An additional appendix is 
published online only. To view 
this file please visit the journal 
online (http://gut.bmj.com). </p>

<p>For numbered affiliations see 
end of article. </p>

<p>Correspondence to 
Dr Clarence C Tam, Department 
of Infectious Disease 
Epidemiology, Faculty of 
Epidemiology and Population 
Health, London School of 
Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, 
London WC1E 7HT, UK; 
clarence.tam@lshtm.ac.uk </p>

<p>Data from the IID2 study will be 
archived and made available 
publicly in due course. 
*Members are: Bob Adak, Eric 
Bolton, Paul Cook (Chair), John 
Cowden, Meirion Evans, Jim 
Gray, Paul Hunter, Louise Letley, 
Jim McLauchlin, Keith Neal, 
Sarah O'Brien, Greta Rait, Laura 
Rodrigues, Gillian Smith, Brian 
Smyth and David Tompkins. </p>

<p>Revised 23 May 2011 
Accepted 25 May 2011 
Published Online First 
27 June 2011 </p>

<p>This paper is freely available 
online under the BMJ Journals 
unlocked scheme, see http:// 
gut.bmj.com/site/about/ 
unlocked.xhtml </p>

<p>Significance of this study </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject? </p>

<p>&lt; Infectious intestinal disease (IID) is a common 
cause of illness in the community and results in 
a high burden of consultations to general 
practice (GP). 
&lt; Most cases of IID are not reported to national 
surveillance systems, making it difficult to 
determine the true burden in the population. 
&lt; Recent interventions and changes in healthcare 
delivery may have resulted in changes in 
disease burden in the community and presenting 
to primary care; population-based studies are 
needed to monitor such changes. </p>

<p>What are the new findings? </p>

<p>&lt; In the UK, there are up to 17 million cases and 1 
million GP consultations due to IID every year. 
&lt; Although IID incidence in the community 
appears to have increased since the 1990s, 
consultations to GP have halved. 
&lt; Norovirus is the most common recognised 
cause of IID, accounting for 3 million cases 
and 130 000 GP consultations annually, while 
Clostridium difficile, an important pathogen in 
healthcare settings, is a rare cause of diarrhoea 
in the community. </p>

<p>How might it impact on clinical practice in the 
foreseeable future? </p>

<p>&lt; Use of recently introduced telephone advice 
services such as NHS Direct is relatively low 
and has little impact on the burden of GP 
consultations for IID. Instead, changes in health-
care use are likely to be behind the decreasing 
trend in IID-related GP consultations. </p>

<p>Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>
Intestinal infections </p>

<p>potentially fatal sequelae, including haemolytic uraemic 
syndrome 
6 and GuillaineBarré syndrome. </p>

<p>7   National statistics underestimate the incidence, because only 
a fraction of IID presents to health services, and many 
presenting cases are not investigated further. Reported cases are 
not a random subset of all cases, as seeking healthcare is related 
to greater disease severity, recent foreign travel and lower 
socioeconomic status. 
8 National statistics can be useful for 
monitoring trends, but difficult to interpret if there are secular 
changes in healthcare-seeking behaviour, faecal sampling, 
diagnostic procedures or surveillance methods. Evaluating 
control strategies requires accurately estimating population 
burden and understanding the relationship between national 
statistics and disease incidence. 
In its first 5 years of operation the UK, Food Standards Agency 
was tasked with reducing food-borne illness by 20%. 
9 The 
Second Study of IID in the UK (IID2 Study) was commissioned 
to assess progress towards this target and determine whether 
changes in healthcare provision might influence the 
interpretation of national statistics. 
We present results from the IID2 Study, a multicentre longi-
tudinal study to estimate the current incidence of IID in the 
community, presenting to general practice (GP) and reported to 
national surveillance. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>The IID2 Study methods are detailed elsewhere. 
10 Briefly, we 
conducted the study between 28 April 2008 and 31 August 2009 
in a population of 800 000 people served by 88 UK GPs. We 
recruited practices from the Medical Research Council General 
Practice Research Framework and Primary Care Research 
Networks in England, Northern Ireland and Scotland. The 
number of practices in the four UK countries was proportional 
to population size. The study comprised a population cohort, 
a GP presentation study and a national surveillance study. </p>

<p>Population cohort study </p>

<p>We followed up participants from 88 practices weekly for 
symptoms of diarrhoea and/or vomiting for up to 52 weeks, 
recruiting throughout the study period. From each practice list, 
we invited randomly selected individuals to a recruitment 
interview with the practice study nurse. People were eligible if 
they did not have: a terminal illness or severe mental incapacity; 
a recognised, non-infectious cause of diarrhoea or vomiting 
(precluding determination of onset date and infectious 
aetiology), such as Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis, cystic 
fibrosis or coeliac disease; or a surgical obstruction. Non-English 
speakers were also excluded. 
We asked participants to report weekly, by email or prepaid 
postcard, whether or not they had experienced diarrhoea and/or 
vomiting. We asked those reporting symptoms to complete 
a case questionnaire, enquiring about type and duration of 
symptoms, healthcare usage and recent travel, and to submit 
a stool specimen for microbiological examination. We asked 
them not to report symptoms related to excess alcohol, morning 
sickness or, among infants, regurgitation. </p>

<p>GP presentation study </p>

<p>In 37 of the 88 participating practices, we asked GPs to refer to 
the study nurse all patients presenting with IID. The nurse 
administered a case questionnaire and requested a stool 
specimen. To assess the degree of under-ascertainment of IID 
cases in this study (ie, the proportion of all IID cases actually 
referred and recruited to the study), study nurses searched the </p>

<p>computerised practice records monthly, using a predefined list of 
diagnostic Read codes, 
11 to identify all IID-related consultations. </p>

<p>National surveillance study </p>

<p>We obtained records of IID cases reported in each UK country 
over the study period, by organism, from the UK national 
surveillance centres. Data on sapovirus and non-O157 VTEC 
were not available, because they are not routinely reported. We 
excluded national C difficile reports because these are mostly 
from healthcare settings rather than the community. </p>

<p>NHS direct usage </p>

<p>We obtained the number of telephone consultations to NHS 
Direct (England only) for diarrhoea and vomiting during the 
study period from the Health Protection Agency Birmingham 
Regional Surveillance Unit. </p>

<p>Ethics approval </p>

<p>All participants gave signed, informed consent. The North West 
Research Ethics Committee granted a favourable ethics opinion 
(07/MRE08/5), and 37 NHS Research Management and Gover-
nance organisations for the 88 practices approved the study. </p>

<p>Case definitions </p>

<p>Definite IID was defined as loose stools or clinically significant 
vomiting lasting less than 2 weeks, in the absence of a known 
non-infectious cause, preceded by a symptom-free period of 
3 weeks. Vomiting was clinically significant if it occurred more 
than once in a 24 h period and if it incapacitated the patient or 
was accompanied by other symptoms such as cramps or 
fever. 
10 12 Symptomatic people not meeting the case definition 
because they did not provide a questionnaire or because 
symptom information was missing were considered possible 
IID cases. Cases in which the patient reported travel outside 
the UK in the 10 days before illness onset were excluded. </p>

<p>Microbiological analysis </p>

<p>First, all stool samples were cultured for Campylobacter jejuni/coli, 
E coli O157, Listeria monocytogenes, Salmonella spp., Shigella spp. 
and Yersinia spp. They were also examined by ELISA for Clos-
tridium perfringens enterotoxin, C difficile cytotoxins A and B, 
Cryptosporidium and Giardia, by a commercial PCR test 
(Cepheid) for C difficile, and by light microscopic examination of 
a stained smear for Cyclospora and Cryptosporidium. Samples that 
were immunoassay positive for C difficile toxin or PCR-positive 
were cultured using National Standard Method BSOP 10, and all 
isolates were ribotyped. 
13 Samples from children under 5 years 
were examined for rotavirus and adenovirus 40/41 by 
immunoassay. 
Next, two nucleic acid extracts were prepared from each stool 
sample. 
14e16 Each extract was examined by real-time PCR for C 
jejuni, C coli, L monocytogenes, Salmonella spp., rotavirus, noro-
virus, sapovirus, adenovirus, astrovirus, Cryptosporidium, Giardia 
and E coli (enteroaggregative and VTEC (genes encoding VT1 
and VT2)). 
Further information on microbiological methods has been 
published elsewhere. 
10 For quantitative PCR assays, a cycle 
threshold value &lt;40 was considered positive for most organisms, 
with two exceptions: a cycle threshold cut-off value &lt;30 was 
used to define clinically significant norovirus and rotavirus 
infection. </p>

<p>17 18   In this study, C difficile-associated diarrhoea (CDAD) was 
defined as symptoms of diarrhoea not attributable to another </p>

<p> 
Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>Intestinal infections </p>

<p>cause (ie, in the absence of other enteropathogens), but with 
a positive C difficile toxin assay, in a patient aged &gt;2 years. </p>

<p>19   Data analysis </p>

<p>We calculated incidence rates of IID with 95% CIs, overall and 
by organism. In the cohort study, the denominator was the total 
person-years at risk among cohort participants. Individuals 
could contribute multiple episodes of illness. We omitted the 
first 3 weeks of follow-up to exclude prevalent cases. Participants 
were followed-up until the 52nd week, or 31 August 2009, or 
until they dropped out or withdrew for other reasons, whichever 
occurred earliest. People were 'dropped out' after four consecu-
tive non-response weeks. 
In the GP presentation study, the denominator in each prac-
tice was the practice population on 31 December 2008 
multiplied by the time the practice was in the study. For the 
national surveillance component, the denominator was the UK 
midyear population at the 2001 census. For the NHS Direct 
component, the mid-2001 England population was used. </p>

<p>Statistical adjustments </p>

<p>We standardised rates in the cohort study to the UK census age 
and sex population structure. We adjusted rates in the GP 
presentation study by an under-ascertainment factor repre-
senting the ratio of all cases identified in the practice records to 
actual cases recruited. We obtained the under-ascertainment 
factors from a two-level logistic regression model using age 
group, sex, Read code category, and a random intercept for GP 
practice to predict the probability of a case being recruited. We 
grouped the Read codes assigned to each consultation into seven 
categories: diarrhoea; vomiting; diarrhoea and vomiting; 
gastroenteritis; organism-specific codes; codes indicating that 
a stool sample was sent for analysis; and codes for symptoms 
compatible with IID, for example, 'gastrointestinal symptoms'. 
We used the inverse of the predicted ascertainment probabilities </p>

<p>obtained from the model as under-ascertainment factors in the 
incidence calculations. 
CIs accounted for clustering of observations within individ-
uals (cohort study) and within practices (GP presentation 
study). </p>

<p>Imputation of specimen data </p>

<p>We used multiple imputation by chained equations 
20 to account 
for missing organism data in participants who did not submit 
a specimen. We developed separate imputation models for cases 
in the cohort and GP presentation studies. For each organism, 
the imputation model included age group, sex and presence or 
absence of five symptoms (diarrhoea, bloody diarrhoea, 
vomiting, abdominal pain and fever) as covariates. Overall, we 
imputed values for 35% of records in the cohort study and 11% 
of records in the GP presentation study. We combined results 
from analysis of 20 imputed datasets to produce a point 
estimate for the rate and 95% CI, accounting for uncertainty in 
the observed rate and the imputation process. </p>

<p>Reporting ratios </p>

<p>We calculated rate ratios comparing rates in the community, 
presenting to the GP and reported to national surveillance. We 
assumed that the rates came from a log-normal distribution 
with the observed mean and SD. The rate ratios were estimated 
by simulating 100 000 random draws from each pair of rate 
distributions. We took the median, 2.5th and 97.5th centiles of 
the resulting RR distribution as the point estimate and lower 
and upper 95% confidence limits. 
Finally, we applied the estimated rates to the mid-2009 UK 
population estimate to calculate the annual number of cases and 
GP consultations associated with each organism. 
Multiple imputation was conducted in <rs id="software-1" type="software">R</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2.11</rs>. Analysis of 
under-ascertainment and analysis of imputed data were 
performed using the glamm 
21 and mi 
22 modules in <rs id="software-2" type="software">Stata</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">11</rs>, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Recruitment in the cohort 
study, Infectious Intestinal Disease 2 
Study, UK 2008e9. </p>

<p>Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>
Intestinal infections </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Participation </p>

<p>Of 77 995 people invited in the cohort study, 8336 (10.5%) 
responded positively and 7033 were recruited (9.0%) (figure 1). 
Some people recruited near the study end date had no eligible 
follow-up time (n¼184), and two people withdrew consent. We 
analysed data from 6836 participants. Compared with the 2001 
census population, cohort participants were more likely to be 
older, female, employed in managerial and professional occupa-
tions, less deprived and in rural areas (online appendix 1). The 
median follow-up duration was 39 weeks (IQR 27e45 weeks); 
overall, 86% of the maximum achievable follow-up time to 31 
August 2009 was completed. Six hundred and ten (9.5%) 
participants dropped out, accounting for 219 (4.5%) lost person-
years of follow-up. 
In the GP presentation study, 2233 eligible symptomatic 
patients were referred and 2203 invited to participate. A total of 
1392 people (63.2%) responded positively, and 1254 (56.9%) 
were recruited (figure 2). We excluded 140 people reporting 
recent foreign travel, 77 with illness lasting over 2 weeks, and 46 
because of missing or inconsistent information on symptoms 
and/or travel. Ultimately, we analysed data from 991 cases. </p>

<p>Rate of overall IID </p>

<p>There were 4658 person-years of follow-up and 1201 definite IID 
cases in the cohort. The crude IID incidence rate was 258 cases 
per 1000 person-years. The age-and sex-standardised rate was 
274 cases per 1000 person-years (95% CI 254 to 296). When both 
definite and possible cases were considered, this rose to 523 cases 
per 1000 person-years (95% CI 497 to 551). There was little 
evidence that rates varied by socioeconomic characteristics or 
between urban and rural areas (data not shown). 
In the under-ascertainment analysis, approximately one case 
was recruited into the GP presentation study for every six 
identified in the medical records, although this varied by age 
group, Read code category and practice. After adjustment for 
under-ascertainment, there were 5546 IID cases and 312 232 
person-years of follow-up, yielding a consultation rate of 17.7 
per 1000 person-years (95% CI 14.4 to 21.8). This was lower </p>

<p>than that estimated from definite cases in the cohort who 
reported consulting their GP for their illness (25.3 cases per 1000 
person-years, 95% CI 20.7 to 31.3). The age-specific rates of GP 
consultation in the two studies were similar except for young 
children and older adults (figure 3). Among children &lt;5 years, 
the rate was 133 consultations per 1000 person-years in the 
cohort study (95% CI 92 to 199) and 85 consultations per 1000 
person-years in the GP presentation study (95% CI 59 to 122), 
while among those aged 65 and over, the corresponding rates 
were 30 consultations per 1000 person-years (95% CI 22 to 42) 
and 20 consultations per 1000 person-years (95% CI 15 to 27), 
respectively. 
Call rates to NHS Direct in England for diarrhoea and 
vomiting were 6.1 per 1000 person-years, similar to that esti-
mated from cohort study patients in England who reported 
contacting NHS Direct for their illness (5.5 per 1000 person-
years, 95% CI 3.4 to 9.5). </p>

<p>Rates of IID by organism </p>

<p>Rates of IID by organism in the community, presenting to the 
GP and reported to national surveillance are shown in table 1. 
For organisms tested by more than one method, rate estimates 
are presented separately for routine diagnostic methods and for 
routine and PCR methods combined. </p>

<p>Rates in the community </p>

<p>Viruses predominated among IID cases in the community: the 
estimated rates (cases per 1000 person-years) were 47 for noro-
virus, 26 for sapovirus, 13 for rotavirus and 10 for adenovirus. 
The most common bacteria were Campylobacter (11 cases per 
1000 person-years) and enteroaggregative E coli (six cases per 
1000 person-years). The Salmonella rate was less than one case 
per 1000 person-years. Based on ELISA, Cryptosporidium and 
Giardia rates were around one case per 1000 person-years, 
although PCR-based estimates were slightly higher. 
E coli O157 was present in only one sample, and there were no 
cases of CDAD or L monocytogenes IID in the community cohort. </p>

<p>GP presentation rates </p>

<p>Norovirus was the most common organism among cases 
presenting to the GP (two consultations per 1000 person-years 
(table 1)); approximately one in every 23 people with norovirus 
IID consulted a GP. Rotavirus and sapovirus were also common 
(w1.5 consultations per 1000 person-years). One in seven 
patients with campylobacteriosis consulted their GP, resulting in 
approximately one consultation per 1000 person-years based on 
culture diagnostics. Other organisms occurred at rates of less 
than one consultation per 1000 person-years. Salmonellosis was 
uncommon (&lt;0.2 consultations per 1000 person-years), 
although one in three patients consulted their GP. 
Only one case of CDAD occurred in the GP presentation 
study, and no cases of L monocytogenes IID were identified. </p>

<p>Ratios to national surveillance </p>

<p>Table 2 presents, by organism, the rates of IID in the community 
and presenting to GP, and the ratios of these rates to those 
estimated from national surveillance data. Figures 4 and 5 
illustrate reporting patterns for all IID and for the four major 
pathogens, Campylobacter, Salmonella, norovirus and rotavirus. In 
each diagram, the rates in the community, presenting to GP and 
reported to national surveillance are represented as ellipses, with 
the area of each ellipse proportional to the rate. 
The ratios of community and GP presentation rates to 
national surveillance rates were much higher for viruses than for </p>

<p>Figure 2 Recruitment in the general practice presentation study, 
Infectious Intestinal Disease (IID) 2 Study, UK 2008e9. </p>

<p> 
Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>Intestinal infections </p>

<p>bacteria and protozoa. For every national surveillance case of 
norovirus IID, there were 12.7 GP consultations (95% CI 8.8 to 
18.3) and 288 community cases (95% CI 239 to 346). The 
corresponding ratios for rotavirus were one in five (95% CI 
3 to 7) and one in 43 (95% CI 30 to 62). By contrast, for every 
national surveillance case of campylobacteriosis, there were 
1.3 GP consultations (95% CI 0.9 to 1.8) and 9.3 community 
cases (95% CI 6.0 to 14.4). For Salmonella, the corresponding 
ratios were 1.4 GP consultations (95% CI 0.6 to 3.3) and 
approximately five community cases (95% CI 1.2 to 18.2). 
Among the protozoa, 2.3 GP consultations (95% CI 1.0 to 5.6) 
and 8.2 (95% CI 2.1 to 31.7) community cases occurred for every 
case of cryptosporidiosis reported to national surveillance. The </p>

<p>corresponding figures for giardiasis were somewhat higher, 
although there was considerable uncertainty in the estimates. </p>

<p>Estimated annual cases and GP presentations </p>

<p>In 2009, there were approximately 16.9 million cases of IID and 
over 1 million IID-related GP consultations. Campylobacter 
accounted for over 500 000 cases and approximately 80 000 GP 
consultations (table 3). Norovirus caused nearly three million 
sporadic (non-outbreak-related) IID cases and approximately 
130 000 GP consultations. The burden from sapovirus was also 
considerable, with an estimated 1.6 million sporadic cases and 
nearly 100 000 GP consultations, while rotavirus caused more 
than 750 000 cases and 80 000 GP consultations. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Age-specific rates of 
infectious intestinal disease general 
practice (GP) consultationsdestimates 
from the cohort and general practice 
presentation studies, Infectious 
Intestinal Disease 2 Study, UK 2008e9. </p>

<p>Table 1 Incidence rates of infectious intestinal disease in the community and presenting to general practice by organism, Infectious Intestinal 
Disease 2 Study, UK 2008e9 </p>

<p>Organism 
Test methods </p>

<p>Community 
Presenting to GP 
Ratio community/GP 
Cases* 
PYy 
Ratez (95% CI) 
Cases* 
PYy 
Ratez (95% CI) 
RR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Bacteria 
C perfringens 
A 
7 
4658.6 
1.5 (0.5 to 3.9) 
78 
312 232 
0.24 (0.11 to 0.52) 
6.0 (1.7 to 20.9) 
Campylobacter spp. 
A 
43 
4658.6 
9.3 (6 to 14.3) 
400 
312 232 
1.28 (0.90 to 1.82) 
7.2 (4.1 to 12.7) 
E 
51 
4658.6 
10.9 (7.4 to 15.9) 
693 
312 232 
2.22 (1.65 to 2.97) 
4.9 (3 to 7.9) 
E coli O157 (VTEC) 
A 
1 
4658.6 
0.3 (0 to 4.3) 
4 
312 232 
0.01 (0.00 to 0.09) 
22.8 (0.9 to 610) 
Enteroaggregative E coli 
D 
28 
4658.6 
5.9 (3.4 to 10.2) 
66 
312 232 
0.21 (0.11 to 0.41) 
28.4 (11.8 to 68.2) 
Salmonella spp. 
A 
3 
4658.6 
0.6 (0.2 to 2.4) 
57 
312 232 
0.18 (0.08 to 0.44) 
3.4 (0.7 to 17.4) 
E 
3 
4658.6 
0.6 (0.2 to 2.4) 
56 
312 232 
0.18 (0.07 to 0.44) 
3.5 (0.7 to 17.9) 
Protozoa 
Cryptosporidium 
B 
3 
4658.6 
0.7 (0.2 to 2.7) 
65 
312 232 
0.20 (0.08 to 0.48) 
3.5 (0.7 to 17.6) 
C 
6 
4658.6 
1.2 (0.4 to 3.9) 
80 
312 232 
0.25 (0.11 to 0.58) 
4.9 (1.2 to 20.6) 
Giardia 
B 
4 
4658.6 
0.8 (0.2 to 3) 
29 
312 232 
0.09 (0.03 to 0.27) 
9.3 (1.8 to 49.2) 
C 
9 
4658.6 
2.0 (0.7 to 5.6) 
35 
312 232 
0.11 (0.05 to 0.26) 
18.2 (4.8 to 69.6) 
Viruses 
Adenovirusx 
C 
48 
4658.6 
10.2 (6.8 to 15.4) 
265 
312 232 
0.84 (0.49 to 1.45) 
12.1 (6.1 to 23.9) 
Astrovirus 
D 
25 
4658.6 
5.3 (3 to 9.4) 
127 
312 232 
0.40 (0.20 to 0.82) 
13.1 (5.2 to 32.7) 
Norovirus 
D 
219 
4658.6 
47.0 (39.1 to 56.5) 
648 
312 232 
2.07 (1.44 to 2.99) 
22.7 (15.1 to 34.2) 
Rotavirusx 
C 
59 
4658.6 
12.7 (8.7 to 18.4) 
424 
312 232 
1.36 (0.89 to 2.07) 
9.4 (5.3 to 16.5) 
Sapovirus 
D 
121 
4658.6 
26.1 (20.1 to 33.8) 
491 
312 232 
1.57 (1.08 to 2.29) 
16.6 (10.5 to 26.2) </p>

<p>*Mean number of cases from 20 imputations. 
yPerson-years. 
zCases per 1000 person-years. 
xELISA for adenovirus and rotavirus was conducted in specimens from patients aged &lt;5 years. 
A, culture; B, enzyme immunoassay; C, ELISA and/or PCR; D, PCR; E, culture and/or PCR; GP, general practice; VTEC, verotoxin-producing E coli. </p>

<p>Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>
Intestinal infections </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Summary of main findings </p>

<p>This is one of the largest population-based studies of IID to date, 
comprising over 4500 person-years of community follow-up and 
over 300 000 person-years of GP follow-up. Few researchers </p>

<p>12 23   have investigated the aetiology of IID in the general population 
so comprehensively. We included a broad panel of organisms 
using conventional and novel quantitative PCR diagnostics. The 
greater sensitivity of PCR methods for viral diagnostics allows 
much more reliable incidence estimates, particularly for noro-
virus and sapovirus. The results show Campylobacter is the major 
bacterial IID agent, causing over half a million cases and 80 000 
GP consultations annually. Norovirus, commonly thought to </p>

<p>cause mild illness in institutional outbreaks, nevertheless 
accounts for nearly 3 million sporadic cases annually and 
130 000 GP consultations. 
To our knowledge, this is the first study to report the high 
population burden of sapovirus, which may partly be due to 
emergence of a novel sapovirus strain during the study. 
24 Low 
population immunity levels may have facilitated its rapid 
spread. Our estimates also provide a useful baseline for rotavirus 
burden before the introduction of routine vaccination in the UK, 
and indicate that C difficile is a very uncommon cause of 
diarrhoea in the community. </p>

<p>Comparison with other studies </p>

<p>In a previous study, 
12 limited to England in the mid-1990s, using 
the same case definition and similar methods, the reported IID 
rates were 194 community cases and 33.1 GP consultations per 
1000 person-years. In our study, the community incidence is 
w40% higher, but GP consultation rates for all the major 
pathogens have almost halved. This is consistent with data from 
the Royal College of General Practitioners Weekly Returns 
Service indicating a threefold decrease in IID-related consulta-
tions to its GP network between 1996 and 2008. 
25 A major 
change to primary care since the 1990s is the introduction of 
telephone information and advice services. However, use of 
services such as NHS Direct in England was low in our study 
and cannot account for the decline in GP consultations. Instead, 
increased self-management and perhaps a decrease in the 
severity of illness from certain pathogens may be responsible. 
Our case definition was more sensitive than those used in 
other studies and may have resulted in milder illness being 
captured. The effect of varying case definitions will be the 
subject of more detailed investigation. The Dutch SENSOR 
Study, which used a definition for IID of three or more loose </p>

<p>Table 2 Incidence rates of infectious intestinal disease (IID) in the community and presenting to general practice by organism, and ratios to national 
surveillance, IID2 Study, UK 2008e2009 </p>

<p>Organism </p>

<p>Community 
Presenting to general practice 
Reported to national surveillance 
Rate* (95% CI) 
Rate* (95% CI) 
Rate* (95% CI) </p>

<p>Bacteria 
C perfringens 
A 
1.5 (0.5 to 3.9) 
0.2 (0.1 to 0.5) 
0.001 (0 to 0.001) 
Reporting ratioy 
2518.7 (890.7 to 7179.4) 
419.1 (181.9 to 962.8) 
1.0 
Campylobacter 
A 
9.3 (6 to 14.3) 
1.3 (0.9 to 1.8) 
0.997 (0.989 to 1.005) 
Reporting ratioy 
9.3 (6 to 14.4) 
1.3 (0.9 to 1.8) 
1.0 
E coli O157 VTEC 
A 
0.3 (0 to 4.3) 
0.0 (0 to 0.1) 
0.042 (0.04 to 0.043) 
Reporting ratioy 
7.4 (0.5 to 104.4) 
e 
1.0 
Salmonella 
A 
0.6 (0.2 to 2.4) 
0.2 (0.1 to 0.4) 
0.133 (0.13 to 0.136) 
Reporting ratioy 
4.7 (1.2 to 18.2) 
1.4 (0.6 to 3.3) 
1.0 
Protozoa 
Cryptosporidium 
B 
0.7 (0.2 to 2.7) 
0.2 (0.1 to 0.5) 
0.086 (0.084 to 0.089) 
Reporting ratioy 
8.2 (2.1 to 31.7) 
2.3 (1 to 5.6) 
1.0 
Giardia 
B 
0.8 (0.2 to 3) 
0.1 (0 to 0.3) 
0.061 (0.059 to 0.063) 
Reporting ratioy 
14.0 (4 to 49) 
1.5 (0.5 to 4.5) 
1.0 
Viruses 
Adenovirus 
C 
10.2 (6.8 to 15.4) 
0.8 (0.5 to 1.5) 
0.055 (0.053 to 0.057) 
Reporting ratioy 
184.5 (122 to 279.3) 
15.3 (8.8 to 26.3) 
1.0 
Astrovirus 
D 
5.3 (3 to 9.4) 
0.4 (0.2 to 0.8) 
0.003 (0.003 to 0.003) 
Reporting ratioy 
1763.5 (970.1 to 3218.1) 
135.1 (65.5 to 278.9) 
1.0 
Norovirus 
D 
47.0 (39.1 to 56.5) 
2.1 (1.4 to 3) 
0.164 (0.011 to 0.02) 
Reporting ratioy 
287.6 (239.1 to 346) 
12.7 (8.8 to 18.3) 
1.0 
Rotavirus 
C 
12.7 (8.7 to 18.4) 
1.4 (0.9 to 2.1) 
0.296 (0.232 to 0.268) 
Reporting ratioy 
42.9 (29.5 to 62.4) 
4.6 (3 to 7) 
1.0 </p>

<p>*Cases per 1000 person-years. 
yThe reporting ratios represent the ratio of rates in the community and presenting to general practice relative to the rate of reports to national surveillance. Enteroaggregative E coli and 
sapovirus are omitted from this table, as data on these organisms are not routinely collected at national level in all UK countries. 
A, culture; B, enzyme immunoassay; C, ELISA and/or PCR; D, PCR; VTEC, verocytotoxin-producing E coli. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Patterns of reporting to national surveillance for all infectious 
intestinal disease (IID), UK 2008e9. Black numbers represent the rates 
(with 95% CIs) in the community, presenting to general practice and 
reported to national surveillance. Red numbers represent the ratios of 
incidence in the community and presenting to general practice 
respective to the incidence of infectious intestinal disease reported to 
national surveillance (with 95% CIs). </p>

<p> 
Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>Intestinal infections </p>

<p>stools in a 24 h period, 
23 produced a similar estimate (283 per 
1000 person-years) to ours. Approximately 20% of patients in 
our cohort experienced fewer than three loose stools in a 24 h 
period, implying that, using comparable definitions, our study 
would produce somewhat lower estimates of all-cause IID in the 
community. Nevertheless, using comparable diagnostic 
methods, rates in the community for Campylobacter, norovirus 
and rotavirus were similar to those in both the previous IID 
Study 
12 26 and the Dutch SENSOR Study. 
23 By contrast, the 
incidence of salmonellosis in our study was considerably lower 
than in those two studies. This reflects a decrease in contami-</p>

<p>nation of poultry products, particularly from Salmonella 
Enteritidis phage type 4, following the introduction of vacci-
nation of breeder and layer flocks in the mid-1990s. </p>

<p>27   We estimate that there are up to 17 million cases of sporadic 
IID in the UK every year. Studies of IID burden in similar 
settings using telephone survey methods generally produce 
incidence estimates two to three times higher. 
28 The reasons are 
unclear, but may include differences in case definitions, tele-
scoping of symptoms among telephone survey respondents, and 
reporting fatigue among cohort participants followed-up for 
long periods. 
28 In the IID2 Study, we conducted a parallel </p>

<p>Figure 5 Patterns of reporting to national surveillance for Campylobacter, Salmonella, norovirus and rotavirus, UK 2008e9. Black numbers represent 
the rates per 1000 person-years (with 95% CIs) in the community, presenting to general practice and reported to national surveillance. Red numbers 
represent the ratios of the incidence rates in the community and presenting to general practice compared with infectious intestinal disease reports to 
national surveillance (with 95% CIs). </p>

<p>Table 3 Estimated annual numbers of infectious intestinal disease (IID) cases in the community and presenting to general practices by organism, IID2 
Study, UK 2008e2009 </p>

<p>Organism </p>

<p>Community 
Presenting to GP </p>

<p>Cases 
95% CI 
Cases 
95% CI </p>

<p>Bacteria 
C perfringens 
A 
89 847 
33 565 to 240 508 
14 983 
6981 to 32 157 
Campylobacter spp. 
A 
571 949 
369 936 to 884 276 
78 973 
55 486 to 112 401 
E coli O157 VTEC 
A 
18 916 
1339 to 267 201 
824 
120 to 5664 
Enteroaggregative E coli 
D 
365 297 
211 351 to 631 374 
12 893 
6501 to 25 567 
Salmonella spp. 
A 
38 606 
9968 to 149 529 
11 291 
4649 to 27 418 
Protozoa 
Cryptosporidium 
B 
43 834 
11 393 to 168 655 
12 488 
5232 to 29 805 
Giardia 
B 
52 434 
15 022 to 183 020 
5617 
1875 to 16 822 
Viruses 
Adenovirus 
C 
630 251 
417 285 to 951 906 
52 106 
30 219 to 89 845 
Astrovirus 
D 
325 642 
1 82 466 to 581 165 
24 982 
12 260 to 50 905 
Norovirus 
D 
2 905 278 
2 418 208 to 3 490 451 
128 022 
88 784 to 184 600 
Rotavirus 
C 
783 737 
539 535 to 1 138 466 
83 850 
54 868 to 128 141 
Sapovirus 
D 
1 610 041 
1 239 580 to 2 091 219 
97 024 
66 661 to 141 217 
All IID 
16 935 420 
15 680 690 to 18 277 944 
1 096 190 
891 659 to 1 348 301 </p>

<p>A, culture; B, enzyme immunoassay; C, ELISA and/or PCR; D, PCR; VTEC, verocytotoxin-producing E coli. </p>

<p>Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>
Intestinal infections </p>

<p>telephone survey to study these differences in detail (to be 
reported elsewhere). 
IID-related GP consultation rates vary considerably by study: 
the SENSOR study rate was half that estimated by us, 
29 while 
the rate recently reported in Germany was double. 
30 These 
differences are difficult to interpret, but variations in primary 
care provision and usage between countries may explain them. </p>

<p>Study limitations </p>

<p>Adherence to weekly follow-up in the cohort study was high. 
Drop-outs accounted for losing &lt;5% of total follow-up time. 
Nevertheless, w10% of those invited were recruited into the 
study. This is lower than previous studies in England (35%)   12   and the Netherlands (42%), 
23 but similar to recent prospective, 
population-based UK studies. 
31 32 Study participants may differ 
from the general population in terms of IID risk or propensity to 
report symptoms. We standardised all rates to account for 
differences in the age and sex structure between the cohort and 
census populations, and we did not find important differences in 
IID rates by ethnicity, socioeconomic group, urbanerural resi-
dence or area-level deprivation (data not shown). 
We based our estimates of community incidence on definite 
IID cases. These could be conservative, since some cohort 
participants reporting illness were classified as possible cases 
because of missing symptom information. If definite and 
possible cases were considered, the community rate nearly 
doubled. We used definite cases only because information from 
them on health service usage agrees with estimates from the GP 
presentation study and NHS Direct, suggesting that these esti-
mates are more reliable than those based on all definite and 
possible cases. In addition, our results show a marked decline in 
community Salmonella incidence, but for Campylobacter, noro-
virus and rotavirus, for which control measures have not been 
implemented, our estimates are similar to those reported 
previously in England 
12 26 and the Netherlands. </p>

<p>23   One in six patients presenting to GP with IID-compatible 
symptoms was recruited into the GP presentation study, with 
considerable variation by practice. Although we publicised the 
study widely in participating practices, some GPs may not have 
referred patients if they were too busy. To satisfy ethics 
requirements, invited patients were given a 24 h cooling-off 
period before providing consent. Some patients were unable or 
unwilling to return for an interview on another day, and others 
were no longer interested because their condition had improved. 
We corrected for under-ascertainment using adjustment factors 
to account for differences in ascertainment by age group, sex, 
diagnostic category and practice. 
In the cohort study, a third of cases did not provide a stool 
specimen for microbiological examination, so we used multiple 
imputation methods to infer missing organism information. Our 
imputation models included variables most likely to predict the 
likelihood of infection with different organisms, namely age 
group and symptom profile, but may not have dealt adequately 
with missing data if other important factors related to positivity 
with specific organisms had been omitted. 
We used both conventional and quantitative PCR methods for 
microbial diagnosis. PCR-based methods have greater sensitivity 
for enteric viruses. For norovirus and rotavirus, however, 
a substantial fraction of asymptomatic people have evidence of 
infection using PCR. 
33 We used previously validated PCR cut-off 
values to distinguish clinically significant from coincidental 
infection with norovirus and rotavirus. Similar data do not exist 
for other organisms, and we opted for a more sensitive 
threshold. We may have overestimated incidence, particularly </p>

<p>for sapovirus, adenovirus and astrovirus, since, in some people, 
infection may have been coincidental rather than causative. 
Conversely, we may have underestimated Cryptosporidium and 
Giardia rates; these organisms often cause illness lasting over 
2 weeks, so cases of longer duration may have been excluded. 
Despite extensive microbiological testing, w50% and 60% of 
specimens tested in the GP presentation and cohort studies, 
respectively, were negative for all the organisms investigated. 
This is similar to previous studies 
23 34 and may reflect the role of 
other organisms for which we did not test, or hitherto unknown 
pathogens. We excluded patients with known non-infectious 
causes of IID, and required cases to be symptom-free for the 
preceding 3 weeks and have illness lasting less than 2 weeks. 
However, it is possible that a fraction of these stool-negative 
cases had non-infectious causes such as transient irritable bowel 
syndrome, either pre-existing or resulting from a prior episode of 
IID. 
The reporting ratios should be interpreted in their epidemio-
logical context. Norovirus cases in national statistics arise 
primarily from institutional outbreaks, which were not included 
in our study. We may therefore have overestimated the propor-
tion of sporadic cases in the community captured by national 
surveillance. For organisms such as Campylobacter, which is 
uncommonly associated with large outbreaks, the reporting 
ratio reflects more accurately the ratio of community incidence 
to national statistics. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The UK burden of IID is substantial, resulting in up to 17 million 
sporadic cases annually. Despite this, IID-related GP consulta-
tions have declined substantially since the 1990s. Changes in 
healthcare usage, rather than increased use of telephone infor-
mation and advice services, probably explain this. Tackling 
Campylobacter is central to the Food Standards Agency's strategy 
and crucial for reducing food-borne illness burden. 
35 This involves 
reducing contamination in poultry, a major source of human 
infection, 
36 and promoting safe food preparation to avoid cross-
contamination. By contrast, salmonellosis has declined dramati-
cally. C difficile, very important in healthcare settings, appears to 
be a rare cause of community IID, while enteric viruses account 
for a large burden of healthcare use and disease in the community. 
New rotavirus vaccines, if deemed cost-effective for routine 
immunisation in the UK, show great promise for reducing burden 
of rotavirus disease in children. 
37 38 Our study provides 
contemporaneous baseline estimates of rotavirus burden before 
introduction of routine immunisation. For norovirus and sapo-
virus, organisms commonly regarded as mainly causing institu-
tional outbreaks, the large pool of community infection raises 
important questions about control. Mitigating the impact of 
these viruses includes scrupulous personal hygiene to avoid 
person-to-person spread, and protecting shellfish beds against 
human sewage contamination to reduce food-related norovirus 
infection. Understanding better the burden of disease that is 
food-borne, and the relationship between virus circulation in the 
community and transmission in institutional and healthcare 
settings, is crucial for developing appropriate control strategies. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Faculty of Epidemiology and 
Population Health, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Medical Research Council General Practice Research Framework and University 
College London, London, UK </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Primary Care and Public Health, Cardiff University, Cardiff, UK </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>School of Medicine, Health Policy and Practice, University of East Anglia, Norwich, UK </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Department of Gastrointestinal, Emerging &amp; Zoonotic Infections, Health Protection 
Agency Centre for Infections, London, UK </p>

<p> 
Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>Intestinal infections </p>

<p>6 Regional Microbiology Network, Health Protection Agency Yorkshire and the Humber, 
Leeds Laboratory, Leeds, UK 
7 School of Translational Medicine, University of Manchester and Manchester 
Academic Health Science Centre, Manchester, UK </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We thank all the participants, study nurses, general 
practitioners, practice staff, laboratory, research and administrative staff who took 
part in the IID2 Study. We are grateful to the Medical Research Council General 
Practice Research Framework, the Primary Care Research Networks in England and 
Northern Ireland and the Scottish Primary Care Research Network for assistance 
with the recruitment of general practices. We thank the UK Food Standards Agency 
and the Department of Health for funding the research component of the IID2 Study 
(Project B18021). We also thank the Department of Health, the Scottish Primary 
Care Research Network, NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde, NHS Grampian, NHS 
Tayside, the Welsh Assembly government (Wales Office of Research and 
Development) and, in Northern Ireland, the Health and Social Care Public Health 
Agency (HSC Research and Development) for providing service support costs. We 
thank Julian Gardiner for help with aspects of the analysis. </p>

<p>Funding This study was funded by the Food Standards Agency and sponsored by 
University of Manchester. Neither the funder nor the sponsor were involved in the 
analysis, interpretation or decision to submit for publication. </p>

<p>Correction notice This article has been corrected since it was published Online First. 
In the results section of the abstract, the following sentence has been corrected as 
follows: "Campylobacter was the most common bacterial pathogen, with a rate of 
9.3 cases per 1000 person-years in the community, and 1.3 GP consultations per 
1000 person-years." </p>

<p>Competing interests All authors have completed the Unified Competing Interest 
form at http://www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf (available on request from the 
corresponding author). </p>

<p>Patient consent Obtained. </p>

<p>Ethics approval This study was conducted with the approval of the North West 
MREC, Stockport PCT, Gateway House, Piccadilly South, Manchester M60 7LP, UK. </p>

<p>Contributors SJOB, GR, JJG, PRH, DST, CCT and LCR conceived the ideas for the 
study. All authors participated in its design and coordination. SJOB, GR, JD and LHL 
led the prospective studies. JJG and DST led the laboratory studies. MRE participated 
in the national surveillance studies. CCT, LCR and LV led and conducted the analysis. 
CCT, LCR and SJOB drafted the manuscript. All authors have read and approved the 
final manuscript. All authors had full access to all of the data (including statistical 
reports and tables) in the study and can take responsibility for the integrity of the data 
and the accuracy of the data analysis. SJOB is the guarantor of the study. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>





<p>Gut 2012;61:69e77. doi:10.1136/gut.2011.238386 </p>

<p>
Intestinal infections </p>

</text></tei>