<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3529402" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Due to their theoretical advantages, hip systems combining modular necks and large diameter femoral heads 
have gradually gained popularity. However, among others, concerns regarding changes in the load transfer patterns were 
raised. Recent stress analyses have indeed shown that the use of modular necks and big femoral heads causes significant 
changes in the strain distribution along the femur. Our original hypothesis was that these changes may affect early distal 
migration of a modular stem. We examined the effect of head diameter and neck geometry on migration at two years of 
follow-up in a case series of 116 patients (125 hips), who have undergone primary Metal-on-Metal total hip arthroplasty 
with the modular grit-blasted Profemur 
® E stem combined with large-diameter heads (&gt;36 mm). We found that choice of 
neck geometry and head diameter has no effect on stem migration. A multivariate regression analysis including the 
potential confounding variables of the body mass index, bone quality, canal fill and stem positioning revealed only a 
negative correlation between subsidence and canal fill in midstem area. Statistical analysis, despite its limitations, did not 
confirm our hypothesis that choice of neck geometry and/or head diameter affects early distal migration of a modular 
stem. However, the importance of correct stem sizing was revealed. </p>

<p>Modern total hip arthroplasty (THA) designs 
incorporating modular necks and second-generation large-
diameter Metal-on-Metal (MoM) articulations have been 
widely implanted worldwide. Due to the increased joint 
stability and the low-wear characteristics of the well-
functioning arthroplasties, an 
extended long-term 
survivorship rate was anticipated. Thus, they were reserved 
for the younger and more active patients [1]. However, in 
predicting longevity, periprosthetic bone remodeling after 
prosthesis insertion is the most important factor. We know 
that adaptive bone remodeling is proportional to the 
magnitude of stress [2]. It is logical to presume that a 
deviated femoral head, at the coronal or sagittal plane, under 
an axial load may have different load transfer patterns than 
when a straight neck is used [3]. Similarly the use of large-
diameter heads may impose alterations in strain distribution 
when compared to 28 mm heads. </p>

<p>Only a few papers in recent literature have dealt with the 
effects of neck modularity and head size on the 
biomechanics of the hip [3-6]. According to these stress 
analyses, the use of modular necks and big femoral heads 
alters significantly the strains developed along profile lines 
across the femur and particularly around the stem tip. For the </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Department of Orthopaedics 
and Traumatology, University Hospital of Patras, Rion, Greece, Postal Code 
GR-26504, Greece; Tel: +302610999940; Fax: +302610994579; 
E-mail: panmegas@gmail.com </p>

<p>retroverted necks particularly, it seems that the implantation 
in the anteriorly bowed femur creates increased bending 
stress and therefore a not so benign scenario for the 
biomechanical environment [3, 4, 7]. Furthermore, a finite 
element analysis (FEA) has shown that for a lateral profile 
line, along linea aspera and for the stem tip area increasing 
the head diameter results in strain rise [5]. Although it 
remains uncertain whether these changes in strain 
distribution patterns are clinically relevant, they raise 
concerns regarding adaptive hypertrophy and possible 
mechanical failure due to increased stress [3]. Mechanical 
failure and loosening of a femoral stem can be predicted 
accurately by early measurement of distal migration at two 
years follow-up [8]. The RSA migration pattern of some 
cemented stem designs has indeed already been found to be 
affected by the version of the femoral component [7, 9]. 
Questions are raised over the effect of neck modularity on 
subsidence of uncemented stems. </p>

<p>On this basis, we examined early stem migration in a 
case series of 116 patients (125 hips), who have undergone 
primary cementless MoM THA with modular necks and 
large-diameter heads and asked whether: a) the choice of a 
particular neck orientation resulted in increased migration 
and b) increasing head size led to an increase in subsidence. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Between January 2006 and January 2008, a consecutive 
series of 138 primary cementless MoM THA in 129 patients 
was performed in our institution. The selection criteria were </p>



<p>Georgiou et al. </p>

<p>an absence of severe deformity of the femoral canal and 
adequate bone stock for cementless fixation [10]. Exclusion 
criteria were renal insufficiency and female gender in 
reproductive age [11]. All patients gave informed consent to 
participate in the study, and the study was approved by our 
university institutional review board. </p>

<p>A collarless, streamlined, tapered modular stem 
(Profemur 
® E stem, Wright Medical Technology Inc., 
Arlington, TN) made of Ti6Al4V alloy was used in all 
patients. The stems have a grit-blasted surface (Ra = 6 
micron) and a rectangular cross-section for enhanced 
rotational stability [12]. They are available in 10 different 
sizes (Fig. 1). The Profemur 
® E stems utilize a patented 
modular neck technology. Eleven options of neck orientation 
are available from five different designs (Fig. 2). These five 
neck versions include a neutral neck, an 8° angled neck for 
varus or valgus, an 8° angled neck for anteversion or 
retroversion, a 15° angled neck for anteversion or 
retroversion, and a neck with a combination of 4° for varus 
and 6° for anteversion. The latter double-angled neck can 
provide varus-anteversion, valgus-retroversion, varus-
retroversion and valgus-anteversion orientation, depending 
on the side implanted (Fig. 3). Each of them can be in short 
or long configurations, so the available options are 22. The 
Conserve 
® (Wright Medical Technology Inc., Arlington, TN) 
CoCr cup, without metal liners and holes or screws, was 
used as acetabular component in all cases. </p>

<p>Fig. (1). The Profemur 
® E stem. Note the grit-blasted surface, the 
proximal ribs and at the lateral view the tapered, rectangular cross-
section. The latter two features provide improved initial rotational 
stability. </p>

<p>Patients who fulfilled the selection criteria underwent a 
complete metabolic workup before operation and a 
cardiologic and pneumonologic evaluation, when necessary. 
Preoperative control included digital radiographic 
examination, with low-centered pelvic radiographs and 
anteroposterior and lateral radiographs of the indexed hip. 
The procedures were performed by a single surgeon, the </p>

<p>senior author, in a single unit and with the abovementioned 
specific implants and MoM articulation. A standard posterior 
surgical approach was used in all cases. Implant type, size, 
neck, and head were selected according to preoperative 
planning and intraoperative axial and rotational stability and 
impingement testing. These implants were accurately 
recorded. A closed suction drainage was used in all cases. 
Postoperatively, antibiotic prophylaxis (cephalosporin) was 
used for two days until the removal of the drainage. Routine 
prophylaxis was not provided for the prevention of 
heterotopic ossification. Low-molecular-weight heparin was 
administered for six weeks together with compression 
stockings. Partial weight-bearing was encouraged for six 
weeks and progressed to full weight-bearing as tolerated 
thereafter. </p>

<p>Fig. (2). The available neck types, each coupled with the plastic 
blue trial. In the first row, from left to right: the straight neck, the 8° 
angled neck for anteversion or retroversion (Ante/Retro 8°) and the 
similarly 15° angled neck (Ante/Retro 15°). In the second row, the 
8° varus or valgus neck is shown first. The next two are actually the 
same neck version, designed separately for the right (ARVV1) and 
the left hip (ARVV2), so as to provide the combination of 4° varus 
and 6° anteversion in each side. </p>

<p>All patients completed at least two years of follow-up 
(mean 38 months, range 26-64 months). Reevaluation was 
performed at regular intervals (1 
st , 3 
rd , 6 
th month and every 
year thereafter) and included clinical assessment and digital 
radiography of the operated hips. During this follow-up 
period, three patients (three hips) died for reasons irrelevant 
to the operations, nine patients (nine hips) were lost to 
follow-up, and one had a stem revision because of aseptic 
loosening, which was attributed to failure of primary fixation 
of the undersized stem. These left 116 patients (125 hips) 
available for analysis. 43 (37%) of them were men and 73 
(63%) women. Mean average age at surgery was 63.7 years 
(range 29 -85 years). The preoperative diagnosis for the 125 
hips was primarily osteoarthritis (93 hips; 74.4%). Other 
etiologies included femoral neck fracture (8 hips; 6.4%), 
avascular necrosis (5 hips; 4%), osteoarthritis secondary to 
developmental dysplasia of the hip -Crowe type I (6 hips; 
4.8%) and II (3 hips; 2.4%) -or Legg-Calve-Perthes disease 
(6 hips; 4.8%), rheumatoid arthritis (2 hips; 1.6%) and 
traumatic osteoarthrosis (2 hips; 1.6%). From the neck 
options available every possible orientation was used, except </p>

<p>Do Head Diameter and Neck Geometry Affect Migration of a Modular Stem? </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2012, Volume 6 595 </p>

<p>from valgus-anteversion (Table 1). Head size, with 2 mm 
increments, varied from 40 mm to 52 mm (mean 44 mm) 
(Table 2). </p>

<p>According to the orientation of the implanted neck, the 
cases were divided into 10 groups (Table 1). The first 
postoperative and subsequent consecutive anteroposterior </p>

<p>Fig. (3). The double-angled necks can provide further orientations depending on the side implanted. For the right hip, the ARVV1 neck can 
provide 4° of varus and 6° of anteversion (Ante-varus) (A), but also 4° of valgus and 6° of retroversion (Retro-valgus) if implanted reversed 
(B). If the ARVV2 neck is used instead, the possible orientations are 4° of varus and 6° of retroversion (Retro-varus) (C) and 4° of valgus 
and 6° of anteversion (Ante-valgus) (D). The same applies vice versa for the left hip. </p>

<p>Table 1. Groups of Cases According to Neck Type and Differences in Mean Stem Migration Across them </p>

<p>Mean stem migration (mm) 
n 
(%) 
Mean 
SD 
Median </p>

<p>Neck Type </p>

<p>Straight 
20 
16,0% 
0,78 
± 
0,41 
0,8 </p>

<p>Varus 
21 
16,8% 
0,85 
± 
0,83 
0,5 </p>

<p>Valgus 
12 
9,6% 
0,78 
± 
0,62 
0,7 </p>

<p>Ante 8° 
16 
12,8% 
0,95 
± 
0,56 
0,9 </p>

<p>Ante 15° 
11 
8,8% 
0,76 
± 
0,48 
0,7 </p>

<p>Ante-varus </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>24 
19,2% 
0,88 
± 
1,17 
0,6 </p>

<p>Retro-types 
Retro-varus 
10 
8% 
0,90 
± 
0,45 
0,9 </p>

<p>Retro 8° 
7 
5,6% 
0,71 
± 
0,56 
0,4 </p>

<p>Retro-valgus 
2 
21 
1,6% 
16,8% 
3,83 
± 
4,03 
3,8 </p>

<p>Retro 15° 
2 
1,6% 
2,00 
± 
0,58 
2,0 </p>

<p>125 
100% 
p 
0,861 </p>

<p>* Ante-valgus neck type was not used, SD: standard deviation, n: number of hips. 
p refer to the p-value of Kruskal-Wallis test of differences between the first 8 groups of neck type (non-parametric equivalent test to ANOVA). </p>



<p>Georgiou et al. </p>

<p>digital radiographs of each hip were examined 
retrospectively by two independent blinded observers (E.T, 
C.P.), neither involved in the clinical care of the patients. 
Stem subsidence at two years postoperatively was measured 
by the two observers, as a change in the vertical distance 
from the proximal tip of the greater trochanter to the 
shoulder of the stem [8]. A computer-assisted method was 
used to perform these measurements. The radiographs were 
originally DICOM and transformed into TIFF greyscale 
format without compression. These digital images were 
processed via <rs id="software-0" type="software">Roman</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v1.7</rs> software (Roman software 
version V1.70; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Robert Jones and Agnes Hunt Orthopaedic Hospital</rs>, Oswestry, UK; http://www.cookedbits.co.uk/roma 
n/). <rs type="software">Roman</rs> is a radiological measurement program designed 
for orthopaedic applications in general. Its accuracy has 
already been demonstrated for the measurement of 
polyethylene wear, where the determination of bone and 
prosthesis landmarks is automated by the computer using an 
edge detection algorithm [13]. Roman has also been 
successfully used in stem migration analyses [14]. </p>

<p>Cortical Index (CI), stem alignment and canal fill were 
also assessed, with the use of <rs id="software-3" type="software">Roman</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">v1.7</rs>. CI was calculated 
at a level 100 mm below the middle of the lesser trochanter 
and Dorr's bone quality for each patient was assigned [15]. 
Varus or valgus malalignment of the stem was defined as 
deviation from the longitudinal femoral axis of &gt; 3° on the 
first postoperative radiograph [16]. On the same radiograph, </p>

<p>canal fill at four different levels (calcar, lesser trochanter, 
midstem, distal fill) was measured [17]. Firstly, lesser 
trochanter level was defined from a line drawn on the 
anteroposterior radiograph through the midpoint of the lesser 
throchanter. Three lines parallel to this were then drawn 
through the diaphysis. One through the medial margin of the 
neck osteotomy (calcar level), another through the middle of 
the stem (midstem level) and the last 100 mm distally, at the 
stem tip area (distal level). Canal fill was calculated as a 
percentage of the stem diameter to the endosteal diameter at 
each level [17]. We defined a stem as undersized when 
midstem fill was 80% [18]. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>As the determination of bone and prosthesis landmarks 
were assessed by hand, before proceeding to further analysis 
an investigation of the intra-and interobserver variability 
was performed to confirm the reliability of the results. 
Intraobserver variability was determined by estimating the 
correlation coefficient of two measurements obtained by one 
observer in 1-week intervals. Interobserver variability was 
determined by simultaneously estimating the correlation 
coefficient (r) and the F-test of equality of variances of the 
two measurements obtained by the two different observers. 
Interobserver reliability was assessed by using the intraclass 
correlation coefficient (ICC). We set 2.4 mm as the threshold 
of distal migration at 24 months follow-up [8]. </p>

<p>Fig. (4). Boxplots showing the relationship between migration and the categorical variables of interest, i.e. neck type (A), bone quality 
(Dorr's A, B, C bone quality) (B), stem positioning (neutral vs varus) (C) and midstem fill (&lt;80% vs &gt;80%) (D). </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Mean stem migration </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Mean stem migration </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Average Stem Migration </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Mean stem migration </p>

<p>straight 
varus ante-varus ante8 
ante15 
valgus retro-types </p>

<p>(122 Hips) </p>

<p>(125 Hips) 
(125 Hips) </p>

<p>(125 Hips) </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Neutral 
Varus 
&lt;=80% 
&gt;80% </p>

<p>Do Head Diameter and Neck Geometry Affect Migration of a Modular Stem? </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2012, Volume 6 597 </p>

<p>Pearson correlation coefficients were used to assess the 
association of mean stem migration with head diameter, 
Body Mass Index (BMI) and canal fill levels, while mean 
differences of the early migration across the rest variables of 
interest were assessed using the Kruskal-Wallis non-
parametric test (equivalent test to ANOVA) and the test of 
equality of medians. </p>

<p>A multivariate regression analysis was performed to 
examine whether neck type and head diameter independently 
affected early migration. In the model, only those variables 
were included, that in the separate univariate regression 
models were found to have a p-value of association with 
early migration lower than 0.150. Among the variables 
examined were BMI (continuously), Dorr's bone quality 
(categorically), stem positioning (neutral, varus, valgus; 
categorically), canal fill in the four levels (continuously). 
Midstem fill was also introduced categorically (&lt;80% vs 
&gt;80%). </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed using the <rs type="software">Stata</rs> 
statistical package (Stata Corporation: Stata/SE 11.0 for 
Windows, Lakeway Drive, College Station, Texas, USA, 
2010). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Intraobserver variability was negligible and the 
measurements of the two observers were highly correlated 
(Pearson r=0.970) with equal variances (p=0.641). The ICC 
was equal to 0.969 indicating very good agreement between 
the two observers, thus the mean migration value for each 
patient was used for further analysis. Mean distal migration 
at two years postoperatively was 0.905±0.9 mm (median 0.8 
mm, range 0-6.7 mm). Four patients exhibited stem 
subsidence more than the 2.4 mm threshold. Distribution of 
migration in the groups is shown in Fig. (4a), where the 
retroverted necks are considered as one group (including 
retro 8° and 15°, retro-varus and retro-valgus). Boxplots of 
early subsidence in relation to the rest categorical variables 
are shown in Fig. (4b-d). </p>

<p>Table 2 presents the Pearson correlation coefficient of the 
association of mean early migration with head size, BMI and 
canal fill levels. Head size and BMI doesn't seem to 
correlate with subsidence. There appeared to be a negative 
association of mean migration with midstem and distal 
levels, although marginally non-significant (Table 2). </p>

<p>Mean differences in early migration across categories of 
neck type and several variables under study are presented in 
Tables 1 and 3. There was no evidence of difference in early 
migration across choices of neck geometry. However, one 
patient with a retroverted 15° neck had a mean distal 
migration of 2.4 mm and another patient with a retro-valgus 
neck had a migration of 6.7 mm. Retroverted 15° and retro-
valgus neck have only been used each twice (Table 1). 
Furthermore, when comparing the retroverted versus the 
straight necks, there was a suggestion of difference (mean 
migration=1.22 for retroverted necks versus 0.78 for straight 
neck type), although not statistically significant at the 5% 
significance level (p=0.176, t-test, data not shown). </p>

<p>Table 4 shows the mutually adjusted linear regression-
derived coefficients of the association of stem migration with 
neck type and head diameter. Their interaction was not 
statistically significant (p=0.208). The only potential 
confounders 
that 
appeared 
to 
affect 
migration 
(untransformed) in the univariate models were midstem ( =-
1.43, p=0.097) and distal fill ( =-1.90, p=0.108) and were 
therefore included in this model. Head size does not seem to 
play a role in stem's early subsidence ( =0.02, p=0.459). 
Migration tended to be higher when retroverted neck types 
were used, compared to other neck types, although the 
association was statistically non-significant ( =0.38, 
p=0.077). In contrast with canal fill in stem tip area, midstem 
fill was found to be negatively associated with stem 
migration, with the difference found marginally significant 
( =-0.36, p=0.046). However, no statistical significant 
difference is evident, when comparing undersized with the 
rest stems (Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Although the risk and benefits of systems combining 
modular necks and large-diameter femoral heads are 
constantly reevaluated [19, 20], interestingly enough, 
biomechanics of these novel systems have not been equally 
investigated. Increased femoral anteversion alters 
significantly loading patterns in monoblock implants, while 
variations of offset seem to cause only minor changes [21]. 
For the modular-neck stems and their complex 
configurations, however, there are only a few reports in the 
literature [3, 4, 6]. In a study by Umeda et al. [3] strain 
gauge measurements of a modular cementless stem 
implanted in a synthetic femur were performed. Changing </p>

<p>Table 2. Descriptive Data for Head Size, BMI, Canal Fill Levels, Early Migration and their Association </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Median 
min 
max 
r </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>Head diameter (mm) 
44 ± 
2 
44 
40 
52 
0,06 
0,477 </p>

<p>BMI (Kg/m 
2 ) 
27,9 ± 5,0 
26,6 
18,5 
51,3 
0,10 
0,661 </p>

<p>Canal fill levels </p>

<p>Calcar fill (%) 
65,4 ± 8,4 
64,9 
49,5 
86,2 
0,021 
0,813 </p>

<p>Lesser trochanter fill (%) 
75,9 ± 7,6 
76,0 
60,1 
94 
-0,032 
0,726 </p>

<p>Distal fill (%) 
69,6 ± 9,4 
70,0 
49,7 
98 
-0,145 
0,108 </p>

<p>Midstem fill (%) 
90,6 ± 6,9 
91,0 
72,2 
100 
-0,149 
0,097 </p>

<p>Stem migration (mm) 
0,905 ± 0,9 
0,8 
0 
6,7 </p>

<p> † Pearson correlation coefficient of the association betweeen mean stem migration and all other variables, BMI: Body Mass Index, SD: standard deviation. </p>



<p>Georgiou et al. </p>

<p>the neck from straight to anteverted or retroverted caused a 
large increase in strains on both, anterior and posterior, 
femoral surfaces, particularly at the distal part of the stem, 
and that increase was highly correlated with the extent of 
neck version. On the aspect toward which the prosthetic neck 
was oriented increased compressive strains were developed, 
while on the opposite side increased tensile strains. Due to 
the anteriorly bowed femur more bending stress was 
produced, especially at the stem tip area, when retroverted 
necks were used, as the femoral head deviates more in the 
sagittal plane than when an anteverted neck is used. The 
highest value of strain increase, compared with the strain 
developed with the straight neck, was 1195% and it was 
recorded with the extensively retro-angled 22.5° neck at the 
anterior aspect of the femur and at the level of the stem tip. It 
is worth noticing that, for both neck types, strain magnitudes 
on the anterior and posterior surfaces exceeded those 
developed on an intact femur [3]. Strains on the medial and 
lateral aspects of the femur were also increased, but at a 
lesser magnitude of maximum 22% [3]. Although it is 
difficult to directly compare results between experimental 
studies, this increase in the tensile strain on the anterior </p>

<p>femoral surface with the retroverted necks was confirmed in 
another strain gauge study on cadaveric femurs [4]. In the 
same study, varus neck angulation was found to have a 
relatively small influence on strain distribution in the 
proximal femur [4]. In contrast with these studies, a FEA 
reported no significant alterations in the strain distribution of 
a cemented stem coupled to a modular neck, positioned in 
anteversion, retroversion and with two different offsets [6]. 
However, this study focused only on the medial and lateral 
femoral aspects. None of these papers examines the changes 
in strain pattern caused by simultaneous alteration of neck-
shaft angle, neck length and version. On the other hand, only 
one study addresses the effect of increasing head size in 
proximal femur loading [5]. Although one anticipates that 
head diameter would not affect the strain pattern of the 
implant [4], this FEA revealed notable changes [5]. With 
respect to the reference model of a 28 mm femoral head, 
changing head diameter in 10 mm increments invoked 
proportional increases of about 15 to 18% in the maximum 
strains developed around the stem tip, and along linea aspera 
and a lateral profile line [5]. </p>

<p>Table 3. Differences in Mean Stem Migration Across Categories of Important Variables Under Study </p>

<p>Mean Stem Migration (mm) </p>

<p>n 
(%) 
Mean 
SD 
Media 
n </p>

<p>Neck type 
Retro-types </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>21 
16,8% 
1,22 
± 
1,38 
1,0 
Straight 20 
16,0% 
0,78 
± 
0,41 
0,8 
Varus 21 
16,8% 
0,85 
± 
0,83 
0,5 
Ante-varus 24 
19,2% 
0,88 
± 
1,17 
0,6 
Ante 8° 16 
12,8% 
0,95 
± 
0,56 
0,9 
Ante 15° 11 
8,8% 
0,76 
± 
0,48 
0,7 
Valgus 12 
9,6% 
0,78 
± 
0,62 
0,7 </p>

<p>p 
0,670 
p* 
0,813 </p>

<p>Dorr's bone quality </p>

<p>A 57 
45,6% 
0,93 
± 
0,94 
0,8 </p>

<p>B 49 
39,2% 
0,87 
± 
0,99 
0,6 </p>

<p>C 19 
15,2% 
0,92 
± 
0,44 
1,0 </p>

<p>p 
0,450 
p* 
0,116 </p>

<p>Stem positioning </p>

<p>Neutral 111 
88,8% 
0,92 
± 
0,94 
0,8 </p>

<p>Valgus 3 
2,4% 
0,80 
± 
0,34 
0,9 </p>

<p>Varus 11 
8,8% 
0,80 
± 
0,46 
0,8 </p>

<p>p** 
0,936 
p** 
1,000 </p>

<p>Midstem fill groups 
&lt; 80% 14 
11,2% 
1,22 
± 
1,64 
0,6 
&gt; 80% 111 
88,8% 
0,87 
± 
0,76 
0,8 </p>

<p>p 0,751 
p* 
0,801 </p>

<p>p refer to the p-value of Kruskal-Wallis test of differences between all groups (non-parametric equivalent test to ANOVA). 
p* denote the p-value of equality of medians. 
p** denote the p-values for Kruskal-Wallis and medians' test respectively for comparing groups Neutral and Varus only (due to insufficient number of valgus stems for analysis). 
 ‡ Retro types include retro 8° and 15°, retro-varus and retro-valgus, SD: standard deviation. </p>

<p>Do Head Diameter and Neck Geometry Affect Migration of a Modular Stem? </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2012, Volume 6 599 </p>

<p>Whether these changes in loading patterns are associated 
with clinical problems remains uncertain. We know that 
bone remodeling after implantation is proportional to the 
magnitude of stress applied [2]. The increased strain induced 
by the increased offset and altered neck angles could 
theoretically act beneficially in preservation of proximal 
bone stock in vivo, minimizing proximal femur stress-
shielding. However, as the postarthroplasty neck version 
becomes excessive, the anterior and posterior femoral 
regions are exposed to noticeably great stresses, with strain 
values exceeding several times, not only those developed 
with straight necks, but also those of unoperated femurs [3]. 
Although none of the existing papers [3 -6] examines the 
scenario, we assume that a neck with reduced neck-shaft 
angle and increased length, implanted in retroversion and 
coupled with a big femoral head, would lead to even greater 
strain concentration. There is a concern that subsequent 
changes in bone quality, due to adaptive remodeling, may 
have undesirable long-term effects on the stability of the 
implant and, thus, may limit the life-span of THA [4]. 
Furthermore, these extended stresses at the implant-bone 
interface seem likely to raise the risk of implant loosening 
[21]. A latest report from the Australian Joint Registry has 
shown indeed a significant higher revision rate for modular-
neck stems, with aseptic loosening identified as the 
predominant reason [22]. Similarly, higher revision rates due 
to loosening/lysis were recorded for large-diameter MoM 
THAs (&gt;32 mm), compared to those with smaller bearings 
[22]. </p>

<p>Loosening of a femoral stem, though, can be predicted by 
measurement of distal migration at two years follow-up [8]. 
Distal stem migration might be, therefore, affected by the 
parameters of head size, neck version and femoral offset. In 
a previous RSA study of cemented THA, it was already 
found that, for some stem designs, anteversion is negatively 
associated with subsidence [9]. In light of these, we 
measured early migration in a series of 125 uncemented 
modular-neck MoM THAs, focusing on the behavior of 
retroverted necks. A multivariate analysis, including several 
potential confounding variables, however, has shown that no 
specific neck geometry resulted in increased migration. 
Retroverted necks, in particular, have not presented 
significant differences in subsidence, when compared with 
straight necks. Similarly, increasing head diameter did not 
also seem to affect stem subsidence and this agrees with </p>

<p>recent EBRA studies [20]. The results revealed only a 
negative association between migration and midstem fill, 
independent of the other covariates. This finding goes along 
with the intention of stem's design for metaphyseal press-fit. </p>

<p>Our study has several limitations. First of all, the number 
of patients receiving a retroverted neck was limited. This 
was due to two reasons. Firstly, as these systems were 
reserved for the younger and more active patients, the overall 
number of patients enrolled was relative small for the neck 
options available. Secondly, it was inapplicable to randomise 
patients to the neck type, because this would have 
endangered joint stability. As posterior approach was used in 
all cases, it was fairly uncommon to use a retroverted neck to 
adjust femoral component version. Certain neck options 
(retroversion-valgus and retroversion 15°) were only used 
twice, thus safe conclusions could not be made from a 
separate analysis. For this reason we performed an initial 
univariate analysis excluding these cases (Table 1) and then 
grouped patients with a retroverted neck into a single group 
and proceeded to further steps. The most incriminated 
combination of strain rise, retroversion-varus, was examined 
in the univariate analysis. Limited number of patients was 
the reason for another premise. To avoid further subdividing 
of the sample, we intentionally ignored the variable of neck 
length; femoral offset was determined only by changes of the 
neck-shaft angle. Consequently, our preliminary results 
should be interpreted with caution; negative results may be 
related to the limitation of the series. Despite, however, the 
small sample size, the strength of this study lies in that it is a 
single-institution, single-surgeon study and that the same 
implants were used in all patients. Thus, migration could not 
be influenced by design or surgeon related factors. </p>

<p>In conclusion, in order to investigate the effect of neck 
modularity and head size on the outcome of cementless 
THA, we measured early distal stem migration in a case 
series with these implants combined. Although literature is 
unfavorable with retroverted necks, statistical analysis of our 
series, despite its limitations, failed to reveal an association 
of migration with retroverted or any other neck type 
whatsoever. Similarly, head diameter could not be related to 
subsidence in our series. The higher incidence of reported 
aseptic loosening of modular-neck stems and large-diameter 
MoM bearings is not confirmed in the preliminary analysis 
of our short-term follow-up series. </p>

<p>Table 4. Mutually Adjusted Linear Regression-Derived Coefficients for the Regression of Stem Migration on Neck Type and Head 
Diameter Controlling for Potentially Confounding Variables in an Analysis of 125 Hips </p>

<p>Dependent 
Stem Migration </p>

<p>Model (n=125 hips) 
Variables </p>

<p>n 
95% CI 
p </p>

<p>Retroverted neck types </p>

<p>No 
104 
ref </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>21 
0,38 
-0,04 
0,80 
0,077 </p>

<p>Head diameter 
0,02 
-0,04 
0,09 
0,459 </p>

<p>Distal fill 
-1,26 
-3,16 
0,64 
0,190 </p>

<p>Midstem fill 
-0,36 
-2,05 
0,32 
0,046 </p>

<p> § Retro types include retroverted 8° and 15°, varus and valgus, 95% CI: 95% Confidence Interval, : regression coefficient. </p>



<p>Georgiou et al. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors confirm that this article content has no 
conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Declared none. </p>



<p>Received: July 9, 2012 
Revised: November 7, 2012 
Accepted: November 7, 2012 </p>

<p>© Georgiou et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. 
This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>