<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3880993" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective: To clarify the precise characteristics of human hepatic progenitor cells (HPCs) for 
future cytotherapy in liver diseases. 
Methods: Hepatic progenitor-like cells were isolated and cultured from the livers of patients who 
had undergone partial hepatectomy for various pathologies but displayed no sign of hepatic dys-
function. These cells were characterized by transcriptomic profiling, quantitative real-time PCR 
and immunocyto/histochemistry. 
Results: Cultured HPCs contained polygonal, high nucleus/cytoplasm ratio and exhibited a global 
gene expression profile similar (67.8%) to that of primary hepatocytes. Among the genes with 
more than 20-fold higher expression in HPCs were a progenitor marker (CD90), a pentrax-
in-related gene (PTX3), collagen proteins (COL5A2, COL1A1 and COL4A2), cytokines (EGF and 
PDGFD), metabolic enzymes (CYBRD1, BCAT1, TIMP2 and PAM), a secreted protein (SPARC) and an 
endothelial protein C receptor (PROCR). Moreover, eight markers (ALB, AFP, CK8, CK18, CK19, 
CD90, CD117 and Oval-6) previously described as HPC markers were validated by qRT-PCR 
and/or immunocyto/histochemistry. Interestingly, human HPCs were also positive for the hem-
atopoietic cell markers CD45 and CD109. Finally, we characterized the localization of HPCs in the 
canals of Hering and periportal areas with six previously described markers (Oval-6, CK8, CK18, 
CK19, CD90 and CD117) and two potential markers (CD45 and CD109). 
Conclusion: The human HPCs are highly similar to primary hepatocytes in their transcriptional 
profiles. The CD45 and CD109 markers could potentially be utilized to identify and isolate HPCs 
for further cytotherapy of liver diseases. </p>

<p>Hepatocyte transplantation presents a promising 
alternative to orthotopic liver transplantation in pa-
tients with end-stage liver disease, including chronic 
viral hepatitis, hepatocellular carcinoma, and alco-
holic liver disease (1-5). However, the supply of 
hepatocytes is limited by a shortage of donor organs 
and the lower proliferation of these cells in vitro (6-8). </p>

<p>Therefore, many researchers are currently focused on 
developing alternative sources of cells (9, 10). Stem 
cells are promising resources for hepatocyte therapy 
to correct inborn errors of metabolism and bridge 
patients with different kinds of end-stage liver failure 
to transplantation or spontaneous recovery (10-13). 
The liver displays an extensive regenerative ca-</p>

<p>Ivyspring </p>

<p>International Publisher </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>pacity in response to loss of mass from injury or par-
tial hepatectomy (1, 14). In most cases, hepatocytes 
can undergo several rounds of proliferation. Howev-
er, this capacity is limited after extensive or chronic 
injury and/or when hepatocyte repopulation is im-
paired (1). Moreover, the cell types that participate in 
liver regeneration remain uncertain, although mature 
hepatocytes and stem cells might both be involved 
(15, 16). Hepatic progenitor cells (HPCs), the human 
counterpart to rodent oval cells, exist in portal or 
periportal areas and contribute to liver regeneration 
(17, 18). These cells emerge into the parenchyma, 
generally in the form of neoductules, and differentiate 
into mature hepatocytes and cholangiocytes to restore 
the damaged liver. However, the precise origin of 
these bipotent progenitors is still unclear (17, 19, 20). 
Bone marrow stem cells (BMSCs) can repopulate an 
injured liver, differentiate into mature hepatocytes in 
vitro, and participate in liver regeneration (8, 16, 21). 
BMSC transplantation has been used to improve a 
mouse model of tyrosinemia (9, 22) and an inborn 
defect in a hepatocytic enzyme (1, 4, 5) by reconsti-
tuting the architecture and function of the injured 
liver. Our previous studies have demonstrated that 
acute hepatic failure-derived rat BMSCs have a he-
patic transcriptional profile, expressing many of the 
same genes expressed by hepatocytes (23, 24). These 
studies indicate that BMSCs are a potential source of 
HPCs for hepatocyte regeneration. 
Species-specific gene expression has been char-
acterized in human and animal HPCs (9, 17). In ro-
dents (25-29), oval cells express markers of both 
hepatocyte and cholangiocyte lineages (such as al-
bumin [ALB], cytokeratin 18 [CK18] and CK19) in 
addition to markers of both hematopoietic and mes-
enchymal stem cells (CD34, CD45 and CD90). In hu-
mans, HPCs with morphological features and im-
munohistological markers similar to those of oval 
cells have been characterized in normal liver and pa-
tients with chronic liver injury or submassive hepatic 
necrosis (30-36). Furthermore, these bipotent progen-
itor cells with characteristics similar to HPCs exist not 
only in human adult liver but also in human fetal liver 
(37, 38). 
However, the precise characteristics of HPCs in 
humans are unknown, as are any gene expression 
differences between HPCs and primary hepatocytes. 
Therefore, studies on human HPCs are urgently 
needed. In this study, we isolated HPCs from the liv-
ers of patients who had undergone partial hepatec-
tomy for various pathologies but displayed no signs 
of hepatic dysfunction. These cells were characterized 
by global gene expression profiling, quantitative re-
al-time reverse-transcription polymerase chain reac-
tion (qRT-PCR) and immunocyto/histochemistry. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Chemicals and reagents </p>

<p>Chemicals for cell isolation and culture including 
ITX mixture, nicotinamide and dexamethasone were 
purchased from Sigma Chemical Corporation (MO, 
USA). Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM), 
Iscove's modifi ed Dulbecco's medium (IMDM), pen-
icillin, 
streptomycin, 
trypsin-ethylenediamine-
tetraacetic acid (EDTA), bovine serum albumin (BSA), 
collagenase IV and fetal bovine serum (FBS) were 
purchased from Invitrogen (CA, USA). Human 
hepatocyte growth factor (HGF) and epidermal 
growth factor (EGF) were from Cell Science (Canton, 
MA). Regular culture dishes and flasks were pur-
chased from BD Falcon (NJ, USA), and immuno-
histochemistry reagents were purchased from Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology (CA, USA) and Bio-Rad Labora-
tories (CA, USA). </p>

<p>Isolation and culture of human hepatocytes 
and HPCs </p>

<p>Human liver tissue specimens (n=12) used in this 
study were harvested from therapeutic partial hepa-
tectomies performed on patients with various pa-
thologies (trauma-induced liver rupture, hepatic 
haemangioma, etc.) who exhibited no sign of hepatic 
dysfunction, hepatitis viruses (including A-E) infec-
tion and hepatic cancer. Informed consent was ob-
tained from the patients and/or their relatives before 
the procedure. All experimental protocols in this 
study were approved by the Ethics Committee of the 
First Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang 
University. The method of primary hepatocyte isola-
tion was previously described (39). Briefly, the liver 
specimens (10 to 20 g) were perfused with four dif-
ferent buffer solutions supplemented with EDTA, 
0.5% dispase, 0.05% collagenase type IV and DNase I. 
The freshly isolated whole liver cell suspensions were 
centrifuged at 50 × g for 1 min at 4 °C. The pellet was 
resuspended in DMEM and centrifuged at 50 × g for 1 
min at 4 °C. The supernatant and pellet were har-
vested separately. The pelleted hepatocytes were re-
suspended in PBS and centrifuged twice at 50 × g for 1 
min at 4 °C. The purified hepatocytes were harvested, 
and total RNA was extracted to perform global gene 
expression profiling by RT-PCR and qRT-PCR. The 
supernatant portion containing the HPCs was centri-
fuged at 150 × g for 2 min at 4 °C. The pellet was re-
suspended in DMEM and centrifuged at 150 × g for 5 
min at 4 °C. The pelleted cells were resuspended in 
DMEM with 10% FBS and purified by Percoll density 
gradient centrifugation. The harvested cells were 
cultured in a 10-mm plastic Petri dish in DMEM sup-
plemented with 10% FBS, 2 mM L-glutamine, 100 </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>U/ml penicillin and 100 µg/ml streptomycin. The 
cultures were maintained at 37 °C in a humidified 
incubator in a mixture of 95% air and 5% CO 2 . The 
medium was changed twice a week. After three or 
four days of culture, some contaminated hepatic cells 
showed a spindly shape including endothelial cells, 
hepatic stellate cells and kupffer cells were scratched 
out from the petri dish by cell scraper. The cells with a 
round or oval shape were remained to proliferate for 
further culture. After one week of culture, the culture 
medium containing FBS was replaced with hepato-
cyte serum-free medium. The fresh medium was 
changed twice a week. To harvest enough HPCs for 
further transcriptional profiling analysis, the cells 
were cultured for three weeks. </p>

<p>Morphological characterization </p>

<p>The morphological features of the cultured HPCs 
were observed under phase-contrast microscopy 
(ECLIPSE TS100, Nikon, Tokyo, Japan) during the 
entire culture period, and cultures were evaluated on 
the basis of cell shape and size, colony formation, cell 
density, cytoplasm to nucleus ratio and colony size. 
Images were acquired and processed using digital 
imaging software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">NIS-Elements</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">F3.0</rs>). </p>

<p>Bipotential differentiation </p>

<p>To characterization of bipotential differentiation 
ability, HPCs were cultured in a commercially avail-
able adipogenic differentiation medium (Cambrex, 
Lonza, Walkersville) for adipocytes differentiation. 
On day 10, the differentiated cells were stained with 
Oil Red O. For hepatogenic differentiation, HPCs 
were cultured in serum-free hepatocyte differentia-
tion medium (IMDM supplemented with 5 ng/mL 
hHGF, 100 μM dexamethasone, 50 mg/mL ITX + 
premix, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 μg/mL strep-
tomycin). On day 10, the morphology of differentiated 
cells were characterized by phase-contrast microsco-
py. For cholangiogenic differentiation, HPCs were 
cultured in cholangiocyte differentiation medium 
(IMDM supplemented with 10% FBS, 50 mg/mL ITX 
+ premix, 10 mM nicotinamide, 5 ng/mL hHGF, 5 
ng/mL EGF, 100 μM dexamethasone, 100 U/mL 
penicillin, and 100 μg/mL streptomycin). On day 10, 
the differentiated cells were characterized by im-
munocytochemistry with the human cholangio-
cyte-specific marker CK19. </p>

<p>Microarray analysis </p>

<p>For transcriptional profiling of HPCs, the 
high-density microarray GeneChip Human Genome 
U133 Plus 2.0 Array (Affymetrix, CA, USA) was used </p>

<p>to characterize mRNA expression following the man-
ufacturer's instructions. Briefly, total RNA was ex-
tracted from cultured HPCs and primary hepatocytes 
using an RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, CA, USA) fol-
lowing the manufacturer's protocol. Single-and dou-
ble-stranded cDNA was synthesized from qualified 
total RNA samples using the GeneChip 3' IVT Express 
Kit (Affymetrix). Three samples of total RNA (200 ng) 
pooled from five different specimens of each cell type 
were used for cDNA synthesis. After double-stranded 
cDNA cleanup and a quality check, in vitro transcrip-
tion was performed using the GeneChip IVT Labeling 
Kit (Affymetrix) to produce biotin-labeled cRNA from 
the cDNA. The Human Genome U133 Plus 2.0 arrays 
were hybridized at 45 °C for 16 h at 60 rpm with a 
hybridization cocktail containing 15 µg of fragmented 
and labeled cRNA in a hybridization oven (Affymet-
rix). The arrays were then washed and stained with 
streptavidin-phycoerythrin (SAPE, Molecular Probes, 
OR, USA). All hybridization assay methods, including 
the preparation of solutions, were performed accord-
ing to the manufacturers' instructions. The distribu-
tion of fluorescent material on the array was detected 
using a 3000 7G GeneChip Scanner (Affymetrix). <rs id="software-2" type="software">Mi-
croarray Suite</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 5.0</rs> and <rs type="software">GeneChip Operating 
Software</rs> supplied by Affymetrix were used for gene 
expression analysis. The pairwise Pearson correlation 
coefficient was used to analyze global gene expression 
similarities between human HPCs and hepatocytes. 
The specimens were hierarchically clustered by in-
putting the probe sets/genes that exhibited a greater 
than 20-fold change between HPCs and hepatocytes. </p>

<p>RT-PCR analysis </p>

<p>To characterize the molecular properties of 
HPCs, we used RT-PCR to analyze selected genes that 
are known to be markers of HPCs and hepatocytes 
(30, 31, 33-36) (albumin [ALB], α-fetoprotein [AFP], 
cytokeratin 8 [CK8], CK18, CK19, CD34, CD45, CD90, 
CD117, tyrosine aminotransferase [TAT], glutamine 
synthase [GS], and glucose-6-phosphate dehydro-
genase [G6PD]). The RT-PCR protocol was previously 
described (23). Briefly, 1 µg of the total RNA used in 
the microarray analysis was reverse transcribed to 
cDNA using the QuantiTect Reverse Transcription Kit 
(Qiagen, Valencia, CA) according to the manufactur-
er's instructions, and then the cDNA was amplified by 
PCR using previously published primers for markers 
of HPCs and hepatocytes (Table 1). The PCR condi-
tions varied according to the primers used. GAPDH 
(glyceraldehyde phosphate dehydrogenase) was used 
as an internal control. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Table 1. Primers used for human HPC gene amplification </p>

<p>Gene 
NCBI accession number 
Length 
Primer 
ALB 
NM_000477.5 
164 
F 
5'-CTGAGCAAAGGCAATCAACA-3' 
R 
5'-CACAGTCTGCTGAGGTTGGA-3' 
AFP 
NM_001134.1 
248 
F 
5'-AGCTTGGTGGTGGATGAAAC-3' 
R 
5'-CCCTCTTCAGCAAAGCAGAC-3' 
CK8 
NM_002273.2 
131 
F 
5'-TCATAGACAAGGTACGGTTCC-3' 
R 
5'-GCCTAAGGTTGTTGATGTAGC-3' 
CK18 
NM_199187.1 
164 
F 
5'-GAGCTGCTCCATCTGTAGGG-3' 
R 
5'-CACAGTCTGCTGAGGTTGGA-3' 
CK19 
NM_002276.4 
138 
F 
5'-CATGAAAGCTGCCTTGGAAGA-3' 
R 
5'-TGATTCTGCCGCTCACTATCAG-3' 
CD34 
NM_001773.2 
206 
F 
5'-TGCATGTGCAGACTCCTTTC-3' 
R 
5'-GAGGACAAGGCTGAGGTCTG-3' 
CD45 
NM_002838.3 
158 
F 
5'-ACGAAGCTCTTAGCGTCAGG-3' 
R 
5'-CTCTCGGGTGGAGTCTTCTG-3' 
CD90 
NM_006288.3 
185 
F 
5'-GACAGCCTGAGAGGGTCTTG-3' 
R 
5'-CCCAGTGAAGATGCAGGTTT-3' 
CD117 
NM_000222.2 
218 
F 
5'-TGCTTCACAGAAGACCATGC-3' 
R 
5'-GTGACCAACATGGAGTCGTG-3' 
TAT 
NM_000353.1 
236 
F 
5'-TAGCTTCTAGGGGTGCCTCA-3' 
R 
5'-AGCCATTGTGGACAACATGA-3' 
GS 
NM_002065.4 
194 
F 
5'-TTGCAAGTCATCCTGCAAAG-3' 
R 
5'-TGATCCTAAGCCCATTCCTG-3' 
G6PD 
NM_000151.1 
140 
F 
5'-CCTGTAACCTGTGAGACTGG-3' 
R 
5'-ATTCAAGCACCGAAATCTGTAG-3' 
GAPDH 
NM_002046.3 
113 
F 
5'-CTCTCTGCTCCTCCTGTTCG-3' 
R 
5'-ACGACCAAATCCGTTGACTC-3' </p>

<p>Note: ALB, albumin; AFP, α-fetoprotein; CK8, cytokeratin 8; CK18, cytokeratin 18; CK19, cytokeratin 19; CD34, cluster of differentiation 34; CD45, cluster of differentiation 45; CD90, also 
known as Thy-1; CD117, also known as c-kit or stem cell factor receptor; TAT, tyrosine aminotransferase; GS, glutamine synthase; G6PD, glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase; and GAPDH, 
glyceraldehyde phosphate dehydrogenase. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time RT-PCR analysis </p>

<p>We used qRT-PCR to confirm the mRNA ex-
pression levels of the following genes: 12 previously 
published marker genes for HPCs and hepatocytes, 
genes with a greater than 20-fold up-regulation in 
HPCs according to the microarray data, and cluster of 
differentiation (CD) antigen genes that showed be-
tween a 2-fold and a 20-fold up-regulation in HPCs or 
that were positive in HPCs but negative in hepato-
cytes. The total RNA used in used in the microarray 
analysis was reverse transcribed, and cDNA was 
synthesized using a QuantiTect Reverse Transcription 
Kit. The qRT-PCR reactions were performed with 
Platinum® Sybr® Green qPCR SuperMix-UDG (Invi-
trogen) as previously described (24). Thermal cycling 
was performed in the ABI 7900HT Fast Real-Time 
PCR system (Applied Biosystems, CA, USA) under 
the following conditions: 50 °C for 2 min, 95 °C for 10 
min, and 35 cycles whose condition depended on the 
primers used (Tables 2 and 3). The target genes were 
assayed in five individual specimens and in triplicate 
on each plate. On each plate, GAPDH was used to 
normalize differences in cDNA concentration be-
tween samples. </p>

<p>Immunocytochemical characterization of 
HPCs </p>

<p>After the microarray and qRT-PCR analyses, 
seven previously reported marker proteins for HPCs 
and hepatocytes and two potential markers found in 
this study were measured by immunocytochemistry 
to characterize the HPC phenotype. HPCs were ana-
lyzed directly in the culture dishes by immunofluo-
rescence and staining with 3,3'-diaminobenzidine 
(DAB) with a FITC-conjugated or biotinylated sec-
ondary antibody and streptavidin-HRP. The culture 
medium was removed, and the cells were rinsed with 
PBS three times and fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde 
for 30 min at RT. The HPCs were then washed three 
times with PBS and permeabilized with 80% methanol 
for 15 min at -20 °C. Following the PBS washes, the 
cells were incubated with a blocking solution (PBS 
with 5% FBS) for 30 min at RT. The cells were then 
incubated overnight with primary antibodies (Table 
4), followed by incubation with nine fluoro-
chrome-coupled goat anti-mouse or mouse anti-goat 
IgG antibodies at 37°C for 1 hr. Between each anti-
body incubation step, the cells were washed three 
times with PBS. Omission of the primary antibodies or 
substitution with nonimmune goat, mouse, and rabbit 
IgG was used as control where appropriate. The flu-
orescently labeled cells were visualized by confocal 
laser scanning microscopy. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Table 2. Primers used for human HPC gene amplification </p>

<p>Gene 
NCBI accession number 
Gene Title 
Length 
Primer 
PTX3 
NM_002852.3 
pentraxin-related gene, rapidly induced by IL-1 beta 
180 
F 
TCAGGCTTTCCTCAGCATTT 
R 
CCAACACTGCAGACCAGAGA 
COL5A2 
NM_000393.3 
collagen, type V, alpha 2 
177 
F 
GGAAATGTGGGCAAGACTGT 
R 
TTGATGGTGGTGCTCATTGT 
COL1A1 
NM000088.3 
collagen, type I, alpha 1 
214 
F 
CCAAATCTGTCTCCCCAGAA 
R 
TCAAAAACGAAGGGGAGATG 
EFEMP1 
NM_004150.3 
EGF-containing fibulin-like extracellular matrix 
protein 1 </p>

<p>212 
F 
CAGGACACCGAAGAAACCAT 
R 
GTTTCCTGCTGAGGCTGTTC 
DKK3 
NM_013253.4 
dickkopf homolog 3 (Xenopus laevis) 
238 
F 
TTCATCCAGCAGTGTTGCTC 
R 
GGTGTGGGGTAGTGGAGAGA 
ACTA2 
NM_001613 
actin, alpha 2, smooth muscle, aorta 
222 
F 
TTCAATGTCCCAGCCATGTA 
R 
GAAGGAATAGCCACGCTCAG 
SLC16A4 
NM_004696 
solute carrier family 16, member 4 (monocarboxylic 
acid transporter 5) </p>

<p>198 
F 
TGGGATGGGACTGACTTTTC 
R 
CCATGTGCAGACAAACTGCT 
TPBG 
NM_006670.4 
trophoblast glycoprotein 
185 
F 
CTGGCTCAAGGAAACAGAGG 
R 
TAGCGCCTATCAGGGCTAAA 
MAP1B 
NM_005909.3 
microtubule-associated protein 1B 
204 
F 
ACTAAGCACCACCCATCCTG 
R 
GGAGATGGGACTTCCACTGA 
GJA1 
NM_000165.3 
gap junction protein, alpha 1, 43kDa 
249 
F 
ATGAGCAGTCTGCCTTTCGT 
R 
TCTGCTTCAAGTGCATGTCC 
CYBRD1 
NM_024843.3 
cytochrome b reductase 1 
150 
F 
GTCACACGGCTCATACATGG 
R 
CTACACCCCACTCCAGCAAT 
BCAT1 
NM_005504.5 
branched chain aminotransferase 1, cytosolic 
192 
F 
CACACAGCAGGAAGAGGTGA 
R 
CTCATAAGGAGCGCATAGCC 
ARMCX2 
NM_014782.5 
armadillo repeat containing, X-linked 2 
156 
F 
TCTGCTCTGGACACAGTTGG 
R 
TATTGCAGAAGCCATTGCAG 
SPARC 
NM-003118.2 
secreted protein, acidic, cysteine-rich (osteonectin) 
172 
F 
GTGCAGAGGAAACCGAAGAG 
R 
TCATTGCTGCACACCTTCTC 
ID4 
NM_001546.2 
inhibitor of DNA binding 4, dominant negative he-
lix-loop-helix protein </p>

<p>224 
F 
ATGGGATGAGGAAATGCTTG 
R 
TGGAGGAAGGAAAGCAGAAA 
PROCR 
NM_006404 
protein C receptor, endothelial (EPCR) 
211 
F 
GGTGTGGCTGTAGGCATCTT 
R 
CTCCCCTCCCTCAAATCTTC 
PDGFD 
NM_025208 
platelet derived growth factor D 
172 
F 
GTGGAGGAAATTGTGGCTGT 
R 
CGTTCATGGTGATCCAACTG 
COL4A2 
NM_001846.2 
collagen, type IV, alpha 2 
204 
F 
AAGGAATCATGGGCTTTCCT 
R 
CTCTGGCACCTTTTGCTAGG 
TIMP2 
NM_003255.4 
TIMP metallopeptidase inhibitor 2 
223 
F 
TGATCCACACACGTTGGTCT 
R 
TTTGAGTTGCTTGCAGGATG 
PAM 
NM_000919.2 
peptidylglycine alpha-amidating monooxygenase 
194 
F 
TTGCTCTTTGCAGTGAATGG 
R 
CACACGGTGTTGGTATGAGC </p>

<p>Table 3. Primers used for human HPC gene amplification </p>

<p>Gene 
NCBI accession number 
Length 
Primer 
CD24 
NM_013230.2 
188 
F 
AACTAATGCCACCACCAAGG 
R 
CCTGTTTTTCCTTGCCACAT 
CD44 
NM_000610.3 
233 
F 
AGCAACCAAGAGGCAAGAAA 
R 
GTGTGGTTGAAATGGTGCTG 
CD99 
NM_002414.3 
209 
F 
CTGGGCGGATGATGTTTACT 
R 
TCGATGGACACGTGATTTGT 
CD109 
NM_133493.3 
193 
F 
TGTCTCCTTCCCACATCCTC 
R 
CAGCTTCTTTCCCAAACTGC 
CD200 
NM_005944.5 
153 
F 
TGACCCAGCCCTATTTTACG 
R 
GGGAAAAGTTAACGCATGGA 
CD320 
NM_016579.2 
153 
F 
GGTCCCTGGACACTCCCTAT 
R 
TTTAATCGCCACCCTCAGAC </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Table 4. Antibodies used in immunocyto/histochemistry </p>

<p>Antigen 
Isotype 
Dilution 
Manufacturer 
Immunocytochemistry 
Immunohistochemistry 
Oval-6 
Monoclonal mouse IGg1 
1:100 
1:200 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
ALB 
Monoclonal goat IGg1 
1:500 
1:500 
Bethyl Laboratories 
CK 8 
Monoclonal mouse IGg1 
1:200 
1:200 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
CK 18 
Monoclonal mouse IGg1 
1:200 
1:200 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
CK 19 
Monoclonal mouse IGg2a 
1:200 
1:200 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
CD45 
Monoclonal mouse IGg1 
1:100 
1:200 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
CD90 
Polyclonal rabbit IGg 
1:400 
1:400 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
CD109 
Polyclonal rabbit or goat IGg 
1:100 
1:200 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology 
CD117(c-Kit) 
Polyclonal rabbit or goat IGg 
1:100 
1:300 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical localization of HPCs in 
human liver tissue </p>

<p>To validate potential HPC markers expressed in 
liver tissue, the same antibodies (except for ALB, be-
cause albumin is co-expressed in hepatocytes and 
HPCs) used for immunocytochemistry were used to 
detect the localization of HPCs in human liver tissue. 
Liver segments (1 to 2 g) were fixed with formalin and 
embedded in paraffin before sectioning. The sections 
(5-μm thick) were applied to poly-L-lysine-coated 
slides. Following an inactivation of endogenous pe-
roxidases with 3% H 2 O 2 for 10 min at RT, the sections 
were incubated overnight with primary antibodies 
(Table 4). Control experiments included omission of 
the primary antibodies and substitution of the pri-
mary antibodies with nonimmune rabbit or mouse 
IgG. Subsequently, the sections were washed with 
PBS three times and incubated with the appropriate 
secondary antibodies at 37°C for 1 hr. After the reac-
tion with DAB Chromogen, the sections were rinsed 
with distilled water, counterstained with hematoxy-
lin, and mounted with Histomount solution (Invitro-
gen), and the labeled cells were visualized with an 
inverted microscope (Nikon, Eclipse E200, Tokyo, 
Japan), and digital images were captured using 
Nis-elements F 3.0 software. Omission of the primary 
antibody or substitution with an unrelated IgG served 
as a negative control. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Only those genes detected as present or absent in 
triplicate arrays were reported as expressed or 
non-expressed genes. The data were analyzed by the 
chi-square test using <rs id="software-4" type="software">SPSS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 16.0</rs>. The 
level of significance for all statistical analyses was P &lt; 
0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Morphological characteristics of HPCs </p>

<p>Many small, scattered and flattened colonies 
were observed under phase-contrast microscopy (Fig. </p>

<p>1) after an initial 7 days of culture. These loose colony 
cells displayed several morphologic characteristics of 
HPCs, such as a round or oval shape and a convex 
cytoplasm. These cells proliferated slowly and formed 
sharply bordered colonies (Fig. 1A-C). After 10 days 
of culture, the cells had a polygonal shape with a low 
cytoplasm/nucleus ratio and started to expand (Fig. 
1D). The colony-forming cells reached confluence 
after 2 weeks (Fig. 1E, F). There was no evidence that 
the human hepatocytes were contaminated, as evalu-
ated by phase-contrast microscopy. All cultured HPCs 
prepared from the different liver specimens exhibited 
similar morphologic characteristics. </p>

<p>Bipotential ability </p>

<p>The bipotential HPC characteristics were 
demonstrated via culture in multilineage differentia-
tion conditions in vitro. The adipogenic differentiation 
of the HPCs was demonstrated by Oil Red O staining, 
and lipid droplets were visible in the differentiated 
adipocytes on day 10 after the induction of differenti-
ation (Fig. 1G). Hepatogenesis was characterized by 
morphology. Under phase-contrast microscopy, the 
differentiated cells showed hepatocyte-like polygonal 
morphology with low cytoplasm/nucleus ratios (Fig. 
1H). Cholangiogenic identification indicated that dif-
ferentiated cholangiocytes were positive for CK19 
(Fig. 1I). These results demonstrated that the isolated 
and cultured HPCs exhibited the classic bipotential 
progenitor cell characteristics. </p>

<p>Gene transcriptional profiles </p>

<p>The Pearson correlation coefficient for compar-
ing gene expression profiles of the same cell types, 
isolated from different liver specimens, was 0.90 to 
0.96 for HPCs and 0.91 to 0.95 for hepatocytes (Fig. 2). 
These data indicate that there was great similarity in 
gene expression between the biological replicates. As 
shown in the Venn diagram in Fig. 3, HPCs and hu-
man hepatocytes share a similar transcriptome. 
Among the 5,054 probe sets/genes present in HPCs, 
67.8% (3427/5054) of the probe sets/genes were also 
expressed in the primary hepatocytes. Conversely, </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>when this similarity was represented as a percentage 
of the probe sets/genes in the primary hepatocytes 
that were also expressed in the HPCs, the similarity 
reached 88.9% (3427/3857). These values indicate a 
high degree of similarity between the gene transcrip-
tional profiles of HPCs and primary hepatocytes. 
Further analysis of global gene expression 
showed that 21 probe sets/genes (Table 5) were 
up-regulated by more than 20-fold in HPCs compared 
to primary hepatocytes. Among those genes were a 
progenitor cell marker (CD90, 39.3-fold), pentrax-
in-related gene (PTX3, 120.5-fold), collagen proteins 
(COL5A2, 88.4-fold; COL1A1, 80.9-fold; and COL4A2, 
20.8-fold), cytokines (EGF, 74.1-fold and PDGFD, 
21.6-fold), hepatocyte-related metabolic enzymes 
(CYBRD1, 27.3-fold; BCAT1, 26.2-fold; TIMP2, 
20.7-fold and PAM, 20.4-fold), a secreted protein 
(SPARC, 23.8-fold) and the endothelial protein C re-
ceptor (PROCR, 22.1-fold). Among 12 previously re-</p>

<p>ported marker genes for HPCs and hepatocytes (Table 
6) that were analyzed in this study, 10 genes were 
expressed in both HPCs and hepatocytes, including 
CD90 (with the above-mentioned 39.3-fold relative 
up-regulation in HPCs) and four genes whose ex-
pression was more than 2-fold but less than 20-fold in 
HPCs relative to primary hepatocytes (CK19, 
18.2-fold; CD45, 6.1-fold; CD117, 5.2-fold; and CK8, 
2.8-fold). CK18 was expressed at the same level 
(1.0-fold) in both cells. In contrast, AFP and ALB were 
expressed at a lower level in HPCs than in hepato-
cytes (AFP, 0.3-fold and ALB, 0.2-fold). Three other 
mature hepatocyte marker genes (GS, TAT and G6PD) 
were absent in HPCs but present in hepatocytes. CD34 
was absent in both cells. Moreover, CD109 genes were 
also expressed more than 2-fold (2.5-fold) in HPCs 
compared to hepatocytes. Five other surface marker 
genes (CD24, CD44, CD99, CD200 and CD320) were 
present in HPCs but absent in hepatocytes (Table 7). </p>

<p>Figure 1. The morphology of HPCs and HPCs differentiated into adipocytes, hepatocytes and cholangiocytes. Under phase-contrast microscopy, small and 
flattened colonies were observed after an initial 7-day culture (A, day 3; B, day 5; C, day 7). The colonies of loosely packed cells displayed a round or oval 
shape and a convex cytoplasm. After 10 days of culture, these cells exhibited a clear and larger cytoplasm, became polygonal and densely packed, and began 
to expand (D, day 10; E, day 15; F, day 20). After 10 days differentiation, differentiated adipocytes contained lipid droplets (G), differentiated hepatocytes 
exhibited a polygonal morphology with a low cytoplasm/nucleus ratio (H) and differentiated cholangiocyte were positive for CK19 (I). Original magnifi-
cation: large view, A-D, 4x; E-F, 10x; small view, A-F, 20x; G, 40 x; H-I, 20 x. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 2. A hierarchical cluster dendrogram of selected genes. The Pearson correlation coefficient was 0.90 to 0.96 for HPCs and 0.91 to 0.95 for 
hepatocytes. HPC, hepatic progenitor cells; Hep, hepatocytes. </p>

<p>Figure 3. A Venn diagram showing that HPCs and primary human hepatocytes had similar transcriptomes. Among the 5,054 probe sets/genes present in 
HPCs, 67.8% (3427/5054) probe sets/genes were also expressed in primary hepatocytes. Conversely, among 3,857 probe sets/genes expressed in primary 
hepatocytes, 88.9% (3427/3857) were also expressed in HPCs. HPC-P 5,054, total number of probe sets/genes present in HPCs; Hep-P3857, total number 
of probe sets/genes present in primary hepatocytes. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Table 5. Genes with &gt;20-fold up-regulation in HPCs </p>

<p>Probe ID 
Gene 
Representative 
Public ID </p>

<p>Fold* 
Gene Title </p>

<p>206157_at 
PTX3 
NM_002852 
120.5 ±13.6 
pentraxin-related gene, rapidly induced by IL-1 beta 
221729_at 
COL5A2 
AL575735 
88.4 ±10.5 
collagen, type V, alpha 2 
1556499_s_at 
COL1A1 
BE221212 
80.9 ±6.2 
collagen, type I, alpha 1 
201842_s_at 
EFEMP1 
AI826799 
74.1 ±8.2 
EGF-containing fibulin-like extracellular matrix protein 1 
214247_s_at 
DKK3 
AU148057 
57.2 ±7.42 
dickkopf homolog 3 (Xenopus laevis) 
200974_at 
ACTA2 
NM_001613 
55.0 ±6.5 
actin, alpha 2, smooth muscle, aorta 
213869_x_at 
CD90 
AL558479 
39.3 ±4.2 
Thy-1 cell surface antigen 
205234_at 
SLC16A4 
NM_004696 
35.3 ±4.9 
solute carrier family 16, member 4 (monocarboxylic acid transporter 5) 
203476_at 
TPBG 
NM_006670 
29.2 ±4.3 
trophoblast glycoprotein 
212233_at 
MAP1B 
AL523076 
28.9 ±4.2 
microtubule-associated protein 1B 
201667_at 
GJA1 
NM_000165 
27.7 ±3.3 
gap junction protein, alpha 1, 43kDa 
222453_at 
CYBRD1 
AL136693 
27.3 ±3.9 
cytochrome b reductase 1 
226517_at 
BCAT1 
AL390172 
26.2 ±3.7 
branched chain aminotransferase 1, cytosolic 
203404_at 
ARMCX2 
NM_014782 
24.1 ±3.5 
armadillo repeat containing, X-linked 2 
200665_s_at 
SPARC 
NM_003118 
23.8 ±4.2 
secreted protein, acidic, cysteine-rich (osteonectin) 
209291_at 
ID4 
AW157094 
22.5 ±4.6 
inhibitor of DNA binding 4, dominant negative helix-loop-helix protein 
203650_at 
PROCR 
NM_006404 
22.1 ±4.01 
protein C receptor, endothelial (EPCR) 
219304_s_at 
PDGFD 
NM_025208 
21.6 ±3.9 
platelet derived growth factor D 
211964_at 
COL4A2 
X05610 
20.8 ±4.2 
collagen, type IV, alpha 2 
224560_at 
TIMP2 
BF107565 
20.7 ±3.1 
TIMP metallopeptidase inhibitor 2 
202336_s_at 
PAM 
NM_000919 
20.4 ±3.3 
peptidylglycine alpha-amidating monooxygenase </p>

<p>*Fold increase in hepatic progenitor cells vs. hepatocytes. The fold change between the two groups was calculated from the normalized average mRNA expression level in each group. </p>

<p>Table 6. Microarray data validated by qRT-PCR: the fold change of mRNA expression between HPCs and hepatocytes </p>

<p>Gene 
Microarray 
qRT-PCR 
Gene Title 
HPC 
Hep 
Fold (M ± SD) a 
Fold (M ± SD) b 
CD90 
P 
P 
39.3 ±4.2 
21.5 ± 4.8 
also known as Thy-1 
CK19 
P 
P 
18.2 ± 2.5 
12.5 ± 2.4 
cytokeratin 19 
CD45 
P 
P 
6.1 ± 1.5 
3.2 ± 0.5 
CD45 
CD117 
P 
P 
5.2 ± 1.3 
2.5 ± 1.4 
also known as c-kit, stem cell factor receptor 
CK8 
P 
P 
2.8 ± 0.5 
2.1 ± 0.2 
cytokeratin 8 
CK18 
P 
P 
1.0 ± 0.3 
2.3 ± 0.1 
cytokeratin 18 
AFP 
P 
P 
0.3 ± 0.1 
0.1 ± 0.01 
a-fetoprotein 
ALB 
P 
P 
0.2 ± 0.01 
0.1 ± 0.01 
albumin 
GS 
A 
P 
N/A 
A/A 
glutamine synthase 
TAT 
A 
P 
N/A 
A/A 
tyrosine aminotransferase 
G6PD 
A 
P 
N/A 
A/A 
glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase 
CD34 
A 
A 
N/A 
A/A 
CD34 </p>

<p>a : The fold change in mRNA expression between HPCs and hepatocytes as determined by microarray analysis was calculated from three chips in each group. b : The fold change in mRNA 
expression between HPCs and hepatocytes as measured by real-time RT-PCR; the results of qRT-PCR are representative of five individual samples, and PCR was performed in triplicate for 
each sample. A, absent; P, present; N/A, not applicable; A/A, absent from both kinds of cells. </p>

<p>Table 7. Microarray data validated by qRT-PCR: the fold change 
of mRNA expression between HPCs and hepatocytes </p>

<p>Gene 
Microarray 
qRT-PCR 
HPC 
Hep 
Fold (M ± SD) a 
Fold (M ± SD) b 
CD24 
P 
A 
N/A 
A/A 
CD44 
P 
A 
N/A 
A/A 
CD99 
P 
A 
N/A 
A/A 
CD109 
P 
P 
2.5 ± 0.6 
3.4 ± 0.5 
CD200 
P 
A 
N/A 
A/A 
CD320 
P 
A 
N/A 
A/A </p>

<p>a : The fold change in mRNA expression between HPCs and hepatocytes as determined by 
microarray analysis was calculated from three chips in each group. b : The fold change in 
mRNA expression between HPCs and hepatocytes as measured by real-time RT-PCR; the 
qRT-PCR results represent five individual samples, and PCR was performed in triplicate 
for each sample. A, absent; P, present; N/A, not applicable; A/A, absent from both kinds 
of cells. </p>

<p>RT-PCR showed that the colony-forming cells 
were positive for several previously reported marker 
genes for HPCs and hepatocytes (Fig. 4). The hepato-
cyte marker genes ALB, CK8 and CK18 exhibited 
strong expression in both cells, whereas AFP was ex-
pressed weakly in HPCs. The cholangiocyte marker 
genes CK7 and CK19 were expressed at an intermedi-
ate level in HPCs but were negative in hepatocytes. 
The progenitor marker gene CD90 exhibited strong 
expression, and CD45, CD117 and vimentin (VIM) ex-
hibited intermediate expression in HPCs but were 
negative in hepatocytes. The hematopoietic cell 
marker CD34 and mature hepatocyte markers TAT, 
GS and G6PD were negative in HPCs and strongly 
positive in hepatocytes. These results were consistent 
with the microarray findings. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 4. RT-PCR analysis of HPC-specific genes. HPCs were positive for 
ALB, AFP (weakly), CK8, CK18, CK19, CD45, CD90 and CD117 but negative 
for CD34, TAT, GS and G6PD. Lane HPC, samples from HPCs; Lane Hep, 
samples from primary hepatocytes. Lane M, DNA marker. </p>

<p>Validation of mRNA expression of selected 
genes by qRT-PCR </p>

<p>To validate the results of the microarray analysis, 
21 enriched genes with a greater than 20-fold 
up-regulation, 12 HPC and hepatocyte marker genes 
described in the literature and six surface marker 
genes present in HPCs were further analyzed by 
qRT-PCR. The validation experiment for the 21 
HPC-enriched genes showed similar results of mi-
croarray (Table 8) in that these genes experienced a 
6.5-fold to 78.1-fold up-regulation. Similarly, for the 
12 previously described HPC and hepatocyte markers 
(Table 6), six presented a 2.1-fold to 21.5-fold 
up-regulation in HPCs (CD90, 21.5-fold; CK19, 
12.5-fold; CD45, 3.2-fold; CD117, 2.5-fold; CK8, 
2.1-fold; CK18, 2.3-fold), two were weakly expressed 
in HPCs compared to hepatocytes (AFP, 0.1-fold; ALB, 
0.1-fold), and 4 (CD34, TAT, GS and G6PD) were ab-
sent in HPCs. The validation of six surface marker 
genes (Table 7) showed that CD109 presented a 
3.4-fold up-regulation in HPCs compared to hepato-
cytes, while the other five genes (CD24, CD44, CD99, 
CD200 and CD320) were absent in both cell types. 
These data indicate a high degree of consistency be-
tween the microarray and qRT-PCR analyses. </p>

<p>Table 8. Microarray data validated by qRT-PCR: the fold change of mRNA expression between HPCs and hepatocytes. </p>

<p>Gene 
Microarray 
qRT-PCR 
Gene Title 
Fold (M ± SD) a 
Fold (M ± SD) b 
PTX3 
120.5 ±13.6 
78.1±10.5 
pentraxin-related gene, rapidly induced by IL-1 beta 
COL5A2 
88.4 ±10.5 
43.6 ±7.2 
collagen, type V, alpha 2 
COL1A1 
80.9 ±6.2 
41.1 ±6.1 
collagen, type I, alpha 1 
EFEMP1 
74.1 ±8.2 
46.2 ±8.3 
EGF-containing fibulin-like extracellular matrix protein 1 
DKK3 
57.2 ±7.42 
36.5 ±4.6 
dickkopf homolog 3 (Xenopus laevis) 
ACTA2 
55.0 ±6.5 
48.2 ±4.3 
actin, alpha 2, smooth muscle, aorta 
CD90 
39.3 ±4.2 
21.5 ±3.2 
Thy-1 cell surface antigen 
SLC16A4 
35.3 ±4.9 
17.1 ±4.2 
solute carrier family 16, member 4 (monocarboxylic acid transporter 5) 
TPBG 
29.2 ±4.3 
16.7 ±2.8 
trophoblast glycoprotein 
MAP1B 
28.9 ±4.2 
18.1 ±3.4 
microtubule-associated protein 1B 
GJA1 
27.7 ±3.3 
15.8 ±4.6 
gap junction protein, alpha 1, 43kDa 
CYBRD1 
27.3 ±3.9 
15.1 ±2.9 
cytochrome b reductase 1 
BCAT1 
26.2 ±3.7 
9.6 ±3.1 
branched chain aminotransferase 1, cytosolic 
ARMCX2 
24.1 ±3.5 
18.2 ±3.7 
armadillo repeat containing, X-linked 2 
SPARC 
23.8 ±4.2 
19.0 ±4.2 
secreted protein, acidic, cysteine-rich (osteonectin) 
ID4 
22.5 ±4.6 
7.4±1.8 
inhibitor of DNA binding 4, dominant negative helix-loop-helix protein 
PROCR 
22.1 ±4.01 
6.5±1.4 
protein C receptor, endothelial (EPCR) 
PDGFD 
21.6 ±3.9 
6.9±2.1 
platelet derived growth factor D 
COL4A2 
20.8 ±4.2 
15.7±3.3 
collagen, type IV, alpha 2 
TIMP2 
20.7 ±3.1 
12.7±2.4 
TIMP metallopeptidase inhibitor 2 
PAM 
20.4 ±3.3 
13.2±2.8 
peptidylglycine alpha-amidating monooxygenase </p>

<p>a : The fold change in mRNA expression between HPCs and hepatocytes as determined by microarray analysis was calculated from three chips in each group. b : The fold change in mRNA 
expression between HPCs and hepatocytes as measured by real-time RT-PCR; the results of qRT-PCR are representative of five individual samples, and PCR was performed in triplicate for 
each sample. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Immunocyto/histochemistry expression 
analysis </p>

<p>Immunocytochemical characterization of cul-
tured HPCs (Fig. 5) showed that these cells were con-
sistently positive for the progenitor-specific markers 
Oval-6, CD90 and CD117; hepatocyte-specific markers 
CK8, CK18 and ALB; and cholangiocyte-specific 
markers CK19. Cultured HPCs were also positive for 
the hematopoietic cell markers CD45 and CD109 after 
3 weeks of culture. The images of negative control are 
showed in the Fig. 6. 
To characterize the localization of HPCs within 
normal liver tissue, the same markers used for im-
munocytochemistry were analyzed in individual liver 
specimens from which HPCs and primary hepato-
cytes had been isolated. Immunohistochemical stain-
ing of the liver specimens (Fig. 7) indicated that most 
of the cells positive for 1 of the 8 selected markers 
were localized in periportal areas and the canal of 
Hering. The progenitor-specific markers Oval-6 (Fig. </p>

<p>7A), CD90 (Fig. 7F) and CD117 (Fig. 7H) labeled cells 
that were scattered in small ductular regions/canals 
of Hering, and these cells were not associated with 
bile ductule-like structures. The cholangio-
cyte-specific markers CK19 (Fig. 7C) labeled cells that 
were scattered in the periportal area, and some of 
these cells resembled bile ductule walls. Although the 
CK8 (Fig. 7D) and CK18 (Fig. 7B) stained weakly 
throughout most of each liver section, the cells highly 
expressing these two markers could easily be distin-
guished from surrounding hepatocytes. The cells that 
expressed the hematopoietic cell markers CD45 (Fig. 
7E) and CD109 (Fig. 7G) appeared similar to the 
CK18-positive cells located in the periportal areas and 
the canals of Hering. CD45 (see Table 6 and Fig. 7E) 
and CD109 (see Table 7 and Fig. 7G) were commonly 
expressed in hepatocytes and progenitor-like cells. 
The images of negative control are showed in the Fig. 
8. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Immunocytochemical staining showing that the colony-forming cells were consistently positive for the progenitor-specific markers Oval-6 (A), 
CD90 (F) and CD117 (H); the hepatocyte-specific markers ALB (I), CK18 (B) and CK8 (D); and the cholangiocyte-specific markers CK19 (C). These cells 
were also positive for two hematopoietic cell markers CD45 (E) and CD109 (G). Original magnification, 20x. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 6. The negative control of immunocytochemical staining. A-I were Oval-6, CK18, CK19, CK8, CD45, CD90, CD109, CD117 and ALB respectively. 
Original magnification, 20x. </p>

<p>Figure 7. Immunohistological staining showing that cells positive for the progenitor-specific markers Oval-6 (A), CD90 (F) and CD117 (H) were scattered 
in the small ductular region/canals of Hering and that these cells were not associated with bile ductule-like structures. Cells positive for the cholangio-
cyte-specific marker CK19 (C) were scattered in the periportal area, and some of these cells resembled the walls of bile ductules. CK8 (D) and CK18 (B) 
were weakly expressed in hepatocytes and strongly expressed in HPCs. The cells expressing hematopoietic cell markers CD45 (E) and CD109 (G) were 
located in the periportal areas and the canals of Hering. Black arrow: specific marker positive HPCs. White arrow in C: specific marker positive cells 
resembled bile ductule wall. White arrow in B and D: specific marker positive hepatocytes. Original magnification: 20x. </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 8. The negative control of immunohistochemical staining. A-I were Oval-6, CK18, CK19, CK8, CD45, CD90, CD109 and CD117 respectively. 
Original magnification, 20x. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Numerous studies have shown that HPCs 
mainly participate in liver regeneration following 
acute and chronic hepatic damage (11, 16, 40). Alt-
hough many reports have demonstrated that progen-
itor cell populations can be isolated from injured ro-
dent and dog livers (25, 41-43), only a few research 
groups have successfully isolated HPCs from adult 
human liver (30-36). The distinction between hepato-
cytes and HPCs in human liver is controversial. 
A summary of previously published phenotypic 
characteristics of human HPCs is shown in Table 9. A 
total of 38 potential marker genes have been identified 
in human HPCs in seven publications. Herrera et al. 
(30) isolated and characterized a population of human 
liver stem cells that were positive for CD29, CD44, 
CD73, CD90, VIM, nestin, ALB, AFP, CK8 and CK18 
and negative for CK19, CD34, CD45, CD117 and 
CD133. Schmelzer et al. (32) characterized the phe-
notypes of pluripotent human hepatic progenitors, 
which were positive for CK19, NCAM, EpCAM, 
CLDN3 and ALB and negative for AFP and adult liv-
er-specific proteins. Dan et al. (31) described mul-
tipotent progenitor cells isolated from human fetal </p>

<p>liver that expressed CD34, CD90, CD117, EpCAM, 
c-met, SSEA-4, VIM, CK18 and CK19 but not ALB or 
AFP. Duret et al. (33) characterized a population of 
nonparenchymal epithelial cells from adult human 
liver that expressed AAT, CK7, CK18 and CK19 as 
well as a low level of ALB but not REX1, AFP, CD34, 
CD90, CD117 or Oval-6. Terrace et al. (34) described 
HPCs isolated from developing human liver that were 
positive for CK18, CK19, ALB, E-cadherin, dlk/pref-1, 
CD90, CD34 and VIM, and these cells were located in 
the portal vein endothelium. Stachelscheid et al. (35) 
and Jozefczuk et al. (36) isolated and characterized 
adult human liver progenitors from ischemic liver 
tissue; these cells were positive for EpCAM, CK7, 
CK8, CK18, CK19, VIM, CYP2B6, ALB, A1AT, γ-GT 
and HNF4 but negative for AFP and CD90. 
In this study, the HPCs isolated from adult hu-
man liver exhibited morphological characteristics 
similar to those described previously (33). These cells 
possessed bipotential differentiation characteristics 
formed colonies after 3 days and presented polygonal, 
densely packed cytoplasm after 10 days in culture. 
Global gene expression analysis of these cells revealed 
a high similarity (67.8%) to primary hepatocytes. 
Compared with primary hepatocytes, 21 genes </p>

<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>



<p>up-regulated more than 20-fold in HPCs were de-
tected, including the progenitor marker CD90, four 
genes related to hepatocyte metabolism (CYBRD1, 
BCAT1, TIMP2 and PAM) and two cytokine genes 
(EGF, PDGFD). The HPC-enriched genes detected by 
microarray analysis were validated by qRT-PCR, with 
consistent results. Further analysis showed that most 
previously reported marker genes for HPCs (ALB, 
AFP, CK8, CK18, CK19, CD90, CD117 and Oval-6) 
were positive in our cultured HPCs. Moreover, two 
hematopoietic cell markers CD45 and CD109 were 
detected in HPCs. Five cell-surface markers and three 
mature hepatocyte-specific genes were not detected in 
HPCs by microarray or qRT-PCR analysis. The po-
tential markers mentioned above were also confirmed 
at 
the 
protein 
level 
by 
immuno-
cyto/immunohistochemistry, with consistent results. 
Although the morphology of the cells expressing 
Oval-6 and CD90 (Fig 6A and F) in human livers </p>

<p>seems different from that of the cells expressing CD45 
and CD109 (Fig 6E and G). It is possible that these 
cells were at the different stages of growth and de-
velopment. 
In summary, our data show that HPCs isolated 
from adult human liver are highly similar to cultured 
primary hepatocytes in their transcriptional profiles, 
and those gene expression data are in accordance with 
immunohistological staining of hepatocytes in liver 
sections. In addition to eight established marker 
genes/proteins (ALB, AFP, CK8, CK18, CK19, CD90, 
CD117 and Oval-6), the novel markers CD45 and 
CD109 can potentially be utilized to identify and iso-
late HPCs for further cytotherapy of liver diseases. 
Based on our findings, future studies should be con-
ducted to validate these two novel HPC-specific 
markers and their roles in hepatocyte development 
and liver regeneration. </p>

<p>Table 9. Phenotypic characteristics of human HPCs in comparison with described markers in publications </p>

<p>Reference 
Positive 
Negative 
Dan et al. (31) 
CK18, CK19, CD34, CD90, CD117, EpCAM, Vimentin c-Met, SSEA-4 
ALB, AFP 
Herrera et al. (30) 
CK8, CK18, CD29, CD44, CD73, CD90, Vimentin, Nestin, ALB, AFP 
CK19, CD34, CD45, CD117, 
CD133 
Schmelzer et al. (32) 
CK19, NCAM, EpCAM, CLDN3, ALB (low) 
AFP 
Duret et al. (33) 
CK7, CK18, CK19, ALB (low), AAT 
REX1, AFP, CD34, CD90, 
CD117, OV-6 
Terrace et al. (34) 
CK18, CK19, CD34, CD90, ALB, E-cadherin, dlk/pref-1, Vimentin 
Stachelscheid et al. (35) 
CK7, CK8, CK18, CK19, EpCAM, Vimentin, CYP2B6, ALB (intermediate), A1AT (inter-
mediate), γ-GT, HNF4 (low) </p>

<p>AFP, CD90 </p>

<p>Jozefczuk et al. (36) 
CK7, CK8, CK18, CK19, CD24, CD133, EpCAM, Vimentin, CYP1B1, ABCC4, ANXA3, 
ANXA1, CLDN4, DDR1, GABRP, ITGB4, MUC1, S100A3, ALB (intermediate), A1AT 
(intermediate), HNF4 (low) </p>

<p>AFP, CD90 </p>

<p>Li, et al. (this study) 
CK8, CK18, CK19, CD45, CD90, CD109, CD117, OV-6, ALB, AFP, PTX3, COL5A2, 
COL1A1, EFEMP1, DKK3, ACTA2, SLC16A4, TPBG, MAP1B, GJA1, CYBRD1, BCAT1, 
ARMCX2, SPARC, ID4, PROCR, PDGFD, COL4A2, TIMP2, PAM </p>

<p>CD24, CD34, CD44, CD99, 
CD200, D320, TAT, GS, G6PD </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Zhejiang Pro-
vincial and National Natural Science Foundation of 
China (LR13H030001, 81271708), Chinese High Tech 
Research 
and 
Development 
(863) 
Program 
(2013AA020102), and National S&amp;T Major Project 
(2012ZX10004503-006, 2012ZX10002004-001). </p>

<p>Competing Interests </p>

<p>The authors have declared that no competing 
interest exists. </p>



<p>Int. J. Med. Sci. 2014, Vol. 11 </p>

<p>http://www.medsci.org </p>





</text></tei>