<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3984761" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Objective: In the wake of intracerebral hemorrhage (ICH), a devastating stroke 
with no effective treatment, hemoglobin/iron-induced oxidative injury leads to 
neuronal loss and poor neurologic outcomes. (-)-Epicatechin (EC), a brain-per-
meable flavanol that modulates redox/oxidative stress via the NF-E2-related 
factor (Nrf) 2 pathway, has been shown to be beneficial for vascular and cogni-
tive function in humans. Here, we examined whether EC can reduce early brain 
injury in ICH mouse models and investigated the underlying mechanisms. 
Methods: ICH was induced by injecting collagenase, autologous blood, or 
thrombin into mouse striatum. EC was administered orally at 3 h after ICH 
and then every 24 h. Lesion volume, neurologic deficits, brain edema, reactive 
oxygen species, and protein expression and activity were evaluated. Results: EC 
significantly reduced lesion volume and ameliorated neurologic deficits in both 
male and female ICH mice. Cell death and neuronal degeneration were 
decreased in the perihematomal area and were associated with reductions in 
caspase-3 activity and high-mobility group protein B1 (HMGB-1) level. These 
changes were accompanied by attenuation of oxidative insults, increased phase 
II enzyme expression, and increased Nrf2 nuclear accumulation. Interestingly, 
in addition to providing neuroprotection via Nrf2 signaling, EC diminished 
heme oxygenase-1 induction and brain iron deposition via an Nrf2-independent 
pathway that downregulated ICH-induced activating protein-1 activation and 
decreased matrix metalloproteinase 9 activity, lipocalin-2 levels, iron-dependent 
cell death, and ferroptosis-related gene expression. Interpretation: Collectively, 
our data show that EC protects against ICH by activation of Nrf2-dependent 
and -independent pathways and may serve as a potential intervention for 
patients with ICH. </p>

<p>Intracerebral hemorrhage (ICH) is the stroke subtype 
with the highest mortality and morbidity. Unfortunately, 
this condition has received far less research attention than 
has ischemic stroke. 1 In the aftermath of ICH, in addition 
to the hematoma causing primary physical compression, 
blood components, hemoglobin, and nonheme iron ele-
vate the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS), 
which contribute to secondary brain injury. 2,3 Evidence 
suggests that excessive hemoglobin and iron released from 
the hematoma accumulate in the brain parenchyma, caus-
ing neurotoxicity and accelerating neurodegeneration. 4,5 </p>

<p>Recently, iron-dependent, nonapoptotic cell death known 
as ferroptosis has been identified as a potential therapeu-
tic target to reduce iron-related cell death. 6 Strategies to 
limit iron toxicity and ROS production could be used to 
reduce brain injury 7 and improve quality of life in 
patients with ICH. 3 
The NF-E2-related factor (Nrf) 2/antioxidant response 
element (ARE) pathway plays a pivotal role in orchestrat-
ing expression of the phase II detoxification and antioxi-
dant genes that combat the pathogenic events associated 
with ICH. 8 Although most products of the Nrf2/ARE 
pathway are protective, heme oxygenase 1 (HO-1), which 
is responsible for iron metabolism, appears to act as a </p>

<p>258 </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and 
distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>prooxidant in the ICH brain. 9 No clear link between 
detoxification of iron overload and Nrf2 activation has 
been reported. Nevertheless, our previous studies in Nrf2-
and HO-1-deficient mice confirmed the neuroprotective 
function of Nrf2 and deleterious effects of HO-1 in the 
pathologic process of ICH. 10,11 Although free radical scav-
enger interventions hold promise for treating ICH, their 
lack of success in clinical trials argues for additional 
investigation. 12,13 
Another potential target for manipulating ICH insults 
is activator protein (AP)-1, a dimeric transcription factor 
composed of a-fetoprotein, Jun, or Fos protein subunits 
that bind to a common DNA site. 14 AP-1 activation leads 
to the expression of many proinflammatory mediators, 
including matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs), which con-
tribute to blood-brain barrier (BBB) breakdown and exac-
erbate brain edema in both hemorrhagic and ischemic 
stroke models. 15,16 Although inhibition or deletion of 
MMPs was shown to be neuroprotective in a mouse 
model of ICH, 17,18 the role of AP-1 in ICH remains to be 
elucidated. 
The cerebrovascular benefits of fruits, vegetables, and 
green tea have been ascribed in part to the polyphenols 
present, particularly flavanols. 19,20 Cocoa and green tea are 
enriched with flavanols such as epicatechins, catechins, and 
procyanidins. Oral consumption of (-)-epicatechin (EC) 
elicits positive effects on vascular function, cognition, and 
ischemic brain injury in animals and humans. 21-23 Addi-
tionally, pharmacokinetic studies of EC have shown that it 
can penetrate the BBB after intravenous or oral administra-
tion in rats. 24-26 This simple molecule scavenges prooxi-
dants and free radicals through activation of the Nrf2 
signaling pathway. 23,27,28 However, whether EC can activate 
Nrf2 in the brain after ICH is still unknown. 
In this study, we examined whether oral EC adminis-
tration after ICH provides neuroprotection in mice and 
investigated potential underlying molecular mechanisms. 
We specifically tested the therapeutic efficacy of EC on 
early ICH-induced brain injury because half of human 
deaths occur within the first 2 days. 13,29,30 We conclude 
that the flavanol EC could potentially be a therapeutic 
agent for treating ICH. Moreover, the results indicate that 
EC achieves this protective effect through Nrf2-dependent 
and alternative Nrf2-independent pathways. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>This study was conducted in accordance with the National 
Institutes of Health guidelines for the use of experimental 
animals. Experimental protocols were approved by the 
Johns Hopkins University Animal Care and Use Commit-</p>

<p>tee. Twelve-month-old (30-36 g) C57BL/6 male and 
female mice (Charles River Laboratories, Germantown, 
MD), specific gene-deficient mice (Nrf2 knockout [KO], 
HO-1 KO), and wild-type (WT) littermates were bred in a 
pathogen-free environment. Nrf2 KO mice and HO-1 KO 
mice were originally generated by Masayuki Yamamoto 31 
and by Drs. Poss and Tonegawa, 32 respectively. Mice were 
genotyped for Nrf2 and HO-1 status by polymerase chain 
reaction (PCR) amplification of genomic DNA extracted 
from tail snips. 10,11 </p>

<p>Experimental groups </p>

<p>Mice were randomly assigned to receive vehicle (sterilized 
water; Hospira, Chicago, IL) or 5, 15, or 45 mg/kg EC 
(Sigma, St. Louis, MO) by gavage at 3 h after ICH and 
then every 24 h thereafter for 72 h. Studies have shown 
that one oral dose of EC (30 mg/kg) can cross the BBB 24-
26,33 and provide marked neuroprotection in b-amyloid-, 
N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA)-, and ischemia-induced 
brain injury. 23,34 We chose the delivery route, dosing, 
and treatment regimens for EC based on previous 
work 22-24,26,34,35 and our preliminary tests. By characteriz-
ing the purity and stability of EC (Fig. S1), we deter-
mined that the compound remained stable in water for 
24 h, which was established as a suitable window for sam-
ple usage. An experimenter blind to treatment group 
tested the mice on a 24-point neurologic scoring sys-
tem 11,36 before EC administration. Mice that had neuro-
logic deficit scores greater than 20 or less than 3 were 
excluded from the study. A total of 172 WT mice were 
allocated into the vehicle group and 216 into the EC 
groups. Fifty-two mice were excluded because of severe 
neurologic deficit (vehicle: 5/172, EC: 7/216) or death 
(vehicle: 18/172; EC: 22/216). Five Nrf2 KO mice were 
excluded because of neurologic deficit standard or death. 
Sixty-six additional sham-operated WT, Nrf2 KO, and 
HO-1 KO and WT control mice were used for histology, 
biochemical assays, and reverse transcriptase PCR (n = 5-
10/group). No animals were excluded from analysis once 
they proceeded into the tests. All behavioral, anatomical, 
and biochemical measures and analyses were carried out 
with a blinded experimental design according to pub-
lished guidelines. 37-39 
For complete details of all the experimental procedures, 
see Data S1. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean AE SD. We evaluated all 
behavioral tests by two-way repeated measure analysis of 
variance (ANOVA) to detect significant differences 
between and among treatment groups. In anatomical and </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>C.-F. Chang et al. 
Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH </p>

<p>biochemical studies, one-way or two-way ANOVA was 
used for comparisons among multiple groups. Bonferroni 
post hoc analysis was used to determine where those dif-
ferences occurred. Differences between two groups were 
tested with the Student's t-test (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SigmaStat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.5</rs>; Systat Soft-
ware Inc., San Jose, CA). The criterion for statistical sig-
nificance was P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>EC reduces ICH-induced early brain injury 
and neurologic deficits </p>

<p>To define the optimal dose of EC in ICH, we first admin-
istered different doses of EC to 12-month-old male mice </p>

<p>subjected to collagenase injection. Injury volume was 
assessed 72 h post-ICH, as collagenase-induced brain 
parenchyma lesion reaches a maximum by this time. 40 
Brain sections were stained with Luxol fast blue/Cresyl 
violet, and lesions were identified by lack of color and 
destruction of myelin architecture (Fig. 1A). The lesions 
were smaller in mice that received 72 h of 15 mg/kg EC 
(EC 15; 5.5 AE 1.5 mm 3 ) or 45 mg/kg EC (EC 45; 
4.5 AE 0.9 mm 3 ) than in those that received vehicle 
(8.9 AE 1.5 mm 3 ; both P &lt; 0.01). Lesion size did not dif-
fer between mice that received vehicle and those that 
received 5 mg/kg EC (EC 5; 7.8 AE 0.8 mm 3 ; P = 0.328) 
or between EC 15 and EC 45 groups (P = 0.318; Fig. 1B). 
Also, no obvious lesion was observed in the sham-oper-
ated group. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>ICH+EC45 
ICH+EC15 </p>

<p>ICH+Veh 
ICH+EC5 </p>

<p>1 mm </p>

<p>Figure 1. Effects of EC on brain injury volume and neurologic function in mice subjected to ICH. (A) Representative Luxol fast blue/Cresyl violet-
stained brain sections at 72 h post-ICH; injured areas lack staining and are circled in white. Scale bar: 1 mm. (B) Quantification analysis shows 
significantly smaller brain injury volumes in EC-treated groups than in the vehicle-treated group at 72 h post-ICH. (C) EC posttreatment improved 
neurologic deficit score (top), forelimb placing (middle), and corner turn test performance (bottom) of mice subjected to ICH. Values are 
mean AE SD; n = 10 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH 
C.-F. Chang et al. </p>

<p>Several sets of behavioral experiments were performed 
at 24 and 72 h post-ICH to determine the effect of EC on 
neurologic deficits. Compared with vehicle, EC 15 showed 
a beneficial effect on neurologic score (9.9 AE 1.7 vs. 
6.7 AE 1.1; P &lt; 0.01), forelimb placing (37.0 AE 11.5% vs. 
72.0 AE 11.3%; P &lt; 0.01), and corner turns (74.0 AE 12.6% 
vs. 60.0 AE 11.5%; P &lt; 0.05) 72 h post-ICH. Although EC 
45 improved performance in the forelimb placing 
(P &lt; 0.01) and corner turn (P &lt; 0.01) tests, it failed to 
improve neurologic score (P = 0.054) because mice in this 
treatment group had deficiency in front limb symmetry 
and compulsory circling tests. 
Sex is one determinant of ICH outcome, and evidence 
has shown that some drugs lack therapeutic efficacy in 
female animals. 41,42 To this end, we tested the efficacy of EC 
for injury reduction after ICH in age-matched female mice. 
Compared to vehicle-treated mice, mice that were adminis-
trated EC 15 had smaller injury volume (6.2 AE 0.8 mm 3 vs. 
4.3 AE 1.2 mm 3 ; P &lt; 0.05) and better neurologic function 
(10.4 AE 0.9 vs. 7.5 AE 1.4; P &lt; 0.01) 72 h post-ICH (Fig. 
S2A and B). Because every rodent model of ICH has draw-
backs that limit its clinical relevance, 3 we further character-
ized the efficacy of EC for ICH in the blood model, another 
common strategy to recapitulate ICH. EC 15 reduced neuro-
logic deficit scores in both male (8.7 AE 1.0 vs. 6.8 AE 1.0; 
P &lt; 0.05) and female (9.3 AE 0.8 vs. 7.4 AE 0.8; P &lt; 0.01) </p>

<p>mice 72 h post-ICH (Fig. S2C and D). 
To assess whether the reduction in early brain injury 
and the improvement of neurologic deficits in EC-treated 
mice correlated with reduced brain edema, we examined 
brain water content 72 h after ICH. EC 15 reduced brain 
water content in ipsilateral striatum in collagenase-injected 
male (P &lt; 0.05) and female (P = 0.004) mice, blood-
injected male (P = 0.021) and female (P &lt; 0.01) mice, and 
thrombin-injected male mice (P &lt; 0.05; Fig. S2E-I). These 
results imply that efficacy of oral EC administration is not 
affected by sex. Clinical study has suggested an association 
between brain edema and subsequent neurologic deficits. 43 
Therefore, we examined long-term neurobehavioral func-
tion by neurologic score and the corner turn test on day 
28 post-ICH. Compared with the vehicle group, EC 15 
mice had better neurologic scores (6.8 AE 1.0 vs. 4.5 AE 1.0; 
P &lt; 0.01) and better performance in the corner turn test </p>

<p>(79.1 AE 3.8% vs. 70.0 AE 4.5%; P &lt; 0.01) on day 28 post-
ICH (Fig. S3A and B). Because lesion size did not differ 
between EC 15 and EC 45 groups, we used EC 15 in the 
following mechanistic studies. </p>

<p>EC decreases perihematoma cell death and 
neuronal degeneration </p>

<p>Because EC 15 significantly alleviated brain injury and 
improved neurologic deficits, we investigated whether this </p>

<p>treatment paradigm ameliorates perihematomal cell death. 
Cells positive for propidium iodide (PI), terminal deoxynu-
cleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL), and 
Fluoro-Jade B (FJB) were evident 72 h after ICH in and 
around the hematoma. Compared to vehicle treatment, EC 
15 reduced the number of PI-positive cells (from 221.5 AE 
13.7 cells/mm 2 to 170.4 AE 26.1 cells/mm 2 ; P &lt; 0.05), the 
percentage of TUNEL-positive cells (from 41.4 AE 11.4% to 
22.8 AE 7.1%; P &lt; 0.01), and the number of FJB-positive 
cells (from 121.4 AE 23.5 cells/mm 2 to 78.8 AE 19.3 cells/ 
mm 2 ; P &lt; 0.01) in the perihematoma area 72 h post-ICH 
(Fig. 2A, B, D, and F). Few PI-, TUNEL-, and FJB-positive 
cells were observed in the contralateral hemisphere of either 
group. EC 15 also reduced ICH-induced upregulation of 
high-mobility group protein B1 (HMGB-1) at 72 h post-
ICH (P &lt; 0.05; Fig. 2C) and the increase in caspase-3 
activity at 48 h (P &lt; 0.05) and 72 h (P &lt; 0.01) post-ICH 
(Fig. 2E). The neuroprotective effect of EC was further 
confirmed by using primary neurons. Hemoglobin-induced 
lactate dehydrogenase release was decreased in primary 
neurons co-treated with EC for 24 h (160.2 AE 4.8% vs. 
135.8 AE 2.6%; P &lt; 0.05; Fig. S4). These results further 
confirm the anatomical observations. </p>

<p>EC alleviates ICH-induced brain oxidative 
injury and increases Nrf2 nuclear 
accumulation </p>

<p>We used the hydroethidine technique to study the effect 
of EC on posthemorrhagic ROS production. The presence 
of ROS was observed as red particles in perihematomal 
cells 24 h post-ICH (Fig. 3A). On the contralateral side, 
ROS signals were present but relatively weak (data not 
shown). EC 15 mice exhibited less ROS production in the 
perihematomal area than did vehicle-treated mice (fluo-
rescence intensity: 0.056 AE 0.007 vs. 0.038 AE 0.007; 
P &lt; 0.01; Fig. 3A). The final product of lipid peroxida-</p>

<p>tion, malondialdehyde (MDA), was markedly elevated in 
hemorrhagic brain tissue compared to that in sham 
groups at 48 h (P &lt; 0.01) and 72 h (P &lt; 0.01) post-ICH. 
Compared with that in the vehicle group, EC 15 reduced 
MDA level in hemorrhagic tissues at 48 h 
(9.2 AE 0.7 nmol/mg vs. 7.3 AE 0.6 nmol/mg; P &lt; 0.01) 
and 72 h (10.0 AE 1.0 nmol/mg vs. 8.1 AE 1.0 nmol/mg; 
P &lt; 0.01) post-ICH (Fig. 3B). Protein carbonyls, another </p>

<p>marker of oxidative stress, were also reduced in the EC 
15 group at 72 h post-ICH (Fig. 3C). 
To test whether EC induces Nrf2 nuclear translocation, 
we assayed Nrf2 protein in cytosolic and nuclear brain 
extracts by Western blot. EC administration did not alter 
cytosolic Nrf2 levels; however, nuclear Nrf2 accumulation 
was increased ~1.8-fold by EC administration at 6 h post-
ICH (P &lt; 0.05; Fig. 3D). We then examined the effect of </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>C.-F. Chang et al. 
Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH </p>

<p>Nrf2 nuclear accumulation on its downstream transcripts, 
SOD1 and NQO1, by RT-qPCR. In EC 15 mice, SOD1 
mRNA expression was increased by ~13%, 33%, and 70% 
of that in the vehicle group at 6 h (P &lt; 0.05), 24 h 
(P &lt; 0.05), and 72 h (P &lt; 0.01) post-ICH (Fig. 3E). Simi-
larly, NQO1 mRNA expression was increased by ~20% 
and 42% of that in the vehicle group at 6 h (P &lt; 0.001) 
and 72 h (P &lt; 0.05) post-ICH (Fig. 3F). </p>

<p>EC decreases hemorrhage-induced iron 
deposition and HO-1 expression through an 
Nrf2-independent mechanism </p>

<p>HO-1 is a key downstream effector of Nrf2. It is upregulat-
ed after ICH and exacerbates neuronal injury. 11 Further-
more, genetic overexpression of HO-1 contributes to </p>

<p>pathologic iron deposition in astrocytes. 44 Here, ICH 
induced an increase in HO-1 protein level in the hemor-
rhagic hemisphere at 72 h that was reduced approximately 
twofold by EC 15 (P &lt; 0.05; Fig. 4A). The relationship 
between HO-1 and iron deposition in ICH brain was fur-
ther confirmed by using HO-1 KO mice. Few iron-positive 
cells were observed in hemorrhagic brain sections from 
HO-1 KO mice (Fig. 4B). Additionally, at 72 h post-ICH, 
iron deposition was lower in EC-treated WT mice 
(15.6 AE 4.6 cells/0.12 mm 2 ) than in vehicle-treated WT 
mice (38.3 AE 3.3 cells/0.12 mm 2 ; P &lt; 0.05; Fig. 4C). To 
identify whether the lower HO-1 expression and iron depo-
sition observed in the EC-treated mice can be attributed to 
a difference in collagenase-induced bleeding volume, we 
measured hemoglobin content at 24 h post-ICH when 
hematoma reaches its maximum in the collagenase </p>

<p>B 
A 
ICH+Veh 
ICH+EC </p>

<p>100 μm </p>

<p>PI </p>

<p>TUNEL </p>

<p>DAPI </p>

<p>FJB </p>

<p>10 μm </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>HMGB-1 </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>Sham ICH Sham ICH 
Veh 
EC 
C </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Figure 2. Identification of cell death, apoptosis, and neuronal degeneration in mice subjected to ICH. (A) Representative propidium iodide (PI)-, 
TUNEL-, DAPI-, and Fluoro-Jade B (FJB)-stained brain sections. The insets are representative TUNEL-and FJB-positive cells at higher magnification. 
Scale bars: 100 lm; 10 lm (inset). (B) Quantification analysis indicates that 15 mg/kg EC (EC 15) significantly reduced PI-positive cells at 72 h 
post-ICH. (C) Top: Representative immunoblots of the HMGB-1 protein in ipsilateral hemispheres from sham-operated and ICH mice treated with 
or without EC 15. Bottom: Densitometric analysis shows that HMGB-1 expression in the ipsilateral hemispheres was significantly lower in EC 15 
mice than in vehicle-treated mice 72 h after ICH. (D) Quantification analysis shows that the percentage of TUNEL-positive cells was significantly 
lower in the EC 15 mice than in the vehicle-treated mice 72 h after ICH. (E) Bar graphs showing caspase-3 enzyme activity in EC and vehicle 
groups at 48 and 72 h after sham surgery or ICH induction. ICH significantly increased caspase-3 enzyme activity in both EC-and vehicle-treated 
mice. The hemorrhagic hemispheres in the EC-treated group exhibited significantly less caspase-3 activity than did those in the vehicle-treated 
group. (F) Quantification analysis of FJB staining indicates that EC-treated mice had significantly fewer degenerating neurons than did vehicle-
treated mice 72 h after ICH. Values are mean AE SD; n = 6-9 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle; # P &lt; 0.05 versus sham. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH 
C.-F. Chang et al. </p>

<p>model. 11,45 No significant difference was observed between 
vehicle-and EC-treated mice (P &gt; 0.05; Fig. 4D). 
To determine whether the effects on ICH injury were due 
to activation of the Nrf2 pathway, we administered EC 
(15 mg/kg per day) to Nrf2 KO mice with or without ICH. 
Interestingly, deletion of Nrf2 did not totally abolish the 
therapeutic effect of EC in ICH brain. Compared with vehi-
cle treatment, EC was still able to reduce brain injury vol-
ume (11.0 AE 1.2 mm 3 vs. 7.9 AE 1.9 mm 3 ; P &lt; 0.05 at 72 h 
post-ICH; Fig. 4E). Accordingly, EC 15 per se decreased 
iron-positive cells in the perihematomal region at 72 h 
post-ICH (50.8 AE 6.1 cells/0.12 mm 2 vs. 33.6 AE 5.6 cells/ 
0.12 mm 2 ; P &lt; 0.01; Fig. 4F). Furthermore, ICH-induced 
HO-1 protein expression (Fig. 4G) and iron deposition were </p>

<p>significantly higher in Nrf2 KO brain (57.1 AE 6.4 cells/ 
0.12 mm 2 ) than in WT brain (38.3 AE 3.3 cells/0.12 mm 2 ; 
P &lt; 0.01) 72 h post-ICH (Fig. 4H). </p>

<p>EC reduces AP-1 and MMP-9 enzyme activity </p>

<p>To elucidate the possible alternative pathway by which 
EC provides neuroprotection, we screened 56 transcrip-
tion factors in brains of mice 72 h post-ICH using a 
protein/DNA array. We observed increases in activity of 
AP-1, nuclear factor of activated T cells (NFAT-1), and 
growth hormone factor 1 (Pit-1) in brain tissue nuclear 
extracts that were diminished by EC treatment (Fig. S5A). 
Because stress-response elements that contain an AP-1 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>50 μm </p>

<p>ICH+Veh 
ICH+EC </p>

<p>A 
C 
Sham 
ICH 
Sham 
ICH </p>

<p>Veh 
EC </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>97 
191 </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>Nrf2 (C) </p>

<p>Nrf2 (N) </p>

<p>Lamin A/C </p>

<p>Veh 
Veh 
EC 
EC </p>

<p>Sham 
ICH 
D </p>

<p>Figure 3. EC alleviates ICH-induced reactive oxygen species (ROS) production. (A) Top: Ethidium fluorescent signal was evident in brain sections 
from mice 24 h after ICH. Scale bar: 50 lm. Bottom: Quantification analysis of fluorescence intensity indicated that EC significantly reduced ROS 
production at 1 day post-ICH. (B) Bar graphs showing malondialdehyde (MDA) level at 48 and 72 h after sham surgery or ICH induction. ICH 
significantly increased MDA level in hemorrhagic brain tissue of both EC-and vehicle-treated mice. EC-treated mice had less MDA than did 
vehicle-treated mice. (C) Representative immunoblot of hemorrhagic brain tissue shows that EC-treated mice had less protein carbonylation than 
did vehicle-treated mice. b-actin served as a loading control. The arrows show the carbonylated proteins at different molecular weights. (D) Top: 
Representative immunoblot of ipsilateral hemispheres from mice treated with or without 15 mg/kg EC; brains were collected 6 h after sham 
surgery or ICH. Bottom: Bar graph of densitometric analysis shows Nrf2 protein level in nuclear extracts from ipsilateral hemispheres of EC-and 
vehicle-treated mice. (E and F) Line graphs show SOD-1 and NQO-1 mRNA expression in EC-and vehicle-treated mice at 6, 24, and 72 h after 
ICH. Compared with vehicle treatment, EC significantly increased SOD-1 mRNA expression at 24 and 72 h and NQO-1 mRNA expression at 6 and 
72 h in the ipsilateral hemisphere. Values are mean AE SD; n = 5-6 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle; # P &lt; 0.05 versus sham. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>C.-F. Chang et al. 
Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH </p>

<p>(Fos/Jun)-binding consensus sequence are major cis-ele-
ments for HO-1 induction, 46 we further examined tran-
scription factor AP-1 activity at 48 and 72 h post-ICH. 
AP-1 activity was increased after ICH in the vehicle-trea-
ted group (P &lt; 0.01; Fig. 5A). However, EC 15 treatment 
reduced AP-1 activity compared with vehicle treatment at 
48 h (P = 0.013) and 72 h (P &lt; 0.01) post-ICH. We also 
determined the activity of MMP-2 and MMP-9, the 
downstream transcripts regulated by AP-1, 47 by gelatin in </p>

<p>situ zymography. EC 15 decreased gelatinolytic activity in 
cells (positive cells, 9.8 AE 1.8 vs. 7.4 AE 0.9 per 0.01 mm 2 ; 
P &lt; 0.05) in the perihematomal area 72 h post-ICH </p>

<p>(Fig. 5B). Gelatinolytic activity was weak in the striatum 
of sham-operated brain sections (data not shown). Gela-
tin gel zymography showed that EC 15 reduced MMP-9 
activity by ~66% compared with that in the vehicle-trea-
ted group. MMP-2 gelatinolytic activity was relatively 
weak (P &lt; 0.01; Fig. 5C). </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D 
G </p>

<p>Nrf2 KO+Veh 
Nrf2 KO+EC 
E </p>

<p>B 
WT+ICH 
HO-1 KO+ICH </p>

<p>HO-1 </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>WT 
Sham 
ICH 
Sham 
ICH 
Nrf2 KO 
A 
Sham </p>

<p>HO-1 </p>

<p>β-actin </p>

<p>ICH 
Sham 
ICH 
Veh 
EC </p>

<p>F 
Nrf2 KO+Veh 
Nrf2 KO+EC </p>

<p>20 µm </p>

<p>N P </p>

<p>50 µm </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>1 mm </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effects of EC on HO-1 protein expression, iron deposition, and hemorrhagic injury volume in WT, Nrf2 KO, and HO-1 KO mice 
subjected to ICH. (A) Top: Representative immunoblot of HO-1 protein from sham-operated and ICH mice treated with or without EC. Bottom: 
Densitometric analysis shows that HO-1 protein level in the ipsilateral hemisphere was significantly less in EC-treated mice than in vehicle-treated 
mice at 72 h after ICH. (B) Representative Perls-stained brain sections from WT and HO-1 KO mice 72 h post-ICH. In the perihematomal region, 
many iron-positive cells can be seen in the WT mice; based on cell morphology, most of them are likely activated microglia/macrophages with 
cytoplasmic iron deposits (arrows). The iron-positive cells with similar morphology are rarely detectable in the HO-1 KO mice. (C) Ferric iron 
accumulation in the perihematomal region of mice at 72 h post-ICH was significantly less in EC-treated mice than in vehicle-treated mice. (D) 
Hemoglobin levels were not significantly different in brains of vehicle-and EC-treated mice at 24 h post-ICH. (E) Representative brain sections 
from Nrf2 KO mice 72 h post-ICH were stained with Luxol fast blue/Cresyl violet. Areas of injury lack staining and are circled with a black line. 
Bottom: Quantification analysis shows significantly smaller brain injury volumes in EC-treated than in vehicle-treated mice. (F) Representative Perls-
stained brain sections from Nrf2 KO mice with or without EC administration 72 h post-ICH. Fewer iron-positive cells are present in the EC-treated 
mice. The inset images show neuron-like and microglia/macrophage-like morphology (Left) and iron-positive (P) and -negative (N) cells (Right). (G) 
Top: Representative immunoblot of HO-1 protein from WT and Nrf2 KO mice subjected to sham operation or ICH induction. Bottom: Bar graph 
of densitometric analysis shows a significant increase in HO-1 expression in the ipsilateral hemispheres of Nrf2 KO mice at 72 h after ICH 
compared with that in WT mice. (H) Nrf2 KO mice had significantly more Perls-positive cells than did WT mice in the perihematomal region 72 h 
post-ICH. Scale bars: 50 lm (B); 1 mm (E); 20 lm (F). Values are mean AE SD; n = 5-10 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle or WT. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH 
C.-F. Chang et al. </p>

<p>EC modulates iron-related chemokine LCN2 
and ferroptosis gene expression </p>

<p>Ferroptosis is a newly recognized, iron-dependent form of 
cell death. 6 A previous study reported that lipocalin-2 
(LCN2) participates in iron homeostasis and enhances 
brain iron clearance after ICH. 48 We sought to determine 
whether EC might act via an iron-related mechanism. 
Compared with that in the sham group, LCN2 protein 
expression increased in the brains of both vehicle-and 
EC-treated mice 72 h after ICH. However, LCN2 
expression was ~1.6-fold higher in the EC-treated mice 
(P &lt; 0.01; Fig. 6A). The enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assay (ELISA) further confirmed that LCN2 protein 
level was higher in brain tissue of EC 15 mice than in </p>

<p>brain tissue of vehicle-treated mice at 6 h (6976.1 AE 
232.3 pg/mL vs. 6430.9 AE 76.7 pg/mL; P &lt; 0.05) and 
24 h (7329.5 AE 30.5 pg/mL vs. 6913.2 AE 225.1 pg/mL; 
P &lt; 0.05) post-ICH (Fig. 6B). To determine if EC alters </p>

<p>the expression of ferroptosis-related genes, we measured 
the expression of iron response element binding protein 2 
(Ireb2), ATP synthase F 0 complex subunit C3 (ATP5G3), 
citrate synthase (Cs), and ATP ribosomal protein L8 (Rpl8) 
at 6, 24, and 72 h after ICH induction. Compared with lev-
els in the vehicle-treated group, EC 15 reduced Ireb2 
mRNA by ~20% at 6 h (P &lt; 0.01) post-ICH and increased 
ATP5G3 mRNA by ~25% at 6 h (P &lt; 0.05), 24 h </p>

<p>(P &lt; 0.01), and 72 h (P &lt; 0.01) post-ICH. However, 
expression of Cs mRNA and Rpl8 mRNA did not differ sig-
nificantly between the two groups. </p>

<p>Pro-MMP-9 </p>

<p>Pro-MMP-2 </p>

<p>Sham 
ICH+Veh 
ICH+EC </p>

<p>C 
A </p>

<p>B 
ICH+Veh 
ICH+EC </p>

<p>Figure 5. Effects of EC on AP-1 and MMP activity in mice subjected to ICH. (A) AP-1 activity was significantly greater in the ipsilateral 
hemisphere of ICH mice than in that of sham-operated mice. EC administration significantly reduced AP-1 activity at 48 and 72 h post-ICH. (B) 
Top: Representative gelatin in situ zymography fluorescent images from ICH mice treated with vehicle or EC. Bottom: Quantification shows that 
gelatinolytic activity was lower in EC-treated mice than in vehicle-treated mice at 72 h post-ICH. (C) Top: Representative gel zymography of 
MMP-9 and MMP-2 activity from vehicle-and EC-treated mice at 72 h post-ICH. The gelatinase activity of pro-MMP-9 was increased in brains 
from both vehicle-and EC-treated mice. Bottom: Quantification analysis indicated that pro-MMP-9 activity was decreased by EC administration. 
Pro-MMP-2 gelatinase activity was weak in all groups. Values are mean AE SD; n = 5-6 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle; # P &lt; 0.05 versus 
sham. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>C.-F. Chang et al. 
Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Natural flavanols have the potential to improve an indi-
vidual's oxidant defense system by activating endogenous 
protective signaling pathways. When flavanol-rich food is 
consumed, EC is absorbed into circulation 22 and crosses 
the BBB. 24-26 In animal models, EC has been shown to 
have neuroprotective effects, such as improving cognitive 
performance, 21 enhancing memory retention, 26 reducing 
b-amyloid toxicity, 34 preventing tau aggregation, 49 attenu-</p>

<p>ating ischemic brain injury, and inhibiting excitotoxic-
ity. 23 In this study, using a collagenase model of ICH, we 
showed that EC reduces early brain injury in 12-month-
old male and female mice and that the improved neuro-
logic function is sustained for at least 4 weeks after ICH. 
We also confirmed the efficacy of EC in the blood and 
thrombin models of ICH. Furthermore, we found that EC 
reduces ICH-induced cell death in the perihematomal 
region, promotes Nrf2 nuclear accumulation, and reduces 
oxidative brain damage. Interestingly, we showed that EC 
decreases HO-1 protein expression and iron deposition 
through an Nrf2-independent mechanism, decreases AP-1 </p>

<p>and MMP-9 activity, increases LCN2 protein level, and 
modulates ferroptosis-related gene expression. Taken 
together, these findings provide clear evidence that oral 
administration of EC protects brain against early hemor-
rhagic injury through Nrf2-dependent and -independent 
pathways. 
Most animal studies of ICH have been carried out in 
2-or 3-month-old animals, limiting the direct translation 
of animal studies into clinical trials. We used 12-month-
old mice in this study to enhance the clinical relevance, 
as stroke is most common in older adults. Additionally, 
because the current, commonly used blood-and collage-
nase-induced ICH models cannot fully and adequately 
mirror human ICH events, we applied multiple models in 
our study to reduce possible translational pitfalls. 3,38,50 
We followed the published guidelines for translational 
studies 37-39 and confirmed the efficacy of EC in three 
ICH-related models. We found that posttreatment of 
mice for 72 h with 15 mg/kg oral EC decreased injury 
volume and brain edema formation in the early stage of 
ICH and improved neurologic deficits for as long as 
28 days after ICH onset. The dose of 15 mg/kg per day in </p>

<p>Figure 6. Effects of EC on lipocalin-2 (LCN2) and ferroptosis-related genes in mice subjected to ICH. (A) Top: Representative immunoblot of 
LCN2 protein expression in hemorrhagic tissue from sham-operated and ICH mice treated with or without EC. Bottom: Densitometric analysis 
shows a significant increase in LCN2 protein expression in the ipsilateral hemisphere of EC-treated mice 72 h after ICH compared with that in 
vehicle-treated mice. (B) Bar graph shows LCN2 protein concentration in the ipsilateral hemispheres of vehicle-and EC-treated mice at 6 and 24 h 
post-ICH. ICH significantly increased LCN2 protein levels in both groups, but LCN2 protein level was significantly higher in the EC-treated group 
than in the vehicle-treated group. (C-F) Line graphs show mRNA expression of Ireb2, Cs, Atp5g3, and Rpl8 in the hemorrhagic hemispheres of 
vehicle-and EC-treated mice at 6, 24, and 72 h post-ICH. EC treatment significantly decreased Ireb2 mRNA expression at 6 h and increased 
Atp5g3 mRNA expression at 6, 24, and 72 h after ICH compared with vehicle treatment. Cs and Rpl8 mRNA expression did not differ significantly 
between the two groups. Values are mean AE SD; n = 5-6 mice per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle; # P &lt; 0.05 versus sham. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH 
C.-F. Chang et al. </p>

<p>mice is approximately equivalent to a human dose of 
1.22 mg/kg per day, based on calculations with a body 
surface area conversion factor. 51 Previous studies also 
provide supportive information on the feasibility of using 
oral EC to treat central nervous system disorders. 22,23,26 
Sex differences may influence stroke outcomes and 
response to pharmacologic therapy. 52 Although sex differ-
ences and possible molecular mechanisms have been stud-
ied in ischemic stroke, 53 few animal studies of ICH have 
been conducted in female mice. 42 In this study, although 
post hoc analysis showed no significant difference 
between males and females owing to limited sample size, 
female mice tended to have smaller lesion volumes and 
less brain water content than did male mice after ICH, 
supporting the idea that sex affects brain injury after 
ICH. It is noteworthy, however, that the efficacy of EC 
did not differ in males and females. 
Cell death from acute ICH in central and perihemato-
mal areas is a sophisticated process that involves several 
different pathways. Necrosis and apoptosis are the major 
forms of pathologic cell death after ICH in animals and 
humans. 54-57 It was reported that the number of necrotic 
and apoptotic cells in the perihematomal area peaks at 
72 h post-ICH. 57,58 This peak correlates with an increase 
in HMGB-1, which is released from necrotic cells and 
correlates positively with stroke severity. 59,60 The EC-
induced attenuation of neuronal death, as evidenced by a 
reduction in FJB staining, is consistent with in vitro stud-
ies showing that EC increases the viability of neurons 
exposed to hemoglobin and suggests a direct protective 
effect of EC on neurons. 
Iron-dependent ferroptosis, a newly recognized form of 
programmed cell death, occurs in hippocampal slice cul-
tures exposed to glutamate. 6 This process is characterized 
by iron-dependent accumulation of ROS, similar to what 
is observed after ICH. To date, however, the role of fer-
roptosis after ICH remains unknown. Research in this 
area has been hindered by a lack of specific markers that 
can be used to characterize this phenomenon in vivo and 
in vitro. On the basis of available information, we tested 
ferroptosis-related gene expression in mice subjected to 
ICH with or without EC posttreatment. The reduction in 
Ireb2 gene expression and iron deposition in the hemor-</p>

<p>rhagic territory demonstrates the ability of EC to amelio-
rate iron-induced cell death after ICH. Ireb2 encodes a 
master regulator of iron metabolism. Neurons lacking 
Ireb2 are highly resistant to hemoglobin toxicity, and 
Ireb2 KO increases cell viability after ICH. 61 Furthermore, </p>

<p>extensive evidence has shown that iron chelation reduces 
hemoglobin/iron-induced toxicity and could be a promis-
ing therapy for ICH. 7,62 
Although flavanols have been speculated to act as iron 
chelators in an in vitro model of Alzheimer's disease, 63 to </p>

<p>our knowledge, this is the first report to provide evidence 
that EC has iron elimination properties after ICH, when 
the brain is exposed to iron overload. Iron, one of the 
hemoglobin/heme degradation products of HO-1, dam-
ages neurons by catalyzing reactions with hydrogen per-
oxide to generate hydroxyl radicals, believed to be the 
most reactive and dangerous form of ROS. ICH-induced 
HO-1 upregulation and overexpression of HO-1 in mice 
each result in iron overload in the brain. 44,64 We showed 
previously that HO-1 deletion reduces early brain injury 
by decreasing oxidative stress in ICH brain. 11 Here, we 
provide direct evidence of a relationship between HO-1 
expression and iron deposition in ICH brain using HO-1 
KO mice. Notably, EC administration reduced HO-1 pro-
tein expression in hemorrhagic tissue and thereby reduced 
ROS-induced DNA damage (hydroethidine), lipid peroxi-
dation (MDA), and protein oxidation (dinitrophenyl hy-
drazone). These antioxidant effects were accompanied by 
increases in Nrf2 nuclear accumulation and phase II 
enzyme (SOD1 and NQO1) expression. 
It has been shown in the middle cerebral artery occlu-
sion model of ischemic stroke that the neuroprotection 
conferred by EC is abolished in mice that lack Nrf2. Simi-
larly, EC-induced neuroprotection in neurons exposed to 
tert-butyl hydroperoxide is absent in neurons isolated 
from Nrf2 KO mice. 23 We and others have shown that 
Nrf2 protects brain against ICH injury. 8,10 Here, we con-
firmed that Nrf2 KO mice have larger ICH-induced lesion 
volume and more iron-loaded cells than do WT mice at 
72 h post-ICH. Interestingly, EC 15 was still able to 
decrease ICH-induced lesion by 28.1% in Nrf2 KO mice 
(compared to 38.2% in WT mice). The fact that Nrf2 KO 
mice still showed some protection from posttreatment 
with EC, suggests that an Nrf2-independent pathway 
might act synergistically under ICH conditions. Although 
no residual neuroprotection from EC was apparent in 
Nrf2 KO mice in a previously published study of ischemic 
stroke, 23 many differences between the studies could 
account for the discrepancy. Most importantly, hemor-
rhagic and ischemic strokes produce different pathological 
events. Additionally, the previous study used younger ani-
mals, a single-dose intervention, and an earlier endpoint. 
Moreover, our findings are in line with those of recently 
published studies which showed that the gene regulation 
of HO-1 can occur through an Nrf2-independent pathway 
in other organs. 65,66 
Nrf2/small Maf heterodimers and AP-1 complexes are 
the two major transcription factors that participate in 
HO-1 activation. In Nrf2 KO fibroblasts treated with arse-
nite, HO-1 gene expression levels increased gradually, 
probably via AP-1 activation. 65 The transactivation of AP-
1, a stress-activated transcription factor, has been defined 
as an inflammatory signaling molecule in ischemic stroke </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>C.-F. Chang et al. 
Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH </p>

<p>and traumatic brain injury. 67 However, the role of AP-1 
in ICH and iron-induced cell death has not been 
explored. One study in an in vitro mouse epidermal 
model showed that AP-1 activation increases after UVB 
stimulation and can be inhibited by deferoxamine, an 
iron chelator that can reduce iron deposition and neuro-
nal death after ICH. 68-70 Furthermore, EC suppresses 
TNFa-mediated AP-1-DNA binding in adipocytes. 71 
These insights imply that although EC increases antioxi-
dant gene expression through Nrf2 activation, its ability 
to chelate iron and suppress AP-1 activity may downregu-
late HO-1 and subsequently reduce iron-induced brain 
damage after ICH. In addition, MMPs and LCN2 are 
coeffectors of AP-1 activation and iron overload after 
brain injury. 48,72 ROS can activate MMP-9, which 
degrades the neurovascular matrix, leading to brain 
edema and tissue injury. 17 LCN2, an acute phase protein 
that is upregulated under various stress conditions, plays 
a central role in iron transport. LCN2 captures iron parti-
cles, reduces cell death, and acts as an antioxidant in vivo 
by regulating iron homeostasis after ICH, sepsis, and 
renal ischemia. 48,73-75 In this study, EC significantly 
reduced ICH-induced brain injury in WT and Nrf2 KO 
mice, suppressed AP-1 activation, reduced MMP-9 activ-
ity, and upregulated LCN2. Taken together, these findings 
suggest that an alternative, Nrf2-independent pathway is 
involved. 
Although we provide proof of concept and elucidate 
the mechanisms of action of EC in our ICH models, 
additional efforts should be made before clinical trials can 
be considered in the future. (1) The effects of a delayed 
treatment regimen and preventive use of EC need to be 
tested in different ICH models and in different animal 
species. We speculate that pretreatment with EC should 
be protective in ICH; however, in this study, EC 45 had 
unfavorable effects on neurologic function, though it did 
not increase brain lesion volume. Additionally, green tea 
catechins were reported to have antiplatelet activity. 76 
Therefore, the pretreatment dosage of EC needs to be 
titrated carefully in animals to prevent bleeding risk. (2) 
Our selection of dose and delivery route in this study was 
based on available pharmacologic studies as described in 
the Methods. Nonoral systemic administration of EC such 
as by intravenous infusion should be tested as an emer-
gency treatment option for ICH patients. Pharmacoki-
netic parameters of EC in humans and rabbits support 
this option. 35,77 (3) Although our data show that EC has 
a direct neuroprotective effect on neurons in our in vitro 
ICH model, several lines of evidence indicate that EC can 
regulate blood pressure and improve vascular function by 
targeting endothelial cells. 22,78 Because hypertension is 
one of the risk factors for ICH, 2,38 multiple cellular thera-
peutic targets of EC should be validated. Moreover, green </p>

<p>tea catechins have the ability to modify the activity of 
multiple intracellular molecular targets, including mito-
gen-activated protein kinase (MAPK), protein kinase C, 
and PI3K/Akt pathways. 79 Studies are needed to deter-
mine whether EC targets multiple signaling pathways that 
trigger signaling crosstalk. 
In conclusion, we found that oral posttreatment of 
mice with EC protects against early hemorrhagic brain 
injury. We confirmed that EC has both antioxidant and 
iron-chelating properties and may act through Nrf2-
dependent and -independent pathways. EC's ability to act 
on multiple targets may provide an opportunity for appli-
cation in other neurologic disorders, such as head and 
spinal cord injury. Although more work is needed, target-
ing AP-1 could provide new mechanistic insight in the 
search for drugs to treat ICH. Furthermore, our evidence 
may help the general public and health care providers 
make informed decisions on whether EC could be 
accepted as an adjunct for ICH treatment. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by AHA 13GRNT15730001, 
NIH K01AG031926, R01AT007317, and R01NS078026 
(J. W.). We thank Lingshu Liu, Joy Ziyi Zhou, and 
Weizhu Tang for blind analysis of histology and immuno-
fluorescence; Herman Kwansa for HPLC analysis of 
(-)-epicatechin purity; and Paul Talalay, PhD, for provid-
ing Nrf2 À/À mice. We thank Claire Levine, MS, ELS, for 
assistance with manuscript preparation; Adam Sapirstein, 
MD, and Zeng-Jin Yang, MD, PhD, for comments on the 
manuscript; Raymond Koehler, PhD, and the Wang lab 
team members for insightful input. </p>

<p>Author Contributions </p>

<p>C. C. and J. W. designed the research, C. C., J. W., and 
S. C. performed the research, C. C. and J. W. analyzed 
the data and wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>None declared. </p>





<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH 
C.-F. Chang et al. </p>



<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>C.-F. Chang et al. 
Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH </p>





<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>

<p>Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH 
C.-F. Chang et al. </p>



<p>Supporting Information </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: </p>

<p>Data S1. Materials and methods. 
Figure S1. HPLC assessment of the stability of EC. The 
stability of an aqueous solution of EC at 4°C after 24 h 
was assessed by HPLC using fluorescence detection. The 
analyte of EC (Sigma, E1753) was 100% pure as can be 
seen from the chromatogram. EC in water remained sta-
ble for more than 24 h. </p>

<p>Figure S2. EC administration improves early ICH out-
comes in male and female mice subjected to three hemor-
rhagic models. (A and B) At 72 h after female mice were 
subjected to collagenase-induced ICH, brain injury vol-
umes were significantly smaller (A) and neurologic deficit 
scores were significantly lower (B) in the EC-treated group 
than in the vehicle-treated group. (C and D) At 72 h after 
induction of ICH by the blood model, male (C) and female 
(D) mice treated with EC had significantly lower neurologic 
deficit scores than did those treated with vehicle. (E and F) 
At 72 h after collagenase-induced ICH, brain water content 
was significantly lower in male (E) and female (F) mice 
treated with EC than in those treated with vehicle. (G and 
H) At 72 h after blood-induced ICH, brain water content 
was significantly lower in male (G) and female (H) mice 
treated with EC than in those treated with vehicle. (I) At 
72 h after male mice were subjected to the thrombin ICH 
model, brain water content in the EC-treated group was 
significantly lower than that in the vehicle-treated group. 
Values are mean AE SD (n = 6-10 animals per group). 
*P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle. Ips, ipsilateral; Cont, contralat-</p>

<p>eral; Stri, striatum; Cerebel, cerebelum. 
Figure S3. EC administration improves long-term func-
tional outcomes in mice subjected to ICH. (A) Neurologic 
deficit scores of male mice were significantly lower in the 
EC-treated group than in the vehicle-treated group 28 days 
after collagenase-induced ICH. (B) Compared with vehicle 
treatment, EC administration improved corner turn test 
performance of male mice on day 28 after collagenase injec-
tion. Values are mean AE SD; n = 10 mice per group. 
*P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle; # P &lt; 0.05 versus 1 day. </p>

<p>Figure S4. EC administration decreases neuronal vulnerabil-
ity to hemoglobin-induced toxicity. Exposure of primary 
neuronal cultures to hemoglobin (Hb; 6 µmol/L) for 24 h 
caused a significant increase in lactate dehydrogenase 
(LDH) release. Co-treatment of neurons with EC (20 µmol/ 
L) significantly reduced Hb-induced LDH release. Values 
are mean AE SD; n = 3 per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus vehicle; 
#P &lt; 0.05 versus Hb alone. 
Figure S5. EC administration modulates transcription factor 
activity profile. (A) Representative chemiluminescence 
images of protein/DNA array from sham-operated mice 
and ICH mice treated with or without EC. At 72 h after 
ICH, activity of AP-1, NFAT-1, and Pit-1 was decreased in 
the ipsilateral hemisphere of EC-treated mice compared 
with that of vehicle-treated mice. (B) The DNA probe 
sequences for detecting specific transcription factors. AP-1, 
activator protein-1; CREB, cAMP response element-binding 
protein 1; GATA, globin transcription factor; NFAT-1, 
nuclear factor of activated T cells; Pit-1, growth hormone 
factor 1; SP-1, Sp1 transcription factor; TR, thyroid hor-
mone receptor; PC, positive control. </p>

<p>ª 2014 The Authors. Annals of Clinical and Translational Neurology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc on behalf of American Neurological Association. </p>



<p>C.-F. Chang et al. 
Epicatechin Protects Brain Against ICH </p>

</text></tei>