<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3589720" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Networks of transcription factors (TFs) are thought to determine and maintain the identity of cells. Here we 
systematically repressed each of 100 TFs with shRNA and carried out global gene expression profiling in 
mouse embryonic stem (ES) cells. Unexpectedly, only the repression of a handful of TFs significantly 
affected transcriptomes, which changed in two directions/trajectories: one trajectory by the repression of 
either Pou5f1 or Sox2; the other trajectory by the repression of either Esrrb, Sall4, Nanog, or Tcfap4. The 
data suggest that the trajectories of gene expression change are already preconfigured by the gene regulatory 
network and roughly correspond to extraembryonic and embryonic fates of cell differentiation, respectively. 
These data also indicate the robustness of the pluripotency gene network, as the transient repression of most 
TFs did not alter the transcriptomes. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>ranscription factors (TFs) bind to cognate DNA motifs in enhancers/promoters of target genes and regulate 
their expression. To decipher the structure and dynamics of gene regulatory networks, we used a strategy to 
monitor the effect of global transcriptome perturbation caused by the altered expression of single transcrip-
tion factors (TFs). Previously we have focused on the gain-of-function assay, i.e., the overexpression of TFs, and 
have carried out detailed whole-genome transcriptome analyses after inducing a total of 137 TFs one at a time </p>

<p>1,2   . 
As a complimentary approach, loss-of-function approaches have been used more often in cell biology. Indeed, 
there has been a prevailing paradigm that loss-of-function assays are a more effective way to reveal such a complex 
TF network. Although large-scale screening of cell phenotypes has been successfully carried out with libraries of 
shRNAs </p>

<p>3,4   , only a limited number of studies have performed global gene expression profiling </p>

<p>5-8   . </p>

<p>Results 
To assess the effectiveness of the loss-of-function approach, here we have repressed the expression of each TF with 
shRNAs, followed by transcriptome analysis with whole-genome expression microarrays (Fig. 1a). We selected 
100 TFs based on their relevance to gene regulation 
1,2 and their relatively high expression 
9 in mouse ES cells 
(Fig. 1b). We developed and tested four independent shRNAs for their effectiveness in repressing the expression 
of each TF in ES cells. We used the best shRNAs for the first round of transcriptome analyses and the second best 
shRNAs for the second round as replications. For the first round, greater than 2-fold knockdown of TFs by gene-
specific shRNAs was confirmed at the mRNA level for the majority of TFs (n 5 89) (Fig. 1c, Supplementary 
Table 1) and at the protein level for all of 28 randomly selected TFs, including some that showed ,2 fold 
reduction in RNA levels (Fig. 1d). If a TF was well repressed (.2 fold change of mRNA) by the first shRNA 
but this manipulation affected the expression of only a small number of downstream genes, we then assigned a low 
priority to this TF and did not use the second shRNA. For the majority of genes (n 5 55), we carried out the 
second round of transcriptome analyses. Based on preliminary time-course experiments (Supplementary 
Figure 1), we chose to collect RNA samples 72 hours after the transient transfection of shRNAs, which permitted 
the detection of early changes in gene expression. The proportion of cells expressing shRNA was maximized by 
high transfection efficiency (,90%) and puromycin selection. The use of two independent shRNAs for each TF </p>

<p>helped us to alleviate the major concern of shRNA experiments -off-
target effects. Specificity of gene response was evident from the pos-
itive correlation between replications with different shRNA (Fig. 2), 
and from the enrichment of TF targets (genes with TF binding sites in 
promoters) within sets of genes that were upregulated or downregu-
lated following the knockdown of TFs (Fig. 3). Results from the 
knockdown of Pou5f1 and Sox2 match well with published data on 
the downregulation of these genes in knockout cell lines with 
tetracycline-controlled transgenes (Supplementary Figure 2). 
Surprisingly, the knockdown with shRNA of only a small subset of 
TFs (12 out of 100) was associated with a substantial transcriptome 
change (response of .100 genes) within 3 days after transfection 
(Fig. 4, Supplementary Tables 1, 2). In particular, it is interesting 
to note that the knockdown of Esrrb showed the most dramatic 
transcriptome changes, suggesting its importance in pluripotency. 
The majority of manipulated TFs (n 5 67) showed very limited 
changes in gene expression profiles (,10 significant downstream 
genes). These results indicate that the TF-network that maintains 
the undifferentiated state of ES cells is surprisingly robust and is 
resistant to change caused by the abrupt loss of highly expressed 
TFs. This may be explained by the functional compensation of other 
factors; for example, the function of Klf4, Klf2, and Klf5 is known to 
be redundant in ES cells </p>

<p>10   . Alternatively, only a small number of TFs 
are indeed hubs of the network and form a core TF-network, whereas 
the majority of TFs, though expressed in undifferentiated ES cells, are 
in the periphery of the entire TF-network, governing only a small 
number of downstream target genes. </p>

<p>To associate gene expression changes caused by the knockdown of 
TFs with the direction of cell state change, we carried out principal 
component analysis (PCA) for expression profiles of 2666 genes that 
showed a significant change of expression based on ANOVA (FDR , 
0.05) (Fig. 5a). The PCA revealed that there were mainly two direc-
tions of state changes from an undifferentiated state in ES cells. A 
change in one direction (tentatively called, ''trajectory 1'') was caused 
by the knockdown of either Pou5f1 or Sox2. A change in the other 
direction (tentatively called, ''trajectory 2'') was caused by the knock-
down of either Esrrb, Sall4, Nanog, or Tcfap4. Gene expression 
changes specific to each trajectories were also evident from the heat-
map (Fig. 5b, Supplementary Table 3). The transition through 
trajectory 1 was associated with the upregulation of 655 genes, which 
include many trophectoderm-related genes (Cdx2, Ascl2, Cebpa, 
Esx1, Hand1, and Rhox6: Group A), indicating the extraembryonic 
direction of differentiation, and the downregulation of 489 genes 
(Group B). By contrast, the transition through trajectory 2 was assoc-
iated the upregulation of 287 genes, which include many epiblast-
related genes inferred from the expression profiles of epiblast stem 
cells 
11 (Fgf5, En1, Sox6, Lrp2, Irx1, Lhx1, Msx1, Hoxa2: Group C), 
indicating the embryonic direction of differentiation, and the down-
regulation of 167 genes (Group D). In addition, 294 genes were 
upregulated and 154 genes were downregulated following both tran-
sitions through trajectory 1 and 2 (Groups E and F, respectively). 
The fact that removing either Pou5f1 or Sox2 had similar tran-
scriptome change (a state change through the trajectory 1) is rea-
sonable, as Pou5f1 and Sox2 are known to form dimers and bind to </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Knockdown of 100 transcription factors (TFs) in mouse ES cells with shRNA. (a) experiment design; (b) list of TFs repressed in this study; TFs </p>

<p>in bold were knocked down with two independent shRNAs; (c) change of mRNA expression of 100 TFs evaluated by microarrays and qPCR 
(see Supplementary Table 1); (d) Western blot shows the reduction of TF proteins; * -non-specific band. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1390 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01390 </p>

<p>
the promoters of target genes </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>. However, it was unexpected that re-
pressing any of Esrrb, Sall4, Nanog, or Tcfap4 caused a similar tran-
scriptome change (a state change through trajectory 2), which was 
distinct from the change caused by repressing either Pou5f1 or Sox2. 
Similar to the situation with trajectory 1, it is possible that Esrrb, 
Sall4, Nanog, and Tcfap4 interact 
13 and regulate the same set of target 
genes. Alternatively, these TFs are a part of a distinct TF subnetwork, 
which together regulates the downstream target genes. 
To gain further insights into these issues, we examined if the TFs 
bind to the promoter region of genes whose expression was changed 
by these TFs by assessing the enrichment of targets (i.e., genes with 
binding sites of TFs) among genes that change their expression in a 
trajectory-specific way (Groups A-D, Fig. 5b). Among 100 TFs 
examined in the current work, we used the information of TF-
binding sites by ChIP-seq analyses that were publicly available for 
28 TFs (Supplementary Table 4), and compared their binding pre-
valence to promoters/enhancers of upregulated versus downregu-
lated genes. We found that genes associated with each trajectory 
differed substantially in the kind of TFs that bind to their promoter 
regions (Fig. 6): the trajectory 1 was characterized by the enrichment 
of targets of Pou5f1, Sox2, Nanog, Btbd14b, and Tcf3 in downregu-
lated genes (Group B); the trajectory 2 was characterized by the </p>

<p>enrichment of targets of Esrrb and Klf4 in downregulated genes 
(Group D) and the enrichment of targets of Polycomb TFs (Eed, 
Suz12, Phc1, Jarid2, and Mtf2) and Trp53 in upregulated genes 
(Group C). Taken together, these results indicate that genes assoc-
iated with the trajectory 1 and 2 are regulated by different sets of TFs. </p>

<p>Discussion 
The data presented here highlight the presence of internal con-
straints in gene regulatory networks, which allow two main ways 
out of the pluripotent state specific for ES cells, something depicted 
as ''Creod'' by Conrad Waddington 
14 . These data also indicate the 
robustness of the pluripotency TF network, as the perturbation 
caused by the transient repression of most TFs did not alter the 
transcriptomes. Considering that the repression of only a handful 
of TFs cause the exit of ES cells from the undifferentiated state, these 
TFs are most likely key TFs that prevent ES cells from cell differenti-
ation. As summarized in Fig. 7, the expression of Pou5f1 and Sox2 
prevent ES cells from differentiating through the trajectory 1, which 
seems to correspond to trophectoderm differentiation; whereas the 
expression of Esrrb, Sall4, Nanog, and Tcfap4 prevent ES cells from 
differentiating through the trajectory 2, which seems to correspond 
to embryonic differentiation. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Gene expression response after the knockdown of 16 trabscription factors with two different shRNA; r 5 correlation, logratio is log10; data </p>

<p>are shown for 13929 genes with average log-expression .2. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1390 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01390 </p>

<p>
Among TFs that preferentially bind to genes downregulated along 
the trajectory 1 (group B in Fig. 5b), only Pou5f1 and Sox2 actively 
prevent extraembryonic differentiation, because the transcriptome 
of cells changed along trajectory 1 after the knockdown of these two 
TFs, but not after the knockdown of Nanog, Btbd14b, and Tcf3 
(Fig. 5a). Although binding sites of Nanog mostly coincide with 
binding sites of Pou5f1 and Sox2 </p>

<p>15,16   , only 86 targets of Pou5f1 and/ 
or Sox2 are downregulated after the knockdown of Nanog, and cells </p>

<p>do not differentiate towards trophectoderm. Nanog-dependent tar-
gets of Pou5f1 and Sox2 included a large number of germline and 
testis-related genes (Prdm1, Prdm14, Kit, Esrrb, Notch4, Inhbb, 
Spats1, Zyg11a, Scgb3a1, Ifitm1, Sfrp1, Hck, Ttpa, Morc1), which is 
consistent with the idea that Nanog is associated with germline 
competence </p>

<p>17   . Initial report on the trophectoderm differentiation 
of mouse ES cells following the knockdown of Nanog 
5 was not 
confirmed by later studies </p>

<p>7,18,19   . 
Among TFs that preferentially bind to the genes downregulated 
along the trajectory 2 (group D in Fig. 5b), only Esrrb actively pre-
vents gene expression change based on our knockdown experiment 
(Fig. 7). Although targets of Klf4 are also over-represented within 
group D, the knockdown of Klf4 did not cause transcriptome change 
along trajectory 2. The lack of effect of Klf4 can be explained by its 
replacement by other TFs of the same gene family (Klf2 and Klf5), 
which can occupy the same binding sites </p>

<p>10   . Published gene expres-
sion data from a triple knockdown of Klf4, Klf2, and Klf5 indicates 
that ES cells undergo differentiation towards embryonic lineages (i.e., </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Knockdown of 100 transcription factors (TFs) with shRNA. </p>

<p>(a) Major TFs that changed transcriptome significantly after the 
knockdown (FDR , 0.05, change .52 fold) (see Supplementary Tables 
1,2). (b) List of other TFs whose knockdown resulted in a change of 
expression of ,20 genes. </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Enrichment of transcription factor (TF) binding to genes that </p>

<p>change their expression after the knockdown of TFs. (a) gene rank plots 
for selected TFs: genes were sorted by the change of their expression and the 
proportion of targets was estimated in a sliding window of 500 genes; (b) z-
value estimated using Parametric Analysis of Gene Set Enrichment (PAGE) 
which evaluates the enrichment of TF targets among genes that were 
upregulated or downregulated after the knockdown (see Supplementary 
Table 4 for the source of ChIP-seq/ChIP-chip data). </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Transcriptome changes of ES cells after the knockdown of transcription factors (TFs). (a) principal components analysis (PCA) of log </p>

<p>expression change of 2666 significant genes after the knockdown of transcription factors; (b) heatmap that shows gene expression changes associated with 
the Trajectory 1 (i.e., knockdown of Pou5f1 or Sox2) and Trajectory 2 (i.e., knockdown of Esrrb, Sall4, Nanog, and Tcfap4) (see Supplementary Table 3). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1390 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01390 </p>

<p>
upregulation of epiblast-related Fgf5, Acta1, Irx5, Msx1 and no upre-
gulation of trophectoderm-related Cdx2, Esx1, Hand1, Plac1, and 
Dlx3 on days 2 and 4) </p>

<p>10   . The importance of Klf4 for sustaining the 
undifferentiated state of ES cells is consistent with its ability to revert 
epiblast stem cells to the ground pluripotent state 
20 . Thus, Esrrb and 
the KLF family of TFs are likely to control the change of gene expres-
sion along the trajectory 2, while core pluripotency TFs (Pou5f1 
and Sox2) are still active (Fig. 7). The importance of Esrrb in ES cell 
differentiation is further supported by the fact that it is a positively-
regulated target of Nanog and Sall4, as follows from our results on 
gene expression change after the knockdown of Nanog and Sall4 
combined with published genome-wide mapping of TF binding 
sites </p>

<p>16   . Because the knockdown of Nanog and Sall4 caused gene 
expression change along trajectory 2, we can hypothesize that the 
effect of these TFs is mediated by downregulation of Esrrb. Also, 
Esrrb is known to be strongly downregulated in epiblast stem cells </p>

<p>11   ; 
its knockdown causes ES cell differentiation towards epiblast-like 
cells 
5 ; and it regulates ES cell self-renewal via Gsk3/Tcf3 pathway </p>

<p>21   . 
The mechanisms that upregulate targets of Polycomb factors 
along trajectory 2 are not clear. None of the Polycomb factors is 
downregulated substantially to explain this effect. Moreover, the </p>

<p>knockdown of each Polycomb TF did not cause much change in 
the expression of downstream genes (Fig. 4, Supplementary 
Table 2). This is consistent with the finding that disruption of 
PRC1 and PRC2 complexes does not affect self-renewal of ES cells </p>

<p>22   . 
It is possible that Esrrb, Klf4, or their downstream targets, directly 
recruit or stabilize Polycomb factors, but there is no sufficient experi-
mental evidence to support such a mechanism. 
The strategy of systematic knockdown of TFs followed by gene 
expression profiling with microarrays allows a higher level of under-
standing of the causative relationship between TFs and their target 
genes, because alternative approaches (e.g., phenotype screening or 
analyzing correlations between gene expression profiles and TF 
binding to promoters) do not differentiate between causation and 
mere correlation. The systematic knockdown of 100 TFs reported 
here is the largest project of this kind in mouse ES cells. These data 
sets are substantial addition to our previous studies, in which a total 
137 TFs are overexpressed in mouse ES cells, individually, followed 
by the global gene expression profilings 
1,2 . The preferred direction of 
perturbation of TFs depends on the level of their expression in a 
given cell type: knockdown is generally more informative for TFs 
with high expression, whereas induction should be used for silent 
and low-expressed TFs. Especially, the use of the standard ES cell 
culture condition in our current and past studies 
1,2 has merits in 
terms of data comparability for the compendium analysis. 
However, this could also limit the generalization of the conclusions 
drawn from the current data sets, and the use of a variety of culture 
conditions in the future is desirable. For example, it is known that 
Esrrb is necessary and sufficient to mediate self-renewal downstream 
of Gsk3 inhibition in LIF 1 2i media, but it is dispensable for the self-
renewal in LIF 1 FBS media </p>

<p>21   . Changing culture conditions would 
certainly add new dimensions to gene regulatory networks and open 
new differentiation pathways. Another limitation of transient 
shRNA-based strategy is that it considers only immediate effects in 
gene expression following the manipulation of TFs, and thus, our 
results do not cover long-term effects related to self-renewal and 
differentiation as previously reported </p>

<p>17,21   . Nonetheless, the global 
inference of gene regulatory networks in ES cells in the standard 
culture condition can facilitate methods for their controlled differ-
entiation into various cell types for therapeutic purposes. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Sequences for 4 shRNA were designed to target the 39 untranslated region of genes, 
and 2 of them were selected (Supplementary Table 5) based on the strong repression 
effect and minimal expression change in a housekeeping gene (Tuba1a) and gene 
associated with antiviral response (Oas1a). ES cells, MC1R (passage 20) established </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Proportion of targets of various transcription factors (TFs) (i.e., genes with TF binding sites) among genes that change their expression </p>

<p>following trajectories 1 (a) and 2(b); (c) z-value that compares the proportions of targets of various TFs between gene groups that were upregulated 
versus downregulated (see Supplementary Tables 3, 4); dashed line -significance level (p 5 0.05). Only those TFs which had a significant difference in 
binding to upregulated genes versus downregulated genes are shown. </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Two trajectories of short-term transcriptome change in ES cells </p>

<p>following manipulation of transcription factors (TFs). Trajectory 1 
(extraembryonic direction) is characterized by the block of Pou5f1 and/or 
Sox2 signaling (via downregulation or interference), which leads to the 
downregulation of targets of Pou5f1 and Sox2. Trajectory 2 (embryonic 
direction) is characterized by the downregulation of targets of Esrrb and 
Klf4 and upregulation of targets of Polycomb factors while Pou5f1 and Sox2 
are still active. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1390 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01390 </p>

<p>
previously 
1 were cultured without feeder cells in standard media. After expansion, 
these cells were co-transfected with 1.6 mg of shRNA expression vector and cultured 
with puromycin starting at 24 h after transfection. Cells were harvested 72 h after 
transfection. We selected 72 h time point as a trade-off between two objectives: (a) to 
capture early responses of target genes and minimize indirect responses, and (b) to 
observe robust changes in gene expression. The early time point (48 h) was not 
chosen due to relatively weak responses: only 111 genes changed their expression by 
.5-fold, as compared to 256 and 579 genes at 72 h and 96 h, respectively. The late 
time point (96 h) was not chosen, because it may include the response of many 
non-target genes that are affected indirectly. In particular, almost 1/2 of genes (48.3%) 
that changed their expression by .2-fold at 96 h did not respond at earlier time 
points (Supplementary Figure 1). The proportion of GFP-positive cells in culture, 
measured by flow cytometry, was high enough (.74% for all shRNA) to justify using 
all cells for gene expression profiling. We chose not to use sorted cells because sorting 
often results in cell damage followed by the induction of stress-related genes. RNA 
was extracted with Trizol 
TM (Invitrogen). Efficiency of knockdown was quantified by 
real time qPCR, microarrays and Western blot (Fig. 1c, d); primers and antibodies are 
listed in Supplementary Tables 6, 7. Gene expression was profiled with NIA Mouse 
44 K Microarray v3.0, Agilent Technologies, #015087 </p>

<p>23   . The data was batch-
normalization for compatibility of experiments. Microarray data are submitted to 
GEO/NCBI (GSE26520). Two shRNA were used for the majority of TFs and we 
treated them as biological replications using ANOVA. Some of these experiments 
included also 2 technical replications where cells were split after transfection cultured 
separately and RNA was hybridized to separate microarrays. Further details on cell 
manipulation and data analysis can be found in the project website: 
http://esbank.nia.nih.gov/. For statistical analysis we used <rs type="software">NIA Array Analysis</rs>, which 
estimates the False Discovery Rate (FDR) to account for multiple hypothesis testing 
24 . 
All genes shown as significant in Fig. 4 and Supplementary Table S2 satisfy stringent 
statistical criteria (FDR , 0.05, fold change .2). Response of genes to the knockdown 
of TFs was measured as a logratio (i.e., difference between mean log-transformed 
expression in the knockdown experiment and global median expression). Principal 
component analysis (PCA) of log-transformed gene expression was done using genes 
that showed statistically significant change in their expression (FDR , 0.05) with 
SVD method applied to the covariance matrix of log-transformed gene expression 
values within the <rs type="software">NIA Array Analysis</rs>. 
Published ChIP-seq data on binding of 28 TFs (Supplementary Table 4) was 
compiled from either provided lists of gene symbols, or genome locations of binding 
sites. We used a distance of 15 Kb from the TSS as a generic threshold for associating 
binding sites with specific genes. TFs associated with ES cell pluripotency are often 
co-localized on DNA, making multiple transcription factor-binding loci (MTLs) 
16 . 
Because these loci are associated with the binding of at least 4 TFs, they are highly 
reliable and can be used for detecting enhancers located far from the TSS. We used 
MTLs to add information on enhancers located within 200 Kb from the TSS for 
Pou5f1, Sox2, Nanog, Esrrb, Tclcp2l1, Klf4, Stat3, and Sall4 (Supplementary Table 4). 
For the TFs that have multiple sets of targets in our database, we selected the data that 
yielded highest enrichment scores (PAGE, see below) for sets of genes affected by 
manipulation of TFs, or combined multiple data sets. 
Enrichment of target genes in subsets of genes that are upregulated and/or 
downregulated following the manipulation of a TF is quantified using a modified 
Parametric Analysis of Gene Enrichment (PAGE) 
25 . PAGE is based on the 
comparison of the average expression change in a specific subset of genes, x set , with 
the average expression change in all genes, x all : </p>

<p>z~x set {x all 
ð 
Þ 
Ã sqrt n set 
ð Þ=SD all 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where n set is the size of the gene set and SD all is standard deviation of expression 
change among all genes. We modified this method by applying equation (1) to the 
subset of N top upregulated and another subset of N top downregulated genes rather 
than to all genes combined, which allowed us to detect enrichment of the same gene 
set among both upregulated and downregulated genes. The value of N 5 5000 was 
selected experimentally because it appeared that enrichment of genes with TF binding 
sites is always limited to the top 5000 upregulated or downregulated genes. The 
probability distribution of expression change within subsets of N upregulated and 
downregulated genes is not normal; however, because we compare averages for large 
sets of genes (usually, n set is .50), the probability distribution of these averages is 
close to normal based on the central limit theorem </p>

<p>26   . Thus, it is reasonable to use 
equation (1) as approximation. 
For the heatmap (Fig. 5b), we selected 2046 named genes (excluding olfactory 
receptors and Riken clones) with .1.5 fold median change following the knockdown 
of Pou5f1 and Sox2 (trajectory 1) or knockdown of Esrrb, Sall4, Nanog, and Tcfap4 
(trajectory 2). These genes were then classified into 6 response groups as follows: if the 
logratio of gene expression change was .2 fold greater following one trajectory that 
another trajectory, then the gene was considered specific to the former trajectory. A 
small number of genes (N 5 18) responded in opposite directions following 
trajectories 1 and 2. We classified them according to the strongest absolute value of 
the median logratio of gene expression change. Within each group, genes were sorted 
using hierarchical clustering, <rs id="software-2" type="software">TMEV</rs>, ver <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.1</rs> 
27 . </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This research was supported in part by the Intramural Research Program of the NIH, 
National Institute on Aging. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>All authors participated in designing the study, carrying out experiments, analyzing the 
results, interpreting the data, or participating in the discussion. AAS and MSHK wrote the 
manuscript text and prepared figures. All authors reviewed the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Nishiyama, A. et al. Systematic repression of transcription factors 
reveals limited patterns of gene expression changes in ES cells. Sci. Rep. 3, 1390; 
DOI:10.1038/srep01390 (2013). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1390 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01390 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>