<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3177212" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Various environmental oxidative stresses are sensed 
by redox-sensitive regulators through cysteine thiol 
oxidation or modification. A few zinc-containing 
anti-sigma (ZAS) factors in actinomycetes have 
been reported to respond sensitively to thiol oxida-
tion, among which RsrA from Streptomyces 
coelicolor is best characterized. It forms disulfide 
bonds upon oxidation and releases bound SigR to 
activate thiol oxidative stress response genes. Even 
though numerous ZAS proteins exist in bacteria, 
features that confer redox sensitivity to a subset of 
these have been uncharacterized. In this study, we 
identified seven additional redox-sensitive ZAS 
factors from actinomycetes. Comparison with redox-
insensitive ZAS revealed characteristic sequence 
patterns. Domain swapping demonstrated the signifi-
cance of the region K 33 FEHH 37 FEEC 41 SPC 44 LEK 47 
that encompass the conserved HX 3 CX 2 C (HCC) 
motif. Mutational effect of each residue on diamide 
responsive induction of SigR target genes in vivo 
demonstrated that several residues, especially those 
that flank two cysteines (E39, E40, L45, E46), con-
tribute to redox sensitivity. These residues are well 
conserved among redox-sensitive ZAS factors, and 
hence are proposed as redox-determinants in sen-
sitive ZAS. H37A, C41A, C44A and F38A mutations, 
in contrast, compromised SigR-binding activity sig-
nificantly, apparently affecting structural integrity of 
RsrA. The residue pattern around HCC motif could 
therefore serve as an indicator to predict redox-
sensitive ZAS factors from sequence information. </p>

<p>Bacteria respond to environmental changes primarily by 
changing transcription profiles in gene expression. An ef-
ficient way of changing transcriptome globally is to use 
alternate sigma factors, whose activities are elaborately 
controlled via various sensing mechanisms including 
anti-sigma factors (1,2). Among s 70 family of sigma fac-
tors, which contain conserved DNA-binding domains for 
recognizing À35 and À10 regions of promoters, group 4 or 
extracytoplasmic function (ECF) sigma factors, are the 
most abundant and diverse subclass (3-6). They constitute 
$60% of all s 70 family of sigma factors predicted from 
bacterial genomes. About one-third of their genes lie next 
to genes for anti-sigma factors containing structurally con-
served sigma-binding (anti-sigma) domain (3). A proto-
typical example of the group 4 sigma-anti-sigma pair is 
RpoE-RseA of Escherichia coli (Eco) that respond to a 
variety of cell envelope stresses (7,8). 
Among group 4 anti-sigma factors, RsrA from 
Streptomyces coelicolor (Sco) that binds s R (SigR) and 
regulates response to thiol oxidative stresses is the first 
reported ZAS (zinc-containing anti-sigma) factor (9,10). 
ChrR from Rhodobacter sphaeroides (Rsp) that binds s E 
and regulates response to singlet oxygen generated during 
photosynthesis also contains zinc (11). These two, along 
with many others, share a conserved sequence motif of 
HX 3 CX 2 C (HCC) in the anti-sigma domain (ASD), 
which can be called as a ZAS motif. About 40% of 
ECF-linked anti-sigma factors are predicted to possess this 
ZAS motif (3). Examples of the anti-sigma factors with 
ZAS motif include SigH-binding RshA of Mycobacterium 
tuberculosis (Mtu) that responds to thiol oxidative stress 
(12), SigW-binding RsiW of Bacillus subtilis (Bsu) that 
responds to cell envelope stresses (13,14), SigU-binding 
RsuA of S. coelicolor that regulates protein secretion </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +82 2 880 4411; Fax: +82 2 872 1993; Email: jhroe@snu.ac.kr </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </p>

<p>7586-7597 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 
Published online 17 June 2011 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr477 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>and cell differentiation (15,16), SigL-binding RslA of 
M. tuberculosis (17), and a RpoE-binding ZAS factor of 
Neisseria meningitides (18). 
In S. coelicolor, RsrA responds to thiol oxidants such as 
diamide by forming disulfide bond primarily between C11 
and C44 residues conserved among ZAS members (19,20). 
Mutational studies revealed that zinc is bound through the 
two conserved cysteine residues in the ZAS motif (C41 
and C44), and possibly through additional conserved resi-
dues H37 and C11 (10,20,21) or less conserved residues C3 
and H7 (19). Zinc release accompanies disulfide bond for-
mation, which causes a drastic conformational change to 
release bound SigR (9,20) to transcribe its target genes to 
cope with thiol oxidative stress (22-24). 
Among verified or predicted ZAS, only ScoRsrA and 
MtuRshA have been shown experimentally to be sensitive 
to thiol oxidation by diamide (9,12). There have been some 
indications that SigH of Corynebacterium glutamicum could 
be regulated by its cognate anti-sigma factor in a similar way 
as ScoSigR or MtuSigH (25,26). However, experimental 
evidence for redox-sensitive regulation of its anti-sigma 
factor has been lacking. Another ZAS from M. tuberculosis, 
RslA, which regulates SigL has been proposed to be 
redox-sensitive on the basis of disulfide bond formation 
in vitro by treating 10 mM H 2 O 2 (27). However, since SigL 
does not respond to oxidative stress in vivo (17), it may not 
respond as sensitively to thiol oxidative stress in vivo as 
ScoRsrA and MtuRshA do. YlaD, which binds its cognate 
sigma factor YlaC in B. subtilis, has been controversial in 
terms of redox sensitivity (28,29). However, since its inacti-
vation was observed only under high concentration of H 2 O 2 
(2.5 mM) in vitro (29), it can be regarded relatively insensitive 
to thiol oxidation. Other ZAS factors such as RspChrR, 
BsuRsiW, and ScoRsuA have all been reported to be insensi-
tive to thiol oxidants (11,13-15). 
What makes certain ZAS factors sensitive to redox 
changes? Before we proceed to find clues to this question, 
we need more ZAS factors at hand that are sensitive to 
oxidation. In this study, we identified seven additional 
redox-sensitive ZAS proteins among close homologs of 
ScoRsrA in Actinomycetes. Comparing their sequences 
with the known redox-sensitive and insensitive ZAS 
proteins, and through swapping and alanine-scanning 
mutagenesis, we define signatures around the ZAS motif 
that contribute to redox sensitivity. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Bacterial strains and culture conditions </p>

<p>Streptomyces coelicolor A3(2) strain M145 (wild-type) 
and the mutants were grown in YEME liquid medium </p>

<p>containing 5 mM MgCl 2 · 6H 2 O and 10% sucrose at </p>

<p>30 C by inoculating spore suspension (30). Other actino-
mycetes obtained either from the stock center at the 
Institute of Microbiology, SNU or from individual re-
searchers were grown to prepare DNA as described 
below. Nocardia farcinica (ATCC 3318) was grown in 
GY medium (1% glucose, 1% yeast extract, pH 7.0) at 
30 C. Corynebacterium glutamicum (ATCC 13032), 
Arthrobacter aurescens (IFO 12136) and Brevibacterium </p>

<p>linens (ATCC 9172) were grown in brain heart infusion 
broth (Difco) at 30 C whereas C. diphtheriae (ATCC 
11913) was grown at 37 C in the same medium. 
Thermobifida fusca (ATCC 27730) was grown in GYM 
medium (0.4% glucose, 0.4% yeast extract, 1% malt 
extract, 0.2% CaCO 3 , pH 7.2) at 50 C. M. smegmatis 
(IFO 3083) was grown in nutrient broth (Difco) at 37 C. 
Rhodococcus jostii RHA1 (from Dr William W. Mohn, 
University of British Columbia) was cultured in LB (1% 
tryptone, 0.5% yeast extract and 1% NaCl) at 30 C. Cells 
were grown by shaking at 200 rpm and harvested at the 
early stationary phase. Cultured cells of Frankia alni 
ACN14, donated by Dr Beth C. Mullin (University of 
Tennessee) were used directly to extract chromosomal 
DNA. The chomosomal DNA of M. tuberculosis H37Rv 
was a kind gift from Dr M.Y. Hahn (Yonsei University). 
Bacillus subtilis strains used in this work were provided by 
Dr Thomas Wiegert (University of Bayreuth). Bacillus 
subtilis and E. coli strains were cultured in LB according 
to standard procedures (14). The strains and plasmids used 
in this study were summarized in the Supplementary 
Table S1. </p>

<p>Homolog prediction and sequence analysis </p>

<p>BlastP algorithm was used to predict sequence homologs 
of ScoRsrA from NCBI nr database (ftp://ftp.ncbi.nih 
.gov/blast/db/). Multiple sequence alignment and gener-
ation of phylogenetic tree were done by using <rs type="software">MEGA4</rs> 
software (31). A probable structure of ScoRsrA was 
created based on the determined structure of 
R. sphaeroides ChrR (3; PDB ID:2Z2S) by using 
<rs type="software">Modeller</rs> program (32), and was visualized through 
<rs type="software">PyMOL</rs> (33). Sequence logos were generated by using 
<rs type="software">TEXshade</rs> (34,35). </p>

<p>Replacement of the rsrA gene in S. coelicolor with 
selected homologs from other actinomycetes </p>

<p>Chromosomal DNAs were prepared from various actino-
mycetes according to standard procedures (30), and were 
subjected to PCR to amplify rsrA ortholog genes. The 
primer pairs amplified the entire open reading frames 
with NdeI and BamHI sites at the start codon and at 
immediately downstream of the stop codon, respectively 
(Supplementary Table S2). The NdeI/BamHI-digested 
PCR products were cloned into pUC19-based recom-
binant plasmid (pUC19sigRrsrA-NB) that harbors 
S. coelicolor sigR-rsrA operon to replace the rsrA gene. 
The resulting hybrid sigR operon was cut with HindIII/ 
BamHI and recloned into the EcoRV site of pSET152H 
that is capable of conjugation (36) (Figure 2A). The final 
pSET152H-based recombinant plasmids where the rsrA 
gene was replaced with nfa45830 (N. farcinica), 
Rv3221A (sigH, M. tuberculosis), DIP0710 (C. diphtheria), 
FRAAL6009 (F. alni), AAur_2640 (A. aurescens), BlinB_ 
010200019545 (B. linens), NCgl0852 (C. glutamicum), 
Tfu_0549 (T. fusca), MSMEG_1915 (M. smegmatis) and 
RHA1_ro06342 (R. jostii), were confirmed by sequencing 
and introduced into the ÁsigR rsrA mutant of S. coelicolor 
through conjugation. The exconjugants that contain the </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7587 </p>

<p>recombinant plasmid in the chromosome were selected and 
confirmed by nucleotide sequencing. </p>

<p>Swapping of HCC region between ScoRsrA and BsuRsiW </p>

<p>The nucleotide sequences corresponding to 15 amino acids 
from K33 to K47 (KFEHHFEECSPCLEK) of ScoRsrA 
and those from V26 to H40 (VLNEHLETCEKCRKH) of 
BsuRsiW, harboring the conserved HCC motif (bold 
letters), were swapped with each other in the rsrA and 
rsiWD2 (deleted of trans-membrane and extracellular 
domains) genes of S. coelicolor and B. subtilis. For this 
purpose, a modified overlapping PCR was done (37). For 
swapped RsrA (S-RsrA), the primer pair S-RsrAP1 (5 0 tcg 
cg cat atg agc tgc gga3 0 ) and S-RsrAP2 (5 0 CTC GCA TGT 
CTC CAG ATG TTC ATT TAA TAC cac gca gtc cga gtc 
cgg3 0 ) were used to create the upstream half, and the pair 
S-RsrAP3 (5 0 CTG GAG ACA TGC GAG AAA TGC 
AGA AAG CAT tac ggg ctg gag cag gcc3 0 ) and 
S-RsrAP4 (5 0 gac gct cag gga tcc tca gga ctc3 0 ) were used 
to create the downstream half, which overlap by 15 com-
plementary nucleotides. The capital letters indicate 
swapped sequence. The second PCR from partially 
hybridized half templates were done with the primer pair 
S-RsrAP1 and S-RsrAP4 to create the entire open reading 
frame for S-RsrA. For swapped and trunctated RsiW 
(ST-RsiW), the primer pair ST-RsiWP1 (5 0 agg tga gga 
tcc atg agc tgt3 0 ) and ST-RsiWP2 (5 0 CGA GCA CTC 
CTC GAA GTG GTG CTC GAA CTT gtg ttc atc ttt 
tgg aag3 0 ) were used to generate the upstream half, and 
the primers ST-RsiWP3 (5 0 TTC GAG GAG TGC TCG 
CCC TGC CTG GAG AAG ttt tac gag atg gag aaa3 0 ) and 
ST-RsiWP4 (5 0 tgc gca tgc tca atg ggt tct gaa cca tct3 0 ) were 
used to generate the downstream half, which overlap by 
15 complementary nucleotides. The second PCR was done 
with ST-RsiWP1 and ST-RsiWP4. The final PCR product 
for S-RsrA was digested with NdeI and BamHI, and 
cloned into the the NdeI/BamHI site of pUC19sigRrsrA-
NB to substitute the rsrA gene, followed by recloning into 
pSET152H and introduction to the DsigRrsrA mutant of 
S. coelicolor as described above. The final PCR product 
for ST-RsiW was inserted into the HindIII/SphI site of 
pALrsiW (14) to replace the wild-type rsiW gene. The re-
sulting pAL-ST-rsiW plasmid was introduced into the 
B. subtilis 1012-1 strain, which is resistant to neomycin and 
spectinomycin resistant (Neo R and Spc R ), to replace the 
Spc R gene in the lacA locus with the erythromycin resist-
ance (Erm R ) gene (14) (Supplementary Table S1). 
Transformants (Neo R , Erm R and Spc S ) were selected to 
isolate 1012-ST-rsiW strain. To knock out the wild-type 
rsiW gene in the 1012-ST-rsiW strain, the rsiW::Spc R 
chromosome was introduced into the strain. The 
ST-rsiW strain was selected by antibiotics (Neo R , Erm R 
and Spc R ) and confirmed by PCR and DNA sequencing. 
Consequently, the ST-rsiW gene at the lacA locus is under 
the control of an IPTG-inducible promoter (14). The re-
combinant B. subtilis strains were grown in LB with ap-
propriate antibiotics, and 0.1-mM IPTG was added to 
induce RsiW variants. For oxidative stress, LB-grown 
cultures were treated with 1 mM diamide at OD 600 of 0.7 
for varying lengths of time before cell harvest. </p>

<p>Alanine-scanning mutagenesis </p>

<p>Each residue from K33 to K47 in ScoRsrA was replaced 
with alanine by site-directed mutagenesis, using alanine-
scanning primers (Supplementary Table S2) and pUC19-
sigRrsrA, according to the protocol provided by 
GENEART Õ site-directed mutagenesis system (Invitrogen). 
The mutated rsrA genes were confirmed by sequencing. 
The HindIII/BamHI fragments from the resulting plas-
mids were cloned into the EcoRV site of pSET152H, 
and the final recombinant plasmids were introduced into 
the ÁsigR rsrA mutant of S. coelicolor through conjuga-
tion. The desired exconjugants were selected and con-
firmed by DNA sequencing. </p>

<p>S1 nuclease mapping </p>

<p>Exponentially growing cells in YEME media were treated 
with different concentrations of diamide for varying 
lengths of time before cell harvest. RNA preparation and 
S1 nuclease mapping were done according to the standard 
procedure (30). Specific probes for SigR-responsive tran-
scripts from the sigR and trxB genes were generated as 
described previously (36). For each sample, 25 mg RNA 
was hybridized at 50 C with gene-specific probes labeled 
with [g-32 P]-ATP. Following S1 nuclease treatment, 
the protected DNA probes were loaded on 5% polyacryl-
amide gel containing 7 M urea, and the radioactive signals 
were detected and quantified by BAS-2500 system (Fuji). </p>

<p>Determination of redox sensitivity of RsrA mutants </p>

<p>The amount of S1 mapped transcripts (response) from 
SigR target genes following treatment with increasing 
amounts of diamide (dose) for 10 min was quantified and 
plotted against diamide concentration. The resulting dose-
response curve was fit to Lineweaver-Burk equation, in an 
analogous way as used in enzyme kinetics or pharmaco-
kinetics to determine K m or LD 50 , respectively, (38). The 
concentration (induction dose) of diamide that allowed 
half-maximal induction of SigR regulon, termed ID IF50 , 
for each variant of ScoRsrA was determined, and was 
regarded as an index to reflect redox sensitivity of each 
RsrA variant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Excavating new redox-sensitive ZAS factors </p>

<p>In order to find more ZAS factors that are sensitive to 
thiol oxidation, close homologs of ScoRsrA in NCBI nr 
database (as of 8 November 2008) were searched by 
BlastP. Only the ASD corresponding to 103 amino acids 
of ScoRsrA was compared. Using a cutoff E-value of 
0.3, 114 candidates were retrieved (See Supplementary 
Table S3 for sequence information). Most of them are 
from actinobacteria, except four; Rmet_0596 (Ralstonia 
metallidurans CH34, Betaproteobacteria), CHU_0600 
(Cytophaga hutchinsonii ATCC 33406, Bacteroidetes), 
Ccel_0804 (Clostridium cellulolyticum H10, Firmicutes) 
and Ctha_1264 (Chloroherpeton thalassium ATCC 35110, 
Chlorobi). The list included reported ZAS factors such as 
RshA from M. tuberculosis (12,17,27) and a predicted </p>



<p>ZAS RshA from C. glutamicum (25). Except for NCgl0852 
from C. glutamicum, all ZAS genes are adjacent to ECF 
sigma factor genes. In M. tuberculosis and M. bovis 
strains, genes for ZAS (RshA) and sigma factor (SigH) 
are separated by a hypothetical ORF. 
We constructed a phylogenetic tree using a neighbor-
joining algorithm provided by <rs type="software">MEGA4</rs> program 
(Figure 1). Four reported redox-insensitive ZAS 
members were included in the phylogenetic analysis for 
comparison. These are RspChrR, BsuYlaD, BsuRsiW 
and ScoRsuA. Only the N-terminal ASD domain was 
included in multiple sequence alignment and phylogenetic 
tree construction. The phylogenetic tree demonstrated 
that the majority of the retrieved homologs cluster closely 
with ScoRsrA (Group I), next to the second cluster </p>

<p>(Group II), which harbors CglRshA from C. glutamicum 
(25). Known insensitive ZAS genes were clustered within 
Groups III and IV. For experimental analysis, we selected 
nine candidates from dispersed branches of group I and 
group II clusters (Figure 1, open circles); Rv3221A 
(MtuRshA), MSMEG_1915 (M. smegmatis), BlinB_ 
010200019545 (Brevibacterium linens), nfa45830 (Nocardia 
farcinica), 
RHA1_ro06382 
(Rhodococcus 
jostii), 
FRAAL6009 (Frankia alni), Tfu_0549 (Thermobifida 
fusca), DIP0710 (C. diphtheria) and AAur_2640 
(Arthrobacter aurescens). A candidate from a branch in 
Group IV, NCgl0852 (C. glutamicum), was also selected 
for experimental analysis. The corresponding genes were 
synthesized through PCR amplification of chromosomal 
DNA as described in 'Materials and Methods' section. We </p>

<p>Figure 1. Phylogenetic relatedness of ScoRsrA homologs. A neighbor-joining tree of RsrA homologs were constructed by using <rs type="software">MEGA4</rs> with 
default parameters. In addition to 104 homologs retrieved by BlastP, ZAS factors which have been reported to be insensitive to oxidation (marked 
with diamonds) were included in the tree. Only the ASD that corresponds to ScoRsrA in each entry was compared. Sequence information for all 
entries is provided in the Supplementary Table S3. Reported redox-senstive RsrA homologs were marked with close circles. 
MtuRshA_M_tuberculosis_and_M_bovis represents 25 identical sequences from M. tuberculosis or M. bovis strains. The 10 homologs whose 
redox-sensitivity was experimentally examined in this study were marked with open circles. Homologs from non-actinobacteria were marked with 
open triangles. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7589 </p>

<p>cloned these genes in pSET152H to replace the rsrA gene 
in the sigR-rsrA operon of S. coelicolor as diagramed in 
Figure 2A. The resulting hybrid operons were introduced 
into the chromosome of DsigRrsrA strain through the att 
site. If the product of the cloned gene behaves similarly to 
ScoRsrA, it is expected to bind SigR in S. coelicolor and 
keep it inactive under non-stressed condition, but will 
release SigR to transcribe its target genes under oxidative 
stress conditions. We analyzed transcripts from SigR-
dependent sigRp2 and trxBp1 promoters by S1 mapping </p>

<p>in various recombinant S. coelicolor strains before and 
after treatment with 0.5-mM diamide for varying lengths 
of time. 
Figure 2B shows representative S1 results, which dem-
onstrate that several homologs behave similarly as 
ScoRsrA and thus deserve to be called its orthologs. For 
example, Tfu_0549, FRAAL6009, RHA1_ro06342, 
BlinB_010200019545, nfa45830, MSMEG_1915 and 
AAur_2640 kept ScoSigR sufficiently inactive under 
non-stressed conditions (0 min), and transiently allowed </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 2. Determination of redox-senstitivity for ten RsrA homologs. (A) Cloning strategy. Genes for ten RsrA homologs were cloned downstream 
of the sigR gene in place of the rsrA gene of S. coelicolor as described in the text. The final pSET152H-based recombinant plasmids were introduced 
into the ÁsigR rsrA mutant of S. coelicolor M145 through conjugation. The resulting exconjugants contain the hybrid sigR operon in the chromo-
some with replaced rsrA homolog from Nocardia farcinica (nfa45830), M. tuberculosis H37Rv (Rv3221A; rshA), C. diphtheriae NCTC13129 
(DIP0710), Frankia alni ACN14a (FRAAL6009), Brevibacterium linens (BlinB_010200019545), C. glutamicum ATCC13032 (NCgl0852), 
Thermobifida fusca YX (Tfu_0549), M. smegmatis MC 2 155 (MSMEG_1915), or Rhodococcus jostii RHA1 (RHA1_ro06342). (B) Diamide-sensitive 
induction of SigR target genes monitored by S1 mapping. The recombinant S. coelicolor strains that harbor different rsrA homologs were grown to 
OD 600 of $0.3 in YEME and treated with 0.5 mM diamide for 20, 40, 80 and 120 min before cell harvest. Transcripts from SigR-dependent sigRp2 
and trxBp1 promoters were analyzed by S1 mapping. The quantified values from more than three independent experiments were presented in 
Supplementary Figure S1. </p>



<p>SigR activation as ScoRsrA did. MtuRshA (Rv3221A) 
was less efficient in sequestering ScoSigR under non-
stressed condition, resulting in higher basal-level expres-
sion. However, it responded to diamide induction as 
expected (12). On the other hand, those from 
Corynebacterium spp. (NCgl0852 and DIP0710) 
appeared inactive in binding SigR, since the basal-level 
expression of both sigRp2 and trxBp1 transcripts were 
constitutively high regardless of diamide treatment. 
Therefore, it is not possible to assess their redox sensitivity 
by our analyses. Considering a difference in GC content 
between Corynebacterium (54%) and S. coelicolor (72%) 
genomes, there also exist a possibility that not enough 
corynebacterial ZAS proteins are expressed due to codon 
bias and other post-transcriptional defects. We quantified 
S1 results from more than three independent experiments 
for each recombinant strain, and presented diamide sensi-
tivity of each homolog as fold-induction values compared 
with the unstressed level (Supplementary Figure S1). This 
analysis, therefore, allowed us to identify seven new 
redox-sensitive ZAS factors, which appear to be function-
al orthologs of ScoRsrA in binding sigma factor SigR and 
responding to thiol oxidative stress. </p>

<p>Comparison of ASDs in redox-sensitive versus -insensitive 
ZAS factors </p>

<p>Multiple sequence alignment of ASDs from nine redox-
sensitive and five insensitive ZAS factors reveal residues 
that are conserved across all ZAS and those that are re-
stricted to redox-sensitive ZAS from actinomycetes 
(Figure 3). In order to delineate broadly functional resi-
dues from subfamily-specific residues in a more systematic 
way, we compared differentially conserved sequence pat-
terns by constructing sequence logos through <rs type="software">TEXshade</rs> 
package (34,35). Figure 3 demonstrated conserved 
sequence logo of all 14 ZAS members, and a differentially </p>

<p>conserved logo of experimentally validated sensitive ZAS 
(nos 1-9) and insensitive ZAS (nos 10-14). Residues 
around the HCC motif (from K33 to E46 in ScoRsrA) 
show some differentially conserved pattern in sensitive 
versus insensitive ZAS proteins. There are also highly con-
served residues among sensitive ZAS such as L22, D23, 
E25, Y48, E51, K55, C62, P68, L71 and R72. However, 
from sequence gazing, it is not possible to distinguish 
residues that are conserved across actinomycetes from 
those that may contribute to redox sensitivity. We there-
fore proceeded to examine the contribution of the region 
that surrounds the conserved ZAS motif to determining 
redox sensitivity. </p>

<p>Evaluation of the HCC region for determining redox 
sensitivity by domain swapping </p>

<p>We created recombinant proteins by exchanging residues 
from K33 to K47 in ScoRsrA with the corresponding resi-
dues (V26 to H40) in RsiW from B. subtilis (Figure 4A). 
The truncated version of RsiW (T-RsiW) that contains 
only the N-terminal 87 amino acid of ASD without 
trans-membrane and extracellular domains was modified 
to make the recombinant. The secondary structure of the 
swapped product (ST-RsiW) was predicted unchanged by 
<rs type="software">Jnet</rs> program (39). The recombinant B. subtilis strains 
that harbor either T-rsiW or ST-rsiW genes in place of 
the wild-type rsiW were examined to determine whether 
diamide can induce SigW-specific gene expression. 
Production of ST-RsiW or T-RsiW was controlled by 
IPTG (14), and the amount of auto-regulated sigW tran-
scripts following diamide treatment was examined by S1 
mapping. 
Figure 4B demonstrates that when T-RsiW is induced, 
sigW expression is drastically reduced, confirming the abil-
ity of T-RsiW to bind and sequester SigW. Treatment with 
diamide did not activate SigW at all, and the sigW gene </p>

<p>Figure 3. Multiple sequence alignment and sequence logo of ScoRsrA homologs. Mulitple sequence alignment was carried out by using <rs type="software">MEGA4</rs>, 
followed by manual curation. Sequence logos were produced by using <rs type="software">TEXshade</rs>. The secondary structure prediction is based on the structural 
information of RspChrR (PDB;2Z2S). For alignment, we trimmed both N-terminal and C-terminal residues that extend beyond the ScoRsrA 
sequence. The nucleotide sequencing identified some sequence differences from the public database, and we used modified sequences for 
BlinB_010200019545, AAur_2640 and FRAAL6009 (+; Supplementary Table S3). Asterisk indicates entries that contain C-terminal domains in 
addition to ASD. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7591 </p>

<p>expression was even lowered compared with the un-
stressed level. Production of ST-RsiW reduced the sigW 
gene expression by $60%, indicating some partial binding 
of SigW by ST-RsiW. When diamide was treated, the ex-
pression level increased up to about 4-fold after 40 min of 
treatment, and then decreased to the basal level at 80 min. 
This result demonstrates that the HCC region of ScoRsrA 
conferred redox sensitivity to the insensitive RsiW. 
We then examined the converse swapping in 
S. coelicolor. In the presence of wild-type RsrA, SigR-
target transcripts (sigRp2) increased dramatically 
after diamide treatment, by 12-to 13-fold as expected 
(Figure 4C). However, in the presence of S-RsrA, the 
diamide induction was significantly reduced to only 
$3-fold level. The low basal level of sigRp2 transcript in 
untreated sample (0 min) indicates that S-RsrA binds SigR </p>

<p>nearly as well as the wild-type. This result again clearly 
indicates that the HCC region of RsrA is a critical deter-
minant of redox sensitivity. The residual low sensitivity of 
S-RsrA appears to reflect contribution from other regions 
in conferring redox sensitivity. </p>

<p>Determination of residues that contribute to redox 
sensitivity in the HCC region </p>

<p>In order to find residue(s) that confer ScoRsrA, its char-
acteristic redox sensitivity, we changed each of the 15 
residues in the swapped HCC region (from K33 to K47) 
to alanine, and introduced the mutated rsrA gene and the 
upstream sigR to DsigR-rsrA strain. As a way to assess 
sensitivity to diamide, we treated each cell samples with 
increasing amounts of diamide from 0 to 0.25 mM for 
10 min, and then monitored the level of SigR-dependent </p>

<p>ScoRsrA </p>

<p>BsuRsiW </p>

<p>Helix 1 
Helix 2 
Helix 3 </p>

<p>MSCGEPHETDCSEILDHLYEFLDKEMPDSDCVKFEHHFEECSPCLEKYGLEQAVKKLVKRCCGQDDVP </p>

<p>MSCPEQIVQLMHMHLDGDILPKDEHVLNEHLETCEKCRKHFYEMEKSIALVRSTSHVEAPA </p>

<p>10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 </p>

<p>10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B. subtilis </p>

<p>S. coelicolor </p>

<p>Swapped T-RsiW </p>

<p>RsrA 
Swapped RsrA </p>

<p>T-RsiW </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>No 
IPTG 
0 
10 
20 
40 
80 </p>

<p>IPTG + 1 mM DA </p>

<p>sigW </p>

<p>1.00 
0.04 
±0.01 </p>

<p>0.01 
±0.00 </p>

<p>0.01 
±0.00 </p>

<p>0.01 
±0.00 </p>

<p>0.01 
±0.01 </p>

<p>sigRp2 </p>

<p>sigRp1 </p>

<p>0.5 mM DA </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
40 
80 
120 </p>

<p>1.00 
12.44 
±0.40 </p>

<p>13.42 
±3.26 </p>

<p>11.96 
±3.10 </p>

<p>1.07 
±0.43 </p>

<p>0.46 
±0.31 </p>

<p>1.00 0.38 
±0.07 </p>

<p>0.49 
±0.05 </p>

<p>1.07 
±0.22 </p>

<p>1.35 
±0.41 </p>

<p>0.30 
±0.17 </p>

<p>No 
IPTG 
0 
10 
20 
40 
80 min </p>

<p>IPTG + 1 mM DA </p>

<p>1.00 
2.69 
±0.55 </p>

<p>3.03 
±0.51 </p>

<p>1.00 
±0.22 </p>

<p>0.88 
±0.12 </p>

<p>0.92 
±0.22 </p>

<p>0.5 mM DA </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
40 
80 
120 min </p>

<p>Figure 4. Swapping of HCC region between ScoRsrA and BsuRsiW. (A) Amino acid sequences and secondary structure predictions were shown for 
B. subtilis RsiW (BsuRsiW) and ScoRsrA. The swapped regions (K33 to K47 in ScoRsrA and V26 to H40 in BsuRsiW) were indicated. (B) The S1 
mapping results of swapped ScoRsrA and T-RsiW (truncated soluble form of BsuRsiW). In B. subtilis, the Tw32Á2 (T-RsiW) and swapped T-RsiW 
(ST-RsiW) strains were grown to OD 600 of 0.7 in LB and harvested at 0, 10, 20, 40, 80 min after diamide (1 mM) treatment. Transcripts from sigW 
promoters were analyzed by S1 mapping. Quantified values of the sigW transcript bands were normalized to ribosomal RNAs in each sample, and 
the relative expression values from three independent experiments were presented in comparison with the level in the absence of RsiW induction by 
IPTG. (C) In S. coelicolor, strains that contain wild-type rsrA (MK2) or swapped rsrA (S-RsrA) in the same genetic background (Supplementary 
Table S1) were grown to OD 600 of $0.3 in YEME, and were harvested at 0, 10, 20, 40, 80, 120 min after treatment with 0.5 mM diamide. Transcripts 
from sigRp2 promoter were analyzed by S1 mapping. Quantified value of the SigR-dependent sigRp2 signal was normalized to the constitutive 
sigRp1 level in each sample. Relative expression values from more than three independent experiments were presented in comparison with the 
un-induced level. </p>



<p>transcripts (sigRp2) by S1 mapping. The quantified results 
were plotted either as expression levels or induction fold 
against diamide concentrations. Figure 5 exhibits profiles 
of the sigRp2 expression in the mutants, in comparison 
with that in the wild-type (black curve). It was evident 
from the graph that some mutations affected SigR-
specific expression drastically in such a way to elevate 
the un-stressed level and lower fold-induction accordingly 
(Figure 5A and C). These mutations are H37A, C41A, 
C44A and F38A. These residues are those that are very 
well conserved in all ZAS, including F38 which shares 
similar hydrophobicity with the conserved leucine at this 
position (Figure 3). Since the highly elevated level of basal 
expression reflects free dissociated SigR, these mutations 
must have damaged the integrity of the overall structure of 
RsrA. The swapped S-RsrA was also examined by this 
assay, and demonstrated very low induction, consistent 
with the observation in Figure 4C. 
The rest of the mutants exhibited relatively subtle effects 
(Figure 5B). Under non-stressed condition, they showed 
low basal-level expression of sigRp2 comparable with the 
wild-type, indicating that the mutations did not damage 
the structural integrity or the activity of RsrA to bind 
SigR. Regarding diamide sensitivity, some behaved </p>

<p>almost like the wild-type whereas the others showed less 
sensitive induction. F34A produced widely varying results. 
In order to normalize different levels of basal expression 
and maximum induction level, we re-plotted the expres-
sion data of Figure 5A and B to present changes in induc-
tion fold for each mutant (Figure 5C and D). The graphs 
in Figure 5B and D can be regarded as dose-dependent 
response curves typically observed in enzyme-or 
pharmaco-kinetic analyses. We therefore applied 
Lineweaver-Burk equations to fit the data and calculated 
the concentration of diamide that caused 50% maximal 
induction for each mutant, defined as ID IF50 (induction 
dose at 50% maximum induction fold) or ID EL50 (induc-
tion dose at 50% maximum expression level). ID EL50 and 
ID IF50 values were very close to each other. The quantified 
values for the basal level sigRp2 expression and ID IF50 
were summarized in Table 1. Compared with the wild-
type (ID IF50 of 39.5 mM diamide), several mutants showed 
significant increases in ID IF50 values. For example, K33A, 
H36A, E39A, E40A, S42A, L45A and E46A caused ele-
vation of ID IF-50 by more than 2-fold, implying that these 
residues contribute to redox sensitivity. Relatively larger 
effects were observed in L45A, E40A, E46A and E39A 
mutants by 7.7, 4.8, 4.0 and 3.2-fold increases in ID IF50 , </p>

<p>Figure 5. Redox sensitivies of Ala-scanned ScoRsrA mutants. Each of the 15 residues from K33 to K47 in ScoRsrA was changed to alanine in 
recombinant S. coelicolor strains that harbor mutated rsrA in sigR-rsrA operon inserted at the att site of the DsigR-rsrA strain. Cells were grown to 
OD 600 of $0.3 in YEME and treated with varying concentrations of diamide (0, 10, 25, 50, 100, 250 mM) for 10 min. Following S1 mapping, the 
normalized sigRp2 signal values were plotted either as expression levels (A and B) or induction fold (C and D) against diamide concentrations. For 
expression values, the uninduced basal level of the wild-type was set as 1.0. For induction folds, the uninduced levels of all strains were set as 1.0. 
Mutants that constitutively induced SigR-specific expression were presented separately (panels A and C) from those that affected primarily sensitivity 
to diamide (panels B and D). Quantified values for induction folds were presented in Table 1. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7593 </p>

<p>respectively. These residues flank the two conserved cyst-
eines (C41 and C44) and show pronounced conservation 
among sensitive ZAS members. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Extended list of redox-sensitive ZAS </p>

<p>Among 9 RsrA homologs selected for experimental ana-
lysis from dispersed branches of a phylogenetic tree com-
posed of 114 homologs of ScoRsrA, we identified seven 
new redox-sensitive ZAS proteins from M. smegmatis, 
B. linens, N. farcinica, R. jostii, F. alni and T. fusca. 
Two candidates from C. glutamicum and C. diphtheria 
were not eligible for our assay, since they appear incapable 
of binding ScoSigR under unstressed conditions, resulting 
in constitutive expression of SigR target genes. 
Considering the difference in GC content, there is also a 
possibility that not enough proteins were expressed. The 
high success rate of finding sensitive ZAS leads to a pre-
diction that the majority of the retrieved homologs, espe-
cially those of groups I and II (Figure 1), are likely to be 
functional orthologs of ScoRsrA, regulating SigR-like 
sigma factor encoded from a neighboring gene, in 
response to thiol oxidative stresses. Since our assay was 
restricted by the ScoSigR-binding ability of the homolog, 
only close homologs that can bind ScoRsrA can be 
evaluated for their redox sensitivity. If a more generalized 
assay that utilizes cognate sigma factor were available, it is 
expected that a broader spectrum of sensitive ZAS 
proteins could be evaluated. </p>

<p>Contribution of zinc-binding domain to determine redox 
sensitivity </p>

<p>Sequence comparison revealed a number of conserved 
residues among sensitive ZAS (Figure 3). However, since 
all the sensitive ZAS proteins are from actinomycetes, it is 
not possible to distinguish the residues that contribute to 
redox sensitivity from those conserved among actinomy-
cetous RsrA homologs. Swapping of zinc-binding regions </p>

<p>between sensitive (ScoRsrA) and insensitive (BsuRsiW) 
ZAS demonstrated that the 15 amino acid stretch centered 
around the HCC motif contributed significantly to deter-
mining sensitivity. Estimation of redox sensitivity of each 
Ala-substituted mutant of this region revealed the import-
ance of residues surrounding the HCC motif (Figure 5 and 
Table 1). In Figure 6, we presented the position of these 
residues in a 3D-structural model of ScoRsrA based on 
the reported structure of RspChrR (3). 
Mutation of the universally conserved residues across 
ZAS (H37, C41 and C44), which are ligands of zinc in 
RspChrR (3), and are reported to serve a similar role in 
ScoRsrA (20,21), all caused constitutive expression of the 
SigR target gene. Another highly conserved hydrophobic 
residue F38 (leucine in most other cases) showed similar 
effect. Based on biochemical analyses of SigR binding and 
disulfide bond formation, loss of zinc in ScoRsrA is 
known to decrease its binding affinity to ScoSigR (19) 
and to render RsrA more labile to oxidation (20). For 
ScoRsrA, whose structural information is not yet avail-
able, the zinc-binding residues are not well resolved. The 
extended X-ray absorption fine structure (EXAFS) spec-
troscopy of a mutant form of RsrA, where non-conserved 
cysteines (C3, C31, C61, C62) were all substituted with 
alanines, suggested that the bound zinc closely interacts 
with C11, H37, C41 and C44, in a way similarly observed 
in the structure of RspChrR as observed previously 
(10,21). Assessment of zinc content in various ScoRsrA 
mutants suggested the possibility of C3 and H7 in the 
extended N-terminal loop, in addition to C41 and C44, 
to participate in zinc binding (19). Even though the 
H37-corresponding residue in ChrR structure (H31) 
serves as a zinc ligand, its mutation did not affect 
anti-sigma activity of ChrR, implying that it may contrib-
ute marginally to zinc-binding affinity (3). Similarly weak 
interaction between H37 and zinc has been reported 
(19,21). Therefore, the conserved H37 may contribute 
further in determining ScoRsrA structure beyond serving 
as a zinc-binding ligand. Based on these studies, it is 
highly likely that C41 and C44 are involved in zinc </p>

<p>Table 1. SigR-binding activity and diamide sensitivity of RsrA variants </p>

<p>RsrA 
BL a 
ID IF50 (mM) b 
Relative 
ID IF50 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>RsrA 
BL 
ID IF50 (mM) 
Relative 
ID IF50 </p>

<p>WT 
0.8 ± 0.1 
39.5 ± 3.5 
1.0 
C41A 
6.7 
ND 
ND 
K33A 
1.1 ± 0.1 
79.6 ± 7.2 
2.0 
S42A 
0.7 ± 0.1 
110.3 ± 21.9 
2.8 
F34A 
2.8 ± 1.9 
49.9 ± 6.8 
1.3 
P43A 
0.4 ± 0.3 
45.5 ± 12.3 
1.2 
E35A 
0.9 ± 0.5 
54.8 ± 38.3 
1.4 
C44A 
7.1 
ND 
ND 
H36A 
0.6 ± 0.2 
103.8 ± 14.0 
2.6 
L45A 
0.7 ± 0.3 
303.3 ± 86.7 
7.7 
H37A 
5.7 
ND 
ND 
E46A 
0.8 ± 0.3 
158.6 ± 34.1 
4.0 
F38A 
8.0 ± 3.1 
ND 
ND 
K47A 
0.7 ± 0.4 
38.5 ± 16.8 
1.0 
E39A 
0.6 ± 0.2 
128.3 ± 42.4 
3.2 
S-RsrA 
1.4 ± 0.5 
9.1 ± 0.6 
0.2 
E40A 
0.9 ± 0.3 
191.4 ± 146.6 
4.8 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The basal-level (BL) expression of sigRp2 was normalized in each sample to the level of constitutive sigRp1 expression in the absence of diamide. 
For each sample, the value was presented as an average ± standard deviation from more than three independent experiments except for H37A, H41A 
and H44A. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The diamide concentration in micromolar (induction dose; ID) needed to induce sigRp2 to the level corresponding to half-maximum induction fold 
(IF 50 ). Each value represents an average ± standard deviation from more than three independent experiments. ND, not-determined. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Relative ID IF50 is in comparison with the wild-type value set as 1.0. </p>



<p>binding. However, identification of additional zinc ligands 
in ScoRsrA requires further studies. Whether zinc binds to 
more than two alternative sites, and whether these alter-
native forms are at equilibrium in the cell remain open for 
deeper investigation. More systematic analyses combined 
with structural studies are in need to get better under-
standing of zinc-binding in ScoRsrA. 
The residues, whose mutation enhanced ID IF50 by more 
than 2-fold, were marked in Figure 6 (sky blue dots; K33, 
H36, E39, E40, S42, L45, E46). The most pronounced 
effect was observed for L45A, E40A, E46A and E39A, 
which increased ID IF50 by 7.7-, 4.8-, 4.0-and 3.2-fold, re-
spectively. These four residues immediately flank the two 
conserved cysteines (C41 and C44), and show pronounced 
differential conservation among sensitive ZAS members 
(Figure 6). In this respect, the presence of negatively 
charged residues (DE) preceding C41, and a hydrophobic 
(L) and a charged residue (R/E) following C44, could be 
a critical determinant of redox sensitivity. The P43A 
mutation did not change sensitivity significantly, but 
lowered the basal level by about 2-fold (Table 1). This 
suggests that the mutation could have caused tighter 
binding of SigR under unstressed condition. </p>

<p>Factors that contribute to the reactivity of 
zinc-coordinated protein thiols </p>

<p>RsrA is an example of redox sensors containing reactive 
zinc-cysteine centers (40,41). Protein thiols with low pKa 
value get easily deprotonated, and exist as an anionic </p>

<p>thiolate form. Zinc can lower pKa of the protein thiol 
through stabilizing the thiolate form, and thus is capable 
of increasing the reactivity of cysteine thiols toward elec-
trophilic oxidants and alkylating compounds (42). 
However, the actual reactivity of the zinc-thiol (or 
thiolate) center also depends on its structural environment 
that includes hydrogen bonding, dielectric properties, elec-
trostatic screening, and protein packing (42-44). For 
example, an increase in the steric and electrostatic 
shielding of anionic zinc cores in zinc fingers is correlated 
with a decrease in their reactivity (43). 
Previous observation that de-metallated RsrA becomes 
more vulnerable to oxidation in vitro can be interpreted to 
suggest that (i) zinc binding in RsrA protects thiolates, 
especially that of C41, from labile oxidation, and/or (ii) 
the reactive thiolate in apo-RsrA is more surface-exposed 
due to structural relaxation compared with the zinc-bound 
form. In this respect, the binding affinity as well as the 
flexibility in choosing ligands of zinc are likely to affect the 
reactivity of active-site cysteine (C41 in ScoRsrA), which 
most likely is located in the middle of the loop between 
helixes 2 and 3 of the ASD (3). Therefore, one can hy-
pothesize that the zinc binding to (H)CC motif in sensitive 
ZAS could be weaker and/or more flexible relative to that 
in insensitive ZAS, due to the specified residue environ-
ment of the motif. Further comparative studies of sensitive 
versus insensitive ZAS are in need to find whether any 
differences in zinc-binding properties, if present, contrib-
ute to determine redox sensitivity. </p>

<p>Figure 6. The conserved sequence pattern and the position of the residues near the HCC motif in 3D structural model of ScoRsrA. Multiple 
sequence alignment and sequence logos for the 15 amino acid region examined for mutational analyses were presented as in Figure 3. A 3D structural 
model was produced through homology modeling, using RspChrR structure (PDB; 2Z2S) as a template. Residues that affected redox-sensitivity 
(ID IF50 ) by more than 2-fold were indicated with cyan circles, whereas those that affected structural integrity of ScoRsrA were indicated with red 
ones. Mutations that partially affected ScoRsrA structure by decreasing interaction with SigR (F34, red open circle) or increasing interaction with 
SigR (P43, blue open circle) were also indicated. In the structure model, Cb atoms of effective residues were highlighted as spheres with indicated 
colors. The mutated 15 amino acid region in 3D structure was highlighted in orange color. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7595 </p>

<p>An extended component of structural environment 
involves protein-protein interaction with interacting 
partners. Studies on the sequence variation of dipeptide 
sequence in the CXXC motifs of thioredoxin and related 
proteins revealed that cysteine reactivity depends not only 
on pKa and redox potential values, but also on interacting 
partners (45-47). Since nearly all RsrA in the reduced 
cytoplasm is thought to exist as a bound complex with 
SigR, the interacting SigR environment around the 
reactive zinc-thiol center can also contribute to redox sen-
sitivity. The HCC motif, which spans from the C-terminal 
end of helix 2 to the N-terminal end of helix 3, is modeled 
to be relatively exposed to the surface, away from the 
interacting sigma factor (3). However, the remaining 
residues of helixes 2 and 3, especially helix 3, are 
thought to interact heavily with the bound sigma factor. 
In the absence of structural information on SigR-RsrA 
complex, it is not possible to delineate residues that 
interact with SigR. A structural model based on the 
template of RpoE-ChrR complex structure suggests that 
S42 and E46 in helix 3 are positioned toward the 
SigR-interacting face (C.O. Seok, personal communica-
tion). However, the relatively distant sequence relatedness 
between ScoSigR and RspRpoE hinders precise modeling. 
To assess the contribution from the interacting sigma 
factor, precise structural information on SigR-RsrA inter-
action is in need. 
Extensive studies on finding determinants of reactivity 
in protein thiols of thioredoxin family demonstrated the 
contribution of dipeptide (XX) residues in the CXXC 
motif in determining pKa, redox potential, and possibly 
interaction with partner proteins (47,48). A sensitive motif 
for cysteine S-nitrosylation in proteins that are nitrosy-
lated by S-nitroso-glutathione has also been proposed 
(49). In this study, a new type of redox-sensitive motif in 
zinc-bound ASD has been suggested. Considering the 
growing list of redox-regulated proteins, where disulfide 
bonds serve as switches for modulating various functional 
aspects such as localization, interaction and stability, we 
expect this study to add a new insight in finding novel 
redox-sensitive proteins (41). Further biochemical and 
structural analyses will reveal the mechanism behind the 
redox-determining function of specific residues in this 
class of proteins, and give insight in understanding the 
mechanism behind redox-sensing in other zinc proteins. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to Drs William Mohn, Beth 
Mullin, Thomas Wiegert and Mi-Young Hahn for 
providing strains, plasmids, or chromosomal DNA. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>NRL of Molecular Microbiology to JH Roe (NRF-2009-
0079278); Post-doctoral and doctoral fellowships, </p>

<p>respectively, from the second-stage BK21 Program for 
Life Sciences at SNU (to Y.-G.J. and J.-S.Y). Funding 
for open access charge: Office of Research Affairs, Seoul 
National University. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 17 7597 </p>

</text></tei>