<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3510025" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT The small GTPase RhoD regulates actin cytoskeleton to collapse actin stress fi-
bers and focal adhesions, resulting in suppression of cell migration and cytokinesis. It also 
induces alignment of early endosomes along actin filaments and reduces their motility. We 
show here that a constitutively activated RhoD generated two types of actin-containing thin 
peripheral cellular protrusions distinct from Cdc42-induced filopodia. One was longer, almost 
straight, immotile, and sensitive to fixation, whereas the other was shorter, undulating, mo-
tile, and resistant to fixation. Moreover, cells expressing wild-type RhoD extended protru-
sions toward fibroblast growth factor (FGF) 2/4/8-coated beads. Stimulation of wild-type 
RhoD-expressing cells with these FGFs also caused formation of cellular protrusions. Nodules 
moved through the RhoD-induced longer protrusions, mainly toward the cell body. Exoge-
nously expressed FGF receptor was associated with these moving nodules containing endo-
some-like vesicles. These results suggest that the protrusions are responsible for intercellular 
communication mediated by FGF and its receptor. Accordingly, the protrusions are morpho-
logically and functionally equivalent to cytonemes. RhoD was activated by FGF2/4/8. Knock-
down of RhoD interfered with FGF-induced protrusion formation. Activated RhoD specifi-
cally bound to mDia3C and facilitated actin polymerization together with mDia3C. mDia3C 
was localized to the tips or stems of the protrusions. In addition, constitutively activated 
mDia3C formed protrusions without RhoD or FGF stimulation. Knockdown of mDia3 ob-
structed RhoD-induced protrusion formation. These results imply that RhoD activated by FGF 
signaling forms cytoneme-like protrusions through activation of mDia3C, which induces actin 
filament formation. </p>

<p>Diverse types of cell protrusions play roles in a variety of cellular 
functions, including cell migration, cell differentiation, and intercel-
lular communication. Among these protrusions, filopodia and lamel-
lipodia have been extensively and intensively studied. In conse-
quence, molecular mechanisms of their generation and their 
structures and functions are relatively well clarified (Small et al., 
2002; Mattila and Lappalainen, 2008; Faix et al., 2009; Mellor, 2010). 
Actin filament formation is responsible for generation of these pro-
trusions. Filopodia contain tight parallel bundles of actin filaments, 
whereas lamellipodia are filled with branched or cross-linked actin 
filaments. Filopodia serve as sensory antennae or tentacles to probe 
microenvironment of cells, although their roles are diverse and not 
fully understood. On the other hand, lamellipodia are essential for 
cell migration by crawling. Both of these protrusions adhere to the 
substratum through integrin-based focal complexes or nascent focal 
adhesions (Nobes and Hall, 1995; Geiger et al., 2009). 
Cytonemes are actin-based, thin, long cell protrusions first re-
ported in Drosophila wing imaginal disk cells and mouse embryo 
limb bud cells (Ramírez-Weber and Kornberg, 1999), although cy-
tonemes of limb bud cells have been inadequately characterized. 
Wing or eye imaginal disk cells and tracheal cells extend cytonemes 
toward signaling center cells in the organizers, producing specific 
morphogen or growth factor signaling proteins, such as Decapen-
taplegic (Dpp)/bone morphogenetic protein (BMP), Spitz/epidermal 
growth factor (EGF), and Branchless (Bnl)/fibroblast growth factor 
(FGF; Hsiung et al., 2005; Roy et al., 2011). Nodules or punctae con-
taining the receptors of each morphogen/growth factor are specifi-
cally segregated in cytonemes and move through cytonemes to-
ward the cell body. Accordingly, cytonemes are proposed to be 
involved in long-distance intercellular communication by directly 
transferring specific morphogens/growth factors with their recep-
tors. Similar protrusions have been reported in a variety of cell types, 
including human neutrophils, mouse B lymphocytes, and mast cells 
treated in various ways (Galkina et al., 2001; Gupta and DeFranco, 
2003; Fifadara et al., 2010). In addition, viral cytonemes, which ex-
tend from uninfected target cells to an infected cell by the interac-
tion between viral envelope glycoprotein with the receptor, transmit 
retroviruses from infected to uninfected cells (Sherer et al., 2007). 
The Rho family of small GTPases participate in the formation of 
filopodia and lamellipodia by regulating actin filament formation. 
Cdc42 binds to activate neural Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein 
(N-WASP) together with phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate 
(PIP 2 ) or Src homology 3 (SH3) domain-containing proteins. Acti-
vated N-WASP induces Arp2/3 complex-mediated, branched actin 
filament formation (Takenawa and Suetsugu, 2007; Campellone 
and Welch, 2010). Cdc42 also binds and activates mDia2, which 
nucleates and elongates unbranched actin filaments. A current 
working model hypothesizes that a subset of uncapped actin fila-
ments of the Arp2/3 complex-nucleated dendritic networks is tar-
geted for continued actin filament elongation by mDia2 (Yang et al., 
2007; Mattila and Lappalainen, 2008; Faix et al., 2009; Mellor, 
2010). mDia2 also nucleates to form new unbranched actin fila-
ments. The barbed ends of these elongating actin filaments are 
converged through the motor activity of myosin-X, leading to the 
formation of filopodia. The actin filaments are cross-linked to be-
come stiff bundles by fascin in the shaft of filopodia. RhoQ (TC10) 
and RhoJ (RhoT or TCL), both of which are phylogenetically close to 
Cdc42, also activate N-WASP and form longer filopodial protru-
sions than does Cdc42 (Abe et al., 2002), although involvement of 
mDia proteins in actin filament formation for the protrusion forma-
tion is unclear. </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 1, 2012 </p>

<p>RhoD induces cytonemes through mDia3C | 4649 </p>

<p>ied, and each nodule occasionally changed 
velocity during movement (Movie S2). Some 
never or hardly moved during observation. 
We assessed whether the former shorter 
protrusions elongated to form the latter lon-
ger ones. However, the shorter protrusions 
barely elongated during the observation of 
EGFP fluorescence (see Discussion). 
When the EGFP-RhoD(G26V)-trans-
fected cells were fixed with PFA and washed 
to be processed for immunofluorescence 
microscopy, the longer protrusions were 
particularly collapsed or fragmented into 
shorter protrusions (Figure 2B). Thus the 
protrusions are sensitive to physical and 
chemical stresses. At least some of the 
shorter protrusions detected in the fixed 
cells (Figures 1 and S1B) were therefore arti-
factually generated as a result of fixation 
and washing. The properties of longer pro-
trusions, that is, their dimension, inclusion of 
nodules or punctae moving in both direc-
tions, and sensitivity to fixation, are reminis-
cent of cytonemes (Ramírez-Weber and 
Kornberg, 1999; Hsiung et al., 2005; Roy 
et al., 2011). </p>

<p>RhoD-induced protrusions are 
extended toward FGFs and transmit 
FGF receptors </p>

<p>The RhoD(G26V)-induced protrusions were 
often extended toward neighboring cells 
(Figures 1A and S1C). These observations 
and those that the protrusions contained 
moving nodules suggest that the protru-
sions participate in intercellular communica-
tion, as do cytonemes. Because cytonemes 
are formed in response to morphogens/ 
growth factors such as Dpp/BMP, Spitz/EGF, 
and Bnl/FGF in Drosophila (Hsiung et al., 
2005; Roy et al., 2011), we examined 
whether RhoD-induced protrusions are ex-
tended toward FGFs. Heparin-conjugated 
acrylic beads soaked in FGF2, FGF4, or 
FGF8 were placed on dishes culturing 
10T1/2 cells, which had been previously 
transfected with EGFP-tagged wild-type 
(wt) RhoD and subjected to serum starvation 
for 24 h. Although the cells close to the 
beads without FGF coating inefficiently 
extended protrusions, the cells near the 
beads coated with each FGF extended thin 
protrusions toward the beads by 3 h after 
the beads were added (Figure 3A). In addi-
tion, protrusions extending in a forward 
direction to the beads were much longer 
than those extending in a backward direc-
tion (Figure S2A). 
To determine whether FGFs diffused from the beads participate 
in the protrusion extension, we then added FGF2, FGF4, or FGF8 to 
the culture medium of EGFP-RhoD(wt)-transfected and serum-
starved 10T1/2 cells. Although we tried to record a time-lapse </p>

<p>Movie S1). The latter contained fluorescent nodules or punctae. 
Although the nodules moved in both anterograde and retrograde 
directions, most of them eventually moved toward the cell body 
(Movies S1 and S2). The velocity of movement of the nodules var-</p>

<p>FIGURE 1: RhoD gives rise to actin filament-based thin protrusions distinct from Cdc42-induced 
filopodia detected in PFA-fixed cells. (A) Distinct morphology between Cdc42-induced filopodia 
and RhoD-induced protrusions. The 10T1/2 cells transfected with EGFP-Cdc42(G12V) or 
EGFP-RhoD(G26V) were fixed with PFA. EGFP fluorescence (green) and actin filaments 
detected with Alexa Fluor 546-phalloidin (magenta) are shown. Arrows point to Cdc42-induced 
filopodia and RhoD-induced thin protrusions. (B) Presence and absence of microtubules in 
Cdc42-induced filopodia and in RhoD-induced protrusions, respectively. Microtubules were 
detected by anti-β-tubulin mAb staining (magenta). Arrows and arrowheads point to 
microtubule-containing filopodia and the protrusions lacking microtubules, respectively. 
(C) Presence and absence of vinculin-containing focal complexes in Cdc42-induced filopodia and 
in RhoD-induced protrusions, respectively. Vinculin was detected by anti-vinculin mAb staining 
(magenta). Arrows and arrowheads point to vinculin-containing focal complexes in filopodia and 
the protrusions lacking vinculin, respectively. (D) Distribution of fascin in Cdc42-induced 
filopodia and RhoD-induced protrusions. Fascin was detected by anti-fascin mAb staining 
(magenta). Arrows and arrowheads point to fascin-containing filopodia and the protrusions 
lacking fascin, respectively. Scale bars: 10 μm. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>Mammalian FGFs bind and activate al-
ternatively spliced forms of four FGF recep-
tors (FGFR1-4). Among them, FGF2 and 
FGF4 exert mitogenic activity through FG-
FR1c (Ornitz et al., 1996). When we coex-
pressed mOrange2-tagged RhoD(G26V), 
C-terminally EGFP-tagged FGFR1c, and 
Cerulean-tagged wild-type Rab5 in 10T1/2 
cells, FGFR1c and Rab5, which is localized 
to the early endosome membranes (Zerial 
and McBride, 2001), were associated with 
the nodules in the RhoD-formed protrusions 
(Figures 2C and S1D and Movie S3). The 
nodules moved through the protrusions to-
ward the cell body. Collectively these results 
suggest that cells extend protrusions toward 
FGF-sourcing cells through activation of 
RhoD and that the protrusions transmit FGFs 
via FGFRs to the cell body. At least some of 
these FGFs-FGFRs might be transported in 
association with early endosome-like vesi-
cles. Therefore these protrusions are likely 
to be involved in intercellular communica-
tion and morphologically and functionally 
equivalent to cytonemes. </p>

<p>RhoD is activated by FGF signaling and 
required for FGF signaling-mediated 
protrusion formation </p>

<p>Because the RhoD(wt)-expressing cells ex-
tended protrusions toward FGFs, and FGF 
stimulation facilitated protrusion formation in 
the cells, we addressed whether RhoD is ac-
tivated by FGFs. The 10T1/2 cells were trans-
fected with Myc-tagged wild-type RhoD, se-
rum-starved, and stimulated with FGFs. 
Activation of RhoD was analyzed by a pull-
down assay with glutathione S-transferase 
(GST)-tagged GTPase-binding domain (GBD) 
of mDia3C (see Figure 6B, discussed later in 
this article), which is a target protein of RhoD 
(Gasman et al., 2003). Any of FGF2, FGF4, 
and FGF8 activated RhoD within 5 min after 
stimulation, and the activation was sustained 
for &gt;30 min (Figure 4, A and B). The peak 
time of RhoD activation (5-15 min) may re-
flect the initiation time of protrusion forma-
tion (∼10 min; see Figure 3C). Because FGF8 
activated RhoD more strongly and formed 
longer protrusions at 60 min than did FGF2 
and FGF8 (see Figure 3C), there might be a 
correlation between the strength of RhoD ac-
tivation and the length of the protrusions. 
To determine whether RhoD is essential for FGF-induced protru-
sion formation, we knocked down RhoD expression by RNA interfer-
ence (RNAi). Either expression of two distinct Stealth small interfer-
ing RNAs (siRNAs) of RhoD in 10T1/2 cells prominently reduced the 
endogenous RhoD mRNA level, whereas neither significantly af-
fected the endogenous RhoF mRNA level (Figure 4C). Thus both 
these siRNAs efficiently knock down RhoD, but neither has an off-
target effect on RhoF, which is most closely related to RhoD among 
small GTPases. As shown above, FGF8 stimulation highly promoted </p>

<p>image of protrusion elongation, the protrusions scarcely elongated 
during the observation of EGFP fluorescence (see Discussion). Thus 
we measured the length of thin protrusions at fixed time points after 
the FGF stimulation. The cells stimulated with each FGF started to 
extend thin and long protrusions 10 min after the stimulation, and 
the protrusions elongated or were maintained for at least 60 min 
(Figure 3, B and C). These results imply that FGFs diffused from the 
beads or added to the medium are responsible for the protrusion 
formation. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: RhoD generates two types of thin protrusions detected in unfixed cells. 
(A) Time-lapse images of two types of RhoD-induced protrusions. The 10T1/2 cells transfected 
with EGFP-RhoD(G26V) were analyzed by time-lapse imaging at the time indicated (min:s). 
Magenta arrowheads indicate shorter protrusions moving flexibly and dynamically. Green 
arrowheads point to a nodule moving in a retrograde direction through a longer immotile 
protrusion. (B) Breakdown of RhoD-induced protrusions by PFA fixation and washing. The 
10T1/2 cells transfected with EGFP-RhoD(G26V) were observed before (top) and after (bottom) 
15-min PFA fixation and washing with PBS. Arrowheads indicate collapsed or fragmented longer 
protrusions. (C) Time-lapse images of FGFR1c-and Rab5-containing nodules moving through 
the RhoD(G26V)-induced protrusions. The 10T1/2 cells cotransfected with mOrange2-
RhoD(G26V) (red), FGFR1c-EGFP (green), and Cerulean-Rab5(wt) (blue) were analyzed by 
time-lapse imaging at the time indicated. Arrowheads point to FGFR1c-and Rab5-containing 
nodules moving through protrusions. Scale bars: 10 μm. </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 1, 2012 </p>

<p>RhoD induces cytonemes through mDia3C | 4651 </p>

<p>the RhoD siRNAs were expressed in the 
presence of FGF8 stimulation, the protru-
sion formation was reduced almost to levels 
comparable with those seen without FGF8 
stimulation and exogenous RhoD(wt) ex-
pression (Figure 4D). If an siRNA-resistant 
RhoD (Figure S2B) was expressed, the cells 
were released from the siRNA-induced sup-
pression of the protrusion formation and 
formed longer protrusions (Figure 4D). In 
addition, expression of the dominant-nega-
tive RhoD(T31K) also interfered with the 
FGF8-induced protrusion formation (Figure 
S2C). These results indicate that endoge-
nous RhoD is indispensable for FGF8-in-
duced protrusion formation. </p>

<p>N-WASP is not required for 
RhoD-induced protrusion formation </p>

<p>Because the RhoD-induced protrusions con-
tain actin filaments, actin filament formation 
seems to be a prerequisite for protrusion 
formation. Intracellular actin filament forma-
tion necessitates factors that nucleate and 
elongate actin filaments (Dominguez, 2009; 
Campellone and Welch, 2010; Chesarone 
et al., 2010). N-WASP activated by Cdc42 
and PIP 2 or SH3 domain-containing pro-
teins activates the Arp2/3 complex to form 
filopodia (Takenawa and Suetsugu, 2007; 
Campellone and Welch, 2010). N-WASP, in 
collaboration with nebulin, also nucleates 
unbranched actin filaments in skeletal 
muscle myofibrils (Takano et al., 2010). Thus 
we examined whether N-WASP was in-
volved in the formation of RhoD-induced 
protrusions. Neither expression of wild-type 
N-WASP nor that of the dominant-negative 
N-WASP(ΔVCA) (Oikawa et al., 2008) af-
fected the RhoD(G26V)-induced protrusion 
formation in 10T1/2 cells (Figure 5, A and B). 
Furthermore, the protrusion formation by 
the expression of RhoD(G26V) was not hin-
dered in mouse C2C12 myoblast clones sta-
bly expressing siRNAs of N-WASP (Takano 
et al., 2010; Figure 5, C and D). Accordingly, 
N-WASP does not participate in the RhoD-
induced protrusion formation, probably be-
cause it is not involved in actin filament for-
mation in the protrusions. </p>

<p>RhoD binds to mDia3C, which is 
associated with the RhoD-induced 
protrusions </p>

<p>Formins exert their functions in both actin 
nucleation and elongation (Chesarone et al., 
2010). Members of the Dia subfamily of 
mammalian formins bind to and are acti-
vated by several Rho family proteins. mDia2, 
which is activated by Cdc42 or RhoF, and mDia1, which is activated 
by RhoF, induce filopodial protrusions (Peng et al., 2003; Pellegrin 
and Mellor, 2005; Goh et al., 2011). On the other hand, RhoD has </p>

<p>protrusion formation if RhoD(wt) was exogenously expressed (Figure 
4D). The stimulation still facilitated protrusion formation, however, 
even without exogenous RhoD(wt) expression (Figure 4D). When </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: RhoD(wt)-transfected cells extend thin protrusions by FGF stimulation. (A) Protrusion 
extension of RhoD(wt)-transfected cells toward FGF-coated beads. FGF2/4/8-coated heparin-
acrylic beads were placed for ∼3 h in the culture of 10T1/2 cells transfected with EGFP-RhoD(wt) 
and then serum-starved. Asterisks indicate the position of FGF-coated beads. (B) Protrusion 
formation of RhoD(wt)-transfected cells stimulated with FGFs. EGFP-RhoD(wt)-transfected and 
serum-starved 10T1/2 cells were stimulated for &gt; 60 min with FGF2/4/8. Scale bars: 10 μm. (C) The 
length of protrusions induced by FGF stimulation in RhoD(wt)-transfected cells. EGFP-RhoD(wt)-
transfected and serum-starved 10T1/2 cells were stimulated with FGF2/4/8 for the time indicated. 
The length is shown as box-and-whisker plots with boxes and whiskers encompassing 75th/25th 
and 95th/5th percentiles, respectively. Dots out of the frame represent the number (but not the 
length) of &gt;50 μm of protrusions. n &gt; 110. *, p &lt; 0.0001 by t test compared with the control. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>designated the isoform coded by the cDNA containing both the 
cassette exons as mDia3A, which had not been registered in the 
DNA databases. The sequence of the second cassette exon codes 
for a part of the GBD. 
We analyzed the localization of EGFP-tagged mDia proteins in 
Cerulean-RhoD(G26V)-transfected 10T1/2 cells. All of the mDia1, 
mDia2, and mDia3A/B/C were diffusely distributed throughout the 
cytoplasm without RhoD(G26V) expression (Figure 7A). When 
mDia1 was coexpressed with RhoD(G26V), it was present in the cell 
body but not in the RhoD(G26V)-induced protrusions (Figure 7A). 
On the other hand, although mDia2 was predominantly distributed </p>

<p>been shown to specifically bind to mDia3C to regulate endosome 
movement by aligning early endosomes along actin filaments 
(Gasman et al., 2003). Thus we tried to clone mouse mDia3 cDNAs 
to assess whether any mDia proteins play essential roles in the for-
mation of RhoD-induced protrusions. We obtained three alterna-
tively spliced forms of mDia3 cDNAs by reverse transcriptase PCR 
(RT-PCR). The longest cDNA contained two alternative cassette ex-
ons, whereas the other two cDNAs contained one or the other of 
the two cassette exons (Figure 6A). The cDNAs containing only the 
first cassette exon and only the second one correspond to mDia3B 
and mDia3C, respectively (Gasman et al., 2003; Mellor, 2010). We </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: RhoD is activated by FGF stimulation and required for FGF-induced protrusion formation. (A) Activation of 
RhoD by FGF stimulation. Activation of RhoD was analyzed by a pulldown assay with GST-mDia3C(GBD) and lysates of 
Myc-RhoD(wt)-transfected 10T1/2 cells stimulated with FGF2/4/8. Myc-RhoD was detected by immunoblotting with the 
anti-Myc mAb. (B) The degree of RhoD activation by FGF stimulation in the analysis of (A). The values are mean ± SD of 
three independent experiments. (C) Specific suppression of RhoD expression by RhoD siRNAs. The 10T1/2 cells were 
transfected with RhoD Stealth siRNA(1) or (2). The levels of endogenous RhoD and RhoF mRNAs were analyzed 48 h 
after the transfection by real-time PCR. The values are normalized with β-actin mRNA levels. ***, p &lt; 0.001; #, p = 0.095; 
##, p = 0.36 (not significant) by t test compared with control siRNA transfection. (D) Requirement of RhoD for FGF8-
induced protrusion formation. The 10T1/2 cells were first transfected with Stealth siRNAs and 48 h later with EGFP-
RhoD(wt) or siRNA(2)-resistant EGFP-RhoD. The cells were stimulated for ∼60 min with FGF8 48 h after the RhoD 
transfection, and the protrusion length was analyzed. n &gt; 390. *, p &lt; 0.0001 by t test. </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 1, 2012 </p>

<p>RhoD induces cytonemes through mDia3C | 4653 </p>

<p>proteins were immunoprecipitated with an 
anti-GFP pAb from lysates of COS-1 cells 
cotransfected with Myc-RhoD(G26V) and 
EGFP-mDia proteins, RhoD(G26V) was 
markedly coprecipitated with mDia3C but 
only marginally with mDia1, mDia2, 
mDia3A, or mDia3B (Figure 7, C and D). 
These results imply that activated RhoD 
can bind to mDia1 and mDia3 isoforms in 
vitro but that it is specifically associated 
with mDia3C in vivo. Indeed, mDia3C was 
exclusively concentrated in the RhoD-in-
duced protrusions but not in the cell body. 
In contrast, mDia1 existed solely in certain 
areas of the cell body in which RhoD may 
not be present. </p>

<p>RhoD-activated mDia3C is essential 
for protrusion formation </p>

<p>We also addressed whether RhoD-bound 
mDia3C is involved in the thin and long pro-
trusion formation. As shown above, 10T1/2 
cells transfected with wild-type mDia3C in 
the absence of activated RhoD barely 
formed such protrusions, whereas the cells 
coexpressing mDia3C and RhoD(G26V) ef-
ficiently formed the protrusions containing 
actin filaments (Figures 7A and 8A). When 
mDia3C(ΔDAD), a constitutively active form 
lacking Dia autoregulatory domain (DAD; 
Figure 6B; Block et al., 2008), was trans-
fected to 10T1/2 cells, the cells formed pro-
trusions regardless of whether RhoD(G26V) 
was cotransfected (Figure 8A). These protru-
sions contained actin filament bundles 
thicker than those in the RhoD(G26V)-in-
duced protrusions. mDia3C(ΔDAD) was re-
stricted to the tips of the protrusions, al-
though mDia3C was associated with both 
tips and stems of the protrusions. These re-
sults suggest that regulated activation of 
mDia3C mediated by RhoD leads to thin ac-
tin filament bundle formation generating 
the thin and long protrusions but that con-
stitutively activated mDia3C gives rise to 
thicker actin filament bundles. 
We therefore analyzed whether mDia3C 
activated by RhoD promotes actin poly-
merization by a fluorometric actin poly-
merization assay. Neither mDia3C nor 
RhoD-GTPγS solely facilitated actin polymerization (Figure 8B). By 
contrast, mDia3C, together with RhoD-GTPγS, prominently acceler-
ated actin polymerization (Figure 8B). Accordingly, mDia3C activated 
by RhoD is likely to form actin filaments responsible for protrusion 
formation. On the other hand, mDia3C(ΔDAD) alone promoted actin 
polymerization remarkably, and addition of RhoD-GTPγS no longer 
increased the enhancement by mDia3C(ΔDAD) (Figure 8B). These 
results are consistent with the above results showing the expression 
of mDia3C(ΔDAD) generated protrusions containing thick actin 
filament bundles irrespective of the presence of RhoD(G26V). 
Next we asked whether mDia3C among mDia proteins plays a 
primary role in the RhoD-induced protrusion formation by applying </p>

<p>in the cell body, it was also located to the tips of some, but not all, 
of the protrusions. By contrast, mDia3A/B/C were highly concen-
trated at the tips or stems of the protrusions and less prominently 
present in the cell body (Figure 7A). Endogenous mDia3 was also 
localized in the RhoD(G26V)-induced protrusions, as detected by 
the staining of PFA-fixed cells with an anti-mDia3 polyclonal anti-
body (pAb; Figure S2D). 
A pulldown assay with GST-tagged GBD of mDia proteins 
showed that GTPγS-loaded active RhoD strongly bound to mDia1 
and mDia3A/B/C but not to mDia2 (Figure 7B). GDP-loaded inac-
tive RhoD only marginally or much less strongly bound to these 
mDia proteins. On the other hand, when EGFP-tagged mDia </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: N-WASP does not participate in RhoD-induced protrusion formation. (A) Neither 
N-WASP nor a dominant-negative N-WASP affects RhoD-induced protrusion formation. The 
10T1/2 cells were cotransfected with mCherry-RhoD(G26V) (green) and EGFP-N-WASP or 
EGFP-N-WASP(ΔVCA) (magenta) and analyzed 48 h after the transfection. (B) Ratio of the cells 
extending thin and long protrusions in the analysis of (A). The values are mean ± SD of three 
independent experiments. *, p &lt; 0.001 by t test compared with respective mock transfection 
(control). (C) Knockdown of N-WASP does not interfere with RhoD-induced protrusion 
formation. C2C12 myoblast clones stably expressing control and N-WASP siRNAs were 
transfected with EGFP-RhoD(G26V) and analyzed 48 h after the transfection. Scale bars: 10 μm. 
(D) Ratio of the cells extending thin and long protrusions in the analysis of (C). The values are 
mean ± SD of three independent experiments. *, p &lt; 0.001 by t test compared with respective 
mock transfection (control). </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>cells detected two types of protrusions, 
shorter motile and longer immotile protru-
sions. The shorter protrusions barely elon-
gated during our observation of EGFP fluo-
rescence. However, we cannot exclude the 
possibility that the shorter protrusions elon-
gate to become the longer ones. The longer 
protrusions were sensitive to physical and 
chemical stresses, such as washing and PFA 
fixation, and collapsed or fragmented. Thus 
both types of the protrusions might be un-
able to elongate under UV illumination ap-
plied to detect EGFP fluorescence. The pro-
trusions induced by FGF stimulation in 
RhoD(wt)-transfected cells also hardly elon-
gated during the observation of EGFP fluo-
rescence. This result favors the above notion 
that the protrusions are sensitive to physical 
and chemical stresses. Accordingly, live im-
aging of unfixed cells is required to detect 
and analyze such structures. 
Some of the RhoD-induced longer pro-
trusions were &gt;60 μm in length. They were 
much longer and thinner than filopodia in-
duced by Cdc42 subfamily members or 
RhoF. The dimensional difference between 
the RhoD-induced protrusions and filopo-
dia suggest that they are generated by dis-
tinct mechanisms and exert distinct func-
tions. Although the length of Drosophila 
cytonemes is variable, some cytonemes are 
as long as 80 μm (Hsiung et al., 2005; Roy 
et al., 2011). Thus the length of RhoD-
induced protrusions is comparable with that of Drosophila 
cytonemes, despite the difference between mammalian cell culture 
system and in developing Drosophila tissues. Wing imaginal disk 
cells, eye disk cells, and tracheal cells extend cytonemes toward 
Dpp/BMP-, Spitz/EGF-, and Bnl/FGF-producing cells, respectively. 
These cytonemes segregate receptors of each morphogen/growth 
factor (Roy et al., 2011). The receptors move in both anterograde 
and retrograde directions in cytonemes (Hsiung et al., 2005). 
RhoD(wt)-expressing 10T1/2 cells extended thin and long protru-
sions toward FGF2/4/8-coated beads or in response to stimulation 
with each of the FGFs separately. The RhoD(G26V)-induced protru-
sions also contained nodules moving in both directions, and most 
of the nodules eventually moved toward the cell body. FGFR1c 
coexpressed with RhoD(G26V) was associated with the nodules and 
moved through the protrusions. Therefore RhoD-induced protru-
sions are likely to be morphologically and functionally equivalent to 
cytonemes. Although there is no RhoD orthologue in Drosophila, 
some Rho family protein, such as Rho-1 or Rac-1, which is most 
closely related to mammalian RhoD, might be involved in cytoneme 
formation in Drosophila. 
Why is FGFR transported to the cell body through cytonemes or 
the RhoD-induced protrusions? Canonically, plasma membrane-as-
sociated receptor tyrosine kinases activated by their growth factor 
ligands transduce signals into the Ras-ERK, phosphatidylinositol 
3-kinase (PI3K)-Akt, or phospholipase C-γ (PLCγ) signaling, which is 
associated with the plasma membrane or the cytosol (Lemmon and 
Schlessinger, 2010). On the other hand, several growth factors and 
their receptor complexes, such as EGFs-EGFRs and FGFs-FGFRs, 
are also translocated to the nucleus (Johnson et al., 2004; Bryant and </p>

<p>RNAi. Expression of Stealth siRNAs of mDia1, mDia2, and mDia3 in 
10T1/2 cells specifically reduced mDia1, mDia2, and mDia3 protein 
levels, respectively, but did not have off-target effects on the other 
mDia isoforms (Figure 8C). Expression of the siRNAs of mDia1 or 
mDia2 together with RhoD(G26V) in 10T1/2 cells did not signifi-
cantly affect the RhoD-induced protrusion formation (Figure 8D). In 
contrast, expression of mDia3 siRNAs reduced the length of thin 
protrusions (Figure 8D). When an siRNA-resistant mDia1, mDia2, 
mDia3A, or mDia3B (Figure S2E) was expressed together with each 
corresponding siRNA, the protrusion length was not affected (Fig-
ure 8D). By contrast, expression of an siRNA-resistant mDia3C (Fig-
ure S2E) rescued the cells from the mDia3 siRNA-induced reduction 
of protrusion length (Figure 8D). Consequently, mDia3C is respon-
sible for the RhoD-induced protrusion formation, but mDia1, mDia2, 
mDia3A, or mDia3B is not. We conclude that these data, taken to-
gether, indicate that activated RhoD forms the protrusions by di-
rectly binding to activate mDia3C, which induces actin polymeriza-
tion in the protrusions. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Several Rho family proteins, including Cdc42, RhoQ, RhoJ, and RhoF, 
bring about filopodial cell protrusions (Abe et al., 2002; Mattila and 
Lappalainen, 2008; Faix et al., 2009; Mellor, 2010). These protrusions 
are relatively thick and stable and resistant to fixation. In contrast, 
cytonemes are thinner and sensitive to fixation (Ramírez-Weber and 
Kornberg, 1999). Although molecular mechanisms of cytoneme for-
mation have been obscure, we have shown here that RhoD-medi-
ated signaling is responsible for the formation of cytoneme-like pro-
trusions. Live imaging of unfixed EGFP-RhoD(G26V)-transfected </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Mouse mDia3 isoforms generated by alternative splicing. (A) Alignment of 
N-terminal amino acid sequences of mDia3A/B/C in comparison with those of mDia1 and mDia2. 
The sequences encoded by two alternative cassette exons are shown in red. The sequences of 
GBD are shown in blue. (B) Functional domains of mDia3 isoforms and deletion mutants of 
mDia3C. Red asterisks indicate the position of amino acid sequence encoded by the second 
cassette exon. DID, diaphanous inhibitory domain; DD, dimerization domain; CC, coiled-coil 
domain; FH1 and FH2, formin homology domains 1 and 2, respectively. </p>

<p>1 MEELGAAASGAGGGGGGGEEHGGGRSNKRGAGNRAANEEETRNKPKLNIQIKTLADDVRD 60 
1 MEELGAAASGAGGGGGGGEEHGGGRSNKRGAGNRAANEEETRNKPKLNIQIKTLADDVRD 60 
1 MEELGAAASGAGGGGGGGEEHGGGRSNKRGAGNRAANEEETRNKPKL-----------RD 49 
1 MERHRARAL--------GRDSKSSRRKGLQSAPPAGPYEPGEKRPKLHLNIRTLTDDMLD 52 
1 MEPSGGGL--------GPGRGTRDKKKGRSPDELPATGGDGGKHKKF-----------LE 41 </p>

<p>61 RITSFRKSATKREKPVIQHSIDYQTAVVEIPPALIVHDDRSLILSEKEVLDLFEKMMEDM 120 
61 RITSFRKSATKREKPVIQHSIDYQTAVVEIPPALIVHDDRSLILSEKEVLDLFEKMMEDM 120 
50 RITSFRKSATKREKPVIQHSIDYQTAVVEIPPALIVHDDRSLILSEKEVLDLFEKMMEDM 109 
53 KFASIRIPGSKKERPPLPHLKTVSGISDSSSLSSETMENNPKALPESEVLKLFEKMMEDM 112 
42 RFTSMRIKKEK-EKPNSAHR-NSSASYGDDPTAQSLQD-----ISDEQVLVLFEQMLVDM 95 </p>

<p>121 NLNEEKKAPLRKKDFSIKREMVVQYISATSKSIVGSKVLGGLKNSKHEFTLSSQEYVHEL 180 
121 NLNEEKKAPLRKKDFSIKREMVVQYISATSKS-------GGLKNSKHEFTLSSQEYVHEL 173 
110 NLNEEKKAPLRKKDFSIKREMVVQYISATSKSIVGSKVLGGLKNSKHEFTLSSQEYVHEL 169 
113 NLNEDKKAPLREKDFGIKKEMVMQYINTASKT-------GSLRSSRQ---ISPQEFLHEL 162 
96 NLNEEKQQPLREKDIVIKREMVSQYLH-TSKA-------GMNQKESS---RSAMMYIQEL 145 </p>

<p>mDia3A 
mDia3B 
mDia3C 
mDia2 
mDia1 </p>

<p>mDia3A 
mDia3B 
mDia3C 
mDia2 
mDia1 </p>

<p>mDia3A 
mDia3B 
mDia3C 
mDia2 
mDia1 </p>

<p>1 
1098 </p>

<p>GBD 
DID 
DD 
CC FH1 
FH2 
DAD </p>

<p>mDia3C </p>

<p>1 
1048 </p>

<p>mDia3C(∆DAD) </p>

<p>NIQIKTLADDV 
mDia3A/B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>1 
298 </p>

<p>mDia3C(GBD) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 1, 2012 </p>

<p>RhoD induces cytonemes through mDia3C | 4655 </p>

<p>FGF2/4/8 activated RhoD, and activated RhoD was required 
for the FGF-induced protrusion formation. Drosophila has three 
FGF genes, including Bnl, whereas mouse or human has 22 FGF 
genes (Itoh and Ornitz, 2011). Mammalian FGF2/4/8 function in a 
paracrine manner and act as morphogens or growth/differentia-
tion factors in developing embryos. Analyses of gene-knockout 
mice have shown that the FGFs are involved in the development 
of particular tissues, such as the limb (Sun et al., 2002; Beenken 
and Mohammadi, 2009; Itoh and Ornitz, 2011). Therefore cells in 
these tissues of developing embryos might also generate the cy-
toneme-like protrusions induced by these FGFs through the acti-
vation of RhoD. 
Activated RhoD bound to mDia1 and mDia3A/B/C but not to 
mDia2 in vitro, whereas activated RhoD bound only to mDia3C in 
vivo. Although mDia1 and mDia2 were predominantly present in the </p>

<p>Stow, 2005; Carpenter and Liao, 2009; Dunham-Ems et al., 2009). 
Following activation by FGF, plasma membrane-associated FGFR is 
internalized into early endosomal compartments, which is an essen-
tial early step in nuclear translocation of FGFR. FGF and FGFR are 
then released from the early endosomes to the cytosol, although it 
is unknown whether they are linked or separated at this time. They 
interact with nuclear import machinery, including importin β, in the 
cytosol and are translocated to the nucleus. In the nucleus, FGFs-
FGFRs interact with transcription regulators, such as CREB-binding 
protein and ribosomal S6 kinase 1, and participate in transcription of 
genes involved in cell growth, differentiation, or development. How-
ever, FGFs-FGFRs should be unable to induce these nuclear events 
when they are on cytonemes or the RhoD-induced protrusions. This 
seems to be the reason why FGFR (as well as EGFR) is transported to 
the cell body through the protrusions (Figure 9). </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: mDia3C is localized to the RhoD-induced protrusions and binds to RhoD. (A) Distribution of mDia proteins in 
RhoD-transfected cells. The 10T1/2 cells were cotransfected with Cerulean-RhoD(G26V) (green) and EGFP-mDia 
proteins (magenta). Scale bar: 10 μm. (B) Binding of active RhoD to mDia1 and mDia3A/B/C in a pulldown assay. The 
binding of GDP-or GTPγS-loaded RhoD to GST-mDia(GBD) was analyzed by immunoblotting with the anti-RhoD pAb. 
*, an unidentified protein present in Sf21 cell lysates that was detected by the anti-RhoD pAb. (C) Specific binding of 
RhoD(G26V) to mDia3C in a coimmunoprecipitation assay. COS-1 cells were cotransfected with Myc-RhoD(G26V) and 
EGFP-mDia proteins, cell lysates were immunoprecipitated with anti-GFP pAb, and coprecipitated Myc-RhoD(G26V) 
was detected with the anti-Myc mAb. (D) Relative intensity of coprecipitated Myc-RhoD(G26V) band in the analysis of 
(C). The values are mean ± SD of three independent experiments. *, p &lt; 0.05 by t test compared with mDia1. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>FIGURE 8: Activated mDia3C is essential for actin filament formation-mediated protrusion formation. (A) A 
constitutively active mDia3C(ΔDAD) forms protrusions independently of RhoD. The 10T1/2 cells were cotransfected with 
EGFP-mDia3C or EGFP-mDia3C(ΔDAD) (magenta) and mOrange2-Lifeact (green) together with or without Cerulean-
RhoD(G26V) (cyan). Scale bar: 10 μm. (B) Facilitation of actin polymerization by mDia3C together with RhoD or solely by 
mDia3C(ΔDAD). Actin polymerization was analyzed by a fluorometric actin polymerization assay. a.u., arbitrary units. 
(C) Specific knockdown of mDia isoforms by respective mDia siRNAs. The 10T1/2 cells were first transfected with mDia 
Stealth siRNAs and 48 h later with EGFP-mDia1, mDia2, or mDia3C. The levels of proteins at 48 h after the second </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 1, 2012 </p>

<p>RhoD induces cytonemes through mDia3C | 4657 </p>

<p>FIGURE 9: Postulated mechanisms of the FGF-RhoD-mDia3C-induced protrusion formation and the transport of 
FGFRs through the protrusions. (A) RhoD is inactive without FGF stimulation. (B) If FGF, even at a low concentration, 
binds to its receptors, a GEF for RhoD is activated by FGFR signaling. The GEF then activates RhoD. (C) Activated RhoD 
binds to activate mDia3C. (D) Activated mDia3C nucleates and elongates actin filaments to form protrusions. (E) Cells 
extend the protrusions toward high concentrations of FGF or the source of FGF. Higher concentrations of FGF can 
efficiently bind to FGFRs. FGF-FGFRs are transported through the protrusions either on the plasma membrane or on 
the early endosome-like vesicle membrane toward the cell body. (F) FGF-FGFRs transported to the cell body activates 
the canonical Ras-ERK, PI3K-Akt, or PLCγ signaling. FGF-FGFRs are also translocated to the nucleus through early 
endosomal compartments and participate in transcription of genes involved in cell growth, differentiation, or 
development. </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>GEF </p>

<p>GEF </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>mDia </p>

<p>mDia </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>mDia </p>

<p>mDia </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>mDia </p>

<p>mDia </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>R h o D </p>

<p>G D P </p>

<p>R h o D </p>

<p>G D P </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>FGFR </p>

<p>FGF </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>R 
h o D </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>mDia </p>

<p>mDia </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Transcription </p>

<p>R 
a s </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>Sos 
Raf 
MEK 
ERK </p>

<p>transfection were analyzed by immunoblotting with anti-GFP pAb. (D) Requirement of mDia3C but not mDia1, mDia2, or 
mDia3A/B for the RhoD-induced protrusion formation. The 10T1/2 cells were first transfected with mDia Stealth siRNAs 
and 48 h later with mCherry-RhoD(wt) and siRNA(1)-resistant EGFP-mDia1, mDia2, or mDia3A/B/C. The protrusion 
length was analyzed 48 h after the second transfection. n &gt; 420. *, p &lt; 0.0001, #, p &gt; 0.01 (not significant) by t test. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>Therefore it is intriguing to determine whether these mutations 
lead to developmental abnormalities due to a lack of cytoneme-
mediated intercellular communication. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Cell culture </p>

<p>Mouse C3H/10T1/2 (10T1/2) mesenchymal progenitor cells 
(Reznikoff et al., 1973) were cultured as described previously 
(Watanabe-Takano et al., 2010). Mouse skeletal muscle C2C12 myo-
blast clones stably transfected with N-WASP siRNA1, siRNA2, and 
control siRNA expression vectors (C2/NW(i)1, C2/NW(i)2, and C2/ 
cont(i), respectively) were established and cultured as described 
previously (Takano et al., 2010). </p>

<p>cDNA cloning and plasmid construction </p>

<p>Mouse mDia2 cDNA (mKIAA4117) was obtained from Kazusa DNA 
Research Institute. Mouse mDia3 cDNA fragments were cloned 
from mouse brain mRNA by RT-PCR using Omniscript Reverse Tran-
scriptase and ProofStart DNA Polymerase (Qiagen, Valencia, CA). 
Three primer sets used were: </p>

<p>AGAGAAAGATGGAGGAGCTCG- AGTTCAGCTG-
1. 
CAGCAGTGATG- </p>

<p>CTGCTATTTGCATTGTTGGGG- GAAGGAAATGT-
2. 
CAAGGCCAGT- </p>

<p>GGTCCAAGATTGAGCCTAAAG- CTTAAATGTCTC-
3. 
CATTCTCCC- </p>

<p>Three distinct cDNA fragments encoding the N-terminal portion 
of mDia3A, mDia3B, and mDia3C were obtained with primer set 1. 
Primer sets 2 and 3 generated cDNA fragments encoding the 
common central and C-terminal portions, respectively. Three cDNA 
fragments obtained with the respective primer sets were digested 
with XbaI and BglII and ligated into single cDNAs encoding full-
length mDia3A, mDia3B, and mDia3C. The sequence of mouse 
mDia3A cDNA has been deposited to the DDBJ/GenBank/EMBL 
database with the accession number AB713187. 
siRNA-resistant (r) RhoD, mDia1, mDia2, mDia3A, mDia3B, and 
mDia3C cDNAs were constructed by introducing point mutations 
into wild-type cDNAs by PCR. The primer sets used were: </p>

<p>siRNA(2)-r RhoD: GTTACAACGCCACTCTGCAGATGAAGG-3ánd GCTCGAACACTGTGGGACTGTAGCTCTC- </p>

<p>siRNA(1)-r mDia1: CTTCCTGTGCAAGCTTCGAGACACCAA 
G TC- GAGATATTGAAGCCGAAAGCACCAGCATTC- </p>

<p>siRNA(1)-r mDia2: CAGAACCTTATAAAGCACCTTCCTGAT-
GAG- GATCATTGACTCTGACAACTGTGTTTCATC- </p>

<p>siRNA(1)-r mDia3A/B/C: CCGCGAACAGTATGACAAACTGTC-
CACC- GCGTTCTGTGTAAAGCTCATCATCTTTTCC- </p>

<p>A cDNA encoding mDia3C(ΔDAD) was constructed by substitut-
ing the codon GAG for Glu-1049 with the termination codon TAG 
by PCR with Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase (New England 
BioLabs, Ipswich, MA). The cDNA of mouse RhoD(wt), RhoD(G26V) 
(Tsubakimoto et al., 1999), Rab5b(wt) (Sun et al., 2003), mDia2, 
mDia3A, mDia3B, mDia3C, mDia3C(ΔDAD), or human Cdc42(G12V) 
(Abe et al., 2002) was inserted into pEGFP-C1, pmCherry-C1, pmO-
range2-C1, or pCerulean-C1 vector (Clontech, Mountain View, CA) 
in frame with each fluorescent protein tag. 
Mouse FGFR1c cDNA fragments were cloned from mRNA of 
mouse embryonic stem cell line R1 by RT-PCR. Two primers sets 
used were: </p>

<p>cell body even when RhoD(G26V) was expressed, exogenously 
expressed mDia3A/B/C were concentrated in the RhoD-induced 
protrusions. These results may imply that mDia1 is not colocalized 
with RhoD in the cell body, even if it can bind to RhoD in vitro. On 
the other hand, although mDia3A/B have the potential to bind to 
RhoD, endogenous mDia3A/B might neither be associated with the 
protrusions nor be involved in the protrusion formation. Neverthe-
less, exogenously overexpressed mDia3A/B might be ectopically 
localized to the protrusions and displace endogenous mDia3C. The 
siRNA-resistant mDia3C, but not the siRNA-resistant mDia3A/B, res-
cued the cells from the interference with the RhoD(G26V)-induced 
protrusion formation by the mDia3 siRNA. These results imply that 
activated RhoD forms the protrusions through activating mDia3C 
but not mDia3A/B. Indeed, mDia3C (hDia2C) has been reported to 
be a specific effector of RhoD (Gasman et al., 2003). Activated RhoD 
binds to mDia3C and associates with early endosomes in the cell 
body. They induce an alignment of early endosomes along actin fila-
ments and markedly reduce the endosome motility by depending 
on Src tyrosine kinase activity. Thus RhoD is likely to utilize mDia3C 
for both the protrusion formation and the regulation of endosome 
movement through actin filaments. mDia3 is also localized to the 
kinetochores and involved in kinetochore-microtubule attachment 
required for correct chromosome alignment and segregation, which 
is regulated by Cdc42 or Aurora B (Yasuda et al., 2004; Cheng et al., 
2011). Although it remains to be determined which mDia3 isoform(s) 
is responsible for this function, each of the mDia3 isoforms is likely 
to be regulated by specific signaling molecules and to exert specific 
functions. 
Both mDia3C, together with active RhoD, and the constitutively 
active mDia3C(ΔDAD) prominently enhanced actin polymerization. 
In addition, mDia3C(ΔDAD) formed protrusions regardless of the 
expression of RhoD(G26V). mDia3C(ΔDAD) was confined to the tips 
of the protrusions. These results may indicate that actin nucleation/ 
elongation function of mDia3C, which is activated by RhoD, is es-
sential for the protrusion formation. However, the protrusions 
formed by mDia3C(ΔDAD) were thicker and contained actin fila-
ment bundles thicker than those in the RhoD(G26V)-induced protru-
sions. Accordingly, although mDia3C is responsible for the thin actin 
filament bundle formation in the RhoD-induced protrusions, regu-
lated activation of mDia3C mediated by RhoD may be required for 
the thin and long protrusion formation. Alternatively, cooperation 
between mDia3C and other effector proteins of RhoD might be nec-
essary for the thin and long protrusion formation. The thicker protru-
sions are reminiscent of those formed by mDia2(ΔDAD) expression 
(Block et al., 2008). Although the mDia2(ΔDAD)-induced protrusions 
are club-shaped, however, mDia3C(ΔDAD)-induced protrusions 
were rod-shaped or tapered and appeared to be longer than the 
mDia2(ΔDAD)-induced protrusions. The difference might be as-
cribed to different nucleation/elongation abilities exhibited by these 
mDia proteins. 
Figure 9 summarizes postulated mechanisms of the protrusion 
formation by FGF-activated RhoD, elongation of the protrusions 
toward the source of FGF, and the transport of FGFRs through the 
protrusions. This study has substantiated the molecular mecha-
nisms of cytoneme or cytoneme-like protrusion formation. Investi-
gation of whether RhoD and mDia3C play central roles in the for-
mation of similar protrusions distinct from filopodia in other cell 
types (Galkina et al., 2001; Gupta and DeFranco, 2003; Sherer 
et al., 2007; Fifadara et al., 2010) may generalize the findings in this 
study. If inactivating mutations occur in the RhoD, RhoD GEF 
(guanine nucleotide exchange factor for RhoD), or mDia3 gene, 
cytonemes or cytoneme-like protrusions may not be formed. </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 1, 2012 </p>

<p>RhoD induces cytonemes through mDia3C | 4659 </p>

<p>mDia1 siRNA(2): GGTTGATCAAATGATTGATAAAACA-3´(nt 
1365-1389); </p>

<p>mDia2 siRNA(1): CAGAGTCCATGATTCAGAACTTAAT-3´(nt 
2186-2210); </p>

<p>mDia2 siRNA(2): AGAAGATTGAATTGGTTAAAGATCG-3´(nt 
1876-1900); </p>

<p>mDia3 siRNA(1): GAGCTTTACCCAGAATGCCAGAGAA-3´(nt 
2868-2892); </p>

<p>mDia3 siRNA(2): GAAAGCATTTATGAATAATAAGTTT-3´(nt 
738-762); </p>

<p>negative control siRNA: GAGTTCACCGAAAGTCCGAATC-
GAA- </p>

<p>The siRNAs were mixed with Lipofectamine RNAiMAX Reagent 
(Life Technologies) in OPTI-MEM (Life Technologies) and transfected 
to 10T1/2 cells. </p>

<p>Real-time PCR </p>

<p>The amounts RhoD and RhoF mRNAs were quantitated by real-time 
PCR. The cDNAs were synthesized from cytoplasmic RNA with 
SuperScript VILO cDNA Synthesis Kit (Life Technologies). The primer 
sets used were: </p>

<p>RhoD: 
GAAGACGTCACTGATGATGGTCTTCG-3ánd 
AAGCAGAGGAGCAAGACATTGGCATC- </p>

<p>RhoF: AGTGTGACAGTGGGTAACAAGGAG- TGAT-
GAGGACGTTGTCGTAACTGG- </p>

<p>The quantitation was conducted with <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Applied Biosystems</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">7300 
Real-Time PCR System</rs> by using SYBR Green I Dye (Life 
Technologies). </p>

<p>Pulldown assay </p>

<p>Activation of RhoD by FGF stimulation was analyzed by a pulldown 
assay with the GST-tagged GBD of mDia3C. A cDNA fragment en-
coding the N-terminal region (aa 1-298) containing the GBD do-
main of mDia3C was fused in frame with the GST tag in pGEX-6P 
vector (GE Healthcare, Waukesha, WI). The GST-mDia3C(GBD) 
cDNA was amplified and inserted into pFastBac1 vector (Life Tech-
nologies). The recombinant GST-mDia3C(GBD) was expressed in 
Sf21 cells with Bac-to-Bac Baculovirus Expression System (Life Tech-
nologies). GST-mDia3C(GBD) was immobilized to glutathione Sep-
harose 4B (GE Healthcare) and affinity-purified. RhoD(wt) cDNA was 
fused in frame with the N-terminal Myc-tag in pEF-BOS/Myc vector 
and transfected to 10T1/2 cells. The transfected cells stimulated 
with FGFs after serum starvation were lysed, and the lysates were 
applied to a GST pulldown assay, as described previously (Takano 
et al., 2010). Bound Myc-RhoD was detected by immunoblotting 
with anti-Myc mAb Myc1-9E10 (American Type Culture Collection, 
Manassas, VA). 
The recombinant GST-mDia2(GBD) (aa 1-307), GST-
mDia3A(GBD) (aa 1-309), and GST-mDia3B(GBD) (aa 1-302) were 
expressed in Sf21 cells with Bac-to-Bac Baculovirus Expression Sys-
tem as GST-mDia3C(GBD). GST-mDia1(GBD) (aa 1-373) and 
RhoD(wt) cDNAs were fused in frame with the GST tag in pGEX-6P 
vector and expressed in the Escherichia coli strain XL1-Blue. The 
GST tag of GST-RhoD was excised with PreScission protease (GE 
Healthcare) in 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 
1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 1 μg/ml leupeptin, and 1 μg/ml pepstatin 
A at 4°C overnight. RhoD (10 μM) was mixed with 2 μM GTPγS or 
GDP at 37°C for 10 min, and the loading was stopped by adding 
15 mM MgCl 2 . GTPγS or GDP-loaded RhoD was applied to a </p>

<p>ACGGATCCTTGTTACCAACCTCTAACCG- TGC-
1. 
CTAAGACCAGTCTGTCTCGTGGC- </p>

<p>TGGAGTCTCCGAATATGAGCTCCCTG- GGGGATC-
2. 
CGGCGCCGTTTGAGTCCACTG- </p>

<p>Two cDNA fragments encoding the N-and C-terminal portions 
of FGFR1c were digested with BamHI and ligated into a single 
cDNA encoding full-length FGFR1c. The FGFR1c cDNA was in-
serted into the BglII-BamHI site of pEGFP-N2 vector in frame with 
the EGFP tag. 
Oligo DNA of Lifeact, a 17-amino acid peptide of Abp140 (Riedl 
et al., 2008), was prepared by annealing complementary 56-base 
synthetic deoxyribonucleotides. It was inserted into the BamHI-
HindIII site of pmOrange2-C1 vector in frame with the fluorescent 
protein tag. </p>

<p>Fluorescence microscopy and live imaging </p>

<p>The recombinant plasmids were transfected to 10T1/2 cells with 
GeneJammer Transfection Reagent (Stratagene, Agilent, Santa 
Clara, CA). The transfected cells were fixed with 4% PFA in phos-
phate-buffered saline (PBS) for 15 min and permeabilized with 0.2% 
Triton X-100 in PBS for 5 min. They were incubated with anti-vinculin 
mAb hVIN-1 (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO), anti-fascin mAb (Merck 
Millipore, Billerica, MA), anti-β-tubulin mAb E7 (Developmental 
Studies Hybridoma Bank, University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA), or 
anti-mDia3 pAb (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA) and 
then incubated with Alexa Fluor 555-goat anti-mouse or rabbit 
immunoglobulin G or Alexa Fluor 546-phalloidin (Life Technologies, 
Carlsbad, CA). The specimens were observed with a Carl Zeiss 
(Oberkochen, Germany) confocal laser-scanning microscope LSM 
410 or with an Olympus (Tokyo, Japan) confocal laser-scanning 
microscope FV-1000D. 
For live imaging, cells were cultured on 35-mm glass base dishes 
and maintained at 37°C in 5% CO 2 during observation. For stimula-
tion of RhoD(wt)-transfected 10T1/2 cells with FGFs, the cells were 
cultured for 24 h in serum-free DMEM before addition of FGFs. The 
cells were stimulated with 100 ng/ml FGF2, FGF4, or FGF8 (Wako 
Pure Chemical Industries, Osaka, Japan) premixed with 15 μg/ml 
heparin sodium (Wako Pure Chemical Industries). For analysis of the 
protrusions extending toward FGF-coated beads, &gt;100-μm-diameter 
heparin-acrylic beads (Sigma-Aldrich) were sorted out with Cell 
Strainer (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ). The beads were soaked 
in 100 ng/ml FGF and washed once with PBS. They were placed in 
the culture of RhoD(wt)-transfected and serum-starved 10T1/2 cells. 
These cells were observed with either the Olympus confocal laser-
scanning microscope FV-1000D or a Carl Zeiss inverted microscope 
Axiovert 200 equipped with a CoolSNAP cf charge-coupled device 
camera (Photometrics, Tucson, AZ) operated with <rs id="software-3" type="software">Openlab</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">PerkinElmer</rs>, Waltham, MA). Time-lapse images were processed 
with <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. </p>

<p>RNAi </p>

<p>Stealth RNAi siRNAs (Life Technologies) were used to knock down 
mouse RhoD and mDia1/2/3. The target sequences of the siRNAs 
were: </p>

<p>RhoD siRNA(1): CCAAACAGCTTTGACAACGTCTCCA-3´(nt 
374-398 from the initiation codon); </p>

<p>RhoD siRNA(2): CCCACAGTGTTTGAGCGCTATAATG-3´(nt 
142-166); </p>

<p>mDia1 siRNA(1): GCTTCAATATCAGCTTCCTTTGTAA-3´(nt 
2942-2966); </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



<p>Actin polymerization assay </p>

<p>A fluorometric actin polymerization assay with pyrene-labeled actin 
was conducted as described previously (Takano et al., 2010), using 
1 μM actin (10% pyrene-labeled), 100 nM mDia3C, 100 nM 
mDia3C(ΔDAD), and 100 nM RhoD-GTPγS. Pyrene fluorescence 
was monitored at 25°C with an FP-8300DS spectrofluorometer 
(JASCO). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Y. Takai for providing recombinant plasmids of Cdc42. 
This work was supported by Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research on 
Priority Areas (18057005 and 20054004 to T.E.) and for Scientific 
Research on Innovative Areas (23117506 to T.E.) from the Ministry of 
Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan; 
Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research (B) (23300144 to T.E.) and for 
Young Scientists (B) (24770118 to K.T.) from the Japan Society for 
the Promotion of Science; and an Intramural Research Grant (23-5) 
for Neurological and Psychiatric Disorders of National Center of 
Neurology and Psychiatry. </p>



<p>Volume 23 December 1, 2012 </p>

<p>RhoD induces cytonemes through mDia3C | 4661 </p>



</text></tei>