<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3033187" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Clinical barriers to stem-cell therapy include the need for efficient derivation of histocompatible stem cells 
and the zoonotic risk inherent to human stem-cell xenoculture on mouse feeder cells. We describe a 
system for efficiently deriving induced pluripotent stem (iPS) cells from human and mouse amniocytes, 
and for maintaining the pluripotency of these iPS cells on mitotically inactivated feeder layers prepared 
from the same amniocytes. Both cellular components of this system are thus autologous to a single 
donor. Moreover, the use of human feeder cells reduces the risk of zoonosis. Generation of iPS cells 
using retroviral vectors from short-or long-term cultured human and mouse amniocytes using four factors, 
or two factors in mouse, occurs in 5 -7 days with 0.5% efficiency. This efficiency is greater than that reported 
for mouse and human fibroblasts using similar viral infection approaches, and does not appear to result from 
selective reprogramming of Oct4 1 or c-Kit 1 amniocyte subpopulations. Derivation of amniocyte-derived iPS 
(AdiPS) cell colonies, which express pluripotency markers and exhibit appropriate microarray expression 
and DNA methylation properties, was facilitated by live immunostaining. AdiPS cells also generate embryoid 
bodies in vitro and teratomas in vivo. Furthermore, mouse and human amniocytes can serve as feeder layers 
for iPS cells and for mouse and human embryonic stem (ES) cells. Thus, human amniocytes provide an effi-
cient source of autologous iPS cells and, as feeder cells, can also maintain iPS and ES cell pluripotency with-
out the safety concerns associated with xenoculture. </p>

<p>Recent advances in stem-cell biology hold the potential to 
change the treatment of many diseases, including neurodegen-
erative diseases, diabetes, myocardial infarction, stroke and 
spinal cord injury. Central to this paradigm is the requirement 
for patient-specific stem cells that can be propagated in a cell-
culture environment suitable for transplantation and other 
therapeutic applications. Presently, NIH-approved human ES </p>

<p>(hES) cell lines are most typically cultured on mitotically inac-
tivated mouse embryonic fibroblast (MEF) cells as xenogenic 
feeder cells (1). Due to concerns about the transmission of 
zoonotic infections to recipients, xenoculture represents a sig-
nificant impediment to stem-cell therapy. At present, the use 
of federal registry hES cells and stem-cell derivatives that 
involve feeder layer xenoculture requires detailed testing for 
adventitious infectious agents, according to the established 
FDA guidelines for xenotransplantation. According to these </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: maas@genetics.med.harvard.edu </p>

<p># The Author 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 
962-974 
doi:10.1093/hmg/ddq542 
Advance Access published on December 14, 2010 </p>

<p>guidelines, 'xenotransplantation' encompasses the transplan-
tation of human cells, including stem cells 'that have had 
ex vivo contact with live nonhuman animal cells' (2). 
On the other hand, a second potential barrier to stem-cell 
therapy-the matter of histocompatibility and tissue rejec-
tion-has recently been addressed. Induced pluripotent stem 
(iPS) cells provide a potentially powerful route for cell thera-
pies based upon autologous, patient-specific stem cells (3,4). 
Most current protocols for iPS cell generation require the 
expression of a cohort of transcription factors (TFs) in the 
target cell, either by gene transfer (5 -7), direct protein intro-
duction (8,9), chemical agents (10-12) or synthetic modified 
mRNA (13) to reprogram terminally differentiated somatic 
cells into iPS cells (3,4,14). Although iPS cells exhibit a 
unique gene expression signature (15), they resemble embryo-
nic stem (ES) cells in many respects, including the expression 
of pluripotency markers, the ability to differentiate into cell 
types that represent all three germ layers, and to contribute 
to chimerism and teratoma formation in mice. Accordingly, 
iPS cells hold promise for cell replacement therapy as well 
as for the study of fundamental disease mechanisms, while cir-
cumventing some of the ethical issues associated with the use 
of hES cells (16-19). 
At least two additional issues remain for iPS cells, including 
the need to identify efficient and readily available sources of 
starting cells for reprogramming and the development of effi-
cient derivation protocols that do not require viral vectors. 
There are several ongoing efforts to develop such viral-free 
protocols, but current approaches exhibit relatively low iPS 
cell derivation efficiencies (8 -13). While human dermal fibro-
blasts (HDFs), hair follicle cells, blood cells and adipose stem 
cells have all been evaluated, recent primary derivation studies 
indicate the relatively inefficient generation of iPS cells (e.g. 
0.2 -0.001% efficiency) and the need for prolonged deri-
vation times, encompassing 10 days to 4 weeks 
(3,4,11,14,20-26). However, an intriguing observation from 
iPS cell derivation protocols that have compared somatic 
cell types of different developmental ages is that younger 
cell types appear to exhibit more efficient reprogramming to 
the iPS cell state (14,27). 
From a clinical perspective, the most readily accessible 
embryonic cells in the body are amniocytes, a heterogeneous 
cell population in the amniotic fluid surrounding the develop-
ing fetus that represent cells exfoliated from the embryo and 
placenta (28). As a result, amniocytes are developmentally 
primitive, undergo rapid proliferation in vivo and in vitro 
and are likely to include embryonic progenitor cells (29). 
Indeed, small subpopulations of amniocytes have been 
suggested to be multipotent (30,31). Studies have used 
mesenchymal stem cells in amniotic fluid that are presumably 
shed from the placenta to perform autologous fetal tissue 
engineering of sternum, trachea, bladder and diaphragm, and 
to generate renal and osteogenic tissue (28,31-33). In 
addition, an amniocyte subpopulation representing 0.9% of 
total amniocytes, termed amniotic fluid-derived stem (AFS) 
cells, can be isolated by virtue of their CD117/c-Kit 
expression and these cells appear to be multipotent (30). Simi-
larly, iPS cell derivation has recently been reported after the 
culture of human amniocytes on mouse feeder cells (34,35). 
In an initial study, following long-term culture, human </p>

<p>amniotic fluid-derived cells (hAFDCs) were correctly repro-
grammed to an iPS cell state with efficiencies ranging from 
0.059 to 1.525% at 6 days post-infection (34), while in a 
second study cultured AF skin cells formed iPS colonies 
approximately twice as fast and at nearly twice the rate as cul-
tured adult skin cells (35). 
It has been hypothesized that amniocytes might be easier to 
directly reprogram to the iPS cell state than other available 
somatic cell types because of the likely similarity of their tran-
scriptional and epigenetic states to those of early embryonic 
cell types (34,35). Over 150 000 second trimester amniocent-
eses are performed annually in the US alone and the extra 
amniocytes that are not used for karyotyping, genetic testing 
or other analyses are typically discarded (36), making them 
potentially available for iPS cell generation. Amniocytes are 
autologous to the fetus and semi-allogeneic to each parent, 
thereby expanding the potential utility of amniocyte-derived 
iPS (AdiPS) cells to other family members. Because of their 
early embryonic origin, amniocytes may have accumulated 
less genetic damage due to replication errors or somatic 
mutation than older cell types, potentially allowing derivation 
of iPS cells with improved lifespan and reduced neoplastic 
tendency. Based on these potential advantages, we therefore 
sought to further optimize this system and to extend its poten-
tial for clinical translation, making use of parallel studies in 
both the human and mouse. 
Here we report the rapid and efficient generation of human 
amniocytes in as few as 5 days in a serum-free system that 
employs freshly discarded amniotic fluid cells from a clinical 
cytogenetics laboratory. This high efficiency of iPS cell gener-
ation appears to reflect general properties of amniotic fluid 
cells, and not selection for, or reprogramming of known sub-
populations of amniotic fluid cells. To make the derivation 
protocol more efficient, we have also used manual picking 
of live immunostained iPS cell colonies to simplify their selec-
tive purification and expansion. Lastly, of specific relevance to 
future translational applications, it would be a significant 
advance if one could avoid the xenoculture of human stem 
cells on MEFs or animal-derived feeder cells. Interestingly, 
AFS cells derived from amniocytes have been reported to 
maintain multipotency in the absence of a supporting feeder 
layer (30). This observation suggested that amniocytes might 
be able to substitute for MEF feeder layers in ES or iPS cell 
culture. Thus, we evaluated and established the feasibility of 
using mitotically inactivated human and mouse amniocytes 
as a source of feeder layers for the propagation of undifferen-
tiated pluripotent iPS and ES cells. This latter innovation may 
further advance the clinical utility of human iPS and ES cell 
systems. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Reprogramming of mouse amniocytes </p>

<p>To explore the reprogramming of amniocytes in depth, we first 
focused on mouse amniocytes, which are more reproducibly 
obtained than human amniocytes and uniform in genetic back-
ground. In 14 separate experiments, performed according to 
the protocol summarized in Figure 1A -C (and detailed in 
Materials and Methods), mouse amniocyte cultures transduced </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>
with Oct4, Sox2, Klf4 and c-Myc and initially cultured in the 
absence of a feeder layer formed multiple ES cell-like colonies 
on day 5 post-infection (Fig. 2A and E, Table 1). When these 
colonies were further cultured, prior to transfer to feeder layers 
for long-term propagation, there was a notable increase in 
colony number between days 5 and 7. Mouse amniocyte cul-
tures transduced with only Klf4 and c-Myc also exhibited mul-
tiple colonies with ES cell morphology, but not until day 7 
post-infection (Fig. 2A and I, Table 1). All other binary com-
binations of TFs failed to generate such colonies in six differ-
ent experiments. In addition, prolonged culture of amniocytes 
in numerous experiments did not result in the formation of iPS 
cell-like colonies. 
The four-factor-and two-factor-derived mouse amniocyte 
colonies, provisionally termed 4-mAdiPS and 2-mAdiPS 
cells, respectively, resembled mouse ES (mES) cells. They 
could be maintained and passaged multiple times using a stan-
dard mES cell protocol with mitotically inactivated MEF 
feeder layers (MEF feeders) and mES cell medium (see 
Materials and Methods). In addition, when mouse amniocyte-
derived colonies were cultured in mES cell medium on low 
adhesion plates without feeder cells and in the absence of 
LIF or bFGF for 3 to 7 days, embryoid bodies (EBs) formed. 
The expression of pluripotency markers by mouse 
amniocyte-derived colonies was first assessed by histochem-
ical staining for alkaline phosphatase (AP) activity and by 
immunocytochemistry for Oct4 and SSEA-1 (Fig. 2A-L). 
Similar to mES cells, both 4-mAdiPS and 2-mAdiPS cell colo-
nies were positive for AP activity and immunoreactive for 
Oct4 and SSEA-1. Using live immunostaining for SSEA-1, 
putative mouse iPS colonies were selectively picked and 
enriched for further characterization. RT-PCR and western </p>

<p>blot analyses further confirmed the expression of SSEA-1 
and other pluripotency markers in the immunoselected iPS 
cell populations (Fig. 2M and N). Specifically, analysis of 
RNA isolated from induced amniocyte cultures that contained 
significant numbers of colonies revealed abundant levels of 
Oct4, Nanog and Sox2 transcripts, comparable with the 
levels detected in G4 mES cells. Oct4 protein expression 
was confirmed by western blot. Both untreated amniocytes 
and MEFs were excluded as sources of significant marker 
expression. These data strongly suggest that the amniocyte-
derived induced colonies represent iPS cells. </p>

<p>4-mAdiPS and 2-mAdiPS cells are pluripotent </p>

<p>To further assess the pluripotency of mAdiPS cells, two types 
of differentiation experiments were performed. In the first 
type, 4-mAdiPS cells were injected subcutaneously into 
severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID) mice and the ter-
atomas that formed after 3 weeks (n ¼ 12) were analyzed by 
H&amp;E staining and immunohistochemistry to assay for differ-
entiation markers specific to cell types from the three germ 
layers (Fig. 2O-T). Teratomas derived from 4-mAdiPS cells 
demonstrated glandular epithelium and smooth muscle differ-
entiation, and expressed alpha-fetoprotein (AFP), smooth 
muscle actin (SMA) and neurofilament (NF), indicative of 
endodermal, mesodermal and ectodermal differentiation, 
respectively. In the second type of experiment, both 
4-mAdiPS and 2-mAdiPS cells, allowed to differentiate in 
vitro in culture for 2 weeks in the absence of LIF, revealed 
immunocytochemical results similar to those observed for ter-
atoma formation, indicating the differentiation of endodermal, 
mesodermal and ectodermal cell types (Fig. 1U-W). </p>

<p>mAdiPS cells can be rapidly and efficiently derived from 
mouse amniocytes </p>

<p>Having determined that the mAdiPS colonies satisfied several 
criteria for iPS cells, we next determined the efficiency of iPS 
cell colony formation from mouse amniocytes, compared with 
the efficiency of iPS cell colony formation from MEFs 
(Table 1). MEFs transduced with four factors initially 
formed colonies with an efficiency of 0.1% (115 + 11 colo-
nies per 10 5 MEFs; mean + SEM; n ¼ 14 experiments) at day 
5 post-infection. In contrast, mouse amniocytes formed 704 + 
125 and 2016 + 560 colonies per 10 5 amniocytes at days 5 and 
7, respectively, for a nominal efficiency at day 7 of 1.4%. 
When assayed for AP activity or Oct4 immunoreactivity, 
about one-third of the colonies were uniformly positive for 
each marker. Since other experiments revealed these markers 
to largely overlap, the overall efficiency of pluripotent 
colony formation (by this and other criteria described below) 
is on the order of 1.4% × 1/3 or 0.5%. These data also indi-
cate that the induction of pluripotency in mouse amniocytes is 
significantly faster (5 days post-infection) relative to that 
reported for other cell types such as MEFs 
(3,4,11,14,20-26). Similar induction efficiencies were also 
observed for pluripotent colony formation from mouse amnio-
cytes when just Klf4 and c-Myc were used. However, a lag of 
two additional days for the emergence of 2-mAdiPS cells com-
pared with 4-mAdiPS cells was observed. No colonies </p>

<p>Figure 1. Reprogramming protocol and infection efficiency of mouse and 
human amniocytes. (A) Mouse or human amniocytes were plated (day 23) 
in the absence of feeder layers and infected (day 0) with four (Oct4, Sox2, 
Klf4, c-Myc) or two (Klf4, c-Myc) retroviral vectors, with colonies emerging 
by 5 days (four factors, mouse and human) or 7 days (two factors, mouse) 
post-infection. Colonies were picked on day 9 via live immunostaining and 
transferred to feeder layers. (B) Phase image of cultured mouse amniocytes 
5 days after plating. (C) The efficiency of retroviral infection of cultured 
amniocytes was .90% as reflected by retroviral GFP reporter expression 2 
days post-infection. (D) A single primitive hAdiPS cell colony on day 5 post-
infection (scale bars, 200 mm). </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>appeared in MEFs that were transduced with just these two 
factors and analyzed out to 9 days post-infection. </p>

<p>Amniotic fluid stem cells do not preferentially contribute 
to mAdiPS cell generation </p>

<p>The finding of endogenous stem cells in amniotic fluid (30) 
suggests a potential explanation for the relative efficiency of 
iPS cell induction. To test the idea that these cells are 
simply being selected for, or are already partly 
re-programmed, c-Kit-positive mouse amniotic fluid-derived 
cells, proposed to represent AFS cells (30), were isolated by 
flow cytometry or by magnetic separation (see Materials and 
Methods), and either cultured without further treatment or sub-
jected to reprogramming. The efficiency and temporal emer-
gence of iPS colonies was no greater or faster for c-Kit 
enriched cultures than for control amniocyte cultures (0.13% 
efficiency of mouse AdiPS cell generation by day 5 for both 
c-Kit enriched and non-c-Kit enriched cells). These data 
suggest that c-Kit-positive AFS cells do not contribute prefer-
entially to the origin of mAdiPS cells. Similarly, to investigate </p>

<p>the potential contribution of rare Oct4 + cells present in amnio-
tic fluid (30,34), we applied our iPS cell induction protocol to 
amniocytes from a transgenic Oct4-GFP reporter mouse strain 
(37). Although eventually many of these colonies express 
GFP, no immediate enrichment for, or recruitment of GFP + 
cells in colonies was observed at 5 days post-infection. 
These results argue against a selective contribution of c-Kit + 
or Oct4 + amniocyte subpopulations to mAdiPS cell deri-
vation. </p>

<p>Human AdiPS (hAdiPS) cells can be rapidly derived from 
fresh and long-term cultured human amniocytes </p>

<p>We next sought to extend our observations on the generation 
of mAdiPS cells from mid-gestation mouse amniocytes to 
second trimester human amniocytes. Amniocytes were col-
lected from three individuals and subjected to reprogramming 
within 2 weeks of initial plating, as soon as the cells were 
released from the clinical cytogenetics laboratory. Human 
amniocytes transduced with four factors demonstrated the 
same rapid and efficient formation of hAdiPS cell colonies </p>

<p>Figure 2. mES, 4-mAdiPS and 2-mAdiPS cells exhibit similar morphology, gene expression and pluripotency. (A-L) Similar morphology, alkaline phophatase 
histochemical staining, Oct4 and SSEA-1 immunoreactivity for R1 mES, 4-mAdiPS and 2-mAdiPS cells (scale bars, 50 mm). (M) RT -PCR analysis shows 
similar Nanog, Oct4 and Sox2 expression in mES, 4-mAdiPS and 2-mAdiPS cells. (N) Western-blot expression of Oct4 in 4-mAdiPS cells at the expected 
40 kDa size. (O) Teratoma derived from 4-mAdiPS cells injected into SCID mouse. (P and Q) Differentiation of histologically distinct tissue types in teratomas 
derived from 4-mAdiPS cells injected into SCID mice, assessed by H&amp;E staining, demonstrates glandular and smooth muscle differentiation (scale bars, 
200 mm). (R-T) Positive immunostaining for AFP, SMA and NF in teratomas derived from 4-mAdiPS cells injected into SCID mice. (U-W) 2-mAdiPS 
cells differentiated in vitro for 7 days exhibit similar immunoreactivity for AFP, SMA and NF (scale bars, 100 mm). mES, mouse embryonic stem cells; 
Alk. Phos., alkaline phosphatase; mAmnio, mouse amniocytes; MEFs, mouse embryonic fibroblasts; AFP, alpha-fetoprotein; SMA, smooth muscle actin; 
NF, neurofilament. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>
by 5 days in vitro (2916 + 8 hAdiPS colonies per 10 5 human 
amniocytes) as seen with mouse AdiPS cells. From one indi-
vidual alone, 18 clonal hAdiPS cell lines were obtained and 
characterized (Fig. 3). These colonies closely resembled hES 
cell colonies in terms of morphology (Fig. 3A and F), immu-
nostaining for OCT4, SSEA-4, TRA-1-60 and TRA-1-81 
(Fig. 3B-E, G -J), and AP reactivity (data not shown). Karyo-
type analysis of one clonal hAdiPS cell line demonstrated a 
normal human male karyotype (Supplementary Material, 
Fig. S1A). </p>

<p>Gene expression analysis of hAdiPS cells </p>

<p>RNA expression of OCT4, SOX2, GDF3, DNMT3B and REX1 
was confirmed in presumptive hAdiPS cells by RT -PCR 
(Fig. 3K). In contrast, primary human amniocytes expressed 
lower levels of OCT4 and did not express SOX2, GDF3, 
DNMTB3B or REX1, and MEFs did not express any of these 
genes at detectable levels. As an additional test of the pluripo-
tency of AdiPS cells, we performed microarray gene 
expression analyses with RNA isolated from live, SSEA-4, 
TRA-1-60 or TRA-1-81 immunostained hAdiPS cells, and 
also from hES cell colonies and primary amniocytes. Based 
on the expression levels of 11328 genes, hAdiPS cells demon-
strated greater similarity in their gene expression profiles 
compared with control H1 hES cells than with human amnio-
cytes (Figs 3L and 4A and B, Supplementary Material, 
Fig. S3). A correlation matrix comparing genome-wide 
mRNA expression data between hES cells, hAdiPS cells and 
human amniocytes demonstrated a correlation coefficient 
(r 2 ) of 0.98 -0.99 between hES and hAdiPS cells, compared 
with 0.82-0.85 between human amniocytes and hES cells, 
and 0.82 -0.85 between human amniocytes and hAdiPS cells 
(Supplementary Material, Fig. S3). Furthermore, methylation 
sequence analysis of genomic DNA for the endogenous 
OCT4 and NANOG promoter regions demonstrated </p>

<p>demethylated patterns for hAdiPS cells comparable with 
those observed in hES cells (Fig. 3M, Supplementary Material, 
Fig. S2). Interestingly, of the 12 amniocyte lines assayed, the 
proportion of methylation sensitive sites in the OCT4 promoter 
that were actually methylated was variable and in all cases less 
than 50%; this suggests some pre-existing epigenetic resem-
blance to the pluripotent state. Nonetheless, hAdiPS cells 
resemble hES cells much more closely than they resemble 
amniocytes in their gene expression profile, and in the 
demethylation pattern of two key pluripotency genes. These 
results support the conclusion that human amniocytes can be 
effectively reprogrammed to a pluripotent state. </p>

<p>hAdiPS cells are pluripotent and can differentiate into 
endoderm, mesoderm and ectoderm </p>

<p>To further establish the pluripotency of hAdiPS cells, we next 
examined their differentiation capacity. Under differentiation 
conditions, cultures of hAdiPS cells (Fig. 5A-C) and 
hAdiPS cell-derived EBs (Fig. 5D -F) demonstrated ectoderm, 
endoderm and mesoderm formation, as reflected by AFP, 
SMA and NF expression, respectively. In addition, we were 
able to efficiently generate teratomas 7 to 8 weeks after 
hAdiPS cells were injected into hind leg muscles of SCID 
mice (see Materials and Methods). Analysis of the cellular 
composition of these teratomas, determined by fixation, cryo-
sectioning and H&amp;E staining, demonstrated histologically dis-
tinct types of tissue that represent the three germ layers 
(Fig. 5G -I). Consistent with the histological findings, immu-
nohistochemistry of these tissue sections revealed positive 
immunostaining for AFP, SMA and NF (Fig. 5J -L). Collec-
tively, the above results indicate that, consistent with other 
reports (34,35), human amniocytes can be reprogrammed to 
functional iPS cells at high efficiency. </p>

<p>Amniocytes can function as feeder cell layers for mES, hES 
and hAdiPS cells </p>

<p>Our results showing that amniocytes can be efficiently repro-
grammed to a pluripotent state, coupled with the observation 
that AFS cells do not require a feeder layer for self mainten-
ance (30), prompted us to consider whether amniocytes them-
selves might function as feeder layers for mouse and human 
ES and AdiPS cells. To test this hypothesis, we first plated 
R1 mES cells that contained an Oct4-GFP reporter gene on 
a monolayer of freshly harvested or previously passaged 
E13.5 mouse amniocytes (amniocyte feeders) that had been 
mitomycin-treated at a density of 10 5 amniocytes per 
1.76 cm 2 (see Materials and Methods). We then propagated 
the mES cell cultures for 20-25 serial passages over 75 
days. During this time, mES cells maintained on mouse 
amniocyte feeder layers exhibited colony morphology associ-
ated with an undifferentiated ES cell state, and behaved indis-
tinguishably from mES cells maintained in parallel on MEF 
feeders. At the end of 75 days, we examined the expression 
of pluripotency markers in mES cells maintained on amnio-
cytes by immunocytochemistry, RT -PCR and qRT -PCR, as 
well as by their capacity for differentiation into derivatives 
of all three germ layers, and for germline competent mouse 
chimera formation (Fig. 6). Colonies of R1 mES cells </p>

<p>Table 1. Efficiency and latency of AdiPS cell generation from mouse and 
human amniocytes </p>

<p>No. of factors 
(species) </p>

<p>Days 
post-infection </p>

<p>No. of colonies per 10 5 treated cells a </p>

<p>Amniocytes 
MEFs </p>

<p>Four factors 
(mouse) </p>

<p>5 
704 + 125 (32% AP + , 
34% Oct4 + ) </p>

<p>115 + 11 </p>

<p>Four factors 
(mouse) </p>

<p>7 
2016 + 560 
89 + 12 </p>

<p>Two factors 
(mouse) </p>

<p>5 
n d 
n d </p>

<p>Two factors 
(mouse) </p>

<p>7 
674 + 59 
nd </p>

<p>Four factors 
(human) </p>

<p>5 
2916 + 8 
115 + 11 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data are shown as mean + SEM from 14 experiments. Mouse amniocytes or 
MEFs were transduced with retroviral vectors expressing either four or two 
factors (Oct4, Sox2, Klf4, c-Myc; or Klf4, c-Myc), and assayed for colony 
formation at the day post-infection indicated. For four-factor day 5 and 
two-factor day 7 protocols, the % AP and % Oct4-positive colonies are shown 
in parentheses. 
MEFs, mouse embryonic fibroblasts; nd, no colonies detected; AP + , alkaline 
phosphatase positive; Oct4 + , Oct4 positive. </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>maintained on mouse amniocyte feeders exhibited AP histo-
chemical staining, BrdU labeling, Oct4-GFP reporter 
expression and Oct4 immunostaining (Fig. 6A-D). These 
results were indistinguishable from the results observed for 
colonies of mES cells maintained and passaged under compar-
able conditions on MEF feeders (data not shown). Further-
more, mES cells cultured on mouse amniocyte feeders 
continued to express Oct4, Nanog and Sox2 at levels compar-
able to those observed for mES cells on MEF feeders by both 
RT-PCR (Fig. 6G) and by qRT -PCR (data not shown). 
Moreover, mES cells cultured on mouse amniocytes and 
allowed to differentiate for 7 -14 days in vitro exhibited 
marker expression for NF and SMA (Fig. 6E and F). mES 
cells cultured on amniocytes also exhibited efficiencies of 
chimera formation (13/35 versus 4/10, for mES cells main-
tained on amniocyte versus MEF feeders, respectively), 
percent of mES cell coat color contribution and rate of germ-
line transmission, comparable to those maintained on MEF 
feeders (Fig. 6H and data not shown). Based on these specific 
analyses, mouse amniocytes and MEFs appear to function 
equivalently as feeders for mES cell culture. 
Next, since the transmission of viruses and other infectious 
agents between animal-derived feeders and hES cells is a 
potential obstacle to human cell therapy, we tested the 
ability of g-irradiated human amniocytes (human amniocyte 
feeders) to maintain H1 hES cells and hAdiPS cells in an 
undifferentiated state. In this case, after passage of stem </p>

<p>cells for 21 days, both hES cells (Fig. 6I-K) and hAdiPS 
(Fig. 6O-T) cells retained OCT4, SSEA-4 and TRA-1-81 
expression by immunostaining, and exhibited normal differen-
tiation in EB (Fig. 6L -N) and teratoma formation (data not 
shown) after 7 and 56 additional days, respectively. In 
addition, H1 hES cells retained a normal karyotype under 
these culture conditions (Supplementary Material, Fig. S1B). 
These results indicate that human amniocytes can function 
as feeder layers for hES and hAdiPS cell culture. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This work describes an amniocyte-based stem-cell derivation 
and culture system that has potential utility for the transla-
tional application of human stem-cell-based therapies 
(Fig. 7). This system has several features that potentially 
address currently problematic aspects associated with existing 
approaches to stem-cell therapy. The advances tendered by 
this work include: (i) the derivation of both iPS and feeder 
cells from a single pool of donor amniocytes, pre-screened 
for pathogenic human viruses; (ii) the avoidance of exposure 
to animal products (serum, feeder cells); (iii) the use of 
live cell immunostaining for efficient selection of repro-
grammed iPS cell colonies; and (iv) the previously described 
enhanced reprogramming efficiency which human amniocytes 
exhibit (34,35). </p>

<p>Figure 3. hES and hAdiPS cells exhibit similar morphology and gene expression. (A-J) Similar morphology and OCT4, SSEA-4, TRA-1-60 and TRA-1-81 
immunoreactivity for H1 hES cells and hAdiPS cells (scale bars, 100 mm). (K) Transcripts for OCT4, SOX2, GDF3, DNMT3B and REX1 are expressed at com-
parable levels in hES and hAdiPS cells. (L) Microarray analysis of hAdiPS cell gene expression compared with H1 hES cells demonstrating 0.99 correlation as 
opposed to 0.82 for human amniocytes relative to H1 hES cells. (M) Bisulfite-treated PCR-amplified sequence of the promoter regions of OCT4 and NANOG. 
Open and closed circles indicate unmethylated and methylated CpGs. hES, human embryonic stem cells; hAmnio, human amniocytes; MEFs, mouse embryonic 
fibroblasts. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>
The central feature of the system is that both cellular com-
ponents of the system (i.e. iPS cells and their supporting feeder 
cells) originate from a single cell source. If these cells orig-
inate from a future recipient, then the transferred cells, and </p>

<p>any feeder cells that might be co-transferred to a recipient, 
either inadvertently or on purpose, will be autologous to the 
recipient. In principle, this would further obviate the potential 
for an immune reaction. The potential availability of human 
amniocytes, which can be banked and which are considered 
a discarded tissue by most institutional review boards 
(IRBs), thus offers the opportunity for the culture of human 
stem cells and feeders that are both autologous to the intended 
recipient. While the banking of fetal amniocytes for future use 
may seem logistically complex, it should be noted that 
banking of umbilical cord blood cells for similar purposes 
has already been implemented clinically. 
We show that mitotically inactivated amniocytes can serve 
as feeder layers for the co-culture and self-renewal of both 
human iPS and ES cells (Fig. 7), thereby circumventing the 
need for MEF feeders and the accompanying concerns about 
xenoculture and resultant zoonosis. The transfer of human 
stem cells that have been cultured with nonhuman animal 
cell feeder layers and then transplanted into a human recipient 
falls under the FDA definition of xenotransplantation, whereby 
any 'human body fluids, cells, tissues, or organs that have had 
ex vivo contact with live nonhuman animal cells, tissues, or 
organs' are themselves xenotransplant materials (38,39). The 
concern regarding xenotransplantation is the potential for 
transmission of recognized, or as yet unrecognized, infectious 
agents from animals to humans (38). Because it avoids the use 
of 'animal cells, tissues or organs,' our iPS cell derivation and 
culture system would not involve xenotransplantation. Our 
hAdiPS cell derivation protocol also avoids the use of fetal 
bovine serum by employing KOSR, a serum-free culture 
medium (see Materials and Methods). In addition, the 
human iPS cell lines derived here originate from human 
amniotic fluid cells that are already routinely screened for 
evidence of infectious agents including hepatitis, human 
immunodeficiency virus and rubella. The use of an individ-
ual's own cells and tissues without exposure to animal cells, 
and after screening for human infectious agents, should help 
obviate concerns about zoonosis associated with the use of 
MEF feeders, and about latent viral infection. These features </p>

<p>Figure 4. (A) Dendrogram and (B) heatmaps showing relationship between two independent samples of each of hES cells, hAdiPS cells and human amniocytes. 
The expression values within heatmaps represent the fold difference of expression from the ES cell lines calculated by the logarithm (base 2) of the ratio between 
the expression level for a gene between the average expression of the ES cell lines for that particular gene. Heatmaps were prepared using unsupervised hier-
archical clustering. </p>

<p>Figure 5. hAdiPS cells demonstrate pluripotency. (A-C) hAdiPS cells differ-
entiated in culture for 14 days exhibit subpopulations of cells immunoreactive 
for AFP, SMA and NF. (D -F) Similar immunoreactivity is observed when 
cryosections of EBs from hAdiPS cells are analyzed (scale bars, 100 mm). 
(G-I) Analysis of teratomas derived from hAdiPS cells injected in SCID 
mice shows differentiation of histologically distinct tissue types such as gland-
ular tissue (endoderm), muscle tissue (mesoderm) and neuroepithelial tissue 
(ectoderm), respectively (scale bars, 100 mm). (J-L) Positive immunostaining 
for AFP, SMA and NF in teratomas derived from hAdiPS cells injected into 
SCID mice (scale bars, 50 mm). EBs, embryoid bodies; AFP, alpha-
fetoprotein; SMA, smooth muscle actin; NF, neurofilament; SCID, severe 
combined immunodeficient mice. </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>could reduce the burden of testing for certain transmissable 
diseases. Another obvious limitation of many current iPS 
cell derivation approaches is the use of viral vectors for effi-
cient derivation. However, research in many laboratories is 
directed towards developing efficient, viral-free derivation 
protocols. Although we employed retroviral vectors in the 
current study, we found it possible to avoid the use of 
serum, both in iPS cell generation and even in reprogramming 
vector preparation. Collectively, these improvements should 
promote clinical translation by improving the overall effi-
ciency of reprogramming from an available clinical source, 
and by establishing the feasibility of using the same individ-
ual's amniocytes as feeders. 
It should be noted that other human feeder layers and 
feeder-free culture media have been described, including 
defined and serum-free media that support undifferentiated 
hES cell growth for up to 10 passages (40,41). However, 
hES cells maintained in feederless systems can eventually 
become karyotypically unstable (42,43). Recently, HDFs 
have been shown to serve as autologous feeders for hiPS 
cells, but HDF-derived iPS cells and HDF-derived feeders 
are limited by prolonged derivation times and the fact that 
not all HDF cell lines efficiently support hES or hiPS cell 
growth (44). Nonetheless, the HDF and amniocyte systems 
may prove complementary, as the former would be useful 
for the vast majority of who did not have the opportunity to 
have their amniocytes banked. However, going forward, the 
large individuals number of amniocenteses performed in the 
USA and other industrialized nations could provide a practical </p>

<p>source for banked amniocytes and for AdiPS cells and feeder 
cells for cell therapy applications. 
Compared to other somatic cell types, amniocytes offer 
several potential advantages for the generation of iPS cells. 
Mouse and human amniocytes provide a source of cells that 
permit the generation of iPS cells with a significantly higher 
efficiency, by more than 10-fold, relative to MEFs or HDFs. 
By our most conservative estimate, 0.5% of mouse or 
human amniocytes can be reprogrammed to a pluripotent 
state, as further confirmed by AP and Oct4 expression and 
by subsequent differentiation experiments (EB formation, ter-
atoma analysis), microarray gene expression and methylation 
analysis of human iPS cell genomic DNA. In contrast, the effi-
ciencies reported for adult human fibroblasts, MEFs, blood 
cells, adipose stem cells and keratinocytes are: 0.01, 0.001, 
0.001, 0.2 and 0.002%, respectively (4,14,20,23,26,45). 
Thus, human amniocytes are a highly efficient target cell for 
iPS cell derivation. Indeed, results from this and other 
studies (34,35) indicate that amniocytes represent the most 
rapidly reprogrammed cell population by primary infection 
yet described, with a latency of 5 -6 days, compared with 
about 10 days to induce iPS cell colonies from keratinocytes 
(20) and 2 weeks or more from MEFs (14,20). Lastly, our 
studies in the mouse system suggest that just two factors 
(Klf4 and c-Myc) are sufficient to initiate pluripotency, and 
the 2-factor mouse AdiPS cells were able to differentiate 
into all three germ layers. No other reprogramming protocol 
that we are aware of permits the omission of Oct4 in iPS 
cell derivation. Although the use of Klf4 and c-Myc, two </p>

<p>Figure 6. Mitotically inactivated amniocytes function as feeder layers for mES, hES and hAdiPS cells. (A and B) Mitomycin C-treated mouse amniocytes func-
tion as feeder layer for R1 mES cells. After 10 passages (30 days) in culture, mES cell colonies demonstrate AP activity and BrdU labeling. (C and D) Oct4-GFP 
reporter fluorescence and Oct4 immunostaining of mES colonies cultured for 30 days on amniocyte feeders. (E and F) NF and SMA immunostaining after 7 and 
14 days of in vitro differentiation, respectively. (G) RT -PCR analysis of Oct4, Nanog and Sox2 expression in early (E, ,3) and late (L, .10) passage mES cells 
maintained on MEFs or mouse amniocytes. Controls (  *  ) are feeders without mES cells. (H) Germline competent chimera from blastocyst injection of mES cells 
maintained for 50 days (15 passages) on mouse amniocyte feeder layer. (I-K) OCT4, SSEA-4 and TRA-1-81H1 immunoreactivity in hES cells cultured for 21 
days (six passages) on g-irradiated human amniocytes. (L-N) AFP, SMA and NF immunostaining after EB differentiation of H1 hES cells cultured on 
g-irradiated human amniocytes. (O-T) g-irradiated human amniocyte feeder layers support growth and self-renewal of hAdiPS cells derived from the same 
amniocytes. After 21 days (five passages) in culture, hAdiPS cell colonies demonstrate AP activity and OCT4, SSEA-4, TRA-1-60 and TRA-1-81 expression 
by immunocytochemistry. mES and hES cells, mouse and human embryonic stem cells; AP or Alk. Phos., alkaline phosphatase; BrdU, bromodeoxyuridine; 
Amnios, mouse amniocytes; MEFs, mouse embryonic fibroblasts; EP, early passage; LP, late passage; AFP, alpha-fetoprotein; SMA, smooth muscle actin; 
NF, neurofilament. Scale bars: 100 mm. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>
oncoproteins, may limit the clinical utility of approaches based 
on these two factors, similar two factor experiments will be of 
interest in human amniocytes. 
Why are mouse and human amniocytes so readily repro-
grammed? One possible explanation relates to the notion 
that embryonic cells more closely resemble the pluripotent 
state in terms of their transcriptional and chromatin states 
than other somatic cell types. Recent work by Hochedlinger 
and colleagues (27) using a secondary system to generate 
iPS cells in the context of hematopoiesis clearly demonstrates 
that the differentiation state of a cell strongly impacts both 
the efficiency and kinetics of reprogramming. In particular, 
progenitor stages for various hematopoietic lineages show 
higher re-programming efficiencies than more differentiated 
stages (27). Thus, while human foreskin fibroblasts and 
MEFs have been used for iPS cell induction and represent 
perinatal and embryonic cell types, respectively, amniocytes 
can be isolated as early as 15 weeks in the human (36) 
and at E8.5 in the mouse (our observations). At these 
early developmental stages, some embryonic cells that are 
shed into the amniotic fluid may retain substantial multipo-
tency, and may even approximate the pluripotent stem-cell 
state. 
Thus, the observation that amniocytes are so readily repro-
grammed may partly reflect their embryonic origin. These 
cells may already possess a partly pluripotent transcriptional 
or epigenetic state and be more readily reprogrammed than 
adult cell types. In this regard, it is notable that while </p>

<p>hAdiPS cells demonstrate a highly concordant transcriptional 
expression profile with hES cells (r 2 ¼ 0.98 -0.99), non-
reprogrammed 
amniocytes 
also 
exhibit 
significant 
concordance with hES and hAdiPS cells (r 2 ¼ 0.82 -0.85) 
(Supplementary Material, Fig. S3). In addition, the donor 
amniocyte OCT4 promoter methylation pattern is heteroge-
nous and incomplete (Fig. 3M). Although we were unable to 
show 
preferential 
reprogramming 
of 
endogenous 
Oct4-expressing amniocytes, the incompleteness of Oct4 pro-
moter methylation in amniocytes could facilitate conversion to 
the demethylated state that characterizes pluripotency. Emer-
ging studies imply that the epigenetic memory of specific 
donor cell types may restrict the subsequent differentiation 
potential of derived iPS cells (46-48). For example, 
fibroblast-, hematopoietic-and myogenic-derived iPS cells 
exhibit distinct transcriptional and epigenetic patterns and 
differentiation potential (48). Moreover, iPS cells harbor 
DNA methylation signatures characteristic of the donor cell, 
which favors differentiation related to the donor cell and 
restricts alternative fates (46,48). In contrast, by the criteria 
of in vitro EB and in vivo teratoma formation, hAdiPS cells 
differentiated into tissues representing all three germ layers 
without obvious preference for a single tissue type or germ 
layer. The current experiments suggest that amniocytes 
could be useful for generating iPS cells that can differentiate 
into a range of cell types. 
An extension of this view is that pluripotent or multipotent 
stem cells already exist within the amniocyte population, and </p>

<p>Figure 7. Patient-specific stem-cell therapy using human amniocytes in a xenoculture-free, autologous system. In this model, discarded amniocytes are obtained 
as a byproduct of routine antenatal screening and can be banked. At an appropriate time, they are cultured and reprogrammed in vitro to become patient-specific 
amniocyte-derived induced pluripotent stem (AdiPS) cells. AdiPS cells may then be maintained and expanded on amniocyte feeder cells from the same patient 
and subsequently banked for later use in cell-based directed differentiation or other protocols to generate new tissues. </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>that our iPS cell protocol simply selects for, or reprograms, an 
existing stem-cell-like population already present in amniotic 
fluid. Indeed, such an AFS cell population has been described 
(30). However, our results show that culture of non-transduced 
amniocytes does not result in colony formation even with 
extended culture and more than 30 passages. Similarly, 
neither AFS cells nor hAFDCs form teratomas in mice 
(30,34), although the requirement for a threshold number of 
pluripotent cells for teratoma formation (49) may constrain 
the sensitivity of this assay. Nonetheless, enrichment for 
amniocytes that express the c-Kit receptor, which operation-
ally defines AFS cells, does not improve the efficiency of 
iPS cell induction. Therefore, while our results do not 
exclude the possibility that a subpopulation of amniocytes 
contributes to the derivation of AdiPS cell colonies, it seems 
unlikely that previously described AFS cells in amniotic 
fluid (30,34) preferentially do so. Additional work is required 
to better understand the heterogeneity of amniocytes and to 
assess how the different cell types present in amniotic fluid 
influence the efficiency of iPS cell induction. 
Our observations on mouse and human amniocytes are gen-
erally in agreement with a recent description of efficient but 
variable frequency of hiPS cell derivation using human amnio-
cytes that were subjected to long-term culture (.10 passages) 
and morphologic selection after infection, and then grown on 
mouse feeder cells (34). Two key differences between these 
derivation protocols include the other study's use of morpho-
logic selection prior to analysis, and of mouse feeder layers 
and serum-containing media for iPS cell derivation. These fea-
tures of the other protocol may partly explain the over 25-fold 
variation in iPS cell derivation efficiency between batches of 
amniocytes that were observed in those studies. In contrast, 
we employed a serum-free and initially feederless system for 
hAdiPS cell derivation, and live cell immunoselection for 
rapid colony purification, prior to long-term propagation on 
feeders (15,25). The use of live cell immufluorescent selection 
enabled us to clone stem-cell lines with relative ease, and to 
exclude incompletely reprogrammed clones from further 
analysis. Lastly, a novel innovation is the finding that amnio-
cytes that are mitotically inactivated with either mitomycin C 
(for mouse) or g-irradiation (for human) appear to function 
with high fidelity for the propagation and maintenance of plur-
ipotent, undifferentiated iPS and ES cells. The amniocyte 
system thus provides an efficient autologous system for 
hAdiPS cell generation and culture that could significantly 
advance the translational application of stem-cell therapy. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Amniocyte isolation and other cell sources </p>

<p>Mouse amniocytes were obtained from the amniotic sacs of 
C57BL6/J mouse embryos by amniocentesis performed on 
pregnant E13.5 wild-type C57BL6/J mice (Charles River Lab-
oratories). Uterine horns of pregnant female mice at day 13.5 
p.c. were excised, washed in PBS and the amniotic fluid aspi-
rated with a 27 gauge needle from the amniotic sacs. Typi-
cally, 10 4 amniocytes were obtained in 100 ml of amniotic 
fluid per sac (0.75-1.0 ml per pooled collection from a 
single litter). Mouse amniocyte cells were washed in PBS, </p>

<p>and plated at 10 5 cells/ml in a-MEM (Gibco)/10% heat inac-
tivated FBS (HyClone)/1% Pen-Strep (100 U penicillin and 
100 mg streptomycin/ml; defined henceforth as 'amniocyte 
media') at 378C, 5% CO 2 . They were passaged twice to elim-
inate contaminating red blood cells and to expand amniocyte 
number, and assessed morphologically prior to use. Following 
two preliminary passages, fresh or frozen-thawed mouse or 
human amniocytes were cultured on 0.1% gelatin (Gibco) 
coated tissue culture plates (typically 6-well plates) for 3 
days at a plating density of 10 5 amniocytes per 1.76 cm 2 . Pas-
saged amniocytes were characterized by a fibroblast-like 
appearance and rapid proliferation (Fig. 1A). In some cases, 
mouse amniocytes were passaged up to 30 times or stored in 
liquid nitrogen, thawed and then subjected to reprogramming. 
No significant difference was observed in the efficiency with 
which iPS cells could be established from amniocytes that 
were continuously passaged, or frozen and thawed. 
Oct4-GFP reporter mice (37) were used for some amniocyte 
isolations. In other experiments, separations of mouse c-Kit 
immunoreactive amniocytes were performed using MACS 
cell separation columns and c-Kit (CD117) antibody conju-
gated to magnetic beads (Miltenyi Biotec) (30). After amniotic 
fluid isolation, cells were immediately cultured, maintained 
and passaged in vitro following standard cell culture protocols. 
Emergence of putative iPS colonies was scored on day 5 post-
infection as described below. 
Anonymous samples of discarded human amniocytes were 
obtained for hAdiPS cell experiments under Brigham and 
Women's Hospital IRB protocol no. 2006p00149 after 2 
weeks (two to four passages) of culture. Mouse R1 and G4 
ES cells were from the Samuel Lunenfeld Research Institute 
(Mt. Sinai Hosp., Univ. Toronto). Human H1 ES cells were 
obtained from the National Stem Cell Bank (WiCell, 
Madison, WI, USA). MEFs from E13.5 embryos were 
treated with mitomycin C and used as feeders for 4-mAdiPS 
and 2-mAdiPS cells, while g-irradiated MEFs were prepared 
in house or purchased (Global Stem, Inc.) and used as 
feeders for hAdiPS cells. In other experiments, feeder layers 
were prepared from mouse and human amniocytes (see 
below). Feeder preparation and ES cell culture were per-
formed using standard methods (50,51). </p>

<p>Retroviral infection, AdiPS cell generation and culture </p>

<p>Retroviral infection, iPS cell generation and culture were per-
formed in standard manner as previously described (52). Ret-
roviral particles containing each of the four reprogramming 
factors, Oct4, Sox2, c-Myc or Klf4, were generated using stan-
dard retroviral production protocols, employing the pMXs ret-
roviral plasmids (53) purchased from Addgene (Cambridge, 
MA, USA). 293T cells were plated in DMEM with 10% 
FBS (GIBCO) until 30-40% confluency; viral vectors were 
then transfected using FuGENE 6 (Roche). Forty-eight hours 
after transfection, media containing viral particles was har-
vested and used for infection of amniocyte cultures with the 
addition of 6 mg/ml polybrene (Millipore). Target cell 
MEFs, mouse amniocytes and human amniocytes were cul-
tured in a feederless system and transduced with two-, three-
and four-factor combinations of pMXs retroviral vectors for 
Oct4, Sox2, Klf4 and c-Myc (Addgene, Inc.) (4,14,52), and </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>
assayed for ES cell-like colony appearance. The infection pro-
tocol involved using subconfluent cultures of mouse or human 
amniocytes (70% confluency) that were infected with 
pluripotency-inducing retroviral vectors in viral media 
[DMEM/10% FBS for mouse cultures; for human amniocytes, 
hES media containing 20% KnockOut w Serum Replacement 
(KOSR, Invitrogen, Inc.) instead of FBS] on day 3 (Fig. 1A 
and B). The retroviral vectors for Oct4, Sox2, c-Myc and 
Klf4 or combinations thereof were added to the amniocyte cul-
tures for 48 h. The media were then changed back to amnio-
cyte media (see Amniocyte isolation and other cell sources 
section) with continued culture in a feederless system until 
the emergence of the first morphologically distinct cell colo-
nies. By day 5 post-infection (four factors, with mouse or 
human amniocytes) or day 7 post-infection (two factors with 
mouse amniocytes) in culture, colonies resembling ES cell 
colonies began to appear (Fig. 2A, E, I, Table 1). By 5 -7 
days post-infection, emerging colonies were manually picked 
(see below) and transferred onto feeder layers. 4-mAdiPS 
and 2-mAdiPS and mES cells were cultured on mitomycin 
C-treated MEF feeders in DMEM (Gibco)/10%FBS 
(HyClone)/LIF at 10 7 units per ml (Millipore)/0.1 mM b-ME 
(Sigma-Aldrich) (henceforth defined as 'mouse ES cell 
media'), while hAdiPS and hES cells were cultured on 
g-irradiated MEF feeders in 80% DMEM-F12 (Gibco)/20% 
KnockOut w Serum Replacement (KOSR, Gibco)/1 mM 
L-glutamine (Gibco)/0.1 mM b-ME (Sigma-Aldrich)/4 ng/ml 
bFGF (Invitrogen) (henceforth defined as 'human ES cell 
media'). AdiPS cell cultures were propagated using standard 
protocols. </p>

<p>Colony picking </p>

<p>Since not all emergent colonies likely represent iPS cell colo-
nies by the criterion of pluripotency marker expression, puta-
tive mAdiPS cell colonies were manually picked via live 
immunostaining for SSEA-1 (25). Primitive mAdiPS cells 
were then transferred to MEF feeders for continued culture 
(52). For hAdiPS cells, live immunostaining was performed 
with TRA-1-60. hAdiPS cell colonies were also manually 
picked and transferred to MEF feeders for continued culture. 
Such manually picked colonies were used for RNA extraction 
and microarray analysis to minimize any contribution from the 
underlying feeder cells or from incompletely reprogrammed 
amniocytes. Once the identity of the picked colonies was 
further verified by immunocytochemistry and RT -PCR analy-
sis, these clones were expanded on MEF feeders in human ES 
cell media. Expanded clones were then additionally character-
ized by differentiation assays, RT -PCR and qRT -PCR, and 
karyotypic analysis (see below). </p>

<p>RNA isolation, RT -PCR and microarray analyses </p>

<p>hAdiPS cell colonies that were live stained for SSEA-4 and 
TRA-1-60 were individually picked to minimize feeder con-
tamination, and to optimize selection for completely 
re-programmed colonies. They were pooled and RNA was iso-
lated with a Qiagen kit (Valencia, CA, USA); RNA from ES 
cell colonies was isolated in parallel. RT -PCR analyses 
were performed using primers and assay conditions listed in </p>

<p>Supplementary Material, Table S1. Microarray expression 
analyses were carried out using Illumina Human WG6 Bead-
Chips (Children's Hospital Boston Microarray Core Facility 
supported by NIH-P50-NS40828 and NIH-P30-HD18655). 
Data analyses were performed by normalizing the gene 
expression data using the lumi Bioconductor package in the 
statistical language R and by clustering relative gene 
expression to assess the expression profiles of the different 
samples. Each microarray was individually normalized by 
quantile normalization provided by the lumi package. 
Quality control was performed within each sample group by 
examining pairwise correlations. After normalization, probes 
that were deemed to have no signal by the lumi package 
across all the human samples were excluded from further cal-
culation. The expression of each gene was calculated from the 
remaining probes by first mapping each probe to its corre-
sponding gene (using the lumiHumanIDMapping package) 
and then by averaging all probes that corresponded to a par-
ticular gene. The expression values within heatmaps represent 
the fold difference of expression from the ES cell lines calcu-
lated by the logarithm (base 2) of the ratio between the 
expression level for a gene between the average expression 
of the ES cell lines for that particular gene. For producing 
the heatmaps, unsupervised hierarchical clustering was used 
based on the heatmap.2 function in the gplots package with 
average linkage. </p>

<p>Bisulfite sequencing of genomic DNA </p>

<p>Genomic DNAs from the different experimental groups of 
cells (MEFs, human amniocytes, H1-hES cells and hAdiPS 
cells) were isolated using the DNAeasy tissue kit (Qiagen). 
Purified DNA was treated with bisulfite to convert cytosine 
to uracil using the EpiTect kit (Qiagen). PCR amplification 
of the human OCT4 and NANOG promoter regions was under-
taken using published primers (54). The PCR products were 
gel purified, cloned into TOPO TA vectors (Invitrogen) and 
sequenced using the forward and reverse M13 primers (Biopo-
lymers Sequencing Core Facility at Harvard Medical School 
and Children's Hospital Boston Sequencing Core Facility). 
Methylation patterns of the cloned sequences were analyzed 
using <rs type="software">CpG viewer</rs> software (Fig. 3M). </p>

<p>Karyotypic analysis </p>

<p>Cytogenetic analyses were performed on hAdiPS and hES 
cells. All of the hAdiPS cell samples and the majority of the 
hES cell samples demonstrated normal karyotypes. Analyses 
were performed by Cell Line Genetics, Inc. (Madison, WI, 
USA). </p>

<p>Alkaline phosphatase staining and immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Cultures of presumptive AdiPS cells were fixed in 4% parafor-
maldehyde (PFA)/4% sucrose and processed for immunostain-
ing. Commercial antibodies for mouse Oct4, SSEA-1 and for 
human OCT4, SSEA-4, TRA-1-60 and TRA-1-81 (Abcam), 
and histochemical reagents for alkaline phosphatase activity 
(Sigma Aldrich) were used for marker studies. Differentiation 
of AdiPS cells was evaluated by immunostaining with </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

<p>antibodies to NF (ectoderm), alpha fetoprotein (AFP, endo-
derm) and alpha SMA (mesoderm) (Abcam). Primary and sec-
ondary antibody immunohistochemistry was performed 
according to standard protocols. Controls included omission 
of primary or secondary antibody, and comparison of differen-
tiated and undifferentiated cells. </p>

<p>EB, teratoma and chimera generation </p>

<p>EBs were generated by replacing ES medium with medium 
consisting of 68% DMEM-F12/1% Pen/Strep (Gibco)/15% 
KOSR/5% Fetal Bovine Serum (Heat inactivated, FBS/1 mM 
L-glutamine/0.1 mM b-ME/1% NEAA, and by plating AdiPS 
or ES cells on ultra low adhesion cell culture plates (CoStar, 
Corning) for 7 -10 days. EBs were fixed in 4% PFA/4% 
sucrose, and either serially dehydrated for paraffin histology 
or sucrose permeabilized and embedded in OCT for frozen 
section analysis and immunohistochemistry. Teratomas were 
generated by injecting 2 × 10 6 cells into the hind legs of 
8-week SCID mice (Jackson Laboratories). After 3 weeks 
(mAdiPS cells) or 7-8 weeks (hAdiPS cells), SCID mice 
were euthanized, and the teratomas harvested and processed 
for immunostaining. Mouse chimeras were generated by injec-
tion of R1 mES cells into BALB/c recipient blastocysts. Chi-
meras were scored by coat color and tested for germline 
transmission. All animal studies were conducted under a 
HMS IACUC approved protocol. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplementary Material is available at HMG online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We gratefully acknowledge the assistance of the late John B. 
Edwards III. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest statement. None declared. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>This work was supported by NIH Road Map grants UL1 
DE019581 and RL1 DE019021 (R.L.M.), TL1 EB008540 
(B.G.-N.); the Harvard Stem Cell Institute (R.L.M., R.M.A.); 
and T32 HD040135, K12 HD001255, ASRM-Serono New 
Investigator and HMS Scholars in Medicine Awards 
(R.M.A.). Funding to pay the Open Access publication 
charges for this article was provided by NIH. </p>



<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>



<p>
 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 5 </p>

</text></tei>