<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3932086" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Insight into the neural mechanisms under-
lying the shared and disparate features of schizophrenia 
(SZ) and bipolar disorder (BD) is limited. The amygdala 
and prefrontal cortex (PFC) appear to have crucial roles 
in SZ and BD, yet abnormalities appear to manifest dif-
ferently in the 2 disorders. Methods: Eighteen participants 
with SZ, 18 participants with BD, and 18 healthy con-
trols (HC) underwent resting-state functional magnetic 
resonance imaging. Resting-state functional connectivity 
(rsFC) between the PFC and the amygdala divided into 
3 subregions (the laterobasal, centromedial, and superfi-
cial amygdala) was examined using probabilistic anatomic 
maps. For each participant, rsFC maps of the 3 amyg-
dala subregions were computed and compared across the 
3 groups. Results: Compared with the HC group, we found 
significant differences in rsFC between the amygdala 
and PFC in the SZ and BD groups. In direct comparison 
between the SZ and BD groups, distinct patterns of rsFC 
between the amygdala and PFC were observed, particularly 
in the superficial amygdala. RsFC between the amygdala 
and the dorsal lateral PFC was significantly decreased in 
the SZ group, whereas rsFC between the amygdyala and 
the ventral PFC was significantly decreased in the BD 
group. Conclusions: These results strongly suggest dorsal 
vs ventral PFC differentiation in amygdala-PFC neural 
system abnormalities between SZ and BD. These regional 
differences in SZ and BD may give rise to the differences 
in clinical characteristics observed in SZ and BD, and may 
implicate potential avenues for differentiating the 2 disor-
ders during early stages of illness. </p>

<p>Key words: schizophrenia/bipolar disorder/resting 
state/functional connectivity/amygdala/prefrontal cortex </p>

<p>Schizophrenia (SZ) and bipolar disorder (BD) have long 
been viewed as separate neuropsychiatric disorders; how-
ever, the distinctiveness of these 2 disorders from each other 
has also long been questioned. SZ and BD have shared 
symptomatology, and neurocognitive deficits persist in 
affected individuals in both disorders. 
1 Additionally, SZ 
and BD share similar susceptibility genes 
2 and frequently 
co-occur within families. 
3 While the debate regarding the 
distinctions between SZ and BD continues, understanding 
of the neural basis for the shared and disparate features 
of the 2 disorders remains limited. Recently, convergent 
evidence suggests disruptions within the frontotemporal 
neural systems that subserve emotional and cognitive pro-
cessing in both SZ and BD, including abnormalities in 2 
regions with critical roles in this system, the amygdala and 
prefrontal cortex (PFC). </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>While it appears that the amygdala and PFC are shared 
regions for abnormalities in SZ and BD, the manifestation 
of abnormalities within these regions may differ between 
the 2 disorders. Postmortem histological studies provide 
preliminary evidence of reduced amygdala volumes and 
alterations in gene expression in the amygdala in SZ. </p>

<p>6,7 </p>

<p>Reduced amygdala volumes in SZ have been confirmed 
by several magnetic resonance image (MRI) studies and 
recent meta-analysis studies. 
8,9 Postmortem histological 
studies have also demonstrated abnormalities in the 
amygdala in BD. These studies have shown decreased 
glial density and neuron somal size in the amygdala in 
BD. 
7,10 However, while decreased amygdala volume is 
one of the most consistent neuroimaging findings in 
pediatric BD, 
11 findings of abnormalities in amygdala 
volume in adult BD, although frequently reported, are 
inconsistent. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>470 </p>

<p>H. Liu et al </p>

<p>With respect to the PFC, previous studies have found 
differences in frontal activation between SZ and BD using 
task-related functional MRI. 
13,14 Moreover, other stud-
ies have found decreased activation in the dorsal PFC in 
SZ, 
15,16 whereas studies using similar methods have found 
altered activation in the ventral PFC (VPFC) in BD. </p>

<p>17,18 </p>

<p>In this article, the dorsal PFC is defined as including the 
dorsal lateral PFC (DLPFC) and dorsal anterior cingu-
late cortex (ACC), and the VPFC is defined as including 
the orbitofrontal cortex (OFC), the inferior and rostral 
frontal cortices, ventral and rostral components of the 
ACC. These contrasting PFC described above are of con-
siderable interest as the dorsal PFC has been associated 
with working memory impairment, a core cognitive pro-
cess abnormality in SZ. 
19 Whereas the VPFC has been 
associated with hedonic processes 
20 linked to the core 
psychopathology of BD. 
The regional differences between SZ and BD observed 
in the PFC (dorsal vs ventral) suggest that differences 
between the 2 disorders may also exist in the connec-
tivity between the PFC and regions such as the amyg-
dala. The amygdala has multiple reciprocal channels of 
communication with the dorsal PFC through the hip-
pocampus, 
21 and it is highly interconnected with the 
VPFC. 
22 The cingulum and uncinate fasciculus provide 
substantial connections between the amygdala and the 
dorsal and ventral PFC. 
23-25 Additionally, the amygdala 
is a complex structure comprised of multiple nuclei with 
varied function and roles. Differences in human resting-
state FC (rsFC) patterns of the laterobasal (LB), centro-
medial (CM), and superficial (SF) amygdala have been 
previously reported in a recent resting-state fMRI study 
in healthy control (HC) individuals. 
26 Moreover, the SF 
amygdala has been particularly implicated in emotional 
processing, for which differences between SZ and BD 
have been demonstrated. </p>

<p>27,28 </p>

<p>In recent years, rsFC has been successfully applied for 
mapping complex neural circuits. Coherent spontaneous 
blood oxygen level-dependent (BOLD) activity during 
rest among specific subsets of brain regions is thought 
to reflect the natural organization of brain networks and 
may have significant implications regarding the patho-
physiology of psychiatric disorders. We are not aware of 
any studies directly comparing SZ and BD with regards 
to rsFC between the amygdala and PFC. 
In this study, we utilized a region-of-interest (ROI)-
based approach to examine rsFC in individuals with SZ 
and BD, and HC participants. We selected the amygdala 
as the ROI and focused on its rsFC with the PFC. Given 
the differences in function and rsFC within the amyg-
dala, we examined the amygdala as 3 subregions, the 
LB, CM, and SF amygdala, to explore rsFC differences 
between these subregions and the PFC in the 3 groups 
(SZ, BC, and HC). Subdivision of the amygdala in this 
study was based on known differences in functional roles 
and connections with other brain regions and a recently </p>

<p>developed stereotaxic, cytoarchitectonic maps. 
29 We 
hypothesized that both the SZ and BD groups would 
show altered rsFC between the amygdala and PFC when 
compared with the HC group; furthermore, we hypoth-
esized that, in direct comparison between the SZ and BD 
groups, altered rsFC between the amygdala and dorsal 
PFC would be more prominent in SZ, whereas it would 
be more prominent with the VPFC in BD. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Participants </p>

<p>Eighteen SZ participants (mean age 33.5 ± SD 11.2 years, 
10 females) and 18 BD participants (mean age 33.0 ± SD 
10.0 years, 9 females) were recruited from the outpatient 
clinics at the Department of Psychiatry, First Affiliated 
Hospital of China Medical University, Shengyang 
China. All participants were independently diagnosed 
by 2 trained psychiatrists using the Structured Clinical 
Interview for Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of 
Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition (DSM-IV) and ful-
filled DSM-IV criteria for SZ or BD. Symptom measures 
consisted of the Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS) in 
the SZ group and the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale 
(HDRS) and Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS) in the 
BD group. No participants with SZ or BD had another 
DSM-IV Axis I disorder. 
Eighteen HC participants (mean age 36.6 ± SD 12.0 
years, 12 females) were recruited from the community of 
Shenyang. The absence of DSM-IV Axis I disorders in 
the HC participants was confirmed using the Structured 
Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Disorders. The HC par-
ticipants did not have any first-degree relatives with a 
DSM-IV Axis I disorder. 
All participants were right handed and scanned within 
24 hours of initial contact. Detailed demographic and 
clinical data of participants are presented in table 1. For 
all participant groups, individuals were excluded if any 
of the following were present: (1) any MRI contraindica-
tions; (2) history of head trauma with loss of conscious-
ness 5 or more minutes or any neurological disorder; and 
(3) any concomitant major medical disorder. All partici-
pants provided written informed consent after detailed 
description of the study. The study was approved by the 
Institutional Review Board of China Medical University. </p>

<p>Data Acquisition and Image Preprocessing </p>

<p>Data were acquired on a GE Signa HDX 3.0T MRI 
scanner. A standard head coil was used with foam padding 
to reduce head motion. Participants were instructed to 
rest with their eyes closed during scanning. No participant 
reported falling asleep during the scan when routinely 
asked immediately after scanning. FMRI data were 
collected using a gradient-echo planar imaging sequence 
sensitive to BOLD contrast (TR = 2000ms, TE = 30ms, </p>



<p>Diverse Amygdala-Frontal Connectivity in Schizophrenia and Bipolar Disorder </p>

<p>flip angle = 90°, FOV = 24 × 24cm, matrix = 64 × 64). 
Thirty-five axial slices were collected with 3-mm thickness 
without gap. For spatial normalization and localization, 
a 3-dimensional fast spoiled gradient-echo T1-weighted 
sequence was used to acquire high-resolution structural 
images (TR = 7.1ms, TE = 3.2ms, FOV = 24 × 24cm, 
matrix = 240 × 240, slice thickness = 1.0mm without gap, 
176 slices, 1 averages). Image preprocessing was carried 
out using SPM5 (http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm) and 
Resting-State fMRI Data Analysis Toolkit (REST) (http:// 
www.restfmri.net). Preprocessing using SPM5 consisted 
of slice-time correction, motion correction, spatial 
normalization, and spatial smoothing full width at half 
maximum (FWHM = 6mm). Movement parameters were 
examined for each participant. Data sets with more than 
2mm maximum translation in x, y or z, or 2° of maximum 
rotation about 3 axes between each image were excluded. 
Preprocessing using REST consisted of removing linear 
drift through linear regression and temporal band-pass 
filtering (0.01-0.08 Hz) to reduce the effects of low-
frequency drifts and physiological high-frequency noise. </p>

<p>Definition of ROIs </p>

<p>Amygdala ROIs were determined using stereotaxic, 
probabilistic maps of cytoarchitectonic boundaries. 
29 The 
amygdala was divided into 3 subregions: The LB amyg-
dala included the lateral, basolateral, basomedial, and 
paralaminar nuclei. The CM amygdala consisted of the 
central and medial nuclei. The SF amygdala included the 
anterior amygdaloid area, the amygdalopyriform tran-
sition area, the amygdaloid-hippocampal area, and the 
ventral and posterior cortical nuclei. The amygdala ROIs 
were created in standard space and based on voxels with 
at least 50% probability of belonging to the subregion of 
interest. Each voxel was assigned to only 1 subregion. For 
each ROI, the BOLD time series of the voxels within the </p>

<p>ROI were averaged to generate the reference time series 
for the ROI. 
A PFC mask was created using the normalized 
T1-weighted high-resolution images of all participants, 
which were stripped using <rs id="software-1" type="software">BrainSuite2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://brainsuite. usc.edu</rs>). The PFC mask included Brodmann areas (BA) 
9-12, 24, 25, 32, and 44-47. Only voxels within this mask 
were further analyzed. </p>

<p>FC and Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>For each participant, a generalized linear model (GLM) 
was created using time-series predictors for each of the 
3 amygdala subregions and 9 nuisance covariates (time-
series predictors for global signal, white matter, cerebro-
spinal fluid, and 6 motion parameters). The global signal is 
thought to reflect a combination of physiological processes 
(ie cardiac and respiratory fluctuations), and therefore, 
it was included in the GLM to control for such factors. 
Correlation analysis was carried out between the seed 
ROIs and PFC in a voxel-wise manner using REST. The 
correlation coefficients were then transformed to Z-values 
using the Fisher r-to-z transformation. In the first-level 
analysis, a 1-sample t test model was used to delineate 
the functional connectivity of each amygdala ROI. In the 
second-level random effects analysis, direct comparisons 
were conducted to identify differences in functional con-
nectivity between SZ vs HC, BD vs HC, and SZ vs BD. 
Statistical significance was determined by a corrected 
P &lt; .05. Correction for multiple comparisons was made 
by combining individual voxel P &lt; .005 with cluster size 
&gt; 432mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, determined by the Monte Carlo simulation 
(AlphaSim command line in AFNI [analysis of functional 
neuroimaging; Cox, 1996] </p>

<p>53 </p>

<p>). An additional Bonferroni 
correction (P = .005/P = .00056) was used as well, because 
a total of 9 two-sample t tests (SZ vs HC, BD vs HC, and 
SZ vs BD, multiplied by 3 ROIs) were performed. </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and Clinical Data of Participants </p>

<p>Group 
Healthy Controls 
Schizophrenia 
Bipolar Disorder </p>

<p>Number 
18 
18 
18 
Age (years, mean ± SD) 
36.6 ± 12.0 
33.5 ± 11.2 
33.0 ± 10.0 
Sex (male:female) 
6:12 
8:10 
9:9 
BPRS (mean ± SD) 
18.0 ± 0.0 
26.3 ± 6.9 
N/A 
HDRS (mean ± SD) 
2.1 ± 1.6 
N/A 
7.9 ± 8.3 
YMRS (mean ± SD) 
0.1 ± 0.3 
N/A 
7.6 ± 9.9 
Medication 
N/A 
18 
18 
Atypical antipsychotics 
N/A 
18 
9 
Typical antipsychotics 
N/A 
1 
1 
Lithium 
N/A 
0 
5 
Anticonvulsant 
N/A 
0 
6 
Antidepressant 
N/A 
0 
5 </p>

<p>Note: SD, Standard Deviation; BPRS, Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale; HDRS, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale; YMRS, Young Mania 
Rating Scale. </p>

<p>472 </p>

<p>H. Liu et al </p>

<p>Exploratory analyses were performed to examine the 
correlation between the Z-values of regions showing 
significant group differences and symptom rating scores 
(the BPRS in the SZ group, and the HDRS and YMRS 
in the BD group). A 2-tailed P level of .05 was considered 
significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>LB-PFC Connectivity </p>

<p>Compared with the HC group, the SZ group showed sig-
nificant decreases in rsFC between the LB amygdala and 
PFC regions that included right DLPFC (BA 46/9) and 
left middle cingulate cortex (BA32/24) as well as increases 
in rsFC between the LB amygdala and left rostral PFC 
(BA10).The BD group had significant decreases in rsFC 
between the LB amygdala and right ventral ACC (BA24) 
and right middle cingulate cortex (BA32/24) when com-
pared with HC (table 2). 
In direct comparison between the SZ and BD groups, 
the SZ group showed significantly decreased rsFC 
between the LB amygdala and right DLPFC (BA 46/9) 
compared with the BD group (figure 1). In contrast, the 
BD group showed significantly decreased rsFC between 
the LB amygdala and pregenual ACC (BA 24) and rostral 
PFC (BA 10) compared with the SZ group (table 2; 
figure 1). These findings correspond to a corrected P &lt; 
.05 by AlphaSim correction. </p>

<p>CM-PFC Connectivity </p>

<p>Compared with the HC group, significant decreases in 
rsFC were observed between the CM amygdala and PFC 
regions that included right DLPFC (BA46/10/9) and left 
middle cingulate cortex (BA32/24) in the SZ group, while 
the BD group showed significant decrease in rsFC with 
right ventral ACC (BA24), left pregenual ACC (BA24), 
and bilateral rostral PFC (BA10) (table 2). 
In direct comparison between the SZ and BD groups, 
the SZ group showed significantly decreased rsFC 
between the CM amygdala and right DLPFC (BA 46/9) 
compared with the BD group (table 2; figure 2). These 
findings correspond to a corrected P &lt; .05 by AlphaSim 
correction. </p>

<p>SF-PFC Connectivity </p>

<p>Compared with the HC group, the SZ group had sig-
nificant decreases in rsFC between the SF amygdala and 
PFC regions that included left middle cingulate cortex 
(BA32/24) and bilateral DLPFC (BA46/9) as well as 
increases in rsFC between the SF amygdala and PFC 
regions that included left rostral PFC (BA10) and left 
DLPFC (BA9). When compared with HC, the BD group 
had significant decreases in rsFC with left ventral ACC 
(BA24) and right rostral PFC (BA10) (table 2). </p>

<p>In direct comparison between the SZ and BD groups, 
the SZ group showed significantly decreased FC between 
the SF amygdala and right DLPFC (BA 46/9) and left 
DLPFC (BA 46/9) compared with the BD group (fig-
ure 3). In contrast, the BD group showed significantly 
decreased rsFC between the SF amygdala and pregenual/ 
ventral ACC, rostral PFC (BA 24/25/32/10), and right 
OFC (BA 47), and left OFC (BA 47) with extension into 
the temporopolar area (BA 38) compared with the SZ 
group (table 2; figure 3). These findings correspond to a 
corrected P &lt; .05 by AlphaSim correction. Findings also 
survived Bonferroni correction for multiple t tests (P = 
.00056) except for those in the right ventral ACC-CM 
amygdala rsFC and left ventral ACC-SF amygdala rsFC 
in HC vs BD, right DLPFC-SF amygdala rsFC in HC vs 
SZ, and left pregenual ACC and rostral PFC-LB amyg-
dala rsFC in SZ vs BD (table 2). 
Exploratory analyses did not reveal significant correla-
tions between rsFC in regions showing significant group 
differences and symptom rating scores in both the SZ and 
BD groups. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we found significant differences in amyg-
dala-PFC rsFC between SZ and BD, when compared with 
HC and each other. Compared with the HC group, the 
SZ group showed significantly decreased rsFC between 
the 3 amygdala subregions and PFC regions, includ-
ing the middle cingulate cortex and DLPFC as well as 
increased rsFC between the 3 amygdala subregions and 
the rostral PFC and DLPFC; the BD group showed sig-
nificantly decreased rsFC between the 3 amygdala subre-
gions and PFC regions, including the rostral PFC, middle 
cingulate cortex, pregenual and ventral ACC. Moreover, 
when the SZ and BD groups were directly compared, 
distinct patterns in amygdala-PFC rsFC were observed 
in SZ and BD, particularly in the SF amygdala. The 
SZ group showed significantly decreased rsFC between 
the amygdala and the DLPFC compared with the BD 
group; whereas the BD group demonstrated significantly 
decreased rsFC between the amygdala and the VPFC, 
including the pregenual and ventral ACC and OFC, com-
pared with the SZ group. These results strongly suggest 
dorsal vs ventral PFC differentiation in neural abnor-
malities between SZ and BD. Differences were greatest in 
the SF amygdala. This region may be key for distinguish-
ing BD and SZ abnormalities within the frontotemporal 
neural system. The specific mechanisms underlying the 
decreases or increases in rsFC in SZ and BD are unclear. 
Altered rsFC may indicate abnormalities such as altered 
structural white connection or altered regulation of activ-
ity between structures. Future studies of the mechanisms 
underlying altered rsFC may better elucidate the patho-
physiology of SZ and BD, as well as implicate more effec-
tive treatment and new targets for treatment. </p>



<p>Diverse Amygdala-Frontal Connectivity in Schizophrenia and Bipolar Disorder </p>

<p>Table 2. Brain Regions Showing Significant Changes in Laterobasal, Centromedial, and Superficial Amygdala Functional Connectivity </p>

<p>Cortical Regions (Brodmann Areas) 
Cluster Size </p>

<p>MNI Coordinates </p>

<p>T Values </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>X 
Y 
Z </p>

<p>Laterobasal amygdala 
HC vs SZ 
Left rostral prefrontal cortex (10) 
93 
−12 
66 
12 
5.34 
Right dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (46/9) 
64 
36 
48 
27 
−4.45 
Left middle cingulate cortex (32/24) 
203 
−6 
15 
36 
−5.50 
HC vs BD 
Right ventral anterior cingulate cortex (24) 
21 
3 
39 
−3 
−4.11 
Right middle cingulate cortex (32/24) 
45 
3 
12 
39 
−3.81 
SZ vs BD 
Right dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (46/9) 
45 
36 
48 
27 
−3.99 
Left pregenual anterior cingulate cortex (24) and rostral 
prefrontal cortex (10) </p>

<p>34 
−12 
54 
6 
3.70 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Centromedial amygdala 
HC vs SZ 
Right dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (46/10/9) 
60 
39 
51 
12 
−4.04 
Left middle cingulate cortex (32/24) 
69 
−3 
18 
39 
−4.53 
HC vs BD 
Right ventral anterior cingulate cortex (24) 
24 
6 
18 
−6 
−3.70 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Left pregenual anterior cingulate cortex (24) 
67 
−12 
42 
3 
−5.11 
Right rostral prefrontal cortex (10) 
27 
15 
54 
3 
−3.88 
Bilateral rostral prefrontal cortex (10) 
16 
0 
66 
6 
−4.26 
SZ vs BD 
Right dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (46/9) 
115 
45 
42 
24 
−4.13 
Superficial amygdala 
HC vs SZ 
Left rostral prefrontal cortex (10) 
44 
−9 
66 
15 
5.29 
Left dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (46/9) 
18 
−36 
51 
18 
−4.21 
Left middle cingulate cortex (32/24) 
132 
−3 
18 
36 
−4.71 
Right dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (46/9) 
49 
36 
48 
27 
−3.76 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Left dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (9) 
19 
−33 
9 
39 
3.83 
HC vs BD 
Left ventral anterior cingulate cortex (24) 
35 
−9 
42 
3 
−3.77 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Right rostral prefrontal cortex (10) 
20 
3 
60 
18 
−3.98 
SZ vs BD 
Right dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (46/9) 
182 
36 
42 
36 
−4.68 
Left dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex (46/9) 
161 
−36 
33 
26 
−5.92 
Left pregenual/ventral anterior cingulate cortex (24) 
and rostral prefrontal cortex (24/25/32/10) </p>

<p>237 
−12 
54 
6 
4.26 </p>

<p>Right orbitofrontal cortex (47) 
31 
42 
27 
−12 
5.31 
Left orbitofrontal cortex (47) 
38 
−39 
21 
−21 
4.15 </p>

<p>Note: Negative or positive T values represent the regions showing decreased or increased connectivity in the SZ (BD) group, compared 
with the HC group or in the SZ group, compared with the BD group. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>These findings correspond to a corrected P &lt; .05 by AlphaSim correction. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Clusters that did not survive Bonferroni correction. </p>

<p>Our findings are consistent with previous reports in 
the literature, indicating that frontal abnormalities in SZ 
are more common in SZ, whereas those in BD are more 
ventral. Decreased DLPFC volumes have been more con-
sistently reported in SZ than BD. 
30,31 Altered susceptibil-
ity gene expression and decreased dendritic spine density 
and neuronal number and size have been implicated in 
the DLPFC in SZ as well. 
32,33 The DLPFC is critically 
involved in working memory and plays key roles in several 
higher-order cognitive and executive functions, 
34 most 
importantly in the integration of emotional and cognitive </p>

<p>processing. 
35 Our finding of SZ amygdala-DLPFC func-
tional dysconnectivity is particularly interesting, given 
a recent study that compared volumetric correlational 
patterns in several areas including PFC and amygdala. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>This study, which employed structural equation model-
ing, compared SZ patients to HC and demonstrated the 
relative absence of DLPFC-amygdala connections in SZ 
compared with HC, thus implicating altered structural 
connectivity between the DLPFC and amygdala in SZ. 
Postmortem histopathological studies have reported 
trait abnormalities in the VPFC in BD. Decreased glial </p>



<p>H. Liu et al </p>

<p>and neuronal densities in the VPFC have been shown in 
BD. 
37,38 FMRI studies have also reported the co-occur-
rence of diminished VPFC and excessive amygdala 
response to emotional stimuli in BD, 
39 implicating disrup-
tions in the VPFC-amygdala connections that subserve 
affective regulation in the disorder. In support of this, a 
recent resting-state fMRI study identified a negative cor-
relation in VPFC-amygdala activity in HC and BD with 
the magnitude of the correlation greater in HC than BD, </p>

<p>suggesting impaired inhibitory control of the VPFC over 
the amygdala in BD. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>The greatest rsFC difference between SZ and BD 
was observed between the SF amygdala and PFC. The 
SZ group demonstrated significantly decreased rsFC 
between the SF amygdala and the DLPFC, compared 
with the BD group; while the BD group showed sig-
nificantly decreased rsFC between the SF amygdala 
and VPFC regions, including the pregenual and ventral </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Functional connectivity between the laterobasal amygdala and dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex in direct comparison between SZ and 
BD groups. (a) Functional connectivity between the laterobasal amygdala and pregenual anterior cingulate cortex and rostral prefrontal 
cortex in direct comparison between SZ and BD groups. (b) Error bars represent standard deviation of Z-values at the peak voxel. 
SZ, schizophrenia; BD, bipolar disorder; L, left side; R, right side. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Functional connectivity between the centromedial amygdala and dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex in the direct comparison between 
the SZ and BD groups. Error bars represent standard deviation of Z-values at the peak voxel. 
SZ, schizophrenia; BD, bipolar disorder; L, left side; R, right side. </p>



<p>Diverse Amygdala-Frontal Connectivity in Schizophrenia and Bipolar Disorder </p>

<p>ACC and OFC, relative to the SZ group. The SF amyg-
dala lies adjacent to the LB subregion and consists of 
the anterior amygdala area and ventral and posterior 
cortical nuclei involved in olfactory and affective pro-
cesses. It appears to be the most conserved amygdala 
subregion and is thought to play important roles in 
social communication. 
41 Findings from animal studies 
have led to hypotheses that the function of the SF amyg-
dala expanded as social behaviors became increasingly 
complex during evolution. 
41 While in lower nonprimates 
the SF amygdala appears involved in intraspecies com-
munication through olfactory stimuli, human studies 
have indicated that the amygdala contains populations 
of cells that respond to faces, particularly facial emo-
tion, with the most robust responses to dynamic facial 
emotion localized to the SF amygdala. 
41 Deficits in 
emotional processing and affect perception have been 
increasingly apparent in both SZ and BD. 
42,43 Future 
studies of the SF amygdala in SZ and BD may provide 
greater insight into the pathophysiology of both dis-
orders. They may also implicate potential markers for 
differentiation between the disorders, particularly given 
our observed regional differences in FC of the SF amyg-
dala with the PFC between SZ and BD. </p>

<p>Interestingly, both the SZ and BD groups exhibited 
decreased rsFC between the middle cingulate cortex and 
amygdala in this study. The middle cingulate cortex area 
is the midsection of the cingulate gyrus in its anterior-
posterior axis and appears involved in motor control and 
cognitive tasks such as response selection, error detection 
and competition monitoring, and working memory. </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>Previous studies have consistently reported aberrant 
motor control in SZ and BD, 
45-48 and deficits in cogni-
tive functions including response inhibition, attention, 
and working memory have been shown in SZ and BD. </p>

<p>49,50 </p>

<p>Future studies are warranted to examine the role of the 
middle cingulate in these motor and cognitive functions 
in SZ and BD. 
Limitations in this study include relatively small 
sample sizes, cross-sectional comparison, medication 
use, and brief clinical characterization of SZ and BD 
participants. All SZ participants and approximately 
50% of the BD participants were taking atypical anti-
psychotics at the time of the study. We did not examine 
the effects of atypical antipsychotics on rsFC in this 
study. Our findings may in part be attributed to treat-
ment differences. Prior studies suggest that atypical 
antipsychotics may influence resting-state functional </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Functional connectivity between the superficial amygdala and dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex in direct comparison between 
SZ and BD groups. (a) Top panel: right dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex; bottom panel: left dorsal lateral prefrontal cortex. Functional 
connectivity between the superficial amygdala and pregenual/ventral anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) and rostral prefrontal cortex 
and orbitofrontal cortex in direct comparison between the SZ and BD groups. (b) Top panel: right orbitofrontal cortex; middle panel: 
pregenual/ventral ACC and rostral prefrontal cortex; bottom panel: left orbitofrontal cortex. Error bars represent standard deviation of 
Z-values at the peak voxel. 
SZ, schizophrenia; BD, bipolar disorder; L, left side; R, right side. </p>



<p>H. Liu et al </p>

<p>connectivity; however, there are some ambiguities in 
such findings. For example, decreased functional con-
nectivity has been observed in first-episode SZ patients 
after short-term treatment with atypical antipsychot-
ics. 
51 In pediatric BD patients, increased functional 
connectivity has been shown in an evaluative affec-
tive circuit, while decreased functional connectivity 
was seen in a reactive affective circuit after risperi-
done treatment. 
52 Future studies in medication naïve 
patients or with specific focus on atypical antipsychot-
ics are needed to clarify these issues. Our findings may 
also reflect differences in symptoms and symptom 
severity between SZ and BD. Correlation analyses did 
not reveal significant relationships between rsFC and 
symptom measures in SZ and BD. In this study, a lim-
ited number of symptom measures were used, and the 
same symptom measures were not performed across all 
groups. The BPRS was assessed only in the SZ group, 
and the HDRS and YMRS was assessed only in the BD 
group. Future studies should include more comprehen-
sive symptom measurements and use of the same mea-
surements across all groups to enhance understanding 
of the relationship between symptom severity and 
functional connectivity as well as state vs trait-related 
abnormalities in SZ and BD. The majority of SZ and 
BD participants in this study were in remitted states, 
and thus our findings more likely reflect trait-related 
differences between SZ and BD. 
In summary, we performed a resting-state fMRI study 
to examine the rsFC between the amygdala, divided into 
3 subregions, and the PFC in SZ, BD, and HC, with 
comparison of SZ and BD to HC and each other. The 
results of this study support our a prior hypothesis that 
although SZ and BD both have abnormalities within 
the frontotemporal neural systems, abnormalities within 
these circuits between the DLPFC and amygdala are 
more prominent in SZ, whereas those between the VPFC 
and amygdala predominate in BD. Moreover, the SF 
amygdala was observed to be a specific region that may 
potentially differentiate SZ and BD. Further studies of 
the amygdala-PFC connectivity may highlight potential 
avenues to further understand the neural basis for differ-
ences between the 2 disorders. Such insight could have 
important implications for early diagnosis and interven-
tion for these disorders. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>National Natural Science Foundation of China 
(81071099 and 81271499 to Y.T.), the Liaoning Science 
and Technology Foundation (2008225010-14 to Y.T.), the 
National Institution of Health (K01MH086621 to F.W.), 
the National Alliance for Research on Schizophrenia 
and Depression (F.W.) and the Klingenstein Foundation 
(F.W.). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors have declared that there are no conflicts of 
interest in relation to the subject of this study. </p>







</text></tei>