<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3049292" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Objectives: To assess the iron status among European adolescents through selected biochemical parameters in a 
cross-sectional study performed in 10 European cities. 
Subjects/Methods: Iron status was defined utilising biochemical indicators. Iron depletion was defined as low serum ferritin 
(SFo15 mg/l). Iron deficiency (ID) was defined as high-soluble transferrin receptor (sTfR48.5 mg/l) plus iron depletion. Iron 
deficiency anaemia (IDA) was defined as ID with haemoglobin (Hb) below the WHO cutoff for age and sex: 12.0 g/dl for girls 
and for boys aged 12.5-14.99 years and 13.0 g/dl for boys aged X15 years. Enzyme linked immunosorbent assay was used as 
analytical method for SF, sTfR and C-reactive protein (CRP). Subjects with indication of inflammation (CRP 45 mg/l) were 
excluded from the analyses. A total of 940 adolescents aged 12.5-17.49 years (438 boys and 502 girls) were involved. 
Results: The percentage of iron depletion was 17.6%, significantly higher in girls (21.0%) compared with boys (13.8%). 
The overall percentage of ID and IDA was 4.7 and 1.3%, respectively, with no significant differences between boys and girls. 
A correlation was observed between log (SF) and Hb (r ¼ 0.36, Po0.01), and between log (sTfR) and mean corpuscular 
haemoglobin (r ¼ À0.30, Po0.01). Iron body stores were estimated on the basis of log (sTfR/SF). A higher percentage of 
negative values of body iron was recorded in girls (16.5%) with respect to boys (8.3%), and body iron values tended to increase 
with age in boys, whereas the values remained stable in girls. 
Conclusions: To ensure adequate iron stores, specific attention should be given to girls at European level to ensure that their 
dietary intake of iron is adequate. </p>

<p>Iron Deficiency (ID) continues to be one of the most 
prevalent nutritional deficiencies in the world, particularly 
in developing countries (World Health Organization (WHO), 
2003). WHO estimated that ID occurs in about 66-80% of </p>

<p>Received 17 January 2010; revised 29 November 2010; accepted 30 
November 2010; published online 19 January 2011 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Dr M Ferrari, Applied Food Science, National Research 
Institute on Food and Nutrition, Via Ardeatina, 546, Rome 00178, Italy. 
E-mail: ferrari@inran.it 
14 See Appendix. </p>

<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition (2011) 65, 340-349 </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 0954-3007/11 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ejcn </p>

<p>the world's population (WHO, 2003). ID has many negative 
effects on health, including changes in immune function, 
cognitive development, temperature regulation, energy 
metabolism and work performance (Dallman, 1986). 
On the other hand, iron is a pro-oxidant and thus a possible 
risk factor for coronary heart disease. However, a recent review 
suggests that there is no strong association between body iron 
stores and coronary heart disease in adults (Zegrean, 2009). 
The diagnosis of ID is based primarily on laboratory 
measurements of biochemical iron indicators. There is no 
full international consensus on the indicators to be used for 
assessing iron status, as each indicator has its own limita-
tions because of either poor sensitivity or specificity, or 
because it is modified by conditions other than ID (Dallman 
et al., 1993). There are three general approaches to assess 
ID in populations. In the first one, used in studies conducted 
by Hallberg et al. (Hallberg et al., 1993) and Amstrong 
(Amstrong, 1989), ID is defined as a low level of serum 
ferritin (SF). In the second one, used in the US in the 
National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 
(NHANES) II and III, the multiple-criteria model is used to 
classify ID; it consists of two or three abnormal values for 
transferrin saturation, SF and erythrocyte protoporphyrin 
(Cogswell et al., 2009). The main limitation of these two 
approaches is that inflammation leads to high ferritin values, 
even though iron stores are low. The third approach 
proposed by WHO (2004) and adopted by Zimmermann 
(2008) is based on the measurements of SF and soluble 
transferrin receptor (sTfR) in combination with C-reactive 
protein (CRP) to eliminate false negative cases in presence of 
inflammation. The third approach was considered more 
appropriate and was therefore used in the present study. It is 
well known that SF concentrations reflect the size of the iron 
stores (Cook, 1999) and that low SF levels identify 'iron depletion' 
(WHO, 2001). On the other hand, the measurement of sTfR 
has been reported to be useful in the diagnosis of 'tissue ID' 
(Skikne et al., 1990) and its values are not influenced by acute 
or chronic inflammatory conditions (Ferguson et al., 1992; 
Olivares et al., 1995). An approach to estimate body iron was 
developed by Cook et al. (Cook et al., 2003) using the 
formula: body iron (mg/kg) ¼ À(log(sTfR/SF)À2.8229)/ 
0.1207 to allow the full range of the iron status of a 
population to be evaluated ,with negative values represent-
ing a deficit of iron with respect to the quantity required to 
maintain a normal haemoglobin (Hb) concentration. 
Adolescents are at risk of ID because of their high iron 
requirements, especially during the growth spurt period 
(Moreno, 2008). In boys, increased muscular growth leads to 
increased demand for iron. In girls, in addition to the fast 
growth, the onset of menstruation leads to iron losses 
(Wharton and Wharton, 1987). As a consequence, ID occurs 
in adolescents also in developed countries, if their additional 
iron needs are not met (Dallman et al., 1996). Some studies 
suggested that ID can have detrimental effects on memory 
and learning processes in preadolescents and adolescents 
(Beard and Connor, 2003). </p>

<p>The data available on iron status in European adolescents, 
are derived from studies utilising different methodologies, 
different indicators of iron status and varying criteria to 
define ID (Hercberg et al., 2001). There was, therefore, a need 
to investigate the situation of ID among European adoles-
cents with a harmonised methodology. 
Within the framework of the HELENA Study (Healthy 
Lifestyle in Europe by Nutrition in Adolescents), funded 
within the 6th EU framework programme, a biochemical 
evaluation of iron status was performed with a cross-
sectional approach. The objective of the present paper is to 
report the iron status of European adolescents. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Study design and sample selection 
A detailed description of HELENA-cross-sectional study 
(HELENA-CSS) in terms of sampling and recruitment 
approaches, standardisation and harmonisation processes, 
data collection, analysis strategies and quality-control activ-
ities has been published elsewhere (Moreno et al., 2008). 
The study was approved by the Research Ethics Committees 
of each country involved according to the Declaration of 
Helsinki and International Conferences on Harmonization 
for Good Clinical Practice. Written informed consent 
was obtained from the parents of the adolescents and the 
adolescents themselves (Béghin et al., 2008). Briefly, subjects 
with an age range of 12.5-17.49 years were recruited in 10 
cities across Europe. Selection of cities was based on two 
criteria: regional distribution and presence of an active 
research group assuring sufficient expertise and resources 
to successfully perform epidemiological studies. Within the 
study, Stockholm (Sweden) represented Northern Europe. 
Athens, Heraklion (Greece), Rome (Italy) and Zaragoza 
(Spain) represented Southern Europe. Pecs (Hungary) repre-
sented Eastern Europe. Ghent (Belgium) and Lille (France) 
represented Western Europe, whereas Dortmund (Germany) 
and Vienna (Austria) represented Central Europe. As the 
overall aim of the HELENA Study was to assess the 
nutritional status of the adolescent population in Europe, 
during the design phase, the variability of a large set of 
nutritional status indices obtained in previous studies was 
checked. Body mass index was the indicator that showed the 
largest variability. Therefore, the sample size was estimated 
according to the mean body mass index and variance values 
for each sex and age strata. This procedure ensured 
to adequately describe all the variables included in the 
study. For the sample size calculation, a confidence level of 
95% and an error of ± 0.3 kg/m 
2 were assumed, leading to a </p>

<p>sample size of 3000 adolescents. More details on the 
procedure are provided by Moreno et al. (2008). 
Blood sampling was performed in one-third of the 
adolescents recruited. Therefore, the total expected 
subsample was 1000 adolescents (100 subjects for each city). 
The size of subsample was chosen, so as to assess the </p>

<p>Iron status in adolescence 
M Ferrari et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>

<p>immunological parameters with sufficient precision. Such 
parameters were those with the highest variability within the 
blood measurements that were included in the study as 
discussed by Moreno et al. (2008). The selection procedure 
for schools and classes including the selection of a subset of 
classes for blood sampling has been applied centrally by one 
partner (Ghent) for all study centres. </p>

<p>Blood sampling and laboratory measures 
The blood sampling procedure and sample logistics have been 
described in detail elsewhere (González-Gross et al., 2008). 
Briefly, fasting blood samples were collected by venipuncture 
at school between 0800 and 1000 hours in the morning. 
Whole-blood samples for the red blood parameters (Hb, red 
blood cell, mean corpuscular volume (MCV), mean corpus-
cular haemoglobin (MCH), mean corpuscular haemoglobin 
concentration and red cell distribution width) were sent 
directly to the local laboratory of each country to be analysed. 
Samples for iron status analyses were clotted at room 
temperature for at least 30 min, followed by centrifuged at 
3500 r.p.m. for 10 min. Serum samples were shipped to the 
central laboratory in Bonn University (IEL, Germany), 
Department of Nutrition and Food Science, to be stored at 
À80 1C before being shipped to Italy in May 2007, within 6 
months of the collection. The aliquots of serum samples were 
analysed in the Human Nutrition Laboratory of the National 
Research Institute on Food and Nutrition (INRAN). SF, sTfR 
and CRP were measured by using an enzyme linked 
immunosorbent assay (Erhardt et al., 2004). A commercially 
available control sample from Bio-Rad Liquichek Immuno-
logy Control Level 3 (Bio-Rad, Milan, Italy) was used to obtain 
a calibration curve on each plate. 
A quality-control serum was produced in house by pooling 
human serum from four healthy volunteers to monitor 
accuracy and precision of the determinations. The coeffi-
cient of variation from 10 replicates of the quality-control 
serum pool was 5.3, 6.4 and 12.4% for SF, sTfR and CRP, 
respectively. Additionally, the interassay coefficient of varia-
tion of the pool samples analysed in a total of 32 different 
analytical runs (four replicates) was 10.8, 14.8 and 23.4% 
for SF, sTfR and CRP, respectively. 
INRAN laboratory is involved in an external quality 
assurance program of CDC Vital-Eqa for SF, sTfR and CRP 
analyses (Haynes et al., 2008). In Spring 2007, the measures 
of iron indicators of this study were within the acceptable 
range, except for CRP that was just below the inferior limit 
(2.42 mg/l versus an acceptable range of 2.70-5.38 mg/l) and 
sTfR that was at the superior limit (7.3 mg/l versus an 
acceptable range of 1.7 and 7.3 mg/l). </p>

<p>Anaemia and iron classification 
Anaemia was defined as Hb concentration below the cutoff 
set by WHO (WHO, 2004), 12.0 g/dl for girls aged 12 years 
and above, and for boys aged 12-14; and 13.0 g/dl for 
boys aged 15 years or above. Abnormal values for iron </p>

<p>indicators were defined as concentration o15 mg/l for low 
SF (WHO, 2004), 4200 mg/l and 4150 mg/l (boys and girls, 
respectively) for high SF (WHO, 2004; severe risk of iron 
overload) and 48.5 mg/l for high sTfR (Cook et al., 1993). 
A participant was considered to have active inflammation, if 
the CRP concentration exceeded 5 mg/l (Woodruff et al., 2006). 
The methodology to classify the iron status is described in 
Table 1. The classification of iron status is considered in 
presence of normal CRP concentration. 
Total body iron was estimated with the use of the 
formula: body iron (mg/kg) ¼ À(log(sTfR/SF)À2.8229)/ 
0.1207 (Cook et al., 2003). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
The Kruskal-Wallis test was used for comparing haematolo-
gical parameters among iron sufficiency, iron depletion and ID. 
The Student's t-test was used to evaluate the significance of 
differences between mean values of iron indicators between 
genders. Pearson correlation was used to test the linear 
relation between haematological variables. The w </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-test was 
used for comparing proportions. Iron status indicators, 
such as sTfR and SF, were transformed to logarithms 
before performing statistical analyses. The results in the 
tables are shown using the original units without any log 
transformation. 
As already performed by Ortega et al. (Ortega et al., 2010), 
all the analyses conducted on the HELENA data were 
adjusted by a weighing factor to balance the sample 
according to the age and sex distribution of the theoretical 
sample to guarantee representation of each of the stratified 
groups. The counts of subjects (n) are reported in the tables 
as unweighted values. All the statistical analyses were 
performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistical software package for 
Microsoft Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 12.00</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Iron indicators and iron status 
The HELENA-CSS consists of 1089 adolescent subjects with 
blood measurements. A total of 102 subjects were excluded </p>

<p>Table 1 Iron status 
a as defined in the present paper </p>

<p>Classification 
Values of iron indicators </p>

<p>SF (mg/l) 
sTfR (mg/l) </p>

<p>Iron sufficiency </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>X15 
p8.5 
Iron depletion </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>o15 
p8.5 
ID </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>o15 
48.5 
IDA 
o15 
48.5 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CRP, C-reactive protein; ID, iron deficiency; IDA, iron deficiency 
with anaemia; SF, serum ferritin; sTfR, soluble transferrin receptor. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Iron status is considered in the presence of CRPo5 mg/l. 
b With or without anaemia. 
c Without ID and with or without anaemia. </p>

<p>Iron status in adolescence 
M Ferrari et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>

<p>because at least one of the iron indicators (SF, n ¼ 80; 
sTfR, n ¼ 84) or Hb (n ¼ 16) was missing. The final 
sample of 987 adolescents included 465 boys and 522 girls, 
that is, 90.7% of the adolescents who participated in the 
blood sampling. 
A total of 47 subjects had high levels of CRP (27 boys and 
20 girls) and were excluded. Therefore, the present study of 
iron status was performed on a total of 940 adolescents 
(438 boys and 502 girls), with no indication of the presence 
of inflammation. 
The mean age (standard deviation) of adolescents was 14.7 
(1.2) years both in boys and in girls, and the mean body mass 
index was 21.2 (3.8) and 21.1 (3.3) kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, respectively, for 
boys and girls. The reported age of menarche in the present 
study ranged from 9 to 16 years of age. A total of 58 (12%) 
girls reported not to have experienced menarche at the time 
of the study. In all, 39 and 43% of the boys and girls, 
respectively, declared to have smoked cigarettes at least once. 
Mean, median and percentiles (25-75th) values of red blood 
parameters, SF and sTfR are summarised in Table 2. Percen-
tage of iron sufficiency, abnormal values of iron indicators, 
anaemia, iron depletion, ID and iron deficiency anaemia 
(IDA) are presented in Table 3. 
In boys, the mean (standard deviation) of Hb was 14.7 (1.2) 
g/dl (14.3 (1.0) g/dl aged 12.5-14.99 years and 15.2 (1.2) g/dl 
aged 15 years or above). In girls it was 13.8 (1.2) g/dl. The mean 
values of SF suggest a gender-related significant difference 
(Po0.05) with a lower mean SF value in girls (27.9 mg/l) than in 
boys (36.6 mg/l). The percentage of low SF values was also 
higher in girls (26.3%) compared with boys (17.9%) (Po0.01) 
(Table 3). No single case of high level of SF was identified 
(SF4200 mg/l for boys and 4150 mg/l for girls), indicating no 
risk of iron overload (WHO, 2004) in the study sample. 
A total of 23 subjects had high values (48.5 mg/l) of sTfR 
(that could have indicated ID) but with normal values 
of SF (indicating no iron depletion), and could therefore not 
be categorised in one of the iron status classifications </p>

<p>(Table 1). They were excluded from the analyses in terms 
of the classification of ID. 
The percentage of iron depletion was 17.6%, significantly 
higher in girls (21.0%) than in boys (13.8%) (Po0.05) 
(Table 3). 
The overall prevalence of anaemia was 4.4% and it ranged 
from 1.1% (Stockholm) to 10.1% (Heraklion) among cities. 
Intermediate prevalences were 1.4% for Zaragoza, 3.2% for 
Pecs, 3.6% for Dortmund, 4.0% for Rome, 4.6% for Ghent, 
5.5% for Lille, 5.6% for Vienna and 5.7% for Athens. The 
overall prevalence of anaemia without ID was 3.1% (4.6% in 
girls and 1.4% in boys) and ranged from 0% (Stockholm and 
Zaragoza) to 7.6% (Heraklion). The second highest 
prevalence was observed in Athens (5.7%). Intermediate </p>

<p>Table 2 Haemoglobin, red blood and iron status parameters in European adolescents </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Parameter 
Boys (n ¼ 438) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Girls (n ¼ 502) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>M 
s.d. 
Me 
25-75th percentiles 
M 
s.d. 
Me 
25-75th percentiles </p>

<p>Hb 
g/dl 
14.7 
1.2 
14.7 
14.0-15.6 
13.8 
1.2 
13.4 
12.8-14.1 
RBC 
10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>/l 
5.2 
0.4 
5.1 
4.9-5.4 
4.7 
0.4 
4.7 
4.5-4.9 
MCV 
fl 
83.6 
4.6 
84.0 
81.5-86.2 
84.9 
5.1 
85.5 
82.4-88.2 
MCH 
pg 
28.6 
1.9 
28.8 
27.7-29.8 
28.6 
2.1 
29.0 
29.0-30.0 
MCHC 
g/dl 
34.3 
1.0 
34.2 
33.6-34.9 
33.7 
1.0 
33.7 
33.7-34.3 
RDW 
% 
12.9 
0.9 
12.9 
12.5-13.3 
12.9 
1.1 
12.8 
12.8-13.4 
SF 
mg/l 
36.6* 
23.9 
32.0 
17.9-49.3 
27.9 
19.7 
24.1 
24.1-38.0 
STfR 
mg/l 
5.9 
1.9 
5.8 
4.6-7.0 
6.0 
3.3 
5.7 
5.7-7.0 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Hb, haemoglobin; M, mean; Me, median; MCH, mean corpuscular haemoglobin; MCHC, mean corpuscular haemoglobin concentration; 
MCV, mean corpuscular volume; RBC, red blood cells; RDW, red cell distribution width; SF, serum ferritin; sTfR, soluble transferrin receptor. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>All data were adjusted by a weighing factor to balance the sample according to the theoretical age distribution of the European adolescent population. 
b The count of subjects (n) are reported in the table as unweighted values. 
The data are presented as M, s.d., Me and 25th and 75th percentiles 
*Po0.05 statistically significant difference between mean values in boys and girls. </p>

<p>Table 3 Proportion of European adolescents having anaemia, abnormal 
values of iron indicators, iron sufficiency, iron depletion, ID and IDA </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Iron status </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Total (n ¼ 940) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Boys (n ¼ 438) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Girls (n ¼ 502) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>n 
% 
n 
% 
n 
% </p>

<p>Low SF 
210 
22.4 
78 
17.9** 
132 
26.3 
High sTfR 
66 
7.0 
30 
6.9 
36 
7.2 
Anaemia 
41 
4.4 
8 
1.8** 
33 
6.6 </p>

<p>Classification </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Iron sufficiency 705 
75.2 
344 
79.3 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>361 
71.7 
Iron depletion 
167 
17.6 
63 
13.8* 
104 
21.0 
ID 
45 
4.7 
18 
3.9 
27 
5.4 
IDA 
11 
1.3 
2 
0.5 
9 
2.0 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ID, iron deficiency; IDA, iron deficiency with anaemia; 
SF, serum ferritin; sTfR, soluble transferrin receptor. 
a All data were adjusted by a weighing factor to balance the sample according 
to the theoretical age distribution of the European adolescent population. 
b The count of subjects (n) are reported in the table as unweighted values. 
c Indicators and cutoff values used to identify abnormal values of iron 
indicators and iron status are reported in Table 1. 
d 23 subjects (13 boys and 10 girls) were excluded because of with high values 
of sTfR and normal values of SF. 
*Po0.05; **Po0.01 statistically significant between girls and boys. </p>

<p>Iron status in adolescence 
M Ferrari et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>

<p>prevalences were 1.8% for Dortmund, 1.9% for Vienna, 3.0% 
for Rome, 3.2% for Pecs, 4.1% for Lille and 4.6% for Ghent. 
Percentage of iron depletion ranged from 9.6% (Zaragoza) to 
23.0% (Pecs). Percentage of ID ranged from 0% (Lille) to 
11.3% (Athens). Percentage of IDA ranged from 0% (Athens, 
Gent, and Pecs) to 2.8 % (Vienna). 
Among adolescents with anaemia (n ¼ 40), 27.5% (n ¼ 11) 
were classified as IDA, with abnormal SF and sTfR values, 
whereas 24.3% (n ¼ 10) had abnormal SF values but with 
normal sTfR values (iron depletion without ID) and 47.5% 
(n ¼ 19) had anaemia without ID, with normal SF and sTfR 
values. 
Log(SF) and log(sTfR) were significantly correlated with 
the red cell parameters (MCV, MCH, mean corpuscular 
haemoglobin concentration and red cell distribution width) 
(Table 4). In the total sample, a significant correlation was 
observed between log(SF) and Hb concentration (r ¼ 0.36, 
Po0.01), and between log(SF) and log(sTfR) (r ¼ 0.33, 
Po0.01). For log(sTfR), a significant correlation was observed 
with log(SF), MCH (r ¼ 0.30, Po0.01) and MCV (r ¼ À0.26, </p>

<p>Po0.01) No significant correlation was observed between red 
blood cell and iron indicators (log(SF) and log(sTfR); r ¼ 0.13 
and r ¼ 0.07, respectively). 
The mean of red cell parameters in the different classifica-
tion of iron status is reported in Table 5. Statistically 
significant differences between iron sufficiency, iron 
depletion and ID were observed for red cell parameters for 
boys and girls. There were significant differences (Po0.001) 
for Hb, MCV, MCH, mean corpuscular haemoglobin 
concentration and red cell distribution width between 
iron sufficiency group and the iron depletion and ID 
groups. No significant difference was observed between 
iron sufficiency group and ID group for any of the red cell 
parameters considered. </p>

<p>Estimation of body iron 
Body iron was calculated according to the formula of Cook 
et al. (Cook et al., 2003), and the cumulative percentage 
distributions by gender are shown in Figure 1. Mean </p>

<p>Table 4 Pearson correlation coefficients and significance of correlations (P) between iron parameters 
a (n ¼ 940) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Hb 
RBC 
MCV 
MCH 
MCHC 
RDW 
Log(SF) 
Log(sTfR) </p>

<p>Boys 
Log(SF) 
0.25** 
0.11* 
0.17** 
0.19** 
0.10** 
À0.14** 
-
À0.25** 
Log(sTfR) 
0.16** 
0.07 
À0.16** 
À0.22** 
À0.20** 
0.09** 
À0.25** 
-</p>

<p>Girls 
Log(SF) 
0.35** 
0.004* 
0.34** 
0.41** 
0.40** 
À0.42** 
-
À0.39** 
Log(sTfR) 
0.21** 
0.11 
À0.32** 
À0.35** 
À0.29** 
0.35** 
À0.39** 
-</p>

<p>Total 
Log(SF) 
0.36** 
0.13 
0.24** 
0.32** 
0.32** 
À0.31** 
-
À0.33** 
Log(sTfR) 
0.16** 
0.07 
À0.26** 
À0.30** 
À0.24** 
0.26** 
À0.33** 
-</p>

<p>Abbreviations: Hb, haemoglobin; MCH, mean corpuscular haemoglobin; MCHC, mean corpuscular haemoglobin concentration; MCV, mean corpuscular volume; 
RBC, red blood cells; RDW, red cell distribution width; SF, serum ferritin; sTfR, soluble transferrin receptor. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>All data were adjusted by a weighing factor to balance the sample according to the theoretical age distribution of the European adolescent population. 
b The count of subjects (n) are reported in the table as unweighted values. 
*Po0.05; **Po0.01 boys versus girls. </p>

<p>Table 5 Haematological characteristics according to iron sufficiency, iron depletion and ID </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Iron sufficiency 
Iron depletion 
ID </p>

<p>Boys 
(n ¼ 344) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Girls 
(n ¼ 361) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Total 
(n ¼ 705) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Boysc 
(n ¼ 63) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Girls 
(n ¼ 104) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Total 
(n ¼ 167) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Boys 
(n ¼ 18) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Girls 
(n ¼ 27) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Total 
(n ¼ 45) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Mean Hb, g/dl (s.d.) 
14.9 (1.2) 
13.6 (0.9) 
14.2 (1.2)* 
14.4 (1.0) 
13.3 (1.6) 
13.7 (1.4) 
13.7 (0.9) 
12.0 (1.4) 
12.7 (1.4) 
Mean RBC, 10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>/l (s.d.) 
5.2 (0.4) 
4.7 (0.3) 
4.9 (0.4) 
5.2 (0.4) 
4.7 (0.5) 
4.8 (0.5) 
5.0 (0.4) 
4.8 (0.3) 
4.8 (0.4) 
Mean MCV, fl (s.d.) 
84.1 (4.4) 
85.7 (4.6) 
84.8 (4.5)* 
82.1 (4.6) 
84.5 (4.5) 
83.4 (4.7) 
82.0 (4.2) 
78.2 (8.0) 
80.1 (6.4) 
Mean MCH, pg (s.d.) 
28.8 (1.8) 
29.0 (1.8) 
28.8 (1.8)* 
28.0 (1.9) 
28.3 (1.8) 
28.3 (1.9) 
27.6 (1.7) 
25.1 (3.5) 
26.3 (2.9) 
Mean MCHC, g/dl (s.d.) 
34.3 (1.0) 
33.8 (0.9) 
34.1 (0.9)* 
34.1 (1.0) 
33.5 (0.9) 
33.7 (1.0) 
33.6 (1.0) 
32.0 (1.8) 
32.8 (1.6) 
Mean RDW, % (s.d.) 
12.9 (0.9) 
12.7 (0.9) 
12.8 (0.9)* 
13.2 (1.0) 
13.2 (1.0) 
13.2 (1.0) 
13.6 (0.9) 
14.6 (2.0) 
14.1 (1.6) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Hb, haemoglobin; ID, iron deficiency; MCH, mean corpuscular haemoglobin; MCHC, mean corpuscular haemoglobin concentration; 
MCV, mean corpuscular volume; RBC, red blood cells; RDW, red cell distribution width. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>All data were adjusted by a weighing factor to balance the sample according to the theoretical age distribution of the European adolescent population. 
b The count of subjects (n) are reported in the table as unweighted values. 
*Po0.001 statistically different between iron sufficiency, iron depletion and ID. </p>

<p>Iron status in adolescence 
M Ferrari et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>

<p>(standard deviation) body iron was significantly higher 
(Po0.001; Student's t-test) in boys (4.4 (3.2) mg/kg) than 
in girls (3.3 (4.1) mg/kg). Girls showed a light shift of 
the body iron distribution curve to the left in comparison 
with boys in which higher positive values were observed. 
The reference line indicates the cutoff point for tissue ID 
(body iron o0 mg/kg). The percentage of negative values was 
significantly higher (Po0.001; w </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) in girls (16.5%) with 
respect to boys (8.3%). 
The distribution of body iron stores by age was also 
examined. Figure 2 shows that the linear relationship 
between the body iron and the age of the adolescents 
is not very strong. The body iron increased slightly with 
age (r ¼ 0.28) but this trend did not reach statistical 
significance. On the other hand, it tended to be stable 
(r ¼ 0.025) in girls. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study is the first report evaluating iron status in 
adolescents across multiple European countries. As discussed 
by Moreno et al. (2008), the selected cities were equivalent 
and comparable between countries but the samples were 
representative for the cities and not for the countries. 
Therefore, the HELENA Study does not allow for statistical 
comparison of differences in iron status between regions. 
However, the prevalence of iron status stages according to 
geographical location of the cities adopted for this study are 
provided underneath for descriptive purpose. 
In the present study, the overall proportion of iron 
depletion was 17.6%; it was significantly higher in girls 
(21.0%) than in boys (13.8%). The prevalence of iron 
depletion by geographical location was: 23% in Eastern 
Europe (Pecs), 19% in Northern Europe (Stockholm), 18% 
in Western Europe (17% in Ghent and 19% in Lille), 17% in 
Central Europe (16% in Dortmund and 19% in Vienna) and 
15% in Southern Europe (14% in Athens, 17% in Heraklion, 
19% in Rome and 10% in Zaragoza). These data are in the 
range of findings from a recent review on iron status in 
European adolescents (Hercberg et al., 2001) where the 
highest prevalence of iron depletion was observed in girls 
in Ireland (43%) and in boys in Denmark (16%), whereas the 
lowest prevalence was observed in girls in Finland (4.7%) and 
in boys in France where no cases were detected. 
For ID, in the present study, there was a tendency for a 
higher percentage in girls (5.4%) with respect to boys (3.9%) 
but the difference was not significant. The percentage of ID 
in girls in our study was slightly lower than the 8.7% 
prevalence observed in girls aged 12-16 years in the US 
(Halterman et al., 2001) but in line with the 6% prevalence 
observed in girls aged 13-19 years in Canada (Deegan et al., 
2005). Both the prevalences observed in our study and in the 
US are below the cutoff established by WHO to determine 
'no prevalence' of ID, that is, 10% (WHO, 2004). Both are </p>

<p>12 
Age (y) </p>

<p>-30 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Body iron (mg/kg) </p>

<p>-30 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Body iron (mg/kg) </p>

<p>Boys 
Girls </p>

<p>8.3% &lt; 0 mg/Kg 
16.5% &lt; 0 mg/Kg </p>

<p>13 14 15 16 17 18 
12 
Age (y) </p>

<p>13 14 15 16 17 18 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Distribution of body iron stores by age in boys and girls in the HELENA Study. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>-20 
20 
Body iron (mg/kg) 
Cunulative percentage </p>

<p>Girls 
Boys </p>

<p>-15 
-10 
-5 
5 
10 
15 
0 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Cumulative percentage distributions of estimated body 
iron in boys and girls from the HELENA Study. Total body iron 
was estimated using the formula: body iron (mg/kg) ¼ À(log(sTfR:-
ferritin ratio)À2.8229)/0.1207 developed by Cook (1999) Positive 
values indicate the presence of storage iron, whereas negative values 
indicate tissue ID. </p>

<p>Iron status in adolescence 
M Ferrari et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>

<p>also far lower than that observed in other parts of the world 
as in Nepal, with an ID prevalence of 56% observed in 
adolescents girls (Woodruff et al., 2006). The slightly lower 
prevalence in our study may, in part, result from a different 
approach to define ID. The impact of ID on the cognitive 
functioning of adolescent girls who are at the highest risk of 
ID requires major clarification. In fact, there is only limited 
evidence that iron supplementation may improve attention, 
concentration and intelligent quotient (Falkingham et al., 
2010). The prevalence of ID by geographical location was: 
6% in both Northern Europe (Stockholm) and Southern 
Europe (11% in Athens, 6% in Heraklion, 3% in Rome and 
Zaragoza) plus Eastern Europe (Pecs), 5% in Central Europe 
(3% in Dortmund and 7% in Vienna) and 2% in Western 
Europe (no cases in Ghent and 4% in Lille). No comparable 
data are available in the literature in relation to ID in 
adolescents in the European context for comparison with 
the results of the present study. 
The percentage of IDA was 1.3% (0.5% in boys and 2.0% in 
girls), with a (non-significantly) higher value in girls. The 
prevalence of IDA by geographical location was: 2% in 
Central Europe (2% in Dortmund and 3% in Vienna), 1% in 
both Northern Europe (Stockholm) and Southern Europe 
(no cases in Athens, 2% in Heraklion, 1% in both Rome and 
Zaragoza), 0.6% in Western Europe (no cases in Ghent and 
1% in Lille) and no cases in Eastern Europe (Pecs). These data 
are similar to the estimates of prevalence in adolescents in 
Canada (Deegan et al., 2005), the United States (Looker et al., 
2002) and Sweden (Samulson et al., 1996), ranging from 
0 to 3%. In the present study, the proportion of anaemia was 
4.4%, consistent with the estimates of the worldwide 
prevalence of anaemia during adolescence: 27% in develop-
ing countries and 6% in developed countries (Kara et al., 
2006). The observed prevalence of anaemia not due to ID 
(3.1%) is probably overestimated because of unavoidable 
misclassifications that are inherent to the definition of 
limits. In fact, the limits set to define anaemia are based 
on 95% reference ranges, and therefore it is assumed that 
2.5% of healthy individuals would be classified as anaemic. 
On the other hand, a proportion of anaemia without ID 
may be originated from genetic Hb disorders, as subjects 
with such disorders were not excluded. In our study, 
the highest prevalence of anaemia without ID among cities 
was observed in two cities of Greece (7.6% in Heraklion and 
6.3% in Athens). Greece is known to be heavily affected by 
haemoglobinopathies (thalassaemia and sickle-cell disease). 
In fact, according to Angastiniotis et al. (1995), the highest 
percentage of carriers of thalassaemia and sickle-cell 
disorders is observed in Greece (9.0%). 
In our study, no single case of iron overload was identified 
through SF, a stored body iron marker. 
Results of the present study on correlations between 
iron status parameters are all plausible. SF and sTfR that 
were chosen in this study as iron indicators showed a 
correlation with red cell parameters. The observed corre-
lation coefficients between log(sTfR) and red cell parameters </p>

<p>(MCV and MCH) are not surprising, as sTfR is a measure of ID 
erytropoiesis (Metzgeroth et al., 2005) as MCV and MCH. The 
present data are in general agreement with the result of a 
previous study showing a correlation between sTfR and red 
cell parameters in iron-deficient adolescents (Choi, 2003). 
These findings are confirmed, as the concentrations of the 
mean of red cell parameters decreased gradually (except for 
red cell distribution width that increased) with increasingly 
negative iron balance, as ID appeared (sTfR 48.5 mg/l) 
(Table 5). The results of the present study document a 
positive correlation between log(SF) level and Hb concentra-
tion (r ¼ 0.39, Po0.01; Table 3) comparable to those 
observed in other studies among children: r ¼ 0.24 (Jeremiah 
et al., 2007) and r ¼ 0.26 (Ayoya et al., 2010). The low 
correlation between these two indicators is because of 
the fact that they are related to differing stages of ID. The 
correlation between the indicators of iron status and red cell 
parameters may be considered as a confirmation of the 
reliability of these indicators (WHO, 2004; Zimmermann, 
2008) in the assessment of iron status in adolescents. 
The correlation of SF with Hb and the higher percentage of 
iron depletion in girls with respect to boys suggest that 
the risk of developing ID anaemia is higher in girls. If iron 
depletion is not corrected, it may indeed progress to ID. In 
addition, the calculated measure of body iron was lower in 
girls than in boys. The distribution of body iron stores by age 
(Figure 2) suggests that in boys, body iron stores may have 
slightly increased during and after their rapid growth 
period, whereas in girls, iron stores remain low during the 
whole pubertal period. One possible explanation for the 
lower iron status in girls, besides growth, is the loss of iron 
with menstruation. In previous studies, it was observed that 
the growth spurt associated with menstrual status, blood loss 
and a low iron intake may have adverse effects on iron stores 
in adolescents girls (Ilich-Ernst et al., 1998). </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Our study confirms SF and sTfR as biochemical indicators 
that could be used in the assessment of iron status in 
adolescents, a problematic group of population, for the 
period of rapid growth. On the basis of WHO guidelines 
(2004) for the interpretation of the iron status data at 
population level, the results indicate that, in the European 
context, ID is not prevalent neither in boys nor in girls, and 
that iron depletion is prevalent in girls but not in boys. 
Adolescent girls therefore constitute a group at risk of ID, 
and specific attention should be given to them during 
adolescence to ensure that their dietary intake of iron is 
adequate to their requirements. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interests. </p>

<p>Iron status in adolescence 
M Ferrari et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We gratefully acknowledge all participating adolescents 
and their parents and teachers for their collaboration. 
We also acknowledge Dr Eugenia Venneria for her contribu-
tion for the enzyme linked immunosorbent assay analyses of 
serum samples. The HELENA Study was supported finan-
cially by the European Community Sixth RTD Framework 
Programme (Contract FOOD-CT-2005-007034). The content 
of this article reflects only the author's view, and the 
European Community is not liable for any use that may be 
made of the information contained therein. </p>





<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>



<p>This work is licensed under the Creative 
Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-No 
Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of 
this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Helena Study group </p>





<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>



<p>Iron status in adolescence 
M Ferrari et al </p>



<p>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition </p>

</text></tei>