<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3467590" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: To determine the effectiveness of a provider-</p>

<p>based intervention to improve medication intensification 
among patients with diabetes. </p>

<p>Design: Effectiveness cluster-randomised trial. Baseline </p>

<p>and follow-up cross-sections of diabetes physicians' 
patients. </p>

<p>Setting: Eleven U.S. Southeastern states, 2006-2008. 
Participants: 205 Rural primary care physicians, </p>

<p>95 completed the study. </p>

<p>Intervention: Multicomponent interactive intervention </p>

<p>including web-based continuing medical education (CME), 
performance feedback and quality improvement tools. </p>

<p>Primary outcome measures: Medication </p>

<p>intensification, a dose increase of an existing medication 
or the addition of a new class of medication for glucose, 
blood pressure and lipids control on any of the three most 
recent office visits. </p>

<p>Results: Of 364 physicians attempting to register, </p>

<p>102 were randomised to the intervention and 103 to the 
control arms; 95 physicians (intervention, n=48; control, 
n=47) provided data on their 1182 of their patients at 
baseline (intervention, n=715; control, n=467) and 945 
patients at follow-up (intervention, n=479; control, 
n=466). For A1c control, medication intensification 
increased in both groups (intervention, pre 26.4% vs 
post 32.6%, p=0.022; control, pre 24.8% vs post 31.1%, 
p=0.033) (intervention, adjusted OR (AOR) 1.37; 95% CI 
1.06 to 1.76; control, AOR 1.41 (95% CI 1.06 to 1.89)); 
however, we observed no incremental benefit solely due 
to the intervention (group-by-time interaction, p=0.948). 
Among patients with the worst glucose control (A1c 
&gt;9%), intensification increased in both groups 
(intervention, pre 34.8% vs post 62.5%, p=0.002; 
control, pre 35.7% vs post 61.4%, p=0.008). </p>

<p>evidence that blood glucose, lipid and blood 
pressure (BP) control forestall the vascular 
complications witnessed with uncontrolled 
diabetes. Thus, control of such diabetes care 
measures are well-accepted indicators-as 
intermediate process outcomes of high quality 
of care, 
2 3 However, diabetes care measures 
of their appropriate control lag behind; only 
7% of diabetes patients in USA meet the 
American Diabetes Association recommenda-
tions for glycated haemoglobin (A1c), BP 
and low-density lipoprotein (LDL) control. </p>

<p>4   Furthermore, diabetes is more endemic in the 
Southern USA and individuals with diabetes in 
this area have worse control. 
5-8 Hence, public 
health interventions, which consider distance 
barriers in rural setting and aimed at </p>

<p>ARTICLE SUMMARY </p>

<p>Article focus </p>

<p>▪ To determine the effectiveness of a wide-reach 
and low-intensity intervention aimed at providers 
to improve medication intensification among 
patients with diabetes in rural areas. </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>▪ In an effectiveness cluster-randomised trial 
among 205 rural physicians in 11 US states 
(Southeastern states; 2006-2008; 24 months), a 
wide-reach, low-intensity, web-based interactive 
multicomponent intervention had no significant 
incremental effect on medication intensification 
for control of glucose, blood pressure or lipids 
for patients with diabetes. 
▪ Medication intensification to control glucose 
increased in both the intervention and control 
groups and it was most significant at very poor 
levels of glucose control. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Strenghts include a designed cluster-randomised 
trial in a diverse rural area. 
▪ Limitations include the self-selection of charts 
for data abstraction. A high attrition rate may 
have introduced bias. </p>

<p>Billue KL, Safford MM, Salanitro AH, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000959. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000959 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>improving diabetes control in patients living in rural areas, 
are warranted. </p>

<p>9-11   The Rural Diabetes Online Care (R-DOC) study was a 
rigorously tested cluster-randomised clinical trial compar-
ing a multicomponent physician intervention including 
web-based continuous medical education (CME), per-
formance feedback 
12-14 and quality improvement tools </p>

<p>13   to a concurrent control website in rural Southeast USA. </p>

<p>15   The primary outcomes were measures of acceptable and 
optimal control for A1c, BP and LDL; the secondary out-
comes were process measures (rate of assessment and 
group means of A1c, BP and LDL). Despite the non-
significant effect attributable to the intervention for any of 
the primary outcomes in the R-DOC study, we observed an 
absolute increase in the rates of assessment of A1c and 
LDL in both study arms (A1c, intervention 30%, control 
29%, p&lt;0.001; LDL, intervention 35%, control 38%, 
p=0.05). 
15 However, whether physicians in rural areas 
adjust medications to control A1c, BP or LDL has 
not been examined in wide-reach, low-intensity interven-
tions 
9-11 such as the one utilised in the R-DOC study. 
Thus, we now report the medication intensification 
outcomes of the R-DOC study-specifically, medication 
intensification to improve overall control of haemoglo-
bin A1c, BP and LDL in the rural Southeastern USA. 
Our findings from the main R-DOC study and this 
report have important implications for distant CME pro-
grammes, quality improvement initiatives and implemen-
tation research. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design and setting 
The R-DOC study was a cluster-randomised trial 
(ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: NCT00403091). The main 
study results-effect of the intervention on diabetes 
control-have been published elsewhere. 
15 Further details 
of the study design, web-content, recruitment and reten-
tion processes and patient characteristics have been pub-
lished elsewhere. 
15-18 Briefly, participants were family, 
general and internal medicine physicians located in rural 
areas of 11 Southeastern US states (population size 
&lt;25 000 habitants). Physicians were enrolled in the study 
sequentially from September 2006 to September 2008, 
provided informed consent online, and were randomised 
to the intervention or control arms using block randomisa-
tion which was concealed to the investigators and statisti-
cians. The unit of randomisation was the physician (and 
not a practice); however, for physicians working in a group 
practice, only one physician per practice could enrol in 
the study. The protocol was approved by the local institu-
tional review boards at The University of Alabama at 
Birmingham and Tuscaloosa medical campuses. </p>

<p>Intervention arm description 
The website focused on helping physicians to 
achieve A1c, BP and LDL control in their diabetic 
patients. 
15 18 Specifically, the intervention site contained: </p>

<p>(1) challenging cases; (2) individualised diabetes per-
formance feedback reports based on the physician's own 
panel of patients; (3) practice timesavers; (4) practical 
goals and guidelines, including guidance for quality 
improvement and systems redesign; </p>

<p>13   (5) patient 
resources; and (6) an area to track and view CME credit. 
Intervention arm physicians also received tailored email 
reminders about website updated and uncompleted sec-
tions of the website. </p>

<p>15   Individualised performance feedback reports were 
based on physician's patients with diabetes. The feedback 
reports compared each intervention arm participant's per-
sonal performance compared to the performance for the 
top 10% of other intervention arm participants. 
12 The 
feedback reports consisted of diabetes control (A1c &lt;7%, 
systolic BP &lt;130 mm Hg, LDL &lt;100 mg/dl), counselling 
on diet or exercise and medication intensification. </p>

<p>15   Control arm description 
The control website contained: (1) links to diabetes prac-
tice guidelines and patient education materials; (2) a list 
of educational conferences on general medical topics 
(updated monthly); (3) an area to track and view their 
CME credit and (4) a link to an external medical blog. 
Physicians in the control group did not receive perform-
ance feedback reports or electronic communications. </p>

<p>Data sources 
All participating physicians provided copies of records of 
15 (intervention arm physicians) or 10 (control arm 
physicians) of their own consecutively seen patients with 
diabetes at baseline and again at follow-up (representing 
two cross-sectional views of each physician's panel of 
patients). Since the focus of the intervention was the 
physician, we were less interested in specific patients but 
rather each physician's panel on average. Therefore, two 
samples as serial cross-sections would better represent 
any change in the physician's own panel on average. 
This method is similar to practice feedback for quality 
improvement purposes. 
19 20 The number of records was 
selected to balance rigour and cost (see also sample size 
description in the statistical section below). 
Patient inclusion criteria were having at least two 
office visits during the past year and no dialysis, demen-
tia, organ transplantation, HIV/AIDS, terminal illness or 
malignancy (except for skin and prostate cancer). Data 
abstraction was performed by trained personnel on 
blinded records sent to the study centre (or abstracted 
on site). Details of data abstracted, quality controls and 
physician compensation are published elsewhere. </p>

<p>15   Outcomes 
In our main study, 
15 the main outcomes were measures 
of acceptable and optimal diabetes control. 
2 3 The main 
outcome for this report is medication intensification, 
defined as a dose increase of an existing medication or 
the addition of a new class of medication for glucose, 
blood pressure and lipids control on any of the three </p>



<p>Billue KL, Safford MM, Salanitro AH, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000959. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000959 </p>

<p>Medication intensification trial </p>

<p>most recent office visits. Medication intensification 
equalled the proportion of patients who had a glucose-
lowering medication, antihypertensive medication or 
cholesterol-lowering medication added or increased over 
the three most recent visits divided by the total number 
of patients assessed at baseline or follow-up. As a second-
ary outcome, we also explored medication intensifica-
tion by level of glucose, BP or lipid control. </p>

<p>Statistical approach 
We calculated the sample size for the main study 
results. 
15 On the basis of clinically important differences, 
the study required 100 physicians per trial arm to detect 
a minimum of 0.4% difference in A1c, 6 mm Hg in BP 
and 6 mg/dl in LDL for the main outcomes ( power 
80%, α=0.05, up to 20% dropout) (10 patients per phys-
ician at baseline and at follow-up). 
15 However, interven-
tion arm physicians were asked to provide 15 patient 
records at baseline (and not at follow-up) because of the 
need to construct audit and feedback reports as part of 
the intervention 
19 20 for A1c, BP and lipids, reflecting 
the fact that not all diabetes patients also have hyperten-
sion and hyperlipidaemia. The initial study was not 
powered to perform adjusted analysis for the intensifica-
tion outcomes of this report. 
All analyses followed the intention-to-treat principle. 
The relationship between the main and secondary out-
comes and the effect of the intervention were examined 
with generalied linear mixed models (GLMM), account-
ing for clustering of patients within physicians. ORs for 
follow-up versus baseline within the two groups were calcu-
lated, adjusting for covariates that differed between base-
line and follow-up patient populations; thus, the covariates 
included in these adjusted analyses included race, and 
clinical diagnosis of hypertension or depression. GLMM 
was implemented by PROC GLIMMIX in <rs type="software">SAS</rs> and was 
adjusted for race, and clinical diagnosis of hypertension or 
depression. Thus, the group coefficient represented differ-
ences between the intervention and control groups at 
baseline; the time of coefficient represented changes in 
the control group over time, thus capturing temporal 
trends. Finally, the group-by-time interaction coefficient 
represented the difference-of-differences for over-time 
change in the intervention versus control group, and was a 
direct comparison of over-time change for the interven-
tion versus the control group. A positive OR meant that 
the odds of a patient being in control increased more over 
time for the intervention versus control group. All analyses 
were performed in <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">9.2</rs> (Cary, North Carolina, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Recruitment scheme, patient characteristics and web 
utilisation 
The Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials diagram 
and patients characteristics at baseline and at follow-up 
(modified from a prior publication 
15 ) are included in 
this report for completeness (figure 1 and table 1). We </p>

<p>obtained baseline and follow-up data on 95 physicians 
(intervention, n=48; control, n=47) and 1182 of their 
patients at baseline (intervention, n=715; control, 
n=467) and 945 diabetes patients at follow-up (interven-
tion, n=479; control, n=466). 
At baseline, intervention group physicians provided 
records for fewer African American patients and more 
patients with hypertension and depression compared 
with control group physicians. Of the 95 physicians, 
90 (94.7%) had access to the Internet in the office. </p>

<p>Main outcomes: medication intensification 
In the adjusted analysis, we saw no significant effect 
attributable to the intervention in the group-by-time 
interaction term for any of the medication intensifica-
tion measures (A1c, BP and LDL; p=0.948, 0.216 and 
0.995; respectively). 
In the unadjusted analysis, intensification of medica-
tions to control A1c increased in both trial arms when 
baseline and follow-up data were compared (interven-
tion, 26.4% vs 32.6%, p=0.022; control, 24.8% vs 31.1%, 
p=0.033; figure 2). This was confirmed in the adjusted 
analysis (intervention, adjusted OR (AOR) 1.37; 95% CI 
1.06 to 1.76; control, AOR 1.41 (95% CI 1.06 to 1.89)). 
In the unadjusted analysis, intensification of medica-
tions to control BP did not differ for patients cared for 
by physicians in either trial arm when comparing base-
line and follow-up data (intervention, 12.3% vs 15.9%, 
p=0.080; control, 16.5% vs16.3%, p=0.941; figure 2). 
This finding was consistent with the adjusted analysis 
(intervention, AOR 1.37 (95% CI 0.99 to 1.88); control, 
AOR 1.00 (95% CI 0.72 to 1.41)). 
In the unadjusted analysis, intensification of medica-
tions to control LDL did not differ for patients cared for 
by physicians in either trial arm when comparing base-
line and follow-up data (intervention, 10.6% vs 11.3%, 
p=0.726; control, 8.1% vs 8.4%, p=0.898; figure 2). This 
finding was consistent with the adjusted analysis (inter-
vention, AOR 1.05 (95% CI 0.73 to 1.50); control, AOR 
1.00, (95% CI 0.65 to 1.53)). </p>

<p>Secondary outcome: medication intensification by strata 
In the unadjusted analysis and among patients with 
worse glucose control (A1c &gt;9%), intensification of med-
ications to control A1c increased in both trial arms 
between baseline and follow-up (intervention, pre 34.8% 
vs post 62.5%, p=0.002; control, pre 35.7% vs post 
61.4%, p=0.008; figure 3 top panel). For patients whose 
last A1c ≥7 to ≤9, we noted an increase in intensifica-
tion between the baseline and follow-up for the inter-
vention group ( p=0.005) but no difference in the 
control group ( p=0.164; figure 3 top panel). Among 
patients with best glucose control (A1c &lt;7%), medica-
tion intensification between baseline and follow-up was 
similar for both trial arms (intervention, p=0.673; 
control, p=0.543; figure 3 top panel). 
In the unadjusted analysis, intensification of BP medi-
cation between baseline and follow-up was similar at all </p>

<p>Billue KL, Safford MM, Salanitro AH, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000959. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000959 </p>



<p>Medication intensification trial </p>

<p>levels of BP control for both trial arms (figure 3 middle 
panel). 
Similarly, in the unadjusted analysis, intensification of 
lipid-lowering medications between baseline and 
follow-up was similar at all levels of LDL control for both 
trial arms (figure 3 bottom panel). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In a rigorously designed cluster-randomised trial, a wide-
reach, low-intensity web-based multicomponent interven-
tion for primary care physicians in the rural Southern 
USA had no significant incremental effect on medica-
tion intensification for their diabetes patients' A1c, BP 
or LDL control as compared to a concurrent control 
website focusing on diabetes care. However, the absolute 
rate of intensification of medications to control A1c </p>

<p>increased in both study arms at the end of the study by a 
modest amount (∼6%). Although the study was not 
designed to perform subgroup analysis, the rate of 
intensification was greatest among the worst-controlled 
patients (A1c &gt;9%) in both study arms (∼25-28%). 
Plausible explanations for our findings include the low 
engagement with the intervention, higher-than antici-
pated attrition rate, Hawthorne's effect or no effect of 
the intervention </p>

<p>15 18   Medication intensification is emerging as a process 
measure for quality improvement efforts among patients 
with diabetes mellitus; pharmacotherapy intensification 
is strongly linked to improved A1c, BP and LDL. For 
example, in a study of over one million members 
with hypertension, hyperlipidaemia and diabetes melli-
tus at Kaiser Permanente Northern California, Selby 
et al 
21 found that a 5% improvement in treatment </p>

<p>Figure 1 Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) diagram (a prior version of this figure has been reported, 
reproduced with permission 
15 ). </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Billue KL, Safford MM, Salanitro AH, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000959. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000959 </p>

<p>Medication intensification trial </p>

<p>intensification led to a 1.0-1.9% improvement in control 
for the entire population. However, the association of 
treatment intensification rates to improved risk factor 
control in rural populations has not been examined. 
Further evidence and reviews of the importance of medi-
cation intensification among patients with diabetes are 
available elsewhere 
22-27 . </p>

<p>Trials using medication intensification outcomes 
Relatively few studies involving physicians have examined 
medication intensification as an outcome, none in a 
rural setting. Studies have tested the impact of a simu-
lated case-based education with opinion leader feed-
back, 
28 customised feedback 
29 and real-time feedback to </p>

<p>patients and their physicians using cell phone software; </p>

<p>30   these studies are summarised below. 
In a group randomised controlled trial 
28 of 57 primary 
care physicians and 2020 patients in an urban setting, phy-
sicians were randomised to no intervention, a simulated 
case-based physician learning intervention, or the same 
case-based and leader feedback. Glucose control, mean 
A1c value, worsened in the control group by 0.06, 
improved in the simulated case-based group by 0.01, and 
worsened in the case-based and leader feedback by 0.18. 
Among the 907 patients with A1c&gt;7%, medication intensi-
fication was similar between groups (31.5%, control; 
32.6%, case-based; 36.8%, case-based and leader feedback; 
p=0.41). Similarly, among the 701 patients with LDL-C 
&gt;99 mg/dl, medication intensification was similar between </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of diabetes patients of 95 physicians randomised to intervention (n=48) or control (n=47) who 
completed follow-up </p>

<p>Patient characteristic </p>

<p>Baseline 
Follow-up 
Intervention 
(n=715) </p>

<p>Control 
(n=467) </p>

<p>Total 
(n=1182) </p>

<p>Intervention 
(n=479) </p>

<p>Control 
(n=466) </p>

<p>Total 
(n=945) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
58.7 (13.59) 
60.6 (13.79) 59.4 (13.70) 61.3 (13.42) 
60.5 (12.71) 60.9 (13.09) 
Gender, female 
360 (51.1%) 
230 (49.5%) 590 (50.5%) 260 (54.5%) 
252 (54.4%) 512 (54.5%) 
Race, African American 
97 (13.9%) 
99 (21.3%) 196 (16.9%) 102 (21.4%) 
143 (30.9%) 245 (26.1%) 
Obesity* 
274 (38.3%) 
193 (41.3%) 467 (39.5%) 
97 (20.3%) 
75 (16.1%) 172 (18.2%) 
Smoker, current 
85 (12.5%) 
55 (12.3%) 140 (12.4%) 
63 (13.8%) 
53 (13.0%) 116 (13.4%) 
No self-testing 
168 (33.6%) 
114 (36.3%) 282 (34.6%) 189 (41.4%) 
183 (44.7%) 372 (43.0%) 
Non-adherence to 
appointments </p>

<p>75 (11.0%) 
54 (12.0%) 129 (11.4%) 
10 (2.2%) 
23 (5.6%) 
33 (3.8%) </p>

<p>Insurance, Medicaid 
65 (9.1%) 
51 (10.9%) 116 (9.8%) 
66 (13.8%) 
58 (12.4%) 124 (13.1%) 
Comorbidities 
Diabetes complications † 
147 (20.6%) 
110 (23.6%) 257 (21.7%) 156 (32.6%) 
134 (28.8%) 290 (30.7%) 
Insulin use 
103 (14.4%) 
66 (14.1%) 169 (14.3%) 
84 (17.5%) 
68 (14.6%) 152 (16.1%) 
Hypertension 
473 (66.2%) 
304 (65.1%) 777 (65.7%) 327 (68.3%) 
283 (60.7%) 610 (64.6%) 
Hyperlipidaemia 
110 (15.4%) 
85 (18.2%) 195 (16.5%) 
11 (2.30%) 
17 (3.7%) 
28 (3.0%) 
Peripheral vascular disease 
47 (6.6%) 
31 (6.6%) 
78 (6.6%) 
41 (8.6%) 
35 (7.5%) 
76 (8.0%) 
Coronary artery disease 
135 (18.9%) 
83 (17.8%) 218 (18.4%) 111 (23.2%) 
95 (20.4%) 206 (21.8%) 
Vascular intervention ‡ 
60 (8.4%) 
47 (10.1%) 107 (9.1%) 
36 (7.5%) 
40 (8.6%) 
76 (8.0%) 
Depression 
105 (14.7%) 
61 (13.1%) 166 (14.0%) 
84 (17.5%) 
60 (12.9%) 144 (15.2%) </p>

<p>A prior version of this table has been reported (reproduced with permission). </p>

<p>15   Values are mean (SD) or n (%). 
*Obesity: body mass index ≥ 30 kg/m 
2 or clinical diagnosis. 
 †Diabetes complications: retinopathy, neuropathy or nephropathy. 
 ‡Vascular intervention: coronary artery bypass grafting, stent, percutaneous coronary angioplasty. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Medication 
intensification for haemoglobin 
A1c (%), blood pressure (BP, 
mm Hg) and cholesterol 
(low-density lipoprotein (LDL), 
mg/dl) control for intervention 
(n=48) or control (n=47) 
physicians, at baseline ( pre, 
n=1182 patients) and follow-up 
(post, n=945 patients). See text 
for definitions of medication 
intensification. </p>

<p>Billue KL, Safford MM, Salanitro AH, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000959. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000959 </p>



<p>Medication intensification trial </p>

<p>groups (20.8%, control; 24.2%, case-based; 21.8%, case-
based and leader feedback; p=0.66). Finally, among the 
949 patients with BP values &gt;130/mm Hg, medication 
intensification was similar between groups (27.3%, 
control; 24.7%, case-based; 28.2%, case-based and leader 
feedback; p=0.61). Medication intensification was defined 
by the initiation or titration in 12 months after the inter-
vention for all patients with goals above target (A1c&gt;=7%, 
LDL-C &gt;=100 mg/dl, BP&gt;130/80 mm Hg); insulin titra-
tion was excluded from the outcome. The attrition rate 
was 33% (38/59 physicians). Our case scenarios took less 
than 10 min to complete as compared with the ones in 
this study (over 60 min each). 
28 Perhaps striking a balance 
between more 'intense' cases to increase physician engage-
ment and providing feedback information may lead to the 
improvement in medication intensification. Finally, the 
medication intensification rates definitions were different 
from ones used in our study; hence, they cannot be 
compared. 
In a randomised trial of 3703 patients with diabetes 
and their 123 physicians, participants were randomised to </p>

<p>receive customised feedback of clinical information in 
four groups: patient only, physician only, both the patient 
and physician, or neither one. 
29 At 12 months, interven-
tions had no effect on A1c test ordering, medication 
intensification or improvement in A1c or LDL control. 
Medication intensification was defined as in the above 
study. 
28 In our study, we included customised feedback as 
one of the many components of the intervention. 
In a pilot-controlled trial, 
30 30 patients with diabetes 
were randomised to an intervention group consisting of 
cell phone-based software which provided real-time feed-
back on glucose levels, medication regimens and sug-
gested treatment algorithms or a control group. 
Intervention providers received patients' logbooks and 
suggested treatment plans to reach A1c&lt;6.5%. During 
the 3 months of the study, the A1c levels decreased 
among patients in the intervention as compared with 
the control group (by 2.0% vs 0.7%; respectively); medi-
cations were changed or intensified in 84% in the inter-
vention group as compared with 23% patients in the 
control group ( p&lt;0.002). The operational definition for </p>

<p>Figure 3 Medication 
intensification for strata of 
haemogloblin A1c (%), blood 
pressure (BP, mm Hg) and 
cholesterol (low-density 
lipoprotein (LDL), mg/dl) control. 
See text for definitions of 
medication intensification. </p>



<p>Billue KL, Safford MM, Salanitro AH, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000959. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000959 </p>

<p>Medication intensification trial </p>

<p>medication intensification in this study was not reported. 
Cell phone technology provides the opportunity for 
wide reach approach. In our study, physicians and not 
their patients received the customised feedback on their 
group of patients. </p>

<p>Limitations 
Our study had limitations. 
15 First, physicians themselves 
provided the records of consecutively seen patients; 
although selection bias was a possibility, the wide range 
of A1c, BP and LDL values suggests that not only well-
controlled patients were selected. Second, the high attri-
tion, 95 of the 205 randomised physicians provided base-
line and follow-up data, may have introduced biases. By 
design, to test a purely online intervention, we chose not 
to enhance retention activities as typically seen in rando-
mised clinical trials and focused on several aspects of 
provider-based implementation tools. 
13 Although a com-
prehensive analysis would have been enlightening, we 
did not perform a systematic examination of this nega-
tive trial, or how such intervention might work it were 
effective. We worried that studying the study while being 
conducted would have introduced another variable. </p>

<p>Implications 
A framework has been proposed to evaluate the public 
health impact of interventions. 
9-11 The components of 
the framework include reach ('How many participate?'), 
effectiveness ('Does it work in usual settings?'), adoption 
('How many use it?'), implementation ('Is it used as 
intended?') and maintenance ('Is it sustained over 
time?') (RE-AIM). In this study, using a wide-reach 
approach, we examined the effectiveness of a potential 
public health intervention. Effective interventions may 
be limited by their low-reach, specificity to fewer settings, 
expense and limited sustainability-thus limiting their 
generalisability. Testing less intensive interventions with 
wider reach in rural settings has been advocated in 
public health interventions. 
11 Finding effective strategies 
to accomplish continuing professional development for 
physicians practising in remote locations is also an 
important objective. 
31 In contrast, higher-intensity inter-
ventions in rural and community settings have shown 
promising results. </p>

<p>32-36 </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
In conclusion, a wide-reach, low-intensity, web-based 
interactive multicomponent intervention had no signifi-
cant incremental effect on medication intensification for 
control of glucose, BP or lipids for patients with diabetes 
of physicians practising in the rural Southeastern USA. 
Despite low engagement in the web-based programme, 
intensification measures improved in both arms of the 
study. Our study raises important issues for wide-reach, 
low-intensity CME programmes that seek to improve 
patient outcomes. </p>

<p>Author affiliations 
1 The University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA 
2 VA Tennessee Valley Healthcare Geriatric Research, Education, Clinical Center 
(GRECC) and Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee, USA 
3 Bedford Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Beford, Massachusetts, USA 
4 The University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, Massachusetts, 
USA 
5 Birmingham Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Birmingham, Alabama, USA 
6 Birmingham VAMC,Veterans Affairs National Quality Scholars Program, 
Birmingham, Alabama, USA </p>

<p>Contributors KB wrote the article and contributed in the interpretation of the 
findings. YK conducted the analyses and contributed to the writing of the 
Methods and Results sections. MMS, AHS, TKH, WC, JJA, CAE contributed to 
the conceptualisation of the project, the interpretation of the findings and to 
the writing of all sections of the article. JJA conceived and supervised the 
study. All authors contributed to reviewing drafts of the article. </p>

<p>Funding This work was supported by the National Institute of Diabetes and 
Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK) 5R18DK065001 to JJA. AHS and CAE 
were supported by the Veterans Affairs National Quality Scholars Program. 
The sponsors had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, 
management, analysis and interpretation of the data; and preparation, review 
or approval of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Competing interests The opinions expressed in this article are those of the 
authors alone and do not reflect the views of the Department of Veterans 
Affairs. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Institutional review boards at The University of Alabama at 
Birmingham and Tuscaloosa medical campuses. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>



<p>Billue KL, Safford MM, Salanitro AH, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000959. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000959 </p>



<p>Medication intensification trial </p>





<p>Billue KL, Safford MM, Salanitro AH, et al. BMJ Open 2012;2:e000959. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-000959 </p>

<p>Medication intensification trial </p>

</text></tei>