<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3276086" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Several dwarf plum genotypes (Prunus salicina L.), due to deficiency of unknown gibberellin (GA) signalling, were 
identified. A cDNA encoding GA 2-oxidase (PslGA2ox), the major gibberellin catabolic enzyme in plants, was cloned 
and used to screen the GA-deficient hybrids. This resulted in the identification of a dwarf plum hybrid, designated as 
DGO24, that exhibits a markedly elevated PslGA2ox signal. Grafting 'Early Golden' (EG), a commercial plum cultivar, 
on DGO24 (EG/D) enhanced PslGA2ox accumulation in the scion part and generated trees of compact stature. 
Assessment of active GAs in such trees revealed that DGO24 and EG/D accumulated relatively much lower 
quantities of main bioactive GAs (GA 1 and GA 4 ) than control trees (EG/M). Moreover, the physiological function of 
PslGA2ox was studied by determining the molecular and developmental consequences due to ectopic expression in 
Arabidopsis. Among several lines, two groups of homozygous transgenics that exhibited contrasting phenotypes 
were identified. Group-1 displayed a dwarf growth pattern typical of mutants with a GA deficiency including smaller 
leaves, shorter stems, and delay in the development of reproductive events. In contrast, Group-2 exhibited a 'GA 
overdose' phenotype as all the plants showed elongated growth, a typical response to GA application, even under 
limited GA conditions, potentially due to co-suppression of closely related Arabidopsis homologous. The studies 
reveal the possibility of utilizing PslGA2ox as a marker for developing size-controlling rootstocks in Prunus. </p>

<p>Modern fruit growing creates an increasing demand for tree 
size control that can offer numerous horticultural advan-
tages. Trees with reduced stature allow high density 
cultivation, facilitate tree management, and minimize spray 
drift. In most temperate fruits, dwarf rootstocks can have 
profound effects on scions such as controlling tree size, </p>

<p>flowering time, yield efficiency, and fruit quality (Janick  et al., 1996). However, the mechanism by which these 
effects are achieved is still not well understood. Attempts to 
explain how rootstocks cause dwarfing of trees, which 
focused on their effects on supply of mineral nutrients and 
water to the scion, have not provided any convincing </p>

<p>Abbreviations: EG/D, Early Golden/DGO24; EG/M, Early Golden/Myrobalan; L.1/G1, L.1/Group-1; L.4/G2, L.4/Group-2; LD, long day; PAC, paclobutrazol; SD, short 
day; WT, wild type. 
ª 2011 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>explanations (Jones, 1984; Ebel et al., 2000). Other studies, 
which focused on the production and movement of 
endogenous hormones, demonstrated that dwarfism could 
be associated with deficiencies in gibberellin (GA) levels or 
signalling (Cristoferi and Filiti, 1981; Erez, 1984; Webster,  2004). 
GA is an essential hormone that is involved in many 
aspects of plant growth and development (Fleet and Sun,  2005). To date, &gt;100 GA forms have been identified in 
plants (MacMillan, 2002). However, only a small number of 
them are considered to be functional, while most other GAs 
are present in plant tissues as precursors for the active 
forms or due to deactivated metabolites. The GA bio-
synthetic pathway has long been studied, and the majority 
of genes encoding enzymes in each biosynthetic and 
catabolic step have been identified in the model species 
(Olszewski et al., 2002). 
In higher plants, the flux of active GAs is regulated by the 
balance between their rates of biosynthesis and deactiva-
tion. The GA20ox and GA3ox genes encode key enzymes of 
bioactive GAs synthesis, whereas GA2ox is the major GA 
inactivation enzyme (Yamaguchi, 2008). Modifying the 
regulation of genes controlling GA flux can subsequently 
alter the processes regulated by GA and, thus, plant 
architecture (Hedden and Phillips, 2000). 
In plants, it is important to maintain optimal levels of 
phytohormones to ensure normal growth and development. 
Hence, it is essential that there is a mechanism in place to 
remove any excess active compounds or their biosynthetic 
precursors to ensure proper function of phytohormones. 
Such a strategy can modulate the signal produced and 
subsequently prevent the progressive accumulation of the 
hormones. A number of inactivation pathways have been 
identified for GA (Thomas and Hedden, 2006; Zhu et al.,  2006). However, based on the prevalence of 2b-hydroxylated 
GAs in many plant species (MacMillan, 2002), the most 
widespread mechanism for GA inactivation seems to be via 
2-oxidation (Thomas et al., 1999). Genes encoding GA 
2-oxidases (GA2oxs) were first identified by screening cDNA 
expression libraries for 2b-hydroxylase activity (Martin et al.,  1999; Thomas et al., 1999). Early characterized GA2oxs are 
active against C 19 -GAs as substrates, including functional 
GAs and their immediate precursors. Later, a new type of 
GA2ox that catabolizes only the non-bioactive C 20 -GAs was 
reported (Schomburg et al., 2003). Apparently, this class of 
GA2ox is not involved in inactivation of functional GAs, but 
may be important in regulating GA biosynthesis through the 
removal of earlier intermediates in the pathway. 
The physiological functions of GA2ox have been studied 
in a variety of plant species using different approaches; 
however, all these studies demonstrated that GA2ox is 
responsible for reducing the level of active GAs in plants. 
Overexpression of GA2ox enhances GA inactivation and 
thus induces dwarfism (Sakamoto et al., 2001; Busov et al.,  2003; Appleford et al., 2007; Dijkstra et al., 2008). Loss-of-
function mutation in a pea PsGA2ox1 results in the hyper-
elongated slender phenotype (Martin et al., 1999). Similarly, 
in Arabidopsis, the ga2ox quintuple mutant results in plants </p>

<p>behaving as the wild type (WT) supplemented with a high 
amount of GA (Rieu et al., 2008a). 
In this study, a dwarf plum hybrid (DGO24) that exhibits 
high levels of PslGA2ox and subsequently displays reduced 
bioactive GAs was identified. DGO24, when used as 
rootstock, reduces the scion ['Early Golden' (EG)] vigour 
and also causes several developmental defects; however, 
these could be temporarily restored by exogenous GA 
application. Moreover, the role of GA during different 
stages of fruit development was determined by studying the 
expression profile of PslGA2ox mRNA that reflects the 
alteration in GA accumulation. A model is proposed in 
which the role played by the plant hormone GA is as 
critical as that of auxin to ensure correct fruit development. 
Further, it was demonstrated that the overexpression of this 
gene results in a GA-deficient phenotype in Arabidopsis with 
growth traits similar to those found in EG/D (EG/DGO24) 
plum trees. In another case, the PslGA2ox transgene caused 
co-suppression of closely related Arabidopsis homologous, 
which triggered GA accumulation and resulted in a GA 
overdose phenotype. The results show that GA2ox can be 
used as a marker for the selection of dwarf rootstocks that 
might be suitable for the tender fruit industry. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plum tissues and post-harvest treatments 
Flowers and fruits from different developmental stages were 
harvested from Japanese plum (Prunus salicina L.) cultivar EG 
as described previously (El-Sharkawy et al., 2007). Leaves from 
10-year old dwarf seedling DGO24 and 7-year old EG grafted 
onto DGO24 (EG/D) or onto vigorous rootstock Myrobalan 
(EG/M) were collected. All plant materials were frozen in liquid 
nitrogen and stored at -80°C. </p>

<p>Isolation and in silico analysis of plum GA2ox cDNA sequence 
Based on the sequence similarity of various GA2ox genes from 
different plant species, a pair of degenerate primers (primers 1 and 2, 
Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online) was designed from the 
conserved regions to amplify the GA2ox orthologues from P. salicina. 
The isolated fragment was cloned in the pGEM-T Easy vector 
(Promega, Madison, WI, USA), sequenced, and analysed using 
BLAST (Altschul et al., 1997). Extension of the partial cDNA clone 
was carried out using the 3'-and 5'-RACE kit (Invitrogen, 
Burlington, ON, Canada). Full-length amplification of the cDNA 
sequence designated PslGA2ox was carried out using the Platinum 
Taq DNA Polymerase High Fidelity kit following the instructions 
provided by the manufacturer (Invitrogen). Alignment of the 
PslGA2ox predicted protein sequence and the Neighbor-Joining tree 
construction were performed as described previously (El-Sharkawy  et al., 2009). </p>

<p>Protoplast isolation and transient expression of PslGA2ox-GFP 
fusion protein 
The coding sequence of PslGA2ox was cloned as a C-terminal 
fusion in-frame with green fluorescent protein (GFP) into the 
pGreenII vector using the BamHI site, and expressed under the 
control of the 35S promoter. Protoplasts used for transfection 
were obtained from suspension-cultured tobacco (Nicotiana taba-
cum) BY-2 cells. Protoplasts were transfected and analysed for 
GFP fluorescence by confocal microscopy as described previously </p>



<p>(El-Sharkawy et al., 2009). All transient expression assays were 
repeated at least three times. </p>

<p>Quantification of bioactive GAs 
Approximately 3 g of fresh leaf and stem tissues from field-grown 
EG/M, DGO24, and EG/D plum trees was collected. Each sample 
was frozen in liquid nitrogen, lyophilised, and finally stored at 
-20°C until analysed. Plant materials were homogenized in 15 ml of 
cold 80% methanol containing 50 ng of deuterated GA 1 and GA 4 , 
and extracted overnight in darkness at 4°C. After filtration, the 
residue was re-extracted with 5 ml of 80% methanol for 2 h and re-
filtered. The extract was purified through a C18 Sep-pack cartridge 
and the eluate was absorbed onto 0.5 g of Celite 545 (ProLab), and 
purified by step-elution silicic acid (SiO 2 ) partition chromatography 
running into an ethyl acetate:hexane (95:5) buffer. The samples were 
then evaporated under reduced pressure at room temperature until 
dry. Phytohormones were analysed by high-performance liquid 
chromatography/mass spectrometry (HPLC/MS) carried out on a 
Varian 1200l triple quadrupole, working in positive electrospray 
ionization mode (ESI+) with a capillary voltage of 5500 V and acid 
voltage of 40 V. HPLC/MS analysis was carried out by MRM 
(multiple reaction monitoring) ion detection mode working with 
three transitions for each compound. Liquid chromatography (LC) 
was performed using a Polaris 3 lm, 15032.1 mm I.D. analytical 
column, maintained at 40°C. The mobile phases consisted of water/ 
0.1% formic acid (A) and methanol/acetonitrile 25/75 (B). The flow-
rate was 0.2 ml min </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>. In each case, 20 ll of sample was injected. 
The gradients used for GAs were: t¼0 min (90% A, 10% B); 
t¼1 min (75% A, 25% B); t¼10 min (0% A; 100% B); and t¼15 min 
(0% A; 100% B). The levels of phytohormones in the plant samples 
were determined from the area ratios of endogenous to correspond-
ing deuterated phytohomones. A curve was prepared always with 
the same quantity of labelled isotope added to samples and with 
concentrations from 1 ppb to 250 ppb for the compounds analysed. 
The minimum quantification level was 1 ppb (1 ng ml </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>) for each 
compound. All experiments were carried out in three independent 
replicates. </p>

<p>Plasmid construction and plant transformation 
For the generation of the 35S::PslGA2ox construct, a high fidelity 
PCR system was used to amplify the full-length sequence using 
specific primers 3 and 4 (Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online), 
subcloned in pGEM-T Easy vector, and then introduced into the 
BamHI site of the pGreen0029 binary vector (Hellens et al., 2000). 
The resulting vector was introduced into Agrobacterium tumefa-
ciens strain C58 by the freeze-thaw method (Holsters et al., 1978)  and then employed for Arabidopsis transformation using the floral 
dip method (Clough and Bent, 1998). The PslGA2ox gene under 
the control of the 35S promoter was introduced into the WT 
Arabidopsis background Col-0. Six T 3 homozygous independent 
lines showing significant PslGA2ox accumulation were identified 
based on transgene levels along with phenotype characteristics. 
These lines were pooled into two groups based on their growth 
behaviour, and a representative from each group was selected for 
further experimental use (L.1/G1 and L.4/G2). All plants were 
divided into four groups (24 plants per group); three groups were 
grown under a long day (LD) photoperiod (16:8 h light/300 lmol 
m 
À2 s </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>; 23:18°C, and 65% relative humidity): control, treated 
with 100 lM GA 3 or 10 lM paclobutrazol (PAC). The fourth 
group was transferred to short day (SD) conditions (8:16 h light 
and 20:18°C). The plant materials were frozen in liquid N 2 
immediately after collection and stored at -80°C until use. </p>

<p>RNA isolation 
Total RNA from plum was extracted using the methods described 
by Meisel et al. (2005). For Arabidopsis, total RNA was extracted 
using a Plant Total RNA Purification kit (Norgen, Thorold, ON, </p>

<p>Canada). All RNA extracts were treated with DNase I (Promega) 
then cleaned up with anRNeasy mini kit (Qiagen, Mississauga, 
ON, Canada). </p>

<p>Real-time quantitative RT-PCR 
DNase-treated RNA (5 lg) was reverse transcribed in a total 
volume of 50 ll using SuperScript III Reverse Transcriptase 
(Invitrogen). Gene-specific primers were designed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Primer Express</rs> (v<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version">3.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Applied Biosystems</rs>, Carlsbad, CA, USA) (primers 
5-30, Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online). Quantitative reverse 
transcription PCRs (qRT-PCRs) were performed using 20 ng of 
cDNA and 300 nM of each primer in a 20 ll reaction volume with 
SYBR GREEN PCR MasterMix (Qiagen, Mississauga, ON, 
Canada). Three biological and three technical replicates for each 
reaction were analysed on an ABI PRISM 7900HT Sequence 
Detection System (Applied Biosystems) with a first step of 95°C 
for 15 min followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 s and 60°C for 
1 min. Melting curves were generated using the following program: 
95°C for 15 s, 60°C for 15 s, and 95°C for 15 s. Transcript 
abundance was quantified using standard curves for both target 
and reference genes, which were generated from serial dilutions of 
PCR products from corresponding cDNAs. Transcript abundance 
was normalized to the reference genes [PsAct (EF585293) and 
AtAct (NM_121018)] that show high stability across the different 
treatments. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Isolation and structural characterization of PslGA2ox 
cDNA </p>

<p>PCR amplification resulted in the isolation of a partial 
DNA fragment with the expected size. Sequence analysis of 
the PCR product indicated that this fragment encoded 
a part of the GA2ox gene family. Extension of the partial 
cDNA clone resulted in a full-length cDNA containing an 
open reading frame of 1482 bp encoding a protein of 342 
amino acids and hence designated PslGA2ox. Alignment of 
the PslGA2ox amino acid sequence with that of other 
reported GA2oxs revealed that the predicted protein shares 
sequence identity ranging from 53% to 68% with closely 
related homologues and highlighted a number of conserved 
motifs and structural similarities that are common within 
the dioxygenase family of GA catabolic enzymes (Supple-
mentary Fig. S1 at JXB online) (Valegård et al., 1998). In 
order to classify the PslGA2ox sequence among the various 
GA2oxs, a phylogenetic tree was constructed (Fig. 1). The 
dendrogram analysis defines that the GA2ox gene family 
could be divided into three main classes based upon 
sequence conservation. PslGA2ox is a member of class I 
that (as well as class II), act as a major C 19 -GA deactivator 
(Thomas et al., 1999). However, tested members of class III 
can only catabolize C 20 -GA2oxs (Schomburg et al., 2003). 
Additionally, analysis of various GA2ox amino acid sequen-
ces, characterized so far, revealed the absence of any obvious 
targeting sequence that can signify the localization of this 
protein in the plant cell. The results show that the GFP 
distribution in both control and PslGA2ox-GFP is spread 
throughout the cytoplasm and nucleus (Supplementary 
Fig. S2 at JXB online). </p>

<p>GA inactivation and plant development | 1227 </p>

<p>Identification of a GA2ox-dependent dwarf plum line </p>

<p>Twenty-five dwarf individual plum hybrids, produced 
through controlled hybridizations in a breeding program, 
were identified phenotypically based on their compact stature 
with short internodes and small dark leaves. In order to 
determine if the dwarf phenotype is due to deficiency in 
bioactive GAs, they were treated with GA 3 . GA application 
showed phenotypic effects in only 10 hybrids as determined 
by their internode length and leaf size. To establish if the 
dwarfism in these hybrids is associated with PslGA2ox, they 
were screened against a vigorously growing plum, EG/M, 
for the accumulation of PslGA2ox (Supplementary Fig. S3 
at JXB online). The expression results defined that only one 
hybrid, designated DGO24, displayed significantly high 
PslGA2ox mRNA levels; therefore, this was selected for 
further analysis. Then, the full-length PslGA2ox cDNA was 
isolated from DGO24 to determine whether there are 
divergences within the amino acid sequence that can 
elucidate the hyper accumulation of transcripts. However, 
sequence analysis revealed a nucleotide sequence identical 
to that isolated from EG/M trees. Compared with EG/M </p>

<p>control trees (tree height 3.7360.22 m), DGO24 displayed 
very short trees along with a slow growth rate (tree height 
1.3760.15 m). Grafting EG onto DGO24 (EG/D) resulted 
in shoots that exhibited shorter internodes and reduced 
stem elongation (tree height 2.0660.25 m) than EG/M 
(Supplementary Fig. S4 at JXB online). To determine 
whether PslGA2ox accumulation is the cause of the EG 
scion's phenotype, its expression was studied in EG/M, 
DGO24, and EG/D shoots. A strong signal was detected in 
both DGO24 and EG/D trees; however, the expression was 
weak in EG/M (Fig. 2). It was thus decided to investigate 
bioactive GA accumulation within the three different plum 
trees with the aim to determine whether there are dissim-
ilarities in GA content that can account for the diversity in 
growth behaviour. Quantification of active GAs revealed 
that DGO24 and EG/D shoots exhibited at least 6-and 8-
fold lower concentrations of the bioactive forms GA 1 and 
GA 4 , respectively, than EG/M (Table 1). </p>

<p>Dwarfism is reversed by GA 3 application </p>

<p>In addition to the compact stature, short internodes, and 
small dark leaves, EG/D trees exhibited malformed flowers 
and small fruit at harvest (Fig. 3A, B) along with significant 
delay in fruit development compared with EG/M 
(1062.74 d). EG/D fruit were ;36% smaller than EG/M 
fruit in size and weight (Fig. 3B, C). In order to confirm 
that these developmental deformities are due to insufficient 
GA necessary to coordinate plant growth, EG/D trees were 
sprayed with GA 3 . GA application restored the growth of 
compact EG scions to near normal, as determined by 
internode length, accelerated the fruit development process 
to levels comparable with those of EG/M fruits, and 
resulted in proper flower organogenesis (Supplementary  Fig. S5 at JXB online; Fig. 3A). Moreover, GA treatment 
caused significant increases in fruit size and weight, and 
these were up to ;2-fold greater at harvest than their 
counterparts from untreated EG/D trees (Fig. 3B, C). </p>

<p>PslGA2ox expression during fruit ontogeny </p>

<p>PslGA2ox transcripts were consistently expressed at moder-
ate levels during different stages of fruit development in 
EG/D. In order to elucidate the physiological role of 
PslGA2ox and subsequently the contribution of GAs in fruit 
development, its expression profile was analysed during 
different stages of EG/M fruits (Fig. 4). PslGA2ox transcripts 
were initially low in flower buds, but greatly increased soon 
after flowering [;4 days after bloom (DAB)] followed by 
sharp inhibition of its mRNA levels after fertilization, ;7 
DAB. The accumulation of PslGA2ox mRNA at bloom 
represented the highest transcript abundance during the 
whole experiment. During early fruit development, 7-15 
DAB, PslGA2ox transcripts increased gradually in young 
fruits. Stone fruits (Prunus spp.) exhibit a typical double 
sigmoid growth pattern during fruit development, with four 
distinct stages, S1-S4 (El-Sharkawy et al., 2007). Within the 
first stage, intense cell division is predominant, while during </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Phylogenetic relationships between Prunus salicina 
PslGA2ox (HM021156), Arabidopsis thaliana AtGA2ox1 (CAB41007), 
AtGA2ox2 (CAB41008), AtGA2ox3 (CAB41009), AtGA2ox4 
(AAG51528), AtGA2ox6 (AAG00891), AtGA2ox7 (AAG50945), 
AtGA2ox8 (CAB79120), Oryza sativa OsGA2ox1 (BAB40934), 
OsGA2ox4 (AAU03107), OsGA2ox6 (CAE03751), Spinacia oleracea 
SoGA2ox1 (AAN87571), SoGA2ox2 (AAN87572), SoGA2ox3 
(AAX14674), Solanum lycopersicum SlGA2ox5 (ABO27636), Lactuca 
sativa LsGA2ox1 (BAB12442), Phaseolus coccineus PcGA2ox1 
(CAB41036), and Cucurbita maxima CmGA2ox (CAC83090) based 
on the full-length amino acid sequence. Bootstrap confidence values 
from 1000 replicates are indicated. I, II, and III represent the three 
different GA2ox protein classes. </p>



<p>S2 phase there is hardly any increase in fruit size but the 
endocarp hardens to form a solid stone. Throughout these 
developmental periods (22-52 DAB), PslGA2ox transcription 
showed a significant and gradual increase, reaching relatively 
maximal levels by the end of the S2 stage. The S3 stage (62-
72 DAB) is accompanied by a considerable increase in fruit 
size, which is mostly attributable to cell expansion. In S3 
phase, when the pulp readily separates from the seed, 
PslGA2ox levels increased in abundance within the pulp 
tissue, but consistently decreased in the seeds during matu-
rity. Throughout the S4 stage, where most metabolic changes 
due to fruit ripening take place, PslGA2ox accumulation was 
generally low. As ripening progressed, the expression level of 
PslGA2ox increased in abundance within the pulp tissue, 
reaching relatively high levels at the post-climacteric phase 
(;83 DAB); however, in the seeds, its transcription increased 
to a peak at the pre-climacteric stage (;80 DAB) and slightly 
decreased thereafter. </p>

<p>Ectopic expression of PslGA2ox in WT Arabidopsis </p>

<p>GA2ox proteins play repressive roles in plant growth 
and development through catabolizing bioactive GAs, in 
particular GA 4 , into inactive forms (Thomas et al., 1999;  Schomburg et al., 2003). The present results suggest the 
involvement of PslGA2ox in the dwarf plum (DGO24); 
however, to confirm this hypothesis, the PslGA2ox gene 
was overexpressed in Arabidopsis, where GA 4 is the major 
active GA controlling different aspects of plant develop-
ment (Xu et al., 1999). Ectopic expression of PslGA2ox led </p>

<p>to a wide range of disturbances in general growth and 
development behaviour. Six independent transgenic lines 
were confirmed after PCR analysis and then divided into 
two groups based on their phenotypic and molecular 
characteristics (Fig. 5). Group-1, including L.1, L.5, and 
L.7, exhibited a typical dwarf phenotype due to a signifi-
cant decline in the length of all stem growth-related 
characters, resulting in ;60% reduction in overall plant 
height, which was associated with considerably high 
PslGA2ox levels. Group-2 that includes L.2, L.3, and L.4 
showed a hypergrowth pattern. The plants were ;41% 
taller than the WT due to notably shorter, but numerous 
internodes, which was associated with low but significant 
PslGA2ox accumulation (Supplementary Table S2 at JXB 
online; Fig. 5A, B). Analysis of the transgene profile in 
mutant plants showed that the level of PslGA2ox corre-
lated negatively with plant height. The tallest plants had 
the lowest transcription levels while the expression was 
weaker in longer plants. Thus a homozygous representative 
from each group (L.1/G1 and L.4/G2) was selected for 
further studies. To assess whether the overexpression of 
PslGA2ox can disturb the GA response pathway, the 
transcription levels of a number of genes that are induced 
(At2g21220, AtGA2ox2, AtGA2ox3, and AtGA2ox8) or 
repressed (AtGA20ox1 and AtGA3ox1) by GA were de-
termined (Phillips et al., 1995; Thomas et al., 1999;  Schomburg et al., 2003; Nemhauser et al., 2006). Expression 
of the various GA-responsive genes was considerably 
different in the two lines (Fig. 5C). All GA-inducible 
transcripts were suppressed by 21-57% in L.1/G1, and the 
GA-repressed genes, AtGA20ox1 and AtGA3ox1, increased 
by ;4.7-and ;5.5-fold, respectively. In contrast to the 
expected results, L.4/G2 accumulated more of the GA-
up-regulated transcripts, while AtGA2ox2 and AtGA2ox3 
were barely detected. Application of GA 3 that cannot be 
metabolized by GA2oxs (Sakamoto et al., 2001) resulted in 
a differential response in the treated plants (Supplementary 
Table S2 at JXB online; Fig. S6). GA treatment rescued 
L.1/G1 height as a result of increasing internode number 
and length. However in L.4/G2, GA treatment caused 
a significant plant height reduction (;47%). To evaluate 
the effect of GA, the expression of the different GA-
regulated genes was assessed (Fig. 5D). In L.1/G1, the 
accumulation profile of the different GA-responsive genes 
was similar to that in the WT, while in L.4/G2, only 
a modest increase in the various GA-up-regulated tran-
scripts was observed; however, AtGA2ox2 and AtGA2ox3 
remained undetectable. Generally, the GA biosynthesis 
inhibitor (PAC) and SD conditions reduced stem elongation 
and shoot growth of all treated plants (Supplementary Fig. 
S6 at JXB online). However, this effect was very pro-
nounced in L.1/G1, and half of the plants were dead before 
completing their life cycle. </p>

<p>Developmental phenotypes of PslGA2ox lines </p>

<p>In order to validate the previous data, the PslGA2ox lines 
were phenotypically characterized for some well known </p>

<p>Fig. 2. PslGA2ox accumulation on EG/M, DGO24, and EG/D. All 
RT-PCR experiments were repeated at least three times with three 
different cDNA synthesized from three different RNA extractions for 
the same sample. The required number of cycles necessary for 
exponential, but non-saturated PCR amplification was determined 
using the cDNA from the highest expressing sample (DGO24). </p>

<p>Table 1. Concentrations of bioactive GAs in plum shoots </p>

<p>Plum tree 
GA concentration (ng g 
À1 DW) </p>

<p>GA 1 
GA 4 </p>

<p>EG/M (control) 
2.8160.91 
16.8362.2 
DGO24 
0.560.18** 
2.060.84** 
EG/D 
0.6660.08** 
4.5360.95** </p>

<p>The GA concentration is given in ng g 
À1 dry weight. The values are the 
average of three replicates. Statistically significant differences from the 
applicable control are indicated by (**) for the probability level (P &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>GA inactivation and plant development | 1229 </p>

<p>GA-related traits. Furthermore, the plants were grown 
under various GA-unlimited or -limited conditions. </p>

<p>Root elongation </p>

<p>Recent studies suggested that GA inhibited root growth by 
suppressing lateral root formation (Eriksson et al., 2000;  Gou et al., 2010). Relative to the WT, all Group-1 plants 
exhibited compact shoot growth associated with accelerated 
root formation. Root lengths of Group-1 plants were 
enhanced by ;30-61%. In contrast, all Group-2 plants 
displayed extended shoot length with roots significantly 
shorter than the WT, ;20-33% (Supplementary Table S3 at 
JXB online; Fig. 6A). GA application caused a rapid stem 
elongation with a concomitant suppression in root de-
velopment in all treated plants; however, these responses 
were much less in the case of Group-1 (Supplementary 
Table S3 at JXB online; Fig. 6B). </p>

<p>Flowering characteristics </p>

<p>GAs are involved in the developmental events leading to 
reproductive competence, as well as in floral determination 
and commitment (Cheng et al., 2004; Rieu et al., 2008b). 
The flowering time was considerably delayed in Group-1 
transgenics (+5.6360.7 d) and accelerated in Group-2 
(-6.9360.7 d) relative to the WT (Supplementary Table S4 
at JXB online). GA application noticeably restored flower-
ing time in Group-1; however, it did not significantly 
influence Group-2. PAC and SD conditions substantially 
retarded the transition to flowering in Group-1 by ;20 d 
and ;65 d, respectively. However, Group-2 treated with 
PAC or exposed to SD started flowering ;10 d earlier than 
the corresponding WT. 
WT Arabidopsis flowers exhibit a typical coordinated 
flower structure that ensures proper self-pollination. Group-1 
plants displayed generally smaller flowers and their filaments </p>

<p>Fig. 3. (A and B) Close-up views of EG/M and EG/D flowers and fruits, respectively, before and after GA application. (C) The changes in 
EG/D fruit size and weight, before and after GA treatment, compared with their counterpart in EG/M fruit. </p>



<p>were usually shorter than their pistils. A similar flower 
structure was observed in Group-2, but this was largely due 
to acceleration of pistil growth (Supplementary Table S4 at 
JXB online; Fig. 7). Such variation between the stamens and 
pistil can cause a major reduction in fertility, especially in 
self-pollinated species. GA application visibly changed the 
flower structure. In Group-1, the flower size, pistil and 
stamen lengths were mostly restored; however, the stamen 
remained shorter than the pistil. In contrast, GA reduced 
overall Group-2 flower size without a visible change in 
structure. In general, PAC and SD treatments reduced the 
size of the various floral organs. In the case of Group-1, SD 
conditions significantly affected pistil elongation, resulting in 
filaments much longer than the pistils. Although Group-2 
pistil length was also reduced due to SD, the flowers were 
generally larger than SD-grown WT. </p>

<p>Role of PslGA2ox in floral organ patterning </p>

<p>Arabidopsis flowers consist of a precise pattern of organs 
arranged in four concentric whorls. In addition to the 
regular flowers, all Group-1 members also exhibited fused 
flowers (Fig. 8A). These abnormal flowers hold eight short 
stamens with often fasciated filaments (Fig. 8B). In some 
instances, the stamens were completely malformed beyond 
recognition (Fig. 8C). Additionally, they also had two 
separate, functional pistils, as they progressed towards 
maturity (Fig. 8B, D). Such fused flowers were alternatively 
arranged in a pre-set pattern along with regular flowers 
within the whole plant (Fig. 8E). In spite of these defects, 
both the pollen and pistil seemed to be at least partially 
viable as pollen germination and occasional seed set could 
be observed. These results indicate that Group-1 plants 
exhibited major disorder in the floral organ identity pro-</p>

<p>cedure, while GA treatment along with LD conditions was 
largely enough to recover all defects in plant development 
including floral organogenesis (Supplementary Fig. S7A at 
JXB online). To investigate the cause of floral organogene-
sis deformities, the expression profile of a set of genes 
involved in floral patterning, such as LFY and the floral 
homeotic genes from classes B (AP3 and PI) and C (AG), 
were studied (Parcy et al., 1998; Lohmann and Weigel,  2002). Relative to the WT, accumulation of all studied 
transcripts dramatically decreased in L.1/G1 (Supplemen-
tary Fig. S7B at JXB online). Thus, it was decided to 
examine further the potential involvement of GA in the 
promotion of floral-related gene expression. Interestingly, 
GA treatment restored the regular flower patterning as well 
as the levels of all studied genes (Supplementary Fig. S7A, 
B at JXB online). Growing Group-1 mutants under SD 
increased the disturbance in the floral organs (Fig. 9). The 
whole plant exhibited flowers with reduced number of 
stamens that were not consistent either in thickness or in 
length. Some flowers displayed fasciations of stamens at 
filaments and/or anthers (Fig. 9A). In other flowers, the 
stamens fused to other floral organs such as petals or carpel, 
and the anthers were malformed (Fig. 9B, C). In yet other 
cases, the filament was totally absent, resulting in anthers 
fused directly to the base (Fig. 9D). The stamens also show 
other deformities such as rudimentary anthers on unusual 
thick filamentous structure (Fig. 9E), such that the filament 
and the anther could not properly differentiate. Similarly, 
an abnormal short and thick stigma was also observed. In 
such cases, the ovary is often split, exposing the ovules (Fig. 
9E). Consequently, such disruptions in the flower organo-
genesis caused complete sterility. The results showed that all 
these major disorders were associated with low or almost 
undetectable floral patterning transcripts. Interestingly, 
treatment of Group-1 plants under SD conditions with GA 
recovered the different aspects of the plant growth pattern 
to near normal (Supplementary Fig. S7C, D at JXB online). </p>

<p>Fruit growth and development </p>

<p>The time from pollination to silique occurrence was not 
significantly altered in Group-2 mutants compared with the 
WT in different growth conditions or treatments. In 
contrast, silique formation was delayed by ;4.1 d in 
Group-1, which could be partially restored by GA. How-
ever, both PAC and SD caused a dramatic delay in silique 
emergence of Group-1 plants (Supplementary Table S4 at 
JXB online). Moreover, WT and Group-2 siliques matured 
at about the same time, while Group-1 siliques shattered at 
least ;7.2 d later. GA treatment delayed silique maturity; 
however, both mutant groups displayed a substantially 
longer time than GA-treated WT to reach maturity. PAC 
and SD treatments remarkably delayed Group-1 silique 
maturation (;13 d and ;27 d, respectively). In contrast, 
Group-2 siliques significantly shattered earlier. Further-
more, both silique length and seed number were drastically 
reduced in both mutant groups (Supplementary Table S5 at 
JXB online; Fig. S8). Siliques of Group-1 and -2 were </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Steady-state transcript levels of PslGA2ox mRNA assessed 
by qRT-PCR in EG/M flowers and throughout fruit ontogeny. 
During S1 and S2 of fruit development, the expression was 
determined in the whole fruit. However, during S3 and S4, the 
expression was determined in pulp (black filled bars) and in seeds 
(grey filled bars). The experiments were carried out in three 
biological replicates, and error bars represent the SD. The y-axis 
refers to the mean molecules of PslGA2ox per reaction/mean 
molecules of PsAct. The x-axis represents the developmental 
stages indicated by the number of days after bloom (DAB). </p>

<p>GA inactivation and plant development | 1231 </p>

<p>reduced in length by ;68% and 30%, respectively. Even 
more strikingly, both mutants exhibited a reduction in seed 
content by ;96% and 61%, respectively. Most Group-1 
seeds were not completely developed as determined by their 
flat shape and low germination. Both mutants strongly 
responded to GA application; however, their responses were 
contradictory. In Group-2, GA caused inhibition in silique 
length and seed number. In contrast, Group-1 siliques 
elongated greatly along with increased seed content; how-
ever, both traits remained less than in the WT. PAC and SD </p>

<p>significantly suppressed both traits, although Group-2 
exhibited more tolerance for these GA-limiting conditions. 
In addition, all Group-1 siliques were short, thin, usually 
seedless, and ;42% of them exhibited a twisted shape 
(Supplementary Fig. S9 at JXB online); and this phenotype 
continued throughout the entire plant ontogeny. GA 
treatment resulted in full recovery of silique shape. Appar-
ently, Group-1 bent siliques seem to be a result of unequal 
distribution of GA levels between the two silique sides 
resulting in differential elongation rate. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. (A) Aerial portions of WT and the two phenotype groups resulting from ectopic expression of PslGA2ox in Arabidopsis under LD 
conditions. (B) PslGA2ox accumulation in the WT and the different transgenic mutants. (C and D) The expression of the different GA-
responsive genes in the WT and a representative from each group of mutants (L.1 and L.4) in the absence (C) and presence (D) of GA. 
Transcripts accumulation was determined using qRT-PCR on three biological replicates. Standard curves were used to calculate the 
numbers of target gene molecules per sample, which were then normalized relative to AtAct expression. </p>



<p>Group-2 mutants show sensitivity to exogenous GA </p>

<p>Endogenous GA levels are the result of an antagonistic 
reaction between GA biosynthesis and inactivation mecha-
nisms (Hedden and Phillips, 2000). Therefore, any distur-
bance in this machinery can modify the accumulation of 
active GAs (Rieu et al., 2008a, b). Previous data illustrated 
that Group-2 exhibited much higher sensitivity to GA than 
the WT. Application of GA caused a major reduction in 
silique length of both the WT and L.4/G2. In order to 
confirm this inhibitory consequence of GA, WT and L.4/G2 
plants were treated with gradually increasing concentrations 
of GA (Supplementary Fig. S10A at JXB online). Significant 
reduction in L.4/G2 silique elongation occurred with a GA 
concentration of 5 lM; however, the WT responded only to 
50 lM GA concentrations (Supplementary Fig. S10B). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Ten dwarf plum hybrids due to deficiency of unknown GA 
signalling were identified. Then, a cDNA sequence encoding 
GA 2-oxidase (PslGA2ox), the major GA catabolic enzyme 
in plants, was used to screen the 10 hybrids. This resulted in 
the identification of a plum hybrid (DGO24) that showed 
extremely high PslGA2ox accumulation, concomitant with 
low accumulation of bioactive GA 1 and GA 4 . The irregular 
growth pattern of DGO24, including the compact stature 
and deformed flowers, is transmissible to the scion in 
grafted trees, to a certain extent. Thus, it is possible to </p>

<p>interpret this to mean that DGO24 rootstock may be 
involved in the inactivation of bioactive GAs within the 
scion part, which is further supported by the low amount of 
active GAs in EG/D compared with control trees. 
PslGA2ox is a member of class I GA2oxs, which catalyse 
the conversion of active C 19 -GAs into inactive forms by 2b-
hydroxylation. As a consequence of lack of any apparent 
targeting sequence in GA2ox proteins, they were assumed 
to be cytosolic enzymes (Sun, 2008). The present results 
showed that PslGA2ox protein is localized in both the 
cytoplasm and the nucleus. Interestingly, the GA receptors 
(GID1s) also exhibit a similar localization behaviour 
(Ueguchi-Tanaka et al., 2005), suggesting that GA2oxs act 
as GID1s by binding the bioactive GAs with high affinity, 
but to convert them into inactive forms. 
In tree fruit crops, dwarfism induced due to GA deficiency 
is an advantage; however, synchronized levels of endogenous 
GA are still very important to ensure correct fruit de-
velopment and production (Serrano et al., 2007). EG/D trees 
exhibited a significant delay in fruit development. The re-
establishment of fruit development is dependent on the 
availability of sufficient GA in the appropriate developmen-
tal stages, when the requirements for GAs are essential. 
Dunberg and Odén (1983) showed that the active GA 4 is the 
most effective GA form leading to flowering promotion and 
reproductive growth. Thus, the scarcity of overall active GA 
content, particularly GA 4 , within EG/D trees can explain the 
distortion in flower structure and the delay in flowering 
events as well as the shift of the overall fruit ripening date. 
Consequently, determining the role of GA during fruit 
ontogeny has convenient implications in understanding and 
controlling the fruit development process. 
Studies on the effect of GA on plant growth and 
development have been hindered by their low abundance 
and variation in forms, time, and localization. However, 
examining the expression of genes encoding enzymes in-
volved in GA biosynthesis and catabolism provides an 
alternative approach for such studies. Interestingly, the 
evolution of PslGA2ox accumulation was generally aligned 
with the quantification of bioactive GAs during plum fruit 
development (Yamaguchi and Takahashi, 1976; Bukvoac  and Yuda, 1979; this study). Analysis of the PslGA2ox 
expression profile indicated that GAs play important roles 
in fruit development, mainly throughout immature stages 
before ripening. In flowers, the abundance of PslGA2ox 
transcripts suggested a dominant task of GA in promoting 
flowering and elucidated the role of PslGA2ox enzyme in 
regulating GA accumulation during this stage (Dunberg  and Odén, 1983; Pharis and King, 1985). 
Throughout fruit development, it is almost certain that 
the series of modifications that make the fruit proceed 
through the consequent developmental stages involve many 
different metabolic pathways. So far, only the hormone 
auxin has been demonstrated to be involved in the 
developmental program of Prunus fruit (Miller et al., 1987;  El-Sharkawy et al., 2008, 2009, 2010). However, previous 
studies suggested cross-talk between GA and other hor-
mones in the regulation of different plant development </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Representative 15-day-old seedlings primary roots of WT, 
L.1, and L.4 genotypes. Plants were grown in MS medium 
(Murashige and Skoog, 1962) without or with (100 lM) GA 3 . 
Bar¼10 mm. </p>

<p>GA inactivation and plant development | 1233 </p>

<p>events, in particular with auxin in processes such as fruit set 
and development (Fleet and Sun, 2005; de Jong et al., 2009;  Csukasi et al., 2011). Additionally, in Prunus spp., the 
evolution of the plant hormones auxin and GA was found 
to exhibit a similar pattern during fruit development 
(Yamaguchi and Takahashi, 1976, Miller et al., 1987). 
Furthermore, earlier studies in Prunus showed the stimula-
tory effect of exogenous auxin and GA on enhancing fruit 
development (Jackson, 1968; El-Sharkawy et al., 2010; this  study). Taken together, apparently during plum fruit 
growth, in particular during S1, S3, and S4 phases, the 
actions of auxin and GA are not independent of each other 
but are coordinated to regulate the progression of fruit 
development, as has been proposed previously in other 
plant systems (Serrani et al., 2007; Csukasi et al., 2011). 
Recent studies reported that the growth of seeded tomato 
fruits is coordinated by a delicate balance between auxin 
and GA (de Jong et al., 2009), where auxin is needed 
to mediate the rate of cell division, and GA is required to 
organize cell expansion. The mutual effect of the two 
phytohormones was further validated in the development 
of parthenocarpic fruit. Either auxin or GA treatment can 
promote parthenocarpic tomato fruit growth, whereas 
neither of them alone was able to maintain the growth rate </p>

<p>to the end of ripening. Only the joint application of both 
hormones resulted in parthenocarpic fruits similar to those 
obtained by pollination (Serrani et al., 2007). This is 
accurate for the different developmental stages, excluding 
the S2 phase. As mentioned previously, during the S2 stage 
there is hardly any increase in fruit size (no evidence of cell 
division and the expansion process), which coincided with 
a significant reduction in auxin content (Miller et al., 1987). 
Therefore, the accumulation of GAs during the S2 stage 
seems to be due to the lignification of the endocarp to form 
a solid stone, which is the only developmental process 
occurring during this stage. Biemelt et al. (2004) demon-
strated that GA mediates lignin formation and deposition 
by polymerization of pre-formed monomers. 
Further, in terms of gene expression, it was noted that 
during fruit maturation and ripening (S3 and S4) when the 
seed separated from the pulp, the signal of PslGA2ox 
detected in the developing seeds was almost 6-fold higher 
than its counterpart in the pulp. Also, PslGA2ox displayed 
a contrasting accumulation profile between fruit pulp and 
seed. The up-regulation of the transcript in the pulp usually 
coincided with its down-regulation in the seed. Accordingly, 
it seems that seed is mainly responsible for GA biosynthesis 
within the plum fruit; however, both seed and pulp could be </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Close-up views of WT, L.1, and L.4 flowers from plants exposed to several growth conditions: LDs, GA, PAC, and SDs. Sepals 
and petals were removed to reveal the anthers and pistil. Bar¼10 mm. </p>



<p>the site of action of this hormone depending on GA 
requirement. Previous studies suggest that as seed germina-
tion proceeds, the GA-dependent transcriptional events are 
not restricted to the sites of GA biosynthesis (Ogawa et al.,  2003). However, there are other cases where bioactive GA is 
produced at their site of action (Kaneko et al., 2003;  Csukasi et al., 2011). Further, the role of seeds in stone 
fruit development was determined by Jackson (1968) and 
Miller et al. (1987) who provided evidence that seeds 
stimulate fruit growth and ripening by providing auxins 
and GAs. 
Ectopic expression of PslGA2ox in Arabidopsis generated 
two groups of plants that exhibited two contradictory 
phenotypes. Group-1 displayed a typical GA-deficient 
phenotype and consequently exhibited substantial disorder 
in all GA-regulated transcripts. Interestingly, both Group-1 
mutants and EG/D trees displayed many common GA-
deficient growth traits, including compact vegetative growth 
and general disturbance in reproductive development events, 
which is indicative of the role of PslGA2ox in producing this 
phenotype. The previous growth properties along with the 
accelerated root formation are a common behaviour in GA-
deficient mutants (Koornneef and van der Veen, 1980;  Griffiths et al., 2006; Rieu et al., 2008b; Gou et al., 2010). 
Although the disturbances in the flowering characteristics 
were the most pronounced outcome in Group-1 mutants, it </p>

<p>still can produce flowers. Previous reports indicated that the 
development of floral organs is usually interrupted in GA-
deficient plants (Goto and Pharis, 1999; Cheng et al., 2004)  or in plants incapable of responding to GA (Griffiths et al.,  2006), which triggers flower infertility. However, most of 
these mutants remained leaky to some degree, and can 
produce small amounts of active GAs, sufficient to induce 
flowering even under severe GA growth conditions such as 
SDs (Wilson et al., 1992). In Arabidopsis, development of 
floral organs is under the control of homeotic genes that 
must be accessible to maintain the typical organogenesis 
process (Weigel and Meyerowitz, 1994). In Group-1 flowers 
under LDs or SDs, transcripts of the different floral organ 
identity genes were significantly lower, which can explain 
the abnormal flower formation. However, the plant pheno-
type along with the expression profile of homeotic genes 
before and after GA treatment suggests its essentiality to 
maintain their accumulation and subsequently have a cor-
rect flower patterning (Lohmann and Weigel, 2002;  Eriksson et al., 2006; this study). Arabidopsis is a facultative 
LD plant and its flowering is controlled by the interplay 
between three different pathways: LDs, an autonomous 
pathway, and the GA pathway. However, only the GA 
pathway plays a central role in the control of flower 
initiation under SDs (Mouradov et al., 2002; Boss et al.,  2004; Putterill et al., 2004). Apparently growing Group-1 </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Close-up views of defective L.1 flowers under LD (A). The arrowheads indicate the fused filaments (B) and stamen-like organ (C). 
The circle in (D) indicates the connection region between the twin siliques. (E) The frequency of the twin silique pattern in an 
inflorescence. </p>

<p>GA inactivation and plant development | 1235 </p>

<p>members under LDs alone can relatively minimize, but not 
prevent, the disturbance in the floral organogenesis pro-
cedure (Weigel et al., 1992). However, the disorders under 
SDs were more severe, and this is largely due to the critical 
LFY levels that are the target of photoperiodic regulation 
(Blázquez et al., 1997) and GA (Eriksson et al., 2006). 
Consequently, GA treatment resulted in proper re-
establishment of most Group-1 growth deformities under 
both LDs and SDs, including vegetative growth and floral 
organogenesis through restoring the accumulation profile of 
the various GA-regulated transcripts especially those of 
floral organ identity mRNAs. 
In contrast, in Group-2 plants, PslGA2ox insertion 
somehow caused co-suppression of the closely related 
Arabidopsis homologous AtGA2ox2 and AtGA2ox3 that 
probably lead to an overall increase in active GAs (Rieu  et al., 2008a). Consequently, the different GA-related tran-
scripts accumulated in a manner resembling unlimited GA 
conditions. Further, at the phenotypical level, Group-2 
mutants demonstrated a characteristic 'GA overdose' 
growth pattern (Sun, 2000). Fleet and Sun (2005) reported 
that plants exhibiting a GA overdose phenotype showed 
excessive growth and increased sterility, suggesting the 
importance of optimal GA levels to ensure proper growth 
and development. The overall growth pattern of Group-2 
plants resembled that of ga2ox quintuple mutant (Rieu  et al., 2008a) or those of GA-treated WT plants. The 
present results showed that any additional GA caused 
contradictory responses in Group-2, probably due to reach-
ing lethal levels of the hormone. Synchronized elongation 
of the pistil and filament is essential to ensure efficient </p>

<p>pollination within the flower. High levels of GA can induce 
male sterility and cause excessive elongation of the pistil 
(Sawhney and Shukla, 1994; Colombo and Favret, 1996). 
Plants carrying mutations in the biosynthetic (GA20oxs) or 
catabolic genes (C 19 -GA2oxs) exhibited extended pistils, 
resulting in partial infertility (Rieu et al., 2008a, b). A loss 
of fertility has also been described for WT plants treated 
with GA (Jacobsen and Olszewski, 1993) and for double 
mutants in the GA signalling repressors, RGA and GAI 
(Dill and Sun, 2001). Here, it is shown that Group-2 plants 
behaved similarly, which appears to be due to increased 
length of the pistil relative to the stamen that consequently 
reduces the self-pollination efficiency. Apparently, many 
GA-dependent mechanisms might be quite saturated within 
this group. Any additional GA results in serious disruptions 
of growth and development. The inhibitory effect of GA 
was clearly demonstrated by treating L.4/G2 with gradually 
increasing GA concentrations, which caused a significant 
reduction in silique length using 10-fold lower GA concen-
trations compared with the WT. The growth pattern of 
Group-2 plants under GA-deprived conditions further con-
firms the GA overdose phenotype. Rieu et al. (2008a)  observed that PAC-treated ga2ox quintuple mutant exhibited 
a general growth spurt in comparison with treated WT. 
Further, PAC-treated and SD-grown L.4 plants exhibited 
earlier flowering onset, earlier silique maturation, and larger 
siliques than the WT exposed to the same conditions. 
Rootstocks play a key role in improving and eventually 
stabilizing productivity in perennial crops, as they can adapt 
to diverse environmental conditions, which makes rootstock 
breeding as important as creating new varieties. </p>

<p>Fig. 9. Developmental defects of L.1 floral organ structure due to SDs. The arrowheads indicate the fused filaments and anthers (A), stamens 
fused to petals (B), the stamen-like organ fused to the carpel (C), the anther fused directly to the base (D), abnormal stamen structure (E), and 
stamen formed inside the ovules accompanied by opened ovule phenotype. </p>



<p>Manipulation of plant stature, through classical plant 
breeding or use of plant growth regulators, has long been 
a major goal in tree fruit horticulture. Though the use of 
'anti-GA' growth regulators showed success in controlling 
plant stature, efficient size reduction in perennial species, 
such as plums, requires repeated application of synthetic 
chemicals, which can be costly both commercially and 
environmentally. Therefore, selection and use of dwarf 
rootstocks that exhibits GA deficiency provides an environ-
mentally attractive approach. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at JXB online. 
Figure S1. Amino acid sequence alignment of PslGA2ox 
with closely related GA2ox sequences using the ClustalX 
program. 
Figure S2. The full-length PsGA2ox gene was fused to the 
GFP tag. Nicotiana tabacum protoplasts were transfected 
with the following constructs: (A) the control 35S::GFP and 
(B) PslGA2ox::GFP. 
Figure S4. View of EG/M, DGO24, and EG/D trees 
under field conditions. 
Figure S5. Branches from EG/M (A) and EG/D before 
(B) and after GA application (C). 
Figure S6. Aerial portions of WT, L.1, and L.4 plants 
exposed to several growth conditions, sprayed with 100 lM 
GA 3 , treated with 10 lM PAC, and short days (SD). 
Figure S7. Close-up view of L.1 plants and defective 
flowers which resulted under LD (A) or SD (C) conditions 
with and without GA treatment. (B and D) Transcript 
accumulation of the Arabidopsis floral meristem identity 
gene (LFY) and floral homeotic genes (AP3, PI, and AG) 
assessed by qRT-PCR in inflorescence apices of WT and 
L.1 plants grown under LDs (B) or SDs (D) with and 
without GA treatment. 
Figure S8. Close-up views of WT, L.1, and L.4 siliques 
from plants exposed to several growth conditions, LDs, 
GA, PAC, and SDs. 
Figure S9. Close-up views of twisted L.1 siliques and the 
suppression of such a phenotype by GA application during 
different stages of silique development. 
Figure S10. Representative image (A) and growth pattern 
(B) of the inhibitory effect of GA on WT and L.4 silique 
elongation. 
Table S1. Oligonucleotide primers. 
Table S2. Stem growth phenotype characterization of WT 
and transgenic Arabidopsis plants expressing PslGA2ox as 
shown in Fig. 5. 
Table S3. The effect of GA treatment on root elongation 
of WT and transgenic Arabidopsis plants expressing 
PslGA2ox as shown in Fig. 6. 
Table S4. Flower growth phenotype characterization of 
WT and transgenic Arabidopsis plants expressing PslGA2ox. 
Table S5. Silique growth phenotype characteristics of WT 
and transgenic Arabidopsis plants expressing PslGA2ox as 
shown in Supplementary Fig. S7. </p>



<p>GA inactivation and plant development | 1237 </p>







<p>GA inactivation and plant development | 1239 </p>

</text></tei>