<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3890939" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>One of key issues in studying iron based superconductors is to understand how the magnetic phase of the 
parent compounds evolves. Here we report the systematic investigation of paramagnetic to 
antiferromagnetic and tetragonal to orthorhombic structural transitions of ''122'' SrFe 2 As 2 parent 
compound using combined high resolution synchrotron Mössbauer spectroscopy and x-ray diffraction 
techniques in a cryogenically cooled high pressure diamond anvil cell. It is found that although the two 
transitions are coupled at 205 K at ambient pressure, they are concurrently suppressed to much lower 
temperatures near a quantum critical pressure of approximately 4.8 GPa where the antiferromagnetic state 
transforms into bulk superconducting state. Our results indicate that the lattice distortions and magnetism 
jointly play a critical role in inducing superconductivity in iron based compounds. </p>

<p>environments. This sheds new light on the interplay of the lattice 
distortions and magnetism in the origin of superconductivity in the 
iron-based superconductors at high pressures and low temperatures. </p>

<p>Results 
SMS spectra were collected up to 5.4 GPa and temperatures as low as 
15 K, while XRD patterns were measured up to 8.2 GPa and 13 K 
(Figs. 1, 2). Fig. 1(a) shows representative pressure-dependent </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>Fe 
SMS spectra of SrFe 2 As 2 at 15 K. At 1.4 GPa and 15 K, the drastic 
appearance of quantum beats manifests the splitting of 
57 Fe nuclear 
level through hyperfine interaction, showing the AFM state. As pres-
sure was increased to 4.3 GPa, the SMS spectrum changed signifi-
cantly with the disappearance of the quantum beats, indicating that 
the magnetic phase had been suppressed via applied pressure at 15 K 
while the PM state started to appear. Since the spectrum could not be 
reasonably fitted using only paramagnetic or magnetic phases, both 
paramagnetic and magnetic phases were used to model the SMS 
spectrum at 4.3 GPa. Analyses of the modeled results showed that 
the magnetic phase accounts for approximately 42 vol.% of the two 
phases. At a higher pressure of approximately 5.4 GPa, the 
57 Fe 
nuclear level is characterized by flat spectral features without any 
splitting quantum beats, indicating the sole existence of the PM state 
with the completely suppressed magnetism by pressure. The derived 
hyperfine parameters show an abrupt increase in the strength of the 
magnetic fields as a function of temperature at a given pressure 
(Fig. 1(b)). For example, at 2.5 GPa the hyperfine magnetic field </p>

<p>Figure 1 | (a) Representative pressure dependent SMS spectra of SrFe 2 As 2 </p>

<p>at 15 K in Ne medium. Open circles: experimental data; red solid lines: 
modeled spectra using <rs type="software">CONUSS</rs> program. Quantum beats in the spectra 
represent the occurrence of the magnetic field and hence the AFM state, 
whereas the absence of the beats (flat spectral feature) is indicative of the 
PM state. (b) Derived hyperfine magnetic fields of the AFM SrFe 2 As 2 as a 
function of temperature at representative high pressures. Appearance and 
disappearance of the magnetic fields are used to construct the magnetic 
PM-AFM transition as a function of P-T. Filled symbol: AFM state; open 
symbol: PM state. (c) Derived hyperfine magnetic fields of SrFe 2 As 2 as a 
function pressure at 15 K. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | (a) Representative synchrotron angle-dispersive x-ray </p>

<p>diffraction of SrFe 2 As 2 as a function of pressure at 13 K. Splitting of the 220 
reflection to 400/040 is indicative of the tetragonal to orthorhombic 
transition at high pressures. Ort: orthorhombic phase; Tet: tetragonal 
phase. At 4.7 GPa, the orthorhombic and tetragonal phases coexist at 13 K. 
(b) Variation of lattice parameters with pressure at 13 K. (c) Volume 
fraction of the orthorhombic phase as a function of pressure at 13 K. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 3685 | DOI: 10.1038/srep03685 </p>

<p>
jumped to 6.7 T from zero as temperature was decreased to 160 K 
and then remains almost constant, indicating a PM to AFM trans-
ition. As pressure increases (Fig. 1(b)), the hyperfine magnetic field 
decreases and the magnetic transition region slightly broadens, 
implying suppressed magnetism by applied pressure; magnetism 
was totally suppressed at 5.1 GPa at each given low temperature as 
shown in Fig. 1(c). 
In order to clarify the relationship between the structural and 
magnetic transitions, we have also performed XRD experiments 
under high pressures and low temperatures (Figs. 2). Analyses of 
the high-pressure XRD spectra showed that the (220) reflection of 
the tetragonal phase splits to (400) and (040) reflections that are 
characteristic of the tetragonal to orthorhombic structural transition 
in SrFe 2 As 2 with decreasing temperature at a given pressure </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>. 
Similar to the magnetic transition, this structural transition is 
strongly suppressed by pressure (Fig. 2(a)). At a constant temper-
ature of 13 K, derived lattices parameters in Fig. 2(b) show the exist-
ence of the orthorhombic phase (space group: Fmmm) below 4 GPa 
and the tetragonal phase (space group: I4/mmm) above 6 GPa, 
respectively, whereas there is a P-T region between 4 GPa and 
6 GPa, in which the tetragonal and orthorhombic phases coexist. 
With increasing pressure, the orthorhombic phase observed in the 
region is suppressed while the abundance of the tetragonal phase is 
enhanced (Fig. 2(c)). 
Combining our synchrotron SMS and XRD results (Figs. 1-2) 
with literature high T c studies, we have constructed the structural, 
magnetic, and superconducting phase diagram of SrFe 2 As 2 under 
high pressures and low temperatures (Fig. 3). The magnetic trans-
ition temperature (T N ) was defined as the mid-point between the first 
appearance of the hyperfine magnetic field and the last appearance of </p>

<p>the paramagnetic phase, while the structural transition temperature 
(T S ) was defined as the mid-point from the pure tetragonal to the 
pure orthorhombic structural phase transition; for the co-existence 
of the tetragonal and orthorhombic phases at 13 K, the T S is defined 
as the point of disappearance for the orthorhombic phase. At ambi-
ent pressure, previous studies showed that the structural transition 
concurs with the magnetic transition </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>. Our results here further 
show that, within experimental uncertainties, these two transitions 
are strongly coupled at high pressures and low temperatures (Fig. 3), 
except the P-T region overlap starting with the T c dome where an 
extended P-T region of the two-phase coexistence was observed (see 
further details in Discussions). These transition temperatures 
decrease with increasing pressures up to approximately 4.6 GPa, 
but are drastically suppressed to zero at a quantum critical pressure 
(P C ) of 4.8 GPa. </p>

<p>Discussions 
As discussed in the previous studies of the ''122'' system, differential 
stress can strongly affect the critical pressure in the BaFe 2 As 2 and 
SrFe 2 As 2 compounds </p>

<p>29-31 </p>

<p>. In order to draw a more direct, meaningful 
comparison with literature results, our structural and magnetic 
results are plotted on top of the superconducting transition from 
Ref. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>, which reported electrical resistivity and ac magnetic suscept-
ibility measurements using a relatively hydrostatic glycerin medium 
that is similar in hydrostaticity to Ne medium used in our experi-
ments. Comparisons of these results show that filamentary super-
conductivity with zero resistivity emerges with the occurrence of the 
tetragonal phase co-existing with the orthorhombic phase in the 
AFM state at around 4.2 GPa and 13 K. Our results also imply that 
filamentary superconductivity can only coexist with the partial mag-
netism in the mixed tetragonal and orthorhombic region in the 
SrFe 2 As 2 at temperatures below 28 K and pressures between 4.2 
and 4.8 GPa as shown in the filled purple region in Fig. 3. 
Furthermore, bulk superconductivity, as observed by an anomaly 
in the field cooling (FC) magnetic susceptibility, only appears in 
the P-T region with the tetragonal phase in the PM state, where 
the T S and T N transitions are fully suppressed. Based on both dif-
fraction and Mössbauer results, the volume fraction of the AFM 
orthorhombic phase as a function of pressure appears to be inversely 
proportional to the high T c (Figs. 2 and 3), further supporting the 
notion that the superconductivity is partially suppressed by the exist-
ence of magnetism in the AFM orthorhombic phase. Thus we assume 
the presence of an AFM quantum critical point (QCP) near the AFM 
phase boundary. Previous NMR experiments indicate an antiferro-
magnetic fluctuation associated with QCP has strong correlation 
with the high-T c superconductivity in chemically-doped BaFe 2 As 2 
compounds </p>

<p>32,33 </p>

<p>. These results indicate that the QCP is likely to con-
nect with the superconductivity in the iron based compound. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Single-crystal SrFe 2 As 2 samples with 20 at.% 
57 Fe enrichment were grown using the 
FeAs self-flux method </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>. XRD analyses of the synthesized samples showed lattice 
parameters of a 5 3.9234(3) Å and c 5 12.371(2) Å at ambient conditions. A sample 
measuring 15 mm thick and 70 mm big was loaded into a symmetric DAC using Ne as 
the pressure medium, together with three ruby spheres for pressure calibration at low 
temperatures. The pressure of the sample chamber was controlled using a membrane 
diaphragm. A helium flow cold-finger cryostat was used to cool down the DAC to as 
low as 10 K; temperatures of the DAC were equilibrated after each cooling and were 
measured using two thermocouples attached to each side of the DAC. Temperature 
uncertainties were less than 5 K. SMS measurements with a resonant energy (E 0 ) of 
14.4125 keV for </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>Fe were performed at the undulator beamline 16-IDD of the 
Advanced Photon Source (APS), Argonne National Laboratory (ANL). The energy 
band-width of the undulator beam was monochromotized to approximately 2 meV 
bandwidth using a water-cooled diamond (1 1 1) double crystal monochromator and 
a high resolution monochromator consisting of 2 channel cut silicon crystals (Si(4 4 
0) and Si(9 7 5)). A pair of KB mirrors was used to focus the x-ray beam to 
approximately 50 mm at the sample position in the DAC. SMS spectra were collected 
using an avalanche photodiode detector at the nuclear forward scattering geometry 
with a collection time of 1-2 hours. SMS spectra were collected in the form of the 
intensity of the </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>Fe nuclear decay as a function of time. When the nuclei in the sample </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Magnetic and structural transition diagram of SrFe 2 As 2 at high </p>

<p>pressures and low temperatures. XRD data: blue diamond symbols (l 5 
0.4047 Å ) and blue square symbols (l 5 0.3737 Å ); SMS data: red circle 
symbols. T S (blue dash line) and T N (red dash line) are extracted from 
analyses of the data in order to define the structural and magnetic 
transition conditions. The superconducting transition temperature T C 
with grey solid line for filamentary SC, as well as T S with darker grey solid 
line for the structural transition is taken from Ref. 25 using single crystals in 
a cubic anvil having glycerin pressure medium, that were similar to our 
experimental conditions. A quantum critical phase transition at a P c of 4.8 
GPa is suggested. Tet: tetragonal structure; Ort: orthorhombic structure; 
AFM: antiferromagnetic; PM: paramagnetic. The half-filled red circles 
represent for the coexistence of PM and AFM phases, while the half-filled 
blue squares represent for the coexistence of Ort and Tet phases. The filled 
purple region represents for the coexistence of filamentary 
superconductivity, AFM Ort and PM Tet phases. Pressure uncertainties are 
smaller to the symbols, whereas temperature uncertainties are less than 5 K. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 3685 | DOI: 10.1038/srep03685 </p>

<p>
are excited by the synchrotron radiation pulse of 14.4125 meV with a bandwidth of 
11 meV, the coherent decay of the excited ensemble of nuclei phases with time. 
Through analyses of the time-resolved intensity of the SMS spectra, hyperfine 
parameters, including hyperfine magnetic fields, containing structural and electronic 
information of the resonating nucleus can be derived. The high resolution (DE/E , 
1*10 </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>) of the SMS technique enables us to detect the AFM to PM phase transition of 
SrFe 2 As 2 at high pressures. The spectra were fitted using the <rs type="software">CONUSS</rs> program 
35 to 
derive hyperfine parameters including hyperfine magnetic fields of the Fe ions. 
Angle-dispersive XRD measurements were performed on powder samples at the 
16-IDB beamline of the APS, ANL. The powder samples were gently ground from the 
same batch of the </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>Fe-enriched single crystals used for SMS experiments and loaded 
into the same symmetric DAC using Ne pressure medium and ruby pressure 
calibrate. XRD measurements of the starting sample showed consistent lattice 
parameters to the single crystals. To avoid systematic errors, care was taken to ensure 
that experimental conditions between SMS and XRD experiments were consistent: 
the same cryostat with the same temperature thermocouples and membrane 
controller were used in both experiments. Two types of XRD experiments were 
conducted: decreasing temperatures at a constant pressure with an x-ray wavelength 
of 0.4072 Å ; increasing pressures at a constant temperature of 50 K or 13 K with 
an x-ray wavelength of 0.3737 Å . Diffraction patterns were collected by a MAR345 
detector and processed using the <rs type="software">FIT2D</rs> software. Rietveld refinements of the patterns 
were performed using the <rs type="software">GSAS</rs> package </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>. </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Work is supported by NFS and MOST of China through research projects. We appreciate C. 
Kenney-Benson for his assistance in setting up the cryogenic and online ruby systems at 
HPCAT. This work was performed at HPCAT (sector 16), Advanced Photon Source (APS), 
Argonne National Laboratory. HPCAT is supported by CIW, CDAC, UNLV and LLNL 
through funding from DOE-NNSA, DOE-BES and NFS. APS is supported by DOE-BES, 
under Contract No. DE-AC02-06CH11357. Work at UT Austin is supported by Energy 
Frontier Research in Extreme Environments (EFree). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>C.Q.J. and J.F.L. conceived &amp; designed the research; J.J.W., J.L.Z., X.C.W., Q.Q.L., Y.M.X. 
and P.C. conducted the experiments; J.J.W., J.F.L. and C.Q.J. wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Wu, J.J. et al. Magnetic and structural transitions of SrFe 2 As 2 at 
high pressure and low temperature. Sci. Rep. 4, 3685; DOI:10.1038/srep03685 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported license. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 3685 | DOI: 10.1038/srep03685 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>