<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3770329" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Apoptosis is a fundamental homeostatic mechanism essential for the normal growth, development and maintenance of every 
tissue and organ. Dying cells have been defined as apoptotic by distinguishing features, including cell contraction, nuclear 
fragmentation, blebbing, apoptotic body formation and maintenance of intact cellular membranes to prevent massive protein 
release and consequent inflammation. We now show that during early apoptosis limited membrane permeabilization occurs in 
blebs and apoptotic bodies, which allows release of proteins that may affect the proximal microenvironment before the 
catastrophic loss of membrane integrity during secondary necrosis. Blebbing, apoptotic body formation and protein release 
during early apoptosis are dependent on ROCK and myosin ATPase activity to drive actomyosin contraction. We identified 231 
proteins released from actomyosin contraction-dependent blebs and apoptotic bodies by adapted SILAC (stable isotope labeling 
with amino acids in cell culture) combined with mass spectrometry analysis. The most enriched proteins released were the 
nucleosomal histones, which have previously been identified as damage-associated molecular pattern proteins (DAMPs) that 
can initiate sterile inflammatory responses. These results indicate that limited membrane permeabilization occurs in blebs and 
apoptotic bodies before secondary necrosis, leading to acute and localized release of immunomodulatory proteins during the 
early phase of active apoptotic membrane blebbing. Therefore, the shift from apoptosis to secondary necrosis is more graded 
than a simple binary switch, with the membrane permeabilization of apoptotic bodies and consequent limited release of DAMPs 
contributing to the transition between these states. 
nuclear condensation and fragmentation, and actomyosin 
contraction-dependent membrane blebbing and apoptotic 
body formation. 10-12 The driving force behind apoptotic 
actomyosin contractility is caspase-mediated cleavage and 
consequent constitutive activation of ROCK1. 11,12 Blebs are 
formed when the plasma membrane delaminates from the 
cortical cytoskeletal network to form blisters that are 
expanded by increased hydrostatic pressure produced by 
actomyosin-mediated cellular contraction. 13,14 As apoptosis 
progresses, blebs may break away from the cell body to form 
membrane-clad apoptotic bodies. A common assumption is 
that apoptotic bodies have a passive role in apoptotic cell 
clearance simply because they are smaller and therefore 
more readily phagocytosed than the intact cell body. 15,16 
Moreover, inhibition of ROCK activity significantly reduces 
apoptotic body formation and apoptotic cell phagocytosis. 15,16 
Therefore, an additional possibility is that apoptotic bodies 
have active roles in promoting apoptotic cell clearance. 
Apoptotic cells signal their demise by displaying markers 
such as phosphatidylserine that help phagocytes dock to the 
dying cell via direct or bridged interactions with recognition 
receptors. 1,3 The membranes of apoptotic bodies present the 
same externalized signals to phagocytic cells, which similarly 
aids their recognition and clearance. However, we now show 
that unlike the membranes of the apoptotic cell body, a 
significant proportion of apoptotic body membranes do not 
form impermeable barriers, allowing for the limited macro-
molecule ingress and egress. Inhibition of actomyosin 
contraction through ROCK or myosin ATPase blockade 
reduces apoptotic body numbers formed during early apop-
tosis and concomitantly represses protein release without 
affecting the apoptotic program. Quantitative mass spectro-
metry (MS) identified nucleosomal histones, which are 
validated DAMPs, as the most highly enriched proteins 
released in an actomyosin-dependent manner before 
secondary necrosis. Stable isotope-labeled histones released 
from apoptotic cells were identified as being phagocytosed by 
macrophages. These results show that the progression from 
apoptosis to secondary necrosis does not occur as a two-state 
switch. Instead, as they are generated, the permeable 
membranes of apoptotic bodies allow the release of limited 
amounts of DAMPs that would locally engage with compo-
nents of the innate immune system, thereby providing a 
mechanism that would contribute to a phased transition 
between apoptosis and full-blown secondary necrosis. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Apoptotic bodies and blebs lose membrane integrity. 
The membrane-impermeable nucleic acid dye PI is often 
used in fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) to 
categorize dead cells as either apoptotic (PI excluded) or 
necrotic (PI permitted). 17 Despite the general application of 
this binary classification, we observed that apoptotic blebs in 
NIH3T3 fibroblasts treated with tumor necrosis factor a 
(TNFa) plus cycloheximide (CHX) can permit PI penetration 
while the cell body continues to exclude the nucleic acid stain 
(Figure 1a). Time-lapse microscopy revealed that shortly after 
blebbing onset (B4 h after TNFa/CHX treatment), newly formed 
blebs and apoptotic bodies (small membrane-encapsulated </p>

<p>subcellular particles that dissociate from blebbing cells) 
appear that do not exclude PI (Figure 1b, from 4 : 14 : 30, 
examples indicated by white, blue, yellow or red arrows). The 
membrane permeability of these newly formed structures 
precedes the loss of membrane integrity of the remaining cell 
body during secondary necrosis by a substantial period 
(Figure 1b, from 5 : 33 onwards). 
To characterize apoptotic body membrane permeability, we 
assessed PI staining of the apoptotic bodies released from 
NIH3T3 cells 4 h after TNFa/CHX treatment. Analysis of small 
subcellular debris (low forward scatter (FSC) and side scatter 
(SSC), Figure 2a first panel) revealed that a large subpopula-
tion of the 100 000 counted apoptotic bodies were PI positive 
(defined by gatings that count r1% of autofluorescent 
apoptotic bodies in the absence of PI, Figure 2a second 
panel), indicating that these apoptotic bodies not only 
contained nucleic acids but also allowed entry of 668 Da PI 
molecules (Figure 2a middle panel). Treatment of apoptotic 
bodies with RNAseA alone, or in combination with DNAse1, 
reduced PI staining (Figure 2a fourth and fifth panels), 
indicating that molecules as large as RNAseA and DNAse1 
(13 and 31 kDa, respectively) accessed the interior of 
apoptotic bodies and degraded nucleic acid cargo, thus 
reducing PI fluorescence. The reduction in PI staining by 
RNAse þ DNAse1 was significant (Po0.01) following the 
induction of apoptosis 4 h after treatment withTNFa/CHX, anti-
CD95 (Fas receptor) antibody/CHX or ultraviolet light (UV) in 
NIH3T3 established mouse fibroblasts (Figure 2b), primary 
mouse embryo fibroblasts (MEFs; Figure 2c), MCF10a 
human mammary epithelial cells (Figure 2d) and primary 
mouse keratinocytes (Figure 2e). These results indicate that 
whether the apoptotic stimulus was extrinsic or instrinsic, or 
whether the cells were primary or established, or epithelial or 
mesenchymal, a significant proportion of apoptotic bodies 
have membranes permissive for macromolecule passage. 
The permeability of apoptotic body membranes to macro-
molecules was additionally validated using NIH3T3 cells-
expressing membrane-tagged green fluorescent protein 
(mGFP; Figure 2f left panel). 18 Following the induction of 
apoptosis for 4 h, B33% of resulting apoptotic bodies had 
mGFP fluorescence greater than the autofluorescence of 
apoptotic bodies from unlabeled cells (Figure 2f right panel). 
Treatment with Proteinase K (MW ¼ 28 kDa) significantly 
(Po0.01) reduced the proportion of GFP-positive apoptotic 
bodies by 70%, indicating that most apoptotic bodies did not 
exclude Proteinase K (Figure 2g). When GFP-positive 
apoptotic bodies were incubated with PI in the absence or 
presence of RNAse þ DNAse1, PI staining of the 11% double 
GFP/PI-positive apoptotic bodies was significantly (Po0.01) 
reduced by over 50% through the actions of RNAse þ 
DNAse1 (Figures 2h and i). These observations indicate that 
many apoptotic bodies failed to exclude molecules as large as 
31 kDa, suggesting that their membranes also would allow 
comparably sized molecules to escape. </p>

<p>Actomyosin contractility drives apoptotic body formation 
and lactate dehydrogenase release. We previously 
showed that apoptotic membrane blebbing results from 
caspase-mediated cleavage and consequent activation 
of ROCK1 to drive actomyosin contraction. 6,11 Scanning </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>electron microscopy (SEM) confirmed that the typical 
pattern of membrane blebbing induced by TNFa/CHX could 
be blocked by the ROCK inhibitor Y27632 19 or the myosin 
ATPase inhibitor Blebbistatin 20 (Figure 3a). By collecting 
equal volumes of media from 100-mm diameter tissue culture 
dishes of NIH3T3 cells that were untreated or treated for 4 h 
with TNFa/CHX, and then adding equivalent numbers of </p>

<p>FITC-labeled polystyrene microbeads as a counting refer-
ence (Figure 3b, left and middle panels), FACS analysis 
revealed that the small number of low FSC/SSC particles 
was greatly and significantly (Po0.01) increased by TNFa/ 
CHX (Figure 3b, right panel), consistent with their being 
apoptotic bodies. Counting the apoptotic bodies from cells 
treated with TNFa/CHX, anti-CD95/CHX or UV in the </p>

<p>2 μm 
PI </p>

<p>Figure 1 Blebs and apoptotic bodies allow pre-necrotic entry of PI. (a) Live confocal image of apoptotic NIH3T3 stained with fluorescent lipid stain DiO (green) and PI 
(red). (b) Time series of apoptotic NIH3T3 reveals PI (red)-positive apoptotic bodies. White, blue, yellow and red arrows track individual apoptotic bodies. Time index is 
hr:min:sec following apoptosis induction with TNFa/CHX </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>

<p>1295 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>SSC </p>

<p>FSC 
PI fluorescence </p>

<p>FSC </p>

<p>TNFα 
TNFα+RNAse 
TNFα+RNAse/DNAse </p>

<p>FSC 
FSC </p>

<p>NIH3T3 
NIH3T3-mGFP </p>

<p>number cells </p>

<p>number apoptotic bodies </p>

<p>GFP+ 
33% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>PI +ve43.1% 
Apoptotic 
bodies </p>

<p>PI +ve27.4% 
PI +ve11.6% </p>

<p>PI fluorescence 
PI fluorescence </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>No PI </p>

<p>FSC </p>

<p>Autofluorescence </p>

<p>TNFα </p>

<p>-
-
+ 
+ 
-
-</p>

<p>-
+ 
-
-
+ 
-
+ 
-
-
-
-
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
-
-
-</p>

<p>TNF α </p>

<p>Anti-CD95 
UV 
RNAse + 
DNAse1 </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>MEFs </p>

<p>PI+ve Apoptotic Bodies(%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>NIH 3T3 cells </p>

<p>PI+ve Apoptotic Bodies (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>MCF10a Mammary Epithelial Cells 
PI+ve Apoptotic Bodies (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Primary Mouse Keratinocytes 
PI+ve Apoptotic Bodies (%) </p>

<p>-
-
+ 
+ 
-
-</p>

<p>-
+ 
-
-
+ 
-</p>

<p>+ 
-
-
-
-
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
-
-
-</p>

<p>TNF α </p>

<p>Anti-CD95 </p>

<p>UV 
RNAse + 
DNAse1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>mGFP 
mGFP+ 
Proteinase K 
GFP+ve Apoptotic 
Bodies (%) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>SSC 
SSC </p>

<p>GFP 
GFP </p>

<p>NIH3T3 
NIH3T3-mGFP </p>

<p>GFP 
GFP </p>

<p>PI </p>

<p>NIH3T3 
NIH3T3 mGFP+ PI </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>mGFP+PI 
mGFP+PI 
+RNAse/DNAse1 
GFP/PI+ve Apoptotic 
Bodies (%) </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>mGFP No PI </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
PI </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>absence or presence of Y27632 or Blebbistatin revealed that 
actomyosin contraction inhibition significantly (Po0.01) 
reduced apoptotic body formation following apoptosis induc-
tion by each stimulus (Figure 3c). In contrast, caspase 
activity induced by TNFa/CHX, anti-CD95/CHX or UV was 
insensitive to Y27632 or Blebbistatin (Figure 3d), indicating 
that actomyosin contraction was required for apoptotic body 
formation, but not for apoptosis induction by these stimuli. 
Similarly, cleavage of the caspase substrate ROCK1 in 
TNFa/CHX-treated cells was not affected by Y27632 
(Figure 3d inset). Consistent with previous findings 16 and 
with the ROCK inhibitory action of Y27632, ROCK1 knock-
down (Figure 3e, inset panels) impaired actomyosin 
contractile force generation leading to significantly (Po0.01) 
reduced apoptotic body formation (Figure 3e) and plasma 
membrane blebbing in a large proportion of cells (Figure 3f), 
without affecting caspase activation as determined by 
PARP1 cleavage (Figure 3e, inset panels). We next 
measured lactate dehydrogenase (LDH, monomer MW ¼ 35 
kDa, tetramer MW ¼ 140 kDa) activity in conditioned media, 
the release of which is often used to measure loss of 
membrane integrity. 21 LDH release was assayed in media 
from each of the four indicated conditions at 4 and 24 h, 
relative to the amount of LDH released from cells induced to 
undergo necrotic death by three freeze/thaw cycles. Parallel-
ing the effects on apoptotic body formation (Figure 3c), the 
increase in LDH activity present in apoptotic cell conditioned 
media (AC-CM) at 4 h compared with untreated cells was 
significantly (Po0.001) reduced when actomyosin contrac-
tility was blocked with Y27632 or Blebbistatin treatment 
(Figure 4a). However, there was no effect of either inhibitor 
on LDH release 24 h after apoptosis induction, consistent 
with protein release at this late time point resulting from loss 
of membrane integrity and lysis during secondary necrosis, 
which was unaffected by the inhibition of actomyosin 
contractility. In addition, release of the chromatin-associated 
nuclear high-mobility group box 1 protein (HMGB1, MW ¼ 25 
kDa) into tissue culture media, which had GFP added as a 
processing/loading control, was undetectable at 12 h after 
apoptosis induction but prominent in each condition at 24 h 
(Figure 4b), consistent with it being a later-released necrosis 
marker. 22 SEM revealed that TNFa/CHX-treated cell 
morphology could not be distinguished from TNFa/CHX þ 
Y27632 or TNFa/CHX þ Blebbistatin-treated cells after 24 h 
(Figure 4c). Although cells undergoing secondary necrosis 
released proteins such as LDH (Figure 4a) and HMGB1 
(Figure 4b), their FSC/SSC profiles revealed that they largely </p>

<p>remain intact with cells sizes smaller than healthy viable cells 
(Figure 4d). The ability of actomyosin contraction inhibitors 
Y27632 and Blebbistatin to suppress LDH release during 
early apoptosis (Figure 4a) was directly associated with the 
significant reduction in apoptotic bodies produced during 
early apoptosis (Figure 3c), which would then allow limited 
protein release before complete loss of membrane integrity 
during secondary necrosis. </p>

<p>Proteomic analysis of AC-CM by quantitative MS. Having 
established that a proportion of apoptotic bodies allow limited 
entry and exit of proteins, we sought to identify proteins 
released during early apoptosis, dependent upon actomyosin 
contractility, to drive blebbing and apoptotic body formation. 
To accomplish this, proteins were concentrated from condi-
tioned media using StrataClean resin and separated on 
polyacrylamide gels. Similar to LDH release (Figure 4a), 
there was a clear increase in bulk protein release 4 h after 
treatment with apoptotic inducer, which was reduced by 
Y27632 or Blebbistatin (Figure 5a). We then performed 
quantitative proteomic analysis using an adapted approach 
combining stable isotope labeling with amino acids in cell 
culture (SILAC) and MS. 23 Individual NIH3T3 fibroblasts 
populations were grown in defined SILAC medium containing 
light (no isotope label), medium (Lys4, Arg6) or heavy (Lys8, 
Arg10) amino acids (Supplementary Figure 1). Each labeled 
cells population was assigned an experimental treatment: 
reference (untreated); apoptosis (TNFa/CHX); apoptosis with 
reduced apoptotic body formation (TNFa/CHX þ Y27632 or 
Blebbistatin) and six replicate experiments performed with 
each set of conditions cycled through the SILAC labels 
(Supplementary Figure 1). After 4 h, AC-CM was collected 
and pooled from each of the three conditions, followed by 
concentration and electrophoresis before tryptic digestion 
and analysis of protein tryptic fragments by MS. A hit-list was 
compiled of proteins that were significantly different (using a 
randomized permutation test, Po0.05) between treatment 
groups, which were enriched for release from apoptotic cells 
relative to control cells, and which were reduced by both 
Y27632 and Blebbistatin to inhibit actomyosin contraction 
(Supplementary Table 1, the top 20 released proteins are in 
Table 1). Using these criteria, 231 proteins were released 
from apoptotic bodies in an actomyosin-dependent manner, 
while the release of five extracellular matrix proteins were 
actually reduced (Fibronectin1, Sparc, Timp2, Thrombos-
pondin2 and Decorin), which could be at least partially 
restored by Y27632 and Blebbistatin (Figure 5b). Consistent </p>

<p>Figure 2 Actomyosin-dependent apoptotic bodies permit macromolecule ingress. (a) Representative FACS scatter plots of FSC and SSC of apoptotic NIH3T3 cells at 4 h 
gated for apoptotic bodies (left) and without or with PI staining plotted versus FSC with TNFa/CHX alone or with RNAseA or RNAseA þ DNAse1 as indicated. (b) Histogram 
indicates mean number ± S.E.M. (*Po0.01, Student's t-test, n ¼ 3-5) of PI-positive apoptotic bodies for each paired condition in NIH3T3 established mouse fibroblasts. 
(c) Histogram indicates mean number ± S.E.M. (*Po0.01, Student's t-test, n ¼ 3-5) of PI-positive apoptotic bodies for each paired condition in primary MEFs. (d) Histogram 
indicates mean number ± S.E.M. (*Po0.01, Student's t-test, n ¼ 3-5) of PI-positive apoptotic bodies for each paired condition in MCF10a human mammary epithelial cells. 
(e) Histogram indicates mean number±S.E.M. (*Po0.01, Student's t-test, n ¼ 3-5) of PI-positive apoptotic bodies for each paired condition in primary mouse keratinocytes. 
(f) Representative FACS histogram plots of fluorescence in NIH3T3 parental cells (no fill) or cells transduced with membrane-targeted GFP (green fill; left panel) and their 
apoptotic bodies at 4 h after apoptosis induction (right panel). Cutoff indicates apoptotic body GFP fluorescence greater than autofluorescence. (g) Histogram indicates 
means±S.E.M. (*Po0.01, Student's t-test, n ¼ 3) of percentage GFP-positive apoptotic bodies without or with Proteinase K treatment as indicated. (h) Representative 
FACS scatter plots of GFP and SSC of unlabeled apoptotic NIH3T3 or cells transduced with membrane-targeted GFP at 4 h gated for GFP-positive apoptotic bodies (upper 
panels) and without or with PI staining plotted versus GFP (lower panels) as indicated. (i) Histogram indicates means±S.E.M. (*Po0.01, Student's t-test, n ¼ 8) of double 
GFP/PI-positive apoptotic bodies in the absence or presence of RNAseA þ DNAse1 as indicated </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>

<p>1297 </p>

<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-
-
-
-
+ 
+ 
-
-
-
+ 
-
-
+ 
-
-
+ 
-
-
-
+ + 
-
-
-
-
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ -
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-+ 
+ 
+ 
-
-
-</p>

<p>TNFα 
Anti-CD95 
UV 
Y27632 
Blebbistatin </p>

<p>+ 
-
-
-
-
+ 
+ 
-
-
-
+ 
-
-
+ 
-
-
+ 
-
-
-
+ + 
-
-
-
-
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ -
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-+ 
+ 
+ 
-
-
-</p>

<p>TNFα 
Anti-CD95 
UV 
Y27632 
Blebbistatin </p>

<p>* * </p>

<p>TNFα 
TNFα+Y27632 </p>

<p>ROCK1 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 12 24 2 
4 12 24 </p>

<p>Δ ROCK1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>SSC </p>

<p>10 0 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 4 
FSC </p>

<p>SSC </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>FSC </p>

<p>SSC </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>FSC </p>

<p>Apoptotic 
bodies </p>

<p>Beads </p>

<p>* 
* * 
* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3.0x10 5 </p>

<p>4.0x10 5 </p>

<p>5.0x10 5 </p>

<p>Beads 
Beads </p>

<p>Untreated 
TNFα </p>

<p>TNFα 
+ 
-</p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>9.0x10 4 </p>

<p>Low 
FSC/SSC 
bodies </p>

<p>Low 
FSC/SSC 
bodies </p>

<p>Non-targeting control </p>

<p>ROCK1 siRNA </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>NTC 
ROCK1 
siRNA 
ROCK1 
Cleaved 
PARP1 
ERK2 </p>

<p>1.0x10 5 </p>

<p>2.0x10 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3.0x10 5 </p>

<p>4.0x10 5 </p>

<p>5.0x10 5 </p>

<p>1.0x10 5 </p>

<p>2.0x10 5 </p>

<p>Apoptotic bodies </p>

<p>3.0x10 4 </p>

<p>1.2x10 5 </p>

<p>6.0x10 4 
Apoptotic bodies </p>

<p>NTC 
ROCK1 
siRNA </p>

<p>5 μm </p>

<p>5 μm </p>

<p>Relative Caspase Activity </p>

<p>Time post induction </p>

<p>Apoptotic bodies </p>

<p>5 μm 
2 μm 
2 μm </p>

<p>TNFα+Blebbistatin 
TNFα+Y27632 
TNFα </p>

<p>Figure 3 Actomyosin-dependent apoptotic bodies permit protein release. (a) Scanning electron micrographs of representative apoptotic NIH3T3 cells treated with TNFa/ 
CHX alone, with Y27632 or with Blebbistatin for 4 h as indicated. (b) Representative FSC and SSC FACS scatter plots of untreated cells or 4-h apoptotic NIH3T3 cell apoptotic 
bodies and added 10 000 FITC-labeled microbeads counted in each treatment. Histogram indicates means±S.E.M. (*Po0.01, Student's t-test, n ¼ 4) of small FSC/SSC 
body numbers generated. (c) Representative FSC and SSC FACS scatter plot of 4-h apoptotic NIH3T3 cell apoptotic bodies and added 10 000 FITC-labeled microbeads 
counted in each treatment. Histogram indicates means±S.E.M. (*Po0.01, ANOVA followed by Dunnett's multiple comparison test, n ¼ 4-5) of apoptotic body numbers 
generated with indicated treatments. (d) Caspase 3/7 activity for each treatment relative to basal level (n ¼ 3). Inset shows western of ROCK1 cleavage time course in 
response to TNFa/CHX ± Y27632. (e) ROCK1 knockdown reduced apoptotic body number. Histogram indicates means ± S.E.M. (*Po0.01, Student's t-test, n ¼ 5) of small 
FSC/SSC body numbers generated in NTC or ROCK1 siRNA transfected conditions. Western blots show ROCK1, caspase-cleaved PARP1 or ERK2 in NTC or ROCK1 siRNA 
transfected cells as indicated. (f) ROCK1 knockdown inhibits apoptotic membrane blebbing. Representative scanning electron micrographs of NTC (left panel) or ROCK1 
(right panel) siRNA transfected cells </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>with LDH as a protein validated for actomyosin-dependent 
release from apoptotic bodies (Figure 4a), it also was 
identified in the MS analysis (Supplementary Table 1). When 
fold enrichment in protein release was compared with protein 
mass, it was apparent that most proteins were r100 kDa, 
while the most abundantly released proteins were among 
the smallest (Figure 5c). Gene ontology analysis revealed 
that most proteins were either enzymes or structural/adapter 
proteins (Figure 5d). After collecting apoptotic bodies by 
sorting, gel electrophoresis revealed Coomassie-stained 
proteins with a range of molecular weights (Figure 5e, left 
panel), whereas western blotting showed Lamin A and 
Gelsolin in apoptotic bodies (Figure 5e, middle and left 
panels). These results indicate that even if proteins may 
be released, apoptotic bodies retain at least a proportion of 
their contents, including the proteins identified as being 
significantly released (Table 1). Relative to their propor-
tions in the proteome, enzymes (P ¼ 3.18 Â 10 À 10 ) and </p>

<p>structural/adapter proteins (P ¼ 0.032) were over-represented 
among released proteins, whereas transcription factors 
(P ¼ 0.018) and receptors (P ¼ 5.55 Â 10 À 5 ) were under-
represented. The presence of a number of enzymes 
associated with glycolysis likely reflects their relatively high 
abundance, solubility and cytoplasmic localization, 24 resulting 
in their tendency to be released from permeabilized apoptotic 
bodies. The majority of the actin-associated proteins were also 
previously found to be more abundant in protrusive lamellipo-
dia than cell bodies. 25 Given that following initial bleb 
protrusion, there is recruitment of actomyosin cytoskeletal 
components to facilitate bleb retraction, 26 it is logical that 
there would be common enriched proteins in protrusive 
lamellipodia and blebs/apoptotic bodies, which in the latter 
case may be released from permeabilized membranes during 
early apoptosis. 
Gelsolin was one such lamellipodia enriched protein 25 that 
also was one of the most highly enriched cytoplasmic proteins </p>

<p>L y s a t e N 
e c r o s is S t a r v e d 
T N 
F α T N 
F α + Y 2 7 6 3 2 
T N 
F α + B le </p>

<p>b b is 
t a t in </p>

<p>HMGB1 
GFP </p>

<p>HMGB1 
GFP </p>

<p>AC-CM </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Time post apoptotic 
induction (hr) </p>

<p>+ 
-
-
-
-
+ 
-
-</p>

<p>-
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
-
-
-
-
+ 
-
-</p>

<p>-
+ 
+ 
+ 
TNFα 
Y27632 
Blebbistatin </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>4 hours 
24 hours </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>% Necrotic LDH activity </p>

<p>2 μm </p>

<p>TNFα 
TNFα+Y27632 
TNFα+Blebbistatin </p>

<p>Beads 
Beads 
Cell 
bodies </p>

<p>Cell 
bodies </p>

<p>Viable cells 
Necrotic cells </p>

<p>Low 
FSC/SSC 
bodies </p>

<p>Low 
FSC/SSC 
bodies </p>

<p>2 μm 
2 μm </p>

<p>Figure 4 Late secondary necrotic cells release LDH and HMGB1. (a) LDH activity in NIH3T3 AC-CM. Histogram indicates means ± S.E.M. (*Po0.001, ANOVA followed 
by Dunnett's multiple comparison test versus TNFa alone at each time point, n ¼ 3). Conditioned media were concentrated and normalized to recombinant GFP that had been 
added before concentration as a processing control. Sample activity is normalized as percentage LDH activity in freeze-thaw necrotic sample at each time point. (b) Western 
blot of HMGB1 in NIH3T3 whole-cell lysate, freeze-thaw necrotic lysate or concentrated conditioned medium from starved cells or apoptotic cells (AC-CM) with Y27632 or 
Blebbistatin as indicated at 12 or 24 h. Recombinant GFP was added to samples before the concentration to control for processing. (c) Scanning electron micrographs of 
representative necrotic NIH3T3 cells treated with TNFa/CHX alone with Y27632 or with Blebbistatin for 24 h as indicated. (d) Representative FSC and SSC FACS scatter plots 
of viable healthy cells and 24-h necrotic NIH3T3 cells with low FSC/SSC bodies and added 10 000 FITC-labeled microbeads counted in each treatment. Indicated position of 
cell bodies was determined for viable cells and transposed to necrotic cell plot </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>identified (Table 1, Supplementary Table 1). Gelsolin reg-
ulates actin filament dynamics, and a secreted form has 
important extracellular roles in the regulation of inflamma-
tion. 27,28 To validate the SILAC/MS results and determine 
whether Gelsolin release was dependent upon actomyosin 
contraction and consequent apoptotic body formation 
(Figure 3c), we blotted AC-CM from cells that were untreated 
or treated with TNFa/CHX for 4 h in the absence or presence 
of ROCK inhibitor Y27632 or myosin ATPase inhibitor 
Blebbistatin. Both Y27632 and Blebbistatin significantly 
(Po0.01) reduced Gelsolin release relative to control 
apoptotic cells (Figure 5f), despite these treatments having 
no effect on caspase activation (Figure 3d). These results </p>

<p>confirm that Gelsolin release during early apoptosis is largely 
dependent upon actomyosin contraction, which drives bleb-
bing and apoptotic body formation. </p>

<p>Actomyosin contractility promotes histone transloca-
tion to membrane blebs and apoptotic bodies. The most 
highly enriched proteins released were nucleosomal histones 
(Table 1; Supplementary Table 1), which have been 
characterized as potent DAMPs that activate cells of the 
innate immune system by binding to Toll-like receptors 2, 4 
and 9 (TLR) either directly or complexed with DNA. 29-31 In 
addition, histones are significant autoantigens in diseases 
such as systemic lupus erythematosus. 32 Additional potential </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>+ + 
-</p>

<p>TNFα 
Y27632 
Blebbistatin </p>

<p>+ 
-
+ 
+ 
-
-
+ 
--
-
--</p>

<p>-
-
-</p>

<p>170 
130 
100 
70 
55 
40 
35 
25 
15 
Fold change protein release </p>

<p>(apoptotic/control) </p>

<p>10 
100 
1000 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Molecular Weight (kDa) 
Fold change protein release </p>

<p>(apoptotic/control) </p>

<p>Enzymes 
Proteases 
Kinases 
Phosphatases 
Transcription factors 
Ligands 
Receptors 
Structural/Adaptor </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>GFP </p>

<p>Gelsolin </p>

<p>Y27632 
Blebbistatin </p>

<p>TNFα 
+ 
+ 
+ 
-
+ 
+ </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>Relative Gelsolin 
released (% of TNF) </p>

<p>170 
130 
100 
70 
55 
40 
35 
25 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>MW 
kDa </p>

<p>Apoptotic 
body 
total 
protein </p>

<p>Lamin A 
Western 
blot </p>

<p>Gelsolin 
Western 
blot </p>

<p>e 
f </p>

<p>Figure 5 Proteins released from actomyosin-dependent blebs and apoptotic bodies. (a) Coomassie-stained polyacrylamide gel of concentrated proteins in AC-CM from 
equal cells numbers for indicated treatments. (b) Log-plot of fold change in individual protein release (apoptotic/control) in AC-CM. (c) Log-plot of fold change in individual 
protein release (apoptotic/control) in AC-CM compared with log-plot of each proteins molecular weight (kDa). (d) Classification of released protein functions as determined by 
GeneGo gene ontology analysis. (e) Coomassie stained polyacrylamide gel of proteins in collected apoptotic bodies (left panel) and western blots of Lamin A (middle panel) 
and Gelsolin (right panel). (f) Representative western blot of AC-CM at 4 h probed for Gelsolin. Conditioned media were concentrated and normalized to recombinant GFP that 
has been added to the samples before concentration as a processing control. Histogram indicates means±S.E.M. of Gelsolin release relative to TNFa/CHX alone at each 
time (*Po0.01, ANOVA followed by Dunnett's multiple comparison test versus TNFa/CHX alone, n ¼ 3) </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>DAMPs were identified in this screen (Supplementary 
Table 1), including S100 and heat shock family proteins. 
Transmission electron microscopy of apoptotic NIH3T3 cells 
revealed that portions of nuclei could be observed within 
membrane blebs (Figure 6a, indicated with arrow). GFP-
labeled histone H3 (GFP-H3) was translocated from the 
nucleus to blebs in a population of apoptotic NIH3T3 cells 
(Figure 6b). FACS sorting apoptotic bodies from untrans-
fected control and GFP-H3-expressing cells and then gating 
for GFP fluorescence greater than the level of autofluores-
cence in untransfected cells (Figure 6c, first to third panels) 
along with FITC-labeled polystyrene microbeads revealed 
that the total number of GFP-H3-positive apoptotic bodies 
was significantly (Po0.01) reduced by Y27632 or Blebbis-
tatin (Figure 6d). In addition to total number, the proportion of 
GFP-H3-positive apoptotic bodies was significantly (Po0.01) 
reduced by Y27632 or Blebbistatin (Figure 6e). These results 
indicate that not only is actomyosin contractility necessary for 
the generation of apoptotic bodies (Figure 3c) within which 
nuclear fragments may be contained, but consistent with our 
previous observation that actomyosin contractility is neces-
sary for the tearing apart of apoptotic nuclei, 33 actomyosin 
contraction contributes to the translocation of histones from 
nuclei into blebs and actomyosin-dependent apoptotic bodies 
from which they may be released into the extracellular 
environment. </p>

<p>Macrophage phagocytosis of released histone proteins. 
Macrophages internalize molecules as part of the innate 
immune response, which may influence the inflammatory 
response and contribute to antigen presentation. 34 To 
identify proteins from AC-CM that were ingested by macro-
phages, stable isotope-labeled-AC-CM from NIH3T3 cells </p>

<p>were collected and then incubated for 2 h with RAW-264.7 
mouse macrophages that had been treated with Bafilomycin 
A1 to block endosome acidification and subsequent proteo-
lysis. Cell lysates were prepared, and for each protein a 
minimum of two SILAC-labeled tryptic peptides were 
unambiguously identified on the basis of their mass 
difference from endogenous peptides. An example trace of 
the peptide LLLPGELAK from histone H2B identified from 
unlabeled endogenous protein and Lys 8 -labeled AC-CM that 
had been taken up by RAW-264.7 cells is shown in 
Figure 7a. All four nucleosomal histones were identified as 
being phagocytosed by RAW-264.7 cells from AC-CM 
(Table 2). In addition, Vimentin was also identified as being 
taken up by RAW-264.7 cells (Table 2). Interestingly, 
citrullinated Vimentin (in which a terminal nitrogen on the 
side chain of arginines is replaced by oxygen) is a major 
autoantigen associated with rheumatoid arthritis pathogen-
esis. 35 Treatment of RAW-264.7 with varying amounts of 
purified recombinant histone proteins resulted in significant 
release of TNFa induced by H2A, H2B and H3, but not H4 
(Figure 7b). Consistent with this response of being the result 
of TLR activation of the NF-kB pathway, 36 H2A treatment 
dramatically increased NFKBIA (IkBa) phosphorylation 
(Figure 7c). These results show that proteins released from 
actomyosin-dependent blebs and apoptotic bodies engage 
with macrophages, revealing a mechanism of communica-
tion between early apoptotic cells and components of the 
innate immune system. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>As cell body membranes remain intact during early apoptosis, 
limited release of intracellular proteins has not been </p>

<p>Table 1 Top 20 most enriched proteins released during early apoptosis that were reduced by inhibition of actomyosin contraction </p>

<p>Protein identified 
Gene 
name </p>

<p>Permutation 
test (p-value) </p>

<p>Fold enrichment ( ± SEM) 
(apoptotic/reference) </p>

<p>Reduction by 
Y27632 (%) </p>

<p>Reduction by 
Blebbistatin(%) </p>

<p>Histone H4 
Hist1h4a 
À 3.50E-11 
11.57 ± 2.58 
13.0 
38.6 
Histone H2B 
Hist1h2bb 
À 2.10E-11 
11.27 ± 2.43 
2.4 
43.2 
Histone H3 
H3f3a 
À 9.40E-06 
11.17±1.52 
10.7 
39.7 
Histone H2A 
Hist1h2af 
À 2.30E-07 
10.67 ± 1.82 
15.9 
32.5 
Histone H1.2 
Hist1h1c 
À 2.30E-04 
9.34±3.01 
31.1 
37.9 
Lamin-B1 
Lmnb1 
À 6.50E-07 
7.65 ± 0.93 
22.4 
35.5 
Heterogeneous nuclear 
ribonucleoprotein K </p>

<p>Hnrnpk 
À 4.90E-04 
6.57 ± 1.35 
7.1 
46.2 </p>

<p>Lamin A 
Lmna 
À 5.00E-15 
6.29 ± 0.93 
22.6 
32.7 
Polypyrimidine tract-binding protein 1 
Ptbp1 
À 1.30E-02 
5.78 ± 1.11 
13.5 
52.4 
Nuclear mitotic apparatus protein 1 
Numa1 
À 1.80E-05 
5.20±1.25 
37.8 
22.4 
Heterogeneous nuclear 
ribonucleoproteins C1/C2 </p>

<p>Hnrnpc 
À 4.90E-02 
4.08 ± 0.93 
4.4 
17.5 </p>

<p>Nuclear ubiquitous casein and 
cyclin-dependent kinases substrate </p>

<p>Nucks1 
À 2.00E-02 
3.98±0.93 
20.9 
40.5 </p>

<p>Heterogeneous nuclear 
ribonucleoprotein U </p>

<p>Hnrnpu 
À 3.80E-04 
3.78±0.62 
1.0 
22.5 </p>

<p>Adenylate kinase 2 
Ak2 
À 2.20E-05 
3.68 ± 0.55 
21.3 
37.6 
Coatomer subunit alpha 
Copa 
À 1.70E-02 
3.64±0.82 
10.3 
16.2 
Caldesomon 
Cald1 
À 7.80E-07 
3.58 ± 0.71 
14.4 
27.4 
Gelsolin Isoform 2 
Gsn 
À 4.20E-08 
3.42±0.59 
26.8 
17.1 
Heat shock 70 kDa protein 5 
Hspa5 
À 2.40E-05 
3.38±0.75 
22.2 
3.4 
Eukaryotic initiation factor 4A-III 
Eif4a3 
À 2.30E-02 
3.35 ± 0.39 
1.5 
27.4 
S-methyl-5'-thioadenosine phosphorylase 
Mtap 
À 1.00E-03 
3.33±0.35 
8.0 
25.0 
Heat shock protein 90 kDa beta member 1 
Hsp90b1 
À 5.10E-04 
3.31 þ 0.71 
33.6 
20.6 </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>considered as a mechanism apoptotic cells might use to 
communicate their demise to the surrounding environment. In 
fact, protein release has generally been regarded to occur 
only during secondary necrosis when cell body membrane </p>

<p>integrity is lost. 1,4 Our data demonstrate that acute protein 
release from apoptotic cells is a bona fide apoptotic process 
and is influenced by actomyosin contractility that drives 
blebbing, apoptotic body formation and nuclear </p>

<p>10 μM </p>

<p>GFP-H3 DAPI Phalloidin </p>

<p>2 μM </p>

<p>Beads </p>

<p>Apoptotic 
bodies </p>

<p>Negative 
Control </p>

<p>GFP-H3 
TNFα </p>

<p>GFP +ve 
10.7% </p>

<p>GFP-H3 
TNFα+Y27632 </p>

<p>GFP +ve 
5.3% </p>

<p>GFP-H3 
TNFα+Blebb. </p>

<p>GFP +ve 
4.2% </p>

<p>+ 
-
-
-
+ 
-</p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
TNFα 
Y27632 
Blebbistatin </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2.0x10 4 </p>

<p>4.0x10 4 </p>

<p>6.010 4 </p>

<p>GFP-H3+ve </p>

<p>Apoptotic bodies </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Percentage GFP+ve 
Apoptotic Bodies </p>

<p>+ 
-
-</p>

<p>-
+ 
-</p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
TNFα </p>

<p>Y27632 </p>

<p>Blebbistatin </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Figure 6 Apoptotic cells release proteins that interact with macrophages. (a) Transmission electron micrograph of an apoptotic TNFa/CHX-treated NIH3T3 cell, arrow 
indicates portion of nucleus within a bleb. (b) Fluorescence micrograph of apoptotic TNFa/CHX-treated NIH3T3 cells-expressing GFP-histone H3, stained for DNA with DAPI 
and filamentous actin with Texas red-conjugated Phalloidin. (c) Representative FSC and SSC FACS scatter plot of 4-h TNFa/CHX-treated NIH3T3 apoptotic bodies (left 
panel). GFP-H3-positive apoptotic bodies were identified by fluorescence greater than autofluorescence evident in control non-expressing cells (second left and middle 
panels). The proportions of gated GFP-positive apoptotic bodies in 10 000 counted events are shown, for example, TNFa/CHX control (middle), TNFa/CHX plus Y27632 
(second right panel) and TNFa/CHX plus Blebbistatin (right panel) treatments. (d) Histogram indicates mean number ± S.E.M. (*Po0.01, ANOVA followed by Dunnett's 
multiple comparison test versus TNFa/CHX alone, n ¼ 4) of GFP-H3-positive apoptotic bodies generated with indicated treatments. (e) Histogram indicates mean 
percentage±S.E.M. (*Po0.01, ANOVA followed by Dunnett's multiple comparison test versus TNFa/CHX alone, n ¼ 4) of GFP-H3-positive apoptotic bodies generated with 
indicated treatments </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>breakdown. 6,11,33 Apoptotic body permeabilization in early 
apoptosis provides a simple route for intracellular proteins to 
participate in complex extracellular signaling events. Further, 
these observations highlight a novel biological function for 
actomyosin-induced blebbing, which is to generate indepen-
dent subcellular apoptotic bodies that could travel away from 
the apoptotic cell and release protein quanta that alert 
surrounding cells before secondary necrotic membrane 
breakdown. 37,38 Protein release from apoptotic bodies would 
potentially increase the distance from which innate immune 
cells could detect apoptotic cells. Apoptotic bodies dispatch-
ing 'suicide notes' may be an important mechanism to trigger 
safe and rapid clearance (Figure 7d). In addition, some of 
these proteins released, such as histones, are taken up by 
macrophages, where they may influence information proces-
sing to influence the type, intensity and/or duration of cellular </p>

<p>responses, or may be processed for antigen presentation. 
Histones and Vimentin, which were identified as phagocy-
tosed by macrophages, are significant autoantigens in 
autoimmune diseases such as systemic lupus erythematosus 
and rheumatoid arthritis, respectively, suggesting that apop-
totic bodies could be a source of immunogens. 39,40 These 
results also reveal that the transition from apoptosis to 
secondary necrosis is not an off/on switch. Apoptotic bodies 
generated during early apoptosis release limited amounts of 
intracellular proteins in advance of secondary necrosis 
thereby providing a means for the phased transition between 
these two states. 
Our systematic quantitative SILAC survey of AC-CM 
identified numerous proteins released during early apoptosis 
that were sensitive to inhibition of actomyosin contraction. The 
most highly enriched proteins were the nucleosomal histones, 
which have previously been validated as DAMPs that 
reportedly act via TLR2, TLR4 and/or TLR9. 29-31,41 Histone 
engagement of TLRs results in the production and release of 
cytokines and chemokines that alert the innate immune 
system to the presence of damage. Other putative DAMPs 
were identified from the S100 and HSP protein families 
(Supplementary Table 1). However, the validation of these 
proteins as genuine DAMPs is controversial because of the 
possibility that bound enterotoxins accounted for the pro-
inflammatory activities of purified forms of these proteins. 7 </p>

<p>Macrophage </p>

<p>Proteins </p>

<p>Apoptotic cell </p>

<p>Apoptotic bodies </p>

<p>477 
476 
478 479 480 481 482 483 484 485 
475 
m/z </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 
LLLPGELAK 
Histone H2B </p>

<p>481.3122 
z=2 
Lys 8 </p>

<p>477.3052 
z=2 
Lys 0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>pNFKBIA </p>

<p>NFKBIA </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>H2A 
(10μg/mL) </p>

<p>H2A 
-0.1 1 10 --------
H2B 
----
-----
H3 
-------
--
H4 
----------</p>

<p>------------</p>

<p>0.1 1 10 
0.1 1 10 
1 10 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>protein 
(μg/mL) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 
Normalized 
pNFKBIA/NFKBIA </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>5000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>TNF secreted (pg/mL) 
Relative Abundance </p>

<p>Control 
H2A 
(10 μg/mL) </p>

<p>D a m </p>

<p>a g e s e n si ng </p>

<p>Figure 7 Histones are phagocytosed and activate macrophages. (a) Mass/charge plot showing relative abundance of unlabeled (Lys 0 ) endogenous and AC-CM 
Lys 8 -labeled histone H2B peptide in RAW-264.7 cell lysates. Peaks for Lys 8 -labeled peptide within the indicated box have been expanded 10-fold for visibility. (b) Histogram 
indicates mean±S.E.M. (*Po0.01, ANOVA followed by Dunnett's multiple comparison test versus TNFa/CHX alone, n ¼ 3) of TNFa release (pg/ml) with indicated histone 
treatments (mg/ml). (c) Increased NFKBIA phosphorylation induced by H2A protein. Representative western blotting of phosphorylated and total NFKBIA in control and H2A 
treated conditions. Histogram indicates mean ± S.E.M. (*Po0.05, one-tailed Student's t-test, n ¼ 3) relative phosphorylated NFKBIA (pNFKBIA) to total NFKBIA ratio, 
normalized to an average control value ¼ 1. (d) Apoptotic blebs and bodies are indicated in gray and red. Red indicates membrane permeabilization and protein release. 
Some proteins released may interact with and be ingested by macrophages to help activate non-infectious inflammatory responses before the complete loss of membrane 
integrity that may occur during secondary necrosis </p>

<p>Table 2 Released SILAC-labeled proteins from which peptides were identified 
within RAW-264.7 cells </p>

<p>Protein identified 
Gene name </p>

<p>Histone H2A 
Hist1h2af 
Histone H2B 
Hist1h2bb 
Histone H3 
H3f3a 
Histone H4 
Hist1h4a 
Vimentin 
Vim </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>Additional potential inducers of inflammatory responses may 
be present on the list of proteins identified by MS experiments. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Cell culture. NIH3T3, MEFs, MCF10a and primary keratinocyte cells were 
maintained as described in 11,33,42,43 , respectively. Generation of ecotropic mGFP 
and GFP-H3 virus and cell transduction was carried out as previously described. 18 
Transfection of NIH3T3 cells with nontargeting and ROCK1 Smartpool 
(Dharmacon, Loughborough, UK) siRNA was performed as previously described. 42 
Murine RAW-264.7 macrophages were maintained in DMEM supplemented with 
10% fetal bovine serum. </p>

<p>Western blotting. Cell lysates were generated with RIPA lysis buffer (10 mM 
TRIS pH 7.5, 5 mM EDTA, 150 mM NaCl, 40 mM NaPPi, 50 mM NaF, 1% (v/v) 
NP-40, 0.5% (v/v) sodium deoxycholate, 0.025% (w/v) SDS and 1mM Na 3 VO 4 , 
1 mM PMSF). Cell lysates and concentrated conditioned medium were diluted 1 : 4 
with sample buffer and warmed to 70 1C for 10 min. Samples were run on 10% 
SDS-polyacrylamide gels transferred to polyvinylidene fluoride or nitrocellulose 
membranes blocked in 5% (w/v) skimmed milk in TBS before probing with 
antibodies against; GFP, cleaved PARP1 (BD Biosciences, Oxford, UK), Gelsolin 
(Abcam, Cambridge, UK), ERK2, HMGB1 (Cell Signaling, Hitchin, UK), actin 
(Santa Cruz, Wembley, UK), ROCK1 (Transduction Labs, Oxford, UK), NFKBIA 
and pNFKBIA (pS32/pS36; Abnova, Heidelberg, Germany). Primary antibodies 
probed with AlexaFluor 680 (Invitrogen, Paisley, UK) and IR800 (Rockland, 
Peterborough, UK) conjugated secondary antibodies. Imaging and analysis was 
performed using a LiCOR-Odyssey instrument and application software. </p>

<p>Induction of apoptosis and generation of conditioned medium. 
Apoptosis was induced with a combination of 50 ng/ml tumor necrosis factor alpha 
(TNFa; R&amp;D Systems, Abingdon, UK) or 2 mg/ml CD95 antibody (BD Biosciences) 
and 10 mg/ml CHX, or treatment with 0.1 J/cm 2 UV, following overnight starvation 
in unsupplemented DMEM medium. Cells were then incubated at 37 1C for 
2-24 h as indicated. Medium was further supplemented with: Y27632 (10 mM; 
Calbiochem, Feltham, UK) or Blebbistatin (50 mM; Sigma, Gillingham, UK), as 
indicated. AC-CM was generated by pelleting apoptotic cells in media at 2000 Â g 
for 10 min. AC-CM was routinely determined to be clear of cells and debris by 
microscopic examination. Necrotic cell supernatant was generated from starved 
cells by three freeze-thaw cycles in dry ice. For western blotting, AC-CM was 
concentrated by centrifugation with 10 kDa cutoff Millipore centrifugal filter units at 
4500 Â g for 30 min. Samples were concentrated B30 fold. Before concentrating, 
0.26 mg of recombinant GFP was added to each sample as an internal standard. </p>

<p>Microscopy. Time-lapse microscopy images were acquired with a Â 20 lens 
using a Nikon A1R confocal microscope with a heated stage and 5% CO 2 gas line. 
Gray scale image is transmitted light. Cells were grown on optical glass coverslips 
and apoptosis was induced in a starved medium supplemented with TNFa/CHX 
and 5 mg/ml PI. Immediately after the induction of apoptosis, cells were relocated 
to confocal microscope and time-lapse images were taken every 30 s for 8 h in 
both transmitted light and red fluorescence. High resolution still images of unfixed 
apoptotic cells were acquired with a Â 60 oil immersion lens using same 
conditions as above. The medium was further supplemented with FAST DiO 
(3,3'-dilinoleyloxacarbocyanine perchlorate; Invitrogen) diluted 1 : 500 from 
2.5 mg/ml dissolved in 100% DMSO. Transmission and SEM was performed as 
described in 33 and 11 respectively. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry 
Apoptotic body PI permeability: For the assessment of apoptotic body PI 
permeability, 4 h apoptotic NIH3T3 samples were generated with the further 
addition of 5 mg/ml PI, 100 mg/ml RNAseA (Sigma) and/or 200 units/ml DNAse1 
(Invitrogen). Apoptotic samples were analyzed with BD FACSCalibur flow 
cytometer. A total of 100 000 apoptotic bodies were gated using FSC and SSC), 
and PI fluorescence wasdetermined in channel FL3. PI-stained non-apoptotic 
control was used to gate samples. 
GFP-labeled apoptotic body permeability: Apoptotic body proteinase K and 
PI/RNAseA/DNAse1 permeability were assessed in NIH3T3-expressing membrane-
tagged GFP. For proteinase K, 50 mg/ml (Sigma) was added to the cells 2 h after the 
addition of TNFa/CHX and incubated for a further 2 h. The apoptotic samples were 
analyzed with BD FACSCalibur flow cytometer. Alternatively, apoptotic bodies were </p>

<p>labeled with PI in the presence or absence of 100 mg/ml RNAseA (Sigma) and/or 
200 units/ml DNAse1 (Invitrogen) as described above. A total of 100 000 apoptotic 
bodies were gated using FSC and SSC), and GFP fluorescence was determined in 
channel FL1. PI fluorescence was determined in channel FL3. GFP-positive apoptotic 
bodies gated against non-GFP-expressing apoptotic bodies. Apoptotic cells without PI 
were used to gate PI stained samples. 
Apoptotic body generation: The generation of apoptotic bodies from NIH3T3 
at 4 h was assessed following treatment with TNFa/CHX, anti-CD95/CHX or UV light 
and Y27632 (10mM) or Blebbistatin (50mM). Apoptotic samples were collected, 
diluted 2 : 3 in PBS and an equivalent volume of FITC-Calibrite microsphere beads 
(BD Biosciences) were added to each sample. Apoptotic bodies were gated on FSC 
and SSC. FITC beads were gated based on fluorescence. The number of apoptotic 
bodies was counted alongside 10 000 gated FITC beads. </p>

<p>LDH, caspase activity and TNFa measurements. LDH activity was 
measured with Roche cytotoxicity detection kit according to manufacturer's 
recommendations. After concentration, the samples were diluted 1 : 10 in DMEM 
before LDH activity measurement. After normalization to GFP as determined by 
western blot, 100 ml of sample mixed with equal concentration of dye solution and 
incubated for 20 min in the dark in a 96-well plate. Reaction was stopped with 
50 ml stop solution and solution absorbance was measured with TECAN Safire 2 at 
490 nm. Sample activity expressed as a percentage of activity detected in necrotic 
sample. Caspase activity was determined from equal cell numbers using 
Caspase-Glo 3/7 kits (Promega, Southampton, UK) according to manufacturer's 
recommendations. TNFa concentrations were determined from equal cell numbers 
and calibrated against a standard curve using a mouse TNFa ELISA kit (R&amp;D 
Systems) according to manufacturer's recommendations. Recombinant purified 
histones were from New England Biolabs (Hitchin, UK). </p>

<p>SILAC and MS. NIH3T3 were grown in DMEM supplemented with dialyzed 
FBS containing specific labeled arginine (Arg) and lysine (Lys) amino acids for five 
passages. Cells were labeled with light/unlabeled (Lys0, Arg0), medium (Lys4, 
Arg6) and heavy (Lys8, Arg10) medium. Amino acids are labeled with the following 
isotopes: Lys4, 2 H 4 ; Lys8, 13 C 6 , 15 N 2 ; Arg6, 13 C 6 ; and Arg10, 13 C 6 , 15 N 4 (Silantes, 
Munich, Germany). Label incorporation was determined to be 495% by MS 
before cells were used for further experiments. Each labeled population of NIH3T3 
were assigned specific treatments, for example, light, control; medium, TNFa/ 
CHX; and heavy, TNFa/CHX þ Y27632. Each labeled population was used in 
each treatment condition, with Blebbistatin substituting for Y27632 in one set of 
experiments, for a total of six replicates. After 4 h, the supernatants were pooled 
and concentrated with StrataClean resin. Protein was eluted from StrataClean 
resin using 100 ml 1X lithium dodecyl sulfate (LDS) sample buffer plus 10 mM DTT 
at 951C for 5 min. This was allowed to cool, adjusted to 50 mM iodoacetamide and 
incubated in the dark for 20 min at room temperature. Macrophage extracts (in 8 M 
urea) were adjusted to 1X LDS sample buffer, reduced with DTT and alkylated 
with iodoacetamide as described above. The samples were electrophoresed for 
3 cm on a NuPAGE 4-12% gel using MOPS running buffer (Life Technologies, 
Paisley, UK) at 200 V and then stained with colloidal coomasie. The gel lane was 
cut into five even sections, each section cut into 2-mm cubes, destained with 50% 
acetonitrile/100 mM TEAB pH 8, dried and digested with 1 mg/ml trypsin in 50 mM 
TEAB overnight at 301C. Gel pieces were extracted with 50% acetonitrile, extracts 
combined, dried under vacuum and reconstituted in 0.1 ml 5% acetonitrile/0.1% 
formic acid in water. In some experiments, macrophage extracts (50 mg) were 
reduced and alkylated in 8 M urea, diluted to 1 M urea with 50 mM TEAB pH 8 and 
digested in solution with trypsin (1 : 10 w/w) at 301C for 5 h. Tryptic digests were 
analyzed by LC-MS on a LTQ-Orbitrap Velos mass spectrometer system coupled 
to a Proxeon Easy-LC HPLC system. The peptide mixtures were loaded onto a 
nanoseparations C18 guard column (0.1 Â 20 mm) equilibrated in 0.1% formic 
acid/water at 5 ml/min and then separated on an LC-Packings PepMap C18 
column (0.075 Â 150 mm equilibrated in 0.1% formic acid/water. Peptides were 
eluted with a 120 min discontinuous gradient of acetonitrile/0.1% formic acid at a 
flow rate of 300 nl/min. The column outlet was connected to a Proxeon Flex 
nanospray source fitted with a New Objective FS360 20-10 uncoated emitter and a 
voltage of 2 kV was applied to the emitter. The orbitrap was set to analyze the 
survey scans (m/z 350-2000) at 30 000 resolution and top 10 ions in each duty 
cycle (minimum ion intensity of 5000 cps) were selected for MSMS in the LTQ 
linear ion trap. Ions were excluded for 20 s after two occurrences. The raw files 
were analyzed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">MaxQuant</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">1.2.0.13</rs> and <rs id="software-6" type="software">Proteome Discoverer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">1.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Thermo- Fisher, Loughborough, UK</rs>) against mouse Swiss-Prot database (2012_09, 55744 </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>entries) database. The Maxquant/ Andromedia search was performed with the 
following criteria (Raw mass spectra were extracted by MaxQuant (Max Planck 
Institute of Biochemistry, Martinsried, Germany, version 1.3.0.5) and searched with 
a fragment ion mass tolerance of 0.50 Da and a parent ion tolerance of 6 p.p.m. 
Trypsin was set as the enzyme with two missed cleavages permitted. 
Carbamidomethyl of cysteine was specified as a fixed modification. SILAC labels 
of lysine and arginine, oxidation of methionine and acetyl of the protein N-terminus 
were specified as variable modifications. The identification criteria included peptide 
length to be greater than 7 amino acids residues and both peptide and protein 
FDR levels set at 0.01 (or 1 if the data were submitted to Scaffold Q þ S 
(<rs id="software-2" type="software">Proteome Software</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 3.6</rs>, Portland, OR, USA). Analysis was undertaken 
both with and without re-quantify active. Proteome Discoverer 1.3 was used to 
search with Mascot using a SILAC (K8/R10) workflow and peptides were validated 
using <rs id="software-4" type="software">Percolator</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">1.17</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">University of Washington</rs>) with a FDR of 0.1%. The Mascot 
search engine (Matrix Science, London, UK) used the following criteria: peptide 
tolerance ¼ 10 p.p.m., MSMS tolerance ¼ 0.8 Da, trypsin as the enzyme (two 
missed cleavages permitted), carboxyamidomethylation of cysteine as a fixed 
modification with oxidation of methionine and label K8, label R10 as a variable 
modification. The output from both <rs type="software">Maxquant</rs> and <rs type="software">Proteome Discoverer</rs> 1.3 were 
processed through Scaffold Q þ S and the data from each gel section from each 
lane were combined into one file. Gene ontology analysis was performed using 
GeneGo (Thomson Reuters). </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported 
License. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on Cell Death and Differentiation website (http://www.nature.com/cdd) </p>

<p>Protein release from apoptotic blebs 
GR Wickman et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

</text></tei>