<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3337072" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Early-onset major depressive disorder (MDD) is a serious and prevalent psychiatric illness in adolescents and young adults. 
Current treatments are not optimally effective. Biological markers of early-onset MDD could increase diagnostic specificity, but 
no such biomarker exists. Our innovative approach to biomarker discovery for early-onset MDD combined results from genome-
wide transcriptomic profiles in the blood of two animal models of depression, representing the genetic and the environmental, 
stress-related, etiology of MDD. We carried out unbiased analyses of this combined set of 26 candidate blood transcriptomic 
markers in a sample of 15-19-year-old subjects with MDD (N ¼ 14) and subjects with no disorder (ND, N ¼ 14). A panel of 11 
blood markers differentiated participants with early-onset MDD from the ND group. Additionally, a separate but partially 
overlapping panel of 18 transcripts distinguished subjects with MDD with or without comorbid anxiety. Four transcripts, 
discovered from the chronic stress animal model, correlated with maltreatment scores in youths. These pilot data suggest that 
our approach can lead to clinically valid diagnostic panels of blood transcripts for early-onset MDD, which could reduce 
diagnostic heterogeneity in this population and has the potential to advance individualized treatment strategies. 
Early-onset major depressive disorder (MDD) is a serious 
psychiatric condition occurring in people under 25 years of 
age. 
1 Early onset of MDD predicts greater familial risk, 
suggesting a substantial genetic etiology. 
2,3 Approximately 
1% of the population of o12 years has MDD, but rates 
increase to 17-25% by late adolescence and young adult-
hood. 
4,5 Early-onset MDD carries a poorer prognosis than 
adult onset, characterized by derailment of normal develop-
ment and, subsequently, increases in the prevalence of 
substance use, physical illness, social maladjustment and 
suicidality. 
6-11 This dysfunction persists into adulthood with 
continued mood disturbance, and often presents comorbid 
anxiety and substance use disorders. </p>

<p>9,12   Treatments for early-onset MDD exist, but medication side 
effects are unpredictable and adolescents have lower 
response rates than adults. 
13,14 Unmeasured heterogeneity 
in the etiology of MDD and the presence of symptom cluster 
subtypes that require unique treatments may explain these 
problems. 
15,16 Current diagnostic practice is limited to patient 
self-report and clinician observation, methods that cannot 
adequately characterize this heterogeneity. Biological mar-
kers of different etiologic pathways and/or endophenotypes 
would provide objective data to augment verbal information 
and improve the accuracy of diagnosis. The diagnosis </p>

<p>and classification of early-onset MDD could lead to a larger 
repertoire of more effective treatments and enhanced 
individualized care. 
The benefit of having valid, reliable, selective and feasible 
biomarkers for MDD is clear, but despite 30 years of research, 
we still do not have them. 
17 Two approaches have been used 
to search for blood biomarkers. The first approach screens 
candidate markers suggested by current knowledge of MDD 
etiology, such as serum levels of cortisol 
18 or brain-derived 
neurotrophic factor. 
19 The other approach takes an explora-
tory route through the use of omic technologies such as the 
proteomic profiling for bipolar disorder 
20 and transcriptomic 
profiling for psychosis 
21 or for mood disorders. 
22 Each 
approach has its advantages and challenges, but neither 
has been successful in identifying biomarkers that survive 
the tests of replication and selectivity. 
23 In the present paper, 
we describe a promising novel approach to discover blood 
biomarkers, and a pilot study focusing on their validity for 
distinguishing early-onset MDD from no disorder in youth. 
Substantial evidence has accumulated for both the genetic 
and the environmental stress-related etiologies of MDD. 
Therefore, in our study we use a theoretical approach that 
recapitulates these etiologies by utilizing animal models of 
both. In previous studies, we have shown that the mole-
cular mechanisms through which genetic predisposition and 
chronic stress precipitate depressive behavior are different. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Received 20 January 2012; revised 29 February 2012; accepted 3 March 2012 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Psychiatry, Dalhousie University Faculty of Medicine; 
2 Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Feinberg School of Medicine, Northwestern 
University, Chicago, IL, USA; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Pediatrics, Ohio State University College of Medicine, Columbus, OH, USA and 
4 The Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, ME, 
USA 
Correspondence: Dr EE Redei, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Feinberg School of Medicine, Northwestern University, Chicago, IL 60611, USA. 
E-mail: e-redei@northwestern.edu </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>These two authors contributed equally to this work. 
Keywords: blood biomarker; chronic stress; comorbid anxiety; genetic animal model; major depression </p>

<p>Citation: Transl Psychiatry (2012) 2, e101, doi:10.1038/tp.2012.26 </p>

<p>&amp; 2012 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 2158-3188/12 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/tp </p>

<p>Additionally, these molecular pathways can interact, which 
could hasten the onset of depression or increase the severity. 
Therefore, if these models are explored in conjunction with 
one another, a greater part of the spectrum of human MDD, or 
its endophenotypes, can be accounted for. 
The genetic model of depression is based on selective 
breeding from the Wistar Kyoto (WKY) rat strain, with many 
behavioral and physiological characteristics mirroring symp-
toms of patients with MDD. 
25-29 The WKY strain is also 
regarded as the optimal model for juvenile depression, 
presumably because it is a genetic model and early-onset 
MDD is associated with a greater familial risk. 
2,30 The two 
substrains of the WKY, identified as WKY More Immobile 
(WMI, the depression model) and WKY Less Immobile (WLI, 
the nondepressed control strain), were generated by bidirec-
tional selective breeding from the WKY strain based on 
depressive behavior in the forced swim test. 
24,31 These two 
inbred strains have maintained clear and significant behavior-
al differences in measures of depressive behavior over 25 
generations; thus, the WMI strain represents a model of 
genetic, or endogenous, depression. Furthermore, the WMI 
rats show depressive-like behavior during early adoles-
cence. 
32 The chronic stress model employed young adult 
males of four phylogenetically, physiologically and behavio-
rally different strains of rats as described previously, and 
half of the animals from each strain were exposed to 
chronic restraint stress and the other half were not. 
24 Genetic 
polymorphisms between the strains ranged from 25.9 to 66%, 
representing a substantial interstrain variation that aims at 
mimicking individual variation among human subjects. 
By conducting genome-wide expression analyses in the 
blood of both of these models and their respective controls, we 
arrived at a set of candidate transcripts whose abundance 
we measured in the blood of human subjects. We elected to 
monitor transcript levels, rather than serum protein levels, as a 
more all-encompassing approach, as not all proteins are 
secreted and not all transcripts are translated. More-
over, current technology allows the collection of blood for 
RNA isolation without refrigeration, an additional practical 
advantage. 
The overarching goal of our research is to develop a panel 
of blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD that are valid, 
reliable and feasible. The core hypothesis for this study 
was that the combined list of transcripts that differen-
tiated depressed-like from non-depressed-like rats would also 
differentiate human subjects with early-onset MDD from those 
without any disorder. We also explored whether a subset 
of these transcripts differentiated youths solely with MDD 
from those with comorbid anxiety, which is one of the best-
described endophenotypes. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Study 1: animal models and procedures. All procedures 
were approved by the institutional animal care and use 
committee of Northwestern University. The animals, dissec-
tion, RNA isolation, labeling, amplification, hybridization and 
scanning to identify 'depression' markers using the WMI and 
WLI strains were described previously 
24 with the following </p>

<p>modifications. Whole blood was also collected into PAXgene 
Blood RNA tubes (PreAnalytiX, Hombrechticon, Switzerland) 
from three males, derived from different litters, of each strain. 
Briefly, total RNA isolated from these four tissue sources was 
reverse-transcribed with an Oligo(dT)-T7 primer (Affymetrix, 
Santa Clara, CA, USA), and double-stranded complementary 
DNA (cDNA) was synthesized with the GeneChip Expression 
3 
0 -Amplification One-cycle kit (Affymetrix). In an in vitro 
transcription reaction with T7 RNA polymerase, the cDNA 
was linearly amplified and labeled with biotinylated nucleo-
tides (Affymetrix). A total of 10 mg of biotin-labeled and fragmented 
cRNA was then hybridized onto Rat Genome 230 2.0 
GeneChip arrays (Affymetrix) for 16 h at 45 1C. Post-hybri-
dization staining and washing were performed according to 
the manufacturer's protocols using the Fluidics Station 450 
instrument (Affymetrix). Finally, the arrays were scanned with 
a GeneChip Scanner 3000 laser confocal slide scanner. 
For the determination of peripheral chronic stress markers, 
whole blood was collected into PAXgene Blood RNA tubes 
from nonstressed and chronically stressed Fisher-344 (F344), 
Brown Norway (BN-SS), Lewis (Lew) and WKY male rats of 
B100 days of age and of different litters (n ¼ 3 per strain per 
experimental condition). The chronically stressed animals 
were restrained in a breathable decapicone for 2 h per day for 
a 2-week period. Total RNA was isolated using the PAXgene 
Blood RNA Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's 
instruction, and then reverse transcribed followed by second-
strand cDNA synthesis. For each sample, an in vitro trans-
cription reaction was carried out incorporating biotinylated 
nucleotides according to the manufacturer's protocol for 
Illumina Totalprep RNA amplification kit (Ambion, Austin, 
TX, USA). Then, 1.5 mg biotin-labeled cRNA was hybridized 
onto RatRef-12 Expression BeadChips (Illumina, San Diego 
CA, USA) for 16 h at 55 1C. Post-hybridization staining and 
washing were performed according to the manufacturer's 
protocols (Illumina). Illumina Sentrix RatRef-12 v1.0 Bead-
Chips were scanned using Illumina's BeadStation 500 
scanner. Images were checked for grid alignment and then 
quantified using the <rs type="software">BeadStudio</rs> software. 
The two sets of blood gene expression data came from 
different microarray platforms. For this reason, we carried out 
a detailed comparison between the Affymetrix and Illumina 
platforms used, and validated a number of selected tran-
scripts' abundances by quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) as 
described previously. </p>

<p>24   Statistical analyses of microarray data. Analyses to establish 
significant differences in gene expression between WMI and 
WLI for the different tissues were carried out as described 
previously. 
24 Briefly, probe intensity data from Rat 230v2 
Affymetrix GeneChip arrays were read into the R software 
environment (http://www.R-project.org) directly from .CEL 
files using the <rs type="software">R/affy package</rs>. 
33 The normalization of the 
Affymetrix data was performed by tissue type using the 
robust multiarray average method for probe set data. </p>

<p>34   Probe intensity data from Illumina Chip arrays were read 
into the R software environment directly from Bead summary 
files produced by <rs type="software">BeadStudio</rs> using the <rs type="software">R/beadarray</rs> pack-
age. 
35 Quantile normalization was applied to the Illumina bead 
summary data using the <rs type="software">R/preprocessCore package</rs>. 
36 Data </p>

<p>Blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD 
K Pajer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>quality was assessed using histograms of signal intensities, 
scatterplots, and hierarchical clustering of samples. 
Analysis of variance methods were used to statistically 
resolve gene expression differences from both studies after 
data processing and normalization using the <rs type="software">R/maanova package</rs>. </p>

<p>37,38   Study 2: human subjects: recruitment and procedures. 
The study was carried out from May through September, 
2009 and from July through December, 2010. Recruitment 
and experimental protocols were exactly the same, except 
for the addition in 2010 of a questionnaire about maltreat-
ment as a measure of chronic stress. 
Male and female subjects, 15-19 years of age, were 
recruited through community posters, other research studies 
at the Research Institute at Nationwide Children's Hospital, 
the Nationwide Children's Hospital (NCH) Adolescent Medi-
cine and Behavioral Health Clinics and private psychologists. 
Exclusion criteria were: age outside 15-19 years; Tanner 
Stage o5; major medical illness; antidepressant use in the 
past 3 months; no MDD, but another psychiatric disorder; 
MDD with psychosis; pregnancy; or history of mental retar-
dation. An additional exclusion criterion for the no disorder 
(ND) group was any lifetime psychiatric disorder. 
A total of 136 youths underwent telephone screening; 
73 were not eligible or refused participation; 10 could not 
be reached because of a disconnected phone. In total, 53 
participants were scheduled for appointments. 
The protocol was approved by the NCH Institutional Review 
Board. Appointments took place at NCH Clinical Research 
Services (CRS) with data collection standardized to 1600-
1700 h. Consent and assent were obtained upon arrival to the 
CRS. Blood was drawn into two PaxGene RNA (Qiagen) 
tubes. Trained research assistants conducted concurrent, but 
separate interviews with parents and youths about the young 
person's lifetime psychiatric symptoms and medical history. 
A youth self-report questionnaire about exposure to maltreat-
ment was added in the 2010 subsample. Parents received 
$30 for time and effort and transportation costs, and youths 
received $45. 
Pubertal stage was assessed with the Tanner Self-Rating 
Schematic Drawings. 
39 Demographic characteristics and the 
youth's lifetime medical history were evaluated through a brief 
interview with the parent and the Risks and Disorders sub-
domains of the Child Health and Illness Profile-Adolescent 
Edition (CHIP-AE). 
40 The lifetime history of psychiatric 
diagnoses was assessed with the computerized version of 
the Diagnostic Interview Schedule for Children and Adoles-
cents-IV (CDISC-IV; NIMH, 1998), Parent and Youth Ver-
sions. The <rs type="software">CDISC</rs> is a structured psychiatric interview, 
organized into six Axis I diagnostic sections: Anxiety 
Disorders, Mood Disorders, Disruptive Behavior Disorders, 
Schizophrenia, Miscellaneous Disorders (for example, Eating 
Disorders) and Substance-Use Disorders. 
41 Psychometric 
testing of the <rs type="software">CDISC</rs> has demonstrated good validity and 
reliability. 
42,43 Every participant and parent received the entire 
diagnostic assessment. 
In 2010, we also explored whether exposure to chronic 
stress in humans, as defined by maltreatment, correlated with 
the levels of gene transcripts derived from the chronic stress </p>

<p>animal model. We used the Childhood Trauma Questionnaire 
(CTQ), a 28-item self-report questionnaire measuring lifetime 
exposure to five types of maltreatment: Emotional, Physical 
and Sexual Abuse and Emotional and Physical Neglect. The 
instrument has been standardized on over 2200 people, 
including adolescents, and has excellent psychometric 
properties. 
44 We used the total CTQ score. </p>

<p>Determination of blood transcript levels of candidate 
markers. Blood was drawn on all participants, but the only 
samples sent to the Redei lab were those of youths suffering 
from current MDD or those without any disorder (ND). The 
Redei lab was blind to any information about the participants. 
Whole-blood RNA was isolated using the PAXgene Blood 
RNA Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's instruction; 
cDNA was prepared using random primers and the TaqMan 
RT reagents (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). 
Specific primers, listed in Supplementary Table S1, were 
designed to amplify the human ortholog of the rat microarray 
probe region of the candidate markers using the ABI's <rs id="software-28" type="software">Primer Express</rs> Software (version <rs corresp="#software-28" type="version-number">3.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-28" type="creator">PE Applied Biosystems</rs>). 
qPCR was carried out using SYBR Green and the ABI 7900 
(Applied Biosystems), with 18s rRNA as the internal control. 
18s was chosen as the normalizing gene after an extensive 
comparative pilot study using several housekeeping genes 
(data not shown). Each sample for each transcript was 
measured in triplicate using 5 ng of template. 
The DCT values from qPCR were used to characterize 
transcript abundance. DCT is the cycle threshold difference 
between the target gene and the housekeeping gene, which in 
this case is 18s. This method, as opposed to the relative 
quantification approach in which the DCT values are normali-
zed to the control group giving DDCT, will also indicate the 
variation within the ND samples. DDCT is the DCT of 
the disorder group subtracting DCT of the ND group. The 
relative expression for each transcript and each sample is 
determined from DCT by raising 2 to the power of the negative 
value of DCT. A fold change can then be calculated by raising 
2 to the power of the negative value of DDCT for each sample. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses of human data. Descriptive statistics 
were used to characterize the sample, and nonparametric 
statistics to analyze gene expression differences between 
the ND and MDD groups or between the MDD subgroups 
with and without comorbid anxiety disorders. Spearman's rho 
correlation coefficients were used to evaluate the relation-
ships between the CTQ scores and gene expression levels. 
Because this is a pilot study, effect sizes are more infor-
mative than statistical significance. We calculated effect 
sizes for all differences between means, using Hedges' 
because of small sample and unequal subgroup sizes. 
Correlation coefficients themselves can serve as estimates 
of effect sizes, and hence we report rho values for these 
analyses. We made an a priori decision to interpret an effect 
size of X0.50 as clinically significant, which corresponds to 
Cohen's medium effect size. 
45 We did not control for multiple 
comparisons, as the goal of a pilot study is to detect as many 
potentially clinically significant relationships as possible. Data 
analyses were performed with <rs id="software-19" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-19" type="version-number">14.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-19" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., 
Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD 
K Pajer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Identification of candidate biomarker transcripts. 
Candidate transcripts were selected with significant 
(Po0.01) expression differences between WMI and WLI 
and an absolute fold change 41.2, or 20%. Using these 
criteria, 238 differentially expressed and annotated 
transcripts were identified in the hippocampus (Supple-
mentary Table S2). Of these, 60.5% had greater abun-
dance in the WLI hippocampus compared with the WMI. 
Congruent selection criteria resulted in 396 annotated trans-
cripts from the amygdala (Supplementary Table S3), of which 
141 (35.6%) had a greater abundance in WLI amygdala. The 
analyses of blood microarray data were carried out similarly. 
These differentially expressed blood transcripts and their 
human orthologs are listed in Supplementary Table S4. 
There were 203 transcripts differentially expressed between 
WMI and WLI blood, and 167 transcripts (82.3%) had greater 
abundance in WLI as it is clearly visualized in the volcano 
plot (Figure 1a). 
Overlap between differentially expressed transcripts in 
either of the two brain regions and blood was established. 
The 11 transcripts selected as candidates had to fulfill the 
criteria that the directional changes had to agree between 
brain and blood. Seven of these candidates (MARCKS, MAF, 
FAM46A, NAGA, UBE3A, CD59, ATP11C and RAPH1) 
fulfilled the selection criteria above and overlapped between 
brain and blood. Additionally, we selected three genes, 
SCAPER/ZNF291, TLR7 and IGSF4A/CADM1, whose tran-
script levels differed between WMI and WLI blood by the same 
criteria as the others, but were selected from brain regions 
based on either high fold change (fold change 41.2) or high 
significance (Po0.01). These transcripts, therefore, could 
have potential clinical relevance. 
The selection criteria for the chronic stress markers differed 
from those of the genetic model, as they are related to a 
change induced by environment, rather than individual 
variation to vulnerability. Chronic restraint stress affected all 
strains of rats, as described previously. 
24 To eliminate strain-
specific effects in our selection, transcripts were selected </p>

<p>based on consistent, significant expression level differences 
in all four strains, in which significance was set at Po0.001 
and absolute fold change at 41.2. We found 125 transcripts in 
the blood that had differentially expressed transcript levels 
between the chronic restraint stress and no stress conditions 
(Figure 1b and Supplementary Table S5). From these, we 
randomly selected 15 representative transcripts with absolute 
fold change between 1.28 and 1.95. 
During the selection processes we eliminated candidates if 
they did not have human orthologs, or if the mRNA sequence 
that the probes were designed for had been retired or 
retracted in the database. Additionally, we also eliminated 
candidates that had UniGene EST (expressed sequence tag)-
only information, as we could not identify associated mRNAs. </p>

<p>Participant characteristics. Of the 53 participants 
examined, 28 (14 MDD and 14 with ND) met all criteria for 
inclusion in testing blood transcript levels of candidate 
markers. There were no statistically significant differences 
between the two groups in mean age, proportion of females 
or proportion of African-Americans and Caucasians. Table 1 
displays the characteristics of our final study group. </p>

<p>Transcript-level differences: MDD vs ND. Mean transcript 
abundance levels for the MDD and ND groups are shown in 
Table 2. The number of subjects (n) varies by one because 
some of the qPCR analyses were repeatedly unsuccessful 
for the particular subject and transcript, possibly because of 
polymorphisms located in the primer sequence(s). Medium 
or large effect sizes were found for group mean differences in 
11 of the 26 transcripts examined (Table 3). The corres-
ponding genes are ATP11C, CD59, IGSF4/CADM1, MAF 
and RAPH1 (derived from the genetic model); and AMFR, 
CAT, CDR2, CMAS, PSME1 and PTP4A3 (derived from the 
chronic stress model). </p>

<p>Transcript-level differences: MDD-only vs MDD with 
anxiety disorders. Intragroup analyses of MDD with and 
without comorbid anxiety disorders revealed medium to large 
effect size differences in 18 of the 26 candidate biomarkers: 
CD59, FAM46A, IGSF4A/CADM1, NAGA, TLR7 and 
ZNF291/SCAPER as well as AHSP, AMFR, CAT, CDR2, 
CMAS, DGKA, GCLM, GGA3, IRF3, KIAA1539, PSME1 and 
SLC4A1 (Table 3). This panel diverged in three ways from 
the panel that differentiated MDD from ND. First, the list of 
potentially clinical markers was longer for the intra-MDD 
analyses. Second, the two panels for MDD versus ND and 
MDD with-versus-without anxiety disorders only overlapped 
by six genes; thus, the non-overlapping candidates FAM46A, 
NAGA, TLR7, ZNF291/SCAPER, AHSP DGKA, GCLM, </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>-1.5 
-0.5 
0.5 
1.5 </p>

<p>-log 
10 (P-val) 
-log 
10 (P-val) </p>

<p>log 2 (Fold Change) 
log 2 (Fold Change) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>-1.5 
-0.5 
0.5 
1.5 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Volcano plots based on microarray analyses depicting individual 
probe P-value (Àlog10) versus expression fold change (log2). (a) WMI/WLI (Wistar 
Kyoto (WKY) More Immobile (WMI) and WKY Less Immobile (WLI)) blood 
microarray plot, with dotted lines depicting the P-value selection threshold 
(Po0.01) and the fold change (FC) threshold (absolute FC 41.20). (b) Chronic 
stress blood microarray plot, with dotted lines depicting the P-value selection 
threshold (Po0.001) and the fold change threshold (absolute FC 41.20). </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of human participants </p>

<p>Variable 
MDD (n ¼ 14) 
ND (n ¼ 14) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age (mean±s.d.) 
16.6±1.3 years 16.2±1.5 years 
0.51 
Sex (% female) 
9 (64%) 
12 (86%) 
0.39 
Race (% Caucasian) 
8 (57%) 
10 (71%) 
0.70 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: MDD, major depressive disorder; ND, no disorder. </p>

<p>Blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD 
K Pajer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>Table 2 Descriptive statistics of blood transcript abundance differences between subjects with no disorder (ND), major depressive disorder (MDD)-only or MDD with 
comorbid anxiety disorder </p>

<p>Groups 
N 
Mean, DC t </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>s.d. 
DDC t </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Fold change </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Endogenous depression genes </p>

<p>ATP11C 
ND 
14 
14.9232 
0.74081 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
15.2596 
0.23454 
0.3364 
À1.26263 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
15.0147 
0.55075 
0.0915 
À1.06542 
CD59 
ND 
14 
13.9868 
0.59346 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
14.6551 
0.09019 
0.6683 
À1.58907 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
14.2498 
0.49290 
0.2630 
À1.20005 
FAM46A 
ND 
14 
15.6206 
0.62560 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
15.3099 
0.51630 
À0.3107 
1.2403 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
15.7898 
0.60560 
0.1692 
À1.12448 
CADM1/IGSF4A 
ND 
14 
16.5055 
2.63519 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
18.4211 
0.68470 
1.9156 
À3.77216 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
17.3174 
1.23838 
0.8119 
À1.75562 
MAF 
ND 
14 
17.7071 
0.88667 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
18.1239 
0.58738 
0.4168 
À1.33494 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
18.1815 
0.55424 
0.4743 
À1.38927 
MARKS 
ND 
14 
13.2903 
1.42679 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
13.5260 
0.57322 
0.2357 
À1.17744 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
13.9042 
1.08966 
0.6139 
À1.53046 
NAGA 
ND 
14 
13.9092 
0.83357 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
13.6951 
0.53240 
À0.2141 
1.16 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
14.3758 
0.73741 
0.4666 
À1.38179 
RAPH1 
ND 
14 
15.7073 
2.56428 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
17.1122 
0.82167 
1.4049 
À2.64831 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
16.8285 
1.18044 
1.1211 
À2.17533 
TLR7 
ND 
14 
15.4338 
0.85478 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
15.0418 
0.56444 
À0.3920 
1.3122 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
15.6474 
0.63404 
0.2136 
À1.15955 
UBE3A 
ND 
14 
15.1981 
1.65462 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
15.8918 
0.32713 
0.6937 
À1.61734 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
15.3906 
1.41887 
0.1925 
À1.14273 
SCAPER/ZNF291 
ND 
14 
16.1619 
1.15379 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
16.1685 
0.59014 
0.0066 
À1.00462 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
16.6744 
0.56655 
0.5125 
À1.42653 </p>

<p>Chronic stress genes 
AHSP 
ND 
14 
12.9605 
0.89321 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
12.3232 
0.52023 
À0.6373 
1.5554 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
12.7443 
0.72712 
À0.2162 
1.1616 
AMFR 
ND 
14 
13.5744 
1.68521 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
13.9849 
0.35561 
0.4105 
À1.32926 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
14.4332 
0.41345 
0.8588 
À1.81357 
CAT 
ND 
14 
14.6880 
1.08626 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
14.9740 
0.60841 
0.2860 
À1.21921 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
15.2509 
0.37033 
0.5629 
À1.4771 
CDR2 
ND 
14 
14.8752 
0.65338 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
15.5524 
0.20734 
0.6771 
À1.59898 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
15.2020 
0.37955 
0.3268 
À1.25423 
CMAS 
ND 
14 
15.5308 
2.43662 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
17.3159 
0.28832 
1.7851 
À3.4459 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
16.6903 
0.82848 
1.1595 
À2.23364 
DGKA 
ND 
14 
11.2385 
1.41685 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
10.3071 
0.68101 
À0.9315 
1.9072 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
11.6179 
0.89919 
0.3793 
À1.30073 
EMB 
ND 
14 
12.7808 
1.05224 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
13.0919 
0.25565 
0.3111 
À1.24069 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
12.8555 
0.73724 
0.0747 
À1.05307 
FECH 
ND 
14 
13.4058 
1.15795 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
13.7521 
0.83616 
0.3463 
À1.27126 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
13.8091 
0.55241 
0.4032 
À1.3224 
GCLM1 
ND 
14 
16.2397 
0.91531 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
16.7181 
0.24730 
0.4784 
À1.39315 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
16.2007 
0.85000 
À0.0390 
1.0274 
GGA3 
ND 
14 
15.3662 
0.88044 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
15.2748 
0.63735 
À0.0914 
1.0654 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
15.7604 
0.84886 
0.3942 
À1.31423 
IRF3 
ND 
14 
13.0719 
0.95953 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
13.0075 
0.60782 
À0.0644 
1.0457 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
13.5359 
0.55548 
0.4641 
À1.3795 
KIAA1539 
ND 
14 
13.4514 
1.32581 
0 
1 
MDD Only 
5 
12.8294 
0.88024 
À0.6220 
1.539 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
13.8681 
1.03397 
0.4168 
À1.33494 
PSME1 
ND 
14 
11.1975 
0.53582 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
11.6564 
0.40741 
0.4588 
À1.37438 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
11.3615 
0.58138 
0.1639 
À1.12032 </p>

<p>Blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD 
K Pajer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>Table 2 (Continued ) </p>

<p>Groups 
N 
Mean, DC t </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>s.d. 
DDC t </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Fold change </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>PTP4A3 
ND 
14 
14.9475 
0.94725 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
15.7955 
0.62373 
0.8480 
À1.80018 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
15.4607 
0.73612 
0.5132 
À1.42714 
SLC4A1 
ND 
14 
13.1906 
1.29940 
0 
1 
MDD only 
5 
12.6948 
1.26028 
À0.4958 
1.4101 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
13.5886 
0.74571 
0.3979 
À1.31752 </p>

<p>a DC t ¼ C t target geneÀC t housekeeping gene; [Target] / [Housekeeping] ¼ 2 </p>

<p>ÀDCt </p>

<p>. 
b DDC t ¼ DC t (MDD or MDD + ANX)À DC t (ND). </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Fold change ¼ 2 </p>

<p>ÀDCt (MDD or MDD </p>

<p>+ ANX)À DCt (ND) . </p>

<p>Table 3 Effect sizes for comparisons between no disorder (ND) vs major depressive disorder (MDD; all), and MDD-only vs MDD with comorbid anxiety disorder </p>

<p>Groups 
N 
Effect size 
Groups 
N 
Effect size </p>

<p>Genetic model genes </p>

<p>ATP11C 
ND 
14 
À0.84 
MDD only 
5 
0.49 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
CD59 
ND 
14 
À0.78 
MDD only 
5 
0.94 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
FAM46A 
ND 
14 
À0.00 
MDD only 
5 
À0.78 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 </p>

<p>IGSF4A/CADM1 
ND 
14 
À0.59 
MDD only 
5 
0.95 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 </p>

<p>MAF 
ND 
14 
À0.62 
MDD only 
5 
À0.10 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
MARKS 
ND 
14 
À0.40 
MDD only 
5 
À0.37 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 </p>

<p>NAGA 
ND 
14 
À0.29 
MDD only 
5 
À0.94 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 </p>

<p>RAPH1 
ND 
14 
À0.63 
MDD only 
5 
0.25 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
TLR7 
ND 
14 
À0.00 
MDD only 
5 
À0.93 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
UBE3A 
ND 
14 
À0.27 
MDD only 
5 
0.41 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 </p>

<p>ZNF291/SCAPER 
ND 
14 
À0.36 
MDD only 
5 
À0.82 
MDD only 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 </p>

<p>Chronic stress model genes 
AHSP 
ND 
14 
À0.46 
MDD only 
5 
À0.59 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
AMFR 
ND 
14 
À0.57 
MDD only 
5 
À1.06 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 </p>

<p>CAT 
ND 
14 
À0.54 
MDD only 
5 
À0.55 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
CDR2 
ND 
14 
À0.87 
MDD only 
5 
0.99 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
CMAS 
ND 
14 
À0.77 
MDD only 
5 
0.85 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
DGKA 
ND 
14 
À0.07 
MDD only 
5 
À1.47 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
EMB 
ND 
14 
À0.19 
MDD only 
5 
0.36 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
FECH 
ND 
14 
À0.41 
MDD only 
5 
À0.08 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 
GCLM 
ND 
14 
À0.19 
MDD only 
5 
0.69 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
GGA3 
ND 
14 
À0.25 
MDD only 
5 
À0.58 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
IRF3 
ND 
14 
À0.34 
MDD only 
5 
À0.86 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 </p>

<p>KIAA1539 
ND 
14 
À0.01 
MDD only 
5 
À0.99 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 </p>

<p>PSME1 
ND 
14 
À0.52 
MDD only 
5 
0.52 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
PTP4A3 
ND 
14 
À0.77 
MDD only 
5 
0.45 
MDD 
13 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
8 
SLC4A1 
ND 
14 
À0.07 
MDD only 
5 
À0.88 
MDD 
14 
MDD + anxiety disorder 
9 </p>

<p>Positive effect size indicates increased fold change compared with ND or MDD-only, whereas negative is the opposite. </p>

<p>Blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD 
K Pajer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>GGA3, IRF3, KIAA1539 and SLC4A1 are specific to MDD 
comorbid with anxiety. Third, 55% of the potential markers in 
the MDD/ND panel are from the chronic stress model, 
whereas nearly 70% of those in the MDD with or without 
Anxiety Disorders panel are from the chronic stress model. </p>

<p>Chronic stress gene transcripts and chronic stress 
in youths. Youths with depression had more exposure to 
maltreatment than did those who did not have any disorder 
(Mean MDD ¼ 41.1 ± 5.9 (s.d.) vs Mean ND ¼ 30.2 ± 5.9 (s.d.), 
effect size ¼ 1.74). CTQ Total score was correlated with 4 of 
the 26 gene transcripts at the level of a medium effect size or 
greater: CMAS, PSME1, PTP4A3 and IRF3. These markers 
were all derived from the chronic stress model. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Despite considerable efforts, there are still no valid, reliable 
and feasible peripheral/blood biomarkers that can diagnose 
MDD, classify MDD subtypes and measure treatment 
response, even in adult-onset MDD. 
23 Our research is unique 
in the attempt to discover a biomarker panel for early-onset 
MDD, a more severe disorder than adult onset. Our approach 
is also innovative in combining theoretical and atheoretical 
strategies in animal models of depression to identify a panel of 
transcripts in the blood that did distinguish subjects with early-
onset MDD from those in the ND group. Moreover, a partly 
overlapping set of transcripts differentiated youths with MDD-
only from those having MDD with comorbid Anxiety Disorders, 
providing the first panel of blood transcripts that might be 
useful for detecting these endophenotypes. 
Previous research to identify panels of blood biomarkers 
has focused on serum factors 
46,47 or on blood expression 
biomarkers using the complex approach of Convergent 
Functional Genomics developed by Le-Niculescu et al. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>The strategy recently being used to identify serum-based 
markers is to select them from biochemical domains 
previously associated with MDD. 
47 This approach has the 
advantage of focusing on the biologically functional protein 
end points. The Convergent Functional Genomics approach 
combined brain and blood expression data from a pharmaco-
genomic animal model with human blood and post-mortem 
expression data and human genetic linkage/association data. 
This elegant assemblage of multiple levels of information has 
the advantage that the markers thus selected could yield 
information about genetic vulnerability and related transcrip-
tomic changes. 
Our approach is not a duplication of these efforts described 
above, but rather one that is based on the atheoretical, or 
unbiased, exploratory exploitation of two theoretical animal 
models of depression. These models comprised the genetic 
and the environmental (chronic stress) components of MDD 
etiology, and thereby these candidate biomarkers for MDD 
highlight genetic vulnerability factors and their transcriptomic 
consequences, in addition to biological costs of a repeated 
stressor. The strengths of our approach include the unique-
ness of the genetic animal model we employed, and the 
selection process of candidate markers. Namely, transcripts 
were selected as candidates when they showed significant 
same-directional differences in any of the brain regions </p>

<p>examined and in the blood of the genetically 'depressed' 
WMI compared with their genetically very close control, the 
WLI. This allowed us to verify that the candidate transcripts 
were relevant to brain functions and, therefore, some of these 
transcripts can be regarded as prospective novel drug targets. 
Another strength is that our chronic stress blood markers were 
compiled from a study of four genetically diverse strains, 
thereby providing a rather narrow, but powerfully informative, 
set of transcripts. These transcripts represent generalizable 
responsiveness to stress and signify the notion that stress 
marks all organisms, regardless of their vulnerability or 
resilience. 
The first biomarker panel we define consists of 11 
transcripts that differentiated youths with MDD from those 
without any disorder. These candidate markers are derived 
almost equally from the genetic and chronic stress models of 
depression. The genes expressing these transcripts belong to 
three broad functional categories: those involved in transcrip-
tion, neurodevelopment and neurodegeneration. Genes with 
transcriptional regulatory functions include MAF, which 
encodes a DNA-binding, leucine zipper-containing transcrip-
tion factor, and the cytoplasmic cerebellar degeneration-
related protein 2 antigen (CDR2), which harbors a helix-
leucine zipper motif and interacts specifically with c-Myc. </p>

<p>48   Genes that regulate, modify or interfere with neurodevelop-
ment include RAPH1 (Ras association and pleckstrin homol-
ogy domains 1, also known as LPD), which is intimately 
involved in proper neuronal migration. 
49 Tyrosine phospha-
tase PTP4A3, also called PRL-3, has oncogenic activity, but 
has also been reported to promote cell migration. 
50 CMAS 
encodes an enzyme, cytidine monophosphate N-acetylneur-
aminic acid synthetase (also known as CMP-Neu5Ac synthe-
tase), which regulates brain sialylation levels and, therefore, 
very likely affects brain development. 
51 Cell adhesion 
molecule 1 (CADM1), also known as immunoglobulin super-
family, member 4 (IGSF4), is a synaptic adhesive molecule 
involved in neural cell adhesion processes and synaptogen-
esis. 
52 CADM1 is thought to contribute to depressive-like 
behavior in a recent mouse genetic study, 
53 and has also 
been linked with social impairments and anxiety-like beha-
vior. </p>

<p>54,55   A group of candidate biomarkers have known functions in 
processes that mediate neuronal damage. PSME1 (protea-
some activator subunit 1, also called PA28a) activates the 
proteosomal hydrolysis of intracellular proteins. Inadequate 
glucose supply causes damage of neuronal cells, and PSME1 
is highly responsive to hypoglycemic environment in neu-
rons. 
56 CD59, also called MIRL or protectin, encodes a single-
chain, glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored cell surface 
protein structurally homologous to snake venom neuro-
toxins. 
57 The protein has complement-inhibitory properties, 
but its capability to mediate complement-mediated damage to 
neurons is also recognized. 
58-61 The CAT gene encodes 
catalase, a key antioxidant enzyme that serves as a defense 
against oxidative stress. Chronic unpredictable stress de-
creases CAT expression in the mouse cerebral cortex and 
hippocampus; 
62 these effects may be mirrored by the 
decreased expression of this gene in the blood of both the 
chronic stress model and subjects with MDD. The expression 
of AMFR (autocrine motility factor receptor), otherwise known </p>

<p>Blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD 
K Pajer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

<p>as GP78, which encodes an endoplasmic reticulum mem-
brane-anchored ubiquitin ligase, is increased by accumulation 
of neurodegenerative disease proteins, such as mutant 
huntingtin, 
63 SOD1 and ataxin-3. 
64 This increase in AMFR 
expression may represent a protective response to enhance 
the removal of these disease proteins, and suggests that a 
decrease of AMFR/GP78 expression, as we found in MDD, 
might make the organism more vulnerable to these diseases. 
The second panel consists of 18 transcripts that distin-
guished youths who had MDD with comorbid anxiety 
disorders from those with MDD alone. Only six gene 
transcripts were in both panels, and thus the majority of these 
markers are unique to this diagnostic category. Furthermore, 
the panel differentiating MDD youths with and without 
comorbid anxiety disorders had a substantially higher number 
of genes derived from the chronic stress model than from the 
genetic model. These latter observations support the long-
standing clinical impression that MDD with comorbid anxiety 
disorders is a unique phenotype. Moreover, it is possible that 
there are different etiologic factors involved in this endophe-
notype, for example, exposure to chronic stress particularly at 
the highly stressful period of adolescence. Most of these 
transcripts have no known function relevant to MDD or brain, 
including three of the four 'genetic depression model' markers: 
FAM46A (family with sequence similarity 46, member A), 
NAGA (N-acetylgalactosaminidase) and ZNF291/SCAPER 
(S-phase cyclin A-associated protein in the ER). Among the 
'chronic stress model' markers, AHSP (a hemoglobin stabiliz-
ing protein), DGKA (diacylglycerol kinase, a), SLC4A1 (solute 
carrier family 4, anion exchanger, member 1) and KIAA1539 
have either no brain-related functions to date or no known 
function. 
Genes whose transcripts differentiated MDD with and 
without comorbid anxiety and which have known functions 
relevant to MDD or stress encode proteins involved in 
immunoregulation or neurodegeneration. IRF3 (interferon 
regulatory factor 3), identified from the chronic stress animal 
model, has been established previously as a chronic 
psychological stress-responsive gene in human peripheral 
blood cells. 
65 TLR7, an intracellular Toll-like receptor, is an 
innate immunity receptor that activates inflammation and 
adaptive immunity. TLR7, or its agonists, induce inflammatory 
responses in the periphery and in the brain, 
66 and greater 
expression of TLR7 are associated with poor functional 
outcome in ischemic stroke patients. 
67 Polymorphism in 
GCLM (glutamate cysteine ligase modulatory subunit), the 
first rate-limiting enzyme of glutathione synthesis, has been 
associated with depression and schizophrenia, although this 
association has not been confirmed. 
68 Nevertheless, glu-
tathione deficits have been observed in several neurodegen-
erative and psychiatric disorders including Alzheimer's, 
Parkinson's or Huntington's diseases 
69 as well as in schizo-
phrenia. GGA3 (golgi-associated, gamma adaptin ear con-
taining ARF binding protein 3) is involved in the pathogenesis 
of Alzheimer's disease. 
70 It is interesting to note that subjects 
with lower levels of GGA3 may be at risk for developing 
Alzheimer's disease, 
70 and that MDD is thought to be a 
triggering or precipitating factor in Alzheimer's disease. 
Several of the blood candidate markers whose expression 
differed between MDD and controls or between MDD </p>

<p>subtypes are involved in different neurodegenerative pro-
cesses, suggesting that MDD, and perhaps other psychiatric 
illnesses, can lead to neurodegeneration. These markers, 
therefore, could present a generic 'neurodegenerative finger-
print' in the brain and blood. Alternatively, as Alzheimer's, 
Parkinson's and other neurodegenerative illnesses are known 
to show symptoms of depression before their regular presen-
tation, depression might be a precipitating factor in these 
illnesses indicated by the presence of these biomarkers. 
When we explored associations between CTQ Total scores 
and transcript levels, we found that the transcripts with 
potential clinical significance were all derived from the chronic 
stress animal model. These four transcripts, CMAS, IRF3, 
PSME1 and PTP4A3, share no close connections in their 
functions, but their altered expressions are likely to represent 
long-term consequences of maltreatment, as these youths 
may have experienced maltreatment for as long ago as 
8-10 years before the time of data collection. 
The current study's limitations lie in its relatively small 
samples sizes and the limited number of target transcripts we 
were able to pursue. Additionally, we recognize that the 
animal models only mirror some aspects of early-onset MDD 
and, therefore, the markers derived from them cannot be all 
inclusive. Nonetheless, the purpose of this type of study in 
biomarker research is to determine if there are sufficient data 
to proceed to a full-size study of the candidate transcripts in 
a large representative sample of young people with and 
without MDD. 
In summary, we have taken a novel approach to identifying 
potential peripheral biomarkers for early-onset MDD. The 
main goal of this pilot study was to determine if blood 
transcripts from both a genetic and a chronic stress animal 
model of depression could lead to candidate blood biomarkers 
for early-onset MDD in human subjects. The pilot data 
presented here suggest that our approach leads to a clinically 
valid diagnostic panel of blood transcripts that can differenti-
ate early-onset MDD from controls and MDD with from MDD 
without anxiety. The next step is to test our findings in a large 
sample of youths with MDD, comparing them with youths 
without any psychiatric disorder and youths diagnosed with 
other psychiatric disorders. Eventually, the effect of treatment 
on validated biomarkers panels can be established, allowing 
for further individualization of MDD treatment strategies. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We acknowledge the following for their help in this </p>

<p>study: Jelena Radulovic, Pradeep Shukla, Claire Will and Fraser Aird. Animal work 
was supported by grants from the Davee Foundation, the RD Foundation and by the 
NIH Grant MH077234. Human work was funded by grants from the Research 
Institute of Nationwide Children's Hospital in Columbus, OH. </p>



<p>Blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD 
K Pajer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>





<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry is an open-access journal 
published by Nature Publishing Group. This work is 
licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-No 
Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on the Translational Psychiatry website (http://www.nature.com/tp) </p>

<p>Blood biomarkers for early-onset MDD 
K Pajer et al </p>



<p>Translational Psychiatry </p>

</text></tei>