<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3859226" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We studied a two-generation family presenting with conditions that included progressive permanent weakness, myopathic 
myopathy, exercise-induced contracture before normokalaemic periodic paralysis or, if localized to the tibial anterior muscle 
group, transient compartment-like syndrome (painful acute oedema with neuronal compression and drop foot). 
23 Na and </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H 
magnetic resonance imaging displayed myoplasmic sodium overload, and oedema. We identified a novel familial Ca v 1.1 calcium 
channel mutation, R1242G, localized to the third positive charge of the domain IV voltage sensor. Functional expression of 
R1242G in the muscular dysgenesis mouse cell line GLT revealed a 28% reduced central pore inward current and a À 20 mV 
shift of the steady-state inactivation curve. Both changes may be at least partially explained by an outward omega (gating pore) 
current at positive potentials. Moreover, this outward omega current of 27.5 nS/nF may cause the reduction of the overshoot by 
13 mV and slowing of the upstroke of action potentials by 36% that are associated with muscle hypoexcitability (permanent 
weakness and myopathic myopathy). In addition to the outward omega current, we identified an inward omega pore current of 
95 nS/nF at negative membrane potentials after long depolarizing pulses that shifts the R1242G residue above the omega pore 
constriction. A simulation reveals that the inward current might depolarize the fibre sufficiently to trigger calcium release in the 
absence of an action potential and therefore cause an electrically silent depolarization-induced muscle contracture. Additionally, 
evidence of the inward current can be found in 
23 Na magnetic resonance imaging-detected sodium accumulation and </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H 
magnetic resonance imaging-detected oedema. We hypothesize that the episodes are normokalaemic because of depolariza-
tion-induced compensatory outward potassium flux through both delayed rectifiers and omega pore. We conclude that the 
position of the R1242G residue before elicitation of the omega current is decisive for its conductance: if the residue is located 
below the gating pore as in the resting state then outward currents are observed; if the residue is above the gating pore because 
of depolarization, as in the inactivated state, then inward currents are observed. This study shows for the first time that 
functional characterization of omega pore currents is possible using a cultured cell line expressing mutant Ca v 1.1 channels. 
Likewise, it is the first calcium channel mutation for complicated normokalaemic periodic paralysis. </p>

<p>Periodic paralyses are recurrent bouts of flaccid limb weakness 
traditionally differentiated by accompanying changes in serum po-
tassium levels, as hyperkalaemic, hypokalaemic or normokalaemic 
episodes (Fontaine, 2008). Each of these variants of periodic 
paralysis is caused by autosomal dominant mutations in skeletal 
muscle cation channels; however, the specific mutations elicit dif-
fering functional defects. Hyperkalaemic periodic paralysis is 
caused by destabilized inactivation of the main ion conducting 
pore, whereas normokalaemic and hypokalaemic periodic paralysis 
are caused by an accessory current through the so-called omega 
pore, resulting from a short circuit of intracellular and extracellular 
compartments produced directly by voltage sensor mutation 
(Cannon, 2010; Catterall 2010; Jurkat-Rott et al., 2012). 
Mutations for all three types of periodic paralysis are found in 
the Na v 1.4 sodium channel encoded by SCN4A. To date, muta-
tions in the Ca v 1.1 calcium channel encoded by CACNA1S have 
been associated only with hypokalaemic periodic paralysis. Nearly 
all of these mutations are located in the transmembrane S4 seg-
ments, and neutralize positive charges important for voltage sen-
sitivity (Matthews et al., 2009). Similar to the hypokalaemic 
periodic paralysis mutations in Na v 1.4, the two most frequent 
Ca v 1.1 mutations (R528H and R1239H) produce inward omega 
currents that result in membrane depolarization, reduced mem-
brane excitability, and muscle weakness (Jurkat-Rott et al.,  2009; Wu et al., 2012). 
In Na v 1.4, the position of the S4 mutation determines the volt-
age range in which the omega current occurs. For example, mu-
tations of the first arginine in domain II, II-R1, as well as II-R2 and 
III-R2 mutations generate omega currents that are activated by 
hyperpolarization, are active at the usual resting potential, and 
are only closed by depolarization large enough to activate S4 
(Sokolov et al., 2007; Struyk et al., 2008; Sokolov et al., 2010;  Francis et al., 2011; Wu et al., 2011). Depending on the substi-
tuting residue, the omega current may be carried by protons or 
cations (Struyk and Cannon, 2007). Omega pores conduct cur-
rents that show an above-linear increase in amplitude with hyper-
polarization that reflects the stochastic process of a voltage-
dependent open probability and follows a Boltzmann distribution. 
In contrast to the hyperpolarization-induced omega currents from 
substitutions of the outer two arginine residues R1 or R2, II-R3 
mutations in Na v 1.4 generate cation-selective currents that are 
activated by depolarization (Sokolov et al., 2008). Such an 
omega current is deactivated by hyperpolarization and the asso-
ciated disease phenotype is normokalaemic (Vicart et al., 2004). 
Here we report an American family with normokalaemic peri-
odic paralysis and recurrent cramping, oedema and neuronal com-
pression with additional progressive myopathy caused by a novel 
Ca v 1.1-R1242G mutation. Similar to normokalaemic periodic par-
alysis mutations in the sodium channel domain II, R1242G affects 
the third arginine of S4. Our results suggest that the pathogenesis 
associated with R1242G differs from the Ca v 1.1 hypokalaemic </p>

<p>periodic paralysis mutations. This is the first report of an omega 
pore induced by functional expression of a calcium channel 
mutation in cultured cells, while previously studied muscle fibres 
may have been altered by secondary changes (Jurkat-Rott et al.,  2009; Wu et al., 2012). </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>The family members gave their written informed consent to the gen-
etic and 3T 
23 Na-MRI studies, which were approved of by the Ethics </p>

<p>Committee of both Ulm and Heidelberg University and were con-
ducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki in its present form. 
The exons and exon-intron boundaries of CACNA1S (Jurkat-Rott  et al., 1994) were amplified from genomic DNA and bidirectionally 
sequenced using an automated 373A sequencer (Applied Biosystems). </p>

<p>Clinical neurophysiology and muscle 
biopsies </p>

<p>In the long exercise test (Tengan et al., 2004), the patients performed 
seven episodes of finger spreading against strong resistance of 35 to 
40 s each, before 2 to 3 s relaxation to ensure sufficient blood flow 
during testing. Compound muscle action potentials were recorded 2 s 
immediately after cessation of exercise, every minute for 5 min, and 
every 5 min for 1 h. Compound muscle action potentials were recorded 
from the left abductor digiti minimi muscle using surface electrodes. 
They were evoked by supramaximal nerve stimulation (constant cur-
rent method, 125%) of the ulnar nerve at the wrist, each lasting 
0.2 ms. 
Triceps muscle sections of Patient II:2 were fixed with formalin and 
stained with haematoxylin-eosin and embedded in paraffin. Fresh-
frozen sections were stained with haematoxylin-eosin, NADH-TR, 
modified trichrome, non-specific esterase, and alkaline preincubated 
ATPase. Additional sections were fixed with glutaraldehyde and 
post-fixed with OsO 4 . For light microscopy, semi-thin plastic 
embedded sections of 1-mm thickness were stained with haematoxy-
lin-eosin and toluidine-blue. For electron microscopy, ultra-thin plastic 
sections were stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate. The immu-
nocytological reactions included dystrophin 1-3 and sarcoglycans. </p>

<p>Imaging </p>

<p>The MRI scans were performed on a 3 T clinical MR system 
(MAGNETOM Trio, Siemens AG Medical Solutions). Hardware specific 
for broadband spectroscopy and a CE-certified double-resonant bird-
cage coil (32.59 MHz/123.2 MHz, Rapid Biomed Inc.) were used for 
recording </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Na as well as </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H signals. The imaging protocol of the 
lower legs comprised axial T 1 -weighted turbo spin-echo for the detec-
tion of fatty muscle degeneration and axial short-tau inversion recov-
ery </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H magnetic resonance sequences for the identification of 
muscular oedema. The muscular signal intensity on short-tau inversion 
recovery images was normalized to the background signal as described 
previously (Jurkat-Rott et al., 2009). 
Two reference phantoms were additionally investigated for use as 
control signal. One was filled with 51.3 mM Na 
+ in NaCl solution to </p>

<p>mimic Na 
+ with unrestricted mobility as in extracellular fluid, and the </p>



<p>C. Fan et al. </p>

<p>other was filled with 51.3 mM Na 
+ in 5% agarose to mimic Na 
+ with </p>

<p>restricted mobility as in myoplasm. In some recordings, a third refer-
ence was present containing 0.6% NaCl in H 2 O. For normalization of </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Na signals, the values of samples from the soleus muscles were 
divided by the signal intensity of the agarose phantom in which 
NaCl was trapped. </p>

<p>Expression of calcium channels </p>

<p>GFP-1 s (Grabner et al., 1998) was used for site-directed mutagenesis 
of R1242G. Expression plasmids were verified by sequencing. 
Myotubes of the homozygous dysgenic cell line GLT were cultured 
as previously described (Jurkat-Rott et al., 1998) and transfected in 
a ratio of 4 ml FuGENE 
Õ HD reagent to 2 mg complementary DNA, 2 to </p>

<p>3 days after changing the fusion medium. </p>

<p>Central pore and omega pore currents </p>

<p>Whole-cell recordings were performed on 8 to 10-day-old myotubes 
with GFP fluorescence. Cells were allowed to stabilize for 5 min after 
establishment of the whole-cell configuration before data acquisition. 
Currents were recorded at room temperature (20-22 
C) after partial </p>

<p>(30-60%) series resistance compensation using an Axopatch 200B 
amplifier (Axon Instruments). The resistance of pipettes was 2.0 to 
3.5 M after filling with internal solution. Data were filtered at 
1 kHz and sampled at 2 kHz (for calcium current recordings) or filtered 
at 1 kHz and sampled at 5 kHz (for omega current recordings). All 
recordings were performed without on-line leak subtraction. For meas-
urements of calcium or omega currents, the linear passive currents at 
various potentials were calculated from the value at the holding po-
tential of À90 mV, and these currents were subtracted from the cur-
rent recordings. 
For the electrophysiological characterization of central pore calcium 
current, the external solution contained (in mM): TEA-Cl 132, CaCl 2 
10, MgCl 2 1, glucose 5, 4-aminopyridine 2.5, HEPES 10, pH 7.4; the 
internal solution contained (in mM): CsCl 128, EGTA 10, Mg-ATP 5, 
phosphocreatine 5, HEPES 12, pH 7.2. For the measurements of 
omega currents, the external solution contained (in mM): TEA-methane-
sulphonate (MS) 80, guanidine sulphate 38, MgSO 4 1, Ca-gluconate 5, 
glucose 5, 4-aminopyridine 2.5, HEPES 10, pH 7.4; the internal solution 
contained (in mM): TEA-MS 65, Cs-MS 65, EGTA 10, Mg ATP 5, Na 2 
creatine PO 4 5, HEPES 12, pH 7.2. For ionic substitution experiments, 
internal Cs-MS was replaced by guanidinium whereas external guanidi-
nium was replaced by NMDG 
+ . Sodium currents were blocked by add-</p>

<p>ition of 5 mM tetrodotoxin to all bath solutions. </p>

<p>Action potentials </p>

<p>Action potentials were measured with the whole-cell current clamp 
technique using an Axopatch 200B amplifier. Hyperpolarizing current 
was injected into the myotubes to bring the membrane potential to 
about À110 mV for 6 s to recover sodium channels from inactivation. 
With anode break of the hyperpolarizing pulse, action potentials were 
elicited. The bath solution contained (in mM): NaCl 130, KCl 4, CaCl 2 
1.8, MgCl 2 1.2, NaHCO 3 18, HEPES 10, glucose 10, pH 7.4; pipette 
solution contained (in mM): KCl 10, K-gluconate 125, CaCl 2 0.6, 
MgCl 2 2, HEPES 5, Na 2 ATP 4, EGTA 5, sucrose 30, pH 7.2. The 
cells were continuously perfused with bath solution and maintained 
at 37 
C. Signals were filtered at 5 kHz and sampled at 2 kHz. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>The current-voltage dependence of whole cell currents through the 
central pore was fit according to </p>

<p>I V 
ð Þ ¼ g leak Â V M À V leak 
ð 
Þ þ g max </p>

<p>Â V M À V Ca 
ð 
Þ = 1 þ exp V 0:5 À V M 
ð 
Þ =k 
ð 
Þ 
À 
Á 
: </p>

<p>V leak and g leak are reversal potential and conductance of linear leak 
current, V Ca and g max are reversal potential and maximum conduct-
ance of calcium channels, V 0.5 is the potential for half-maximal 
current, V M is the test potential and k is the slope factor. Steady-
state inactivation curves were fit to the equation </p>

<p>I=I max ¼ A= 1 þ exp V 0:5 À V M 
ð 
Þ =k 
ð 
Þ 
À 
Á 
þ C: </p>

<p>V M represents the prepulse potential, V 0.5 is the potential at which half 
of channels are inactivated, and C is the fraction of non-inactivated 
channels, or asymptote. Recovery from inactivation was fitted to 
I (t) /I max = À A Â exp( Àt/) + C, with as time constant of recovery, 
A as respective amplitude of time constant and C as asymptote of recov-
ery. Data were analysed by a combination of <rs id="software-0" type="software">pClamp</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Axon Instruments</rs>), <rs id="software-1" type="software">Excel</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Microsoft</rs>), <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">IBM</rs>) and ORIGIN (Microcal 
software). Data were presented as mean AE standard error of the mean 
(SEM). Student's t-tests were applied for statistical evaluation with the 
significance levels set to *P 5 0.05, **P 5 0.01, ***P 5 0.001. </p>

<p>Simulation </p>

<p>To compare our results with earlier models of pathogenesis of periodic 
paralysis, we simulated the membrane current based on the implemen-
tation of the inward rectifying potassium current IK by the Boltzmann 
empirical equation described as </p>

<p>IK ¼ g Kmax = 1 þ exp E m À E h 
ð 
Þ =s 
ð 
Þ 
À 
Á 
Â E m À E K 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>(Hagiwara and Takahashi, 1974). The K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>reversal potential 
E K = À95.8 mV was given by the Nernst equation with 
K </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>I = 145 mM and K </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>o = 4 mM. A maximal conductance g Kmax of 
48 mS/cm 
2 for normal human muscle fibres was taken from </p>

<p>Kwiecinski et al. (1984). E h = À80 mV and s = 12 mV are constants 
that were deduced from measured membrane currents of human 
muscle (Ruff, 1999; Jurkat-Rott et al., 2009). Similarly, values used 
to describe the delayed rectifier potassium current were g Kmax = 20 mS/ 
cm 
2 , E h = À 80 mV, and s = 12 mV. </p>

<p>For the simulation of hypokalaemic periodic paralysis, a correspond-
ing Boltzmann fit using E Na = 61.5 mV given by the Nernst equation 
with Na </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>I = 15 mM and Na </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>o = 150 mM was performed. This procedure 
resulted in fit parameters of E h = À110 mV and s = 10 mV and the 
maximum conductance of 12 mS/cm 
2 for R528H (Jurkat-Rott et al., </p>

<p>2009). For the R1242G omega current, attempts to fit the almost 
constant omega current using Boltzmann fits yielded unrealistic 
values. Therefore, we took the original data and upscaled them to 
the maximum conductance of 0.5 Â 95 = 47.5 nS/nF to reflect the 
heterozygous situation in human muscle (95 nS/nF calculated in the 
results section on omega currents). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Clinical features </p>

<p>The family over two generations consisted of four affected mem-
bers (Fig. 1A). The three adults, Patients I:1, II:2 and II:4, had </p>

<p>Novel phenotype by Ca v 1.1 mutation </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 3775-3786 | 3777 </p>

<p>episodes characterized by painful muscle cramping for several 
hours followed by flaccid weakness lasting up to days. The male 
child, Patient II:1, was completely paralysed at birth and died from 
respiratory failure on the seventh post-natal day after the mother 
received anaesthesia when giving birth. 
Of the adults, male Patient I:1 had onset in infancy and delayed 
motor development. Triggers for the weakness episodes were cold 
and rest after exercise. Progressive weakness started in adulthood 
and led to wheelchair dependence at the age of 57. Ictal potas-
sium levels were normal and KCl three times daily did not improve 
muscle strength. Death occurred at the age of 71 from respiratory 
failure after anaesthesia. 
Female Patient II:2 (63-years-old) had painful muscle cramping 
in the lower legs elicited by walking and by febrile infections be-
tween early teens and adulthood. The cramping muscles were 
solid for days, could not be relieved by passive stretching, and 
were paralysed for months or permanently, requiring leg braces </p>

<p>for dropped feet. Weakness spells without preceding cramps only 
occurred twice, once by stress and once following a meal, and 
both resolved after 1 h. A permanent weakness causing inability 
to participate in physical education during elementary school 
increased in late adolescence and adulthood. The overall muscle 
strength declined, as an inability to climb stairs without railing, to 
arise from a chair, to get up from a prone position or to arise from 
bed became the characteristic features. She became wheelchair 
bound at the age of 50. Progressive weakness led to the latest 
status at age 62 according to MRC rating scale: diffuse atrophy of 
extremities, bilateral scapular winging, forearm flexion 2/2 (right/ 
left), wrist extension 5/4, finger flexion 4/4, hip flexion 1/1, knee 
extension 1/1, knee flexion 1/1, foot dorsiflexion 4/1, and foot 
plantar flexion 4/4. Tendon reflexes were absent. Ictal and inter-
ictal potassium levels always were normal at 4.1 AE 0.3 mM 
(n = 78), with 500 mg/d acetazolamide administered for decades 
with equivocal benefit. Diclofenamide was more effective and </p>

<p>Figure 1 (A) Pedigree of the family. (B) Long exercise tests obtained from the two sisters (normokalaemic periodic paralysis Patients </p>

<p>(NPP) II:2 and II:4), a hypokalaemic periodic paralysis patient (HypoPP), and a control subject. (C-E) MRI results of Patient II:2: The T 1 -
weigthed 
1 H-MRI (C) detected a pronounced fatty degeneration of both triceps surae muscles and the left, paralysed tibialis anterior and </p>

<p>the deep posterior compartment, whereas these compartments were spared on the stronger right side. The fat-suppressed T 2 -weighted 
1 H-MRI (D) showed an increased water signal of the right tibialis anterior and both deep posterior compartments. The 
23 Na-MRI (E) </p>

<p>identified an elevated sodium signal of the tibialis anterior and the deep posterior compartments on the right side as well as the left 
peroneal compartment whereas the dystrophic left tibialis anterior showed no increased Na 
+ signal. Interposed between the lower legs are </p>

<p>two references (right tube containing 51.3 mM Na 
+ in 5% agarose and left tube containing the same Na 
+ concentration in NaCl-</p>

<p>solution). (F-H) MRI results of Patient II:4. Although the T 1 -weighted 
1 H-MRI (F) only revealed degeneration of the calf muscles, the fat-</p>

<p>suppressed T 2 -weighted 
1 H-MRI (G) showed a marked oedema of all other lower leg muscles. The </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Na-MRI (H) identified an elevated 
sodium signal of the right tibialis anterior. </p>



<p>C. Fan et al. </p>

<p>improved permanent muscle weakness at 25 mg/d but was dis-
continued because of cognitive impairment including mental fa-
tigue, uneasiness, irritability, depression, drowsiness and confusion. 
A combination of acetazolamide 125 mg/d, eplerenone 50 mg/d 
and KCl 40 mmol/d increased serum potassium to 4.8 to 5.2 mM 
and subjectively improved muscle endurance. 
Female Patient II:4 (54-years-old) was born floppy and showed 
delayed motor development. Cramps leading to solid muscles 
were triggered by walks and cold environment and were not 
relieved by passive stretching. During cramping, all muscles inner-
vated by the profound peroneus nerve were weak and exhibited 
electrical silence in the EMG. Additionally, the corresponding skin 
of the anteriolateral lower leg and the dorsal foot was hypaesthe-
sic and hypalgesic. After one of these episodes of cramping, serum 
values for creatine kinase (15 500 U/l), serum glutamic oxaloacetic 
transaminase (1185 U/l) and potassium (5.4 mM) were markedly 
increased. Weeks later, EMG recordings of tibialis and peroneus 
longus muscles revealed fibrillations and positive waves as well as 
small compound muscle action potentials and long distal latencies. 
Because of the dropped foot (Supplementary Fig. 1A), a leg 
brace was required. The only weakness episode without preceding 
cramps was triggered by local anaesthesia containing epinephrine. 
The latest status at the age of 53 revealed a positive 
Trendelenburg sign bilaterally, ubiquitous muscle atrophy espe-
cially in the feet, and inability to squat or walk on toes or heels. 
Foot dorsiflexion was + 4 on the right, and + 1 on the left side. 
Tendon reflexes were reduced but not absent. Proximal muscles 
showed mild myopathic changes in the EMG. Interictal potassium 
levels were always normal (4.0 AE 0.7 mM, n = 22), also with 
500 mg/d acetazolamide administered for decades with equivocal 
benefit. Similarly, diclofenamide improved permanent muscle 
weakness at 25 mg/d but was discontinued because of semantic 
deficit i.e. misusing the names of everyday items, which strikingly 
reduced her professional practice. A combination of acetazolamide 
125 mg/d, eplerenone 50 mg/d and KCl 40 mmol/d increased 
serum potassium to 4.8 to 5.2 mM and stabilized muscle function. 
See Supplementary material on ictal potassium, diet and treatment 
response of the two sisters. </p>

<p>Molecular diagnosis </p>

<p>Sanger sequencing of all coding exons of the CACNA1S and 
SCN4A genes predicted a novel glycine substitution at arginine 
1242 in the Ca v 1.1 calcium channel of skeletal muscle (Fig. 1A). 
R1242G is located as the third charged residue in the fourth 
domain voltage sensor of the channel. SCN4A and KCNJ2 muta-
tions were excluded in all exons by Sanger sequencing. RYR1 was 
negatively screened by high resolution melting. </p>

<p>Neurophysiology and muscle biopsy </p>

<p>The long exercise tests of the sisters Patients II:2 and II:4 revealed 
small compound action potentials of unchanging amplitude and 
shape, but did not reveal the late decrease typically observed in 
patients with hypokalaemic periodic paralysis (Fig. 1B). 
Several muscle biopsies of Patient I:1 primarily contained fat and 
connective tissue and led to the diagnosis of atypical muscle </p>

<p>dystrophy. In Patient II:2, a triceps brachialis muscle sample 
taken at the age of 19 showed fibrosis and chronic myopathic 
changes with internal nucleation, necrotic fibres, increased fibrosis 
and fatty replacement (Supplementary Fig. 1B). A biopsy of the 
contralateral triceps at the age of 40 showed mild type I predom-
inance and mild to moderate type I atrophy with diameter vari-
ation from 30 to 120 mm. Endomysial fibrosis of severe degree was 
noted in several areas, and was absent in others. Occasionally 
myofibres were observed in a state of necrosis, myophagocytosis, 
or regeneration. Electron microscopy showed neither sarcoplasmic 
reticulum nor T-tubule dilations. Dystrophins and sarcoglycans 
were present. In Patient II:4, a deltoid muscle sample biopsied at 
the age of 17 showed regenerating fibres, a slight increase in fat 
and perimysial connective tissue, but no vacuoles. Histochemistry 
was normal. </p>

<p>Imaging </p>

<p>1 H-MRI of Patient II:2 at age 58 showed marked symmetrical fatty </p>

<p>degeneration and atrophy of all lower leg muscles except the right 
tibialis anterior, which displayed a normal muscle signal in the T 1 -
weighted sequences (Fig. 1C). However, increased signal intensity 
was observed in the fat-suppressed T 2 -weighted (i.e. short-tau 
inversion recovery) sequences corresponding to muscular 
oedema (Fig. 1D). The 
23 Na signal was markedly higher in those </p>

<p>muscles with oedema on short-tau inversion recovery images than 
in the dystrophic muscles displaying distinct fatty changes 
(Fig. 1E). 
The 
1 H-MRI of Patient II:4 at the age of 47 years of the lower </p>

<p>legs revealed a symmetrical fatty degeneration and atrophy more 
pronounced in the gastrocnemius than in the soleus muscles. The 
peroneus muscles were affected to a lesser degree (Fig. 1F). The 
long extensor muscles of the foot such as (bilaterally) the tibialis 
anterior showed increased signal intensity in the fat-suppressed 
T 2 -weighted sequences corresponding to a muscular oedema 
(Fig. 1G), whereas the intensity of the T 1 -weighted images was 
normal (Fig. 1H). When normalized to a 0.3% saline reference 
solution, the </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Na-MRI of the lower legs showed a muscular 
sodium signal intensity of 1.32 for the left and 1.26 for the 
right lower leg. This intensity was higher than in controls 
(n = 10; mean value AE SD: 0.99 AE 0.12, 95% confidence interval 
of 0.934-1.053) (Weber et al., 2006). Taking the measurements 
of the right leg and the left leg of the patient as two measure-
ments and comparing them to the 20 measurements of both legs 
of the controls, a one-sided t-test yielded a significant difference 
with P = 0.0007. </p>

<p>Central pore currents </p>

<p>Whole-cell recordings showed that R1242G conducted voltage-
dependent calcium currents through the central ion conducting 
pore (Fig. 2A). Current density of the mutant R1242G, 
at + 30 mV, was significantly reduced to À 3.17 AE 0.11 pA/pF 
compared with wild-type À 4.45 AE 0.33 pA/pF (Fig. 2B). 
Additionally, the current-voltage relationship (Fig. 2B) was 
shifted slightly to the left (V 0.5 = 21.39 AE 1.51 mV in R1242G 
versus V 0.5 = 25.77 AE 1.26 mV in wild-type). R1242G produced a </p>

<p>Novel phenotype by Ca v 1.1 mutation </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 3775-3786 | 3779 </p>

<p>hyperpolarizing (left) shift of steady-state inactivation of about 
À 20 mV in comparison with wild-type (V 0.5 = À 5.88 AE 2.19 mV 
versus V 0.5 = 14.68 AE 1.43 mV, Fig. 2C) indicating a loss-
of-function for inactivation, in addition to activation. Recovery 
from inactivation was significantly more complete in R1242G, 
demonstrating a gain-of-function component (Fig. 2D). 
Parameter values with significance levels are given in Table 1. </p>

<p>Omega currents </p>

<p>Using solutions to omit effects of the central pore, we were able 
to detect omega currents in the transfected myotubes when using 
permeant ions guanidinium and cesium. Steady-state currents eli-
cited by 200 ms step pulses showed that in all myotubes, there 
was an inward current induced at hyperpolarized potentials with 
guanidinium in the external solution (Fig. 3A-C). Based on the 
current-voltage relationship and the fact that the inward current 
was present in both mutant and wild-type myotubes, we </p>

<p>hypothesize that this inward current reflects guanidinium passing 
through the inwardly rectifying Kir2.1 channels and is not the 
result of mutation. In contrast, the mutant R1242G showed de-
polarization-induced outward omega currents carried by caesium 
that were small or absent in wild-type or in untransfected myo-
tubes which we interpret to be an effect of the mutation (Fig. 3A 
and B). Ion substitution experiments showed that the large organic 
ion NMDG 
+ was not conducted by the omega pore (Fig. 3C). </p>

<p>From Fig. 3B, the omega outward current showed at 40 mV a 
mean conductance of about (1.1 pA/pF)/40 mV = 27.5 nS/nF, 
which is comparable to the 28 nS/nF in the homozygous 
Ca v 1.1-R528H mouse myotubes (Wu et al. 2012). Wu et al. 
(2012) used a membrane capacitance of $1 mF/cm 
2 to estimate </p>

<p>their conductance to be 28 mS/cm 
2 in the homozygous mouse </p>

<p>muscle fibres. In the only work measuring omega currents in 
human muscle fibres (Jurkat-Rott et al. 2009), which are always 
heterozygous because of the autosomal dominant inheritance of 
the disease, R528H native muscle fibres had a conductance of </p>

<p>Figure 2 Electrophysiological characteristics of wild-type (WT, filled circles) or mutant R1242G (open circles) 1 s subunits in GLT cells. </p>

<p>(A) Whole-cell currents through wild-type and R1242G calcium channels were recorded at various test potentials between À 60 and 
+ 55 mV in 5 mV for 600 ms with holding potential of À 90 mV. (B) Normalized current-voltage relationships after linear passive current 
subtraction. (C) Voltage dependence of steady-state inactivation was determined from a holding potential of À 90 mV using a series of 
60 s prepulses to potentials ranging from À 90 mV to + 40 mV in 10 mV steps before a test depolarization to + 30 mV. (D) Recovery from 
inactivation was obtained by a two-pulse protocol: a 20-s lasting depolarization prepulse to + 30 mV to inactivate the calcium channels, a 
second 500 ms test pulse to + 30 mV followed after an increasing interval (from 0.5 s to 69.7 s) at different holding potentials ( À 90 mV, 
À 80 mV, and À 70 mV). Data are shown as means AE SEM. Solid lines represent fits to corresponding equations given in the text. Fitting 
parameters are listed in Table 1. </p>



<p>C. Fan et al. </p>

<p>12 mS/cm 
2 , which is indeed about half of the conductance of the </p>

<p>homozygous R528H mouse muscle fibres of 28 mS/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Therefore 
our data in mouse myotube preparations are comparable to all 
previous data available on Ca v 1.1 omega currents. 
In addition, R1242G showed a hyperpolarization-induced 
inward omega pore current carried by guanidinium, observed 
over the entire range of physiological voltages, after 1 min pre-
depolarization to + 30 mV to inactive calcium channels followed 
by a ramp from À 140 mV to + 30 mV over 7 s (Fig. 3D). This 
current is not because of a shift in the electrode junction potential 
because pipette offset before and after the recordings remained 
unchanged. Also, subtraction of the wild-type from R1242G yields 
a current that is neither constant nor linear (Supplementary Fig. 
2A). One explanation could be that the IVS4 segment recovers 
during the ramp. To test this hypothesis, we recorded the reverse 
ramp (7 s ramp from + 30 mV to À 140 mV after 1 min + 30 mV 
depolarization pulse). The resulting inward omega current 
(Supplementary Fig. 2B) exhibited reduced current values for po-
tentials more negative than À 100 mV in agreement with the idea 
of a recovery of IVS4 after $5.5 s. It has a maximal conductance 
of about ( À 3.2 + 2.25 pA/pF) / ( À 140 + 130 mV) = 95 nS/nF in 
the range of À 140 mV to À 130 mV. We conclude that the 
inward omega current is conducted by a IVS4 segment that has 
moved above the omega pore constriction. As the omega current 
is visible over the whole voltage range, linear fitting of the values 
obtained during the ramp was not performed since it would sub-
tract part of the non-linear omega current. 
Taken together, the decisive element for the omega current 
seems to be the position of the R1242G residue with respect to </p>

<p>the gating pore constriction before testing for the omega currents. 
If the residue is located below the gating pore as in the resting 
state then outward currents are observed; if the residue is above 
the gating pore due to depolarization as in the inactivated state 
then inward currents are observed. As the inward omega currents 
are $3-fold larger than the outward omega currents, there seems 
to be some degree of rectification. </p>

<p>Action potentials </p>

<p>We tested the direct effect of the omega current on action 
potentials using whole-cell current clamp recordings in GLT myo-
tubes. Injection of a negative holding current was followed by an 
increasing positive current pulse from 0 to 8 nA that did not affect 
the amplitude or shape of action potentials (Fig. 4A), indicating 
saturation. The R1242G-expressing myotubes exhibited action 
potentials with a significantly reduced overshoot by 13 mV, 
decreased maximal rise slope by 36% and increased threshold 
compared to wild-type by 4 mV (Fig. 4B, P 4 0.05). All measured 
parameters are shown in Table 2. </p>

<p>Simulation </p>

<p>We simulated the pathogenesis to compare the situation for the 
novel phenotype with the situation in hypokalaemic periodic par-
alysis. By estimating the current-voltage relationship of human 
control muscle and then adding the omega currents for hypokal-
aemic periodic paralysis, we simulated the current voltage relation-
ship of hypokalaemic periodic paralysis muscle. Likewise, our 
omega current was added to the control to mimic current-voltage 
relationships for normokalaemic periodic paralysis muscle (Fig. 5). 
The decisive elements for the model are the voltage dependencies 
and reversal potentials of the omega currents. Although the 
omega current for hypokalaemic periodic paralysis mutations 
R528H or R2139H follow a single Boltzmann relationship 
(Jurkat-Rott et al., 2009; Wu et al., 2012), the omega current 
of R1242G is almost constant in the range of À 120 mV to 
À 20 mV (Supplementary Fig. 2A). 
At normal extracellular K </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>o of 4 mM, there is only stable mem-
brane potential (where current is zero). Typically paralysis is 
achieved by hypokalaemia, which reduces the inwardly rectifying 
potassium conductance by collapsing the pore thereby reducing 
the steepness of the curves so much that a second stable resting 
potential at À 60 mV appears (Jurkat-Rott et al., 2009). In con-
trast, at K </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>o of 4 mM a depolarizing trigger (i.e. exertional exercise) 
can depolarize R1242G muscle to À 40 mV at which there would 
be electrically silent contractures (Fig. 5). The contracture results 
because À 40 mV is the mechanical threshold at which Ca v 1.1 can 
interact with the ryanodine receptor to initiate intracellular calcium 
release (this threshold is below the threshold of the Ca v 1.1 central 
pore current of about À 20 mV). The electrical silence observed in 
the cramping patients is because at À 40 mV sodium channels are 
inactivated as well. Depolarization to this value has been shown to 
produce electrically silent cramps followed by weakness previously, 
such as in paramyotonia congenita (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Table 1 Parameters of calcium currents </p>

<p>Parameter 
Wild-type 
R1242G </p>

<p>Current density (pA/pF) 
À4.45 AE 0.33 
À3.17 AE 0.11** 
Capacitance (pF) 
334.7 AE 13.67 
326.89 AE 16.23 
n 
10 
9 
Current activation 
V 0.5 (mV) 
25.77 AE 1.26 
21.39 AE 1.51* 
k 
6.81 AE 0.36 
6.50 AE 0.26 
n 
10 
9 
Steady state inactivation 
V 0.5 (mV) 
14.68 AE 1.43 
À5.88 AE 2.19*** 
k 
À9.65 AE 1.63 
À9.40 AE 1.31 
n 
8 
5 
Recovery from inactivation 
À90 mV 
(s) 
7.99 AE 0.65 
7.29 AE 0.37 
C 
0.65 AE 0.04 
0.79 AE 0.02* 
n 
8 
1 0 
À80 mV 
(s) 
9.76 AE 0.77 
9.24 AE 0.83 
C 
0.61 AE 0.20 
0.75 AE 0.40** 
n 
10 
5 
À70 mV 
(s) 
10.92 AE 1.19 
11.48 AE 0.88 
C 
0.56 AE 0.21 
0.71 AE 0.43** 
n 
7 
8 </p>

<p>*P 5 0.05, **P 5 0.01, ***P 5 0.001. </p>

<p>Novel phenotype by Ca v 1.1 mutation </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 3775-3786 | 3781 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the periodic paralyses, the level of serum potassium during a 
paralytic attack determines the diagnosis (Table 3). While hyper-
kalaemic and hypokalaemic periodic paralysis are accepted as sep-
arate entities, ictal normokalaemia has been a matter of debate. 
The term normokalaemic periodic paralysis was coined in the 
1960s. The disorder resembled hyperkalaemic periodic paralysis 
and its existence as a nosological entity was questioned when 
the identification of the most frequent hyperkalaemic periodic 
paralysis mutation, Na v 1.4-M1592V, in one of the two original 
families was identified (Chinnery et al., 2002). Later a potas-
sium-sensitive periodic paralysis with normokalaemia caused by 
Na v 1.4 mutations at the third arginine of the voltage sensor of 
domain II at codon 675 also was diagnosed as normokalaemic 
periodic paralysis (Vicart et al., 2004) and again interpreted as </p>

<p>hyperkalaemic periodic paralysis because of the triggering effect 
of potassium (Song et al., 2012). 
Because almost all ictal potassium levels of our patients were in 
the normal range (100 values altogether; Supplementary material), 
we diagnosed our family as normokalaemic periodic paralysis. In 
agreement with this, our family shows a number of symptoms that 
may be found in all types of periodic paralysis such as post-natal 
hypotonia, periodic paralysis triggered by stress and cold, and re-
sponse to carboanhydrase inhibitors (Table 3). Further, myoplas-
mic sodium and water accumulation as an indicator for the 
permanent weakness was present in our family as in both hypo-
kalaemic and hyperkalaemic periodic paralysis (Jurkat-Rott et al.,  2009; Amarteifio et al., 2012). However, our family additionally 
displays features not found in other forms of periodic paralysis 
such as: (i) triggering by exercise rather than by rest after exercise; 
(ii) absence of the periodic paralysis typical late decline in the long </p>

<p>Figure 3 Omega currents for R1242G (open circles), but not wild-type (WT, filled circles) or untransfected myotubes (filled triangles). </p>

<p>(A) Representative whole-cell currents were measured by a series of 200 ms voltage steps from a À 90 mV holding potential to voltages 
between À 140 mV to + 40 mV in 5 mV steps without leak subtraction. The R1242G-expressing myotubes showed obvious depolariza-
tion-induced outward omega current carried by caesium compared with non-transfected and wild-type-expressing myotubes. 
(B) Normalized steady-state current-voltage relationships revealed the depolarization-induced outward omega current carried by caesium. 
(C) Substitution experiments showed that the large organic ion NMDG 
+ could not pass the omega pore. (D) Current responses of wild-</p>

<p>type and R1242G to a ramp pulse (inset). The protocol was: from a holding potential of À 90 mV, a 1 min pre-depolarization to + 30 mV 
followed by a ramp from À 140 mV to + 30 mV over 7 s was performed. The current-voltage curve was constructed by currents versus 
their corresponding voltages calculated using the known time course of the ramp protocol. The plotted points are not steady-state current 
values but averages of the corresponding values of the measurements during the ramp. SEM bars were determined at every 5 mV instead 
of each voltage for clarity. R1242G showed obvious inward current carried by guanidinium responding to ramp depolarization. For 
consistency, subtraction of linear passive current was done by the values measured at À 90 mV for all figure parts. Data are shown as 
means AE SEM. </p>



<p>C. Fan et al. </p>

<p>exercise test; and (iii) pre-ictal painful muscle swelling and cramp-
ing rather than post-ictal muscle soreness (Table 3). The episodes 
resulted in rhabdomyolysis and compression of nerves, leading up 
to the development of drop feet and muscle degeneration in the </p>

<p>tibialis anterior group. This is in contrast to the previously reported 
25 patients with hypokalaemic periodic paralysis in whom mainly 
the triceps surae muscles, but not the tibilias anterior groups, were 
affected (Jurkat-Rott et al. 2009). As in the acute phase the pa-
tients showed an albeit reduced pulse of the arteria dorsalis pedis 
and as no operative pressure release was required, our patients did 
not experience complete compartment syndrome. Therefore, we 
used the term 'transient compartment-like syndrome' to describe 
the phenomenon (in analogy to transient ischaemic attack and 
ischaemic brain insult). 
Molecular genetics identified R1242G of the Ca v 1.1 voltage 
sensor in domain IV; such mutations in Ca v 1.1 have so far only 
been related to hypokalaemic periodic paralysis. Although previ-
ously identified mutations neutralize the superficial first or second 
voltage sensor arginines (Jurkat-Rott et al., 2012), the novel 
R1242G amino acid substitution neutralizes the deeper third volt-
age sensor arginine. This location is in agreement with Na v 1.4 
mutations of a third arginine in domain II (R675Q/G/W) 
(Sokolov et al., 2008) that cause normokalaemic periodic paralysis 
(Vicart et al., 2004), whereas more superficially located replace-
ments of voltage sensor arginines cause hypokalaemic periodic 
paralysis (reviewed in Cannon, 2010; Jurkat-Rott et al., 2012). </p>

<p>Figure 4 Action potentials generated in myotubes expressing wild-type (WT) and R1242G. (A) Action potential was evoked by a series of </p>

<p>1 ms increasing depolarizing current stimulation (from 0 to 8 nA in 2 nA increments) after 6 s hyperpolarizing current injection to set 
membrane potential to about À 110 mV. (B) Reduced excitability for the R1242G-(n = 11) than wild-type-expressing myotubes (n = 11): 
reduced overshoot, decreased slope of maximal rise and decreased threshold. Data are shown as means AE SEM. *P 5 0.05. </p>

<p>Table 2 Mean values of action potential parameters 
generated in the wild-type/R1242G-expressing myotubes </p>

<p>Parameter 
Wild-type (n = 11) 
R1242G (n = 11) </p>

<p>Overshoot (mV) 
34.31 AE 2.30 
21.25 AE 4.45* 
Time of overshoot (ms) 
6151.26 AE 4.42 
6151.75 AE 4.09 
20-80% rise time (ms) 
0.57 AE 0.04 
0.78 AE 0.11 
Half-width (ms) 
4.34 AE 0.74 
4.93 AE 0.70 
Maximal rise 
slope (mV/ms) </p>

<p>118.32 AE 6.33 
84.40 AE 10.56* </p>

<p>Time of maximal 
rise slope (ms) </p>

<p>6150.81 AE 4.40 
6151.26 AE 4.07 </p>

<p>Maximal decay 
slope (mV/ms) </p>

<p>À 23.10 AE 2.27 
À19.58 AE 2.87 </p>

<p>Time of maximal 
decay slope (ms) </p>

<p>6151.73 AE 4.42 
6152.49 AE 4.17 </p>

<p>Threshold (mV) 
À 53.49 AE 1.38 
À49.57 AE 1.18* 
Time to threshold (ms) 
24.94 AE 3.96 
25.25 AE 3.83 </p>

<p>*P 5 0.05. </p>

<p>Novel phenotype by Ca v 1.1 mutation </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 3775-3786 | 3783 </p>

<p>As typical for all types of periodic paralysis, the patients 
responded with benefit to the carbonic anhydrase inhibitors acet-
azolamide and diclofenamide, as well as to the aldosterone antag-
onist eplerenone. Both drug groups can repolarize and re-establish 
the excitability of depolarized muscle fibres and thereby wash out 
intracellular sodium ion and reduce oedema (Jurkat-Rott et al.,  2009; Tricarico and Camerino, 2011; Lehmann-Horn et al.,  2012). The triple therapy consisting of low to moderate doses of 
acetazolamide, eplerenone and potassium seems to be a favour-
able medication with low risk of adverse effects, at least in this 
family harbouring the novel normokalaemic periodic paralysis 
mutation Ca v 1.1-R1242G. The previous statement that acetazola-
mide worsens periodic paralysis if caused by an R-to-G mutation 
(Matthews et al., 2011), was not confirmed. 
Our data revealed that R1242G currents produced biophysical 
defects different from those previously reported for periodic par-
alysis mutations. First, R1242G revealed a reduced central pore 
inward current and a left-shift of its steady-state inactivation 
curve. However, Ca v 1.1-R1242G also revealed a depolarization-
induced outward omega current that could at last partially explain 
these two features. Similarly, the depolarization-activated outward 
omega current would oppose the inward sodium current during 
the rising phase of the action potential and contribute to the 
reduced size and altered shape of action potentials. This would 
explain the hypoexcitability of the patients' musculature which 
furthers the permanent weakness (Gong et al., 2003). Next to 
the delayed rectifiers, the outward omega current carried by 
potassium might help maintain the ictal normokalaemia determin-
ing the diagnosis. 
In addition to the outward omega current, we identified an 
inward omega current over a range of negative membrane poten-
tials, after a long depolarization of 1 min duration. According to 
our simulation for patient muscle, the sodium conductance of the 
omega pores may be high enough to depolarize the membrane 
beyond the mechanical threshold of À 40 mV and thereby induce </p>

<p>Table 3 Clinical features </p>

<p>Features 
Hypokalaemic 
periodic paralysis </p>

<p>Hyperkalaemic 
periodic paralysis </p>

<p>Normokalaemic 
periodic paralysis </p>

<p>Patients II:1/II:2/II:4 </p>

<p>Onset age 
First or second decade 
First decade 
First decade 
Post-natally 
Duration 
Hours to days 
Minutes to hours 
Hours to days 
Hours to days 
Dietary triggers 
Carbohydrates 
K-rich food 
À 
À 
Exercise-related triggers 
Rest after exercise 
Rest after exercise 
Rest after exercise 
Exercise 
Other triggers 
Stress, cold 
Stress, cold 
Stress, cold 
Stress, cold 
Myotonia 
À 
+ 
À 
À 
Permanent weakness 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Cramping 
À 
À 
À 
Pre-ictally 
Compartment-like syndrome 
À 
À 
À 
Pre-ictally 
Ictal K 
Decrease 
Increase 
Normal/decrease/increase 
Normal/decrease/increase 
Ictal oedema 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Mutations 
CACNA1S/SCN4A 
SCN4A 
SCN4A 
CACNA1S 
Medication 
Acetazolamide/K 
Acetazolamide 
Acetazolamide 
Acetazolamide/K 
Response to K 
Improves strength 
Triggers weakness 
Depends on ictal k 
Maintains strength 
Long exercise test 
Late decline 
Late decline 
Late decline 
No late decline </p>

<p>Figure 5 Simulation of periodic paralysis. On basis of simulated </p>

<p>inwardly rectifying potassium current IK, comparison of the 
steady-state current voltage relationships in controls, 
hypokalaemic periodic paralysis and our family (normokalaemic 
periodic paralysis), the latter both obtained by addition of omega 
currents to the control curve. Note that at normal K </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>o of 4 mM, a 
depolarizing trigger can depolarize the membrane to À 40 mV at 
which there would be electrically silent cramps. In the inset, a 
similar depolarization contracture is shown in paramyotonia 
congenita in which cooling causes a severe depolarization to 
about À 35 mV: after the fifth electrically induced muscle 
twitch, the excised bundle, that consisted of only few muscle 
fibre layers, contracted without electrical activity (lower trace; 
modified from Ricker et al., 1986). The electrical silence during 
the contracture is verified by wire electrodes that crossed the 
fibres on both surfaces of the bundle and recorded random 
action potential spikes; during the time of stimulation the 
EMG amplifier was overloaded (upper trace). PP = periodic 
paralysis. </p>



<p>C. Fan et al. </p>

<p>muscle contracture. This is experienced by the patients as cramps 
that cannot be relieved by passive stretching and that are char-
acterized by electrical silence in the EMG. We hypothesize that 
depolarized muscle fibres take up not only sodium through the 
omega pore but also osmotic water, to cause fibre swelling that 
may compress nerves, experienced by the patients as pain and 
drop foot (transient compartment-like syndrome). The sustained 
membrane depolarization would inactivate Na v 1.4 channels and 
impair the generation of action potentials, an effect experienced 
by the patients as weakness as in the classical model of periodic 
paralysis (Jurkat-Rott et al., 2009). Additionally the whole-cell 
measurements revealed that R1242G recovered faster than 
wild-type channels from the inactivated state, revealing gain of 
function and furthering the tendency towards muscle fibre 
depolarization. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank the very cooperative family and appreciate the support 
of Drs. Armin Nagel, Teun de Boer and S. Rosenberg. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>Chunxiang Fan is supported by the International Graduate 
School of Ulm University, sponsored by the Excellence Program 
of the German Research Foundation (D.F.G.), and supervised by 
Frank Lehmann-Horn (F.L.H.) and Karin Jurkat-Rott (K.J.R.). 
F.L.H. and K.J.R. receive grants from the non-profit Else Krö ner-
Fresenius-Stiftung, the German Federal Ministry of Research 
(BMBF) for the IonNeurOnet RD project, and the German 
Society for Muscle Disorders (DGM). F.L.H. is endowed Senior 
Research Professor of Neurosciences of the non-profit Hertie-
Foundation. </p>

<p>Supplementary material </p>

<p>Supplementary material is available at Brain online. </p>



<p>Novel phenotype by Ca v 1.1 mutation </p>

<p>Brain 2013: 136; 3775-3786 | 3785 </p>





<p>C. Fan et al. </p>

</text></tei>