<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3202792" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Metabolic network reconstruction encompasses existing knowledge about an organism's 
metabolism and genome annotation, providing a platform for omics data analysis and phenotype 
prediction. The model alga Chlamydomonas reinhardtii is employed to study diverse biological 
processes from photosynthesis to phototaxis. Recent heightened interest in this species results from 
an international movement to develop algal biofuels. Integrating biological and optical data, we 
reconstructed a genome-scale metabolic network for this alga and devised a novel light-modeling 
approach that enables quantitative growth prediction for a given light source, resolving wavelength 
and photon flux. We experimentally verified transcripts accounted for in the network and 
physiologically validated model function through simulation and generation of new experimental 
growth data, providing high confidence in network contents and predictive applications. The 
network offers insight into algal metabolism and potential for genetic engineering and efficient 
light source design, a pioneering resource for studying light-driven metabolism and quantitative 
systems biology. 
Algae have garnered significant interest in recent years for their 
potential commercial applications in biofuels (Hu et al, 2008;  Hemschemeier et al, 2009) and nutritional supplements 
(Spolaore et al, 2006). Among eukaryotic microalgae, Chlamy-
domonas reinhardtii has arisen as the hallmark, model organism 
(Harris, 2001). C. reinhardtii has been widely used to study 
photosynthesis, cell motility and phototaxis, cell wall biogen-
esis, and other fundamental cellular processes (Harris, 2001). 
Commercial use and basic scientific research of photosyn-
thetic organisms could benefit from better understanding of 
how light is absorbed and affects cellular systems. The quality 
of light sources implemented in photobioreactors largely 
determines the efficiency of energy usage in industrial algal 
farming (Fernandes et al, 2010). Light spectral quality also 
affects how photon absorption induces various metabolic 
processes: photosynthesis, pigment and vitamin synthesis, 
and the retinol pathway required for phototaxis. 
Metabolic network reconstruction provides a framework to 
integrate diverse experimental data for investigation of global </p>

<p>properties of metabolism, and as such, can provide clear 
advantages as a mode of studying the effects of light upon a 
photosynthetic biological system if light input is accounted for 
explicitly. The standardized reconstruction process (Thiele  and Palsson, 2010) yields a biochemically and genomically 
structured knowledgebase and, coupled with the standard 
simulation approach of flux balance analysis (FBA) (Orth et al,  2010), provides a basis for predictive phenotype modeling; 
both contexts have been used for a variety of applications 
(Durot et al, 2009; Oberhardt et al, 2009; Gianchandani et al,  2010), among them the design of genetic engineering strategies 
for production strains (Bro et al, 2006; Park et al, 2011). To date, 
however, photon flux, with associated spectral constraints, has 
not been integrated into a metabolic network reconstruction. 
Characterizing algal metabolism is key to engineering 
production strains and framing the study of photosynthesis. 
Extensive literature on C. reinhardtii metabolism, reviewed in 
Stern et al (2008), and multiple metabolic mutants (Harris  et al, 2008) provide a solid foundation for detailed character-
ization of its metabolic functions. The availability of complete 
genome sequence data for C. reinhardtii (Merchant et al, 2007) </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 7; Article number 518; doi:10.1038/msb.2011.52 
Citation: Molecular Systems Biology 7:518 </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 1744-4292/11 </p>

<p>www.molecularsystemsbiology.com </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2011 1 </p>

<p>and its functional annotation have enabled bioinformatic 
approaches to inform the presence of genome-encoded 
enzymes (Grossman et al, 2007; Boyle and Morgan, 2009;  Manichaikul et al, 2009). We have employed these resources to 
reconstruct and experimentally validate a genome-scale 
metabolic network of C. reinhardtii, the first network to 
account for detailed photon absorption permitting growth 
simulations under different light sources. This network 
accounts for the activity of substantially more genes with 
metabolic functions than existing reconstructions (Boyle and  Morgan, 2009; Manichaikul et al, 2009). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Reconstruction contents and advances </p>

<p>The genome-scale C. reinhardtii metabolic network (Figure 1A; 
Supplementary Figure S1; Supplementary Table S1; Supple-
mentary Table S2; Supplementary Model S1) accounts for 1080 
genes, associated with 2190 reactions and 1068 unique 
metabolites, and encompasses 83 subsystems distributed across 
10 compartments. As per convention (Reed et al, 2003), we call 
this network iRC1080 based on the primary reconstructionist 
and the scope of genomic content. Of the putative protein-
coding genes in the C. reinhardtii genome (http://augustus.go-
bics.de/predictions/chlamydomonas/augustus.u5.aa), an esti-
mated 20% function in metabolism (Supplementary Table S3). 
iRC1080 accounts for the activity of 432% of the estimated </p>

<p>genes with metabolic functions, a significant expansion over 
existing reconstructions (Boyle and Morgan, 2009; Manichaikul  et al, 2009). iRC1080 is the most comprehensive metabolic 
network reconstruction of C. reinhardtii to date based on 
inclusion of pathways and a level of detail absent from previous 
reconstructions. 
A major emergent feature of C. reinhardtii metabolism, 
apparent in Figure 1A, is the relative centrality of the 
chloroplast and its importance in light-driven metabolism. 
The chloroplast, including the thylakoid and eyespot sub-
compartments, accounts for 430% of the total reactions in the 
network and 9 of the 10 photon-utilizing reactions. The 
thylakoid contains essential pathways for photoautotrophic 
growth including photosynthesis, chlorophyll synthesis, and 
carotenoid synthesis, producing photoprotective pigments 
also valuable as fish feed additives and nutritional supple-
ments for human consumption. The eyespot accounts for 
retinol metabolism, the mechanistic basis for phototaxis. 
Several pathways are partially duplicated across the chlor-
oplast and other cellular compartments, in agreement with 
known biochemistry. A few crucial pathways are divided 
between the chloroplast and cytosol, including glycolysis and 
glycerolipid metabolism. Among the glycerolipids, triacylgly-
cerides carrying high energy, long-chain fatty acids relevant for 
biofuel production accumulate substantially in microalgae. 
iRC1080 provides a thorough resource for studying these and 
other metabolic products and a basis for strain design for 
genetic engineering. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Contents of the iRC1080 metabolic network reconstruction. (A) Compartmentalized network diagram. The full genome-scale metabolic network is depicted, 
denoting compartments. A high-resolution diagram without compartment labels is also available (Supplementary Figure S1). (B) Global transcript verification status. The 
graph shows the distribution of transcripts accounted for in the network categorized by their verification status. Color codes correspond to the noted percentage of 
transcript sequence verified experimentally. For example, 42% of transcripts in the network were verified experimentally by 100% sequence coverage. (C) Latent 
VLCPUFA pathway diagram. Blue nodes represent metabolites included in iRC1080, and orange nodes represent metabolites not included in iRC1080, hypothesized to 
be absent in C. reinhardtii. Green edges represent enzyme activities accounted for in our functional annotation, and the red edge represents the VLCFA elongase 
missing from our annotation and hypothesized to have been lost in C. reinhardtii's evolution. This pathway diagram also demonstrates the detail of the high-resolution 
network diagram (Supplementary Figure S1). </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>iRC1080 considerably expands lipid metabolic pathways 
over previous reconstructions. We compared the lipid path-
ways of iRC1080 with several previously published metabolic 
reconstructions (Duarte et al, 2007; Feist et al, 2007; Boyle and  Morgan, 2009; Mo et al, 2009; Montagud et al, 2010) counting 
the number of genes, reactions, and chemically distinct lipid 
molecules included in pathways for each lipid class (Table I). 
The extent of gene, reaction, and metabolite content of lipid 
pathways in iR1080 is, in general, greater than previous 
reconstructions. The coverage of ketoacyl lipid chemical 
properties represented in each network was also analyzed 
for all metabolites in fatty acyl, glycerolipid, glyceropho-
spholipid, and sphingolipid classes; the fraction of lipid 
metabolites in the networks that account for a given applicable 
property was determined (Table I). Lower coverage signifies 
incompletely specified molecular species and often lumped </p>

<p>lipid reactions and metabolites. iRC1080 accounts explicitly for 
all metabolites in these pathways, providing sufficient detail to 
completely specify all individual molecular species: backbone 
molecule and its stereochemical numbering of acyl-chain 
positions; acyl-chain length; and number, position, and 
cis-trans stereoisomerism of carbon-carbon double bonds. 
This level of detail enables a significantly higher degree of 
precision in lipid studies and in metabolic engineering design 
involving these pathways. </p>

<p>Experimental transcript verification </p>

<p>We have analyzed iRC1080 via experimental transcript 
verification under permissive growth conditions (Supplemen-
tary Table S4), representing the largest genome-scale trans-
cript validation effort to date. More than 75% of included </p>

<p>Table I Lipid pathway reconstruction properties in iRC1080 in comparison to other metabolic network reconstructions </p>

<p>Reconstructions </p>

<p>iRC1080 C. 
reinhardtii </p>

<p>[iNB305] 
C. reinhardtii </p>

<p>iSyn669 
Synechocystis </p>

<p>iMM904 
S. cerevisiae </p>

<p>iAF1260 
E. coli </p>

<p>Recon 1 
Homo sapiens </p>

<p>Ketoacyl lipid chemical properties </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Backbone molecule 
1.00 
0.94 
1.00 
1.00 
1.00 
1.00 
Stereochemical numbering 
1.00 
0.00 
0.60 
0.85 
1.00 
0.00 
Acyl-chain length 
1.00 
0.72 
0.90 
0.91 
1.00 
0.70 
C¼C number 
1.00 
0.72 
0.75 
0.91 
1.00 
0.70 
C¼C positions 
1.00 
0.00 
0.80 
0.42 
0.91 
0.60 
E-Z stereoisomerism 
1.00 
0.00 
0.80 
0.50 
0.42 
0.53 </p>

<p>Fatty acyls 
G </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>64 
7 
13 
32 
26 
91 
R </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>167 
41 
71 
108 
139 
233 
M </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>104 
21 
55 
55 
95 
137 </p>

<p>Glycerolipids 
G </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>40 
0 
0 
18 
0 
27 
R </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>292 
4 
0 
12 
0 
13 
M </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>135 
4 
2 
4 
7 
4 </p>

<p>Glycerophospholipids 
G </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>47 
0 
8 
46 
22 
87 
R </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>126 
5 
7 
52 
227 
51 
M </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>56 
4 
3 
4 
102 
22 </p>

<p>Sphingolipids 
G </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>8 
0 
0 
2 1 
0 
5 4 
R </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>10 
0 
0 
63 
0 
79 
M </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>6 
0 
0 
3 1 
0 
5 9 </p>

<p>Sterol lipids 
G </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>22 
0 
1 
32 
0 
87 
R </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>34 
0 
3 
49 
0 
156 
M </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>26 
0 
4 
22 
0 
105 </p>

<p>Prenol lipids 
G </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>37 
4 
15 
9 
16 
21 
R </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>59 
5 
53 
17 
20 
50 
M </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>43 
4 
42 
15 
17 
41 </p>

<p>Total lipids 
G </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>218 
11 
37 
158 
64 
367 
R </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>688 
55 
134 
301 
386 
582 
M </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>370 
33 
106 
131 
221 
368 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values are the fraction of lipid metabolites in each network that account for each property, when applicable. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Gene transcripts (can be duplicated across lipid classes). </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Lipid pathway reactions (non-transport). </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Lipid metabolites (unique lipids). </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2011 3 </p>

<p>transcripts were verified at 490% sequence coverage, and 
92% of tested transcripts were at least partially validated 
experimentally (i.e. a portion of the sequence was recovered in 
the sequenced transcripts) (Figure 1B). We also analyzed the 
strength of transcript verification by specific metabolic 
subsystems (Figure 2, a representative subset; Supplementary 
Figure S2, the full set). The full lengths of all transcripts 
associated with 10 subsystems were verified, notably includ-
ing biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids, histidine metabo-
lism, and phenylalanine, tyrosine and tryptophan 
biosynthesis, with 12, 12, and 24 transcripts, respectively. 
Many more subsystems were also well verified, 61 out of 76 
gene-associated subsystems with 490% of associated tran-
scripts at least partially validated. It should be noted that only 
sequencing reads that uniquely map to reference transcript 
sequences were counted toward the percentage of length 
validation; thus, sequencing reads unique enough to un-
ambiguously specify the corresponding reference transcript 
were detected for every transcript with 40% validation. A few 
subsystems stood out as being more poorly verified, including </p>

<p>chloroplast and mitochondrial transport systems and 
sphingolipid metabolism, all of which exhibited o80% of 
transcripts validated to any extent. This may reflect low 
expression level or imperfect structural annotation of these 
genes, particularly compartmental transporters. Low expres-
sion levels or complete deactivation of these genes is 
consistent with a hypothesized evolutionary trend (see below) 
in the case of sphingolipid metabolism. </p>

<p>Evolution of latent lipid pathways </p>

<p>The comprehensive reconstruction of lipid metabolism in 
iRC1080 revealed hypothetical latent pathways, the functions 
of which have likely been lost through evolution. Previous 
studies established that C. reinhardtii lacks the practically 
ubiquitous membrane lipids phosphatidylcholine (Giroud  et al, 1988) and phosphatidylserine (Riekhof et al, 2005). 
Similarly, our reconstruction suggests that C. reinhardtii also 
lacks very long-chain fatty acids (VLCFAs), their polyunsatu-
rated analogs (VLCPUFAs) (Figure 1C), and ceramides. 
Surveys of C. reinhardtii lipid species have not detected 
VLCFAs (Giroud et al, 1988; Giroud and Eichenberger, 1989;  Tatsuzawa et al, 1996; Dubertret et al, 2002; Kajikawa et al,  2006; Lang, 2007), likely due to a lack of functional VLCFA 
elongase (Weers and Gulati, 1997; Guschina and Harwood,  2006; Kajikawa et al, 2006). No candidate VLCFA elongase was 
identified in our comprehensive functional annotation (Sup-
plementary Table S3), and our annotation suggests several 
downstream gaps in arachidonic acid metabolism as well, 
corroborating this hypothesis. Arachidonic acid, the 20-carbon 
parent fatty acid of all VLCFAs and VLCPUFAs, is synthesized 
by a VLCFA elongase-catalyzed extension of g-linolenic acid, 
which is present in C. reinhardtii (Griffiths et al, 2000). 
Notably, C. reinhardtii does encode a fatty acid desaturase that 
accepts arachidonic acid as substrate (Kajikawa et al, 2006)  and, based on our functional annotation, encodes several 
other enzymes that act upon this substrate, indicating that 
algal ancestors likely had a functional VLCFA elongase. 
Multiple lines of evidence uncovered during the reconstruc-
tion also support the absence of ceramides in C. reinhardtii. 
Our functional annotation did not uncover a convincing 
candidate for ceramide synthetase (EC:2.3.1.24), a required 
enzyme for ceramide synthesis, nor, to our knowledge, has one 
been discovered by previous efforts, including C. reinhardtii 
enzyme annotations of the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and 
Genomes. Similarly, our functional annotation suggests 
substantial gaps downstream in the sphingolipid metabolic 
pathway. As aforementioned, C. reinhardtii also lacks VLCFAs, 
and VLCFA-CoA is a required substrate for the ceramide 
synthetase reaction (Hills and Roscoe, 2006). Finally, our 
experimental transcript analysis failed to verify 2 out of 8 
transcripts associated with sphingolipid metabolism (Figure 2) 
that were included in iRC1080, 1 of 2 serine C-palmitoyl-
transferases and a putative sphingosine 1-phosphate aldolase. 
This result may reflect still further gene function loss in this 
pathway, perhaps occurring more recently in evolutionary 
time given that our functional annotation actually detected 
candidate sequences for these enzymes. Considering this 
evidence, we suggest that the evolutionary history of 
C. reinhardtii includes the loss of ceramide metabolism, </p>

<p>Figure 2 Experimental transcript verification by subsystem. The graph 
summarizes transcript verification status (see Materials and methods and 
Supplementary information for details) for 30 of the 76 gene-associated 
subsystems of iRC1080. Identical analysis for the full complement of 
76 subsystems is also available (Supplementary Figure S2). The x axis 
corresponds to the percentage of subsystem-associated transcripts that were 
experimentally verified to the extent noted by the color code. </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>although this hypothesis remains to be verified. Annotated 
enzymes in this pathway separated from the broader network 
by gaps may represent multifunctional proteins or proteins 
that have evolved to function in a pathway distinct from 
ceramide synthesis. These gaps in C. reinhardtii metabolism 
not only increase understanding of the evolution of algal lipid 
pathways but also represent potential targets for genetic 
engineering in an effort to expand the diversity of lipids this 
alga can synthesize. Such engineering efforts serve as valuable 
test cases for engineering industrial strains and could improve 
C. reinhardtii as a model alga for biofuel development. </p>

<p>Modeling metabolic light usage </p>

<p>Our reconstruction accounted for effective light spectral ranges 
by analyzing biochemical activity spectra (Figure 3A), either 
reaction activity or absorbance at varying light wavelengths. 
Defining effective spectral bandwidths associated with each 
photon-utilizing reaction enabled our network to model 
growth under different light sources via stoichiometric 
representation of the spectral composition of emitted light, 
which we term prism reactions. The coefficients for different </p>

<p>photon wavelengths in prism reactions correspond to the 
ratios of photon flux in the defined effective spectral ranges to 
the total photon flux in the visible spectrum emitted by a given 
light source (Figure 3A and B). In this manner, it is possible to 
distinguish the amount of emitted photons that drive different 
metabolic reactions. We created prism reactions for 11 distinct 
light sources (Supplementary Figure S3), covering most 
sources that have been used in published studies for algal 
and plant growth including solar light, various light bulbs, 
and LEDs. 
The network reconstruction provides a detailed account of 
metabolic photon absorption by light-driven reactions. 
Photosystems I and II in iRC1080 stoichiometrically absorb 
photons according to the Z-scheme (Berg et al, 2007). The 
light-dependent protochlorophyllide oxidoreductases require 
a single photon per catalysis as demonstrated in wheat 
(Griffiths et al, 1996). Extrapolation of UVB energy require-
ments for spontaneous provitamin D 3 conversion to vitamin 
D 3 (Bjorn, 2007) based on the average photon energy in the 
UVB range suggests a stoichiometric ratio of approximately 
one. Two phototactic rhodopsins, reactants of the rhodopsin 
photoisomerase reaction, are encoded by C. reinhardtii, one </p>

<p>Figure 3 Analysis of light spectra. (A) Activity and irradiance spectra. The top graph displays activity spectra for photon-utilizing reactions included in iRC1080. The 
abbreviated reactions are defined as follows: VITD3, vitamin D 3 synthesis; OPSIN, rhodopsin photoisomerase; PCHLD, both protochlorophyllide photoreductase and 
divinylprotochlorophyllide photoreductase; PSI, photosystem I; PSII, photosystem II. The y axis for the activity spectra is the fraction of maximum-measured activity with 
respect to each noted reaction. Four of the eleven sample irradiance spectra (Supplementary Figure S3) are depicted with y axes set as the percentage of total visible 
photon flux at each wavelength (x axis). Effective spectral bandwidths are denoted by vertical dashed lines color coded to match the activity spectra for each reaction. 
(B) Prism reaction derivation. The photon flux from wavelengths a to b is normalized by the total visible photon flux from 380 to 750 nm to yield the effective spectral 
bandwidth coefficient C. The coefficients for each range are compiled into a single prism reaction for a given light source, representing the composition of emitted light as 
defined by photon-utilizing metabolic reactions. Equation variables are defined at top. </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2011 5 </p>

<p>requiring a single photon and one requiring two photons for 
activation; the average effective stoichiometric photon count 
was measured to be 1.6 (Hegemann and Marwan, 1988). 
A prism reaction is the intermediate step between light input 
and the specific photon-utilizing metabolic reactions men-
tioned above. Flux through the photon exchange reaction 
'EX_photonVis(e)' represents the total metabolically active 
photon flux incident upon the cell. Flux passing through this 
exchange reaction then passes through a single user-specified 
prism reaction, for example 'PRISM_solar_litho,' and is 
distributed across specific spectral ranges. These ranges are 
specified explicitly in the photon-dependent metabolic reac-
tion formulas (Supplementary Table S2), thereby making these 
reactions wavelength specific. Flux through the photon-
dependent metabolic reactions is then propagated through 
the network. Excess wavelength-specific photon fluxes that 
are not absorbed metabolically leave the system via demand 
reactions, for example 'DM_photon298(c),' completing the 
pathway of light through the network. 
To accurately model metabolic activity of a photosynthetic 
organism, it is also important to consider regulatory effects 
resulting from lighting conditions. Indeed, light and dark 
conditions have been shown to affect metabolic enzyme 
activity in C. reinhardtii at multiple levels: transcriptional 
regulation (Bohne and Linden, 2002), chloroplast RNA 
degradation (Salvador et al, 1993), translational regulation 
(Cahoon and Timko, 2000), and thioredoxin-mediated 
enzyme regulation (Lemaire et al, 2004). As a preliminary 
attempt to incorporate light and dark regulatory effects, 
literature was reviewed to identify such regulation upon 
enzymes in iRC1080 (Supplementary Table S5), focusing 
mainly on thioredoxin regulation of chloroplast enzymes since 
most published data relate to this mode. In the absence of 
activity spectra for these effects, it is not yet possible to 
represent these effects via prism reactions. Therefore, we 
modeled regulation with Boolean reaction flux constraints 
following published approaches (Covert et al, 2001). </p>

<p>Environmental and genetic validation of iRC1080 </p>

<p>Implementing light-regulated constraints and basic environ-
mental exchange constraints (Supplementary Table S6) 
yielded photoautotrophic, heterotrophic, and mixotrophic 
models from iRC1080. We simulated various growth condi-
tions (Supplementary Table S7) and all gene knockouts for 
which phenotypes have been published and are assessable 
in our network (Supplementary Table S8) to validate the 
predictive ability of the models. All 30 validations involving 
environmental parameters displayed very close agreement 
with experimental results (Supplementary Table S7). 
Of particular note is the ability of our photosynthetic model 
in sunlight to accurately recapitulate O 2 -PAR (photosyntheti-
cally active radiation) energy conversion efficiency, predicting 
an efficiency of 2% compared with the experimental result 
(Greenbaum, 1988) of 1.3-4.5%. Of the 14 gene knockouts 
simulated, 7 were partially or completely validated relative to 
experimental results (Supplementary Table S8). The uncon-
firmed gene knockout phenotypes may result from network 
errors or an incomplete set of constraints in the model 
(e.g. enzyme capacity, regulatory, thermodynamic, or other </p>

<p>constraints). No internal model reactions were constrained in 
the models except indirectly via constraints on the input 
exchanges and the few explicitly noted Boolean regulatory 
constraints imposed (Supplementary Table S5). The uncon-
firmed knockout phenotypes were investigated through model 
analysis and literature search, although in most cases, current 
literature evidence could not completely explain these 
discrepancies, leaving them to be fully accounted for by future 
studies. 
Two discrepancies may result from incomplete genome 
functional annotation or missing constraints. Knockout of 
mitochondrial NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase complex I 
(EC:1.6.5.3) in the model fails to recapitulate a reduced 
heterotrophic growth phenotype (Remacle et al, 2001a). The 
NDA2 and NDA3 genes can substitute completely for this 
activity in the current model. Sequence-based localization 
analysis places both proteins in the mitochondria, but this may 
be incorrect as a recent study suggests that both may be plastid 
localized (Desplats et al, 2009). Two other network reactions 
can also substitute for the reduction of ubiquinone, succinate 
dehydrogenase (ubiquinone) (EC:1.3.5.1) and electron trans-
fer flavoprotein-ubiquinone oxidoreductase (EC:1.5.5.1). 
The cytochrome c oxidase complex IV (EC:1.9.3.1) knockout 
does not result in an obligate photoautotrophic phenotype 
(Remacle et al, 2001b) in the model because the cytochrome c 
peroxidase (EC:1.11.1.5) reaction is capable of compensating. 
The C. reinhardtii CCPR1 protein is homologous to mitochon-
drial cytochrome c peroxidases from a number of species, 
but no focused studies have been carried out to provide further 
evidence for this enzyme. In the model, the complex IV and 
CCPR1 double knockout is an obligate photoautotroph. These 
discrepancies point out important genes that should be the 
focus of subsequent experimentation in order to more clearly 
understand these metabolic phenotypes. 
Another discrepancy may result from missing thermody-
namic constraints. The zeaxanthin epoxidase (EC:1.14.13.90) 
knockout does not preclude antheraxanthin, violaxanthin, 
or neoxanthin production (Baroli et al, 2003) in the model 
because violaxanthin de-epoxidase (EC:1.10.99.3) reactions 
compensate. This substitution depends on the reversibility of 
these de-epoxidase reactions and may point to missing 
thermodynamic constraints or to undiscovered regulation 
under this condition. 
Two discrepancies result from the lack of accounting for 
kinetics of the reactions of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carbox-
ylase oxygenase (RuBisCO) from the model. Both phospho-
glycolate phosphatase (EC:3.1.3.18) (Suzuki et al, 1990)  and glycolate dehydrogenase (EC:1.1.99.14) (Nakamura  et al, 2005) deficient mutants require high CO 2 for photo-
autotrophic growth in vivo, not recapitulated in simulations. 
This phenotype results from dominance of the oxygenase over 
carboxylase activity of RuBisCO under lower CO 2 conditions, 
both reactions sharing the same catalytic site. In vivo, these 
two mutants are deficient in the salvage of carbon from 
2-phosphoglycolate, a product of the oxygenase activity of 
RuBisCO. Although these two reactions are carried out by the 
same enzyme in the model, their fluxes are treated as 
independent and not competitive; due to an absence of kinetic 
parameters in the model, the effect of relative CO 2 and O 2 
concentrations upon RuBisCO activity cannot be explicitly </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>expressed. Because the carboxylase activity more efficiently 
promotes growth, both high and low CO 2 conditions drive only 
this reaction and not the oxygenase reaction in the model; 
therefore, the salvage pathway is unnecessary in the model to 
achieve wild-type growth rates. 
Finally, two mutant phenotype discrepancies in the model 
result from complex compensatory pathways that convert an 
input carbon source to the mutant-required carbon source. 
The high CO 2 requirement for photoautotrophic growth due to 
knockout of the chloroplast carbonic anhydrase (EC:4.2.1.1) 
(Spalding et al, 1983; Funke et al, 1997) can be compensated 
for in the model by activity of a six-reaction pathway of 
pyrimidine metabolism leading from bicarbonate incorpora-
tion via carbamoyl-phosphate synthase (EC:6.3.5.5) to con-
version to CO 2 via orotidine-5 
0 -phosphate decarboxylase 
(EC:4.1.1.23). The chloroplast ATP synthase (EC:3.6.3.14) 
deficient mutant (Smart and Selman, 1991; Dent et al, 2005;  Drapier et al, 2007) with an acetate-requiring phenotype can 
be compensated for in the model by a complex pathway 
consisting of 415 reactions by which CO 2 is converted to 
acetate, which is then used in pathways similar to those 
supporting heterotrophic growth. Although this complex 
pathway has many branch points, it is notable that chloroplast 
malate dehydrogenase (EC:1.1.1.40) and the diffusion of 
pyruvate between the cytosol and chloroplast are essential to 
coupling the CO 2 fixation reactions to pyruvate metabolism 
and ultimate conversion to acetate but are not essential to 
the wild-type photoautotrophic or heterotrophic models. Loss 
of either of these conditionally essential reactions prevents the 
CO 2 -to-acetate conversion and recapitulates the acetate-
requiring phenotype. Given the complexity of these compen-
satory pathways, a number of possible missing constraints 
could explain their inactivity in vivo under photosynthetic 
conditions, and the model offers a starting point to explore 
possible targets of regulation under these conditions. </p>

<p>Gene essentiality analysis </p>

<p>To demonstrate the prospective use of iRC1080 in predi-
cting phenotypic outcomes of genetic manipulations of 
C. reinhardtii, comprehensive essentiality analysis of all 
simulated single-gene knockouts was performed in models 
under four basic environmental conditions: growth in sunlight 
with and without acetate, aerobic growth in dark on acetate, 
and anaerobic subsistence in dark on starch. Phenotypes were 
defined as growth equivalent to wild-type, reduced growth 
relative to wild-type, or lethal based on the comparative 
objective fluxes of the mutant and wild-type models 
(Supplementary Table S9). A lethal phenotype was defined 
as no flux through the biomass reaction (defined as the 
objective function) in the mutant. Simulation results exhibited 
distinct metabolic system dependencies under each condition. 
There were 201 and 144 lethal knockouts in the model with 
sunlight and with and without acetate, respectively. There 
were 147 and only 3 lethal knockouts in the aerobic and 
anaerobic dark model, respectively. The metabolic processes 
associated with essential genes were ranked, and the three 
subsystems associated with the essential genes were compared 
under each condition. Photosynthesis, porphyrin and 
chlorophyll metabolism, and phenylalanine, tyrosine, and </p>

<p>tryptophan biosynthesis were the most essential subsystems in 
light without acetate. Phenylalanine, tyrosine, and tryptophan 
biosynthesis, porphyrin and chlorophyll metabolism, and 
purine metabolism were the most essential subsystems in 
light with acetate. Expectedly, photosynthesis is most crucial 
for photoautotrophic growth and not required in the presence 
of acetate. The dark, aerobic condition had the same top 
ranked essential subsystems as in the mixotrophic condition, 
which is also expected as amino acids, chlorophyll, and 
nucleotides make up a high proportion of the required biomass 
components under both conditions. For subsistence in dark on 
starch, glycolysis/gluconeogenesis, starch metabolism, and 
starch and sucrose metabolism were the most essential 
subsystems, paralleling the expected core pathways for ATP 
maintenance with starch breakdown. While these predicted 
genotype-phenotype relationships demonstrate a compelling 
prospective use of the network, the majority of the mutant 
phenotypes remain to be validated experimentally; however, 
these predictions could be used to help define the scope 
and expected outcomes of such future studies. </p>

<p>Light-source-specific model validations </p>

<p>Next, we performed more extensive validations of light models 
grown under specific light sources at varying intensities. 
Varying sunlight intensity in our model and evaluating 
photosynthetic O 2 evolution, we observed that the model 
reached photosynthetic saturation at light intensity consistent 
with experimental measurement (Polle et al, 2003)  (Figure 4A). Our model under red LED light (653 nm) also 
showed fair agreement with our experimentally measured 
maximum growth rate across the range of unsaturated photon 
flux (Figure 4B), despite divergence above the experimental 
saturation point. The principal explanation for this divergence 
lies in the relative CO 2 supplies of the experimental setup and 
the model. All reported photoautotrophic model simulations 
utilize the same maximum CO 2 exchange constraint corre-
sponding to the maximum-measured cellular uptake rate 
under non-CO 2 -limiting conditions (Supplementary Table S6), 
while the CO 2 supply in our bioreactor setup was clearly 
growth-limiting given that the light-saturated maximum 
growth rate was 0.01 gDW/h, much lower than the maximum 
growth rate of 0.14 gDW/h under non-CO 2 -limiting conditions 
(Janssen et al, 2000). It should also be noted that the linearity 
of the simulation trends is a property of steady-state system 
modeling, which is incapable of kinetic representation of 
growth shifts observable in the in vivo experiments. For further 
validation, we present that the maximum biomass yield under 
incandescent white light is 5.7 Â10 
À5 gDW/mE (Janssen et al,  2000), in close agreement with our analogous prediction of 
2.6 Â10 
À5 gDW/mE (Figure 4C). Similarly, our predicted 
biomass yield on 674 nm peak LED light of 1.1 Â10 
À4 gDW/ 
mE is on the same order of magnitude as our experimental 
results for C. reinhardtii under 660 nm peak LED light near 
growth-saturating photon flux, 4.3 Â10 
À4 gDW/mE. This 
agreement is striking given that the network explicitly 
accounts for the spectral photon flux of these light sources 
and the subsequent processing of this energy to generate all of 
the constituents of biomass without any parameter fitting to 
the experimental data. Together, these results constitute an </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2011 7 </p>

<p>important validation of our models using three different light 
sources. 
To quantitatively evaluate the significance of the agreement 
between our reported model simulations using prism reactions 
derived through analysis of irradiance spectra and experi-
mental measurements under the three light sources reported 
above, we compared the reported simulation results for each 
of these light sources with an unbiased sample of results 
representative of potential solutions achievable using our 
network. We sampled the space of possible light models by 
generating random prism reactions with the same total 
metabolically active photon flux. To obtain stoichiometric 
coefficients for a random prism reaction, a set of random 
fractions of the sum of stoichiometric coefficients of the 
prism reaction representing the evaluated light source was 
generated, contingent upon resulting in the same sum of 
coefficients. The simulations as reported above for sunlight, 
red LED, and white incandescent light were repeated using 
such random prism reactions. The Euclidean distance between </p>

<p>the simulated and experimental results was compared with the 
distribution of distances for 10 000 randomly sampled results 
(Figure 5). The probability of randomly achieving experi-
mental agreement closer than seen in our simulations was 
determined empirically based on these distributions 
of distances. Only 77 of 10 000 randomized simulations 
(Figure 5A) had experimental agreement better than the 
simulated oxygen photoevolution under sunlight (Figure 4A), 
yielding an empirical P-value of 0.0077, and indicating our 
model had experimental agreement statistically significantly 
better than a random model constrained to have the same total 
metabolically active photon flux. Simulated growth under 
665 nm peak LED (Figure 4B) had a suggestive P-value of 
0.1947 (Figure 5B), although the reported simulation was still 
closer to experiment than the mean of randomized simula-
tions. Our simulated growth under white incandescent light 
was statistically significantly closer to experiment (Janssen  et al, 2000) than random (Figure 5C) with a P-value of 0.0285. 
This analysis shows that the reported model for each of these </p>

<p>Figure 4 Photosynthetic model simulation results. (A) O 2 photoevolution under solar light. Simulated (blue line) and experimentally measured (green dots) O 2 
evolution are compared. (B) Photosynthetic growth under red LED light. Simulations were performed using the 653-nm prism reaction, and experimentally grown culture 
was exposed to 660 nm LED light. Simulated (blue line) and experimentally measured (green dots) growth are compared. (C) Efficiency of light utilization. The minimum 
photon flux required for maximum-simulated growth (bottom), biomass yield (middle), and energy conversion efficiency (top) are presented for 11 light sources derived 
from measured spectra and for the designed growth-efficient LED. </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>light sources is exceptionally close to recapitulating experi-
mental results and thus serves as an excellent validation. 
These results indicate that the network has the capacity to 
broadly differentiate light-dependent growth based on spectral 
properties and that the formulation of a prism reaction serves 
to accurately narrow the space of possible flux distributions 
relevant to a specific light source. </p>

<p>Application of iRC1080 to evaluate light source 
efficiency and design </p>

<p>Our photosynthetic model was applied prospectively to 
evaluate the efficiency of light utilization under different light 
sources. The photon energy conversion efficiency (Supple-
mentary Equation 1) and biomass yield on light (Supplemen-
tary Equation 2) were computed for each light source given the 
minimum incident photon flux required to achieve maximum 
growth rate (Figure 4C); the minimum photon flux for 
maximum growth rate is the growth-saturating photon flux 
value for a given light source. One clear result is that red LEDs 
provide the greatest efficiency in terms of both absorbed </p>

<p>photon energy and biomass yield, about two and three times as 
efficient as can be optimally achieved in sunlight by these 
respective measures. Although experimental growth data for 
validation is only presented for three light sources, simulation 
results are presented for all 11 light sources for which 
irradiance spectra were obtainable (Figure 4C). This analysis 
demonstrates the prospective extensibility of the network and 
modeling approach to any possible lighting condition, natural 
or manmade, for which an irradiance spectrum can be 
measured. 
Given the capability of our photosynthetic model to evaluate 
light source efficiency, we applied it to design an LED spectrum 
providing maximum photon utilization efficiency for growth 
(Supplementary Figure S3). The result was a 677-nm peak LED 
spectrum with a total incident photon flux of 360 mE/m 
2 /s 
(Figure 4C; Supplementary Figure S3), which is quite close to 
the 674-nm LED with a minimum incident photon flux of 
362 mE/m 
2 /s for maximum growth. This result suggests that 
for the simple objective of maximizing growth efficiency, 
LED technology has already reached an effective theoretical 
optimum, which is further supported by experimental 
measurements of the spectral peak of light absorption for 
green algae (Akkerman et al, 2002) and the quantum action 
spectrum of land plants (Barta et al, 1992) (Supplementary 
Table S7). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We have presented a genome-scale network reconstruction of 
C. reinhardtii metabolism, well validated in content and 
function, and its application for detailed modeling of diverse 
light sources. Initial model validations also highlight the need 
for more experimental studies to uncover regulatory mechan-
isms in order to expand understanding of the complexity of 
light regulation of algal metabolism. This open research topic 
presents important challenges and opportunities in enumerat-
ing such effects on a genome scale. 
Given the importance of lipid metabolism in biofuel 
production, iRC1080 was reconstructed enumerating all lipids 
supported by evidence in the literature and genome functional 
annotation. The capacity of iRC1080 as a knowledgebase was 
demonstrated through analysis of lipid metabolism to generate 
novel hypotheses about latent metabolic pathways resulting 
from algal evolution. In particular, the exclusion of certain 
enzymatic reactions in VLCFA and sphingolipid pathways 
from iRC1080 suggests evolutionary recession of these path-
ways in C. reinhardtii, a hypothesis supported by undetected 
lipids in experimental measurements, gaps in genome func-
tional annotation for these enzymes, and incomplete transcript 
verification for other enzymes included in these pathways. Not 
only do these network gaps reflect the relatively simple lipid 
biosynthetic capabilities of C. reinhardtii among microalgae, 
but their identification suggests gene insertions that could 
expand its lipid metabolic repertoire, relevant for industrial 
and scientific purposes. Of particular interest may be the 
potential for enabling algal synthesis of essential fatty acids for 
human health such as docosahexaenoic acid (Yashodhara  et al, 2009). Candidate enzymes for the conversion 
of arachidonic acid to essential fatty acids downstream of the </p>

<p>Figure 5 Distributions of randomly sampled distances from experimental 
measurements. (A) O 2 photoevolution under solar light. (B) Photosynthetic 
growth under red LED light. (C) Photosynthetic growth under white incandescent 
light. All three distance distributions result from 10 000 unbiased sampling results 
in which random prism reactions were generated with the same total 
metabolically active photon flux as the given light source. Each distribution is 
depicted in 25 equal-sized bins. The red dot in each plot is placed over the 
bin in which the distance of the reported simulation result for the given light 
source falls; the vertical placement of each red dot indicates the number of 
randomly sampled distances within the same bin that are less than that of 
the reported result. </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2011 9 </p>

<p>apparently absent VLCFA elongase reaction are present in our 
functional annotation. 
The models developed from iRC1080 provide a platform for 
prediction of phenotypic outcomes of system perturbations, 
light source evaluation and design, and genetic engineering 
design for production of biofuels and other commodity 
chemicals. We demonstrated an approach applying iRC1080 
to the design of an energetically efficient light source 
for growth, a novel application of metabolic networks. 
Other light sources may be more efficient for other metabolic 
objectives or under other environmental conditions or 
genetic backgrounds. This result could be of significant 
interest to the metabolic engineering and bioreactor-design 
communities because it demonstrates that our network 
and light-modeling approach are capable of accurately 
predicting light source efficiencies in terms of a metabolic 
objective. 
The prism reactions developed and applied in this study to 
quantitatively integrate spectral quality with biological activ-
ity represent a significant integration of diverse data types for 
biological system modeling, which hopefully will encourage a 
new paradigm for systems biology. This modeling approach 
could be used for applications beyond light source design, 
including as a metabolic basis for studying and simulating 
phototaxis. Given the acquisition of appropriate biological 
spectral activity data, this approach could be extended to other 
biological light-response phenomena and other organisms. 
The importance of understanding how light parameters affect 
biological systems may also extend beyond natural phenom-
ena with recent progress in protein engineering leading to 
chimeric light-inducible proteins (Shimizu-Sato et al, 2002;  Levskaya et al, 2005). 
The iRC1080 network and presented metabolic modeling 
represent a milestone in systems biology. Our network 
provides a broad knowledgebase of the biochemistry and 
genomics underlying global metabolism of a photoautotroph, 
and our modeling of light-driven metabolism exemplifies how 
integration of largely unvisited data types, such as physico-
chemical environmental parameters, can expand the diversity 
of applications of metabolic networks. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction </p>

<p>Building from our previously published reconstruction of C. reinhard-
tii central metabolism (Manichaikul et al, 2009), iAM303, the iRC1080 
network was reconstructed in a bottom-up manner according 
to current standards (Thiele and Palsson, 2010) on a pathway-by-
pathway basis, drawing biochemical, genomic, and physiological 
evidence from 4250 publications (Supplementary Table S2). The 
genomic evidence was derived from our own functional annotation 
(Supplementary Table S3) of metabolic enzymes, coenzymes, and 
transport proteins. Network gap-filling was performed to make 
pathways functional and account for dead-end metabolites. Global 
quality control checks were then performed, including elemental 
balancing and elimination of as many internal thermodynamically 
infeasible loops and new photon-driven, input-only pathways as 
possible (Supplementary Figure S4; Supplementary information). We 
also accounted for subcellular compartment pH in the protonation 
states of metabolites as much as possible. 
iRC1080 is publicly available at http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels 
(Accession: MODEL1106200000) and as Supplementary Model S1. </p>

<p>Functional annotation of transcripts </p>

<p>Functional annotation for iRC1080 was performed using a consensus 
of two separate approaches. In the first approach, gene models (http:// 
augustus.gobics.de/predictions/chlamydomonas/augustus.u5.aa) from 
the Augustus update 5 (Au5) of C. reinhardtii genome assembly 
version JGI v4.0 were functionally annotated by assigning enzyme 
classification (EC) terms using BLASTP results against UniProt (http:// 
www.uniprot.org/) and AraCyc (http://www.arabidopsis.org/biocyc/) 
enzyme protein sequences and their EC annotations as the basis. The 
second approach followed from mapping of Au5 gene models 
to annotated JGI v3.1 gene models, for which EC terms and Gene 
Ontology annotation were assigned using a combination of BLASTP, 
AutoFACT, <rs type="software">InterProScan</rs>, and PRIAM. The comprehensive annotation 
is presented in Supplementary Table S3. See Supplementary informa-
tion for full details. </p>

<p>Growth simulations </p>

<p>Simulation procedures consisted of FBA (Orth et al, 2010) and flux 
variability analysis (FVA) (Mahadevan and Schilling, 2003) as 
implemented in the COBRA toolbox (Becker et al, 2007), testing 
model capabilities while optimizing biomass functions to simulate 
growth (Supplementary Table S10) or subsistence on starch by 
optimizing ATP maintenance. FBA is a widely used simulation 
approach for large-scale, constraint-based metabolic models and has 
become a standard method in the systems biology field with a long 
history of success (Gianchandani et al, 2010). Different environmental 
conditions were modeled by appropriately setting reaction flux 
constraints in iRC1080 (Supplementary Table S6) including environ-
mental exchanges, non-growth associated ATP maintenance, O 2 
photoevolution, starch degradation, and light-or dark-regulated 
enzymatic reactions (Supplementary Table S5). </p>

<p>C. reinhardtii strains and growth conditions </p>

<p>For transcript verification experiments, C. reinhardtii strain CC-503 
was grown in tris-acetate-phosphate medium containing 100 mg/l 
carbamicillin without agitation, at room temperature (22-251C) and 
under continuous illumination with cool white light at a photosyn-
thetic photon flux of 60 mE/m 
2 /s. 
For growth experiments under 660 nm peak LED light (Supplementary 
Figure S5), C. reinhardtii strain UTEX2243 was grown in a bubble 
column photobioreactor at 23-271C with P49 medium. The total volume 
of algal culture was 300 ml, and the gas supply was 180 ml/min air with 
2.5% CO 2 . The 660-nm peak LED light supply was set at 10 kHz 
frequency and different duty cycles to get varied average photon fluxes. </p>

<p>Transcript verification by sequencing </p>

<p>ORF amplicons were generated from C. reinhardtii cells by RT-PCR 
from RNA or PCR from Gateway clones. The Roche 454FLX Titanium 
sequencing system was used for sequencing of the generated ORF 
amplicons according to the manufacturer's instructions. The gener-
ated data were processed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">GS FLX</rs> data analysis software v<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.3</rs>. 
Minimum overlap length of 40 nucleotides and minimum overlap 
identity of 90% were used to align the sequencing reads against the 
Au5 reference sequences. ORFs encoding transporter proteins were 
verified by capillary Sanger sequencing. </p>

<p>Prism reaction derivation </p>

<p>Spectral bandwidths that effectively drive each photon-utilizing 
reaction in iRC1080 were determined from published experimental 
activity spectral data or absorbance data. Effective spectral band-
widths were defined as the full width half maximum of activity, 
denoted by color-paired dashed lines in Figure 3A. The effective 
spectral bandwidths were used to derive stoichiometric coefficients of 
the prism reactions used to quantitatively represent different light 
sources from the composition of their published irradiance spectra, 
converted to photon flux units according to Supplementary Equations </p>

<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>3 and 4. Coefficients for each of the effective spectral bandwidths were 
computed based on Equation 1. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a ¼ </p>

<p>R b 
a LðlÞ dl 
R 750 nm 
380 nm LðlÞ dl 
C </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>LðlÞ 
a 
b </p>

<p>¼ 
¼ 
¼ 
¼ </p>

<p>effective bandwidth coefficient 
photon flux as a function of wavelength 
effective bandwidth lower limit 
effective bandwidth upper limit </p>

<p>ð1Þ </p>

<p>Each coefficient represents the ratio of photon flux in the defined 
effective bandwidth to total visible photon flux. Definite integrals in 
Equation 1 were approximated using the trapezoidal rule. For each 
light source, all effective bandwidth coefficients were compiled into a 
single reaction in the form of Equation 2. </p>

<p>photonVis À! </p>

<p>ðC </p>

<p>306nm </p>

<p>281nm Þphoton298 þ ðC </p>

<p>454nm </p>

<p>406nm Þphoton437 
þ ðC </p>

<p>482nm </p>

<p>378nm Þphoton438 þ ðC </p>

<p>472nm </p>

<p>417nm Þphoton450 
þ ðC </p>

<p>526nm </p>

<p>451nm Þphoton490 þ ðC </p>

<p>666nm </p>

<p>608nm Þphoton646 
þ ðC </p>

<p>685nm </p>

<p>661nm Þphoton673 þ ðC </p>

<p>691nm </p>

<p>662nm Þphoton680 </p>

<p>ð2Þ </p>

<p>Constraints on prism reaction fluxes (Supplementary Table S6) were 
derived from the total visible photon flux, the definite integral of the 
spectrum from 380 to 750 nm. The total experimentally measured 
emitted visible photon flux was converted to model units of incident 
photon flux using the values in Supplementary Table S11 and 
Supplementary Equations 5 and 6. Prism reactions for 11 different 
light sources (Supplementary Figure S3) were generated. </p>

<p>Random sampling of prism reaction space and 
significance test </p>

<p>For a given prism reaction, first the sum of the stoichiometric 
coefficients was calculated, representing the total quantity of 
metabolically active photons per incident photon from the specified 
light source. Next, to sample the space of prism reactions, 10 000 
random prism reactions with the same sum of stoichiometric 
coefficients were generated and used in growth simulations. In these 
simulations, input photon flux was constrained to the reported 
experimental values, generating a set of simulated results (biomass 
or photosynthetically evolved O 2 flux, depending on the experimental 
parameter) with one value corresponding to each experimental data 
point. The Euclidean distance between the sampled and experimental 
results was calculated for each of the 10 000 randomized prism 
reactions (Figure 5). The significance of the experimental agreement 
with simulations reported for a given prism reaction derived directly 
from analysis of irradiance spectra was established by comparison 
between the corresponding Euclidean distance and the distribution of 
distances from the randomly sampled prism reactions. Probability of 
achieving equal or closer results to experiments by chance was 
computed as the proportion of smaller values in the randomly sampled 
distribution of 10 000 distances. </p>

<p>Procedure for efficient LED design </p>

<p>Multiple iterations of FVA were used to maximize growth while 
minimizing the energy of the sum of individual wavelengths of model 
photon flux. The ratios of these individual wavelength photon fluxes to 
total photon flux were set as stoichiometric coefficients for a 
theoretical maximum-efficiency prism reaction. The Euclidean vector 
distance was computed (Supplementary Figure S6) between this set of 
coefficients and prism reaction coefficients calculated for an LED 
spectrum of the same shape as the experimentally measured 674 nm 
peak LED but centered at varying wavelengths across the visible 
spectrum, with a total photon flux equal to the total theoretical 
maximum-efficiency photon flux. The spectrum corresponding to the 
minimum distance was taken as the solution and subsequently tested 
through growth simulation. </p>

<p>Supplementary information </p>

<p>Supplementary information is available at the Molecular Systems 
Biology website (www.nature.com/msb). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Harish Nagarajan for his critical assessment of this work. 
This research was supported by the Office of Science (Biological and 
Environmental Research), US Department of Energy, Grant DE-FG02-
07ER64496 (to JP and KS-A), New York University Abu Dhabi Research 
funds (to KS-A), and Institute Sponsored Research funds from the 
Dana-Farber Cancer Institute Strategic Initiative (to CCSB). RLC was 
supported by the National Science Foundation IGERT training Grant 
DGE0504645, and EFYH was supported by the Jane Coffin Childs 
Memorial Fund for Medical Research. 
Author contributions: RLC wrote the manuscript and developed the 
light-modeling approach. RLC and AM reconstructed the metabolic 
network and performed model simulations and analysis. LG, YS and 
TH performed transcript verification experiments and associated 
computational analyses. EFYH and SB performed genome functional 
annotation. WF performed bioreactor growth experiments. B+P, JAP, 
and KS-A designed the study. </p>



<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2011 11 </p>



<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>



<p>Metabolic network reconstruction of Chlamydomonas 
RL Chang et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2011 EMBO and Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2011 13 </p>

</text></tei>