<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3789260" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2) is a gene that, upon mutation, causes autosomal-dominant familial Parkinson's disease 
(PD). Yeast two-hybrid screening revealed that Snapin, a SNAP-25 (synaptosomal-associated protein-25) interacting protein, 
interacts with LRRK2. An in vitro kinase assay exhibited that Snapin is phosphorylated by LRRK2. A glutathione-S-transferase 
(GST) pull-down assay showed that LRRK2 may interact with Snapin via its Ras-of-complex (ROC) and N-terminal domains, 
with no significant difference on interaction of Snapin with LRRK2 wild type (WT) or its pathogenic mutants. Further analysis 
by mutation study revealed that Threonine 117 of Snapin is one of the sites phosphorylated by LRRK2. Furthermore, a Snapin 
T117D phosphomimetic mutant decreased its interaction with SNAP-25 in the GST pull-down assay. SNAP-25 is a component 
of the SNARE (Soluble NSF Attachment protein REceptor) complex and is critical for the exocytosis of synaptic vesicles. 
Incubation of rat brain lysate with recombinant Snapin T117D, but not WT, protein caused decreased interaction of 
synaptotagmin with the SNARE complex based on a co-immunoprecipitation assay. We further found that LRRK2-dependent 
phosphorylation of Snapin in the hippocampal neurons resulted in a decrease in the number of readily releasable vesicles and 
the extent of exocytotic release. Combined, these data suggest that LRRK2 may regulate neurotransmitter release via control of 
Snapin function by inhibitory phosphorylation. 
cellular protein aggregations, 6-8 shortening of neurite length, 
and decrease of neurite branch number during neurite 
outgrowth, 9,10 as well as enhanced, oxidative stress-induced 
neurotoxicity. 11-13 In most studies, these phenotypes were 
intensified in cells expressing mutants, especially G2019S, 
which showed increased kinase activity, compared to cells 
expressing WT. 10,14-16 Therefore, that part of LRRK2 research 
conducted thus far has focused on identifying its kinase 
substrates with the goals of elucidating the PD-pathogenic 
mechanism and developing PD therapeutics. 
Several biochemical and genetic methods such as yeast 
two-hybrid screening and co-immunoprecipitation have been 
carried out to identify LRRK2-interacting proteins. 4,6,15,17-23 
From these studies, moesin, mitogen-activated protein 
kinase kinase, 4E-BP, eukaryotic initiation factor 4E-binding </p>

<p>1 Institute for Brain Science and Technology, Inje University, Gaegumdong, South Korea; 2 Department of Physiology and Biomedical Sciences, Seoul 
National University, College of Medicine, Seoul, South Korea; 3 Biomembrane Plasticity Research Center, Seoul National University, College of Medicine, 
Seoul, South Korea; 4 InAm Neuroscience Research Center, Sanbon Medical Center, College of Medicine, Wonkwang University, Gunpo-Si, Gyeonggido, 
South Korea; 5 Department of Molecular and Life Sciences, Hanyang University, Ansanshi, South Korea and 6 Department of Neurology, Sanbon Medical 
Center, College of Medicine, Wonkwang University, Gunpo-Si, Gyeonggido, South Korea 
Correspondence: Dr I Son or Dr W Seol, InAm Neuroscience Research Center, Sanbon Hospital, Wonkwang University, Sanbondong, Gunposhi, 
Gyeonggido, Republic of Korea. 
E-mail: sonih@wku.ac.kr or wseol@wmcsb.co.kr 
Received 7 December 2012; revised 20 May 2013; accepted 10 June 2013 </p>

<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine (2013) 45, e36; doi:10.1038/emm.2013.68 
&amp; 2013 KSBMB. All rights reserved 2092-6413/13 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/emm </p>

<p>protein, Drosophila microtubule-binding protein Futsch 
and ARHGEF7 were identified as substrates for LRRK2 
kinase, 15,24-27 although it remains unclear how their 
phosphorylation affects PD pathogenesis. 
We previously identified Rab5b, an early endosome marker, 
as an LRRK2-interacting protein by yeast two-hybrid screening 
and showed that their interaction slows endocytosis of synaptic 
vesicles. 18 From the same screening, we also isolated Snapin as 
an LRRK2-interacting protein. Snapin was originally reported as 
a SNAP-25-binding protein that is associated with soluble 
N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor attachment protein receptor 
(SNARE) complex proteins. 28 In Snapin knockout mice, 
association of SNAP-25 with synaptotagmin-1 was impaired 
and calcium-dependent exocytosis was significantly reduced. 29 
Recent studies reported that in Snapin knockout mice, late 
endocytic proteins were increased 30 and that synaptic vesicle 
fusion was desynchronized. 31 In addition, Snapin was also 
reported to be an important link between the aquaporin 
water channel and the target SNARE complex, 32 and as a 
regulator of late endosomal transport, which is critical for 
autophagy-lysosomal function in neurons. 33 It was also 
reported that protein kinase A (PKA) phosphorylated Snapin 
at its Ser50 residue, and increased both its binding of SNAP-25 
and interaction of synaptotagmin-1 with the SNARE complex. 34 
The results from these studies implied that Snapin is a critical 
protein to regulate synaptic vesicle trafficking and the fusion of 
synaptic vesicles to the plasma membrane. A recent study 
showed that Snapin also functions in fine-tuning of neurite 
outgrowth via interaction with AC6 (type VI adenylyl cyclase), 35 
suggesting that Snapin negatively regulates neurite outgrowth. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Materials </p>

<p>Human Snapin gene (KU35533) was purchased from KUGI (Korean 
UniGene Information) and cloned into modified pcDNA3.1MycHis 
vector (Invitrogen, Calsbad, CA, USA), which contained a Flag tag 
instead of a Myc tag, and into the bacterial expression vector pET29b 
(Novagen, Darmstadt, Germany) using EcoRI and XhoI restriction 
enzymes. Vectors containing Snapin T20A, T117A or T117D muta-
tion were synthesized by in vitro site-directed mutagenesis using a 
mutagenesis kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA, USA) with proper primer 
pairs (Table 1), and the desired mutations were confirmed by 
sequencing the full length of the cloned open reading frame. GST-
Snapin was constructed by cloning the Snapin gene into pGEX4T-1 
(GE Healthcare, Seoul, Korea). Construction of LRRK2 and its 
mutant plasmids was previously described. 13,18 The DApaI and </p>

<p>DXcmI deletion of LRRK2 was carried out by ApaI and XcmI 
digestion, respectively, and re-ligation of the longer DNA fragment, 
resulting in deletion of a specific region of the LRRK2 gene generated 
by the enzyme treatment. Recombinant GST-LRRK2 WT, G2019S or 
D1994A proteins with truncated N-terminal 970 amino acids were 
purchased from Invitrogen. 
GST-SNAP-25 was obtained from Dr Sheng, Z.H. at NIH 
(Bethesda, MD, USA). Antibodies against Myc and flag tags were 
purchased from Sigma (St Louis, MO, USA) and Snapin antibodies 
from SySy (#148002, Goettingen, Germany) or Abnova (H00023557-
A01, Taipei City, Taiwan). The HEK293T cell stably expressing flag-
tagged LRRK2 WT, G2019S or an empty vector 36 was purchased from 
University of Dundee, UK. The vGlut1-pHluorin was kindly provided 
by Prof. Rubenstein, John L.R. at UCSF (San Francisco, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection </p>

<p>Human embryonic kidney 293T cells were maintained with DMEM 
containing 10% fetal bovine serum at 37 1C with 5% CO 2 . To 
overexpress LRRK2 domains or Snapin, the indicated plasmids were 
transiently transfected by the standard CaCl 2 precipitation method or 
using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). To induce LRRK2 proteins, 
HEK293T cells stably expressing flag-tagged LRRK2 WT, G2019S or 
an empty vector were treated with doxycycline (2 mM) for 2 days, 36 
and expression of LRRK2 proteins was confirmed by western blot 
analysis with flag antibody. 
Human SH-SY5Y cells were cultured in DMEM containing 10% 
fetal bovine serum at 37 1C with 5% CO 2 and differentiated in the 
medium containing all-trans retinoic acid (10 mM) for 5 days to obtain 
neuron-like properties. 37 </p>

<p>In vitro kinase assay </p>

<p>To measure the kinase activity of LRRK2, two kinds of LRRK2 
proteins were used as enzyme sources. One was Myc-LRRK2 WT, 
G2019S or D1994A proteins overexpressed in HEK293T cells and 
immunoprecipitated by anti-myc antibody and the other is commer-
cial GST-LRRK2 WT, G2019S or D1994A proteins whose N-terminal 
969 amino acids were deleted and fused to GST protein (Invitrogen). 
For the former, proteins expressed in one well of a 6-well plate were 
used for one kinase reaction, and for the latter, 30 ng of proteins was 
used for each kinase reaction. The indicated proteins were incubated 
in 40 ml of kinase buffer (10 mCi of g 32 P-ATP(SBP-501, IZOTOP 
Budapest, Hungary), 50 mM ATP, 25 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5 mM b-
glycerol phosphate, 2 mM DTT, 0.1 mM NA 3 VO 4 , 10mM MgCl 2 ) 
containing approximately 1.5 mg of Snapin WT or mutant proteins 
purified from Escherichia coli BL21 strain, at 37 1C for 20 min. The 
samples were analyzed by autoradiography or a PhosphorImager 
analyzer (Typhoon 9200 imager, GE Healthcare). </p>

<p>Yeast two-hybrid screening, immunoprecipitation, and GST 
pull-down assay </p>

<p>The yeast two-hybrid screening method has been described in 
detail. 18,38 For the GST pull-down assay, GST, GST-Snapin or GST-
SNAP-25 fusion proteins were expressed in E. coli BL21 strain and 
isolated using glutathione beads (GE Healthcare), as previously 
described. 39 Lysates of HEK293T cells over-expressing Myc-tagged 
LRRK2 WT or mutant proteins were incubated with purified GST or 
GST-Snapin proteins and bound proteins were eluted, subjected to 
SDS-PAGE (polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis), and detected by 
anti-myc antibody. To test whether phosphorylation of Snapin by 
LRRK2 affected Snapin-SNAP-25 interaction, Myc-tagged LRRK2 </p>

<p>Table 1 Primer sequence </p>

<p>Oligomer name 
Sequence (5 
0 to 3 
0 ) </p>

<p>Snapin T20A-F 
GTGGCGGGGCCCGCAGGCCGCGACC 
Snapin T20A-R 
GGTCGCGGCCTGCGGGCCCCGCCAC 
Snapin T117A-F 
GTTGCCAAGGAAGCAGCCCGCAGGAG 
Snapin T117A-R 
CTCCTGCGGGCTGCTTCCTTGGCAAC 
Snapin T117D-F 
GTTGCCAAGGAAGACGCCCGCAGGAG 
Snapin T117D-R 
CTCCTGCGGGCGTCT TCCTTGGCAAC </p>

<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>G2019S protein was overexpressed in 293T cells, immunoprecipitated 
by anti-Myc antibody and then incubated with Snapin recombinant 
proteins for phosphorylation. Supernatants containing Snapin phos-
phorylated by LRRK2 were incubated with GST-SNAP-25 recombi-
nant proteins. Snapin bound to GST-SNAP-25 was detected -by a 
GST pull-down assay and western blot analysis using anti-Snapin 
antibody (SySy). 
To test the effect of Snapin phosphorylation mediated by LRRK2 
on synaptotagmin, we followed the previously described protocol. 40 
Rat brain lysate (3 mg) was mixed with recombinant Snapin WT or 
T117D proteins (5 mg) and incubated with anti-syntaxin (Abcam, 
#ab3265, Cambridge, UK) or mouse control immunoglobulin G 
(Santa Cruz, Santa Cruz, CA, USA) in a binding buffer (phosphate-
buffered saline with 0.1% Triton X-100, 0.1% BSA, 200 mM CaCl 2 , 1 Â 
protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche)) overnight at 4 1C. The mixture 
was then incubated with protein-G agarose (Peptron, Daejeon, Korea) 
for 2 h at 4 1C. The purified complex was washed with a washing 
buffer (phosphate-buffered saline with 0.1% Triton X-100) three 
times and subjected to SDS-PAGE and western blot analyses using the 
indicated antibodies (synaptotagmin-1: Santa Cruz, #sc-12466; SNAP-
25: BD, #610366; VAMP2: Synaptic Systems, SySy #69.1). 
For immunoprecipitation of mouse brain lysate, G2019S transgenic 
(TG, #009609, purchased from Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, ME, 
USA) and normal control mice were killed by cervical dislocation. 
Whole mouse brains were isolated with a scalpel blade. Co-immu-
noprecipitation analysis was carried out as previously described. 41 
Briefly, whole brains were disrupted in 1 ml of 50 mM Tris, pH 7.5, 
50 mM NaCl, 0.5% Triton X-100 and 1% protease inhibitor cocktail 
using a Dounce Homogenizer (10 stroke) and lysed by passing the 
extracts through a 22-gauge needle five times. Extracts were 
centrifuged at 12 000 g for 30 min at 4 1C to remove insoluble 
material, and supernatants were mixed with equivalent volume of 
binding buffer (50 mM Tris, pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 0.1% bovine serum 
albumin (BSA), 0.1% Triton X-100 and 1% protease inhibitor cocktail 
(PIC)) and then centrifuged at 20 000 g for 30 min at 4 1C. The 
supernatants were finally immunoprecipitated with anti-SNAP25 or 
anti-LRRK2 (MJFF2, Epitomics, Burlingame, CA, USA) at 4 1C for 
2 h and further incubated with protein-G agarose (Pierce, Rockford, 
IL, USA) for 2 h. The antibody-protein complexes were washed three 
times with binding buffer minus BSA and protease inhibitor cocktail, 
and subjected to western blot analysis using the indicated antibodies 
(Snapin:Abnova, H00023557, LRRK2:1E11 or UDD 3 30 (Epitomics)). 
The flag-tagged LRRK2 protein was induced from HEK293T stable 
cells 36 by treatment of doxycycline (2 mM for 2 days). The cell lysates 
centrifuged at 14 000 g for 20 min at 4 1C and were incubated with the 
agarose immobilized flag epitope tag antibody (Novus, Littleton, CO, 
USA, #NB600-351). Then, immunoprecipitation and western blot 
analysis were performed as above. </p>

<p>Neuron culture and transfection </p>

<p>The hippocampal neurons derived from E-18 pregnant Sprague-
Dawley female rats were prepared as described. 42 Briefly, the 
embryonic hippocampi were dissected, dissociated with papain and 
triturated with a polished, half-bore Pasteur pipette. Dissociated 
neurons (2.5 Â 10 5 ) in minimum Eagle's medium supplemented 
with 0.6% glucose, 1 mM pyruvate, 2 mM L-glutamine, 10% fetal 
bovine serum and antibiotics were plated on poly-D-lysine-coated 
glass coverslips in a 60 mm Petri dish. Four hours after plating, the 
medium was replaced with Neurobasal media (Invitrogen) 
supplemented with 2% B-27, 0.5 mM L-glutamine, to which 4 mM of </p>

<p>1-b-D-cytosine-arabinofuranoside (Ara-C, Sigma) was added as 
needed. Neurons were transfected using a modified calcium-
phosphate method. 18 Briefly, 6 mg of cDNA and 9.3 ml of 2 M CaCl 2 
were mixed in distilled water to a total volume of 75 ml, and the same 
volume of 2X BBS was added. Neurobasal medium was completely 
replaced by transfection medium (minimum Eagle's medium, 1 mM 
pyruvate, 0.6% glucose, 10 mM glutamine and 10 mM N-2-hydroxyl 
piperazine-N 
0 -2-ethane sulfonic acid, pH 7.65), and the cDNA 
mixture was added to the neurons, and incubated in a 5% CO 2 
incubator for 90 min. Neurons were washed twice with washing 
medium (minimum Eagle's medium, 1 mM pyruvate, 0.6% glucose, 
10 mM glutamine and 10 mM N-2-hydroxyl piperazine-N 
0 -2-ethane 
sulfonic acid (N-2-hydroxyl piperazine-N 
0 -2-ethane sulfonic acid), 
pH 7.35) and then returned to the original culture medium. The 
vGlut-pHluorin (vGpH) and pU6mRFP constructs were co-
transfected in a ratio of 5:1. The construct vGpH harbors vesicular 
glutamate transporter 1 fused with pHluorin, a modified GFP with 
high pH sensitivity. 43 When targeted to the synaptic vesicle lumen, 
vGpH is quenched and upon exocytosis, the relatively basic pH of the 
extracellular space allows it to fluoresce. Its fluorescence is again 
quenched after endocytosis and re-acidification of the synaptic 
vesicles. Thus, this process accurately reflects the kinetics of exo-
endocytic trafficking of synaptic vesicles. 43,44 </p>

<p>Synaptic vesicle pool size measurement and image analysis </p>

<p>Coverslips were mounted in a perfusion/stimulation chamber 
equipped with platinum-iridium field stimulus electrodes (EC-S-10, 
LCI, Seoul, Korea) on the stage of an Olympus IX-71 inverted 
microscope with Â 40, 1.0 NA oil lens (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan). 
Neurons were continuously perfused at room temperature with 
Tyrode solution (136 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl 2 , 1.3mM 
MgCl 2 , 10mM N-2-hydroxyl piperazine-N 
0 -2-ethane sulfonic acid, 
10 mM glucose, pH 7.3). To reduce spontaneous activity and prevent 
recurrent excitation during stimulation, 10 mM 6-cyano-7-nitroqui-
noxaline-2, 3-dione and 50 mM of DL-2-amino-5-phosphonovaleric 
acid were added to the Tyrode solution. Time-lapse images were 
acquired every 5 s for 4 min using a back-illuminated Andor iXon 897 
EMCCD camera (Andor Technologies, Belfast, Northern Ireland) 
driven by MetaMorph Imaging software (Molecular Devices, Sunny-
vale, CA, USA). From the fourth frame, neurons were stimulated 
(1 ms, 20-50 V, bipolar) using an A310 Accupulser current stimulator 
(World Precision Instruments, Sarasota, FL, USA) to mimic action 
potential generation. Quantitative measurement of fluorescence 
intensity at individual boutons was obtained by averaging a selected 
area of pixel intensities using <rs type="software">MetaMorph</rs> software. Individual regions 
were selected by hand. Then, rectangular regions of interest were 
drawn around the synaptic boutons, and average intensities were 
calculated. Large puncta, typically representative of smaller synapse 
clusters, were rejected during the selection procedure. The center of 
intensity of each synapse was calculated to correct for any image shift 
over the course of the experiment. Fluorescence was expressed in 
intensity units that correspond to fluorescence values averaged over all 
pixels within the region of interest. Changes in net fluorescence were 
obtained by subtracting the average intensity of the first four frames 
(F 0 ) from the intensity of each frame (F t ) for individual boutons. 
They were then normalized to the maximum fluorescence intensity 
(F max ÀF 0 ) and averaged. For the exocytosis assays, neurons were pre-
incubated with bafilomycin A1 (Calbiochem, San Diego, CA, USA) 
for 60 s to block re-acidification and stimulated for 30 s at 20 Hz/600 
action potentials (APs), a combination, which is known to totally </p>

<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>deplete the recycling pool of vesicles. 44 Bafilomycin A1 was dissolved 
in Me 2 SO at 0.2 mM and diluted to a final concentration of 0.5 mM 
prior to the experiments. Bafilomycin A1 was applied throughout the 
fluorescence measurements. 
To estimate the size of each fraction of the synaptic vesicle pool, 
vGpH-transfected neurons at DIV 18 were stimulated with 40 APs at 
20 Hz, which is known to release the store of readily releasable pool of 
synaptic vesicles in the hippocampal synapses, 44 followed by 1800 APs 
at 20 Hz stimulation in the presence of 1 mM bafilomycin A1 to release 
the entire recycling pool of synaptic vesicles. 39,44 The resting pool that 
cannot be mobilized by such neuronal activity can be uncovered by 
applying NH 4 Cl solution to unquench all acidic vesicles not yet 
released. Data are presented as means ± s.e.m. Statistical analysis was 
carried out with PASW Statistics 19 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). For 
multiple conditions, we compared means by analysis of variance 
followed by Tukey's honestly significant difference post hoc test or 
Fisher's LSD test (depending on the number of groups). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
LRRK2 phosphorylates Snapin at Thr-117 residue 
To investigate the mechanism for LRRK2 to generate PD, we 
attempted to elucidate the normal physiological functions of 
LRRK2. We employed yeast two-hybrid screening to isolate 
proteins interacting with LRRK2, and tried to deduce LRRK2's 
function by identifying the functions of the LRRK2-interacting </p>

<p>proteins. Snapin (SNAP-25-interacting protein) was originally 
isolated as an LRRK2-interacting protein by yeast two-hybrid 
screening using regions from ROC to the kinase (GK) domain 
or containing the WD40 domain as baits. Both screenings 
yielded multiple identical Snapin clones whose open reading 
frame started at the 33rd amino acid. The Snapin clone also 
interacted with the bait containing the full length LRRK2 gene 
(data not shown). 
As both Snapin and LRRK2 were reported to have roles in 
vesicle trafficking, 18,29,31,45 we first tested the possibility that 
Snapin was a LRRK2 kinase substrate. An in vitro kinase assay 
was performed with bacterially expressed, recombinant Snapin 
and immunoprecipitated, Myc-tagged LRRK2 WT, G2019S or 
kinase-dead D1994A proteins overexpressed in HEK293T cells. 
The results showed that LRRK2 phosphorylated Snapin in 
the order of G2019S4WT, and this order was also observed 
in LRRK2 autophosphorylation, as previously reported 
(Figure 1a). 3,15,24 As expected, the kinase dead mutant 
D1994A 11 showed weaker phosphorylation of Snapin and no 
autophosphorylation, a pattern similar to the reaction with the 
vector control (Figure 1a). The weak phosphorylation of 
Snapin observed in the vector and D1994A lanes might be 
derived from other kinases non-specifically immuno-
precipitated by the myc antibody (Figures 1ai and iii, lanes </p>

<p>Figure 1 Snapin phosphorylation by leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2). (a) Immunoprecipitated LRRK2 phosphorylates Snapin. 
Recombinant Snapin protein was expressed in E. coli as His-tagged fusion protein and isolated by affinity chromatography with nickel 
resin. Indicated LRRK2 wild-type (WT) or mutant proteins were expressed in HEK293T cells as Myc-tagged forms and 
immunoprecipitated by anti-myc antibody. The immunoprecipitates (IP) were incubated with Snapin for an in vitro kinase assay. 
Autoradiograms of phosphorylated LRRK2 (i) and phosphorylated Snapin (iii) are shown. In addition, the amount of immunoprecipitated 
LRRK2 (ii) and recombinant Snapin (iv) proteins were detected by anti-myc antibody and Coomassie blue staining, respectively. 
The empty vector was also transfected to HEK293T cells and the cell lysates were used as a control (vector). (b) Recombinant 
GST-LRRK2 (Invitrogen) proteins also phosphorylate Snapin, but not ARF1. The purchased LRRK2 WT (WT), G2019S (G) or R1441C (R) 
proteins were used for an in vitro kinase assay. Autoradiograms showed that LRRK2 and Snapin (i), but not ARF1, proteins (ii) were 
phosphorylated by LRRK2 (ii). (iii) Positions of both Arf1 and Snapin proteins are indicated by arrows. (c) The amino-acid sequence 
of human Snapin. The conserved phosphorylation candidate sites at the 20th and 117th threonine residues are indicated as bold letters. 
(d) LRRK2 phosphorylates Snapin at Thr-117. GST-LRRK2 WT or G2019S (Invitrogen) were subjected to an in vitro kinase assay 
with recombinant Snapin WT, T20A or T117A protein. Autoradiograms of autophosphorylated GST-LRRK2 (i) and phosphorylated Snapin 
(ii) are shown. For each kinase assay, use of equal amounts of substrates was confirmed by SDS-PAGE and Coomassie blue staining 
(aiv, biii, diii). </p>

<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>1, 4). A similar pattern of Snapin phosphorylation was also 
observed using commercially available GST-LRRK2 proteins 
(Invitrogen, Figure 1b). As a negative control, we tested ARF1 
proteins that were expressed in the same pET 29 vector as 
Snapin, as substrates for an in vitro kinase assay. GST-LRRK2 
G2019S could not phosphorylate the ARF1 proteins 
(Figure 1bii; strongly suggesting that phosphorylation of 
Snapin by LRRK2 is specific. 
To identify the phosphorylation site of Snapin by LRRK2, 
we searched an F/Y-X-T-X-R/K motif (the underlined T is the 
phosphorylation site), a putative phosphorylation site by 
LRRK2 that was previously reported. 46 Out of four Thr 
residues in Snapin, two at the 20th (PVAGPTGRD) and 
117th (SVAKETARR) amino acid contained a conserved 
arginine (indicated by an underlined letter) at the þ 2 
position (Figure 1c). We mutated each threonine to alanine 
(Snapin T20A and T117A), and purified them as bacterially 
expressed recombinant proteins. Using the purified Snapin 
proteins, we performed an in vitro kinase assay with the 
GST-LRRK2 WT or G2019S proteins. The results showed that </p>

<p>phosphorylation of T117A by the recombinant GST-LRRK2 
G2019S proteins was almost, but not completely, eradicated, 
whereas that of T20A remained at a level similar to that of WT. 
This suggests that Thr-117 is at least one of the phosphoryla-
tion sites of Snapin by LRRK2 (Figure 1dii). </p>

<p>LRRK2 interacts with Snapin via its ROC domain 
To confirm interaction between Snapin and LRRK2, we 
conducted a GST pull-down assay. Figure 2a shows that 
LRRK2 overexpressed in 293T cells specifically interacted with 
bacterially expressed GST-Snapin. As Snapin was reported to 
interact with many different proteins of various functions by 
yeast two-hybrid screening, 41,47-51 and it has even been 
suggested that its interaction with SNAP-25 is non-specific, 52 
we used murine-constitutive androstane receptor (CAR, 
NR1I3), a nuclear receptor, as a nonspecific negative control 
in the GST pull-down assay. As expected, CAR did not interact 
with GST-Snapin whereas LRRK2 specifically interacted with 
GST-Snapin (Figure 2a). Three PD-pathogenic mutants 
(G2019S, I2020T and R1441C), interacted with GST-Snapin </p>

<p>Figure 2 Leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2) interacts with Snapin. (a) Lysates of 293T cells transfected with myc-LRRK2 (LRRK2 
WT) or HA-murine CAR (CAR) were co-incubated with purified GST-Snapin (S) or GST proteins and subjected to a GST pull-down assay 
and western blot analysis using anti-myc or anti-HA antibody. (b) LRRK2 WT, G2019S, R1441C or I2020T was expressed in HEK293T 
cells and the cell lysates were used for a GST pull-down assay as (a) Input (I) of each sample is 2.5% of the total proteins. The amount 
of GST-Snapin or GST proteins used was detected by Coomassie staining, and it was confirmed that similar amounts of GST proteins 
were used (a, b). (c) Co-immunoprecipitation of flag-LRRK2 with myc-Snapin. The HEK293T cells were induced by doxycycline to stably 
express flag-LRRK2 and transfected with plasmids expressing myc-Snapin. Cell lysates were immunoprecipitated with flag antibody-
agarose. The immunoprecipitate (IP) was washed and prepared for western analysis with anti-flag or anti-myc. 10% of cell lysates 
were shown as input (Input). * indicates a non-specific band. (d) SH-SY5Y cells differentiated by retinoic acid (10 mM for 5 days) 
were immunoprecipitated by LRRK2 (MJFF2, Epitomics) antibody and the immunoprecipitates were analyzed by antibody against 
LRRK2 (1E11) or Snapin (SYSY). An input of 2% was not enough to detect endogenous LRRK2, but sufficient for Snapin detection. 
WB, western blot. </p>

<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>with little differences in their affinities to Snapin in compar-
ison with WT (Figure 2b). To further test the interaction of 
Snapin with LRRK2, we expressed Myc-tagged Snapin in 
HEK293T cells stably expressing flag-tagged LRRK2, and 
performed co-immunoprecipitation of LRRK2 by flag anti-
body. The result showed that LRRK2 co-immunoprecipitated 
Snapin (Figure 2c). We also tested the interaction of LRRK2 
with Snapin in the differentiated SH-SY5Y cells without any 
overexpression. The endogenous LRRK2 weakly, but specifi-
cally interacted with endogenous Snapin (Figure 2d). 
To identify the LRRK2 domain interacting with Snapin, we 
constructed several LRRK2 deletion mutants (Figure 3a), 
overexpressed them in HEK293T cells and then repeated the 
GST pull-down assay using the HEK293T cell lysates and 
GST-Snapin. The results suggested both ROC and N-terminal 
(1-937 amino acids) domains as the interaction domains 
(Figure 3b). As we isolated the Snapin clone from the yeast 
two-hybrid screening using the GK and WD40 domains as 
baits, the GST pull-down assay results partially supported the 
yeast two-hybrid results. However, we were unable to test the 
interaction of Snapin with the WD40 domain, because 
transient expression of the WD40 domain in HEK293T cells 
was too weak to perform a GST pull-down assay. </p>

<p>Snapin phosphorylation by LRRK2 decreases interaction of 
Snapin with SNAP-25 
To investigate the physiological function of Snapin phosphor-
ylation by LRRK2, we constructed Snapin T117D, a </p>

<p>phosphorylation mimetic mutant, and both Snapin WT and 
T117D recombinant proteins were expressed in E. coli, purified 
and tested for specific interaction with GST-SNAP-25. 
Figure 4a exhibits that Snapin T117D very weakly interacted 
with GST-SNAP-25 in comparison with interaction of Snapin 
WT and T117A. This suggested that the phosphorylation of 
Snapin T117 inhibited the interaction of SNAP-25 with 
Snapin. To determine whether Snapin phosphorylation by 
LRRK2 exhibits similar results, Myc-tagged, G2019S proteins 
expressed in HEK293T cells were immunoprecipitated by anti-
myc antibody and the precipitate was incubated with recom-
binant Snapin WT protein so that Snapin WT could be 
phosphorylated. The resultant Snapin proteins were tested for 
interaction with GST-SNAP-25 by a GST pull-down assay. The 
results showed that Snapin, which might be phosphorylated by 
LRRK2, considerably decreased the interaction of SNAP-25 
with Snapin (Figure 4b), similar to the Snapin T117D 
mutants. We could not, however, directly confirm the phos-
phorylation status of Snapin, because no phospho-Snapin-
specific antibody is currently available. 
To confirm that Snapin phosphorylation by LRRK2 causes 
its interaction with SNAP25 to be weaker than with non-
phosphorylated Snapin, we carried out co-immunoprecipita-
tion of SNAP25 from brain lysates of G2019S TG and control 
normal mice, and the co-immunoprecipitated complex was 
subjected to the western blot analysis using Snapin antibody. 
The result showed that the amount of co-immunoprecipitated 
Snapin in the TG brain lysates, which contained more LRRK2 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Mapping of leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2) domain interacting with Snapin. (a) A scheme of several LRRK2 deletion 
mutant constructs. LRR: Leucine-rich repeats; Roc, Ras of complex proteins; CoR, C-terminal of Roc domain. (b) GST pull-down assay of 
LRRK2. The indicated LRRK2-mutant proteins were expressed in 293T cells as a Myc-tagged form by transient transfection and total cell 
lysates were subjected to a GST pull-down assay using GST (-) or GST-Snapin (S). Input (I) of each sample was 2.5% of the total 
proteins. The LRRK2 proteins were detected with anti-myc antibody, except for the kinase domain, which was detected by a previously 
reported LRRK2 antibody, 1E11. 67 Because expressions of the DApaI, Roc and kinase domains were weaker those of the other domains, 
exposure times of these domains were extended. * indicates nonspecific protein band. </p>

<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>kinase activity, was reduced by almost half compared with that 
of the normal brain lysates (Figure 4c, lanes 3 and 4) although 
the amount of input Snapin was slightly higher in the control 
lysates (Figure 4c lanes 1 and 2). </p>

<p>LRRK2-mediated phosphorylation of Snapin decreased 
interaction of synaptotagmin-1 with SNAP25-syntaxin-
VAMP2 complex 
To identify the physiological functions of LRRK2-mediated 
Snapin phosphorylation, we tested Snapin-mediated interac-
tion of synaptotagmin with SNAP-25. It was shown that 
PKA phosphorylated Snapin at serine 50 and the phospho-
mimetic Snapin S50D protein, enhanced synaptotagmin 
association with the core synaptic fusion complex con-
taining SNAP-25, VAMP2 (synaptobrevin-2) and syntaxin. 40 </p>

<p>We assumed that inhibitory phosphorylation of Snapin by 
LRRK2 might decrease association of synaptotagmin with the 
SNARE complex, in contrast to PKA-mediated activatory 
phosphorylation of Snapin. 
To test our hypothesis, rat brain lysate was incubated with 
Snapin WT or T117D protein and the complex was co-
immunoprecipitated by syntaxin antibody. The immunopre-
cipitates were analyzed using western blot analysis with 
synaptotagmin-1 antibody. Figure 5 shows that Snapin WT 
increased the association of synaptotagmin-1 with the core 
SNARE complex. In contrast, T117D-mutant protein 
decreased the association. The amount of each component 
of the SNARE complex was similar except for SNAP-25, whose 
interaction with syntaxin might be decreased by the addition 
of Snapin. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Phosphorylation of Snapin by leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2) causes a decrease of interaction with SNAP-25. (a) Snapin 
T117D-mutant mimicking phosphorylation by LRRK2 interacts with SNAP-25 more weakly than the wild type (WT). Recombinant Flag-
tagged Snapin WT and indicated mutant proteins were subjected to a GST pull-down assay using GST-SNAP-25 and detected by western 
blot analysis using anti-Flag antibody. Coomassie blue staining of GST and GST-SNAP-25 showed that similar amounts of each protein 
were used. (b) Snapin WT protein phosphorylated by LRRK2 exhibited weaker interaction with SNAP-25 than the untreated and 
presumably unphosphorylated Snapin (control). The myc-tagged LRRK2 G2019S was transiently expressed in HEK293T cells and 
immunoprecipitated by anti-myc antibody. The immunoprecipitated beads were co-incubated with recombinant flag tagged Snapin WT 
protein with ATP under the in vitro kinase assay conditions. The supernatant was co-incubated with purified GST-SNAP-25 and subjected 
to a GST pull-down assay and SDS-PAGE. The bound Snapin was detected by anti-flag antibody (Sigma) and the amount was compared 
to the control transfected with an empty vector (i). The presence of LRRK2 in immunoprecipitates was confirmed by anti-myc antibody 
(ii). Coomassie blue staining (iii) confirmed that equal amounts of GST-SANP25 protein were used for both incubations (control and 
G2019S). (c) Interaction of SNAP25 with Snapin was weaker in G2019S transgenic (TG) than in a control (C) mouse brain lysate. Whole 
brain lysates were prepared from both G2019S TG and normal control mice and immunoprecipitated with SNAP25 antibody. The amount 
of Snapin in each brain lysates (20% input) was shown with Snapin antibody (Abnova, 1:500 dilution, Snapin-low). The 
immunoprecipitates, which showed no signal under the diluted condition above, were subjected to western blot analysis with more 
concentrated Snapin antibody (Abnova, 1:50 dilution, Snapin-high). The amount of specific immunoprecipitated Snapin was calculated as 
the amount of immunoprecipitated Snapin divided by the amount of immunoprecipitated SNAP25. An arrow or * indicated Snapin or 
nonspecific protein band, respectively. </p>

<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>LRRK2-dependent phosphorylation of Snapin decreased the 
fraction of readily releasable pool and the extent of 
exocytotic release. 
As we found that LRRK2-induced phosphorylation on Snapin 
T117 decreased the interaction of synaptotagmin-1 with the 
SNAP25-syntaxin-VAMP2 complex, we next tested the effect 
of LRRK2-induced phosphorylation of Snapin on synaptic 
transmission of the cultured hippocampal neurons. We co-
transfected WT Snapin alone, T117D alone, G2019S and WT 
Snapin or D1994A and WT Snapin with vGpH in cultured 
rat hippocampal neurons. 43 The vesicles of a synapse are 
organized into three distinct pools, two of which recycle 
(readily releasable pool (RRP) and a reserve pool), and one 
which normally does not (resting pool). The vesicles of the 
RRP are known to be docked at the plasma membrane, ready 
for immediate release upon stimulation. 44 After the RRP has 
been depleted, continued release occurs from the reserve pool. 
The amplitude of the response to a train of 40 APs at 20 Hz 
corresponds to the size of the RRP of the synaptic vesicles. 
Those recycling vesicles released by a stimulus of 1800 APs at 
20 Hz after the addition of bafilomycin A1, a V-type ATPase 
inhibitor that blocks acidification of endocytosed synaptic 
vesicles, represent the remainder of the total recycling 
pool. 44,53 The resting pool of vesicles, which are refractory to 
stimulation and normally do not participate in recycling, can 
be uncovered by adding NH 4 Cl to trap all the vesicles in an 
alkaline state and hence unquench all acidic vesicles that have 
not been released (Figure 6a 44,53 ). 
We found that LRRK2 G2019S with WT Snapin resulted in 
a decrease in the RRP fraction at the expense of the reserved 
fraction (Figure 6b, RRP fraction:reserved fraction ¼ 
20.7±2.8%:29.6±3.0% for control; 12.4±1.3%:41.6±2.9% 
for G2019S). Subsequently, the extent of exocytotic release 
during 100 APs stimulation was also significantly decreased 
by G2019S (Figure 6c). LRRK2 D1994A with WT Snapin </p>

<p>expression showed somewhat opposite effects: the RRP and 
reserve pool fractions were increased at the expense of the 
resting pool fraction (Figure 6). The extent of exocytotic 
release was also significantly increased by D1994A. 
Although Snapin T117D itself did not show any effect on 
the synaptic vesicle pool size and the extent of exocytotic 
release (Figure 6), we assume that this might be attributed to 
the compensatory effect of endogenous Snapin or the presence 
of LRRK2-induced phosphorylation sites other than T117 in 
Snapin. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
We reported here that LRRK2 interacts with and phosphorylates 
Snapin, possibly at threonine 117. Snapin has been reported to 
interact with numerous proteins including SNAP-25, 28 EBAG9, 47 
cypin, 54 casein kinase 1-delta, 50 a subunit of Exo70, 49 TRPC6, 51 
EHD1, 55 disbindin-1, 56 type VI adenylyl cyclase, 48 ryanodine 
receptor 57 and UT-A1 urea transporter. 41 Most of these Snapin-
interacting proteins function in vesicle trafficking. However, the 
various functions of interaction partners also suggest a possibility 
that Snapin might non-specifically interact with these proteins. 52 
However, a Snapin knockout animal model exhibited impaired 
calcium-dependent exocytosis of large dense-core vesicles in 
chromaffin cells, confirming specific physiological roles of 
Snapin in synaptic vesicle trafficking. 29 
Until now, PKA and casein kinase 1d were known to 
phosphorylate Snapin. 40,50 We report here LRRK2 as another 
Snapin kinase. One of the phosphorylation sites of Snapin 
by LRRK2 was identified as threonine 117. Although we 
identified this site based on the conserved sequences for 
LRRK2's phosphorylation site, 46 a recent study on LRRK2's 
phosphorylation site suggested that LRRK2 phosphorylates 
amino acids whose surrounding regions have high pI values, 
rather than the conserved amino-acid sequences. 58 The pI of 
the peptide containing the 113rd amino acid to 121st amino </p>

<p>Figure 5 T117D Snapin, a phosphomimetic mutant, decreased interaction of synaptotagmin with VAMP2-syntaxin-SNAP 25 complex. Rat 
brain lysate was incubated with none ( À), recombinant Snapin wild type (WT) or T117D overnight and immunoprecipitated with 
syntaxin1 antibody or control rabbit immunoglobulin G antibody. The immunoprecipitate was subjected to SDS-PAGE for western blot 
analysis. Co-precipitated synaptotagmin-1 was detected by synaptotagmin-1 antibody and each component of the VAMP2-syntaxin-SNAP-
25 SNARE complex was also detected by specific antibodies. The experiment was repeated three times and then band densities were 
analyzed. Data are presented as means ± s.e.m. *Pp0.01 (analysis of variance and Turkey's honestly significant difference post hoc test). 
A representative image (a) and the resulting graph are shown (b). Five percent of the total brain lysate (a) is shown as input. Use of 
similar amounts of the recombinant Snapin proteins was confirmed (c). Snapin was detected by the His tag, which was used for 
purification of the recombinant protein. *Pp0.05 (analysis of variance and Turkey's honestly significant difference post hoc test). </p>

<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>acids (VAKETARRR) of Snapin is 11.7 (calculated by a 
program from http://web.expasy.org/protparam/), confirming 
that threonine 117 is acceptable as a phosphorylation site of 
LRRK2 regardless of the rule that is applied. 46,58 However, 
LRRK2's phosphorylated motif sequence is not well conserved. 
Several studies have reported that LRRK2 could phosphorylate 
threonine or even serine at sites unrelated to the reported 
F/Y-X-T-X-R/K threonine sites. 59,60 Therefore, it is possible 
that serines or threonines in Snapin are phosphorylated by 
LRRK2 in addition to T117, because T117A mutant proteins 
were still weakly phosphorylated by LRRK2 in the in vitro 
kinase assay (Figure 1d). We found that Snapin T117D did not 
significantly affect synaptic vesicle composition and extent of 
exocytosis, and this might be due to the presence of additional 
phosphorylation sites in Snapin by LRRK2 (Figure 6b). 
We did not observe any significant differences in the 
interaction of Snapin with LRRK2 WT and its pathogenic 
mutants (Figure 2). This suggests that interaction of LRRK2 </p>

<p>with Snapin is not directly related to PD pathogenicity. 
However, it is still possible that G2019S phosphorylates Snapin 
more than WT given G2019S's stronger kinase activity. This 
may result in stronger inhibitory phosphorylation of Snapin 
by the G2019S mutant (Figures 1a and b), which may be 
related to PD pathogenesis. 
Previously, we showed that LRRK2 was enriched in the soluble 
synaptosome fraction, suggesting the possibility that LRRK2 
interacts with synaptic proteins. 18 A recent report suggested 
that LRRK2 is part of a presynaptic protein network and controls 
synaptic vesicle trafficking. 61 Silencing of the expression of 
LRRK2 caused redistribution of vesicles within the bouton and 
altered recycling dynamics. 61 Neurons from Snapin-deficient 
mice also showed desynchronized fusion of synaptic vesicles 
and impairment of synaptic efficacy and precision. 31 
Snapin was reported to promote SNAP-25 binding to 
synaptotagmin-1 and to stabilize binding of synaptotagmin-1 
to the SNARE complex. 31 This resulted in an increase in the </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>RRP fraction </p>

<p>Normalized F </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>n.s </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>Reserve pool fraction </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>n.s </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>Resting pool fraction </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>n.s </p>

<p>SNAPIN </p>

<p>Time (sec) </p>

<p>200 
300 
400 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>RRP </p>

<p>RP </p>

<p>Resting 
Pool </p>

<p>20 Hz w/ Baf NH 4 Cl 
20Hz 20Hz </p>

<p>SNAPIN T117D </p>

<p>Time (sec) </p>

<p>200 
300 
400 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>20 Hz w/Baf 
20Hz 20Hz </p>

<p>G2019S &amp; WT </p>

<p>Time (sec) </p>

<p>200 
300 
400 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>20 Hz w/ Baf 
20Hz 20Hz </p>

<p>D1994A &amp; WT </p>

<p>Time (sec) </p>

<p>20 Hz w/ Baf 
20Hz 20Hz </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>Exocytotic extent </p>

<p>n.s </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>LRRK2 : </p>

<p>SNAPIN : 
WT </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>T117D WT 
WT </p>

<p>LRRK2 : 
G/S 
D/A </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>T117D WT 
WT </p>

<p>G/S 
D/A </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>T117D WT 
WT </p>

<p>G/S 
D/A </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>T117D WT 
WT </p>

<p>G/S 
D/A </p>

<p>SNA PIN : </p>

<p>LRRK2 : </p>

<p>SNA PIN : </p>

<p>LRRK2 : </p>

<p>SNA PIN : </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>NH 4 Cl 
NH 4 Cl 
NH 4 Cl </p>

<p>100 
0 
0 
100 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
100 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
200 
300 
400 
0 
100 </p>

<p>Figure 6 Leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 (LRRK2)-dependent phosphorylation of Snapin decreased the size of RRP and the extent of 
exocytotic release. (a) Rat hippocampal neurons were co-transfected with wild-type Snapin alone, T117D alone, G2019S and wild-type 
Snapin, or D1994A and wild-type Snapin with vGpH. To measure RRP size, neurons were stimulated with 40 APs at 20 Hz. They were 
then stimulated with 1800 APs at 20 Hz in the presence of bafilomycin (baf). Subtraction of RRP fluorescence from the fluorescence 
plateau reflected the reserve pool (RP). All remaining acidic vesicles were alkalized by NH 4 Cl treatment, revealing the size of the resting 
pool. Fluorescence intensity was normalized to the maximum fluorescence change upon NH 4 Cl treatment. (b) (left) Average fraction of 
RRP in wild-type Snapin alone, T117D alone, G2019S and wild-type Snapin, or D1994A and wild-type Snapin (20.7% ± 2.8% for wild-
type Snapin; 16.6%±2.2% for T117D; 12.4%±1.3% for G2019S and wild-type Snapin; 29.2%±3.6% for D1994A and wild-type 
Snapin). (middle) Average fraction of reserve pool (29.6% ± 3.0% for wild-type Snapin; 32.8% ± 3.1% for T117D; 41.6% ± 2.9% for 
G2019S and wild-type Snapin; 37.4%±6.4% for D1994A and wild-type Snapin). (right) Average fraction of resting pool (49.7%±3.0% 
for wild-type Snapin; 50.5% ± 1.4% for T117D; 46.0% ± 2.8% for G2019S and wild-type Snapin; 33.8% ± 6.6% for D1994A and wild-
type Snapin). (c) The extent of exocytotic release. Rat hippocampal neurons were co-transfected with wild-type Snapin alone, T117D 
alone, G2019S and wild-type Snapin, or D1994A and wild-type Snapin with vGpH. The neurons were stimulated with 100 APs at 10 Hz, 
and then treated with NH 4 Cl to obtain the total synaptic vesicle pool size. Fluorescence intensity was normalized to the maximum 
fluorescence change upon NH 4 Cl treatment. Data are presented as means ± s.e.m. *Pp0.01 (analysis of variance and Turkey's honestly 
significant difference post hoc test). </p>

<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

<p>number of synaptic vesicles in the readily releasable state. 29,31 
Thus far, both positive and negative regulators for the 
interaction between Snapin and SNAP-25 have been 
reported. PKA phosphorylated Snapin at serine 50, increased 
the Snapin interaction with SNAP-25, and caused an increase 
of synaptic vesicle release. 34,40 Two negative regulators, EBAG9 
and EHD1, inhibited interaction of Snapin with SNAP-25 47,55 
and interaction of SNAP25 with synaptotagmin-1. Consistent 
with these previous findings, we also found that LRRK2-
mediated phosphorylation of Snapin decreased interaction of 
synaptotagmin with the core SNARE complex (Figure 5). This 
subsequently resulted in a reduced RRP fraction and extent of 
exocytosis, suggesting that LRRK2 is another negative regu-
lator of the Snapin and SNAP-25 interaction during synaptic 
transmission. 
Snapin has been reported to directly interact with synapto-
tagmin 31 in addition to indirect interaction via SNAP25. 
Whether Snapin S50D protein enhances its direct interaction 
with synaptotagmin is yet unknown. It would be interesting to 
investigate the effect of LRRK2-mediated phosphorylation of 
Snapin, on its direct interaction with synaptotagmin. 
One of the well-known LRRK2 kinase functions is negative 
regulation of neurite length. In contrast, SNAP-25 is known as 
a positive regulator of neurite length. 62 Recently, type VI 
adenylyl cyclase (AC6) was reported as a Snapin-interacting 
protein and a suppressor of neurite extension. 63 Down-
regulation of Snapin or overexpression of SNAP-25 reversed 
neurite shortening by AC6. 63 Investigation of the effect of 
LRRK2-mediated Snapin phosphorylation on neurite length 
could be of further interest. 
In addition, it would be interesting to investigate whether 
the pattern of interaction of Snapin phosphorylated at Thr-117 
with various other previously reported Snapin partner proteins 
is changed. 28,41,47,49-51,54-56 
Both Snapin and LRRK2 have been reported to regulate 
trafficking of proteins from late endosomes to lysosomes 
positively and negatively, respectively. 33,64 In addition, several 
papers have reported that overexpression of a-synuclein or 
LRRK2 causes defects in synaptic vesicle trafficking. 45,65,66 Our 
data may provide a clue to explain this phenotype in another 
direction, possibly by inhibitory phosphorylation of Snapin by 
LRRK2, although this requires further experiments. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Drs ZH Sheng (NIH, USA) and CJ Gloeckner (Munich, 
Germany) for GST-SNAP-25 and LRRK2 antibody (1E11), 
respectively. This research was supported by the Global Partnership 
Program (2009-00505 to WS) and Basic Science Research Program 
(2012R1A1A3008447 to WS) and SRC (MSIP No. 2011-0030775, 
2009-0070560, 2009-0070562 to SH) through the National Research 
Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education, 
Science and Technology, and by a grant from InAm Neuroscience 
Research Center (Sanbon Hospital, Wonkwang University, Korea). 
The research herein was also supported by a grant from the Korea </p>

<p>Health Technology R&amp;D Project (A092058 to SC) funded by the 
Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, and by a grant from the Biomembrane 
Plasticity Research Center (No. 20100029395 to SC) funded by the 
NRF of Korea. </p>

<p>1 Zimprich A, Biskup S, Leitner P, Lichtner P, Farrer M, Lincoln S et al. 
Mutations in LRRK2 cause autosomal-dominant parkinsonism with pleo-</p>

<p>
Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>



<p>Snapin as an LRRK2 kinase substrate 
HJ Yun et al </p>



<p>Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine </p>

</text></tei>