<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3694184" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Germanium biotite (GB) is an aluminosilicate mineral 
containing 36 ppm germanium. The present study was 
conducted to better understand the effects of GB on immune 
responses in a mouse model, and to demonstrate the 
clearance effects of this mineral against Porcine 
reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus (PRRSV) in 
experimentally infected pigs as an initial step towards the 
development of a feed supplement that would promote 
immune activity and help prevent diseases. In the mouse 
model, dietary supplementation with GB enhanced 
concanavalin A (ConA)-induced lymphocyte proliferation 
and increased the percentage of CD3+CD8+ T lymphocytes. 
In pigs experimentally infected with PRRSV, viral titers in 
lungs and lymphoid tissues from the GB-fed group were 
significantly decreased compared to those of the control 
group 
12 
days 
post-infection. 
Corresponding 
histopathological analyses demonstrated that GB-fed pigs 
displayed less severe pathological changes associated with 
PRRSV infection compared to the control group, indicating 
that GB promotes PRRSV clearance. These antiviral effects 
in pigs may be related to the ability of GB to increase 
CD3+CD8+ T lymphocyte production observed in the mice. 
Hence, this mineral may be an effective feed supplement for 
increasing immune activity and preventing disease. </p>

<p>Porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus 
(PRRSV), an Arterivirus, emerged in the late 1980s in the 
United States and Europe [24]. It quickly spread </p>

<p>worldwide and became enzootic among pig populations in 
most countries [24]. The virus strongly modulates host 
immune responses and changes host gene expression 
patterns. PRRSV inhibits the production of key cytokines, 
such as interferon (IFN)-α [2,3], and may induce the 
expression of regulatory cytokines including interleukin 
(IL)-10 [20]. Moreover, the appearance of neutralizing 
antibodies is delayed in pigs infected with PRRSV 
[4,16,23] and these animals are more prone to develop 
concomitant infectious diseases [10,19]. Data from these 
and other studies indicate that PRRSV causes 
immunosuppression in the affected pigs [5,15]. Therefore, 
strengthening the host defense mechanisms may be 
important for controlling PRRSV infection. 
Germanium biotite (GB) is an aluminosilicate mineral 
that contains 36 ppm germanium. This compound 
possesses a number of biological activities that are 
beneficial for animal health, especially immune function 
and host defense. A previous study reported that GB 
enhances the production of tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α 
in mouse spleen lymphocyte [11]. Continuous ingestion of 
the mineral also increases phytohemagglutinin 
(PHA)-induced cytokine expression and enhances 
antibody production in mice in a dose-dependent manner 
[9]. Moreover, dietary supplementation with GB expedites 
the clearance of porcine circovirus type 2 (PCV2) in 
experimentally infected pigs [9] as well as bovine 
herpesvirus type 1 (BHV1) clearance from experimentally 
infected calves [12]. These findings suggest that GB as a 
feed supplement can potentially protect against respiratory 
viral diseases through the potent stimulation of 
non-specific immune responses. However, the underlying 
immunological mechanisms remain unclear and 
anti-PRRSV effects of the mineral have not yet been </p>

<p>136 Bock-Gie Jung et al. </p>

<p>examined. 
The purpose of the present study was to better understand 
the effects of GB on immune responses in a mouse model, 
and to demonstrate the effects of this mineral on PRRSV 
clearance in experimentally infected pigs. Lymphocyte 
proliferation and changes in lymphocyte subpopulations in 
the mice were evaluated. In addition, PRRSV titers in lung 
and various lymphoid tissues of experimentally infected 
pigs were measured. This investigation was performed as 
an initial step towards the development of a feed 
supplement that increases immune activity and helps 
prevent diseases. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Source and composition of the GB feed supplement 
GB used in this study as a feed supplement was provided 
by Seobong Biobestech (Korea). The supplement was 
composed of silicon dioxide (SiO 2 , 61.90%), aluminum 
oxide (Al 2 O 3 , 23.19%), iron oxide (Fe 2 O 3 , 3.97%), sodium 
oxide (Na 2 O, 3.36%), and 36 ppm germanium. </p>

<p>Animals and animal care 
Specific pathogen-free female 6-week-old BALB/c mice 
(DBL, Korea) were used to investigate the effects of GB on 
host immune responses. The mice were randomly divided 
into three groups of eight mice each. The control group 
received a commercial, nutritionally complete, extruded 
dry rodent feed (Superfeed, Korea). The experiment 
groups received the same rodent feed supplemented with 
either 0.1% (0.1% GB-fed group) or 0.3% (w/w) GB (0.3% 
GB-fed group). 
Conventional 6-week-old pigs (Korea) were used to 
evaluate GB-mediated clearance of PRRSV. Prior to 
purchase, sera from the littermates were tested and the 
animals were confirmed to be negative for antibodies 
against PRRSV using a commercial enzyme-linked 
immunosorbent assay kit (IDEXX Laboratories, USA). 
The pigs were randomly divided into two groups of six pigs 
each. The control group received a commercial and 
nutritionally complete swine feed (Daehan Livestock and 
Feed, Korea). The experiment group received the same 
swine feed supplemented with 0.3% (w/w) GB. 
All animals were housed in an air-controlled separate 
room, and allowed free access to tap water and their 
particular diets. All animal procedures were approved (no. 
CNU IACUC-YB-2010-1) by the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use Committee of Chonnam National University 
(Korea). </p>

<p>Isolation of mouse lymphocytes 
The mice were fed the control or experimental diets for 2 
weeks. The animals were then sacrificed and the spleen was 
collected. The spleens were aseptically removed with </p>

<p>scissors and forceps, placed in cold phosphate-buffered 
saline (PBS), and single-cell suspensions were prepared by 
pushing the tissue through a 40-μm nylon mesh (BD 
Biosciences, USA). Erythrocytes in the cell mixture were 
destroyed by incubation with Tris-NH 4 Cl. The lymphocytes 
were washed with PBS twice prior to resuspension in 
complete medium consisting of RPMI-1640 medium 
(Lonza, Switzerland) containing 10% (v/v) fetal bovine 
serum (FBS; Gibco, USA) and 2% (v/v) 
antibiotic-antimycotic solution (Lonza, Switzerland). Live 
cells were detected by staining with trypan blue. </p>

<p>Measurement of lymphocyte proliferation in mice 
Mouse lymphocyte proliferation was measured as 
previously described [8]. Cell suspensions were diluted to 
a final concentration of 3 × 10 
6 cells/mL in complete 
medium. One hundred μL of the cell suspension and 100 
μL complete medium with or without 5 μg/mL 
concanavalin A (ConA; Sigma-Aldrich, USA) or 50 
μg/mL lipopolysaccharide (LPS; Sigma-Aldrich) were 
added into each well of a 96-well plate (SPL Life Sciences, 
Korea). The cultures were set up in duplicate. After a 48-h 
incubation at 37 
o C in a 5% CO 2 incubator, 20 μL of 
3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium 
bromide (MTT, 5 mg/mL; Sigma-Aldrich, USA) were 
added to each well and the plate was incubated for another 
4 h. The plate was then centrifuged at 2,000 × g for 10 min 
and the supernatants were discarded. A total of 200 μL 
dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO; Sigma-Aldrich, USA) was 
added to each well and the plate was shaken until the 
formazan crystals dissolved. The absorbance of each 
sample was read using a microplate spectrophotometer 
(Thermo Labsystems, Finland) at 540 nm. </p>

<p>Evaluation of mouse T lymphocyte subpopulations 
Immunofluorescent staining was performed to measure 
the CD3+CD4+ T and CD3+CD8+ T cell populations in 
the spleen of each sacrificed mouse as previously 
described [7]. Lymphocytes were stained with both 
phycoerythrin (PE)-conjugated hamster anti-mouse CD3 
(BD Biosciences, USA) and fluorescein isothiocyanate 
(FITC)-conjugated rat anti-mouse CD4 (BD Biosciences, 
USA) antibodies, or FITC-conjugated rat anti-mouse CD8 
antibody (BD Biosciences, USA). After incubating for 30 
min at room temperature in the dark, the cells were washed 
twice with PBS and the T lymphocyte subpopulations were 
analyzed using a FACSort flow cytometer (BD 
Biosciences, USA). Viable lymphocytes were gated 
according to forward and side-scatter characteristics 
(FSC/SSC), and 10,000 events were analyzed to evaluate 
FITC-and PE-positive signals. Results for each T 
lymphocyte subpopulation are expressed as percentages of 
events in the FSC/SSC lymphocyte gate. </p>

<p>Antiviral effects of germanium biotite 137 </p>

<p>Experimental PRRSV infection of pigs 
All pigs were fed the experimental or control diet for 2 
weeks before being experimentally infected with the virus. 
PRRSV was obtained from the Animal, Plant and Fisheries 
Quarantine and Inspection Agency (Korea). For the 
inoculum, a virus stock was propagated in confluent 
monolayers of MARC-145 cells as previously described 
[13]. Five mL of the viral culture (1 × 10 
6.1 50% tissue 
culture infective dose/mL) was administered intranasally 
through each nostril of the pigs. The rectal temperatures of 
pigs were measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, 12, 14, 21, 24, and 28 days 
post-infection (DPI). Three pigs from each group were 
randomly sacrificed at 12 and 28 DPI. Lung and lymphoid 
tissues (bronchial lymph node, tonsil, and thymus) were 
then collected. </p>

<p>Measurement of viral titers in tissues from PRRSV-
infected pigs 
Lung and lymphoid tissues were homogenized (10%, w/v) 
in minimum essential medium alpha modification 
(alpha-MEM; Welgene, Korea) containing 2% (v/v) 
antibiotic-antimycotic solution (Lonza, Switzerland). The 
tissues were homogenized using a Tissue Tearor 
homogenizer (Biospec Products, USA) and then 
centrifuged at 4,000 × g for 30 min at 4 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. The supernatant 
was passed through a nonpyrogenic syringe filter with 
0.2-μm pores (Pall Corporation, USA). The resulting 
suspensions were used as inocula to determine the viral titer 
using a plaque assay [14]. Briefly, each suspension was 
serially diluted 10-fold in alpha-MEM (Welgene, Korea) 
containing 2% (v/v) antibiotic-antimycotic solution (Lonza, 
Switzerland). One mL of each dilution was used to inoculate 
confluent monolayers of MARC-145 cells prepared in a 
6-well plate (SPL Life Sciences). The cells were incubated 
with the inoculum in 5% CO 2 at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 1 h with manual 
rocking every 10 min. The inoculum was then replaced with 
an overlay medium consisting of alpha-MEM (Welgene, 
Korea) supplemented with 5% (v/v) FBS (Lonza, 
Switzerland), 2% (v/v) antibiotic-antimycotic solution 
(Lonza, Switzerland), and 1.6% (w/v) carboxymethylcellulose 
sodium salt (Sigma-Aldrich, USA). The cells were further 
incubated for up to 5 days in 5% CO 2 at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C until plaques 
were clearly observed. After overnight fixation of the 
monolayers in 10% (v/v) neutral buffered formalin, the 
supernatant was removed and 1% (w/v) crystal violet 
(Sigma-Aldrich, USA) was added to each well. The plates 
were kept at room temperature for 30 min, washed with tap 
water until the excess crystal violet was removed, inverted 
over absorbent paper, and allowed to dry. The plaques were 
counted and viral titers are expressed as plaque forming 
unit (pfu)/gram tissue. Each sample was tested in duplicate. </p>

<p>Histopathologic analysis of tissues from PRRSV-
infected pigs 
Lung and lymphoid tissues were fixed in 10% 
neutral-buffered formalin, embedded in paraffin, cut into 
sections (5-μm thick), and stained with hematoxylin and 
eosin (H&amp;E) for histopathological examination. 
Microscopic lesions were evaluated using a previously 
described scoring system [18]. In sections of lung, the 
presence and severity of type 2 pneumocyte hypertrophy and 
hyperplasia, alveolar septal infiltration by inflammatory 
cells, peribronchial lymphoid hyperplasia, volume of 
alveolar exudate, and degree of inflammation in the lamina 
propria of the bronchi and bronchioles were scored on a scale 
ranging from 0∼6 (0, normal; 1, mild and multifocal; 2, mild 
and diffuse; 3, moderate and multifocal; 4, moderate and 
diffuse; 5, severe and multifocal; or 6, severe and diffuse). 
Sections of lymphoid tissues were evaluated for lymphoid 
depletion using a scale ranging from 0∼3 (0, normal; 1, mild 
lymphoid depletion with loss of overall cellularity; 2, 
moderate lymphoid depletion; and 3, severe lymphoid 
depletion with loss of lymphoid follicular structure) and the 
presence of inflammation with a scale ranging from 0∼3 (0, 
normal; 1, mild histiocytic-to-granulomatous inflammation; 
2, moderate histiocytic-to-granulomatous inflammation; 
and 3, severe histiocytic-to-granulomatous inflammation 
with replacement of follicles). Scores representing the 
microscopic lesion severity in sections of lymphoid tissues 
were calculated as the sum of the individual scores for both 
parameters. All histological evaluations were performed in a 
blinded manner. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
All data are expressed as the mean ± standard deviation 
(SD). A one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed 
by Tukey's multiple comparison tests was used to analyze 
results from the mouse model. Student's t-test was 
performed to analyze data from the swine experiments. A 
Mann-Whitney U test (nonparametric test) was also used 
to compare microscopic lesion scores (ordinal data) for 
tissues from the experimentally PRRSV-infected pigs. All 
statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS, USA</rs>). P-values ＜ 0.05 were 
considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Impact of GB on lymphocyte proliferation in mice 
Lymphocytes were incubated with or without mitogens 
(ConA or LPS) and lymphocyte proliferation was 
measured as the OD 540 value using an MTT assay. 
Lymphocyte proliferation in response to ConA was 
significantly enhanced (p ＜ 0.05) in the GB-fed groups 
(0.745 ± 0.084 and 0.762 ± 0.093 for the 0.1% and 0.3% </p>



<p>Fig. 1. Effects of germanium biotite (GB) on lymphocyte 
proliferation in mice. Lymphocytes were with or without 
mitogens (ConA or LPS), and lymphocyte proliferation was 
measured as OD540 using an MTT assay. Lymphocyte 
proliferation in response to ConA was significantly enhanced in 
the GB-fed mice compared to the control group (*p ＜ 0.05). 
However, proliferation of the unstimulated or LPS-treated 
lymphocytes did not differ among the groups. Data are presented 
the mean ± SD (n = 8). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effect of GB on rectal temperature in pigs experimentally 
infected with PRRSV. Mean rectal temperature of the pigs 
gradually increased up to 14 days post-infection (DPI) after 
which the temperature declined until the end of the experiment. 
Rectal temperature of the 0.3% GB-fed group was lower than that 
of the control group throughout the experimental period. In 
particular, the difference in rectal temperature between the two 
groups was statistically significant at 12 and 14 DPI (*p ＜ 0.05). 
Data are presented as the mean ± SD (0 ~ 12 DPI: n = six in each 
group, 14∼28 DPI: n = three in each group). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effect of GB on T lymphocyte subpopulation ratios in 
mice. The percentage of CD3+CD8+ T lymphocytes in the 
spleens of GB-fed mice was significantly increased compared to 
that observed for the control group (***p ＜ 0.001). However, no 
significant difference in the percentage of spleen CD3+CD4+ T 
lymphocytes was observed among the groups. Data are presented 
as the mean ± SD (n = 8). </p>

<p>GB-fed groups, respectively) compared to the control 
group (0.650 ± 0.044). However, proliferation of the 
unstimulated or LPS-treated lymphocytes did not vary 
among the groups (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Effects of GB on T lymphocyte subpopulations in mice 
Percentages of CD3+CD8+ T lymphocytes in spleens 
from the GB-fed groups (12.82 ± 1.39% and 13.96 ± 1.60% </p>

<p>for the 0.1% and 0.3% GB-fed groups, respectively) were 
significantly increased (p ＜ 0.001) compared to those 
observed in the control group (9.63 ± 0.61%). However, no 
significant differences in the percentages of CD3+CD4+ T 
lymphocytes in the spleen were observed among the 
groups (Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Rectal temperature of PRRSV-infected pigs 
Mean rectal temperature of the pigs gradually increased 
up to 14 DPI. The temperature subsequently declined until 
the end of the experiment. Rectal temperature of the 
GB-fed group was lower than that of the control group 
throughout the experimental period. In particular, a 
significant difference in rectal temperature (p ＜ 0.05) was 
observed between the groups at 12 and 14 DPI (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Viral titer of tissues from PRRSV-infected pigs 
At 12 DPI, viral titer of the lungs was significantly 
decreased (p ＜ 0.05) in the GB-fed group (3.19 ± 1.14 log 
pfu/g tissue) compared to the control group (5.73 ± 0.41 
log pfu/g tissue). Moreover, viral titers of the lymphoid 
tissues including bronchial lymph node, tonsil, and thymus 
were also significantly decreased (p ＜ 0.05) in the GB-fed 
group compared to the control group (Fig. 4). However, 
viral titers of lungs and lymphoid tissues from both groups 
were almost under the limit of detection (10 pfu/g tissue) at 
28 DPI (data not shown). </p>

<p>Antiviral effects of germanium biotite 139 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effects of GB on PRRSV clearance in experimentally 
infected pigs. At 12 DPI, the viral titer of lung (LUN) tissues 
from the 0.3% GB-fed pigs was significantly decreased 
compared that for the control group (*p ＜ 0.05). Moreover, viral 
titers of lymphoid tissues including bronchial lymph node 
(BLN), tonsil (TON), and thymus (THY) were significantly 
decreased in the 0.3% GB-fed animals compared to the control 
group (*p ＜ 0.05). Data are presented as the mean ± SD (n = 3). </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Histopathological features of lung and thymus, and 
microscopic lesion scores for tissue samples from 
PRRSV-infected pigs. Pigs fed 0.3% GB (B) had milder cases of 
interstitial pneumonia at 12 DPI (based on lung histopathological 
features) compared to the control animals (A). Additionally, 
lymphoid depletion was less severe in the 0.3% GB-fed group, 
and clearer separation between the cortex and medulla of the 
thymus (D) compared to the control group (C) was observed. 
Lung (LUN) microscopic lesion scores for pigs fed 0.3% GB 
were significantly decrease compared to those for the control 
group (*p ＜ 0.05). Moreover, microscopic lesion scores for the 
lymphoid tissues [bronchial lymph node (BLN), tonsil (TON), 
and thymus (THY)] from the 0.3% GB-fed group were lower 
than those for the control group although this difference was not 
significant. Scale bar = 100 μm. Data are presented as the mean 
± SD (n = 3). </p>

<p>Histopathologic analysis of tissues from PRRSV-
infected pigs 
At 12 DPI, the experimentally PRRSV-infected pigs 
developed interstitial pneumonia characterized by type 2 
pneumocyte hypertrophy and hyperplasia along with 
alveolar wall thickening by macrophages and 
lymphocytes. These lesions were milder in the GB-fed 
group (Fig. 5B) compared to the control group (Fig. 5A). 
Additionally, lymphoid depletion was less severe in the 
GB-fed animals, and clearer separation between the cortex 
and medulla of the thymus was observed (Fig. 5D) 
compared to the control group (Fig. 5C). Scores for 
microscopic lesions in the collected tissue samples are 
shown in Fig. 5E. Scores for the lung microscopic lesions 
in the GB-fed pigs were significantly decreased compared 
to ones for the control group (p ＜ 0.05). Moreover, scores 
for the lymphoid microscopic lesions in the GB-fed group 
were also lower compared to those for the control group 
although this difference was not significant. Lesions in the 
lungs and lymphoid tissues of both groups were almost 
fully healed at 28 DPI (data not shown). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, dietary supplementation with GB 
enhanced ConA (T-cell mitogen)-induced lymphocyte 
proliferation in mice. This finding was consistent with data 
from our previous study showing that GB markedly 
increases the ability of PHA (a T-cell mitogen) to induce 
cytokine expression in mice [9]. Furthermore, the 
CD3+CD8+ T lymphocyte ratio was significantly </p>

<p>increased in the spleens of mice fed GB compared to those 
of the control group. In contrast, the CD3+CD4+ T 
lymphocyte ratio did not vary between the groups in the 
present study. These results imply that dietary GB 
supplementation enhances immune responses and the 
proliferation of T lymphocytes, especially CD3+CD8+ 
cells. Previous studies have demonstrated that </p>

<p>140 Bock-Gie Jung et al. </p>

<p>aluminosilicate, the main component of GB, acts as a 
non-specific immunostimulant similar to superantigens 
[1,22], a class of extremely potent T cell mitogens [21]. It 
is also well known that germanium activates T 
lymphocytes, especially cytotoxic T cells [6]. Collectively, 
observations from the present study and data from the 
literature indicate that dietary supplementation with GB 
mainly affects CD3+CD8+ T lymphocytes. 
In the current investigation, dietary supplementation with 
GB alleviated high fever in pigs experimentally infected 
with PRRSV throughout the experimental period. 
Moreover, the viral titer for lungs from the GB-fed group 
was significantly decreased at 12 DPI compared to that for 
the control group; however, viral titers for both groups 
were under the limit of detection at 28 DPI. Similar trends 
were also observed in all tested lymphoid tissues. 
Histopathological analysis also revealed that GB 
supplementation resulted in less severe abnormal changes 
associated with PRRSV infection compared to the control 
group. These results imply that dietary supplementation 
with GB promotes PRRSV clearance in experimentally 
infected pigs. This is consistent with findings from our 
previous studies showing that GB enhances the clearance 
of respiratory viruses such as PCV2 and BHV1 in 
experimentally infected pigs and calves [9,12]. It is 
generally accepted that CD8+ cytotoxic T lymphocytes 
inhibit the replication of intracellular pathogens like 
viruses by secreting soluble mediators that interfere with 
pathogen replication and/or induce the death of infected 
cells [17]. Therefore, the antiviral activities of GB may be 
related to the CD3+CD8+ T lymphocyte stimulatory 
effects observed in the mice. 
In summary, findings from the present investigation 
suggest that dietary supplementation with GB primarily 
stimulates CD3+CD8+ T lymphocyte proliferation in mice 
and expedites the clearance of PRRSV in experimentally 
infected pigs. Hence, GB may serve as a feed supplement 
that promotes immune activity and helps prevent disease. 
However, the effects of GB on immune responses in swine 
were not assessed in the present study. Additionally, the 
exact mechanisms underlying virus clearance promoted by 
GB were not identified. Further experiments need to be 
performed to understand effects of GB on immune 
responses and virus clearance in pigs. PRRSV clearance 
following GB administration should also be measured in 
pigs with naturally occurring cases of PRRS. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research was supported by the Technology 
Development Program for Agriculture and Forestry, 
Ministry for Food, Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, 
Korea. A graduate fellowship was also provided by the 
Korean Ministry of Education and Human Resources </p>

<p>Development through the Brain Korea 21 Project. </p>



</text></tei>