<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3641357" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Despite initial and often dramatic responses of epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR)-addicted lung tumors to the EGFR-specific 
tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs), gefitinib and erlotinib, nearly all develop resistance and relapse. To explore novel mechanisms 
mediating acquired resistance, we employed non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) cell lines bearing activating mutations in EGFR and 
rendered them resistant to EGFR-specific TKIs through chronic adaptation in tissue culture. In addition to previously observed 
resistance mechanisms including EGFR-T790M 'gate-keeper' mutations and MET amplification, a subset of the seven chronically 
adapted NSCLC cell lines including HCC4006, HCC2279 and H1650 cells exhibited marked induction of fibroblast growth factor (FGF) 
2 and FGF receptor 1 (FGFR1) mRNA and protein. Also, adaptation to EGFR-specific TKIs was accompanied by an epithelial to 
mesenchymal transition (EMT) as assessed by changes in CDH1, VIM, ZEB1 and ZEB2 expression and altered growth properties in 
Matrigel. In adapted cell lines exhibiting increased FGF2 and FGFR1 expression, measures of growth and signaling, but not EMT, were 
blocked by FGFR-specific TKIs, an FGF-ligand trap and FGFR1 silencing with RNAi. In parental HCC4006 cells, cell growth was strongly 
inhibited by gefitinib, although drug-resistant clones progress within 10 days. Combined treatment with gefitinib and AZD4547, an 
FGFR-specific TKI, prevented the outgrowth of drug-resistant clones. Thus, induction of FGF2 and FGFR1 following chronic adaptation 
to EGFR-specific TKIs provides a novel autocrine receptor tyrosine kinase-driven bypass pathway in a subset of lung cancer cell lines 
that are initially sensitive to EGFR-specific TKIs. The findings support FGFR-specific TKIs as potentially valuable additions to existing 
targeted therapeutic strategies with EGFR-specific TKIs to prevent or delay acquired resistance in EGFR-driven NSCLC. </p>

<p>progression on EGFR-targeted therapies is 8-10 months. 11,12 
Multiple mechanisms of acquired resistance to EGFR-targeted 
inhibitors have been discovered and validated in patients. 
Secondary gate-keeper mutations, which increase EGFR-ATP 
binding affinity, occur in 50% of patients whose tumors progress 
on EGFR-specific TKIs. 13 In addition, MET amplification following 
treatment with EGFR inhibitors has been reported in B5-15% of 
NSCLC patients. 12,14,15 EGFR-T790M and MET-amplified tumor cells 
can be detected in tumors before EGFR-targeted therapies, 
suggesting these cells are selectively enriched upon treatment. 
Furthermore, detection of either T790M or amplified MET with 
HGF expression before EGFR TKI treatment is associated with 
decreased duration of response to EGFR-targeted treatments. 16,17 
Interestingly, both of these resistance mechanisms retain 
downstream signaling through the AKT pathway. Also, Sequist 
et al. 12 found a small percentage of patients who acquire PI3KCA 
mutations post EGFR TKI therapy, further highlighting the 
PI3K-AKT pathway as a survival pathway in NSCLC with gain-of-
function EGFR. Importantly, this same study failed to detect 
acquired mutations in B30% of TKI-resistant lung tumors. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Craniofacial Biology, School of Dental Medicine, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO, USA; 2 Department of Medicine, 
University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO, USA and 3 Department of Pediatrics, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO, USA. 
Correspondence: Dr LE Heasley, Department of Craniofacial Biology, School of Dental Medicine, University of Colorado Denver Anschutz Medical Campus, Mail Stop 8120, 
PO Box 6511, Aurora, CO 80045, USA. 
E-mail: Lynn.Heasley@ucdenver.edu 
Received 13 August 2012; revised 23 January 2013; accepted 3 February 2013 </p>

<p>Citation: Oncogenesis (2013) 2, e39; doi:10.1038/oncsis.2013.4 
&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 2157-9024/13 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/oncsis </p>

<p>We hypothesize that alternative receptor tyrosine kinases that are 
neither mutated nor amplified may contribute to acquired 
resistance to EGFR-targeted therapies. As precedent, induction 
of AXL has been recently demonstrated during in vitro and in vivo 
acquired resistance to EGFR-specific TKIs in lung cancer. 18,19 
Alternative receptor tyrosine kinases, also referred to as 'bypass 
pathways', have been identified as mechanisms of both intrinsic 
and acquired resistance to targeted therapeutics including EGFR 
TKIs. 20-24 Compared with resistance via acquisition of gate-keeper 
mutations, acquired resistance mechanisms involving induction of 
distinct signaling pathways lacking genetic alterations are less 
documented in the literature. To date, the insulin-like growth 
factor 1 receptor and AXL has been demonstrated to have a role in 
acquired resistance to gefitinib. 18,19,25,26 Recently, we reported the 
protective role of rapidly upregulated fibroblast growth factor 
receptor 2 (FGFR2) and FGFR3 in response to gefitinib treatment in 
NSCLC with either wild-type or mutant EGFR. 27 In the present 
study, we deployed standard chronic adaptation techniques 
previously described in the literature 12,14,15 to develop EGFR-
mutant NSCLC cell lines with acquired resistance to gefitinib. 
Herein, we demonstrate that FGFR1 and FGF2 are induced during 
chronic acquisition of resistance to gefitinib, highlighting FGFR1 as </p>

<p>an additional candidate for a bypass mechanism contributing to 
EGFR inhibitor resistance. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Establishment and characterization of gefitinib-resistant NSCLC 
cell lines 
In vitro modeling of acquired resistance to EGFR-specific TKIs has 
identified resistance mechanisms also observed in patients upon 
tumor progression on erlotinib and gefitinib. For example, HCC827 
cells undergo MET amplification and AXL induction upon adaption 
to gefitinib 14,15,17,19 and PC9 cells acquire the T790M mutation in 
EGFR that confers resistance to erlotinib and gefitinib. 13 In 
addition, studies with TKI-resistant tumor specimens suggest 
alternative mechanisms that remain to be defined. 12 To further 
explore mechanisms which mediate gefitinib resistance, a panel of 
eight NSCLC cell lines (Supplementary Table S1) with EGFR-
activating mutations rendering them sensitive to EGFR-targeted 
therapies were adapted to increasing concentrations of gefitinib 
until they could be cultured in 3 mM gefitinib (see Materials and 
methods). In addition, H1975 cells, which express EGFR bearing 
the activating L858R mutation and the T790M gate-keeper </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>H C C 8 2 7 </p>

<p>D R D R D R D R D R D R D R </p>

<p>200 
FGF2 Protein </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>FGF2 (pg/μg protein) 
50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>FGFR1 </p>

<p>pEGFR </p>

<p>EGFR </p>

<p>Nak ATPase 
α-subunit </p>

<p>D=DMSO Control R=TKI resistant </p>

<p>H C C 4 0 0 6 
H C C 2 2 7 9 
H 1 9 7 5 
H 1 6 5 0 
P C 9 
H C C 4 0 1 1 </p>

<p>H 
C 
C 
8 2 7 </p>

<p>H 
C 
C 
4 0 0 6 
H 
C 
C 
2 2 7 9 
H 
1 6 5 0 
H 
C 
C 
4 0 1 1 
P C </p>

<p>-9 
H 
1 9 7 5 </p>

<p>10 
Relative FGFR1 mRNA 
Expression </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>FGFR1 mRNA </p>

<p>Control 
Gefitinib-resistant 
BIBW2992-resistant </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>H 
C 
C 
8 2 7 </p>

<p>H 
C 
C 
4 0 0 6 
H 
C 
C 
2 2 7 9 
H 
1 6 5 0 
H 
C 
C 
4 0 1 1 
P C </p>

<p>-9 
H 
1 9 7 5 </p>

<p>2000 
Relative FGF2 mRNA 
4000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>8000 </p>

<p>10000 </p>

<p>FGF2 mRNA </p>

<p>Control 
Gefitinib-resistant </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>DMSO 
Gefitinib-resistant 
BIBW2992-resistant </p>

<p>H 
C </p>

<p>C 
8 2 7 </p>

<p>H 
C </p>

<p>C 
4 0 0 6 
H 
C </p>

<p>C 
2 2 7 9 
H 
1 6 5 0 
H 
C 
C 
4 0 1 1 
P C </p>

<p>-9 
H 
1 9 7 5 </p>

<p>Figure 1. FGFR1 and FGF2 are induced following adaption of EGFR-dependent NSCLC cell lines to EGFR-specific TKIs. (a, b) Total RNA was 
purified from the indicated cell lines following chronic adaption to a reversible EGFR inhibitor (gefitinib 3 mM) or irreversible EGFR inhibitor 
(BIBW2992 2 mM) that inhibits EGFR-T790M and submitted to quantitative RT-PCR analysis of (a) FGFR1 or (b) FGF2. The data are presented as 
relative expression following normalization for GAPDH expression. Statistical analysis by t-test revealed significant increases in mRNA 
expression where *indicates Po0.05, **indicates Po0.01 and ***indicates Po0.001. (c) Cell lysates from the indicated NSCLC cell lines resistant 
to 3 mM gefitinib or 2 mM BIBW2292 (R) or DMSO-treated passage control (d) were immunoblotted for FGFR1, phospho-EGFR-Y1046, EGFR and 
the a subunit of the NaK-ATPase as a loading control. (d) The cell extracts from panel C were submitted to measurement of FGF2 protein by 
ELISA using a commercially available kit (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA). The levels of FGF2 are presented as picograms per mg of 
cellular protein. </p>

<p>FGF2 and FGFR1 mediate EGFR-specific TKI resistance 
KE Ware et al </p>



<p>Oncogenesis (2013), 1 -9 
&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>mutation, were selected for resistance to the irreversible EGFR 
inhibitor, BIBW2992. 28 All TKI-resistant and passage control cell 
lines were submitted to DNA fingerprint analysis to verify 
authenticity, both before and after adaptation. As shown in 
Supplementary Figure S1 and Supplementary Table S2, the 
gefitinib-adapted cell lines exhibited IC 50 s to EGFR TKIs that were 
several orders of magnitude larger than that exhibited by the 
DMSO-cultured control cell lines. Of note, gefitinib-resistant 
cultures of HCC2935 cells were not obtained after two-indepen-
dent attempts and this cell line was not studied further. In general, 
gefitinib-resistant cell lines demonstrated decreased phospho-
EGFR expression as compared with passage controls cells, 
although total EGFR did not change significantly (Figure 1c). In 
addition, EGFR mRNA sequences were amplified by PCR to verify 
retention of EGFR gain-of-function mutations (E746-A750 del, 
L747-A750 del, L858R) and to detect any acquired T790M 
mutations. Consistent with published studies, our findings reveal 
that gefitinib-resistant PC9 cells acquired a T790M gate-keeper 
mutation and gefitinib-resistant HCC827 cells exhibited markedly 
increased MET expression levels 13-15,17 (Supplementary Figures S2 
and S3). Moreover, gefitinib-resistant PC9 cells retained sensitivity 
to BIBW2992 as predicted (Supplementary Figure S2) and 
gefitinib-resistant HCC827 cells exhibited acquired sensitivity to 
the MET inhibitor, crizotinib, as assessed by inhibition of phospho-
MET and reduction of anchorage-independent growth 
(Supplementary Figure S3). Interestingly, H1650, H1975, 
HCC2279, HCC4006 and HCC4011 cells neither acquired T790M 
mutations nor exhibited MET amplification (data not shown). </p>

<p>RNA-seq reveals FGF2 and FGFR1 as a novel pathway of acquired 
resistance to EGFR-specific TKIs 
To explore novel mechanisms involved in EGFR-specific TKI 
resistance, mRNA from control and adapted HCC4006 and 
HCC827 cells was submitted to RNA-seq analysis by genome 
analyzer-based deep sequencing. The resulting analysis confirmed 
the marked increase in MET mRNA expression in gefitinib-resistant 
cultures of HCC827, 13-15,17 but not HCC4006 cells (Supplementary 
Table S3). However, RNA-seq analysis of the HCC4006 cells 
revealed 2.5-and 9-fold increases in the expression of FGF2 and 
FGFR1 mRNAs in gefitinib-resistant cells, respectively. Neither MET </p>

<p>nor ErbB family members, EGFR and ErbB2, exhibited any changes 
in expression (Supplementary Table S2). A recent report identifies 
amplification of MAPK1 as a putative mechanism of resistance to 
EGFR TKIs. 29 Our data indicate a modest increase (B2-fold) in 
MAPK1 (ERK2) mRNA in gefitinib-resistant HCC4006 cells, although 
this was accompanied by a reduction in MAPK3 (ERK1) mRNA 
expression (Supplementary Table S3). Moreover, no significant 
increases in ERK2 protein or activity are apparent in our TKI-
adapted cell lines (see Figure 2, Supplementary Figures S2 and S6). 
To test if induction of FGFR1 and FGF2 occurred in additional cell 
lines, the panel of control and gefitinib-resistant NSCLC cell lines 
was submitted to quantitative RT-PCR and immunoblot analyses 
for FGFR1 and FGF2 mRNA (Figures 1a and b) and protein levels 
(Figures 1c and d). TKI-resistant cultures of HCC4006, HCC2279, 
H1650 and H1975 cells, and to a lesser extent, HCC4011 cells, 
exhibited significantly increased levels of FGFR1 mRNA (Figure 1a) 
and protein (Figure 1c). Of these, adapted cultures of HCC4006, 
HCC2279, H1650 and HCC4011 cells also exhibited increased 
expression of FGF2 mRNA (Figure 1b) and protein (Figure 1d). 
Combined, the findings suggest that FGF2 and FGFR1 may 
comprise an acquired autocrine growth loop in gefitinib-resistant 
cultures of HCC4006, HCC2279, HCC4011 and H1650 cells. 
Although gefitinib-resistant H1975 cells exhibit increased FGFR1 
levels, FGF2 mRNA was not detected. </p>

<p>Gefitinib-resistant HCC4006, HCC2279 and H1650 cells are FGFR1-
dependent for growth and proliferation 
To analyze the dominant growth pathways in gefitinib-resistant 
NSCLC cell cultures, control and gefitinib-resistant cultures of 
HCC4006, HCC2279 and H1650 were treated for 2 h with inhibitors 
of EGFR (lapatinib, gefitinib), EGFR-T790M (BIBW2992), FGFRs 
(AZ8010 and R04383596 30,31 ) or MET (crizotinib) and phospho-ERK 
and phospho-AKT were measured as downstream signaling 
targets. In the DMSO-adapted cell cultures, phospho-ERK and 
phospho-AKT-T308 were decreased or abolished following 
treatment with the EGFR-targeted TKIs, lapatinib, gefitinib and 
BIBW2992 (Figure 2, Supplementary Figures S4 and S6). In 
addition, phosphorylation of EGFR on Y1068 was also inhibited 
(Supplementary Figures S5 and S6). By contrast, these TKIs had no 
effect on phospho-ERK or phospho-AKT-T308 levels in the </p>

<p>pERK </p>

<p>pAKT 
(S473) </p>

<p>pAKT 
(T308) </p>

<p>AKT </p>

<p>ERK </p>

<p>HCC4006 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>M 
S O 
L a p a t i n i b 
B I B W </p>

<p>2 9 9 2 </p>

<p>C 
r i z o t i n i b 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
R O 
4 3 8 3 5 9 6 
D </p>

<p>M 
S O 
L a p a t i n i b 
B I B W </p>

<p>2 9 9 2 </p>

<p>C 
r i z o t i n i b 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
R O 
4 3 8 3 5 9 6 
D </p>

<p>M 
S O 
L a p a t i n i b 
B I B W </p>

<p>2 9 9 2 </p>

<p>C 
r i z o t i n i b 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
R O 
4 3 8 3 5 9 6 
D </p>

<p>M 
S O 
L a p a t i n i b 
B I B W </p>

<p>2 9 9 2 </p>

<p>C 
r i z o t i n i b 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
R O 
4 3 8 3 5 9 6 </p>

<p>Resistant </p>

<p>H1650 </p>

<p>Control 
Resistant </p>

<p>Figure 2. Effect of TKIs on ERK and AKT phosphorylation in control and gefitinib-resistant HCC4006 and H1650 cells. (a, b) HCC4006 and H1650 
control (DMSO) or gefitinib-resistant cells were treated for 2 h with inhibitors: Reversible EGFR inhibitor (lapatinib/gefitinib, 1 mM), irreversible 
EGFR inhibitor (BIBW2992, 0.1 mM), FGFR inhibitors (AZD8010, 0.3 mM, RO4383596, 1 mM) or Met inhibitor (crizotinib, 0.2 mM). Cell lysates were 
immunoblotted for phospho-ERK and phospho-AKT-T308 and phospho-AKT-S473 as indicated. The filters were stripped and reprobed for 
total ERK1/2 and AKT as loading controls. The phospho-AKT-T308 blot was submitted to densitometry and a graphical presentation is shown 
in Supplementary Figure S4. </p>

<p>FGF2 and FGFR1 mediate EGFR-specific TKI resistance 
KE Ware et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Oncogenesis (2013), 1 -9 </p>

<p>gefitinib-resistant cell lines (Figure 2, Supplementary Figure S6). 
Instead, phospho-ERK in the gefitinib-resistant cultures of 
HCC4006, HCC2279 and H1650 cells was reduced or abolished 
by the FGFR1-specific TKI, AZ8010, and the FGFR-active TKI, 
RO4383596 (Figure 2 and Supplementary Figure S4). Importantly, 
FGFR inhibitors failed to effect phosphorylation of either T308 or 
S473 on AKT, indicating that the induced FGFR1 pathway does not 
significantly engage the PI3K/AKT signal pathway. In addition, the 
FGFR inhibitor, AZ8010, did not inhibit ERK phosphorylation in 
gefitinib-resistant PC9 (Supplementary Figure S2) or HCC827 cells 
(Supplementary Figure S3), consistent with EGFR-T790M or MET 
functioning as the major drivers in these two cell lines. 
Next, control and gefitinib-resistant HCC4006 cells were 
submitted to anchorage-independent growth assays and prolif-
eration assays in the presence of lapatinib, BIBW2992 and AZ8010. 
Anchorage-independent growth of control HCC4006 cells was 
potently inhibited by lapatinib and BIBW2992 (Figure 3a, 
Supplementary Figure S1), but not by AZ8010. By contrast, 
gefitinib-resistant HCC4006 cells were highly sensitive to 
AZ8010, but the two EGFR inhibitors were without effect </p>

<p>(Figure 3a, Supplementary Figure S1). The FGF trap, FP-1039, 32 
completely inhibited growth of gefitinib-resistant HCC4006 cells, 
but not control cells (Figure 3b), indicating a requirement for 
induced FGF2 for growth of the gefitinib-adapted cell cultures. As 
a molecular test of the requirement for FGFR1 in gefitinib-resistant 
HCC4006 cells, both control and gefitinib-resistant HCC4006 cells 
were transiently transfected with an FGFR1-targeting small 
interfering RNA (siRNA) or a non-silencing control siRNA. The data 
in Supplementary Figure S7 demonstrate effective silencing of 
FGFR1 mRNA, but not FGFR2 mRNA. Moreover, significant 
inhibition of cell proliferation was observed in response to 
transfection of the FGFR1 siRNA into gefitinib-resistant, but not 
control HCC4006 cells. Combined, the data indicate that HCC4006 
cells switch from EGFR dependency to dependency on FGFR1 and 
FGF2 following acquired resistance to gefitinib. 
We similarly tested the sensitivity of the panel of control and 
gefitinib-resistant cell lines to gefitinib/BIBW2992 and AZ8010. The 
findings in Figures 3c and d, Supplementary Figure S1 and 
Supplementary Table S2 demonstrate that HCC2279 and H1650 
also undergo a switch in sensitivity from EGFR-specific TKIs to the </p>

<p>0 
0.01 
0.1 </p>

<p>TKI, μM </p>

<p>1 
0.01 
0.1 </p>

<p>AZ8010, μM </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 
Colony Number (% Untreated) 
Colony Number (% Control) </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Control-Lapatinib </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Resistant-Lapatinib </p>

<p>Resistant-BIBW2992 </p>

<p>Resistant </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>FP-1039 </p>

<p>Control-BIBW2992 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>0 
Control 
Resistant </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>HCC4006 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>D 
M 
S O </p>

<p>L a p a t i n i b 
B I B W </p>

<p>2 9 9 2 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
D 
M 
S O </p>

<p>L a p a t i n i b 
B I B W </p>

<p>2 9 9 2 
A G 
1 4 8 
A Z 8 0 1 0 </p>

<p>A Z 8 0 1 0 + A G </p>

<p>1 4 7 8 D 
M 
S O </p>

<p>L a p a t i n i b 
B I B W </p>

<p>2 9 9 2 
A G 
1 4 8 
A Z 8 0 1 0 </p>

<p>A Z 8 0 1 0 + A G </p>

<p>1 4 7 8 
D 
M 
S O </p>

<p>L a p a t i n i b 
B I B W </p>

<p>2 9 9 2 
A Z 8 0 1 0 </p>

<p>20 
*** *** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** *** *** 
*** </p>

<p>40 
Cell Number 
(Percent Untreated) 
Cell Number 
(Percent Untreated) </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>DMSO Control 
Gefitinib Resistant </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>H1650 </p>

<p>DMSO Control 
Gefitinib Resistant </p>

<p>ns 
ns ns </p>

<p>HCC2279 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Gefitinib-resistant HCC4006, H1650 and HCC2279 cell cultures are dependent on FGFR signaling for cell growth. (a) HCC4006 control 
and gefitinib-resistant cells were analyzed for anchorage-independent growth. Cells were treated with increasing concentrations of the EGFR 
reversible inhibitor, lapatinib (0, 0.03, 0.05, 0.1, 0.3, 1 mM), the irreversible EGFR inhibitor, BIBW2992 (0, 0.03, 0.05, 0.1, 0.3, 0.5 mM), and the FGFR 
inhibitor AZ8010 (0, 0.03, 0.05, 0.1, 0.3, 0.5 mM). (b) HCC4006 control and gefitinib-resistant cells were analyzed for anchorage-independent 
growth with 0.1 mg/ml FGF-ligand trap (FP-1039). (c) HCC2279 control (DMSO) and gefitinib-resistant cells were analyzed for cell proliferation 
by cell counts after 7 days of treatment with DMSO or inhibitors: (1 mM, lapatinib, 0.1 mM BIBW2992 or 0.3 mM AZ8010. D) H1650 control (DMSO) 
and gefitinib-resistant cells were analyzed for proliferation as above except with the addition of EGFR inhibitor AG1478 (0.1 mM). Statistical 
analysis by two-way ANOVA revealed significant decreases in cell growth where *indicates Po0.05, **indicates Po0.005 and ***indicates 
Po0.001. </p>

<p>FGF2 and FGFR1 mediate EGFR-specific TKI resistance 
KE Ware et al </p>



<p>Oncogenesis (2013), 1 -9 
&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>FGFR-specific TKIs. Control HCC4011 cells were already somewhat 
sensitive to AZ8010 (IC 50 ¼ 84 nM) and gefitinib-resistant HCC4011 
cells were only slightly more sensitive (IC 50 ¼ 33 nM), a finding that 
is consistent with detectable levels of FGFR1 and FGF2 in control 
HCC4011 cells (Figure 1). To test whether treatment with FGFR 
inhibitors induced measures of apoptosis, control and adapted 
HCC827, HCC4006 and H1650 cells were cultured with gefitinib or 
AZ8010 for 3 days and cells were collected for measurement of 
caspase 3 activity as a biochemical measure of apoptosis. The data 
in Supplementary Figure S8 demonstrate a marked increase (B12-
fold) in caspase 3 activity in DMSO control cultures of HCC827 cells 
treated with gefitinib, but only a 1.5-fold increase in caspase 3 
activity in gefitinib-resistant HCC827 cells treated with gefitinib. 
Neither DMSO control cultures of H1650 nor HCC4006 cells 
exhibited evidence for induction of apoptosis following treatment 
with gefitinib. Gefitinib-resistant cultures of H1650 cells exhibited 
a modest (B1.3-fold) increase in caspase 3 activity in response to 
AZ8010 treatment, but gefitinib-resistant cultures of HCC4006 
cells showed no increase in caspase 3 activity following FGFR 
inhibitor treatment (Supplementary Figure S8). Thus, the findings 
are consistent with a cytostatic, not a proapoptotic, activity of 
FGFR inhibitors in gefitinib-adapted cell lines. </p>

<p>Evidence for cellular reprogramming in gefitinib-resistant NSCLC 
cells with induced FGFR1 
In addition to upregulation of FGFR1 and FGF2, RNA-seq analysis 
of HCC4006 cells revealed decreased mRNA expression of the </p>

<p>epithelial genes E-cadherin (CDH1) and junctional plakoglobin 
(JUP), as well as increased expression of the mesenchymal 
markers, vimentin, ZEB1, ZEB2 and N-cadherin (CDH2), in 
gefitinib-resistant 
cultures 
relative 
to 
control 
cells 
(Supplementary Table S3). This presumptive epithelial to 
mesenchymal transition (EMT) is not universal to the acquired 
resistance response as these changes were not observed in TKI-
adapted HCC827 cells (Supplementary Table S3). However, 
reduced E-cadherin protein expression was observed in gefiti-
nib/BIBW2992-resistant cultures of HCC4006, H1650 and H1975 
cells (Figure 4a). HCC2279 cells lacked E-cadherin protein before 
adaptation. In addition, vimentin protein levels were increased in 
gefitinib-resistant cultures of HCC4006, HCC2279, H1650 and 
HCC4011 cells. These changes in EMT markers correlate with 
phenotypic differences in HCC4006 control and gefitinib-resistant 
cells grown in Matrigel containing medium, where gefitinib-
resistant HCC4006 cells form unorganized structures in Matrigel 
relative to organized spheres produced by control HCC4006 cells 
(Figure 4b). Thus, the findings in Supplementary Table S3 and 
Figure 4 indicate that acquisition of gefitinib resistance in a subset 
of the EGFR-specific TKI-resistant cell lines is accompanied by an 
EMT program that includes induction of FGFR1 and FGF2 
expression. 
To test the role of FGFR1 signaling as the potential driver of the 
EMT program in these cells, HCC4006 control and gefitinib-
resistant cell cultures were treated with AZ8010 or DMSO for 1, 3 
or 6 days and E-cadherin protein expression was measured. 
As shown in Figure 4c, AZ8010 treatment did not restore </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>R 
D 
R 
D 
R </p>

<p>D=DMSO Control R=TKI resistant </p>

<p>HCC4006-DMSO </p>

<p>Day 1 
Day 3 
Day 6 
Day 1 
Day 3 
Day 6 </p>

<p>HCC4006-Resistant </p>

<p>D 
R 
D 
R 
D 
R 
D 
R </p>

<p>E-cadherin </p>

<p>HCC4006-DMSO </p>

<p>HCC4006-Resistant </p>

<p>Vimentin </p>

<p>Na + /K + ATPase 
α-subunit </p>

<p>E-cadherin </p>

<p>Na + /K + ATPase </p>

<p>H C C 8 2 7 
H C C 4 0 0 6 
H C C 2 2 7 9 
H 1 9 7 5 
H 1 6 5 0 
P C 9 
H C C 4 0 1 1 </p>

<p>D 
M 
S O 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
D 
M 
S O 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
D 
M 
S O 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
D 
M 
S O 
A Z 8 0 1 0 
D 
M 
S O 
A Z 8 0 1 0 D </p>

<p>M 
S O 
A Z 8 0 1 0 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Induction of EMT in EGFR TKI-resistant NSCLC cell lines is associated with induction of FGFR1. (a) Cell lysates from the indicated 
NSCLC cell lines resistant to 3 mM gefitinib or 2 mM BIBW2292 (R) or DMSO-treated passage control (d) were immunoblotted for E-cadherin, 
vimentin and the a subunit of the NaK-ATPase as a loading control. (b) HCC4006 DMS0 and gefitinib-resistant cells were plated in media 
containing 2% Matrigel and allowed to form colonies over 7 days. Colonies were imaged at Â 100 magnification using a Nikon Eclipse TS100 
camera. (c) HCC4006 control and gefitinib-resistant cells were treated 1, 3 or 6 days with DMSO or 0.3 mM AZ8010. Cell lysates were 
immunoblotted for E-cadherin and the a-subunit of NaK-ATPase as a loading control. </p>

<p>FGF2 and FGFR1 mediate EGFR-specific TKI resistance 
KE Ware et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Oncogenesis (2013), 1 -9 </p>

<p>E-cadherin expression in the gefitinib-adapted HCC4006 cultures, 
indicating that FGFR1 signaling is not directly regulating 
E-cadherin expression. In addition, H1975 cells rendered resistant 
to BIBW2992 also undergo an EMT response (Figure 4a and 
Sequist et al. 12 ), but do not establish a functional FGFR1-driven 
autocrine loop. Therefore, FGFR1, FGF2, E-cadherin and vimentin 
are likely to be co-regulated in a transcriptional program 
mediating resistance and suggest potential value for identifying 
patients who might respond to FGFR-targeted therapies following 
progression on EGFR inhibitors. Further supporting our findings of 
co-regulated FGFR1 and mesenchymal genes, a study examining 
metastasis in NSCLC found FGFR1 expression to be a poor 
prognostic marker for metastasis (hazard ratio of 43). 33 Another 
group found both FGFR1 and vimentin to positively correlate with 
ZEB1 expression in NSCLC, 34 consistent with the gene changes 
reported in our study (Supplementary Table S3). 
Finally, a prediction of the results presented thus far is that 
combined treatment of EGFR-driven NSCLC cell lines with gefitinib 
and an FGFR-specific TKI would yield superior growth inhibition. 
As shown in Supplementary Figure S9, a clonogenic growth assay 
shows greater reduction in the emergence of TKI-resistant 
HCC4006 cells following treatment with gefitinib plus AZD4547, 
an FGFR-specific TKI, 35 relative to gefitinib alone. Likewise, 
inhibition of anchorage-independent growth of H1650 cells by 
gefitinib was markedly enhanced by inclusion of AZ8010. 
The data support the increased efficacy of combinations 
of EGFR and FGFR-specific TKIs for inhibiting growth of EGFR-
mutant cell lines that employ FGFR1 as an acquired resistance 
mechanism. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Acquired resistance has emerged as a major limitation of 
monotherapy with TKIs. 22,36 EGFR-targeted therapies can 
significantly improve disease control in EGFR-mutant NSCLC 
patients, but the response is short-lived. To this end, many 
studies defining mechanisms of resistance to EGFR-targeted 
therapies have been reported, and technological advances in 
genome-based medicine have led to the identification of distinct 
resistance mechanisms including acquisition and amplification of 
EGFR-T790M mutations, selection for PIK3CA mutations, and MET 
and MAPK1 amplification. 12,29,37 However, B30% of acquired 
resistance cases lack identifiable mutations 12 and thus, may rely 
on mutation-independent mechanisms of resistance. In support of 
this hypothesis, we used a previously validated approach 
involving chronic adaption of NSCLC cell lines to increasing 
concentrations of gefitinib 12,14,15 and identified a subgroup of 
EGFR-mutant NSCLC cell lines that undergo cellular 
reprogramming accompanied by induction of an FGFR1-FGF2 
autocrine signaling pathway. FGFR signaling is sufficient to drive 
transformed growth as evidenced by the findings that gefitinib-
resistant cells are growth arrested by FGFR-specific TKIs, an FGF-
ligand trap and RNAi-mediated FGFR1 silencing. Notably, the 
failure of FGFR-specific TKIs to markedly increase apoptosis in lung 
cancer cell lines bearing an induced FGF2-FGFR1 pathway 
suggests that FGFR inhibitors may yield stable disease, not 
tumor regressions, if these drugs are deployed to target this 
mechanism of resistance to EGFR-specific TKIs. 
Using a chronic resistance model, we demonstrate that co-
induction of FGFR1 and FGF2 occur in concert with dramatic 
cellular reprogramming leading to multiple EMT-associated gene 
changes (Figure 4 and Supplementary Table S3). This finding is in 
support of previous observations that an EMT phenotype is 
associated with both intrinsic and acquired resistance to EGFR-
specific TKIs in NSCLC cell lines (including H1975, HCC4006 and 
H1650). 12,21,38-40 Moreover, we have significantly expanded these 
observations by demonstrating that FGFR1 and FGF2 function as 
the 'driver' of growth, but not EMT, in these adapted cell lines. </p>

<p>Thus, these findings provide an example distinct from MET of how 
an alternative receptor tyrosine kinase can serve as a bypass 
growth pathway in NSCLC cell lines rendered resistant to EGFR-
specific TKIs. Similar to our findings demonstrating induction of 
FGFR1 in gefitinib-resistant HCC4006, HCC2279 and H1650, AXL 
has also been shown to be induced in gefitinib-resistant HCC827 
cells and in human tumors that have progressed on erlotinib. 19 
Although we observe induction of MET, but not AXL, in our 
cultures of gefitinib-resistant HCC827 cells (Supplementary Figure 
S10), we detect induction of AXL mRNA in HCC4006, HCC2279, 
H1650, PC9 and H1975 cells. Except for PC9, induction of AXL 
mRNA following acquired resistance to EGFR-specific TKIs is 
associated with an EMT program. Importantly, Byers et al. 18 have 
demonstrated that AXL induction is also associated with an 
acquired resistance-induced EMT program. Despite the induction 
of AXL simultaneous with FGFR1, our data support FGFR1 as the 
dominant bypass growth driver in HCC4006, HCC2279 and H1650 
cells based on sensitivity to FGFR inhibitors and the lack of growth 
and signaling inhibition by crizotinib (Figure 2, Supplementary 
Figures S2 and S6), a TKI which exhibits activity against AXL. 41,42 
Clearly, elucidation of the underlying molecular pathways and 
their prevalence in human lung tumor biopsies post progression 
with EGFR-specific TKIs will be critical for a full understanding of 
acquired resistance. Evidence of cellular reprogramming as a 
mechanism to relieve EGFR dependency during EGFR-targeted 
therapy has been observed in clinical samples. 12 In fact, it may be 
a common means to escape multiple types of treatment. For 
example, analysis of multiple serial biopsies of one patient 
demonstrated transdifferentiation from EGFR-dependent NSCLC 
to small-cell lung cancer following erlotinib therapy and back to 
EGFR-dependent NSCLC following treatment with a cytotoxic 
therapy appropriate for small-cell lung cancer. 12 The tumor re-
sensitized to EGFR-targeted therapy only after treatment with 
chemotherapy and radiation for small-cell lung cancer revealing 
the ability of cancer cells to reprogram as a mechanism for cell 
survival. The EGFR mutation was identified in all biopsies 
indicating the tumors arose from a common clone. 12 
In support of epigenetic alterations as common mechanisms of 
resistance, Sharma et al. 26 demonstrated that drug resistant 
persister cells readily arise in vitro following treatment, regardless 
of the oncogene being targeted. Importantly, an HDAC inhibitor 
reduced the outgrowth of drug resistant persister cells, 
presumably through disrupting the necessary chromatin 
remodeling-dependent gene expression changes. The EMT 
phenotype observed upon acquired resistance to EGFR-targeted 
therapy appears to be exclusively observed in the subset lacking 
identified mutations. 12,39 Therefore, HCC4006, H1650 and 
HCC2279 cells could be potentially used to develop an 
expression signature predictive of tumors that undergo 
epigenetic reprogramming as a mechanism of resistance and as 
a biomarker for patients that would benefit from EGFR-FGFR 
combination therapies. 
Although there is increasing support that epigenetic mechan-
isms of resistance are prevalent in response to targeted therapies, 
it is well known that other cancer cells are predisposed to 
pathways involving genetically acquired resistance mechanisms 
(mutation and amplifications). In fact, germline mutations not 
specific to tumor cells that occur in the host can be important in 
predicting response. A germline deletion of the proapoptotic 
protein BIM poises tumor cells for survival when confronted by the 
relevant TKI in CML and NSCLC, thus serving a crucial role in how a 
tumor responds to treatment. 43 Therefore, a more thorough 
understanding of a patient tumor's mutation status (germline and 
somatic) and epigenetic volatility will be relevant in designing 
treatment regimens to prevent resistance to targeted therapies. 
Although FGFR1 and FGF2 induction as a mechanism of resistance 
has not yet been verified in clinical samples from matched pre-
and post-treatment biopsies, in vitro studies with NSCLC cell lines </p>

<p>FGF2 and FGFR1 mediate EGFR-specific TKI resistance 
KE Ware et al </p>



<p>Oncogenesis (2013), 1 -9 
&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>thus far have been consistent with established in vivo mechanisms 
of resistance. 15,44,45 A phase I clinical trial (NCT01515969) 
combining erlotinib and the FGFR TKI, dovitinib, in metastatic 
NSCLC will give retrospective information on patients who 
respond to EGFR-FGFR combination treatment. The molecular 
heterogeneity of oncogene drivers in NSCLC, which demands 
flexibility in treatment regimens, will likely be recapitulated in 
resistance mechanisms to targeted therapies. Therefore, rational 
treatment regimens entailing combinations of TKIs must be 
founded on extensive molecular understanding of the tumors. 
Finally, the history of therapeutics for infectious diseases such as 
HIV and TB demonstrates that long-term disease management 
occurs by preventing resistance rather than treating resistance. 22 
Consistent with the advantages of treating with combinations of 
inhibitors at onset, clinical benefit from treating lung cancer 
patients that progress on erlotinib with irreversible EGFR inhibitors 
or MET inhibitors has been rather modest. 46,47 Based on the 
findings in this study and the increased efficacy of combined EGFR 
and FGFR inhibitors on specific NSCLC cell lines (Supplementary 
Figure S8), if supported by future demonstration of increased 
FGF2 and FGFR1 in lung tumor biopsies following progression on 
EGFR inhibitors, we suggest that treatment with combinations of 
EGFR and FGFR inhibitors may be superior to sequential treatment 
with an FGFR inhibitor. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Cell culture </p>

<p>H1650, H1975, HCC827, HCC2279, HCC4006 and PC9 cells were obtained 
from the University of Colorado Cancer Center Tissue Culture Core and 
HCC4011 and HCC2935 cells were purchased from ATCC (Manassas, VA, 
USA). The passage controls and TKI-adapted cell lines used in this study 
were submitted to fingerprint analysis to verify their authenticity relative to 
established sources and to demonstrate that the control and TKI-resistant 
cultures were genetically equivalent. All cell lines were routinely cultured in 
RPMI-1640 growth medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum 
(Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) at 37 1C in a humidified 5% CO 2 incubator. 
Resistant cell population were cultured with the addition of 3 mM gefitinib 
or 2 mM BIBW2992. </p>

<p>In vitro adaptation of gefitinib-resistant cell lines </p>

<p>Cells were serially passaged initially with low concentrations of gefitinib or 
BIBW2992 (5 nM) and sequentially cultured in increasing concentrations of 
these TKIs. Cells were considered resistant when they could be routinely 
cultured in growth medium containing 3 mM gefitinib or 2 mM BIBW2992. </p>

<p>Three-dimensional matrigel growth </p>

<p>For three-dimensional growth experiments, 5000 control and gefitinib-
resistant HCC4006 cells were suspended in RPMI-1640 media containing 
2% Matrigel and overlaid on a base layer of 50% Matrigel containing 
RPMI-1640 media in 8-well Tissue Tek II chamber slides. Wells were covered 
with 100 ml growth media and allowed to form colonies over a week. 
Colonies were imaged at Â 100 magnification using a Nikon Eclipse TS100 
camera. </p>

<p>RNA-seq analysis </p>

<p>Total RNA purified from two-independent cultures of DMSO passaged 
control and gefitinib-resistant cultures of HCC4006 cells and HCC827 cells 
was used to prepare cDNA for sequencing with the Illumina Genome 
Analyzer IIx using the Illumina mRNA sequencing preparation kit 
(San Diego, CA, USA). Sequenced reads were mapped against hg19 
using <rs type="software">Tophat</rs> and transcripts were assembled against ensemble reference 
using <rs type="software">Cufflinks</rs>. Expression is reported as fragments per kilobase transcript 
per million reads (FPKM). Data were submitted to applied bias correction 
and quartile normalization. </p>

<p>Quantitative Real-Time PCR (RT-PCR) </p>

<p>Total RNA (5 mg) was reverse transcribed in a volume of 20 ml using Maxima 
First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Fermentas, Glen Burnie, MD, USA). Aliquots </p>

<p>(1 ml) of 5-fold diluted reverse transcription reactions were subjected to 
PCR in 25 ml reactions with SYBR green Jumpstart Taq Readymix (Sigma) 
and primers previously described for FGFR1 and FGF2 24 using a My iQ real-
time PCR detection system (BioRad, Hercules, CA, USA). AXL mRNA was 
measured by quantitative RT-PCR using a TaqMan Gene Expression Assay 
primer/probe set (no.HS01064444) from Applied Biosystems (Carlsbad, CA, 
USA). GAPDH mRNA levels were measured by quantitative RT-PCR in 
replicate samples as a housekeeper gene for normalization and the data 
are presented as 'Relative Expression'. </p>

<p>Anchorage-independent growth and cell proliferation assays </p>

<p>For measurement of anchorage-independent cell growth, 50 000 cells 
(HCC4006, control or gefitinib resistant) were suspended in 1.5 ml RPMI 
1640 containing 10% fetal bovine serum and 0.35% Difco agar noble 
(Becton Dickinson and Co., Sparks, MD, USA) and overlaid on base layers 
containing 1.5 ml RPMI 1640 containing 10% fetal bovine serum and 0.5% 
agar noble in six-well plates. The wells were covered with 2 ml growth 
medium containing drugs. This media was replaced with fresh media 
containing drugs every 7 days. The plates were incubated in a 37 1C CO 2 
incubator for 21 days after which viable colonies were stained for 24 h with 
200 ml of 1 mg/ml nitroblue tetrazolium. Following digital photography, the 
colony number was quantified using the <rs type="software">MetaMorph</rs> imaging software 
program. 
For measurement of proliferation, 10 000 control or gefitinib-resistant 
cells were plated in 500 ml RPMI 1640 containing 10% fetal bovine serum in 
24-well plates or 20 000 HCC2279 control or gefitinib-resistant cells were 
plated in 1 ml RPMI 1640 containing 10% fetal bovine serum in 12-well 
plates. Cells were allowed to attach overnight, then treated with the 
indicated drug treatments and cultured over 7 days. Following trypsiniza-
tion, viable cells were counted with a Cellometer (Nexcelom, Lawrence, 
MA, USA) and compared with untreated cell number for each cell line and 
presented as percent control. In some experiments (Supplementary Figure 
S1), cell proliferation was determined using the CyQUANT assay. DMSO 
and resistant cells were seeded at 100 cells per well in 96-well tissue 
culture plates and treated in triplicate with inhibitors at various doses for 7 
days. Relative cell numbers were measured using a CyQUANT Direct Cell 
Proliferation Assay (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, USA) according to 
the manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>RNAi-mediated silencing of FGFR1 </p>

<p>Control and gefitinib-resistant HCC4006 cells were plated at 100 000 cells 
per 35 mm dish. The next day, the cells were transfected (16 h) with 12 nM 
of an FGFR1-targeting siRNA (5 0 -phos TGGTATTAACTCCAGCAGTCTT-
CAAGA-3 0 ) or a non-silencing control siRNA using HiPerfect reagent from 
Qiagen (Valencia, CA, USA). The cells were fed with fresh growth medium 
and total RNA was prepared following 3 days of culture and FGFR1 mRNA 
was measured by quantitative RT-PCR. Replicate dishes were further 
cultured for a total of 7 days and cell number was determined by direct cell 
counting. </p>

<p>Immunoblot analyses </p>

<p>For analysis of specific phosphorylation status of signaling proteins in 
response to drug treatment, cells were seeded in six-well dishes to allow 
cell attachment. After 24 h, cells were treated with DMSO, 1 mM lapatinib or 
gefitinib, 0.1 mM BIBW2992, 0.3 mM AZ8010, 1 mM RO4383596 or 0.2 mM 
crizotinib for 2 h. Cells were collected in 1 ml phosphate-buffered saline, 
centrifuged at 1000 g for 5 min, lysed in MAP kinase lysis buffer (MKLB; 
0.5% Triton X-100, 50 mM b-glycerophosphate (pH 7.2), 0.1 mM Na 3 VO 4 , 
2 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM DTT, 0.3 M NaCl, 2 mg/ml leupeptin and 4 mg/ 
ml aprotinin) and centrifuged (5 min at 13 000 r.p.m.). The particulate 
fractions were discarded, aliquots of the extracts were mixed with SDS 
sample buffer and submitted to SDS-PAGE. Following electrophoretic 
transfer onto nitrocellulose, the filters were blocked in 3% bovine serum 
albumin (Cohn Fraction V, ICN Biomedicals, Inc., Aurora, OH, USA) in Tris-
buffered saline with 0.1% Tween 20 (TTBS) and then incubated with 
antibodies to phospho-ERK, phospho-AKT-T308, phospho-AKT-S473, phos-
pho-EGFR-Y1068 or phospho-MET-Y1234/1235 (Cell Signaling Technology, 
Inc.; Danvers, MA, USA) for 16 h at 4 1C. The filters were washed thoroughly 
in TTBS, then incubated with alkaline phosphatase coupled goat anti-rabbit 
or mouse antibodies and developed with LumiPhos reagent (Pierce, 
Rockford, IL, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The filters 
were subsequently stripped and reprobed for total ERK1 and ERK2, AKT, 
EGFR or MET. For immunoblot analysis of FGFR1, the a subunit of the NaK-</p>

<p>FGF2 and FGFR1 mediate EGFR-specific TKI resistance 
KE Ware et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Oncogenesis (2013), 1 -9 </p>

<p>ATPase, vimentin and E-cadherin, NSCLC cells were collected in phosphate-
buffered saline, centrifuged (5 min, 1000 g) and suspended in MKLB. 
Aliquots of the cell lysate preparations containing 150 mg of protein were 
submitted to SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted for FGFR1 (Origene, Rockville, 
MD, USA no.TA301021), a-subunit NaK-ATPase (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, 
Dallas, TX, USA), vimentin (Sigma, no.V6630), or E-cadherin (BD Biosciences, 
San Jose, CA, USA, no.610182). </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was supported by NIH grants P50 CA58187 and R01 CA127105. The 
funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, 
or preparation of the manuscript. DNA sequencing and cell line fingerprinting were 
performed through the University of Colorado Cancer Center Molecular Pathology 
shared resource facility. The completion of the deep sequencing for the RNA-seq 
analysis was performed by the University of Colorado Next-Generation Sequencing 
Development Core. Investigational drugs were provided through materials transfer 
agreements with AstraZeneca and Five Prime Therapeutics. </p>





<p>Oncogenesis (2013), 1 -9 
&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>





<p>&amp; 2013 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Oncogenesis (2013), 1 -9 </p>

</text></tei>