<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3293421" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>Pre-determining fetal sex is against the random and equal opportunity that both conceptus 
sexes have by nature. Yet, under a wide variety of circumstances, populations shift their birth 
sex ratio from the expected unity. Here we show, using fluorescence in situ hybridization, that in 
a population of pygmy hippopotamus (Choeropsis liberiensis) with 42.5% male offspring, males 
bias the ratio of X-and Y-chromosome-bearing spermatozoa in their ejaculates, resulting in 
a 0.4337 ± 0.0094 (mean ± s.d.) proportion of Y-chromosome-bearing spermatozoa. Three 
alternative hypotheses for the shifted population sex ratio were compared: female counteract 
male, female indifferent, or male and female in agreement. We conclude that there appears 
little or no antagonistic sexual conflict, unexpected by prevailing theories. our results indicate 
that males possess a mechanism to adjust the ratio of X-and Y-chromosome-bearing 
spermatozoa in the ejaculate, thereby substantially expanding currently known male options 
in sexual conflict. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1700 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 3:697 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1700 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2012 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>oth male and female gametes are produced through the process 
of meiosis. It is usually assumed that because an equal number 
of X-and Y-chromosome-carrying spermatozoa are produced 
during spermatogenesis 1 , any observed shift from a 1:1 sex ratio 
among offspring must be the result either of differences in the fer-
tilizing ability of the two gamete types 2,3 or cryptic female choice 4 . 
Factors such as population density 5 , female social status 6 , female 
body condition or resource availability 7 and stress 8 are known to 
'shift' sex ratios away from the expected equal birth sex ratio, but the 
biological mechanism through which a mammal (humans included) 
can and will bias offspring sex ratio is still unknown. 
Noting the difference between the sexes in terms of investment in 
offspring and the benefits gained thereby, it has been assumed that 
owing to its usually much larger investment, the female has con-
siderably more to win or lose, and if mechanisms to bias offspring 
sex ratios do exist, they would be operated by the female 9 . Hence, 
both empirical and theoretical work has traditionally concentrated 
on the female and dismissed any potential paternal contribution as 
minor and irrelevant. 
Still, it is surprising how small is the number of studies that have 
evaluated the ratio between the X-and Y-chromosome-bearing 
spermatozoa, the so-called 'primary sex ratio' . Most available stud-
ies, conducted on samples from boar 10 , cattle 10-14 or humans 15-17 , 
used inaccurate evaluation techniques such as fluorescence stain-
ing of the F-body or PCR amplification on pooled semen samples. 
Correlation between the ratio in the ejaculate and the birth sex 
ratio was found in those studies that made the comparison 12,16,17 . 
The few studies that were based on the more accurate fluorescence 
in situ hybridization (FISH) evaluation technique 18-20 either suf-
fered from a considerably smaller sample size compared with their 
control (176 samples compared with the pooled national data on 
birth sex ratio from several European countries and the United 
States) and counted too few cells to detect a sex ratio variation (only 
200 cells per ejaculate) 18 , dealt with samples obtained from infertile 
patients (where actually an excess of X-chromosome-bearing sper-
matozoa was detected) 19 , or had too small sample size to detect a 
small difference (N = 7 compared with N = 12) 20 . 
As offspring sex is the result of the combined inputs of both 
parents and their interaction, three scenarios of sexual conflict can 
be envisaged: antagonistic interests, one sex neutral or coinciding 
interests. Under the first scenario, if it is in the male interest to bias 
sex ratio in favour of females, the female interest might be to bias 
the sex ratio in favour of male offspring, for instance by activating 
mechanisms that increase fertilization by Y-chromosome-bearing 
spermatozoa or by selective death of female embryos. If selection 
intensity is equal or in favour of the females, male and female inputs 
would be likely to cancel each other out and result in a sex ratio 
at birth of ~0.5, or higher. In the second scenario, there is either a 
lower selection pressure on the females to counteract male interests 
or the females' interests are neutral with respect to the male interest. 
In this case, the female input will be ~0.5. According to the third 
scenario, male and female interests coincide and there is effectively 
no sexual conflict. In this case, both male and female input should 
be shifted in the same direction. 
The endangered pygmy hippopotamus (Choeropsis liberiensis), an 
endemic species to waterways and forests of West Africa in Sierra 
Leone, Guinea, Ivory Coast and Liberia, resembles the common 
hippopotamus but is much smaller in size. It is a long-lived, soli-
tary species where the sexes only meet for mating and where males 
defend territories, sometimes in fierce fights with competing males, 
which may have fatal consequences 21 . While little is known about 
their reproduction in the wild, the captive population reproduces 
well. In the captive population, offspring sex ratio is shifted towards 
an excess of females-at birth only 41% of offspring were reported 
to be males 22 . The cause of this shift and the mechanism by which it 
is achieved are unknown. </p>

<p>While most sex ratio skews investigated to date were believed 
to be due to the female, this study was designed to challenge this 
assumption by showing that male-based offspring sex ratio-shifting 
mechanism may also exist. We therefore investigated semen sam-
ples obtained from pygmy hippopotamus males and found the ratio 
of X-and Y-chromosome-bearing spermatozoa in these samples to 
be similar to the sex ratio at birth, as derived from an examination 
of the most recent data on the captive pygmy hippopotamus popu-
lation 23 . Using both sources of information, we derived the likely 
influence of any female post-copulatory mechanism to assess the 
direction and strength of male and female biases in terms of sexual 
conflict. Our analysis suggests the existence of little or no antagonis-
tic sexual conflict in the study population where males seem to pos-
sess a mechanism to actively shift the sex ratio in their ejaculates. </p>

<p>Results 
Fluorescence in situ hybridization. After applying FISH, sper-
matozoa from all individuals were successfully painted with the 
X-and Y-chromosome-specific dyes. Accordingly, the mean sex 
ratio of all samples was biased in favour of X-chromosome-bearing 
spermatozoa, as the mean proportion of Y-chromosome-bearing 
spermatozoa was 0.4337 (s.d. = 0.0094, Wilcoxon signed-ranks test, 
P = 0.005, N = 10, Table 1). The sex ratio of the sampled sperm was 
skewed towards an excess of X-chromosome-bearing spermatozoa 
in all individuals and significantly differed from the expected ratio 
of 0.5 (binomial test, P &lt; 0.00001 in all cases, Table 1). Plotting 
ejaculated sperm sex ratio against bull age showed no correlation 
(Spearman correlation coefficient = − 0.152, P = 0.674). 
FISH efficiency, evaluated as the ratio of stained cells to the total 
number of cells counted, was 97.61 ± 1.65% (mean ± s.d.; N = 10). The pro-
portion of ambiguous staining was 1.43 ± 0.85% (mean ± s.d.; N = 10). </p>

<p>Studbook analysis. The 2008 pygmy hippopotamus studbook lists 
1,089 captive births between 1919 and 2008. Of these, 32 births 
were of infants with unknown sex. The sex ratio of all captive births 
of known sex was 0.4248 (449 males out of 1057 births), signifi-
cantly lower than the expected unity (binomial test, P &lt; 0.0001) but 
similar to the observed ratio between X-and Y-chromosome-bear-
ing spermatozoa observed in this study (binomial test, one-tailed, 
P = 0.290). The sex ratio of animals that survived to the age of 5 years 
was 0.3829 (242 males out of 632 captive born pygmy hippopot-
ami surviving to adulthood), significantly lower than the expected 
0.5 ratio (binomial test, P &lt; 0.0001). Thirty nine percent (425/1,089) 
of all captive born individuals died before the age of 5 years. The </p>

<p>Table 1 | Numbers and proportion of X-and Y-chromosome-
bearing spermatozoa in the ejaculates of individual pygmy 
hippopotamus bulls. </p>

<p>Bull 
Y* 
X* 
Y/(X + Y) 
P † </p>

<p>1 
876 
1143 
0.4339 
&lt; 0.00001 
2 
951 
1325 
0.4178 
&lt; 0.00001 
3 
854 
1194 
0.4170 
&lt; 0.00001 
4 
918 
1186 
0.4363 
&lt; 0.00001 
5 
881 
1129 
0.4383 
&lt; 0.00001 
6 
931 
1206 
0.4357 
&lt; 0.00001 
7 
959 
1203 
0.4436 
0.00001 
8 
939 
1223 
0.4343 
&lt; 0.00001 
9 
935 
1215 
0.4349 
&lt; 0.00001 
10 
899 
1121 
0.4450 
&lt; 0.00001 
mean 
0.4337 
0.005 ‡ </p>

<p>* The number of X-or Y-chromosome-bearing spermatozoa, respectively, as identified by 
fluorescence in situ hybridization (FIsH). 
 † Binomial test, exact cumulative probabilities, two-tailed, against the expected ratio of 0.5. 
 ‡ Wilcoxon signed-ranks test, two-tailed, using the proportion of Y-chromosome-bearing 
spermatozoa against the expected ratio of 0.5. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1700 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 3:697 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1700 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2012 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>studbook lists 72 wild-born males and 85 wild-born females, a ratio 
of 0.4586, not different from unity (binomial test, P = 0.338). There 
are 130 living males listed in the studbook, 103 of them are adults 
being over five years old. 
The current captive pygmy hippopotamus population has 61 
founders, 44.39 of their genomes still survive. The average inbreed-
ing coefficient of the population is 0.0666, with gene diversity of 
0.9699 and mean kinship coefficient of 0.0301. Mean kinship coeffi-
cient of the individual males in this study ranged between 0.012 and 
0.053 (Table 2). There was no correlation between individual mean 
kinship coefficient and its sperm sex ratio (Spearman correlation 
coefficient = − 0.322, P = 0.361, N = 9). 
Of the ten males participating in this study, three never sired off-
spring (Table 2). Comparison of offspring sex ratio of the other bulls 
to the expected 0.5 found no differences in any of them (binomial 
test, P&gt;0.05 for all). </p>

<p>Evaluation of sexual conflict scenarios. Evaluations of the three 
possible scenarios were made with reference to the observed popu-
lation sex ratio at birth: antagonistic interests, one sex neutral and 
coinciding interests. 
For antagonistic interests, if selection intensity is equal or in 
favour of females, the observed male input of 0.4337 (95% confi-
dence interval (CI): 0.4270-0.4404) and female input would be 
likely to cancel each other out and result in a sex ratio at birth of 
~0.5, or higher. This would require a female bias in the order of 
0.5663 (95% CI: 0.5366-0.5963) or higher. The observed sex ratio at 
birth of 0.4258 is significantly below that. 
For one sex neutral, the female input will be ~0.5 (95% CI: 
0.4704-0.5306). In combination with the male input of 0.4337 (95% 
CI: 0.4270-0.4404), the resulting sex ratio would be in the range 
of 0.4487-0.4855, approaching or significantly higher than the 
observed sex ratio (binomial test, one-tailed, P = 0.063 for lower 
value and P = 0.00004 for higher value). 
For coinciding interests, the male and female inputs are shifted in 
the same direction. Given the observed male input of 0.4337 (95% CI: 
0.4270-0.4404), the required female bias to produce the observed 
population sex ratio (0.4248) is 0.4159 (95% CI: 0.3869-0.4462). </p>

<p>Discussion 
The results indicate that male and female interests most probably 
converged and that both male (0.4337) and female (0.4159) biases 
in sex allocation result in the production of an excess of female off-
spring. Although remote (P = 0.063 for lower CI value), the possibil-
ity that the female is neutral to the outcome and the bias is by the 
males only cannot be ruled out. It is also possible that the females 
cannot counter the males' skew because the selective pressure on the </p>

<p>captive population did not act long enough to produce a response. 
Owing to the small number of offspring produced by each male, no 
shifts from the expected 0.5 sex ratio were or could be detected. 
A comparison of these skewed sex ratios in the captive popula-
tion with data from free-ranging populations is currently not pos-
sible, as there are no data from wild populations. Such data will be 
difficult to obtain because male and female pygmy hippopotamus 
have no external distinctive features. The next best comparison is 
a comparison of sex ratios of wild-born male and female pygmy 
hippopotami in the international studbook. The observed ratio of 
0.4586 among wild-caught animals in the population did not sig-
nificantly differ from the expected 0.5. Hidden selection bias may 
exist in the probability of catching males or females, as is the case for 
instance in cheetahs 25 , or in post-capture selection. 
In the study population, the already skewed secondary sex ratio 
was further biased in favour of females at adulthood because male 
infants and juveniles were more likely to die than their female coun-
terparts. This results in an even stronger female-biased sex ratio at 
adulthood of 0.3829 and a significantly lower sex ratio than the ratio 
of wild-born pygmy hippopotami in the captive population (bino-
mial test, one-tailed, P &lt; 0.0001). 
Why should males opt to produce more females? If a male is long-
lived, the ownership of a territory being a pre-condition to mating 
success, and the habitat is saturated with occupied territories, then 
sons are unlikely to find an empty territory and are likely to compete 
with their fathers for territory ownership. Under such conditions, 
fathers have an interest in directing the sex of the progeny in a direc-
tion that will enable it to increase its own reproductive success and 
avoid father-son competition. 
How could males decide on producing more females? In order 
to alter the ratio of X-and Y-chromosome-bearing spermatozoa 
in their ejaculate, male pygmy hippopotami would benefit from 
a mechanism activated by environmentally induced stimuli. One 
possible stimulus previously shown to induce a sex ratio bias in 
favour of females is high population density 5 . There is currently 
no information on densities of free-ranging pygmy hippopotamus 
populations in their natural habitat. They are known to live mostly 
a solitary life in and around the streams and swamps of the densely 
forested regions of West Africa 26 , with the two sexes joining only 
for mating. At other times, male-male or male-female encounters 
often take an aggressive course and fighting may lead to severe inju-
ries and death 21 . When in captivity, animals are usually housed in 
the same enclosure. Even when males and females are separated 
from each other, they would still have visual, olfactory or auditory 
contact with nearby animals. The captive enclosure and proximity 
to other pygmy hippopotami may convey a sense of high population 
density, thereby possibly activating mechanisms that could induce a 
shift in sex ratio. Female-biased sex allocation by both parents sug-
gests that females are the dispersing sex in pygmy hippopotamus. 
Thus, by producing more females, parents could reduce competition 
over local resources 7 . 
Other possible causes can also be envisioned. Scrotal heat stress 
was shown to produce a bias in the resulting foetus sex ratio in mice 
if mating took place on the day of heat stress, though it had no effect 
on epididymal sperm sex ratio 27 . In our study, scrotal heat stress can 
be ruled out for several reasons: in hippopotami there is no scro-
tum and the testes descend only as far as the inguinal canal so they 
are less affected by environmental temperature changes. All males 
evaluated for this study reside in zoos in the temperate zone, and 
heat stress was not an issue on or around any of the collection days. 
Furthermore, pygmy hippopotamus enclosures in all zoos contain 
a wallowing pool where animals can immerse to cool themselves 
when needed. Finally, whatever effect heat stress might have, it 
is not on the ratio between X-and Y-chromosome-bearing sper-
matozoa but rather on survival of the embryos/foetuses. Another 
possible mechanism is the correlation reported in humans between </p>

<p>Table 2 | Individual bull information. </p>

<p>Bull 
Age 
Mean kinship 
coefficient </p>

<p>Birth origin 
Offspring 
P </p>

<p>1 
17 
0.021 
CB 
7.1 
ns 
2 
20 
0.031 
CB 
0.1 
ns 
3 
17 
0.053 
CB 
5.5.3 
ns 
4 
34 
0.012 
CB 
0 
5 
18 
nA 
CB 
1.3 
ns 
6 
40 
0.049 
CB 
13.5 
ns 
7 
9 
0.032 
CB 
1.0 
ns 
8 
12 
0.03 
CB 
0 
9 
31 
0.016 
CB 
1.2 
ns 
10 
15 
0.03 
CB 
0 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CB, captive born; nA, not available; ns, not significant; offspring are listed as 
'male.Female' or 'male.Female.offspring of unknown sex'. 
Evaluation of offspring sex ratio by the binomial test, exact cumulative probabilities, two-tailed, 
against the expected ratio of 0.5 found no difference in any of the males (P &gt; 0.05 for all). </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1700 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 3:697 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1700 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2012 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>paternal age and offspring sex ratio 28,29 . Evaluation of the sampled 
sperm sex ratio against bulls' age in the present study found no such 
correlation. Inbreeding might be yet another possibility. Inbreed-
ing is known to cause a decline in sperm quality 30 and thus might 
also affect its sex ratio. The captive pygmy hippopotamus, however, 
cannot be considered highly inbred having an average inbreeding 
coefficient of 0.0666 and gene diversity of 0.9699 31 . Evaluation of 
the mean kinship coefficient of the males in this study against their 
sperm sex ratio found no such correlation. Coital rate was also 
reported to affect offspring sex ratio 32,33 . High coital rate, how-
ever, is not an issue in pygmy hippopotami as males and females 
are often housed separately to avoid between-individual aggression. 
Finally, the issue of stress should also be considered. It was shown, 
for instance in humans, that offspring sex ratio declines when the 
parents are subjected to chronic 34 or acute 8 stress. Causes for such 
stress, including the perception of high population density men-
tioned above or other issues related to captivity, might exist in the 
study population though it has never been evaluated. Regardless of 
what the cause might be, and even if the reasons for the bias in male 
and female sex allocation may not be the same in this population, 
the outcome is in agreement. 
Spermatozoa carrying X-chromosome or Y-chromosome show 
very small or no phenotypic differences 35 . Regardless of whether 
the observed shift in ejaculated and epididymal sperm sex ratio has 
an adaptive or non-adaptive explanation, our data suggest the exist-
ence of a mechanism that selectively favours or eliminates sperma-
tozoa of a specific type. What this mechanism might be can only be 
speculated on at this stage. Possible mechanisms that can be con-
sidered include selective removal during spermatogenesis, meiotic 
drive, selective apoptosis or selective epididymal sperm phagocy-
tosis. Although a single male cannot provide any concrete answer, 
the fact that the ratio found in epididymal sperm was similar to that 
found in ejaculated sperm suggests that when looking for such a 
mechanism, we should concentrate on the testes and whatever takes 
place in them. If this mechanism is not unique to the pygmy hip-
popotamus but an integral part of male mammalian reproduction 
at large, it may provide an alternative explanation for a number of 
sex ratio shifts, such as the excess in human male births 36 , which 
hitherto have been explained by female cryptic choice. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Animals. Sperm was collected from captive pygmy hippopotami by electroejacu-
lation as part of a general assessment of reproductive health (N = 9) or from the 
cauda epididymis following euthanasia (N = 1). These ten males constitute 10% 
of the entire world captive adult male population in this species. Semen assess-
ment results, reported elsewhere 24 (and Table 1 therein), demonstrated that the 
ejaculates were of good to excellent quality. Ages of the males ranged between 9 
and 40 years. </p>

<p>Materials. Unless otherwise mentioned, all materials were of reagent grade or 
higher, and were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Chemie GmbH, Taufkirchen, 
Germany. </p>

<p>Anaesthesia. All semen electroejaculation collection procedures were conducted 
under general anaesthesia. Animals were injected in the neck muscles by remote 
darts with a combination of medetomidine (Zalopine®, Orion Farmos Corporation, 
Espoo, Finland) at a dosage of 0.08 mg kg − 1 and ketamine (WDT eG, Garbsen, 
Germany) at 1.2 mg kg − 1 on the basis of estimated body mass. Animals were then 
manually intubated using a long-blade laryngoscope and maintained with isoflu-
rane (Isobo®, Nbl. Der Essex Pharma GmbH, Munich, Germany) and air, air mixed 
with oxygen or pure oxygen throughout the procedure. Anaesthesia was partially 
antagonized by intramuscular injection of atipamezole hydrochloride (Antisedan, 
Pfizer GmbH, Karlsruhe, Germany) at five times the dosage of medetomidine. All 
animals had sufficiently recuperated to be up and standing within 10 to 15 min 
after application of the antidote. </p>

<p>Semen collection and evaluation. Semen from nine of the males was collected 
by electroejaculation and assessed in terms of volume, concentration, morphol-
ogy, acrosome integrity and subjective total motility, as previously described 24 and 
Table 1 therein. Seminal plasma osmolarity (N = 4) and resistance to hypoosmotic 
conditions (N = 3) were also evaluated (ref. 24 and Table 1 therein). Cauda epididymal </p>

<p>spermatozoa sample (N = 1) was obtained by removal of the testes from the in-
guinal canal following euthanasia. The tunicas were excised and the epididymis was 
removed. Cuts were made in the cauda epididymis with sterile surgical scalpel, and 
the spermatozoa were aspirated and transferred directly into Carnoy's fixative for 
preparation (see next section). </p>

<p>Semen preparation and FISH. Semen was washed at least three times in freshly 
made, ice-cold Carnoy's fixative (glacial acetic acid and methanol at a ratio of 1:3). 
Each washing step included suspending the sample in 8 ml fixative, vortexing and 
then centrifugation at 400 g for 10 min. After centrifugation the supernatant was 
discarded. Subsequent to the final washing, the semen sample was resuspended in 
ice-cold fixative and kept at − 20 °C pending further treatment. 
For the FISH procedure, the fixed semen sample was vortexed and one drop of 
the suspension was placed on a microscopic slide and set aside horizontally to air 
dry. The position of the drop was marked with a glasscutter. A 500 µl of 10 mM 
dithioerythritol in 0.1 M Tris-aminomethan (Tris base) were applied to each slide, 
covered with parafilm and incubated at room temperature for 15 min. Following 
incubation, the parafilm was removed, excess liquid discarded and the slides were 
lightly washed in 2×SSC (saline-sodium citrate) buffer solution at room tempera-
ture. After washing, the slides were left to air dry and then 100 µl of 70% (v/v) 
formamid (Carl Roth GmbH + Co., Karlsruhe, Germany)/30% (v/v) 2×SSC were 
applied to each slide, covered with a cover slip and incubated for 10 min at 80 °C 
in a slide processing system (ThermoBrite, Abbott, Wiesbaden, Germany). 
At the end of incubation, the cover slip was removed and slides were washed in 
cold distilled water and then left to air dry. Subsequently, slides were dehydrated 
in an ice-cold ethanol series (70%, 90%, 100%, 1 min in each) and set aside to 
air dry thoroughly. When ready, 1 µl of each of the pygmy hippopotamus X-and 
Y-chromosome-specific FISH probes (Cambridge Resource Centre for Compara-
tive Genomics, Cambridge, UK) was mixed with 8 µl of hybridization mix, applied 
to the marked area on the slide, covered with a cover slip and sealed with rubber 
cement. The X-chromosome probe was labelled with Cy3 (fluorescence red) and 
the Y-chromosome probe was labelled with FITC (fluorescence green). The probe 
and target DNA were co-denatured using the ThermoBrite system set at 65 °C for 
10 min followed by hybridization at 37 °C overnight. After hybridization, rubber 
cement and cover slip were removed, and slides were washed for 1 min in 0.4×SSC 
at 75 °C followed by 1 min in 2×SSC/0.1% (v/v) NP-40 at room temperature. After 
air drying in the dark, slides were counterstained with Vectashield antifade solu-
tion with 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, 
CA, USA) and covered with a cover slip. Slides were assessed under a fluorescence 
microscope (BZ-8000; Keyence Corporation, Osaka, Japan) equipped with an ×60 
oil immersion lens. At least 2,000 cells were assessed per ejaculate. Cells with 
ambiguous staining were excluded from analysis. </p>

<p>Studbook analysis. The most recent international pygmy hippopotamus studbook 
available at the time of the study 23 , updated till 31 December 2008, was analysed. 
Data extracted from the studbook on all captive births included sex, sire, dam, dam's 
origin (captive or wild-born), birth date, birth location and death date. Animals that 
died before the age of 5 were regarded as dying prematurely. Calves with unknown 
sex were excluded from sex ratio analysis. Data on the genetic diversity of the popu-
lation and the mean kinship coefficient as well as information about offspring of the 
males participating in this study were also extracted from the studbook. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Throughout, the sex ratio is expressed as the fraction of males 
or Y-chromosome-bearing spermatozoa in a sample or population. All binomial 
tests were exact tests based on cumulative probabilities and, unless otherwise 
stated, all tests (Spearman correlation coefficient, binomial and Wilcoxon signed-
ranks test) are two-tailed. Statistical tests were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">PASW Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">18.0.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, NY, USA) 
statistical software. Differences were considered significant when P &lt; 0.05. The 
modified Wald method 37 was used to calculate CIs. </p>



<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1700 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 3:697 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1700 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2012 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We wish to thank Ms Beatrice Steck, International studbook keeper of pygmy 
hippopotamus, for her support to this project, and Ms Nana Satake from the Taronga 
Western Plains Zoo, Australia, for her help in sample collection. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>J.S., R.H, F.G. and T.B.H. designed the research, J.S., R.H, T.B., F.G. and T.B.H conducted 
the research, J.S. and H.H. analysed the data, J.S. and H.H. wrote the paper and R.H., 
T.B., F.G. and T.B.H. edited the paper. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Saragusty, J. et al. Male pygmy hippopotamus influence offspring 
sex ratio. Nat. Commun. 3:697 doi: 10.1038/ncomms1700 (2012). </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

</text></tei>