<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3173807" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The most significant change in the global response 
to HIV has been the rapid expansion of anti-
retroviral therapy (ART) using drug combinations 
in developing countries. Since WHO and UNAIDS 
launched the '3 by 5' strategy in 2003, 
1 the number 
of people on ART has grown to exceed 4 million 
people by the end of 2008. 
2 High levels of ART in 
many countries are now having a major impact on 
HIV prevalence. Because survival of individuals on 
ART is greatly prolonged, HIV prevalence in the 
population as a whole will be higher than in the 
absence of ART. These increased prevalence effects 
are often reflected in surveillance data which the 
UNAIDS Estimation and Projection Package (EPP) 
fits to the model developed by the UNAIDS 
Reference Group on Estimates, Modelling and 
Projections (hereafter, the Reference Group 
model). 
3e6 EPP has been used extensively for 
modelling national epidemics. 
7e10 The EPP model 
must incorporate these effects of ART on preva-
lence before fitting to the data. High levels of ART 
can also lower the HIV incidence for a given </p>

<p>prevalence level through decreases in viral load 
reducing individuals' infectiousness. To respond to 
both sets of treatment-related effects, EPP 2009 
now uses a modified Reference Group model that 
includes the impacts of ART on prevalence and 
incidence. 
Estimates of the number of persons living with 
HIV have been the major focus of routine moni-
toring and reporting on HIV epidemics. However, 
a number of problems have been identified with the 
reliance on prevalence as an indicator for analysing 
the impact of HIV programs. During the early 
phases of an epidemic prevalence grows rapidly, but 
changes in the slope due to saturation and to 
program impact are difficult to separate. After 
several years HIV prevalence tends to plateau, with 
new infections and deaths balancing each other 
out. An effective program introduced as this 
plateau phase begins may induce a gradual decline 
in prevalence, but this decline may be difficult to 
distinguish from mortality-related declines. Several 
years ago, the global epidemic entered a plateau 
phase, with most countries in sub-Saharan Afri-
cadwhere the majority of people living with HIV 
residedshowing stable or only slowly declining 
HIV prevalence. As a result, in 2007 UNAIDS began 
to focus more attention on new infections, that is, 
incidence, as a more informative measure of global 
progress. 
11 In response, the UNAIDS Reference 
Group recommended that the tools UNAIDS 
prepares to assist countries in analysing their 
epidemics, EPP and <rs type="software">Spectrum</rs>, shift to a focus on 
incidence. 
12 This change was made in the 2009 
version of the software, which still fits prevalence 
data, but provides incidence from the model along 
with prevalence as outputs. Because incidence is 
derived by fitting prevalence, it reflects an averaged 
national trend in new infections and may not 
capture short-term rises and falls in incidence 
occurring in specific groups or geographical areas. 
EPP 2009 includes a number of additional 
changes to resolve issues that have arisen in the 
application of the package at country level. EPP 
2007's uncertainty estimation procedures evaluated 
50 000e200 000 sets of Reference Group model 
parameters for their fit to the observed prevalence 
data, normally selecting out 50 or more that were 
close to the data (described in Brown et al 
5 and 
Alkema et al 
13 ). In a few countries, the defaults set 
in the uncertainty procedures produced relatively 
few unique curves, leading to inaccurate estimation 
of uncertainty. A new procedure, incremental 
mixture importance sampling (IMIS), has been 
introduced to solve this problem. In many African 
countries the population has been rapidly shifting </p>

<p>1 Population and Health Studies, 
East-West Center, Honolulu, 
Hawaii, USA 
2 Department of Statistics, 
University of Washington, 
Seattle, Washington, USA 
3 Harvard School of Public 
Health, Boston, Massachusetts, 
USA 
4 Department of Infectious 
Disease Epidemiology, Imperial 
College London, London, UK 
5 Futures Institute, Glastonbury, 
Connecticut, USA 
6 Population Division, 
Department of Economic and 
Social Affairs, New York, New 
York, USA </p>

<p>Correspondence to 
Tim Brown, Population and 
Health Studies, East-West 
Center, 1601 East-West Road, 
Honolulu, HI 96848, USA; 
tim@hawaii.edu </p>

<p>Accepted 7 September 2010 </p>

<p>This paper is freely available 
online under the BMJ Journals 
unlocked scheme, see http://sti. 
bmj.com/site/about/unlocked. 
xhtml </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii3eii10. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.044784 
ii3 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>from rural to urban areas, but earlier versions of EPP assumed 
fixed urban and rural population sizes. 
12 EPP 2009 now allows 
the urban/rural proportions to vary over time. In a small number 
of countries, fits to the data in EPP 2007 produced zero incidence 
within a few years, a situation which has never been observed in 
any country. A modified Reference Group model was developed 
for use in these countries. Finally, user interface changes were 
introduced to allow user input of the data needed for ART 
calculations, improve overall calibration procedures, and support 
the shift to an incidence basis. </p>

<p>INCORPORATING ART INTO THE REFERENCE GROUP MODEL 
AND EPP FITS </p>

<p>The widespread availability of ART is altering the course of HIV 
epidemics. People living with HIV who start ART have 
substantially increased survival. 
14 As a result, HIV prevalence is 
higher than it would be otherwise. Figure 1 illustrates the 
impact that scaling up ART from 0% coverage among those in 
need in 2005 to 100% coverage by 2015 would have on an 
advanced epidemic. Prevalence increases slightly because fewer 
people are dying from HIV-related causes. At the same time, </p>

<p>incidence declines because a substantial fraction of those living 
with HIV are now on ART, which substantially reduces their 
infectivity, that is, their ability to infect their partners. In EPP 
2009, based on a review by Baggaley and colleagues (unpub-
lished), the default value for the infectivity of those on ART is 
set at 0.11 of the infectivity of persons not on ART, but the user 
can change this value on the User Preferences page. This figure 
was based on an extensive review of the relative HIV trans-
mission probability of treated individuals compared to people 
not eligible for ART, estimated from the best field data available 
at the time as 0.20, an 80% reduction in infectivity. This figure 
was then adjusted for the average duration and relative infec-
tiousness of the stages of HIV infection to provide the 0.11 figure 
for relative infectiousness compared to all infected individuals, 
that is, both those eligible for and ineligible for ART. This value 
is similar to those in another literature review and a recent 
cohort study, both of which found a 92% reduction in hetero-
sexual transmission among those on ART relative to those not 
on therapy. </p>

<p>15 16   Adding ART to EPP 2009 required substantial changes to both 
the internal Reference Group model and the user interface: 
&lt; The underlying equations describing the Reference Group 
model were modified to include the effects of ART on survival 
and new infections (see the appendix). 
&lt; The EPP interface added an ART Data page for the user to 
provide information about the CD4 eligibility criterion, HIV 
progression rate and numbers on first-and second-line ART. 
&lt; The Results page added a button, labelled 'ART results' which 
brings up a table displaying the number of people on ART and 
estimated percentage of ART need met. 
The original Reference Group model, described in detail 
previously, 
4 5 divided the population into three groups: (1) those 
not at risk (X); (2) those at risk, but not yet infected (Z); and (3) 
those at risk and living with HIV (Y). These three groups are 
shown in the upper left of figure 2. New members can enter the 
two uninfected compartments at age 15 and only leave 
a compartment by contracting HIV or dying. Those in the 
uninfected compartments have only background mortality 
applied, while those living with HIV also have additional HIV-
related mortality, which depends on when they contracted HIV. 
As seen in the lower right of figure 2, the model in EPP 2009 
has been modified to add several new compartments: those 
newly eligible for ART, divided among those untreated and those 
on first-line ART; and those on second-line ART. While previous 
versions of EPP and Spectrum used a single Weibull survival 
function for time from infection to death, EPP 2009 and current 
versions of Spectrum replaced this single function with four 
functions: a Weibull curve describing progression from infection 
to eligibility for ART, a second Weibull curve describing 
progression from eligibility to death in the absence of ART (see 
figure 3), and simple survival functions for those on first-and 
second-line ART expressed as the percentage of those on each 
treatment surviving from year to year. The eligibility Weibull 
function is used to progress people from the infected at-risk 
compartment into the currently eligible compartment based on 
their time since infection. EPP 2009 then uses current numbers 
of people on first-and second-line ART supplied by the user to 
divide eligible individuals into those untreated, those on first-line 
ART and those on second-line ART. For persons remaining in the 
untreated category, survival will follow the Weibull distribution 
of time from eligibility to death based on the time at which they 
became eligible. For those on first-line ART, survival is deter-
mined by two values: (1) the percentage surviving the first year 
on first-line ART, and (2) the percentage surviving subsequent </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 1 The impact that scaling up to 100% of antiretroviral therapy 
(ART) need by 2015 would have if begun in 2005 in an advanced 
epidemic. (A) Prevalence increases as a result of prolonged survival of 
those on ART, while (B) incidence declines. Note that the UNAIDS 
Estimation and Projection Package (EPP) estimates incidence using the 
traditional epidemiological definition of percentage of susceptibles 
contracting HIV rather than on a whole-population basis. </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii3eii10. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.044784 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>years on first-line ART. By default these are set to 86% and 90%, 
respectively, but may be changed by the user. If a person fails 
first-line therapy and slots are open for second-line therapy, they 
are moved to second-line therapy and 90% survival per year is 
assumed in subsequent years. If no slots are open, they progress 
to death. By tracking people's evolution through these addi-
tional compartments, the outputs of EPP 2009 incorporate the 
impacts of ART on prevalence and incidence. The equations 
describing this model are provided in the appendix. 
The Weibull curves used depend on both an eligibility criterion 
in terms of CD4 count and a fast or normal progression rate 
from HIV infection to death chosen by the user: four sets of 
Weibull parameters are provided to cover possible combinations 
of CD4 eligibility threshold (CD4&lt;200 and CD4&lt;350) and </p>

<p>progression pattern (normal with median 11-year survival, fast 
with median 9-year survival without ART). Fast and slow 
progression patterns address the wide variability in survival 
observed between African and Thai cohorts. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>This modified model requires several decisions and numerical 
inputs from the user in order to fully calculate ART effects: 
&lt; CD4 eligibility threshold. The user must select eligibility for 
ART as a CD4 count below 200 cells/mm 
3 or a CD4 below 
350 cells/mm 
3 . 
&lt; Progression pattern. The user must select a progression pattern 
with an overall survival in the absence of ART of 11 years 
(normal pattern) or one with survival of 9 years (fast 
pattern). 
&lt; Year-by-year estimates of percentage survival in the 1st year of 
ART. By default this is set to 86% surviving the first year and 
is kept at this value throughout the projection. However, 
expansion of voluntary counselling and testing (VCT) 
programs in most countries is expected to allow for detection 
of individuals living with HIV at higher CD4 counts. 
When therapy starts at higher CD4 counts, survival is 
improved. 
18 19 As VCT programs expand, it is expected that 
first year survival will improve, so EPP and Spectrum allow 
the user to change it over time. 
&lt; Year-by-year numbers on first-line and second-line ART nationally. 
The user must provide the total number of individuals on 
first-and second-line therapies. For years in the past, values 
should be based on historical program data. For years in the 
future, values can be based on projections of anticipated 
numbers on ART. To simplify future projections, the user can 
enter values for historical data and an estimate for the 
numbers on ART in the final year of the projection and then 
select an option to project the intervening years (the 'ART 
project' button). This will linearly extrapolate from the last 
historical value entered and the estimate for the final year. 
&lt; Distribution of ART among user defined subpopulations. Finally, 
the user must distribute the national ART numbers among 
the different subpopulations. This distribution may be either 
done in absolute numbers or as percentages of all those on 
ART who are members of each subpopulation. </p>

<p>Figure 2 The compartments in the 
modified Reference Group model with 
antiretroviral therapy (ART) used in the 
UNAIDS Estimation and Projection 
Package (EPP) 2009. Once they 
become eligible for ART, those living 
with HIV can move to untreated or first-
line therapy compartments based on 
the number of treatment slots available. 
If they fail first-line therapy they can 
move to second-line therapy. </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Not at-risk 
Entrants by 
"birth" at age 15 </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>population </p>

<p>Z </p>

<p>Uninfected </p>

<p>Death </p>

<p>Number gated by 
at-risk </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Infe </p>

<p>access slots. All 
untreated + newly 
eligible have equal 
chance </p>

<p>cted 
at-risk </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>Untreated </p>

<p>Newly 
eligible for ART </p>

<p>L 1 </p>

<p>First-line ART </p>

<p>Death </p>

<p>L 2 </p>

<p>Second-line ART </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>0 
. 
1 </p>

<p>8 
. 
0 </p>

<p>6 
. 
0 </p>

<p>4 
. 
0 </p>

<p>2 
. 
0 </p>

<p>0 
. 
0 </p>

<p>0 
1 
5 
1 
0 
2 
5 
2 
0 
3 
Percent progressing to endpoint (eligibility or death) </p>

<p>0 
5 </p>

<p>) 
s 
r 
a 
e 
y 
( 
V 
I 
H 
g 
n 
i 
t 
c 
a 
r 
t 
n 
o 
c 
e 
c 
n 
i 
s 
e 
m 
i 
T </p>

<p>y 
t 
i 
l 
i 
b 
i 
g 
i 
l 
e 
T 
R 
A 
o 
t 
n 
o 
i 
t 
c 
e 
f 
n 
I 
) 
a 
( 
h 
t 
a 
e 
d 
o 
t 
y 
t 
i 
l 
i 
b 
i 
g 
i 
l 
E 
) 
b 
( 
h 
t 
a 
e 
d 
o 
t 
n 
o 
i 
t 
c 
e 
f 
n 
I 
) 
c 
( </p>

<p>Figure 3 Example of the Weibull distributions for time (A) from 
infection to antiretroviral therapy (ART) eligibility and (B) from ART 
eligibility to death. When combined, they approximate (C) the original 
Weibull survival function used in previous versions of the UNAIDS 
Estimation and Projection Package (EPP) and Spectrum. This figure is for 
a CD4 eligibility threshold of 200 cells/mm 
3 and normal (11-year 
survival) progression pattern. </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii3eii10. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.044784 
ii5 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>The user enters this information on a single ART Data page in 
EPP 2009. The subsequent year survival on ART is specified on 
the User Preferences page and can be altered by the user if 
desired, although the Reference Group generally recommends 
against this in the absence of convincing local data to the 
contrary. </p>

<p>THE SHIFT TO INCIDENCE </p>

<p>In EPP incidence is defined using the standard epidemiological 
definition of the percentage of those susceptible to infection 
contracting HIV in a specified year. The shift from prevalence to 
incidence in EPP 2009 required primarily changes in the user 
interface. Internally, the EPP implementation of the Reference 
Group model has always explicitly calculated incidence while 
fitting prevalence. For EPP 2009, however, this was made visible 
to the user. There are a number of places where the shift to 
incidence becomes apparent: 
&lt; The files containing the national projection and uncertainty 
estimates (*.spt and *.spu) that EPP passes to Spectrum now 
provide incidence as well as prevalence. Spectrum then uses 
this incidence to calculate its outputs for national projections. 
&lt; On the Results page, incidence can now be displayed both in 
terms of estimated number of new infections and percentage 
of susceptibles contracting HIV in a given year (see figure 4). 
Users should always take final new and current infection 
numbers from Spectrum rather than EPP because Spectrum 
has a more complete demographic model, while EPP uses 
a simplified demographic model inherent in the Reference 
Group model. 
&lt; A graph for displaying the incidence distribution (see figure 5) 
has been added to the Results page and is activated by 
clicking the button labelled 'Incidence distribution'. This 
displays the distribution of incidence among the various user 
defined subpopulations in EPP. It can help to track the 
evolution of the epidemic and provide countries with a better 
idea of which populations are giving rise to new infections at 
a given point in time. </p>

<p>IMPROVING UNCERTAINTY ESTIMATION </p>

<p>EPP 2007 adopted an uncertainty estimation method known as 
Bayesian melding. 
5 13 This method generates random combina-</p>

<p>tions of the Reference Group model parameters (r, f 0 , t 0 and 4) in </p>

<p>accord with user-specified distributions of each of the variables, 
weights them by how well they fit the surveillance data, and 
then resamples them to provide an estimate of the uncertainty 
in the fit of the model to the data. 
20 This method worked fairly 
well in most cases, but for some surveillance data sets the 
method found relatively few unique curves close to the data 
among the resamples (see figure 6A). This meant that the 
uncertainty bounds were not very well-determined. The 
problem could be alleviated by generating more parameter 
combinations, but this was very computationally demanding 
and time-consuming. 
EPP 2009 replaced the simple random sampling of possible 
combinations of variables in the Bayesian melding module with 
a procedure known as incremental mixture importance sampling 
(IMIS). </p>

<p>21 22 In IMIS, a smaller initial set of (r, f 0 , t 0 and 4) 
combinations is generated. (Note: If one is using the 4-shift </p>

<p>described later in this paper, this group is expanded by two </p>

<p>variables, 4 </p>

<p>9 and the year in which the shift begins, t 4eshift .) 
These are then evaluated and weighted by their fit to the data. 
New combinations of the variables are then generated centred 
on the combination with the highest weight. This process is 
repeated iteratively until the desired number of unique curves is 
obtained. The IMIS algorithm has several control parameters: 
the number of initial samples, N 0 , the sample size at each 
importance sampling iteration, B, and the number of resamples, 
J. The algorithm is unbiased for any choice of these parameters, 
but they do affect its efficiency. After extensive experimentation, 
good results were found with N 0 ¼4000, B¼400 and J¼3000. For 
3000 resamples, finding 1900 unique curves ensures the resam-
pled curves will be a good approximation to the actual distri-
bution, so this was set as the default for national projections. For 
training purposes the number of unique curves was set at 400, 
which allows fits to be generated in a few minutes during 
workshops. Figure 6B illustrates how this procedure has gener-
ated a much higher number of unique curves, making the 
uncertainty bounds more accurate. </p>

<p>ALLOWING FOR URBAN/RURAL POPULATION SHIFTS </p>

<p>Urbanisation is a global phenomenon, and large urban/rural HIV 
prevalence differentials are often observed in countries with 
generalised epidemics. 
23 24 Across Africa, United Nations Popu-
lation Division projections show urban populations growing </p>

<p>Figure 4 Incidence display on the Results page. The user can select to display new infections, that is, incidence as either (A) the percentage of those 
susceptible to infection who contracted HIV in the last year or (B) an absolute number of new infections in a year. </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii3eii10. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.044784 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>from 27.6% in 1980 to 39.9% in 2010 
25 ; and in a few countries 
with generalised epidemics, the rate of urbanisation is extreme. 
Between 1980 and 2010, Botswana went from 16.5% to 61.1% 
urban, while Angola went from 24.3% to 58.5%. 
25 In an era of 
increasing urbanisation, urban/rural prevalence differentials can 
have a major influence on national HIV estimates. 
26 To adjust for 
this influence, EPP 2009 allows for changes in the urban/rural 
population proportions over time in generalised epidemics. 
In most generalised epidemics, the national projection is 
divided into two subpopulations: one urban and one rural. In 
EPP 2009 the user first fits the epidemics in each subpopulation 
to the corresponding HIV surveillance data. EPP 2009 then 
combines these two separate fits with weights proportional to 
the number of people living in urban or rural areas. By default, 
the urban percentage is set based on the numbers entered on the 
Define Pops page and is kept constant over time. However, the 
user can change the annual urban/rural proportions over time on 
the Pop Change page, which contains a table showing the overall 
percentage of urban population along with the percentage of 
national population in each subpopulation. The user can also 
adjust urbanerural proportions to the values provided by the 
United Nations Population Division by clicking on an 'Adjust to </p>

<p>UN values' button. If the user has defined multiple urban and 
rural subpopulations, then the total urban population is divided 
among them according to their relative size as specified on the 
Define Pops page. The actual resulting population sizes and the 
impacts on national HIV prevalence can then be examined on 
the Results page. </p>

<p>UNUSUAL CASES FORCE MODIFICATIONS TO THE MODEL </p>

<p>One final issue seen in the field was a small number of data sets, 
for example, in Cambodia or Zimbabwe, that approached zero 
incidence by the end of the projection period when fit with EPP 
2007. No national HIV epidemic has ever been observed that 
actually declined to zero incidence. The problem here is that 
epidemics are dynamic, that is, the behaviours that drive them 
can and do change over time. However, the Reference Group 
model is static, that is, the four parameters that define the model </p>

<p>(r, f 0 , t 0 and 4) are fixed and do not vary over timedthey must fit 
both the early epidemic and the late epidemic. While the 4 </p>

<p>parameter was introduced to represent increased or decreased 
levels of risk behaviour over the course of the epidemic, 
6 it forces 
a particular behaviour change pattern on a projection that is </p>

<p>Figure 5 Incidence distribution displays. UNAIDS Estimation and Projection Package (EPP) 2009 allows the display of the distribution of incidence 
among the subpopulations comprising a national projection. The vertical axis shows the number of new infections in thousands. </p>

<p>Figure 6 A comparison of the outcomes of the Bayesian melding routines as implemented in the UNAIDS Estimation and Projection Package (EPP) 
2007 (A) and EPP 2009 (B) with the same data set. This illustrates how the incremental mixture importance sampling (IMIS) procedure used in EPP 
2009 provides many more unique curves and better uncertainty estimates in similar amounts of computational time. </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii3eii10. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.044784 
ii7 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>itself static. In the real world, behaviours change, the proportion 
of people at risk changes, and any model with static parameters 
will not be able to capture the full complexity. In fact, in a few 
epidemics incidence is once again rising, something that the 
original Reference Group model was never intended to reproduce 
and which cannot be fitted with the standard four-parameter 
model. 
In order to address these issues, a number of variants to the 
Reference Group model were considered. One alternative 
allowed for a one-time change in r, which represents the rate at 
which new infections occur among the susceptible population. 
However, this approach was found to be insufficient, as the 
change in r often occurred when there were no susceptibles left 
in the population to become infected. Other alternatives were </p>

<p>also explored, including variants in which both r and 4 were </p>

<p>allowed to change, and in which r shifted gradually over some 
time frame; but neither of these resolved the zero incidence 
issues. The solution finally adopted was to allow a slow shift in </p>

<p>4 over some period before the end of the projection period. The </p>

<p>interpretation of this scenario is that as prevalence declines from 
its peak, some individuals who had reduced their risk behaviours 
in response to the epidemic, might return to riskier behaviours, 
which would increase recruitment into the susceptible popula-
tion. By allowing such changes and applying constraints on 
incidence, more reasonable incidence patterns could be produced 
while still fitting the data. This produced a six-parameter model </p>

<p>with (r, f 0 , t 0 and 4) supplemented by a 4 </p>

<p>9 and a year, t 4eshift in </p>

<p>which 4 began a slow shift to 4 </p>

<p>9 by the end of the projection 
period. Using this approach, it was possible to fit the more 
problematic data sets without having incidence drop to zero (see 
figure 7). </p>

<p>ANTICIPATED FUTURE DIRECTIONS </p>

<p>In the 2009 round of estimations, even after decomposing the 
population in homogeneous groups (eg, urban/rural, provinces, 
etc) more complex epidemic patterns were observed in a number 
of countries, for example, an early peak and subsequent decline 
in prevalence followed by an increase in prevalence. These 
patterns almost certainly result from behavioural changes, 
where lower levels of risk behaviour in the past are giving way to 
higher levels today, producing higher incidence. Such changes 
may result from prevention fatigue, perceptions of lower HIV </p>

<p>severity with the availability of ART, new generations of 
susceptibles, or newly emerging epidemics in populations 
previously unaffected. Addressing these will require a more </p>

<p>complex model than the simple four-parameter (r, f 0 , t 0 and 4) 
Reference Group model or even the new six-parameter 4-shift </p>

<p>model outlined above. Work is currently underway to develop 
models that allow r to vary smoothly over time (described in 
Hogan et al 
27 and in Bao and Raftery 
28 ), thus permitting the 
combined SpectrumeEPP package to better handle the more 
complex behavioural trends being observed as the global 
pandemic enters its fourth decade. 
The focus on incidence in this round of global estimates 
highlighted some issues with the current separation of respon-
sibilities between EPP and Spectrum, with EPP fitting the 
prevalence data and Spectrum subsequently applying a more 
complete age-structured demographic model to the resulting 
prevalence curve to produce comprehensive national outputs. 
Since incidence was calculated as the percentage of susceptible 
individuals contracting HIV, the variations in their underlying 
population models resulted in slightly different calculations of 
the number of new infections between EPP and Spectrum. In 
some countries, migration, which is included in Spectrum's 
demographic model but not in EPP's, made a substantial 
difference in incidence levels. In addition, it became clear that 
better incidence estimates would be obtained if the Reference 
Group model was adapted to use a population between 15 and 
49 years of age and allowed ageing out at 50, instead of the 
current 15+ population. These factors also contributed to 
differing ART estimates between the two models, sometimes 
requiring countries to go through an iterative process to reach an 
acceptable result. These problems are being addressed in the 
next round of EPP and Spectrum by combining them into 
a more tightly integrated package. EPP will take its demo-
graphics directly from Spectrum and will pass its incidence 
calculations to Spectrum without direct user intervention, thus 
ensuring better consistency. The user will actually invoke EPP 
from within Spectrum, thus providing a more holistic user 
experience. 
In light of evolving global and national policies and recom-
mendations for initiation of ART at higher and higher CD4 
counts, the next versions of Spectrum and EPP are adopting 
a CD4 model allowing for a fuller range of CD4 criteria, for 
example, 200, 250, 350 and 500. </p>

<p>Figure 7 An example of the impact of applying a 4-shift with an incidence constraint to Zimbabwe urban data. The left-hand figure shows the near-
zero incidence resulting from a four-parameter Reference Group model fit, while the right-hand side shows the results of allowing 4 to vary, providing </p>

<p>a low, but stable incidence pattern. </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii3eii10. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.044784 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>The Reference Group also recognises that many countries rely 
on case reporting systems as opposed to cross-sectional seros-
urveillance and has begun to explore methodologies for esti-
mating the levels of under-reporting in such systems as 
diagnoses increase, but these discussions are still at an early 
stage. In the future, as techniques for such estimation improve, 
their incorporation into the UNAIDS estimation and projection 
suite may be considered. As they have since the beginning, these 
tools will continue to evolve to address new problems and issues 
that arise as the global pandemic enters its fourth decade. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We greatly appreciate the ongoing technical inputs of the 
many and varied members of the UNAIDS Reference Group on Estimates, Modelling 
and Projections, and the willingness of country counterparts to share the data used 
in preparing examples here with UNAIDS and WHO. </p>

<p>Funding The authors acknowledge the support of UNAIDS for the ongoing 
development of EPP and Spectrum. National Institute of Child Health and Development 
grant no. R01 HD054511 supported the development of the uncertainty estimation 
methodologies in EPP. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Contributors Tim Brown drafted the first version of the paper and incorporated 
extensive feedback from the other authors. Adrian Raftery and Le Bao developed the 
IMIS and Bayesian melding methodologies used in uncertainty estimation. Rebecca 
Baggaley conducted the analysis to estimate reductions in infectiousness for those on 
ART. John Stover developed the Weibull distributions used to progress individuals 
from infection to eligibility for ART and from eligibility to death and also supervises 
Spectrum development. Josh Salomon first recognised the limitations of the 
Reference Group model and suggested approaches involving steps and shifts in the 
model parameters to better fit some epidemics. Patrick Gerland first suggested the 
approach for combining urban and rural populations, and he and his colleagues at 
the United Nations Population Division provided the trends in urban/rural proportions 
incorporated into the software. Tim Brown coded these features into the EPP package. 
All seven serve as members of the UNAIDS Reference Group on HIV Estimates, 
Modelling and Projections which advises UNAIDS on the techniques to be used in EPP 
and Spectrum. All authors contributed to revising the manuscript and approving the 
final content. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>We wish to make clear that the examples used here are illustrative in nature only. 
They may differ from actual national projections in the countries referenced, as they 
do not necessarily incorporate all data and information available at the country level. 
The views and opinions expressed in this paper are those of the authors and do not 
necessarily represent those of the United Nations. Its contents have not been formally 
edited or cleared by the United Nations. </p>



<p>APPENDIX 
The mathematics of antiretroviral therapy (ART) in EPP 2009 </p>

<p>The Reference Group model modifications used in EPP 2009 are shown in figure 2. 
They primarily consist of calculating the number newly eligible for ART (E) at a given 
time step, and then dividing these among two new compartments for those who 
remain untreated (U) and those who go on first-line ART (L 1 ). An additional 
compartment is added for those failing first-line ART and going on second-line ART 
(L 2 ). The original compartments in the model are retained: not at risk (X), at risk and 
infected but not on ART (Y), and at risk but uninfected (Z). The total population at any 
point in time is then calculated as: </p>

<p>Key messages </p>

<p>&lt; The UNAIDS Estimation and Projection package has contin-
ually evolved to adapt to new issues arising in estimating and 
projecting national HIV epidemics. 
&lt; EPP 2009 derives incidence, an essential indicator for program 
impact assessment. 
&lt; EPP 2009 includes the effects of ART: reducing incidence, 
increasing prevalence and decreasing HIV-related mortality. 
&lt; Computational efficiency in EPP 2009 has been greatly 
improved through the use of incremental mixture importance 
sampling. </p>

<p>Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii3eii10. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.044784 
ii9 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

<p>N ¼ X þ Y þ Z þ U þ L 1 þ L 2 </p>

<p>Demographic parameters, calculated from the United Nations Population Division 
non-AIDS projections, include background mortality (m), birth rate to those aged 15 
and older (b) and survival to age 15 (l). These are used along with the probability of 
vertical transmission (n) and the fertility reduction among HIV+ women (3) to 
calculate the number of new entrants E t in a given time step, t, in terms of the 
populations 15 years (tÀ15) earlier as: 
E t ¼ B </p>

<p>À </p>

<p>tÀ15 l </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>À </p>

<p>tÀ15 ¼ b </p>

<p>Â 
X tÀ15 þ Z tÀ15 þ 
À </p>

<p>1 À n 
Á 3 </p>

<p>À 
Y tÀ15 þ U tÀ15 þ L 1ðtÀ15Þ þ L 2ðtÀ15Þ 
ÁÃ </p>

<p>The four primary Reference Group parameters remain unchanged: the force of 
infection (r), the initial fraction entering the at-risk population (f 0 ), the start year of the 
epidemic (t 0 ) and the behaviour-change parameter (4); and the fraction, f, entering 
the at-risk population at a given point in time is determined by the size of the not-at-
risk and total populations as: </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>
X=N </p>

<p>
¼ 
exp 
Â </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>À X </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>À 
À 
1 À f 0 
ÁÁÃ </p>

<p>exp 
Â </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>À X </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>À 
À 
1 À f 0 
ÁÁÃ 
þ </p>

<p>1 
f 0 </p>

<p>À 1 </p>

<p>To implement ART, a number of ART-specific inputs must be provided or selected 
by the user: </p>

<p>&lt; Time series for the number on first-and second-line ART: L 1 (t) and L 2 (t) 
&lt; The infectivity of individuals on ART relative to those not on ART: R inf (default 0.11, 
but user adjustable, R inf ¼0 means no transmission) 
&lt; Weibull 
for 
progression 
from 
infection 
to 
ART 
eligibility: 
g 1 ðxÞ ¼ ða 1 x a1À1 =b </p>

<p>a1 </p>

<p>1 Þexp½Àðx=b 1 Þ 
a1 
&lt; Weibull for progression from eligibility to death if no ART: 
g 2 ðxÞ ¼ ða 2 x a 2 À1 =b </p>

<p>a 2 </p>

<p>2 Þexp½Àðx=b 2 Þ 
a2 
&lt; First year survival on first-line ART (time varying): s 1 (t) (default 86%, held constant, 
but user can change on an annual basis) 
&lt; Second and subsequent year survival on both first-and second-line ART: s 2+ 
(default 90%, but user adjustable) 
The latter two survivals are then used to calculate a third distribution for 
progression to first-line failure once ART has commenced: </p>

<p>g 3 
À 
x 
Á 
¼ </p>

<p>( 
0 
if x ¼ 0 
s 1 e </p>

<p>Às 1 x </p>

<p>if x#1yr 
s 2 þ e 
Às 1 e 
Às 2 þ ðxÀ1Þ if x &gt; 1yr </p>

<p>EPP then calculates the distribution for the rate at which infections occur at time 
x as: </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>new 
x </p>

<p>¼ ½ðr½Y x þ U x þ R inf ðL 1x þ L 2x Þ=N x þ i x ÞZ x ; </p>

<p>where t i is the pulse of infection that initiates the epidemic. Note that those on ART 
receive the reduced infectiousness described by R inf . The equations describing the 
changes in the number in each of the compartments: X, Y and Z becomes: </p>

<p>DX ¼ ½ð1 À fðX=NÞÞE t À mXDt </p>

<p>DY ¼ </p>

<p>h 
r 
Â 
Y þ U þ R inf </p>

<p>
L 1 þ L 2 </p>

<p>i. </p>

<p>N þ i </p>

<p>
Z À </p>

<p>Z t </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>new </p>

<p>x g 1 </p>

<p>À 
t À x 
Á 
dx À mY </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Dt </p>

<p>DZ ¼ ½fðX=NÞE t À ðm þ r½Y þ U þ R inf ðL 1 þ L 2 Þ=N þ iÞZDt </p>

<p>And the number newly eligible for ART in a given time step is calculated from the 
progression from infection to eligibility and the temporal distribution of new infections: </p>

<p>DE ¼ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Z t </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>new </p>

<p>x g 1 </p>

<p>À 
t À x 
Á 
dx </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>5 Dt </p>

<p>The newly eligible must then be allocated into the compartments for those on first-
line treatment (L 1 ) and those remaining untreated (U). The number failing first-line ART 
is calculated by applying the g 3 (x) distribution to estimate the number who fail first-
line therapy, and thus leave the L 1 compartment: 
Z t </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>new </p>

<p>1x g 3 </p>

<p>À 
t À x 
Á 
dx </p>

<p>Where L </p>

<p>new </p>

<p>1x is the number who entered first-line therapy at time x. L </p>

<p>new </p>

<p>1x is kept at zero 
until ART is initiated. The number failing first-line therapy is then combined with the 
user-provided time series L 1 (t) and L 2 (t), for numbers on first-line and second-line ART, 
to calculate the number entering each arm of ART at the next time step as: </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>new 
1 </p>

<p>¼ </p>

<p>h 
L 1 </p>



<p>t þ Dt </p>

<p>
À L 1 </p>

<p>
t </p>

<p>i 
þ </p>

<p>Z t </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>new </p>

<p>1x g 3 </p>

<p>À 
t À x 
Á 
dx </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>new 
2 </p>

<p>¼ 
Â 
L 2 
À </p>

<p>t þ Dt </p>

<p>Á 
À L 2 
À 
t 
ÁÃ 
þ 
À 
1 À s 2 þ 
Á 
L 2 
À 
t </p>

<p>Á Dt </p>

<p>that is, the number newly entering first-line ART is the increase in numbers on first-
line ART specified by the user plus replacements for those who fail on ART. For 
second-line therapy, it is assumed that a constant fraction of those currently on ART 
fail at every time step, the second term in the above equation. The remaining number 
of newly eligible must then be allocated into the untreated compartment, U: </p>

<p>DU ¼ DE À L </p>

<p>new 
1 </p>

<p>À </p>

<p>h 
mU þ </p>

<p>Z t </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>newAdj 
x </p>

<p>g 2 
À 
t À x 
Á 
dx </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Dt </p>

<p>The final term in brackets in this equation represents background mortality (mU) 
and HIV-related mortality for those remaining untreated through the present. U </p>

<p>newAdj 
x </p>

<p>is 
the distribution of the number untreated who became eligible for ART at time x. When 
people are placed on ART at each time step, this distribution must be adjusted 
downward to account for the fraction of the untreated going on to ART and also to 
correct for background mortality: </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>newAdj 
x </p>

<p>À </p>

<p>t þ Dt </p>

<p>Á 
¼ U </p>

<p>newAdj 
x </p>

<p>À 
t 
Á </p>

<p>1 À 
L </p>

<p>new 
1 </p>

<p>UðtÞ </p>

<p>
À 
1 À mDt 
Á </p>

<p>This effectively assumes that those selected for ART are chosen uniformly without 
regard to their duration of infection. If all of those eligible at any point in the projection 
are placed on ART, this distribution is set to zero for all previous times. The total 
number living with HIV in the population is then defined as: </p>

<p>H þ ¼ Y þ U þ L 1 þ L 2 </p>

<p>which accounts for the effects of ART on total HIV prevalence and incidence. </p>

<p> 
Sex Transm Infect 2010;86(Suppl 2):ii3eii10. doi:10.1136/sti.2010.044784 </p>

<p>Supplement </p>

</text></tei>