<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3792603" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The objective of this study was to examine the relationship between dairy product intake 
and the incidence of metabolic syndrome (MetS) and its components among middle-aged 
Koreans. We examined 7,240 adults aged 40-69 yr without MetS at baseline over a 
45.5-month follow-up period. They were taken from the Anseong and Ansan cohort of 
the Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study. Dairy product intake including milk, yogurt, 
and cheese was assessed with food frequency questionnaire. At the follow-up, the 
incidence of MetS was 17.1%. The incidences of MetS components were as follows: low 
HDL cholesterol (16.2%), abdominal obesity (14.0%), hypertriglyceridemia (13.8%), 
hyperglycemia (13.3%), and hypertension (13.1%). Adjusting for potential confounders, 
dairy product consumption frequency was inversely associated with the risk of MetS and 
abdominal obesity. Hazard ratio (HR) (95% confidence interval) for dairy product 
consumption more than 7 times/week compared to never was 0.75 (0.64-0.88, P for trend 
&lt; 0.001) for MetS and 0.73 (0.61-0.88, P for trend &lt; 0.001) for abdominal obesity. HR 
for milk intake was 0.79 for MetS and 0.82 for abdominal obesity. The results of this study 
suggest that daily intake of dairy products protects against the development of MetS, 
particularly abdominal obesity, in middle-aged Koreans. </p>

<p>Obesity has become a global public health concern in recent 
decades. The prevalence of diet-related chronic diseases, in-
cluding obesity and metabolic syndrome (MetS), are increasing 
worldwide (1). In accordance with lifestyle changes following 
economic development, the leading causes of death in Korea 
are cancer, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and liver disease 
(2). The prevalence of obesity, hypertension, and other adverse 
cardiometabolic outcomes has increased among Koreans. Ac-
cording to the Korea National Health and Nutrition Examina-
tion Survey (KNHANES), the prevalence of obesity among adults 
was more than doubled from 20.5% in 1995 to 30.9% in 2009 (3,  4). The prevalence of MetS in adults has increased primarily as 
a result of changes in lifestyle and diet, such as automobile use 
and fast food consumption (4). Obesity and MetS have become 
primary targets for public health intervention owing to the rap-
id change in mortality and chronic disease prevalence among 
Koreans. </p>

<p>Several cross-sectional and prospective studies have investi-
gated the association between dairy product consumption and 
the risk of cardiometabolic disease. However, the results were 
inconsistent and varied among population groups (5, 6). A re-
view of 10 cross-sectional studies and 3 prospective studies of 
the relationship between dairy product consumption and MetS 
suggested a protective effect of dairy product consumption on 
MetS, but the evidence was inconclusive (7). The effects of dairy 
product consumption on obesity have been extensively explor-
ed. A recent meta-analysis suggested a protective effect of dairy 
product consumption on obesity; however, the effect was small 
(6). In general, dairy product consumption in Asia is much lower 
than in Western countries. There is little evidence that increas-
ing dairy product consumption has protective effects against 
obesity and MetS in Asians. 
The present study hypothesized that dairy product intake is 
inversely related to the development of MetS and MetS compo-
nents in middle-aged Korean adults living in urban and rural 
communities. </p>

<p>Shin H, et al. • Dairy Product Intake and Metabolic Syndrome </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.10.1482 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study population 
Raw data of the Anseong and Ansan cohort of the Korean Ge-
nome and Epidemiology Study (KoGES) was obtained with the 
support of the Korea National Institute of Health, which repre-
sents rural and urban communities in Korea. The baseline sur-
vey for the KoGES, a prospective community study, was con-
ducted between May 2001 and February 2003 and included 
10,038 adults aged 40-69 yr. Of these subjects, 76.6% were fol-
lowed up in the 2005-2006 survey. The present study excluded 
individuals who had MetS at the baseline or who did not com-
plete the nutritional survey; thus, a total of 7,240 participants 
were included in our study. The average follow-up period was 
45.5 months with an interquartile range of 44.4-47.1 months. 
Detailed information on the Anseong and Ansan cohort has 
been previously published (8). </p>

<p>Dietary assessment 
A semi-quantitative food-frequency questionnaire (FFQ) that 
assessed intake of 110 commonly consumed food items and di-
etary habits was administered at baseline and at the follow-up 
interview. The questionnaire included nine categories of intake 
frequency ranging from "never" to "three times a day" and pho-
tographs illustrating three portion sizes for each item. The FFQ 
was developed based on dietary intake data from the KNHANES 
(9) and has been previously validated using dietary records tak-
en over 3 days during each of the four seasons in 124 partici-
pants as described elsewhere (10). The amount and frequency 
of milk, yogurt, and cheese intake were summed to calculate 
dairy product intake. For example, the amount of each food 
item was categorized into three serving sizes, 1/2, 1 (standard), 
and 2 servings. For milk, 1/2 cup equals to 100 mL. For the anal-
yses, food intake was recoded into serving categories consider-
ing both frequencies and the amount. Intake frequency was re-
grouped into five categories from none to more than 7 times 
per week for the statistical analyses. The frequency of milk in-
take was analyzed separately from the other dairy products. </p>

<p>Clinical assessment 
The definition of MetS was based on the modified National Chol-
esterol Education Program, Adult Treatment Panel III (NCEP-
ATP III) criteria (11) with the exception of abdominal obesity. 
We defined abdominal obesity according to the Korean Society 
for the Study of Obesity (KSSO) criteria; the cut-off value for waist 
circumferences was ≥ 90 cm for men and ≥ 85 cm for women 
(12). 
We defined MetS as the presence of three or more of the fol-
lowing five components: abdominal obesity, waist circumfer-
ence of &gt; 90 cm for men and &gt; 85 cm for women; elevated blood 
pressure, &gt; 130/85 mmHg; increased triglycerides, &gt; 150 mg/dL; </p>

<p>low high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, &lt; 40 mg/dL in 
men and &lt; 50 mg/dL in women; and elevated blood glucose 
levels, fasting blood glucose &gt; 100 mg/dL. 
The details of the clinical assessment are described elsewhere 
(13). Briefly, blood pressure was measured by trained health 
professionals using a conventional mercury sphygmomanom-
eter. The participants sat in a chair and following a 5-min rest 
period, three blood pressure readings were taken with a 30-sec 
interval between each reading. The average of the three values 
was used in the analysis. The 8-hr fasting blood samples were 
collected in EDTA-containing tubes and separated serum was 
stored at -70°C until analysis was performed. The samples were 
analyzed for each parameter at two clinical laboratories using 
an autoanalyzer (ADVIA 1650, Bayer Diagnostics, Tarrytown, 
NY, USA). Reliability of the serological parameters was checked 
with three years of quality control data as explained elsewhere 
(14). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> statistical software (Ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">11</rs>, Col-
lege Station, TX, USA). Baseline characteristics are expressed as 
mean ± standard deviation or percentage. Differences between 
measurements and groups were assessed using an analysis of 
variance (ANOVA) and Pearson chi-square tests. Age-and sex-
adjusted and multivariate Cox proportional hazard models were 
used to examine the association between dairy product and 
milk intake and MetS components. An additional multivariate 
model including age, sex, physical activity, alcohol consump-
tion, total energy intake, smoking status, education, and income 
as covariates was used. The proportional hazards assumption 
was graphically assessed using log-log plots and statistically as-
sessed on the basis of Schoenfeld residuals (15). No major vio-
lations of the proportional hazard assumption were detected. A 
two-sided P value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Ethics statement 
The present study was approved by the institutional review board 
of the Dongguk University Ilsan Hospital (#2010-1-64), Goyang, 
Korea. Informed consent was waived by the board. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The mean age of participants at baseline was 51.5 yr and 49.9% 
were women. When we classified the participants into 5 groups 
based on the frequency of dairy product intake, the group with 
participants consuming greater amount of dairy products were 
more likely to be women, be more educated, have higher income, 
drink less alcohol, and smoke less (Tables 1, 2). 
During the average follow-up period of 45.5 months, the in-
cidence of MetS was 17.1%. Lower HDL cholesterol (16.2%) was 
the most common MetS components followed by abdominal </p>

<p>Shin H, et al. • Dairy Product Intake and Metabolic Syndrome </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.10.1482 </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of participants according to the frequency of dairy product consumption at baseline </p>

<p>Parameters 
Frequency of Dairy product intake (times/week) </p>

<p>None 
1 
2-3 
4-6 
≥ 7 
P value </p>

<p>No. of subjects 
1,446 
1,022 
1,070 
1,282 
2,420 
Age, mean (SD) (yr) 
53.4 (9.4) 
51.7 (8.9) 
49.9 (8.4) 
49.5 (8.0) 
51.0 (8.6) 
&lt; 0.001 
Female (%) 
43.3 
47.2 
48.7 
48.7 
56.2 
&lt; 0.001 
Body mass index, mean (SD) (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
23.8 (3.0) 
23.8 (2.9) 
24.1 (3.0) 
23.9 (2.7) 
23.8 (2.8) 
0.061 
Education level (%) 
Elementary school graduate 
Middle school graduate 
High school graduate 
College graduate or higher </p>

<p>40.8 
22.0 
28.6 
8.6 </p>

<p>36.8 
24.3 
26.3 
12.6 </p>

<p>24.4 
24.0 
35.7 
15.9 </p>

<p>20.3 
24.2 
38.1 
17.5 </p>

<p>24.8 
23.3 
36.1 
15.8 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Income level (KRW/mo.) (%) 
&lt; 1 million 
1 million-1.99 million 
2 million-2.99 million 
&gt; 3 million </p>

<p>44.5 
27.8 
14.4 
13.3 </p>

<p>39.6 
30.7 
16.6 
13.1 </p>

<p>28.5 
32.5 
19.5 
19.5 </p>

<p>23.2 
31.4 
23.5 
22.0 </p>

<p>26.3 
31.0 
20.7 
22.0 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Physical activity, mean (SD) (METs/day) 
1,707.7 (1,120.0) 
1,636.0 (1,116.1) 
1,469.7 (1,031.4) 
1,416.8 (964.0) 
1,470.3 (986.9) 
&lt; 0.001 
Alcohol consumption, mean (SD) (g/day) 
20.5 (46.2) 
16.3 (40.0) 
20.4 (51.9) 
15.3 (37.6) 
16.0 (44.7) 
0.001 
Smoking, mean (SD) (pack-year) 
8.4 (15.6) 
7.3 (15.3) 
6.2 (13.9) 
5.4 (12.1) 
4.7 (11.5) 
&lt; 0.001 
Component of metabolic syndrome* (%) 
Abdominal obesity 
High blood pressure 
High fasting blood glucose 
High triglyceride 
Low HDL Cholesterol </p>

<p>26.7 
24.4 
5.6 
29.9 
39.5 </p>

<p>27.8 
22.1 
6.7 
28.6 
46.1 </p>

<p>26.3 
17.5 
6.9 
27.7 
44.5 </p>

<p>20.5 
18.1 
5.8 
28.2 
45.3 </p>

<p>25.4 
19.5 
6.5 
24.8 
43.8 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
0.618 
0.008 
0.006 </p>

<p>*Abdominal obesity, waist circumference of &gt; 90 cm for men and &gt; 85 cm for women; high blood pressure, systolic/diastolic blood pressure &gt; 130/85 mmHg; high fasting 
blood glucose, fasting blood glucose &gt; 100 mg/dL; high triglyceride, triglyceride &gt; 150 mg/dL; low high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, HDL cholesterol &lt; 40 mg/dL in 
men and &lt; 50 mg/dL in women. KRW/mo., Korean Won/month; MET, Metabolic Equivalent. </p>

<p>Table 2. Characteristic of participants according to the frequency of milk consumption at baseline </p>

<p>Parameters 
Frequency of milk intake (times/week) </p>

<p>None 
1 
2-3 
4-6 
≥ 7 
P value </p>

<p>No. of subjects 
2,658 
985 
1,068 
937 
1,592 
Age, mean (SD) (yr) 
52.7 (9.2) 
50.5 (8.4) 
49.2 (7.9) 
49.6 (8.2) 
51.2 (8.6) 
&lt; 0.001 
Female (%) 
47.9 
42.8 
47.4 
52.6 
57.7 
&lt; 0.001 
Body mass index, mean (SD) (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
23.8 (3.0) 
23.9 (2.8) 
24.0 (2.8) 
24.0 (2.8) 
23.7 (2.8) 
0.014 
Education level (%) 
Elementary school graduate 
Middle school graduate 
High school graduate 
College graduate or higher </p>

<p>38.4 
21.5 
29.3 
10.9 </p>

<p>26.3 
26.6 
33.5 
13.7 </p>

<p>19.6 
22.4 
38.6 
19.4 </p>

<p>19.7 
25.1 
37.3 
17.8 </p>

<p>25.9 
24.5 
35.0 
14.5 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Income level (KRW/mo.) (%) 
&lt; 1 million 
1 million-1.99 million 
2 million-2.99 million 
&gt; 3 million </p>

<p>39.1 
28.9 
15.5 
16.5 </p>

<p>33.9 
32.9 
18.5 
14.7 </p>

<p>22.4 
30.7 
23.3 
23.7 </p>

<p>23.1 
32.5 
24.8 
19.6 </p>

<p>28.7 
30.9 
19.8 
20.7 </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Physical activity, mean (SD) (METs/day) 
1,601.7 (1,081.2) 
1,599.6 (1,081.2) 
1,358.2 (932.7) 
1,431.0 (959.6) 
1,541.1 (1,032.8) 
&lt; 0.001 
Alcohol consumption, mean (SD) (g/day) 
17.8 (43.6) 
19.6 (49.7) 
19.1 (44.9) 
15.4 (40.5) 
15.8 (44.0) 
0.082 
Smoking, mean (SD) (pack-year) 
7.3 (15.2) 
7.1 (14.1) 
5.5 (12.3) 
4.9 (11.8) 
4.7 (11.4) 
&lt; 0.001 
Component of metabolic syndrome* (%) 
Abdominal obesity 
High blood pressure 
High fasting blood glucose 
High triglyceride 
Low HDL Cholesterol </p>

<p>26.8 
22.9 
5.8 
28.9 
43.5 </p>

<p>25.8 
19.5 
7.2 
29.0 
45.5 </p>

<p>20.8 
18.4 
5.7 
28.8 
43.5 </p>

<p>24.2 
17.0 
6.1 
26.7 
43.0 </p>

<p>25.9 
19.8 
7.0 
23.2 
43.1 </p>

<p>0.003 
&lt; 0.001 
0.312 
0.001 
0.783 </p>

<p>*Abdominal obesity, waist circumference of &gt; 90 cm for men and &gt; 85 cm for women; high blood pressure, systolic/diastolic blood pressure &gt; 130/85 mmHg; high fasting 
blood glucose, fasting blood glucose &gt; 100 mg/dL; high triglyceride, triglyceride &gt; 150 mg/dL; low high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, HDL cholesterol &lt; 40 mg/dL in 
men and &lt; 50 mg/dL in women. </p>

<p>Shin H, et al. • Dairy Product Intake and Metabolic Syndrome </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.10.1482 </p>

<p>obesity (14.0%), hypertriglycerides (13.8%), high fasting blood 
glucose levels (13.3%), and high blood pressure (13.1%). Accor-
ding to the age-and sex-adjusted model, the risk of MetS was 
inversely associated with dairy product consumption (P for trend 
&lt; 0.001, Table 3). In this model, the risk of MetS was significant-
ly decreased in participants who consumed dairy products two 
to three times per week with a hazard ratio (HR) of 0.82 (95% 
confidence interval [CI], 0.68-0.99) as compared with those who 
never consumed dairy products. For participants who consum-
ed dairy products seven or more times a week, the HR was 0.72 </p>

<p>(95% CI, 0.62-0.84). Using the multivariate model, the HR for 
MetS for participants who consumed dairy products seven or 
more times a week was 0.75 (95% CI, 0.64-0.88), which was slight-
ly higher than the HR of the age-and sex-adjusted model. The 
trend test in the multivariate model was statistically significant 
across the frequency of dairy product consumption (P &lt; 0.001, 
Table 3). Analyses of the individual MetS components revealed 
that only abdominal obesity showed an inverse relationship with 
the frequency of dairy product consumption. The consumption 
of dairy products seven or more times per week was associated </p>

<p>Table 3. Hazard ratios (HRs) for the association between dairy product consumption and incident metabolic syndrome </p>

<p>Frequency of dairy product intake (times/week) 
None 
1 
2-3 
4-6 
≥ 7 
P for trend </p>

<p>Metabolic syndrome, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>1,446 (307) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>1,022 (193) 
0.93 (0.78-1.12) 
0.94 (0.78-1.13) </p>

<p>1,070 (174) 
0.82 (0.68-0.99) 
0.84 (0.70-1.02) </p>

<p>1,282 (199) 
0.80 (0.67-0.96) 
0.83 (0.69-1.00) </p>

<p>2,420 (367) 
0.72 (0.62-0.84) 
0.75 (0.64-0.88) </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
Components of metabolic syndrome 
Abdominal obesity, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>1,214 (231) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>854 (154) 
0.99 (0.80-1.21) 
0.92 (0.50-1.14) </p>

<p>912 (167) 
1.03 (0.84-1.26) 
1.05 (0.85-1.28) </p>

<p>1,144 (162 ) 
0.80 (0.65-0.98) 
0.82 (0.67-1.01) </p>

<p>2,098 (302) 
0.72 (0.61-0.86) 
0.73 (0.61-0.88) </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
High blood pressure, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>1,073 (209) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>778 (149) 
1.07 (0.87-1.32) 
1.11 (0.90-1.38) </p>

<p>862 (145) 
0.98 (0.79-1.21) 
1.03 (0.83-1.28) </p>

<p>1,027 (149 ) 
0.87 (0.71-1.08) 
0.95 (0.76-1.18) </p>

<p>1,903 (296) 
0.92 (0.77-1.10) 
0.97 (0.80-1.16) </p>

<p>0.143 
0.380 
High fasting blood glucose, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>1,122 (228) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>787 (148) 
0.98 (0.79-1.21) 
1.01 (0.81-1.26) </p>

<p>861 (127) 
0.81 (0.64-1.01) 
0.83 (0.66-1.04) </p>

<p>1,038 (157 ) 
0.85 (0.69-1.06) 
0.90 (0.72-1.12) </p>

<p>1,937 (300) 
0.89 (0.74-1.06) 
0.91 (0.75-1.10) </p>

<p>0.134 
0.268 
High triglyceride, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>1,004 (226) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>723 (139) 
0.86 (0.69-1.06) 
0.86 (0.69-1.07) </p>

<p>756 (132) 
0.76 (0.61-0.94) 
0.78 (0.62-0.97) </p>

<p>912 (178) 
0.89 (0.73-1.09) 
0.92 (0.75-1.13) </p>

<p>1,805 (327) 
0.81 (0.68-0.96) 
0.85 (0.71-1.02) </p>

<p>0.058 
0.224 
Low HDL Cholesterol, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>865 (273) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>544 (163) 
1.02 (0.84-1.23) 
1.01 (0.83-1.23) </p>

<p>576 (149) 
0.75 (0.62-0.92) 
0.79 (0.64 ,0.97) </p>

<p>685 (191) 
0.89 (0.74-1.08) 
0.92 (0.76-1.12) </p>

<p>1,340 (394) 
0.91 (0.78-1.06) 
0.95 (0.81-1.13) </p>

<p>0.185 
0.572 </p>

<p>Model 1; adjusted for age (continuous), sex (category). Model 2; adjusted for age (continuous), sex (category), physical activity (continuous), daily alcohol consumption (contin-
uous), smoking pack-year (continuous), income (category), education (category), total energy intake (continuous). </p>

<p>Table 4. Hazard ratios (HRs) for the association between milk intake and incident metabolic syndrome </p>

<p>Variables 
Frequency of milk intake (times/week) 
P for trend 
None 
1 
2-3 
4-6 
≥ 7 </p>

<p>Metabolic syndrome, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>2,658 (524) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>985 (171) 
0.90 (0.75-1.07) 
0.92 (0.77-1.19) </p>

<p>1,068 (157) 
0.84 (0.70-1.01) 
0.88 (0.73-1.06) </p>

<p>937 (142) 
0.80 (0.66-0.97) 
0.83 (0.69-1.01) </p>

<p>1,592 (246) 
0.77 (0.66-0.90) 
0.79 (0.67-0.92) </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001 
0.002 
Components of metabolic syndrome 
Abdominal obesity, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>2,243 (402) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>831 (145) 
1.01 (0.84-1.23) 
1.01 (0.83-1.22) </p>

<p>953 (145) 
0.96 (0.79-1.16) 
1.03 (0.85-1.25) </p>

<p>816 (116) 
0.84 (0.68-1.03) 
0.88 (0.71-1.09) </p>

<p>1,379 (208) 
0.81 (0.68-0.95) 
0.82 (0.68-0.97) </p>

<p>0.005 
0.019 
High blood pressure, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>2,006 (380) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>777 (139) 
1.01 (0.84-1.24) 
1.05 (0.86-1.28) </p>

<p>853 (118) 
0.86 (0.70-1.06) 
0.92 (0.75-1.14) </p>

<p>763 (112) 
0.92 (0.74-1.13) 
0.94 (0.76-1.17) </p>

<p>1,244 (199) 
0.94 (0.79-1.12) 
0.96 (0.80-1.14) </p>

<p>0.294 
0.448 
High fasting blood glucose, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>2,479 (391) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>900 (135) 
0.97 (0.79-1.19) 
0.98 (0.79-1.20) </p>

<p>1000 (119) 
0.80 (0.65-0.99) 
0.82 (0.66 ,1.02) </p>

<p>868 (121) 
0.98 (0.79-1.21) 
0.98 (0.79-1.22) </p>

<p>1,458 (194) 
0.94 (0.78-1.12) 
0.94 (0.78-1.13) </p>

<p>0.414 
0.447 
High triglyceride, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>1,872 (380) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>687 (145) 
1.06 (0.88-1.29) 
1.06 (0.87-1.29) </p>

<p>750 (125) 
0.84 (0.69-1.03) 
0.86 (0.70-1.06) </p>

<p>681 (129) 
0.99 (0.81-1.21) 
1.02 (0.83-1.25) </p>

<p>1,210 (223) 
0.94 (0.79-1.10) 
0.97 (0.82-1.16) </p>

<p>0.333 
0.680 
Low HDL cholesterol, No. (No. of cases) 
Model 1 
Model 2 </p>

<p>1,478 (439) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>527 (154) 
1.08 (0.90-1.30) 
1.10 (0.91-1.32) </p>

<p>592 (155) 
0.94 (0.79-1.14) 
0.99 (0.82-1.19) </p>

<p>524 (157) 
1.08 (0.90-1.30) 
1.16 (0.96-1.40) </p>

<p>889 (265) 
1.02 (0.87-1.19) 
1.07 (0.91-1.20) </p>

<p>0.789 
0.313 </p>

<p>Model 1; adjusted for age (continuous), sex (category). Model 2; adjusted for age (continuous), sex (category), physical activity (continuous), daily alcohol consumption (continu-
ous), smoking pack-year (continuous), income (category), education (category), total energy intake (continuous). </p>

<p>Shin H, et al. • Dairy Product Intake and Metabolic Syndrome </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.10.1482 </p>

<p>with a decreased risk of abdominal obesity in both models (HR, 
0.73; 95% CI, 0.61-0.88, P for trend &lt; 0.001 with multivariate 
model). The age-and sex-adjusted model showed that partici-
pants who consumed dairy products seven or more times per 
week had a significantly lower risk of hypertriglyceridemia (HR, 
0.81; 95% CI, 0.68-0.96) with marginal significance in the trend 
test. However, we found no significant association between dairy 
product intake and MetS components other than abdominal 
obesity in the multivariate-adjusted model. 
A similar trend was observed for milk intake (Table 4). The 
multivariate model revealed that milk intake was inversely as-
sociated with the risk of abdominal obesity and MetS and show-
ed a dose-response relationship such that the more frequently 
milk was consumed, the lower the risk of abdominal obesity and 
MetS was. The HR of the most frequent milk intake (&gt; 7 times/ 
week) compared to none was 0.79 (95% CI, 0.67-0.92) for MetS 
and 0.82 (95% CI, 0.68-0.97) for abdominal obesity. No associa-
tions with other components of MetS were observed. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our community-based prospective study of 7,240 middle-aged 
men and women revealed an inverse association between dairy 
product consumption and the risk of abdominal obesity and 
MetS. Our results agreed with those of previous studies (6, 16- 19). Literature reviews of the effects of dairy products on MetS 
and risk factors for cardiovascular disease suggest that dairy 
products play a role in the prevention of MetS development (16,  17). van Meijl et al. (16) reported that various cross-sectional 
studies support an inverse association between dairy product 
consumption and the prevalence of MetS in some, but not all, 
populations. Recently, Otsuka et al. (18) examined the associa-
tion between the number of MetS components and dietary fac-
tors in community-dwelling middle-aged and elderly Japanese 
subjects. In this cross-sectional study, a low intake of calcium, 
milk, and dairy products was associated with a high number of 
MetS components after adjusting for possible confounders, 
particularly in women. Nevertheless, the authors concluded 
that the majority of epidemiological studies showed an associa-
tion between dairy product consumption and a lower risk of 
MetS. 
In our previous study, both obesity and abdominal obesity 
were associated with dairy product consumption (19). The re-
sults of present study are consistent with those of previous stu-
dies (6, 20) suggesting a protective effect of dairy product con-
sumption on obesity. Furthermore, a systematic review of pro-
spective cohort studies concluded that dairy product consump-
tion had a protective effect on the risk of obesity (6). Calcium, 
one of the many nutrients in dairy products, has been exten-
sively investigated for its effect on weight loss. In a recent review 
of dairy product consumption and weight loss, Abargouei et al. </p>

<p>(21) reported that epidemiological studies demonstrated low 
calcium intake was a risk factor for obesity in various popula-
tion groups. The Coronary Artery Risk Development in Young 
Adults (CARDIA) study comprising 3,157 black and white adults 
aged 18 to 30 yr of age (22), found that the odds ratio for lower-
ing the risk for obesity by adding one serving per day of dairy 
products was 0.82 (0.72-0.93) over the next 10 yr. A recent cross-
sectional study on supplementary or dietary calcium intake 
and the risk of obesity in 8,127 Chinese men and women found 
an inverse relationship in women with a 14% reduction in ab-
dominal obesity with the increase of each quartile of dietary 
calcium (23). Our finding of a significant inverse association 
between dairy product intake and abdominal obesity is consis-
tent with these results. 
A previous urban population-based cohort study with an av-
erage 12-yr follow-up period reported that a high intake of fer-
mented milk, but not other dairy products including non-fer-
mented milk or cheese, was associated with a decreased risk of 
cardiovascular disease (24). A study analyzing US National Heal-
th and Nutrition Examination Survey 1999-2004 data for adult 
population revealed an inverse association between whole milk, 
yogurt, calcium, and magnesium intake, and metabolic disor-
ders (20). These investigators reported that the intake of one 
more daily serving of yogurt, but not other dairy products, low-
ered the risk of MetS by 60% (OR, 0.40; 95% CI, 0.18-0.89). Fur-
thermore, the authors suggested that ethnic differences in dairy 
product consumption and nutrient intake from dairy products, 
such as magnesium or phosphorus, might explain variations in 
the effect of dairy products on MetS. Moreover, they suggested 
that because of the complexity of the effect of dairy products and 
their nutrient contents on health, MetS might not have been a 
useful endpoint for the study. Although some studies resulted 
in the positive effect of conjugated linoleic acid in dairy fat on 
protecting metabolic syndrome, low fat dairy product is recom-
mended to reduce cardiovascular risks (16). Overall, different 
components of diary products act synergistically, showing ben-
eficial effects on prevention of metabolic syndrome. In the pre-
sent study of Korean adults, most of the dairy product consum-
ed was whole milk and yogurt because low-fat milk is not pop-
ular. Thus, the lack of significant association between dairy pro-
duct intake and the lipid related components of MetS in this 
population may be explained by the lack of variation in dairy 
products consumed. 
Although dairy product consumption has rapidly increased 
over the last few decades in Asia, consumption in Western coun-
tries is at least twice that of East Asian countries (25). According 
to the 2008 KNHANES (26), less than 10% of adults aged 50-64 
yr old reported milk consumption at dietary intake assessment 
using 24-h recall method. The average intake of dairy products 
of people aged 50-64 yr was 52.69 ± 4.16 g/day, which is lower 
than the average dairy product intake of all subjects (94.58 ± </p>

<p>Shin H, et al. • Dairy Product Intake and Metabolic Syndrome </p>

<p>http://jkms.org </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3346/jkms.2013.28.10.1482 </p>

<p>3.13 g/day). Thus, the results of the present study confirm the 
protective effect of dairy products against obesity and MetS in 
Asian population with low dairy product consumption. Fur-
thermore, the prospective cohort data in our study supports the 
temporal causal-relationship between dairy product consump-
tion and MetS. 
The present study has several strengths. The large sample 
size in the community setting increased the generalizability of 
our results. Furthermore, the high response rate, comprehen-
sive data collection through face-to-face interviews, inclusion 
of demographic and lifestyle factors, and the use of a validated 
FFQ all strengthened the results of our study. In the statistical 
analysis of this study, most well-known factors affecting MetS 
were included in the analysis as covariates, such as age, sex, phy-
sical activity, alcohol consumption, total energy intake, smok-
ing status, education, and income . Due to the multicolinearity 
problem among dietary factors, we took parsimonious model 
for the statistical analysis by including total energy intake as 
one of the covariates. However, our follow-up period may have 
been a limitation. An average of 45.5 months follow-up period 
may not have been long enough to observe a dietary effect on 
components of MetS other than abdominal obesity. Thus, the 
possibility of a type 2 error existed and our study may lack enou-
gh power to detect other associations. However, the substantial 
incidence of abdominal obesity and MetS indicated sufficient 
statistical power to detect these differences. Future studies with 
greater statistical power are warranted to further examine the 
relationship between dairy product consumption and the risk 
of MetS components other than abdominal obesity. 
Overall, the results of our study suggest that dairy product in-
take is an important dietary factor for lowering the risk of ab-
dominal obesity and MetS in middle-aged Koreans. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank the Korea National Institute of Health for providing 
data. </p>

<p>DISCLOSURE </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. </p>



<p>Shin H, et al. • Dairy Product Intake and Metabolic Syndrome </p>





</text></tei>