<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3598424" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>In a non-model staple crop like wheat (Triticum aestivumI L.), functional validation of potential drought stress respon-
sive genes identified in Arabidopsis could provide gene targets for breeding. Virus-induced gene silencing (VIGS) of 
genes of interest can overcome the inherent problems of polyploidy and limited transformation potential that hamper 
functional validation studies in wheat. In this study, three potential candidate genes shown to be involved in abi-
otic stress response pathways in Arabidopsis thaliana were selected for VIGS experiments in wheat. These include 
Era1 (enhanced response to abscisic acid), Cyp707a (ABA 8'-hydroxylase), and Sal1 (inositol polyphosphate 1-phos-
phatase). Gene homologues for these three genes were identified in wheat and cloned in the viral vector barley stripe 
mosaic virus (BSMV) in the antisense direction, followed by rub inoculation of BSMV viral RNA transcripts onto wheat 
plants. Quantitative real-time PCR showed that VIGS-treated wheat plants had significant reductions in target gene 
transcripts. When VIGS-treated plants generated for Era1 and Sal1 were subjected to limiting water conditions, they 
showed increased relative water content, improved water use efficiency, reduced gas exchange, and better vigour 
compared to water-stressed control plants inoculated with RNA from the empty viral vector (BSMV 0 ). In comparison, 
the Cyp707a-silenced plants showed no improvement over BSMV 0 -inoculated plants under limited water condition. 
These results indicate that Era1 and Sal1 play important roles in conferring drought tolerance in wheat. Other traits 
affected by Era1 silencing were also studied. Delayed seed germination in Era1-silenced plants suggests this gene 
may be a useful target for developing resistance to pre-harvest sprouting. </p>

<p>Drought is a major problem that affects wheat production 
worldwide. Tolerance to water stress is a quantitative trait 
with a complex phenotype that is often confounded by plant 
phenology (Fleury et al., 2010). Because of the complexity 
of water stress tolerance and the effect of other harsh envi-
ronmental factors in the field, improvement of this trait has 
largely relied on direct phenotypic selection for improved </p>

<p>performance under drought conditions. On the other hand, 
the application of genomic tools in Arabidopsis has produced 
large datasets of gene expression profiles that result from 
exposure to water stress (Seki et al., 2001). Experimental 
validation of candidate genes identified from such transcript 
profiling studies has identified genes that appear to contrib-
ute to plant performance under limiting water conditions in </p>



<p>greenhouse studies. Two such genes are Era1 and Cyp707a, 
which are both involved in abscisic acid (ABA) regulation 
in the abiotic stress pathway. Era1 is a gene that encodes the 
β-subunit of farnesyltransferase (Cutler et al., 1996), whose 
loss of function in Arabidopsis thaliana caused greater ABA-
induced guard cell S-type anion-channel activation and a 
rapid increase in the cytosolic Ca 2+ concentration. Era1 
mutation resulted in significantly tighter stomatal closure at 
a wide range of physiologically relevant ABA concentrations 
(Pei et al., 1998; Allen et al., 2002). Transgenic Brassica napus 
silenced for Era1 showed enhanced ABA sensitivity as well as 
significant reduction in stomatal conductance and water tran-
spiration under drought stress conditions (Wang et al., 2005). 
Cyp707a is a catabolic gene encoding ABA 8'-hydroxylase, 
an enzyme playing a key role in ABA catabolism and in con-
trolling ABA levels in various aspects of the plant life cycle 
(Kushiro et al., 2004). The Cyp707a gene reportedly degrades 
ABA during seed imbibition and dehydration stress (Kushiro 
et al., 2004; Saito et al., 2004). A T-DNA insertion mutant 
of Cyp707a3, which is the most abundantly expressed gene 
among the four Cyp707a members under stress conditions, 
exhibited elevated drought tolerance with a concomitant 
reduction in transpiration rate (Umezawa et al., 2006). A third 
gene is Sal1, an inositol polyphosphate1-phosphatase-encod-
ing gene. Sal1 was originally isolated from Arabidopsis for its 
ability to complement a salt-sensitive yeast strain (Quintero 
et al., 1996). In Arabidopsis, mutation of this gene has shown 
increased drought tolerance (Wilson et al., 2009). Sal1 acts 
as a negative regulator of predominantly ABA-independent 
and also ABA-dependent stress response pathways. As far 
as is known, none of these three genes have been experimen-
tally proven to have a role in drought tolerance in wheat. 
Furthermore, wheat homologues for Sal1 have not been iden-
tified prior to this study. 
Homologous genes in different species may not have the 
same function due to the different course of evolution that 
each species has taken. The high frequencies of duplication 
and deletion events in the wheat genome make it difficult to 
predict the function of a gene in one species based on the func-
tion of the homologous gene in the other species (Dubcovsky 
and Dvorak, 2007). Furthermore, it has been shown that 
while common regulatory mechanisms exist across species in 
response to abiotic stress, the conservation of the molecular 
response to dehydration across experiments (Mohammadi 
et al., 2007; Aprile et al., 2009) is low due to variation in stress 
dynamics, stage of development and tissue analysed. 
Functional validation of the role of genes in stress can be 
studied either by overexpression or downregulation. For gene 
overexpression studies, full-length sequence information and 
an efficient genetic transformation protocol are required. 
However, wheat has been the most recalcitrant cereal spe-
cies to culture in vitro (Shah et al., 2009). Transformation 
in wheat is still confined mainly to a few responsive varie-
ties with quite different transformation frequencies such as 
the model spring genotype 'Bobwhite' (Cheng et al., 1997, 
2003; Hu et al., 2003). For downregulation studies, knockout 
mutants are used. Not only will this require a transforma-
tion step, but the functional redundancy of homeologous </p>

<p>genes present in the other wheat genomes could complement 
the absence of gene expression resulting from a single gene 
knockout (Lawrence and Pikaard, 2003). This limitation 
can be overcome by generating double and triple mutants, 
although this process is cumbersome and time consuming. 
Therefore, faster alternatives are required for functional gene 
analysis in polyploid wheat. 
Virus-induced gene silencing (VIGS) provides an alterna-
tive strategy for gene functional analysis through the simul-
taneous knockdown of expression of multiple related gene 
copies. This is a technique that was first developed in dicots 
(Burch-Smith et al., 2006) and is based on post-transcriptional 
gene silencing of host sequences that are complementary to 
host-derived sequences contained in a recombinant viral vec-
tor inoculated on plants. VIGS was developed in barley using 
barley stripe mosaic virus (BSMV), a natural pathogen in 
this species and consisting of a tripartite genome (Holzberg 
et al., 2002; Lu et al., 2003). The usefulness of VIGS in wheat 
was first demonstrated by Scofield et al. (2005) and has now 
been used to study genes for resistance to pathogens and the 
Russian wheat aphid (Scofield et al., 2005; Cloutier et al., 
2007; Zhou et al., 2007; Van Eck et al, 2010). VIGS has not 
been used for characterization of water stress response genes 
in wheat. 
The main objective of this study was to evaluate the roles 
of Era1, Cyp707a, and Sal1 in the response of wheat to limit-
ing water conditions using VIGS. Optimization of the VIGS 
protocol was required in order to accomplish this. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant material 
All experiments were conducted using hexaploid spring wheat 
(Triticum aestivum L.) cv UC1041, a breeding line (Yecora 
Rojo/'Tadinia') from the University of California-Davis Wheat 
Breeding Program, which was kindly provided by Dr Jorge 
Dubcovsky. </p>

<p>Silencing construct development 
PCR products used in the construction of silencing vectors 
were amplified from wheat cDNA using the VIGS primers listed 
in Table 1. Primers were designed using Primer3 (Rozen and 
Skaletsky, 2000) and used to amplify a 297-bp fragment of Cyp707a 
(accession EU430344.1) and a 316-bp fragment of Era1 (accession 
ABI74692). For identification of Sal1 sequences in wheat, anno-
tated Arabidopsis Sal1 (TAIR accession 4010745380) sequences 
were screened against publicly available wheat expressed sequence 
tag sequences (http://wheat.pw.usda.gov/wEST/) which were then 
assembled into one contig using CAP3 at a stringency level of 
95% similarity over a 20-bp overlap (Huang and Madan, 1999). 
The assembled sequences were validated by PCR amplification of 
wheat cDNA followed by sequencing, resulting in a 1077-bp region. 
A PCR product of 275 bp was generated from this 1077 bp using 
primers listed in Table1. 
Vector constructs were made by the method described by Cakir 
and Scofield (2008). The orientation of the cloned inserts was deter-
mined via PCR using a combination of vector-specific (Cakir and 
Scofield, 2008) and fragment-specific primers (Table 1). Clones puta-
tively containing the fragments in the antisense orientation relative 
to the γ genes were sequenced to confirm their identity and subse-
quently used for gene silencing. </p>

<p>VIGS for functional analysis of drought tolerance genes in wheat | 1383 </p>

<p>Viral inoculation 
The α, β, and γ RNAs of the BSMV genome were synthesized 
from linearized plasmids containing cloned cDNA genome seg-
ments (Petty et al., 1989), using the mMessage mMachine T7 kit 
(Ambion, Austin, TX, USA). Capped in vitro transcripts of each 
RNA segment were combined in an equimolar ratio and added to 
an abrasive FES buffer (0.1 m glycine, 0.06 m K 2 HPO 4 , 1% w/v tet-
rasodium pyrophosphate, 1% w/v bentonite, 1% w/v celite, pH 8.5) 
according to the procedures of Scofield et al. (2005). Each silencing 
construct consisted of BSMV α, β, and γ with the target gene insert. 
The original BSMV, BSMV 0 , was used as the viral control, and was 
constituted from α, β, and γ RNA derived from the original empty 
pSL038-1 vector. A volume corresponding to 3 μg viral RNA was 
rub inoculated onto the second leaf of silenced seedlings at the 3-4 
leaf stage. For Era1, another silencing experiment was done at the 
booting stage by rub inoculating the stem just underneath the grow-
ing spike. Seeds were collected at 23 days post-inoculation (dpi). </p>

<p>Quantitative PCR 
Eleven days after viral inoculation of plants, leaf tissue was collected 
to determine the efficiency of silencing. Quantitative real-time PCR 
(qRT-PCR) was performed to determine changes in Era1, Sal1, and 
Cyp707a transcript abundance in each treatment group. All the qRT-
PCR primers are listed in Table 1. The distal 5 cm of the third leaf 
from four experimental plants per treatment was collected into liquid 
nitrogen. For Era1 inflorescence silencing, heads from silenced spikes 
were harvested on day 17 after viral inoculation. First-strand cDNA 
synthesis was conducted using the Retroscript reagent (Ambion) on 
purified RNA for each sample and primed with a mix of poly A and 
random decamers. All amplifications were performed on the iCycler 
iQ instrument (Biorad, Hercules, CA, USA) using the Perfecta SYBR 
Green Supermix (Quanta Biosciences, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) and 
input cDNA equivalent to 2.5 ng total RNA. The following cycling 
parameters were used: initial denaturation at 95 °C for 2 min, 30 
cycles consisting of denaturation at 95 °C for 15 s and annealing and 
extension at 57 °C for 45 s. Single-fragment amplification was verified 
by dissociation curve analysis. Gene expression values were normal-
ized as previously described (Willems et al., 2008). Relative transcript 
abundance was calibrated to the mean expression of the viral control 
(water-stressed BSMV 0 -treated plants) treatment group and normal-
ized against the level of housekeeping gene glyceraldehyde-3-phos-
phate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) in each sample (Pfaffl, 2001). </p>

<p>Imposition of water stress 
Each of the five treatment groups consisted of 10 plants. Plants were 
grown in plastic pots holding 500 g of potting mixture. Plants were </p>

<p>maintained in a temperature-controlled growth room at 22-25 °C 
and relative humidity of 60% with a 12 h photoperiod with light 
intensity ranging from 300 to 400 μE m −2 s −1 . Prophylactic meas-
ures were taken to maintain the plants disease and pest free. Samples 
from plants were not pooled, and each plant was observed as an 
independent biological replicate for a total of 10 biological rep-
licates per treatment. For each experiment, two subsets of plants 
were maintained. One set of plants was maintained at 100% field 
capacity (FC) and stress was imposed on the other set of plants by 
withholding water until 50% FC, which was achieved by withhold-
ing water continuously for 3 days. Withholding water up to 50% FC 
was found to induce the water stress phenotype in the experimental 
plants placed in 500 g of potting mix within the time frame of the 
experiment (24 days). The plants were maintained at 100% FC until 
imposition of moisture stress. Withholding of water started 3 days 
after rub inoculation of BSMV. Plants were maintained at 50% FC 
during the entire duration of the study. Soil moisture regimes were 
monitored gravimetrically by weighing the pots every day. </p>

<p>Estimation of plant water status 
To assess the drought stress effects, leaf relative water content 
(RWC) was estimated according to the method of Ekanayake et al. 
(1993). Water use efficiency (WUE, seedling dry weight increment 
per weight of water used) was also estimated. The soil evapora-
tion across all pots was assumed to be similar. Water used by the 
plant was estimated by the amount of water required to maintain 
the weight for each experimental pot with plants. At day 11 after 
initiation of water stress moisture, stress responses were assessed 
by taking leaf samples from the uppermost fully expanded leaves 
of both stressed and non-stressed plants. Samples were collected at 
midday, quickly sealed, and kept on ice. After determining the fresh 
weight, the leaf segments were floated on deionized water for 24 h 
to determine their turgid weight. The dry weight was determined 
after oven drying at 70 °C to a constant weight. The RWC was cal-
culated using the formula RWC (%) = [(W -DW) ÷ (TW -DW)] 
× 100, where W is sample fresh weight, TW is turgid weight after 
rehydrating plant sample for 24 hours, and DW is sample dry weight 
(Ekanayake et al., 1993). </p>

<p>Gas exchange 
Plants in all treatment groups (water-stressed silenced plants, 
water-stressed viral control, non-silenced well-watered (WW), and 
non-silenced water-stressed (WS) plants) were tested for variation 
in photosynthetic gas exchange since the genes under considera-
tion may have direct or indirect effects on stomatal opening/closure 
(Wang et al., 2009). The level of water stress used was selected to 
cause immediate visible phenotypes to accommodate the transient 
nature of the VIGS assay. This led to all the water-stressed wheat 
seedlings looking wilted and chlorotic compared to well-watered 
plants. To carry out the gas exchange studies, this study used a 
higher light intensity compared to normal greenhouse light condi-
tions to ensure that photosynthesis and transpiration were not light 
limited and that the difference in gas exchange among treatment 
plants is due to the effect of silencing stomatal conductance-regu-
lating genes. The light intensity was set at 800 μmol m -2 s -1 with a 
red/blue light source and the CO 2 level was set at 400 μmol mol -1 . 
A portable, open flow, gas-exchange system (LCpro+, Opti-Sciences, 
Hudson, NH, USA) was used to record the gas exchange on the fifth 
fully expanded leaf. One day prior to the gas exchange reading, the 
pots were watered to maintain the exact 50 or 100% FC depending 
on the treatment. Leaf gas-exchange rates were measured at 7, 14, 
and 20 dpi. </p>

<p>Germination study 
Seeds from plants inoculated with BSMV Era1 during the booting 
stage were collected 23 days post-inoculation. Seeds from the control </p>

<p>Table 1. Wheat primers used in this study. </p>

<p>Name/ 
Accession </p>

<p>Type 
Target 
region </p>

<p>Primer (5'-3') </p>

<p>Era1 
VIGS 
57-372 
AATGGCAGGGTCTGATGAAC 
TGCGCTGTACTGGCTAACTG 
qRT-PCR 
216-307 
TGAAGCTCATGGTGGGTACA 
AGCCAATCAAGCTAGGCAAA 
Sal1 
VIGS 
219-494 
TCTATGGTGGCCGAAGAGGA 
CCAACACGCCCAAAACAACT 
qRT-PCR 
104-201 
ACAATTGGTTGTGGTGCTGA 
AAAAACGAGGCATTCACTGG 
Cyp707a 
VIGS 
368-664 
GTCCCCAGGCCATCTTCTTC 
GTCCCCAGGCCATCTTCTTC 
qRT-PCR 
375-469 
GGGTGATCCAGGAGACGAT 
GGGAATCAGGTACCCTTGGT </p>



<p>BSMV 0 -inoculated plants were also collected. Seeds from silenced 
and control plants of similar size were surface sterilized with 5% 
(w/v) calcium hypochlorite for 15 min and washed four times with 
sterile deionized water. These seeds were then transferred to sterile 
Petri dishes (five seeds per dish) containing moist Whatman No. 1 
filter paper. Four replicates of five seeds per dish were used in each 
treatment. Seeds were allowed to germinate at room temperature 
in the dark and germination percentages were recorded daily up to 
6 days using radicle extrusion as a criterion. A seed was considered 
germinated if the radicle length was ≥2 mm. </p>

<p>Bacterial pathogen study on Era1-silenced plants under drought 
Xanthomonas translucens pv. undulosa (denoted as strain B75) and 
Xanthomonas translucens pv. translucens (denoted as strain B74) 
were incubated at 28 °C for 72 h on modified Wilbrink's media 
and a single colony was selected and grown in nutrient broth for 
16 hours at 28 °C. An aqueous suspension of 10 9 colony-forming 
units ml -1 were inoculated by syringe infiltration on the flag leaf at 
the 3-leaf stage, and the plants were incubated in the greenhouse. 
Sterilized water was used as the negative control for inoculation 
treatments. The bacterial pathogen inoculation was done at 7 dpi 
with BSMV Era1 or BSMV 0 . In a pilot study, it was determined 
that the strains used exhibit a compatible interaction with wheat 
cv. UC1041 (data not shown). Seven days after inoculation with 
X. translucens, the leaf lesion area was quantified using digital image 
analysis using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ASSESS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">American Phytopathological Society</rs>, St. Paul, MN, USA). The experiment was arranged in a 
completely random design. There were 24 individual treatments (3 
bacterial inoculants × 2 water stress conditions × 3 silencing types) 
and each of these treatments was replicated 24 times. Statistical 
analysis was carried out using the general linear model of the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">9.1</rs> statistical package (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, USA). Data were 
subjected to two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) for finding 
the effect of drought and Era1 silencing on disease, followed by a 
comparison of the means according to a Duncan's multiple range 
test at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Reduction in the transcript levels of silenced genes </p>

<p>qRT-PCR was performed to determine the transcript levels 
of Era1, Sal1, and Cyp707a in water-stressed silenced plants 
relative to the water-stressed viral controls at 11 dpi. As 
Fig. 1 shows, the transcript levels of the genes were reduced 
in silenced plants compared to transcript levels of the genes 
in plants inoculated only with BSMV 0 . Plants that were inoc-
ulated with BSMV Era1 showed average 2.3-fold and 2.6-fold 
reductions in Era1 at the inflorescence and seedling stages, 
respectively, while the mean Sal1 transcript level was reduced 
14.2-fold in BSMV Sal1 -inoculated plants (P &lt; 0.0001, Fig. 1A 
and B). The largest reduction was observed in BSMV Cyp707a 
plants with an average 22-fold reduction in transcript 
level compared to water-stressed BSMV 0 -treated plants 
(P &lt; 0.0001, Fig. 1C). 
Transcript levels were also determined in non-silenced WW 
and WS plants. The transcript levels of Sal1 and Cyp707a in 
WW and WS plants were not statistically different from water-
stressed viral control plants (P = 0.1550 and P = 0.2700, for 
Sal1 in WW and WS, respectively; P = 0.3250 and P = 0.3300 
for Cyp707a in WW and WS, respectively, Fig. 1B and C). 
Interestingly, the mean transcript levels of Era1 in WW and 
WS plants were statistically higher compared to the viral </p>

<p>controls (P &lt; 0.0350 and P &lt; 0.0175, Fig. 1A). This suggests 
that Era1 was downregulated as a result of virus infection. </p>

<p>Silencing alters the rate of gas exchange </p>

<p>Era1 and Sal1 function to modulate a plant's ABA-mediated 
stomatal response to control the rate of transpiration (Pei 
et al., 1998; Wilson et al., 2009). Cyp707a is involved in the 
catabolism of ABA and also has the potential to regulate sto-
matal response under drought (Umezawa et al., 2006). The 
present study therefore tested whether and how the rate of 
gas exchange would be affected by silencing of these genes. 
Water-stressed BSMV 0 -treated plants and non-silenced WS 
plants did not show statistically significant differences in 
stomatal conductance and transpiration rate (Fig. 2). The 
water-stressed BSMV Era1 -and BSMV Sal1 -treated lines showed 
statistically significant reductions in stomatal conductance 
and transpiration rate under limiting water conditions com-
pared to the water-stressed viral control plants at both 7 and 
14 dpi. This is consistent with previous reports of reduced sto-
matal conductance in loss-of-function mutants in Arabidopsis 
(Pei et al., 1998; Rossel et al., 2004; Wilson et al., 2009). These 
loss-of-function mutant plants also showed increased toler-
ance in drought stress conditions in greenhouse experiments. 
At 14 dpi, the transpiration level of BSMV Sal1 -treated plants 
showed further reduction in stomatal conductance rela-
tive to that at 7 dpi. A slight reduction was also observed in 
BSMV Era1 -treated plants at 14 dpi compared to 7 dpi (Fig. 2). 
On the other hand, BSMV Cyp707a -treated plants did not show 
a significant reduction in stomatal conductance compared to 
viral control plants. Photosynthesis measurements taken dur-
ing this study were inconclusive due to the total shut down 
of photosynthesis across all water-stressed treatment groups. </p>

<p>Impact of silencing on plant water status under water 
limitation </p>

<p>Water stress was examined in terms of RWC and WUE at 14 
dpi in all the treatment groups (Fig. 3). The RWC and WUE 
measurements indicate potential photosynthetic gain during 
a water stress period. The WUE values obtained were lower 
than typically observed in potted plants (usually in the range 
0.6-0.9 g kg -1 ). This is most likely a result of the plants not 
getting sufficient light in the greenhouse during the winter 
when these experiments were carried out. This would have 
resulted in reduced photosynthesis and consequently low bio-
mass gain. However, since all plants were grown under the 
same conditions, it was possible to compare plants in the dif-
ferent treatments. The non-silenced plants showed a drastic 
reduction in both WUE and RWC in the WS plants relative to 
the WW plants, which was expected. The WS plants also did 
not differ significantly from the water-stressed viral control, 
indicating that virus inoculation had no effect on these two 
measurements. Similarly, plants silenced for Cyp707a did not 
differ significantly from the viral control in both WUE and 
RWC. On the other hand, plants silenced for Era1 and Sal1 
showed significant gains in RWC and WUE over viral control 
and WS plants. </p>

<p>VIGS for functional analysis of drought tolerance genes in wheat | 1385 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Silencing efficiency as revealed by quantitative real-time PCR. Gene expression values were standardized across six 
independent biological replicates with three technical replicates. Expression of Era1 (A), Sal1 (B), and Cyp707a (C) in well-watered 
non-silenced (WW), water-stressed non-silenced (WS), and silenced plants (denoted by the gene name) at 11 dpi were calibrated to the 
mean level of expression of the respective gene in the water-stressed BSMV 0 -treated plants. </p>



<p>Plants silenced for Era1 and Sal1 showed improved 
vigour under water stress </p>

<p>Phenotypes of the plants were observed daily during the 
entire course of the experiment (27 days). Slight chlorosis was 
observed in all the silenced and viral control plants immediately 
after rub inoculation of the BSMV constructs. This has been 
reported in previous VIGS studies in wheat (Scofield et al., 
2005; Van Eck et al., 2010) and is due to the plant's response 
to virus infection. Typical wilting symptoms and poor vigour 
were observed in all water-stressed plants, whether silenced for 
a gene or not (Fig. 4). The BSMV 0 -treated control plants were 
visibly similar to the non-silenced WS plants under water stress. 
The water-stressed BSMV Cyp707a -treated plants showed similar 
symptoms as the water-stressed viral control plants. On the 
other hand, water-stressed BSMV Era1 -and BSMV Sal1 -treated 
plants showed distinctly better turgidity and appeared more 
vigourous compared to plants in all the other water-stressed 
treatments. This improved vigour held up during the entire 
24 day-stress period. Interestingly, more tillers were observed 
in BSMV Sal1 -treated plants compared to plants in all other 
treatments, including BSMV Era1 -treated plants. However, the 
BSMV Sal1 -treated plants were smaller compared to BSMV Era1 -
treated plants under limiting water conditions during the ini-
tial 5-7 days of water stress. By day 24 of water stress, both 
BSMV Era1 and BSMV Sal1 -treated plants were of similar size. 
All in all, silencing of Era1 and Sal1 had similar effects 
on the plant. This includes reduced stomatal conductance, 
increased WUE, and increased RWC. These physiological 
measurements matched the observed improved vigour in 
BSMV Era1 -and BSMV Sal1 -treated plants under water stress. 
Decreased stomatal conductance under limiting water con-
ditions may have contributed to improved WUE and RWC. 
Stomatal conductance was significantly and negatively </p>

<p>correlated with the level of expression of Era1 (r = -0.80, 
P ≤ 0.01) and Sal1 (r = −0.89, P ≤ 0.01). In comparison, 
BSMV Cyp707a -treated plants did not show significant changes 
in any of the physiological measurements or phenotypes rela-
tive to non-silenced or BSMV 0 -treated plants, despite a sig-
nificant reduction in expression level of Cyp707a. </p>

<p>Effects of Era1 silencing on seed germination and 
response to fungal pathogens </p>

<p>Silencing of Era1 potentially makes plants hypersensitive to 
ABA. Since ABA is involved in seed germination, a germina-
tion study was conducted on BSMV Era1 -treated plants. Seeds 
harvested from plants inoculated with BSMV Era1 at the boot-
ing stage were tested for germination capacity. As Fig. 5A 
shows, the earliest germination of Era1-silenced seeds 
occurred 6 days later than those of control (BSMV 0 treated) 
plants, 6-8 days after 100% of seeds from control plants have 
germinated, only 60% of seeds from Era1-silenced plants had 
germinated, and 100% germination was achieved 10 days 
later than those of control plants. 
Goritschnig et al. (2008) recently showed that loss of func-
tion in Arabidopsis results in enhanced susceptibility to viru-
lent bacterial and oomycete pathogens. This led the authors 
to suggest that farnesylation is involved in basal defence. 
To study the potential for increased susceptibility in Era1-
silenced wheat plants, two known wheat pathogenic bacte-
rial strains (X. translucens B74 and B75) were tested for their 
increase or decrease in virulence against Era1-silenced wheat 
plants compared to non-silenced wheat plants under drought 
and well-watered conditions (Fig. 5B). Two-way ANOVA 
showed no significant difference in the lesion area of plants 
under drought and silencing treatments compared to con-
trol plants in both bacterial strains (P D75 = 0.52, P s75 = 0.46 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Mean stomatal conductance (mmol m -2 s -1 ) at 7 and 14 dpi. Measurements were taken daily from each treatment group for 
14 days. Water-stressed BSMV 0 -inoculated plants served as control. Values are means of six observations. Asterisks denote significant 
difference from the control WS (P = 0.05). WW, non-silenced well-watered; WS, non-silenced water-stressed; all others plants were 
water-stressed and inoculated with BSMV targeted to specific genes. </p>

<p>VIGS for functional analysis of drought tolerance genes in wheat | 1387 </p>

<p>and P D73 = 0.51, P s73 = 0.304). Also, there was no significant 
interaction between two treatments (drought X silencing) for 
both strains' lesion area (P D75*S75 = 0.12 and P D73*S73 = 0.28), 
suggesting that a combination of drought and Era1 silenc-
ing does not affect bacterial growth in wheat individually and 
interactively. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study was undertaken to test whether single genes that 
have been shown to enhance drought tolerance in Arabidopsis 
when mutated would have similar effects in wheat. Three 
genes, namely Era1, Cyp707a, and Sal1, that represent </p>

<p>Fig. 3. (A) Water use efficiency by gravimetric determination (g kg -1 ) at the end of treatment (24 dpi). (B) Mean relative water content 
(g) per treatment at 14 dpi. Water-stressed BSMV 0 -inoculated plants served as control. Values are means of six observations. Asterisks 
denote significant difference from the control WS (P = 0.05). WW, non-silenced well-watered; WS, non-silenced water-stressed; all 
others plants were water-stressed and inoculated with BSMV targeted to specific genes. </p>



<p>different abiotic stress pathways were selected. The VIGS 
technique offered the best approach for testing the func-
tion of these genes in wheat for several reasons. The most 
important reason is that VIGS does not require a transforma-
tion step, which is still technically challenging in wheat. The 
potential of homologous copies of a gene to compensate for 
the absence of a homologue that has been silenced can be 
overcome in VIGS. All endogenous mRNA with at least 80% 
similarity to the host-derived sequence contained in the viral 
vector are targets for degradation. While this is an advantage 
of VIGS, it is also a disadvantage in that the specific gene 
responsible for the effect is not known and would require fur-
ther experiments. 
One concern of using VIGS for evaluating putative drought 
tolerance genes is the fact that environmental conditions used 
for stress induction might not favour viral replication lead-
ing to poor silencing. The stress protocol used in the pre-
sent study involved initial exposure of silenced plants to an 
acclimation stress prior to exposure to severe stress. The viral 
inoculation was done at late evening on well-watered healthy 
plants and water stress was imposed gradually over 4 dpi by 
gradually withholding water. The initial adjustment time was </p>

<p>important as the virus also imparts some level of stress on 
the plants. The protocol to characterize genes involved in the 
stress-recovery response involved inoculation of VIGS vector 
4 days prior to water stress induction to coincide with higher 
transcript downregulation of targeted genes. The levels of 
silencing (from 2.6-to 22-fold) achieved for the targeted genes 
were comparable to other VIGS wheat studies (Scofield et al., 
2005; Bruun-Rasmussen et al., 2007; Van Eck et al., 2010). 
The consistent phenotype across the silenced plants also neu-
tralized the concern of the stress response to BSMV masking 
the effect of water stress effects, suggesting that drought trait 
functional studies can be carried out by VIGS in wheat. 
Of the three genes tested, only Era1 and Sal1 showed simi-
lar phenotypes in wheat upon loss of function as has been 
reported in Arabidopsis (Wang et al., 2005; Wilson et al., 
2009). A possible role of regulation of stomatal conductance 
was indicated for the improved performance of Era1-and 
Sal1-silenced plants. Closed stomata has been suggested to 
lead to decreased photosynthesis and therefore decreased pro-
ductivity for the plant in well-watered conditions (Farquhar 
and Sharkey, 1982; Schulze, 1986). The present experiment 
observed improved WUE compared to the viral control </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Phenotypes of wheat plants at 24 dpi with BSMV RNA transcripts containing one of the following wheat genes: Sal1, Cyp707A, 
or Era1. Water stress was imposed on these plants by withholding water until 50% of field capacity. Water-stressed BSMV 0 -inoculated 
plants served as control. Non-silenced well-watered (100%), non-silenced water-stressed (50%) plants, and water-stressed (50%) plants 
were included for comparison of phenotypes. Note the improved vigour of plants silenced for Sal1 and Era1 compared to the viral 
control plants. </p>

<p>VIGS for functional analysis of drought tolerance genes in wheat | 1389 </p>

<p>water-stressed BSMV 0 -inoculated plants, indicating better 
dry weight production under limiting water condition for 
BSMV Era1 -and BSMV Sal1 -treated plants. A likely explanation 
is that plants which regulate the stomatal opening 'efficiently' 
and conserve water can achieve larger biomass per gram of 
water used (Farquhar and Richards 1984; Araus et al., 2008). 
In the case of Sal1, loss of function was reported to yield 
shorter and rounder leaves in Arabidopsis with an enhanced 
drought tolerance (Umezawa et al., 2006). Down-regulation of </p>

<p>Sal1 leads to constitutively increased ABA content in A. thal-
iana (Wilson et al., 2009). Sal1 acts as a negative regulator of 
predominantly ABA-independent as well as ABA-dependent 
stress response pathways, such that its inactivation results in 
altered osmoprotectants, higher leaf RWC, and maintenance 
of viable tissues during prolonged water stress (Wilson et al., 
2009). This study also showed that reduced expression of Sal1 
in wheat resulted in increased RWC, and increased WUE, as 
well as improved vigour, suggesting a similar function of Sal1 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Effect of Era1 silencing on wheat seed germination and response to pathogens. (A) Number of germinated seeds in Era1-
silenced and non-silenced plants, determined according to the 2-mm radicle extrusion criterion. (B) Cumulative lesion area observed 
after 7 days post infection with Xanthomonas translucens B74 and B75 on Era1-silenced or non-silenced plants under drought or 
non-drought conditions. Era1, plants silenced in Era1; BSMV 0 , plants inoculated with empty BSMV viral vector; non-silenced, plants not 
inoculated with BSMV. </p>



<p>in wheat. No other unusual phenotype was observed except 
increased/accelerated tillering, which is difficult to interpret 
at this point due to limited understanding of the mode of 
action of Sal1. 
Interestingly, the effect of silencing Cyp707a homologues 
in wheat was different from previous findings in Arabidopsis. 
Loss of function of Cyp707a was reported to enhance drought 
tolerance in A. thaliana (Umezawa et al., 2006). In contrast, 
Cyp707a-silenced wheat plants did not show any improve-
ments in terms of dry weight, WUE, or RWC of silenced 
plants compared to water-stressed BSMV 0 -treated control 
plants under water stress. The differences in response between 
Arabidopsis and wheat plants to loss of function of Cyp707a 
may be due to differences in stress adaptation pathways 
between wheat and Arabidopsis. Another possible reason for 
the observed difference may have to do with the structure of 
the Cyp707a gene family in the two species. In A. thaliana, the 
Cyp707a gene family consists of Cyp707a1-Cyp707a4, all of 
which are upregulated in response to dehydration and subse-
quent rehydration, suggesting that the function of Cyp707a 
genes is redundant (Kushiro et al., 2004). Although there is 
only one Cyp707a cDNA sequence reported for wheat (acces-
sion EU430344.1), with three copies amplified by PCR in 
hexaploid wheat in this study, it is possible that other copies 
of Cyp707a exist in wheat. The DNA sequences of these other 
copies could potentially be different enough to cause ineffec-
tive silencing using the VIGS construct used in this study, 
leading to compensation of gene function by the remaining 
active genes. This emphasizes the importance of having the 
wheat genome sequence information in attempts to function-
ally test Arabidopsis gene homologues in wheat. 
Out of the three genes tested in this study, Era1 appeared 
to be the most promising as a potential target for drought tol-
erance breeding in wheat. Mutations in Era1 could be readily 
identified through TILLING, taking advantage of resources 
that already exist in wheat (Slade and Knauf, 2005; Uauy 
et al., 2009). Because of the role of ABA in germination and 
dormancy, the present study tested Era1-silenced plants for 
germination rates. Indeed, Era1-silencing done at the booting 
stage resulted in a 6-10-day delay in germination compared 
to non-silenced plants. This trait may provide a solution for 
tackling pre-harvest sprouting in wheat. Pre-harvest sprout-
ing is a consequence of ABA deficiency and leads to loss of 
grain weight and a reduction in end-use quality of wheat 
(Fang and Chu, 2008). While Era1 has also been suggested 
to play a role in basal defence against bacteria and oomycytes 
(Goritschnig et al., 2008), the Era1-silenced wheat plants 
showed similar phenotypes in response to bacterial infection 
as non-silenced wheat plants under both water stress and 
well-watered conditions. This implies that there is no fitness 
cost to Era1-silenced plants under favourable conditions. It 
would be interesting to further study the differences in the 
function of Era1 in pathogen susceptibility between wheat 
and Arabidopsis. 
In conclusion, this study showed the involvement of 
Era1 and Sal1 in response to water deficit stress tolerance 
in wheat. This is the first report of VIGS being successfully 
used in wheat to functionally characterize genes thought to </p>

<p>be involved in drought tolerance. The transient nature of 
VIGS did not deter from generating valuable observations 
for screening potential drought tolerant genes in wheat. One 
major strategy adopted by plants during drought tolerance 
is avoiding dehydration (Serraj and Atlin, 2009). Results 
from the present study indicate that downregulation of genes 
which reduce stomatal conductance may be a useful strategy 
for enhancing drought tolerance in wheat, if the same results 
hold in the field. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was supported by the US Department of 
Agriculture (Cooperative Agreements USDA contract nos. 
2009-34205-19960 and 2010-34205-21350 and Hatch Funds 
project no. 644, to NL). The authors thank Leon Van Eck 
(University of Stellenbosch, South Africa) and Hong Wang 
(Colorado State University) for helping with the VIGS 
experiment. </p>



<p>VIGS for functional analysis of drought tolerance genes in wheat | 1391 </p>







</text></tei>