<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3302168" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: To elucidate the activity and expression of cyclic nucleotide phosphodiesterase (PDE) families in omental (OM) and 
subcutaneous (SC) adipose tissue and adipocytes, and to study alterations in their activity in human obesity. 
Design: Cross-sectional, translational research study. 
Patients: In total, 25 obese and 9 non-obese subjects undergoing gastrointestinal surgery participated in the study. 
Results: Inverse correlations between PDE activities and body mass index (BMI) were seen in both SC and OM adipose tissue. 
Inverse correlations between total PDE and PDE3 activity and BMI were seen in OM adipocytes but not in SC adipocytes. In both 
SC and OM adipose tissue of obese patients, total PDE and PDE3 activities were decreased compared with the controls. In SC 
adipose tissue of Type 2 diabetes (T2D) patients, the PDE activity not inhibitable by PDE3 or PDE4 inhibitors (PDEn) was 
increased compared with obese non-diabetic patients. In addition to PDE3 and 4 isoforms, PDE7B, PDE9A and PDE10A proteins 
were also detected in adipose tissue or adipocytes. 
Conclusions: Multiple PDE families are present in human adipose tissue and their activities are differentially affected by obesity 
and T2D. 
The incidence of obesity in the developed world is increasing 
at an alarming rate. Concurrent with the increase in the 
incidence of obesity is an increase in the incidence of Type 2 
diabetes (T2D). It has been reported that over 80% of adults 
diagnosed with T2D are obese. 
1 The connection between </p>

<p>obesity and the development of T2D has been the focus of 
intense research in recent years. It has been demonstrated 
that a low-grade, systemic inflammation originating from 
adipose tissue is one of the factors associated with systemic 
insulin resistance. 
2 Adipose tissue secretes numerous adipo-</p>

<p>kines, which have been shown to affect whole body's insulin 
sensitivity and dysregulation of the secretion of these factors 
could contribute to the development of insulin resistance in 
obesity. 
3 Also, excess fatty acids released from the adipocytes </p>

<p>of obese persons contribute to ectopic fat storage in non-
adipose tissues such as liver and muscle, exacerbating their 
insulin resistance. </p>

<p>4   Cyclic nucleotide phosphodiesterases (PDEs) regulate in-
tracellular signaling in many different cell types by degrad-
ing cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) and cyclic 
guanosine monophosphate (cGMP). 
5 There are currently 21 </p>

<p>genes, which code for distinct PDE enzymes. The enzymes 
can be further divided, based on sequence and chemical 
properties, into 11 different families denoted PDE1-11. 
5 PDEs </p>

<p>are expressed in virtually all cell types in the body and have 
specific roles in the regulation of diverse biological functions 
by controlling discrete pools of cyclic nucleotides. Inhibitors 
to specific PDE families, such as PDE3 and PDE5 inhibitors, 
are currently used in clinical practice. </p>

<p>6,7   In adipocytes, the ability of insulin to antagonize cAMP-
induced lipolysis is mainly due to insulin-induced activation 
of PDE3B. 
8-9 PDE3B has also been shown to have a role in </p>

<p>calcium-induced anti-lipolysis in human adipocytes. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>PDE3B has a central role in the regulation of not only 
lipolysis but also other biological functions in adipocytes 
such as lipogenesis and glucose uptake, as evidenced by </p>

<p>Received 4 February 2011; revised 10 June 2011; accepted 24 June 2011 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Dr B Omar, Department of Experimental Medical Sciences, 
Division of Diabetes, Metabolism and Endocrinology, Lund University, 
Biomedical Center C11, Sölvegatan 19, Lund SE 211 84, Sweden. 
E-mail: bilal.omar@med.lu.se </p>

<p>Citation: Nutrition and Diabetes (2011) 1, e13; doi:10.1038/nutd.2011.9 
&amp; 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 2044-4052/11 
www.nature.com/nutd </p>

<p>studies with PDE3B-deficient mice and PDE3 inhibitors. </p>

<p>11,12 </p>

<p>PDE4 is another PDE, which is highly expressed in adipo-
cytes. There are four different isoforms of PDE4, which have 
been shown to be expressed in rodent adipocytes; 
13 however, </p>

<p>there is little known about their function in adipocytes. A 
deletion mutant mouse model of one PDE4 isoform suggests 
a potential role in metabolic homeostasis. Mice deficient in 
PDE4B show reduced body weight and reduced adipose 
tissue mass compared with wild-type animals, and are 
resistant to high-fat diet-induced weight gain and adipose 
tissue inflammation. 
14 Although PDE3B and PDE4 isoforms </p>

<p>appear to comprise most of the PDE activity in rodent 
adipocytes, the activity of other PDEs in adipocytes and 
adipose tissue have been described. Calcium-inducible 
(PDE1) and cGMP inducible (PDE2) PDE activities have been 
identified in rat adipocytes. 
15,16 PDE5A has been studied in </p>

<p>differentiated human adipocytes, but its expression de-
creases as adipocytes mature. 
17 The mRNA expression level </p>

<p>of a number of PDE family members has been recently 
determined in a number of rat tissues, including adipose 
tissue. 
18 Among the PDEs expressed were PDE9A, PDE10A </p>

<p>and PDE11A. 
18 The protein regulation and biological func-</p>

<p>tion of these PDEs in adipose tissue are not known at this 
time, however, there are indications that some of these 
enzymes contribute to the regulation of adipose tissue 
homeostasis. Deletion mutant mouse models of PDE9A and 
PDE10A display reduced body weight or reduced adipose 
tissue mass compared with wild-type mice. </p>

<p>19,20   Although there have been previous reports to changes in 
PDE activity in subcutaneous (SC) adipose tissue in patients 
with non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus, 
21 to date </p>

<p>there have been no thorough investigations of PDE expres-
sion and activities in different human adipose tissue depots. 
In this study, we investigated PDE expression and activities 
in human adipose tissue. We further compared the activities 
of PDEs in different adipose tissue depots in non-obese and 
obese subjects. </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>Patients 
Patients with scheduled gastrointestinal surgeries at Skåne 
University Hospital were recruited by the surgeons involved 
in the study. Adipose tissue biopsy samples, weighing 
0.25-2.5 g, were obtained from patients undergoing bariatric 
surgery or cholecystectomy operations. The criterion for 
acceptance for bariatric surgery was morbid obesity defined 
as a body mass index (BMI) greater than 35 kg m </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>. In this 
study, patients with a BMIX30 were considered obese and 
BMIo30 were considered non-obese. Subcutaneous adipose 
tissue biopsy samples were obtained from the abdomen and 
visceral adipose tissue biopsy samples were obtained from 
the greater omentum in each patient after informed consent 
was given. Patients were not excluded for any conditions and </p>

<p>a detailed accounting of all pre-existing conditions and 
medications taken by the patients was kept for reference. All 
experiments were approved by the Regional Ethics Commit-
tee in Lund, Sweden. </p>

<p>Adipocyte isolation 
Human adipocytes were isolated by collagenase digestion as 
previously described. 
22 Adipocytes were diluted in Krebs-</p>

<p>Ringer buffer containing 25 mM Hepes, 200 nM adenosine, 
2 mM glucose and 1% bovine serum albumin. Adipocytes 
were washed twice in BSA-free Krebs-Ringer buffer and 
homogenized in 1.5 volumes of a buffer containing 50 mM 
TES, 2 mM EGTA, 1 mM EDTA, 250 mM sucrose, 40 mM 
phenylphosphate, 5 mM NaF, 1 mM dithioerythriol, 0.5 mM 
sodium orthovanadate, 10 mg ml 
À1 antipain, 10 mg ml 
À1 leu-</p>

<p>peptin, 1 mg ml 
À1 pepstatin A, pH 7.4. Homogenates were </p>

<p>centrifuged at 10 000 Â g for 10 min at 4 1C, the fat cake was 
removed and protein concentrations were determined by the 
method of Bradford. </p>

<p>23   Immunoblotting 
Adipose tissue homogenates were prepared as described 
above for adipocytes. Human adipocytes and adipose tissue 
homogenates, 20 and 30 mg protein, respectively, were 
subjected to SDS-PAGE on 7-8% acrylamide gels followed 
by transfer to nitrocellulose membranes (GE Healthcare, 
Amersham UK). Membranes were blocked in 10% non-fat 
dry milk with 0.1% Tween-20 for 1 h before overnight 
incubation at 4 1C with primary antibodies (Scottish Biome-
dical, Glasgow, Scotland, UK), as indicated in Results. After 
primary antibody incubation, membranes were washed and 
incubated with HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies (Thermo 
Scientific, Rockford, IL, USA) and diluted in 5% non-fat dry 
milk for 1 h at room temperature. Chemiluminesence of 
immunoreactive bands was obtained using Supersignal West 
Pico Stable reagents (Thermo Scientific). Immunoblot images 
were captured with an IR-LAS1000 ECL camera (FUJIfilm, 
Stamford, CT, USA). </p>

<p>cAMP PDE assay 
PDE activities were measured in duplicate in the presence or 
absence of the PDE3 inhibitor OPC3911 (Otsuka Pharma-
ceuticals, Tokyo, Japan) or the PDE4 inhibitor Rolipram 
(Biomol International, Exeter, UK) as previously described. </p>

<p>24   The assay was performed at 30 1C for 45 min in a total 
volume of 300 ml of reaction buffer containing 50 mM TES, 
pH 7.4, 250 mM sucrose, 1 mM EDTA, 0.1 mM EGTA, 8.3 mM 
MgCl 2 , 0.5 mM cAMP, 1 mCi ml </p>

<p>À1 3 </p>

<p>H-cAMP and 0.6 mg ml </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>ovalbumin. PDE activity was calculated as pmol 
3 H-cAMP </p>

<p>hydrolyzed per minute per milligram of protein. The PDE3 
and PDE4 activities were calculated as the proportion of the 
total activity that is inhibited by the PDE3 and PDE4 
inhibitors, respectively. </p>

<p>Phosphodiesterase activities in obesity 
B Omar et al </p>



<p>Nutrition and Diabetes </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data are expressed as the mean ± s.e.m. Statistical signifi-
cance was determined using unpaired two-tailed Student's 
t-tests, unless otherwise indicated. Correlation was deter-
mined using Pearson's correlation coefficient. The differ-
ences were considered statistically significant if Po0.05. 
Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Graph Pad Prism</rs> 
version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, La Jolla, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Correlation between PDE activities and BMI in adipose tissue 
Analysis of adipose tissue biopsy samples revealed a sig-
nificant inverse correlation between total PDE activity and 
BMI in both SC and omental (OM) adipose tissue (Figures 1a 
and b). The total PDE activity is the sum of the activities of 
several different PDE enzyme families. Selective inhibitors to 
PDE3 and PDE4 family enzymes were used to identify PDE3 
and PDE4 activities in adipose tissues. In SC adipose tissue, 
there was a negative correlation between PDE3 activity and 
BMI, which was the strongest correlation of all measured 
(Figure 1c). The negative correlation between PDE3 activity 
and BMI in OM adipose tissue was also significant 
(Figure 1d), as was the negative correlation between PDE4 
and BMI in both depots (Supplementary Figures 1a and 1b). 
There was a substantial amount of PDE activity remaining 
after inhibiting PDE3 and PDE4. The combined activities of 
these isoforms are hereafter referred to as PDEn. PDEn 
activity was significantly negatively correlated with BMI in </p>

<p>SC adipose tissue (Supplementary Figure 1c), but did not 
correlate with BMI in OM adipose tissue (Supplementary 
Figure 1d). </p>

<p>PDE activities in adipose tissue: effects of obesity and adipose 
tissue depot 
PDE activity was investigated with respect to differences in 
obesity and between adipose tissue depots. In obese patients, 
total PDE, PDE3 and PDE4 activities were significantly 
reduced in both OM and SC adipose tissue depots compared 
with non-obese patients (Table 1). PDEn activity in SC 
adipose tissue from obese patients was significantly lower 
than that of non-obese patients (Table 1), whereas no 
differences were seen in PDEn activity in OM adipose tissue. 
When comparing the SC and OM adipose tissue depots, 
non-obese patients had no significant differences in any of 
the PDE activities, whereas obese patients had significantly </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 
20 
25 
30 
35 
40 
45 
BMI </p>

<p>50 
55 
60 
65 </p>

<p>Total PDE activity (pmol/min/mg) 
SC adipose tissue </p>

<p>Total PDE activity (pmol/min/mg) 
SC adipose tissue </p>

<p>PDE3 activity (pmol/min/mg) 
SC adipose tissue 
PDE3 activity (pmol/min/mg) 
OM adipose tissue </p>

<p>20 
25 
30 
35 
40 
45 
BMI </p>

<p>50 
55 
60 
65 
20 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>0 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>25 
30 
35 
40 
45 
BMI </p>

<p>50 
55 
60 
65 </p>

<p>35 
40 
45 
BMI </p>

<p>50 
55 
60 
65 </p>

<p>R 
2 = 0.4688 
p = 0.0004 </p>

<p>R 
2 = 0.4759 </p>

<p>p = 0.0004 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 
R 
2 = 0.3914 
p = 0.0014 </p>

<p>R 
2 = 0.4294 </p>

<p>p = 0.0007 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Correlation between BMI and PDE activities in adipose tissue. Correlation between BMI and SC (a) (n ¼ 22) or OM (b) (n ¼ 23) adipose tissue total PDE </p>

<p>activity. Correlation between BMI and SC (c) (n ¼ 22) or OM (d) (n ¼ 23) adipose tissue PDE3 activity. The squares of the Pearson correlation coefficients are shown 
on each graph. </p>

<p>Table 1 PDE activities in whole adipose tissue </p>

<p>Activity 
(pmol min 
À1 per mg) </p>

<p>Non-obese SC 
n ¼ 6 </p>

<p>Obese SC 
n ¼ 16 </p>

<p>Non-obese OM 
n ¼ 6 </p>

<p>Obese OM 
n ¼ 17 </p>

<p>Total 
18.9±4.4 
6.7±0.9 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>21.1±4.0 
11.7±1.8 </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>PDE3 
9.1±2.3 
2.8±0.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8.1±1.5 
4.2±0.8 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>PDE4 
4.1±1.4 
1.7±0.3 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>6.4±1.0 
3.4±0.8 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>PDEn 
6.3 ± 1.6 
2.3 ± 0.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.1 ± 2.1 
3.9 ± 0.5 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PDE, phosphodiesterase; OM, omental; SC, subcutaneous. 
a Non-obese SC vs obese SC, Po0.01; </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Non-obese OM vs obese OM, Po0.05; 
c Obese SC vs Obese OM, Po0.05; 
d Non-obese SC vs obese SC, Po0.05. </p>

<p>Phosphodiesterase activities in obesity 
B Omar et al </p>



<p>Nutrition and Diabetes </p>

<p>lower total PDE, PDE4 and PDEn activity in SC adipose tissue 
compared with OM adipose tissue (Table 1). PDE3 activity 
did not differ significantly between depots in obese patients. </p>

<p>PDE activity in patients with T2D 
Phosphodiesterase activities were measured in the adipose 
tissues of patients with T2D (n ¼ 5) and compared with 
patients without diabetes (n ¼ 11) with matching mean BMI. 
There was a significant increase in PDEn activity in the SC </p>

<p>adipose tissue of patients with T2D compared with obese 
patients without diabetes (Figure 2). This difference was not 
seen in OM adipose tissue. There were no other significant 
differences in PDE activities when comparing obese T2D 
patients with obese patients without diabetes. </p>

<p>PDE activities in isolated adipocytes: effects of obesity and 
adipose tissue depot 
Adipose tissue not only contains primarily adipocytes but 
also a stromal and vascular cell fraction. In a subset of 
patients, adipose tissue biopsy samples were used for 
isolation of primary adipocytes and measurement of PDE 
activities. There were inverse correlations between BMI and 
both total PDE (Figure 3b) and PDE3 activities in isolated 
adipocytes from OM adipose tissue (Figure 3d). There were 
no such correlations in the SC depot (Figures 3a and c). 
Furthermore, there were no correlations between BMI and 
PDE4 or PDEn activities in adipocytes from OM or SC depots 
(data not shown). 
There were significantly lower total PDE and PDE3 
activities in adipocytes from OM adipose tissue of obese 
patients compared with that of non-obese patients (Table 2), 
but there were no significant differences in the activities of 
PDE4 or PDEn in OM adipocytes, when comparing non-
obese and obese patients (Table 2). When comparing the 
different PDE activities in adipocytes from SC adipose tissue 
from obese and non-obese patients, no significant differ-
ences were detected (Table 2). </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ND 
T2D </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Omental 
Subcutaneous 
PDEn activity (pmol/min/mg) 
adipose tissue </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Comparison of PDEn activitiy in adipose tissue from obese non-</p>

<p>diabetic and T2D patients. PDEn activity in adipose tissue from obese non-
diabetic patients (black bars) (n ¼ 11) compared with T2D patients (white 
bars) (n ¼ 4). Data are presented as mean ± s.e. *Po0.05. </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 
Total PDE activity (pmol/min/mg protein) 
SC adipocytes </p>

<p>Total PDE activity (pmol/min/mg protein) 
OM adipocytes </p>

<p>PDE3 activity (pmol/min/mg protein) 
OM adipocytes </p>

<p>PDE3 activity (pmol/min/mg protein) 
SC adipocytes </p>

<p>25 
30 
35 
40 
45 </p>

<p>BMI </p>

<p>50 
55 
60 
65 </p>

<p>R 
2 = 0.0881 </p>

<p>R 
2 = 0.1253 </p>

<p>R 
2 = 0.3531 
p = 0.0195 </p>

<p>R 
2 = 0.3391 
p = 0.0289 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 
20 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
20 
25 
30 
35 
40 
45 
BMI </p>

<p>BMI </p>

<p>55 
60 
65 
50 </p>

<p>25 
30 
35 
40 
50 
55 
60 
65 
45 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>20 
25 
30 
35 
40 
BMI </p>

<p>45 
50 
55 
60 
65 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Correlation between BMI and PDE activities in primary adipocytes. Correlation between BMI and total PDE activity in SC (a) (n ¼ 15) or OM (b) (n ¼ 20) </p>

<p>primary adipocytes. Correlation between BMI and PDE3 activity in SC (c) (n ¼ 16) or OM (d) (n ¼ 14). The squares of the Pearson correlation coefficients are shown 
on each graph. </p>

<p>Phosphodiesterase activities in obesity 
B Omar et al </p>



<p>Nutrition and Diabetes </p>

<p>In an effort to identify which PDE proteins are expressed in 
adipose tissue and adipocytes in addition to PDE3 and 4 
isoforms, we made use of antibodies raised against multiple 
human PDE isoforms. PDE7B, PDE9A and PDE10A were 
detected in homogenates from adipose tissue (Supplemen-
tary Figure 2a), whereas in isolated adipocytes, PDE9A and 
PDE10A were detected (Supplementary Figure 2b). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study investigated the activity of PDEs in human 
adipose tissue and the differences seen in obesity, T2D and 
between adipose tissue depots. 
In adipose tissue there was a negative correlation between 
PDE activities and BMI. Although the exact effects of 
reductions in PDE activities with increasing obesity are not 
known, the decreased PDE activities in adipose tissue seen in 
obesity might have potential physiological consequences. In 
obese subjects the anti-lipolytic effect of insulin is dimin-
ished. 
25 PDE3B is the central enzyme controlling the anti-</p>

<p>lipolytic effect of insulin. 
26 Thus, decreased PDE3B activity </p>

<p>with increasing obesity, as seen in our study, may be a 
contributing factor to the diminished anti-lipolytic effect of 
insulin seen in obese patients. Decreased PDE4 activity in the 
adipose tissue of obese patients might also have conse-
quences for lipolysis. Decreased PDE4 activities may poten-
tially raise the rate of lipolysis, as seen in rat adipocytes, </p>

<p>12   and lead to an increase in fatty acid release to the circulation. 
Excess fatty acids have been shown to interfere with insulin 
signaling in liver and skeletal muscle, contributing to the 
development of insulin resistance in these tissues. </p>

<p>4   This study also demonstrated that PDE activities other 
than PDE3 and PDE4 are present in adipose tissue and 
adipocytes. These activities were collectively referred to as 
PDEn and were also affected by obesity and T2D. PDEn 
activity was unique from PDE3 and PDE4 activity in certain 
aspects. PDEn activity was increased in SC adipose tissue 
from patients diagnosed with T2D. As PDEn does not include 
PDE3B, the only PDE isoform known to be regulated by 
insulin, it is not likely that the increased PDE activity reflects 
insulin supplementation or endogenous hyperinsulinemia. 
However, increased PDEn could reflect some other aspect of 
T2D. Further work using selective inhibitors of the PDE </p>

<p>families that potentially contribute to PDEn will need to be 
carried out in a larger sample of T2D patients to determine 
which PDE families are responsible for this increased activity. 
One of the hallmarks of obesity is an increase in the 
infiltration of adipose tissue by inflammatory cells, with 
visceral adipose tissue being more prone to infiltration than 
SC adipose tissue. 
27 The consequences of decreased PDE </p>

<p>activities in adipose tissue in obesity could also include 
altered states of inflammation. Previous studies have shown 
that the PDE3 inhibitor Cilostazol inhibited inflammatory 
cytokine expression in cultured adipocytes as well as in the 
db/db mouse, a mouse model of T2D. 
28 Inhibitors to PDE3 </p>

<p>and PDE4 enzymes show anti-inflammatory properties in 
certain immune cell types. 
29,30 In addition, mice deficient in </p>

<p>the PDE4B protein were shown to have reduced adipose 
tissue tumor necrosis factor-a, a marker of inflammation, 
when fed a high-fat diet. </p>

<p>14   In an attempt to understand more about the PDEn pool of 
PDEs, we performed western blot analysis of some PDEs for 
which selective inhibitors are not available. PDE9A and 
PDE10A were expressed in adipose tissue as well as in 
adipocytes. PDE7B was detected in adipose tissue but not 
in isolated adipocytes. Although PDE9 is selective for cGMP, 
PDE10 can hydrolyze both cGMP and cAMP. 
5 It has been </p>

<p>demonstrated that genetic deficiency of PDE10A in mice 
results in decreased body weight, particularly in females. </p>

<p>19   PDE9A deficient mice fed a high-fat diet are reported to have 
reduced weight gain and fat mass compared with wild-type 
mice. 
20 These studies suggest a role for these PDEs in adipose </p>

<p>tissue homeostasis. Furthermore, the presence of a cGMP-
dependent lipolytic pathway, which is stimulated by atrial 
natiuretic peptide has been described in human adipo-
cytes. 
31 PDE9A and PDE10A might be candidates for the </p>

<p>PDE, responsible for regulating the cGMP pool in adipocytes 
associated with atrial natiuretic peptide-induced lipolysis. 
In summary, we conclude that PDE activities are reduced 
in obesity. Further studies will be performed in order to 
connect the altered activity profile of PDEs to different 
biological functions and thereby determine whether and 
how they have a role in the development of adipose tissue 
insulin resistance. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We acknowledge Dr Jan Hedenbro, Dr Ann-Cathrin Moberg, 
Dr Dan Sevonius, Dr Jonas Hedström and the nurses of the 
operation unit of Landskrona Hospital. We thank Eva 
Ohlson and Ann-Kristin Holmén-Pålbrink for their dedicated 
technical assistance. </p>

<p>Table 2 PDE activities in primary adipocytes </p>

<p>Activity 
(pmol min 
À1 per mg) </p>

<p>Non-obese SC 
n ¼ 6 </p>

<p>Obese SC 
n ¼ 16 </p>

<p>Non-obese OM 
n ¼ 6 </p>

<p>Obese OM 
n ¼ 17 </p>

<p>Total 
35.7 ± 7.5 
26.3 ± 7.0 
73.6 ± 20.2 
21.7 ± 8.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>PDE3 
31.8 ± 7.2 
20.2 ± 7.4 
50.0 ± 13.9 
15.1 ± 8.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>PDE4 
6.8 ± 2.7 
4.3 ± 1.7 
20.5 ± 8.1 
5.6 ± 2.5 
PDEn 
2.4±0.7 
4.2±1.7 
9.9±4.5 
2.5±0.9 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: PDE, phosphodiesterase; OM, omental; SC, subcutaneous. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Non-obese OM vs obese OM, Po0.05. </p>

<p>Phosphodiesterase activities in obesity 
B Omar et al </p>



<p>Nutrition and Diabetes </p>

<p>This work was supported by a fellowship from the Tage 
Blucher foundation and grants from the Swedish Society of 
Physicians, Diabetes Society of Malmö, the Royal Physio-
graphic Society in Lund, the Swedish Medical Research 
Council, Novo Nordisk Foundation, the Swedish Society of 
Medicine and the Crafoord Foundation. </p>



<p>This work is licensed under the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-No 
Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy 
of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on the Nutrition and Diabetes website (http://www.nature.com/nutd) </p>

<p>Phosphodiesterase activities in obesity 
B Omar et al </p>



<p>Nutrition and Diabetes </p>

</text></tei>