<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3521687" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Tau is a neuronal protein that stabilizes the microtubule (MT) network, but it also 
forms filaments associated with Alzheimer's disease. Understanding Tau-MT and Tau-Tau 
interactions would help to establish Tau function in health and disease. For many years, 
literature reports on Tau-MT binding behavior and affinity have remained surprisingly contra-
dictory (e.g., 10-fold variation in Tau-MT affinity). Tau-Tau interactions have also been inves-
tigated, but whether MTs might affect Tau filament formation is unknown. We have addressed 
these issues through binding assays and microscopy. We assessed Tau-MT interactions via 
cosedimentation and found that the measured affinity of Tau varies greatly, depending on the 
experimental design and the protein concentrations used. To investigate this dependence, 
we used fluorescence microscopy to examine Tau-MT binding. Strikingly, we found that Taxol-
stabilized MTs promote Tau filament formation without characterized Tau-filament inducers. 
We propose that these novel Tau filaments account for the incongruence in Tau-MT affinity 
measurements. Moreover, electron microscopy reveals that these filaments appear similar to 
the heparin-induced Alzheimer's model. These observations suggest that the MT-induced Tau 
filaments provide a new model for Alzheimer's studies and that MTs might play a role in the 
formation of Alzheimer's-associated neurofibrillary tangles. </p>

<p>Tau protein is expressed in neurons and functions to stabilize micro-
tubules (MTs; Makrides et al., 2004; Choi et al., 2009). MTs are dy-
namic polymers, able to grow and shrink, and these dynamics are 
regulated by a group of MT-associated proteins, including Tau 
(Desai and Mitchison, 1997; Amos, 2000; Askham and Morrison, 
2002; Howard and Hyman, 2003). In neurons, MTs are linearly and 
densely packed along the length of the axon, inducing a global cel-
lular polarity critical for neuronal signaling (Tanaka and Kirschner, 
1991; Slaughter et al., 1997; Witte et al., 2008). In normal cells, Tau </p>

<p>is found distributed throughout axons and is localized to MTs. The 
interaction of Tau with MTs is regulated through many mechanisms, 
including alternative splicing (there are six known human Tau iso-
forms) and phosphorylation (Alonso et al., 2010; Fauquant et al., 
2011). However, in Alzheimer's disease, Tau becomes aggregated to 
form neurofibrillary tangles (NFTs), and it is no longer associated 
with the MT network (Goedert et al., 1999; Sun and Gamblin, 2009). 
The Tau in these tangles is quite different from that in normal cells, 
in that it is hyperphosphorylated and has a different ratio of 
expressed isoforms. It is also structurally altered: normal Tau is 
soluble with very little secondary structure, but Tau molecules in 
NFTs bind together to form straight, ribbon-like filaments or paired 
helical filaments with beta-sheet content (Mizushima et al., 2007; 
Jeganathan et al., 2008). 
As yet, it is not clear whether the formation of NFTs is a cause 
or effect of Alzheimer's, but the correlation between Tau-rich 
NFTs and Alzheimer's has made Tau a target of much research. 
One focus has been on studying interactions between MTs and 
Tau, with the goal of establishing the normal physiological func-
tion of the protein. This work has shown that Tau promotes MT </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Monica Bettencourt-Dias 
Instituto Gulbenkian de Ciência </p>

<p>Received: May 15, 2012 
Revised: Oct 9, 2012 
Accepted: Oct 11, 2012 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E12-05-0374) on October 19, 2012. 
Address correspondence to: Holly V. Goodson (hgoodson@nd.edu). </p>

<p>© 2012 Duan and Goodson. This article is distributed by The American Society for 
Cell Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is avail-
able to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," "The American Society for Cell Biology </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell 
® " are registered trademarks of The American Society of Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: EM, electron microscopy; MT, microtubule; NA, numerical 
aperture; NFT, neurofibrillary tangle; TcMv, Tau constant MT varied; TEM, trans-
mission electron microscopy; TvMc, Tau varied MT constant. </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 15, 2012 </p>

<p>MTs promote formation of Tau filaments | 4797 </p>

<p>binding behavior determined according to approach TcMv, with total 
MT concentrations ranging from 0 to 8 μM (see Materials and 
Methods). When the data were fitted (solid line) using nonlinear 
regression according to the standard binding equation (Eq. 1; see 
Appendix), a K D of 0.11 ± 0.02 μM was obtained. (C) Tau-MT binding 
behavior determined according to approach TvMc, with total Tau 
concentrations ranging from 0 to 26 μM. The dotted line shows a 
theoretical curve plotted according to Eq. 2 using the K D value 
calculated in (B); the data are clearly inconsistent with this curve. The 
solid line shows a fit of the data to Eq. 3, which includes an additional 
linear term meant to account for Tau-Tau interactions on the MTs 
(see the Appendix). According to this fit, K D = 2.02 ± 1.03 μM and 
ρ = 6.88 ± 0.37 μM. The red arrow indicates the point at which 
supersaturation (greater than 1:1 binding) begins to occur, and the 
red data points show the sedimentation behavior of moderate (4 μM) 
and high (20 μM) concentrations of Tau in the absence of MTs. 
(D) Approach TcMv at 2 μM (orange) and 4 μM (blue) Tau, with total 
MT concentrations ranging from 0 to 8 μM. When these data were 
fitted to the standard binding equation (Eq. 1), K D values of 1.39 ± 
0.35 μM and 0.67 ± 0.16 μM for 2 and 4 μM Tau, respectively, were 
obtained. The gray data and curve are reproduced from (B) and are 
provided for comparison. The variability in the data at higher [Tau] 
is discussed in the Appendix. (E) Approach TvMc at 0.5 μM (green) 
and 0.1 μM (red) MT, with total Tau concentrations ranging from 0 to 
10 μM. When these data were fitted to Eq. 3 (see Appendix), the 
following values were obtained: for 0.5 μM MT, K D = 0.84 ± 0.41 μM 
and ρ = 3.53 ± 0.21 μM, while for 0.1 μM MT, K D = 0.10 ± 0.32 μM and 
ρ = 1.06 ± 0.04 μM. The gray data and curve are reproduced from (C) 
and are provided for comparison. Data in all panels are the average of 
≥3 trials ± SD. </p>

<p>stability and reduces MT dynamics (Panda et al., 1995; Al-Bassam 
et al., 2002; Bunker et al., 2004). The MT-binding and MT-stabiliz-
ing activities of Tau are contained within the C-terminal domain, 
which contains four MT-binding repeat motifs sandwiched by 
proline-rich regions (Figure 1A). The N-terminus of Tau (also 
called the projection domain) is believed to space apart MTs 
within the crowded axon by bridging with the Tau N-termini pro-
jecting from neighboring MTs (Hirokawa et al., 1988; Kempf et al., 
1996). While there is general agreement about these aspects of 
Tau-MT interactions, the literature contains conflicting informa-
tion about others. As previously noted by Ackmann and col-
leagues, the reported values for the Tau-MT affinity vary by more 
than an order of magnitude, from less than 100 nM to more than 
1 μM (Goode and Feinstein, 1994; Ackmann et al., 2000; Makrides 
et al., 2004). Research has shown that different isoforms have dif-
ferent affinities, but wide ranges of affinities have been reported, 
even for the same isoform (Goode and Feinstein, 1994; Sillen 
et al., 2007; Fauquant et al., 2011), and the origin of these dis-
crepancies remains unresolved. 
Another research focus has been on understanding the process 
of NFT formation. Because the Tau in Alzheimer's NFTs is highly 
phosphorylated and does not bind to MTs (Paudel and Li, 1999; 
Alonso et al., 2010), in vitro studies of NFT formation have gener-
ally utilized systems devoid of MTs. These studies have concluded 
that unmodified Tau can form filaments similar to Alzheimer's NFTs 
in vitro, but that the process requires a lot of time (days) and the 
presence of promoters, such as heparin, arachidonic acid, or poly-
glutamates (Friedhoff et al., 1998; Barghorn and Mandelkow, 2002; 
Hiraoka et al., 2004; Jeganathan et al., 2008). Some previous stud-
ies have shown that Tau-Tau oligomerization can occur in the pres-
ence of MTs and even that Tau-Tau oligomerization is promoted </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: The apparent Tau-MT affinity depends on the methods 
and protein concentrations used. (A) Schematic diagram of the 
domains of the full-length Tau used in this study (441 amino acids, not 
drawn to scale). The C-terminus contains four MT-binding repeat 
motifs (R1-R4) surrounded by proline-rich regions (P). (B) Tau-MT </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>by MTs (Ackmann et al., 2000; Makrides et al., 2003). On the basis 
of these observations, researchers have concluded that Tau can 
bind to the subset of Tau molecules that are bound to MTs 
(Ackmann et al., 2000; Makrides et al., 2003; Sillen et al., 2007). 
However, while there is clear evidence that MTs promote Tau 
oligomerization on the surface of MTs, to our knowledge, no stud-
ies have investigated whether Tau filament formation might be in-
fluenced by the presence of MTs. 
In the course of other experiments, we became puzzled by the 
surprising range of reported Tau-MT affinity values. We decided to 
investigate the possibility that differences in experimental approach 
could explain (at least partially) the discrepancies in the values of the 
reported dissociation constant. MT-binding studies are typically per-
formed using cosedimentation assays in which the [Tau] is held con-
stant and the [polymerized tubulin] is varied, or alternatively where 
[polymerized tubulin] is held constant and [Tau] is varied. In either 
case, the amount of Tau that cosediments with the MTs is interpreted 
as Tau that is bound to MTs. By performing experiments in which we 
used both experimental designs in parallel, we found that the ap-
parent affinity of Tau for MTs depends both on the approach used 
to study the interaction and on the concentration of each binding 
partner. We found that this dependence is observed when the data 
are fitted using both standard binding models or binding models 
designed to account for Tau-Tau oligomerization at the MT surface, 
suggesting that an interaction not accounted for by these models is 
occurring in these reactions. 
To investigate this question, we used fluorescence microscopy 
to examine the behavior of labeled Tau in the presence and ab-
sence of MTs. Surprisingly, we found that MTs induce the rapid 
formation of Tau-only filaments. This observation is important for 
two reasons. First, the existence of these filaments confounds at-
tempts to measure Tau-MT interactions by any method, because 
they deplete the pool of free Tau available to bind to MTs, and they 
spin down in cosedimentation assays. More significantly, these fila-
ments form in regular MT-binding buffers, are induced by MTs, and 
are seen by electron microscopy (EM) to be similar to the well-
established Alzheimer's-like Tau filaments induced by heparin. 
These observations suggest that the MT-induced filaments might 
provide a useful new in vitro model for the formation of Tau fila-
ments in Alzheimer's disease, and they raise the possibility that 
MTs play a previously unappreciated role in the formation of 
Alzheimer's-associated NFTs. 
Our article is divided into two sections. The first focuses on 
measuring the Tau-MT binding affinity, as estimated by different 
experimental approaches and binding models, and on the failure of 
any of the commonly used binding models to fit the range of data. 
An overview of the experiments and interpretations is provided in 
the main text, while a more detailed discussion can be found in the 
Appendix. The second section focuses on the observation that MTs 
induce the formation of Tau filaments. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION 
Investigations of Tau-MT interactions </p>

<p>To elucidate the origin of the inconsistencies in the reported Tau-
MT affinity values (Goode and Feinstein, 1994; Ackmann et al., 
2000; Makrides et al., 2004), we first investigated the possibility 
that different experimental designs yield different apparent disso-
ciation constants. In measuring dissociation constants, the re-
searcher usually holds one protein constant, while varying the con-
centration of the other, and then evaluates the amount of complex 
formed under each condition. As noted above, binding to MTs is 
typically assessed by cosedimentation, in which the experimenter </p>

<p>assumes that the reaction has reached equilibrium and that any 
test protein that sediments does so by binding to the MTs. In some 
analyses of Tau-MT binding, researchers hold Tau constant, while 
varying the concentration of polymerized tubulin (e.g., Goode and 
Feinstein, 1994). In others, polymerized tubulin is held constant, 
while Tau is varied (e.g., Ackmann et al., 2000). We refer to these 
approaches as "Tau constant MT varied" (TcMv) and "Tau varied 
MT constant" (TvMc), respectively (see Materials and Methods). To 
test whether differences between TcMv and TvMc could account 
for the differences in published Tau-MT affinity values, we mea-
sured Tau-MT interactions using both approaches under otherwise 
identical conditions. 
As shown in Figure 1 and discussed more in the Appendix, the 
apparent affinity of Tau for Taxol-stabilized MTs depends on the 
method used to assess the interaction (Figure 1, compare B and C). 
The measured affinity also depends on the concentration of Tau 
used in the assay (Figure 1D). This dependence on [Tau] is expected, 
based on previous experiments that were interpreted as showing 
that Tau binds to MT-bound Tau (Ackmann et al., 2000; Makrides 
et al., 2003). It also provides an explanation for the observation that 
the apparent affinity depends on the approach used to assess the 
interaction, because [Tau] is held constant in approach TcMv and 
varies in approach TvMc. 
Ackmann and colleagues generated a binding model that at-
tempts to account for both Tau-MT interactions and the binding 
of Tau to MT-bound Tau (Ackmann et al., 2000). In this model, 
the Tau-MT dissociation constant could be calculated from the 
fit of their equation to the binding data. However, contrary to 
the predictions of this model, we observed that the apparent 
affinity of Tau for MTs also depends on the concentration of MTs 
(Figure 1E). This observation suggests that an as yet unac-
counted for reaction is occurring in the Tau-MT binding assays, 
and it led us to consider the possibility that Tau might be form-
ing filaments in our MT-binding assays (for a more in-depth 
discussion of these experiments and their interpretations, see 
Appendix). </p>

<p>Investigations of Tau-Tau interactions: MTs induce 
the formation of Tau filaments </p>

<p>It is well-established that Tau forms filaments under pathological 
conditions (e.g., Alzheimer's disease) and that solutions of purified 
Tau form filaments in vitro upon exposure of a Tau solution to induc-
ers, such as heparin (Jeganathan et al., 2008; Wegmann et al., 2011). 
As discussed above, it is also accepted that Tau can engage in Tau-
Tau interactions on the MT surface (Ackmann et al., 2000; Kar et al., 
2003; Makrides et al., 2003). We wondered whether the unusual be-
havior of Tau in the MT-binding assays might be caused at least in 
part by the formation of Tau filaments during the assays. Such an 
observation would be surprising, because formation of heparin-in-
duced Tau filaments is very slow, taking days to accumulate signifi-
cant concentrations of filaments, and is normally performed at much 
higher [Tau] than used in our experiments. However, we decided 
that it was worthwhile to investigate, because, as discussed above, 
the dependence of the apparent Tau-MT K D on the concentration 
of MTs was inconsistent with Ackmann's mathematical model for 
Tau-MT interactions. Moreover, the Tau in our TvMc assays ap-
peared to be cosedimenting with MTs at levels beyond what could 
be explained solely by limited Tau oligomerization at the MT sur-
face, as predicted using the mathematical models of MTBindingSim 
(Philip et al., 2012; unpublished data). These observations sug-
gested that we should investigate the possibility that MTs induce 
the formation of Tau filaments. </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 15, 2012 </p>

<p>MTs promote formation of Tau filaments | 4799 </p>

<p>filaments requires the presence of MTs: we 
saw no such Tau-only filaments form under 
otherwise identical conditions in the absence 
of MTs (Figure 2D). The number of these 
Tau-only filaments also seems to depend on 
the different Tau concentrations used (Figure 
2). Furthermore, we found that the Tau-only 
filaments remained intact after we allowed 
the MTs to depolymerize by lengthy incuba-
tions in buffer without Taxol (Figure 3). This 
observation indicates that while the Tau fila-
ments do require MTs to form (Figure 2), 
they do not require MTs to be maintained. </p>

<p>Effect of Tau filament formation on 
measuring Tau-MT affinity </p>

<p>The formation of MT-induced Tau filaments 
could interfere with MT-binding assays in 
two different ways that would be reflected in 
the binding data found in Figure 1. First, the 
Tau filaments could cosediment with MTs, 
either by being associated with MTs or by 
sedimenting independently. If the Tau fila-
ments cosediment, filament formation is ex-
pected to increase both the apparent affinity 
and the apparent Tau bound :tubulin ratio by 
increasing the fraction of Tau that sediments 
at a given concentration. To test the hypoth-
esis that the Tau filaments do cosediment 
with MTs, we incubated fluorescently labeled 2 μM Tau and 4 μM 
MTs for 15 min at 37°C and performed a standard cosedimentation 
assay. However, this time, instead of loading the supernatant and 
pellet fractions on a gel, we imaged them using fluorescence micros-
copy. We observed that both MTs and Tau filaments sediment nearly 
to completion-few of either were found in the supernatant (Figure 
4). These data show that the central assumption of cosedimentation 
assays (the idea that Tau in the pellet is bound to MTs) is being vio-
lated under any condition in which the Tau filaments are being 
formed. Thus cosedimentation assays cannot be used to provide a 
valid measurement of Tau-MT interactions if filaments are present. 
Because Tau filament sedimentation perturbs affinity measure-
ments, our initial conclusion was that this problem likely accounts for 
the failure of binding models to match the data, and that we needed 
to find a different technique (one that did not use sedimentation) to 
measure Tau-MT interactions. However, we realized that no ap-
proach would be sufficient to provide a valid measurement, because 
the formation of Tau filaments perturbs affinity measurements in a 
second way as well: assembly of Tau into filaments depletes the 
pool of free Tau available to bind to MTs, which would decrease the 
apparent affinity by decreasing the effective concentration of Tau 
present in a given reaction. While the first problem (sedimentation 
of Tau filaments) is specific to cosedimentation assays, the second 
problem (depletion of the pool of free Tau) impacts any technique 
that can be used to measure Tau-MT interactions, regardless of 
whether sedimentation is involved. 
Therefore we decided to see whether there was a Tau concentra-
tion at which filament formation was minimal over the relevant range 
of MT concentrations. Our expectation was that identifying such a 
concentration would allow for a nonperturbed measurement of 
Tau-MT interactions. Experiments in which we varied the concentra-
tion of Tau incubated with 4 μM MTs showed that 1 μM Tau formed 
relatively few filaments (Figure 5). This observation indicates that the </p>

<p>Cross-linking supports the existence of Tau-Tau interactions 
in the MT-binding assays </p>

<p>Our first goal in testing the hypothesis that filaments might be form-
ing in our assays was to reproduce the results of Makrides et al. 
(2003), who showed that MTs promote the formation of cross-link-
able Tau-Tau complexes that were interpreted as evidence that MTs 
promote the formation of Tau oligomers. Supplemental Figure S1 
provides evidence that Tau does cross-link to Tau in our assays and, 
as expected, does so only in the presence of MTs (Figure S1). While 
encouraging, these experiments did not reveal whether the Tau-Tau 
interactions are occurring in a limited way on the MT surface, consis-
tent with previous understanding, or might be occurring as part of a 
previously unrecognized polymerization process. </p>

<p>Novel Tau filament formation revealed 
by fluorescence microscopy </p>

<p>To more directly investigate the possibility that the Tau in our assays 
was forming filaments, we turned to fluorescence microscopy. More 
specifically, we performed experiments in which we added varying 
amounts of Alexa Fluor-labeled Tau (1-4 μM) to a constant amount 
of rhodamine-labeled MTs (4 μM), incubated the mixtures for 15 min 
(similar to the cosedimentation assays), and imaged the samples at 
the appropriate wavelengths. The first thing we noticed was that the 
Tau decorated the MTs very unevenly: some MTs were well-deco-
rated, some appeared to be lacking Tau entirely, and others were 
sporadically decorated (Figure 2). Atomic force microscopy work 
performed by Schaap et al. (2007) also showed sporadic Tau deco-
ration on MTs. 
However, the more striking observation is the appearance of 
filaments that appear to be composed of Tau alone: in the right 
panels of Figure 2, one can see green Tau-labeled filaments (blue 
arrowheads) that do not correspond at all to the position of MTs in 
the left panels (Figure 2). Importantly, the assembly of these Tau-only </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Fluorescently labeled Tau and MTs reveal sporadic Tau-MT decoration and the 
formation of Tau filaments. Incubations of (A) 1 μM Tau:4 μM MTs, (B) 2 μM Tau:4 μM MTs, and 
(C) 4 μM Tau:4 μM MTs for 15 min at 37°C. Individual MTs vary from being sparsely decorated 
with Tau (red arrowheads) to being moderately and heavily decorated with Tau (yellow 
arrowheads). Tau filaments that are not associated with MTs are also evident (blue arrowheads). 
In the right-most panels, colored images display tubulin as red and Tau as green; the overlay of Tau 
and tubulin appears as yellow. (D) The results of control experiments performed with Tau protein 
alone at low (1 μM) and high (4 μM) concentrations, in which no Tau filaments are observed. Scale 
bars: 8 μm. The images shown represent the typical results of more than 10 independent 
experiments performed with Tau from multiple purifications and labeling reactions. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>dissociation constant measured in Figure 1B 
likely provides a reasonable estimate of 
the actual Tau-MT dissociation constant in 
agreement with previous measurements 
performed at low [Tau], e.g., Goode and 
Feinstein (1994). Moreover, it suggests that 
other measurements of Tau-MT affinity 
should be performed at a similarly low Tau 
concentration, unless conditions are found 
under which filament formation does not 
occur. 
Two remaining issues are the surprising 
variability in the fraction of Tau that sedi-
ments in Figure 1D and the inconsistent 
trend in apparent affinity when Tau in-
creases from 1 to 2 and 4 μM. We hypoth-
esized that one reason for the variability 
might be that Tau polymerization takes lon-
ger than 15 min to reach its endpoint and 
that small differences in the nucleation pro-
cess or the incubation time would vary the 
amount of polymerized Tau within this short 
time frame. To test this hypothesis, we in-
cubated the Tau with MTs for a longer time 
and collected images at different time 
points. Working with 2 μM Tau and 4 μM 
MTs, we found that Tau starts out in both 
MT-bound and Tau filament form at 15 min, 
but shifts completely into Tau filament form 
after 1 h (Figure 6). After 60 min, the Tau is 
found mostly in Tau filament form and the 
MTs are largely undecorated; only relatively 
few MTs have Tau bound in a very heavily 
decorated manner (Figure 6). 
To assess the impact of this time-depen-
dent polymerization on the cosedimenta-
tion assays, we repeated the 2 μM Tau TcMv 
experiments of Figure 1D by incubating the 
Tau-MT mixture for 1 h instead of 15 min. 
Consistent with the observations of Figures 
4 and 6, we saw that all of the Tau shifted to 
the pellet as long as MTs were present (see 
Figure S2), making it appear that the in-
creased incubation time shifted the Tau-
MT interaction from a low binding affinity 
to a high binding affinity. However, this 
would be an incorrect interpretation: Tau 
sedimentation results from a combination 
of fast MT binding and slower Tau polymer-
ization. One impact of this sedimentation 
behavior is that the apparent affinities ob-
tained from the experiments of Figure 1D 
are not legitimate measurements of the 
Tau-MT binding interaction. Moreover, be-
cause the kinetics of the Tau polymerization 
process likely vary in a complicated way 
with the number of nucleation sites, this 
time-dependent polymerization behavior 
also provides an explanation for the vari-
ability seen at particular MT concentrations. 
These issues require further study. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Tau filaments form in the presence of MTs and remain after MTs dissociate. MTs 
(4 μM) were incubated at 37°C in the absence or presence of Tau (2 μM) and/or the MT-
stabilizing drug Taxol (10 μM). Samples of the incubations were taken at different time intervals 
(from 15 min to 4 h, as indicated) and imaged. Colored images display tubulin as red and Tau as 
green and their overlay as yellow. Scale bars: 8 μm. (A) MTs incubated with Taxol and Tau; the far 
right pair of panels shows grayscale images for the 4-h time point. (B) MTs incubated with Tau in 
the absence of Taxol; the far right pair of panels shows grayscale images for the 4-h time point. 
(C) MTs incubated alone with Taxol. (D) MTs incubated without Taxol or Tau. Note that MTs 
without Taxol dissociate over time (more slowly when Tau is present), but the Tau filaments 
remain. Images shown represent the typical results of more than six different fields of collected 
data. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Tau filaments spin down in ultracentrifugation. Tau (2 μM) and MTs (4 μM) were 
incubated at 37°C for 15 min. The mixture was ultracentrifuged, and the supernatant and pellet 
were separated according to MT-binding assay protocol for imaging. While the "before spin" 
and pellet images are representative, the supernatant image shows one of very few MTs left in 
the supernatant. These data show that cosedimentation assays are likely to yield invalid 
measurements of the Tau-MT affinity, because cosedimentation assumes that all Tau in the 
pellet is bound to MTs. Colored images display tubulin as red and Tau as green and their overlay 
as yellow. Scale bars: 10 μm. Images shown represent the typical results of three independent 
experiments. </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 15, 2012 </p>

<p>MTs promote formation of Tau filaments | 4801 </p>

<p>is how MTs promote the formation of Tau filament nuclei. We first 
hypothesized that this process might be promoted by the gluta-
mate-rich C-terminal tails of tubulin, since polyglutamates can in-
duce Tau fibrillization in vitro (Friedhoff et al., 1998). To test this idea, 
we incubated Tau with MTs from which the α-and β-tails of the tu-
bulin dimers had been removed by subtilisin digestion (Figures 7 
and S3). Surprisingly, we found that when we used MTs stripped of 
their glutamate-rich tails, there was no obvious effect on formation 
of the Tau filaments (Figure 7). 
This observation indicates that the tubulin tails are not involved 
in the nucleation process, but does not provide any information 
about what aspect of the MT structure is involved. Further work will 
be required to resolve this question. However, one speculation is 
that the filaments might be nucleated by MT tips, as suggested by 
fluorescence microscopy images showing Tau filaments extending 
from MT tips (Figure S4). We used EM to better visualize the Tau fila-
ments and perhaps gain insight into the nucleation mechanism, as 
discussed in the following section. </p>

<p>Possible relationship of MT-induced Tau filaments 
to Tau NFTs </p>

<p>Up to now, the only in vitro experimental model for the formation of 
Tau NFTs seen in Alzheimer's disease has been the assembly of Tau 
filaments by inducers, such as heparin, arachidonic acid, and poly-
glutamates (e.g., Friedhoff et al., 1998; Jeganathan et al., 2008). 
Heparin fibrillizes full-length human Tau into a combination of 
twisted and flat, ribbon-like filaments. EM, thioflavin-S fluorescence, 
Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy, and circular dichroism stud-
ies have provided evidence that these filaments can be used as 
an acceptable model of the NFTs that form in Alzheimer's disease 
(Ramachandran and Udgaonkar, 2011; Wegmann et al., 2011). As 
noted earlier, this filament assembly typically occurs over a period of 
days or at least hours, often uses very high Tau concentrations, re-
quires anionic inducers, and is performed in systems devoid of MTs. 
To investigate the relationship between our novel Tau filaments and 
the heparin-induced filaments used as models for NFTs, we turned 
to transmission electron microscopy (TEM). 
We prepared samples made with MTs alone, Tau alone, and 
mixtures of MTs and Tau under the same conditions as used for the </p>

<p>Investigations into how MTs nucleate Tau filaments </p>

<p>The observation that Tau filaments do not form in the absence of 
MTs or other inducers indicates that Tau polymerization (also called 
fibrillization) is a nucleation-limited process. One obvious question </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Experiments using 1 μM Tau minimize Tau filament 
formation. Tau (1 or 2 μM) was incubated for 15 min at 37°C with 
4 μM MTs, and then the solution was imaged by fluorescence 
microscopy. The number of MTs and Tau filaments were counted 
from three separate optical fields spanning a total imaged area of 
35.6 square mm under each condition. The number of MTs counted 
exceeded 300 within each field. The fields chosen for counting were 
typical representations of more than 10 experiments. </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Formation of Tau filaments is a time-dependent process. 
Tau (2 μM) was incubated with 4 μM MTs periodically supplemented 
with Taxol at 37°C, and images were collected at 15-min, 1-h, 2-h, and 
3-h time points. By 1 h, the number of Tau filaments had reached a 
maximum. The bar graph data were generated as described in 
Figure 5, counted from three separate optical fields spanning a total 
imaged area of 35.6 square mm. The number of MTs counted exceeded 
300 within each field. The fields chosen for counting are typical 
representations of more than six different fields of collected data. </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: Subtilisin-treated MTs can promote the formation of Tau 
filaments. (A) Tau (2 μM) incubated with 4 μM normal Taxol-stabilized 
MTs for 15 min. (B) Tau (2 μM) incubated for 15 min with 4 μM 
subtilized MTs that have both C-terminal tubulin tails cleaved (tested 
by Western blot analysis; see Figure S3). Left panels show MTs, 
middle panels show Tau, and the right panels show the overlay; the 
MTs are displayed in red, the Tau in green, and the overlay in yellow. 
Scale bar: 10 μm. Images shown represent the typical results of 
more than 30 different fields of collected data. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>(Jeganathan et al., 2008; Ramachandran and 
Udgaonkar, 2011; Wegmann et al., 2011). As 
shown in Figure 8A, the MTs in our experi-
ments can be recognized as straight fila-
ments that have clear protofilament ridges. 
When full-length Tau is incubated with hepa-
rin in the NFT-promoting buffer, it forms 
many straight and a few twisted filaments, in 
agreement with previous reports (Figure 8B; 
Wille et al., 1992; Jeganathan et al. 2008; 
Wegmann et al., 2010, 2011; Ramachandran 
and Udgaonkar, 2011). When Tau is incu-
bated by itself in MT buffer (PEM), no fila-
ments are visible (Figure 8B, inset). However, 
when Tau and MTs are incubated together, 
numerous nonhelical filaments without 
ridges appear (Figure 8C). These filaments 
appear superficially similar to the classical 
heparin-induced filaments (compare Figure 
8, C and B). Strikingly, we were also able to 
observe a number of incidences in which the 
Tau filament appeared to be polymerizing 
from the MT ends (Figure 8D), in agreement 
with our previous fluorescence observations 
(Figure S4). 
To conduct a more detailed comparison 
of the MT-induced and heparin-induced fila-
ments, we measured the widths of the vari-
ous filaments that occurred in our prepara-
tions. The MT-induced Tau filaments were 
most similar in appearance and width to the 
straight heparin-induced Tau filaments 
(Figure 8, B, C, and F). The significance of the 
slight differences in width between these two 
types of filaments is not clear, but could be 
due to buffer conditions. Indeed, many EM 
studies observing in vitro-generated Tau 
filaments have shown that the filament 
morphologies can vary depending on the 
Tau construct used, the anionic inducer used, 
or the buffer conditions (Crowther, 1991; 
Goedert et al., 1992; Barghorn and 
Mandelkow, 2002; Jeganathan et al., 2008). 
Recent studies have readdressed the issue 
of varying Tau filament morphologies and 
found that the thicker regions of Tau fibrils 
range between ∼9 and 18 nm, and the thin-
ner regions range between ∼10 and 15 nm 
(Wegmann et al., 2010). The observation that 
the width of the MT-induced Tau filaments 
falls within these values supports the idea 
that the MT-induced and heparin-induced 
filaments are similar structures. Given that 
the heparin-induced filaments are recog-
nized as models for Alzheimer's-induced NFT 
filaments, the sum of these data suggest that 
these MT-induced Tau filaments provide a 
new in vitro model for Tau NFT formation. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>We have found that under the conditions of typical MT-binding 
assays, MTs induce the rapid formation of novel Tau filaments. The </p>

<p>cosedimentation experiments above. We also prepared a control 
consisting of Tau alone in a heparin-containing buffer that has been 
classically used to promote the formation of NFT-like filaments </p>

<p>FIGURE 8: Novel Tau filaments resemble the heparin-induced Tau filaments that are models for 
Alzheimer's disease and appear to polymerize from MT ends. All samples used 2 μM Tau and 4 μM 
MTs incubated for 15 min at 37°C. For the samples in (D) and (E), the MTs were incubated with Tau 
for 5 min in order to catch the initial stages of the fibrillization process. (A) TEM image of MTs alone. 
The protofilament ridges can be seen. (B) Heparin-induced Tau filaments: full-length Tau forms a 
combination of many straight and a few twisted filaments upon incubation with heparin. The inset is 
a representative image of a Tau-only control: no filament formation was seen over multiple fields 
and samples. (C) TEM image of the Tau filaments that formed upon incubation with MTs. Note that 
the ribbon-like, MT-induced Tau filaments in (C) are most similar to the straight, heparin-induced Tau 
filaments seen in (B) and to others reported previously (Barghorn and Mandelkow, 2002; 
Jeganathan et al., 2008). Although the MT-induced Tau filaments do not have the periodical twist of 
the twisted heparin-induced Tau filaments, the MT-induced Tau filaments appear twisted in a 
braid-like way. (D) Image showing what appears to be a Tau filament polymerizing from an MT end. 
(E) Image showing a normal blunt MT end at which Tau polymerization is not occurring. 
(F) Histogram of filament widths. Width measurements were taken as described in Materials and 
Methods. (a) shows the thicker width of MT-induced Tau filaments; (a′) shows the thinner width of 
MT-induced Tau filaments; (b) shows the thicker width of twisted heparin-induced Tau filaments; 
(b′) shows the thinner width of twisted heparin-induced Tau filaments; (c) shows the width of 
straight heparin-induced Tau filaments; (d) shows the width of MTs. All images shown are 
representative images of three experiments and were acquired by TEM. Scale bars: 50 nm. </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 15, 2012 </p>

<p>MTs promote formation of Tau filaments | 4803 </p>

<p>Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO]) in HEPES buffer (pH 7.6, 10 mM 
HEPES, 100 mM NaCl, 0.125 mM EDTA, 5 mM dithiothreitol) at 
37°C for ∼4.5 d (Barghorn and Mandelkow, 2002; Jeganathan et al., 
2008). </p>

<p>MT-binding assay </p>

<p>MTs (concentration measured as polymerized tubulin dimers) were 
incubated at 37°C with Tau protein for 15 min in PEM buffer (100 mM 
PIPES, pH 6.8, 2 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM ethylene glycol tetraacetic acid 
[EGTA]) supplemented with 10 μM Taxol. The MTs and associated 
Tau (and any other sedimentable assemblages) were pelleted out of 
solution at 23,000 × g for 20 min at 37°C. The supernatants contain-
ing free Tau were separated from the pellets, and the pellets were 
resuspended in PEM. Samples were mixed with SDS buffer, boiled, 
and run on a 10% SDS-PAGE gel. Controls with Tau and MTs alone 
were included in each MT-binding assay. Background-corrected in-
tensities of the bound and free fractions of the Coomassie Blue-
stained Tau protein bands were measured using <rs type="software">Image J</rs> software. 
GraphPad Prism (La Jolla, CA) was used for all curve fitting, as 
described below. </p>

<p>Approach TcMv </p>

<p>An MT-binding assay in which the Tau concentration is held constant 
and the MT concentration is varied over multiple samples run in 
parallel. Calculations for the data shown assume a 1 Tau:1 tubulin 
dimer binding ratio (N). The total MT concentrations used were 0, 1, 
2, 4, 6, and 8 μM. Data were fitted using nonlinear regression 
according to Eq. 1, that is, fraction Tau bound = B max [MT free ]/([MT free ] 
+ K D ), with B max = 1.0. </p>

<p>Approach TvMc </p>

<p>An MT-binding assay in which the Tau concentration is varied and 
the MT concentration is held constant over multiple samples run in 
parallel. The total Tau concentrations used ranged between 0 and 
26 μM. Data were fitted using nonlinear regression according to 
Eq. 2 or 3, as indicated in the text. </p>

<p>Fluorescence studies </p>

<p>MTs were polymerized using an ∼1:3 ratio of carboxytetramethyl-
rhodamine-(TAMRA-) or Alexa Fluor 561-labeled tubulin to unla-
beled tubulin; the ratio of dye molecules to tubulin dimers in the 
labeled tubulin stock solution ranged between 1:5 and 1:3. Tau 
was labeled with Alexa Fluor 488 (A30052; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, 
CA), following Invitrogen's protocol for amine-reactive probes. 
The labeling ratio was generally one dye molecule to ∼10 Tau mol-
ecules. Labeled Tau generated from multiple different Tau preps 
formed similar Tau filaments, and control cosedimentation experi-
ments showed that for all preps the binding activity of 2 μM 
labeled Tau with 2 μM labeled MTs was similar to that of the unla-
beled proteins (unpublished data). The labeled MTs and labeled 
Tau protein were incubated together in BRB80 buffer (80 mM 
PIPES, pH 6.8, 1 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM EGTA) in the presence of 
10 μM Taxol; samples were diluted 1:10 and supplemented with 
an oxygen-scavenging system (mixture containing catalase, glu-
cose oxidase, β-mercaptoethanol, and glucose) just prior to imag-
ing. Images were acquired on a Nikon inverted microscope 
TE2000 using a 60×/1.4 numerical aperture (NA) objective and a 
Cascade 512B camera (Photometrics, Tucson, AZ). Figure 4 alone 
was imaged on a Zeiss Axiovert S100TV inverted microscope us-
ing 63×/1.4 NA objective and a Princeton Instruments (Trenton, 
NJ) Micromax camera. Both microscopes were fitted with a High 
Q filter set from Chroma (Bellows Falls, VT). All images were </p>

<p>assembly of these filaments is significant for two reasons. First, we 
propose that it accounts both for the failure of Tau-MT interactions 
to fit standard binding models and for the wide ranges of reported 
affinity values measured under different conditions (Goode and 
Feinstein, 1994; Sillen et al., 2007; Fauquant et al., 2011). The pos-
sibility remains that Tau also binds to MTs in a cooperative manner, 
as is suggested by the inconsistent nature of the decoration of MTs 
by Tau (Figure 2). However, it will be difficult to address this issue in 
a quantitative way until conditions are found that eliminate MT-in-
duced Tau filament formation over a range of Tau concentrations. 
Questions such as the significance of the Tau purification method for 
filament formation (i.e., the classic boiling method vs. other ap-
proaches) and the mechanism of filament nucleation remain impor-
tant additional avenues for future research. 
The second reason that the formation of MT-induced Tau fila-
ments is significant is that it may have relevance to the function of 
Tau in both health and disease. First, the observation that Tau forms 
the filaments rapidly in relatively gentle conditions indicates that 
Tau-Tau interactions do not require phosphorylation or the pres-
ence of chemical inducers. Additionally, the Tau filaments are found 
to form from the unlabeled protein, as shown by TEM (Figure 8). 
These observations suggest that Tau-Tau interactions might have a 
role in normal Tau function. Moreover, the similarity of the MT-in-
duced Tau filaments to those formed in Alzheimer's disease implies 
that MT induction of Tau filament assembly might provide an easier 
way to make Tau filaments and thus open new avenues for studying 
and perhaps inhibiting filament formation. Finally, the induction of 
Tau filament assembly by MTs in vitro provides additional support 
for the suggestion (Friedhoff et al., 1998; Ackmann et al., 2000) that 
MTs might play a role in the formation of Alzheimer's-associated 
NFTs in vivo. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Tubulin purification </p>

<p>Tubulin was purified from porcine brain using two polymerization 
cycles and separation on a P-11 column according to the Mitchison 
protocol (Mitchison and Kirschner, 1984). Aliquots of purified tubulin 
were flash-frozen and stored at −80°C. </p>

<p>MT polymerization </p>

<p>Tubulin was assembled into MTs with the stabilizing drug Taxol ac-
cording to an established protocol (Mitchison and Kirschner, 1984). </p>

<p>Subtilisin digestion of MTs </p>

<p>MT were digested with subtilisin to remove both the α-and β-tubulin 
tails according to a previously established protocol (Zhu et al., 2009). 
Removal of both tubulin tails was confirmed by Western blot analysis 
probed with mouse monoclonal 1A2 anti-α-tubulin antibody (a gift 
from the lab of Thomas Kreis, University of Geneva), which targets 
the α-tubulin tail, the second tail to be digested (see Figure S3). </p>

<p>Full-length human Tau </p>

<p>Full-length human Tau protein was recombinantly expressed in 
Escherichia coli BL21(DE3) cells from the vector pRK-172 kindly pro-
vided by Khalid Iqbal (Alonso et al., 2010) and purified by the boil-
ing method outlined by Smith et al. (2000). Tau concentration was 
determined by amino acid analysis, and aliquots were stored at 
−80°C. </p>

<p>Heparin-induced Tau filament formation </p>

<p>Full-length Tau (50 μM) was incubated with 12.5 μM heparin 
(heparin sodium salt from porcine intestinal mucosa [SKU: H3393; </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>acquired and processed using MetaMorph software (Molecular 
Devices, Sunnyvale, CA) and further processed using Adobe Pho-
toshop 7.0 (San Jose, CA). </p>

<p>TEM </p>

<p>Images were acquired on a FEI Titan 80-300 D3203 TEM (Hillsboro, 
OR) at 80 kV and collected by a Gatan camera (Oxford, UK). Sam-
ples were fixed with EM-grade glutaraldehyde and spread onto car-
bon type B, 400-mesh formvar/carbon-coated grids. The grids were 
previously exposed to Ar/O 2 for 12 s in a Fishione Instruments 
model 1020 plasma cleaner to make the surfaces hydrophilic. Sam-
ples were negatively stained with 2% uranyl acetate. </p>

<p>Filament width measurements </p>

<p>The width of an individual MT-induced Tau filament varies with 
thicker (Figure 8Fa) and thinner (Figure 8Fa′) regions. Three mea-
surements of the thicker widths along an individual Tau filaments 
were averaged together to represent the filament's thick width. 
Three measurements of the thinner widths along an individual Tau 
filament were averaged together to represent the filament's thin 
width. The average over multiple filaments (n) was taken and is plot-
ted as a bar graph, with the thicker average shown in (Figure 8Fa) 
and the thinner average shown in (Figure 8Fa′). The same approach 
was taken to measure the thicker (Figure 8Fb) and thinner (Figure 
8Fb′) regions of the heparin-induced, twisted Tau filaments. For the 
heparin-induced, straight Tau filaments (Figure 8Fc) and for the MTs 
(Figure 8Fd), three measurements of the width of an individual fila-
ment were averaged to count as the individual filament's width. The 
average over multiple filaments (n) was taken and is plotted; the 
straight heparin-induced Tau filament widths are shown in Figure 
8Fc, and the MT widths are shown in Figure 8Fd. </p>

<p>APPENDIX 
Discussion and analysis of the binding data in Figure 1 </p>

<p>When the value of the dissociation constant for a protein-protein 
interaction is measured, one protein is typically held constant, 
while the other is varied, and the data are fitted to an appropriate 
equation to extract the dissociation constant (more about this 
later in the Appendix). If the binding is simple, the same answer 
should be obtained by holding either protein constant in the ex-
periment-it should not matter which is held constant and which 
is varied. Similarly, the measured affinity should not depend on 
the concentration of proteins used. We refer to the approach in 
which Tau concentration, [Tau], is held constant and the concen-
tration of MTs, [MT], is varied as TcMv, and the converse as TvMc. 
Note that throughout this article, [MT] is measured as the concen-
tration of polymerized tubulin dimers. To test whether differences 
between the apparent behavior of Tau in the TcMv and TvMc ap-
proaches could account for the discrepancies in published Tau-
MT affinity values, we measured Tau-MT interactions using both 
approaches under otherwise identical conditions. To further char-
acterize the interaction, we then tested the dependence of the 
obtained values on [MT] (in TvMc) and [Tau] (in TcMv). As dis-
cussed more below, our results are not only inconsistent with the 
idea that Tau binds to MTs via a simple interaction, they are also 
inconsistent with the more sophisticated binding model devel-
oped by Ackmann et al. (2000), which attempts to incorporate Tau 
binding to MT-bound Tau. This inconsistency suggests that an-
other interaction not accounted for by the Ackmann model occurs 
when Tau and MTs are mixed. The main text provides evidence 
that this "other interaction" is the MT-induced formation of Tau 
filaments. </p>

<p>Binding of Tau to MTs using the TcMv approach yields a high 
apparent Tau-MT affinity </p>

<p>Using the TcMv approach, we measured the fraction of a constant 
amount of Tau that cosediments with different concentrations of 
Taxol-stabilized MTs. To calculate a K D value using this approach, 
one must assume a particular binding ratio between Tau and tubulin 
and build it into the analysis. This allows one to calculate the con-
centration of free binding sites on the MTs ([MT free ]) and to fit the 
resulting data according to the standard binding Eq. 1 to calculate 
the Tau-MT K D apparent (K Dapp ), as shown: </p>

<p>Fra tionT u ound MT 
MT </p>

<p>free 
free 
D pp </p>

<p>= 
+ 
[ 
] / ([ 
] 
) 
K 
b 
a 
c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>When we assume a binding ratio (N) of 1 Tau:1 tubulin dimer, 
our data for 1 μM Tau result in an apparent Tau-MT dissociation 
constant of 0.11 ± 0.02 μM (Figure 1B), in agreement with many 
reports that Tau binds MTs very tightly (Goode and Feinstein, 1994; 
Ackmann et al., 2000). </p>

<p>TvMc approach yields a different apparent Tau-MT binding 
affinity </p>

<p>In parallel to the TcMv experiments described above, we quantified 
Tau-MT interactions using the TvMc approach. More specifically, we 
performed experiments in which [MT] was held constant over mul-
tiple assays as the amount of Tau was varied, and we measured the 
amount of Tau that cosedimented with MTs at each [Tau]. By sub-
tracting Tau bound from Tau total in each assay (or, alternatively, by di-
rectly measuring the amount of Tau in the supernatant), we ascer-
tained the amount of Tau that remained free ([Tau] free ). We then 
used these values and the standard binding equation for the TvMc 
approach as shown in Eq. 2 to determine the Tau-MT K D : </p>

<p>( [ 
][ 
] ) / ([ 
] 
[ 
] 
Tau 
TTau 
T u </p>

<p>bound 
free </p>

<p>+ 
= 
K 
N 
) 
M 
a ree </p>

<p>f 
app 
D </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>where N is the ratio of bound Tau to tubulin dimer (set to be 1 Tau:1 
tubulin dimer for all data sets, consistent with the N used in the 
TvMc approach). 
We first measured the Tau-MT K D at 1 μM MTs (Figure 1C) and 
then compared the data with the theoretical curve (dotted line) that 
results when Eq. 2 is plotted with the K Dapp value measured by the 
TcMv approach (Figure 1B). Two major differences between the dot-
ted curve and the data are evident: </p>

<p>At low [Tau], the theoretical curve rises much faster than do 
1. 
the actual data points. This observation implies that Tau is 
binding to MTs more weakly in the TvMc experiments than in 
the TcMv experiments. Thus, the two approaches do yield 
different apparent affinities, even when all other variables are 
held constant. </p>

<p>The theoretical curve saturates at 1 μM bound Tau, while the 
2. 
experimental data keep rising in an approximately linear 
manner well beyond the expected saturation point (as shown 
by the red arrow in Figure 1C). This second issue makes 
it impossible to obtain a reasonable fit of Eq. 2 to the data 
in Figure 1C, regardless of the K D and N values allowed 
(Figure 1C and unpublished data). </p>

<p>In previous work, Ackmann and colleagues also observed Tau 
supersaturation, and they attributed this behavior to Tau-Tau inter-
actions occurring at the MT surface (Ackmann et al., 2000). To adjust 
for this additional interaction, they modified Eq. 2 by adding a linear 
term to fit the supersaturation of Tau, as shown in Eq. 3: </p>

<p>( [ 
][ 
] )/ ([ 
] 
) 
T 
TTau 
T u 
[ 
] 
u 
M </p>

<p>bound 
f ree </p>

<p>+ 
= N 
] 
Tau free 
a </p>

<p>ree 
f </p>

<p>+ ( ( / )[ 
][ 
1 ρ MT </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>K 
a 
(3) </p>

<p>Volume 23 December 15, 2012 </p>

<p>MTs promote formation of Tau filaments | 4805 </p>

<p>Interpretation of the binding experiments </p>

<p>To yield valid dissociation constants when using standard binding 
models to fit cosedimentation data, several assumptions must be 
met. These include the ideas that: 1) Tau-MT binding events 
are independent and reversible, 2) Tau-MT binding is the only 
significant interaction occurring in the solution, 3) the interactions 
have reached equilibrium, and 4) cosedimentation of Tau with 
MTs reflects the binding of Tau to MTs. Our observation that the 
apparent affinity depends on the concentration of both Tau and 
MTs demonstrates that at least one of these assumptions is being 
violated, and, therefore, that neither Eq. 1 nor Eq. 2 can be val-
idly applied to the Tau-MT cosedimentation data. This conclu-
sion is consistent with that of Ackmann et al. (2000), who deter-
mined on the basis of TvMc analysis that Tau-Tau interactions are 
occurring on the MT and Eq. 2 is not sufficient to describe bind-
ing of Tau to MTs. To address these issues, Ackmann and col-
leagues modified Eq. 2 to include a term that attempts to ac-
count for the Tau-Tau interactions on the MT surface (Eq. 3). 
However, we find that even Ackmann's modified binding equa-
tion (Eq. 3) is insufficient to describe Tau-MT binding behavior, 
because the observed K D and ρ values (implied by Ackmann to 
be constants) vary with [MT] (Figure 1E). One explanation for 
these observations is that an as yet unaccounted for interaction is 
occurring in the Tau-MT binding assays. As discussed in the sec-
tion of the article on investigations of Tau-Tau interactions, we 
provide evidence that this additional interaction is the MT-
induced formation of Tau-only filaments. </p>

<p>where N is the ratio of bound Tau to tubulin dimer (set to be 1 
Tau:1 tubulin dimer for all data sets, consistent with the N used 
in the TcMv approach), and ρ is an additional overloading pa-
rameter described by Ackmann et al. (2000) as being "formally 
reminiscent of a K D value describing a weak affinity of Tau 
[for Tau]." The first half of Eq. 3 is identical to Eq. 2 and calcu-
lates the affinity between the protein and the ligand. The second 
half of Eq. 3 is a linear term introduced by Ackmann and col-
leagues to account for the amount of Tau that sediments beyond 
saturation. 
When we fit our data using this biphasic Eq. 3, we obtain a K D of 
2.02 ± 1.03 μM and a ρ of 6.88 ± 0.37 μM (Figure 1C). This K D value 
is inconsistent with the K D = 75 nM reported by Ackmann and col-
leagues, and it is more than an order of magnitude weaker than the 
value produced by analysis of the TcMv data (Figure 1B). </p>

<p>The apparent affinity of Tau-MT interactions depends on 
the concentrations of both Tau and MTs </p>

<p>As seen above, different experimental designs lead to different ap-
parent values for the Tau-MT affinity (Figure 1, B and C). However, 
differences in method and/or model alone cannot account for the 
discrepancies in the literature: when comparing the results of the 
TvMc approach as reported by different research groups, the affinity 
values still vary more than an order of magnitude from 75 nM to 
&gt;1 μM (Ackmann et al., 2000; Sun and Gamblin, 2009; Fauquant 
et al., 2011). One potential explanation for the variation is that the 
strength of Tau-MT interactions depends on [Tau]. Indeed, such a 
concentration dependence would be expected from Ackmann's evi-
dence that Tau-Tau interactions can occur at the MT surface. The 
existence of a Tau concentration dependence could also explain 
why the apparent affinity depends on the method, because [Tau] is 
held constant in the TcMv approach, but varies in the TvMc 
approach. 
To test this possibility, we repeated the experiments of Figure 
1, B and C, using the same two approaches, but with different 
concentrations of proteins under otherwise identical conditions. 
When we changed [Tau] used in the TcMv approach, we found 
that the apparent Tau-MT affinity also changed (Figure 1D): while 
1 μM Tau yielded an apparent affinity of 0.11 ± 0.02 μM (Figure 
1B), 2 μM and 4 μM Tau yielded K Dapp values of 1.39 ± 0.35 μM 
and 0.67 ± 0.16 μM, respectively (Figure 1D). The change in ap-
parent affinity is expected from the idea that Tau binds to Tau on 
the MT surface (Ackmann et al., 2000), but we were puzzled by 
the inconsistent nature of the change: the K D value extracted from 
the fit rose (i.e., the apparent affinity weakened) from 1 μM to 
2 μM Tau and then fell from 2 to 4 μM Tau. It is also notable that 
the data for the 2 and 4 μM Tau experiments are more variable 
than the data for the 1 μM Tau. While this variability made it diffi-
cult to fit the curves, the general trends observed in Figure 1D 
were consistent across many experiments (Figure 1D and unpub-
lished data). Possible origins of this variability are discussed more 
in the main text. 
We then studied how Tau-MT interaction measured by the TvMc 
approach depends on the [MT]. Using Eq. 3 to fit the data and set-
ting N = 1 for consistency, we found that when [MT] changes from 1 
to 0.5 to 0.1 μM, the measured K D changes from 2.02 ± 1.03 μM to 
0.84 ± 0.41 μM to 0.10 ± 0.32 μM, respectively (Figure 1E). More-
over, the ρ parameter (described as being similar to an apparent K D 
for the Tau-Tau interaction; Ackmann et al., 2000) also changes, 
ranging from 6.8 ± 0.37 μM at 1 μM MTs to 1.06 ± 0.04 μM at 0.1 μM 
MTs. Allowing N to vary did not improve the consistency of the 
extracted K D or ρ values (unpublished data). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by grant MCB-0951264 from the National 
Science Foundation. We thank William Archer for his technical TEM 
assistance and the Goodson lab members for insightful discussions. </p>





<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



</text></tei>