<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3865143" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">Actiware</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.71.0</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Philips Respironics Inc</rs><rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">22.0</rs>Confidence 
Challenge 
Immersion </p>

<p>Figure 2 Flow checklist scores (range 1-7). 
Notes: *P,0.05; **P,0.01. Confidence refers to "confidence in competence", 
challenge refers to "achieving goals", and immersion refers to "positive emotion and 
absorption". Vertical lines (ie, deviation) in the figures show standard errors. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Sleep deprivation and flow experience </p>

<p>and negatively correlated with fatigue (r=−0.43 to −0.68) and 
sleepiness (r=−0.38 to −0.55). However, none of the three 
factors of flow showed any significant correlations with PVT 
indices (median reaction time and lapses). Median PVT was 
significantly and positively correlated with fatigue (r=0.35) 
and sleepiness (r=0.37). Median PVT and lapses were 
strongly correlated with each other (r=0.91). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study reveals that all aspects of flow experience 
(confidence, challenge, and immersion) decrease after sleep 
deprivation. In addition, flow indices were significantly 
and negatively correlated with fatigue (r=−0.43 to −0.68) 
and sleepiness (r=−0.38 to −0.55). These results suggest 
that sleep/sleepiness is an important factor in flow experi-
ence, and maintaining a low level of sleepiness is essential 
in order to induce flow. To the best of our knowledge, </p>

<p>the relationship between sleep loss and flow experience has 
not been previously examined. 
Consistent with previous studies, positive mood (vital-
ity) was reduced and negative mood (sleepiness, fatigue, 
confusion, anger) was increased after sleep deprivation. 19,31-34 
Importantly, this study found that flow experience and vitality 
were positively related (r=0.45 to 0.57). The results support 
our assumption based on the cognitive energy model 11,12 that 
lower levels of cognitive energy, due to sleep deprivation, 
reduce the motivation to engage in challenging tasks and 
hence impede flow experience. This is consistent with another 
report in which sleep deprivation was found to impede con-
centration and creative thinking. 35 
In the present study, confusion and anxiety ratings 
increased after sleep loss, although the result for anxiety 
did not reach statistical significance (P=0.07). These results 
are consistent with previous studies reporting that 36 hours 
of prolonged wakefulness increases self-reported anxiety 
on the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory questionnaire. 36 It has 
been reported that panic attacks are more likely to occur 
in insomniacs, 22 and this may be related to deterioration in 
mood due to sleep loss. 
There were no significant correlations between flow 
indices and PVT performances. This suggests that flow may 
not influence basic cognitive ability as reflected in simple 
reaction skills. The present study used PVT because it is sen-
sitive to sleep loss. A number of other performance tasks have 
been developed and tested to evaluate the effect of sleep loss; 
these include the Stroop task, 16 switching task, 13 visual search 
task, 37 and a working memory task. 38 However, these tasks 
are less associated with sleep deprivation than with PVT, 39 </p>

<p>This work was supported by JSPS KAKENHI (25705022). </p>

<p>Table 1 Pearson's product-moment correlation coefficient (r) </p>

<p>PVT 
Median </p>

<p>Lapses </p>

<p>Flow 
confidence </p>

<p>Challenge </p>

<p>Immersion </p>

<p>POMS 
anxiety </p>

<p>Sadness </p>

<p>Anger </p>

<p>Vitality </p>

<p>Fatigue </p>

<p>Confusion </p>

<p>Sleepiness </p>

<p>PVT 
Median </p>

<p>0.91 </p>

<p>−0.05 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>−0.07 </p>

<p>0.19 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>−0.34 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>−0.01 </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>lapses </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>−0.22 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>−0.07 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>Flow 
Confidence </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>−0.45 </p>

<p>−0.07 </p>

<p>−0.38 </p>

<p>0.45 </p>

<p>−0.43 </p>

<p>−0.63 </p>

<p>−0.55 </p>

<p>challenge </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>−0.24 </p>

<p>−0.02 </p>

<p>−0.34 </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>−0.43 </p>

<p>−0.43 </p>

<p>−0.38 </p>

<p>immersion </p>

<p>−0.10 </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>−0.02 </p>

<p>0.57 </p>

<p>−0.68 </p>

<p>−0.15 </p>

<p>−0.52 </p>

<p>POMs 
anxiety </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>−0.15 </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>sadness </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>−0.51 </p>

<p>0.29 </p>

<p>−0.15 </p>

<p>anger </p>

<p>−0.32 </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>0.54 </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>Vitality </p>

<p>−0.59 </p>

<p>−0.38 </p>

<p>−0.67 </p>

<p>Fatigue </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p>confusion </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>Note: Bold type indicates statistical significance at P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: PVT, psychomotor vigilance test; POMS, Profile of Mood Status. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/neuropsychiatric-disease-and-treatment-journal </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment is an international, peer-
reviewed journal of clinical therapeutics and pharmacology focusing 
on concise rapid reporting of clinical or pre-clinical studies on a 
range of neuropsychiatric and neurological disorders. This journal 
is indexed on PubMed Central, the 'PsycINFO' database and CAS. </p>

<p>The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Sleep deprivation and flow experience </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>