<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3134982" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Background: The effects of freezing-thawing cycles on intramedullary bone-implant interfaces have been 
studied in a rat model in mechanical pull-out tests. </p>

<p>Implants: Twenty TiAl6V4 rods (Ø 0.8 mm, length 10 mm) implanted in rat tibiae </p>

<p>Methods: 10 rats underwent bilateral tibial implantation of titanium rods. At eight weeks, the animals were sacrificed and 
tibiae harvested for biomechanical testing. Eight tibiae were frozen and stored at -20°C for 14 days, the remaining eight 
were evaluated immediately post-harvest. Pull-out tests were used to determine maximum force and interfacial shear 
strength. </p>

<p>Results: There were no significant differences between fresh and those of the frozen-thawed group in maximum force or 
in interfacial shear strength. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Frozen Storage of rat tibiae containing implants at -20° C has no effects on the biomechanical properties of 
Bone/ Implant interface. </p>

<p>Orthopaedic and Dental implants rely on osseointegration 
to achieve mechanical fixation to the host bone, which is a 
prerequisite for a good clinical outcome [1, 2]. In the past, 
various approaches have been used to enhance peri-implant 
bone formation. Hydroxyapatite coatings [3], in combination 
with growth factors [4, 5], bisphosphonates [6] or 
biomimetic surfaces [7] have been shown to improve 
osseointegration of titanium implants. Traditionally, large 
animal models have been used to study orthopaedic and 
dental implant fixation [5, 8-10]. More recently, rat models 
have generated an increased interest [6, 11, 12]. Molecular 
studies are easy to perform, care and handling of rodents is 
more manageable and overall costs are reduced. In the rat 
model a tibial or femoral implant is frequently used to assess 
osseointegration. The conditions and procedures for all parts 
of the trial, e. g. anaesthesia, implantation procedures [13], 
storage of tissue samples and mechanical testing must be 
defined and replicated at each stage. </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Klinik für Unfall-, Hand-und 
Wiederherstellungschirurgie, Universitätsklinikum Jena, Erlanger Allee 101, 
07747 Jena, Germany; Tel: 0049 3641 9 322800; Fax: 0049 3641 9 322802; 
E-mail: Michael.Diefenbeck@med.uni-jena.de </p>

<p>Biomechanical testing has been performed under at least 
three conditions: fresh explanted bone [3, 5], frozen/thawed 
bone [4, 13] and dehydrated/rehydrated bone [14, 15]. In many 
reports, the condition of the bone during testing is not 
mentioned [6, 16, 17]. </p>

<p>The use of fresh bone in biomechanical tests should reveal 
optimal results, but is logistically difficult, especially when the 
sample size is large or the biomechanical testing laboratory is at 
some distance from the surgical laboratory. Additionally, there 
is a risk of losing specimens, due to unforeseen complications 
during mechanical testing. </p>

<p>The purpose of the present study was to determine, if 
freezing and storage of bones with implants at -20° C have any 
effect on its biomechanical properties utilizing mechanical pull-
out tests in a rat model. A modified rat tibial implantation 
model, described by Gao et al. [6] with bilateral implantation of 
titanium rods was used. We compared the results of mechanical 
pull out tests of samples which had been stored at -20°C and 
thawed, with those of fresh explanted tibiae. </p>

<p>2. MATERIALS AND METHODOLOGY </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>All experiments were approved by the Animal Care 
Committee of Thuringia (Reg. No. G 02-008/10). Ten, 3-</p>



<p>Diefenbeck et al. </p>

<p>months-old male Sprague Dawley rats (Harlan Laboratories 
GmbH, Eystrup, Germany) weighing 300g -389 g were 
used. All were given free access to standard rat-chow and 
water. The environment was air-conditioned with a 
controlled light cycle of 12 h/dark 12 h, relatively steady 
temperature and humidity. An institutional guideline for the 
care and treatment of laboratory animals was followed. </p>

<p>Implants </p>

<p>Twenty custom TiAl6V4 rods (Königsee Implantate 
GmbH, Aschau, Germany) 0.8 mm in diameter and 10 mm 
in length were used. All implants were blasted with ceramic 
beads as a standard procedure for orthopaedic implants. </p>

<p>Sterilization of the implants at 134 °C -138 °C, 2.16 bar 
pressure for 35 minutes (Vacuklav 44B, Melag, Berlin, 
Germany) prior to implantation was performed. </p>

<p>Conditions </p>

<p>Two different conditions were tested: </p>

<p>Group A) Fresh explanted bone with implant in situ </p>

<p>Group B) Stored bone with implant in situ at -20°C for 14 
days </p>

<p>Implant Procedure </p>

<p>Surgery was performed under general anaesthesia by 
weight-adopted intraperitoneal injection of Domitor </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>(Meditomidin) 0.15 mg/kg BW(Pfizer, Berlin, Germany), 
Dormicum 
® (Midazolam) 2.0 mg/kg BW (Ratiopharm, Ulm, 
Germany) and Fentanyl 
® (Fentanyl) 0.005 mg/kg BW 
(Janssen-Cilag, Neuss, Germany). </p>

<p>Animals were prepared for surgery: Both hind legs were 
shaved and disinfected with alcohol. Sterile conditions were 
adhered to throughout the surgery using sterile drapes and 
sheets. Both hind legs were draped with a sterile incision foil 
(Raucodrape, Lohmann &amp; Rauscher, Rengsdorf, Germany). 
A medial incision to expose the knee joint in both hind limbs 
was made 5 mm longitudinally, and a pilot hole was marked 
at the intercondylar eminence. A custom-made awl, tip size 
0.9 mm in diameter and 10 mm in length was gradually 
rotated to create a channel from the proximal tibia epiphysis 
into the medullary canal. The implants were inserted via this 
channel and positioned 2 mm beyond the articulating 
cartilage. Soft tissue was irrigated with sterile saline with 
fascia and skin incisions were closed in single-knot 
technique (Vicryl 5/0 and Prolene 5/0, Ethicon, Norderstedt, 
Germany). Prophylactic IM antibiotic (Terramycin, Pfizer 
GmbH, Berlin, Germany) and analgesics (Buprenovet, 
Bayer, Leverkusen, Germany) were administered once at the 
time of surgery. Implant position was monitored and 
confirmed by X-ray. General anaesthesia was reversed by 
Antisedan 
® (Atipamezol) 0.75 mg/kg BW (Pfizer, Berlin, 
Germany), Flumazenil-hameln 
® (Flumazenil) 0.2 mg/kg BW 
(Invera Arzneimittel GmbH, Freiburg, Germany) and 
Naloxon (Naloxon) 0.12 mg/kg BW (Deltaselect GmbH, 
Dreieich, Germany). </p>

<p>Explant Procedure </p>

<p>The animals were sacrificed at eight weeks. Tibiae were 
harvested and cleared of all soft tissue. In group A), the 
tibiae were processed immediately and mechanical testing </p>

<p>was completed within 4 hours while samples of group B) 
were stored at -20°C for the next 14 days. </p>

<p>Tibia epi-and metaphysis were trimmed to expose the 
proximal tip of implant for 2 mm -3 mm by using a bur 
(Minimot 40IE, Proxxon, Niersbach/Eifel, Germany) to 
prepare the implant for mechanical testing. </p>

<p>This was carried out in group A) right after explantation; 
in group B) the samples were frozen, processed and then re-
frozen at -20°C. </p>

<p>Biomechanical Testing </p>

<p>Due to one surgical site infection and one anaesthetic 
complication the sample size was reduced to 8 implants in 
each group. </p>

<p>The biomechanical property of the bone/implant-
interface was assessed using a pull-out test. The distal part of 
the tibia was embedded in polyester resin (CEM 2000, 
Cloeren Technology GmbH, Wegberg, Germany), which is 
selected as it does not develop high temperatures during 
polymerisation. For embedding, a custom made fixture was 
used to permit coaxial alignment of the implant in the 
direction of force (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>The tibiae were tested in a commercial material testing 
system (Tiratest 2710, Tira GmbH, Schalkau, Germany) post 
air-thawing at room temperature (Fig. 2). A distraction speed 
of 1 mm/min was set for the test, with a load-displacement 
curve recorded simultaneously. The resultant curves allow a 
maximum force to be determined and interfacial shear 
strength then calculated by dividing the force (N) at the point 
of failure by the surface area of the implant in contact with 
tissue (mm 
2 ). </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Data are presented in Figs. (1, 2) as box-and-whisker 
plots indicating median, quartiles, whiskers and outliers. 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">StatGraphics Centurion</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Statpoint Technologies, Inc</rs>., 
Warrenton, Virginia, USA) was used for statistical analysis. 
One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) following multiple 
comparisons with Fisher's least significant difference (LSD) 
procedure at the 95.0% confidence level was performed to 
determine if there were significant differences. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 8 tibiae from each group have been included in 
this analysis. Biomechanical testing revealed no significant 
influence of the different conditions (fresh vs. frozen-
thawed) on maximum force required to extract the implant or 
on the corresponding interfacial shear strength (Figs. 3, 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Several studies have been performed to assess the effects 
of tissue preservation on the mechanical properties of bone 
in different animal models [18-23]. Usually, mechanical 
properties of whole bone in 4-point bending tests [20, 21, 23,  24] or of bone slices in compression tests [18, 19] and 
indentations tests [19] are evaluated. Almost all of these 
studies have found no significant difference between fresh 
and frozen samples on mechanical testing [18-21, 23, 24]. </p>

<p>Given the large difference in linear thermal expansion 
coefficients between fresh bone (89 ± 2 x 10 
-6/ K) [25] and </p>

<p>Frozen/Thawed Rat Tibiae Maintain Mechanical Properties </p>

<p>The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2011, Volume 5 221 </p>

<p>titanium (8.5 x 10 
-6/ K) [26], we hypothesized that a 
significant difference may exist between fresh and frozen-
thawed samples in mechanical testing of bone/implant-
interfaces. </p>

<p>Fig. (2). Mechanical pull out tests: The implant was fixed via a 
three jaw drill chuck to the testing system. </p>

<p>Fig. (3). Maximum force in [N] measured by pull out tests: No 
statistically significant differences between fresh (Group A) and 
frozen-thawing (Group B) samples at the 95.0% confidence level 
(Fisher's least significant difference (LSD) procedure). </p>

<p>We utilized an in vivo tibial implant model in rats to 
analyze the osseointegration of titanium alloy implants. The 
intramedullary implants are fixed by de novo bone 
formation. This thin bone/implant-interface, which had 
developed over the eight weeks, may be more susceptible to 
effects of tissue preservation. </p>

<p>Reports of different preservation techniques in 
intramedullary implant fixation and mechanical pull-out tests 
are scarce. Huss BT et al. reported no difference in pull-out 
testing of cortical Steinmann pins in frozen or fresh 
cadaveric canine bone and also of implants placed in in vivo 
[22]. In our in vivo model, we compared fresh to frozen 
implant-bone interfaces. </p>

<p>Group B (frozen/thawed) showed a trend towards a lower 
shear strength in the mechanical testing, which was not 
significant (average shear strength group B 0.45 ± 0.13 </p>

<p>Fig. (1). Photo of the experimental set-up: The implant was fixed in a custom made device, permitting coaxial alignment and then embedded 
in a polyester resin. </p>

<p>222 The Open Orthopaedics Journal, 2011, Volume 5 </p>

<p>Diefenbeck et al. </p>

<p>N/mm 
2 vs. group A 0.63 ± 0.09 N/mm 
2 ). A possible 
explanation for this trend could be that the bone/implant 
interface was weakened by the freezing/thawing cycles. No 
significant difference regarding maximal pull out force and 
shear strength was found between fresh samples and those 
stored at -20° and air thawed. These results seem to be in 
general agreement with the findings on whole bone without 
implants, despite the bone-implant interface being prone to 
adverse effects of tissue preservation. </p>

<p>Fig. (4). Shear strength in [N/mm 
2 ] measured by pull out tests: No 
statistically significant differences between fresh (Group A) and 
frozen-thawing (Group B) samples at the 95.0% confidence level 
(Fisher's least significant difference (LSD) procedure). </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Freezing and thawing does not significantly affect the 
maximum force and interfacial shear strength in mechanical 
pull-out tests when evaluating implant fixation in a rat tibial 
model. Sample storage at -20°C can be used to simplify the 
experimental set-up. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>This work was supported by Thüringer Aufbaubank 
through a grant from the "Europäischer Fonds für regionale 
Entwicklung" [EFRE] (2008 VF 0048). </p>



<p>Received: February 19, 2011 
Revised: May 6, 2011 
Accepted: May 9, 2011 </p>

<p>© Diefenbeck et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. 
This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>