<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3490414" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Gene duplication is an important evolutionary mechanism and no eukaryote has more duplicated gene families than the parasitic 
protist Trichomonas vaginalis. Iron is an essential nutrient for Trichomonas and plays a pivotal role in the establishment of infection, 
proliferation, and virulence. To gain insight into the role of iron in T. vaginalis gene expression and genome evolution, we screened 
iron-regulated genes using an oligonucleotide microarray for T. vaginalis and by comparative EST (expressed sequence tag) sequen-
cing of cDNA libraries derived from trichomonads cultivated under iron-rich (+Fe) and iron-restricted (ÀFe) conditions. Among 
19,000 ESTs from both libraries, we identified 336 iron-regulated genes, of which 165 were upregulated under +Fe conditions 
and 171 under ÀFe conditions. The microarray analysis revealed that 195 of 4,950 unique genes were differentially expressed. Of 
these, 117 genes were upregulated under +Fe conditions and 78 were upregulated under ÀFe conditions. The results of both 
methods were congruent concerning the regulatory trends and the representation of gene categories. Under +Fe conditions, the 
expression of proteins involved in carbohydrate metabolism, particularly in the energy metabolism of hydrogenosomes, and in 
methionine catabolism was increased. The iron-sulfur cluster assembly machinery and certain cysteine proteases are of particular 
importance among the proteins upregulated under ÀFe conditions. A unique feature of the T. vaginalis genome is the retention 
during evolution of multiple paralogous copies for a majority of all genes. Although the origins and reasons for this gene expansion 
remain unclear, the retention of multiple gene copies could provide an opportunity to evolve differential expression during growth in 
variable environmental conditions. For genes whose expression was affected by iron, we found that iron influenced the expression of 
only some of the paralogous copies, whereas the expression of the other paralogs was iron independent. This finding indicates a very 
stringent regulation of the differentially expressed paralogous genes in response to changes in the availability of exogenous nutrients 
and provides insight into the evolutionary rationale underlying massive paralog retention in the Trichomonas genome. </p>

<p>Gene duplications are important in evolution (Lynch and 
Conery 2000), and no genome has more recently duplicated 
genes than the parasitic flagellate Trichomonas vaginalis, the 
causative agent of trichomoniasis (Carlton et al. 2007; Cui 
et al. 2010). Trichomoniasis is the most common sexually </p>

<p>transmitted infection of nonviral origin in humans. Although 
trichomoniasis is usually self-limiting in males, it causes serious 
health problems for female patients, including an increased 
risk of cervical cancer, pelvic inflammatory disease, infertility, 
and transmission of the HIV (Laga et al. 1993; Zhang and Begg 
1994; Viikki et al. 2000; Moodley et al. 2002). Trichomoniasis 
during pregnancy is associated with low birth weight, the </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits non-
commercial reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 4(10):1017-1029. doi:10.1093/gbe/evs078 Advance Access publication September 12, 2012 </p>



<p>premature rupture of membranes and preterm birth (Cotch 
et al. 1997). The establishment of a T. vaginalis infection as 
well as infections by other pathogenic microorganisms is 
dependent on the efficient acquisition of essential nutrients 
such as iron, from the host environment. Trichomonads 
can utilize various host iron-containing proteins such as lacto-
ferrin, transferrin, ferritin, hemoglobin, and low-molecular-
weight-iron complexes (Sutak et al. 2008). Iron is required 
for critical housekeeping functions such as proteosynthesis, 
genome duplication, and energy fixation. A significant portion 
of the trichomonad energy metabolism takes place in 
hydrogenosomes, whose function is particularly dependent 
on iron (Gorrell 1985; Vaná cová et al. 2001). These specific 
mitochondria-related organelles contain a number of FeS pro-
teins that catalyze key steps in ferredoxin-linked electron 
transport, hydrogen production, and ATP synthesis at the 
level of substrate phosphorylation (Hrdy et al. 2004). The for-
mation of FeS clusters in the catalytic centers of apoproteins is 
mediated by the hydrogenosomal iron-sulfur cluster (ISC) as-
sembly machinery, which consists of approximately 10 pro-
teins, of which cysteine desulfurase (IscS) and the molecular 
scaffold protein IscU are the main components (Tachezy et al. 
2001; Sutak, Dolezal, et al. 2004. Iron is also required for the 
functions of cytosolic and nuclear FeS proteins such as Rli1p, 
which is a protein essential for ribosome biogenesis and func-
tion (Kispal et al. 2005; Yarunin et al. 2005). This protein is 
highly conserved in eukaryotes, including T. vaginalis (Smíd 
et al. 2008). 
In addition to housekeeping functions, iron affects specific 
host-pathogen interactions associated with the virulence of 
the parasite. Experiments performed in vitro have shown that 
iron regulates the cytoadherence of T. vaginalis to target cells 
(Mundodi et al. 2006) as well as the expression of cysteine 
proteinases (Sommer et al. 2005; Solano-Gonzá lez et al. 
2007; Kummer et al. 2008), ecto-ATPases and ecto-phosphat-
ases (De Jesus et al. 2006), and it increases trichomonad re-
sistance to complement-mediated lysis (Alderete et al. 1995). 
Iron-dependent enhancement of experimental infections in 
mice was demonstrated with the related bovine parasite 
Tritrichomonas foetus (Kulda et al. 1999). However, little is 
known about the mechanisms underlying the iron-dependent 
regulation of these processes. Positive iron regulation at the 
transcriptional level was observed for the expression of some 
hydrogenosomal proteins, including malic enzyme (ME) and 
pyruvate:ferredoxin oxidoreductase (PFOR) (Vaná cová et al. 
2001). A detailed study of the iron-dependent regulation of 
hydrogenosomal ME, which may alternatively be present on 
the cell surface as the adhesin (AP65-1) (Hirt et al. 2007), led 
to the identification of Myb recognition elements and novel 
Myb proteins that appear to be components of a multifarious 
regulatory machinery in T. vaginalis (Ong et al. 2006, 2007). 
Two cysteine proteases, TVCP4 and TVCP12, were recently 
reported to be regulated at the posttranscriptional level by 
an iron-responsive element/iron response protein-like system </p>

<p>(Solano-Gonzá lez et al. 2007; Torres-Romero and Arroyo 
2009). 
We combined cDNA microarray analysis with an expressed 
sequence tag (EST) approach to map iron-regulated genes and 
to reconstruct iron-regulated pathways in T. vaginalis. Our 
data revealed numerous iron-responsive genes that are 
involved in several essential pathways, particularly in cytosolic 
glycolysis and extended glycolysis in hydrogenosomes, as well 
as genes that encode components of the FeS cluster assembly 
machinery. Moreover, iron affected the expression of many 
genes with unknown functions. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Cell Cultures </p>

<p>Axenic cultures of T. vaginalis strain T1 were grown in trypti-
case-yeast extract-maltose medium supplemented with 10% 
heat-inactivated horse serum, pH 6.2 (Diamond 1957). Iron-
rich medium (+Fe) and iron-restricted medium (ÀFe) were 
supplemented with 100 mM Fe-nitrilotriacetate; and 50 mM 
2-2-dipyridyl (Sigma), respectively. The cells were subcultured 
daily in +Fe and ÀFe media for 5 days prior to experiment. </p>

<p>cDNA Library Construction and DNA Sequencing </p>

<p>RNA isolation kit (Pharmacia) was used to extract the total 
RNA from cells grown under +Fe and ÀFe conditions, and 
contaminating genomic DNA was digested with DNase I. 
PolyA+ RNA was isolated using a PolyA+ tract mRNA isolation 
kit (Promega). Complementary DNA was synthesized using a 
ZAP-cDNA synthesis kit after priming with oligo-dT. The cDNA 
was then directionally cloned into the EcoRI and XhoI sites of 
the Uni-ZAP XR vector (Stratagene). Single and well-separated 
plaques were cored out from agar plates and transferred to 
96-well microtiter plates containing SM buffer. The phage 
stocks were used as templates for cDNA insert amplification 
with T3 and T7 primers (1 nM for each primer). The amplified 
products were separated in 1.5% agarose gels, and clones 
that yielded single polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-amplified 
bands were collected for sequencing. Single-pass sequencing 
from the 5 
0 -end of the cDNA insert was initiated with a T3 
primer using the ABI PRISM BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequen-
cing Kit (Applied Biosystems). The sequencing products were 
resolved and analysed on an ABI PRISM 377 (Applied Biosys-
tems) or a MEGABACE DNA Sequencer (GE). The nucleotide 
sequences obtained were processed with the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Phred/Phrap/ 
Consed package</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.phrap.org/phredphrapconsed.html</rs>). </p>

<p>Functional Annotations and Sequence Analysis </p>

<p>BLAST tools were used to compare the assembled sequence 
contigs to known Trichomonas mRNAs, putative open-read-
ing-frames from the T. vaginalis G3 genome (Carlton et al. 
2007) and NCBI's nonredundant (nr) nucleotide (E value ¼ </p>

<p>Horvá thová et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>1018 Genome Biol. Evol. 4(10):1017-1029. doi:10.1093/gbe/evs078 Advance Access publication September 12, 2012 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>À15 </p>

<p>) and protein database. Genes were functionally anno-
tated based on the Interpro and Gene Ontology databases. 
Contigs with identity greater than 60% of their length were 
annotated and assigned to KEGG pathways. 
Putative coding regions from the EST data were collected 
from BLASTX alignments, and the codon usage bias was cal-
culated. A Perl script was also written to locate poly-A tails and 
to search 10-35 bp upstream for putative mRNA poly-adeny-
lation signals; the script allowed one mismatch and two 
mismatches from the sequence AAUAAA. Putative signal se-
quences and transmembrane domains in the coding regions 
were identified by <rs id="software-2" type="software">SignalP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.0</rs> and <rs id="software-3" type="software">TMHMM</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">2.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services</rs>/), respectively. Putative Trichomonas pro-
tein kinases and peptidases were identified by sequence com-
parison with datasets downloaded from the KinBase (http:// 
www.kinase.com) and the MEROPS (http://merops.sanger.ac 
.uk) databases, respectively. </p>

<p>Microarray Sample Preparation </p>

<p>RNA from trichomonads grown in +Fe and ÀFe conditions 
was isolated using a QuickPrep Total RNA Extraction Kit 
(Amersham Biosciences) according to the manufacturer's in-
structions. The total RNA was further purified using an RNeasy 
CleanUp Kit (Qiagen). The RNA concentration and purity were 
determined using a NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer 
(NanoDrop Technologies). The integrity of the RNA was 
checked by agarose gel electrophoresis. The same RNA sam-
ples were used in parallel experiments for cDNA microarray 
analysis and quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). cDNA 
probes were synthesized using 2 mg of total RNA and primers 
labeled with Cy3 and Cy5, respectively, according to the 
manufacturer's instructions (3DNA Array 900 Expression 
Array Detection Kit, Genisphere). Four independent RNA sam-
ples (biological replicates) from T. vaginalis strain T1 grown 
under +Fe and ÀFe conditions were compared. A dye-swap 
design was used to prevent dye-associated effects on cDNA 
synthesis. </p>

<p>Microarray Analysis </p>

<p>A T. vaginalis customized cDNA microarray (TvArray V2.0) was 
implemented by the Molecular Regulation and Bioinformatics 
Laboratory, Chang Gung University, Taiwan. The TvArray chip 
contained PCR products amplified from 7,688 EST clones with 
an average GC content of 38.36% and an average length of 
384 bp. The cDNA inserts were fabricated on GAPS 
TM II 
Coated Slides (Corning. USA). The microarrays were prehy-
bridized in Coplin chambers using a solution containing 1% 
bovine serum albumine, 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate, and 3X 
saline sodium citrate buffer (1X SSC consists of 0.15 M NaCl 
with 0.015 M sodium acetate). The slides were incubated at 
50 
C for 30 min, washed with water and isopropanol and 
dried by centrifugation at 90 Â g for 3 min. Hybridization 
with the cDNA hybridization mix and washes were performed </p>

<p>following the protocol for the 3DNA Array 900 Expression 
Array Detection Kit (Genisphere). cDNA hybridizations were 
performed in a VersArray Hybridization Chamber (Bio-Rad) at 
60 
C overnight. Hybridizations with fluorescent 3DNA re-
agents were performed in the same chamber at 60 
C for 
4 h. After the final washing step, the slides were dried by 
centrifugation at 90 Â g for 3 min and scanned using the 
GenePix 4200A scanner (Axon). GenePix Pro 5.1 software 
was used to determine the average signal intensity and the 
local background for each spot. The Cy3/Cy5 fluorescence 
ratios were Log 2 transformed and normalized by LOWESS 
normalization method in the TIGR microarray data analysis 
system <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 2.19</rs> (Saeed et al. 2003). In total, 10 independ-
ent hybridizations using samples from 4 independent cultures 
and RNA extractions were performed and data of the inde-
pendent experiments were combined. We used MeV v4.8.1 
to determine significantly regulated genes. One-class Student 
t test was performed and P values were based on all 1,024 
possible permutations (cut-off was 0.01) and the proportion 
of false significant genes was set to not exceed 10 genes. 
The results of all experiments are available in the Array-
Express database (http://www.ebi.ac.uk/arrayexpress/) under 
the array design name TvArray v1.0. </p>

<p>qRT-PCR Analysis </p>

<p>Oligonucleotide primers (supplementary table S1, Supplemen-
tary Material online) were designed using <rs id="software-5" type="software">Primer Designer</rs> 
software <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">v1.01</rs> (Scientific and Education software). The pri-
mers were tested prior to qRT-PCR analysis using DNA as a 
template, and single amplicons of the proper size were 
sequenced. The RT reaction contained 1 mg of total RNA, 
500 ng of Oligo(dT) 15 Primer (Invitrogen), 5 mM DTT 
(Invitrogen), 2 U of RNasin (Invitrogen), 10 U of SuperScriptII 
reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen), and 500 mM each of dATP, 
dCTP, dGTP, and dTTP. The reactions were incubated at 42 
C 
for 50 min followed by 15 min at 70 
C. For qRT-PCR, 1 ml of 
cDNA was amplified in a 25 ml reaction mixture containing 
each gene-specific primer at 50 nM and 12.5 ml of iQTM 
SYBR green Supermix (Bio-Rad). All reactions were performed 
in triplicate using a RotorGene 2000 Real-Time PCR cycler 
(Corbett Life Science). The expression levels of each gene 
were normalized to those of the housekeeping gene b-tubu-
lin, expression of which is not affected by the availability of 
iron. Relative quantitative values were obtained by the com-
parative threshold cycle (2 </p>

<p>ÀÁÁC </p>

<p>T ) method as described by 
(Livak and Schmittgen 2001). </p>

<p>Analysis of 5 
0 Untranslated Regions </p>

<p>An application based on the NetBeans Platform (http://plat 
form.netbeans.org) was developed to search for MRE-like 
motifs in 300 bp of the upstream regions of all iron-regulated 
genes. We searched for the MRE eukaryotic consensus (C/T) 
AACG(G/T) and the specific MREs of the ME gene as described </p>

<p>Transcriptomic Identification of +Fe and ÀFe Gene Copies </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 4(10):1017-1029. doi:10.1093/gbe/evs078 Advance Access publication September 12, 2012 </p>



<p>by Hsu et al. (2009): MRE1/MRE2r (A[A/T/C/G]AACGAT, CGA 
TA, AACGATA, and TAACGA) and MRE2f (TATCGT and TAT 
CGTC). </p>

<p>Results and Discussion </p>

<p>Microarray Analysis </p>

<p>To investigate changes in gene expression caused by iron avail-
ability, trichomonads were grown in media supplemented 
with 100 mM Fe-nitrilotriacetate (iron-rich conditions, +Fe) or 
with the iron chelator 2,2-dipyridyl (50 mM; iron-restricted 
conditions, ÀFe). To estimate timeframe for cultivation prior 
to RNA isolation, we monitored enzymatic activities of PFOR 
and ME (Rasoloson et al. 2002) as their expression is known to 
be affected by iron availability in trichomonads (Vaná cová 
et al. 2001). The activities of both enzymes decreased 
during 24 h cultivation under ÀFe conditions and then 
remained stable (supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary Mate-
rial online). Thus, to assure ultimate effect of iron on tricho-
monads, we cultivated the cells for 5 days under +Fe/ÀFe 
conditions prior to each experiment. The total RNA was 
then isolated from both treatment groups and hybridized 
onto DNA microarray slides containing PCR products amplified 
from 7,688 EST clones representing 4,950 unique T. vaginalis 
genes. A direct pairwise comparison strategy was used to 
identify differentially expressed genes. Altogether, 10 inde-
pendent hybridizations were performed using samples from 
four independent experiments. Genes whose expression ratios 
changed by a factor of at least 1.3 and had P values lower 
than 0.01 were considered to be significantly regulated by 
iron. In total, 195 genes met this criterion that represent ap-
proximately 4% of unique genes; 117 and 78 genes were 
upregulated in cells cultivated under +Fe and ÀFe conditions, 
respectively (fig. 1 and supplementary table S2a, Supplemen-
tary Material online). The distribution of genes into fold 
change categories is given in supplementary table S2b, Sup-
plementary Material online. The complete dataset including 
genes expression of which was not affected by iron was de-
posited in the ArrayExpress database (http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ 
arrayexpress/) under the array design name TvArray v1.0. 
To verify the cut-off limit and to validate the microarray 
data, we selected 15 genes for qRT-PCR analyses. The selec-
tion included genes that were not affected by iron (ferredoxin 
6, IscS-2), genes with moderate changes in expression (À1.42-
to 1.67-fold change) and genes with a greater than 2-fold 
change in expression (hydrogenase, alcohol dehydrogenase, 
and PFOR) according to the microarray data (table 1). In each 
instance, the qRT-PCR confirmed regulation trends observed 
in the microarray analysis. The ratios between paired samples 
(fold change) determined by qRT-PCR were, however, greater 
than the fold change obtained for the same gene by micro-
array analysis. These results are consistent with those of Yuen 
et al. (2002) and Dallas et al. (2005), who showed that </p>

<p>microarray analysis underestimates the changes in gene ex-
pression compared with the more qRT-PCR assay, although 
correlations between microarray and qRT-PCR data are gen-
erally strong. The list of genes that met the cut-off limit 1.3 in 
our study included majority of genes coding for proteins that 
were showed previously to be affected by iron on protein level 
in T. vaginalis and related parasite T. foetus such as PFOR, 
hydrogenosomal ME, hydrogenase, ferredoxin, cytosolic 
malate dehydrogenase, and cysteine protease (Vaná cová 
et al. 2001; De Jesus et al. 2007; Dolezal et al. 2007) that 
further supports validity of the microarray analysis. </p>

<p>Comparative EST Analysis </p>

<p>As a second technique to identify differentially expressed 
genes, we employed a comparative EST approach (Lee et al. 
1995). 10,042 and 9,032 ESTs were sequenced from two 
distinct cDNA libraries that were derived from trichomonads 
grown under +Fe and ÀFe conditions, respectively. The rela-
tive frequency (RF) of an EST was calculated as the number of 
ESTs per 10,000 clones. The upregulation index was calcu-
lated as the difference between the RF under +Fe conditions 
and the RF under ÀFe conditions. The distribution of unique 
genes to upregulation index categories is summarized in sup-
plementary table S2d, Supplementary Material online. The 
upregulation index values ranged from 1 to 70, which was 
considerably higher than the range of the fold change based 
on microarray analysis. Consequently we used higher cut-off 
limit: a gene was considered to be significantly upregulated if 
the upregulation index was greater than or equal to five. This 
criterion met 336 genes ($5%) out of a total number of 
6,381 unique genes that were generated by the assembly of 
the ESTs. Of those genes, 165 were upregulated under +Fe 
conditions, and 171 were upregulated under ÀFe conditions 
(supplementary table S2c, Supplementary Material online). A 
representation of the gene categories that were affected by 
iron availability is shown in figure 2. </p>

<p>Major Iron-Regulated Pathways </p>

<p>Glycolysis </p>

<p>The energy metabolism of T. vaginalis relies on fermentative 
carbohydrate catabolism in the cytosol that is extended to 
malate or pyruvate degradation in the hydrogenosome 
(Mü ller et al. 2012). At least one (but usually several) of mul-
tiple gene copies encoding glycolytic proteins showed signifi-
cant iron-dependent regulation (fig. 3 and supplementary 
table S3, Supplementary Material online), with similar results 
obtained from both methods (microarray and EST analysis). 
The enzymes that supply the glycolytic pathway with sub-
strates (glucokinase, glycogen phosphorylase, and phospho-
glucomutase) and the successive glycolytic enzymes were 
significantly upregulated under +Fe conditions. A striking 
exception was the upregulation of one of the four detected 
glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) genes </p>

<p>Horvá thová et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>α </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>FIG. 1.-Heatmap visualization of iron-regulated genes based on microarray analysis. Results of 10 experiments are given in columns A-J. (A) genes 
upregulated in +Fe conditions; (B) genes upregulated in ÀFe conditions. </p>

<p>Transcriptomic Identification of +Fe and ÀFe Gene Copies </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 4(10):1017-1029. doi:10.1093/gbe/evs078 Advance Access publication September 12, 2012 </p>



<p>(TVAG_366380) under ÀFe conditions according to the EST 
analysis, as the other three GAPDH genes were upregulated 
under +Fe conditions (fig. 3 and supplementary table S3, 
Supplementary Material online). It is tempting to speculate 
that GAPDH TVAG_366380 gene copy encodes protein 
with the function distinct from other paralogs. 
Multifunctional character of GAPDH was reported in macro-
phages where GAPDH serves as a surface receptor that is 
upregulated upon iron depletion (Rawat et al. 2012). 
Interestingly, T. vaginalis possesses two types of phosphofruc-
tokinase (PFK) (Liapounova et al. 2006) Inorganic pyrophos-
phate 
(PPi)-dependent 
PFK 
catalyzes 
reversible 
phosphorylation of fructose-6-phosphate in the cytosol 
(Mertens et al. 1998). More recently, putative 
ATP-dependent PFK has been identified in proteome of hydro-
genosomes (Rada et al. 2011). Two of the three genes that 
encode the PPi-dependent PFK and one of two genes for the 
ATP-dependent PFK were upregulated under +Fe conditions 
(supplementary table S3, Supplementary Material online). The 
most significant changes in iron-dependent gene expression 
were associated with the pathways that follow the conversion 
of phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP), the branch-point of carbohy-
drate metabolism. The enzymes that catalyze the formation of 
malate from PEP via oxaloacetate (PEP carboxykinase and 
malate dehydrogenase) were considerably upregulated 
under +Fe conditions (fig. 3). In contrast, the pathway that 
converts malate to lactate was upregulated under ÀFe condi-
tions. This pathway involves cytosolic NADP-dependent ME 
and NADH-dependent lactate dehydrogenase (fig. 3). These 
findings indicate that under +Fe conditions, malate </p>

<p>preferentially enters the hydrogenosome and serves as a sub-
strate for hydrogenosomal energy metabolism. However, 
under ÀFe, when hydrogenosomal metabolism is ceased, 
malate is metabolized in the cytosol via pyruvate to lactate. 
Thus, the ability to switch between hydrogenosomal and cyto-
solic malate metabolism seems to be important for the ability 
of trichomonads to quickly adapt to changes in iron availability 
in their environment. Similar changes in carbohydrate metab-
olism were reported in T. vaginalis that had impaired hydro-
genosomal metabolism because of the induction of 
metronidazole resistance (Kulda et al. 1993). 
Besides lactate, T. vaginalis also produces low amount of 
ethanol (Cerkasovová et al. 1986). In our dataset, we identi-
fied two types of alcohol dehydrogenases (ADHs) that differ in 
the metal ion present in the active site of the enzyme. Notably, 
four of five genes coding for the iron-containing ADH were 
upregulated under +Fe conditions, whereas one gene was 
upregulated under ÀFe conditions together with one of two 
genes coding for the zinc-containing ADH (fig. 3). In the 
related organism T. foetus, acetaldehyde that is reduced by 
ADH to ethanol is formed from pyruvate by the enzyme pyru-
vate decarboxylase (Sutak, Tachezy, et al. 2004). However, 
pyruvate decarboxylase activity was not detected in T. vagina-
lis, and the gene encoding this enzyme was not identified in 
the genome (Carlton et al. 2007). Thus, the pathway respon-
sible for the formation of acetaldehyde remains unclear. </p>

<p>Hydrogenosomal Energy Metabolism </p>

<p>Iron increased the transcription of all critical enzymes in hydro-
genosomal carbohydrate catabolism; at least one copy of each 
gene was significantly upregulated (fig. 4 and supplementary 
table S3, Supplementary Material online). PFOR and ME, 
which are the enzymes that catalyze the oxidative decarboxyl-
ation of the hydrogenosomal substrates pyruvate and malate, 
respectively, were the most highly upregulated enzymes of 
the pathway. Three genes encoding PFOR (PFOR-A, BI and 
BII) displayed the highest upregulation observed in the micro-
array analysis (4.01, 3.71, and 3.64, respectively), and also had 
high upregulation scores determined by the EST analysis (32, 
18, and 9, respectively) (supplementary table S2a and c, Sup-
plementary Material online). The gene coding for ME-H was 
the most highly upregulated according to the EST analysis, 
with an upregulation index value of 63 (supplementary 
table S2c, Supplementary Material online). The re-oxidation 
of NADH resulting from ME activity is mediated by heterodi-
meric NADH dehydrogenase (remnant of respiratory complex 
I). The 51 kDa subunit of this enzyme was significantly upre-
gulated under +Fe conditions according to EST analysis, but 
the upregulation of the 24 kDa subunit did not reach the cut-
off limit. Electrons generated by PFOR are transferred via fer-
redoxin to the hydrogenase responsible for the synthesis of 
molecular hydrogen. The genes that code for ferredoxin-1 and 
the 64 kDa [Fe]-hydrogenase were upregulated under +Fe </p>

<p>Table 1 
Fold Changes Detected by qRT-PCR in Comparison with Results of 
Microarray Analysis </p>

<p>TrichDB 1.2 
Accession No. </p>

<p>Annotation 
Microarrays 
Upregulation </p>

<p>Rate* </p>

<p>Fold Change 
Detected by </p>

<p>qRT-PCR** </p>

<p>TVAG_239660 
IscS-2 
NSC 
NSC 
TVAG_251200 
Ferredoxin 6 
NSC 
NSC </p>

<p>TVAG_129940 
IBP39 
1.11 
1.88 
TVAG_348330 
Glycogen phosphorylase 
1.24 
1.95 </p>

<p>TVAG_281070 
Phosphofructokinase 
1.31 
4.62 
TVAG_292710 
Ferredoxin 4 
1.33 
2.89 </p>

<p>TVAG_104250 
Hmp-35-2 
1.56 
2.28 
TVAG_238830 
Malic enzyme B 
1.67 
2.51 </p>

<p>TVAG_198110 
PFO A 
4.01 
24.96 
TVAG_037570 
Iron hydrogenase 64 kDa 
2.48 
109.64 </p>

<p>TVAG_422780 
Alcohol dehydrogenase 
2.57 
31.44 
TVAG_165030 
Malate dehydrogenase 
À1.33 
À1.62 
TVAG_381311 
Lactate dehydrogenase 
À1.81 
À5.02 
TVAG_361540 
IscA-2 
À1.36 
À2.26 
TVAG_008840 
NfU-2 
À1.42 
À1.47 </p>

<p>NOTE.-NSC, no significant change of gene expression. 
*P 0.01. 
**P 0.05. </p>

<p>Horvá thová et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>conditions. Finally, the acetyl-CoA that is generated by PFOR 
activity is used in two steps of ATP synthesis: the reactions 
catalyzed by acetate:succinate-CoA transferase (ASCT) and 
heterodimeric succinyl-CoA synthase (SCS). One of the four 
ASCT genes and all of the genes that encode SCS subunits 
showed significant upregulation under +Fe conditions. </p>

<p>FeS Cluster Assembly </p>

<p>The biosynthesis of the ISCs that are necessary for the matur-
ation of FeS proteins is an indispensable process that occurs in 
the hydrogenosomes of T. vaginalis. In contrast to the com-
ponents of energy metabolism, the ISC assembly machinery 
appeared to be upregulated under ÀFe conditions (fig. 4 and 
supplementary table S3, Supplementary Material online). Our 
screen detected genes that encode two paralogs of the 
scaffold protein IscA, three Nfu paralogs, and the cysteine 
desulfurase IscS-2. Frataxin was previously shown to be </p>

<p>upregulated under ÀFe conditions using a nuclear run-on 
assay (Dolezal et al. 2007). This trend was also observed in 
our analysis, but the cut off limit was not reached (EST upre-
gulation index À2). Interestingly, ÀFe conditions also caused a 
significant increase in the expression of the hydrogenase 
maturase (Hyd-G) that is required for the assembly of the 
hydrogenase-specific H cluster (Putz et al. 2006). Altogether, 
these results suggest a common regulatory mechanism for the 
genes that encode the multiple components of the ISC assem-
bly machinery that are upregulated under ÀFe conditions. This 
regulation might be related to the sensing of an increased 
cellular demand for FeS cluster synthesis during ÀFe 
conditions. </p>

<p>Hydrogenosomal Membrane Proteins </p>

<p>Hydrogenosomes are surrounded by two membranes that 
possess a specific set of proteins that facilitate the exchange </p>

<p>amino acids metabolism </p>

<p>carbohydrate metabolism </p>

<p>cytoskeleton and interacting proteins </p>

<p>FeS clusters assembly </p>

<p>hypothetical proteins </p>

<p>kinases and phosphatases </p>

<p>membrane and vesicular transport </p>

<p>oxidoreductases </p>

<p>peptidases </p>

<p>protein folding and modification </p>

<p>transcription and translation </p>

<p>unknown function </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>+Fe </p>

<p>Number of proteins </p>

<p>Functional category </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>-Fe </p>

<p>Number of proteins </p>

<p>Functional category </p>

<p>microarrays </p>

<p>ESTs </p>

<p>FIG. 2.-Classification of iron-regulated genes by functional category. Numbers of genes that were upregulated under iron-rich (+Fe) and iron-restricted 
(ÀFe) conditions. Results of microarray and EST analysis are represented by open and hatched bars, respectively. Color code of functional categories is given 
in the legend. </p>

<p>Transcriptomic Identification of +Fe and ÀFe Gene Copies </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 4(10):1017-1029. doi:10.1093/gbe/evs078 Advance Access publication September 12, 2012 </p>



<p>Glucose </p>

<p>Glucose </p>

<p>Glucose-6-P </p>

<p>Fructose-6-P </p>

<p>Fructose-1,6-bisP </p>

<p>P 
-
3 
-
e 
d 
y 
h 
e 
d 
l 
a 
r 
e 
c 
y 
l 
G 
P 
-
e 
n 
o 
t 
e 
c 
a 
y 
x 
o 
r 
d 
y 
h 
i 
D </p>

<p>ATP </p>

<p>ADP </p>

<p>ATP </p>

<p>ADP </p>

<p>ATP </p>

<p>ADP </p>

<p>glucokinase </p>

<p>glucose-6-P 
isomerase </p>

<p>Glycogen 
Glucose-1-P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>glycogen 
phosphorylase </p>

<p>P-glucomutase </p>

<p>CELL 
MEMBRANE </p>

<p>PP </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>PFK </p>

<p>fructose-1,6-bisP aldolase </p>

<p>triose-P 
isomerase </p>

<p>1,3-bisP-glycerate </p>

<p>3-P-glycerate </p>

<p>2-P-glycerate </p>

<p>P-enolpyruvate </p>

<p>Pyruvate </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>PP </p>

<p>Oxaloacetate </p>

<p>Malate </p>

<p>PEPCK </p>

<p>malate 
dehydrogenase </p>

<p>CO </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>NADH </p>

<p>NADPH </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Lactate </p>

<p>P-glycerate kinase </p>

<p>pyruvate-P 
dikinase </p>

<p>pyruvate 
kinase </p>

<p>enolase </p>

<p>lactate dehydrogenase 
malic enzyme </p>

<p>glyceraldehyde-3-P 
dehydrogenase </p>

<p>? </p>

<p>acetaldehyde </p>

<p>Ethanol </p>

<p>NAD(P)H </p>

<p>NADH </p>

<p>NAD + </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>NAD(P) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>NADP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>alcohol dehydrogenase </p>

<p>NAD </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>iron 
zinc </p>

<p>NADH 
NAD </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>AMP </p>

<p>ATP </p>

<p>P-glycerate mutase </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>Microarrays 
fold change </p>

<p>-2.1 to -4 </p>

<p>-1.5 to -2 </p>

<p>-5 to -15 </p>

<p>2 to 1.51 </p>

<p>4 to 2.1 </p>

<p>1.5 to 1.3 
15 to 5 </p>

<p>-16 to -30 </p>

<p>-1.3 to -1.5 </p>

<p>unregulated gene </p>

<p>30 to 16 </p>

<p>&gt;-31 </p>

<p>&gt;31 
Fe+ </p>

<p>Fe-</p>

<p>EST analysis 
upregulation index </p>

<p>HYDROGENOSOME </p>

<p>FIG. 3.-Iron-dependent regulation of genes encoding enzymes in glycolytic pathway. Each double square represents a single gene copy. Triangles 
represent the results of the microarray analysis, and circles represent the results of the EST analysis. Upregulation under +Fe and ÀFe conditions is indicated 
by red and green colors, respectively. The empty squares represent detected, but unregulated gene copies. </p>

<p>Horvá thová et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>of metabolites between the cytosol and organelles. We de-
tected four hydrogenosomal membrane proteins [two Hmp35 
and two ADP/ATP carriers (AACs)] that were differentially 
expressed in response to iron availability (supplementary 
table S3, Supplementary Material online). Hmp35, which is 
a unique form of a b-barrel protein that is localized to the 
outer hydrogenosomal membrane, was significantly upregu-
lated under +Fe conditions. Hmp35 is a cysteine-rich protein 
with the cysteine residues clustered near the C terminus, 
where they form a metal-binding motif (Dyall et al. 2003; 
Rada et al. 2011). These structural properties, together with 
the observed upregulation of the protein under +Fe condi-
tions, allow us to speculate that Hmp35 may be involved in 
iron transport. Five members of the mitochondrial carrier pro-
tein family (MCF) that serve as AACs in the inner </p>

<p>hydrogenosomal membrane have been identified (Dyall 
et al. 2000; Rada et al. 2011). In this study, two of these 
proteins showed significant iron-dependent regulation: 
AAC-1 was upregulated under ÀFe conditions, whereas 
AAC-2 was upregulated under +Fe conditions (fig. 4 and sup-
plementary table S3, Supplementary Material online). As 
described earlier, active hydrogenosomal energy metabolism 
is dependent on iron. Under these conditions, a portion of the 
ATP synthesized in the hydrogenosomes is directly used by 
processes such as ISC assembly and HSP-70-dependent pro-
tein transport and maturation. Some ATP could also be ex-
ported by AACs to the cytosol in exchange for ADP as in 
mitochondria. However, ATP is also required for hydrogeno-
somal functions under iron-limiting conditions when the ex-
pression of enzymes necessary for ATP synthesis is ceased. </p>

<p>CoA </p>

<p>Malate 
Malate 
NAD + </p>

<p>NADH </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>2H + </p>

<p>Pyruvate 
Pyruvate </p>

<p>Acetate 
Acetate </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>Succinate 
Succinate-CoA </p>

<p>Pi </p>

<p>ATP 
ADP </p>

<p>Acetyl-CoA </p>

<p>2H 
+ </p>

<p>H 2 
H 2 </p>

<p>H 2 
H 2 </p>

<p>-
fdx </p>

<p>-
fdx </p>

<p>+ 
fdx </p>

<p>+ 
fdx </p>

<p>51kDa 
24kDa </p>

<p>hydrogenase </p>

<p>malic enzyme </p>

<p>ASCT </p>

<p>complex 1 </p>

<p>+ 
fdx </p>

<p>-
fdx </p>

<p>Hydrogenase </p>

<p>IscA </p>

<p>[FeS] </p>

<p>Isd11 
IscS </p>

<p>Cysteine 
Alanine </p>

<p>Fe 
S </p>

<p>frataxin </p>

<p>HydG </p>

<p>Nfu </p>

<p>AAC-2 </p>

<p>Hmp35 </p>

<p>Fe? </p>

<p>Cysteine </p>

<p>Fe </p>

<p>AAC-1 </p>

<p>hydrogenase </p>

<p>Microarrays 
fold change </p>

<p>-2.1 to -4 </p>

<p>-1.5 to -2 </p>

<p>-5 to -15 </p>

<p>2 to 1.51 </p>

<p>4 to 2.1 </p>

<p>1.5 to 1.3 
15 to 5 </p>

<p>-16 to -30 </p>

<p>-1.3 to -1.5 </p>

<p>unregulated gene </p>

<p>30 to 16 </p>

<p>&gt;-31 </p>

<p>&gt;31 
Fe+ </p>

<p>Fe-</p>

<p>EST analysis 
upregulation index </p>

<p>Apoproteins </p>

<p>SCS </p>

<p>PFOR </p>

<p>FIG. 4.-Iron-dependent regulation of hydrogenosomal metabolism. Each double square represents a single gene copy. Triangles represent the results of 
the microarray analysis, and circles represent the results of the EST analysis. Upregulation under +Fe and ÀFe conditions is indicated by red and green colors, 
respectively. The empty squares represent detected, but unregulated gene copies. </p>

<p>Transcriptomic Identification of +Fe and ÀFe Gene Copies </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 4(10):1017-1029. doi:10.1093/gbe/evs078 Advance Access publication September 12, 2012 </p>



<p>Thus, ATP might be imported from the cytosol by AACs. The 
expression of AAC-1 is increased under ÀFe conditions, which 
renders it the most likely candidate for the transportation of 
ATP into hydrogenosomes. </p>

<p>Amino Acid Metabolism </p>

<p>The arginine dihydrolase pathway contributes to energy me-
tabolism in T. vaginalis (Yarlett et al. 1996). Two components 
of the pathway, ornithine carbamoyltransferase and carba-
mate kinase, were significantly upregulated under +Fe condi-
tions (supplementary table S3, Supplementary Material 
online), whereas arginine deiminase, which was recently 
shown to be localized in hydrogenosomes (Morada et al. 
2011), was not regulated by iron availability. 
Methionine can be directly degraded to a-ketobutyrate, 
ammonia, and thiols or converted to homocysteine. These 
two metabolic pathways appear to be regulated by iron in 
opposing manners. Methionine degradation is catalyzed by 
the unique enzyme methionine g-lyase (McKie et al. 1998). 
We found that one of the two genes that encode this enzyme 
was upregulated under +Fe conditions. In contrast, genes that 
encode three components of the homocysteine-forming path-
way (methionine adenosyltransferase, S-adenosyl methionine-
dependent methyltransferase, and S-adenosyl homocysteine 
hydrolase) appear to be upregulated under ÀFe conditions </p>

<p>(fig. 5 and supplementary table S3, Supplementary Material 
online). </p>

<p>Proteases </p>

<p>Multiple proteinases have been found in T. vaginalis (Carlton 
et al. 2007), and many of them have been implicated in the 
virulence of the parasite (Dailey et al. 1990; Ramon-Luing et al. 
2010). The expression of 16 genes coding for cysteine prote-
ases and metallopeptidases was found to be regulated by iron, 
and 9 of these genes were upregulated under ÀFe conditions 
(supplementary table S3, Supplementary Material online). De 
Jesus et al. (2007) used comparative proteomics to show that 
CP3 and the legumain-like cysteine proteinase-1(LEGU1) are 
downregulated under ÀFe conditions, and their results are 
consistent with upregulation of these proteins that we 
observed with EST under +Fe conditions. Kummer et al. 
(2008) isolated an extracellular protein fraction from T. vagi-
nalis that they called CP30 and that contained CP2, CP3, CP4, 
and CPT, and they demonstrated that trichomonads grown 
under ÀFe conditions had increased CP30 fraction protease 
activity. These results are consistent with the increased tran-
scription of CP2 observed in our experiments (supplementary 
table S3, Supplementary Material online), whereas opposite 
trend we obtained for CP3 and CPT (supplementary table S3, 
Supplementary Material online). </p>

<p>methionine </p>

<p>S-adenosyl methionine </p>

<p>S-adenosyl homocysteine </p>

<p>homocysteine </p>

<p>ATP, H O </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Pi,PPi </p>

<p>Methionine adenosyltransferase </p>

<p>Methionine γ-lyase </p>

<p>acceptor </p>

<p>methylated acceptor </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>adenosine </p>

<p>NH , methanthiol </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>α -ketobutyrate </p>

<p>S-adenosyl methionine dep. 
methyltransferase </p>

<p>S-adenosyl homocysteine 
hydrolase </p>

<p>Microarrays 
fold change </p>

<p>-2.1 to -4 </p>

<p>-1.5 to -2 </p>

<p>-5 to -15 </p>

<p>2 to 1.51 </p>

<p>4 to 2.1 </p>

<p>1.5 to 1.3 
15 to 5 </p>

<p>-16 to -30 </p>

<p>-1.3 to -1.5 </p>

<p>unregulated gene </p>

<p>30 to 16 </p>

<p>&gt;-31 </p>

<p>&gt;31 
Fe+ </p>

<p>Fe-</p>

<p>EST analysis 
upregulation index </p>

<p>FIG. 5.-Iron-regulated genes involved in methionine metabolism. Each double square represents a single gene copy. Triangles represent the results of 
the microarray analysis, and circles represent the results of the EST analysis. Upregulation under +Fe and ÀFe conditions is indicated by red and green colors, 
respectively. The empty squares represent detected, but unregulated gene copies. </p>

<p>Horvá thová et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>



<p>Regulation of Transcription </p>

<p>Proteins that are involved in the regulation of transcription 
and translation, including ribosomal proteins and proteins 
that affect DNA metabolism, constitute approximately 10% 
of the iron-regulated genes (fig. 2 and supplementary table 
S3, Supplementary Material online). Of particular interest are 
the Myb-like transcription factors, which are exceptionally 
abundant in the T. vaginalis genome and have been suggested 
to be major regulators of gene transcription (Hsu et al. 2009). 
In our dataset, we detected the expression of 97 Myb-like 
DNA-binding proteins, five of which were significantly regu-
lated by iron. One gene was upregulated under +Fe condi-
tions, and four genes were upregulated under ÀFe conditions 
(supplementary table S3, Supplementary Material online). To 
date, four T. vaginalis Myb-like proteins have been chara-
cterized (Ong et al. 2006, 2007; Hsu et al. 2009; Smith 
et al. 2011). It was demonstrated that the temporal and 
iron-inducible transcription of the ME is regulated by the syn-
ergistic or antagonistic actions of three proteins that can se-
lectively bind to two discrete Myb protein recognition sites in 
the 5 
0 -untranslated regions (5'-UTR) of the ME gene. Myb1 
and Myb2, that play the roles of a repressor and an activator, 
respectively, are able to bind to both sites with affinities that 
differ over time and according to iron availability (Ong et al. 
2006, 2007). Myb3 activates basal and prolonged iron-indu-
cible transcription by binding solely to the MRE1 site (Hsu et al. 
2009). In the T. vaginalis genome, there are three genes that 
encode Myb-3-like proteins, and all three products contain 
conserved base-contacting amino acids. Hsu et al. (2009) </p>

<p>showed that the gene copy TVAG_475500 is upregulated 
under +Fe conditions. In our screen, we detected a second 
copy (TVAG_252420) that was upregulated under ÀFe con-
ditions. We also identified a Myb2 gene; however, under our 
experimental conditions, Myb2 was not regulated by iron, 
which contradicts the findings of Ong et al. (2007). 
Because MRE sites were demonstrated to be essential for 
the iron-dependent regulation of ME, we searched 300 bp of 
the 5 
0 -UTR of all iron-regulated genes detected in our screen 
for the presence of MRE motifs. We found numerous genes 
that had upstream sequences containing the MRE eukaryotic 
consensus sequence (C/T)AACG(G/T) or specific MRE-like sites 
similar to those found in the ME gene (supplementary table 
S4, Supplementary Material online). The genes that contain 
both MRE1/MRE2r and MRE2f in their upstream regions, and 
that have the motifs in the same order as in ME upstream 
region, are listed in table 2. Interestingly, the 5 
0 -UTR of the 
genes that encode ADH, hypothetical protein TVAG_383310 
and thioredoxin reductase contain both elements at positions 
similar to those in the 5 
0 -UTR sequence of the ME gene 
(table 2), which suggests a similar multifarious Myb-mediated 
regulation of transcription. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The 160 Mb T. vaginalis genome is the largest protozoan 
genome that has been sequenced thus far (Carlton et al. 
2007). A unique feature of the Trichomonas genome among 
all sequenced eukaryotes is the massive expansion of many 
gene families and the retention of multiple copies for almost </p>

<p>Table 2 
Iron-Regulated Genes That Contain Both MRE1/MRE2r and MRE2f in Their Upstream Regions </p>

<p>TrichDB 1.2 Accession No. 
Annotation 
MRE1/MRE2r 
MRE2f </p>

<p>+Fe 
ANAACGATA 
TATCGT 
À111/À103 
À59/À54 </p>

<p>TVAG_422780 
Alcohol dehydrogenase 
À136/À129 
À37/À32 </p>

<p>CGATA 
TATCGT 
À107/À103 
À59/À54 </p>

<p>TVAG_035180 
Arp2/3 complex subunit 
À300/À296 
À45/À40 
TVAG_218790 
Conserved hypothetical protein 
À230/À226 
À110/À105 
TVAG_405900 
Phosphoglucomutase 
À286/À282 
À199/À194 </p>

<p>TAACGA 
TATCGTC 
À110/À105 
À59/À53 </p>

<p>TVAG_072120 
Conserved hypothetical protein 
À173/À168 
À19/À13 </p>

<p>ÀFe 
CGATA 
TATCGT 
À107/À103 
À59/À54 </p>

<p>TVAG_383370 
Conserved hypothetical protein 
À114/À110 
À81/À76 
TVAG_474980 
Thioredoxin reductase 
À151/À147 
À107/À102 </p>

<p>NOTE.-The numbers indicate position of the sequence motifs of translation start site. Values in bold indicate position of the motifs in the 5 
0 -UTR of ME (Ong et al. 2006). </p>

<p>Transcriptomic Identification of +Fe and ÀFe Gene Copies </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 4(10):1017-1029. doi:10.1093/gbe/evs078 Advance Access publication September 12, 2012 </p>



<p>all genes (Cui et al. 2010). The mechanistic origins and biolo-
gical functions of these multiple gene copies are yet unknown, 
but it is clear that they provided abundant starting material for 
evolutionary innovation while also contributing to the genetic 
robustness of the organism (Li et al. 2010). Indeed, because 
the T. vaginalis genome appears to be haploid, genetic redun-
dancy might be particularly important to buffer gene muta-
tions. Moreover, the differential expression of paralogous 
copies could be necessary for optimal growth in response to 
various environmental conditions (Giaever et al. 2002). We 
demonstrated that iron, a critical nutrient for T. vaginalis, 
has broad effects on the parasite's trancriptome, which is 
consistent with the observation that iron modulates tricho-
monad growth, metabolic fluxes, and virulence phenotypes 
such as cytoadherence (Mundodi et al. 2006). However, we 
found that in most cases iron regulated the expression of a 
single gene or a portion of the gene copies, whereas the ex-
pression of other paralogous copies of the gene was iron 
independent. 
The strongest iron-dependent upregulation we observed 
was for ME and PFOR, enzymes that play critical roles in hydro-
genosomal energy metabolism and that are known to exhibit 
iron-dependent changes in protein expression and enzyme 
activity (Vanacova et al. 2001; Leitsch et al. 2009. However, 
we also found that there were four gene copies for ME, and 
two for PFOR, whose expression was not iron dependent. Of 
all major enzymes involved in hydrogenosomal energy metab-
olism, only SCS, which mediates the final step of ATP synthe-
sis, appears to be an exception in that the expression of all 
copies of both SCS subunits was iron dependent. Further stu-
dies of expression profiles for cells grown under various con-
ditions such as the absence of external glucose, temperature 
or oxygen stress, the induction of the amoeboid form or com-
parison with nonpathogenic forms should lead to further in-
sights as to how individual copies among the myriad 
trichomonad gene families have come to fall under differential 
iron regulation during evolution. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Supplementary figure S1 and tables S1-S4 are available 
at Genome Biology and Evolution online (http://www.gbe 
.oxfordjournals.org/). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank M. Marcinčiková for technical support and 
J. Horvá th for the development of the sequence motif search-
ing software. This work was supported by the Czech Ministry 
of Education grants [MSM0021620858, LC07032] to J.T. and 
the Charles University GAUK 179/2006/B-BIO/PrF to L.Š . The 
T. vaginalis EST sequencing project was supported by the </p>

<p>
Horvá thová et al. </p>

<p>GBE </p>





<p>Transcriptomic Identification of +Fe and ÀFe Gene Copies </p>

<p>GBE </p>

<p>Genome Biol. Evol. 4(10):1017-1029. doi:10.1093/gbe/evs078 Advance Access publication September 12, 2012 </p>



</text></tei>