<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3278723" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Circadian oscillation and cell cycle progression are the two most essential rhythmic events present in almost all organisms. 
Circadian rhythms keep track of time and provide temporal regulation with a period of about 24 h. The cell cycle is optimized for 
growth and division, but not for time keeping. Circadian gated cell divisions are observed in nearly all organisms. However, the 
implications of this coupling to the physiology of mammals are unknown. A mutation (S662G) in the clock protein PERIOD2 
(PER2) is responsible for familial advanced sleep phase syndrome in which sleep onset occurs in the early evening and 
wakefulness occurs in the early morning. Here, we provide evidence that the PER2 
S662 mutation leads to enhanced resistance to 
X-ray-induced apoptosis and increased E1A-and RAS-mediated oncogenic transformation. Accordingly, the PER2 
S662 mutation 
affects tumorigenesis in cancer-sensitized p53 
R172H/ þ mice. Finally, analyzing the clock-controlled cell cycle genes p21, c-Myc, 
Cyclin D1 and p27, we found that the relative phases between p21 and Cyclin D expression profiles have been changed 
significantly in these Per2 allele mutant mouse embryonic fibroblasts. This key role of the Per2-mediated phase alteration of p21 
provides what we believe to be a novel mechanism in understanding cell cycle progression, its plasticity and its resistance to 
interference. 
The circadian clock is essential for the maintenance of 
physiological homeostasis, as well as the coordination of 
responses to external signals. In mammals, the circadian clock 
is composed of interlocking positive and negative feedback 
loops. In the primary feedback loop, three basic helix-loop-helix 
(bHLH)/PAS domain-containing transcription factors, Clock, 
Npas2 and Bmal1, activate the transcription of two period genes 
(Per1 and Per2) and two cryptochrome (Cry) genes (Cry1 and 
Cry2) by binding to the E-box cis elements in the promoters of 
these genes. Subsequently, the PER/CRY complex inhibits the 
transcription of its own genes by blocking BMAL1/CLOCK 
activity. The second feedback loop is mediated by the orphan 
nuclear receptors RORa and Rev-erba. Transcription of RORa 
and Rev-erba is activated during the day by the CLOCK/BMAL1 
complex, after which they exert positive and negative transcrip-
tional effects on the Bmal1 gene through Rev-erba/RORa 
responsive elements (ROREs) in the Bmal1 promoter. 
These two authors contributed equally to this work. 
Mutation of S662 promotes oncogenic E1A-RAS-
induced transformation in MEFs. A previous study has 
shown that primary embryo fibroblasts can be immortalized 
by the expression of at least two oncogenes; for example, 
E1A, myc and ras. 
20 This technique has been used to 
evaluate whether inactivation or deletion of a tumor 
suppressor gene can hasten the activation of oncogenes 
and promote oncogenic transformation. 
21 To determine 
whether the PER2 
S662 mutation results in a transformation-
permissive phenotype in vitro, PER2 
S662G , PER2 
S662D , wild-
type and Per2 
À/À MEFs were infected with a retroviral vector 
that co-expressed the oncogenes E1a and Ras. The ability of 
E1a and Ras to induce cellular transformation was far greater 
in PER2 
S662G mice than in wild-type MEFs, while the level of 
transformation was comparable to that of Per2 KO MEFs 
(Figures 4a and b). Furthermore, consistent with the 
phenotype shown for X-ray-induced apoptosis, PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>MEFs formed more colonies than PER2 
S662G and Per2 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>MEFs (Figures 4a and b). Finally, we assessed whether 
overexpression of wild-type PER2 could trigger cellular 
transformation. As expected, the MEFs with a high-copy 
number of Per2 from H line grew more colonies than 
those with a low-copy number of Per2 or wild-type MEFs, 
but they grew fewer colonies than PER2 
S662D mutant MEFs 
(Figures 4c and d). The numbers for E1a-and Ras-induced 
transformation foci are 310±107 for PER2 
S662D , 205±52 for 
H line, 158 ± 25 for Per2 
À/À , 150 ± 36 for PER2 
S662G , 96 ± 24 
for L line, 74 ± 35 for wild type and 8 ± 5 for no-transfection 
control. These mice are on a wild-type background because 
of technical difficulty getting all embryos from seven </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, cell cycle and tumorigenesis 
X Gu et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>genotype mice on a Per2 
À/À background at one time. These 
findings are consistent with the apoptotic responses 
observed after X-ray exposure. Furthermore, similar 
transformation rates between PER2 
S662G on wild-type 
background and Per2 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>MEFs suggest that PER2 
S662G is 
not just a loss of function mutation but has a dominant role. 
Altogether, these results illustrate the importance of the S662 
site and of maintaining an appropriate level of PER2 to 
mediate the cellular response to environmental mutagens. </p>

<p>Mutations in PER2 
S662 accelerate tumorigenesis in 
p53 
R172H/ þ background mice. The influence of PER2 </p>

<p>S662 </p>

<p>mutations on both X-ray-induced apoptosis and in vitro 
transformation led us to assess the relevance of the 
PER2 
S662 mutation with regard to tumorigenesis in vivo. It 
has been noted that a mutation in one or more core clock 
genes is not sufficient to elicit increased tumor incidence in 
the absence of a cancer-sensitized genetic background. </p>

<p>22   As the PER2 
S662 mutation is found in a human circadian 
variant, we mated PER2 
S662 mutant mice with p53 </p>

<p>R172H </p>

<p>knock-in mice. These knock-in mice have a mutation </p>

<p>that corresponds to the p53 
R175H hot spot in human 
cancers. 
16 Through breeding, we established cohorts of 
p53 </p>

<p>R172H/ þ </p>

<p>(n ¼ 54), PER2 
S662G2H :p53 </p>

<p>R172H/ þ </p>

<p>(n ¼ 41), 
PER2 </p>

<p>S662D2H </p>

<p>:p53 
R172H/ þ (n ¼ 31) and Clock 
D19/ þ :p53 </p>

<p>R172H/ þ </p>

<p>(n ¼ 29) compound mutant mice. These mice all had the same 
genetic background of C57BL/6. We monitored these mice for 
tumor development and survival for up to 700 days. As shown 
in Figure 5a, Kaplan-Meier overall survival curves of these 
compound mutant mice showed slight but significant differ-
ences (log-rank test, P ¼ 0.049). A closer inspection of the 
data revealed that the survival of female p53 
R172H/ þ and 
Clock 
D19/ þ :p53 
R172H/ þ mice was decreased markedly com-
pared with that of male mice (Supplementary Figures S1A and 
B). But the survival of PER2 
S662G2H :p53 </p>

<p>R172H/ þ </p>

<p>and 
PER2 
S662D2H :p53 
R172H/ þ mice did not show any gender-
based differences (Supplementary Figures S1C and 1D). 
Thus, to further dissociate the effects of the PER2 </p>

<p>S662 </p>

<p>mutation on tumor development, we assessed male and 
female survival curves separately. The survival curve for 
males was significantly affected by circadian gene mutations 
(Figure 5b, log-rank test, Po0.001). The median life spans </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>ZT 0 
ZT 9 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>ZT 0 </p>

<p>ZT 9 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
0 
200 
400 
600 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Per2 
-/-PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>/Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>/Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>/Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>/Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>WT Per2 
-/-PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>/Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>/Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>/Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>/Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>PI fluorescence </p>

<p>Cell count </p>

<p>Cell count </p>

<p>Cell count </p>

<p>Cell count </p>

<p>Percentages of apoptotic cells </p>

<p>Percentages of apoptotic cells </p>

<p>PI fluorescence </p>

<p>Ap 
Ap </p>

<p>Ap 
Ap </p>

<p>Ap 
Ap </p>

<p>33.1% </p>

<p>Ap </p>

<p>37% </p>

<p>Ap </p>

<p>17.3% 
17.2% </p>

<p>15.5% 
16.5% </p>

<p>9.05% 
9.9% </p>

<p>Data.010 
Data.001 </p>

<p>Data.008 
Data.003 </p>

<p>Data.006 
Data.002 </p>

<p>Data.004 
Data.008 </p>

<p>Figure 1 The PER2 
S662 mutation leads to decreased levels of apoptosis. (a) Wild-type, Per2 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>, PER2 
S662G :Per2 
À/À and PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>:Per2 
À/À mice were irradiated with 
6 Gy X-rays at ZT 0 (0800 hours) and ZT 9 (1700 hours). Spleen cells were isolated 6 h after irradiation, stained with propidium iodide (PI) and analyzed by flow cytometry. One 
representative experiment is shown. Ap, apoptotic percentage. (b) Percentages of apoptotic cells measured by flow cytometry are shown in the histograms. Experiments were 
repeated at least three times with consistent results and at least two mice were used per group for each time (N ¼ 3 for each genotype; ***Po0.001; one-way ANOVA 
followed by Dunnett's test) </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, cell cycle and tumorigenesis 
X Gu et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>were also reduced for male PER2 
S662D2H :p53 
R172H/ þ (15.0 
months) and PER2 
S662G2H :p53 
R172H/ þ (16.6 months) mice 
compared with those of male p53 
R172H/ þ (17.9 months) and 
Clock 
D19/ þ :p53 
R172H/ þ (19.8 months) mice (Figure 5b). As 
tumors in p53 
R172H/ þ mice arise after a similar length 
of latency, these differences in the survival curves and 
median life spans reflected changes that contributed to 
tumorigenesis. 
This raises the question of why female and male on a 
p53 
R172H/ þ background have different survival rates, and 
why we did not observe a difference between 
PER2 
S6622H :p53 
R172H/ þ 2 and p53 
R172H/ þ female mice, in 
contrast to the male mice. Of note, we did not obtain any 
p53 
R172H/R172H female homozygous mice from 75 pups 
(Supplementary Table 1), and we found that they all died by 
13.5 days as a result of fatal embryonic exencephaly 
(Figure 6). These findings are consistent with a previous 
reporting that lack of the tumor suppressor protein p53 causes 
a female-specific disruption of neural tube closure associated 
with embryonic or neonatal death. 
23 This suggests that female 
p53 
R172H/ þ mice may have a penetrant phenotype that could 
have masked the effects of PER2 
S662 mutations on female 
tumorigenesis. These data demonstrate collectively that the 
PER2 
S662 mutation has an impact on tumor development in 
the p53 
R172H/ þ mutant background. </p>

<p>Circadian cycle length is not tightly associated with 
tumorigenesis. Then, we tested whether the accelerated 
tumorigenesis caused by PER2 
S662 mutation was related to 
the alteration in circadian period. As shown in Supplementary 
Figures 2A and B, the p53 
R172H/ þ mutation did not 
affect the circadian period or the expression of core 
clock genes. Furthermore, in the PER2 
S662G2H : 
p53 
R172H/ þ , 
PER2 
S662D2H :p53 </p>

<p>R172H/ þ </p>

<p>and 
Clock </p>

<p>D19/ </p>

<p>þ :p53 
R172H/ þ mice, circadian period was not closely 
related to tumor development (Figure 5a and 
Supplementary Figure S2C). 
The most common tumor types observed in mice of the 
above genotypes are lymphomas and sarcomas, consistent 
with the reported tumor ratio of p53 
R172H/ þ mice (Supple-
mentary Figure S3). 
16 It is noteworthy that the incidence of 
primary hepatic malignancy and metastatic tumors was 
increased in PER2 </p>

<p>S662G2H </p>

<p>:p53 </p>

<p>R172H/ þ </p>

<p>(27.3%) and 
PER2 
S662D2H :p53 
R172H/ þ mice (19.4%) compared with that 
in p53 
R172H/ þ mice (8.7%), although it did not reach statistical 
significance (P ¼ 0.17) (Table 1). We observed that circadian 
cycle length was also not associated with certain types of 
tumors (Table 1). These results support the notion that 
mutation of PER2 at S662 promotes tumorigenesis, 
independent of the acceleration or deceleration of the 
circadian clock. </p>

<p>Per2 
low copies </p>

<p>Per2 
middle copies </p>

<p>Per2 
high copies </p>

<p>ATG 
TGA </p>

<p>FLAGTag </p>

<p>Wild-type PER2 BAC Transgenic Vector </p>

<p>τ = 23.6 
τ = 24.3 
τ = 25 </p>

<p>LD </p>

<p>DD </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Relative mRNA levels </p>

<p>PER2S662G 
PER2S662D 
L </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>CT </p>

<p>H line </p>

<p>PER2 
S662D </p>

<p>20 
10 
5 
2 
0 
L 
M 
H </p>

<p>130 kd </p>

<p>250 kd </p>

<p>130 kd </p>

<p>250 kd </p>

<p>Standard copy number 
Transgenic mice </p>

<p>Relative genome copy </p>

<p>L 
M 
H </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>Relative mRNA levels </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>Relative mRNA levels </p>

<p>MEFs 
day2 </p>

<p>MEFs 
day3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>L 
M 
H </p>

<p>2 
8 
14 
20 
CT 2 
8 
14 
20 </p>

<p>CT 
2 
8 
14 
20 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Generation and characterization of PER2 BAC transgenic mice. (a) Generation of different copy BAC transgenic mice. (b) Transgene copy number was 
estimated by Southern blot by comparing with copy standards. Experiments were repeated two times with consistent results and one mouse was used per line. (c) The relative 
transgene copy number was further estimated by q-PCR. (d-f) The mRNA expression level was assessed by qRT-PCR in liver tissues (d), spleen tissues (e) and non-
synchronized MEFs (f) of different BAC transgenic mice as indicated genotypes. Experiments were repeated independently at least three times with consistent results and at </p>

<p>least two replicates were used per time point. '-' denotes the band of PER2 and ' * ' denotes a unspecific band. (g) PER2 protein levels in spleen tissues of H line and </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>. Experiments were repeated three times with consistent results, and one mouse for each time point was used for western blot. (h) Voluntary locomotor activities 
were recorded as wheel-running activity. BAC transgenic mice were subjected first to LD (light and dark cycle) and then released into DD (dark and dark cycle). Representative 
actograms from low-(23.64±0.11, n ¼ 6), middle-(24.34±0.18, n ¼ 7) and high-copy BAC transgenic mice (25.07±0.17, n ¼ 9). Alternating white and dark bars indicate 
the LD cycles during entrainment before release in DD </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, cell cycle and tumorigenesis 
X Gu et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>PER2 
S662 affects changes in the relative phases of clock-
controlled cell cycle gene. To understand the mechanism 
underlying tumorigenesis, the clock-related cell cycle genes </p>

<p>p21, c-Myc, Cyclin D1 and p27 were assayed in Per2 
allele mutant MEFs. Unexpectedly, in several independent 
experiments, the expression levels of these circadian-related </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 
200 400 
600 
0 
200 400 
600 
0 200 400 
600 </p>

<p>Low Copy 
Middle Copy 
High Copy </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 
ZT 9 </p>

<p>WT 
Per2 dose </p>

<p>Cell Count </p>

<p>Percentages of </p>

<p>Apotosis cells </p>

<p>PI fluorescence 
PI fluorescence 
PI fluorescence </p>

<p>36.3% 
35.7% 
28.5% </p>

<p>Data.001 
Data.004 
Data.009 </p>

<p>Figure 3 High-dose PER2 results in resistance to apoptosis induced by X-rays. (a) Low-, middle-and high-copy PER2 mice were irradiated with 6 Gy X-rays at ZT 9. 
Spleen cells were isolated 6 h after irradiation and the DNA content was analyzed by flow cytometry. One representative experiment is shown. (b) Percentages of apoptotic 
cells detected by flow cytometry from low-, middle-and high-copy BAC transgenic spleens (***Po0.001; one-way ANOVA followed by Dunnett's test) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Foci Numbers </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &gt; 0.05 </p>

<p>WT 
Low High </p>

<p>E1a+Ras </p>

<p>High Copy </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>Foci Numbers </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Mock 
E1a+Ras 
Vector only </p>

<p>E1a+Ras </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>WT </p>

<p>PER2 
S662G </p>

<p>PER2 
S662D </p>

<p>Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>WT PER2 
S662G </p>

<p>PER2 
S662D </p>

<p>Per2 
KO </p>

<p>Low Copy </p>

<p>Per2 copy </p>

<p>Figure 4 Dysregulation of PER2 increases formation of oncogenic E1A-RAS-mediated foci in MEFs. (a) and (c) Passage 0 MEFs with the indicated genotypes were 
infected with retroviruses encoding E1A-RAS. Transfections with empty virus vector were used as negative controls. Two representative culture plates are shown per 
genotype from at least two repeated independent experiments. (b) and (d) The numbers of foci per 60-mm plate in the assays are expressed as means±S.D. (N ¼ 6 for each 
group; one-way ANOVA followed by Dunnett's test) </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, cell cycle and tumorigenesis 
X Gu et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>cell cycle regulators are not significantly different in Per2 
allele mutant MEFs compared with the wild-type (Figure 7 
and Supplementary Figure S4). We noticed that p21 
transcripts show peak levels when Cyclin D attains trough 
levels in the wild-type MEFs. However, the relative phases of 
p21 and Cyclin D appear to be highly similar in these Per2 
allele mutant MEFs in contrast to the wild-type MEFs. It is 
important to note that p21 transcript phases are delayed in 
Per2 allele mutant MEFs, which may bring changes in the 
relative phases between p21 and Cyclin D (Figure 7). </p>

<p>For the p21 gene, it has been described previously that its 
regulatory region contains a RORE binding site and is 
regulated by the antagonistic activities of the orphan nuclear 
receptors NR1D1/2 and NR1F1. 
24 The question then arises 
as to whether NR1D1 mediates the p21 phase shifting. 
Therefore, we examined the transcription profiles of Nr1d1 to 
compare the results obtained from p21 and Cyclin D. We 
found the accumulation of Nr1d11 cycles with an antiphase to 
that of p21 transcription in the wild-type MEFs, indicating that 
NR1D1 inhibits the transcription of p21 expression as </p>

<p>% Survival Probability </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
8 0 
100 </p>

<p>PER2S662D/ 
p53R172H </p>

<p>p53R172H </p>

<p>Clock/ 
p53R172H </p>

<p>P = 0.049 </p>

<p>Time (weeks) </p>

<p>PER2S662G/ 
p53R172H 
n = 41 </p>

<p>n = 31 </p>

<p>n = 29 </p>

<p>n = 54 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Time (weeks) </p>

<p>Time (weeks) </p>

<p>% Survival Probability </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>P = 0.000 </p>

<p>PER2S662D/ 
p53R172H </p>

<p>PER2S662G/ 
p53R172H </p>

<p>p53R172H </p>

<p>Clock/ 
p53R172H </p>

<p>n = 15 </p>

<p>n = 16 </p>

<p>n = 18 </p>

<p>n = 34 </p>

<p>+ 10.6% 
-16.2% 
-7.8% </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 
8 0 
1 0 0 </p>

<p>Figure 5 PER2 
S662 mutations increased tumor incidence in the p53 
R172H/ þ background. (a) Overall survival. (b) Male survival. Survival curves (Kaplan-Meier 
representation) of the indicated mouse cohorts. n ¼ number of mice per genotype. The survival curves are plotted with respect to the number of weeks using <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> software. 
Statistical significance was assessed using the log-rank test and is indicated (P-value). Alterations in median life span of the indicated genotypes relative to control (increase as 
plus or decrease as minus) are labeled </p>

<p>p53 
+/+ ; 
p53 
R172H/+ ; </p>

<p>p53 R172H/+ ; 
p53 
R172H/R172H ; </p>

<p>p53 
R172H/R172H ; 
p53 
R172H/R172H ; </p>

<p>p53 R172H/+ ; 
p53 
R172H/+ ; </p>

<p>p53 
R172H/R172H ; </p>

<p>p53 R172H/+ ; </p>

<p>Figure 6 Female-specific neural tube defects in p53 
R172H/R172H mice. (a) p53 
R172H/R172H female embryos develop exencephaly, which results from a failure of neural tube 
defects. This is a represent from 13.5-day mouse embryo from p53 
R172H/ þ and p53 
R172H/ þ crosses. Two p53 
R172H/R172H females all develop exencephaly (arrow). (b) HE 
staining for female embryo neural tubes with exencephaly (arrow) </p>

<p>Table 1 Tumor spectrum analysis of PER2 </p>

<p>S662G2H </p>

<p>:p53 
R172H/+ , PER2 </p>

<p>S662D2H </p>

<p>:p53 
R172H/+ and p53 
R172H/+ mice </p>

<p>Tumor types 
p53 </p>

<p>R172H </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G2H </p>

<p>:p53 </p>

<p>R172H </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662D2H </p>

<p>:p53 </p>

<p>R172H </p>



<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, cell cycle and tumorigenesis 
X Gu et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>described previously. 
24 While in these mutant MEFs, p21 
expression profiles are uncoupled at least in part from Nr1d1 
expression (Figure 7), thereby offering the possibility that 
NR1D1 needs wild-type PER2 to regulate the phase of p21 
expression. In addition, as shown in Figure 7, the cycles of 
Nr1d1 transcripts respond to intrinsic circadian period in these 
mutant MEFs, while the periods of p21 and Cyclin D seem to 
be fixed 24 h in these mutant MEFs no matter whether they 
own short or long circadian period. Moreover, the phases of 
p21 transcripts delay to the same extend in Per2 allele mutant 
MEFs, suggesting that the ability of the circadian control of 
p21 expression has been abolished when PER2 is mutated, 
which is mediated mainly through NR1D1. This assumption is 
supported by a recent study by Isabelle Schmutz et al. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>demonstrating that PER2 coordinates circadian output by 
interacting with NR1D1. 
The p21 protein inhibits the activity of cyclin-CDK2 or -CDK4 
complexes, and functions as a regulator of cell cycle progression 
at G1. 
25 Although the p21 expression levels in these PER2 
mutant MEFs remains comparable to that of wild-type MEFs, 
the peak of p21 is locked to the abnormal region that overlaps 
with the peak of the cyclin D phase. It is conceivable that the 
p21/cyclin D interval variations may trigger cell cycle progression. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The physiological relevance of the PER2 
S662 mutation to 
human cancer. In this study, we provided evidence that the 
human PER2 
S662G mutation, which causes the FASPS 
circadian variant, is also responsible for increased cancer 
risk. To our knowledge, this represents the first instance of 
experimental evidence that links a human circadian mutation </p>

<p>to cancer risk. Although the cancer incidence data in FASPS 
individuals are unavailable owing to scarcity of sampling (one 
family), a missense mutation in the evolutionarily conserved 
residue of hPER2 (L823V) has been identified in some human 
breast cancer samples 
26 and altered PER2 expression is 
common in human breast malignancies. 
27,28 By comparing the 
X-ray-induced apoptosis level and transformation rate among 
Per2 
À/À , PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, PER2 
S662D and PER2 dose-dependent 
BAC transgenic mice, we suggested that PER2 
S662G is a 
dominant negative mutation and PER2 
S662D gains extra 
function to prevent apoptosis and increase transformation 
rate. Interestingly, the functional alternations of PER2 
S662G and 
PER2 
S662D displayed in the aspect of cell cycle are different 
from that in circadian clock, because PER2 
S662G mice show 
shorter circadian period length than Per2 
À/À mice and 
PER2 
S662D might elongate the circadian period through 
increasing PER2 protein level. Furthermore, our data that 
overexpressing and knockout PER2 both trigger more 
transformation foci and affect normal apoptosis function 
suggest that maintaining an optimal level of PER2 is critical 
to reduce the risk of tumorigenesis. Our functional studies of 
human variants of PER2, together with unbiased analyses in 
human cancer by other groups, indicate the importance of 
PER2 in human tumorigenesis. But the hypothesis that the 
FASPS mutation increases cancer risk in humans remains to 
be tested in future. </p>

<p>Impaired gene expression or impaired circadian 
rhythms? Previous work has demonstrated that the 
PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>and PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>mutations give rise to 
completely contrary circadian phenotypes in terms of 
circadian period, phase and amplitude; 
15 thus, we predicted </p>

<p>Nr1d1 </p>

<p>p21 </p>

<p>CyclinD </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662D </p>

<p>Per2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>H line 
Wild-type </p>

<p>CT 13 16 19 21 24 27 30 33 36 39 CT13 16 19 21 24 27 30 33 36 39 CT 13 16 19 21 24 27 30 33 36 39 CT 13 16 19 21 24 27 30 33 36 39 CT13 16 19 21 24 27 30 33 36 39 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Relative mRNA levels </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Relative mRNA levels </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Relative mRNA levels </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Figure 7 The relative phases of cell cycle genes are shifted by PER2 mutations. Wild-type and different PER2 mutant MEFs were synchronized by a dexamethasone 
treatment, and RNA was extracted at 3 h intervals stating 10 h after the shock. p21, Cyclin D1 and Nr1d1 expression analysis were done by q-PCR. Experiments were 
repeated independently at least three times with consistent results. Plotted values are the mean values ± S.D. Cosinor analysis was performed on mRNA profiles using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">17.0</rs>. The amplitude and acrophase obtained from cosinor analysis were further analyzed by Students t-test. The null hypothesis was rejected at Po0.05 </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, cell cycle and tumorigenesis 
X Gu et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p>that the PER2 
S662G and PER2 
S662D mutant mice should have 
contrary cancer risks if impaired rhythm is the culprit. 
However, 
the 
enhanced 
cancer 
risk 
in 
both 
PER2 
S662G2H :p53 </p>

<p>R172H/ þ </p>

<p>and PER2 
S662D2H :p53 </p>

<p>R172H/ þ </p>

<p>mice strongly suggested that the impaired PER2 gene, not 
the impaired circadian rhythm, is responsible for the 
increased cancer risk in these mice. This observation is 
further 
supported 
by 
survival 
data 
from 
the 
PER2 
S662D2H :p53 
R172H/ þ and Clock 
D19/ þ :p53 
R172H/ þ mice, 
both of which exhibited lengthened circadian periods, but 
showed highly contrary cancer risks. Interestingly, the 
'impaired gene' theory is consistent with the observation 
from cancer risks in Cry1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>:Cry2 
À/À mice 
22,29 and Clock </p>

<p>D19 </p>

<p>mutant mice. 
30 In addition, we wish to point out that our 
experiments share an important similarity with the above-
mentioned investigations; all of these experimental systems 
retain the circadian mutant mice on normal light/dark cycles 
and subject these mice to entrainment from external time 
cues. Accordingly, the 'impaired gene' theory may only apply 
to circadian mutant mice kept in normal light/dark cycles. 
Circadian disruption is not as intense or detrimental in normal 
cycles as the disruption experienced by shift workers. In this 
regard, an important future direction may focus on both the 
respective contribution and the composite consequence of 
disrupted circadian genes, as well as disrupted circadian 
rhythm to cancer risk in persistent phase-shifted schedules. </p>

<p>The cell cycle, circadian clock and relative 
phase. Recent studies have shown that the circadian clock 
is coupled to the cell cycle processes through clock-
controlled genes, which may contain E-box or ROR 
elements in their promoters. Somewhat surprisingly, 
although we found that deregulation of PER2 has a strong 
effect on the induced transformation of MEFs and 
tumorigenesis; the gene expression changes in these 
clock-controlled genes are less profound in Per2 allele 
mutant MEFs. This leads us to think about their phase 
implication. Although the Nr1d1 transcripts displayed obvious 
phase shift and period length changes in these mutant 
MEFS, p21 transcripts displayed fixed 24-h-period oscillation 
with phase delay to the same extent, leading to a similar 
phase to that of Cyclin D. It indicates that in the wide-type 
MEFs, the opposite phases of p21 and Cyclin D are a result 
of coordination between circadian clock and cell cycle, with 
circadian clock adjusting transcription phase of p21 and the 
main driver of cell cycle. With the interaction of PER2, 
NR1D1 may be a critical circadian factor in exerting the 
phase adjusting function. At present, the physiological 
significance of the altered phases of these genes is 
unclear, and the phase shifting cannot explain all the 
phenotypes that are seen in these mutant mice. It is likely 
that modifier relative phases between the cycle genes 
influence features such as the number of transformation 
foci and the development of the tumor-associated fibroblasts. 
One of the possibilities comes from interfering with phase 
locking. Oscillation-based synchrony is the most energy-
efficient physical mechanism for temporal coordination. It 
occurs in many biological systems, including two oscillators 
of cell division and the circadian phase 
31 or within a cell cycle 
oscillator through multiple regulatory interactions. 
32 It is </p>

<p>conceivable that, if phase-coupled p21 appears at a later 
phase of the inhibitory cycle while Cyclin D remains 
unchanged, the corresponding inhibition of the CDK 
complex becomes weak. In other words, if the threshold is 
reached, CDK activation can initialize unexpected cell cycle 
progression. It would be interesting, therefore, to investigate 
the extent to which relative phase changes might affect cell 
cycle progression, transformation and tumorigenesis. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods 
Animals. Mice were observed daily and killed when they showed signs of 
morbidity or tumor growth in accordance to the Guidelines for Human Endpoints for 
Animals Used in Biomedical Research. Mice were housed in an Assessment And 
Accreditation Of Laboratory Animal Care credited SPF animal facility. 
PER2 </p>

<p>S662G5H </p>

<p>:p53 
R175H/ þ , PER2 </p>

<p>S662D5H </p>

<p>: p53 
R175H/ þ , Clock 
D19/ þ :p53 </p>

<p>R175H/ þ </p>

<p>mice and their littermates were derived from PER2 
S662 mutants and Clock </p>

<p>D19 </p>

<p>mutants 
33 by crossing with p53 
R175H/ þ mice. All mutant animals have been 
backcrossed for more than 10 generations onto a C57BL/6 inbred background. 
Low-, middle-and high-copy PER2 BAC transgenic mice were generated, as 
described previously. 
15 Locomotor activity and activity pattern analyses were 
performed, as described previously. </p>

<p>34   X-ray and flow cytometer. Mice were radiated at the indicated ZT times with 
a single dose of 6 Gy (100 cGy/min) with a XHA600C Medical Electron Linear Accelerator 
(Shinva Medical Instrument Co., Ltd, Zibo, Shandong, China). Splenic lymphocytes were 
isolated at 6 h after irradiation, and red cells were removed using Gey's solution. For flow 
cytometer analyses, splenic lymphocytes were centrifuged at 1000 r.p.m., and the 
supernatants were thoroughly removed by aspiration and fixed in 70% ethanol. After 
incubation with 40 mg/ml propidium iodide and 100 mg/ml RNase at 37 1C for 30 min, the 
samples were analyzed with a Becton Dickinson FACScan flow cytometer using 
<rs type="software">CellQuest</rs> software (Becton Dickinson, Auckland, New Zealand). </p>

<p>Retroviral transfection and focus formation assays. The Plate-E 
virus packaging cells were transfected with the retroviral vector pMXs carrying the 
cDNA encoding E1A and Ras or pMXs with GFP as the control using PEI as the 
transfection reagent. 
35 Culture media collected 2 days after transfection were used 
for infection. MEFs were isolated from 13.5-day embryos as described. P1 MEFs 
were incubated with fresh virus for 6 h. One day after infection, the medium was 
replaced with fresh DMEM supplemented with 5% fetal bovine serum and 
purimycin, and the cells were selected after another 48 h. The infection efficiency 
was 495%, as estimated by a control experiment. After selection, the cells were 
plated at 1 Â 10 
6 cells/6 cm 
2 for 14 days. The medium was changed every 2 days. 
Confluent monolayer cultures with foci were rinsed with phosphate buffered saline 
(PBS), fixed in 10% formalin and stained with 0.1% crystal violet for 20 min; 
subsequently, the colonies were scored. </p>

<p>Tumorigenesis. Cohorts of mice were monitored carefully for signs of 
morbidity or obvious tumor burden. Mice with visible neoplasms around 2 cm in 
diameter were killed and necropsied. Mice with ill health but no visible neoplasms 
were monitored carefully for signs of morbidity. Moribund mice or mice that died 
without signs of morbidity were also necropsied. In most cases, tumor-burdened 
mice could be identified through necropsy and all tissues with suspected gross 
lesions or neoplasms were further examined by histopathological examination. 
Samples were fixed in neutral buffered formalin. Tissues with osseous structure 
were decalcified with 10% hydrochloric acid. Paraffin sections were prepared and 
stained with hematoxylin and eosin following standard procedures. Tumor spectrum 
analysis was performed blindly with the assistance of a clinical pathologist. </p>

<p>Q-PCR and reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR). Primers are listed 
in Supplementary Table 2. All procedures were carried out as previously 
described. </p>

<p>34   Western blotting. Tissue proteins were prepared as described previously 
using a nuclear extraction kit at the indicated circadian time (Active Motif, Carlsbad, 
CA, USA). Rabbit anticyclin E and antiPPARa (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa 
Cruz, CA, USA) were utilized for western blotting according to the manufacturer's 
suggested protocol. </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, cell cycle and tumorigenesis 
X Gu et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

<p><rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">17.0</rs></p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. We thank David Weaver for reading the paper and 
giving insightful comments. We appreciate JS Takahashi for Clock mice and Fu &amp; 
Ptáèek labs for PER2S662 transgenic mice. This work was funded by the National 
Science Foundation of China, the Distinguished Young Scholar Foundation 
(30725011 to YX), (10971152 to LY) and Ministry of Science and Technology 
(2010CB945102 to YX). </p>



<p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
License. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on Cell Death and Differentiation website (http://www.nature.com/cdd) </p>

<p>PER2 </p>

<p>S662G </p>

<p>, cell cycle and tumorigenesis 
X Gu et al </p>



<p>Cell Death and Differentiation </p>

</text></tei>