<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3821792" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR-4) is well known for its host innate immunity. Despite the 
fact that TLR-4 activation confers antitumor responses; emerging evidence suggests that TLR-4 
is associated with tumor development and progression. It is now clear that overactivation of 
TLR-4, through various immune mediators, may cause immune response dysfunction, resulting 
in tumorigenesis. Different cancers could have different extents of TLR-4 involvement during 
tumorigenesis or tumor progression. In this review, we focus on infection-and inflammation-
related TLR-4 activation in noncancer and cancer cells, as well as on the current evidence about 
the role of TLR-4 in ten of the most common cancers, viz, head and neck cancer, lung cancer, 
gastrointestinal cancer, liver cancer, pancreatic cancer, skin cancer, breast cancer, ovarian 
cancer, cervical cancer, and prostate cancer. 
Toll-like receptors (TLRs) are a recently discovered family of pattern recognition 
receptors that show homology with the Drosophila Toll protein and the human inter-
leukin (IL)-1 receptor family. The first member of the TLR family to be identified 
was a Drosophila protein 
1 implicated in dorsoventral patterning during embryonal 
development. TLRs are evolutionarily conserved proteins characterized by an 
extracellular leucine-rich repeat (LRR) domain, the transmembrane domain, and the 
cytoplasmic intracellular Toll/IL-1 receptor-like (TIR) domain. LRRs, found in both 
cytoplasmic and transmembrane proteins, play a vital role in ligand recognition and 
signal transduction. There are 12 TLRs, in which ten human isoforms of TLRs (TLR-1 
to 10) have been identified. The LRR, which is deputed to recognition of the ligand, 
is composed of 19-25 tandem repeats of 24-29 amino acids, folded in strands and 
in helices that are linked by loops. 
2 The transmembrane domain and TIR domain are 
highly conserved among the TLRs. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>TLR-4 structure </p>

<p>Recently, TLR-4 was the first identified TLR whose crystal structure (Protein Data 
Bank [PDB] ID: 3FXI) was solved (Figure 1), 
4 leading to the derivation of computa-
tional simulation models that predict the mechanism of its interaction with its cognate 
ligands. The TIR domain, which shares homology with the IL-1 receptor (IL-1R), </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
4 November 2013 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>TLR-4 </p>

<p>TLR-4 
LPSEc </p>

<p>MD-2 
MD-2 </p>

<p>LPSEc </p>

<p>TLR-4 </p>

<p>TLR-4 </p>

<p>LPSEc </p>

<p>MD-2 </p>

<p>MD-2 </p>

<p>LPSEc </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 1 Structure of the TLR-4/MD-2/LPSec complex. 
Notes: (A) Side view of the symmetrical dimer of TLR-4/MD-2/LPSec complex. 
(B) Top view of the complex. LPSec folded in between TLR-4 and MD-2 and formed 
a homodimer complex. The TLR-4/MD-2 complex will initiate signal transduction 
that is essential for the activation of TLR-4. The images were captured in <rs id="software-0" type="software">vida</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.2.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Open Eye Scientific Software</rs>, Santa Fe, NM, USA) software; using the human 
TLR-4/MD-2 crystal structure, with LPSec cocrystalized (PDB iD: 3FXi). 
Abbreviations: LPSec, lipopolysaccharide from Escherichia coli; MD-2, myeloid 
differentiation protein-2; PDB, Protein Data Bank; TLR-4, Toll-like receptor 4. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1574 </p>

<p>Mai et al </p>

<p>is responsible for the propagation of the signal within the 
cell, through interaction with a complex signaling cascade. 
Human TLR-4 is located on chromosome 9q32-q33 and 
contains four exons. </p>

<p>5   TLR-4 signaling pathway </p>

<p>TLR-4 regulates the inflammatory responses against gram-
negative bacteria, as shown in Figure 2. Lipopolysaccharide 
(LPS) is the major component of the outer membrane of 
gram-negative bacteria and triggers TLR-4 signaling. </p>

<p>6,7   TLR-4 requires myeloid differentiation factor 2 (MD-2) for 
its activation. 
8 LPS will first bind to the LPS-binding protein 
(LBP) and then to the cluster of differentiation (CD)-14 before 
binding to TLR-4/MD-2 complex. The role of CD-14 is to 
enhance the sensitivity of the TLR-4/MD-2 complex. 
9,10 The 
binding of LPS to the TLR-4/MD-2 complex triggers confor-
mational changes in the structure of the TLR-4/MD-2 complex, </p>

<p>leading to TLR-4/MD-2 homodimerization (activation) and 
resulting in the production of proinflammatory cytokines, 
through the myeloid differentiation primary response protein 
88 (MyD88)-dependent pathway, and the production of type 
1 interferons, through a MyD88-independent pathway (via the 
interaction of TIR domains with adaptor molecules). </p>

<p>11   TLR-4 plays an important role in innate immunity as the 
first line of host defense. TLR-4 is expressed in normal epithe-
lial cells, immune cells, and in cancer cells. 
12 Most human cells 
express a low level of TLR-4 and high levels of TLR-antagonist 
proteins, such as Toll-interacting protein (TOLLIP), which 
prevent the overexpression of TLR. 
13−16 The normal immune 
and epithelial cells present in the skin, digestive, respiratory, 
and reproductive systems activate the host's immune systems 
pathways through pathogen-associated molecular patterns 
(PAMPs) and danger associated molecular patterns (DAMPs). 
TLR-4 responds to the various invading exogenous pathogens 
through PAMPs and recognizes the endogenous ligands from 
necrotic cells through DAMPs (Figure 3). 
17 Although innate 
immunity appears to be a nonspecific response, it could dif-
ferentiate "self " molecules and pathogens through the pattern 
recognition receptors on TLR-4. </p>

<p>18   Despite the promising innate immune responses from TLR-
4, there is growing evidence that TLR-4 activation appears to 
act as a double-edged sword in cancers, ie, TLR-4 activation 
has been linked to both cancer inhibition and growth. Given 
the links of infection and inflammation with cancer, further 
evaluation of the role of TLR-4 in cancer is warranted. The 
detailed biological relationships between TLR-4 and cancers 
are still poorly understood. Therefore, in this review article, 
we gather the knowledge of TLR-4 activation in infection and 
inflammation related cancers. Also, we surveyed TLR-4 expres-
sion and its effects in various cancers (Table 1), viz, head and 
neck cancer, lung cancer, gastrointestinal cancer, liver cancer, 
pancreatic cancer, skin cancer, breast cancer, ovarian cancer, 
cervical cancer, and prostate cancer. Ultimately we wish to 
establish the therapeutic indication for whether TLR-4 agonist 
or antagonist is required in treating cancers. The details of the 
role of TLR-4 as one of the key mediators in innate immunity 
responses 
19−21 and of the brief relationship between TLRs and 
inflammatory diseases, 
22−25 TLR-4 and infections, 
26,27 and poten-
tial TLR-4 ligands 
28,29 are not the focus of this review paper, as 
these topics have been covered by other authors. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in infection and its relation 
to cancer </p>

<p>The recognition of PAMPs by TLR-4 during microorgan-
ism invasion occurs at the plasma membrane, endosomes, </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>TLR-4 
TLR-4 </p>

<p>MD-2 
MD-2 </p>

<p>MyD88-
dependent 
pathway </p>

<p>MyD88-
independent 
or 
TRIF-dependent 
pathway </p>

<p>Cytoplasm </p>

<p>Cell surface </p>

<p>IKK activation 
IRF3 activation </p>

<p>IFNγ induction </p>

<p>Type 1 interferon </p>

<p>NF-κB activation </p>

<p>Proinflammatory cytokines </p>

<p>MyD88 </p>

<p>IRAK4 </p>

<p>IRAK1/2 </p>

<p>TRAF6 </p>

<p>TRAM </p>

<p>TRIF </p>

<p>TRAF3 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Schematic illustration of the TLR-4 signaling pathway. 
Notes: TLR-4/MD-2 complex homodimerization activates the MyD88-dependent pathway and TRiF-dependent pathway. in the MyD88-dependent pathway, MyD88 recruits 
IRAK4, IRAK1/2, and TRAF6 to activate IKK and leads to NF-κB activation; in the TRIF-dependent (or MyD88-independent pathway), TRAM/TRIF activates TRAF3 and leads 
to IRF3 activation and induction of IFNγ. 
Abbreviations: IFN, interferon; IKK, inhibitory kappa B alpha kinase; IL-1R, interleukin 1 receptor; IRAK, interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinase; IRF3, interferon 
regulatory factor 3; MD-2, myeloid differentiation protein-2; MyD88, myeloid differentiation protein 88; NF-κB, nuclear factor-kappaB; TLR-4, Toll-like receptor 4; TRAF, 
tumor necrosis factor receptor-associated factor; TRAM, TRIF-related adapter protein; TRIF, Toll/IL-1R-domain containing adapter-inducing IFN-β. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1575 </p>

<p>Should a TLR-4 agonist or antagonist be designed to treat cancer? </p>

<p>lysosomes, and endolysosomes. 
30 The innate immunity usually 
enhances epithelial proliferation, wound healing, and the acute 
inflammatory responses. 
31 In normal host homeostasis, host 
immune cells activate various antitumor activities to prevent 
noncarcinogenic cells from evolving into carcinogenic cells. 
In acute pathogenic infection, CD8 
+ T-cells are activated and in 
turn, induce natural killer cells activation. The activated CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T-cells eliminate any tumor through tumor-associated antigen-
specific immunity, while the activated natural killer cells 
stimulate dendritic cells (DCs) to modulate adaptive antitumor 
immunity. However, studies have suggested that in a tumor 
microenvironment, the antitumor activities of the infiltrating 
immune cells were downregulated, due to the activated TLR-4 
present in cancer cells. </p>

<p>32−36   A recent human study reported that Helicobacter pylori, 
one of the common pathogenic gram-negative bacteria, 
induced a high expression of TLR-4 in normal gastric mucosa 
at the initial exposure. The authors suggested that early expo-
sure to LPS in the gastric mucosa reduces the expression of </p>

<p>TOLLIP and leads to the production of proinflammatory 
cytokines. The overexpression of TLR-4 and the chronic 
production of these inflammatory cytokines contributes to 
aberrant transcription of caudal type homeobox 2 (CDX-
2), phenotypic change to intestinal metaplasia, and a lower 
TOLLIP expression in the cells. The progressive increase in 
the levels of CDX-2 activates pro-oncogenic intracellular 
pathways and may lead to cancer. </p>

<p>16   An animal study supported that TLR-4-deficient mice 
were protected from colitis-associated tumors. 
37 The authors 
found that the MyD88 pathway of TLR-4 contributed to 
microbiota-induced colitis-associated cancer. The severity 
of chronic colitis was directly correlated with its colorectal 
cancer development. 
38 Several other studies have also sug-
gested that MyD88 promoted carcinogenesis in epithelial 
cells, in several in vivo studies. </p>

<p>39−41   Bacterial-induced inflammation via TLR-4 can also 
induce tumor progression. 
38 Killeen et al reported that LPS 
increases the expression of urokinase plasminogen activator </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1576 </p>

<p>Mai et al </p>

<p>and urokinase plasminogen activator receptor in colorectal 
cancer cells. 
42 LPS also enhances the colorectal cancer cell 
adhesion and invasion, but not in the presence of TLR-4 
blocking antibody. 
42 LPS helps the cancer cells evade immune 
surveillance via the production of IL-6, IL-12, inducible nitric 
oxide synthase as well as via the expression of antiapoptotic 
proteins, such as X-linked inhibitor of apoptosis. 
43,44 Studies 
have also suggested that the chronic activation of TLR-4 from 
microorganism invasion induces oncogenic potential in the 
host, through the chronic activation of nuclear factor-kappaB 
(NF-κB) and cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2). </p>

<p>31,45,46   TLR-4 in inflammation and its 
relation to cancer </p>

<p>The association between cancers and inflammation induced by 
PAMPs is clearly evident; however, the association between 
PAMPs and TLR-4 expression in cancers is minimal. This 
suggests nonpathogenic TLR-4-induced inflammation also 
plays an important role in cancers. In the noncancerous condi-
tion, cell death is usually driven by phagocytosis or apoptosis. </p>

<p>On the other hand, in cancer cells, necrosis-induced cell 
death is related to the release of DAMP (Figure 3). Certain 
DAMP, such as high mobility group box-1 protein (HMGB1), 
could potentially promote cancer progression. 
19,47 HMGB1 
is a deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)-binding protein secreted 
from cells upon cytokine stimulation or necrotic cell death. 
Cancer cells have been found to have high expression of 
HMGB1. 
48,49 HMGB1 has also been reported to induce cancer 
cell invasion, migration, and metastasis 
50,51 as well as in vitro 
endothelial cell proliferation and in vivo neovascularization. </p>

<p>52   Anti-HMGB1 antibody was also shown to inhibit angiogen-
esis. 
53 This evidence collectively suggests HMGB1 as an 
endogenous TLR-4 ligand that induces carcinogenesis. 
28,54 In 
one study, it was found that the levels of these DAMP-derived 
molecules were high in the tumor microenvironment and that 
they induced TLR-4-related chronic inflammation, leading 
to carcinogenesis, cancer progression, and metastasis. </p>

<p>12   Another study highlighted that the TLR-4/MD-2 complex 
enhanced the formation of regions of hyperpermeability, 
through upregulation of C-C chemokine receptor type 2 </p>

<p>PAMP/ DAMP </p>

<p>CD4 
+ T cells </p>

<p>Tregs </p>

<p>TAM </p>

<p>MDSCs </p>

<p>Dysfunctional DCs </p>

<p>Cancer-associated 
fibroblasts </p>

<p>CD8 
+ cells </p>

<p>Macrophages </p>

<p>MDSCs </p>

<p>DCs </p>

<p>Fibroblasts </p>

<p>NK cells </p>

<p>Nontumor 
microenvironment </p>

<p>Tumor 
microenvironment </p>

<p>TLR-4 
TLR-4 </p>

<p>LPS from 
microorganisms </p>

<p>Necrotic cells/ 
endogenous ligands </p>

<p>TLR-4 </p>

<p>Angiogenesis 
Tumor growth 
Tumor progression 
Tumor invasion 
Tumor metastasis </p>

<p>Chronic inflammation </p>

<p>Figure 3 TLR-4 signaling induces the transformation of the nontumor microenvironment to a tumor microenvironment. 
Notes: Lipopolysaccharide from Escherichia coli produces PAMP while the necrotic cells and other endogenous ligands produce DAMP. Both activate TLR-4 in both 
nontumor and tumor environments. Prolonged activation of TLR-4 induces CD4 
+ cells to be transformed into CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD25 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Foxp3 
+ Tregs; macrophages to be transformed 
into TAM; MDSCs are recruited into tumor microenvironments and activated; dendritic cells will lose antitumor effects; fibroblasts are transformed into cancer associated 
fibroblasts; anti-tumor effects of CD8 
+ and NK cells are impaired. In the presence of immunosuppressive cytokines, pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines, there is 
chronic inflammation, tumor growth, progression, angiogenesis, invasion, and tumor metastasis. 
Abbreviations: CD, cluster of differentiation; DAMP, danger-associated molecular patterns; MDSCs, myeloid derived suppressor cells; NK, natural killer; PAMP, pathogen-
associated molecular patterns; TAM, tumor associated macrophages; TLR-4, Toll-like receptor 4; Tregs, regulatory T cells; DCs, dendritic cells; LPS, lipopolysaccharide. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1577 </p>

<p>Should a TLR-4 agonist or antagonist be designed to treat cancer? </p>

<p>(CCR2) expression, in inflamed mice and thus increased the 
rate of lung metastasis. 
55 Metastasis was found to be initiated 
also by serum amyloid, through TLR-4-dependent NF-κB 
inflammation pathways. 
56 All these latest findings clearly 
suggested the pivotal role of the TLR-4/MD-2 complex in 
inflammation-associated cancers. </p>

<p>TLR-4 signaling in tumor cells 
versus immune cells </p>

<p>The hallmarks of inflammation-associated cancers are the 
presence of inflammatory cells and cytokines in the tumor 
microenvironments that leads to tumor growth, angiogen-
esis, tumor invasion, and/or metastasis. 
57,58 TLR-4 activation </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary of TLR-4 expression and its effects on various tumors </p>

<p>Type of cancer 
TLR-4 expression 
Effect of TLR-4 </p>

<p>Head and neck cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>70-72 </p>

<p>• Enhances cancer cell growth, NF-κB translocation, activated phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/Akt 
pathway, and upregulation of iRAK-4 expression, iL-6 production, iL-8 production, veGF, and 
granulocyte macrophage colony-stimulating factor </p>

<p>71   Lung cancer 
↓ </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>• inhibits lung carcinogenesis </p>

<p>75   • increases immunosuppressive cytokines, production of proangiogenic chemokine, and 
resistance to apoptosis </p>

<p>35   esophageal cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>35,78   • Overexpression in esophageal cancers </p>

<p>86   Gastric cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>86 </p>

<p>• Increases NF-κB signaling and iL-8 secretion </p>

<p>88   • increases Helicobacter pylori-induced gastric tumor cells </p>

<p>90   • increases further interaction with H. pylori and induces secretion of gastric carcinoma-
promoting factors </p>

<p>90   • increases COX-2 and PGe2 </p>

<p>33   • Higher risk of gastric cancer in the TLR-4 gene polymorphism </p>

<p>92−100   Colorectal cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>87-89 </p>

<p>• increases COX-2 and PGe2 signaling and early colorectal carcinogenesis, inhibit apoptosis, 
and promotes angiogenesis </p>

<p>99,100   • increases the generation of reactive oxygen species </p>

<p>168   • Blocking of TLR-4 inhibits cancer proliferation </p>

<p>45   • Blocking of TLR-4 reverses the tumor-mediated suppression of T-cell proliferation and 
natural killer cell activity </p>

<p>45   • Blocking of TLR-4 prolonged tumor-bearing mice survival </p>

<p>45   • increases colon cancer cell adhesion and invasion, through the urokinase plasminogen 
activator system and β1 integrin </p>

<p>42,117,118   • Higher risk of colorectal cancer with the TLR-4 gene polymorphism </p>

<p>115   Liver cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>103,104 </p>

<p>• increases the liver tumor formation </p>

<p>123   • increases Nanog gene expression, which induces liver oncogenesis </p>

<p>123   • Stimulates carcinogen-induced liver injury and cancer </p>

<p>42   Pancreatic cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>123 </p>

<p>• Poor prognosis with overexpressed TLR-4 patients </p>

<p>126   • Blocking of TLR-4 or MyD88 decreased the LPS-dependent increase of cancer invasive ability </p>

<p>6   Skin cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>• Increases NF-κB signaling, upregulation of MMP-2, expression, and iL-8 production </p>

<p>130   • increases tumor progression with persistent TLR-4 activation </p>

<p>34   • Protects against chemical carcinogen-induced tumor formation </p>

<p>133   Breast cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>• Blocking of TLR-4 inhibits cancer proliferation </p>

<p>137   • Blocking of TLR-4 reduces iL-6 and iL-8 </p>

<p>138   • Breast cancer metastasis is associated with activation of TLR-4 </p>

<p>138-142   Ovarian cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>• increases cytokine (iL-6, MCP-1, and CXCL1) secretion </p>

<p>36   • Increases NF-κB signaling </p>

<p>36   • Blocking of TLR-4 improves paclitaxel resistance </p>

<p>36,146,148   • inducible heat shock proteins from ovarian cancer induce neutrophil activation through 
TLR-4 and cause tumor progression as well as tumor lysis </p>

<p>147   Cervical cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>36,146   • Pathogenic microorganisms induce upregulation of integrin β6, TLR-3, and TLR-4 in cervical 
cancer cells </p>

<p>152   Prostate cancer 
↑ </p>

<p>124,152 </p>

<p>• Increases MyD88-dependent NF-κB signaling </p>

<p>158   • increases veGF </p>

<p>159   • increases TGF-β1 </p>

<p>159 </p>

<p>Notes: ↑ = increased compared with normal cells; ↓ = decreased compared with normal cells. 
Abbreviations: Akt, protein kinase B; COX-2, cyclooxygenase-2; IL, interleukin; IRAK-4, interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinase; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; MCP-1, 
monocyte chemoattractant protein 1; MMP-2, matrix metalloproteinase-2; MyD88, myeloid differentiation protein 88; NF-κB, nuclear factor-kappaB; PGE2, prostaglandin E2; 
TGF, transforming growth factor; TLR-4, Toll-like receptor 4; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor; CXCL1, chemokine C-X-C motif ligand 1. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1578 </p>

<p>Mai et al </p>

<p>upregulates the proinflammatory cytokines and chemokines 
(CCL, CXCL, CCR, CXCR, IL-6, IL-18, tumor necrosis 
factor [TNF]-α, etc) as well as immunosuppressive cytokine 
(transforming growth factor [TGF-β]1, IL-10 etc), especially 
in tumor microenvironment (Figure 3). 
12 CD4 
+ , CD25 
+ , 
and Foxp3 
+ regulatory T cells in the tumor microenviron-
ment secrete IL-10 and TGF-β, which limit the antitumor 
effect of non-regulatory T-cells. 
12,59 In tumors, associated 
macrophages have been shown to release angiogenic and 
lymphangiogenic factors that promote metastasis. </p>

<p>12,60   Myeloid-derived suppressor cells recruited to the tumor 
microenvironment under the influence of IL-1β, IL-6, and 
prostaglandin (PG)E 2 were also shown to impair the antitu-
mor response of the host, through the release of nitric oxide 
synthase and TGF-β. 
12 DCs too, were found to be dysfunc-
tional in the tumor microenvironment, due to the suppressive 
effects of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), IL-6, 
IL-1, TGF-β, COX-2 and PGE 2 . 
12,61 Elsewhere, fibroblast 
was transformed into cancer-associated fibroblast (CAF) 
in the tumor microenvironment, and TGF-β-induced CAF 
activation promoted tumor growth and proliferation. TLR-4 
activation has also been related to TGF-β signaling−related 
cancer growth. </p>

<p>12,62−64   As a result of these findings, these infiltrating immune 
cells were hypothesized to support cancer progression, 
angiogenesis, and metastasis. 
32−36 All the above suggest that 
the release of various immunosuppressive cytokines, proin-
flammatory cytokines, and chemokines during the activation 
of TLR-4 could contribute to cancer formation in normal 
epithelial cells, immune cells, and cancer cells. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in modulation of 
angiogenesis and its relation 
in limiting tumor progression </p>

<p>Despite the fact that activated TLR-4 has procarcino-
genic effects, the antitumor effect induced by activated 
TLR-4 should not be neglected. One study reported that 
the Mycobacterium bovis bacillus Calmette−Guérin cell 
wall skeleton enhanced the cytotoxic activity of T-cells and 
macrophages against cancer cells, probably through TLR-4. 
Bacillus Calmette−Guérin cell wall skeleton induced TNF-α 
secretion from DCs through TLR-2 and TLR-4 signaling and 
thus induced the maturation of DCs. 
65 Elsewhere, OK-432, a 
penicillin-killed and lyophilized preparation of Streptococ-
cus pyogenes exhibited potent immunotherapeutic effect in 
cancers. 
66 Studies supported that OK-PSA, the molecule 
isolated from a butanol extract of OK-432, induced anticancer 
immunity and DC maturation, via TLR-4. 
67 It was also found </p>

<p>that OK-PSA-induced cytokine production was inhibited by 
anti-TLR-4 monoclonal antibody. In other work, the com-
pound isolated from Aeginetia indica L. (AILb-A) induced 
NF-κB activation in NF-κB-dependent reporter cells contain-
ing TLR-4 plasmid; AILb-A also did not induce any cytokine 
production in TLR-4 deficient mice. 
67 Finally, synthetic ser-
ine-based glycolipid (CCL-34)-activated macrophages were 
shown to induce cancer cell death through TLR-4 dependent 
pathways. 
68 These findings suggest TLR-4 activators induce 
antitumor immunity through TLR-4 signaling. </p>

<p>Role of MD-2 in cancer </p>

<p>The expression of MD-2 in most cancer cells has not been 
well studied. Limited evidence has concluded that MD-2 
plays a role in cancer progression only. One study highlighted 
that MD-2 was overexpressed in highly invasive colorectal 
cancer cells (SW837), in poorly differentiated, moderately 
invasive colorectal cancer cells (HT-29), and in well-differ-
entiated but non-invasive colorectal cancer cells (Caco-2). </p>

<p>69   Another study reported that serum amyloid A 3, a major 
component of acute phase inflammation, binds to MD-2 and 
activates the MyD88-dependent TLR-4/MD-2 pathway and 
thus facilitates lung metastasis. 
70 Therefore, MD-2 could be 
related to the degree of differentiation, proliferation, and 
migration capacity of cancers. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in head and neck cancer </p>

<p>The laryngeal carcinomas predominate in this category. 
71 The 
treatment of head and neck cancers remains a big challenge 
for oncologists. A study in Poland of 20 laryngeal cancer 
patients with no distant metastasis (M 0 =100%) reported 
TLR-2-, TLR-3-, and TLR-4-expression in the laryngeal 
carcinoma microenvironment. Although TLR-4 is the least 
frequently expressed TLR on laryngeal tumors, it is still the 
most frequently expressed TLR on inflammatory cells in 
all tumor masses and tumor stroma. This fact suggests the 
possibility of TLR-4 involvement in the escape of tumors 
from immune surveillance. The detection of TLR-2, TLR-3, 
TLR-4, and major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class 
II antigens in all laryngeal carcinoma suggests the role of 
TLRs in the activation of adaptive immunity. </p>

<p>72   TLR-4 was also detected in laryngeal tumor tissue (n=27), 
oral cavity tumor tissue (n=10), and cancer cells (PCI-1, PCI-
13, and PCI-30). 
73 Moreover, TLR-4 levels in tumors were 
correlated with tumor differentiation. TLR-4 was shown to 
enhance the release of tumor progression mediators, resulting 
in tumor proliferation and progression. 
73,74 A study reported 
cancer cells express significantly higher levels of TLR-4 and </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1579 </p>

<p>Should a TLR-4 agonist or antagonist be designed to treat cancer? </p>

<p>NF-κB compared with noncancerous cells. A positive corre-
lation was also established between TLR-4 levels in laryngeal 
tumor central cells, with tumor front grading. 
74 Another study, 
published in 2012, suggested the increased activity of TLR-4, 
TNF receptor-associated factor (TRAF) 6, and IL-1 receptor-
associated kinase (IRAK) 1 in advanced laryngeal carcinoma, 
suggesting the TLR-4/MyD88-dependent signaling pathway 
involvement in laryngeal carcinoma progression. </p>

<p>75   TLR-4 in lung cancer </p>

<p>Worldwide, lung cancer is the most common cause of 
cancer-related deaths in men and women. Lung cancer 
mortality rates have been rising in recent decades. Chronic 
inflammatory disease, such as chronic obstructive pulmo-
nary disease (COPD), has been identified as a risk factor for 
lung cancer. 
76 Since TLR-4 is also actively involved in the 
immune response against cancers, researchers have postu-
lated that TLR-4 exerts both a defensive role in normal cells 
and a negative role in cancer cells. However, the available 
evidence is still not conclusive on the link between TLR-4 
and lung cancer. 
A study of functional TLR-4 and mutated TLR-4 in 
mice found that mice with the former had less lung capil-
lary permeability, less weight loss, leukocyte inflammation, 
and primary tumor formation. Thus, the authors, Bauer et al, 
postulated that TLR-4 inhibits lung carcinogenesis by inhib-
iting tumor progression. 
77 The researchers proved TLR-4 
activation could protect the lungs from being inflamed dur-
ing any potential tumorigenesis. 
78 Elsewhere, a lower level 
of TLR-4 in the nasal epithelium of a smoker compared 
with a nonsmoker was observed, with a profound reduction 
in patients with severe COPD. 
79 This finding suggests the 
potential role of TLR-4 for airway inflammation and lung 
cancer progression. 
In vitro studies have also found that TLR-4 is constantly 
expressed and upregulated on human lung cancer cells. 
33,80 In 
one study, the level of TLR-4 was significantly linked with 
the production of immunosuppressive cytokines, production 
of proangiogenic chemokine, and with resistance to apoptosis 
by lung cancer cells. 
33 Despite the reported significance of 
TLR-9 in lung cancer progression, 
81−84 a positive correlation 
(P,0.05) of TLR-4, but not TLR-9, with tumor differentia-
tion in lung cancer patients was reported. </p>

<p>80   TLR-4 in gastrointestinal cancer </p>

<p>The gastrointestinal tract (esophagus, stomach, and 
small and large intestine) is often exposed to pathogens 
and carcinogens. Epidemiological studies suggest chronic </p>

<p>inflammation, whether pathogen-related or not, increases the 
risk of gastrointestinal cancer. </p>

<p>31,85   Globally, there has been an increase in esophageal cancer. </p>

<p>86   Esophageal cancer usually occurs in Barrett's esophagus. The 
link or relationship between inflammation and tumorigenesis 
in esophageal cancer remains controversial. Esophageal 
motility allows pathogen transit from the oral cavity to the 
stomach, making it difficult to quantify PAMP and bacteria 
exposure. Single nucleotide polymorphism arrays have 
suggested that in patients with esophageal squamous cell 
carcinoma, genetic alterations in TLR-4 (9q32-q33) along 
with other chromosomal mutations are associated with higher 
cancer proliferation and metastasis. 
87 Immunohistochemistry 
and reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction of sam-
ples from 87 esophageal cancer patients revealed that TLR-4 
as well as TLR-3, TLR-7, and TLR-9 are overexpressed in 
esophageal cancer. The isolated mononuclear inflammatory 
cells associated with higher lymph node metastasis and inva-
sion were also shown to express a high level of TLR-4. 
88 The 
level of mucosal expression of TLRs in the esophagus has 
not yet been elucidated. </p>

<p>31   H. pylori infection has been identified as the root cause 
of stomach cancer. Gastric inflammation is an invariable 
finding in patients infected with H. pylori and represents the 
host immune response to the organism. H. pylori infection 
leads to gastric inflammation, characterized histologically by 
surface epithelial degeneration and infiltration of the gastric 
mucosa, through acute and chronic inflammatory cells. In 
H. pylori infections, TLR-4 on the gastric epithelial cells 
regulates the LPS response. 
89−91 Gastric biopsy samples have 
suggested H. pylori infections accelerate TLR-4 and MD-2 
expression in human gastric epithelial cells, 
90 which in turn 
enables the gastric carcinoma cells to further interact with 
H. pylori and consequently, induce the secretion of gastric 
carcinoma promoting factors. 
92 Elsewhere, anti-TLR-4 anti-
body inhibited H. pylori-induced messenger ribonucleic acid 
(mRNA) expression of human β-defensin in gastric cancer 
cells (MKN 45). 
93 These results further strengthened the 
hypothesis that H. pylori induce the expression of TLR-4 in 
gastric epithelial cells. 
Based on the report of TLR-4 signaling in colonic 
COX-2 expression and PGE 2 production, Fukata et al sug-
gested that there is a high correlation between TLR-4 sig-
naling and the expression of COX-2 as well as PGE 2 in 
H. pylori-associated gastric cancers. 
94 The expression of 
NF-κB in association with COX-2 and TNF-α was postu-
lated to be mediated through TLR-4, but not through TLR-2 
or -9, based on the findings from previous research, in which </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1580 </p>

<p>Mai et al </p>

<p>guinea pig gastric epithelial cells were preincubated with 
H. pylori LPS. </p>

<p>89   Patients with poorly differentiated gastric adenocarci-
nomas have been shown to have Thr35 Ala polymorphism 
in the LRR of TLR-4, but not TLR-2, TLR-6, or TLR-9. </p>

<p>95   This finding supports the hypothesis that TLR-4 gene 
polymorphism is related to poorly-differentiated gastric 
adenocarcinoma. In addition, a significantly higher risk of 
gastric carcinoma has been found with TLR-4 Ala896Gly 
polymorphism. 
96 A case-control study of 171 Italian gastric 
cancer patients and 151 controls reported TLR-4 Thr399Ile 
polymorphism, but not TLR-4 Asp299Gly polymorphism, is 
linked with increased risk of gastric cancer (P=0.023, hazard 
ratio [HR] =3.62). Further, an increased risk of intestinal 
gastric cancer (P=0.006, HR=5.38), but not diffuse gastric 
cancer (P=0.612, HR=1.85) was reported in carriers of 
TLR-4 Thr399Ile allele. 
97 Similar results were reported by 
repeated studies on the role of TLR-4 Asp299Gly/Thr399Ile 
single nucleotide polymorphism in relation to gastric 
carcinogenesis. 
98,99 However, another case-control study 
carried out in Mexico reported neither TLR-4 Asp299Gly 
polymorphism (P=0.82) nor TLR-4 Thr399Ile polymor-
phism (P=0.2) was associated with significant incidence 
of gastric cancer. </p>

<p>100   TLR-4 in colorectal cancer can be a double-edged sword, 
enhancing the host anticancer immunity and promoting 
tumor growth at the same time. In acute intestinal mucosa 
injury, in response to LPS, TLR-4 expression induces COX-2 
expression, which leads to wound healing. Thus, mice that 
lack MyD88 or TLR-4 signaling have been shown to have 
a reduced healing ability after an acute injury. However, in 
chronic intestinal inflammation, TLR-4 induces COX-2 and 
PGE 2 production, which may result in early colorectal car-
cinogenesis, inhibition of apoptosis, and increase of angio-
genesis. 
94,101 Thus, blocking of TLR-4 signaling can prevent 
colon cancer cell (MC26 cells) proliferation and reverse 
tumor-mediated suppression of T-cell proliferation. Just as 
in other cancers, chronic inflammation in intestinal epithe-
lial cells is closely related to the incidence rate of colorectal 
cancer. Healthy intestinal epithelial cells constitutively 
express TLR-3 and TLR-5, where TLR-2 and TLR-4 are 
lower in quantity. 
102 However, altered expression of TLRs 
is observed in chronically inflamed intestinal epithelial 
cells. 
101−103 TLR-4 expression is significantly upregulated in 
inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), but expression of TLR-2 
and TLR-5 remains unchanged. 
102 A significant induction 
of TLR-2 and TLR-4 expression has been observed on the 
submucosa of inflamed intestinal epithelial cells. 
104 Also, a </p>

<p>significant increase in TLR-4 expression was identified in 
the colon cancer cells. 
105,106 Patients with higher levels of 
TLR-4 in colon tumor stroma were shown to have an earlier 
relapse (14 months) compared with those who had lower 
expression (40 months). 
105 This clearly suggests the role of 
TLR-4 in colorectal tumorigenesis and progression. 
Patients suffering with IBD do have increased risk of 
cancer (0.5%−1% yearly). 
31 The impact of TLR-4 polymor-
phism on IBD is controversial. No association was reported 
with TLR-4 Asp299Gly and Thr399Ile polymorphism, in a 
group of IBD patients from Southern Italy, 
107 New Zealand, </p>

<p>108   Germany, and Hungary. 
109 However, some studies have 
suggested a significant link between TLR-4 Asp299Gly 
polymorphism and either ulcerative colitis or Crohn's 
disease or both. 
110−115 In addition, a meta-analysis reported 
in 2010, showed a significant association between TLR-4 
(Asp299Gly and Thr399Ile) polymorphism with ulcerative 
colitis (odds ratio [OR] =1.08, 95% confidence interval 
[CI]: 1.08−1.51), Crohn's disease (OR: 1.29, 95% CI: 
1.08−1.54), and IBD (OR: 1.25, 95% CI: 1.06−1.48). 
116 As 
well, TLR-4 Asp299Gly polymorphism was significantly 
higher in colorectal patients compared with normal healthy 
adults (P=0.0269). 
117 Also, studies report that LPS enhanced 
colorectal cancer cell adhesion and invasion, through TLR-
4-and NF-κB-dependent activation of the urokinase plasmi-
nogen activator system and beta-1 integrin, which ultimately 
leads to tumor progression. 
64,118,119 In vivo data suggests 
TLR-4 inhibition has prolonged the survival rate of tumor-
bearing mice (BALB/c). 
43 Stimulation of the TLR-4/MD-2 
complex by LPS can activate phosphoinositide-3-kinase 
(PI3 K) signaling and thus promotes the adhesiveness and 
metastatic capacity of colorectal cancer cells. 
120 All these 
findings have consolidated the role of TLR-4 in colorectal 
cancer progression. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in liver cancer </p>

<p>Dysregulated innate immunity is an integral component 
in liver disease. Chronic liver diseases, such as alcoholic 
liver cirrhosis, have also been established as the major 
cause of liver cancer. 
121 Many liver cells (Kupffer cells, 
hepatocytes, stellate cells, biliary epithelium, and sinusoi-
dal endothelium) constantly express TLR-4. 
122 The levels 
of TLR-4 have been found to be upregulated in hepatitis 
B− and hepatitis C−infected cells 
123,124 and further upregu-
lated in alcohol-induced liver damage and tumors. </p>

<p>125,126   On the other hand, diethylnitrosamine, a carcinogen, was 
shown to stimulate TLR-4 signaling in mice, resulting in an 
increase in the size and number of tumors, while the size </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1581 </p>

<p>Should a TLR-4 agonist or antagonist be designed to treat cancer? </p>

<p>and number of tumors were found be reduced in MyD88 
deficient mice. </p>

<p>40   TLR-4 in pancreatic cancer </p>

<p>It is very difficult to detect pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma 
at early stage because of its anatomic location and insidious 
nature. LPS could be a triggering factor in the initiation and 
progression of pancreatitis and pancreatic cancer. 
7,127 This 
suggests the possible role of TLR-4 in pancreatic cancer since 
LPS is a well-established agonist of TLR-4. 
Significant expression of TLR-4 (P=0.002) was detected 
in a study of pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma as compared 
with adjacent normal tissues. 
128 In this study, there was no 
correlation found between the levels of TLR-4 and age, 
gender, location and differentiation of tumor; however, 
TLR-4 levels were correlated with tumor size, lymph node 
involvement, venous invasion, and pathological stage. 
Positive correlations were also observed between TLR-4 
and hypoxia-inducible transcription factor-1α (HIF-1α). The 
expression of NF-κB phosphorylated p65 was also higher in 
the tumor cells. The patients with overexpressed TLR-4 or 
overexpressed HIF-1α had a significantly shorter survival 
period than did the patients with normal expression (P=0.011 
and P=0.005, respectively). Longer survival (P=0.014) was 
noted among patients with neither TLR-4 nor HIF-1α over-
expressed compared with patients who had both TLR-4 and 
HIF-1α overexpressed. 
130 A separate in vitro study on human 
pancreatic cancer cells (Panc-1 and AsPC-1) revealed that 
TLR-4 was responsible for the invasive ability of cancer 
cells, mostly due to TLR-4-dependent NF-κB activation. </p>

<p>6   These results demonstrated the importance of TLR-4 in 
pancreatic cancer proliferation. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in skin cancer </p>

<p>Not only is skin the largest organ in our human body, it also 
protects us from pathogen invasion through its innate and 
adaptive immunity. A study has drawn attention to the role 
of TLRs in atopic dermatitis, psoriasis, acne vulgaris, and 
skin infection and has suggested the potential of TLRs as 
a therapeutic target to treat skin cancer. 
129 Melanoma cells 
have a significantly higher amount of TLR-4 levels. 
130−133 An 
in vitro analysis showed the consistent expression of TLR-4 
on 13 out of 15 established human metastatic melanoma cells 
(ME1, ME2, ME5, ME7, ME8, ME9, ME16, ME17, ME18, 
ME19, ME20, ME21, and ME22) tested. The expression 
of TLR-2 and -3 was also detected in some, but not in all. 
TLR-1,-5,-6,-7,-8,-9, and -10 were either absent or weakly 
expressed. The TLRs, including TLR-4, were upregulated </p>

<p>in melanoma, 
32 and it was noted that the coadministration 
of paclitaxel and icariside II (isolated from Herba Epime-
dii) enhanced apoptosis and decreased the levels of IL-8 
and VEGF in human melanoma A375 cells, through the 
inhibition of TLR-4/MyD88 signaling. 
134 A group of Ger-
man scientists found that TLR-4 was involved in melanoma 
responses to hyaluronic acid-induced tumor invasion and 
metastasis. </p>

<p>132   Another study suggested that the chemical carcinogen 
7,12-dimenthylbenz(a)anthracene (DMBA) is associated with 
endotoxin hypersensitivity mediated through TLR-4-trig-
gered T-cell activation, resulting in cell-mediated immunity. 
In that study, TLR-4-deficient mice were found to have more 
tumors compared with normal mice. 
135 Another study showed 
that melanoma inhibits macrophage activation by suppress-
ing TLR-4 signaling. 
136 An interesting theory, proposed by 
Sanchez-Perez et al, is that the intentional generation of an 
autoimmune response by normal cells could generate a poten-
tial antitumor response against tumors of the same type cells. 
This would explain their finding that the heat shock protein 
(Hsp)70, a potent immune adjuvant acting through TLR-4 
activation, kills inflammatory melanocytes. 
131 Thus, TLR-4 
activation could be beneficial, at the initial stage, to control 
melanoma progression. However, the persistent activation of 
TLR-4 may be harmful to the host. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in breast cancer </p>

<p>Breast cancer is one of the most common cancers affect-
ing women worldwide. The current available therapy has 
yet to meet the desired outcomes. Two research teams 
have suggested the role of TLR-2 
137 and TLR-9 
138 in breast 
cancer proliferation. In 2010, Yang et al reported that ten 
TLRs were expressed in MDA-MB-231 cells, the estrogen 
receptor−negative human breast cancer cells. Among all the 
TLRs, TLR-4 expression was the highest and was five times 
higher than TLR-3 expression (the least expressed among 
the remaining TLR-1 to TLR-10). Functional analyses of 
ribonucleic acid interference (RNAi) against TLR-4 revealed 
this successfully inhibited the growth and proliferation of 
MDA-MB-231 cells and resulted in a significant (P,0.05) 
reduction of inflammatory cytokines. </p>

<p>139   In other work, 4T1 (spontaneously metastasizing mam-
mary adenocarcinoma) cells challenged with lipopolysac-
charide induced tumor growth and metastasis, by increasing 
angiogenesis, vascular permeability, and tumor invasion. </p>

<p>140,141   An immunohistochemical study on clinical carcinomas 
showed a significant association of high TLR-4 expression 
with local cancer proliferation and lymph node metastasis. </p>

<p>142 </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1582 </p>

<p>Mai et al </p>

<p>A total of 74 breast carcinomas were collected from patients 
to study the clinical relevance of TLRs in breast cancer. 
Tumors with high TLR-4 expression, but not TLR-9 expres-
sion, in mononuclear cells were found to have a higher 
probability of metastasis. 
143 In metastatic breast cancer cells, 
activated TLR-4 regulates the expression of mediators that 
promote cancer adhesion and invasion. In addition to this, 
TLR-4 signaling increases microRNA 21 (miR-21) in breast 
cancer cells, through NF-κB. </p>

<p>144   Incidents of relapses have been shown to be high in breast 
cancer patients harboring the TLR-4 Asp299Gly polymor-
phism who were treated with anthracycline-based chemo-
therapeutic drugs. 
145 This polymorphism also confers to an 
increased risk of breast cancer progression. 
146 However, the 
levels of the TLR-4 Ala896Gly allele in breast cancer patients 
were not found to be significantly different from those levels 
in normal healthy Caucasian women. 
147 These studies suggest 
TLR-4 involvement in breast cancer progression. Future stud-
ies are warranted, in developing novel therapeutic approaches 
targeting TLR-4 against breast cancer. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in ovarian cancer </p>

<p>A proinflammatory environment in the ovary, such as with 
ovarian endometriosis, predisposes women to ovarian cancer. 
Epithelial ovarian cancer cells have been found to express 
TLR-4, but not the adjacent nondysplasia cells. 
34,148 It has 
been found that ovarian tumors derived from the surface 
epithelium of normal ovaries express TLR-4, which leads 
to NF-κB inhibitor (IkB) degradation and the activation 
of NF-κB for its proinflammatory responses. The MyD88 
pathway, a downstream signal of TLR-4, is reported to be 
essential for LPS-induced ovarian tumor growth. 
34 The tumor 
growth and survival could be due to the interaction between 
the inducible HspA1 A from ovarian cancer cells with TLR-4 
expressed on the neutrophil surface. These neutrophils 
enhance the production of reactive oxygen species and induce 
tumor progression as well as tumor lysis. </p>

<p>149   Paclitaxel has been the drug of choice for the treatment 
of ovarian cancer. A recent study has proven the associa-
tion of MyD88 expression with paclitaxel resistance, and 
paclitaxel-induced proinflammatory cytokine release. </p>

<p>34   Paclitaxel resistance is probably due to the activation 
of the protein kinase B (Akt) survival pathways and the 
expression of the antiapoptotic protein X-linked inhibitor 
of apoptosis protein (XIAP) following TLR-4 ligation. </p>

<p>34,150   The tumors have been found to be resistant to paclitaxel, a 
TLR-4 ligand, but not to carboplatin. 
34 Another laboratory 
finding has suggested that five ovarian cancer (OVCAR3, </p>

<p>SKOV3, AD10, A2780, CP70) cells with TLR-4 liga-
tion induced IL-1 receptor-associated kinase (IRAK)-4 
activation, c-Jun phosphorylation, NF-κB activation, 
and IL-8, IL-6, VEGF, and monocyte chemotactic pro-
tein-1 (MCP)-1 production, all of which promote tumor 
survival and chemoresistance. 
148 These findings suggest 
that further research on the role of TLR-4 in relation to 
management and chemotherapy for ovarian cancer should 
be carried out. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in cervical cancer </p>

<p>The female reproductive tract is constantly exposed to patho-
gens and carcinogens. Cervical cancer is one of the most 
common cancers closely linked to infection and inflammation. 
Human papillomavirus (HPV) has been identified as the lead-
ing cause of cervical cancer. HPV cervical infection results in 
cervical morphological lesions ranging from normal to invasive 
cancer. 
151 The presence of other infectious agents, such as bac-
teria, protozoa, and viruses, in the female genital tract induce 
the inflammation and cancer. 
152 A multi-center case-control 
study revealed that Chlamydia trachomatis infection induced 
the cervical cancer. 
153 Also, pathogenic Escherichia coli and 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection, but not the nonpathogenic 
Lactobacillus reuteri infection, caused the upregulation of 
TLR-4 in cervical cancer cells. 
154 In human cervical cancer 
(HeLa) cells, TLR-4 was found to be the highest expressed TLR, 
more than 100 times higher compared with the other TLRs. </p>

<p>126   This observation provides proof of the linkage between TLR-4 
and the progression of cervical cancer. 
Unlike other studies linking higher levels of TLR-4 with 
cancer, it was found that TLR-4 is downregulated in cervi-
cal intraepithelial neoplasia patients compared with healthy 
women. TLR-4 expression was found to decrease as the 
histopathologic grade of cervical intraepithelial neoplasia 
increased. TLR-4 expression was found to be inversely 
proportional (P,0.001) with the expression of p16INK4A, 
a marker of high-risk HPV infection. 
155,156 There are limited 
studies that conclude on the role of TLR-4 in cervical can-
cer progression; thus, the TLR-4 Thr399Ile polymorphism 
(P=0.044, OR=2.51, 95% CI: 1.03−6.12) was, again, found 
to be significantly associated with early stages of cervical 
cancers among North Indian women. 
157 Therefore, further 
research is needed to fully understand the role of TLR-4 in 
cervical cancer. </p>

<p>TLR-4 in prostate cancer </p>

<p>Prostate cancer is one of the most common causes of mor-
bidity and mortality in men. Prostate epithelial cells are </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1583 </p>

<p>Should a TLR-4 agonist or antagonist be designed to treat cancer? </p>

<p>actively involved in inflammatory processes. 
158 Higher levels 
of proinflammatory cytokines, produced through TLR-3, -4, 
and -9 downstream signaling pathways, were observed in 
the prostate tissues of cancer patients. In this study, TLR-3 
-4 and -9 were highly expressed in prostate cancer tissues 
but not in benign tissues. Only TLR-3 levels, and not TLR-4 
or TLR-9 levels, were found to have statistical significance 
(P=0.016) with levels of preoperative serum prostate-specific 
antigen, in prostate cancer patients. </p>

<p>159   However, in vitro studies have shown the expression of 
higher levels of TLR-4 on human prostate adenocarcinoma 
(DU-145) cells and its activation, leading to NF-κB and 
proinflammatory cytokine production through the MyD88-
dependent pathway. 
160 Also, TLR-4 activation was 
found to increase the proangiogenic factor (VEGF) and 
immunosuppressive cytokine (TGF-β1) secretion in human 
prostate adenocarcinoma (PC3) cells. 
161 Further, a knockdown 
of TLR-4 in PC3 cells resulted in the reduction of tumor cell 
migration and invasion. 
162 These results support the negative 
impact of TLR-4 upregulation in prostate cancer. 
In addition, single nucleotide polymorphism in the 
TLR-4 gene is suspected to be associated with the risk of 
prostate carcinoma. 
163 The sequence variant (11381 G/C, 
also known as rs11536889) in the 3′-untranslated region 
of the TLR-4 gene was found to be higher in patients with 
prostate carcinoma, in studies conducted on 1,383 Swedish 
patients 
164 and 157 Korean patients. 
165 In one study, a 
significantly higher risk of prostate cancer (OR: 1.26; 
95% CI: 1.01−1.57) was detected among men who had 
a single nucleotide polymorphism of TLR-4 (GC or CC) 
compared with the wild-type genotype (GG). 
164 However, 
other studies found no association of prostate cancer (OR: 
1.01; 95% CI: 0.79−1.29) with this rs11536889 sequence 
variant of TLR-4; 
166,167 one of these, a study involving 700 
prostate cancer patients found that homozygosity of the 
variant alleles of these eight single-nucleotide polymor-
phisms of TLR-4 including rs2149356 were found to have 
a lower risk of prostate cancer. 
166 A case-control study of 
506 incident advanced prostate cancer patients found two 
single nucleotide polymorphisms of TLR-4 (rs10759932 
and rs2149356) were associated with a higher cancer 
risk. 
167 Nevertheless, Lindstrom et al have suggested that 
the association of TLR-4 with prostate cancer risk is a 
chance finding and that to ascertain the relationship, large 
sample sizes are needed. 
168 The inconsistent findings of the 
association of genetic polymorphism of TLRs with cancer 
progression clearly supports the need for further investiga-
tion in this field. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The activation of TLR-4 is required for host defense against 
gram-negative bacteria. However, TLR-4 activation may be 
a double-edged sword, with both antitumor and protumor 
responses. The general expression of TLR-4 by all the tumor 
cells, suggesting TLR-4 signaling, may be continually acti-
vated and contribute to tumor initiation, progression, and 
also invasion. Tumor progression involves TLR-4-mediated 
irregular and uninhibited production of proinflammatory 
cytokines, chemokines, and also immunosuppressive cytok-
ines; suggesting that the discovery of TLR-4 antagonists 
might be an ideal strategy to treat cancer. However, TLR-4 
antagonists could pose the risk of the compromise of host 
immunity. Hence, it is a scientific dilemma whether a TLR-4 
agonist or antagonist should be targeted for the treatment 
of cancer. Further studies need to be carried out to fully 
elucidate the effects of TLR-4 agonists and antagonists in 
various cancers. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Authors wish to thank International Medical University for 
financial support (IMU 226/2010). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Mai et al </p>



<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Mai et al </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open access 
journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>