<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3575563" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Introduction: Tamoxifen is associated with a twofold increased risk of 
thromboembolic events. Third generation aromatase inhibitors (AIs), </p>

<p>Andreas Jokuszies 1 
Christine Radtke 1 </p>

<p>such as letrozole, anastrozole, and exemestane have therefore replaced </p>

<p>Christopher Betzler 1 </p>

<p>tamoxifen in the adjuvant therapy of hormone receptor-positive breast </p>

<p>Ludwik Branski 1 </p>

<p>cancer. A retrospective review was performed in patients who underwent 
delayed microvascular breast reconstruction and received tamoxifen </p>

<p>Robert Krämer 1 </p>

<p>at the time of surgery in order to assess the risk of both minor and 
major flap complications including thromboembolic events. </p>

<p>Peter M. Vogt 1 </p>

<p>Patients and methods: Twenty-nine patients who underwent delayed 
microsurgical breast reconstruction with autologous tissue between </p>

<p>1 Department of Plastic, Hand 
and Reconstructive Surgery, </p>

<p>2006 and 2012 were included in the study. The overall complication 
rates were compared between patients who did versus those who did 
not receive tamoxifen at the time of microsurgical breast reconstruction. </p>

<p>Hannover Medical School, 
Hannover, Germany </p>

<p>Results: Breast reconstruction was performed with a DIEP flap in 
25 patients and with a TRAM flap in 4 patients. Overall, the complication 
rate was 37.9% (n=11) consisting of 5 major (including one total flap 
loss) and 6 minor complications. In patients receiving tamoxifen (n=5), 
we observed one minor complication and one major complication with 
a total flap loss due to thrombus formation at the anastomosis site. In 
one patient pulmonary embolism occurred without association to 
tamoxifen. The number of thromboembolic events was equivalent in 
both groups (p=0.642). No increase of major (p=0.858) or minor 
(p=0.967) complications in the tamoxifen group could be observed. 
Taking the overall complication rate into account there was no statistic-
ally difference between the two groups (p=0.917). 
Conclusion: In our study we could not observe an increased risk for 
thromboembolic events in patients receiving tamoxifen while undergoing 
autologous microvascular breast reconstruction. </p>

<p>Keywords: Tamoxifen, breast cancer, adjuvant therapy, microvascular 
breast reconstruction </p>

<p>Zusammenfassung </p>

<p>Aromatasehemmer der dritten Generation haben mittlerweile Tamoxifen 
in der neoadjuvanten und adjuvanten Therapie des hormonrezeptor-
positiven Brustkrebses postmenopausaler Frauen abgelöst. Tamoxifen 
ist mit einem ca. zweifach erhöhten Risiko für thrombembolische 
Komplikationen (tiefe Beinvenenthrombose, Lungenembolie) assoziiert. 
Vor dem Hintergrund einer aktuellen und im Februar 2012 im Journal 
of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery erschienenen retrospektiven 
Studie mit Nachweis einer erhöhten Komplikationsrate freier Lappen-
transplantate zur Brustrekonstruktion unter Tamoxifen-Einnahme haben 
wir unser Patientenkollektiv nach mikrochirurgischer Brustrekonstruk-</p>

<p>1/5 
GMS German Medical Science 2013, Vol. 11, ISSN 1612-3174 </p>

<p>Research Article </p>

<p>OPEN ACCESS </p>

<p>tion retrospektiv auf Minor-und Major-Komplikationen einschließlich 
thrombembolischer Ereignisse insbesondere vor dem Hintergrund einer 
perioperativen Tamoxifeneinnahme untersucht. Eingeschlossen wurden 
insgesamt 29 Patientinnen nach mikrochirurgischer autologer Brustre-
konstruktion. Es wurden mikrovaskuläre Lappenkomplikationen und 
Lappenverluste von Patientinnen ohne und mit Einnahme von Tamoxifen 
und Aromatasehemmern zum Zeitpunkt der mikrochirurgischen Brust-
rekonstruktion verglichen. 25 Patientinnen (86,2%) erhielten eine DIEP-
Lappenplastik und 4 (13,8%) eine TRAM-Lappenplastik. Fernerhin ver-
glichen wir die Rate allgemeiner thrombembolischer Ereignisse unter 
Berücksichtigung sonstiger Nebendiagnosen und Risikofaktoren. 
Von insgesamt 29 Patientinnen standen zum Zeitpunkt der mikrovas-
kulären Brustrekonstruktion 3 unter einer Aromatasehemmer-Therapie 
und 5 unter einer Tamoxifen-Therapie. Insgesamt traten in 11 Fällen 
(37,9%) postoperative Komplikationen auf, in 5 Fällen handelte es sich 
hierbei um Major-Komplikationen (mit einem Lappenverlust) und in 
6 Fällen um Minorkomplikationen. 
Unter Tamoxifeneinnahme kam es in einem Fall zu einer Minorkompli-
kation, und in einem anderen Fall zu einem thrombembolisch bedingten 
Lappenverlust. 
Insgesamt kam es postoperativ zu einem thrombembolischen Ereignis 
in Form einer Lungenembolie ohne Assoziation zur Tamoxifen-Therapie. 
Die Anzahl thrombembolischer Ereignisse stellten sich mit und ohne 
Tamoxifen-Einnahme im Rahmen der Mamma-Rekonstruktion durch 
freie DIEP-oder TRAM-Lappenplastik als äquivalent dar (p=0,642). 
Weder die Komplikationsraten an Major-Komplikationen (p=0,858) 
noch an Minor-Komplikationen (p=0,967) waren unter Tamoxifen-Ein-
nahme signifikant erhöht. Somit zeigte sich auch die allgemeine Kom-
plikationsrate zwischen beiden Gruppen als nicht signifikant unterschied-
lich (p=0,917). </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Breast cancer is the most common malignancy affecting 
women in Germany with an annual incidence of approx-
imately 72,000 cases [1]. Early diagnosis and adequate 
therapy have led to a survival rate that exceeds 90% [2]. 
A broad arsenal of diagnostic and therapeutic ap-
proaches, such as early detection methods, sentinel 
lymph node biopsy, adjuvant radio-and chemotherapy, 
and breast-conserving surgery, have increased the overall 
survival rate in breast cancer patients [2]. In the case of 
estrogen-receptor-positive tumors, there is a strong 
evidence for recurrence and mortality reduction after five 
years of treatment with tamoxifen [3]. 
Third-generation aromatase inhibitors (AIs) are the pre-
ferred treatment for hormone receptor-positive breast 
cancer in postmenopausal women. They suppress aro-
matase activity by reversible (anastrozole and letrozole) 
or irreversible (exemestane) binding to the aromatase 
enzyme [4], [5]. They are associated with fewer adverse 
events than former generations, which includes hot 
flushes, loss of libido, vaginal dryness, fatigue, joint stiff-
ness, arthralgias and loss of bone mineral density with 
subsequent increased risk of fracture [4], [5]. 
In contrast to the aforementioned AIs, tamoxifen, a select-
ive estrogen receptor modulator, is known to be associ-
ated with increased rates of thromboembolic events, in-
cluding deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism </p>

<p>[6]. Therefore third generation aromatase inhibitors (AIs) 
have replaced Tamoxifen in the adjuvant therapy of hor-
mone receptor-positive breast cancer [7]. De Pinho 
Pessoa et al. showed a tamoxifen-induced intima hyper-
plasia in rats, and many clinical studies describe an in-
creased risk for venous and arterial thrombosis under 
tamoxifen therapy [8], [9], [10], [11]. 
The Deep Inferior Epigastric Perforator or DIEP flap can 
be considered a gold standard for immediate or delayed 
breast reconstruction with free tissue transfer. For pa-
tients in which perforator vessels are difficult to dissect, 
the free Transverse Rectus Abdominis Myocutaneus or 
TRAM flap still represents a viable option. In any case, 
the success of free tissue transfer depends particularly 
on a patent venous and arterial anastomosis. A thrombo-
sis within the anastomosed vessels leads to flap 
compromise or flap failure. 
The current study assesses whether tamoxifen application 
is associated with a greater risk for microvascular flap 
complications in patients undergoing microvascular breast 
reconstruction. We reviewed minor and major complica-
tions in patients after delayed microvascular breast re-
construction, including thromboembolic events. </p>

<p>2/5 
GMS German Medical Science 2013, Vol. 11, ISSN 1612-3174 </p>

<p>Jokuszies et al.: Is tamoxifen associated with an increased risk for ... </p>

<p>Table 1: Comorbidities in patients receiving and not receiving tamoxifen </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>All patients undergoing free microvascular tissue transfer 
for breast reconstruction after breast cancer related 
mastectomy between 2006 and 2012 at a single Plastic 
Surgery Department were reviewed. Deep Inferior Epigas-
tric Perforator and TRAM flaps are routinely performed 
for delayed breast reconstruction at this department. 
Patients were divided in the following groups: </p>

<p>• Tamoxifen group: patients who took tamoxifen during 
the month before breast reconstruction. 
• No tamoxifen (control) group: Patients who had never 
used tamoxifen or who had not taken tamoxifen during 
the month before breast reconstruction </p>

<p>Complications were divided into minor and major compli-
cations. Minor complications were defined as seroma, 
hematoma and fat necrosis without compromised flap 
perfusion. Major complications were defined as flap 
compromise due to venous congestion or arterial insuffi-
ciency at the anastomosis site and thrombosis of the 
microvascular bed with the need for immediate reexplo-
ration to prevent partial or total flap loss. Furthermore, 
deep venous thrombosis and pulmonary embolism were 
defined as major complications. Data analyis was per-
formed using the Chi-square-test. A p-value less than 0.05 
was considered statistically significant. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistical 
software package <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0</rs> for Windows (SPSS Inc., Chicago, 
Ill, USA) was used for statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Twenty-nine patients who underwent breast reconstruc-
tion with free tissue transfer between 2006 and 2012 
were included in the study. A total of 5 patients received 
tamoxifen during the month before surgery (tamoxifen </p>

<p>group), 24 patients received no tamoxifen (no tamoxifen 
group). Three patients in the latter group received an 
aromatase inhibitor. A DIEP flap was used in 25 patients 
and a TRAM flap in 4 patients. Table 1 outlines the 
demographics of the two groups. A total of 11 complica-
tions, all of which occurred in patients with a DIEP flap 
breast reconstruction, were recorded. These 11 compli-
cations were divided into 5 major complications, including 
one case of complete flap loss, and 6 minor complica-
tions. Two complications occurred in the tamoxifen group 
and 9 complications were recorded in the no tamoxifen 
group, including a systemic event in terms of pulmonary 
embolism. No significant differences between the groups 
were observed in terms of cardiovascular comorbidities 
(p=0.436). The risk for thromboembolic (p=0.642) occur-
rence of major (p=0.858) and minor complications 
(p=0.967) events also did not differ significantly between 
the groups. All results are summarized in Figure 1. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study was encouraged by the recently published work 
of Kelley et al. in the Journal of Plastic and Reconstructive 
Surgery who demonstrated an increased risk of microvas-
cular flap complications in patients undergoing microvas-
cular breast reconstruction [12]. In contrast to this study, 
we did not observe an increase of microvascular flap 
complications in patients receiving tamoxifen within 28 
days before microsurgical breast reconstruction [12]. 
Additionally, it appeared that tamoxifen did not increase 
the risk of pulmonary embolism during or after delayed 
microvascular breat reconstruction. Tamoxifen, a selective 
estrogen receptor modulator, uses multiple mechanisms 
to block the effects of estrogen on vascular endothelium. 
Estrogen, which is located in the vascular endothelium, 
mediates its beneficial vascular effects by binding to the </p>

<p>3/5 
GMS German Medical Science 2013, Vol. 11, ISSN 1612-3174 </p>

<p>Jokuszies et al.: Is tamoxifen associated with an increased risk for ... </p>

<p>Figure 1: Frequency distribution of complications in the tamoxifen and no tamoxifen group </p>

<p>nuclear estrogen receptor resulting in arterial and venous 
vasodilatation via nitric oxide and cyclooxygenase pathway 
[12], [13]. Furthermore, it activates intracellular pathways 
resulting in relaxation of vascular rings and inhibition of 
proliferation in cultured vascular smooth muscle cells 
[13]. As a consequence of this interaction, we also expect-
ed an increased rate of microvascular flap complications 
in the tamoxifen group but could not confirm this result 
in our patient population. This could partly be caused by 
the very small sample size of our study. One also has to 
consider the fact that in the retrospective study of Kelley 
et al. there was a significantly higher incidence of flap 
loss in patients with less common and technically more 
challenging flaps (e.g., superior and inferior gluteal artery 
perforator flap) compared with patients who received 
abdominal flaps. This aspect was emphasized by Joseph 
Disa in his discussion of Kelley's results, calling for retro-
spective and especially prospective studies to increase 
the level of evidence of the data [14]. 
Another result of Kelley's study we could not confirm was 
a higher risk of microvascular complications in patients 
with cardiovascular comorbidities receiving tamoxifen. In 
our study, patients receiving tamoxifen were younger than 
patients not receiving tamoxifen. Age did not affect the 
risk of complications in women receiving tamoxifen, al-
though it is known that premenopausal women are at 
high risk for adverse effects, whereas in postmenopausal 
women acute vascular responses decline with age [2], 
[15]. 
An analysis of multiple study variables, such as comorbid-
ities and surgical management, implies a much higher 
study population. We therefore also postulate the need 
for a prospective multi-center-study with a large amount 
of patiens that focuses on a few selected clinically signi-
ficant variables. Due to the fact that vascular responsive-
ness to estrogen may differ significantly between various 
vascular locations, it seems that this study should also 
focus on only one region of flap origin, such as the abdo-
men (DIEP-, TRAM-, SIEP flaps) [8], [16]. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In comparison to the retrospective study of Kelley et al. 
our study is limited by the small sample size. Although 
we could not show an increased risk of flap failure or 
other microvascular flap complications in patients receiv-
ing tamoxifen at the time of delayed microsurgical breast 
reconstruction, we support the suggestion of Kelley and 
colleagues to pause tamoxifen for one month before 
surgery in order to avoid potential adverse effects of 
tamoxifen on the vascular endothelium of a microsurgi-
cally reconstructed breast. This treatment algorithm is 
supported by our oncologists who do not expect any ad-
verse effects related to the pause in tamoxifen treatment. 
Further prospective and randomized studies have to ad-
dress the question when tamoxifen should be paused 
before surgery and when it should be given again. They 
should also focus on only one region of flap origin, such 
as the abdomen (DIEP-, TRAM-, SIEP flaps), in order to 
exclude further variables. While reconstructive and mi-
crosurgical methods are mostly standardized, anticoagu-
lative protocols and practices lack sufficient evidence. 
The influence of perioperative anticoagulative protocols 
on the outcome of free flap surgery should therefore also 
be considered in future studies. </p>

<p>Notes </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>The authors have no financial and personal relationships 
with other people or organisations that could inappropri-
ately influence (bias) this study. </p>

<p>4/5 
GMS German Medical Science 2013, Vol. 11, ISSN 1612-3174 </p>

<p>Jokuszies et al.: Is tamoxifen associated with an increased risk for ... </p>



<p>Corresponding author: 
Andreas Jokuszies, MD 
Department of Plastic, Hand and Reconstructive Surgery, 
Hannover Medical School, Carl-Neuberg-Str. 1, 
30625 Hannover, Germany, 
Phone: +49-(0)511-532-8864, 
Fax: +49-(0)511-532-8890 
jokuszies.andreas@mh-hannover.de </p>

<p>Please cite as 
Jokuszies A, Radtke A, Betzler C, Branski L, Krämer R, Vogt PM. Is 
tamoxifen associated with an increased risk for thromboembolic 
complications in patients undergoing microvascular breast 
reconstruction? GMS Ger Med Sci. 2013;11:Doc05. 
DOI: 10.3205/000173, URN: urn:nbn:de:0183-0001732 </p>

<p>This article is freely available from 
http://www.egms.de/en/journals/gms/2013-11/000173.shtml </p>

<p>Received: 2012-12-20 
Revised: 2013-02-09 
Published: 2013-02-18 </p>

<p>Copyright 
©2013 Jokuszies et al. This is an Open Access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/deed.en). You 
are free: to Share -to copy, distribute and transmit the work, provided 
the original author and source are credited. </p>

<p>5/5 
GMS German Medical Science 2013, Vol. 11, ISSN 1612-3174 </p>

<p>Jokuszies et al.: Is tamoxifen associated with an increased risk for ... </p>

</text></tei>