<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3044586" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>INTRODUCTION: Echocardiographic, electrocardiographic and other cardiorespiratory variables can change during 
weaning from mechanical ventilation. </p>

<p>OBJECTIVES: To analyze changes in cardiac function, using Doppler echocardiogram, in critical patients during 
weaning from mechanical ventilation, using two different weaning methods: pressure support ventilation and T-
tube; and comparing patient subgroups: success vs. failure in weaning. </p>

<p>METHODS: Randomized crossover clinical trial including patients under mechanical ventilation for more than 48 h 
and considered ready for weaning. Cardiorespiratory variables, oxygenation, electrocardiogram and Doppler 
echocardiogram findings were analyzed at baseline and after 30 min in pressure support ventilation and T-tube. 
Pressure support ventilation vs. T-tube and weaning success vs. failure were compared using ANOVA and Student's 
t-test. The level of significance was p,0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS: Twenty-four adult patients were evaluated. Seven patients failed at the first weaning attempt. No 
echocardiographic or electrocardiographic differences were observed between pressure support ventilation and T-
tube. Weaning failure patients presented increases in left atrium, intraventricular septum thickness, posterior wall 
thickness and diameter of left ventricle and shorter isovolumetric relaxation time. Successfully weaned patients had 
higher levels of oxygenation. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION: No differences were observed between Doppler echocardiographic variables and electrocardio-
graphic and other cardiorespiratory variables during pressure support ventilation and T-tube. However cardiac 
structures were smaller, isovolumetric relaxation time was larger, and oxygenation level was greater in successfully 
weaned patients. </p>

<p>Weaning from mechanical ventilation (MV) involves 
changes in the interaction between patient and ventilator. 
During weaning, the support provided by the ventilator is 
reduced, while the patient progressively takes over the 
work of breathing. 
1 Changes associated with transition from 
MV to spontaneous ventilation overload the cardiorespira-
tory system with increases in: venous return, left ventricle </p>

<p>(LV) afterload, O 2 consumption and catecholamine secre-
tion. 
The return of spontaneous breathing can increase 
myocardial O 2 demand and the product of heart rate 6 
arterial blood pressure by as much as 35%, which can lead 
to myocardial ischemia. However, this increase was not 
associated with weaning failure. 
2-4 A study of 15 patients 
with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease who failed 
during weaning from MV demonstrated that, during the 
first 10 min of spontaneous breathing, there was an increase 
in cardiac index (CI), heart rate (HR), central venous 
pressure (CVP) and arterial blood pressure (BP). 
5 An 
increase in pulmonary capillary wedge pressure (PCWP) 
from 8 to 25 mmHg was associated with evidence of acute 
respiratory failure due to increased preload. 
5 After 1 week 
of treatment with diuretics, these patients were weaned </p>

<p>Copyright ß 2011 CLINICS -This is an Open Access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-
commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(1):107-111 
DOI:10.1590/S1807-59322011000100019 </p>



<p>successfully. 
5 There is evidence that 6-10% of patients 
exhibit electrocardiographic findings of cardiac ischemia 
while being weaned, mainly those with coronary artery 
disease. </p>

<p>5   Echocardiography is being used routinely in some 
intensive care units (ICUs). It permits direct observation of 
all cardiac structures and the patient's hemodynamic status, 
allowing immediate intervention related to volume replace-
ment and the use of inotropic agents. 
6,7 In patients on MV, 
its use can explain some cardiac morphological and 
functional analyses that may influence weaning from MV, 
particularly when weaning is difficult or there is refractory 
hypoxemia that cannot be explained by lung disease alone. </p>

<p>8   Nevertheless, there are few descriptions in the literature of 
bedside studies of these cardiorespiratory changes during 
weaning from MV using echocardiography. </p>

<p>9,10   The objective of this study was to analyze changes in 
cardiac function using Doppler echocardiogram in critical 
patients in a general ICU during weaning from MV using 
pressure support ventilation (PSV) and T-tube, and to 
compare a subgroup of patients: success vs. failure during 
the weaning trial. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This study included adult patients (18 years or more) 
admitted to the adult general ICU of a hospital requiring 
invasive MV for at least 48 h and considered ready for 
weaning by the medical team. It was a randomized 
crossover clinical trial aiming to study changes in echocar-
diographic cardiac function variables (both systolic and 
diastolic) and other cardiorespiratory and electrocardio-
graphic variables related to weaning from MV during two 
methods of weaning (PSV and T-tube). The research 
protocol was approved by the appropriate research ethics 
committee. 
All patients were hemodynamically stable with normal 
central blood pressure values, conscious (Glasgow scale 
$13), with adequate gaseous exchange (O 2 saturation 
$95%, fraction of inspired oxygen (FiO 2 ) #40% and positive 
end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) = 5, with pulmonary radi-
ological characteristics as in baseline conditions, no acidosis 
or alkalosis), normal electrolyte levels and the presence of 
respiratory drive. Informed consent was signed by the 
patients and/or family members. Exclusion criteria 
included hemodynamic instability, severe intracranial dis-
ease and barotrauma. 
The sequence in which the methods were implemented 
was determined by randomly selecting sealed envelopes. 
This randomization was carried out by the duty physician 
before the patient was enrolled in the protocol. Patients 
were submitted to a baseline assessment and then placed on 
the first method of weaning for 30 min. After a rest period of 
30 min, patients were submitted to the other method for 
30 min. 
One weaning method was T-tube, in which patients made 
the inspiratory and expiratory effort unaided, receiving 
oxygen at 5 L/min. The other method was PSV in which 
patients breathing was aided by equipment with graduated 
inspiratory pressure at an inspiratory level of 10 cmH 2 O. 
This PSV level is routinely used in the ICU during weaning 
trials. The humidification system used was heat-and 
moisture-exchanging (HME) filters. </p>

<p>The weaning protocol was interrupted if the patient 
exhibited: oxygen arterial saturation (SaO 2 ) ,88%, oxygen 
arterial pressure (PaO 2 ) ,60-55 mmHg; respiratory rate (f) 
.35-38 rpm or increased by 50%; HR .140 bpm or 
increased by 20%; systolic blood pressure .180 mmHg or 
,90 mmHg or increased/reduced by 20%; and agitation, 
diaphoresis or a reduced level of consciousness. This was 
considered failure of the weaning trial. 
Clinical status, respiratory mechanics and arterial blood 
gas analyses, electrocardiograms (ECG) and echocardio-
grams were performed during the trial period (at baseline 
and at the 30th minute of each ventilation mode). If 
the patient showed signs of decompensation before the 
predetermined time, the assessment was performed 
immediately and the patient placed back on MV with 
the same parameters used at the beginning of the weaning 
protocol. 
Clinical assessment included data on identification, diag-
nosis, Acute Physiologic and Chronic Health Evaluation 
(APACHE) II score for the first 24 h after admission, level of 
consciousness, preexisting heart disease, use of sedative 
drugs and opioids, type of mechanical ventilator used, 
ventilation mode, MV parameters and arterial blood gas 
analysis. Patients were also monitored non-invasively: BP, 
HR, f and SaO 2 using a multiparameter monitor (Philips; 
USA). Ventilation mechanics were monitored using a 
VENTRAK 1500 (Novametrix Medical Systems, Walling-
ford, CT, USA) connected to a PC Pentium 100 using 
software provided by Novametrix for data storage and later 
analysis. The following parameters were analyzed: f (rpm), 
tidal volume (V T = mL), minute volume (Ve = L/min), 
rapid-shallow breathing index (RSBI or f/V T ) and airway 
occlusion pressure (P 0.1 ). 
Cardiac performance was assessed using 12-lead ECG 
and echocardiogram using a Caris ultrasound machine 
(Esaote Spa, Genova, Italy) with pulse, continuous and 
color Doppler, and a 2.5-3.5 MHz transducer, coupled to a 
17-inch Sony Cpd-e200 monitor. The following data were 
analyzed: Mode M; bidimensional mode; spectral and 
tissue Doppler and myocardial performance index (Tei 
index). Ejection fraction was determined using the Teicholz 
method as it offers greater accuracy than the Cubo method, 
has less interobserver variation and is less dependent on an 
optimal echocardiographic window to obtain measure-
ments than the Simpson method. 
11 Doppler echocardio-
graphy was used to assess LV systolic and diastolic 
function and structural abnormalities. Echocardiogram 
was always performed by the same cardiologist. Echo-
cardiogram and ECG were done at baseline and in the 30th 
minute of each method after resting for 30 min between 
methods. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Measurements obtained during PSV and T-tube were 
compared. Patients were classified into two groups based on 
weaning success or failure. 
Analyses were performed with the aid of <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS</rs>) <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">12.0</rs>, and results 
were presented as mean¡standard deviation or median 
(interquartile 25-75). Comparisons were made using 
Student's t-test for paired and unpaired samples and 
analysis of variance (ANOVA) for repeated measures. The 
level of significance was set at p,0.05. </p>

<p>Echocardiography and weaning from ventilation 
Schifelbain LM et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(1):107-111 </p>



<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>During the period between December 2005 and August 
2007, 24 patients were assessed. Thirteen (58%) patients 
were male, and the mean age was 53¡20 years. Mean 
APACHE score was 18¡14. Median time on MV was 13 (8- 21) days and length of stay in the ICU was 22 (13-35) days. 
Eight patients (33%) had neurological diseases, and the 
remaining patients had been admitted for sepsis, general 
postoperative care, neoplasms and respiratory infections. 
Ten patients (41.7%) had a history of hypertension and/or 
thoracic pain, with no history of myocardial infarction or 
previous left ventricular failure. Eleven patients were 
tracheostomized. Seven patients failed during the weaning 
trial. Two of them died and five were weaned later. Of the 
successfully weaned patients, only one was reintubated 
after 5 days, and one died because of a lymphoma. The 
individual characteristics of the patients assessed are 
described in Table 1. 
At baseline, all patients were on MV settings, with PSV at 
15-20 cmH 2 O, PEEP at 5 cmH 2 O and a FiO 2 of 0.4. With 
respect to the variables analyzed at baseline and at the end 
of 30 min using Doppler echocardiogram, the size of the left 
atrium (LA), the interventricular septum, the posterior wall 
and LV diastolic diameter (LVD) were all significantly 
smaller among patients who were successfully weaned from 
MV at the first attempt. Isovolumetric relaxation time 
(IVRT) was significantly shorter among patients whose 
weaning failed. The Tei index values were slightly higher 
among patients who failed, but without statistical signifi-
cance (Table 2). 
The mean Doppler echocardiography results during the 
two weaning modes (PSV, T-tube) were very similar, and no 
differences were observed when comparing the outcome 
(success vs. failure in Table 3). Results observed during PSV 
and T-tube were similar to values observed at baseline. </p>

<p>Twelve-lead electrocardiograms did not detect any differ-
ences between baseline assessment and weaning modes 
assessed. No changes in ST segment were detected during 
continuous cardiac monitoring. 
There were no statistical differences for cardiorespiratory 
assessment during baseline and weaning trials. However, 
patients whose weaning was successful showed higher 
PaO 2 and SaO 2 (133¡30 vs. 103¡33, p = 0.04; and 98¡1.1 
vs. 96¡1.9, p = 0.01). We also observed a tendency to a lower 
f/V T (75¡39 vs. 91¡19, p = 0.13) and to a lower P 0.1 
(0.46¡0.17 vs. 0.62¡0.09, p = 0.4) during T-tube in this 
group of patients. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>There were no differences between the Doppler echocar-
diography variables during the two weaning methods. The 
analysis of the Doppler echocardiograms demonstrated that 
the sizes of cardiac structures were significantly smaller in 
patients who were successfully weaned from MV at the first 
attempt, whereas IVRT was significantly shorter among 
patients whose weaning failed. Considering cardiorespira-
tory variables, PaO 2 and SaO 2 were significantly higher 
among successfully weaned patients with no other sig-
nificant differences. 
Several research teams have investigated prognostic 
indices for weaning success, including f/V T ratio 
12-14 and 
P 0.1 . 
15 The lower the f/V T , the greater the chance of 
successfully withdrawing MV. 
12,14,16 In our study, f/V T 
was higher and P 0.1 was lower among patients who could 
not be weaned, although without statistical difference. 
However, in agreement with the literature, successfully 
weaned patients showed better oxygenation levels. </p>

<p>15   Physiological changes associated with the transition from 
MV to spontaneous breathing involve an overload of the 
cardiorespiratory system: increased venous return (pre-
load), increased LV afterload, increase in O 2 consumption 
from 15% to 25% and increased secretion of catecholamines. </p>

<p>Table 1 -Clinical characteristics of the patients assessed. </p>

<p>Age 
Sex 
APACHE II </p>

<p>Time on 
MV </p>

<p>Hypertension/ 
thoracic pain 
Outcome </p>

<p>57 
W 
22 
7 
Yes 
Success 
35 
W 
22 
8 
No 
Success 
65 
W 
18 
31 
Yes 
Failure 
90 
M 
24 
45 
No 
Failure 
27 
W 
11 
66 
No 
Success 
45 
M 
6 
4 
No 
Success 
32 
M 
19 
50 
Yes 
Success 
64 
M 
17 
12 
No 
Success 
51 
M 
23 
28 
Yes 
Failure 
66 
W 
32 
13 
No 
Success 
74 
W 
17 
11 
Yes 
Success 
27 
M 
21 
23 
Yes 
Failure 
68 
W 
24 
8 
No 
Success 
76 
M 
16 
16 
Yes 
Success 
51 
M 
6 
7 
Yes 
Success 
21 
M 
16 
15 
No 
Success 
22 
M 
19 
21 
No 
Success 
51 
W 
22 
19 
No 
Success 
34 
M 
2 
12 
No 
Failure 
45 
W 
22 
7 
No 
Success 
78 
M 
34 
11 
Yes 
Failure 
72 
M 
15 
14 
Yes 
Success 
63 
W 
12 
7 
No 
Success 
68 
M 
23 
13 
No 
Failure </p>

<p>APACHE = Acute Physiologic and Chronic Health Evaluation; M = man; 
MV = mechanical ventilation; W = woman. </p>

<p>Table 2 -Baseline Doppler echocardiographic assessment 
of the patient sample (mean¡SD). </p>

<p>Success (n = 17) 
Failure (n = 7) 
p* </p>

<p>LA (mm) 
34.4¡5.1 
41.9¡2.9 
0.001 
RV (mm) 
18.3¡3.2 
22.6¡6.3 
0.135 
LVS (mm) 
39.9¡4.4 
33.4¡7.1 
0.416 
LVD (mm) 
50.5¡4.7 
56.3¡5.3 
0.016 
SEP (mm) 
9.3¡1.5 
11.3¡0.8 
0.006 
PW (mm) 
9.3¡1.6 
11.3¡0.9 
0.006 
EF (%) 
70.2¡5.9 
69.6¡11.7 
0.900 
E (m/s) 
0.71¡0.14 
0.82¡0.29 
0.352 
A (m/s) 
0.76¡0.25 
0.67¡0.3 
0.444 
E/A Ra 
1.02¡0.39 
1.53¡0.98 
0.221 
IVRT (m/s) 
112¡31.4 
84.5¡20.8 
0.046 
DT (m/s) 
239¡72 
187¡43 
0.101 
E9 (m/s) 
0.09¡0.03 
0.13¡0.04 
0.053 
A9 (m/s) 
0.14¡0.12 
0.29¡0.36 
0.329 
E/E9 Ra 
8.25¡2.95 
7.24¡3.62 
0.480 
Tei index 
0.60¡0.18 
0.66¡0.46 
0.614 </p>

<p>A = peak velocity of A wave; A9 = A9 wave; DT = deceleration time; E = peak 
velocity of E wave; E9 = E9 wave; E/A Ra = E/A ratio; E/E9 Ra = E/E9 ratio; 
EF = ejection fraction; IVRT = isovolumetric relaxation time; LA = left 
atrium; LV = left ventricle; LVD = left ventricle diastolic diameter; LVS = left 
ventricle systolic diameter; Tei index = myocardial performance index; 
PW = posterior wall; RV = right ventricle; SEP = interventricular septum. 
* Unpaired t-test. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(1):107-111 
Echocardiography and weaning from ventilation 
Schifelbain LM et al. </p>



<p>In patients with preexisting heart disease (coronary artery 
disease and LV insufficiency), these physiological changes 
associated with spontaneous breathing can trigger LV 
failure, which in turn may lead to respiratory failure and 
unsuccessful weaning. 
2,3,17 In our study, there were no 
differences in cardiorespiratory variables analyzed by 
echocardiography between the two weaning methods, 
suggesting equivalency between both methods of weaning 
in the population studied. Our results are in disagreement 
with recent data published in the literature. 
10,18 Caille et al. </p>

<p>10   analyzed weaning patients and observed that echocardio-
gram can detect T-tube-induced changes in the central 
hemodynamic status, helping to identify patients at high 
risk of cardiac-related weaning failure. Cabello et al., </p>

<p>18   monitoring weaning patients with a Swan-Ganz catheter, 
also observed differences in cardiovascular responses 
comparing T-tube with PSV. It is important to consider 
that, in these studies, there was a large number of patients 
with cardiac diseases and/or signs of cardiac failure. In our 
sample, patients were under MV for a long period of time, 
but there was no evidence of preexisting defined heart 
disease or LV failure. 
The baseline LA diameter, intraventricular septum thick-
ness, posterior wall thickness and LV diastolic diameter 
were significantly larger among patients whose weaning 
failed. It has been demonstrated that increased LA size 
could cause an increased filling pressure due to reduced LV 
compliance or diastolic dysfunction. There is evidence in the 
literature suggesting that this increase in the size of the LA 
measured by echocardiography could be predictive of 
cardiovascular outcomes even in individuals without atrial 
pathologies or valve disease. </p>

<p>19,20   We also observed in our study that the value of IVRT was 
significantly lower among failing weaning patients. Also, 
the pressure gradient represented by the deceleration time, 
which normally changes in line with IVRT, was lower, 
although not statistically significant among patients 
who failed. The deceleration time is characteristically pro-
longed when relaxation is abnormal and becomes shorter 
when relaxation is rapid or high ventricular filling pressures 
occur. 
21 The IVRT can be influenced by factors including 
ischemia, hypoxemia and right ventricle overload (which 
prolong the time) and blood volume status (indirect 
variation). Its absolute value is inversely related to 
PCWP, 
22 i.e. the lower the value of IVRT, the higher the 
PCWP. 
23 Our patients did not exhibit hypervolemia, 
which could have influenced the behavior of echocardio-
graphic measurements. The preload, assessed in terms 
of the E/E9 ratio measured by tissue Doppler, demon-
strated variation within normal limits (below 15), 
24 without 
any significant difference between the two groups of 
patients. 
Our research did not demonstrate electrocardiographic 
abnormalities at all assessment situations, suggesting less or 
no heart disease among these patients who were admitted 
predominantly as a result of neurological and infectious 
diseases, with only prior history of hypertension recorded. 
Research evaluation of weaning from MV has demonstrated 
cardiac ischemia mainly in patients with known coronary 
artery disease, and sometimes also in normal patients. </p>

<p>4,25-29   In an earlier study carried out by our team, ST segment 
abnormalities suggestive of myocardial ischemia were also 
observed on ECG during both methods of weaning, but in 
this previous study, a greater number of severe cardiac 
patients was included. </p>

<p>30   As limitations of this study, we have to consider that the 
number of patients evaluated was small. In addition, no 
severe ischemic heart or heart failure patients were 
included, which may explain the absence of ischemia and 
cardiac dysfunction during weaning. Another limitation is 
that, although no patient had clinical signs of cardiac failure, 
fluid balance or the use of diuretic drugs before the weaning 
trial were not recorded. </p>

<p>Table 3 -Mean Doppler echocardiogram results for 
minute 30 using PSV and T-Tube: weaning success vs. 
failure (mean¡SD). </p>

<p>PSV 
T-tube 
p* </p>

<p>LA (mm) 
Success 
33¡3.8 
34¡6 
Failure 
35¡3.2 
35¡2.6 
0.68 
RV (mm) 
Success 
18¡3.8 
18¡4.1 
Failure 
20¡5.7 
22¡2.7 
0.12 
LVS (mm) 
Success 
31¡4.4 
31¡4.1 
Failure 
32¡6.1 
31¡8.7 
0.32 
LVD (mm) 
Success 
51¡3.9 
51¡5.2 
Failure 
54¡6.2 
54¡7.7 
0.77 
SEP 
Success 
9¡1.9 
9¡1.8 
Failure 
11¡0.8 
11¡0.8 
0.81 
PW 
Success 
9¡1.6 
9¡2.3 
Failure 
11¡0.9 
11¡0.8 
0.83 
EF (%) 
Success 
70¡8.4 
69¡6.1 
Failure 
71¡10 
73¡10 
0.23 
E (m/s) 
Success 
0.70¡0.23 
0.80¡0.17 
Failure 
0.82¡0.22 
0.81¡0.24 
0.16 
A (m/s) 
Success 
0.77¡0.23 
0.76¡0.26 
Failure 
0.71¡0.23 
0.69¡0.22 
0.34 
E/A Ra 
Success 
1.12¡0.47 
1.15¡0.46 
Failure 
1.31¡0.65 
1.38¡0.84 
0.84 
IVRT (m/s) 
Success 
107¡24 
97¡17 
Failure 
84¡24 
88¡19 
0.21 
DT (m/s) 
Success 
233¡64 
215¡61 
Failure 
192¡36 
198¡35 
0.48 
E9 (m/s) 
Success 
0.105¡0.03 
0.102¡0.03 
Failure 
0.108¡0.03 
0.096¡0.03 
0.23 
A9 (m/s) 
Success 
0.121¡0.03 
0.140¡0.8 
Failure 
0.123¡0.04 
0.106¡0.03 
0.11 
E/E9 Ra 
Success 
7.92¡4.33 
8.54¡3.39 
Failure 
7.83¡2.37 
8.62¡1.84 
0.86 
Tei index 
Success 
0.61¡0.19 
0.53¡0.13 
Failure 
0.58¡0.20 
0.48¡0.12 
0.94 </p>

<p>A = peak velocity of A wave; A9 = A9 wave; DT = deceleration time; E = peak 
velocity of E wave; E9 = E9 wave; E/A Ra = E/A ratio; E/E9 Ra = E/E9 ratio; 
EF = ejection fraction; IVRT = isovolumetric relaxation time; LA = left 
atrium; LVD = left ventricle diastolic diameter; LVS = left ventricle systolic 
diameter; Tei index = myocardial performance index; PSV = pressure 
support ventilation; PW = posterior wall; SEP = interventricular septum. 
* ANOVA. </p>

<p>Echocardiography and weaning from ventilation 
Schifelbain LM et al. </p>

<p>CLINICS 2011;66(1):107-111 </p>



<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>In the present study, there were no differences in 
echocardiographic evaluation or in electrocardiographic 
and other cardiorespiratory variables comparing PSV and 
T-tube in this population of cardiac patients receiving MV 
for a long period of time. Weaning failure patients pre-
sented LA diameter, intraventricular septum thickness, 
posterior wall thickness and LV diameter significantly 
larger than weaning success patients. Further studies with 
a greater number of patients and including subjects with 
heart disease are necessary in order to clarify echocardio-
graphic changes during weaning from MV and differences 
between cardiac and non-cardiac patients. It seems that 
echocardiogram tests could be useful in identifying failure 
weaning patients in a subgroup of cardiac ones. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank the Cardiovascular Institute in Santa Maria/RS (ICARDIO) for 
assistance with Doppler echocardiography and ECG tests. </p>



<p>CLINICS 2011;66(1):107-111 
Echocardiography and weaning from ventilation 
Schifelbain LM et al. </p>



</text></tei>