<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3529531" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Relative changes in the dimensions of apical, lateral, and 
basal membranes control various morphogenesis processes 
(St Johnston and Sanson, 2011). For example, the constriction 
of the apical membrane in a group of epithelial cells leads to 
their invagination, a mechanism that is used in diverse devel-
opmental programs, such as Drosophila melanogaster gastru-
lation or neural tube formation in vertebrates. Although we are 
beginning to understand the molecular machinery controlling 
apical constriction (Harris, 2012; Levayer and Lecuit, 2012), it 
remains unclear how the formation of squamous and columnar 
epithelia is regulated. 
Morphogenesis of a columnar epithelium from cuboidal 
precursors involves the expansion of the lateral membrane. In 
contrast, formation of squamous epithelia requires shrinking of 
the lateral membrane and expansion of the apical and basal 
membranes. It is unclear how these changes in membrane size 
and cell shape are regulated. Previous studies suggest roles for 
cell junctions and the cytoskeleton. It has been shown that the 
reorganization of the microtubule cytoskeleton is involved in </p>

<p>the stretching of the Drosophila amnioserosa (Pope and Harris, 
2008). A potential role of actin-Myosin-based contractility in 
preventing cell stretching can be deduced from data in the Dro-
sophila follicular epithelium, where cells lacking Myosin func-
tion undergo a transition from a cuboidal to squamous cell 
shape (Wang and Riechmann, 2007). The same phenotype was 
observed when the function of adherens junctions is disturbed 
(Müller, 2000; Tanentzapf et al., 2000). The finding that com-
promised cell adhesion results in cell flattening suggests that 
squamous cell morphogenesis can be induced by reducing ad-
hesion between cells. This raises the possibility that epithelial 
cells control the size of their lateral membrane by regulating the 
abundance or localization of cell adhesion molecules. An in-
crease in the number of adhesion molecules could lead to an 
expansion of the lateral membrane, whereas their reduction al-
lows membrane shrinking. 
Two important protein families mediating cell adhesion 
are cadherins and immunoglobulin superfamily of cell adhesion 
molecules. A prominent member of the latter family is N-CAM 
(neural cell adhesion molecule) and its insect homologue Fas2 
(Fasciclin 2), which mediate homophilic interactions in the </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>egulation of epithelial cell shape, for example, 
changes in relative sizes of apical, basal, and lat-
eral membranes, is a key mechanism driving mor-
phogenesis. However, it is unclear how epithelial cells 
control the size of their membranes. In the epithelium of 
the Drosophila melanogaster ovary, cuboidal precursor 
cells transform into a squamous epithelium through a pro-
cess that involves lateral membrane shortening coupled 
to apical membrane extension. In this paper, we report 
a mutation in the gene Tao, which resulted in the loss of 
this cuboidal to squamous transition. We show that the </p>

<p>inability of Tao mutant cells to shorten their membranes 
was caused by the accumulation of the cell adhesion mol-
ecule Fasciclin 2, the Drosophila N-CAM (neural cell ad-
hesion molecule) homologue. Fasciclin 2 accumulation at 
the lateral membrane of Tao mutant cells prevented mem-
brane shrinking and thereby inhibited morphogenesis. In 
wild-type cells, Tao initiated morphogenesis by promoting 
Fasciclin 2 endocytosis at the lateral membrane. Thus, we 
identify here a mechanism controlling the morphogenesis 
of a squamous epithelium. </p>

<p>Tao controls epithelial morphogenesis by promoting 
Fasciclin 2 endocytosis </p>

<p>Juan Manuel Gomez, Ying Wang, and Veit Riechmann </p>

<p>Department of Cell and Molecular Biology, Medical Faculty Mannheim, Heidelberg University, D-68167 Mannheim, Germany </p>

<p>© 2012 Gomez et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 199 • NUMBER 7 • 2012 
1132 </p>

<p>cell polarity (Timm et al., 2003). Analysis of Tao in Drosophila 
revealed functions in controlling microtubule plus-end growth 
in cultured cells (Liu et al., 2010), in regulating apoptosis of 
germ cells in the embryo (Sato et al., 2007), and in the develop-
ment of the adult brain (King et al., 2011). Two recent studies 
show that Tao is also involved in growth regulation of ima-
ginal discs, in which Tao activates the Salvador-Warts-Hippo 
(SWH) pathway by phosphorylating Hippo kinase (Boggiano 
et al., 2011; Poon et al., 2011). Here, we report the generation of 
a Tao allele lacking kinase activity, which allowed us to study a 
new function of Tao in regulating morphogenesis of the follicu-
lar epithelium. Tao reduces lateral adhesion between epithelial 
cells by promoting Fas2 endocytosis. Decreased cell adhesion 
permits shrinking of the lateral membrane and initiates the mor-
phogenesis of the squamous epithelium. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Tao is required for follicle cell </p>

<p>morphogenesis </p>

<p>We have identified Tao protein in a biochemical screen for 
proteins that are phosphorylated by Par-1 (Riechmann and 
Ephrussi, 2004). To identify a possible function of Tao during 
Drosophila oogenesis, we performed an ethane methyl sulfo-
nate (EMS) screen, in which we generated one chromosome 
with a point mutation in the second exon of the Tao gene (Tao </p>

<p>eta </p>

<p>), 
resulting in a premature stop codon at aa 64. The predicted pro-
tein harbors only a 37-aa fragment of the kinase domain lacking 
its active site. As homozygous Tao 
eta mutants are lethal, we re-
combined the mutation onto a FLP recombination target (FRT) 
chromosome to generate genetic mosaics with the FRT/FLP 
technique (Xu and Rubin, 1993). Par-1 controls the establish-
ment of the anterior-posterior axis of the oocyte by polarizing 
the microtubule cytoskeleton, which is necessary for the local-
ization of Oskar to the posterior pole of the oocyte (Shulman 
et al., 2000; Tomancak et al., 2000). Surprisingly, neither Oskar 
localization nor microtubule polarity is affected in Tao mutant 
oocytes, indicating that Tao is not necessary for establishment 
of anterior-posterior polarity (Fig. S2 A). 
Closer inspection of egg chambers with Tao 
eta mutant 
cells revealed morphological defects in the follicular epithe-
lium, which become apparent during stage 8/9 when a mono-
layer of cuboidal precursors is transformed into a squamous 
anterior and a columnar posterior epithelium. Tao mutant cell 
clones in the anterior part of the epithelium fail to stretch and 
stay cuboidal (Fig. 1 A, left clone). Posterior clones show milder 
morphological defects, which are reflected by an increase in the 
length of the lateral membrane compared with wild-type cells 
(Fig. 1 A, right clone). To test whether Tao 
eta behaves as a loss-
of-function allele, we generated a chromosome with a small de-
letion that uncovers the entire open reading frame of Tao and 
two neighboring genes (see Materials and methods). Cell clones 
generated with this deletion show the same epithelial defects as 
Tao 
eta clones, indicating that Tao 
eta is indeed a loss-of-function 
allele (Fig. 1 B). 
To confirm that the morphogenesis defect is caused by 
loss of Tao function, we performed rescue experiments with </p>

<p>extracellular space. E-cadherin is a central component of the 
adherens junctions, the site of apicolateral cell contacts. The 
extracellular part of E-cadherin connects neighboring cells, 
whereas its intracellular part serves as an anchoring point for 
the actin cytoskeleton and several other proteins, including 
-Catenin (Harris and Tepass, 2010; Baum and Georgiou, 2011). 
Epithelial morphogenesis can be studied in the follicular 
epithelium of the Drosophila ovary. This organ is composed of 
follicles of different ages, which are subdivided into 14 differ-
ent developmental stages (Horne-Badovinac and Bilder, 2005). 
Follicles or egg chambers consist of an inner cyst of germline 
cells (made of 15 nurse cells and one oocyte) surrounded by a 
monolayered follicular epithelium with initially cuboidal-shaped 
cells (Fig. S1 A). During early oogenesis, the germline cyst 
grows in size, leading to a volume increase that is accommo-
dated by cell divisions in the epithelium. This changes after 
stage 6 when cell divisions cease because of the expression of 
Delta in the germline activating Notch signaling in the epithe-
lium (Deng et al., 2001; López-Schier and St Johnston, 2001). 
Although the germline cyst continues to increase its volume 
after stage 6, the epithelium undergoes morphogenesis and sub-
divides into an anterior squamous and a posterior columnar part 
(Fig. S1 B). As a result, egg chambers develop with a posterior 
columnar epithelium covering the oocyte and an anterior squa-
mous epithelium consisting of large and flat cells covering the 
nurse cells. 
Morphometric analysis and mechanical modeling suggest 
that the growth of the inner cyst is a critical force for the mor-
phogenesis of the squamous epithelium. Kolahi et al. (2009) 
propose a model in which the volume increase of the inner cyst 
exerts a tensile force on the outer epithelium inducing flattening 
of cells specifically in anterior epithelium. In the posterior epi-
thelium, this force is counteracted by the apical actin cytoskele-
ton, which is organized by -Spectrin and contracted by Myosin 
(Zarnescu and Thomas, 1999; Wang and Riechmann, 2007). 
Anterior cells are unable to counteract cyst pressure and flatten. 
A possible reason for their inability to resist pressure is the lo-
cally restricted disassembly of their adherens junctions at posi-
tions where three or four cells meet (Grammont, 2007). As the 
adherens junctions anchor the actin cytoskeleton, their local 
breakdown could destabilize the apical actin network and trig-
ger cell flattening (Kolahi et al., 2009). Adherens junction dis-
assembly proceeds from anterior to the middle region of the 
follicle concomitant with stretching, suggesting a critical role 
for squamous cell morphogenesis (Grammont, 2007). It has 
been shown that Notch signaling is required for adherens junc-
tion breakdown during stretching (Grammont, 2007), but other 
genes contributing to epithelial stretching are unknown. Here, 
we identify the gene Tao as a critical regulator for squamous 
cell morphogenesis. 
The Ser/Thr kinase Tao has been shown to activate the 
stress-responsive MAPK pathway in mammalian cell lines 
(Hutchison et al., 1998; Raman et al., 2007). Tao uses the same 
pathway in cultured hippocampal neurons to trigger endocyto-
sis of N-cadherin in dendritic spines (Yasuda et al., 2007). 
A biochemical study isolated Tao because of its ability to phos-
phorylate Par-1, a kinase regulating microtubule dynamics and </p>

<p> 
Tao controls epithelial morphogenesis • Gomez et al. </p>

<p>no cell proliferation after stage 6 as detected by phospho-
Histone H3 stainings (n = 51; Fig. S2, B-E). We therefore con-
clude that Tao is not acting via the SWH pathway in the follicu-
lar epithelium. We also ruled out that the morphogenesis defects 
in Tao mutant cells results from patterning defects in the fol-
licular epithelium by analyzing the localization of the cell fate 
specification markers Eya and phospho-Mad (Fig. S2, F-I). 
In mammalian cell lines, Tao activates the p38 signaling 
cascade in response to cellular stress (Hutchison et al., 1998; 
Raman et al., 2007). To test whether this signaling module is 
activated by Tao in the follicular epithelium, we analyzed the 
function of five kinases that were shown to act downstream of 
Tao. Neither cell clones for Mpk2D/p38a and Dsor nor double 
mutant clones for licorne and hemipterous showed defects in 
follicle cell morphology (Fig. S2, J-L). Moreover, expression 
of a dominant-negative form of p38b in the follicular epithelium 
did not produce defects in the follicular epithelium (unpub-
lished data). These data suggest that Tao is unlikely to regulate 
morphogenesis by activating the p38 cascade. 
As Tao regulates microtubule dynamics in mammalian 
and Drosophila cell lines (Timm et al., 2003; Liu et al., 2010), 
we examined whether Tao controls epithelial cell shape by 
acting on the cytoskeleton. Careful analysis of the microtubule 
cytoskeleton showed no differences in the organization of </p>

<p>an upstream activation sequence (UAS)-Tao transgene, which 
rescues lethality of homozygous Tao 
eta mutants when induced 
by the ubiquitous Tubulin-Gal4 driver line. The same trans-
gene is able to fully rescue the stretching process in the anterior 
epithelial cells with a follicle cell-specific driver (GR1-Gal4; 
Fig. 1 C). We analyzed the subcellular localization of Tao by 
expressing a HA fusion protein, which also rescues morpho-
genesis (Fig. 1 D). HA-Tao protein accumulates in the baso-
lateral cytoplasm and at the lateral membrane of the follicular 
epithelium (Fig. 1 I). </p>

<p>Tao regulates accumulation of polarity </p>

<p>proteins at the plasma membrane </p>

<p>We tested whether Tao controls epithelial morphogenesis by 
one of its known mechanism or pathways. It has been shown 
that Tao regulates the SWH pathway in imaginal discs (Meignin 
et al., 2007; Polesello and Tapon, 2007). In the follicular epithe-
lium, SWH signaling is involved in ceasing cell proliferation 
after stage 6 of oogenesis, and cell clones with loss of SWH 
activity show prolonged proliferation as well as aberrant local-
ization and delayed down-regulation of Notch. Moreover, SWH 
mutant clones express Fasciclin 3 and Eyes absent (Eya) ectopi-
cally after stage 6. Homozygous Tao 
eta clones, however, reveal 
a normal localization of Notch, Fasciclin 3, and Eya and show </p>

<p>Figure 1. Tao regulates epithelial cell shape and accumulation of membrane proteins. Egg chambers are shown harboring homozygous Tao mutant cell 
clones, which are marked by the absence of GFP. Follicles are stained with the indicated markers. Insets show enlarged areas of the region marked by the 
white frame. Blue dotted lines mark the border of the Tao mutant clones. (A-D) Stage 9 egg chambers. (A) Follicle with two Tao mutant cell clones in the 
anterior and posterior epithelium showing elongated epithelial cells and overaccumulation of Arm and DE-cadherin (DE-Cad). (B) Cell clones homozygously 
mutant for a deletion uncovering the open reading frame of the Tao gene (Df(1)14.1) showing elongated lateral membranes and overaccumulation of Arm. 
The bottom inset shows a magnified area of mutant cells, and the top inset shows wild-type cells for comparison. (C) Egg chamber in which the stretching 
defect and Arm accumulation in the anterior epithelium is rescued by expression of a GR1-Gal4-driven UAS-Tao transgene. (D) Rescue of the Tao stretching 
defect with a GR1-Gal4-driven UAS-HA-Tao transgene. On the left side of the inset, a Tao 
eta mutant clone is shown, which is rescued by Gal4-driven Tao 
expression. Note that cells stretch and that Fas2 is not detectable. (E-H) Stage 8 egg chambers. (E) Tao mutant cell clones showing the increased accumu-
lation of aPKC at the apical membrane (right insets). Levels of Dlg protein at the lateral membrane show no obvious increase (left insets). Tao mutant cells 
(top insets) have an elongated apical-basal axis. (F) Tao mutant cell clones showing overaccumulation of Crb and Par-6 proteins at the apical membrane. 
(G) Tao mutant cell clones showing an elongated apical-basal axis and expressing normal levels of the lateral membrane marker Coracle. (H) Tao mutant 
cells show a strong increase of Fas2 at the lateral membrane. (I) Expression of the UAS-HA-Tao transgene in an otherwise wild-type background showing 
the localization of Tao protein at the lateral membrane and in the basolateral cytoplasm. Processing of the images involved adjustment of  settings. Bars: 
(white) 50 µm; (black) 12.5 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 199 • NUMBER 7 • 2012 </p>

<p>
knockdown and providing an explanation why the rescue is not 
fully penetrant (Fig. 2 H, inset). 
To quantify the results of the interaction screen, we mea-
sured the length of the apicobasal axis of anterior epithelial cells 
to calculate a mean apicobasal length proportion (see Fig. S4). 
The mean value for wild-type versus Tao mutant cells is 1.8, 
meaning that the mean apicobasal axis of anterior Tao mutant 
cells is almost twice as long. This is in contrast to the mean 
value of 1.2 measured in egg chambers, in which Tao mutant 
clones and Fas2 knockdown have been induced. Thus, a reduc-
tion of Fas2 protein levels suppresses the morphogenetic de-
fects of Tao mutant cells. Interestingly, Fas2 knockdown in Tao 
mutant cells suppresses not only the morphological defects but 
also the overaccumulation of Arm at the membrane (Fig. 2 D). 
As no other gene knockdown in our candidate approach was 
able to suppress Tao defects, we conclude that the overaccu-
mulation of Fas2 protein in Tao cells is a major reason for their 
inability to undergo morphogenesis. 
To further support that Fas2 accumulation is causing Tao 
morphogenesis defects, we generated Fas2 Tao double mutants 
by recombining a null allele (Fas2 </p>

<p>eb1112 </p>

<p>) with Tao </p>

<p>eta </p>

<p>. Larger ho-
mozygous mutant cell clones in the follicular epithelium are 
lethal, suggesting an interaction of the two genes in cell viability 
during early oogenesis. However, we could recover small clones 
in stage 8/9 egg chambers, which all stretch normally (n = 8; 
Fig. 2, I and J). Moreover, double mutant clones accumulate 
normal Arm protein levels at their membranes, indicating a 
complete rescue of the Tao phenotype. Thus, Fas2 Tao double 
mutant clones strongly support that the morphogenesis defects 
in Tao mutant cells are caused by Fas2 accumulation. We 
therefore hypothesized that Tao acts through Fas2 during epi-
thelial morphogenesis. </p>

<p>Timely controlled down-regulation of Fas2 </p>

<p>is critical for epithelial stretching </p>

<p>The transmembrane protein Fas2 harbors five immunoglobulin 
domains, which mediate homophilic cell adhesion between the 
lateral membranes of follicle cells (Szafranski and Goode, 
2004). The homophilic adhesion properties of Fas2 suggest a 
simple explanation for the stretching failure of Tao mutant 
cells: the increased accumulation of Fas2 at the lateral mem-
brane results in increased cell-cell adhesion, which prevents 
membrane shrinking and hence morphogenesis. As this hy-
pothesis implies that Fas2 is lost from the lateral membrane 
before stretching, we reexamined Fas2 localization during 
morphogenesis. It has been reported that the Fas2 protein is 
absent from anterior follicle cells at stage 8 (Szafranski and 
Goode, 2004). Our analysis of the temporal changes in Fas2 
localization showed that anterior epithelial cells loose Fas2 
when they are still cuboidal, indicating that down-regulation 
precedes stretching (Fig. 3 B). This supports the idea that Fas2 
has to be removed from the lateral membrane to allow stretch-
ing. Fas2 is no longer detectable in stretching follicle cells 
(Fig. 3, C-D), whereas DE-cadherin forms a zonula adherens 
(Fig. 3 D, red channel). This suggests that cell adhesion in 
stretching cells is mainly mediated by DE-cadherin. In con-
trast to the anterior cells, posterior cells maintain Fas2 at their </p>

<p>microtubules between wild-type and Tao mutant cells. Neither 
the density of -Tubulin-stained microtubules nor microtubule 
polarity revealed by the localization of -Tubulin, Nod-lacZ, 
and Kinesin-lacZ is affected in Tao mutant cells (Fig. S3, A-D). 
Moreover, Tao mutant cells do not show significant differences 
in the distribution of F-actin, -Spectrin, and Myosin activity, 
indicating that Tao does not act on the actin cytoskeleton 
(Fig. S3, E and F). We therefore conclude that Tao does not 
regulate morphogenesis via the cytoskeleton. 
To examine a possible role of Tao in cell polarity, we ana-
lyzed epithelial membrane domains, which are established by 
polarity proteins localizing to the apical or lateral membrane. 
Crumbs (Crb), Par-6, and atypical PKC (aPKC) localize to the 
apical membrane, whereas Discs large (Dlg), Coracle, and Fas2 
distribute laterally (Laprise and Tepass, 2011). Tao mutant fol-
licle cells localize all aforementioned proteins correctly, indi-
cating that the overall apicobasal polarity of the follicular 
epithelium is not affected (Fig. 1, E-H). Analysis of the adher-
ens junction components DE-cadherin and -Catenin/Arma-
dillo (Arm) revealed that they are present in the apicolateral 
region of the epithelium but accumulate at higher levels com-
pared with neighboring wild-type cells (Figs. 1 A and 2 A). 
Moreover, their localization is not restricted to the apicolateral 
region but spreads into the apical membrane domain of Tao mu-
tant cells. The apical marker Crb, Par-6, and aPKC also accu-
mulate at higher levels but are still restricted to their domain 
(Fig. 1, E and F). Among the lateral markers, only Fas2 shows 
an increased membrane accumulation, whereas we detected no 
obvious difference in Dlg and Coracle levels (Fig. 1, E, G, and H). 
Thus, although Tao is not essential for the establishment of 
membrane polarity, it regulates the accumulation proteins at the 
plasma membrane. </p>

<p>Fas2 suppresses epithelial morphogenesis </p>

<p>defects in Tao mutant cells </p>

<p>To assess whether the increased accumulation of membrane pro-
teins causes the morphogenesis defects in Tao mutant cells, we 
tested whether a reduction of this accumulation by RNAi res-
cues Tao defects. To identify possible mediators of the defects, 
we performed a candidate in vivo RNAi interaction screen. We 
generated Tao mutant cell clones, in which candidate proteins 
are knocked down by inducing UAS-RNAi and UAS-Flippase 
transgenes with the same Gal4 driver line (see Materials and 
methods). In this screen, we included not only proteins that 
accumulate in Tao mutant cells but also other possible Tao-
interacting genes, such as par-1 and Eb1 (encoding a microtubule 
plus end-binding protein), and genes encoding members of the 
SWH pathway (Table S1). 
Fig. 2 compares the results for the interaction of Tao with 
genes encoding the transmembrane proteins Crb, DE-cadherin, 
and Fas2 as examples. Among the 10 genes tested in this ap-
proach, only Fas2 RNAi rescues Tao morphogenesis defects. 
In approximately half of the analyzed stage 9 egg chambers, 
the stretching defects of Tao mutant cell clones (n = 16) were 
clearly suppressed when Fas2 function was simultaneously re-
duced by RNAi. Analysis of Fas2 expression in this experiment 
revealed residual protein after RNAi, indicating an incomplete </p>

<p> 
Tao controls epithelial morphogenesis • Gomez et al. </p>

<p>shrinking. Thus, timely controlled removal of Fas2 is critical 
for stretching of the anterior follicle cells. 
The critical role for Fas2 in epithelial morphogenesis raised 
the question whether the adhesion molecule is required for cell 
shape maintenance before stretching starts. Analysis of Fas2 
mutant cell clones showed that they stay cuboidal until stage 7 
and then undergo normal morphogenesis (Fig. 3, F and G). 
Thus, although the down-regulation of Fas2 is critical for 
stretching, the protein is not essential for maintaining epithelial 
cell shape before morphogenesis. </p>

<p>Fas2 removal from the lateral membrane </p>

<p>is mediated by endocytosis </p>

<p>Fas2 down-regulation in the follicular epithelium is controlled 
at the transcriptional level (Szafranski and Goode, 2004). We 
confirmed this by analyzing three enhancer trap lines, which re-
flect the transcriptional activity of the Fas2 locus (Fig. S5, A-C; </p>

<p>membranes, where it is now confined to the apicolateral region 
(Fig. 3 C, arrowheads). 
To test the hypothesis that Fas2 interferes with stretching 
of anterior cells, we overexpressed a UAS-Fas2-YFP construct 
using traffic jam-Gal4, a driver line providing high expression 
levels in all follicle cells. Fas2 overexpression delays stretching 
and results in the formation of elongated egg chambers, in 
which anterior follicle cells retain a cuboidal cell shape at stage 9 
(Fig. 3 E). Interestingly, these cell shape defects are accompa-
nied by increased levels of the adherens junction component 
Arm at the apical membrane closely resembling Tao mutant 
cells (Figs. 3 E and 2 A, compare insets). Thus, Fas2 over-
expression mimics the Tao phenotype, strongly supporting the 
hypothesis that increased Fas2 levels cause the defects of Tao 
mutant cells. In summary, our data show that Fas2 is lost from 
anterior follicle cells before they undergo stretching and that 
prolonged Fas2 expression interferes with lateral membrane </p>

<p>Figure 2. Morphogenesis defects in Tao mutant cells are mediated by Fas2 overaccumulation. (A-I) Stage 9 egg chambers. Insets show enlarged areas 
of the region marked by the white frames. (A-H) Egg chambers with Tao mutant clones marked by the absence of GFP and stained for Arm (A-D) or Fas2 
(E-H). The indicated apical-basal length proportions (a-b prop.; see also Fig. S4) is the mean value obtained in at least three different asymmetric clones. 
A and E show Tao clones in a wild-type background, and B, C, and F-H show clones in follicles in which crb, DE-cadherin (DE-Cad), and Fas2 are knocked 
down using GR1-Gal4-driven UAS-inverted repeat transgenes. (B and F) crb knockdown neither suppresses the stretching defects nor the overaccumula-
tion of Arm and Fas2 in Tao clones. (C and G) DE-cadherin knockdown results in defects in egg chamber morphology and mislocalization of Arm, which 
are explained by defects in zonula adherens formation. Fas2 accumulates at the lateral membrane of Tao mutant cells, which fail to stretch. (D and H) 
Fas2 knockdown suppresses the stretching defects in Tao mutant cells, and Arm accumulation reverts to normal levels. Note that the residual Fas2 protein 
is detectable, indicating that the knockdown is not complete (inset in H). (I and J) Follicles with cell clones doubly mutant for Tao and Fas2 stained for 
Arm protein. Images to the right of I and J show the Arm channel alone. Mutant cells are marked by red asterisks and reveal no stretching defects. J (left) 
shows an optical confocal section at the level of the zonula adherens, revealing the onset of stretching in the anterior-most cells. Arm overaccumulation is 
suppressed. Eight double mutant clones were obtained in total, two of them were in an asymmetric position (not depicted), allowing the calculation of the 
apical-basal length proportion with a value of 1.1. Blue dotted lines mark the border of the Tao mutant clones. Processing of the images involved adjust-
ment of  settings. Bars: (white) 50 µm; (black) 12.5 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 199 • NUMBER 7 • 2012 </p>

<p>
with a Fas2-specific antibody and overexpressed GFP-tagged 
Rab5 protein (Fig. 4 A). 
To examine whether vesicle trafficking contributes to 
Fas2 removal from the lateral membrane, we counted the total 
number of Fas2 puncta and puncta that colocalize either with 
Rab5 or Rab11 vesicles. We distinguished between egg cham-
bers of three different stages: early follicles that were still round 
(stage 5/6), oval follicles with no signs of anterior Fas2 disap-
pearance (stage 7), and follicles with cuboidal anterior cells, 
in which the anterior Fas2 signal starts to disappear (stage 8; 
Fig. 4 D, pictures). This analysis revealed a continuous in-
crease in the number of Fas2 vesicles between stages 6 and 8 
(Fig. 4 D). Moreover, the total number of Fas2-Rab5-positive 
vesicles per cell increases strongly during this period (Fig. 4 E). 
Similarly, the proportion of Fas2-Rab5 vesicles in relation to 
the total number of Rab5 vesicles rises from 3 to 13%, sug-
gesting that an increasing part of the endocytic machinery is 
engaged in the internalization of Fas2 before stretching occurs 
(Table S3). We therefore conclude that Fas2 removal from the 
lateral membrane is mediated by endocytosis. </p>

<p>Fas2 endocytosis is impaired in Tao 
mutant cells </p>

<p>Tao mutant clones exhibit Fas2-positive tubular structures as-
sociated with the plasma membrane (Fig. 5 A, arrowheads). 
These structures are reminiscent of tubules that have been </p>

<p>and not depicted). To examine whether Tao is involved in Fas2 
repression, we recombined the enhancer trap insertions with 
the Tao 
eta mutation and induced mutant cell clones. A compar-
ison of reporter signal intensities between mutant and hetero-
zygous cells provided no evidence for a function of Tao in 
repressing Fas2 transcription (Table S2 and Fig. S5, D and E). 
Thus, Tao does not appear to regulate Fas2 gene expression 
and might mediate down-regulation of Fas2 at a posttranscrip-
tional level. 
A possible level of control is the removal of existing 
protein from the lateral membrane, which is most commonly 
achieved by packaging the protein into vesicles that are destined 
for degradation. To investigate the role of vesicle trafficking, we 
analyzed Fas2 distribution in optical sections perpendicular to 
the apicobasal axis of the epithelium and identified cytoplasmic 
Fas2-positive puncta (Figs. 4 A and 3 D). We characterized 
these puncta using an exon trap line, which tags endogenously 
expressed Fas2 protein with GFP (Silies and Klämbt, 2010) and 
which shows the puncta in the same pattern as the Fas2 antibody 
(Fig. 4, B and C). Using this line, we performed triple stainings 
with antibodies detecting Fas2 (GFP), endosomes (Rab5), and 
recycling vesicles (Rab11), which identify only endogenously 
expressed proteins. This analysis showed many Fas2 puncta 
that colocalize with one of the two Rab proteins, indicating that 
Fas2 is endocytosed and recycled at the membrane (Fig. 4, 
B and C). Fas2 endocytosis was further supported by stainings </p>

<p>Figure 3. The role of Fas2 during morphogenesis of the squamous epithelium. (A-D) Localization of Fas2 and DE-cadherin (DE-Cad) in stage 7 (A), 
stage 8 (B), and stage 9 (C and D) follicles. Insets show the Fas2 signal in the framed regions at a higher magnification. Fas2 is down-regulated in anterior 
follicle cells between stages 7 and 8. (B) Note the disappearance of the Fas2 signal when the cells are still cuboidal. (C) Arrowheads show Fas2 signal in 
the apicolateral region of the posterior epithelium. (D) Surface view of the anterior epithelium during stretching. DE-cadherin highlights the zonula adherens, 
which is continuous at two cell borders (yellow arrow) and which disassembles at the four cell border (white arrow). White arrowhead marks a Fas2 puncta 
in the cytoplasm. D shows the Fas2 channel alone. Fas2 is no longer detectable at the membrane of the anterior follicle cells (arrow) and appears in puncta 
in more posterior cells. (E) Stage 9 egg chamber in which a UAS-Fas2-YFP transgene is overexpressed. Only the anterior-most follicle cells flatten, whereas 
the remaining anterior cells retain a cuboidal shape. Egg chamber morphology is affected as revealed by the elongated shape of the follicle (compare 
with stage 9 follicles in C and F). The inset shows the accumulation of Arm at the apical membrane. (F and G) Follicle cell clones mutant for the null allele 
Fas2 
eb1112 marked by the absence of GFP. Mutant cells show no shape defects before (G) and during (F) morphogenesis. Processing of the images involved 
adjustment of  settings. Bars: (white) 50 µm; (black) 12.5 µm. </p>

<p> 
Tao controls epithelial morphogenesis • Gomez et al. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Cytoplasmic Fas2 puncta colocalize with endosomal and recycling vesicles. (A-C) Optical confocal sections through the follicular epithelium 
perpendicular to the apical-basal axis. (A) Double staining with an anti-Fas2 and an anti-GFP antibody detecting GR1-Gal4-driven UAS-Rab5-GFP. 
(B and C) Triple staining for Fas2-GFP, Rab5, and Rab11. B shows the Fas2 overlap with Rab5, and C shows the Fas2 overlap with Rab11. Examples of 
Fas2 vesicles that costain with one of the Rab proteins are marked by arrowheads. (D) Diagram showing Fas2-GFP vesicle numbers at different stages of 
oogenesis. Bars show the number of Fas2 vesicles counted in optical confocal sections divided by the number of analyzed cells. Below the graph, three 
follicles are depicted showing examples for the corresponding stages. Error bars indicate standard error. (E) Bars show the number Fas2-GFP vesicles that 
colocalize with Rab5 and Rab11 during different oogenesis stages. Fas2 vesicles that colocalize with both Rab5 and Rab11 were not included in the 
diagram. The data shown in D and E summarize the analysis of 15 egg chambers (five for each developmental stage). Processing of the images involved 
adjustment of  settings. Error bars indicate standard error. St, stage. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 199 • NUMBER 7 • 2012 </p>

<p>
indicating that Tao is required for efficient Fas2 endocytosis 
in the follicular epithelium (Fig. 5 C). 
To further characterize the endocytosis defect in Tao 
mutants, we quantified the formation of Rab5-positive Fas2 
vesicles in homozygous mutant and heterozygous cells. To this 
end, we recombined the Fas2 exon trap GFP insertion with the 
Tao 
eta mutation. To mark cell clones independently of GFP, 
we generated a P(neoFRT)19A chromosome with a follicle 
cell-specific enhancer trap, enabling us to detect follicle cell 
nuclei that are wild type for Tao with -Galactosidase (Müller, 
2000). Using these chromosomes, we generated cell clones 
colabeled for Fas2-GFP and Rab5 and quantified confocal pic-
tures by counting the number of Rab5 vesicles, vesicular Fas2 
structures, and their colocalization. Moreover, we determined 
the subcellular localization of vesicular Fas2-Rab5 structures </p>

<p>described for mutants that affect vesicle scission and endocy-
tosis in the epithelium of the Drosophila notum (Georgiou 
et al., 2008; Leibfried et al., 2008). To test whether Tao is 
required for endocytosis, we performed uptake experiments, in 
which we incubated mosaic egg chambers with fluorescently 
labeled dextran. Quantification of dextran vesicle numbers in 
confocal pictures revealed that dextran internalization is sig-
nificantly reduced in Tao mutant cells compared with neigh-
boring heterozygous cells (Fig. 5 B). We also tested whether 
this approach monitors Fas2 endocytosis by staining ovaries 
after dextran incubation with an anti-Fas2 antibody. Notably, 
many dextran vesicles were Fas2 positive in wild-type cells, 
indicating that dextran was included in Fas2 endocytotic vesi-
cles (Fig. 5 D, arrowheads). In Tao mutant cells, the number 
of dextran vesicles colocalizing with Fas2 is strongly reduced, </p>

<p>Figure 5. Fas2 endocytosis is impaired in Tao mutant cells. A, B, D, and E show optical confocal sections perpendicular to the apical-basal axis of the 
follicular epithelium. (A) Tao mutant cell clone (left) stained with an anti-Fas2 antibody showing increased Fas2 levels at the lateral membrane. In addition, 
tubular Fas2 extensions sprout from the lateral membrane (arrowheads). (B) Tao mutant clone in a follicle that has been incubated with fluorescently labeled 
dextran. Dextran signal is shown in black, and dotted line marks the clone border. Homozygous mutant cells are to the left. Dextran particles that were 
internalized into follicle cells vary in size. Right arrowhead shows an example for the minimal particle size counted in these experiments. Left arrowhead 
marks a bigger dextran particle. Analysis of four cell clones generated in three independent uptake experiments revealed a mean reduction of internalized 
dextran vesicles by 54%. (C) Diagram summarizing the results of three dextran uptake experiments (five clones) in which follicles were subsequently stained 
for Fas2. Left bars show the total number of dextran vesicles per cell, and right bars show the numbers of cytoplasmic dextran vesicles that colocalize with 
Fas2. Error bars indicate standard error. A statistical test (t two-tailed paired test) was performed to analyze dextran internalization between wild-type 
(WT) and Tao mutant cells (P = 0.001) and dextran-Fas2 colocalization (P = 0.0171). (D) Follicle with a Tao clone incubated in dextran and subsequently 
stained with an anti-Fas2 antibody. Tao mutant cells are left, and wild-type cells are right of the white dotted line. Arrowheads indicate dextran vesicles 
that colocalize with Fas2. (E) Tao mutant cell clone stained for Fas2-GFP and Rab5. Tao mutant cells are to the left of the white dotted line. Fas2 and Rab5 
channels alone are shown in the right two images. Examples for cytoplasmic Fas2-Rab5 vesicles are marked by arrowheads, whereas membrane-associated 
vesicular structures are marked by arrows. Processing of the images involved adjustment of  settings. Blue dotted lines mark the border of the Tao mutant 
clones. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p> 
Tao controls epithelial morphogenesis • Gomez et al. </p>

<p>by distinguishing between cytoplasmic puncta (Fig. 5 E, arrow-
heads) and semicircular or tubular structures associated with 
the plasma membrane (Fig. 5 E, arrows). This analysis revealed 
that in Tao mutant cells, plasma membrane-associated Fas2-
Rab5 structures were increased, whereas Fas2-Rab5 vesicles in 
the cytoplasm were reduced (Table 1). The increased accumula-
tion of Fas2-Rab5 structures at the plasma membrane suggests 
that formation or scission of endocytic Fas2 vesicles is impaired 
in Tao mutant cells. Moreover, it is possible that Tao predomi-
nantly affects the formation of endocytotic Fas2 vesicles, as 
the spatial distribution of other (Fas2 negative) Rab5 vesicles 
was not affected in Tao mutant cells. Collectively, these results 
suggest that Tao activates Fas2 endocytosis by promoting the 
formation of Rab5 vesicles. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Here, we report a novel mechanism regulating the morphogene-
sis of a squamous epithelium. Our data show that timely con-
trolled removal of the adhesion molecule Fas2 from the lateral 
membrane is critical for the stretching of cuboidal precursor 
cells. In this process, Tao initiates morphogenesis by promoting 
Fas2 endocytosis from the lateral membrane, which reduces ad-
hesive forces and thereby provides plasticity for the cuboidal to 
squamous cell shape change. Our results are consistent with a 
model in which homophilic Fas2 interactions act as a glue pre-
venting shortening of the membrane. </p>

<p>A role for Tao in promoting endocytosis </p>

<p>Tao function is essential for the process of stretching of epi-
thelial cells. However, our data indicate that Tao uses none of 
its known pathways to control morphogenesis. Similarly, we 
found no evidence that Tao regulates cell stretching via the cy-
toskeleton. Moreover, our results argue against a role for Tao 
in transcriptional repression of Fas2, indicating a function in 
posttranslational regulation. Indeed, our quantitative analysis 
of Fas2 vesicles in wild-type follicles indicates that membrane 
shrinking is initiated by enhanced endocytosis. Tao mutant cells 
have a reduced ability to internalize Fas2 vesicles, contain tu-
bular Fas2 structures typical for endocytosis defects, and show 
fewer endocytotic Fas2 vesicles in the cytoplasm. This indi-
cates that the overaccumulation of Fas2 at the lateral membrane </p>

<p>is caused by defective Fas2 internalization, suggesting a role 
for Tao in promoting endocytosis at the lateral membrane. 
A similar function of Tao in triggering endocytosis of homo-
philic adhesion proteins has been identified in cultured hippo-
campal neurons (Yasuda et al., 2007). In contrast to the follicular 
epithelium, however, Tao is acting via the p38 MAP signaling 
pathway in this cell type. 
Tao promotes Fas2 endocytosis not only in the anterior 
squamous epithelium but acts also in the posterior epithelium, 
whose cells become columnar by elongating their lateral mem-
brane (Fig. 1, A and H). Although it is surprising that these cells 
down-regulate a protein that is able to induce cell elongation, it 
appears that during stage 7/8, all epithelial cells clear their lat-
eral membrane from Fas2 to allow morphogenesis. This sug-
gests that other proteins than Fas2 are responsible for cell 
elongation in the posterior epithelium. </p>

<p>Is Tao an endocytosis promoter specific </p>

<p>for the lateral membrane? </p>

<p>Endocytosis is only impaired but not blocked in Tao mutant 
cells, as they are still able to internalize reduced levels of dex-
tran and Fas2. Consistent with this, the Tao phenotype differs 
from mutants affecting endocytosis in general. Although cell 
clones mutant for Rab5, the syntaxin family member Ava-
lanche, and Dynamin/Shibire show severe polarity defects and 
massive overproliferation in the follicular epithelium (unpub-
lished data; Lu and Bilder, 2005), the Tao phenotype is restricted 
to overaccumulation of membrane proteins and cell shape 
defects. We therefore conclude that Tao is not a general endo-
cytosis factor but enhances endocytosis at a critical develop-
mental stage to allow epithelial morphogenesis. 
This timely controlled requirement of Tao function raises 
the question whether Tao expression starts just before the onset 
of morphogenesis or whether the protein is present also in early 
stages and only activated when Fas2 has to be removed from the 
lateral membrane. We were unable to detect endogenous Tao 
protein, as antibodies generated by us and others showed no 
specific signal in the follicular epithelium. Moreover, analysis 
of Tao mRNA expression does not allow unambiguous conclu-
sions about the onset of Tao transcription in the follicular epi-
thelium as a strong signal from the germline cyst covers the 
signal in the surrounding epithelium. </p>

<p>Table 1. Quantification of endocytotic vesicles in Tao mutant genetic mosaics </p>

<p>Genotype 
Cytoplasmic 
Fas2 puncta 
per cell </p>

<p>Total Rab5 
vesicles </p>

<p>Rab5 vesicles within 
membrane </p>

<p>Membrane-associated Rab5 vesicles 
Cytoplasmic Rab5 vesicles </p>

<p>+Fas2 
Fas2 
+Fas2 
Fas2 </p>

<p>Tao </p>

<p>eta </p>

<p>/+ 
2.16 ± 0.69 12.15 ± 4.13 
4.50 ± 1.39 
1.55 ± 0.43 
0.73 ± 0.20 
0.84 ± 0.35 
4.53 ± 2.50 
Tao </p>

<p>eta </p>

<p>/Tao </p>

<p>eta </p>

<p>2.42 ± 0.52 12.56 ± 3.24 
4.38 ± 2.11 
2.47 ± 0.73 
0.68 ± 0.32 
0.39 ± 0.19 
4.73 ± 1.30 
P-value (t test) 
0.4884 
0.8530 
0.9070 
0.0278 
0.7517 
0.0249 
0.8666 </p>

<p>Confocal pictures of seven stage 8/9 genetic mosaic egg chambers were analyzed, which were stained with GFP to highlight Fas2, Rab5 to mark endosomes, 
and -Galactosidase to identify wild-type cells. Total counts of Fas2 puncta per cell reflect only cytoplasmic puncta and do not include plasma membrane-associ-
ated structures. Rab5 vesicles are distinguished between vesicles that overlap with the center of the plasma membrane (within membrane), vesicles whose signal 
overlaps with the plasma membrane but does not touch its center (membrane associated), and vesicles that do not overlap with the plasma membrane (cytoplasmic). 
Membrane-associated Rab5 vesicles are further distinguished between vesicles that reveal Fas2-positive semicircular or tubular membrane protrusions (+Fas2) and 
vesicles without such protrusions (Fas2). t test (two-tailed equal variance;  = 0.05) was performed to describe the statistical significance of the difference between 
the values obtained for vesicle numbers in homozygous versus homozygous cell clones. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 199 • NUMBER 7 • 2012 </p>

<p>
proteins, which then concentrate within a restricted area. We 
therefore propose that the accumulation of Arm, DE-cadherin, 
and apical proteins in Tao mutant cells is not caused by im-
paired endocytosis but a result of the inability of these cells to 
increase their surface area. Consistent with this, we found that 
cells whose stretching is prevented by Fas2 overexpression (and 
which are wild type for Tao function) also concentrate Arm 
within their restricted apical surface (Fig. 3 E). 
A membrane domain-specific endocytosis function for 
Tao is also supported by experiments, which deplete Fas2 in 
Tao mutant cells. If Tao would act all along the plasma mem-
brane, Fas2 removal from the lateral membrane should selec-
tively rescue the lateral defect (i.e., Fas2 accumulation) but 
should not suppress the accumulation of apical and apicolateral 
proteins (e.g., Arm). However, Fas2 Tao double mutant cells 
do suppress Arm accumulation (Fig. 2 J). Thus, the primary de-
fect of Tao mutants is Fas2 accumulation, which prevents 
stretching and expansion of the apical surface. The concentra-
tion of Arm is only a secondary effect of the cell shape defect. 
In conclusion, our data favor a model in which Tao promotes 
endocytosis specifically at the lateral membrane to relieve Fas2-
mediated cell adhesion. </p>

<p>The role of Tao in squamous 
cell morphogenesis </p>

<p>The identification of a mechanism initiating epithelial mor-
phogenesis in the follicular epithelium allows us to update the 
current model of squamous cell morphogenesis in the follicu-
lar epithelium. Before morphogenesis, all epithelial cells are 
cuboidal and adhere apicolaterally via DE-cadherin and more 
basolaterally via Fas2 interactions. In this period, Fas2 is en-
docytosed and recycled back to the membrane (Fig. 6, stage 6). 
Morphogenesis is primed by the Tao kinase, which promotes 
the endocytosis of Fas2 vesicles. We assume that a large pro-
portion of the Fas2 vesicles enter the lysosomal pathway, lead-
ing to Fas2 degradation (Fig. 6, stage 8). The removal of Fas2 
from the lateral membrane is a critical first step, which allows 
morphogenesis to occur. Once Fas2 has disappeared, the cuboi-
dal shape of the epithelial cells is solely stabilized by the zonula 
adherens. Cell flattening requires a tensile force, and morpho-
metric analysis indicates that this force originates from the con-
tinuously growing germline cyst, which stretches cells in the 
anterior epithelium (Fig. 6, stage 9; Kolahi et al., 2009). Flat-
tening correlates well with the local breakdown of the zonula 
adherens, suggesting an important role for adherens junctions 
remodeling in cell stretching (Grammont, 2007). Although the 
exact molecular mechanism controlling remodeling has still to 
be elucidated, our data indicate that before cell stretching, lat-
eral cell adhesion has to be reduced to provide morphogenetic 
plasticity to the lateral membrane. 
Given the critical role of Fas2 down-regulation for epi-
thelial stretching, it is counterintuitive that Fas2 mutant cells 
undergo normal morphogenesis. However, a similar scenario 
has been shown for the morphogenesis of the peripheral ner-
vous system (PNS) in Drosophila. Here, Fas2 has to be en-
docytosed in axons to allow glia cell migration. Despite this 
important function for Fas2 down-regulation, Fas2 mutants </p>

<p>Using a HA fusion protein, we detected Tao protein at the 
lateral membrane and in the basolateral cytoplasm of the follic-
ular epithelium. Interestingly, Tao protein accumulation ap-
pears as a gradient with the lowest levels in the apical and the 
highest levels in the basal region of the follicular epithelium 
(Fig. 1 I). As our rescue experiments demonstrate the function-
ality of the fusion protein, a gradient of endogenous Tao activ-
ity might also exist. This raises the possibility that Tao promotes 
endocytosis more strongly in basal regions of the lateral mem-
brane. We speculate that there is a switch in Tao activity at the 
border between the lateral and the basal membrane and that the 
basal membrane domain is protected from Tao function. A spa-
tial restriction of Tao function to the lateral membrane could be 
achieved by the localization of a yet unidentified target of Tao 
kinase. Such a Tao mediator could exclusively localize to the 
lateral membrane. 
The finding that not only Fas2 but also apical and apico-
lateral proteins, such as DE-cadherin and Crb, overaccumulate 
in Tao mutants might argue against a restriction of Tao function 
to the lateral membrane. However, in the light of the dramatic 
change in the geometry of stretching cells, an alternative expla-
nation for the accumulation of these proteins seems more likely. 
Squamous cell morphogenesis involves a 15-fold surface expan-
sion, which is accompanied by a strong increase in the amounts 
of proteins determining the apical membrane and forming the 
adherens junctions. Interestingly, also, posterior cells expand 
their surface, albeit in less dramatic manner (Kolahi et al., 2009). 
Tao mutant cells are unable to increase their surface area, but they 
nevertheless produce the same amount of apical and apicolateral </p>

<p>Figure 6. Model for squamous cell morphogenesis. See last chapter of the 
Discussion for explanation. </p>

<p> 
Tao controls epithelial morphogenesis • Gomez et al. </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">Photoshop</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">CS3</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Adobe</rs></p>

<p>Generation of UAS-Tao transgenes 
mRNA from ovaries was purified using an mRNA isolation kit (µMACS; 
Miltenyi Biotec) in the fist step for the generation a full-length Tao cDNA. 
mRNA was used for a reverse transcription reaction with a reverse tran-
scriptase kit (SuperScript III; Invitrogen) and a Tao-specific oligonucleotide 
(5-GGGTTGTGTGTCGTGTGTCTTCTTTC-3) hybridizing with the 3 un-
translated region. With the resulting template and two primers hybridizing 
with 5 and 3 untranslated (5-CACTGTGTGCTGTGTGAACGTGAAC-3 
and 5-CACTTGTTGTGGGGGTTGGCATTG-3) regions of Tao, a PCR re-
action was performed. The product was cloned into a cloning kit (pCR 
TOPO II; Invitrogen) and subsequently sequenced. An EcoR1 fragment con-
taining the full-length open reading frame was subcloned into the pUASp2 
vector, and germline transformation was performed using standard proto-
cols. To generate a construct encoding a Tao protein with an N-terminal 
HA fusion, a PCR fragment containing EcoR1 and Xba1 restriction sites 
was cloned into a pUASp2 vector containing the HA-encoding sequence. </p>

<p>Quantification of genetic interaction experiments 
The quantification of the interaction between the Tao 
eta allele and knock-
down of candidate genes was conducted in stage 9 egg chambers car-
rying asymmetric clones with respect to the anterior-posterior axis (see 
Fig. S4). To assess the interaction, the apical-basal cell length of both 
Tao 
eta + RNAi and RNAi only (or wild-type control) cells was measured at 
the level of the nuclei using the confocal microscope (LSM 700) software or 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">ImageJ</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>). The apical-basal length proportion </p>

<p>show no gross morphological defects in the PNS (Silies and 
Klämbt, 2010). Thus, although Fas2 down-regulation is criti-
cal for epithelial and PNS morphogenesis, both tissues can 
compensate for the complete loss of the protein. We propose 
that Fas2 helps to stabilize a morphological state and allows 
development to proceed only after its timely controlled en-
docytosis. This mechanism guarantees the correct timing of 
morphogenesis and thereby helps to coordinate the develop-
ment of different cell types and tissues. In the follicular epi-
thelium, Fas2 might collaborate with the zonula adherens in 
counteracting the pressure from the growing germline cyst. 
As a result, the cuboidal cell shape is stabilized and premature, 
and uncontrolled stretching is prevented. Subsequently, Fas2 
internalization overcomes this control mechanism, and epithe-
lial morphogenesis proceeds. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Generation of Tao mutants 
To generate EMS-induced Tao mutants, we made use of an EP element that 
is inserted into the first, untranslated exon of the Tao locus (EP1455). This 
transposon neither affects viability nor fertility of the mutant flies. EP ele-
ments integrate UAS sequences into the genome, allowing the overexpres-
sion of adjacent genes by a Gal4 driver line. Induction of Tao expression 
by combining EP1455 with the ubiquitous driver Tubulin-Gal4 results in le-
thality. We used this lethal combination of chromosomes to screen for sup-
pressor mutations. To this end, we fed males harboring the EP element with 
EMS and crossed them to females expressing the Tubulin-Gal4 driver. After 
screening of more than 10,000 crosses, we obtained 13 suppressors of le-
thality, which are good candidates to carry mutations in the Tao locus. 
Among those, one suppressor mutation was lethal by itself, which we 
named Tao </p>

<p>eta </p>

<p>. Sequence analysis revealed a point mutation in the kinase 
domain of Tao, in which a CAG triplet encoding glutamine (aa 64) is 
mutated to TAG, resulting in a stop codon. 
To generate a deficiency uncovering the Tao locus, we used two 
transposons carrying FRT sites, which allow the recovery of chromosomes 
with deletions of molecularly defined endpoints (Parks et al., 2004). Fol-
lowing the instructions of Parks et al. (2004), chromosomes harboring the 
transposons PBac{XP}CG32532 
d02300 and PBac{RB}e01713 were crossed 
in trans to induce a small deficiency that we named Df(1)14.1 and which 
uncovers the genes Grip84, carnation, and Tao. The deficiency and the 
Tao 
eta allele were recombined with FRT19A to generate genetic mosaic 
flies (see following paragraph). </p>

<p>Drosophila genetics 
Drosophila stocks used were as follows: yw FRT19A (Bloomington Stock 
Center), w Tao 
eta FRT19A/FM6, Df(1)14.4 FRT19A/FM6 (both from this 
work), w Fas2 
eb112 FRT19A/FM6 (provided by C. Klämbt, University of 
Münster, Münster, Germany; Grenningloh et al., 1991), w ;UAS-Fas2-YFP 
(provided by A. Nose, Tokyo University, Tokyo Japan; Kohsaka et al., 
2007), w Fas2 
GFP397 (exon trap insertion in the Fas2 locus; provided 
by C. Klämbt), w ;;UAS-Tao/TM3 Sb, w ;UAS-HA-Tao/CyO, w Fas2 </p>

<p>eb112 </p>

<p>Tao 
eta FRT19A/FM6 (all from this work), GR1-Gal4/TM3Ser (provided 
by S. Roth, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany; Gupta and Schüpbach, 
2003), w ;traffic jam-Gal4/CyO (provided by J. Brennecke, Institute of 
Molecular Biotechnology, Vienna, Austria; Olivieri et al., 2010), w ;;GR1-
Gal4 UAS-FLP/TM3 Ser, w ;;Kinesin-Gal/TM3Ser, w ;;Nod-Gal/ 
TM3Ser (both provided by S. Roth; Clark et al., 1997), yw AN365 
FRT19A (recombination of the a follicle cell-specific enhancer trap with 
FRT19A; the original enhancer trap stock was provided by A. Müller, 
University of Dundee, Dundee, Scotland, UK), G2H FRT101/FM7, H6 
FRT101/FM7 (deletions uncovering licorn and hemipterous; provided by 
S. Noselli, University of Nice, Nice, France; Suzanne et al., 1999), and 
w ;;FRT82B Mpk2 
1 , w Dsor1 
lh110 FRT101/FM7a (both obtained from the 
Bloomington Stock Center). Strains that were used in RNAi experiments 
have been provided by the Vienna Drosophila RNAi Center and are 
listed in Table S1. 
Genetic mosaics were generated by using either a heat shock or a 
UAS/Gal4-inducible Flippase. Heat shock follicle cell clones were induced 
during prepupae and pupae stages by placing the vials in a 37°C water </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 199 • NUMBER 7 • 2012 </p>

<p>
We thank V. Benecke for generating the Tao 
eta allele and S. Költzer for gener-
ating transgenic flies. We thank C. Klämbt, E. Kunst, A. Wodarz, J. Knoblich, 
A. Müller, B. Baum, S. Noselli, A. Matsumoto, M. Gonzalez-Gaitan, A. Nose, 
A. Ephrussi, J. Brennecke, the Vienna Drosophila RNAi Center, and the 
Bloomington Stock Center for reagents and fly stocks. Support by F. Bestvater 
and the German Cancer Research Center Light Microscopy Facility is gratefully 
acknowledged. We thank S. Roth, T. Vaccari, M. Carl, and N. Berns for 
comments on the manuscript. 
This work was supported by grants (Sonderforschungsbereich 572, 
project B9, and Sachmittelbeihilfe) of the German research council and a fel-
lowship from the Medical Faculty Mannheim to J.M. Gomez. </p>

<p>Submitted: 24 July 2012 
Accepted: 20 November 2012 </p>



<p>was calculated between each Tao 
eta + RNAi and RNAi only counterpart. 
The proportion values obtained from one egg chamber were used to calcu-
late a mean apical-basal length proportion value. The apical-basal length 
proportion values of four egg chambers were averaged and used to deter-
mine whether the Tao phenotype was suppressed. Comparison between 
the candidates' apical-basal length proportion was performed with a one-
way analysis of variance and honestly significant difference Tukey's post 
hoc statistical test. </p>

<p>-Galactosidase signal intensity measurement 
The signal intensity of immunofluorescent -Galactosidase stainings was 
measured using <rs id="software-3" type="software">ImageJ</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">1.42j</rs> (Mac OS X; <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Apple</rs>). To quantify the signal 
intensity, the area corresponding to the -Galactosidase signal within each 
analyzed cell was selected manually, and its intensity was measured. Mea-
surements of signal intensities were performed with raw confocal pictures. 
The statistical analysis of Tao </p>

<p>eta </p>

<p>/Tao 
eta versus Tao </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>/Tao 
+ data were per-
formed with a t nonpaired two-tailed nonequal variance test. </p>

<p>Vesicle number and vesicle colocalization quantification 
For wild-type follicles, puncta counted within one follicle were added and 
divided by the number of analyzed cells. We considered puncta that are 
distinguishable from the background and not linked to the membrane sig-
nal. To quantify the colocalization between Fas2, Rab5, and Rab11, 10 cells 
per follicle were selected in the midanterior follicular epithelium. Sub-
sequently, Fas2 vesicles that colocalized with Rab5 or Rab11 within the 
selected cells were counted. For each follicle, the number of Fas2-Rab5-or 
Fas2-Rab11-colocalizing vesicles was added and divided by the number 
of cells analyzed. 
To quantify the colocalization between Fas2 and Rab5 in the Tao 
mutant genetic mosaics, three categories of puncta were distinguished: 
Fas2-GFP-Rab5-positive structures embedded within the membrane, Fas2-
GFP-Rab5-positive tubular structures that protrude from the plasma mem-
brane (Fas2-GFP-Rab5 membrane associated), and Fas2-GFP-Rab5-positive 
vesicles in the cytoplasm. The statistical analysis of Fas2-GFP-Rab5 colocal-
ization for the three categories, between Tao 
eta homozygous and Tao </p>

<p>eta </p>

<p>heterozygous cells, was performed with a t nonequal variance test. The cri-
teria used to count a colocalization event as positive were that 50% or 
more of the Fas2 structure colocalized with Rab5 or Rab11. </p>

<p>Dextran uptake assay 
Ovaries were dissected in S2 medium and immediately transferred to a 
0.6 mM dextran (fluorescein labeled, lysine fixable, 3,000 molecular 
weight; Molecular Probes) solution (S2 medium supplemented with 10% 
fetal bovine serum) for 3 min at 25°C in a thermomixer (450 rpm). Subse-
quently, the ovaries were washed with 1 ml PBS and fixed in 4% formalde-
hyde in PBS for 10 min. Staining procedures were performed as described 
in Antibodies and histology. To assess dextran-Fas2 colocalization, the 
Fas2 antibody was used at a 1:25 dilution. To quantify the dextran uptake 
in the Tao mutant genetic mosaics, the total number of dextran vesicles 
within the wild-type and Tao mutant clone was quantified and averaged by 
the number of cells analyzed within each clone. To quantify the dextran-
Fas2 colocalization, the total number of dextran-Fas2-colocalizing vesicles 
was counted in the wild-type and mutant clones (only the cytoplasmic Fas2 
signal was considered). The total number of dextran-Fas2 vesicles was av-
eraged by the number of cells analyzed within each clone. The statistical 
analysis of Tao versus wild-type cells was performed with a t two-tailed 
paired test. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The dataset analysis was performed in <rs id="software-4" type="software">Excel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-date">2008</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Microsoft</rs>) for Mac OS 
X (v<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">12.2.0</rs>) and <rs id="software-5" type="software">Prism</rs> 5 (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>) for Mac OS X (v5.0d). For 
all statistical tests, the significance level was set at  = 0.05. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 shows the process of epithelial stretching in wild-type follicles. 
Fig. S2 shows exclusion of possible Tao functions and pathways during 
oogenesis. Fig. S3 shows that Tao function is not mediated via the cytoskel-
eton. Fig. S4 explains how the anterior-posterior length proportion was 
determined. Fig. S5 shows the expression of a reporter for Fas2 transcrip-
tion. Table S1 lists candidates tested in the Tao interaction screen. Table S2 
shows quantification of -Galactosidase signal intensities in wild-type and 
homo-and heterozygous Tao mutant cell clones. Table S3 shows quantifi-
cation of Fas2, Rab5, and Rab11 puncta and their subcellular distribution 
in wild-type egg chambers. Online supplemental material is available at 
http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201207150/DC1. </p>

<p> 
Tao controls epithelial morphogenesis • Gomez et al. </p>



</text></tei>