<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3829989" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Mediterranean Carthamus tinctorius (Safflower) is used for treatment of inflammatory conditions 
and neuropsychiatric disorders. Recently C. tinctorius lignans arctigenin and trachelogenin but not 
matairesinol were described to interfere with the activity of tryptophan-degrading enzyme indoleamine 
2,3-dioxygenase (IDO) in peripheral blood mononuclear cells in vitro . We examined a potential direct 
influence of compounds on IDO enzyme activity applying computational calculations based on 3D ge-
ometry of the compounds. The interaction pattern analysis and force field-based minimization was 
performed within <rs id="software-3" type="software">LigandScout</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">3.03</rs>, the docking simulation with <rs id="software-4" type="software">MOE</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">2011.10</rs> using the X-ray crystal 
structure of IDO. Results confirm the possibility of an intense interaction of arctigenin and trachelogenin 
with the binding site of the enzyme, while matairesinol had no such effect. 
The herbaceous Asteraceae plant Carthamus tinctorius (Safflower) 
has been used in traditional Chinese medicine to promote circula-
tion and menstruation [ 1 ] and to treat neuropsychological disorders 
such as major depression [ 2 ]. In the Mediterranean area, C. tinctorius 
extracts play a role in the treatment of cancer and are known for an-
tihelmintic, antiseptic, diuretic and febrifugal properties [ 3 ]. Most of 
the clinical conditions mentioned are associated with immune activa-
tion and inflammation which is characterized by specific biochemical 
alterations. Among them alterations of tryptophan metabolism ap-
pear to be most prominent. Tryptophan breakdown due to enzyme 
indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase (IDO) is involved in several physiologi-
cal and pathophysiological conditions. IDO is an iso-enzyme of trypto-
phan 2,3-dioxygenase (TDO), and both enzymes catalyze the first and 
rate limiting step of tryptophan catabolism namely the conversion of </p>

<p>ଝ This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike License, which permits non-commercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source 
are credited. 
Abbreviations: GBVI / WSA, generalized-born volume integral / weighted surface 
area; 5-HT, 5-hydroxytryptamine, serotonin; IDO, indoleamine 2,3-dioxygenase; IFN-
γ, interferon-γ; 1-MT, d -1-methyl tryptophan; Kyn / Trp, kynurenine to tryptophan 
ratio; MMFF94, Merck Molecular Force Field 94; PBMC, peripheral blood mononuclear 
cells; TDO, tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase; Treg, regulatory T-cells. 
* Corresponding author. Tel.: + 43 512 9003 70350; fax: + 43 512 9003 73110. 
E-mail address: dietmar.fuchs@i-med.ac.at (D. Fuchs). </p>

<p>tryptophan to N -formyl kynurenine. Whereas TDO is mainly located 
in the liver, IDO is more widely distributed in the organism [ 4 ]. During 
immune activation and inflammation IDO is mainly up-regulated by 
Th1-type cytokine interferon-γ (IFN-γ), and this is detectable locally 
and systemically by an increased tryptophan breakdown rate as is 
indicated by an increased kynurenine to tryptophan ratio (Kyn / Trp) 
[ 5 ], whereas in healthy conditions, the expression and activity of IDO 
is low. In animal model systems and in vitro , increased tryptophan 
breakdown was found to lead to immune tolerance via the induction 
of regulatory T-cells (Treg) and dendritic cells [ 6 , 7 ]. 
Tryptophan is also the substrate of the serotonin (5-
hydroxytryptamine, 5-HT) pathway and its breakdown leads to re-
duced synthesis of serotonin which is related to depression, as ob-
served, e.g., in cancer patients during treatment with IFNs [ 5 , 8 ]. Ad-
ditionally, the accumulation of tryptophan catabolites, such as 3-
hydroxykynurenine, kynurenic acid and quinolinic acid are believed 
to play a role in the pathogenesis of the AIDS-dementia complex, 
Huntington's disease, Alzheimer's disease, complex partial seizures, 
depression, anorexia and schizophrenia [ 9 ]. Thus, in neurological dis-
orders, IDO inhibitors are supposed to reduce the production of the 
neurotoxic tryptophan metabolites [ 10 ]. 
Based on the observations made in patients and the ethnophar-
macological use of Safflower, the three major lignans trachelogenin, 
arctigenin, and matairesinol ( Fig. 1 ) were isolated from C. tinctorius 
extracts and pharmacologically investigated for their ability to in-
terfere with activation of IDO in freshly isolated peripheral blood 
mononuclear cells (PBMC) [ 11 ]. Arctigenin and also trachelogenin </p>

<p>2211-5463/ $ 36.00 c 2013 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of Federation of European Biochemical Societies. All rights reserved. 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.fob.2013.08.008 </p>

<p>Veronika Temml et al. / FEBS Open Bio 3 (2013) 450-452 </p>



<p>Fig. 1. Chemical structures of compounds trachelogenin (1), arctigenin (2) and 
matairesinol (3). </p>

<p>exerted a significant and dose-dependent effect to suppress trypto-
phan breakdown in the PBMC model, whereas matairesinol was only 
weakly effective [ 12 ]. Because of the relatively strong effect of com-
pounds on tryptophan breakdown, we became interested to simulate 
possible direct interaction of the lignans with IDO, so a docking sim-
ulation was performed. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>During the docking simulation the previously energetically mini-
mized molecules were placed within the binding pocket of a protein, 
generating a set of energetically favorable poses. These poses are then 
ranked according to a score that the docking program assigns to each 
pose, estimating the binding free energy. The best ranked pose of each 
molecule was then further optimized and a three dimensional repre-
sentation of its interaction pattern, a pharmacophore, was calculated 
to analyze the structure-activity relationship. 
The possible direct interaction of the three lignans with IDO 
was simulated, 3D geometries of trachelogenin, arctigenin, and 
matairesinol were calculated with Discovery Studio [ 13 ] and ener-
getically minimized with <rs id="software-6" type="software">Omega</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">2.2.1</rs>. [ 14 ]. The docking simulation 
was performed with the software package <rs id="software-7" type="software">MOE</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">2011.10</rs> [ 15 ] using 
the X-ray crystal structure of IDO (Protein Data Bank entry 2d0t ) [ 16 ]. 
A pharmacophore of the metal binding feature was generated within 
LigandScout 3.03 [ 17 ] based on the ligand (4-phenyl-imidazole) co-
crystallized in the crystal structure and used as a constraint in the 
docking simulation. This means that the docked ligand must form a 
coordinated interaction with the heme iron ion from the IDO active 
site. For the docking, the A chain of 2d0t, which was crystallized as 
a dimer, was used. The original ligand 4-phenyl-imidazole, the two 
co-crystallized detergent molecules of 2-[ N -cyclohexylamino]ethane 
sulfonic acid, and water were removed. The binding site of the origi-
nal ligand was chosen for the docking. The program defines the open 
space in the binding pocket with so called alpha spheres that rep-
resent available atom positions. Placement was done by the triangle 
matcher algorithm using standard settings. The triangle matcher al-
gorithm generates poses by aligning triplets of ligand atoms with 
triplets of alpha spheres to find possible binding orientations of the 
ligand within the binding site. 
Rescoring was performed with London [ 18 ] and GBVI / WSA 
(Generalized-Born Volume Integral / Weighted Surface area) [ 19 ] scor-
ing functions to rank the resulting poses of each molecule. The London 
scoring function estimates the free energy of a pose by forming a sum 
of energy term (considering ligand flexibility, H-bonds and desolva-
tion) and geometric imperfections. The GBVI / WSA estimates the elec-
trostatic solvation using a weighted solvent-accessible surface area. 
For structure activity analysis the best ranked docking pose of each 
molecule was energetically minimized within LigandScout using the 
Merck Molecular Force Field 94 (MMFF94) force field for optimiza-
tion of the intermolecular interactions. 3D Protein-ligand interaction </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Arctigenin fitted into the active site of IDO. Yellow spheres signify hydrophobic 
interactions between the molecule and the binding pocket. The blue cone stands for a 
metal bond between the lactone ring and the iron of the heme group. The red arrows 
mark hydrogen bond acceptors between Cys129 and a phenolic hydroxyl group and 
Ser235 and an aromatic methoxy group. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. (A) Docking pose of trachelogenin inside the IDO active site. Yellow spheres 
show hydrophobic parts of the molecule. Red arrows mark hydrogen bond acceptors, 
the green arrow marks a hydrogen bond donor. The hydrogen bonds to Ser263 and 
Ala264 stabilize a position farther removed from the iron compared to arctigenin. (B) 
The missing methoxy group in matairesinol leads to a loss of stabilization, because the 
hydrogen bond to Ser235 is not formed. </p>

<p>patterns (pharmacophores) were automatically generated using de-
fault settings. The final structure-activity relationship investigation 
was based on these pharmacophores and not on the absolute dock-
ing scores, due to their well known limited quantitative reliability, 
especially in small datasets [ 20 ]. </p>

<p>3. Results and discussion </p>

<p>In order to suggest a binding mode for the three ligands, the com-
pounds were docked and energetically minimized into the active site 
of human IDO [ 16 ] ( Figs. 2 and 3 ). For arctigenin the lactone ring was 
placed very close to the catalytic iron, forming a metal binding fea-
ture that explains the strong activity. This pose was stabilized by two 
hydrogen bonds to Ser235 and Cys129 on each side of the molecule. 
Trachelogenin was placed in a similar pose, but due to hydrogen bonds 
between the lactone hydroxyl group and Ser263 / Ala264, the lactone 
was disposed from its ideal interaction geometry with the iron, pos-
sibly explaining the loss in activity ( Fig. 3 A). Compound matairesinol 
did not form the hydrogen bond with Ser235 and was less stabilized 
within the pocket ( Fig. 3 B). 
The computational calculations confirmed the possibility of an in-
tense interaction of two of out of the three lignin compounds with 
the binding site of the enzyme, and this was true for arctigenin and </p>



<p>Veronika Temml et al. / FEBS Open Bio 3 (2013) 450-452 </p>

<p>trachelogenin only while matairesinol had no such effect. So even 
in the case when the structural differences between the three com-
pounds appeared to be small at first glance, the interaction of them 
with the IDO binding site declined drastically. Thereby it is of par-
ticular interest to note that the dose-dependent suppressive effects 
which were observed in the in vitro test system of human PBMC were 
quite similar to the results of the calculations: also in PBMC arctigenin 
had the strongest influence on IDO activity followed by trachelogenin 
whereas matairesinol had no relevant effect. The calculated 50% in-
hibitory concentration (IC 50 value) was 26.5 μmol / L for arctigenin 
followed by trachelogenin (IC 50 = 57.4 μmol / L). Matairesinol showed 
only weak suppressive effects, decreasing KYN / TRP significantly only 
at a 193 μmol / L concentration. Moreover, IC 50 concentration of arcti-
genin was only approximately 2.5-fold higher than that of the classical 
IDO inhibitor d -1-methyl tryptophan (1-MT) with and IC 50 of 9.3 μM 
[ 12 ]. 
Molecular modeling calculation results showed that arctigenin 
and to a lesser extent also trachelogenin strongly interact with the 
IDO binding site, whereas matairesinol was predicted to be less stabi-
lized within the binding pocket. Especially a hydrogen bond between 
the ligand and Ser235 was predicted as crucial for activity. Any effect 
of arctigenin and possibly also of trachelogenin to directly inhibit IDO 
activity would have several therapeutic consequences for antidepres-
sant and immunomodulatory treatment strategies. It might explain 
treatment effects observed with C. tinctorius extracts in traditional 
medicine. However, further studies are needed to clarify this point 
and the possible application of arctigenin as an IDO inhibitor with 
additional immunomodulatory properties needs to be further tested 
in appropriate animal model systems. 
Several natural products such as curcumin or reservatrol have 
been tested for IDO inhibitory activity [ 21 , 22 ]. However, most of pub-
lished work employed assays based on cellular models like the hu-
man peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) assay [ 11 , 12 , 21 , 22 ], 
which was used also in this study and can detect a general effec-
tiveness on IFN-γ-induced biochemical pathways like IDO but no di-
rect influence of compounds on IDO is demonstrable. In most cases 
the suppression of tryptophan breakdown can be referred to an ef-
fect of compounds on IDO expression when the production of pro-
inflammatory cytokines like IFN-γ becomes diminished. Therefore 
in most studies also parallel suppression of neopterin production is 
demonstrable. From a structural perspective the lactone moiety can 
been observed in some other IDO inhibitory compounds, like war-
farin, coumarin and garvin B [ 23 ]. The lignan scaffold itself was (to 
our knowledge and recent literature search) not known to act on IDO 
previously. 
The inhibitory effect of compounds on IDO cannot imply 
a similar influence on tryptophan 2,3-dioxygenase (TDO), be-
cause structural homology between TDO and IDO is rather lim-
ited, Uniprot identity 12.357%, ( http: // www.uniprot.org / uniprot / 
?query = reviewed%3Ayes ), ClustalW alignment score −14 ( http: // 
www.ebi.ac.uk / Tools / msa / clustalw2 / ). While both the enzymes act 
via an activated heme, the binding pocket anatomy is very different 
[ 24 , 25 ]. We assume it is unlikely that compounds like arctigenin or 
trachelogenin would also bind to TDO. </p>



</text></tei>