<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3225968" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT The stress-responsive alternative sigma factor B is conserved across diverse Gram-positive bacterial genera. In Liste-
ria monocytogenes, B regulates transcription of &gt;150 genes, including genes contributing to virulence and to bacterial survival 
under host-associated stress conditions, such as those encountered in the human gastrointestinal lumen. An inhibitor of 
L. monocytogenes B activity was identified by screening~57,000 natural and synthesized small molecules using a high-
throughput cell-based assay. The compound fluoro-phenyl-styrene-sulfonamide (FPSS) (IC 50 ‫؍‬ 3.5 M) downregulated the ma-
jority of genes previously identified as members of the B regulon in L. monocytogenes 10403S, thus generating a transcriptional 
profile comparable to that of a 10403S ⌬sigB strain. Specifically, of the 208 genes downregulated by FPSS, 75% had been identi-
fied previously as positively regulated by B . Downregulated genes included key virulence and stress response genes, such as 
inlA, inlB, bsh, hfq, opuC, and bilE. From a functional perspective, FPSS also inhibited L. monocytogenes invasion of human in-
testinal epithelial cells and bile salt hydrolase activity. The ability of FPSS to inhibit B activity in both L. monocytogenes and 
Bacillus subtilis indicates its utility as a specific inhibitor of B across multiple Gram-positive genera. </p>

<p>IMPORTANCE The B transcription factor regulates expression of genes responsible for bacterial survival under changing envi-
ronmental conditions and for virulence; therefore, this alternative sigma factor is important for transmission of L. monocyto-
genes and other Gram-positive bacteria. Regulation of B activity is complex and tightly controlled, reflecting the key role of this 
factor in bacterial metabolism. We present multiple lines of evidence indicating that fluoro-phenyl-styrene-sulfonamide (FPSS) 
specifically inhibits activity of B across Gram-positive bacterial genera, i.e., in both Listeria monocytogenes and Bacillus subti-
lis. Therefore, FPSS is an important new tool that will enable novel approaches for exploring complex regulatory networks in 
L. monocytogenes and other Gram-positive pathogens and for investigating small-molecule applications for controlling patho-
gen transmission. </p>

<p>Citation Palmer ME, Chaturongakul S, Wiedmann M, and Boor KJ. 2011. The Listeria monocytogenes B regulon and its virulence-associated functions are inhibited by a small 
molecule. mBio 2(6):e00241-11. whole-genome microarray, quantitative reverse transcription-
PCR (qRT-PCR) of B -dependent genes, and phenotypic profil-
ing, including Caco-2 cell invasion assays and qualitative assess-
ment of bile salt hydrolase activity. The compound also was 
evaluated for its ability to inhibit B activity in B. subtilis. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A high-throughput cell-based screen identifies promising small 
molecules that interfere with B activity. A high-throughput 
cell-based screening assay (HTS) was used to identify compounds 
that inhibit expression of the B -dependent opuCA promoter (15) 
without affecting L. monocytogenes growth (Chembank Screening 
Project: SigBInhibition). Based on the primary screen, 41 putative 
inhibitors of B activity were selected for secondary cell-based 
screening (Fig. S1). Compounds that induced B activity were not 
analyzed further. 
IC 50 values, i.e., compound concentrations needed to inhibit 
50% of B activity, were determined from secondary screening 
results for each of the 41 compounds. For 14 compounds, B 
activity was inhibited at a concentration lower than that used in 
the primary screen; however, 11 compounds were eliminated 
from further consideration based on mammalian cell cytotox-
icity data in ChemBank (http://chembank.broad.harvard.edu). 
The three remaining L. monocytogenes B inhibitors were 
4-hydrazino[1]benzofuro[3,2-d]pyrimidine; 3-(cyclohexyla-
cetyl)-4-hydroxy-2H-chromen-2-one; 
and 
(E)-N,2-
diphenylethenesulfonamide. Among these, the most effective 
B activity inhibitor, (E)-N,2-diphenylethenesulfonamide 
(IC 50 ϭ~15 M), which was a member of the ChemDiv3 library 
(Table S1), was not commercially available. Therefore, fluoro-
phenyl-styrene-sulfonamide (FPSS), an analog of the original 
compound, was obtained for further study. Relative to (E)-N,2-
diphenylethenesulfonamide, FPSS has fluorine substituted for a 
hydrogen (Fig. 1). Based on quantitative reverse transcriptase 
PCR (qRT-PCR) results, FPSS was the most effective B inhibitor 
among the three compounds. Data available in ChemBank indi-
cated minimal evidence and no evidence of mammalian cell cyto-
toxicity for (E)-N,2-diphenylethenesulfonamide and FPSS, re-
spectively. 
We hypothesized that a small molecule that directly binds B 
might also prevent B from associating with core polymerase, 
thereby inhibiting B activity. Therefore, the ability of various 
small molecules to bind B was assessed using a small-molecule 
(SMM) screen with His-tagged B (Fig. S2; Table S1). Of three 
putative ligands-i.e., 3-amino-4-oxo-N-(pyridin-3-ylmethyl)-
3,4-dihydroquinazoline-2-carboxamide [Maybridge], ethyl 
1-benzyl-5-[3-(tert-butylamino)-2-hydroxypropoxy]-2-methyl-</p>

<p>1H-indole-3-carboxylate [Chemical Diversity], and 5-phenyl-
4,7-dihydrotetrazolo[1,5-a]pyrimidine [Maybridge])-none in-
hibited B activity in the bile salt hydrolase activity assay, and 
therefore, none were evaluated further. 
Multiple lines of evidence support B activity inhibition by 
FPSS. Quantitative qRT-PCR assessment of the effects of FPSS 
concentrations from 1 M to 64 M on B -dependent transcrip-
tion showed that exposure to 64 M FPSS resulted in a~40-fold 
reduction in transcript levels for both B -dependent genes opuCA 
and gadA relative to their transcript levels in cells not treated with 
FPSS (Fig. 2) (P Ͻ 0.05, GLM [general linear model] with post-
hoc Tukey's honestly significant difference [HSD] test). opuCA 
and gadA transcript levels in cells treated with FPSS (ranging from 
8 M to 64 M) were not significantly different from those in the 
⌬sigB strain (P Ͼ 0.05). At 4 M, FPSS significantly reduced 
opuCA and gadA transcript levels compared to those in 10403S 
without FPSS (P Ͻ 0.05) but not to levels equivalent to those in the 
⌬sigB strain (Fig. 2). The FPSS concentration yielding half the 
maximal inhibition (IC 50 ) was calculated as 3.5 M for opuCA 
and 3.0 M for gadA. Importantly, absolute transcript levels for 
the housekeeping genes rpoB and gap were not different in 
L. monocytogenes with and without exposure to FPSS, indicating 
that FPSS specifically inhibits transcription of B -dependent 
genes without affecting transcription of housekeeping genes. 
The phenotypic effects of various concentrations of FPSS on 
the activity of bile salt hydrolase, the product of the B -dependent 
gene bsh, which is required for L. monocytogenes survival in vivo 
(6), were qualitatively assessed. L. monocytogenes treated with 
96 M and 193 M FPSS showed no bile salt hydrolase (BSH) 
activity, with no apparent effect on the ability of L. monocytogenes 
to grow on brain heart infusion (BHI) agar. When treated with 
290 M FPSS, L. monocytogenes produced no BSH activity but also 
grew poorly on BHI (data not shown). 
L. monocytogenes whole genome microarray identified 208 
genes downregulated by treatment with FPSS. Transcriptional 
consequences of FPSS treatment were profiled using an L. mono-
cytogenes whole-genome microarray. FPSS treatment downregu-
lated transcript levels for 208 genes and upregulated transcript 
levels for 32 genes (adjusted P value of Ͻ0.05 and an absolute fold 
change [FC] value of Ն2). In previous studies with L. monocyto-
genes 10403S and EGD-e, 281 genes were identified as positively 
regulated by B under at least one assay condition, and 137 genes 
as positively regulated by B under two or more of the seven assay 
conditions examined (5-8, 16, 17) (Table S2). Overall, FPSS sig-
nificantly reduced transcript levels of 56% (156/281) of genes pre-
viously identified as being upregulated by B in at least one study 
and of Ͼ91% (125/137) of genes identified as being upregulated 
by B in two or more studies (Table 1; Table S3). Of the 208 
FPSS-downregulated genes, 115 were reported to be positively 
regulated by B in both 10403S and EGD-e (5-8, 16, 17), with an 
additional 21 genes reported to be positively regulated by B in 
10403S (5, 7, 8, 17) and 20 reported to be positively regulated by 
B in EGD-e (6, 16). FPSS downregulated transcript levels for 
Ͼ90% of genes with previously reported hidden Markov model-
identified B -dependent promoters (17). A number of operons 
previously identified as being positively regulated by B (8) were 
also significantly downregulated after treatment with FPSS, in-
cluding inlAB, which mediates entry into nonprofessional phago-
cytes (18), and opuCABCD, which is involved in compatible solute 
transport. The autoregulated sigB operon (7, 8, 19), consisting of </p>

<p>FIG 1 Chemical structure of the B activity inhibitor FPSS (fluoro-phenyl-</p>

<p>styrene-sulfonamide). FPSS is a derivative of (E)-N,2-diphenylethene-
sulfonamide, the compound originally identified by HTS as the most effective 
inhibitor of B activity. Relative to the structure of (E)-N,2-
diphenylethenesulfonamide, FPSS has a fluorine substituted for a hydrogen. </p>

<p>Palmer et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>

<p>lmo0893 to lmo0896 (rsbV, rsbW, sigB, and rsbX), was also down-
regulated by FPSS. 
To evaluate FPSS effects on the function of other alternative 
sigma factors, transcript levels for genes in the H and L regulons 
were assessed. Among the 30 genes previously identified as H 
dependent (with an FC Ն 2.0), 14 were significantly downregu-
lated by FPSS (adjusted P Ͻ 0.05, fold change Յ Ϫ2); however, 12 
of those 14 genes are also B dependent. Gene set enrichment 
analysis (GSEA) showed that the H -only regulon (i.e., genes that 
are regulated only by H and not coregulated by B ) was not 
significantly enriched among the genes differentially transcribed 
as a result of FPSS treatment (false discovery rate [FDR] q ϭ 
0.472). GSEA also showed that the L regulon was not significantly 
enriched as a result of treatment with FPSS (FDR q ϭ 0.836). </p>

<p>GSEA was used to determine if genes from specific biological 
role categories were overrepresented among those differentially 
affected by FPSS. Consistent with B 's role in bacterial stress re-
sponse, gene sets enriched among FPSS-downregulated genes in-
cluded those classified as (i) "Cellular Processes: Adaptations to 
Atypical Conditions" and (ii) "Energy Metabolism (other)" (FDR 
q ϭ 0.060 and q ϭ 0.201, respectively). Previously identified B -
regulated genes also were significantly enriched among FPSS-
downregulated genes (FDR q Ͻ 0.0001). Gene sets enriched 
among FPSS-upregulated genes included those classified as (i) 
"Cellular Processes: Chemotaxis and Motility," (ii) "Protein Fate: 
Protein Folding and Stabilization," and (iii) "Amino Acid Biosyn-
thesis: Histidine Family" (FDR q Ͻ 0.0001, q ϭ 0.008, and q ϭ 
0.031, respectively). </p>

<p>FIG 2 FPSS treatment reduces transcript levels of B -dependent opuCA and gadA. Normalized log-transformed opuCA (A) and gadA (B) transcript levels in 
L. monocytogenes 10403S exposed to 0.3 M NaCl to induce B activity in the presence of FPSS at concentrations ranging from 1 to 64 M; controls included strains 
10403S and its isogenic ⌬sigB mutant exposed to 0.3 M NaCl. Transcript levels were quantified by qRT-PCR, log 10 transformed, and normalized to the geometric 
mean of the transcript levels for the housekeeping genes rpoB and gap. The data are means from three replicates; error bars show the standard deviations. </p>

<p>Small-Molecule Inhibitor of L. monocytogenes B </p>

<p>November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 3 </p>

<p>Of the 208 FPSS-downregulated genes, 126 were positively reg-
ulated by B during infection in the murine intestine (6), includ-
ing 17 genes that had been identified as B dependent only in the 
intestinal environment (Table S2). Among these 17 genes, 9 genes 
were of unknown or hypothetical function. Several FPSS-
downregulated genes are recognized as contributing to virulence 
and host infection (i.e., inlA, inlB inlD, bilEAB, bsh, hfq, clpC, 
opuC, and gadA). Further, the PrfA regulon (i.e., genes regulated 
by the pleiotropic virulence gene regulator PrfA) was significantly 
enriched among the genes downregulated by FPSS (FDR q ϭ 
0.095). Interestingly, 19 genes that were previously classified as 
coregulated by PrfA and B (10, 20) were both upregulated in the 
mouse spleen (10) and downregulated by FPSS, further support-
ing their B -dependent transcription. Among these 19 genes, 
three were identified as potential virulence factors in murine and 
tissue culture models (10, 22), including lmo1601 (encoding a 
general stress protein), lmo1602 (encoding an unknown protein), 
and lmo2157 (encoding SepA, a metalloprotease in Staphylococcus 
epidermidis [21]), which is upregulated in L. monocytogenes dur-
ing intracellular infection (22). FPSS also downregulated lmo0937, 
a PrfA-regulated gene that is upregulated in the mouse spleen at 
48 h postinfection (10), and lmo0915, which encodes a component 
of a phosphotransferase system identified as a potential virulence 
factor by Camejo et al. (10); neither gene had been identified pre-
viously as B dependent. Other B -dependent genes downregu-
lated by FPSS and upregulated during intracellular infection (22)  include lmo0232 (clpC); lmo0445, which encodes a transcriptional 
regulator; lmo2672, which encodes a protein similar to a transcrip-
tional regulator; and lmo0783, which is a member of an operon 
encoding mannose phosphotransferase system components. </p>

<p>FPSS-treated cells had lower transcript levels for a number of 
genes that encode cell wall-associated proteins previously shown 
to be upregulated under intracellular conditions (22) and in the 
murine intestine (6); these genes include inlA, inlD, lmo0610, 
lmo0880, and lmo2085, which all encode proteins with an LPXTG 
sorting motif for cell wall anchoring, and inlB, which encodes a 
protein with a GW domain that is important for binding host 
ligands (23). 
Three genes important for glycerol utilization (i.e., lmo1538, 
lmo1539, and lmo1293) were also downregulated by FPSS; utiliza-
tion of glycerol as a carbon source in intracellular environments 
(22) is required for intracellular survival (24). While lmo1538 (en-
coding a glycerol kinase) and lmo1539 (encoding a glycerol uptake 
facilitator) were downregulated by FPSS, they were previously re-
ported to be negatively regulated by B in stationary phase and 
under salt stress conditions (8). Interestingly, however, both genes 
were upregulated by B in the intestine (6) and during intracellu-
lar replication (22). lmo1293 (glpD), which encodes a glycerol-3-
phosphate dehydrogenase, was previously reported to be posi-
tively regulated by B in L. monocytogenes exposed to salt stress (8)  or grown intracellularly (24) and in the gastrointestinal tract (6)  but was downregulated by B in stationary-phase cells (8). Taken 
together, our data provide additional evidence supporting the hy-
pothesis that the composition of the B regulon is dynamically 
dependent on environmental conditions (7). Importantly, our 
data also demonstrate that a number of genes downregulated by 
FPSS are specifically regulated by B in the gastrointestinal envi-
ronment. For example, three additional genes downregulated by 
FPSS (i.e., lmo0642, lmo1251, and lmo1930) had higher transcript 
levels in the L. monocytogenes parent strain than in the ⌬sigB strain 
when both were grown in the murine intestine (6), but these genes 
did not appear to be B dependent under other in vitro conditions 
(5, 7, 8, 16, 17)  Only a small number of genes upregulated by FPSS have been 
identified previously as negatively regulated by B . Overall, 32 
genes were identified with significantly higher transcript levels in 
FPSS-treated L. monocytogenes than in untreated cells (Table 1), 
suggesting negative regulation of these genes by B . While 264 
genes were previously identified as negatively regulated by B un-
der at least one condition (5-8, 16, 17), only 7 of the 32 FPSS-
upregulated genes were represented among these 264 genes. Fur-
ther, only 14 genes were previously identified as negatively 
regulated by B under at least two environmental conditions (5-8,  16, 17) and none of the 32 FPSS-upregulated genes were repre-
sented among these 14 genes. Very few genes appear to be consis-
tently repressed by B under various conditions, likely because 
these genes are indirectly rather than directly regulated by B . Six 
of the 7 FPSS-upregulated genes previously identified as nega-
tively regulated by B encode proteins with known functions, in-
cluding an ABC transporter (lmo2114), a posttranslocation chap-
erone (prsA), a methyl-accepting chemotaxis protein (lmo1699 
and lmo1700), NADP glutamate dehydrogenase (lmo0560), and a 
D-alanine-activating enzyme (dltA). While dltA (the first gene in 
an operon encoding proteins that modify lipoteichoic and wall 
teichoic acids) was previously shown to be negatively regulated by 
B , other genes in this operon (i.e., lmo0973 [dltB] and lmo0971 
[dltD]) not previously identified as B dependent were also signif-
icantly upregulated following FPSS treatment, suggesting that this 
entire operon is negatively regulated by B , at least under some 
conditions. Two genes, lmo2568 (unknown function) and </p>

<p>TABLE 1 Relationships between genes identified as differentially 
expressed after treatment with FPSS and genes identified previously as 
B dependent </p>

<p>Gene type </p>

<p>No. of genes (no. with an upstream 
B -dependent promoter a ) </p>

<p>Downregulated 
by FPSS </p>

<p>Upregulated 
by FPSS </p>

<p>Identified previously 
as positively regulated by Bb </p>

<p>152 (86) 
2 (0) </p>

<p>Identified previously 
as negatively regulated by Bc </p>

<p>2 (0) 
7 (0) </p>

<p>Reported previously 
to be positively or negatively 
regulated under different conditions 
or in different studies d </p>

<p>4 (0) 
0 </p>

<p>Having no previous evidence 
of B -dependent transcript levels </p>

<p>50 (0) 
23 (0) </p>

<p>Total 
208 (86) 
32 (0) </p>

<p>a Genes were classified with upstream B -dependent promoters by in silico analysis 
using a hidden Markov model as described by Oliver et al. (17). 
b Genes were classified as positively regulated by B based on evidence from at least one 
of six previous microarray or RNA-Seq studies (5-8, 16, 17) (see Tables S2 and S3 for 
details). 
c Genes were classified as negatively regulated by B based on evidence from at least 
one of six previous microarray or RNA-Seq studies (5-8, 16, 17) (see Tables S2 and S4 
for details). 
d Genes reported as differentially regulated in previous microarray or RNA-Seq studies 
(5-8, 16, 17), including genes reported as negatively regulated by B in one study and 
positively regulated by B in another study and genes that were found to be negatively 
and positively regulated by B under different conditions in the same study (see 
Table S2). </p>

<p>Palmer et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>

<p>lmo1637 (encoding a protein similar to a membrane protein), 
were upregulated by FPSS but had previously been reported to be 
positively regulated by B in the intestine (6) and during various 
growth phases (16), respectively. Among the genes not previously 
reported as B dependent that were upregulated by FPSS, some 
were involved in ABC transport, motility, and cell division, but 
most had unknown functions (Table S4). 
Further supporting the idea that FPSS treatment of L. monocy-
togenes generates the equivalent of a ⌬sigB phenotype, GSEA iden-
tified genes in the "motility and chemotaxis" role category as en-
riched among genes upregulated by FPSS (FDR q Ͻ 0.0001), 
consistent with previous reports that B negatively regulates 
motility-related functions (8). In addition, six FPSS-upregulated 
genes (lmo0678 to lmo0681, lmo0685, and lmo0686) not described 
previously as negatively regulated by B were located in a large 
flagellar biosynthesis and motility operon (lmo0673 to lmo0718) 
containing 13 genes recognized as negatively regulated by B (8). 
As transcription of a number of motility related genes was affected 
by FPSS, GSEA was also performed on the regulons of the known 
chemotaxis-and motility-related regulators DegU, MogR, and 
CodY. The DegU operon, as defined by Williams et al. (25), was 
enriched among FPSS-upregulated genes (FDR q Ͻ 0.0001); 
DegU is an activator of flagellum biosynthesis (26). Specific 
DegU-regulated genes identified among the FPSS-upregulated 
genes include six genes in the flagellum biosynthesis operon 
(lmo0673 to lmo0718) as well as the B -repressed (8) methyl-
accepting chemotaxis operon (lmo1699 and lmo1700) (25). The 
CodY regulon was also significantly enriched among FPSS-
upregulated genes (FDR q Ͻ 0.0001); CodY is a negative regulator 
of genes encoding flagellar components in L. monocytogenes (27). 
Although MogR, the transcriptional repressor of flagellum genes 
(28, 29), was shown previously to be B dependent (6), its regulon 
(29) was not significantly enriched among the genes differentially 
regulated by FPSS (FDR q ϭ 0.257). 
FPSS reduces L. monocytogenes invasion of human entero-
cytes. FPSS treatment (at either 8 M or 64 M) reduced L. mono-
cytogenes' ability to invade Caco-2 human enterocytes by 1.50 log 
(Ϯ 0.49) and 1.42 log (Ϯ 0.39), respectively, compared to the 
untreated control bacteria (Fig. S3) (P Ͻ 0.05). Invasion of 
L. monocytogenes treated with 8 M FPSS was not significantly </p>

<p>different from invasion by the ⌬sigB strain, which also showed 
significantly reduced invasion compared to the untreated parent 
strain (P Ͻ 0.05), providing phenotypic evidence of FPSS inhibi-
tion of B -regulated virulence functions that contribute to orally 
acquired listeriosis (9). 
FPSS inhibits B activity in B. subtilis, indicating effective-
ness across genera. To determine if FPSS affects B activity in 
bacteria other than L. monocytogenes, the compound was tested 
for its ability to specifically inhibit B activity in B. subtilis. FPSS 
(64 M) significantly inhibited B -dependent ctc-lacZ activity (P 
Ͻ 0.05; GLM with post-hoc Tukey's HSD test) to levels equivalent 
to those in a ⌬sigB strain (Fig. 3) (P Ͼ 0.05) without reducing 
␤-galactosidase activity from a A -dependent lacZ fusion (30) 
(Fig. 3), further supporting FPSS specificity for inhibiting B ac-
tivity. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>By using a high-throughput screen of approximately 57,000 small 
molecules, 41 candidate compounds were identified as potential 
inhibitors of L. monocytogenes B activity. Through subsequent 
screens, we identified a compound designated FPSS that specifi-
cally inhibits B -mediated transcription, as shown by qRT-PCR of 
B -dependent genes and whole-genome microarray analysis of 
cells treated with the compound. This compound also signifi-
cantly reduces L. monocytogenes invasion into human intestinal 
epithelial cells and inhibits B -directed activity in the Gram-
positive bacterium B. subtilis, indicating that this compound in-
hibits B -mediated transcription across genera. Overall, our data 
show that FPSS (i) inhibits expression of the B regulon with high 
specificity, yielding transcriptional profiles similar to those gener-
ated by a genetic null mutation of the sigB gene, and (ii) specifi-
cally inhibits expression of B -dependent genes important for vir-
ulence, stress response, and other functions associated with 
L. monocytogenes survival and growth in the gastrointestinal tract. 
In combination with previous reports that identified small mole-
cules that interfere with virulence factors and virulence activation 
and that show therapeutic promise (14, 31), our results suggest 
that, in addition to its role as a promising tool for studying regu-
latory networks involving B , FPSS also may represent a com-
pound that can be developed into a therapeutic agent. </p>

<p>FIG 3 B. subtilis ␤-galactosidase assay. (A) ␤-Galactosidase activity of a B. subtilis strain with a B -dependent Pctc-lacZ reporter fusion treated with (i) 0.3 M 
NaCl and DMSO, (ii) 0.3 M NaCl and 64 M FPSS, and (iii) 0.3 M NaCl and 8 M FPSS; this panel also shows the activity for an isogenic ⌬sigB strain with the 
Pctc-lacZ reporter fusion treated with 0.3 M NaCl and DMSO. (B) ␤-Galactosidase activity of a B. subtilis strain with a A -dependent PrsbRSTU-lacZ fusion 
treated with either (i) 0.3 M NaCl and 64 M FPSS or (ii) 0.3 M NaCl and DMSO. The data are means from at least three biological replicates; error bars show 
the standard deviations. Different letters above the bars indicate strains or treatments that differed significantly (P Ͻ 0.05; GLM Tukey). </p>

<p>Small-Molecule Inhibitor of L. monocytogenes B </p>

<p>November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 5 </p>

<p>FPSS specifically inhibits expression of B -dependent viru-
lence, stress response, and other functions that are associated 
with L. monocytogenes growth and survival in the gastrointesti-
nal tract. B is well recognized as an important transcriptional 
regulator in multiple Gram-positive genera. For example, B reg-
ulates transcription of genes contributing to stress response, vir-
ulence, or both in low-GC Gram-positive microbes, including hu-
man pathogens such as Bacillus cereus (32, 33), Bacillus anthracis 
(34), Staphylococcus aureus (35, 36), and the opportunistic patho-
gen S. epidermidis (37). B activates transcription of a large num-
ber of target genes across the genera and species reported to date 
(e.g., L. monocytogenes, Listeria innocua, S. aureus, and B. subtilis) 
(8, 38, 39). FPSS treatment of L. monocytogenes affects expression 
of B -dependent genes that are upregulated in the host intestine 
but that had not been identified previously as B dependent under 
other in vitro conditions. Specifically, among 172 genes in 
L. monocytogenes EGD-e that were upregulated by B in the mu-
rine intestinal lumen (6), FPSS treatment significantly downregu-
lated 126 genes; 17 genes downregulated by FPSS had been iden-
tified as B dependent only in the intestinal lumen (6) but not in 
other in vitro test systems. Thus, identification of B -dependent 
genes in L. monocytogenes treated with FPSS may provide new 
insight into B -dependent gene regulation that may be critical 
during the gastrointestinal stage of infection. For example, the 
PrfA regulon was significantly enriched among genes downregu-
lated by FPSS treatment, including two PrfA-dependent genes 
(i.e., lmo0937 and plcA) that had not been identified previously as 
B regulated. These findings are consistent with B 's role, via the 
P2 prfA promoter, in directly upregulating prfA transcription (11- 13) and also support the idea that B -dependent upregulation of 
prfA transcription plays a critical role during intestinal stages of 
infection. Activation of B in the intestinal lumen thus appears to 
increase expression of B -dependent inlA, which is required for 
intestinal epithelial cell invasion (40), and also primes expression 
of PrfA, which is critical for regulating virulence gene expression 
during the subsequent intracellular stages of infection. 
FPSS-treated L. monocytogenes also had higher transcript levels 
than nontreated cells for a number of genes involved in che-
motaxis and motility. Several genes in a large operon encoding 
flagellar structural components were previously reported to be 
negatively regulated by B (8), and sigB-null mutants also exhib-
ited increased swarming (6, 8). B -dependent downregulation of 
transcripts encoding flagellar components and overall motility ap-
pear to be at least partially due to B -dependent transcription of a 
long untranslated region (UTR) upstream of mogR, which en-
codes a negative regulator of L. monocytogenes motility. Reduced 
transcription of this UTR not only reduces mogR transcript levels 
(thereby increasing flagellar motility) but also appears to increase 
transcript levels for some flagellar genes, as the B -dependent 
UTR also decreases flagellin gene transcripts through an 
antisense-RNA-type mechanism (6, 8). While L. monocytogenes 
flagellar motility appears to contribute to intestinal invasion (41), 
B -dependent downregulation of flagellar expression in the intes-
tinal lumen may be critical for subsequent stages of infection, as 
Listeria downregulates flagellar gene expression during infection 
(10) to evade the immune system; increased expression of flagellar 
components can induce potent proinflammatory effects via 
TLR5-mediated immunogenicity (42). 
Inhibitors of alternative factor activation represent poten-
tial avenues for development into therapeutics. In addition to its </p>

<p>value as a compound that can be used to study regulatory path-
ways involving B , FPSS also may provide a starting point for 
development of new therapeutic compounds that interfere with 
regulatory pathways critical for infection and virulence. Several 
small molecules that target transcription regulators inhibit viru-
lence and virulence-associated characteristics in vitro and in vivo, 
suggesting that these targets are suitable for development of novel 
therapeutics against bacterial infections (43, 44). Importantly, 
prokaryotic transcriptional machinery, as represented by interac-
tions between 70 and the ␤= subunit of core RNA polymerase in 
Escherichia coli, can be disrupted by small molecules without af-
fecting eukaryotic transcription (45). Consequently, the thera-
peutic potential of novel compounds that interfere with transcrip-
tional regulation of bacterial virulence functions is of emerging 
interest. 
Virstatin is an example of a small molecule with therapeutic 
potential that has been shown to inhibit transcriptional regulation 
in V. cholerae. Virstatin interferes with the virulence gene regula-
tor ToxT, a member of the AraC family of transcriptional regula-
tors, thus showing potential for treatment of Vibrio infections 
(14). Small-molecule inhibitors also have been identified for other 
members of the AraC transcription factor family, e.g., MarA, SoxS 
and Rob in E. coli (43) and LcrF in Yersinia spp. (44). As with B , 
AraC-type regulators typically contribute to transcription of mul-
tiple stress response (46) and virulence factors (47, 48); therefore, 
inhibition of these and similar transcriptional regulators can re-
sult in broad physiological consequences for the affected microbes 
(43). 
The small molecule identified here, FPSS, inhibits B activity at 
an IC 50 of 3 to 3.5 M. By comparison, the ToxT inhibitor virsta-
tin (14) has an MIC between 3 and 40 M, depending on the 
target strain. Minimal bactericidal concentrations of gentamicin, 
ampicillin, and streptomycin against L. monocytogenes range from 
2 to 46 M (49). In addition to its promising IC 50 prior to struc-
tural optimization, FPSS produces highly specific, genome-wide 
reduction of B -directed activity, including inhibited expression 
of B -dependent virulence genes such as inlAB, bsh, bilE, clpC, and 
hfq (5-8, 16, 17). Furthermore, opuC (50) and gadA (51), which 
are important for gastrointestinal survival in the host, are also 
significantly downregulated by FPSS. FPSS clearly inhibits tran-
scription of a number of genes with functions in virulence and 
infection, thus increasing its therapeutic potential over com-
pounds that target only one virulence factor (43). The contribu-
tions of B to L. monocytogenes virulence are also supported by 
phenotypic evidence, including reduced virulence of a ⌬sigB 
strain in a guinea pig model of infection (9) and reduced invasion 
of human Caco-2 cells by a ⌬sigB strain (9, 40), consistent with the 
reduced invasiveness for FPSS-treated L. monocytogenes observed 
here. Importantly, B also contributes to establishment of infec-
tion and virulence in other Gram-positive pathogens, including 
B. anthracis and S. aureus. A B. anthracis sigB mutant is less viru-
lent than the parent strain, producing a 1-log reduction in 50% 
lethal dose, perhaps because B enhances the ability of B. anthracis 
to persist in the bloodstream of a mammalian host (34). In S. au-
reus, B directly and indirectly modulates global regulatory ele-
ments involved in virulence functions (52). Functional loss of B 
results in decreased S. aureus virulence in central venous catheter-
related diseases manifested by significantly reduced multiorgan 
infection (53). Similar to B. anthracis, B is suggested to promote 
S. aureus survival in the bloodstream, preventing clearance and </p>

<p>Palmer et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>

<p>allowing establishment of infection (54). Further development 
and optimization of FPSS thus may provide an opportunity to 
develop novel therapeutics for some important Gram-positive 
pathogens. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Strain and media selection. Strains used in this study included the 
L. monocytogenes parent strain 10403S (serotype 1/2a) (55), its otherwise 
isogenic ⌬sigB derivative (FSL A1-254) (56), a reporter strain for B ac-
tivity (FSL S1-063 [10403S opuCA-gus]) (7, 57, 58), and a negative-
control reporter strain for B activity (FSL S1-059 [⌬sigB opuCA-gus]) 
(Table S5). To evaluate the effectiveness of a selected small molecule to 
inhibit B activity in a Gram-positive genus other than Listeria, B. subtilis 
strains bearing reporter fusions for either B or A activity and a ⌬sigB 
negative-control reporter strain (Table S5) were also tested. To achieve 
low background fluorescence, a chemically defined minimal medium (59)  with 25 mM glucose (DMG) (60) was used for the high-throughput 
screen. Cells were grown in brain heart infusion broth (BHI; Difco, 
Sparks, MD) for phenotypic and transcriptional profiling assays. 
Primary high-throughput cell-based small-molecule screen. The 
L. monocytogenes opuCA-gus fusion strain FSL S1-063 was used in a cell-
based high-throughput screen (HTS) against~57,000 compounds. As 
reported at http://ChemBank.Broad.Harvard.edu, the libraries included 
the following: (i) known bioactive compounds, including FDA-approved 
drugs (i.e., the SPBio and SMP libraries); (ii) synthetic compounds from 
diversity-oriented synthesis (e.g., the CMLD, ICCB, PK04, Ald1.1-H, and 
Sulf1.1-A libraries); (iii) natural products (i.e., the PhilEx and ICBGEx 
libraries); and (iv) commercially available compounds (e. g., the Chem-
Div3, Maybridge4, and TimTec1 libraries). Table S1 contains a complete 
listing of libraries screened for this study. 
Multidrop liquid-handling robots (Matrix, Thermo Fisher) were used 
to dispense 27 l of DMG into black-walled clear-bottom 384-well plates 
(Nunc, Rochester, NY), and then 100 nl of each small-molecule stock was 
transferred from the library stock or source plate to the assay plates with a 
CyBi-Well Vario pipettor (CyBio AG, Jena, Germany). Final experimental 
concentrations of the small molecules used in the assays were dependent 
on each stock concentration [e.g., (E)-N,2-diphenylethenesulfonamide 
had a stock concentration of 19.3 mM, producing a 64.3 M final con-
centration in each well]. Each source plate contained approximately 15 
wells to which only dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) was added, as the small 
molecules were dissolved in DMSO; these wells are referred to as DMSO-
only negative-internal-control wells. All source plates were prepared in 
duplicate to provide experimental replicates (i.e., plates A and B). Two 
plates in which all wells contained medium with DMSO and L. monocy-
togenes (inoculated as detailed below) were included as external plate con-
trols. L. monocytogenes strains were grown to an optical density at 600 nm 
(OD 600 ) of approximately 0.4 (3 hours) in BHI, cultures were diluted 1:50 
with DMG, and then 3 l of the appropriate diluted culture was added to 
each well. As a control, a custom assay plate containing 192 wells of the 
10403S opuCA-gus strain FSL S1-063 and 192 wells of the otherwise iso-
genic ⌬sigB opuCA-gus strain FSL S1-059 was treated with only DMSO. 
All plates were sealed and incubated for 18 h at 37°C. To determine 
bacterial growth or inhibition in the presence of the compounds, absor-
bance (OD 600 ) was measured using a Synergy HT multimode microplate 
reader (Biotek Instruments, Winooski, VT) after~18 h of incubation. To 
measure fluorescence for ␤-glucuronidase (GUS) activity determination, 
black seals (PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA) were affixed to the bottoms of 
the plates after the absorbance readings were completed. Cells were then 
lysed using 5 l of 2ϫ CelLyticB (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) and a protease 
inhibitor cocktail mixture (1 ml 2ϫ CelLyticB and 0.05 ml protease in-
hibitor cocktail; Sigma), immediately prior to the addition of 4 l of 
1.6 mg/ml 4-methylumbelliferyl ␤-D-glucuronide hydrate (4-MUG; 
Sigma) in DMSO. Reaction mixtures were incubated in the dark for 1 h at 
room temperature (~23°C), and reactions were stopped by the addition of 
0.2 M Na 2 CO 3 . Fluorescence was read using a Wallac 2102 EnVision Mul-</p>

<p>tilabel Reader (PerkinElmer) with an excitation wavelength of 355 nm and 
an emission of 460 nm. 
Statistical analysis of primary screen data. To identify compounds 
that inhibited B activity without affecting L. monocytogenes growth, 
opuCA-directed GUS activity in the presence of each compound was cal-
culated by dividing relative fluorescence units (RFU) by cell density in 
OD 600 units (RFU/OD) (61). Statistical analyses were conducted in col-
laboration with the Broad Institute and performed as previously described 
(62, 63). Raw and analyzed data were deposited in ChemBank (64, 65). 
The software package <rs id="software-1" type="software">Spotfire DecisionSite Analytics</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">TIBCO Spotfire</rs>, 
Somerville, MA) was used for two-dimensional data visualization. 
Secondary screen and dose response curve. Forty-one compounds 
that appeared to inhibit B activity (Z score of Յ-3 in both replicates) 
were selected for secondary cell-based screening using the assay and re-
porter fusion described above to calculate initial IC 50 s. Each compound 
was diluted in DMSO in a series of six 1/5 dilutions of the initial stock 
concentration [e.g., starting from 19.3 mM stock, (E)-N,2-
diphenylethenesulfonamide was diluted in a series of six 1 to 5 dilutions, 
yielding concentrations of 3.86 mM to 1.24 M]. The small molecules at 
these concentrations were then dispensedinto the assay plates. 
Small-molecule microarray screens. Two different arrays, each 
printed with 8,500 small-molecule (SM) spots and 1,500 DMSO control 
spots, were used to screen for binding of B to the small molecules. Small-
molecule microarrays (SMMs) were printed on glass slides at the Broad 
Institute as described previously (66-68). The immobilized SMs included 
8,500 compounds created by diversity-oriented synthesis and 8,500 com-
pounds representing natural products, FDA-approved drug-like com-
pounds, commercial compounds, and known bioactive compounds (Ta-
ble S1) (68; http://Chembank.broadinstitute.org). SMM screening (three 
replicates) was performed as described by Bradner et al. (66). His-tagged 
B was purified from E. coli M15, kindly provided by W. Goebel (69). Data 
analyses included (i) assessment of signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) of the spot 
feature; (ii) Z score calculations based on comparison of signals from 
compound spots to signals from DMSO control spots within a slide; and 
(iii) composite Z score calculations for data from the three replicates. 
Spotfire Analytics software was used for three-dimensional data visualiza-
tion. 
FPSS. (E)-N,2-diphenylethenesulfonamide, the compound identified 
by HTS as being responsible for the greatest inhibition of B activity, was 
not commercially available. Therefore, the analog fluoro-phenyl-styrene-
sulfonamide [IUPAC name (E)-N-(4-fluorophenyl)-2-phenylethenesul-
fonamide; ChemBank ID, 2063822; MW 277.3] was obtained from Enam-
ine Ltd. (Kiev, Ukraine). FPSS was dissolved in DMSO to a concentration 
of 10 mM. The solution was filter sterilized using with a 0.1-m filter 
(Omnipore membrane filter; Millipore Corporation, Billerica, MA) and a 
Swinney stainless 13-mm holder for syringe filtration (Millipore Corpo-
ration). 
Bile salt hydrolase (BSH) activity assay. As L. monocytogenes bsh, 
which encodes bile salt hydrolase, is B dependent (5, 7, 15), a qualitative 
BSH activity assay was used to determine the FPSS concentration needed 
for B inhibition. Four-well multidish plates (26 mm by 33 mm; Nunc) 
containing 6 ml of either BHI agar or de Man, Rogosa and Sharp (MRS) 
agar medium (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA) containing 0.5% (wt/vol) 
glycodeoxycholic acid sodium (GDCA) salt (Calbiochem, San Diego, CA) 
(70) with either no FPSS or 96, 193, or 290 M of FPSS [1.5, 3, or 4.5 times 
the 64.3 M concentration used for (E)-N,2-diphenylethenesulfonamide 
in the HTS] were prepared and allowed to dry overnight. L. monocytogenes 
10403S and ⌬sigB were grown in BHI broth to exponential phase, defined 
as an OD 600 of 0.4, and then 4 l of culture was spotted in parallel on MRS 
and BHI agars. The MRS agar plates were incubated anaerobically using 
the BD-BBL GasPak anaerobic system (Becton Dickinson, Franklin Lakes, 
NJ), while BHI plates were incubated aerobically. Both sets of plates were 
incubated for 48 h at 37°C and then were visually assessed for growth (BHI 
plates) or the presence of a white precipitate comprised of deconjugated </p>

<p>Small-Molecule Inhibitor of L. monocytogenes B </p>

<p>November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 7 </p>

<p>bile salts indicating BSH activity (MRS plates). The assay was performed 
three times. 
RNA isolation. For RNA isolation, L. monocytogenes 10403S and ⌬sigB 
strains were initially grown overnight in 5 ml of BHI broth at 37°C with 
shaking (230 rpm), followed by subculturing twice, each time at an OD 600 
of 0.4, using a 1% (vol/vol) transfer into 5 ml of prewarmed BHI. When 
the second subculture reached an OD 600 of 0.4, cells were treated with a 
total volume of 76 l comprising FPSS (to yield final concentrations rang-
ing from 1 M to 128 M) and/or DMSO, followed immediately by 
addition of 324 l of either 5 M NaCl (to yield a final concentration of 
0.3 M NaCl, an osmotic stress that induces B activity [8]) or (ii) sterile 
distilled water. Treated cultures were then incubated at 37°C with shaking 
(230 rpm) for 10 min, followed by addition of 2 volumes of RNAprotect 
(Qiagen Inc., Valencia, CA) and subsequent incubation at room temper-
ature for 10 min. The cells were harvested following centrifugation for 
10 min at 5,000 ϫ g, and cell pellets were stored at Ϫ80°C until RNA was 
extracted and DNase treated using an Ambion RiboPure kit (Ambion, 
Austin, TX) according to the manufacturer's instructions. RNA concen-
trations and purity were assessed using a NanoDrop ND-1000 spectro-
photometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Rockland, DE). RNA quality was 
analyzed using a 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, 
CA), and only RNA with an integrity number of Ն8 was used. Each treat-
ment was performed 3 times. 
TaqMan qRT-PCR. Transcript levels for the B -dependent genes 
opuCA and gadA and the housekeeping genes rpoB and gap were quanti-
fied with TaqMan primers and probes (13, 58, 71) using RNA prepared as 
described above and an ABI Prism 7000 sequence detection system (Ap-
plied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) as previously described (71). qRT-PCR 
was also used to determine the FPSS IC 50 . Inhibition was measured using 
opuCA transcript levels determined with RNA isolated from cells treated 
with a series of 1:2 dilutions of FPSS, with concentrations ranging from 
128 to 1 M. These data were assessed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SigmaPlot</rs> 10.0 (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SYSTAT Software Inc</rs>., Evanston, IL) standard curve analysis under the pharma-
cology function. 
Whole-genome microarray. cDNA labeling for microarray analyses 
and microarray hybridization were performed as previously described (5) 
using L. monocytogenes whole-genome microarrays (8, 72). Raw intensity 
values for all probes on each array were normalized using pin-tip <rs id="software-3" type="software">LOW- ESS</rs> (8) in R version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">2.2.1</rs> with the LIMMA package. Signals from two 
replicate probes on each array were then averaged and log 2 transformed. 
Differences in transcript levels between strains were determined using a 
linear model, and P values were determined using eBayes. Differences in 
transcript levels were considered meaningful if they met the following 
three criteria: (i) adjusted P values of Ͻ0.05 (ii) absolute fold changes of 
Ն2 and (iii) a probe cross-hybridization index (CHI) of Ͼ90%. One gene 
(i.e., lmo0263) fulfilled criteria (i) and (ii) but not (iii) (probe CHI was 
80%) and therefore was not included in our analyses. 
Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA; Broad Institute, Cambridge, 
MA) (73) was used to identify gene sets that were significantly enriched 
among up-or downregulated genes. GSEA was run on the ranked list of 
log fold change values obtained from the fitted normalized data in 
LIMMA with 1,000 permutations and exclusion of gene sets with Ͻ5 or 
Ͼ2,000 members. Genes were classified into sets based on the TIGR Com-
prehensive Microbial Resource (http://cmr.tigr.org) subrole categories 
for L. monocytogenes EGD-e. False discovery rate q values of Ͻ0.25 were 
considered significant (73). 
Caco-2 invasion assay. L. monocytogenes invasion assays using the 
human colorectal adenocarcinoma epithelial cell line Caco-2 (ATCC 
HTB-37) were performed as described by Garner et al. (9). L. monocyto-
genes 10403S and ⌬sigB strains were initially grown overnight in 5 ml of 
BHI broth at 37°C with shaking (230 rpm), then were subcultured twice, 
at an OD 600 of 0.4, using a 1% (vol/vol) transfer into 5 ml of prewarmed 
BHI. When the second subculture reached an OD 600 of 0.4, cells were 
treated with (i) FPSS to yield final concentrations of 64 M or 8 M 
(lowest concentration with full efficacy according to qRT-PCR) or (ii) </p>

<p>DMSO as well as NaCl (0.3 M final concentration) as described above, 
except that treated cultures were incubated at 37°C for 30 min. For infec-
tion, the Caco-2 cells were inoculated with approximately 2 ϫ 10 7 
L. monocytogenes organisms; bacterial numbers were confirmed by plating 
on BHI agar. Four biological replicates were each performed in triplicate 
wells. Statistical analysis was performed using one-way analysis of vari-
ance (ANOVA) and Tukey's studentized range (honestly significant dif-
ference [HSD]) test, performed in SAS 9.0 (SAS Institute). 
␤-Galactosidase enzyme assays in B. subtilis. B. subtilis strain PB198 
(amyE::pDH32-ctc trpC2 [74]) and the otherwise isogenic ⌬sigB strain 
PB345 (amyE::pDH32-ctc sigB⌬3::spc trpC2 [75]) were used as reporter 
strains for measuring B activity (Table S5). Effects of FPSS on the A 
housekeeping sigma factor in B. subtilis were tested using B. subtilis strain 
PB252 (amyE::P A -lacZ trpC2 [30]). Strains were grown overnight in 5 ml 
of buffered Luria-Bertani (LB) broth at 37°C with shaking (230 rpm) and 
then were subcultured twice, at an OD 600 of 0.4, using a 1% (vol/vol) 
transfer into 5 ml of prewarmed LB. When the second subculture reached 
OD 600 of 0.4, cells were treated with (i) FPSS (8 or 64 M) or DMSO only 
(as a control) and (ii) DMSO as well as NaCl (0.3 M final concentration) 
as described above, with treated cultures being incubated at 37°C for 
30 min. After this incubation, the OD 600 was recorded, and 0.2 ml of the 
culture was added to a tube containing 2.8 ml Z buffer, followed by the 
addition of 20 l toluene to permeabilize the cells. A prewarmed 0.4-ml 
volume of 4-mg/ml ortho-nitrophenyl-␤-galactoside (ONPG) was 
added, and the time of addition was noted. After 85 min, 1 ml of 1 M 
sodium carbonate was added to stop the reaction, and the OD 420 was read. 
Miller units were calculated as previously described (76). ␤-Galactosidase 
activity results were analyzed using one-way ANOVA and Tukey's studen-
tized range (HSD) test. 
Microarray data accession number. Data from microarray experi-
ments were submitted to the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database, 
assigned accession number GSE16887, and approved. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank C. W. Price and T. A. Gaidenko for the gift of B. subtilis strains 
used in this study and for helpful discussions. We also thank T. Bergholz 
for discussions regarding statistical analyses. The project described was 
supported National Institutes of Health award no. 5R01AI052151-07 (to 
K. J. B.). The funding agency had no role in study design, data collection 
and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. This 
project has been funded in part with federal funds from the National 
Cancer Institute's Initiative for Chemical Genetics, National Institutes of 
Health, under contract no. N01-CO-12400 and was performed with the 
assistance of the Chemical Biology Platform of the Broad Institute of 
Harvard and MIT. The content of this publication does not necessarily 
reflect the views or policies of the Department of Health and Human 
Service, nor does mention of trade names, commercial products or orga-
nizations imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplemental material for this article may be found at http://mbio.asm.org 
/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1128/mBio.00241-11/-/DCSupplemental. 
Figure S1, TIF file, 0.5 MB. 
Figure S2, TIF file, 1.8 MB. 
Figure S3, TIF file, 0.7 MB. 
Table S1, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S2, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S3, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S4, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S5, DOCX file, 0.1 MB. </p>



<p>Palmer et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>



<p>Small-Molecule Inhibitor of L. monocytogenes B </p>

<p>November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 9 </p>



<p>Palmer et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00241-11 </p>

</text></tei>