<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3822109" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective To quantify and compare the time doctors 
and nurses spent on direct patient care, medication-
related tasks, and interactions before and after electronic 
medication management system (eMMS) introduction. 
Methods Controlled pre-post, time and motion study 
of 129 doctors and nurses for 633.2 h on four wards in 
a 400-bed hospital in Sydney, Australia. We measured 
changes in proportions of time on tasks and interactions 
by period, intervention/control group, and profession. 
Results eMMS was associated with no significant 
change in proportions of time spent on direct care or 
medication-related tasks relative to control wards. In the 
post-period control ward, doctors spent 19.7% (2 h/10 h 
shift) of their time on direct care and 7.4% (44.4 min/ 
10 h shift) on medication tasks, compared to 
intervention ward doctors (25.7% (2.6 h/shift; p=0.08) 
and 8.5% (51 min/shift; p=0.40), respectively). Control 
ward nurses in the post-period spent 22.1% (1.9 h/8.5 h 
shift) of their time on direct care and 23.7% on 
medication tasks compared to intervention ward nurses 
(26.1% (2.2 h/shift; p=0.23) and 22.6% (1.9 h/shift; 
p=0.28), respectively). We found intervention ward 
doctors spent less time alone ( p=0.0003) and more time 
with other doctors ( p=0.003) and patients ( p=0.009). 
The extent to which computerized provider order 
entry (CPOE) systems significantly hinder or assist 
clinical work efficiency has been a subject of debate 
and investigation for over 20 years. Yet the evi-
dence base to address this issue remains sparse. </p>

<p>1-3   Zheng and colleagues 
4 recently drew attention to 
the poor and inconsistent methods used in con-
ducting time and motion studies to measure the 
impact of systems on work patterns. Controlled 
studies to measure the effects of CPOE on doctors' 
work are rare and we identified no published con-
trolled studies of the impact on hospital nurses' 
work. 
1 2 4 Studies in ambulatory care 
5-9 and speci-
ality areas in hospitals, such as the ICU, 
10 11 pre-
dominate. Despite considerable developments in 
CPOE systems, the body of evidence regarding the 
impact of these systems on doctors' and nurses' 
work on general hospital wards is relatively sparse </p>

<p>and reliance continues to be placed on results from 
important early studies. </p>

<p>5 12 13   Significant advances have been made in under-
standing the ways in which systems may disrupt 
and enhance work patterns and qualitative studies 
have played a vital role in understanding the 
complex socio-technical issues associated with inte-
grating information systems into clinical work. </p>

<p>14-19   However, concerns of clinicians regarding the 
impact that systems have on the efficiency of their 
work continue to be raised and are a significant 
barrier to adoption. 
20-22 Prior to the imminent 
introduction of an electronic medication manage-
ment system (eMMS) (with electronic prescribing 
and medication administration records (eMAR)), 
we interviewed 50 hospital clinicians (doctors and 
nurses) and managers to determine their expecta-
tions of system introduction. 
23 Work practice 
change associated with the system was the most 
strongly and frequently raised issue by all groups. </p>

<p>23   Specific issues often center on the perceived 
increased time it takes for doctors to prescribe medi-
cations and for nurses to perform medication 
administration using a computer compared to paper 
medication charts. 
7 22 24 As a result of this, there are 
concerns that there will be less time for clinicians to 
spend on direct patient care activities. 
20 These 
beliefs are often in contrast to the system benefits 
promoted to clinicians, namely that information 
systems will improve efficiency and patient care. </p>

<p>21 25   Time savings are anticipated by re-distributing time 
across medication tasks. 
12 For example, while it may 
take longer to type a prescription compared to 
writing it, the ability to modify existing orders 
rather than prepare new orders and to use ordersets 
is expected to save time. Redistribution of time-
benefits to others is also anticipated. For example, 
improving the legibility of orders is expected to 
reduce nurses' time spent clarifying orders. 
However, there are few data available to indicate 
whether time savings made in a particular sub-task 
are offset by time losses in other sub-tasks to make 
medication practice more or less efficient overall. 
Qualitative studies have revealed that many doctors 
and nurses report both improved and worsening 
efficiency. </p>

<p>26-28   Improved sharing of medication information is 
possible with CPOE, but reduced face-to-face com-
munication between clinicians has also been identi-
fied as a potentially negative impact of system 
introduction, but there is little quantitative evi-
dence to clarify this issue. </p>

<p>15 29   We aimed to undertake a large controlled time 
and motion study of hospital doctors and nurses to </p>

<p>Open Access 
Scan to access more 
free content </p>

<p> 
Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>measure whether the proportions of time spent in medication 
tasks, direct care, and communication with each other signifi-
cantly changed following the introduction of an eMMS with 
electronic prescribing and eMAR. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design, setting, and sample </p>

<p>We used a controlled before and after study design and used a 
direct time and motion observational approach. Data were col-
lected from staff on four wards (respiratory, renal/vascular, and 
two acute geriatric medical wards) in a 400-bed major public 
hospital in Sydney. 
We recruited a sample of 70 nurses and 59 doctors on the 
wards and collected data as outlined in table 1. Nurses of all 
classifications were included: registered nurses (RN) (new gradu-
ates, RN with 2-4 years of experience, and RN with 5+ years 
of experience) and clinical nurse specialists (CNS). 
Approximately 80% participation by eligible nurses was 
obtained in both the pre-and post-periods. 
We sought to include all medical registrars, residents, and 
interns on the study wards. Physician specialists were excluded 
as they defer the vast majority of prescribing ordering tasks to 
more junior staff. A major challenge for the recruitment of 
doctors was the transitory nature of the medical workforce. For 
example, in the pre-period we identified a possible study popu-
lation of 38 doctors of whom nine refused to participate (four 
because they did not want to be observed and five for a range of 
reasons such as about to go on leave and pending resignation or 
transfer). Nine who had agreed to participate were transferred 
from the study wards prior to observation, leaving 20 who par-
ticipated. Thus, approximately 69% (20/29) of eligible doctors 
participated, although 76% had agreed (29/38) to do so. In the 
post-period we were able to capture more doctors as they 
rotated into the study wards. 
There was a gap of approximately 2.6 years between pre-and 
post-data collection due to a delay in system implementation on 
the intervention wards. Post-data collection occurred at least 
9 months after system implementation to ensure clinicians were 
familiar with the system. 
For the nurses' study, two wards acted as controls and one (a 
geriatric ward) was the intervention ward (the fourth ward was 
initiating implementation and thus was excluded). For the 
doctors' study, two wards acted as controls and two (both geriat-
ric wards) were intervention wards. </p>

<p>Intervention </p>

<p>At baseline all wards used paper medical records and medication 
charts. All wards had a CPOE system for ordering diagnostic 
tests and viewing results as well as ordering diets, transport, </p>

<p>porters, and allied health consultations. The CPOE system did 
not allow clinical documentation. In the pre-intervention 
period, prescribing doctors wrote orders directly onto the medi-
cation chart. These charts were then used by nursing staff for 
medication administration. There was no intermediate transcrip-
tion step between a prescriber's order and the final medication 
chart entry, as is the case in some countries. Clinical pharmacists 
undertake ward rounds and review patients' medication charts. 
They will notate or contact the prescribing physician if changes 
are required. However, this step is not a pre-requisite for nurses 
to administer medications once a physician has documented an 
order. This process did not change after eMMS implementation. 
On the intervention wards in the post-period, the Cerner 
Millennium PowerOrders system, allowing electronic medication 
management functions, was integrated with the hospital's exist-
ing CPOE system in November 2007. Prescribers were required 
to use the system to prescribe medications in the post-period. 
Prescribing is mainly by menu selection of pre-prepared order 
sentences which are triggered upon drug selection and which 
can be modified by the prescriber. 'Care sets' allow for a group 
of related orders to be selected and ordered simultaneously with 
a single click. Active decision-support at the time consisted of 
allergy alerts and drug-drug interaction alerts set at the most 
severe level. During the intervention period, heparin infusions 
and patient controlled analgesia remained on paper charts. The 
intervention did not include bedside verification technology, for 
example, bar coding. Intervention wards had access to both 
computers on wheels (COWs) and fixed computers (desk PCs) 
to access the eMMS. The control wards continued to use paper 
medication charts in the post-period. </p>

<p>Procedures </p>

<p>All nurses and doctors were invited to participate via informa-
tion sessions followed by a direct approach. Rosters (schedules) 
from each ward were used to calculate the full-time equivalents 
for each nurse classification (RN new graduate, RN 2-4 years, 
RN 5+ years, and CNS) and medical classification (intern, resi-
dent, and registrar). The sampling strategy was prepared in 
order to ensure all hours of the work day and weekdays were 
sampled proportionately to ensure the sample was representa-
tive. Representative sampling was used to determine the number 
of minutes that participants needed to be observed for each 
hour of the day for each classification. Following signed 
consent, nurses and doctors were assigned a study identification 
number, and demographic information regarding their age, clas-
sification, and length of experience was collected. We did not 
store staff names once a unique identifier was assigned and did 
not match data for individual staff in the pre-and post-periods. 
Nurses were given no prior warning of observation periods. </p>

<p>Table 1 Details of study samples in each study period </p>

<p>Nurses 
Doctors </p>

<p>Baseline data collection 
3 wards 
13 July 2005-2 March 2006 </p>

<p>4 wards 
6 July 2006-21 December 2006 
Post-eMMS data collection 
2 control and 1 intervention ward 
13 August 2008-4 December 2008 
Minimum of 9 months after intervention </p>

<p>2 control and 2 intervention wards 
18 March 2009-13 July 2009 
Minimum of 14 months after intervention 
Number of staff observed 
70 (30 pre: 8 new graduates, 15 RN, and 7 CNS; 40 post: 
9 new graduates, 21 RN and 10 CNS) </p>

<p>59 (20 pre: 7 interns, 8 residents, and 5 registrars; 39 post: 
13 interns, 13 residents, and 13 registrars) 
Hours observed 
276.90 h (pre: 133.17 h; post: 143.73 h) 
356.26 h (pre: 150.88 h; post: 205.38 h) </p>

<p>CNS, clinical nurse specialists; eMMS, electronic medication management system; RN, registered nurses. </p>

<p>Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>
Research and applications </p>

<p>Observers randomly allocated nurses to a list for each observa-
tion session according to the sampling strategy. If a nurse at the 
top of the list was not working that day, observers selected the 
next nurse on the list. A similar approach was used for doctors, 
but on occasion pre-arranged times were requested as doctors 
were more mobile and locating them in the hospital could be 
difficult without this step. Nurses were observed between the 
hours of 7:00 and 19:00 and doctors from 8:00 to 20:00 on 
weekdays. Nurses and doctors were observed while both on and 
off the ward. 
The <rs type="software">Work Observation Method by Activity Timing (WOMBAT</rs>) method was applied. 
30-33 This is a technique for 
undertaking direct observational studies of health professionals. 
Using software on a handheld computer, observers capture 
multi-dimensional aspects of work and communication patterns. 
The <rs type="software">WOMBAT</rs> tool automatically captures all time data related 
to tasks and also details interruptions to work and multi-tasking 
(ie, tasks conducted in parallel). For example, details of tasks 
conducted in parallel, such as documenting and answering a 
question from a colleague, could be recorded and time-stamped 
automatically. Figure 1 provides a screenshot of the data collec-
tion tool. The tool can be reconfigured for different task types 
and study designs. Research teams interested in using this soft-
ware should contact the corresponding author ( JIW). </p>

<p>Information about 10 broad, mutually exclusive work categor-
ies was collected. Online supplementary appendix 1 gives the 
definitions for each of the tasks reported in this paper. This clas-
sification was developed following extensive observations and 
pilot testing. 
34 35 The method has been applied in Australian 
studies of health professionals 
31 36 and was most recently vali-
dated in Canadian studies of intensive care clinicians. 
32 37 The 
observers shadowed clinicians for an average of 1 h blocks, 
recording data using the handheld computer. For each task, the 
data collector recorded with whom the nurse/doctor completed 
the task, the information tools used, and any interruptions to 
work (defined as ceasing a task in order to respond to an exter-
nal stimuli) or tasks completed in parallel (multi-tasking). Tasks 
are continually recorded and include work, social/personal 
(including breaks), and activities carried out in transit. 
When the participant nurse/doctor engaged with patients, 
visitors, or other health professionals, the nurse/doctor was 
asked to introduce the observer and seek permission to con-
tinue. Alternatively, the observer would identify themselves. 
Several dummy observation sessions were undertaken as part of 
observer training conducted over 2-3 weeks. This also allowed 
participants to become accustomed to being observed. </p>

<p>Observer training </p>

<p>All eight observers were clinically experienced RNs or medical 
doctors. Inter-rater reliability tests were performed with two 
data collectors simultaneously, but independently, observing a 
clinician and comparing data. Kappa scores 
38 for task classifica-
tion were &gt;0.85 throughout data collection, indicating high 
levels of agreement between observers. On average inter-rater 
reliability observation sessions lasted 35 min each. 
The study was approved by the human research ethics com-
mittees of the University of New South Wales and the study 
hospital. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>To assess changes in time spent on direct care and medication 
tasks for each profession, we calculated the proportion of total 
observed time in each task category by study period ( pre/post) 
and group (control/intervention wards). We further examined 
medication sub-tasks for doctors and nurses as proportions of 
the total time spent in medication tasks. 95% CIs of proportions 
were obtained using the large sample normal approximation. 
The difference in changes post-eMMS in intervention groups 
relative to control groups was defined as the differences in the 
proportions (P) over time between control and intervention 
groups, that is, (P Intervention_post -P Intervention_pre )−(P Control_post -
P Control_pre ). We compared the difference in changes post-eMMS 
between intervention and control groups in each task category 
using the z test for proportions with the level of significance set 
at p&lt;0.05. Other descriptive statistics for number, average 
length, and frequency of tasks in each task category were also 
presented by study period and group. 
Information sources (eg, desk PC, COW) used in medication 
tasks were determined by calculating the proportions of total 
medication task time undertaken using each source. Time spent 
in interactions was examined in terms of both proportion of 
total observation time in professional communication, and the 
proportion of overall task time completed with others. Data 
were analyzed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">9.2</rs>. </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Screenshot of Work Observation Method by Activity Timing 
(WOMBAT) data collection tool. </p>

<p> 
Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Proportion of time spent in direct patient care by doctors 
and nurses before and after eMMS implementation </p>

<p>On all wards there was no significant change after eMMS intro-
duction in the proportion of time nurses and doctors on the 
intervention wards spent in direct patient care activities relative 
to control ward clinicians ( p=0.23 and p=0.08, respectively; 
table 2). Doctors on the control wards in the post-period spent 
19.7% (average of 3.1 min/task; 2 h/10 h shift) of their time in 
direct patient care (excluding medication tasks) and those on the 
intervention wards 25.7% (average of 2.6 min/task; 2.6 h/10 h 
shift). Nurses spent 22.1% of their time in direct care activities 
on the control wards in the post-period and 26.1% on the inter-
vention wards (table 2). 
There was an overall significant temporal change in the pro-
portions of time spent in direct care across all wards not asso-
ciated with eMMS introduction. Over the 2.6 years of the study 
(the time from pre-to post-data collection) the proportion of 
time spent in direct patient care significantly increased for 
doctors from 15.0% (95% CI 12.7% to 17.3%) in the pre-
period to 22.6% (95% CI 20.9% to 24.3%) in the post-period 
( p&lt;0.0001), and for nurses from 20.2% (95% CI 18.2% to 
22.1%) in the pre-period to 24.2% (95% CI 22.4% to 26.0%) 
in the post-period ( p=0.003). </p>

<p>Proportion of time spent by doctors and nurses on 
medication tasks before and after eMMS implementation </p>

<p>Following the introduction of the eMMS on the intervention 
wards there was no significant change in the proportions of time 
spent by doctors or nurses on medication-related tasks (table 2) 
relative to clinicians on the control wards ( p=0.4 and p=0.28, 
respectively). Doctors in the post-period on the control wards 
spent 7.4% (average of 49.6 s/task; 44.4 min/10 h shift) of their 
time on medication tasks and those on the intervention wards 
8.5% (average of 45.1 s/task; 51 min/10 h shift). Medication 
tasks consumed a greater proportion of nurses' overall time 
taking 23.7% (approximately 2 h in an 8.5 h shift) of their time 
on the control ward in the post-period and 22.6% (1.9 h/shift) 
on the intervention wards (table 2). 
We examined time distribution for specific types of 
medication-related tasks to assess if time was redistributed across 
tasks following eMMS introduction (tables 3 and 4). Both 
doctors and nurses on the intervention wards significantly 
increased the proportion of time spent reviewing medications 
using the eMMS compared to their colleagues on the control 
wards ( p=0.01 and p&lt;0.0001, respectively). However, no 
overall changes occurred in the time proportions of medication 
tasks since this increase was offset by (non-significant) decreases 
in nearly all other medication-related tasks (tables 3 and 4). 
Over time doctors and nurses on all wards experienced an 
increase in the percentage of time devoted to medication tasks. 
For doctors, it increased from 7.0% (95% CI 6.4% to 7.5%) in 
the pre-period to 7.9% (95% CI 7.3% to 8.6%) in the post-
period ( p=0.03), while for nurses, it increased from 20.2% 
(95% CI 19.4% to 21.1%) in the pre-period to 23.1% (95% CI 
21.7% to 24.5%) in the post-period ( p=0.001). This increase 
was not associated with eMMS intervention. </p>

<p>Information sources used during medication tasks </p>

<p>We examined the percentage of medication tasks performed 
with different information sources before and after eMMS 
introduction. Nurses on the intervention wards in the post-
period significantly reduced their reliance on patients' paper </p>

<p>medical records as part of the medication process. Before 
eMMS introduction, nurses spent 89.0% (95% CI 81.0% to 
97.0%) of medication task time (and 88% of all medication 
tasks) using a paper record, which declined to only 14.4% 
(95% CI 12.4% to 16.4%) after eMMS introduction (11% of 
medication tasks), while there was a much smaller change on 
the control wards, from 79.6% (95% CI 75.5% to 83.6%) of 
medication time to 66.9% (95% CI 62.0% to 71.8%). There 
was a significant relative reduction in the percentage of medica-
tion time where paper medical records were used of 61.9% on 
the intervention wards after eMMS introduction compared to 
the control wards (p&lt;0.0001). On the intervention wards after 
eMMS introduction, 52.5% (95% CI 48.9% to 56.0%) of 
medication tasks involved a COW (63% of medication task 
time) and 2.5% (95% CI 2.0% to 3.1%) a desk PC (3% of 
medication task time). No computers were used in the 
pre-eMMS period and no COWs were available on the control 
wards in the post-period. 
We found no significant change before and after eMMS intro-
duction in the use of paper medical records during medication 
tasks by intervention ward doctors relative to the control wards 
(p=0.6). However, intervention ward doctors completed a sig-
nificantly greater percentage of their medication task time using 
a desk PC compared to the control ward doctors (27.0% vs 
15.2%; p=0.022) and used a COW for 22.0% (95% CI 17.7% 
to 26.4%) of medication task time. Desk PCs were used on the 
control wards during medication tasks, for example, to access 
pathology results from the CPOE system. </p>

<p>Interactions between doctors and nurses and others before 
and after eMMS implementation </p>

<p>There was no significant change on the intervention wards in 
the proportion of time nurses and doctors spent in professional 
communication following the introduction of the eMMS 
(p=0.57 and p=0.8; table 2). There was also no temporal 
change in the proportion of time spent on professional commu-
nication for either doctors ( pre: 33.2% (95% CI 28.6% to 
37.9%) vs post: 37.1% (95% CI 35.0% to 39.3%); p=0.13) or 
nurses ( pre: 23.8% (95% CI 20.9% to 26.7%) vs post: 21.4% 
(95% CI 19.5% to 23.4%); p=0.17). In the post-period, nurses 
spent about 1.8 h/8.5 h shift of their time on professional com-
munication, while doctors spent about 3.7 h/10 h shift. 
However, when we examined task time spent alone and with 
others, we found that doctors on the intervention wards in the 
post-period spent significantly more time with patients (6.3% 
increase; p=0.009), more time with other doctors (21.4% 
increase; p=0.003), and significantly less time working alone 
(14.8% decrease; p=0.0003) compared to doctors on the 
control wards (table 5). Doctors on the intervention wards 
spent a significantly greater proportion of their time with other 
doctors, largely due to an increase in the frequency of interac-
tions (tasks per hour) (table 5). Nurses on the intervention 
wards spent a significantly lower proportion of time working 
with doctors following eMMS implementation compared to 
nurses on the control wards (4.2% decrease; p=0.0001; table 
6). This was due to both fewer interactions (tasks per hour) and 
shorter interactions (mean task time) (table 6). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Implementation of the eMMS was not associated with signifi-
cant changes in the proportions of time doctors and nurses 
spent on direct patient care or medication-related tasks, relative 
to their colleagues on the control wards. As the hospital already 
had in place CPOE for orders other than medications, we were </p>

<p>Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>
Research and applications </p>

<p>Table 2 Task time distribution for doctors before (pre) and after (post) electronic medication management system (eMMS) implementation </p>

<p>Task 
Group 
Period </p>

<p>No. of 
tasks </p>

<p>Total task 
time (h) </p>

<p>Mean task 
time (s) </p>

<p>Frequency of 
task per hour </p>

<p>% Total* 
time 
95% CI 
Diff † 
p Value </p>

<p>Nurses 
Direct care 
Control 
Pre 
952 
20.9 
79.0 
9.2 
20.1 
18.0 
22.3 
3.77 
0.23 
Post 
769 
15.7 
73.4 
10.9 
22.1 
20.0 
24.3 
Intervention 
Pre 
257 
6.0 
83.4 
8.8 
20.3 
15.8 
24.9 
Post 
886 
19.1 
77.4 
12.2 
26.1 
23.3 
29.0 
Medication 
Control 
Pre 
1806 
20.8 
41.6 
17.4 
20.1 
19.1 
21.0 
−1.93 
0.28 
Post 
1264 
16.8 
47.8 
17.9 
23.7 
21.2 
26.2 
Intervention 
Pre 
532 
6.1 
41.3 
18.2 
20.9 
19.0 
22.7 
Post 
1506 
16.4 
39.3 
20.7 
22.6 
21.2 
23.9 
Professional 
Control 
Pre 
1525 
24.7 
58.2 
14.7 
23.7 
20.4 
27.1 
2.24 
0.57 
communication 
Post 
1536 
14.2 
33.3 
21.7 
20.1 
17.7 
22.5 
Intervention 
Pre 
345 
7.1 
73.9 
11.8 
24.2 
18.4 
30.1 
Post 
1536 
16.6 
38.9 
21.1 
22.8 
19.8 
25.7 
Doctors 
Direct care 
Control 
Pre 
270 
14.4 
191.5 
2.7 
14.5 
11.4 
17.7 
4.60 
0.08 
Post 
378 
19.6 
186.4 
3.8 
19.7 
17.3 
22.1 
Intervention 
Pre 
248 
8.3 
120.4 
4.8 
16.0 
13.6 
18.3 
Post 
562 
26.8 
172.0 
5.4 
25.7 
23.4 
28.0 
Medication 
Control 
Pre 
475 
6.8 
51.6 
4.8 
6.9 
6.2 
7.6 
0.76 
0.4 
Post 
541 
7.5 
49.6 
5.4 
7.4 
6.6 
8.3 
Intervention 
Pre 
272 
3.7 
49.4 
5.2 
7.2 
6.3 
8.1 
Post 
707 
8.9 
45.1 
6.7 
8.5 
7.6 
9.5 
Professional 
Control 
Pre 
1237 
33.1 
96.4 
12.5 
33.5 
28.2 
38.8 
1.72 
0.8 
communication 
Post 
1795 
36.8 
73.8 
17.9 
36.6 
33.4 
39.8 
Intervention 
Pre 
726 
17.0 
84.2 
14.0 
32.7 
23.7 
41.8 
Post 
1989 
39.5 
71.4 
19.0 
37.6 
34.7 
40.4 </p>

<p>*Tasks which made up the remainder of clinicians' time were: social/personal time, documentation (other than medication-related), transit time, administration, responding to pages, 
indirect care, and supervision/education. 
 †Percentage difference in change over time (pre vs post) between intervention and control groups, that is, Diff=(P Intervention_post -P Intervention_pre )−(P Control_post -P Control_pre ). </p>

<p>Table 3 Time spent on individual medication tasks by doctors* </p>

<p>Task 
Group 
Period </p>

<p>No. 
tasks </p>

<p>Total time in 
medication 
task (min) </p>

<p>Mean 
task 
time (s) </p>

<p>Frequency of 
task per 
hour </p>

<p>% Total 
medication 
task time 
95% CI 
Diff † 
p Value </p>

<p>Prescribe 
Control 
Pre 
78 
57.6 
44.3 
11.46 
14.1 
11.3 
16.9 
−0.24 
0.95 
Post 
86 
83.2 
58.1 
11.53 
18.6 
14.3 
22.9 
Intervention 
Pre 
46 
33.2 
43.3 
12.32 
14.8 
10.5 
19.1 
Post 
93 
101.2 
65.3 
10.51 
19.1 
14.9 
23.2 
Prepare 
Control 
Pre 
34 
45.3 
79.9 
5.00 
11.1 
7.5 
14.7 
−0.54 
0.9 
Post 
18 
37.6 
125.2 
2.41 
8.4 
5.3 
11.5 
Intervention 
Pre 
18 
25.0 
83.3 
4.82 
11.2 
5.4 
17.0 
Post 
17 
42.1 
148.4 
1.92 
7.9 
2.7 
13.2 
Clarify 
Control 
Pre 
41 
30.0 
43.9 
6.03 
7.4 
5.8 
8.9 
−3.76 
0.3 
Post 
17 
19.4 
68.4 
2.28 
4.3 
2.2 
6.5 
Intervention 
Pre 
29 
24.7 
51.0 
7.77 
11.0 
6.4 
15.6 
Post 
12 
22.5 
112.3 
1.36 
4.2 
0.3 
8.2 
Discuss 
Control 
Pre 
224 
183.0 
49.0 
32.93 
44.8 
39.7 
50.0 
0.10 
0.99 
Post 
273 
168.4 
37.0 
36.60 
37.6 
32.3 
42.9 
Intervention 
Pre 
133 
100.9 
45.5 
35.63 
45.1 
37.6 
52.5 
Post 
377 
201.6 
32.1 
42.59 
38.0 
34.0 
42.0 
Review 
Control 
Pre 
77 
66.8 
52.1 
11.32 
16.4 
9.4 
23.3 
11.87 
0.01 
Post 
100 
65.8 
39.5 
13.41 
14.7 
11.3 
18.1 
Intervention 
Pre 
34 
21.6 
38.0 
9.11 
9.6 
6.5 
12.7 
Post 
151 
105.3 
41.8 
17.06 
19.8 
15.4 
24.2 </p>

<p>*Excludes the medication-related tasks of administration, transcribe, and find medication chart, as these categories had fewer than 10 tasks in each period. 
 †Percentage difference in change over time (pre vs post) between intervention and control groups, that is, Diff=(P Intervention_post -P Intervention_pre )−(P Control_post -P Control_pre ). 
Bold p values represent significance at p&lt;0.01. </p>

<p> 
Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>Table 4 Time spent on individual medication tasks by nurses* </p>

<p>Task 
Group 
Period </p>

<p>No. 
tasks </p>

<p>Total time in 
medication 
tasks (min) </p>

<p>Mean 
task 
time (s) </p>

<p>Frequency 
of task 
per hour </p>

<p>% Total 
medication 
task time 
95% CI 
Diff † 
p Value </p>

<p>Prepare 
Control 
Pre 
529 
430.23 
48.80 
25.38 
34.40 
31.49 
37.30 
−6.61 
0.171 
medication 
Post 
415 
382.58 
55.31 
24.74 
38.02 
33.5 
42.53 
Intervention 
Pre 
190 
152.93 
48.29 
31.14 
41.77 
35.3 
48.24 
Post 
513 
382.57 
44.74 
31.20 
38.78 
34.44 
43.12 
Check 
Control 
Pre 
117 
75.65 
38.79 
5.61 
6.05 
5.27 
6.82 
0.65 
0.576 
medication 
Post 
54 
44.95 
49.94 
3.22 
4.47 
3.52 
5.42 
Intervention 
Pre 
32 
19.93 
37.38 
5.24 
5.44 
3.78 
7.11 
Post 
58 
44.52 
46.05 
3.53 
4.51 
3.56 
5.47 
Administer 
Control 
Pre 
287 
271.55 
56.77 
13.77 
21.71 
19.12 
24.30 
−5.43 
0.122 
medication 
Post 
194 
211.75 
65.49 
11.57 
21.04 
17.68 
24.4 
Intervention 
Pre 
99 
94.05 
57.00 
16.22 
25.69 
21.26 
30.12 
Post 
196 
193.28 
59.17 
11.92 
19.59 
16.48 
22.7 
Chart 
Control 
Pre 
284 
141.10 
29.81 
13.62 
11.28 
10.19 
12.38 
−0.41 
0.789 
medication 
Post 
147 
66.03 
26.95 
8.76 
6.56 
5.57 
7.56 
Intervention 
Pre 
111 
50.60 
27.35 
18.19 
13.82 
11.44 
16.2 
Post 
190 
85.72 
27.07 
11.55 
8.69 
7.6 
9.78 
Discuss 
Control 
Pre 
200 
122.40 
36.72 
9.59 
9.79 
8.52 
11.06 
−1.6 
0.712 
medication 
Post 
153 
133.80 
52.47 
9.12 
13.29 
5.07 
21.52 
Intervention 
Pre 
37 
18.82 
30.51 
6.06 
5.14 
3.84 
6.44 
Post 
123 
69.48 
33.89 
7.48 
7.04 
5.91 
8.18 
Review 
Control 
Pre 
312 
151.88 
29.21 
14.97 
12.14 
11.19 
13.09 
9.99 
0.00001 
medication 
Post 
118 
46.85 
23.82 
7.03 
4.66 
4 
5.31 
Intervention 
Pre 
48 
21.77 
27.21 
7.87 
5.95 
4.45 
7.44 
Post 
194 
83.48 
25.82 
11.80 
8.46 
7.14 
9.78 </p>

<p>*Excludes low frequency tasks of find order, and clarify or order medication, as these categories had fewer than 10 tasks in each period. 
 †Percentage difference in change over time (pre vs post) between intervention and control groups, that is, Diff=(P Intervention_post -P Intervention_pre )−(P Control_post -P Control_pre ). 
Bold p values represent significance at p&lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Table 5 Frequency and proportion of time doctors interacted with others during tasks before (pre) and after (post) electronic medication 
management system (eMMS) implementation </p>

<p>Doctors 
interacting with 
Group 
Period 
No. tasks </p>

<p>Mean task 
time (s) </p>

<p>Frequency of 
task per hour </p>

<p>% Total 
task time 
95% CI 
Diff* 
p Value </p>

<p>No one 
Control 
Pre 
868 
90.49 
8.77 
18.40 
15.60 
21.20 
−14.80 
0.0003 
Post 
1587 
75.75 
15.79 
24.63 
21.90 
27.36 
Intervention 
Pre 
552 
106.57 
10.63 
27.44 
20.92 
33.97 
Post 
1696 
58.43 
16.18 
18.87 
16.55 
21.19 
Patient 
Control 
Pre 
556 
136.20 
5.62 
17.74 
14.96 
20.51 
6.32 
0.009 
Post 
806 
131.77 
8.02 
21.77 
19.60 
23.93 
Intervention 
Pre 
368 
103.00 
7.09 
17.68 
15.38 
19.99 
Post 
1210 
121.64 
11.54 
28.03 
25.92 
30.14 
Relative 
Control 
Pre 
121 
144.73 
1.22 
4.10 
2.83 
5.38 
0.99 
0.41 
Post 
237 
136.69 
2.36 
6.64 
5.43 
7.85 
Intervention 
Pre 
60 
109.70 
1.16 
3.07 
1.89 
4.25 
Post 
309 
112.10 
2.95 
6.60 
5.58 
7.61 
Nurse 
Control 
Pre 
420 
78.39 
4.24 
7.71 
5.84 
9.58 
−2.53 
0.45 
Post 
607 
57.16 
6.04 
7.11 
5.63 
8.59 
Intervention 
Pre 
281 
87.70 
5.41 
11.50 
5.57 
17.42 
Post 
691 
63.60 
6.59 
8.37 
7.18 
9.55 
Doctor 
Control 
Pre 
2213 
136.27 
22.36 
70.65 
62.62 
78.67 
21.40 
0.003 
Post 
2872 
105.49 
28.57 
62.09 
57.38 
66.80 
Intervention 
Pre 
1101 
108.42 
21.21 
55.69 
45.79 
65.58 
Post 
3768 
95.52 
35.94 
68.53 
64.18 
72.88 </p>

<p>*Percentage difference in change over time (pre vs post) between intervention and control groups, that is, Diff=(P Intervention_post -P Intervention_pre )−(P Control_post -P Control_pre ). 
Bold p values represent significance at p&lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>
Research and applications </p>

<p>able to specifically examine the impact of the addition of this 
module on work. The results provide little support for argu-
ments that eMMS use results in redistribution of time away 
from direct patient care or towards medication tasks. 
However, task time redistribution did occur within some spe-
cific areas. Examination of medication sub-tasks showed that 
increases in time spent, for example, reviewing medications in 
the system, were compensated by reduced time in other areas. 
Increased time spent reviewing patients' medication charts may 
be a potentially positive work practice change for patient care, 
or indicate that it took longer to scroll through medication 
charts to find information relative to paper charts. These results 
suggest that eMMS use may result in a redistribution of time 
within and across medication-related tasks. 
There are limited comparative data, and differences in set-
tings, work task classifications, and methods further hinder 
comparisons between studies. Early research, such as that by 
Bates et al 
12 published in 1994, showed that following CPOE 
introduction time spent by doctors ordering increased. They 
found medical interns significantly increased ordering time from 
5.3% to 10.5% ( p&lt;0.001) and surgical house officers from 
6.4% to 15.5% ( p&lt;0.001). However, they also found that the 
use of ordersets took less time using CPOE compared to paper. 
In a more recent before and after study of CPOE, Zheng et al </p>

<p>40   observed medical residents for 68 h in a pediatric intensive care 
unit. They found no significant change in the time doctors spent 
in direct care or ordering. Our results from a larger controlled 
study are consistent with these findings. Further, we provide 
some of the first such data on nurses' work patterns following 
CPOE introduction. CPOE systems and clinicians' computer 
skills are likely to have substantially improved over time and 
both may have contributed to reducing the potential negative 
impact of CPOE on clinicians' time. 
Intervention ward doctors spent a significantly greater pro-
portion of time with patients and other doctors. Interactions </p>

<p>with patients may have increased as a result of the use of COWs 
at patients' bedsides, particularly during ward rounds. The 
increased time with other doctors may have been due to 
increased use of a shared doctors' room on wards in which 
several PCs are located. These hypotheses are consistent with 
observations from our previous studies of doctors' use of com-
puting devices on wards with eMMS at this site. 
41 We observed 
that paper medication charts were often reviewed and com-
pleted at the central nurses' work station. However, the eMMS 
moved these tasks to either the COWs or the PCs in the 
doctors' rooms. This physical shifting of work to another loca-
tion may also have contributed to the observed significant 
decrease in interactions nurses had with doctors post-eMMS 
compared to control ward nurses. Interestingly, Zheng et al </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>also found that doctors spent a greater proportion of time inter-
acting with patients (increasing from 1.18% to 4.05%; p&lt;0.05) 
after compared to before CPOE implementation. However, as 
there was no control group in that study, it is not possible to be 
certain if this was associated with the CPOE system or a tem-
poral change. No reasons for this increase in interactions were 
suggested by the authors. We found significant temporal 
changes in the proportion of time both nurses and doctors 
spent on direct patient care and medication tasks in the post-
period. This may reflect the increased complexity and age of 
hospital patients over time. This finding also starkly demon-
strates the importance of controlled studies of work patterns. 
Very few previous studies have measured changes in nurses' 
time in relation to the introduction of an eMAR system. 
2 A 
study 
42 on one surgical ward in a UK hospital reported that fol-
lowing the introduction of a closed-loop medication system 
(comprising e-prescribing, automatic dispensing, bar code iden-
tification, and eMAR), medication administration rounds were 
significantly shorter, but nurses spent a significantly greater pro-
portion of time on medication tasks outside these rounds. That 
study timed medication rounds and then used work sampling </p>

<p>Table 6 Frequency and proportion of time nurses interacted with others during tasks before (pre) and after (post) electronic medication 
management system (eMMS) implementation </p>

<p>Nurses 
interacting with 
Group 
Period 
No. tasks </p>

<p>Mean 
task time (s) </p>

<p>Frequency of 
task per hour </p>

<p>% Total 
task time 
95% CI 
Diff* 
p Value </p>

<p>No one 
Control 
Pre 
2546 
40.63 
24.50 
24.93 
22.34 
27.51 
−5.23 
0.26 
Post 
1978 
51.12 
27.93 
35.65 
31.35 
39.95 
Intervention 
Pre 
671 
44.93 
22.93 
25.54 
19.29 
31.79 
Post 
1912 
47.58 
26.22 
31.03 
26.84 
35.21 
Patient 
Control 
Pre 
2267 
60.14 
21.82 
32.85 
30.65 
35.05 
1.34 
0.67 
Post 
1475 
60.11 
20.83 
31.26 
29.06 
33.47 
Intervention 
Pre 
678 
57.38 
23.17 
32.96 
28.53 
37.39 
Post 
1492 
64.28 
20.46 
32.71 
29.87 
35.55 
Relative 
Control 
Pre 
345 
58.46 
3.32 
4.86 
4.14 
5.58 
1.28 
0.07 
Post 
229 
56.35 
3.23 
4.55 
3.76 
5.34 
Intervention 
Pre 
78 
47.58 
2.67 
3.14 
2.43 
3.85 
Post 
266 
45.28 
3.65 
4.11 
3.6 
4.62 
Nurse 
Control 
Pre 
2550 
80.57 
24.54 
49.5 
44.49 
54.52 
7.84 
0.20 
Post 
2007 
52.37 
28.34 
37.06 
33.04 
41.09 
Intervention 
Pre 
737 
81.14 
25.19 
50.66 
41.59 
59.74 
Post 
2500 
54.02 
34.28 
46.06 
41.92 
50.19 
Doctor 
Control 
Pre 
318 
44.23 
3.06 
3.39 
3.02 
3.76 
−4.20 
0.0001 
Post 
217 
43.95 
3.06 
3.36 
2.78 
3.95 
Intervention 
Pre 
123 
62.02 
4.2 
6.46 
4.56 
8.37 
Post 
180 
36.29 
2.47 
2.23 
1.78 
2.67 </p>

<p>*Percentage difference in change over time (pre vs post) between intervention and control groups, that is, Diff=(P Intervention_post -P Intervention_pre )−(P Control_post -P Control_pre ). 
Bold p values represent significance at p&lt;0.01. </p>

<p> 
Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

<p>over 20 h to determine time on medication tasks outside 
rounds, but did not consider time in non-medication tasks such 
as direct care or professional communication. 
Importantly, we are able to link the patterns of work observed 
in our study with previously published prescribing error rates 
from these same hospital wards during the same study periods. 
A review of the medication charts of 1948 patient admissions 
from these wards before and after eMMS implementation 
showed prescribing error rates significantly declined with 
eMMS by 66.1% (from 6.25 errors per admission (95% CI 
5.23 to 7.28) to 2.12 (95% CI 1.71 to 2.54); p&lt;0.0001), with 
no significant change in the prescribing error rates on three 
control wards. 
43 Thus doctors on these eMMS wards achieved 
significant improvements in medication safety while devoting 
the same proportion of their time to medication and direct 
patient care tasks compared to doctors on the control wards 
where no improvement in prescribing error rates was observed. 
Time and motion data are very valuable in addressing specific 
concerns that clinicians have about reduced efficiency and 
decreases in time spent on patient care associated with CPOE. 
CPOE systems induce strong emotional reactions 
44 and ques-
tions raised about efficiency may be conflated with apprehension 
about other underlying matters such as shifts in roles and 
responsibilities which are often less well articulated. </p>

<p>45-47   Gaining an understanding of the dimensions of these concerns 
requires both quantitative and qualitative studies. 
48 Our results 
suggest concerns about dramatic reductions in efficiency are 
unfounded. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations </p>

<p>Studies of this type in real-world clinical settings are complex 
and subject to bias from different sources. In relation to pub-
lished research on this topic, our study has made advances in 
addressing methodological issues identified as problematic in 
previous studies. 
40 Our study complies with the criteria outlined 
in the STAMP guidelines 
40 in relation to observational work 
study designs. We applied a controlled design which allowed us 
to account for temporal changes in patterns of work. We 
worked closely with hospital staff to identify possible confoun-
ders. Hospital staff did not identify any significant policy or 
practice changes which occurred only in the intervention or 
control wards during this period. It is possible that other factors 
which we did not measure may have influenced our results. The 
large sample sizes, a sampling strategy to reflect both staff com-
position and work at different times of the day, and our ability 
to account for multi-tasking are particular strengths of the study. 
Limitations of our study include that we only examined 
weekday work. The results may thus not be representative of 
evenings or weekends. We only included four wards, and prac-
tices on wards may vary. However, we found that at baseline 
there were no significant differences in task time distributions 
for direct care, medication tasks, or professional communication 
by ward. A further potential limitation of the study was that 
both intervention wards were acute geriatric wards. However, it 
is important to note that almost all admissions to these wards 
were via the emergency department. Also this hospital has no 
general medicine service and therefore we believe that the find-
ings are likely to be generalizable to general wards. Patients on 
these wards have a high number of medications and often 
complex medication regimens. Thus, we believe these wards 
with heavy prescribing and medication administration loads are 
good test cases regarding the impact of the eMMS on staff 
efficiency. </p>

<p>We used a direct observational approach which lends itself to 
the 'Hawthorne effect' whereby participants may change their 
behavior while being observed. The extended length of our 
study reduced the chance of sustained behavioral change, par-
ticularly on busy hospital wards. Further, observational studies 
of clinicians in situ have suggested that the extent of behavior 
change is minimal. 
34 49 50 We had high participation rates for 
nurses (80%) and doctors (69%). It is possible that doctors and 
nurses who did not participate were systematically different 
from the remaining population in terms of the factors under 
investigation, namely the amount of time that doctors and 
nurses spend particularly on medication tasks, and that these 
clinicians' work was affected in different ways to clinicians in 
the study. One of the most frequent reasons for not participating 
in the study was that a doctor was about to go on leave or move 
to another ward. The large sample sizes guard against the likeli-
hood that this would be a significant form of sampling bias in 
this study. As indicated in the Methods section, we did not 
match nurses in the pre-and post-data analysis as ethics 
approval prohibited retaining individual nurse identification to 
allow repeated measures analysis. 
For doctors we collected data on tasks undertaken beyond 
their official shift times, but there were insufficient data in this 
category to assess whether there had been any significant change 
after eMMS introduction. This is an area that should be consid-
ered in future studies. We calculated kappa scores on multiple 
occasions to test for the reliability of task classification. 
Methods for applying kappa scores for assessing both task and 
time concurrently in time and motion studies have not been 
developed. We are currently developing these methods and such 
techniques would strengthen future time and motion studies. 
Empirical evidence to demonstrate the ideal length of time 
after the introduction of clinical information systems to assess 
impact on work practices is lacking. The long time period 
between pre-and post-data collection in our study is both a 
potential strength and weakness of the study. These systems can 
take a long time to bed-down and there have been criticisms 
that measurements taken too soon after system implementation 
may not reflect what will become 'standard' practice with these 
systems. However, we also acknowledge that a longer follow-up 
period may introduce the potential for other significant factors 
to confound the results. Hence, the importance of applying a 
controlled design. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This is one of the few controlled studies of the impact of 
eMMS on hospital clinicians' task time distribution. The results 
demonstrate that clinicians' concerns related to reduced effi-
ciency and time away from direct clinical care as a result of 
eMMS implementation voiced in interviews and focus groups </p>

<p>23   were not realized. Most importantly, significant improvements 
were achieved with reductions in prescribing error rates, while 
maintaining similar patterns of task time distribution relative to 
colleagues on control wards. However, the implications of 
reduced interactions between doctors and nurses after eMMS 
implementation for safe medication administration should be a 
focus of future investigations. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We thank the hospital site and staff for their support in 
conducting this study. </p>

<p>Contributors JIW conceived of and designed the study. RP and AG provided 
detailed input into the study design and JC provided input into practical issues of 
clinician recruitment and facilitated access to the study site. JIW and LL devised the 
analysis plan and LL performed the analyses. RP and JC provided detailed input 
regarding the functionality of the eMMS and assisted in understanding the </p>

<p>Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>
Research and applications </p>

<p>interpretation of results. JIW drafted the manuscript and all authors contributed to 
the review of the manuscript and approved the final version. JIW is guarantor and 
takes overall responsibility for the integrity of the study. </p>

<p>Funding This work was supported by funding from the Australian Research Council 
(ARC Discovery DP110100090) and the National Health and Medical Research 
Council (NHMRC Program grant 568612). </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The study was approved by the human research ethics 
committees of the University of New South Wales and the study hospital. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which 
permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, 
and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is 
properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>



<p> 
Westbrook JI, et al. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:1150-1158. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-001414 </p>

<p>Research and applications </p>

</text></tei>