<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3589639" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Transformation of MDS into ALL during childhood is extremely rare. We report a rare case 
of an 8-yr-old girl who presented with refractory cytopenia of childhood (RCC) that trans-
formed into ALL only 3 months after the diagnosis of childhood MDS. Although no cytoge-
netic abnormalities were observed in conventional karyotype and FISH analysis, we found 
several deletions on chromosomes 5q, 12q, 13q, and 22q. Partial homozygous deletion of 
the RB1 gene was observed on microarray analysis, with the bone marrow specimen diag-
nosed as ALL. This is the first case report of transformation of ALL from childhood MDS in 
Korea. We also compared the clinical, cytological, and cytogenetic features of 4 previously 
reported childhood MDS cases that transformed into ALL. </p>

<p>MDS is a heterogeneous group of clonal hematopoietic stem 
cell disorders characterized by bone marrow (BM) failure, dys-
plasia of peripheral blood and BM cells, and a high risk of trans-
forming into an acute leukemic phase [1]. MDS occurs as a re-
sult of ongoing DNA damage, natural depletion of stem cells, 
and accumulated exposure of the BM to environmental stresses 
or toxins [2]. Thus, the risk of MDS increases with age. Child-
hood MDS is relatively rare compared to adult MDS [3]. The in-
cidence of childhood MDS is less than 5% of all hematologic 
malignancies in childhood [4, 5]. 
Overall, approximately 30% of MDS progresses to acute leu-
kemia, typically AML. The risk of transformation into AML differs 
among MDS subtypes according to WHO classification. In less </p>

<p>than 5% and up to more than 50% of cases, MDS eventually 
progresses to AML after 5 yr [6]. However, progression of MDS 
to ALL is rare, occurring in less than 1% of adult cases, and 
even fewer in the pediatric population [7]. To our knowledge, 
there has been no case report of childhood MDS transforming 
into ALL in Korea, and there are only a few case reports world-
wide [8-10]. Here, we report a rare case of an 8-yr-old Korean 
girl who presented with childhood MDS-refractory cytopenia that 
transformed into ALL 3 months after the initial diagnosis of MDS. </p>

<p>CASE REPORT </p>

<p>An 8-yr-old girl was transferred to our hospital for further evalua-
tion of severe pancytopenia that was discovered 4 days earlier at 
a local hospital, to which she had been admitted for fever per-</p>

<p>Koh YR, et al. 
Transformation of childhood MDS to ALL </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.2.130 </p>

<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>sisting for 2 weeks. Her hemoglobin was 6.0 g/dL, white blood 
cell (WBC) count was 0.9 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L, and platelet count was 71 × </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L. She had mild, easy bruising on both legs and night sweat-
ing. At admission, the patient had an acute ill appearance with-
out fever and showed no splenomegaly, lymphadenopathy, or 
organomegaly on physical examination. A complete blood cell 
count (CBC) test showed hemoglobin of 5.8 g/dL, WBC count of </p>

<p>2.4 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L, and platelet count of 214 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L. A peripheral blood 
smear revealed severe normocytic normochromic anemia with 
mild anisocytosis and poikilocytosis, including some dacrocytes, 
moderate neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count of 0.78 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L) 
with left shifting, and a few giant platelets. Her reticulocyte 
count was in the reference range (1.11%) and nucleated red 
blood cells (RBC) were observed (1/100 WBCs). Schistocytes 
were not observed. Most biochemical tests for liver and renal 
function tests were within the reference intervals, except in-
creased serum lactate dehydrogenase (LDH; 638 IU/L, refer-
ence interval, 218-472 IU/L) and alkaline phosphatase (ALP; 506 
IU/L, reference interval, 95-280 IU/L). Serum C-reactive protein 
(CRP) was slightly increased at 5.3 mg/L (reference interval, </p>

<p>0-5.0 mg/L). Urinalysis results were not specific except a few 
WBCs, 3-5/high-power field. 
BM aspirate smears and touch print preparation of the BM 
biopsy revealed hypercellular marrow with dysplastic changes 
in 3 hematopoietic cell lineages. Erythroid dysplasia, including 
nuclear budding, multinuclearity, and nuclear irregularity, was 
present in 15% of all erythroid precursors (Fig. 1A). Granulocytic 
dysplastic changes, including megaloid change, hyposegmenta-
tion, and hypogranularity of the cytoplasm, was present in 15%   of granulocytic cell lines. Megakaryocytes were adequate in 
number and exhibited dysplastic changes, including unequivo-
cal micromegakaryocytes, separated nuclear lobes, and non-
lobulated or round nuclei in 10% of all megakaryocytes. Myelo-
blasts accounted for 0.8% of nucleated cells in the BM. A BM 
biopsy section exhibited nearly 100% cellularity with a marked 
increase of erythroid precursor cells. Dysplastic changes in all 
hematopoietic cell lines were the same as in BM aspirates. Few 
histiocytes were observed in the biopsy section (Fig. 1B). 
The pathologic findings of aplastic anemia or BM failure dis-
eases such as adipocytosis and hypocellular or acellular marrow 
were not observed. Flow cytometric analysis for CD55 and CD59 
performed to rule out paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria re-
vealed normal levels of CD55 and CD59 in both RBC and WBC. 
Epstein-Barr virus real-time quantitative PCR and parvovirus 
B19 IgM tests revealed no evidence of viral infection. Nutritional 
deficiencies and metabolic diseases were excluded based on 
medical history and physical examination. 
Cytogenetic analysis of the BM revealed a normal karyotype 
(46, XX). No cytogenetic abnormalities were detected in FISH 
analysis with probes for EGR1 (5q-), D7S486 (7q-), CEP8 (tri-
somy 8), and D20S108 (20q-). The patient was diagnosed as 
having refractory cytopenia of childhood (RCC) based on the </p>

<p>2008 WHO classification system. She received only supportive 
treatment in our hospital. After her general condition recovered, 
she was discharged and followed up with CBC and liver func-
tion tests. 
Three months after the initial diagnosis of MDS, she was 
re-admitted to our hospital because of a relapse of high fever. A </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Refractory cytopenia of childhood at first admission. (A) Bone marrow (BM) aspiration smear revealing dysplastic erythroid hyper-
plasia (arrows) (Wright-Giemsa stain, × 1,000). (B) BM biopsy section revealing hypercellularity with erythroid hyperplasia (H&amp;E stain, 
× 400). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Koh YR, et al. 
Transformation of childhood MDS to ALL </p>

<p>132 </p>

<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.2.130 </p>

<p>CBC test revealed hemoglobin of 9.4 g/dL, WBC count of 410.5 × </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L, and platelet count of 15 × 10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L. A peripheral blood smear 
revealed severe microcytic hypochromic anemia, marked leuko-
cytosis with many leukemic blasts (90%), and severe thrombo-
cytopenia. The results of several biochemistry tests were in-
creased as follows: AST, 134 IU/L; ALT, 74 IU/L; ALP, 498 IU/L; 
LDH, 11,306 IU/L; CRP, 54 mg/L. 
BM aspirate smears (Fig. 2A) and a biopsy section (Fig. 2B) 
revealed a markedly hypercellular marrow that had been com-
pletely replaced by small leukemic blasts (95%). Normal hema-
topoietic cells were markedly decreased. Cytochemical staining 
demonstrated that the cells were all negative for myeloperoxi-
dase (MPO), Sudan black B (SBB), and periodic acid-Schiff 
(PAS). Flow cytometric immunophenotyping revealed that the 
blasts expressed B lymphoid markers that were CD10 (+), CD19 
(+), CD79a (+), cytoplasmic IgM (+), and terminal deoxynucleo-
tidyl transferase (TdT) (+). The myeloid cell markers of CD13 
and CD33 and T cell markers of CD2, CD5, and CD7 were not 
expressed. Karyotype analysis of BM leukemic cells revealed 
normal chromosomes (46, XX). BCR-ABL, E2A-PBX, and TEL-
AML gene rearrangements were not detected using reverse 
transcription-PCR and FISH analyses. MLL gene rearrange-
ments and p16 (9p21) deletion analysis by FISH were also not 
detected. 
Based on the 2008 WHO classification system, the patient was 
diagnosed with B lymphoblastic leukemia not otherwise speci-
fied that was transformed from childhood MDS-refractory cyto-
penia. She received chemotherapy beginning the day after BM 
examination. Unfortunately, her general condition deteriorated </p>

<p>rapidly due to tumor lysis syndrome during chemotherapy. She 
expired from hyperkalemia on the third day of chemotherapy. 
Retrospectively, we analyzed the purified mononuclear cell 
fractions of the first (MDS-diagnosed) and second (ALL-diag-
nosed) BM specimens using microarray analysis, <rs id="software-0" type="software">Affymetrix Cytogenetics Whole Genome 2.7 Mb Array</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Affymetrix</rs>, Santa 
Clara, CA, USA) to identify genetic abnormalities. In the first 
BM sample, no chromosomal or genetic abnormalities were 
observed. However, in the second BM sample, we found several 
large interstitial deletions of 27 Mb and 5.7 Mb on 5q21.2q31.1 
and 13q14.1q21.1, respectively, and many microdeletions on 
chromosomes 5q, 12q, 13q, and 22q. Particularly, a partial ho-
mozygous loss of 200 kb was observed in a region of heterozy-
gous loss on chromosome 13q14.1q21.1 in the second BM 
sample. The chromosome views of the second BM sample us-
ing cytogenetic microarray analysis are shown in Fig. 3. To con-
firm this result, additional FISH analysis of the second BM sam-
ple was performed using 2 probes for EGR1 (5q31) and RB1 
(13q14), and produced the same result: 5q31.2 was not deleted 
and 13q14.3 was deleted in 84% of the examined nuclei (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>MDS originates from a multipotent hematopoietic stem cell 
with the potential for myeloid and lymphoid differentiation [11]. 
Based on flow cytometric immunophenotyping, approximately </p>

<p>85% of blast cells in the leukemic transformation from MDS dis-
played a myeloid phenotype, while 15% of blast cells displayed 
a hybrid (myeloid-lymphoid) phenotype. It is extremely rare for </p>

<p>Fig. 2. ALL at second admission. (A) Bone marrow (BM) aspiration smear exhibiting a markedly increased number of lymphoblasts 
(Wright-Giemsa stain, × 1,000). (B) BM biopsy section exhibiting marked hypercellularity with lymphoblasts (H&amp;E, × 400). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Koh YR, et al. 
Transformation of childhood MDS to ALL </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.2.130 </p>

<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>only the lymphoid phenotype to be displayed [12, 13]. Previous 
studies have suggested 2 reasons for the rarity of transformation 
to ALL from MDS. First, stem cells of MDS may have lympho-
poietic potential as well as myelopoietic potential, but there may 
be specific impairment of lymphopoiesis by intrinsic or extrinsic 
factors. Second, the rarity of the development of ALL from MDS 
may reflect a relative deficiency of MDS-derived target cells ca-
pable of lymphoid leukemogenesis [14-16]. 
Transformation to ALL is extremely rare in MDS patients. In 
adults, several cases of lymphoid transformation from MDS 
have been reported [17-22]. However, there are only a few case </p>

<p>Fig. 4. FISH analyses. (A) Two green signals of the 5p15.2 (D5S23, 
D5S721) probe and two red signals of the 5q31 (EGR1) probe. (B) 
Two green signals of the 13q34 probe and only one red signal of 
the 13q14 (RB1) probe, indicating the loss of 13q14. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>reports of transformation of childhood MDS to ALL worldwide [8-  10]. The profiles of our case and the previously reported 3 simi-
lar cases are shown in Table 1. In 1996, Bader-Meunier et al. [8]  described the clinical, cytological, and cytogenetic features of 
one childhood MDS patient, a 4-yr-old boy presenting with re-
fractory anemia and excess blasts (RAEB) who had transformed 
to ALL. The karyotype of the patient was 46 XY, 5q-. In 2007, 
Goel et al. [9] described a case of 9-yr-old boy with childhood 
MDS-refractory anemia that transformed into B-precursor ALL 
after cyclosporine chemotherapy. Cytogenetic analysis of the 
patient revealed a normal karyotype. In 2010, Gupta et al. [10]  reported a 5-yr-old girl who presented with RAEB that evolved </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Chromosome views of the second (ALL-diagnosed) bone 
marrow sample using cytogenetic microarray analysis. (A) Deletions 
on chromosome 5q (5q-). (B) Deletions on chromosome 12q (12q-). 
(C) Deletions on chromosome 13q (13q-) and homozygous loss of 
the RB1 gene at 13q14. (D) Deletions on chromosome 22q (22q-). </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Koh YR, et al. 
Transformation of childhood MDS to ALL </p>



<p>www.annlabmed.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3343/alm.2013.33.2.130 </p>

<p>into B cell ALL 4 months later. Cytogenetic analysis of the pa-
tient was not performed. In contrast to most RCC cases, 2 sub-
sequent cases exhibited erythroid hyperplasia and hypercellu-
larity, similarly to our case [9, 10]. Although most cases of RCC 
exhibit a normal karyotype irrespective of BM cellularity, the 
prospective multicenter study EWOG-MDS 98 determined that 
RCC patients with normal or increased BM cellularity exhibited 
cytogenetic abnormalities more frequently than in the patients 
with hypocellular RCC [23]. 
In our case, conventional karyotyping was first performed to 
detect cytogenetic abnormalities of RCC and ALL. As there are 
no cytogenetic abnormalities useful for predicting prognosis, we 
performed FISH analysis with ALL-and MDS-specific probes. In 
the retrospective microarray analysis of BM specimens, we dis-
covered cytogenetic abnormalities only in the second BM speci-
men on chromosomes 5q, 12q, 13q, and 22q.  Recently, the spectrum of genetic abnormalities has shown 
that MDS can progress to leukemia through the acquisition of 
multiple genetic abnormalities [24]. Chromosomal abnormalities 
such as monosomy 7, trisomy 8, and trisomy 21 are common in 
the transformation of childhood MDS to acute leukemia [25]. In 
our case, these common abnormalities were not observed. MDS 
normal karyotype and deletions of chromosome 5q, 20q, and Y 
are considered favorable prognostic factors, while monosomy 7  and complex abnormalities are considered poor prognostic fac-
tors [26]. Particularly, in our case, there was a homozygous loss 
of 13q14.2, including most of the retinoblastoma gene (RB1). In </p>

<p>50% of de novo MDS cases, chromosomal aberrations and rear-
rangements involving the RB1 gene in 13q14 are observed [25]. 
Deletion or translocation involving chromosomal band 13q14, 
the locus of the RB1 gene, are observed in a variety of hemato-
logical malignancies, including AML, plasma cell myeloma, and 
CLL. Deletion of most of the RB1 gene may be associated with 
poor prognosis, as the patient died 3 months after the diagnosis 
of MDS. 
We have described a case of an 8-yr-old girl who presented 
with childhood MDS-RCC that had transformed into ALL. This is 
the first case report in Korea of transformation into ALL from 
childhood MDS. Our case shows that there can be similar cases 
of lymphoid transformation of MDS in the Korean population; it 
supports, again, the nature of MDS as a pluripotent hematopoi-
etic stem cell disorder. Notably, the patient had a very short pro-
gression period compared with the 3 previously reported cases, 
and multiple cytogenetic aberrations that could not be detected 
using conventional cytogenetic testing methods. Studies are 
needed to determine whether cytogenetic analysis methods 
provide improved means of identifying high-risk patients in 
childhood MDS. </p>

<p>Authors' Disclosures of Potential Conflicts of 
Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were re-
ported. </p>



<p>Table 1. Cases of childhood MDS transforming to ALL </p>

<p>Present 
case </p>

<p>Bader-Meunier 
et al. [8] </p>

<p>Goel et al. 
[9] </p>

<p>Gupta et al. 
[10] </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
8 
4 
9 
5 </p>

<p>Gender 
F 
M 
M 
M </p>

<p>MDS subtype 
RCC 
RAEB 
RA 
RAEB </p>

<p>Time to progression 
3 months 
NA 
21 months 4 months </p>

<p>Transformed phenotype B cell ALL 
ALL 
B cell ALL B cell ALL </p>

<p>Karyotype 
46, XX[6]* 46, XY, 5q-
46, XY 
NA </p>

<p>Outcome 
Expired 
Expired 
Lost to 
follow-up </p>

<p>Complete 
remission </p>

<p>Survival 
3 months 
1.6 yr 
NA 
≥ 1.5 yr </p>

<p>*Metaphase karyotyping result; combined result with microarray as follows: 
46,XX.arr5q21.2q31.1(103,748,441-130,800,60)x1,5q31.3q32(157,944, 
613-158,525,411)x1,5q33.3q33.3(157,944,613-158,525,411)x1,13q14. 
1q21.1(46,634,783-52,327,858)x1,13q14.2(48,943,369-49,145,935)X0,1 
3q21.2(59,699,506-61,715,367)x1,12q21.33q21.33(92,280,194-92,537, 
298)x1,22q11.2q11.22(22,549,708-23,207,076)x1. 
Abbreviations: M, male; F, female; RCC, refractory cytopenia of childhood; 
RA, refractory anemia; RAEB, refractory anemia with excess blasts; NA, not 
available. </p>

<p>Koh YR, et al. 
Transformation of childhood MDS to ALL </p>





</text></tei>