<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3939454" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>High-throughput AP-MS methods have allowed the identification of many protein complexes. However, 
most post-processing methods of this type of data have been focused on detection of protein complexes and 
not its subcomplexes. Here, we review the results of some existing methods that may allow subcomplex 
detection and propose alternative methods in order to detect subcomplexes from AP-MS data. We assessed 
and drew comparisons between the use of overlapping clustering methods, methods based in the 
core-attachment model and our own prediction strategy (TRIBAL). The hypothesis behind TRIBAL is that 
subcomplex-building information may be concealed in the multiple edges generated by an interaction 
repeated in different contexts in raw data. The CACHET method offered the best results when the evaluation 
of the predicted subcomplexes was carried out using both the hypergeometric and geometric scores. 
TRIBAL offered the best performance when using a strict meet-min score. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he discovery of protein complexes through high-throughput co-purification methods has increased the 
amount of available data to the extent that 43% of the reported protein complexes in interaction databases 
are estimated to be a result of this kind of experiments (see Supplementary Code). Traditionally, it has been 
argued that these methods produce high levels of noise 
1 although this claim has been contested 
2 . Either way, 
complex detection from affinity-purification (AP) high-throughput (HT) data is not a straightforward process 
and to convert such data to a list of complexes demands the application of a series of post-processing steps that are 
still an open field of research </p>

<p>3   . 
Raw data from an AP experiment is essentially a list of bait proteins mapped to all the prey proteins that they 
pulled out. Such a list is subject to false positives and false negatives (see Supplementary file, section 1, for a 
detailed review) and it is traditionally corrected by scoring the interactions according to different methods that 
measure the propensity of two proteins to interact given the background of interactions. Reliable interactions are 
integrated into a network which is then clustered to generate protein complexes </p>

<p>3,4   . These methods became very 
relevant as it was noticed that the differences between the conclusions of the first two main comprehensive maps 
of the yeast complexome were mainly a result of the pre-processing methods they employed </p>

<p>3,5   . 
The way in which the scoring step is done has adopted a multiplicity of forms. The socio-affinity index (SA) 
scored the interaction between proteins i and j by including terms for how often i retrieves j and a term for how 
often pairs of proteins are seen together as preys. These were calculated as the log-odds of the number of times the 
proteins were observed together relative to what would be expected from their frequency in the data set 
6 . Hart 
et al. postulated a scoring system based on the use of a hypergeometric distribution relative to a matrix model of 
interactions 
7 . The Purification Enrichment score (PE) pointed out the limitants of the SA method, such as to 
include only positive evidence and not the inability of a protein to be identified by another, and as being suitable 
mainly for cases where all proteins were both baits and preys. Alternatively, the authors used a naïve Bayes 
classifier, which estimates the probability of one hypothesis (interaction is reliable) relative to the probability of a 
second hypothesis (interaction is not reliable). The score was the log-ratio of these probabilities, computed using 
Bayes' theorem 
5 . Finally, the Dice score was suggested as a simple alternative that focuses on comparing the co-
purification patterns of two proteins across all different purification experiments; this is, constructing a pull-
down matrix of proteins versus experiments and using a Dice index to compare each pair of protein profiles </p>

<p>4   . 
Additional scoring systems have been proposed in recent years </p>

<p>8,9   . </p>

<p>Regarding the clustering step, the options are even wider. The 
classical AP HT studies 
5,6 used methods such as Markov Clustering 
(MCL) and variations of Hierarchical Clustering </p>

<p>3   . However, many 
novel clustering methods have been proposed since then. We will 
review these methods below. 
Finally, after scoring and clustering, the quality of the prediction 
strategy is commonly evaluated by comparison of the list of predicted 
complexes to a gold standard, that is, a manually curated database of 
protein complexes. A good agreement with this gold standard 
increases the confidence on the new complex predictions. 
Protein subcomplex detection is an interesting special case of the 
more general complex prediction problem. A subcomplex can be 
defined as a functional (or predicted) complex which is a subset of 
a larger functional (or predicted) complex. In other words, the pro-
tein subunits of the subcomplex must be a subset of the protein 
subunits of the larger complex. Subcomplexes have been approached 
in different ways in the literature. One line of work depict them as 
clusters lying inside bigger network clusters, this is, the most con-
nected region inside a bigger connected region, which is found using 
clustering strategies tailored for that purpose 
10 . Other authors pay 
attention to the ''cores'' that repeat in several complexes and the 
''attachments'' that make them different to each other 
6 . Here the core 
of a core-attachment structure could be considered as a subcomplex. 
A similar approach focuses on studying multi-cluster and mono-
cluster proteins after applying overlapping clustering algorithms to 
protein interaction networks </p>

<p>11   . Together with all these approaches, 
the ''subcomplex'' term can also be used to strictly define a biologic-
ally-relevant subcomplex, i.e., the subcomplexes that have been 
experimentally found to be functional and independent from the 
complex that contain them. Examples of subcomplexes are the 
TFIIK complex (related to the TFIIH complex), ADA-GCN5 com-
plex (with SAGA complex), pre-replication complex (with replica-
tion complex) and ribonuclease MRP (with ribonuclease P). We will 
reserve the name ''subcomplex'' for these biologically meaningful 
macromolecular structures, while we will refer to ''subcomplex pre-
dictions'' to denote specific subcomplex representations. 
The problem of subcomplex detection from an AP experiment is 
interesting due to the fact that we can find a high number of complex-
subcomplex pairs in protein interaction databases. For example, the 
iRefIndex, which is a consolidation of 13 of the most popular protein 
interaction databases, contains 8145 cases of complex-subcomplex 
pairs </p>

<p>12   . But, at the same time, some of the algorithms used in the AP 
complex prediction pipeline, such as MCL, are non-overlapping 
clustering algorithms, making impossible any subcomplex detection. 
New methods that face the subcomplex detection problem have 
recently appeared but they need to be assessed and compared. The 
first line of research would be the incorporation of overlapping clus-
tering algorithms to the complex detection pipeline. The second type 
of methods is based on the core-attachment model. Further on, we 
will introduce a third type of strategy in this paper and compare it to 
the other two. 
Regarding the first type of methods employed to detect subcom-
plexes in AP data, there are many available clustering algorithms that 
could be applied to the networks resulting from the scoring step. 
Most have been proposed following the assumption that complexes 
can be reconstructed from highly densely connected regions in the 
network </p>

<p>13   : RNSC and MCL are some important examples </p>

<p>14   . A review 
of twelve of these algorithms 
15 claim that the best prediction method 
is ''Infomap'', followed by ''Fast modularity'', and ''Potts model 
approach''. However, it has also been argued that densely connected 
regions do not reflect functional units; hence, alternative ways to look 
at the complex prediction problem have been proposed </p>

<p>13,16,17   . In 
addition, complex prediction algorithms have also evolved from 
algorithms that generate non-intersecting or non-overlapping clus-
ters to algorithms that take into account the fact that protein com-
plexes share subunits with other complexes, i.e., overlapping </p>

<p>community detection algorithms. Some of these methods are 
<rs type="software">MCODE</rs> </p>

<p>18   , <rs type="software">CFinder</rs> </p>

<p>19   , Link-communities </p>

<p>10,20   , OCG 
11 , Cluster-
ONE 
21 and RSRGM </p>

<p>17   . 
Regarding the second type of methods that allow subcomplex 
detection, an early strategy to take into account the overlapping 
nature of complexes and apply it to complex identification from 
AP experiments was introduced by Gavin et al. </p>

<p>6   , who, after applying 
the SA score to AP data, performed repeated hierarchical clustering 
using different parameters to generate overlapping complexes that 
they described as composed of common ''cores'' and ''attachments''. 
Two recent papers, 
22 and 
23 , present a review of current clustering 
methods applied to protein complex identification. A group of meth-
ods, including <rs type="software">CORE</rs> </p>

<p>24   , COACH 
25 and CACHET 
26 , deserve a special 
mention for explicitly incorporating the above-mentioned ''core-
attachment'' model (other methods include: Markov random fields </p>

<p>27   and CODEC </p>

<p>28   ). 
In this paper, we will explore the detection of biologically relevant 
subcomplexes from AP data through some of the above-mentioned 
techniques, and suggest a new strategy which might be able to 
improve them. We will evaluate the use of some recent methods that 
are able to detect ''nested communities'' or ''hierarchies'', in order to 
prove whether or not these nested communities can detect biologic-
ally meaningful subcomplexes, while we introduce a new method to 
identify subcomplexes from AP data. We start from the premise that 
most of the previous procedures remove the multi-edge nature of 
pull-down data in an interaction network (i.e., bait-prey co-occur-
rences), which is the network signature of a subcomplex. For 
example, some scoring methods reduce all co-appearances of a bait 
and a prey protein to one single weighted interaction, whereas some 
clustering methods explicitly remove any subcomplex candidates. 
An example of this is the Leu4-Leu9 interaction from Gavin's data-
set </p>

<p>6   : This interaction does not end up in any complexes when using 
the PE score, whilst the SA scores produce three complexes and the 
Dice score produces 2 complexes containing Leu4, Leu9 and a few 
more subunits. A Leu4-Leu9 complex does not appear in the results 
with any scoring method and, in fact, Leu4 and Leu9 are the subunits 
of the alpha-isopropylmalate synthase. This demonstrates how a 
highly scored copurification, which happens to be a complex, may 
get filtered out by the clustering method. Here we introduce TRIBAL 
(TRIad-Based ALgorithm), a novel method to identify subcomplexes 
from AP data that preserves and exploits this co-occurrence 
information. </p>

<p>Results 
TRIBAL algorithm. In order to predict subcomplexes, we have 
designed a simple strategy that keeps the multi-edge information 
after the scoring and clustering steps, assuming that such informa-
tion could include subcomplex information to some yet undeter-
mined extent. 
The first step of our algorithm is the generation of a pull-down 
matrix in order to compare purification patterns; this is similar to 
what is done in Zhang et al., but, instead of recording the purification 
or non-purification of a protein per experiment, we recorded the co-
purification of pairs of proteins per experiment. This way, the Dice 
score is not used to compare patterns of purification between pro-
teins but patterns of co-purification between pairs of proteins. 
Each interaction between a bait and a pair of co-purifying preys 
will be scored using a Dice index, and the ones above the cutoff (we 
will explain cutoff selection below) will be considered reliable. 
Each reliable interaction (formed by three proteins) will be con-
verted to a graph, using a spoke model representation, i.e., the bait 
will have an edge to each of the two prey proteins. All of these triads 
are integrated into a purification network. Unlike other methods, the 
conversion from triads of proteins to a network will generate mul-
tiple (repeated) edges. We have kept the multi-edge nature of this 
network, as this was our initial goal. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4262 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04262 </p>

<p>
We then take one set of known or predicted complexes as a tem-
plate and we insert the multiple edges inside the complexes. The 
proteins with multiple edges inside a complex will be predicted to 
be a subcomplex. Figure 1 summarizes these four steps. 
In order to select the best cutoff value for the modified Dice score 
and the best template for the final step, the performance of the 
method was assessed by applying it to different templates and 11 
different cutoff values of the modified Dice reliability score, ranging 
from 0.0001 to 0.2. This range was selected due to the size of the 
resulting PIN: Below 0.001, the size of the PINs does not increase, 
whereas, after 0.2, PINs then contain a small amount of edges (less 
than 1000). The best setup for TRIBAL (the one that maximizes the 
precision and the number of validated subcomplex predictions, while 
minimizes the size of the network) is the set of predicted complexes 
using Link communities clustering plus PE scoring, with a cutoff 
value of the reliability score of 0.05. In this case, TRIBAL predicts 
18 subcomplexes with a precision of 100%. Details regarding tem-
plate and cutoff selection can be found in the Supplementary file 
(section 3). </p>

<p>Complex and subcomplex predictions. Protein complex predic-
tions using each combination of scoring and overlapping cluster-
ing methods were performed. First, we scored Gavin's raw data </p>

<p>using four of the most popular scoring systems: The SA score 
6 , the 
Hart score 
7 , the PE score 
5 and the ''Dice'' score 
4 (see Methods). We 
used the cutoff values defined in the original papers (SA , 4, Hart . 
0.01, PE ,5 1.5, Dice ,5 0.15) and we obtained four lists of reliable 
edges. The size of these lists varied from 6528 edges for Hart to 18278 
for PE, including 14004 for SA and 16447 for Dice. 
The edge lists were used to generate four Protein Interaction 
Networks (PINs). PIN-Dice contains 2192 nodes and 16447 edges, 
PIN-Hart contains 639 nodes and 6528 edges, PIN-PE contains 2344 
nodes and 18278 edges, and PIN-SA contains 2005 nodes and 14004 
edges. 
The four PINs were clustered using two different overlap-detect-
ing clustering methods: ''Link-communities'' 
10,20 and ''<rs type="software">OCG</rs>'' </p>

<p>11   . A 
description of the results can be observed in the Supplementary file 
(Supplementary Table 1). 
For comparison purposes, we also constructed clusters by using 
traditional hierarchical clustering. Dice-H (Dice scoring and hier-
archical clustering) produces 2293 communities, Hart-H produces 
544 and SA-H produces 608. 
Subcomplex predictions using the above-mentioned overlapping 
clustering strategies were generated by extracting all predicted com-
plexes which were contained (meet-min 5 1.0) by at least one other 
predicted complex. The result was a prediction of 102 subcomplexes </p>

<p>Pull-down matrix of 
baits vs pairs of preys </p>

<p>Comparison through the Dice 
score of the pull-down vectors </p>

<p>Selection of reliable records 
(score above cutoff) </p>

<p>Generation of a list of interactions 
(using a Spoke model) </p>

<p>Location of predicted interactions inside a 
template of predicted complexes generated by a 
reliable clustering method </p>

<p>Figure 1 | TRIBAL algorithm. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4262 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04262 </p>

<p>
by using Dice score and Link communities, 35 subcomplexes by PE 
score and Link communities, 67 subcomplexes by SA score and Link 
communities, 29 subcomplexes by Dice score and OCG, 7 subcom-
plexes by Hart score and OCG, and 34 subcomplexes by PE score and 
OCG. 
Subcomplexes predictions using the <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> method were gen-
erated by removing all complexes without attachments and then 
selecting the cores of the remaining complexes, as explained in 
Methods. The result was 309 subcomplex predictions. 
TRIBAL is a subcomplex prediction strategy, so all its predictions 
are subcomplexes. TRIBAL was applied to Gavin's dataset as 
explained in Methods, producing 18 subcomplex predictions. It is 
important to notice that the edges of the Dice-scored network are a 
subset of the edges of the PE-network, and, even more, TRIBAL's 
edges are a subset of the Dice-score (and, therefore, PE) methods. 
Therefore, TRIBAL seems to be generating a more strict network, 
with edges already validated for other methods, but with the differ-
ence that we keep the multiple edges that the other methods have 
removed. </p>

<p>Analysis of predictions. As explained in Methods, protein complex 
predictions were compared to a MIPS gold standard. For compari-
son purposes, we added examples using traditional hierarchical </p>

<p>clustering. Table 1 summarizes the percentage of predicted 
complexes that can be found in the MIPS reference set (i.e., the 
Precision or PPV) and the percentage of MIPS complexes that can 
be found at the predicted set (i.e., the Recall or Sensitivity), when 
using a p-value smaller than 0.05 (after a hypergeometric test) to 
determine a match. Some researchers might be more interested in 
a few high precision results (despite having a high number of false 
negatives or missing hits), and some others might be interested in a 
high recall (many results, despite having a high number of false 
positives). However, it is a common practice to find a balance 
between false positives and false negatives, or between precision 
and recall. There are several computational methods to do that, 
and two of the most popular are the F-measure and the area under 
the ROC curve. In the following tables, we show the first one. Results 
suggest that PE schemes offer the best precision while OCG 
outperforms Link communities in terms of recall. Therefore, it is 
the PE score plus OCG clustering which offers the best F-measure. 
Other studies use different methods to determine what a match is. 
For example, Wu et al. 
26 use a ''geometric index'' (also called NA-
score) smaller than 0.2. The results under this alternative method can 
be found in Table 2. In this case, results partially contradict the 
previous analysis, and now Link communities has the best perform-
ance, with the best F-measure belonging to a combination of Dice </p>

<p>Table 1 | Precision and recall analysis for different complex prediction strategies, using the hypergeometric index as match criterion (p-value 
, 0.05) </p>

<p>Methods 
#Predicted matches 
#All_Predicted_comp 
Precision 
#Reference_matches 
#All_Reference_comp 
Recall 
F-measure </p>

<p>Raw-non-
repeated </p>

<p>1280 
1849 
0.69 
196 
214 
0.92 
0.79 </p>

<p>Raw-repeated 
260 
317 
0.82 
96 
214 
0.45 
0.58 
Dice-H 
798 
2293 
0.35 
201 
214 
0.94 
0.51 
Hart-H 
200 
544 
0.37 
198 
214 
0.92 
0.53 
PE-H 
349 
1353 
0.26 
202 
214 
0.94 
0.40 
SA-H 
181 
608 
0.30 
187 
214 
0.87 
0.44 
Dice-lcomm 
559 
770 
0.73 
165 
214 
0.77 
0.75 
PE-lcomm 
489 
553 
0.88 
126 
214 
0.59 
0.71 
SA-lcomm 
468 
694 
0.67 
154 
214 
0.72 
0.70 
Dice-OCG 
323 
474 
0.68 
187 
214 
0.87 
0.76 
Hart-OCG 
127 
194 
0.65 
65 
214 
0.30 
0.41 
PE-OCG 
404 
467 
0.86 
182 
214 
0.85 
0.86 
SA-OCG 
201 
249 
0.81 
173 
214 
0.81 
0.81 </p>

<p>Purification Enrichment seems to offer the best precision, as the best results are PE-lcomm (88%) followed by PE-ocomm (86%). Regarding recall, hierarchical clustering methods seem to offer the best results, 
as the best values are Dice-H and PE-H (94%). OCG outperforms linkcomm in terms of recall. The PE-OCG combination offers the best F-measure results. </p>

<p>Table 2 | Precision and recall analysis for different complex prediction strategies, using the geometric index as match criterion 
(index . 0.2) </p>

<p>Methods 
#Predicted matches 
#All_Predicted_comp 
Precision 
#Reference_matches 
#All_Reference_comp 
Recall F-measure </p>

<p>Raw-non-
repeated </p>

<p>323 
1849 
0.17 
118 
214 
0.55 
0.26 </p>

<p>Raw-repeated 
47 
317 
0.15 
23 
214 
0.11 
0.12 
Dice-H 
264 
2293 
0.11 
149 
214 
0.70 
0.20 
Hart-H 
80 
544 
0.15 
99 
214 
0.46 
0.22 
PE-H 
153 
1353 
0.11 
148 
214 
0.69 
0.19 
SA-H 
87 
608 
0.14 
102 
214 
0.48 
0.22 
Dice-lcomm 
227 
770 
0.29 
89 
214 
0.42 
0.34 
PE-lcomm 
164 
553 
0.30 
73 
214 
0.34 
0.32 
SA-lcomm 
185 
694 
0.27 
84 
214 
0.39 
0.32 
Dice-OCG 
101 
474 
0.21 
67 
214 
0.31 
0.25 
Hart-OCG 
22 
194 
0.11 
17 
214 
0.08 
0.09 
PE-OCG 
73 
467 
0.16 
46 
214 
0.21 
0.18 
SA-OCG 
63 
249 
0.25 
41 
214 
0.19 
0.22 </p>

<p>Results with the more strict geometric criterion show that Link communities has a better performance than the alternatives. Thus, the best F-measure belongs to Dice 1 lcomm, while the second and third best 
belong to PE 1 lcomm and SA 1 lcomm. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4262 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04262 </p>

<p>
score and Link communities clustering. We hypothesize that the 
reason of this difference might be the fact that the hypergeometric 
score is more sensitive to the size of the complexes and <rs type="software">OCG</rs> is 
predicting complexes of a size larger than expected, as it can be 
observed in the Supplementary file (section 4). 
However, our main interest is not to evaluate the ability to identify 
complexes but the ability to identify subcomplexes. We begin by 
verifying that all datasets under study contain subcomplexes: The 
MIPS dataset (our reference set) includes 16 subcomplexes. Raw data 
includes 348 groups of proteins contained in others. None of the sets 
produced by hierarchical clustering display subcomplexes, as these 
are non-overlapping methods. The predicted sets (Dice-lcomm, PE-
lcomm, SA-lcomm, Dice-OCG, Hart-OCG, PE-OCG, CACHET and 
TRIBAL) display between 7 and 309 subcomplexes. 
In order to evaluate the subcomplex detection abilities of these 
methods, we performed two different analyses. Table 3 summarizes 
the precision and recall analysis for predicted subcomplexes when 
compared to the full MIPS dataset, using a hyper-geometric score as a 
criterion for a match. Table 4 does the same when using the geomet-
ric score. The results show that <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> has the best F-measure in 
both cases. Despite the fact that TRIBAL has the best precision in 
both cases, <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> has a far better recall which ultimately leads to a 
better F-measure. </p>

<p>Meet-min index evaluation. The hyper-geometric index, likewise 
the Jaccard index, the geometric index and the Dice score, is 
designed to measure similarity between two sets. However, we are 
not only interested in the similarity; we are also interested in the fact 
that one set contains the other. In this case, the meet-min index is the 
best validation criterion, as discussed in Figure 3. A meet-min value 
of 1.0 indicates that the smaller complex is a subset of the larger, and 
(1 -meetmin) gives the proportion of proteins in the subcomplex left 
out of the complex. </p>

<p>For this reason, we use the meet-min index to verify that predicted 
subcomplexes are not only similar but contained by MIPS complexes. 
Figure 2 depicts the number and percentage of validated predicted 
subcomplexes for TRIBAL, <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> and six other methods which 
combine different scoring and clustering systems, using the meet-
min index as comparison criterion. The results show that TRIBAL 
outperforms all other methods for meet-min equal to 1.0. <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> 
shows a good performance to low meet-min values, but it decreases 
strongly when meet-min increases. </p>

<p>Analysis of subcomplexes. In order to understand the reasons of the 
inferior performance of the overlapping clustering methods, we 
studied the structure and identity of their predicted subcomplexes. 
Initially, we identified some real biological complex-subcomplex 
pairs among the complexes in MIPS, including: </p>

<p>1. TIM22 complex with TIM9-TIM10 complex 
2. TFIIH complex with TFIIK complex 
3. SAGA complex with ADA-GCN5 complex 
4. Replication complex with: pre-replication complex, replication 
initiation complex, post-replication complex, DNA polymerase 
deltaIII, DNA polymerase epsilonII, and DNA polymerase zeta. 
5. Ribonuclease P with ribonuclease MRP 
6. Cytoskeleton with: microtubules and tubulin-associated proteins </p>

<p>However, when reviewing the complexes predicted by link-com-
munities and PE, we found real subcomplexes that the method fails 
to predict and false subcomplexes that the method is predicting. For 
instance: </p>

<p>1. NUP84-NPC subcomplex: This is a subcomplex of the nuclear 
pore complex (NPC). The algorithm does not predict this; 
instead, it predicts three other subcomplexes which are trun-
cated versions of NUP84-NPC. </p>

<p>Table 3 | Precision and recall analysis for different subcomplex prediction strategies, using the hypergeometric index as match criterion (p-
value , 0.05) </p>

<p>Methods 
#Predicted matches #All_Predicted_comp Precision 
#Reference_matches 
#All_Reference_comp 
Recall 
F-measure </p>

<p>Raw data 
139 
263 
0.53 
108 
214 
0.50 
0.52 
Dice-lcomm 
55 
102 
0.54 
64 
214 
0.30 
0.38 
PE-lcomm 
24 
35 
0.69 
30 
214 
0.14 
0.23 
SA-lcomm 
37 
67 
0.55 
43 
214 
0.20 
0.29 
Dice-OCG 
20 
29 
0.69 
11 
214 
0.05 
0.10 
Hart-OCG 
4 
7 
0.57 
6 
214 
0.03 
0.05 
PE-OCG 
34 
34 
1.00 
19 
214 
0.09 
0.16 
CACHET 
231 
309 
0.75 
130 
214 
0.61 
0.67 
TRIBAL 
18 
18 
1.00 
14 
214 
0.06 
0.12 </p>

<p>For subcomplexes and the hypergeometric criterion, CACHET is visibly the best performing method (higher F-measure). Both TRIBAL and PE-OCG display perfect results in terms of precision but a very poor 
recall. The good performance of CACHET is mainly due to its comparatively higher recall. </p>

<p>Table 4 | Precision and recall analysis for different subcomplex prediction strategies, using the geometric index as match criterion 
(score . 0.2) </p>

<p>Methods 
#Predicted matches #All_Predicted_comp Precision 
#Reference_matches 
#All_Reference_comp 
Recall 
F-measure </p>

<p>Raw data 
78 
263 
0.30 
65 
214 
0.30 
0.52 
Dice-lcomm 
29 
102 
0.28 
32 
214 
0.20 
0.38 
PE-lcomm 
14 
35 
0.40 
17 
214 
0.13 
0.23 
SA-lcomm 
21 
67 
0.31 
21 
214 
0.15 
0.29 
Dice-OCG 
1 
29 
0.03 
1 
214 
0.01 
0.10 
Hart-OCG 
1 
7 
0.14 
1 
214 
0.01 
0.05 
PE-OCG 
3 
34 
0.09 
4 
214 
0.03 
0.16 
CACHET 
106 
309 
0.34 
74 
214 
0.34 
0.67 
TRIBAL 
14 
18 
0.78 
8 
214 
0.07 
0.12 </p>

<p>For subcomplexes and the geometric criterion, CACHET is visibly the best performing method (higher F-measure). TRIBAL displays the best result in terms of precision but a very poor recall. The good 
performance of CACHET is mainly due to its comparatively higher recall. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4262 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04262 </p>

<p>
2. GLE2-NUP116-NUP82 subcomplex: This is also a subcomplex 
of the NPC, and has a biologically relevant subcomplex which is 
NUP82. The algorithm does not detect these two but two trun-
cated versions of GLE2-NUP116-NUP82 instead. 
3. NUP57 subcomplex: Similar to NUP84-NPC, the algorithm 
detects one truncated version of NUP57 instead of the relation-
ship to the NPC. </p>

<p>4. Polymerase-alpha-primase complex: This one contains two 
real subcomplexes: DNA primase and DNA polymerase alpha. 
The algorithm identifies two truncated versions of Polymerase-
alpha-primase instead. 
5. TREX complex has a subcomplex called THO complex, and in 
turn, there is an extended version of TREX that contains it. 
However, the algorithm shows three truncated versions of TREX. </p>

<p>Figure 3 | An example of similarity and containment metrics. The Jaccard and Geometric indexes are able to measure the similarity between two sets. </p>

<p>The higher Jaccard and Geometric indexes indicate that the two sets in (a) are more ''similar'' to each other than the two sets in (b). In opposition, 
the Meet-min is a better measure of containment. The higher meet-min index shows that the two sets in (b) are a perfect set and subset, while the two sets 
in (a) are only overlapping. The scores show that case (a) is an example of a good similarity with a not so good containment, while (b) is an example 
of a good containment with a poor similarity. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Number and percentage of validated predicted subcomplexes using TRIBAL and six other methods. TRIBAL outperforms CACHET and all </p>

<p>combinations of scoring strategies and overlapping clustering methods, for a meet-min equal to 1.0, that is, in terms of perfect containment of a 
subcomplex by a reference complex. This aplies to both (a) the number of validated subcomplexes and (b) the precision or percentage of validated 
subcomplexes. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4262 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04262 </p>

<p>
6. alpha-alpha-trehalose-phosphate-synthase complex: This one 
contains one subcomplex called TPS1-TPS2 complex (treha-
lose biosynthetic pathway). The algorithm instead detects two 
truncated versions of the larger complex. 
7. The NuA4-HAT complex contains a few real subcomplexes: 
EAF3-EAF5-EAF7 subcomplex, ACT1-ARP4-SWC4-YAF9 
subcomplex and ESA1-EPL1-YNG2-EAF6 subcomplex. The 
algorithm instead detects two versions of NuA4-HAT. </p>

<p>Details of the previous comparisons can be found in Supplemen-
tary Code. 
At the same time, OCG produced complexes and subcomplexes of 
a very large size. While the average size of a complex in MIPS is 6.3 
subunits, the predicted subcomplexes display the following average 
sizes: TRIBAL 5 5.61, CACHET 5 5.58, Dice 1 lcomm 5 4.71, PE 
1 lcomm 5 4.69, SA 1 lcomm 5 4.25, raw data 5 4.00, Dice 1 OCG 
5 24.93 and PE 1 OCG 5 24.00. The large size of the OCG com-
plexes allows them to intersect many subcomplexes. Such complexes 
do not have a biological meaning but our first comparison method 
(hyper-geometric) seems to be favouring this case. A complete 
description of the size distribution of complexes and subcomplexes 
can be found in the Supplementary file (section 4). 
In summary, results suggest that Link-communities's predicted 
subcomplexes are mainly truncated versions of a well-predicted 
complex, while OCG's subcomplexes lack biological meaning. </p>

<p>Discussion 
We have unveiled the limitants of AP-MS processing methods 
regarding their ability to predict subcomplexes and we have also 
suggested TRIBAL as an alternative solution to this. 
We have traditionally assumed that the fact that a pair of proteins 
shows multiple evidence of co-purification and few evidences of 
independent purification is a demonstration of the confidence that 
we can have in the quality of such an interaction. However, here we 
start from the assumption that it could also mean that the interaction 
can be repeated in multiple overlapping complexes. The current 
complex detection pipeline discards the second type of information 
because the scoring step converts all co-purifications to one inter-
action record. For this reason, a method to score interactions without 
removing the information of proteins co-purifying in different con-
texts (i.e. different complexes), could be useful. 
The scoring of triads of proteins instead of interactions has been 
our first attempt to design such a method. This is, instead of studying 
the pattern of co-purification and independent purification of a bait 
and a prey, we study the bait and pairs of preys. This way, we apply 
the Dice score to a modified pulldown matrix which contains the 
baits versus the pairs of preys that copurify with them. After remov-
ing low quality data and generating a PIN with the high quality triads, 
we also get a PIN with multiple edges. 
We tested and compared the performance of different combina-
tions of scoring methods (Dice, PE, Hart, SA) and overlapping clus-
tering algorithms (Link-communities, <rs type="software">OCG</rs>), with one method 
based on the core-attachment model (<rs type="software">CACHET</rs>) and our own 
method (TRIBAL). All these three types of methods are based on 
different assumptions; for example, that subcomplexes can be 
extracted from high-degree (highly connected) regions of the net-
work or, in our case, that co-purification information with different 
baits is not only useful as a data quality measure but can also include 
co-complex information in different biological contexts. These 
assumptions can be partially validated through the performances 
of the methods. The results show that <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> gives the best results 
in terms of similarity (geometric or hypergeometric indexes) to the 
MIPS reference set (this is mainly due to its better recall), while 
TRIBAL offers the best precision in terms of similarity and the best 
performance in terms of containment metrics (meet-min index). 
From the group of overlapping clustering methods, Link-communit-
ies shows better results than <rs type="software">OCG</rs>. </p>

<p>Regarding limitations, the nature of the TRIBAL method leads to a 
small number of predictions. New strategies to solve this limitation 
and address the subcomplex problem will be needed. The possibility 
of replacing the use of templates with clustering algorithms that do 
not find dense modules but functional subunits, or the possibility of 
using clustering algorithms designed for multiple edges, should be 
considered. Another important limitation is the lack of a gold stand-
ard or reference set specifically designed for subcomplexes. 
We have made a thorough analysis of the traditional complex 
prediction pipeline for AP-MS experiments. Besides problems due 
to coverage, false positives and inconsistencies regarding mutual 
pull-down (see Supplementary File), most traditional methods are 
not able to detect subcomplexes due to decisions made in the scoring 
and clustering steps. Based on this knowledge, we have identified the 
best strategies to detect subcomplexes, including the development of 
TRIBAL, a simple strategy that improves the precision of subcom-
plex prediction compared to previous methods. These strategies are 
the initial attempts to specifically address the subcomplex detection 
problem in co-purification data. This paper suggests that overlap-
ping clustering methods fail to detect subcomplexes from AP data 
while the core-attachment model used by <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> and similar 
software seems to be the best option to this date. However, it also 
suggests that alternatives such as the co-purification matrix intro-
duced by TRIBAL deserve more attention, as they show potential 
thanks to a high precision, especially when we evaluate the meet-min 
index, i.e., subcomplexes absolutely contained by larger complexes. 
Finally, research in subcomplex identification demands the genera-
tion of curated gold standards for subcomplexes, which will be an 
important step to achieve a better validation of predictions. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>All analyses in this paper were performed using R v.2.15.2 and some of its packages, 
including ''iRefR'' v.1.00 
12 , ''<rs id="software-41" type="software">igraph</rs>'' v.<rs corresp="#software-41" type="version">0.64</rs>, and ''<rs id="software-42" type="software">org.Sc.sgd.db</rs>'' v.<rs corresp="#software-42" type="version">2.9.1</rs>. All code 
needed to reproduce the following analyses can be found as Supplementary code. </p>

<p>Purification data. The raw purification dataset used in this study was taken from the 
Tandem Affinity Purification study of Gavin et al. 
6 on S.cerevisiae, available as 
supplementary material of their paper. It consists of 2166 experiments, using 1849 
baits in one experiment each, and 143 baits in 317 experiments repeated two or more 
times. A degree distribution of the purified proteins shows a power-law-like 
distribution, with a few high-degree nodes (Apa1, Cic1, Hhf1, Mak21, Psa1 and 
Pwp2) and a greater number of low-degree nodes, including 254 baits only purifying 
themselves. 912,333 out of 2,344,695 pairs of purified groups display some overlap of 
one or more proteins, while 601 out of 2,344,695 pairs display a meet-min index of 1, 
indicating that one is a subset of the other one. 
The ''org.Sc.sgd.db'' R library was used to convert SGD IDs to gene names. </p>

<p>Scoring indexes. After data is collected, it is scored using the four above-mentioned 
popular scoring methods. The SA score is defined as follows: </p>

<p>A i,j 
ð Þ~S i,jji~bait zS i,jjj~bait zM i,j 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>S i,jji~bait~l og 
n i,jji~bait </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>bait 
i </p>

<p>n bait f </p>

<p>prey 
j </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>prey 
i~bait </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>ð2Þ </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>M i,j~l og 
n </p>

<p>prey 
i,j </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>prey 
i </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>prey 
j </p>

<p>S all baits n prey n prey {1 
À 
Á 
2 </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>ð3Þ </p>

<p>Here A denotes the socio-affinity index, S is a spoke model-related term and M is a 
matrix model-related term. </p>

<p>n i,jji~bait is the number of times that protein i retrieves protein j when i is 
tagged. 
f </p>

<p>bait 
i </p>

<p>is the fraction of purifications where i was a bait. 
f </p>

<p>prey 
j </p>

<p>is the fraction of all retrieved preys that were j. 
n bait is the total number of purifications (i.e., of baits). 
n </p>

<p>prey </p>

<p>i~bait is the number of preys retrieved with protein i as bait. 
n </p>

<p>prey </p>

<p>i,j is the number of times that i and j co-purify with baits different to i or j. 
n prey is the number of preys observed with a specific bait (excluding itself). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4262 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04262 </p>

<p>
The Hart score makes use of a hypergeometric test to compute the probability of an 
interaction being observed at random: </p>

<p>p #interactions §kjn,m,N 
ð 
Þ 
X min n,m </p>

<p>ð 
Þ </p>

<p>i~k </p>

<p>p ijn,m,N 
ð 
Þ 
ð 4Þ </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>p ijn,m,N 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>N{n </p>

<p>m{i </p>



<p>
N 
m </p>

<p>
ð5Þ </p>

<p>Here k is the number of times the interaction is observed (success sample), n is the 
total number of interactions for the first protein (sample), m is the total number of 
interactions for the second protein (success population) and N is the total number of 
interactions in the full data set (population). Here, the interactions assume a matrix 
model. 
The PE score is computed as follows: </p>

<p>PE i,j~Sij zS ji zM ij 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>S ij~X k s ijk 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>M ij~X k m ijk 
ð8Þ </p>

<p>s ijk~l 
og 10 </p>

<p>rz 1{r 
ð 
Þ pijk 
pijk </p>

<p>if j is prey for bait i in purification k </p>

<p>log 10 1{r 
ð 
Þ 
otherwise </p>

<p>8 
&lt; </p>

<p>: 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>m ijk~l og 10 
rz 1{r 
ð 
Þp ijk 
p ijk 
ð10Þ </p>

<p>Here S is a spoke-term, M is a matrix-term, i is a bait, j is a prey and k is a purification. r 
is the probability of a true association to be detected, while p ijk is the probability of i 
and j being observed together for non specific reasons. For details regarding the 
estimation of these parameters, we refer the reader to Collins et al. </p>

<p>5   . 
The Dice score is defined as follows: </p>

<p>D i,j 
ð Þ~2 
q 
2qzrzs 
ð11Þ </p>

<p>Where i and j are two proteins vectors, with values of 1 for each experiment where that 
protein was pulled down as a prey, and a value of zero otherwise. q is the number of 
elements (experiments) where both i and j have 1's (appear in the same purification), r 
is the number of elements where i has 1 and j has 0, and s is the number of elements 
where i has 0 and j has 1, this is, (r 1 s) is the number of cases where the i-j pair does 
not co-purify. 
SA, Hart, PE and Dice scores applied to the raw data and to the clustering methods 
below specified, were computed using the ProCope software </p>

<p>29   . 
Our modified Dice score for the TRIBAL algorithm is explained in Results. </p>

<p>Clustering methods. Link-communities is a method that uses communities of edges 
and not of nodes. <rs type="software">OCG</rs> hierarchically merges edges into modules, checking the value 
of a special modularity function Q. Both <rs type="software">OCG</rs> and Link-communities were 
performed using the ''<rs type="software">linkcomm</rs>'' R package </p>

<p>20   . </p>

<p>CACHET. The 369 complexes generated by <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> from Gavin's dataset, were 
retrieved from their web page 
26 . 
In order to generate subcomplexes, we selected all complexes containing both core 
and attachments (i.e., we removed all only-core complexes). Subcomplexes were 
defined as the cores of those core-attachment sets. </p>

<p>Evaluation methods. In order to evaluate the quality of the complex predictions, we 
used the S.cerevisiae complex MIPS dataset as a gold standard, and compared it to 
every predicted complexes dataset. We highlight that alternative gold standard sets 
have been proposed 
30 ; however, the MIPS data set is still used as a validation 
instrument for the complex detection tools above mentioned </p>

<p>17,21,29   . 
The comparison is done through three strategies: Firstly, through a hypergeometric 
test, as defined in eq. (5). In this test, the population is the total number of proteins, 
the population success is the size of the MIPS complex, the sample is the predicted 
complex (predicted either by any combination of the scores and clustering algorithms 
here employed, <rs type="software">CACHET</rs> or TRIBAL) and the success sample is the size of the 
intersection between MIPS and the predicted complex. The overlap is considered 
significant when p-value , 0.05. </p>

<p>Secondly, the geometric index, defined as follows: </p>

<p>Geom~(length(Complex1\Complex2))^2=(length(Complex1) 1 length(Complex2)) 
ð12Þ </p>

<p>Where one complex is predicted and the other one belongs to the reference set. The 
overlap is considered significant when Geom . 0.2. 
Thirdly, the meet-min index, defined as follows: </p>

<p>Meet{min~length(Complex1\Complex2)=min length Complex1 
ð 
Þ ,length Complex2 
ð 
Þ 
ð 
Þ 
ð13Þ </p>

<p>Where one complex is predicted and the other one belongs to the reference set. A 
meet-min index of 1.0 indicates that one complex perfectly contains the other one. 
The relationship and distinction between the meet-min and the other metrics can 
be observed in figure 3. 
The performance of each method was assessed by computing their precision, recall 
and F-measure, defined as follows: </p>

<p>Precision~TP= TPzFP 
ð 
Þ 
ð 14Þ </p>

<p>Recall~TP= TPzFN 
ð 
Þ 
ð 15Þ </p>

<p>F{measure~2 1 Precision 1 Recall= PrecisionzRecall 
ð 
Þ 
ð 16Þ </p>

<p>Where TP 5 True positives (matches), FP 5 False positives (mispredictions) and FN 
5 False negatives. </p>

<p>TRIBAL algorithm. Both TRIBAL and its evaluations were coded using R 2.15.2 and 
its packages ''<rs type="software">iRefR</rs>'' and ''<rs type="software">igraph</rs>'', and they are available as Supplementary code. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to acknowledge the assistance provided by the Office of the Deputy 
Vice Chancellor for Research and Graduate Studies (NRF Grant Ref. No. 21T021 and 
31T046) at the United Arab Emirates University (UAEU). AM also thanks the Institute of 
Clinical Physiology (CNR, Pisa, Italy) for hosting him during the end of this project. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>N.Z. and A.M. contributed to the conceptual idea of the study and directed the writing of the 
manuscript. A.M. and N.Z. conceived and designed the experiments. A.M. performed the 
experimental work. A.M. and N.Z. analyzed the results. N.Z. and A.M. wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Zaki, N. &amp; Mora, A. A comparative analysis of computational 
approaches and algorithms for protein subcomplex identification. Sci. Rep. 4, 4262; 
DOI:10.1038/srep04262 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported license. To view a copy of this license, 
visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4262 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04262 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>