<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3351187" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Modifications of rRNAs are clustered in functional 
regions of the ribosome. In Helix 74 of Escherichia 
coli 23S rRNA, guanosines at positions 2069 
and 2445 are modified to 7-methylguanosine(m 7 G) 
and N 2 -methylguanosine(m 2 G), respectively. We 
searched for the gene responsible for m 7 G2069 
formation, and identified rlmL, which encodes the 
methyltransferase for m 2 G2445, as responsible for 
the biogenesis of m 7 G2069. In vitro methylation 
of rRNA revealed that rlmL encodes a fused 
methyltransferase responsible for forming both 
m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445. We renamed the gene 
rlmKL. The N-terminal RlmL activity for m 2 G2445 
formation was significantly enhanced by the 
C-terminal RlmK. Moreover, RlmKL had an unwind-
ing activity of Helix 74, facilitating cooperative 
methylations of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 during bio-
genesis of 50S subunit. In fact, we observed that 
RlmKL was involved in the efficient assembly of 
50S subunit in a mutant strain lacking an RNA 
helicase deaD. </p>

<p>The ribosome is a ribonucleoprotein complex that trans-
lates genetic information on mRNA into the corres-
ponding amino acid sequence to generate a protein. The 
ribosome consists of small and large subunits, each of 
which is composed of ribosomal RNAs (rRNAs) and ribo-
somal proteins. The rRNAs form the basic structure of the 
ribosome, and play central roles in the fundamental 
processes of protein biosynthesis (1-6). In all domains of 
life, rRNAs contain residues with various chemical modi-
fications that are enzymatically introduced after transcrip-
tion. These modifications are primarily base methylation, </p>

<p>ribose methylation and pseudouridylation (7,8). In pro-
karyotes, rRNA modifications are introduced by 
site-specific RNA-modifying enzymes, whereas in eukary-
otes, most rRNA modifications, namely 2 0 -O-methyla-
tions and pseudouridylations, are introduced by a series 
of small nucleolar RNA-protein complexes (snoRNPs) 
composed of a protein methyltransferase or pseud-
ouridylase and a specific snoRNA as a guide RNA to de-
termine the precise position for modification (9). rRNA 
modifications are clustered near the active sites of the 
ribosome such as the decoding center, subunit interfaces, 
transfer RNA (tRNA) or mRNA binding sites and the 
peptidyl-transferase center (10,11), implying that these 
modifications are required for proper function of the 
rRNAs. However, many rRNA modifications are dispens-
able for cell viability (12). In fact, the lack of a single 
rRNA modification confers only a mild defect in cell 
growth and ribosomal function. Hence, the exact 
function of each modification is unknown. However, col-
lective disruption of several modifications causes a severe 
defect in ribosomal function and cell growth (13,14). 
Therefore, each rRNA modification plays a specific role 
in fine-tuning ribosomal activity and/or biogenesis (8). 
The Escherichia coli ribosome contains 17 species 
of modified nucleotides at 36 positions in the rRNAs: 
7 species are found at 11 positions in 16S rRNA and 
15 species at 25 positions in 23S rRNA (8). The modifica-
tions are 10 pseudouridines, 24 methylated nucleosides, 
1 dihydrouridine and 1 5-hydroxycytidine (15). Although 
all of the pseudouridine synthase genes have been identi-
fied in E. coli, several methyltransferases still remain to be 
identified. In the decoding center of the small subunit of 
the ribosome, rRNA modifications play roles in maintain-
ing the translational fidelity by suppressing frameshifts 
and read-through activity (16-18), and ensuring accurate 
translational initiation (19,20). In the large 50S subunit of 
the ribosome, rRNA-modifying enzymes such as RrmJ/ 
FtsJ and RluD are required for efficient assembly of the 
subunit (21-24), indicating that the enzymes themselves </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +81 3 5841 8752; Fax: +81 3 5841 0550; Email: ts@chembio.t.u-tokyo.ac.jp </p>

<p>Published online 30 December 2011 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4071-4085 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkr1287 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>act as assembly factors for efficient biogenesis of the 
ribosome (25). In addition, some rRNA modifications 
are involved in modulating susceptibility to certain anti-
biotics (26,27). 
To understand the functional and physiological as-
pects of rRNA modifications, identifying the genes and 
enzymes responsible for each modification is essential. 
We developed a method of genome-wide screening called 
ribonucleome analysis to identify genes responsible 
for RNA modifications using a reverse genetic approach 
combined with mass spectrometry (MS) (28). This 
approach has successfully identified many genes respon-
sible for tRNA modifications among the uncharacterized 
genes in E. coli and Saccharomyces cerevisiae (29-33). 
Recently, we used this method to identify two methyl-
transferases, encoded by rsmH and rsmI, which are 
responsible for biogenesis of N 4 , 2 0 -O-dimethylcytidine 
(m 4 Cm) at position 1402 in the E. coli 16S rRNA (20). 
In Helix 74, in domain V of the 23S rRNA, G2069 and 
G2445 are modified to form 7-methylguanosine (m 7 G) 
and N 2 -methylguanosine (m 2 G), respectively (Figure 1A 
and B). The methyltransferase RlmL, encoded by 
rlmL/ycbY, catalyzes S-adenosylmethionine (Ado-Met)-
dependent m 2 G2445 formation (34). Although deletion 
of rlmL/ycbY resulted in a slight growth reduction pheno-
type, the functional and physiological role of m 2 G2445 
remains unclear (34). The methyltransferase mediating 
the biogenesis of m 7 G2069 has not yet been identified. 
In this study, we employed a genome-wide screen of 
uncharacterized genes in E. coli using the ribonucleome 
analysis to search for the gene responsible for m 7 G2069 
formation. We happened to identify rlmL/ycbY as respon-
sible for the biogenesis of m 7 G2069. In fact, rlmL/ycbY 
encodes a fused methyltransferase with dual active sites 
responsible for forming both m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 
(Figure 1C). Thus, rlmL/ycbY has been renamed rlmKL. 
Genetic and biochemical characterization of this unique 
enzyme has revealed that cooperative methylation of Helix 
74 by RlmKL plays a key role in the efficient assembly of 
the 50S subunit. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>RNA mass spectrometry </p>

<p>Each rRNA fraction (200 fmol) was digested at 37 C for 
30 min in a 10 ml reaction mixture containing 10 mM 
ammonium acetate (pH 5.3) and 5 U/ml RNase T1 
(Epicentre), or 10 mM ammonium acetate (pH 7.7) and 
1 ng/ml RNase A (Ambion). Subsequently, an equal 
volume of 0.1 M triethylamine-acetate (TEAA) (pH 7.0) 
was added to the reaction mixture for LC/MS. Analysis of 
RNA fragments by capillary liquid chromatography (LC) 
coupled with nano electrospray (ESI) LC/MS was carried 
out using a tandem quadrapole time-of-flight (QqTOF) 
mass spectrometer (QSTAR XL, Applied Biosystems) 
and a linear ion trap-orbitrap hybrid mass spectrometer 
(LTQ Orbitrap XL, Thermo Fisher Scientific). Both 
systems are equipped with a nano electrospray source 
and a splitless nano HPLC system (KYA Technologies), 
as described previously (20). Conditions and solvent </p>

<p>systems for capillary LC have been described previously 
(28). All procedures for the ribonucleome analysis were 
conducted as described previously (20). </p>

<p>Sucrose density gradient centrifugation </p>

<p>Subunit profiling by sucrose density gradient (SDG) cen-
trifugation was carried out as previously described (35). 
Briefly, E. coli cells were grown in 250 ml of Luria-Bertani 
(LB) medium in a 500-ml flask with vigorous shaking at 
25 C. Cells were harvested from 50 ml culture by centri-
fugation when the cell density reached an A 600 of 0.5. The 
cell pellet was resuspended in 1 ml of cold buffer [20 mM 
HEPES-KOH (pH 7.6), 0.5 mM Mg(OAc) 2 , 100 mM 
NH 4 Cl, 6 mM b-mercaptoethanol]. A cell lysate was 
prepared by the lysozyme-freeze-thaw method, as des-
cribed (35) and cleared by centrifugation at 15 000 rpm 
for 15 min at 4 C. The concentration of total RNA in 
the lysate was estimated by measuring A 260 . In total, 
10 U of A 260 of the lysate were layered on top of a 10-
40% SDG prepared in cold buffer and then separated by 
ultracentrifugation in a Beckman SW-28 Rotor at 
20 000 rpm for 14 h at 4 C. Fractions were collected 
from the gradient using a Piston Gradient Fractionator 
(BIOCOMP) and the position of the ribosomal subunits 
was monitored by A 260 using a ultra violet (UV) monitor 
(ATTO AC-5200). </p>

<p>In vitro methylation assay </p>

<p>For in vitro reconstitution of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 for-
mation, we used 23S rRNA or a series of rRNA fragments 
as substrates. rRNA fragments and transcripts 1-9 except 
for transcript 6 were transcribed in vitro by T7 RNA poly-
merase (see Supplementary Data, 'Materials and 
Methods' section). The transcript 6 was chemically 
synthesized (Sigma genosys). 
A reaction mixture (50 ml) consisting of 200 mM 
NH 4 OAc, 40 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 3 mM MgCl 2 , 
6 mM b-mercaptoethanol, 1 mM Ado-Met, 0.2 mM 23S 
rRNA (or rRNA fragments) and 0.1 mM recombinant 
RlmKL [or RlmK(CTD), or RlmL(NTD)] was incubated 
at 37 C for 2 h. Substrate RNAs were recovered from 
aliquots of the reaction mixture by phenol-chloroform 
extraction and ethanol precipitation. RNA was digested 
by RNase T1 or RNase A and analyzed by LC/MS. To 
examine the time course of methylation (Figure 4C and D 
and Supplementary Figures S2 and S4), a 100-ml reaction 
mixture was prepared and 10-ml aliquots were taken at 
each time point and mixed with phenol-chloroform to 
stop the reaction. For preparing the m 7 G2069-containing 
domain V RNA, 50 pmol domain V RNA was incubated 
at 37 C with 200 pmol RlmK (CTD) in 100 ml reaction 
mixture for 2 h. Phenol-chloroform-extracted RNA was 
passed through NAP-5 column (GE healthcare) to 
remove Ado-Met (Ado-Hcy), and recovered by ethanol 
precipitation. In RNase T1 digested samples, we 
detected a 16-mer fragment bearing m 7 G2069 (Um 7 GA 
ACCUUUACUAUAGp), or a 14-mer fragment without 
methylation (AACCUUUACUAUAGp). In RNase A 
digested samples, a tetramer fragment with (m 7 GAACp) 
or without (GAACp) m 7 G2069 and a hexamer fragment </p>

<p>4072 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 1. Tertiary and secondary structures of the E. coli 23S rRNA domain V and enzymatic formation of 7-methylguanosine (m 7 G2069) and N 2 -
methylguanosine (m 2 G2445). (A) The tertiary structure of domain V in E. coli 23S rRNA (PDB ID 2aw4). The strands G2061-C2084, G2235-C2258, 
C2422-D2449 are colored blue, green and red, respectively. Coordinates for Helix 93 are not displayed because it lies in front of Helix 74. The 
silhouette of 50S subunit was showed in gray line. (B) The secondary structure of domain V in the E. coli 23S rRNA with modified nucleotides, 
7-methylguanosine (m 7 G), N 2 -methylguanosine (m 2 G), 2 0 -O-methylguanosine (Gm), dihydrouridine (D), pseudouridine (É), 2 0 -O-methylcytidine 
(Cm), 5-hydroxycytidine (ho 5 C), N 2 -methyladenosine (m 2 A) and 2 0 -O-methyluridine (Um). The numbers of the RNA helices and nucleotides are 
indicated. Watson-Crick-type base pairs are shown by bars, and wobble base pairs by black dots. Helix 74 and surrounding regions are boxed on the 
left. The color code for each strand is the same as (A). (C) Enzymatic formation of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 is catalyzed by RlmK and RlmL, 
respectively, using Ado-Met as a methyl-group donor. Ado-Met is converted to Ado-Hcy (S-adenosylhomocysteine) by the reaction. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4073 </p>

<p>with (Gm 2 GGGAUp) or without (GGGGAUp) m 2 G2445 
were detected. The methylated and unmethylated frag-
ments were quantified by summing the areas of the mass 
chromatograms (±0.1 tolerance) of all detected ions. The 
frequency of methylation was calculated from the ratio of 
the areas of the mass chromatograms for the methylated 
and unmethylated fragments. For accurate quantification 
of both methylations, we generated a standard curve for 
the area ratio of the chromatograms against the ratio of 
the methylated fragments (Supplementary Figure S5). 
Using these curves, we could determine the exact values 
for methylation. 
For the mutational study of transcript 3, methylation 
assay was performed as followed. The reaction mixtures 
(20 ml) consisting of the same buffer, except for the 1 mM 
of substrate RNA and 48 mM of 14 C-labeled Ado-Met 
(MP Bio Inc.), were incubated at 37 C for 30 min. 
Reaction was stopped and the RNA substrate was ex-
tracted by the addition of 50 ml phenol-chloroform. The 
half-volume of the extracted RNA was spotted onto a 
Whatman 3 mm filter disc. The discs were washed three 
times with 5% trichloroacetic acid (Nacalai Tesque) and 
dried with ethanol. Total radioactivity for both m 7 G2069 
and m 2 G2445 methylations was then measured by liquid 
scintillation counting. The remaining half of RNA was 
treated by chloroform and precipitated with ethanol. 
The recovered RNA was digested with MazF (Takara) 
in the reaction mixture (5 ml) consisting of 1 Â MazF di-
gestion buffer (Takara), 10 U MazF and the RNA at 37 C 
for 1 h. A digested RNA was mixed with 5 ml of 
2 Â loading solution (9 M urea, 0.025 % bromophenol 
blue and 0.025% xylene cyanol) and electrophoresed by 
10% polyacrylamide gel with 7 M urea. The gel was 
stained by Toluidine blue O and dried in vacuo. 
Radioactivity was visualized and quantified using a 
FLA7000 system (Fujifilm). There were mainly three 
bands, which were the intact 123-mer substrate undigested 
by MazF, m 7 G2069-containing 27-mer fragment and 
m 2 G2445-containing 96-mer fragment (Supplementary 
Figure S7). The ratio of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 
was determined from the signal intensities of both 
fragments. Each methylation was determined from the 
ratio of both methylations and the total sum of the methy-
lations measured by the liquid scintillation counting. </p>

<p>RNA unwinding assay </p>

<p>The unwinding assay was basically carried out according 
to the literatures for RNA helicases (36,37). 5 0 -32 P-labeled 
transcript 8 and non-labeled transcript 9 were annealed to 
prepare the duplex substrate for RlmKL. In this experi-
ment, one guanosine residue was added to 5 0 -end of 
transcript 8 for efficient in vitro transcription. Annealing 
was performed in 8 ml aliquot containing 200 mM 
NH 4 OAc, 40 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.6), 3 mM MgCl 2 , 
6 mM b-mercaptoethanol, 2 pmol transcript 8, 2 pmol 
transcript 9 and 5 0 -32 P-labeled transcript 8 (220 000 cpm) 
as a tracer. The mixture was heated at 90 C for 1 min and 
stood at room temperature for 20 min. After 3 min 
pre-incubation at 30 C, 0.8 ml of the mixture was mixed 
with 19.2 ml solution containing 200 mM NH 4 OAc, 70 mM </p>

<p>Tris-HCl (pH 7.6), 3 mM MgCl 2 , 60 mM KCl, 6 mM 
b-mercaptoethanol, 0.6 mM dithiothreitol (DTT) 1 mM 
Ado-Met, 4 pmol non-labeled transcript 8 and 10 mg of 
RlmKL (100 pmol) or acetylated bovine serum albumin 
(BSA) (B2518 Sigma-Aldrich). The reaction mixture was 
incubated at 30 C. At each period of time, 5 ml aliquot 
was taken and mixed with 1.67 ml of 4 Â quench solution 
containing 120 mM ethylenediaminetetra acetic acid, 
2.4% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS), 40% glycerol and 
bromphenol blue (BPB) and left on ice. The quenched 
mixtures were analyzed by 15% native polyacrylamide 
gel electrophoresis (PAGE) (29:1) at 4 C. The gel was 
exposed to the imaging plate to visualize and quantify 
the duplex and the unwound single strand by FLA7000 
imaging analyzer system (Fujifilm). The plot was fitted to 
one phase decay equation [dsRNA unwound] = [dsRNA] 0 
Á(1Àexp(ÀkÁtime/[dsRNA] 0 )) and the half-life was calcu-
lated, using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad PRISM</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Graph Pad software</rs>). 
Other materials and methods are described in 
Supplementary Data. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Identification of rlmL/ycbY as the enzyme mediating 
m 7 G2069 formation </p>

<p>To identify gene products responsible for rRNA modifi-
cations in E. coli, we employed a reverse genetic approach 
combined with RNA MS (ribonucleome analysis) for 
genome-wide screening in E. coli (20,28). Total RNA, con-
sisting primarily of rRNAs and mRNAs, was prepared 
from 94 genomic-deletion strains of E. coli (38), each of 
which lacks about 20 kb ($20 genes) (see Supplementary 
Data). Thus, this analysis covered almost 2000 genes, 
$40% of the total 4762 genes of E. coli. Total RNA 
was digested into fragments by base-specific ribonucleases 
(RNase T1 or RNase A) and the digests were analyzed by 
capillary LC coupled with nano ESI LC/MS. In these 
complex mixtures of RNA fragments, we can detect 
RNA fragments containing modified nucleoside(s) as 
multiply-charged negative ions by monitoring the 
specific mass-to-charge ratio (m/z) value. Using both 
RNase T1 and RNase A, we can detect all modifications 
to be analyzed. In wild-type E. coli, we clearly detected the 
triple-charged negative ion (m/z 1706) of a 16-mer 
fragment including m 7 G2069 (Um 7 GAACCUUUACUA 
UAGp; MW 5120) produced by RNase T1 digestion, and 
the double-charged negative ion (m/z 1024) of a hexamer 
fragment including m 2 G2445 (Gm 2 GGGADp; MW 2049) 
produced by RNase A digestion (Figures 1B and 2A). 
Each fragment was analyzed by collision-induced dissoci-
ation (CID) by MS/MS to confirm the exact position of 
the modification (Figure 2B). When we analyzed RNA 
fragments from the deletion strain OCR55 (DpncB-rmf), 
the 16-mer fragment bearing m 7 G2069 was absent 
(Figure 2A). If 7-methylation of G does not occur at 
position 2069, an unmodified 14-mer fragment (AACCU 
UUACUAUAGp; m/z 1485, MW 4454) should be 
detected. In fact, we clearly detected this 14-mer 
fragment from the OCR55 strain (data not shown), con-
firming the absence of m 7 G2069. These data indicated that </p>



<p>a gene responsible for m 7 G2069 formation resides in this 
deleted region. Since rlmL/ycbY is also localized in this 
region, no hexamer fragment bearing m 2 G2445 was 
observed (Figure 2A). To identify the gene responsible 
for m 7 G2069 formation, we analyzed 23 single gene 
knockout strains (KO collections), each of which 
lacks one gene in the deleted region of OCR55. The 
DrlmL/ycbY strain was found to lack the 16-mer 
fragment bearing m 7 G2069 (Figure 2A). To our surprise, </p>

<p>rlmL/ycbY gene encodes a known methyltransferase, 
RlmL, which is responsible for m 2 G2445 formation (34) 
and in fact, no hexamer fragment bearing m 2 G2445 was 
detected in this strain (Figure 2A). When a plasmid 
encoding rlmL/ycbY was introduced into the DrlmL/ 
ycbY strain, both m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 were detected 
in the total RNA (Figure 2A). These data clearly 
demonstrated that rlmL/ycbY is responsible not only for 
m 2 G2445 formation, but also for m 7 G2069 formation. </p>

<p>824.9 
M-mG </p>

<p>362.1 
y1 
815.6 
y5 </p>

<p>852.4 
M </p>

<p>662.6 
y4 </p>

<p>691.1 
y2 </p>

<p>305.0 
c1 </p>

<p>419.0 
a2_B </p>

<p>997.1 
y3 </p>

<p>1000 
400 
600 
800 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A C C U U U A C U A A 
A 
m 7 G 
p 
G 
U 
U </p>

<p>c1 a2_B </p>

<p>y1 
y2 
y3 
y4 
y5 </p>

<p>m/z 
Relative abundance </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 
1 
0 
0 
3 </p>

<p>1079.1 
w3 </p>

<p>325.1 
y1 
344.1 
c1 </p>

<p>405.0 
w1 
654.1 
y2 
458.1 
a2_B 
703.1 
c2 
974.7 
M-P </p>

<p>1023.7 
M </p>

<p>999.2 
y3 </p>

<p>734.1 
w2 817.1 
a3_B </p>

<p>1048.1 
c3 </p>

<p>500 
900 
700 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>G A Dp 
G 
m 2 G 
G </p>

<p>a2_B a3_B </p>

<p>c1 c2 c3 </p>

<p>y3 y2 y1 
w3 w2 w1 </p>

<p>m/z 
Relative abundance </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Relative abundance </p>

<p>ΔycbY </p>

<p>ycbY </p>

<p>(rlmKL) 
+ pYcbY(pRlmKL) </p>

<p>28.2 
28.8 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
23.6 
24.2 </p>

<p>) 
n 
i 
m 
( 
e 
m 
i 
T 
) 
n 
i 
m 
( 
e 
m 
i 
T </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>36.6 
37.4 
0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
22.7 
23.3 </p>

<p>7 
. 
8 
2 
1 
. 
8 
2 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
23.6 
24.2 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Δ 
(rlmKL) </p>

<p>28.2 
28.8 
0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
23.6 
24.2 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Relative abundance </p>

<p>Um 7 GAACCUUUACUAUAGp 
(m/z 1706) </p>

<p>m 7 G2069 
m 2 G2445 </p>

<p>Gm 2 GGGADp 
(m/z 1024) </p>

<p>Wild-type </p>

<p>Figure 2. ycbY (rlmKL) is responsible for both m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 formation. (A) LC/MS analyses of RNase T1 (left panels) and RNase A 
(right panels) digests of rRNAs from the wild-type (Top row of panels), genome-deletion strain OCR55 (Second row), DycbY (rlmKL) strain (Third 
row) and DycbY (rlmKL) strain carrying pRlmKL (Bottom row). Left and right panels show mass chromatograms detecting the triply-charged ions 
of the 16-mer fragment bearing m 7 G2069 (m/z 1706) and the doubly charged ions of the hexamer fragment bearing m 2 G2445 (m/z 1024), respectively. 
(B) Collision-induced dissociation (CID) spectra of RNA fragments bearing m 7 G2069 (left panel) and m 2 G2445 (right panel). The six-charged ion 
(m/z 852.4) of the 16-mer fragment carrying m 7 G2069 and doubly charged ion (m/z 1023.7) of the hexamer fragment carrying m 2 G2445 were used as 
parent ions for CID. The sequences were confirmed by assignment of the product ions. The nomenclatures for product ions of nucleic acids are as 
suggested in the literature (41). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4075 </p>

<p>Therefore, we renamed the gene rlmKL according to the 
preferred nomenclature (39,40). </p>

<p>RlmKL is a fused methyltransferase consisting of an 
N-terminal RlmL domain and a C-terminal 
RlmK domain </p>

<p>Escherichia coli RlmKL is a fused methyltransferase 
consisting of 702 amino acid residues, containing a 
thiouridine synthases, methylases and PSUSs (THUMP) 
domain and two methyltransferase domains (Figure 3A). 
According to the cluster of orthologous group (COG) 
database (42), the N-terminal domain (NTD) and 
C-terminal domain (CTD) of RlmKL have been 
annotated as COG0116 and COG1092, respectively. 
Each domain has an Ado-Met-dependent methyl-
transferase motif (Figure 3A). The rlmKL gene is 
conserved in g-proteobacteria (Supplementary Figure S1). 
However, in b-proteobacteria, Neisseria meningitidis bears 
COG0116 and COG1092 as separate proteins encoded at 
different genomic loci (Supplementary Figure S1). Since 
rlmKL appears to be responsible for two different methyl 
modifications, we hypothesized that each methyltransferase 
domain catalyzes the formation of one modification, either 
m 7 G2069 or m 2 G2445. To examine this possibility, 
we carried out complementation tests for the two methyl 
modifications in the DrlmKL strain by introducing various 
rlmKL mutants. We constructed rlmKL mutants in which 
conserved amino acid residues were substituted with Ala, 
including D195A, N309A, N397A, R530A, D568A and 
D597A. As a positive control, introduction of 
plasmid-encoded rlmKL into the DrlmKL strain restored 
both methyl modifications (Figure 3B). Subsequently, 
each of the rlmKL mutants was introduced into the 
DrlmKL strain, and formation of the methyl modifications 
was examined. The N309A mutation in the NTD impaired 
m 2 G2445 formation, but rescued m 7 G2069 formation 
(Figure 3B). In contrast, the D568A mutation in the CTD 
did not rescue m 7 G2069 formation, but m 2 G2445 was effi-
ciently formed in this mutant (Figure 3B). These observa-
tions suggested that the NTD and CTD of RlmKL encode 
an RlmL for m 2 G2445 formation and an RlmK for 
m 7 G2069 formation, respectively. Asn397 is located in the 
linker region between the NTD and CTD. Since the N397A 
mutant exhibited no m 2 G2445 formation but rescued 
m 7 G2069 formation, Asn397 should be considered part of 
RlmL. The other mutations, including D195A, R530A and 
D597A, did not affect methylation (data not shown). 
We next examined complementation of methyl modifi-
cations by the separate N-terminal domain [RlmL(NTD)] 
and C-terminal domain [RlmK(CTD)] constructs. Given 
the C-terminal end of the N. meningitidis RlmL homolog 
(Supplementary Figure S1) and that Asn397 should be 
part of RlmL, Met1 to Arg398 of RlmKL was used for 
RlmL(NTD), while Asn376 to Ala702 was cloned for 
RlmK(CTD). The RlmL(NTD) construct rescued 
m 2 G2445 formation, and the RlmK(CTD) construct 
restored m 7 G2069 formation (Figure 3B). These data 
indicated that each methyltransferase domain could com-
plement each methylation defect when supplied on a 
multicopy plasmid. Moreover, m 7 G2069 formation did </p>

<p>not require pre-existing m 2 G2445 and vice versa: both 
methylations occur independently. 
Neisseria meningitidis has separate protein homologs for 
RlmL and RlmK. We next examined whether these 
homologs have the same activities as the E. coli RlmKL. 
We cloned the N. meningitidis rlmL (NMB0455) and 
rlmK (NMB1367) homologs into multicopy plasmids, 
and introduced each construct into the E. coli DrlmKL 
strain. As shown in Figure 3C, the N. meningitidis 
rlmL and rlmK homologs rescued m 2 G2445 and 
m 7 G2069 formation, respectively, demonstrating that the 
N. meningitidis RlmL and RlmK proteins have activities 
corresponding to the NTD and CTD of rlmKL. </p>

<p>In vitro reconstitution of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 
catalyzed by RlmKL </p>

<p>Methylation of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 was reconstituted 
in vitro using recombinant RlmKL. The E. coli RlmKL 
and the RlmK(CTD) and RlmL(NTD) constructs were 
expressed recombinantly and purified to homogeneity 
(Figure 4A). As substrates, we isolated 50S ribosomal 
subunits and naked 23S rRNA lacking both m 7 G2069 
and m 2 G2445 from the DrlmKL strain. The recombinant 
proteins were incubated with the 50S subunit and the 
naked 23S rRNA in the presence or absence of Ado-Met 
as a methyl donor and the rRNAs were then extracted and 
analyzed by LC/MS. No methylation was formed when 
the 50S subunit was used as the substrate for RlmKL 
(Figure 4B). When the naked 23S rRNA was used as a 
substrate, both m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 were successfully 
reconstituted by RlmKL in the presence of Ado-Met 
(Figure 4B). These results clearly showed that RlmKL 
uses the naked 23S rRNA as a substrate, indicating that 
methyl modifications of Helix 74 by RlmKL are likely to 
be introduced at an early step in 50S assembly in the cell. 
Next, m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 formation by RlmK(CTD) 
and RlmL(NTD), respectively, was reconstituted. As 
expected, m 7 G2069 was generated by RlmK(CTD), 
whereas m 2 G2445 was generated by RlmL(NTD) 
(Figure 4B). These data demonstrated that RlmKL is a 
fused methyltransferase, with each of the domains, 
N-terminal RlmL and C-terminal RlmK, acting independ-
ently as a methyltransferase. To facilitate the in vitro 
experiments, we examined the 23S rRNA domain V, 
which was transcribed in vitro. In fact, both methylations 
were efficiently introduced to the domain V transcript. </p>

<p>RlmK supports the N 2 -methylation of G2445 catalyzed 
by RlmL </p>

<p>To investigate the functional advantages of a fused 
methyltransferase, we examined the cooperativity of 
methylations by the two domains. We employed the 
domain V transcript as a substrate to compare the activi-
ties of m 2 G2445 formation catalyzed by RlmL(NTD) 
and RlmKL (Figure 4C). The initial velocity of 
m 2 G2445 formation by RlmKL was much higher than 
that by RlmL(NTD). Whether the RlmL(NTD)-catalyzed 
m 2 G2445 formation was affected by the addition of 
RlmK(CTD) in trans was also examined (Figure 4C). 
The initial velocity of m 2 G2445 formation was increased </p>



<p>depending on the concentration of RlmK(CTD), showing 
that the addition of RlmK(CTD) elevated the m 2 G2445-
forming activity of RlmL(NTD). In the presence of 
0.8 mM RlmK(CTD), 0.1 mM RlmL(NTD) exhibited an </p>

<p>m 2 G2445-forming activity level similar to 0.1 mM 
RlmKL (Figure 4C). It was speculated that m 2 G2445 
formation by RlmL(NTD) might be enhanced by the 
presence of m 7 G2069 generated by RlmK(CTD) in </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Figure 3. Complementation study of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 formation by plasmid-encoded RlmKL and mutants. (A) Domain structure of E. coli 
RlmKL. RlmKL consists of two methyltransferase domains, COG0116 and COG1092. We designated the N-terminal domain (COG0116) as RlmL 
and the C-terminal domain (COG1092) as RlmK. Each domain has an Ado-Met-dependent methyltransferase motif, UPF0020 in the RlmL domain 
and Cons_hypoth 95 in the RlmK domain. A THUMP domain was found in the N-terminal region of the RlmL domain. (B) Complementation of 
the DrlmKL strain by introducing plasmid-encoded RlmKL or RlmKL mutants. On the left hand side, the domain structures and the mutation 
positions of RlmKL are shown. On the right hand side, mass chromatograms detecting the 16-mer fragment carrying m 7 G2069 (m/z 1706) and the 
hexamer fragment carrying m 2 G2445 (m/z 1024), respectively, are shown for the DrlmKL strain transformed with pRlmKL (top panels), pRlmKL 
N309A (second panels), pRlmKL N397A (third panels), pRlmK (fourth panels), pRlmKL D568A (fifth panels) and pRlmL (bottom panels). 
(C) Complementation of the E. coli DrlmKL strain by introducing N. meningtidis RlmL (NMB0445) or RlmK (NMB1367). Mass chromatograms 
on the right panels are the same as in (B). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4077 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A 
C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Figure 4. In vitro reconstitution of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 formation by RlmKL. (A) SDS-PAGE analysis of the purified recombinant RlmKL, 
RlmL(NTD) and RlmK(CTD) stained with coomassie Brilliant Blue R-250. (B) In vitro reconstitution of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 by RlmKL, 
RlmL(NTD) or RlmK(CTD). Left and right panels show mass chromatograms detecting the triple-charged ions of the 16-mer fragment bearing 
m 7 G2069 (m/z 1706) and the double-charged ions of the hexamer fragment bearing m 2 G2445 (m/z 1024), respectively. Conditions for in vitro </p>

<p>4078 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 </p>

<p>(continued) </p>

<p>substrate RNA. To examine this possibility, we prepared 
the domain V transcript with m 7 G2069 (82% was 
modified). However, the presence of m 7 G2069 did not 
affect the m 2 G2445-forming activity (Supplementary 
Figure S2). In contrast, the initial velocities of m 7 G2069 
formation by RlmKL and RlmK were very similar 
(Figure 4D). In these experiments, we clearly demon-
strated that the fusion of these two methyltransferases 
enhances the efficiency of m 2 G2445 formation. </p>

<p>Minimization of the substrate recognized by RlmKL </p>

<p>To investigate substrate recognition by RlmKL, we 
minimized the substrate RNA by preparing six truncated 
RNAs, based on domain V, by in vitro transcription and 
examined the transcripts for methylation by RlmKL 
(Figure 4E and F and Supplementary Figure S3). By the 
end point measurement, over 90% of the domain V tran-
script (transcript 1) was methylated at both positions 
(Figure 4E and F). The methylation of transcript 2 
indicated that the lower parts of domain V, including 
Helices 73, 89 and 90-93, are not necessary for either 
methylation (Figure 4E and F). Even when the upper 
part of domain V was truncated, as in transcripts 3, 4 
and 5 (Supplementary Figure S3) m 7 G2069 and 
m 2 G2445 were efficiently formed (Figure 4E and F). 
These results indicated that removal of the upper part 
(Helices 76-79), as well as the right part (Helices 81-88) 
with connecting residues C2258 and C2422 (transcript 4) 
or connecting residues C2258 and A2426 (transcripts 3 
and 5) resulted in little effect on either methylation 
(Figure 4E and F). In contrast, transcript 7 (Figure 4E 
and Supplementary Figure S3), which lacks Helix 80 and 
the 12 nt single-strand (ss) region (Figure 1B), was not 
methylated at either position (Figure 4F). This result 
indicated that Helix 80 and the 12 nt ss region are 
critical sites necessary for m 2 G2445 and m 7 G2069 forma-
tion. Additionally, in the 29-mer single-stranded transcript 
6 which consists of residues C2422 to A2450 (Figure 4E 
and Supplementary Figure S3), m 2 G2445 was efficiently 
formed (Figure 4F). This result indicated that duplex for-
mation of H74 is not required for the m 2 G2445 formation. 
As the single-stranded RNA (transcript 6) was a good 
substrate for RlmKL, we examined a substrate specificity 
of RlmL(NTD) using transcripts 4 and 6 as substrates 
(Supplementary Figure S4). RlmL(NTD) catalyzed the 
m 2 G2445 formation on transcript 6, but did not efficiently 
methylate transcript 4 which forms Helix 74 (Figure 4E). 
This result strongly suggests that RlmL prefers the 
single-stranded RNA substrate for the m 2 G2445 </p>

<p>formation. Taken together with the observation that 
RlmK domain has a function to support the m 2 G2445 
formation by RlmL(NTD), we speculated that RlmK 
domain unwinds the duplex structure of Helix 74, 
thereby facilitating the efficient N 2 -methylation of G2445 
catalyzed by the RlmL domain. </p>

<p>Unwinding activity of RlmKL </p>

<p>To examine the unwinding activity of RlmKL, we per-
formed the unwinding assay used for RNA helicases 
(36,37). The 5 0 -32 P-labeled transcript 8 and non-labeled 
transcript 9 were annealed to prepare the duplex substrate 
for RlmKL (Figure 5A). The duplex and single strands 
were resolved by native PAGE to monitor the unwind-
ing of the duplex with the passage of reaction time 
(Figure 5B). In the presence of RlmKL, 71% of the 
duplex substrate was unwound in the first 3 min, and 
92% was unwound in 30 min (Figure 5B). As a control, 
in the presence of BSA, 29% of the duplex substrate was 
spontaneously converted to the single strand, and 66% 
was unwound in 30 min (Figure 5B). In the presence of 
RlmKL, the half-life (t 1/2 ) of the duplex substrate was 
2.5 min, whereas in the presence of BSA, t 1/2 was 6.0 min 
(Figure 5C). We also examined the unwinding activity of 
RlmKL in the absence of Ado-Met, and found no change 
in the activity (data not shown). These results suggested 
that RlmKL has an activity to unwind Helix 74 during 
substrate recognition and methylation. </p>

<p>Substrate recognition by RlmKL </p>

<p>To identify the sites required for both methylations, we 
constructed a series of variants based on transcript 3 and 
measured the methylation capacity of each variant. The 
secondary structure of transcript 3, the detailed constructs 
of the variants and their methylation activities are shown 
in Figure 6A, B and C, respectively. The efficiency of 
methylation was measured as described in 'Materials 
and Methods' section (Supplementary Figure S7). The 
base flipping of Helix 80 reduced m 7 G2069 formation. 
In the P-loop, three variants, G2250C, G2251C and 
G2252C, lacked m 7 G2069 formation, and G2253C 
reduced m 7 G2069 formation, whereas the C2254A 
variant showed normal activity. All mutants in P-loop 
and H80 have efficient m 2 G2445 forming capacities. In 
the 12 nt ss region, three variants, C2427U, G2429A and 
A2430U showed reduced m 7 G2069 forming activity, 
whereas G2428C and G2429A lacked m 2 G2445 formation 
and C2427U and A2430U and 2431-2433 mutation 
reduced the m 2 G2445 formation. In Helix 74, decreased </p>

<p>Figure 4. Continued 
methylation are indicated in the right hand side. The hexamer fragment with m 2 G2445 produced by RNase A digestion of domain V is 
Gm 2 GGGAUp (m/z 1023, MW 2047). (C) Time-course of m 2 G2445 formation in domain V (transcript 1) catalyzed by 0.1 mM RlmL(NTD) 
(open circle), 0.1 mM RlmL(NTD) with 0.1 mM RlmK(CTD) (closed triangle), 0.1 mM RlmL(NTD) with 0.2 mM RlmK(CTD) (open triangle), 
0.1 mM RlmL(NTD) with 0.4 mM RlmK(CTD) (closed square), 0.1 mM RlmL(NTD) with 0.8 mM RlmK(CTD) (open square) and 0.1 mM RlmKL 
(closed circle). (D) Time-course of m 7 G2069 formation in domain V (transcript 1) catalyzed by 0.1 mM RlmK(CTD) (open circle) and 0.1 mM RlmKL 
(closed circle). (E) Truncated RNA substrates. Open and closed circles in the secondary structures indicate the positions of G2069 and G2445, 
respectively. Detailed constructs for transcripts 3-7 are shown in Supplementary Figure S3. (F) Truncation of domain V (transcript 1) to identify the 
minimum substrate. The ratio of methylation (%) was calculated from the area of mass chromatograms for the methylated and unmethylated 
fragments at the end point of the reaction (see Materials and Methods). White and black bars represent the efficiency of m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 
formation, respectively. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4079 </p>

<p>m 2 G2445 formation was detected in the base-flipping 
variant C2072G/G2437C. In addition, A2070G/U2441C, 
G2067C/C2443G and C2066G/G2444C mutants lacked 
the m 2 G2445 formation. The five base-flipping variants, 
A2071U/U2438A, A2070G/U2441, G2067C/C2443G, 
C2066G/G2444C, C2064G/G2446C and the base substitu-
tion mutant U2068A showed no m 7 G2069 forming 
activity. The decreased m 7 G2069 formation was observed 
in C2065G/G2445C mutant. No significant change in the 
methylation of the A2439G and C2440G variants of the 
internal loop of Helix 74 were observed. 
In summary, the sites required for m 7 G2069 formation 
and m 2 G2445 formation are illustrated in Figure 6D. 
In Helix 80 and the P-loop, G2250, G2251, G2252 and 
G2253 are critical only for 7-methylation of G2069, and 
the stem of H80 is also involved in m 7 G2069 formation. 
In the 12 nt ss region, C2427, G2429 and A2430 are 
recognized for both methylations, and especially G2428 
and G2429 were critical for N 2 -methylation of G2445 
and additionally, the residues 2431-2433 are recognized 
for m 2 G2445 formation. In Helix 74, C2064/G2446, 
C2065/G2445, C2066/G2444, G2067/C2443, U2068, 
A2070/U2441 and A2071/U2438 were essential for 
7-methylation of G2069. For m 2 G formation, duplex for-
mation was not necessary as described above. Therefore, 
in the 3 0 single strand of Helix 74, U2441, C2443 and 
G2444 were required for N 2 -methylation of G2445. The 
relative orientations of these bases are shown in the crystal 
structure of the 50S subunit (Figure 6E). These results 
clearly demonstrated that different sets of residues were 
involved, respectively, in 7-methylation of G2069 and </p>

<p>N 2 -methylation of G2445, suggesting that the N-terminal 
RlmL and C-terminal RlmK domains in RlmKL recog-
nize distinct residues in the substrate. </p>

<p>rlmKL is involved in efficient 50S assembly </p>

<p>The protein product of ycbY has been reported to 
co-sediment with the early assembly intermediate of the 
50S ribosomal subunit in E. coli (43). In addition, YcbY 
interacts with the DeaD and SrmB proteins, which are 
DEAD-box RNA helicases involved in 50S subunit for-
mation (44-46). These results suggested that RlmKL may 
be involved in an early stage of the biogenesis of the 50S 
subunit. However, disruption of the rlmKL gene showed 
almost no growth phenotype even when cells were 
cultured at low temperature (Figure 7A), and no signifi-
cant change in ribosome profile was detected (Figure 7B). 
Since YcbY interacts with DeaD and SrmB in E. coli (45), 
we explored the synthetic growth phenotype of the 
DrlmKL strain in which RNA helicases, including deaD, 
srmB, rhlE and dbpA, were knocked out. As shown in 
Figure 7A, we observed a synthetic growth phenotype 
with deaD, in particular at low temperature. When 
cultured at 37 C, the doubling time of the DrlmKL/ 
DdeaD strain (28.4 min) was delayed by 4.5 min relative 
to the DrlmKL strain (23.9 min) and 2.9 min relative to 
the DdeaD strain (25.5 min). At 28 C, the 
DrlmKL/DdeaD strain exhibited a growth defect resulting 
in a doubling time of 99.0 min, a 50 min delay relative to 
the DrlmKL strain (49.0 min) and a 21.7 min delay relative 
to the DdeaD strain (77.3 min). This result suggested that </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>A 
C </p>

<p>A 
C </p>

<p>A U </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>H74 </p>

<p>U 
A 
U </p>

<p>U 
A 
C 
G 
C 
G 
A 
U </p>

<p>A 
U </p>

<p>G 
C 
C 
G </p>

<p>C 
G </p>

<p>A 
U </p>

<p>C 
G </p>

<p>U 
A </p>

<p>A 
U </p>

<p>U 
G </p>

<p>H75 </p>

<p>H80 </p>

<p>A 
G </p>

<p>U 
G 
C </p>

<p>C 
G </p>

<p>Ploop </p>

<p>A 
A 
U </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>G 
A 
G C A 
A 
C </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>U G C </p>

<p>A U </p>

<p>C G </p>

<p>U G </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>G G G </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>2450 </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>32 P </p>

<p>3' 
5' </p>

<p>5' 
3' </p>

<p>Transcript 8 
Transcript 9 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
0 
5 
10 15 20 25 30 </p>

<p>Ratio of duplex (%) </p>

<p>Reaction time (min) </p>

<p>t 1/2 6.0 ± 0.9 </p>

<p>t 1/2 2.5 ± 1.1 </p>

<p>Duplex 
ratio (%) </p>

<p>ss </p>

<p>ds </p>

<p>(min) </p>

<p>RlmKL+ 
BSA+ 
0 3 7 15 30 0 3 7 15 30 </p>

<p>63 18 12 7 5 70 50 44 35 24 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 5. Unwinding activity of RlmKL. (A) The RNA substrate used for the unwinding assay. 5 0 -end of transcript 8 was labeled by 32 P. (B) The 
unwinding assay by RlmKL. The duplex and single strands were separated by native PAGE and the radio activity of transcript 8 was visualized and 
quantified by the imaging analyzer. Duplex ratio (%) described at the bottom of the panel stands for the remaining duplex proportion in total radio 
activity of transcript 8. The left 5 lanes and the right 5 lanes show time course monitoring of the unwinding activity in the presence of RlmKL 
(RlmKL + ) and BSA (BSA + ), respectively. (C) Duplex ratio (%) was plotted against reaction time (min). Open and closed circles indicate BSA + and 
RlmKL + , respectively. The half-lives (t 1/2 ) for both conditions were calculated by non-linear curve fitting and shown as average ±SD; values of three 
independent experiments. </p>

<p>4080 Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 </p>

<p>Figure 6. Substrate recognition of RlmKL. (A) The secondary structure of transcript 3, which contains base flipping mutation C2096G/G2193C to 
be cut by MazF at the single position. Closed arrowhead show the cleavage position by MazF. (B) Design of mutants based on the transcript 3. 
Arrows and boxes indicate the substitutions. (C) Methylation activities of the transcript 3 variants. The left and right graphs show the end point of 
m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 formation, respectively. The relative activities of methylation (%) were calculated and normalized by wild-type sequence. 
(D) The recognized residues for m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 formation in transcript 3. The residues whose mutations reduced m 7 G2069 or m 2 G2445 
formation to &lt;50% are depicted as white letters. In the left panel, the residues that are depicted in blue background indicates the m 7 G2069 forming 
activity. In the right panel, the residues that are depicted in red background indicates the m 2 G2445 formation activity. Color gradation of blue and 
red background for each residue represents magnitude of importance for the methylation. (E) Crystal structure of Helix 74 and surrounding region in 
the E. coli 50S subunit. Coordinates were obtained from PBD (2aw4) (3). We added the methyl groups for m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445, shown in red, 
respectively. The recognized residues for m 7 G2069 and m 2 G2445 formation are shown in blue and red, respectively. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4081 </p>

<p>RlmKL and the DeaD RNA helicase are cooperatively 
involved in efficient assembly of the 50S subunit. 
Therefore, the ribosome profile of the DrlmKL/DdeaD 
strain was analyzed by sucrose density gradient centrifu-
gation. In the DdeaD strain (Figure 7B), a slight decrease 
in the 50S subunit compared with the wild-type strain, and 
an accumulation of a 40S fraction that contains an inter-
mediate of the 50S subunit, were detected. In the DrlmKL/ 
DdeaD strain (Figure 7B), an apparent decrease in the 50S 
subunit compared with the wild-type and DrlmKL strains 
and an accumulation of an intermediate 30-40S fraction 
were observed. These results indicated that deletion of 
rlmKL in the DdeaD background caused a considerable 
defect in 50S assembly. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We identified RlmKL as a unique methyltransferase 
responsible for the formation of both m 2 G2445 and 
m 7 G2069 in 23S rRNA. Genetic and biochemical studies 
revealed that RlmKL is composed of tandem methyl-
transferase domains, an N-terminal RlmL and 
C-terminal RlmK. Each domain is a distinct individual 
methyltransferase responsible for one of the methylations. 
RlmKL is a novel type of fused methyltransferase bearing 
dual active sites responsible for different methyl modifica-
tions at distinct positions. 
In general, the conjugation of enzymes involved in the 
same pathway has the advantage of facilitating efficient 
and rapid catalysis of sequential reactions. There are 
some examples in metabolic pathways for the biogenesis 
of amino acids and fatty acids (47). Another example of 
conjugated enzymes can be found in non-ribosomal 
peptide synthesis in bacteria (48). Among RNA-modifying 
enzymes, we reported previously that a series of enzymes 
responsible for wybutosine (yW) synthesis are fused in 
some cases (32,49). 
Another example of a fused methyltransferase for 
rRNAs is RsmC, the methyltransferase responsible 
for N 2 -methylation of G1207 in 16S rRNA (50). RsmC 
consists of two methyltransferase domains. The CTD has 
a bona fide methyltransferase that catalyzes m 2 G1207 
formation using Ado-Met. The NTD has homology 
to Ado-Met-dependent methyltransferases but has no 
methyltransferase activity due to mutations in the 
conserved residues for Ado-Met binding. However, the 
NTD is required for the stability of the CTD and plays 
a supportive role in substrate recognition by the 
CTD (50). In RlmKL, conjugation of RlmL and RlmK 
is advantageous for facilitating the m 2 G2445 formation. 
In addition, the m 2 G2445 formation catalyzed by the 
RlmL(NTD) can be enhanced by the supportive substrate 
recognition by the RlmK(CTD), similar to the function of 
the non-catalytic methyltransferase domain in RsmC. 
COG0116 and COG1092 are widely distributed in 
bacteria and archaea. Due to their sequence similarity, 
COG0116 and COG1092 can be aligned and placed in 
the same phylogenetic tree (Supplementary Figure S6). 
The non-rooted neighbor-joining (NJ) tree shown in 
Supplementary Figure S6 reveals that COG0116 and 
COG1092 are clearly separate from each other with 
100% bootstrap probability. In this analysis, we found 
that both COGs were composed of at least two distinct 
classes of enzymes. COG0116 contains RlmL, as well as 
Trm14 which is a N 2 -methyltransferase for archaeal 
tRNAs (51), while COG1092 contains RlmK, as well as 
RlmI, which is responsible for m 5 C1962 formation in 23S 
rRNA (52). The strong similarity between these RNA 
methyltransferases makes classification of the enzymes 
complicated. By examining the phylogenetic clusters con-
taining RlmL and RlmK, we can confirm that RlmKL is 
only present in g-proteobacteria, and that the separated 
RlmK and RlmL are found in the genus Neisseria, 
suggesting that the conjugation of these two enzymes 
should have occurred in the common ancestor of 
g-proteobacteria. </p>

<p>ΔdeaD </p>

<p>Wild-Type </p>

<p>ΔdeaD ΔrlmKL </p>

<p>ΔrhlE ΔrlmKL </p>

<p>ΔrhlE </p>

<p>ΔrlmKL </p>

<p>ΔsrmB 
ΔsrmB ΔrlmKL </p>

<p>ΔdbpA ΔrlmKL </p>

<p>ΔdbpA </p>

<p>37 C 
28 C </p>

<p>ΔdeaD / ΔrlmKL </p>

<p>Wild-type </p>

<p>Absorbance at 254 nm </p>

<p>top 
bottom </p>

<p>30S </p>

<p>50S </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>40S </p>

<p>ΔdeaD </p>

<p>Wild-type </p>

<p>ΔrlmKL 
Wild-type </p>

<p>Figure 7. Synthetic growth phenotype of DrlmKL and ribosomal 
subunit profiling. (A) Exploring the synthetic growth phenotype of 
DrlmKL in the presence of the disruption of RNA helicases, 
including deaD, rhlE, srmB and dbpA. Each strain was serially 
diluted (1:10 dilutions), spotted onto LB plates and incubated at 
37 C or 28 C for 11 and 22 h, respectively. The doubling time 
(in minutes) is shown to the right of each panel. (B) SDG profiling 
of ribosomal subunits in cell lysates in the presence of 0.5 mM Mg 2+ for 
the wild-type (blue line), DrlmKL (red line), DdeaD (red line) and 
DrlmKL/DdeaD (red line) strains. The amount of each subunit was 
quantified by UV absorbance at 254 nm. The peak positions for the 
30S and 50S subunits are indicated. The peak height was normalized to 
the 30S peak. </p>



<p>According to the phylogenetic analysis of COG1092 
(Supplementary Figure S6), RlmK is a paralog of RlmI. 
Structural analysis revealed that RlmI has three domains, 
a Rossman-fold domain, an EEHEE domain, and a PUA 
domain (53). RlmK also has two first domains, the 
Rossman-fold and EEHEE domains. The Rossman-fold 
is found in a typical methyltransferase domain containing 
the Ado-Met binding motif. The EEHEE domain is an 
RNA recognition module composed of b-sheets and 
an a-helix, and is found in rRNA methyltransferases 
including RlmI and RlmD (54). RlmD is the 
methyltransferase responsible for m 3 U1939 formation. 
According to the crystal structure of the ternary 
complex consisting of the partial RNA substrate, RlmD 
and Ado-Met (54), the EEHEE domain binds to the 
single-stranded RNA 5 0 of the target uridine, U1939. 
Therefore, the EEHEE domain is thought to be a 
single-stranded RNA binding module that recognizes the 
sequence immediately 5 0 of the target site. Together with 
our observation that RlmK recognizes residues C2064, 
C2065 C2066, G2067 and U2068, which are residues im-
mediately 5 0 of the target G2069, it is possible that the 
EEHEE domain of RlmK recognizes the 5 0 strand 
adjacent to G2069 in Helix 74. 
RlmL has a THUMP domain (55) in its N-terminal 
region. The THUMP domain is frequently found in 
various tRNA-modifying enzymes including ThiI (56), 
CDAT8 (57), Tan1p (58), Pus10 (59) and PAB1281 (60). 
The THUMP domain is an RNA-binding domain, and, 
according to a structural study of ThiI, the THUMP 
domain together with the ancillary N-terminal domain 
configures the surface for RNA binding (56). Deleting 
these two domains of ThiI resulted in the complete loss 
of tRNA binding (61). These results indicate that the 
THUMP domain of RlmL may be involved in recognizing 
G2428 and G2429 in the 12 nt ss region which are apart 
from the methylated residue G2445. 
Based on this study, we propose a catalytic mechanism 
for the cooperative modifications of Helix 74 (Figure 8). 
Our biochemical data has shown that RlmK recognizes 
Helix 80, the conserved bases in the P-loop, 12 nt ss 
region and Helix74, whereas RlmL recognizes critical 
residues in the 12 nt ss region and the 3 0 strand of Helix </p>

<p>74 (Figure 6D). As shown in the crystal structure of the 
50S subunit (Figure 6E), the residues required for 
m 2 G2445 formation are interrupted by the residues essen-
tial for m 7 G2069 formation. Thus, both domains of 
RlmKL cannot bind Helix 74 at the same time in 
the folded structure of the 23S rRNA. In addition, 
RlmL(NTD) preferentially recognizes and methylates the 
single-stranded substrate rather than the duplex substrate, 
suggesting that Helix 74 should be unwound to serve as 
the preferred substrate for RlmL(NTD) during dimethyl-
formation. In fact, we could directly observe an unwinding 
activity of RlmKL with the duplex substrate formed by 
transcripts 8 and 9 (Figure 5C), strongly supporting the 
proposed mechanism of cooperative methylation by 
RlmKL. As discussed above, RlmK has an EEHEE 
domain that may recognize the 5 0 residues neighboring 
G2069 in Helix 74. Since several residues in the 5 0 strand 
of Helix 74 are essential for m 7 G2069 formation, the 
EEHEE domain may recognize these bases and unwind 
Helix 74, releasing the 3 0 ss for RlmL(NTD) recognition. 
We observed that the DrlmKL/DdeaD strain exhibited a 
synthetic growth phenotype, especially at low tem-
peratures and had defects in 50S subunit assembly 
(Figure 7). This result indicated that RlmKL and the 
DeaD RNA helicase work redundantly in ribosome 
assembly. As the DeaD RNA helicase possess an 
ATP-dependent RNA chaperone activity that modulates 
the local structure of rRNA, RlmKL may act as an 
assembly factor. RlmKL does not recognize the assembled 
50S subunit but uses the naked 23S rRNA as a substrate. 
In addition, RlmKL co-sediments with the assembly inter-
mediate of the 50S subunit (43), suggesting that RlmKL 
directly interacts with the 23S rRNA at an early step in 
50S assembly. Since RlmKL unwinds Helix 74 during 
dimethyl formation, the local structural alterations in 
domain V, induced by RlmKL recognition, may be 
involved in the correct folding of the rRNA after tran-
scription, domain-domain interactions, and/or hierarchic-
al association of ribosomal proteins in the early steps of 
50S assembly. Further study will be required to elucidate 
the precise role of RlmKL as an assembly factor in 
ribosome biogenesis. </p>

<p>RlmK </p>

<p>RlmL </p>

<p>RlmKL </p>

<p>H74 </p>

<p>H80 </p>

<p>12nt ss </p>

<p>m 7 G2069 
m 2 G2445 
L1 stalk </p>

<p>Figure 8. Schematic depiction of a catalytic mechanism for the cooperative modifications of Helix 74. After transcription of domain V in the 23S 
rRNA, the C-terminal RlmK domain of RlmKL unwinds Helix 74 upon recognizing Helix 80 and Helix 74, and then methylates G2069. The 
single-stranded 3 0 side of Helix 74 is then recognized by the N-terminal RlmL domain, and G2445 is methylated. Finally, Helix 74 reforms a duplex, 
and domain V is restructured. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4083 </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online: 
Supplementary Table 1, Supplementary Figures 1-7, 
Supplementary Methods and Supplementary References 
[20,38,62-69]. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We are grateful to the Suzuki lab members for many 
fruitful discussions and technical advice. We also 
thank J. Kato (Tokyo Metropolitan University) and 
NBRP-E. coli at National Institute of Genetics (NIG) 
for providing materials. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Grants-in-aid for scientific research on priority areas from 
the Ministry of Education, Science, Sports and Culture of 
Japan (to T.S.); JSPS Fellowship for Japanese Junior 
Scientists (to S.K.); the New Energy and Industrial 
Technology Development Organization (NEDO) (grant 
to T.S.). Funding for the open access charge: Japan 
Ministry of Education, Science, Sports and Culture. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2012, Vol. 40, No. 9 4085 </p>

</text></tei>