<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3001089" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Ribonucleotide reductase (RNR) is the rate-limiting 
enzyme in deoxyribonucleoside triphosphate 
(dNTP) biosynthesis, with important roles in 
nuclear genome maintenance. RNR is also essential 
for maintenance of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) in 
mammals. The mechanisms regulating mtDNA 
copy number in mammals are only being dis-
covered. In budding yeast, RNR overexpression 
resulted in increased mtDNA levels, and rescued 
the disease phenotypes caused by a mutant 
mtDNA polymerase. This raised the question of 
whether mtDNA copy number increase by RNR in-
duction could be a strategy for treating diseases 
with mtDNA mutations. We show here that high-
level overexpression of RNR subunits (Rrm1, Rrm2 
and p53R2; separately or in different combinations) 
in mice does not result in mtDNA copy number ele-
vation. Instead, simultaneous expression of two 
RNR subunits leads to imbalanced dNTP pools and 
progressive mtDNA depletion in the skeletal muscle, 
without mtDNA mutagenesis. We also show that en-
dogenous RNR transcripts are downregulated in 
response to large increases of mtDNA in mice, 
which is indicative of nuclear-mitochondrial cross-
talk with regard to mtDNA copy number. Our results 
establish that RNR is not limiting for mtDNA copy 
number in mice, and provide new evidence for the 
importance of balanced dNTP pools in mtDNA main-
tenance in postmitotic tissues. </p>

<p>Ribonucleotide reductase (RNR) catalyzes the rate-
limiting step in de novo synthesis of deoxyribonucleoside 
triphosphates (dNTPs) [reviewed in (1)]. The enzyme is 
known to contribute to malignant transformation (2,3). 
During S-phase, RNR is abundant as a tetramer 
composed of homodimers of the large Rrm1 and small 
Rrm2 subunits. In non-cycling cells, Rrm2 is replaced by 
the alternative small subunit p53R2 (4). The latter is 
induced by the tumor suppressor p53 and was initially 
considered to contribute to nuclear DNA damage re-
sponses (5,6). 
Mutation of p53R2 has recently been found to be an 
important cause of human inherited diseases. Inactivating 
mutations of RRM2B, the gene encoding p53R2, were not 
associated with neoplasms, but caused early onset fatal de-
pletion of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) (MIM #612075) 
(7). Similarly, knock-out mice lacking p53R2 exhibited 
near-total loss of mtDNA and died shortly after weaning 
(7,8). We recently reported that a dominant RRM2B 
mutation led to truncated p53R2 and caused adult-onset 
progressive external ophthalmoplegia (PEO) with multiple 
mtDNA deletions (9). Certain compound heterozygote 
RRM2B mutations have also been shown to result in mito-
chondrial neurogastrointestinal encephalopathy (MNGIE; 
MIM #603041) (10). Defects in p53R2 can therefore cause 
diseases of differing severity, ranging from fatal 
multisystem disorders with mtDNA depletion in children, 
to an adult-onset muscle disorder with multiple mtDNA 
deletions. These results highlight the essential role of 
RNR in mtDNA maintenance in postmitotic cells. 
Increasing mtDNA copy number has emerged as an 
attractive target of intervention for mtDNA diseases. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +358 9 4717 1965; Fax: +358 9 4717 1964; Email: anu.wartiovaara@helsinki.fi 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Robert S. Weiss. Tel: +607 253 4443; Fax: +607 253 4212; Email: rsw26@cornell.edu </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </p>

<p>8208-8218 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 
Published online 19 August 2010 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq735 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Even a minimal amount of wild-type mtDNA can compen-
sate a functionally recessive mutant (11). In the budding 
yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae, RNR overexpression led 
to elevation of mtDNA copy number (12) and to the 
rescue of the 'petite' phenotype of mtDNA polymerase 
mutants that carried mutations equivalent to those in auto-
somal dominant PEO (13). This suggested that RNR levels, 
by affecting dNTP pools, might be rate limiting for 
mtDNA synthesis, and that increasing the availability of 
the enzyme might be a tool for increasing mtDNA abun-
dance. Whether RNR induction could increase mtDNA in 
mammals, as it does in yeast, has so far not been 
investigated. 
In mice, considerable increase of mtDNA copy number 
has only been achieved in two mouse models, 
overexpressing the mitochondrial transcription factor A 
(TFAM) or the mtDNA helicase Twinkle (14,15). 
TFAM is required for mtDNA transcription, but it also 
binds DNA with low specificity and packages mtDNA in a 
histone-like manner (16-18). Its levels closely follow 
mtDNA levels. Twinkle helicase is known to increase 
mtDNA copy number by affecting the replication initi-
ation rate (19). In this study, we set out to determine 
whether overexpression of RNR subunits, alone or in 
combination with each other, influence mtDNA copy 
number in mammalian tissues. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Generation of transgenic mice </p>

<p>The Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>, Rrm2 
Tg and p53R2 
Tg mice have been previ-
ously described (3). Briefly, the mice were maintained 
on a pure FVB/N strain background and expressed their 
transgene under the control of chicken b-actin promoter 
and cytomegalovirus enhancer regulatory sequences. 
The transgenic mice seemed grossly normal and were 
fertile. The presence of the transgene was verified by 
PCR analysis as described earlier (3). Rrm1 
Tg mice 
showed restricted overexpression of Rrm1 protein primar-
ily in the skeletal muscle by immunoblotting whereas 
Rrm2 
Tg and p53R2 
Tg mice had widespread, high-level 
overexpression of the transgene in all tested tissues. For 
this study, we created mice overexpressing Rrm1 together 
with either Rrm2 or p53R2 by cross-breeding mice that 
were hemizygous for each transgene. Because the PCR 
assay used to detect Rrm1 
Tg and p53R2 
Tg is not 
transgene-specific (3), the presence of Rrm1 
Tg or 
p53R2 
Tg in offspring from these crosses was determined 
by Southern blotting. Briefly, tail DNA obtained from 
offspring was digested overnight with BamHI (Rrm1 
Tg ) 
or EcoRV (p53R2 
Tg ). After DNA was immobilized on a 
nylon membrane (GeneScreen Plus, Perkin Elmer), trans-
gene bands were detected by hybridization with 
radio-labeled probes derived from previously described 
pCaggs RNR expression constructs (3). Pathological 
examination of lung neoplasms was performed as 
before (3). 
The Twinkle 
Tg (15) and TFAM 
Tg mice (20) used here 
were also described earlier. Both were in C57BL/6 back-
ground, and expressed the transgene under a ubiquitous </p>

<p>b-actin promoter. The Twinkle-mice were backcrossed to 
C57BL/6 from FVB/N for more than 12 generations, and 
the congeneity was confirmed with the Mouse Medium 
Density SNP Panel (Illumina). </p>

<p>Quantification of RNR transgene overexpression </p>

<p>Western blotting for RNR subunits was performed as 
described earlier (3). Chemiluminescent signal was 
detected on a VersaDoc Imaging system and quantified 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Quantity One</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Bio-Rad Laboratories</rs>). 
Band intensity was determined for each dilution series 
sample and plotted following subtraction of background 
signal. The measured intensity for each undiluted 
wild-type band was fitted to the generated line for the 
corresponding 
RNR </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>dilution 
series. 
Fold 
overexpression values were corrected for loading by stand-
ardization based on a-tubulin signal. </p>

<p>Southern blotting for mtDNA copy number determination </p>

<p>Total DNA was isolated from tissues by proteinase K di-
gestion and standard phenol-chloroform extraction. 
Southern blotting was performed essentially as previously 
described (21). Briefly, 3 mg total DNA was digested with 
SacI overnight at 37 
C, samples were then separated by 
electrophoresis in an agarose gel and blotted by alkaline 
transfer onto a Hybond N+ membrane (Amersham 
Biosciences). The membrane was hybridized overnight at 
68 
C in a roller hybridizer using 5 mCi/ml 
32 P-dCTP 
labeled (PCR-generated) mouse mtDNA probe, and 18S 
rDNA probe in pBR322 plasmid. Phosphoimager analysis 
was done with Typhoon 9400 (Amersham Biosciences) 
and mtDNA was quantified against the 18S rDNA 
signal using <rs id="software-1" type="software">ImageQuant</rs> v<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Amersham Biosciences</rs>). </p>

<p>Real-time PCR </p>

<p>For mtDNA quantification, the quantitative real-time 
(q)PCR reactions were done with 25 ng total DNA used 
as template and normalizing the mt-Cytb gene amplifica-
tion level (primer sequences: 5 
0 -GCTTTCCACTTCATCT 
TACCATTTA-3 
0 and 5 
0 -TGTTGGGTTGTTTGATCC 
TG-3 
0 ) against the nuclear b-actin gene (primer sequences: 
5 
0 -GGAAAAGAGCCTCAGGGCAT-3 
0 and 5 
0 -GAAGA 
GCTATGAGCTGCCTGA-3 
0 ). Samples were run on an 
Abi Prism SDS 7000 machine (Applied Biosystem). 
Amplification conditions were: 95 
C for 7 min followed 
by 35 cycles of 95 
C for 10 s and 60 
C for 30 s. 
Dissociation curves were checked to ensure the existence 
of a single PCR product. Each sample was run in dupli-
cate, and samples with significant variation between du-
plicates were excluded. qPCR data were analyzed using 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">7000 System Sequence Detection</rs> Software version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">1.2.3</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Applied Biosystems</rs>). 
For gene expression analysis, 1000 ng total RNA was 
DNase digested using the Amplification Grade DNase I 
kit (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. Reverse transcription was done using M-MLV 
reverse transcriptase (Promega). Taqman gene expression 
assay for Rrm2b (assay ID Mm01165706_m1) and the 
Gapdh endogenous control were purchased from Applied </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8209 </p>

<p>Biosystems. The PCR reactions for Rrm2b and Gapdh 
were done using TaqMan Universal PCR Master Mix 
(Applied Biosystems), and run on an Abi Prism SDS 
7000 machine (Applied Biosystem) according to the manu-
facturer's protocol. The PCR for Rrm1 was done using 
the DyNAmo 
TM Flash SYBR 
Õ Green QPCR Kit 
(Finnzymes) as above (primer sequences 5 
0 -TGGACTCA 
ACATGGACTTTG-3 
0 and 5 
0 -GGCCTTGGATTACTTT 
CATG-3 
0 ). QPCR data were analyzed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">7000 System Sequence Detection</rs> Software version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">1.2.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Applied Biosystems</rs>). The amplification level of Rrm2b or Rrm1 
was normalized by dividing by the Gapdh amplification 
level. </p>

<p>MtDNA point mutation analysis </p>

<p>For mtDNA point mutation analysis we used primers 
that specifically amplified the mt-Cytb gene (nucleotide 
pair 14 073-14 906) and non-coding control region 
(15 357-138) of mouse mtDNA. In the PCR, we utilized 
the high-fidelity Phusion polymerase (Finnzymes) accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions, with 25 ng total 
DNA from quadriceps femoris muscle as template. The 
PCR program was 98 
C for 30 s followed by 30 cycles of 
98 
C for 10 s, 61 
C for 10 s and 72 
C for 30 s. PCR 
products were cloned into pCR 
Õ 2.1 plasmid using the 
TA cloning kit (Invitrogen) according to the manufactur-
er's instructions. Multiple PCR clones were sequenced to 
generate $30 000 bp of sequence for each region. </p>

<p>Long PCR </p>

<p>Long PCR to amplify the entire mitochondrial genome 
or selectively deleted mtDNA molecules was done using 
the Expand Long Template PCR System (Roche). Fifty-
nanogram total DNA was used as template. Cycling 
conditions were: 92 
C for 2 min followed by 30 cycles of 
92 
C for 10 s and 68 
C for 12 min. PCR products were 
separated by electrophoresis on 1% agarose gels and 
visualized with a Typhoon 9400 scanner (Amersham 
Biosciences). Primers hybridized to the control region of 
mtDNA located at nucleotide positions 1953-1924 and 
2473-2505. </p>

<p>Measurement of nucleotide pools in skeletal muscle </p>

<p>Nucleotides were extracted from skeletal muscle of aged 
mice using previously described methods with modifica-
tions (22,23). Briefly, skeletal muscle was excised following 
euthanasia by CO 2 asphyxiation and snap-frozen in liquid 
nitrogen. When sufficient tissue was available, samples 
were divided into two equal portions, processed separ-
ately, and compared to assess measurement consistency. 
Tissues were weighed and immersed in $5 ml/mg 10% tri-
chloroacetic acid, 10 mM MgCl 2 . Tissues were 
homogenized in a Qiagen Tissue Lyser by six cycles of 
30 s at 30 Hz followed by 30 s on ice. Tissue homogenates 
were incubated on ice for 20 min, then spun at 13 000 g 
for 1 min. The supernatant was taken to a fresh tube 
and re-spun. An approximately equal volume of 0.5N 
trioctylamine in fluorotrichloromethane was added to 
the supernatant. The samples were vortexed briefly and 
spun for 2 min at 16 000 g. The volume of the upper </p>

<p>phase was estimated by pipetting and aliquots were 
snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at À80 
C until 
nucleotide measurements were performed. dNTPs were 
measured using an indirect enzymatic assay as reported 
by Ferraro et al. (24). Standard curves were prepared 
from concentrated stocks of pure individual dNTPs 
(Fermentas). Reactions in 50 ml total volume were 
incubated for 1 h and then 30 ml was spotted to 
Whatman DE81 paper discs and dried. Discs were 
washed three times in 5% Na 2 HPO 4 , and once each 
in dH 2 O and 95% EtOH. Discs were dried and counted 
on a Beckman Coulter LS6500 scintillation counter. 
Measurement of ribonucleosides was performed as in 
Kochanowski et al. (25) with modifications. Analyses 
were carried out on a Shimadzu UHPLC system. 
Samples were separated on a Supelco LC-18T column in 
30 mM KH 2 PO 4 and 10 mM tetrabutylammonium 
hydrogen sulfate, pH 6.5: methanol (A = 91.7:8.3, 
B = 71.6:28.4) over a 40-min time period. The program 
ran 0-100%B from 0-24 min, 1 min at 100% B and 
100-0% B from 25-30 min at a flow rate of 1 ml/min. 
Identities of analytes were confirmed both by comparison 
of elution time to known standards and by wavelength of 
maximum absorbance (l max ). Sample extracts in which 
ATP comprised &lt;65% of the total adenine nucleotides 
were excluded from further analysis. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Generation of RNR transgenic mice </p>

<p>Transgenic mice that express recombinant Rrm1, Rrm2 or 
p53R2 (referred to as 'Rrm1 
Tg ', 'Rrm2 
Tg ' and 'p53R2 
Tg ' 
mice hereafter) were generated previously and showed 
broad, high-level RNR overexpression (3). Since active 
RNR requires the presence of the large and the small 
subunit, simultaneous overexpression of both subunits 
could cause a greater increase in RNR activity. We there-
fore interbred Rrm1 
Tg mice with Rrm2 
Tg or p53R2 
Tg mice 
to generate bitransgenic mice. The Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 
Tg and 
Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 
Tg mice were born at expected frequencies 
and showed no gross abnormalities (Supplementary 
Table S1). The endogenous RNR subunits were barely 
or not at all detectable by western blotting of 25 mg 
protein for each muscle tissue extract, whereas significant 
overexpression was observed in RNR 
Tg samples. We 
therefore made serial dilutions from each RNR </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>sample, and plotted the band intensities against the 
dilution level. Fitting the corresponding wild-type 
samples onto this plot allowed us to estimate the fold 
overexpression for each transgene-encoded protein 
(Figure 1). The calculated threshold dilutions for 
bitransgenic mice are shown in Table 1. The level of trans-
gene overexpression was comparable between single 
RNR transgenic and bitransgenic mice (Supplementary 
Figure S1). 
Rrm2 
Tg and p53R2 
Tg mice were previously found to 
have increased lung tumor prevalence at $17 months of 
age (3), Rrm2 being a more potent tumor inducer than 
p53R2. In bitransgenic mice, the lung tumor formation 
occurred with similar frequency as in mice overexpressing </p>



<p>either of the small RNR subunits alone (Supplementary 
Table S2). The bitransgenic mice were followed up to 
$17-month age and, excluding lung tumor formation, 
they appeared grossly normal during this time. </p>

<p>RNR overexpression does not elevate mtDNA copy 
number in mouse tissues </p>

<p>We used Southern blotting to investigate the effect of 
RNR expression on mtDNA copy number in the 
skeletal muscle (Figure 2A), heart (Figure 2B), liver and 
kidney (Supplementary Figure S2) of the various RNR </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>mice. No significant increases in mtDNA copy number 
were observed in any of the tissues from 9-12-weeks-old 
mice. In the skeletal muscle of the bitransgenic mice, there 
was actually a modest reduction in mtDNA abundance: 
Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 
Tg mice had on average 71% (P = 0.026) 
and Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 
Tg mice 62% (P = 0.0075) residual 
mtDNA amounts compared to their wild-type littermates 
(Figure 2A). The mtDNA depletion in skeletal muscle 
was progressive; at 11-15 months of age, the residual 
mtDNA copy number was 42% in Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>mice (P = 0.030) and 34% in Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 
Tg mice 
(P = 0.0011) (Figure 2A). The mtDNA levels in the </p>

<p>other examined tissues remained unchanged also at the 
older age. Therefore, overexpression of RNR did not 
elevate mtDNA copy number in differentiated mouse 
tissues and was associated with progressive mtDNA de-
pletion in bitransgenic animals. </p>

<p>RNR overexpression does not affect mtDNA integrity 
or mutagenesis </p>

<p>Overexpression of RNR causes nuclear genome mutagen-
esis and promotes cancer (3). We therefore asked whether 
RNR overexpression leads to mtDNA instability as well. 
We examined the presence of mtDNA point mutations in 
the skeletal muscle of a 16-month-old Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>mouse by amplifying and cloning mtDNA regions from 
the control region (1080 bp) and mt-Cytb gene (833 bp), 
which encodes cytochrome b, followed by sequencing of 
$30 kb of DNA from each region. We previously reported 
the point mutation rate in wild-type FVB/N mice to be 
$0.5 mutations per 10 kb in the control region and 
$0.25 mutations per 10 kb in the mt-Cytb gene (15). The 
16-month-old Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 
Tg showed similar or lower 
point mutation loads compared to a wild-type control 
(Table 2). In a long-range PCR assay, full-length </p>

<p>Figure 1. RNR overexpression in skeletal muscle and cardiac muscle from Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 
Tg and Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 
Tg bitransgenic mice. Western-blot 
analysis of RNR protein expression was performed on total protein extracts prepared from skeletal muscle (A and C) or cardiac muscle (B and D) 
from wild-type (WT) as well as Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 
Tg or Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 
Tg bitransgenic mice. Extracts were left undiluted (1Â) or diluted as indicated 
and then subjected to immunoblotting with antibodies specific to Rrm1, Rrm2 or p53R2. The asterisk indicates a non-specific band in the anti-Rrm2 
immunoblot. a-Tubulin signal in undiluted skeletal (C) and cardiac (D) muscle samples was used to normalize for protein loading. The analysis was 
performed on three mice of each genotype, and representative bands are shown for clarity of comparison. The calculated fold overexpression values 
are shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8211 </p>

<p>mtDNA was readily amplified in the skeletal muscle of 
aged bitransgenic mice, with no additional small amplify-
ing products. This ruled out the presence of large mtDNA 
deletions (Figure 3). These analyses showed that 
bitransgenic RNR overexpression did not increase </p>

<p>deletion formation or point mutagenesis of mtDNA, but 
only caused mtDNA depletion. </p>

<p>RNR overexpression leads to dNTP pool imbalance in 
skeletal muscle </p>

<p>In many human diseases and mouse models, mtDNA de-
pletion and instability have been suggested to occur as the 
result of perturbed dNTP pools (26-28). To understand 
the mechanism of mtDNA depletion in RNR 
overexpressors, we measured the relative levels of dNTP 
pools in muscle extracts. Nucleotides are known to easily 
undergo quick dephosphorylation during the extraction 
procedure (29-31). Under conditions when dNTPs are 
dephosphorylated during sample preparation, ATP is 
similarly degraded to ADP and AMP. Therefore, the 
level of ATP in the extract closely mirrors that of the 
dNTPs, and can be used as an internal marker of 
unwanted dNTP destruction (30). We measured dNTP 
levels in skeletal muscle extracts from 12-month-old mice 
by a primer extension assay, using 2-3 mice of each </p>

<p>Figure 2. mtDNA quantification in young (9-12 weeks) and aged (11-15 months) mice. Southern blots of digested total DNA from skeletal (A) and 
cardiac and (B) muscle were probed for full-length mtDNA and the nuclear 18S rDNA gene to control for loading. (A) mtDNA to nuclear DNA 
ratios were determined by densitometric quantification of Southern blots and by QPCR, both methods yielding similar results. mtDNA depletion was 
found in young and aged bitransgenic mice. (B) No change in mtDNA copy number was observed in the cardiac muscle of RNR 
Tg mice. Error bars 
indicate SEM. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, Student's t-test compared to wild-type where N ! 3 individual animals. </p>

<p>Table 1. Transgene-encoded protein levels </p>

<p>Genotype 
Protein 
Skeletal muscle 
Cardiac muscle </p>

<p>Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>Rrm1 
3.3 (±2.1) 
33.7 (±7.6) 
Rrm2 
37.0 (±7.2) 
&gt;23.7 (±3.8) 
Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>Rrm1 
11.7 (±6.7) 
34.7 (±24.5) 
p53R2 
355.3 (±25) 
975.3 (±726.3) </p>

<p>The relative levels of transgene encoded proteins were determined by 
western blotting serial dilutions of skeletal and cardiac muscle tissue 
lysates, as shown in Figure 1. The table shows the average (±standard 
deviation) calculated threshold dilutions from three mice of each 
genotype, for each of the proteins in Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 
Tg and 
Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+p53R2 
Tg bitransgenic mice. </p>



<p>genotype. The levels of ATP, ADP and AMP were 
measured from the same extracts by HPLC. 
The average ATP levels were similar across the geno-
types, the levels of ADP were &gt;10-fold lower than that of 
ATP, and AMP amounted to &lt;1% of the total adenine </p>

<p>nucleotide pools (Figure 4). These ATP/ADP ratios 
corresponded well with previously reported numbers 
from mouse liver (30), and suggested that general dNTP 
dephosphorylation did not have a major effect on 
the dNTP level determination. The only exceptions were 
the Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 
Tg mice, which did exhibit a somewhat 
lower average ATP/ADP ratio than the other genotypes 
(Figure 4), suggesting that dNTP measurements may 
have been underestimated in those mice. To ensure that 
the high level of RNR overexpression did not lead to 
substrate depletion, we also measured the levels of CDP, 
UDP and GDP, and found no significant differences 
in their levels between the genotypes (Supplementary 
Figure S3). 
The amounts of the individual dNTPs are shown in 
Figure 5. Data are presented according to the respective 
crosses, with the Rrm1 
Tg X p53R2 
Tg crosses in panels 
A-D and the Rrm1 
Tg X Rrm2 
Tg crosses in panels E-H. 
We observed increases in the levels of dATP and dCTP in 
all of the transgenic lines, as compared to wild-type 
control samples. The mice expressing either small 
subunit showed greater relative increases in dATP and </p>

<p>Figure 3. Analysis of mtDNA integrity in RNR 
Tg mice by mtDNA 
deletion assay. To look for mtDNA deletions, a long-PCR assay was 
used to amplify the entire mtDNA genome from the skeletal muscle of 
12-month old wild-type, Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 
Tg and Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>mice. The full-length mtDNA (16 kb) was readily amplified from all 
samples. A Deletor mouse sample was included as a positive control; 
this sample shows multiple mtDNA fragments of smaller size. The 
DNA ladder Hind was used as a size marker. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Measurement of AMP, ADP, and ATP levels in skeletal 
muscle extracts from RNR 
Tg mice. The pools of ATP, ADP and 
AMP were measured from skeletal muscle extracts by an HPLC 
assay and quantified relative to standard curves. Results are presented 
as the means of results from two (for wild-type) or three (for all other 
genotypes) mice. The average levels of the adenine nucleotides were 
plotted on linear (A) and logarithmic (B) scales, and found to be 
similar across genotypes, which suggested comparable extraction 
efficiencies. The only exception was with the Rrm1 
Tg +Rrm2 
Tg mice, 
which had lower average ATP levels and ATP/ADP ratios compared to 
the other genotypes. This may cause dNTP pool levels in these mice to 
be underestimated. Error bars indicate SEM. </p>

<p>Table 2. Effect of RNR overexpression upon mtDNA point 
mutagenesis </p>

<p>Mouse (genotype) 
mt-Cytb gene 
Control region </p>

<p>Sequenced 
(base pairs) </p>

<p>Mutation 
rate 
(per 10 kb) </p>

<p>Sequenced 
(base pairs) </p>

<p>Mutation 
rate 
(per 10 kb) </p>

<p>Wild-type 
30 844 
0.648 
27 332 
0.366 
Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>39 438 
0.000 
28 034 
0.356 </p>

<p>Fragments from the control region (1080 bp) and mt-Cytb gene (833 bp) 
of mtDNA, were amplified by PCR, cloned and multiple clones were 
sequenced. Data are from the skeletal muscle of a 16-month-old 
Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 
Tg mouse and a 14.5-month old wild-type mouse. The 
mtDNA point mutation load was not increased in the bitransgenic 
mouse. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8213 </p>

<p>dCTP than the Rrm1 
Tg mice. There was also a clear 
tendency towards higher dATP and dCTP values in the 
bitransgenic Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 
Tg and Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>mice as compared to the p53R2 
Tg (Figure 5A and D) 
and Rrm2 
Tg (Figure 5E and H) single transgenic mice, 
respectively. In contrast to the elevated levels of dATP 
and dCTP, the levels of dGTP were unchanged in all of 
the transgenic mice (Figure 5B and F), and the levels of 
dTTP were actually decreased significantly in the p53R2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>and Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 
Tg mice (Figure 5C), and, to a lesser 
degree, in the Rrm1 
Tg , Rrm2 
Tg and Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>mice (Figure 5G). Taken together, these data suggested 
that RNR overexpression led to significant changes in 
dNTP pools and considerable imbalances between the dif-
ferent dNTPs, with the most pronounced changes in 
bitransgenic RNR 
Tg mice. </p>

<p>Increased mtDNA copy number is associated with 
decreased RNR expression </p>

<p>RNR is involved in a signalling pathway that regulates 
mtDNA copy number in yeast (12), and regulation of 
RNR expression could be part of a homeostatic mechan-
ism to control mtDNA copy number in mammals. We </p>

<p>therefore utilized mouse models that express recombinant 
wild-type mouse Twinkle (15) or human TFAM (20), with 
$2-and $3-fold respective increases of mtDNA copy 
numbers in their skeletal muscle at the age of ten weeks. 
We measured the expression levels of Rrm1 and Rrm2b, 
the genes encoding Rrm1 and p53R2, respectively, in 
skeletal muscle of Twinkle 
Tg and TFAM 
Tg mice. Rrm1 
mRNA was decreased to 76% (P = 0.011) and 70% 
(P = 0.010) in the Twinkle 
Tg and TFAM 
Tg mice, respect-
ively (Figure 6A). Rrm2b mRNA was similarly decreased 
to 78% (P = 0.045) and 77% (P = 0.0093) of normal 
in the Twinkle 
Tg and TFAM 
Tg mice, respectively 
(Figure 6B). Thus the expression of RNR genes was 
found to correlate inversely with mtDNA copy number 
in two mouse models. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>RNR is essential for both nuclear and mtDNA replica-
tion. The enzyme is limiting for mtDNA copy number in 
yeast, but whether the same is true in mammals has not 
been studied earlier. </p>

<p>Figure 5. RNR overexpression alters dNTP pools in skeletal muscle. The levels of the four dNTPs were measured by polymerase assay and 
expressed per unit weight of skeletal muscle. Pool sizes for the indicated dNTPs were compared between wild-type control mice and mice from 
Rrm1 
Tg Â p53R2 
Tg (A-D) or Rrm1 
Tg Â Rrm2 
Tg (E-H) breedings. Results are presented as the means of results from two (for wild-type) or three (for 
all other genotypes) mice. Results for the same wild-type and Rrm1 
Tg mice are presented in (A-D) and (E-H) for comparative purposes. The levels 
of dATP (A and E) were significantly increased in p53R2 
Tg and Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+p53R2 
Tg mice as well as in Rrm2 
Tg and Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 
Tg mice. The dGTP 
levels (B and F) were unchanged in all mice. dTTP (C and G) was decreased in p53R2 
Tg and Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+p53R2 
Tg mice and to a lesser degree also in 
Rrm1 
Tg , Rrm2 
Tg , and Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 
Tg mice. dCTP (D and H) showed a similar pattern as dATP, with increases in p53R2 
Tg and Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+p53R2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>mice as well as in Rrm2 
Tg and Rrm1 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>+Rrm2 
Tg mice. In each case, the Rrm1 
Tg mice showed similar but less pronounced dNTP changes as the mice 
overexpressing the small subunits. Error bars indicate SEM, *P &lt; 0.05, Student's t-test as compared to wild-type. </p>



<p>dNTP pool regulation has emerged as a potential tool 
to increase mtDNA levels, and thereby to slow down pro-
gression of mtDNA disease. In vitro supplementation with 
two deoxyribonucleoside monophosphates (dNMPs) 
rescued mtDNA depletion in cultured patient myotubes 
with mutations in the mitochondrial deoxyribonucleoside 
salvage pathway enzyme deoxyguanosine kinase (dGK) 
(32). However, mtDNA depletion due to patient muta-
tions in the mtDNA polymerase gamma (Pol g) was not 
restored through nucleotide supplementation in the same 
study. Likewise, nucleotide supplementation to healthy 
myotubes did not increase mtDNA levels significantly 
above normal (32). These results suggested that although 
dNTP pool expansion may be beneficial in cases of dNTP 
deficiency, other factors than the size of the mitochondrial 
dNTP pool are limiting for mtDNA copy number in 
normal cells or in mtDNA replication defects. </p>

<p>RNR overexpression in yeast resulted in elevated 
mtDNA levels (12), and complementation of the respira-
tory chain deficient phenotype of Pol g disease mutations 
(13). The results presented here suggest that RNR 
overexpression has partially opposite effects in mammals, 
which illustrates the marked differences in dNTP pool 
maintenance between organisms. However, we cannot 
exclude the possibility that increased RNR activity or 
dNTP availability in vivo could be beneficial in cases with 
increased mtDNA turnover or mutagenesis. The increased 
carcinogenesis in RNR 
Tg mice (3) illustrates the hazards of 
altering dNTP pool maintenance and further reduces the 
potential of RNR as a therapeutic tool. 
The mechanisms governing mtDNA copy number in 
tissues are starting to come into focus. In mice, 
overexpression of the histone-like packaging protein 
TFAM or of the mtDNA helicase Twinkle increase 
mtDNA copy number 2-to 3-fold (14,15). The mRNA 
level of Twinkle and the protein level of TFAM correlate 
linearly with mtDNA content, suggesting that these may 
be limiting factors in determining the amount of mtDNA. 
Defects in mitochondrial dNTP pool maintenance 
proteins cause loss of mtDNA, indicating that these 
factors are essential for mtDNA maintenance (7,33-36). 
However, their contribution to the physiological control 
of mtDNA copy number is not well characterized. 
Heart-specific overexpression of the salvage pathway 
enzyme thymidine kinase 2 (TK2) in mice resulted in a 
300-fold increase in enzyme activity and produced a 
$30% increase in mtDNA copy number (37). Therefore, 
a very large increase in TK2 activity modestly influences 
mtDNA levels, potentially through increases in 
deoxycytidine and thymidine nucleotide pools. Our 
results show that although RNR is involved in the synthe-
sis of all four dNTPs, very high levels of the enzyme do 
not increase mtDNA copy number and instead perturb 
mtDNA homeostasis. This finding is in line with 
Twinkle and TFAM being the main regulators of 
mtDNA level under normal circumstances. 
A possible mechanism for nuclear control over mtDNA 
copy number would be to alter the transcription of 
mtDNA maintenance genes. In yeast, the first established 
signaling pathway that regulated mtDNA copy number is 
activated by the Mec1p/Rad53p kinases and leads to in-
duction of RNR expression (12). The related ATM 
(ataxia-telangiectasia mutated) kinase in humans was 
also found to influence RNR expression and mtDNA 
homeostasis (38). We found the transcription of Rrm1 
and Rrm2b to be downregulated in two independent 
mouse models with increased mtDNA copy number, sug-
gesting an intimate feedback mechanism between tran-
scriptional regulation of RNR subunits and mtDNA 
levels. RNR could thus contribute to a regulatory mech-
anism for nuclear control of mtDNA copy number in vivo. 
Such a signaling pathway could involve p53, a tumor sup-
pressor and ATM target, which influences the expression 
level of p53R2 and is known to localize in small amounts 
to mitochondria (39). 
RNR is rate-limiting for de novo dNTP synthesis, so any 
alteration to RNR activity is expected to induce changes 
in dNTP pools. These changes are transmitted into </p>

<p>Figure 6. RNR expression levels in mice with high mtDNA copy 
number. A QPCR assay was used to measure the expression levels of 
Rrm1 and Rrm2b, the genes encoding Rrm1 and p53R2, respectively, in 
the skeletal muscle of mice overexpressing Twinkle or TFAM. These 
mice have increased mtDNA copy number. (A) Rrm1 expression was 
downregulated in the Twinkle-mice and TFAM-mice compared to 
controls. (B) Rrm2b was similarly downregulated. Error bars indicate 
SEM, *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, Student's t-test compared to wild-type 
where N ! 3 individual animals. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8215 </p>

<p>mitochondria, since the mitochondrial and cytosolic 
dNTP pools are in rapid communication (40). Direct 
measurement of dNTP pools from animal tissues is 
complicated by dNTP dephosphorylation caused by the 
anaerobiosis that immediately follows the death of the 
animal (30). Our extraction method was optimized to 
minimize nucleotide degradation during extraction, and 
the ATP, ADP and AMP levels were used as internal 
controls to ensure comparability across samples. We 
documented clear and reproducible differences in total 
dNTP pools between RNR overexpressors and wild-type 
mice. 
First, there were significant increases in the levels of 
dATP and dCTP both in the Rrm2 
Tg and p53R2 
Tg mice. 
Rrm2 induced higher dNTP increases than p53R2, which 
is consistent with Rrm2 being more active than p53R2 
in vitro (41). Rrm1 overexpression alone was able to 
induce a detectable, albeit not statistically significant, 
increase in dATP and dCTP levels, and overexpression 
of Rrm1 together with either small subunit led to a clear 
trend towards higher levels of dATP and dCTP. This 
apparent synergy suggested that co-overexpression of 
both subunits led to an increase in the abundance of the 
tetramer, with subsequent effects on nucleotide pools. 
The allosteric regulation of RNR promotes a balanced 
production of all four dNTPs and therefore manipulation 
of RNR expression might be expected to influence the 
levels of all four dNTPs equally (1). However, we found 
remarkable dNTP pool imbalances in the RNR 
Tg mice. 
The dGTP pools were unchanged whereas dTTP pools 
were actually decreased in p53R2 </p>

<p>Tg </p>

<p>as well as 
Rrm1 
Tg +p53R2 
Tg mice. This finding illustrates the need 
for tight control of the relative activities of the large 
number of anabolic and catabolic enzymes that determine 
the final dNTP composition in vivo (42). For instance, the 
synthesis of thymidine phosphates requires-as an add-
itional step-reductive methylation of RNR-generated 
deoxyuridine monophosphate, which is catalyzed by 
thymidylate synthase. Hence, induction of RNR could 
cause a substrate overload for the endogenous 
thymidylate synthase, which in turn could explain why 
increased RNR does not increase the dTTP level. 
Furthermore, the specificity of RNR for GDP reduction 
is induced by the binding of dTTP to the specificity site of 
Rrm1 (1). Thus, a relative lack of dTTP could explain why 
the dGTP pools did not increase in our mice. The dNTP 
imbalance was not due to depletion of any of the sub-
strates of RNR, since the levels of ADP, CDP, UDP 
and GDP were similar in all genotypes. 
Unbalanced dNTP pools are known to cause mutagen-
esis in both nuclear (43) and mitochondrial (28) genomes. 
Given the presence of altered dNTP pools in RNR 
Tg mice, 
the likely mechanism of progressive mtDNA depletion in 
bitransgenic mice is inefficient mtDNA replication caused 
by perturbed dNTP balance. Initiation of nuclear DNA 
replication is influenced by the dNTP pool (44,45), and an 
imbalanced pool could lead to reduced frequency of 
mtDNA replication initiation. mtDNA depletion was spe-
cifically restricted to bitransgenic mice, which was consist-
ent with them displaying the largest dNTP alterations. 
The fact that Rrm2 
Tg and p53R2 
Tg mice also had </p>

<p>altered dNTP pools but no mtDNA depletion, suggests 
a threshold effect for the relative dNTP levels above 
which 
mtDNA 
replication 
becomes 
inefficient. 
Nevertheless, we cannot exclude that co-overexpression 
of Rrm1 and the small subunit gave rise to additional, 
unidentified effects, which did not occur upon 
overexpression of one subunit. Moreover, mtDNA deple-
tion was observed only in the skeletal muscle, although the 
transgenes were overexpressed in both the skeletal and 
cardiac muscles, suggesting tissue specific mechanisms in 
the regulation of nucleotide pools and/or mtDNA 
maintenance. 
Altered dNTP pool balance is a hallmark of MNGIE 
disease, where deficiency of the catabolic enzyme thymi-
dine phosphorylase (TP) leads to elevated dTTP pools, 
which cause mtDNA depletion, deletions and point muta-
tions in humans (28). Contrary to MNGIE, however, we 
found no increase in mtDNA point mutations or deletions 
in the RNR 
Tg mice. There are at least two possible explan-
ations for the absence of mtDNA instability, other than 
depletion, in our mice. First, the dNTP changes were 
almost opposite to those in MNGIE, i.e. the relative 
dTTP level decreased instead of increasing. Further 
studies are needed to elucidate the exact effect of 
changes in the relative levels of each of the four dNTPs 
on mtDNA replication frequency and fidelity. Second, the 
life-span of a mouse may be too short to develop signifi-
cant amounts of mtDNA deletions or point mutations in 
the setting of dNTP imbalance. In support of this, the 
MNGIE mouse model lacking TP and the related 
uridine phosphorylase (UP) displayed increased dTTP in 
brain, and, similar to RNR 
Tg mice, developed progressive 
mtDNA depletion, but no deletions or point mutations 
(27). The authors argued that this was at least partly 
due to the short life-span of mice, emphasizing the differ-
ences in dNTP maintenance and disorders between 
species. 
In conclusion, we have established that expression of 
recombinant RNR in mice leads to dNTP pool imbalance 
and progressive depletion of mtDNA. This is in contrast 
to previous findings in yeast, in which RNR is a positive 
regulator of mtDNA abundance. Furthermore, endogen-
ous RNR expression is responsive to increased mtDNA 
copy number and a potential modifier of mtDNA homeo-
stasis. The dNTP pool imbalance and mtDNA decrease 
caused by excess RNR suggests that balanced amounts of 
RNR are essential for mtDNA maintenance in vivo, and 
that RNR is unlikely to be an optimal target for thera-
peutic engineering of mtDNA levels in mammals. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Prof. Gerald S. Shadel for reagents, 
Dr Patrick Stover for use of UHPLC system and 
Prof. Vera Bianchi for expert advice. </p>



<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>This work was supported by Academy of Finland (to H.T. 
and A.S.); University of Helsinki (to A.S.); Sigrid Juselius 
Foundation (to A.S.); Jane and Aatos Erkko Foundation 
(to A.S.); Helsinki Biomedical Graduate School (to E.Y.); 
the Cornell University Center for Vertebrate Genomics (to 
J.L.P. and X.X.); National Institutes of Health training 
grant number T32 GM07617 (to J.L.P.). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 22 8217 </p>





</text></tei>