<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3994306" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>This study was to determine the correlation between endothelial function and neuro-endocrine-
immune (NEI) network through observing the changes of NEI network under the different endothelial 
dysfunction models. Three endothelial dysfunction models were established in male W istar rats after 
exposure to homocysteine (Hcy), high fat diet (HFD) and Hcy+HFD. The results showed that there 
was endothelial dysfunction in all three models with varying degrees. However, the expression of NEI 
network was totally different. Interestingly, treatment with simvastatin was able to improve vascular 
endothelial function and restored the imbalance of the NEI network, observed in the Hcy+HFD group. 
The results indicated that NEI network may have a strong association with endothelial function, and 
this relationship can be used to distinguish different risk factors and evaluate drug effects. </p>

<p>The neuro-endocrine-immune (NEI) network, first pro-
posed by Besedovsky in 1977 [1], plays a pivotal role in 
regulating homeostasis and optimizing health and makes 
great contributions to various complex diseases. Endothe-
lial dysfunction of either the coronary-, the peripheral-or 
the cerebral vasculature is a predictor of vascular events 
and appears to be a marker of atherosclerotic risk. As the 
largest endocrine organ of the body, the endodermis can 
receive signals of neurotransmitters, hormones and cyto-
kines [2], and can this way be controlled by the NEI 
network. This fact suggested that NEI network may be a 
potentially ideal index for the evaluation of endothelial 
dysfunction. 
A variety of cardiovascular risk factors have been shown 
to induce vascular endothelial dysfunction, including smok-
ing [3], hyperlipidemia [4], hypertension [5], hypoxia [6] 
and high levels of homocysteine (Hcy). Hyperlipidemia and </p>

<p>hyperhomocysteinemia are closely associated with diet, and 
are currently occurring more often with the popularity of 
fast food. This problem has been attained global scale. 
Therefore, in this study high fat diet (HFD) and high me-
thionine diet were used to induce endothelial dysfunction 
model in rats. 
Statins are powerful lipid-lowering drugs, widely used in 
patients with hyperlipidemia and coronary artery disease. 
It was found that statins appear to have a pleiotropic effect 
beyond their lipid-lowering ability. They can also exert an-
ti-inflammatory, anti-thrombotic and anti-oxidant effects, 
increase NO production and improve endothelial function 
[7]. Here, an interesting question is proposed that whether 
statins can also improve the expression of NEI network. 
The objective of the present study was to determine the 
correlation between endothelial function and NEI network 
under different endothelial dysfunction models caused by 
HFD, Hcy and Hcy+HFD. The effect of simvastatin (Sim) 
on NEI network profile was also evaluated in the models 
of endothelial dysfunction. </p>



<p>L Li, et al </p>

<p>
TC (mmol/L) 
TG (mmol/L) 
LDL-C (mmol/L) 
Hcy (μmol/L) </p>

<p>Control 
1.78±0.19 
0.94±0.17 
0.55±0.09 
7.23±1.49 
Hcy 
2.03±0.24 
1.18±0.21 
0.73±0.17 
23.71±4.38** 
HFD 
4.23±0.68** 
1.56±0.33** 
2.08±0.34** 
9.21±1.37 
Hcy+HFD 
4.31±0.52** 
1.83±0.51** 
2.24±0.48** 
27.27±3.89** 
Hcy+HFD+Sim 
1.97±0.16 </p>

<p>△△ </p>

<p>1.34±0.22 </p>

<p>△△ </p>

<p>1.36±0.31 </p>

<p>△△ </p>

<p>13.68±2.53 </p>

<p>△△ </p>

<p>*p＜0.05, **p＜0.01 vs control group; 
△ p＜0.05, 
△△ p＜0.01 vs Hcy+HFD group. </p>

<p>Table 1. The levels of lipids and Hcy in the different treatment groups (mean±SD, n=10 per group) </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Animals and experimental groups </p>

<p>The experiment was approved by the Institutional Ani-
mal Care and Use Committee of Shanghai University of 
Chinese Medicine. Fifty male Wistar rats (Shanghai Lab. 
Animal Research Center, China) weighing 200∼250 g were 
randomly divided into five groups fed on either ordinary 
diet (control group), high fat diet (HFD group; every 100 
g ordinary diet was supplemented with 15 g of palm oil, 
5 g of dried whole milk, 3 g of cholesterol and 0.5 g of so-
dium cholate), high Hcy diet (Hcy group; ordinary diet con-
taining 3% methionine), high Hcy and high fat diet (Hcy+ 
HFD group), or high Hcy and high fat diet combined with 
simvastatin (Hcy+HFD+Sim group; simvastatin was ad-
ministered via gavage with a dose of 5 mg/kg per day, sim-
vastatin was provided by Hangzhou MSD Pharmaceutical 
Co. Ltd). The animals were housed in an environmentally 
controlled room (temperature 20∼25 
o C; humidity 45%∼ 
65%) for 12 weeks. Throughout the study, the animals were 
allowed free access to food and tap water. </p>

<p>Sample preparation and measurement </p>

<p>To evaluate endothelial function, some indices such as 
endothelin (ET), nitric monoxide (NO), von Willebrand fac-
tor (vWF) [8] and soluble intercellular adhesion molecule-1 
(sICAM-1) [9,10] were determined. In addition, nineteen in-
dices were measured to reflect the profile of NEI network, 
they are: 
Neurotransmitters: 5-Hydroxytryptamine (5-HT), dop-
amine (DA); 
Hypothalamus-hypophysis-adrenal cortex axis (HPAA): 
corticotropin releasing hormone (CRH), adrenocorticotropic 
hormone (ACTH), corticosterone (CORT); 
Hypothalamus-hypophysis-thyroid gland axis (HPTA): 
Thyrotropin releasing hormone (TRH), thyrotropic stim-
ulating hormone (TSH), thyroid hormone (T3,T4); 
Sympathesis-adrenal-medulla axis (SAM): norepineph-
rine (NE), epinephrine (E); 
Renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS): plasma re-
nin activity (PRA), angiotensin II (AngII), aldosterone 
(ALD); 
Immune factors: Interleukin (IL)-1β, IL-2, IL-6, interfer-
on-γ (IFN-γ), tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α). 
At the end of the experiment, blood samples were collected 
from the carotid artery after the rats were anesthetized (30 
mg/kg butaylone intraperitoneally). Each blood sample was 
divided into three aliquots. The first aliquot (1 ml) was 
mixed with 30μL of 10% EDTA and 40μL of aprotinin. 
Samples were centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 5 min at 4 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. </p>

<p>Radio-immunoassays were performed to measure the levels 
of ET, CRH, ALD and ACTH (test kits were provided by 
Purevalley Biotech, China). The second aliquot of serum 
(0.5 ml) put into an anticoagulant tube with 10% EDTA-Na2 
and enzyme inhibitor, and was kept on ice. After mixing 
the serum was centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 5 min. at 4 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. 
Radio-immunoassays were used to measure the levels 
AngII of and PRA (test kits were provided by Beijin North 
Institute of Biological Technology, China), the total Hcy 
were determined using high-performance liquid chromatog-
raphy (HPLC) [11]. A third aliquot of serum (3 ml) was 
used for ELISA detection of vWF, sICAM-1, NE, E and 
TRH. The levels of TSH, T3, T4, CORT, IL-1β, IL-2, IL-6, 
IFN-γ and TNF-α were measured by radio-immunoassays 
(test kits were provided by Beijin North Institute of 
Biological Technology). Serum NO concentration was meas-
ured by the method of nitric acid reductase (test kits were 
provided by Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, 
China). The serum concentrations of triglyceride (TG), the 
total cholesterol (TC) and the low density lipoprotein cho-
lesterol (LDL-C) were measured using an auto-biochemical 
analyzer (OLYMPUS AU-600). 
After the blood sampling, the hypothalamus was resected 
immediately and the obtained tissue was snap-frozen in dry 
ice (-70 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C) and stored until use for biochemical assess-
ments. DA and 5-HT were assayed by electrochemical de-
tection using HPLC [12]. </p>

<p>Data Processing </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v9.1.3</rs> software was used for data analysis. Results 
were presented as means±SD. The significance of differ-
ences between groups were analyzed by the Dunnett's t-test 
and the student's t-test. Statistical significance was set at 
p＜0.05. 
The bootstrapping method was repeated 1000 times to 
estimate the 95% confidence interval of the ratio of each 
NEI index between the groups. If 95% confidence interval 
of the ratio is lower or higher than 1, this indicates that 
the expression of the index in the test group is significantly 
lower or higher than that in the control group. 
The NEI network data with 19 indices can be simplified 
by principal component analysis (PCA) [13,14], which can 
transform a large number of indices into only two or three 
latent variables known as principal components. Thus, the 
high dimension information can be visualized as a scatter 
plot, in which each data point represents one rat sample, 
and the distance between points in the score plot is an in-
dication of the similarity between samples. In addition, 
loading plots from PCA were used to rank the importance 
of each variable to further capture the differentially ex-
pressed indices accountable for the separation between </p>

<p>NEI Network Study </p>

<p>179 </p>

<p>
ET (ng/L) 
NO (μmol/L) 
vWF (%) 
sICAM-1 (ng/L) </p>

<p>Control 
86.92±8.50 
30.45±7.25 
115.85±65.26 
43.49±20.56 
Hcy 
108.33±8.83** 
19.44±4.80** 
209.48±75.21** 
71.38±30.95** 
HFD 
81.21±7.08 
23.78±9.04* 
188.83±53.55** 
84.59±22.71** 
Hcy+HFD 
112.19±12.07** 
21.76±4.26** 
257.11±49.49** 
89.51±11.13** 
Hcy+HFD+Sim 
100.66±10.92 </p>

<p>△ </p>

<p>27.65±7.06 </p>

<p>△ </p>

<p>175.63±36.67 </p>

<p>△△ </p>

<p>60.57±14.41 </p>

<p>△△ </p>

<p>*p＜0.05, **p＜0.01 vs control group; 
△ p＜0.05, 
△△ p＜0.01 vs Hcy+HFD group. </p>

<p>Table 2. Endothelial function indices (mean±SD, n=10 per group) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Scatter plot of the ratio of 
each NEI network index of the test 
group relative to that of the related 
control group. Error bars represent 
the 95% confidence interval of the 
ratio value. Squares, triangles and 
circles in the figure indicate that the 
95% confidence interval of the ratio 
value is less than 1, covers 1 or is 
higher than 1, respectively. The 95% 
confidence interval of the ratio value 
was estimated by a 1000 times re-
peated bootstrapping method. </p>

<p>groups. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The levels of lipids and Hcy in each group </p>

<p>As shown in Table 1, the levels of TC, TG and LDL-C 
in the HFD and Hcy+HFD groups were significantly in-
creased as compared with the control group. In addition, 
the Hcy level was significantly increased in the Hcy and 
the Hcy+HFD groups compared to those of the control </p>

<p>group. These results indicated that the models were suc-
cessfully established. </p>

<p>Vascular endothelial function </p>

<p>As shown in Table 2, vascular endothelial function was 
found to be impaired at different levels in the Hcy-, HFD-
and Hcy+HFD groups. Hcy+HFD induced endothelial dys-
function was most serious. However, ET level was not sig-
nificantly changed following HFD when compared with nor-
mal rats. In addition, simvastatin showed a protective ef-
fect on endothelial function. </p>



<p>L Li, et al </p>

<p>Fig. 2. PCA scores (A) and loading plots (B) derived from the scores 
of separate principle component analyses of the Hcy-, HFD-and 
Hcy+HFD groups. PCA score plots illustrate that the Hcy-, HFD-
and Hcy+HFD groups are well separated from the control, 
suggesting that the NEI network has been affected due to the 
different treatments. The major markers responsible for class 
separation are revealed by the PCA loading plots, which represent 
the importance to the inter-group differences within the discri-
mination model. The established PCA model was then used to 
predict the scores of PCs in the Hcy+HFD+Sim group (C), providing 
a visual picture of the recovery of the NEI network after treatment 
with simvasatin. The heat map (D) shows the changes in the NEI 
network of control group, compared with the Hcy-, HFD-and 
Hcy+HFD groups, or the Hcy+HFD+Sim group compared with 
Hcy+HFD group. Shades of red and blue represent fold increase 
and decrease of the different indices in the indicated groups. </p>

<p>NEI network profile </p>

<p>A number of marked changes in the NEI network were 
observed in rats following the different treatments. The 
bootstrapping method was used to estimate the 95% con-
fidence interval of the ratio of the test group, relative to 
the control group (Fig. 1). In order to make the results bet-
ter interpretable, principle component analyses (PCA) were 
employed for processing these complex data. 
The PCA score plots showed an almost complete separa-
tion among the control and model groups (Fig. 2A), princi-
pal components 1 (PC1) and 2 (PC2) explained 26.38% and </p>

<p>14.63% of the total variance. The PCA loading plots (Fig. 
2B) indicated the contribution of the 19 indices to the differ-
ences observed among the samples. Hcy+HFD treated ani-
mals were well separated from the normal animals along 
the first PC, and this mainly arose from the variation of 
T4, PRA, AngII, TNF-α, IFN-γ and CORT data. The re-
sults indicated that the PC1 mainly reflected the infor-
mation of the RAAS and immune system. HFD treaded ani-
mals were separated from Hcy treated animals along the 
PC2, and this arose from the main variation of 5-HT, ACTH 
and E data. These key indices selected from PCA model 
showed significant differences between the control and the 
experimental groups (Fig. 3). 
The PCA model calculated from the data of the control 
and model groups was then used to predict the scores of 
PCs in the Hcy+HFD+Sim group. As shown in Figure 2B, 
the expression of NEI network in the Hcy+HFD+Sim group 
obviously deviated from that in the Hcy+HFD group, and 
approached the state of the control group. The results sug-
gested that simvastatin has an obvious regulatory effect on 
the NEI network. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Endothelial dysfunction is thought to be a key event in 
the development of atherosclerosis and has been reported 
to predate clinically obvious vascular pathology by many 
years. Previous literatures have demonstrated that ex-
posure to homocysteine (Hcy) and high fat diet (HFD) can 
lead to vascular endothelial dysfunction, but the main dif-
ferences between Hcy and HFD is still unclear. In this 
study, we compared two models of exposure to Hcy and 
HFD respectively, with the combined model of Hcy+HFD 
on vascular endothelial function. The results showed that 
the vascular endothelial function was affected in all three 
model groups, in which the No level was significantly de-
creased and the vWF and sICAM-1 levels were significantly 
increased. However, there were still some differences among 
the model groups. For example, the ET level was not ob-
viously changed in the HFD group, and endothelial function 
was impacted most seriously in the Hcy+HFD group. In ad-
dition, endothelial function of the rats in the Hcy+HFD+ 
Sim group showed a recovery tendency because the levels 
of ET, vWF and sICAM-1 were significantly lower and NO 
was significantly higher than in the Hcy+HFD group. 
The interdisciplinary fields of neuroendocrine and im-
mune systems have undergone explosive growth in recent 
years [15]. Increasing evidence has shown that the NEI net-
work plays a pivotal role in regulating homeostasis and op-
timizing health and makes great contributions to various 
complex diseases [16]. In this study, we also observed the 
changes of the NEI network in the three models. The re-
sults suggested that Hcy mainly affected the balance of 
neurotransmitters, HPTA and SAM, while HFD mainly in-
fluenced the HPAA, HPTA and RAAS. The combination of 
Hcy and HFD impacted almost the whole NEI network and 
showed synergetic damaging effects. It is worth mentioning 
that, simvastatin reversed the imbalance of the NEI net-
work disturbed by the Hcy+HFD, especially visible at the 
levels of DA, CRH, CORT, T4, PRA, ALD, IL-6 and TNF-α, 
suggesting that the regulatory role of simvastatin on endo-
thelial function may be associated with the NEI network. 
A growing number of reports have demonstrated the close 
relationship between endothelial function and NEI net-</p>

<p>NEI Network Study </p>



<p>Fig. 3. The key indices selected from PCA model exemplified a clear distinction among the groups (Mean±SD). Significant difference between 
each model group (n=10) and the control group (n=10) is based on a two-tailed Dunnett's t-test (*p＜0.05, **p＜0.01), and significant 
difference between the Hcy+HFD group (n=10) and the simvastatin group (n=10) is based on a two-tailed student's t-test ( 
△ p＜0.05, 
△△ p 
＜0.01). </p>

<p>work: (1) Endothelial function in patients with severe 
chronic heart failure can be improved by DA [17], suggest-
ing that neurotransmitters may play a key role in the 
pathogenesis of endothelial dysfunction; (2) AngII can lead 
to endothelial dysfunction via AngII receptor subtypek 1 
activation and reactive oxygen-and nitrogen species gen-
eration [18]; (3) L-thyroxine therapy can improve endothe-
lial function in the subclinical hypothyroidism patients [19]; 
(4) CRH can induce a significant increase of ET-1 release 
[20]; (5) Endothelial dysfunction occurring in the metabolic 
syndrome is the result of effects of the inflammatory cyto-
kine TNF-α and subsequent production of superoxide [21, 
22]. The studies mentioned above indicated that NEI net-
work has a tight connection with endothelial function. 
Observing the profile of NEI network is a good method 
to distinguish disease states induced by different risk fac-
tors, this approach is similar to the Metabonomics [23], 
which used metabolic fingerprints to study the physi-
opathologic state. However, the potential biomarkers found 
by metabonomics may be surrogates of the metabolic proc-
ess rather than direct reporters of disease target. Converse-
ly, NEI network has tight connection with disease state, 
and the discriminating indices captured in the PCA loading 
plots may lead to therapeutic targets. For example, in this 
study, we found the levels of T4 in the three model groups 
were significantly lower than the control group, and these </p>

<p>changes can be reserved by simvastatin. This result sug-
gested that T4 may be the key index for vascular endothe-
lial dysfunction. Clinical studies have shown that there is 
an association between subclinical hypothyroidism and cor-
onary artery disease, and that after treatment with L-thy-
roxine the endothelial function in the subclinical hypo-
thyroidism patients was improved [19,24]. This fact sup-
ported the idea that T4 plays a key role in endothelial 
function. 
In addition, NEI network can also be used to evaluate 
drug effects. In this study, significant effects on the NEI 
network were observed in the simvastatin group. It is par-
ticularly suitable for the evaluation of Chinese medicine, 
which acts through complex mechanisms featured as multi-
compound, multitarget and multipathway. It has become 
more recognized that Chinese medicine produces the heal-
ing efficacy in a more holistic way. However, researchers 
typically only focus on a single or several indices associated 
with a disease. Obviously, NEI network is a better indicator 
for Chinese medicine to evaluate its holistic effect on the 
body. 
In summary, the changes of NEI network were well ob-
served in the three endothelial dysfunction model groups. 
The effect of simvastatin treatment in the NEI network was 
also studied. The results indicated that NEI network has 
a tight connection with endothelial function, and this rela-</p>



<p>L Li, et al </p>

<p>tionship can be used to distinguish different risk factors 
and evaluate drug effects. It should be noted that, the 
mechanisms of endothelial dysfunction are now well recog-
nized, therefore, these aspects are not the focus of the 
study. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science 
Funds Fund (81303279), grants from the National Basic 
Research Program of China (2012CB518600), the National 
Key Project for IND (2012ZX09303-003, 2012ZX09303009-
001), and the Leading Academic Discipline Project of 
Shanghai Municipal Education Commission (085ZY1202, 
SYZ11056, ZYSNXD-CC-LCPJ). </p>



</text></tei>