<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3507205" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>have shown that NRAS 
Q61K and BRAF 
V600E mutations contribute 
to melanoma's resistance to apoptosis in part by down-regulating 
BH3 (Bcl-2 homolog domain 3)-only pro-apoptotic Bcl-2 family 
members such as Bim and Bad (Wang et al., 2007; Boisvert-Adamo 
and Aplin, 2008; Cartlidge et al., 2008; Goldstein et al., 2008; 
Hendrickson et al., 2008). These studies suggest that BH3-only pro-
apoptotic Bcl-2 family members are possible treatment targets for 
overriding melanoma's inherent defenses against cell death. 
Application of BH3 mimetics to activate the intrinsic apoptotic 
pathway is a promising approach to treating various cancers 
(Labi et al., 2008). Using a BH3 mimetic bypasses the need to 
induce endogenous expression of BH3-only proteins, an ability 
which is often strongly inhibited in many cancers, including 
melanomas. One promising BH3 mimetic is ABT-737 
(developed by Abbott). ABT-737 is a mimetic of the BH3-only 
pro-apoptotic protein Bad, and is a potent small molecule 
inhibitor of the anti-apoptotic proteins Bcl-2, Bcl-X L , and Bcl-w 
with an affinity 2-3 orders of magnitude higher than any 
previously reported compounds (Letai, 2005; Oltersdorf et al., 
2005). It acts like a BH3-only protein to antagonize anti-
apoptotic Bcl-2 family members, thereby diminishing their 
ability to inhibit apoptosis (Oltersdorf et al., 2005). Many 
groups have reported on the high efficacy of ABT-737 either as a </p>

<p> 
Research Article </p>

<p>Biology Open </p>

<p>single agent or as a chemo-potentiator in combination with other 
chemotherapeutic agents to treat multiple types of cancers 
(Adams et al., 2005; Oltersdorf et al., 2005; Certo et al., 2006; 
Konopleva et al., 2006; Shoemaker et al., 2006; van Delft et al., 
2006; Chauhan et al., 2007; Chen et al., 2007; Kang et al., 2007; 
Kohl et al., 2007; Olberding et al., 2010; Reynoso et al., 2010; 
Song et al., 2010). 
Previously, we showed that the combination of ABT-737 with 
a proteasome inhibitor (MG-132) synergistically killed 
melanoma cells in vitro. Recent studies have also shown that 
Bcl-2 overexpression mediates resistance to another proteasome 
inhibitor, Bortezomib, and that ABT-737 can overcome this 
resistance in lymphoid cells (Paoluzzi et al., 2008; Smith et al., 
2011). Bortezomib (Velcade) is the first therapeutic proteasome 
inhibitor approved in the U.S. for treating cancers (Chen et al., 
2011), and combining ABT-737 with an already approved drug 
would be a more efficient way of moving it to clinic. In this 
study, we explored whether ABT-737 is effective in killing 
melanoma cells either alone or in combination with Bortezomib 
in vitro and in vivo, and evaluated the mechanisms of action. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Cell lines and culture conditions </p>

<p>The following melanoma cell lines were obtained from ATCC (Manassas, VA): 
A375, 1205Lu, and HT-144. WM852c, WM115, and 451Lu were kindly provided 
by Dr. Meenhard Herlyn (Wistar Institute, Philadelphia, PA). Cells were maintained 
in RPMI1640 (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY) with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gemini 
Bio-Products, Inc., West Sacramento, CA). All cell lines except WM852c harbor 
BRAF 
V600E mutations and no common mutations in NRAS (exons 1 or 2), and 
WM852c exhibits an NRAS 
Q61R mutation but no BRAF mutations (exons 11 or 15). </p>

<p>Reagents </p>

<p>Bortezomib for in vitro experiments was purchased from LC Laboratories 
(Woburn, MA). For mouse experiments, Bortezomib formulated as a mannitol 
boronate ester (Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Cambridge, MA) was purchased 
from the University of Colorado Hospital pharmacy. ABT-737 was kindly 
provided by Abbott Laboratories (Abbott Park, IL). </p>

<p>Cell Titer 96 
TM Aqueous One solution cell proliferation assay for 
quantification of cell viability (MTS assay) </p>

<p>Cells were seeded in a 96-well plate for 24 h, and then treated with indicated 
compounds for 48 h before being subjected to MTS assays. The assay was 
obtained from Promega Corp. (Madison, WI), and procedures were followed as 
previously described (Shellman et al., 2005). All control treatments used vehicle 
(DMSO) concentrations equal to that of the highest concentration of the drug 
treatment groups. </p>

<p>Measurement of apoptosis using Annexin V staining </p>

<p>Cells were seeded in 10 cm dishes for indicated treatments before being subjected 
to analyses. The Annexin V-FITC Apoptosis Detection Kit (BD Biosciences, San 
Jose, CA) was used according to the manufacturer's protocol. Cells were analyzed 
by flow cytometry using a Beckman Coulter FC500 with CXP software (Hialeah, 
FL) in the University of Colorado Cancer Center Flow Cytometry Core. </p>

<p>Immunoblots </p>

<p>Cells, both floating and adherent, were harvested with 1x Laemmli Sample Buffer 
(Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). Samples were used in the standard Western blot analysis 
protocol as described previously (Ruth et al., 2006). Blots were developed with 
HRP substrate (SuperSignal West Pico or Femto solutions, Pierce, Rockford, IL) 
for 5 min at room temperature, and analyzed using a Chemi-doc 
chemiluminescence detector (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). The following antibodies 
were used at suggested dilutions from the manufacturers: Bax, Bcl-X L , PARP, and 
a/b Tubulin were from Cell Signaling Technology (Danvers, MA); Noxa was from 
EMD Biosciences, Inc. (San Diego, CA); Mcl-1 was from BD Biosciences (San 
Jose, CA); Bcl-2 was from Dako (Glostrup, Denmark); Bak was from Millipore 
Corp. (Billerica, MA); and HRP-conjugated goat anti-mouse and anti-rabbit 
antibodies were from Jackson Immuno-Research (West Grove, PA). 
Densitometry measurements were obtained using the Quantity OneH program 
(Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA), normalizing all samples to a/b Tubulin to account for 
loading variation. </p>

<p>RNA interference </p>

<p>ON-TARGETplus SMARTpools of siRNA were purchased from Dharmacon, Inc. 
(Lafayette, CO), targeting human Noxa (PMAIP1, NM_021127), human Mcl-1 
(MCL1, NM_182763), human Bcl-2 (BCL2, NM_000657), human Bcl-X L (BCL2L1, 
NM_001191), and the non-targeting control pool. siRNA was introduced into cells 
using an Amaxa Nucleofector II device (Amaxa Inc., Gaithersburg, MD) as described 
previously (Miller et al., 2009). Cells were nucleofected with the indicated siRNAs 
and cultured for indicated periods of time. Subsequently, all growth medium was 
removed and fresh medium containing indicated compounds was added for indicated 
time periods before the cells were harvested for analysis. </p>

<p>Mouse tumor model </p>

<p>Female NCRNU nude mice, aged 5-6 weeks, were purchased from Taconic 
(Hudson, NY). Each mouse was subcutaneously injected on each flank with 1 million 
1205Lu cells in a 100 ml volume consisting of 50% BD Matrigel Matrix (BD 
Biosciences) prepared according to the manufacturer's protocol. We performed 
in vitro experiments with 1205Lu cells to ensure that they responded to the drugs in a 
similar fashion as the other cell lines (supplementary material Fig. S3). 
Drug treatments began after tumors reached approximately 100 mm 
3 , at around 
1 week. Mice were randomly divided into four treatment groups: (1) vehicle only 
(control, n510 tumors); (2) ABT-737 only (n510); (3) Bortezomib only (n512); 
(4) Bortezomib plus ABT-737 (n518). Bortezomib and ABT-737 were 
administered at 0.8 mg/kg and 80 mg/kg respectively. All mice received either 
the drug or vehicle for both drugs. ABT-737 was prepared fresh every 7 days by 
dissolving it in vehicle consisting of 65% D5W, 30% propylene glycol, 5% 
Tween-80, pH 1.0. The pH was raised to ,3.5 after the drug was fully dissolved. 
ABT-737 or vehicle was administered daily for 21 days via intraperitoneal (i.p.) 
injection. Bortezomib was diluted in normal saline (0.9%) each day prior to use 
and administered on days 1, 5, and 9 via intravenous (i.v.) tail vein injection. On 
days when both drugs were administered, Bortezomib was administered at least 
5 h prior to ABT-737. All experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use Committee of the University of Colorado Denver. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>One-Way Analyses of Variance (ANOVA) were performed to compare group 
means, and Tukey's Post Hoc tests were used for subsequent pair-wise 
comparisons. Kaplan-Meier curve analysis was used to compare individual 
tumor doubling rates. Log-rank (Mantel-Cox) tests were used to compare Kaplan-
Meier curves with the program <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, San Diego, 
CA), and p-values of 0.05 and below were considered significant. </p>

<p>Supplemental Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Calculation of combination indexes using Calcusyn. </p>

<p>The cytotoxic effects from MTS assays were entered into Calcusyn 
software (Biosoft, Ferguson, MO) to determine whether the 
treatment combinations had synergistic, additive, or antagonistic 
effects with the Chou-Talalay method (Chou and Talalay, 1984). 
When the CI value is less than 1, it indicates synergistic effects, 
and the lower the CI, the stronger the synergism. </p>

<p>Creation of shRNA 1205Lu cells. </p>

<p>1205Lu cells expressing short hairpin RNA (shRNA) against 
Noxa, or scrambled control, were constructed using shRNA 
Lentiviral Particles from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, 
CA) according to the manufacturer's instructions with slight 
modification. Briefly, cells were seeded in 12-well plates for 24 h 
at concentrations sufficient to reach 50% confluency. The media 
was removed from each well and replaced with 1 ml of chilled 
polybrene working solution (5 mg/ml in RPMI medium) and 
incubated at RT for 5 min. The solution was removed and 
replaced with 1 ml of chilled polybrene working solution with up 
to 20 ml of viral particle and incubated at 37˚C. The solution was 
then removed 24 h later, cells were rinsed once with fresh media, 
and then 1 ml of fresh media was added. Cells were grown until 
sufficient numbers were available for selection. Transduced cells 
were selected by supplementing the media with puromycin 
(1-4 mg/ml) for several days, replacing the medium with fresh 
puromycin-containing medium every 3-4 days until resistant </p>

<p>ABT-737 synergizes with Bortezomib in melanoma </p>

<p>
Biology Open </p>

<p>colonies could be identified. Knockdown of Noxa was confirmed 
by immunoblotting of cell lysates (data not shown). </p>

<p>Results 
Targeting Mcl-1, but not Bcl-2 or Bcl-X L , sensitizes melanoma 
cells to ABT-737 </p>

<p>ABT-737 treatment alone was only moderately effective at killing 
melanoma cells at 10 mM for 48 h, and ineffective at lower doses 
(Fig. 1A). We thus examined how the anti-apoptotic proteins 
Bcl-2, Bcl-X L , and Mcl-1 modulate melanoma's sensitivity to </p>

<p>ABT-737 using RNA interference techniques. Fig. 1 shows that 
simply knocking-down protein expression of these anti-apoptotic 
Bcl-2 family members individually did not induce cell death in 
melanoma cells. This suggests that melanoma cells have multiple 
redundant anti-apoptotic defenses. In contrast, knocking-down 
Mcl-1 (but not Bcl-2 or Bcl-X L ) protein expression sensitized these 
cells to ABT-737 treatment dramatically (Fig. 1B,D), from 16.4% 
to 77.6% Annexin V+ cells in WM852c cells (Fig. 1B), and from 
16.8% to 67.4% Annexin V+ cells in A375 cells (Fig. 1D) (note 
that transfection of siRNA increased background cell death by </p>

<p>Fig. 1. ABT-737 alone has only a small killing effect on melanoma cells, and Mcl-1 is the main mediator of resistance. MTS assays (A) of WM852c, A375, and 
1205Lu cells show only a small killing effect from ABT-737 after 48 h treatments. The control for each cell line was set to 100%. Annexin V Assays (B,D) and 
Immunoblots (C,E) were performed with melanoma cells transfected with indicated siRNAs. Cells were then treated for 24 h with DMSO control or 3.3 mM ABT-
737, 24 h post-transfection. Total Annexin V-positive cells were averaged6s.e.m. for WM852c cells (B) and A375 cells (D), representing two or three independent 
experiments, respectively. * One-Way ANOVA; p50.001; ** p50.0004. Remaining WM852c cells (C) and A375 cells (E) from Annexin V assays were lysed for 
immunoblot analyses. </p>

<p>ABT-737 synergizes with Bortezomib in melanoma </p>

<p>
Biology Open </p>

<p>5-10% as compared to data in Fig. 2C). These changes were 
highly significant statistically, and demonstrate that Mcl-1 is the 
critical factor for melanoma resistance to ABT-737. Immunoblot 
analyses (Fig. 1C,E) and densitometry measurements confirmed 
50-90% inhibition of target proteins in these experiments. </p>

<p>ABT-737 synergistically kills human melanoma cells when 
combined with Bortezomib </p>

<p>We examined the effects of ABT-737 alone or in combination 
with Bortezomib for treating A375 and WM852c human </p>

<p>melanoma cells using MTS assays to measure relative cell 
viability. We found that ABT-737 alone at 1.1 mM caused no 
cytotoxicity, consistent with results shown in Fig. 1A, but ABT-
737 increased the effect of Bortezomib on relative cell viability 
(Fig. 2A,B). To quantify whether these drug combinations 
exhibited synergistic, additive, or antagonistic effects, we used 
Calcusyn software to calculate the combination index (CI) value 
for each experimental combination (supplementary material 
Fig. S1). CI values less than, equal to, or greater than one 
indicate synergy, additivity, or antagonism, respectively. Most of </p>

<p>Fig. 2. ABT-737 combined with Bortezomib 
synergistically kills melanoma cells. For MTS 
viability assays, WM852c (A) and A375 
(B) melanoma cells were treated with indicated 
compounds for 48 h. Results represent at least three 
independent experiments. For Annexin V assays 
(C), A375 and WM852c cells were seeded 24 h 
prior to treatment with indicated compounds for 
another 24 h. Total Annexin V-positive cells were 
averaged6s.e.m., representing three independent 
experiments. *One-Way ANOVA; Tukey's post-
hoc test; p,0.001 (individual Bortezomib 
treatments compared to combination treatment 
with ABT-737). </p>

<p>ABT-737 synergizes with Bortezomib in melanoma </p>

<p>
Biology Open </p>

<p>the CI values were less than 0.7 (indicating synergy), and many 
CI values were less than 0.3 (indicating strong synergy). These 
results show that a majority of the combination conditions of 
ABT-737 with Bortezomib displayed strong synergistic killing 
effects for these melanoma cell lines (supplementary material </p>

<p>Fig. S1). We have observed similar results in treating several 
additional melanoma cell lines (supplementary material Figs. S2, 
S3 and data not shown). 
We then performed Annexin V/PI apoptosis assays to determine 
if the combination treatments induced killing synergistically in </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Combination of Bortezomib with 
ABT-737 increases the Noxa/Mcl-1 
protein ratio and induces Noxa-
dependent apoptosis. Immunoblots 
(A) show changes in Bcl-2 family member 
proteins upon treatments. Numbers at the 
bottom indicate relative Noxa/Mcl-1 ratios. 
Cells were treated with vehicle control 
('DMSO'), 1.1 mM ABT-737 ('ABT'), 15 
nM Bortezomib ('Bort.'), or a combination 
of both drugs ('Combo') for 24 h before 
being lysed. Annexin V Assays (B) and 
Immunoblots (C,D) were performed with 
A375 and WM852c cells transfected with 
indicated siRNAs. 24 h post-transfection, 
cells were then treated for 18 h with the 
indicated compounds before being 
harvested for analyses. Total Annexin V-
positive WM852c or A375 cells were 
averaged6s.e.m., representing three 
independent experiments. One-Way 
ANOVA; * p,0.05; ** p,0.01. </p>

<p>ABT-737 synergizes with Bortezomib in melanoma </p>

<p>
Biology Open </p>

<p>A375 and WM852c melanoma cells (Fig. 2C). Consistent with our 
MTS results, ABT-737 single treatments did not significantly 
increase the percentage of Annexin V+ cells compared to the 
DMSO control. Similarly, Bortezomib single treatments only 
induced a small increase in the Annexin V+ cell populations. 
However, the ABT-737 combination treatments significantly 
increased the percentage of Annexin V+ cells compared to 
Bortezomib single treatments for both cell lines (Fig. 2C). The 
killing effect of the combination treatment was significantly higher 
than the sum effects of the individual treatments. Thus, MTS and 
Annexin V assays both indicate that combining ABT-737 with 
Bortezomib induces synergistic killing of melanoma cells. </p>

<p>Combination of ABT-737 and Bortezomib induces expression of 
the pro-apoptotic protein Noxa and degradation of the anti-
apoptotic protein Mcl-1 </p>

<p>To investigate the mechanism involved in synergy, we examined 
the effects of the treatments on Bcl-2 family members. Only 
Noxa and Mcl-1 protein levels exhibited consistent and dramatic 
changes induced by either the Bortezomib single treatment or the 
combination of Bortezomib and ABT-737 (Fig. 3A and data not 
shown). The ABT-737 single treatment had little effect on most 
proteins examined, while the Bortezomib single treatment 
increased both Noxa and Mcl-1 levels substantially (Fig. 3A). 
The combination treatment of Bortezomib and ABT-737 
increased Noxa protein expression to levels similar to the 
Bortezomib single treatment. However, Mcl-1 protein levels in 
cells treated with the drug combination were reduced to similar 
levels as those treated with vehicle control or ABT-737 alone 
(Fig. 3A). This is very similar to what we observed for the 
treatment of ABT-737 combined with MG-132 (Miller et al., 
2009). Thus, these data suggest that the combination treatment of 
ABT-737 and Bortezomib induces protein expression of pro-
apoptotic Noxa and degradation of anti-apoptotic Mcl-1. </p>

<p>Noxa protein knockdown protects cells from killing induced by 
the combination of ABT-737 with Bortezomib </p>

<p>The major function of Noxa in regulating apoptosis is to 
antagonize Mcl-1, since pro-apoptotic Noxa mainly binds to the 
anti-apoptotic protein Mcl-1, but binds to Bcl-2 and Bcl-X L with 
20-and 70-fold less affinity, respectively, and is not known to 
bind to Bcl-w (Chen et al., 2005; Willis et al., 2005; Smith et al., 
2011). To further investigate the roles of Noxa expression in cell 
death induced by the combination drug treatments, we used 
RNAi techniques in WM852c and A375 cells (Fig. 3B,C,D). 
When cells were treated with combinations of ABT-737 and 
Bortezomib, blocking Noxa expression by siRNA significantly 
decreased Annexin V+ cells in both cell lines (Fig. 3B) (note the 
higher than usual positivity, compared to Fig. 2C, in the control 
cells due to siRNA transfection). Further, immunoblot analyses 
indicate that our siRNA inhibited Noxa protein induction by 
,50% under the combination treatment conditions (Fig. 3C,D). 
Similar results were also observed in 1205Lu cells 
(supplementary material Fig. S3). These results suggest that 
Noxa is the major mediator of apoptosis induced by the 
combination drug treatment of ABT-737 and Bortezomib. </p>

<p>ABT-737 and Bortezomib reduce melanoma tumor growth in a 
mouse model </p>

<p>We tested the ability of ABT-737, Bortezomib, or a combination 
of the drugs to affect melanoma tumors in vivo. While ABT-737 </p>

<p>alone caused no observable adverse effects, Bortezomib 
treatment caused weight loss, lethargy, and the appearance of 
flaky skin. These effects were more pronounced in mice treated 
with both drugs, limiting the dose sizes. Although Bortezomib at 
doses of 1 mg/kg and above have been used in other mouse 
studies (Adams and Kauffman, 2004), we found that doses above 
0.8 mg/kg, when combined with ABT-737 doses above 80 mg/ 
kg, had a profound effect on tumor growth but also caused 
unacceptable weight loss (data not shown), requiring premature 
euthanasia of the mice. Therefore, we used relatively low drug 
doses (0.8 mg/kg Bortezomib, 80 mg/kg ABT-737). Since larger 
tumors had a tendency to ulcerate, requiring mice to be removed 
prior to the end of the study period, we constructed Kaplan-Meier 
curves (Fig. 4) to compare the rates at which individual tumors 
doubled their original size, which allowed the inclusion of every 
tumor. Both ABT-737 and Bortezomib treated mice showed 
significantly decreased tumor doubling rates compared to vehicle 
treated mice (p50.005 and 0.011, respectively). Mice treated 
with both drugs showed decreased tumor doubling rates 
significantly compared to the control (p,0.0001) and to mice 
treated individually with ABT-737 (p50.008) or Bortezomib 
(p50.0173). This indicates that ABT-737 and Bortezomib can 
effectively reduce melanoma tumor growth in vivo, and that 
combining them at these doses has a small but significant 
additive effect. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The Bcl-2 family plays an important role in regulating apoptosis 
(see review (Thomadaki et al., 2006)), and targeting anti-
apoptotic Bcl-2 family members combats the drug resistance 
exhibited by many cancer types (see review (Kang and Reynolds, 
2009)). In this study, we investigated the effects and mechanisms 
of treating melanoma cells with a BH3 mimetic Bcl-2 inhibitor, 
ABT-737, as a single treatment or combined with a chemo-
therapeutic drug already used in clinic, Bortezomib. 
We found that knocking-down protein expression of the anti-
apoptotic proteins Bcl-2, Bcl-X L , or Mcl-1 individually with 
siRNAs is not sufficient to induce cell death in melanoma cells. 
We determined that ABT-737 single treatment induced moderate </p>

<p>Fig. 4. ABT-737 and Bortezomib reduce tumor growth in a mouse model. 
Tumors were grown in nude mice by injecting 1205Lu cells subcutaneously. 
Mice were divided into four groups: (1) vehicle only, (2) ABT-737, (3) 
Bortezomib, (4) both drugs. Kaplan-Meier curves are based on tumor doubling 
times over the course of the experiment. Both ABT-737 and Bortezomib 
treatment groups were significantly different from the control (p50.005 and 
0.014, respectively). The combination group was significantly different from 
the control (p,0.0001), ABT-737 (p50.008) and Bortezomib 
groups (p50.0173). </p>

<p>ABT-737 synergizes with Bortezomib in melanoma </p>

<p>
Biology Open </p>

<p>cytotoxicity at 10 mM, but little or no cytotoxicity at lower doses 
(Fig. 1A). However, knocking-down Mcl-1, but not Bcl-2 or Bcl-
X L , dramatically sensitized these melanoma cells to ABT-737 
(Fig. 1B,D), demonstrating that Mcl-1 is the critical mediator of 
melanoma's resistance to ABT-737 treatment. Results here also 
indicate that melanoma cells have multiple anti-apoptotic 
defenses, and that neutralizing multiple anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 
members at the same time is necessary to induce optimal killing 
effects for melanoma cells. 
The Bcl-2 family can be divided into 3 groups (see review 
(Thomadaki et al., 2006)): (1) Anti-apoptotic proteins, including 
the homologous proteins Bcl-2, Bcl-X L , Bcl-w, Mcl-1, and A1; 
(2) Multi-domain pro-apoptotic proteins Bax and Bak (and the 
less-studied Bok), which are critical downstream mediators of 
apoptosis; (3) Pro-apoptotic BH3-only proteins, including Noxa, 
Bad, Bim, Bid, Puma, Bmf, BNIP3, BNIP3L, Hrk, and Bik, 
which antagonize the function of anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 family 
members. 
Binding affinities between different Bcl-2 family members are 
not equal and are important for their respective functions. For 
example, the BH3-only pro-apoptotic protein Bad binds tightly to 
the anti-apoptotic proteins Bcl-2, Bcl-X L , and Bcl-w, but not to 
Mcl-1 or A1, whereas Noxa binds to Mcl-1 and A1 but far less 
strongly to Bcl-2 and Bcl-X L , and is not known to bind Bcl-w 
(Chen et al., 2005; Willis et al., 2005; Smith et al., 2011). 
ABT-737 is a mimetic of Bad, and as such, it binds tightly to 
Bcl-2, Bcl-X L , and Bcl-w, antagonizing their anti-apoptotic 
function (Oltersdorf et al., 2005). However, ABT-737 does not 
bind to Mcl-1 or A1, just as Bad does not. Thus, Mcl-1 (or A1) 
may act as a barrier to ABT-737-induced cell death, and it has 
been shown that neutralizing Mcl-1 significantly potentiates the 
cytotoxicity induced by ABT-737 in treating multiple cancer 
types (Adams et al., 2005; Certo et al., 2006; Konopleva et al., 
2006; Letai, 2006; Lin et al., 2006; van Delft et al., 2006; Chen et 
al., 2007; Tahir et al., 2007; Olberding et al., 2010; Harrison et 
al., 2011). Our results for treating melanomas are consistent with 
these studies, implying that combination treatments that 
antagonize multiple anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 family members are 
needed. 
We attempted to determine if the anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 family 
member, A1, regulates melanoma's sensitivity to ABT-737. We 
found it was difficult to detect A1 protein expression in 
melanoma cells, probably due to low expression levels (data 
not shown). In addition, the dramatic increase in melanoma's 
sensitivity to ABT-737 with Mcl-1 protein knockdown indicates 
that Mcl-1 is the critical mediator of resistance to ABT-737 in 
melanoma cells. These results indicate that combination 
treatments of ABT-737 with drugs that neutralize the anti-
apoptotic function of Mcl-1 are good treatment strategies. 
Moreover, resistance of melanoma cells to Bortezomib has 
been shown to be mediated by anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 family 
members (Wolter et al., 2007), making ABT-737 and Bortezomib 
a promising combination. 
We therefore examined whether combining ABT-737 with the 
chemotherapeutic drug Bortezomib would synergistically kill 
melanoma cells. MTS and Annexin V assays showed that 
combining ABT-737 with Bortezomib synergistically killed 
melanoma cells (Fig. 2), and immunoblots of cleaved PARP 
corroborate the fact that the combination treatment induced 
apoptosis synergistically (Fig. 3A). Immunoblot analyses also 
demonstrated a significant increase in Noxa protein expression </p>

<p>and loss of Mcl-1 protein for the combination treatment, 
significantly increasing the Noxa/Mcl-1 protein ratio (Fig. 3A). 
Bortezomib primarily achieves this through drastic up-regulation 
of Noxa protein expression, though agents that promote Mcl-1 
protein loss in the absence of Noxa up-regulation should have a 
similar effect. 
Interestingly, Bortezomib treatment alone led to a significant 
increase of Mcl-1 levels at 24 h, most likely due to decreased 
proteolysis. While this effect has been observed previously in 
melanoma cells (Qin et al., 2006), it is in marked contrast to what 
is observed in multiple myeloma cells, where Mcl-1 undergoes 
caspase-dependent cleavage (Podar et al., 2008). Likewise, ABT-
737 alone can decrease Mcl-1 in multiple myeloma (Kline et al., 
2007), whereas we did not observe any Mcl-1 decrease with the 
concentrations used in the present study. These differences are 
likely due to the fact that apoptosis can induce caspase-dependent 
degradation of Mcl-1 (Podar et al., 2008; Miller et al., 2009), and 
that ABT-737 alone at 3.3 mM or less did not induce apoptosis in 
the present study, whereas similar concentrations induce 
significant cell death in multiple myeloma cell lines (Kline 
et al., 2007). Rather, in the present study, Mcl-1 degradation 
appears to have taken place only upon large-scale apoptosis 
induced by the combination treatment. These differences underscore 
the different sensitivities of various cancers to chemotherapeutic 
drugs, and show why, in the case of melanoma, targeting multiple 
cellular defenses is likely necessary. 
To test whether Noxa up-regulation was responsible for the 
effects observed in the combination treatment of ABT-737 with 
Bortezomib, we inhibited Noxa expression via siRNA. This 
inhibition protected melanoma cells from cytotoxicity induced by 
the combination treatments (Fig. 3B). These results indicate that 
Bortezomib neutralizes Mcl-1's function specifically through 
Noxa. 
Our in vivo mouse experiments showed that ABT-737 and 
Bortezomib treatments reduce the rate of tumor growth. Using 
relatively low doses of the drugs, we found reduced tumor growth 
for all treatment groups and significant decreases in the tumor 
doubling rate (Fig. 4), suggesting that each drug is promising as a 
candidate for treating melanoma. The combination treatment 
increased this time further still, and was statistically significant 
compared to both Bortezomib and ABT-737 individual 
treatments. 
One critical limiting factor with the use of Bortezomib and 
ABT-737 in our mouse model was acute toxicity, particularly of 
Bortezomib. We therefore used relatively low doses that did not 
cause weight loss and found that the effect of the drug combination 
was still significant. However, without this dosing limitation, it is 
likely that we would observe a much more pronounced effect on 
tumor growth in the mice treated with the drug combination. This 
implies that newer proteasome inhibitors that are less toxic than 
Bortezomib, and can be used at higher doses, may work even better 
with ABT-737 and hold more promise for clinical trials. 
The results from our in vitro Bortezomib treatments are 
consistent with our previous study on the combination treatment 
of ABT-737 with another proteasome inhibitor, MG-132 (Miller 
et al., 2009). In that study, we found that the combination 
treatment of MG-132 and ABT-737 antagonizes Mcl-1 through 
increased Noxa expression and caspase-dependent Mcl-1 
cleavage (Miller et al., 2009). Noxa induction appears to be a 
consistent mechanism for cell death in melanoma cells treated 
with various proteasome inhibitors (Qin et al., 2005). These data </p>

<p>ABT-737 synergizes with Bortezomib in melanoma </p>

<p>
Biology Open </p>

<p>indicate that various proteasome inhibitors function through the 
same mechanisms when combined with ABT-737 in treating 
melanoma cells. Currently, more potent and less toxic, next-
generation proteasome inhibitors are in development for clinical 
use (Orlowski and Kuhn, 2008; Kuhn et al., 2011). Our data 
suggest that combining these newer proteasome inhibitors with 
ABT-737 would be an effective means of treating melanomas, if 
they are less toxic, and that this is worthy of further investigation. 
In conclusion, the data reported here indicate that drugs that 
neutralize Mcl-1's function are good candidates for combination 
therapy with ABT-737 for treating melanomas. This validates 
rational molecular approaches for targeting multiple anti-
apoptotic Bcl-2 members in developing cancer treatments. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by NIAMS grant R01AR26427-18 
(DAN); by a Veterans Administration merit grant from the 
Department of Veterans Affairs, Veterans Health Administration, 
Office of Research and Development, Biomedical Laboratory 
Research and Development (DAN); and by NIAMS training grant 
5T32AR007411-29 (PI: DAN, support to SNR). We thank Abbott 
Laboratories (Saul Rosenberg, Steven Elmore, and colleagues) for 
providing the ABT-737 compound. We also thank Karen Helm, 
Christine Childs, and Alistaire S. Acosta at the University of 
Colorado Cancer Center Flow Cytometry Core (supported by NIH 
grant P30 CA 046934) for their expert technical assistance. </p>



<p>ABT-737 synergizes with Bortezomib in melanoma </p>

<p>
Biology Open </p>



<p>ABT-737 synergizes with Bortezomib in melanoma </p>

<p>
Biology Open </p>

</text></tei>