<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3639448" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>One of the most disputed issues in primate evolution and thus of our own primate roots, is the phylogenetic 
position of the Southeast Asian tarsier. While much molecular data indicate a basal place in the primate tree 
shared with strepsirrhines (prosimian monophyly hypothesis), data also exist supporting either an earlier 
divergence in primates (tarsier-first hypothesis) or a close relationship with anthropoid primates 
(Haplorrhini hypothesis). The use of retroposon insertions embedded in the Tarsius genome afforded us the 
unique opportunity to directly test all three hypotheses via three pairwise genome alignments. From 
millions of retroposons, we found 104 perfect orthologous insertions in both tarsiers and anthropoids to the 
exclusion of strepsirrhines, providing conflict-free evidence for the Haplorrhini hypothesis, and none 
supporting either of the other two positions. Thus, tarsiers are clearly the sister group to anthropoids in the 
clade Haplorrhini. </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>ome mammalian species resist our attempts to reconstruct their true ancestry. Conflicting or weak phylo-
genetic signals may suggest more than one possible solution depending on marker systems, partitions of 
data, method and model of reconstruction, or the selected set of compared species. The reasons for 
controversies can be variable and often are due to polymorphisms of characters in populations before their 
speciation or to hybridization, but more often to lineage-specific accumulation of noise (random mutations) 
at the organismal and molecular levels. Lineages formally rich in both individuals and species and then reduced to 
a few remaining representatives are especially exposed to bottleneck effects, apparently diverging them from the 
general characteristics of related species. 
The Southeast Asian tarsier (Tarsiiformes: Primates) is one example of such a phylogenetic history. The once 
species-rich Eocene tarsiers were broadly distributed over the Holarctic region, but today are restricted, with just 
one surviving genus and 11 species, to a few refuges in Southeast Asia. During the last decades of phylogenetic 
reconstructions, tarsiers have ''jumped'' from one phylogenetic branch to another (Figure 1): once to split off 
from primates before the Anthropoidea-Strepsirrhini split (tarsier-first hypothesis 1,2 ), then close to strepsirrhines 
in the Prosimii clade (prosimian monophyly hypothesis 3,4 ), then in the immediate vicinity of monkeys and apes 
(haplorrhine hypothesis 5-7 ), or to land in an unresolvable trichotomy of strepsirrhines, tarsiers, and anthropoids 8 . 
These different positions on the evolutionary tree span a phylogenetic era of some 20 million years. With more 
recent large-scale sequencing efforts, it seemed to be over with such ''great leaps''. Compelling support fixed 
tarsiers on a common branch with strepsirrhines in a joined group of prosimians 9 . While this study, based on 
more than 10 kb of sequence information, provided one of the most important and influential mammalian 
phylogenies, subsequent data would show that it failed significantly in this particular part of the primate tree. 
The reason was rather simple and was later revealed after sequencing of the mitochondrial genome of Tarsius 
bancanus 10 (a species recently renamed Cephalopachus bancanus 4 ); the nucleotide composition of mitochondrial 
genes changed drastically on the lineage leading to anthropoids from high AT to a significant accumulation of GC 
nucleotides. Consequently, most mitochondrial phylogenies of primates artificially formed the clade Prosimii, 
based on their shared high mitochondrial AT nucleotide content, apart from the GC-rich genes of higher 
primates. The mixed nuclear/mitochondrial sequence data used in the Murphy et al. 9 study, yielded the same 
problematic results because the major nuclear dataset contributed only weak phylogenetic signals to counter the 
strong mitochondrial noise. At that time most molecular evolutionists confirmed the significant mitochondrial 
grouping of strepsirrhines and tarsiers (i.e., the prosimian monophyly hypothesis). Molecular geneticists 
attempted to improve the sequence-based phylogenetic reconstruction methods to compensate for artificial </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>PHYLOGENETICS </p>

<p>EVOLUTIONARY BIOLOGY </p>

<p>BIOINFORMATICS </p>

<p>PHYLOGENY </p>

<p>sequence effects. As reviewed in Goodman et al. 11 , sequence-based 
evidence for the position of tarsiers was still ambiguous, and mito-
chondrial supermatrix approaches continued to group tarsiers with 
strepsirrhines 3 . However, the hitherto largest comparative genomic 
analysis of primate species, involving 186 representatives and about 
8 MB of sequence, found some support for the Haplorrhini clade 
(haplorrhine hypothesis 12 ). Furthermore, a recent analysis of geno-
mic data provided statistically significant data to reject a prosimian 
monophyly 13 . The currently popular coalescence-based genome ana-
lysis method also supports the Haplorrhini clade 14,15 . Zietkiewicz et 
al. 16 compared Alu element sequences derived from strepsirrhines, 
tarsiers, and human genomes and found that tarsier elements cluster 
with human Alu subfamilies and show RNA secondary structure 
elements absent in strepsirrhines; however, this sequence similarity </p>

<p>analysis of Alu elements is not quite as reliable as the highly inform-
ative content of retroposon presence/absence analyses. 
Screening for phylogenetic diagnostic insertions of shared ortho-
logous retroposons enabled an escape from this conflicting phylogen-
etic trap. Four Alu short interspersed elements (SINEs) supported a 
close relationship between tarsiers and anthropoids (haplorrhine 
hypothesis 7,17 ). Independent of nucleotide composition effects, evolu-
tionary rate variation, saturation of substitutions, etc., the comparison 
of orthologous insertions of retroposed elements provides a noise-free 
evaluation of phylogenetic affiliations. An exactly shared retroposon 
insertion is characterized by specific target site duplications (TSD) of 
5-30 nucleotides flanking the insertion site produced during the 
insertion process 18 . Similar shared TSDs together with an identical 
retroposon with the identical length and identical orientation in two </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Three competing hypotheses of tarsier phylogeny. Hypothesis #1, tarsiers as the first divergence of the primate tree, with Strepsirrhini and </p>

<p>Anthropoidea on the same branch, hypothesis #2, tarsiers close to strepsirrhines, together forming the Prosimii clade, and hypothesis #3, tarsiers closely 
related to Anthropoidea in the Haplorhini clade. The images are provided by  n Baldur . </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1756 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01756 </p>

<p>
species strongly indicates an insertion event in their common 
ancestor, and thus their close relatedness; conversely, an empty inser-
tion site in one or the other indicates more distantly related species. 
The quantitative genome-wide distribution of certain primate-
specific Alu SINE elements also supported the haplorrhini hypo-
thesis. Churakov et al. 19 found hundred thousand AluJb elements 
well distributed in the genomes of tarsiers and anthropoids but 
absent in strepsirrhines. 
However, our initial search for diagnostic retroposon insertions 7 
was biased by screening only from the human genome, the only 
genomic source available at the time, thus making it impossible to 
test all three hypotheses equally. Therefore, combined with the inher-
ent problems associated with even the most modern sequence-based 
reconstructions, the placement of tarsiers was still uncertain. 
Alu SINEs, long interspersed elements (LINEs), and long terminal 
repeats (LTRs) are exceptionally suitable as phylogenetic markers in 
primates because of the high number of insertions (e.g., 1.5 million 
Alu insertions in human 20 ) and their broad activity covering the full 
diversity of primates. This makes them unrivaled as phylogenetic 
markers compared to other rare genomic changes in primates. </p>

<p>The present genome-wide approach aimed to screen for diagnostic 
retroposons starting from different sources of genome information, 
including genomes of mouse lemurs, bushbabies, tarsiers, and human, 
to present the first genome-wide, multi-genome screening to find 
perfect phylogenetically informative Alu SINEs, LINEs, and LTRs 
among all these lineages, and thereby definitively test all three possible 
hypotheses of tarsier origin using a virtually homoplasy-free approach. </p>

<p>Results 
In an initial run of our <rs type="software">PERL</rs> pipeline for the three search strategies 
described above, we identified genome-wide a total of 260 prelim-
inary informative Alu and Alu-like loci, 200 preliminary LINE loci, 
and 120 preliminary LTR loci. All of these loci were then subjected to 
careful manual inspections of the insertion sites, looking for only 
those with exact orthologous insertions according to the criteria 
explained below. Only 19 Alu-like, 22 LINE, and 63 LTR loci with 
retroposed elements present in both tarsier 1 human fulfilled these 
criteria (Supplementary Information; Figure 2); none were found 
with shared elements in either strepsirrhines 1 human or tarsier 
1 strepsirrhines. The diagnostic elements active at the time of the </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Genome-wide consolidation of Haplorrhini. Nineteen genomic Alu SINE insertions, 22 LINEs, and 63 LTR elements provide overwhelming </p>

<p>evidence in support of the close relationship of tarsiers to anthropoids. The images are provided by  n Baldur . </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1756 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01756 </p>

<p>
common ancestor of tarsiers and anthropoids were fossil Alu mono-
mers (2 FAMs), free left Alu monomers (12 FLAMs), Alu dimers (2 
AluJb, 3 AluSx), LINEs (22 L1PB4), and LTRs (62 MSTB; 1 MSTC) 
(Supplementary Information). According to the Waddell statistics 21 , 
with 104 conflict-free phylogenetic informative markers for haplor-
rhine the probability of supporting the wrong tree topology is less 
than 7.2 3 10 250 . Thus, tarsiers are clearly the closest relatives of 
higher primates. 
When using retroposons as phylogenetic markers, it is important 
to note the absolute necessity of applying a strict definition of orthol-
ogy, including a careful inspection of the lengths and locations of the 
TSDs and a reliable definition of the type of insertion. This requires 
improved manual alignments and knowledge of the genomic 
changes introduced during the retroposon insertion process. 
Interestingly, none of the previously identified retroposons support-
ing the haplorrhine hypothesis 7,17 were among the 104 new elements, 
as the present genome-wide search was focused on perfect insertions 
only. Diagnostic Alu, LINE, and LTR elements were selected only if 
flanked by nearly perfect TSDs (maximum 30% divergence for Alu </p>

<p>and LINE, 40% for LTR, from the solitary target site of reference 
species with absent state) and clear absence in both strepsirrhines 
and outgroup species. Furthermore, only orthologous elements with 
more than 70% sequence similarity were considered. Two of the 
previously identified haplorrhine markers were located in sequence 
regions not represented in the current low-coverage 2X-based assem-
blies of human/tarsier and human/strepsirrhines. The third marker 
was located in a region subsequently identified to be a misaligned 
part of the genome alignment, and one marker exhibited more than 
30% divergence between human and tarsier. </p>

<p>Discussion 
In our current dataset, we did not find any conflicting retroposon 
presence/absence patterns, indicating that at the time of the diver-
gence of haplorrhines most or all retroposons were fixed and are thus 
well suited for phylogenetic reconstructions and clearly do not 
support a trifurcation as some previous data might have suggested 8 . 
Such a clear and conflict-free pattern is not always evident from 
retroposon data. Ancestral polymorphisms of retroposons and </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Screening strategy to find genome-wide, phylogenetically informative, Alu SINE insertion markers using genome sequences and pairwise </p>

<p>genome alignments. (A) Pairwise genome alignment of human and bushbaby. Locus with a gap of 287 nt (insertion in human). Coordinates are 
abbreviated: human chromosome 2, 4728 5 227644728, 4827 5 227644827, 5114 5 227645114, 5219 5 227645219; bushbaby scaffold identifier GL873532 
in reverse complement (rc) orientation, 8385 5 6388385, 8296 5 6388296, 8295 5 6388295, 8220 5 6388220. (B) The insertion is represented by the 
integration of an Alu SINE element. (C) Corresponding region of the human alignment with tarsier. The Alu element is present in human and tarsier. 
(D) MULTIZ alignment from the UCSC server. The Alu element is present in human and in tarsiers but not in strepsirrhines. (e) The MULTIZ alignment is 
transferred to a Fasta alignment using the UCSC2FASTA java application. The Fasta file is the basis for manual crosscheck. In analyzing gap positions, a 
variation of 1/230 nts is allowed. We used the UCSC axt alignment format. TSD 5 target site duplications. The retroposon sequence is only partially 
shown interrupted by a double-slash. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1756 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01756 </p>

<p>
subsequent speciation before fixation may lead to conflicting signals 
of relationships, as was previously demonstrated for the three main 
lineages of placental mammals (Afrotheria, Xenarthra, Boreothe-
ria) 22,23 . Although such examples of conflicting retroposon patterns 
are rare, they are invaluable for diagnosing zones of incomplete 
lineage sorting or ancestral hybridization effects that influence the 
evolutionary patterns of species. 
In contrast to the highly significant support afforded by the 104 
new genome-wide-extracted, conflict-free haplorrhine retroposon 
markers, the ,50 million years of nuclear sequence evolution and 
possibly the extremely reduced number of tarsier individuals led to 
the fixation of much random noise, causing the previous problems to 
determine the correct tree based on these data. 
Our analysis now provides overwhelming, conflict-free support at 
the genome-wide level for the haplorrhine hypothesis and a clear 
rejection of both the prosimian monophyly and tarsier-first hypo-
theses, as suggested by previous data 7,14-19 . The previous retroposon 
insertion data supporting the Haplorrhini hypothesis 7 was likely 
biased by screening only human genome data and a clear rejection 
of the prosimian monophyly and tarsiers-first hypotheses were lack-
ing; both of these limitations have now been overcome. Many 
molecular sequence studies demonstrated support for the prosimian 
monophyly based on data that appeared to be significant 3,9,24,25 but 
were likely artificial signals connected to the dominance of mito-
chondrial data 10 . The strong but artificial mitochondrial noise and 
missing nuclear signals challenged the use of sequence data in certain 
mammalian branches. A similar example of an extreme misinter-
pretation based on mitochondrial DNA was the artificial placement 
of the order Dermoptera amidst the primate phylogenetic tree 9,24,26 , 
suggesting that primates were paraphyletic. 
Ten years later with the use of genome-scale data, special recon-
struction methods involving coalescence models have also correctly 
placed tarsiers at their natural phylogenetic branch close to 
Anthropoidea 14,15 . Also, increasingly dense fossil records bolster 
our current picture of the Paleogene fauna 27 and will be strengthened 
by the highly significant evidence in favor of the haplorrhine hypo-
thesis. This will, in turn, provide a strong base for addressing the 
anthropoid origin, with tarsiers as the ''link'' between basal primates 
and humans. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>To test all three possible hypotheses, we used tarsier (Tarsius syrichta recently 
renamed Carlito syrichta 4 ), two representatives of the Strepsirrhini lineage, mouse 
lemur (Microcebus murinus) and bushbaby (Otolemur garnetti), and human as rep-
resentative of anthropoids. 
To perform a multi-genome screening, we retrieved the following genomes, all 
covered by 23 genome sequences: 
Tarsius syrichta (tarSyr1) 28 ; 
Microcebus murinus (micMur1) 29 ; 
Otolemur garnetti (otoGar3) 30 . 
To find diagnostic insertions we used a combination of pairwise (2-way) align-
ments from the UCSC Genome Bioinformatics center in Santa Cruz: 
Human/tarsier (tarSyr1) 31 ; 
Human/mouse lemur (micMur1) 32 ; 
Human/bushbaby (otoGar1) 33 . </p>

<p>Data mining. Our search strategies were designed to accomplish two concrete 
objectives: 1) a genome-wide screening and detection of perfect, phylogenetically 
informative retroposons for the phylogenetic position of tarsiers, and 2) multi-
genome screenings that consider all three possible phylogenetic tree topologies 
equally: (1) tarsiers as the first split of primates (strepsirrhines 1 human), (2) tarsiers 
on a shared branch with strepsirrhines (tarsiers 1 strepsirrhines), (3) tarsiers together 
with anthropoids (tarsiers 1 human). </p>

<p>Screening for potential markers: tarsier 1 human, strepsirrhines 1 human. To test 
the haplorrhine hypothesis, we developed bioinformatics tools (a) to screen available 
pairwise alignments of human/mouse lemur and human/bushbaby for Alu SINE 
elements, LINEs (L1Ps), and LTRs (MSTs), present in human but absent in both 
strepsirrhine species (Figure 3a). Such pairwise or 2-way alignments were organized in 
'axt alignment format' (compiling alignment blocks with genomic coordinates for both 
the primary organism (first sequence) and aligning organism (second sequence)) 34 . 
Alignment gaps (e.g., caused by an insertion of an Alu SINE, LINE, or LTR element in </p>

<p>the genome of one species) were recognized by interrupted coordinates (Figure 3a; e.g., 
human coordinates chromosome 2_227644827-227645114 (287 nt insert) vs. 
bushbaby coordinates of GL873532 (reverse complement) 6388296, 6388295 (no 
insert). (b) We compared the coordinates of the extracted locus with the coordinates of 
the previously RepeatMasked human genome to detect loci with specific retroposon 
insertions absent in strepsirrhines (Figure 3b). (c) We inspected the pairwise alignment 
of human/tarsier at the selected human coordinates (Figure 3c; e.g., human 
coordinates on chromosome 2_227644728-227645219). (d) We used the human 
coordinates to extract orthologous MULTIZ sequences from the UCSC Genome 
server 35 (Figure 3d). We extracted the resulting concatenated sequence blocks in 
FASTA format using a new java application (Figure 3e; UCSC2FASTA; available upon 
request). We manually realigned and analyzed the sequences, especially the insertion 
site of the diagnostic retroposed elements that were shared between human and tarsier 
but absent in both strepsirrhines. 
To test the hypothesis that tarsiers diverged early from primates (tarsier-first 
hypothesis), we used a similar approach to search for potential markers merging 
human and strepsirrhines starting from a 2-way alignment of human/tarsier and 
searching for retroposons specific for human. Such loci were projected/compared to a 
second and third 2-way alignment of human/bushbaby and human/mouse lemur. 
Loci with elements present in human, present in strepsirrhine, but absent in tarsier 
were extracted for closer inspection. Again, the complete loci were extracted via the 
UCSC MULTIZ alignment by querying the human coordinates and settings. </p>

<p>Screening for potential markers: tarsier 1 strepsirrhines. To test the third potential 
hypothesis (prosimian monophyly hypothesis), with tarsiers and strepsirrhines on 
one branch, we applied a slightly different strategy because tarsier/strepsirrhine 
pairwise alignments are not yet available. For this search we (a) started with a 2-way 
alignment of human/bushbaby and human/mouse lemur and derived all loci with a 
gap of 100-400 nt in human and an orthologous Alu SINE, LINE, or LTR insertion in 
strepsirrhines. (b) The pairwise alignment of human/tarsier was correspondingly 
screened for Alu SINE, LINE, and LTR insertions in tarsier. (c) We analyzed the two 
sets of selected alignments for overlapping coordinates in human. (d) We extracted 
and merged all corresponding sequences. (e) Loci with elements present in both 
tarsier and strepsirrhines but absent in human and an insertion sequence similarity of 
more than 70% were manually inspected. With this screening we examined the 
potential shared evolution of tarsiers and strepsirrhines. </p>

<p>Derived computer pipelines for automated screening. To automatize the search for 
phylogenetically informative markers, we developed a PERL pipeline connected to a 
MySQL database (available upon request). The search criteria were (1) expected 
minimum size of element 5 50 nt, (2) expected maximum size of element 5 6,000 nt, 
(3) selected 'search for retroposons', (4) pairwise distance cut off 5 30% (more than 
70% similarity) (5) gap expansion 1/-30 nt, (6) extracted length of flanks 5 100 nt. 
(7) Only loci in which sequences of both mouse lemur and bushbaby were available, 
well alignable, free from large deletions around the insertion site, and both with the 
same presence/absence state of the inserted element. </p>

<p>Manual alignment editing. We selected only cases with nearly perfect TSDs for Alu-
like elements and LINEs (maximal 30% divergence from the solitary target site of 
reference species with absent state, considering the classical TSD length of 8-30 nt), 
and if available, identical truncation points in the shared orthologous markers. 
Because LTR elements have only very short TSDs of ,5 nt, we selected cases with 
maximally 40% divergence between TSDs and the solitary target sites. All Alignments 
are available as Supplementary Information. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
Acknowledegments </p>

<p>We thank Norbert Grundman for assistance in programming, Marsha Bundman for editing 
the manuscript, and  Baldur  for providing the paintings. We very much thank 
Joachim Kurtz and the  Graduate School of Evolution initiative (MGSEi) for 
providing initial financial support for the PhD position of GH. We thank Christian Roos 
and Mike Montague for valuable comments on an early version of the manuscript. This 
paper is dedicated to the memory of Johanna Solbach, who co-organized the MGSE 
Symposium 2012, where these results were first presented. This work was supported by the 
Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (SCHM1469/3-2; SCHM1469/4-1). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>J.S., G.C., and G.H. designed the study, developed the screening strategy and analyzed the 
data. G.H. performed the bioinformatic screenings of Alus in WMs group, G.C. screened for 
informative LINEs and LTRs. W.W. contributed special access to genome data. W.M., J.B. 
and W.W. discussed the results. J.S. wrote the manuscript and all authors contributed their 
comments. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Hartig, G. et al. Retrophylogenomics Place Tarsiers on the 
Evolutionary Branch of Anthropoids. Sci. Rep. 3, 1756; DOI:10.1038/srep01756 (2013). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1756 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01756 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>