<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3960616" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-03-25T11:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: A significant proportion of squamous cell carcinomas of the oropharynx (OP-SCC) are related to human 
papillomavirus (HPV) infection and p16 overexpression. This subgroup proves better prognosis and survival but no evidence exists 
on the correlation between HPV and p16 overexpression based on diagnostic measures and definition of p16 overexpression. 
We evaluated means of p16 and HPV diagnostics, and quantified overexpression of p16 in HPV-positive and -negative OP-SCCs 
by mode of immunohistochemical staining of carcinoma cells. </p>

<p>Methods: PubMed, Embase, and the Cochrane Library were searched from 1980 until October 2012. We applied the following 
inclusion criteria: a minimum of 20 cases of site-specific OP-SCCs, and HPV and p16 results present. Studies were categorised into 
three groups based on their definition of p16 overexpression: verbal definition, nuclear and cytoplasmatic staining between 5 and 
69%, and X70% staining. </p>

<p>Results: We identified 39 studies with available outcome data (n ¼ 3926): 22 studies (n ¼ 1980) used PCR, 6 studies (n ¼ 688) used 
ISH, and 11 studies (n ¼ 1258) used both PCR and ISH for HPV diagnostics. The methods showed similar HPV-positive results. 
Overall, 52.5% of the cases (n ¼ 2062) were HPV positive. As to p16 overexpression, 17 studies (n ¼ 1684) used a minimum of 5-69% 
staining, and 7 studies (n ¼ 764) used X70% staining. Fifteen studies (n ¼ 1478) referred to a verbal definition. Studies showed high 
heterogeneity in diagnostics of HPV and definition of p16. The correlation between HPV positivity and p16 overexpression proved 
best numerically in the group applying X70% staining for p16 overexpression. The group with verbal definitions had a significantly 
lower false-positive rate, but along with the group applying 5-69% staining showed a worse sensitivity compared with </p>

<p>X70% staining. </p>

<p>Conclusions: There are substantial differences in how studies diagnose HPV and define p16 overexpression. Numerically, p16 staining 
is better to predict the presence of HPV (i.e. larger sensitivity), when the cutoff is set at X70% of cytoplasmatic and nuclear staining. </p>

<p>Oral and pharyngeal cancers are the sixth most frequent tumour 
with over 482 000 new cases and 273 000 deaths worldwide in 2008 
(Ferlay et al, 2010). The role of high-risk human papillomavirus </p>

<p>(HR-HPV) in the carcinogenesis of the uterine cervix is well 
recognised (Bosch et al, 1995), and owing to numerous studies in 
the past 10 years, HR-HPV is now also a well-known risk factor in </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr C Grønhøj Larsen; E-mail: c.gronhoj@gmail.com </p>

<p>Received 27 August 2013; revised 17 December 2013; accepted 7 January 2014; published online 11 February 2014 </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/14 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: p16; hpv; oropharyngeal tumours; head and neck tumours; human papillomavirus; p16ink4a </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2014) 110, 1587-1594 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>

<p>
oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinomas (OPSCCs) in addition to 
established factors such as tobacco and alcohol exposure 
(Dayyani et al, 2010). Compared with other head and neck 
squamous cell carcinomas (HNSCCs), HPV-related OPSCCs 
have different epidemiology, histopathological characteristics, 
therapeutic response, and clinical outcome (Shah and Patel, 2003; 
Fakhry and Gillison, 2006; De Vita et al, 2008; Robinson et al, 
2010; Westra, 2012). 
The small, non-enveloped, DNA virus HPV belongs to the 
Papillomaviridae family and is known commonly to infect 
squamous epithelial cells (Doorbar et al, 2012). Cell morphology 
alone is insufficient to determine the presence of HPV (Lewis et al, 
2012), although HPV-positive oropharyngeal cancers are often 
characterised histologically by a non-keratinising or basaloid 
morphologic pattern. Two techniques are generally used to 
diagnose HPV: polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and in situ 
hybridisation (ISH). Both have strengths and limitations. Human 
papillomavirus-specific PCR is not routinely available in most 
diagnostic laboratories; few HPV PCR tests are approved for 
clinical use, and the method requires a high level of technical skills 
and special laboratory facilities to prevent contamination. When 
applied to extracts made from fresh-frozen biopsy samples, the 
highest sensitivity is obtained, but the PCR analysis does not 
distinguish the mere presence of HPV from a clinically relevant 
HPV infection, where the HPV genome is often integrated into the 
host genome and actively transcribes HPV oncoproteins. Detection 
of HPV with ISH provides evidence of viral genomes through 
mRNA or DNA present in the tumour nuclei and is highly specific, 
although less sensitive than PCR (Robinson et al, 2010). 
This method does not differentiate between integrated and non-
integrated genomes. 
The presence of HR-HPV DNA is insufficient to classify 
accurately tumours as an HPV infection as it may be biologically 
inactive and not the cause of malignancy. Along with HPV 
diagnostics, immunohistochemical detection of p16 (p16-IHC) is 
often used as a surrogate marker for HPV infection and an activity 
of viral oncoproteins. P16 is a tumour suppressor gene that inhibits 
cyclin-dependent kinase 4A. In the presence of transcriptionally 
active HPV, hypophosphorylated retinoblastoma protein (pRb) 
bind to the HPV oncoprotein E7, allowing the transcriptional 
activator E2F to be constitutionally active while effectively stopping 
the negative feedback of free pRb on p16. Overexpression of 
p16 ensues. Independent of treatment modality, OPSCC patients 
with p16 overexpression have better prognosis and clinical 
outcome (Langendijk and Psyrri, 2010). P16-IHC is generally 
accessible and its technical costs are estimated to be 2-16 times 
lower than other HPV-specific tests (Lewis, 2012). Several studies 
have reported difficulties in HPV and p16 diagnostics, as there is 
no consensus on defining overexpression of p16 by a clear 
percentage cutoff level, and definitions vary from X5%, X75% to 
numerous less specific verbal definitions, for example, 'diffuse and 
strong nuclear and cytoplasmatic staining' (Smeets et al, 2007; 
Lewis, 2012). This may be problematic because different staining 
patterns can correlate differently to HPV-positive and -negative 
tumours, and staining patterns may ultimately distinguish 
transcriptionally from non-transcriptionally active HPV infections 
and thereby help determine prognosis and clinical outcomes. 
The aim of this systematic review was to define and categorise 
overexpression of p16 based on immunohistochemical staining and 
correlate the categories to HPV-positive and -negative OP-SCCs. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Search strategy and selection criteria. One author (CGL) 
undertook electronic literature searches within PubMed (Medline), </p>

<p>Embase, and the Cochrane Library. The search strategy 
was as follows including MESH terms and keywords: 'HPV' or 
'papillomavirus' or 'papillomaviridae' and 'p16' or 'cdkn2a' or 
'cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p16' or 'p16 genes' and 
'oropharynx' or 'oropharyngeal' or 'palatine tonsil' or 'tonsil' or 
'palatine' or 'tongue' or 'mouth' or 'oral'. Two authors (CGL and 
MG) independently reviewed the relevance of all resulting study 
titles and abstracts identified through the above search, and full-
text copies of potentially eligible articles were assessed. Finally, one 
author (CGL) reviewed reference lists of the initially included 
studies. Studies with identical authors were contacted to avoid 
including the same study population twice. 
We included all studies published in English from January 1980 
to October 2012 regardless of funding source. The inclusion 
criteria were restricted to: age above 18 years, a minimum 20 cases 
of site-specific OP-SCCs (morphologic variants were included), 
and HPV and p16 results stated. </p>

<p>Data synthesis. Two authors (CGL and MG) independently 
extracted relevant data from the included studies and entered 
them into a piloted data extraction form. The following 
information were recorded: country, year(s) of biopsy collection, 
demographics, number of cases, tumour site (base of tongue, 
palatine tonsils, or other), tumour morphology (keratinising, non-
keratinising, or mixed), histopathological grade (carcinoma in situ, 
poor, moderate, or high differentiation), IHC staining probe, 
definition of p16 overexpression, biopsy preservation (fresh frozen 
or paraffin embedded), IHC evaluation by pathologists (yes or no), 
HPV results (negative or HPV-16, HPV-18, HPV-33, HPV-35, and 
HPV-58 positive), HPV diagnostics (HPV DNA PCR, HPV DNA 
ISH, and HPV DNA ISH followed by PCR, HPV RNA RT-PCR, 
and HPV RNA ISH), and the number of p16-positive and negative 
cases. 
Included studies were categorised into three groups by their 
definition of p16 overexpression: (a) a verbal definition (e.g. 'Cases 
were classified in a binary manner as either positive (any cells with 
nuclear and cytoplasmatic staining) or negative'), (b) 5-69% 
nuclear and cytoplasmatic staining, and (c) X70% staining. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Statistics were carried out using IBM SPSS 
Statistics 19.0 (IBM SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Descriptive statistics 
are presented as actual numbers and percentages, or median and 
range where appropriate. We conducted a meta-analysis using the 
bivariate model (Reitsma et al, 2005). In the bivariate model, the 
logit-transformed sensitivities and specificities and the correlation 
between them across studies are modelled directly. The model 
accounts for sampling variability within studies and also account 
for between-study variability through the inclusion of random 
effects. In the preliminary meta-analyses for each definition of p16 
positivity, we fitted the bivariate model separately for each test, and 
obtained a diagnostic odds ratio, sensitivity, and specificity. 
Hierarchical summary receiver-operator curve (HSROC) was 
applied in the meta-analysis and is recommended in the current 
meta-analytic literature for diagnostic meta-analyses (Leeflang 
et al, 2013). In addition, HSROCs were plotted with 95% CI. 
Afterwards, we compared the tests in two separate models, where 
the definitions used were included as covariates in a meta-
regression. Variance components were estimated by restricted 
maximum likelihood, because of the number of studies and the 
heterogeneity of the included studies. Statistical analyses on meta-
regression were performed in R using the <rs type="software">mada</rs> package function 
reitsma. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The initial literature search yielded a total of 778 records. From 
these, we manually selected 160 articles for full-text assessment, </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
HPV and p16 oropharyngeal tumours </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>

<p>of which 112 articles were later excluded. Accordingly, 48 studies 
were left eligible for inclusion (Figure 1). Additional three studies 
were later identified through searching reference lists. Studies with 
identical authors were contacted and resolved in 12 studies 
excluded; 11 studies were confirmed duplicates by authors; and one 
study excluded without reply from authors. Thus, a total of 39 
studies (n ¼ 3926) were included in the review (Table 1). 
In the pooled analysis of all studies with demographic 
information (n ¼ 3625), the majority of patients were male subjects 
(n ¼ 2921, 80.6%). Age ranged from 20 to 93 years with a median 
of 58 years. Thirty-four studies (n ¼ 3420 subjects) were European, 
Australian, or US based, and five studies (n ¼ 506 subjects) were 
Asian. Ethnicity was reported in 22 studies (n ¼ 2265), with 69.2% 
of these patients being Caucasian (n ¼ 1568), 11.9% (n ¼ 269) were 
of Asian origin, and 18.9% (n ¼ 428) had mixed ethnicity. 
Tumours were represented throughout the oropharynx, but were 
primarily located in the palatine tonsils (n ¼ 1420, 36.2%). 
Tumours at the base of the tongue (n ¼ 414, 10.5 %) and of 
unspecified location represent the remaining (n ¼ 2092, 53.3%) 
(Table 2). 
A total of 52.5% cases (n ¼ 2062) were found HPV positive by 
PCR, ISH, or both. For HPV diagnostics, 22 studies (n ¼ 1980) 
used PCR, 6 studies (n ¼ 668) used ISH, and 11 studies (n ¼ 1258) 
used both techniques. In the PCR-based HPV-testing group, 49.6% 
(n ¼ 984) of cases were said to be positive and 59.8% of cases 
(n ¼ 412) were positive in the ISH group, whereas 52.9% (n ¼ 666) 
were positive when both diagnostic approaches were used. The 
definition of p16 overexpression varied, but all studies dichoto-
mised the results to either negative or positive. In the pooled 
analysis, p16 overexpression was shown by 37.6% (n ¼ 1478) 
of subjects based on a verbal definition, by 42.9% (n ¼ 1684) of 
subjects based on staining between 5 and 69%, and finally, by 
19.5% (n ¼ 764) of subjects based on staining equal to or exceeding 
70% (Table 2). 
Centres placed in the United States defined p16 as positive when 
staining was between 5 and 69% (6 centres, n ¼ 770) or based on 
staining equal to or exceeding 70% (4 centres, n ¼ 482). Six centres 
(n ¼ 507) used a verbal definition. European centres either defined 
p16 as positive when staining was between 5 and 69% (9 centres, 
n ¼ 602) or based on staining exceeding 70% (3 centres, n ¼ 282). </p>

<p>Four centres (n ¼ 562) used a verbal definition. Three centres 
(n ¼ 194) in Asia used a verbal definition, and two centres 
(n ¼ 312) defined p16 as positive when staining was between 5 and 
69%. No Asian centres defined p16 as positive based on staining 
equal to or exceeding 70%. 
Eleven studies (n ¼ 861) reported data on histopathologic grade 
(poorly differentiated, moderate differentiated, highly differentiated, 
or carcinoma in situ), and six studies (n ¼ 634) reported status on 
tumour morphology (keratinising, non-keratinising, mixed, or 
unknown). The limited availability of data on tumour morphology 
did not allow us to examine systematically to what degree the non-
keratinising tumours were related to the presence of HPV, as has 
been observed previously. We found no trends regarding publication 
year and definition of p16, likely owing to the fact that the included 
studies were all published in the past 10 years. 
Twenty-five studies (n ¼ 2888) provided sufficient information 
to construct a two-by-two table of both p16-negative/-positive and 
HPV-negative/-positive biopsies. The correlation between HPV 
and p16 overexpression was numerically greater, when positivity 
was defined as staining above X70% with a sensitivity of 
0.927 (95% CI: 0.793-0.974). The verbal group and 45-o70% 
group had a sensitivity of 0.791 (95% CI: 0.608-0.888) and 
0.894 (95% CI: 0.805-0.942), respectively. The false-positive 
rate of 0.059 (95% CI: 0.031-0.112) for the verbal group was 
superior to the rate of 0.201 (95% Cl: 0.12-0.337) of p16 X70% 
(see Figure 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This is the first systematic review exploring the correlation between 
HPV infection and p16 overexpression in OPSCCs. This review 
shows that p16 overexpression correlates numerically better to 
HPV results if staining of tumour cells exceeds 70% rather than 
lower percentages or positivity based on a verbal definition. The 
issue of determining a specific cutoff value for p16 positivity has 
earlier been addressed in smaller samples supporting staining 
above 75% or staining above 50% combined with 425% confluent 
areas to define p16 positivity (Begum and Westra, 2008). We found </p>

<p>Records identified through 
database searching 
(n = 778) </p>

<p>Records excluded 
(n = 618) </p>

<p>Full-text articles 
assessed for eligibility 
(n = 160) </p>

<p>Studies included in the 
analysis 
(n = 39) </p>

<p>Records excluded 
(n = 124) </p>

<p>Additional articles identified 
from reference lists 
(n = 3) </p>

<p>Figure 1. PRISMA diagram. </p>

<p>HPV and p16 oropharyngeal tumours 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>

<p>
Table 1. Overview of studies </p>

<p>Author (year) </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>Year 
Study years </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>Age 
(years) </p>

<p>M/F </p>

<p>HPV 
þ Analysis P16 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>P16 
cutoff (%) 
P16 antibody </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>of p16 (%) </p>

<p>Specificity </p>

<p>of p16 (%) </p>

<p>Al-Swiahb et al </p>

<p>(2010) </p>

<p>Taiwan </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>1992-2008 </p>

<p>220 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>206/14 </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>X5% </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
Clone unknown (Neomarkers, Fremont, 
CA, USA) </p>

<p>86 </p>

<p>99 </p>

<p>Ang et al (2010b) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>2002-2005 
323 Unknown </p>

<p>271/52 </p>

<p>206 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>214 </p>

<p>X70 
E6H4 (MTM Laboratories AG, 
Heidelberg, Germany) </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>Charfi et al (2008) </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>2007 </p>

<p>1987-2005 </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>61 </p>

<p>36/16 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
E6H4 (MTM Laboratories AG, 
Heidelberg, Germany) </p>

<p>84 </p>

<p>59 </p>

<p>Chenevert and 
Chiosea (2012) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2012 
1956-1969 and 
2007-2009 </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>80/17 </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>X70 
G175-405 (BD Pharmingen, San Diego, </p>

<p>CA, USA) </p>

<p>69 (second 
period: 86%) </p>

<p>80 (second 
period: 90%) </p>

<p>El-Mofty and Patil 
(2006) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2006 </p>

<p>Unknown 
20 Unknown Unknown </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>11 
Verbal definition Clone unknown (Novacastra Labs Ltd, </p>

<p>Newcastle, UK </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>El-Mofty et al 
(2008) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2008 </p>

<p>Unknown 
32 Unknown </p>

<p>28/4 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>X70 
Clone unknown (Novacastra Labs Ltd, 
Newcastle, UK) </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Evans et al (2011) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>2000-2007 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>25/5 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>X70 
JC8 (Lab Vision, Fisher Scientific, 
Pittsburgh, PA, USA) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Farshadpour et al </p>

<p>(2011) </p>

<p>The 
Netherlands </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>1980-2004 
32 Unknown Unknown </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>X70 
Clone unknown (Neomarkers, Fremont, 
CA, USA) </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Friedland et al 
(2012) </p>

<p>Australia </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>1996-2008 
20 Unknown Unknown </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>19 
Verbal definition Clone unknown (Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA, USA) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Gao et al (2013) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>1997-2006 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>136/14 </p>

<p>122 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
E6H4 (MTM Laboratories AG, 
Heidelberg, Germany) </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Hafkamp et al 
(2008) </p>

<p>The 
Netherlands </p>

<p>2008 </p>

<p>1992-2001 </p>

<p>81 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>59/22 </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
E6H4 (Dako, Glostrup, Denmark) </p>

<p>86 </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>Hoffmann et al </p>

<p>(2012) </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>2004-2009 
20 Unknown </p>

<p>16/4 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
CINtecÒ (MTM Laboratories AG, 
Heidelberg, Germany </p>

<p>79 </p>

<p>83 </p>

<p>Holzinger et al </p>

<p>(2012) </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>1990-2008 </p>

<p>196 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>146/50 </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>54 
Verbal definition E6H4 (MTM Laboratories AG, </p>

<p>Heidelberg, Germany) </p>

<p>78 </p>

<p>59 </p>

<p>Hong et al (2010) </p>

<p>Australia </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>1987-2006 </p>

<p>195 </p>

<p>59 </p>

<p>159/36 </p>

<p>83 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>65 
Verbal definition JC2 (Neomarkers, Fremont, CA, USA) </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>84 </p>

<p>Junor et al (2012) </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>2012 
1999-2001 and 
2003-2005 </p>

<p>254 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>182/72 </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>94 
Verbal definition E6H4 (MTM Laboratories, Heidelberg, </p>

<p>Germany) </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>Kim et al (2007) </p>

<p>South Korea 2007 </p>

<p>1995-2005 
52 Unknown Unknown </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>37 
Verbal definition Unknown </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Klussmann et al </p>

<p>(2009) </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>2009 </p>

<p>1997-2005 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>47/13 </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>33/57 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
16P04 (Neomarkers, Fremont, CA, USA) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Kuo et al (2008) </p>

<p>Taiwan </p>

<p>2008 </p>

<p>1997-2005 </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>79/13 </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
JC8 (Neomarkers, Fremont, CA, USA ) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Laco et al (2011) </p>

<p>Crech 
Republic </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>2000-2009 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>13/9 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>22 
Verbal definition CINtec (MTM Laboratories AG, </p>

<p>Heidelberg, Germany) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Lewis et al (2010) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>1997-2008 </p>

<p>239 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>211/28 </p>

<p>144 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>187 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
Clone unknown (MTM Laboratories AG, 
Heidelberg, Germany) </p>

<p>74 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>Li et al (2007) </p>

<p>China </p>

<p>2007 </p>

<p>1985-2004 </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>37/12 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>11 
Verbal definition 16p04 (Neomarkers, Fremont, CA, USA ) </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
HPV and p16 oropharyngeal tumours </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>

<p>Table 1. ( Continued ) </p>

<p>Author (year) </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>Year 
Study years </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>Age 
(years) </p>

<p>M/F </p>

<p>HPV 
þ Analysis P16 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>P16 
cutoff (%) 
P16 antibody </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>of p16 (%) </p>

<p>Specificity </p>

<p>of p16 (%) </p>

<p>Licitra et al (2006) </p>

<p>Italy </p>

<p>2006 </p>

<p>1990-1999 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>69/21 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>32 
Verbal definition Clone unknown (Neomarkers, Fremont, </p>

<p>CA, USA ) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Lindquist et al 
(2012) </p>

<p>Sweden </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>1970-2002 </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>59 </p>

<p>59/14 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
Clone unknown (Pharmingen, San 
Diego, CA, USA) </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>Mellin Dahlstrand </p>

<p>et al (2005) </p>

<p>Sweden </p>

<p>2005 </p>

<p>1983-1999 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>39/12 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
E6H4 (DakoCytomation A/S, 
Carpinteria, CA, USA) </p>

<p>74 </p>

<p>79 </p>

<p>Mills et al (2012) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>Unknown 
62 Unknown Unknown </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
E6H4, predilute, Tris (pH 9.0) (MTM 
Laboratories Inc., Westborough, MA, </p>

<p>USA) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Nichols et al 
(2009) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2008 </p>

<p>Unknown 
44 Unknown </p>

<p>35/9 </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>29 
Verbal definition Clone unknown (MTM Laboratories, </p>

<p>Heidelberg, Germany) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Ukpo et al (2011) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>211 </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>188/23 </p>

<p>153 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>148 
Verbal definition E6H4 (MTM, Laboratories Inc., </p>

<p>Westborough, MA, USA) </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>Park et al (2012) </p>

<p>Korea </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>2002-2007 </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>62 </p>

<p>80/13 </p>

<p>53 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>46 
Verbal definition P2D11F11 (Novocastra Labs Ltd, </p>

<p>Newcastle, UK) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>Preuss et al (2008) </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>2008 </p>

<p>1998-2005 </p>

<p>106 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>77/29 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>61 
Verbal definition 16p04 (Neomarkers, Fremont, CA, USA) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Quon et al (2013) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>Unknown 
48 Unknown Unknown </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>35 
Verbal definition E6H4 (MTM Laboratories Inc., </p>

<p>Westborough, MA, USA) </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>69 </p>

<p>Reimers et al 
(2007) </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>2007 </p>

<p>1997-2002 </p>

<p>106 </p>

<p>59 </p>

<p>83/23 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
16p04 (Neomarkers, Fremont, CA, USA ) </p>

<p>86 </p>

<p>86 </p>

<p>Schache et al 
(2011b) </p>

<p>UK </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>1988-2009 </p>

<p>108 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>83/25 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>X70 
CINtec (MTM Laboratories AG, 
Heidelberg, Germany) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Semrau et al 
(2012) </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>2000-2008 </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>42/10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 
Clone unknown (Roche MTM 
Laboratories, Westborough, MA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Shi et al (2009) </p>

<p>Canada </p>

<p>2009 </p>

<p>2003-2006 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>82/29 </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>72 
Verbal definition CINtec (MTM Laboratories, </p>

<p>Westborough, MA, USA) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Thavaraj et al 
(2011) </p>

<p>UK </p>

<p>2011 </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>142 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>108/34 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>PCR and 
ISH </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>X70 
CINtec (MTM Laboratories 
Westborough, MA, USA) </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>Ukpo et al (2012) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>1996-2007 </p>

<p>154 </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>133/21 </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>104 
Verbal definition E6H4 (MTM Laboratories Inc., </p>

<p>Westborough, MA, USA) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Weinberger et al </p>

<p>(2010) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>1980-1999 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>106/34 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>25 
Verbal definition JC8 (Abcam Corporation, Cambridge </p>

<p>MA, USA) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>57 </p>

<p>Weiss et al (2012) </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>Unknown 
61 Unknown Unknown </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>PCR </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>X5 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>o70 </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Zhao et al (2012) </p>

<p>USA </p>

<p>2012 </p>

<p>2002-2006 
38 Unknown Unknown </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>ISH </p>

<p>22 
Verbal definition MAB4133 (Chemicon International 
Company/Millipore Corporation, </p>

<p>Temecula, CA, USA) </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Abbreviations: HPV 
¼ human papillomavirus; ISH </p>

<p>¼ in situ hybridisation; NA </p>

<p>¼ not applicable; PCR 
¼ polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>HPV and p16 oropharyngeal tumours 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>

<p>
no statistically significant difference between groups of p16 definition 
correlated to HPV, which may be because of the great heterogeneity 
among studies, including different p16 antibodies. In addition, ISH 
and PCR methods vary from centre to centre, leading to a loss of 
statistical power to detect differences. The explanation might also be 
that all p16 groups are equally correlated to HPV status; thus, the 
level of p16 staining is less important and the status of positivity or 
negativity is evident for a given staining, that is, most p16-positive 
tumours are above 70% when positive. Histopathologic grade and 
morphology was insufficiently reported and an agreement on a 
grading scheme applicable to OPSCC and consensus on reporting 
data is important for future research. As to p16 antibodies, an 
FDA-approved recommendation might be profitable to uniform 
research methods. It is widely assumed that HPV-related orophar-
yngeal cancers are poorly differentiated based on the immature 
appearance of the tumour cells, but in fact they are commonly highly 
differentiated as they emulate the specialised epithelium of the 
tonsillar crypts (Westra, 2009). Further data for analysis on this 
matter might question the challenge of interpreting p16-IHC in 
mixed and keratinising SSCs. In addition, it should be considered if 
carcinoma in situ should be included in future similar studies. 
In future studies applying p16-IHC and HPV diagnostics, the 
real value of IHC must be questioned once the site of the tumour is 
known (oropharynx) and the morphology is recognised (non-
keratinising); the chance of a non-keratinising OPSCC being HPV 
positive is still not known. 
Previous data report a prevalence of HPV in OPSCC of 51%, 
which is similar to our results (O'Rorke et al, 2012). Regardless if 
studies used PCR, ISH, or both, similar results were achieved. 
Oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinomas are characterised by a 
heterogeneous clinical and molecular profile (Huang et al, 2002; 
Shah and Patel, 2003; Bosch et al, 2004; De Vita et al, 2008) and </p>

<p>have interestingly proven to have a better prognostic outcome in 
cases with p16 overexpression (Lewis et al, 2010; Ang et al, 2010a). 
P16-IHC is, however, a diagnostic method causing much debate, 
and concerns have been raised: p16 overexpression might be 
associated with functional pRb disturbances irrelevant for the HPV 
infection (Marur et al, 2010). High-risk human papillomavirus-
infected OPSCCs have not necessarily lost the 9p21 allele encoding 
p16 (Braakhuis et al, 2004), and p16-IHC has been reported 100% 
sensitive but 79% specific as to carcinomas with HPV infection 
(Smeets et al, 2007). P16-IHC is performed on just one slide of 
tumour tissue and staining might vary allowing false-negative 
results explaining a lower specificity. Lately, cutoff values above 70 
or 75% have proven to be of wider use (Ang et al, 2010a; Evans 
et al, 2011; Schache et al, 2011a) as compared with, e.g., 
values 410% as a 'validated' definition of p16 overexpression. In 
a retrospective study based on material from The Danish Society 
for Head and Neck Oncology (DAHANCA), the cutoff value was 
changed in a Letter to the Editor after publication from 410 to 
470% (Lassen and Overgaard, 2012). 
In conclusion, substantial differences exist in the definition of 
p16 overexpression and means of HPV diagnostics between 
studies. To achieve the highest correlation between p16-IHC and 
HPV results, we advise clinicians and researchers to define p16 
overexpression as 470% staining of tumour cells. Future research 
in this field should report on p16 and HPV results, allowing a 
better understanding of the association between the two. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>AUTHORS CONTRIBUTION </p>

<p>CB concepted the idea of the study. CGL and MG searched the 
scientific literature, extracted data, and led the writing. LK, CGL, </p>

<p>Table 2. Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Demographics 
Total (n ¼ 3926) </p>

<p>Age, median (range) 
58 (20-93) </p>

<p>Sex a , n ¼ 3625 </p>

<p>Male 
2921 
Female 
704 </p>

<p>Country, n ¼ 3926 </p>

<p>Europe 
1446 
Australia 
215 
USA 
1759 
Asia 
506 </p>

<p>Ethinicity, n ¼ 3926 </p>

<p>Caucasian 
1568 
Asian 
269 
Mixed 
428 
Unspecified 
1661 </p>

<p>Tumour origin, n ¼ 3926 </p>

<p>Base of tongue 
414 
Palatine tonsils 
1420 
Unspecified/oropharynx 
2092 </p>

<p>Definition of p16 overexpression, n ¼ 3926 </p>

<p>Staining equals or exceeds 70% of nuclei and cytoplasm 
764 
Staining between 5 and 69% of nuclei and cytoplasm 
1684 
Verbal definition 
1478 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>N ¼ 301 subject's sex is unknown. </p>

<p>Comparison of verbal, &lt;70% and &gt;70% </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 
0.5 
False-positive rate </p>

<p>Verbal 
&lt;70% 
&gt;70% </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>Figure 2. Hierarchical summary receiver-operator curve (HSROC) of 
the studies from Table 1. The studies have been divided into three 
groups based on their definition of p16 staining: a verbal group, a 
o70% group, and a 470% group, including 95% CIs for the summary </p>

<p>point. The verbal group has a lower false discovery rate, while the 
470% group had a greater overall sensitivity and a smaller 95% CI. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
HPV and p16 oropharyngeal tumours </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>

<p>and DHJ performed statistics. All authors provided conceptual 
input, interpreted the findings, and contributed in significant ways 
to the final article. </p>



<p>HPV and p16 oropharyngeal tumours 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>



<p>
This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
HPV and p16 oropharyngeal tumours </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.42 </p>

</text></tei>