<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3819903" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Dementia is a series of symptoms that is represented by 
lack of cognitive capabilities or memory impairment, and 
mainly caused by Alzheimer's disease (AD) or vascular de-
mentia. Especially, the pathological hallmark of AD is the loss 
of cholinergic neurons in the basal forebrain that innervate the 
neocortex and hippocampus involved in learning and memory 
(Daulatzai, 2010; Schliebs and Arendt, 2011). Therefore, the 
most effective agent for dementia would be expected to have 
neuroprotective and enhancing effects on the cholinergic neu-
rotransmitter system. Donepezil, developed by those hypoth-
eses, is a prescribed drug for AD (Birks et al., 2000). However, 
there are several issues to be overcome such as nausea, </p>

<p>diarrhea, anorexia, or vomiting (Shintani and Uchida, 1997; 
Farlow et al., 2011). We are working on the development for 
anti-amnesic or anti-dementic agent using in vivo screening 
from herbal materials which are traditionally known to be ac-
tive to the central nervous system (CNS). 
The seed of Zizyphus jujuba var. spinosa (Rhamnoceae) 
has been used for traditional medicine in many Asian coun-
tries as a hypnotic agent. Most of the previous studies about 
the seed of Z. jujuba var. spinosa have been focused on its 
traditional use as sedative or hypnotic agent. Jujubosides, 
some of the main components in Z. jujuba var. spinosa, have 
been suggested to play roles in hypnotic effects, and seroto-
nergic neurotransmitter systems may be involved in their hyp-
notic effects (Cao et al., 2010). Jujubogenin, which easily pen-</p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 21(4), 299-306 (2013) </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author </p>

<p>E-mail: jhryu63@khu.ac.kr 
Tel: +82-2-961-9230, Fax: +82-2-966-3885 </p>

<p>Received May 15, 2013 Revised Jul 8, 2013 Accepted Jul 22, 2013 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2013.043 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2013 The Korean Society of Applied Pharmacology </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licens-
es/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>In the present study, we investigated the effect of ethanolic extract of the seed of Zizyphus jujuba var. spinosa (EEZS) on choliner-
gic blockade-induced memory impairment in mice. Male ICR mice were treated with EEZS. The behavioral tests were conducted 
using the passive avoidance, the Y-maze, and the Morris water maze tasks. EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.) signifi cantly amelio-
rated the scopolamine-induced cognitive impairment in our present behavioral tasks without changes of locomotor activity. The 
ameliorating effect of EEZS on scopolamine-induced memory impairment was signifi cantly reversed by a sub-effective dose of 
MK-801 (0.0125 mg/kg, s.c.). In addition, single administration of EEZS in normal naïve mouse enhanced latency time in the pas-
sive avoidance task. Western blot analysis was employed to confi rm the mechanism of memory-ameliorating effect of EEZS. Ad-
ministration of EEZS (200 mg/kg) increased the level of memory-related signaling molecules, including phosphorylation of extra-
cellular signal-regulated kinase or cAMP response element-binding protein in the hippocampal region. Also, the time-dependent 
expression level of brain-derived neurotrophic factor by the administration of EEZS was markedly increased from 3 to 9 h. These 
results suggest that EEZS has memory-ameliorating effect on scopolamine-induced cognitive impairment, which is mediated by 
the enhancement of the cholinergic neurotransmitter system, in part, via NMDA receptor signaling, and that EEZS would be useful 
agent against cognitive dysfunction such as Alzheimer's disease. </p>

<p>Key Words: Zizyphus jujuba var. spinosa, Scopolamine, Memory impairment </p>

<p>Ethanolic Extract of the Seed of Zizyphus jujuba var. 
spinosa Ameliorates Cognitive Impairment Induced by 
Cholinergic Blockade in Mice </p>

<p>Hyung Eun Lee 1,2 , So Young Lee 3 , Ju Sun Kim 3 , Se Jin Park 1,2 , Jong Min Kim 1,2 , Young Woo Lee 1,2 , </p>

<p>Jun Man Jung 1,2 , Dong Hyun Kim 1,2 , Bum Young Shin 1,4 , Dae Sik Jang 1,2 , Sam Sik Kang 3 and Jong Hoon Ryu 1,2, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 Department of Life and Nanopharmaceutical Science, 2 Kyung Hee East-West Pharmaceutical Research Institute, 
4 Department of Oriental Pharmaceutical science, College of Pharmacy, Kyung Hee University, Seoul 130-701, 
3 Natural Products Research Institute and College of Pharmacy, Seoul National University, Seoul 151-742, Republic of Korea </p>

<p>Abstract </p>



<p>Biomol Ther 21(4), 299-306 (2013) </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2013.043 </p>

<p>etrates into blood brain barrier, is one of active constituents in 
Z. jujuba var. spinosa against insomnia by the activation of the 
GABA A receptor (Chen et al., 2008). In addition, methanolic 
extract of the seed of Z. jujuba var. spinosa protects NMDA-
induced neuronal cell damage in cultured rat cerebellar granu-
lar cells in vitro (Park et al., 2004). However, there is no report 
regarding with the cognitive function of the seed of Z. jujuba 
var. spinosa. 
In the present study, we wanted to investigate whether the 
ethanolic extract of the seed of Z. jujuba var. spinosa (EEZS) 
has memory-ameliorating effect on scopolamine-induced 
cognitive impairment or memory enhancing effect in normal 
naïve mice. We employed several behavioral tests including 
the passive avoidance task, the Y-maze task and the Morris 
water maze task. Moreover, Western blot analysis was also 
employed to confi rm the effect of EEZS on the levels of memo-
ry-related biochemical parameters, including phosphorylation 
levels of extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) or cAMP 
response element-binding protein (CREB), or the expression 
levels of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Male ICR mice (25-30 g, 6 weeks old) were purchased from 
the Orient Co. Ltd, a branch of the Charles River Laboratories 
(GyeongGi-do, Korea). Mice were housed 5 per cage, provid-
ed with food and water ad libitum, and kept under a 12 h light/ 
dark cycle (light on 07:30-19:30 h) at a constant temperature 
(23 ± 1 o C) and relative humidity (60 ± 10%). Animal treatment 
and maintenance were carried out in accordance with the Ani-
mal Care and Use Guidelines issued by Kyung Hee University. 
All experimental protocols were approved by the Institutional 
Animal Care and Use Committee of Kyung Hee University (ap-
proved number; KHP-2011-01-03). </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Donepezil hydrochloride monohydrate, scopolamine hydro-
bromide, and dizocilpine (MK-801) were purchased from Sig-
ma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO, USA). Rabbit polyclonal an-
ti-phosphorylated ERK (pERK) antibody was purchased from 
Cell Signaling Technology (Cell Signaling, MA, USA). Rabbit 
polyclonal anti-ERK, rabbit polyclonal anti-CREB, rabbit poly-
clonal anti-BDNF and mouse polyclonal β-tubulin antibodies 
were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc. (Santa 
Cruz, CA, USA). An anti-phosphorylated CREB (pCREB) an-
tibody was purchased from Chemicon (Temecula, CA, USA). 
All other materials were obtained from normal commercial 
sources and were of the highest grade available. </p>

<p>Preparation of herbal extracts and drug administration </p>

<p>The seed of Z. jujuba var. spinosa were cultivated at Jinan, 
Shandong province, China, harvested in October 2009, and 
authenticated by Dr. J. H. Lee, Dongguk University. A voucher 
specimen was deposited in the Herbarium of the Traditional 
Herb Research Center, Korea Food and Drug Administration 
(No.11E-1001). The seed of Z. jujuba var. spinosa (1,240 g) 
were crushed and extracted two times with 70% ethanol (3 
L) under refl ux (60 o C) for 2 h. The extract was evaporated to 
dryness under reduced pressure to give the 70% ethanolic 
extract (94.5 g; yield, 7.6%). To ensure the quality, EEZS was </p>

<p>standardized based on the amount of jujuboside A, A2, B or 
naringin using a Shisheido C18 CAPCELL PAK column (5 μm, 
4.6×250 mm; Shisheido, Tokyo) (Fig.1). The mean level of ju-
juboside A in EEZS was 0.54%. </p>

<p>Passive avoidance task </p>

<p>Assessment of acquisition and retention trials of the passive 
avoidance task was carried out for 2 days. Testing was per-
formed in a box consisting of two identical chambers (20×20 
×20 cm) with one illuminated with 50 W bulb and another non-
illuminated chamber that were separated by a guillotine door 
(5×5 cm). The fl oor of the non-illuminated compartment was 
composed of 2 mm stainless steel rods spaced 1 cm apart as 
described previously (Park et al., 2012). Mice were adminis-
tered of EEZS (25, 50, 100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.) or donepezil (5 
mg/kg, p.o.) 1 h before an acquisition trial. The control group 
received 10% Tween 80 solution rather than EEZS. Mice were 
treated with scopolamine (1 mg/kg, i.p.) or 0.9% saline 30 min 
before the acquisition trial. Mice were initially placed in the il-
luminated compartment during the acquisition trial. The door 
between the two compartments was opened 10 s later. The 
door automatically closed when the mice entered the non-
illuminated compartment, and a 3 s electrical foot shock (0.5 
mA) was delivered through the stainless steel rods. Mice that 
did not enter non-illuminated compartment within 60 s after 
the opening of the door were excluded from retention trial. The 
retention trial was conducted 24 h after the acquisition trial by 
returning individual mice to the illuminated compartment. The 
time for the mouse to enter the dark compartment after the 
door opening was defi ned as latency in both trials. Latencies </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Representative HPLC chromatogram of standard mixture (15 </p>

<p>μg/ml) (A) and the 50% aq-methanolic extract of Z. jujuba var. spinosa 
(EEZS) (B). Jujuboside A was detected at around 47.09 min in this 
system. In the presented case, the concentration of jujuboside A in 
EEZS was 11.0 μg/ml. 1: jujuboside A, 2: jujuboside A2, 3: jujuboside B, 
I.S: naringin. </p>



<p>Lee et al. Eff ects of Zizyphus jujuba var. spinosa on Cognition </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>were recorded for up to 300 s. In a separate antagonism study, 
EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg) was administered 1 h before the ac-
quisition trial, and sub-effective dose of MK-801 (0.0125 mg/ 
kg), an N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor antagonist, 
was treated after the administration of EEZS. Scopolamine (1 
mg/kg) was administered 5 min after the treatment with MK-
801. The acquisition trial was conducted at 25 min after the 
administration of scopolamine. The dose of MK-801 in the 
present study was used not to impair the passive avoidance 
task performance when administered alone (Kim et al., 2010; 
Park et al., 2010). In the memory enhancing study, EEZS (100 
or 200 mg/kg) alone without scopolamine was administered 1 
h before the acquisition trial. When the mice entered the non-
illuminated compartment, a 3 s electrical foot shock (0.25 mA) 
was delivered through the stainless steel rods to avoid ceiling 
effects. Other procedures were the same as described above. </p>

<p>Y-maze task </p>

<p>The Y-maze is a three-arm horizontal maze (40 cm-long 
and 3 cm-wide with 12 cm-high walls) in which the arms are 
symmetrically disposed at 120 o angles from each other. The 
maze fl oor and walls were constructed of dark opaque poly-
vinyl plastic as described elsewhere (Kim et al., 2006). Mice 
were initially placed within one arm, and the sequence (i.e., 
ABCCAB, etc.) and number of arm entries were recorded 
manually for each mouse over an 8 min period. An actual al-
ternation was defi ned as entries into all three arms on con-
secutive choices (i.e., ABC, CAB, or BCA but not BAB). One 
hour before the test, mice were administered EEZS (100 or 
200 mg/kg, p.o.) or donepezil (5 mg/kg, p.o.). Control group 
animals received 10% Tween 80 solution rather than EEZS 
or donepezil. Scopolamine (1 mg/kg, i.p.) was introduced to 
induce memory impairment 30 min before the test. Maze arms 
were thoroughly cleaned with water spray between each test 
to remove residual odors and residues. The alternation score 
(%) for each mouse was defi ned as the ratio of the actual 
number of alternations to the possible number (defi ned as the 
total number of arm entries minus two) multiplied by 100 as 
shown by the following equation: % Alternation=[(Number of 
alternations)/(Total arm entries-2)]×100. The number of arm 
entries was used as an indicator of locomotor activity. </p>

<p>Morris water maze task </p>

<p>The Morris water maze is a circular pool (90 cm in diameter 
and 45 cm in height) with a featureless inner surface. The pool 
was fi lled to a depth of 30 cm with water containing 500 ml of 
black pigment (24 ± 1 o C). The tank was placed in a dimly lit, 
soundproof test room with four visual cues. A black platform 
(6 cm in diameter and 29 cm high) was then placed in one of 
the pool quadrants. The fi rst experimental day was dedicated 
to swimming training for 60 s in the absence of the platform. 
During the fi ve subsequent days the mice were given two trials 
per session per day with the platform in place. When a mouse 
located the platform, it was permitted to remain on it for 10 s. If 
the mouse did not locate the platform within 60 s, it was placed 
on the platform for 10 s. The time interval between each trial 
per session was 30 min (Kim et al., 2006). During each trial 
session, the time taken and distance moved to fi nd the hidden 
platform (latency time) was recorded using a video camera-
based Ethovision System (Nodulus, The Netherlands). One 
day after the last training trial session, mice were subjected to 
a probe trial session in which the platform was removed from </p>

<p>the pool, allowing the mice to swim for 60 s to search for it. 
A record was kept of the swimming time in the pool quadrant 
where the platform had previously been placed. EEZS (100 
or 200 mg/kg, p.o), or donepezil (5 mg/kg, p.o.) was given 1 
h before the fi rst trial at each session at every consecutive 
day. Memory impairment in mice was induced by scopolamine 
administration (1 mg/kg, i.p.) at 30 min before the fi rst trial in 
each session. Control group received 10% Tween 80 solution 
only. </p>

<p>Open fi eld test </p>

<p>The open fi eld test was conducted in clear black Plexiglas 
box (40×40×40 cm) equipped with a video-based Ethovision 
System (Noldus, The Netherlands) as described previously 
(Jung et al., 2006). Mice were administered EEZS (100 or 200 
mg/kg, p.o.) or 10% Tween 80 solution 1 h before the test. 
Mice were initially placed in the center of the apparatus, and 
total distance moved was recorded for 1 h. The horizontal lo-
comotor activity is expressed in terms of the total ambulatory 
distance. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Mice were decapitated immediately after the retention 
trial of the passive avoidance task or designated time points 
after the administration of EEZS in normal naïve mice, and 
the brains were isolated for Western blotting. Isolated hippo-
campal tissues from both hemispheres were homogenized 
in ice-cold Tris-HCl buffer (20 mM, pH 7.4) containing 0.32 
M sucrose, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM PMSF, 1 mM 
sodium orthovanadate and one tablet of protease inhibitor 
(Roche, Seoul, Korea) per 50 ml of buffer. Samples of homog-
enates (15 μg of protein) were subjected to SDS-PAGE (8% 
gel for pERK, ERK, pCREB and CREB, 12% gel for BDNF 
and β-tubulin) under reducing conditions. Proteins were trans-
ferred to PVDF membranes in transfer buffer [25 mM Tris-HCl 
buffer (pH 7.4) containing 192 mM glycine and 20% v/v metha-
nol] at 400 mA for 2 h at 4 o C. Western blots were incubated 
for 2 h with a blocking solution (5% skim milk) at room tem-
perature followed by incubation in a 1:5,000 dilution of anti-
pERK, anti-ERK, anti-pCREB and anti-CREB antibodies, or a 
1:1,000 dilution of anti-BDNF and anti-β-tubulin antibodies for 
24 h at 4 o C. The blots were washed ten times with a solution 
of Tris-buffered saline/Tween 20 (TBST) and incubated in a 
1:10,000 (for pERK, ERK, pCREB, CREB) or a 1:3,000 (for 
BDNF and β-tubulin) dilution of horseradish peroxidase-conju-
gated secondary antibodies for 1 h at room temperature. The 
blots were washed ten times with TBST, and developed us-
ing enhanced chemiluminescence (Amersham Life Science, 
Arlington Heights, IL). Immunoreactivity was analyzed using 
the <rs type="software">Multi-gauge</rs>, bio-imaging program on an LAS-4000 mini 
(Fujifi lm Lifescan USA, Stamford, CT, USA). </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Values are expressed as means ± S.E.M. The latencies in 
the passive avoidance task, the spontaneous alternation in 
the Y-maze task, and the swimming time in the probe trial of 
the Morris water maze test were analyzed by one-way analy-
sis of variance (ANOVA) followed by the Student-Newman-
Keuls test for multiple comparisons. Western blot analysis was 
analyzed by one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey's post-hoc 
analysis for multiple comparisons. The interactions between 
the agonist and the antagonist in the passive avoidance task </p>



<p>Biomol Ther 21(4), 299-306 (2013) </p>



<p>were analyzed by two-way ANOVA, and Tukey's post-hoc test 
was used to perform pair-wise comparisons to determine an-
tagonist or agonist effects. Training-trial latencies in the Morris 
water maze test were analyzed by two-way ANOVA followed 
by Tukey's post-hoc analysis using the day as one variable 
and treatment as a second. Statistical signifi cance was set at 
p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>EEZS ameliorates cognitive dysfunction induced by sco-
polamine on the passive avoidance task </p>

<p>The passive avoidance task was employed to investigate 
whether EEZS ameliorates memory impairment induced by 
scopolamine (1 mg/kg, i.p) (Fig. 2). There were signifi cant 
group effects in terms of step-through latency [F(6, 54)= 27.96, 
p&lt;0.05]. The reduction of step-through latency was observed 
in the scopolamine-injected group, but the administration of 
EEZS signifi cantly reversed the latency reduction (100 or 200 
mg/kg, p&lt;0.05; Fig. 1), as observed in the donepezil-treated 
group. There were no signifi cant differences in the latency 
time during the acquisition trial across all groups. Thereafter, 
we adopted 100 or 200 mg/kg of EEZS for further study. </p>

<p>EEZS ameliorates cognitive dysfunction induced by sco-
polamine on the Y-maze task </p>

<p>The Y-maze task was performed to examine the effect of 
EEZS on the spontaneous alternation behavior. A signifi cant 
group effect was observed on the spontaneous alternation be-
havior by the administration of EEZS [F(4, 39)=7.561, p&lt;0.05, 
Fig. 3A]. The percentage of spontaneous alternation in the 
scopolamine-treated group was signifi cantly lower than that in 
the vehicle-treated control group (p&lt;0.05), and the reduction 
of the spontaneous alternation was signifi cantly ameliorated 
by EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.) or donepezil (5 mg/kg, p.o.) 
(p&lt;0.05, Fig. 3A). However, the mean numbers of the arm 
entries were similar across all experimental groups (Fig. 3B), </p>

<p>which demonstrated that general locomotor activity was not 
affected by EEZS (Sarter et al., 1988). </p>

<p>EEZS ameliorates cognitive dysfunction induced by sco-
polamine on the Morris water maze task </p>

<p>The effect of EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.) on spatial 
learning and memory was evaluated using the Morris water 
maze task. As shown in Fig. 4A, the scopolamine-treated 
group exhibited longer escape latencies throughout the train-
ing days than the vehicle-treated control group. However, es-
cape latencies of the EEZS (200 mg/kg, p.o.)-or donepezil 
(5 mg/kg, p.o.)-treated group were signifi cantly shortened 
compared with those of the scopolamine-treated group dur-
ing the training trial sessions 4 and 5 [trial session 4, F (4, 
45)=5.439, p&lt;0.05; trial session 5, F(4, 45)=5.520, p&lt;0.05]. 
On the day following the fi nal day of training sessions, the 
shortened swimming time within the target zone induced by 
scopolamine was signifi cantly reversed by EEZS (100 or 200 
mg/kg) or donepezil (p&lt;0.05, Fig. 4B). However, there were 
no signifi cant differences in swimming speed within the target 
zone across all groups (data not shown). </p>

<p>EEZS did not aff ected the locomotor activity in the open 
fi eld test </p>

<p>To determine whether EEZS modifi es stimulatory effect on 
the exploratory behavior, the open fi eld test was performed 
and spontaneous locomotor activity was observed. EEZS-
treated groups (100 or 200 mg/kg) had no signifi cant changes 
in total ambulatory distances compared to the control group 
(p&gt;0.05, Fig. 5). </p>

<p>The eff ect of EEZS is antagonized by MK-801 in the pas-
sive avoidance task </p>

<p>To determine whether the memory-ameliorating effect of 
EEZS is mediated via NMDA receptor signaling, sub-effective 
dose of MK-801 (0.0125 mg/kg) was co-treated with scopol-
amine to the EEZS-treated mice (100 or 200 mg/kg), and the </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The effects of the ethanolic extract of the seed of Z. jujuba </p>

<p>var. spinosa (EEZS) on scopolamineinduced memory impairment in 
the passive avoidance task. EEZS (25, 50, 100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.), 
donepezil (DNZ, 5 mg/kg, p.o.), or the same volume of vehicle (10% 
Tween 80 solution) was administered to mice 1 h before the acquisi-
tion trial. Memory impairment was induced by scopolamine (1 mg/kg, 
i.p.) 30 min before the acquisition trial. Twenty four hours after the ac-
quisition trial, a retention trial was conducted for 300 s. Data represent 
means ± S.E.M (n=8-10/group) (*p&lt;0.05, versus the vehicle-treated 
controls, # p&lt;0.05, versus the scopolamine-treated group). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The effects of the ethanolic extract of the seed of Z. jujuba var. </p>

<p>spinosa (EEZS) on scopolamineinduced memory impairment in the 
Y-maze task. Mice were administered EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.), 
donepezil (DNZ, 5 mg/kg, p.o.), or the same volume of vehicle (10% 
Tween 80 solution) 60 min before the Ymaze test. Memory impair-
ment was induced by scopolamine (1 mg/kg, i.p.) 30 min before the 
Y-maze tests. Spontaneous alternation behavior (A) and the numbers 
of arm entries (B) during an 8 min session were recorded. Data rep-
resent means ± S.E.M (n=8-10/group) (*p&lt;0.05, versus the vehicle-
treated controls, # p&lt;0.05, versus the scopolamine-treated group). </p>



<p>Lee et al. Eff ects of Zizyphus jujuba var. spinosa on Cognition </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>passive avoidance task was conducted. The reduced step-
through latency induced by scopolamine was signifi cantly re-
versed by EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg) [F(7, 71)=33.150, p&lt;0.05] 
(Fig. 6). The ameliorating effect of EEZS on scopolamine-in-
duced memory impairment was disappeared by the adminis-
tration of MK-801, and the step-through latency was reached 
to that of scopolamine alone-treated group. There were sig-
nifi cant group effects between EEZS-treated group and MK-
801-treated groups determined by two-way ANOVA [F(1, 52)= 
23.740, p&lt;0.05]. In the acquisition trial, signifi cant differences 
in step-through latency were not observed across all groups. </p>

<p>EEZS enhances cognitive performance in naive mice mea-
sured by the passive avoidance task </p>

<p>The memory-enhancing effect of EEZS in the nave animal 
was evaluated using the passive avoidance task (Fig. 7). Dur-
ing the acquisition trial, there were no signifi cant differences 
in the step-through latency between groups. The retention 
trial was performed 24 h after the acquisition trial. As a result, 
dose-dependent increase of the step-through latency was ob-
served in the EEZS-treated group [F(2, 28)=3.946, p&lt;0.05, 
Fig. 7]. EEZS (200 mg/kg) signifi cantly increased step-through 
latency compared with the vehicle-treated control (p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>The eff ects of EEZS on the expression levels of pERK, 
pCREB or BDNF in the hippocampus </p>

<p>The effect of EEZS on the levels of ERK or CREB phos-
phorylation in the hippocampus was determined using the 
Western blot analysis. Mice were sacrifi ced 1 h after the ad-
ministration of EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg). Signifi cant group 
effects on the levels of memory-related signaling molecules 
in the hippocampus were observed in the EEZS-treated 
groups. The administration of EEZS (200 mg/kg) signifi cantly 
increased the phosphorylation levels of ERK [F(2, 21)=3.975, 
p&lt;0.05, Fig. 8A] or CREB [F(2, 19)=3.385, p&lt;0.05, Fig. 8A] 
compared to the levels of vehicle-treated group. To investigate 
the changes of time-dependent BDNF levels in the hippocam-</p>

<p>Fig. 4. The effects of the ethanolic extract of the seed of Z. jujuba </p>

<p>var. spinosa (EEZS) on the scopolamineinduced memory dysfunction 
in the Morris water maze task. The training sessions were conducted 
for 5 days. Mice were administered EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.), 
donepezil (DNZ, 5 mg/kg, p.o.), or the same volume of vehicle (10% 
Tween 80 solution) 60 min before the fi rst training trial of each ses-
sion. Memory impairment was induced by the administration of sco-
polamine (1 mg/kg, i.p.) 30 min before the fi rst training trial. Training 
trial and probe trial sessions were performed over 60 s as described 
in materials and methods section. Escape latencies during the train-
ing sessions (A), the swimming time in the target quadrant (B) during 
the probe-trial session in the Morris water maze task were measured. 
Data represent means ± S.E.M (n=10/group) (*p&lt;0.05, versus the 
vehicle-treated controls, # p&lt;0.05, versus the scopolamine-treated 
group). </p>

<p>Fig. 5. The effects of the ethanolic extract of the seed of Z. jujuba var. </p>

<p>spinosa (EEZS) on the locomotor activity in the open fi eld test. The 
exploratory behaviors of mice in the open fi eld test were observed for 
60 min. Mice were administered EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.) or the 
same volume of vehicle (10% Tween 80 solution) 1 h before the test. 
Data are expressed as means ± S.E.M (n=10/group). </p>

<p>Fig. 6. The role of NMDA receptor signaling in the effects of the etha-</p>

<p>nolic extract of the seed of Z. jujuba var. spinosa (EEZS) on scopol-
amine-induced memory impairments in mice. EEZS (100 or 200 mg/ 
kg, p.o.) or the same volume of vehicle (10% Tween 80 solution) was 
administered 60 min before the acquisition trial, and subeffective dose 
of MK-801 (0.0125 mg/kg, s.c.) was injected to the mice 30 min after 
the oral injection. Scopolamine (1 mg/kg, i.p.) was treated 5 min after 
the injection of MK-801. The retention trial was conducted 24 h after 
the acquisition trial. Data represent means ± S.E.M (n=8-10/group) 
(*p&lt;0.05, versus the vehicle-treated controls, # p&lt;0.05, versus sco-
polamine-treated groups, $ p&lt;0.05, versus EEZS plus scopolamine-
treated group). </p>



<p>Biomol Ther 21(4), 299-306 (2013) </p>



<p>pus, mice were sacrifi ced 0 h, 1 h, 3 h, 9 h and 12 h after the 
administration of EEZS (200 mg/kg). The BDNF expression 
level was signifi cantly increased from 3 to 9 h after administra-
tion of EEZS [F(4, 20)=9.292, p&lt;0.05, Fig. 8B]. However, the 
effect of EEZS on BDNF level did not last more than 12 h. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the present study, we investigated whether EEZS has 
memory-ameliorating effect on the scopolamine-induced am-
nesic mouse model. Scopolamine-induced amnesia model in 
rodents has been widely used to screen benefi cial treatments 
for cognitive dysfunction (Polster, 1993; Potter et al., 2000). To 
examine the effect of EEZS, several behavioral tests were em-
ployed. First, the passive avoidance task was used to exam-
ine the behavioral outcome after the administration of EEZS. 
Scopolamine caused memory impairments, and EEZS signifi -
cantly reversed these impairments. These results suggest that 
EEZS rescued the cognitive dysfunctions related to learning 
and memory in the cholinergic dysfunction state. Second, in 
the Y-maze task, the administration of EEZS improved spon-
taneous alternation impairment induced by scopolamine, sug-
gesting that EEZS ameliorates short-term or working memory 
impairment in scopolamine-induced amnesic model (Sarter et 
al., 1988; Myhrer et al., 2003). We also observed the memory-
ameliorating effect of EEZS in the Morris water maze task. 
The Morris water maze task is dependent on hippocampal 
function or spatial memory that is commonly assessed using 
the rodents (Morris, 1984; Barnes et al., 1996). EEZS signifi -
cantly shortened the escape latencies during the training ses-
sions, and also ameliorated scopolamine-induced reduction in 
swimming time within the quadrant where the target platform 
was existed during the probe trial session. According to these 
behavioral results, EEZS could be considered to have mem-
ory-ameliorating effect in the case of cholinergic dysfunction 
without affecting spontaneous locomotor activity. 
It has been suggested that both cholinergic and glutama-
tergic neurotransmissions are related to the learning and 
memory processes. Furthermore, interactions between cen-
tral cholinergic and glutamatergic neurotransmitter systems </p>

<p>have been suggested to be a crucial role in memory forma-
tion (Gray et al., 1996; Shimohama et al., 1996; Timofeeva 
and Levin, 2011). Cooperations between cholinergic and 
glutamatergic neurotransmitter systems are also essential to 
induce BDNF-dependent long-lasting memory storage (Na-
vakkode and Korte, 2012) and necessary for the induction of 
long-term potentiation (Jerusalinsky et al., 1997). Moreover, 
increasing evidences indicate that NMDA receptor activity af-
fects acetylcholine release in the basal ganglia (Ikarashi et al., 
1998; Knauber et al., 1999; Palencia and Ragozzino, 2006). 
Thus, cholinergic neurotransmitter system would be associ-
ated with the NMDA receptor signaling. In the present study, 
the memory-ameliorating effects of EEZS on scopolamine-
induced memory dysfunction were completely antagonized by 
a sub-effective dose of MK-801. The relation between NMDA 
receptor and Zizyphi semen extract in vitro was demonstrated 
by previous researchers (Park et al., 2004), and was also ob-
served in the present study in vivo. Moreover, the administra-
tion of EEZS enhanced memory performances in a dose-de-
pendent manner in naive mice. Because of its weak inhibitory 
effect on the acetylcholinesterase inhibition activity (data not 
shown), these results suggest that the ameliorating effects of 
EEZS on the cognitive dysfunction may be attributed to the 
activity of cholinergic neurotransmitter system which is also 
regulated by glutamatergic signaling. This possibility could be 
supported by the changes of memory-related signaling mol-
ecules. 
The administration of EEZS signifi cantly increased the lev-
els of pERK or pCREB in the hippocampus. Furthermore, the 
time-dependent expression level of BDNF was signifi cantly 
increased 3 h after, and lasted at least 9 h after the admin-
istration of EEZS. A growing number of evidences show that </p>

<p>Fig. 7. The effects of the ethanolic extract of the seed of Z. jujuba </p>

<p>var. spinosa (EEZS) on the cognitive performances in the naïve mice. 
EEZS (100 or 200 mg/kg, p.o.) or the same volume of vehicle (10% 
Tween 80 solution) was administered to mice 1 h before the acquisi-
tion trial in the passive avoidance task. In the acquisition trial, mild 
electrical shock (0.25 mA) was given to the mice. A 10-min retention 
trial was performed 24 h after the acquisition trial. Data represent the 
means ± S.E.M. (n=9-10/group) (*p&lt;0.05, versus the vehicle-treated 
controls). </p>

<p>Fig. 8. The effects of the ethanolic extract of the seed of Z. ju-</p>

<p>juba var. spinosa (EEZS) on the phosphorylation levels of ERK 
or CREB, and the changes of time-dependent expression level of 
BDNF in the hippocampus. Mice were administered EEZS (100 or 
200 mg/kg, p.o.) or the same volume of vehicle (10% Tween 80 solu-
tion), and sacrificed 1 h (A) or designated time points (B) after the 
EEZS administration. Immunoreactivity and quantitative analysis of 
pERK, pCREB, and BDNF were measured in the hippocampal tissue. 
Note that EEZS enhanced the level of phosphorylated ERK or CREB 
in the hippocampus (A), and the time-dependent expression level of 
BDNF in the hippocampus (B). Data represent the means ± S.E.M. 
(pERK and pCREB, n=7-8/group; BDNF, n=5/group) (*p&lt;0.05, versus 
the vehicle-treated controls; **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.005, versus the 0 h 
level). </p>



<p>Lee et al. Eff ects of Zizyphus jujuba var. spinosa on Cognition </p>



<p>activation of NMDA receptors stimulates ERK signaling (Xu 
et al., 2012), which is essential for the expression of LTP in 
the hippocampaus (English and Sweatt, 1996; English and 
Sweatt, 1997; Davis et al., 2000). Others also indicate that 
NMDA receptor activation affects ERK-CREB signaling (Zhou 
et al., 2009), suggesting that cognitive performance could be 
enhanced via NMDA receptor activation. (Bourtchuladze et 
al., 1994; Tully et al., 2003). The activation of CREB is related 
with transcription of many genes, including BDNF (Tao et al., 
1998), a member of neurotropin family of growth factors, which 
plays an important role in memory formation and LTP (Zheng 
et al., 2012). Taken together, we suggest that the administra-
tion of EEZS enhances cognitive performance through the up-
regulation of ERK-CREB-BDNF signaling, and these results 
are related with the activation of NMDA receptors. 
Several biological active compounds were isolated from Z. 
jujuba var. spinosa. For example, dammarane-type saponins 
including jujubosides A and B, or fatty acids such as lauric, lin-
oleic, arachidonic and docosanoic acid were isolated (Zhao et 
al., 2006). Carotenes are also reported to be isolated from the 
extract of the seed of Z. jujuba var. spinosa (Guil-Guerrero et 
al., 2004). We isolated several compounds mentioned above, 
and obtained jujuboside A and B in large amount enough to 
conduct behavioral tests. However, jujuboside A or B did not 
exert any memory ameliorating activities (data are not shown). 
Recently, it has been reported that jujuboside A increases the 
expression of GABA A receptor subunits in the hippocampal 
neurons (You et al., 2010). If EEZS activates GABA A recep-
tors, the cognitive functions may be impaired or no affected. 
Therefore, it is not likely that the cognitive functions of EEZS 
are associated with the GABA A receptor signaling. Further 
studies should be taken to investigate active constituent(s) of 
EEZS for cognitive function. 
In conclusion, the present study demonstrated that EEZS 
ameliorated scopolamine-induced memory impairment in the 
passive avoidance, the Y-maze, and the Morris water maze 
tasks in mice. Moreover, the ameliorating effect of EEZS is 
mediated by enhancement of the cholinergic neurotransmitter 
system, in part, through the NMDA receptor signaling concom-
itant with the enhancement of ERK-CREB-BDNF signaling. 
Our present fi ndings suggest that EEZS may be a potential 
therapeutic for treating cognitive dysfunction such as AD. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This research was supported by a grant (09112KFDA890) 
from Korean Food &amp; Drug Administration in 2011. </p>







</text></tei>