<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3467446" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background and Objectives: Irregular RR intervals in atrial fibrillation (AF) make beat-to-beat changes in left ventricular (LV) systolic 
performance. Early diastolic mitral annular velocity (E') is one of the well-established parameters for evaluating LV diastolic function. The 
relation between RR intervals and E's is unknown. The aim of this study was to observe the influence of continuous changes in RR inter-
val on the parameter for diastolic function in AF. 
Subjects and Methods: Echocardiography was performed in 117 patients with AF. E' was adjusted for the effect of pre-preceding RR in-
terval (RR-2) using the logarithmic equation between RR-2 and E' . The logarithmic equation between adjusted E' and preceding RR inter-
val (RR-1) was calculated. 
Results: The slope in the relation between RR-1 and E' varied from -2.5 to 2.6. The slope was lower (more likely negative) in patients with 
higher ratio of early diastolic mitral flow velocity (E) to E' (r=-0.21, p=0.023), ischemic heart disease (IHD, r=0.21, p=0.026), and higher sys-
tolic blood pressure (r=-0.19, p=0.046). When patients were divided into these 3 groups on the basis of slope, the lowest slope group (&lt;-0.55, 
n=39) was associated with higher E'/E (p=0.004) and IHD (p=0.018) compared with the highest slope group (&gt;0.57, n=39). The slope with 
regards to the relationship between RR-2 and E' also varied from -3.4 to 3.1. 
Conclusion: Changes in RR intervals had variable effects on E's according to clinical variables in AF. (Korean Circ J 2012;42:618-624) </p>

<p>KEY WORDS: Ventricular function, left; Atrial fibrillation; Electrocardiography; Pulsed Doppler echocardiography; Heart rate. </p>

<p>Received: February 1, 2012 
Revision Received: March 14, 2012 
Accepted: April 4, 2012 
Correspondence: Chee Jeong Kim, MD, Division of Cardiology, Depart-
ment of Internal Medicine, College of Medicine, Chung-Ang University, 
102 Heukseok-ro, Dongjak-gu, Seoul 156-755, Korea 
Tel: 82-2-6299-1398, Fax: 82-2-822-2769 
E-mail: cjkim@cau.ac.kr </p>

<p>• The authors have no financial conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work 
is properly cited. </p>

<p>often determined by echocardiographic parameters. 
5-7) However, </p>

<p>all parameters have limitations and there is no golden standard to 
evaluate diastolic function non-invasively. One of the most prom-
ising parameters is early diastolic mitral annular velocity (E'). E' is re-
latively less dependent on preload than other parameters. 
7)8) E' is lo-</p>

<p>wer in systolic dysfunction than in normal systolic function. Even in 
normal systolic function, E' becomes lower with the development 
of diastolic dysfunction. 
8) There are few reports observing the asso-</p>

<p>ciation between parameters representing systolic and diastolic 
functions of the left ventricle. 
8-10) We investigated the influences of </p>

<p>continuous change in RR interval on diastolic function in AF by ob-
serving the relationship between RR interval and E' . </p>

<p>Subjects and Methods </p>

<p>One hundred and forty-three patients with AF were screened and 
117 patients were enrolled in our study. Exclusion criteria included 1) 
hemodynamically significant mitral stenosis (mitral valvular area &lt;2 
cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, n=8) or aortic stenosis (aortic valvular area &lt;1.6 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, n=2), 2) </p>



<p>Eun Young Kim, et al. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2012.42.9.618 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>pericardial diseases (n=2), 3) cardiac myxoma (n=1), 4) hyperthy-
roidism (n=2), 5) poor tissue Doppler image (n=2) and 6) other acute 
medical conditions including acute stroke, acute thromboembo-
lism, pneumonia, and sepsis (n=9). 
Two-dimensional and Doppler echocardiograms (Philips Sonos 
7500, 2-to 2.5-MHz transducer, Phillips Healthcare, Bothell, WA, USA) 
were obtained in the left lateral position. Dimensions were measur-
ed according to the American Society of Echocardiography stan-
dards. 
11) Fractional shortening was measured using an M-mode echo-</p>

<p>cardiogram at the beat with the longest preceding RR interval (RR-1). 
Thirty to 40 consecutive E's were recorded using tissue Doppler im-</p>

<p>aging from the apical 4-chamber view with a sample volume in the 
septal border of the mitral annulus. Electrocardiogram was recorded 
simultaneously, and E' and RR interval were measured (Fig. 1). 
The relationship between RR interval and E' was obtained using 
a method reported previously with some modification. 
12)13) The loga-</p>

<p>rithmic equation for the relation between pre-preceding RR interval 
(RR-2) and E' was obtained. Using this equation, E' was adjusted for 
the effect of RR-2 assuming that RR-2 was fixed to the mean RR 
interval (Fig. 2). By this modification, the mean squared correlation 
coefficient (r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) of the relation between RR-1 and E' improved slightly, 
however, significantly from 0.109±0.115 to 0.121±0.120 (p=0.006). 
The slope was obtained rom the logarithmic equation between RR-1 
and adjusted E' . Patients with very rapid or slow ventricular rates 
(most RR intervals &lt;0.6 or &gt;1.0 second, n=21) were excluded and 
the logarithmic equation between RR-1 and adjusted E' was recal-
culated in co-ordination with RR-1 ranging from 0.6 to 1 second 
(n=96). 
Data were presented as mean±SD. Statistical analysis was per-
formed using <rs type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS</rs>) (Ver-
sion 9.0, SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The Pearson correlation anal-
ysis was used to evaluate the relationship between the parameters, 
and multiple stepwise linear regression analysis was used to find in-
dependent variables. The simple or forward logistic regression meth-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Examples of measuring pre-preceding RR interval (RR-2), preceding 
RR interval (RR-1), and early diastolic mitral valve annular velocity (E'). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Representative example of processes to obtain slope in the relation between preceding RR interval (RR-1) and early diastolic mitral valve annular 
velocity (E'). Logarithmic equation for the relationship between pre-preceding RR interval (RR-2) and E' (A). Relationship between RR-1 and E' before (B) 
and after (C) adjustment for effect of RR-2 on E' . Logarithmic equation between RR-1 and adjusted E' was recalculated in coordinates with RR-1 ranging 
from 0.6 to 1 second (D). </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Pre-preceding RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Preceding RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Preceding RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Preceding RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral valve 
annulus velocity (cm/sec) </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral valve 
annulus velocity (cm/sec) </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral valve 
annulus velocity (cm/sec) </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral valve 
annulus velocity (cm/sec) </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 </p>

<p>y=1.12×Ln(x)+9.5 
r 2 =0.24 </p>

<p>y=1.19×Ln(x)+9.56 
r 2 =0.41 </p>

<p>y=1.44×Ln(x)+9.58 
r 2 =0.40 </p>

<p>y=1.36×Ln(x)+9.63 
r 2 =0.25 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2012.42.9.618 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>od was used to compare the parameters between the 2 groups. Sta-
tistical significance was inferred at a p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics of study patients 
Demographic, clinical, and laboratory characteristics of 117 pa-
tients are presented in Table 1. The mean age was 67.0±10.8 years 
and 81 (69%) were males. Fifty-nine patients (50%) and 23 patients 
(20%) were taking digoxin and β-blocker, respectively. </p>

<p>Parameters associated with slope from the relationship 
between RR-1 and E' 
The slope in the relationship between RR-1 and E' varied from 
-2.5 to 2.6 in total coordinates (Fig. 3). The slope was lower (nega-
tive) in patients with higher ratio of early diastolic mitral flow velo-
city (E) to E' ratio (r=-0.21, p=0.023) (Fig. 4), ischemic heart disease 
(IHD; r=0.21, p=0.026), smaller diastolic LV dimension (r=0.19, p= 
0.039), and higher systolic blood pressure (r=-0.19, p=0.046) in the </p>

<p>Pearson correlation analysis (Table 2). Among these parameters, 
higher E/E', the presence of IHD, and higher systolic blood pressure 
were independent according to the multiple stepwise linear regres-
sion analysis (r=0.34, p=0.004). 
When patients were divided into the 3 groups according to the 
slope in the relationship between RR-1 and E', the lowest slope gr-
oup (&lt;-0.55, n=39) was associated with higher E/E' (p=0.004), IHD 
(p=0.018), lower E' (p=0.023), and smaller diastolic LV dimension 
(p=0.047) compared with the highest slope group (&gt;0.57, n=39) (Ta-
ble 3). Among these parameters, higher E/E' and the presence of 
IHD were independent according to the forward logistic regression 
analysis. In the relationship between RR-1 and E' in co-ordinates with 
RR-1 ranging from 0.6 to 1 second (n=96), lower slope (negative) 
was associated with a history of hypertension (r=0.25, p=0.014) and 
IHD (r=0.21, p=0.041). In this case, only history of hypertension was 
independent with regards to the multiple stepwise linear regression 
analysis. </p>

<p>Parameters associated with slope from the relationship 
between RR-2 and E' 
The slope in the relationship between RR-2 and E' also varied from 
-3.4 to 3.1 (Fig. 3). The slope was associated with many variables 
with respect to the Pearson correlation analysis (Table 2). Among 
these, lower slope (negative) was independently related to larger 
systolic LV dimension (r=-0.38, p=0.000) and lower E' (r=0.30, p= 
0.001) in the multiple stepwise linear regression analysis (r=0.49, 
p=0.000). </p>

<p>Relationship between E' and RR-1 or RR-2 
In the relationship between E' and RR-2, r 
2 was quite variable (from </p>

<p>0 to 0.65) patient-to-patient and very weak (0.11±0.14). Additional-
ly, r 
2 was negatively associated with ejection fraction (r=-0.31, p= </p>

<p>0.0008) and positively with systolic LV dimension (r=0.26, p=0.005). 
Among these, ejection fraction was an independent variable in the 
multiple stepwise linear regression analysis. In the relationship be-
tween E' and RR-1, r 
2 was also quite variable (from 0 to 0.58), very </p>

<p>weak (0.12±0.12), and was not associated with any variables. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study demonstrated that beat-to-beat changes in RR inter-
vals in AF had variable effects on E' according to several clinical 
variables and that the slope in the relationship between RR-1 and 
E' tended to be negative in patients with high diastolic filling pres-
sure, IHD, and/or other several parameters. Thus, the longer the RR 
interval is, the lower E' becomes in these patients. 
To our knowledge, there have been no reports that investigated </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic, clinical, and laboratory characteristics of study pa-
tients </p>

<p>Age (years) 
67.0±10.8 </p>

<p>Male/Female 
81/36 </p>

<p>Mean RR interval (sec) 
0.79±0.18 </p>

<p>Diastolic dimension of left ventricle (cm) 
5.1±0.6 </p>

<p>Systolic dimension of left ventricle (cm) 
3.4±0.7 </p>

<p>Ejection fraction (%) 
55.8±9.7 </p>

<p>Interventricular septum (cm) 
1.01±0.20 </p>

<p>Left ventricular posterior wall (cm) 
0.96±0.14 </p>

<p>Left atrium (cm) 
5.3±0.6 </p>

<p>Aorta (cm) 
3.5±0.4 </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral flow velocity (cm/s) 
80.8±19.2 </p>

<p>Acceleration time (ms) 
78.0±15.0 </p>

<p>Deceleration time (ms) 
178±41.5 </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral annular velocity (cm/s) 
6.75±1.80 </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral flow velocity/ 
Early diastolic mitral annular velocity 
13.0±5.4 </p>

<p>Mitral regurgitation (no/mild/moderate/severe) 
82/16/8/11 </p>

<p>Aortic regurgitation (no/mild/moderate/severe) 
90/13/11/3 </p>

<p>Medication (%) </p>

<p>Digoxin 
59 (50) </p>

<p>β blocker 
23 (20) </p>

<p>Associated diseases (%) </p>

<p>Hypertension 
79 (68) </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 
26 (22) </p>

<p>IHD 
14 (12) </p>

<p>IHD: ischemic heart disease </p>



<p>Eun Young Kim, et al. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2012.42.9.618 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>the relationship between RR intervals and E's in AF. It was difficult 
to assume the relation between RR intervals and E's due to the rel-
atively wide variation of E' by respiration and sample volume (Fig. 3). 
We evaluated several simple mathematical equations, and found 
that compared with the linear equation, the logarithmic equation 
showed minimally higher r 
2 although it was not statistically signif-</p>

<p>icant (0.121±0.120 vs. 0.119±0.116, p=0.26). 
There are several echocardiographic parameters representing LV </p>

<p>diastolic function well in sinus rhythm. 
5-7) However, it is difficult to </p>

<p>evaluate diastolic function in AF due to beat-to-beat changes of pa-
rameters and loss of atrial contraction. 
14) We chose E' as a marker of </p>

<p>diastolic function because it was relatively easier to obtain mea-
surements of many beats. E' is one of the most promising echocar-
diographic parameters for diastolic function. It is relatively preload-
independent 
7)8) and is also useful in AF. </p>

<p>14)15) </p>

<p>In AF, irregular RR intervals make beat to beat changes in LV sys-
tolic performance. With a longer RR interval, preload and contrac-
tility increase, and afterload decreases resulting in higher cardiac per-
formance. 
1)2) Preload has minimal or no effects on E' in the presence </p>

<p>of heart disease. 
10)16)17) However, a small but significant increase of </p>

<p>E' was noted with large volume loading in normal diastolic func-
tion. 
10)17)18) The effect of systolic function on E' is controversial. Aug-</p>

<p>mented contractility with dopamine markedly increased E' . 
10) How-</p>

<p>ever, E' was not related to ejection fraction. </p>

<p>8) </p>

<p>Based on previous reports, it is expected that a longer RR interval 
increases or does not change E' compared with a shorter RR inter-
val in AF. Yet in the present study, RR interval showed variable ef-
fects on E' and the slope in the relation between RR-1 and E' was 
negative in a portion of patients with several clinical characteris-
tics. Thus the relation between E' and preload or contractility may be 
more complicated than previously understood. Heart rate and blood 
pressure were not associated with E' . </p>

<p>8)19) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The most negative and positive slopes in the relationship between preceding RR interval and E' (A and B) and in the relationship between pre-pre-
ceding RR interval and E' (C and D). </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Preceding RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Pre-preceding RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Preceding RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Pre-preceding RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral valve 
annulus velocity (cm/sec) </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral valve 
annulus velocity (cm/sec) </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral valve 
annulus velocity (cm/sec) </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral valve 
annulus velocity (cm/sec) </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 </p>

<p>y=-2.5×Ln(x)+3.88 
r 2 =0.49 
p=0.001 </p>

<p>y=-3.4×Ln(x)+3.65 
r 2 =0.65 
p=0.000 </p>

<p>y=2.6×Ln(x)+8.00 
r 2 =0.19 
p=0.044 </p>

<p>y=3.1×Ln(x)+11.5 
r 2 =0.46 
p=0.000 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>E/E' </p>

<p>Slope </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 </p>

<p>y=-0.041×0.52 
r=-0.21 
p=0.023 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. The relationship between ratio of early diastolic mitral flow velocity 
to early diastolic mitral annular velocity (E/E') and slope with respect to the 
relationship between preceding RR interval and E' . </p>

<p>622 RR Intervals and Early Diastolic Mitral Annular Velocities </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2012.42.9.618 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>Rate control is often the therapy of choice for AF. The guidelines 
have recommended a resting heart rate &lt;80/minute without solid 
evidence. 
20) Recently, it has been reported that lenient rate control is </p>

<p>as effective as strict rate control for the prevention of cardiovascular 
events. 
21) In clinical settings, dyspnea or dyspnea on exertion is usu-</p>

<p>ally improved with rate control therapy. However, several patients 
complain of ambiguous discomfort with the therapy. The present st-
udy showed that rate control decreased E' in patients with higher 
E/E', IHD, and several clinical characteristics. This finding suggests 
that tight rate control may deteriorate LV diastolic function in these 
patients and may partially explain the discrepancies between the 
guidelines and recent clinical studies, as well as patient-to-patient 
differences observed in the effectiveness of the therapy. Consider-
ing that E' cannot represent diastolic function in all situations, fur-
ther studies are needed to confirm this hypothesis. 
The slope in the relationship between RR-2 and E' also varied from 
-3.4 to 3.1. The slope tended to be negative in patients with larger </p>

<p>LV systolic dimension (r=-0.38, p=0.000) and lower E' (r=0.30, p= 
0.001). This finding suggests that a longer RR-2 makes E' lower and 
is not beneficial in patients with systolic and/or diastolic dysfunc-
tion. Considering together with the relation between RR-1 and E', 
too low heart rate may be potentially harmful in patients with LV dy-
sfunction and fluid overload state. 
In the present study, several parameters were associated with the 
slope in reference to the relationship between RR interval and E' 
with statistical significance. However, the associations were rather 
weak and these parameters explained only 11.5% of the variation 
of the slope in the multiple stepwise linear regression analysis. In 
addition, associated variables were different according to the vary-
ing situations. For example, history of hypertension was not associ-
ated with the slope in the relationship between RR-1 and E' in all 
co-ordinates (r=-0.09, p=0.32), but was the most important deter-
minant for the slope in the relationship between RR-1 and E' in co-
ordinates with RR-1 ranging from 0.6 to 1 second (r=-0.25, p=0.014). </p>

<p>Table 2. Relationship of the slope derived from the correlation between RR intervals and early diastolic mitral annular velocities with clinical and echo-
cardiographic variables </p>

<p>Slope between 
RR-1 &amp; E' </p>

<p>Slope between RR-1 &amp; E' 
in co-ordinates with RR-1 
from 0.6 to 1 second </p>

<p>Slope between 
RR-2 &amp; E' </p>

<p>r 
p 
r 
p 
r 
p </p>

<p>Sex 
0.11 
0.23 
0.06 
0.57 
0.11 
0.23 </p>

<p>Age 
-0.08 
0.37 
0.01 
0.94 
-0.06 
0.53 </p>

<p>Heart failure history 
0.13 
0.16 
0.14 
0.17 
0.25 
0.00 </p>

<p>Mean RR 
-0.03 
0.74 
-0.15 
0.16 
0.22 
0.01 </p>

<p>Systolic blood pressure 
-0.19 
0.04 
-0.11 
0.29 
0.14 
0.12 </p>

<p>Diastolic blood pressure 
-0.15 
0.12 
-0.11 
0.28 
0.09 
0.33 </p>

<p>Diastolic dimension of left ventricle 
0.19 
0.03 
0.17 
0.11 
-0.29 
0.00 </p>

<p>Systolic dimension of left ventricle 
0.13 
0.16 
0.09 
0.37 
-0.38 
0.00 </p>

<p>Ejection fraction 
-0.03 
0.76 
0.00 
0.98 
0.37 
0.00 </p>

<p>Interventricular septum 
0.12 
0.25 
0.00 
0.99 
0.03 
0.79 </p>

<p>Left ventricular posterior wall 
0.05 
0.58 
0.09 
0.39 
-0.08 
0.41 </p>

<p>Aorta 
0.12 
0.18 
0.04 
0.68 
-0.20 
0.03 </p>

<p>Left atrium 
-0.05 
0.57 
0.00 
0.99 
-0.01 
0.89 </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral flow velocity (E, cm/s) 
-0.16 
0.08 
-0.07 
0.51 
0.18 
0.05 </p>

<p>Acceleration time (ms) 
0.10 
0.29 
-0.02 
0.89 
-0.14 
0.13 </p>

<p>Deceleration time (ms) 
-0.03 
0.73 
-0.02 
0.86 
0.08 
0.39 </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral annular velocity (E', cm/s) 
0.16 
0.09 
0.05 
0.66 
0.30 
0.00 </p>

<p>E/E' 
-0.21 
0.02 
-0.08 
0.46 
-0.08 
0.38 </p>

<p>Mitral regurgitation 
0.09 
0.35 
0.13 
0.22 
-0.03 
0.78 </p>

<p>Aortic regurgitation 
0.07 
0.44 
0.06 
0.56 
-0.09 
0.35 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
-0.09 
0.32 
0.25 
0.01 
0.15 
0.12 </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 
0.12 
0.21 
0.09 
0.41 
0.03 
0.78 </p>

<p>Ischemic heart disease 
0.21 
0.02 
0.21 
0.04 
-0.06 
0.51 </p>

<p>RR-1: preceding RR interval, E': early diastolic mitral annular velocity, RR-2: pre-preceding RR interval </p>



<p>Eun Young Kim, et al. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2012.42.9.618 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>Therefore, individualization is necessary for the clinical application 
of this phenomenon. 
In a study observing the relationship between RR intervals and LV 
systolic performances in AF, RR-1 and RR-2 explained 52% and 29% 
of the variation of LV outflow peak ejection velocity, respectively. </p>

<p>22) </p>

<p>In the present study, the relationship between E' and RR-1 or RR-2 
was quite variable from patient-to-patient and also very weak. RR-1 
and RR-2 explained only 12% and 11% of the variation of E', respec-
tively. This finding suggests that E' is mainly determined by intrinsic 
properties of the left ventricle and partially by LV systolic perfor-
mances. The relationship between E' and RR-2 was stronger in pa-
tients with systolic dysfunction than in those with normal systolic 
function. 
Several parameters seemed to be related to the slope in the RR-1 
and E' relationship, but were not statistically significant. For exam-
ple, the mean RR interval was negatively associated with the slope 
in the pilot study and not in the present study. 
13) As shown in Fig. </p>

<p>5, the mean RR interval was positively associated with the slope in </p>

<p>the relationship between RR-1 and E' in patients with a mean RR in-
terval &lt;0.8 second (r=0.21, p=0.082) and negatively in patients with 
a mean RR interval &gt;0.75 second (r=-0.21, p=0.097), although it did 
not reach statistical significance. This finding suggests that the re-
sponse of LV diastolic function to some variables may be biphasic. 
Therefore, the relation between RR-1 and E' is rather complicated 
and further studies are needed in a large number of patients with 
controlled clinical characteristics. In addition, left atrium size was as-
sociated with the slope in the previous study. 
13) The authors have not </p>

<p>been able to elucidate the reasons for the discrepancy and further 
studies are required in a large number of patients. 
There are several limitations in this study. This study was perform-
ed at a single hospital in Asia, lending to small population size. We 
assume that E' represents LV diastolic function well. Although E' is 
one of the most promising parameters for LV diastolic function, it 
is unclear whether E' is also valuable in the condition of AF with 
beat-to-beat changes in LV systolic performance. The candidates of 
this study are heterogeneous with respect to the causes. We could </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparisons between patients with the lowest (negative, slope &lt;-0.55) and the highest (positive, slope &gt;0.57) tertile groups of slopes in the re-
lationship between RR intervals and early diastolic mitral annular velocities (E') </p>

<p>Negative slope (n=39) 
Positive slope (n=39) 
p </p>

<p>Age (years) 
68.0±10.2 
65.2±11.0 
0.25 </p>

<p>Men/Women 
25/14 
31/8 
0.21 </p>

<p>Heart failure history (%) 
17 (44) 
23 (59) 
0.17 </p>

<p>Mean RR interval (sec) 
0.80±0.22 
0.79±0.16 
0.68 </p>

<p>Systolic blood pressure (mm Hg) 
126.2±15.7 
121.3±12.2 
0.13 </p>

<p>Diastolic blood pressure (mm Hg) 
81.6±11.8 
78.6±11.1 
0.26 </p>

<p>Diastolic dimension of left ventricle (cm) 
5.0±0.6 
5.3±0.7 
0.04 </p>

<p>Systolic dimension of left ventricle (cm) 
3.3±0.6 
3.6±0.8 
0.10 </p>

<p>Ejection fraction (%) 
55.6±9.1 
53.7±11.4 
0.41 </p>

<p>Interventricular septum (cm) 
0.99±0.22 
1.03±0.16 
0.32 </p>

<p>Left ventricular posterior wall (cm) 
0.96±0.11 
0.97±0.15 
0.80 </p>

<p>Aorta (cm) 
3.44±0.39 
3.57±0.48 
0.20 </p>

<p>Left atrium (cm) 
5.36±0.75 
5.26±0.69 
0.55 </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral flow velocity (cm/s) 
85.7±22.8 
77.1±18.0 
0.07 </p>

<p>Acceleration time (ms) 
77.4±14.7 
80.9±17.5 
0.34 </p>

<p>Deceleration time (ms) 
185±44.3 
180±41.1 
0.61 </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral annular velocity (cm/s) 
6.43±1.88 
7.36±1.65 
0.02 </p>

<p>Early diastolic mitral flow velocity/ 
Early diastolic mitral annular velocity 
14.4±5.8 
11.1±3.8 
0.00 </p>

<p>Mitral regurgitation (no/mild/moderate/severe) 
29/5/3/2 
27/3/3/6 
0.26 </p>

<p>Aortic regurgitation (no/mild/moderate/severe) 
31/3/5/0 
31/2/4/2 
0.67 </p>

<p>Associated diseases (%) </p>

<p>Hypertension 
30 (77) 
22 (56) 
0.05 </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus 
6 (15) 
9 (23) 
0.38 </p>

<p>Ischemic heart disease 
7 (18) 
1 (3) 
0.01 </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4070/kcj.2012.42.9.618 
www.e-kcj.org </p>

<p>not perform a subgroup analysis due to the limited number of pa-
tients. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This Research was supported by the Chung-Ang University Re-
search Grant in 2010. </p>



<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>Mean RR interval (sec) </p>

<p>Slope </p>

<p>0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 
1.2 
1.4 </p>

<p>RR interval ≥0.75 seconds 
y=-1.54x+1.42 
r=-0.21 
p=0.097 </p>

<p>RR interval ≤0.8 seconds 
y=2.69×-1.78 
r=0.21 
p=0.082 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Biphasic association between mean RR interval and slope in the re-
lationship between preceding RR interval and early diastolic mitral annular 
velocity; Positive in co-ordinates with mean RR interval ≤0.8 second and 
negative in co-ordinates with mean RR interval ≥0.75 second with border-
line statistical significance. </p>

</text></tei>