<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3638180" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
The findings of a case study assessing the design and 
implementation of an <rs id="software-1" type="software">electronic health record</rs> (EHR) in 
the <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">public health system of Colima</rs>, Mexico, its 
perceived benefits and limitations, and 
recommendations for improving the implementation 
process are presented. In-depth interviews and focus 
group discussions were used to examine the 
experience of the actors and stakeholders participating 
in the design and implementation of EHRs. Results 
indicate that the main driving force behind the use of 
EHRs was to improve reporting to the two of the 
main government health and social development 
programs. Significant challenges to the success of the 
EHR include resistance by physicians to use the 
ICD-10 to code diagnoses, insufficient attention to 
recurrent resources needed to maintain the system, 
and pressure from federal programs to establish 
parallel information systems. Operating funds and more 
importantly political commitment are required to 
ensure sustainability of the EHRs in Colimaima. </p>

<p>The electronic health record (EHR) is a tool with 
the potential to improve the quality, safety, and 
efficiency of health services. 
1-9 It can also provide 
data for assessing the health status of the popula-
tion and the performance of the health system 
itself. 
10 11 Many countries in the developing world 
are considering EHR adoption. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>In Mexico, different public and private health-
care institutions have adopted EHRs, including 
Mexico's Social Security Institute, 
13 the Institute 
for Social Security and Services for Government 
Employees, and the health services of several states 
and many private hospitals. As part of the national 
strategy for monitoring and improving the quality, 
functionality, and interoperability of EHRs in 
Mexico, in 2010 the General Directorate of Health 
Information published the Official Mexican 
Standard NOM-024-SSA3-2010. 
14 However, the 
way in which EHRs have been introduced and 
their specific functionality have varied between 
institutions and states, mainly because they were 
developed and implemented before publication of 
the official standard. </p>

<p>13 15 16 </p>

<p>Mexico's health system consists of public insti-
tutions and private providers, all of which are </p>

<p>under the governance of the Ministry of Health. 
The public social security institutions provide ser-
vices to the employees of the formal economic 
sector and civil servants, as well as other public 
sector specific institutions (eg, the federal oil 
company PEMEX and the Armed Forces). Together 
these account for approximately 44% of the popu-
lation. 
17 The rest of the population is served either 
by the System for Social Protection in Health 
(SSPH), also known as Seguro Popular, or by 
private providers. The SSPH is a health insurance 
program for the poor and other vulnerable indivi-
duals and has become one of the main funding 
agencies for the health system in Mexico. Its bene-
ficiaries receive healthcare services through the 
Ministry of Health and the 32 decentralized State 
Health Services (SHS). Colima's SHS provide 
health care to approximately 42% of the state's 
population including the beneficiaries of the SSPH 
and the Oportunidades Program, a conditional 
cash transfer program designed to address health 
and poverty. 
18 These two programs are important 
sources of funds for the operation of the SHS and 
demand detailed and systematic information about 
their affiliates, most often by imposing specialized 
parallel systems. 
The state of Colima demonstrated leadership 
and foresight with the development and imple-
mentation of an EHR beginning in 2005, called 
SAECCOL. Other states, such as Coahuila, 
Aguascalientes, and Yucatán, have expressed inter-
est in adopting SAECCOL. 
19 In fact, the state of 
Coahuila has already started to implement it in 
several hospitals. As they have improved and devel-
oped new modules, they have shared back these 
improvements with Colima, in the spirit of open 
source software development. 
Given the potential benefits of SAECCOL in 
Colima and the possibility that other states in 
Mexico may adopt the system, our purpose was 
to assess the design and implementation of 
SAECCOL, its perceived benefits and limitations, 
and to make recommendations to improve the 
system and implementation process. Despite the 
number of states implementing EHRs, there are no 
studies that document the design and implementa-
tion process or assess the effectiveness of EHRs in 
improving the quality and efficiency of care deliv-
ered in Mexico's public healthcare facilities, and </p>

<p>Open Access 
Scan to access more 
free content </p>

<p>238 
J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:238-244. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-000907 </p>

<p>Case report </p>

<p>few in low and middle income countries. We explored the tech-
nical, organizational, and behavioral issues that may have 
affected EHR adoption and use, and their possible implications 
for other states and countries. Our results have implications 
that can guide other states in Mexico and other countries in 
the design and implementation of an EHR in the public health 
system. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>SAECCOL is an EHR developed and implemented by Colima's 
SHS. It is based on the <rs type="software">MS-SQL</rs> Server database management 
system and <rs type="software">Visual Basic</rs> was used for the development of the 
main application and specific modules. It is a modular system 
(figure 1) that at the time of the study operated mainly in the 
outpatient and emergency departments, offering support ser-
vices such as laboratory, imagery, pharmacy, social work and 
archive modules, the last of which is linked to SSPH's data-
bases. The system allows physicians to record and retrieve the 
clinical history of patients, as well as all consultation data 
including drug prescriptions and laboratory studies requested. 
The system had not been fully implemented in the hospital 
environment at the time of the study, with working sub-
modules only operating in admissions and the pharmacy 
department. The archive module also transfers administrative 
data for the management of the SSPH. 
Framework analysis, a method developed specifically for 
applied research where there are particular questions to be 
answered, a limited time frame, and a pre-designed sample, </p>

<p>20 21 </p>

<p>was used and included in-depth interviews and focus group dis-
cussions to examine the experiences of the actors and stake-
holders who participated in the design and implementation of </p>

<p>EHRs in the state of Colima. 
21 Key informants were selected 
using purposive sampling to ensure that all SHS officials and IT 
experts in Colima who were involved in the development, 
implementation, and operation of SAECCOL were included. In 
addition, four officials of the SSPH and the Oportunidades 
Program at the federal level were also interviewed so that the 
perspectives of the financing agencies would be represented 
(table 1). 
In total, 27 in-depth interviews were held (table 2). Four focus 
groups were conducted with physicians at two health centers 
and two hospitals who were categorized as either pioneer users 
of the system or as new users (table 3). The views were obtained 
of 35 physicians or about 10% of all general physicians working 
in outpatient departments using SAECCOL: (1) doctors 
working in facilities that adopted the system relatively early 
(Centro de Salud Gustavo Vázquez Montes); (2) doctors 
working in facilities that adopted the system relatively recently 
(Centro de Salud Colima); (3) doctors working in hospitals that 
adopted the system relatively early (Hospital de Tecoman); and 
(4) doctors working in hospitals that adopted the system rela-
tively recently (Hospital de Manzanillo). 
The Gustavo Vázquez Montes health center is an urban out-
patient center with three general consultation rooms and 
10 general physicians. The Colima health center has 12 con-
sultation rooms and 22 general physicians. Tecoman and 
Manzanillo hospitals are general hospitals with the four basic 
services (internal medicine, surgery, pediatric, and obstetric) 
with 47 and 60 beds, respectively. Tecoman hospital has 
13 consultation rooms and 12 general physicians, while 
Manzanillo hospital has 15 consultation rooms and 11 general 
physicians. </p>

<p>Figure 1 SAECCOL home-grown modular electronic health record (EHR). SSPH, System for Social Protection in Health. </p>

<p>J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:238-244. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-000907 </p>

<p>
Case report </p>

<p>The Institutional Review Boards of the National Institute 
of Public Health (INSP) and Tulane University approved the 
research protocol. Informed consent was obtained verbally 
from all participants to ensure they fully understood that their 
participation was strictly voluntary, that the data collected 
were to be kept anonymous, and that their comments in the 
discussions would not affect their jobs in any way. Participants 
were also informed they could leave the interview or focus 
group at any time without repercussion. 
Standardized interview and discussion guides were designed 
and tested with volunteer physicians in Mexico City. 
Interviewers were trained to adhere to the interview protocol 
in order to minimize interviewer bias. After informed consent 
was received from key informants, face-to-face interviews were 
conducted, recorded, and transcribed, and focus group discus-
sions were audio and video recorded and transcribed. All inter-
views and focus group discussions were conducted in Spanish. 
Audio and video recordings were kept for further reference and 
will be destroyed at the end of the study. </p>

<p>Interviews were conducted by two native Spanish speak-
ing female researchers with experience in qualitative 
research (August 3-19, 2011, in Colima state and September 
1-19, 2011, in Mexico City). A group of experienced, 
Spanish speaking researchers from INSP and Tulane 
University read the interview and focus group transcripts to 
code the data and group them into key concepts and ana-
lytical axes. Some of the codes were generated according to 
the research questions, while others emerged from the inter-
views. <rs id="software-6" type="software">NVivo</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">9.2</rs> software 
22 was used to analyze the data 
around three analytical axes: design and development of the 
EHR ( planning and organization, criteria, and require-
ments), implementation of the EHR (users, constraints, and 
resources), and the impact of the EHR (benefits, recommen-
dations, and vision for the future) (table 4). Each researcher 
coded separate interviews. Before starting, a coding exercise 
was conducted to make sure all researchers were interpret-
ing the codes in the same way and there was constant dis-
cussion during the analysis to ensure there was agreement 
across researchers. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Design </p>

<p>The EHR in Colima was conceived in 2004 by the General 
Directorate of the SSPH in the state as a way to collect health 
and administrative data on its beneficiaries. The development 
process was an extensive and collaborative exercise, which 
involved practitioners, medical specialists, hospital directors, 
and information technology experts, and lasted more than a 
year (box 1: quote 1). The information technology department 
of the state office of the SSPH was at first in charge of the 
design and development of the EHR but this responsibility 
was later transferred to Colima's SHS IT department. The 
SSPH Affiliation Director, in cooperation with IT specialists 
from the Colima SHS, physicians, and consultants, continued 
to lead the development effort. All participants understood 
that the EHR was being developed to meet the information 
needs of the SSPH, including the need to provide data to the 
federal health information system (box 2: quote 2). Although 
the EHR was not designed to provide information to physi-
cians and other caregivers at the point of care as the key </p>

<p>Table 1 Types of actors and their respective roles in the design, 
implementation, and operation of SAECCOL </p>

<p>Type of actor 
Roll/functions 
N </p>

<p>Federal level officials 
Federal health system governance 
Financing state health services (SHS) through the 
System for Social Protection in Health and/or 
Oportunidades ProgramDeveloping and publishing 
official norms </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>State level officials 
State level governance 
Operate SHSState public policy to establish the 
conditions for SAECCOL development, 
implementation, and operationParticipation in the 
design and implementation of SAECCOL </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Hospital and health 
center managers </p>

<p>Directing health center/hospitals 
Administrative tasks using of information generated 
by SAECCOL </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>IT staff 
Participation in the design of SAECCOL 
Development of SAECCOL's softwareImplementation 
of SAECCOL in health centers and hospitals including 
installation and training of physicians </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Physicians in outpatient 
departments </p>

<p>Use SAECCOL as a tool to improve doctor/patient 
interaction through the use of data recorded in 
SAECCOL </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>Total 
62 </p>

<p>Table 3 Demographic characteristics of focal group discussion 
participants </p>

<p>Demographic characteristics 
N 
% </p>

<p>Type of health center 
Pioneer 
16 
45.7 
Recently implemented 
19 
54.3 
Sex 
Male 
19 
54.3 
Female 
16 
45.7 
Age groups 
20-39 years 
22 
62.9 
40 years or more 
13 
37.1 
Time using SAECCOL 
None 
3 
8.6 
Less than 2 years 
27 
77.1 
2 years or more 
5 
14.3 
Training 
Physician 
31 
88.6 
Nurse 
3 
8.6 
Other 
1 
2.9 </p>

<p>Table 2 Demographic characteristics of in-depth interview 
participants </p>

<p>Demographic characteristics 
N 
% </p>

<p>Type of actor 
Federal level officials 
4 
14.8 
State level officials 
7 
25.9 
Hospital and health center managers 
10 
37.0 
IT staff 
6 
22.2 
Sex 
Male 
20 
74.1 
Female 
7 
25.9 
Age 
20-39 years 
14 
51.9 
40 years or more 
13 
48.1 
Training 
Physician 
17 
63.0 
IT specialist 
6 
22.2 
Other 
4 
14.8 </p>

<p> 
J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:238-244. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-000907 </p>

<p>Case report </p>

<p>objective, it does make some relevant information available 
to them. It was also clear that a key objective was that the 
EHR should comply with the International Classification of 
Diseases, Tenth Revision (ICD-10). At the time SAECCOL 
was first conceived and developed, the official standard 
NOM-024-SSA1-2010 for EHRs had not yet been published, 
but there is now pressure for 100% compliance with it within 
the next 3 years. </p>

<p>Implementation </p>

<p>Colima's SHS IT department led the process of implementing 
the EHR in the state. They implemented the EHR using a 
gradual, phased approach following its launch in 2005. In 
selecting facilities for implementation, priority was placed on 
outpatient services in medium-sized health centers in urban 
areas that had the minimum infrastructure required, including 
electricity, wiring, and internet connectivity. Training in how 
to use the system was conducted by the SHS IT department 
both through facility-specific sessions attended by physicians 
and facility directors, and through pre-service training of resi-
dents of the University of Colima's Medical School (box 3: 
quote 3). The first phase of implementation took place from 
2005 to 2006 with the acquisition of 300 computers, and 
covered almost 80% of the state's health centers and hospitals. 
By that time, the SHS IT department had three areas servicing 
SAECCOL: system development, implementation (installation </p>

<p>and training), and technical support, but no additional operat-
ing funds (box 3: quote 4). </p>

<p>Benefits of the EHR </p>

<p>Facility directors and physicians using the EHR suggest that 
the system has produced a number of important benefits, 
motivating them to continue using the system. For example, 
many respondents mentioned that the organization of health-
care delivery has been improved through the use of the 
appointment scheduling features of the EHR. This saves time 
for patients, who no longer need to wait for hours at the facil-
ity in order to receive care, and for physicians, by saving time 
during consultations and improving the standardization, com-
pleteness, and legibility of medical records (box 4: quote 5). 
A number of physicians also mentioned that the improved 
information from the EHR has allowed them to better under-
stand the medical history of their patients, make diagnoses 
earlier, and reduce medication errors (box 4: quote 6). Facility 
directors also commented that the use of the administrative 
data produced by SAECCOL had improved their management 
capabilities, allowing them to monitor the performance of 
health centers and hospitals. </p>

<p>Challenges </p>

<p>Respondents also identified a number of challenges to the 
adoption and continued use of the EHR. Some respondents </p>

<p>Table 4 Analytical axes and key concepts </p>

<p>Analytical 
axis 
Key concept 
Description of key concept 
Sources References </p>

<p>Design 
Consensus 
Design and development of SAECCOL was with the agreement of all actors and stakeholders 
14 
24 
Advocacy 
Advocacy to develop SAECCOL 
12 
15 
Motivation 
Reasons behind the decision to develop and implement SAECCOL 
8 
19 
Requirements 
Experiences, best practices, and requirements of EHRs 
15 
23 
Time 
Time dedicated to the design and development of SAECCOL 
10 
12 
Funding 
Funds allocated for the design and development of SAECCOL 
7 
8 
Implementation 
Training 
Initial training process 
22 
23 
Hardware and 
communications </p>

<p>Availability of computers and internet connectivity 
20 
26 </p>

<p>Infrastructure 
Health centers and hospitals where SAECCOL was implemented 
19 
27 
Budget 
Budget allocated for SAECCOL's implementation 
8 
10 
Time 
Time dedicated by hospital and health center managers and medical staff to implement SAECCOL 
11 
15 
Benefits 
Quality of care 
Monitoring health care 
16 
35 
Reliable information 
Availability of quality data produced by SAECCOL 
13 
17 
Information improvement 
Availability of statistical data for decision making based on SAECCOL's data 
15 
21 
Health system organization 
Organization of health services (appointments, waiting time, consultation time, process 
standardization) </p>

<p>15 
33 </p>

<p>Data safety 
Data safety 
6 
1 5 
Challenges 
ICD-10 
Physicians experience with the use of SAECCOL and diagnoses using ICD-10 classification 
7 
26 
Difficulties 
Difficulties experienced in the use of SAECCOL 
18 
48 
Implementation discontinuity 
Reasons for interrupting implementation 
10 
18 
Disarticulation 
Disarticulation in the development of SAECCOL by different actors 
13 
15 
Mixed health records 
Need to maintain paper-based records coexisting with EHR 
17 
22 
Lack of infrastructure 
Availability of computers/computers obsolete/no electricity or supplies 
25 
36 
Lack of training 
Experiences with lack of training 
11 
13 
Does not cover all needs 
Evidence that SAECCOL does not cover all the needs of doctors 
20 
33 
Resistance to change 
Evidence of resistance to change from paper-based to EHRs 
12 
14 
Partial use of EHR 
Experiences in partial use of SAECCOL 
11 
13 
Challenges 
Documenting challenges in the implementation of an EHR 
14 
14 </p>

<p>EHR, electronic health record; ICD-10, International Classification of Diseases, Tenth Revision. </p>

<p>J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:238-244. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-000907 </p>

<p>
Case report </p>

<p>mentioned issues of trust. For example, physicians expressed 
suspicion that the SHS introduced EHRs in order to monitor 
medical staff. Respondents at the state level mentioned that 
federal program administrators sometimes have a paternalistic 
view of state officials, are dubious about the quality of EHR 
information, and insist on receiving paper-based reports. A fre-
quently mentioned issue during the interviews and focus group 
discussions was the ICD-10 classification scheme, which plays 
a large role in the EHR system. Physicians complained about 
the difficulty in identifying ICD-10 disease codes, which was 
not part of their medical education (box 5: quotes 7-9). They 
mentioned that they are not trained to use ICD-10, and that 
although most cases are easy to code, a small portion are diffi-
cult, resulting in substantial frustration. SHS officials and staff 
insisted that physicians must make diagnoses using ICD-10, 
but were trying to develop alternative ways to facilitate phys-
ician coding of diagnoses according to ICD-10 to address phys-
ician concerns. To help implement diagnosis coding according 
to ICD-10, at the time of the study, the IT department was 
building a list of the most common diagnoses (as usually 
reported by physicians) with their respective ICD-10 codes; 
however, this effort has still not completely resolved the coding 
issue. Other challenges mentioned include insufficient training, 
which causes excessive time to be spent on entering data, frus-
tration with features that ensure the security of records, the 
rigidity of the system, and resistance to change. </p>

<p>General results </p>

<p>There was a common view that the EHR (SAECCOL) is a valu-
able tool, and most of those interviewed agreed it was neces-
sary to use it more effectively to improve the quality of 
healthcare so that it mainly benefits patients. There were 
important differences among the respondents regarding its 
functionality and usability. While young doctors found no diffi-
culty in adapting their workflow in the consultation room to 
work with the EHR, older doctors complained that it was diffi-
cult to use. Doctors in health centers and hospitals where 
SAECCOL has recently been deployed also complained, but 
they also indicated interest in receiving more training in order 
to master its use. The one issue that respondents agreed upon 
was the difficulties with the use of ICD-10. They all expressed 
frustration with the need to classify their diagnoses and that it 
was not part of their training as physicians. They also agreed 
that Colima's SHS IT department has made important efforts 
to address those difficulties, but that the issue is still not 
resolved. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The purpose of the study was to assess the development and 
implementation of SAECCOL, its perceived benefits and limita-
tions, and to make recommendations to improve the system and 
implementation process. Our results show that the main driving 
force behind the design, development, and implementation of 
SAECCOL was the strengthening of mandated reporting to the 
SSPH and Oportunidades Program, two of the main programs to 
improve health and social development in Mexico. The decision 
to design and develop an EHR to meet the information-reporting 
requirements of the SSPH and federal health information systems 
affected the potential of the EHR to influence the quality, effi-
ciency, and cost of health service delivery. The collaborative effort 
of physicians, hospital administrators, IT specialists, and state 
officials was fundamental in the design and development process. 
The University of Colima was instrumental in the decision to </p>

<p>follow a 'home grown' EHR development strategy. As a result, 
and in spite of its reporting focus, physicians saw benefits from 
improved data availability, a better understanding of their 
patient's history, and reduced medication errors. However, these 
benefits fall short of the potential benefits of an EHR for improv-
ing quality of care. 
The SHS of Colima was able to take advantage of the infor-
mation needs of important health programs to secure funds for 
initial investment for the development and implementation of 
their EHR, which proved to be a very successful strategy. The 
implementation process was phased and systematic, with 
appropriate attention to infrastructure requirements, and 
included efforts to involve stakeholders and generate support 
for adoption among health workers. From our perspective, this 
is a highly recommended best practice. However, there were 
several significant challenges to the success of the EHR. First, 
physicians were concerned that the EHR was designed primar-
ily to evaluate their performance. They also felt strongly that 
coding ICD-10 diagnoses is a clerical function being forced on 
them through the EHR and should not be part of their medical 
practice. 
23 Emphasizing the importance of performance moni-
toring as part of the culture of information and as a way to 
receive organizational feedback may positively influence the 
way physicians perceive and react to the EHR's monitoring cap-
acity. Additionally, as ICD-10 coding is needed for standardiza-
tion of the collection and reporting of EHR data, it must be 
complied with; nevertheless, the efforts of the IT department 
to develop alternative features to help the use of this classifica-
tion scheme may improve the experience of physicians. 
Another solution to this controversial aspect of SAECCOL 
would be to allow doctors annotate unclassified diagnoses 
which would be coded later by specialized coders. 
However, following the initial investment, the SHS did not 
receive further funds and the EHR was not explicitly supported 
by state policy. Nevertheless, SHS IT personnel continued with 
the development of new modules. Difficulties in providing 
technical support and computer maintenance developed, 
mainly because of a lack of resources (eg, gas, vehicles, and 
computer parts). In addition, the political environment pre-
vented the channeling of financial resources to the project. 
EHR use started to decline as providers required training and 
computers needed to be repaired or replaced, and the project 
faltered. As part of a set of innovative strategies to make the 
EHR sustainable, the SHS signed an agreement with the 
University of Colima medical school that all students should be 
trained in the use of the EHR. 
Another factor endangering the sustainability of the EHR was 
the lack of an information policy and normative framework at 
the time of design and development, which impeded the ability 
to promote governance and to negotiate for operating funds. 
Also, any change in Colima's SHS administration presents sus-
tainability challenges because newly appointed leaders need to 
be convinced of the value of the EHR so that they will provide 
resources for its ongoing maintenance, operation, and develop-
ment. Fortunately, with the change of administration in 2010, a 
new perspective on e-government was adopted and the EHR 
was incorporated into the Governor's State Development Plan, 
which provided the political basis for directing the necessary 
resources from both state and federal health programs to 
strengthen the EHR project. Moreover, the Oportunidades 
Program, through the SSPH, requested that additional informa-
tion requirements be met through a parallel information system 
called Sistema Nominal de Información en Salud, but inclusion </p>

<p> 
J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:238-244. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-000907 </p>

<p>Case report </p>

<p>of the EHR in the State's Development Plan served as leverage 
to negotiate its use as the sole source of information for federal 
health programs, thus avoiding the need for parallel systems and 
allowing a more efficient use of resources. 
The implementation of an EHR in the public health sector is 
subject to multiple pressures and requires a vast amount of 
financial and human resources. Operating funds are required to 
ensure sustainability, but political commitment is also neces-
sary. This must be expressed in a state or national strategic 
plan in order to withstand administrative/political changes. 
The authors are well aware that most public institutions do 
not follow or adhere to such a process. Colima did not begin 
with a clear strategic plan but rather was responding to the 
information needs of funding agencies, but nevertheless was 
able to recover midway under the incoming new administra-
tion. This was a lesson learned the hard way. 
Overall, our results suggest that designing and implementing 
EHRs is a gradual and often slow process which requires atten-
tion to be given to technical, organizational, and behavioral 
factors. The results of the study are very much in line with 
those of previous research. For example, in a study on the imple-
mentation and adoption of national EHRs in secondary care 
facilities in England, Sheikh et al 
24 found that the speed of 
implementation was slower than expected, and that the EHRs 
had a narrower focus and substantially less functionality than 
originally planned, with no discernible benefits for clinicians or 
patients among early adopters of the system. In a systematic 
review of studies on this issue, Boonstra and Broekhuis 
25 also 
found that, overall, EHR adoption rates are low and that there is 
often resistance from physicians. The authors concluded that 
the process of EHR implementation should be treated as a man-
agerial change project, rather than simply as a technical strategy. 
Ideally, the decision to move towards an EHR at the state or 
national level should be part of a national strategic plan. This 
promotes ownership and evidence of ability to meet informa-
tion needs in order to advocate for funds, thus avoiding the cre-
ation of parallel systems. The evidence from Colima highlights 
the importance of including stakeholders in the planning phase 
in order to address their specific information needs. 
26 Just as 
important is the sharing of experiences within a country and 
south-south collaboration can improve the chances of success-
ful implementation, scalability, and sustainability. It is impera-
tive that funders recognize the potential synergies of their 
investments in health information systems and technology as a 
way to promote diagonal effects with positive spill-over effects 
to other health problems beyond the intended programs. </p>

<p>Box 1 Consensus </p>

<p>Quote 1 </p>

<p>▸ … the designers from the Secretary of Health came to meet 
with us, talk to us, and give us their comments after seeing 
the EHR [electronic health record]. "What should it contain?" 
they asked. The records, ok, the health record has this and 
that. Then, they would go do their job, bring it back and 
present it to us. We would then give them feedback: "Do you 
know? This window should move from here to there. Maybe 
apply a drop down menu, add this or that, or this is easier." 
That's how it was done. (Health center director) </p>

<p>Box 2 Source of information for the System for Social 
Protection in Health (SSPH) and the Oportunidades Program </p>

<p>Quote 2 </p>

<p>▸ From the start, the project was developed with the belief that 
it would cover everything, that it was going to be installed in 
every health center and that it was going to be the primary 
source of information, and we keep going in this process to 
reach that goal; fortunately it was developed to that purpose 
from the beginning. (State IT specialist) </p>

<p>Box 3 Implementation </p>

<p>Quote 3 </p>

<p>▸ Training was done at different levels; we went to the univer-
sity and explained, because many doctors are still students. 
It was easier dealing with them because they all have a good 
understanding of computers. So, we went to the university, 
took the EHR system to them, and left it with them. At the 
beginning we used to provide training to the young doctors 
and in a couple of days they were ready to use the system, 
even in one day. We did this so that once they graduated 
they each had a EHR chip and when they got to their com-
munities we didn't have to train them again… and start all 
over again… (State director) </p>

<p>Quote 4 </p>

<p>▸ When the first computer buying was done, 300 computers 
to cover about 80% of the facilities, it's when it is decided 
to make a structure based in three areas: software devel-
opment, and of course most of us continued working 
there, an implementation area, dedicated exclusively to 
training and follow up, and another for technical support, 
which was the infantry, the one in which to serve… (State 
IT specialist) </p>

<p>Box 4 Benefits </p>

<p>Quote 5 </p>

<p>▸ When the system works ok I think it's perfect; you enter 
your password and access the EHR, you can check your 
starting time, your patient list, you select a patient, open his/ 
her file and I can review observations in past encounters and 
make a medical note a lot easier and clearer and it can be 
reviewed by any other doctor who may access the record. 
(Hospital director) </p>

<p>Quote 6 </p>

<p>▸ We now have a more specific, focused, and simpler 
clinical history. (Health center focus group discussion 
participant) </p>

<p>J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:238-244. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-000907 </p>

<p>
Case report </p>

<p>Box 5 Challenges </p>

<p>Quote 7 </p>

<p>▸ It happened to me many times that I was not able to write in the 
diagnosis and since I wasn't able to do so, I had to write the 
diagnosis in a separate box in the hope that when it was 
printed, at least my diagnosis would show up somewhere in the 
form. But it wasn't the correct diagnosis… (Hospital director) </p>

<p>Quote 8 </p>

<p>▸ It is very difficult to fill in the form in a short period because there 
is a set amount of time for the consultation: for the use of 
devices and systems, to conduct a physical check-up and make 
a presumptive diagnosis plus writing the prescription; and for the 
preparation of the particulars and setting up the next appoint-
ment. If we put this in time, it would take 30-40 minutes per 
patient. If we only did the health consultation note, we are talking 
about a period of 10-15 minutes per patient. (Hospital director) </p>

<p>Quote 9 </p>

<p>▸ In our case, what we do is to print it with a diagnostic, the 
closest we can find, and write notes in the analysis section 
to register our diagnostic, the real one, to put it that way. 
This is how we have being functioning. (Hospital focus group 
participant) </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We would like to thank the state of Colima and all 
participants in this project. </p>

<p>Contributors JEHA, LSPM, ALE, MAB, MLD, DH, BP, ES, and ASP: conception and 
study design; LSPM, MAB, and ASP: field work supervision; LSPM, MAB, and ES: 
data analysis and interpretation; JEHA, LSPM, ALE, MLD, DH, BP, ES, and ASP: 
drafting the paper, critical review, and final review and approval of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding Support for this study was obtained from MEASURE Evaluation, which is 
funded by the US Agency for International Development (USAID) through Cooperative 
Agreement GHA-A-00-08-00003-00. The views expressed in this publication do not 
necessarily reflect the views of USAID or the US Government. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which permits 
others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license 
their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited 
and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>



<p> 
J Am Med Inform Assoc 2013;20:238-244. doi:10.1136/amiajnl-2012-000907 </p>

<p>Case report </p>

</text></tei>