<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3202757" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Kaposi's sarcoma (KS) is caused by Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV; human herpesvirus 8). KS is an 
AIDS-defining cancer, and it is changing in the post-antiretroviral therapy (post-ART) era. In countries with ready access to 
ART, approximately one-third of KS cases present in patients with undetectable HIV loads and CD4 counts of &gt;200 cells/l. 
This is in contrast to pre-ART era KS, which was associated with systemic HIV replication and CD4 counts of &lt;200 cells/l. Us-
ing primary patient biopsy specimens, we identified a novel molecular signature that characterizes AIDS KS lesions that develop 
in HIV-suppressed patients on ART: KSHV transcription is limited in HIV-suppressed patients. With one exception, only the 
canonical viral latency mRNAs were detectable. In contrast, early AIDS KS lesions expressed many more viral mRNAs, including, 
for instance, the viral G protein-coupled receptor (vGPCR). </p>

<p>IMPORTANCE This is the first genomewide study of Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV) transcription in KS lesions 
in the post-antiretroviral (post-ART) era. It shows that the gene expression of KSHV is altered in patients on ART, and it pro-
vides clinical evidence for active AIDS (as characterized by high HIV load and low CD4 counts) being a potential modulator of 
KSHV transcription. This implies a novel mode of pathogenesis (tightly latent KS), which may inform KS cancer treatment op-
tions in the post-ART era. </p>

<p>Citation Dittmer DP. 2011. Restricted Kaposi's sarcoma (KS) herpesvirus transcription in KS lesions from patients on successful antiretroviral therapy. mBio 2(6):e00138-11. mean cycle threshold (C T ) of 26.69, with a 95% confidence inter-
val (CI) of 24.69 to 28.68. The ␤-actin mRNA level for a group of 
AIDS KS samples had a mean C T of 29.31 with a 95% CI of 26.52 
to 32.10. There was no statistical difference in the ␤-actin levels 
based on the Welch two-sample t test. If anything, we had slightly 
more mRNA from the post-HAART biopsy specimens, and thus a 
higher sensitivity of detecting lytic KSHV mRNAs if there were 
any. This suggests that the lack of lytic mRNA detection in the 
HIV-suppressed KS lesions was not due to lesser sensitivity or 
systematic technical differences among both groups, but reflects 
the biology of the virus. 
Based on our recent experience in analyzing KS mRNA levels in 
clinical trials (12, 13), we choose to normalize to a common stable 
mRNA that encodes latency-associated nuclear antigen (LANA), 
vCycl, and vFLIP (9). This mRNA as well as the LANA protein is 
expressed in every KSHV-infected KS tumor cell, latent and lytic, 
based on in situ studies (9, 14). The level of this "tricistronic" 
mRNA does not change dramatically upon reactivation in pri-
mary effusion lymphoma (PEL) (15, 16) and is also present upon 
replication in endothelial cells (17). We therefore normalized all 
mRNA signals to LANA gene expression. Normalizing to LANA 
mRNA thus normalized to the number of KS tumor cells within a 
biopsy specimen rather than nonneoplastic tumor infiltrating 
and/or stromal cells. Figure 2C demonstrates the heterogeneity of 
KS lesions with regard to LANA-expressing cells. This uses a larger 
data set of KS lesions in HIV-suppressed patients than that in 
reference 13. The mRNA levels of two different so-called house-
keeping genes, coding for actin and hypoxanthine phosphoribo-
syltransferase (HPRT), correlated well (Pearson correlation, r ϭ 
0.85) (Fig. 2C). The mRNA levels of two different latent genes, 
coding for vCyc and LANA, correlated well (Pearson correlation, r 
ϭ 0.96). However, the correlation between either viral mRNA and 
either host mRNA was substantially lower, with a mean of 0.54 
and a range of 0.45 to 0.64. This attests to the fact that different KS 
lesions contain different numbers of KSHV-infected cells. The 
possibility to thus factor out non-tumor cells represents one of the 
major advantage of using viral mRNA levels as biomarkers as op-
posed to cellular mRNAs, for which it is often not possible to 
discern between tumor cell inherent changes and changes due to 
differences in tumor content within a biopsy specimen. 
Median mRNA levels for each gene were computed (Fig. 2B). 
Every KSHV lytic mRNA was present at higher levels in KS biopsy 
specimens from the early ART, high-HIV, low-CD4 patients com-
pared to post-ART KS samples from patients with undetectable 
HIV loads. The average difference was 3.77-fold with 95% CI of 
2.97-to 4.56-fold and P Յ 0.005 by paired Wilcoxon's rank sum 
test of medians for each mRNA. The two exceptions (indicated by 
* in Fig. 2A) were orf26 and orf61. 
Within-group variation in mRNA levels was higher for KS bi-
opsy specimens from patients in the pre-HAART era compared to 
biopsy specimens from HIV-suppressed KS patients, with a mean 
difference of standard deviations (SDs) between groups of a 2.32 
C T (95% CI, 1.95 to 2.68; P Յ 0.005 by paired Wilcoxon's rank 
sum test). As expected, latent viral mRNAs were most abundant 
and varied the least. Analysis of residuals identified the following 
genes that did not differ between groups: the KSHV latent genes 
coding for vCYC and LANA, but also orf10, orf17, orf44, orf46, 
and orf75 and the K7 and kBZIP genes. 
Representative examples of individual mRNAs are shown in 
Fig. 2B. As expected, the levels of a latent mRNA, vCYC, did not </p>

<p>FIG 1 Unsupervised cluster analysis of KSHV transcription in KS (heat map </p>

<p>representation). Shown are relative levels of KSHV mRNAs in KS biopsy spec-
imens obtained from patients with low CD4 counts and detectable HIV viral 
loads (pre) or with CD4 Ն200 and no detectable HIV (post). Red indicates 
maximal, yellow intermediate, and white low levels of individual mRNAs. 
With the exception of a single case (arrow at bottom), none of the post-
HAART KS biopsy specimens show evidence of KSHV lytic mRNAs. In con-
trast, in Ͼ50% of lesions from pre-HAART KS, the full complement of lytic 
mRNAs was detectable. </p>

<p>Dittmer </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00138-11 </p>

<p>differ significantly between groups. In contrast, levels of the viral 
GPCR homolog (an early lytic mRNA) were lower in lesions from 
HIV-suppressed patients. 
Next, we compared the pattern of lytic mRNA levels in KS 
biopsy specimens to the pattern of lytic mRNAs in PEL. We saw no 
significant correlation between lytic mRNAs in KS and those in 
PEL after viral reactivation (data not shown): i.e., those that are 
part of the canonical cascade of gene expression leading to suc-
cessful viral replication, viral egress, and consequent host cell 
death (18). This suggests that within a KS lesion, KSHV expression 
is dysregulated. It does not seem to follow the highly ordered 
cascade of gene expression needed for viral replication, and many 
KSHV proteins that were classified as lytic, based on early studies 
in PEL, seem to serve a function in tumorigenesis as well as for 
virus production. The precedent here is the K1 protein, which we 
found in a subset of KS lesions (19), even though the gene coding 
for it had been classified as a "lytic" gene. Another one is K2/vIL6, </p>

<p>which responds directly to interferon 
(IFN) signaling in the absence of produc-
tive replication and to the viral transacti-
vator RTA (replication and transcription 
activator) in the context of viral reactiva-
tion and replication (20). Culture-based 
studies also lend credence to the involve-
ment of many more than the canonical 
latent genes in KS pathogenesis. Grund-
hoff and Ganem postulated a role for in-
termittent lytic reactivation for KSHV 
persistence (21), and Chandriani and 
Ganem recently found evidence for vari-
able, but significant expression of vIL6 
and K1 in PEL cell lines (22). This is the 
first report of this phenomenon in clinical 
KS biopsy specimens. 
Implications for clinical studies. 
AIDS KS takes a more aggressive clinical 
course than transplant-associated or clas-
sic KS (reviewed in reference 23). Classic 
KS in particular is associated with minus-
cule amounts of systemically circulating 
virus (24). Our study provides new evi-
dence for a postulated role of HIV in 
AIDS KS, perhaps through HIV-tat (25) 
or perhaps through cellular cytokines that 
reactivate KSHV in the setting of low CD4 
T cells. There exists another explanation 
with potentially great clinical relevance. 
Particular drugs within the ART regimen 
could stymie KSHV reactivation and rep-
lication. One such candidate drug, nelfi-
navir, has recently emerged (26). Finally, 
to borrow from detailed insights into 
HSV-1 reactivation (27), it may be that in 
patients with high CD4 counts there ex-
ists a sufficient number of KSHV cognate 
CD8 cells, which even though they cannot 
prevent lesion occurrence per se, may 
limit viral reactivation and rapidly elimi-
nate cells that express lytic KSHV pro-
teins. There are limitations to this inter-
pretation, which need further studies. We could not separate the 
effect of HIV levels from CD4 depletion, as these were coupled 
AIDS KS. We also cannot discern the impact of different ART 
regimens with regard to KSHV transcription. It is quite possible 
that particular drug regimens influence KS and KSHV differen-
tially (28). 
By profiling KSHV mRNAs genomewide, we find evidence for 
two molecular classes of KS: those with a "lytic" viral mRNA pro-
file, as defined by detectable mRNA levels for Ն50% of viral genes, 
and those with tightly latent KSHV. This was not a consequence of 
copy number or fraction of infected cells, as in our comparisons, 
the signals were normalized to the constitutive viral LANA 
mRNA. This is the first study of KS lesions from HIV-suppressed 
KS patients in the post-HAART era. It establishes a novel bio-
marker for the stratification of KS. 
We speculate that KS lesions that express viral lytic proteins, 
such as the viral thymidine kinase or the viral phosphorylase, may </p>

<p>FIG 2 (A) Three-point moving averages of mean KSHV mRNA levels in KS biopsy specimens from the </p>

<p>patients with low CD4 counts (solid line) and patients with undetectable HIV load and CD4 counts of 
Ն200 (open circles). Since real-time qPCR is quantitative within an extended linear range, we calcu-
lated the relative abundance of each viral mRNA compared to LANA mRNA as 1.8 Ϫ⌬CT(LANA) and 
expressed it as percentage of LANA mRNA on a logarithmic scale (vertical axis). (B) Pairwise compar-
isons of individual KSHV mRNAs. Shown are box plots for the levels of two KSHV lytic mRNAs 
(v-cyclin [cyc], vGPCR) relative to a KSHV latent mRNA (LANA). The vertical axis is on a log 10 scale. 
The horizontal labels signify patients with AIDS or nondetectable HIV KS. The bold horizontal line 
indicates the median, box ends the lower and upper quartiles, and dotted lines the range of the data. 
Outliers are indicated by dots. (C) Pairwise correlations of log 2 mRNA levels (C T ) for the two cellular 
genes coding for actin (hu. actin) and hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyltransferase (HPRT) and 
two latent viral genes coding for the viral cyclin (orf72f1) and LANA (lat273F), which originate from the 
same constitutive promoter. Note that higher mRNA levels correspond to lower C T numbers. Shown 
are scatter plots and a linear regression fit line below the diagonal, distribution of C T s for the individual 
genes across all samples on the diagonal, and pairwise Pearson correlation coefficients above the diag-
onal of this panel matrix. </p>

<p>Restricted KSHV Transcription in Post-ART KS Lesions </p>

<p>November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00138-11 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 3 </p>

<p>be susceptible to treatment with antiviral drugs, but that the ma-
jority of lesions in HIV-suppressed individuals are not. 
Viral RNA profiling. RNA was isolated and analyzed by real-
time qPCR for all KSHV mRNAs as previously described (18). All 
primers have a predicted melting temperature (T m ) of 60 Ϯ 1°C. 
Real-time qPCR was conducted under universal cycling condi-
tions (40 cycles) with SYBR green dye as the method of detection. 
The final primer concentration was 250 nM in a total 20.0-l 
reaction. Total RNA was isolated using triazole (Sigma, Inc.) and 
subjected to DNase I treatment (Zymed, Inc.). RNA was reverse 
transcribed using a cDNA archive kit (Applied Biosystems, Inc.). 
RNA integrity was evaluated using an <rs id="software-0" type="software">Agilent 2100 bioanalyzer 
series C and software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Agilent, Inc.</rs>.) and qPCR conducted on an 
Opticon-2 MJR instrument (Bio-Rad Inc.). The instrument error 
was Յ6%. Control reactions (reverse transcriptase [RT] negative) 
were uniformly negative. All measurements were conducted in 
triplicate. 
The mean cycle threshold (C T ) values, representing relative 
mRNA abundance on a log 2 scale, were first normalized to KSHV 
latency-associated nuclear antigen (LANA) mRNA and then stan-
dardized (Z-transformation [29]) to the median of each biopsy 
specimen. We did not find a correlation between variability of 
gene expression as measured by SD and overall expression levels 
(data not shown). This demonstrates that the data were not bi-
ased. 
Unsupervised clustering was conducted using Arrayminer 
(Optimaldesign, Inc.). Additional calculations were performed in 
R, version 2.5.0. The linear trend was computed using robust re-
gression (30). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank first and foremost the patients for contributing biopsy speci-
mens, Susan Krown for advice and invaluable insights, B. Damania, and 
A. O'Hara for critical reading and C. Hilscher for expert technical help. 
Additional deidentified KS biopsy specimens were obtained from the 
AIDS and cancer specimen resource (ACSR). 
This work was supported by the AIDS malignancy consortium and 
Public Health Service grants CA109232, DE018304, and CA019014 to 
D.P.D. </p>



<p>Dittmer </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2011 Volume 2 Issue 6 e00138-11 </p>

</text></tei>