<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3013677" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Alternative splicing is emerging as a major mech-
anism for the expansion of the transcriptome and 
proteome diversity, particularly in human and other 
vertebrates. However, the proportion of alterna-
tive transcripts and proteins actually endowed 
with functional activity is currently highly debated. 
We present here a new release of <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> which 
now provides a unique annotation resource of 
human protein variants generated by alternative 
splicing. A total of 256 939 protein variants from 
17 191 multi-exon genes have been extensively 
annotated through state of the art machine learn-
ing tools providing information of the protein type 
(globular 
and 
transmembrane), 
localization, 
presence of PFAM domains, signal peptides, GPI-
anchor propeptides, transmembrane and coiled-
coil segments. Furthermore, full-length variants can 
be now specifically selected based on the annotation 
of CAGE-tags and polyA signal and/or polyA sites, 
marking transcription initiation and termination 
sites, respectively. The retrieval can be carried out 
at gene, transcript, exon, protein or splice site level </p>

<p>allowing the selection of data sets fulfilling one or 
more features settled by the user. The retrieval inter-
face also enables the selection of protein vari-
ants showing specific differences in the annotated 
features. <rs id="software-17" type="software">ASPicDB</rs> is available at <rs corresp="#software-17" type="url">http://www .caspur.it/ASPicDB</rs>/. </p>

<p>Alternative splicing is a well characterized mechanism 
which, coupled with alternative initiation and termination 
of transcription (1), may expand the transcriptome and 
proteome complexity in human and other organisms by 
over one order of magnitude with respect to the number of 
annotated genes (2,3). In particular, it is now widely 
demonstrated that virtually all multi-exon genes may 
generate multiple transcripts and protein variants (3,4)  and that the splicing process is tightly regulated in differ-
ent physiological conditions, tissues or developmental 
stages (5). Furthermore, alterations of the splicing 
process can be observed in several genetic diseases and 
in cancer (6-10). 
The huge amount of EST sequences (11) together with 
the relevant reference genome sequence has been used to 
carry out an extensive analysis of alternative splicing in </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +39 080 5443588; Fax: +39 080 5443317; Email: graziano.pesole@biologia.uniba.it 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Rita Casadio. Tel: +39 0512094005; Fax: +39 051242576; Email: casadio@alma.unibo.it </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that in their opinion, the first two authors are the joint First Authors. </p>

<p>D80-D85 Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue 
Published online 4 November 2010 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq1073 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>human through the ASPIC algorithm (12-14). The alter-
native splicing pattern of human multi-exon genes, 
determined by ASPIC, has been collected in <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs>, a 
database resource which presents some unique features 
with respect to other similar databases (15). The ASPIC 
algorithm implements an optimization strategy that, per-
forming a multiple alignment of all available transcript 
data (including full-length cDNA and EST sequences) to 
the relevant genome sequence, detects the set of introns 
that minimizes the number of splicing sites. It also gener-
ates through a directed-acyclic graph combinatorial 
procedure the minimal set of non-mergeable transcript 
isoforms compatible with the detected splicing events 
(14). The reliability of splicing isoforms detected 
by ASPIC has been recently established through a 
comparative assessment (16). 
The advent of massive transcriptome sequence data 
generated by RNA-Seq (17) is steadily increasing the 
number of validated splicing sites and isoforms in 
human and other organisms thus suggesting that a 
fraction of alternative splicing events are the result of 
background noise in the splicing process (18) which gen-
erates non-functional isoforms expressed at low level. 
Therefore, extensive research efforts are required to dis-
tinguish functional species-specific variants from 
non-functional ones originated from neutral drift in the 
splicing process, as well as to asses the biological role of 
functional isoforms. 
The annotation of the protein variants predicted with 
ASPIC is an essential step for exploring the functional 
and structural diversity of the proteins originating 
from the same gene by means of alternative splicing and 
therefore for unraveling the complex physiological effects 
of alternative splicing events (19). Indeed, currently avail-
able databases, such as <rs type="software">ASD</rs> (20), <rs id="software-20" type="software">ASAP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-20" type="version-number">II</rs> (21), 
<rs type="software">ASTALAVISTA</rs> (22) and <rs type="software">H-DBAS</rs> (23), mostly collect 
information on alternative transcripts at the mRNA level, 
without considering the effect of alternative splicing on the 
protein structure and function. The <rs type="software">ProSAS</rs> (24) database 
contains structural information as derived from compara-
tive modeling procedure, but due to the limitations of the 
modeling techniques, only $15% of the human transcripts 
are endowed with a reliable protein structure prediction. 
<rs type="software">ASPICdb</rs> aims at filling the gap of structural and func-
tional annotation of protein splicing variants, by adopting 
a set of analysis and prediction tools that do not rely only 
on annotation transfer by sequence similarity. It provides 
a thorough computational annotation of predicted human 
protein variants including PFAM domains (25), 
N-terminal signal peptides, GPI-anchor propeptides, 
transmembrane domains, subcellular localization and 
other features, also reporting the relevant crosslinks to 
<rs type="software">UniprotKB/Swissprot</rs> (26) and <rs type="software">PDB</rs> databases (27). A 
comprehensive annotation of the domain architecture 
and other structural features could also be extremely 
useful to critically assess the reliability of the functional 
classification provided the GO System (25), which still 
neglects much of the relevant information for alternative 
splicing products. 
In addition, in consideration of the fragmented nature 
of the available transcript data, the new version of </p>

<p><rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> include the annotation of CAGE tags (28) in 
order to identify truly transcription initiation sites and 
discriminate between full-length isoforms using alternative 
transcription initiations and 5 
0 -partial transcripts for 
which a full-length CDS and the encoded protein cannot 
be reliably predicted. </p>

<p>ANNOTATION PIPELINE OF HUMAN PROTEIN 
VARIANTS </p>

<p>The computational pipeline implemented for supplement-
ing the <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> protein sequences with functional and 
structural annotations is represented in Figure 1 and inte-
grates several state-of-the-art tools for similarity search 
and for machine-learning based prediction of protein 
features starting from residue sequence. 
For each one of the 256 939 protein variants coming 
from 17 191 human genes, a first layer of annotation 
consists in the retrieval of similar sequences from the two 
major repositories containing well-characterized proteins, 
namely: (i) the <rs type="software">UniProtKB/SwissProt</rs> data base (26) 
(rel. 2010_07, June 2010), that contains 547 011 protein 
sequences with curated annotations, including 517 802 
principal entries and 29 209 splicing variants (UniProt 
Consotium, 2010); (ii) <rs type="software">the Protein Data Bank</rs> (rel. July 
2010), that contains resolved three dimensional structures 
for 50 171 different protein sequences (29). 
Similarity searches were performed with <rs type="software">BLAST</rs> (30) 
setting the E-value threshold to 10 
À3 . 
A second layer of annotation is obtained by mapping the 
structural and functional domains collected in the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Pipeline for the annotation of alternative transcripts. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue D81 </p>

<p>PFAM-A database (rel. 24.0, October 2009) that contains 
curated multiple sequence alignments based on hidden 
Markov models (HMM) for 8691 families, 2985 domains, 
162 repeats and 74 motifs (25). The PFAM models were 
mapped on the <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> protein sequences by means of 
the pfam_scan.pl program (ftp://ftp.sanger.ac.uk/pub/ 
databases/Pfam/Tools/), based on <rs id="software-34" type="software">HMMER</rs><rs corresp="#software-34" type="version-number">3.0</rs> (31). 
The third layer of annotation results from the integra-
tion of several predictors based on machine learning tools, 
such as neural networks, hidden Markov models, support 
vector machines and conditional random fields. Since 
most of the methods take advantage of the evolutionary 
information encoded in sequence profiles, we compiled 
them starting from the similar sequences retrieved with 
two PSI-BLAST iterations (setting the E-value threshold 
to 10 
À3 ) from the UniRef90 data set consisting of 
6 955 504 sequences (July 2010). The first predicted 
features are the presence of N-terminal signal peptide 
and of C-terminal GPI-anchor propeptides, with 
SPEPlip (32) and PredGPI (33), respectively. Both the 
methods are among the best available predictors, scoring 
with accuracy as high as 95% the former and 88% the 
latter. When present, the signal peptide and the propeptide 
are cleaved from the protein sequence. The presence of 
coiled-coil domains is predicted with CCHMM-PROF 
that is able to locate coiled-coil segments in protein se-
quences with 80% accuracy (34). a-Helical transmem-
brane domains are then predicted with <rs type="software">ENSEMBLE</rs> 
(35), that discriminates transmembrane from globular 
proteins with false positive and false negative rates both 
equal to 3%. The same tool is adopted for predicting the 
number and the position of transmembrane segments 
along the sequence, with an accuracy of 90% on the 
protein base. The subcellular localization of globular 
proteins is predicted with <rs type="software">BaCelLo</rs> (36), which discrimin-
ates four localizations in animals (secretory pathway, 
cytoplasm, nucleus and mitochondrion) with 74% 
accuracy. </p>

<p>ASPicDB CONTENT AND ANNOTATION OF 
PROTEIN VARIANTS </p>

<p>Table 1 reports some statistics on the data contained in the 
current version of <rs id="software-37" type="software">ASPicDB</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-37" type="version-number">2.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-37" type="version-date">August 2010</rs>) 
which refers only to human multi-exon genes annotated 
in NCBI Entrez Gene (37) with at least one RefSeq </p>

<p>transcript (38) and the relevant Unigene cluster (39)  collecting all available gene-specific cDNA and EST 
sequences. 
In the current version of <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> some more features 
are available including the annotation of the CAGE tags 
(28) which define truly transcription initiation sites and a 
comprehensive protein annotation. A total of 12 789 394 
CAGE tags have been mapped thus supporting constitu-
tive or alternative transcription start sites. To each tran-
script variant a 'unique identifier' (16) has been associated 
in order to make possible the unambiguous comparison 
with alternative transcripts collected in other databases. 
All alternative proteins collected in <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> have been 
compared with <rs type="software">UniprotKB/SwissProt</rs> (26) and <rs type="software">PDB</rs> (29)  databases. The results of similarity searches are reported 
in Table 2. Only 17% of the <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> protein sequences 
are identical to proteins deposited in <rs type="software">UniProtKB/ SwissProt</rs> database. However, 94% of the sequences 
share significant similarity with proteins annotated in the 
same database, prompting the possibility of a reliable an-
notation transfer. Moreover, 54% of <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> sequences 
are similar to proteins deposited in the <rs type="software">PDB</rs> suggesting 
that their structures can be modeled, at least partially. 
A considerable amount of PFAM models map on the 
<rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> sequences (Table 2). On the overall, 71% of 
sequences match with at least one model. This result is 
in agreement with the reported sequence coverage on the 
human proteome of the current PFAM release, which is 
equal to 72.5% (25). It is worth noticing that, although all 
the models map with an E-value &lt; 10 
À5 , only 20% of the 
matches are complete (that is, involve the whole model). A 
note of caution is necessary when inferring features from 
partial matches and the actual extent of the match has to 
be evaluated for each instance. 
Table 3 summarizes the results of the annotation 
process performed with machine learning based predict-
ors. Two percent of proteins were not predicted since they 
are shorter than 50 residues, 16% of proteins are predicted 
as transmembrane and 82% are predicted as globular. 
Among the globular proteins, 12% are predicted as 
secreted, 35% as cytoplasmic, 27% as globular and 8% 
as mitochondrial. Signal peptides and GPI-anchor 
propeptides are predicted in the 12 and 0.7% of the </p>

<p>Table 2. Annotation of human variants upon similarity and PFAM 
searches </p>

<p>Sequence repository 
No of proteins </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>No of genes </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>UniProtKB/SwissProt, % 
E-value &lt; 10 
À3 , % 
239 814 (93) 
17 054 (99) 
Identical, % 
42 601 (17) 
13 043 (76) 
PDB 
E-value &lt; 10 
À3 , % 
137 528 (54) 
11 062 (64) 
Identical, % 
1079 (0.4) 
316 (2) 
PFAM 
All matches, E-value &lt; 10 
À5 , % 
183 483 (71) 
14 205 (83) 
Complete matches, 
E-value &lt; 10 
À5 , % </p>

<p>46 630 (18) 
5621 (33) </p>

<p>a The percentages are computed with respect to 256 939 protein variants 
and 17 191 genes. </p>

<p>Table 1. Statistics of the <rs id="software-50" type="software">ASPicDB</rs> content (v<rs corresp="#software-50" type="version-number">2.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-50" type="version-date">August 2010</rs>) </p>

<p>ASPicDB v2.0 </p>

<p>Genes 
17 191 
Transcripts 
319 092 
Proteins 
256 939 
Exons 
390 886 
Splicing sites 
351 345 
U2 
302 164 
U12 
1712 
Splicing events 
233 717 </p>

<p>The number of splicing sites belonging to the U2 or U12 class and of 
splicing events is also reported. </p>



<p>sequences, respectively. Coiled-coil domains are predicted 
in 1.3% of the proteins. At the gene level, 30 and 92% of 
genes encode for transmembrane and globular proteins, 
respectively. Since the sum exceed 100%, it follows that 
22% of the genes encode for both globular and transmem-
brane variants. The same consideration holds for the other 
annotations as reported in Table 4. The amount of genes 
predicted to encode for proteins with different subcellular 
localization achieves 56%. This is partially explained by 
the fact that <rs type="software">BaCelLo</rs> scores with an accuracy equal to 
74%, which is the lowest among the methods included in 
the pipeline. Indeed the discrimination between the 'cyto-
plasmic' and the 'nuclear' classes is still a difficult task for 
all subcellular localization predictors (40). When the two 
classes are merged together, the <rs type="software">BaCelLo</rs> accuracy in-
creases up to 91%, but the rate of genes encoding for 
proteins with different localizations is still as high as 
44%, suggesting that localization diversity is inherent in 
the <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> protein variants. The structure of PFAM 
annotations is also highly variable: 38% of genes encode 
for variants matching with different number and/or type 
of PFAM models. Altogether, results listed in Table 4 
suggest that alternative transcripts can encode for 
proteins endowed with different structural and functional 
features. <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> provides a unique resource reporting 
the annotation of alternative splicing variants at the 
protein level and an interface enabling the discovery of 
such differences. </p>

<p>ASPicDB RETRIEVAL INTERFACE </p>

<p><rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> can be accessed though simple or advanced 
query forms. The simple query form allows the user to 
obtain the splicing pattern of one or more genes selected 
according to several criteria (e.g. HGNC name, RefSeq or 
Unigene accession IDs, etc.). The advanced query form 
allows the user to search for (i) genes, (ii) transcripts; 
(iii) exons; (iv) splicing sites; and (v) proteins, fulfilling 
different criteria (e.g. exons in a given length range, 
etc.). Depending on the choice separate query forms 
appear. The 'gene', 'transcript' and 'splicing sites' query 
forms have been described previously (15) whereas the 
'exon' and 'protein' query forms are novel features of 
this version of <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs>. The exon query form allows 
the user to select exons in a given length range, belonging 
to a specific type (initial, internal or teminal), flanked by 
specific splicing sites or associated to one or more 
Affimetrix ExonArray probeset IDs. 
The 'protein' query form allows the retrieval of tran-
scripts encoding proteins isoforms of a specific class (e.g. 
globular or transmembrane), subcellular localization (e.g. 
mitochondrion, nucleus, secretory, cytoplasm) or contain-
ing one or more features, including occurrence and 
number of PFAM or transmembrane domains, GPI-
anchor propeptides, signal peptides. Finally, it is also 
possible to retrieve genes encoding for alternative 
proteins that show differences in the above mentioned 
features. </p>

<p>ASPicDB OUTPUT </p>

<p>After a simple or advanced query has been submitted the 
output for each selected gene is shown which is organized 
in eight panels. </p>

<p>(1) Gene information reports a summary of the genomic 
and transcript data used by ASPIC to generate the 
prediction, downloadable by the user and links to 
other popular prediction programs such as ASAP2 
(21), ASD (20) and ACEVIEW (41) as well as to 
ASPIC results for orthologous genes in other species. 
(2) Gene structure view provides a schematic graphical 
view of the gene structure including all predicted 
exons/introns. 
(3) Predicted transcripts show a graphical representation 
of the assembled transcripts with predicted annota-
tions of 5 
0 -UTR, CDS and 3 
0 -UTR, CAGE tag 
mapping, Premature Termination Codons (PTC) 
and polyA sites. 
(4) Transcript table lists the details of all predicted alter-
native transcripts including their length, number of 
exons and presence of a protein coding sequence. 
The 'variant type' column lists all the alternative 
splicing events using a RefSeq mRNA as the refer-
ence transcript. The transcript signature is also 
reported which consists in a unique ID for alterna-
tively spliced variants generated according to (16). 
(5) Predicted proteins show a graphical representation 
of the encoded proteins with matching domains 
(Figure 2). For each mapped domain the sequence </p>

<p>Table 3. Machine learning-based prediction of the human proteins 
deposited <rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> </p>

<p>Annotation 
No. of proteins </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>No. of genes </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Type 
Globular, % 
210 608 (82) 
15 513 (90) 
Transmembrane, % 
41 561 (16) 
5439 (32) 
Localization (globular proteins) 
Secretory pathway, % 
31 917 (12) 
7348 (43) 
Cytoplasm, % 
90 046 (35) 
10 327 (60) 
Nucleus, % 
69 167 (27) 
8183 (48) 
Mitochondrion, % 
19 478 (8) 
4698 (27) 
Domains 
Signal peptide, % 
30 508 (12) 
5153 (30) 
GPI-anchor propeptide, % 
1673 (0.7) 
629 (4) 
Coiled-coil segments, % 
3423 (1.3) 
497 (2.8) </p>

<p>a The percentages are computed with respect to 256 939 protein variants 
and 17 191 genes. </p>

<p>Table 4. Differences among alternative proteins encoded by the same 
human gene </p>

<p>Annotation 
No. of genes </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, % </p>

<p>Type (globular/transmembrane) 
3817 (22) 
Subcellular localization (globular proteins) 
9593 (56) 
Presence of signal peptide 
3939 (23) 
Presence of GPI-anchor propeptide 
591 (3.4) 
Presence of coiled-coil domains 
464 (2.7) 
Number of transmembrane helices 
2140 (12) 
PFAM models (all matches) 
6575 (38) </p>

<p>a The percentages are computed with respect to 17 191 genes. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue D83 </p>

<p>coordinates are reported and different symbols 
indicate whether the mapping involves the complete 
domain or only a part of it. 
(6) Protein table lists the predicted features of the alter-
native proteins that include: (i) the best hits obtained 
from the similarity searches against the <rs type="software">UniProtKB/ SwissProt</rs> and <rs type="software">PDB</rs> databases, along with the 
identity value and coverage of the alignment with 
respect to both the query and the subject sequence 
lengths; (ii) the features predicted by the pipeline 
based on machine-learning tools. 
(7) Predicted splice sites shows the multiple alignment 
between the genomic sequence and the expressed se-
quences (i.e. mRNAs and ESTs) near the boundaries 
(splice sites) of all predicted introns. 
(8) Intron table lists all predicted introns and their 
relevant features; All results can be also downloaded 
by the user in textual format following the 'gene 
transfer format' (GTF) (see the Gene Information 
panel). </p>

<p>After a query at the gene, transcript, exon, protein or 
splice site level has been completed, the user can also 
download specific sets of sequences in FASTA format 
for further analyses, e.g. genes, transcripts, exons, 
proteins, 5 
0 -UTRs, coding sequences, 3 
0 -UTRs, introns 
as well as sequence regions surrounding splice site 
boundaries. </p>

<p>FUTURE PERSPECTIVES </p>

<p><rs type="software">ASPicDB</rs> is an ongoing project and we plan to further 
develop it in the next releases. In particular we plan to </p>

<p>add specific annotations on splicing regulatory elements 
and their interacting RNA-binding proteins located both 
in exonic and intronic regions. We also plan to update 
alternative splicing prediction by using the huge amount 
of RNA-Seq data which are now being produced by next 
generation sequencing, possibly annotating splicing events 
as constitutive or tissue-specific. Furthermore, literature-
screened splicing patterns related to diseases will be 
annotated as they represent potential molecular biomark-
ers and possible targets for therapy. Finally, the inclusion 
in the database of data related to other organisms will 
certainly favor a better understanding of the alternative 
splicing process through comparative analyses. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Ministero dell'Istruzione, dell'Universita`e della Ricerca: 
Fondo Italiano Ricerca di Base: 'Laboratorio 
Internazionale di Bioinformatica' (LIBI); Laboratorio di 
Bioinformatica per la Biodiversita`Molecolare (MBLAB) 
and Telethon (project GGP01658). Funding for open 
access charge: Ministero dell'Universita`e della Ricerca: 
Fondo Italiano Ricerca di Base: 'Laboratorio 
Internazionale di Bioinformatica' (LIBI). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Figure 2. 'Predicted proteins' panel for gene CSMD3 (CUB and Sushi multiple domains 3). The gene is predicted to encode for 12 transcripts and 7 
different protein sequences. Variants labeled as PR1, PR2 and PR3 are identical to the isoforms reported in the CSMD3_HUMAN entry of 
<rs type="software">SwissProt/UniprotKB</rs>. Two more variants are reported in that file, although lacking of experimental annotations. Several repetitions of Sushi 
and CUB domains are predicted with PFAM (25) and represented with symbols indicating whether the model is completely or partially mapped 
to the sequence. The two transmembrane helices are predicted with <rs type="software">ENSEMBLE</rs> (35). </p>





<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, Database issue D85 </p>

</text></tei>