<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3865143" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The purpose of this study was to examine the effect of sleep deprivation on 
flow experience. 
Methods: Sixteen healthy male volunteers of mean age 21.4±1.59 (21-24) years participated 
in two experimental conditions, ie, sleep-deprivation and normal sleep. In the sleep-deprived 
condition, participants stayed awake at home for 36 hours (from 8 am until 10 pm the next day) 
beginning on the day prior to an experimental day. In both conditions, participants carried out a 
simple reaction time (psychomotor vigilance) task and responded to a questionnaire measuring 
flow experience and mood status. 
Results: Flow experience was reduced after one night of total sleep deprivation. Sleep 
loss also decreased positive mood, increased negative mood, and decreased psychomotor 
performance. 
Conclusion: Sleep deprivation has a strong impact on mental and behavioral states associated 
with the maintenance of flow, namely subjective well-being. 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Actiware</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.71.0</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Philips Respironics Inc</rs>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Kaida and Niki </p>

<p>from 2 to 10 seconds. Participants have to detect a stimulus and 
respond using a button on a keyboard as quickly as possible. 
The stimulus (a small counter increasing in milliseconds) is dis-
played in the center of a computer screen. The PVT used in the 
present study was the 5-minute version. 
30 Median reaction times 
and lapses (times more than 500 msec) were calculated. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>Paired t-tests were used to compare the sleep-deprived and 
normal sleep conditions. The Wilcoxon signed-rank test 
(nonparametric test, n=16) was also applied. Significance 
levels were set at P,0.05. All statistical analyses were 
conducted using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs> 
version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">22.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). </p>

<p>Results 
actigraphy and sleep diary data </p>

<p>Sleep deprivation was confirmed by sleep diary and acti-
graphy data. Total sleep time on the day preceding the 
experiment was also calculated from the actigraphy data. 
The results indicate no significant difference between the 
conditions [371.5±97.67 minutes in the sleep depriva-
tion condition; 434.37±126.12 minutes in the normal 
sleep condition; t(15)=1.67, effect size (d)=0.40, P=0.12]. 
Total sleep time on the night before the experiment in the 
normal sleep condition was 457.2±124.40 minutes. Sleep effi-
ciency was 98.7% (calculated by dividing total sleep time in 
the actigraphy data by time in bed recorded in the sleep diary). 
Times of going to sleep and waking (actigraphy data) were 
1.59±101.42 minutes and 9.36±148.77 minutes, respectively. 
This "night owl" sleep schedule may have been due to the 
flexible time schedule typical of university students. 
We also calculated the number of periods of immobility 
using the actigraphy data. This was done using only 15 data sets 
because data from one of the subjects could not be analyzed 
due to technical problems with one of the recording devices. 
From this inspection, six immobile periods were detected in 
four participants. The cumulative immobile periods for the 
four participants were 42, 44, 82, and 122 minutes (mean 
48.3±18.42 minutes) over 36 hours. Although our results show 
that the participants did not undergo total sleep deprivation in 
the strict sense (ie, absolutely no sleep at all), they were still in 
a condition of "severe sleep loss", which would be sufficient 
to examine the effects of sleep loss on flow experience. </p>

<p>Flow experience </p>

<p>Flow experience along all three dimensions decreased in 
the sleep-deprived condition as compared with the normal </p>

<p>sleep condition [confidence, t(15)=3.70, d=0.69, P,0.01, 
Wilcoxon's T (T) =2.84, P,0.01; challenge, t(15)=3.18, 
d=0.64, P,0.01, T=2.72, P,0.01; and immersion, t(15)=2.30, 
d=0.51, P,0.05, T=2.05, P,0.05], as shown in Figure 2. </p>

<p>Profile of mood status </p>

<p>Mood status deteriorated after sleep loss, except for the 
anxiety and sadness dimensions, as shown in Figure 3. 
Sleepiness, confusion, and fatigue scores were higher in the 
sleep-deprived condition than in the normal sleep condition 
[sleepiness, t(15)=4.14, d=0.73, P,0.01, T=2.98, P,0.01; 
confusion, t(15)=2.92, d=0.60, P,0.01, T=2.35, P,0.05; 
fatigue, t(15)=3.79, d=0.70, P,0.01, T=3.00, P,0.01; and 
anger, t(15)=2.07, d=0.47, P,0.05, T=1.62, P,0.10]. Vitality 
was lower in the sleep-deprived condition [t(15)=3.90, d=0.71, 
P,0.01, T=2.79, P,0.01]. There were no significant differ-
ences for anxiety and sadness [anxiety, t(15)=1.49, d=0.36, 
P=0.07, T=1.39, P=0.16; sadness, t(15)=0.35, d=0.09, P=0.72, 
T=0.36, P=0.71]. </p>

<p>Psychomotor vigilance test </p>

<p>Median reaction times were significantly longer in the sleep-
deprived condition compared with the normal sleep condition 
[t(15)=2.09, d=0.48, P,0.05, T=3.05, P,0.01], which means 
that psychomotor vigilance deteriorated after a night of sleep 
loss, as shown in Figure 4. There was no significant difference 
in lapse rates between the two conditions [t(15)=1.40, d=0.34, 
P=0.18, T=1.62, P=0.10], as shown in Figure 4. </p>

<p>correlation analysis </p>

<p>As shown in Table 1, all three factors of flow were signifi-
cantly and positively correlated with vitality (r=0.45 to 0.57), </p>

<p>Confidence 
Challenge 
Immersion </p>

<p>Figure 2 Flow checklist scores (range 1-7). 
Notes: *P,0.05; **P,0.01. Confidence refers to "confidence in competence", 
challenge refers to "achieving goals", and immersion refers to "positive emotion and 
absorption". Vertical lines (ie, deviation) in the figures show standard errors. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Sleep deprivation and flow experience </p>

<p>and negatively correlated with fatigue (r=−0.43 to −0.68) and 
sleepiness (r=−0.38 to −0.55). However, none of the three 
factors of flow showed any significant correlations with PVT 
indices (median reaction time and lapses). Median PVT was 
significantly and positively correlated with fatigue (r=0.35) 
and sleepiness (r=0.37). Median PVT and lapses were 
strongly correlated with each other (r=0.91). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study reveals that all aspects of flow experience 
(confidence, challenge, and immersion) decrease after sleep 
deprivation. In addition, flow indices were significantly 
and negatively correlated with fatigue (r=−0.43 to −0.68) 
and sleepiness (r=−0.38 to −0.55). These results suggest 
that sleep/sleepiness is an important factor in flow experi-
ence, and maintaining a low level of sleepiness is essential 
in order to induce flow. To the best of our knowledge, </p>

<p>the relationship between sleep loss and flow experience has 
not been previously examined. 
Consistent with previous studies, positive mood (vital-
ity) was reduced and negative mood (sleepiness, fatigue, 
confusion, anger) was increased after sleep deprivation. </p>

<p>19,31-34   Importantly, this study found that flow experience and vitality 
were positively related (r=0.45 to 0.57). The results support 
our assumption based on the cognitive energy model 
11,12 that 
lower levels of cognitive energy, due to sleep deprivation, 
reduce the motivation to engage in challenging tasks and 
hence impede flow experience. This is consistent with another 
report in which sleep deprivation was found to impede con-
centration and creative thinking. </p>

<p>35   This work was supported by JSPS KAKENHI (25705022). </p>

<p>Table 1 Pearson's product-moment correlation coefficient (r) </p>

<p>PVT 
Median </p>

<p>Lapses </p>

<p>Flow 
confidence </p>

<p>Challenge </p>

<p>Immersion </p>

<p>POMS 
anxiety </p>

<p>Sadness </p>

<p>Anger </p>

<p>Vitality </p>

<p>Fatigue </p>

<p>Confusion </p>

<p>Sleepiness </p>

<p>PVT 
Median </p>

<p>0.91 </p>

<p>−0.05 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>−0.07 </p>

<p>0.19 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>−0.34 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>−0.01 </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>lapses </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>−0.22 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>−0.07 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>Flow 
Confidence </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>−0.45 </p>

<p>−0.07 </p>

<p>−0.38 </p>

<p>0.45 </p>

<p>−0.43 </p>

<p>−0.63 </p>

<p>−0.55 </p>

<p>challenge </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>−0.24 </p>

<p>−0.02 </p>

<p>−0.34 </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>−0.43 </p>

<p>−0.43 </p>

<p>−0.38 </p>

<p>immersion </p>

<p>−0.10 </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>−0.02 </p>

<p>0.57 </p>

<p>−0.68 </p>

<p>−0.15 </p>

<p>−0.52 </p>

<p>POMs 
anxiety </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>−0.15 </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>sadness </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>−0.51 </p>

<p>0.29 </p>

<p>−0.15 </p>

<p>anger </p>

<p>−0.32 </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>0.54 </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>Vitality </p>

<p>−0.59 </p>

<p>−0.38 </p>

<p>−0.67 </p>

<p>Fatigue </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p>confusion </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>Note: Bold type indicates statistical significance at P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: PVT, psychomotor vigilance test; POMS, Profile of Mood Status. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/neuropsychiatric-disease-and-treatment-journal </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment is an international, peer-
reviewed journal of clinical therapeutics and pharmacology focusing 
on concise rapid reporting of clinical or pre-clinical studies on a 
range of neuropsychiatric and neurological disorders. This journal 
is indexed on PubMed Central, the 'PsycINFO' database and CAS. </p>

<p>The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2014:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Sleep deprivation and flow experience </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>