<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3400965" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Summary: Alternative Splicing Effects ASsessment Tools (AS-EAST) 
is an online tool for the functional annotation of putative proteins 
encoded by transcripts generated by alternative splicing (AS). When 
provided with a transcript sequence, AS-EAST identifies regions 
altered by AS events in the putative protein sequence encoded by the 
transcript. Users can evaluate the predicted function of the putative 
protein by inspecting whether functional domains are included in the 
altered regions. Moreover, users can infer the loss of inter-molecular 
interactions in the protein network according to whether the AS 
events affect interaction residues observed in the 3D structure of 
the reference isoform. The information obtained from AS-EAST will 
help to design experimental analyses for the functional significance 
of novel splice isoforms. 
Availability: The online tool is freely available at http://as-alps. 
In higher eukaryotes, genes often produce alternatively spliced 
transcripts (AS transcripts). Many AS events have been actively 
detected with high-throughput experimental methods, such as 
RNA-Seq and microarrays (Hallegger et al., 2010). However, the 
functions of putative proteins encoded by AS transcripts (termed 
'AS isoforms') have not been experimentally analyzed in many 
cases. Functional annotation tools for transcripts with novel patterns 
of splicing are desirable to infer the functional significance of AS 
isoforms. There are few tools for analyzing AS isoforms translated 
from novel transcripts queried by users. <rs id="software-4" type="software">AltAnalyze</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="url">http://www. altanalyze.org</rs>) identifies AS events using RNA-Seq or microarray 
data and shows how these events may affect domain composition. 
However, it does not provide information on the effects of AS on 
the 3D structures of AS isoforms. MAISTAS (Floris et al., 2011)  assesses whether user-queried AS isoforms are structurally plausible 
proteins, but explicit functional annotations are not provided. 
Previously, we developed a pipeline that detects regions altered 
by AS events (termed 'AS regions') in AS isoforms using genome 
sequences and full-length transcript data (Yura et al., 2006). 
The pipeline then evaluates the impact of AS events on the </p>

<p> *  To whom correspondence should be addressed. </p>

<p>interactions between the AS isoforms and other molecules by 
identifying interaction residues from 3D structure data of relevant 
molecular complexes. All of the data derived from the pipeline 
are provided in the AS-ALPS database (Shionyu et al., 2009). 
In this article, we describe AS-EAST that annotates and analyzes 
user-uploaded transcript sequences using AS-ALPS. AS-EAST 
determines whether the transcript encodes a novel AS isoform 
and annotates such functional sites in the AS isoform as residues 
interacting with other molecules. We provide an example: AS-EAST 
predicts that a novel AS isoform of mitogen-activated protein kinase 
1 (MAPK1) in human skeletal muscle inhibits the signaling pathway 
by removing residues that interact with ATP and substrate proteins. </p>

<p>2 OVERVIEW OF AS-EAST </p>

<p>2.1 Input data </p>

<p>To detect and annotate AS events in a user-submitted transcript 
(termed 'query transcript'), AS-EAST accepts a FASTA-formatted 
transcript sequence. A novel pattern of splicing detected with RNA-
Seq or exon junction microarray often determines whether a certain 
exon in a known transcript model is skipped. AS-EAST has a user 
interface for generating an exon-skipped transcript sequence from 
the known transcript sequences stored in AS-ALPS. For example, 
RNA-Seq data (Wang et al., 2008) shows that the fourth exon of 
the MAPK1 transcript tends to be skipped in human skeletal muscle 
(Fig. 1a). This splicing pattern is novel because no fourth exon-
skipped transcript is found in RefSeq or Ensembl transcript datasets 
stored in AS-ALPS. Users can build a fourth exon-skipped transcript 
sequence by checking the checkbox of 'exon 4' and selecting the 
'Generate' button. Then, the transcript sequence excluding the fourth 
exon is shown in FASTA format. </p>

<p>2.2 AS region detection </p>

<p>First, a genome contig sequence aligned to the query transcript 
sequence with the largest value of both length coverage and sequence 
identity is selected using MEGABLAST (Altschul et al., 1997). 
An alignment of the query transcript and the contig sequence 
is performed using SPLIGN (Kapustin et al., 2008). AS-EAST 
searches the AS-ALPS database for transcripts mapped on the 
same region of the contig as the query transcript. The user can 
select one of the transcripts as a reference transcript. Second, the 
protein-coding sequence (CDS) of the query transcript is predicted 
by identifying the longest open reading frame (ORF) or FrameDP 
program (Gouzy et al., 2009). Users can also use the ORF starting </p>

<p>© The Author(s) 2012. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>AS-EAST </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (a) User interface for generating query transcript data. As a reference 
of exon-skipped transcript sequence generation, the mapping results of RNA-
Seq data from Wang et al. (2008) are shown at the top of the schematic 
figure in the human dataset. Mapping of the RNA-Seq data was performed 
using the <rs id="software-8" type="software">TopHat</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">Trapnell et al</rs>., <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-date">2009</rs>) with default parameters. 
(b) Interaction residues obtained from 3D structure information assigned to 
a reference isoform. The deletion-type AS region is shown in red. Interaction 
residues are denoted with arrowheads in the schematic view and stick models 
in the 3D structure view. The ligand is shown in a space-filling model. The 
3D structure is shown with <rs id="software-9" type="software">Jmol</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="url">http://www.jmol.org</rs>/) </p>

<p>with the users' chosen first codon as the CDS. By comparing the 
genomic regions corresponding to the CDSs of a reference transcript 
and the query transcript, AS-EAST identifies CDSs changed through 
AS (termed 'AS CDSs'). The AS CDSs of a reference transcript that 
have no corresponding region in the query transcript are classified 
as deletions, and the AS CDSs of the query transcript that have 
no corresponding region in a reference transcript are classified as 
insertions. 
From the AS CDSs, AS-EAST identifies amino acid sequence 
regions changed through AS, termed 'AS regions'. An amino acid 
sequence encoded by a deletion AS CDS whose length is a multiple 
of 3 is identified as a deletion-type AS region. In addition, an amino 
acid sequence encoded by an insertion AS CDS whose length is 
a multiple of 3 is identified as an insertion-type AS region. When 
the length of an AS CDS is not a multiple of 3 and the reading 
frame of the 3 -flanking CDS is shifted, the amino acid sequence 
encoded by the AS CDS and the 3 -flanking CDS is identified as a 
substitution-type AS region. </p>

<p>2.3 Functional annotation </p>

<p>To analyze the functional effect of AS on a putative protein encoded 
by the query transcript (query isoform), annotations of the query 
isoform with functional regions are performed using InterProScan 
(Zdobnov and Apweiler, 2001). From the results of <rs type="software">InterProScan</rs>, 
functional domains from the Pfam, Gene3D and SUPERFAMILY 
databases and transmembrane regions predicted with TMHMM 
are shown in AS-EAST. Moreover, AS-EAST annotates the query 
isoform using functional amino acid residue information (Fig. 1b). 
Amino acid residues interacting with other molecules (interaction 
residues) are identified from the 3D structure data of protein 
complexes (Yura et al., 2006). AS-EAST assigns 3D structures to 
the query isoform with BLASTP (Altschul et al., 1997). AS-EAST 
determines whether 3D structures are assigned to AS regions on 
the basis of the criteria by Yura et al. (2006). According to the 
alignment of the sequences of the reference isoform and the assigned 
3D structures, interaction residues are projected to the corresponding 
residues in the AS regions. In the MAPK1 example, the query 
isoform has a protein kinase domain, according to the results of 
InterProScan. However, the query isoform lacks a region that has 
some residues constituting the ATP-binding pocket and interaction 
residues and is predicted to lose protein kinase activity. Therefore, 
the expression of the AS isoform encoded by the fourth exon-skipped 
transcript in human skeletal muscle might inhibit the MAP kinase 
signaling pathway and regulate cell proliferation/differentiation as 
a result. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Akihiro Yamaguchi, Kei Iida, Atsushi Hijikata, 
Kazuki Shinoda and Kei Yura for helpful comments and discussions. </p>

<p>Funding: Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (B) #18370061 (to 
M.G.) and the Targeted Proteins Research Program (TPRP) and a 
Grant-in-Aid for Young Scientists (B) #23770187 (to M.S.) from 
the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology 
of Japan. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: none declared. </p>





</text></tei>