<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3297833" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>† Rosaria Santangelo and Cesare 
Mancuso have contributed equally to 
this work. </p>

<p>Bilirubin-IX-alpha (BR) is the final product of heme metabolism through the heme oxyge-
nase/biliverdin reductase (HO/BVR) system. Previous papers reported on the microbicidal 
effects of the HO by-products biliverdin-IX-alpha, carbon monoxide and iron, through either 
direct or indirect mechanisms. In this paper the evidence of a virucidal effect of BR against 
human herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) and the enterovirus EV71 was provided. 
Bilirubin-IX-alpha, at concentrations 1-10 μM, close to those found in blood and tissues, 
significantly reduced HSV-1 and EV71 replication in Hep-2 and Vero cell lines, respectively. 
Bilirubin-IX-alpha inhibited viral infection of Hep-2 and Vero cells when given 2 h before, con-
comitantly and 2 h after viral infection. Furthermore, BR retained its antiviral activity even 
complexed with a saturating concentration of human serum-albumin. Moreover, 10 μM BR 
increased the formation of nitric oxide and the phosphorylation of c-Jun N-terminal kinase 
in Vero and Hep-2 cell lines, respectively, thus implying a role of these two pathways in 
the mechanism of antiviral activity of the bile pigment. In conclusion, these results support 
the antiviral effect of BR against HSV-1 and enterovirus in vitro, and put the basis for fur-
ther basic and clinical studies to understand the real role of BR as an endogenous antiviral 
molecule. </p>

<p>The heme oxygenase/biliverdin reductase (HO/BVR) axis is the 
main metabolic pathway by which heme is degraded. The com-
bined action of these enzymes converts heme into ferrous iron 
(FeII), carbon monoxide (CO), and biliverdin-IX-alpha (BV) 
which is the precursor of bilirubin-IX-alpha (BR; Maines, 1997; 
Mancuso and Barone, 2009). For several years, the by-products 
of the HO/BVR axis were considered mere waste products, but 
over the past two decades, a number of investigators have focused 
their attention on both HO/BVR and their products in an attempt 
to elucidate their true biological functions. Stocker et al. (1987b) 
described the antioxidant properties of BR, and 6 years later Verma 
et al. (1993) proposed a role for CO as an endogenous neuro-
modulator. These observations were followed by numerous papers 
demonstrating CO's important role as a regulator of synaptic 
transmission, cardiac function, and vessel tone (Wu and Wang, 
2005). Bilirubin-IX-alpha helps maintain the cell's redox equi-
librium by activating important pro-survival signaling pathways, 
such as those involving the proto-oncogene Akt or the mitogen-
activated protein kinase family (MAPK), and by scavenging reac-
tive oxygen and nitrogen species (ROS and RNS, respectively; 
Stocker et al., 1987b; Minetti et al., 1998; Kaur et al., 2003; Man-
cuso et al., 2006b, 2008). These findings suggest that up-regulation 
of the HO/BVR axis is a useful mechanism for improving cells' 
responses to stress, and substances known to increase HO activity </p>

<p>in vitro are being explored as potential drugs for the treatment 
of free radical-induced diseases (Mancuso and Barone, 2009). In 
addition, the up-regulation of HO was shown to play an impor-
tant role against bacterial and viral infections. The overexpression 
of the inducible isoform of HO (HO-1) displayed a significant 
antiviral activity against enterovirus and hepatitis viruses (Zhu 
et al., 2010; Tung et al., 2011). With regard to the by-products of 
the HO system involved in this antiviral activity, BV was shown to 
interfere with human hepatitis C virus (HCV) and human herpes 
virus (HHV)-6 replication as well as to reduce the cytopathic effect 
of human immunodeficiency type 1 virus (HIV) in Huh or MT-
4 cells (Mori et al., 1991; Nakagami et al., 1992; Lehmann et al., 
2010; Zhu et al., 2010). In addition, CO inhibited the growth of 
enterovirus, E. coli, P. aeruginosa as well as S. aureus (Nobre et al., 
2007; Tung et al., 2011; Desmard et al., 2012) and iron almost 
completely decreased HCV core mRNA and protein (Hou et al., 
2009). Taken together these results underlined a major role for HO 
in antiviral and antibacterial defense. That said, it is noteworthy 
to mention that no data are available to date about the potential 
antiviral activity of BR produced by BVR. As mentioned before, BR 
was shown to serve as an efficient scavenger for ROS which, in turn, 
are currently viewed as effectors of the antimicrobial activity of the 
immune response (Bogdan et al., 2000; Fang, 2004; Fialkow et al., 
2007), therefore a direct antiviral role for BR is unlikely. On the 
other hand, recent findings demonstrated alternative mechanisms </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>March 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 36 | 1 </p>

<p>Santangelo et al. </p>

<p>The antiviral effect of bilirubin </p>

<p>for the cytoprotective activity of BR, including the stimulation of 
nitric oxide (NO) release and the modulation of the MAPK system 
in pheochromocytoma cells and primary cultures of rat cerebel-
lar granules (Mancuso et al., 2008). NO plays an important role 
in the antiviral defense (Croen, 1993; Akaike and Maeda, 2000) 
and it is also an intermediate in the bactericidal activity of certain 
drugs (Timmins et al., 2004; Koide et al., 2009). Moreover, the up-
regulation of specific MAPK, such as the c-Jun N-terminal kinase 
(JNK), was shown to increase the cytoprotective defense against 
viruses (Hrincius et al., 2010). 
The aim of this work was to explore the antiviral activity of BR 
in vitro and the plausible intracellular systems involved in this pro-
tective effect. Since intracellular BR exists in the free form whereas 
in the bloodstream the bile pigment is bound to human serum-
albumin (HSA), the antiviral activity of both BR and BR-HSA 
were studied. The viral species against which BR and BR-HSA 
were tested are the human herpes simplex type 1 virus (HSV-
1), a DNA virus which belong to the Herpesviridae family, and 
enterovirus 71 (EV71) which belong to the Picornaviridae family 
(RNA viruses). Both these viruses are responsible for important 
acute and chronic diseases in humans. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>CHEMICALS AND ANTIBODIES </p>

<p>All chemicals were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, 
MO, USA) unless otherwise stated. Bilirubin-IX-alpha (Frontier 
Scientific, Carnforth, Lancashire, UK) was dissolved in sodium 
hydroxide (0.1 M) at a concentration of 10 mM and further diluted 
in double-distilled water. Bilirubin-IX-alpha solution was freshly 
prepared before each experiment and protected from light. The 
formation of the BR-HSA complex, at saturating concentra-
tions of the protein, was allowed by incubating BR and HSA 
for 10 min at 37˚C in the dark at a ratio up to 1:2 (Mancuso 
et al., 2006a). The fluorescent cell-permeant dye 4-amino-5-
methylamino-2 ,7 -difluorofluorescein (DAF-FM) diacetate was 
purchased from Molecular Probes (Invitrogen Carlsbad, CA, USA) 
and the JNK inhibitor SP600125 was from Assay Design (Enzo 
Life Sciences International, Inc., Plymouth Meeting, PA, USA). 
Anti-pJNK Thr183/Tyr185, antibody was purchased from Cell 
Signaling, (Danvers, MA, USA) and the anti-α-tubulin rabbit 
monoclonal antibody was from Thermo Scientific (Rockford, IL, 
USA). </p>

<p>CELL CULTURE AND VIRUS PROPAGATION </p>

<p>The human laryngeal carcinoma cell line (Hep-2) and African 
green monkey kidney epithelial cells line (Vero) were maintained 
in Minimum-Essential-Medium (MEM) additioned with 10% 
fetal calf serum (FCS), glutamine (200 mM), penicillin (100 U/ml) 
and streptomycin (100 μg/ml). Human herpes simplex virus type 
1 (KOS strain) and EV71 were purchased from the ATCC (Milan, 
Italy) and propagated and titrated in Hep-2 and Vero cells, respec-
tively. The virus titre for both HSV-1 and EV71 was calculated by 
the plaque assay (Saijets et al., 2003; Hung et al., 2010). 
The day before the experiment, 1 × 10 5 Hep-2 or Vero cells were 
seeded in 24-multiwell plates at a density of 400 cells/mm 2 . After 
overnight incubation, cells were treated with HSV-1 or EV71 alone 
or in the presence of test substances as described in Protocols 1-4. </p>

<p>STUDY DESIGN </p>

<p>In order to mimic the different conditions during which BR 
could interfere with viral infectivity, four different protocols were 
designed. </p>

<p>Protocol 1 </p>

<p>Hep-2 and Vero cells were pre-incubated with BR (1-10 μM) for 
2 h. At the end of incubation, the BR-containing medium was 
discarded, replaced with fresh medium and the cells infected with 
HSV-1 and EV71. After 2 h, the inocula were removed and the cells 
incubated in fresh culture medium for 24-48 h. These time points 
were selected considering the replication cycles of both HSV-1 and 
enterovirus which are 10-20 h. </p>

<p>Protocol 2 </p>

<p>Herpes simplex virus type 1 and EV71 were pre-incubated with 
BR (1-10 μM) alone or complexed with saturating HSA (20 μM) 
for 1 h and then transferred to Hep-2 and Vero monolayers for 
the infection. After 2 h, the inocula were removed and the cells 
incubated in fresh culture medium for 24-48 h. The effect of HSA 
per se on viral replication was also evaluated by incubating either 
HSV-1 or EV71 with 20 μM HSA and then transferring the inocula 
to Hep-2 and Vero cells as described above. </p>

<p>Protocol 3 </p>

<p>Hep-2 and Vero cells were exposed to BR (1-10 μM) alone or com-
plexed with saturating HSA (20 μM) and concomitantly infected 
with HSV-1 and EV71 for 2 h. At the end of incubation, the inocula 
were removed and the cells incubated in fresh culture medium for 
24-48 h. The antiviral effect of HSA per se was also evaluated by 
infecting Hep-2 and Vero cells with either HSV-1 or EV71 in the 
presence of 20 μM HSA as described above. </p>

<p>Protocol 4 </p>

<p>After 2 h of infection with HSV-1 and EV71, the inocula were 
removed and Hep-2 and Vero monolayers treated with BR (1-
10 μM) for further 2 h. At the end of incubation the BR-containing 
medium was discarded and the cells incubated in fresh culture 
medium for 24-48 h. </p>

<p>In preliminary experiments, both Hep-2 and Vero cells were 
incubated with 10-100 μM NaOH for 2 h and then incubated 
with fresh medium for 24-48 h to evaluate whether or not this 
substance affected viral infectivity. 
In selected experiments, performed following protocols 1 and 
3, Hep-2 and Vero cells were pre-incubated with the NO synthase 
(NOS) inhibitor L-NG-monomethyl arginine citrate (L-NMMA, 
1 mM) for 1 h and further for 2 h in the presence of BR (10 μM) 
or BR (10 μM)-HSA (20 μM). 
The number of infected cells were calculated by immunofluo-
rescence as described below. </p>

<p>QUANTIFICATION OF INDIVIDUAL INFECTED CELLS </p>

<p>At the end of the 24 or 48-h incubation, cells were washed with PBS 
to remove residual culture medium, gently scraped and counted. 
Twenty-five thousand infected cells were seeded on single slide 
(four slides for each well) and incubated with anti HSV-1 mon-
oclonal antibody (Imagen Herpes simplex virus direct IF test, </p>

<p>Frontiers in Pharmacology | Drug Metabolism and Transport </p>

<p>March 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 36 | 2 </p>

<p>Santangelo et al. </p>

<p>The antiviral effect of bilirubin </p>

<p>Dako Cytomation, UK) or Pan-enterovirus antibody blend (PAN 
ENTERO BLEND, Light Diagnostics, Temecula, CA, USA) accord-
ing to the manufacturers' instructions. Immunofluorescence is a 
simple and reliable method to assess viral infection and is routinely 
used to estimate either herpesvirus or enterovirus infectivity (Kle-
spies et al., 1996; Saijets et al., 2003; Copeland et al., 2009; Prichard 
et al., 2009). Both total cells and immunofluorescence-positive 
cells in each sample were counted in at least five microscopy fields 
(120-160 total cells and ∼5-140 positive cells per field) by two 
independent blinded investigators and this latter expressed as per-
centage respect to total cells. The inter-investigator variability rate 
of cell count was less than 10%. </p>

<p>MEASUREMENT OF NO </p>

<p>Intracellular NO was detected in Vero cells treated for 2 h with 
BR (1-10 μM) in 0% FCS MEM by using the fluorescent probe 
DAF-FM-DA as previously described (Mancuso et al., 2008). </p>

<p>WESTERN BLOT ASSAY </p>

<p>Confluent Hep-2 and Vero cells were lysed in lysis buffer (150 mM 
NaCl, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8, 2 mM EDTA, 1 mM phenylmethyl-
sulfonyl fluoride, 1 μg/ml aprotinin, leupeptin, and pepstatin, 
1 mM sodium orthovanadate) containing 1% Triton X-100 and 
0.1% SDS; lysates were cleared by centrifugation, and equal 
amounts of protein (40 μg) for each sample were subjected to 
SDS-PAGE on 10% gel. Western blot analysis was performed as 
previously described (Mancuso et al., 2008) by using primary anti-
bodies (see above) diluted 1:1000 and HRP-conjugated secondary 
antibodies as appropriate. </p>

<p>STATISTICAL ANALYSIS </p>

<p>Data are expressed as mean ± SEM of (N) individual samples 
per group. Statistical analysis was performed using ANOVA com-
bined with Dunnet's or two-tailed Student's t -tests for compar-
ison within the same group or two groups, respectively. Dif-
ferences were considered significant at P &lt; 0.05. The maximal 
inhibitory activity values were calculated and confirmed by non-
linear regression analysis using a <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>EFFECTS OF BR OR BR-HSA ON HSV-1 AND EV71 INFECTIVITY </p>

<p>The first step was to titrate both HSV-1 and EV71 by the plaque 
assay. The titer for HSV-1 was calculated to be 1.3 × 10 7 plaque 
forming unit (PFU)/ml whereas for EV71 was 1 × 10 9 PFU/ml. At 
these titers both HSV-1 and EV71 completely detached the Hep-2 
and Vero cell monolayers as early as 24 from infection and this 
did not allow us to carry out any experiment to prove the possible 
protective effect of 1-10 μM BR. For this reason, in all the exper-
imental protocols described below, cells were infected with either 
HSV-1 or EV71 at the titer 1 × 10 5 PFU. 
In preliminary experiments, the unspecific effects of NaOH, the 
vehicle for BR, on viral replication was studied. Sodium hydroxide 
in the range 10-100 μM (i.e., the concentrations in 1-10 μM BR) 
did not have any significant effect on HSV-1 or EV71 infectivity at 
24-48 h of incubation (data not shown). </p>

<p>Protocol 1 </p>

<p>As shown in Figure 1, Hep-2 and Vero cells pre-incubated with BR 
(1-10 μM) for 2 h and then infected with HSV-1 and EV71, were 
markedly resistant to the lethal effect of both the viruses and the 
percentage of infected cells were significantly reduced both at 24 
and 48 h after infection (Figure 1). However, in this experimental 
setting BR was slightly more efficacious against HSV-1 than EV71 
at 48 h from infection (mean maximal inhibitory activity 95 and 
83%, respectively) whereas the efficacy at 24 h was comparable. It 
is noteworthy to mention that BR displayed a greater potency in 
inhibiting both HSV-1 and EV71 infectivity at 24 h than at 48 h 
from the infection. </p>

<p>Protocol 2 </p>

<p>When HSV-1 and EV71 were pre-incubated with BR (1-10 μM) 
alone or complexed with HSA (20 μM) for 2 h and then transferred </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 | Effect of bilirubin (BR) on herpes simplex virus type 1 
(HSV-1) and enterovirus EV71 replication. Hep-2 (A) and Vero (B) cells 
were pre-incubated with BR (1-10 μM) for 2 h. At the end of incubation, BR 
was removed and Hep-2 and Vero cells infected with HSV-1 and EV71, 
respectively, both at the titer 1 × 10 
5 PFU. After 2 h, the inocula were 
removed and the cells incubated in culture medium for 24 (white columns) 
or 48 h (black columns). Data are expressed as the percentage of infected 
cells, mean ± SEM of six individual samples per group. *P &lt; 0.05 and 
**P &lt; 0.01 versus control (C) after 24 h from infection;˚P &lt; 0.05 and˚P 
&lt; 0.01 versus control after 48 h from infection. </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>March 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 36 | 3 </p>

<p>Santangelo et al. </p>

<p>The antiviral effect of bilirubin </p>

<p>onto Hep-2 and Vero monolayers, the bile pigment significantly 
inhibited viral infectivity (Figure 2). In particular, BR alone exhib-
ited lower efficacy against HSV-1 than EV71 at 24 h from infection 
(mean maximal inhibitory activity 98 versus 82%, respectively) 
whereas at 48 h the efficacy was comparable. Furthermore, the 
complexation with HSA did not alter the efficacy of BR against 
HSV-1 and EV71 at shorter time from infection whereas reduced 
the efficacy after 48 h (mean maximal inhibitory activity 54 versus 
82%, respectively). Moreover, the complexation with HSA reduced 
the potency of BR to block HSV-1 replication after 24 h from 
infection. </p>

<p>Protocol 3 </p>

<p>In Hep-2 and Vero cells treated with BR (1-10 μM) alone or com-
plexed with HSA (20 μM) and concomitantly infected with HSV-1 </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 | Direct effect of bilirubin (BR) and albumin-bound bilirubin 
(BR-HSA) on herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) and enterovirus EV71 
and how this affects viral replication. Both HSV-1 and EV71 (1 × 10 
5 PFU) 
were pre-incubated with BR (1-10 μM) alone or complexed with saturating 
HSA (20 μM) for 1 h and then transferred to Hep-2 (A) and Vero (B) cell 
monolayers for the infection. After 2 h, the inocula were removed and the 
cells incubated in culture medium for 24 h (white and dashed columns) or 
48 h (black and dotted columns). Both dashed and dotted columns refer to 
HSA treatment as described in the Section "Materials and Methods." Data 
are expressed as the percentage of infected cells, mean ± SEM of six 
individual samples per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control (C) after 24 h from 
infection; ** or 
 † P &lt; 0.01 versus respective controls after 24 h from </p>

<p>infection;˚or 
# P &lt; 0.05 and˚˚or 
## P &lt; 0.01 versus respective controls after 
48 h from infection. </p>

<p>and EV71, the linear tetrapyrrole significantly modified viral infec-
tivity (Figure 3). In details, BR alone showed a comparable efficacy 
against HSV-1 and EV71 at both 24 and 48 h. The complexation 
with HSA only partially confirmed this trend, since BR exhibited 
similar efficacy against HSV-1 and EV71 at 24 h, but a lower effi-
cacy at 48 h of incubation (mean maximal inhibitory activity 62 
and 82%, respectively). Similarly to Protocol 2, the complexation 
with HSA reduced the potency of BR to block HSV-1 replication 
after 24 h from infection. </p>

<p>Protocol 4 </p>

<p>When given after viral infection, BR (1-10 μM) significantly 
reduced HSV-1 virulence only within the first 24 h from the 
infection, whereas after 48 h only the higher concentration was </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 | Effect of bilirubin (BR) and albumin-bound bilirubin 
(BR-HSA) given concurrently with herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) 
and enterovirus EV71 and how this affects viral replication. Hep-2 (A) 
and Vero (B) cells were exposed to BR (1-10 μM) alone or complexed with 
saturating HSA (20 μM) and concomitantly infected with HSV-1 and EV71 
(1 × 10 
5 PFU) for 2 h. At the end of incubation the inocula were removed 
and the cells incubated in culture medium for 24 (white and dashed 
columns) or 48 h (black and dotted columns). Both dashed and dotted 
columns refer to HSA treatment as described in the Section "Materials and 
Methods." Data are expressed as the percentage of infected cells, 
mean ± SEM of six individual samples per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control 
(C) after 24 h from infection; ** or 
 † P &lt; 0.01 versus respective controls after </p>

<p>24 h from infection;˚or 
# P &lt; 0.05 and˚˚or 
## P &lt; 0.01 versus respective 
controls after 48 h from infection. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Pharmacology | Drug Metabolism and Transport </p>

<p>March 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 36 | 4 </p>

<p>Santangelo et al. </p>

<p>The antiviral effect of bilirubin </p>

<p>active (Figure 4). Conversely, BR maintained its antiviral action 
against EV71 at both 24 and 48 h from the infection (Figure 4). </p>

<p>INTRACELLULAR MECHANISMS THROUGH WHICH BR COULD EXERT 
ITS ANTIVIRAL ACTIVITY </p>

<p>Bilirubin-IX-alpha (1-10 μM) stimulated the phosphorylation of 
the member of the MAPK family JNK in Hep-2 and Vero cell 
lines (Figure 5A and data not shown), but a positive correlation 
between BR concentrations and JNK phosphorylation was not 
found. The JNK inhibitor SP600125 (10 μM) partially reversed 
the BR (10 μM)-induced block of HSV-1 and EV71 replication in 
Hep-2 and Vero cells at both 24 and 48 h from infection (protocols 
1 and 3), but this result only approached statistical significance 
(data not shown). 
In addition, BR (10 μM) increased the production of NO in 
Vero cells in a time-dependent manner reaching statistical signif-
icance as early as 2 h after the administration (Figure 5B). The 
involvement of BR-dependent generation of NO in the inhibition </p>

<p>FIGURE 4 | Effects of bilirubin (BR) on cell monolayers infected with 
herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) and enterovirus EV71. After 2 h of 
infection with HSV-1 and enterovirus (1 × 10 
5 PFU), Hep-2 (A) and Vero (B) 
cell monolayers were treated with BR (1-10 μM) for further 2 h. At the end 
of incubation the inocula were removed and the cells incubated in culture 
medium for 24 (white columns) or 48 h (black columns). Data are expressed 
as the percentage of infected cells, mean ± SEM of six individual samples 
per group. *P &lt; 0.05 and **P &lt; 0.01 versus control (C) after 24 h from 
infection;˚˚P &lt; 0.01 versus control after 48 h from infection. </p>

<p>of viral replication was confirmed in specific experiments per-
formed by incubating Hep-2 and Vero cells with L-NMMA (1 mM) 
1 h before and then in the presence of BR (10 μM, 2 h) as described 
in protocol 1. These experiments demonstrated that the inhi-
bition of NOS activity reversed the BR-induced block of viral 
replication in HSV-1 and EV71 after 24 h and 48 h from infec-
tion (Figure 6). A similar degree of inhibition of viral replication 
was found when HSV-1 and Vero cells were pre-incubated with 
L-NMMA for 1 h and then exposed simultaneously to BR alone or 
complexed with HSA plus HSV-1 or EV71 according to protocol 
3 (data not shown). This effect of BR was comparable at both 24 
and 48 h from infection (data not shown). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Over the last years, several studies reported on the microbici-
dal activity of HO-1 and its by-products. Biliverdin-IX-alpha was 
shown to inhibit the replication of HCV, HHV-6, and HIV (Mori 
et al., 1991; Nakagami et al., 1992; Lehmann et al., 2010; Zhu et al., 
2010), CO reduced the growth of E. coli, P. aeruginosa, and S. aureus 
(Nobre et al., 2007, 2009; Davidge et al., 2009; Desmard et al., 2012) 
and iron almost completely decreased HCV core mRNA and pro-
tein (Hou et al., 2009). The results shown in this paper provided 
original evidence about the antiviral role of BR, the formation 
of which requires the concerted action of both HO and BVR, </p>

<p>FIGURE 5 | Effect of bilirubin (BR) on cellular expression of the c-Jun 
N-terminal kinase (JNK) and nitric oxide (NO) production. Hep-2 and 
Vero cells were pre-incubated with BR (1-10 μM) for 2 h. At the end of 
incubation, BR was removed, the Hep-2 cells lysed and assayed for JNK 
phosphorylation by Western Blot (A) as described under the Section 
"Materials and Methods." α-tubulin was used as housekeeping gene to 
verify protein equal loading. On the contrary, Vero cells were assayed for 
NO production by using the fluorescent probe DAF-FM-diacetate 
[DAF-FM-DA, (B)] as described under the Section "Materials and Methods." 
(A) Shows a representative gel. In (B), data are expressed as DAF-FM-DA 
fluorescence arbitrary units (A.U), mean ± SEM of six individual samples 
per group. *P &lt; 0.05 versus control (C). </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>March 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 36 | 5 </p>

<p>Santangelo et al. </p>

<p>The antiviral effect of bilirubin </p>

<p>FIGURE 6 | Effect of bilirubin (BR) plus the nitric oxide synthase 
inhibitor L-NG-monomethyl arginine citrate (L-NMMA) on herpes 
simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) and enterovirus EV71 replication. Hep-2 
(A) and Vero (B) cells were pre-incubated with 1 mM L-NMMA for 1 h and 
then with L-NMMA plus 10 μM BR for further 2 h. At the end of incubation, 
the medium containing L-NMMA plus BR was removed and Hep-2 and Vero 
cells infected with HSV-1 and EV71 (1 × 10 
5 PFU), respectively. After 2 h, the 
inocula were removed and the cells incubated in culture medium for 24 
(white columns) or 48 h (black columns). Data are expressed as the 
percentage of infected cells, mean ± SEM of six individual samples per 
group. **P &lt; 0.01 versus respective controls (C) and˚P &lt; 0.05 and˚P 
&lt; 0.01 versus 10 μM BR after 24 h (white columns) and 48 h (black 
columns) from viral infection. </p>

<p>thus expanding the cytoprotective role of this linear tetrapyrrole. 
However, in order to appreciate the novelty of our study, some 
considerations about the pathophysiology of the HO/BVR system 
are needed. 
Although HO-1 is considered ubiquitous, this isoform is abun-
dantly expressed in liver, spleen, heart, kidney, and selected brain 
regions and its activity increases greatly under stressful condi-
tions (Maines, 1997). On the contrary, the constitutive HO-2 
isoform prevails in neurons and testicular germ cells (Maines, 
1997). Almost all organs retain BVR activity which transforms BV 
into BR (Maines, 1997, 2005). That said, it is plausible to wonder 
whether or not the antiviral activity of BV against HHV-6, HIV, 
or HCV (Mori et al., 1991; Nakagami et al., 1992; Lehmann et al., </p>

<p>2010; Zhu et al., 2010) should be attributable to its conversion into 
BR by the MT-4 or Huh cells used in those studies rather than a 
distinct effect of BV. The lack of inactivation of HHV-6 virions by 
BV and the consequent reduced antiviral effect lend support to this 
hypothesis. Another concern raised from the studies by Nakagami 
et al. (1992) and Mori et al. (1991) is related to the concentrations 
of BV used to inhibit HHV-6 and HIV replication. In these studies 
the antiviral effect of BV was observed at concentrations ranging 
from 10 to 66.7 μg/ml, equivalent to ∼17 and 113 μM, respec-
tively, two values much higher than those expected to be produced 
by the HO activity in humans (Coburn, 1970). These potential 
biases were overcome in our study which demonstrated a direct 
antiviral effect for BR, the stable end product of heme metabo-
lism, at concentrations from 1 to 10 μM which are very close to 
those found in human plasma (Berk et al., 1969; Bloomer et al., 
1971) and about 1 order of magnitude lower than those previously 
used to demonstrate the antiviral effect of BV. From the analysis 
of the pharmacodynamic data, it emerges a different sensitivity of 
HSV-1 and EV71 to both free and albumin-bound BR under the 
various experimental conditions. A careful comparative evalua-
tion of the mechanisms which underlie the ability of BR to inhibit 
HSV-1 and EV71 infectivity under the conditions which charac-
terized Protocols 1-4, is out of the scope of this paper. However, it 
is important to highlight that, in this study, both BR and BR-HSA 
significantly inhibited the infectivity of both HSV-1 and EV71 in 
all the experimental settings well within the range of physiologic 
concentrations. A preliminary conclusion drawn from our results 
was that BR was much more efficacious to inhibit viral infectivity 
after 24 h from infection and, in particular, when the bile pigment 
was complexed to HSA. 
The results shown in this study suggest that BR reduce viral 
replication by acting at several stages. The ability of BR to decrease 
HSV-1 and EV71 infectivity if pre-incubated with Hep-2 and Vero 
cells (Figure 1) resembles the pathophysiologic condition in which 
a virus infects cells endowed with high concentration of BR (e.g., 
hepatocytes, neurons). This finding is clinically relevant because 
nervous system and liver are both target organs for HSV-1 and 
enterovirus. Taking into consideration that there is not a direct 
clinical evidence of a reduced incidence of viral diseases in subjects 
affected by conditions characterized by unconjugated hyperbiliru-
binemia, such as Gilbert's syndrome (Hirschfield and Alexander, 
2006), we hypothesize a protective role for BR in viral diseases in 
analogy with the well known protective effect of the bile pigment 
against respiratory diseases and cardiovascular accidents (Vitek 
et al., 2002; Horsfall et al., 2011). With regard to the inhibition of 
viral infectivity by both BR and BR-HSA pre-incubated directly 
with virions (Figure 2), it recalls the pathophysiologic condition in 
which a virus comes in contact with BR or BR-HSA in the blood, 
as during the viremic phase, and then infects tissues. Similarly, 
both BR and BR-HSA reduced viral replication if given cells con-
comitantly with HSV-1 and EV71 (Figure 3) and this mimics the 
pathophysiologic condition in which a virus comes in contact with 
BR/BR-HSA and cells at the blood/tissue interface. However, it is 
well known that both herpesviruses and enteroviruses have a short 
viremic phase since they colonize target organs very fast and, there-
fore, the potential clinical importance of both these mechanisms 
is limited to severe diseases characterized by long-lasting veremic </p>

<p>Frontiers in Pharmacology | Drug Metabolism and Transport </p>

<p>March 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 36 | 6 </p>

<p>Santangelo et al. </p>

<p>The antiviral effect of bilirubin </p>

<p>phase such as in immunocompromised patients (Stanberry et al., 
1994). Finally, BR was efficacious in reducing viral infection even 
when administered to Hep-2 and Vero cells already infected by 
HSV-1 and EV71, respectively (Figure 4). This experimental con-
dition reminds of the clinical situation in which jaundice is sec-
ondary to a viral infection, such as hepatitis. As a matter of fact, in 
viral hepatitis unconjugated BR increases when hepatic function 
decreases under a critical threshold and it is very often accom-
panied by hypoalbuminemia and hypofibrinogenemia and these 
alterations represent a life-threatening condition. The possible 
protective effect of BR at this stage is, therefore, unlikely. 
Overall speaking, the mechanisms involved in the antiviral 
activity of BR within the cell or at the interface blood/tissue could 
be related either to the stimulation of intracellular pro-survival 
pathways, such as the MAPK system, or the production of micro-
bicidal molecules such as NO. The BR-induced stimulation of 
NO release in Vero cells (Figure 5) should be considered as one 
of the main mechanisms involved in the antiviral effect of the 
linear tetrapyrrole against both HSV-1 and EV71. The impor-
tance of NO to decrease HSV-1 and EV71 infectivity was also 
corroborated by the evidence that the blockade of NOS, by the 
inhibitor L-NMMA, reverted the reduction of viral infectivity due 
to 10 μM BR (Figure 6). This result is not surprising and is in 
good agreement with previous studies which demonstrated the 
virucidal effect of NO (Croen, 1993; Akaike and Maeda, 2000). 
The JNK signaling cascade is also a crucial effector of the antivi-
ral immune response in influenza virus (Hrincius et al., 2010), 
but there are no data in favor of a cytoprotective effect against 
HSV-1 or EV71. The lack of a positive correlation between BR 
concentrations and JNK phosphorylation (Figure 5A, in partic-
ular the 55-KDa isoform) could be explained keeping in mind 
that the bile pigment was used within the range 1-10 μM. It is 
interesting to recall that higher concentrations of BR (50 μM) 
were necessary to clearly stimulate the phosphorylation of MAPK 
members including JNK (Fernandes et al., 2007). In addition, the 
lack of any significant effect of the JNK inhibitor SP600125 (data </p>

<p>not shown) on HSV-1 and EV71 infectivity lends support to the 
hypothesis that this pathway is not so efficacious to prevent viral 
infection as NO production. The parallel antiviral activity of BR 
against HSV-1 and EV71, characterized by important differences 
in terms of virion structure, a DNA-containing core surrounded 
by an envelope in HSV-1 and a RNA-containing core within a 
capsid without envelope in EV71, suggests that BR acts directly 
on the virion particles or on nucleic acids. In this light, some 
studies reported on a toxic effect of BR, in the presence of tran-
sition metals, on nucleic acids (Asad et al., 1999). Furthermore, 
the lack of direct antiviral activity of BV on HHV-6 and HSV-1 
(Nakagami et al., 1992) vis-à-vis with the efficient antiviral effect 
of BR against HSV-1 and EV71, implies an important role of 
the C-10, in analogy with previous results. The absence of dou-
ble bonds at the γ-bridge (which includes C-10) stabilizes the 
structure of BR and increases its liposolubility with respect to BV. 
Moreover, the C-10 can undergo redox modifications under con-
ditions of oxidative stress (Stocker et al., 1987a; Baranano et al., 
2002). According to this hypothesis, free radicals could oxidize 
protein-bound BR at the C-10 generating BV which, in turn, is 
quickly reduced back to BR by the ubiquitous BVR (Baranano 
et al., 2002). However, this hypothesis is still debated in the scien-
tific community (Maghzal et al., 2009), but it cannot be excluded 
to explain the antiviral effect of BR toward both HSV-1 and 
EV71. 
In conclusion, the results in this paper provide the first evi-
dence, to our knowledge, of a virucidal effect of BR against HSV-1 
and EV71. The implication of these results for the development 
of new antiviral drugs designed to modulate the HO/BVR system 
are profound and research on these subjects is ongoing in our 
laboratories. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The Authors want to thank Mrs. Simona Galuppi, Franca Pedone, 
and Creola Rocchetti for the expert technical assistance. This work 
was supported by Fondi Ateneo to Cesare Mancuso. </p>





<p>March 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 36 | 7 </p>

<p>Santangelo et al. </p>

<p>The antiviral effect of bilirubin </p>



<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The 
authors declare that the research was 
conducted in the absence of any com-
mercial or financial relationships that 
could be construed as a potential con-
flict of interest. </p>

<p>Received: 09 January 2012; paper pend-
ing published: 27 January 2012; accepted: 
20 February 2012; published online: 09 
March 2012. 
Citation: Santangelo R, Mancuso C, 
Marchetti S, Di Stasio E, Pani G and 
Fadda G (2012) Bilirubin: an endoge-
nous molecule with antiviral activity 
in vitro. Front. Pharmacol. 3:36. doi: 
10.3389/fphar.2012.00036 
This article was submitted to Frontiers 
in Drug Metabolism and Transport, a 
specialty of Frontiers in Pharmacology. 
Copyright © 2012 Santangelo, Mancuso, 
Marchetti, Di Stasio, Pani and Fadda. 
This is an open-access article distributed 
under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution Non Commercial License, 
which permits non-commercial use, dis-
tribution, and reproduction in other 
forums, provided the original authors and 
source are credited. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Pharmacology | Drug Metabolism and Transport </p>

<p>March 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 36 | 8 </p>

</text></tei>