<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3758215" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: C-reactive protein (CRP) is inversely related to prognosis in many cancers, 
however, no studies regarding the predictive value of CRP in small cell carcinoma of the 
esophagus (SCCE) are available. The aim of this study was to determine the prognostic value 
of preoperative CRP in patients with SCCE. 
Methods: From January 2001 to December 2010, a retrospective analysis of 43 consecutive 
patients with SCCE was conducted. Univariate and multivariate analyses were performed to 
evaluate the prognostic parameters. 
Results: In our study, elevated CRP levels (.10 mg/L) were found in 16 patients (37.2%). 
CRP levels were significantly higher in patients with deeply invasive tumors (P = 0.018) 
and those associated with nodal metastasis (P = 0.018). Patients with CRP #10 mg/L had 
a significantly better overall survival than patients with CRP .10 mg/L (25.9% vs 6.3%, 
P = 0.004). Multivariate analyses showed that CRP was a significant predictor for overall 
survival. CRP .10 mg/L had a hazard ratio of 2.756 (95% confidence interval: 1.115-6.813, 
P = 0.028) for overall survival. 
Conclusion: Preoperative CRP is an independent predictive factor for long-term survival in 
patients with SCCE. 
Small cell carcinoma of the esophagus (SCCE) is a rare disease, which was first 
described in 1952 by McKeown. 
1 The incidence of SCCE within all esophageal cancers 
(ECs) is 0.05%-2.4% in Western populations, and this rate rises up to 7.6% in Chinese 
and Japanese literature. 
2,3 Previous studies suggested that SCCE is a highly aggressive 
disease with poor prognosis. 
3 Although advances have occurred in multidisciplinary 
treatment, the 5-year survival in SCCE is still poor. Therefore, assessing the prognostic 
factors in SCCE patients will become more and more important. 
Recently, there has been increasing evidence that a systemic inflammatory response 
is of prognostic value in various cancers. 
4,5 C-reactive protein (CRP) is an index of 
systemic inflammation. Recent publications have suggested that preoperative CRP is 
inversely related to prognosis in many cancers; a high level is associated with poor 
prognosis. 
6,7 Furthermore, a few recent studies investigated the value of CRP levels in 
patients with EC and obtained encouraging results in terms of prognosis prediction. </p>

<p>8-10 </p>

<p>However, to the best of our knowledge, no studies regarding the predictive value of 
CRP in SCCE are available. Therefore, the aim of this study was to determine the 
prognostic value of CRP in patients with SCCE. </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
21 August 2013 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1148 </p>

<p>Feng et al </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Patients </p>

<p>From January 2001 to December 2010, a retrospective 
analysis was conducted of 43 patients with SCCE who 
underwent curative esophagectomy at Zhejiang Cancer 
Hospital (Hangzhou, People's Republic of China). All of 
the patients included in the analysis fit the following criteria: 
(1) SCCE confirmed by histopathology; (2) limited disease 
without distal metastasis; (3) curative esophagectomy with 
margins free of disease. Based on the medical records, the 
following data were collected for each patient: age, gender, 
tumor length, tumor location, preoperative CRP, depth of 
invasion, nodal metastasis, treatment, and other miscella-
neous characteristics. 
All of the above patients were followed up by posting 
letters or by telephone interviews. The last follow-up was 
November 30, 2011. All subjects gave written informed 
consent to the study protocol, which was approved by the 
Ethical Committees of Zhejiang Cancer Hospital, Hangzhou, 
People's Republic of China. </p>

<p>Preoperative CRP measurement </p>

<p>Data on preoperative CRP were extracted in a retrospec-
tive fashion from the medical records. All blood test results 
were taken within 1 week prior to surgery. Serum CRP was 
determined by latex-enhanced homogeneous immunoas-
say (wide-range) (Hitachi 917; Skill, Munich, Germany). 
Normal values provided by the manufacturer were lower 
than 10 mg/L. </p>

<p>Adjuvant chemoradiotherapy </p>

<p>Adjuvant chemoradiotherapy was used in 26 cases. Among 
them, 13 cases were treated with four to six courses of 
platinum-based combination chemotherapy, eight cases 
with radiotherapy, and five cases with chemoradiotherapy, 
respectively. For chemotherapy, eight patients were treated 
with etoposide plus cisplatin, three with paclitaxel plus 
cisplatin, and one with 5-fluorouracil plus platinum. For 
radiotherapy, radiation was delivered from 2 Gy per day, 
5 days per week, to a total dose of 45-68 Gy. No patients 
were treated with neoadjuvant. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical evaluation was conducted with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v17.0</rs>; 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>, Chicago, IL, USA). The patients were divided into 
two groups according to the CRP measured preoperatively: 
those with CRP values in the normal range (#10 mg/L) 
and those with elevated CRP levels (.10 mg/L). The Pearson </p>

<p>Chi-squared test was used to determine the significance of 
differences between the two groups. The overall cumulative 
probability of survival was calculated by the Kaplan-Meier 
method, and the difference was assessed by the log-rank 
test. A univariate analysis was used to examine the asso-
ciation between various prognostic predictors and survival. 
Possible prognostic factors associated with overall survival 
were considered in a multivariable Cox proportional hazards 
regression analysis (Enter). Hazard ratios (HR) with 95% 
confidence intervals (CI) were used to quantify the strength 
of the association between predictors and survival. A P-value 
less than 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The baseline characteristics are shown in Table 1. Among 
the 43 patients, 13 (30.2%) were women and 30 (69.8%) 
were men. The mean age was 58.7 ± 7.8 years, with an age 
range of 45-74 years. 
There were no significant differences between the two 
groups in terms of age, gender, tumor location, tumor 
length, or vessel involvement. However, CRP levels were 
significantly higher in patients with deeply invasive tumors 
(T3-4a vs T1-2, P = 0.018) and those associated with nodal 
metastasis (positive vs negative, P = 0.018) (Table 2). 
Univariate analyses were performed using the Kaplan-
Meier method to assess the predictive capability of each 
variable assessed. Multivariate analyses were then per-
formed with the Cox proportional hazards model. In that </p>

<p>Table 1 The baseline characteristics of 43 patients with SCCE </p>

<p>Cases (n, %) </p>

<p>age (mean ± SD, years) 
58.7 ± 7.8 
gender 
Female 
13 (30.2) 
Male 
30 (69.8) 
Tumor size (mean ± SD, cm) 
4.1 ± 1.9 
Tumor location 
Upper 
2 (4.7) 
Middle 
23 (53.5) 
lower 
18 (41.8) 
Depth of invasion 
T1 
9 (20.9) 
T2 
10 (23.3) 
T3 
22 (51.1) 
T4 
2 (4.7) 
nodal metastasis 
n0 
15 (34.9) 
n1 
13 (30.2) 
n2 
8 (18.6) 
n3 
7 (16.3) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: SCCE, small cell carcinoma of the esophagus; SD, standard 
deviation. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1149 </p>

<p>Preoperative CRP as a parameter in patients with SCCE </p>

<p>survival of SCCE was achieved after esophagectomy with 
or without adjuvant chemotherapy. </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>There is a strong link between inflammation and cancer. It 
is well known that cancer promotes the release of proinflam-
matory cytokines from tumor cells. The cytokines interact 
with the immunovascular system and facilitate growth, 
invasion, and metastasis. 
4,5 Recent studies have shown that 
elevated preoperative serum CRP levels may be associated 
with tumor size, depth of invasion, and nodal metastasis, 
resulting in poor prognosis in patients with various cancers, 
including EC. 
6,7,9 Thus, in our study, we wanted to determine 
whether preoperative CRP level is associated with overall 
survival after esophagectomy for SCCE. 
Our results demonstrated that CRP levels were sig-
nificantly higher in patients with deeply invasive tumors 
(P = 0.018) and those associated with nodal metastasis 
(P = 0.018). This observation is in line with data from 
Shimada et al 
8 and Nozoe et al, 
9 but is contrary to the result 
of Guillem et al, 
10 who suggested that preoperative CRP is not 
significantly correlated with the above clinicopathological 
factors. However, in our study, no relationship was found 
between CRP level and tumor size. 
A number of studies have shown that increased preopera-
tive CRP levels in various solid tumors are associated with 
poor prognosis. 
6,7 Shimada et al 
8 demonstrated that although 
the difference in survival was mainly attributable to differ-
ences in TNM staging between the low and high CRP groups, 
preoperative CRP was an independent prognostic factor 
according to multivariate analysis. In our study, the survival 
of patients in the high CRP group (.10 mg/L) was signifi-
cantly worse than that of the low CRP group (#10 mg/L; 
25.9% vs 6.3%, P = 0.004). In addition, preoperative CRP 
was an independent prognostic factor according to multivari-
ate analysis (P = 0.028). 
The reasons why CRP levels can be correlated with 
prognosis in cancer patients remain to be determined. Any 
explanation of accumulating data showing that serum CRP 
is involved in host defenses against infections as highlighted 
by murine transgenic models must be speculative. 
15-17 As 
with other proteic markers of acute inflammation, CRP has 
several biological functions including complement activa-
tion through the classical pathway, opsonization, leukocyte 
chemotactism, and platelet activation. </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>The potential limitations of the present study include 
the relatively small number of patients, as well as the fact 
that the analysis was retrospective, and the short mean 
follow-up duration. Furthermore, due to the limited number 
of patients with SCCE, our analysis may suffer from type I or </p>

<p>Table 2 The characteristics between patients with CRP #10 mg/l 
and .10 mg/l </p>

<p>CRP #10 mg/L 
(n, %) </p>

<p>CRP .10 mg/L 
(n, %) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Age (years) 
0.965 
#60 
.60 </p>

<p>15 (55.6) 
12 (44.4) </p>

<p>9 (56.3) 
7 (43.7) 
gender 
0.086 
Female 
Male </p>

<p>11 (40.7) 
16 (59.3) </p>

<p>2 (12.5) 
14 (87.5) 
Tumor length (cm) 
0.278 
#3.0 
.3.0 </p>

<p>13 (48.1) 
14 (51.9) </p>

<p>5 (31.3) 
11 (68.7) 
Tumor location 
0.141 
Upper/middle 
lower </p>

<p>18 (66.7) 
9 (33.3) </p>

<p>7 (43.7) 
9 (56.3) 
Vessel involvement 
0.719 
negative 
Positive </p>

<p>20 (74.1) 
7 (25.9) </p>

<p>13 (81.3) 
3 (18.7) 
Depth of invasion 
0.018 
T1-2 
T3-4a </p>

<p>15 (55.6) 
12 (44.4) </p>

<p>3 (18.7) 
13 (81.3) 
nodal metastasis 
0.018 
negative 
Positive </p>

<p>13 (48.1) 
14 (51.9) </p>

<p>2 (12.5) 
14 (87.5) </p>

<p>Abbreviation: CRP, C-reactive protein. </p>

<p>model, we demonstrated that CRP (HR: 2.756, 95% CI: 
1.115-6.813, P = 0.028), and chemoradiotherapy (HR: 
0.294, 95% CI: 0.129-0.673, P = 0.004) were independent 
prognostic factors (Table 3). In addition, patients with 
CRP #10 mg/L had a significantly better overall sur-
vival than patients with CRP .10 mg/L (25.9% vs 6.3%, 
P = 0.004) (Figure 1). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to deter-
mine the prognostic value of preoperative CRP in predicting 
the prognosis for patients with SCCE. Our study showed that 
preoperative CRP is an independent predictive factor for 
long-term survival in patients with SCCE (HR: 2.756, 95% 
CI: 1.115-6.813, P = 0.028). 
The standard therapy for SCCE has not been yet 
established. Because of the rarity of SCCE, prospective, ran-
domized controlled trials of its optimal treatment are unlikely. 
The histology and clinical characteristics of SCCE are similar 
to small cell carcinoma of the lung (SCCL); subsequently, 
investigations have recommended that a multimodal approach 
be used for SCCE as it is for SCCL. 
11 The most commonly 
used regimens include platinum-based agents, which are 
often used for SCCL. 
12 However, the optimal radiation dose 
for SCCE has not been established. For patients with limited 
disease, there were several reports showing that long-term </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1150 </p>

<p>Feng et al </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0 
2 0 
4 0 
6 0 </p>

<p>Time (m) </p>

<p>Cum survival </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>≤10 </p>

<p>CRP (mg/L) </p>

<p>&gt;10 
≤10-censored 
&gt;10-censored </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Patients with CRP #10 mg/L had a significantly better 5-year overall survival rate than patients with CRP .10 mg/L (25.9% vs 6.3%, P = 0.004). 
Abbreviation: CRP, C-reactive protein. </p>

<p>Table 3 Univariate and multivariate analyses of overall survival in SCCE patients </p>

<p>Survival (%) 
Chi-square 
P-value 
HR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age (years) 
#60 
.60 </p>

<p>16.7 
21.1 </p>

<p>0.686 
0.408 </p>

<p>gender 
Female 
Male </p>

<p>38.5 
10.0 </p>

<p>1.841 
0.175 </p>

<p>Tumor length (cm) 
#3 
.3 </p>

<p>33.3 
8.0 </p>

<p>6.846 
0.009 
1.000 
1.267 (0.546-2.937) </p>

<p>0.582 </p>

<p>Tumor location 
Upper/middle 
lower </p>

<p>20.0 
16.7 </p>

<p>0.024 
0.877 </p>

<p>CRP (mg/L) 
#10 
.10 </p>

<p>25.9 
6.3 </p>

<p>8.115 
0.004 
1.000 
2.756 (1.115-6.813) </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>Vessel involvement 
negative 
Positive </p>

<p>21.2 
10.0 </p>

<p>1.068 
0.301 </p>

<p>Depth of invasion 
T1-2 
T3-4a </p>

<p>33.3 
8.0 </p>

<p>7.433 
0.006 
1.000 
1.716 (0.708-4.161) </p>

<p>0.232 </p>

<p>nodal metastasis 
negative 
Positive </p>

<p>40.0 
7.1 </p>

<p>9.687 
0.002 
1.000 
1.891 (0.731-4.892) </p>

<p>0.189 </p>

<p>chemoradiotherapy 
no 
Yes </p>

<p>5.9 
26.9 </p>

<p>5.577 
0.018 
1.000 
0.294 (0.129-0.673) </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein; HR, hazard ratio; SCCE, small cell carcinoma of the esophagus. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open access 
journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2013:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1151 </p>

<p>Preoperative CRP as a parameter in patients with SCCE </p>

<p>type II errors. The results of the study should therefore be 
regarded with caution. In addition, no control population 
study was undertaken; hence, there are limitations in the 
scientific observations. Larger prospective studies will need 
to be performed to confirm these preliminary results. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Our study showed that preoperative CRP is an independent 
predictive factor for long-term survival in patients with 
SCCE. Serum CRP is a simple, reliable, cheap, and repro-
ducible method, for which interpretation is relatively easy in 
the context of a non-septic neoplasia. We therefore propose 
pretreatment CRP as a useful adjunct that can be associated 
in routine practice with pretreatment screening in patients 
with SCCE. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Ms Ying Huang (Department 
of Nursing, Zhejiang Cancer Hospital) for data collection 
and statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>