<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3374072" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Obesity is associated with increased health risk and has been associated with alterations in bacterial gut 
microbiota, with mainly a reduction in Bacteroidetes, but few data exist at the genus and species level. It has been reported that 
the Lactobacillus and Bifidobacterium genus representatives may have a critical role in weight regulation as an anti-obesity effect 
in experimental models and humans, or as a growth-promoter effect in agriculture depending on the strains. 
Objectives and methods: To confirm reported gut alterations and test whether Lactobacillus or Bifidobacterium species found 
in the human gut are associated with obesity or lean status, we analyzed the stools of 68 obese and 47 controls targeting 
Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes, Methanobrevibacter smithii, Lactococcus lactis, Bifidobacterium animalis and seven species of Lactobacillus 
by quantitative PCR (qPCR) and culture on a Lactobacillus-selective medium. 
Findings: In qPCR, B. animalis (odds ratio (OR) ¼ 0.63; 95% confidence interval (CI) 0.39-1.01; P ¼ 0.056) and M. smithii 
(OR ¼ 0.76; 95% CI 0.59-0.97; P ¼ 0.03) were associated with normal weight whereas Lactobacillus reuteri (OR ¼ 1.79; 95% CI 
1.03-3.10; P ¼ 0.04) was associated with obesity. 
Conclusion: The gut microbiota associated with human obesity is depleted in M. smithii. Some Bifidobacterium or Lactobacillus 
species were associated with normal weight (B. animalis) while others (L. reuteri) were associated with obesity. Therefore, gut 
microbiota composition at the species level is related to body weight and obesity, which might be of relevance for further studies 
and the management of obesity. These results must be considered cautiously because it is the first study to date that links 
specific species of Lactobacillus with obesity in humans. 
Obesity, defined as a body mass index (BMI) over 30 kg m </p>

<p>À2 (ref. 1)   and a massive expansion of fat, is related to a significantly 
increased mortality and is a risk factor for many diseases, 
including diabetes mellitus, hypertension, respiratory disorders, 
ischemic heart disease, stroke and cancer. 
2,3 Obesity can be </p>

<p>considered as a transmissible disease because maternal obesity </p>

<p>predisposes children to adulthood obesity. 
4 Its prevalence is </p>

<p>increasing steadily among adults, adolescents and children, 
and has doubled since 1960; and obesity is now considered 
a worldwide epidemic as, for example, over 30% of the 
population of North America is obese. The WHO data 
indicate that obesity currently affects at least 400 million 
people worldwide and 1.6 billion are overweight. The WHO 
further projects that by 2015, B2.3 billion adults will be 
overweight and more than 700 million will be obese. </p>

<p>5   The causes behind the obesity epidemic appear to be 
complex and involve environmental, genetic, neural and 
endocrine origins. </p>

<p>6   More recently, obesity has been associated with a specific 
profile of the bacterial gut microbiota, including a decrease </p>

<p>Received 24 November 2010; revised 27 June 2011; accepted 2 July 2011; 
published online 9 August 2011 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Professor D Raoult, Unité des Rickettsies, URMITE -CNRS 
UMR 6236 IRD 198, IFR 48, Faculté de Médecine, Université de la 
Méditerranée, 27 Bd Jean Moulin, Marseille, 13005 France. 
E-mail: Didier.raoult@gmail.com </p>

<p>International Journal of Obesity (2012) 36, 817-825 
&amp; 2012 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 0307-0565/12 
www.nature.com/ijo </p>

<p>in the Bacteroidetes/Firmicutes ratio 
7-10 and a decrease in </p>

<p>Methanobrevibacter smithii, the leading representative of the 
gut microbiota archaea. 
11 Since these pioneering studies, </p>

<p>significant associations were found between the increase of 
some bacterial groups and obesity (Lactobacillus, 
12 Staphylo-</p>

<p>coccus aureus, 
13-15 Escherichia coli, 
15 Faecalibacterium praus-</p>

<p>nitzii </p>

<p>16   ). Conversely, other groups have been associated with 
lean status, mainly belonging to the Bifidobacterium 
genus. 
11,13-16 To date, controversial studies make it clear </p>

<p>that the connection between the microbiome and excess 
weight is complex. </p>

<p>17   As many probiotic strains of Lactobacillus and Bifidobacterium 
are marketed in products for human consumption, altering 
the intestinal flora 
18 and stimulating indigenous lactobacilli </p>

<p>and bifidobacteria strains, 
19 we hypothesized that wide-</p>

<p>spread ingestion of probiotics may promote obesity by 
altering the intestinal flora. 
20-22 However, this remains </p>

<p>controversial. 
23,24 In a first step to elucidate the interactions </p>

<p>between probiotics for human consumption and obesity, 
only a few studies have compared the obese and lean subjects 
by focusing on the Lactobacillus and Bifidobacterium genera 
at the species level 
13,16 and they have not been able to </p>

<p>demonstrate significant differences probably because of a 
too small sample size. As a result, by increasing the sample 
size, we analyze the composition of the digestive microbiota 
for Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes, the archaea M. smithii, 
Lactobacillus genus, L. lactis, and explore the relationships 
between seven selected species of Lactobacillus and one 
species of Bifidobacterium, used elsewhere in marketed 
probiotics for human consumption and obesity. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Ethics, participants and samples 
All aspects of the study were approved by the local ethics 
committee 'Comité d'éthique de l'IFR 48, Service de 
Médecine Légale' (Faculté de Médecine, Marseille, France) 
under the accession number 10-002, 2010. Only verbal 
consent was necessary from patients for this study. This is 
according to the French bioethics decree Number 2007-
1220, published in the official journal of the French 
Republic. Obese patients, as defined by a BMI430 kg m </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>(BMI: weight over height squared (kg m </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>)), were selected 
from two endocrinology units (Hopital La Timone and 
Hopital Sainte Marguerite, Marseilles, France) from a group 
of patients attending the clinic for excessive body weight. 
BMI provides the most useful population-level measure of 
overweight and obese, as it is the same for both sexes and for 
all ages of adults. 
5 However, it may not correspond to the </p>

<p>same degree of fatness in different individuals (The Y-Y 
paradox). 
25 Control subjects were healthy volunteers over 18 </p>

<p>years of age with BMIs between 19 and 25 kg m </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>. Only a few 
patients had participated in the previous study conducted by 
our laboratory. 
12 The control subjects were predominantly </p>

<p>Caucasian and were approached in different geographical 
locations using a snowball approach. This approach was 
helpful in making the period of recruitment of cases and 
controls comparable. The exclusion criteria included the 
following: non-assessable BMI value, BMIo19 kg m </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>, 
BMI425 kg m 
À2 and o30 kg m </p>

<p>À2 </p>

<p>, gastric bypass, history of 
colon cancer, bowel inflammatory diseases, acute or chronic 
diarrhea in the previous 4 weeks and antibiotic administra-
tion o1 month before stool collection. Clinical data (gender, 
date of birth, clinical history, weight, height and antibiotic 
use) were recorded using a standardized questionnaire. The 
samples, collected using sterile plastic containers, were 
transported as soon as possible to the laboratory and frozen 
immediately at À80 1C for later analysis. For Firmicutes, 
Bacteroidetes, M. smithii and Lactobacillus species, analyses 
were first performed on the whole population and then after 
exclusion of common subjects with our previous study. </p>

<p>12   Analysis of gut microbiota 
Culture on specific Lactobacillus medium (LAMVAB 
medium). After thawing at room temperature, 100 mg of 
stool was suspended in 900 ml of cysteine-peptone-water 
solution 
26 and homogenized. A serial dilution was under-</p>

<p>taken in phosphate buffered saline. Samples diluted to 1/10 
and 1/1000 were inoculated using a 10 ml inoculation loop 
on LAMVAB medium. 
27 After a 72-hour incubation in jars </p>

<p>(AnaeroPack, Mitsubishi Gas Chemical America, Inc., New 
York, NY, USA) in an anaerobic atmosphere (GasPak EZ 
Anaerobe, Becton Dickinson, Heidelberg, Germany) at 37 1C, 
the number of morphotypes were identified and 1-4 colonies 
per morphotype were placed on four spots of an MTP 384 
Target plate made of polished steel (Bruker Daltonics GmbH, 
Bremen, Germany) and stored in trypticase cases in soy 
culture medium (AES, Bruz, France). </p>

<p>Lactobacillus strain collection and MALDI-TOF spectra 
database. The Lactobacillus strain collection of our labora-
tory has been completed by the strains from the Pasteur and 
DSMZ collections, and reference spectra have been created 
from those missing in the Bruker database. Bacterial identifica-
tion was undertaken with an Autoflex II mass spectrometer 
(Bruker Daltonik GmbH). Data were automatically acquired 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Flex control</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.0</rs> and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Maldi Biotyper Automation Control</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2.0</rs>. (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Bruker Daltonics GmbH</rs>). Raw spectra, ob-
tained for each isolate, were analyzed by standard pattern 
matching (with default parameter settings) against the 
spectra of species used as a reference database. An isolate 
was regarded as correctly identified at the species level when 
at least one spectrum had a score X1.9, and one spectrum 
had a score X1.7. 
28 The reproducibility of the method was </p>

<p>evaluated by the duplicate analysis of 10 samples. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR for M. smithii, Bacteroidetes, 
Firmicutes and Lactobacillus genus. DNA was isolated from 
stools as described in Dridi et al. 
29 The purified DNA samples </p>

<p>Gut microbiota and obesity 
M Million et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity </p>

<p>were eluted to a final volume of 100 ml and stored at À80 1C 
until analysis. Real-time PCR was performed on a Stratagene 
MX3000 system (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) using 
QuantiTect PCR mix (Qiagen, Courtaboeuf, France) as 
described previously. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR specific for Lactococcus lactis, 
Bifidobacterium animalis and seven Lactobacillus species. The 
primer and probe sequences were located on the Tuf 
(elongation factor Tu) gene. The Tuf gene from the 
Lactobacillus strains, reported in Supplementary Table 1, were 
sequenced and compared, where possible, to the sequence 
reported in Genbank as described in Supplementary Text 1. 
All of these sequences were compared by <rs id="software-2" type="software">ClustalX</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">1.8</rs>; 
<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://www.clustal.org</rs>) using global-multiple sequence 
alignment by the progressive method. A distance is calcu-
lated between every pair of sequences and these are used to 
construct the phylogenetic tree, which guides the final 
multiple alignment. The scores are calculated from separate 
pairwise alignments using the dynamic programming 
method. A consensus sequence was obtained and compared 
with the Tuf sequences of Lactobacillus acidophilus, Lactoba-
cillus casei-paracasei, Lactobacillus plantarum, Lactobacillus 
reuteri, Lactobacillus gasseri, Lactobacillus fermentum and 
Lactobacillus rhamnosus, Bifidobacterium animalis and Lacto-
coccus lactis, and sequences of primers and probes of highly 
specific real-time PCR were established. The primer and 
probe sequences are reported in Supplementary Table 2. The 
Lactobacillus strain-specific detection proceeded in duplex 
real-time PCR: L. acidophilus (FAM) and L. casei/paracasei 
(VIC), L. plantarum (FAM) and L. reuteri (VIC), L. gasseri (FAM) 
and fermentum (VIC), and L. rhamnosus (FAM). B. animalis 
(VIC) and Lactococcus lactis (FAM) detection utilized simplex 
real-time PCR. The duplex real-time PCR was executed as 
described above and in Armougom et al. 
12 The specificity was </p>

<p>tested on the DNA of the reference strains reported in 
Supplementary table 1. The stool-purified DNA was analyzed 
in samples that were pure, diluted at 1/10, and diluted at 1/ 
100 to confirm the absence of inhibitors. Negative controls 
were included on each plate. The different lactobacilli, B. 
animalis and Lactococcus lactis were quantified using a 
plasmid standard curve from 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>-10 copies per assay. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
First, the results of Lactobacillus-specific culture and quanti-
tative PCR (qPCR) were compared in the two groups (obese 
and control group) using the Fisher's exact test when 
comparing proportions, and the Mann-Whitney test when 
comparing bacterial concentrations. A difference was con-
sidered statistically significant when Po0.05. In order to 
identify which qPCR bacterial groups (Bacteroidetes, B. animalis, 
Lactococcus lactis, L. acidophilus, L. casei/paracasei, L. fermentum, 
L. gasseri, L. plantarum, L. reuteri, L. rhamnosus) was most 
associated with the likelihood of being obese while taking into </p>

<p>account possible confounders like age or gender, a logistic 
regression model was used. Variables with a liberal Po0.20 in 
the univariate logistic regression analysis were considered 
eligible for the multiple logistic regression analyses. 
30 A </p>

<p>secondary analysis based on logistic regression analysis was 
used to identify which culture variables (Lactobacillus species 
concentration) where associated with obesity. Data analyses 
were conducted using <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs> v.<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">9.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patients 
In total, 115 subjects (68 obese patients and 47 controls) 
were included. Thirteen obese subjects and nine controls 
were part of the previous study conducted in our labora-
tory. 
12 The two populations were homogeneous in sex and </p>

<p>height, but not in age (Table 1). </p>

<p>Culture 
In total, 68 obese and 44 controls samples were analyzed. 
The number of positive samples was greater among the 
controls vs obese (32/44 vs 30/68, Fisher's exact test, 
P ¼ 0.002). For positive samples, the concentration was not 
significantly different between obese subjects and controls, 
respectively (median 4.15 (interquartile range 4-6) vs 5.2 
(4-6) log10 CFU ml 
À1 , Mann-Whitney test, P ¼ 0.93). The </p>

<p>proportion (Table 2) and non-parametric quantitative com-
parison of the concentration of Lactobacillus species between 
obese subjects and controls has been achieved for the species 
present in at least six individuals. L. paracasei was found 
more frequently in controls (17/44 vs 10/68, Fisher's exact 
test, P ¼ 0.004). L. reuteri was found more frequently in obese 
patients (6/68 vs 1/44, Fisher's exact test, P ¼ 0.15), although 
this was not significant. L. plantarum was found only in </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics </p>

<p>Obese (n ¼ 68) Controls (n ¼ 47) P (obese vs controls) </p>

<p>Age 
50.5 ± 14.4 
42.6 ± 17.5 
0.01 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Male sex 
31 (45.6%) 
21 (51.2%) 
0.35 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Body mass index 
43.6 ± 7.8 
22.1 ± 1.8 
o0.0001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a Mann-Whitney test. 
b Fisher's exact test </p>

<p>Table 2 Results of Lactobacillus-specific culture </p>

<p>Obese (n ¼ 68) 
Controls (n ¼ 44) 
P-value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>L. paracasei 
10 (14.7%) 
17 (38.6%) 
0.004 
L. plantarum 
0 (0%) 
8 (18.2%) 
0.0004 
L. reuteri 
6 (8.8%) 
1 (2.3%) 
0.16 
L. rhamnosus 
3 (4.4%) 
4 (9.1%) 
0.27 
L. ruminis 
3 (4.4%) 
4 (9.1%) 
0.27 
L. salivarius 
5 (7.4%) 
2 (4.5%) 
0.43 </p>

<p>a Species present in at least six individuals. Fisher's exact test. </p>

<p>Gut microbiota and obesity 
M Million et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity </p>

<p>controls (8/44 vs 0/68, Fisher's exact test, P ¼ 0.0004). 
Quantitative comparison found higher levels of L. paracasei 
and L. plantarum in controls (Mann-Whitney test, P ¼ 0.005 
and P ¼ 0.0004, respectively), while L. reuteri was higher in 
the obese subjects; however, this was not significant (Mann-
Whitney test, P ¼ 0.14) (Figure 1). Variables eligible for the 
final logistic regression model were L. paracasei, L. reuteri, 
L. plantarum, L. brevis, L. fermentum and age. The final 
multiple logistic regression model showed that after adjust-
ment for age, only L. paracasei was significantly associated 
with lean status (odds ratio ¼ 0.79; 95% confidence interval 
0.64-0.97; P ¼ 0.03). </p>

<p>Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes, M. smithii and Lactobacillus 
species-specific qPCR 
M. smithii was found more frequently in controls (40/ 
45(89%) vs 50/67(75%), Fisher's exact test, P ¼ 0.05). The 
analysis did find a lower concentration of M. smithii in 
obese subjects (Mann-Whitney test, P ¼ 0.002; Table 3) and 
a higher concentration of Lactobacillus (Mann-Whitney 
test, P ¼ 0.04). Bacteroidetes was found in lower concen-
tration in obese, but this result was not significant (Mann-
Whitney test, P ¼ 0.25) (Figure 2). The same results were </p>

<p>found after the exclusion of the common subjects from 
our previous study (Mann-Whitney test; higher level of 
Lactobacillus genus in obese people, P ¼ 0.026; lower level 
of M. smithii, P ¼ 0.008 and lower level of Bacteroidetes, 
P ¼ 0.09). </p>

<p>Bifidobacterium-Lactococcus-Lactobacillus species-specific 
qPCR 
The different Bifidobacterium-Lactococcus-Lactobacillus spe-
cies-specific real-time PCRs were tested for their specificity 
against purified DNA of the strains reported in Supplemen-
tary Table 1. The different real-time PCR systems were tested 
for their sensitivity and we obtained a cycle threshold of 
about 35 for 10 copies of DNA per 5 ml of sample. All of these 
real-time PCRs have good sensitivity and specificity (Supple-
mentary Table 3). In total, 64 obese samples and 43 control 
samples were analyzed. The presence of B. animalis was 
associated with normal weight (Table 4, Fisher's exact test, 
P ¼ 0.007), and L. reuteri was associated with obesity (Fisher's 
exact test, P ¼ 0.03). Comparison using non-parametric 
statistics found that levels of B. animalis were lower 
(Mann-Whitney test, P ¼ 0.004) and that of L. reuteri were 
higher in obese people (Mann-Whitney test, P ¼ 0.02) 
(Figure 3). By comparing the culture and the Lactobacillus 
species-specific PCR, the sensitivity was higher for all seven 
tested species by PCR vs culture except for L. acidophilus, 
which was not found by culture or species-specific PCR. 
Overall, results of culture and PCR were consistent for the 
presence of L. casei/paracasei (Fisher's exact test, P ¼ 0,017), 
L. plantarum (Fisher's exact test, P ¼ 0,05) and L. reuteri 
(Fisher's exact test, P ¼ 0,00001). </p>

<p>Logistic regression analysis 
The results of the logistic regression analysis on the qPCR 
results are presented in Table 5. Variables eligible for the final 
model were L. casei/paracasei, L. reuteri, L. gasseri, B. animalis, 
M. smithii and age. The final multiple logistic regression 
model showed that after adjustment for age, L. reuteri, 
B. animalis and M. smithii were significantly associated with </p>

<p>Figure 1 Quantification of L. paracasei, L. plantarum and L. reuteri in culture (LAMVAB medium) Àlog (colony forming units per ml of feces)FMann-Whitney test. </p>

<p>Table 3 Results of Bacteroidetes, Firmicutes, Methanobrevibacter smithii and 
Lactobacillus genus quantitative PCR </p>

<p>Obese (n ¼ 67) 
Controls (n ¼ 45) 
P </p>

<p>Presence of phyla, genus or species </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Bacteroidetes 
41 (61.2%) 
27 (60%) 
0.52 
Firmicutes 
67 (100%) 
45 (100%) 
F 
Lactobacillus 
23 (34.3%) 
8 (17.8%) 
0.04 
Methanobrevibacter smithii 
50 (74.6%) 
40 (88.9%) 
0.05 </p>

<p>Quantitative comparison (log copies DNA ml 
À1 ) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Bacteroidetes 
4.26 (0-5.82) 
5.65 (0-6.37) 
0.25 
Firmicutes 
6.43 (5.32-7.29) 6.62 (5.86-7.21) 0.30 
Lactobacillus 
0 (0-3.31) 
0 (0-0) 
0.039 
Methanobrevibacter smithii 2.31 (0-3.51) 
3.78 (1.71-5.30) 0.002 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values noted as number (percentage), Fisher's exact test. 
b Values noted as 
log copies DNA ml </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>, median (interquartile range), Mann-Whitney test. </p>

<p>Gut microbiota and obesity 
M Million et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity </p>

<p>obesity. L. reuteri was the only one which showed higher 
levels in obese individuals while B. animalis and M. smithii 
were found at greater levels in non-obese subjects. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>To our knowledge, we report the largest case-control study 
comparing human obese gut microbiota to controls focusing 
on Archaea, Bacteroidetes, Firmicutes, Lactobacillus genus, 
Lactococcus lactis and B. animalis and, for the first time, we 
used a culture-dependent and culture-independent method 
to compare the Lactobacillus population at the species level 
between obese and normal-weighted humans. Our results 
confirm global alteration in obese gut microbiota with a 
lower level of M. smithii as already reported in the 
literature, 
11 and newly report lower levels of B. animalis, </p>

<p>L. paracasei, L. plantarum and higher levels of L. reuteri in 
obese gut microbiota. 
The qPCR system used in this study to detect and quantify 
Bacteroidetes, Firmicutes, Lactobacillus genus and M. smithii in 
human feces has already been evaluated and validated. </p>

<p>12,29   LAMVAB-selective media has also been used successfully to </p>

<p>Figure 2 Quantification of Bacteroidetes, Firmicutes, M. smithii and Lactobacillus genus by qPCRFMann-Whitney test. </p>

<p>Table 4 Results of Bifidobacterium animalis, Lactococcus lactis and seven 
Lactobacillus species-specific quantitative PCR </p>

<p>Obese (n ¼ 64) 
Controls (n ¼ 43) 
P </p>

<p>Presence of targeted taxa </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>L. acidophilus 
0 (0%) 
0 (0%) 
F 
L. casei/paracasei 
24 (37.5%) 
24 (55.8%) 
0.047 
L. fermentum 
11 (17.2%) 
9 (20.9%) 
0.40 
L. gasseri 
21 (32.8%) 
9 (20.9%) 
0.13 
L. plantarum 
14 (21.9%) 
12 (27.9%) 
0.31 
L. reuteri 
16 (25.0%) 
4 (9.3%) 
0.03 
L. rhamnosus 
11 (17.2%) 
9 (20.9%) 
0.40 
Lactococcus lactis 
55 (85.9%) 
34 (79.1%) 
0.25 
Bifidobacterium animalis 
1 (1.6%) 
7 (16.3%) 
0.007 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values expressed as number (percentage). Fisher's exact test. </p>

<p>Gut microbiota and obesity 
M Million et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity </p>

<p>identify and enumerate lactobacilli from human feces. 
27 As </p>

<p>in our previous study, 
12 we found an increase in Lactobacillus </p>

<p>in obese patients using the same Lactobacillus genus-specific 
PCR system. However, we found that its sensitivity profile 
was heterogeneous among the Lactobacillus species found in 
human feces by culture (data not shown). We subsequently 
developed a novel Lactobacillus species-specific qPCR system </p>

<p>targeting species associated with obesity or normal weight in 
our preliminary culture study, and targeting other species 
present in marketed probiotics products as Lactococcus lactis 
and B. animalis. Species-specific Lactobacillus PCR based 
on the Tuf gene and designed for this new study showed 
good reproducibility, sensitivity and specificity. However, 
we found significant discrepancies between culture and 
Lactobacillus species-specific PCR species. First, L. gasseri 
and L. acidophilus could not be identified in culture due 
to the presence of vancomycin in the LAMVAB medium. 
Conversely, although qPCR was much more sensitive than 
culture to detect selected species of Lactobacillus, we showed 
that the two methods were consistent for L. casei/paracasei, 
L. plantarum and L. reuteri. For these three Lactobacillus 
species, both techniques resulted in the same effect direction 
with human obesity gut microbiota enriched in L. reuteri, 
and depleted in L. casei/paracasei and L. plantarum. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Quantification of B. animalis, L. casei/paracasei, L. plantarum and L. reuteri by qPCRFMann-Whitney test. </p>

<p>Table 5 Factors associated with obesity based on multiple logistic regression 
(qPCR results, logistic regression analysis, n ¼ 107) </p>

<p>OR (95%CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>Lactobacillus reuteri 
1.79 (1.03-3.10) 
0.04 
Bifidobacterium animalis 
0.63 (0.39-1.01) 
0.056 
Methanobrevibacter smithii 
0.76 (0.59-0.97) 
0.03 
Age 
1.05 (1.01-1.08) 
0.006 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio; qPCR, quantitative PCR. </p>

<p>Gut microbiota and obesity 
M Million et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity </p>

<p>The decrease of Bacteroidetes was historically the first 
alteration significantly associated with obesity as reported 
by Ley and Turnbaugh,  8 in mice and in North American </p>

<p>individuals, 
7,9 and by Santacruz et al., 
15 who observed </p>

<p>overweight pregnant women in Spain. We found the same 
correlation in our previous study, 
12 and the same effect </p>

<p>direction in the present study with the same PCR system on 
the whole population and after the exclusion of common 
subjects. Schwiertz et al. 
11 reported opposite results, but the </p>

<p>methodology was objectionable because the Bacteroidetes 
proportion was obtained by summing Bacteroides and 
Prevotella genera. Other studies found no interaction 
between the relative or absolute abundance of Bacteroidetes 
and obesity. </p>

<p>31-33   In our previous study, 
12 abundance of M. smithii was </p>

<p>significantly higher in patients with anorexia but not in 
lean controls. In this new study, we found that M. smithii 
was less frequent and significantly less abundant in obese 
patients on the whole population and after the exclusion of 
common subjects. Schwiertz et al. 
11 using a specific qPCR for </p>

<p>Methanobrevibacter species, found similar results in a German 
population. These results are in contradiction to those of 
Zhang et al. 
33 who found that Methanobacteriales was present </p>

<p>only in obese individuals using a qPCR but only three obese 
vs three controls were compared. 
In this study, we report an association between lower levels 
of B. animalis and obesity for the first time. Five studies 
reported a decreased number of Bifidobacterium representatives 
in the feces of obese subjects at the genus level. 
11,13-16 At the </p>

<p>species level, Kalliomaki et al. 
13 using a Bifidobacterium species-</p>

<p>specific PCR, found that Bifidobacterium longum and Bifidobac-
terium breve were higher in normal weight controls, but this 
result was not significant probably because of a small sample 
size. Experimental data report that administration of a B. breve 
strain to mice with high-fat diet-induced obesity led to a 
significant weight decrease. 
34 Administering four different </p>

<p>Bifidobacterium strains to high-fat diet induced obese rats, Yin 
et al. 
35 reported that one strain increased body weight gain, </p>

<p>another induced a decrease and the two other strains lead to no 
significant change in body weight but species were not 
mentioned in this study. In this way, Cani et al. 
36 reported </p>

<p>that high-fat feeding was associated with higher endotoxaemia 
and lower Bifidobacterium species cecal content in mice. The 
selective increase of bifidobacteria by oligofructose, improving 
mucosal barrier function, significantly and positively correlated 
with improved glucose tolerance, glucose-induced insulin 
secretion and decreased endotoxaemia. 
L. plantarum and L. paracasei were associated with normal 
weight in culture, consistent with experimental models in 
the literature reporting an anti-obesity effect of L. plantarum 
in mice. 
37 Other Lactobacillus strains have shown an anti-</p>

<p>obesity effect in animals and humans similar to the L. gasseri 
SBT2055 (LG2055) strain in lean Zucker rats 
38 and in </p>

<p>humans. 
39 This anti-obesity effect may be linked to the </p>

<p>production of specific molecules that can interfere with 
host metabolism, such as conjugated linoleic acid (CLA) for </p>

<p>L. plantarum or L. rhamnosus. 
37,40 In vivo and in vitro analyses </p>

<p>of physiological modifications imparted by CLA on protein 
and gene expression suggest that CLA exerts its delipidating 
effects by modulating energy expenditure, apoptosis, fatty 
acid oxidation, lipolysis, stromal vascular cell differentia-
tion and lipogenesis. 
37 Authors who have investigated the </p>

<p>mechanisms linking conjugated linoleic acid and anti-
obesity effects have reported the upregulated expression of 
genes encoding uncoupling proteins (UCP-2), which could 
be a primary mechanism through which CLA increases 
energy expenditure and produces an anti-obesity effect. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>L. reuteri has been associated here with obesity. L. reuteri 
has been one of the most studied probiotic species especially 
for its ability to inhibit the growth of other potentially 
pathogenic microorganisms by secreting antibiotic sub-
stances such as reuterin. 
41 When introduced in pigs, turkeys </p>

<p>and rats, L. reuteri led to a significant weight gain and was 
isolated in higher concentrations from feces after probiotic 
administration. 
42-44 The mechanism by which L. reuteri is </p>

<p>able to support the healthy growth of these animals is not 
entirely understood. It is possible that L. reuteri simply serves 
to protect livestock against illness caused by Salmonella 
typhimurium and other pathogens. However, other studies 
have revealed that L. reuteri can also help when the growth 
depression is caused entirely by a lack of dietary protein and 
not by contagious disease. 
45 This raises the possibility that </p>

<p>L. reuteri somehow improves the intestines' ability to absorb 
and process nutrients, and increase food conversion. </p>

<p>46   As a theoretical basis for the causal link between the 
gut microbiota alterations and obesity, several mechanisms 
have been suggested. First, the gut microbiota could inter-
act with weight regulation by hydrolysis of indigestible 
polysaccharides to monosaccharides easily absorbable acti-
vating lipoprotein lipase. Consequently, glucose is rapidly 
absorbed producing substantial elevations in serum glucose 
and insulin, both factors that trigger lipogenesis and fatty 
acids excessively stored with de novo synthesis of triglycerides 
derived from liver, these two phenomena causing weight 
gain. 
47 Second, the composition of gut microbiota has been </p>

<p>shown to selectively suppress the angiopoietin-like protein 
4/fasting-induced adipose factor in the intestinal epithelium, 
known as a circulating lipoprotein lipase inhibitor and 
regulator of peripheral lipid and glucose metabolism. </p>

<p>48   Third, it has been suggested that bacterial isolates of gut 
microbiota may have pro-or anti-inflammatory properties, 
impacting weight as obesity, having been associated with a 
low-grade systemic inflammation corresponding to higher 
plasma endotoxin lipopolysaccharide concentrations defined 
as metabolic endotoxaemia. 
49-52 Fourth, extracting crude fat </p>

<p>in feed and excreta, Nahashon et al. 
53 reported that feeding </p>

<p>laying Leghorn with Lactobacillus improved significantly 
retention of fat with increased cellularity of the Peyer's 
patches of the ileum, which indicated ileal immune response. 
Conversely, Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus species have 
been cited to deconjugate bile acids, which may decrease 
fat absorption. </p>

<p>54   Gut microbiota and obesity 
M Million et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity </p>

<p>Finally, specific strains of Lactobacillus and Bifidobacterium 
fed to farm animals have been shown to increase daily 
weight gain, 
55 and this fact has been used for decades in </p>

<p>agriculture to increase feed conversion. In this context, one 
cannot exclude that the 'growth promoter' effect in animals 
associated with oral administration of specific probiotics 
strains is similar to the mechanisms involved in human 
obesity. For instance, Abdulrahim et al. 
56 reported that </p>

<p>L. acidophilus significantly increased abdominal fat deposi-
tion in female chickens when administered alone and up to 
31% when it was associated with zinc bacitracin. Further 
studies are therefore mandatory in exploring the interactions 
between probiotics and weight regulation. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, reduced levels of M. smithii has been 
confirmed as being associated with obesity. In addition, 
higher levels of B. animalis, L. paracasei or L. plantarum were 
associated with a normal weight whereas higher levels of 
L. reuteri were associated with obesity, suggesting a 
possible interrelationship between certain probiotic species, 
marketed elsewhere for human consumption, and obesity. 
These results must be considered cautiously because it is the 
first study to date that links specific species of Lactobacillus 
with obesity in humans. This issue will be of critical 
importance in the management of the twenty-first century 
worldwide epidemic that is obesity and especially consider-
ing the booming market of probiotics. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank all the volunteers without whom this study would 
not have been possible. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DR. Performed the 
clinical study: MM, MM, RV, BV and DR. Performed the 
experiments: MM and MH. Analyzed the data: FA, HR and 
PC. Wrote the paper: MM, MH, HR and DR. </p>

<p>Disclaimer </p>

<p>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and 
analysis, decision to publish or preparation of the manuscript </p>





<p>International Journal of Obesity </p>



<p>This work is licensed under the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-No 
Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy 
of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies the paper on International Journal of Obesity website (http://www.nature.com/ijo) </p>

<p>Gut microbiota and obesity 
M Million et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Obesity </p>

</text></tei>