<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3284254" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Imprinted loci play a critical role in fetal development.Their expression is often regulated by 
CCCTC-binding factor (CTCF) protein binding at imprinting control regions (ICRs). Prenatal 
alcohol exposure has been shown to reduce global DNA methylation in the developing 
mouse fetus. This study explored the effect of preconception paternal alcohol exposure 
on DNA methylation at two paternally methylated ICRs (H19 and Rasgrf1) in the sperm 
of exposed males and somatic DNA of sired offspring. Significant reductions at the H19 
CTCF 1 (p = 0.0027) and CTCF 2 (p = 0.0009) binding sites were observed in the offspring 
of ethanol-treated sires, which was significantly correlated with reduced weight at post-
natal days 35-42 (p &lt; 0.05). As birth weight was unaffected and growth was only delayed 
during the postnatal weaning period, with subsequent re-convergence, we hypothesize 
that this may be the result of a mental deficit causing delayed establishment of indepen-
dent feeding following weaning and would explain why this effect is transient. No difference 
in DNA methylation was observed in the sperm of alcohol-exposed males, indicating that 
the transmission of the epigenetic signal at conception is not due to altered methylation, 
but may be the result of an RNA-mediated mechanism or altered chromatin remodeling. </p>

<p>Excessive maternal alcohol exposure during pregnancy has been 
implicated in a range of unfavorable fetal outcomes, collectively 
known as fetal alcohol spectrum disorders (FASD; Burd et al., 
2003). The most severe of these outcomes, fetal alcohol syndrome 
(FAS), is characterized by pre-and postnatal growth retardation, 
mental and cognitive disability, distinct craniofacial abnormalities, 
and severe mental retardation that persist throughout life. 
Fetal alcohol syndrome has been described as the leading cause 
of preventable mental retardation in the world, and presents a con-
siderable health concern, globally (Abel and Sokol, 1987; Guerri 
et al., 2009). The global prevalence of FAS has been reported to 
be 0.5-2.0/1000 live births (May and Gossage, 2001), and poses 
a significant financial burden on health care services (Klug and 
Burd, 2003). These prevalence rates are vastly increased in some 
communities (May, 1991; Burd and Moffatt, 1994; Sampson et al., 
1997). In particular, the Western and Northern Cape regions of 
South Africa have been reported to have the highest rates of FAS 
in the world, with over 70/1000 school-going children affected 
(Viljoen et al., 2005; May et al., 2007; Urban et al., 2008). 
The etiology of FASD is poorly understood despite its high 
prevalence and detailed clinical characterization. There is evi-
dence for a genetic contribution as part of the underlying 
cause -which may affect alcohol susceptibility in the devel-
oping fetus (as reviewed in Ramsay, 2010). The globally esca-
lating prevalence rates of FAS, in conjunction with our lim-
ited understanding of its etiology and the considerable cost </p>

<p>to health services, highlight the importance of alcohol-related 
research. 
Although FAS research has focused primarily on maternal alco-
hol consumption during pregnancy, paternal contributions have 
been reported where infants were born with characteristic FASD 
symptoms to mothers who had not consumed alcohol during preg-
nancy, but whose fathers were alcoholics (Lemoine et al., 1968). 
One study reported that 75% of children with FAS had biolog-
ical fathers who were heavy drinkers or alcoholics (Abel et al., 
1983); and several rodent and human studies have reported that 
preconception paternal alcohol intake has been associated with 
congenital malformations, low birth weights, growth retardation, 
and neonatal mortality (Friedler, 1996; Passaro et al., 1998). These 
effects are not consistent between inbred rodent strains, suggest-
ing a genetic contribution to the phenotype outcome. On balance, 
however, there is evidence that FASD attributed to gestational 
alcohol exposure, may be the result of, or partly due to, exces-
sive paternal preconception alcohol consumption (Abel, 2004). 
The etiology of paternal contributions to FASD is however, largely 
unexplored to date. 
Epigenetic modifications are independent of the DNA sequence 
and regulate gene expression (as reviewed in Holliday, 2006). Epi-
genetic mechanisms are vital components in regulating cell cycle 
and developmental processes in a spatial and temporal manner. 
These mechanisms include DNA methylation of cytosine bases 
and modifications to the core histone proteins, as well as RNA 
interference. Imprinted genes rely on DNA methylation to silence </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 1 </p>

<p>Knezovich and Ramsay </p>

<p>Perception alcohol effects on ICRs </p>

<p>and activate alleles in a parent-of-origin specific manner, ensur-
ing the reciprocal expression of specific genes. In some instances, 
expression is regulated through the methylation-sensitive binding 
of the insulator protein, CCCTC-binding factor (CTCF), at differ-
entially methylated imprinting control regions (ICRs), through its 
enhancer-blocking activity. Initial Igf2 knockout studies demon-
strated that the Igf2/H19 imprinted locus is involved in mam-
malian embryonic development and placentation (Barlow et al., 
1991; DeChiara et al., 1991). According to the mechanism by 
which the Igf2/H19 locus is regulated, the hypomethylated state 
of the maternal ICR allows for the binding of the CTCF pro-
tein, insulating the downstream common enhancer from accessing 
the upstream paternally expressed H19 gene promoter, while the 
downstream maternally expressed Igf2 gene promoter is selec-
tively acted upon. Conversely, the hypermethylated ICR on the 
paternal allele prevents CTCF binding and allows downstream 
enhancers to act on Igf2, while H19 expression is suppressed -
effectively achieving reciprocal, monoallelic, parent-of-origin gene 
expression. 
Imprinted genes are vital for fetal growth and development 
(Fowden et al., 2006), and their dysregulation leads to profound 
congenital abnormalities (Piedrahita, 2011). The dynamic nature 
of the mechanisms governing epigenetic regulation and their 
sensitivity to environmental influences (Bernal and Jirtle, 2010; 
Chmurzynska, 2010; Skinner et al., 2010; Ferguson-Smith and 
Patti, 2011), make them an attractive target to study the effect 
of environmental contributions to disease etiology. 
Alcohol is a well-studied teratogen and its metabolites have 
been shown to directly interfere with epigenetic mechanisms 
through its influence on one carbon metabolism and the 
methyl donor pathway. Alcohol enhances the catabolism and 
loss of methyl groups, which in turn disrupts subsequent SAM-
dependent transmethylation reactions of the folate pathway, which 
are required for DNA methylation (Schalinske and Nieman, 2005). 
Investigations using mouse models demonstrated that alcohol 
exposure during gestation can result in global hypomethylation 
of fetal DNA (Garro et al., 1991), locus specific hypermethyla-
tion (Kaminen-Ahola et al., 2010) and selected hypomethylation 
of the paternally imprinted H19 ICR in the mouse placenta (Hay-
cock and Ramsay, 2009; although these authors did not observe 
a difference in fetal DNA). In addition, site-specific hypomethy-
lation of male gametes have been noted in both mice (Stouder 
et al., 2011) and humans (Ouko et al., 2009) chronically exposed 
to alcohol. Together, these findings provide a link between altered 
DNA methylation and FAS. 
Given that imprinted genes are essentially haploid in nature -
due to their reliance on DNA methylation to silence one of the 
parental alleles and achieve monoallelic expression -and that per-
turbations to such regulation results in abnormal fetal phenotypes, 
makes this group of genes particularly vulnerable to epimuta-
tions. Considering the impact of alcohol on DNA methylation, 
this study aimed to investigate the effect of paternal alcohol expo-
sure on the methylation status of two paternally imprinted loci 
[Insulin-like growth factor 2 (Igf2)/H19 and Ras protein-specific 
guanine nucleotide-releasing factor 1 (Rasgrf1)] in both the sperm 
of exposed males, and their sired offspring. H19 is highly expressed 
in the developing embryo (Poirier et al., 1991), where it works in </p>

<p>conjunction with Igf2, a potent mitogen, to regulate fetal growth 
and development (Kim and Kim, 2005; Chao and D'Amore, 
2008), while Rasgrf1 encodes a guanine-nucleotide exchange fac-
tor involved in fetal growth and memory (Brambilla et al., 1997; 
Itier et al., 1998). Expression of these genes is tightly regulated by 
the methylation-sensitive binding of CTCF at the ICRs contained 
within both of these loci (Schoenherr et al., 2003; Yoon et al., 2005). 
Contrary to expectation, this study did not observe differences 
in DNA methylation at the H19 and Rasgrf1 ICRs in the sperm of 
alcohol-exposed male mice. We did however observe significantly 
decreased DNA methylation profiles at the H19 ICR CTCF bind-
ing sites in the somatic tissue of offspring sired by ethanol-exposed 
male mice, which was correlated with postnatal growth restriction. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>ALCOHOL EXPOSURE IN THE MOUSE MODEL </p>

<p>Eight C57BL/6 male mice were treated with 7.5 μl/g of a 50% 
solution of ethanol (5.917 g/kg), simulating a pharmacologi-
cally significant effect (Rhodes et al., 2005), which resulted in a 
blood ethanol concentration of &gt; 1.0 mg/ml. Seven control males 
received an isocaloric solution of a 0.704 g/ml sucrose solution at 
7.5 μl/g. Food and water was given ad libitum. Oral gavaging was 
carried out over a five week period. During the first week, mice 
were gavaged every second day; during week two, daily for five 
days; and daily thereafter. In week six, each male mouse was mated 
with two C57BL/6 females. Successful mating was determined by 
the presence of a vaginal plug. A total of 46 offspring (17 sired 
by ethanol-treated males, 29 sired by sucrose-treated males) were 
obtained. Offspring were weighed every second day for 30 days, 
and weekly thereafter, until postnatal day 63. Tail biopsies were 
taken at four weeks of age. Animal ethics clearance was obtained 
from the Animal Ethics Screening Committee, University of the 
Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa (clearance certificate 
no. 2007/41/03). </p>

<p>DNA EXTRACTION AND BISULFITE MODIFICATION </p>

<p>Mature sperm was harvested within 24 h of the last day of mating 
by epididymal dissection and spermatozoa isolated using the Dif-
ferex™System (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). DNA from sperm 
and offspring tail biopsies were extracted using the QIAamp DNA 
Micro Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, North Rhine-Westphalia, Germany) 
and bisulfite modified using the EpiTect ® Bisulfite Kit (Qiagen, 
Hilden, North Rhine-Westphalia, Germany). </p>

<p>ICR PCR AMPLIFICATION </p>

<p>The approximately 2 kb H19 ICR (located on contig AC13548.13) 
lies 2 kb upstream of the H19 transcriptional unit. The 423 bp 
region amplified in the present study contains two of the four 
H19 ICR CTCF binding sites and a total of 16 CpG sites (approx-
imately 40% of the CpGs contained within the ICR). Six CpGs of 
the first and five CpGs of the second CTCF binding sites (CTCF 1 
and CTCF 2, respectively) were analyzed. The 284 bp Rasgrf1 ICR 
region amplified is located on contig AC102545.9 and contains 29 
CpG sites, with the CTCF binding site spanning CpGs 20-27. A 
420 bp region of the Snrpn ICR, containing 16 CpGs, was included 
as a control for the detection of somatic contamination in sperm 
DNA. ICRs were PCR amplified using a GeneAmp 2720 thermal </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Epigenomics </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 2 </p>

<p>Knezovich and Ramsay </p>

<p>Perception alcohol effects on ICRs </p>

<p>cycler (Applied Biosystems, Kotoku, Tokyo, Japan) in a final vol-
ume of 50 μl containing 0.2 mM dNTPs, 1 × PCR Gold Buffer, 
1.5 mM MgCl 2 , 1 U AmpliTaq Gold (Applied Biosystems, Kotoku, 
Tokyo, Japan), 2 μl DNA (100 ng/μl), 10 μM of each forward (F) 
and reverse (R) primer according to the following conditions: 
95˚C 5 min (95˚C 30 s, Ta˚C 1 min, 72˚C 1 min) for 50 cycles, 
72˚C 5 min. The annealing temperatures and primer sequences 
for amplification of the ICRs from bisulfite modified DNA were as 
follows: H19 55˚C (F 5 -GAGTATTTAGGAGGTATAAGAATT-3 , 
R 5 -ATCAAAAACTAACATAAACCCCT-3 ); Rasgrf1 59˚C (F 5 -
TAGAGAGTTTATAAAGTTAG-3 , R 5 -ACTAAAACAAAAACAA 
CA-3 ); Snrpn 59˚C (F 5 -TATGTAATATGATATAGTTTAGAAATT 
AG-3 , R 5 -AATAAACCCAAATCTAAAATATTTTAATC-3 ). A 
second round of PCR was performed using 1 μl PCR prod-
uct from the first round under the same reaction con-
ditions. Forward and reverse primers were designed using 
the <rs id="software-1" type="software">PSQ Assay Design Software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Biotage</rs>, Uppsala, Uppsala 
County, Sweden). A universal biotin-labeled primer (5 -biotin-
GACGGGACACCGCTGATCGTTTA-3 ) was used to generate 
labeled DNA fragments (Colella et al., 2003). A priming site for 
the universal primer was achieved by the addition of a com-
plementary 5 23 bp tail onto each reverse primer. H19 (CTCF 
1) 60˚C (F 5 -AGGAGGTATAAGAATTTTGTAAGG-3 , R 5 -
GACGGGACACCGCTGATCGTTTATTAAATAACCCACAACAT 
TACCAT-3 ); H19 (CTCF 2) 66˚C (F 5 -TTGTGTGTAAAGATTAG 
GGTTGTT-3 , R 5 -GACGGGACACCGCTGATCGTTTAAACTA 
ACATAAACCCCTAACCTCA-3 ); Snrpn 66˚C (F 5 -TGGTAGTTG 
TTTTTTGGTAGGATA-3 ,R 5 -GACGGGACACCGCTGATCGTT 
TATCCACAAACCCAACTAACCTT-3 ); Rasgrf1 50˚C (F 5 -
GTTATAGTTGAGTTATAATTATTA-3 , R 5 -ACTAAAACAAAAA 
CAACACTACAAC-3 ). </p>

<p>QUANTIFICATION OF DNA METHYLATION AT SELECTED CpG SITES </p>

<p>DNA methylation was quantified by pyrosequencing in tripli-
cate using the PSQ 96 MA System in conjunction with Pyro 
Q-CpG Software (Biotage, Uppsala, Uppsala County, Sweden). 
Sequencing (S) primers were designed using the PSQ Assay 
Design Software (Biotage, Uppsala, Uppsala County, Sweden) 
as follows: H19 (CTCF 1; S 5 -GGAATTAGTTGTGGGGTT-
3 ); H19 (CTCF 2; S 5 -GTGTAAAGATTAGGGTTGTT-3 ); 
Snrpn (S 5 -GTGTAGTTATTGTTTGGGA-3 ); Rasgrf1 (S 5 -
CCAAATACCACAACAACAA-3 ). Two non-CpG cytosine bases 
were included in all pyrosequencing assays as an internal control 
for successful bisulfite conversion, and samples containing &gt; 5% 
unsuccessfully converted non-CpG cytosines were discarded. </p>

<p>STATISTICAL ANALYSES </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney U tests were used to assess changes in methy-
lation in sperm DNA and somatic DNA of ethanol-exposed 
males and sired offspring, respectively, between the two treat-
ment groups. Average methylation values were obtained by aver-
aging triplicate data values. A Kruskal-Wallis analysis of vari-
ance (ANOVA) and Spearman's correlations tested for differ-
ences in offspring postnatal growth. All data were tested for 
normality using the Shapiro-Wilk's W test, and appropriate non-
parametric tests were applied. P-values ≤ 0.05 were considered 
significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>METHYLATION ANALYSES OF OFFSPRING SOMATIC DNA </p>

<p>Analysis of individual CpG sites (Table 1) of H19 CTCF 1 revealed 
that sites 2, 3, 5-7 (p &lt; 0.01), and 4 (p &lt; 0.05) were significantly 
less methylated in offspring whose sires were exposed to ethanol. 
Likewise, the H19 CTCF 2 demonstrated significant hypomethy-
lation at CpG sites 11, 12 and 13 (p = 0.0040, 0.0018 and 0.0014, 
respectively) when compared to controls. Analysis of the Rasgrf1 
CTCF binding site revealed no significant differences in DNA 
methylation. It was interesting to note evidence of site-specific 
alterations in DNA methylation at the Snrpn locus in offspring 
of ethanol-treated sires, with increases at CpG sites 8 and 11 
(p &lt; 0.05), and a decrease at CpG site 9 (p = 0.0924) within 
the ICR. Deviation from the expected average methylation of 
50% at these loci (as would normally be expected at imprinted 
regions) in the control group, is not uncommon, as documented 
in other studies (Ollikainen et al., 2010; Turan et al., 2010; Cho-
ufani et al., 2011). Thus, when comparing the offspring group sired 
by ethanol-treated males with the control group sired by sucrose-
treated males, significant differences observed in DNA methylation 
can be attributed to the ethanol treatment of sires. The variation 
in DNA methylation percentage within each of the H19 CTCF 
binding sites was relatively low from site to site, and was repro-
ducible. The decreases in methylation over consecutive CpG sites 
were consistent between treatment groups. </p>

<p>OFFSPRING POSTNATAL GROWTH </p>

<p>The postnatal growth (weight) of offspring sired by ethanol-
treated males (n = 17, "ethanol offspring") and control males 
(n = 29, "sucrose offspring") was recorded over a 63 day period. 
There was no observed difference in birth weight. When strati-
fied by sex, there was a notable trend between the two treatment 
groups with both ethanol male and female offspring exhibiting 
a lower postnatal growth rate compared to their sucrose coun-
terparts (Figure 1). This trend was most pronounced after day 
30. A Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA (Supplementary Material) revealed 
that the divergence of sucrose male offspring from ethanol male 
offspring was significant at day 35 (p = 0.0389) with days 42, 
49, and 56 approaching significance (p = 0.0640, 0.0640, and 
0.0901, respectively). Similarly, female ethanol offspring showed 
lower weights than their sucrose counterparts at days 35 and 42 
(p = 0.0353 and 0.0353, respectively). </p>

<p>CORRELATION OF OFFSPRING ICR DNA METHYLATION WITH WEIGHT 
AT DAY 35 </p>

<p>Analyses were conducted on offspring DNA methylation profiles 
at the level of individual CpG sites, and were correlated with off-
spring weight at day 35 -where a significant difference in weight 
between the treatment groups was observed (Table S1 in Sup-
plementary Material). Significant, positive correlations suggested 
that decreased DNA methylation was associated with decreased 
offspring weight. Such correlations were observed for all CpG 
sites (2-7) comprising the H19 CTCF 1 region at day 35. Simi-
larly, DNA methylation at the CpG sites contained within the H19 
CTCF 2 region (11-14) were significantly correlated with offspring 
weight at day 35 (p &lt; 0.05), with CpG 15 approaching significance 
(p = 0.0509). </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 3 </p>

<p>Knezovich and Ramsay </p>

<p>Perception alcohol effects on ICRs </p>

<p>Table 1 | Quantitative pyrosequencing data of sperm DNA from ethanol-treated males and tail biopsy DNA from sired offspring. 
Region </p>

<p>Treated male sperm </p>

<p>Offspring tail biopsies </p>

<p>Ethanol mean 
methylation (%) </p>

<p>SD 
Sucrose mean 
methylation (%) </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney </p>

<p>U test Z adjusted </p>

<p>p-Value Ethanol mean 
methylation (%) </p>

<p>SD 
Sucrose mean 
methylation (%) </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney </p>

<p>U test Z adjusted </p>

<p>p-Value </p>

<p>CTCF1 </p>

<p>96.28 </p>

<p>1.47 </p>

<p>97.32 </p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p>−1.45 </p>

<p>0.1320 </p>

<p>68.61 </p>

<p>6.34 75.51 </p>

<p>7.40 </p>

<p>−2.92 </p>

<p>0.0027** </p>

<p>H19CpG2 </p>

<p>95.33 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>94.92 </p>

<p>1.69 </p>

<p>−0.52 </p>

<p>0.5887 </p>

<p>66.89 </p>

<p>6.16 73.84 </p>

<p>7.70 </p>

<p>−2.95 </p>

<p>0.0025** </p>

<p>H19CpG3 </p>

<p>98.83 </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>99.00 </p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p>−0.60 </p>

<p>0.5887 </p>

<p>68.90 </p>

<p>5.10 75.95 </p>

<p>8.13 </p>

<p>−3.03 </p>

<p>0.0019** </p>

<p>H19CpG4 </p>

<p>100.00 </p>

<p>0.00 100.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>N/A </p>

<p>N/A </p>

<p>76.07 </p>

<p>9.34 82.08 </p>

<p>8.59 </p>

<p>−2.45 </p>

<p>0.0129* </p>

<p>H19CpG5 </p>

<p>96.92 </p>

<p>1.66 </p>

<p>97.50 </p>

<p>0.89 </p>

<p>−0.41 </p>

<p>0.6991 </p>

<p>67.04 </p>

<p>6.62 73.41 </p>

<p>7.47 </p>

<p>−2.54 </p>

<p>0.0098** </p>

<p>H19CpG6 </p>

<p>94.67 </p>

<p>7.15 </p>

<p>98.83 </p>

<p>2.40 </p>

<p>−0.80 </p>

<p>0.4848 </p>

<p>68.95 </p>

<p>6.20 75.75 </p>

<p>7.75 </p>

<p>−2.79 </p>

<p>0.0043** </p>

<p>H19CpG7 </p>

<p>91.92 </p>

<p>1.96 </p>

<p>93.67 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>−1.97 </p>

<p>0.0411* 63.83 </p>

<p>10.07 72.04 </p>

<p>8.07 </p>

<p>−2.79 </p>

<p>0.0043** </p>

<p>CTCF2 </p>

<p>97.15 </p>

<p>1.65 </p>

<p>96.60 </p>

<p>2.98 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.9372 </p>

<p>75.23 </p>

<p>9.84 83.87 </p>

<p>5.38 </p>

<p>−3.20 </p>

<p>0.0009*** </p>

<p>H19CpG11 </p>

<p>99.00 </p>

<p>1.14 </p>

<p>95.58 </p>

<p>10.09 </p>

<p>−0.42 </p>

<p>0.6991 </p>

<p>71.84 </p>

<p>19.96 84.06 </p>

<p>6.52 </p>

<p>−2.82 </p>

<p>0.0040** </p>

<p>H19CpG12 </p>

<p>96.25 </p>

<p>0.69 </p>

<p>94.33 </p>

<p>2.54 </p>

<p>1.56 </p>

<p>0.1320 </p>

<p>70.59 </p>

<p>15.93 81.28 </p>

<p>6.24 </p>

<p>−3.04 </p>

<p>0.0018** </p>

<p>H19CpG13 </p>

<p>97.42 </p>

<p>0.86 </p>

<p>95.75 </p>

<p>3.37 </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>0.4848 </p>

<p>66.08 </p>

<p>24.59 81.51 </p>

<p>6.06 </p>

<p>−3.12 </p>

<p>0.0013** </p>

<p>H19CpG14 </p>

<p>96.58 </p>

<p>5.96 </p>

<p>99.08 </p>

<p>1.39 </p>

<p>−0.98 </p>

<p>0.3095 </p>

<p>84.46 </p>

<p>11.40 </p>

<p>86.69 </p>

<p>7.66 </p>

<p>−0.56 </p>

<p>0.5732 </p>

<p>H19CpG15 </p>

<p>96.50 </p>

<p>4.23 </p>

<p>98.25 </p>

<p>2.62 </p>

<p>−0.81 </p>

<p>0.3939 </p>

<p>83.16 </p>

<p>9.27 85.82 </p>

<p>7.08 </p>

<p>−1.46 </p>

<p>0.1466 </p>

<p>Rasgrf1 </p>

<p>85.92 </p>

<p>3.96 </p>

<p>87.62 </p>

<p>3.62 </p>

<p>−0.56 </p>

<p>0.5887 </p>

<p>68.08 </p>

<p>9.49 65.36 </p>

<p>11.22 </p>

<p>0.82 </p>

<p>0.4175 </p>

<p>Rasgrf1CpG20 </p>

<p>90.25 </p>

<p>8.02 </p>

<p>93.25 </p>

<p>5.72 </p>

<p>−0.89 </p>

<p>0.3939 </p>

<p>74.91 </p>

<p>9.88 </p>

<p>72.62 </p>

<p>9.24 </p>

<p>0.94 </p>

<p>0.3529 </p>

<p>Rasgrf1CpG21 </p>

<p>84.75 </p>

<p>16.13 </p>

<p>91.42 </p>

<p>5.54 </p>

<p>−0.64 </p>

<p>0.4848 </p>

<p>71.84 </p>

<p>16.70 65.33 </p>

<p>21.79 </p>

<p>0.98 </p>

<p>0.3289 </p>

<p>Rasgrf1CpG22 </p>

<p>69.00 </p>

<p>17.29 </p>

<p>79.33 </p>

<p>10.69 </p>

<p>−1.04 </p>

<p>0.3095 </p>

<p>52.38 </p>

<p>9.89 49.66 </p>

<p>14.22 </p>

<p>0.31 </p>

<p>0.7516 </p>

<p>Rasgrf1CpG23 </p>

<p>83.75 </p>

<p>9.36 </p>

<p>75.75 </p>

<p>4.89 </p>

<p>1.21 </p>

<p>0.2403 </p>

<p>54.50 </p>

<p>8.28 53.48 </p>

<p>13.51 </p>

<p>−0.42 </p>

<p>0.6814 </p>

<p>Rasgrf1CpG24 </p>

<p>99.58 </p>

<p>1.02 </p>

<p>99.58 </p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p>0.32 </p>

<p>0.8182 </p>

<p>86.84 </p>

<p>8.48 80.95 </p>

<p>15.93 </p>

<p>1.17 </p>

<p>0.2435 </p>

<p>Rasgrf1CpG25 </p>

<p>75.50 </p>

<p>8.90 </p>

<p>74.00 </p>

<p>7.44 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.9372 </p>

<p>49.00 </p>

<p>16.39 46.95 </p>

<p>12.18 </p>

<p>1.30 </p>

<p>0.1904 </p>

<p>Rasgrf1CpG26 </p>

<p>98.58 </p>

<p>1.43 100.00 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>−2.20 </p>

<p>0.0649 a </p>

<p>87.06 </p>

<p>10.15 88.53 </p>

<p>12.20 </p>

<p>−0.95 </p>

<p>0.3408 </p>

<p>Snrpn </p>

<p>2.96 </p>

<p>0.89 </p>

<p>3.81 </p>

<p>1.52 </p>

<p>−0.72 </p>

<p>0.4848 </p>

<p>63.42 </p>

<p>9.49 60.65 </p>

<p>8.99 </p>

<p>1.38 </p>

<p>0.1668 </p>

<p>SnrpnCpG6 </p>

<p>2.11 </p>

<p>1.71 </p>

<p>3.14 </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>−1.36 </p>

<p>0.1797 </p>

<p>60.71 </p>

<p>4.09 59.21 </p>

<p>9.43 </p>

<p>1.10 </p>

<p>0.2679 </p>

<p>SnrpnCpG7 </p>

<p>5.42 </p>

<p>2.51 </p>

<p>5.75 </p>

<p>1.16 </p>

<p>−0.65 </p>

<p>0.4848 </p>

<p>64.62 </p>

<p>5.48 62.41 </p>

<p>8.47 </p>

<p>1.31 </p>

<p>0.1889 </p>

<p>SnrpnCpG8 </p>

<p>4.94 </p>

<p>1.57 </p>

<p>5.22 </p>

<p>1.74 </p>

<p>−0.24 </p>

<p>0.8182 </p>

<p>78.74 </p>

<p>7.98 74.03 </p>

<p>8.87 </p>

<p>2.28 </p>

<p>0.0217* </p>

<p>SnrpnCpG9 </p>

<p>1.25 </p>

<p>0.76 </p>

<p>2.06 </p>

<p>1.29 </p>

<p>−1.53 </p>

<p>0.1320 </p>

<p>50.00 </p>

<p>6.14 53.41 </p>

<p>10.74 </p>

<p>−1.69 </p>

<p>0.0924 a </p>

<p>SnrpnCpG10 </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>0.80 </p>

<p>2.92 </p>

<p>1.41 </p>

<p>−2.67 </p>

<p>0.0043* 61.74 </p>

<p>3.79 58.72 </p>

<p>10.41 </p>

<p>1.06 </p>

<p>0.2881 </p>

<p>SnrpnCpG11 </p>

<p>3.72 </p>

<p>2.72 </p>

<p>4.86 </p>

<p>4.48 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>1.0000 </p>

<p>66.53 </p>

<p>5.81 59.48 </p>

<p>10.87 </p>

<p>2.43 </p>

<p>0.0138* </p>

<p>SnrpnCpG12 </p>

<p>2.53 </p>

<p>1.86 </p>

<p>2.69 </p>

<p>2.54 </p>

<p>−0.08 </p>

<p>0.9372 </p>

<p>61.65 </p>

<p>5.50 57.26 </p>

<p>10.07 </p>

<p>1.22 </p>

<p>0.2217 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>p 
&lt; 0.1, *p 
&lt; 0.05, **p 
&lt; 0.01, ***p </p>

<p>&lt; 0.001. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Epigenomics </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 4 </p>

<p>Knezovich and Ramsay </p>

<p>Perception alcohol effects on ICRs </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 | Postnatal growth rate of sired offspring. Postnatal weight of 
offspring sired by sucrose-exposed (control) males and ethanol-exposed 
males was measured over a 63 day period and stratified by sex (sucrose 
male/female and ethanol male/female, respectively). Measurements were 
taken every second day until postnatal day 30, and weekly thereafter. </p>

<p>METHYLATION ANALYSES OF SPERM DNA </p>

<p>The Snrpn ICR was included as a control for the detection of cont-
aminating somatic DNA in sperm samples. The DNA methylation 
status at this ICR was consistently low in 12 samples -ranging 
between 0.72 and 5.75% -and were used for subsequent analy-
ses. The sperm of one of the 13 male mice had an average level 
of over 10% DNA methylation and was excluded from the study. 
The Snrpn ICR revealed significantly decreased DNA methylation 
at CpG 10 (p = 0.0043; Table 1). Overall, there was no significant 
demethylation at the H19 and Rasgrf1 ICRs, with only one CpG 
site demonstrating a significant reduction in DNA methylation 
in the ethanol-treated male group (H19 CpG 7, p = 0.0411), and 
Rasgrf1 CpG 26 bordering on significance (p = 0.0649; Table 1). 
Fluctuations in the Snrpn methylation status suggests that these 
difference are unlikely to be of significance. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The findings of this study are consistent with the prediction that 
preconception alcohol treatment of male mice has an adverse effect 
on sired offspring. This included age restricted growth retarda-
tion and a reduction in DNA methylation at the H19 paternally 
imprinted ICR. 
There is conflicting evidence about the effect of paternal 
preconception alcohol exposure on offspring birth weight. While 
some studies have shown that alcohol orally administered to male 
mice for periods of between 24 h and 3 months prior to concep-
tion tends to result in decreased birth weights of sired offspring 
(Cicero et al., 1994; Ledig et al., 1998); others have not observed 
such an effect in both humans and rodent models (Anderson and 
Willis, 1981; Abel and Lee, 1988; Abel and Tan, 1988; Abel, 1989, 
1993; Passaro et al., 1998; Livy et al., 2004). Although these latter 
findings are supported by our study (when offspring are stratified </p>

<p>by sex; data not shown), evidence of significant age-dependent 
growth restriction of both male and female offspring sired by 
ethanol-exposed males was observed, from approximately post-
natal day 35-42. This is supported by rodent studies which noted 
inferior growth rates of offspring sired by alcohol-exposed males 
when compared to control offspring (Stockard, 1913; Stockard and 
Papanicolaou, 1916a,b); and findings of significantly decreased 
postnatal growth in children of alcoholic men (Abel and Sokol, 
1983; Little and Sing, 1987). 
When the regulation of imprinted loci is dependent on the 
methylation-sensitive binding of CTCF within the ICR, changes 
in DNA methylation may have profound effects on CTCF binding 
and gene expression. In the present study, the average decrease 
in DNA methylation across the CpG sites of the H19 ICR in the 
offspring sired by ethanol-treated males when compared to their 
controls, ranged between 2.23 and 15.43% (Table 1). This decrease 
could potentially allow increased CTCF binding at the paternal 
ICR, essentially switching the allele to a maternal epigenotype, 
and significantly reducing paternally expressed Igf2, while overex-
pressing H19, contributing to a growth restricted phenotype (as 
highlighted in Bourque et al., 2010). It has been demonstrated 
that inhibition of DNA methyltransferases (Dnmts) results in 
decreased DNA methylation at the Igf2/H19 locus in mice, and 
subsequent activation of H19 from the paternal allele (Li et al., 
1992). Furthermore, decreased placental methylation at the H19 
ICR has been associated with significantly underexpressed IGF2 
in placental villi, correlated with postnatal growth restriction in 
humans (Bartholdi et al., 2009; Bourque et al., 2010). 
There is evidence to suggest that modest changes in DNA 
methylation at CTCF binding regions can elicit a significant bio-
logical effect. Induced loss of DNA methylation at the human 
telomerase reverse transcriptase (hTERT ) promoter from between 
10 and 39% (Renaud et al., 2007; Choi et al., 2010), resulted in sig-
nificantly increased CTCF binding, with a concomitant reduction 
in hTERT expression. Furthermore, demethylation of the Inter-
leukin 6 gene promoter (Nile et al., 2008) and a single CpG site 
within the Interleukin 2 promoter-enhancer region (Murayama 
et al., 2006), have been associated with elevated interleukin expres-
sion via increased protein interaction at these regions, and in the 
case of increased Interleukin 6 expression, has been shown to con-
tribute to the risk of developing rheumatoid arthritis. The changes 
observed in the present study are similar to these findings and may 
suggest a functional impact on gene expression in the offspring of 
ethanol-treated sires. 
Imprinted genes have collectively been associated with fetal 
growth and development (Fowden et al., 2006), postnatal adap-
tation to feeding (Plagge et al., 2004), and perturbations to both 
paternally and maternally expressed genes have been linked to 
behavioral phenotypes that include deficits in feeding, pup suck-
ling and energy metabolism (Curley and Mashoodh, 2010). Sire 
treatment with ethanol was significantly correlated with decreased 
offspring somatic DNA methylation and weight restriction at day 
35, but not at birth. This coincides with the post-weaning period, 
and may suggest difficulties in establishing independent feeding 
due to potential mental deficit and subsequent undernourishment 
during the transition period from maternal mammary milk to 
solid foods. It has been shown that rat pups prenatally exposed </p>

<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 5 </p>

<p>Knezovich and Ramsay </p>

<p>Perception alcohol effects on ICRs </p>

<p>to alcohol demonstrated postnatal growth deficiencies which were 
attributed to suckling difficulties (Chen et al., 1982). Furthermore, 
children born with FAS frequently suffer from feeding difficul-
ties -which are said to be an indication of central nervous dys-
function -and exacerbates postnatal growth deficiencies (Driscoll 
et al., 1990). The teratogenic effect of alcohol associated with FAS 
severely affects neural development (Kotch and Sulik, 1992a,b) 
which results in central nervous system dysfunction. The etiology 
of these effects is not fully understood, but alcohol exposure during 
early neurulation has been shown to ubiquitously decrease DNA 
methylation, which is associated with changes in gene expression 
in the developing mouse brain (Liu et al., 2009). This finding sug-
gests that aberrant DNA methylation at several loci may contribute 
to the mental deficits associated with FAS. The fact that ethanol 
can exert its effect on DNA methylation throughout the genome, 
and that there is support for the hypothesis that environmental 
perturbations of the epigenotype occur most readily at loci where 
the epigenome is undergoing developmental change (Waterland 
et al., 2006), opens the possibility that several imprinted loci in 
the sperm may have been significantly affected by preconception 
alcohol exposure. 
Aberrant H19 ICR methylation has been associated with the 
growth retardation syndrome, Silver-Russell syndrome (SRS), 
which is characterized by severe fetal growth restriction. 
Hypomethylation of the H19 ICR has been reported in 20-65% 
of SRS patients, whose degree of hypomethylation has been asso-
ciated with phenotype severity (Bruce et al., 2009). Patients with 
moderate methylation (9-35%) did not appear to be significantly 
growth restricted at birth, but did exhibit postnatal growth defi-
ciencies -where the degree of H19 ICR hypomethylation was 
associated with increasing feeding difficulties (Blissett et al., 2001). 
Recently, hypomethylation at the H19 ICR CTCF binding sites and 
the consequent aberrant binding of CTCF at this locus has been 
linked with SRS etiology (Nativio et al., 2011). Feeding difficulties 
associated with SRS have been attributed to cognitive defects that 
affect oral-motor dysfunction, including problems with chewing 
unfamiliar textures, and has been observed in 90% of children 
with SRS (Blissett et al., 2001). There are interesting parallels 
with the current study. Firstly, as noted by Bruce et al. (2009), 
we did not observe significant reductions in birth weight in off-
spring who demonstrated a moderate (approximately 15%), yet 
significant reduction in H19 ICR methylation, but did observe 
postnatal growth deficiencies. Secondly, a growth restricted phe-
notype similar to SRS, was correlated with hypomethylation of 
the H19 ICR CTCF binding sites that was associated with reduced 
offspring growth in the period following weaning (Marques et al., 
2008; Nicholson et al., 2009). Lastly, weight recovery was observed 
during the post-weaning period, similar to findings of Blissett et al. 
(2001). Taken together, it is therefore plausible that the observed 
postnatal growth restricted phenotype during the post-weaning 
period could be attributed to feeding difficulties associated with 
altered DNA methylation of one or more ICRs that influence 
mental functioning and postnatal feeding behavior. 
Although the exact mechanism that contributed to the age-
dependent growth-restricted phenotype observed in the offspring 
in our study is only speculative, the fact that significantly reduced 
methylation profiles at the H19 ICR were evident in offspring of </p>

<p>ethanol-treated sires, suggests that an epimutation was inherited 
via the paternal germline. It has been demonstrated that ethanol 
exposure causes epigenetic remodeling, affecting both histone pro-
teins and DNA methylation. A recent study by Stouder et al. (2011), 
exposed pregnant mice to a low dose of ethanol (0.5g/kg) to deter-
mine aberrant effects on DNA methylation at imprinted loci in 
their offspring, including their gametes. These authors found that 
direct in utero exposure to ethanol resulted in significant decreases 
in sperm DNA methylation at the H19 ICR CTCF 2 binding site, 
but no difference in somatic tissues of offspring. This might sug-
gest that sperm DNA methylation, specifically at the H19 ICR, is 
particularly sensitive to ethanol exposure. However, findings of 
reduced methylation in the sperm DNA of ethanol exposed males 
in our study were nuanced and significantly evident at only two 
CpG sites in the two loci investigated (H19 CpG 7 and Rasgrf1 
CpG 26). Stouder et al. (2011) subsequently produced offspring 
from males with sperm H19 ICR DNA methylation aberrations, 
and contrary to their previous findings, did not observe methyla-
tion differences in the sperm DNA of these offspring, but rather, 
significantly decreased DNA methylation at the H19 ICR CTCF 2 
binding site in whole brain tissue. 
Despite the presence of significantly reduced DNA methyla-
tion at the H19 CTCF 1 and CTCF 2 binding sites in offspring 
sired by ethanol-treated males in our study, only a single CpG 
site (H19 CpG 7) correlated with a similar significant decrease in 
sire sperm DNA. The lack of evidence of reduced DNA methyla-
tion in the sperm of ethanol-exposed males, may also suggest that 
the methylation deficiency observed at the corresponding ICRs in 
their offspring occurs post conception, but may be "programmed" 
in sperm prior to conception via alternate mechanisms suscep-
tible to ethanol. These could include RNA mediated effects and 
histone modifications. RNA molecules present in, and unique to, 
sperm (Ostermeier et al., 2002, 2005; Geijsen et al., 2004; Ras-
soulzadegan et al., 2006) have been reported to be successfully 
transmitted to the oocyte during fertilization (Ostermeier et al., 
2004). These RNAs (which include miRNAs) play a vital role in 
gene regulation and fetal development (Geijsen et al., 2004), and 
perturbations to these molecules in sperm have been shown to 
elicit aberrant offspring phenotypes (Rassoulzadegan et al., 2006). 
Ethanol has been found to disrupt miRNA expression (Sathyan 
et al., 2007; Wang et al., 2008) and is correlated with significant 
decreases in offspring weight (Wang et al., 2009). Furthermore, 
evidence of RNA directed DNA methylation has been described in 
two studies that demonstrated the establishment of DNA methy-
lation by small RNA intermediates (Kawasaki and Taira, 2004; 
Morris et al., 2004). Alcohol exposure is also known to result 
in folate deficiency which, causes significant biological effects by 
altering histone modifications at lysine residues (Park et al., 2003; 
Kim and Shukla, 2005, 2006; Esteller, 2008; Shukla et al., 2008) 
and are associated with altered gene expression (Pal-Bhadra et al., 
2007). Although sperm DNA is mainly protamine-bound, approx-
imately 15% of human sperm DNA is retained in histone-bound 
structures (Gatewood et al., 1987; Bench et al., 1996; Hammoud 
et al., 2009) which, through epigenetic modifications, acquire pre-
cise nucleosome organization that regulates gene expression. It has 
been demonstrated that nucleosomes retained in sperm are sig-
nificantly enriched at developmentally significant loci, including </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Epigenomics </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 6 </p>

<p>Knezovich and Ramsay </p>

<p>Perception alcohol effects on ICRs </p>

<p>imprinted regions (Wykes and Krawetz, 2003; Hammoud et al., 
2009). It is interesting to note that the hypomethylated and hyper-
methylated state of the H19 ICR of the maternal and paternal 
alleles, respectively, are associated with allele-specific histone mod-
ifications, particularly at lysine residues (Kacem and Feil, 2009). 
Considering the effect of alcohol on these histone modifications, 
alterations at these residues could convert paternal allele histone 
modifications to those characteristic of the maternal allele -a type 
of epigenotype switching. Dobosy et al. (2008) demonstrated that 
although mice fed on choline-methionine deficient diets demon-
strated significant changes in gene expression levels of Igf2 and 
H19, this occurred without depression in CpG methylation, but 
was associated with changes in lysine residue modifications at 
both Igf2 and H19 promoter regions. Taken together, the evidence 
that a methionine deficient diet can alter histone modifications 
without significant changes in DNA methylation, in conjunction 
with ethanol's ability to induce changes in histone modifications -
which are typically associated with hypomethylated regions (syn-
onymous with the H19 ICR methylation status of the maternal 
allele), and the ability of such histone modifications to negatively 
influence the establishment of DNA methylation (Mutskov et al., 
2002), supports the proposed mechanism for the transmission of 
epimutations without a loss of DNA methylation at imprinted loci 
in sperm, but which abrogates subsequent establishment of DNA 
methylation in sired offspring. These mechanisms do however 
require further investigation. 
A caveat of the present study, is that bisulfite sequencing 
does not distinguish between 5-methylcytosine (5mC) and 5-
hydroxymethylcytosine (5hmC) (Nestor et al., 2010). 5hmC 
occurs naturally via the hydroxylation of 5mC by the Tet dioxy-
genases and has been implicated in active DNA demethylation 
(Wossidlo et al., 2011). Its strong association with Purkinje cells, 
embryonic stem cells, and the paternal pronucleus may suggest an 
intermediate functional role in 5mC reprogramming by influenc-
ing the binding of 5mC-specific proteins (as described in Wossidlo 
et al., 2011). This may be of particular importance to the present 
study, as alcohol metabolism has been proposed to induce oxi-
dation of 5mC to form 5hmC (Jenner et al., 1998; Wright et al., </p>

<p>1999). The apparent lack of methylation alterations in sperm DNA 
of ethanol-exposed males may be the result of the inadequacy of 
bisulfite sequencing to distinguish 5mC from 5hmC, but which 
may have manifested later as demethylated DNA in sired off-
spring, accounting for the observed reduction in somatic DNA 
methylation. 
In conclusion, this study suggests that offspring sired by male 
mice exposed to ethanol for a five week period prior to conception 
inherit aberrant epigenetic signatures at a developmentally signif-
icant locus, the H19 ICR. These changes were correlated with an 
age-related growth retardation phenotype in the immediate post-
weaning period, suggesting that it is a consequence of a postnatal 
feeding behavioral aberration, as opposed to a direct effect on 
growth regulation in utero. It is proposed that reduced levels of 
ICR DNA methylation are as a result of an ethanol-induced insult 
to the sperm DNA prior to conception. As ethanol exposure did 
not appear to reduce DNA methylation at the corresponding locus 
in sperm DNA, it is proposed that the inability of bisulfite sequenc-
ing to discriminate 5mC from 5hmC may have masked ethanol's 
effect on sperm DNA, or that other epigenetic mechanisms sus-
ceptible to the effects of ethanol mediated this effect. Our data 
support an epigenetic mechanism for the transmission of altered 
epigenetic states through the male germline, caused by excessive 
paternal ethanol exposure prior to conception, with important 
implications for the etiology of FAS. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to acknowledge the March of Dimes (Grant # 6-
FY04-70), the National Health Laboratory Service Research Trust 
and the Medical Faculty Research Endowment Fund (University of 
the Witwatersrand) for funding; and to thank all staff at the Uni-
versity of the Witwatersrand's Central Animal Services for their 
support. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL </p>

<p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online 
at http://www.frontiersin.org/epigenomics/10.3389/fgene.2012. 
00010/abstract </p>



<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Epigenomics </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 8 </p>

<p>Knezovich and Ramsay </p>

<p>Perception alcohol effects on ICRs </p>



<p>www.frontiersin.org </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 9 </p>

<p>Knezovich and Ramsay </p>

<p>Perception alcohol effects on ICRs </p>

<p>methylation-sensitive 
enhancer 
blocker. Mol. Cell. Biol. 25, 
11184-11190. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest Statement: The 
authors declare that the research was 
conducted in the absence of any 
commercial or financial relationships </p>

<p>that could be construed as a potential 
conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Received: 02 November 2011; accepted: 
18 January 2012; published online: 22 
February 2012. 
Citation: Knezovich JG and Ramsay 
M (2012) The effect of preconception </p>

<p>paternal alcohol exposure on epige-
netic remodeling of the H19 and 
Rasgrf1 imprinting control regions in 
mouse offspring. Front. Gene. 3:10. doi: 
10.3389/fgene.2012.00010 
This article was submitted to Frontiers in 
Epigenomics, a specialty of Frontiers in 
Genetics. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2012 Knezovich and Ram-
say. This is an open-access article dis-
tributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non Commercial 
License, which permits non-commercial 
use, distribution, and reproduction in 
other forums, provided the original 
authors and source are credited. </p>

<p>Frontiers in Genetics | Epigenomics </p>

<p>February 2012 | Volume 3 | Article 10 | 10 </p>

</text></tei>