<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3105518" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cyclic nucleotide-gated (CNG) channels bind cGMP or cAMP in a cytoplasmic ligand-binding domain (BD), and 
this binding typically increases channel open probability (P o ) without inducing desensitization. However, the cat-
fish CNGA2 (fCNGA2) subtype exhibits bimodal agonism, whereby steady-state P o increases with initial cGMP-
binding events ("pro" action) up to a maximum of 0.4, but decreases with subsequent cGMP-binding events ("con" 
action) occurring at concentrations &gt;3 mM. We sought to clarify if low pro-action efficacy was either necessary or 
sufficient for con action to operate. To find BD residues responsible for con action or low pro-action efficacy or 
both, we constructed chimeric CNG channels: subregions of the fCNGA2 BD were substituted with corresponding 
sequence from the rat CNGA4 BD, which does not support con action. Constructs were expressed in frog oocytes 
and tested by patch clamp of cell-free membranes. For nearly all BD elements, we found at least one construct 
where replacing that element preserved robust con action, with a ratio of steady-state conductances, g (10 mM cGMP) / 
g (3 mM cGMP) &lt; 0.75. When all of the BD sequence C terminal of strand 6 was replaced, g (10 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) was 
increased to 0.95 ± 0.05 (n = 7). However, this apparent attenuation of con action could be explained by an in-
crease in the efficacy of pro action for all agonists, controlled by a conserved "phosphate-binding cassette" motif 
that contacts ligand; this produces high P o values that are less sensitive to shifts in gating equilibrium. In contrast, 
substituting a single valine in the N-terminal helix A abolished con action (g (30 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) increased to 
1.26 ± 0.24; n = 7) without large increases in pro-action efficacy. Our work dissociates the two functional features of 
low pro-action efficacy and con action, and moreover identifies a separate structural determinant for each. </p>



<p>Contributions to bimodal agonism in CNG channels </p>

<p>acts will depend on the receptor structure, and previ-
ously bound ligands must be included in describing that 
receptor structure. In the thermodynamic cycle for pro 
action at the left side of the Fig. 1 reaction scheme, 
cGMP binding preferentially stabilizes the open chan-
nel only when the number of bound ligands is less than 
some critical number, m. When some partially liganded 
channel state is attained (m ligands in Fig. 1), the cou-
pling relationship between binding and gating becomes 
reversed. Subsequent binding of the same agonist spe-
cies now preferentially destabilizes the open state (con 
action) with counterproductive interactions. 
Con action in CNG channels represents a special ex-
ample of negative agonism that manifests "alongside" pos-
itive agonism, caused by the same cGMP ligand species 
and relying on the same BD region. Thus, it becomes 
pressing to clarify the causal relationship between them. 
For instance, the previous BD substitution studies found 
that the rCNGA4 BD not only imparted normal cGMP 
agonism but also imparted a much higher efficacy of pro 
action by both cGMP and cAMP compared with the 
fCNGA2 BD. Might the particular structural deficien-
cies responsible for poor pro-action efficacy in fCNGA2 
be necessary for operation of the con-action mechanism? 
If true, this would imply that any future compounds se-
lected for effective con action in fCNGA2 will fail to in-
duce con action in any of the numerous CNG channels 
whose pro-action mechanism is highly efficient. Con-
versely, might the poor pro-action efficacy be in itself 
sufficient to bring a con-action mechanism into opera-
tion? If true, this would imply that cGMP-negative ago-
nism should already operate in every example of a low 
efficacy CNG channel, perhaps going undiscovered be-
cause higher cGMP concentrations were not previously 
tested. Here, we identify counterexamples against both 
the necessity hypothesis and the sufficiency hypothesis. 
That is, we show that con-action and low pro-action effi-
cacy, the two distinctive functional features of the fCNGA2 
BD, derive from independently operating structural de-
terminants in the BD and are thus not causally related. 
Moreover, we isolate a single residue in the fCNGA2 BD 
with a critical role in con action, opening the door for 
future elucidation of a specific mechanism for negative 
agonism in CNG channels. </p>

<p>M A T E R I A L S A N D M E T H O D S </p>

<p>Recombinant DNA 
Previous reports (Tibbs et al., 1997; Young et al., 2001) have de-
scribed the design of the "X-chimera" series of BD substitution 
constructs, with invariant non-BD sequence derived from bovine 
CNGA1 (bCNGA1; Kaupp et al., 1989) and fCNGA2 (Goulding 
et al., 1992). New X-chimera constructs were generated with pre-
viously reported PCR/restriction/ligation techniques (Young and 
Krougliak, 2004), incorporating BD sequences from fCNGA2, 
residues L455-A583, and from rCNGA4 (Bradley et al., 1994; 
Liman and Buck, 1994), residues L356-A484. Some constructs </p>

<p>a falling phase for higher concentrations. This contrasts 
with the normal (monotonically rising) dose-response 
curve of the positive agonist cAMP. Single-channel re-
cordings have shown (Young et al., 2001) that the fall-
ing phase of the cGMP dose-response reflects a decrease 
in steady-state open probability (P o ) induced by a new 
cGMP molecule binding to a partially liganded channel 
(see reaction scheme in Fig. 1). That is, it does not involve 
a reduction of open-channel unitary conductance as 
typically found with agonist pore block (Ogden and 
Colquhoun, 1985; Karashima et al., 2007), or a sponta-
neous gate-closing conformational change as found 
with traditional desensitization in ligand-gated channels 
(Cachelin and Colquhoun, 1989; Robert and Howe, 2003) 
or inactivation in voltage-gated channels (Hoshi et al., 
1991). We have termed this unusual phenomenon bi-
modal agonism because cGMP exhibits two opposite 
modes of action: "pro action" that enhances receptor ac-
tivity by a positive agonism mechanism, and "con action" 
that suppresses activity by a negative agonism mechanism. 
Our distinct terminology "con action" is used to denote 
negative agonism in this special context where more than 
one agonism mode is possible. 
Besides being specific for cGMP and not cAMP, several 
additional features of con action argue against mecha-
nisms that involve nonspecific interference with channel 
function. A neutral agonism mechanism, where cGMP is 
displaced from its pro-action site by a competitor mole-
cule that binds open and closed channels equally, is 
ruled out because the agonist responsible for con action 
is cGMP itself. BD substitution studies showed that al-
though the fCNGA2 BD imparted bimodal cGMP agonism 
and normal cAMP agonism, the BD from the rat CNGA4 
type (rCNGA4; Bradley et al., 1994; Liman and Buck, 
1994) imparted solely normal cGMP and cAMP agonism. 
Thus, particular sequences within the fCNGA2 BD are 
required for con action (Young et al., 2001; Chan and 
Young, 2009), as would be expected for a modification 
of gating under BD-mediated control. Negative agonism 
acting through the BD is previously unknown in CNG 
channels because the known "antagonists" such as phos-
phorothioate analogues (Kramer and Tibbs, 1996) are 
merely weakly effective ("partial") positive agonists. It may 
be noted that the cGMP affinity of the binding site re-
sponsible for con action seems to be weak (millimolar) 
in constructs containing the fCNGA2 BD, but it is in fact 
comparable to the cAMP affinity of canonical pro-action 
sites in the same channels. Moreover, the operation of 
con action in heteromeric CNG channels (with fCNGA2 
sequence in only two of four BDs) is conditional on sub-
unit arrangement, consistent with the notion that the 
mechanism requires a specific geometry in the ligand-
channel complex (Chan and Young, 2009). 
Bimodal agonism illustrates how it is misleading to say 
a ligand "is" a negative agonist; strictly, we can say only 
that the ligand "acts as" a negative agonist. How a ligand </p>

<p>Wong et al. </p>



<p>Comparative models 
Models were built for the X-fA2 C-linker and BD (211 residues, 
consisting of bCNGA1 M401-G484 followed by fCNGA2 L455-
V581) and for several constructs and mutant forms studied. Each 
target sequence was aligned to a single template of D443-L643 
from mouse HCN2 (Protein Data Bank accession no. 1Q5O; 
Zagotta et al., 2003), which was the closest relative with struc-
tural data available; there was 27% identity with three gaps intro-
duced in the template sequence. Models were built using the 
"Fit Raw Sequence" function in <rs id="software-6" type="software">DeepView</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">4.0.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Guex and Peitsch</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-date">1997</rs>) and the Project mode of SWISS-MODEL (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">version 8.05</rs>) (Arnold et al., 2006). Root-mean-squared distance calcula-
tions and detection of atoms within 5 Å of particular side chains 
were performed using <rs type="software">DeepView</rs>; hydrogen bonds were detected 
using <rs id="software-9" type="software">VADAR</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">version 1.6</rs>) (Willard et al., <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-date">2003</rs>). For model images 
(Fig. 4 C), <rs id="software-10" type="software">PYMOL</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">DeLano Scientific</rs>) was used for the ribbon 
diagram and GRASP2 for the electrostatic potential (Petrey and 
Honig, 2003). </p>

<p>R E S U L T S </p>

<p>Rationale of BD substitution </p>

<p>The example macroscopic current trace in Fig. 1 illustrates 
pro and con action in homomeric bimodal CNG chan-
nels formed by a recombinant chimeric construct, X-fA2, 
whose composition and functional properties have been 
described in detail (Young et al., 2001). X-fA2 contains 
the fCNGA2 BD sequence and reconstitutes the gating 
and permeation characteristics of intact fCNGA2, just 
with improved levels of homologous expression resulting 
from selected non-BD sequence substitutions. Notably, 
the dose-response curves of X-fA2 for both cGMP and 
cAMP match those of intact fCNGA2, including matching 
maximal P o values (Young et al., 2001). A subsequent 
series of BD substitution constructs (X-chimeras) were 
based on substituting BD sequence in the original X-fA2 
parent (Young et al., 2001; Young and Krougliak, 2004; 
Chan and Young, 2009). This enables comparisons of the 
activation properties of various BD sequences, set within 
one context of invariant non-BD sequence (Fig. 2 A). 
Each X-chimera subunit can be expressed alone in 
Xenopus oocytes to form functional homomeric CNG 
channels, which are then assayed as in Fig. 1 (inside-out 
excised patch clamp with agonist solutions perfused on 
the cytoplasmic side). 
Perfusion of 3 mM cGMP on X-fA2 homomers elicits 
a nondesensitizing channel current (pro action; Fig. 1 
trace), and throughout this study we use the steady-state 
conductance elicited by 3 mM cGMP, g (3 mM cGMP) , as a 
normalization reference for steady-state conductances 
in other agonist conditions in the same patch (see Fig. 1 
caption and Young et al., 2001 for interpretation of 
"spiked" current traces showing con action with cGMP 
dosages &gt;3 mM). The BD incorporated in each X-chimera 
tested can then be classed as either bimodal or normal, 
according to whether the cGMP dose-response curve of 
the X-chimera exhibits the peculiar negative slope asso-
ciated with con action. </p>

<p>were previously reported with different names in Young et al. 
(2001): X-fA2 is synonymous with X-, X-rA4 with X-, Construct 
1 with X- R / C , and Construct 6 with X- R / C ; in addition, Con-
struct 2 is synonymous with X-bimP reported previously (Chan 
and Young, 2009). There are six constructs new in this study 
(not including point mutants), with the following concatena-
tions: Construct 3, fCNGA2 (L455-C511) + rCNGA4 (F413-A484); 
Construct 4, fCNGA2 (L455-K488) + rCNGA4 (E390-A484); Con-
struct 5, fCNGA2 (L455-K488) + rCNGA4 (E390-S426) + fCNGA2 
(G526-A554) + rCNGA4 (E456-A484); Construct 7, rCNGA4 
(L356-R389) + fCNGA2 (E489-A583); Construct 8, rCNGA4 
(L356-G372) + fCNGA2 (D472-A583); Construct 9, fCNGA2 
(L455-G471) + rCNGA4 (E373-R389) + fCNGA2 (E489-A583). 
Sequence regions subjected to PCR were confirmed by dide-
oxy sequencing. </p>

<p>Electrophysiology 
Oocytes were harvested from mature female Xenopus laevis frogs 
(procedures approved by the Canadian Council on Animal Care), 
injected with in vitro-transcribed RNA, and assayed in the excised 
inside-out patch clamp configuration, with all procedures done as 
previously reported (Young et al., 2001; Young and Krougliak, 
2004; Chan and Young, 2009). Recording conditions are briefly 
summarized: Pipette and bath solutions both contained (in mM): 
67 KCl, 30 NaCl, 10 HEPES, 10 EGTA, and 1 EDTA, pH 7.2 with 
KOH. Na salts of cAMP or cGMP were included by iso-osmolar re-
placement of NaCl. For Ni 
2+ potentiation experiments (Young et al., 
2001), the bath solution was modified to include 10 µM NiCl 2 
(Sigma-Aldrich), omit EGTA and EDTA, and increase KCl to 89 mM. 
Current measurements were acquired at room temperature 
(19-23°C) with either an Axopatch 200B or GeneClamp500 am-
plifier, filtered at 10 kHz using the amplifier's low-pass Bessel fil-
ter, and recorded at 0.1-1 kHz by a Digidata 1322 and <rs id="software-5" type="software">pClamp</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">9.0</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Axon Instruments</rs>). 
Patches were held at 40 mV, and steady-state currents in the 
presence of cyclic nucleotide were corrected by subtraction of 
leak currents in the absence of cyclic nucleotide. Spontaneous ac-
tivity changes (run-up and run-down) of CNG channels in excised 
patches were typically complete after 10-20 min, somewhat lon-
ger than previously noted for bCNGA1 (Molokanova et al., 1997). 
With the exception of specific experiments examining this run-up 
(Fig. 3 B), all reported measurements were collected after run-up 
was completed, as shown by a difference of &lt;10% among multiple 
conductance measurements in 3 mM cGMP. Steady-state conduc-
tance in 3 mM cGMP after completion of run-up was used in each 
patch to normalize conductances in other conditions, including 
those before the completion of run-up (Fig. 3 B). Unless otherwise 
noted, means are reported ± SD with n the sample size, and con-
ductance ratios were compared with unity using t test. 
For selected constructs, the P o for the 3-mM cGMP normaliza-
tion condition (after run-up) was estimated as the conductance ratio 
g (3 mM cGMP) /g (30 mM cAMP+Ni) , where the denominator is the conduc-
tance in the presence of 30 mM cAMP and 10 µM Ni 
2+ ion 
(Varnum et al., 1995; Young et al., 2001). Ratio values recorded for 
constructs in this study were as follows: Construct 2, 0.180 ± 0.050 
(n = 3); Construct 3, 0.73 ± 0.15 (n = 3); Construct 8, 0.337 ± 0.092 
(n = 4); X-fA2 V457E, 0.359 ± 0.079 (n = 4). This method as-
sumes P o ≈ 1 in the nickel-potentiated fully liganded channel and 
that unitary open-channel conductance is unaffected by either 
cyclic nucleotide or Ni 
2+ . These two assumptions were vali-
dated for previously studied X-chimeras (Young et al., 2001); all 
X-chimera sequences are identical in the transmembrane domain 
(including the pore region determining unitary conductance; 
Goulding et al., 1993) and the C-linker (including the Ni </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-binding 
histidine residue; Gordon and Zagotta, 1995). Dose-response 
relations in Figs. 4 and 5 were fitted with the Hill equation, P o = 
P max /(1 + K 1/2 /[cNMP]) </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>. </p>



<p>Contributions to bimodal agonism in CNG channels </p>

<p>Considering the two bimodal Constructs 2 and 5 to-
gether enables us to exclude a critical role for a large 
number of residues that are unique to the fCNGA2 
BD. Specifically, each unconserved residue C-terminal 
of strand 3 has been replaced in either Construct 2 
or Construct 5, or both, without abolishing con ac-
tion. On the contrary, con action is robustly main-
tained with g (10 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) &lt; 0.75. Therefore, 
if there exists a critical residue, it must be located at 
the amino end of the BD, within the region spanning 
helix A through strand 3 (to be discussed further in 
a later section). </p>

<p>Within the 130-residue BD sequence of CNG chan-
nels, there are 36 residues that are not conserved between 
fCNGA2 and rCNGA4 (Fig. 2, A, alignment, and B, 
black ticks). In this study, we substituted subsets of these 
36 nonconserved residues with their rCNGA4 counter-
parts and tested the effects on cGMP gating. The BD is ho-
mologous to those of other cyclic nucleotide-dependent 
proteins (Weber et al., 1982; Kaupp et al., 1989), with an 
N-terminal helix (A), a -roll fold (strands 1-8), and 
two C-terminal helices (B-C); an additional "PB" helix 
and loop interrupt the  roll. The PB elements form a 
conserved "cassette" that participates in ligand binding 
in all known cyclic nucleotide-dependent proteins using 
the BD (Diller et al., 2001). The 36 nonconserved resi-
dues are spread throughout the BD. Any of the fCNGA2 
BD residues that we substituted might be "critical" for 
con action, meaning that its substitution would abolish 
con action; there might be several such critical residues. 
Or, substitution of one or more fCNGA2 residues might 
not abolish con action but might instead modify quanti-
tative features of the falling phase in the cGMP dose-
response curve. Such residues would be properly described 
as "contributing" to con action but not critical for it. 
In addition, substitutions might change pro-action effi-
cacy; this would modify the quantitative features of the 
rising phase of the dose-response curve. The key ques-
tions are whether it might be possible to increase pro-
action efficacy without abolishing con action (showing 
that low pro action is not necessary for con action), and 
whether it might be possible to abolish con action with-
out increasing pro-action efficacy (showing that low pro 
action is not sufficient for con action). </p>

<p>Extensive BD sequence substitutions preserve con action </p>

<p>We had previously constructed Constructs 1 and 2 with 
portions of the C-terminal region of the fCNGA2 BD 
replaced with rCNGA4 residues (Fig. 2 B); both of these 
constructs were bimodal (Young et al., 2001; Chan 
and Young, 2009). We extended the X-chimera series 
with Constructs 3 and 4, replacing larger amounts of 
C-terminal sequence from the fCNGA2 BD, and these 
progressive replacements increased the value of the ratio 
g (10 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) . Indeed, the g (10 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM </p>

<p>cGMP) value for Construct 3 is very close to unity (although 
still significantly less, P &lt; 0.02), and the value for Con-
struct 4 is not significantly different than unity (P &gt; 0.3). 
These results might suggest a critical role for some of 
the 10 fCNGA2-specific residues from 5 through the PB 
cassette. However, surprisingly, we were able to con-
struct a counterexample to this hypothesis: starting 
from a Chimera 4 background, we added back a set of 
seven fCNGA2-specific residues in another region, 7 
through the B helix, and in doing so we "rescued" con 
action. The resulting Construct 5 has a ratio of g (10 mM </p>

<p>cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) = 0.72 ± 0.12 (n = 7), significantly below 
unity (P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Simple allosteric reaction scheme for bimodal ago-
nism. Reaction scheme (Chan and Young, 2009) is illustrated by a 
cell-free inside-out macroscopic patch recording of bimodal CNG 
channels with cGMP washed into and out from the bath (solid 
and dashed black bars, respectively). Applying cGMP elicits in-
ward channel current with no desensitization up to 3 mM cGMP, 
but with 10 mM cGMP, the steady-state macroscopic conductance 
(white arrow) is smaller than for 3 mM. During wash-in and wash-
out of the 10-mM cGMP solution, there are brief intervals with 
bath cGMP concentration near 3 mM giving rise to "spikes" of 
maximal conductance. Details of reaction scheme notation: 
Closed-(C) and open-(O) channel states are equilibrating rap-
idly compared with agonist wash-in and wash-out. Sizes of black 
reaction arrows indicate the favored direction of equilibrium. 
P o increases with cGMP binding of up to m molecules of cGMP 
(pro action). Binding of the (m+1) 
th cGMP molecule decreases 
the steady-state P o (con action) to below the value obtained with 
m ligands. Experimental details of current trace: The previously 
characterized channel, X-fA2, incorporates the BD from fCNGA2 
channel in a chimera with sequence from other CNG channel 
types (see Young et al., 2001, and Fig. 2). X-fA2 was expressed 
as homomers in Xenopus oocytes; patches were held at 40 mV. 
White arrows mark times where steady-state conductance, g, was 
measured with cGMP concentrations fixed at their nominal con-
centrations; for this example, g (10 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) = 0.63. </p>

<p>Wong et al. </p>



<p>fCNGA2-specific residues in the PB cassette were not 
critical for con action, we anticipated that they might be 
important determinants of the low pro-action efficacy 
of X-fA2. 
We converted macroscopic conductances into P o values 
by determining the maximum conductance in each patch 
(P o = 1) elicited by 30 mM cAMP and 10 µM Ni 
2+ (see 
Materials and methods). The cGMP dose-response curves 
(Fig. 3 A, down triangles vs. gray solid curve) show that 
both Constructs 2 and 3 are bimodal with a con phase at 
concentrations &gt;3 mM. However, the maximal P o at 3 mM 
cGMP for Construct 3 (0.73 ± 0.15; n = 3) is far higher </p>

<p>Substitution of the fCNGA2 PB cassette increases 
pro-action efficacy </p>

<p>We selected Construct 3 for a more detailed compari-
son with the previously characterized Construct 2, because 
these two constructs differ only in five residues within 
the key PB cassette region. In multiple cyclic nucleotide-
activated proteins, movement of the PB cassette in re-
sponse to ligand binding is believed to be essential for 
propagating conformational change to other parts of the 
BD (Canaves and Taylor, 2002; Rehmann et al., 2003; 
Clayton et al., 2004; Kim et al., 2005; Mazhab-Jafari 
et al., 2007). Thus, although we knew that the five </p>

<p>Figure 2. Extensive BD sequence substitutions preserve con action. (A) Topology of the CNG channel subunit, highlighting the BD 
region substituted in the X-chimera series of constructs. Alignment compares the substituted BD sequences (bounded by vertical dotted 
lines) originating from rCNGA4 (in X-rA4) and fCNGA2 (in X-fA2). Invariant non-BD sequences (Young et al., 2001) include bCNGA1 
sequence in the C-linker and the extreme C-terminal region, respectively, before and after the BD. Dots in the sequence alignment 
indicate fCNGA2 residues conserved with rCNGA4; secondary structure elements are marked ( for helices,  for strands) as predicted 
by comparative modeling (Fig. 4). (B) X-chimera testing substitutions in the C-terminal portion of the BD. Bar represents BD sequence; 
below the bars, secondary structure elements are marked (letters for helices, numbers for strands, and PB for the PB cassette). Gray back-
ground color in bar represents amino acids conserved between fCNGA2 and rCNGA4; black ticks mark unconserved amino acids found 
in fCNGA2 but not in rCNGA4. Mean g (10 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) values (±SD, number of patches in parentheses) include those previously 
reported for Construct 1 (Young et al., 2001) and for Construct 2 and X-rA4 (Chan and Young, 2009). (C) Examples of current traces 
for selected constructs during 10-mM cGMP pulses, with g (10 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) as marked (based on applications of 3 mM cGMP; not 
depicted). Horizontal bar, 10 s; vertical bar, 1 nA. </p>



<p>Contributions to bimodal agonism in CNG channels </p>

<p>The P o parameter traditionally plotted in dose-
response curves does not bear a simple relation with the 
underlying energetics of gate opening; the more perti-
nent parameter is the equilibrium constant for the pore-
gating reaction ([open]/[closed], in a simple model of </p>

<p>than for Construct 2 (0.18 ± 0.05; n = 3), so that the entire 
cGMP dose-response curves for the two channels are 
dramatically separated. Thus, introducing the rCNGA4 
PB cassette sequence into the background of Construct 2 
resulted in higher P o values for cGMP agonism. How-
ever, with a bimodal dose-response curve, cGMP pro 
action cannot be reliably quantified separately from con 
action; even at low cGMP concentrations, some binding 
events may be operating with con action at the same 
time as other binding events are operating with pro ac-
tion. Thus, we entertained an alternative explanation 
where the PB cassette substitution in Construct 3 merely 
attenuated cGMP con action without affecting pro action. 
To clarify the effect of the PB cassette on pro action, 
we evaluated efficacy for cAMP, which appears never to 
participate in the con-action mechanism. The Construct 
2 background channel had mean P o values ranging from 
0.36 at 3 mM cAMP to 0.62 at 30 mM cAMP; at compa-
rable concentrations, the P o for Construct 3 was higher, 
with means ranging from 0.82 at 3 mM cAMP to 0.94 at 
30 mM cAMP (Fig. 3 A, up-triangles vs. gray dashed curve). 
The trajectory of PB cassette movement in the normal 
(pro) action of cyclic nucleotide-activated proteins is 
proposed to be essentially the same whether the bind-
ing agonist is cGMP or cAMP (Canaves and Taylor, 2002; 
Flynn et al., 2007). Thus, our results are consistent with 
PB cassette replacement in Construct 3 causing a gen-
eral increase in efficacy for both cAMP and cGMP. The 
highly efficacious function of the rCNGA4 BD that was 
previously reported (Young et al., 2001) is also consis-
tent with associating high efficacy with the rCNGA4 PB 
cassette sequence. </p>

<p>Necessity hypothesis: construct 3 exhibits efficient con 
action that is masked by its high pro-action efficacy </p>

<p>In previous examples of bimodal CNG channels such 
as fCNGA2, X-fA2, and Constructs 1 and 2, the P o elic-
ited by cGMP was relatively low, limited to 0.4 at most. 
This might suggest that some defect in the structural 
apparatus for pro action might be necessary (a pre-
requisite) for con action. This necessity hypothesis 
could be disproven if a counterexample were found, 
namely a channel with both efficient con action and 
efficient pro action. In this light, Construct 3 provides 
the first example of a bimodal CNG channel whose 
cGMP pro action is efficient enough to produce P o &gt; 0.7. 
We note that Construct 3 also had a higher value for 
g (10 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) compared with the other 
bimodal channels, which might suggest that its con-
action mechanism was not as efficient. However, as 
we explain below, it is not true that an increase in g (10 mM </p>

<p>cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) always indicates attenuation of con 
action in mechanistic or energetic terms, and the dose-
response curves of Construct 3 match what would be 
predicted if the con action was unaffected by PB cas-
sette replacement. </p>

<p>Figure 3. PB cassette substitution masks con action by raising gat-
ing efficacy: refutation of necessity hypothesis. (A) Dose-response 
relations of Construct 3 activated with cGMP (down-triangles) or 
cAMP (up-triangles). Points show means and error bars show SD 
(n ≥ 3 for each point); points are joined by straight lines without 
fitting. To plot P o values, conductances were normalized to the 
steady-state conductance measured at 3 mM cGMP (solid down-
triangle) in the same patch. Then, P o at 3 mM cGMP was fixed as 
0.73 based on Ni 
2+ potentiation (see Materials and methods). For 
comparison, gray curves show dose-response relations for Con-
struct 2 activated by cGMP (solid) or cAMP (dashed); these were 
previously reported on a relative scale without conversion to P o 
values (Chan and Young, 2009), and new Ni 
2+ potentiation exper-
iments in this study fix the P o at 3 mM cGMP as 0.18. All measures 
for both constructs in this plot were collected after completion 
of spontaneous run-up. (B) Example macroscopic current trace 
from one patch of Construct 3 before and after completion of 
run-up, tracking progressive increase in pro-action efficacy and 
masking of con action. P o scale at right is based on fixing P o = 0.73 
for 3 mM cGMP after run-up. Arrows and asterisks, respectively, 
mark steady-state and spike currents as in Fig. 1. For this example, 
P steady /P spike = 0.80 before run-up and 0.95 after run-up. </p>

<p>Wong et al. </p>



<p>P &lt; 0.008). This is consistent with the masking of con 
action arising progressively as P o increases during run-up. 
In summary, the difference in dose-responses of Con-
structs 2 and 3 can be explained as a potentiation of pro 
action that is general (i.e., applying to both cAMP and 
cGMP); the con phase in the cGMP dose-response of 
Construct 3 appears flattened not because of attenua-
tion of cGMP con-action energetics but because of high 
P o masking. Construct 3 possesses both efficient con ac-
tion and efficient pro action, which suggests strongly that 
the poor pro-action efficacy exemplified by X-fA2 is not 
a prerequisite mechanistic condition for the operation 
of con action. That is, low pro-action efficacy is not nec-
essary for con action. Construct 3 does not exclude the 
possibility that a disabled pro-action mechanism could 
be sufficient in itself to induce operation of con action. </p>

<p>Sufficiency hypothesis: abolishing con action without high 
pro-action efficacy </p>

<p>Masking with high pro-action efficacy represents one way 
that the manifestation of con action can be suppressed, 
but it does not represent a way to disable the operation 
of the con-action mechanism. We found above (Fig. 2) 
that many fCNGA2 residues from 5 through C were 
not critical for con action. Therefore, we performed an-
other mutagenesis search with progressive replacements 
in the N-terminal region of the BD. We knew from pre-
vious work (Young et al., 2001) that con action could in-
deed be abolished by replacing very extensive N-terminal 
sequence (Fig. 4 A, Construct 6). The new Constructs 7 
and 8 contain BD sequences &gt;94% identical to the 
fCNGA2 BD, yet like Construct 6, they both lack con ac-
tion (Fig. 4 A); wash-in and wash-out current spikes were 
never observed either before or after run-up, and steady-
state activity increased with cGMP concentration up to 
30 mM (Fig. 4 B, solid down-triangles). Thus, substitu-
tion of as few as three residues (in helix A and strand 
1 of Construct 8) abolished observable evidence for 
con action in the range of 3-30 mM cGMP (we phrase 
this statement conservatively because we could not test 
cGMP concentrations above 30 mM because of viscosity 
and solubility problems, and it is in any case impossible 
to prove a negative assertion for all possible conditions). 
Notably, bimodal agonism was observed in another Con-
struct 9 where strands 2 and strands 3 were replaced, 
showing that those sequence elements are not critical 
for con action. 
Although the cGMP response relation of Construct 8 
is not suppressed by a con phase, there is no evidence for 
high P o that could mask con action as in Construct 3. 
The P o for Construct 8 at 3 mM cGMP was only 0.37 ± 
0.09 (n = 4) and did not exceed 0.5, even at 30 mM 
cGMP. For both cGMP and cAMP, the Construct 8 dose-
response curves are very similar to those of X-fA2 (Fig. 4 B, 
black points vs. gray curves), with the exception of cGMP 
&gt;3 mM. This shows that the A-1 replacement did not </p>

<p>a single open and closed state). As the numerical value 
of P o increases toward unity, the P o parameter becomes 
less sensitive to changes in the gating equilibrium constant 
(Varnum and Zagotta, 1996). Thus, if a structural modi-
fication (for example, PB cassette replacement) were 
to increase pro-action efficacy without affecting other 
gating features, this would as a consequence also flatten 
the P o versus concentration curve, so that significant 
concentration-dependent changes in gating energetics 
caused by either pro or con action would be "masked." 
The gating equilibrium constant cannot be evaluated 
with precision at a subsaturating agonist concentration 
because the individual channel molecules in the popu-
lation will have different binding site occupancies and 
hence different gating equilibrium constants with differ-
ent corresponding open probabilities. As a surrogate pa-
rameter, we can calculate Z = P o /(1P o ) from the 
average P o at a given subsaturating cGMP concentra-
tion; Z represents an approximate central value, around 
which the individual equilibrium constants in the chan-
nel population will be clustered. This analysis shows that as 
cGMP concentration increases from 3 to 10 mM, Z de-
creases by a similar factor for both Constructs 2 and 3. 
For Construct 2, Z changes by a factor of 0.7, decreasing 
from 0.23 at 3 mM cGMP (P o = 0.18) to 0.15 at 10 mM 
cGMP (P o = 0.13); for Construct 3, Z changes by a factor 
of 0.8, decreasing from 2.6 at 3 mM cGMP (P o = 0.73) to 
2.2 at 10 mM cGMP (P o = 0.69). Although we emphasize 
that Z is not numerically equivalent to a microscopic equi-
librium constant, the similarity of Z shifts in Constructs 
2 and 3 is consistent with a scenario where the energet-
ics of con action are similar in these two channels. 
Further evidence for the "masking" of con action in 
Construct 3 is observable during spontaneous "run-up" 
of channel activity in the minutes immediately after 
patch excision. Run-up in X-chimeras, as in many CNG 
channels (Molokanova et al., 1997), typically causes a po-
tentiation of cyclic nucleotide activation, including an 
increase in efficacy (unpublished data). For patches of 
Construct 3, we noticed that wash-in and wash-out current 
spikes indicative of bimodal agonism were more promi-
nent in pulses of 10 mM cGMP given early after patch 
excision compared with later pulses (Fig. 3 B). To quan-
tify con action in individual pulses of 10-mM cGMP per-
fusion, we compared the P o value at steady state (P steady ) 
and at the peak of the wash-in spike (P spike ), which cor-
responds to an interval where cGMP is momentarily near 
3 mM (Fig. 1); this avoids reference to the steady-state 
g (3 mM cGMP) standard, which would not be stable during 
run-up. In four patches of Construct 3, pulses of 10 mM 
cGMP were applied less than 5 min after excision (mean 
P steady = 0.53 ± 0.02) as well as after completion of run-up 
(P steady = 0.69 ± 0.04). Con action in these four patches was 
more robustly exhibited before run-up (P steady /P spike = 
0.84 ± 0.04) compared with after (P steady /P spike = 0.97 ± 
0.03; significantly different than before by paired t test, </p>



<p>Contributions to bimodal agonism in CNG channels </p>

<p>location of the key A-1 region in the fCNGA2 BD 
using comparative modeling (see Materials and methods) 
based on the crystal structure of a C-terminal fragment 
from the related HCN2 channel (Zagotta et al., 2003). 
Models were built for the C-linker and BD of X-fA2 and 
Constructs 7 and 8 (Fig. 4 C); the independently built 
models were closely superimposable with each other 
with a small root-mean-squared distance (0.2 Å) for all 
atoms excluding unconserved residues. In other words, 
introducing up to seven substitutions to the X-fA2 
model did not result in any steric clashes forcing a large 
shift of nonsubstituted atoms during the energy mini-
mization. The model shows that cGMP bound to the ca-
nonical ligand-binding pocket, which is highly conserved 
in crystal structures of other cyclic nucleotide-activated 
proteins (Weber and Steitz, 1987; Su et al., 1995; Clayton 
et al., 2004; Rehmann et al., 2008), does not lie close 
to the A-1 region. However, it remains possible that </p>

<p>observably potentiate pro action for either agonist, a quite 
different effect than that of PB cassette replacement. 
The lack of con action and the low pro-action efficacy 
in Construct 8 refutes the hypothesis that a low pro-
action efficacy is sufficient to produce a con-action mech-
anism. Together with Construct 3, our findings show that 
low pro-action efficacy is neither necessary nor sufficient 
to cause the con action found in X-fA2. This strongly 
suggests that there is no causal relation between con 
action and low pro-action efficacy as they are found in 
X-fA2 and intact fCNGA2. </p>

<p>V457 in helix A rather than R464 in strand 1 is critical 
for bimodal agonism </p>

<p>Might the critical A-1 region contribute to a distinctive 
cGMP-binding site responsible for con action? There is 
no available high resolution structural information on 
the BD of CNG channels, so we assessed the approximate </p>

<p>Figure 4. Substitution of N-terminal region of BD abolishes con action: refutation of sufficiency hypothesis. (A) Bars show substitutions 
in the N-terminal portion of the BD, with mean values of g (30 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) , including previously reported data for Construct 6 
(Young et al., 2001). (B) Dose-response relation of Construct 8 activated with cGMP and cAMP (down-triangles and up-triangles, respec-
tively; n ≥ 4 for all points). Conductances were converted to P o using the methods of Fig. 3, fixing P o = 0.337 at 3 mM cGMP. Black curves 
are Hill equation fits (see Materials and methods). Fitted parameters (±SE) are: cGMP, K 1/2 = 368 ± 26 µM, h = 0.85 ± 0.04, and P max = 
0.399 ± 0.006; cAMP, K 1/2 = 520 ± 220 µM, h = 0.81 ± 0.23, and P max = 0.58 ± 0.05. For comparison, gray curves show X-fA2 dose-response 
data (Young et al., 2001) for cGMP (solid) and cAMP (dashed). (C) Model of the C-linker and BD from X-fA2 (see Results). (Left) Ribbon 
diagram highlights helix A and strand 1 (orange) with the three unconserved residues (magenta) whose substitution in Construct 8 
abolished con action; numbering follows fCNGA2 sequence (Fig. 1 alignment) with the substituted amino acid from rCNGA4 in paren-
theses. Hash marks (#) indicate three loops (B-C, PB cassette, and 4-5), which were built without template residues. The canonical-
binding site (dashed ellipse) uses key ligand contacts with R529 and T530 (green), which are universally conserved in CNG channels. 
(Right) Electrostatic potential mapped to molecular surface. </p>

<p>Wong et al. </p>



<p>con action up to 30 mM cGMP. X-fA2 V457E does have 
slightly higher P o for a given cGMP concentration than 
does X-fA2, but the increase in efficacy is slight and not 
large enough to raise P o above 0.5. The low P o , along with 
the significant increase in P o going from 3 to 30 mM cGMP, 
rule out high P o masking as a cause for the failure to 
observe con action in X-fA2 V457E. This suggests that 
V457 on helix A is critical for operation of the con-
action mechanism in CNG channels. </p>

<p>D I S C U S S I O N </p>

<p>Our most important new findings in this work are as fol-
lows. Although there are many BD residues that are not 
conserved between fCNGA2 and rCNGA4, only one is crit-
ical for con action, namely V457 in helix A of fCNGA2. 
At least some of the structural determinants of pro and 
con action operate independently of each other: pro-
action efficacy can be controlled by substituting the PB 
cassette sequence without affecting con-action energet-
ics, whereas con action can be enabled or disabled by 
substitution of the A-1 sequence without affecting 
pro action. We produce an example (Construct 3) where 
a con-action mechanism operates efficiently, yet its sup-
pressive effects on P o are partially masked as an indirect 
consequence of efficient pro action. </p>

<p>Does helix A contribute to a cGMP-binding site? </p>

<p>All evidence at hand shows that V457 is critical for con 
action, not simply "contributing" to it. We found no con 
action in any channel that we tested with a V457E muta-
tion, namely X-rA4, Constructs 6-8, and the point muta-
tion in X-fA2 background. We emphasize that "critical" 
means "necessary" but does not mean "sufficient"; for 
instance, the presence of valine at position 457 may not 
ensure the operation of con action in every possible </p>

<p>the A-1 region contributes to a noncanonical cGMP-
binding site. We emphasize that although cGMP concen-
trations &gt;3 mM are required for con action in constructs 
like X-fA2 with the fCNGA2 BD, this BD also shows gen-
erally weak binding for cAMP, so that the cAMP dose-
response curve does not saturate at 3 mM. Thus, the cGMP 
affinity of the binding site responsible for con action 
seems to be comparable to the cAMP affinity of canonical 
pro-action sites found in the fCNGA2 BD. 
Electrostatic potential calculations on our X-fA2 model 
(Petrey and Honig, 2003) indicate that helix A and 
strand 1 are in, respectively, negative and positive elec-
trostatic environments (Fig. 4 C). Although a negative 
environment cannot reliably exclude the binding of phos-
phate groups (Ledvina et al., 1996), the positive environ-
ment around strand 1 would seem an intuitive choice 
for binding cGMP. For instance, the canonical site has an 
essential arginine R529 (Tibbs et al., 1998), and strand 
1 also contains an arginine R464, which in Construct 8 
was neutralized to glutamine. However, we found that an 
isolated R464Q mutation introduced to X-fA2 did not 
significantly change the low ratio g (30 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) 
(Fig. 5 A, X-fA2 R464Q vs. X-fA2). Similarly, an isolated 
V467T mutation preserved con action and indeed en-
hanced its observed effects, with a significant decrease in 
g (30 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) compared with that of X-fA2. 
These results argue against strand 1 contributing to con 
action at all, and in fact the presence of valine at posi-
tion 467 in the fCNGA2 BD seems to favor channel open-
ing compared with the threonine found in rCNGA4. 
In contrast, X-fA2 with an isolated V457E mutation 
shows a mean g (30 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) ratio much higher 
than those of the other two point mutants and X-fA2 itself 
(1.26 ± 0.23; n = 7), and significantly greater than unity 
(P &lt; 0.02). The cGMP dose-response curve for X-fA2 
V457E (Fig. 5 B) resembles that of Construct 8 with no </p>

<p>Figure 5. V457E mutation abolishes con action. (A) Bar shows BD of Construct 8. Sequence alignment of the region from helix A 
through strand 2 is shown for point mutants, along with their respective mean g (30 mM cGMP) /g (3 mM cGMP) ratios. Dots in alignment indicate 
residues conserved between fCNGA2 and rCNGA4. Amino acids mutated in each construct are circled. (B) Dose-response relation of 
X-fA2 V457E activated with cGMP (down-triangles; n ≥ 3 for all points). Conductances were converted to P o using the methods of Fig. 3, 
fixing P o = 0.359 at 3 mM cGMP. Black curve is a Hill equation fit. Fitted parameters (±SE) are: K 1/2 = 350 ± 97 µM, h = 0.78 ± 0.17, and 
P max = 0.45 ± 0.03. For comparison, gray curve shows cGMP dose-response data for X-fA2 (Young et al., 2001) as in Fig. 4 B. </p>



<p>Contributions to bimodal agonism in CNG channels </p>

<p>of mechanistic possibilities will require future mutagen-
esis in these three helices, which are implicated in con 
action for the first time by our analysis. </p>

<p>Does helix A control coupling? </p>

<p>Another possible role for the Fig. 6 network could be to 
govern the coupling of ligand binding to gate opening, 
like the transmission gearbox in an automobile that 
enables the crankshaft to propel the vehicle in reverse. 
Postulating that the Fig. 6 network is a coupling controller 
and therefore not a noncanonical binding site does not 
force us to assume the existence of a noncanonical site 
somewhere else. Workable con-action mechanisms can 
be conceived in which cGMP binds only to canonical 
binding sites, and it is only the number of vacant versus 
occupied sites that determines whether the coupling re-
lationship will be reversed (Chan and Young, 2009). 
Helices D and B in the network have previously 
been identified as coupling-control elements governing 
the efficiency of pro action in CNG channels (Li and 
Lester, 1999; Paoletti et al., 1999; Young and Krougliak, 
2004) as well as in other cAMP receptors with homologous 
BDs (Rehmann et al., 2003; Zagotta et al., 2003; Kim et al., 
2005). It may seem odd that these same coupling-control 
elements could reverse the direction of their effects </p>

<p>sequence context, because we did not find con action in 
Construct 4. We also acknowledge the impossibility of 
confirming the criticality of V457 in all possible sequence 
contexts. Thus, conceivably, con action might be restored 
to X-fA2 V457E by some as yet untested mutations out-
side position 457. However, any such mutations would 
have to introduce amino acids not found in the fCNGA2 
BD, because X-fA2 V457E currently possesses all fCNGA2 
BD residues except V457. (This contrasts with our suc-
cessful restoration of con action to Construct 4 by adding 
back noncritical fCNGA2 BD residues to make Construct 
5). Our identification of V457 as critical for con action is 
certainly consistent with known current evidence. Of 
broader importance, the low pro-action efficacy of X-fA2 
V457E (and, more clearly, Construct 8) refutes the suffi-
ciency hypothesis. Thus, con action does not arise as an 
unavoidable consequence of the rather inefficient pro 
action in fCNGA2; rather, con action can be removed or 
added on top of a preexisting pro-action mechanism by 
virtue of the amino acid at position 457. 
Could V457 then make contact with cGMP, forming 
counterproductive interactions during con action? This 
would constitute a noncanonical cGMP-binding site that 
is structurally distinct from known sites, based on analy-
sis of our comparative models as follows. We enumerated 
"first neighbor" residues located within 5 Å of the resi-
due 457 side chain in our comparative models (Fig. 6, 
black dashed lines), and then identified "second neigh-
bor" residues within 5 Å of each of the first neighbors' 
side chains (Fig. 6, gray dashed lines). The residues of the 
"neighbor network" are limited to three noncontiguous 
helices: helix A itself, plus helix D of the C-linker, 
and helix B at the C-terminal end of the BD (second 
neighbors only). All network residues other than V457 
were conserved in all constructs of this study. Based on 
corresponding residues in the HCN2 template structure, 
none of the network residues are proximal to ligand 
bound at the canonical site. Moreover, none of them 
correspond to residues forming the previously reported 
noncanonical cAMP-binding site in Escherichia coli catab-
olite activator protein (Passner and Steitz, 1997), which 
relies on the 4-5 loop along with the DNA BD that 
has no counterpart in CNG channels. 
The neighbor network includes multiple residues 
that could contribute to ligand binding in varied ways. 
Several first neighbors are hydrophobic, suitable for in-
teraction with the entire valine side chain or with the 
C and C methylene groups of glutamate. Additionally, 
however, the salt-bridged residue pair E458+K462 is in-
cluded, available for stabilizing polar contact with the 
carboxylate group of E457 (H bonds identified by <rs type="software">VA-
DAR</rs> software; Willard et al., 2003). The effect of the 
V457E mutation could thus be a result of any of multiple 
features such as side-chain packing, charge, or specific 
H bonds, and might be as subtle as a slight reorientation 
of one of the three helices. Addressing the large scope </p>

<p>Figure 6. Neighbor network around position 457 proposed by 
comparative modeling. All residues in this structural schematic 
are numbered according to fCNGA2 sequence position. Gluta-
mate is shown in position 457, with black dashed lines indicating 
its interactions with first neighbors (see Discussion). Parentheses 
indicate residues that are not identified as first neighbors when 
valine occupies position 457. Gray dashed lines indicate interac-
tions between first neighbors (black type) and second neighbors 
(gray type). E458 is capable of forming hydrogen bonds or po-
lar contact with both E457 and K462 (thick dashed lines); other 
neighbor interactions shown are not polar. </p>

<p>Wong et al. </p>





<p>after a certain number of ligands are bound. How-
ever, occupancy-dependent coupling has already been 
proposed for pro action in CNG channels, based on 
observations that successive ligand-binding events make 
nonidentical energetic contributions even in a homo-
tetrameric channel (Ruiz and Karpen, 1997; Biskup et al., 
2007). Ligand-dependent subunit interactions such as 
those mediated by helix D (Craven and Zagotta, 2004) 
have been proposed to explain occupancy-dependent 
coupling in pro action (Liu et al., 1998; Ulens and 
Siegelbaum, 2003) as well as the dependence of con ac-
tion on the arrangement of subunits in a heteromer 
(Chan and Young, 2009). </p>

<p>PB cassette region and high P o masking </p>

<p>Unlike the A-1 region, the PB cassette contributes 
essential residues to the canonical-binding pocket 
(Altenhofen et al., 1991; Tibbs et al., 1998; Zagotta et al., 
2003; Flynn et al., 2007), and it is therefore not surprising 
that significant effects on pro-action efficacy result from 
substitution of the fCNGA2 cassette. We caution that the 
effects of PB cassette substitution are expected to depend 
on the background sequence context, as in any structure-
function study. Unfortunately, the structural effects of PB 
cassette substitution cannot be reliably explored through 
our comparative model, because fCNGA2 contains a 
six-residue insertion in its cassette region with no ho-
mologous counterpart in the cassette of HCN2. Further 
investigations of efficacy determinants may benefit from 
testing cassettes from different CNG channels, because 
the insertion is shorter in some CNG family members. 
The broader significance of the PB cassette replace-
ment producing Construct 3 is that it illustrates the 
principle of masking through an increased gating equi-
librium constant. The persistence of efficient con ac-
tion in Construct 3 is detectable when this masking is 
taken into account, refuting the necessity hypothesis. 
Because low pro-action efficacy is not a prerequisite for 
the operation of con action, it may be that the con-action 
mechanism exists in some other previously studied CNG 
channels but has gone undetected because of masking 
(see discussion of rat CNGA2 in Biskup et al., 2007, and 
Chan and Young, 2009). </p>

<p>We thank D.M. Sciubba and N.B. Olivier for preliminary plasmid 
construction; K.E. Magee, Z. Madden, and other Young labora-
tory members for technical assistance; and Drs. R. Cornell and 
E. Accili for comments on the manuscript. 
This work was supported by a Natural Sciences and Engineer-
ing Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Discovery Grant to 
E.C. Young, an NSERC Undergraduate Student Research Award 
to M.S. Michaleski, and awards from Simon Fraser University to 
K.S.C. Chan (Graduate Fellowship) and W.-F. Wong (VP Research 
Award). E.C. Young is a Scholar of the Michael Smith Foundation 
for Health Research. </p>

<p>Author contributions: W.-F. Wong, K.S.C. Chan, and E.C. Young 
designed research and wrote the paper; W.-F. Wong, K.S.C. Chan, </p>



<p>Contributions to bimodal agonism in CNG channels </p>



<p>Wong et al. </p>





</text></tei>