<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3329502" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cancer is rare among children throughout the world. In devel-
oped countries, only about 0.5% of all cancers occur among chil-
dren under 15 years. In contrast to adult malignancies, where 
carcinomas predominate, childhood cancers are histologically 
very diverse. There are 12 major groups including leukemias, 
lymphomas, brain and spinal tumors, sympathetic nervous 
system tumors, retinoblastoma, kidney tumors, liver tumors, 
bone tumors, soft tissue sarcomas, gonadal and germ-cell 
tumors, epithelial tumors and other unspecified neoplasms. The 
International Classification of Childhood Cancer is based on 
morphology and topography. 1 Diagnostic groups are defined in 
the second edition of the International Classification of Diseases 
(ICD) for Oncology. 
Cancer formation is generally considered as a genetic dis-
ease involving alterations in DNA structure ranging from gene 
mutations to gross chromosomal rearrangements. However, </p>

<p>We describe monozygotic twins discordant for childhood leukemia and secondary thyroid carcinoma. We used bisulfite 
pyrosequencing to compare the constitutive promoter methylation of BRCA1 and several other tumor suppressor genes 
in primary fibroblasts. The affected twin displayed an increased BRCA1 methylation (12%), compared with her sister (3%). 
Subsequent bisulfite plasmid sequencing demonstrated that 13% (6 of 47) BRCA1 alleles were fully methylated in the 
affected twin, whereas her sister displayed only single CpG errors without functional implications. This between-twin 
methylation difference was also found in irradiated fibroblasts and untreated saliva cells. The BRCA1 epimutation may 
have originated by an early somatic event in the affected twin: approximately 25% of her body cells derived from different 
embryonic cell lineages carry one epigenetically inactivated BRCA1 allele. This epimutation was associated with reduced 
basal protein levels and a higher induction of BRCA1 after DNA damage. In addition, we performed a genome-wide 
microarray analysis of both sisters and found several copy number variations, i.e., heterozygous deletion and reduced 
expression of the RSPO3 gene in the affected twin. This monozygotic twin pair represents an impressive example of 
epigenetic somatic mosaicism, suggesting a role for constitutive epimutations, maybe along with de novo genetic 
alterations in recurrent tumor development. </p>

<p>Monozygotic twins discordant for constitutive 
BRCA1 promoter methylation, childhood cancer 
and secondary cancer </p>

<p>Danuta Galetzka, 1, † Tamara Hansmann, 2, † Nady El Hajj, 2 Eva Weis, 1 Benjamin Irmscher, 1 Marco Ludwig, 1 
Brigitte Schneider-Rätzke, 1 Nicolai Kohlschmidt, 1 Vera Beyer, 1 Oliver Bartsch, 1 Ulrich Zechner, 1 Claudia Spix 3 
and Thomas Haaf 2, * </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Institute of Human Genetics; University Medical Center; Mainz, Germany; 2 Institute of Human Genetics; Julius Maximilians University; Würzburg, Germany; 
3 Institute of Medical Biometry, Epidemiology and Informatics; University Medical Center; Mainz, Germany </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>Key words: BRCA1, DNA methylation, childhood cancer, epimutation, monozygotic twins, secondary cancer, somatic mosaicism </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CNV, copy number variation; HNPCC, hereditary non-polyposis colorectal cancer; 
ICD, International Classification of Diseases; MZ, monozygotic; qPCR, quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>dysregulation of gene expression can also be acquired by epigen-
etic abnormalities, which are a hallmark of cancer evolution at all 
stages. 2,3 In contrast to the rest of the genome where most CpGs 
are methylated, CpG islands in 5' cis-regulatory regions of genes 
are usually unmethylated. Methylation of these CpG islands 
during development or disease processes is associated with gene 
silencing. 4,5 Inactivation of tumor suppressor genes by promoter 
hypermethylation provides an important mechanism for tumor 
initiation and progression. 
The genomic caretaker BRCA1 is necessary for faithful rejoin-
ing of broken DNA ends and one mutated BRCA1 allele may 
already be sufficient to impair this process. The compromised 
genomic stability in BRCA1 germline mutation carriers may trig-
ger the genetic changes necessary for neoplastic transformation 
in hereditary breast cancer patients. Methylation of the BRCA1 
promoter occurs in approximately 20% of sporadic breast can-
cers. 6,7 Sporadic breast tumors with BRCA1 promoter methyla-
tion are mainly estrogen-and progesterone-receptor negative and </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p>48 
Epigenetics 
Volume 7 Issue 1 </p>

<p>history nor clinical examination gave any hints for a DNA repair 
syndrome or another hereditary disease. Apart from the affected 
twin there were no other cases of cancer in four generations. 
Considering her medical history, it is not unexpected that the 
affected twin differed from her sister in some features, including 
height (156 cm vs. 168 cm) and occipitofrontal circumference (52 
cm vs. 51 cm). Monozygosity was confirmed by genotyping short 
tandem repeats. Chromosome banding analysis (at the 500 band 
level) of fibroblast cultures revealed normal female karyotypes in 
both sisters. 
Methylation analysis. Because MZ twins are genetically 
identical, epigenetic differences are one plausible explanation 
for discordant phenotypes. To test this hypothesis, we analyzed 
the methylation patterns of several representative tumor suppres-
sor genes (ATM, BRCA1, BRCA2, MLH1, RAD51C and TP53). 
One of the studied genes, BRCA1, showed constitutive promoter 
hypermethylation in normal body cells of the affected twin, but 
not of the healthy twin. Bisulfite pyrosequencing is a rapid and 
highly accurate method for epimutation screening. It can exactly 
(±2%) quantify the methylation of individual CpG sites located 
in the 30-50 bp 3' from the sequencing primer. 9 Our pyrose-
quencing assay measures the methylation levels of five adjacent 
CpG sites in the BRCA1 5' promoter. Because the density of 
methylated CpGs in a cis-regulatory region rather than individ-
ual CpGs turn a gene on or off, 5,10 the average methylation of all 
analyzed CpGs (in two independent DNA samples) was used as 
an epigenetic marker for BRCA1 promoter methylation. 
By bisulfite pyrosequencing of exponentially growing fibro-
blasts, the affected twin showed an increased BRCA1 methyla-
tion level of 12% (Fig. 1), compared with 3% in her healthy 
sister. Primary skin fibroblasts were used for epimutation screen-
ing, because they constitute a homogenous cell population with 
intact cell cycle and DNA repair checkpoints. Ten additionally 
analyzed two-cancer patients, who survived a childhood malig-
nancy and then, unrelated to the first event, developed a second-
ary cancer, as well as 10 carefully matched one-cancer patients 
without a second malignancy all showed normal methylation 
levels (range 0-3%) in fibroblasts. Induction of DNA damage by 
γ-irradiation (1 Gy) of primary fibroblast cultures did not affect 
the BRCA1 methylation levels. In the affected twin, we found 
10% methylation at 0 h, 10% at 1 h, 9% at 4 h, 11% at 12 h and 
10% at 24 h after irradiation. The control twin displayed 4%, 
4%, 3%, 2% and 4% methylation, respectively. 
Lymphoblastoid cells of both the affected and the control 
twin exhibited equally low BRCA1 methylation levels (3% and 
2%, respectively). However, because the affected twin was bone 
marrow-transplanted, her blood cells were also derived from the 
healthy twin's stem cells. The normal range of BRCA1 meth-
ylation in blood cells of a large number (&gt;100) of controls was 
0-5%. Similar to fibroblasts, saliva DNA of the affected twin 
showed a much higher BRCA1 methylation (9%) than that of 
her sister (2%). The normal methylation range in 10 saliva con-
trol samples was 2-4%. In addition to cells from buccal mucosa 
and salivary epithelium, saliva may also contain blood cells. This 
may explain the somewhat lower methylation level of saliva DNA 
compared with fibroblast DNA in the affected twin. </p>

<p>display similar pathological features as hereditary tumors with 
BRCA1 mutations. 8 
The concordance rates in monozygotic (MZ) and dizygotic 
pairs of twins allow one to estimate the heritability of complex 
phenotypic traits. MZ twins arise from the same zygote, which 
then divides into two genetically identical embryos. MZ twins 
discordant for monogenic disorders are generally thought to rep-
resent rare examples of somatic mosaicism due to genetic muta-
tions after the twinning event, which are then propagated to 
subsets of cells from one twin. Here we report on a pair of MZ 
twins discordant for recurrent tumor development. Our results 
suggest that post-zygotic epimutations are another source of 
somatic mosaicism leading to different disease susceptibility in 
MZ twins. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Case report. The twin sisters were born in 1977 by spontane-
ous delivery, seven weeks before term. No intensive care or 
icterus treatment were necessary. Until 1982 the development of 
both twins was normal. At the age of 4 y and 8 mo, one sis-
ter was diagnosed with precursor B-cell lymphoblastic leukemia 
(ICD10:C910). Chemotherapy had to be discontinued because 
of intolerability. A first relapse of the leukemia occurred in 1984. 
The second chemotherapy could be completed, but another 
relapse made bone marrow transplantation from her healthy twin 
sister necessary. Following bone marrow transplantation at age 7 y 
she was monitored until 1988. From 1985 until 1990 she received 
human growth hormone. In 2002 at the age of 25 y, she was 
diagnosed with thyroid carcinoma (ICD10:C730). She under-
went thyroidectomy and since then receives steroid hormone 
replacement. She was not treated with radiation or radioactive 
iodine. In 2006 a type 2 diabetes became manifest, but other-
wise she is healthy. In 2009 she gave birth to a healthy daughter. 
When re-examined at age 34 y, the affected twin and her sister 
did not show any clinical manifestation of cancer. Neither family </p>

<p>Figure 1. Box plots showing the distribution of BRCA1 methylation 
values in fibroblasts of 10 one-cancer and 10 two-cancer patients. The 
star symbol (extreme outlier) represents the affected twin. The median 
is represented by a horizontal line. The bottom of the box indicates the 
25th percentile, the top the 75th percentile. The T bars extend from the 
boxes to 1.5 times the height of the box. </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
Epigenetics </p>

<p>
a first hit according to Knudson's two-hit hypothesis of tumor 
development. 
Because constitutional epimutations in different tumor sup-
pressor genes have been linked to sequence variants in the 5' cis-
regulatory region, 11-13 we sequenced a 3.4 kb upstream fragment 
including the BRCA1 promoter and exon 1. However, we did 
not find any genetic defect/sequence variant in the affected twin 
(data not shown). 
In addition to BRCA1, we performed an epimutation screen-
ing by bisulfite pyrosequencing for several other tumor suppressor 
genes (ATM, BRCA2, MLH1, RAD51C and TP53) in fibroblasts 
of the twin pair and the 20 one-or two-cancer patients. However, 
apart from the BRCA1 epimutation in the affected twin, all ana-
lyzed samples and promoters displayed normal (&lt;5%) meth-
ylation values (data not shown), indicating that constitutive 
epimutations in tumor suppressor genes are rare events in child-
hood-cancer patients. 
Protein expression analysis. Customized antibody micro-
arrays were used to compare the basal protein levels (without 
induction of DNA damage) of BRCA1 and several other genomic 
caretakers (ATM, BRCA2, MLH1, RAD51 and TP53) in expo-
nentially growing primary fibroblasts of the affected twin vs. 
her healthy sister. Triplicate measurements (technical replicates) 
of the protein levels were performed on protein samples from 
three independent cell cultures each (biological replicates). The 
BRCA1 protein expression ratio between the affected and the </p>

<p>To distinguish between single CpG methylation errors, which 
are most likely stochastic errors without pathological conse-
quences, and true epimutations (allele methylation errors), which 
can be expected to interfere with gene regulation, it is necessary 
to study the methylation patterns of individual DNA molecules. 
Classic bisulfite plasmid sequencing has the added advantage that 
it allows one to look at a larger number of CpG sites. Here we 
analyzed a BRCA1 amplicon with 13 CpG sites including the 
five sites targeted by the pyrosequencing assay (Fig. 2). Forty-
seven clones (individual DNA molecules) were recovered from 
primary fibroblasts of each twin. Six (13%) clones of the affected 
twin exhibited epimutations, indicating that most (at least 70%) 
CpG sites on these DNA molecules were aberrantly methylated, 
typical for epigenetically silenced alleles. In contrast, all 47 alleles 
of the healthy twin displayed normal hypomethylated patterns. 
The BRCA1 epimutation rate was significantly (χ 2 test; p = 0.01) 
higher in the affected twin, compared with her sister. Both sis-
ters showed approximately 2% stochastic (single CpG) methyla-
tion errors: 10 of 531 CpG sites in the affected twin (excluding 
abnormal alleles) and 14 of 609 in the healthy twin were methyl-
ated. Collectively, our results suggest a constitutively increased 
methylation level at the BRCA1 promoter in normal body cells 
of the affected twin. Approximately 25% cells (skin fibroblasts, 
cells from buccal mucosa and salivary epithelium) derived from 
different embryonic lineages are endowed with one hypermeth-
ylated copy of the BRCA1 tumor suppressor gene, representing </p>

<p>Figure 2. Methylation patterns of the BRCA1 promoter in fibroblasts of the affected twin and her healthy sister. Each line represents an individual allele 
(DNA molecule) analyzed by bisulfite plasmid sequencing. Filled circles indicate methylated CpG and open circles unmethylated CpG sites. Missing 
dots indicate CpG sites that could not be analyzed because of poor sequence quality. The five framed CpG sites correspond to those in the bisulfite 
pyrosequencing assay. Both twin sisters display alleles with single CpG (stochastic) methylation errors. Six of 47 analyzed alleles (indicated by arrows) 
in the affected twin represent epimutations with the majority of CpGs being aberrantly methylated, whereas all 47 alleles in the healthy twin are 
hypomethylated. </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p> 
Epigenetics 
Volume 7 Issue 1 </p>

<p>also quantified in fibroblast cells at 1 h and 4 h 
after 1 Gy γ-irradiation (Fig. 3B). In the healthy 
twin, the amount of BRCA1 protein increased 
1.8-fold at 1 h after irradiation, compared with 
untreated cells, and reached basal levels at 4 h 
(the z ratio of treated vs. untreated cells was 0.9). 
In the affected twin, BRCA1 protein expression 
was induced 2.7-fold at 1 h and also back to 
basal levels (z ratio of 1.1) at 4 h. 
Molecular karyotype analysis. Microarray 
analysis revealed a 181 kb heterozygous deletion 
containing the RSPO3 gene on chromosome 
6q22.33 and a 90 kb heterozygous deletion 
containing the open reading frame C5orf13 on 
chromosome 5q22.1 in primary fibroblasts of 
the affected twin. We did not see similar dele-
tions in &gt;40 additionally studied childhood can-
cer patients and 100 normal healthy individuals 
(from the Gutenberg Heart Study 14 ). We did not 
find evidence for a microdeletion or duplica-
tion affecting the BRCA1 cis-regulatory region 
in the affected twin. By quantitative real-time 
PCR (qPCR) we confirmed the presence of the 
heterozygous RSPO3 and C5orf13 deletions in 
a mosaic state (Fig. 4A). All qPCR experiments 
were performed on three independent DNA 
samples (biological replicates) of the affected twin and a mix-
ture of control DNAs, respectively. Using RFC3 as reference for 
a normal diploid gene (with two copies), qPCR revealed a copy 
number of two for both RSPO3 and C5orf13 in the controls. In 
contrast, the affected twin displayed copy numbers around 1.5, 
indicating loss of one RSPO3 and one C5orf13 copy in approxi-
mately 50% of cells. This does not necessarily imply that both 
genes are deleted in the same cells. Expression analysis with 
GeneAtlas microarrays using four independent RNA samples 
(from different cell cultures of the affected and the healthy twin) 
demonstrated reduced (approximately 50%) RSPO3 mRNA lev-
els in fibroblasts of the affected twin (Fig. 4B), whereas C5orf13 
levels were comparable in both twins (data not shown). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Traditionally, phenotypic discordances between MZ twin pairs 
have been attributed to environmental factors; however, accu-
mulating experimental evidence also suggests a role for genetic 
and, more importantly, epigenetic differences between co-twins. 
Microarray-based karyotype analyses revealed somatic mosa-
icism for copy number variations (CNVs) in a number (estimated 
10%) of both phenotypically discordant (for Parkinson disease, 
parkinsonism or Lewy body dementia) and concordant MZ twin 
pairs. 15 Other molecular karyotype and genome sequence stud-
ies could not detect any CNV differences between MZ twins 
that were discordant for cleft lip palate 16 or multiple sclerosis, 17 
suggesting that post-zygotic genomic alterations are at least not 
a common cause of phenotypic discordance. Several recent stud-
ies clearly demonstrated the existence of genome-wide epigenetic </p>

<p>healthy twin (z ratio normalized with log10 transformation and z 
scores) was 0.75 (Fig. 3A), consistent with constitutively reduced 
expression in the affected twin. ATM expression was slightly 
increased (1.25) in the affected twin, whereas ACTB (positive 
control), BRCA2, MLH1, RAD51 and Tp53 all showed compa-
rable protein levels in both twins. The BRCA1 protein levels were </p>

<p>Figure 3. (A) Constitutive protein expression of ACTB (control), ATM, BRCA1, BRCA2, MLH1, 
RAD51 and Tp53 in untreated fibroblasts of the affected vs. the healthy twin. Relative 
protein expression (z ratio normalized by log10 transformation and z scores) was measured 
by antibody microarrays using three biological replicates. Note the decreased BRCA1 level 
(75% expression ratio) in the affected twin. (B) Differential induction of BRCA1 protein in 
fibroblasts of the healthy twin (gray bars) and the affected twin (black bars) at 1 h and 4 h 
after 1 Gy γ-irradiation. Relative protein expression in treated vs. untreated cells of each 
twin was measured by antibody microarrays using three biological replicates. </p>

<p>Figure 4. (A) C5orf13 and RSPO3 copy numbers in fibroblast cells of the 
two-cancer twin, compared with healthy controls, as determined by 
qPCR (using the RFC3 gene copy number as reference). Standard devia-
tions represent three independent DNA samples (biological replicates) 
of the affected twin and a mixture of control DNAs. (B) RSPO3 mRNA 
expression ratio between the affected twin and her healthy sister, as 
determined by GeneAtlas microarrays. Standard deviations represent 
RNA samples from four different cell cultures of the affected and the 
healthy twin, respectively. </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
Epigenetics </p>

<p>
methylation patterns at the KCNQ1OT1 locus (imprinting con-
trol region 2 on chromosome 11p15) have been described in a 
number of MZ twin pairs discordant for Beckwith-Wiedemann 
syndrome, which is characterized by tumor predisposition and 
multiple congenital abnormalities. 35 Constitutive H19 epimuta-
tions (imprinting control region 1 on chromosome 11p15.5) were 
found in several patients with sporadic Wilms tumor without fea-
tures of Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome. 36 
Somatic gene mutations and mosaicism (with or without 
involvement of the germline) are an important etiological mech-
anism for monogenic disorders with high de novo mutations 
rates such as Duchenne muscular dystrophy, neurofibromatosis 
type 1 and retinoblastoma. 37-39 In contrast, constitutive epimu-
tations, characterized by soma-wide methylation abnormalities 
in functionally relevant cis-regulatory regions of disease genes, 
are an understudied phenomenon. Constitutive epimutations in 
the DNA mismatch repair gene MLH1 have been identified in 
a small number of mutation-negative cases of hereditary non-
polyposis colorectal cancer (HNPCC). 40 In rare familial cases 
with dominant transmission of mosaic MLH1 methylation, the 
constitutional epimutation was linked to a single nucleotide vari-
ant in the 5' UTR of MLH1. 13 Similarly, constitutional epimu-
tations in the DNA mismatch repair gene MSH2, another rare 
cause of HNPCC, were linked to 3' end deletions of EPCAM, a 
gene directly upstream of MSH2. 12 Constitutive epimutations in 
the DAPK1 gene that predispose to B cell chronic lymphocytic 
leukemia are caused by a point mutation upstream of the DAPK1 
promoter. 11 Neither sequencing nor microarray analysis of the 5' 
cis-regulatory region of BRCA1 revealed any detectable genetic 
differences between the discordant MZ twin pair studied here. 
Although we cannot exclude a causative genetic defect elsewhere, 
our findings are consistent with the view that the affected twin 
exhibits a true BRCA1 epimutation. 
Our study revealed the existence of a constitutive BRCA1 
epimutation only in the affected sibling of a MZ twin pair. 
Compared with her healthy sister, the two-cancer twin showed 
reduced basal BRCA1 protein levels (in untreated fibroblasts) 
and a higher induction of protein expression by DNA damage. 
Upregulation of BRCA1 in irradiated cells of both the affected 
and the healthy twin was not mediated by demethylation of 
the BRCA1 promoter. In the affected twin the percentage of 
aberrantly methylated alleles remained constant (at about 10%) 
after DNA damage and in the healthy twin the BRCA1 pro-
moter was already completely demethylated in untreated cells. 
It is well known that the methylation of CpGs in 5' promoters 
that are usually protected from methylation in somatic tissues 
can suppress gene expression during development, differentia-
tion and disease processes. 4,5 However, other mechanisms, i.e., 
gene body methylation, may be more important for regulating 
the cell-context specific efficiency of transcription. 41 The basal 
ATM protein levels were also increased in the affected twin, 
although both twins showed equally low promoter methylation 
levels (around 1%) of the ATM gene. We speculate that ATM 
is constitutively upregulated by a compensation mechanism 
to counterbalance the reduced BRCA1 levels. ATM mediates 
the cellular DNA damage response. BRCA1 is regulated by an </p>

<p>differences between MZ twins. 18,19 Spontaneous epimutations 
may occur 10-100 times more frequently than somatic DNA 
mutations. 20,21 This spontaneous epimutation rate can be modi-
fied by environmental factors, providing a link between lifestyle 
and phenotypic differences. 22-24 In this light, stochastic and/or 
environmentally induced epimutations represent a major source 
of phenotypic variation and discordance for complex diseases 
between MZ twins. The accumulation of epigenetic differences 
may also explain the phenotypic divergence of MZ twins, as they 
age. 18 
Here we studied a MZ twin pair discordant for childhood can-
cer and a second primary cancer. Microarray analysis and qPCR 
revealed mosaic heterozygous deletions on chromosome 5q22.1 
(C5orf13) and 6q22.33 (RSPO3) in the affected twin. C5orf13 
encodes an 8 kDa intracytoplasmic protein initially identified in 
neurons and muscles. 25 It contains a conserved PEST domain, 
which is important for targeting proteins for degradation by the 
ubiquitin proteasome. R-Spondin family members are modula-
tors of the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway which plays a cru-
cial role in cell growth, development and disease pathogenesis. 26 
RSPO3 is frequently upregulated in human breast cancers and 
correlated with several tumor parameters, suggesting that it 
can function as a breast cancer oncogene. 27 However, RSPO3 
was downregulated in normal fibroblasts of the affected twin. 
Although C5orf13 and RSPO3 haploinsufficiency may contribute 
to the discordant cancer phenotype, they are unlikely to be the 
primary cause. 
We propose that epigenetic changes, specifically hypermeth-
ylation of one BRCA1 allele constituted the first hit leading to 
inactivation of an important tumor suppressor gene and tumor 
initiation. Germline mutations in BRCA1 are associated with 
hereditary breast cancer, ovarian cancer and some other malig-
nancies; however, so far they are generally not considered as a 
risk factor for childhood cancer. 28 Our index patient developed 
precursor B-cell lymphoblastic leukemia at the age of 4 y and 
8 mo. There are only few data linking BRCA1 to hematologic 
malignancies. In chronic myeloid leukemia, expression of the 
BCR-ABL fusion protein leads to posttranscriptional downregu-
lation of BRCA1. 29 One study reported partial hypermethylation 
and reduced expression of BRCA1 in primary and therapy-related 
acute myeloid leukemia, 30 whereas others did not find abnormal 
BRCA1 methylation in leukemia samples. 7,31 
In the MZ twin pair studied here, only one sister exhibited 
a BRCA1 epimutation in a mosaic state in multiple tissues/ 
cell types, whereas the unaffected twin did not. This epimuta-
tion most likely originated by a methylation error during early 
embryogenesis after the twinning event. It affects a substantial 
subset of cells derived from different embryonic cell lineages, 
resulting in somatic mosaicism. Genome-wide demethylation 
waves in the early embryo erase most germline methylation pat-
terns, followed by de novo methylation and establishment of 
somatic methylation patterns. 32 Most constitutive epimutations 
may occur during this vulnerable time window, where epigenetic 
genome reprogramming occurs, and represent stochastic and/or 
environmentally induced errors in the establishment or mainte-
nance of an epigenetic state. 33,34 Similar to our case, discordant </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p> 
Epigenetics 
Volume 7 Issue 1 </p>

<p>18.8 μl PCR-grade water and 1 μl (~100 ng) template DNA. For 
amplicons 6-8, 10 and 11, the PCR mixture (25 μl) contained 
25 mM ammonium sulfate, 750 mM TRIS-HCl, 0.1% Tween 
20, 240 μM dNTPs, 2.4 mM magnesium sulfate, 2.4x PCRx 
Enhancer Solution (Invitrogen), 0.4 μM of each primer, 1 Unit 
of Platinum Taq (Invitrogen) and 1 μl (~100 ng) template DNA. 
All PCR amplifications were performed with an initial denatur-
ation step at 95°C for 5 min, 40 cycles of 95°C for 30 sec, primer-
specific annealing temperature (Table S1) for 30 sec, 72°C for 
45 sec and a final extension step at 72°C for 7 min. Sequencing 
of the resulting PCR products was done on an ABI 3130xl auto-
mated sequencer. 
Methylation analysis. Genomic DNA from fibroblasts and 
EBV-transformed lymphoblasts was extracted using the Qiagen 
Mini DNA kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). Saliva DNA was 
extracted using the ORAGENE DNA extraction kit (DNA 
Genotek, Kanata, ON Canada). Bisulfite conversion of genomic 
DNA was performed with the EpiTect Bisulfite kit (Qiagen). 
Bisulfite pyrosequencing was performed on a PyroMark Q96 
MD Pyrosequencing System with the PyroMark Gold Q96 CDT 
Reagent kit (Qiagen). An assay quantifying the methylation 
levels of five representative CpG sites in the BRCA1 promoter 
was designed using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">PyroMark Assay Design</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2.0</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Qiagen</rs>). A 232 bp amplicon (HSA17: 41,277,292-41,277,523 
bps; Ensembl release 60) was PCR amplified from bisulfite-
treated DNA using forward primer 5'-ATT TAG AGT AGA 
GGG TGA AGG-3' and biotinylated reverse primer 5'-TCT 
ATC CCT CCC ATC CTC TAA TT-3'. The reaction mix-
ture consisted of 2.5 μl 10x PCR buffer, 20 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 μl 
10 mM dNTP mix, 1 μl (10 pmol) of each primer, 0.2 μl (1 U) 
FastStart Taq DNA Polymerase (Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, 
Germany), 18.8 μl PCR-grade water and 1 μl (~100 ng) template 
DNA. PCR amplifications were performed with an initial dena-
turation step at 95°C for 5 min, 35 cycles of 95°C for 30 sec, 55°C 
for 30 sec and 72°C for 45 sec and a final extension step at 72°C 
for 5 min. Sequencing was performed with primer 5'-TTG AGA 
AAT TTT ATA GTT TGT TTT-3'. The <rs id="software-2" type="software">Pyro Q-CpG</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Qiagen</rs>) was used for data analysis. 
For classic bisulfite plasmid sequencing BRCA1 PCR products 
were cloned into pCR2.1-TOPO vector using T4-DNA ligase, 
the TA cloning kit and One Shot TOP10 chemically compe-
tent Escherichia coli (Invitrogen). Plasmid DNA of individual 
clones was isolated with the ZR Plasmid Miniprep Classic Kit 
(Zymo Research, Freiburg, Germany). Insert-containing clones 
were sequenced using dye terminator cycle sequencing with M13 
primers on an ABI 3130xl automated sequencer. Sequences were 
analyzed with <rs type="software">BiQ Analyzer</rs> software tool. 46 
Protein expression analyses. Cells were resuspended two 
times in 500 μl of 10 mM HEPES, 1.5 mM MgCl 2 , 10 mM 
KCl, pH 7.9 and incubated on ice for 10 min. After 10 sec cen-
trifugation at maximum speed the supernatant was discarded. 
The pellet was resuspended in 100 μl of 20 mM HEPES, 0.42 M 
NaCl, 1.5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.2 mM EDTA, 25% glycerol, pH 7.9 
and homogenized. After incubation on ice for 30 min and cen-
trifugation for 30 min at maximum speed at 4°C, the superna-
tant containing the nuclear protein extract was separated from </p>

<p>ATM-dependent mechanism and, on the other hand, essential 
for the recruitment of previously activated ATM to the sites of 
DNA damage. 42 Although we cannot exclude the formal pos-
sibility of a chance coincidence or a late (i.e., therapy-related) 
somatic event, it is plausible to assume that epigenetic silencing 
of one copy of the BRCA1 tumor suppressor gene in 25% body 
cells and differences in the DNA damage response contrib-
uted to the discordant cancer phenotype in the affected twin. 
Preliminary evidence suggests that BRCA1 promoter hyper-
methylation can also be found in blood cells of a subset of breast 
cancer patients. 43,44 Collectively, these results suggest that con-
stitutive BRCA1 epimutations occur in normal tissues and may 
be associated with an increased cancer risk. Our pyrosequencing 
assay may prove useful for high-throughput screening of larger 
patient populations. 
The DNA methylation analysis performed in this study was 
limited to a number of key tumor suppressor genes. Considering 
the enormous epigenetic variability due to stochastic methylation 
errors or extrinsic variations during post-zygotic genome repro-
gramming, 20,21,34,45 we cannot rule out the possibility that epi-
mutations in the affected twin in genes other than those studied 
are responsible for the discordant phenotype. Nevertheless, 10% 
soma-wide promoter methylation in an essential tumor suppres-
sor gene such as BRCA1 can be expected to contribute to a tumor 
susceptibility phenotype. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Patients and cell substrates. The study was approved by the 
Ethics Committee of the Medical Association of Rhineland-
Palatinate [(Nr. 837.440.03(4102)]. With the help of the German 
Childhood Cancer Registry, we recruited a discordant MZ twin 
pair. One twin suffered from childhood leukemia and later 
on thyroid carcinoma, whereas her twin sister was completely 
healthy (without malignancy). In addition, we recruited 10 
two-cancer patients as well as 10 carefully matched one-cancer 
patients (same sex, same primary cancer, equal age at first diag-
nosis) who did not develop a second malignancy. 
Primary fibroblasts from skin biopsies were cultured in mini-
mal essential medium with Earle's salts (Invitrogen, Karlsruhe, 
Germany), supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, vitamins 
and antibiotics. The cell cultures of the twin sisters were always 
passaged in parallel and harvested in a subconfluent stage. To 
induce DNA damage, subconfluent cultures were γ-irradiated 
with a dose of 1 Gy using a GammaCell 2000 (Cs 137 ) irradia-
tor. Cells were harvested at 1, 4, 12 h and 24 h after irradiation. 
Lymphoblastoid cell lines were established by Epstein-Barr virus 
transformation of peripheral blood lymphocytes. 
DNA sequence analysis. For Sanger sequencing of the 5' UTR 
and exon 1 of the BRCA1 gene, a 3.4 kb fragment on chromo-
some 17 (41,277,112-41,280,530 bps, Ensembl release 64) was 
divided into 11 amplicons (Table S1). For amplicons 1-5 and 8, 
the PCR reaction mixture (25 μl) consisted of 2.5 μl 10x PCR 
buffer, 20 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 μl 10 mM dNTP mix, 1 μl (10 pmol) 
of each forward and reverse primer, 0.2 μl (1 U) FastStart Taq 
DNA Polymerase (Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany), </p>

<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
Epigenetics </p>

<p>
Molecular karyotype analysis. High-resolution screening 
for microdeletions and duplications was performed with the 
Affymetrix GeneChip Genome Wide Human SNP array 6.0 and 
the GeneChip Genome Wide SNP Sty Assay Kit 5.0/6.0, follow-
ing the protocol developed by the manufacturer. Copy numbers 
were determined using the <rs id="software-5" type="software">Affymetrix Genotyping Console</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">4.0</rs> 
and <rs id="software-6" type="software">Chromosome Analysis Suite</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">1.0.1.</rs>. 
Quantitative real-time PCR with the Universal Probe 
Library Set 04683633001 (Roche Diagnostics) was used to 
validate copy number changes of C5orf13 (UPL probe #24) and 
RSPO3 (#23). PCR was performed on an ABI 7500 Fast Real-
Time PCR system (Life Technologies) with one cycle of 95°C 
for 10 min and 45 cycles of 95°C for 30 sec and 60°C for 60 
sec. Copy number calculation was performed with the ΔΔ-CT 
method, using the RFC3 (UPL probe #32) gene copy number 
as reference. All experiments were performed on three biologi-
cal replicates. 
Genome-wide expression analyses were performed with RNA 
samples from four fibroblast cell cultures of each twin using the 
GeneAtlas Personal Microarray System (Affymetrix). Data were 
analyzed with the Affymetrix Expression Console program. Data 
were corrected for background noise and normalized with the 
RMA and Quantil algorithms. </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Stiftung Rheinland-Pfalz für 
Innovation (project no. 698). First of all, we thank the patients 
whose participation made this study possible. We also thank 
Annalisa Tiozzo (Affymetrix), Tanja Zeller (Clinical Chemistry 
and Laboratory Medicine, University Medical Center Mainz), 
Niels Boehm and Franz Grus (Experimental Ophthalmology, 
Ocular Proteomics and Immunology Center, University Medical 
Center Mainz) for help with the DNA and antibody arrays, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Note </p>

<p>Supplemental material can be found at: 
www.landesbioscience.com/journals/epi/article/18814 </p>

<p>the cytoplasmic pellet and stored at -80°C. The protein concen-
tration was measured according to Bradford, using Roti Quant 
(Roth, Karlsruhe, Germany). 
Customized antibody microarrays for quantification of BRCA1 
(antibody #sc-1553, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Heidelberg, 
Germany) and several other DNA repair-associated proteins 
(ATM, BRCA2, MLH1, RAD51 and TP53) were prepared by 
spotting triplicate drops, each containing approximately 0.5 pg 
antibody onto nitrocellulose-coated slides (Oncyte, nitrocellulose 
16 multi-pad slides, Grace Bio-Labs, Bend, OR), using a sciFLEX-
ARRAYER 3 non-contact spotter (Scienion, Berlin, Germany). 
Antibodies against β-actin (ACTB) (#A5441, Sigma-Aldrich, 
Munich, Germany) served as positive, spotting buffer as nega-
tive control. Slides were stored at 4°C in dry condition. Nuclear 
proteins were labeled with an amine reactive fluorine dye, which 
forms a covalent amide bond between the primary amines of 
proteins. Two micrograms of protein and 0.12 μl fluorescent dye 
(Dylight 649 NHS Ester, Pierce, Rockford, IL) were incubated 
for 1 h at room temperature in the dark. Then, excess fluores-
cent dye was inactivated by adding 100 mM glycine to the reac-
tion. Prior to use, antibody microarrays were covered with 16-pad 
FAST frame hybridization chambers (Whatman, Maidstone, 
UK). Unspecific binding sites were blocked for 1 h at 4°C with 
120 μl PBS containing 4% non-fat dry milk per subarray, fol-
lowed by three washes with 120 μl PBS each for 10 min. Labeled 
protein samples were incubated on subarrays overnight at 4°C. 
Afterwards, the slides were washed two times for 15 min with 
PBS, 5% Tween 20 and two times for 15 min with HPLC-grade 
water. Finally, the slides were dried in a SpeedVac and scanned 
with a high-resolution confocal Affymetrix array scanner 428 TM 
(Affymetrix, High Wycombe, UK). Slide images were analyzed 
using the <rs id="software-3" type="software">TM4 Spotfinder</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">3.1.1.</rs>) software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Dana Faber Cancer Institute</rs>, Boston, MA). Background subtraction was per-
formed according to the formula: spot intensity = mean intensity 
SP -[(sum bkg -sum top25 bkg)/(number of pixelSP -number 
of pixel top25 bkg)], where SP represents any spot, bkg the corre-
sponding background and top25 bkg the top 25% of background 
pixel. Microarray data were analyzed using log10 transformation, 
z score and z ratio calculations. 47 Three biological replicates (using 
protein samples from different cell cultures of the affected and the 
healthy twin) were performed for each experiment. </p>



<p>© 2012 Landes Bioscience. </p>

<p>Do not distribute. </p>

<p> 
Epigenetics 
Volume 7 Issue 1 </p>



</text></tei>