<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3765960" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>In Drosophila, anatomically discrete dopamine neu-
rons that innervate distinct zones of the mushroom 
body (MB) assign opposing valence to odors during 
olfactory learning. Subsets of MB neurons have 
temporally unique roles in memory processing, but 
valence-related organization has not been demon-
strated. We functionally subdivided the ab neurons, 
revealing a value-specific role for the 160 ab core 
(ab c ) neurons. Blocking neurotransmission from ab 
surface (ab s ) neurons revealed a requirement during 
retrieval of aversive and appetitive memory, whereas 
blocking ab c only impaired appetitive memory. The 
ab c were also required to express memory in a differ-
ential aversive paradigm demonstrating a role in rela-
tive valuation and approach behavior. Strikingly, 
both reinforcing dopamine neurons and efferent 
pathways differentially innervate ab c and ab s in the 
MB lobes. We propose that conditioned approach 
requires pooling synaptic outputs from across the 
ab ensemble but only from the ab s for conditioned 
aversion. </p>

<p>Understanding how nervous systems represent sensory cues, 
store memories, and support decision making and appropriate 
action selection is of major interest. 
Olfactory learning in Drosophila is ideally suited to address 
these questions. Conditioning flies with aversive electric shock 
or sugar reward assigns value to otherwise meaningless odors 
and alters naive odor preferences so that subsequent odor-
driven behavior becomes goal-directed movement (Tully and  Quinn, 1985; Tempel et al., 1983). Trained flies either avoid or 
approach the previously conditioned odor, driven by the expec-
tation of punishment or food, respectively. Although progress 
has been made toward delineating how specific odors are repre-
sented (Turner et al., 2008; Murthy et al., 2008; Honegger et al.,  2011) and reinforcement signals conveyed (Claridge-Chang   et al., 2009; Aso et al., 2010, 2012; Liu et al., 2012; Burke  et al., 2012), it is not known how opposing behavioral programs 
of avoidance or approach are generated. 
Olfactory memories are believed to be represented within the 
2,000 intrinsic Kenyon cells (KCs) of the Drosophila mushroom 
body (MB) (Heisenberg, 2003). Individual odors activate rela-
tively sparse populations of KCs within the overall MB ensemble 
providing cellular specificity to odor memories (Turner et al.,  2008; Murthy et al., 2008; Honegger et al., 2011). Prior research 
of fly memory suggests that the KCs can be functionally split into 
at least three major subdivisions: the ab, a 
0 b 
0 , and g neurons. The 
current consensus suggests a role for g in short-term memory, 
for a 
0 b 
0 after training for memory consolidation, and for ab in later 
memory retrieval, with the ab requirement becoming more pro-
nounced as time passes (Zars et al., 2000; Yu et al., 2006;  Krashes et al., 2007; Blum et al., 2009; Trannoy et al., 2011;  Qin et al., 2012). Importantly, odor-evoked activity is observable 
in each of these cell types (Yu et al., 2006; Turner et al., 2008;  Wang et al., 2008; Akalal et al., 2010; Honegger et al., 2011), 
consistent with a parallel representation of olfactory stimuli 
across the different KC classes. 
Value is assigned to odors during training by anatomically 
distinct dopaminergic (DA) neurons that innervate unique zones 
of the MB (Waddell, 2013). Negative value is conveyed to MB g 
neurons in the heel and junction and to ab neurons at the base of 
the peduncle and the tip of the b lobe (Claridge-Chang et al.,  2009; Aso et al., 2010, 2012). In contrast, a much larger number 
of rewarding DA neurons project to approximately seven 
nonoverlapping zones in the horizontal b, b 
0 , and g lobes (Burke  et al., 2012; Liu et al., 2012). This clear zonal architecture of 
reinforcing neurons suggests that plastic valence-relevant KC 
synapses may lie adjacent to these reinforcing neurons. 
Furthermore, presumed downstream MB efferent neurons also 
have dendrites restricted to discrete zones on the MB lobes 
(Tanaka et al., 2008), consistent with memories being formed 
at KC-output neuron synapses. 
Long before the zonal DA neuron innervation of the MB was 
fully appreciated, experiments suggested that appetitive and 
aversive memories were independently processed and stored 
(Tempel et al., 1983). Subsequently, models were proposed 
that represented memories of opposite valence at distinct output 
synapses on the same odor-activated KCs or on separate KCs 
(Schwaerzel et al., 2003). Importantly, memory retrieval through </p>

<p>Neuron 79, 945-956, September 4, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 945 </p>

<p>Open access under CC BY-NC-ND license. </p>

<p>these modified KC-output synapses was predicted to guide 
either odor avoidance or approach behavior. A KC synapse-
specific representation of memories of opposing valence would 
dictate that it is not possible to functionally separate the 
retrieval of aversive and appetitive memories by disrupting 
KC-wide processes. We therefore tested these models by sys-
tematically blocking neurotransmission from subsets of the 
retrieval-relevant ab neurons. We found that aversive and 
appetitive memories can be distinguished in the ab KC popula-
tion, showing that opposing odor memories do not exclusively 
rely on overlapping KCs. Whereas output from the ab s neurons 
is required for aversive and appetitive memory retrieval, the ab 
core (ab c ) neurons are only critical for conditioned approach 
behavior. Higher-resolution anatomical analysis of the inner-
vation of reinforcing DA neurons suggests that valence-
specific asymmetry may be established during training. 
Furthermore, dendrites of KC-output neurons differentially 
innervate the MB in a similarly stratified manner. We therefore 
propose that aversive memories are retrieved and avoidance 
behavior triggered only from the ab surface (ab s ) neurons, 
whereas appetitive memories are retrieved and approach 
behavior is driven by efferent neurons that integrate across 
the ab ensemble. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>GAL4 Control of Subsets of MB ab Neurons 
Several studies have reported the importance of output from MB 
ab neurons for the retrieval of aversive and appetitive olfactory 
memories (Dubnau et al., 2001; McGuire et al., 2001; Schwaerzel  et al., 2003; Krashes et al., 2007; Krashes and Waddell, 2008;  Trannoy et al., 2011). However, genetic labeling reveals further 
anatomical segregation of the 1,000 ab neurons into at least 
ab posterior (ab p or pioneer), ab surface (ab s or early), and ab 
core (ab c or late) subsets that are sequentially born during devel-
opment (Ito et al., 1997; Lee et al., 1999; Lin et al., 2007; Tanaka  et al., 2008). We therefore investigated the role of these ab sub-
sets in memory retrieval. We first obtained, or identified, GAL4 
lines with expression that was restricted to ab subsets and veri-
fied their expression. Prior reports showed that the c739 GAL4 
(McGuire et al., 2001) labels ab neurons contributing to all three 
classes (Aso et al., 2009). In contrast, NP7175 expresses in ab c 
neurons and c708a in ab p neurons (Murthy et al., 2008; Tanaka  et al., 2008; Lin et al., 2007). Lastly, we identified the 0770 </p>

<p>GAL4 line from the InSITE collection (Gohl et al., 2011) with 
strong expression in ab s neurons and weaker expression in 
ab p neurons. We expressed a membrane-tethered GFP (uas-
mCD8::GFP) using the c739, 0770, NP7175, and c708a GAL4 
drivers and localized expression within the overall MB neurons 
using a LexAop-rCD2::RFP transgene driven by 247-LexA::VP16 
(Pitman et al., 2011). Projections of confocal stacks through the 
MBs revealed labeling within the MB in each of these 
GAL4 driver lines that is restricted to the respective ab subdivi-
sion (Figure 1 and S1 available online). In addition, the ab s and 
ab c lines have dendrites in the main calyx, whereas ab p neurons 
innervate only the accessory calyx (Lin et al., 2007; Tanaka et al.,  2008). </p>

<p>MB ab c Neurons Are Only Required for Appetitive 
Memory Retrieval 
We used 0770, NP7175, and c708a GAL4-driven expression of 
the dominant temperature-sensitive uas-shibire 
ts1 (shi 
ts1 ) trans-
gene (Kitamoto, 2001) to examine the role of neurotransmission 
from ab s , ab c , and ab p neurons in olfactory memory retrieval. In 
each experiment, we also compared the effect of blocking all MB 
ab neurons with c739. We first tested sucrose-reinforced appe-
titive memory (Krashes and Waddell, 2008). Flies were trained at 
the permissive 23 
C and ab subsets were blocked by shifting 
the flies to restrictive 33 
C 30 min before and during testing 
3 hr memory. Performance of c739;shi </p>

<p>ts1 </p>

<p>, 0770;shi 
ts1 , and </p>

<p>NP7175;shi 
ts1 flies, but not that of c708a;shi 
ts1 flies, was statisti-</p>

<p>cally different to shi 
ts1 and their respective GAL4 control flies 
(Figure 2A). Experiments at permissive 23 
C did not reveal signif-
icant differences in performance between the relevant groups 
(Figure S2A). Therefore, output from the ab s and ab c neurons is 
required for the retrieval of appetitive memory, whereas ab p 
neuron output is dispensable. 
We similarly tested the role of ab subsets in retrieval of electric-
shock-reinforced aversive memory. Memory performance 
of c739;shi 
ts1 and 0770;shi 
ts1 , but not NP7175;shi 
ts1 or </p>

<p>c708a;shi 
ts1 , flies was statistically different to that of shi 
ts1 and </p>

<p>their respective GAL4 control flies (Figure 2B). Importantly, con-
trol aversive experiments performed at 23 
C did not reveal 
significant differences between the relevant groups (Figure S2B). 
Therefore, these data reveal that output from the ab s neurons is 
required for the retrieval of aversive memory, whereas the ab c 
and ab p neurons are dispensable, implying a possible appetitive 
memory-specific role for ab c neurons. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Anatomically Distinct Subsets of MB ab Neurons </p>

<p>(A) Model of the left fly MB outlining the different subsets of intrinsic ab KCs within the lobes. 
(B-E) Projection views of confocal stacks at the level of the left MB lobes from c739-ab scp (B), 0770-ab s (C), NP7175-ab c (D), and c708a-ab p (E) flies driving 
mCD8::GFP (green). In all panels, the overall MB is labeled with rCD2::RFP (magenta). The inset shows a horizontal cross-section through the vertical collateral at 
the level of the dashed line in (A). Scale bar represents 20 mm. See also Figure S1. </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>



<p>Since odors are represented as activation of sparse collections 
of MB neurons (Honegger et al., 2011), it is conceivable that 
certain odor pairs might be biased in their odor representations 
in particular ab subsets. The reciprocal nature of the conditioning 
assays should account for this caveat. Nevertheless, we also 
tested the effect of ab subset block when flies were appetitively 
or aversively trained using ethyl butyrate and isoamyl acetate-
two odors shown to activate ab c neurons (Murthy et al., 2008). 
These experiments again revealed a role for ab s and ab c in 
appetitive memory but only ab s in aversive memory (Figures 2C 
and 2D). The ab p neurons remained dispensable. The appetitive 
retrieval defect is unlikely to result from defective odor perception 
since flies with blocked ab c neurons (NP7175;shi </p>

<p>ts1 </p>

<p>) exhibit 
normal aversive memory. Furthermore, control experiments 
demonstrated that c739;shi 
ts1 and 0770;shi 
ts1 exhibit normal </p>

<p>olfactory acuity at the restrictive temperature (Table S1). 
We further challenged a valence-specific role for ab neuron 
subsets using additional genetic approaches. We first confirmed 
that ab s neurons are required for both appetitive and aversive 
memory retrieval using NP5286, another GAL4 line with strong 
expression in ab s neurons and weaker expression in ab p neurons 
(Figures 3A and S1F; Tanaka et al., 2008). Appetitive and aver-
sive memory performance of NP5286;shi 
ts1 flies was statistically </p>

<p>different to that of shi 
ts1 and GAL4 control flies (Figures 3E and </p>

<p>3F). No statistical differences were apparent when experiments </p>

<p>were performed at permissive 23 
C (Figure S3) and the 
NP5286;shi 
ts1 flies exhibit normal olfactory acuity at the restric-
tive temperature (Table S1). 
We next challenged an appetitive memory-specific role for 
ab c neurons using an intersectional genetic strategy. Combining 
a ChaGAL80 transgene with c739 removes expression in the ab s 
and ab p neurons from the c739-labeled ab population and 
leaves robust expression in ab c neurons (Figures 3B and 
S1G). We again trained flies at the permissive temperature 
and blocked ab c during retrieval. Similar to the analysis with 
NP7175;shi </p>

<p>ts1 </p>

<p>flies, appetitive memory performance of 
c739;ChaGAL80/shi 
ts1 flies was impaired, being statistically 
different to the relevant control groups (Figure 3E). Moreover, 
the c739 disruptive effect on aversive memory was abolished 
with ChaGAL80, consistent with removal of ab s expression 
from c739 (Figure 3F). Control experiments at 23 
C did not 
reveal significant differences between the relevant groups 
(Figure S3). 
A role for ab c in memory consolidation has been reported 
(Huang et al., 2012). Blocking NP6024-labeled ab c neurons for 
several hours after training disrupted appetitive and aversive 
memory consolidation, whereas blocking NP7175-labeled neu-
rons only impaired aversive memory consolidation (Huang  et al., 2012). Although others defined the ab neurons labeled in 
NP6024 as inner and outer ab c neurons (Tanaka et al., 2008; </p>

<p>Figure 2. Functional Subdivision of ab Neu-
rons in 3 hr Memory Retrieval </p>

<p>Flies were trained at the permissive 23 
C and ab </p>

<p>subsets blocked by shifting the flies to restrictive 
33 
C 30 min before and during testing 3 hr </p>

<p>memory (schematic). 
(A) ab c and ab s neurons are required for retrieval of 
3 hr appetitive memory. Blocking transmission 
from c739, 0770, and NP7175 neurons during 
testing impaired appetitive memory (all p &lt; 0.001), 
whereas blocking c708a neurons had no effect 
(p = 0.10). 
(B) ab c neurons are not required for retrieval of 
aversive memory. Blocking transmission from 
c739 and 0770 neurons during testing impaired 
aversive memory (both p &lt; 0.001), whereas 
blocking NP7175 or c708a neurons had no 
effect (p &gt; 0.9 and p &gt; 0.5). Odors used in (A) 
and (B) are 4-methylcyclohexanol (MCH) and 
3-octanol (OCT). 
(C and D) Repeat of experiments in (A) and (B) 
using isoamyl acetate (IAA) and ethyl butyrate (EB) 
as odors. The requirement for output from the ab s 
and ab c neurons for the retrieval of 3 hr appetitive 
memory was reproduced, whereas ab p neuron 
output remained dispensable. (C) Blocking trans-
mission from c739, 0770, and NP7175 neurons 
during testing impaired appetitive memory (all p &lt; 
0.001), whereas blocking c708a neurons had no 
effect (p &gt; 0.5). (D) Blocking transmission from 
c739 and 0770 neurons during testing impaired 
aversive memory (p &lt; 0.01 and p &lt; 0.001), whereas 
blocking NP7175 or c708a neurons had no effect 
(p &gt; 0.4 and p &gt; 0.2). An asterisk denotes significant difference between marked group and the relevant genetic controls (all p &lt; 0.01, ANOVA). The wild-type group 
corresponds to pooled data from independent experiments and all data are represented as the mean ± SEM. See also Figures S1, S2, S4, and S7 and Table S1. </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>

<p>Neuron 79, 945-956, September 4, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 947 </p>

<p>Huang et al., 2012), our anatomical analysis revealed that outer 
ab c neurons occupy the area of the vertical MB lobe that is 
anatomically indistinguishable from that containing the ab s neu-
rons (Figures 3A-3D). Furthermore, blocking output during 
retrieval in NP6024;shi 
ts1 flies significantly impaired both appeti-
tive and aversive memory (Figures 3E and 3F), consistent with 
NP6024 expressing in ab c and ab s neurons. Control experiments 
at the permissive temperature did not reveal significant differ-</p>

<p>ences between the relevant groups (Figure S3) and the 
NP6024;shi 
ts1 flies exhibit normal olfactory acuity (Table S1). 
Perhaps more importantly, a consolidation effect cannot 
account for our appetitive memory retrieval-specific function 
because the retrieval role for ab c is not time dependent. As 
shown for 3 hr memory (Figures 2A and 2C), blocking NP7175 
ab c neurons during retrieval also impaired appetitive 24 hr LTM 
(Figure S4A), whereas it did not impair aversive 24 hr LTM (Huang </p>

<p>Figure 3. ab c Neurons Only Contribute to Appetitive Memory Expression </p>

<p>(A-C) Projection views of confocal stacks at the level of the left MB lobes from ab subset GAL4 lines driving mCD8::GFP (green). The inset shows a cross-section 
through the vertical collateral at the level of the dashed line in Figure 1A. The overall MB is labeled with rCD2::RFP (magenta). Scale bar represents 20 mm. (A) 
NP5286 ab s neurons. (B) ChaGAL80 inhibits GAL4 in c739 labeled ab s neurons and leaves expression in ab c neurons. (C) NP6024 labels ab c neurons and inner ab s 
neurons. 
(D) Illustration of a cross-section of the a lobe neurons labeled by NP5286-ab s , c739;ChaGAL80-ab c , and NP6024-ab sc GAL4 lines. 
(E) Flies were trained at the permissive 23 
C and ab subsets were blocked by shifting the flies to restrictive 33 
C 30 min before and during testing 3 hr memory </p>

<p>(schematic). The ab s and ab c neurons are required for 3 hr appetitive memory retrieval. Blocking transmission from NP5286, c739;ChaGAL80, or NP6024 neurons 
during testing impaired appetitive memory (p &lt; 0.01). 
(F) The ab s but not the ab c neurons are required for 3 hr aversive memory retrieval. Blocking transmission from NP5286 or NP6024 neurons during testing impaired 
aversive memory (both p &lt; 0.05), whereas suppressing ab s expression in c739 reversed the 3 hr aversive memory retrieval phenotype. Blocking c739;ChaGAL80 
neuron output did not impair aversive memory retrieval (p = 0.9). An asterisk denotes significant difference between marked group and the relevant genetic 
controls (all p &lt; 0.05, ANOVA). Odors used are OCT and MCH. Data are represented as mean ± SEM. See also Figure S3. </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>



<p>et al., 2012). We therefore conclude that ab c have a unique role in 
appetitive memory retrieval. </p>

<p>Odors Activate MB ab s and ab c but Inhibit ab p Neurons 
As a final step to rule out odor-specific effects, we used live Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>imaging to determine whether the four odors used in condition-
ing activate ab subsets. We expressed a uas-GCaMP5 trans-
gene and live-imaged odor-evoked changes in fluorescence in 
a cross-section of the a axons in the vertical lobe tip. Each 
odor evoked a robust, odor-specific positive response in ab scp , 
ab s , and ab c neurons labeled by c739, 0770, and NP7175 (Fig-
ures 4A and 4B). In contrast, the odors evoked a marked reduc-
tion of GCaMP5 fluorescence in c708a ab p neurons (Fig-
ure 4A). We also observed odor-specific responses in ab s , ab c , </p>

<p>Figure 4. Odors Evoke Responses in All ab 
Neuron Subsets </p>

<p>(A) The four odors used in conditioning evoke a 
robust increase in GCaMP5 fluorescence in ab s 
and ab c neurons and a decrease in ab p neurons of 
naive flies. Time courses of odor-evoked GCaMP5 
responses (DF/F) collected at the level of the tip of 
the MB a-lobe represented by the panels shown in 
(B). Responses from individual flies are shown as 
light traces and the average responses from all 
flies in bold traces. The ab c and ab s KCs were 
activated by all odors, whereas ab p KCs were 
inhibited by all odors used in this study. n = 4-5. 
(B) Anatomical segregation and distribution of 
odor-evoked responses. Pseudocolored activity 
maps of odor responses overlaid on grayscale 
images of baseline fluorescence. The four odors 
used elicit different patterns of activation in each 
KC subgroup. Scale bar represents 5 mm. See also 
Figure S5. </p>

<p>and ab sc neurons labeled by NP5286, 
c739;ChaGAL80, and NP6024, respec-
tively (Figure S5). Therefore, the odors 
employed in conditioning activate the 
functionally critical ab s and ab c neurons 
in an odor-specific manner, whereas 
they inhibit the dispensable ab p neurons. </p>

<p>MB ab c Are Required for Retrieval 
in a Differential Aversive Learning 
Paradigm 
Appetitive memories are more stable 
than aversive memories formed after a 
single training session (Tempel et al.,  1983; Krashes and Waddell, 2008;  Colomb et al., 2009). To rule out that the 
role of ab c neurons reflected a temporally 
restricted anatomical difference between 
appetitive versus aversive memory pro-
cessing, we employed a differential aver-
sive conditioning paradigm (Yin et al.,  2009). In this assay, flies are trained by 
sequential exposure to one odor X 
without reinforcement (X 0 ), odor Y with a 60 V shock (Y 60 ), and 
then odor Z with 30 V (Z 30 ) (Figure 5A). They are then tested 
30 min after training for relative choice between Y 60 and Z 30 or 
absolute choice between X 0 and Y 60 . We speculated that 
retrieval of the relative choice memory between Y 60 and Z 30 
odors might involve an approach component to odor Z 30 , similar 
to retrieval of appetitive memory. 
We first investigated this notion by determining whether the 
odor coupled with lesser voltage (Z 30 ) was coded as an appeti-
tive memory. We expressed shi 
ts1 in a recently described subset </p>

<p>of rewarding dopaminergic neurons with 0104-GAL4 (Burke  et al., 2012) and blocked them during acquisition in the differen-
tial aversive paradigm (X 0 -Y 60 -Z 30 ). Flies were shifted to 33 
C for 
30 min prior to and during training and then returned to 23 
C and </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>

<p>Neuron 79, 945-956, September 4, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 949 </p>

<p>tested for 30 min choice memory. Strikingly, performance of 
0104/shi 
ts1 flies was statistically different to shi 
ts1 and 0104 con-</p>

<p>trol flies when tested for relative Y 60 versus Z 30 memory (Fig-
ure 5B) but was not different to controls when tested for absolute 
X 0 versus Y 60 memory (Figure 5C). No differences were apparent 
between the relevant groups when flies were trained and tested 
at the permissive temperature for relative choice (Figure 5D). 
Therefore, in this paradigm only, learning the odor presented 
with the relatively lesser voltage (Z 30 ) requires rewarding rein-
forcement. The Z 30 memory can therefore be considered to be 
appetitive. 
We next tested whether retrieval of relative Y 60 versus Z 30 
memory required the ab c neurons. Flies were trained at permis-
sive 23 
C and were shifted to 33 
C to block ab c neurons during </p>

<p>Figure 5. Output from ab c Neurons Is 
Required for Relative Aversive Choice </p>

<p>(A) Schematic of the absolute and relative aversive 
training paradigm. 
(B-D) Relative but not absolute aversive condi-
tioning requires output from rewarding DA neu-
rons during acquisition. (B) Blocking transmission 
from 0104 neurons during training impaired 30 min 
Y 60 versus Z 30 relative choice memory (p &lt; 0.001). 
(C) Blocking 0104 DA neurons during training did 
not disrupt 30 min X 0 versus Y 60 absolute choice 
memory (p &gt; 0.05). (D) No differences were 
apparent when flies were trained and tested for 
relative Y 60 versus Z 30 choice memory at permis-
sive 23 
C (p &gt; 0.9). </p>

<p>(E-H) Relative but not absolute choice 
memory retrieval requires output from ab c neu-
rons. (E) Blocking output from NP7175 ab c , 
c739;ChaGAL80 ab c , or 0770 ab s neurons during 
retrieval impaired 30 min Y 60 versus Z 30 relative 
choice memory (p &lt; 0.001). (F) No statistical dif-
ferences were apparent when flies were trained 
and tested for relative Y 60 versus Z 30 choice 
memory at permissive 23 
C (p &gt; 0.05). (G) Block-</p>

<p>ing transmission from 0770 ab s (p &lt; 0.01) but not 
NP7175 ab c or c739;ChaGAL80 ab c (both p &gt; 0.5) 
impaired X 0 versus Y 60 absolute choice memory. 
(H) No statistical differences were evident be-
tween 0770 flies trained and tested for absolute X 0 
versus Y 60 choice memory at permissive 23 
C (p &gt; </p>

<p>0.05). An asterisk denotes significant difference 
between marked group and the relevant controls 
(all p &lt; 0.05, ANOVA). Odors used are OCT, MCH, 
and IAA. Data are represented as mean ± SEM. </p>

<p>retrieval of 30 min choice memory. As 
expected, blocking NP7175;shi 
ts1 neuron </p>

<p>output during retrieval of relative Y 60 
versus Z 30 memory revealed a significant 
defect (Figure 5E). No significant differ-
ences were apparent between the 
relevant groups at the permissive temper-
ature (Figure 5F). In contrast, ab c neuron 
block did not significantly impair expres-
sion of absolute X 0 and Y 60 choice mem-
ory (Figure 5G). We also tested the role 
for ab c neurons using the c739;ChaGAL80 approach of manipu-
lating these neurons. Like NP7175 neurons, blocking c739;Cha-
GAL80 ab c neurons significantly disrupted retrieval of relative Y 60 
versus Z 30 choice memory (Figure 5E) but not absolute X 0 and Y 60 
choice (Figure 5G). Again, no significant differences were 
observed in control experiments at the permissive temperature 
(Figure 5F). We also tested the requirement of ab s neurons in 
this paradigm. Consistent with previous experiments with aver-
sive and appetitive reinforcement (Figure 2), blocking 0770 ab s 
neurons significantly disrupted retrieval of relative Y 60 versus 
Z 30 choice (Figure 5E) and absolute X 0 and Y 60 choice memory 
(Figure 5G). Again, no significant differences were observed in 
permissive temperature control experiments (Figures 5F and 
5H). We conclude from this diverse collection of appetitive </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>



<p>memory experiments that the ab c neurons provide critical synap-
tic input for the expression of conditioned approach behavior. </p>

<p>Reinforcing and Output Neurons Innervate Consistent 
Strata in the MB Lobes 
We reasoned that the approach-specific role for ab c might be re-
flected in the anatomy of reinforcing and output neurons within 
the MB lobes. We therefore investigated at higher resolution 
the innervation patterns within the MB of positive and negative 
reinforcing DA neurons and described output neurons. </p>

<p>Rewarding DA neurons reside in the protocerebral anterior 
medial (PAM) cluster and project to a number of nonoverlap-
ping zones in the horizontal b, b 
0 , and g lobes (Liu et al., 
2012; Burke et al., 2012). PAM DA neurons labeled by 
R58E02 (Liu et al., 2012) innervate the b s and b c regions (Fig-
ure S6), but the individual neurons are difficult to discern. By 
visually screening the InSITE collection, we identified the 
0279 GAL4 line that labels 15 PAM neurons that bilaterally 
innervate the b 1 and b 2 regions of the medial b lobe (Figure 6A). 
We name these neurons MB-M8, in accordance with existing </p>

<p>Figure 6. Reinforcing DA Neurons and MB 
Efferent Neurons Differentially Innervate 
ab Layers </p>

<p>(A-D) Rewarding DA input neurons from the PAM 
cluster ramify throughout the b lobe. (A) Frontal 
projection view of a confocal stack of the brain 
from a fly expressing mCD8::GFP (black) driven by 
0279 GAL4. The MB is labeled with rCD2::RFP 
(red). Scale bar represents 50 mm. The 0279 
labeled neurons ramify throughout the b lobe 
(inset, magnified sagittal section through the b 
lobe at the level of the dashed black line in A; scale 
bar represents 10 mm). (B) uas-dTrpA1-mediated 
activation of 0279 neurons contingent with odor 
presentation (2 min at 33 
C, red) forms robust </p>

<p>appetitive olfactory memory (ANOVA between the 
relevant control groups, p &lt; 0.001, denoted by an 
asterisk). Odors used are OCT and MCH. Data are 
represented as mean ± SEM. (C) 0279 neurons 
(GFP/green) colocalize with tyrosine hydroxylase 
immunoreactivity (TH-ir, magenta), suggesting 
they are dopaminergic. (D) 0279 DA neurons are 
presynaptic to the ipsilateral b 1 and contralateral 
b 2 lobe (DSyd1::GFP, green). DenMark (magenta) 
labels the postsynaptic compartment in the 
superior lateral protocerebrum. Scale bar repre-
sents 20 mm. 
(E and F) Aversive DA input neurons mostly 
innervate the ab surface. (E) Single frontal section 
(0.5 mm) of the left MB (labeled with rCD2::RFP, 
magenta) at the level of the heel/peduncle transi-
tion (dashed box in inset) showing innervation of 
the aversive reinforcing and appetitive motiva-
tional control MB-MP1 neurons, labeled by 
c061;MBGAL80-driven mCD8::GFP (green). MB-
MP1 neurons do not innervate the region of the 
distal peduncle that is occupied by ab c KCs. Scale 
bar represents 10 mm. (F) Single sagittal section 
(0.5 mm) through the left MB (labeled with 
rCD2::RFP, magenta) at the level of the horizontal 
lobe tips (dashed line in inset) showing MB-M3 
neurons labeled by NP5272-driven mCD8::GFP 
(green). Aversive reinforcing MB-M3 neurons only 
innervate the surface and not the core of the b lobe 
tip (white dashed circles). Scale bar represents 
10 mm. 
(G) Single horizontal section (0.5 mm) of the left MB 
(labeled with rCD2::RFP, magenta) through the 
vertical lobe tips (at the level of the dashed line in 
inset) showing MB-V3-nonselective output neurons labeled by 12-244-driven mCD8::GFP (green). MB-V3 ramifies across the ab c and ab s layers in the a lobe tip. 
(H) Single horizontal section (0.5 mm) of the left MB (labeled with rCD2::RFP, magenta) through the vertical lobe stalk (at the level of the dashed line in inset) 
showing MB-V2a-aversive output neurons labeled by NP2492-driven mCD8::GFP (green). MB-V2a more densely innervates the a surface than a core. Scale bar 
represents 10 mm. (E-H) Each inset shows the expression pattern of the respective GAL4 line (GFP/green) within the left MB lobes, labeled with rCD2::RFP 
(magenta). Scale bar represents 20 mm. See also Figure S6. </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>

<p>Neuron 79, 945-956, September 4, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 951 </p>

<p>MB extrinsic cell nomenclature (Tanaka et al., 2008). A cross-
section through the b lobe reveals that MB-M8 ramify 
throughout the b s and b c regions (Figure 6A, inset). We 
confirmed that the MB-M8 neurons are positively reinforcing 
by stimulating them during odor presentation, achieved by 
expressing uas-dTrpA1 with 0279 GAL4. MB-M8 activation 
with odor exposure is sufficient to induce robust appetitive 
memory (Figure 6B). Lastly, colocalizing GFP expression with 
tyrosine hydroxylase immunoreactivity (TH-ir) verified that 
MB-M8 neurons are dopaminergic (Figure 6C) and coex-
pression of the neural compartment markers DenMark and 
DSyd1::GFP reveals that arbors throughout the b s and b c 
regions of the MB lobe are presynaptic (Figure 6D). 
Negative value can be conveyed by the MB-MP1 and MB-
MV1 DA neurons in the protocerebral posterior lateral (PPL) 1 
cluster and by the MB-M3 neurons in the PAM cluster (Aso 
et al., 2012). MB-MV1 only innervates the proximal a 
0 region 
and g lobe, MB-MP1 the heel of g, and base of the peduncle 
(Figure 6E), and MB-M3 ramifies in the tip of the b lobe (Fig-
ure 6F). In contrast to the positively reinforcing MB-M8 neurons, 
cross-sections through the relevant parts of the MB revealed 
that the aversive reinforcing MB-M3 and MB-MP1 DA neurons 
preferentially arborize in the ab s layer and exhibit no or much 
weaker innervation of ab c . 
Differential innervation of the ab neuron subsets is also evident 
with behaviorally relevant MB efferent neurons. Two indepen-
dent recent studies have determined that MB-V3 neurons that 
innervate the tip of the a lobe are required for either appetitive 
(P.Y. Plaç ais and T. Preat, personal communication) or aversive 
memory (Pai et al., 2013). A cross-section view through the tip of 
the a lobe reveals MB-V3 arbors throughout the b s and b c regions 
(Figure 6G). In contrast, dendrites of the aversive memory-spe-
cific MB-V2a output neurons (Sé journé et al., 2011) are most pro-
nounced in the a s (Figure 6H). 
Therefore, the fine anatomy of reinforcing DA neurons and 
output neurons supports our observed functional difference 
between ab s and ab c MB neurons. Furthermore, their architec-
ture indicates that the stratified functional asymmetry in the ab 
ensemble may be established by reinforcement during training, 
whereas differential pooling of outputs is critical for the expres-
sion of conditioned avoidance or approach. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>When faced with a choice, animals must select the appropriate 
behavioral response. Learning provides animals the predictive 
benefit of prior experience and allows researchers to influence 
behavioral outcomes. After olfactory learning, fruit flies are pro-
vided with a simple binary choice in the T-maze. Aversively 
trained flies preferentially avoid the conditioned odor, whereas 
appetitively conditioned flies approach it. A major goal of the 
field is to understand the neural mechanisms through which 
the fly selects the appropriate direction. 
In mammals, mitral cells take olfactory information direct from 
the olfactory bulb to the amygdala and the perirhinal, entorhinal, 
and piriform cortices (Davis 2004; Wilson and Mainen, 2006). In 
doing so, odor information is segregated into different streams, 
allowing it to be associated with other modalities and emotionally </p>

<p>salient events. In contrast, most olfactory projection neurons in 
the fly innervate the MB calyx and lateral horn or only the lateral 
horn (Wong et al., 2002; Jefferis et al., 2007). The lateral horn has 
mostly been ascribed the role of mediating innate responses to 
odors (Heimbeck et al., 2001; Suh et al., 2004; Sachse et al.,  2007), leaving the MB to fulfill the potential roles of the mamma-
lian cortices. 
Although morphological and functional subdivision of the ab, 
a 
0 b 
0 , and g classes of MB neuron has been reported (Crittenden  et al., 1998; Zars et al., 2000; Yu et al., 2006; Krashes et al., 2007;  Wang et al., 2008; Akalal et al., 2010; Trannoy et al., 2011; Qin  et al., 2012; Tanaka et al., 2008), until now a valence-restricted 
role has been elusive. In this study, we investigated the func-
tional correlates of substructure within the ab population. We 
identified an appetitive memory-specific role for the ab c neurons. 
Whereas blocking output from the ab s neurons impaired aversive 
and appetitive memory retrieval, blocking ab c neurons produced 
only an appetitive memory defect. These behavioral results, 
taken with functional imaging of odor-evoked activity, suggest 
that beyond the ab, a 
0 b 
0 , and g subdivision, odors are repre-
sented as separate streams in subsets of MB ab neurons. These 
parallel information streams within ab permit opposing value to 
be differentially assigned to the same odor. Training therefore 
tunes the odor-activated ab c and ab s KCs so that distinct popu-
lations differentially drive downstream circuits to generate 
aversive or appetitive behaviors. Such a dynamic interaction 
between appetitive and aversive circuits that is altered by 
learning is reminiscent of that described between the primate 
amygdala and orbitofrontal cortex (Barberini et al., 2012). It will 
be important to determine the physiological consequences of 
appetitive and aversive conditioning on the ab c and ab s neurons. 
Positively and negatively reinforced olfactory learning in rats 
produced bidirectional plasticity of neurons in the basolateral 
amygdala (Motanis et al., 2012). 
The ab p neurons, which do not receive direct olfactory input 
from projection neurons in the calyx (Tanaka et al., 2008), are 
dispensable for aversive and appetitive 3 hr memory and for 
24 hr appetitive memory. The ab p neurons were reported to be 
structurally linked to dorsal anterior lateral (DAL) neurons and 
both DAL and ab p neurons were shown to be required for long-
term aversive memory retrieval (Chen et al., 2012; Pai et al.,  2013). We found that, like ab p neurons, DAL neurons are not 
required for appetitive long-term memory retrieval (Figures 
S4C-S4E), consistent with recent results from others (Hirano  et al., 2013). In addition, the ab p neurons were inhibited by 
odor exposure, which may reflect cross-modal inhibition within 
the KC population. 
Observing a role for the ab c neurons in the relative aversive 
paradigm argues against the different requirement for ab c neu-
rons in the routine shock-reinforced aversive and sugar-
reinforced appetitive assays being due to different timescales 
of memory processing. In addition, we observed a pronounced 
role for ab c neurons in retrieval of 24 hr appetitive LTM, whereas 
others have reported that ab c neurons are not required for the 
retrieval of 24 hr aversive LTM (Huang et al., 2012). Nevertheless, 
time and the methods of conditioning may be important vari-
ables. Although appetitive and aversive memory retrieval 
requires output from the ab ensemble at 3 hr and 24 hr after </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>



<p>conditioning (McGuire et al., 2001; Isabel et al., 2004; Krashes  et al., 2007, 2009; Trannoy et al., 2011), ab neurons were shown 
to be dispensable for 2 hr appetitive memory retrieval (Trannoy  et al., 2011). Instead, appetitive retrieval required g neuron 
output at this earlier point (Trannoy et al., 2011). Our experiments 
were generally supportive of the g-then-ab neuron model but 
revealed a slightly different temporal relationship. The ab neu-
rons were dispensable for memory retrieved 30 min after training 
but were essential for 2 hr and 3 hr memory after training (Figures 
2 and S7). An early role for g neurons is further supported by the 
importance of reinforcing DA input to the g neurons for aversive 
memory formation (Qin et al., 2012). It will be interesting to deter-
mine whether there is a stratified representation of valence within 
the g neuron population. 
Finding an appetitive memory-specific role for ab c neurons 
suggests that the simplest model in which each odor-activated 
KC has plastic output synapses driving either approach or avoid-
ance (Schwaerzel et al., 2003) appears incorrect. Such a KC 
output synapse-specific organization dictates that it would not 
be possible to functionally segregate aversive and appetitive 
memory by blocking KC-wide output. We however found a 
specific role for the ab c neurons in conditioned approach that 
supports the alternative model of partially nonoverlapping 
KC representations of aversive and appetitive memories 
(Schwaerzel et al., 2003). The anatomy of the presynaptic termi-
nals of reinforcing DA neurons in the MB lobes suggests that the 
functional asymmetry in ab could be established during training 
in which ab c only receive appetitive reinforcement. Rewarding 
DA neurons that innervate the b lobe tip ramify throughout the 
b s and b c , whereas aversive reinforcing DA neurons appear 
restricted to the ab s . Consistent with this organization of memory 
formation, aversive MB-V2a output neurons (Sé journé et al.,  2011) have dendrites biased toward a s , whereas the dendrites 
of aversive (Pai et al., 2013) or appetitive (P.Y. Plaç ais and 
T. Preat personal communication) MB-V3 output neurons are 
broadly distributed throughout the a lobe tip. We therefore pro-
pose a model that learned odor aversion is driven by ab s neu-
rons, whereas learned approach comes from pooling inputs 
from the ab s and ab c neurons (Figure 7). 
Another property that distinguishes appetitive from aversive 
memory retrieval is state dependence; flies only efficiently 
express appetitive memory if they are hungry (Krashes and  Waddell, 2008). Prior work has shown that the dopaminergic 
MB-MP1 neurons are also critical for this level of control 
(Krashes et al., 2009). Since the MB-MP1 neurons more densely 
innervate the ab s than ab c , it would seem that satiety state differ-
entially tunes the respective drive from parts of the ab ensemble 
to promote or inhibit appetitive memory retrieval. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Fly Strains 
Fly stocks were raised on standard cornmeal food at 25 
C and 40%-50% </p>

<p>relative humidity. The wild-type Drosophila strain used in this study is 
Canton-S. The uas-mCD8::GFP, 247-LexA::VP16 and LexAop-rCD2::RFP 
flies are described in Lee and Luo (1999) and Pitman et al. (2011). The uas-
DenMark and uas-DSyd1::GFP are described in Nicolaï et al. (2010) and 
Owald et al. (2010). The c739, NP7175, c708a, NP2492, NP5272, NP5286, 
NP6024, 0104, G0431, and c739;ChaGAL80 flies are described in McGuire </p>

<p>et al. (2001), Tanaka et al. (2008), Burke et al. (2012), Chen et al. (2012), Kita-
moto (2002), Sé journé et al. (2011), and Aso et al. (2012). The 0770, 0279, 
0104, and 0006 flies, more correctly named PBac(IT.GAL4)0770, 
PBac(IT.GAL4)0279, PBac(IT.GAL4)0104, and PBac(IT.GAL4)0006, were 
generated and initially characterized by Marion Sillies and Daryl Gohl as 
part of the InSITE collection (Gohl et al., 2011). The 12-244 flies were obtained 
from Ulrike Heberlein. The MB-MP1 expressing c061:MBGAL80 is described 
in Krashes et al. (2009). We used flies carrying the uas-shi 
ts1 transgene (Kita-</p>

<p>moto, 2001) on the third chromosome. We generated flies expressing shi 
ts1 in </p>

<p>MB ab subsets, DA neurons, or DAL neurons by crossing uas-shi 
ts1 females </p>

<p>to homozygous c739, 0770, c739;ChaGAL80, NP5286, 0104, 0006, or G0431 
males. NP7175, c708a, and NP6024 reside on the X chromosome. Therefore, 
NP7175, NP6024, and c708a females were crossed to uas-shi 
ts1 males. Het-</p>

<p>erozygote uas-shi 
ts1 /+ controls were generated by crossing uas-shi </p>

<p>ts1 </p>

<p>females to wild-type males. Heterozygote GAL4/+ controls were generated 
by crossing GAL4 males to wild-type females. We generated flies expressing 
dTrpA1 in 0279 neurons by crossing uas-dTrpA1 females to homozygous 
0279 males. Heterozygote uas-dTrpA1/+ controls were generated by 
crossing uas-dTrpA1/+ females to wild-type males. Heterozygote GAL4/+ 
controls were generated by crossing GAL4 males to wild-type females. 
GCaMP5G is described in Akerboom et al. (2012) and was subcloned into 
pUAST by David Owald. Transgenic flies were raised commercially 
(BestGene). </p>

<p>Behavioral Analysis 
Mixed sex populations of 4-to 8-day-old flies raised at 25 
C were tested </p>

<p>together in all behavior experiments. Appetitive memory was assayed as 
described in Krashes and Waddell (2008) with the following modifications. 
Groups of 100 flies were food-deprived for 18-22 hr before training in a 
25 ml vial, containing 1% agar and a 20 3 60 mm piece of filter paper. To 
test 30 min, 2 hr, or 3 hr memory, we trained flies and stored them in the 
same vials used for starvation until testing. For 24 hr memory, flies were 
trained and immediately transferred for 1 hr into a standard cornmeal/agar 
food vial. They were then transferred into food-deprivation vials for 23 hr until 
testing. 
Memory implantation experiments using uas-dTrpA1-mediated neural acti-
vation were performed as described in Burke et al. (2012). We starved 8-to 
11-day-old flies raised at 18 
C and presented them with one odor at the </p>

<p>permissive 23 
C for 2 min in filter paper-lined tubes. They were then trans-</p>

<p>ferred into a new prewarmed filter paper-lined tube and immediately presented 
with a second odor at restrictive 33 
C for 2 min. Flies were then returned to </p>

<p>23 
C and tested for immediate memory. </p>

<p>Aversive memory was assayed as described in Tully and Quinn (1985) with 
some modifications. Groups of 100 flies were housed for 18-20 hr before 
training in a 25 ml vial containing standard cornmeal/agar food and a 20 3 
60 mm piece of filter paper. Reinforcement was 120 V. Relative aversive choice 
experiments (Figure 5) were performed as described in Yin et al. (2009) with 
some modifications. Flies were prepared as above for aversive memory and 
were conditioned as follows: 1 min odor X without reinforcement, 45 s fresh 
air, 1 min odor Y with 12 60 V shocks at 5 s interstimulus interval (ISI), 45 s fresh 
air, and 1 min odor Z with 12 30 V shocks at 5 s ISI. 
Memory performance was tested by allowing the flies 2 min to choose 
between the odors presented during training. Performance index (PI) was 
calculated as the number of flies approaching (appetitive memory) or avoiding 
(aversive memory) the conditioned odor minus the number of flies going the 
other direction, divided by the total number of flies in the experiment. A single 
PI value is the average score from flies of the identical genotype tested with the 
reciprocal reinforced/nonreinforced odor combination. 
Odor acuity was performed as described in Burke et al. (2012). Fed flies were 
transferred to 33 
C 30 min before a 2 min test of odor avoidance. </p>

<p>Odors used in conditioning and for acuity controls were 3-octanol (6 ml in 
8 ml mineral oil) with 4-methylcyclohexanol (7 ml in 8 ml mineral oil) or isoamyl 
acetate (16 ml in 8 ml mineral oil) with ethyl butyrate (5 ml in 8 ml mineral oil). 
Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">PRISM</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>). 
Overall ANOVA was followed by planned pairwise comparisons between the 
relevant groups with a Tukey honestly significant difference HSD post hoc 
test. Unless stated otherwise, all experiments are n R 8. </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>

<p>Neuron 79, 945-956, September 4, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 953 </p>

<p>Imaging 
To visualize native GFP or mRFP, we collected adult flies 4-6 days after 
eclosion and brains were dissected in ice-cold 4% paraformaldehyde solu-
tion in PBS (1.86 mM NaH 2 PO 4 , 8.41 mM Na 2 HPO 4 , and 175 mM NaCl) 
and fixed for an additional 60 min at room temperature. Samples were 
then washed 3 3 10 min with PBS containing 0.1% Triton X-100 (PBT) 
and 2 3 10 min in PBS before mounting in Vectashield (Vector Labs). 
Imaging was performed on Leica TCS SP5 X. The resolution of the image 
stack was 1,024 3 1,024 with 0.5 mm step size and a frame average of 4. 
Images were processed in <rs id="software-2" type="software">AMIRA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">5.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Mercury Systems</rs>). The immuno-
staining against tyrosine hydroxylase and GFP was performed as described 
previously in Burke et al. (2012). </p>

<p>Calcium Imaging 
GCaMP5 signals were imaged using two-photon microscopy. Adult flies were 
fixed to a piece of aluminum foil secured to a perfusion chamber (P-1, Harvard 
Technologies) using dental floss and an Electra Waxer (Almore International). 
Cuticle, trachea, and fat bodies obscuring the mushroom body were removed 
and the exposed brain was superfused with saline (5 mM TES, 103 mM NaCl, 
3 mM KCl, 1.5 mM CaCl 2 , 4 mM MgCl 2 , 26 mM NaHCO 3 , 1 mM NaH 2 PO 4 , 
8 mM trehalose, 10 mM glucose [pH 7.3], bubbled with 95% oxygen, 5% 
carbon dioxide) using a perfusion pump (Watson-Marlow). 
Fluorescence was excited using 140 fs pulses centered on 910 nm gener-
ated by a Ti-sapphire laser (Chameleon Ultra II, Coherent), attenuated by a 
Pockels cell (Conoptics 302RM). Brains were imaged using a Movable </p>

<p>Figure 7. Model Illustrating the Differential Role of ab Surface and Core Neurons in Conditioned Approach and Aversion </p>

<p>(A) During appetitive conditioning, rewarding dopaminergic MB-M8 neurons (green) from the PAM cluster reinforces odor-activated synapses of ab s (blue) and 
ab c (black) neurons in the b 1 and b 2 zones of the horizontal b lobe. 
(B) During testing, appetitive memory is retrieved at least in part through MB-V3 efferent neurons (dark red) that pool inputs from across the ab ensemble in the a 3 
region of the vertical a lobe tip region and drive approach behavior through a putative premotor area. Expression of conditioned approach is additionally gated in a 
hunger state-dependent manner by the MB-MP1 DA neurons (orange; Krashes et al., 2009). 
(C) During aversive training, MB-MP1 and MB-M3 DA neurons (green) reinforce odor-activated synapses in the ab s region of the peduncle and only ab s neurons in 
the b 2 region of the horizontal b lobe tip. 
(D) During testing, aversive memory is retrieved at least in part through MB-V3 neurons and the MB-V2a efferent neurons (both dark red) that collect inputs from 
the ab s neurons in the tip and a 2 region of the vertical a-stalk and drive avoidance behavior through the putative premotor area. </p>

<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>



<p>Objective Microscope (Sutter) with a Zeiss 203, 1.0 NA W-Plan-Apochromat 
objective. Emitted photons were separated from excitation light by a series 
of dichromatic mirrors and dielectric and colored glass filters and detected 
by GaAsP photomultiplier tubes (Hamamatsu Photonics H10770PA-40 SEL). 
Photomultiplier currents were amplified (Laser Components HCA-4M-500K-
C) and passed through a custom-designed integrator circuit to maximize the 
signal-to-noise ratio. The microscope was controlled through MPScope 2.0 
(Nguyen et al., 2006) via a PCI-6110 DAQ board (National Instruments). Odor 
stimuli were delivered by switching mass-flow-controlled carrier and stimulus 
streams (CMOSense Performance Line, Sensirion) via software-controlled so-
lenoid valves (The Lee Company). Flow rates at the exit port of the odor tube 
were 0.5 l/min. 
Images were converted to Analyze format and motion corrected by maxi-
mizing the pixel-by-pixel correlation between each frame and a reference 
frame. DF/F traces were calculated in ImageJ using manually drawn regions 
of interest (ROIs) for the background and brain structure of interest. Activity 
maps were generated in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> from Gaussian-smoothed, background-
subtracted images. A baseline fluorescence image was calculated as the 
average over a 10 s prestimulus interval. Minor z direction movement was 
ignored by correlating each frame to the baseline fluorescence and discarding 
it if the correlation fell below a threshold value. This threshold value was manu-
ally selected for each brain by noting the constant high correlation value when 
the brain was stationary and sudden drops in correlation when the brain 
moved. For each pixel, the difference between mean intensity during the stim-
ulus and the mean baseline fluorescence (DF) was calculated. The DF during 
the presentation of a dummy stimulus (no odor) was subtracted to control 
for mechanical artifacts from the odor delivery system. If DF was less than 
two times the SD of the intensity of that pixel during the prestimulus interval, 
that pixel was considered unresponsive. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION </p>

<p>Supplemental Information includes seven figures and one table and can 
be found with this article online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2013. 
07.045. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank David Owald, Daryl Gohl, Marion Sillies, Tom Clandinin, and Ulrike 
Heberlein for flies. We also thank Peter Dayan, Gero Miesenbö ck, and 
members of the Waddell and Miesenbö ck laboratories for discussion. E.P. 
thanks the Philippe and Bettencourt-Schueller Foundations. A.C.L. and S.L. 
are supported by a Sir Henry Wellcome Postdoctoral Fellowship and an 
EMBO Long-Term Fellowship, respectively. S.W. is funded by a Wellcome 
Trust Senior Research Fellowship in the Basic Biomedical Sciences, grant 
MH081982 from the National Institutes of Health, and by funds from the Gatsby 
Charitable Foundation and Oxford Martin School. </p>

<p>Accepted: July 3, 2013 
Published: September 4, 2013 </p>



<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>

<p>Neuron 79, 945-956, September 4, 2013 ª2013 The Authors 955 </p>



<p>Neuron </p>

<p>Neural Representations of Mnemonic Valence </p>



</text></tei>