<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3630328" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We report the discovery of an entirely new three-dimensional (3D) swimming pattern observed in human 
and horse sperms. This motion is in the form of 'chiral ribbons', where the planar swing of the sperm head 
occurs on an osculating plane creating in some cases a helical ribbon and in some others a twisted ribbon. 
The latter, i.e., the twisted ribbon trajectory, also defines a minimal surface, exhibiting zero mean curvature 
for all the points on its surface. These chiral ribbon swimming patterns cannot be represented or understood 
by already known patterns of sperms or other micro-swimmers. The discovery of these unique patterns is 
enabled by holographic on-chip imaging of .33,700 sperm trajectories at .90-140 frames/sec, which 
revealed that only ,1.7% of human sperms exhibit chiral ribbons, whereas it increases to ,27.3% for horse 
sperms. These results might shed more light onto the statistics and biophysics of various micro-swimmers' 
3D motion. </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>ocomotion in an aqueous environment plays an important function in the lives of many micro-organisms, 
such as bacteria, protists, and sperms. Without this kind of self-propelled swimming act, these micro-
organisms cannot actively find food, escape predators, or produce offsprings to sustain their species. 
Understanding the swimming patterns of these micro-organisms and the underlying biophysical processes is 
important to advance our existing knowledge in microbiology. To resolve the spatial and temporal details of these 
tiny (e.g., 1-50 mm) micro-organisms' fast locomotion (with speeds of for example 50-500 mm/sec), lens-based 
optical microscopes with high-speed cameras (e.g., .60 frames per sec, FPS) have been typically employed to 
digitally record their trajectories. Due to the restricted imaging volume of microscope objective lenses (having a 
limited field-of-view and depth-of-field), most of the earlier studies on these micro-organisms' locomotion have 
been limited to their two-dimensional (2D) dynamics </p>

<p>1-11   . Relatively recently, three-dimensional (3D) optical 
tracking techniques have also emerged, enabling the observation of various unique 3D swimming patterns of 
these micro-organisms, including for example helical, star-spin and planar motion </p>

<p>12-23   . Among these recent 
techniques, computational lensfree on-chip microscopy tools are especially well suited to analyze rare 3D 
swimming events that occur at the micro-scale because, unlike their lens-based counterparts, they have a much 
higher throughput to track a large number of individual trajectories in 3D </p>

<p>14,16,23,24   . 
Using a dual-angle and dual-color illumination based computational on-chip imaging platform </p>

<p>23   , here we 
report the discovery of an entirely new swimming pattern observed in human and horse sperms. This rare 3D 
motion is in the form of 'chiral ribbons' that resemble the chiral structures observed in several other biological 
systems 
25-28 (see Fig. 1 for a 3D illustration of chiral ribbons). In this swimming pattern, left-to-right and right-to-
left planar swing of the sperm head occurs on an osculating plane creating in some cases a 'helical ribbon' and in 
some others a 'twisted ribbon'. Quite interestingly, the twisted ribbon trajectory mathematically defines a min-
imal surface, exhibiting zero mean curvature for all the points on its surface, which will be proved and further 
discussed in our Discussion Section. These dynamic trajectories defined by chiral ribbons cannot be represented 
or understood by already known patterns of sperms of various species or other micro-swimmers </p>

<p>1-21,23   . The 
discovery of these unique 3D patterns is enabled by lensfree holographic on-chip imaging and tracking of 
,1,000-1,600 sperms (per experiment) at a frame rate of .90-140 frames per second over a large sample 
volume of e.g., ,9 mL, which is more than an order-of-magnitude larger compared to a lens-based optical 
microscope. Our high-throughput imaging experiments revealed that only ,1.7% of human sperms (out of 
24,090 individual sperm trajectories) exhibit chiral ribbons, whereas the same percentage increases to ,27.3% for 
horse sperms (out of 9,625 individual sperm trajectories). We also observed that the majority (,65%) of the chiral 
ribbons displayed by human sperms are right-handed, whereas ,85% of the chiral ribbons observed in horse 
sperms exhibit left-handed rotations. We believe that these results could help us better understand the statistical 
behavior of various micro-swimmers and might shed more light onto the biophysics of their 3D motion. </p>

<p>Results 
Using a dual-view and dual-wavelength holographic on-chip micro-
scopy platform (see Fig. 2), we initially imaged and reconstructed 3D 
spatio-temporal trajectories of horse sperms within large sample 
volumes (,9 mL) at ,140 FPS (refer to the Methods Section for 
details). Based on these experiments, we observed that horse sperms 
display a unique 'chiral ribbon' pattern (see Fig. 3-4), which occurs 
with a frequency of ,27.3% among 9,625 individual 3D trajectories 
that we reconstructed using our high-throughput on-chip imaging 
platform. These horse sperms that follow a chiral ribbon swimming 
pattern have locally planar lateral displacements as if they are con-
fined in 2D. In contrast to regular planar trajectories, however, in a 
chiral ribbon the plane on which the lateral displacements occur 
rotates continuously around a central axis as the sperm is moving 
forward, forming a 'twisted' ribbon within e.g., a ,0.7-sec long seg-
ment of the sperm trajectory (see Fig. 3(b,e)). Not only is this twisted 
ribbon trajectory quite tight with a typical side-to-side displacement </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Schematics which illustrate the 3D structures of chiral ribbons. </p>

<p>(a) A helical ribbon. (b) A twisted ribbon. </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Dual-view and dual-wavelength lensfree 3D tracking of sperms on a chip. (a) The picture of the imaging system. Two partially-coherent light </p>

<p>sources (LED-coupled multimode fibers, core size: 400 mm) illuminate the observation chamber from two different angles with two different wavelengths 
(vertical one: 625 nm; oblique one at 45u: 470 nm; bandwidth ,20 nm). A CMOS image sensor records the dual-view lensfree holograms that encode the 
position information of each sperm. (b) The close-up image of an observation chamber that is placed on the top of the CMOS image sensor. (c) The 
reconstructed 3D spatio-temporal trajectories of 998 horse sperms that were tracked inside a volume of ,9.0 mL at a frame rate of 143 FPS. The inset in 
(c) shows the trajectories reconstructed inside a sub-volume of the lensfree imaging system. The time position of each track point is encoded by its color 
(see the color bar). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1664 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01664 </p>

<p>
of ,5 mm, but also it beats rather fast, crossing over the central axis 
roughly 30 times within a second, making it rather challenging 
to observe with other 3D optical tracking techniques 
12-22,29,30 due to 
the tight requirements in 3D localization accuracy and video frame 
rate. 
Further investigation of these chiral ribbon swimming patterns in 
horse sperm samples revealed that in longer durations of observation 
(.2.1 sec), we can also observe spatio-temporal super-structures that 
mimic a different type of a chiral ribbon, namely a ''helical ribbon'' 
(see e.g., Fig. 3(a,d) and Supplementary Movies S1-S2). With this type 
of super-structure, the osculating plane of the sperm trajectory (i.e., 
the beating of the sperm head) not only twists as the sperm moves 
forward, but also forms a 3D helix in the form of a chiral ribbon (see 
for example the left-handed twisting planes that form the left-handed 
helical ribbons shown in Fig. 3(a) and (d); or Supplementary Movies 
S1 and S2, respectively). We should emphasize that such a helical 
ribbon trajectory should not be confused with already-known helical 
trajectories of sperms </p>

<p>23   , where the sperm head defines a simple helix, 
not a 3D ribbon (i.e., without any chiral planar motion). As a matter 
of fact, these chiral ribbon swimming patterns cannot be represented 
by already known patterns of sperms or other micro-swimmers, and 
are reported in the literature for the first time, enabled by our high-
throughput on-chip imaging platform. The same lensfree imaging 
system also permits us to track each one of these ,1,000 horse sperms </p>

<p>(per experiment) within a large sample volume of ,9 mL across a time 
window of e.g., ,7-10 sec (at ,140 FPS), and analyze the spatio-
temporal transitions of their swimming patterns into or out of the 
chiral ribbon pattern. Figure 4 and Supplementary Movie S3 illustrate 
such a swimming pattern transition observed when an individual 
horse sperm encountered the bottom glass surface of our observation 
chamber, where its 3D trajectory switched from a right-handed chiral 
ribbon pattern to a simple planar swimming pattern. This example 
illustrates that boundary confinement could be an influential factor in 
the transitions of sperm swimming patterns. 
We also statistically quantified the 3D motion dynamics, such as 
Rate of Twisting (RTW), Linearity (LIN), Straight-Line Velocity 
(VSL), Curvilinear Velocity (VCL), and Amplitude of Lateral Head 
Displacement (ALH) of the chiral ribbon trajectories observed in 
horse sperms (see Fig. 5 and the Methods Section for details). For 
this statistical analysis, we digitally processed 2,625 individual chiral 
ribbon patterns (out of a total of 9,625 trajectories, each ,0.7 sec 
long) to reveal that ,85% of the ribbon horse sperm trajectories 
prefer left-handed twisting over right-handed twisting (see 
Fig. 5(c)), exhibiting a side-to-side displacement of 1-12 mm and a 
twisting rate (RTW) of 0.5-22 rad/sec. 
After discovering chiral ribbon trajectories in horse sperm sam-
ples, we also searched for similar 3D swimming patterns in human 
sperms (see the Methods Section). For this end, we digitally </p>

<p>Figure 3 | The chiral ribbon patterns displayed by horse sperm trajectories. (a) and (d) are two chiral ribbon trajectories recorded over a duration of </p>

<p>4.6 sec. (b) and (e) are digitally zoomed segments (,0.7-sec long each) of the two ribbon trajectories shown in (a) and (d), respectively. Both of the 
trajectories in (a) and (d) have left-handed twisting and form left-handed helical ribbons. (c) and (f) are two simulated trajectories that were generated by 
equation 2 to match the measured chiral ribbon trajectories shown in (a) and (d), respectively (see Table 1 for the simulation parameters). The magenta 
ribbon surfaces in (b) and (e) designate the osculating planes of the twisting ribbon trajectories. The inset in each panel represents the lateral displacement 
of the straightened sperm trajectory (front view). The arrows indicate the directions of the sperms' forward movement. The time position of each track 
point is encoded by its color (see the color bar). See Supplementary Movies S1 and S2 for the spatio-temporal evolution of the ribbon trajectories shown in 
(a) and (d), respectively. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1664 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01664 </p>

<p>
processed 24,090 individual human sperm trajectories to find out 
that only ,1.7% of the time chiral ribbons were formed (see e.g., 
Fig. 6 and Supplementary Movie S4 for a twisted ribbon pattern). 
This lower percentage also partially explains why this twisted ribbon 
type of swimming pattern remained unidentified in earlier studies 
and was in fact broadly classified as part of the ''typical'' 
23 trajectories 
for human sperms (see Fig. 7). Despite their low percentages, we still </p>

<p>observed that right-handed twisting in human sperm ribbons is more 
frequent than left-handed twisting (1.1% vs. 0.6% of 24,090 traject-
ories), which is quite the opposite of what is observed with horse 
sperm ribbons. Another interesting difference between the chiral 
ribbons of these two species is that human sperms, even in longer 
observation time windows, still follow twisted ribbons rather than 
helical ribbons (see e.g., Fig. 6(a)). </p>

<p>Figure 4 | A 5.0-sec long 3D trajectory showing the transitions between different swimming patterns of a horse sperm. This trajectory switched from a </p>

<p>right-handed chiral ribbon pattern to a simple planar swimming pattern when the sperm encountered the bottom glass surface of the observation 
chamber. (b), (c), and (d) illustrate digitally zoomed segments (,0.7-sec long each) of the whole sperm trajectory shown in (a). The inset in each panel 
represents the lateral displacement of the straightened sperm track segment (front view). The arrows indicate the directions of the sperm's forward 
movement. The time position of each track point is encoded by its color (see the color bar). See Supplementary Movie S3 for the spatio-temporal 
evolution of this trajectory. </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Dynamic swimming parameters of 2,625 chiral ribbon trajectories (out of a total of 9,625 motile horse sperms, each ,0.7 sec long). Color </p>

<p>bar represents the relative density of data points in each graph. Magenta lines enclose 90% of the chiral ribbon trajectories presented in each panel. VSL: 
straight-line velocity. VCL: curvilinear velocity. ALH: amplitude of lateral head displacement. LIN: linearity. RTW: rate of twisting. A chiral ribbon 
trajectory with RTW . 0 (RTW , 0) is defined as right-handed (left-handed). These measurements were all made with horse sperms suspended in equine 
semen extender (BotuSemen) after .30 min of incubation. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1664 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01664 </p>

<p>
Discussion 
Mathematically, the equation of a 'chiral ribbon' surface s can be 
broadly defined as: </p>

<p>s~x y </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
5~r </p>

<p>h cos 2p </p>

<p>l 
p h 
zh h </p>



<p>
r h sin 2p 
l 
p h 
zh h </p>



<p>
l </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>z 
a 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>1z 2p 
r h 
p h </p>

<p>
2 
s </p>

<p>sin 2p 
l 
p h 
zh h </p>



<p>
{ cos 2p 
l 
p h 
zh h </p>



<p>
2p 
r h 
p h </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>ð1Þ </p>

<p>where 0 # l # L, 
{D 
2 
ƒaƒ 
D 
2 
, L is the length of the chiral ribbon </p>

<p>that is aligned along the z-direction, D and r h are the width and the </p>

<p>radius of the chiral ribbon, respectively, P h is the pitch of the chiral 
ribbon (defined as positive for a right-handed ribbon and negative 
for a left-handed ribbon), and h h is the offset angle of the chiral 
ribbon. This chiral ribbon equation can form a ''helical'' or a 
''twisted'' ribbon when r h is significantly larger than zero or close 
to zero, respectively. 
The chiral ribbons observed in our sperm tracking experiments 
(see e.g., Figs. 3(a) and 3(d)) can be mathematically reproduced by 
adding a periodic lateral oscillation (e.g., sinusoidal) along the ribbon 
surface that is defined by equation 1, i.e., </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>y 
z </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
5~r </p>

<p>h cos v h tzh h 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>r h sin v h tzh h 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>v z t </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
5z 
r b cos v b tzh b 
ð 
Þ 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 
v 2 
z zv 2 
h r 2 </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>v z sin v h tzh h 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>{v z cos v h tzh h 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>v h r h </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
5, </p>

<p>ð2Þ </p>

<p>where n z is the forward-moving velocity along the z direction, v h 5 
2p(n z /p h ) is the angular velocity of the helical ribbon (positive for a 
right-handed ribbon and negative for a left-handed one), r b is the 
radius of the sperm beating waveform, v b and h b are the angular 
velocity and the offset angle of the same beating waveform. Two </p>

<p>Figure 6 | (a) A 4.4-sec long human sperm trajectory that forms a twisted ribbon. The magenta ribbon surface in (b) designates the right-handed </p>

<p>osculating plane of the trajectory. The insets in the panels represent the lateral displacement of the straightened sperm trajectories (front view). The arrows 
indicate the directions of the sperms' forward movement. The time position of each track point is encoded by its color (see the color bar). See 
Supplementary Movie S4 for the spatio-temporal evolution of the sperm trajectory shown in (a). </p>

<p>Figure 7 | The statistics of human sperm chiral ribbon swimming patterns compared to other swimming patterns observed in human sperms. The </p>

<p>right-handed and left-handed chiral ribbon patterns (excluding hyperactivated ribbons) account for 1.1% and 0.6% of all the 24,090 human sperm 
trajectories that we reconstructed, respectively. These measurements were made in human sperm baseline medium (artificial HTF) after .2 h of 
incubation </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1664 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01664 </p>

<p>
examples of simulated sperm trajectories that are computed based on 
equation 2 are shown in Fig. 3(c) and 3(f), with their parameters 
(Table 1) tuned to match the measured chiral ribbon trajectories of 
Fig. 3(a) and 3(d), respectively. Note that the osculating planes of the 
measured sperm trajectories reported in Fig. 3(a) and 3(d) are in very 
good agreement with our theoretical trajectories shown in Fig. 3(c) 
and 3(f), respectively, both calculated based on equation 2 with the 
parameters of Table 1. 
Interestingly, when r h 5 0, the ''twisted'' ribbon surface exactly 
becomes a minimal surface in the form of a helicoid (which should 
not be confused with a helix) 
31 . Minimal surfaces minimize their 
surface area with respect to a particular boundary, and also have local 
mean curvature equal to zero at all points on their surface. Besides a 
helicoid, a simple plane and a catenoid also define minimal surfaces. 
The mean curvature (H) of a chiral ribbon surface can be computed 
from the partial derivatives of s with respect to its parameters, l and a, 
and it can be written as </p>

<p>32   : </p>

<p>H~s </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>: s l 
ð Þ s aa : n </p>

<p>_ </p>



<p>{2 s l : s a 
ð 
Þ s la : n </p>

<p>_ </p>



<p>z s a : s a 
ð 
Þ s ll : n </p>

<p>_ </p>



<p>
2 s l : s l 
ð Þ s a : s a 
ð 
Þ{ s l : s a 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>where subscripts indicate partial derivatives (e.g., s l~L s=Ll), and 
n </p>

<p>_~s </p>

<p>l |s a 
ð 
Þ= s l |s a 
k 
kis the unit normal vector. For the chiral ribbon 
surfaces defined by equation 1, the mean curvature can be calculated 
as: </p>

<p>H~{ 
r h </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
p h 
2p </p>

<p>4 
zr 4 
h z </p>

<p>p h 
2p </p>

<p>2 
2r 2 
h za 2 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
r 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>As the term inside the square root is strictly positive in equation 4, 
H 5 0 and s is a minimal surface if and only if r h 5 0, proving that an 
ideal twisted ribbon indeed defines a minimal surface. 
Note that minimal surfaces are also naturally found in a wide 
range of other fields. For example, minimal surfaces (in the form 
of catenoids) describe the shape soap films adopt on a wire frame </p>

<p>33   . 
Additionally, nano-catenoid minimal surfaces have recently been 
shown to describe the shape of self-assembled liquid nanolenses that 
can spontaneously form around nanoparticles or viruses adhered to a 
substrate </p>

<p>34   . As another related example, one of the phases of di-block 
copolymer mixtures, the gyroid phase, is also a minimal surface </p>

<p>35   . 
Here the gyroid surface describes the interphase boundary between 
the two nanoscopic domains of the polymer. Other materials whose 
structure can be described as minimal surfaces include inorganic 
crystal structures, biological cell membranes, and in certain cases, 
the structure of folded proteins </p>

<p>32,36   . 
We should emphasize that the actual cause and the biological 
function of these chiral ribbon swimming patterns are not clear 
and should be the subject of future work. In many of the situations 
where minimal surfaces arise, a common theme is that of energy 
minimization. Hence, the fact that different modes of sperm loco-
motion (e.g., twisted ribbon as well as simple planar trajectories) 
follow a minimal surface may also indicate energy minimization 
corresponding to maximal propulsion efficiency in these modes. 
However, significantly more investigation into the hydrodynamics 
and biomechanics of the sperm motion would be required to validate 
this proposition. Another related speculative cause is that a small 
asymmetry in the shape or the location of the center-of-mass of 
the sperm head might generate a net torque through the surrounding 
fluid when the sperm tail is pushing its body forward. Similar </p>

<p>phenomena have been discussed previously using hydrodynamics 
numerical simulations to partially explain regular helical trajectories 
(not chiral ribbons) of sperm cells </p>

<p>37   . Based on such a structural 
asymmetry, the local movement of the sperm head can still be gov-
erned by the planar beating of its tail, however the whole body can 
gradually rotate due to a net torque and the sperm trajectory can 
slowly deviate from the central axis of the beating. Once the whole 
sperm body finishes a full rotation, the trajectory would also com-
plete a cycle of the helical ribbon. As for the biological function of 
such a chiral ribbon swimming pattern, it might possibly be similar to 
what has been proposed for regular helical trajectories </p>

<p>38-40   ; in other 
words, these chiral swimming patterns could potentially help reor-
ienting the motion of the micro-organisms into the direction of 
stimulus gradient due to for example the concentration of a 
chemo-attractant or just the environmental temperature distri-
bution. These chiral ribbons that we observed, compared to simple 
planar trajectories, might permit sperms to sense such gradient pro-
files over larger 3D volumes, which could then help detection of 
weaker stimuli, assisting in e.g., sperms' chemotaxis 
41,42 or ther-
motaxis 
41,43 behavior. These and other possible hypotheses would 
need to be further studied in greater detail to better understand the 
origins and possible functions of chiral ribbon swimming patterns in 
general. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Preparing and incubating sperm suspension. Frozen sperm specimens of a 
Warmblood stallion were obtained from the Center for Equine Health at the 
University of California, Davis. Before freezing, fresh semen specimens were first 
diluted to a concentration of 50 million sperms per ml with equine semen extender 
(E-Z Mixin BFT, Animal Reproduction Systems) and then were centrifuged at 400 G 
for 15 min. After centrifugation the pellet was re-suspended in freezing extender (E-Z 
Freezin Equine Semen Extender, Animal Reproduction Systems) with a final 
concentration of 400 million sperms per ml. The processed sperms specimens were 
packaged in 0.5 ml straws and frozen in a programmable freezer. When the straws 
had reached 2150uC they were plunged in liquid nitrogen for storage. 
To prepare the horse sperm suspension for imaging, the frozen specimens were 
first thawed at 38uC water bath for 30 sec, and then rehydrated for 15 min by mixing 
with equine semen extender (BotuSemen, Nidacon, Sweden) by a ratio of 151. After 
rehydration, gradient density centrifugation with isotonic density medium 
(Equipure, Nidacon, Sweden, 200 g for 30 min) was used to concentrate the motile 
sperms within the semen specimens. The centrifuged sperm pellet was re-suspended 
with the same equine semen extender at a concentration of ,1 million sperms per ml 
(.50% motile) and then incubated for another 30 min. Right before lensfree on-chip 
imaging experiments, ,25 mL of the sperm suspension was put into a disposable 
observation chamber prepared by taping a laser-cut Acetal film (,0.15 mm thick) 
between two pieces of No. 1 cover slips. 
The methods and related procedures for preparing and incubating human sperm 
suspensions have been explained in detail in our previous work </p>

<p>23   . </p>

<p>Dual-view and dual-wavelength lensfree on-chip holographic imaging and 
tracking set-up. A dual-view and dual-wavelength lensfree on-chip holographic 
imaging setup, as illustrated in Fig. 2, was utilized to record the 3D movement of 
sperms. Two partially-coherent light sources (LED-coupled multimode fibers, core 
size: 400 mm) illuminated the observation chambers from two different angles with 
two different wavelengths (vertical one: 625 nm; oblique one at 45u: 470 nm; 
bandwidth ,20 nm). When recording the 3D movement of sperms, the observation 
chamber was placed directly on the top of the protection glass of our CMOS 
(Complementary Metal-Oxide-Semiconductor) image sensor (Aptina 
MT9P031STC, 5 megapixels, 2.2 mm pixel size, monochrome; see Fig. 2(b)). The 
power of this image sensor chip was cut off between video acquisition sessions to 
maintain the temperature of the sperm observation chamber at ,37-39uC. 
The frame rate of the computational imaging system used in this manuscript was 
raised to 143 FPS to oversample the faster beating of horse sperms (beat-cross-
frequency, BCF: ,30 Hz), whereas it was operated at ,92 FPS for imaging of human 
sperms </p>

<p>23   . Such high frame rates reduced the imaging area of individual regions-of-
interest (ROIs) that the CMOS image sensor chip can record at its full speed. 
Therefore, the whole field of view (FOV) of the image sensor was digitally divided into </p>

<p>Table 1 | The parameters used in equation 2 for simulating the helical ribbons shown in Fig. 3(c) and 3(f) </p>

<p>r h (mm) 
v h (rad/sec) 
h h (rad) 
r b (mm) 
v b (rad/sec) 
h b (rad) 
n z (mm/sec) </p>

<p>Fig. 3(c) 
3.0 
24.7 
20.3 
2.0 
188.5 
0.5 
40.0 
Fig. 3(f) 
10.0 
25.7 
3.5 
3.0 
125.7 
0.0 
20.0 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1664 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01664 </p>

<p>
16 (for human sperms) or 50 (for horse sperms) ROIs, which were sequentially 
recorded for continuous intervals of e.g., 0.7-7.0 seconds each. Further details of the 
human sperm imaging and tracking experiments can be found in Ref. 23. For horse 
samples, scanning over 50 such ROIs (with .5,000 lensfree holographic frames) and 
recording the 3D trajectories of .1,000 sperms took approximately 30 min for each 
semen sample. At the same time, the exposure time of the imaging system was also 
shortened to ,3 ms to avoid motion blur in recording the high-speed movement of 
horse sperms (which exhibit a typical instantaneous speed of e.g., ,150 mm/sec). </p>

<p>Reconstructing the 3D trajectories of sperms. For horse sperms, due to the high 
density of dead sperms and undissolved extender solute in the suspension liquid, each 
lensfree holographic frame was subtracted from a stationary image to remove the 
holograms of non-moving objects within the ROI. This stationary image was 
generated by averaging 100 consecutive lensfree frames that are nearest to the 
processing frame in the video sequence of the same ROI. These digital background 
cleaning steps were not needed and were not used for human sperm data. 
The 3D trajectories of mobile sperms inside the FOV of the image sensor were then 
reconstructed following the procedures detailed in our previous work </p>

<p>23   . The vertical 
and oblique lensfree projections of each sperm head were digitally reconstructed on 
all the possible depth (i.e., z) planes individually. Once passed the morphological 
screening process, the centroid positions of both the vertical and the oblique head 
projections were calculated by their centers-of-gravity within their corresponding 
reconstructed amplitude images. The x and y coordinates of the sperms were taken 
directly from the centroid positions of the vertical head projections, while the z 
(depth) coordinates of the sperms were calculated by dividing the distance between 
their vertical and oblique projection centroids with the tangent of the oblique illu-
mination angle in water. A space-time matrix containing the spatial and temporal 
coordinates of all the sperms within the observation volume was generated by 
repeating the same 3D localization procedures depicted above on all the holographic 
frames. Finally, the 3D trajectory of each sperm was constructed by linking the 
detected points across the recorded frames by a Brownian-statistics-based algo-
rithm 
44 . Note that the shapes of the sperm heads are assumed to be either spherical or 
ellipsoidal so that the orientation of the heads will not create a systematic error in the 
centroid-based position estimation. For tracking of sperms with deformed heads (see, 
e.g., images in References 45 and 46), processing techniques reported in Ref. 47 can 
potentially be used to minimize such errors and improve the reliability of our lensfree 
3D tracking technique for deformed sperms. </p>

<p>Definitions of sperms' 3D dynamic swimming parameters. To quantify the 3D 
dynamics of sperm motion, we extracted a series of parameters from individual 
reconstructed sperm trajectories. All the parameters reported for horse sperms in this 
work were extracted from either 0.7 sec-long trajectories (,100 lensfree frames at 
143 FPS) or track segments of such length that were digitally cropped from longer 
trajectories (e.g., ,4-7 sec long). For human sperms, however, these parameters were 
extracted from 1.1 sec-long tracks (,100 lensfree frames at 92 FPS). Similar to our 
previous work 
23 , a digital ''straightening'' process was performed to compensate the 
curvature in sperm's forward motion before extracting these dynamical parameters. 
The definitions of parameters such as straight-line velocity (VSL), curvilinear velocity 
(VCL), linearity (LIN), amplitude of lateral head displacement (ALH) have been 
described in detail in our previous work </p>

<p>23   . Here we elaborate on the definition of the 
dynamical parameters that were newly introduced in this work: 
Rate of twisting (RTW) represents the rotation speed (units: rad/sec) of the head 
beating plane for a sperm swimming in a ribbon pattern. It is defined as the angular 
frequency of the linear function that best fits the time evolution of the osculating plane 
angle for a track segment. The osculating plane angle on each position along the track 
segment is calculated by finding the most frequent angle of the lateral displacements 
occurring in the adjacent beating cycle, whose duration is defined by 2/BCF. 
Twisting stability (TWS) is defined as the ratio between the accumulated angle 
change of the osculating plane and the averaged error to the best-fit linear function in 
the osculating plane angle. Both the angle change accumulation and the error aver-
aging (by taking root mean square) were performed across the whole duration of each 
track segment. TWS represents how much a track segment is confined to a twisted 
ribbon (see, e.g., the magenta ribbon surfaces in Fig. 3 (b) and (e)). The value of TWS 
is reported in logarithm to the base 10. For example, a track segment with 10 radians 
of accumulated osculating plane angle change and 1 radians of mean linear-fit error 
would have a TWS of 1. </p>

<p>Digital classification of sperm trajectories. The 3D swimming patterns of sperms 
were classified based on the dynamic parameters defined in the previous section. Note 
that all the horse sperm trajectories with VCL smaller than 60 mm/sec and VSL 
smaller than 20 mm/sec are considered as immotile and are excluded from the 
reported statistics. The following are the specific criteria that we have used in this 
work to distinguish different categories of horse sperm trajectories: 
Ribbon trajectory: TWS $ 1.2. 
Hyperactivated trajectory: VCL $ 180 mm/sec and ALH $ 12 mm (following the 
definition used in Ref. 48). 
Hyper-ribbon trajectory: A hyperactivated trajectory that also forms a ribbon (TWS 
$ 1.2). 
Because human sperm trajectories were recorded at a lower frame rate (92 FPS 
instead of 143 FPS), the criteria for categorizing these trajectories for human sperms 
were modified as such: 
Immotile trajectory: VCL , 30 mm/sec. </p>

<p>Ribbon trajectory: TWS $ 1.3. 
Hyperactivated trajectory: VCL $ 150 mm/sec; LIN # 0.5 and ALH $ 7 mm 
(following the definition used in Ref. 49). 
The other criteria remained the same as the ones used for horse sperms. </p>

<p>Automated processing of 3D sperm trajectory data. Data processing procedures, 
including the reconstruction of lensfree holographic images, the localization of 
sperms' 3D centroids, the linking and resolution of sperms' 3D spatio-temporal 
trajectories, and the classification of their 3D swimming patterns were all performed 
with a fully-automated custom-designed <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> program. The typical computation 
time for automatic processing of e.g., ,5,000 lensfree images from a single semen 
sample is ,4 hours (using Matlab R2011a running on a PC with an eight-core Intel 
Core i7-930 2.80 GHz processor). </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank Barbara Stewart (Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital, University of 
California, Davis, CA, USA) and Stuart Meyers (Department of Anatomy Physiology and 
Cell Biology, University of California, Davis, CA, USA) for their valuable discussions and 
help on collecting horse semen specimens. A.O. acknowledges the support of the Army 
Research Office (ARO), ARO Young Investigator Award, National Science Foundation 
CAREER Award, the Office of Naval Research Young Investigator and PECASE Awards, 
and the National Institutes of Health Director's New Innovator Award DP2OD006427 
from the Office of The Director, National Institutes of Health. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>T.S. conducted the experiments and processed the resulting data. I.C., J.F. and K.H. 
contributed to experiments. E.M. contributed to the discussion section. T.S. and A.O. 
planned and executed the research. T.S., E.M. and A.O. wrote the manuscript. A.O. 
supervised the project. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: A.O. is the co-founder of a start-up company that aims to 
commercialize lensfree microscopy tools. </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this 
license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Su, T. et al. Sperm Trajectories Form Chiral Ribbons. Sci. Rep. 3, 
1664; DOI:10.1038/srep01664 (2013). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 3 : 1664 | DOI: 10.1038/srep01664 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>