<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3064789" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Deamination of 5-methylcytosine to thymine creates </p>

<p>mutagenic G · T mispairs, contributing to cancer </p>

<p>and genetic disease. Thymine DNA glycosylase </p>

<p>(TDG) removes thymine from these G · T lesions, 
and follow-on base excision repair yields a G · C </p>

<p>pair. A previous crystal structure revealed TDG (cata-
lytic domain) bound to abasic DNA product in a 2:1 
complex, one subunit at the abasic site and the other 
bound to undamaged DNA. Biochemical studies 
showed TDG can bind abasic DNA with 1:1 or 2:1 
stoichiometry, but the dissociation constants were 
unknown, as was the stoichiometry and affinity for 
binding substrates and undamaged DNA. We </p>

<p>showed that 2:1 binding is dispensable for G · U 
activity, but its role in G · T repair was unknown. </p>

<p>Using equilibrium binding anisotropy experiments, 
we show that a single TDG subunit binds very </p>

<p>tightly to G · U mispairs and abasic (G · AP) sites, and 
somewhat less tightly G · T mispairs. Kinetics experi-
ments show 1:1 binding provides full G · T activity. </p>

<p>TDG binds undamaged CpG sites with remarkable </p>

<p>affinity, modestly weaker than G · T mispairs, and </p>

<p>exhibits substantial affinity for nonspecific DNA. 
While 2:1 binding is observed for large excess TDG 
concentrations, our findings indicate that a single 
TDG subunit is fully capable of locating and process-</p>

<p>ing G · U or G · T lesions. </p>

<p>A large percentage of point mutations in cancer and 
genetic disease are C!T transitions at CpG sites, result-</p>

<p>ing largely from replication of G · T mispairs created by </p>

<p>deamination of 5-methylcytosine (m 
5 C) to thymine (1-4). 
Thymine DNA glycosylase (TDG) is charged with </p>

<p>finding these G · T lesions and removing thymine to </p>

<p>initiate base excision repair, which ultimately restores a </p>

<p>G · C base pair (5,6). Methyl binding domain IV (MBD4) 
is another DNA glycosylase that processes G · T mispairs </p>

<p>arising from m 
5 C deamination at CpG sites (7,8). About 
4% of cytosines in mammalian DNA are methylated, 
selectively at CpG sites, and this key modification 
promotes transcriptional silencing and is essential for 
many cellular processes and for embryonic development 
(9). It is known that cytosine 5-methyltransferases 
catalyze the conversion of C to m 
5 C at CpG sites in 
DNA, but the mechanism for 'demethylation' of 
m 
5 CpG has remained elusive (9). Several recent studies 
indicate a BER-mediated pathway for active 
demethylation (10,11); many indicate a mechanism for 
active m </p>

<p>5 C deamination, giving a G · T mispair that </p>

<p>could be processed by TDG (or MBD4) and BER to </p>

<p>restore a G · C pair (12-16). A preliminary report that </p>

<p>inactivation of TDG causes embryonic lethality in mice 
(17), the first such finding for any DNA glycosylase, is 
consistent with an essential role for TDG in transcrip-</p>

<p>tional regulation, in addition to processing G · T mispairs </p>

<p>arising from spontaneous m 
5 C deamination. 
Given the critical role of TDG in protecting against 
C!T mutations and its emerging role(s) in transcription-
al regulation, it is important to obtain a detailed under-
standing of how TDG recognizes and processes lesions, 
how its activity is stimulated by the follow-on BER 
enzyme, APE1 and to characterize its interaction with 
undamaged CpG sites and nonspecific DNA. Our 
recent crystal structure of TDG (catalytic domain) 
bound to abasic DNA (18) revealed a remarkable 2:1 
complex, with one TDG subunit bound at the abasic 
site and an adjacent subunit bound to undamaged 
DNA (Figure 1). Such 2:1 binding had not previously 
been observed for TDG, MUG or UNG. Our previous 
biochemical studies showed TDG, full length and cata-
lytic domain, can bind abasic DNA with 1:1 or 2:1 stoi-
chiometry, depending on TDG concentration (18). 
However, the affinity for each TDG subunit (K d1 
and K d2 ) remained unknown. Determining these values 
is important for understanding the catalytic mechanism 
of TDG and how its activity is stimulated by APE1, i.e. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 410 706 8118; Fax: +1 410 106 8297; Email: adrohat@som.umaryland.edu </p>

<p>Published online 21 November 2010 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 6 2319-2329 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq1164 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>how the first steps of BER are coordinated. In addition, </p>

<p>the stoichiometry for binding G · T or G · U substrates had </p>

<p>not been examined. Although we previously showed 1:1 </p>

<p>binding provides full catalytic activity for G · U lesions </p>

<p>(18), TDG exhibits much weaker binding and catalysis </p>

<p>for G · T relative to G · U substrates (19-22), raising the </p>

<p>question of whether 2:1 binding could be needed for effi-</p>

<p>cient G · T repair. This is important, because G · T lesions </p>

<p>are considered the predominant biological substrate for 
TDG (21,23). Our previous studies demonstrate TDG 
can excise bulky cytosine analogs from a CpG site in 
DNA (24), suggesting TDG may have substantial affinity 
for undamaged CpG sites, but this had not been 
determined. Additionally, previous studies suggest TDG 
possesses significant affinity for nonspecific DNA (25), 
but this has not been quantitatively examined. 
Determining the affinity and stoichiometry of TDG for 
binding CpG sites and nonspecific DNA is important for 
understanding its functions in DNA repair and transcrip-
tional regulation. We address these important questions </p>

<p>here using pre-steady-state kinetics and equilibrium 
binding experiments. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>DNA synthesis and purification </p>

<p>The DNA used for this work is shown in Figure 2. Duplex 
DNA was hybridized by rapid heating to 80 
C followed by 
slow cooling to room temperature. DNA oligonucleotides 
were synthesized at the Keck Foundation Biotechnology 
Resource Laboratory of Yale University (trityl-on), 
purified using Glen-Pak purification cartridges (Glen 
Research), and quantified by absorbance (260 nm) as 
described (22,24). Purity was verified by analytical 
anion-exchange high-performance liquid chromatography 
(HPLC) under denaturing (pH 12) conditions (24). 
The oligonucleotides containing substrate analogs 
2 
0 -deoxy-2 
0 -flouroarabinothymidine (T 
F , Figure 2) or 
2 
0 -deoxy-2 
0 -flouroarabinouridine (U 
F ) were obtained as 
described (22). Control experiments demonstrate DNA 
containing U 
F or T 
F is completely resistant to cleavage 
by TDG (saturating concentration) for &gt;48 h, consistent 
with previous findings for TDG (26) and MUG (27). 
Previous studies and our findings here indicate T 
F and 
U 
F are excellent mimics of dT and dU, and do not signifi-
cantly perturb the structure of B-type DNA (22,26-29). 
The DNA used for fluorescence anisotropy experiments 
was labeled with sulphorhodamine (Texas Red, TR) in the 
non-target strand (5 
0 amino C6 modifier), and was </p>

<p>Figure 1. TDG can form a 2:1 complex with DNA. (A) Our previous 
crystal structure shows TDG (catalytic domain) can form a 2:1 complex 
with abasic DNA, one subunit (dark gray) binds the flipped abasic 
nucleotide and the adjacent subunit (light gray) binds to undamaged 
DNA. The protein-protein interface buries $300 Å 
2 of accessible 
surface area per subunit. (B) Cartoon depicting the contacts to DNA 
phosphates made by the specific TDG subunit (black triangles) and the 
nonspecific subunit (gray triangles) with respect to the lesion site (red). 
The DNA constructs used for the studies reported here are 16X11 
(28 bp) and 3X11 (15 bp), where X represents the target nucleotide 
(Figure 2). The 16X11 DNAs can accommodate 2:1 binding as 
observed in the crystal structure, but the 3X11 DNAs cannot. </p>

<p>Figure 2. DNA used in this work. We used two non-cleavable 
substrate analogs, 2 
0 -deoxy-2 
0 -flouroarabinothymidine (T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>) and 
2 
0 -deoxy-2 
0 -flouroarabinouridine (U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>) to monitor TDG binding to 
substrate in the absence of base excision. Two DNA constructs were 
used; 16X11 can accommodate 2:1 binding as seen in the crystal structure, 
while 3X11 cannot (Figure 1). The target nucleotide (x = U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>, T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>, AP, T or 
C) is paired with guanine (bold) and placed in a CpG dinucleotide context, 
in keeping with the specificity of TDG. The DNA contains no other CpG 
site. The DNA was labeled at the 5 
0 end of the non-target strand (*) with 
sulforhodamine (also called Texas Red or TR) for anisotropy experiments 
or with fluorescein for EMSAs. The 28 bp nonspecific DNA (NS28) 
contains no mispair or CpG site. </p>



<p>synthesized and purified (RP-HPLC) by the Midland 
Certified Reagent Co. (Midland, TX, USA). 
Abasic (AP) DNA was generated by incubating 16U11 
or 3U11 (2000 nM) with a 1000-fold lower concentration 
(2 nM) of uracil DNA glycosylase (UNG) at 23 
C for 
30 min, sufficient time for complete conversion of sub-
strate to abasic product (16AP11 or 3AP11), and used 
immediately for anisotropy or electrophoretic mobility 
shift assay (EMSA) experiments. After dilution of AP 
DNA (4000-fold) to the concentration used for anisotropy 
(0.5 nM), the residual UNG (0.0005 nM) is far too dilute 
to bind the AP DNA (K d &gt; 15 uM) (30) or effect the 
binding of TDG. Although the higher AP-DNA concen-
tration used for EMSA (0.5 mM) resulted in a higher 
residual UNG concentration (0.5 nM), given its weak 
affinity for AP DNA, and the 1000-fold excess concentra-
tion of AP DNA, UNG will have no effect on TDG 
binding. </p>

<p>Enzyme purification </p>

<p>Human thymine DNA glycosylase (TDG) was expressed 
and purified as described (18,21), flash frozen, and stored 
at À80 
C. The enzyme concentration is determined by ab-
sorbance, using a molar absorption coefficient of 
e 
280 = 31.5 mM 
À1 cm 
À1 , measured using the Edelhoch 
method, as described (31). We typically find TDG is 
fully active, as indicated by observation that for 
pre-steady-state multiple turnover kinetic experiments col-</p>

<p>lected for G · U and G · FU substrates, the amplitude of </p>

<p>the exponential phase is equal to the TDG concentration, 
(Supplementary Figures S1 and S2). </p>

<p>Kinetics experiments </p>

<p>We used single turnover kinetics experiments under 
saturating enzyme conditions ([E] &gt; [S] &gt;&gt; K d ) to obtain 
a rate constant (k max ) that is not influenced by product 
release or product inhibition. This is important because 
TDG exhibits very slow product release and strong 
product inhibition, which dominates k cat values 
determined using steady-state kinetics (19,32,33). 
Experiments were collected at room temperature (23 
C) 
in HEMN.1 buffer (0.02 M HEPES, 0.2 mM EDTA, 
2.5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.1 M NaCl). Experiments were initiated 
by adding concentrated TDG to buffered substrate, 
followed by rapid mixing. At various time points, 
aliquots were removed, quenched with 50% (v:v) 0.3 M 
NaOH and 0.03 M EDTA, and heated at 85 
C for 
15 min to cleave the DNA backbone at enzyme-produced 
abasic sites. The fraction product was determined by 
HPLC (21,24). The data were fitted to Equation (1) 
using nonlinear regression with <rs type="software">Grafit</rs> 6 (34): </p>

<p>fraction product ¼ Að1 À e 
Àkt Þ 
ð 1Þ </p>

<p>where A is the amplitude, k is the rate constant and t is the 
reaction time (min). The DNA substrate concentration 
was 0.5 mM, and the TDG concentration, 5 mM, was </p>

<p>nearly 300-fold higher than the K d for G · T substrate </p>

<p>binding determined here (see below). These saturating 
enzyme conditions provide the maximal rate constant 
for product formation (k &amp; k max ). </p>

<p>We also determined the maximal rate of product forma-
tion using kinetics experiments as described above, but 
with saturating substrate conditions ([S] &gt;&gt; K d , and 
[S] &gt;&gt; [E]) (22,33). The data were fitted to Equation (2) 
using nonlinear regression with <rs id="software-12" type="software">Grafit</rs> <rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-number">6</rs>: </p>

<p>product ð nMÞ ¼ Að1 À e 
Àkt Þ+vt 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>where A and k are the amplitude and rate constant of the 
exponential phase, v is steady-state velocity and t is time. 
The steady-state rate constant (k cat ) is calculated by 
dividing steady-state velocity by enzyme concentration. </p>

<p>Fluorescence anisotropy experiments and data fitting </p>

<p>Equilibrium binding of TDG to DNA was studied by fluor-
escence anisotropy using a QuantaMaster 40 
spectrofluorometer (PTI), monitoring the fluorescence 
of sulphorhodamine (Texas Red, or TR) conjugated to 
the 5 
0 -end of the non-target strand (Figure 2). Previous 
studies show the benefits of using X-rhodamine or 
sulphorhodamine for monitoring protein nucleic acid 
interactions by fluorescence anisotropy (35-37). TDG 
was titrated into HEMN.1 buffer (above) that contained 
TR-labeled DNA, supplemented with 1% glycerol and 
1 uM BSA. The DNA concentration was maintained at a 
fixed value throughout the titration by adding concentrated 
enzyme in buffer that also contained DNA. After each 
addition of TDG, the sample was incubated for at least 
2 min before data collection to ensure binding was at equi-
librium. This was confirmed by observation that the anisot-
ropy was constant for at least 5 min (for some data points). 
Anisotropy data were collected in T-format, where one 
PMT is connected directly to the sample compartment 
(no monochromator) with wavelength selection provided 
by a 628-nm band pass filter (Semrock, Inc.). The excitation 
wavelength was 590 nm (3-nm band pass) and the 
single-emission monochromator was set to 615 nm (5-nm 
band pass). Wavelength selection for the monochromators 
was enhanced with 586 and 624 nm band-pass filters 
(Semrock, Inc.) for excitation and emission, respectively. 
The equilibrium dissociation constants for TDG binding 
to TR-labeled DNA were determined by fitting the fluor-
escence anisotropy data to appropriate models using 
<rs id="software-5" type="software">DynaFit</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">4</rs> (38,39). The models and <rs type="software">DynaFit</rs> scripts used 
for data fitting are given in the Supplementary Data. The 
fitted parameters included dissociation constants for one or 
two binding sites on the DNA, and anisotropy values for 
free DNA (r D ) and for 1:1 and 2:1 complexes with TDG 
(r ED and r EED ). In many cases, the data clearly indicate two 
nonequivalent binding sites. Model discrimination was also 
informed by the probability value of the Fisher's F-statistic, 
obtained from data fitting, where P &lt; 0.05 is considered 
significant. The reported parameters are derived from 
global fitting of at least two independent binding experi-
ments. We determined the equilibrium dissociation 
constant for TDG binding to unlabeled DNA using equi-
librium competition anisotropy experiments, where TDG 
binding to TR-labeled 16U 
F 11 was monitored in the 
presence of varying concentrations of unlabeled DNA. 
<rs type="software">DynaFit</rs> was used for global fitting of the data to a 
model involving one or two TDG binding sites for the </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 6 2321 </p>

<p>unlabeled DNA and two binding sites for TR-labeled 
16U 
F 11. A benefit of using <rs type="software">DynaFit</rs> for the data presented 
here is that data fitting does not require an analytical 
equation, which could involve assumptions that are not 
compatible with experimental restraints. Indeed, the 
standard model for two nonequivalent binding sites 
assumes the species being monitored (DNA) is present at 
much lower concentration than the dissociation constant. 
This is not feasible for monitoring TDG binding to 
16U 
F 11, because the minimal DNA concentration needed 
for sufficient sensitivity in the anisotropy experiment 
(0.5 nM) approximates the dissociation constant 
(K d1 = 0.6 nM, see below). </p>

<p>Electrophoretic mobility shift assays </p>

<p>EMSAs were performed, essentially as described (18), to 
provide an independent method for determining the stoi-
chiometry of TDG-DNA complexes. The EMSAs were 
performed with precast 6% polyacrylamide native gels 
(Invitrogen) and analyzed using a Typhoon 9400 imager 
(GE Healthcare). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Experimental approach </p>

<p>We used fluorescence anisotropy and EMSAs to determine 
the affinity and stoichiometry for TDG binding to DNA 
containing a U 
F or a T 
F substrate analog, an abasic (or AP) 
site, an undamaged CpG site, and nonspecific DNA. We 
and others have shown the U 
F and T 
F analogs are excellent 
mimics of the natural dU and dT substrates, because they 
allow formation of the catalytically competent enzyme-
substrate complex in the absence of base excision 
(22,26,27,29). The U 
F and T 
F analogs differ from dU and 
dT only by replacement of 2 
0 -H with fluorine (2 
0 -fluoro-
arabino, Figure 2), which renders the base-sugar 
(N-glycosylic bond) of these and other nucleotides highly 
resistant to spontaneous and enzymatic cleavage. Previous 
studies show the 2 
0 -fluoroarabino substitution, in dT and 
other deoxynucleotides, promotes an O4 
0 -endo sugar 
pucker (rather than C2 
0 -endo), which is fully compatible 
with B-DNA geometry (28,40,41). Although the O4 
0 -endo 
conformation in a substrate analog could potentially alter 
the binding of a DNA glycosylase, our previous studies 
indicate the effect is small for TDG binding to DNA con-
taining a T 
F analog (22). 
Our studies employed two different DNA lengths 
(Figure 2), one that can accommodate 2:1 binding as 
observed in the TDG AP-DNA crystal structure 
(16X11, X = target nucleotide) and a shorter construct 
(3X11) that lacks the nonspecific binding site seen in the 
crystal structure (Figure 1). For all DNAs used here, the </p>

<p>target base is paired with guanine (i.e. G · T </p>

<p>F ), in keeping 
with the specificity of TDG (19,21). 
For the fluorescence anisotropy experiments, the DNA 
was labeled with sulphorhodamine (Texas Red, TR) as 
indicated in Figure 2. Previous studies indicate 
sulphorhodamine and X-rhodamine are well suited for 
characterizing protein-DNA interactions (35-37,42,43). 
When conjugated to DNA, these fluorophores are bright </p>

<p>and typically exhibit fluorescence decay that is dominated 
by a single lifetime and relatively independent of condi-
tions and protein binding, and their anisotropy is strongly 
correlated with DNA rotation, with minimal contribution 
from independent fluorophore mobility. These properties 
are highly desirable for studying protein-DNA inter-
actions, particularly for complex binding mechanisms as 
shown below for TDG. </p>

<p>TDG binding to a G · U mispair </p>

<p>We first consider equilibrium binding of TDG to 16U 
F 11, 
which is long enough to accommodate 2:1 binding as </p>

<p>observed in the TDG · AP-DNA crystal structure </p>

<p>(Figure 3A). As shown in Figure 3B, the fluorescence 
anisotropy data clearly indicate two nonequivalent 
binding sites, and fitting to a two-site model reveals a 
huge difference in affinity, K d1 = 0.63 ± 0.16 nM and 
K d2 = 662 ± 108 nM (Table 1). Thus, TDG forms a very </p>

<p>tight 1:1 complex with the G · U </p>

<p>F site, and a second TDG 
subunit binds with 1000-fold weaker affinity to give a 2:1 
complex at high TDG concentrations. TDG binding to 
16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 was qualitatively assessed using an EMSA, 
which confirms the binding stoichiometry indicted by the 
anisotropy data (Figure 3C). 
We also examined TDG binding to 3U 
F 11, a DNA con-
struct which lacks the entire binding site for the second 
TDG subunit of the 2:1 complex, as seen in the crystal 
structure (Figure 1. The anisotropy data show TDG forms </p>

<p>a tight 1:1 complex with the G · U </p>

<p>F site of 3U 
F 11, 
K d1 = 8.4 ± 2.9 nM, and a second TDG subunit can 
bind with very weak affinity, K d2 = 2650 ± 463 nM 
(Figure 3D). The results of an EMSA confirm this 
binding stoichiometry (Figure 3E). Although 2:1 binding 
to 3U 
F 11 is observed at high TDG concentrations, the 
second subunit must bind an alternate site from that 
seen in the crystal structure, as discussed below. Kinetics 
experiments show this alternate 2:1 complex does not con-</p>

<p>tribute to G · U binding or processing, because catalytic </p>

<p>activity is nearly the same for conditions that give 2:1 
binding (saturating TDG) or 1:1 binding (saturating sub-
strate, Supplementary Figure S.2). The finding that TDG 
binds tightly to 3U 
F 11 shows the 2:1 complex observed in 
the crystal structure is not required for specific recognition </p>

<p>of a G · U lesion, consistent with previous kinetics experi-
ments showing 2:1 binding is not needed for full G · U </p>

<p>catalytic activity (18). 
A number of observations suggest the alternate 2:1 
complex for 3U 
F 11 (and other 3X11 DNAs) involves tran-
sient and nonspecific binding of the catalytic domain and/ 
or the N-terminal region of TDG to DNA, and perhaps 
some degree of protein-protein interactions. Sedimentation 
velocity experiments show TDG is predominantly a 
monomer at concentrations of 20 and 50 mM 
(Supplementary Figure S3). This indicates the alternate 
2:1 complex, with K d2 = 2.7 mM (for 3U 
F 11), is not 
comprised solely of protein-protein interactions (though 
such interactions might be enhanced for DNA-bound 
TDG). Previous studies show the disordered N-terminal 
domain of TDG (residues 1-120) forms nonspecific inter-
actions with DNA (25,44), which may contribute to the </p>



<p>alternate 2:1 complex. Consistent with this, K d2 is much 
weaker for the catalytic domain (TDG-core, 111-308), 
which binds 3U 
F 11 with K d1 = 83 ± 46 nM and 
K d2 = 21 ± 3 mM (Supplementary Figure S4). Previous </p>

<p>sedimentation velocity experiments show TDG-core is 
fully monomeric at 120 mM (18). Thus, K d2 = 21 mM for 
TDG-core binding to 3U 
F 11 suggests the catalytic 
domain also exhibits nonspecific DNA interactions, 
because DNA binding seems unlikely to promote 
protein-protein interactions for TDG-core (18,45). 
Although the detailed nature of the alternate 2:1 complex 
is not presently clear, it only arises for large and excess 
concentrations of TDG, and it does not substantially 
alter catalytic activity. </p>

<p>TDG binding to a G · T mispair </p>

<p>The anisotropy and EMSA data for TDG binding to 
16T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11, a G · T substrate analog that can accommodate </p>

<p>2:1 binding, are shown in Figure 4A and B. Inspection of 
the anisotropy data suggests two nonequivalent sites, and 
fitting to a two-site model reveals tight binding of one TDG </p>

<p>subunit to the G · T </p>

<p>F site, K d1 = 18 ± 3 nM, and weak 
binding of a second TDG subunit to give a 2:1 complex, 
K d2 = 1279 ± 279 nM. The total change in anisotropy 
(Ár = 0.090) is nearly identical to that observed for </p>

<p>Figure 3. TDG binding to G · U </p>

<p>F substrate analogs monitored by fluorescence anisotropy and EMSA. (A) Model for sequential 2:1 binding of TDG 
to two different sites on a 28 bp DNA with a 16X11 construct. (B) Anisotropy data for equilibrium binding of TDG to the 16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 substrate analog 
(0.5 nM), obtained from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting the data to a two-site binding model using <rs id="software-9" type="software">DynaFit</rs> <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">4</rs> 
gives K d1 = 0.63 ± 0.16 nM and K d2 = 662 ± 108 nM, and anisotropy values of r D = 0.182, r ED = 0.220, r EED = 0.275. (C) EMSA for TDG binding 
to 16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 (0.5 uM), with the [TDG]:[DNA] ratio indicated. Arrows indicate anisotropy values or gel bands corresponding to free DNA (D), the 1:1 
complex (ED), and the 2:1 complex (EED). (D) Anisotropy data for TDG binding to the 3U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 analog (0.5 nM) from two independent experiments 
(open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site binding model gives K d1 = 8.4 ± 2.9 nM and K d2 = 2650 ± 463 nM (and r D = 0.144, r ED = 0.170, 
r EED = 0.247). (E) EMSA for TDG binding to 3U 
F 11 (0.5 uM). </p>

<p>Table 1. Equilibrium dissociation constants for TDG binding to 
specific and nonspecific DNA </p>

<p>DNA 
K d1 (nM) 
K d2 (nM) 
K d2 /K d1 </p>

<p>16U 
F 11 
0.63 ± 0.16 
662 ± 108 
1051 
3U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 
8.4 ± 2.9 
2650 ± 463 
315 
16T 
F 11 
18 ± 3 
1279 ± 279 
71 
3T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 
124 ± 25 
818 ± 80 
7 
16AP11 
1.4 ± 0.4 
1926 ± 762 
1376 
3AP11 
6.2 ± 1.3 
3480 ± 1173 
561 
16C11 
63 ± 10 
965 ± 148 
15 
NS28 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>293 ± 64 
1172 ± 254 
4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a Parameters obtained from equilibrium competition experiments fitted 
to a model for two equivalent and independent binding sites (restrained 
to K d2 = 4*K d1 ). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 6 2323 </p>

<p>16U 
F 11 (Ár = 0.093). The EMSA for TDG binding to 
16T 
F 11 confirms 1:1 binding at lower TDG:DNA ratios 
and 2:1 binding at high TDG concentrations. The anisot-
ropy data for TDG binding to 3T 
F 11 (Figure 4C), which 
cannot accommodate 2:1 binding (crystallographic), indi-</p>

<p>cates relatively tight binding to the G · T site, </p>

<p>K d1 = 124 ± 25 nM, and weak binding of a second TDG 
subunit, K d2 = 818 ± 80 nM, to give an alternate 2:1 
complex. The EMSA for TDG binding to 3T 
F 11 is consist-
ent with this binding stoichiometry (Figure 4D). The rela-
tively tight binding of TDG to 3T 
F 11 shows the 2:1 
complex in the crystal structure is not required for </p>

<p>specific binding of TDG to a G · T mispair. 
2:1 binding is not required for G · T repair activity 
Our results indicate 2:1 binding to G · T mispairs is highly </p>

<p>unlikely under limiting enzyme conditions, because K d2 is 
weak, and K d2 &gt;&gt; K d1 . Nevertheless, we sought to deter-
mine whether 2:1 binding, if it occurs, could enhance </p>

<p>catalytic activity for G · T substrates. We showed previous-
ly that 2:1 binding is dispensable for G · U activity (18), 
but the result could potentially differ for G · T activity, 
since binding and catalysis is much weaker for G · T 
relative to G · U substrates (Table 1) (19,22). We used </p>

<p>single turnover kinetics experiments with saturating </p>

<p>TDG (5000 nM) and limiting G · T substrate (500 nM) </p>

<p>such that 2:1 binding predominates. As shown in 
Figure 5A, the maximal rate of base excision is the same </p>

<p>for a G · T substrate that can accommodate 2:1 binding </p>

<p>(k max = 0.16 ± 0.03 min 
À1 ) and one that cannot 
(k max = 0.14 ± 0.03 min 
À1 ). We conclude 2:1 binding </p>

<p>does not enhance catalytic activity for G · T substrates. </p>

<p>We also approached this question using pre-steady-
state multiple turnover kinetics, collected with saturating </p>

<p>G · T substrate (2000 nM) and limiting TDG (200 nM), </p>

<p>such that 2:1 binding is negligible (Figure 5B). Under 
these conditions, TDG exhibits an exponential phase, 
k obs = 0.12 ± 0.02 min 
À1 , reflecting the maximal rate of 
base excision, followed by a much slower steady-state </p>

<p>Figure 4. TDG binding to G · T </p>

<p>F substrate analogs monitored by fluorescence anisotropy and EMSAs. (A) Anisotropy data for equilibrium binding 
of TDG to 16T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 (0.5 nM), obtained from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site binding model gives 
K d1 = 18 ± 3 nM, and K d2 = 1279 ± 279 nM (and anisotropy of r D = 0.189, r ED = 0.237, r EED = 0.278). (B) EMSA for TDG binding to 16T 
F 11 
(0.5 uM); the [TDG]:[DNA] ratio is indicated. (C) Anisotropy data for TDG binding to 3T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 (0.5 nM) obtained from two independent experiments 
(open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site model gives K d1 = 124 ± 25 nM, and K d2 = 818 ± 80 nM (and r D = 0.150, r ED = 0.176, 
r EED = 0.273). To obtain a proper fit it was necessary to fix r ED = 0.176, which is based on r D = 0.150 (fitted for 3T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11) and Ár for 1:1 binding 
to 3U 
F 11 (Ár 1:1 = r ED À r D = 0.026). (If r ED is not fixed, K d2 and r EED are poorly constrained and unreasonably high). The data are better fitted to a 
two-site rather than one-site binding model (P = 0.011). Moreover, 2:1 binding to 3T 
F 11 is indicated by observation that the total anisotropy change 
is slightly larger for 3T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 (r EED À r D = Ár tot = 0.123) than for 3U 
F 11 (Ár tot = 0.103), for which 2:1 binding is demonstrated by anisotropy and 
EMSA. (D) EMSA for TDG binding to 3T 
F 11 (0.5 uM). Low population of the 2:1 complex at the highest TDG:DNA ratio is likely due to 
dissociation during electrophore2sis, as 3T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 exhibits very rapid dissociation (k off ) from TDG (unpublished data). </p>



<p>phase (33). Observation that the maximal base excision 
rate is nearly the same for conditions of saturating TDG </p>

<p>or saturating G · T substrate confirms that 2:1 binding, if it 
occurs, does not substantially enhance G · T activity. </p>

<p>TDG binding to abasic DNA product </p>

<p>It is also important to determine the stoichiometry and 
affinity for TDG binding to its abasic (or AP) DNA 
product. Anisotropy data for TDG binding to 16AP11 </p>

<p>DNA, which contains a G · AP site and is long enough </p>

<p>to accommodate 2:1 binding, are shown in Figure 6A. 
The anisotropy data indicate two nonequivalent sites, 
and fitting to a two-site model reveals tight binding of 
one TDG subunit to the AP site, K d1 = 1.4 ± 0.4 nM 
and very weak binding of a second TDG subunit to give 
a 2:1 complex, K d2 = 1926 ± 762 nM. The EMSA for 
TDG binding to 16AP11 (Figure 6B) confirms the 
binding stoichiometry indicated by anisotropy; 1:1 
binding at lower TDG:DNA ratios and 2:1 binding for 
large and excess TDG concentrations. 
Anisotropy data for TDG binding to 3AP11 indicates 
relatively 
tight 
binding 
to the </p>

<p>G · AP site, </p>

<p>K d1 = 6.2 ± 1.3 nM, and very weak binding of a second 
TDG subunit to give an alternate 2:1 complex, 
K d2 = 3480 ± 1173 nM (Figure 6C). The stoichiom-
etry and relative affinities indicated by the anisotropy </p>

<p>experiments are qualitatively confirmed by an EMSA 
(Figure 6D). The tight binding of a single TDG 
subunit to 3AP11 shows that a second TDG subunit </p>

<p>is not required for specific binding to a G · AP product </p>

<p>site. </p>

<p>TDG binding to an undamaged CpG site </p>

<p>It is known that TDG is specific for G · T mispairs and </p>

<p>other lesions located in a CpG sequence context 
(19,21,23,46), but the affinity of TDG for an undamaged 
CpG site had not been determined. Such knowledge is </p>

<p>important for understanding how TDG locates G · T </p>

<p>mispairs arising at CpG sites and its role(s) in transcrip-
tional regulation. We previously showed TDG exhibits 
exceedingly low activity for cleaving cytosine from a 
CpG site (&lt;1% product in 8 h), thus binding studies can 
be performed in the absence of base cleavage (24). 
Anisotropy and EMSA data for TDG binding to 28-bp 
DNA containing a CpG site (16C11) are shown in 
Figure 7A and 7B. The anisotropy data indicate that 
TDG binds the CpG site with remarkably tight affinity, 
K d1 = 63 ± 10 nM, and a second TDG subunit binds with 
much weaker affinity, K d2 = 965 ± 148 nM, at high TDG 
concentrations. The EMSA confirms the stoichiometry 
indicated by the anisotropy data. </p>

<p>Figure 6. TDG binding to abasic (AP) DNA product monitored by 
fluorescence anisotropy and EMSA. (A) Anisotropy data for equilib-
rium binding of TDG to 16AP11 (0.5 nM). Fitting to a two-site binding 
model gives K d1 = 1.4 ± 0.4 nM and K d2 = 1926 ± 762 nM (and anisot-
ropy of r D = 0.178, r ED = 0.233, r EED = 0.276). Due to slow dissoci-
ation of AP DNA from TDG, the anisotropy data were collected using 
individual samples that were incubated for at least 2 h prior to data 
collection to ensure equilibration. Our unpublished data by 
stopped-flow and other kinetic methods show 2 h is sufficient for equili-
bration (confirmed in some cases by repeating measurements after add-
itional equilibration time). (B) EMSA for TDG binding to 16AP11 
(0.5 uM), with the [TDG]:[DNA] ratio indicated. (C) Anisotropy data 
for TDG binding to 3AP11 (0.5 nM) obtained from two independent 
experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to a two-site binding 
model gives K d1 = 6.2 ± 1.3 nM and K d2 = 3480 ± 1173 nM (and an-
isotropy of r D = 0.144, r ED = 0.200 and r EED = 0.271). (D) EMSA 
for TDG binding to 3AP11 (0.5 uM). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Kinetics experiments show 2:1 binding is not needed for pro-</p>

<p>cessing G · T substrates. (A) Single turnover kinetics collected with 
saturating TDG (5000 nM) and limiting G · T substrate (500 nM), one </p>

<p>of which can accommodate 2:1 binding (16T11, open circle) and one 
that cannot (4T11, open rectangle). Fitting the data (multiple experi-
ments) to Equation (1) gives k max = 0.16 ± 0.03 min 
À1 (16T11) and 
k max = 0.14 ± 0.03 min 
À1 (4T11). We note that 4T11 is the minimal </p>

<p>DNA construct that provides full G · T activity, due likely to </p>

<p>non-specific interactions between the DNA (5 
0 of the dT target) and 
the N-terminal region of TDG (unpublished data). However, 4T11 still 
lacks the entire binding site for the second TDG subunit as seen in the 
crystal structure (Figure 1). (B) Pre-steady-state multiple-turnover </p>

<p>kinetics collected with saturating G · T substrate (2000 nM) and </p>

<p>limiting TDG (200 nM). Fitting the data (multiple experiments) for 
16T11 (open circle) to Equation (2) gives a rate constant of 
k obs = 0.12 ± 0.02 min 
À1 and amplitude A = 134 ± 3 nM for the expo-
nential phase, and a rate constant of k cat = 0.0006 ± 0.0003 min 
À1 for 
the steady-state phase. The parameters are very similar for 4T11 (open 
rectangle); 
k obs = 0.12 ± 0.02 min 
À1 , 
A = 117 ± 3 nM, 
and 
k cat = 0.0002 ± 0.0001 min 
À1 . Observation of slightly greater amplitude 
for 16T11 indicates 1:1 binding to both substrates, because 4T11 cannot 
accommodate 2:1 binding, consistent with other results above. For </p>

<p>G · T substrates, we typically find A &lt; [TDG]. However, for G · U and 
G · FU substrates, we find A = $[TDG], indicating TDG is fully active </p>

<p>(Supplementary Figure S1). We are currently investigating the basis of </p>

<p>the diminished amplitude for G · T substrates. However, this does not 
alter our conclusion that 2:1 binding is not needed for G · T activity. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 6 2325 </p>

<p>To obtain another measure of TDG affinity for an un-
damaged CpG site, we performed equilibrium competition 
experiments, by collecting anisotropy data for TDG 
binding to 16U 
F 11 (labeled) in the presence of two differ-
ent concentrations of unlabeled 16C11 (Figure 7C). 
Global fitting of all the data to a model describing two 
TDG binding sites for 16U 
F 11 and 16C11 gives 
K d1 = 26 ± 8 nM for 1:1 binding to 16C11, but K d2 is 
poorly constrained by the data (and unreasonably large). 
The global fitting provides another measure of TDG 
affinity for 16U 
F 11 in the presence of a DNA competitor, 
giving dissociation constants identical to those obtained in 
the absence of 16C11. Our results show TDG binds tightly 
to undamaged CpG sites, with an affinity that is merely </p>

<p>4-fold lower than for G · T mispairs. </p>

<p>TDG binding to nonspecific DNA </p>

<p>To gain perspective on the binding affinity of the second 
TDG subunit (K d2 ) of the 2:1 complex, which binds a 
nonspecific region of DNA (Figure 1), we determined 
the affinity of TDG for binding DNA that is entirely 
nonspecific (contains no mispair or CpG site). We 
determined the affinity of TDG for 28-bp nonspecific 
DNA (NS28) using equilibrium competition binding ex-
periments, by collecting anisotropy data for TDG binding 
to 16U 
F 11 (labeled) in the presence of fixed concentrations 
of unlabeled NS28 (Figure 8A). Global fitting of data col-
lected in the presence and absence of NS28 to a competi-
tive model describing two binding sites for 16U 
F 11 and 
two equivalent and independent binding sites for NS28 </p>

<p>Figure 7. TDG binding to DNA containing a single CpG site, monitored by fluorescence anisotropy and an EMSA. (A) Anisotropy data for 
equilibrium binding of TDG to the 28-bp 16C11 DNA (0.5 nM) obtained from two independent experiments (open circle, open rectangle). Fitting to 
a two-site binding model gives K d1 = 63 ± 10 nM, and K d2 = 965 ± 148 nM (and anisotropy of r D = 0.180, r ED = 0.223, r EED = 0.275). To obtain a 
good fit, it was necessary to fix r ED = 0.223. This value is the sum of r D = 0.180 (fitted for 16C11) and Ár 1:1 = 0.043 (average of Ár 1:1 values for 
16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 and 16T </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11). Otherwise, the fitted r ED is unreasonably high (0.25), and K d2 and r EED are poorly constrained. The data are better fitted to 
model for two-site versus one-site binding (dashed line, P = 0.010). (B) EMSA for TDG binding to 16C11 (0.5 uM), with the [TDG]:[DNA] ratios 
given. (C) Equilibrium competition anisotropy experiments for TDG binding to TR-labeled 16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 (0.5 nM) collected in the absence of 16C11 (open 
circle and open triangle, data from Figure 3B) and in the presence of 16C11 at a concentration of 50 nM (open rectangle) or 125 nM (open rhombus). 
The data were fitted globally to model with two TDG binding sites for 16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 and 16C11, giving K d1 = 26 ± 8 nM for 16C11, and 
K d1 = 0.59 ± 0.14 nM and K d2 = 673 ± 100 nM for 16U 
F 11 (anisotropy for 16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 of r D = 0.182, r ED = 0.221, r EED = 0.274). K d2 for 16C11 is 
poorly constrained by the data (and unreasonably large). Fitting the data to a competition model with one site for 16C11 gives the same K d1 (within 
error). However, the data in (A) and (B) show TDG can form a 2:1 complex with 16C11. </p>

<p>Figure 8. TDG binding to nonspecific DNA monitored fluorescence anisotropy and an EMSA. (A) Equilibrium competition anisotropy experiments 
for TDG binding to TR-labeled 16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 (0.5 nM) collected in the absence of NS28 (open circle, open triangle) and with NS28 concentrations of 
200 nM (open rectangle) or 500 nM (open rhombus). Global fitting of all data to model involving two TDG binding sites for 16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 and two 
equivalent and independent sites for NS28 (i.e. restrained to K d2 = 4*K d1 ) gives K d1 = 293 ± 64 nM and K d2 = 1172 ± 254 nM for NS28. For 
16U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11, the fitting gives K d1 = 0.88 ± 0.13 nM and K d2 = 654 ± 62 nM (and anisotropy of r D = 0.189, r ED = 0.221, r EED = 0.278). Fitting the 
data to a model involving a single site for NS28 gives essentially the same result for NS28 binding, K d1 = 279 ± 69 nM, and for the 16U 
F 11 
parameters (data not shown). (B) EMSA for TDG binding to 28 bp nonspecific DNA (NS28, 0.5 uM) with the [TDG]:[DNA] ratio indicated. </p>



<p>(i.e. restrained to K d2 = 4*K d1 ) gives K d1 = 293 ± 64 nM 
and K d2 = 1172 ± 254 nM. The latter value falls in the 
range of K d2 values for other DNAs examined here 
(Table 1). Fitting the data to a model with just one site 
for NS28 gives essentially the same result, 
K d1 = 279 ± 69 nM. However, the two-site model is con-
sistent with a binding analysis by EMSA (Figure 8B), 
which shows a 1:1 complex at lower [TDG]/[NS28] 
ratios and a 2:1 complex for large and excess TDG con-
centrations. Global fitting of the data in Figure 8A also 
provides a measure of TDG affinity for 16U 
F 11 in the 
presence of nonspecific DNA, and gives essentially the 
same dissociation constants as obtained in the absence 
of NS28. Our findings show TDG possesses substantial 
affinity for nonspecific DNA. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The remarkable observation from previous structural 
and biochemical studies that TDG can bind abasic DNA 
with 1:1 or 2:1 stoichiometry (18) raised the important 
questions of whether 2:1 binding contributes to the </p>

<p>ability of TDG to find and initiate the repair of G · T and 
G · U lesions or to the mechanism by which APE1 stimu-</p>

<p>lates TDG activity. We investigated these questions by 
determining the stoichiometry and affinity for TDG </p>

<p>binding to a G · U or G · T substrate analog, an abasic </p>

<p>site, an undamaged CpG site, and to nonspecific DNA. 
Our findings provide insight into how TDG recognizes </p>

<p>and processes G · U mispairs. TDG forms a very tight 1:1 
complex with a G · U mispair (K d1 = 0.6 nM, Table 1), and </p>

<p>a second subunit can bind with much weaker affinity 
(K d2 = 660 nM) for high concentrations of TDG that are </p>

<p>in great excess over G · U DNA. The tight binding to a 
G · U mispair observed here is consistent with previous 
results using DNA containing a G · U </p>

<p>F analog (26). 
TDG also binds tightly to 3U </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>11 (K d = 8 nM), showing 
the 2:1 complex observed in the TDG crystal structure is </p>

<p>not needed for specific recognition of a G · U mispair. This </p>

<p>is consistent with our previous kinetics experiments </p>

<p>showing 1:1 binding provides full G · U catalytic activity </p>

<p>(18). The 1000-fold difference in binding affinity for the 
two sites of the 2:1 complex, and the weak affinity of the 
second site relative to nonspecific DNA (NS28), indicates 
that under conditions of limiting enzyme and a huge </p>

<p>excess of nonspecific DNA, TDG processes G · U lesions </p>

<p>with 1:1 stoichiometry. This conclusion is supported by 
previous footprinting experiments, which indicated 1:1 </p>

<p>binding to DNA containing a G · U </p>

<p>F analog under condi-
tions of limiting TDG (26). However, given that other </p>

<p>glycosylases process G · U lesions much more efficiently </p>

<p>than TDG, the more relevant question is whether 2:1 </p>

<p>binding contributes to repair of G · T lesions, the </p>

<p>primary biological target of TDG. 
Our results indicate that TDG also binds and processes </p>

<p>G · T lesions with 1:1 stoichiometry. TDG binds tightly 
to 28 bp DNA containing a G · T substrate analog </p>

<p>(K d1 = 18 nM), and a second subunit binds with much 
weaker affinity (K d2 = 1280 nM) for large and excess 
concentrations of TDG. The large difference in affinity </p>

<p>for the two sites (K d2 /K d1 = 71) and the weak affinity of 
TDG for the second site (K d2 ) relative to nonspecific DNA </p>

<p>indicates 2:1 binding to G · T mispairs is unlikely for </p>

<p>cellular conditions of limiting TDG and a large excess of 
nonspecific DNA. Moreover, the relatively tight affinity of 
TDG for 3T 
F 11 indicates the 2:1 complex is not needed </p>

<p>for specific recognition of G · T lesions. Finally, our </p>

<p>kinetics experiments show that 1:1 binding provides full </p>

<p>catalytic activity for G · T processing. 
We find TDG binds a G · T mispair with about 30-fold 
weaker affinity than a G · U mispair. This is likely ex-</p>

<p>plained by the methyl group at C5 of thymine (uracil 
has hydrogen at C5), which may diminish the lifetime of 
the dT nucleotide in the flipped state due to steric hin-
drance in the TDG active site, as suggested by our </p>

<p>previous kinetics results (21,22,24). Given that G · T </p>

<p>lesions arising at CpG sites are likely the predominant 
biological target of TDG (21,23), one might expect TDG </p>

<p>to have evolved to bind more tightly to G · T mispairs. The 
weaker affinity for G · T mispairs may reflect a comprom-</p>

<p>ise between the competing needs for efficient processing of </p>

<p>G · T lesions and avoiding the excision of T from the huge 
excess of A · T base pairs, which is governed in part by the 
18 000-fold specificity of TDG for excising T from G · T 
versus A · T pairs (21). </p>

<p>Previous studies show TDG binds tightly to its AP 
DNA product, and that AP DNA is a potent inhibitor 
of the TDG reaction (32,33,47). Our anisotropy results 
here show TDG forms a very tight 1:1 complex with its </p>

<p>reaction product, a G · AP site (K d1 = 1.4 nM), and a </p>

<p>second subunit binds with much weaker affinity 
(K d2 = 1.9 mM) for large and excess concentrations of 
TDG. The huge difference in affinity for the two sites 
(K d2 /K d1 = 1376) and the weak affinity of TDG for the 
second site (K d2 ) relative to nonspecific DNA indicates 
2:1 binding to abasic sites is unlikely for cellular condi-
tions of limiting TDG and excess nonspecific DNA. The 
conclusion that a second TDG subunit is not needed for </p>

<p>tight binding to G · AP sites is supported by the high </p>

<p>affinity of TDG for 3AP11 (K d1 = 6 nM). 
Our findings have important implications for the stimu-
lation of TDG activity by the follow-on base excision 
repair enzyme, APE1 (32). We previously showed that 
APE1 greatly enhances TDG activity, increasing its rate </p>

<p>of steady-state turnover (k cat ) by 42-and 26-fold for G · T 
and G · U substrates, respectively (33). Our results here </p>

<p>indicate that under the conditions used for these 
previous studies, limiting concentrations of TDG (and 
APE1) and a saturating amount of TDG substrate, 
TDG binds its product with 1:1 stoichiometry. Thus, the 
stimulatory effect of APE1 does not involve a TDG 
product complex with 2:1 stoichiometry. Consistent with 
this conclusion, we previously observed potent stimulation 
of TDG by APE1 for a short DNA that cannot accom-
modate two TDG subunits (3U12 substrate or 3AP12 
product) (33). Together, these studies indicate the stimu-
latory effect of APE1 involves a TDG product complex 
with 1:1 stoichiometry. 
The affinity of TDG for an undamaged CpG site had 
not been quantitatively examined, despite the strong </p>

<p>specificity of TDG for G · T mispairs (and other </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 6 2327 </p>

<p>lesions) that are located in a CpG sequence context. We 
find TDG binds DNA containing a CpG site (16C11) with 
remarkable affinity, K d1 = 63 nM, about 4-fold weaker </p>

<p>than its affinity for the same DNA containing a G · T </p>

<p>lesion (Table 1). The specificity for a CpG site is also 
indicated by observation that TDG binds 4-fold tighter 
to 16C11 than to nonspecific DNA (NS28) that contains 
no CpG site but is otherwise identical. On an experimental 
note, our findings indicate that studies of TDG binding to </p>

<p>a particular site (i.e. a G · T mispair) should use DNA that </p>

<p>does not contain an undamaged CpG site. 
Preferential binding to CpG requires a mechanism for 
recognizing these sites within a large background of 
nonspecific DNA. Previous studies suggest TDG may ac-
complish this by transiently flipping 2 
0 -deoxycytidine (dC) 
out of a CpG site and into its active site (or flipping it 
partially into the active site). Our crystal structure indi-
cates specificity for excising lesions from a CpG site 
involves interactions with the 3 
0 -guanine (5 
0 -XpG, 
X = lesion) that cannot be formed in the absence of nu-
cleotide flipping (18), which suggests nucleotide (dC) 
flipping may be required for recognizing undamaged 
CpG sites. The ability of TDG to flip dC into its active 
site is indicated by our previous finding that TDG can 
cleave analogs of dC that have a weakened N-glycosylic 
bond (e.g. 5-fluoro-dC, 5-hydroxy-dC, etc.) (24). 
However, these results do not rule out a mechanism 
whereby TDG recognizes CpG sites in the absence of nu-
cleotide flipping. Further studies are needed to resolve this 
question. 
The ability of TDG to bind CpG sites and transiently 
flip dC into its active site, suggested by the findings 
herein and in our previous studies, may be important </p>

<p>in the search for G · T lesions arising from deamination </p>

<p>of m 
5 C, a modified base found selectively at CpG sites. 
In addition, the affinity of TDG for undamaged CpG 
sites and nonspecific DNA may be important for its 
ability to modulate the activity of transcription factors 
including retinoic acid and retinoid X receptors (48), 
estrogen receptor a (49) and thyroid transcription 
factor 1 (50), and co-activators such as CBP/p300 (51). 
Additional studies are needed to explore these ideas 
further. </p>

<p>In summary, we find TDG binds tightly to G · U and 
G · T mispairs, with subnanomolar and low nanomolar </p>

<p>affinity, respectively, and that 1:1 binding provides full </p>

<p>G · T repair activity. TDG forms a very tight 1:1 
complex with abasic (G · AP) sites, indicating the stimula-</p>

<p>tory effect of APE1 does not require 2:1 binding of TDG 
to its product. TDG binds tightly to undamaged CpG </p>

<p>sites, about 4-fold weaker than to G · T mispairs, and it </p>

<p>exhibits substantial affinity for nonspecific DNA. While 
2:1 binding to DNA is observed in vitro for large and 
excess concentrations of TDG, our results indicate that 
a single TDG subunit is fully capable of finding and pro-</p>

<p>cessing G · U and G · T lesions. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Petr Kuzmic for assistance with <rs type="software">DynaFit</rs>, Jim 
Stivers (Johns Hopkins University) for providing purified 
human uracil DNA glycosylase, L. Eisele (NY State 
Department of Health) for collecting sedimentation 
velocity analytical ultracentrifugation data and the review-
ers for excellent suggestions. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>The National Institutes of Health (R01-GM-072711). 
Funding for open access charge: National Institutes of 
Health, USA. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2011, Vol. 39, No. 6 2329 </p>

</text></tei>