<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC3112533" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>synchronous oscillations of thousands of cellular clocks in the suprachiasmatic nucleus (sCn), 
the circadian centre, are coordinated by precisely timed cell-cell communication, the principle 
of which is largely unknown. Here we show that the amount of RGs16 (regulator of G protein 
signalling 16), a protein known to inactivate Gαi, increases at a selective circadian time to allow 
time-dependent activation of intracellular cyclic AmP signalling in the sCn. Gene ablation of 
Rgs16 leads to the loss of circadian production of cAmP and as a result lengthens circadian 
period of behavioural rhythm. The temporally precise regulation of the cAmP signal by clock-
controlled RGs16 is needed for the dorsomedial sCn to maintain a normal phase-relationship 
to the ventrolateral sCn. Thus, RGs16-dependent temporal regulation of intracellular G protein 
signalling coordinates the intercellular synchrony of sCn pacemaker neurons and thereby 
defines the 24 h rhythm in behaviour. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:327 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>n mammals, the hypothalamic suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) is 
a central pacemaker, governing daily rhythms in behaviour and 
physiology </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>. Individual neurons in the SCN act as cell-autono-
mous oscillators, exhibiting circadian fluctuations of firing rate and 
gene expression </p>

<p>4-7 </p>

<p>. We and others have recently shown that autono-
mous SCN neuronal oscillators maintain a high degree of synchrony 
with each other, so that they can generate coherent signals required 
for the circadian control of behaviour and physiology </p>

<p>6-10 </p>

<p>. 
While individual SCN neurons share the same circadian period 
as a result of synchronization, the phases of their rhythms are strik-
ingly diverse </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>. This observation reflects the reality that the SCN is 
an anatomically heterologous cellular assemblage, in which cohorts 
of differentially phased cellular clocks are deployed in a topographi-
cally specific manner </p>

<p>11,12 </p>

<p>: neurons in the dorsomedial part of the 
SCN reach their daily peak in clock gene expression earlier in the 
day than those in the rest of the SCN. However, the mechanism by 
which dorsomedial SCN cells maintain their relatively advanced 
phasing, and to what extent this differential phasing influences the 
rhythms in behaviour have remained unknown. 
Much better understood is the molecular mechanism underlying 
cell-autonomous circadian oscillations. These rely on the opposing 
effects of transcriptional activators and repressors that generate nega-
tive feedback loops </p>

<p>13-15 </p>

<p>. Briefly, the transcriptional activators CLOCK 
and BMAL1 drive transcription of Period (Per1 and Per2) and 
Cryptochrome (Cry1 and Cry2) genes via binding to E-box elements 
present in their promoters. Once the repressor proteins PER and 
CRY reach a critical concentration, they form complexes and repress 
their own expression by inhibiting the CLOCK/BMAL1 complexes. 
In addition to E-box elements, the promoter regions of Per genes con-
tain D-boxes, through which the PAR bZip family of transcriptional 
activators (DBP, TEF and HLF) and the related repressor E4BP4 exert 
their opposing effects on the expression of target genes </p>

<p>16-20 </p>

<p>. Finely 
controlled transcriptional regulation through the E-box and D-box 
motifs is thought to generate robust circadian expression of Per genes 
as well as a wide variety of clock-controlled genes </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>. 
Although cell-autonomous transcriptional regulation of clock 
genes could provide a common mechanism underlying the oscilla-
tions of individual cells, this does not explain the phasic differences 
between the neurons in the SCN. In this regard, it is important to 
note that the promoter region of Per1 gene contains a functional 
cyclic AMP-responsive element </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>, and that the extracellular signal-
ling that activates cAMP pathway can acutely induce Per1 expres-
sion </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>. Because a light pulse given in the night time induces Per1 
expression in the SCN, this pathway has long been considered 
crucial for light-dependent resetting of the phase of the molecular 
clock </p>

<p>24-26 </p>

<p>. Yet, the cAMP-dependent control of Per1 may also have 
a role in coordinating circadian rhythms (phase-arrangement) of 
neurons in the SCN </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>. Supporting this hypothesis, the concentra-
tion of cAMP and transcriptional activity of the cAMP-responsive 
element in the SCN are both highly rhythmic even in constant dark-
ness </p>

<p>27-29 </p>

<p>. Moreover, pharmacological reduction in the rate of cAMP 
synthesis in the SCN lengthens the circadian period of the behav-
ioural rhythm </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>, demonstrating a role of cAMP in the determina-
tion of the circadian period. 
RGS16 is a potential regulator of rhythmic cAMP synthesis in 
the SCN. Biochemically, RGS16 functions as a GTPase-accelerating 
protein for Gαi/o subtypes of G protein α subunits </p>

<p>30-32 </p>

<p>. By promot-
ing GTP hydrolysis, RGS16 terminates GTP-bound (thus activated) 
Gαi/o signalling. Microarray studies and the subsequent expression 
analyses revealed that the gene encoding RGS16 exhibits circadian 
variations in the levels of transcript in the SCN </p>

<p>33-36 </p>

<p>. These data raise 
the possibility that Gαi/o-mediated cAMP signalling in the SCN is 
under circadian regulation via RGS16. 
Here we show that gene ablation of Rgs16 leads to the loss of 
circadian production of cAMP in the SCN, which results in a period 
lengthening of the locomotor activity rhythm. Extensive analysis of </p>

<p>the intercellular phase-relationship within the SCN reveals that the 
RGS16-mediated daily activation of cAMP is necessary to acceler-
ate the expression of Per1 in the dorsomedial cells. Our data there-
fore demonstrate that RGS16-mediated cAMP signalling defines 
the advanced phasing of dorsomedial cells, and as such, is a critical 
determinant for the period of circadian rhythms in behaviour. </p>

<p>Results 
Gene expression profiles of the RGS family in the SCN. It is 
known that pharmacological inhibition of Gαi/o activity with 
pertussis toxin hampers intercellular synchronization 
37 and causes 
dampened rhythms of the entire SCN (Supplementary Fig. S1) </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>. 
These observations prompted us to hypothesize that member(s) of 
the regulator of G protein signalling (RGS) family might contribute 
to synchronized cellular oscillations in the SCN. We surveyed all 
known mouse Rgs genes for their expression in the SCN by using 
DNA microarray analysis (Supplementary Fig. S2a). Then, the genes 
highly expressed in the SCN were selected and further analysed 
with quantitative in situ hybridization to specify their histological 
distribution and circadian time (CT)-dependent expression profile 
(Supplementary Fig. S2b) </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>. This survey led us to notice that Rgs16 
is the only RGS family member that displays marked SCN-specific 
expression particularly in the subjective daytime (see CT4 in 
Fig. 1a; CT4 corresponds to 4 h after subjective onset of daytime 
under constant dark conditions). This expression profile, together 
with a prior work showing that RGS16 regulates Gαi/o activity </p>

<p>31,32 </p>

<p>, 
raised the prospect that RGS16 contributes to SCN circadian clock 
physiology. </p>

<p>Cyclic expression of Rgs16 is driven by the circadian clock. Time-
dependent profiling revealed that Rgs16 exhibits overt circadian 
expression in the SCN (Fig. 1b), which persists even in constant 
darkness (DD) with a drastic increase of expression in the early 
subjective morning. Topographical analysis by digoxigenin in situ 
hybridization (Fig. 1c) further demonstrated that Rgs16 expression 
began to increase by subjective dawn (CT0) in the periventricular 
part of the dorsomedial SCN (a narrow but cell-dense area near the 
third ventricle). Thereafter, Rgs16-positive staining spread widely 
across the SCN at CT4. At CT8, Rgs16 levels began to decrease in all 
SCN regions, and throughout the subjective night (that is, CT12-
20) expression was limited to a few SCN cells. The spatiotemporal 
expression of Rgs16 resembles that of Per1, a clock gene showing 
peak messenger RNA expression during the daytime in the SCN </p>

<p>11,12 </p>

<p>. 
Similar to the Per1 promoter, the 5′-flanking genomic sequence 
of Rgs16 contains E-box and D-box cis-regulatory elements, thus 
allowing the circadian regulators CLOCK-BMAL1 and DBP to 
activate transcription. In a further parallel with Per1, CRY1 and 
E4BP4 repressed CLOCK-BMAL1-and DBP-evoked Rgs16 expres-
sion, respectively (Supplementary Figs. S3 and S4). Consistent with 
the promoter characteristics, in vivo circadian expression of Rgs16 
was dramatically altered in the PAR bZip proteins-deficient mice 
(Dbp 
-/-Tef 
-/-Hlf </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>) 
39 as well as Clock mutant and Cry1 
-/-Cry2 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>mice (Supplementary Fig. S4f). In Clock mutant mice, the early 
subjective day peak in Rgs16 expression was damped whereas in 
Cry1 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Cry2 
-/-mice Rgs16 expression was high at both the subjec-
tive day and night time points. These data clearly demonstrate that 
expression of Rgs16 is under the control of the intracellular clock 
machinery. It is also noteworthy that the expression of Rgs16 was 
not light-inducible (Supplementary Fig. S5). Thus, the internal clock 
seems to drive the morning expression of Rgs16 in the SCN. </p>

<p>RGS16 deficiency lengthens the circadian period of behaviour. 
To characterize the in vivo function of RGS16, we generated RGS16-
deficient mice, in which a genomic region spanning whole coding 
sequence of Rgs16 was deleted and replaced with a lacZ reporter 
cassette (Fig. 1d,e). In situ hybridization analysis (Fig. 1f) con-</p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:327 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>firmed the loss of the Rgs16 transcript in Rgs16 homozygous mutant 
(Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>) mice. β-galactosidase tissue staining (Fig. 1g) further cor-
roborated gene targeting and replacement by LacZ: the spatio-tem-
poral expression of the transgene reflected Rgs16 expression in the 
SCN. Moreover, we generated an antibody to RGS16 and performed 
immunoblot analysis with SCN extracts (Fig. 1h). As expected, the 
expression of RGS16 was not detected in Rgs16 
-/-mice, whereas 
wild-type (WT) mice exhibited an increased expression of RGS16 
protein in the subjective morning (Fig. 1h). We thus conclude that 
Rgs16 mutant mice are indeed RGS16-deficient. 
Behavioural analysis was performed with Rgs16 mutant mice 
that had been backcrossed to the C57BL/6J background over ten 
generations. We observed that the gene ablation of Rgs16 causes a 
lengthening of circadian period of the locomotor activity rhythm 
(Fig. 1i): under constant darkness, all Rgs16 
-/-mice tested (n = 27) 
showed a free-running period longer than 24 h (circadian period 
(mean ± s.e.m) determined with a χ 
2 periodogram, 24.28 ± 0.01 h). 
The phenotype of Rgs16 knockout sharply contrasts with that of 
Rgs16 
+ / + control mice (n = 29), whose period is shorter than 24 h 
(23.76 ± 0.01 h). The difference between the two genotypes is statis-
tically significant (Fig. 1j, P &lt; 0.001, Student's t-test) and does not 
depend on the way of measuring circadian period (periods deter-</p>

<p>mined with a linear regression line method: Rgs16 
+ / + , 23.77 ± 0.01 
h; Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>, 24.31 ± 0.01 h, P &lt; 0.001, Student's t-test), revealing that 
Rgs16 is a critical determinant of the behavioural rhythm period 
length. In contrast to the altered circadian periodicity under con-
stant darkness, Rgs16 
-/-mice displayed a normal 24 h rhythm when 
maintained in 12-h-light/12-h-dark cycle (Fig. 1i) and their reset-
ting response to early and late night light pulses were indistinguish-
able from WT mice (Supplementary Fig. S6). Thus, RGS16 is not 
necessary for light entrainment of the circadian clock. Rather, sig-
nalling through RGS16 comprises a pathway responsible for the 
maintenance of the normal circadian rhythm. </p>

<p>RGS16 targets Gαi and regulates cAMP production in the SCN. 
RGS16 is known to negatively regulate Gαi proteins, which down-
regulate cAMP production by inhibiting adenylate cyclase (AC) 
activity 
31,32 . Double in situ hybridization revealed that both Gnai1 
mRNA and Gnai2 mRNA (encoding Gαi1 and Gαi2, respec-
tively) colocalize with Rgs16 in SCN neurons (Fig. 2a). Intrigu-
ingly, whereas the levels of Gαi1 and Gαi2 proteins were nearly 
constant throughout the day, the amount of RGS16 protein in the 
SCN showed overt circadian oscillation (Fig. 2b). Consistent with 
the GTPase-accelerating protein activity of RGS16, protein pull-</p>

<p>a 
c 
e </p>

<p>i 
h 
j </p>

<p>b 
d </p>

<p>CT4 
CT16 
CT20 
CT12 
CT8 
CT0 </p>

<p>Relative mRNA 
abundance (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>SCN </p>

<p>CT4 
CT16 
Thalamus 
Mouse brain 
SCN-Gene Project </p>

<p>RGS family 
Rgs16 </p>

<p>0 
8 
12 
16 
20 
4 </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>CT: 
4 
16 
4 
16 </p>

<p>Anti-RGS16 </p>

<p>Anti-Gαi </p>

<p>Rgs16 
+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 
+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 
-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 
-/-</p>

<p>8.8 kb </p>

<p>11.0 kb </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>-/-
+/-
+/+ </p>

<p>LD </p>

<p>DD </p>

<p>Days 
14 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>0 
0 
12 
0 
12 </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>0 
0 
12 
0 
12 </p>

<p>Rgs16 
mRNA </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>oc </p>

<p>Circadian time </p>

<p>frt 
frt </p>

<p>loxP </p>

<p>ATG 
TGA </p>

<p>Probe </p>

<p>lox71 </p>

<p>LacZ-pA 
Neo </p>

<p>Kpn I 
Kpn I </p>

<p>Kpn I 
KpnI </p>

<p>Wild-type (+) allele </p>

<p>Mutant (-) allele </p>

<p>Targeting construct </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 
5 </p>

<p>8.8 kb </p>

<p>11 kb </p>

<p>frt 
frt </p>

<p>loxP 
lox71 </p>

<p>LacZ-pA </p>

<p>Free-running period (h) </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>24.5 </p>

<p>24.0 </p>

<p>23.5 </p>

<p>23.0 
Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>LD </p>

<p>DD </p>

<p>Days 
14 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>kDa </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>CT4 
CT16 
CT16 
CT4 </p>

<p>SCN </p>

<p>Hybridize with 
LacZ probe 
LacZ Thalamus </p>

<p>Rgs16 
+/-</p>

<p>CT4 
CT0 </p>

<p>CT16 </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>oc </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Neo </p>

<p>Figure 1 | RGS16 deficiency lengthens the circadian period of the locomotor activity rhythm. (a) Autoradiographs showing mouse coronal brain sections 
hybridized with an Rgs16 probe. CT4 and CT16 correspond respectively to 4 and 16 h after the subjective onset of daytime in DD. Bar, 1 mm. (b) Circadian 
expression of Rgs16 in the sCn in DD. Relative RnA abundance was quantified with radioisotopic in situ hybridization. Values means ± s.e.m (n = 5) with 
the peak value adjusted to 100. Representative autoradiographs at the indicated time points are shown on the top. Bar, 200 µm. (c) Digoxigenin in situ 
hybridization showing the distribution of Rgs16-positive cells in the sCn. oc, optic chiasm; v, third ventricle. Bar, 100 µm. (d) schematic representation of 
the mouse Rgs16 gene, targeting construct, and the mutant allele. numbered boxes are the exons. The DnA probe used for southern blots is marked 
by a grey box. (e) southern blot of KpnI-digested DnA from Rgs16 
+ / + , Rgs16 
+ /-and Rgs16 
-/-mice, WT (8.8 kb) and mutant (11 kb) allele. (f) Radioisotopic 
in situ hybridization autoradiographs showing WT and Rgs16 
-/-sCn. Bar, 200 µm. (g) Rgs16 
+ /-coronal brain slice stained with X-gal (blue) with a 
magnified view of the sCn in a thin brain section at CT0. Autoradiographs show quantitative LacZ mRnA in situ hybridization at CT4 and CT16. scale bars: 
black, 1 mm, grey, 100 µm, white, 300 µm. (h) Western blots of RGs16 and Gαi in the sCn at CT4 and CT16. Arrowhead indicates a non-specific band. 
(i) Representative locomotor activity records of C57BL/6J-backcrossed Rgs16 
+ / + and Rgs16 
-/-mice. mice were housed in a 12L:12D light-dark cycle 
and then transferred to DD. Periods of darkness are indicated by grey backgrounds. The data are shown in double-plotted format. Each horizontal 
line represents 48 h; the second 24-h period is plotted to the right and below the first. The coloured lines delineate the phase of activity onset in DD. 
(j) Period-length distribution of C57BL/6J-backcrossed Rgs16 
+ / + and Rgs16 
-/-mice. Free-running period measurements were based on a 14-day 
interval taken after 3 days of a DD regime and were executed with a χ 
2 periodogram. Plotted are the period lengths of individual animals. Bars indicate 
mean ± s.e.m. ***P &lt; 0.001, student's t-test. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:327 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>down assays demonstrated that Gαi proteins in the SCN displayed 
an increased binding affinity for RGS16 when SCN extracts were 
treated with aluminium fluoride (AlF 4 
− -GDP complex forms a 
transition state analogue of GTP hydrolysis) (Fig. 2c). Further-
more, immunoprecipitation of endogenous RGS16 protein at CT0 
showed that the Gαi proteins coprecipitated with RGS16 from the 
protein extract of the WT SCN, but not from that of the Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>SCN (Fig. 2d). 
Time-of-day specific inhibition of Gαi by RGS16 might affect 
circadian production of cAMP in the SCN, which has recently been 
proved crucial for the maintenance of robust circadian oscillations </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>. 
Consistent with this model, we found that cAMP concentrations in 
the WT SCN fluctuated in a circadian fashion, rising synchronously 
with the expression of RGS16 in the subjective morning (Fig. 2e). 
Furthermore, we observed that the circadian fluctuation of cAMP 
was abolished as a result of RGS16 deletion (Fig. 2e). Interestingly, 
in Rgs16 
-/-mice, cAMP was maintained at intermediate levels 
throughout the day, implying that compensatory processes augment 
cAMP production. Hence, our data indicate that RGS16 is indis-
pensable for conferring circadian rhythmicity (that is, time-of-day 
specificity) on the production of cAMP in the SCN. </p>

<p>Delayed Per1 cycling in RGS16-deficient dorsomedial cells. The 
Per1 gene is a central clock component that is linked to cAMP sig-
nalling through a cAMP-responsive element within its promoter 
region 
22 (Supplementary Fig. S3). Therefore, we examined the 
integrity of Per1 expression in the Rgs16 
-/-SCN (Fig. 3). Although 
circadian expression of Per1 in the mutant SCN was grossly nor-
mal, close inspection with digoxigenin in situ hybridization led 
us to identify a defect of Per1 expression in a small subset of cells 
located in the periventricular part of the dorsomedial SCN (Fig. 3a). 
Intriguingly, this region is anatomically characterized by a cluster 
of 'phase-leading' cells 
11,12 in which Per1 mRNA levels peak at the 
beginning of the day, preceding the Per1 mRNA peak in ventral 
SCN cells. We observed that in Rgs16 
-/-SCN, the rising phase of </p>

<p>Per1 mRNA expression in the periventricular part of the dorsome-
dial SCN is significantly delayed, relative to that of WT SCN (Fig. 3a 
and detailed profiles of Per1 expression in Supplementary Figs. S7 
and S8). Thus, we speculated that cAMP signalling through RSG16 
might be crucial for the phase-advanced expression of Per1 at dawn 
in the dorsomedially located phase-leading cells. 
To complement these observations, we analysed the Per1 
expression profile in organotypic brain slices from Per1 promoter-
luciferase (Per1-luc) transgenic mice 
6 (Fig. 3b-f). Real-time bio-
luminescence imaging with high-resolution video microscopy </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>allows us to monitor the circadian dynamics of hundreds of indi-
vidual neurons in morphologically preserved SCN slices 
40 , where 
the luminescence driven by the Per1 promoter recapitulates the 
topographic-and time-dependent expression of Per1 mRNA (Fig. 
3b-f, Supplementary Fig. S9 and Supplementary Movie 1, Per1-luc 
Rgs16 
+ / + SCN). Thus, the phase-advanced oscillation, observable 
ex vivo in WT dorsomedial cells (Fig. 3b-f) is a property inherent 
to the SCN 
6 . Taking advantage of this system, we examined Per1-luc 
rhythms in SCN slices from Rgs16 
-/-mice (Fig. 3b-f, Supplemen-
tary Fig. S9 and Supplementary Movie 1, Per1-luc Rgs16 
-/-SCN). In 
line with in vivo data from Rgs16 
-/-mice, the luminescence of the 
Rgs16 
-/-SCN slice was basically circadian, and its period was rela-
tively long compared with that of WT slice (circadian period (h), 
mean ± s.e.m., Rgs16 
+ / + , 24.35 ± 0.03; Rgs16 
-/-, 24.82 ± 0.07, n = 6 for 
each genotype, P &lt; 0.05, t-test). Furthermore, when the phase dif-
ferences across three SCN zones (dorsal, middle and ventral) were 
examined, the dorsal zone, which includes phase-leading cells, 
exhibited a delayed (relative to Rgs16 
+ / + ) circadian oscillation, with 
a resultant phase close to that of the remaining zones (Fig. 3d and 
Supplementary Fig. S9b). Importantly, such alteration of dorsal 
rhythm was observed in all Rgs16 
-/-SCN slice cultures tested, and 
statistical analysis revealed that the luminescence from the dorsal 
zone of the Rgs16 
-/-SCN reached its peak at a time significantly 
later than that of the Rgs16 
+ / + SCN (Fig. 3e and Supplementary 
Fig. S9c). </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Gnai1 
Gnai2 </p>

<p>Rgs16 (blue) 
Gnai1 (grain) </p>

<p>Rgs16 (blue) 
Gnai2 (grain) </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>cAMP (pmol per mg SCN protein) 
Relative RGS16 protein levels </p>

<p>cAMP (+/+) </p>

<p>cAMP (-/-) </p>

<p>RGS16 (+/+) </p>

<p>Circadian time </p>

<p>0 
2 
0 
6 
4 
1 0 
8 
1 4 
1 2 
1 8 
1 6 
2 2 0 
2 0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>RGS16 </p>

<p>CT: 0 4 8 12 16 20 0 4 8 12 16 20 </p>

<p>Gαi </p>

<p>kDa 
37 </p>

<p>25 
20 </p>

<p>d 
c </p>

<p>His-RGS16 </p>

<p>GDP </p>

<p>SCN extract 
His-RGS16 </p>

<p>AlF 4 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Gαi </p>

<p>+ 
-
kDa </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>SCN extract </p>

<p>RGS16 </p>

<p>IgG </p>

<p>Gαi </p>

<p>Gαi (input) </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>kDa </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>+/+ -/-</p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>Figure 2 | RGS16 protein targets Gi and regulates circadian production of cAMP in the SCN. (a) (upper) Low-power film autoradiography showing the 
mouse coronal brain sections in situ hybridized with radioisotopic probe for Gnai1 or Gnai2. Arrows indicate the positions of the sCn. Bar, 2 mm. (Lower) 
High-power photomicrographs of the sCn double in situ hybridized with digoxigenin-labelled probe for Rgs16 (blue) and isotope-labelled probe for Gnai1 or 
Gnai2 (silver grains). Arrows indicate representative double-labelled cells. Bar, 5 µm. (b) Western blots analysing the temporal changes in the protein levels 
of RGs16 and Gαi in the WT mouse sCn. The animals kept in DD were killed at 4-h intervals across two circadian cycles (sampling times indicated at the 
top). The microdissected sCn extracts were probed with antibodies to RGs16 and Gαi. The Gαi antibody used recognizes both Gαi1 and Gαi2. 
(c) Increased binding affinity of RGs16 and Gαi in aluminium fluoride-treated sCn extracts. The microdissected sCn extract was incubated with His-
tagged RGs16 protein in the presence of GDP with or without aluminium fluoride. shown are Western blots of the proteins affinity purified with ni-nTA 
beads. (d) Immunoprecipitation (IP) of endogenous Gαi with endogenous RGs16. The microdissected sCn extracts from Rgs16 
+ / + or Rgs16 
-/-mice at CT0 
(input) were subjected to IP with RGs16 antibody. shown are Western blots of the immunoprecipited RGs16 and Gαi (upper) and input Gαi (lower). 
(e) Circadian changes of cAmP content in the microdissected sCn from Rgs16 
+ / + (blue) and Rgs16 
-/-(red) mice (means ± s.e.m, n = 10, for each time 
point). P &lt; 0.01, CT2 (peak) versus CT16 (trough) in Rgs16 
+ / + mice. such a temporal difference is not detected in Rgs16 
-/-mice. To characterize more 
precisely the cAmP rhythm seen in WT mice, cAmP contents in the WT sCn were determined at shorter sampling intervals. The bar graph shows the 
levels of RGs16 protein in the sCn (means ± range of variation) assessed from the results in b by densitometric analysis. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:327 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>Impaired cAMP signalling in RGS16-deficient dorsomedial cells. 
The observations thus far indicate that dorsomedial SCN cells are 
the major (or sole) site where the RGS16-cAMP pathway could con-
tribute to the rising phase of the Per1 mRNA. Consistent with this 
finding, we observed that the dawn expression of Per1 in the dorso-
medial cells was unique in that it accompanied a strong induction of 
cFos (Fig. 4a and Supplementary Fig. S10) </p>

<p>41,42 </p>

<p>. as well as a simultane-
ous activation of extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) (Fig. 
4b and Supplementary Fig. S10) </p>

<p>43-45 </p>

<p>. Of note, both of these events 
were cAMP-dependent (Fig. 4c-e); hence, the pharmacological 
inhibition of cAMP synthesis in vivo with 9-(tetrahydro-2-furyl)-
adenine (THFA, a noncompetitive AC inhibitor, which slows the 
rate of cAMP production but does not completely deplete cAMP </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>suppressed the dawn induction of cFos and phospho-ERK that oth-
erwise appeared in the periventricular part of the dorsomedial SCN 
(Fig. 4c-e and Supplementary Fig. S10). Thus, the activated cAMP 
pathway at dawn is a feature characterizing the phase-leading cells. 
Importantly, the dorsomedial cell-specific induction of cFos and 
ERK phosphorylation at dawn were both severely compromised by 
RGS16 deficiency (Fig. 4a,b), demonstrating that RGS16 determines 
the state of cAMP-dependent signalling in the phase-leading cells. 
We also observed that the animals treated with THFA phenocopied 
Rgs16 
-/-mice (Figs. 1i and 4c), displaying a relatively long circadian 
locomotor activity rhythm (Figs. 1j and 4f). Thus, we concluded 
that cAMP signalling at dawn in the phase-leading cells depends 
on RGS16, and that the loss of RGS16-cAMP signalling causes a </p>

<p>Per1 
mRNA </p>

<p>Per1-Luc </p>

<p>CT2 
CT22 
CT4 </p>

<p>6 
2 
Time (h) 
after trough 
10 
6 
2 
10 </p>

<p>CT2 
CT22 
CT4 </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 
+/+ Per1-Luc 
Rgs16 
-/-Per1-Luc </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>oc </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>oc </p>

<p>2 4 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 
2 0 
2 2 </p>

<p>Bright field </p>

<p>Dorsal </p>

<p>Dorsal </p>

<p>Middle 
Middle </p>

<p>Hourly change of number 
of peaked cells 
Ventral </p>

<p>Dorsal </p>

<p>Middle </p>

<p>Ventral </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 
60 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 
60 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 
60 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 
60 
Zonal intensity 
(arbitrary) 
0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Dorsal </p>

<p>Middle </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>2 4 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 
1 0 1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 
2 0 
2 2 </p>

<p>2 4 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 </p>

<p>8 
7 
10 
9 
11 
13 
12 </p>

<p>1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 
2 0 
2 2 </p>

<p>2 4 
0 2 4 6 8 1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 
2 0 
2 2 </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>ooc </p>

<p>ov </p>

<p>ov </p>

<p>ooc </p>

<p>ov </p>

<p>ooc </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Dorsal </p>

<p>Middle </p>

<p>Ventral </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>2 4 
0 2 4 
6 8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 
2 0 
2 2 </p>

<p>2 4 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 
2 0 
2 2 </p>

<p>Ventral </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 
60 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>80 
60 
Ventral </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>2 4 
0 2 4 
6 8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 
2 0 
2 2 </p>

<p>2 4 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 
1 8 
2 0 
2 2 </p>

<p>Time (h) </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Time since second trough of middle SCN (h) </p>

<p>0 
12 
6 
1 
13 
7 
2 
14 
8 
3 
15 
9 
4 
16 
10 
5 
17 
11 
20 21 22 23 24 
18 19 </p>

<p>Figure 3 | RGS16 deficiency impairs Per1 expression in dorsomedially located phase-leading cells. (a) Digoxigenin in situ hybridization photomicrographs 
showing the topographical distributions of Per1-positive cells in the sCn at CT22, CT2 and CT4. (b) Bioluminescent images of whole sCn slices from Per1-
luc -bearing Rgs16 
+ / + and Rgs16 
-/-mice. The red spots on the right-side nucleus indicate the positions of the peaked cells at the indicated time point after 
the trough of the total sCn bioluminescence. (c) The range of peak times of randomly chosen cells from the subdivided dorsal (n = 116, for each genotype), 
middle (n = 281) and ventral (n = 193) sCn zones of WT and mutant slices. For non-biased definition of the regions of interest, the sCn was divided into 
three regions with equal proportions along vertical axis (from the dorsal-most to the ventral-most). The x axis represents time (h) since 2nd trough of 
middle sCn luminescence. note that the region selected as a dorsal zone encompasses the phase-leading cells. (d) The temporal changes in the levels of 
total luminescence from each zone (means ± s.e.m (n = 4); the peak and trough values were adjusted to 100 and 0, respectively). Two-way AnoVA with 
repeated measures identify a statistically significant interaction between zone and genotype (F(2, 18) = 6.88, P &lt; 0.001). Bonferroni's post hoc tests reveal 
statistically significant difference between WT and Rgs16 
-/-slices only in dorsal zone, but not in middle and ventral zones. (e) The average times of peaks 
( ± s.d.) from subdivided dorsal, middle and ventral sCn zones of WT and mutant slices (n = 4, for each genotype). *P &lt; 0.001 (Bonferroni test). (f) Hourly 
images of the sCn slices from Rgs16 
+ / + and Rgs16 
-/-mice. see also supplementary movie 1. scale bars in (a-f) are 100 µm. v, third ventricle; ov, original 
third ventricle; oc, optic chiasm; ooc, original optic chiasm. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:327 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>lengthening of the circadian period (or a constantly delayed phase) 
of the locomotor activity rhythm of mice. </p>

<p>Discussion 
A critical issue for understanding SCN function is to identify how 
individual cellular clocks synchronize with a defined intercellu-
lar phase-relationship to broadcast coherent circadian signals to 
peripheral tissues and thereby coordinate physiology and behav-
iour. We previously showed that the dorsomedial SCN cells run 
ahead of the remaining cells, and that this differential phasing is an 
intrinsic property arising from the intercellular network of the SCN. 
However, the molecular mechanism underlying the phase-advanced 
oscillations of the dorsomedial cells and how they contribute to 
behavioural rhythms have remained unknown. In the present study, 
we have shown that the induction of dorsomedial Per1 expression at 
dawn is constantly accelerated by the circadian activation of intra-
cellular cAMP signalling, which requires coordinated inhibition of 
Gαi by the clock-controlled RGS16 (see a schematic model in Fig. 5). 
Importantly, RGS16 deficiency, which delays dorsomedial Per1 
expression, results in a period lengthening of behavioural rhythm. 
These data therefore reveal that the temporal regulation of intra-
cellular G protein signalling that dictates the phasic arrangement </p>

<p>within the SCN contributes to the determination of the circadian 
period of locomotor activity rhythm. 
We found that despite the disappearance of the cAMP rhythm, 
Rgs16 
-/-mice still show Per1 oscillations in the SCN (Fig. 3). This 
observation may be somewhat unexpected because pharmacologi-
cal depletion of cAMP by an irreversible potent AC inhibitor (MDL-
12,330A) constitutively reduces Per1 expression to basal levels </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>. It 
should be noted, however, that the concentrations of cAMP in the 
Rgs16 
-/-SCN (Fig. 2e) and in THFA (a mild AC inhibitor)-treated 
cells 
29 were not markedly reduced (kept at intermediate levels), and 
that under these conditions behavioural rhythms were sustainable, 
albeit with a relatively long circadian period (Figs. 1i and 4c) </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>. 
Consistent with this behavioural rhythm, the circadian fluctuations 
of Per1 in the Rgs16 
-/-SCN were mostly unimpaired: rhythms in 
the vast majority of middle-to-ventral cells remained intact, and 
intriguingly, even in the dorsomedial cells, Per1 was still capable of 
oscillating, albeit with its peak phase significantly delayed due to 
RGS16 deficiency (Fig. 3d,e). Thus, the oscillations of Per1 in the 
SCN are not necessarily depending on the cAMP rhythm, but are 
rather self-sustainable, presumably due to transcriptional control 
through E-box and D-box, which might suffice to drive 'normal' 
(that is, non-phase-leading) Per1 expression. Our data therefore </p>

<p>Rgs16 
+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 
+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 
+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 
+/+ </p>

<p>Rgs16 
-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 
-/-</p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
0 4 8 12 16 20 
Circadian time </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>CT4 
CT8 
CT20 </p>

<p>pERK 
CT0 
CT8 
CT12 
CT16 
CT20 
CT4 </p>

<p>v 
v </p>

<p>oc </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>oc </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>oc 
20 µm </p>

<p>20 µm 
oc </p>

<p>CT0 
CT0 </p>

<p>Dorsomedial SCN 
CT0 </p>

<p>CT0 </p>

<p>CT16 </p>

<p>CT16 </p>

<p>Rgs16 
-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 
-/-
Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>CT0 
CT12 
CT16 </p>

<p>cFos </p>

<p>cFos </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Days in DD </p>

<p>THFA 
Time (h) 
0 
0 
0 
12 
12 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>pERK 
cFos </p>

<p>CT0 </p>

<p>Days in DD </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Vehicle 
Time (h) 
0 
0 
12 
0 
12 </p>

<p>Number of cFos -
positive cells in SCN </p>

<p>d 
e </p>

<p>THFA 
Vehicle </p>

<p>pERK 
cFos </p>

<p>CT0 </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>oc </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>THFA 
Vehicle </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>pERK </p>

<p>Number of pERK-
positive cells in SCN </p>

<p>Pre 
Post 
Period length (h) </p>

<p>THFA </p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>23.4 </p>

<p>23.6 </p>

<p>23.8 </p>

<p>24.0 </p>

<p>24.2 </p>

<p>24.4 </p>

<p>24.6 </p>

<p>24.8 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Number of cFos-
positive cells in SCN </p>

<p>Figure 4 | RGS16 deficiency impairs cAMP-dependent induction of cFos and ERK phosphorylation. (a) Digoxigenin in situ hybridization 
photomicrographs showing the circadian profiles of cFos expression in the sCn of Rgs16 
+ / + and Rgs16 
-/-mice under DD conditions. The graph indicates the 
number of cFos-positive cells (per section) across the circadian time (means ± s.e.m, n = 5). (b) Immunoreactivity to the pERK in the sCn of Rgs16 
+ / + and 
Rgs16 
-/-mice under DD conditions. (c) Representative locomotor activity records of WT mice under DD conditions before and after the surgery (asterisk) 
for the continuous infusion of THFA or vehicle (delivered to third ventricle just upper to the sCn via osmotic minipump). Arrowheads indicate the day on 
which the mice were killed at CT0 (estimated by the phase of the activity onset) for the analysis of cFos and pERK expression in the sCn. Representative 
photomicrographs are shown below the locomotor activity records. scale bars in a-c are 100 µm unless otherwise noted. (d, e) The histograms showing 
the number (means ± s.e.m) of cFos-(d) or pERK-(e) positive cells in the sCn (per section) at CT0 after 14-days infusion of either THFA (n = 6) or vehicle 
(n = 6) in DD. **P &lt; 0.01, t-test, compared with vehicle treatments. (f) Pair-wised comparisons of behavioural periods before and after infusion of THFA 
(n = 6) or vehicle (n = 4). ***P &lt; 0.001, paired t-test in THFA-treated mice. pERK, phosphorylated form of ERK. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:327 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>propose that the major role of the daily activation of cAMP in the 
SCN is to accelerate the expression of Per1 in the dorsomedial cells, 
thereby advancing the phases of these cells, relative to those of the 
cells in the middle-to-ventral SCN. 
RGS16 is an inhibitor of Gαi. How Gαi is activated in the SCN 
remains unknown. Gαi could be activated by extracellular or intra-
cellular signals. One candidate, Dexras1, is a nonreceptor-associ-
ated activator for Gαi </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>. Interestingly, the gene encoding Dexras1 
is highly and rhythmically expressed in the SCN, with a phase 
almost anti-phasic to that of Rgs16, and mice lacking Dexras1 show 
abnormal desynchronization of the behavioural rhythm in con-
stant light </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>. These results raise the prospect that the temporally 
segregated activation and inhibition of Gαi by Dexras1 and RGS16 
might contribute to circadian control of Gαi. Besides Dexras1, Gαi-
coupled GPCR signalling may also be involved. Defining which spe-
cific Gαi activators are required for SCN synchrony and how they 
act in concert with RGS16 will be our next challenge. It is also note-
worthy that pharmacological (global) silencing of Gαi/o with per-
tussis toxin treatment could dampen SCN rhythm </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>, a phenotype 
differing from that of RGS16 deficiency. Thus, the mechanism(s) 
by which pertussis toxin affects SCN physiology remains unknown. 
We should also mention that RGS16 can target Gαq </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>. Given that in 
multiple cell types, Gαq-mediated Ca 
2 + signalling interferes with 
cAMP production 
48-50, , it will be worth testing whether Gαq signal-
ling in the SCN is subject to the circadian regulation by RGS16 and 
how this potential pathway contributes to the altered cAMP signals 
in the RGS16-deficient SCN. 
In line with previous reports, we observed that the expression 
of cFos at dawn in the SCN is highly confined to the dorsomedial 
cells (Fig. 4a) </p>

<p>41,42 </p>

<p>. This spatially limited activation of cFos cannot be 
explained by RGS16 distribution (Fig. 1c): cFos expression does not 
parallel the expression of Rgs16 in middle-to-ventral SCN regions, 
making it unlikely that RGS16 expression by itself suffices to drive 
cFos induction. Rather, given that the role of RGS16 is to inhibit </p>

<p>Gαi and temporarily permit the production of cAMP in the SCN, it 
would be reasonable to speculate that RGS16 is necessary (Fig. 4a) 
but not sufficient to drive cAMP synthesis that triggers the expres-
sion of cFos in the dorsomedial cells. It is conceivable that the cir-
cadian regulation of cAMP is a multifactorial process involving not 
only Gαi but also Gαs. Along these lines, the vasoactive intestinal 
peptide, a neurotransmitter mediating cell-cell communication 
in the SCN, activates Gαs by acting through its cognate receptor 
VPAC 2 </p>

<p>8,9,51 </p>

<p>. As it has been speculated that vasoactive intestinal pep-
tide acts on the dorsomedial SCN </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>, further investigations aimed 
at deciphering the rules governing the precisely timed and topo-
logically specific activation of Gαs and Gαi pathways in the SCN 
will be required to understand how cAMP synthesis in the SCN is 
controlled. 
Because the lengthened period of the Rgs16 
-/-behavioural 
rhythm (Fig. 1i,j) is closely associated with the delayed phase of the 
periventricular part of the dorsomedial SCN (Fig. 3a and Supple-
mentary Figs. S7 and S8), we envisage that the functional changes in 
a small subset of neurons (for example, phase-leading cells) could 
alter the global timing property of the SCN. We observed that this 
prediction is mathematically feasible at least in a two-coupled cell-
oscillator model that we constructed in silico (Supplementary Fig. 
S11). The mathematical configuration used was based on a pub-
lished model which hypothesizes a mutual coupling between the two 
oscillators 
53,54 and was modified by introducing a term accounting 
for the dawn cAMP signal in a phase-leading cell (see Supplemen-
tary Methods for details). Under these conditions, the cell oscillating 
in silico with cAMP signalling at dawn runs ahead of the cell without 
cAMP signalling, and both cells exhibit the same circadian period 
(23.6 h) (see Supplementary Fig. S11). By contrast, once cAMP 
signalling was deleted from the phase-leading cell, then the two 
cells began to oscillate in phase with an elongated circadian period 
(24.4 h) (Supplementary Fig. S11), a situation similar to what was 
observed for Rgs16 
-/-mice under constant dark conditions. Thus, 
a modified two-coupled cell-oscillator model predicts the period 
lengthening by delayed circadian oscillation of phase-leading cells, 
whereas further elucidation of SCN network will be needed to faith-
fully recapitulate whole SCN function (see Supplementary Methods 
for detailed discussion). 
In conclusion, we provide evidence that RGS16, known as the 
regulator of intracellular Gαi protein signalling, is a key component 
to establish the intercellular phase-relationship of multi-phased 
SCN neurons. Mechanistically, RGS16 forms an integration point 
whereby the intracellular molecular clock exerts its effect on cAMP 
signalling (Fig. 5). Through allowing cAMP synthesis at dawn, 
RGS16 in turn facilitates the phase-advanced expression of Per1 in 
the dorsomedial cells. Thus, our work adds a new layer of complex-
ity to the rules that govern the intercellular synchrony of SCN neu-
rons. We propose that signalling at the cell surface is not everything. 
Rather, the circadian time-dependent regulation of intracellular G 
protein signalling is also important to coordinate temporal and spa-
tial order across the SCN. Furthermore, our work extends the role 
of RGS16 from cellular biology to behaviour. A major challenge in 
systems neuroscience is to integrate intracellular molecular events 
with the intercellular neural organization that gives rise to complex 
behavioural states. Using the SCN as a model, we show that the reg-
ulated intracellular G-protein signalling that controls intercellular 
synchrony across the SCN contributes to the determination of the 
period of daily rhythms in behaviour. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Creation of Rgs16 knockout mice. Rgs16 mutant mice (Acc. No. CDB0436K: 
http://www.cdb.riken.jp/arg/mutant%20mice%20list.html) were generated according 
to our standard method </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>. The targeting vector was constructed using a bacterial arti-
ficial chromosome clone containing the mouse Rgs16 gene (RP24-576N23, BACPAC). 
We generated the 5′-and 3′-arms of Rgs16 (Fig. 1d) by PCR and cloned them into 
the corresponding sites of the DT-A/lox71/LacZ-pA/frt/PGK-Neo/frt/loxP/pA </p>

<p>At DAWN 
(CT0) </p>

<p>CORE 
OSCILLATOR </p>

<p>D 
B 
D-box </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D 
B 
C </p>

<p>E-box </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>CREB 
CRE </p>

<p>AC </p>

<p>PKA </p>

<p>P 
P </p>

<p>ERK </p>

<p>D-box 
E-box </p>

<p>Per1 </p>

<p>Gαi </p>

<p>GPCR </p>

<p>GDP </p>

<p>Gαi </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>Dorsomedial SCN cell </p>

<p>Rgs16 </p>

<p>cAMP </p>

<p>RGS16 </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Schematic model depicting a role of RGS16 in regulated cAMP 
signalling at dawn in the dorsomedial cells. Through allowing cAmP 
synthesis at dawn, RGs16 regulates Per1 expression in the dorsomedial 
phase-leading cells. B, BmAL1; C, CLoCK; CRE, cAmP responsive element; 
CREB, CRE-binding protein; D, DBP; P, phosphate; ERK, extracellular signal-
regulated kinase; PKA, cAmP-dependent protein kinase. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:327 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>vector (the details of the vector are available in http://www.cdb.riken.go.jp/arg/ 
cassette.html). Gene targeting was carried out in TT2 cells </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>, an embryonic stem 
cell line established from F1 embryo between C57BL/6J female and CBA male 
(50% C57BL/6J, 50% CBA). Chimeric males were bred to wild type C57BL/6J 
females producing F1N0 progeny (75% C57BL/6J, 25% CBA). Germline trans-
mission was verified by PCR as well as Southern blotting on tail DNA. F1N0 males 
were further backcrossed with C57BL/6J females to create F1N1 progeny (87.5% 
C57BL/6J). For behavioural analysis (Fig. 1i,j), we continued back-crossing up to 
F1N10 generation, which corresponds to 12 times backcrossing to the C57BL/6J 
background ( &gt; 99.9% C57BL/6J) as the F1N0 mice with which we started back-
crossing were already 75% C57BL/6J background. To conduct biochemical and 
histological analyses, we used F1N5 generation mice (~99.2% C57BL/6J), the 
behavioural phenotypes of which are equivalent to those of F1N10 mice (free-
running period (h) of F1N5 generation mice: Rgs16 
+ / + , 23.58 ± 0.03 (s.e.m.), Rgs16 </p>

<p>-/-</p>

<p>, 
24.35 ± 0.03, n = 6 for each genotype, P &lt; 0.01, t-test). We analysed littermate 
wild-type control mice having equivalent genetic backgrounds than the mutant 
mice. To this end, males and females from a specific generation (either F1N5 
or F1N10 mice) were interbred to create a large colony. No difference in gross 
morphology or fertility was detected between the genotypes. Unless otherwise 
mentioned, in vivo comparative analyses of WT and mutant mice were conducted 
in DD. All the studies were approved by the animal experimentation committee of 
Kyoto University. </p>

<p>Behavioural activity monitoring. Single caged adult Rgs16 
-/-mice and their 
wild-type littermates (male, 8-15 weeks old) were housed individually in light-
tight, ventilated closets within a temperature-and humidity-controlled facility. 
The animals were entrained on a 12-h-light (~200 lux fluorescent light)-12-h-dark 
cycle at least two weeks and then transferred to DD. Locomotor activity was 
detected with passive (pyroelectric) infra-red sensors (FA-05 F5B; Omron) </p>

<p>24,57 </p>

<p>and the data obtained were analysed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Clocklab</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Actimetrics</rs>) 
developed on <rs id="software-1" type="software">MatLab</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Mathworks</rs>). Free-running period was determined with 
either a χ 
2 periodogram or a linear regression line fit to the activity onsets. The 
data used for period measurements were based on animal behaviours in a 14-day 
interval taken 3 days after the start of DD condition. For the pulse-induced shift 
experiments, mice put in DD were exposed to a 15 min light pulse at either CT14 
or CT22. Phase shifts (delay at CT14, advance at CT22) were quantified as the 
time difference between regression lines of activity onset before and after the 
light application. </p>

<p>Microdissection of the mouse SCN. The microdissection of the SCN was 
performed as described 
27 with slight modifications. In brief, animals kept in DD 
were killed by cervical dislocation, and the eyes were removed under a safety red 
light. The brain was then isolated from the skull under room light and frozen 
immediately on dry ice. Coronal brain section (300 µm thick) containing the 
SCN was prepared using a cryostat microtome (CM3050S, Leica) and mounted 
on a silicon rubber stage at − 17 °C. Under a magnifying glass, the bilateral SCN 
was punched out from the frozen section using a blunt 20-gauge syringe needle 
whose edge had been sharpened by filing. For the analysis of circadian expression 
of RGS16 and Gαi (Fig. 2b), the SCN punches (n = 3, for each time point) were 
pooled in Laemmli buffer, and the lysates were subjected to Western blot analysis 
with antibodies to RGS16 and Gαi. We generated rabbit polyclonal RGS16 anti-
body. The details of the antibodies used are available in Supplementary Methods. </p>

<p>Pull down assay with His-tagged RGS16. RGS16 binding assay was performed as 
described 
58 with slight modifications. In brief, the SCN punches (n = 5) were pooled 
in 300 µl of pull-down buffer (20 mM Na-HEPES, pH 8.0, 380 mM NaCl, 3 mM 
DTT, 6 mM MgCl 2 ) and homogenized by sonication at 4 °C (Bioruptor, COSMO 
BIO). The homogenate was divided into two aliquots and incubated with 
His-RGS16 protein (10 µg) in the presence of either GDP (10 µM) or GDP (10 µM) 
plus AlF 4 
− (30 µM) for 30 min at 4 °C. The reaction mixtures were then treated with 
1% cholate and centrifuged at 105,000 g (Optima MAX ultracentrifuge, Beckman). 
The detergent-soluble protein extracts were incubated with Ni2 + -NTA agarose 
beads (Qiagen) for 15 min at 4 °C. Following three time washes with pull-down 
buffer supplemented with 20 mM imidazole (plus 10 µM GDP with or without 
30 µM AlF 4 
− ), the beads were boiled in Laemmli buffer. The protein complexes 
copurified with His-tagged RGS16 were analysed by Western blot. </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation with RGS16 antibody. Immunoprecipitaion (IP) of RGS16 
was performed with the SCN protein extracts from Rgs16 
+ / + and Rgs16 
-/-mice. 
The microdissected SCN punches (n = 5, for each pool) were homogenized in 
300 µl of IP buffer (20 mM Na-HEPES, pH 8.0, 380 mM NaCl, 3 mM DTT, 6 mM 
MgCl 2 ,10 µM GDP and 30 µM AlF 4 
− ) by sonication at 4 °C (Bioruptor, COSMO 
BIO). The homogenates were treated with 1% cholate and then centrifuged at 
105,000 g (Optima MAX, Beckman). The detergent-soluble protein extracts were 
subjected to IP with RGS16 antibody and Protein A-Sepharose beads. After three 
time washes with IP buffer, the beads were boiled in Laemmli buffer. The proteins 
precipitated with RGS16 antibody were analysed by Western blot. </p>

<p>cAMP measurement. cAMP concentration was determined by enzyme 
immunoassay (EIA) using cAMP EIA kit (Cayman Chemical) according to the </p>

<p>manufacturer's protocol. The microdissected SCN (one punch per assay) was 
collected in 300 µl of 0.1 N HCl solution and then sonicated at 4 °C (Bioruptor, 
COSMO BIO). The protein content was determined with BCA Protein Assay kit 
(Takara). Following centrifugation at 1,000 g for 10 min, the supernatant 
was diluted 1:2 with EIA buffer (Cayman Chemical). All SCN samples underwent 
acetylation before determination of cAMP level by EIA. We conducted the 
assays in duplicate, with measurement at l = 405 nm on a plate reader (ARVO, 
Perkin-Elmer). </p>

<p>Per1-luc SCN slice culture. Per1-luc transgenic mice carry a firefly luciferase 
reporter gene linked to a 7.2 kb genomic DNA fragment covering the 5′ upstream 
region of the mouse Per1 gene 
59 . Per1-luc-Rgs16 
-/-mice were generated by crossing 
Per1-luc transgenic mice and Rgs16 
-/-mice. The SCN slices were prepared accord-
ing to our standard method 
6 and kept at 35 °C in a sealed 35 mm petri dish with 
1 ml of the culture medium containing 1 mM luciferin. The bioluminescence from 
the cultured SCN was measured with a highly sensitive cryogenic CCD camera 
(Spectra Video SV16KV/CT: Pixelvision) equipped with a microscope (Axiovert 
135TV: Carl Zeiss). Observed data of images were filtered through a median 
filter to eliminate cosmic-ray-induced background noise. The luminescence was 
recorded every 20 min. Periods of SCN luminescence recordings were estimated 
using Fast Fourier Transform-Nonlinear Least Squares analysis 
60 as part of the 
<rs type="software">Biological Rhythms Analysis Software System (BRASS</rs>). For all SCN to be com-
pared, identical segments of raw SCN luminescence values, starting from the first 
trough since the start of the measurement, and containing at least four complete 
cycles, were analysed. <rs id="software-3" type="software">BRASS</rs> has been developed by <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Dr Brown PE and co-workers</rs> 
and is available from http://millar.bio.ed.ac.uk/Downloads.html. </p>

<p>Intraventricular infusion of THFA. THFA (Tocris) was continuously delivered 
to the SCN via osmotic pump as described 
29 . In brief, the tip of the infusion 
cannula (Alzet, Brain Infusion Kit 2) was directed stereotaxically to the SCN 
and the osmotic pump (Alzet, pump model 1002) containing 100 mM THFA 
(118 µg/day, infused at 0.24 µl/h) was placed in a subcutaneous pouch by surgery 
under anaesthesia. We performed the surgery during the subjective daytime 
(CT8-10) when the phase of circadian clock is considered irresponsive to light. 
Following the surgery, animals were returned to their home cages and 
maintained in DD. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. For the experiments in which three or more test groups 
were compared, we used one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Bonferroni 
post-hoc test and evaluated the differences derived from genotypes and circadian 
time points tested. To assess the difference of circadian rhythm (phase) between 
the zones in Per1-luc SCN slices, we analysed the interaction between zone and 
circadian time with two-way repeated measures ANOVA, followed by Bonferroni's 
multiple comparison test. </p>

<p>Additional methods. Specific reagents and detailed methodology for DNA 
microarray analysis, in situ hybridization, X-gal staining, immunoblotting, 
immunohistochemistry and the antibodies used are all described in 
Supplementary Methods. Microarray data has been deposited in the Gene 
Expression Omnibus under accession code GSE28574. </p>



<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 </p>

<p>nATuRE CommunICATIons | 2:327 | DoI: 10.1038/ncomms1316 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank M. Jounouchi for their expert assistance. This work was supported by Special 
Coordination Funds for Promoting Science and Technology from the Ministry of 
Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology, the Japanese Government. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>M.D. and A.I. are equally contributing first authors. H.O. conceived the project. M.D. 
and H.O. designed the research. A.I., A.M., M.D. R.T., K.N., S.A. and H.O. created Rgs16 
mutant mice. M.D., A.I., A.M. M.S., R.K., F.Y., I.K., S.T., K.S., Y.Y., M.M., Y.S., H.Y., Y.T., 
K.O., G.T. and H.O. conducted biochemical and histochemical analyses. M.S., K.S., 
M.M., J.-M.F. M.K. and H.O. conducted slice culture analyses. H.K., M.A. and M.D. 
performed mathematical modelling. M.D., K.O., J.-M.F. and H.O. drafted the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Accession codes: Microarray data has been deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus 
under accession code GSE28574. </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Doi, M. et al. Circadian regulation of intracellular G-protein 
signalling mediates intercellular synchrony and rhythmicity in the suprachiasmatic 
nucleus. Nat. Commun. 2:327 doi: 10.1038/ncomms1316 (2011). </p>

<p>License: This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

</text></tei>