<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4687766" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cerebellar ataxias are rare and progressive neurological con-
ditions that affect coordination, mobility and speech. 1 More 
than 10,000 people in the United Kingdom are thought to be 
living with a progressive ataxia, 2 and the prevalence is likely 
to increase with an ageing population. 3 Due to an absence of 
epidemiological studies, the incidence of cerebellar ataxia is 
currently unclear. 4  A familial predisposition is observed in about 30% of 
cases 5 with a definitive genetic diagnosis in around 60% of 
those that are inherited. 3 It is important to stress that progres-
sive ataxias are a heterogeneous group of neurodegenerative 
conditions. In clinical practice, distinctions are commonly 
made between hereditary and sporadic ataxias. Age at onset 
is an important tool in the diagnostic algorithm, although this 
can vary considerably, for example, even between spinocer-
ebellar ataxia (SCA) patients of the same genotype. 6 In the </p>

<p>majority of cases, there is no available medical treatment for 
the ataxia, and management focuses on monitoring, treat-
ment of associated symptoms (e.g. spasticity, cardiomyopa-
thy and diabetes) and physical therapies. 1 In the United </p>

<p>Trouble with ataxia: A longitudinal 
qualitative study of the diagnosis and 
medical management of a group of rare, 
progressive neurological conditions </p>

<p>Gavin Daker-White 1 , John Ealing 2 , Julie Greenfield 3 , Helen Kingston 4 , 
Caroline Sanders 1 and Katherine Payne 5 </p>

<p>Abstract 
Objectives: An exploratory investigation of diagnosis and management in progressive ataxias: rare neurological conditions 
usually affecting balance, mobility and speech. 
Methods: A longitudinal qualitative study into the experiences of people with ataxia and neurologists. Thematic analysis and 
follow-up interviews were used to determine diagnosis and management issues over time. 
Results: People with ataxia recruited via two hospital departments and Ataxia UK were interviewed at baseline (n = 38) and 
12-month follow-up (n = 31). Eight consultant neurologists were interviewed once. Patient accounts were diverse, but many 
expressed frustration at having an incurable condition and dissatisfaction with service outcomes. At follow-up, there was 
variation in their contact and satisfaction with helping agencies. Service issues regarding continuity of care and the primary/ 
secondary care interface were evident. Neurologists' accounts also varied. One-half reported that there is nothing that can 
be done, and one-half favoured specialist referral to increase the likelihood of finding an underlying aetiology within budget 
constraints. 
Conclusions: Diagnostic uncertainties existing at baseline remained for patients at follow-up interviews, although some had 
learned to deal with the uncertainties brought by the diagnosis of a largely untreatable condition. Care pathways only seemed 
to operate in the case of defined conditions, such as Friedreich's Ataxia, the most commonly inherited cause. The findings 
point to a need to develop the evidence base to inform the relative utility of diagnostic procedures in the context of finite 
resources for patient care and support. </p>

<p>Keywords 
Diagnosis, neurology, qualitative study, patient experience, professional views </p>

<p>1 Centre for Primary Care, The University of Manchester, Manchester, UK 
2 Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust, Salford, UK 
3 Ataxia UK, London, UK 
4 Central Manchester University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, 
Manchester, UK 
5 Centre for Health Economics, The University of Manchester, 
Manchester, UK </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Gavin Daker-White, Centre for Primary Care, Institute of Population 
Health, The University of Manchester, Suite 7, 5th Floor, Williamson 
Building, Oxford Road, Manchester M13 9PL, UK. 
Email: gavin.daker-white@manchester.ac.uk </p>

<p>505560S OM0010.1177/2050312113505560SAGE Open MedicineDaker-White et al. </p>

<p>2013 </p>

<p>505560 </p>

<p>Original Article </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine 0(0) </p>

<p>Kingdom, there are four national specialist neurological cen-
tres for patients with ataxia (London, Newcastle, Oxford and 
Sheffield). There is no specialist centre in Greater Manchester, 
where this study was based. 
The longitudinal qualitative study described in this article 
aimed to explore patients' and doctors' experiences and per-
ceptions of the clinical treatment and management of pro-
gressive ataxias. The findings form part of a wider programme 
of study, which began from a concern with investigating care 
pathways and resource use issues in a rare and complex con-
dition with limited treatment and management options. The 
fact that some ataxias are inherited also offered opportunities 
for considering the value of genetic testing in relation to 
diagnosis and management. Given the low knowledge base 
in relation to progressive ataxias, as well as a concern with 
resource use, we also set out to examine the patient and ser-
vice experience from a 'micro' perspective. Thus, we adopted 
a mixed-methods research strategy, the overall aim of which 
was to triangulate data from different sources in order to 
learn more about the provision and utilisation of health ser-
vices by people with progressive ataxia. For clarity, in this 
article, we report solely qualitative findings from semi-
structured interviews. An analysis of statistical data related 
to resource use will be presented elsewhere. 
A recent study utilising data posted to Internet discussion 
fora found that diagnosis in ataxia was widely regarded as an 
arduous and frustrating process for patients. An idiopathic 
designation (anecdotally about 30%-40% of all cerebellar 
ataxias) was regarded by many as a 'non-diagnosis', and 
there was some evidence that patients in this category had 
withdrawn from medical contact. However, people with an 
idiopathic designation were over-represented in the sample. 7  An analysis of patient interviews at baseline found that peo-
ple generally had more experience of diagnosis than man-
agement, although physical therapies and disability aids 
were the most valued aspects of health service provision. 8 In 
this article, we focus on the diagnostic process and also 
incorporate the views of consultant neurologists. More 
importantly, we include the results of patient follow-up inter-
views, which allow a more detailed consideration of the sub-
jective effects on patients of diagnostic processes and 
outcomes over time. Follow-up interviews took place in 
2011, 12 months after baseline interviews. The time period 
for which we gathered data on service use and provision 
allows for comparison alongside existing benchmarked data 
on services for people with long-term neurological condi-
tions more generally. 9 </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Interviews were undertaken as part of a wider study con-
cerned with the provision, utilisation, experiences and costs 
of health services for people with ataxia. An exploratory 
study design was adopted that incorporated triangulation of 
data collected from patient interviews, diaries, hospital case </p>

<p>notes and interviews with health professionals. Overall, a lon-
gitudinal and mixed-methods approach was adopted, although 
quantitative findings in relation to costs and care pathways 
are considered elsewhere (manuscript in preparation). This 
article focuses on experiences and perceptions as gleaned 
from semi-structured interviews that were analysed themati-
cally. Patients were interviewed at two time points, 12 months 
apart, whereas neurologists were only interviewed once. 
At the outset, it was expected that patient interviewees 
would articulate a narrative describing symptom history and 
health service use. An interview guide was initially con-
structed in relation to this expectation. Given the exploratory 
nature of the study, a grounded theory approach was used in 
the collection and analysis of interview data. However, this 
grounded theory approach was applied mainly as a means of 
'coding' and constantly comparing the data collected, rather 
than as a means of generating substantive social theory. 10 We 
were more concerned with generating themes for investiga-
tion in future studies and pointers towards ways of improv-
ing services for people with progressive ataxia. 
The issue of diagnosis rapidly emerged as a core category 
in the patient interviews and became a research focus in the 
ongoing collection and analysis of data. While we were mainly 
concerned with health service use, many people with ataxia 
interviewed had not used medical services beyond diagnostic 
investigation. Many perceived that there is nothing that can be 
done for people with ataxia or reported that they had been told 
this directly by medical staff. Thus, a key concern of the inter-
views with neurologists was to compare their views on the 
diagnosis process and the perceived utility of medical man-
agement with those of patients. The longitudinal component 
allowed us to capture patients who were currently involved in 
ongoing diagnostic investigations and assess their views on 
how a diagnosis (or the absence of or changes to a diagnostic 
label) had affected the management of their condition. </p>

<p>The sample </p>

<p>A total of 38 people with ataxia and 8 consultant neurologists 
were enrolled and completed an interview. The patient sam-
pling strategy was purposive. First, 22 members of Ataxia 
UK living in North West England were invited to join the 
study by letter, following identification on a national mem-
bership list. Of them, 10 (45%) agreed to take part. Second, 
the research worker visited meetings of two local Ataxia UK 
groups where a further 10 people were recruited following a 
presentation about the study. A further 8 people were 
recruited by letter via a clinical genetics department (36% of 
the 22 asked to take part) and a further 10 through a consult-
ant neurologist (50% of 20 invited to participate by letter). A 
total of 29 neurologists working in North West England were 
approached by invitation letters, emails and word of mouth 
about the study and 7 were recruited (28% response rate). 
One neurologist from outside the region, who was an ataxia 
specialist, was also interviewed. The 7 neurologists from </p>

<p>Daker-White et al. </p>



<p>within the region were all notionally 'based' at one regional 
neurological centre, although 4 of them chiefly ran neuro-
logical clinics at other hospital sites across Greater 
Manchester. </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>The study had ethical approval, and written, informed 
consent was obtained from all respondents prior to inter-
view. People with ataxia were interviewed in their own 
homes about the effect of ataxic symptoms on their lives 
and their views and experiences of services. At 12-month 
follow-up, they were asked about perceptions of symptom 
changes and interaction with health services (n = 31). 
Neurologists were interviewed at their workplace about 
their experiences of diagnosis and management in pro-
gressive ataxia and their views of service provision. 
Separate semi-structured topic guides were used for 
patient baseline and follow-up interviews and those with 
neurologists. Interviews were tape-recorded, except in the 
case of two patients who did not give consent to be 
recorded. In these cases, notes were taken by hand. Two 
external transcription agencies were used to transcribe the 
tape recordings. Follow-up interviews were transcribed 
by the first author (G.D.-W.). </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>Transcripts and notes of interviews were analysed with the 
aid of <rs id="software-0" type="software">ATLAS.ti</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.2</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Scientific Software Development GmbH</rs>, Berlin), a computer software package 
for qualitative data. The semi-structured interview sched-
ule was employed flexibly and was also grounded in that it 
was adapted as the study progressed. A preliminary analy-
sis on the first 12 patient interviews was undertaken by the 
first author (G.D.-W.), who also conducted the interviews. 
Subsequently, the conceptual framework was expanded in 
discussion with all the authors of this article. Although the 
original aim was to describe patient experiences relating to 
investigation and management of their ataxia, it rapidly 
became evident as the baseline interviews progressed that 
most people's contact with health services ended when 
diagnostic investigations were completed, whether or not 
an underlying aetiology was found. Accordingly, diagnosis 
became a focus in the interviews and in the analysis. This 
article focuses especially on the follow-up data as these 
experiences are likely to better reflect the current situation 
for users in services, as opposed to their own historical 
experiences of health services, which in some cases 
stretched back several decades. In the results to follow, 
interview extracts are labelled using two or three fields 
showing the participant ID, quotation number and (in base-
line interviews only) line numbers from the interview 
transcript (e.g. P14: 6: 74-78 or P37: 12). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patients' perspectives and experiences at baseline 
interview </p>

<p>A total of 20 men and 18 women with a mean age of 52.5 
years (median = 50.5, range = 22-77) were interviewed at 
time point one. Of them, 14 (36.8%) had received an aetio-
logical diagnosis for a specific type of inherited ataxia. These 
included Friedreich's ataxia (FA) (n = 7); SCA (SCA1 (n = 
1), SCA2 (n = 2), SCA7 (n = 2), SCA8 (n = 1)) and ataxia 
linked to the fragile-X (FMR1) gene (n = 1). A total of 11 
patients reported that their ataxia was linked to a family his-
tory, but a specific type had not been identified by genetic 
testing. Two pairs of respondents were blood relatives. A 
total of 13 patients (34% of 38) reported that no explanation 
had been found for their symptoms or that their ataxia had 
been designated as 'idiopathic'. The time since patients had 
received a diagnosis ranged from 1 to 38 years (median = 5.5 
years), although there was also wide variation in age of onset 
of symptoms. It was apparent that several had lived with 
symptoms but without a diagnostic label for considerable 
periods of time. 
Most of those interviewed reported that it had not taken 
long to achieve a diagnosis of ataxia once they had seen a 
neurologist. However, given the typically slow and insidious 
onset characteristics of progressive ataxia, most had been on 
a long journey between initial symptom onset and diagnosis. 
A small number reported having initial symptoms dismissed 
by general practitioners (GPs) and/or spending some time 
being investigated and treated in ENT (ear, nose and throat) 
departments before being referred to a neurologist. In these 
cases, it had taken some years to achieve a diagnosis of 
ataxia. In all, five patients had previous diagnoses (vertigo, 
chronic headache syndrome, suspected sinus infection, sco-
liosis and cerebral palsy) changed to cerebellar ataxia. Of 
them, three of those with an idiopathic designation, or who 
had a family history of ataxia unconfirmed by the available 
genetic tests, had pursued further diagnostic testing, for 
example, by attending one of the four national specialist 
ataxia centres in an attempt to find the definitive cause for 
their symptoms. One would have liked to attend a specialist 
centre but was unable to secure the necessary funding 
arrangements in order to do so. In general terms, it was pos-
sible to discern two different approaches to dealing with a 
diagnosis of progressive ataxia: engaging with biomedicine 
or withdrawing from the health system and coping alone 
(results shown elsewhere). 8  The interviews undertaken indicated that the study group 
was composed of individuals with extremely diverse illness 
histories in terms of symptoms, onset, disabilities and speed 
of progression. However, most shared a dissatisfaction with 
health services and a frustration that their condition was 
incurable and sometimes of unknown cause. It was also 
widely reported by patients that the majority of health </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine 0(0) </p>

<p>workers do not know what 'ataxia' is, which was confirmed 
by one person with ataxia who was a nurse: </p>

<p>She was the first doctor after six years of investigation who said, 
'[Mary] you've got ataxia'. And I said, 'I've got what?' And she 
said 'You've got ataxia it's biological, genetic'. (Female, SCA2 
diagnosis, P14: 6: 74-78) </p>

<p>For some patients, the lack of clarity surrounding their 
diagnosis led them to characterise 'ataxia' as 'something that 
[doctors] can't explain' (as in P32: 18: 225-230). Only three 
patients reported the diagnosis process as being in anyway 
positive. Two of these had an underlying aetiology identi-
fied, and one remained idiopathic. 
Patients' accounts of the diagnostic process focused on 
interactions with medical professionals who were character-
ised as being either expert or inexperienced with regard to 
ataxia. Most people who had been for neurological work-up 
reported having a series of tests, sometimes over a long 
period of time and on other occasions in more intensive ses-
sions focused on one, two or three hospital visits. One young 
man with an FA diagnosis, who had undertaken research into 
his condition on the Internet, wondered why he had had so 
many 'unnecessary' tests when the diagnosis was proven by 
a blood test for FA gene analysis. However, more commonly, 
patients' accounts of these issues echoed those of doctors 
(see below), concerning structural limitations in the National 
Health Service (NHS) around appointment slots for follow-
ups and the time taken to receive test results. 
Although most patients' accounts of the diagnostic pro-
cess focused on biotechnological tests (e.g. scans, blood 
tests, electro-conductive studies or genetic tests), they some-
times defined neurologists as being specialists in ataxia by 
their ability to diagnose ataxia by use of history taking and 
physical examination alone: </p>

<p>She gave me a diagnosis; even though she didn't test my blood, 
she just knew what it was, by examining me and talking to me 
and that. So that made me feel a lot better. But because I went to 
see her, I mean, it did take hold. (Female, idiopathic ataxia, P22: 
29: 169-174) </p>

<p>In the case described above, the patient reported improved 
well-being, brought about by having confidence in the ataxia 
specialist. However, she says that her ataxia 'took hold' after 
seeing a clinical expert. This would suggest a form of 'symp-
tom amplification', 11 whereby people become more aware of 
their symptoms as a result of the diagnostic process. 
Symptom amplification was most evident in the account of 
an older woman with mild episodic ataxia, who received her 
diagnosis following investigation in her son: </p>

<p>Partner of patient: Since [my son] has been diagnosed, 
we've all been more focussed on the </p>

<p>symptoms you've been having, 
before we just ignored them. 
Patient: 
Before I just thought it was me, you 
know, I get tired, I get dizzy. 
Partner of patient: So in effect we feel they have been 
worse since [my son was diagnosed], 
because things that would have been 
shrugged off before, we now attrib-
ute to ataxia. (P17: 19: 346-357). </p>

<p>The preceding two interviewees cited that both had forms 
of ataxia that were presumed to be inherited, but this could 
not be confirmed by the genetic tests currently available. 
Those with a family history seemed to have most to gain 
from recent technological advances in genetic testing, but 
perhaps also the most to 'lose' when the promise of biomedi-
cine failed to yield the kinds of certainty expected via the 
diagnosis process. Many patients were aware that a certain 
number of types of cerebellar ataxia are currently identifia-
ble, 3 although this knowledge did not seem to provide any 
solace when they were found to have a type of ataxia not 
currently identifiable: </p>

<p>No, the professor thought that it was something I was born with, 
they couldn't pinpoint what was actually causing it at that 
specific time … I think with Ataxia you go up to a certain 
number and they hadn't gone possibly beyond that range where 
they thought I could have had, I don't know, whatever number it 
was up to at the time or beyond. (Female, idiopathic ataxia, P30: 
7: 159-170) </p>

<p>Patient responses to this clinical uncertainty varied. In 
some, it provoked fear and criticisms of medical compe-
tence, as in the case of a young woman with a presumed 
genetic diagnosis: </p>

<p>Patient: 
I was so frightened of what was happening 
and nobody could tell me what was caus-
ing it. 
Interviewer: … [Later, during the same interview] … 
What's been the worst thing in health 
services? 
Patient: 
Not getting a proper diagnosis. All those 
years and years knowing something was 
wrong, and almost having to tell them 
myself. Come on I've got these symptoms 
and they match my father's and brother's, so 
just the length of time it took. Is that normal? 
(P12: 19: 154-156 and 64: 1031-1040) </p>

<p>Other patients appeared to be less concerned by the limits 
of medicine in the context of ataxia diagnosis, as demonstrated 
by a patient who had had extensive investigations as a child: </p>

<p>Daker-White et al. </p>



<p>Interviewer: So has anybody ever told you exactly what 
you've got or what the cause of it is? 
Patient: 
No, no. As I say, I'm not that bothered. 
Interviewer: Okay. 
Patient: 
I'm genuinely not that bothered (Male, 
assumed genetic ataxia, P23: 17: 99-106) </p>

<p>Neurologists' perspectives </p>

<p>Eight neurologists were interviewed. Two were specialists in 
ataxia diagnosis (i.e. they had a larger ataxia patient case 
load than the 'one or two' patients encountered by most), 
while the remainder specialised in other fields of neurology 
(e.g. multiple sclerosis (MS) and movement disorders). As 
with the patients interviewed, the consultant neurologists 
interviewed described the diagnosis process in ataxia as con-
sisting of a possible plethora of tests to exclude treatable 
conditions or identify the cause of the illness. Neurologists 
regularly complained that most test results come back as 
'normal' or 'negative' when investigating ataxia. In relation 
to this 'negative yield' of diagnostic tests, some consultants 
also discussed the financial resource implications of order-
ing a large number of tests that would be unlikely to provide 
a definitive diagnosis or affect the medical management of 
the condition. The typical diagnostic pathway is character-
ised in the following extract: </p>

<p>It is a presentation which often leads to a circuitous diagnostic 
process with increasing desperation regarding tests and you're 
often left with an uncertain scenario … where diagnosis will 
come to light later on down the line as new symptoms perhaps 
develop. Sometimes, you know, in a significant proportion of 
patients, you do all the tests you can do for treatable and [other] 
conditions … and you're left with a blank concluding some sort 
of idiopathic or presumed genetic condition for which you 
haven't been able to identify at the moment. So that often puts 
them in a sort of situation where they've got this ongoing 
diagnostic doubt which, you know, some patients and clinicians 
find difficult to cope with. (Consultant P6: 1: 136-146) </p>

<p>Several consultants pointed to the fact that 'ataxia' is an 
umbrella term describing a medical syndrome or condition, 
for example, </p>

<p>Because we as neurologists feel slightly uneasy of the fact because 
we know that 'ataxia' is just a word that describes a syndrome and 
it's not really, it's a level of a diagnosis but it's not the final level 
which might be a gene test or antibody test or whatever. But 
patients, 'ataxia' is not a word that they use, so 'ataxia' for many 
patients is as good a diagnosis as MS or epilepsy or, you know 
that's the name of the disease 'ataxia'. But others want a more 
specific diagnosis than that. (Consultant P4: 10: 376-382) </p>

<p>Several consultants alluded to the notion of the 'level of 
diagnosis' in ataxia, with one ataxia specialist describing a 
generic 'ataxia' diagnosis as a 'black box diagnosis of ataxia' 
(Consultant P1: 39: 947-949), which results in inevitable </p>

<p>uncertainty about management. However, most of the neu-
rologists interviewed suggested that there is little that neu-
rologists can do in management terms in any case: </p>

<p>The primary role as a neurologist is actually to diagnose the 
existence of ataxia and then work out why that might have 
occurred. So look for an underlying cause such as MS or 
whatever. Once we have got a diagnosis or excluded as many 
treatable things as we can and we are left with an idiopathic 
ataxia, then I am a bit limited really in what I can do. Sometimes 
in the case of idiopathic ataxias I may continue to follow patients 
up in case something emerges that helps with the diagnosis at a 
later date, and as part of that follow-up time I am interested in 
disability and how that's affecting the patient. Having said that 
often that is looked after more by Professions Allied to Medicine 
(PAMs) and even neuro-rehabilitation consultants. So when I 
see someone with primary ataxia … I have a tendency to refer 
on to a neuro-rehabilitation consultant so that they can provide 
more of a holistic approach to sort of, managing the disorder 
than I can. (Specialist Consultant P2: 4: 27-51) </p>

<p>It should be noted that all of those interviewed, with the 
exception of one specialist, believed that the primary role of the 
neurologist in ataxia ends with the diagnostic process. One-half 
of the non-specialist neurologists interviewed held the view 
popularly reported by patients that 'there is nothing that can be 
done' for people with ataxia. One questioned the value of fol-
low-up appointments in this context (Consultant P4: 17: 512-
515). Of the six non-specialist neurologists, one-half were 
explicit that they would refer the patients to an ataxia specialist, 
in order to increase the likelihood of a 'definitive' diagnosis 
and to enable more effective targeting of finite NHS resources. 
One of the ataxia specialists reported that on occasion diagno-
sis was achieved as if by accident, when a result surprisingly 
came back positive. Two of the non-specialists suggested that 
extensive testing in ataxia was wasteful of resources and ques-
tionable on clinical grounds, especially when the outcome was 
seen as having little impact on illness management. One of the 
specialist consultants also held these views. 
For both specialist and non-specialist neurologists, the 
'successful' diagnosis of a cause of progressive ataxia was 
described as a rare event. As in the patients' accounts, there 
we also regularly reported structural problems associated 
with working within the constraints of NHS bureaucracy. 
These issues were seen to exacerbate the diagnostic prob-
lems faced by ataxic patients. When one doctor was asked 
about a specific case of SCA6, her response showed how the 
number of tests ordered by a neurologist, as well as the pro-
portion of positive results, might be seen to reflect the skills 
of an individual clinician (Consultant P5: 16: 844-874), thus 
supporting the notion of referral to specialist centres. </p>

<p>Patient follow-up interviews </p>

<p>Of the 38 patients interviewed at baseline, 7 were lost to fol-
low-up at 1 year for the following reasons: (1) non-contactable 
(n = 2); (2) withdrew, no reason given (n = 1); (3) withdrew: </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine 0(0) </p>

<p>'She's never had any treatment, she has it very mild, there's 
nothing else she can tell you' (n = 1); (4) missed interview 
appointments (n = 1); (5) moved away (n = 1); and (6) 
declined, stress over problems at work due to ataxia (n = 1). 
The follow-up interviews were short in comparison with the 
baseline interviews, with an average length of only 21 min. 
Many people had not experienced symptom changes, and/or 
they had no or minimal contact with health services, which 
were the primary topics of interest. One patient provided an 
email follow-up response that was analysed alongside the 
interview transcripts. 
Patient's accounts at follow-up highlighted themes found 
in other qualitative studies of chronic conditions such as in 
a review of studies of rheumatoid arthritis 12 and related to 
acceptance, adaptation and coping strategies. Many patients 
continued to discuss the stigmatising effects of ataxia, as 
found at baseline 8 and as highlighted by Boutté in her semi-
nal study of Machado-Joseph disease (now known as 
SCA3). 13 Accounts of health-care services were focused on 
the themes illustrated in Table 1. As at baseline, a dispropor-
tionate amount of discussion focused on problems negotiat-
ing or getting service inputs, with a specific issue around 
neurological follow-up appointments for people with idio-
pathic ataxia. Table 1 also reveals a consumerist approach to 
service provision, with people 'pushing' for provision. One 
interviewee's carer specifically recommended that people 
with a diagnosis of a progressive disabling condition like 
ataxia should be given an 'A4 signpost of helping agencies' 
(P19: 20). When considering specific positive and negative 
comments about services (Table 2), it appeared that physi-
otherapy input was generally viewed favourably and most 
negative comments were directed towards interaction with 
mainstream health-care workers or doctors seen for other 
health problems, including GPs. It should be stressed that in 
some cases, involvement in the study seemed to have 
spurred patients into seeking out services and care more 
proactively. It was noteworthy that most of those who gave 
more favourable accounts of neurological services had an 
FA diagnosis, perhaps because there is screening for, and 
management of, the associated non-neurological complica-
tions of the condition. 
Scrutiny of Tables 1 and 2 suggests that dealing with 
ataxia is as much about dealing with a diagnostic process as 
it is about dealing with symptoms. Rather than increasing 
certainty in relation to disease label and prognosis, the diag-
nostic process had in some cases magnified these uncertain-
ties. However, in one case, an interviewee suggested that 
patients accepted their condition more following a period of 
extensive diagnostic testing (P30: 12 and Table 1). By exten-
sion, it can be argued that recognising that answers to ques-
tions may never be found is one of the things that patients 
have to adapt to in response to a diagnosis of progressive 
ataxia. Comments from another interviewee at follow-up in 
this regard (P31: 9 and Table 2) would suggest that patients 
might benefit from being informed at the outset that </p>

<p>diagnosis may take a long time and that answers might never 
be found. This may be equally applicable to other neurode-
generative conditions of course. However, in the case of 
ataxia, the health service and illness experience seem to be 
fundamentally distinguishable according to whether a defini-
tive -as opposed to a 'black box' -diagnosis is achieved, 
with negative accounts associated with people with idio-
pathic diagnoses. Fundamentally, many in this group describe 
being, or feeling, 'lost' to services, and the potential impor-
tance of diagnosis as the key to access therapies and clinical 
follow-up is underlined. 
Commonly, people with ataxia -whenever they were 
interviewed -expressed frustration at having a condition for 
which either there is no cure or 'nothing can be done'. 
Against this background and expectations, when people had 
found therapies or other interventions (e.g. physiotherapy or 
a prescription for coenzyme Q10), they were highly valued. 
However, in management terms, there appeared problems in 
this regard as their care was often undertaken by GPs who 
are generally seen as lacking knowledge in relation to pro-
gressive ataxias. Thus, in broad terms, a key issue for people 
with ataxia in their encounters with health professionals 
related to the individual expertise of each health worker 
encountered. Perceived lack of knowledge about ataxia 
caused trouble for people with the condition in their encoun-
ters with health professionals about other matters and in set-
tings other than clinical neurology or primary care. From the 
viewpoint of the people with ataxia interviewed for this 
study, the need for more health workers to be made aware 
about ataxia appears unequivocal. In the perceived absence 
of medical interventions, an expert sympathetic ear was 
highly valued. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Medical sociologists have considered the diagnosis process 
as a means by which patients' symptoms are 'made intelligi-
ble' 14 or rendered 'coherent'. 15 The accounts of both neurol-
ogists and patients suggest that ataxia remains a problematic 
diagnosis of uncertainty. For those who did not manage to 
secure a 'definitive' explanation for their progressively disa-
bling conditions, the diagnostic process seemed somehow 
incomplete, engendering what one clinician termed 'ongoing 
diagnostic doubt': a challenge for patient and doctor alike. 
Of the 38 patients interviewed for this study, only 3 (8%) 
perceived anything positive in achieving a medical diagnosis 
of 'ataxia' for their symptoms, although some patients were 
coping better with their diagnostic status when seen at fol-
low-up. The findings suggest that the diagnosis of 'ataxia' 
represents the first step in identifying an underlying cause, 
which can give more certainty. This was achieved for some 
patients by the time of the follow-up interview, where, for 
example, the disease category was defined as being multi-
system atrophy in two cases. One interviewee had undergone 
genetic testing, which identified a specific type of SCA, but </p>

<p>Daker-White et al. </p>



<p>declined to know details and implications of the final result. 
On the whole, defining the underlying cause of their ataxia 
made little difference to patients when there was still no cure 
for whatever aetiological label they had been given. 
As an umbrella term for a group of conditions, progressive 
ataxias present patients and their doctors with a range of trou-
bles and challenges beyond the debilitating nature of the 
symptoms. The length of time it took some patients in this 
study for their condition to be labelled as 'ataxia' points to a 
need for greater awareness of ataxic symptoms in primary 
care in order to reduce the length of the diagnostic journey for 
patients. Despite differences of opinion, one issue that seemed 
to unite neurologists was the importance of excluding treata-
ble forms of ataxia. However, given that treatable forms are </p>

<p>rare (within a group of conditions that are rare as a whole), it 
is perhaps understandable that neurologists would not explic-
itly impart the details of these investigations in order to avoid 
a possibly false hope that a treatment might be found. While 
the approach taken by neurologists reflects their wide experi-
ence that extensive tests will be returned with 'normal' or 
'negative' results, the confusion and uncertainty demon-
strated in some patient accounts suggest a need for a more 
structured approach to diagnosis and subsequent referral, 
such that patients -perhaps especially those with an idio-
pathic designation -do not get 'lost in the system' following 
diagnostic investigation. Our results also point to a need for 
an evidence base to support the clinical utility of current diag-
nostic processes, including the role of genetic tests. </p>

<p>Table 1. Themes in accounts of patients' experiences of health services between baseline and follow-up (n = 31). </p>

<p>Theme 
Diagnostics 
Management </p>

<p>Adapting with 
experience </p>

<p>'The future is not as bad as I first thought 
… When you are first diagnosed nobody 
can tell you how fast it's going to progress' 
(P2: 35); 'I have fully embraced now, my 
condition' (P14: 5); now accepts it more 
following long period of diagnostic tests 
(P30: 12) </p>

<p>Fatigue has got stronger over the past year 'to the 
point that I can't fight it at all' (P22: 16); 'I just can't 
walk anywhere … To be honest its getting me down 
… I've tried to carry on' (P38: 5-7); 'My family must 
come first' (P2: 32); 'I know how to go about things 
better than I did … Now I know you can go and get 
things' (P24: 11) 
I do not see 
anyone about my 
ataxia </p>

<p>Complains the neurologists he knew have all 
retired. They used to say, 'I'm sorry we can't 
do anything for you, but we'd like to see you 
anyway'. Has not seen a neurologist for 6-8 
years (P1: 21) </p>

<p>'See if they send another appointment' (P4: 18); 
'Hospital keep missing my appointments out' (P9: 8 
and P16: 6); 'I think I got lost in the system' (P29: 8); 
'I thought they would send for me and tell me how it 
was getting on' (P8: 10 and P13: 5); 'I very rarely visit 
the hospital nowadays' (P11: 32); does not want regular 
follow-up with neuro/physio (P14: 9); does not see 
health-care workers about ataxia (P23: 4); 'Nobody's 
been to see me' (P10: 6) </p>

<p>'Just keep an eye on me really' (P33: 9) </p>

<p>Negotiating 
access to 
services </p>

<p>'Because I'm helping them' by attending 
for medical education sessions; hoping to 
be pushed 'to the top of the list' (P3: 4, 24 
and 29); went for a test at an ataxia clinic 
but has received letters saying the NHS are 
reviewing whether they will pay for the test 
or not (P37: 12) </p>

<p>Passes on ataxia info to GP: 'I think I'm educating them'; 
'My GP would listen to me because I insist' (P2: 31 and 
41); reports funding for physiotherapy being withdrawn. 
GP exploring other funding options (P12: 8); wife 
assertive in arranging therapists (P19: 14); 'Everything 
I get done, I instigate it' (P24: 7); 'You're sort of left 
abandoned' (P16: 10) 
They could not 
do anything (was 
in vivo code) </p>

<p>Diagnosis changed from FA to Charcot 
Marie Tooth disease. 'My first reaction was, 
"Is there a cure for it?" Unfortunately not.' 
(P3: 10); 'Nothing they can do' (P2: 6); 'He's 
done all the tests, he can't do anymore' 
(P24: 6); discharged by neurologist: 'There's 
nothing I can do for you' (P27: 10) </p>

<p>'The doctor says there's nothing wrong with it'; 
'Definitely there is nothing he can find'; 'They couldn't 
do anything' re: cough, GP and speech therapist (P1: 
9, 10 and 15); GPs -'No point in getting involved with 
them' (P1: 26); 'Doctor prescribed voltarol but they 
don't seem to do anything' (P3: 37); 'Can't get pain 
relief from anything [uses cannabis instead]' (P20: 10); 
when asked what happened at annual neurological 
appointment: 'Very little' (P7: 13); 'I don't think there is 
anything much anyone can do' re: hearing (P11: 17) </p>

<p>'The doctor said, "We can't do anything 
for you, see you in 9 months." It used to 
be every 6 months, so he must think I'm 
better'. (P30: 8) 
Value of specialist 
services (±) </p>

<p>Had genetic tests but declined to know the 
detail of the diagnosis (P9: 10) </p>

<p>Visit with neurologist perceived as useful now attends 
larger hospital (P5: 8); 'I don't think the GP is as aware 
of ataxia as he could be' (P7: 10); 'He doesn't know 
anything about [ataxia]' (P8: 13); stayed with old GP 
after moving as he knew about ataxia (P9: 17) </p>

<p>GP: general practitioner. </p>



<p>SAGE Open Medicine 0(0) </p>

<p>Complex conditions such as ataxia can affect a range of 
physical functions, which often means that care needs to be 
coordinated between different health professionals. From the 
patient's viewpoint, it is helpful if someone is overseeing 
their care and that provision of different service is 'joined 
up'. In ataxia centres, specialist ataxia nurses are able to pro-
vide the kinds of general information and support (e.g. how 
to access mobility aids or social care benefits) needed by 
patients in addition to medical care and expertise. However, 
given that such a service would be valued by those with other 
neurological conditions, a challenge for services is how to 
provide such generic advice within a specialist model of 
care. 
While analysis of patient baseline 8 material noted that a 
definitive diagnostic label may not be important in terms 
of access to treatment and services, the results at follow-up 
suggested that a genetic diagnosis of FA is useful in terms 
of accessing a care pathway and management plan. This 
was reflected in study participants with a diagnosis of FA </p>

<p>seemingly reporting greater satisfaction with neurology 
services than other groups of ataxia patients. FA is the 
most commonly inherited form of ataxia found in the 
United Kingdom and has specific clinical features includ-
ing an increased risk of diabetes and cardiomyopathy, 
which can be monitored and managed by other specialist 
medical services. 1 In this respect, there is a better defined 
clinical pathway for FA than for SCAs and idiopathic 
ataxia. This could explain why those with an idiopathic 
ataxia seemed more negative about neurology services 
(Table 2) and less satisfied with issues relating to clinical 
management and follow-up. The fact that people with a 
specific diagnosis report a better experience of neurologi-
cal services highlights the importance of a diagnosis. 
However, given an ageing population, the number of peo-
ple with idiopathic late onset ataxias is likely to increase. 
In the context of budget constraints and finite resources, 
the clinical need for an aetiological diagnosis may need to 
be weighed against the costs of meeting the needs of </p>

<p>Table 2. Patient's views of selected health services used between baseline and follow-up (n = 24). </p>

<p>Service 
Positive views 
Negative views </p>

<p>Neurology 
Neurologist seen as useful (P5: FA diagnosis) 
Complaints about neurology department missing or 
not offering appointments (P4: idiopathic diagnosis, 
P8: idiopathic diagnosis, P9: presumed genetic, 
P13: Fragile-X linked, P16: idiopathic diagnosis, P29 
idiopathic diagnosis) 
Sees a neurologist at a specialist ataxia centre: 'He tries 
to get [a test] done on my heart every year' (P22: FA 
diagnosis) </p>

<p>Attended specialist ataxia clinic but felt it was 'a bit 
of a waste of time' (P37: idiopathic diagnosis) </p>

<p>'I understand better that it takes time to diagnose this 
thing and then once they've put the label on it … just 
try and take the edge off some of the symptoms. And 
that seems to be working for me'. (P31: 9, presumed 
genetic ataxia) 
Physiotherapy 
Physio taught her Pilates and strategies. 'It's up to 
me to do [the exercises]'. Feels improvement in 
confidence; given practical tips (P2: 21 and 39); 'They 
were very good, they gave me strategies … But 
it made me feel better. It made me feel as though 
someone was temporarily interested in me' (P2: 8-11) </p>

<p>'Quite disgusted' that funding for physiotherapy was 
withdrawn: 'It's the only treatment, isn't it?' (P12: 9) </p>

<p>Wife links lack of progression with extensive 
physiotherapy involvement (P13: 9); 'What I find helpful 
is I see my physiotherapist regularly' (P18: 4) 
General 
Practice </p>

<p>GP putting her on a 'trial' of coenzyme Q10 was 
reported as the best thing that had happened in last 12 
months (P2: 43) </p>

<p>'I don't think the GP is as aware of ataxia as he 
could be' (P7: 10 and P8: 13) </p>

<p>GP arranging another neurological referral after the 
neurologist discharged her (P27: 11)   Disagreed with GP that back pain was anything to 
do with ataxia (P14: 7) 
'He just randomly googled it' (P22: 15) 
Services used 
for other 
medical 
conditions </p>

<p>'In hospital, they didn't know what cerebellar ataxia 
was'; 'Oh let's look that up' (P4: 15 and 21) 
Critical of incident involving reinsertion of catheter. 
Received formal apology from hospital (P5: 11) 
'They hadn't even read my notes … They didn't 
even know I was in a wheelchair' (P22: 8 and 9) </p>

<p>Daker-White et al. </p>



<p>patients with a progressively disabling and incurable 
condition. 
Through the unusual case of a woman in her 70s who had 
lifelong symptoms of 'vertigo' changed to ataxia as a result of 
investigations for ataxic symptoms in her son, the circum-
stances under which a diagnosis of ataxia can lead to a form 
of 'symptom amplification' 11 were revealed. However, the 
mechanisms of symptom amplification are by no means clear 
from this isolated case but point to a fruitful area for further 
research. In the case of ataxia, however, the fact that there are 
putative treatments for vertigo, whereas there are none for 
ataxia may form the kernel of the matter. What remains 
unclear on the basis of our findings is whether people are bet-
ter or worse off following a diagnostic process in the context 
of ataxic symptoms. Historically, attention has not been paid 
to the potential utility of diagnostic processes in the context 
of conditions for which there are no clear management out-
comes. However, in the context of the financial limits of 
health-care budgets, these issues are receiving increasing 
attention. As well as highlighting factors that present poten-
tially negative consequences for patients as a result of diag-
nostic processes, our findings underline the need for better 
integration of diagnostic algorithms and procedures with sub-
sequent care and support for people with ataxia. Finally, the 
setting for this study was an English health region, and it 
would be fruitful for others to compare our findings with 
those in other countries, settings and health systems in order 
to ascertain the best way of providing services to people liv-
ing with the challenges of progressive ataxia. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Krystle Kontoh (formerly of Genetic Alliance UK) also worked on 
the study described in this article. Karen Tricker and Beverley 
Leather provided administrative support. We thank the neurologists 
and people with ataxia who volunteered to be interviewed. We 
thank the members of our expert study panel: John Guhry, Paola 
Giunti, Marios Hadjivassilliou, Sue Lowe, Marion McAllister and 
the late David Gregory. </p>

<p>Declaration of conflicting interests </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This study presents independent research funded by the National 
Institute for Health Research (NIHR) under its Research for Patient 
Benefit (RfPB) Programme (Grant Reference Number PB-PG-0807-</p>

<p>13181). The views expressed are those of the authors and not neces-
sarily those of the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health. </p>



</text></tei>