<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4665705" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. A clinical requirement exists for early biomarkers 
that can predict the severity of acute pancreatitis (AP). In 
order to determine whether E-cadherin is associated with the 
severity of AP, a pancreatitic rat model was established and 
the expression levels of E-cadherin were detected. A study 
population of 24 Sprague Dawley rats was administered intra-
peritoneal injections of various concentrations of L-arginine 
in order to induce pancreatitis. Rats were assigned to the 
severe acute pancreatitis (SAP) or mild acute pancreatitis 
(MAP) group based on the results of histological evaluations 
and the serum levels of amylase. An additional 8 rats received 
intraperitoneal injections of NaCl solution, as a control 
group. For each group, the serum concentrations of soluble 
E-cadherin and the expression levels of E-cadherin protein in 
the pancreatic tissue were detected. The results indicated that 
the rat model of pancreatitis was successfully established. Rats 
in the high concentration L-arginine treatment group, which 
exhibited a higher pancreatitis pathology score and level of 
serum amylase, were assigned to the SAP group. Low concen-
tration L-arginine group rats were assigned to the MAP group. 
The pathology scores and levels of serum amylase in the SAP 
and MAP group rats were higher compared with the control 
group rats. The levels of serum E-cadherin were the most 
elevated in the SAP group. Statistically significant differences 
were detected in the SAP and MAP groups compared with 
the control group, and in the SAP group compared with the 
MAP group (P&lt;0.05). Furthermore, the levels of E-cadherin 
protein in the pancreatic tissue were elevated in the SAP group 
compared with the MAP and control groups. In conclusion, 
the present study demonstrated that E-cadherin was overex-</p>

<p>pressed in SAP rats, and the overexpression of E-cadherin may 
be associated with the severity of AP. </p>

<p>Acute pancreatitis (AP) is a severe inflammatory disease 
that accounts for &gt;220,000 hospital admissions in the United 
States each year (1). Although there has been recent progress 
in the diagnosis and treatment of AP, the incidence of AP has 
not decreased and its serious systemic complications are a 
worldwide health issue (2). In certain cases, severe AP (SAP) 
may lead to multiple organ failure, and thus the mortality rate 
among patients with SAP may approach 30% (3). Therefore, 
it is crucial to identify effective early diagnostic markers for 
AP, and particularly for SAP. The level of serum amylase is 
a commonly-used clinical indicator for the severity of AP; 
however, this level not particularly sensitive and it is often 
difficult to obtain a pancreatic specimen from patients with 
AP for pathological analysis (4,5). 
E-cadherin is a calcium-dependent cell-cell adhesion 
molecule that has been linked to cancer development and 
inflammatory disorders (6,7). During the inflammatory 
process, cell-cell contacts tend to dissolve, which permits 
the unregulated movement of fluids and electrolytes into the 
interstitial space, resulting in tissue edema (8). Once AP has 
been initiated, the appearance of inflammatory infiltration 
and interstitial edema are common features (9). Therefore, it is 
hypothesized that the expression levels of E-cadherin fluctuate 
during the progression of AP. The aim of the present study was 
to establish an animal model of pancreatitis and evaluate the 
levels of soluble E-cadherin, in order to assess its efficacy as a 
marker of AP severity. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Pancreatitic animal model and experimental design. Animal 
experiments were authorized according to the Guidance 
Suggestions for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals 
issued by the Ministry of Science and Technology of the 
People's Republic of China, and were approved by the Ethics 
Committee of the Nanjing Medical University Affiliated 
Wuxi Second Hospital (Wuxi, China). Sprague Dawley (SD) 
rats were supplied by the Sino-British SIPPR/BK Laboratory 
Animal Co., Ltd., (Shanghai, China). Animal experiments 
were conducted as described in previous studies (10,11) at </p>

<p>E-cadherin expression in a rat model of acute pancreatitis </p>

<p>WEIHONG YUAN 
1* , QI PAN 
1* , GUOCHANG CHEN 
1 , JUN YAN 
2 , JIAZENG XIA 
3 and YIGANG CHEN </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Gastroenterology, Yixing People's Hospital, Yixing, Jiangsu 214200; 
2 Department of General Surgery, </p>

<p>Shanghai Jiao Tong University Affiliated Sixth People's Hospital, Shanghai 200233; 
3 Department of General Surgery, </p>

<p>Nanjing Medical University Affiliated Wuxi Second Hospital, Wuxi, Jiangsu 214002, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received August 29, 2014; Accepted July 14, 2015 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/etm.2015.2786 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Yigang Chen or Dr Jiazeng Xia, </p>

<p>Department of General Surgery, Nanjing Medical University 
Affiliated Wuxi Second Hospital, 68 Zhongshan Road, Wuxi, 
Jiangsu 214002, P.R. China 
E-mail: iamyigang@126.com 
E-mail: xjz_wuxi@alumni.sjtu.edu.cn </p>

<p>* Contributed equally </p>

<p>Key words: pancreatitis, severe acute pancreatitis, mild acute </p>

<p>pancreatitis, E-cadherin </p>

<p>YUAN et al: OVEREXPRESSION OF E-CADHERIN IN RATS WITH ACUTE PANCREATITIS </p>



<p>Nanjing Medical University Affiliated Wuxi No. 2 People's 
Hospital between June 2013 and July 2014. In brief, 24 healthy 
adult male Sprague Dawley (SD) rats, weighing 170±15.5 g, 
were randomly assigned into two treatment groups (n=12 per 
group). In the high concentration L-arginine (HCLa) group, 
each SD rat received two intraperitoneal injections of 20% 
L-arginine (Sinopharm Chemical Reagent Co., Ltd., Shanghai, 
China; 2.5 g/kg body weight), at an interval of 1 h. In the low 
concentration L-arginine (LCLa) group, each SD rat received 
two intraperitoneal injections of 6% L-arginine (2.5 g/kg body 
weight), at an interval of 1 h. At 24 h after the induction of 
pancreatitis using L-arginine, all SD rats were sacrificed under 
ether anesthesia. The pancreas of each rat was then rapidly 
removed, and separated from the surrounding lymph nodes 
and fat. Each pancreatic tissue sample was divided into two 
parts: One part was fixed in 10% buffered formaldehyde 
for histological evaluation and the second part was reserved 
for protein extraction. The severity of the pancreatitis was 
determined based on the histological scoring, including the 
degrees of edema, inflammation, vacuolization and necrosis, 
and by measurement of serum amylase levels. Furthermore, 
8 additional rats received intraperitoneal injections of an equal 
quantity of 0.9% NaCl solution, and were designated as the 
control group. </p>

<p>Histological evaluation. Pancreatic samples were fixed in 10% 
buffered formaldehyde, cut into 5 µm sections, and stained 
with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E; Maixin Biotech Co., Ltd., 
Fuzhou, China) and assessed blindly by two senior patholo-
gists (Qi Pan and Guochang Chen). The tissue sections were 
graded as described previously (12). A total of 10 high-power 
fields (HPF) of each section were selected at random and were 
visualized under a CX31 microscope (Olympus America Inc., 
Center Valley, PA, USA). Samples were scored on a scale of 
0-4, according to the degree of edema, necrosis, vacuolization 
and inflammation. The degree of edema was scored as follows: 
0, No edema; 1, diffuse expansion of interlobar septa; 2, severe 
diffuse expansion of interlobar septa; 3, diffuse expansion of 
interacinar septa; and 4, diffuse expansion of intercellular 
septa. The degree of inflammation was scored as follows: 0, 
No inflammation; 1, inflammation around ductal margin; 2, 
inflammation in parenchyma (&lt;50% of lobules); 3, inflamma-
tion in parenchyma (50-75% of lobules); and 4, inflammation 
in parenchyma (&gt;75% of lobules). The degree of vacuolization 
was scored as follows: 0, No vacuolization; 1, peroductal 
vacuolization (&lt;5%); 2, focal vacuolization (5-20%); 3, 
diffused vacuolization (21-50%); and 4, severe vacuolization 
(&gt;50%). The degree of necrosis was scored as follows: 0, No 
necrosis; 1, 1-4 necrotic cells/HPF; 2, 5-10 necrotic cells/HPF; 
3, 11-15 necrotic cells/HPF; and 4, &gt;16 necrotic cells/HPF. 
The final score was calculated as the sum of the results of all 
parameters (including degrees of edema, necrosis, vasculariza-
tion and inflammation). The final score was between 0 and 16. </p>

<p>Serum levels of amylase. During the animal experiments, a 
2-ml blood sample was extracted from each rat following anes-
thetization. The blood samples were centrifuged at 1,509 x g 
for 15 min, and stored at -80˚C until further use. The levels of 
serum amylase were measured using a Hitachi 7600-020 auto-
matic biochemical analyzer (Hitachi, Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) (13). </p>

<p>Serum levels of E-cadherin. A 2-ml blood sample was 
extracted from each rat following anesthetization. The levels 
of E-cadherin were measured using a commercially available 
MK117 E-cadherin ELISA kit (Takara Bio, Inc., Otsu, Japan). </p>

<p>Western blot analysis to determine the expression of 
E-cadherin protein. Whole cell lysates were prepared from 
pancreatic tissue specimens. Briefly, pancreatic tissue samples 
were homogenized using a glass-on-glass tissue homogenizer. 
Subsequently, the homogenates were centrifuged (10 min, 4˚C, 
11,750 x g) and the supernatants were collected. Total protein 
was extracted using a Qproteome Mammalian Protein Prep kit 
(Qiagen GmbH, Hilden, Germany). The levels of E-cadherin 
protein in the pancreatic tissue were measured using 
Coomassie blue staining (Maixin Biotech Co., Ltd.). A stan-
dard western blot assay was performed using a primary goat 
polyclonal antibody against rat E-cadherin (dilution, 1:1,000; 
catalog no. ab1416; Abcam, Cambridge, UK) and an anti-goat 
IgG antibody, which was a horseradish peroxidase-linked 
F (ab') 2 fragment obtained from a rabbit (dilution 1:2,000; 
catalog no. BA1060; Wuhan Boster Biological Technology, 
Ltd., Wuhan, China). The loading of equal quantities of protein 
samples was verified using an anti-β-actin antibody (dilution, 
1:1,000; catalog no. sc-47778; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., 
Dallas, TX, USA), with a secondary antibody (dilution, 1:2,000; 
cat. no. BA1051; Wuhan Boster Biological Technology, Ltd.), 
as a loading control. The proteins under investigation were 
detected using the Pierce Enhanced Chemiluminescence 
Western Blotting substrate (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., 
Waltham, MA, USA). The intensity of the bands was visu-
alized using an Amersham enhanced chemiluminescence 
system (ImageQuant LAS 4000; GE Healthcare Bio-Sciences, 
Pittsburgh, PA, USA), according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Statistical analysis was performed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). The 
experimental values were analyzed using the paired-samples 
t-test and were expressed as the mean ± standard deviation. 
One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was calculated to 
determine the differences between groups for each parameter 
at each time point. Non-parametrical Kruskal-Wallis tests 
were used when equal variances were not assumed in one-way 
ANOVA. P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate a statistically 
significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Histological analysis. No rats died unexpectedly following the 
intraperitoneal injections, and the rats were sacrificed at 24 h 
after the injections. In the control group (NaCl-treated), no 
pancreatic edema or peritoneal exudate were detected (Fig. 1A). 
H&amp;E staining of the control group pancreatic tissue revealed 
no significant swelling, inflammation or necrosis (Fig. 2A). In 
the LCLa group, edema of the pancreas and necrosis of the 
fat surrounding the pancreas were observed in all rat tissue 
samples (Fig. 1B). H&amp;E staining revealed interlobular edema 
and inflammatory cell infiltration in the pancreatic tissue 
(Fig. 2B). In the HCLa group, edema, hemorrhage, necrosis of 
the pancreas and bloody ascites were observed in all rat tissue </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL AND THERAPEUTIC MEDICINE 10: 2088-2092, 2015 </p>



<p>samples (Fig. 1C). Furthermore, the destruction of pancreatic 
lobules, interstitial edema, vascular congestion and infiltration 
of neutrophils and monocytes were observed in the HCLa 
group samples (Fig. 2C). 
Pathology scores for the HCLa (10.38±0.56) and LCLa 
(6.75±2.12) groups were higher compared with the control 
group (1.75±0.16). Statistically significant differences were 
detected in the HCLa and LCLa groups compared with 
the control group, and in the HCLa group compared with 
the LCLa group (P&lt;0.05). These results are presented in 
Table I and Fig. 3. </p>

<p>Serum levels of amylase. The levels of serum amylase 
were higher in the HCLa (1,497.29±319.57 U/l) and LCLa 
(1,003.83±111.52 U/l) groups compared with the control </p>

<p>group (301.75±26.89 U/l). Statistically significant increases in 
serum amylase were detected in the HCLa and LCLa groups 
compared with the control group, and in the HCLa group 
compared with the LCLa group (P&lt;0.05). The results are 
presented in Fig. 4. </p>

<p>SAP and mild AP (MAP) groups. All the HCLa and LCLa 
group rats exhibited inflammation and edema of the pancreas. 
However, hemorrhage and bloody ascites were only observed 
in the HCLa group rats. The most elevated pancreatitis 
pathology scores and serum amylase levels were observed in 
the HCLa group rats. In addition, the pathology scores and </p>

<p>Figure 1. Differences in the pancreatic tissues between the (A) control, 
(B) low concentration L-arginine (LCLa) and (C) high concentration 
L-arginine (HCLa) groups. Arrow 1 indicates normal pancreas tissue in the 
control group. Arrow 2 indicates edema of the pancreas and necrosis of fat 
around the pancreas tissue in the LCLa group. Arrow 3 indicates edema, 
hemorrhage and necrosis of a pancreas tissue in the HCLa group, and arrow 4 
indicates bloody ascites in the HCLa group. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Hematoxylin and eosin-stained pancreatic tissue from Sprague 
Dawley rats in the (A) control, (B) low concentration L-arginine (LCLa) and 
(C) high concentration L-arginine (HCLa) groups. No significant pancre-
atic swelling, inflammation or necrosis was observed in the control group. 
Interlobular edema and inflammatory cell infiltration was observed in the 
pancreatic tissue of the LCLa group. Destruction of the pancreatic lobules, 
interstitial edema, vascular congestion and inflammatory cell infiltration 
were observed in the HCLa group. </p>

<p>Table I. Histological scoring for rats with acute pancreatitis. </p>

<p>Group 
Edema 
Inflammation 
Vacuolization 
Necrosis 
Score </p>

<p>Control 
0.65±0.22 
0.44±0.19 
0.35±0.06 
0.31±0.09 
1.75±0.16 
LCLa 
3.52±2.13 
2.34±1.65 
0.45±0.07 
0.44±0.13 
6.75±2.12 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>HCLa 
3.08±1.77 
3.24±1.65 
1.85±0.92 
2.21±0.88 
10.38±0.56 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data are present as the mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. control group. LCLa, low concentration L-arginine group; HCLa, high concen-
tration L-arginine group. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>YUAN et al: OVEREXPRESSION OF E-CADHERIN IN RATS WITH ACUTE PANCREATITIS </p>



<p>levels of serum amylase in the HCLa and LCLa group rats 
were higher compared with the control group rats. Therefore, 
the HCLa rats were assigned as the SAP group, and the LCLa 
rats were assigned as the MAP group. </p>

<p>Serum levels of E-cadherin. The levels of E-cadherin were 
highest in the SAP group rats. In addition, the levels of 
E-cadherin were higher in the SAP (1,561.75±144.82 pg/ml) 
and MAP (1,025.50±131.33 pg/ml) groups compared with 
the control group (626.50±72.12 pg/ml; P&lt;0.05). Statistically 
significant elevations in serum E-cadherin were detected in 
the MAP and SAP groups compared with the control group 
(P&lt;0.05), and in the SAP group compared with the MAP 
group (P&lt;0.05). The results are presented in Fig. 5. </p>

<p>Expression of E-cadherin protein. The expression of 
E-cadherin protein was evaluated using western blot 
analysis. The levels of E-cadherin protein were higher in 
the SAP group compared with the MAP and control groups </p>

<p>(Fig. 6). Statistically significant differences in E-cadherin 
protein expression were detected between the SAP and MAP 
group rats, and between the SAP and control group rats. No 
statistically significant differences in E-cadherin protein 
expression were detected between the MAP and control 
group rats. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Pathology scores for the low concentration L-arginine, high con-
centration L-arginine and control groups. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05. 
Figure 5. Levels of E-cadherin in the MAP, SAP and control groups. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05. 
MAP, mild acute pancreatitis; SAP, severe acute pancreatitis. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Levels of serum amylase for the low concentration L-arginine, high 
concentration L-arginine and control groups. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Western blot analysis results for E-cadherin protein expression 
levels in the control, MAP and SAP groups. (A) Differential expression of 
E-cadherin protein in the control, MAP and SAP groups. (B) Statistical results 
of the levels of E-cadherin protein in the control, MAP and SAP groups. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05. MAP, mild acute pancreatitis; SAP, severe acute pancreatitis. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL AND THERAPEUTIC MEDICINE 10: 2088-2092, 2015 </p>



<p>Discussion </p>

<p>To date, a number of inflammatory molecules, have been 
identified as potential predictive markers of SAP, including 
interleukin (IL)-1, IL-6 and IL-10 (14,15). However, the 
majority of studies on E-cadherin have focused on the devel-
opment and recurrence of cancer (16), and thus, few studies 
have investigated the role played by E-cadherin in inflam-
mation. To the best of our knowledge, the role of E-cadherin 
in pancreatitis remains controversial. In 2009, Sewpaul et al 
observed that the mean concentration of soluble E-cadherin in 
patients with SAP at &lt;12 h was significantly higher compared 
with that in healthy volunteers and patients with other gastro-
intestinal pathologies (17). However, Pezzilli et al reported 
that the serum levels of E-cadherin were not associated with 
the severity of AP (18). 
In the present study, a rat model of pancreatitis was 
successful established using L-arginine. The SAP and MAP 
groups were designated according to the results of histological 
evaluations and the serum levels of amylase. The levels of 
serum E-cadherin and E-cadherin protein were highest in rats 
in the SAP group, which were evidently increased compared 
with the levels detected in rats in the MAP and control groups. 
These results suggest that the expression of E-cadherin is 
associated with the severity of AP. 
The mechanism underlying E-cadherin overexpres-
sion in rats with SAP remains unclear. It is possible that 
E-cadherin-associated apoptosis may serve a crucial function 
in the pathogenesis of SAP. Takeyama reported that apoptosis 
was involved in the mechanism of infectious complications, 
in addition to organ dysfunction, in SAP (19). It is known that 
apoptosis is regulated by numerous genes, and E-cadherin is 
one among a variety factors that may influence the apoptotic 
process (20). During apoptosis, E-cadherin is efficiently 
cleaved in epithelial cells, and fragments with apparent molec-
ular masses of 24, 29 and 84 kDa are generated following the 
induction of apoptosis by staurosporine or camptothecin (21). 
Another possible cause of the overexpression of E-cadherin 
is that it may contribute to the extravasation of erythrocytes 
and leukocytes in the early stages of SAP (8,21). In the present 
rat experiments, hemorrhage of the pancreas and bloody 
ascites were observed in the SAP group rats. The process 
of extravasation into the parenchyma involves a number of 
molecular interactions between blood cells and endothelial 
cells, including tight adhesions, rolling and diapedesis (22). 
Vonlaufen et al reported that, in cerulein-induced AP, the 
junctional adhesion molecule C is upregulated (23). In addi-
tion, Mayerle et al demonstrated that a variant that was 
15 kDa smaller than E-cadherin, which was detected in the 
early stage of pancreatitis, was the product of E-cadherin 
cleavage at amino acid 394 in the extracellular domain; this 
phenomenon was consistent with E-cadherin cleavage by 
leukocyte-produced elastase (8). Therefore, previous results 
suggested that polymorphonuclear leukocyte-released elastase 
may be involved in the dissociation of cell-cell contacts, the 
extracellular cleavage of E-cadherin and, ultimately, the trans-
migration of leukocytes into the epithelial tissue during the 
initial phase of experimental pancreatitis (8). 
In conclusion, the role of E-cadherin in pancreatitis 
remains unclear. However, the present results indicate that </p>

<p>the expression levels of E-cadherin in SAP rats were higher 
compared with those in MAP rats. Therefore, E-cadherin may 
be associated with the severity of AP. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The present study was supported by grants from the National 
Natural Science Foundation of China (nos. 30901422 
and 51271117). </p>



</text></tei>