<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4189227" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: Late gadolinium enhancement (LGE) on </p>

<p>cardiac MRI (CMR) has been described as an 
independent predictive factor of cardiovascular events 
among patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 
(HCM). LGE and Q waves are considered as myocardial 
scar markers but their relation in the context of HCM is 
poorly established and has to be more supported. The 
objective of the study was to compare ECG findings in 
the presence or absence of LGE. </p>

<p>Methods: 42 patients with HCM confirmed by CMR </p>

<p>were included in the study. ECG abnormalities 
including abnormal Q waves and five ECG scores of left 
ventricular hypertrophy were assessed and compared 
according to LGE presence and its extension. Some 
CMR features, such as septal to posterior wall 
thickness ratio, were also studied according to the 
presence of LGE and the presence of abnormal Q 
waves. </p>

<p>Results: Abnormal Q waves were more prevalent in </p>

<p>the LGE (+) group (60% vs 12%; p=0.002), but there 
was no correlation between location of Q waves on 
ECG and territory of LGE on CMR. Among patients 
with LGE, quantitative analysis of LGE was not different 
in the presence or absence of Q waves. In contrast to 
the LGE mass, septal to posterior wall thickness was 
higher in patients with abnormal Q waves (2.3±0.7 vs 
1.6±0.5; p=0.012). </p>

<p>Conclusions: Although abnormal Q waves were more </p>

<p>prevalent in the presence of LGE, no correlation was 
found with the LGE location and extent. These data 
suggest that abnormal electrical activation of the 
hypertrophied ventricular septum represented by a high 
septal to posterior wall thickness ratio seems to be an 
important mechanism of abnormal Q waves in HCM. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>HCM 
is 
a </p>

<p>heterogeneous disease with a diverse ana-
tomical and clinical presentation and 
course. 1 3-5 Several risk markers for ven-
tricular arrhythmia and SCD have been 
described and applied to manage the 
primary prevention of SCD in clinical prac-
tice with the use of implantable cardioverter-
defibrillators therapy. 
Cardiac MRI (CMR) may be considered as 
the gold-standard technique to assess left 
ventricular (LV) volume and mass 4 6 and 
consequently for the diagnosis of the differ-
ent phenotypic patterns of HCM. 3 5 7 8 CMR </p>

<p>KEY MESSAGES </p>

<p>What is already known about the subject? </p>

<p>▸ Relation between Q waves on electrocardiogram 
and late gadolinium enhancement on MRI 
reflecting myocardial fibrosis has been demon-
strated by some studies. </p>

<p>What does this study add? </p>

<p>▸ Our study described a higher prevalence of Q 
waves in patient with myocardial late gadolinium 
enhancement on MRI but without correlation 
concerning extent and location of late gadolin-
ium enhancement (LGE) and Q waves. We sug-
gested that Q waves are mainly explained by 
abnormal electrical activation due to asymmet-
rical hypertrophy. </p>

<p>How might this impact on clinical practice? </p>

<p>▸ LGE on MRI is associated with worse prognosis 
in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM). but 
absence of strong correlation with Q waves 
should not allow us considering Q waves as sur-
rogate endpoint to predict LGE. MRI has to be 
performed to precise extent and location of LGE 
in HCM. Secondly, pathologic Q waves on ECG 
could suggest an asymmetrical hypertrophy and 
could lead to further exploration in asymptom-
atic patient in order to screen HCM. </p>

<p>Grall S, Biere L, Clerfond G, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000101 </p>



<p>Heart failure and cardiomyopathies </p>

<p>also contributes to the detection of myocardial fibrosis 
by late gadolinium enhancement (LGE) imaging. 9 10 
LGE has a high prevalence in HCM that may vary from 
57% to 79%, 11 12 and its predictive role for cardiovascu-
lar death and SCD has been widely suggested. 6 10 13 
Recently, a meta-analysis including four studies and 1063 
patients described extensive LGE as a significant predict-
ive tool for adverse cardiovascular events in HCM. 2 5 6 
ECG is abnormal in 75-95% of patients with HCM 
and is useful for the screening of HCM. 1 The patterns 
of ECG abnormalities are large and their mechanisms 
largely studied with poor correlation to morphology and 
severity of hypertrophy. 1 14 15 Pathologic Q wave in HCM 
is one of the most studied ECG findings with different 
pathophysiology described. 16 17 In the era of CMR, some 
studies suggested an association between abnormal Q 
wave and LGE. 14 18 19 However, few studies compared 
ECG findings to the mere presence of LGE. 
The main aim of our study was to compare ECG 
characteristics including abnormal Q waves to the pres-
ence of LGE assessed by CMR and to identify ECG para-
meters that might be predictors of LGE. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Study population 
Fifty consecutive patients with HCM referred to a univer-
sity hospital for a CMR assessment between February 
2008 and May 2012 were studied retrospectively. 
Diagnosis of LV hypertrophy (LVH) was made by two-
dimensional echocardiography and confirmed by CMR 
analysis. Morphological diagnosis of HCM was based on 
the association of unexplained LVH (maximal wall thick-
ness ≥15 mm in sporadic adult patients or ≥13 mm in 
adult relatives of patients with confirmed HCM) with a 
non-dilated left ventricle in the absence of another 
cardiac or systemic disease capable of producing the </p>

<p>magnitude of hypertrophy observed. 1 2 Forty-two 
patients comprised the final study group. Patients with 
LV non-compaction (n=2), 20 severe hypertension (n=2), 
previous myocardial infarction (n=2) and cardiac amyl-
oidosis (n=2) were excluded from the analysis (see 
figure 1). Clinical characteristics were collected through 
data extraction from medical records. </p>

<p>ECG procedure and criteria 
A standard 12-lead ECG was obtained in all patients in 
the supine position during quiet respiration. Cardiac 
rhythm, PR interval (upper normal limit was 200 ms), 14 
QRS duration, QRS axis and QT interval duration cor-
rected for cardiac frequency (upper normal limits were 
440 ms for men and 460 ms for women) 14 were col-
lected. Repolarisation abnormalities were defined as ST 
depression ≥0.1 mV at 0.08 s from J point, asymmetrical 
T wave inversion ≥0.1 mV deep in two or more leads 
except aVR, ST elevation ≥0.2 mV. 15 21 An abnormal Q 
wave was determined as described by Konno et al 22 by a 
Q wave &gt;0.3 mV in depth and/or &gt;0.04 s in duration in 
at least two leads except aVR. 19 22 
We assessed LVH with the Romhilt-Estes score (≥4 for a 
probable LVH, ≥5 for a definite LVH), 23 24 the Sokolow-
Lyon voltage score (positive for a score ≥3.5 mV), 23 25 the 
Sokolow-Lyon product (positive for a score ≥371 mV/ 
ms), 26 the Cornell voltage score (≥2.8 mV for men and 
≥2 mV for women) 27 28 and the Cornell product 
(≥244 mV/ms). </p>

<p>CMR protocol 
CMR was performed with a 1.5-T imager (Avanto, 
Siemens, Erlangen, Germany) by using an eight-element 
phased-array cardiac receiver coil. Localisation was per-
formed using breath-hold real-time and steady-state free 
precession images of true anatomical axes of the heart. 
Functional parameters were determined with cine 
imaging using a segmented steady-state free precession 
pulse sequence in multiple short-axis and four-chamber 
views covering the entire left ventricle. Typical in-plane reso-
lution was 1.6×1.9 mm, with a section thickness of 7.0 mm 
(repetition time/echo time: 2.6 ms/1.3 ms; flip angle: 80°; 
matrix: 256×208; temporal resolution: 35-45 ms). 
LGE was performed 12-15 min after gadolinium-based 
contrast agent administration (cumulative dose, 
0.2 mmol/kg of body weight) with a two-dimensional 
segmented inversion recovery gradient-echo pulse 
sequence. Typical in-plane resolution was 1.68×1.68 mm; 
section thickness was 7.0 mm (TE: 4.66 ms; flip angle: 
30°; imaging was triggered to every other heartbeat; 
matrix: 256×208). The inversion time was individually 
adjusted to null normal myocardium. </p>

<p>Image analysis 
All images were analysed at the central core laboratory 
by two investigators blinded to all patient data and ECG 
findings. Commercial software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Qmass MR</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6.2.1</rs>; 
Leiden, The Netherlands) was used for the analysis. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart for retrospective analysis in order to 
compare CMR and ECG parameters in HCM. CMR, cardiac 
MRI; HCM, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy; LV, left ventricular. </p>



<p>Grall S, Biere L, Clerfond G, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000101 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>Endocardial and epicardial borders were outlined manu-
ally on all end-diastolic and end-systolic short-axis cine 
slices. LV end-systolic and end-diastolic volumes, LV ejec-
tion fraction (EF) and LV mass were then calculated in a 
standard fashion. The LV maximal wall thickness was 
automatically measured by the software. 
Short-axis slices were divided into four equal parts: 
septal, anterior, lateral and inferior. The ratio of septal 
to posterior wall thickness was calculated. 19 
As described previously, 3 the pattern of HCM was defined 
according to the number of hypertrophied segments in 
focal HCM (1-2 hypertrophic segments), moderate HCM 
(3-7 segments) and diffuse HCM (≥8 segments). Then a 
second classification 4 was determined according to the LV 
mass index (LVMI): normal LVMI (men &lt;81 g/m 2 , women 
&lt;62 g/m 2 ), mildly increased LVMI (men 81-91 g/m 2 , 
women 62-69 g/m 2 ), markedly increased LVMI (men 
&gt;91 g/m 2 , women &gt;69 g/m 2 ). Four-chamber views were 
used to assess the presence of apical hypertrophy. 
LGE was considered to be present (LGE (+) vs LGE 
(−) groups) when the signal of any area of the myocar-
dium was highly hyperintense in artefact-free images. 
Semiautomatic quantification of the LGE mass was 
made using the 'full width half maximum' (FWHM) 
method. 29 The extent of LGE was quantified as a per-
centage of the LV mass. 10 29 30 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Continuous variables were presented as mean±SD. 
Categorical variables were given as a number and </p>

<p>percentage. Between-group differences were assessed 
using the Pearson χ 2 test or Fisher's exact test (for sub-
groups containing ≤5 observations) for categorical data 
and t test for continuous data. Statistical significance was 
defined as p&lt;0.05 for all tests. Statistical analysis was per-
formed by using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">V.15</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS, Inc</rs>, Chicago, Illinois, 
USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Clinical characteristics 
Forty-two patients were 47±16 years of age, of which 
28.5% (n=12) were female (table 1). Family history of 
HCM and sudden death were, respectively, 31% (n=13) 
and 15% (n=6), without any difference between the two 
groups. Seventy-four per cent (n=31) of patients 
received medical therapy most often by β-blockers 
(71.8%; n=30) and only one took a calcium antagonist. </p>

<p>ECG characteristics 
Sinus rhythm was encountered in 93% of patients (table 2). 
Repolarisation was normal in 14% of cases (n=6); the most 
frequent repolarisation abnormalities were ST segment 
depression in 24 patients (55%) and negative T wave in 32 
patients (76%). There was no left bundle branch block. </p>

<p>CMR findings 
The mean end-diastolic maximal wall thickness was 
19.16±3.8 mm, ranging from 13.2 to 27.3 mm (table 3). 
LGE was found in 25 patients (59.5%). History of </p>

<p>Table 1 Clinical characteristics </p>

<p>All patients (n=42) LGE (−) (n=17; 40.5%) LGE (+) (n=25; 59.5%) p Value </p>

<p>Age at CMR 
47.57±16 
50.29±16.58 
45.73±15.68 
NS 
Female 
12 (28.5) 
5 (29.4) 
7 (28) 
NS 
Hypertension 
15 (35.7) 
9 (52.9) 
6 (24) 
0.055 
Family history of HCM 
13 (30.9) 
4 (23.5) 
9 (36) 
NS 
Family history of sudden death 
6 (15) 
2 (11.7) 
4 (16) 
NS 
Atrial fibrillation history 
10 (23.8) 
4 (23.5) 
6 (24) 
NS 
Chest pain 
11 (26.2) 
8 (47) 
3 (12) 
0.029 
Syncope 
6 (14.3) 
1 (5.8) 
5 (20) 
NS 
Heart failure 
7 (16.7) 
2 (11.7) 
5 (20) 
NS 
NYHA class 
NS 
1 
30 (71.4) 
12 (70.5) 
18 (72) 
2 
10 (23.8) 
4 (23.5) 
6 (24) 
3 
2 (4.8) 
1 (5.8) 
1 (4) 
Mean NYHA class 
1.33±0.57 
1.35±0.58 
1.32±0.55 
NS 
β-blockers 
30 (71.4) 
12 (70.5) 
18 (72) 
NS 
Calcium antagonist 
1 (2.4) 
0 (0) 
1 (4) 
NS 
Echocardiography 
NS 
Ejection fraction 
65±9 
63±9 
66±9 
NS 
Maximum wall thickness (mm) 
18±3 
17±3 
18±4 
NS 
Wall thickness &gt;30 mm 
1 (2.4) 
0 (0) 
1 (4) 
NS 
Rest LVOTO &gt;30 mm Hg 
1 (2.4) 
1 (5.8) 
0 (0) 
NS 
Non-sustained VT on 24H-Holter ECG 9 (21.4) 
3 (17.6) 
6 (24) 
NS 
Abnormal BP response to exercise 
4 (9.5) 
1 (5.8) 
3 (2) 
NS </p>

<p>Data are presented as the mean value±SD or number (%) of subjects. 
BP, blood pressure; CMR, cardiac MRI; HCM, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy; LGE, late gadolinium enhancement; LVOTO, left ventricular 
outflow tract obstruction; NS, not significant; NYHA, New York Heart Association. </p>

<p>Grall S, Biere L, Clerfond G, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000101 </p>



<p>Heart failure and cardiomyopathies </p>

<p>hypertension was present in 35% of patients with a 
trend towards higher rates in patients without LGE 
(52.9% vs 24%; p=0.056; table 1). Notably, patients with 
LGE (−) patients presented a higher prevalence of 
chest pain (47%; n=8) compared to the LGE (+) group 
(12%; n=3; p=0.015; table 1). 
The mean left ventricular mass (LVM) was 141.2±52g 
in all population without difference between two groups. 
Similarly, there was no difference concerning LVEF and 
LV volumes. The ratio of septal to posterior wall </p>

<p>thickness was significantly higher in patients with LGE 
than in those without. No difference was found between 
LGE (+) and LGE (−) in the HCM pattern and mass dis-
tribution. None of the patients had apical hypertrophy 
on four-chamber views. 
The mean wall thickness of LGE (+) segments was 
18.2±3.0 mm and each and every LGE (+) segment 
showed hypertrophy. The LGE extent ranged from 1.3 
to 35 g (mean 12±10 g), corresponding to 1-29% (mean 
9±8%) of the entire myocardium. </p>

<p>Table 2 ECG characteristics </p>

<p>All patients (n=42) </p>

<p>LGE (−) 
(n=17; 40.5%) </p>

<p>LGE (+) 
(n=25; 59.5%) 
p Value </p>

<p>Sinus rhythm 
39 (93) 
16 (94) 
23 (92) 
NS 
Atrial fibrillation 
3 (7) 
1 (6) 
2 (8) 
NS 
QRS duration 
102.14±18.4 
101.06±19.6 
102.88±17.9 
NS 
Normal repolarisation 
6 (14) 
4 (23) 
2 (8) 
NS 
ST elevation 
11 (26) 
6 (35) 
5 (20) 
NS 
ST depression 
23 (23) 
10 (59) 
13 (52) 
NS 
Negative T wave 
32 (76) 
12 (71) 
20 (80) 
NS 
Abnormal Q wave 
17 (40) 
2 (12) 
15 (60) 
0.003 
Abnormal Q wave in V1-V2 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
NA 
Abnormal Q wave in D1-aVL 
9 (21) 
0 (0) 
9 (36) 
0.006 
Abnormal Q wave in V3-V4 
3 (7) 
0 (0) 
3 (12) 
NS 
Abnormal Q wave in V5-V6 
5 (12) 
0 (0) 
5 (20) 
0.07 
Abnormal Q wave in DII-DIII-aVF 
6 (14) 
2 (0) 
4 (16) 
NS 
Sokolow ≥3.5 mV 
12 (29) 
6 (35) 
6 (24) 
NS 
Cornell ≥2 mV for women, ≥2.8 mV for men 
14 (33) 
10 (59) 
4 (16) 
0.007 
Romhilt-Estes score 
4.5±3 
5±3.45 
4±2.66 
NS 
Sokolow product (mV/ms) 
243.1±115.3 
258.1±112.3 
233.5±118.5 
NS 
Cornell product (mV/ms) 
233.3±103.1 
251.0±109.9 
221.4±98.2 
NS </p>

<p>Data are presented as the mean value±SD or number (%) of subjects. 
LGE, late gadolinium enhancement; NA, not available; NS, not significant. </p>

<p>Table 3 CMR findings </p>

<p>All patients (n=42) 
LGE (−) (n=17; 40.5%) 
LGE (+) (n=25; 59.5%) 
p Value </p>

<p>LVEF (%) 
62±9 
64±12 
61±7 
NS 
LVEDV index (mL/m 2 ) 
80±18 
85±17 
77±18 
NS 
LVESV index (mL/m 2 ) 
31±12 
33±17 
30±8 
NS 
LVM (g) 
141±52 
143±60 
140±46 
NS 
LVMI (g/m 2 ) 
73±25 
75±30 
72±22 
NS 
Maximum wall thickness (mm) 
19±4 
18±3 
20±4 
0.074 
LGE mass (g) 
12±10 
0±0 
12±10 
NA 
LGE mass/LVM (%) 
9±8 
0±0 
9±8 
NA 
Septal WT/posterior WT ratio 
1.8±0.6 
1.5±0.4 
2.0±0.7 
0.01 
HCM pattern 
NS 
Focal HCM 
12 (28.6) 
6 (35) 
6 (24) 
Moderate HCM 
19 (45.2) 
7 (41.1) 
12 (48) 
Diffuse HCM 
11 (26.2) 
4 (23.5) 
7 (28) 
LVMI class 
NS 
Normal 
29 (69) 
11 (64.7) 
18 (72) 
Mildly increased 
2 (4.7) 
2 (11.7) 
0 (0) 
Markedly increased 
11 (26.2) 
4 (23.5) 
7 (28) </p>

<p>Data are presented as the mean value±SD or number (%) of subjects. 
CMR, cardiac MRI; HCM, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy; LGE, late gadolinium enhancement; LVEDV, LV, end-diastolic volume; LVEF, left 
ventricular ejection fraction; LVESV, LV end-systolic volume; LVM, Left ventricle mass; LVMI, left ventricular mass index; NA, not available; 
WT, wall thickness. </p>



<p>Grall S, Biere L, Clerfond G, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000101 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>Relationships between ECG and LGE 
ECG parameters including conduction disturbances, 
QRS axis, repolarisation abnormalities and LV hyper-
trophy scores did not show any difference in patients 
with or without LGE (table 2). 
Patients with LGE showed a greater prevalence of 
abnormal Q waves (60%; n=15 vs 12%; n=2) than those 
without ( p=0.002; table 2). 
However, on segmental analysis, there was no relation 
between Q waves' location on ECG and LGE territory </p>

<p>(see figure 2). Remarkably, the preferential location of 
Q waves was DI-aVL, whereas only one patient presented 
with LGE on the lateral wall (figure 2). </p>

<p>Q waves and quantitative analysis of LGE 
Among patients with LGE (n=25; table 4), the LGE 
extent was similar in patients with or without abnormal 
Q waves. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Illustration of 
discordance between location of 
Q waves on ECG derivations and 
location of LGE in the 
myocardium on CMR. 
(A) Incidence of LGE within cited 
location among all patients 
(n=42). LGE was predominantly 
on the anterior, septal and inferior 
territory. (B) Incidence of Q waves 
in the cited derivations among all 
patients. Q waves were more 
likely in the derivations 
corresponding to the lateral 
territory. (C) Comparison of septal 
to posterior WT ratio according to 
the presence (Q+) or absence (Q 
−) of Abnormal Q waves in their 
different derivations. * p&lt;0.05. 
CMR, cardiac MRI; HCM, 
hypertrophic cardiomyopathy; 
LGE, late gadolinium 
enhancement; WT, wall 
thickness. </p>

<p>Table 4 Abnormal Q waves and quantitative analysis of LGE </p>

<p>No abnormal Q wave (n=10; 40%) 
Abnormal Q wave (n=15; 60%) 
p Value </p>

<p>LVEF (%) 
62±8 
60±7 
NS 
LVEDV index (mL/m 2 ) 
79±11 
76±22 
NS 
LVESV index (mL/m 2 ) 
30±6 
30±9 
NS 
LVM (g) 
154±56 
130±38 
NS 
LVMI (g/m 2 ) 
78±24 
69±20 
NS 
Maximum wall 
thickness (mm) </p>

<p>20±5 
20±4 
NS </p>

<p>LGE mass (g) 
12±10 
12±10 
NS 
LGE mass/LVM (%) 
7±7 
10±8 
NS 
Septal WT/posterior 
WT ratio </p>

<p>1.6±0.5 
2.2±0.7 
0.012 </p>

<p>Data are presented as the mean value±SD. 
HCM, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy; LVEDV, LV end-diastolic volume; LGE, late gadolinium enhancement; LVEF, left ventricular ejection 
fraction; LVESV, LV end-systolic volume; LVM, Left ventricle mass; LVMI, left ventricular mass index; NS, not significant; WT, wall thickness. </p>

<p>Grall S, Biere L, Clerfond G, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000101 </p>



<p>Heart failure and cardiomyopathies </p>

<p>Relationship between septal to posterior wall thickness 
ratio and abnormal Q waves 
Patients with abnormal Q waves had a significantly higher 
septal to posterior wall thickness ratio (2.2±0.7) compared 
to those without abnormal Q waves (1.6±0.5; p&lt;0.001; table 
4 and figure 2). This difference was also encountered 
among the subgroup of patients with LGE. Patients with 
DI-aVL Q waves also had a higher ratio than those without 
(2.4±0.7 vs 1.6±0.5; p=0.001; figures 2 and 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In the present study, we exhibited that patients with LGE 
on CMR more often had Q waves on ECG but that the 
location of LGE in the myocardium was not correlated 
to the corresponding derivation on ECG. The presence </p>

<p>of abnormal Q waves seems to be better related to 
higher septal to posterior wall thickness than LGE. 
LGE was found in 59.5% of the 42 patients. Recent 
studies considering LGE in HCM showed similar data 
from 55% to 63%. 10 31 As previously described, we 
found a higher prevalence of abnormal Q waves in 
patients with LGE (+). 9 10 31 We found that 60% of 
patients with LGE presented with Q waves on the ECG, 
but the location of Q waves on the ECG was dissimilar to 
those of LGE on CMR in our study. For example, only 
one patient with the DI-VL Q wave exhibited lateral 
LGE. The same result was suggested in the study by 
Dumont et al 18 concerning the predominant location of 
septal LGE in patients with lateral Q waves. In contrast, 
Papavassiliu et al 19 described a good correspondence 
between Q waves and LGE though defining only three 
main territories (anterior, inferior and lateral) </p>

<p>Figure 3 Examples of association between CMR features and abnormal Q waves. (A) HCM with high septal to posterior WT 
ratio, LGE on right to left ventricular junctions, Q waves in DI-VL discordance between location of Q waves and LGE. (B) Q 
waves in inferior leads associated with asymmetrical HCM but no LGE. (C) Diffuse HCM with lower septal to posterior WT ratio, 
LGE in lateral wall but no Q waves. CMR, cardiac MRI; HCM, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy; LGE, late gadolinium enhancement; 
WT, wall thickness. </p>



<p>Grall S, Biere L, Clerfond G, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000101 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>corresponding to the coronary arteries 32 -as a conse-
quence, the interventricular septum was not individua-
lised, although it is a common location of hypertrophy 
and LGE. 18 33 Moreover, owing to the high incidence of 
LGE in the superior and inferior right ventricular inser-
tion points, the American Heart Association 17-segment 
model was not used for LGE analysis. 18 32 34 
Among patients with LGE, those with abnormal Q 
waves did not present a higher extent of LGE as assessed 
by a semiautomatic quantitative analysis technique. This 
result is also different from the study by Papavassiliu 
et al, because the quantitative analysis was performed by 
the visual assessment of the transmural nature of LGE 
and not the absolute LGE extent. To the best of our 
knowledge, there is no other study on pathologic Q 
waves and quantitative LGE evaluation. FWHM is a semi-
automatic technique to assess LGE mass. Studies demon-
strated that FWHM was well correlated with ex-vivo 
quantification of fibrosis and adverse outcome. 10 30 In 
study by Spiewak et al 29 there was no difference in mass 
of LGE assessment with FWHM technique and 6-SD (6-
standard deviations) threshold technique when com-
pared to visual planimetry. In this study, FWHM tech-
nique had the best reproducibility. 
The pathophysiology of abnormal Q waves in HCM is 
debated and two main hypotheses have been 
described. 35 Q waves in HCM were first correlated with 
presence of myocardial fibrosis in old necropsy studies. 36 
Later, Maron et al 37 explained Q waves by the loss of 
local electrical forces secondary to transmural scar. This 
was again supported in a previous CMR study, but a key 
role was also given to the distribution of hypertrophy 
and particularly to the increase of the septal to posterior 
wall thickness ratio. 19 Indeed, abnormal electrical activa-
tion of the markedly hypertrophied septum compared 
to normal posterior wall thickness is another explan-
ation to abnormal Q waves considering several echocar-
diographic, 17 38 ECG 39 and electrophysiological 
studies. 16 Consistent with this hypothesis, two studies 
exhibited a disappearance of abnormal Q waves after 
septal myectomy. 40 41 In our study, not only was the 
septal to posterior wall thickness ratio most common in 
patients with Q waves but also it presented with higher 
values, even among patients with LGE. This difference 
was present in segmental analysis considering DI-aVL Q 
waves, the most frequent Q wave location in our study. 
Thus, the hypertrophy pattern seems to be predominant 
in the pathophysiology of Q waves considering the lack 
of correlation of Q waves with the LGE location and its 
quantitative analysis. 19 
The results of this study should be interpreted in the 
light of certain limitations. First, the retrospective nature 
of the study may have introduced selection biases. The 
number of patients is limited and in one single centre 
compared to some prospective or retrospective studies 
on HCM, 3 33 and hypertrophy was mildly severe consid-
ering a great number of focal and intermediate patterns 
as described by Maron et al and few massive septal </p>

<p>hypertrophy (≥30 mm) and few LV outflow tract obstruc-
tions ≥30 mm Hg. This limit could have biased the 
characteristics of these patients with HCM. 
In addition, diffuse fibrosis was exclusively analysed by 
LGE and CMR studies including T1 mapping sequences 
might be of interest to investigate HCM. 
Finally, genetic testing was not available for our 
patients. However, some ECG differences and prognosis 
impact has been described in line with genetics. 42 43 
Moreover, the monocentric nature of our work may be 
responsible for the selection of some specific genetic 
mutations predominantly encountered in our region. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
In HCM, it seems that the presence and extent of LGE 
cannot be presumed by any ECG parameter. Abnormal 
Q waves on the ECG may be partly attributable to the 
septal to posterior wall thickness ratio rather than myo-
cardial fibrosis. </p>

<p>Contributors SG, GC and VM performed CMR analysis. SG and LB 
contributed to data management. LB, FP, AF and SW were involved in 
reviewing. </p>

<p>Funding This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in 
the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Comité d'éthique CHU Angers. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>





<p>Heart failure and cardiomyopathies </p>





<p>Grall S, Biere L, Clerfond G, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000101. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000101 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

</text></tei>