<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4968915" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>G laucoma is a leading cause of blindness. 1,2 Due to its </p>

<p>insidious nature, an objective method to detect early 
glaucoma and glaucoma progression could help prevent vision 
loss and blindness. Optical coherence tomography (OCT) 
provides accurate and precise anatomic measurements of the 
optic nerve and retinal layers. Yet, its diagnostic sensitivities for 
detecting perimetric glaucoma (PG) are only 57% to 83% 3-7 at a 
fixed specificity of 95% using the nerve fiber layer (NFL). In the 
Advanced Imaging for Glaucoma (AIG) study, using the 
combination of NFL and ganglion cell complex and disc 
variables, at a 95% specificity set point, the sensitivity to detect 
PG was 100% for middle to late glaucoma stages (stages 3-5 on 
Glaucoma Staging System 2). 8 However, the sensitivity for early 
(stages 0-2) glaucoma was only 67%, still not sufficient for 
reliable early detection of glaucoma. 9 It has been estimated that 
approximately half of the glaucoma patients in the United 
States do not know that they have the disease. 10 To tackle this 
public health problem, further improvement in objective 
diagnostic technology is needed. 
Due to the high contrast between the retinal internal limiting 
membrane (ILM) and the overlying clear vitreous, the ILM can be 
delineated with high transverse resolution. This provides an 
excellent basis for detecting small scale, focal damage to the NFL. 
Qualitatively, when studying the circumferential profile of the 
ILM around the optic nerve head, we have noted two types of </p>

<p>change in glaucomatous eyes (Fig. 1). First, there are focal 
depressions secondary to loss of nerve fiber bundles. Second, 
there are increased protrusions of retinal vessels above the plane 
of the NFL, presumably from loss of the NFL, which allows 
vessels to stand out in greater relief above the retinal plane. 
These focal depressions and vessel elevations will increase the 
variations in height of the ILM profile. This novel parameter of 
focal NFL loss may be a sensitive indicator in early glaucoma, 
when total or average NFL loss is incomplete and variable. 
We developed a spatial frequency analysis method to 
measure the height variation in the ILM profile, and tested its 
diagnostic power for detecting glaucoma. </p>

<p>same eligibility and endpoint protocol as the AIG study, but 
used an advanced swept-source OCT prototype system 
instead of commercially available OCT instruments. The 
inclusion and exclusion criteria of the AIG study have been 
reported previously. 4 Briefly, normal control participants met 
the following criteria in both eyes: IOP of less than 21 mm Hg 
in both eyes, and a normal Humphrey visual field (HVF) on 
achromatic standard automated perimetry by Swedish Inter-
active Threshold Algorithm 24-2 testing (HFA II; Carl Zeiss 
Meditec, Inc., Dublin, CA, USA) with mean deviation (MD), 
Glaucoma Hemifield Test (GHT), and pattern standard 
deviation (PSD) within normal limits. In addition, normal 
subjects had a normal-appearing optic nerve head (ONH) and 
NFL on ophthalmoscopic examination, and an open angle by 
gonioscopy. Glaucoma participants were required to have a 
glaucomatous ONH rim or NFL thinning on ophthalmoscopic 
examination. Glaucomatous eyes were classified in the PG 
subgroup if they have visual field (VF) PSD or GHT outside 
normal limits (P &lt; 0.05 and P &lt; 1%, respectively) in a 
consistent pattern on two qualifying VF exams. Otherwise, 
they were classified as preperimetric glaucoma (PPG). 
Exclusion criteria for all groups included visual acuity less 
than 20/40, age &lt;40 or &gt;79 years at enrollment, any ocular 
surgery other than uncomplicated cataract extraction, other 
diseases that might cause VF or ONH abnormality, and factors 
that might preclude the participant from performing study 
procedures or completing the study. </p>

<p>OCT and Scanning </p>

<p>A prototype high speed swept-source Fourier-domain OCT 
system was used in this study. 10 The device operated at an axial </p>

<p>scan speed of 100 kHz using a swept-source cavity laser 
operating at 1050 nm with a tuning range of 100 nm. A 
resolution of 5.3 lm axially and 18 lm laterally at an imaging 
depth of 2.9 mm in tissue was achieved. The ocular light 
power exposure was 1.9 mW, within the American National 
Standards Institute (ANSI) safety limit. 11 
Participants were scanned using a high density 8 3 8 mm 
raster scan pattern, centered at the ONH. In the fast transverse 
scan direction, the B-scan consisted of 640 A-scans. The slow 
transverse scan direction included 640 B-scans. The time to 
acquire each 3D volumetric scan was 4.3 seconds. In the scan 
protocol, one eye of each participant was scanned with 4 scans 
consisting of 2 horizontal and 2 vertical scans. An orthogonal 
registration algorithm was applied to register and merge all 4 
scans to reduce eye motion. 12 
Concentric, cylindrical, cross-sectional OCT images of 
varying radii were resampled from the volume scan (Fig. 2) 
and upsampled to 1024 transverse points using interpolation. 
We selected rings with radii of 1.5, 1.7, 2, 2.5, 3, and 3.5 mm 
for analysis. The disc center was decided manually by one of us 
(LL) by matching the disc boundary with an ellipse on the en 
face view (Fig. 2A). </p>

<p>ILM Detection </p>

<p>The ILM was detected as the most inner boundary of retina in 
the cylindrical cross-section images. An automated algorithm 
was developed to follow the vessel bumps and avoid artifacts, 
such as points of vitreous macular adhesion. The ILM elevation 
profile (contour) was extracted for each circle (Fig. 2B). One of 
us (LL) inspected the cross-sectional images with ILM contour </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Superior quadrants of cylindrical OCT cross sections of the peripapillary retina at 3 mm radius. (A) Normal. (B) Glaucoma. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. (A) En face view (average projection of log reflectance intensity) of the 8 3 8 mm volumetric ''cube'' scan of the ONH region in a 
glaucomatous eye. The 3-mm radius circle centered on the ONH is outlined in blue. (B) The 3-mm radius cylindrical cross section is resampled from 
the cube scan. The ILM contour (white dashed line) is measured from this circular cross section. (C) En face OCT showing resampling circles at 
radii of 1.5, 1.7, 2.0, 2.5, 3.0, and 3.5 mm. </p>

<p>Retinal Surface Contour Variability 
IOVS j Special Issue j Vol. 57 j No. 9 j OCT439 </p>

<p>overlay and performed manual correction of the contour if 
necessary. </p>

<p>Retinal Surface Contour Variability (RSCV) </p>

<p>The ILM elevation profile was transformed to spatial frequency 
domain using the fast Fourier transform (Fig. 3A). The spatial 
frequency components at lowest frequencies were removed 
because they simply relate to the average axial position and the 
tilt of the OCT scan beam relative to the ONH plane. The 
highest frequency components also were nondiagnostic 
because of high noise and little anatomic information. The 
middle frequency band that optimized the detection of retinal 
vessel relief and NFL bundle defects was determined empiri-
cally based on the difference between the average normal and 
glaucoma ILM spatial frequency spectrum (Fig. 3B). The RSCV 
is defined as the average log value within a middle spatial 
frequency band of the Fourier transform to the elevation 
profile of the inner retinal surface. The spatial frequency band 
was optimized to distinguish glaucoma from normal. These 
optimized bands were determined separately for each cylin-
drical section radius (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Nerve Fiber Layer Thickness (NFLT) </p>

<p>On the cylindrical cross-sectional OCT image with radius of 1.7 
mm, the lower NFL boundary also was detected using a 
method described previously. 13 The NFLT profile was defined 
as the distance between ILM and lower NFL boundary. The 
NFLT parameter was averaged along the profile. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The Wilcoxon rank sum test was performed to determine 
statistical significance between the study groups. The area 
under receiver operating characteristic curve (AROC) was 
calculated for the diagnostic accuracy. Pearson correlation was 
used to determine correlations between RSCV, axial length, 
NFLT, and visual field test MD. A coefficient of variance (CV) 
was applied to evaluate reproducibility. Two reproducibility 
tests were performed. The first one compares RSCV value at R 
¼ 2.8 mm and R ¼ 3.0 mm. The second test compares results 
graded independently by two of the authors (OT and LL). All 
image processes and statistical analyses were done using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Matlab</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Mathworks</rs>, Natick, MA, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Of 17 participants in the glaucoma group (8 in the PG and 9 in 
the PPG subgroups), 15 had early VF damage (MD &gt; À6 dB) </p>

<p>and 2 had more severe VF damage. We enrolled 25 participants 
in the normal control group, but due to their younger average 
age, only the 17 oldest control participants were used in the 
present analysis. The age matching was not exact, as the 
control participants still averaged 9 years younger (Table 1). 
There were more females in the control group (Table 1). As 
expected, the glaucoma group had significantly worse VF MD 
and thinner NFL in the overall area, superior and inferior 
quadrants. The image quality of the normal group is 
significantly higher than that of the glaucoma group based on 
signal strength index. 
The spatial frequency transforms of the ILM profile were 
averaged for the normal and glaucoma groups (Fig. 3). 
Optimized bands were detected at frequency components 
where the glaucoma group was significantly larger than the 
normal group (Fig. 4). We averaged RSCVs in the optimized 
bands for each circle and the RSCV distribution for normal and 
glaucoma groups are illustrated in Figure 5. The RSCV was 
significantly higher at all sampling radii in the glaucoma group 
compared to the normal control group (Table 2). 
The diagnostic accuracy of NFL and RSCV were assessed 
using AROC values at each sampling radius (Table 3). The 
diagnostic accuracy of RSCV improved with larger radii and the 
highest AROC value (0.90) was found at a radius of 3.5 mm. 
This was higher than that for NFLT parameters, but only 
significantly in the temporal and nasal quadrants (&lt;0.01). We 
examined averages of RSCV over various ranges of radii and 
found that the average over 2.5 to 3.5 mm had the highest 
AROC (0.91). The averaged RSCV then was combined with 
NFL using principal component analysis. The combination had 
marginally higher AROC (0.91) than NFL only (P ¼ 0.08). </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. (A) Spatial frequency spectrum of ILM elevation showing the averages of all glaucoma eyes and all normal eyes derived from the 3.0-mm 
OCT cylindrical sections. (B) shows the difference spectrum (glaucoma À normal) and the optimize frequency band (between dotted lines) used to 
compute the RSCV. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Optimized passbands for RSCV calculation at different radii. </p>

<p>Retinal Surface Contour Variability 
IOVS j Special Issue j Vol. 57 j No. 9 j OCT440 </p>

<p>Venn diagram analysis (Fig. 6) showed that RSCV had higher 
sensitivity for glaucoma diagnosis (53%) than NFLT (29%). It 
also was notable that all abnormal eyes detected by NFLT also 
were detected by RSCV. However, the difference in sensitivity 
was not statistically significant (P ¼ 0.13). Both parameters had 
100% specificity (Fig. 6). 
The correlations between averaged RSCV and NFLT, or 
between averaged RSCV and VF MD, were estimated for 
glaucomatous participants. Significant correlations were found 
between RSCV and NFL (r ¼À0.54, P ¼ 0.03) but not MD (R ¼ 
À0.32, P ¼ 0.21). A significant correlation also was found 
between NFL and MD (r ¼ 0.68, P ¼ 0.002). We also evaluated 
the correlation between RSCV and NFL for normal participants, 
which was not significant (r ¼ À0.10, P ¼ 0.70). 
We tested whether the RSCV was sensitive to transverse 
magnification changes (i.e., axial eye length variation) by 
comparing the values evaluated at the sampling radii of R ¼ 2.8 
and 3 mm. No significant difference was found between the 
two radii in either the glaucoma or normal group (P &gt; 0.26). 
The CV was 1.4% for normal eyes and 1.3% for glaucoma eyes. 
We also tested the between-grader (OT and LL) reproducibility 
of RSCV because the ONH boundary and center were defined 
manually. The reproducibility (CV) was 1.6% for normal eyes 
and 1.1% for glaucoma eyes. 
We tested the correlation between axial length and RSCV. 
We did not find a significant correlation between axial length 
and RSCV parameter (R ¼ 3.5 mm) for the normal (r ¼ 0.06, P ¼ 
0.83) and glaucoma (r ¼ 0.42, P ¼ 0.09) groups. We also did not 
find a significant correlation between axial length and RSCV 
parameters at any radius for the normal group (P &gt; 0.32). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this pilot study, we reported, to our knowledge, the first use 
of spatial frequency analysis to detect small scale retinal surface 
contour change in glaucoma. The RSCV, measured in the 
peripapillary area, was significantly larger in glaucoma eyes. 
The diagnostic accuracy of RSCV was at least as good as NFLT, 
although a larger study would be needed to see if there is a 
significant advantage. In early glaucoma, NFLT has limited 
diagnostic sensitivity, with literature values of 33.3% to 67.4% 
at a fixed specificity of 99%. 3,7,9 This is not surprising as there 
is a relatively wide range of population variation in the average 
NFLT, which has been reported as between 9.0% and 10.0% 
SD. 5,7,14 Because the RSCV measures small scale, focal changes 
that are unlikely to be due to the inborn variation of NFLT, it 
may be able to better detect glaucoma in the earlier stages, 
when NFL damage is small and variable in the location. In this 
study, NFLT was abnormally (99% specificity cutoff) thin in </p>

<p>only 5 of 17 participants in the glaucoma group, while RSCV 
was abnormally elevated in 9 of 17 glaucoma participants. 
While this advantage is not statistically significant, it shows a 
promising trend that deserves further study. 
Because the NFLT and the RSCV measure different aspects 
of NFL damage-global versus focal-their combination may 
enhance diagnostic accuracy. While we previously have 
developed another parameter to measure focal peripapillary 
NFL and macular ganglion cell complex (GCC) thinning called 
focal loss volume (FLV), that algorithm was optimized to detect 
relatively larger areas (500 lm superpixels) of focal dam-
age. 15,16 By contrast, this new RSCV parameter is able to detect 
smaller focal changes. The RSCV spatial frequency analysis 
detects changes in the 2 to 100 radians/mm, which corre-
sponds to spatial features as small as 60 lm (the diameter of a 
small arteriole). 17,18 Thus, we believe all three parameters will 
be synergistic based on the fact they measure glaucoma 
damage on different spatial scales. 
We found that the RSCV appeared to have higher diagnostic 
accuracy in circles with large radii (2.5-3.5 mm) than small 
radii (1.5-2 mm). This could be explained by two observations. 
Firstly, we observed that, in the normal eye, larger retinal 
vessels submerge into the retina further from the disc margin. 
Thus, the inner retinal surface is smoother and RSCV is lower 
further from the disc. This makes it easier to detect even small 
focal changes in the glaucomatous eyes. This observation also 
might be due to the fact that glaucoma damages axon bundles 
nonuniformly within the ONH (laminar pores, and so forth) 
and these bundle losses may be more detectable within the 
NFL where all bundles are more spread out. Another 
assumption is that the thinner NFL away from the disc is 
going to be less likely to mask blood vessels and loss of axon </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Participant Characteristics </p>

<p>Normal 
Glaucoma 
P Value </p>

<p>Eye, n 
17 
17 
N/A 
Age, y 
59 6 8 
6 86 8 
0.11 
Female 
68% 
29% 
0.001 
Axial length, mm 
24.1 6 1.4 
24.1 6 1.2 
0.88 
VF MD, dB 
0.13 6 0.79 
À2.48 6 3.73 
0.002 
NFLT, lm 
Overall 
108.0 6 9.9 
88.6 6 17.1 
0.001 
Nasal quadrant 
88.3 6 13.4 
77.5 6 19.9 
0.07 
Superior quadrant 
127.3 6 12.6 
105.7 6 23.4 
0.002 
Temporal quadrant 
77.6 6 15.4 
75.8 6 13.6 
0.72 
Inferior quadrant 
135.6 6 17.4 
97.4 6 25.8 
&lt;0.001 
Signal strength index 
60 6 9 
5 06 12 
0.01 </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Retinal Surface Contour Variability </p>

<p>Radius, mm 
Normal 
Glaucoma 
Difference </p>

<p>3.5 
1.58 6 0.06 
1.73 6 0.10 
0.15 
3 
1.57 6 0.07 
1.71 6 0.10 
0.14 
2.5 
1.58 6 0.06 
1.72 6 0.13 
0.14 
2 
1.59 6 0.07 
1.70 6 0.12 
0.11 
1.7 
1.64 6 0.08 
1.77 6 0.13 
0.13 
1.5 
1.67 6 0.09 
1.80 6 0.13 
0.13 </p>

<p>Listed values are mean 6 SD of groups; all differences between the 
glaucoma and normal groups are significantly greater than zero (P &lt; 
0.003) by the Wilcoxon rank sum test. </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Diagnostic Accuracy Comparison </p>

<p>Parameter 
Radius, mm AROC 6 SE </p>

<p>P Value 
to Inferior 
NFL Quadrant </p>

<p>NFLT 
Overall 
1.7 
0.84 6 0.07 
0.26 
Nasal quadrant 
1.7 
0.65 6 0.10 
0.01 
Superior quadrant 
1.7 
0.82 6 0.07 
0.29 
Temporal quadrant 
1.7 
0.51 6 0.10 
&lt;0.01 
Inferior quadrant 
1.7 
0.89 6 0.05 
N/A 
RSCV 
3.5 
0.90 6 0.05 
0.87 
3.0 
0.87 6 0.06 
0.73 
2.5 
0.86 6 0.06 
0.69 
2.0 
0.78 6 0.08 
0.19 
1.7 
0.76 6 0.09 
0.14 
1.5 
0.77 6 0.08 
0.16 
3.5-2.5 Average 0.91 6 0.05 
0.76 </p>

<p>Retinal Surface Contour Variability 
IOVS j Special Issue j Vol. 57 j No. 9 j OCT441 </p>

<p>bundles may reveal blood vessels more readily in these regions. 
The second observation is that the population variances were 
tighter with larger radii (Table 2). We suspected this was 
simply due to the larger number of A-scans in sampling circles 
of larger radii. Thus, maximizing the OCT scan density in the 
2.5-to 3.5-mm radius annulus around the optic disc may 
improve RSCV evaluation. 
An additional advantage of RSCV over NFLT is that the RSCV 
value is relatively insensitive to magnification variation or 
decentration relative to the optic disc center. Between the scan 
radii of 2.5 to 3.5 mm, the mean RSCV values varied less than 
2% in the normal and glaucoma groups. Intergrader variation in 
disc boundary identification also affected RSCV by less than 
2%. By comparison, NFLT does vary proportionately with 
magnification (axial eye length). 19-21 Furthermore, NFL quad-
rant thickness averages are known to be exquisitely sensitive to 
decentration of the sampling circle relative to the optic 
disc. 22,23 Therefore, RSCV may be a more robust diagnostic 
parameter that is relatively resistant to the introduction of bias 
due to patients, OCT operators, or graders. 
In previous studies, contour variability was accessed by 
Heidelberg retinal tomography (HRT) but was considerably 
inferior in its ability to diagnose glaucoma or progression 
compared to NFL measured by OCT. 24-26 We believe there are 
two reasons why contour variability by HRT was considerably 
inferior in diagnostic power. First, HRT had lower axial 
resolution comparing to OCT. Thus, it is difficult for HRT to 
catch small changes in the contour variability caused by 
protrusions of retinal vessels. Second, HRT measures the 
contour variability near the disc margin. In our study, we found 
that the contour variability is less sensitive in location near the 
disc edge. 
One of the limitations of this study is the relatively small 
number of participants, especially for advanced glaucoma (VF 
&lt; À6dB). A power calculation shows that our sample size of 17 
normal and 17 glaucoma subjects should be able to detect a 
difference in AROC of 0.67 compared to the AROC of RSCV of 
0.90 with a probability of 0.80 at a significance threshold of P 
&lt; 0.05. Thus, a large study is necessary to validate the RSCV 
parameters. 
Another limitation is that the age and sex are not exactly 
matched. First, our control participants were not sex-matched 
to the glaucoma group. However, RSCV was not significantly </p>

<p>affected by sex in our control group (P ¼ 0.62). Second, the 
glaucoma group also is 9 years older than the normal group. As 
a consequence, the OCT image quality in normal group is 
significantly higher. However, the SSI is good for the normal 
(60 6 9) and glaucoma (50 6 12) groups. The RSCV 
parameters are not sensitive to SSI when the image quality is 
good enough for accurate ILM boundary detection. We also 
tested the correlation between SSI and RSCV but did not find 
any significance for the normal and glaucoma groups (P &gt; 
0.38). Furthermore, RSCV was not correlated with age in the 
normal group (P ¼ 0.43). 
Retinal surface contour variability also may be sensitive to 
focal NFL loss caused by other optic neuropathies, such as 
anterior ischemic optic neuropathy (AION) and optic neuritis. 
Since RSCV is a nonspecific detector of NFL loss on a small 
spatial scale, specific diagnosis of particular conditions would 
require the physician to consider the clinical presentation as 
well as patterns of NFL, GCC, optic disc topography, and VF 
changes. 
In summary, the retinal surface contour variability was 
increased significantly in glaucoma eyes. The diagnostic 
accuracy of RSCV was at least equal to NFLT in early glaucoma. 
Since the RSCV detects small-scale focal damage and the 
average NFLT measures global damage, they provide different </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Distribution of RSCV values for normal (N) and glaucoma (G) groups at sampling radii between 1.5 and 3.5 mm. </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. Venn diagram for glaucoma diagnosis using RSCV and NFLT 
parameters. The threshold for RSCV was set 2.33 SD above the mean of 
the normal group (99 percentile cutoff assuming normal distribution) 
and the threshold of NFL was 2.33 SD below the mean of normal 
group. In the normal group, all eyes were within the cutoff for both 
parameters, indicating 100% specificity. In the glaucoma groups, RSCV 
detected abnormality in nine participants, including the five detected 
by NFL. </p>

<p>Retinal Surface Contour Variability 
IOVS j Special Issue j Vol. 57 j No. 9 j OCT442 </p>

<p>diagnostic information that may be synergistic. A larger study is 
needed to validate the utility of RSCV in glaucoma detection. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH; Bethesda, MD, 
USA) Grants R01 EY023285, R01 EY013516, P30 EY10572 
(Ophthalmology Core Facility), and R01 EY010145, and an 
unrestricted grant from Research to Prevent Blindness. 
Disclosure: O. Tan, Optovue (F, I), P; L. Liu, None; X. Zhang, 
None; J.C. Morrison, None; D. Huang, Optovue (F, I), P </p>



<p>Retinal Surface Contour Variability 
IOVS j Special Issue j Vol. 57 j No. 9 j OCT443 </p>

</text></tei>