<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4592051" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: The prognostic value of lysine-specific demethylase 1 (LSD1) overexpression in 
various cancers has been investigated by many studies with inconsistent results. A meta-analysis 
was performed to assess the association between LSD1 and overall survival (OS) in cancer 
patients. Eligible studies were identified by searching the online databases PubMed and China 
National Knowledge Infrastructure up to February 2015. Hazard ratios (HRs) with 95% confi-
dence intervals (CIs) were calculated to clarify the correlation between LSD1 expression and 
prognosis of different cancers. In total, nine studies with 1,149 cancer patients were included 
for final analysis. The meta-analysis suggested that LSD1 overexpression was associated with 
poor OS in cancer patients (HR =1.80, 95% CI: 1.39-2.34, P=0.000). Subgroup analysis by 
ethnicity, cancer type and HR estimate also showed that high levels of LSD1 were significantly 
correlated with OS. The meta-analysis showed that LSD1 overexpression may be associated 
with a worse prognosis in cancer patients. 
Lysine-specific demethylase 1 (LSD1) was the first characterized histone demethylase, 
which could specifically remove the methyl groups from mono-and dimethylated 
lysine (Lys)4 of histone H3 (H3K4me1/2) and Lys9 of histone H3 (H3K9me1/2). </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>LSD1 is essential for mammalian development and is involved in many biological 
processes, including cell type differentiation, gene activation, and gene repression. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>A recent study indicated that LSD1 might promote cell phase transition (deficiency 
in LSD1 led to partial cell cycle arrest in G 2 /M) and cell proliferation, suggesting that 
its overexpression might promote tumorigenesis. 
3 The expression of LSD1 has been 
associated with tumor recurrence during therapy in various cancers, further implicat-
ing LSD1 as a tumor promoter. </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>Many studies investigated the prognostic value of LSD1 in various cancers. Some 
studies found that the upregulation of LSD1 was associated with worse outcome in 
cancer patients. 
6-11 However, some other studies showed insignificant or opposite 
result. 
12-14 Therefore, the relation between LSD1 expression and patient survival across 
different cancers remains controversial. To overcome the limitations of the single 
study, this meta-analysis was carried out with the aim of evaluating the relationship 
between LSD1 expression and prognosis of cancer patients. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
literature search and selection criteria </p>

<p>We searched PubMed and China National Knowledge Infrastructure up to February 
2015 to identify relevant studies. We used the search terms: "LSD1", "lysine specific </p>

<p>correspondence: Yueyin Pan 
Department of Oncology, The First 
Affiliated Hospital of Anhui Medical 
University, number 218, Ji Xi road, 
hefei 230022, anhui, People's republic 
of china 
Tel +86 551 6292 2987 
email yueyinpan1965@gmail.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
15 September 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2566 </p>

<p>Wu et al </p>

<p>demethylase 1", "tumor", "cancer", "neoplasm", "carcinoma", 
"malignant", "survival", "prognosis", and "prognostic". The 
citation lists associated with the studies were used to identify 
additional eligible studies. The reviews and bibliographies 
were also manually inspected to find related articles. </p>

<p>inclusion and exclusion criteria </p>

<p>The studies were included in our meta-analysis if they met 
the following inclusion criteria: 1) LSD1 expression evalu-
ated in the human tissues; 2) tumors should be confirmed 
by pathological or histological examinations; 3) evaluation 
of the relationship between LSD1 expression and survival; 
4) sufficient information provided to estimate the hazard ratios 
(HRs) with their 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for overall 
survival (OS). The exclusion criteria were as follows: 1) let-
ters, case reports, reviews, and conference abstracts without 
original data; 2) articles from which the relevant data could 
not be extracted. Of the studies which had duplicate data, only 
the most complete study was included in the analysis. </p>

<p>Data extraction </p>

<p>Data were evaluated and extracted independently from the 
eligible studies by two investigators (LXH and JW) under 
the guidelines of a critical review checklist of the Dutch 
Cochrane Centre proposed by Meta-analysis of Observa-
tional Studies in Epidemiology. 
15 The following items were 
recorded: first author's name, year of publication, ethnicity, 
method, tumor type, total number of patients, and HRs with 
their 95% CIs for OS. If available, we calculated HRs with </p>

<p>their 95% CIs using the data of observed deaths/cancer 
recurrences, the data of samples in each group, or the data 
provided by the authors. 
16 If not, the HRs with their 95% CIs 
and P-values were collected from the original article. If only 
Kaplan-Meier curves were available, data were extracted 
from graphical survival plots to extrapolate HRs with their 
95% CIs using previously described methods. 
17,18 Disagree-
ments were resolved by discussion among all authors. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>HRs with their 95% CIs were calculated on the basis of the 
association between LSD1 expression and the OS of cancer 
patients. The χ 
2 test and the I 
2 statistic were used to evaluate the 
heterogeneity among studies. 
19 If the heterogeneity was signifi-
cant between studies (I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>.50% or P,0.10), the random effects 
model was used; otherwise, the fixed effects model was used. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Sensitivity analysis was also conducted by sequential omis-
sion of individual studies to evaluate stability of the results. 
Publication bias was estimated by Egger's linear regression test 
with a funnel plot. 
21 The statistical analyses were performed 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 12.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Stata Corporation</rs>, 
Collage Station, TX, USA). All P-values were two-sided, and 
P,0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
study characteristics </p>

<p>The results of the search strategy are described in Figure 1. 
With our retrieval strategy, a total of 73 references were 
found. After review of abstracts, we identified 29 potential </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flowchart of the meta-analysis. 
Abbreviation: LSD1, lysine-specific demethylase 1. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2567 </p>

<p>Prognostic role of lsD1 in various cancers </p>

<p>studies eligible for inclusion in the evaluation. Upon full-text 
review, nine studies 
6-14 were selected for our meta-analysis, 
and the study characteristics are summarized in Table 1. The 
total number of patients included was 1,149, ranging from 
63 to 261 patients per study. Eight studies 
6-11,13,14 evaluated 
Asians and one 
12 evaluated Caucasian. The types of cancers 
in these studies included esophageal cancer, non-small-cell 
lung cancer, colon cancer, hepatocellular carcinoma, breast 
cancer, human melanomas, and tongue cancer. The method 
of LSD1 detection was based on immunohistochemistry. 
HRs with 95% CIs were reported directly in five studies, </p>

<p>8,10-13 </p>

<p>calculated from available data in one study, 
14 and extrapolated 
from Kaplan-Meier curves in three studies. </p>

<p>6,7,9 </p>

<p>Meta-analysis results </p>

<p>The main results of this meta-analysis are listed in Table 2. 
Our analysis suggested that LSD1 overexpression was asso-
ciated with poor OS in cancer patients (HR =1.80, 95% CI: 
1.39-2.34, P=0.000) with heterogeneity (I </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=53.6%, P=0.028) 
(Figure 2). 
To explain the heterogeneity in OS, subgroup analysis was 
performed by ethnicity, cancer type, and HR estimate. Sub-
group analysis by ethnicity suggested a significant association 
in Asian patients (HR =1.97, 95% CI: 1.61-2.41, P=0.000). 
When grouped according to cancer type, a significant </p>

<p>relationship between LSD1 expression and OS was observed 
in esophageal cancer patients (HR =1.77, 95% CI: 1.34-2.33, 
P=0.000). When stratifying by HR estimate, significant rel-
evance was observed both in "reported directly from articles" 
subgroup (HR =1.63, 95% CI: 1.17-2.29, P=0.004) and 
"survival curves" subgroup (HR =2.20, 95% CI: 1.63-2.96, 
P=0.000). </p>

<p>sensitivity analysis and publication bias </p>

<p>Sensitivity analysis indicated that the pooled HRs were 
not significantly influenced by omitting any single study 
(Figure 3). The shape of the funnel plot did not reveal any 
evidence of obvious asymmetry (Figure 4). The P-value of 
Egger's regression intercept was 0.134, indicating that there 
was no significant publication bias in the meta-analysis. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>LSD1 consists of several domains, including an N-terminal 
SWIRM domain, a conserved motif shared by many chro-
matin regulatory complexes, an amine oxidase domain, and a 
C-terminal tower domain. 
22-24 It cooperates with the CoREST 
and CtBP24 corepressor complex and demethylates histone 
H3K4 and H3K9 through this interaction. 
25,26 Epigenetic 
changes in LSD1 have been shown to play a key role in 
carcinogenesis. 
27 LSD1 can prevent the accumulation of the </p>

<p>Table 1 Main characteristics and results of the eligible studies </p>

<p>Study (year) 
Tumor type 
Ethnicity 
Number of 
patients </p>

<p>Method 
HR estimate 
HR (95% CI) </p>

<p>lv et al 
6 (2012) 
non-small-cell lung cancer 
asian 
80 
ihc 
survival curve 
2.49 (1.51-4.08) 
Zhao et al 
8 (2012) 
hepatocellular carcinoma 
asian 
198 
ihc 
reported 
2.456 (1.234-3.932) 
Ding et al 
7 (2013) 
colon cancer 
asian 
108 
ihc 
survival curve 
1.74 (1.03-2.94) 
Yu et al 
9 (2013) 
esophageal cancer 
asian 
134 
ihc 
survival curve 
2.42 (1.43-4.07) 
lin et al 
10 (2014) 
esophageal cancer 
asian 
135 
ihc 
reported 
1.645 (1.182-2.5) 
Derr et al 
12 (2014) 
Breast cancer 
caucasian 
261 
ihc 
reported 
1.182 (0.935-1.495) 
chen et al 
13 (2014) 
esophageal cancer 
asian 
103 
ihc 
reported 
1.34 (0.69-2.6) 
Miura et al 
14 (2014) 
human melanomas 
asian 
63 
ihc 
available data 
0.689 (0.083-5.715) 
Yuan et al 
11 (2015) 
Tongue cancer 
asian 
67 
ihc 
reported 
3.908 (1.238-12.339) </p>

<p>Abbreviation: ihc, immunohistochemistry. </p>

<p>Table 2 Main meta-analysis results of lsD1 expression in cancer patients </p>

<p>Analysis 
Studies 
(N) </p>

<p>Number of 
patients </p>

<p>HR (95% CI) 
P-value 
Heterogeneity </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>I 
2 (%) 
P-value </p>

<p>Os 
9 
1,149 
1.80 (1.39-2.34) 
0.000 
17.25 
53.6 
0.028 
ethnicity 
asian 
8 
888 
1.97 (1.61-2.41) 
0.000 
6.72 
0.0 
0.459 
hr estimate 
survival curves 
3 
322 
2.20 (1.63-2.96) 
0.000 
1.13 
0.0 
0.567 
reported directly 
5 
764 
1.63 (1.17-2.29) 
0.004 
9.38 
57.4 
0.052 
Tumor type 
esophageal cancer 
3 
372 
1.77 (1.34-2.33) 
0.000 
2.20 
9.0 
0.333 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: LSD1, lysine-specific demethylase 1; OS, overall survival. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2568 </p>

<p>Wu et al </p>

<p>Figure 2 Forest plots for the relationship between lsD1 expression and overall survival. 
Note: Weights are from random effects analysis. 
Abbreviation: LSD1, lysine-specific demethylase 1. </p>

<p>Figure 3 sensitivity analysis for meta-analysis of lsD1. 
Abbreviation: LSD1, lysine-specific demethylase 1. </p>

<p>dimethyl groups of p53, repressing p53-mediated transcrip-
tional upregulation, preventing apoptosis, and contributing 
to human carcinogenesis via a chromatin modification 
mechanism. Recently, many studies have been carried out 
to identify the prognostic role of LSD1 in various cancers. </p>

<p>Zhao et al 
8 demonstrated that high-level LSD1 predicts unfa-
vorable overall survival in hepatocellular carcinoma patients 
(HR =2.456, 95% CI: 1.234-3.932, P,0.001). Similar results 
were obtained in reports by Lin et al 
10 and Yuan et al 
11 with 
pooled HR for OS 1.645 (95% CI: 1.182-2.500, P=0.020) </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2569 </p>

<p>Prognostic role of lsD1 in various cancers </p>

<p>and 3.908 (95% CI: 1.238-12.339, P=0.020), respectively. 
However, insignificant or opposite results were also observed 
in some studies. Since the prognostic value of LSD1 for 
tumor patients remains controversial, a meta-analysis was 
needed to explore the issue clearly. 
To the best of our knowledge, this is the first meta-analysis 
focused on the association between LSD1 expression and 
patient survival. The present study pooled the survival 
data of 1,149 cancer patients from nine studies and found 
that LSD1 overexpression was associated with poor OS in 
cancer patients (HR =1.80, 95% CI: 1.39-2.34, P=0.000). 
The subgroup analyses grouped by ethnicity, cancer type, 
and HR estimate were consistent with the overall analysis. 
It may suggest that detected LSD1 expression could be a 
prognostic factor in cancers. 
Our meta-analysis also has several limitations that should 
be acknowledged. First, only one study focused on Caucasian 
patients, which made it difficult to draw a firm conclusion 
on the prognostic value of LSD1 for Caucasian patients. 
Second, the number of prognostic studies dealing with each 
type of cancer was relatively small, which might weaken the 
reliability of our results. Moreover, well-designed clinical 
studies with a large number of cases for each specific cancer 
should be performed in the future to validate the relationship 
between LSD1 expression level and prognosis of patients 
with cancer. Third, although the method for detecting LSD1 
level in all included studies was immunohistochemistry, it 
was difficult to follow entirely consistent monitoring stan-
dards for the dyeing process, antibody concentration, and 
cutoff value of different tissues. Fourth, we extracted data 
from survival curves because not all survival data of the 
enrolled studies were presented directly. These calculated </p>

<p>HRs with their 95% CIs might be less reliable than the 
directly given data. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The present meta-analysis indicated that increased LSD1 
level was significantly associated with poor OS. More multi-
center clinical investigations with larger sample sizes should 
be conducted to confirm these findings. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>OncoTargets and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>