<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4540966" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Environmental control of flowering allows plant reproduction to occur under optimal conditions and facilitates adapta-
tion to different locations. At high latitude, flowering of many plants is controlled by seasonal changes in day length. The 
photoperiodic flowering pathway confers this response in the Brassicaceae, which colonized temperate latitudes after 
divergence from the Cleomaceae, their subtropical sister family. The CONSTANS (CO) transcription factor of Arabidopsis 
thaliana, a member of the Brassicaceae, is central to the photoperiodic flowering response and shows characteristic 
patterns of transcription required for day-length sensing. CO is believed to be widely conserved among flowering plants; 
however, we show that it arose after gene duplication at the root of the Brassicaceae followed by divergence of 
transcriptional regulation and protein function. CO has two close homologs, CONSTANS-LIKE1 (COL1) and COL2, 
which are related to CO by tandem duplication and whole-genome duplication, respectively. The single CO homolog 
present in the Cleomaceae shows transcriptional and functional features similar to those of COL1 and COL2, suggesting 
that these were ancestral. We detect cis-regulatory and codon changes characteristic of CO and use transgenic assays to 
demonstrate their significance in the day-length-dependent activation of the CO target gene FLOWERING LOCUS T. Thus, 
the function of CO as a potent photoperiodic flowering switch evolved in the Brassicaceae after gene duplication. The 
origin of CO may have contributed to the range expansion of the Brassicaceae and suggests that in other families CO genes 
involved in photoperiodic flowering arose by convergent evolution. </p>

<p>Gene duplication is one of the mechanisms by which genes 
conferring novel functions arise during evolution (Ohno 1970; 
Soltis et al. 2009; Levin 2011; Ramsey 2011). Such duplications 
occur at the level of single genes through tandem or transpo-
sition duplication or as part of whole-genome duplications 
(WGDs) (Freeling 2009). Although one of the duplicates is 
usually lost, in some cases both are retained allowing diver-
gence in their function and evolution of novel activities. 
Different models for retention of duplicates have been pro-
posed including subfunctionalization, where each duplicate 
takes on part of the function of the original gene, and neo-
functionalization in which one of the duplicates exhibits a 
novel advantageous activity (Lynch and Conery 2000; 
Freeling et al. 2008; Flagel and Wendel 2009; Freeling 2009). 
In plants, WGDs have occurred many times and are impli-
cated in providing the genetic flexibility required for species 
diversification (Soltis et al. 2009; Schranz et al. 2012). During 
the evolutionary history of the model species Arabidopsis 
thaliana at least five WGDs have occurred. The oldest 
(At-z) is shared with all seed plants (Jiao et al. 2011), whereas 
the most recent (At-a) is specific to the Brassicaceae. At-a is 
detected in the genomes of species in the core Brassicaceae </p>

<p>and their sister tribe Aethionemae (Vision et al. 2000; Bowers 
et al. 2003; Jiao et al. 2011; Haudry et al. 2013), but is not 
present in the Cleomaceae, the sister family of the 
Brassicaceae. Rather the Cleomaceae underwent an indepen-
dent genome triplication (Th-a) as revealed in the genome of 
Tarenaya hassleriana (Cheng et al. 2013; Haudry et al. 2013). 
Thus At-a occurred in the progenitor of the core Brassicaceae 
and their sister tribe Aethionemae around 30-40 Ma, and this 
duplication may have provided the flexibility required for the 
evolutionary success of the core Brassicaceae (Couvreur et al. 
2010; Schranz et al. 2012). 
Tandem duplications are also commonly found in plant 
genomes (Leister 2004; Casneuf et al. 2006; Rizzon et al. 2006). 
These are gene family members located adjacent or close to 
one another on the same chromosome. They are likely to 
mainly arise through recombination-based mechanisms, par-
ticularly unequal crossing over, because they are present at 
highest frequency in regions of the genome where recombi-
nation occurs most frequently and genes in tandem arrays are 
most often present in the same orientation (Zhang and Gaut 
2003; Rizzon et al. 2006). In the well-characterized genome of 
A. thaliana, such tandemly arrayed genes comprise only a 
slightly lower proportion of all genes (18%) than those 
retained after WGDs (25%) (Lockton and Gaut 2005; Rizzon </p>

<p>ß The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p> 
Mol. Biol. Evol. 32(9):2284-2301 doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 Advance Access publication May 13, 2015 </p>

<p>et al. 2006). As discussed above for genes involved in WGD, 
genes that arise by tandem duplication can also diverge in 
function and expression pattern (Zhang et al. 2000; 
Kliebenstein et al. 2001; Vlad et al. 2014). Indeed, tandemly 
duplicated genes are reported to be more divergent in their 
expression patterns than those that arise by WGD (Casneuf 
et al. 2006). Also, WGDs occur rarely within a phylogeny, 
whereas tandem duplications can occur frequently and 
thus can be restricted to closely related species or even 
only be present within a species (Leister 2004; Hanikenne 
et al. 2008; Vlad et al. 2014). In this way, they can contribute 
to adaptation to particular environments or to species spe-
cific traits (Zhang et al. 2000; Hanikenne et al. 2008; Vlad et al. 
2014). Consistent with this conclusion, analysis of proteins 
encoded by tandemly duplicated genes indicated that those 
involved in environmental responses to biotic or abiotic sti-
muli are overrepresented (Leister 2004; Rizzon et al. 2006). 
Environmental control of the transition to flowering, the 
first step in plant reproduction, is an important adaptive trait 
in many species. These responses allow flowering to be 
induced at the optimal time to maximize opportunities for 
cross-fertilization, to minimize floral damage and to ensure 
completion of seed development before the onset of adverse 
conditions (Anderson et al. 2011). Seasonal cues such as 
changes in photoperiod (day length) and response to verna-
lization (prolonged periods of cold) are critical in the adapta-
tion of flowering time to environment in many plant families 
(Hayama et al. 2003; Yan et al. 2003; Turck et al. 2008; Wang 
et al. 2009; Blackman et al. 2011). Consistent with this, latitu-
dinal or altitudinal clines for flowering responses to seasonal 
cues and allelic variation in some of the genes conferring 
them have been reported (Ray and Alexander 1966; 
Stinchcombe et al. 2004; Mendez-Vigo et al. 2011) as have 
selection for flowering in response to other environmental 
pressures (Hall and Willis 2006; Toomajian et al. 2006; Franks 
et al. 2007). The molecular-genetic control of seasonal flower-
ing is best understood in the model species A. thaliana 
(Andr es and Coupland 2012). 
The vernalization response to winter cold is widely dis-
persed in the Brassicaceae. The FLOWERING LOCUS C (FLC) 
gene encodes a MADS box transcription factor that plays a 
critical role in vernalization response of A. thaliana and other 
Brassicaceae species by repressing flowering until plants are 
exposed to winter temperatures (Michaels and Amasino 
1999; Sheldon et al. 1999; Schranz et al. 2002; Okazaki et al. 
2007; Wang et al. 2009). Allelic variation at FLC and its 
upstream regulator FRIGIDA is widespread in natural popula-
tions of different species (Johanson et al. 2000; Michaels et al. 
2003; Lempe et al. 2005; Shindo et al. 2005), and some of this 
shows patterns of variation consistent with selection 
(Stinchcombe et al. 2004; Toomajian et al. 2006; Mendez-
Vigo et al. 2011). 
Flowering of A. thaliana is also regulated by seasonal 
changes in day length, being accelerated by long days (LDs) 
typical of spring and summer. The CONSTANS (CO) gene is a 
key regulatory component of the photoperiodic flowering 
time pathway (Putterill et al. 1995), and natural genetic varia-
tion has been described at this locus in A. thaliana (Rosas et al. </p>

<p>2014). In the genetic cascade that triggers flowering in 
response to photoperiod, a class of redundant repressive 
transcription factor called CYCLING DOF FACTOR (CDF), 
which are regulated by both light and the circadian clock, 
contains the major regulators of CO transcription (Imaizumi 
et al. 2005; Sawa et al. 2007; Fornara et al. 2009). This regula-
tion ensures that CO mRNA levels are low when plants are 
exposed to light under short days (SDs), but high during the 
evening under LDs, when exposure to light stabilizes CO 
protein (Suarez-Lopez et al. 2001; Valverde et al. 2004; Sawa 
et al. 2007; Fornara et al. 2009). Consequently CO protein only 
accumulates to promote flowering under inductive LDs, and 
does so by activating the transcription of FLOWERING LOCUS 
T (FT) and TWIN SISTER OF FT (TSF) in the leaf vasculature 
(Samach et al. 2000; Corbesier et al. 2007; Jaeger and Wigge 
2007; Mathieu et al. 2007; Song et al. 2012). This regulatory 
cascade confers photoperiodic flowering even in distantly 
related monocotyledons (Yano et al. 2000; Hayama et al. 
2003; Campoli et al. 2012), and CO homologs are also asso-
ciated with other day-length-dependent developmental pro-
cesses such as tuberization in potato or bud dormancy in 
poplar trees (Bohlenius et al. 2006; Gonz alez-Schain et al. 
2012). Moreover, CO homologs confer diverse responses to 
photoperiod, functioning as photoperiodic sensors in plants 
that respond to long photoperiods, such as A. thaliana, or to 
short photoperiods, such as Oryza sativa and Solanum tuber-
osum (Yano et al. 2000; Gonz alez-Schain et al. 2012). Thus CO-
related genes have been utilized during evolution to confer 
different photoperiodic responses on diverse developmental 
processes. 
CO was the first member of a small family of CONSTANS-
LIKE (COL) genes to be identified (Putterill et al. 1995). In 
A. thaliana, the family contains 17 members (Robson et al. 
2001; Khanna et al. 2009). All COL proteins contain one or 
two zinc finger B-Boxes that are assumed to be protein-
protein interaction domains and a CO, CONSTANS-LIKE, 
TOC1 (CCT) domain important for mediating interaction 
with DNA (Griffiths et al. 2003; Tiwari et al. 2010; Song 
et al. 2012). Although CO is a master regulator of photoper-
iodic flowering in A. thaliana, its closest homologs COL1 and 
COL2 were implicated in circadian clock function but not 
reproductive development (Putterill et al. 1995; Ledger et al. 
2001; Kim et al. 2013). CO, COL1, and COL2 represent a single 
clade within the family referred to as subgroup Ia COL genes 
(Griffiths et al. 2003). COL1 exists as a tandem duplication 
with CO on chromosome 5, a structure also present in 
Brassica napus (Robert et al. 1998), whereas COL2 is located 
on chromosome 3. These two chromosomal regions of 
A. thaliana arose in the most recent WGD (At-a) early in 
the evolution of the Brassicaceae (Bowers et al. 2003; Khanna 
et al. 2009; Cheng et al. 2013; Haudry et al. 2013). Interestingly 
COL1 and COL2 are differently expressed than CO with a high 
amplitude peak of transcription only in the morning (Ledger 
et al. 2001). Similar diurnal expression patterns to COL1/2 
have been identified in close homologs of CO from many 
dicot plants including Pharbitis nil, S. tuberosum, and Vitis 
vinifera (Ledger et al. 2001; Liu et al. 2001; Almada et al. 
2009; Gonz alez-Schain et al. 2012). In contrast, CO homologs </p>

<p>2285 </p>

<p>Evolution of CONSTANS . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>in the monocot models rice and barley show transcriptional 
patterns similar to CO of A. thaliana (Hayama et al. 2003; 
Turner et al. 2005; Campoli et al. 2012). How the photoper-
iodic role of CO genes and their characteristic patterns of 
expression evolved has not been investigated. 
In this study, we investigate the evolution of the photo-
periodic flowering pathway in the Brassicaceae. We examine 
the evolutionary history of subgroup Ia COL genes, which 
includes both WGD and tandem duplication. We analyze 
the expression patterns of the single CO homolog ThCOL 
from T. hassleriana of the Cleomaceae family (Schranz and 
Mitchell-Olds 2006) as well as those of subgroup Ia COL genes 
of the basal Brassicaceae species Aethionema arabicum, the 
sister of the core Brassicaceae, and demonstrate that the CO 
transcriptional pattern is shown by CO genes in the 
Brassicaceae but not by COL genes in the Brassicaceae or 
Cleomaceae. This novel transcriptional pattern seems to 
have originated with the tandem duplication of COL1 and 
CO in the Brassicaceae, which led to a significant and con-
served increase in DOF binding sites in the promoters of CO 
genes. In addition, functional tests in A. thaliana showed that 
the Brassicaceae CO proteins are more effective at promoting 
flowering than subgroup Ia COL proteins from the 
Brassicaceae or of T. hassleriana. We conclude that the 
change in expression pattern together with enhancement 
of the functionality of CO protein in promoting FT transcrip-
tion compared with its ancestral gene generated a potent 
photoperiodic switch early in the evolution of the 
Brassicaceae and this was then conserved throughout the 
family. These responses are likely to have been important as 
Brassicaceae, in contrast to the Cleomaceae, colonized north-
ern latitudes where responses to seasonal fluctuations of day 
length are particularly significant. The origin of CO at the root 
of the Brassicaceae suggests that similarly expressed CO-like 
genes involved in photoperiodic responses in monocotyledo-
nous plants or in potato arose by convergent evolution. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Aethionema arabicum, a Member of a Basal 
Brassicaceae Lineage, Contains a Functional 
CO Homolog </p>

<p>CO orthologs are found in many Brassicaceae species but the 
conservation of their expression patterns and functions has 
not been analyzed across distantly related family members. 
To this end, we identified subgroup Ia orthologs of CO in the 
Brassicaceae species Ae. arabicum, which belongs to a basal 
sister lineage of the core Brassicaceae (Bailey et al. 2006; 
Haudry et al. 2013; supplementary fig. S1, Supplementary 
Material online). Orthologs of CO (AeCO) and COL2 
(AeCOL2) were identified in Ae. arabicum based on their 
sequence homology and synteny with A. thaliana (fig. 1A), 
but the ortholog of COL1 was not present due to an appar-
ently recent rearrangement (fig. 1A). 
The flowering time of Ae. arabicum was tested under 
controlled conditions to determine whether the presence 
of AeCO was associated with a photoperiodic flowering 
response. Aethionema arabicum plants flowered with </p>

<p>approximately 20 leaves in LDs (fig. 1B) but did not flower 
under SDs, indicating that these plants exhibit an obligate 
photoperiodic flowering response. To test the functionality 
of AeCO its cDNA was fused to the A. thaliana CO promoter 
(pCO) to confer a similar transcriptional pattern as CO. This 
construct was introduced into A. thaliana co-10 null mutants. 
Plants carrying the transgene flowered at a comparable time 
to the control line carrying an CO transgene, and significantly 
earlier than the co-10 progenitor or Col-0 wild-type (wt) (fig. 
1C). Thus Ae. arabicum contains a CO ortholog that shares 
protein activity with CO of A. thaliana, suggesting that CO 
was already present before diversification of the major 
lineages of the Brassicaceae. </p>

<p>Distinct Transcriptional Patterns of CO and COL2 Are 
Conserved in Ae. arabicum </p>

<p>CO exhibits a temporal transcriptional pattern distinct from 
COL1 and COL2 in A. thaliana. In order to determine whether 
this difference is conserved in Ae. arabicum, the mRNA levels 
of AeCO and AeCOL2 were examined every 3 h for 24 h in 
seedlings growing under LDs or SDs (fig. 2). Under LDs, AeCO 
showed a similar pattern of mRNA accumulation to CO, 
including high mRNA levels at lights on (dawn) that fall in 
the middle of the day before rising again to high amplitude in 
the evening and night (fig. 2A). Under SDs, AeCO mRNA levels 
were low during day light but increased during the night, 
again similar to CO (fig. 2B). AeCOL2 mRNA levels exhibited 
a single peak in the morning (lights on, Zeitgeber Time (ZT)0) 
and trough levels in the evening (ZT9 and ZT15) under both 
LDs and SDs (fig. 2C and D). AeCOL2 expression levels rose 
earlier in the night in SD grown seedlings compared with 
those grown in LD. This pattern of transcription is highly 
consistent with the expression patterns of COL2 and COL1 
(fig. 2C and D). Thus both CO and COL2 have conserved 
expression patterns in A. thaliana and Ae. arabicum, suggest-
ing that these differences arose very early in the diversification 
of the Brassicaceae and have been conserved in distinct 
lineages. </p>

<p>Tarenaya hassleriana COL Exhibits the Transcriptional 
Pattern and Protein Activity of COL1/2 </p>

<p>CO, COL1, and COL2 represent a monophyletic group that 
diversified in the Brassicaceae, whereas T. hassleriana of the 
Cleomaceae family, which is sister to the Brassicaceae, con-
tains only a single gene (ThCOL) in this group. ThCOL is there-
fore believed to be homologous to CO, COL1, and COL2 
(Schranz and Mitchell-Olds 2006; supplementary fig. S3C, 
Supplementary Material online). ThCOL expression pattern 
and protein function were tested to determine whether 
they are more similar to CO or COL1/2. The expression pat-
tern of ThCOL in T. hassleriana seedlings grown under LD and 
SD (fig. 3A) was highly similar to the temporal expression 
patterns of COL1 and COL2 genes in the Brassicaceae but 
clearly distinct from CO and AeCO (fig. 2). This result suggests 
that the last common ancestor of the Brassicaceae and 
Cleomaceae families carried a single subgroup Ia COL gene 
that was expressed similarly to COL1/2 and that the mRNA </p>



<p>Simon et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>expression pattern of CO arose early in the diversification of 
the Brassicaceae so that it was conserved in each lineage. 
The amino acid sequences of Brassicaceae subgroup Ia 
COL proteins were compared with the sequence of ThCOL 
and the amino acid sequence of a COL protein from Carica 
papaya was used to root the phylogenetic tree (fig. 3B). CO, 
COL1, and COL2 proteins from the Brassicaceae family form 
monophyletic groups and ThCOL acts as an outgroup to all 
Brassicaceae subgroup Ia COL proteins (fig. 3B). The ratio 
of nonsynonymous to synonymous substitution rates 
(d n /d s ratio) between A. thaliana or Ae. arabicum Ia COL 
genes and ThCOL was lower than 1.0, suggesting stabilizing 
selection (supplementary fig. S3B, Supplementary Material 
online). Based on this analysis ThCOL is equally distantly 
related to all three subgroup Ia COL genes (CO, COL1, and 
COL2). 
In order to identify functional differences among them, 
subgroup Ia COL proteins were tested in a transgenic com-
plementation assay. To examine the capacity of subgroup Ia 
COL proteins to accelerate flowering in A. thaliana, cDNAs 
encoding these proteins in A. thaliana, Ae. arabicum and 
T. hassleriana were fused to the strong, phloem-specific 
SUCROSE TRANSPORTER 2 (SUC2) promoter (pSUC2, Imlau 
et al. 1999). This promoter was chosen because CO and 
its downstream target FT are expressed in the phloem </p>

<p>companion cells in A. thaliana and overexpression of CO 
from pSUC2 greatly accelerates flowering (An et al. 2004; 
Corbesier et al. 2007). All constructs were introduced into 
the co-10 null mutant of A. thaliana to test their functionality. 
The co-10 plants carrying each of the pSUC2 driven constructs 
flowered much earlier than the co-10 progenitor and at least 
as early as wt (Col-0) (fig. 3C and supplementary fig. S2A, 
Supplementary Material online). Nonetheless, the lines carry-
ing either CO or AeCO were among the earliest flowering, with 
a mean number of approximately seven to approximately 
eight total leaves compared with lines carrying COL genes 
that had a mean number of approximately 9 to 
approximately 16 total leaves. In all lines tested early flowering 
was associated with elevated FT mRNA levels compared with 
co-10 control, suggesting that each of these proteins is capable 
of activating FT transcription when expressed from pSUC2 
(supplementary fig. S2C and D, Supplementary Material 
online). Thus, expression from the SUC2 promoter demon-
strates that all subgroup Ia COL proteins as well as the 
Cleomaceae ortholog of these proteins are able to promote 
flowering when overexpressed in the appropriate cells in 
A. thaliana. 
The SUC2 promoter causes high expression levels in 
phloem companion cells (Imlau et al. 1999) that might 
reduce the specificity of these proteins. Thus, similar </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>AT5G15400 AT5G15410 
AT5G15450 </p>

<p>1kb </p>

<p>Ae. Arabicum 
contig 3716 (15kb) </p>

<p>Ae. Arabicum 
contig 451 (26kb) </p>

<p>AT3G02420 </p>

<p>AT5G15850 (COL1) </p>

<p>AT5G15840 (CO) </p>

<p>AT3G02360 
AT3G02410 </p>

<p>AT3G02380 (COL2) </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Ae. Arabicum </p>

<p>LD 
SD </p>

<p>Leaf Number </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>n=12 </p>

<p>N.F. </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Flowering time in LD </p>

<p>Total Leaf Number </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>n=12 </p>

<p>** p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>pCO::3xHA:(cDNA) in co-10 </p>

<p>C o l -0 c o -1 0 
CO 
AeCO </p>

<p>#2 #5 #8 #10 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* 
** 
** ** </p>

<p>* p&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Identification of a functional CO homolog in the LD plant Aethionema arabicum. (A) Two contigs containing subgroup Ia COL genes in 
Ae. arabicum. AGI locus identifiers indicate homologous genes in Arabidopsis thaliana (Tair 10). A chromosomal rearrangement removed most of the 
COL1 ortholog in Ae. arabicum of which only the last 59 bp were retained (black arrow). (B) Flowering time of Ae. arabicum as total number of leaves at 
appearance of first inflorescence in LD (16 h light/8 h dark) and SD conditions (8 h light/16 h dark). Mean AE SD; n = 12; N.F., not flowering. (C) Flowering 
time of A. thaliana as mean (AESD) of total leaf number of Col-0, co-10, pCO::3xHA:CO (co-10) and pCO::HA:AeCO (co-10) in LD conditions 
(Ae, Aethionema arabicum). Transgenic plants are independent homozygous T 3 lines with n = 12 plants per genotype. Asterisks (*P &lt; 0.05; 
**P &lt; 0.001) indicate statistically significantly earlier flowering compared with Col-0 (wt). </p>



<p>Evolution of CONSTANS . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>experiments were performed using the native A. thaliana pCO 
that were expected to more reliably reveal the capacity with 
which these proteins can promote flowering. CO and AeCO 
expressed from pCO were judged to fully complement the 
late-flowering phenotype of co-10 (figs. 1C and 3D), because 
transgenic lines carrying these constructs flowered with a 
mean of approximately 10 to approximately 14 total leaves, 
which was much earlier than the co-10 mutant (~44 leaves) 
and even earlier than the wt control (~18 total leaves). The 
other proteins (COL1, COL2, AeCOL2, ThCOL) were not able 
to fully replace CO function leading to flowering times 
later than wt but earlier than co-10 (fig. 3D and supplemen-
tary fig. S2B, Supplementary Material online). The level of 
mRNA expressed from the transgenes was tested in each 
line (supplementary fig. S2E, Supplementary Material 
online). Those lines that promoted earliest flowering (expres-
sing CO and AeCO) did not express higher levels of transgene 
mRNA than later flowering lines (expressing COL1, COL2, 
AeCOL2, ThCOL) (supplementary fig. S2E, Supplementary 
Material online). Furthermore, transgenic lines expressing 
COL1, COL2, AeCOL2, and ThCOL from pCO consistently 
expressed lower levels of FT mRNA than those expressing 
CO or AeCO (supplementary fig. S2F, Supplementary 
Material online). Collectively, these experiments show that 
CO and AeCO are more potent in promoting FT transcription 
and flowering than the COL1/2 homologs and the 
Cleomaceae ortholog. </p>

<p>To identify residues potentially responsible for these differ-
ences in protein activity, the COL and CO proteins from 
different species were aligned. Amino acid differences in the 
B-Boxes and CCT domain were searched for because these 
regions are functionally important based on the analysis of co 
mutant alleles (Robson et al. 2001). Our analysis revealed four 
amino acid positions that are conserved in COL1/2 homologs 
(including ThCOL and CpCO) and different in all CO homo-
logs (supplementary fig. S3A, Supplementary Material online). 
Three are located in the B-Boxes (S49A; D79A; I90V) and the 
remaining residue is in the CCT domain (N342A). These four 
residues are candidates for conferring functional differences 
between COL and CO proteins. 
These experiments indicate that COL1 and COL2 are able 
to accelerate flowering and activate FT transcription when 
expressed from pSUC2 or pCO, but the late-flowering pheno-
type and very low FT mRNA level of the co-10 mutant suggest 
that COL1 and COL2 do not carry out these functions when 
expressed from their native promoters (Jang et al. 2009). We 
thus also examined the spatial expression patterns of COL1 
and COL2 by using promoter -glucuronidase (GUS) fusion 
constructs in transgenic A. thaliana plants. pCO::GUS, which 
serves as a control, is expressed mainly in leaf vascular tissue, 
where CO activates FT transcription (supplementary fig. S3D, 
Supplementary Material online; Takada and Goto 2003; An 
et al. 2004). GUS activity driven by pCOL1, on the other hand, 
is more evenly distributed in the leaf and therefore differs </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>CO mRNA in SD </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
1 2 
1 5 
1 8 
2 1 
2 4 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>CO 
AeCO </p>

<p>CO mRNA in LD </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
21 
24 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>CO 
AeCO </p>

<p>COL mRNA in LD </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
21 
24 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>COL1 
COL2 
AeCOL2 </p>

<p>COL mRNA in SD </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
21 
24 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>COL1 
COL2 
AeCOL2 </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Diurnal patterns of CO and COL1/2 mRNA abundance in Arabidopsis thaliana and Aethionema arabicum. (A, B) Diurnal pattern of CO mRNA 
was measured in LD and SD grown seedlings of A. thaliana (CO) and Ae. arabicum (AeCO). (C, D) Diurnal expression patterns of COL1 and COL2 from A. 
thaliana and Ae. arabicum (AeCOL2) in LD or SD conditions. Values are shown as mean AE SD of two biological replicates after normalization to PP2A (A. 
thaliana) or ACTIN (Ae. arabicum). Gray areas indicate darkness. </p>



<p>Simon et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>Total Leaf Number </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>n=12 
* p&lt; 0.05 
** p&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>C o l -0 
c o -1 0 
CO 
AeCO 
COL1 
COL2 
AeCOL2 
ThCOL </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>pCO::3xHA:(cDNA) in co-10 </p>

<p>#7 #8 #9 #10 
#2 #5 #8 #10 
#1 </p>

<p>* 
** * ** </p>

<p>Flowering time in LD </p>

<p>#1 #5 #9 #10 
#6 #8 #10 #11 
#4 #6 #8 #9 </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>** 
** ** </p>

<p>** 
** ** </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** ** </p>

<p>ThCOL mRNA </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
21 
24 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>LD 
SD </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Total Leaf Number </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>n=12 
* p&lt; 0.05 
** p&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>#1 #2 #7 #8 </p>

<p>C o l -0 
c o -1 0 
CO 
AeCO 
COL1 
COL2 
AeCOL2 
ThCOL </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>#1 #2 #3 #4 </p>

<p>pSUC2::3xHA:(cDNA) in co-10 </p>

<p>#3 #5 #8 #9 
#5 #10 #11 #13 
#2 #3 #4 #10 
#3 #4 #5 </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>** ** ** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>* 
** ** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** ** 
** </p>

<p>Flowering time in LD </p>

<p>CrCO 
BsCO 
AtCO 
AaCO 
EsCO 
BrCO 
AeCO 
CrCOL1 
BsCOL1 
AtCOL1 
AaCOL1 
EsCOL1 
BrCOL1 
BrCOL1 
CrCOL2 
AtCOL2 
BsCOL2 
BrCOL2 
BrCOL2 
AaCOL2 
AeCOL2 
ThCOL 
CpCO </p>

<p>75 
67 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>82 </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>13 
85 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Properties of ThCOL in comparison to Brassicaceaen subgroup Ia COL genes. (A) Diurnal expression of ThCOL mRNA in Tarenaya hassleriana 
seedlings grown under LD or SD conditions. Values are shown as mean AE SD for two biological replicates after normalization to ACTIN. Light gray area 
indicates darkness in SD, whereas dark gray indicates darkness in both light conditions. (B) Neighbor-joining tree of amino acid sequence from subgroup 
Ia COL proteins from Arabidopsis thaliana (At), Arabis alpina (Aa), Aethionema arabicum (Ae), Boechera stricta (Bs), Brassica rapa 
(Br), Capsella rubella (Cr), Carica papaya (Cp), Eutrema salsugineum (Es), and T. hassleriana (Th). Numbers indicate bootstrap values of 10,000 </p>

<p>2289 </p>

<p>Evolution of CONSTANS . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>(continued) </p>

<p>from the pCO expression pattern. More precisely, pCOL1::GUS 
activity is less pronounced in the vascular tissue compared 
with pCO::GUS and it is also detectable in the lower part of 
young leaves (supplementary fig. S3D, Supplementary 
Material online). In pCOL2::GUS plants, enzyme activity is 
detected in the stem below or overlapping with the shoot 
apical meristem but it is very weak in other tissues (supple-
mentary fig. S3D, Supplementary Material online). Thus, in 
addition to differences between CO and COL1/2 protein 
activity, cis-regulatory differences in the temporal and spatial 
expression of COL1/2 in comparison to CO likely contribute to 
subfunctionalization (Ledger et al. 2001; Kim et al. 2013) of the 
three genes following duplication. </p>

<p>The Promoter of CO Is Conserved in the 
Brassicaceae Family and Differs from COL Gene 
Promoters in Cis-Element Composition </p>

<p>The CO transcriptional pattern is a novelty that arose in the 
Brassicaceae and is conserved in the different lineages repre-
sented by A. thaliana and Ae. arabicum (fig. 2). Therefore, the 
extent of promoter sequence conservation among these 
genes was examined. The intergenic region between CO 
and COL1 was identified and aligned with those from ten 
Brassicaceae species. The comparison using Ae. arabicum as 
a base genome revealed conserved regions ( 4 70% identity, 
fig. 4A). Three conserved blocks, about À 200 bp, À1.4 kb 
and À 2.2 kb upstream of the ATG of CO (supplementary 
fig. S4A, Supplementary Material online), were identified 
(about À 300 bp, À 1.2 kb, and À 1.7 kb in Ae. arabicum; 
fig. 4A), which were named Conserved Proximal Motif 
(CPM), Conserved Middle Motif (CMM), and Conserved 
Distal Motif (CDM). In agreement with the differential expres-
sion patterns of ThCOL and CO, the promoter of ThCOL does 
not exhibit conservation of more than 50% of nucleotides 
(in a 100-bp sliding window) to Brassicaceae CO promoters 
(fig. 4A and supplementary fig. S4A, Supplementary Material 
online). 
Next, we investigated the cis-element composition of the 
three conserved motifs (fig. 4A and supplementary fig. S6, 
Supplementary Material online). We found two or three 
DOF binding sites in all three conserved motifs. The extended 
DOF binding site (AAAGTG) occurs in clusters in the CO 
promoter and was shown to be recognized by the CO repres-
sor CDF1 (Imaizumi et al. 2005; Sawa et al. 2007; Rosas et al. 
2014). Additionally all three conserved elements contain a 
CCAAT Box (CCAAT), which has not previously been 
described to be important in CO transcriptional regulation. 
However, CCAAT-Boxes are linked to vascular cell-specific 
transcriptional regulation through Nuclear Factor Y transcrip-
tion factors and in promotion of transcription of FT, a down-
stream target of CO (Wenkel et al. 2006; Siefers et al. 2008; 
Cao et al. 2014). The CPM and CDM motifs additionally </p>

<p>contain two elements not so far linked to CO transcriptional 
regulation: A G-Box (CACGTG) and a LUX Binding site (LBS) 
(GATWCG). G-Boxes are cis-elements implicated in control of 
transcription by light (Terzaghi and Cashmore 1995), whereas 
LBS motifs are bound by the Evening Complex through the 
LUX TF and are found in the promoters of circadian clock 
regulated genes (Helfer et al. 2011; Nusinow et al. 2011). CMM, 
but not CPM and CDM, contains a cis-element (GGACCA) 
that was associated with regulation by TCP4, a member of the 
TEOSINTE BRANCHED/CYCLOIDEA/PCF (TCP) transcrip-
tion factor family, that has not been associated with regula-
tion of CO (Schommer et al. 2008). In summary, CO promoter 
has two conserved motifs, CPM and CDM containing the 
same combination of cis-elements (3 Â DOF, CCAAT-Box, 
G-Box, LBS) and one motif, the CMM with a partially over-
lapping combination (2 Â DOF, CCAAT-Box, TCP) (fig. 4A 
and supplementary fig. S6, Supplementary Material online). 
To investigate the functional importance of the three con-
served motifs, the short promoter regions (fig. 4A and sup-
plementary fig. S6, Supplementary Material online) were 
fused to the NOPALINE SYNTHASE (NOS) minimal promoter 
(pnos; Shaw et al. 1984; Puente et al. 1996) to drive 
LUCIFERASE (LUC) expression in transgenic A. thaliana 
plants. Luminescence due to LUC expression was detected 
in the vasculature of CPM:pnos::LUC, CMM:pnos::LUC and 
CDM:pnos::LUC plants but not in the pnos empty vector 
control line (supplementary fig. S5E, Supplementary 
Material online). The temporal expression of LUC mRNA 
was then tested using reverse transcriptase polymerase 
chain reaction (PCR), which was more precise than following 
luminescence due to the low expression level of each trans-
gene. Compared with the full-length CO promoter (2.6 kb) 
driving LUC cDNA, CPM (135 bp), CMM (171 bp), and CDM 
(93 bp) confer much lower overall expression levels (supple-
mentary fig. S5B, Supplementary Material online). 
Nevertheless, normalization of the expression patterns and 
comparison to endogenous CO transcription revealed that 
these short motifs confer diurnal transcriptional patterns 
similar to those of native CO (fig. 5), whereas the pnos 
empty vector control does not (supplementary fig. S5A, 
Supplementary Material online). In CPM:pnos::LUC and 
CMM:pnos::LUC lines, a shoulder was present in the peak of 
expression of LUC mRNA (ZT12-15) and a peak was present 
during the night (ZT18), which are characteristic of the CO 
mRNA temporal pattern, whereas CDM:pnos::LUC lines 
showed a more gradual upregulation in the evening and 
night (fig. 5). In summary, three conserved parts of CO pro-
moter are independently sufficient to confer a diurnal and 
spatial pattern of expression similar to that of CO but at lower 
amplitude. 
The functional impact on flowering-time regulation of the 
three conserved elements was tested in a promoter </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Continued 
iterations. Arabidopsis thaliana co-10 null mutant was complemented with cDNA of COL1, COL2, AeCO, AeCOL2, and ThCOL fused to 3xHA-tag 
expressed from pSUC2 (C) or pCO (D). Flowering time (mean total leaf number AE SD) was examined in independent homozygous transgenic lines (T 3 ) 
in LD conditions. Col-0, co-10, and homozygous pCO::3xHA:CO, pAeCO::3xHA:CO (from fig. 1C) and pSUC2::3xHA:CO lines are shown as controls. 
Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences in leaf number (*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.001) compared with Col-0 (wt). </p>



<p>Simon et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>complementation assay. The elements are distributed along 
the full length of the region previously defined as the CO 
promoter (fig. 4A; An et al. 2004). The pCO::GFP:CO fusion 
construct was used to complement the co-2 mutation in A. 
thaliana Landsberg erecta (Ler) accession. Complementation 
with this 2.6-kb promoter caused early flowering in homo-
zygous transgenic lines (supplementary fig. S5C and D, 
Supplementary Material online). Although co-2 mutant </p>

<p>plants flowered with 20-30 leaves in LD conditions, the 
pCO::GFP:CO (2.6 kb) co-2 lines flowered with approximately 
six total leaves. The CDM motif was deleted from the CO 
promoter in the 2.1 kb pCO fragment (fig. 4A), and 
pCO::GFP:CO (2.1 kb) co-2 plants flowered significantly later 
(9-15 total leaves) than those carrying the full-length 2.6-kb 
promoter construct in three of four independent transgenic 
lines (supplementary fig. S5C, Supplementary Material </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C 
D </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Conservation and cis-element composition of CO promoter in the Brassicaceae. (A) Pairwise alignment of the Aethionema arabicum CO 
promoter to orthologous sequences from ten Brassicaceae CO promoters as well as Tarenaya hassleriana COL promoter displayed as VISTA plots. 
Sequence similarity (%) was calculated in 100-bp sliding window while light-red color indicates greater than 75% identity. For clarity a diagram of 
Arabidopsis thaliana CO promoter is displayed above, indicating position of cis-elements (DOF = AAAGTG, TCP = GGACCA, E-Box = CANNTG, 
G-Box = CACGTG, LBS = GATWCG, and CCAAT-Box = CCAAT). Approximate positions of CO promoter sequences used for LUC reporter 
(CDM:pnos:LUC, CMM:pnos::LUC, CPM:pnos::LUC) and GFP:CO (2.6, 2.1, and 0.6 kb) complementation constructs in this study are indicated in relation 
to the vista plot. (B-D) Short motif search (MEME, 6-10 bp) in CO promoters from ten Brassicaceae species (see A) resulted in three elements that were 
found 70 (B), 40 (C), and 73 times (D), respectively (displayed as WEBLOGO). Identified motifs (underlined) contain the extended DOF binding site 
(B, AAAGTG), the TCP binding site (C, GGACCA), and the E-Box (D, CANNTG). Mean Abundance of these three cis-elements was determined in 
promoters (À4 kb) of Brassicaceae CO, COL1, and COL2 as well as non-Brassicaceae COL orthologs (COL) (B-D, Experiment, AESEM). The same analysis 
was performed 100 times with shuffled data sets as control for base composition (Shuffle Control). Brassicaceae sequences include homologs from 
A. thaliana, A. alpina, Eutrema parvulum, Brassica rapa (1 Â CO, 2Â COL1, and 2 Â COL2), and Ae. arabicum (CO and COL2). Promoters from non-
Brassicaceae species include T. hassleriana (ThCOL), Medicago truncatula (MtCOLa), Populus Trichocarpa (PtCO1; PtCO2), Solanum tuberosum (StCO1; 
StCO2), and Vitis vinifera (VvCO). Statistical analysis indicates significant differences (*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.001) in mean abundance compared with CO. </p>

<p>2291 </p>

<p>Evolution of CONSTANS . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>online). This result indicates that the distal conserved motif 
(CDM) is located in a functionally important part of the CO 
promoter and that this segment is required for full accelera-
tion of flowering in LDs. Whether a fusion of the proximal 
0.6 kb of CO promoter to GFP:CO is sufficient to cause earlier 
flowering of co-2 mutants was then examined. However, no 
significant acceleration of flowering of pCO::GFP:CO (0.6 kb) 
co-2 was detected compared with co-2, although this prox-
imal promoter contains the CPM motif (supplementary fig. 
S5D, Supplementary Material online). This promoter comple-
mentation assay indicates that the activity of pCO gradually 
decreases with progressive deletions from 2.6, 2.1, and 0.6 kb 
and only the fragment containing all three conserved regions 
provides full promoter activity. 
The CO promoter evolved in the Brassicaceae and contains 
functionally important conserved sequences that harbor dis-
tinct combinations of cis-elements (figs. 4A and 5 and sup-
plementary fig. S5 and S6, Supplementary Material online). To 
identify cis-element motifs associated with CO expression 
pattern, 6-10 bp motifs overrepresented in the ten 
Brassicaceae CO promoters were sought using the <rs id="software-9" type="software">Multiple 
Em for Motif Elicitation</rs> (MEME) tool (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Bailey</rs> et al. 2009). The 
most enriched sequences (present 73 Â in the ten promoters) 
contain the E-Box (CANNTG, fig. 4D), which is the binding 
site for FLOWERING BHLH (FBH) transcription factors that 
activate CO transcription in A. thaliana (Ito et al. 2012). The </p>

<p>second most abundant motif (70Â) contains the extended 
DOF binding site (AAAGTG, fig. 4B) described earlier. The 
third motif identified (40Â) carries a core sequence (GGAC 
CA) that is bound by TCP transcription factors (Schommer 
et al. 2008; fig. 4C) and is part of the CMM. In order to 
investigate whether the identified cis-elements represent a 
novelty in CO promoters, the abundance of these elements 
was determined in CO, COL1 and COL2 promoters (À4 kb) 
from five Brassicaceae as well as subgroup Ia COL genes from 
six non-Brassicaceae species (fig. 4B-D). Available mRNA data 
for these COL genes indicated that they showed an expression 
pattern similar to COL1/2 of A. thaliana (Hecht et al. 2005, 
2007; Bohlenius et al. 2006; Almada et al. 2009; Gonz alez-
Schain et al. 2012; Hsu et al. 2012; Kloosterman et al. 2013). 
CO promoters contained significantly more DOF and TCP 
binding sites compared with the COL gene promoters of 
Brassicaceae COL genes as well as those from other species 
and significantly more than the CO promoters shuffle control 
(fig. 4B and C). Additionally, the CO promoters contained 
more E-Boxes compared with the shuffle control and non-
Brassicaceae COL promoters (fig. 4D) but were not signifi-
cantly different in this respect to COL1 and COL2 genes 
from the Brassicaceae. A significant enrichment of G-Boxes 
was detected in Brassicaceae CO promoters compared with 
the shuffle control (supplementary fig. S4C, Supplementary 
Material online), but no enrichment for LBSs and CCAAT </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>CO mRNA in LD </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
21 
24 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>CDM:pnos::LUC mRNA in LD </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
21 
24 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>CPM:pnos::LUC mRNA in LD </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
21 
24 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>CMM:pnos::LUC mRNA in LD </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 
12 
15 
18 
21 
24 </p>

<p>normalized expression </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Functional analysis of conserved sequences in the Arabidopsis thaliana CO promoter. (A) Diurnal expression pattern of CO mRNA in LD 
conditions in 10-day-old A. thaliana Col-0 seedlings. CO expression values were determined in the material used in (B) to (D) and represent the mean 
data from four biological replicates. Diurnal expression of LUC driven by Conserved Proximal Motif (CPM:pnos::LUC, #4, #7, B), Conserved Middle Motif 
(CMM:pnos::LUC, #1, #2, C), or Conserved Distal Motif (CDM:pnos::LUC, #2, #4, D) in LD conditions. Expression values were normalized to PP2A and the 
average of each experiment. Each data point represents the mean AE SD of two independent transgenic lines from two biological replicates. Position and 
composition of CPM, CMM, and CDM are explained in figure 4A and supplementary figure S6, Supplementary Material online. </p>



<p>Simon et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>Boxes (supplementary fig. S4B and D, Supplementary Material 
online). In conclusion, a significant increase in cis-element 
number between CO and COL promoters was always 
observed for DOF binding sites, TCP binding sites, and G-
Boxes. </p>

<p>Model for Evolution of CO Regulation by CDF 
Transcription Factors in the Brassicaceae Family </p>

<p>DOF binding sites are present in CPM, CMM, and CDM that 
confer a CO expression pattern and CDFs regulate the tran-
scription of CO in A. thaliana (Imaizumi et al. 2005; Sawa et al. 
2007; Fornara et al. 2009; fig. 5B-D). The cdf1-R, cdf2-1, cdf3-1, 
and cdf5-1 (cdf1235) quadruple mutant exhibits higher levels 
of CO mRNA (Fornara et al. 2009; supplementary fig. S7A and 
B, Supplementary Material online). To test how important 
CDFs and DOF binding sites are for discriminating CO from 
COL1/2 expression patterns, COL1 and COL2 transcript levels 
were tested in the cdf1235 quadruple mutant (supplementary 
fig. S7C-F, Supplementary Material online). No significant 
difference in the expression levels of these mRNAs was 
detected, indicating that, in contrast to CO, the COL1 and 
COL2 genes are not regulated by CDFs. These data suggest 
that CDF regulation of CO is either a novelty that arose in the 
Brassicaceae or that it was present in the last common ances-
tor of CO, COL1 and COL2 but was lost in COL1 and COL2 
during the process of subfunctionalization. 
Another indication that DOF regulation is a novelty asso-
ciated with the CO gene came from further comparison of the 
cdf1235 mutant and wt (Col-0). In wt A. thaliana, CO mRNA 
levels are efficiently downregulated in the morning to ensure 
the gene is not transcribed when plants are exposed to light 
early in the day. The CDFs contribute to this repression of CO, 
because in the cdf1235 mutant CO mRNA levels are generally 
higher (Fornara et al. 2009). However, if the cdf1235 mutant 
seedlings grown in LDs remain in darkness at subjective dawn, 
even higher CO mRNA levels are observed than if the plants 
are transferred to light (fig. 6A). This suggests that CO tran-
scription is also repressed at dawn by a second mechanism 
that is independent of CDFs but dependent on light. This 
light-dependent mechanism is not detected in wt plants 
because it is overridden by CDF activity that strongly represses 
CO transcription. A similar effect of light is detected for 
ThCOL mRNA (fig. 6B) as well as COL1 and COL2 (supple-
mentary fig. S8, Supplementary Material online; Ledger et al. 
2001). These data indicate that ThCOL, such as COL1 and 
COL2, is not repressed by CDF transcription factors at dawn 
but by exposure to light, and that this regulation can also be 
detected for the CO promoter if CDF activity is removed in 
the cdf1235 mutant. 
CO but not COL1/2 transcription is regulated by CDFs, 
raising the question of how this novelty arose. The number 
of DOF binding sites, which were shown to be bound by at 
least CDF1 (Sawa et al. 2007), increased during the evolution 
of the CO promoter based on the comparison with the pro-
moters of ThCOL and Brassicaceae COL1/2 genes (fig. 4B). 
However, a conserved region was identified 3 
0 of the coding 
sequence of subgroup Ia COL genes, and specifically in the </p>

<p>case of COL1 this sequence represents CDM found in the CO 
promoter (fig. 6C). Indeed, the 2 kb downstream of subgroup 
Ia COL genes is enriched in DOF binding sites, so that all of 
these loci contain between 1 and 3 such sites in the homo-
logous region (CDM; fig. 6C). Thus, the tandem duplication 
that led to COL1 and CO in the Brassicaceae introduced this 
sequence motif distally upstream of CO to form the CDM (fig. 
6D). This event placed DOF binding sites in the promoter of 
CO which probably influenced its mRNA expression pattern 
based on the functional analysis of deleted versions. Taken 
together the tandem duplication leading to CO in the 
Brassicaceae probably changed the transcriptional pattern 
of the gene by including sequences 3 
0 of the COL ancestor 
in the CO promoter. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Gene duplications are often associated with the evolution 
of novelties or range expansions (Ohno 1970; Soltis et al. 
2009; Levin 2011; Ramsey 2011). Such duplications can 
occur at the level of single genes or of whole genomes 
(Freeling 2009). In plants, WGDs have occurred many 
times and have been implicated in species diversification 
(Soltis et al. 2009; Schranz et al. 2012). The WGD At-a 
occurred prior to diversification of the core Brassicaceae 
(Vision et al. 2000; Bowers et al. 2003; Jiao et al. 2011; 
Haudry et al. 2013), around 30-40 Ma, and may have con-
tributed to the evolutionary success of these plants in a 
cooling climate during the Late Eocene (Bowers et al. 2003; 
Couvreur et al. 2010). This capacity to survive in cool con-
ditions likely also contributed to the range expansion of 
the core Brassicaceae into temperate and cold regions of 
central Asia as well as the Northern Hemisphere, where 
they are now predominately found (Couvreur et al. 
2010). Brassicaceae species are rare in the tropics, in con-
trast to their sister family, the Cleomaceae. Most plant 
species in temperate regions show responses to photoper-
iod, synchronizing key stages of their life cycle with the 
changing seasons and thereby adapting to extreme seaso-
nal fluctuations in their environment (Thomas and Vince-
Prue 1997). Photoperiodic control of flowering or of bud 
dormancy is proposed to be adaptive (Ray and Alexander 
1966; Bohlenius et al. 2006), and the expansion of the 
Brassicaceae into temperate regions extending to high lati-
tudes likely required the evolution of photoperiodic 
responses. Here we demonstrate that one of the key 
genes in the photoperiodic flowering response of the 
Brassicaceae, CO, evolved by tandem duplication in a simi-
lar time interval to At-a. Our data indicate that CO arose 
by tandem duplication of COL1 in the ancestor of the 
Brassicaceae and is thus, like the At-a, shared by 
Aethionemae but absent from the Cleomaceae species 
T. hassleriana. We show that the characteristic spatial 
and temporal transcriptional patterns of CO as well as 
the capacity of its protein product to efficiently activate 
transcription of the downstream gene FT evolved soon 
after the tandem duplication and prior to diversification 
of the core Brassicaceae and Aethionemae but after diver-
gence from the Cleomaceae. Therefore, efficient </p>

<p>2293 </p>

<p>Evolution of CONSTANS . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>promotion of flowering upon exposure to inductive long-
day stimuli likely arose in the Brassicaceae around the time 
they were exposed to a cooling climate. This conclusion is 
supported by the finding that a strong photoperiodic 
response is conserved between A. thaliana and Ae. arabi-
cum but weak in the non-Brassicaceae species T. hassleri-
ana that does not contain CO (Koevenig 1973; fig. 1B). 
Several models of gene retention after duplication have 
been proposed (Freeling 2009) and the history of several </p>

<p>duplicate genes has been followed in the Brassicaceae 
(Hanikenne et al. 2008; Hofberger et al. 2013; Vlad et al. 
2014). The duplication of CO was initially present in all 
Brassicaceae lineages after duplication, similar to what 
has been described for some genes involved in glucosino-
late biosynthesis and regulation (Hofberger et al. 2013). In 
the case of CO this is likely due to positive selection after 
neofunctionalization, because after duplication and diver-
gence of promoter and amino acid sequences, it appears to </p>

<p>CO mRNA </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 </p>

<p>CO/PP2A </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Col-0 Light 
Col-0 Dark 
cdf1235 Light 
cdf1235 Dark </p>

<p>ThCOL mRNA </p>

<p>Zeitgeber Time </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 </p>

<p>ThCOL/ACTIN </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>Light 
Dark </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Base sequence: T. hassleriana COL </p>

<p>A. thaliana CO </p>

<p>Ae. Arabicum CO </p>

<p>Ae. Arabicum COL2 </p>

<p>A. thaliana COL1 </p>

<p>A. thaliana COL2 </p>

<p>Gene </p>

<p>CONSTANS </p>

<p>♠ DOF </p>

<p>♠♠ 
♠ </p>

<p>COL ancestor 
+3.5kb 
-1.5kb 
♠♠ 
♠ </p>

<p>CONSTANS-LIKE 1 </p>

<p>duplication </p>

<p>♠ </p>

<p>♠ 
♠ </p>

<p>♠♠ 
♠ </p>

<p>♠♠ 
♠ </p>

<p>♠♠ 
♠ </p>

<p>♠♠ 
♠ </p>

<p>0bp 
-1kb 
+1kb 
+2kb 
+3kb </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>50% 
100% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>CDM </p>

<p>+1 </p>

<p>+1 </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Model for evolution of CO regulation by CDF transcription factors in the Brassicaceae family. CO (A) or ThCOL (B) mRNA levels in LD grown 
seedlings (Arabidopsis thaliana Col-0 compared with cdf1235, A) (Tarenaya hassleriana, B) either kept in light or moved to dark before lights on. 
Mean AE SD after normalization to PP2A for technical triplicates and a biological replicate gave similar results. (C) Pairwise alignment of subgroup Ia COL 
gene loci (À1.5 to 3.5 kb) from A. thaliana (CO, COL1, and COL2), Aethionema arabicum (AeCO, AeCOL2), and T. hassleriana (ThCOL) displayed as VISTA 
plot. Sequence similarity (%) was calculated in 100-bp sliding window while color indicates greater than 75% base identity. Blue color indicates protein 
coding region of CO as annotated in TAIR10. € indicates position of DOF binding sites (AAAGTG) in the conserved downstream region. (D) Model for 
the tandem duplication that led to COL1 and CO in the Brassicaceae. CO/COL1 gene body (À1.5 to +3.5 kb) became duplicated including conserved 
DOF binding sites in the downstream sequence of the ancestor (see C). In Brassicaceae CO promoters, this region overlaps with CDM (fig. 4A). </p>

<p>2294 </p>

<p>Simon et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>have provided a strong photoperiodic flowering response 
that was then frequently retained throughout the family. </p>

<p>Evolution of CO Protein Function </p>

<p>CO is a potent activator of flowering in A. thaliana (R edei 
1962; Putterill et al. 1995) and was the first identified member 
of a family of proteins that arose early during plant evolution, 
as indicated by their presence in algae and mosses (Zobell 
et al. 2005; Serrano et al. 2009). To compare the function of 
CO from A. thaliana with its closest homologs COL1 and 
COL2 as well as with orthologs from related species, all pro-
teins were expressed in A. thaliana co null mutants from the 
same promoters. Overexpression of these proteins from a 
phloem specific promoter (pSUC2) demonstrated that 
Brassicaceae COL1 and COL2 proteins as well as their putative 
ortholog from T. hassleriana (ThCOL) induced co-10 plants to 
flower earlier than wt, although slightly later than plants 
carrying pSUC2::3xHA:CO or pSUC2::3xHA:AeCO (fig. 3C). 
Therefore, when overexpressed in the appropriate cells all 
subgroup Ia COL genes tested can activate transcription of 
FT and induce flowering of A. thaliana, although CO proteins 
are the most effective. When the native CO promoter was 
used instead of pSUC2, the difference in activity between CO 
(CO and AeCO) and COL proteins (COL1, COL2, AeCOL2, 
ThCOL) was more pronounced, and most of the 
pCO::3xHA:COL transformants flowered later than wt plants 
(fig. 3D). Taken together these data demonstrate that when 
expressed in A. thaliana from the same promoters, CO pro-
teins are more effective at activating FT transcription and 
flowering than the most closely related COL proteins. 
Four amino acids were identified that were altered in the 
B-Boxes and CCT domains of all Brassicaceae CO proteins 
compared with the Brassicaceae COLs. These are functionally 
important domains of the protein based on analysis of avail-
able mutant alleles (Putterill et al. 1995; Robson et al. 2001). 
After divergence these amino acids are highly conserved in 
the CO and COL proteins of species in different Brassicaceae 
lineages, and are candidates for explaining the functional 
differences between these proteins. Interestingly, in three of 
four cases (AAs 49, 79 and 342; supplementary fig. S3A, 
Supplementary Material online) CO is the derived state 
when compared with B-Box and CCT domain proteins 
from other plant families (Griffiths et al. 2003; Khanna et al. 
2009; Gendron et al. 2012), suggesting that these changes 
contributed to a novel Brassicaceae-specific function of CO 
proteins compared with COLs. No effect of the S49A substi-
tution on CO protein function was found in a previous report, 
but the interpretation of this experiment was complicated by 
overexpression of the mutant form using the 35 S promoter 
(Kim et al. 2013) and changing all four amino acids might 
have a synergistic effect that is required to detect functional 
differences. </p>

<p>CO Promoter Conservation and Evolution </p>

<p>The temporal and spatial patterns of transcription of CO differ 
from those of COL1 and COL2. The temporal differences are 
maintained in all species tested in the core Brassicaceae and </p>

<p>Aethionemae, whereas the gene of T. hassleriana shows the 
temporal expression pattern of COL1/2. These results suggest 
that the ancestral gene at the root of the Brassicaceae family, 
prior to the diversification of the core Brassicaceae and 
Aethionemeae but after separation from Cleomaceae, 
showed a similar temporal pattern of expression to COL1/2. 
Thus evolutionary changes, particularly the CO/COL1 tandem 
duplication (fig. 6D), which occurred before radiation of the 
core Brassicaceae and the Aethionemae lineage, generated a 
novel transcriptional pattern characteristic of CO. Cis-regula-
tory regions responsible for the novel expression pattern of 
CO are conserved among all Brassicaceae species investigated 
and are not found in COL gene promoters (fig. 4A). 
The temporal expression pattern of CO is strongly shaped 
by CDFs (Imaizumi et al. 2005; Sawa et al. 2007; Fornara et al. 
2009). More DOF binding sites were found in the promoters 
of CO genes than in those of COL genes, and many of these 
sites are organized in clusters (CPM, CMM, and CDM). 
Interestingly, two conserved and functionally important clus-
ters have the same organization and combination of cis-ele-
ments but appear to have differing origins (fig. 4 and 
supplementary fig. S6, Supplementary Material online). The 
distal conserved cluster (CDM) shows homology with a con-
served region downstream of subgroup Ia COL genes and that 
we propose was introduced into the CO promoter as part of 
the tandem duplication that produced CO and COL1 (fig. 6C 
and D). A similar scenario in which 3 
0 -sequences of an ances-
tral gene contributed to the promoter of a tandemly dupli-
cated copy was previously described for tandemly duplicated 
MYB transcription factors in maize (Zhang et al. 2000), and 
may be a more general mechanism by which the transcrip-
tional patterns of tandemly duplicated copies diverge 
(Casneuf et al. 2006). The proximal and middle clusters 
(CPM and CMM) may have subsequently arisen to reinforce 
the transcriptional pattern of CO. How these evolved is 
unknown, but the G-Box element in CPM is also present in 
the proximal promoters of COL1 and COL2, indicating that 
the proximal promoter of the COL ancestral gene was mod-
ified to give rise to the CPM. The number of DOF binding sites 
in CPM varies among Brassicaceae species and even among 
A. thaliana accessions (supplementary fig. S6, Supplementary 
Material online; Rosas et al. 2014). The DOF binding sites in 
this region are multiples of the same sequence (ACACTTT) 
which may have originated from a single site by defective 
DNA replication or also by unequal crossing over. These var-
iations in the number of DOF binding sites in the proximal 
promoter probably affected its regulation (Rosas et al. 2014). 
Further examination of the role of classes of cis-elements in 
CO regulation such as the DOF binding sites or TCP motifs 
requires systematic site directed mutagenesis of all members 
of specific classes of motifs and the mutant versions could 
then be functionally tested in complementation assays. </p>

<p>Evolution of CO as a Photoperiod Sensor in 
Flowering Plants </p>

<p>We propose that the promoter of CO and the activity of its 
protein product coevolved to generate a photoperiodic </p>

<p>2295 </p>

<p>Evolution of CONSTANS . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>switch in the Brassicaceae. Tandem duplication of a COL gene 
produced the progenitors of COL1 and CO early in 
the diversification of the Brassicaceae family (fig. 6C and D). 
On the protein level, changes in the coding sequence of CO 
occurred after the duplication, causing the protein to be more 
potent in the promotion of FT transcription and acceleration 
of flowering. Furthermore, the tandem duplication created a 
novel CO promoter by bringing the gene under the control of 
sequences present at the 3 
0 -end of COL1. This arrangement is 
suggested to have initiated evolution of the characteristic 
temporal and spatial patterns of CO expression. These 
changes to CO transcription and protein function are pro-
posed to have produced a potent photoperiodic flowering 
switch that conferred an adaptive advantage contributing to 
the expansion of Brassicaceae species into cooler, temperate 
environments. 
The function of COL1 and COL2 as well as of the ancestral 
COL gene that gave rise to CO remains unclear. The high 
sequence conservation of CO, COL1, and COL2 suggested 
that these genes might be functionally redundant (Ledger 
et al. 2001). However, in contrast to CO, overexpression of 
COL1/2 from the ubiquitous 35 S promoter had no effect on 
flowering time, but altered circadian clock period length 
(Ledger et al. 2001; Kim et al. 2013). The failure of COL1 or 
COL2 to promote flowering when expressed from 35 S is 
probably caused by this promoter not being highly active in 
companion cells, because we detected clear acceleration of 
flowering when either protein was expressed from the SUC2 
or CO promoter. In wt plants, a strong role for COL1 and COL2 
in the promotion of flowering in response to LD under stan-
dard light conditions seems unlikely because the co-10 
mutant is almost unresponsive to LD, showing a similar phe-
notype to plants carrying null mutations of FT and the related 
gene TSF (Jang et al. 2009). Nevertheless, COL1/2 might pro-
mote flowering under specific environmental conditions such 
as particular wavelengths of light, different light intensities or 
under nonstandard growth temperatures. No loss of function 
mutants for COL1 or COL2 has been studied in detail prevent-
ing thorough analysis of their function in wt plants. 
Furthermore, the similarity of their temporal expression pat-
terns and protein sequences suggests that double mutants 
might be required to overcome functional redundancy. We 
are in the process of analyzing existing insertion alleles to 
determine whether they abolish activity of COL1 and COL2, 
and we are using CRISPR/Cas technology to generate true null 
alleles (Hyun et al. 2015). Nevertheless, at present whether 
these genes contribute to flowering-time control in wt plants 
remains unclear. Similarly, whether the ancestral COL gene 
that gave rise to CO had any effect on flowering time is 
unknown, although the observation that T. hassleriana is 
almost insensitive to photoperiod with respect to flowering 
time makes it less likely that the ancestral COL gene controlled 
photoperiodic responses. Reverse genetic analysis of the evo-
lutionarily related COL gene in T. hassleriana would allow 
analysis of whether it plays a role in flowering-time control. 
Genes related to CO regulate photoperiodic flowering in 
other plant families, and these are probably examples of con-
vergent evolution. In potato, COL genes have been implicated </p>

<p>in controlling the photoperiodic response of tuberization 
(Gonz alez-Schain et al. 2012). In particular, a subgroup Ia 
COL gene, S. tuberosum CO1 (StCO1), that acts in this process 
is also under control of a potato CDF gene (StCDF1.2) and 
exhibits a similar expression pattern to CO in A. thaliana 
(Kloosterman et al. 2013; Morris et al. 2013). Interestingly 
StCO1 is found in the context of a recent tandem duplication 
where it is located directly downstream of its closest ortholog 
(StCO2). Furthermore, as in the tandem duplication in A. 
thaliana, StCO2 is not regulated by StCDFs and shows a 
clear morning pattern of expression similar to COL1 and 
COL2 (Kloosterman et al. 2013; Morris et al. 2013). The com-
parison of potato StCO1/2 and A. thaliana CO/COL1 indicates 
that changes in expression pattern are tightly linked to 
tandem duplication events and suggests that these two occur-
rences arose independently. In the cereals rice and barley, 
OsHd1 and HvCO1 (the closest homologs of CO) are also 
expressed in a similar temporal pattern to A. thaliana CO 
and contribute to photoperiodic flowering (Yano et al. 2000; 
Hayama et al. 2003; Turner et al. 2005; Li et al. 2009; Campoli 
et al. 2012; Huang et al. 2012). There are no reports on regula-
tion of these genes by DOF transcription factors. Our results 
indicate that the transcriptional patterns of CO, OsHd1, and 
StCO1 are the result of convergent evolution and that these 
evolved independently to confer strong photoperiodic 
responses. Such a conclusion might also explain why in 
some families, such as legumes, CO-related genes do not 
appear to be involved in controlling photoperiodic flowering 
(Wong et al. 2014). CO genes might be particularly suited to 
confer photoperiodic flowering leading to their independent 
recruitment in different families. Their transcriptional and 
posttranslational regulation by light as well as their transcrip-
tional control by the circadian clock is highly appropriate for 
conferring responses to day length (Andr es and Coupland 
2012). In addition they encode transcription factors that can 
activate expression of FT gene homologs, which seem to trans-
duce the photoperiodic signal in all plants tested. This combi-
nation of attributes might result in the independent 
recruitment of CO-related genes and proteins as sensitive 
photoperiodic sensors in different families of flowering plants. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Plant Material and Growth Conditions </p>

<p>Arabidopsis thaliana plant material from the Col-0 accession 
includes co-10 (Laubinger et al. 2006) and the quadruple cdf1-
R cdf2-1 cdf3-1 cdf5-1 mutant (Fornara et al. 2009) as well as 
the co-2 mutant in the Ler accession (Koornneef et al. 1991). 
Experiments were performed on T. hassleriana (ES1100; 
Cheng et al. 2013) and Ae. arabicum (Bioproject Accession 
code PRJNA202984; Haudry et al. 2013). Flowering time mea-
surements were done on soil grown plants in controlled 
environment rooms under LD (16 h light/8 h dark) or SD 
(8 h light/16 h dark). </p>

<p>Plasmid Construction and Plant Transformation </p>

<p>Full length coding sequences (CDS) from COL1 (At5g15850), 
COL2 (At3g02380), AeCO (AA40G00516, v2.5, id23428), </p>

<p>2296 </p>

<p>Simon et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>AeCOL2 (AA10G00370, v2.5, id23428), and ThCOL 
(gb j ABD96940.1 j ) were amplified from cDNA made from 
A. thaliana (Col-0), Ae. arabicum or T. hassleriana and intro-
duced into SUC2::3xHA:GW and pCO::3xHA:GW (2.5 kb CO 
promoter) using GATEWAY (GW) technology. Both vectors 
were derived from pAlligator2 (Bensmihen et al. 2004; Jang 
et al. 2009). The NOS gene minimal promoter (pnos 105 bp; 
Shaw et al. 1984) was inserted into GW::LUC using HINDIII 
restriction sites to produce GW:pnos::LUC. Short motifs from 
CO promoter (Ler, CDM, À2,308 to -2,214 bp; CMM, À1,599 
to À1,428 bp; and CPM, À237 to À102 bp) were introduced 
into GW:pnos::LUC using GW technology. For complementa-
tion of co-2 mutation in A. thaliana, CO promoter fragments 
of 2.6 kb (À2,617 to À5 bp), 2.1 kb ( À2,075 to À5 bp), or 
0.6 kb (À621 to À5 bp) were introduced by GW technology 
into GW::GFP:CO (An et al. 2004) or GW::LUC (both pGreenII). 
For GUS expression analysis, promoters of COL1 (1,102 bp 
from ATG) and COL2 (1,105 bp from ATG) were introduced 
by GW recombination into pGreenII (GW::GUS). All 
plasmids for plant transformation were introduced into 
Agrobacterium strain GV3101 (pMP90RK) and transformed 
into Col-0, co-10 or co-2 plants by the floral dip method 
(Clough and Bent 1998). All pGreenII transgenic lines were 
selected using BASTA (Bayer CropScience). For pAlligator2 
transgenic lines, GFP-positive seeds were selected using a 
Leica MZFLIII stereomicroscope equipped with GFP filters. </p>

<p>DNA and Protein Sequences Used for Phylogenetic 
Reconstruction </p>

<p>Sequences for protein alignment were either identified by 
Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) search or pre-
dicted from genomic and cDNA sequencing data (Arabis 
alpina, Ae. arabicum, and C. papaya) and accession numbers 
can be found in supplementary table S2, Supplementary 
Material online. For the phylogenetic analysis of CO promoter, 
intergenic region of CO (including its start codon) and the 
upstream gene COL1 were used for analysis (except for ThCOL 
where no COL1 is present). Arabis alpina CO promoter was 
assembled from short reads identified by BLAST search of the 
preliminary genome assembly (MPIPZ, Cologne). Sequences 
were assembled using <rs id="software-10" type="software">SeqMan Pro</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">DNASTAR Lasergene</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-number">Version 8.0.2</rs>). CO Promoters from Capsella rubella, 
Nasturtium officinale, and Sisymbrium officinale were ampli-
fied from genomic DNA (kindly provided by Markus Berns, 
MPIPZ, Cologne) using degenerate primers that anchor in 
COL1 and CO, respectively (COL1 Fw: TGACACMGGATATG 
GAATTG; CO Rv: TGGCAGAGTGRACTTGAGCA). The inter-
genic region between COL1 and CO orthologs was subse-
quently sequenced by primer walk. The CO promoter of 
Ae. arabicum was identified by BAC (bacterial artificial chro-
mosome) screen using an CO probe (BAC probe Fw: ACTGGT 
GGTGGATCAAGAGG; Rv: TCTTGGGTGTGAAGCTGTTG) 
and sequenced by primer walk from two independent 
BACs. Accession numbers for CO promoters used in the 
alignment can be found in supplementary table S3, 
Supplementary Material online. For the comparison of cis-
element composition, 5 
0 -sequences (4,000 bp including the </p>

<p>start codon) were identified in publicly available genomes. 
Accession numbers are given in supplementary table S4, 
Supplementary Material online. The accession numbers for 
the comparison of whole loci can be found in supplementary 
table S5, Supplementary Material online. To obtain Ae. arabi-
cum, whole loci sequences paired-end next generation 
sequencing reads of Ae. arabicum genomic sequence 
(http://mustang.biol.mcgill.ca:8885/cgi-bin/hgGateway?org= 
A.+arabicum&amp;db=aa_4&amp;hgsid=1696, last accessed May 19, 
2015) were de novo assembled using <rs id="software-11" type="software">CLC Genomics 
Workbench</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">CLC Bio</rs>) with standard parameters. Desired 
genes (AeCO, AeCOL2) were subsequently identified in the 
Ae. arabicum genome running BLAST on a local database. </p>

<p>Bioinformatics Data Analysis Tools </p>

<p>Phylogenetic tree for relationship of subgroup Ia COL protein 
sequences was inferred using the Neighbor-Joining method in 
<rs id="software-12" type="software">MEGA</rs><rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-number">5</rs> with bootstrap values from 10,000 replicates (Saitou 
and Nei 1987; Tamura et al. 2007). Substitution rates were 
calculated from a codon alignment of the respective CDS 
followed by calculation of substitution rates corrected by 
Jukes-Cantor method using <rs id="software-13" type="software">SNAP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-13" type="version-number">v1.1.1</rs> (Rodrigo and 
Learn <rs corresp="#software-13" type="version-date">2001</rs>, Chapter 4, p. 55-72). CO promoter and COL 
locus alignments were performed using LAGAN algorithm 
on <rs id="software-14" type="software">mVISTA</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-14" type="creator">Mayor et al.</rs>. <rs corresp="#software-14" type="version-date">2000</rs>; Brudno et al. 2003). Output 
is displayed as conservation in per cent in 100-bp sliding 
windows to the corresponding reference sequence. 
Alignments are displayed using <rs id="software-15" type="software">ClustalX</rs> <rs corresp="#software-15" type="version-number">2.0.11</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-15" type="creator">Larkin et al.</rs>. 
<rs corresp="#software-15" type="version-date">2007</rs>). For motif identification in CO promoters, data sets 
were submitted to <rs id="software-16" type="software">MEME</rs> motif identification tool (<rs corresp="#software-16" type="version-number">Version 4.6</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-16" type="creator">Bailey and Elkan</rs> 1994) and searched for 6-10 bp motifs 
that can occur in any number. <rs id="software-17" type="software">WebLogo</rs> was used to present 
conserved motifs (<rs corresp="#software-17" type="version-number">Version 2.8.2</rs>; Crooks et al. 2004). For sta-
tistical comparison of cis-element number, the À 4 kb 
sequence beginning with the start codon was used from 
the indicated genes. Cis-elements were counted using custo-
mized Perl script (supplementary material, Supplementary 
Material online, Geo Velikkakam James, MPIPZ, Cologne). 
Shuffle control data sets were generated with the 
algorithm "shuffle" (100 times, Version 1.02, Press et al. 
2007, p. 281). To test for statistical differences in cis-element 
analysis and flowering time, one-way analysis of variance and 
Tukey test were performed using <rs id="software-18" type="software">SigmaStat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-18" type="version-number">3.5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-18" type="creator">Systat Software</rs>). </p>

<p>GUS Assay </p>

<p>GUS staining was performed as described earlier (Sieburth 
and Meyerowitz 1997). In brief, 14-day-old A. thaliana seed-
lings were vacuum infiltrated (10 min) and incubated in X-
Gluc solution at 37 
C for 4 h (pCO, pCOL1) or 12 h (pCOL2) 
and fixed in FAA (formaldehyde [3.7%], acetic acid [5%], 
ethanol [50%]) for 30 min. Plant material was destained 
using an ethanol series of 30%, 50%, and 70%. pCO control 
line was previously described (An et al. 2004). Images were 
taken with Leica MZFLIII stereomicroscope. </p>

<p>2297 </p>

<p>Evolution of CONSTANS . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

<p>Spatial Expression of LUC </p>

<p>Ten-day-old, LD grown seedlings of pnos::LUC transgenic lines 
(Col-0) were sprayed with Luciferin (2.5 mM) and chemilumi-
nescence was imaged with the Image Quant LAS4000 biomo-
lecular imager (GE Healthcare Life Sciences) for 15 min at high 
resolution. </p>

<p>Quantification of mRNA Expression </p>

<p>RNA was extracted from 10-day-old seedlings of A. thaliana 
(~25 seedlings per sampling), Ae. arabicum (~25 seedlings per 
sampling), and T. hassleriana (2-5 seedlings per sampling) 
grown in indicated light conditions (LD, SD, and LD + dark 
shift) using RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen). Samples were 
treated with Ambion DNase (life technologies) and 1.5-
3 mg of RNA was used for cDNA synthesis (SuperScript II 
Reverse Transcriptase; Invitrogen). Real time PCR was per-
formed using IQ SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad) on 
LightCycler480 (Roche) for the genes indicated (supplemen-
tary table S1, Supplementary Material online) using standard 
protocol (95 
C 5 min; [95 
C 20 s; 60 
C 20 s; 72 
C 20 s] 45Â) 
followed by melting curve. Data were normalized against 
arbitrary dilution series to check PCR efficiency. 
Concentrations were calculated as 2 </p>

<p>(cycle number) </p>

<p>. Values are 
normalized to PROTEIN PHOSPHATASE 2 A (PP2A) 
(AT1G69960) for A. thaliana and ACTIN for Ae. arabicum 
and T. hassleriana. For comparison of expression pattern, 
samples were additionally normalized to the mean of each 
data set (8 ZT values). Mean and standard deviation (SD) of 
two biological replicates were calculated. For dark shift experi-
ments and comparison of pCO::LUC to CDM:pnos::LUC, 
CMM:pnos::LUC and CPM:pnos::LUC, single biological repli-
cates are displayed as three technical replicates AE SD. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Supplementary tables S1-S5 and figures S1-S8 are available at 
Molecular Biology and Evolution online (http://www.mbe. 
oxfordjournals.org/). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank Eric Schranz, Geo Velikkakam James, and 
Markus Berns for providing material; Rafael Martinez-Gallegos 
and Tobias Gabriel for technical support; and Christiane 
Kiefer as well as Federico Valverde for critical comments on 
the manuscript. This work was supported by the International 
Graduate School for Development Health and Disease, 
Cologne, Germany, as well as by the Deutsche 
Forschungsgemeinschaft through SFB680 and the Cluster of 
Excellence in Plant Sciences (CEPLAS). The laboratory of G.C. 
receives a core grant from the Max Planck Society. Accession 
numbers can be found in supplementary tables S2-S5, 
Supplementary Material online. </p>





<p>Simon et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>









<p>Simon et al. . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>





<p>Evolution of CONSTANS . doi:10.1093/molbev/msv110 </p>

<p>MBE </p>

</text></tei>