<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4567174" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Nanoparticles have been widely used for nonviral gene delivery. Recently, cationic 
hybrid nanoparticles consisting of two different materials were suggested as a promising delivery 
vehicle. In this study, nanospheres with a poly(d,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid) (PLGA) core and 
cationic lipid shell were prepared, and the effect of cationic lipid concentrations on the properties 
of lipid polymer hybrid nanocarriers investigated. Lipid-polymer hybrid nanospheres (LPHNSs) 
were fabricated by the emulsion-solvent evaporation method using different concentrations 
of cationic lipids and characterized for size, surface charge, stability, plasmid DNA-binding 
capacity, cytotoxicity, and transfection efficiency. All LPHNSs had narrow size distribution with 
positive surface charges (ζ-potential 52-60 mV), and showed excellent plasmid DNA-binding 
capacity. In vitro cytotoxicity measurements with HEK293T, HeLa, HaCaT, and HepG2 cells 
also showed that LPHNSs exhibited less cytotoxicity than conventional transfection agents, such 
as Lipofectamine and polyethyleneimine-PLGA. As cationic lipid concentrations increased, 
the particle size of LPHNSs decreased while their ζ-potential increased. In addition, the in vitro 
transfection efficiency of LPHNSs increased as lipid concentration increased. 
Gene therapy has emerged as a potent therapeutic approach for numerous diseases, 
including cancer. 
1 Accordingly, gene therapy using traditional Chinese medicine, 
gene-delivery systems, and genetic engineering have been widely studied. However, 
the clinical success of gene therapy is still uncertain. 
2-4 In particular, designing efficient 
gene-delivery vectors with low cytotoxicity is considered a major challenge among 
scientists. 
5,6 In clinical trials, viral vectors that have been widely used as gene-delivery 
carriers have exhibited severe toxicity and caused side effects. 
1,2,7 Therefore, there is 
an increasing demand for the development of nonviral delivery vectors with the ability 
to overcome physiological barriers. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Among the various nonviral gene vectors, cationic lipids are ideal gene carriers 
because of their high transfection efficiency, excellent gene-incorporation ability, 
and ease of preparation. 
1,9 However, their clinical uses are limited, because of their 
instability and poor reproducibility caused by high batch-to-batch variation. 
10 Alter-
natively, biodegradable polymeric nanoparticles (NPs) have been investigated, due 
to their small particle size, ease of surface functionalization, excellent physiological 
stability, and sustained-release profiles. 
11 However, the low transfection efficiency of 
polymeric NPs has hindered their clinical success. </p>

<p>correspondence: hansoo Park 
Department of Integrative engineering, 
chung-ang University, 202 -4th Floor, 
221 heukseok-dong, Dongjak-gu, 
seoul 156-756, south Korea 
Tel +82 2 820 5804 
Fax +82 2 814 2651 
email heyshoo@cau.ac.kr </p>

<p>soo-hong lee 
Department of Biomedical science, 
college of life science, cha University, 
335 Pangyo-ro, Bundang-gu, seongnam, 
gyeonggi-do 463-400, south Korea 
Tel +82 31 8017 9415 
Fax +82 31 8017 9892 
email soohong@cha.ac.kr </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
2 September 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5368 </p>

<p>Bose et al </p>

<p>Therefore, there is an increasing demand for a hybrid 
vector to overcome the barriers associated with conventional 
gene carriers. 
12 Recently, lipid-polymer hybrid nanospheres 
(LPHNSs) were designed to achieve complementary benefits 
of liposomes and polymeric NSs. 
13-15 They were designed 
to have a biodegradable polymer core and lipid layers. </p>

<p>14,16 </p>

<p>Depending on their application, specific fabrication methods 
have been reported. 
17 In the past, LPHNSs were prepared by 
two-step methods that required introducing lipid vesicles 
into preformed polymeric NSs. 
18 However, this method 
is inefficient, because of practical difficulties and process 
complexity. 
12 Alternatively, a single-step fabrication method 
was developed, which combined the fabrication process 
of emulsion-solvent evaporation with the self-assembly of 
lipids. 
15 Although successful outcomes have been achieved 
using the single-step method, a better understanding of the 
parameters involved in the fabrication process is required in 
order to significantly improve the design and fabrication of 
LPHNSs. 
19,20 Specifically, cationic lipids forming outer shells 
could allow for superior gene-delivery capabilities. However, 
it is still not clear how lipid concentration affects the forma-
tion of LPHNSs. Furthermore, it is important to balance the 
amount of lipids, because despite being a key factor for DNA 
delivery, a high concentration of cationic lipids could result 
in cytotoxicity. Therefore, in order to optimize their perfor-
mance, it is necessary to understand the influence of cationic 
lipid concentration on various properties of LPHNSs. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>The present study describes a simple and efficient method 
for fabrication of LPHNSs, and examined the influence of 
cationic lipid concentration on the structural and functional 
characteristics of LPHNSs. We rationally designed LPHNS 
formulations with four different ratios of cationic lipids to 
polymer during the fabrication step. Then, the LPHNSs were 
compared with various controls, including poly(d,l-lactic-
co-glycolic acid) (PLGA), liposomes, and polyethyleneimine 
(PEI)-PLGA NSs. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Materials </p>

<p>PLGA (50:50) (Resomer 
® RG 502 H, molecular weight 
7,000-17,000) was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Co 
(St Louis, MO, USA). Cationic lipid 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-
3-trimethylammonium-propane (chloride salt) and fluorescent 
lipid 1-oleoyl-2-[12-[(7-nitro-2-1,3-benzoxadiazol-4-yl) 
amino]dodecanoyl]-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine] (NBD-PC) 
were purchased from Avanti Polar Lipids (Alabaster, AL, 
USA). Lipofectamine 2000 was obtained from Life Technolo-
gies Korea (Seoul, South Korea). TE buffer (10 mM Tris/HCl, </p>

<p>pH 8.0, 1 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid) was purchased 
from Cosmo Genetech (Seoul, South Korea). Plasmid EGFP 
(pEGFP) was obtained from Clontech (Palo Alto, CA, USA), 
and the plasmids were amplified in Escherichia coli and puri-
fied using a Qiagen Plasmid Giga Kit (Qiagen NV, Venlo, 
the Netherlands). Polyvinyl alcohol (PVA; molecular weight 
13-23 kDa), Protamine sulfate, rhodamine (Rho), and all 
other chemicals were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich. </p>

<p>lipid-polymer hybrid nanosphere 
preparation and characterization </p>

<p>The four sets of LPHNSs were prepared as described previ-
ously by the modified double-emulsion solvent-evaporation 
method with self-assembly. 
20 Briefly, protamine sulfate 
(10 µg/mL) was dissolved in aqueous solution. The cationic 
lipid (1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-
propane (chloride salt) [DOTAP]) and PLGA (3% w/v) were 
dissolved in dichloromethane. The water-in-oil emulsion was 
formed by the addition of an aqueous phase into an organic 
phase with sonication (ultrasonic probe; Sonics &amp; Materials 
Inc, Newtown, CT, USA). The primary emulsion was trans-
ferred to 1% w/v PVA aqueous solution and sonicated in an ice 
bath. The resultant secondary (water in oil in water) emulsion 
was stirred overnight at room temperature until evaporation 
of dichloromethane was complete. The final formulated 
LPHNSs were collected by ultracentrifugation at 20,000 rpm 
for 30 minutes (Optima L-100 XP Ultra Centrifuge; Beckman 
Coulter, Brea, CA, USA). Then, they were washed three times 
by a repeating centrifugation step and freeze-dried at -20°C 
for 48 hours. At least three batches were prepared for each 
formulation. To investigate the influence of cationic lipid 
concentrations on size, charge, and in vitro performance, we 
prepared four formulation groups of LPHNSs with different 
concentrations of cationic lipid (DOTAP) to polymer ratio, 
as shown in Table 1. All other parameters were kept constant. 
PLGA NSs were also fabricated as described and used to 
prepare the PEI-PLGA NSs for comparison. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Preparation of fluorescent lipid-polymer 
hybrid nanospheres </p>

<p>Fluorescent (NBD-PC lipid and Rho-PLGA) NSs were 
prepared using the same modified solvent evaporation 
with self-assembly procedure with few changes. 
23 Briefly, 
200 µL of a 1 mg/mL of Rho B solution was added to the 
polymer-solvent mixture (3% w/v of polymer) with 0.5 mg of 
NBD-PC and DOTAP (24% w/w to polymer). The resultant 
water-in-oil emulsion was processed in the same way as the 
aforementioned procedure. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5369 </p>

<p>Influence of lipid concentration on LPHNS properties </p>

<p>characterization of hybrid nanospheres </p>

<p>The mean particle diameter (z-average) and size distribution 
(polydispersity index) of LPHNSs and LPHNS-plasmid 
DNA (pDNA) complexes were determined by dynamic light 
scattering (DLS) using a Zetasizer Nano ZS (Malvern Instru-
ments, Malvern, UK), and the surface charge of the LPHNSs 
and LPHNS-pDNA complexes was determined by analysis 
of the ζ-potential as described previously. 
24,25 Both types of 
measurements were performed at 25°C using deionized water 
and repeated three times for each sample (50 µg/L). The 
shape and surface morphology of the LPHNSs were initially 
investigated by field-emission scanning electron microscopy 
(FESEM; JSM-6700F; JEOL, Tokyo, Japan) at an accelerat-
ing voltage of 5 kV. For the sample preparation, one drop of 
the NS dispersion was drop casted on a carbon tape supported 
by the stub, and the water was evaporated under reduced pres-
sure. Thin layers of dried particle were sputter coated with 
platinum by an Auto Fine Coater (JEOL) for 30 seconds at 
30 mA. The core-shell structures of LPHNSs and LPHNS-
pDNA complexes were further confirmed by energy-filtered 
transmission electron microscopy (EFTEM). 
26 EFTEM 
experiments were carried out with a Libra 120 microscope 
(Carl Zeiss Meditec AG, Jena, Germany), and samples were 
prepared by depositing 20 µL of LPHNS suspension (0.5 mg/ 
mL) onto a 200-mesh carbon-coated copper grid. Samples 
were blotted away after 30 minutes' incubation, and grids were 
negatively stained with freshly prepared and sterile-filtered 
2% (w/v) uranyl acetate aqueous solution. The grids were then 
washed twice with distilled water and air-dried prior to imag-
ing. The core-shell hybrid structure of LPHNSs was further 
confirmed by a confocal laser scanning microscopy (CLSM; 
Carl Zeiss LSM 510 Meta) with fluorescent LPHNSs. </p>

<p>Formation of lPhNs-pDNa complexes 
and gel retardation assay </p>

<p>LPHNS-pDNA complexes were prepared using 1 µg of 
pDNA mixed with the resuspended freeze-dried LPHNS 
group (A, B, C, and D) at different ratios of NSs to pDNA </p>

<p>(LPHNS:pDNA 15:1, 30:1, 60:1, and 90:1 w/w, respec-
tively) in nuclease-free deionized water. The mixture was 
incubated at room temperature for 30 minutes to allow 
for LPHNS-pDNA complex formation. After incubation, 
the LPHNS-pDNA complexes were diluted in serum-free 
medium (Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium [DMEM]). 
The incorporation efficiency of each LPHNS group (A, B, 
C, and D) was verified by gel retardation assay. 
27 For the 
assay, we prepared LPHNS-pDNA complexes from each 
experimental group (A, B, C, and D) by mixing 15, 30, 60, 
and 90 µg of LPHNSs with 1 µg of pDNA and incubating 
them for 30 minutes at room temperature. After 30 minutes, 
5 µL of each group of LPHNS-pDNA complexes was mixed 
with 1 µL of loading buffer (0.25% w/w bromophenol blue 
in TE buffer) and applied to 1% agarose gel. Electrophoresis 
was carried out at 100 V for 20 minutes at room temperature 
in 0.5× TAE buffer. The gels were stained with ethidium 
bromide solution (10 mg/mL) for DNA visualization. Images 
were captured by a gel documentation system (GDS-200 D; 
Korea Lab Tech, Seongnam, Korea). Similarly, to investigate 
the supportive role of protamine, we fabricated LPHNSs 
(DOTAP 24% w/w) without protamine for comparison. </p>

<p>cell cultures and transfection </p>

<p>HEK293, HeLa, HepG2, and HaCaT cells were obtained 
from the American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA, 
USA) and cultured at 37°C and 5% CO 2 in DMEM supple-
mented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 1% penicillin 
(5,000 U/mL)-streptomycin (5,000 U/mL). For LPHNS 
transfections, HEK293, HeLa, HaCaT, and HepG2 cells were 
seeded in 24-well plates at a density of 6×10 
4 cells per well in 
0.5 mL DMEM (GE Healthcare Bio-Sciences AB, Uppsala, 
Sweden) supplemented with 10% FBS for 24 hours to reach 
approximately 60%-80% confluence before transfection. 
For the transfection experiment, the cells was cultured with 
serum-free medium (0.5 mL) and incubated with each group 
for 4 hours. Then, the medium was replaced with serum con-
taining medium and incubated for 48 hours. After 48 hours of </p>

<p>Table 1 Physical characterizations of lPhNss </p>

<p>Formulation groups 
z-average (nm) 
PDI 
ζ-potential (mV) </p>

<p>Bare Plga 
247±12.8 
0.173±0.024 
-24±2.5 
group a (6% w/w DOTaP) 
209±10.4** 
0.08±0.018 
36±5.4*** 
group B (12% w/w DOTaP) 
186±7.9*** 
0.07±0.015 
49±2.3*** 
group c (18% w/w DOTaP) 
163±5.6*** 
0.08±0.008 
57±2.5*** 
group D (24% w/w DOTaP) 
154±5.2*** 
0.09±0.005 
64±3.2*** </p>

<p>Notes: experimental groups compared with control; differences with P-values less than 0.05 were considered significant: **P,0.01, ***P,0.001. Data are presented as 
mean ± standard error of the mean (seM). 
Abbreviations: lPhNss, lipid-polymer hybrid nanospheres; PDI, polydispersity index; Plga, poly(D,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid); w/w, weight/weight; DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-
octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane (chloride salt). </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5370 </p>

<p>Bose et al </p>

<p>incubation, transfected cells were examined by fluorescence 
microscopy (Leica Microsystems, Wetzlar, Germany), and the 
fluorescence intensity was quantified by C6 flow cytometry 
(Accuri™ C6; BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA) and 
analyzed under excitation and emission wavelengths of 488 
and 520 nm, respectively. The autofluorescence of untreated 
cells was used as an internal control. Forward and side light-
scatter gates were set to exclude dead cells, debris, and cell 
aggregates. At least 10,000 events were acquired and analyzed 
per sample. To calculate the relative transfection efficiency of 
LPHNSs, all experiments were designed to compare LPHNS 
groups with Lipofectamine 2000. PEI-PLGA NSs were used 
as a positive control, and pDNA alone was used as the nega-
tive control. Lipofectamine-pDNA complexes were prepared 
according to manufacturer's instructions and equalized to 
our experimental conditions by optimizing the concentration 
(1-2.5 µL with 1 µg of DNA). Similarly, PEI-PLGA-pDNA 
complexes were prepared by a mixing (90:1 w/w) ratio. The 
cell experiment in this study was done in the CHA University. 
All the immortalized human cell lines were purchased from 
ATCC and have been subcultured with the approval of the 
Ethics Committee at CHA University. </p>

<p>cellular uptake and intracellular release 
study </p>

<p>The cellular uptake and intracellular release behaviors of 
the LPHNS groups (A, B, C, and D) were investigated as 
described previously. 
28 HeLa cells were seeded in 24-well </p>

<p>plates at a density of 6×10 
4 cells per well in 0.5 mL DMEM </p>

<p>supplemented with 10% FBS to reach approximately 
60%-80% confluence. After 24 h, fluorescently labeled Rho 
LPHNSs (90 µg) with different cationic lipid-concentration 
groups (A, B, C, and D) were added into the culture medium. 
Following various incubation times of 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 12, 
and 24 hours, the cells were washed twice with phosphate-
buffered saline (PBS), trypsinized, and quantified by flow 
cytometry. Initially, a threshold of fluorescence was gener-
ated using HeLa cells without exposure to the LPHNSs as a 
control sample. The autofluorescence of untreated cells was 
used as an internal control. Forward and side light-scatter 
gates were set to exclude dead cells, debris, and cell aggre-
gates. At least 10,000 events were acquired and analyzed per 
sample. All events corresponding to the control sample were 
located at intensities below this threshold. The number of 
cells carrying Rho LPHNSs was found from the area match-
ing the events located at higher intensities than the threshold. 
The cellular uptake ratio was calculated as follows: </p>

<p>Number of events over the threshold 
Total number of events 
×1 100% 
(1) </p>

<p>Further, the cellular uptake and intracellular behaviors of 
LPHNSs with different surface coatings were studied in HeLa 
cells with CLSM (LSM 510) using fluorescently labeled 
Rho LPHNSs. The PEI-modified PLGA NSs were used as 
controls. 
28 In brief, HeLa cells were plated on coverslips 
in 24-well plates (cell density 6×10 
4 cells/well) and main-
tained in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS at 37°C in a 
humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO 2 for 1 day. Then, 
fluorescent Rho LPHNSs (90 µg) with different cationic 
lipid-concentration surface coatings were added to the cells 
and incubated for 12 hours at 37°C. The cells were washed 
with PBS and fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde solution in 
PBS and washed three times, and the nuclei were stained with 
5 µL of DAPI (4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole; 1 µg/mL) for 
1-2 minutes at room temperature and washed. Finally, the 
cells were mounted and observed using CLSM. </p>

<p>cytotoxicity assay </p>

<p>The cytotoxicity of LPHNS-pDNA complexes were evalu-
ated using HEK293, HeLa, HaCaT, and HepG2 cells by 
CCK-8 assay. 
29 Cells were seeded in a 24-well plate at a 
density of 6×10 
4 cells/mL. After incubation for 24 hours, 
the medium was exchanged with 0.5 mL of culture medium 
containing 90 µg of LPHNS-pDNA complexes (90:1 w/w) 
from each group. Lipofectamine 2000 and PEI-PLGA NSs 
were used as control groups. After incubation for 48 hours, the 
medium was replaced with fresh medium. CCK-8 solution (10 
µL) was added to each well, followed by incubation for 1 hour 
at 37°C. Then, the absorbance at 450 nm was measured by 
a VersaMax ELISA Microplate Reader (Molecular Devices 
LLC, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). Cell viability was expressed as 
a percentage based on control (untreated) cells. Additionally, 
CCK-8 assays were performed with HEK293 cells for groups 
with different concentrations (15, 30, 60, and 90 µg). </p>

<p>short-term stability testing </p>

<p>Stability is a crucial factor affecting the practicality of hybrid NS 
formulations. For stability testing, three batches of each LPHNS 
group (A, B, C, and D) and bare PLGA were stored in transpar-
ent glass vials at 4°C. The particle sizes of the experimental 
groups were used to determine the stability by DLS (Nano ZS), 
and measurements were taken at selected time intervals. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>At least three independent sets of experiments for each con-
dition were performed in triplicate. Data were pooled, and </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5371 </p>

<p>Influence of lipid concentration on LPHNS properties </p>

<p>are statistically expressed in terms of means and standard 
deviation. Analysis of variance was used for analysis of 
quantitative values, and the Bonferroni post hoc test was used 
for comparisons among groups. Differences were considered 
significant at P,0.05. The <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> software package (ver-
sion 5.02; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc</rs>, La Jolla, CA, USA) was 
used to perform the statistical tests. </p>

<p>Results and discussion </p>

<p>In the past few decades, numerous nanocarriers have been 
developed for safe and efficient gene delivery. 
30 We aimed 
to develop a simple and efficient hybrid nanocarrier as a 
nonviral gene-delivery vehicle, which has the complementary 
features of both liposome and polymeric NSs. We synthe-
sized relatively monodisperse core-shell LPHNSs (Figure 
1), consisting of a positively charged cationic lipid (DOTAP) 
with a protamine layer forming the outer shell and an inner 
spherical PLGA core. The LP HNSs were fabricated by 
modifying the double-emulsion solvent-evaporation process 
by allowing lipids and protamine to self-assemble on the 
surface of a polymer core. 
14,20 Protamine was used as the con-
densing agent. 
31 In this study, four different concentrations </p>

<p>of lipids with constant protamine were used to construct 
LPHNSs, and their properties and transfection efficiencies 
were compared. </p>

<p>Influence of cationic lipid concentration 
on size and size distribution of lPhNss </p>

<p>In order to study the influence of cationic lipid concentra-
tion on LPHNS properties, LPHNSs with different con-
centrations of lipids were prepared using different ratios 
of cationic lipid to polymer in the organic phase, with a 
constant amount of protamine (10 µg/mL) in the aqueous 
phase. As shown in Table 1, it was observed that the mean 
diameters (z-average sizes) of LPHNSs with cationic lipid 
concentrations of 6% w/w (group A), 12% w/w (group B), 
18% w/w (group C), and 24% w/w (group D) were 
209±10.4, 186±7.3, 163±5.6, and 154±5.2 nm, respec-
tively. DLS analysis revealed that there was a significant 
size reduction (Figures 2A, S1) compared to bare PLGA 
NSs (247±12.8 nm), which could be explained by the 
fact that the processing of those particles in a single step 
was stabilized by the function of the lipids with PVA. </p>

<p>15,20 </p>

<p>It was also found that there was a decrease in particle size </p>

<p>Figure 1 schematic diagram of lPhNs nanoparticles as gene-delivery vectors. 
Notes: LPHNSs that consisted of DOTAP-protamine-PLGA for efficient gene delivery were fabricated by emulsion-solvent evaporation with a self-assembly process. 
The superior cationic charges of lPhNss assisted to form a complex with pDNa and enhance condensation ability, which facilitated the higher cellular uptake and 
intracellular release of pDNa. The scale represents 100 µm. 
Abbreviations: lPhNs, lipid-polymer hybrid nanosphere; pDNa, plasmid DNa; Plga, poly(d,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid); DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-
trimethylammonium-propane (chloride salt); PVa, polyvinyl alcohol; w/w, weight/weight. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5372 </p>

<p>Bose et al </p>

<p>Figure 2 (Continued) </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5373 </p>

<p>Influence of lipid concentration on LPHNS properties </p>

<p>(209-154 nm) as the lipid concentrations increased in the 
organic phase from 6% to 24% w/w (lipid-to-polymer 
weight ratio). The concentration of cationic lipids could play 
a significant role in controlling the size of LPHNSs, pos-
sibly reducing the coalescence of particles. 
32 Furthermore, 
it was found that the higher lipid concentration (24% w/w 
DOTAP) with constant protamine considerably decreased 
LPHNS-pDNA complex size (z-average) than the less lipid 
group (6% w/w DOTAP). The synergistic effect of cationic 
lipid and protamine could have been the possible reason, 
as observed in earlier studies. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Influence of cationic lipid concentration 
on surface charge of lPhNss </p>

<p>Surface charge is an important indication of the stability of 
a colloidal system in a particular medium. 
34 We investigated 
the influence of cationic lipid concentrations on LPHNS 
surface charge (Figures 2B, S1). As expected, the inclusion 
of cationic lipids changed the surface charges of the par-
ticles. All LPHNSs had positive charges compared with the 
negative charge of bare PLGA NSs (-24±4 mV). As shown 
in Table 1, the ζ-potentials of LPHNSs with cationic lipid 
concentrations of 6% w/w (group A), 12% w/w (group B), </p>

<p>Rhodamine 
PLGA NSs </p>

<p>0.5 µm 
0.5 µm </p>

<p>0.5 µm 
0.5 µm </p>

<p>NBD-PC </p>

<p>DOTAP 18% </p>

<p>DOTAP 12% 
DOTAP 6% </p>

<p>DOTAP 24% </p>

<p>Core-shell 
(merged) </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Figure 2 characterizations of lPhNss. 
Notes: Influence of cationic lipid concentration on size and surface charge of LPHNSs. LPHNS size analysis by DLS (A). surface-charge (ζ-potentials) measurement by Dls (B). 
Differences with P-values of less than 0.05 were considered significant. **P,0.01, ***P,0.001. FeseM and eFTeM images of bare Plga Nss and core-shell structure of lipid 
Plga-hybrid Nss (C). eFTeM images of lPhNss fabricated with different DOTaP concentrations (6%-24% w/w). Inner arrow explained for Plga core and outer arrow 
explained for lipid shell. (D). Visualization of core-shell structure of lPhNss by clsM (E). rhodamine Plga (red) and NBD-Pc (green). scale bar 0.5 µm. 
Abbreviations: LPHNS, lipid-polymer hybrid nanosphere; DLS, dynamic light scattering; FESEM, field-emission scanning electron microscopy; EFTEM, energy-filtered 
transmission electron microscopy; Plga, poly(d,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid); DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane (chloride salt); clsM, confocal laser 
scanning microscopy; NBD-Pc, 1-oleoyl-2-[12-[(7-nitro-2-1, 3-benzoxadiazol-4-yl)amino]dodecanoyl]-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine; w/w, weight/weight; Nss, nanospheres. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5374 </p>

<p>Bose et al </p>

<p>18% w/w (group C), and 24% w/w (group D) were 36±3, 
50±1.8, 57±2.2, and 64±2 mV, respectively. However, the 
addition of negatively charged pDNA to the LPHNSs led 
to a slight charge reduction, as shown in Figure 3C. Con-
sidering that the surface area of LPHNSs decreased with 
increasing concentration, which might lead to a decrease in 
the incorporation of cationic lipids, an increase in the surface 
charges with increasing lipid concentration was unexpected. </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>We believe that this finding will help with the optimization 
of LPHNSs for the purpose of transfection and delivery of 
multiple bioactive molecules in the future. </p>

<p>Influence of cationic lipid concentration 
on lPhNs morphology </p>

<p>The overall structure of the NSs was examined to ensure 
that they were hybrid particles of lipid and a polymeric </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>270 </p>

<p>240 </p>

<p>210 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>150 
15/1 
30/1 
60/1 
90/1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA complex ratio (w/w) </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (6% DOTAP) size </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (12% DOTAP) size </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (18% DOTAP) size </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (24% DOTAP) size </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (6% DOTAP)-ζ </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (12% DOTAP)-ζ </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (18% DOTAP)-ζ </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (24% DOTAP)-ζ </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA complexes-
size (nm) 
LPHNSs:pDNA complexes 
ζ-potential (mV) </p>

<p>p D </p>

<p>N 
A 
l a d d e r </p>

<p>1 5 : 1 
3 0 : 1 
6 0 : 1 </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (w/w) (without protamine) </p>

<p>9 0 : 1 
1 2 0 : 1 
1 5 : 2 
3 0 : 2 
6 0 : 2 
9 0 : 2 
1 2 0 : 2 </p>

<p>p D </p>

<p>N 
A 
l a d d e r </p>

<p>1 5 : 1 
3 0 : 1 
6 0 : 1 </p>

<p>Group A 
G roup B 
G roup C 
G roup D </p>

<p>LPHNSs:pDNA (w/w) (with protamine) </p>

<p>9 0 : 1 
1 5 : 1 
3 0 : 1 
6 0 : 1 
9 0 : 1 
1 5 : 1 
3 0 : 1 
6 0 : 1 
9 0 : 1 
1 5 : 1 3 0 : 1 6 0 : 1 
9 0 : 1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 3 gel retardation assay and Dls analysis for lPhNs-pDNa complex formation. 
Notes: lPhNs-pDNa complexes (without protamine) (A). lane 1, pDNa ladder; lanes 2-5 (lipid Plga Ns:pDNa ratios of 15:1, 30:1, 60:1, 90:1, and 120:1 (w/w), 
respectively; lanes 6-10 (lipid Plga Ns:pDNa ratios of 15:2, 30:2, 60:2, 90:2, and 120:2 (w/w), respectively. lPhNs-pDNa ternary complex (with protamine) (B). lane 1, 
control, lPhNs-pDNa complex (fabricated with different DOTaP concentrations [groups a-D having 6%-24% w/w of DOTaP]); lanes 2-5, group a (DOTaP 6%) 
with lPhNs:pDNa ratios of 15:1, 30:1, 60:1, and 90:1 w/w, respectively; lanes 6-9, group B (DOTaP 12%) with lPhNs:pDNa ratios of 15:1, 30:1, 60:1, and 90:1 w/w, 
respectively; lanes 10-13, group c (DOTaP 18%) with lPhNs:pDNa ratios of 15:1, 30:1, 60:1, and 90:1 w/w, respectively); lanes 14-17, group D (DOTaP 24%) with 
lPhNs:pDNa ratios of 15:1, 30:1, 60:1, and 90:1 w/w, respectively). Dls analysis of lPhNs-pDNa complexes for size and surface-charge (ζ-potentials) changes (C). results 
shown as means ± standard error of mean (n=3). 
Abbreviations: Dls, dynamic light scattering; lPhNs, lipid-polymer hybrid nanosphere; pDNa, plasmid DNa; w/w, weight/weight; Ns, nanosphere; Plga, poly(d,l-lactic-
co-glycolic acid); DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane (chloride salt). </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5375 </p>

<p>Influence of lipid concentration on LPHNS properties </p>

<p>core, rather than a random combination of liposomes and 
unprotected PLGA NPs. As shown in Figure 2C and D, 
FESEM and EFTEM showed that all formulation groups 
(A, B, C, and D) exhibited the perfect HNS size (~150-250 nm). 
The particle size observed from the EFTEM image was in 
agreement with that determined by DLS (Figures 2A, S1). 
Further, EFTEM confirmed the formation of an HNS con-
sisting of a PLGA core covered by a thin lipid monolayer. 
The negative staining further confirmed the core-shell 
structure of LPHNSs. Additionally, EFTEM confirmed the 
particle-size reduction (~209-154 nm) when the lipid con-
centration was increased from 6% to 24% w/w. It appeared 
that 6% DOTAP was unable to control the NS aggrega-
tion, whereas 24% w/w DOTAP effectively controlled 
the aggregation. We speculated that the DOTAP played 
a synergistic role as a stabilizer of PVA more efficiently 
at higher concentrations than at lower concentrations. To 
visualize the core-shell structure and lipid assembly further, 
two different fluorescent dyes -NBD-PC (0.5 mg/mL) with 
DOTAP and Rhodamine (1 mg/mL) with PLGA -were 
used to synthesize fluorescent LPHNSs and examined using 
confocal microscopy. The fluorescence image in Figure 2E 
clearly illustrates the self-assembly process of the lipid-
polymer core-shell structure by forming a uniform green 
fluorescence on a red fluorescence from the surface of the 
inner core. Furthermore, EFTEM clearly shows the dif-
ference between LPHNSs and LPHNS-pDNA complexes 
(Figure S2). </p>

<p>Influence of cationic lipid concentration 
on lPhNs-DNa complexes and 
transfection efficiency </p>

<p>The binding ability of the cationic LPHNSs to the polyan-
ionic pDNA (pEGFP) was studied using electrophoresis, 
DLS, and microscopic analysis. 
36 It has been proven that 
the condensation of DNA is important for the protection 
of DNA from enzymatic degradation, as well for allowing 
easy entry into the nucleus. The LPHNS-pDNA complexes 
were prepared as described in the Materials and methods 
section. As shown in Figure 3A, with increasing cationic 
lipid (DOTAP) concentration in the LPHNS formulation, 
DNA-incorporation efficiency increased. When the DOTAP 
lipid concentration was increased from 6% to 24% w/w, the 
pDNA-incorporation ability improved significantly (results 
not shown). However, the NS-pDNA ratio played a crucial 
role in DNA incorporation, and it was observed that at higher 
LPHNS particle concentrations (.130 µg), 1 µg of pDNA 
was retained. However, at such a high NS concentration, 
cytotoxicity increased and cell viability decreased below 
80% (results not shown). On the other hand, less than 100 µg 
of LPHNS particle concentration (,100 µg) was unable 
to compact the pDNA completely, as shown in Figure 3A. 
Therefore, we included protamine in the LPHNSs during the 
fabrication process (Figure 1). Incorporation of protamine 
in the LPHNS formulation resulted in strong pDNA binding 
and retention in all LPHNS-formulation groups (A, B, C, 
and D) at various NS concentrations (15, 30, 60, and 90 µg) </p>

<p>Figure 4 (Continued) </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5376 </p>

<p>Bose et al </p>

<p>Lipofectamine </p>

<p>PEI-PLGA-pDNA </p>

<p>LPHNSs-pDNA 
(6% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs-pDNA 
(12% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs-pDNA 
(18% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs-pDNA 
(24% DOTAP) </p>

<p>HEK293 
HeLa 
HaCaT 
HepG2 
Transfection efficiency (%) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
HEK293 
HeLa 
HaCaT 
HepG2 </p>

<p>** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Lipofectamine-pDNA </p>

<p>PEI-PLGA-pDNA </p>

<p>LPHNSs-pDNA (6% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs-pDNA (12% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs-pDNA (18% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs-pDNA (24% DOTAP) </p>

<p>Figure 4 Influence of cationic lipid concentration of LPHNSs on cell viability and transfection efficiency. 
Notes: cytotoxicity (cell viability) of lPhNs-pDNa complexes (90:1 w/w) with different DOTaP concentrations were compared with lipofectamine (2 µl) and Ns 
polyplexes (PeI-Plga 90 µg) in 293T, hela, hacaT, and hepg2 cells by ccK-8 assay (A). Transfection efficiency of LPHNS-pDNA complexes (90:1 w/w) with different 
DOTaP concentrations (6-24 w/w%) were investigated in 293T, hela, hacaT, and hepg2 cells (B). lipofectamine (2 µl) and PeI-Plga (90:1 w/w) were used as controls. 
The scale represents 100 µm. Fluorescence-microscopy images for transfection efficiency of LPHNS-pDNA complex with different DOTAP concentrations in 293T, HeLa, 
hacaT, and hepg2 cells (C). results are presented as means ± standard deviation of three independent experiments. Significant results as compared to the control are 
marked with asterisks (*P,0.05, **P,0.01, ***P,0.001). 
Abbreviations: lPhNss, lipid-polymer hybrid nanospheres; w/w, weight/weight; Ns, nanosphere; pDNa, plasmid DNa; DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-
propane (chloride salt); PeI, polyethyleneimine; Plga, poly(d,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid). </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5377 </p>

<p>Influence of lipid concentration on LPHNS properties </p>

<p>(Figure 3B and C). Furthermore, the synergistic effect of 
protamine and lipid resulted in a higher degree of compl-
exation with pDNA, explaining the role of protamine as a 
DNA-condensing agent (Figures 3C, S2). </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>Influence of cationic lipid concentration 
on cell viability </p>

<p>Cytotoxicity is a crucial problem associated with most non-
viral vectors, limiting their clinical use. 
38 The cytotoxicity of 
LPHNSs-pDNA complexes as well as control groups (PEI-
PLGA and Lipofectamine 2000-pDNA complexes) was 
investigated with HEK293, HeLa, HaCaT, and HepG2 cells 
by CCK-8 assays. It is well known that lipoplexes and poly-
plexes exhibit high cytotoxicity. 
8 The experimental results 
confirmed similar cytotoxicity for Lipofectamine and PEI-
PLGA-pDNA complexes, as shown in Figure 4. Notably, 
all LPHNS-pDNA complexes exhibited low cytotoxicity 
(cell viability .70%), even at higher NS concentrations (90 
µg) for 293T, HeLa, HaCaT, and HepG2 cells. In addition, 
groups with higher lipid concentrations, such as LPHNS 
group C with 18% w/w DOTAP and group D with 24% w/w 
DOTAP, did not exhibit severe cytotoxicity (.70% cell 
viability in all tested cells). Furthermore, we investigated 
the effect of concentration of LPHNS-pDNA complexes 
on cell viability of HEK293 cells by using 15, 30, 60, and 
90 µg of LPHNSs with 1 µg of pDNA. The experimental 
results confirmed that all tested NS-pDNA complexes 
exhibited comparatively lower cytotoxicity than PEI-PLGA 
NS-pDNA complexes (90:1 w/w) (Figure S3). 
It was also observed that there was a slight increase in 
cytotoxicity for both PEI-PLGA and LPHNSs. It has been 
confirmed in various tissues that cationic liposome-based 
lipoplexes show dose-dependent toxicity. 
8,39 The size, 
charge ratio, and amount of free lipid present in the cationic 
liposome may be the reason for the increased cytotoxicity 
of cationic lipoplexes. 
40 However, our LPHNS system's 
nanosize (~150-200 nm) and biodegradable lipid-polymer 
hybrid could be the major contributors to the low cytotoxic-
ity. Furthermore, the spherical shape and less aggregation 
of LPHNSs could be the reason for low cytotoxicity, since 
cytotoxicity of NSs depends on the nature of the aggregates 
formed and morphology of lipoplexes (Figure 3). 
41 Ample 
evidence exists showing that polymeric NPs or liposomes 
alone cause cytotoxicity. Therefore, to overcome this prob-
lem, lipid-polymer hybrid architectures have been designed, 
which combine the mechanical (stability) advantages of 
biodegradable polymeric NPs and the biomimetic advantages 
of liposomes. </p>

<p>8,17 </p>

<p>Influence of cationic lipid concentration 
on transfection efficiency of LPHNSs </p>

<p>The in vitro transfection activity of LPHNSs with protamine 
at different concentrations of cationic lipid were studied in 
HEK293, HeLa, HaCaT, and HepG2 cells using pEGFP as 
a reporter gene at a 90:1 w/w (NS:pDNA) ratio. 
Transfection efficiency exhibited a strong correlation 
with cationic lipid concentration and NS concentration 
(results not shown) of the LPHNS gene carriers. Transfec-
tion efficiency in all four cell lines was slightly different, as 
shown in Figure 4B. When the cationic lipid concentration 
increased from 6% to 24% w/w at a specific NS concentra-
tion (90 µg), the transgene-expression level increased from 
48% to 85% in HEK293 cells. At the same NS concentration, 
the transgene-expression level increased from 27% to 50% 
in the HeLa cells. Similar trends were observed in human 
hepatocellular carcinoma cells, where transfection efficiency 
increased from 13% to 40%, and in immortalized human 
keratinocytes, where transgene-expression level increased 
from 30% to 53%. Interestingly, all formulation groups of 
LPHNSs showed markedly enhanced transfection efficiencies 
in HEK293 cells compared with other tested cells, as shown 
in Figure 4C. This could be attributed to the biochemical 
machinery of HEK293 cells, capable of carrying out most 
of the posttranslational folding and processing required to 
generate functional and mature protein from a wide spectrum 
of both mammalian and nonmammalian nucleic acids. </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>Lipid concentration-dependent transfection efficiency was 
observed in all four tested cell lines (Figure 4C). The transfec-
tion efficiencies of LPHNSs with protamine increased signifi-
cantly as expected, but was slightly different in different cell 
types. For instance, in HEK293 cells, LPHNS group D exhib-
ited enhanced gene expression (85%) compared to group A 
(48%), group B (61%), and group C (72%), while transgene 
expression in other cell types was not as different as in HEK293 
cells. However, we observed that the type of cells marginally 
influenced transgene expression (Figure 4C). It was evident in 
the cervical cancer (HeLa) cells that experimental group D had 
a higher transgene-expression level (50%) compared to group A 
(27%), group B (33%), and group C (45%). Particularly, the 
transgene-expression capability of LPHNSs and the effect 
of cell type on transgene expression among cell lines were 
investigated in additional cells. (Figure 4C) A similar trend of 
lipid concentration-dependent transfection was also observed 
in HepG2 cells, where group D had a higher gene-expression 
level (40%) compared to group A (17%), group B (24%), and 
group C (32%). In immortalized human keratinocytes, the </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5378 </p>

<p>Bose et al </p>

<p>transgene expression of group D showed superior efficiency 
(54%) compared to the lower lipid-concentration counterparts, 
as observed in group A (30%), group B (42%), and group C 
(46%), demonstrating that the transfection activity of the 
cationic lipid-protamine polymer hybrid nanocarrier was 
significantly dependent on their cationic lipid concentration. 
The transgene-expression level induced by the LPHNSs at 
the optimal NS:pDNA ratio in HEK cells was lower than that 
mediated by Lipofectamine, whereas it was at the same order 
of magnitude as that mediated by PEI-PLGA in HEK293 
cells. However, groups D and C exhibited 30% more transfec-
tion efficiency than that induced by PEI-PLGA in HeLa cells 
and 25% higher transfection in HepG2 cells. Specifically, 
group D demonstrated 2.6-fold higher transfection activity 
in HepG2 than Lipofectamine. One possible explanation for 
the good transfection activity of LPHNSs may be the cationic 
lipid-protamine ternary complex having a hybrid structure 
with optimal cationic charge and uniform size. </p>

<p>Influence of cationic lipid concentration 
of lPhNss on cellular uptake and 
intracellular processing </p>

<p>The cellular uptake of NSs can take place through multiple 
pathways, depending on the hybrid NS characteristics and </p>

<p>specific cell type. 
28 High cellular uptake of LPHNSs is an 
essential qualification for gene transfection. 
43 The fluores-
cently labeled Rho LPHNSs taken up by HeLa cells were 
quantified as a function of incubation time. The cellular 
uptake of LPHNSs in all tested groups (A, B, C, and D) was 
higher than PEI-modified PLGA NSs for the same incubation 
time. As shown in Figure 5A, group D (DOTAP 24% w/w) 
had a higher cellular uptake, reaching more than 85% after 
24 hours of incubation, while group A had ~60% uptake of 
LPHNSs. Based on these results, the particle-uptake rate 
and the final amount of HNSs inside the cells were strongly 
dependent on the cationic lipid concentrations. The results 
from flow cytometry were further evaluated with CLSM, as 
shown in Figure 5B. Interestingly, LPHNSs were found in 
the cytoplasm of cells, and were in close proximity to the 
nucleus. With increasing concentrations of DOTAP in the 
LPHNS formulation, the HNSs were formed as aggregates 
in the proximity of the nucleus. The possible explanation 
for the formation of an aggregated vesicle-like structure 
may be that DOTAP-mediated gene-delivery carriers are 
internalized by cells via clathrin-mediated endocytosis and 
efficiently released from the acidic endosomal compart-
ment prior to endosome/lysosomal degradation. Therefore, 
the DNA is accumulated near the perinuclear region of the </p>

<p>Figure 5 Influence of cationic lipid concentration of LPHNSs on cellular uptake and intracellular behaviors. 
Notes: Cellular uptake kinetics for LPHNSs with different DOTAP concentrations were quantified by flow cytometry (fluorescence intensity) as a function of the incubation 
time with the hela cell line (A). clsM images of hela cells after coculture with lPhNs-rhodamine (rho) with different DOTaP concentrations (6%-24%) incubated for 
12 hours (B).The cell nucleus was stained with DAPI (blue) and fluorescently labeled LPHNS-Rho (red) was used in all formulations. The scale in (B) represents 20 µm. Images 
were taken from the mid-plane of the cells in the z-direction. 
Abbreviations: lPhNss, lipid-polymer hybrid nanospheres; DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane (chloride salt); clsM, confocal laser 
scanning microscopy; PeI, polyethyleneimine; Plga, poly(d,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid); DaPI, 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5379 </p>

<p>Influence of lipid concentration on LPHNS properties </p>

<p>cells; our results demonstrated that the size of the aggregates 
may be indirectly proportional to the DOTAP concentra-
tion. Alternately, polyplexes (PEI-PLGA) probably follow 
caveolae-mediated uptake, leading to scattered fluorescence 
in the cytoplasm. </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>The group with the lowest concentration of cationic lipid 
(group A [6% w/w of DOTAP]) formed large, scattered aggre-
gates close to the nucleus. When the concentration of cationic 
lipid in the LPHNS formulation was increased from 6% to 
24% w/w (Figure 5B), the ζ-potentials (positive charge) of 
the hybrid nanocarriers also increased significantly, probably 
leading to vesicle-like aggregate formation. 
45 The propensity 
to form aggregates in the cytoplasm, particularly close to the 
nucleus, is a special feature of lipid-based nanocarriers. </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>On the contrary, PEI-PLGA NSs do not form vesicle-like 
structures, and become scattered in the cytoplasm. 
28 Analysis 
of LPHNSs with different concentrations of DOTAP lipid 
(6%, 12%, 18%, and 24% w/w) demonstrated that cationic 
lipid concentration played a crucial role in cellular uptake and 
transfection efficiency of LPHNSs. 
28 The data were consistent 
with the major role of clathrin-mediated endocytosis in the 
internalization of DOTAP lipoplexes. </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>stability and aggregation of lPhNss 
during storage </p>

<p>Nanocarrier stability is a critical factor for long-term storage 
and practical use. To test the shelf life of LPHNSs, three 
batches of each LPHNS formulation from groups A, B, C, 
and D were prepared by modified solvent evaporation with 
self-assembly and stored in transparent glass vials at 4°C. The 
average intensity-weighted diameters (z-average) were used 
to study LPHNS stability by DLS measurements at 5-day 
intervals. 
19 As shown in Figure S4, LPHNSs and control 
NSs stored at 4°C remained stable during the entire observed 
period of 15 days, maintaining a z-average slightly higher 
than that on the day of production and showing no visible 
signs of instability, such as sedimentation or aggregation. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Herein, we have demonstrated the potential role of cationic 
lipid concentration in the physical and biological perfor-
mances of LPHNSs. Cationic lipids potentially reduce the 
size of LPHNSs, and significantly increase the surface charge 
toward the positive side. We postulate that the transfection 
efficiency of our LPHNSs could be greatly enhanced by 
optimizing the cationic lipid concentration and controlling 
process. We believe that these LPHNS vectors will allow for 
the optimization of LPHNSs for safe and efficient nonviral 
gene transfection, and have great promise as a systematic </p>

<p>delivery system for multiple bioactive molecules, such as 
small interfering RNA and small-molecule drugs for the 
treatment of various diseases. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research was supported by the National Research Foun-
dation of Korea (NRF), funded by the Ministry of Science, 
ICT and Future Planning (NRF-2013R1A2A1A09013980). 
This research was also supported by the Korea Health Tech-
nology R&amp;D Project through the Korea Health Industry 
Development Institute (KHIDI), funded by the Ministry of 
Health and Welfare, Republic of Korea (HI14C3484). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Bose et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5381 </p>

<p>Influence of lipid concentration on LPHNS properties </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
0.1 
1 
1 0 
100 </p>

<p>-100 
+100 
0 </p>

<p>ζ-potentials </p>

<p>Diameter (nm) </p>

<p>Intensity (%) </p>

<p>Total counts </p>

<p>Negative-to-positive charge shifting </p>

<p>Emulsion-stabilizing effect of lipids </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>1,200,000 </p>

<p>1,000,000 </p>

<p>800,000 </p>

<p>600,000 </p>

<p>400,000 </p>

<p>200,000 </p>

<p>Bare PLGA </p>

<p>LPHNSs (6% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs (12% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs (18% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs (24% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs (6% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs (12% DOTAP) </p>

<p>LPHNSs (18% DOTAP) </p>

<p>Bare PLGA </p>

<p>LPHNSs (24% DOTAP) </p>

<p>Figure S1 representative dynamic light-scattering (Dls) graphs. 
Notes: Influence of cationic lipid concentration on LPHNS size and surface changes. The concentration-dependent size reduction and surface-charge changes are shown in 
the representative Dls images. 
Abbreviations: lPhNs, lipid-polymer hybrid nanosphere; Plga, poly(d,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid); DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane 
(chloride salt). </p>

<p>Supplementary materials </p>

<p>Figure S2 Microscopic analysis. eFTeM analysis of lPhNss and lPhNs-pDNa complex. scale bar represents 0.5 µm. 
Abbreviations: EFTEM, energy-filtered transmission electron microscopy; LPHNSs, lipid-polymer hybrid nanospheres; pDNA, plasmid DNA; DOTAP, 1,2-di-(9Z-
octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane (chloride salt); w/w, weight/weight. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nanomedicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nanomedicine is an international, peer-
reviewed journal focusing on the application of nanotechnology 
in diagnostics, therapeutics, and drug delivery systems throughout 
the biomedical field. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, CAS, SciSearch®, Current Contents®/Clinical Medicine, </p>

<p>Journal Citation Reports/Science Edition, EMBase, Scopus and the 
Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>5382 </p>

<p>Bose et al </p>

<p>Figure S3 effect of Ns:pDNa complex concentration on cell viability. 
Notes: effect of lPhNs:pDNa complex concentrations (15, 30, 60, and 90:1 w/w) on heK293 cell viability compared with PeI-Plga:pDNa complex concentration (90:1 
w/w). error bars represent standard error of mean; n=3. 
Abbreviations: lPhNs, lipid-polymer hybrid nanosphere; pDNa, plasmid DNa; DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane (chloride salt); 
PeI, polyethyleneimine; Plga, poly(d,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid); w/w, weight/weight; Ns, nanosphere. </p>

<p>Figure S4 short-term stability studies of lPhNss by dynamic light scattering (Dls). 
Notes: The particle sizes of the lPhNss were used to determine the stability of lPhNss by Dls (Malvern Nano Zs), and measurements were taken at 5-day intervals. 
Abbreviations: lPhNss, lipid-polymer hybrid nanospheres; Plga, poly(d,l-lactic-co-glycolic acid); DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane 
(chloride salt). </p>

</text></tei>