<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4296915" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 16 for Windows</rs>International Journal of COPD 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>Long-term efficacy of exercise program for advanced COPD patients </p>

<p>effect on muscle strengths </p>

<p>Upper and lower limbs muscle strength </p>

<p>After 4 weeks of training, only patients in SET group had 
statistically significant improvements in upper and lower 
limb muscle strengths (P=0.017 and 0.003, respectively). The 
improvement was maintained till the end of the follow-up 
period (Figure 2A and B). Significant differences between </p>

<p>the groups were detected at months 3, 6, 9, and 24 in upper 
limb muscle strength, and in all of the follow-up visits in 
lower limb muscle strength (P,0.05). </p>

<p>Respiratory muscle strength </p>

<p>After 4 weeks of training, only patients in the SET 
group had statistically significant improvements in MIP </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Watts 
Upper limb muscle strength </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>SET (n) </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>12 
12 </p>

<p>12 
15 
21 
18 
24 </p>

<p>27 
27 
27 
26 
25 
23 </p>

<p>8 
7 
5 
5 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) 
22 
14 </p>

<p>14 
14 
14 </p>

<p>13 
13 
14 </p>

<p>−5 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control (n) </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Watts </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Lower limb muscle strength </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>SET (n) </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>−5 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>12 
12 </p>

<p>12 
15 
21 
18 
24 </p>

<p>8 
7 
5 
5 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) </p>

<p>14 
14 
14 </p>

<p>26 
25 
23 
22 
14 
13 
13 
14 
27 
27 
27 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Control (n) </p>

<p>Figure 2 (Continued) </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>138 </p>

<p>Pothirat et al </p>

<p>Figure 2 Change from baseline over 24 months in muscle strength. 
Notes: (A) Change from baseline over 24 months in upper limb muscle strength. (B) Change from baseline over 24 months in lower limb muscle strength. (C) Change 
from baseline over 24 months in respiratory muscle strength. Values and error bars represent the mean ± standard error. Within-group change from baseline; *P,0.05. 
Comparison between patients with SET and control groups; </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: MIP, maximum inspiratory pressure; SET, Suandok exercise training. </p>

<p>SET (n) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>12 
12 </p>

<p>12 
15 
21 
18 
24 </p>

<p>8 
7 
5 
5 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) </p>

<p>14 
14 
14 </p>

<p>26 
24 
23 
22 
15 
16 
14 
14 
27 
27 
27 </p>

<p>Control (n) </p>

<p>cmH 2 O </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>MIP </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>and the gains were maintained throughout month 24 
(Figure 2C). There were no significant differences between 
the groups (P=0.69). </p>

<p>Effect on exercise capacity </p>

<p>After 8 weeks of training, only patients in the SET group 
had clinically significant improvement in 6-MWD. The 
improvement was maintained until month 9 (Figure 3A). 
No statistically significant differences between the groups 
were detected throughout the follow-up period (P=0.065). 
After 4 weeks of training, only patients in the SET group 
had statistically significant improvement in endurance time 
(P,0.01). The improvement was maintained throughout 
the testing period (month 12; Figure 3B). Significant differ-
ences between groups were also detected at all follow-up 
visits (P,0.01). </p>

<p>effect on breathlessness </p>

<p>The dyspnea score by mMRC did not show clinically 
significant differences in both groups and the statistical 
significant differences between groups were only detected 
at months 3, 6, and 9 (P,0.05; Figure 4A). However, the 
dyspnea score showed clinically significant changes by TDI 
only in the SET group at all follow-up visits and so did </p>

<p>the statistical significant differences between the groups 
(P,0.01; Figure 4B). </p>

<p>effect on hrQol </p>

<p>After 4 weeks of training, only patients in the SET group 
had clinically significant improvements in SGRQ score. The 
improvement was maintained till the end of follow-up period 
(Figure 5). The patients in the control group had clinically sig-
nificant improvements in SGRQ score only in months 3 and 21. 
The statistically significant differences in SGRQ score between 
the groups were detected at all follow-up visits (P=0.004). </p>

<p>effects on survival </p>

<p>The overall survival curves for both groups are shown in 
Figure 6. After 2 years of follow-up, 34 of the original 
41 patients were alive (survival rate, 82.9%), 24 of the 
27 patients in the SET group (88.9%) and 10 of the 14 patients 
in the control group (71.4%). The difference in survival 
rate of the patients between the groups was not statistically 
significant (P=0.092). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Exercise training, a multidisciplinary and structured inter-
vention for patients with chronic pulmonary diseases has </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>139 </p>

<p>Long-term efficacy of exercise program for advanced COPD patients </p>

<p>been shown to improve exercise tolerance, reduce dyspnea, 
and improve HRQoL. Exercise training represents the cor-
nerstone of every pulmonary rehabilitation program. 
24 This 
study indicates definite benefits of intensive ergometer exer-
cise training for patients with advanced COPD as compared </p>

<p>to the patients who participated in the control group. Our 
study reveals that ergometer exercise training produced both 
clinically meaningful and statistically significant improve-
ments in respiratory and peripheral muscle strength, 
exercise capacity, degree of dyspnea (by BDI/TDI), and </p>

<p>SET (n) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
6 
9 
1 2 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) </p>

<p>18 
17 
16 
14 
13 
18 
18 </p>

<p>6 
5 
5 
5 
4 
6 
6 
Control (n) </p>

<p>Minutes </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Endurance time </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>−5 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Figure 3 Change from baseline over 24 months in exercise capacities. 
Notes: (A) Change from baseline over 24 months in 6-MWD. (B) Change from baseline over 12 months in endurance time. Values and error bars represent the mean ± 
standard error. Within-group change from baseline in 6-MWD. Within-group change from baseline in endurance time; *P,0.05. Comparison between patients with seT and 
control groups; </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: 6-MWD, 6-minute walk distance; SET, Suandok exercise training; MCID, minimal clinically important difference. </p>

<p>SET (n) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>12 
12 </p>

<p>12 
15 
21 
18 
24 </p>

<p>8 
7 
5 
5 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) </p>

<p>MCID +54 m </p>

<p>14 
14 
14 </p>

<p>26 
25 
23 
22 
14 
13 
14 
13 
27 
27 
27 </p>

<p>Control (n) </p>

<p>Meters </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>6-MWD </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>Pothirat et al </p>

<p>Figure 4 effect on breathlessness. 
Notes: (A) Change from baseline over 24 months in mMRC score. (B) Change from baseline over 24 months in TDI score. Values and error bars represent the mean ± 
standard error. Within-group change from baseline in TDI; *MCID +1 unit. Comparison between patients with SET and control groups; </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: mMRC, modified Medical Research Council; TDI, transitional dyspnea index; SET, Suandok exercise training; MCID, minimal clinically important difference; 
BDI, baseline dyspnea index. </p>

<p>SET (n) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>10 
11 </p>

<p>12 
15 
21 
18 
24 </p>

<p>8 
7 
6 
5 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) </p>

<p>MCID =+1 unit </p>

<p>14 
14 
14 </p>

<p>26 
25 
23 
21 
19 
18 
13 
16 
27 
27 
27 </p>

<p>Control (n) </p>

<p>Units </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>BDI/TDI </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>#, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>#, </p>

<p>* 
#, * </p>

<p>#, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>#, </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>,# </p>

<p>SET (n) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
6 </p>

<p># </p>

<p># </p>

<p># </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>11 
12 </p>

<p>12 
15 
21 
18 
24 </p>

<p>9 
7 
7 
6 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) </p>

<p>MCID =−1 unit </p>

<p>14 
14 
14 </p>

<p>26 
24 
23 
22 
20 
19 
14 
17 
27 
27 
27 </p>

<p>Control (n) </p>

<p>Units </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>mMRC </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>−0.5 </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>HRQoL, even though no significant effect was observed 
on survival outcome. Exercise intensities were started from 
mild-to-moderate (30%-35% to 50%-55% of HRR) and 
duration of exercise was increased from 30-40 minutes to 
50-60 minutes per session. The guidelines of American 
College of Sports Medicine (ACSM) recommended that </p>

<p>the training intensity should be targeted at 50%-80% of 
the maximal oxygen uptake or HRR for endurance exer-
cise. 
25 The ACSM also advised to sustain intensity for 
20-45 minutes and to stop cycling for 2-3 minutes during 
cycle ergometry when the breathlessness reaches 5-6 RPE 
because interval training is well accepted and shows similar </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>141 </p>

<p>Long-term efficacy of exercise program for advanced COPD patients </p>

<p>SET (n) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
6 
9 </p>

<p>10 
11 </p>

<p>12 
15 
21 
18 
24 </p>

<p>8 
7 
6 
5 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) </p>

<p>MCID =−4 unit </p>

<p>14 
14 
14 </p>

<p>26 
25 
23 
21 
19 
18 
13 
16 
27 
27 
27 </p>

<p>Control (n) </p>

<p>Units 
SGRQ </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>−18 </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>−16 </p>

<p>−14 </p>

<p>* # 
* # 
* # </p>

<p>* # </p>

<p>* # </p>

<p>* # 
* # 
* # 
* # </p>

<p>* # </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>−12 </p>

<p>−8 </p>

<p>−6 </p>

<p>−4 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>Figure 5 effect on hrQol. 
Notes: Change from baseline over 24 months in sgrQ score. Values and error bars represent the mean ± standard error. Within-group change from baseline; *MCID −4 unit. 
Comparison between patients with SET and control groups; </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P,0.05. 
Abbreviations: HRQoL, health-related quality of life; SGRQ, St George's Respiratory Questionnaire; SET, Suandok exercise training; MCID, minimal clinically important 
difference. </p>

<p>improvements in patients with severe COPD. 
26 Few studies 
have been able to demonstrate the long-term maintenance of 
benefits beyond 2 years 
5,6,27-30 but our study has confirmed 
that most of the benefits of the SET program were well 
maintained throughout the 24-month follow-up. </p>

<p>In our study, there were statistically significant improve-
ments in respiratory muscle, upper and lower limb muscle 
strengths, endurance time, and clinically and statistically 
significant improvements in BDI/TDI, and QoL since the 
first month after SET was started, except the 6-MWD, which </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Time 
(month) </p>

<p>SET </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>21 
18 
15 
12 
9 
6 
3 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>Proportion surviving </p>

<p>Figure 6 Kaplan-Meier survival curves for patients in SET and control groups during 2 years of follow-up. 
Abbreviation: SET, Suandok exercise training. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Pothirat et al </p>

<p>improved one month later. Some parameters (respiratory, 
upper and lower limb muscle strength, BDI/TDI, and QoL) 
were improved throughout the study period (24-month 
follow-up). In addition, these parameters were continually 
improved for quite a long period after SET ended. Although 
there was clinically significant improvement in the severity of 
dyspnea in the patients in the SET group measured by TDI, 
the dyspnea score measured by mMRC did not show clinically 
significant improvement. Therefore, we could conclude that 
the change in TDI is more sensitive than mMRC for measur-
ing the dyspnea severity. For exercise capacities, we measured 
both 6-MWD and endurance time. The 6-MWD started to 
improve clinically from month 2 and persistentally improved 
up to month 9. The endurance time started to significantly 
improve from month 1 (one month earlier than 6-MWD) 
and persistently improved throughout the one-year testing 
period (at least 3 months longer than 6-MWD). The earlier 
and persistently longer improvement of endurance time than 
the 6-MWD might indirectly reflect that endurance time is a 
more sensitive parameter than 6-MWD for measuring change 
of exercise capacity in COPD. The severity of dyspnea signifi-
cantly improved both clinically and statistically as indicated 
by the mean change in the TDI score but not by mMRC 
score. Other studies have suggested that the latter, by using 
a rougher scale, is not sensitive enough to detect changes in 
patients with advanced COPD. 
31 For the QoL, the patients in 
the SET group showed persistent improvement throughout 
all visits over the 2-year period. Varying results on survival 
were reported in previous retrospective, non-randomized 
survival analyses. 
1,32 Our results indicated that there was a 
slight but not significant difference in survival rate between 
the SET (89%) and the control (71%) groups. The absence of 
significant difference in survival rate between the SET and the 
control groups might be due to a small sample size, signifi-
cant dropout rate, and only a 2-year follow-up. As expected, 
FEV 1 was the most significant predictor of survival. Our SET 
program did not affect the measures of pulmonary function 
that were shown in previous studies to be significant predic-
tors of survival in patients with COPD. </p>

<p>33,34 </p>

<p>ATS/ERS had suggested that the exercise training pro-
gram should offer at least three sessions per week to achieve 
any physiologic benefits. 
35 This was modified later to twice 
weekly supervised plus one unsupervised home session. Our 
results were contrary to those of Ringbaek et al 
36 who did not 
find any improvement in exercise capacity while exercising 
twice a week for 8 weeks. The reason could be that our SET 
exercise program was more intensified and the patients were 
more deconditioned. </p>

<p>Although our study had benefits of training on 2-year 
follow-up, all outcome measurements showed peak response 
at month 9. These benefits, which were similar to other stud-
ies, suggested that after 9 months, the rehabilitation program 
should have some reinforcements after the core phase in 
the form of supervised periods of exercise, group sessions 
to discuss progress and problems, and the introduction of 
maintenance techniques. </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>Our study had some limitations. First, the study was 
conducted in a single university-based center and it might 
not be applicable to large-scale practices, especially those 
that do not have specialized physiotherapists and nurses. 
Second, the study was not designed as a double-blinded 
randomized control trial with sham exercise in the con-
trol group; we had divided the patients following their 
preferences. The patients in SET group might have had 
more motivation for coping with their COPD than the 
control group and might have been more enthusiastic 
about continuing their self-exercise program after the first 
2 months of the intensive supervised one. Third, our study 
had significantly high dropout rates in both groups. There 
were 19.5% versus 50% and 49.1% versus 64.3% of patients 
dropped out from the study by 12 months and 24 months in 
the SET group versus the control group, respectively. The 
proportion of respondents declining rehabilitation appears 
similar to other studies (9%-50%). </p>

<p>37-40 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Our results confirm that the SET program, as an intensive 
ergometer exercise, is effective for patients with advanced 
COPD. This program proved to be a feasible approach for 
improving peripheral and respiratory muscle strengths, 
dyspnea, and QoL up to 2 years and exercise capacity up 
to at least the 9-month follow-up. These promising results 
should encourage the health care professionals to promote 
exercise training for patients with advanced COPD who are 
prone to limit most of their daily activities despite optimal 
medication control. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank the patients who kindly took part 
in this study and to acknowledge the staff members of the 
Division of Pulmonary Critical Care and Allergy, Department 
of Internal Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai 
University for their contribution to this trial. Our gratitude 
also goes to Jatuporn Wongsatitkul for her consultation for 
developing the SET program and Monsicha Somrit for pro-
viding her expertise as a skillful physiotherapist. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>143 </p>

<p>Long-term efficacy of exercise program for advanced COPD patients </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>CP (pulmonologist) developed study design and carried out 
acquisition and interpretation of data, statistical analysis, 
manuscript preparation, and critical revision of intellectual 
contents. WC (physical therapist) helped CP conducting 
acquisition and interpretation of data and critical reviews of 
the manuscript, revised the article for important intellectual 
content and gave final approval of the version to be published. 
The other authors contributed to acquisition and interpretation 
of data, revised the article for important intellectual content 
and gave final approval of the version to be published. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest in connection with 
the work submitted. </p>



<p>International Journal of COPD </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-copd-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of COPD is an international, peer-reviewed 
journal of therapeutics and pharmacology focusing on concise rapid 
reporting of clinical studies and reviews in COPD. Special focus is given 
to the pathophysiological processes underlying the disease, intervention 
programs, patient focused education, and self management protocols. </p>

<p>This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, MedLine and CAS. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of COPD 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>