<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4066774" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Semen contains relatively ill-defined regulatory com-
ponents that likely aid fertilization, but which could 
also interfere with defense against infection. Each 
ejaculate contains trillions of exosomes, membrane-
enclosed subcellular microvesicles, which have im-
munosuppressive effects on cells important in the 
genital mucosa. Exosomes in general are believed 
to mediate inter-cellular communication, possibly by 
transferring small RNA molecules. We found that 
seminal exosome (SE) preparations contain a sub-
stantial amount of RNA from 20 to 100 nucleotides 
(nts) in length. We sequenced 20-40 and 40-100 
nt fractions of SE RNA separately from six semen 
donors. We found various classes of small non-
coding RNA, including microRNA (21.7% of the RNA 
in the 20-40 nt fraction) as well as abundant Y RNAs 
and tRNAs present in both fractions. Specific RNAs 
were consistently present in all donors. For example, 
10 (of ∼2600 known) microRNAs constituted over 
40% of mature microRNA in SE. Additionally, tRNA 
fragments were strongly enriched for 5'-ends of 18-
19 or 30-34 nts in length; such tRNA fragments re-
press translation. Thus, SE could potentially deliver 
regulatory signals to the recipient mucosa via trans-
fer of small RNA molecules. </p>

<p>Human semen contains immunosuppressive agents that 
induce tolerance to paternal antigens and maximize the 
chances of successful fertilization. This helps explain the 
low incidence in women of antibodies against sperm and </p>

<p>soluble components to semen (1). On the other hand, se-
men's immunosuppressive properties could also contribute 
to the prevalence of sexually transmitted infections, which 
may take advantage of subdued immune responses follow-
ing exposure to semen (2). For example, the most globally 
devastating sexually transmitted disease, human immunod-
eficiency virus (HIV), has proven difficult to be prevented 
by vaccination, even with vaccine candidates that induced 
strong anti-HIV immunity in the bloodstream (3,4). This 
could be partially explained by localized immunosuppres-
sion mediated by semen at the time of initial exposure to 
HIV. Similarly, decreased exposure to semen through the 
use of condoms helps to clear active human papillomavirus 
infection (5), consistent with an immunosuppressive func-
tion for semen. 
Semen is a complex fluid composed of cells and semi-
nal plasma. The immunosuppressive fraction of semen is 
likely contained in seminal plasma, because isolated washed 
sperm cells can elicit immunity against paternal antigens, 
while the plasma alone promotes tolerance to paternal anti-
gens, possibly by redirecting dendritic cells towards a tolero-
genic profile (6-8). Seminal plasma contains a high concen-
tration of subcellular lipid-bound microparticles, tradition-
ally termed prostasomes, because the majority of them were 
thought to derive from epithelial cells in the prostate gland 
(9). However, these microparticles likely originate from mul-
tiple cellular sources in the male genital tract (10) and are 
morphologically and molecularly consistent with exosomes, 
so we use the term 'seminal exosomes' (SE). SE have already 
been implicated as immunosuppressive, inhibiting lympho-
proliferative responses (2), the activity of phagocytic cells 
(11) and natural killer cell function (12). Thus, the immuno-
suppressive properties of seminal plasma appear to reside at 
least in large part within its exosome fraction. </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 206 616 3876; Fax: +1 206 667 7767; Email: luciav@uw.edu 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Florian Hladik. Tel: +1 206 667 6848; Fax: +1 206 667 7767; Email: fhladik@fhcrc.org </p>

<p>C The Author(s) 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 11 7291 </p>

<p>Exosomes are shed from most cell types and are present 
in a wide variety of body fluids. They can be taken up by spe-
cific target cells via membrane surface proteins, and though 
exosomes were initially thought to be non-specific waste 
from cells, evidence that exosomes are important mediators 
of intercellular communication is rapidly accumulating. De-
pending on the cell type of origin, exosomes can be involved 
in both immune stimulation and tolerization. For example, 
tumor-derived exosomes have been shown to suppress im-
mune responses, promote metastasis, and confer drug resis-
tance to recipient cells in cancer (13-15). In contrast, den-
dritic cell-derived exosomes loaded with infectious disease 
antigens can induce immune responses (16-18). The exoso-
mal cargo mediating effects on recipient cells includes cy-
tokines, growth factors and membrane proteins, as well as 
both messenger and microRNA (19). MicroRNAs (miR-
NAs) regulate biological functions through degradation or 
inhibition of specific mRNA targets (20-24). Other small 
non-coding RNAs carried by exosomes could also act as 
regulatory elements (25-27). Fragments of transfer RNA 
(tRNA), for example, can non-specifically inhibit protein 
translation or function as miRNAs by binding components 
of the RNA-induced silencing complex (28-30). 
We hypothesized that SE, like other exosomes, carry non-
coding RNA molecules and that the immunosuppressive ef-
fects of SE, and of seminal plasma in general, are at least in 
part mediated by the activities of these regulatory RNAs. 
In this study, we found that SE indeed contain substantial 
amounts of small RNAs (&lt;100 nucleotides [nt]). In contrast 
to blood plasma and cell culture supernatant, where only a 
minor fraction of miRNA appears contained within exo-
somes (31,32), about half of extracellular RNA in seminal 
plasma purified with the exosomal fraction rather than the 
exosome-depleted supernatant. We then comprehensively 
surveyed exosomal small RNAs by deep sequencing, find-
ing that known human miRNAs are carried by SE. SE 
also contained other potentially immunomodulatory small 
non-coding RNAs, including tRNAs, Y RNAs and protein-
coding mRNA fragments. These findings point to the selec-
tive transport and delivery of small RNA molecules in SE 
as a potentially important mechanism of semen-mediated 
immunoregulation in the recipient genital mucosa. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Semen samples </p>

<p>All semen samples were obtained from healthy HIV-
negative men at the HIV Vaccine Trials Unit Clinic in Seat-
tle. All protocols were approved by the Institutional Re-
view Boards of the University of Washington and the Fred 
Hutchinson Cancer Research Center. Written informed 
consent was obtained from each donor. Donors abstained 
from sexual activity for &gt; 48 h before semen donation. The 
entire ejaculates were collected in a sterile container, mixed 
with 3 ml of Roswell Park Memorial Institute media and 
kept on ice for &lt;3 h prior to processing. </p>

<p>Isolation of exosomes from semen </p>

<p>Semen samples were allowed to liquefy for 20 min at room 
temperature. Seminal plasma, containing exosomes, was </p>

<p>separated from the cell fraction by centrifugation at 1000 
× g for 10 min. Cell debris was removed by subsequent cen-
trifugation at 2400 × g for 30 min followed by 0.45 m and 
0.22 m syringe filtration (Millex HA). Exosomes were pu-
rified from the entire cell-and debris-free seminal plasma 
(ranging from 0.9 to 4.0 ml in our donors) by ultracen-
trifugation over a sucrose cushion using a method adapted 
from Lamparski et al. (33). Up to 2.5 ml of supernatant was 
added to ultracentrifuge tubes and under-layered with 300 
l of a 20 mM Tris/30% sucrose/deuterium oxide (D 2 O) 
cushion (pH 7.4) (Sigma). Samples were ultra-centrifuged 
at 100 000 × g for 90 min at 4 
• C in an SW 50 swinging 
bucket rotor (Beckman). The upper layer was collected and 
ultracentrifuged again at 100 000 × g for 14 h at 4 
• C over 
a 20 mM Tris/25% sucrose/D 2 O cushion (pH 7.4). The up-
per layer of exosome-depleted seminal plasma was stored at 
−80 
• C. The 30% and 25% sucrose cushions containing the 
exosome fraction were pooled and brought to 15 ml with 
Dulbecco's phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). The exosomes 
were washed by centrifuging at 2400 × g through an Ami-
con Ultracel 100 kDa cellulose centrifugal filter with 10 ml 
of PBS and concentrated to a final volume of 425 l-3.2 ml. 
Exosomes were stored at −80 
• C. </p>

<p>Exosome quantification and size determination </p>

<p>Concentration and size distribution of the isolated exo-
somes were measured by nanoparticle tracking analysis us-
ing a Nanosight LM-10 instrument (Nanosight) accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions. In brief, SE sam-
ples were vortexed and serially diluted to a final dilution 
of 1:8000 -1:80 000 in filtered molecular grade H 2 O. Blank 
filtered H 2 O was run as a negative control. 97 nm ± 3 nm 
polystyrene latex standards of known concentration (Life 
technologies) were analyzed along with the diluted exosome 
solution to validate the instrument. Each sample analysis 
was conducted for 60 s using Nanosight automatic analysis 
settings. Samples were evaluated in triplicate and concen-
tration values were averaged. </p>

<p>Western blotting </p>

<p>Total protein concentrations were determined for all SE 
and SE-depleted plasma samples by Coomassie protein as-
say (Thermo Scientific) according to the manufacturer's in-
structions. For western blotting, 40 g samples of total pro-
tein were heated to 95 
• C for 7 min in 1x DTT-containing 
sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS) sample buffer (New Eng-
land Biolabs) and electrophorized in 4-12% NuPage Bis-
Tris-polyacrylamide gel (Novex by Life Technologies), fol-
lowed by transfer to Immobilon polyvinylidene difluoride 
membranes (Millipore) and blocking for 1 h or overnight 
with 5% blotting-grade blocker (Bio-Rad). Monoclonal an-
tibodies used for immunoblotting were anti-Ro/SSA and 
anti-CD63, both from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, anti-
HSP-70 from Enzo Life Sciences and anti-Calnexin from 
MBL. The secondary antibody was horseradish peroxidase-
conjugated goat-anti-mouse IgG (Thermo Pierce). Blots 
were developed using the Femto ECL chemiluminescent de-
veloping kit (Thermo Scientific). </p>



<p>Transmission electron microscopy </p>

<p>Preparation for transmission electron microscopy (EM) 
analysis was done using the method described by Thery 
et al. (34), except that an airfuge (Beckman-Coulter) was 
used to deposit fixed samples onto grids. In brief, SE sam-
ples were mixed with an equal volume of 4% PFA and 
deposited by airfuge onto Formvar/Carbon coated EM 
grids (Ted Pella). Samples were contrasted and embedded 
by treatment with uranyl-oxalate solution (Electron Mi-
croscopy Services), pH 7, for 5 min, followed by methyl-
cellulose-uranyl-acetate (Sigma) on ice for 10 min. </p>

<p>RNAse protection assays and RNA isolation </p>

<p>For RNAse, protease and detergent protection assays, SE 
and SE-depleted seminal plasma samples were divided into 
equal fractions, which received: 1) no treatment, 2) RNAse 
digestion, 3) protease treatment then RNAse digestion, 
or 4) detergent treatment followed by protease and RNAse 
digestion. For RNAse treatment, samples were incubated 
with 12 units/ml of RNAse A and 500 units/ml of RNAse 
T1 (Ambion RNAse cocktail enzyme mix) for 30 min at 
37 
• C. For protease treatment, samples were digested with 
pronase (Roche) at 600 g/ml for 20 min at 40 
• C. Pronase 
was inactivated by incubation for 15 min at 80 
• C. For deter-
gent treatment, samples were incubated with 1% NP-40 de-
tergent for 15 min on ice. Total RNA for RNAse protection 
assay, sequencing studies or qRT-PCR assays was isolated 
from SE samples and from SE-depleted seminal plasma us-
ing the miRCURY 
TM RNA Isolation Kit (Exiqon), accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions. All RNA samples 
were quantified using fluorometry (Qubit RNA Assay Kit, 
Life Technologies). RNA size distributions were assessed by 
Agilent Bioanalyzer small RNA chips. </p>

<p>Library generation for small RNA sequencing </p>

<p>Library generation and small RNA sequencing were per-
formed by Ocean Ridge Biosciences. RNA samples for se-
quencing were digested with RNase-free DNase I and re-
purified on RNeasy MinElute columns (Qiagen). Template 
DNA molecules suitable for cluster generation were pre-
pared from 100 ng of the re-purified RNA samples using 
the ScriptMiner 
TM Small RNA-Seq Library Preparation 
Kit (Epicentre Biotechnologies) according to the manufac-
turer's instructions, except that following the RNA linker 
ligation, but before cDNA synthesis, the RNA was frac-
tionated using a 10% acrylamide-urea gel. RNA fragments 
consisting of inserts of ∼15-40 nt were excised as a lower 
band, and RNA fragments containing inserts of ∼40-100 
nt were excised as an upper band. These two fractions were 
processed separately through the rest of the library prepa-
ration procedure. Following the ScriptMiner protocol, the 
purified cDNA libraries were electrophorized through a 
freshly cast 8% native polyacrylamide gel. The library frag-
ments of appropriate size were recovered from the gel by 
shaking fragments in 1X acrylamide elution buffer (0.01 
M Magnesium Acetate, 0.1% SDS, 0.01 M EDTA and 0.5 
M Ammonium Acetate) at 37 
• C at 200 rpm, passage of the 
eluted cDNA through a 0.45 m filter and ethanol precipi-
tation. The quality and size distribution of the amplified li-</p>

<p>braries were confirmed by electrophoresis on Agilent DNA 
500 Bioanalyzer microfluidic chips. Libraries were quanti-
fied using the KAPA Library Quantification Kit (KK4824, 
Kapa Biosystems). The libraries were pooled at equimolar 
concentrations and diluted to 13 pmol prior to loading onto 
the flow cell of the cBot cluster station (Illumina). The li-
braries were extended and bridge-amplified to create single 
sequence clusters using the TruSeq SR Cluster Kit version 
3 -HS (Illumina). The flow cell carrying amplified clus-
ters was loaded on the HiSeq 2000 sequencing system (Il-
lumina) and sequenced with 50-bp single-end reads using 
the TruSeq SBS Kit version 3 -HS (Illumina). Ten percent 
X174 phage DNA was spiked into all sequencing lanes for 
sequencer calibration. Real-time image analysis and base 
calling were performed on the instrument using the <rs type="software">HiSeq 
Sequencing Control Software</rs>. <rs id="software-6" type="software">CASAVA</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">version 1.8</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Illumina</rs>) was used for de-multiplexing and production 
of FASTQ sequence files. </p>

<p>Analysis of small RNA sequence data </p>

<p>The <rs id="software-7" type="software">FASTX application</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="url">www.molecularevolution.org</rs>) 
was used to trim adapter sequences from the 3'-end of 
the sequence read, discard any sequence of &lt;17 nts after 
trimming and to collapse identical reads into single en-
tries retaining the read count for each unique sequence. 
Non-redundant sequences were then aligned to genomic 
RNA and mRNA sequences of hg19 using <rs id="software-8" type="software">Bowtie 2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="url">www.bowtie-bio.sf.net</rs>) (35) and matched sequences were re-
tained and aligned to common and abundant non-coding 
RNAs (tRNAs, rRNAs, snoRNAs). Remaining sequences 
were further aligned to known mature and precursor 
miRNAs using the miRbase 19 database (www.mirbase. 
org). Additional alignments to a transcript database (En-
sembl version 75, http://www.ensembl.org) (36) and the spe-
cific piRNA database <rs id="software-17" type="software">piRNABank</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-17" type="url">http://pirnabank.ibab. ac.in</rs>/) were also performed (37). Alignment result files 
were parsed using the R statistical language (http://www. 
R-project.org) and the <rs id="software-10" type="software">Bioconductor</rs> project (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="url">http://www.bioconductor.org</rs>) (38) to generate tables including the read 
count and annotation information for each entry in the tar-
get database. Raw read counts for each RNA class from all 
samples in the study were then joined in raw data tables. 
The raw reads were converted to reads per kilobase of target 
length per million mapped reads (39). All sequences were 
deposited into the <rs id="software-20" type="software">GEO</rs> database (<rs corresp="#software-20" type="url">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo</rs>/) under accession number GSE56076. Calculation 
of percent of reads by biotype was based on raw read counts 
of perfectly matched transcripts for each biotype compared 
to total reads for each library. </p>

<p>Digital droplet PCR </p>

<p>Taqman miRNA assays were used to validate sequencing 
data on the Biorad digital droplet PCR (ddPCR) platform. 
miRNA reverse transcription kits and primer probe sets 
were purchased from Applied Biosystems. ddPCR super-
mix for probes was purchased from Biorad. During RNA 
extraction of SE samples for qPCR, 5 l of 5nM synthetic 
cel-miR-39 (Qiagen) was added during lysis to normalize 
extractions and reverse transcription across samples. Re-
verse transcription was carried out as in (40), starting with </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 11 7293 </p>

<p>10 ng of RNA. After reverse transcription cDNA was di-
luted 7-fold with water and 9 l was used in a 20 l final 
PCR reaction volume. Droplets were generated and read us-
ing a QX100 droplet digital PCR system (Biorad), accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>Analysis of potential mRNA targets of abundant SE-
associated miRNAs </p>

<p>Validated immune-related mRNAs targeted by abundant 
miRNAs in SE were identified using miRTarBase and con-
firmed by checking original publication references (41). </p>

<p>General statistics </p>

<p>Abundance of RNA biotypes in SE across donors was an-
alyzed using Spearman's correlation coefficient. The dif-
ference in RNA content between exosomes and seminal 
plasma was tested using a paired t test. All statistics were 
calculated using <rs id="software-11" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-11" type="version-number">6.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">Graphpad</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characterization of exosomes from semen </p>

<p>SE isolated from 12 different donors had an average diame-
ter of 93 nm, with &gt;75% of SE between 50 and 200 nm, the 
characteristic size range of exosomes and small microvesi-
cles (Figure 1A). From these 12 donors, we isolated more 
than 10 
12 particles per ejaculate (mean concentration 1.37 
× 10 
13 /ml, range 4.7 × 10 
11 -3.12 × 10 
13 SE/ml). Trans-
mission EM confirmed that our SE samples contained lipid 
bilayer-bound single and small clumps of particles in the 
expected size range of exosomes and microvesicles (Figure 
1B). Western blotting showed the presence of the universal 
exosome markers heat shock protein (HSP)-70 and CD63 in 
the exosomal but not the exosome-depleted seminal plasma 
fraction. Calnexin was present in cells, but not in either cell-
free fraction, indicating that the vesicles are not derived 
from the endoplasmic reticulum (Figure 1C). These data 
confirm that the previously described prostasomes are in-
deed exosomes and microvesicles and that they are present 
in high concentrations in human semen. </p>

<p>Exosomes in semen carry extracellular RNA </p>

<p>Reports in other systems demonstrate that exosomes can 
contain RNA and transfer it between cells, delivering reg-
ulatory micro and other small RNA molecules that mod-
ulate the function of recipient cells (20,22-24,42,43). We 
found that SE carry an average of 1477 ng of RNA (range 
215-3534 ng, n = 8 semen donations) per sample. To test 
how much RNA in filtered seminal plasma is associated 
with the exosome fraction, we compared RNA content 
in three pools of SE, isolated from three separate donors 
each (nine donors total), with their respective pooled SE-
depleted plasmas. Isolated exosomes contained an average 
of 55% of the total RNA isolated from our samples. The 
remaining 45% was in the exosome-depleted supernatant 
(Figure 2A). To show that the SE-associated RNA is car-
ried within intact exosomes, we treated a part of these same 
samples with either RNAse alone, or with protease followed </p>

<p>by RNAse, or with detergent followed by protease then 
RNAse. More than 88% of RNA in the exosome fractions 
was protected from combined RNAse/protease digestion. 
Treatment with detergent to lyse exosomes prior to pro-
tease and RNAse treatment resulted in a loss of 83% of the 
RNA. (Figure 2A). In contrast, 47% of RNA in the sem-
inal plasma fraction was degraded with RNAse/protease 
treatment alone, confirming that much of this RNA is not 
protected by vesicles. These data show that a substantial 
fraction of extracellular RNA in 0.22 m filtered seminal 
plasma is exosome-associated and that the majority of SE-
associated RNA is enclosed and protected within intact mi-
crovesicles or protein complexes. </p>

<p>SE contain several small RNA biotypes </p>

<p>Given the extremely high concentration of exosomes in se-
men and their high RNA content, which suggests biological 
significance, we analyzed the RNA isolated from SE prepa-
rations in six healthy semen donors by next-generation se-
quencing. A table outlining RNA yields per SE count and 
volume is provided as Supplemental Table S1. Because a 
substantial fraction of exosomal RNA was &lt;100 nt in size, 
and within that size range there were two clearly distinguish-
able peaks (20-40 nt and 40-100 nt) (Figure 2B), we pre-
pared and sequenced the RNA in two separate size frac-
tions encompassing the two peaks. A total of 195 828 379 
raw reads were obtained from the smaller size-fraction li-
braries, and 212 663 023 reads from the larger. Mapped 
RNA was analyzed separately by biotype, and total reads 
for ribosomal RNA, tRNA, miRNA, piwi-RNA, Y RNA 
and protein-coding mRNA are given in Table 1. The distri-
bution of reads corresponding to the RNA biotypes corre-
lated highly between donors for the larger size-fraction li-
braries (median Spearman's = 0.96, range 0.89-1.0) (Ta-
ble 2 and Supplemental Table S2) and less so for the smaller 
size-fraction libraries (median Spearman = 0.46, range 
0.25-0.89) (Table 3 and Supplemental Table S3). Thus, most 
small RNA in SE mapped to known RNA sequences, and 
the distribution of reads across the different RNA biotypes 
was surprisingly consistent between semen donors. 
As expected, the 20-40 nt and 40-100 nt RNA fractions 
exhibited some notable differences in RNA biotypes (Fig-
ure 2C). An average of 21.7% of mappable RNA in the 
smaller size fractions was identified as miRNA. The larger 
size fractions contained only 2.89% miRNA. The larger 
size libraries should have carried only pre-miRNA hairpins, 
which are ∼70 nt long, and indeed the guide and passen-
ger strands were present in approximately equal abundance 
in the larger libraries, indicating that the miRNA in the 
larger size fractions was primarily pre-miRNA. Piwi-RNA, 
which has a size range of 26-31 nt (44), was present in the 
smaller RNA fraction (mean 2.75%) and, as expected, was 
almost undetectable in the larger fractions (0.03%). Full-
length tRNA ranges from 73 to 94 nt and therefore was ex-
pected in the larger fractions, where tRNA reads accounted 
for 5.93% of the RNA. Surprisingly, sequences mapping 
to tRNA were also found in abundance in the smaller li-
braries, accounting for 16.02% of the sequencing reads, im-
plying that some tRNAs are fragmented in SE. Similarly, 
Y RNA, the 83-112 nt long non-coding RNA component </p>



<p>Figure 1. Microparticles isolated from semen exhibit the characteristic features of exosomes and microvesicles. (A) Representative particle size distribution 
profiles from four different semen donors. Microparticles were isolated as described in Materials and Methods and their sizes were determined by Nanopar-
ticle Tracking Analysis. (B) Transmission electron micrographs of SE preparation. Panel i--overview of purified microvesicles showing individual exosomes 
and a few clumps; panels ii-iv--individual exosomes of varying densities with intact lipid bilayers. (C) Western blots on SE and exosome-depleted seminal 
plasma from four different donors using antibodies against the common exosome markers CD63 and HSP70, and the endoplasmic reticulum marker 
calnexin. Lysates from HeLa cells were used as a control. </p>

<p>Figure 2. SE contain protected small RNAs. (A) The majority of extracellular RNA in semen is protected in exosomes. Total RNA was isolated from SE 
or exosome-depleted seminal plasma from three pools of three donors each and treated with RNAse alone, with pronase followed by RNAse, or with 
detergent followed by pronase and RNAse prior to quantification. Equal fractions of each sample type were used for treatment and RNA isolation. Error 
bars are standard deviations from separate experiments using the three different pools. (B) Small and normal bioanalyzer profiles of SE RNA from one 
representative donor showing two distinct size fractions of 15-40 nts and 40-100 nts, and enrichment for small RNA. (C) Distribution of RNA biotypes in 
SE RNA libraries spanning 15-40 nts and 40-100 nts. Segments of the bar indicate the percent of reads attributed to each RNA biotype among all RNA 
reads that mapped perfectly to known sequences, averaged across six semen donors. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 11 7295 </p>

<p>Table 1. Total number of sequencing reads by library </p>

<p>Sequencing 
library </p>

<p>Reads mapped 
to genome 
tRNA reads 
miRNA reads 
Y RNA reads </p>

<p>Protein-coding 
reads </p>

<p>Piwi-RNA 
reads 
rRNA reads </p>

<p>40-100 nt libraries 
Donor 1 
12 046 098 
795 771 
404 379 
1 356 599 
403 392 
4288 
6 029 886 
Donor 2 
611 273 
46 425 
25 027 
78 063 
28 859 
321 
296 372 
Donor 3 
10 774 524 
632 011 
204 732 
895 982 
881 806 
3448 
5 663 162 
Donor 4 
13 367 134 
462 958 
310 106 
1 633 277 
569 234 
2145 
7 414 568 
Donor 5 
8 902 958 
588 513 
212 253 
664 106 
305 079 
2554 
5 064 024 
Donor 6 
13 727 563 
749 751 
447 043 
1 303 950 
1 097 515 
1873 
6 835 460 
15-40 nt libraries 
Donor 1 
8 732 973 
1 744 258 
2 396 753 
1 043 526 
1 021 534 
411 768 
1 806 844 
Donor 2 
9 478 197 
2 292 092 
1 971 024 
1 723 312 
672 676 
219 097 
1 438 469 
Donor 3 
10 244 365 
1 021 183 
2 355 598 
3 002 703 
1 073 212 
200 640 
1 399 439 
Donor 4 
9 437 222 
1 211 062 
1 850 259 
3 089 860 
761 352 
277 548 
1 305 193 
Donor 5 
6 821 354 
1 250 648 
1 123 228 
1 076 614 
385 910 
155 471 
1 636 394 
Donor 6 
7 218 397 
781 771 
1 668 618 
861 667 
899 625 
165 147 
1 710 309 </p>

<p>Table 2. Percent of each RNA type in the larger size-fraction libraries (40-100 nt) </p>

<p>Donor 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>tRNA 
6.61 
7.59 
5.87 
3.46 
6.61 
5.46 
Ribosomal RNA 
50.06 
48.48 
52.56 
55.47 
56.88 
49.79 
Y RNA 
11.26 
12.77 
8.32 
12.22 
7.46 
9.50 
miRNA 
3.36 
4.09 
1.90 
2.32 
2.38 
3.26 
piwi-RNA 
0.04 
0.05 
0.03 
0.02 
0.03 
0.01 
Protein coding 
3.35 
4.72 
8.18 
4.26 
3.43 
7.99 
Other 
25.33 
22.28 
23.14 
22.25 
23.21 
23.98 </p>

<p>Table 3. Percent of each RNA type in the smaller size-fraction libraries (15-40 nt) </p>

<p>Donor 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>tRNA 
19.97 
24.18 
9.97 
12.83 
18.33 
10.83 
Ribosomal RNA 
20.69 
15.18 
13.66 
13.83 
23.99 
23.69 
Y RNA 
11.95 
18.18 
29.31 
32.74 
15.78 
11.94 
miRNA 
27.44 
20.80 
22.99 
19.61 
16.47 
23.12 
piwi-RNA 
4.72 
2.31 
1.96 
2.94 
2.28 
2.29 
Protein coding 
11.70 
7.10 
10.48 
8.07 
5.66 
12.46 
Other 
3.53 
12.25 
11.63 
9.98 
17.49 
15.67 </p>

<p>of the Ro and La ribonucleoprotein complexes (45), unex-
pectedly accounted for a substantial fraction of the RNA 
in both size fractions, with the smaller size fractions again 
holding a higher percentage of Y RNA reads than the larger 
fractions (mean 19.98% versus 10.25%), implying smaller 
fragmented Y RNA. Ribosomal RNA constituted 18.6% of 
the smaller fractions but was the most abundant of all RNA 
biotypes in the larger fractions (52.2%). The larger fractions 
also contained more 'other' RNA, which consists mainly 
of retained introns, processed transcripts, signal recognition 
particle RNA and fragments of larger non-coding RNA 
(mean for all 'other' RNA 23.4% versus 11.8% in the smaller 
libraries). Protein-coding mRNA fragments were present 
in both fractions (9.2% for smaller fractions and 5.3% for 
larger). These results show that SE carry several small RNA 
biotypes in likely full-length and fragmented forms, which 
could potentially exert regulatory activities when delivered 
to target cells. </p>

<p>A few mature miRNA species are highly enriched in SE </p>

<p>The abundance of mature miRNA in SE from all six semen 
donors encouraged us to look more closely at SE-specific 
miRNA signatures. Of the 2578 mature human miRNA </p>

<p>species identified in miRBase 20 (46-49), only 175 miR-
NAs were present in all six SE samples (6.8% of all known), 
and 436 miRNAs in at least one sample (16.9%). However, 
the miRNAs present in some but not all six donors were 
at extremely low abundance, never individually represent-
ing more than 0.05% of miRNA-specific sequencing reads 
in any given donor (Supplemental File 1). 
The distribution of reads mapping to each of the 175 
mature miRNA species common to all six donors corre-
lated highly between donors (median Spearman's = 0. 
86, range 0.78-0.92) (Supplemental Table S4). The most 
abundant miRNA in all donors was let-7b, accounting for 
a mean of 19.5% of the total miRNA reads (median 20.1%, 
range 13.7-25.1%) (Figure 3A). Let-7b and the next four 
most abundant miRNAs (miR-148a, let-7a, miR-375 and 
miR-99a) together accounted for 33.1% of the total miRNA 
reads (median 33.0%, range 29.7-37.7%), and adding in the 
next five most abundant miRNAs covered 41.8% of total 
miRNA reads (median 42.9%, range 37.9-43.7%) (Figure 
3A). We validated the hierarchical miRNA distribution de-
rived from the sequencing reads by quantifying the first 
through fifth most abundant miRNas (let-7b, miR-148, let-
7a, miR-375 and miR-99a) as well as two randomly selected 
miRNAs with much lower read counts (miR-28 and miR-</p>



<p>Figure 3. SE contain a few abundant miRNAs. (A) Top 15 most highly expressed unique miRNAs in SE. Left axis and bars: percent of total miRNA reads 
that mapped to each of the top 15 most abundant miRNAs. Error bars are standard deviation. Right axis and line: cumulative percent of total miRNA 
reads. (B) ddPCR analysis of miRNAs. RNA was isolated from three additional SE samples that had not been sequenced and assayed for miRNA levels 
by ddPCR assay. The five highest abundant (by sequencing) and two low abundance miRNAs were tested. Counts per l of input cDNA are shown for 
each of the three donors. All reactions were run in triplicate with extremely low standard deviations (error bars always fell within each symbol and are not 
shown for better visual clarity). miR28 was analyzed in two donors only. </p>

<p>103), using ddPCR assays with RNA isolated from SE from 
three additional, unsequenced donors. We confirmed the 
overall general hierarchical distribution of miRNAs, with 
the two lower abundant miRNAs by sequencing counts also 
being much lower by ddPCR copy number counts (on aver-
age 15 [miR-103] and 89 [miR-28] fold lower than the five 
most abundant miRNAs) (Figure 3B). These data demon-
strate high consistency of miRNA loading into SE from dif-
ferent healthy semen donors, with only a few select miRNA 
species being present in abundance. 
Because only a few miRNA species accounted for the ma-
jority of miRNA sequencing reads, we focused on the top 
10 miRNAs for our analysis of potential regulatory targets. 
Within these top 10 miRNAs there was one family with an 
identical 5' end seed regions: let-7b/7a, suggesting the pos-
sibility that some specific mRNA sequences are targeted by 
multiple SE-associated miRNAs. The current scientific lit-
erature indicates that a number of mRNA sequences that 
translate to immunity-related proteins could be regulated 
by miRNAs among the list of the top 10 miRNAs (Table 4) 
(50-61). Thus, it is feasible that the few abundant miRNAs 
in SE could influence pathways important for the immuno-
physiology of the genital tract. Thus, it is feasible that the 
few abundant miRNAs in SE could influence pathways im-
portant for the immunophysiology of the genital tract. </p>

<p>Y RNA in SE </p>

<p>Y RNAs are evolutionarily conserved small RNAs (83-112 
nt in humans) that fold into characteristic stem-loop struc-
tures similar to tRNAs. Y RNAs are known as compo-
nents of the autoantigen ribonucleoprotein complexes tar-
geted by antibodies from patients with Sjogren's syndrome 
and systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) (62). Their phys-
iological functions are poorly characterized, though they 
are reported to be involved in chromosomal DNA repli-
cation, in the response to UV damage, and in regulating 
small RNA biogenesis (63-69). Humans have four types of 
Y RNAs: hY1, hY3, hY4 and hY5, all of which are present 
in SE (Figure 4A). Sequencing reads demonstrate the pres-</p>

<p>ence of both full-length or ≥50 nt fragments (in the larger 
size-fractionated libraries) and smaller fragmented Y RNA 
forms (&lt;50 nts, in the smaller size-fractionated libraries), 
but the relative distribution of Y RNA types differed be-
tween the two libraries. The majority of Y RNA in both 
libraries was hY4. The larger library contained about 30% 
hY5, while the smaller library contained almost no hY5. 
Both libraries contained small amounts of hY1 and hY3 
(Figure 4A). The ratios of larger to smaller fragmented Y 
RNA read counts for the four Y RNA types were extremely 
consistent between the six donors (Table 5). Many Y RNAs 
in both size fractions mapped to genomic sequences anno-
tated as pseudogenes and predicted genes (Supplemental 
File 2). For all four Y RNA types, smaller fragment lengths 
consistently centered around 30-33 nt (Supplemental Fig-
ure S1A). For hY1, hY3 and hY5, &gt;95% of the smaller 
fragments mapped to the 5' ends of Y RNA, while for 
hY4 ∼80% of the smaller fragments mapped to the 5' end 
and 20% mapped to the 3' end (Supplemental Figure S1B). 
These data indicate that each Y RNA type is loaded into SE 
in a distinctive manner, implying a selective process. 
Y RNAs bind to the proteins Ro60 (SSA) and La (SSB) to 
form the Ro/La ribonucleoprotein complexes, which were 
first discovered and described as the auto-antigens targeted 
by antibodies generated in patients with auto-immune dis-
eases. To determine whether such ribonucleoprotein com-
plexes might also be present in SE, we stained SE protein ex-
tracts from four semen donors with anti-Ro antibody (Fig-
ure 4B). SE carried at least one of the two Ro isoforms (52 
kD and 60 kD) in each donor, while only one of the four SE-
depleted seminal plasma fractions contained Ro, suggesting 
that SE carry Ro ribonucleoprotein complexes. </p>

<p>tRNA in SE </p>

<p>We expected to find tRNAs in the larger sized RNA li-
braries, since mature tRNAs are ∼ 72 nt long and have been 
shown to be carried by exosomes (70). Indeed, tRNA ac-
counted for an average of 5.9% of reads in the larger size 
fractions (median 6.2%, range 3.5-7.6%) (Figure 2C and </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 11 7297 </p>

<p>Table 4. Immune related mRNAs are targeted by several of the most common miRNAs in SE </p>

<p>miRNAs among the top 10 most abundant SE-associated miRNAs with 
validated regulatory functions 
Immune-related mRNA targets </p>

<p>let-7 family 
SOC3 50 , CCL7 50 , IL-23R 51 , CIS 52 , IL-13 53 , IL-6 55 , IL-10 54,55 
miR-148a 
CaMKIIa 56 , HLA-C 57 , HLA-G 58 
mir-375 
JAK2 59 , TSLP 60 
miR-22 
IRF5 61 </p>

<p>Figure 4. SE carry Y RNA and the binding partner Ro protein. (A) Bar chart of the distribution of Y RNA in larger or smaller libraries by type. Percent 
reads mapping to each type are averaged across the six donors. (B) Western blot using anti-Ro antibody against SE lysate and exosome-depleted seminal 
plasma. SE lysates and plasma from four different individual SE samples were tested. HeLa cell lysate served as a positive control. </p>

<p>Table 5. Ratio of full-length to fragmented Y RNA for each donor </p>

<p>Donor 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>hY1 
0.29 
0.18 
0.16 
0.29 
0.26 
0.21 
hY3 
1.05 
1.61 
3.89 
3.28 
1.47 
1.20 
hY4 
0.83 
0.73 
0.61 
0.65 
0.58 
0.69 
hY5 
17.32 
57.32 
45.62 
30.85 
34.00 
23.51 </p>

<p>Table 2), the sequences of which corresponded to tRNAs 
with mature ends. Surprisingly, a substantial amount of 
fragmented tRNA was also present in the smaller size frac-
tions, accounting for 16.0% (median 15.6%, range 10.0-
24.2%) of total RNA (Figure 2C and Table 3). tRNA frag-
ments in the smaller library differed in amino acid isoac-
ceptor types from the tRNAs in the larger library (Fig-
ure 5A and Table 6), and these differences were highly 
consistent between donors (median Spearman's = 0.93, 
range 0.48-1.0, for smaller fragmented tRNA; = 0.95, 
range 0.90-1.0, for larger tRNA) (Supplemental Tables S5 
and S6). For example, tRNA-Gly sequences accounted for 
23.0% (median 21.8%, range 20.8-26.9%) of the tRNA in 
the larger libraries and 44.4% (median 40.8%, range 37.9-
58%) of the smaller fragmented tRNA, while tRNA-Ala 
represented only 0.62% (median 0.62%, range 0.27-0.84%) 
of tRNA reads in the larger libraries and 23.1% (median 
24.8%, range 13.5-30.0%) of smaller fragmented tRNAs. 
Fragment lengths also varied by isoacceptor type. For ex-
ample, tRNA-Gly and tRNA-Val fragments were primarily 
30-34 nt, while tRNA-Ala fragments were mostly 18-19 nt 
long (Figure 5B). Regardless of the length, the vast major-
ity of tRNA fragments mapped to the 5'-ends of mature tR-
NAs, with the exception of a few low-abundance isoaccep-
tor types (Met and Asp), which mapped to more diverse re-
gions including the 3' ends (Figure 5C). Thus, like miRNA </p>

<p>and Y RNA, tRNA types and fragments appear to be se-
lectively loaded into SE. </p>

<p>Protein-coding fragments in SE </p>

<p>Though exosomes can transfer mRNAs capable of trans-
lation to target cells (20,71), it is thought that the major-
ity of protein-coding RNA in exosomes is fragmented (26). 
Because we focused on sequencing small RNAs, our anal-
ysis does not include full-length mRNA in SE, but we did 
find protein-coding mRNA fragments of various sizes, ac-
counting for 5.3% of the total sequencing reads in the larger 
libraries and 9.2% in the smaller (Figure 2C). In contrast 
to miRNA, Y RNA and tRNA, the distribution of the 80 
most abundant mRNA fragments was much more variable 
between donors (median Spearman's = 0.18 range 0.11-
0.22, for the larger size fractions; = 0.20 range 0.16-0.26, 
for the smaller size fractions) (Supplemental Tables S7 and 
S8). Only one mRNA fragment, ENST0000360737, cor-
responding to an uncharacterized protein, was abundant 
in the libraries (Table 7), accounting for over 50% of the 
protein-coding reads in the smaller libraries. This transcript 
also contains the newly described miR-4763, however the 
fragments carried by SE map to a 24 bp region of the 3' 
UTR and not to the miRNA sequence. Other abundant 
protein-coding fragments are listed in Table 7. The remain-
ing majority of protein-coding fragments in SE each rep-
resented &lt;1% of total protein-coding reads. Despite this </p>



<p>Figure 5. SE carry tRNAs. (A) Bar chart of the distribution of tRNA in larger or smaller libraries by amino acid isoacceptor type. Percent reads mapping to 
each type are averaged across the six donors. (B) Histogram of fragment lengths in nucleotides for tRNA-Gly, tRNA-Ala and tRNA-Val smaller fragments. 
(C) Sequence coverage of tRNA fragments compared to full-length tRNAs to a resolution of 10 bps. The Y axis indicates the number of reads × 10 000. </p>

<p>Table 6. Ratio of full-length to fragmented tRNA for each donor </p>

<p>Donor 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>Gly 
0.64 
0.45 
0.57 
0.53 
0.42 
0.55 
Ala 
0.02 
0.06 
0.03 
0.02 
0.03 
0.01 
Val 
1.71 
1.50 
1.69 
1.89 
1.46 
1.47 
Glu 
5.00 
7.43 
4.28 
3.53 
5.06 
3.44 
Lys 
3.37 
0.75 
2.23 
2.77 
2.70 
3.14 
Leu 
0.53 
0.09 
0.54 
1.21 
0.96 
0.69 
Asp 
15.26 
3.40 
4.20 
6.23 
3.94 
4.95 
Other 
0.27 
0.97 
0.15 
0.24 
0.25 
0.17 </p>

<p>diversity, the relatively more abundant fragments mapped 
to only one small segment in the 5' or 3' untranslated re-
gions (UTR) of the mRNA (Table 7), rather than randomly 
across sequences as would be expected if fragments were 
non-selectively packaged into SE. Of interest, we could not 
identify any of the mRNA sequences loaded into SE as po-
tential target sequences for the co-loaded miRNAs, indicat-
ing that mRNA and miRNA molecules in SE do not asso-
ciate with each other. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Sexual intercourse is the primary route of transmission for 
many infections. Semen, beyond simply carrying pathogens, 
has well-documented immunosuppressive effects which 
may influence the infection of new hosts (72). The pre-
cise impact of semen on cellular functions important in 
pathogen response remains poorly understood and is com-
plicated by the fact that unfractionated seminal plasma con-
tains many components, some of which can enhance and 
others inhibit viral infection of mucosal cells (7,72-78). 
Thus, the overall role semen plays in infectious disease de-</p>

<p>pends on multiple complex factors in semen itself as well as 
the interactions of these factors with the specific pathogens 
and with resident genital tract cells. 
Given that exosomes are demonstrated agents of immune 
information (79), and that small RNAs in exosomes can af-
fect target cells (80), we explored the small RNA content 
of SE for potential immunomodulatory features. We have 
established a protocol to isolate SE from semen, which con-
sistently results in 10 
12 or more purified particles per ejac-
ulate. These particles have the characteristics of exosomes 
and microvesicles: (i) lipid-bound round shape and size of 
40-200 nm, (ii) purify in a density of 1.10-1.27 g/cm 
3 and 
(iii) express common exosome markers CD63 and HSP70 
and lack expression of the endoplasmic-reticulum marker 
calnexin (Figure 1 A-C). We were surprised that a substan-
tial fraction of RNA in 0.22 m filtered seminal plasma was 
found in the exosomal fraction, because this is in contrast 
to findings from blood plasma and cell culture supernatant, 
where the majority of extracellular RNA and particularly 
miRNA appears independent of exosomes (21-24,31,32). 
The RNA in SE was particularly enriched for small RNAs </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 11 7299 </p>

<p>Table 7. mRNA fragments found in SE. Abundance number indicates the mean percent of reads mapping to protein-coding sequences (range). UTR = 
untranslated region </p>

<p>mRNA 
Abundance 
Location </p>

<p>Number (length) of regions 
represented </p>

<p>ENST00000360737 
56.1% (47.4-67.6%) 
3' UTR 
1 (24 bp) 
ENST00000335648 
7.3% (3.8-9.5%) 
5' UTR 
1 (32 bp) 
ATAD-5 
4.6% (2.7-6.0%) 
3' UTR 
1 (32 bp) 
NSRP1 
3.7% (2.6-4.7%) 
5' UTR 
1 (34 bp) 
ENST00000284727 
2.6% (1.2-3.3%) 
3' UTR 
1 (48 bp) </p>

<p>ranging in lengths from 20 to 100 nts (Figure 2A and B). By 
deep sequencing of these small RNAs, we found that their 
repertoire included miRNAs with known immunomodula-
tory functions, as well as other small non-coding RNAs rep-
resenting short, &lt;50 nt fragments and larger, possibly full-
length, fragments of &gt;50 nts. 
Numerous reports demonstrate that in cell culture condi-
tions, intercellular communication can be mediated through 
miRNA delivered by exosomes, affecting processes includ-
ing viral infection, immune responses and cancer progres-
sion (19,20). However, most of these experiments were con-
ducted in somewhat artificial conditions and the relevance 
of this kind of messaging in vivo has yet to be demonstrated. 
The concentration of individual RNA molecules in each ex-
osome is very small, and whether they can be delivered to 
the proper location in cells in sufficient quantities to actu-
ally regulate cellular targets in vivo remains unclear (19,81). 
In contrast to exosomes from blood plasma, however, exo-
somes in semen are delivered at a high concentration to a 
limited anatomical area--the recipient female genital tract. 
Our preliminary evidence suggests that phagocytic cells of 
the genital mucosa preferentially take up exosomes (data 
not shown). Based on measurement of the size of the vagi-
nal cavity (82), the density of intraepithelial dendritic cells 
(Langerhans cells) (83) and the high number of SE in each 
ejaculate it is feasible that phagocytes in the recipient geni-
tal tract are exposed to and could take up thousands to tens 
of thousands of SE per cell, likely above the threshold for 
triggering physiological effects. Experiments to clarify this 
hypothesis are in progress in our laboratory. 
Based on the observation that all cells studied thus far 
secrete exosomes and microvesicles (68), it is likely that SE 
are derived from all tissues in the male genital tract that are 
connected to the semen-carrying ejaculatory system. In this 
work we describe in SE the presence of piwi-RNA, a small 
RNA species expressed primarily in germline cells (84), im-
plying that some SE are derived from spermatozoa. Addi-
tionally, polyclonal antisera that were raised against SE sug-
gested a polytopic origin of the microvesicles, because when 
used for immunostaining the antisera reacted with testes, 
the epididymis, accessory sex glands and the prostate (10). 
Thus, since the complex makeup of SE cannot be mimicked 
by a single cell culture system, we could not compare the 
small RNA profiles of SE to their cells of origin. However, 
based on similar sequencing studies comparing exosomes 
and the cells that make them, it is likely that the RNA con-
tent of SE is also distinct from the cells of origin and that 
small RNAs are specifically packaged and secreted in SE, 
potentially for the purpose of altering the function of target 
cells (21,27,70). </p>

<p>miRNA </p>

<p>Mature functional miRNAs of 22 nts are derived from hair-
pin precursors of ∼70 nts. By sequencing two distinct RNA 
size fractions, we easily distinguished between mature and 
pre-miRNA and found that SE contained mature miRNAs 
and also pre-miRNA. miRNA accounted for ∼21.7% of the 
total sequencing reads in our smaller size fractions (Fig-
ure 2C). Only a small subset of miRNAs are packaged in 
SE; of 2578 known human miRNAs, 175 mature miRNAs 
were found in all six semen donors and 434 were detected at 
greater than the detection threshold in at least one donor. 
The abundance of specific miRNAs was remarkably con-
sistent between SE isolated from different donors; the cor-
relation coefficient of sequencing reads of the 175 com-
mon miRNAs was &gt;0.78 for all donors (Supplemental Ta-
ble S4). Furthermore, only a few miRNAs accounted for 
the majority of sequencing reads (Figure 3A). A compari-
son of sequencing studies of miRNA in exosomes isolated 
from saliva, breast milk, dendritic cell-T cell co-cultures, 
human blood plasma, prion-infected cells, glioma cells and 
trophoblast cultures show that SE share at most 3 of the 
10 most abundant miRNAs (21,27,70,85-89). Let-7b is the 
most common, being an abundant exosomal miRNA in five 
of these eight studies, with miR-30d found in four of eight. 
Thus, the profile of abundant miRNAs carried by exosomes 
varies according to their cell of origin and may represent 
the different functions of exosomes in various body systems. 
Accordingly, exosomes in semen exhibited a unique miRNA 
profile that differed markedly from the profiles found in ex-
osomes of other origins. 
Micro and piwi-RNAs in seminal plasma and/or semi-
nal microvesicles have been described in three other papers, 
primarily with the intent of finding RNA markers for as-
sessing fertility (90-92). Hu et al. (90) focused on RNAs 
differing between the unfractionated seminal plasma from 
vasectomized and normal men, making a comparison to 
our study difficult, though 89% of miRNAs they found 
were also found in our study. Belleannee et al. (92) used 
a microarray approach to identify known miRNAs in mi-
crovesicles isolated from semen. They report 293 miRNAs 
detected in SE pooled from normal men; in comparison 
we detected 175 present in all donors, and another 271 in 
at least one donor. Microarray and RNAseq technologies 
have platform-inherent biases and the reliability of miRNA 
quantification likely differs between these two approaches 
(93). Nevertheless, we found a notable degree of overlap be-
tween the miRNAs they report and those we found; for ex-
ample, all of our top 10 most abundant miRNAs are within 
the top 100 ranked miRNAs in their study, and the top 10 </p>



<p>from their study are all within our top 85. The third study 
by Li et al. (91) suggested that in contrast to our study sem-
inal miRNAs are mostly in the supernatant rather than the 
vesicle-associated fraction of seminal plasma. The authors 
base this conclusion on only four particular miRNAs tested 
(detected by qPCR), which represent &lt;0.02% of miRNA 
reads in our study. This very limited universe of miRNAs 
studied may explain why their conclusions differed from 
ours. 
The abundant miRNAs in SE could significantly impact 
the immune function of target cells in the recipient genital 
mucosa. A number of immune-related mRNAs are targeted 
by several of the most abundant miRNAs carried by SE (Ta-
ble 4) and impaired production of any of these proteins in 
SE-exposed genital leukocytes would alter the normal im-
mune response to pathogens, as some studies have shown. 
For example, miR-148a was the second most abundant 
miRNA in SE; it can also be induced by lipopolysaccha-
ride in dendritic cells, where it targets calcium/calmodulin-
dependent protein kinase II (CaMKII), leading to reduced 
MHC II expression and secretion of cytokines, and inhi-
bition of DC-mediated T cell expansion (56). Let-7 family 
members, also abundant in SE, control the expression of IL-
10 and IL-13 in macrophages following pathogenic stimu-
lus, as well as IL-13 in T cells (53,55). 
Whether miRNAs can be delivered by SE to genital 
leukocytes in sufficient quantity to target genes and change 
cellular function is unknown. However, given the potential 
for miRNAs delivered by SE to play important roles in reg-
ulating immune responses and viral infection in target cells 
and the selective enrichment of a few miRNAs in SE, this 
possibility should be studied further. </p>

<p>Y RNA </p>

<p>The presence of putatively full-length and fragmented Y 
RNA in SE is consistent with other sequencing studies of 
exosomal small RNAs (70). In a study comparing exoso-
mal small RNA to small RNA profiles in their cells of ori-
gin, it was found that Y RNA was enriched in the small 
RNA fraction of exosomes as compared to cells, suggesting 
that it is selectively incorporated into exosomes (27). The 
majority of sequences we identified in the larger libraries 
were likely full length, because ∼99% of sequences started 
at the 5' end and were 50 nts long (the length limit of our 
sequencing assay). In our exosomal samples hY4 was the 
most abundant Y RNA, in both larger and smaller sequenc-
ing libraries, while hY1 was present mainly as smaller frag-
ments and hY5 mainly as larger or full-length Y RNA (Fig-
ure 4A). Sequences that mapped to Y RNA transcripts in 
Ensembl fell into one of three categories: (i) the four hu-
man Y RNAs (hY1, hY2, hY3 and hY5), (ii) pseudogenes 
from the four human genes and (iii) Y RNAs predicted in 
the Rfam database (94). We found that 45% of Y RNA in 
the larger libraries mapped to Y RNA pseudogenes (Sup-
plemental File 2) (95), providing strong evidence that these 
genes are actually expressed. 
In apoptotic cells, a caspase-dependant mechanism gen-
erates 5' Y RNA fragments that are 33 nt in length, mapping 
to a predicted internal loop (69). Such 33 nt fragments rep-
resented the majority of smaller fragments in our data. Y </p>

<p>RNA fragments of 33 nt mapping to pseudogenes have also 
been found as complexes in blood serum (96). Most proteins 
that bind Y RNAs are involved in alternative splicing and 
the regulation of translation, thus one function of Y RNAs 
could be post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression 
(95). Interestingly, Y RNAs are among the few host RNAs 
that are packaged along with viral genomes into virions, 
where it has been suggested that they enhance viral assem-
bly, stability or infectivity (97,98). Otherwise, it is currently 
unknown what roles Y RNA or Y RNA fragments might 
play in exosomes, though Nolte-t'-Hoen et al. suggest that 
they could be involved in sorting regulatory RNAs into ex-
osomes, in stabilizing other RNAs for export, or in guiding 
other RNAs to specific locations in target cells (27). 
We also found that the Y RNA-binding protein Ro is car-
ried by exosomes (Figure 4B), most likely bound to full-
length Y RNAs. Ro/La/Y-RNA ribonucleoprotein com-
plexes (RNPs) are the major autoantigenic targets in the 
autoimmune diseases Sjögren's syndrome and SLE. These 
complexes have also been found in exosomes secreted by 
epithelial cells derived from salivary glands, which are the 
main target organs for autoimmunity in Sjögren's syndrome 
(99). Sjögren's syndrome and SLE occur nearly 10 times as 
frequently in women than men, and clinical onset of SLE 
is most often between 15 and 35 years of age when sexual 
activity begins and is highest. It is therefore tempting to hy-
pothesize that exposure to RNPs carried by SE plays a role 
in triggering or maintaining SLE in young women. </p>

<p>tRNA </p>

<p>We found tRNA of full-length or ≥50 nt fragments, as well 
as numerous smaller tRNA fragments in SE (Figure 5a). 
tRNA fragments have been described in other types of ex-
osomes (27), as well as in sperm (100,101) and as abundant 
complexes in blood serum (96). Many studies have demon-
strated that tRNA fragmentation is a specific process that 
depends on cell type and cell state, and tRNA fragments 
have recently gained attention for their regulatory poten-
tial and a possible role in stress response (25,102,103). In 
mammalian cells, the stress-activated ribonuclease angio-
genin cleaves tRNAs in or near the anti-codon internal loop 
to generate fragments of 30-34 nt, known as tRNA halves 
(104). The 5' ends of these tRNA halves inhibit translation 
by displacing components of the translation initiation com-
plex (105). We find 5' end tRNA fragments, predominantly 
30-34 nt tRNA halves derived from tRNA-Gly and tRNA-
Val, consistent with angiogenin cleavage, in SE (Figure 5b). 
Though only nine different 5'-tRNA fragments were tested, 
tRNA-Gly halves, which are the most abundant tRNA frag-
ments in SE, were one of the few found to be significant re-
pressors of translation (105). Additionally, smaller tRNA 
fragments of 19 nt have also been shown to inhibit transla-
tion non-specifically (106). These fragments require a GG 
motif in the 3' end of the molecule to repress translation, 
which is present in the 19 nt tRNA-Ala fragments we ob-
serve in SE. Thus, multiple tRNA fragments found in SE 
could globally and non-specifically inhibit translation in 
cells that take up SE. In addition, some 3'-derived tRNA 
fragments have been found to be associated with argonaute 
proteins and thus potentially act as miRNAs. However, we </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 11 7301 </p>

<p>observed very few 3' tRNA fragments in SE, so tRNA-
derived specific translation repression mediated by SE is un-
likely. </p>

<p>Protein-coding mRNA fragments </p>

<p>It has recently become apparent that post-transcriptional 
cleavage of messenger RNA is a regulated and tissue-
specific process (107). The mRNA fragments we detected 
in SE were not individually abundant, with the vast ma-
jority of transcripts each accounting for &lt;1% of the total 
reads attributed to protein-coding RNA (Table 5). In addi-
tion to the diversity of different transcripts in SE, mRNA 
fragments found in SE were diverse across donors, with the 
lowest correlations of sequencing counts for any RNA bio-
type analyzed (Supplemental Tables S7 and S8). However, it 
is unlikely that these RNAs are non-selectively incorporated 
into SE, because for most transcripts very specific small 
fragments of mRNA corresponding to only one region were 
found, rather than fragments spread over entire transcripts 
(Table 5). We found that all protein-coding fragments that 
represented over 2% of the reads in this category mapped 
to untranslated rather than coding regions (Table 5). Small 
untranslated mRNA fragments have been proposed to play 
a role in regulating translation of their matching transcripts 
(26), though whether the particular mRNA fragments in SE 
function in this way are unknown. 
For all of the small RNA classes we detected in SE, the 
distribution of cleavage fragments was not random between 
donors, suggesting some mechanism of selective loading 
or retention. The discrepancy between tRNA and Y RNA 
types in the larger and smaller libraries in SE further sug-
gests a selective loading process beyond simply reflecting 
abundance in the cells or origin. For tRNA and Y RNA, 
5' end fragments generated by cleavage in predicted inter-
nal loops in the secondary RNA structures appear to be 
preferentially loaded into SE. The 5' ends of cleaved nucleic 
acids are likely to be 5'-monophosphates, while the 5' ends 
of 3' fragments are more likely to be hydroxyl groups (104). 
miRNAs and piwi-RNAs have 5' monophosphates as well. 
Thus the structural predilection for 5'-monophosphate ends 
could hold clues regarding the mechanism of selective RNA 
loading into exosomes, occurring either by selection of 
molecules with 5' phosphates during the process of load-
ing or merely by providing increased stability and longevity. 
More research will be required to clarify how small RNA 
molecules are selectively loaded into exosomes. 
In conclusion, we classified the extracellular RNA in hu-
man semen, finding the majority was contained and pro-
tected within the exosomal fraction. We found that RNA 
loading into SE is a biologically consistent and highly selec-
tive process, with very little variation between different se-
men donors. Many of the most abundant small RNAs in SE 
have important regulatory potential for target cells that take 
up exosomes. Given the rapidly accumulating evidence that 
exosomes in other systems can deliver regulatory RNAs, 
and that SE carry a unique and selective profile of RNAs, 
it will be interesting to study their functional consequences 
on immune cells in the mucosa in detail. This may lead to a 
better understanding of how exosomal RNA-mediated reg-</p>

<p>ulation contributes to fertilization, but also how it may com-
promise natural or vaccine-induced immunity to infection. </p>

<p>ACCESSION NUMBER </p>

<p>GEO GSE56076 </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank the semen donors who 
contributed to this study. M. Juliana McElrath is head of 
the clinic where samples were collected. Julie Czartoski, 
Janine Maenza, Christine Galloway and Gina Braun as-
sisted with collecting samples and with donor recruitment. 
Thanks to Kim Woodrow from the Department of Bio-
engineering at the University of Washington and David 
Willoughby from Ocean Ridge Biosciences for very help-
ful discussions and comments. We also were assisted by the 
Electron Microscopy Shared Resource at the Fred Hutchin-
son Cancer Research Center. The content is solely the re-
sponsibility of the authors and does not necessarily repre-
sent the official view of the National Institutes of Health or 
other funders. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>R01 [HD051455]; R21 [AI095023]; Royalty Research Grant 
from the University of Washington (to F.H.); Damon 
Runyon-Rachleff Innovation Award, US National In-
stitutes of Health Transformative R01 [R01DK085714]; 
Stand Up To Cancer Innovative Research [SU2C-AACR-
IRG1109, all to M.T.]; CFAR Emerging Opportunities 
Grant [P30 AI027757]; Interdisciplinary Training Grant 
funded by the National Cancer Institute of the National 
Institutes of Health [T32CA080416 to L.V.]. Source of 
Open Access funding: National Institutes of Health R21 
[AI095023]. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







</text></tei>