<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4826955" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury increases the risk of meniscus and articular cartilage damage, but the causes 
are not well understood. Previous in vitro studies were static, required extensive knee dissection, and likely altered meniscal and 
cartilage contact due to the insertion of pressure sensing devices. </p>

<p>Hypothesis: ACL deficiency will lead to increased translation of the lateral meniscus and increased deformation of the medial 
meniscus as well as alter cartilage contact location, strain, and area. </p>

<p>Study Design: Descriptive laboratory study. </p>

<p>Methods: With minimally invasive techniques, six 1.0-mm tantalum beads were implanted into the medial and lateral menisci of 
6 fresh-frozen cadaveric knees. Dynamic stereo x-rays (DSXs) were obtained during dynamic knee flexion (from 15 
to 60 
, 
simulating a standing squat) with a 46-kg load in intact and ACL-deficient states. Knee kinematics, meniscal movement and 
deformation, and cartilage contact were compared by novel imaging coregistration. </p>

<p>Results: During dynamic knee flexion from 15 
to 60 
, the tibia translated 2.6 mm (P ¼ .05) more anteriorly, with 2.3 
more internal 
rotation (P ¼ .04) with ACL deficiency. The medial and lateral menisci, respectively, translated posteriorly an additional 0.7 mm 
(P ¼ .05) and 1.0 mm (P ¼ .03). Medial and lateral compartment cartilage contact location moved posteriorly (2.0 mm [P ¼ .05] and 
2.0 mm [P ¼ .04], respectively). </p>

<p>Conclusion: The lateral meniscus showed greater translation with ACL deficiency compared with the medial meniscus, which may 
explain the greater incidences of acute lateral meniscus tears and chronic medial meniscus tears. Furthermore, cartilage contact 
location moved further posteriorly than that of the meniscus in both compartments, possibly imparting more meniscal stresses that 
may lead to early degeneration. This new, minimally invasive, dynamic in vitro model allows the study of meniscus function and 
cartilage contact and can be applied to evaluate different pathologies and surgical techniques. </p>

<p>Clinical Relevance: This novel model illustrates that ACL injury may lead to significant meniscus and cartilage abnormalities 
acutely, and these parameters are dynamically measurable while maintaining native anatomy. </p>

<p>Keywords: knee; meniscus; meniscal deformation; meniscal movement; cartilage contact </p>

<p>The anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) is an important 
restraint against anterior tibial translation, medial trans-
lation, and internal rotation, working in concert with other 
soft tissues and bony geometry to guide tibiofemoral kine-
matics during knee motion. 
2,13 The medial and lateral 
menisci deform along the tibiofemoral joint line to guide </p>

<p>tibiofemoral contact and improve load distribution and play 
a pivotal role in maintaining joint health after ACL injury, 
with or without reconstruction. Injury to the ACL is asso-
ciated with high risk for subsequent meniscal injury and 
degenerative changes of the articular surfaces. </p>

<p>6,8,15,19,20   Because ACL injury alters knee kinematics, meniscal 
loading and movement may also be altered, possibly com-
promising knee joint load distribution and contact con-
gruity. 
2,6,26 There are, however, few data to support this 
conjecture. </p>

<p>The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine, 4(4), 2325967116639895 
DOI: 10.1177/2325967116639895 </p>

<p>ª The Author(s) 2016 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>This open-access article is published and distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution -NonCommercial -No Derivatives License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/), which permits the noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction of the article in any medium, provided the original author and source are 
credited. You may not alter, transform, or build upon this article without the permission of the Author(s). For reprints and permission queries, please visit SAGE's Web site 
at http://www.sagepub.com/journalsPermissions.nav. </p>

<p>Numerous biomechanical studies have attempted to 
evaluate meniscal function and injury by measuring tibio-
femoral contact area or stress; however, few have directly 
examined meniscal motion and deformation as well as car-
tilage parameters in healthy and ACL-deficient knees. Pre-
vious studies assessing tibiofemoral contact and/or 
meniscal motion have employed methods requiring exten-
sive dissections that disrupt the native knee anatomy and 
function. 
3,18,23 Many of these have used sensing methods 
such as strain gauges to characterize meniscal strain or, 
more commonly, pressure sensors to measure contact. It 
is likely that the insertion of these types of devices alters 
the contact mechanics and the devices themselves result in 
unrepresentative measurements and an inaccurate model 
of the joint's true dynamics. 
16 Studies evaluating the 
meniscus have used static in vivo magnetic resonance ima-
ging (MRI) at various flexion angles but with low loads and 
in varying positions, limiting their clinical application. </p>

<p>10,27,31   Furthermore, although previous studies have evaluated 
these parameters individually, none have evaluated the 
complex dynamic interaction between knee kinematics, car-
tilage contact, meniscal motion, and deformation in the 
intact knee as well as changes in these relationships after 
ACL injury of the same knee. 
Based on these shortcomings, the purpose of this study 
was to develop a new cadaveric model that was physiologi-
cally loaded, dynamic, and simulated a functional activity 
while maintaining native knee anatomy. We hypothesized 
that with ACL deficiency there will be greater lateral 
meniscal translation and greater medial meniscal deforma-
tion as well as changes in cartilage contact location, strain, 
and area. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Specimen Preparation </p>

<p>Six fresh-frozen human cadaveric knees (mean age, 44 
years; range, 39-49 years) were screened with fluoroscopy 
(Philips BV Pulsera) to ensure they were free of osteoar-
thritis and abnormal ligamentous laxity. Six 1.0 mm-dia-
meter tantalum beads were implanted into the medial and 
lateral menisci using minimally invasive surgical tech-
niques. For each bead, a vertical incision was made and 
dissection was carried down to the meniscus, being careful 
to maintain native ligamentous structures and minimize 
capsular trauma; then the meniscus was marked with a 
marking pen. The bead was placed in a hip arthroscopy 
needle with a bone wax plug in the tip and the needle 
pushed into the meniscus. The plunger was then used to 
evacuate the bead (Figure 1A). Two beads were placed in </p>

<p>each of 3 regions: anterior horn, midportion, and posterior 
horn. Bead locations were confirmed with fluoroscopy, and 
the capsule and other soft tissues were sutured (Figure 1, B 
and C). Three additional beads were implanted into the 
femur and tibia for bone tracking by dissecting down to 
bone, where a pilot hole was drilled. The beads were placed 
in different planes, and locations were confirmed with 
fluoroscopy. Bone wax was again placed during implanta-
tion as well as over the pilot hole to secure the bead, and the 
overlying soft tissue was sutured. The quadriceps tendon 
was isolated, and the femur and tibia were potted in custom 
molds using fiberglass resin (Bondo Body Filler). </p>

<p>Computed Tomography and 
Magnetic Resonance Imaging </p>

<p>3-T MRIs (0.6-mm isotropic voxels; 3D double-echo steady-
state [DESS]; Siemens Trio) were acquired to generate 
3-dimensional (3D) bone and meniscal models and to con-
firm bead placement and identify meniscal root insertions. 
Cartilage was manually segmented on MRI 3D DESS 
sequences and models were created using <rs id="software-4" type="software">Mimics Software</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Materialise</rs>). 
28 Computed tomography (CT) images (0.6-
mm slices; GE LightSpeed 16) were obtained to identify </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>Address correspondence to Christopher D. Harner, MD, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, University of Texas at Houston, 6400 Fannin Street, Suite 
1700, Houston, TX 77030, USA (email: christopher.harner@uth.tmc.edu). 
*Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA. </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Department of Mechanical Engineering, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA. </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, University of Texas at Houston, Houston, Texas, USA. 
One or more of the authors has declared the following potential conflict of interest or source of funding: This study was sponsored by the 2013 American 
Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine (AOSSM) Young Investigator Award. </p>

<p>Figure 1. (A) Minimally invasive bead implantation technique. 
(B) Meniscus bead locations confirmed (n ¼ 12) with fluoro-
scopy. (C) Knee in testing apparatus with quadriceps clamp 
after 12 meniscus beads and 6 bone beads were implanted. </p>

<p> 
The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine </p>

<p>bone bead placement and to create 3D femur and tibia 
models. 
Bead migration was evaluated by comparing bead-to-
bead distance on MRI and all dynamic and static trials. 
DSX data were collected before knees were loaded, between 
trials without load, and without load after all trials were 
completed. If any change in bead-to-bead distance occured 
between these unloaded trials, these data were not used. 
Two knees were excluded due to bead migration and quad-
riceps failure at this load. Only knees with no bead migra-
tion were included. </p>

<p>Dynamic Stereo X-ray Testing </p>

<p>The knees were secured in a custom-designed Oxford-style 
knee apparatus (5 degrees of freedom) with actuator-
controlled quadriceps tendon force (Figures 1C and 2). The 
apparatus was unlocked and the actuator was tensioned so 
the knee was held in extension while a 46-kg axial load was 
applied on the top of the knee apparatus. This load repre-
sents approximately 1.3Â body weight during a 2-legged 
squat of a person weighing 80 kg and is within the limits 
of the quadriceps clamp used in the study. The quadriceps 
was then allowed to lengthen, providing an eccentric load, 
using a remote control via the actuator. This allowed the 
knee to undergo controlled dynamic flexion by the 46-kg 
axial load on top of the apparatus from 15  to 60 
, simulat-
ing a squat, all while high-speed dynamic stereo x-ray 
(DSX) images (90 kVp, 160 mA) were collected at 30 frames 
per second. The 60 
of flexion angle was chosen as it is a 
common knee flexion angle during daily activities and was 
within the range of our testing apparatus. 
21 The ACL was 
then arthroscopically transected while the knee remained 
in the apparatus, and testing was repeated using a goni-
ometer to insure the same starting position. </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>DSX data were transferred to custom computerized soft-
ware, and radiographic images were corrected for distor-
tion and intensity gradient. As previously described, the 
positions of the implanted bone and meniscal beads were 
tracked and reconstructed into the 3D laboratory coordi-
nate system in custom software with 0.1-mm precision 
(Figure 3). 
4,5,26 The CT scans were segmented and recon-
structed into 3D specimen-specific femur and tibia models, 
and anatomic coordinate systems were manually estab-
lished. 
25 Knee kinematics (femoral and tibial bone positions) 
was determined by 3D locations of bone beads. Meniscal 
kinematics and deformation were determined by evaluating 
movement of meniscal beads relative to the tibia using cus-
tom <rs id="software-7" type="software">MATLAB software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="creator">MathWorks Inc</rs>). 
An ellipse, using the least-squares method, was mathe-
matically fit to the 6 meniscal beads and the meniscal root 
insertions for each meniscus, which were identified on MRI 
as described (Figure 4). The overall meniscal translation 
was characterized by the movement of the center of the 
ellipse and was compared between the ACL-intact and 
ACL-deficient states. The change in arc length between 
beads was used to measure circumferential meniscal defor-
mation in the anterior, middle, and posterior regions in the 
2 states. Radial deformation was measured between the 
center of the ellipse and the bead locations in these same 
regions. Finally, we measured vertical deformation, or 
meniscal compression, by the vertical movement of the 
beads relative to the underlying tibia, which was converted 
to a percentage relative to the unloaded knee. Each knee 
was compared with its unloaded static state. 
MRI bone and cartilage models as well as CT bone mod-
els were coregistered with DSX data, and the overlap of the 
cartilage models was evaluated using a previously </p>

<p>Figure 2. Custom Oxford-style knee apparatus in the dynamic stereo x-ray system. </p>

<p>The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine 
ACL Deficiency Effects on the Meniscus and Cartilage 3 </p>

<p>validated method to determine centroid weighted cartilage 
contact location, mean strain, and mean area of both the 
ACL-intact and ACL-deficient states (Figure 5). 
9,14,28 Two-
way repeated-measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) 
using <rs id="software-8" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">IBM Corp</rs>) was utilized to compare the 2 states 
at angle increments of 5 
of flexion (P &lt; .05). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Kinematics </p>

<p>During a simulated squat, with ACL deficiency, the tibia 
translated 2.6 ± 0.26 mm more anteriorly (P ¼ .05) with 
2.3 
± 0.34 
more internal rotation (P ¼ .04), with the 
highest values seen from 25  to 35 
with both parameters 
(Figures 6 and 7). </p>

<p>Meniscal Movement and Deformation </p>

<p>The medial meniscus translated, on average, 2.3 mm pos-
teriorly during dynamic knee flexion while the lateral 
meniscus translated 3.2 mm posteriorly in the intact knee. 
In the ACL-deficient state, the medial and lateral meniscus 
translated an additional 0.7 ± 0.12 mm (P ¼ .08) and 1.0 ± 
0.16 mm (P ¼ .05) in the posterior direction; in the lateral 
meniscus, this change was statistically significant. Vertical 
deformation, or meniscal compression, increased with ACL 
deficiency-anterior (14% ± 1.1%, P ¼ .08), middle (12% ± 
0.90%, P ¼ .09), and overall-but was not significantly dif-
ferent. The change in circumferential and radial deforma-
tion was minimal. Dynamic data can be seen in Figure 8. </p>

<p>Cartilage Contact </p>

<p>With ACL deficiency, medial and lateral compartment car-
tilage contact location moved significantly posteriorly (2.0 ± 
0.20 mm [P ¼ .05] and 2.0 ± 0.23 mm [P ¼ .04]). Cartilage-
to-cartilage contact percent area decreased by 2.2% ± 0.32% 
in the lateral compartment but was not significant 
(P ¼ .06), while the medial compartment showed no change 
in contact area. Medial-to-lateral cartilage contact location 
movement was no different between the 2 states. These 
differences from the intact state were greater at lower knee 
flexion angles. Cartilage strain was not significantly differ-
ent in either compartment. Dynamic data can be seen in 
Figure 9. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The majority of our results are consistent with previous 
static in vitro and in vivo studies and our hypothesis; how-
ever, the model and means are novel. ACL-deficient knees 
had greater anterior tibial translation and internal rotation 
compared with knees in the intact state. 
12,24 Meniscal 
translation was greater in the lateral compartment than 
in the medial compartment in the intact state and 
increased with ACL deficiency, and cartilage contact loca-
tion was more posterior in both compartments after ACL 
transection. These dynamic results confirm our hypotheses 
and qualitatively are consistent with static in vitro 
studies. </p>

<p>12,17   We expect that modifications to the testing protocol 
would elicit more pronounced changes in these parameters 
with ACL deficiency. The flexion angles of this initial study 
were limited to 60 
maximum, and the applied weight was 
limited to 46 kg due to limitations of the quadriceps clamp 
and the testing apparatus used. Deeper flexion, we believe, 
will lead to greater meniscal displacements and deforma-
tions, 
33 as will increased loads. Although our load was con-
siderably greater than that of other studies, for future work 
we plan to develop an improved quadriceps clamp that can 
sustain increased loads. However, the peak quadriceps 
force measured during testing was similar to that of squat-
ting. 
30 Furthermore, our knee apparatus limits us to only 
test the activity of a squat. A greater number of specimens 
may provide better statistical data: a post hoc power </p>

<p>Figure 4. Model created from combining computed tomogra-
phy, magnetic resonance imaging, and dynamic stereo x-ray 
testing data that shows the meniscus beads with the mathe-
matically fitted ellipse (used for evaluation of meniscal defor-
mation) and its center (used for evaluation of meniscal 
translation). Blue, anterior cruciate ligament (ACL)-intact; 
pink, ACL-deficient. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Images obtained from dynamic stereo x-ray testing. </p>

<p> 
The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine </p>

<p>analysis suggested a much greater sample size (&gt;100) for 
detecting a significant difference in the deformation results 
with a power of &gt;0.8. Standardized bead placement was 
difficult due to the minimally invasive technique as was 
securing the beads. This may impart some form of experi-
mental error; however, the algorithm used mathematically 
minimized that error. For future testing, we plan to use 
better bead fixation techniques and also increase knee flex-
ion angle and axial loading. 
The changes in meniscus translation observed with ACL 
deficiency appear to reflect the greater mobility of the lat-
eral meniscus, possibly having implications for meniscal 
tears, both acutely and chronically. Although not able to 
be concluded from this study, the authors believe 1 or more 
millimeters of shift in the meniscus and/or cartilage may </p>

<p>lead to degeneration overtime due to loss of normal contact 
between the articular cartilage of the tibia and femur. Dur-
ing dynamic knee flexion in the intact knee, the lateral 
meniscus translated more than the medial meniscus, and 
as knee flexion angle increased so did lateral meniscus pos-
terior translation. With ACL deficiency, both menisci 
showed increased posterior translation, with a greater 
increase in the lateral compared with the medial meniscus. 
A greater difference was seen at low knee flexion angles. 
These results are consistent with our hypotheses; as the 
tibia translates anteriorly with knee flexion, the menisci 
are pulled posteriorly on the tibia, with greater effect on 
the more mobile lateral meniscus. </p>

<p>24,29,33   Using different methodologies and low loads, previous 
studies found highly variable normal meniscal translations, </p>

<p>Figure 7. Tibial internal rotation, used to evaluate knee kine-
matics, was increased with anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) 
deficiency. </p>

<p>Figure 5. (A) Manually segmented cartilage from magnetic resonance imaging. (B) A nondeformable cartilage model is created and 
coregistered with computed tomography and dynamic stereo x-ray testing data. The model's overlap region is calculated, which 
allows determination of contact location, area, and strain. (C) Example of evaluation of the overlapped region for 1 specimen. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Anterior tibial translation, used to evaluate knee 
kinematics, was increased with anterior cruciate ligament 
(ACL) deficiency, which is consistent with in vivo literature, 
indicating this model is viable. </p>

<p>The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine 
ACL Deficiency Effects on the Meniscus and Cartilage 5 </p>

<p>Figure 8. Change in meniscal motion between anterior cruciate ligament (ACL)-intact and ACL-deficient knees: The lateral 
meniscus translated significantly more posterior with ACL deficiency compared with the intact state, indicating the lateral meniscus 
is at risk with ACL deficiency. </p>

<p>Figure 9. Change in cartilage contact location between anterior cruciate ligament (ACL)-intact and ACL-deficient knees: Both the 
medial and lateral compartment contact locations moved significantly more posterior when comparing intact with ACL-deficient 
states. This was greater than meniscal translation, possibly imparting more stresses on the meniscus. </p>

<p>6 Arner et al 
The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine </p>

<p>making their interpretation difficult. 
22,27 Furthermore, 
studies comparing knee pathologies are sparse. Our finding 
of increased meniscal translation with ACL deficiency is 
contrary to limited other studies that found meniscal trans-
lation was influenced by loading and not by ACL defi-
ciency. 
22,24,32 Those studies, however, were static and were 
further limited by MRI slice thickness or invasive tech-
niques. 
27 Dynamic meniscal evaluation, as performed in this 
study, likely is a better representation of true motion due to 
the complex nature of the meniscus and knee. The authors 
do not know if the observed increase in meniscal movement 
may lead to greater rates of meniscal tears. However, the 
greater change in translation of the lateral versus medial 
meniscus may explain the increased incidences of acute lat-
eral meniscus tears and chronic medial meniscus tears. The 
medial meniscus likely sees greater stresses, and with time, 
likely experiences greater tear rates. 
24 It is known, however, 
that meniscal translation is essential to prevent stress con-
centrations between the cartilage surfaces during knee 
range of motion. </p>

<p>1   When evaluating deformation of the menisci during 
dynamic knee flexion, although not statistically significant, 
vertical deformation or meniscal compression increased 
while the change in radial and circumferential deformation 
was minimal. These changes may lead to early meniscal 
degeneration. These results may be secondary to inconsis-
tent medial-lateral and rotatory tibiofemoral kinematics 
with ACL deficiency, as described in the literature; how-
ever, studies evaluating meniscal deformation are limited, 
and the authors are not aware of any doing so dynami-
cally. 
7,17 With flexion angles limited to 60 
and a 46-kg load, 
forces may not have been sufficient to produce marked 
changes in meniscal deformation. Again, we expect that 
with deeper flexion angles and larger loading, the circum-
ferential fibers would be further stressed and therefore 
show more significant meniscal deformation. 
Cartilage contact location is altered with ACL deficiency, 
possibly leading to abnormal wear and osteoarthritis. Con-
sistent with our hypothesis, we found cartilage contact loca-
tion to be significantly more posterior with ACL deficiency 
in both the medial and lateral compartments and exceeded 
the change in meniscal translation. This difference is likely 
due to meniscal roots and capsular attachments, which con-
strain the movement of the meniscus. 
27 These results illus-
trate that the lateral compartment is more at risk for injury 
with ACL deficiency acutely, as seen with the pivot-shift 
phenomenon and the common bone bruise pattern, and 
chronically may lead to early osteoarthritis. 
11 We found 
minimal differences in cartilage contact area and strain 
between ACL intact and deficient states. The lack of change 
in acute contact area and strain is consistent with the 
thought that the menisci are secondary restraints, so the 
menisci likely are picking up the forces that the ACL usu-
ally experiences, 
27 thereby reducing the effects on the car-
tilage. These results are also consistent with the theory that 
chronically overloading the meniscus leads to degeneration 
and subsequent changes to the cartilage. 
32,33 Our dynamic 
study evaluated only the acute phase without meniscal 
injury or degeneration, and therefore, cartilage changes 
have not yet occurred. For this reason, quantitative values </p>

<p>found in our study are slightly different than others in the 
literature. 
Some differences can be noted between the results of this 
study and those of a previous in vivo investigation of 
changes in tibiofemoral cartilage contact after ACL recon-
struction. 
17 During a static lunge with cartilage contact 
positions estimated at knee flexion angles of 0 
, 30 
, 60 
, 
and 90 
in 9 patients, Li et al 
17 reported a similar posterior 
shift of the contact point in ACL-deficient knees, but only in 
the medial compartment and only at flexion angles less 
than 30  . These discrepancies are most likely due to signif-
icant differences in the loading scenarios for the 2 studies. 
While the true axial load for the in vivo studies is unknown, 
the lunge position most likely requires active stabilization, 
with cocontraction between the quadriceps and hamstrings 
to maintain a static knee flexion angle. Hamstrings activa-
tion would tend to reduce anterior tibial translation (and 
the associated posterior shift of tibial cartilage contact) 
relative to the present cadaver study, which utilized only 
quadriceps force to control knee flexion. While it could be 
argued that in vivo studies are more relevant to actual 
function, Li et al 
17 were unable to assess meniscal function 
in their model. Interactions between tibiofemoral kine-
matics, meniscal motion, and cartilage contact were a key 
goal for this study. 
This study overcomes many limitations of previous cada-
ver models by enabling dynamic evaluation of meniscal 
function in a loaded knee with minimal disruption to native 
anatomy. The core technical innovation is the unique com-
bination of implanted radiopaque markers, DSX, and CT/ 
MRI-based 3D geometric modeling to assess meniscal 
movement and deformation during dynamic knee flexion, 
while maintaining native anatomy without implantation of 
devices within the joint that likely alter meniscal and car-
tilage contact mechanics. The authors are not aware of any 
previous studies that investigate the complex dynamic 
interplay between knee kinematics, meniscal motion and 
deformation, and cartilage contact in the intact knee as well 
as changes in these relationships after ACL injury. Com-
bining simultaneous assessment of multiple parameters is 
essential to elucidate the role of the meniscus in the path-
way from ACL injury to osteoarthritis. This knowledge is 
fundamental for developing and evaluating optimal treat-
ments that preserve long-term knee joint health. 
This study indicates that ACL deficiency leads to 
altered meniscal and cartilage mechanics. Can these 
changes be reversed with surgical intervention? We plan 
to utilize this methodology to better characterize the 
effects of different knee injuries and different surgical 
treatments such as ACL reconstruction, extra-articular 
tenodesis (iliotibial band), posterior cruciate ligament 
deficiency and reconstruction, as well as meniscal injury, 
surgery, and transplantation. 
In summary, the lateral meniscus showed greater trans-
lation with ACL deficiency compared with the medial 
meniscus, which may explain the greater incidences of 
acute lateral meniscus tears and chronic medial meniscus 
tears. Furthermore, cartilage contact location moved fur-
ther posterior than that of the meniscus in both medial and 
lateral compartments. This study introduces a novel </p>

<p>The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine 
ACL Deficiency Effects on the Meniscus and Cartilage 7 </p>

<p>minimally invasive dynamic in vitro model to study knee 
kinematics, meniscus function, and cartilage contact, 
which found significant changes with ACL deficiency and 
will be applied to study the effects of different pathologies 
and surgical techniques in restoring joint function. </p>



<p>8 Arner et al 
The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine </p>

</text></tei>