<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4091108" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The volatile organic compound (VOc) profile in plant leaves often changes after biotic and abiotic stresses. Monitor-
ing changes in VOcs in plant leaves could provide valuable information about multitrophic interactions. In the current 
study, we investigated the effect of asian citrus psyllid (acP) infestation, citrus greening pathogen (Candidatus Liberi-
bacter asiaticus [CLas]) infection, and simultaneous attack by acP and CLas on the VOc content of citrus leaves. Leaf 
volatiles were extracted using hexane and analyzed with gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (Gc-Ms). although 
acP is a phloem-sucking insect that causes minimal damage to plant tissues, the relative amount of 21 out of the 27 VOcs 
increased 2-to 10-fold in acP-infested plants. The relative amount of d-limonene, β-phelandrene, citronellal, and unde-
canal were increased 4-to 20-fold in CLas-infected plants. a principle component analysis (Pca) and cluster analysis 
(ca) showed that VOc patterns of acP-infested and CLas-infected plants were different from each other and were also 
different from the controls, while the VOc pattern of double-attacked plants was more like that of the controls than that 
of acP-infested or CLas-infected plants. VOc amounts from leaves were compromised when plants were attacked by acP 
and CLas. The results of this study showed that a simple direct extraction of citrus leaf volatiles could be successfully used 
to discriminate between healthy and CLas-infected plants. Information about the effects of insect and pathogen attack 
on the VOc content profile of plants might contribute to a better understanding of biotic stress. </p>

<p>Herbivory by the insect Diaphorina citri 
induces greater change in citrus plant 
volatile profile than does infection by the 
bacterium, Candidatus Liberibacter asiaticus </p>

<p>Faraj hijaz, Ibrahim el-shesheny, and Nabil Killiny* </p>

<p>The main functions of plant volatiles are to protect plants 
from insect and pathogen attack, attract pollinators and other 
beneficial animals, and serve as communication signals within 
plant and among plants. 
1 Both biotic and abiotic stress can trigger 
plant volatiles. </p>

<p>2   Plant volatiles are synthesized and stored in different sites 
such as glandular trichomes, secreting ducts and cavities, secre-
tory cells in flowers and root, and in extra-floral nectar. 
3 In Citrus 
sp L. species, essential oils are present in special oil glands in 
leaves, flowers, peel, juice vesicles, and seeds. 
4 The composition 
of citrus leaf oils is mainly stable and shows small variation from 
one season to another. 
5 In addition, it is slightly affected by the 
rootstock. </p>

<p>4   The Asian citrus psyllid (ACP), Diaphorina citri (Kuwayama) 
(Hemiptera: Psyllidae), is the main vector of the citrus greening 
pathogen (Candidatus Liberibacter asiaticus [CLas]), a phloem-
limited, uncultivable, and gram-negative bacterium. 
6 Recent </p>

<p>studies using 16S rRNA gene sequencing showed that 3 species 
of the bacterium, Candidatus Liberibacter, have been implicated 
in citrus greening: asiaticus (CLas)(in Asia, North America, and 
Brazil), africanus (CLaf) (in Africa), and americanus (CLam) (in 
Brazil). 
7 CLas and Clam are transmitted by ACP, while CLaf 
is transmitted by the African citrus psyllid Trioza erytrea (Del 
Guercio) (Hemiptera: Triozidae). 
8 The ACP transmits the HLB 
pathogen during feeding activities on citrus phloem sap. 
Most studies on the insect-plant interactions focused on 
volatiles released from herbivore-damaged plants. 
9 Rupturing of 
the storage glands by insect feeding causes immediate release of 
stored volatiles. 
Volatiles released from herbivore-damaged plants are dis-
tinctively different from those released from mechanically dam-
aged plants. 
10 Mechanical damage of cotton leaf induces glands 
to release stored terpenes and induced emissions of green-leaf 
volatiles (GLVs). Some volatiles like indole and hexenyl acetate 
are released in higher levels in herbivore-damaged plants than </p>

<p>e25677-2 </p>

<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
Volume 8 Issue 10 </p>

<p>mechanically damaged plants. 
11 Volatile emissions and plant 
defense are triggered by enzymes and elicitors from insect 
herbivores. </p>

<p>10,12   Volatiles from herbivore-attacked plant are released immedi-
ately or synthesized after several hours or even days after attack </p>

<p>.9   In general, plant responses differentially to chewing insects than 
piercing-sucking insects. In the case of chewing insects, damaged 
tissue release GLVs that are produced immediately after insect 
damage. 
13 GLVs contain C6 aldehydes, alcohols, and esters such 
as hexanal, hexenol, and hexyl acetate, respectively. Piercing-
sucking insects cause release of stored volatiles after enhancing 
by elicitors. 
Volatiles released from herbivore-damaged plants may result 
in direct or indirect defense against herbivores; deterring her-
bivores as well as attracting natural enemies such as arthropod 
predators, parasitoids, and birds. 
14 Plant volatiles released by her-
bivore-damaged plant can also transmit information within plant 
and potentially among plants. 
1 For example, laboratory studies 
showed that the expression of several genes involved in defense 
metabolism were elevated in Phaseolus vulgaris (lima bean) that 
was exposed to volatiles from herbivore-infested neighbors. </p>

<p>15   Released volatiles are usually collected using a closed push/ 
pull system. In this method, volatiles are pulled out through a 
trap that contains specific adsorbent. The collected volatiles are 
eluted with an organic solvent and analyzed using GC-MS. </p>

<p>16-18   Although this procedure is simple and does not require sample 
cleanup, the type and the size of the adsorbent, collecting time, 
and collecting rate affect the quantity and quality of collected 
volatiles. Accordingly, the results obtained by this method may 
not reflect the actual released volatiles. 
Studying the emission of plant volatiles in response to biotic 
stress is important because they are involved in direct and indirect 
defense. However, studying the total volatile contents of plant 
leaves after the attack might contribute to a better understanding 
of plant response to pathogen and insect attack, mechanism of 
volatile release, and the relationship between stored and released 
volatiles. 
Because volatile extraction from plant leaves is difficult and 
require purification, in some studies volatile contents of plant 
leaves were collected from grounded samples using purge and 
trap apparatus 
19 or were extracted with solid phase micro-extrac-
tion (SPME). </p>

<p>20   Available information about the response of citrus leaf volatiles 
to ACP feeding and CLas infection is limited and only 2 reports 
have considered the response of citrus leaf volatiles to CLas infec-
tion. In first report, researchers used solid-phase microextrac-
tion (SPME) coupled with (GC-MS) to study the effect of CLas 
on citrus leaf volatiles. 
20 In second study, they used GC-MS to 
identify citrus leaf volatiles that were released in the headspace 
of CLas-infected citrus trees and studied their effect on psyllid 
behavior. 
18 The objective of this study was to determine the effect 
of ACP infestation, CLas infection, and the double attack of ACP 
and CLas on the volatile content of citrus leaves. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Insect colonies and citrus tree maintenance 
Field-collected ACP adults were used to establish insect colo-
nies. Colonies were maintained in controlled growth rooms at 28 
± 1 °C, 60 ± 2% RH, and under an L16:D8 h photoperiod. Eight-
month-old seedlings of Valencia sweet orange (Citrus sinensis (L.) 
Osbeck) were used in this study when we initiated the experi-
ment. Trees were maintained in an insect-proof, AC-controlled 
greenhouse (28 °C, 40% RH, L16:D8). To obtain infected trees 
with CLas, 8-mo-old sweet orange seedlings from Valencia were 
grafted with 4 pieces of budwood sticks from a PCR-positive 
HLB source. Eight months later, the infection was confirmed 
using PCR as described by Tatineni et al. 
21 PCR was also used to 
check for the presence of CLas in citrus trees and to insure that 
ACP colonies were negative from CLas. 
Tree exposure to Asian citrus psyllid (Diaphorina citri) 
Eighteen-month-old healthy or CLas-infected Valencia seed-
lings were experimentally exposed to healthy psyllids. Each tree 
was challenged with 50 adults and individually caged using 
insect rearing cages (30 × 15.5 × 15 inches). Exposed trees were 
kept in growth rooms under the condition as described before. 
Five months post exposure; 6 mature leaves were collected from 
each tree from different positions for further analysis. Control 
(healthy) and CLas-infected trees without any exposure to ACP 
were also kept under the same condition in separate cages. For 
each of the 4 treatments, 6 replications have been used. 
Extraction of citrus leaf volatiles 
Leaves were ground to a fine powder with liquid nitrogen 
and 100 mg was transferred to a 1.5 ml micro-centrifuge tube. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Gc-Ms chromatogram of healthy Valencia leaf hexane extract. The numbers above the peaks refer to the numbers listed in Table 1. Is: internal 
standard used to calculate the absolute amount of each compounds. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
e25677-3 </p>

<p>A 0.5-ml aliquot of hexane (Sigma) was added to the samples 
and vortexed for 30 sec. Samples were left on ice for 10 min and 
the vortexing was repeated 2 times. At the end of the extraction, 
samples were removed from the ice and centrifuged at 12,000 
rpm for 1 min. A 0.2-ml aliquot of the organic layer was spiked 
with trans, trans-2,4-nonadienal (Sigma) as internal standard at 
a final concentration of 200 ppm, and 1 μl of the spiked sample 
was injected into the GC-MS running in the full scan mode. 
Overall, 6 plants and 6 leaves from each were used for each treat-
ment and two runs/replicate were performed. 
GC-MS analysis 
Citrus leaf volatiles were analyzed using a Clarus 500 GC-MS 
system (Perkin Elmer) fitted with an HP-5MS column (cross-
linked 5% Ph Me siloxane, 50 min × 0.22 mm × 0.025 μm film 
thickness). The flow rate for the helium carrier gas was 0.7 ml/ 
min. The following GC temperature program was used: hold at 
50 °C for 3 min, then increase to 200 °C at a rate of 5 °C/min, 
increase further to 250 °C at 10 °C/min, and finally hold at 250 
°C for 2 min.22 The injector and the detector temperatures were 
250 °C and 180 °C, respectively. 
Peak identification and quantification 
GC-MS chromatograms were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">TurboMass</rs> 
software version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.4.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Perkin Elmer</rs>). Peak identifications were </p>

<p>achieved using NIST (Natl. Inst. of Standards and Technology) 
and Wiley 9th edition (John Wiley and Sons, Inc.,) mass spectra 
database libraries and linear retention index (LRI). The LRI val-
ues were calculated using a calibration curve generated by inject-
ing a mixture of alkane (C8-C18) under previously described 
conditions. The percentage peak areas were calculated by divid-
ing the peak area of each compound by the total area. To fairly 
compare the relative amount of each compound in different treat-
ments, we normalized the peak areas using trans, trans-2,4-non-
adienal as the internal standard (IS). The compounds' amounts 
were normalized by dividing their peak areas by IS peak area. 
Statistical analyses 
Statistical analyses were performed using JMP version 9.0 
(SAS Institute Inc,). Data were normally distributed. Analysis 
of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare estimated volatiles 
in different treatments as a percentage (proportion) or normal-
ized (amounts). Post hoc pairwise comparisons between treat-
ments were performed with the Tukey honestly significant 
different test. Principal component analysis (PCA) and cluster 
analysis (CA) were used to discriminate among treatments. The 
PCA and CA were performed using the normalized data of indi-
vidual VOCs and 3 main groups. PCA was used to summarize 
the pattern of correlation among the detected compounds in the </p>

<p>Figure 2. Relative amount of volatile compounds in different treatment. The peak areas were normalized using internal standard (trans, trans-2,4-non-
adienal). horizontal thick lines indicate the medians; boxes show the interquartile ranges including 50% of the values; whiskers reflect the highest and 
the lowest number of visits; and different letters indicate statistically significantly different treatments (P &lt; 0.05). </p>



<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
Volume 8 Issue 10 </p>

<p>different treatments. CA based on the Mahalanobi's squared dis-
tance between groups from the discriminant function analysis 
(DFA), with 95% confidence, was used to construct the similar-
ity dendograms. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Volatile profile in Valencia orange leaf 
In order to study the effect of ACP-infestation and/or CLas 
infection on the composition of volatile components in citrus 
leaves, we used hexane to extract the total volatiles. The compo-
sition of Valencia leaf individual volatiles is presented in Table 
1 and the corresponding chromatogram is shown in (Fig. 1). 
Overall, 27 compounds were detected and identified in Valencia 
leaf. The main components were sabinene 26.2%, β-elemene 
11%, δ-3-carene 9.1%, linalool 8.4%, citronellal 7.4%, ocimene 
5.7%, (Z)-citral 6.3%, and neral 4.4% (Table 1). 
Citrus responses systemically to biotic stress 
In order to examine whether citrus plants respond systemi-
cally to the infection with CLas, the infestation with ACP or 
both together, leaves from different locations in plants were ana-
lyzed. No changes in volatile profile or volatile relative amounts 
were found among all tested leaves within each treatment. 
Additionally, for CLas-infected plants, no differences were found </p>

<p>between symptomatic and asymptomatic 
leaves (data non shown). Data were pooled 
in further analyses. This result suggests a 
systematic response within the plant to the 
biotic stresses. 
Infection with CLas and/or infestation 
with ACP alter the volatile proportions 
profile 
To compare the profile of different treat-
ments, we calculated the proportion of 
each compound to all others for each treat-
ment. The volatile profile of CLas-infected 
plants was more affected than that of ACP-
infested or combined ACP and CLas. Four 
compounds were increased and 10 com-
pounds were decreased in the profile of 
CLas-infected plants compared with control 
(healthy). The percentages of d-limonene, 
β-phellandrene, citronellal, and undeca-
nal were significantly higher in leaves from 
CLas-infected plant. A dramatic increase in 
d-limonene percentage from 3.5 to 40.1% 
was observed. This observation could be 
used as a biomarker for fast identification of 
CLas-infected plants. A significant reduc-
tion in the percentage of (E)-2-hexen-1-ol, 
myrcene, α-phellandrene, δ-3-carene, 
γ-terpinene, α-terpinolene, 2,4-nonadi-
enal, neral, (Z)-citral, and α-humulene was 
found in CLas-infected plants (Table 1). 
The volatile profile of leaves from plants 
infested with ACP was relatively similar to 
the control profile with the exception of two compounds that 
were increased (linalool and d-limonene) and five compounds 
that were decreased [(E)-2-hexen-1-ol, (E)-2-hexenal, 2,4-nona-
dienal, citronellal, and δ-3-carene] (Table 1). 
The volatile profile of attacked plants by ACP and CLas was 
more affected than ACP-infested plants and less affected than 
those infected by CLas. Seven compounds were decreased and 
two compounds were increased significantly within the pro-
file. The percentages of the C6-GLVs [(E)-2-hexen-1-ol, (E)-2-
hexenal, and 2,4-nonadienal], citronellal, (E)-β-caryophllene, 
α-humelen, and caryophyllene oxide were significantly lower, 
while the percentage of linalool and d-limonene was higher in 
the double-attacked plants (Table 1). 
Infection with CLas and/or infestation with ACP alter vola-
tile amounts 
The intensive increase in d-limonene percentage (3.5 to 40%) 
in the CLas-infected plants affected the proportion of com-
pounds to each other. Subsequently, the profile of CLas-infected 
looked significantly different from those of the healthy or the 
ACP-infested plants. To compare the relative amount of each 
compound in different treatments, we used the normalized data 
as described above. Unlike the profiles, we found that most com-
pounds responded to the infestation with ACP, while only a few 
of them responded to the infection with CLas. The compounds </p>

<p>Figure 3. Proportions (percentages) and relative amount of volatile compounds categorized into 
groups in hexane extract of Valencia leaves. (A) Proportions (percentage). Number followed by 
each compound represents its percentage. (B) Relative amounts. horizontal lines indicate the 
medians; boxes show the interquartile ranges including 50% of the values; whiskers reflect the 
highest and the lowest number of visits; and different letters indicate statistically significantly 
different treatments (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
e25677-5 </p>

<p>Table 1. Proportions (percentages) of of VOcs detected in healthy, Clas-infected, acP-infected, and double-attacked Valencia leaves </p>

<p>Group(1) 
Compound 
RI </p>

<p>Volatile proportion to each other (%)(2) </p>

<p>Healthy 
Clas-infected 
ACP-infested 
Double-attacked 
C 6 -GLVs </p>

<p>alc. 
(E)-2-hexen-1-ol 
825 
0.9 
0.9 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3 
0.3 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.2 
0.2 ± 0.0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.2 
0.2 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>ald. </p>

<p>(E)-2-hexenal 
834 </p>

<p>2.1 </p>

<p>0.4 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>0.5 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.0 ± 0.0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.0 ± 0.0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>2,4-nonadienal 
1222 
1.5 ± 0.6 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.6 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.2 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.7 ± 0.5 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>undecanal 
1230 
0.2 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.5 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.1 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.1 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Total c 6 -GLVs 
3.0 
1.9 
0.5 
1.0 </p>

<p>Monoterpenes (C 10 ) </p>

<p>Mt. alc. </p>

<p>β-fenchyl alcohol 
1224 
8.8 </p>

<p>0.4 ± 0.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7.6 </p>

<p>0.3 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>15.4 </p>

<p>0.8 ± 0.7 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>0.4 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Linalool 
1113 
8.4 ± 1.8 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7.3 ± 3.6 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>14.6 ± 5.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>14.6 ± 4.9 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mt. ald. </p>

<p>citronellal 
1171 </p>

<p>18.1 </p>

<p>7.4 ± 1.8 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>15.1 </p>

<p>14.0 ± 4.0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>15.2 </p>

<p>2.5 ± 2.2 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>15.8 </p>

<p>1.7 ± 1.5 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Neral 
1267 
4.4 ± 3.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.8 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>5.7 ± 2.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.6 ± 2.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(Z)-citral 
1297 
6.3 ± 4.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7.0 ± 3.6 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7.5 ± 2.6 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mt. est. 
t-sabinene h2O 
1082 
0.2 
0.2 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.3 
0.3 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.6 
0.6 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.5 
0.5 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mt. hd. </p>

<p>α-pinene 
919 </p>

<p>50.4 </p>

<p>0.9 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>66.9 </p>

<p>0.6 ± 0.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>56.0 </p>

<p>0.9 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>59.6 </p>

<p>0.8 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>sabinene 
965 
26.2 ± 10.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>19.8 ± 13.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>27.8 ± 2.9 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>25.0 ± 2.7 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Pinene 
973 
0.8 ± 0.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.6 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.8 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.8 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Myrcene 
982 
2.8 ± 0.6 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.5 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>2.7 ± 0.8 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.7 ± 0.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>α-phellandrene 
1005 
0.2 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.1 ± 0.0 b 
0.2 ± 0.0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>δ-3-carene 
1008 
9.1 ± 1.9 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.7 ± 1.1 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>6.0 ± 2.3 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7.4 ± 1.7 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>d-limonene 
1032 
3.5 ± 1.7 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>40.1 ± 22.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>9.7 ± 8.9 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>13.8 ± 7.8 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>β-phellandrene 
1042 
0.1 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.4 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.1 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.1 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Ocimene 
1049 
5.7 ± 2.1 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>3.0 ± 1.3 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7.0 ± 2.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7.9 ± 1.7 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>γ-terpinene 
1093 
0.1 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0 ± 0.0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.1 ± 0.0 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>0.1 ± 0.0 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>α-terpinolene 
1098 
1.0 ± 0.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.1 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.7 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.8 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Total monoterpenes 
77.5 
90 
87.2 
91 </p>

<p>Sesquiterpenes (C 15 ) </p>

<p>sqt. hd. </p>

<p>β-elemene 
1419 </p>

<p>19.1 </p>

<p>11.6 ± 9.0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7.7 </p>

<p>4.8 ± 6.9 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>12.1 </p>

<p>7.3 ± 2.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>8.1 </p>

<p>5.5 ± 2.8 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(E)-β-caryophyllene 
1452 
3.0 ± 0.6 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.8 ± 0.9 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>2.4 ± 1.0 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>1.6 ± 0.3 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(E)-β-farnesene 
1473 
1.4 ± 1.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3 ± 0.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.5 ± 0.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>α-humulene 
1486 
0.9 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.5 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>0.3 ± 0.1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>β-sinensal 
1691 
2.2 ± 2.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.5 ± 0.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.4 ± 1.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.5 ± 0.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>sqt. ox. 
caryophyllene oxide 
1521 
0.4 
0.4 ± 0.3 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>0.5 
0.5 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2 
0.2 ± 0.2 </p>

<p>bc </p>

<p>0 
0.0 ± 0.0 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Total sesquiterpenes 
19.5 
8 
12.3 
8.1 </p>

<p>(1)abbreviations of groups: alc, alcohol; ald, aldehyde; Mt. alc, Monoterpene alcohol; Mt. ald., Monoterpene aldehyde; Mt. est., Monoterpene esters; Mt. 
hd., Monoterpene hydrocarbon; sqt. hd., sesquiterpene hydrocarbon; sqt. ox., sesquiterpene oxide. (2) Numbers that share the same superscript letters, in 
the same row, are not statistically different at 95% level of confidence. </p>



<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
Volume 8 Issue 10 </p>

<p>were divided into two groups depending on their response to 
ACP or CLas as described below. 
Specific response to ACP 
The first group included 21 volatile compounds that were 
affected in ACP-infested plants (Fig. 2). Seventeen of these com-
pounds were significantly higher. Fourteen out of the 17 were 
monoterpenes (α-pinene, sabinene, pinene, myrcene, ocimene, 
t-sabinene H2O, γ-terpinene, linalool, (Z)-citral, δ-3-carene, 
α-phelandrene, α-terpinolene, neral, and β-fenchyl alcohol) 
and the other 3 were sesquiterpens (β-elemene, α-humlene, 
and (E)-β-caryophllene). The abundance of these compounds 
increased between 2 to 10-fold (Fig. 2). None of these com-
pounds were increased in CLas-infected plants. The amounts of 
these volatiles in CLas-infected trees that were also attacked by 
ACP were lower than those exposed to ACP only, and higher 
than those infected with CLas. This finding suggests a com-
promising effect due to the double attack (Fig. 2). The other 4 
compounds displayed non-significant trends were caryophyllene 
oxide, β-sinensal, and (E)-β-farnesene (increased), and 2,4, non-
adienal (decreased). 
Specific response to CLas 
Four volatiles were induced at significantly higher amounts 
in CLas-infected plants compared with the control (Fig. 2). 
These compounds were three monoterpenes (d-limonene, 
β-phelandrene, and citronellal) and an aldehyde (undecanal). </p>

<p>These compounds were higher in CLas-infected 
plants than ACP-infested plants. The amounts of 
β-phelandrene, citronellal, and undecenal were 
induced 4-fold, while d-limonene induced to more 
than 20-fold (Fig. 2). Surprisingly, the amount 
of δ-3-carene, known for its antimicrobial activ-
ity, was decreased significantly in CLas-infected 
plants. We also observed that the double attack 
compromised the amount of these compounds. As 
expected, the C 6 -GLVs [(E)-2-hexenal and (E)-2-
hexen-1-ol] were not significantly affected. 
The effect of CLas and/or infestation with 
ACP on volatiles as categories 
The 27 detected compounds were classified 
into 3 main categories; C6: GLVs, C10: mono-
terpenes, and C15: sesquiterpenes (Table 1 and 
Fig. 3). The percentages of these categories in 
healthy leaves were 3%, 77.5%, and 19.5%, 
respectively. These 3 categories consisted of 8 
groups based on their functional group. C6-GLVs 
included 2 groups: Alcoholic (0.9%) and alde-
hyde (2.1%) compounds. Monoterpenes include 
monoterpenes hydrocarbon (50.4%), monoter-
penes aldehyde (18.1%), monoterpene alcohol 
(8.8%), and monoterpene esters (0.2%). The 2 
functional groups of sesquiterpenes were sesqui-
terpene hydrocarbons (19.1%) and sesquiterpene 
oxide (0.4%). 
The monoterpenes category was increased sig-
nificantly in all treatments while both C6-GLVs 
and sesquiterpenes were decreased (Fig. 3A). 
The percentage of monoterpene hydrocarbon increased to 66.9, 
56.0, and 59.6% in the CLas-infected, ACP-infested, and double-
attacked leaves, respectively. These increases were due to the great 
increase in d-limonene and β-phellandrene in CLas-infected and 
d-limonene, sabinene, and ocimene in ACP-infested and double-
attacked plants. Finally, the percentages of monoterpene alcohols, 
especially linalool, were increased in ACP-infested and double-
attacked plants but remained constant in CLas-infected plants 
compared with the control. 
Changes of the relative amounts of the main group due to 
CLas-infection and/or ACP-infestation are shown in Figure 3B. 
There was a significant increase in monoterpenes in all treatments 
compared with control. ACP-infested plants possessed a higher 
amount of monoterpenes than CLas-infected and double attacked 
plants. No significant differences in the amount of monoterpenes 
were observed between CLas infected and double attacked. 
Sesquiterpenes increased significantly only in ACP-infested 
plants. No significant differences among treatments were found 
in C6-GLVs. 
Clustering and multivariate analysis 
PCA using the individual VOCs showed clear clustering 
among treatments and we were able to discriminate between 
CLas-infected and ACP-infested plants (Fig. 4A), The principal 
components (PC) 1 and 2 accounted for 71.1% of the variation. 
Pinene, α-pinene, sabinene, myrcene, α-phellandrene, ocimene, </p>

<p>Figure 4. Principal components and cluster analysis of volatile organic compounds in dif-
ferent treatments (A) Principal component analysis of individual components. (B) Principle 
component analysis of volatile compounds categorized into main groups (monoterpenes, 
sesquiterpenes, and green leaf volatiles). (C): cluster analysis using the individual com-
pounds. (D) cluster analysis of volatile compounds categorized into main groups (mono-
terpenes, sesquiterpenes, and green leaf volatiles). </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
e25677-7 </p>

<p>t-sabinene H2O, α-terpinolene, linalool, neral, and (Z)-citral 
were the compounds with the highest absolute loading values 
in PC1. While d-limonene, β-phellandrene, citronellal, undeca-
nal, (E)-β-caryophyllene oxide, and (E)-β-caryophyllene were 
among the compounds with the highest absolute PC 2 loading. 
In addition, PCA using the three main groups of VOCs showed 
a clear discrimination between control and ACP-infested plants 
(Fig. 4B). The principal components (PC) 1 and 2 accounted 
92.2% of the variation. Monoterpenes has the highest sum of the 
absolute PC 1 and 2 loading, followed by sesquiterpenes. Because 
VOC patterns of the samples in each treatment were clustered 
around their centroid, this supports our findings that plant 
responses to ACP and CLas attack were systematic. 
Likewise PCA and CA using individual VOCs or main 
groups showed that VOCs profile in the leaves from double-
attacked plants was closer to the profile of CLas-attacked plants 
than ACP-attacked plants (Fig. 4C and D). CA using the 3 main 
categories showed high similarity between CLas-infected and 
double-attacked plants (95.13%) (Fig. 4D). The ACP-infested 
plants were more distinguished from the control (39.76% simi-
larity) than CLas-infected and double-attacked plants (63.45%) 
(Fig. 4D). CA analysis using individual volatiles showed that 
VOCs profile in the leaves from double-attacked plants was closer 
to the profile of CLas-attacked plants than ACP-attacked plants 
(Fig. 4C). VOCs in double-attacked plants were closer to the 
control (59.61% similarity) than the ACP-infested (39.01% simi-
larity) or CLas-infected (37.05% similarity) (Fig. 4C). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Twenty-seven VOCs were successfully identified and quanti-
fied. Most of the compounds detected in our study were reported 
to be released by citrus leaf. 
18,23 No significant changes in volatile 
profile or volatile relative amounts were found among leaves from 
different positions within the plant in each treatment suggesting 
a systemic response in citrus plants as previously described. </p>

<p>24   In our study, the major group of VOCs in leaf from healthy 
plants was terpenes (97%), while C6-GLVs represented only 
3%. Terpenoids represent the largest VOCs in most plant 
leaves. 
9,25 Both monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes protect plants 
against biotic or abiotic stresses. </p>

<p>24,26   Plant infestation by herbivores induces compounds implicated 
in antixenosis or antibiosis, 
27 and attracts natural enemies. 
28 In 
addition, the infection with pathogens induces the production 
of antimicrobial compounds. 
29 In general, terpenoids play an 
important role in plant-herbivore-pathogen interaction. 
30 Many 
plants show high emission of monoterpenes after herbivory and/ 
or pathogen attack. Monoterpenes may act as kairomones in 
attracting predators and parasitoids to attacked plants, 
14 as well 
as function as phytoalexins, 
31 affect oviposition behavior, </p>

<p>32,33   and act as feeding deterrents for insects. 
34 Monoterpenes and 
sesquiterterpenes were found to be induced systemically in Pinus 
sylvestris by egg deposition of the sawfly Diprion pini. </p>

<p>24   As expected, in our results, there were no significant differ-
ences in the abundances of GLVs (C6) between ACP-infested 
and/or CLas-infected and control plants. In fact, the plant </p>

<p>bleeds GLVs instantaneously from disrupted tissue as a wound-
ing response, but AC P causes minimal damage to plant tissue; 
therefore, no effect on GLVs was found. 
Plant response for piercing-sucking insects such as aphids, 
mealy bugs, leafhoppers, and psyllids is different than that for 
chewing insects. 
35 Although piecing-sucking insects do not 
cause significant cell damage, during their prolonged stylet 
interactions, injected elicitors might induce specific reactions. </p>

<p>36   In general, chewing insects induce the expression of jasmonic 
acid pathway (JA) regulated gene and wound-responsive gene 
while the piercing-sucking insects such as ACP induces salicylic 
acid (SA) signaling pathway 
3 and JA pathway. 
36 In ACP-infested 
leaves, 17 compounds were significantly higher in ACP-infested 
plants. Attack with other species of psyllids induces many 
changes in leaf VOCs. For example, Psylla pyricola feeding 
causes simultaneous changes in the composition of released and 
stored VOCs in pear trees. 
37 Relative abundance of secondary 
metabolite volatiles in the leaves of avocado was correlated posi-
tively with psyllid (Trioza anceps) attack. 
38 Aphids also induce 
the release of VOCs including α-pinene, β-pinene, cymene, 
α-phellandrene, and d-limonene. </p>

<p>39   In our study, monoterpene alcohol in ACP-infested and dou-
ble-attacked plant leaves was changed from 8.8% to 15.4%. The 
main volatile compound of monoterpene alcohol was linalool, 
which increased 7-fold compared with the control. In fact, lin-
alool is a cue molecule that helps insects locate and recognize 
plants. 
40 Linalool synthase in tomato was induced in leaf tri-
chomes by spider mite infestation. 
41 Linalool and ocimene were 
induced in lima bean after spider mite attack. 
42 Ocimene was 
increased in ACP-infested and double-attacked but not in CLas-
infected leaves as compared with the control. It seems that to 
induce ocimene, plants need several events such as several feed-
ing periods by insect. A study supporting this idea showed that a 
single event of damage for Lotus japonicus plants did not induce 
the release of (E)-β-ocimene from the plants. 
43 The monoter-
pene myrcene, was also increased in ACP-infested plants. This 
observation was found in Arabidopsis infested by P. rapae. </p>

<p>44   α-humulene, (E)-β-caryophyllene, and caryophyllene oxide were 
increased as a response to ACP-infestation. Both α-humulene 
and caryophyllene oxide were also induced in response to simul-
taneous infestation with sap-feeder insect, Frankliniella occi-
dentalis, and chewing insect, Heliothis virescens. </p>

<p>45   Some induced volatiles in ACP-infested plants were reported 
to be biologically active and attractive for natural enemies such 
as sabinene and α-pinene. 
46 (E)-β-caryophyllene was increased 
in ACP-infested plants. The release of (E)-β-caryophyllene 
attracts entomopathogenic nematodes to Diabrotica virgifera 
larvae around maize roots. </p>

<p>47   Plants infested with sap-feeder insects such as aphids are 
induced to release VOCs that attract parasitoid wasps 
48 and 
determine aphid densities on host plants. 
49 β-ocimene, linalool, 
α-farnesene, β-farnesene were induced by corn leaf aphid feed-
ing. 
10,49 Our findings revealed that (E)-β-farnesene was higher 
in ACP-infested than CLas-infected plants and control. (E)-β-
farnesene is an aphid alarm pheromone and is also released from 
aphid-infested plants to call parasitoids. </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
e25677-8 </p>

<p>α-pinene was found to repel spruce beetle from Pinus resinosa 
plants and enhance predator's attraction. 
50 In our study, α-pinene 
increased 5-fold in ACP-infested plants compared with control. 
The monoterpenes p-cymene, α-terpinene, and α-phellandrene 
repelled Bemisia tabaci when these compounds were applied 
on tomato. 
51 β-sinensal was increased (4-fold) in ACP-infested 
plants. β-sinensal represents 9.4% of compounds in sandalwood 
oil. This oil produced mortality and deterrent effects against 
two-spotted spider mite, Tetranychus urticae Koch. 
52 (E)-β-
caryophyllene which increased 3-fold in ACP-infested plants 
compared with control was reported as attractant to newly 
emerged females of phloem-sap psyllid, Cacopsylla picta, the 
vector of Candidatus Phytoplasma mali in apple. 
53 Sabinene 
was the highest compound in healthy trees and increased in all 
treatments especially in ACP-infested trees (more than 4-fold) 
and in double-attacked trees (more than 2-fold). (E)-ocimene, 
d-limonene, myrcene, and sabinene were the main volatiles 
produced by the new shoots of citrus that attract ACP. </p>

<p>23   The infection with plant pathogens induces the production of 
plant volatiles that possess a powerful antimicrobial activity to 
inhibit the movement of the pathogens within plant tissues. </p>

<p>3,54   Although, the percentage profile of VOCs in CLas-infected 
plants was highly affected, only 4 compounds were increased in 
leaves from CLas-infected plants. These compounds include 3 
monoterpenes (d-limonene, β-phelandrene, and citronellal) and 
an aldehyde (undecanal). 
The accumulated compounds could play an important role in 
plant-pathogen interactions. In vitro studies showed that tomato 
leaf volatiles, including β-phelandrene and other compounds 
inhibited Botrytis cinerea fungus. 
55 The antimicrobial activity of 
d-limonene was also assessed against 8 organisms. 
56 It has been 
found that CLas-infected citrus plants released less d-limonene 
than healthy plants. 
18 In current study, we showed an accumula-
tion of d-limonene in leaves from CLas-infected plants. It could 
be a result of the induction of its biosynthesis and/or inhibition 
of its release. Theoretically, the level of any volatile in plant leaf 
is controlled by the rate of its formation and the rate of its loss 
(release or catabolism). 
57 Volatiles could be released from storage 
glands or biosynthesized de novo following insect damage. </p>

<p>58   A previous study showed that CLas-infected citrus plants 
were initially more attractive to D. citri adults than non-infected 
plants. However, after probing, psyllids moved to non-infected 
plants and settled. 
18 Volatile cues may be implicated in the initial 
movement of psyllids to CLas-infected plants; while the arrest-
ment is determined by the nutritional status of the host, a phe-
nomenon was reported in other vector-borne diseases 
.17,59 The 
results of the previous studies together indicate that the infec-
tion makes plants more attractive to insect-vectors by suppress-
ing the plants basal defense, releasing attractive volatiles, or by 
inhibiting the release of deterrent volatiles. This will help in con-
tinuously spreading the disease by the vector. From the evolu-
tionary view, there is a two-edge benefit for both the releaser and </p>

<p>the receiver. First, for the releaser, it is a kind of resistance and 
may be used to invite natural enemies of ACP; second, for the 
receiver (ACP), this will direct the adults of insects to infest new 
trees, subsequently, less competition and increased distribution. 
The accumulation of volatiles in citrus leaves induced by 
ACP attack was compromised when citrus plants were attacked 
simultaneously by CLas and ACP. It has been shown in other 
systems that the double biotic stress may compromise the plant 
response. 
45 Plants attacked by more than 1 attacker produce 
some compounds that may induce a pathway and reduce the 
activity of another pathway and cause synergistic or antagonistic 
effects on other pathways. Pathogen-inducible SA causes down-
regulation of the JA/ethylene-regulated defense-response genes, 
as well as JA-regulated wound responses and secondary metabo-
lite accumulation. </p>

<p>60,61   CA analysis using individual volatiles or main groups showed 
that VOCs profile in the leaves from double-attacked plants was 
closer to the profile of CLas-attacked plants than ACP-attacked 
plants. PCA of normalized data using individual volatiles or 
main group showed that double-attacked plants were closer to 
control than other treatments. These results prove that CLas 
infection compromises the responses of plant to ACP for its 
benefit. 
Our findings suggest that CLas-infected and double-attacked 
plants might be more susceptible to other insects and pathogens 
since some biologically important compounds were decreased. 
These compounds possess antimicrobial activity or attrac-
tion to natural enemies. (E)-β-farnesene, the natural enemies 
attractant, decreased 3-fold in CLas-infected. (E)-2-hexenal 
and (E)-2-nonenal have an antimicrobial effect and are related 
to plant hypersensitive response. 
62 Although, (E)-2-hexenal 
increased in CLas-infected plants and possesses high antibacte-
rial properties even in low concentration, 
62 it decreased severely 
in CLas-infected after attacking with ACP. (E)-2-hexenal and 
δ-3-carene, which has been reported as an antibacterial com-
pound, 
63 were reduced significantly in the infected plants with 
CLas. This suggests that the double attack of CLas and ACP 
in citrus makes plants more susceptible to other pests and 
pathogens. 
Studying the effect of CLas and ACP in citrus plant volatile 
contents may lead to producing transgenic plants that over-or 
down-express certain compounds to enhance citrus resistance. </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Dr L Duncan for critical reading of the manuscript, 
Shelly Jones for technical assistance in GC-MS analyses, Dr J 
Reyes for generously providing access to GC-MS and the lab 
members for the helpful discussion. This work was supported by 
grant from citrus research and development foundation to NK. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
e25677-9 </p>



<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>Plant signaling &amp; Behavior 
e25677-10 </p>



</text></tei>