<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4355434" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>There are well-recognized complications associated 
with TURBT, such as bladder perforation, irrigation fluid 
absorption, bleeding, infection, damage to the ureteric 
orifices, obturator nerve stimulation, and tumor cell im-
plantation [1]. Among these, bladder perforation is one 
of the most f requent complications of TURBT and is 
sometimes associated with obturator ref lex. Several 
researchers have reported that the risk of obturator nerve 
stimulation is from 10.6% to 11% [2,3]. 
Several advances in instruments and techniques, in-
cluding modifications of resectoscope design and snare 
resection, have been proposed to remove pedunculated 
bladder tumors [4,5]. However, difficulties remain in safe ly 
collecting adequate specimens for flat tumors. We intro-
duce an easy technique for superficial bladder cancer that 
uses a standard monopolar resectoscope loop. </p>

<p>In this study, we demonstrate the easy resection tech-
nique for superficial bladder tumors that we have termed 
the "grasp and bite" TURBT technique and compare it 
with conventional TURBT. </p>

<p><rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS Statistics</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 20.0</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>This study was f inancially supported by Chonnam 
National University, 2009 and Basic Research Program, 
through the National Research Foundation of Korea 
(NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and 
Technology (2012-0002947). This research received a 2014 
academic award by The Korean Endourological Society. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>

<p>An accompanying video can be found in the 'urology in 
motion' section of the journal homepage (www.kjurology. 
org). The supplementary data can also be accessed by 
scanning a QR code located on the Fig. 1 of this article, or </p>

<p>be available on YouTube (http://youtu.be/2xJDgSpZvY4). </p>



</text></tei>