<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4355434" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Transurethral resection of bladder tumor (TURBT) 
is well-established modality for treating non-muscle-
invasive bladder cancer. Furthermore, it is essential for </p>

<p>A novel transurethral resection technique for 
superficial flat bladder tumor: Grasp and bite 
technique </p>

<p>Kyung Jin Oh, Yoo-Duk Choi </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, Ho Suck Chung, Eu Chang Hwang, Seung Il Jung, Dong Deuk Kwon, 
Kwangsung Park, Taek Won Kang </p>

<p>Departments of Urology and </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Pathology, Chonnam National University School of Medicine, Gwangju, Korea </p>

<p>Purpose: Transurethral resection of bladder tumor (TURBT) can be a challenging procedure for an inexperienced surgeon. We sug-
gest an easy technique for TURBT, which we have named the "grasp and bite" technique. We describe this technique and compare 
its effectiveness and safety with that of conventional TURBT. 
Materials and Methods: Monopolar TURBT (24-Fr Karl Storz) was performed in 35 patients who had superficial bladder tumors. 
After defining the tumor margin, the tumor and surrounding mucosa were grasped by use of a loop electrode and resectoscope 
sheath. With tight grasping, linear moving resection was performed. The patients' demographic, intraoperative, and postoperative 
data were analyzed between the conventional and grasp and bite TURBT groups. 
Results: Of 35 patients, 16 patients underwent conventional TURBT (group 1), and the other 19 patients underwent grasp and bite 
TURBT (group 2). Both groups were similar in age, tumor multiplicity, size, anesthesia method, and location. Grasp and bite TURBT 
could be performed as safely and effectively as conventional TURBT. There were no significant differences in irrigation duration, 
urethral catheterization, postoperative hemoglobin drop, or length of hospital stay. No significant side effects such as bladder 
perforation, severe obturator reflex, or persistent bleeding occurred. There were no significant pathological differences between 
specimens according to the type of resection technique. 
Conclusions: The grasp and bite TURBT technique was feasible for superficial bladder tumors. It may be a good tool for inexperi-
enced surgeons owing to its convenient and easy manner. </p>

<p>Keywords: Transurethral resection; Urinary bladder neoplasms; Urologic surgical procedures </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted 
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Original Article -New Technology/Lasers in Urology </p>

<p>Received: 1 October, 2014 • Accepted: 14 January, 2015 
Corresponding Author: Taek Won Kang 
Department of Urology, Chonnam National University Hospital, Chonnam National University School of Medicine, 
42 Jebong-ro, Dong-gu, Gwangju 501-757, Korea 
TEL: +82-62-220-6703, FAX: +82-62-227-1643, E-mail: sydad@hanmail.net </p>

<p>ⓒ The Korean Urological Association, 2015 </p>

<p>evaluating the pathological depth of bladder tumors in 
resected specimens. Despite improvements in endoscopic 
instruments and imaging systems, however, TURBT 
remains a challenging technique for unskilled surgeons to 
master. </p>

<p>www.kjurology.org </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2015;56:227-232. 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4111/kju.2015.56.3.227 
pISSN 2005-6737 • eISSN 2005-6745 </p>



<p>Oh et al </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4111/kju.2015.56.3.227   There are well-recognized complications associated 
with TURBT, such as bladder perforation, irrigation fluid 
absorption, bleeding, infection, damage to the ureteric 
orifices, obturator nerve stimulation, and tumor cell im-
plantation [1]. Among these, bladder perforation is one 
of the most f requent complications of TURBT and is 
sometimes associated with obturator ref lex. Several 
researchers have reported that the risk of obturator nerve 
stimulation is from 10.6% to 11% [2,3]. 
Several advances in instruments and techniques, in-
cluding modifications of resectoscope design and snare 
resection, have been proposed to remove pedunculated 
bladder tumors [4,5]. However, difficulties remain in safe ly 
collecting adequate specimens for flat tumors. We intro-
duce an easy technique for superficial bladder cancer that 
uses a standard monopolar resectoscope loop. </p>

<p>In this study, we demonstrate the easy resection tech-
nique for superficial bladder tumors that we have termed 
the "grasp and bite" TURBT technique and compare it 
with conventional TURBT. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>1. Patients </p>

<p>This was a retrospective study in the Department of 
Urology of Chonnam National University Hospital (Gwangju, 
Korea) between January 2012 and April 2013. This study 
included a total of 29 men and 6 women who had bladder 
tumors with superficial lesions and who underwent TURBT. 
Patients with a huge unresectable mass, an invasive tumor 
shown during preoperative imaging, or an irradiated 
bladder were excluded. Bladder tumors were diagnosed </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Grasp and bite technique. Define the tumor margin and grasp the tumor with the loop and end portion of the resectoscope sheath. 
The photos and illustrations demonstrate the technique schematically: (A, a) defining tumor, (B, b) "grasp" step, and (C, c) after "bite" step. 
Scan this QR code to see the accompanying video, or visit www.kjurology.org or http://youtu.be/2xJDgSpZvY4. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>



<p>Korean J Urol 2015;56:227-232. 
www.kjurology.org </p>

<p>Novel TURBT technique </p>

<p>preoperatively with cystoscopy under local anesthesia. Group 
1 patients were treated by use of the conventional TURBT 
technique, and group 2 patients underwent the grasp and 
bite technique. We applied each technique during a distinct 
time period. Conventional TURBT was performed in 2012 
and grasp and bite TURBT was performed in 2013. All 
procedures were performed by a single experienced operator. 
This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board 
of Chonnam National University Hospital (IRB No. CNUH-
2014-025). </p>

<p>2. TURBT technique </p>

<p>Transurethral resection was performed with a mono-
polar resectoscope system (24-Fr Karl Storz, Tuttlingen, 
Germany). For the grasp and bite technique, the operator 
initially defined the tumor morphology and safe margin. 
In small and f lat lesions, the tumor and surrounding 
mucosal lesions were positioned between the resection 
loop and the end portion of the resectoscope sheath. The 
resectoscope sheath was then moved backward carefully. 
The tumor could be held tightly with the loop electrode </p>

<p>and sheath. We call this the "grasp" step (Fig. 1; Video clip, 
Supplementary material). Using the grasping technique, the 
tumor lesions were lifted up. In the "bite" step, the surgeon 
maintained a tight hold and resected the tumor while 
grasping. A cystoscopic view and schematic illustrations 
are shown in Fig. 1. For resection during the bite step, the 
movement of the electrode loop was straight backward in 
a linear direction. Resection was performed carefully so as 
not to cause bladder perforation without excessive bladder 
wall distention. Poorly located tumors were accessed by 
suprapubic pressure and nearly emptying the bladder. 
When necessary, cold cup biopsy was done at the tumor 
base and edges. The resection site was carefully inspected 
for bleeding and coagulation. In bulky or pedunculated 
tumors, the protruding mass was resected rapidly with the 
grasp and bite technique. After removal of the bulging 
mass, the base lesion and surrounding mucosa were resected 
carefully by using grasp and bite TURBT as mentioned 
earlier. Also, the tumor margin could be resected in the 
same manner repeatedly. 
Resected specimens were reviewed by a pathologist to </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and intraoperative data of groups 1 and 2 </p>

<p>Variable 
Group 1 (n=16) 
Group 2 (n=19) 
p-value 
Age (y), mean±SD 
70.69±7.62 
67.63±9.32 
0.302 
Size (cm), median (range) 
1.25 (0.5-5.0) 
1.0 (0.5-5.0) 
0.806 
Gender 
0.817 
Male 
13 (81.3) 
16 (84.2) 
Female 
3 (18.7) 
3 (15.8) 
Tumor multiplicity 
0.316 
1 
9 (56.3) 
6 (31.6) 
2 
3 (18.7) 
5 (26.3) 
≥3 
4 (25.0) 
8 (42.1) 
Tumor morphology 
0.600 
Pedunculated 
9 (56.3) 
9 (47.4) 
Flat 
7 (43.7) 
10 (52.6) 
Anesthesia 
0.138 
General 
13 (81.3) 
11 (57.9) 
Spinal 
3 (18.7) 
8 (42.1) 
Tumor location 
0.321 
Lateral 
3 (18.8) 
7 (36.8) 
Anterior 
0 (0) 
2 (10.5) 
Ureteral orifice 
2 (12.5) 
0 (0) 
Posterior 
1 (6.3) 
2 (10.5) 
Posterolateral 
5 (31.3) 
4 (21.1) 
Anterolateral 
1 (6.3) 
0 (0) 
Dome 
1 (6.3) 
3 (15.8) 
Whole bladder 
3 (18.8) 
1 (5.3) </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%) unless otherwise indicated. 
TURBT, transurethral resection of bladder tumor; group 1, conventional TURBT; group 2, grasp and bite TURBT; SD, standard deviation. </p>



<p>Oh et al </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4111/kju.2015.56.3.227 </p>

<p>evaluate the depth of resection. Specimens were mea sured 
by hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) staining and immu no-
histochemical smoothelin stain to determine the muscularis 
mucosae. </p>

<p>3. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Independent t-tests were used to compare the mean 
values of two independent parametric continuous varia-
bles. The Mann-Whitney test was used to compare the 
median values of two nonparametric continuous variables. 
Categorical variables were verified by Pearson chi-square 
or Fisher exact test. p&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate 
statistical significance. Statistical analyses were performed 
with <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS Statistics</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Co</rs>., Armonk, NY, </p>

<p>USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>From January to April 2012, 16 patients were enrolled 
who had undergone conventional TURBT. From January 
to April 2013, the grasp and bite technique was applied to 
19 patients with superficial bladder tumors. Tumors ranged 
in size from 0.5 to 5 cm. The two groups had comparable 
demographic and intraoperative data, including patient 
age, tumor size, patient gender, multiplicity, tumor mor pho-
logy, and tumor location (Table 1). 
The mean operative time was similar in the conventio-
nal and grasp and bite groups (35 minutes vs. 35 minutes, </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Histologic findings of resected tumors in the grasp and bite group. (A) H&amp;E stain shows papillary urothelial carcinoma containing muscularis mu-
cosae (×100). (B) Muscularis mucosae bundles stained intensely with smoothelin (×40). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Table 2. Postoperative data of groups 1 and 2 </p>

<p>Variable 
Group 1 (n=16) 
Group 2 (n=19) 
p-value 
Operative time (min) 
35 (10-100) 
35 (10-115) 
0.683 
Hemoglobin drop (g/dL) 
0.4 (0.1-1.2) 
0.5 (0.1-2.8) 
0.659 
Irrigation (d) 
1.0 (1-2) 
1.0 (1-2) 
0.961 
Catheterization (d) 
2.0 (1-3) 
2.0 (1-3) 
0.781 
Hospital stay (d) 
2.0 (1-3) 
2.0 (1-3) 
0.707 
Stage 
0.285 
Ta 
13 (81.3) 
12 (63.2) 
T1 
3 (18.7) 
7 (36.8) 
Grade 
0.557 
G2 
10 (62.5) 
10 (52.6) 
G3 
6 (37.5) 
9 (47.4) 
Recurrence 
0.458 
Yes 
7 (43.7) 
6 (31.6) 
No 
9 (56.3) 
13 (68.4) </p>

<p>Values are presented as median (range) or number (%). 
TURBT, transurethral resection of bladder tumor; group 1, conventional TURBT; group 2, grasp and bite TURBT. </p>



<p>Korean J Urol 2015;56:227-232. 
www.kjurology.org </p>

<p>Novel TURBT technique </p>

<p>respectively). The mean duration of irrigation, duration of 
catheterization, and hospital stay were not significantly 
different between the groups. Hemoglobin change and 
complication rates were also comparable between the 
two groups. There were no cases of bladder perforation, 
excessive obturator reflex, or persistent hematuria in ei-
ther group. The tumor stages and grades were similar in 
the two groups. Specimens were adequate for accurate 
pathological staging of the muscularis mucosae. H&amp;E 
staining and smoothelin immunohistochemistry positivity 
identified the muscularis mucosae in the grasp and bite 
group (Fig. 2). There was no significant difference in recu-
rrence rates between the conventional and grasp and bite 
TURBT groups during the 14-month follow-up (43.8% vs. 
31.6%, p=0.458). The detailed postoperative outcomes are 
given in Table 2. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The purpose of TURBT is complete removal of all visi-
ble tumors for curative intent and acquisition of adequate 
tissue for pathologic evaluation. Achievement of the above 
purposes is not so easy for an inexperienced surgeon. Also, 
tumor recurrence after TURBT is relatively high. For 
non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer, the probability of 
recurrence after 1 year ranges from 15% to 70% [6,7]. Many 
obstacles can arise during the procedure, such as bladder 
perforation, bleeding, obturator reflex, and damage to the 
ureteral orifices. To overcome these difficulties, many 
surgical techniques and innovative devices have been 
developed. For example, endoscopic snare resection of a 
bladder tumor can be used to remove pedunculated tumors 
[5]. Although the snare method offers the advantage of 
en block resection, smaller and sessile tumors are not 
suitable for this technique. New devices such as water 
jet hydrodissection and the thulium:yttrium aluminium 
garnet laser may be applicable for en block resection of 
superf icial tumors [8,9]. However, further studies and 
development of these techniques are necessary to deter-
mine efficacy and oncologic outcomes. 
Variable methods of tumor resection have been devel op ed 
and used in association with tumor size and location. These 
also are determined by a surgeon's preference and surgical 
experience. Modifications of TURBT equipment and tech-
niques also have the possibility of improving surgical 
out comes. Accurate surgical technique is mandatory for 
dealing with safety and efficacy issues. Innovative re sec-
to scope modifications have also been developed. The side-
to-side bidirectional lateral rotating handgrip and loop </p>

<p>allows excellent precision and control over the loop under 
direct vision [4]. Loop modification, the so-called "runner," 
can push the bladder wall away during resection, thereby 
widening the view and decreasing the risk of perforation 
[10]. We developed an easy and safe technique for an in-
experienced operator. We wanted a technique in which 
we could use a conventional resectoscope and loop without 
accessory equipment. 
When using a wire-loop resectoscope, the tumor must 
be resected thoroughly to obtain adequate muscle tissue. 
The movement of the loop is somewhat fast and deep to 
avoid charring of the surrounding mucosa and bladder 
perforation [11]. These are key technique of TURBT, but 
not so easy to perform. Our technique has the merit of 
acquiring adequate tissue. Direct pressure to the bladder 
wall may allow deeper tissue to protrude into the bladder 
wall and then be easily removed by use of the resectoscope. 
Instead of the curvilinear movement of the resectoscope 
end according to the curved bladder surface, the easy 
linear motion can make a curved resection with grasping. 
Using our "grasp and bite" technique, beginners can easily 
perform TURBT safely. Often, small and sessile tumors 
are missed and severely damaged during resection and 
cauterization. The grasp and bite technique can effectively 
be applied to small, flat, sessile lesions. For larger tumors, 
the protruding tumor can be removed f irst by the 
conventional method, and then the stalk and base lesion 
can be removed by the grasp and bite technique. Poorly 
accessible tumors are difficult for complete resection. In 
theory, the grasp and bite technique could have difficulties 
in a posterior or posterolateral located tumor because of its 
moving mechanism. In our series, two posterior and four 
posterolateral tumors were successfully accessed by use 
of suprapubic pressure and nearly emptying the bladder. 
Similar to conventional TURBT, it was also difficult to 
access posterior tumors with the grasp and bite method. 
In our consecutive cases, obturator reflex was not prob-
lematic. There were no cases of excessive obturator reflex 
or bladder perforation in either group. General anesthesia 
was preferred in the conventional and grasp and bite 
groups (81.3% vs 57.3%, p=0.138). Also, tumor locations did 
not differ significantly between the two groups (p=0.253). 
We postulated that the grasping method, which lifts the 
tissue away from the obturator nerve and tightly holds 
the grasped tissue, may eventually weaken the reflex. 
Considering this small population, however, we cannot 
make conclusions and need to f urther study a larger 
population. 
This study had some limitations that may have limited </p>



<p>Oh et al </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4111/kju.2015.56.3.227 </p>

<p>the conclusions. First, the two groups were classif ied 
by the date of operation. Thus, there could have been a 
selection bias. Also, the study population was small, and 
thus we were unable to perform statistical analysis of 
the oncologic outcome as recurrence-free survival. This 
was a preliminary study to develop a surgical techni-
que performed by an experienced surgeon. Larger pro-
spective studies with a long f ollow-up period will be 
necessary to show the oncologic advantage of this tech-
nique. To determine the feasibility of the technique for 
inexperienced surgeons, future study will address a tea-
ching protocol comparing the conventional and grasp 
and bite methods. Owing to the nature of retrospective 
research, histologic information was not fully acquired. 
Investigation of tissue adequacy of proper muscle and 
effect of coagulation will be our next subject of study. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Our study demonstrated that grasp and bite TURBT 
is a safe and effective method for removing superficial 
bladder tumors. This technique has merit for flat tumors 
and can also be used for pedunculated and poorly acce-
ssible tumors. The grasp and bite method may be a short-
cut for overcoming the difficulties of TURBT. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was f inancially supported by Chonnam 
National University, 2009 and Basic Research Program, 
through the National Research Foundation of Korea 
(NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and 
Technology (2012-0002947). This research received a 2014 
academic award by The Korean Endourological Society. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>

<p>An accompanying video can be found in the 'urology in 
motion' section of the journal homepage (www.kjurology. 
org). The supplementary data can also be accessed by 
scanning a QR code located on the Fig. 1 of this article, or </p>

<p>be available on YouTube (http://youtu.be/2xJDgSpZvY4). </p>



</text></tei>