<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4225296" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: Cilostazol is an oral antiplatelet agent </p>

<p>currently indicated for treatment of intermittent 
claudication. There is evidence that cilostazol may 
reduce femoropopliteal restenosis after percutaneous 
endovascular intervention. </p>

<p>Methods: We searched PubMed, Scopus and </p>

<p>Cochrane databases from 1966 through September 
2013 for randomised controlled trials (RCTs) evaluating 
the addition of cilostazol to standard care in patients 
receiving femoropopliteal endovascular treatment. 
Restenosis, target lesion revascularisation and 
combined adverse outcomes (death, revascularisation 
and amputation) within 1-2 years postprocedure were 
evaluated. </p>

<p>Results: Of 205 articles, three RCTs were included in </p>

<p>the analysis. The pooled data provided a total of 396 
patients, 195 of whom received cilostazol. When 
compared to standard medical therapy alone, cilostazol 
significantly reduced the risk of restenosis (risk 
difference −0.20; 95% CI −0.29 to −0.11; p&lt;0.0001; 
number needed to treat 5), target lesion 
revascularisation (risk difference −0.17; 95% CI −0.25 
to −0.09; p&lt;0.0001; number needed to treat 6). Death 
and amputation were not different in between groups. </p>

<p>Conclusions and limitation: Cilostazol significantly </p>

<p>increases femoropopliteal patency and decreases 
adverse outcomes in percutaneous endovascular 
intervention. However, further RCTs are needed because 
of limited sample size; this meta-analysis represents the 
best current evidence. </p>

<p>three quarters of lower extremity PAD. 3 4 
Revascularisation is required for patients with 
critical limb ischaemia. The most recent guide-
lines on the management of femoropopliteal 
PAD have expanded the indications for endo-
vascular therapy (EVT) to the detriment of 
surgical revascularisation. 5-7 
Antiplatelet therapy is recommended 
after EVT for PAD. 5 Cilostazol is a 
phosphodiesterase-3 inhibitor indicated for 
the treatment of intermittent claudication. 5 8 
The potential benefits of cilostazol after EVT 
for PAD are not addressed in current guide-
lines. Therefore, we decided to perform a 
systematic literature review and meta-analysis 
of the outcomes of randomised controlled 
trials (RCTs) that compare cilostazol to </p>

<p>KEY MESSAGES </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject? </p>

<p>▸ Cilostazol could decrease restenosis rates after 
endovascular therapy for peripheral artery 
disease, but the current randomised controlled 
trials evaluating this have small sample size. </p>

<p>What does this study add? </p>

<p>▸ We sought to improve the current level of evidence 
by conducting a systematic review and meta-
analysis of cilostazol and outcomes after endovas-
cular therapy for peripheral artery disease. We 
discovered that compared to standard medical 
therapy alone, cilostazol significantly reduced the 
risk of restenosis and target lesion revascularisa-
tion without any significant side effects. </p>

<p>How might this impact on clinical practice? </p>

<p>▸ Our study provides the best current evidence for 
using cilostazol after endovascular therapy in per-
ipheral artery disease as well as a rationale for a 
large, multicentre randomised controlled trial. </p>

<p>Benjo AM, Garcia DC, Jenkins JS, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000154. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000154 </p>



<p>Meta-analysis </p>

<p>standard therapy alone after EVT for femoropopliteal 
PAD disease. Cilostazol could potentially improve pro-
cedural outcomes at a low cost, as it has been demon-
strated to be cost-effective for the treatment of 
intermittent claudication due to PAD. 9 10 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Search strategy 
We systematically searched PubMed, Scopus and 
Cochrane Central Register of Controlled Trials for RCTs 
from 1966 to September 2013, which compared cilosta-
zol to standard medical therapy in patients with femoro-
popliteal EVT. The review was performed in accordance 
with established methods for systematic reviews in car-
diovascular medicine. 11 The following medical subject 
heading terms were included for a MEDLINE search 
and adapted for other databases as needed: "cilostazol" 
AND ("peripheral arterial disease" OR "endovascular 
therapy" OR "femoropopliteal"). In addition to search-
ing databases, reference lists of all included studies, 
meta-analyses and reviews were manually searched, 
including unpublished data. There was neither language 
nor patient population size restriction for the search. </p>

<p>Data extraction 
Two authors independently completed data extraction 
after following defined search criteria and quality assess-
ment. They obtained data from tables, text and graphs. 
When the data were presented in percentage the absolute 
values were calculated. Disagreements were resolved by 
consensus after review by the senior author of the study. </p>

<p>Selection criteria 
Inclusion criteria were RCTs with (1) a direct compari-
son between patients treated with cilostazol and a 
control group who received standard medical therapy 
alone; (2) patients with femoropopliteal lesions due to 
PAD; (3) patients who received EVT; and (4) reports of 
the primary and secondary outcomes. Exclusion criteria 
were (1) studies that only reported outcomes of cilosta-
zol, without a direct comparison to a control group; (2) 
observational studies; (3) non-randomised clinical trials; 
and (4) overlapping patient population, identified by 
studies developed over the same period of time with 
common authors or common study centres. In this case, 
only the study with a greater number of patients was 
included. </p>

<p>Outcomes 
The primary outcome studied was 1-2-year incidence of 
restenosis after endovascular treatment defined by 
Doppler. Secondary outcomes of interest were 1-2-year 
target lesion revascularisation and combined major 
adverse outcomes, which included death, target lesion 
revascularisation, surgical revascularisation and amputa-
tions. When major combined outcomes were not pre-
sented as defined it was calculated adding the individual 
outcomes. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Meta-analysis was performed according to recommenda-
tions of the Cochrane Collaboration and the Quality of 
Reporting of Meta-analyses (QUORUM) guidelines and 
PRISMA statement using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Review Manager</rs> (RevMan) 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.5.2 version</rs> (Copenhagen, Nordic Cochrane Centre, </p>

<p>Figure 1 Studies selection. </p>



<p>Benjo AM, Garcia DC, Jenkins JS, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000154. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000154 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of studies included in the meta-analysis </p>

<p>Author 
Iida et al 14 
Iida et al 16 
Soga et al 15 
Follow-up 
24 months 
12 months 
24 months 
Inclusion criteria 1. De novo FP lesions &gt;50% 
2. Occlusion without inflow lesions 
3. Outflow lesions of below-the-knee arteries of 
&gt;1 vessel runoff 
4. Symptomatic PAD with claudication (Fontaine 
2, 3 or 4) </p>

<p>1. Patients with symptomatic PAD greater than 
Rutherford 1 screened by non-invasive tests to 
detect limb ischaemia and the presence of de 
novo FP lesions </p>

<p>1. Symptoms not improved by 
pharmacotherapy or exercise therapy 
2. Age &gt;18 years and &lt;80 years old 
3. ABI &lt;0.9 
4. DS &gt;50% by visual estimate on 
angiography 
Exclusion 
criteria </p>

<p>1. Acute onset critical limb ischaemia 
2. Previous bypass surgery or 
3. Previous angioplasty for the FP lesions 
4. Presence of untreated pelvic lesions 
5. Intolerance to the medication or contrast 
agents </p>

<p>1. Treated with coronary DES 
2. Heart failure symptoms with systolic or diastolic 
dysfunction evaluated by cardiac 
echocardiography 
3. Inflow aortoiliac lesions 
4. FP lesions with severe calcification 
5. Poor below-the-knee runoff defined as number of 
below-the-knee runoff &lt;1 </p>

<p>1. Patients with previous lower extremity 
bypass surgery 
2. Previous EVT in the femoropopliteal 
artery 
3. Acute onset limb ischaemia 
4. Rutherford category 4, 5 or 6 </p>

<p>Control group 
1. Aspirin (100 mg/day)+ticlopidine (200 mg/day) 
1. Aspirin (100 mg/day) 
2. Patients who received stents were also treated 
with a thienopyridine </p>

<p>1. Aspirin (81-100 mg/day) and ticlopidine 
(200 mg/day) </p>

<p>Intervention 
group </p>

<p>1. Aspirin (100 mg/day) and cilostazol (200 mg/ 
day) </p>

<p>1. Aspirin (100 mg/day) and cilostazol (200 mg/day) 
2. Patients who received stents were also treated 
with a thienopyridine </p>

<p>1. Aspirin (81-100 mg/day), ticlopidine 
(200 mg/day) and cilostazol (200 mg/ 
day) 
Outcomes 
definition </p>

<p>1. Lesion patency: peak systolic velocity ratio 
&gt;2.4 by DUS </p>

<p>1. Target lesion revascularisation: reintervention 
performed for &gt;50% diameter stenosis identified 
by angiography within 5 mm of the target lesion 
after documentation of recurrent symptoms of 
PAD 
2. Angiographic restenosis: recurrence of ≥50% 
diameter stenosis; a peak systolic velocity ratio 
of &gt;2.0 on Duplex ultrasonography </p>

<p>1. Target lesion: treated segment from 
10 mm proximal to 10 mm distal 
2. TLR: any repeat EVT for restenosis or 
other complication of the target lesion 
with a %DS of &gt;50% in angiography 
3. Restenosis: peak systolic velocity ratio of 
≥2.4 on Duplex ultrasonography </p>

<p>Endovascular 
procedure </p>

<p>After balloon inflation for at least 1 min, 
self-expanding stent was done if: 
1. Pressure gradient &gt;10 mm Hg OR 
2. &gt;30% residual stenosis OR 
3. flow-limiting dissection 
A nitinol stent (Luminexx, CR Bard, Murray Hill, 
NJ) or cobalt metallic stent (Wallstent, Boston 
Scientific, Natick, Mass) with the diameter 1 mm 
larger than the reference diameter was used 
Stents of 6 mm in diameter were used in most 
cases </p>

<p>After balloon inflation for at least 1 min, stent was 
done if: 
1. Flow-limiting dissection OR 
2. Pressure gradient &gt;10 mm Hg OR 
3. &gt;30% residual stenosis 
Patients received SMART stents (Cordis Corp, 
Miami Lakes, Florida, USA) with a diameter 1 mm 
larger than the reference vessel diameter </p>

<p>After balloon inflation for at least 1 min, 
self-expanding stent was done if: 
1. Angiographic residual stenosis of &gt;30% 
OR 
2. Flow-limiting dissection 
A commercially available self-expandable 
stent was used 
Stent type was determined by the operators, 
and the stent size was chosen to be 1-
2 mm larger than the vessel diameter 
determined </p>

<p>ABI, Ankle Brachial Index; DES, drug-eluting stent; DS, diameter of stenosis; EVT, endovascular therapy; DUS, distal ultrasound; FP, femoropopliteal lesion; MI, myocardial infarction; PAD, 
peripheral arterial disease; SMART, stent: Cordis Corp, Miami Lakes; TLR, target lesion revascularisation. </p>

<p>Benjo AM, Garcia DC, Jenkins JS, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000154. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000154 </p>

<p> 
Meta-analysis </p>

<p>The Cochrane Collaboration, 2012). 12 13 Pooled treat-
ment effects were estimated using risk difference (RD) 
with the Mantel-Haenszel method. We calculated the 
number needed to treat (NNT) according to the recom-
mendations 
of 
the 
Cochrane 
Collaboration. 13 
Heterogeneity was assessed using χ 2 tests and I 2 statistic; 
we defined I 2 &lt;25% as low heterogeneity according to 
the Cochrane Handbook of Systematic Reviews. We per-
formed fixed effect analysis when I 2 was less than 25% 
or p value at least 0.10; otherwise we used random 
effect. We assessed quality for each included trial accord-
ing to the methods of the Cochrane Collaboration. 13 All 
included studies were controlled trials and were consid-
ered high quality. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
The process of study selection is shown in figure 1. 
Initial MEDLINE search using a systematic approach 
yielded 205 studies. The search in EMBASE and 
Cochrane registries did not yield additional studies. 
Through a review of titles and abstracts, 173 studies were 
rejected due to lack of relevance to our meta-analysis. 
The remaining 32 articles were reviewed and assessed 
for satisfaction of the inclusion or exclusion criteria. 
Three studies met all criteria and were included in this 
analysis. 
The first study 14 had a follow-up period of 24 months 
and compared cilostazol/aspirin with ticlopidine/aspirin 
in 200 patients with femoropopliteal lesions. At 12 and 
24 months, the cilostazol/aspirin group reduced resten-
osis rates (18% vs 43% and 27% vs 52%, respectively). A 
smaller study in 2009 15 also found similar results with 
restenosis rates (43% vs 70.3%). These findings were 
validated in a larger multicentre study in 2013 with 200 
patients 16 that demonstrated an angiographic restenosis 
rate at 12 months of 20% in cilostazol group versus 49% 
in the non-cilostazol group. 
In order to obtain pooled estimates, a total of 396 
patients were included in this analysis. Following EVT 
for femoropopliteal PAD lesions, 195 individuals were 
treated with cilostazol and standard medical therapy, 
whereas 201 received standard medical therapy alone, 
which included aspirin and a thienopyridine. The main 
characteristics of individual studies can be found in 
table 1. Of note, stent restenosis by Doppler was defined 
as a peak systolic velocity ratio &gt;2.4 in Iida et al 14 and 
Soga et al 15 and &gt;2 in Iida et al. 16 
Table 2 illustrates baseline characteristics of popula-
tions in the individual studies. All baseline variables 
including stenting ratio were similar in all studies with 
the exception of preprocedural Ankle Brachial Index 
(ABI) in Iida et al 16 ; despite both groups having the ABI 
on the moderate disease range it was higher on the cilos-
tazol group (0.71 vs 0.66). 
For the primary outcome, as seen in figure 2, the 
follow-up revealed a significantly reduced incidence of 
restenosis in patients who received cilostazol in addition </p>

<p>Table 2 
Baseline characteristics in individual studies </p>

<p>Study </p>

<p>Iida 
et al 14 </p>

<p>Iida 
et al 16 </p>

<p>Soga 
et al 15 </p>

<p>CLSZ </p>

<p>CTR </p>

<p>p Value </p>

<p>CLSZ </p>

<p>CTR </p>

<p>p Value </p>

<p>CLSZ </p>

<p>CTR </p>

<p>p Value </p>

<p>Number of patients (n) </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Age, mean±SD </p>

<p>70±9 </p>

<p>70±8 </p>

<p>0.94 </p>

<p>72±9 </p>

<p>73±8 </p>

<p>0.51 </p>

<p>69.8±7 </p>

<p>71.6±8.1 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>Male, n (%) </p>

<p>19 (30.2) </p>

<p>16 (25) </p>

<p>0.51 </p>

<p>64 (69) </p>

<p>67 (68) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>31 (79) </p>

<p>34 (87) </p>

<p>0.36 </p>

<p>Diabetes, n (%) </p>

<p>46 (73) </p>

<p>46 (72) </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>52 (56) </p>

<p>55 (56) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>12 (31) </p>

<p>16 (41) </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>Hypertension, % </p>

<p>59 (94) </p>

<p>59 (92) </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>75 (81) </p>

<p>80 (82) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>19 (49) </p>

<p>19 (49) </p>

<p>0.99 </p>

<p>Dyslipidaemia, n (%) </p>

<p>33 (52) </p>

<p>34 (53) </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>41 (44) </p>

<p>49 (50) </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>15 (38) </p>

<p>11 (28) </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>Current smoking, n (%) </p>

<p>39 (62) </p>

<p>37 (58) </p>

<p>0.63 </p>

<p>41 (44)* </p>

<p>47 (48)* </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>13 (33) </p>

<p>17 (44) </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>Renal insufficiency, n (%) † </p>

<p>16 (25) </p>

<p>19 (30) </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>15 (16) </p>

<p>15 (15) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>8 (21) </p>

<p>7 (18) </p>

<p>0.77 </p>

<p>Coronary artery disease, n (%) </p>

<p>38 (60) </p>

<p>42 (66) </p>

<p>0.53 </p>

<p>35 (38) </p>

<p>39 (40) </p>

<p>0.77 </p>

<p>21 (54) </p>

<p>21 (54) </p>

<p>0.99 </p>

<p>Preprocedure ABI, mean±SD </p>

<p>0.60 ±0.23 </p>

<p>0.57±0.22 </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>0.71±0.15 </p>

<p>0.66±0.14 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.59±0.12 </p>

<p>0.64±0.15 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>Statin use, n (%) </p>

<p>19 (30) </p>

<p>22 (34) </p>

<p>0.29 </p>

<p>30 (32) </p>

<p>38 (39) </p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>10 (26) </p>

<p>9 (23) </p>

<p>0.79 </p>

<p>Stent, n (%) </p>

<p>56 (89) </p>

<p>54 (84) </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>82 (88) </p>

<p>88 (90) </p>

<p>0.82 </p>

<p>16 (41) </p>

<p>20 (51) </p>

<p>0.36 </p>

<p>*Iida 
et al: 16 
combines current and prior smoking. </p>

<p> †Renal insufficiency definitions: Cr &gt;2 in Iida </p>

<p>et al; 14 
dialysis in Iida </p>

<p>et al; 16 
Cr &gt;1.5 in Soga </p>

<p>et al. 15 </p>

<p>CLSZ, cilostazol; CTR, control group; NA, not applicable; ABI, Ankle Brachial Index. </p>



<p>Benjo AM, Garcia DC, Jenkins JS, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000154. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000154 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>to standard medical (RD −0.20; 95% CI −0.29 to −0.11; 
p&lt;0.0001; NNT 5). This was reflected on a reduced 
need for target lesion revascularisation (RD −0.17; 95% 
CI −0.25 to −0.09; p&lt;0.0001; NNT 6) with a NNT of 5 
for both outcomes (figure 3). We also conducted a sen-
sitivity analysis utilising OR as the primary pooled esti-
mate and the effect size did not change. Death and 
amputations did not statistically differ between the two 
groups. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The potential benefit of cilostazol following EVT for 
femoropopliteal PAD was investigated in this study. Our 
meta-analysis of RCTs revealed that 75 of 201 patients 
not treated with cilostazol have developed restenosis 
within 12-24 months and that the chance of restenosis 
may be mitigated in more than 50% with cilostazol. This 
result is particularly significant when taken into account 
that cilostazol is a generic and inexpensive drug that has 
been shown to be a cost-effective drug in other clinical 
scenarios, such as treatment of intermittent claudication 
and secondary prevention of cerebral infarction 9 10 and 
that the benefit is obtained with a small NNT. 
One-year incidence of restenosis after balloon angio-
plasty of femoropopliteal lesions has been reported as 
high as 64%. 17 18 Sirolimus-eluting stents 19-21 and endo-
vascular brachytherapy 22 23 have failed to demonstrate a 
long-term decrease in the restenosis incidence following 
lower extremity EVT for PAD, but paclitaxel-eluting 
stents have shown increased patency and a lower rate of 
events. 23 Nevertheless, patency has greatly improved 
since the introduction of nitinol stents. 18 24 When com-
pared to percutaneous transluminal angioplasty, the use 
of nitinol stenting decreased the 12-month restenosis </p>

<p>incidence from 81.3% to 36.7% in a RCT. 18 
Nevertheless, the results of this meta-analysis suggest 
that patency rates can be further increased with cilosta-
zol in addition to nitinol stents, given that stent use did 
not differ among cilostazol and control groups, as illu-
strated in table 2. 
Cilostazol has been shown to decrease restenosis and 
repeat revascularisation after percutaneous coronary 
intervention in patients with coronary artery disease, 
without an increased bleeding risk. 25 Similarly, in this 
meta-analysis, target lesion revascularisation occurred in 
about every third patient on the control group over a 
12-24 month follow-up. The chance of requiring a 
repeat target lesion revascularisation was reduced in 
more than 60% with the use of cilostazol. The combined 
incidence of death, revascularisation and amputation 
was also significantly reduced in the cilostazol group 
but it was mostly driven by the reduced need for 
revascularisation. 
The main mechanism for cilostazol-mediated decrease 
in restenosis and target lesion revascularisation after EVT 
is likely inhibition of intimal hyperplasia. Cilostazol has 
been shown to suppress neointimal hyperplasia in animal 
models. 26 27 Furthermore, RCTs have demonstrated that 
triple antiplatelet therapy with aspirin, clopidogrel and 
cilostazol was more effective than dual therapy alone in 
suppressing intimal hyperplasia. 28 A second mechanism 
for improved outcomes in the cilostazol group is vasodila-
tion. Studies have shown that cilostazol increases walking 
distance in patients with PAD and improves ankle-brachial 
index due to vasodilation. 29-31 Moreover, cilostazol med-
iates an in-vitro inhibition of smooth muscle cell prolifer-
ation. 32 Whether this effect contributes to improved EVT 
procedural outcomes is unknown. Cilostazol also inhibits 
platelet aggregation. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Twelve-month to 24-month incidence of restenosis. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Twelve-month to 24-month incidence of target lesion revascularisation. </p>

<p>Benjo AM, Garcia DC, Jenkins JS, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000154. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000154 </p>



<p>Meta-analysis </p>

<p>This meta-analysis has some limitations. Owing to the 
limited number of studies the sample size is small. 
However, despite the limited sample size, our 
meta-analysis represents the best available evidence for 
the use of cilostazol to increase femoropopliteal patency 
after endovascular intervention. As with any meta-
analysis, our study is subject to publication bias that is 
potentially mitigated by the exclusive use of RCTs. 
Although the time frame of outcomes varied from 12 to 
24 months, most cases of restenosis following EVT for 
femoropopliteal lesions occurred from 6 to 12 months, 33 
a time frame that was included in this study. The avail-
able data are exclusively from Asian populations and it is 
possible that our results apply exclusively to Asian popu-
lations, but that is unlikely due to prior positive cilosta-
zol studies in other populations. Finally, regarding the 
antiplatelet properties of cilostazol, bleeding complica-
tions could not be assessed given that this outcome was 
not reported in all included studies and this could be 
considered to be an important limitation of our analysis. 
Only Soga's study attempted comparing major bleeding 
in dual versus triple therapy but no patients had events. 
Although not reported in these studies, there is robust 
evidence that when cilostazol is used in combination 
with dual antiplatelet therapy for other indications, 
there is no increased risk of bleeding compared to dual 
antiplatelet therapy alone. For example, in an RCT with 
patients with acute coronary syndrome undergoing stent-
ing, triple therapy had similar bleeding events compared 
with dual antiplatelet therapy. 34 
In summary, in our meta-analysis of RCTs, cilostazol 
following endovascular treatment for femoropopliteal 
PAD was shown to significantly reduce restenosis, target 
lesion revascularisation and combined adverse outcomes 
when compared to a standard therapy control group. 
Large RCTs are urged to confirm our findings. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Division of Interventional Cardiology, Ochsner Medical Center, New Orleans, 
Louisiana, USA </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Internal Medicine, University of Miami, Miami, Florida, USA </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Internal Medicine, Centro Universitario Luziadas School of 
Medicine, Santos, Brazil </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Department of Cardiology, St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center at Mount 
Sinai, New York, USA </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Division of Nephrology, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, 
USA </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Cardiology Department, St. Luke's Mid America Heart Institute, Kansas City, 
Missouri, USA </p>

<p>Contributors AMB, DCG, JSJ and TC were involved in the conception and 
study design. AMB, JSJ, RMNC and TPM were involved in the literature 
review. GEE-H, GNN, EFA and JJD were involved in the data collection. GNN, 
GEE-H, EFA and TPM were involved in the statistical analysis. AMB, DCG, 
GNN and TC were involved in the revising manuscript critically for important 
intellectual content. AMB, DCG, RMNC, TPM, GEE-H, GNN, EFA, JJD and TC 
were involved in the final approval of the manuscript submitted. </p>

<p>Competing interests No authors have any relationship with industry related 
to this manuscript. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Benjo AM, Garcia DC, Jenkins JS, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000154. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000154 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>





<p>Meta-analysis </p>

</text></tei>