<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4198632" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Results: Maintaining due thoroughness when dissecting tissues and treating the cutting line in this area with liga-
tures and tissue puncture are the most reliable methods of minimizing the risk of lymphatic leakage after surgical 
procedures performed in a classical way. The lymphatic complication under analysis is far less likely to occur when 
procedures are performed as planned and an endovascular technique is used -statistical significance p &lt; 0.05. Min-
imally invasive and fully percutaneous procedures performed via needle puncture, including the use of the fascial 
closure technique to close the femoral artery, eliminate the likelihood of the occurrence of this vascular complication 
-statistical significance was found with p value less than 0.05. 
Conclusions: We concluded that in every case by minimizing the vascular approach we protected the patient against 
lymphatic complications. </p>

<p>Key words: lymphatic leakage, vascular prosthetics, access complications. </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 3, September/2014 </p>

<p>Lymphatic complications after vascular interventions </p>

<p>421 </p>

<p>a vascular prosthetics or a patch) can occur, which 
can result in septic bleeding [2], septicemia [7], or 
multi-organ failure [8] (Table I). </p>

<p>Aim </p>

<p>The aim of the study was to analyze lymphat-
ic complications after vascular surgery in patients 
treated at the Department of Vascular and Endovas-
cular Surgery of the Military Institute of Medicine 
in Warsaw in 2005-2012, and in the Department of 
Interventional Cardiology and Angiology of the Insti-
tute of Cardiology in Anin, Warsaw, in 2009-2012, 
where aortic valve implantations through femoral 
access were performed. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>The analysis included 1,580 patients who under-
went surgery during this period. The procedures per-
formed involved the following vascular areas: neck, 
thorax, abdomen, retroperitoneal space, and lower 
extremities. The sample group consisted of 1,232 
(77.9%) men and 348 (22.1%) women. The mean 
age was 45 years (35-95 years). One hundred and 
eight transcatheter aortic valve implantation (TAVI) </p>

<p>procedures were performed. Three hundred and sev-
enty patients underwent a planned endovascular 
aneurysm repair (EVAR) procedure due to abdominal 
aorta aneurysm whereas 42 were operated on due 
to a ruptured abdominal aorta aneurysm (rAAA). At 
that time, 51 patients with a thoracic aorta aneu-
rysm underwent a planned thoracic EVAR (TEVAR) 
procedure and 22 emergency TEVAR procedures. In 
the latter case, they were traumatic ruptures of the 
thoracic descending aorta, immediately beneath the 
point where the left subclavian artery branches off. 
Moreover, 39 stent graft implantations to the tho-
racic artery due to acute aorta dissection (AAD) were 
performed. From the group of patients treated clas-
sically due to an abdominal aorta aneurysm (AAA), 
only those patients who required the implantation of 
a bifurcated (aortobifemoral) prosthesis were select-
ed, since lymphorrhea was only observed in those 
patients. This group consisted of 112 patients oper-
ated on as planned and 13 patients who underwent 
emergency surgery due to a ruptured aneurysm. Fur-
thermore, in the period under analysis, 212 patients 
were surgically treated due to an aortobiiliac occlu-
sion. Another type of surgery was a femoropopliteal 
bypass graft, which was performed in 136 patients. </p>

<p>Table I. Lymphorrhea -a summary overview according to surgical procedure </p>

<p>Type of surgery 
Number of 
procedures, n </p>

<p>Number of lymphatic 
leakages, n </p>

<p>Percentage 
(in groups) [%] </p>

<p>TAVI 
108 
2 
1.8 </p>

<p>EVAR (planned) 
370 
18 
4.8 </p>

<p>EVAR (emergency) 
42 
5 
11.9 </p>

<p>TEVAR (planned) 
51 
3 
5.8 </p>

<p>TEVAR (emergency) 
22 
3 
13.6 </p>

<p>AAD 
39 
2 
5.1 </p>

<p>Classical AAA 
112 
5 
4.4 </p>

<p>Classical rAAA 
13 
2 
15.4 </p>

<p>Aortobifemoral bypass graft 
212 
13 
6.1 </p>

<p>Femoropopliteal bypass graft 
136 
15 
11.02 </p>

<p>Femoral artery embolectomy 
166 
15 
7.2 </p>

<p>Profundoplasty 
111 
12 
10.8 </p>

<p>Suprapubic vascular graft 
36 
4 
11.1 </p>

<p>Subclavian artery transposition 
21 
2 
9.5 </p>

<p>Femoral artery pseudoaneurysm 
83 
15 
18.07 </p>

<p>Fascial closure 
58* 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Total number of procedures 
1,580 </p>

<p>*Fascial closure was performed in 58 patients closing 116 common femoral arteries. </p>

<p>Andrzej Obara, Miroslaw A. Dziekiewicz, Marek Maruszynski, Adam Witkowski, Maciej Dąbrowski, Zbigniew Chmielak </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 3, September/2014 </p>



<p>At the same time, 166 patients required femoral ar-
tery embolectomy. Profundoplasty was performed in 
111 patients. A suprapubic vascular graft was sug-
gested to 36 patients. Twenty-one procedures of 
subclavian artery transposition were performed in 
patients with subclavian steal syndrome. Another 
examined group was made up of patients with fem-
oral artery pseudoaneurysms. This group consisted 
of 83 patients. The last group comprised patients in 
whom fully percutaneous stent-graft implantations 
due to an abdominal or thoracic aorta aneurysm 
were performed. Thus, the femoral artery was closed 
by performing fascial closure. This group consisted 
of 58 patients in whom homeostasis was achieved 
after bilateral removal of stent-graft implantation 
sets in the manner mentioned above. In this way, 
116 common femoral arteries were closed. 
After 94-240 h, lymphatic leakage occurred in 
all patients and persisted from 7 to 24 days. Lym-
phatic leakage was reported in 2 patients (1.8%) af-
ter TAVI, 18 (4.8%) after planned EVAR procedures, 
5 (11.9%) after emergency EVAR procedures, 3 (5.8%) 
after planned TEVAR procedures and 3 (13.6%) after 
emergency TEVAR procedures. Following endovas-
cular treatment of acute thoracic aorta dissection, 
lymphatic leakage occurred in 2 patients (5.1%). In 
patients on whom open AAA surgery was carried 
out, 5 (4.4%) cases of lymphorrhea were observed 
-and 2 (15.4%) in those operated on due to rAAA. 
In the group of patients with aortobiiliac occlusion, 
after performing aortobifemoral (bypass) graft sur-
gery, 13 (6.1%) cases of lymphatic leakage were re-
ported. Another group was made up of patients who 
underwent femoropopliteal bypass graft surgery, in 
which 15 (11.02%) cases of lymphatic leakage were 
detected. In 2 patients from this group, the leakage 
occurred in the wound in the popliteal fossa. Fifteen 
(7.2%) cases of lymphorrhea were observed after 
femoral artery embolectomy, 12 (10.8%) after pro-
fundoplasty, and 4 (11.1%) after a suprapubic graft 
procedure. A further 2 (9.5%) cases of lymphatic 
leakage were detected in the group of patients who 
underwent subclavian artery transposition. After the 
surgical treatment of a femoral artery pseudoaneu-
rysm, lymphorrhea occurred in 15 (18.07%) patients. 
Only in the group of patients who underwent per-
cutaneous procedures, i.e. when treating thoracic 
and abdominal aorta aneurysms without dissecting 
femoral arteries, were no lymphatic complications 
observed. </p>

<p>Postoperative wound suppuration in the groin 
occurred in 11 (0.7%) cases whereas in 2 instances 
(0.1%) septic bleeding was reported due to complete 
decay of the femoral artery in patients after profun-
doplasty with a Dacron patch sewn in, and femo-
ropopliteal bypass graft surgery. Prolonged wound 
healing, after the lymphatic leakage had stopped 
and the infection had been cured, led to femoropop-
liteal bypass graft clotting in 2 (0.1%) patients. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>For the purposes of statistical evaluation, the 
post-hoc ANOVA test of <rs type="software">Statistica v. 10</rs> was used. 
Statistically significant results were those for which 
p &lt; 0.05. They are highlighted in red in Table II. 
What can be clearly observed when analyzing the 
scores in the first column is that the frequency of 
occurrence of lymphatic leakage is statistically sig-
nificant in comparison to TAVI with the emergency 
EVAR procedure, and then with femoropopliteal by-
pass graft surgery, femoral embolectomy, profundo-
plasty, and pseudoaneurysm. The second column 
contains a comparison of results between patients 
who underwent planned endovascular surgery due 
to an abdominal aorta aneurysm and other surgical 
procedures. As above, these scores are statistical-
ly significant for similar groups of patients, except 
the patients after femoral embolectomy, where no 
statistical significance was determined (p = 0.084). 
The third column presents a comparison of results 
in relation to an emergency EVAR procedure. In such 
a perspective, statistical significance only emerged 
for the comparison with the TAVI procedure and fas-
cial closure. In the remaining pairs, this significance 
was not detected. Comparing the TEVAR procedure 
with other procedures, statistical significance only 
occurred in relation to the femoral artery pseu-
doaneurysm surgical procedure, where p = 0.008. 
A comparison between the emergency TEVAR pro-
cedure and all other types of procedures included 
in the study and presented in column 5 indicated 
statistical significance only when compared to fas-
cial closure (p = 0.035). The sixth column contains 
scores for patients operated on due to AAD relative 
to other groups. Statistical significance was demon-
strated only for a pair-wise comparison with pseu-
doaneurysm surgery. Column 7 shows a comparison 
between planned classical AAA treatment results 
with the remaining types of surgery. In this case, sta-</p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 3, September/2014 </p>

<p>Lymphatic complications after vascular interventions </p>



<p>tistical significance was discovered for the compari-
son with patients operated on due to femoral artery 
pseudoaneurysm, and in patients who underwent 
femoropopliteal bypass graft surgery. The eighth 
column shows the results of a pair-wise comparison 
between the patients operated on due to rAAA and 
the remaining groups. In this configuration, none of 
the compared pairs of procedures showed statistical 
significance. It needs to be noted that the score clos-
est to statistical significance was the comparison 
with fascial closure (p = 0.052). The ninth column 
presents the scores of comparisons for the aortobi-
femoral bypass graft surgery. Statistical significance 
occurred only in comparison with the group of pa-
tients operated on due to femoral artery pseudoan-
eurysm. The tenth column contains the results of 
a comparison relative to lymphatic leakage after the 
femoropopliteal bypass graft surgery. Statistical sig-
nificance also occurred when comparing the afore-
mentioned surgery with TAVI, EVAR, planned AAA 
surgery, and fascial closure. The eleventh column 
shows the results of a comparison between femoral 
artery embolectomy and the remaining operations. </p>

<p>Statistical significance was established when fem-
oral artery embolectomy was compared with TAVI, 
the femoral artery pseudoaneurysm procedure, and 
fascia closure. The twelfth column presents a com-
parison of results for profundoplasty. Values of 
p &lt; 0.05 were found for the comparison with TAVI, 
EVAR, as well as the pseudoaneurysm procedure 
and fascial closure. The thirteenth column compris-
es scores for the suprapubic vascular graft proce-
dure. Statistical significance was determined for the 
pair-wise comparison with the group of patients in 
whom fascial closure was performed. The fourteenth 
column presents the comparison of results for the 
subclavian artery transposition surgery. As we can 
see, no statistical significance was determined here. 
In the fifteenth column, a comparison between 
the pseudoaneurysm procedure and other types of 
surgery indicated statistical significance for TAVI, 
planned EVAR, planned TEVAR, AAD, planned clas-
sical AAA, aortobifemoral bypass graft surgery, and 
fascial closure. The sixteenth and last column shows 
the results of a comparison with fascial closure. Here, 
statistical significance was observed when compar-</p>

<p>Table II. Post-hoc analysis, ANOVA </p>

<p>{1} 
{2} 
{3} 
{4} 
{5} 
{6} 
{7} 
{8} 
{9} 
{10} {11} {12} {13} {14} {15} 
{16} </p>

<p>Mean 0.018 0.048 0.119 0.058 0.136 0.051 0.044 0.153 0.061 0.110 0.090 0.108 0.111 0.095 0.180 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>{1} </p>

<p>0.287 0.032 0.359 0.051 0.498 0.454 0.075 0.162 0.006 0.024 0.010 0.063 0.214 1.8E-Q5 0.660 </p>

<p>{2} </p>

<p>0.287 
0.095 0.792 0.122 0.951 0.885 0.150 0.569 0.017 0.084 0.033 0.167 0.422 2.8E-Q5 0.183 </p>

<p>{3} </p>

<p>0.032 0.095 
0.264 0.799 0.239 0.112 0.671 0.186 0.848 0.521 0.815 0.892 0.730 0.208 0.023 </p>

<p>{4} </p>

<p>0.359 0.792 0.264 
0.240 0.891 0.745 0.237 0.950 0.226 0.446 0.260 0.353 0.587 0.008 0.236 </p>

<p>{5} </p>

<p>0.051 0.122 0.799 0.240 
0.217 0.128 0.846 0.195 0.661 0.433 0.640 0.718 0.602 0.474 0.035 </p>

<p>{6} </p>

<p>0.498 0.951 0.239 0.891 0.217 
0.890 0.216 0.823 0.209 0.396 0.238 0.317 0.530 0.010 0.338 </p>

<p>{7} </p>

<p>0.454 0.885 0.112 0.745 0.128 0.890 
0.150 0.581 0.047 0.148 0.067 0.180 0.411 0.0003 0.286 </p>

<p>{8} </p>

<p>0.075 0.150 0.671 0.237 0.846 0.216 0.150 
0.211 0.562 0.394 0.546 0.610 0.521 0.727 0.052 </p>

<p>{9} </p>

<p>0.162 0.569 0.186 0.950 0.195 0.823 0.581 0.211 
0.0852 0.279 0.123 0.286 0.566 0.0004 0.110 </p>

<p>{10} 0.006 0.017 0.848 0.226 0.661 0.209 0.047 0.562 0.085 </p>

<p>0.505 0.947 0.986 0.804 0.050 0.006 </p>

<p>{11} 0.024 0.084 0.521 0.446 0.433 0.396 0.148 0.394 0.279 0.505 </p>

<p>0.576 0.662 0.935 0.009 0.022 </p>

<p>{12} 0.010 0.033 0.815 0.260 0.640 0.238 0.067 0.546 0.123 0.947 0.576 </p>

<p>0.951 0.834 0.053 0.010 </p>

<p>{13} 0.063 0.167 0.892 0.353 0.718 0.317 0.180 0.610 0.286 0.986 0.662 0.951 </p>

<p>0.823 0.178 0.043 </p>

<p>{14} 0.214 0.422 0.730 0.587 0.602 0.530 0.411 0.521 0.566 0.804 0.935 0.834 0.823 </p>

<p>0.176 0.148 </p>

<p>{15} 1.8E-Q5 2.8E-Q5 0.208 0.008 0.474 0.010 0.0003 0.727 0.0004 0.050 0.009 0.053 0.178 0.176 </p>

<p>4.7E-Q5 </p>

<p>{16} 0.660 0.183 0.023 0.236 0.035 0.338 0.286 0.052 0.110 0.006 0.022 0.010 0.043 O.148 4.7E-Q5 </p>

<p>Andrzej Obara, Miroslaw A. Dziekiewicz, Marek Maruszynski, Adam Witkowski, Maciej Dąbrowski, Zbigniew Chmielak </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 3, September/2014 </p>



<p>ing fascial closure with emergency EVAR, emergency 
TEVAR, femoropopliteal bypass graft surgery, femo-
ral artery embolectomy, profundoplasty, the supra-
pubic vascular graft procedure, and femoral artery 
pseudoaneurysm. 
The number of procedures comprising the groups 
under comparison has an influence on the final re-
sults. Hence, for sets with the lowest number, the 
scores are unreliable. Nevertheless, the analysis of 
1,580 procedures allows certain regularities to be 
discerned. It has been established beyond doubt 
that mini-invasive and planned procedures bring 
about the fewest lymphatic complications. In addi-
tion, particular attention should be paid to closing 
the femoral artery by using the fascial closure tech-
nique where this complication was not observed. In 
addition, procedures necessitating the dissection of 
the femoral artery, particularly those performed mul-
tiple times, increase the risk of lymphatic leakage. 
For instance, profundoplasty or the suprapubic vas-
cular graft procedure is performed as a last resort, 
when no other options for lower-extremity revascu-
larization are available. Most frequently, they supple-
ment previous interventions. 
During the observation period, the leakage of 
lymphatic fluid stopped spontaneously in the ma-
jority of patients. The remaining patients were 
treated conservatively, with postoperative wounds 
being healed completely within 7-16 days from the 
moment the leakage occurred. All patients were 
administered multitarget antibiotics (third-gener-
ation cephalosporin and metronidazole), whereas 
in selected cases a targeted antibiotic therapy was 
applied. At that time, in severe cases of lymphor-
rhea, i.e. in patients where &gt; 500 ml/day of lymph 
fluid was drained, nutrition administered orally was 
stopped. Instead, the patients were fed parenter-
ally for 5-7 days. In some cases, good results were 
achieved by attempting compression therapy used 
after mini-invasive procedures, which involved put-
ting a dressing on the femoral puncture site and 
wrapping it with an elastic bandage. This type of 
compression was successfully applied in 11 patients. 
It was maintained for 72 h, with dressings changed 
1-2 times every day and a new elastic bandage ap-
plied. In the treatment of the most unresponsive pa-
tients, wound revision was performed along with the 
multilayer suture of the wound and the puncturing 
of sites that could constitute potential sources of 
lymphorrhea. The wound was revised in 8 (0.5%) pa-</p>

<p>tients. In 4 (0.25%) patients with partial wound de-
hiscence and lymphatic leakage, a vacuum-assisted 
closure therapy was applied. In all these cases, the 
wound was healed within 120 h after the surgery 
when the lymph fluid had stopped leaking. Further 
treatment was typical and involved granulation tis-
sue formation. 
In the aforementioned 2 patients in whom septic 
bleeding occurred, common femoral artery ligation 
was performed. Forty-eight and 72 h respectively af-
ter the surgical intervention, the patients had to un-
dergo thigh-level amputation surgery. In both cases, 
wounds in the groin healed by granulation, and the 
stumps healed per primam. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The lymphatics of the lower extremity consist 
of superficial and deep layers including vessels and 
nodes. The clusters of lymph nodes are variably 
distributed throughout the body and linked to one 
another by lymphatic vessels. These clusters form 
so-called vertical and horizontal bands. The number 
of superficial nodes is considerably higher than the 
deep nodes [1, 9]. Scarpa's triangle is the most com-
mon surgical access site to the femoral artery. Due 
to the close anatomic location of the vessel-abun-
dant lymphatic and blood circulatory systems, it 
is impossible to bypass reactively enlarged lymph 
nodes and connections between them. Reactive en-
largement of lymph nodes in this area is quite of-
ten observed due to prolonged lower extremity ar-
teriosclerosis, and in effect limb ischemia, but also 
due to abrasions, injuries, as well as toe and foot 
inflammation. This occurs particularly frequently in 
patients with a diabetic foot [10]. The latter can be 
symptomatic of the currently ongoing or past in-
flammatory condition. Inflammation may originate 
in the inflammatory processes of the perineum, gen-
itals, anus, rectum, and reproductive organs. It also 
happens that cancerous and tuberculous changes 
in lymphatic nodes are diagnosed. (*Hence, within 
the authors' department, in all cases where enlarged 
lymphatic nodes are diagnosed in this area, a sample 
is taken for pathomorphological examination. Based 
on the sample material taken thus far, 1 patient was 
diagnosed with tuberculosis and another with lym-
phoma.) Despite a very thorough examination of 
patients prior to planned surgery, it is very often 
impossible to establish based on the patient inter-</p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 3, September/2014 </p>

<p>Lymphatic complications after vascular interventions </p>



<p>view an unequivocal cause for the lymphatic nodes 
to be enlarged in this area. Further risk factors con-
ducive to the development of lymphatic fistula are: 
advanced age of patients, diabetes, wound infection, 
reoperation, the use of a synthetic prosthesis result-
ing in an inflammatory response and tissue irritation 
(e.g. PTFE or Dacron), excessive wound electrocoagu-
lation, incorrect suture technique that leaves empty 
spaces, and excessive patient mobility after an oper-
ation [1, 2, 7, 10, 11]. 
To prevent potential lymphorrhea from occurring, 
the lymphatic nodes should be bypassed by dissect-
ing tissues lateral to them. In the event of lymph 
node dissection, it is necessary to puncture and liga-
te them (*optional resection of lymph nodes entails 
the possibility of lymphedema of the surrounding 
tissues or the entire extremity on the operated side, 
associated with a temporary disturbance of lymph 
drainage). From a technical point of view, in order to 
avoid lymph node dissection, a longer curved skin in-
cision can be made externally to the lymph nodes, 
with the formation of a skin flap that is moved me-
dially. This can give access to the subcutaneous layer 
and the femoral fascia. This approach is particularly 
recommended in patients with inflammatory and ne-
crotic changes of the distal lower extremity [12]. Un-
fortunately, this approach does not entirely eliminate 
the incidence of lymphorrhea due to the transection 
of connecting small lymph vessels, which, if solely 
electrocoagulated or imprecisely ligated, have a ten-
dency to reopen. Lymphorrhea prevention can also 
involve multilayer suture and thorough closure of the 
surgical wound. In the past, attempts were made to 
use fibrin glue to treat these patients [1, 13]. 
The incidence of lymphorrhea after vascular 
surgery undoubtedly impedes wound healing, in-
creasing the cost of treatment, whereas prolonged 
lymphorrhea can lead to infection and wound sup-
puration. Mild lymphorrhea is cured following con-
servative treatment. However, more intense lym-
phorrhea triggering an inflammatory response in the 
surgical wound, as well as causing internal lymph 
pockets and partial wound dehiscence, necessitates 
surgical reintervention, or local vacuum-assisted 
therapy application [14-17]. Persistent lymphatic 
leakage, i.e. above 100 ml/day, is an indication for 
surgical intervention. In extreme cases, when the 
lymphatic leak reached 500 ml/day, parenteral nutri-
tion was stopped and intravenous supplementation 
was administered instead. In selected cases, a dose </p>

<p>of 3.5 µg/kg b.w./h of somatostatin IV was adminis-
tered by means of an infusion pump [5, 6, 18]. The 
somatostatin infusion was maintained for 72 h on 
average. Moreover, conservative treatment involved: 
lying with slightly lifted lower extremities, compres-
sion dressings, the puncture of the lymph pocket 
and the evacuation of the lymph fluid, local wound 
treatment, and, depending on the local wound con-
dition, intravenous administration of antibiotics. 
The healing of a wound itself, after persistent 
lymphorrhea accompanied by the inflammatory re-
sponse in the wound, does not eradicate the prob-
lem. The problem lies in the deep and hard scar 
tissue that can "draw in" vessels, i.e. an artery or 
a bypass graft, in the area where anastomosis was 
previously performed. As a consequence, this can 
lead to narrowing of the vessel or the anastomotic 
site, and subsequently to clotting. Hard scars make 
it difficult to reoperate in this area. It is not so rare 
that lymphorrhea can also complicate the technical 
success of reoperation [19]. 
The lymphatic system has, however, an amazing 
regenerative and continuity restoring capacity after 
transection or ligation. Therefore, the proportion of 
lymphatic fistulas occurring for this reason is rela-
tively low, which indicates that the choice of incision 
is not entirely responsible for it. 
As we can see, the problem of lymphatic fistula 
occurrence is quite complex. They are not limited to 
vascular interventions but can occur after any type 
of surgery. They can be observed after other proce-
dures, particularly oncological procedures, for exam-
ple as a consequence of extensive lymphadenec-
tomy [4]. It should be stressed that video-assisted 
surgery as a minimally invasive technique protects 
sufficiently against lymphorrhea [20, 21]. 
Maintaining due thoroughness when dissecting 
tissues and treating the cutting line in this area with 
ligatures and tissue puncture are the most reliable 
methods of minimizing the risk of lymphatic leak-
age after surgical procedures performed in a classi-
cal way. The lymphatic complication under analysis 
is far less likely to occur when procedures are per-
formed as planned and an endovascular technique 
is used. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Minimally invasive and fully percutaneous pro-
cedures performed via needle puncture, including </p>

<p>Andrzej Obara, Miroslaw A. Dziekiewicz, Marek Maruszynski, Adam Witkowski, Maciej Dąbrowski, Zbigniew Chmielak </p>

<p>Videosurgery and Other Miniinvasive Techniques 3, September/2014 </p>



<p>the use of the fascial closure technique to close the 
femoral artery, eliminate the likelihood of the occur-
rence of this vascular complication. </p>



<p>Received: 1.02.2014, accepted: 17.02.2014. </p>

</text></tei>