<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4016806" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: In an earlier study, we showed that human antigen R (HuR) and β-actin expression levels were downregulated 
in fibroblasts isolated from human keratoconus stroma compared to normal corneal stroma. To further extend the finding, 
we determined whether HuR expression affects β-actin gene expression and in turn affects corneal fibroblast migration 
and wound healing. 
Methods: Stromal keratocytes from normal human corneas were cultured in the presence of serum. Cells were trans-
fected with siRNA specific for β-actin or HuR. SiRNAs specific for GAPDH or a scrambled sequence were used as 
positive and negative controls (siCTR) for transfection, respectively. The effects of gene silencing were analyzed at the 
transcriptional and translational levels. Specific proteins were immunohistochemically localized using confocal imaging. 
The effects of gene silencing on cell migration and cell proliferation were analyzed using a modified Boyden chamber 
and with a wound healing assay, respectively. 
Results: Reverse-transcription PCR (RT-PCR) and western blot analyses showed that when the HuR gene was si-
lenced, β-actin expression was significantly downregulated. This was further confirmed at the translational level with 
immunohistochemical-confocal analysis. However, when the β-actin gene was silenced, its expression was significantly 
decreased but showed no effect on HuR gene expression. When the β-actin or HuR gene was individually silenced, the 
motility and proliferation of corneal fibroblasts were significantly reduced. 
Conclusions: The results show that downregulation of the HuR gene results in decreased β-actin gene expression, which 
in turn results in decreased motility and proliferation of corneal fibroblasts. We conclude that decreased β-actin expres-
sion in normal corneal stroma clearly disrupts the cytoskeletal structure and functions, including keratocyte motility 
and wound healing. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>Our previous studies on keratoconus stroma showed that 
β-actin and HuR expression levels were downregulated at the 
mRNA and protein expression levels compared to normal 
stroma. This raised the possibility that downregulation of 
HuR and β-actin could be a result of the interplay between 
the two [12]. In the present study, we used siRNA-mediated 
gene knockdown to determine if HuR gene silencing affects 
the stability of β-actin mRNA. The decreased HuR expres-
sion resulted in decreased β-actin gene and protein expres-
sion leading to decreased fibroblast wound healing and their 
proliferation. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Human corneas: Normal corneas, stored in Optisol (Chiron 
Ophthalmics, Irvine, CA) at 4 °C, were obtained within 12 
h after enucleation from the Alabama Eye Bank. The central 
8-mm region of the normal corneas was trephined and recov-
ered. The epithelium and the endothelium were scraped off, 
leaving the stroma to be used in these experiments. The 
procurement of human corneas in this study was approved by 
the Institutional Review Board of the University of Alabama 
at Birmingham, following the tenets of the Declaration of 
Helsinki for Research Involving Human Subjects. </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection: The stroma was incubated 
overnight in collagenase (1 mg/ml; Worthington, Lakewood, 
NJ). The resulting keratocytes were washed in Dulbecco's 
modified Eagles medium (DMEM; Invitrogen, Grand Island, 
NY) containing 1% antibiotics (penicillin-streptomycin 
solution, Mediatech, Herndon, VA). The primary cultures of 
human corneal fibroblasts were established [12], and the cells 
from passage 2 were used for this study. The cells were then 
seeded onto six-well plates (Corning, Franklin Lakes, NJ) in 
DMEM containing 10% fetal bovine serum (Hyclone, Logan, 
UT) and 1% antibiotics (penicillin-streptomycin solution) at 
37 °C in a 5% CO 2 . Four individual cell cultures were gener-
ated from four different donor corneas, and all experiments 
were performed using these cultures. </p>

<p>Gene knockdown studies: Knockdown of HuR or β-actin 
genes in normal human corneal fibroblasts was performed 
using siRNA duplexes. The siRNA transfection was done 
on fibroblasts derived from four different corneas. The cells 
were plated at 1.5×10 
5 cells per well in a six-well plate and 
grown overnight at 37 °C with 5% CO 2 . The silencer select, 
predesigned, and validated siRNA sequences were purchased 
from Ambion (Life Technologies, Invitrogen, Cambridge, 
MA). The siRNA sequences that targeted the specific coding 
regions of GAPDH (used as a positive control), β-actin, 
or HuR were used. In addition, a nonspecific, scrambled 
siRNA duplex was used as a control to examine its effect of </p>

<p>transfection, and it was denoted as siCTR. A dose-response 
curve established that the 5 nM concentration of siRNA gave 
an optimal response in transfected cells. We used a scrambled 
sequence and the GAPDH siRNA as the siRNA controls. 
The siRNA sequences were diluted in OPTI-MEM1 reduced 
medium (Invitrogen, Grand Island, NY) and transfected 
using Lipofectamine Plus (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) using 
the manufacturer's protocol. The cells were processed at 24 
h and 72 h after transfection to determine the expression of 
the targeted genes at the transcriptional and translational 
levels. The following siRNA duplex sequences were used: 
HuR (5ʹ-GCG UUU AUC CGG UUU GAC ATT UGU CAA 
ACC GGA UAA ACG CAA-3ʹ; β-actin (5ʹ-CCU GUA CAC 
UGA CUU GAG ATT UCU CAA GUC AGU GUA CAG 
GTA-3ʹ). Proteins were recovered from cultured corneal 
fibroblasts after transfection and homogenization in radio-
immunoprecipitation assay (RIPA) buffer (Thermo Scientific, 
Rockford, IL). </p>

<p>Reverse transcription-PCR and real-time PCR analysis: 
The reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR) analysis was 
performed using the Access RT-PCR system (Promega, 
Madison, WI), with 500 ng of RNA. The primers were 
designed using Primer 3 for β-actin, HuR, and GAPDH are 
as follows: β-actin forward (5′-GTT GCT ATC CAG GCT 
GTG-3′); β-actin reverse (5′-TGA TCT TGA TCT TCA TTG 
TG-3′); HuR forward (5′-ATG AAG ACC ACA TGG CCG 
AAG ACT-3′); HuR reverse (5′-AGT TCA CAA AGC CAT 
AGC CCA AGC-3′); GAPDH forward (5′-GAG TCA ACG 
GAT TTG GTC GT-3′); GAPDH reverse (5′-TTG ATT TTG 
GAG GGA TCT CG-3′). The PCR products were analyzed 
using agarose gel electrophoresis. Images were captured with 
a gel documentation system. Four fibroblast cultures from 
four different normal corneas were used for gene silencing, 
and experiments were performed in triplicate. Real-time PCR 
quantification was performed using the Bio-Rad iCycler iQ 
system (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). Real-time quantitative PCR 
(qPCR) was performed using 96-well reaction plates in a total 
volume of 25 μl. The reaction mixture included 12.5 μl of 
Real-Time SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Bio-Rad), 2.5 μl 
of reverse transcription product, 1 μl of forward and reverse 
primers, and 8 μl of DNase/RNase free water. The reaction 
mixtures were initially heated at 95 °C for 10 min to activate 
the polymerase, followed by 40 cycles, which consisted of 
the denaturation step at 95 °C for 15 s, annealing at 56 °C for 
60 s, and the elongation step at 72 °C. The data were normal-
ized to 18S RNA. The qRT-PCR data were analyzed with the 
comparative ∆Ct method. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis: Samples containing 30 μg protein 
were lysed with 1X sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) gel-loading </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>buffer and analyzed with SDS-polyacrylamide gel elec-
trophoresis (SDS-PAGE) using 12% polyacrylamide gels 
[13]. Proteins were transferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride 
membrane (Bio-Rad) by using a semidry transfer cell (Bio-
Rad, Trans-blot SD), and blocked with 3% nonfat milk in PBS 
(1X; 137 mM NaCl, 2.7 mM KCl, 10 mM Na 2 HPO 4 , 2 mM 
KH 2 PO 4 , pH 7.4) for 1 h at room temperature. The membranes 
were probed with anti-β-actin monoclonal antibody (Sigma, 
St. Louis, MO) at a 1:100 dilution, followed by incubation in 
goat anti-mouse secondary antibody conjugated to infrared 
fluorescent dye (IRD; LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE) 
at 1:10,000 dilution. Blots were scanned using the Odyssey 
Imaging system (LI-COR Biosciences). If reprobing of a 
blot was desired, the antigen-antibody complex was stripped 
using a mild stripping solution (0.2 M glycine-HCl, pH 2.2, 
0.1% SDS, 0.01% Tween-20) for 1 h at room temperature, 
followed by 3X washing with PBS-0.1% Tween-20. The 
membranes were then blocked as described and reprobed 
with anti-vimentin monoclonal antibody (Sigma) at 1:200 
dilution, followed by incubation with the secondary anti-
body as described, and scanning using the Odyssey Imaging 
system. The pixel intensity of the western blots, normalized 
to vimentin, was analyzed using <rs type="software">Image-J</rs> software [14]. The 
normalized value of siCTR was considered 100%, and the 
other values were calculated compared to the siCTR value. 
The results are shown in a bar graph with standard deviations. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence-confocal Imaging: Normal corneal 
fibroblasts were seeded on 18-mm cover-glasses for 24 h, and 
then the cells were transfected as described in the Methods 
section. After 72 h, the cells were fixed with 4% formal-
dehyde for 30 min at room temperature, and washed three 
times with PBS. The cells were permeabilized by incubation 
in 0.5% Triton X-100 in PBS for 10 min, followed by washing 
three times in PBS. The cells were then incubated with a 
blocking solution containing 10% normal serum and 0.5% 
bovine serum albumin (BSA) in PBS for 1 h, and incubated 
with the desired primary antibody at 4 °C for 24 h. Next, 
the cells were washed three times in PBS, followed by incu-
bation with a secondary antibody for 1 h in the dark. The 
cells were washed three times in PBS, and incubated with 
Hoechst nuclear stain for 10 min, washed again one time 
in PBS, and mounted on slides with a mounting medium 
(Fluromount-G, Southern Biotech, Birmingham, AL). Mouse 
immunoglobulin G (IgG) was used as a negative control with 
the identical protein concentration as that of the primary anti-
bodies. Confocal imaging was performed using a Zeiss LSM 
710 confocal microscope (Carl Zeiss Microscopy, Göttingen, 
Germany) at the High Resolution Imaging Facility of the 
University of Alabama at Birmingham. </p>

<p>Cell migration assay: A modified Boyden chamber was 
used for the cell migration assay. We used a 96-well format 
ChemoTx system (Neuro Probe, Gaithersburg, MD), and 
the experiment was performed according to the manufac-
turer's protocol. The siRNA transfection was performed 
with four different human corneal fibroblast cells. Forty-
eight hours after transfection with the siRNA duplexes, 
the corneal fibroblasts were trypsinized, resuspended in 
serum-free medium, and seeded in the upper chamber of the 
Boyden chamber. The reservoir of the chamber was filled 
with complete medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum 
(FBS), and cells were allowed to migrate to the lower surface 
through a filter for 22 h at 37 °C. The cells that remained 
in the top membrane surface were thoroughly wiped out 
using a moistened Kimwipe (Kimberly-Clark Global Sales, 
Roswell, GA). Next, the membrane was cut out and inverted 
on a slide. The cells that had migrated to the lower surface 
were stained using hematoxylin stain. The siRNA treatment 
and the cell migration assay were performed in triplicate. 
The migratory cell images were photographed using the 
Zeiss AxionPlan 2 Imaging System Microscope (Carl Zeiss 
Microscopy, Thornwood, NY) at the Core Facility of Vision 
Sciences Research Center of the University of Alabama at 
Birmingham. The cells were counted from six images, and 
the data are presented with standard deviations. </p>

<p>Wound healing assay: The cells were plated at 1.5×10 
5 cells per 
well of a 12-well plate and grown overnight at 37 °C with 5% 
CO 2 . The siRNA transfection was performed on four different 
human corneal fibroblast cells. The 80% confluent cells were 
treated with siRNA as described, and after 72 h, a straight 
line scratch was made on a confluent monolayer of cells using 
a sterile 1 ml disposable serological pipette. To remove debris 
and smooth the edge of the scratch, the cells were washed 
with 1 ml DMEM. Images of the cell proliferation were taken 
using a Nikon Eclipse TS100 microscope (NiKon Eclipse TS 
100 , Southern Micro Instruments, Marietta GA) at 0 h and 24 
h after the scratch with a Nikon Coolpix camera attached to 
the microscope. The siRNA treatment and the scratch assay 
were performed in triplicate. The cells were counted manu-
ally at 0 h and after 24 h post-scratch from six images, and 
the data are presented with standard deviations. To observe 
the effects of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) inhibition, 
the cells were treated with 10 µM LY 292,004 (Sigma) for 24 
h after wounding. A p value of &lt;0.05 was judged (±standard 
error of the mean [SEM]) to be statistically significant as 
determined by the Student t test. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Human antigen R knockdown leads to a decrease in β-actin 
expression in stromal fibroblasts at transcriptional and trans-
lational levels: Our previous results showed downregulation 
in the expression of β-actin and HuR genes in keratoconus 
corneal stroma relative to normal corneas [12]. In the present 
study, we used RNAi-mediated gene silencing for β-actin 
or HuR in normal corneal fibroblasts to understand the 
respective gene functions. The GAPDH gene and scrambled 
sequence (which do not affect any targeted genes) were used 
as positive and negative controls for transfection, respectively. 
The sequences of the siRNA duplex were selected from the 
coding region of the desired target mRNAs, and the transfec-
tion was performed as described in the Methods section. The 
desired mRNA levels were analyzed using RT-PCR at 24 h 
post-transfection. Figure 1A(I) shows β-actin gene expression 
using β-actin primers after transfection of human corneal 
fibroblasts with the scrambled siRNA, siGAPDH, siβ-actin, 
or siHuR. Expression of the β-actin gene was downregulated 
after the HuR gene was silenced, which suggested that HuR 
has a regulatory role in β-actin gene expression. Addition-
ally, β-actin gene silencing also showed downregulation 
of the β-actin gene, which was used as the control. Figure 
1A(II) shows HuR gene expression using HuR primers after 
transfection of human corneal fibroblasts with siRNA for 
scrambled, GAPDH, β-actin, or HuR. Expression of the HuR 
gene was downregulated on HuR gene silencing, whereas 
β-actin gene silencing had no effect on HuR expression. 
Figure 1B shows western blot analysis of β-actin expression 
after transfection with the siRNA of scrambled, GAPDH, 
β-actin, and HuR. The western blot results show the reduced 
expression of β-actin and HuR relative to vimentin (used as 
the control). For visualization of vimentin with anti-vimentin 
antibody, the blot that was used for β-actin visualization was 
stripped and used again for the vimentin visualization. RT-
PCR analysis showed that after 24 h, GAPDH gene silencing 
had no effect, and the expression remained at the same level 
(data not shown), which was confirmed with the western blot 
analysis. Figure 1C shows the percentage of β-actin expres-
sion levels after they normalized to vimentin and calculated 
as described in the Methods section. Relative to the expres-
sion of vimentin, the levels of β-actin expression were 24% 
and 18% lower after HuR and β-actin gene silencing, respec-
tively. This suggests that the loss of HuR results in down-
regulation of the β-actin gene. There was no change in the 
β-actin expression levels after the GAPDH gene or negative 
control (siCTR) was silenced. Figure 1D shows the real-time 
PCR analysis after 72 h of siRNA treatments for the siCTR, 
GAPDH, HuR, and β-actin genes. The y-axis in the figure 
shows the relative fold expression, and the x-axis shows the </p>

<p>β-actin primer used for the real-time PCR analysis. β-actin 
gene expression decreased by 80-90% after the β-actin and 
HuR genes were silenced, which was similar to the RT-PCR 
analysis. Whereas GAPDH gene silencing suppressed β-actin 
gene expression after 72 h of gene silencing (Figure 1D). </p>

<p>Localization of proteins after downregulation of their genes 
using immunohistochemical-confocal imaging: To further 
verify the western blot results, we used confocal imaging 
to localize the individual proteins after siRNA treatment. 
We analyzed whether β-actin gene silencing affected HuR 
expression in corneal fibroblasts (Figure 2). Figure 2 shows 
the immunoreactivity to the anti-HuR antibody of the corneal 
fibroblasts transfected with GAPDH siRNA, HuR siRNA, 
or β-actin siRNA. The effect on HuR gene expression was 
analyzed after the GAPDH gene was silenced. Figure 2A,D,G 
show Hoechst nuclear staining (blue fluorescent staining), 
and Figure 2B,E,H shows the immunoreactivity to the anti-
HuR antibody. Green fluorescent staining in the nuclear 
region (punctate in appearance) was observed on immunore-
activity with the anti-HuR antibody in the cells treated with 
siGAPDH (Figure 2B), and with β-actin siRNA (Figure 2E). 
Figure 2C,F,I is an overlay of Figure 2A,B,D,E,G,H. GAPDH 
gene silencing had no effect on HuR gene expression. β-actin 
gene silencing had no effect on the expression of HuR as 
represented by the presence of green fluorescent staining in 
the nuclear region (Figure 2E). The effect of β-actin gene 
silencing on HuR expression was in concordance with our 
previously described RT-PCR and western blot results. In 
contrast, HuR gene silencing resulted in the loss of HuR 
expression, which representing a loss of green punctate fluo-
rescent staining (Figure 2H). Together, the results show that 
HuR expression was downregulated in corneal fibroblasts 
after transfection with HuR siRNA (Figure 2H), whereas 
β-actin and GAPDH gene silencing had no effect on HuR 
expression (Figure 2B,E). </p>

<p>Next, we analyzed whether HuR gene silencing affects 
β-actin gene expression (Figure 3). Figure 3 shows the 
immunoreactivity of corneal fibroblasts to the anti-β-actin 
antibody following transfection with GAPDH siRNA, HuR 
siRNA, or β-actin siRNA. F-actin was visualized by using 
rhodamine-labeled phalloidin (toxin from the mushroom 
Amanita phalloides). Figure 3A,E,I,M shows the Hoechst 
nuclear blue stain, and Figure 3B,F,J,N shows the immunore-
activity to the anti-β-actin antibody of the corneal fibroblasts 
after transfection with scrambled siRNA, siGAPDH, siHuR, 
or siβ-actin, respectively. The scrambled siRNA treatment 
showed no effect on β-actin expression as seen by the pres-
ence of uniform green fluorescent stain in cells with the 
anti-β-actin antibody (Figure 3B). Figure 3C,G,K,O shows </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>Figure 1. Gene expression analysis 
after gene silencing. A: Detection 
of the expression of glyceralde-
hyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase 
(GAPDH ), β-actin, and human 
antigen R (HuR) genes after gene 
silencing using RT-PCR. In the 
analyses, cells were examined 
24 h after the treatments. In (A), 
(I): RT-PCR analysis of β-actin 
gene expression in corneal fibro-
blasts after gene silencing using 
siScrambled, siGAPDH, siβ-actin, 
or small interfering human antigen 
R (siHuR). (II): RT-PCR analysis 
of HuR gene expression in corneal 
fibroblasts after gene silencing 
using siScrambled, siGAPDH, 
siβ-actin, or siHuR. B: Western 
blot analysis of β-actin expression 
using the anti-β-actin antibody 
in corneal fibroblasts after gene 
silencing using siScrambled, 
siGAPDH, siβ-actin or siHuR. 
Vimentin expression was used as 
a control. β-Actin expression was 
downregulated on either β-actin 
gene silencing or that of HuR gene. 
C: A bar graph shows the percent 
of β-actin levels after the gene 
silencing. D: Real-time PCR anal-
ysis of the β-actin gene after the 
following treatments: siScrambled 
(siCTR), siGAPDH, siβ-actin, and 
siHuR. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>F-actin staining with rhodamine-labeled phalloidin (red 
fluorescence), following transfection with scrambled siRNA, 
siGAPDH, siHuR, or siβ-actin, respectively. Figure 3D,H,L,P 
shows an overlay of Hoechst nuclear stain, immune-stain with 
anti-β-actin antibody, and F-actin staining after transfection. 
Together, the results show that scrambled siRNA treatment 
had no effect on β-actin gene expression. </p>

<p>On examination of the effects of GAPDH knockdown on 
β-actin expression (Figure 3E-H), decreased levels of green 
fluorescence (due to β-actin [Figure 3F]) and red fluores-
cence (due to F-actin [Figure 3G]) were observed. Together, 
the results showed that β-actin expression affected GAPDH 
gene silencing (Figures 3F,G), whereas it remained unaffected 
with the use of scrambled siRNA. We analyzed the effect of 
HuR gene silencing on β-actin gene expression (Figure 3I-K), 
which showed an absence of green fluorescence (due to 
β-actin, Figure 3J) and decreased red fluorescence (staining 
F-actin; Figure 3K). β-actin gene knockdown was used as 
a positive control to examine the effects of gene silencing. 
Similarly, β-actin gene knockdown (Figure 3M-P) resulted in 
an absence of green fluorescence (due to β-actin, Figure 3N) 
and decreased red fluorescence of F-actin (staining F-actin, </p>

<p>Figure 3O). Together, the results suggested that the silencing 
of HuR or β-actin gene (Figure 3J,N) resulted in downregula-
tion of the β-actin gene, as observed earlier during western 
blot analysis (Figure 1B). Further, the HuR gene seems to 
be a stability factor for β-actin mRNA, and plays a role in 
gene expression. In contrast, the β-actin gene had no effect 
on HuR gene expression. However, the downregulation of the 
β-actin gene after gene silencing of GAPDH (Figure 3F) was 
a surprise to us, and has been shown for the first time. </p>

<p>Effects of gene silencing on migration of normal corneal 
fibroblasts: Next we analyzed the functional significance of 
the loss of the HuR gene and whether it leads to a loss in the 
cytoskeletal function such as corneal fibroblast migration. 
Cell migration is an important biologic process mainly gener-
ated by the β-actin cytoskeleton [3]. The modified Boyden 
chamber assay was used to determine if targeted deletion of 
the HuR or β-actin gene affected migration of normal corneal 
fibroblasts. Figure 4A shows the migrated cells (pointed 
arrows denote the cells) in the corneal fibroblasts, and Figure 
4B,C,D,E shows cell migration following silencing of scram-
bled siRNA, and siRNA of the GAPDH gene, HuR gene, or 
β-actin gene, respectively. Cells migrated per image (Figure </p>

<p>Figure 2. Localization of human 
antigen R after gene silencing. 
The normal corneal fibroblasts 
were treated with GAPDH siRNA, 
β-actin siRNA, or human antigen 
R (HuR) siRNA. The immunore-
activity of HuR was analyzed at 72 
h post-transfection. A: Fibroblasts 
stained with Hoechst nuclear stain 
after a treatment with GAPDH 
siRNA. B: Immunoreactivity of 
fibroblasts with anti-HuR antibody 
after a treatment with GAPDH 
siRNA. C: Overlay of (A) and (B). 
D: Fibroblasts stained with Hoechst 
nuclear stain after a treatment with 
β-actin siRNA. E: Immunoreac-
tivity of fibroblasts with anti-HuR 
antibody after a treatment with 
β-actin siRNA. F: Overlay of (D) 
and (E). G: Fibroblasts stained 
with Hoechst nuclear stain after 
treatment with HuR siRNA. B: 
Immunoreactivity of fibroblasts 
with anti-HuR antibody after treatment with HuR siRNA. C: Overlay of (G) and (H). Note that the GAPDH siRNA and β-actin siRNA 
treatments had no effect on HuR expression and its nuclear localization. HuR gene silencing significantly reduced the expression of HuR, 
as shown by the absence of green fluorescence in nuclei. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>Figure 3. Localization of β-actin 
in corneal fibroblasts after gene 
silencing. The normal corneal fibro-
blasts were treated with scrambled 
siRNA, GAPDH siRNA, β-actin 
siRNA, or human antigen R (HuR) 
siRNA. The immunoreactivity of 
anti-β-actin antibody was analyzed 
at 72 h after transfection. A: Fibro-
blasts stained with Hoechst nuclear 
stain after treatment with scrambled 
siRNA. B: Immunoreactivity of 
fibroblasts with anti-β-actin anti-
body after treatment with scram-
bled siRNA. C: Fibroblasts stained 
with rhodamine-labeled phalloidin 
stain after treatment with scram-
bled siRNA. D: Overlay of (A), 
(B), and (C). E: Fibroblasts stained 
with Hoechst nuclear stain after 
treatment with GAPDH siRNA. 
F: Immunoreactivity of fibroblasts 
with anti-β-actin antibody after 
treatment with GAPDH siRNA. 
G: Fibroblasts stained with rhoda-
mine-labeled phalloidin stain after 
treatment with GAPDH siRNA. 
H: Overlay of (E), (F), and (G). I: 
Fibroblasts stained with Hoechst 
nuclear stain after treatment with 
HuR siRNA. J: Immunoreactivity 
of fibroblasts with anti-β-actin 
antibody after treatment with HuR 
siRNA. K: Fibroblasts stained with 
rhodamine-labeled phalloidin stain 
after treatment with HuR siRNA. 
L: Overlay of (I), (J), and (K). M: 
Fibroblasts stained with Hoechst 
nuclear stain after treatment with 
β-actin siRNA. N: Immunore-
activity of fibroblasts with anti-
β-actin antibody after treatment 
with β-actin siRNA. O: Fibroblasts 
stained with rhodamine-labeled 
phalloidin stain after treatment with β-actin siRNA, and (P): Overlay of (M), (N), and (O). Note that β-actin and HuR gene silencing affected 
β-actin expression. Scrambled siRNA transfection of normal corneal fibroblasts showed no effect on β-actin expression, whereas GAPDH 
siRNA treatment had a drastic effect on β-actin expression. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>4F) were counted using Image-J software, incorporating 
multiple images and standard deviation analysis. Together, 
the results show that scrambled siRNA treatment had no 
effect on cell migration, which was identical to that of normal 
cell migration (Figure 4A,B). GAPDH gene silencing resulted 
in reduced cell migration compared to the scrambled siRNA. 
Silencing the HuR gene significantly decreased cell migra-
tion, whereas β-actin gene silencing abolished the migration. 
Although it is known that β-actin is an essential component of 
cell migration [15], the role of HuR in cell migration is shown 
for the first time in this report. </p>

<p>Effects of gene silencing on wound healing: Next we analyzed 
whether HuR gene silencing affects the migration and prolif-
eration of corneal fibroblasts. A normal corneal fibroblast 
cell layer, grown to 85% confluency, was transfected with 
scrambled siRNA and siRNA of GAPDH, β-actin, or HuR, 
and the non-transfected cells were used as a control. A scratch 
wound was created at 72 h after transfection, and the dotted 
line in Figure 5 shows the wounded area. The images were 
taken at 0 h and 24 h post-scratch using a phase contrast 
microscope with a Nikon camera (Figure 5). The cells that 
migrated to the region between the dotted lines (wound) were 
counted from multiple images and the standard deviation 
determined (Figure 5K). Figure 5A,B shows the extent of the 
migration of the corneal fibroblasts at 0 h and 24 h post-
scratch, respectively. Figure 5C-J shows the cell migration at </p>

<p>0 h and 24 h post-scratch following treatment with scrambled 
siRNA, GAPDH siRNA, HuR siRNA, or β-actin siRNA, 
respectively. The untreated normal corneal fibroblast layer 
had almost 100% wound closure in the region between the 
dotted lines (Figure 5B) with similar results observed with 
scrambled siRNA (Figure 5D). GAPDH siRNA treatment 
showed cell migration decreased after 24 h (Figure 5F), but 
greater decreased migration was seen in the cells treated 
with HuR siRNA (Figure 5H) or with β-actin siRNA (Figure 
5J). Together, the results showed that the wound healing 
process was decreased after GAPDH gene silencing but a 
relatively greater decrease occurred with HuR and β-actin 
gene silencing. Figure 5K summarizes cell migration at 24 
h after wound healing subjected to different siRNA treat-
ments. Similarly, GAPDH siRNA treatment also resulted in 
decreased cell migration, GAPDH, an enzyme in the glyco-
lytic pathway shown to have multiple functions, including an 
effect on cell motility during wound healing [16]. </p>

<p>PI3K, is a known regulator of various cellular processes, 
including cell adhesion, vesicular trafficking, protein 
synthesis, cell growth, differentiation, cell survival, and cell 
transformation [17]. We performed a wound healing assay 
with Ly292004, a PI3K inhibitor, to examine how the inhibi-
tion of PI3K affects fibroblasts migration (Figure 6). Figure 
6A,B,D,E,G,H shows cell migration at 0 h and 24 h post-
scratch following treatment with scrambled siRNA, β-actin </p>

<p>Figure 4. Analysis of cell migration 
after gene silencing (n = 4), using 
a modified Boyden chamber. Cell 
migration is shown with arrows. A: 
Migration of normal corneal fibro-
blast. B: Migration of cells after 
treatment with scrambled siRNA. 
C: Migration of cells after treatment 
of corneal fibroblast with GAPDH 
siRNA. D: Migration of cells after 
treatment of normal corneal fibro-
blast with human antigen R (HuR) 
siRNA. E: Migration of cells after 
treatment of normal corneal fibro-
blast with β-actin siRNA. F: Bar 
graph showing cell migration after 
different treatments (A to E). Cells 
were counted from six different 
frames. All the treatments were 
performed in tetraplicate, and stan-
dard deviations were calculated. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>Figure 5. Effect of wound healing 
after gene silencing (n = 4). A 
scratch wound was created using 
1 ml sterile serological pipette in a 
confluent corneal fibroblast culture 
after gene silencing of GAPDH, 
β-actin, or human antigen R 
(HuR). The images were taken at 0 
h and 24 h. The dotted lines show 
the area where the scratch wound 
was created. A: Normal cells with 
a scratch wound at 0 h. B: Cells 
migrating to the site of wound 
after 24 h. C: Scratch wound at 0 
h in cells that were treated with 
scrambled siRNA. D: Migra-
tion of cells to the site of wound 
after 24 h in cell culture that was 
treated with scrambled siRNA. 
E: Scratch wound at 0 h in cells 
that were treated with GAPDH 
siRNA. F: Migration of cells to the 
site of wound after 24 h that were 
treated with scrambled siRNA. G: 
Scratch wound at 0 h in cells that 
were treated with HuR siRNA. H: 
Migration of cells to the site of 
wound after 24 h that were treated 
with HuR siRNA. I: Scratch wound 
at 0 h in cells that were treated with 
β-actin siRNA. J: Cells migrated 
to the site of wound after 24 h in 
cells that were treated with β-actin 
siRNA. K: A bar graph showing the 
number of cells that migrated after 
24 h following the scratch wound 
in cells treated with siScrambled, 
siGAPDH, siHuR, or siβ-actin. The 
scratch wound assay was performed 
in tetraplicate, and standard devia-
tions were calculated. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>siRNA, or HuR siRNA, respectively. Similarly, Figure 6C,F,I 
shows the results of PI3K inhibition using LY292004 after 
24 h. After 24 h post-scratch, the untreated cells migrated to 
the wound (Figure 6B) where on PI3K inhibition, severely 
impaired wound healing occurred (Figure 6C). β-Actin and 
HuR gene silencing resulted in inhibition of wound healing 
after 24 h post-scratch as seen in Figure 6E,H, respectively. 
The inhibition of PI3K and gene silencing had the same 
effects as that of gene silencing alone (Figure 6F,I). Figure 
6J shows the downstream pathway of PI3K, and its inhibition </p>

<p>would have a similar effect as that of β-actin and HuR gene 
silencing. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our previous report showed that the expression levels of 
β-actin and HuR were downregulated in the human kerato-
conic corneal stroma but not in the normal corneal stroma 
[12]. In the present study, we used gene silencing to deter-
mine the functional properties of β-actin, and whether HuR 
gene silencing affects β-actin gene expression in cultured </p>

<p>Figure 6. Effect of phosphatidylino-
sitol 3-kinase inhibitor on wound 
healing after gene silencing (n = 
4). The scratch wound was created 
using 1 ml sterile serological 
pipette in a confluent corneal fibro-
blast culture after gene silencing 
of β-actin or human antigen R 
(HuR). The images were taken at 
0 h and 24 h. The lines show the 
area where the scratch wound 
was created. A: Scratch wound at 
0 h in cells that were treated with 
scrambled siRNA. B: Migration of 
cells to the site of the wound after 
24 h in cells that was treated with 
scrambled siRNA. C: Migration of 
cells to the site of the wound after 
24 h in cells that were treated with 
scrambled siRNA + phosphati-
dylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) inhib-
itor Ly292004. D: A scratch wound 
at 0 h in cells that were treated with 
β-actin siRNA. E: Migration of 
cells to the site of the wound after 
24 h that were treated with β-actin 
siRNA. F: Migration of cells to the 
site of wound after 24 h in cells that 
was treated with β-actin siRNA 
+PI3 kinase inhibitor Ly292004. 
G: A scratch wound at 0 h in cells 
that were treated with HuR siRNA. 
H: Migration of cells to the site of 
the wound after 24 h in cells that 
were treated with HuR siRNA. 
I: Migration of cells to the site of 
the wound after 24 h in cells that 
was treated with HuR siRNA +PI3 
kinase inhibitor Ly292004. The scratch wound assay was performed in tetraplicate. J: A schematic representation of PI3K-induced actin 
filament remodeling and migration. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>fibroblasts derived from the keratocytes of normal human 
corneas. Gene silencing using RNA interference has been 
a popular method for in vitro gene functional studies using 
a method in which introducing dsRNA, homologous in 
sequence to the silenced gene, results in post-transcriptional 
gene silencing [18]. </p>

<p>Our RT-PCR analysis showed that gene silencing of 
β-actin or HuR for 24 h resulted in downregulation of β-actin 
gene expression. The silencing of the HuR gene also resulted 
in downregulation of β-actin gene expression. The levels 
of β-actin and HuR gene expression were reduced by 72% 
and 64% after β-actin and HuR gene silencing, respectively. 
The mRNA of HuR is ubiquitously expressed in all prolifer-
ating cells, and it is the most important post-transcriptional 
regulator of gene expression [9]. HuR binding to the U-rich 
element is involved in mRNA stability [5,11], and prolongs the 
half-life of β-actin mRNA [10]. Together, our present study 
showed that silencing the HuR gene resulted in downregula-
tion of β-actin at the transcriptional and translational levels 
in corneal fibroblasts. This downregulation could be due to 
the loss of HuR, a stability factor for β-actin mRNA. These 
expression levels were downregulated for up to 96 h post-
siRNA treatment (results not shown). </p>

<p>In the present study, the immunohistochemical-
confocal imaging technique was used to localize proteins 
that were affected by gene silencing. When the HuR gene 
was silenced, its expression was decreased, but its expres-
sion was not affected after the GAPDH gene, the β-actin 
gene, or scrambled siRNA (data not shown) was silenced. 
Gene silencing of either the HuR-or β-actin gene resulted 
in decreased expression of the β-actin gene. Therefore, the 
HuR gene has a regulatory role in β-actin expression, which 
was confirmed at translational levels with confocal imaging. 
Surprisingly, β-actin gene expression was also decreased 
after the GAPDH gene was silenced (Figure 3F). This could 
be due to diverse functions of GAPDH, such as DNA repair 
[19], tRNA export [20], and in cell death [21,22]. GAPDH is 
also known to interact with tubulin and actin and thus plays 
a role in cytoskeleton dynamics [23]. </p>

<p>Actin isoforms have highly conserved amino acid 
sequences. Gama-actin expression was not affected when 
the β-actin gene was silenced in normal corneal fibroblasts 
(data not shown). Cell culture studies have shown that β-and 
γ-actins have distinct physiologic roles. In the motile cells, 
β-actin accumulates at the leading edge, and γ-actin tends 
to be at the stress fibers [24]. Complementing this was the 
finding that the β-actin mRNA was located at the leading 
edge of the moving fibroblast whereas γ-actin was local-
ized at the stress fibers [25]. Recent studies using knockout </p>

<p>mouse models have also shown that β-actin and γ-actins show 
distinct phenotypes. This is further supported by the fact 
that in a β-actin knockout mouse, the embryonic fibroblasts 
showed a decreased G-actin pool compared to F-actin [15]. 
Our results also showed positive F-actin staining in fibro-
blasts that showed the absence of β-actin staining in normal 
fibroblasts following β-actin gene silencing. The presence of 
F-actin staining could be due to the presence of γ-actin in 
these cells. This could also be due to the absence of the mono-
meric G-actin pool, which could lead to increased expres-
sion of megakaryoblastic leukemia (MAL also known as 
MKL) gene ID 89880, OMIM 60607; serum response factor 
(SRF) gene ID 6722 , OMIM 600589 (MAL-SRF) target 
genes. Monomeric actins are known to inhibit coactivator 
MAL-SRF [26] and α-smooth muscle actin. </p>

<p>One of the major functions of β-actin, but not that of 
γ-actin, is in cell motility [27]. Overexpression of the β-actin 
gene results in plasma membrane protrusions and cell migra-
tion [28]. Our cell motility analysis using Boyden chambers 
showed that gene silencing of β-actin drastically reduced the 
cell migration (Figure 4E). Cell migration was also decreased 
when HuR was downregulated (Figure 4D) but was unaf-
fected in untreated cells or those treated with scrambled 
siRNA. Cell motility is an important feature of multicellular 
organisms, maintained by actin-based protrusions such as 
lamellipodia, ruffles, and filopodia [29]. We observed for 
the first time that GAPDH gene silencing also affected cell 
migration, possibly by way of its known function as an actin-
binding protein. It has been recently reported that glycolytic 
enzymes, which included GAPDH, are associated with actin 
and other membrane proteins [30]. This association might 
satisfy the high ATP energy demand during actin dynamics. </p>

<p>Keratocytes repopulate the stroma at the site of an injury 
by a combination of proliferation and migration, which is 
stimulated by cytokines released from the epithelium [31]. 
This leads to a series of events that causes the keratocyte 
transformation to fibroblasts and myofibroblasts, and irreg-
ular spacing of collagen fibrils [32]. Silencing of the β-actin 
and HuR genes resulted in a significant decrease in wound 
healing as evidenced by the decrease in the cell migration in a 
scratch-wound gap in a confluent cell layer (Figure 5H,J). In 
contrast, complete wound healing occurred in normal corneal 
fibroblasts, and those treated with scrambled siRNA, whereas 
GAPDH siRNA also showed decreased cell migration. 
Together, the results suggest the importance of β-actin and 
HuR in cell motility during wound healing. The unexpected 
role of GAPDH in cell migration and proliferation requires 
further study. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>The actin cytoskeleton is indispensable for wound 
repair, and PI3K is one of the key enzymes involved in this 
process [33]. Small G-protein, Rac1, which is an effector 
of PI3K, mediates stress-activated kinase c-Jun N-terminal 
kinases (JNKs), and is essential for basic fibroblastic growth 
factor ( bFGF)-induced fibroblast migration [33]. A specific 
inhibitor of PI3K, LY292004, causes significant inhibition 
of cell growth and migration. Our results also show inhibi-
tion of PI3K by LY292004 significantly inhibited cell growth 
and migration in siCTR cells (Figure 6J). This was similar 
to cells that had undergone β-actin or HuR gene silencing. 
The absence of β-actin monomers (an effect of β-actin gene 
knockdown) hinders actin cytoskeleton polymerization and 
thus affects cell migration and proliferation. This result 
was similar to that of inhibition of PI3K (Figure 6J) and an 
upstream element in the pathway (Figure 6J). </p>

<p>In summary, our findings show that downregulation of 
the HuR gene significantly reduces β-actin gene expression, 
and affects the migration and proliferation of corneal fibro-
blasts. These results also confirm our earlier findings that 
downregulation of the β-actin gene in keratoconus corneal 
stromal keratocytes is due to downregulation of the HuR 
gene. Our future work will explore the significance of down-
regulation of the β-actin and HuR genes in the progression of 
keratoconus disease. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank the Alabama Eye Bank for providing 
normal corneas for the study. The study was partly supported 
by a NIH grant NEI P30EYE3039. </p>



<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:593-605 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/593&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>





</text></tei>