<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4767401" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: Nonketotic hyperglycinemia is a neurometabolic disorder characterized by intellectual disability, seizures, 
and spasticity. Patients with attenuated nonketotic hyperglycinemia make variable developmental progress. Predic-
tive factors have not been systematically assessed. 
Methods: We reviewed 124 patients stratified by developmental outcome for biochemical and molecular predictive 
factors. Missense mutations were expressed to quantify residual activity using a new assay. 
Results: Patients with severe nonketotic hyperglycinemia required multiple anticonvulsants, whereas patients with 
developmental quotient (DQ) &gt; 30 did not require anticonvulsants. Brain malformations occurred mainly in patients 
with severe nonketotic hyperglycinemia (71%) but rarely in patients with attenuated nonketotic hyperglycinemia 
(7.5%). Neonatal presentation did not correlate with outcome, but age at onset 4 months was associated with 
attenuated nonketotic hyperglycinemia. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) glycine levels and CSF:plasma glycine ratio corre-
lated inversely with DQ; CSF glycine &gt; 230 lM indicated severe outcome and CSF:plasma glycine ratio 0.08 pre-
dicted attenuated outcome. The glycine index correlated strongly with outcome. Molecular analysis identified 99% of 
mutant alleles, including 96 novel mutations. Mutations near the active cleft of the P-protein maintained stable pro-
tein levels. Presence of 1 mutation with residual activity was necessary but not sufficient for attenuated outcome; 2 
such mutations conferred best outcome. Divergent outcomes for the same genotype indicate a contribution of other 
genetic or nongenetic factors. 
Interpretation: Accurate prediction of outcome is possible in most patients. A combination of 4 factors available 
neonatally predicted 78% of severe and 49% of attenuated patients, and a score based on mutation severity pre-
dicted outcome with 70% sensitivity and 97% specificity. </p>

<p>of intellectual disability and seizures, hyperactivity, cho-
rea, and intermittent episodes of lethargy and 
ataxia. 
2,3,7,8 Up to 15% of neonatally presenting patients </p>

<p>and 50% of infancy-presenting patients show this attenu-
ated phenotype, 
2,3 but elements predicting the neurode-</p>

<p>velopmental outcome in NKH have not been 
systematically studied. 
The glycine cleavage enzyme complex is composed 
of 4 proteins. The P-protein, encoded by the GLDC gene, 
is a pyridoxal phosphate-dependent glycine decarboxylase; 
the H-protein, encoded by the GCSH gene, is a lipoic 
acid containing hydrogen-carrier protein; the T-protein, 
encoded by the AMT gene, is a tetrahydrofolate-
dependent protein; and the L-protein is a lipoamide dehy-
drogenase. Patients with classic NKH have mutations in 
GLDC or AMT, including exonic deletions in GLDC. </p>

<p>9-11   The glycine cleavage enzyme is expressed in liver, brain, 
and placenta, and at low levels in Epstein-Barr virus 
(EBV)-transformed lymphoblasts. </p>

<p>12   Deficient enzyme 
activity causes elevated glycine levels in plasma and cere-
brospinal fluid (CSF) with an elevated CSF:plasma glycine 
ratio. 
13 Lower CSF glycine levels and a lower ratio were </p>

<p>reported for some patients with attenuated NKH. </p>

<p>7,14   Treatment most commonly involves sodium benzoate 
given to lower plasma glycine levels, and dextromethor-
phan or ketamine with the intent to reduce the excessive 
stimulating activity of glycine on N-methyl-D-aspartate 
receptors, with unclear effect on outcome. 
Predicting the prognosis of patients with NKH is 
important for families to make decisions on treatment 
following diagnosis, particularly in the neonatal intensive 
care setting, where withdrawal of life-sustaining therapy 
may be considered. 
15 Differences in treatment response </p>

<p>may exist between outcome categories, requiring early 
identification for appropriate treatment. In this study, we 
reviewed the outcome of patients with NKH in relation 
to biochemical, enzymatic, and molecular markers in 
addition to basic clinical and radiological findings. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods </p>

<p>Clinical Studies </p>

<p>The primary study was approved by the ethics committees of 
the Colorado Multiple Institutional Review Board and Catholic 
University Leuven, and written informed consent was obtained 
from all study subjects. A second limited exempt chart review 
study was approved by the Colorado Multiple Institutional 
Review Board. Some clinical details of 12 patients were previ-
ously described. 
2,5,16-18 All patients had classic NKH evidenced </p>

<p>by elevated CSF glycine levels, elevated CSF:plasma glycine 
ratio, normal urine organic acids, and mutations in either 
GLDC or AMT excluding variant NKH. 
19,20 Medical records </p>

<p>were abstracted through a questionnaire with data listed in the </p>

<p>Supplementary Table, and a clinical investigator (J.L.K.V.H. or 
J.B.H.) examined the vast majority of patients. Age at symptom 
onset was considered neonatal if symptoms occurred in the first 
week of life, with later onset specified. Glycine levels were 
recorded at diagnosis, excluding blood contaminated CSF sam-
ples. 
20 Brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) reports were </p>

<p>reviewed for structural abnormalities. Because in NKH seizure 
propensity increases during the first year of life and improves 
on benzoate treatment, therapy resistance of the seizure disorder 
was estimated from the number of concurrent antiepileptic 
drugs (AEDs) used after age 1 year and while on benzoate ther-
apy. 
2 The glycine index was calculated by subtracting the molar </p>

<p>glycine intake in food from a dietary recall from the molar dose 
of sodium benzoate needed to normalize plasma glycine levels 
divided by body weight, which reflects a whole body balance of 
glycine metabolism. 
18 Enzyme assay results were recorded. Neu-</p>

<p>rodevelopmental outcome was systematically assessed. Patients 
whose sole developmental milestone consisted of the ability to 
smile were given a developmental age of 6 weeks and catego-
rized as severe NKH. Those making developmental progress 
beyond this stage were categorized as attenuated NKH, and for-
mal developmental testing at an age &gt; 2 years was used to 
derive a developmental quotient (DQ). Typical measures used 
were Bayley Scales of Infant Development, Mullen Scales of 
Early Learning, or Wechsler Scale of Intelligence. For each 
child, a DQ was calculated. The DQ is a measure of the rate 
of development. By using the mean or median age at which a 
milestone presents, a functional age equivalent for a child's 
development is given. It is the ratio of development age to 
chronological age. Subjects were subcategorized as poor attenu-
ated NKH if DQ &lt; 20, as intermediate attenuated NKH if 
DQ 20 and &lt; 50, and as mild attenuated NKH if DQ 50. 
Patients without formal developmental assessment were catego-
rized as attenuated NKH, not otherwise specified, if they could 
grasp and sit or walk independently, and as severe NKH if they 
could only smile. </p>

<p>Molecular Studies </p>

<p>Exons and at least 50 nucleotides into the flanking intron 
sequences of AMT (GenBank NM_000481.2, NP_000472.2; 
Ensembl ENSG00000145020) and GLDC (GenBank 
NM_000170.2, NP_000161.2; Ensembl ENSG00000178445) 
were sequenced. Phase was established from parental samples. 
Deletions and duplications in GLDC were analyzed by either 
multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification, 
10 or by a tar-</p>

<p>geted array-based comparative genomic hybridization utilizing a 
customized 60k oligonucleotide microarray with a positive 
threshold of 3 consecutive probes allowing the detection of 
300bp deletions, and verified by dual real-time polymerase 
chain reaction (PCR) with Taqman probes. Sequence variants 
were compared with 6 other species, and conservation was 
recorded. Splice site mutations were analyzed in silico using the 
<rs type="software">BDGP Splice Site Prediction</rs> by Neural Network program, </p>

<p>21   and for select patients by analysis of mRNA in EBV trans-
formed lymphoblasts. To evaluate the effect on splicing of a 
deep intronic mutation in AMT (Patient 75), the generated </p>

<p>Swanson et al: Nonketotic Hyperglycinemia </p>

<p>October 2015 
607 </p>

<p>cDNA was sequenced in 2 overlapping fragments. To evaluate 
whether the maternal mutation c.2203-2A&gt;G; IVS18-2A&gt;G 
(Patient 310) created a leaky splicing error, we evaluated for the 
presence of normally spliced mRNA not containing the paternal 
mutation c.547delG in the mRNA of the patient and mother 
by digestion of the cDNA with NcoI followed by agarose elec-
trophoresis, where the paternal mutation abolishes a restriction 
site. </p>

<p>Protein Expression and Modeling Studies </p>

<p>The impact of each mutation on residual enzyme activity was 
systematically evaluated. Exonic deletions, nonsense mutations, 
and frameshift mutations were categorized as having no residual 
activity, except for a frameshift mutation that affected the final 
20 amino acids. Splice site mutations affecting the 2 conserved 
donor or acceptor nucleotides and predicted in silico as likely 
affecting splicing were considered to leave no residual activity. 
For missense mutations in GLDC, the impact on residual 
P-protein activity was assessed by expression in vitro in COS 
cells and measuring the residual enzyme activity on a glycine 
exchange assay modified by the use of purified human recombi-
nant lipoylated H-protein. 
22 Missense mutations were intro-</p>

<p>duced by site-directed mutagenesis into a full-length GLDC 
cDNA in the pCMV6-Entry vector (RC211292; Origine, 
Rockville, MD), and with mock and wild-type GLDC included 
in each experiment, were transfected into COS7 cells using Lip-
ofectamine 2000 (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA). Cells were 
harvested after 48 hours, and P-protein activity was measured 
by the glycine exchange assay containing excess lipoylated, 
recombinant human H-protein. 
22 Activities were normalized by </p>

<p>protein concentration measured by the Bradford method 
23 and </p>

<p>mutant enzyme activity expressed as percentage of concurrent 
wild-type enzyme activity determined in the same experiment. 
Transfection efficiency was monitored by quantitative PCR for 
GLDC cDNA content. To generate recombinant, lipoylated 
human H-protein, GCSH cDNA PCR amplified from a human 
liver cDNA library was cloned as a thioredoxin fusion protein 
into the pBAD-DEST 49 vector (Life Technologies), expressed 
in bacteria, and purified from the cell lysate by boiling for 1 
minute followed by chromatography on a diethylaminoethyl 
cellulose column. Lipoate-protein ligase (LplA) from Escherichia 
coli was expressed, purified, and used to lipoylate purified 
human H-protein as described using a molar ratio of 0.5:1.0 
LplA:H-protein. 
24 Lipoylation was confirmed by Western blot-</p>

<p>ting (ab97625; Abcam, Cambridge, MA) and by mass spec-
trometry. The N-terminal thioredoxin tag was removed from 
the lipoylated H-protein by enterokinase digestion (New Eng-
land Biolabs, Ipswich, MA), and reaction products were sepa-
rated using a Q Sepharose Fast Flow (GE Healthcare Bio-
Sciences, Pittsburgh, PA). 
Following transfection in COS cells, steady state P-
protein levels were identified by Western blotting following 
sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis using 
an antibody against the P-protein from Abcam (ab97625), with 
b-actin as a loading control. Coexpression studies used cotrans-
fection with vectors containing both mutants compared to </p>

<p>transfection with a single mutation and an empty vector. A 
model of human P-protein encoded by the GLDC gene was 
created using the homology modeling program <rs type="software">ESyPred3D</rs> 
based on the crystal structure of holo glycine decarboxylase 
from Synechocystis (Protein Data Bank ID: 4LHC). 
25,26 The rel-</p>

<p>ative locations of mutated residues in the 3-dimensional model 
were viewed using the program RasTop 2.2 (http://www.genein-
finity.org/rastop/). </p>

<p>Mutation Score </p>

<p>A mutation score was constructed as the sum of both alleles 
with a mutation without residual activity scored 21 and with 
residual activity 12. For the presumed mutation score, the 
AMT mutations p.M1T and p.R320H were considered to have 
no residual activity and the mutation p.I106T to have residual 
activity based on the occurrence in multiple families. Thus, the 
presence of 2 mutations without residual activity will give a 
score of 22, whereas the presence of at least 1 mutation with 
known residual activity will give a score of 1. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Descriptive statistics were used to summarize the data. The dif-
ference between severe and attenuated variables is evaluated by 
Student t test for variables that have normal distribution, and 
by Mann-Whitney U test for variables that are not normally 
distributed as evaluated with Wilk-Shapiro. Subcategories of 
attenuated NKH were evaluated by 1-way analysis of variance 
(ANOVA). The significance of a difference in proportion is cal-
culated by the chi-square test. Pearson and Spearman correla-
tion tests were conducted to identify the correlation between 
outcomes and predictors, and identify colinearity among the 
predictors according to the data distribution. Multiple linear 
regression was performed to model the DQ in relation to pre-
dictors. Multiple ordinal logistic regression was performed to 
model the relationship between predictors and disease severity 
or AEDs. <rs id="software-4" type="software">SPSS</rs> Statistics package version <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">21</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">IBM, Armonk, NY</rs>) and <rs id="software-5" type="software">SAS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">SAS, Cary, NC</rs>) were used to per-
form the analyses. A p value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Clinical Severity: Developmental Outcome, 
Seizures, and Brain Malformations 
Of 124 patients, there were 26 patients (21%) who died 
in the neonatal or early infantile period. The 56 patients 
(45%) with severe outcome NKH represent a uniform 
very poor development limited to smiling, or rarely able 
to roll from side to prone. There were 42 patients (34%) 
with attenuated NKH: 6 patients with poor attenuated 
NKH (DQ &lt; 20), 12 with intermediate attenuated NKH 
(DQ 5 20-50), 15 with mild attenuated NKH 
(DQ 50), and 9 with attenuated NKH where the DQ 
was not available. The development presented a contin-
uum from a DQ &lt; 10 up to the normal range with intel-
ligence quotient of 82 in a child who follows regular </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>608 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>education curriculum with assistance. The number of 
AEDs used for seizure control related to the degree of 
developmental delay. All patients with severe NKH were 
treated with multiple (2) anticonvulsants and had per-
sistent seizures, whereas patients with a DQ &gt; 30 never 
required anticonvulsant therapy. The difference between 
severe NKH patients (mean 3.1 AEDs), attenuated poor 
and intermediate NKH combined (mean 1 AED), and 
mild NKH (mean 0 AEDs) was significant (p &lt; 0.001; 
Fig 1A). In patients with severe NKH, 71% had brain 
malformations identified on MRI, whereas only 7.5% of 
patients with attenuated NKH had malformations, all 
hypoplastic corpus callosum (chi-square, p &lt; 0.001; Table 
1). Severe brain malformations (corpus callosum agenesis 
or cerebellar cyst with hydrocephalus) only occurred in 
patients with severe NKH or in neonatal death. Thus, 3 
features related to clinical severity-developmental delay, 
number of AED, and brain malformation-interrelated 
as a class. We next examined clinical predictors of these 
severity classes. </p>

<p>Basic Predictors: Age at Onset and Gender 
Age at onset was commonly neonatal in all categories 
(see Table 1). Onset delayed beyond the first week was 
present in 12% of patients with severe NKH, and in </p>

<p>52% of patients with attenuated NKH. Delayed onset in 
severe NKH was between 2 weeks and 2 months, and 
4 months of age in poor or intermediate attenuated 
NKH. In mild attenuated NKH, 53% of patients had 
onset beyond the first week of life, 7 patients at &gt;4 
months of age, which predicted good outcome. There 
was no significant gender difference in age at onset, DQ, 
or number of AEDs used, but mean CSF glycine was 
higher in females than in males (219 vs 155 lM, 
p 5 0.02). </p>

<p>Glycine Biochemistry 
The plasma glycine levels, the CSF glycine levels, and 
the CSF:plasma glycine ratio were higher in severe NKH 
than in attenuated NKH (see Table 1). Despite substan-
tial overlap in the ranges, the following findings were 
predictive: a CSF glycine level &gt;230 lM predicted severe 
NKH with a sensitivity of 43%, and a CSF:plasma gly-
cine ratio 0.08 predicted attenuated NKH with a sensi-
tivity of 28%. Within the group of attenuated NKH, 
there was a significant difference in CSF glycine and in 
the CSF:plasma ratio between subclasses (ANOVA, both 
p &lt; 0.02) but not in plasma glycine levels (see Fig 1B, 
C). Attenuated mild NKH had significantly lower CSF 
glycine levels (good 73 vs intermediate/poor 121 lM, </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Differences in antiepileptic drugs, glycine levels, and glycine index by disease category. (A) The differences between 
severe nonketotic hyperglycinemia (NKH), poor attenuated NKH, intermediate attenuated NKH, and mild attenuated NKH are 
shown for the number of antiepileptic drugs (A), the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) glycine levels (B), the CSF:plasma glycine ratios (C), 
and the glycine index (D). [Color figure can be viewed in the online issue, which is available at www.annalsofneurology.org.] </p>

<p>Swanson et al: Nonketotic Hyperglycinemia </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
TABLE 1. Clinical Predictors: Age at Onset, Brain Malformations, Glycine Levels, and Ratio </p>

<p>Category </p>

<p>Severe </p>

<p>Attenuated All </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Attenuated Poor 
Attenuated Intermediate </p>

<p>Attenuated Mild </p>

<p>Age at onset 
No. </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>1st week </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>&gt;1 </p>

<p>week </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 (&gt;4 months in 7) </p>

<p>Oldest </p>

<p>2 months </p>

<p>3 year </p>

<p>2 months </p>

<p>4 months </p>

<p>3 year </p>

<p>Brain malformation 
No. (with brain imaging data) </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Corpus callosum agenesis </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Corpus callosum hypoplasia </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Cerebellar cyst/hydrocephalus </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Brain atrophy </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>No malformations </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Glycine levels 
Plasma glycine levels, lM 
Median, No. </p>

<p>1,055, n 5 </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>827, n 5 </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>844, n 5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>760, n 5 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>829, n 5 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Range </p>

<p>324-2,048 </p>

<p>342-1,590 </p>

<p>552-1,433 </p>

<p>509-1,120 </p>

<p>470-1,196 </p>

<p>CSF glycine levels, lM 
Median, No. </p>

<p>213, n 5 </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>89, n 5 </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>138, n 5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>89, n 5 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>63, n 5 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Range </p>

<p>40-510 </p>

<p>41-230 </p>

<p>103-172 </p>

<p>51-230 </p>

<p>41.4-154 </p>

<p>CSF:plasma glycine ratio 
Median, No. </p>

<p>0.22, n 5 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>0.12, n 5 </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.17, n 5 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0.14, n 5 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>0.08, n 5 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Range </p>

<p>0.09-0.45 </p>

<p>0.04-0.22 </p>

<p>0.11-0.21 </p>

<p>0.06-0.22 </p>

<p>0.04-0.17 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The category Attenuated All also included patients with attenuated nonketotic hyperglycinemia not otherwise specified where the developmental quotient is not known. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>p &lt; </p>

<p>0.01, </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>p &lt; 
0.001, Mann-Whitney U test. </p>

<p>CSF 5 
cerebrospinal fluid. </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>610 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>p &lt; 0.01) and ratios (good 0.095 vs intermediate/poor 
0.15, p &lt; 0.01). 
In attenuated NKH patients, the continuous outcome 
variable of DQ correlated significantly with age at onset, 
number of AEDs, CSF glycine level, CSF:plasma glycine 
ratio, and glycine index (Table 2 and Fig 2). Multiple linear 
regression showed a best model of outcome in DQ when 
related to both age at onset 5 1.06 6 0.42 and CSF glycine 
level 5 20.19 6 0.075 lM with constant 53 6 9.1, 
p 5 0.01. Multiple logistic regression identified only 2 inde-
pendent predictors for disease severity: age at onset (point 
estimate 5 1.526, 95% confidence interval [CI] 5 1.183-
1.968, p 5 0.001) and CSF glycine level (point 
estimate 5 0.993, 95% CI 5 0.989-0.997, p &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Protein, Enzyme Activity, Glycine Index 
Patients affected with AMT mutations (15%) are less 
common than patients with GLDC mutations (85%), 
with no GCSH mutations identified. The proportion of 
T-protein-deficient patients was not significantly differ-
ent in severe NKH (12 of 56) versus attenuated NKH (5 
of 42; chi-square, p 5 0.25). Also, plasma and CSF gly-
cine levels, CSF:plasma glycine ratio, age at onset, and 
DQ did not differ significantly between patients deficient 
in P-and T-protein. The enzyme activity in liver 
depended on the affected protein (P-protein 0-10%, 
n 5 4; T-protein 10-31%, n 5 4), as previously </p>

<p>reported. 
27 Residual activity in EBV-transformed lym-</p>

<p>phoblasts (n 5 10) ranged from 0 to 83% of normal 
activity, and as previously noted proved unreliable, with 
a patient with a severe outcome who had 83% residual 
activity. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>In contrast, the glycine index had a strong relation with 
outcome (see Fig 1D). It was highest in the severely affected 
patients (average 5 4.01, range 5 2.84-4.87, n 5 8), 
between 2 and 3 in poor attenuated patients (average 5 2.69, 
range 5 2.30-3.10, n 5 4), and &lt;2 in all intermediate or 
mild attenuated patients (average 5 1.27, range 5 0.24-
1.90, n 5 8; ANOVA, p &lt; 0.001). As the glycine index 
reflects residual glycine catabolism on a whole body level, </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Relation of Developmental Quotient with Outcome and Predictive Variables </p>

<p>Predictive Factor 
No. 
Pearson R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>p 
Spearman Rho 
p </p>

<p>Attenuated NKH only </p>

<p>Age at onset 
33 
0.247 
0.003 
0.384 
0.03 </p>

<p>Antiepileptic drugs 
33 
20.260 
0.002 
20.582 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>CSF glycine 
28 
20.315 
0.002 
20.664 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>CSF:plasma glycine 
24 
20.328 
0.003 
20.544 
0.005 </p>

<p>Glycine index 
12 
20.424 
0.02 
20.765 
0.004 </p>

<p>Attenuated and severe </p>

<p>Age at onset 
88 
0.311 
&lt;0.001 
0.433 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Antiepileptic drugs 
56 
20.599 
&lt;0.001 
20.827 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>CSF glycine 
74 
20.296 
&lt;0.001 
20.681 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>CSF:plasma glycine 
70 
20.289 
&lt;0.001 
20.622 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Plasma glycine 
81 
20.081 
0.01 
20.266 
0.02 </p>

<p>Glycine index 
20 
0.645 
&lt;0.001 
20.904 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Mutation score 
81 
20.479 
&lt;0.001 
0.674 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Correlation between developmental quotient and each of the predictive factors. 
CSF 5 cerebrospinal fluid; NKH 5 nonketotic hyperglycinemia. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Relation between cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) gly-
cine levels and developmental quotient (DQ). There is a 
direct linear correlation between CSF glycine levels and DQ. 
The cutoff at 230 lM is shown. </p>

<p>Swanson et al: Nonketotic Hyperglycinemia </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
this indicated that patients with intermediate and mild atten-
uated NKH had more residual activity than patients with 
poor attenuated NKH and severe NKH, suggesting a con-
tributing genetic factor. </p>

<p>Genetic Studies 
The mutation spectrum showed extensive intragenic 
molecular heterogeneity in classic NKH, including 78 
novel mutations in GLDC and 18 novel mutations in 
AMT. All mutations identified are listed in the Supple-
mentary Table at the cDNA and protein level and were 
submitted to the Leiden Open Variant Databases (http:// 
databases.lovd.nl/shared/genes) of GLDC and AMT (Figs 
3 and 4). Of the 209 alleles in GLDC, there were 50.2% 
missense mutations, 8.1% nonsense mutations, 5.7% fra-
meshift mutations, 13.4% splice site mutations, 20.6% 
exonic deletions, 1 exonic duplication, and 1 in-frame 
3bp deletion resulting in a single amino acid deletion. 
Of the 114 mutations, 72 mutations were only identified 
in a single allele. Recurring mutations (53) included 
p.R515S (133), del exon 1-2 (123), IVS2211G&gt;C </p>

<p>(103), p.A389V (83), del exon 3-21 (73), p.A802V 
(63), p.A202V (53), p.E167X (53), and IVS19-1G&gt;A 
(53). The exonic deletions were heterogeneous, ranging 
from a single exon to entire gene deletions, and were as 
frequent on the maternal (n 5 21) as the paternal 
(n 5 22) allele. Some patients had 2 small nonoverlap-
ping deletions not detectable by sequencing, making 
deletion analysis diagnostically imperative. A mutation 
was not identified in 2 alleles, giving current analysis 
methods 99% sensitivity in GLDC. The AMT gene with 
38 alleles had a different mutation spectrum, with 76.3% 
missense mutations, 7.9% splice site mutations, 13.2% 
frameshift mutations, and 1 nonsense mutation, but no 
exonic deletions or duplications. All recurring mutations 
were missense: p.R320H (73), p.M1T (43), and 
p.I106T (43). In silico analysis confirmed the expected 
pathogenicity of mutations of the 2 nucleotides of each 
consensus splice site (score &lt; 0.46), except for IVS18-
2A&gt;G in GLDC (score 5 0.64), where RNA analysis 
confirmed the presence of normally spliced mRNA, indi-
cating a leaky splicing mutation (data not shown). The </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Mutations in GLDC. Missense mutations are shown above the diagram of the exonic structure of the GLDC gene. 
Missense mutations with residual activity are shown in green, missense mutations without residual activity are shown in red, 
and mutations not expressed are shown in yellow. Frameshift mutations (gray) and splice site mutations (orange) are shown 
below the exonic structure. The length of observed exonic deletions is shown in red and duplications in blue. The frequency of 
occurrence is provided for recurring mutations. </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>612 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>in silico prediction of pathogenicity of the deep splice 
site mutation IVS615G&gt;C in AMT was confirmed by 
RNA analysis showing the presence of sequence compati-
ble with the insertion of intron 6 sequence. The in silico 
predicted pathogenicity of the deep splice site mutation 
IVS2315G&gt;A in GLDC could not be further verified, 
as lymphoblasts were unavailable. An ethnic concentra-
tion was present for AMT p.I106T in the Southern 
Netherlands and GLDC p.S132L in New Zealand, 
reflecting a founder effect. Most parents were carriers, 
but a de novo mutation not present in the blood of the 
parents was identified in 3 patients (1% of alleles), 
although germline mosaicism could not be excluded. </p>

<p>Residual Activity of Mutations in Expression 
Analysis 
In many metabolic conditions, residual enzyme activity 
determines clinical outcome. We analyzed the impact of 
mutations on residual activity and in relation to neurode-
velopmental outcome. There were differences in the muta-
tion classes between severe NKH and attenuated NKH. 
Nonsense mutations, frameshift mutations, exonic dele-</p>

<p>tions, and duplications, which have no residual activity, 
were more frequent in severe than in attenuated NKH 
patients (38 % vs 11% of alleles, p &lt; 0.001), and adding 
mutations affecting consensus donor and acceptor splice 
sites, which usually result in absent activity, accentuated 
this difference (severe NKH 57 of 109, attenuated NKH 
18 of 84 alleles, p &lt; 0.001). Patients with both alleles from 
these classes had severe NKH, whereas each attenuated 
NKH patient had at least 1 missense mutation. Two excep-
tional mutations were classified as mild: a frameshift muta-
tion that affects only the penultimate 20 amino acids, and 
a leaky splice site mutation IVS18-2A&gt;G. 
We hypothesized that missense mutations that 
recurred in attenuated NKH (p.A202V, p.T269M, 
p.A389V, p.A802V in GLDC and p.I106T in AMT) 
conferred residual enzyme activity, whereas others that 
occurred in homozygosity in severe NKH patients 
(p.S132L and p.R515S in GLDC and p.R320H and 
p.M1T in AMT) had no residual activity. We expressed 
selected missense mutations and measured residual activity 
of the P-protein using the glycine exchange reaction with 
recombinant human H-protein, which after the lipoyl-</p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Mutations in AMT. Missense mutations (yellow) are shown above the diagram of the exonic structure of the AMT 
gene. Frameshift mutations (gray) and splice site mutations (orange) are shown below the exonic structure. </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Number of residual activity-conferring mutations and disease severity. (A) The frequency of developmental outcome 
in categories of severe, attenuated (Att) poor, attenuated intermediate, attenuated mild, or attenuated not otherwise specified 
(NOS; without known developmental quotient [DQ]) is shown in relation to the number of alleles with a mutation conferring no 
residual activity (severe mutation) or alleles with a mutation conferring residual activity (mild mutation). (B) The frequency of 
patients requiring a number of antiepileptic medications in relation to the number of severe or mild alleles. </p>

<p>Swanson et al: Nonketotic Hyperglycinemia </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
ligase reaction was &gt;80% lipoylated by mass spectrometry, 
and was no longer rate limiting at 4 lM. The mutations 
p.S132L, p.P304L, p.C382Y, p.T437I, p.R515S, p.A569T, 
p.G618R, p.S657R, p.G761R, p.S808R, p.A833V, 
p.P893L, and p.H950R had no measurable residual activ-
ity. Mutations with residual activity were classified as very 
mild with &gt;10% activity (p.L82S, p.A202V, p.I381T, 
p.A389V, p.L548V, p.A802V, p.A802E), mild with 1 to 
10% activity (p.T269M, p.C291Y, p.Q366R, p.G607S, 
p.R630P), and intermediate with measurable activity 0.5 
to 1% of wild-type activity (p.A283P, p.R461Q, 
p.A678del; see Supplementary Table). 
To relate residual activity to outcome, we analyzed 
60 patients who survived the neonatal period with 
known neurodevelopment outcome, and for whom both 
mutations in GLDC were identified and the residual 
activity determined (Fig 5). Both developmental outcome 
as DQ and number of AEDs used differed significantly 
with the number of alleles with residual activity (Fisher 
exact test, both p &lt; 0.001). Patients with 2 severe muta-
tions used multiple (2-4) AEDs; patients with 2 residual 
activity-conferring alleles used no or rarely 1 AED; 
whereas patients with a single residual activity-conferring 
allele used no (in 47%) or 1 to 3 AEDs. All 29 patients 
with 2 severe mutations had severe NKH; all 8 patients 
with 2 mutations with measurable residual activity had 
attenuated NKH, 6 of them mild, whereas 91% of 
patients with a single allele with residual activity had 
attenuated NKH, the majority poor or intermediate. 
Even patients with a single intermediate mutation still </p>

<p>had attenuated outcome (Patients 18, 61, 79), indicating 
that very little in vitro residual activity is required. 
Exceptions exist where severe outcome occurred even in 
the presence of a single very mild allele (eg, p.A802V 
[Patient 39] and p.A389V [Patient 35]). This indicates 
that an allele with residual activity is necessary but not 
sufficient for attenuated outcome, and that factors in 
addition to genotype influence outcome. Further illus-
trating this, the average DQ was higher in patients with 
2 residual activity-conferring mutations than in those 
with a single such mutation (53 vs 28, p 5 0.01), but 
within the group of attenuated patients there was no cor-
relation between DQ and the summed residual activity 
of both alleles (r 
2 &lt; 0.001). Substantial phenotypic differ-</p>

<p>ences existed within the same genotype; for instance, 
p.A389V/p.R515S was seen in a severe (Patient 35) and 
an attenuated intermediate phenotype (Patient 148). 
Expanding this analysis to all patients showed a sig-
nificant difference in the mutation score between out-
come categories (ANOVA, p &lt; 0.001; post hoc Tukey 
difference only significant between severe 1.38 6 1.41 
and attenuated 21.43 6 0.83, p &lt; 0.001; Fig 6). A score 
of 22 predicted severe outcome with sensitivity of 62% 
and specificity of 100%, and a score 1 predicted atten-
uated outcome with a sensitivity of 81% and a specificity 
of 94% (Table 3). Combined, this mutation score had a 
predictive sensitivity of 70% and specificity of 97%. </p>

<p>Molecular Modeling and Protein Stability 
The relative locations of the expressed mutations are 
shown on the tertiary structure of human P-protein mod-
eled on the homologous a2 homodimer structure of Syn-
echocystis species glycine decarboxylase (Fig 7). 
26 Mutated </p>

<p>amino acids located near the active site pocket (A833, 
L548, H950, A389, S808, I381, Q366, C382, G607, 
P893) tended to have stable protein levels but highly 
variable residual activity. For instance, mild mutations 
Q366R, I381T, and G607S affect amino acids located in 
a loop or domain that is mobile upon pyridoxal-phos-
phate binding in Thermus thermophilus, and Q366 </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Mutation score by disease category. The muta-
tion score is compared between neonatal deceased, severe 
nonketotic hyperglycinemia (NKH), poor attenuated NKH, 
intermediate attenuated NKH, mild attenuated NKH, and 
attenuated NKH not otherwise specified (NOS). The muta-
tion score is significantly higher in attenuated NKH than in 
severe or neonatal decreased NKH. [Color figure can be 
viewed in the online issue, which is available at www.annal-
sofneurology.org.] </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Presumed Mutation Score as a Predictor </p>

<p>Score 
Severe 
Attenuated </p>

<p>22 
3 4 
0 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 4 </p>

<p>Other 
19 
10 </p>

<p>Total 
55 
42 </p>

<p>Number of severe or attenuated nonketotic hyperglycinemia 
patients with a specific mutation score. </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>614 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>resides in the lipoamide channel. 
28 In contrast, mutated </p>

<p>amino acids located on the outer side of protein away 
from the active pocket (A283, A202, C291, T269, 
R461, P304, R515, S132, A569, A678, T437, A802) 
tended to have decreased protein levels of variable resid-
ual activity, likely due to protein instability. For instance, 
mild mutations p.T269M and p.A202V located in the 
9th a-helix, and severe mutations p.R515S and p.G761R 
affected the structural interaction of the N-and C-
terminal halves of the protein. 
28 Cotransfection studies </p>

<p>were done to review if observed combination of 2 muta-
tions would affect the residual activity given the dimeric 
structure of P-protein. The severe but stable mutant 
p.S657R did not significantly reduce the residual activity 
or protein levels of p.A802V (5.9%; Patient 39) com-
pared to sham (7.2%, p 5 0.28; Patient 52), but the 
unstable p.R515S decreased the activity and the protein 
amount of p.A389V (4.2% activity; Patients 35, 148) 
compared to sham (11.2%, p &lt; 0.001; Patient 278), indi-
cating a dominant negative effect for unstable mutants at 
the protein level (Fig 8). </p>

<p>Neonatal and Early Infantile Deceased Patients 
As a group, neonatally deceased patients were similar to 
severe patients. They had more severe mutations (65% vs </p>

<p>54% of alleles, p &lt; 0.001) and fewer brain malformations 
(48% vs 71%, p &lt; 0.001), but similar CSF glycine levels 
and CSF:plasma glycine ratio. On close observation, we 
identified a few patients who had residual activity-con-
ferring mutations, without brain malformations, and 
with low CSF glycine level and CSF:plasma glycine ratio 
(eg, Patients 33a and 33b with p.T269M, and Patient 19 
with p.G607S). Because &gt;50% of attenuated NKH 
patients presented neonatally, we presume that these 
patients at least had the potential for attenuated 
outcome. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>At the outset of this study, we encountered patients who 
presented neonatally and had been given a dismal prog-
nosis, but who made substantial developmental progress. 
This inaccurate prognostic information was frustrating 
for the families. The majority of patients with attenuated 
NKH, even mild, presented neonatally, and predicting 
prognosis based on age at onset alone was inaccurate. 
Moreover, single case studies of a new treatment, such as 
dextromethorphan, exhibited the same prognostic pitfall 
attributing the attenuated outcome to the drug treatment 
when, because of the neonatal presentation, the patient 
was expected to have a severe outcome. 
29 A more accu-</p>

<p>rate prognostic stratification is required for adequate clin-
ical trial evaluation. A reliable measure to predict 
outcome in NKH was not yet available, 
30 and past small </p>

<p>studies had contradictory conclusions on the predictive 
value of glycine levels. 
7,14 In this study, we categorized </p>

<p>patients with NKH according to outcome, rather than 
age at onset, using developmental attainment as the pri-
mary outcome measure, which correlated well with neu-
rological indicators such as the presence of brain 
malformations and the number of AEDs used to treat 
epilepsy. Attenuated NKH was distinguished from severe 
NKH by the presence of a variable degree of develop-
ment, 
2 and despite its continuous nature was subdivided </p>

<p>in categories to facilitate statistical analysis. </p>

<p>FIGURE 8: Western blot analysis of expressed mutations in 
GLDC. The missense mutations present in 2 patients were 
expressed in COS cells, and the level of P-protein identified 
by Western blot. The amount of b-actin protein is shown as 
a loading control. WT 5 wild type. [Color figure can be 
viewed in the online issue, which is available at www.annal-
sofneurology.org.] </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: Molecular modeling of mutated amino acids on 
the structure of the P-protein. The homology structure of 
the human P-protein dimer modeled from Synechocystis 
species is shown with the amino acids of the expressed mis-
sense mutations highlighted. Amino acids involved in mis-
sense mutations without residual activity on expression 
study are shown in red, with &lt;1% residual activity in blue, 
with 1 to 10% residual activity in yellow, and with &gt;10% 
residual activity in green. The active site lysine 754 is shown 
in pink. Amino acids that when mutated result in a stable 
protein (identified in the lower part) tend to cluster around 
the active site fold (red circle), whereas amino acids that 
when mutated result in unstable protein (identified in the 
upper part) tend to be located away from the active site 
fold. </p>

<p>Swanson et al: Nonketotic Hyperglycinemia </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>

<p>
This study provides strong evidence that genotype 
is a primary determinant of outcome, and presence of 
residual activity relates to outcome, as had previously 
been hypothesized from individual cases. 
7,8,11,22 Two </p>

<p>mutations without residual enzyme activity are associated 
with severe outcome, and attenuated outcome requires at 
least 1 mutation providing residual enzyme activity. Lack 
of residual enzyme activity in severe patients results in a 
larger glycine pool, which requires more sodium benzoate 
to normalize glycine levels as reflected in a greater glycine 
index, 
18 which showed the best discrimination between </p>

<p>outcome categories. This larger glycine pool results in 
increased brain and CSF glycine levels. CSF glycine cor-
related significantly although not strongly with outcome 
measures, but at the extremes CSF glycine &gt;230 lM 
predicted severe outcome and low CSF:plasma glycine 
ratio 0.08 predicted attenuated outcome. Of the clini-
cally useful predictors, which are listed with sensitivity 
and specificity in Table 4, age at onset, brain imaging, 
CSF glycine, and CSF:plasma glycine ratio are available 
in the immediate newborn period to enable counseling 
of parents. Using these 4 predictors available at diagnosis 
(age at onset 4 months, CSF glycine &gt;230 lM, 
CSF:plasma glycine ratio 0.08, and brain malforma-
tions on MRI), 78% of severe patients and 49% of 
attenuated patients would be accurately identified. A sim-
plified panel of 7 mutations (p.A202V, p.A389V, 
p.A802V/E, p.T269M, p.L548V, p.G607S in GLDC and </p>

<p>p.I106T in AMT) identified 55% of attenuated patients, 
and could be implemented for rapid prediction in the 
neonatal period. 
Molecular analysis provides an important predictor. 
This report greatly expands the number of mutations 
beyond those previously reported. Combined sequencing 
and exonic deletion-duplication analysis identified 99% 
of causative alleles in GLDC and all in AMT, and consti-
tutes the preferred confirmatory diagnostic testing. Due 
to the documented 1% de novo mutation rate, carrier 
status of parents should be verified and not assumed in 
the context of recurrence risk counseling and prenatal 
diagnosis. The large genetic heterogeneity complicates 
the analysis of genotype to phenotype relation. Caution 
is necessary when using generic rules in predicting 
whether a mutation would retain residual activity. Phylo-
genetic conservation was unhelpful, with most mutations 
affecting conserved amino acids regardless of residual 
activity, yet p.A569T affects a poorly conserved amino 
acid but had no residual activity. Mutations affecting the 
2 essential splice donor/acceptor nucleotides severely dis-
rupted splicing, but IVS18-2A&gt;G was a notable excep-
tion. To evaluate missense mutations, we developed a 
new effective expression study, with results agreeing with 
the few previous publications. 
27,31 The amount of resid-</p>

<p>ual activity associated with attenuated outcome was very 
low. Mutations that result in unstable protein tend to be 
located away from the active cleft, and even reduce the </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Clinically Useful Predictors of Outcome </p>

<p>Parameter 
Outcome 
Sensitivity 
Specificity </p>

<p>Onset &gt; 4 months 
Attenuated mild 
47% 
100% </p>

<p>Onset 1st week 
Severe 
87% 
70% </p>

<p>CSF glycine &gt; 230 lM 
Severe 
43% 
100% </p>

<p>CSF:plasma glycine ratio 0.08 
Attenuated 
28% 
100% </p>

<p>Brain malformation severe 
Severe 
29% 
100% </p>

<p>Brain malformation all (including HCC) 
Severe 
71% 
92% </p>

<p>No epilepsy (no AEDs) 
Attenuated 
70% 
100% </p>

<p>Glycine index &gt; 3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Severe 
87% 
100% </p>

<p>2 nonmissense mutations 
Severe 
36% 
95% </p>

<p>Mutation score 
b 5 22 
Severe 
59% 
97% </p>

<p>Mutation score 
b 1 
Attenuated 
76% 
94% </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>A glycine index of 3 mmol/kg/day for a child on breast milk or regular infant formula with intake of 150 ml/kg/day calculates to 
a sodium benzoate dose of 510-540 mg/kg/day to bring glycine levels within therapeutic range (120-300 lM). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The mutation score provides a score of 21 for a mutation expected to leave no residual activity and 12 for a mutation that is 
expected to have residual activity. The sum of both alleles scored as is currently known is used. 
AED 5 antiepileptic drug; CSF 5 cerebrospinal fluid; HCC 5 hypoplastic corpus callosum. </p>

<p>ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>616 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

<p>protein amount of the other allele likely due to dimer, 
formation as was shown for the p.R515S mutation. In 
this study, 69 of 124 patients carried at least 1 GLDC 
missense mutation, and 13 of 27 GLDC missense 
mutants created unstable proteins, including common 
mutations such as p.R515S. The impact of current ther-
apy with benzoate and dextromethorphan has been lim-
ited. A theoretically new therapeutic option of a 
chaperone or a proteostasis regulator that increases pro-
tein levels could increase enzyme activity and positively 
affect outcome in at least 27% of patients. 
32 The relation </p>

<p>between residual activity and outcome is complex. The 
number of alleles with residual activity relates to out-
come, but there was not a direct correlation between DQ 
and the amount of residual activity in this eukaryotic 
expression system. Patients with a similar mild mutation 
sometimes had a very different outcome in this study, 
and substantial intrafamilial variability in large families 
has been noted. 
14 This suggests that factors additional to </p>

<p>genotype contribute to outcome. 
11,31 For patients with </p>

<p>attenuated NKH, the nature and timing of early treat-
ment has been suggested as a potential factor. </p>

<p>30   Although this study is the largest ever in NKH, it 
does have limitations. Patients were evaluated from a 
very wide geographic region, allowing for generalization 
in this rare condition, and therefore encountered a vari-
ety of methods to evaluate developmental outcome. Anal-
ysis of developmental and behavioral outcome 
subcategories was not possible and will require a system-
atic analysis at a few centers using standardized measures. 
A wide spectrum of behavioral and developmental prob-
lems was noted in preliminary analysis of a few patients 
with attenuated NKH. The MRI review was limited to 
brain malformations as described in the report of the 
reading radiologist, and detailed analysis, such as the dis-
tribution of diffusion restriction, requires further 
study. 
33,34 A detailed description of the seizure type, elec-</p>

<p>troencephalogram, or response to specific antiepileptic 
medications could not be systematically captured, and 
requires a separate study. The number of AEDs used, 
which could be accurately recorded, is significant because 
the need for &gt;2 AEDs, as seen in severe NKH, relates to 
the presence of therapy-refractory epilepsy. </p>

<p>35   This study documented several factors predicting 
prognosis, including the presence of brain malformations, 
the CSF glycine level, the CSF:plasma glycine ratio, and 
the type of genetic mutation. This information is valua-
ble to parents and clinicians to allow better prediction of 
outcome. Prediction of severe outcome can help families 
in considering withdrawal of life-sustaining therapy in 
the neonatal apneic phase, given the current lack of effec-
tive therapies in this setting. 
15,36 It is also important in </p>

<p>the stratification of patients in treatment studies. Differ-
ent treatment responses may exist between severe and 
attenuated NKH. 
30,36 The relation between residual </p>

<p>activity and outcome suggests that novel strategies to 
improve residual activity such as chaperones may have a 
beneficial clinical effect and should be researched. The 
complex relationship between genotype and phenotype 
indicates that additional factors will need to be identified 
to make such a strategy fully successful. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>This study was supported by the NKH Crusaders Fund, 
Hope for NKH Fund, CU Nonketotic Hyperglycinemia 
Fund, Joseph's Goal Fund, Brodyn's Friends Fund, Smiles 
for Miles NKH Research Fund, Lucy's BEElievers Fund, 
Madi's Mission to Find a Cure for NKH Fund, Les 
Petits Bourdons, Children's Clinical Research Organiza-
tion at Children's Hospital Colorado, and vector core of 
the Rocky Mountain Neurological Disorders Core Center 
Grant NIH/NS048154. Sequencing was supported by 
the University of Colorado DNA Sequencing and Analy-
sis Core. 
We thank the families who participated in this study; 
the numerous physicians and genetic counselors who 
referred patients and provided clinical information; the 
nutritionists who calculated glycine intake, S. Gaughan, 
C. Burns, and K. Vande Kerckhove; the genetic counse-
lors who helped with patient enrollment, M. Raymond 
and L. Sremba; and Drs T. Benke and A. Brooks-Kayal 
for helpful discussions. </p>

<p>Authorship </p>

<p>Conception, design, and coordination of the study was by 
J.L.K.V.H. Acquisition and analysis of clinical data were 
by J.L.K.V.H., J.B.H., C.R.C., K.J.B., and G.H.S., and of 
laboratory data were by M.A.S., G.H.S., H.J.S., E.B.S., 
G.C.-S., V.M., G.M., D.A.A., J.R.T., and K.W. Statistical 
analysis was done by J.L.K.V.H. and S.T. The manuscript 
was written by J.L.K.V.H., M.A.S., and C.R.C. </p>

<p>Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>Nothing to report. </p>



<p>Swanson et al: Nonketotic Hyperglycinemia </p>

<p>October 2015 </p>



<p>
ANNALS of Neurology </p>

<p>618 
Volume 78, No. 4 </p>

</text></tei>