<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4832390" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cathepsin B is a cysteine proteinase that primarily functions as an endopeptidase within endolysosomal compartments 
in normal cells. However, during tumoral expansion, the regulation of cathepsin B can be altered at multiple levels, thereby 
resulting in its overexpression and export outside of the cell. This may suggest a possible role of cathepsin B in alterations 
leading to cancer progression. The aim of this study was to determine the contribution of intracellular and extracellular 
cathepsin B in growth, tumorigenesis, and invasion of colorectal cancer (CRC) cells. Results show that mRNA and activated 
levels of cathepsin B were both increased in human adenomas and in CRCs of all stages. Treatment of CRC cells with the 
highly selective and non-permeant cathepsin B inhibitor Ca074 revealed that extracellular cathepsin B actively contributed 
to the invasiveness of human CRC cells while not essential for their growth in soft agar. Cathepsin B silencing by RNAi in 
human CRC cells inhibited their growth in soft agar, as well as their invasion capacity, tumoral expansion, and metastatic 
spread in immunodeficient mice. Higher levels of the cell cycle inhibitor p27 
Kip1 were observed in cathepsin B-deficient 
tumors as well as an increase in cyclin B1. Finally, cathepsin B colocalized with p27 
Kip1 within the lysosomes and efficiently 
degraded the inhibitor. In conclusion, the present data demonstrate that cathepsin B is a significant factor in colorectal 
tumor development, invasion, and metastatic spreading and may, therefore, represent a potential pharmacological target 
for colorectal tumor therapy. Colorectal cancer (CRC) is one of the major 
malignancies worldwide and the second leading cause 
of cancer death in North America. CRC develops 
through multiple steps, with the sequential acquisi-
tion of genetic alterations in key tumor suppressors 
and oncogenes. This knowledge has been largely 
derived from early research on CRC [1]. The pheno-
typic hallmarks of cancer cells include the ability to 
invade and metastasize which depends on the action 
of proteases actively taking center stage in extracellu-
lar proteolysis during cancer progression [2]. Of all the 
proteases, the cysteine protease cathepsin B is of 
significant importance as it is involved in various 
pathologies and oncogenic processes [3]. Cathepsin B 
primarily functions as an endopeptidase within 
endolysosomal compartments in normal cells. How-
ever, during malignant transformation, the regula-
tion of cathepsin B can be altered at multiple levels 
thereby resulting in its overproduction [3,4]. Mech-
anisms that increase cathepsin B expression in tumors 
and in tumor-associated cells include genetic amplifi-
cation or alternative splicing [4]. Moreover, in 
tumors, cathepsin B can either be secreted, bound 
to the cell membrane or released by shedding 
vesicles [4]. Expression and redistribution of active 
cathepsin B to the basal plasma membrane occurs in </p>

<p>late colon adenomas [5,6] coincident with the 
activation of KRAS [1]. In line with these results, 
Cavallo-Medved et al. [7] have demonstrated that 
trafficking of cathepsin B to caveolae and its secretion 
are regulated by active KRAS in CRC cells in culture. 
Accordingly, secretion of cathepsin B is increased in 
the extracellular environment of CRC [8,9] where it is 
suspected to play an essential role in disrupting 
extracellular matrix barriers between tumors and 
surrounding tissue, thereby facilitating invasion and </p>

<p>Abbreviations: APC, adenomatous polyposis coli; CDK, cyclin-
dependent kinase; CHX, cycloheximide; CRC, colorectal cancer; CTSB, 
cathepsin B; ERK, extracellular signal regulated kinase; FCS, fetal calf 
serum; HEK, human embryonic kidney; IEC, intestinal epithelial cells; 
Kip1, kinase inhibitory protein 1; Kip2, kinase inhibitory protein 2; 
MAPK, mitogen-activated protein kinase; Min, multiple intestinal 
neoplasia; MMP, matrix metalloproteases; RNAi, RNA interference; 
uPA, urokinase-type plasminogen activator; Wnt, Wingless. 
Grant sponsor: Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR); 
Grant numbers: CTP-82942; MT-14405 
*Correspondence to: D epartement d'Anatomie et de Biologie 
Cellulaire, Facult e de M edecine et des Sciences de la Sant e, Universit e 
de Sherbrooke, 3201, Jean-Mignault, Sherbrooke, QC, Canada 
J1E4K8. 
Received 29 July 2014; Revised 5 February 2015; Accepted 21 
February 2015 
DOI 10.1002/mc.22312 
Published online 25 March 2015 in Wiley Online Library 
(wileyonlinelibrary.com). </p>

<p>ß 2015 THE AUTHORS. MOLECULAR CARCINOGENESIS PUBLISHED BY WILEY PERIODICALS, INC. 
This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and 
distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are 
made. </p>

<p>metastasis [10-12]. Altogether, these data are consis-
tent with the link between cathepsin B protein 
expression in colorectal carcinomas and shortened 
patient survival [6]. 
In a recent prospective cohort study of 558 men and 
women with colonic tumors accessible for immuno-
histochemical assessment, Chan et al. [13] found that 
82% of patients had tumors that expressed cathepsin 
B, irrespective of stage, while the remaining 18% had 
tumors that did not express cathepsin B. Moreover, 
other studies have suggested that cathepsin B expres-
sion or activity may actually peak during early stage 
cancer and subsequently decline with advanced 
disease [14,15]. Thus, the above data point to a 
possible role of cathepsin B in both early and late 
alterations leading to tumor formation in the colon. 
In light of the above, the present study used two 
strategies to specifically counteract the action of 
cathepsin B. The first involved the use of RNA 
interference (RNAi) to inhibit the expression of 
cathepsin B protein into CRC cells while the second 
approach employed the highly selective cathepsin 
inhibitor Ca074 to block extracellular cathepsin B 
activity. Results suggest that extracellular cathepsin B 
is involved in cell invasion whereas intracellular 
cathepsin B controls tumoral properties of CRC cells. 
Of further importance, biochemical analysis suggests 
that intracellular cathepsin B regulates tumorigenesis 
by degrading the p27 
Kip1 cell cycle inhibitor. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Antibodies </p>

<p>Primary antibodies were obtained from the follow-
ing sources: Na 
þ /K 
þ ATPase-a, calnexin, calpain 2, 
CDK2, cyclin B1, cyclin E, ERK2, lamin B, HA tag, p21, 
p27 
Kip1 , p57 
Kip2 , b-tubulin from Santa Cruz Biotech-
nology (Santa Cruz, CA), b-actin from Chemicon 
International (Billerica, MA), phospho-AKT (Ser473), 
AKT, phosphorylated ERK1/2 (T202/Y204), and 
Lamp1 from Cell Signaling Technology (Danvers, 
MA) and Cathepsin B from R&amp;D Systems (Mississauga, 
ON, Canada). Mouse and rabbit horseradish peroxi-
dase antibodies were purchased from Amersham 
Biosciences (Pittsburg, PA), goat horseradish peroxi-
dase antibody from Santa Cruz, and alkaline phos-
phatase-conjugated antibodies were purchased from 
Promega (Madison, WI). </p>

<p>Inhibitor and protease </p>

<p>Cathepsin B inhibitor IV CA074 and recombinant 
human cathepsin B were obtained from EMD Milli-
pore (Billerica). </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>Colorectal adenocarcinoma cell lines (except Caco-
2/15 cell line) and HEK293T cells were all obtained 
from ATCC (Manassas, VA). The cell line Caco-2/15 </p>

<p>was obtained from Dr A. Quaroni (Cornell University, 
Ithaca, NY) and cultured in DMEM containing 10% 
FCS (Wisent, St-Bruno, QC, Canada). The colon 
carcinoma cell lines HCT116 (CCL-247) and HT29 
(HTB-38) were cultured in McCoy's medium contain-
ing 10% FCS. The colon adenocarcinoma cell line 
Lovo (CCL 229) was cultured in Ham's F12 medium 
containing 10% FCS. SW480 (CCL 228), SW620 
(CCL-227), and HEK293T cell lines were maintained 
in DMEM containing 10% FCS. The colon adenocar-
cinoma cell lines DLD-1 (CCL-21) and Colo205 (CCL-
222) were cultured in RPMI medium containing 10% 
FCS [16]. </p>

<p>Mice </p>

<p>CD1 nu/nu and Fox Chase SCID Beige mice were 
purchased from Charles River Laboratory (Wilming-
ton, MA). Mice were housed in individually ventilated 
cages and sterilized food, water, bedding, and cages 
were used. Experiments were approved by the Animal 
Research Committee of the Faculty of Medicine and 
Health Sciences of the Universit e de Sherbrooke. </p>

<p>Human Colorectal Tissues </p>

<p>Sixty-six samples of colon tumors and paired 
normal colon tissues (at least 10 cm from the tumor) 
were obtained from patients undergoing surgical 
resection. Patients did not receive neoadjuvant 
therapy. Tissues were collected after obtaining the 
patient's written informed consent, according to the 
protocol approved by the Institutional Human 
Subject Review Board of the Centre Hospitalier 
Universitaire de Sherbrooke. Paired tissues were 
frozen in liquid nitrogen within 15 min from resec-
tion as recommended by the Canadian Tumor 
Repository Network [http://www.ctrnet.ca] and 
stored in liquid nitrogen until total RNA or protein 
extraction. Total RNA was extracted using the Totally 
RNA kit (Invitrogen, Burlington, ON) and processed 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. For 
protein extraction, paired tissues were lysed in Triton 
sample buffer (100 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA [pH 8.0], 
50 mM Tris-HCl [pH 7.5], 1% Triton X-100, 5% 
glycerol, 1 mM PMSF, 0.2 mM orthovanadate, 
40 mM b-glycerophosphate, 50 mM NaF, and 2% 
protease inhibitor cocktail [Sigma-Aldrich]) and 
immunoblotted as described in the Western blot 
analysis section. Clinical and pathological data were 
obtained from medical records and are provided in 
supplementary Table S1. Adenoma samples were 
endoscopically unresectable and defined as advanced 
because of their size larger than 1 cm or by the 
presence of high-grade dysplasia or villous compo-
nent. Tumors were histologically classified and 
graded according to overall TNM staging criteria 
(based on Tumor-, Lymph Node-, and Metastatic-
status). Genomic DNA was extracted from formalin-
fixed paraffin-embedded tissue using a FFPE DNA 
Isolation Kit for Cells and Tissues (Qiagen, Toronto, </p>



<p>BIAN ET AL. </p>

<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>ON, Canada). APC (exon 15) and KRAS (exons 1 and 2) 
were amplified by PCR and the presence of mutations 
was detected by direct sequencing (Plateforme de 
S equenS cage et de G enotypage des G enomes, Qu ebec, 
QC, Canada). </p>

<p>Reverse Transcription PCR </p>

<p>For human colorectal tissues, reverse transcription 
was performed using AMV-RT (Roche, Laval, QC, 
Canada) 
according 
to 
the 
manufacturer's 
instructions while Q-PCR was performed by the 
RNomics Platform at the Universit e de Sherbrooke 
(QC, Canada). CTSB expression was normalized 
using the <rs type="software">qBase quantification Framework software</rs> 
with three reference genes: MRLP19,PUM1, and 
RPL13A. For cultured cells, total RNA was extracted 
with the RNeasy plus mini kit (Qiagen). Reverse 
transcription was performed using AMV-RT accord-
ing to the manufacturer's instructions and Q-PCR 
performed using a LightCycler 
1 Carousel-Based 
System (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Roche</rs>). Experiments were run and analyzed 
with the <rs id="software-0" type="software">LightCycler</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.0</rs> according to the 
manufacturer's recommendations (Roche). Synthesis 
of double-stranded DNA during PCR was monitored 
using SYBR Green I according to the manufacturer's 
recommendations (QuantiTect SYBR Green PCR Kit; 
Qiagen). Target expression was quantified relative to 
PDGB expression. Primer sequences and conditions 
are available upon request. </p>

<p>Plasmid Constructions and Lentiviruses Production </p>

<p>The lentiviral shRNA expression vector (pLenti6-
U6) was constructed [16] and shRNA oligonucleotides 
against human cathepsin B were designed according 
to Ambion guidelines (technical bulletin #506). 
siRNA sequences were 5 
0 -GGATCACTGTGGAATG-
GAATC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(Cathepsin B) or 5 
0 -GAGCCATTAG-
GACGGTTAGAT-3 
0 (Scrambled) and TTCAAGAGA 
as loop sequence. The oligonucleotide-annealed 
products were subcloned into pLenti6-U6 between 
the BamHI and XhoI sites. Lentiviruses produced in 
293 T cells were used for infection according to 
Invitrogen recommendations (ViraPower Lentiviral 
Expression System). No induction of OAS1 gene 
expression was detected by Q-PCR analysis in the 
experiments involving lentiviruses infection (data 
not shown). OAS1 is a classic interferon target gene 
recommended as a key test for interferon induction 
before attributing a particular response to the targeted 
gene [17]. The full-length human p27 
Kip1 cDNA was 
subcloned after PCR amplification in expression 
vector pCDNA3.1. The HA tag was inserted in frame 
between a Kozak sequence and the N-terminal end by 
PCR using the following sequences: 5 
0 -TCA CTA GGA 
TCC ACC ATG TCA AAC GTG CGA G -3 
0 and 5 
0 -AGT 
GAT CTC GAG TTA CGG GAG GCT AGC ATA ATC 
AGG AAC ATC ATA CGT TTG ACG TCT TCT GAG 
GCC AGG CTT-3 
0 . PCR products were next ligated in 
BamHI/EcoRI-digested pCDNA3.1 vector. The p27 </p>

<p>Kip1 </p>

<p>mutants R58A, R152A, D96-100, and D189-198 were 
generated by site-directed mutagenesis and deletion 
mutagenesis using the following oligonucleotides, 
respectively: R58A: 5 
0 -GAA GAG GCG AGC CAG GCT 
AAG TGG AAT TTC-3 
0 ; 5 
0 -GAA ATT CCA CTT AGC 
CTG GCT CGC CTC TTC-3 
0 ; R152A: 5 
0 -TGC GCA GGA 
ATA CCA AAG CGA CCT GCA ACC-3 
0 ; 5 
0 -GCT TGC 
AGG TCG CTT TGC TAT TCC TGC-3 
0 ; D96-100: 5 
0 -
CCC CCG CGG CCC CCC GTC CCG GCG-3 
0 ; 5 
0 -CTC 
CTG CGC CGG CAC GGG GGG CCG-3 
0 ; D198-198 : 
5 
0 -TCA CTA GGA TCC ACC ATG TCA AAC GTC-3 
0 ; 5 
0 -
AGT GAT CTC GAG TTA GGG CGT CTG CTC CTC 
CAC AGA-3 
0 . PCR products were next digested and 
ligated in BamHI/EcoRI-digested PCDNA3.1 vector. </p>

<p>Western Blot Analysis </p>

<p>Cells were washed with ice-cold PBS and lysed in 
Laemmli sodium dodecyl sulfate-sample buffer 
(90 mM Tris-HCl [pH 6.8], 2.5% sodium dodecyl 
sulfate, 15% glycerol). Samples were then boiled, 
sonicated, and protein concentrations were deter-
mined using the bicinchoninic acid (BCA) assay 
(Fisher Healthcare, Houston, TX) with bovine serum 
albumin as standard. b-mercaptoethanol and bromo-
phenol blue were then added to a final concentration 
of 1% and 0.005%, respectively. Proteins (5-50 mg) 
were separated by SDS-PAGE in 7.5% or 10% gels and 
were detected immunologically following electro-
transfer onto PVDF membranes (PerkinElmer, Wood-
bridge, ON, Canada). PVDF membranes were stained 
with Ponceau Red to assure a correct transfer of 
proteins and molecular weight markers (Bio-Rad, 
Mississauga, ON, Canada). Membranes were blocked 
in PBS containing 5% powdered milk and 0.05% 
Tween 20 for 1 h at 258C. Membranes were then 
incubated overnight at 48C with primary antibodies 
in blocking solution and thereafter with horseradish 
peroxidase or alkaline phosphatase-conjugated IgG 
for 1 h. Blots were visualized using the Amersham ECL 
system (Amersham-Pharmacia Biotech) or Millipore 
Immobilon AP substrate (Millipore, Etobicoke, ON, 
Canada). </p>

<p>Expression of Extracellular Cathepsin B Protein </p>

<p>For culture medium analysis, subconfluent CRC 
cells were serum-deprived during 24 h. Medium was 
collected and centrifuged 5 min at 4 500g to remove 
non-adherent cells and possible cellular debris. 
Thereafter, 4 mL of the medium was collected and 
concentrated through an Amicon(r) Ultra-10 kDa 
centrifugal filter unit (Millipore) after which Laemmli 
buffer was added to the retentate and boiled for 5 min. 
Cells were lysed in Laemmli sodium dodecyl sulfate-
sample buffer and samples subsequently boiled and 
sonicated. Protein concentration in cell lysates was 
determined using the bicinchoninic acid (BCA) assay. 
Volumes of culture media proportional to the 
intracellular protein concentration were separated 
on 10% SDS-PAGE gels for Western blot analysis. </p>

<p>CATHEPSIN B PROMOTES COLORECTAL CANCER PROGRESSION </p>



<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Cathepsin B Activity Assay </p>

<p>Purified human cathepsin B (Calbiochem) was 
activated by incubation at 378C with 5 mM DTT in 
50 mM Tris (pH 6.1). The activity of cathepsin B was 
then measured in presence or absence of 10 mM Ca074 
using the Cathepsin B Activity Fluorometric Assay Kit 
from BioVision according to the manufacturer's 
instructions (BioVision, Milpitas, CA). Subconfluent 
HT29 and HEK293 cells were incubated with 10 mM 
Ca074 for 12 h. Cells were then washed twice with 
PBS, lysed in cell lysis buffer provided in the assay kit 
and the resulting activity measured according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>Cell Proliferation Assays </p>

<p>Cell populations were plated for growth assay in 6-
well plates at a concentration of 2 Â 10 
5 (HT-29) or 
1.2 Â 10 
5 (DLD1) cells/well in 2% FCS-containing 
medium. Proliferation was measured during 7-8 d 
using a Cell particle counter. </p>

<p>Soft Agarose </p>

<p>DMEM 2X medium without phenol red was 
prepared from powder (Wisent) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. DMEM (DLD1 and 
SW480) and McCoy5A (HT-29) media were subse-
quently supplemented with 20% FCS, 8 mM gluta-
mine, 100 U/mL penicillin, 100 mg/mL streptomycin 
(Invitrogen), and 40 mM HEPES. Pre-warmed media 
were mixed 1:1 with autoclaved 1.4% agarose type VII 
maintained at %428C, and 6-well dishes were pre-
coated with 1 mL/well. Cells were added to the 
medium-agarose mix at a concentration of 5 Â 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>(HT-29), 3 Â 10 
4 (DLD1), and 7.5 Â 10 
3 cells/mL 
(SW480), and seeded at 1.5 mL/well. Plates were 
allowed to solidify under the hood and then placed 
at 378C and 5% CO 2 . Fresh media supplemented with 
10% FCS were added on the surface of the agarose 
every 1-2 d. After 2-3 wk, colonies were stained by 
adding 500 mL of PBS containing 0.5 mg/mL MTT on 
the surface of the agarose and incubated for 2 h at 
378C and 5% CO 2 . Images were acquired using an 
AlphaImager camera (Alpha Innotech Corporation) 
and colonies counted using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. </p>

<p>Invasion Assays </p>

<p>Invasion assays were conducted using BD Matrigel-
(tm) Invasion Chamber 24-well plates 8.0 micron 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, 
plates were thawed at room temperature for 30 min 
after which Matrigel was humidified with serum-free 
culture medium for at least 2 h at 378C and 5% CO 2 . 
Thereafter, 3 Â 10 
4 HT29 cells, 1 Â 10 
4 DLD-1 cells, or 
4 Â 10 
4 SW480 cells in serum-free medium were 
seeded into the upper chamber while culture medium 
containing 20% FCS was placed into the lower 
chamber as chemoattractant. Cells were allowed to 
migrate for the next 48 h in the presence of 2 mM </p>

<p>hydroxyurea in both chambers to prevent HT29 and 
DLD1 proliferation. For SW480 cells, hydroxyurea 
was not added since these cells are particularly 
sensitive to this compound and do not proliferate 
significantly within 48 h under these conditions. 
Non-migrating cells were removed with two cotton 
swabs, while migrating cells were fixed for 2 min with 
methanol and stained with DAPI for manual counting 
under the microscope. The number of invading cells 
was counted in seven fields per chamber. </p>

<p>Xenograft Assays in Mice </p>

<p>A total of 1 Â 10 
6 cells suspended in 100 mL McCoy 
5 A medium were injected into the dorsal subcutane-
ous tissue of 6-wk-old female CD1 nu/nu mice. Mice 
were sacrificed after 23 d post-injection. Tumors were 
excised, weighed, and lysed in RIPA buffer. </p>

<p>Experimental Tail Vein Assays in Mice </p>

<p>The tail-vein of 5-wk-old female Fox Chase SCID 
mice was injected with 10 
6 cells suspended in 100 mL 
McCoy 5 A medium. Mice were sacrificed after 28 d 
post-injection. Lungs were maintained in Bouin's 
fixative for 24 h before visualization of surface-visible 
metastases. </p>

<p>p27 
Kip1 Cleavage by Cathepsin B </p>

<p>293T cells were transfected by Lipofectamine 
(Invitrogen) with 3 mg/60 mm Petri dish of each 
expression vectors encoding for HA-tagged wild-
type p27 
Kip1 or mutants described above. Thirty-six 
hours after transfection, cells were washed twice with 
ice-cold PBS then lysed in Triton lysis buffer. Protein 
concentrations were determined using the BCA assay. 
For the reaction step, 7.5 mg of each cellular extract 
was incubated with reaction buffer containing 50 mM 
Tris-HCl (pH 6.0), 5 mM DTT, and 300 ng of purified 
human cathepsin B (Calbiochem) at 378C. After 
different time points, 4X Laemmli buffer was added 
to the samples for gel analysis. </p>

<p>Confocal Microscopy </p>

<p>Cells grown on glass coverslips were fixed for 
15 min at room temperature with 3.7% paraformal-
dehyde, permeabilized for 15 min with 0.1% Triton X-
100/PBS, and then blocked for 1 h with 2% BSA/PBS. 
To visualize lysosomes, cells were incubated for 1 h at 
378C with LysoTracker Red probe (DN99, Invitrogen). 
Cells were incubated overnight at 48C with anti-
cathepsin B antibodies (AF-953, R&amp;D systems). 
Cathepsin B was visualized with donkey anti-goat 
AlexaFluor 
1 488 (Invitrogen). For double p27 
Kip1 -
cathepsin B immunofluorescence, cells were incubat-
ed overnight at 48C with anti-p27 
Kip1 (C-19, Santa 
Cruz) and anti-cathepsin B. Cathepsin B and p27 </p>

<p>Kip1   were visualized using donkey anti-goat AlexaFluor 
594 and chicken anti-rabbit AlexaFluor </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>488 (Invi-
trogen), respectively. In double immunofluorescence 
experiments, single staining of each protein was </p>



<p>BIAN ET AL. </p>

<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>performed to ensure nonoverlapping fluorescence. 
Images were acquired on a Zeiss Axio Observer 
LSM700 confocal microscope with an x63 oil-immer-
sion objective (N.A. 1.4, Carl Zeiss Canada). Confocal 
microscope settings were adjusted to produce the 
optimum signal/noise ratio. The sequential mode was 
used in image acquisition to avoid any interference 
from overlapping fluorescence. Fluorescence analysis 
was performed using <rs id="software-4" type="software">Zen Black edition software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Carl Zeiss</rs>). </p>

<p>Subcellular Fractionation (Differential Centrifugations) </p>

<p>Cells were washed twice with ice-cold PBS and 
scraped in cell fractionation buffer: 50 mM Tris (pH 
7.5), 5 mM MgCl 2 , 25 mM KCl, 250 mM sucrose, 
supplemented with protease inhibitors (0.1 mM phe-
nylmethylsulfonyl fluoride [PMSF], 10 mg/mL leupep-
tin, 1 mg/mL pepstatin, 10 mg/mL aprotinin). Cell 
membranes were disrupted through a 25 G syringe 
(five strokes). Crude cellular extracts were centrifuged 
at 500g for 5 min. The pellet containing nuclei was 
homogenized in fractionation buffer, washed, and 
lysed by addition of 4X Laemmli buffer. After 
centrifugation of the supernatant at 20 000g for 
15 min, the resulting pellet containing plasma mem-
brane, mitochondria, lysosomes, and peroxisomes 
was washed and homogenized in fractionation buffer 
and lysed by addition of 4X Laemmli buffer. The 
20 000g supernatant was then centrifuged at 105 000g 
for 60 min. The pellet containing microsomes was 
homogenized in fractionation buffer and lysed by 
addition of 4X Laemmli buffer. The remaining final 
supernatant corresponding to the cytosolic fraction 
was lysed by addition of 4X Laemmli buffer. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Densitometric analyses were performed using Im-
ageJ software. Results shown in the graphs were 
analyzed by the paired Student's t-test or the 
Wilcoxon matched ranks t-test depending on the 
normality of sample distribution. Data are presented 
as means AE SEM. Statistical significance was set at 
P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>mRNA and Activated Levels of Cathepsin B Are Increased 
in Adenomas and in Colorectal Tumors of All Stages </p>

<p>Cathepsin B expression was analyzed at both the 
mRNA and protein levels in a series of human paired 
specimens at various tumor stages. As shown in 
Figure 1A, increased transcript levels of cathepsin B 
were observed in colorectal tumors, regardless of 
tumor stage, including in adenomas. Of note, 
increased cathepsin B expression was more promi-
nent in tumors exhibiting APC mutations. By 
contrast, there did not appear to be a significant 
difference relative to KRAS mutations (Figure 1B). To 
establish whether these increased mRNA levels could </p>

<p>be correlated with increased cathepsin B protein levels 
and more importantly with increased activity, expres-
sion of the active processed forms of the protease (25 
and 30 kDa) was analyzed by Western blot. Both pro-
cathepsin B and active cathepsin B were also increased 
in colorectal tumors compared to normal tissues 
(Figure 1C and D). These data hence suggest that 
increased transcription contributes to a greater 
expression of active cathepsin B in CRC. </p>

<p>Extracellular Cathepsin B Contributes to Invasiveness of 
Human CRC Cells but is Dispensable for Their Growth in 
Soft Agar </p>

<p>Cathepsin B protein levels were next examined in 
lysates obtained from various human CRC cell lines. 
As shown in Figure 2A, the proactive and catalytically 
active processed forms of cathepsin B were detected at 
various levels in CRC cell lines. Selected cathepsin B 
presence was also confirmed in conditioned culture 
medium of CRC cells, again at various levels 
(Figure 2A, lower panel). However, while the pro-
form of cathepsin B was readily observed in condi-
tioned culture medium of all CRC cells, the catalyti-
cally-active processed forms of cathepsin B were not 
detected in Western blot analyses. Additionally, using 
a fluorescence-based enzymatic assay, no cathepsin B 
enzyme activity was detected in conditioned medi-
um. Since the pro-protease form might be activated 
under acidic pH conditions (peri-or extracellular) and 
by extracellular components of the extracellular 
matrix, the impact of extracellular inhibition of 
cathepsin B activation on CRC cell invasion was 
verified using Biocoat Matrigel chambers. HT-29, 
DLD1, and SW480 CRC cell lines secreting different 
levels of pro-cathepsin B (Figure 2A) were tested. 
Experiments were performed using the highly selec-
tive and non-permeant inhibitor Ca074 to reduce 
extracellular cathepsin B activity. At 10 mM, Ca074 
produced a &gt;99% inhibition of recombinant cathep-
sin B levels while barely reducing intracellular 
cathepsin B, that is, 5-8%, even upon 12 h exposure 
to the inhibitor (data not shown). Of note, treatment 
with 10 mM Ca074 significantly inhibited Matrigel 
invasion by approximately 45-60% in HT29, DLD1, 
and SW480 CRC cell lines (Figure 2B). By contrast, 
treatment with Ca074 had no significant effect on 
their capacity to form colonies in soft agarose 
(Figure 2C). </p>

<p>Cathepsin B Silencing in Human CRC Cells Inhibits 
Growth in Soft Agar and Invasion Capacity </p>

<p>Recombinant lentiviruses encoding anti-cathepsin B 
short hairpin RNA (shRNA) were developed in order to 
stably suppress cathepsin B expression in CRC cells. As 
shown in Figure 3A, intracellular cathepsin B mRNA 
and protein levels were decreased in HT29 and DLD1 
cells in comparison to a control shRNA which had no 
effect. Reduction of cathepsin B expression modestly 
slowed the proliferation rate of HT29 and DLD1 </p>

<p>CATHEPSIN B PROMOTES COLORECTAL CANCER PROGRESSION </p>



<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Figure 1. Cathepsin B expression is increased in adenomas and in 
colorectal cancers of all stages. (A) Relative CTSB mRNA levels were 
determined by Q-PCR in human advanced adenomas and adenocarci-
nomas compared to the paired adjacent healthy tissue. Data presented 
are the means AE SEM of 7 to 20 tissue samples per stage. Significantly 
different at *P &lt; 0.05 (Student's t-test); **P &lt; 0.005 (Student's t-test). 
(B) Correlation of induction levels of CTSB transcripts with the presence 
of KRAS or APC mutations. The induction of CTSB transcripts was 
analyzed in 15-20 tumors in terms of KRAS and APC mutation status. 
Data presented are the means AE SEM. Significantly different at 
*P &lt; 0.05 (Student's t-test). (C) Representative immunoblot analysis </p>

<p>of cathepsin B protein (CTSB) performed on protein extracts from eight 
paired resection margins and tumor specimens. Tubulin expression is 
shown as a control of protein loading. (D)Western blot analysis of 
cathepsin B protein expression in a series of 50 paired specimens 
(resection margins and primary tumors). Protein levels of cathepsin B 
pro-form and active forms were normalized to the intensity of b-actin 
staining and to a reference sample, resulting in a dimensionless 
value. Amounts of normalized cathepsin B proteins in tumor tissues 
relative to their matched normal samples were analyzed by paired 
Student's t-test. Significantly different at *P 0.05, **P 0.005, and 
****P 0.0005. </p>



<p>BIAN ET AL. </p>

<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Figure 2. Extracellular cathepsin B contributes to invasiveness of 
human CRC cells but is dispensable for their growth in soft agar. (A) CRC 
cell lines were serum-deprived during 24 h and then lysed in Laemmli 
buffer and analyzed by Western blotting with specific antibodies against 
cathepsin B (CTSB) and b-tubulin. Four milliliter of culture medium from 
each cell line was concentrated and also analyzed by Western blotting 
for the expression of extracellular cathepsin B. (B) HT29, DLD1, and 
SW480 seeded in Matrigel-coated Transwells were treated with DMSO 
or Ca074 (10 mM) during 48 h. Thereafter, cells were fixed and stained </p>

<p>with DAPI solution for assessment of their capacity to invade Matrigel. 
The experiments were performed in triplicate and the number of control 
cells treated with DMSO which had migrated was set at 1. Significantly 
different at *P 0.05 and **P 0.005 (Student's t-test). (C) HT29, 
DLD1, and SW480 were cultured in soft agarose in the presence or 
absence of 10 mM Ca074 for 2-3 wk prior to MTT staining. The number 
of colonies was determined using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. Results are the 
means AE SEM of at least three independent experiments. ns: not 
significant (Student's t-test). </p>

<p>CATHEPSIN B PROMOTES COLORECTAL CANCER PROGRESSION </p>



<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Figure 3. Cathepsin B silencing in human CRC cells inhibits growth 
in soft agar and invasion capacity. (A) HT29 and DLD1 cells were stably 
infected with lentiviruses encoding for a control shRNA (scrambled 
sequence, shSCR) or encoding cathepsin B-specific shRNAs (shCTSB). 
Stable cell populations were thereafter lysed and RNA isolated to 
determine CTSB or PBGD gene expression by Q-PCR. The relative level 
of CTSB was normalized to the corresponding PBGD mRNA level. Cell 
populations were also lysed and protein lysates were analyzed by 
Western blotting for cathepsin B and b-actin expression. (B) HT29 and 
DLD1 cells expressing either shSCR or shCTSB were seeded in a 6-well 
plate at 2 Â 10 
5 (HT-29) and 1.2 Â 10 
5 (DLD1) cells per well. Cells were </p>

<p>harvested and counted after different times. (C) HT29 and DLD1 cells 
were cultured in soft agarose before MTT staining. The number of 
colonies was determined using ImageJ software. Results are the 
means AE SEM of at least three independent experiments. (D) HT29 and 
DLD1 cell populations were seeded in Matrigel-coated Transwells and 
cultured during 48 h. Thereafter, cells were fixed and stained with DAPI 
solution for assessment of their capacity to invade Matrigel. The 
experiments were performed in triplicate and the number of control 
cells (shSCR) which had migrated was set at 1. For all experiments 
described above: *, significantly different from shSCR cells at P &lt; 0.05 
(Student's t-test). **P &lt; 0.005; ***P &lt; 0.001. </p>



<p>BIAN ET AL. </p>

<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>populations in 2D cell culture (Figure 3B). Conversely, 
cathepsin B silencing significantly reduced the ability 
of HT29 and DLD1 cells to form colonies in soft 
agarose (Figure 3C). This indicates that intracellular 
cathepsin B controls anchorage-independent growth 
of CRC cells given the absence of Ca074 effect 
(Figure 2C). Moreover, cathepsin B silencing also 
reduced the number of invading HT29 and DLD1 cells 
to a similar extent as Ca074 treatment (Figure 3D vs. 
Figure 2B). </p>

<p>Cathepsin B Silencing in Human CRC Cells Inhibits 
Tumorigenicity and Metastasis in Immunodeficient Mice </p>

<p>Suppression of cathepsin B expression was found to 
significantly attenuate the metastatic potential of 
CRC cells in vivo in experimental metastasis assays. 
Indeed, immunodeficient mice injected with control 
CRC cells into the tail vein showed extensive 
lung metastasis within 28 d, whereas cells expressing 
shRNA against cathepsin B exhibited reduced lung 
colonization (Figure 4A). Cathepsin B silencing also 
altered the capacity of CRC cells to form tumors in 
mice as assessed by subcutaneous xenograft assays. 
HT29 cells induced palpable tumors with a short 
latency period of 9 d after their injection while 
downregulation of cathepsin B expression in these 
cells severely impaired their capacity to grow as 
tumors (Figure 4B). 
Expression of factors reported to be involved in 
colorectal tumor growth was next verified in tumor 
lysates. As shown in Figure 4C, the expression and 
activated phosphorylated levels of ERK1/2 MAP 
Kinases and Akt in tumor lysates were not signifi-
cantly altered in tumors expressing or not cathepsin 
B. However, higher levels of the cell cycle inhibitor 
p27 
Kip1 were observed in cathepsin B-deficient tumors 
while p21 
Cip and p57 
Kip2 levels were not significantly 
affected. Of note, this increase in p27 
Kip1 expression 
observed in cathepsin B-deficient tumors was associ-
ated with significant lower cyclin B1 expression in 
most tumors (Figure 4C and D), suggesting reduced 
proliferative activity. These data thus suggest that 
cathepsin B silencing in CRC cells severely reduces 
their capacity to form tumors in vivo likely through 
the increased expression of p27 
Kip1 . </p>

<p>Cathepsin B Cleaves the Cell Cycle Inhibitor p27 </p>

<p>Kip1   In order to verify whether p27 
Kip1 is in fact a 
substrate for cathepsin B, both proteins were first 
overexpressed in 293 T cells and cells subsequently 
lysed 2 d later for Western blot analysis of their 
respective expression. As shown in Figure 5A, forced 
expression of cathepsin B in 293 T cells dose-depen-
dently reduced p27 
Kip1 protein levels. Next, to 
determine whether p27 
Kip1 could be degraded by 
cathepsin B in vitro, lysates from 293 T cells over-
expressing HA-tagged p27 
Kip1 were incubated with 
purified cathepsin B and analyzed by Western blot. 
Figure 5B and C shows that cathepsin B degraded </p>

<p>p27 
Kip1 in a time-dependent manner as visualized by 
the accumulation of three lower molecular mass species 
(26, 20, and 12 kDa) in addition to the full-length 
p27 
Kip1 protein (see arrows versus arrowhead). 
Cathepsin B is capable of endopeptidase, peptidyl-
dipeptidase, and carboxydipeptidase activities [18- 20]. Cathepsin B also possesses a basic amino acid in 
the catalytic subsite in position S2 enabling the 
protease to preferentially split its substrates after 
Arg-Arg or Lys-Arg or Arg-Lys sequences. At least five 
of these sequences can be found within the human 
p27 
Kip1 sequence (Figure 5D). Therefore, the first 
amino acid of these doublets was mutated into 
alanine to test whether it would affect the degrada-
tion by cathepsin B. Mutation of arginine 58 
(Figure 5E) and lysine 189 (Figure 5F) did not alter 
the cleavage profile of p27 
Kip1 by cathepsin B. 
Mutation of lysine 165 and arginine 194 also had 
no altering effect (not shown). On the other hand, 
mutation of arginine 152 into alanine markedly 
reduced the detection of the 20-kDa fragment 
(Figure 5E). 
In order to identify other cleavage sites, deletion 
mutants of p27 
Kip1 were generated by removal of 
different sequences of five to ten amino acids 
(Figure 5D). All of these mutants were expressed in 
293 T cells and lysates subsequently exposed to 
cathepsin B cleavage (data not shown). The lower 
fragment was not observed with the p27 D96-100 
mutant following cathepsin B cleavage, suggesting 
the presence of a cleavage site within this sequence 
(Figure 5E). This particular sequence contains a 
glycine, and cathepsin B endopeptidase specificity 
has been reported to be also guided by the presence of 
a glycine in position P3 
0 of the scissile bound [21]. Of 
note, the 12-and 20-kDa fragments were not observed 
when arginine 152 was mutated in alanine in the 
D96-100 mutant (Figure 5E). Moreover, with the 
p27D189-198 mutant, both the 12-and 20-kDa 
fragments were still detected (Figure 5F), although 
the modest shift-down of 1-2 kDa normally produced 
following cathepsin B cleavage of full-length p27 </p>

<p>Kip1 </p>

<p>was not observed (Figure 5F, lower less-exposed gel). 
Single point mutation of each amino acid in the 189-
198 sequence did not prevent the generation of the 
26-kDa fragment following cathepsin B treatment 
(Figure 5F for residue 189 as an example). This 
suggests that this 26-kDa fragment probably results 
from the exopeptidase activity of cathepsin B. 
The protein stability of wild-type p27 
Kip1 was then 
compared to that of the p27 
Kip1 R152A/D189-198 
mutant, which is more resistant to cathepsin B 
cleavage. 293T cells were transiently transfected 
with either wild-type p27 
Kip1 or p27 
Kip1 mutant and 
subsequently treated with cycloheximide to inhibit 
protein neosynthesis. Thereafter, cells were lysed at 
different time intervals in order to analyze protein 
expression levels of p27 
Kip1 forms. As shown in 
Figure 6A, following cycloheximide treatment, </p>

<p>CATHEPSIN B PROMOTES COLORECTAL CANCER PROGRESSION </p>



<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Figure 4. Cathepsin B silencing in human CRC cells inhibits 
tumorigenicity and metastasis in immunodeficient mice. (A) Represen-
tative digital images of mouse lungs 28 d after tail vein injection of 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>HT29 cells expressing either shScrambled (shSCR) or shCathepsin B 
(shCTSB). (B) HT29 cells expressing either shSCR or shCTSB were 
injected subcutaneously in immunodeficient mice and the growth of 
tumors (mm 
3 ) over time was measured. The results represent the mean 
tumor volume obtained from two independent experiments in which 
at least six mice were injected for each cell line. *, significantly different 
from shCTSB tumors at P &lt; 0.05 (Student's t-test). (C) Equal amounts </p>

<p>of whole cell lysates from tumors were analyzed by Western blotting 
for the expression of cathepsin B, cyclin B1, phosphorylated ERK1/2 
(pERK1/2), total ERK2, phosphorylated Akt (pAkt), p27 
Kip1 , p21, 
p57 
Kip2 , and b-actin. (D) Densitometric analysis of cathepsin B, 
p27 
Kip1 , and cyclin B1 was determined in each tumor (cells expressing 
shSCR and cells expressing shCTSB were injected in different flanks of 
the same mouse) using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. *, significantly different 
from shSCR tumors at P &lt; 0.05 (Wilcoxon matched-pairs signed-ranks 
t-test). </p>



<p>BIAN ET AL. </p>

<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Figure 5. Cathepsin B exhibits endo-and exopeptidase activity 
against p27 
Kip1 . The pcDNA3 vectors without or with the HA-
tagged wild-type p27 </p>

<p>Kip1 </p>

<p>cDNA were transiently co-transfected 
with 0, 150, 300, or 600 ng of the cDNA encoding cathepsin B in 
293T cells. After 48 h, lysates were analyzed by Western blotting for 
the expression of HA-27 
Kip1 , cathepsin B, and b-actin. (B and C) The 
cDNA encoding HA-tagged p27 
Kip1 was transfected transiently in 
293T cells. After 48 h, cells were lysed and 15 mg of protein lysate 
was incubated during 30 min (B) or during 1, 5, 10, 20, and 30 min 
(C) with purified human cathepsin B (300 ng) at 378C (pH 6.0). 
Proteins were then solubilized in Laemmli buffer and analyzed by </p>

<p>Western blotting for the expression of HA-27 
Kip1 and b-actin. 
(D) Amino acid sequence of human p27 
Kip1 ; putative cleavage sites 
of cathepsin B are indicated in bold and underlined. The sequence 
of amino acids deleted in each p27 
Kip1 deletion mutant generated is 
highlighted in grey. (E and F) The cDNA encoding HA-tagged 
p27 
Kip1 and indicated mutants were transfected transiently in 293T 
cells. After 48 h, cells were lysed and 7.5 mg of protein lysates were 
incubated during 30 min with purified human cathepsin B (300 ng) 
at 378C (pH 6.0). Proteins were then solubilized in Laemmli buffer 
and analyzed by Western blotting for the expression of HA-27 
Kip1 , 
cathepsin B, and b-actin. </p>

<p>CATHEPSIN B PROMOTES COLORECTAL CANCER PROGRESSION </p>



<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Figure 6. Cathepsin B reduces p27 
Kip1 stability. (A) The cDNA 
encoding HA-tagged wild-type p27 
Kip1 and R152A/496-100 mutant 
were transiently transfected in 293T cells. Twenty-four hours following 
transfection, cells were treated with cycloheximide (CHX, 30 mg/mL) and 
harvested after 0, 2, 6, 8, or 10 h. Cells were processed and lysed at the 
same time. Expression of HA-27 
Kip1 proteins and b-actin was analyzed 
by Western blotting. Representative Western blot analysis is shown in 
upper panel. The graph illustrates the densitometric analysis of data </p>

<p>from three independent experiments. HA-p27 
Kip1 expression at 0 h of 
cycloheximide was set at 100%. Relative HA-p27 
Kip1 protein levels were 
calculated using b-actin as reference. (B) The pcDNA3 vectors without or 
with the cDNA encoding HA-tagged wild-type p27 
Kip1 or HA-tagged 
R152A/496-100 mutant were transiently co-transfected with 0, 150, 
300, or 600 ng of the cDNA encoding cathepsin B in 293T cells. After 
48 h, protein lysates were analyzed by Western blotting for the 
expression of HA-27 </p>

<p>Kip1 </p>

<p>, cathepsin B, and b-actin. </p>



<p>BIAN ET AL. </p>

<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>protein levels of the p27 
Kip1 mutant decreased much 
more slowly than that of wild-type protein. Specifi-
cally, 10 h after cycloheximide addition, expression of 
p27 
Kip1 protein was clearly decreased while expres-
sion of the p27 
Kip1 mutant remained at control (time 
0) levels. Of note, forced expression of cathepsin B in 
293 T cells dose-dependently reduced the wild-type 
form of p27 
Kip1 protein levels while expression of 
p27 
Kip1 R152A/D189-198 mutant was only very 
slightly affected (Figure 6B). </p>

<p>Colocalization of Endogenous p27 
Kip1 With Cathepsin B 
Into Lysosomes </p>

<p>To confirm that p27 
Kip1 also interacts with cathep-
sin B in CRC cells, their respective putative colocal-
ization was examined by immunofluorescence 
confocal microscopy. As shown in Figure 7A, the 
anti-cathepsin B antibody confirmed the colocaliza-
tion of cathepsin B (in green) with the lysosomal 
acidotropic probe LysoTracker (in red). As expected, 
most of p27 
Kip1 staining (in green) was observed in the 
cell nucleus (Figure 7B). However, certain areas of 
colocalization were observed between endogenous 
p27 
Kip1 (in green) and cathepsin B (in red) (Figure 7B, 
asterisks). Moreover, Western blot analyses revealed 
the presence of p27 
Kip1 protein in lysosome-enriched 
fractions obtained from differential centrifugation of 
Caco-2/15 and SW480 cell lysates (Figure 7C and D). 
These lysosomal fractions were enriched in lysosome-
associated membrane protein 1 (LAMP1) and exhib-
ited very low or undetectable levels of the nuclear 
lamin B protein. Of note, p27 
Kip1 protein was mostly 
detected in the cytosolic fraction and not in the 
nuclear fraction contrary to its expected localization. 
Significant levels of cyclin E and Cdk2 were also found 
in the cytosolic fraction (Figure 7C). Since p27 </p>

<p>Kip1   along with cyclins and mitogen-activated protein 
kinases are proteins whose functions are spatially and 
temporally regulated and, therefore, are actively 
transported between the nucleus and cytoplasm, 
one could speculate that during the fractionation 
procedure, these proteins easily exit from the nucleus. 
On the other hand, cathepsin B silencing in CRC cells 
specifically enhanced p27 
Kip1 levels in lysosome-
enriched fractions (Figure 7D). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The most extensive literature to date regarding 
cathepsin B highlights a key role of this protease in the 
invasiveness and metastasis of various carcinoma 
cells [3,8,10-12]. The present findings demonstrate 
that cathepsin B has not only a role in facilitating CRC 
invasion and metastasis, but also in mediating early 
premalignant processes. Results herein show that 
cathepsin B promotes anchorage-independent CRC 
cell growth, which translates in vivo to enhanced 
tumor growth. In addition, cathepsin B was identified 
as a new protease capable of proteolytic cleavage of </p>

<p>the cell cycle inhibitor p27 
Kip1 . This is especially 
relevant since the loss of p27 
Kip1 expression has been 
strongly associated with aggressive tumor behavior 
and poor clinical outcome in CRC [22,23]. 
While many studies have been conducted on 
cathepsin B expression in CRC [8,13-15,24-26], the 
present study specifically analyzed the expression of 
this protease at both the mRNA and active protein 
levels as well as its putative association with muta-
tions in APC or KRAS. Results revealed increased 
cathepsin B mRNA and protein levels in colorectal 
tumors, irrespective of tumor stage. These data are 
reminiscent of the immunohistochemistry data re-
ported by Chan et al. [13] showing that cathepsin B 
protein was expressed in the vast majority of colon 
cancers analyzed (558 tumors), which was also 
independent of tumor stage. The present data also 
revealed that increased transcription of cathepsin B 
was associated with the presence of mutations in APC 
but not in KRAS, thus emphasizing the fact that 
cathepsin B gene expression is already deregulated in 
early stages of colorectal carcinoma. Indeed, most 
CRCs acquire loss-of-function mutations in both 
copies of the APC gene, resulting in inefficient 
breakdown of intracellular b-catenin and enhanced 
nuclear signaling [27]. Given the importance of the 
Wnt/APC/b-catenin pathway in human tumorigene-
sis initiation, the present data showing an association 
between cathepsin B expression and APC mutations 
are particularly noteworthy. Further studies will be of 
interest to determine whether this association is 
correlative or causative. Additional evidence stem-
ming from other studies with APC 
Min/+ mice nonethe-
less suggests the contribution of this protease in 
tumorigenesis with mutated APC. These mice are 
heterozygous for a germ-line mutation in the mouse 
homologue of the human APC gene and develop 
multiple adenomas in the intestine [28]. Cathepsin B 
was also found to be consistently overexpressed in 
these adenomatous polyps both at the mRNA and 
protein levels [12]. In addition, genetic ablation of 
cathepsin B resulted in suppression of tumor infiltrat-
ing pro-inflammatory cells and in attenuation of 
polyposis in these mice [29]. In a proteomic screening 
study, cathepsin B was also recently identified as one 
of the six upregulated proteins in the tumors of 
APC 
D580 mice [9]. Such observations again suggest 
that cathepsin B may be implicated early in the 
process of tumorigenesis. These results hence support 
a role for cathepsin B in APC-mutated tumors and 
lend credence to the possibility of cathepsin B being a 
therapeutic target for these cancers. 
In agreement with other studies that have shown 
that secretion of cathepsin B is increased in the 
extracellular environment of several types of cancer 
cells [7,11,30,31], results obtained herein in CRC cells 
in culture confirmed the presence of the pro-form of 
cathepsin B in conditioned culture medium of all CRC 
cells. However, the catalytically active processed </p>

<p>CATHEPSIN B PROMOTES COLORECTAL CANCER PROGRESSION </p>



<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Figure 7. Colocalization of p27 with cathepsin B in lysosomes. 
(A) Representative confocal microscopy images of Caco-2/15 CRC cells 
showing cathepsin B (in green), LysoTracker staining (in red), and DAPI 
(in blue). (B) Representative confocal microscopy images of Caco-2/15 
CRC cells showing cellular distribution of endogenous p27 </p>

<p>Kip1 </p>

<p>(in green) and cathepsin B (in red) in a double immunofluorescence 
experiment. Boxed region in the low-magnification image is enlarged 
on the right. The graph represents fluorescence profiles along the 
dashed white line showing areas of colocalization (white asterisks). 
(C) Caco-2/15 cell lysates were fractionated by differential centrifuga-
tion (see Material and Methods), and equal amounts of proteins from </p>

<p>each fraction were analyzed by Western blotting for the expression of 
p27 
Kip1 and cathepsin B. Expression of lysosomal (LAMP1), nuclear 
(lamin B), cytosolic (calpain 2), and nuclear/cytoplasm shuttling 
markers (cyclin E and CDK2) was analyzed to assess purity of 
subcellular fractions. (D) SW480 cells stably expressing either shSCR or 
shCTSB were harvested and lysates were fractionated by differential 
centrifugation (see Material and Methods). Equal amounts of proteins 
from each fraction were analyzed by Western blotting for the 
expression of p27 
Kip1 and cathepsin B. Expression of lysosomal 
(LAMP1), nuclear (lamin B), and cytosolic (calpain 2) markers was 
analyzed to assess purity of subcellular fractions. </p>



<p>BIAN ET AL. </p>

<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>forms of cathepsin B were not detected by Western 
blot analysis. In keeping with this finding, no 
cathepsin B enzyme activity was detected in the 
conditioned medium. This indicates that CRC cells 
massively secrete pro-cathepsin B but not the active 
forms of cathepsin B and is consistent with previous 
studies showing that overexpression of cathepsins is 
frequently accompanied by the secretion of pro-
cathepsins (reviewed in [32]). With regard to CRC, it 
has been reported that cathepsin B moves from the 
apical region of the cells to the basal plasma 
membranes, in parallel with malignant progression 
to late adenomas and early carcinomas. Prior studies 
using HCT116 human colorectal carcinoma cells have 
shown that trafficking of cathepsin B to caveolae and 
its subsequent secretion were regulated by active 
KRAS [7]. Outside of the cells, cathepsin B was 
moreover ideally positioned to degrade basal mem-
brane components [33,34] or to activate uPA and 
MMPs [7,35,36], hence promoting cancer cell inva-
sion and metastasis. Since pro-cathepsin B is catalyti-
cally inactive, the contribution of secreted cathepsin 
B to extracellular matrix degradation can, therefore, 
be questioned. Nevertheless, several studies have 
reported that extracellular components of the extra-
cellular matrix can facilitate the processing of 
cathepsins [19,37,38]. Furthermore, under acidic pH 
conditions, pro-cathepsins are effectively processed 
into catalytically mature proteases either autocatalyt-
ically [39,40] or by other proteases. Accordingly, 
inhibition of extracellular cathepsin B activity in the 
present study by the non-permeant inhibitor Ca074 
markedly attenuated CRC cell invasion through 
Matrigel suggesting that secreted pro-cathepsin B 
was in fact activated under such conditions. Cathep-
sin B silencing in these same CRC cells also reduced 
the number of invading cells to a similar extent as that 
observed with Ca074 in vitro, in addition to inhibit-
ing their metastatic properties in vivo. In keeping 
with these results, increased serum levels of cathepsin 
B have been found in patients with CRC [41]. Taken 
together, these results further support the notion that 
extracellular cathepsin B may play an important 
function in CRC invasion and metastasis. Of note, 
intraperitoneal administration of Ca074 was reported 
to reduce bone metastasis in a model of breast 
cancer [42], demonstrating the therapeutic potential 
of targeting extracellular cathepsin B activity. This 
metastasis suppression by Ca074 was maintained in a 
late treatment setting, pointing to a role for this 
protease in metastatic outgrowth. 
An additional finding of this study is the require-
ment of cathepsin B for anchorage-independent 
growth and tumorigenesis. Cathepsin B silencing in 
CRC cells inhibited their capacity to grow in soft agar 
and to form tumors in mice. One could speculate that 
intracellular cathepsin B possibly mediates these 
functions since Ca074 did not alter growth in soft 
agar. However, in vivo approaches targeting extracel-</p>

<p>lular active cathepsin B are nonetheless needed to 
clearly confirm such activity. Furthermore, investiga-
tion of the molecular mechanisms underlying the 
inhibitory effect of cathepsin B silencing on tumor 
growth revealed reduced levels of cyclin B1 and 
increased levels of p27 
Kip1 protein in cathepsin B-
deficient tumors. Cyclin B1 is the major controlling 
cyclin in the G 2 phase of the cell cycle and its 
expression may reflect the proliferative state of the 
tumor [43]. p27 
Kip1 is a cell cycle regulator which 
negatively inhibits cyclin-CDK complexes and acts as 
a key protein in the decision between proliferation 
and cell cycle exit. As cells progress toward S-phase, 
transcriptional regulation, translational control, and 
ubiquitin/proteasome-mediated degradation lead to a 
decline in p27 
Kip1 (reviewed in [44,45]). Moreover, 
increased proteasome-dependent degradation of 
p27 
Kip1 is particularly observed in aggressive colorec-
tal carcinomas and other cancers [23,46,47]. In 
keeping with this observation, the absence of 
p27 
Kip1 protein expression is a powerful negative 
prognostic 
marker 
in 
colorectal 
carcino-
mas [22,23,47]. For instance, homozygous p27 </p>

<p>Kip1   mutation was consistently found to increase the 
number of intestinal polyps in Apc mutant mice by 
five-to sixfold [48]. Herein, cathepsin B was also 
identified as a novel protease potentially involved in 
the regulation of p27 
Kip1 expression. Results show 
that, in vitro, this protease was able to specifically 
cleave the p27 
Kip1 protein. The observation that 
cathepsin B and p27 
Kip1 partially colocalized into 
the lysosomes suggests that some p27 
Kip1 cleavage 
occurred in lysosomes. Supporting this notion, 
mutations of cathepsin B cleavage sites increased 
p27 
Kip1 protein stability. Accordingly, endolysosomal 
degradation of p27 
Kip1 was also previously demon-
strated in Hela and NIH3T3 cells, contributing to the 
progression of their cell cycle [49]. This particular 
pathway of p27 degradation appears to be mediated 
by its interaction with the endosomal protein SNX6, a 
member of the sorting nexin family of vesicular 
trafficking regulator [49]. However, the molecular 
mechanisms regulating this SNX6-dependent p27 </p>

<p>Kip1   proteolytic pathway remain unknown. The present 
cell models cultured on a plastic substratum (2D 
culture) did not allow to consistently detect signifi-
cant modulation of total p27 
Kip1 protein expression 
following cathepsin B silencing (data not shown). In 
addition, Western blot analyses of p27 
Kip1 expression 
demonstrated that this cell cycle inhibitory protein 
was expressed at various levels in CRC cells without 
any correlation with intracellular cathepsin B expres-
sion (Supplementary Figure S1). This suggests that in 
cultured CRC cells and as previously reported in other 
cancer cell lines (reviewed in [46]), p27 
Kip1 protein 
expression may be regulated by multiple oncogenic 
pathways. By contrast, a decrease in p27 
Kip1 expres-
sion was observed after forced overexpression of 
cathepsin B in 293 T cells, although p27 
Kip1 fragments </p>

<p>CATHEPSIN B PROMOTES COLORECTAL CANCER PROGRESSION </p>



<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>could not be detected in cell lysates. One could 
speculate that once generated, these fragments are 
rapidly degraded in the lysosomes. However, a 
marked increase in p27 
Kip1 protein levels was found 
in cathepsin B-deficient colorectal tumors derived 
from mice suggesting that this lysosomal proteolytic 
pathway is likely to occur in the context of tumori-
genesis or 3D CRC cell culture. 
In conclusion, the present data demonstrate that 
cathepsin B plays a significant role in colorectal tumor 
development, invasion, and metastasis. Results sug-
gest that intracellular cathepsin B activity controls 
premalignant processes such as anchorage-indepen-
dent growth and tumor formation while extracellular 
cathepsin B regulates invasive properties of CRC cells. 
p27 
Kip1 is furthermore identified as a new molecular 
target of cathepsin B in CRC cells. Since p27 
Kip1 acts as 
a tumor suppressor, the impairment of its function 
may increase the tumoral properties of colorectal 
cells, as shown previously in APC 
Min/þ mice [48,50]. 
As such, cathepsin B may, therefore, represent a 
valuable target for colorectal tumor therapy. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Anne V ezina for technical 
assistance, Claude Asselin for critical reading of the 
manuscript, and Pierre Pothier for editing of the 
manuscript. N.R is a recipient of a Canadian Research 
Chair in Colorectal Cancer and Inflammatory 
Signalling. J.C. and F.B. are scholars from the Fonds 
de la Recherche en Sant e du Qu ebec. N.R., J.C., and 
F.B. are members of the FRQS-funded "Centre de 
Recherche du CHUS." </p>





<p>BIAN ET AL. </p>

<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>



<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION </p>

<p>Additional supporting information may be found in 
the online version of this article at the publisher's 
web-site. </p>

<p>CATHEPSIN B PROMOTES COLORECTAL CANCER PROGRESSION </p>



<p>Molecular Carcinogenesis </p>

</text></tei>