<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4667234" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Recent evidence has suggested that epithelial cancers including colorectal cancer (CRC) have driven by a small population 
of self-renewing, multi-potent cells termed cancer stem cells (CSCs) which could be responsible for recurrence of cancer. Aldehyde 
dehydrogenase 1 (ALDH1) activity has used as a functional stem cell biomarker to isolate CSCs in different cancers such as colorectal cancer. 
Objectives: The main aim of this research was to determine the utility of ALDH1 activity along with CD44 and EPCAM in identifying stem 
cell-like cells in human HT-29 colonic adenocarcinoma cell line. 
Materials and Methods: In this experimental study, colon CSCs biomarkers including CD44, EPCAM and ALDH1 in colonospheres and 
parent cells have analyzed by flow cytometry. The expression levels of stemness genes in spheroid and parental cells have investigated 
using SYBR Green real-time PCR. In addition, in vivo xenografts assay has performed to determine tumorigenic potential of tumor 
spheroid cells in nude mice. 
Results: According to results, over 92% of spheroids were CD44+/EpCAM+, while parent cells only have expressed 38% of CD44/EpCAM 
biomarkers (P &lt; 0.001). Controversially, ALDH activity was about 2-fold higher in the parent cells than spheroid cells (P &lt; 0.05). In 
comparison with the parental cells, expression levels of ''stemness'' genes, like Sox2, Oct4, Nanog, C-myc, and Klf4 have significantly 
increased in colonosphere cells (P &lt; 0.05). Further, administration of 2500 spheroids could be sufficient to initiate tumor growth in nude 
mice, while 1x106 of parental cells has needed to form tumor. 
Conclusions: For the first time, we have shown that colonospheres with low ALDH1 activity has indicated increased tumorigenic potential 
and stemness properties. So, it hasn't seemed that ALDH1 could become a useful biomarker to identify CSCs population in HT-29 cell line. </p>

<p>Keywords: Colorectal Cancer, Cancer Stem Cell, HT-29, ALDH, Biomarker </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, Iranian Journal of Cancer Prevention. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCom-
mercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial us-
ages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Increasing evidence has recently reported that malig-
nancies have originated from a small population of can-
cer cells termed cancer stem cells (CSCs), indicating main 
properties including self-renewal and pluripotency. CSCs 
have widely known to responsible for initiating and sus-
taining tumor growth in all cancers including CRC (1). Ac-
cording to several studies, CRC tumorigenic cell popula-
tion could mainly identified by the expression of specific 
cell surface biomarkers such as CD133 (Prominin-1) (2, 3), 
CD44 (4, 5), CD166 (ALCAM) (4, 6), CD24 (7), EpCAM (ESA) 
(4), CD29 (7), nuclear β catenin (7), Lgr5 (7), Oct-4, Sox-2, 
Nanog, Lin-28, Klf-4, C-myc (8-10). 
It has shown that ALDH 1 induced proliferation and dif-
ferentiation of stem cells through oxidizes of retinol to 
retinoic acid (11). High ALDH1 activity has used to define 
stem cell populations in large number of cancers includ-
ing human multiple myeloma, acute myeloid leukemia </p>

<p>(12), pancreatic cancer (13) and breast cancer (14). There-
fore, ALDH1 activity might be useful as a common bio-
marker for malignant stem cell populations (15). 
More recently, it has reported that ALDH-1 as a useful bio-
marker for colon cancer stem cells (5, 16). Recent studies 
have shown that implantation of only 25 ALDH1+ colon can-
cer cells in NOD/SCID mice lead to tumor xenografts. Fur-
ther isolation of colon cancer cells using a second marker 
(CD44 or CD133) has only modestly increased enrichment 
based on tumor-initiating ability (11). Therefore, ALDH1 has 
seemed to be a valuable biomarker for identifying and iso-
lating human colonic SC during CRC development. 
Based on existing evidence that cell lines have represented 
the tumors from which they have originally isolated (17, 18) 
and regarding the cumbersome accessibility to primary can-
cer cells isolated from patients, in this study we have select-
ed a colon adenocarcinoma cell line, HT-29, as a model. To </p>

<p>Khorrami S et al. </p>

<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2015;8(5):e3446 
 
www.ijcancerprevention.com </p>

<p>date, association of CSC markers such as CD44, EPCAM and 
CD24 have evaluated in HT-29 cell line however correlation 
between ALDH activity, as a novel biomarker in colon CSCs 
and tumorigenicity in this cell line have not investigated. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>In this study we have investigated stemness proper-
ties and colon CSCs markers in spheroid and parent 
cells of HT-29. Additionally in vivo xenografts assay has 
performed to evaluate tumorigenic potential of tumor 
spheroid cells. </p>

<p>3. Materials and Methods </p>

<p>3.1. Cell Line and Culture Conditions </p>

<p>In this experimental study, the human colonic adeno-
carcinoma cell line HT-29 (wild type, no: 300215) has pur-
chased from Iranian Biological Resource Center (IBRC). 
Cells have cultured in Dulbecco's modified eagle me-
dium: nutrient mixture F-12 (DMEM/F-12, 1:1, GIBCO, USA) 
supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, GIBCO, 
USA) and 1% penicillin/streptomycin (Invitrogen, USA) in 
a humidified incubator (Memert, Germany) at 37°C and 
5% CO 2 . Cells have suspended using trypsinization (0.25% 
trypsin/EDTA (GIBCO, USA) for 3 -5 minutes) </p>

<p>3.2. Colonosphere Formation </p>

<p>For colonosphere formation, single-cell suspensions 
have cultured at a density of 15,000 to 20,000 cells/ 
mL in ultra-low attachment 6 well plates (Getbiofil, UK) 
in serum-free medium containing DMEM/F-12, supple-
mented with 20 ng/mL EGF (Sigma, USA) , 10 ng/mL FGF 
(Millipore, USA) and 1% B27 (50X, Invitrogen, USA) (19). To 
determine the differentiation potential of spheroid cells, 
tumor spheres have cultivated without EGF and FGF-2 in 
the presence of 10% serum. </p>

<p>3.3. Extreme Limiting Dilution Analysis </p>

<p>Extreme limiting dilution analysis (<rs type="software">ELDA</rs>) has carried out 
to evaluate self-renewal capacity as previously explained by 
Hu and Smyth (20). Briefly, single cell suspension has ob-
tained from parent and spheroid cells have plated at con-
centration of 1000, 100, 10 cells and 1 cell per well in 0.2 ml 
of CSC medium in 96-well ultra-low attachment (Getbiofil, 
UK) and cultured for 7 days in a humidified incubator at 
37°C and 5% CO 2 . The number of wells containing of colono-
spheres has counted after 7 days. The frequency of sphere 
forming cells in a particular cell type has determined using 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">ELDA</rs> web tool at <rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://bioinf.wehi.edu.au/software/elda</rs>. </p>

<p>3.4. Evaluation of Surface Markers by Flow Cytometry </p>

<p>Single cell suspension from colonospheres and parent 
cells has stained according to standard protocol (19). 
Briefly, cells have detached by trypsin and re-suspended </p>

<p>in PBS containing 1% BSA for 10 minutes on ice. Subse-
quently cells have washed and stained with anti-human/ 
mouse CD44-APC (eBioscience, USA) and anti-human EP-
CAM-PE (Abcam, UK) for 20 minutes on ice. The cells have 
stained with rat IgG 2b isotype control APC (eBioscience, 
USA ) and mouse IgG 1 isotype control PE (Abcam, UK) 
have served as gating control. Flow-cytometry analysis 
was performed using FACS CantoII (BD, USA). </p>

<p>3.5. Measurement of Aldehyde Dehydrogenase 
(ALDH) Activity </p>

<p>Identification of ALDH+ cells have performed using the 
ALDEFLUOR kit (StemCell Technologies, Canada). To per-
form the assay, an aliquot of the activated substrate has 
added to the colonospheres and parent cells suspended 
in ALDEFLUOR Assay Buffer. An aliquot of this cell mixture 
has immediately transferred to a tube containing DEAB 
for the control. These mixtures have incubated for 30 -60 
minutes to allow conversion of the substrate to the fluo-
rescent product. ALDH + cells have identified by compar-
ing the fluorescence of test samples against background 
fluorescence from identical samples that have treated 
with the ALDH inhibitor diethylamino benzaldehyde 
(DEAB) by flow cytometry. </p>

<p>3.6. Real-Time PCR </p>

<p>Total RNA has extracted from the parent and colono-
sphere-derived cells using high pure RNA isolation kit 
(Roche, USA) according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. cDNA has synthesized by Sensiscript ® Reverse 
Transcription Kit (QIAGEN, USA) from total RNA and 
stored at -20°C until use. Quantitative reverse transcrip-
tase PCR has performed to quantify the expression of 
stemness genes including c-myc, Klf-4, Nanog, Oct-4, Sox-
2 using LightCycler FastStart ® DNA Master PLUS SYBR 
GreenI (Roche, USA) according to the manufacturer's 
protocol on Roche light cycler version 3.5 (Roche, USA) 
. As an internal control for the normalization of these 
genes, Hypoxanthine-guanine phosphor ribosyl transfer-
ase (HGPRT) have used. PCR amplification has conducted 
with the following conditions: 1 cycle pre-incubation at 
95°C for 10 minutes, followed by 40 cycles: denaturation 
for 10 seconds at 95°C, annealing for 10 seconds at 60°C 
or 61ºC, and extension for 10 seconds at 72°C. The primer 
sequences and specifications have summarized in (Table 
1). The relative amount of each mRNA has normalized to 
HGPRT. The fold-change from colonospheres relative to 
the control (parent) has calculated using 2-ΔΔCt method. 
Each sample has assayed in triplicate. </p>

<p>3.7. In Vivo Tumorigenicity </p>

<p>Tumorigenicity has determined by subcutaneous injec-
tion of single-cell suspensions from colonosphere and par-
ent cells in 6 to 8 week-old female C57BL/6 nude mice. Before 
injection, cells have prepared at 1:1 ratio of PBS: collagen (sig-</p>

<p>Khorrami S et al. </p>



<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2015;8(5):e3446 
www.ijcancerprevention.com </p>

<p>ma, USA) in a total volume of 100 µL. 1 ×10 3 , 2.5 × 10 3 and 5 ×10 3 
cells of colonospheres and 5 ×10 5 and 1 × 10 6 of parent cells 
have injected in nude mice There were 3 mice in each group. 
Mice have purchased from animal laboratory of Imam Kho-
meini Hospital and maintained under standard conditions 
according to the guidelines of the animal care committee 
of cancer institute. Animal studies have approved by the 
animal ethics committee from Tarbiat Modares university. 
When tumor size has reached ~1 cm 3 , usually 7 -9 weeks 
after injection, mice have killed and tumors samples have 
obtained for pathology analysis and in vitro culture. Tumor 
volume has calculated by the following formula: </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(Short diameter) 2 × </p>

<p>(long diameter) 
2 </p>

<p>3.8. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Data have presented as means ± standard error of the 
mean (SEM). Statistical analysis has performed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Graph-
Pad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc</rs>, USA). The unpaired 
t-test has used to analyze the median value of expression be-
tween the groups. Statistical significance has determined at 
P &lt; 0.05. All tests have performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1. Generation and Characterization of Colono-
spheres </p>

<p>In this study, we have found that human HT-29 colonic 
adenocarcinoma cells could form spheroid colonies in a se-
rum-free medium containing. To investigate the capability 
of colon spheres differentiation, these cells have cultivated 
in 10% FBS medium rather than EGF and FGF-2. In present se-
rum, spherical undifferentiated cells have attached to the 
plate, and differentiated into adherent cells with epithelial 
cell morphology (Figure 1). In serum free condition, the 
expression levels of EpCAM and CD44 were significantly 
higher in spheroid than parent cells (P &lt; 0.001) (Figure 2). 
The results have demonstrated that 92.3 ± 3.6% of these tu-</p>

<p>mor spheroid cells were CD44+/EpCAM+, while parent cells 
only have expressed 38.4 ± 1.6% of CD44+/EpCAM+ markers. 
We have measured ALDH1 activity in colonospheres and 
parent cells-derived colonic HT-29 cell line. Interestingly, 
we have found that HT29 cells have exhibited substantial-
ly high levels of ALDH activity in the parent fractions in 
compared with the spheroid fractions. ALDH activity was 
16.9 ± 1.2 in spheroid cells in comparison with 34.6 ± 2.3 in 
parental cells (P &lt; 0.05) (Figure 3). 
We have evaluated the frequency of sphere-forming cells 
by doing an extreme limiting dilution analysis (<rs type="software">ELDA</rs>) for 
spheroid and parent-derived HT-29 cells. The results have 
indicated that the frequency of spheroid formation in 
cell line -derived colonospheres were 6.4 fold higher than 
-derived the parent cells (P &lt; 0.005) (Table 2). The findings 
have suggested that colonospheres have formed by the co-
lon cancer cell have enriched population of CSCs. </p>

<p>4.2. Stem-Like Features of Colonospheres In Vitro </p>

<p>To study the molecular features of colon CSCs, the ex-
pression of genes has involved in stem cell related path-
ways has investigated by real-time PCR in colonospere 
and parental cells, as shown in (Figure 4). 
In comparison with the parental cells, expression level of 
''stemness'' genes, like Sox2, Oct4, Nanog, C-myc, and Klf4 
have significantly increased in colonosphere cells (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>4.3. Colonospheres Can Generate Tumors Upon Xe-
notransplantation </p>

<p>To determine tumorigenicity in colonosphere and paren-
tal cells in vivo, nude mice have subcutaneously injected 
with either colonosphere or parent cells. The results have 
shown the ability of spheroid cells in tumor formation 
was significantly higher in comparison with parental cells 
(Figure 5A). The data have shown that as few as 2500 spher-
oid cells were sufficient to induce tumor growth, whereas 
1 × 10 6 of parental cells capable to form tumor (Table 3). 
Histological analyses have shown that tumors-induced of 
both xenografts have derived from spheroid and parental 
cells had the same character of original tumor (Figure 5B). </p>

<p>Table 1. The Primer Sequences and PCR Conditions </p>

<p>Gene Name 
Primer Sequences 
Annealing Temperature 
Product Length </p>

<p>c-myc 
F: 5'-AGCGACTCTGAGGAGGAAC-3' 
60ºC 
184 bp 
R: 5'-CTGCGTAGTTGTGCTGATG-3' </p>

<p>Sox-2 
F:5'-GGACTGAGAGAAAGAAGAGGAG-3' 
61ºC 
197 bp 
R: 5'-GAAAATCAGGCGAAGAATAAT-3' </p>

<p>Oct-4 
F: 5'-CGCCGTATGAGTTCTGTG-3' 
61ºC 
284 bp 
R: 5'-GGTGATCCTCTTCTGCTTC-3' </p>

<p>Nanog 
F: 5'-GCTAAGGACAACATT GATAGAAG-3' 
60ºC 
127 bp 
R: 5'-CTTCATCACCAATTCGTACTTG-3' </p>

<p>Klf-4 
F: 5'-CCCAATTACCCATCCTTCC-3' 
60ºC 
303 bp 
R: 5'-GTGCCTGGTCAGTTCATC-3' </p>

<p>HGPRT 
F: 5'-CCTGGCGTCGTGATTATGG-3' 
60ºC 
125 bp 
R: 5'-TCAGTCCTGTCCATAATTAGTCC-3' </p>

<p>Khorrami S et al. </p>

<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2015;8(5):e3446 
 
www.ijcancerprevention.com </p>

<p>Figure 1. Generation Spheroid Cells From HT-29 Cell Line </p>

<p>(A-D): Representative photographs have been showing colon cancer cells expanded in vitro as undifferentiated spheres in serum-free medium contain-
ing EGF and FGF-2. Pictures have shown a typical colon sphere observed by the inverted phase contrast microscope. (e): Microscopically analysis of colon 
cancer spheres have cultivated in differentiation conditions (growth factors removal and addition of 10% FBS) for 7 days (200 ×). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Characterization of Colon CSCs in HT-29 Cell Line </p>

<p>Isotype control 
Parental cells 
Spheroid cells </p>

<p>EPCAM-PE </p>

<p>CD44-APC </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 
10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 
10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 </p>

<p>0.05% 
38.4% 
92.3% </p>

<p>Representative scattered plots of flow cytometry analyses have been showing CD44 and EPCAM positive cells in spheroid and parental cells. </p>

<p>Khorrami S et al. </p>



<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2015;8(5):e3446 
www.ijcancerprevention.com </p>

<p>ALDH-FITC </p>

<p>BAAA+DEAB </p>

<p>+BAAA 
+BAAA </p>

<p>Partental cells 
Spheroid sells </p>

<p>SSC </p>

<p>1K </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1K </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1K </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 
10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 
10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Representative Flow Cytometry Plots for the Analysis of ALDH Enzymatic Activity in Spheroid and Parental Cells in the Presence of ALDH Sub-
strate (BAAA) (Left and Middle Plots, Respectively) and in the Parental Cells in the Presence of ALDH Enzyme Inhibitor Diethylaminobenzaldehyde (DEAB) 
(Right Plot) </p>

<p>Table 2. Extreme Limiting Dilution Analysis of Colonospheres Forming Frequency, by Parent and Colonospheres-Derived Cells of 
HT-29 a 
Number of Cells/Well 
Number of Wells Plated 
Number of Wells Showing Colonospheres 
Colonospheres-Derived Cell 
Parent 
1000 
24 
24 
24 
100 
24 
24 
22 
10 
24 
19 
8 
1 
24 
9 
2 
Sphere forming frequency (95% CI) 
1.5 (1.3 -1.7) 
1.32 (1.20 -1.51) </p>

<p>a P value &lt; 0.005. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Stemness Genes Expression of Spheroid and Parental Cells Have Assessed by Real-Time PCR </p>

<p>Parental </p>

<p>Spheroid 
5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
Parental 
Spheroid </p>

<p>Parental 
Spheroid 
Parental 
Spheroid 
Parental 
Spheroid </p>

<p>c-Myc </p>

<p>Nanog 
0ct4 
sox2 </p>

<p>Parental 
Spheroid 
Kif4 
Gene expression level </p>

<p>Gene expression level 
Gene expression level 
Gene expression level </p>

<p>Gene expression level </p>

<p>Spheroid cells have shown higher expression of stemness genes, in comparison with parental cells (P &lt; 0.05). Results have presented as means ± SEM. </p>

<p>Khorrami S et al. </p>

<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2015;8(5):e3446 
 
www.ijcancerprevention.com </p>

<p>Table 3. Tumorigenicity of Colonospheres and Parental Cells From HT-29 Cell Lines in Nude Mice </p>

<p>Cell Type/Cell Number Injected 
Tumor Incidence 
Engraftment-Derived Spheres </p>

<p>Colonospheres </p>

<p>1 × 10 3 
0/3 
-</p>

<p>2.5 × 10 3 
3/3 
Yes </p>

<p>5 × 10 3 
3/3 
Yes </p>

<p>Parental cells </p>

<p>5 × 10 5 
0/3 
-</p>

<p>1 × 10 6 
3/3 
Yes </p>

<p>Figure 5. Tumorigenicity of Spheroid Cells In Vivo </p>

<p>(A) The photograph of a representative mouse has taken at 7 weeks after cell transplantation (B) Haematoxylin-eosin analysis of mouse xenografts have 
generated by spheres expanded in culture (400 ×). (C) Haematoxylin-eosin analysis of mouse xenografts have generated by parental cells expanded in 
culture (400 ×) </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>Previous studies have demonstrated that in addition 
to primary tumors, established cancer cell lines might 
be contained a subpopulation of cells possessing CSCs 
properties (21, 22). In this research, we have identified 
and characterized CSCs in the colorectal cancer-derived 
cell line HT-29 through investigation of sphere formation 
and surface biomarkers. Studies have shown that under 
serum-free defined media, CSCs had ability to form float-
ing spheroids (19). In consistent with previous observa-
tion, we have shown that in serum-free conditions HT-29 
cell line could form spheroid colonies (colonospheres) 
and following exposure to 10% FBS differentiate into 
large and adherent cells , maintaining self-renewal capac-
ity and differentiation potential. 
Moreover, <rs type="software">ELDA</rs> has resulted for survey functional CSCs 
in colonospheres has revealed that colonospheres has 
marked increasing frequency of cells with sphere-form-
ing ability. Thus, it has suggested under extreme limited 
dilution and in serum-free conditions, spheroids could 
only formed from stem-like cells. Consequently, the for-
mation of colonospheres with a very small number of HT-
29 cell line has demonstrated enrichment CSCs in colono-</p>

<p>spheres (2, 7, 20). 
Furthermore, we have shown that colonospheres have 
expressed the specifics markers including Sox2, Oct4, 
Nanog, C-myc and KLF4 which were important for stem-
ness properties. In several studies have reported correla-
tions between multi potent genes expression and stem-
ness maintenance of human CSCs (8-10). Saigusa et al. has 
reported meaningful correlations among the expression 
level of OCT4, SOX2 and CD133 with distant recurrence, 
and poor prognosis of rectal cancer patients with pre-
operative chemo radiotherapy (9). Consistent with these 
results, Saiki et al. has also shown that lin-28 and SOX2 ex-
pression has highly associated with lymph node metasta-
sis and Dukes stage (10). 
Currently, several molecules have identified as markers 
for colon cancer stem cells such as CD133, CD44, CD166 
and CD24 (2-6). Previous reports via flow cytometry analy-
sis in tumor spheres and parent cells have shown associ-
ating between CD44 and EPCAM expression with colon 
CSCs. The results of present study has indicated signifi-
cant expression of CD44 and EPCAM in colonospheres in 
comparison with parent cells so that colonospheres-de-</p>

<p>Khorrami S et al. </p>



<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2015;8(5):e3446 
www.ijcancerprevention.com </p>

<p>rived cells were over 96% CD44+and EPCAM+. In line with 
these results, Kanwar et al. has shown that spheroid cells 
derived from HT-29 and HCT116 have higher expression 
of CD44 and EPCAM in comparison with parental cells 
(19). Thus these data strongly has indicated that colono-
spheres have generated under present conditions have 
mainly composed of CSCs. 
More recently, ALDH1 has proposed as a promising new 
biomarker in normal and malignant human colonic SCs. 
Chu et al. has revealed that in vivo implantation of CD-
44hi ALDH+ colon tumor cells were significantly more tu-
morigenic than matched CD44hi ALDH-cells. Therefore, 
as few as 100 CD44hi ALDH+ cells could lead to tumor for-
mation (5). In addition, Huang et al. (16) has shown that 
implantation of only 25 ALDH+ cancer cells have tumori-
genicity in NOD/SCID mice. However, further isolation of 
cancer cells ALDH+ using CD44 or CD133 only modestly 
has resulted in tumor-initiating ability (11). Thus, we have 
suggested that ALDH1 activity could be a valuable bio-
marker for identifying CSC in colonosphere population. 
Controversy, our findings have revealed that colono-
spheres exhibit have decreased levels of ALDH1 activity in 
comparison with the corresponding parental cells. Nev-
ertheless, low ALDH1 activity in colonospheres had no ef-
fect on their tumorigenic potential, so this population 
even has shown higher ability for initiating tumor, in 
comparison with parental cell with high ALDH1 activity 
in in vivo situation. Our results have shown that adminis-
tration of 2500 colonospheres could be sufficient to initi-
ate tumor growth in nude mice while 1 × 10 6 of parental 
cells has needed to form tumor. It would be important to 
point out that results of primary tumor could not gener-
alized to colonic cell line like HT-29. The present data has 
indicated that there was no correlation between ALDH 
activity and the tumorigenic capacity, and it could not be 
as a universal biomarker for identifying CSCs. 
Expression of ALDH1 could be different in population 
of tumor cell lines indicating CSCs properties. For in-
stance, recently Yuval Shaked et al. has demonstrated 
that spheroid of U-87MG, MCF7, and PANC1cell lines 
rather than their types of parental have increased levels 
of ALDH1 activity. It has also shown that ALDH activity 
in A549 and HT-29 cells was substantially high levels in 
the parental in comparison with the spheroid. However, 
higher expression of p21 and p53 has found in spheroid 
of HT-29, showing more angiogenic effects and resistant 
to chemotherapy than parent cells (23). A similar result 
has also reported by Yu et al. who have shown that high 
level expression of ALDH or the present of CD44 in CSCs 
of prostate cancer cell lines could not be relevant with 
tumorigenicity capacity, so that ALDHlo CD44-cells and 
ALDHhiCD44+cells has exhibited the same proliferative, 
clonogenic and metastatic capacity, indicating their po-
tential importance for further exploration (24). 
Moreover, ALDH-melanoma cells could be equally resis-
tant to treatment and tumorigenic with ALDH+ which in-
dicates the functional ''marker'' ALDH has not played an </p>

<p>exclusive role in tumor initiation and/or in low response 
to therapy (25). 
For the first time, our current experimental data have 
shown that ALDH activity has not appeared to specifically 
identify CSCs in HT-29 cell line. It could suggested that 
isolation of CSC-derived HT-29 cell line base on CD44 and 
EPCAM markers might be useful for characterization and 
further investigation of this cell line. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We would like to express our gratitude to animal lab of 
Imam Khomeini hospital for providing nude mice. This 
study has financially supported by Tarbiat Modares uni-
versity and digestive disease research institute of Tehran 
university, Tehran, Iran. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution:All the authors have contrib-
uted to the design, and the interpretation and discussion 
of the results. All the authors have critically revised the 
manuscript. 
Conflict of Interest:We had no conflicts of interest to 
declare. 
Financial Disclosure:None declared. </p>



<p>Khorrami S et al. </p>

<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2015;8(5):e3446 
 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>