<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4327489" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>bjective: The objective of this study was to evaluate the incidence of adverse effects reported by adolescents following 
14 days of use of a mouthrinse containing 0.05% NaF+0.12% chlorhexidine. Methods: This double-blind study was developed 
as part of a randomized clinical trial. The adolescents enrolled to the study were randomly divided into two groups to use either: 
0.05% NaF+0.12% chlorhexidine (G1, n=85) or 0.05% NaF (G2, n=85). Both groups used a 10mL solution of the mouthwash 
during 1 minute daily for 2 weeks under supervision. After that period, the subject's acceptance of taste was measured using 
a verbal descriptive scale (Labeled Magnitude Scale -LMS) 
11 . Participants were also interviewed regarding the occurrence of 
possible adverse effects during treatment (temporary palate disorders, tooth staining or unpleasant taste). The proportional 
differences between the groups were tested using the chi-square test. Results: Palate changes were reported by 26% of 
participants of each group; 17.7% of G1 and 32% of G2 reported an unpleasant taste (p = 0.062), while staining was reported by 
55% of G1 and 68.9% of G2 (p = 0.117). Absenteeism rates were similar in both groups (G1= 2.58 ± 2.69; G2=2.81 ± 2.39), p=0.362. 
Conclusion: adherence was high in both groups and side effects reported by subjects were not perceived by them as being 
important. Since subjects' acceptance and compliance is fundamental to the success of an oral health program, chlorhexidine-
fluoride could be a useful resource in a program of plaque control. 
Uniterms: Mouthwashes; Chlorhexidine, adverse effects; Randomized clinical trials. </p>

<p>bjetivo: Este estudo se propôs a calcular taxa de efeitos adversos após 14 dias de uso de solução de bochecho de NaF 
0,05% + clorexidina 0,12% realizados por adolescentes. Métodos: Este estudo duplo-cego foi desenvolvido como parte de um 
ensaio clínico randomizado. Os adolescentes foram divididos aleatoriamente em dois grupos: NaF 0,05% + clorexidina 0,12% 
(G1) ou NaF 0,05%, (G2) de 85 estudantes cada que bochecharam diariamente, 10mL de solução sob supervisão, durante 1 
minuto, por 2 semanas. Após esse período, a aceitação dos participantes ao gosto das soluções foi avaliada através de uma 
escala descritiva verbal -(LMS) 
11 . Os participantes foram entrevistados também quanto a possíveis efeitos adversos acontecidos 
durante tratamentos (desordens temporárias de paladar, manchamento dental e o gosto de soluções desagradáveis). As 
diferenças entre proporções em ambos os grupos foram testadas pelo teste do qui-quadrado. Resultados: Alteração de paladar 
foi informada por 26% dos estudantes de cada grupo; 17,7% dos G1 e 32% do G2 notaram o gosto desagradável (p = 0,062); 
manchas foram observadas por 55% dos G1 e 68,9% dos G2 (p = 0,117) e, as taxas de absenteísmo foram semelhantes (G1 = 
2,58±2,69; G2=2,81(2,39), p=0,362. Conclusão: A aderência dos participantes foi alta e os efeitos colaterais percebidos não 
pareceram importantes pelos adolescentes nos dois grupos. Implicação prática: porquanto a aceitação e aderência dos 
participantes são fundamentais para o sucesso de um programa de saúde bucal, a associação da clorexidina-fluoreto poderia 
ser um recurso adicional favorável dentro de um programa de controle de placa. 
Unitermos: Enxagüatórios bucais; Clorexidina, efeitos adversos; Ensaio clínico randomizado. </p>

<p>The chemical control of plaque can be a useful resource 
in a subgroup of patients whose mechanical control becomes 
difficult and ineffective </p>

<p>2,7,15,16   . An antimicrobial agent should 
inhibit the adhesion stage of bacterial colonization, and affect 
the growth and metabolic activity of dental plaque, without, 
however, interfering with any other biological process. In 
addition, its toxicity must be low, since such solutions could 
be inadvertently swallowed 
24 . The enhancement of the 
cariostatic effect of the fluoride by its combination with 
antimicrobial agents has been suggested 
16 and this 
combination has been shown to be effective in arresting 
caries lesions in irradiated patients with minimal salivary 
buffering capacity due to lower saliva flow rates </p>

<p>16   Chlorhexidine is the most commonly used antimicrobial 
substance because of its proven efficacy in altering 
membrane function, controlling oral biofilm and inhibiting 
the metabolism of microorganisms. In addition, it interferes 
with the acid production of dental plaque, reducing the pH 
level during cariogenic challenges 
22 . 
On the other hand, chlorhexidine is known to cause 
certain adverse effects directly related to higher 
concentrations 
25 , long-term regimens 
13,25 , and undisturbed 
biofilm. Consumption of some chromogenic agents 
17 , such 
as coffee or tea, for example, may also increase 
toothstaining </p>

<p>17   , which is one of the most recognized problems 
associated with chlorhexidine. Cationic antiseptics, such as 
chlorhexidine, may activate anionic chromatic particles 
contained in some food and drinks, causing interaction with 
tooth surfaces </p>

<p>1   . In vitro, these colored particles can produce 
identically colored complexes such as those caused by 
chlorhexidine and observed clinically in individuals who 
drink tea, coffee or red wine compared with those who do 
not ingest these drinks 
17 . Randomized controlled clinical 
trials have shown that tea and coffee associated with the 
use of chlorhexidine mouthrinses contribute significantly 
to staining the teeth and tongue. On the other hand, 
abstaining from tea and coffee notably reduces this effect 
17 . 
In addition, the bitter taste of chlorhexidine and the 
temporary reduction in the subjects' perception of bitterness 
and saltiness 
4,10 could compromise their adherence to a 
program based on this antiseptic. Moreover, loss of taste 
could reduce patients' capacity to distinguish possible toxic 
foods, and may decrease their appetite. However, no serious 
adverse effects associated with the use of chlorhexidine 
mouthrinse have been reported in clinical trials 
24 . 
However, there is a paucity of data in the scientific 
literature concerning the incidence of adverse effects 
reported by subjects using a mouthrinse containing 0.12% 
chlorhexidine and 0.05% sodium fluoride in a single solution. 
This association has been used as an adjunct to oral 
hygiene 
15 , in the control of active carious infection in high-
risk patients 
2 , in handicapped children 
7 , orthodontic 
patients 
5,21 , irradiated patients 
16 , lymphoma patients 
receiving cytostatic drugs 
19 , persons with disabilities 
7,18 and 
in the elderly 
9,20,23 . Therefore, the purpose of this study was 
to estimate the prevalence and intensity of adverse effects </p>

<p>in patients using a mouthrinse containing 0.05% sodium 
fluoride or the combination of 0.12% chlorhexidine solution 
and 0.05% sodium fluoride after fourteen days of use. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>This current study was part of a larger, therapeutic, 
randomized, double-blind, clinical trial whose main objective 
was to compare the effectiveness of 0.05% sodium fluoride 
alone (NaF) and the combination of 0.12% chlorhexidine 
solution (CHX) and 0.05% sodium fluoride in arresting active 
carious lesions after 14 school days 
12 . Carried out within 
the randomized clinical trial, the objective of this study was 
to evaluate the occurrence of side effects during the use of 
these mouthrinses. The study was carried out in a public 
school in Florianópolis, capital of the Brazilian state of Santa 
Catarina. </p>

<p>Individual selection and eligibility criteria </p>

<p>Children with at least one active white spot carious lesion 
in smooth enamel surfaces were enrolled to the study. 
Exclusion criteria comprised schoolchildren who were taking 
some medication, those in use of orthodontic brackets or 
dental prosthesis, those who had undergone aesthetic tooth 
restoration, and pregnant or breastfeeding girls. A sample 
size of 71 individuals, 11-15 years of age, was required for 
each group. An additional fifteen percent was added to 
each group to compensate for possible dropouts; therefore, 
82 individuals were enrolled to each group. The Epi Info 
software program 
8 was used to calculate sample size. The 
criterion for statistical significance was set at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Personnel and Training </p>

<p>Eight previously trained dental students, supervised by 
a dental PhD student (MLRJ), provided both groups with 
mouthrinses in identical plastic cups. Three dental students, 
also previously trained, asked the children questions 
regarding their perception of adverse effects. Dental 
students and the children were blinded with respect to the 
contents of the solution. </p>

<p>Randomization and blinding </p>

<p>A double-blind study was carried out and subjects were 
randomly allocated to one of two groups: Group 1 (G1 -
0.05% NaF + 0.12% CHX) or Group 2 (G2-0.05% NaF). A 
randomization method was used to form the groups. A 
number was given to each eligible child and then put into a 
sealed opaque envelope. The envelopes were randomly 
selected by the supervisor (MLRJ) to allocate the individuals 
to each group of mouthrinsing solution, either 0.05% fluoride 
or 0.05% plus 0.12% chlorhexidine. Two pure solutions 
containing the same pharmacological formulation were used, 
the only difference being the presence or absence of 0.12% 
chlorhexidine in solutions A and B, respectively 
12 . The 
solutions were in identical, unlabeled, amber-colored bottles, 
bearing only the codes A or B. Neither the eligible children, 
the mouthrinsing supervisors or the examiners knew to </p>



<p>SELF-PERCEPTION OF SIDE EFFECTS BY ADOLESCENTS IN A CHLORHEXIDINE-FLUORIDE-BASED PREVENTIVE ORAL HEALTH PROGRAM </p>

<p>which group the children belonged. 
Dental examinations were carried out at baseline and 
after fourteen days of treatment. Prior to the examinations, 
the children were asked to brush their teeth under the 
supervision of the dental students using toothbrushes 
provided by the study. </p>

<p>Mouthrinsing </p>

<p>The children were instructed by the team to rinse during 
1 minute/day for 14 consecutive school days using the 10 
mL solution provided in plastic cups. The components 
common to the two solutions were 0.05% sodium fluoride, 
glycerin, non-cariogenic anise aroma, blue food coloring, 
preservative and vehicle (qsp). The solutions were prepared 
exclusively for the study (Fórmula &amp; Ação, São Paulo) and 
both solutions had identical color, flavor and artificial taste. 
The toothbrushing was performed without the use of 
toothpaste since Brazilian dentifrices contain SLS (sodium 
lauryl sulfate), which inactivates CHX, thereby requiring a 
minimum interval of 30 minutes between toothbrushing and 
rinsing </p>

<p>3   , which would be an unreasonable interruption of 
the schoolchildren's routine. Although an effect of 
fluoridated water, concentration of water fluoridated and 
dentifrice in the arrestment of dental caries was expected, 
both groups were randomly exposed to these variables and 
any influence should therefore have been distributed 
randomly. </p>

<p>Interviews </p>

<p>To evaluate subjects' perception of the side-effects 
caused by either treatment, only one examiner (RMF), who 
was aware of the objectives of the study, carried out all the 
interviews. After 14 days of rinses, the children were 
screened for their ability to assign a bitterness intensity 
rating to each solution, using a simplified scale based on 
the "Labeled Magnitude Scale" (LMS) 
11 . The method used 
to estimate the impact caused by side effects related to the 
solutions was subjective. However, the instrument used is 
an adaptation of the Labeled Scale Measurement (LSM) 
that has been widely used in physiological science 
11 . The 
instrument underwent previous validation in the Portuguese 
language and was adapted to the local culture to ensure 
optimal comprehension by the study population (Figure 1). 
This scale is a method used for obtaining estimates of 
intensity. The method consists of a line (usually vertical) 
with verbal descriptions of intensity, using adjectives to 
describe intensity that ranged from weak, moderate, strong 
and very strong to the strongest imaginable sensation. 
Afterwards, the adolescents stated whether the perceived 
intensity was acceptable or not. They were also asked about 
possible adverse effects occurring during or after that period, 
such as transitory alterations in the patient's perception of 
taste during or following the test period, any change in the 
appearance of teeth perceived by the subjects, as well as 
questions related to weekly consumption of staining 
products such as tea, coffee, colored snacks, Coca-Cola®, 
other soft drinks, cigarettes and chocolates. Stain was 
evaluated in a dichotomy way considering its presence or </p>

<p>not after the test period. All natural teeth in the dentition 
were included. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>To test the methodology, a pre-test was performed in a 
sample of 30 adolescents, whose characteristics were similar 
to those of the study population. Absenteeism was 
measured daily and was defined as being when a student 
failed to carry out the scheduled mouthrinsing or did not 
attend the final clinical examination. 
Both dental examinations were carried out by the same 
examiner (ARDG). After the second dental examination, all 
new tooth staining that had not been registered at the first 
examination was recorded. The examiner did not know to 
which group the adolescents belonged. 
The Mann-Whitney U and Chi-square tests were used 
to assess differences in variables between the two groups 
at baseline and at the end of the trial. The differences 
between proportions were tested using the chi-square test 
and comparison in the perception of tooth staining was 
analyzed using Fisher's exact test. Significance was 
established when p&lt;0.05. The <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> software package (SPSS, 
Chicago, Illinois, USA) was used for the data analysis. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Eighty-five adolescents were enrolled in each group and 
participated in the study. There were no statistically 
significant differences in gender or age between adolescents 
in the test group (0.05% sodium fluoride combined with 
0.12% chlorhexidine -G1) and those in the control group 
(0.05% sodium fluoride mouthrinse alone -G2), (Table 1). 
Absenteeism, which could have modified the results, was 
almost identical in the two groups studied (Table 1). 
Temporary taste disorders were perceived by exactly 26% 
of students in each group; unpleasant taste by 17.7% of 
participants of G1 and 32.3% of G2 (p = 0.062), and staining 
by 55% of G1 and 68.9% of G2 (p = 0.117), (Table 2). The 
staining was easily removed by professional dental 
prophylaxis. 
There was no difference in the consumption of colored 
snacks, chocolates, juices, Coca-Cola®, other soft drinks, 
tea or colored flavoring between the two groups. However, 
coffee consumption was higher in the test group (G1) than 
in the control group (G2). The consumption of tea was 
slightly higher among participants in the control group 
compared to the test group (Table 3). None of the subjects 
reported current tobacco use. 
Regarding patients' perception of tooth staining, there 
was in ten cases, a discrepancy between theirs and the 
dentist's opinion. The dentist has noticed the tooth staining 
more frequently than the adolescent (Table 4). Brown stain 
was usually found on the cervical third of anterior teeth. </p>



<p>GUIMARAES A R D, PERES M A, VIEIRA R de S, FERREIRA R M, RAMOS-JORGE M L, APOLINARIO S, DEBOM A </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Considering the widespread use of chlorhexidine in 
dentistry, there are few reports of side effects, other than 
some local effects such as discoloration of teeth, tongue, 
restorations and dentures 
1,14,17,25 , and temporary taste 
disorders, especially related to the 0.2% rinses </p>

<p>4,9   . It is difficult 
to compare the results of this present study with those from 
previous randomized clinical trials due the variability of 
fluoride and chlorhexidine combinations, concentrations, 
pharmaceutical presentation (gels, varnishes or rinses), and 
the presence or not of both elements in the same product. In 
a previous randomized clinical trial (RCT) 
16 , chlorhexidine 
associated with fluoride in the same product achieved excellent 
patient acceptance and adherence in a daily mouthrinse 
program (0.05% NaF -0.2% CHX) and tooth staining was not 
reported by the users of chlorhexidine. In another study, 
staining was intensified after 6 months of use of 1% CHX-F 
toothpaste, but the program participants considered the local 
side effects acceptable 
25 . The acceptability and tolerability of 
chlorhexidine and benzydamine oral rinse agents used in a 
protocol on oral hygiene in children receiving chemotherapy 
was evaluated and both agents were acceptable and well-
tolerated by children over the age 6 years old </p>

<p>6   . However, 
these studies used different regimes from those used in the 
current trial. 
In this study, subject absenteeism was very low and did 
not differ between the two groups, indicating high adherence 
to the program. It is, therefore, reasonable to speculate that </p>

<p>the use of CHX-F could be recommended as an adjunct 
procedure for plaque control. 
A similar number of subjects in both groups (26%) 
reported temporary taste disorders, reflecting the successful 
randomization procedure. A greater proportion of subjects 
using the fluoridated solution (G2), (32.3%) reported an 
unpleasant taste when compared to those in the CHX-F 
solution group (G1), (17.7%), indicating that the anise flavor 
contained in both solutions successfully masked any 
unpleasant taste. Moreover, the subjects reported the taste 
as being strong but refreshing and stated that it gave them 
the sensation of oral cleanliness. In addition, the adolescents 
perceived the changes in tooth color as being something 
positive, probably associated with the therapeutic effect of 
the two substances. 
There was no significant difference between the two 
groups with respect to the consumption of any of the staining 
agents investigated (Table 3), demonstrating the homogeneity 
of the two groups. Coffee consumption was higher than tea 
consumption in both groups and there was a discretely higher 
consumption in the chlorhexidine-fluoride group. These 
results hindered the comparison with previous studies in 
which coffee was shown to stain teeth less than tea </p>

<p>17   . Cigarette 
smoking was not mentioned by any subject in either group. 
To demonstrate whether tooth staining was correlated 
with the solution, the perception of the subjects themselves 
was compared with the perception of the study dentist. All 
the tooth staining perceived by the dentist was caused by 
the chlorhexidine rinse, and these results are in agreement </p>

<p>Characteristics 
G1 (n=85) 
G2 (n=85) 
p </p>

<p>(%) 
(%) </p>

<p>Female participants 
55.3 
58.8 
0.64 * 
n s </p>

<p>Age (years) -mean (SD) 
13.01 (1.34) 
12.96 (1.38) 
0.88** 
n s </p>

<p>Absenteeism -mean (SD) 
2.58(2.69) 
2.81(2.39) 
0.362** n s </p>

<p>TABLE 1-Differential aspects of both groups at baseline </p>

<p>ns: not significant 
SD: Standard deviation; 
* Chi-square test; 
** Mann-Whitney U test </p>

<p>Reported Side Effect % 
G1 (n=85) 
G2 (n=85) 
p </p>

<p>(%) 
(%) </p>

<p>Temporary taste disorders 
26 
26 
n s </p>

<p>Unpleasant taste 
17.7 
32.3 
0.062 
n s </p>

<p>Staining 
55 
68.9 
0.117 
n s </p>

<p>TABLE 2-Chi-square test for the perception of the side effects on both groups </p>

<p>*Significant (p &lt; 0.05) 
ns: not significant </p>



<p>SELF-PERCEPTION OF SIDE EFFECTS BY ADOLESCENTS IN A CHLORHEXIDINE-FLUORIDE-BASED PREVENTIVE ORAL HEALTH PROGRAM </p>

<p>with previous reports </p>

<p>1,15,17 </p>

<p>, confirming chlorhexidine as a tooth-
staining agent. On the other hand, although the adolescents 
reported the occurrence of a few cases of tooth staining, it 
did not seem important to them and did not affect their 
participation in the program. 
Another aspect that should be considered is the 
possibility of the participants being psychologically biased 
in favor of the treatment. However, this possibility is minimal 
since participants were just as likely to be randomized to 
either treatment group. 
Therefore, the inherent characteristics of the study design, 
such as randomization and blinding (subjects, dental examiner 
and interviewer), which avoided any bias in variables, confirm 
its suitability and validate our findings. For the same reason, 
the occurrence of tooth staining was recorded during the 
dental examinations in an effort to guarantee that only tooth 
staining relative to the treatment was analyzed. Another 
positive feature of the study design is the adequate sample 
size that enables the results to be extrapolated to a larger 
population and confers external validity to the study. Finally, 
it is important to emphasize that the length of time spent in 
this study was sufficient to observe positive effect of CLX-F 
on arrestment of active caries lesions </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>, with a high compliance </p>

<p>rate in both groups and no relevant side effects. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Adherence was high in both groups and side effects 
perceived by subjects did not appear relevant to them. Since 
patient compliance was considered highly satisfactory and 
the side effects perceived by the subjects did not seem 
important to them, the use of chlorhexidine combined with 
fluoride may be recommended as an auxiliary resource in 
plaque control. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by FUNPESQUISA (337/2002, 
UFSC, Brazil). The authors would like to thank the dental 
students who helped them during the fieldwork and Ana Nere 
Santos for her technical support. The authors would also like 
to thank the local education authorities and teachers. Condor 
S.A. kindly provided the toothbrushes used in the study. As 
the solutions were specifically prepared for the study, there </p>

<p>Food /beverage 
G1 
G2 
p </p>

<p>Mean (SD) 
Mean (SD) </p>

<p>Colored Snacks 
2.00 (0.30) 
2.57 (0.28) 
0.194 </p>

<p>Chocolate 
2.58 (0.30) 
2.89 (0.32) 
0.499 </p>

<p>Juices 
3.67 (0.32) 
3.40 (0.33) 
0.623 </p>

<p>Coca-Cola® 
3.64 (0.27) 
3.37 (0.23) 
0.264 </p>

<p>Other soft drinks 
3.00 (0.33) 
2.80 (0.30) 
0.477 
Coffee 
3.69 (0.43) 
4.77 (0.36) 
0.037* </p>

<p>Tea 
1.03 (0.26) 
0.46 (0.17) 
0.075 </p>

<p>Colored seasoning 
2.67 (0.47) 
3.34 (0.46) 
0.233 </p>

<p>TABLE 3-Mann Whitney U test for the consumption frequency of possible staining agents reported by the adolescents </p>

<p>* Significant (p &lt; 0.05) </p>

<p>Dentist's perception 
Total </p>

<p>of tooth staining </p>

<p>yes 
no </p>

<p>Subjects' perception 
yes 
n 
6 
6 </p>

<p>of tooth staining 
% perceived 
100% 
100% </p>

<p>no 
n 
10 
19 
29 </p>

<p>% perceived 
34.5% 
65.5% 
100% </p>

<p>Total 
n 
16 
19 
35 </p>

<p>% perceived 
45.7% 
54.3% 
100% </p>

<p>TABLE 4-Fisher's exact test for the comparison of dentist's and subjects' perception of tooth staining </p>



<p>GUIMARAES A R D, PERES M A, VIEIRA R de S, FERREIRA R M, RAMOS-JORGE M L, APOLINARIO S, DEBOM A </p>

<p>was no conflict of interest that could influence the results. </p>





<p>SELF-PERCEPTION OF SIDE EFFECTS BY ADOLESCENTS IN A CHLORHEXIDINE-FLUORIDE-BASED PREVENTIVE ORAL HEALTH PROGRAM </p>

</text></tei>