<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4568189" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>BACKGROUND: Renal failure is a frequent event after coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG). 
Hemodynamic alterations during surgery as well as the underlying disease are the predisposing 
factors. We aimed to study intermittent furosemide therapy in the prevention of renal failure in 
patients undergoing CABG. </p>

<p>METHODS: In a single-blind randomized controlled trial, 123 elective CABG patients, 18-75 
years, entered the study. Clearance of creatinine, urea and water were measured. Patients were 
randomly assigned into three groups: furosemide in prime (0.3-0.4 mg/kg); intermittent 
furosemide during CABG (0.2 mg/kg, if there was a decrease in urinary excretion) and control 
(no furosemide). </p>

<p>RESULTS: There was a significant change in serum urea, sodium and fluid balance in 
"intermittent furosemide" group; other variables did not change significantly before or after the 
operation. Post-operative fluid balance was significantly higher in "intermittent furosemide" 
group (2573 ± 205 ml) compared to control (1574.0 ± 155.0 ml) (P &lt; 0.010); also, fluid balance 
was higher in "intermittent furosemide" group (2573 ± 205 ml) compared to "furosemide in 
prime" group (1935.0 ± 169.00 ml) (P &lt; 0.010). </p>

<p>CONCLUSION: The study demonstrated no benefit from intermittent furosemide in elective 
CABG compared to furosemide in prime volume or even placebo. </p>

<p>Keywords: Renal Failure, Coronary Artery Bypass Grafting, Furosemide </p>

<p>Date of submission: 25 Oct 2014, Date of acceptance: 06 Apr 2015 </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Acute renal failure (ARF) is a complex disorder, 
which is commonly seen in the perioperative period 
and in the intensive care unit (ICU). This 
phenomenon occurs in a variety of settings with 
clinical manifestations ranging from a minimal 
elevation in serum creatinine to anuric renal 
failure. 1,2 It would be associated with a prolonged 
hospital stay and high morbidity and mortality. 3 
ARF after coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) 
is an important and independent risk factor of 
mortality and morbidity. 4,5 As a result, the 
implications of acute kidney injury after cardiac 
surgery are very well-known to cardiac 
anesthesiologists and intensivists. 6-8 
Recent studies have focused on the preventive 
strategies; which could be used for the high risk </p>

<p>subsets for ARF. 9 Moreover, it has been 
demonstrated that in high-risk cardiac surgical 
patients, post-operative furosemide infusion could 
not improve the clinical outcome of the patients in 
preventing the occurrence of ARF. 10 Here, we aimed 
to study the possible role of early furosemide 
administration (as two different modes) compared 
with control, in the prevention of renal failure in 
patients undergoing elective CABG. Hence, there are 
some controversial issues regarding the need for 
more sophisticated studies to come to a final decision 
to define which therapeutic option is more effective. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This study was a single-blinded, randomized 
controlled trial; which was performed from January 
2009 to November 2010, in a tertiary level, referral </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>www.mui.ac.ir </p>



<p>Furosemide as prophylaxis of ARF in CABG </p>



<p>university hospital which is only a cardiovascular 
center. After institutional review board (IRB) approval, 
Tehran University of Medical Science, Iran, regarding 
ethical considerations and also, after taking informed 
written consent, among a total of 250 patients, after 
considering inclusion and exclusion criteria, 126 
patients aged 40-75 entered the study; but among 
them, 123 could finish the study. 
Inclusion criteria were: 
• Age 40-75 
• Elective CABG with cardiopulmonary bypass 
(CPB) 
• Constant surgeon 
• Informed written consent. 
Exclusion criteria were: 
• Old age (&gt; 75 years) 
• Emergency and high-risk surgery 
• Ischemic heart disease 
• Diabetes mellitus 
• Diabetic ketoacidosis 
• Non-kenotic hyperosmolar diabetic coma 
• ARF 
• Chronic kidney disease causing serum Cr &gt; 2 
mg/dl 
• Glomerulonephritis 
• Hepatic failure causing liver function test 
failure (&gt; 3 times than normal) 
• Off-pump CABG 
• Any unwanted complication in the operation 
period 
• Re-starting CPB after weaning from bypass 
• Pulmonary artery pressure &gt; 30 before operation 
• Ejection fraction &lt; 30 (%) 
• Re-operation in the post-operative period 
• Congestive heart failure 
• Thyroid disorders 
• Acute infections 
• Stroke 
• Pregnancy 
• Hospital admission in the recent 3 months. 
Sample size calculation is discussed below. Our 
sampling strategy was a randomized single blind 
clinical trial; neither the patients nor the directly 
involved physicians knew who will belong to which 
group. For randomization of the patients, first, we 
prepared 126 small sized papers and divided them 
into three groups: 42 in each; A, B, or C; 
accordingly; Group A, Group B, or Group C. 
All the patients were scheduled for elective 
CABG. The diagnosis of acute coronary syndrome </p>

<p>was confirmed according to the criteria of American 
College of Cardiology. 11 Renal function was 
assessed by calculating the clearance of creatinine, 
urea and water. 
The patients were fully blinded regarding the 
study group in which they were allocated; also, they 
were randomly assigned into three groups (Figure 1). 
1. The first group (Group A): Intra-prime 
furosemide therapy was performed; i.e., these 
patients received 0.3-0.4 mg/kg furosemide in the 
prime solution; it means that furosemide was added 
to the CPB reservoir and when the bypass was 
initiated, it was mixed with patients' blood 
2. The second group (Group B): Intermittent 
furosemide therapy was done; i.e., patients received 
0.2 mg/kg furosemide during CABG only in the 
case of decreased urinary excretion rate; the method 
of monitoring intra operation decrease in urinary 
output was exact control of hourly urinary flow by 
urine flow meter; if urine flow was &lt; 1 ml/kg/h, it 
was considered as decreased urinary flow 
3. The third group (Group C): i.e., the control 
group, the patients did not receive furosemide or 
any other drug as renal failure prophylaxis. 
All the other therapeutic protocols were adjusted 
the same in the three groups. Also, we hold the 
diuretics before surgery. 
Furthermore, those patients with the previous 
furosemide administration were excluded since 
patients who receive pre-operative furosemide may 
have a different response to diuretic during CABG. 
The study variables were measured using one of 
the three following approaches: 
• Clinical observation (for pre-operative, 
intraoperative and post-operative clinical findings) 
• Laboratory measurements (for measuring the 
results of blood levels of hemoglobin and 
hematocrit, serum electrolytes, and serum 
metabolites) 
• Patients' clinical files for assessing and 
registering their demographic and clinical data. 
All the measurements for variables were done by 
the same person; she was blind to the patients' group. 
Blood samples were collected after almost 12 ho of 
fasting and, serum creatinine, lactate, blood urea 
nitrogen (BUN), sodium (Na) and potassium (K) were 
measured for all the patients before and after CABG. 
Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) was calculated using 
the Cockcroft-Gault formula; which estimated the 
creatinine clearance rate. 12 The patients did not receive 
any other diuretics except for furosemide during the 
operation. Although Risk, Injury, Failure, Loss of 
kidney function, and End-stage kidney disease </p>

<p>www.mui.ac.ir </p>



<p>Bayat, et al. </p>

<p>ARYA Atheroscler 2015; Volume 11, Issue 3 175 </p>

<p>(RIFLE) criteria have been proposed as useful criteria 
for staging of patients with acute kidney injuries; this 
criteria focuses mainly on GFR. However, the current 
study has used many other factors, including GFR and 
other criteria, including a number of electrolytes, 
hemoglobin, and fluid balance. 
Inside the operating theater, demographic and 
anthropometric data including age, sex, presence of 
diabetes and blood pressure in sitting position were 
recorded. Blood pressure was measured twice after 
5 min on average. Also, body mass index was 
calculated as kg/m 2 . 
All patients underwent catheterization using 
standard Judkins or Sones techniques. Angiographic 
scoring was performed by 2 cardiologists. Coronary 
angiographies were interpreted visually and were 
always analyzed in 2 orthogonal views. Stenosis of 
&gt; 50% in any of the main epicardial vessels 
reflected a significant coronary artery disease. 
CABG was performed according to the guidelines 
of American College of Cardiology. 13 
Sample size was determined after a power 
analysis (power = 0.8, β = 0.2, α = 0.02); using the 
power analysis and sample size software: <rs id="software-0" type="software">PASS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2005</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">NCSS Statistical Software</rs>, Utah, USA). The clinical 
criterion for sample size determination was the 
observed frequency of "per hour urinary output 
needing medical intervention;" so, we required 35 
patients in each group; equals a total of 105; 
however, to compensate for possible dropouts, we 
added 20% to the calculated sample size to have a 
final sample of 126 (42 in each group). 
The statistical package <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> software for Windows 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 16</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA), was used 
for analysis. Quantitative variables were presented as 
mean ± standard deviation. Qualitative variables were 
presented as number and percentage. Paired sample t-
test was employed for the comparison of the pre-
operative and post-operative variables in each group. 
T-test and ANOVA were used for the </p>

<p>comparison of the studied variables between groups. 
This study has been registered in www.irct.ir, under 
the number: 201502122804N8. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Of 126, 123 patients could finally finish the trial. 
Among the study population (123 patients) the 
majority were men: 87 (70.7%) men versus 35 
(28.4%) women. The mean age of the patients was 
58 ± 1.2 years. There were 39 (31.7%) patients in 
intra-prime furosemide group; 42 (34.1%) in 
intermittent furosemide therapy group and 42 
(34.1%) in the control group. Basic demographic 
data of the participants are presented in table 1. 
There was no significant difference between the 
three groups regarding basic variables; including age 
(years), gender, duration of operation, ejection 
fraction, pre-operative serum levels of "creatinine, 
sodium (Na), potassium (K), lactate, GFR, BUN, 
hemoglobin" and also, pre-operative fluid balance 
(Table 1). Also, the CPB and aortic cross-clamp 
times were similar between the three study groups. 
During the post-operative period, the patients were 
transferred to the cardiac ICU; meanwhile, significant 
changes in fluid balance, serum levels of BUN and 
serum levels of sodium (Na) were seen in Group A (P 
value for ANOVA &lt; 0.010); while there was no 
significant difference regarding other variables before 
and after the operation. However, there was a 
significant positive fluid balance during the early post-
operative period in Group B (2573 ± 205 ml) 
compared to Group C (1574.0 ± 155.0) and Group A 
(1935.0 ± 169.00); (P value for ANOVA &lt; 0.010). 
Also, after performing ANOVA test, we 
performed the Tukey post-hoc test; this test was 
done to assess, which group was different from the 
others in between the three groups; the group, which 
was different from the two others was indicated with 
a asterix (*) in table 2; i.e., the group differed 
significantly from the two other groups (P &lt; 0.050). </p>

<p>Table 1. Basic variables of the study groups </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Intra-prime 
furosemide (Group A) 
(n = 42) </p>

<p>Intermittent 
furosemide therapy 
(Group B) (n = 42) </p>

<p>Control 
(Group C) 
(n = 42) </p>

<p>P (for 
ANOVA) </p>

<p>Age (year) 
61.0 ± 1.4 
62.0 ± 1.8 
57.0 ± 2.3 
0.147 
BUN 
21.4 ± 2.1 
24.2 ± 3.3 
19.6 ± 2.5 
0.151 
Creatinine 
1.5 ± 0.4 
1.4 ± 0.3 
1.6 ± 0.5 
0.382 
Hemoglobin 
15.5 ± 3.1 
15.6 ± 3.3 
16.3 ± 3.3 
0.307 
Sodium 
142.0 ± 1.4 
140.0 ± 1.3 
140.0 ± 1.2 
0.391 
Lactate 
1.8 ± 0.2 
2.1 ± 0.1 
2.1 ± 0.2 
0.223 
Fluid balance (intra-operative) 
1833.0 ± 405.0 
1379.0 ± 292.0 
1411.0 ± 117.0 
0.141 
Potassium 
4.2 ± 1.0 
4.1 ± 1.0 
4.1 ± 1.0 
0.092 
GFR (ml/min) 
71.0 ± 8.3 
58.0 ± 3.2 
63.0 ± 3.9 
0.079 </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean ± SD; One-way ANOVA test was used for data analysis; SD: Standard deviation; BUN: Blood urea 
nitrogen; GFR: Glomerular filtration rate </p>

<p>www.mui.ac.ir </p>



<p>Furosemide as prophylaxis of ARF in CABG </p>



<p>Table 2. Pre-operative and post-operative findings in three study groups </p>

<p>Data variables </p>

<p>Intra-prime 
furosemide 
(Group A) (n = 42) </p>

<p>Intermittent 
furosemide 
therapy (Group 
B) (n = 42) </p>

<p>Control 
(Group C) 
(n = 42) </p>

<p>P for 
ANOVA </p>

<p>Pre-operative blood urea nitrogen 
19.4 ± 3.02 
19.2 ± 3.3 
19.6 ± 2.9 
0.311 
Post-operative blood urea nitrogen 
16.1 ± 1.00 
25.7 ± 3.3 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>15.8 ± 1.2 
0.002 
1 
st day post-operative blood urea nitrogen 
18.9 ± 1.35 
19.9 ± 1.5 
18.1 ± 1.1 
0.271 
2 </p>

<p>nd </p>

<p>day post-operative blood urea 
nitrogen 
20.1 ± 1.50 
28.3 ± 3.6 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>19.3 ± 1.4 
0.001 </p>

<p>Pre-operative creatinine 
1.5 ± 0.40 
1.4 ± 0.4 
1.7 ± 0.5 
0.132 
Post-operative creatinine 
1.2 ± 0.10 
1.3 ± 0.1 
1.2 ± 0.1 
0.320 
1 
st day post-operative creatinine 
1.2 ± 0.10 
1.4 ± 0.1 
1.3 ± 0.1 
0.211 
2 
nd day post-operative creatinine 
1.2 ± 0.10 
1.5 ± 0.1 
1.2 ± 0.1 
0.103 
Pre-operative hemoglobin 
14.5 ± 1.20 
14.9 ± 1.4 
14.3 ± 1.3 
0.111 
Post-operative hemoglobin 
10.3 ± 1.30 
9.8 ± 1.2 
9.9 ± 1.2 
0.101 
1 
st day post-operative hemoglobin 
9.1 ± 1.10 
9.4 ± 1.2 
9.1 ± 1.1 
0.171 
2 
nd day post-operative hemoglobin 
9.3 ± 1.20 
9.7 ± 1.1 
9.7 ± 1.3 
0.262 
Pre-operative sodium 
142.0 ± 1.50 
140.0 ± 1.6 
140.0 ± 1.6 
0.251 
Post-operative sodium 
136.0 ± 1.40 
148.0 ± 3.2 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>139.0 ± 1.1 
0.004 
1 
st day post-operative sodium 
140.0 ± 1.00 
148.0 ± 0.8 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>141.0 ± 1.0 
0.002 
2 
nd day post-operative sodium 
142.0 ± 1.90 
148.0 ± 1.4 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>139.0 ± 1.0 
0.001 
Pre-operative lactate level 
1.9 ± 1.150 
2.0 ± 1.1 
2.1 ± 1.2 
0.320 
Intra-operative lactate 
4.0 ± 1.40 
3.9 ± 0.3 
3.8 ± 0.8 
0.162 
Pre-operative fluid balance 
1333.0 ± 405.00 
1379.0 ± 392.0 
1411.0 ± 417.0 
0.120 
Postoperative fluid balance 
1908.0 ± 381.00 
2514.0 ± 662.0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1717.0 ± 295.0 
0.003 
Post-operative fluid balance in first day 
of ICU 
2798.0 ± 194.00 
2849.0 ± 171.0 
2717.0 ± 150.0 
0.114 </p>

<p>Post-operative fluid balance in second 
day of ICU 
1935.0 ± 169.00 
2573.0 ± 205.0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1574.0 ± 155.0 
0.005 </p>

<p>Intra-operative urine output 
543.0 ± 280.00 
583.0 ± 246.0 
550.0 ± 296.0 
0.211 
Post-operative urine output 
298.0 ± 23.00 
280.0 ± 29.0 
298.0 ± 27.0 
0.130 
Preoperative glomerular filtration rate 
71.5 ± 4.30 
58.0 ± 3.8 
63.0 ± 3.9 
0.120 
Post-operative glomerular filtration rate 
70.6 ± 3.70 
59.5 ± 4.1 
65.6 ± 3.9 
0.121 
Preoperative potassium 
4.2 ± 1.00 
4.1 ± 1.0 
4.1 ± 1.0 
0.222 
Postoperative potassium 
4.4 ± 1.00 
4.2 ± 1.0 
4.3 ± 1.0 
0.271 
First day post op potassium 
4.2 ± 1.00 
4.4 ± 1.0 
4.2 ± 1.0 
0.232 
Second day post-operative potassium 
4.2 ± 1.00 
4.4 ± 1.0 
4.2 ± 1.0 
0.221 </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean ± SD; There was no difference within the two other groups, one-way ANOVA test was used for data 
analysis; 
* The results of this test demonstrated that the group indicated by asterix (*) differed significantly from the two other groups 
(P &lt; 0.050); SD: Standard deviation; ICU: Intensive care unit </p>

<p>Admission to the study: 126 patients 
Three patients out of the study because of re-starting CPB after weaning from bypass due to hemodynamic instability: 
Final number of patients: 123 </p>

<p>Elective coronary artery bypass surgery; constant surgeon; informed written consent; aged 40-75 years; no emergency 
and high risk surgery; no history of end stage renal failure, an ejection fraction &gt; 30%; no history of ischemic heart 
disease, diabetes mellitus and its complications, no history of hepatic failure or hepatic disease, no history of thyroid 
disease, no history of acute infection 
Then randomized between the three following groups </p>

<p>Group A (n = 42): intra-prime 
furosemide: 0.3-0.4 mg/kg 
furosemide in the prime 
solution </p>

<p>Group B (n = 42): intermittent furosemide 
therapy: 0.2 mg/kg furosemide during 
CABG only in the case of decreased urinary 
excretion rate (i.e. urine flow &lt; 1 ml/kg/h) </p>

<p>Group C (n = 42): control group: 
the patients did not receive 
furosemide or any other drug as 
renal failure prophylaxis </p>

<p>The three groups were compared regarding postoperative serum markers of renal function 
Figure 1. Study flowchart </p>

<p>CPB: Cardiopulmonary bypass; CABG: Coronary artery bypass grafting </p>

<p>www.mui.ac.ir </p>



<p>Bayat, et al. </p>

<p>ARYA Atheroscler 2015; Volume 11, Issue 3 177 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study demonstrated that intermittent 
furosemide therapy does not significantly improve 
the renal outcome of the patients undergoing 
elective CABG compared with the patients 
receiving either an intra-prime dose or the patients 
in the control group. 
However, the findings indicated that patients 
receiving intermittent furosemide therapy had the 
greatest positive fluid balance (i.e., extra fluid 
remaining in the body) compared to the other patient 
groups. The question here is why patients with 
positive fluid balance had decreased urine production 
during the operation; this finding could possibly be 
due to hypotension during the operation. 
Besides, the patients receiving intra prime 
furosemide had significantly improved serum levels of 
BUN and Na, and also, improved fluid balance status. 
Based on other studies, renal function is an 
important determinant of post-operative clinical 
outcome. 14 also, ARF after cardiac surgery is a 
significant predictor of hospital mortality. 15 
On the other hand, some studies have 
demonstrated different independent risk factors, 
including old age, previous renal failure, emergency 
and high risk surgery, ischemic heart disease, 
congestive heart disease, and the need for inotropic 
drugs for ARF in CABG patients. 6-8 ARF is also 
independently associated with early mortality 
following cardiac surgery, even after adjustment for 
comorbidities and post-operative complications. 16 
These findings are of great clinical importance. 
Inconsistent with our findings, many other studies 
have questioned the role of intermittent furosemide 
therapy in the prevention of ARF. 17 In a recent 
randomized clinical trial by Mahesh et al., 10 and 
Faritous et al. 18 furosemide-infusion did not showed 
any benefit in high-risk cardiac surgical patients and 
despite an increase in urinary output with 
furosemide, there was no decrease in renal injury, 
and no decrease in incidence of renal dysfunction. It 
could be concluded that the intermittent furosemide 
therapy, only increases urinary output and is not 
effective in the prevention of ARF. Moreover, we 
showed that in some parameters, intermittent 
furosemide therapy might deteriorate some of the 
renal function test indices in patients undergoing 
CABG with CPB. 
Could we conclude that intermittent furosemide 
therapy is not effective in the prevention of ARF? 
We are not reaching to this final conclusion in this 
research; however, there are studies demonstrating 
that in cardiac surgery patients, perioperative </p>

<p>furosemide administration could not reduce the 
patients' need for renal replacement therapy. 19,20 
Hence, other studies have failed to demonstrate any 
benefit from administration of perioperative 
furosemide in patients undergoing cardiac surgery; 
our study demonstrated that perioperative 
furosemide in cardiac surgery patients has no 
superiority even compared with placebo. 
Finally, this study demonstrated that in patients 
undergoing CABG with CPB, intermittent 
furosemide administration has no documented 
benefit regarding kidney protection; even, adding 
furosemide to the intra-prime volume or 
intermittent doses of furosemide administered 
during CPB should be regarded cautiously, 
especially in patients with decreased urinary output; 
this finding which is a novel finding from the 
current study may be controversial with some of the 
routine practice that anesthesiologists do during 
daily CABG cases. 
Limitations 
The main limitation of this study is its short term 
follow up. However we took advantage of a relatively 
large sample size and the close similarity between 
groups in most of the potentially confounding 
variables. Also, we did not perform post-hoc analysis 
for ANOVA; so we had limitations regarding the 
completion of ANOVA analysis. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors would like to acknowledge the kind 
cooperation of physicians and nurses in cardiac 
surgery operating room and cardiac ICU, Shahid 
Rajaei Heart Center, Tehran, Iran, for their kind 
cooperation and support. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interests </p>

<p>Authors have no conflict of interests. </p>



<p>www.mui.ac.ir </p>



<p>Furosemide as prophylaxis of ARF in CABG </p>





</text></tei>