<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4356689" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: In the present study, we developed a self-assembled biodegradable polyglutamic 
acid (PGA)-based formulation of amphotericin B (AmB) and evaluated its in vitro antifungal 
potential against Candida albicans. The AmB-loaded PGA nanoparticles were prepared in-house 
and had a mean size dimension of around 98±2 nm with a zeta potential of -35.2±7.3 mV. 
Spectroscopic studies revealed that the drug predominantly acquires an aggregated form inside 
the formulation with an aggregation ratio above 2. The PGA-based AmB formulation was 
shown to be highly stable in phosphate-buffered saline as well as in serum (only 10%-20% 
of the drug was released after 10 days). The AmB−PGA nanoparticles were less toxic to red 
blood cells (15% lysis at an AmB concentration of 100 µg/mL after 24 hours) when compared 
with Fungizone </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, a commercial antifungal product. An MTT assay showed that the viability 
of mammalian cells (KB and RAW 264.7) was negligibly affected at AmB concentrations as 
high as 200 µg/mL. Histopathological examination of mouse kidney revealed no signs of tis-
sue necrosis. The AmB−PGA formulation showed potent antimicrobial activity similar to that 
of Fungizone against C. albicans. Interestingly, AmB-bearing PGA nanoparticles were found 
to inhibit biofilm formation to a considerable extent. In summary, AmB−PGA nanoparticles 
showed highly attenuated toxicity when compared with Fungizone, while retaining equivalent 
active antifungal properties. This study indicates that the AmB−PGA preparation could be a 
promising treatment for various fungal infections. 
Amphotericin B (AmB), a broad-spectrum antifungal agent, is a polyene-based 
compound that has a propensity to aggregate in an aqueous environment. 
1,2 Exploiting 
its exclusive physicochemical properties, a commercial antifungal product known as 
Fungizone 
® (AmB-D) was introduced to treat various life-threatening fungal infections. </p>

<p>3,4   Fungizone is basically a micellar deoxycholate-based formulation of AmB. 
Effective antifungal therapy often requires long treatment regimens lasting up to 
30 days; this in turn leads to various toxic manifestations (eg, nausea, chills, fevers, 
vomiting). 
5,6 Moreover, clinical use of AmB-D is often marred with acute and chronic 
infusion-related toxicities, the most serious being dose-dependent nephrotoxicity. </p>

<p>5,7,8   To circumvent AmB-D-related toxicity issues, various lipid formulations of AmB 
have been developed, including the commercially available AmBisome 
® (AmB-L), 
ie, liposomal AmB. 
2,9-11 AmB-L has a far superior therapeutic index with highly </p>

<p>correspondence: Mohammad Owais 
Interdisciplinary Biotechnology 
Unit, aligarh Muslim University, 
aligarh 202002, India 
Tel +91 571 272 0388 
Fax +91 571 272 1776 
email mdowais2012@gmail.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
5 March 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1770 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>attenuated toxicity when compared with AmB-D. However, 
the complex process involved in the production of AmB-
L, 
12,13 its high cost, 
14,15 and issues related to stability tend to 
offset its benefits and limit its utility, especially in third world 
countries. Since lipids are the principal constituent of the 
formulation, it is difficult to imagine AmB-L ever becoming 
affordable. Efforts to make generic forms that have efficacy 
comparable with existing formulations have met with limited 
success. 
16,17 Furthermore, the existing AmB formulations are 
not therapeutically bioequivalent and are reported to have 
clear differences in toxicity. 
16,18 Taking into consideration 
the various limitations associated with lipid formulations 
of AmB, 
19 it would be desirable to develop alternative drug 
delivery systems that can be used widely in the treatment of 
an array of fungal diseases. 
Much preclinical research on polymeric nanoparticles 
has suggested some potential for delivery of active drug 
substances. 
20 Polymer nanoparticulate technologies can be 
used to improve water solubility and bioavailability of the 
active drug component. 
21,22 Nanoparticles shield the drug 
from interacting directly with normal healthy cells, thus 
minimizing its detrimental effects to a considerable extent. 
Biodegradable polymers have also been shown to optimize 
pharmacokinetics (including controlled and prolonged 
release of the drug with tissue retention), improve efficacy, 
and address drug safety issues. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Our earlier efforts to develop a biodegradable polymer 
drug complex based on PLGA (poly[lactic-co-glycolic acid]) 
have been quite encouraging, 
24,25 and led us to hypothesize 
that a delivery vehicle based on an analogous polymer, ie, 
polyglutamic acid (PGA), would have potential to circumvent 
the toxicity of AmB to a greater extent. PGA was selected for 
its biodegradable, nontoxic, and biocompatible properties. 
Pilot studies established PGA to be nonimmunogenic and 
well tolerated, even at high doses. Moreover, nanoparticles 
composed of PGA have been shown to immobilize proteins, 
peptides, and other related chemicals onto their surfaces 
and/or interior bulk. 
26,27 PGA has also been extensively evalu-
ated in cancer chemotherapy and been implied at various 
stages of clinical trials. 
28-30 Moreover, the development of 
PGA based nanoparticles involves simple and easy prepara-
tion protocol, making it a superb strategy for the encapsula-
tion of AmB. AmB-bearing PGA nanoparticles prepared 
in-house were investigated for their physical characteristics, 
stability, safety (both in vitro and in vivo), and in vitro 
antifungal efficacy in comparison with two commonly used 
formula tions of AmB, ie, AmBisome and Fungizone. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
chemicals </p>

<p>Poly-l-glutamic acid sodium salt (20-40 kDa and 50-70 kDa; 
catalog numbers G0546 and G0421, respectively), AmB 
(European Pharmacopoeia reference standard), polyvinyl 
alcohol (PVA), Roswell Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) 
1640 medium, and dimethyl sulfoxide were purchased from 
Sigma Aldrich (St Louis, MO, USA). The antifungal agents 
AmBisome (Gilead Sciences Inc, San Dimas, CA, USA) and 
Fungizone (Apothecon, Princeton, NJ, USA) were reconsti-
tuted according to the manufacturers' instructions. KB cells 
(HeLa contaminant, cervical adenocarcinoma-derived 
epithelial cells) and mouse leukemia RAW 264.7 cells 
(macrophage-like, Abelson leukemia virus transformed 
cell line derived from BALB/c mice) were sourced from 
the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Manassas, 
VA, USA). Detection kits for liver and kidney function 
test parameters were purchased from Span Diagnostics Ltd 
(Mumbai, India). The rest of the chemicals were of analytical 
grade of purity and sourced locally. </p>

<p>Fungal isolates </p>

<p>The test strain of Candida albicans (ATCC 18804) was 
obtained from the ATCC while Candida glabrata (MTCC 
3019) was sourced from the Microbial Type Culture 
Collection (MTCC, Chandigarh, India). Sabouraud dextrose 
agar/broth was used for growing both the fungal strains. The 
C. albicans and C. glabrata strains were characterized using 
Hi-Chrome agar as well as germ tube formation with a stan-
dard protocol prior to its use in various studies. C. albicans 
(ATCC 10231) was used as a quality control strain. </p>

<p>animals </p>

<p>Inbred female Balb/c mice (aged 6-8 weeks, mean weight 
20±2 g) were obtained from the animal facility at the Indian 
Institute of Toxicological Research, Lucknow, India. The 
animals were then acclimatized for a few days under standard 
husbandry conditions, ie, room temperature (22°C±3°C), 
relative humidity (65%±10%), and a 12-hour light/dark cycle. 
They had free access to a standard dry pellet diet and water 
ad libitum under strict hygienic conditions. The animals were 
anesthetized with ketamine 5 mg/kg and xylazine 4 mg/kg 
prior to being euthanized. Humane endpoints were applied 
for mice that survived at the conclusion of the experiment. In 
all experimental procedures, efforts were made to minimize 
pain and suffering. All animal experiments were reviewed 
and approved by the Institutional Animal Ethics Committee </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1771 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>of the Interdisciplinary Biotechnology Unit, Aligarh 
Muslim University, India and were performed according 
to the national regulatory guidelines issued by Committee 
for the Purpose of Control and Supervision of Experiments 
on Animals (CPCSEA), Government of India (approval 
identifier 332/CPCSEA). </p>

<p>Preparation of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>Preparation of PGA nanoparticles was achieved following 
a published method that was modified in our laboratory. </p>

<p>31   Briefly, 10 mg of PGA and 5 mg of AmB were dissolved 
in 10 mL of dimethyl sulfoxide in a 30 mL sample vial. 
The above solution was then added dropwise to the PVA 
solution (10 mg/0.5 mL) under constant stirring. The AmB/ 
PGA mixtures were stirred at room temperature for 1 hour. 
To prepare the nanoparticles, the solution was dialyzed 
against deionized water (500 mL) for 24 hours (Spectra/ 
Por 
® membrane tubing, molecular weight cutoff 2 kDa, 
Spectrum Labs, Rancho Dominguez, CA, USA). After 
dialysis, the particles were centrifuged at 20,000 g for 1 hour 
and the nanoparticles were washed with deionized water 
several times to remove free PVA. The precipitated mass 
was probe-sonicated briefly, followed by dialysis to remove 
free AmB. The solution was then filtered using a Millipore 
Express Plus Membrane microsyringe filter (hydrophilic, 
polyethersulfone, 0.22 µm) (Millipore, Bangalore, India). 
Finally, the solution was freeze-dried to yield a yellow 
fluffy product. </p>

<p>Determination of entrapment efficiency 
of Pga-intercalated amB </p>

<p>The entrapment efficiency (EE) of AmB in the PGA for-
mulation was determined by dissolving an aliquot of the 
AmB−PGA formulation in methanol. To rule out the pos-
sibility that the observed results were due to the AmB−PGA 
nanoparticles only and not because of the PGA molecule 
itself, we included plain PGA nanoparticles that were not 
loaded with AmB as a control throughout the study; these 
are referred to herein as "sham PGA" nanoparticles. 
The AmB content was determined using a high 
performance liquid chromatography method following the 
published procedure. 
32 A standard calibration curve of the 
drug was plotted at 405 nm by determining the area under 
the curve corresponding to the increasing amount of drug 
(3.125-200 ng of AmB equivalent in a 20 µL sample injec-
tion volume). The highest AmB concentration was 10 µg/mL 
(equivalent to 200 ng of AmB in 20 µL). Dilutions of AmB </p>

<p>were performed in methanol to ensure that AmB remained 
in the monomeric form. Details of the high-performance 
liquid chromatography procedure are provided in the 
Supplementary materials section. 
The percent EE was calculated as the percentage of 
the ratio between the entrapped AmB and the total amount 
of AmB added at the beginning during preparation of the 
formulation: </p>

<p>% EE 
Amount of AmB entrapped 
Total amount of AmB added 
100 
= 
× </p>

<p>Determination of particle size and zeta 
potential of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>The zeta potential gives an indication of the charge acquired 
by a particulate system on its suspension in aqueous medium. 
The zeta potential of the nanoparticles was determined using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">DTS software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Malvern Instruments Limited, Malvern, UK</rs>) based on M3-PALS technology. The concentration 
of the AmB−PGA formulation used was 10 
-4 M. Particle 
size was determined by photon correlation spectroscopy 
(90Plus/BI-MAS, Brookhaven Instruments, Holtville, NY, 
USA). Samples were filtered using a 0.22 µm syringe filter 
(polyethersulfone, Millipore) to remove contamination with 
dust particles. Dynamic light scattering measurements were 
carried out using DynaPro-TC-04 equipment (Protein Solu-
tions, Wyatt Technology, Santa Barbara, CA, USA) equipped 
with a temperature-controlled microsampler. The size and 
surface morphology of the AmB-loaded nanoparticles were 
characterized using an electron microscope (CM-10, Philips, 
Hamburg, Germany). For transmission electron microscopy 
studies, the AmB−PGA formulation was used at a concen-
tration of 10 µg/mL AmB equivalents in double-distilled 
water. The details of these procedures are provided in the 
Supplementary materials section. </p>

<p>Pga nanoparticle-mediated transfer 
of entrapped calcein to macrophages </p>

<p>Successful elimination of the intracellular pathogen 
C. albicans requires effective delivery of a drug pay load 
to the infected macrophages. We determined the uptake of 
PGA-encapsulated fluorescent dye (calcein) by macrophages 
to assess the ability of the newly developed PGA formula-
tion to home the intercalated drug to C. albicans-harboring 
macrophages. The details of the uptake study are provided 
in the Supplementary materials section. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1772 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>spectrophotometric analysis 
of amB-Pga formulation </p>

<p>Ultraviolet spectroscopic analysis of various formulations of 
AmB was carried out in the range 300-450 nm on a double-
beam spectrophotometer (model V-750, Jasco Inc, Easton, 
MD, USA) operated at a resolution of 1 nm. AmB is known 
to give four absorption peaks. The aggregation ratio was 
calculated as the ratio of peak I (315-340 nm) to peak IV 
(410 nm). 
33 Fungizone and the AmB−PGA formulation were 
both scanned at the same concentration (10 
-5 M). </p>

<p>In vitro release kinetic studies </p>

<p>In vitro release of AmB from the AmB−PGA complex in 
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and serum was evaluated 
by dialysis, 
34 as standardized in our laboratory. The quanti-
fication was carried out using high-performance liquid chro-
matography 
32 as described in the Supplementary materials 
section. In order to determine the release kinetics, a stock 
solution of AmB−PGA nanoparticles was prepared in water 
at a concentration of 1,000 mg/L AmB equivalents. The 
aqueous solution of nanoparticles (1 mL) was added to either 
20 mM sterile PBS (pH 7.4) or serum (1 mL, containing 5% 
dimethyl sulfoxide). The final concentration of AmB−PGA 
was 500 µg/mL AmB equivalents (total amount of AmB, 
1 mg in 2 mL). The PBS and serum also contained a small 
amount of sodium azide to avoid microbial growth. The 
AmB−PGA solution (2 mL) was placed in a dialysis bag 
(molecular weight cutoff 12-14 kDa) and dialyzed against 
50 mL of PBS (pH 7.4) containing 5% dimethyl sulfoxide 
at 37°C. The dialysis medium was completely removed at 
regular time intervals for analysis of drug concentration and 
replaced with fresh medium to prevent drug saturation (main-
taining strict sink conditions throughout the experiment). 
Release runs were continued for 240 hours. The absorbance 
of the collected samples was measured at 405 nm by high-
performance liquid chromatography in aqueous methanol 
(50% v/v). The AmB concentration was extrapolated from 
the calibration curve of AmB in aqueous methanol (50% 
v/v). The calculated amount of the released drug was plotted 
against time. The results recorded are the mean of three runs 
carried out independently. </p>

<p>Drug toxicity studies </p>

<p>In vitro red blood cell lysis test </p>

<p>Fresh blood (15-20 mL) was kindly provided by the 
blood bank at Jawaharlal Nehru Medical College, Aligarh 
Muslim University, Aligarh, and collected in anticoagulant 
(ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid 1 mg/mL, at 10% w/v) </p>

<p>syringes, followed by centrifugation at 1,000 g for 15 minutes 
at 4°C. Plasma was carefully aspirated and the exposed buffy 
coat was removed and discarded. The red blood cells were 
washed three times by centrifugation (1,000 g for 15 minutes 
at 4°C) and suspended in five volumes of normal saline (NaCl 
0.9% w/v). The cells were then resuspended in 4 mL of saline, 
counted in a Neubauer™ chamber (Splabor, São Paulo, 
Brazil), and resuspended again until the desired concentra-
tion (5×10 
7 cells/mL) was achieved. AmB-D, AmB-L, and 
empty PGA vesicles were included as controls and prepared 
according to the manufacturers' protocol in double-distilled 
sterile water (Sigma-Aldrich). 
To study the extent of hemolysis, 1 mL of red blood cells 
(5×10  7 cells/mL) was incubated with 1 mL of the various 
AmB formulations (containing 1, 5, 10, 50, and 100 µg/ 
mL AmB equivalents) at 37°C for 1 hour and for 24 hours. 
The free form of AmB was dissolved in 50 µL of dimethyl 
sulfoxide and made up to a final volume of 1 mL with PBS 
(final 5% dimethyl sulfoxide). After the stipulated periods 
of time, the reaction mixture was centrifuged at 1,200 g. The 
supernatant was then collected and analyzed by ultraviolet-
visible spectroscopy (λ max =576 nm) for released hemoglobin. 
Triton X-100 (nonionic surfactant) at a concentration of 0.1% 
was used as a positive control for 100% cell lysis. The result 
was expressed graphically as a percentage of 100% cell lysis 
and was determined by the following equation: </p>

<p>Percent hemolysis 
Abs Abs 
Abs 
Abs 
100 </p>

<p>T 
C </p>

<p>100% 
C </p>

<p>= 
− 
− 
× </p>

<p>where Abs T is the absorbance of the supernatant from samples 
incubated with the drugs, Abs C is the absorbance of the super-
natant from the control (PBS), and Abs 100% is absorbance in 
the presence of 0.1% Triton X-100. The results are the mean 
of three independent experiments. </p>

<p>In vitro cytotoxicity test </p>

<p>KB cells and RAW 264.7 cells were plated in 96-well flat 
bottom tissue culture plates (NalgeNunc International, 
Rochester, NY, USA) at a density of 4×10 
4 cells/mL and 
1×10 
5 cells/mL, respectively, in RPMI 1640 medium and 
10% fetal calf serum and allowed to adhere overnight at 
37°C in 5% CO 2 . The cells were treated by adding 100 µL 
of the AmB−PGA formulation at various concentrations (1, 
5, 10, 50, 100, and 200 µg/mL AmB equivalents) into the 
respective well. AmB-D, AmB-L, and pure AmB used in 
preparation of the complex were taken as the controls. The 
plates were then incubated for 24 hours at 37°C in 5% CO 2 . </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1773 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>Cell viability was evaluated using the 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-
2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay, as 
follows. After washing the cells, 200 µL of a 0.5 mg/mL 
MTT solution in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium was 
added to each well and incubated at 37°C for 2 hours. The 
supernatants were removed, and 200 µL of extraction solution 
was added in order to solubilize the formazan salt. After 30 
minutes at room temperature, the absorbance of each well 
was measured at 550 nm and the percentage of living cells 
was calculated using the following formula: </p>

<p>Percent 
Sample absorbance blank absorbance 
Co 
cell viability 
= 
− 
n ntrol absorbance blank absorbance 
100 
− 
× </p>

<p>where blank absorbance is the medium alone and control absor-
bance is cells with medium alone. All assays were carried out 
in quadruplicate and the results are expressed as the mean. </p>

<p>liver and kidney function test </p>

<p>A single injection of AmB−PGA (containing 5, 10, and 
15 mg/kg body weight AmB equivalent in 200 µL), was 
administered via the lateral tail vein to healthy female 
Balb/c mice. AmB-D was administered at a concentration 
of 5 mg/kg body weight. Twenty-four hours later, blood was 
collected by retro-orbital puncture from the mice in the vari-
ous experimental groups into lithium heparin Microtainers </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>(BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA) and spun at 
2,000 g for 10 minutes at 4°C to isolate the plasma. The 
samples were frozen at -80°C until use. Serum chemistry 
analysis was performed for investigation of creatinine, alanine 
aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase, and blood urea 
nitrogen levels as per the respective guidelines provided by 
the manufacturer of each detection kit. The data recorded are 
the mean of three experiments carried out independently. </p>

<p>histopathological studies </p>

<p>The toxic effects of AmB−PGA nanoparticles on the kid-
neys of the experimental animals were also assessed by 
histopathological studies. The kidneys of experimental mice 
from the control (PBS), AmB-D, AmB-L, and AmB−PGA 
nanoparticle-treated groups were processed as reported pre-
viously. 
35 The details of the experimental procedure used are 
provided in the Supplementary materials section. </p>

<p>In vitro susceptibility testing </p>

<p>The broth microdilution method, as described by the Clinical 
and Laboratory Standards Institute (M27-A2), was used to 
determine the anti-Candida activity of the various AmB </p>

<p>formulations. 
36 The antifungal activity of AmB was evaluated 
over a final concentration range of 0.015-8 µg/mL. The wells 
containing fungal inoculum with various concentrations 
of drugs and appropriate controls (drug-free as well as 
inoculum-free) were incubated at 35°C for 48 hours. For 
AmB, the endpoint is the lowest concentration that inhibits 
visual growth. An endpoint score of 0 (100% inhibition) 
was taken as the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC). 
Minimum fungicidal concentrations (MFCs) were deter-
mined by seeding the entire volumes from all clear MIC 
wells with the highest inoculum onto Sabouraud dextrose 
agar plates. The MFC is the lowest drug concentration that 
kills 99.9% (with less than three colonies remaining) of the 
final inoculum. All assays were performed in duplicate and 
repeated at least twice. Details of the procedure are provided 
in the Supplementary materials section. </p>

<p>Time-kill analysis </p>

<p>C. albicans was grown overnight at 35°C on Sabouraud 
dextrose agar. Isolated colonies were selected and sus-
pended in 0.9% NaCl to a turbidity equivalent to that of 
a 0.5 McFarland standard. Wells containing RPMI 1640 
medium (buffered with morpholinepropanesulfonic acid 
0.165 M to pH 7.0) plus AmB−PGA nanoparticles or 
AmB at 4× the MIC or no antibiotic (growth control) were 
inoculated with the yeast suspension to a final concentration 
of ∼10 
5 colony forming units (CFU) per mL. The cultures were 
incubated at 35°C for up to 24 hours. At the indicated times, 
aliquots were removed and the numbers of CFU/mL were 
determined on Sabouraud dextrose agar after serial dilutions 
in PBS. The assay was performed in quadruplicate. Each result 
is representative of at least three separate experiments. </p>

<p>In vitro antifungal activity of amB-Pga 
against intracellular C. albicans </p>

<p>RAW 264.7 cells were cultured in 24-well plates at a density 
of 5×10 
5 cells/well. After 2 hours, an inoculum containing 
1×10 
6 CFU of C. albicans was cocultured with the adhered 
monolayer. After a 30-minute incubation period, 
37 the non-
ingested yeast was removed by washing the monolayer three 
times with Hank's Balanced Salt Solution (Sigma-Aldrich). 
The macrophages were reincubated in the presence of the 
AmB−PGA formulation at various concentrations (1, 5, 10, 
and 50 µg/mL AmB equivalent). AmB-D and AmB-L were 
included as controls. Percentage of infection was calculated 
by lysing the macrophages (after 24 hours of treatment) 
with Triton X-100 (0.2%) and subculturing in Sabouraud 
dextrose agar plates, and compared with an untreated control. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1774 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>Experiments were carried out in triplicate and the results are 
expressed as mean of the data obtained. </p>

<p>Biofilm formation </p>

<p>Biofilms were formed in the wells of microtiter plates as previ-
ously described. 
38 Fresh C. albicans cells grown overnight in 
an orbital shaker at 30°C were harvested and washed in sterile 
PBS (10 mM phosphate buffer, 2.7 mM potassium chloride, 
137 mM sodium chloride, pH 7.4). The cells were resuspended 
in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with l-glutamine and 
buffered with morpholinepropanesulfonic acid to a cellular 
density equivalent to 1×10 
6 cells/mL. All experiments were 
performed on commercially available, presterilized, poly-
styrene, flat-bottomed, 96-well microtiter plates (Corning 
Incorporated, Corning, NY, USA). Biofilms were formed by 
pipetting 100 µL of the standardized cell suspensions into 
selected wells of the microtiter plate and incubating the plate 
for 48 hours at 37°C. After biofilm formation, the medium was 
discarded and nonadherent cells were removed by thoroughly 
washing the biofilms three times in sterile PBS. </p>

<p>Visualization of inactivation of C. albicans 
cells in biofilm </p>

<p>Preliminary microscopic visualization of C. albicans biofilms 
after treatment with the AmB−PGA formulation was done by 
phase contrast microscopy, 
39 details of which are provided 
in the Supplementary materials section. </p>

<p>scanning electron microscopy studies 
of C. albicans biofilm </p>

<p>An already published protocol for scanning electron 
microscopy (SEM) of C. albicans biofilm was followed. </p>

<p>38   C. albicans biofilms were formed on plastic Thermanox 
coverslip disks (15 mm diameter; NalgeNunc International) 
in six-well cell culture plates (Corning Incorporated) by dis-
pensing standardized cell suspensions (4 mL of a suspension 
containing 1.0×10 
6 cells/mL of RPMI 1640 medium) onto 
the appropriate disks and incubating the plates at 37°C for 
24 hours. After washing with PBS, a AmB−PGA formula-
tion (5 µg/mL) was added to the preformed biofilms and the 
plates were incubated for a further 48 hours at 37°C. Control 
biofilms were incubated in RPMI 1640 medium only. After 
incubation, the biofilms were washed with PBS and placed 
in fixative (4% formaldehyde [v/v] and 1% glutaraldehyde 
[v/v] in PBS) overnight. The samples were rinsed in 0.1 M 
phosphate buffer (twice for 3 minutes each time) and then 
placed in 1% Zetterquist's osmium for 30 minutes. The 
samples were subsequently dehydrated in a series of ethanol </p>

<p>washes (70% ethanol for 10 minutes, 95% ethanol for 
10 minutes, 100% ethanol for 20 minutes), and then treated 
(twice for 5 minutes each time) with hexamethyldisilazane 
(Polysciences Inc, Warrington, PA, USA) and finally air-
dried in a desiccator. The specimens were coated with 40% 
gold-60% palladium. The samples were then observed by 
SEM (JSM-6510LV, JEOL, Tokyo, Japan) at 15 kV. </p>

<p>Biofilm quantitation by XTT assay </p>

<p>A semiquantitative measure of the antibiofilm activ-
ity of the PGA nanoparticles was performed by XTT (2, 
3-bis(2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl)-5-[(phenylamino) 
carbonyl]-2H-tetrazolium hydroxide) reduction assay as 
described elsewhere. 
38 Briefly, XTT solution was prepared 
by mixing 0.5 mg/mL XTT in Ringer's lactate. This solu-
tion was filter-sterilized and stored at -70°C. Prior to each 
assay, an aliquot of stock XTT was thawed, and menadione 
(10 mM prepared in acetone; Sigma-Aldrich) was added 
to obtain a final concentration of 1 µM. The solution was 
filter-sterilized using a 0.22 µm syringe filter (Millipore). 
The biofilms (developed as above) were then incubated in 
the presence of the different concentrations of AmB−PGA 
formulation (final concentrations from 0.195 to 100 µg/mL) 
for 48 hours. After treatment with the AmB−PGA formula-
tion, 100 µL of XTT was added to each prewashed biofilm 
(to remove nonadhered cells). The plates were then incu-
bated in the dark for up to 2 hours at 37°C. A colorimetric 
change in the XTT reduction assay, a direct correlation of 
the metabolic activity of the biofilm, was then measured in 
a microplate reader (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) at 450 
nm and expressed as percent viability in comparison with 
control cells. Untreated biofilms containing RPMI 1640 
medium were included as positive controls. AmB-D and 
AmB-L were also included in the study as controls. Wells 
without biofilms served as a blank. Four replicate biofilms 
were included for each experiment. </p>

<p>Percent 
viability </p>

<p>Sample absorbance blank absorbance 
Contr 
= 
− 
o ol absorbance blank absorbance 
100 
− 
× </p>

<p>where blank absorbance is the medium alone and control 
absorbance is fungal cells with medium alone. </p>

<p>Biofilm time-kill curves </p>

<p>Biofilms were grown under shaking (100 rpm) for 24 or 
48 hours at 37°C. Various AmB formulations were then added 
to the preformed biofilms, and the plates were incubated for 
selected time periods (2, 4, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours). Antifungal </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1775 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>effects were monitored by a metabolic assay based on the 
reduction of XTT as described above. 
38 Details of the experi-
ment are provided in the Supplementary materials section. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>In order to assess the statistical differences among various 
groups, the data were analyzed using the Student's t-test 
and one way analysis of variance (Holm-Sidak method), 
using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Sigma-Plot</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">10</rs> software. P-values &lt;0.05 were 
considered to be statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results and discussion </p>

<p>Despite a worldwide search during the last three decades for a 
broad-spectrum, nontoxic, and well tolerated antifungal drug, 
AmB remains an ideal therapeutic agent for patients with 
unidentified invasive fungal infections. In the present scenario, 
a cheap, nontoxic, effective, and highly stable delivery system 
for AmB is needed to address the limitations of its existing 
delivery systems. Investigators have employed different water-
soluble polymers to develop encapsulated, conjugated AmB-
based delivery systems, but have met with little success. </p>

<p>40-48   In some of the earlier efforts, polymers synergized the toxicity 
of AmB, 
49 while in others the AmB was unable to retain the 
beneficial physicochemical properties associated with its 
liposomal form (AmB-L). 
50 Although, AmB-cyclodextrin 
complexes showed improved water solubility, 
49,51 they were 
found to be toxic to human red blood cells. 
52,53 On the other 
hand, polyvinylpyrrolidone has been shown to complex AmB, 
but suffers from very low (0.249% w/w) AmB loading. </p>

<p>54   Polymeric micelle systems have also been developed; however, 
encapsulation in the polymeric micelles decreased the in vitro 
antifungal activity of the drug. 
40 Moreover, these micelles have 
been shown to be unstable in the presence of serum due to dis-
ruption of their integrity, 
55 resulting in rapid and near-complete 
release of core-loaded molecules from circulating micelles 
in an uncontrolled fashion. 
56 Herein, we aimed to develop a 
stable, easy-to-prepare, nontoxic preparation of AmB with 
physicochemical characteristics comparable with those shown 
by AmB-L. Replacing the lipid moiety with a water-soluble 
homopolymer could reduce the costs and stability issues 
associated with the lipid components of AmB-L. In addition, </p>

<p>an amphiphilic PGA-based delivery system may have some 
advantages, including biocompatibility, biodegradability, </p>

<p>27,57   negligible toxicity, and cytoplasmic delivery of the entrapped 
molecules. The homopolymer contains carboxylic groups that 
can form ionic complexes with a charged compound such as 
AmB. Furthermore, PGA has the potential to encapsulate or 
immobilize a variety of molecules. 
26,27,57 For example, PGA 
has been used in clinical trials in the form of a covalently 
bound conjugate with paclitaxel (Opaxio, Cell Therapeutics, 
Seattle, WA, USA). </p>

<p>29,30   The low aqueous solubility of amphiphilic AmB 
(1 µg/mL) 
58 makes it a suitable candidate for association 
with an amphiphilic PGA homopolymer. The initial reaction 
of AmB with PGA was carried out in the presence of dimethyl 
sulfoxide, a water-miscible organic solvent. Next, an aqueous 
solution of PVA (a base) was added followed by extensive 
dialysis against water. In high abundance of an aqueous 
environment, AmB can either choose to associate with the 
PGA polymer or can form precipitates. The amphiphilic 
nature of both AmB and the PGA polymer enables them to 
remain in association, resulting in spontaneous formation of 
nanoparticles. The base is added to increase the solubility of 
the PGA, which ensures that the polymer remains in solution. 
The nanoparticles show unusually high stability in the pres-
ence of PVA. 
59,60 The simple and straightforward preparation 
protocol makes development of a AmB−PGA formulation an 
excellent strategy. The AmB−PGA formulation was found 
to be readily and rapidly soluble in water (Table 1). The EE 
was found to be around 20.5% and 45% for the two polymers 
in the 20-40 kDa and 50-70 kDa molecular weight range, 
respectively (Table 1). Since high AmB loading (40%) 
ensures applicability in the clinical setting, the PGA nano-
particle having a molecular weight of 50-70 kDa (with high 
complexation efficiency and aqueous solubility) was used in 
the subsequent studies. </p>

<p>characterization of amB-Pga 
nanoparticles </p>

<p>The AmB−PGA nanoparticles prepared in-house were 
characterized for their size, shape, and zeta potential. The </p>

<p>Table 1 Entrapment efficiency, particle size, and zeta potential of various amphotericin B formulations </p>

<p>Sample 
PGA MW (kDa) 
%EE 
Average zeta 
diameter (nm) </p>

<p>Zeta 
potential (mV) </p>

<p>Z-average </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(nm) </p>

<p>PDI 
Aqueous solubility 
(mg AmB/mL) </p>

<p>amB-Pga 1 50-70 
45.0%±5.2% 
102±7 
-35.2±7.3 
107±0.7 
0.12±0.004 
3.0 
amB-Pga 2 20-40 
20.5%±2.5% 
98±4 
-12.6±2.6 
112±2.0 
0.32±0.003 
1.0 </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Z-average is the intensity weighted hydrodynamic size of a collection of particles measured by dynamic light scattering. 
Abbreviations: AmB, amphotericin B; EE, entrapment efficiency; MW, molecular weight; PDI, polydispersity index; PGA, polyglutamic acid. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1776 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>average zeta diameter and zeta potential of the AmB−PGA 
nanoparticle (molecular weight 50-70 kDa) were found to 
be 102±7 nm and -35.2±0.73 mV, respectively (Table 1). 
Generally, a high zeta potential (either positive or negative), 
more than 30 mV, maintains a stable system. 
61,62 Extremely 
positive or negative zeta potential values cause larger repul-
sive forces; this repulsion between similarly charged par-
ticles prevents aggregation of the particles and thus ensures 
easy redispersion. 
63,64 Thus, it can be said that AmB−PGA 
nanoparticles prepared using a 50-70 kDa molecular weight 
polymer are more stable than nanoparticles prepared with 
PGA having a molecular weight of 20-40 kDa (Table 1). 
The mean size of the AmB−PGA nanoparticle was 
107±0.7 nm as measured by dynamic light scattering 
(Figure 1A). A population of nearly spherical PGA nano-
particles with an average size of 98±2 nm was observed by </p>

<p>transmission electron microscopy (Figure 1B). This is in 
agreement with the sizes determined by dynamic light scat-
tering analysis (average diameter 107±0.7 nm, Figure 1A) 
and nanosizer (102±7 nm, Figure 1C). 
To ascertain their fate after uptake by macrophages, 
calcein-loaded PGA nanoparticles were incubated with 
mouse macrophage cells (thioglycollate elicited). Incubation 
of the PGA nanoparticles resulted in a punctate fluorescence 
pattern owing to their active endocytic uptake by macrophages 
(Figure 1D). Commonly, drugs associated with colloidal 
carriers enable higher accumulation of drug inside macro-
phages and a small size enables them to be taken up through 
endocytosis via clathrin, caveolae, or specific independent 
receptors. 
65,66 The particle-loaded macrophages act as a 
secondary depot for the drug. Once internalized, a direct 
interaction of AmB with the intracellular yeast seems to be </p>

<p>Figure 1 size distribution and morphology of amB-Pga nanoparticles. 
Notes: (A) The Z-average diameter of the amB-Pga nanoparticles determined by dynamic light scattering measurements was 107±0.7 nm. (B) Transmission electron 
microscopy showed that the amB-Pga nanoparticles were spherical in shape with an average size of 98±2 nm. (C) Particle size distribution of amB-Pga nanoparticles 
assessed by photon correlation spectroscopy. (D1) Phase contrast light and (D2) fluorescence micrographs of normal peritoneal macrophages after their interaction with 
calcein (fluorescent probe)-loaded PGA nanoparticles. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; Pga, polyglutamic acid. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1777 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>plausible. The released AmB can then readily act upon the 
C. albicans cells, resulting in effective killing. </p>

<p>spectroscopic studies </p>

<p>Earlier studies have shown that the degree of aggregation of 
AmB is directly correlated with its toxicity, 
33,67,68 antimicro-
bial activity, 
67,69,70 and stability. 
71,72 In aqueous dispersions, 
the antifungal compound AmB has a tendency to exist in 
three different forms, ie, a monomer state, a soluble state, 
and an insoluble aggregate state. 
3,73 Small aggregates or 
soluble oligomers are responsible for the toxic reactions in 
mammalian cells and are usually the predominant species 
present in AmB-D solutions. 
3,74 Association of monomers 
with ergosterol leads to pore formation in the fungal mem-
brane, while the oligomeric form of the drug complexes with 
cell membrane sterols in mammalian cells, which facilitates 
leakage of electrolytes. 
3,74 This drug-sterol interaction can 
lead to systemic toxicity, including adverse renal, hepatic, 
and cardiac effects, along with blood dyscrasias and death. </p>

<p>5   The oligomers also seem to be susceptible to oxidation, which 
may enhance their toxicity. 
71 However, when AmB in solu-
tion is below the critical concentration (1 µM) required for 
self-association, toxicity against fungi is still observed, while 
toxic effects on mammalian cells are minimized. </p>

<p>75,76   The ultraviolet-visible spectra of polyenes (such as AmB) 
are very sensitive to conformational changes induced by differ-
ent molecular interactions, including aggregation. It has been 
reported that the monomeric form of AmB absorbs maximally 
at about 405-409 nm (λ max ), 
77 while soluble self-aggregates 
display an absorption with a λ max of about 328-340 nm. </p>

<p>73   In higher order aggregates, the maximum absorption shifts to 
wavelengths lower than 322 nm. Nonetheless, the optimum 
aggregation state is not simple, and cannot be defined using 
a single measure. 
In order to assess the aggregation state of AmB inside 
PGA nanoparticles, we performed ultraviolet-visible spec-
troscopy. When AmB−PGA nanoparticles were suspended 
in water, shifting of λ max toward a shorter wavelength was 
observed (ie, a hypsochromic effect), suggesting the presence 
of aggregated AmB. The principal absorption was found to 
be at around 345 nm, with AmB showing a minimal peak at 
410 nm (Figure 2A). As AmB is known to exist in monomeric 
form in organic solvents, we also determined its absorption 
spectrum in dimethyl sulfoxide. AmB showed an absorption 
pattern characteristic of a heptaene chromophore, with the 
lowest peak at around 355 nm and the highest peak at 415 nm 
(Figure 2B). The spectral modifications induced by aggrega-
tion may be represented by the ratio of absorbance at two 
different peaks (A 340 /A 410 ), ie, 340 nm (peak I) and 410 nm 
(peak IV). The degree of aggregation of AmB can be easily 
monitored using this ratio. 
33 The higher the aggregation ratio, 
the lower the amount of monomeric AmB present. When the 
PGA nanoparticles were dispersed in water, this ratio was 
found to be 2.39, whereas when dimethyl sulfoxide was used 
as the solvent, this ratio decreased to 0.24. 
Absorption peaks at a lower wavelength are gener-
ally observed when aggregated AmB is complexed with 
deoxycholate 
77 or upon formation of superaggregates by 
heat treatment of AmB alone. 
73 Taken together, these results 
suggest that AmB is present in a highly aggregated form </p>

<p>Figure 2 absorption spectra of the amB-Pga nanoparticle formulation and commercially available formulations of amB (amB-l, amB-D) in (A) aqueous medium and 
(B) organic solvent. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® ; Pga, polyglutamic acid. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1778 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>inside PGA nanoparticles. Interestingly, it has been shown 
that AmB exists in a highly aggregated form in both AmB-D 
and AmB-L formulations. However, in AmB-L, there is an 
hypsochromic (blue) shift of 7−9 nm at λ max . 
78 This shift could 
be attributed to the close association between AmB and the 
lipid bilayer in AmB-L. 
79 Interaction of AmB with the PGA 
polymer in an aqueous environment results in formation 
of AmB aggregates that become entrapped inside the self-
assembled PGA nanoparticles during their formation. </p>

<p>Release profile for AmB nanoparticle 
formulation </p>

<p>The PGA nanoformulation developed in the present study 
was assessed for its degradability under simulated physiologi-
cal conditions (in PBS and in serum). The AmB−PGA nano-
particle was found to be stable in PBS, with 2.30%±0.09% 
of the total AmB being released into PBS after 24 hours 
of incubation (Figure 3A). This was followed by sustained 
release that continued for 240 hours; 13.6%±0.21% of the 
drug was released over this period of time. A latency period 
characterized by no drug release is observed in the initial 
phase. The occurrence of a lag time in the release process 
indicates that the polymer has to be degraded to a consider-
able extent before the drug can leave the nanoparticle. 
In order to assess the fate of AmB−PGA nanoparticles in 
the plasma circulation, a simulation study involving incuba-
tion in mouse serum at 37°C was performed. The AmB−PGA 
nanoparticles showed high stability in serum, with only 
20.9%±4.21% of AmB released from the nanoparticles after 
240 hours (Figure 3B). Sustained stability in serum ensures that 
AmB does not bind to low-density plasma lipoproteins. </p>

<p>76   The stability of encapsulated AmB in serum has been 
extensively studied in other systems, including ones derived 
from polymers. 
80,81 The AmB−PGA formulation showed bet-
ter stability in PBS (pH 7.4) than AmB polymeric micelle sys-
tems, such as AmB-PEG-PLA (∼45% of AmB was released 
after 24 hours), 
82 AmB-poly-lactic glycolic acid/dextran 
micelles (∼20% AmB released after 24 hours), AmB-PEG-
PLA polymersomes (∼50% AmB released after 24 hours), </p>

<p>83   and AmB-poly(2-ethyl-2-oxazoline)-block-poly-(aspartic 
acid) polyion complex micelles (∼40% AmB released after 
24 hours). 
84 Furthermore, the stability of these polymeric 
micelle systems was only examined in PBS, and there have 
been no data available for serum. The release pattern of the 
AmB−PGA nanoparticles in PBS and serum was similar to 
the stability data of AmBisome. The high stability of the 
AmB−PGA formulation could be attributed (in part) to the 
stabilizing properties of the PVA 
59,60 used in the preparatory 
cocktail during formation of the nanoparticles. </p>

<p>In vitro toxicity tests </p>

<p>Before introducing the novel formulation of AmB−PGA as 
a potential antifungal therapy approach, we investigated the 
associated intrinsic toxicity issues both in vitro and in vivo. 
Given that hemolysis is a serious toxic manifestation of 
AmB-D, 
85 we tested for acute toxicity using an in vitro red 
blood cell toxicity test. The association of AmB with poly-
mers resulted in a large decrease in their hemolytic activity. 
At a lower concentration (1 µg/mL) and shorter duration 
(1 hour), no significant hemolysis was observed with any 
of the formulations (Figure 4A). In fact, no hemolysis was 
observed with the PGA formulation across the whole range </p>

<p>Figure 3 Time course of amB release from Pga formulation over a period of 10 days. 
Notes: amB-loaded Pga nanoparticles were incubated in (A) sterile 20 mM phosphate-buffered saline (ph 7.4) and (B) serum. The amount of amB released at different 
time points was spectrophotometrically analyzed at 405 nm. each time point represents mean of triplicate readings ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; Pga, polyglutamic acid. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1779 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>of tested concentrations, ie, 1-100 µg/mL (maximum leakage 
was 4.0%±0.9%; P0.001). AmB-L, used as a control, also 
showed negligible hemolysis (2.60%±0.7%). However, 
the positive control, AmB-D, showed a sharp increase in 
toxicity as the concentration was increased from 5 µg/mL 
to 10 µg/mL (20.0%±5.0% and 90.0%±7.3% respectively); 
with complete hemolysis at the 50 µg/mL concentration of 
AmB (Figure 4A). 
Incubation for longer durations (24 hours) at 37°C did 
not affect the toxic properties of AmB−PGA nanoparticles 
and did not induce significant hemolysis (Figure 4B). Only 
14.7%±2.2% hemolysis at 100 µg/mL (AmB equivalents) 
was observed (Figure 4B). AmB-D showed 100% hemolysis 
at an AmB equivalent concentration of 50 µg/mL. Empty 
nanoparticles (sham group) showed no signs of toxicity 
(1.40%±0.50%) and AmB-L displayed negligible hemolysis 
(5.6%±0.3%). 
The low toxicity of AmB when formulated in AmB−PGA 
nanoparticles can be attributed to the shielding effect of 
the PGA nanoparticles resulting from association of AmB 
with PGA. In the case of AmB-D, the drug is available in 
total at a given time point, so has a direct adverse effect on 
the membrane of the red blood cell, resulting in leakage of 
hemoglobin and ions. On the other hand, the PGA formula-
tion regulates drug release, so that the drug is not readily 
available to bind to the red blood cell membrane, thereby 
reducing toxicity. Moreover, the slow release of the drug 
from the PGA formulation ensures that the drug remains as 
a monomer and does not form oligomer aggregates, which 
is the species mainly responsible for drug toxicity. </p>

<p>The cytotoxic effect of the AmB−PGA formulation was 
also assessed in mammalian cells. The AmB−PGA nano-
particle was not toxic to mammalian cells (KB and RAW 
264.7), whereas AmB-D showed dose-dependent toxicity 
(Figure 5A and B). A 10 µg/mL concentration of free drug 
(pure AmB) allowed survival of only 55.4%±7.6% of the 
cells. On the other hand, our PGA formulation prepared 
in-house had much less toxicity at the same concentration 
(86.3%±3.4% cell survival), comparable with that of AmB-L 
(90.01%±9.75%). A cell survival rate of 79.2%±6.7% was 
observed for PGA nanoparticles at an AmB concentration of 
50 µg/mL, whereas AmB-D was completely cytotoxic to KB 
cells at the same AmB concentration (Figure 5A). At a con-
centration of 200 µg/mL AmB equivalents, the viability of KB 
cells was maintained at 75.7%±3.2% when treated with the 
AmB−PGA formulation. AmB-L maintained a cell survival 
of 84.5%±9.7%; whereas the pure drug was 100% lethal at the 
same concentration (200 µg/mL AmB equivalents). The MTT 
assay performed on RAW 264.7 cells treated with AmB−PGA 
nanoparticles showed similar results. However, the survival 
rate was much higher (∼93% at 200 µg/mL AmB equivalents) 
than that observed with KB cells (Figure 5B), equivalent to 
the cell survival rate seen with AmB-L. The sodium salt of 
PGA alone did not display toxicity toward KB cells or RAW 
264.7 cells at much higher doses (data not shown). </p>

<p>In vivo toxicity of amB-Pga formulation </p>

<p>Next, we evaluated the toxic manifestations (if any) of the 
AmB−PGA nanoformulation in in vivo models treated with 
three different doses (5, 10, and 15 mg/kg body weight). </p>

<p>Figure 4 hemolytic activity of amB and amB-Pga nanoparticles. The extent of damage caused to red blood cells by the amB formulation was measured as percent lysis 
of total erythrocytes used in the individual sample. 
Notes: (A) hemolysis caused by the amB-Pga formulation after 1 hour of incubation with human red blood cells. (B) hemolysis after a 24-hour incubation period. amB-D, 
amB-l and pure amB used in preparation of the complex were used as controls. Data are pooled from three different experiments. each datum point is a mean ± standard 
deviation. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; DMsO, dimethyl sulfoxide; Pga, polyglutamic acid; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® . </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1780 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>AmB-D was administered at a dose of 5 mg/kg body weight. 
Liver and renal function tests (Table 2) suggest that while 
AmB-D imparts significant toxicity to the host liver and kid-
ney, the AmB−PGA formulation was not toxic even at a dose 
of 15 mg/kg body weight and did not significantly alter serum 
biochemical parameters for renal and hepatic function. There 
was no significant elevation in serum alanine transaminase lev-
els, while aspartate transaminase levels were slightly elevated. 
However, animals treated with AmB-D exhibited significantly 
elevated levels of both alanine aminotransferase and aspartate 
aminotransferase. Creatinine concentrations were within the 
normal range for mouse serum in the AmB−PGA-treated 
groups, whereas mice treated with AmB-D showed relatively 
higher levels of creatinine (Table 2). The AmB−PGA nano-
particle was well tolerated by the experimental animals up to 
a dose of 15 mg/kg body weight, with no signs of illness or 
loss of body weight (data not shown). 
The possible toxicity issues related to the formulation 
were further ruled out by histopathological examination of 
the kidneys from treated animals. As observed under light 
microscopy, features of the renal parenchyma from animals 
treated with the AmB−PGA nanoparticles (Figure S1C) </p>

<p>were very much comparable with those of healthy controls 
(Figure S1D) as well as AmB-L (Figure S1B). There were 
no changes in the normal morphology of the kidneys, which 
showed normal renal corpuscles in terms of glomerular mass, 
cellularity, and urinary space. Intact renal tubules with charac-
teristic cell linings as well as interstitial space could be identi-
fied. Both the proximal and distal convoluted tubules appear 
normal in architecture. AmB-D showed toxic effects on the 
kidney, with varying degrees of tissue necrosis (Figure S1A). 
These results are consistent with preclinical reports by other 
investigators that AmB-D is more toxic than AmB-L and 
ABLC (amphotericin B lipid complex) at the cellular level </p>

<p>86,87   and more toxic than AmB-L and AmB colloidal dispersion 
(Amphotec 
® ) in organs. </p>

<p>88,89 </p>

<p>In vitro antifungal activity </p>

<p>The antifungal activity of the AmB−PGA formulation was 
evaluated over a final concentration range of 0.015 µg/mL 
to 8 µg/mL using a broth microdilution method. The relative 
potency of the AmB−PGA complexes in vitro was similar 
to that of AmB-D (Table 3). The MIC of PGA-formulated 
AmB as well as AmB-D was 0.125 µg/mL, while the MIC </p>

<p>Figure 5 In vitro cytotoxicity assay. Dose-response effects of amB-Pga formulation on cytotoxicity against (A) KB cells and (B) raW 264.7 cells. 
Notes: The cells were exposed for 24 hours to various amB formulations at different drug concentrations. MTT values were normalized to the control cells. The data are 
reported as the mean ± standard deviation of four experiments. Free drug is pure amB used in preparation of the complex. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; MTT, 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide; Pga, polyglutamic acid; amB-D, Fungizone </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>; amB-l, ambisome </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Table 2 effects of amB-Pga on serum chemistry in mice </p>

<p>Groups 
Creatinine (mg/dL) 
ALT (IU/L) 
AST (IU/L) 
BUN (mg/dL) </p>

<p>healthy control 
0.18±0.01 
30.2±5.90 
97.5±8.19 
21.6±1.4 
amB-D (5 mg/kg BW) 
0.51±0.13 
91.0±32.89 
222.0±50.91 
56.9±3.5 
amB-Pga (5 mg/kg BW) 
0.12±0.02 
32.0±5.09 
130.21±6.29 
20.8±0.07 
amB-Pga (10 mg/kg BW) 
0.20±0.07 
28.2±0.04 
128.0±2.10 
26.9±2.1 
amB-Pga (15 mg/kg BW) 
0.22±0.03 
36.7±1.34 
139.0±2.56 
22.1±0.5 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; alT, alanine transaminase; asT, aspartate transaminase; BUN, blood urea nitrogen; BW, body weight; Pga, 
polyglutamic acid. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1781 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>of AmB-L against the C. albicans strain was found to be 
0.5 µg/mL. In the case of C. glabrata, AmB−PGA nanopar-
ticles (MIC 0.25 µg/mL) were found to be more potent than 
either AmB-D (MIC 0.5 µg/mL) or AmB-L (MIC 1.0 µg/mL). 
Fungicidal activity has been routinely expressed as a 99.9% 
reduction in CFU over a fixed sampling period. MFC values 
were found to be 0.5 µg/mL for the AmB−PGA formulation, 
while AmB-D showed an MFC of 1.0 µg/mL. The MIC and 
MFC of the AmB−PGA nanoparticle and of AmB-D against 
the C. albicans quality control strain (ATCC 10231) was 
found to be 0.25 µg/mL and 0.5 µg/mL, respectively (Table 3). 
When the different AmB formulations were tested at 4× MIC, 
the AmB−PGA nanoparticle as well as AmB-D caused a 99% 
loss of yeast viability after 4 hours of incubation (Figure 6). 
The PGA polymer was inactive against the pathogen up to a 
concentration of 500 µg/mL (data not shown). </p>

<p>antifungal activity of amB-Pga 
nanoparticles against intracellular 
C. albicans </p>

<p>Occasionally, the dimorphic C. albicans may opt for intra-
cellular life cycle inside the macrophages in order to avoid </p>

<p>antibody onslaught. This intracellular abode also offers 
protection against the circulating antibiotics. Taking this fact 
into consideration, we assessed the antifungal potential of 
AmB entrapped in PGA nanoparticles against macrophages 
harboring intracellular C. albicans. It should be noted that 
no complete eradication of C. albicans was observed up to a 
drug concentration of 50 µg/mL (Figure 7). Overall, AmB-L 
was found to be less effective for killing intracellular C. 
albicans than either of the formulations tested (ie AmB-PGA 
and AmB-D). At a dose of 5 µg/mL, AmB-D showed higher 
intracellular antifungal activity than AmB-L (log 2.5 versus 
log 3.9, respectively). For AmB-D, doses higher than 10 µg/ 
mL were not studied because of their detrimental effects 
toward the host cell. The antifungal activity of AmB−PGA 
was comparable with that of AmB-D (log 1.6 versus log 1.5, 
respectively) at a concentration of 10 µg/mL AmB equivalent; 
with a log 2 decrease in CFU (Figure 7). A further increase in 
AmB dose (to 50 µg/mL) caused a 1 log decrease in CFU. 
The reduced toxicity of AmB following liposomal 
encapsulation (ie, AmBisome) seemed to be associated 
with a substantial reduction of its direct antifungal activity. </p>

<p>Table 3 In vitro antifungal activity of various amphotericin B formulations </p>

<p>Formulation 
Candida albicans (ATCC 18804) 
Candida glabrata (MTCC 3019) 
Candida albicans (ATCC 10231) </p>

<p>MIC (µg/mL) 
MFC (µg/mL) 
MIC (µg/mL) 
MFC (µg/mL) 
MIC (µg/mL) 
MFC (µg/mL) </p>

<p>amB-Pga 
0.125 
0.25 
0.25 
0.5 
0.25 
0.5 
amB-D 
0.125 
0.25 
0.5 
1.0 
0.25 
0.5 
amB-l 
0.5 
1.0 
1.0 
2.0 
0.5 
1.0 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® ; aTcc, american Type culture collection; Pga, polyglutamic acid; MIc, minimum 
inhibitory concentration; MFc, minimum fungicidal concentration; MTT, Microbial Type culture collection. </p>

<p>Figure 6 representative time-kill curve plot for Candida albicans in the presence of 
amB-D, amB-l, or amB-Pga at 4× minimum inhibitory concentration. 
Notes: Wells containing no antibiotic were taken as the control. assays were 
performed in quadruplicate. Each result is representative of at least three separate 
experiments. all values are shown as the mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® ; 
cFU, colony forming units; Pga, polygluta mic acid. </p>

<p>Figure 7 In vitro killing assay. 
Notes: Intracellular antifungal activity of the amB-Pga formulation against Candida 
albicans inside raW 264.7 cells. Macrophages were infected with C. albicans and 
treated with amB-Pga nanoparticles. Percentage of infection was calculated by lysing 
macrophages (after 24 hours of treatment) with Triton X-100 (0.2%), subculturing in 
sabouraud agar plates, and comparing with an untreated control. experiments were 
carried out in triplicate. each datum point represents the mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® ; 
cFU, colony forming units; Pga, polygluta mic acid. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1782 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>Low antifungal activity of AmB-L against intracellular 
C. albicans has also been reported by other investigators. </p>

<p>37   This may be accounted for by the low uptake of AmBisome 
(demonstrated in the J774 macrophage-like cell line) in 
comparison with other lipid based AmB formulations. 
90 A 
higher level of uptake of AmB−PGA nanoparticles than of 
AmBisome in murine peritoneal macrophages and RAW 
264.7 cells (our unpublished data) seems to be responsible 
for the observed high antifungal activity of the AmB−PGA 
formulation. The particulate nature of PGA nanoparticles 
allows them to be efficiently taken up by these cells, giving 
rise to a higher concentration of drug. Simultaneous endo-
cytosis of the AmB−PGA complex and C. albicans brings 
them into close proximity, which favors more pronounced 
killing, presumably by apoptosis of target cells. </p>

<p>91   regression of C. albicans biofilm induced 
by amB-Pga </p>

<p>In order to determine the potential of AmB−PGA nanopar-
ticles to interfere with formation of C. albicans biofilm, we </p>

<p>studied their antibiofilm activity. Preliminary experiments 
on the antibiofilm activity of the nanoparticles were per-
formed using phase contrast microscopy. Surprisingly, the 
AmB−PGA formulation prevented formation of biofilm to a 
considerable extent (Figure S2). This effect was unexpected, 
given the fact that the AmB−PGA nanoparticles would 
only reduce cell growth and not completely inhibit it. These 
encouraging results prompted us to examine its antibiofilm 
activity employing SEM and XTT studies. 
SEM studies revealed that complete eradication of the 
biofilms was not achieved by treatment with AmB−PGA 
nanoparticles, and fungal cells adhering to the biomaterial 
were still visible (Figure 8). However, compared with control 
(untreated) biofilms, AmB−PGA-treated biofilms were less 
hyphal and some of the cells within the biofilms showed 
aberrant morphology. The XTT assay was also performed to 
quantitatively assess the potential of the AmB−PGA formu-
lation to inhibit C. albicans biofilm (Figure 9). Substantial 
inhibition of biofilm growth was observed upon exposure to 
the AmB−PGA formulation. The AmB−PGA nanoparticles </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>× 
× </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>Figure 8 scanning electron micrographs of inhibition of Candida albicans biofilm mediated by the AmB-PGA formulation. 
Notes: (A) Untreated control image of biofilm, (B) AmB-L treated biofilm, (C) biofilm treated with AmB-D, and (D) biofilm treated with AmB-PGA. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® ; Pga, polyglutamic acid. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1783 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>Figure 9 Semiquantitative measure of antibiofilm activity of PGA nanoparticles. 
Notes: growth percentage was analyzed by comparing relative metabolic 
activity obtained by XTT metabolic assay taking the untreated control as 100%. 
The data represent the mean ± standard deviation of three determinants and are 
representative of three different experiments (ie, the experiment was done in 
triplicate) with similar observations. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® ; 
PGA, polyglutamic acid; XTT, 2, 3-bis(2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfoph enyl)-5-[(pheny-
lamino) carbonyl]-2h-tetrazolium hydroxide. </p>

<p>showed concentration-dependent activity on C. albicans 
biofilm. Approximately 30%-35% of viable biofilm was 
observed in fully developed film at a concentration of 100 µg/ 
mL. AmB-L was the least effective against Candida biofilm, 
with a higher cell survival percentage (55.0%±2.8%). On 
the other hand, AmB-D showed viability of 43.5%±2.4% 
(Figure 9). 
The antifungal susceptibility of C. albicans biofilm was 
tested using highly developed biofilms of intermediate phase 
(24 hours) and maturation phase (48 hours). 
92 All three 
antifungal formulations (AmB-D, AmB-L, and AmB−PGA) 
were found to be more effective against 24-hour biofilm than 
48-hour biofilm. AmB−PGA nanoparticles demonstrated 
slightly higher activity than AmB-D for both 24-hour and 
48-hour biofilm (Figure S3), with AmB-L being the least 
effective. Despite the improved activity of the AmB−PGA 
formulation, complete eradication of sessile organisms within 
mature biofilms was not observed (Figure S3). For 24-hour 
preformed biofilm, AmB−PGA reduced the optical density 
of the biofilm by 50% (P0.001) after 4 hours of incuba-
tion time. In the case of 48-hour biofilm, the AmB−PGA 
formulation achieved a 50% reduction in biofilm only after 
24 hours. This decrease in antibiofilm activity as the biofilm 
matures is a common phenomenon with antifungal agents. </p>

<p>92   Similar results were obtained for AmB-D. 
Consistent with our results (Figures 9 and S3), other 
researchers have shown that the antifungal killing effects 
of AmB against biofilms is generally more pronounced at 
the highest concentration (64 µg/mL) but not at therapeu-
tic concentrations (0.125 and 0.5 µg/mL). 
93 Researchers </p>

<p>have observed that 20 times the MIC of commonly used 
antifungals was required to achieve a significant reduction 
in cell numbers. 
94 Thus, higher levels of AmB-D are required 
to manage biofilm-related infection in the clinic, and this is 
not advisable because of the toxic behavior of AmB. We 
have shown here that our AmB−PGA formulation prepared 
in-house is well tolerated even at high concentration and has 
little or no toxicity (Figures 4 and 5, Table 2). Therefore, it 
can be said that this AmB−PGA formulation represents a 
good alternative to improve the management of Candida 
biofilm-associated infection, to disrupt biofilms, and to pre-
vent the emergence of resistance. 
C. albicans biofilm, like many other microorganisms, 
arises from microcolonies embedded in an extracellular 
matrix. 
95 The prominence of hyphal filaments is the hall-
mark of C. albicans biofilm maturation. 
92 In addition to 
assisting evasion of host defense mechanisms, hyphal 
transformants are lethal to macrophages and endothelial 
cells. 
96,97 A reduction in hyphal content as well as lower 
fungal viability (Figures 8 and 9) makes the AmB−PGA 
nanoformulation a promising strategy for dealing with bio-
films. The mechanism behind the unique antibiofilm activity 
of our formulation prepared in-house is unknown. Given 
the size of the formulation, it is somewhat surprising that it 
can penetrate the extracellular matrix to target fungal cells; 
however, it can be speculated that the dispersion of AmB in 
the polymer may in fact facilitate passage through the charged 
polysaccharide extracellular matrix. 
More elaborate studies involving confocal laser scanning 
microscopy are required to ascertain the potent antibiofilm activ-
ity of AmB-PGA nanoparticles. We are presently undertaking 
studies to evaluate the effect of AmB−PGA nanoparticles on 
the morphogenesis of C. albicans during biofilm formation by 
means of real-time polymerase chain reaction and other tech-
niques. Further, the potential of the AmB−PGA formulation in 
the treatment of oral and systemic C. albicans infection is also 
currently under investigation in a mouse model. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In summary, the results of the present study indicate that encap-
sulation with PGA markedly improves the antifungal activity 
of AmB, without signs of drug-induced toxicity. A PGA 
homopolymer can associate with AmB to produce a formula-
tion that is water-soluble, efficacious, well tolerated, and highly 
stable, and can be used as an alternative to the presently avail-
able AmB formulations. PGA-based AmB nanoparticles offer 
a safe and efficacious drug delivery vehicle with potential for 
future use as a nanomedicine in the clinical setting. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Zia et al </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1787 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>Supplementary materials 
animals </p>

<p>Inbred female Balb/c mice (aged 6-8 weeks, mean weight 
20±2 g) were obtained from the animal facility at the Indian 
Institute of Toxicological Research, Lucknow, India. After 
procurement, the animals were acclimatized for a few days 
under standard husbandry conditions (room temperature 
22°C±3°C, relative humidity 65%±10%, and a 12-hour light/ 
dark cycle). They had free access to a standard dry pellet diet 
and water ad libitum under strict hygienic conditions. Animals 
were anesthetized with ketamine 5 mg/kg and xylazine 4 mg/ 
kg prior to sacrifice. Humane endpoints were necessary for 
mice that survived at the conclusion of the experiment. Mice 
were administered an anesthetic cocktail of ketamine and 
xylazine intraperitoneally and then euthanized by cervical 
dislocation. Experiments involving bleeding, injection, and 
sacrifice of animals were strictly performed following the 
mandates approved by the institutional animal ethics commit-
tee constituted as per the recommendations of the Committee 
for the Purpose of Control and Supervision of Experiments on 
Animals (CPCSEA), Government of India (http://moef.nic.in/ 
division/committee-purpose-control-and-supervision-experi-
ments-animals-cpcsea-1). During the experimental procedures, 
all efforts were made to minimize pain and suffering. </p>

<p>ethics statement </p>

<p>All animal experiments were reviewed and approved by the 
institutional animal ethics committee of the Interdisciplinary 
Biotechnology Unit, Aligarh Muslim University, India, 
and were performed according to the National Regulatory 
Guidelines issued by CPCSEA, Ministry of Environment 
and Forest, Government of India. Our approval identifier 
was 332/CPCSEA. </p>

<p>Determination of particle size and zeta 
potential </p>

<p>The zeta potential of the nanoparticles was determined using 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">DTS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Malvern Instruments Limited, Malvern, UK</rs>) based on M3-PALS technology. Samples were filtered 
using a 0.22 µm polyethersulfone syringe filter (Millipore, 
Bangalore, India) to remove contamination with dust 
particles. The formulation was lyophilized in a 2.0 mL 
microfuge tube and the samples were reconstituted in 20 
mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.4). This dispersion was then 
rapidly dispensed to an electrophoresis cell to measure the 
electrophoretic mobility, and zeta potential values were 
calculated. The concentration of the AmB−PGA formula-
tion used was 10 
-4 M. The experiments were repeated three 
times and the average zeta potential and standard deviations </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>g 
g </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>Figure S1 histopathological studies. 
Notes: Photomicrographs of kidney samples from amB-D (A), amB-l (B), amB-Pga (C), and healthy control (D) groups. The amB-Pga-treated group shows intact renal 
corpuscle with normal glomerular cellularity (g), urinary space, and lining cells of the renal tubules (t). 200×, hematoxylin and eosin stain. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; Pga, polyglutamic acid; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® . </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1788 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>were calculated. The particle size of the nanoparticles was 
determined by photon correlation spectroscopy (90Plus/BI-
MAS, Brookhaven Instruments, Holtville, NY, USA). For 
size measurements, samples were diluted in Milli-Q water 
and measured for at least 120 seconds. The concentration of 
AmB−PGA formulation used was 10 
-4 M. All measurements 
were performed in triplicate. </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy was performed to char-
acterize the size and surface morphology of AmB-loaded 
nanoparticles using an electron microscope (CM-10, Philips, 
Hamburg, Germany). For these studies, the AmB−PGA 
formulation was used at a concentration of 10 µg/mL AmB 
equivalents in double-distilled water. The lyophilized 
pre paration of nanoparticles was suspended in 20 mM </p>

<p>phosphate-buffered saline (pH 7.4) and a drop of the for-
mulation was mounted on a clear glass stub, air-dried, and 
coated with gold-palladium alloy using a sputter coater. An 
accelerating voltage of 20 kV was used for imaging. </p>

<p>Dynamic light scattering measurements </p>

<p>Dynamic light scattering measurements were carried out 
using DynaPro-TC-04 equipment (Protein Solutions, 
Wyatt Technology, Santa Barbara, CA, USA) equipped 
with a temperature-controlled microsampler. The PGA 
nanoparticles (2 mg/mL) were filtered serially through 
0.22 µm and 0.02 µm Whatman syringe filters directly into a 
12 µL quartz cuvette. For each experiment, 20 measurements 
were taken. Mean hydrodynamic radius (R h ) was analyzed 
using <rs type="software">Dynamics software</rs> at optimized resolution. The R h was 
estimated on the basis of an autocorrelation analysis of </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Figure S2 Antibiofilm activity of AmB-PGA nanoparticles analyzed by phase contrast microscopy. Candida biofilm was subjected to AmB-PGA and AmB-D, and phase 
contrast images were captured after 24 hours. 
Notes: (A) Candida biofilm + no treatment as control. (B) Candida biofilm + treatment with amB-D. (C) Candida biofilm + treatment with amB-Pga nanoparticles. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; Pga, polyglutamic acid; amB-D, Fungizone 
® . </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Time (hours) </p>

<p>Percent viability </p>

<p>Time (hours) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Percent viability </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 
0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 </p>

<p>AmB-PGA 
AmB-D 
AmB-L </p>

<p>AmB-PGA 
AmB-D 
AmB-L </p>

<p>Figure S3 Time-killing kinetics of AmB-PGA nanoparticles against preformed biofilms of Candida albicans of (A) intermediate (24 hours) and (B) maturation phase (48 
hours). Various amphotericin B formulations were added to the preformed biofilms and plates were incubated for selected time intervals (2, 4, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours). The 
results are shown as the mean of four replicate biofilms for each time point tested and are expressed as percentages of reduction in viability by the XTT assay. 
Abbreviations: amB, amphotericin B; Pga, polyglutamic acid; amB-D, Fungizone 
® ; amB-l, ambisome 
® . </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1789 </p>

<p>characterization and antifungal activity of amB-Pga nanoparticles </p>

<p>scattered light intensity data based on a translation diffusion 
coefficient by Stokes-Einstein relationship: </p>

<p>R 
kT 
h = 
π 
6 η D </p>

<p>where R h is the hydrodynamic radius, k is the Boltzmann 
constant, T is temperature, η is the viscosity of water, and 
D is the diffusion coefficient. </p>

<p>Pga nanoparticle-mediated transfer 
of entrapped molecules to macrophages </p>

<p>Mice were injected intraperitoneally with 2 mL of 4% thio-
glycolate, and peritoneal exudate cells were harvested 4 days 
later using cold Roswell Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) 
1640 medium. 
1 Peritoneal macrophages (1×10 
4 cells) were 
cultured on a glass coverslip using complete RPMI 1640 
medium overnight in a CO 2 incubator (with 5% CO 2 ) at 
37°C. The next morning, the cells were washed thoroughly 
with Hank's Balanced Salt Solution and incubated with 
fluorescent dye (calcein)-loaded PGA nanoparticles for 
30 minutes at 37°C. The calcein-loaded PGA nanoparticles 
were prepared using the same procedure as that used for 
AmB−PGA nanoparticles. The noninteracted PGA popula-
tion was removed by thorough washing followed by mount-
ing of the macrophage-harboring coverslip in glycerol. The 
cells were observed under a fluorescence microscope (Zeiss, 
Oberkochen, Germany). Phase contrast and fluorescent 
micrographs were recorded accordingly. </p>

<p>High-performance liquid chromatography 
analysis </p>

<p>Quantitation of AmB was performed by a slight modifi-
cation of the method described by Nilsson-Ehle et al 
2 as 
standardized in our laboratory. High performance liquid 
chromatography was conducted using a MicroBondapak 
C-18 column (30 cm ×4 mm [diameter]; particle size 5 
µm; Waters Associates, Milford, MA, USA) with a Waters 
high-performance liquid chromatography system. The 
mobile phase was a mixture of methanol and 0.005 M 
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (8:2 vol/vol) deaerated by 
vacuum. The injection volume was 20 µL, delivered at a 
rate of 1.0 mL/min. The eluent was monitored at 405 nm 
for AmB content with a run time of 15 minutes. The reten-
tion time of AmB was 8 minutes. The internal standard was 
1-amino-4-nitronaphthalene. The limit of detection was 1 ng. 
The results were quantified by comparison of the AmB peak 
at 405 nm with a standard of known concentration eluted at 
the same retention time. A standard calibration curve of the </p>

<p>drug was plotted at 405 nm by determining the area under 
the curve corresponding to the increasing amount of the drug 
(3.125-200 ng of AmB equivalent in 20 µL of sample injec-
tion volume). The highest AmB concentration was 10 µg/mL 
(equivalent to 200 ng of AmB in 20 µL). Dilutions of AmB 
were performed in methanol to ensure that AmB remained 
in the monomeric form. </p>

<p>histopathological analysis </p>

<p>Histopathological evaluation was also done on the kidneys of 
nonimmunosuppressed, uninfected mice following intrave-
nous treatment with a single dose of 15 mg/kg AmB−PGA, 
AmB-L, or phosphate-buffered saline (control) following the 
published protocol. 
3 AmB-D was administered at a dose of 
5 mg/kg body weight. The tissue sample was aseptically col-
lected 24 hours after treatment. At necropsy, kidney samples 
were fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin. Tissue blocks of 
kidney (1×0.2 cm) were processed routinely. They were dehy-
drated in alcohol, cleared in xylene, and infiltrated and embed-
ded in paraffin. Sections (5 µm thick) were cut and mounted on 
glass slides. The slides were then rehydrated in water, stained 
with hematoxylin and eosin, dehydrated, cleared in xylene, 
mounted with a synthetic resin, and covered with a coverslip. 
All tissue sections were examined and photographed with a 
light microscope (BX45, Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) at ×200 by 
a board-certified pathologist form Jawaharlal Nehru Medical 
College, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh, India. </p>

<p>In vitro susceptibility testing </p>

<p>A concentrated (1,000 mg/L) stock solution of AmB (Sigma 
Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) was dissolved in dimethyl 
sulfoxide. The solution was diluted with dimethyl sulfoxide 
and then with the appropriate test medium. AmB was tested 
over a concentration range of 0.015-8 µg/mL. Candida 
albicans ATCC 10231 was used as a quality control strain. 
The broth microdilution method was used as the refer-
ence method, as described by the Clinical and Laboratory 
Standards Institute (document M27-A2 
4 ). The inoculum 
was prepared from Sabouraud dextrose agar subcultures 
incubated at 35°C for 24 hours and the resulting suspension 
was adjusted spectrophotometrically to a density equivalent 
to a 0.5 McFarland standard at 530 nm (1.5×10 
6 colony 
forming units [CFU]/mL). A working suspension was made 
by 1:100 dilution of the suspension in RPMI 1640 medium 
with l-glutamine and without bicarbonate (Sigma-Aldrich), 
buffered to pH 7.0 with 0.165 M morpholinepropanesulfonic 
acid (Sigma-Aldrich). Next, 100 µL of the diluted inoculum 
was added to each well. The final inoculum size was (0.5-2.5) 
10 
3 CFU/mL. The broth dilution tests were incubated at </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nanomedicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nanomedicine is an international, peer-
reviewed journal focusing on the application of nanotechnology 
in diagnostics, therapeutics, and drug delivery systems throughout 
the biomedical field. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, CAS, SciSearch®, Current Contents®/Clinical Medicine, </p>

<p>Journal Citation Reports/Science Edition, EMBase, Scopus and the 
Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1790 </p>

<p>Zia et al </p>

<p>35°C, and minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) were 
determined after 48 hours of incubation by observation of 
the presence or absence of visible growth. For AmB, the 
MIC endpoint is the lowest concentration that inhibits visual 
growth or an endpoint score of 0 (100% inhibition). 
After determination of the MICs, the entire contents 
(200 µL) of each well with drug concentrations above the MIC 
were plated onto two drug-free Sabouraud agar plates (100 µL 
aliquots/plate). Aliquots were placed in a single spot on the agar 
plate and, after drying, the cells were dispersed by streaking. 
Plates were incubated at 35°C for 48 hours; the minimum fungi-
cidal concentrations (MFC) was the lowest drug concentration 
that showed either no growth or fewer than three colonies to 
obtain approximately 99%-99.5% killing activity. All assays 
were performed in duplicate and repeated at least twice. </p>

<p>Microscopic visualization of C. albicans 
biofilms </p>

<p>C. albicans biofilms were grown on sterile glass coverslips 
placed in six-well polystyrene plates. 
5 After 2 hours of 
incubation of the fungal cell suspension (at the density of 
10 
7 cells) on the glass coverslips at 37°C, the coverslips were 
washed three times to remove nonadhered cells. Further, 
the glass coverslips were incubated in RPMI 1640 medium 
for 48 hours at 37°C to allow development of biofilm. 
Following biofilm formation, the medium was aspirated and 
nonadherent cells were removed by thoroughly washing the 
biofilms three times in sterile phosphate-buffered saline. The 
AmB−PGA formulation was then added and the coverslips 
were incubated further at 37°C. After 24 hours, the coverslips 
were fixed in 2% paraformaldehyde followed by washing, and 
the activity of AmB−PGA nanoparticles against C. albicans 
biofilm was visualized using a Z1 Axio Inverted microscope 
(Carl Zeiss, Thornwood, NY, USA). </p>

<p>Time-kill kinetics of biofilm </p>

<p>Biofilms were grown under shaking (100 rpm) for 24 or 
48 hours at 37°C. Various amphotericin B formulations were 
then added at a concentration of 8 µg/mL to the preformed </p>

<p>biofilms and the plates were incubated for selected time 
intervals (2, 4, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours). At each time interval, 
the antifungal effects were monitored by a metabolic assay 
based on the reduction of XTT as described previously. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>After treatment, 100 µL of the XTT/menadione solution, ie, 
2, 3-bis(2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl)-5-[(phenylamino) 
carbonyl]-2H-tetrazolium hydroxide, was added to each pre-
washed biofilm and to the negative control wells. The plates 
were covered with aluminum foil and incubated in the dark 
for 2 hours at 37°C. The plates were then read in a microtiter 
plate reader at 490 nm. Untreated biofilms containing RPMI 
1640 medium were included as positive controls. AmB-D and 
AmB-L were also included in the study as controls. Wells 
without biofilms served as a blank. Four replicate biofilms 
were included for each experiment. </p>

<p>Percent Sample absorbance blank absorbance </p>

<p>Contro 
viability 
= 
− 
l l absorbance blank absorbance 
100 
− 
× </p>

<p>where blank absorbance is the medium alone and control 
absorbance is fungal cells with medium alone. </p>



</text></tei>