<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4640439" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In Brief </p>

<p>van Boxtel et al. show how temporal 
information in the zebrafish embryo is 
transformed into a spatial pattern. They 
demonstrate that the dimensions of the 
earliest Nodal signaling domain are 
determined by a temporal signal 
activation window created by a 
microRNA-mediated delay in the 
translation of Lefty, a Nodal antagonist. </p>

<p>van In the development and patterning of embryonic and adult tissues, 
secreted signaling molecules of the Wnt, Fgf, Hedgehog, and 
transforming growth factor b (TGF-b) families can act as mor-
phogens to activate different transcriptional programs along a 
signaling gradient (Perrimon et al., 2012). Ideas of how morpho-
gens impart spatial information have been dominated by the 
assumption that these molecules form concentration gradients 
by diffusion, inducing dose-dependent responses in the receiving 
field of cells. However, it is becoming increasingly clear that for 
some ligands, for example, Hedgehog, Wnt, and Fgf, other mech-
anisms, such as short-range signaling activation, transcriptional 
feedback, and cellular rearrangements, underlie morphogen func-
tion (Alexandre et al., 2014; Cohen et al., 2013; Durdu et al., 2014). 
Regulation of Nodal signaling in the zebrafish embryo has 
long served as a paradigm for understanding how morphogens </p>

<p>pattern tissues (Schier, 2009). Nodals are secreted ligands that 
belong to the TGF-b superfamily of growth and differentiation 
factors. During vertebrate development, Nodal is required for 
stem cell maintenance, specification of mesoderm and endo-
derm (mesendoderm), and establishment of left-right asymmetry 
(Shen, 2007). Recent work has also suggested that Nodal 
signaling is reactivated in advanced cancers, where it may be 
important for self-renewal of cancer stem cells (Wakefield and 
Hill, 2013). 
Nodal ligands signal through serine/threonine kinase receptor 
complexes comprising two type I receptors (Acvr1ba [Taram-a]), 
two type II receptors (Acvr2a/b), and the co-receptor Tdgf1 
(Cripto/Oep) (Schier, 2009; Shen, 2007). Ligand binding acti-
vates the receptors, after which the type I receptor phosphory-
lates the intracellular signal transducers Smad2 and Smad3, 
which then bind Smad4 ( , 2012). These Smad2/3-
Smad4 complexes accumulate in the nucleus, where, together 
with transcription factors such as Foxh1, Mixer, and Oct4, they 
regulate gene transcription (Gaarenstroom and Hill, 2014). 
At zebrafish blastula stages, two Nodal-related ligands, 
Ndr1 (Squint) and Ndr2 (Cyclops), specify mesendoderm in 
marginal cells around the circumference of the embryo by 
inducing a Smad2-Smad4-Foxh1-dependent transcriptional 
program (Feldman et al., 1998; Gritsman et al., 1999). Ndr1/2 
are thought to form a signaling gradient by diffusion, extending 
up to about ten cell tiers from the margin (Dubrulle et al., 2015; 
Harvey and Smith, 2009; Schier, 2009). Indeed, expression of 
presumed long-range Nodal target genes such as ta (ntla) and 
fscn1a suggests low-level signaling up to ten cell tiers from the 
margin (Bennett et al., 2007). This appears supported by bimo-
lecular fluorescent complementation experiments (Harvey and 
Smith, 2009). However, other Nodal target genes are expressed 
in up to five to six cell tiers from the margin, which coincides with 
nuclear accumulation of Smad2-GFP fusion protein (Dubrulle 
et al., 2015). Importantly, other signaling pathways, such as 
Bmp, Wnt, and Fgf, are also active at the margin, which can 
potentially co-regulate Nodal target genes and thus contribute 
to their expression domains. 
Formation of the Nodal signaling domain at the correct time 
and of appropriate dimensions is thought to be controlled by a 
reaction-diffusion system (Meinhardt, 2009; Schier, 2009). This 
model requires positive and negative feedback, which is pro-
vided by Nodal-induced expression of both the ligands Ndr1/2 
and the antagonists Lefty1 (Lft1) and Lefty2 (Lft2) (Chen and </p>

<p>Developmental Cell 35, 175-185, October 26, 2015 ª2015 The Authors 175 </p>

<p>Shen, 2004; Cheng et al., 2004). Besides these feedback mech-
anisms, the model requires Lft1/2 to be more diffusible than 
Ndr1/2 ( ller et al., 2012; Schier and Talbot, 2005). These con-
ditions are thought to allow Ndr1/2 to activate signaling at the 
margin, whereas Lft1/2 proteins would inhibit signaling in more 
distal cells. Overexpression studies have shown that Ndr1/2 
and Lft1/2 can differentially diffuse and that Ndr1, but not 
Ndr2, can diffuse over a distance to activate signaling (Chen 
and Schier, 2001, 2002;  ller et al., 2012). However, the impor-
tance of diffusion of endogenous Ndr1/2 remains unclear, as 
mesendoderm can develop normally in zygotic ndr1 mutants 
(Dougan et al., 2003; Feldman et al., 1998; Lim et al., 2013). 
In addition to the negative feedback provided by Lft1/2, Nodal 
signaling is regulated by the miR-430/427/302 family of micro-
RNAs (miRNAs) (Bassett et al., 2014; Choi et al., 2007; Rosa 
et al., 2009). At blastula stages, the miR-430 family is the most 
abundant family of miRNAs in the zebrafish. Importantly, miR-
430 regulates ndr1, lft1, and lft2, but not ndr2, and this is thought 
to dampen Nodal signaling (Choi et al., 2007). However, to 
what extent miR-430s contribute to the formation of the Nodal 
signaling domain is unknown. 
To develop a specific readout for endogenous Nodal signaling, 
avoiding overexpression of any pathway components, we 
generated a transgenic zebrafish Nodal reporter line. Using this 
line combined with immunofluorescence for phosphorylated 
Smad2 (P-Smad2), we show that Nodal signals exclusively in 
cells that express Ndr1/2, up to five to six cell tiers from the 
margin. This prompted us to revisit the mechanism underlying 
the formation of the Nodal signaling domain. Our data do not 
support the reaction-diffusion model, but instead, we propose 
that Nodal activates signaling in a temporal window that is 
defined by a miR-430-mediated delay of Lft1/2 translation. In 
this way, temporal information is converted into spatial informa-
tion in the developing embryo. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Regulation of Presumed Long-Range Nodal Target Gene 
Expression by Fgf Signaling 
The range of activity of the Nodal signaling pathway in the blas-
tula margin has mainly been inferred from the expression of 
endogenous target genes, such as fscn1a and in particular ta 
(ntla) (Bennett et al., 2007; Gritsman et al., 1999). However, in 
addition to Nodal, Fgf signaling is also known to regulate ta 
expression (Griffin et al., 1995; Rodaway et al., 1999; Schier 
and Talbot, 2005). Genes encoding Fgf ligands, such as fgf3 
and fgf8a, are expressed in the margin (Figure S1A) and are 
known Nodal targets (Mathieu et al., 2004), suggesting that Fgf 
signaling at the margin of blastula-stage embryos is downstream 
of Nodal signaling (Rodaway et al., 1999). This is clearly demon-
strated by treating embryos with the Nodal inhibitor SB-505124 
(Hagos and Dougan, 2007), which results in a near complete loss 
of phosphorylated Erk (P-Erk), a readout for Fgf pathway activity 
(Dorey and Amaya, 2010) (Figures 1A and 1B). 
Given that both Nodal and Fgf signaling are active at the 
margin, we examined to what extent Fgf signaling regulates 
endogenous Nodal target genes, focusing on the expression of 
ta and fscn1a as examples of long-range genes and lft1 and 
lft2 as examples of short-range target genes (Bennett et al., </p>

<p>2007; Dubrulle et al., 2015; Harvey and Smith, 2009). To inhibit 
Fgf signaling, wild-type (WT) embryos were treated with the 
Fgf receptor (FgfR) inhibitor SU-5402 (Mohammadi et al., 1997) 
or were injected with mRNA encoding a dominant-negative 
FgfR (dnFgfR) (Amaya et al., 1991) (Figure 1C). Both treatments 
resulted in a reduction in the size of the expression domains of 
ta and fscn1a in the margin of 40%-50% epiboly embryos, but 
not of lft1 or lft2 (Figure 1D). In fact, lft2 expression was 
increased. Similarly, morpholinos (MOs) against fgf3 and fgf8a 
resulted in a reduction of ta expression, but not of lft1 (Fig-
ure S1B). qPCR on SU-5402-treated 50% epiboly embryos 
confirmed the whole-mount in situ hybridization (WISH) results 
(Figure 1E), and as expected, inhibition of Nodal signaling by 
SB-505124 led to reduction in expression of all four genes (Fig-
ure 1E). Importantly, FgfR inhibition had no effect on C-terminal 
phosphorylation of Smad2 (P-Smad2) or overall Smad2 levels, 
demonstrating that Nodal signaling is not affected by Fgf 
signaling inhibition (Figure 1F). 
To quantitate the effect of inhibiting Fgf signaling on the ta 
expression domain, we performed serial sectioning on ta-
stained embryos at 40% epiboly. In control embryos, ta is ex-
pressed in an average of about 10 cell tiers from the margin, 
whereas expression was reduced to six cell tiers in SU-5402-
treated embryos (Figures 1G and 1H). This indicated that ta 
expression beyond six cell tiers was due to Fgf signaling and 
not directly dependent on Nodal. In support of this idea, injection 
of increasing doses of fgf8a mRNA into a maternal zygotic (MZ) 
tdgf1 À/À background confirmed that Nodal signaling is not 
required for induction of ta by Fgf, excluding a requirement for 
synergism between Nodal and Fgf signaling for ta expression 
beyond six cell tiers (Figure S1C). This was further confirmed 
by the observation that inhibition of Nodal signaling from the 
16-cell stage resulted in the loss of both ta and lft1 expression, 
but when Nodal signaling was inhibited from dome stage, only 
lft1 expression was severely reduced, whereas the expression 
of ta was unaffected (Figure S1D). Thus ta expression is not 
dependent on Nodal activity after Fgf signaling has been 
initiated. 
Together these data demonstrate that Fgf signaling regulates 
presumed long-range endogenous Nodal target genes beyond 
six cell tiers. </p>

<p>Direct In Vivo Visualization of Nodal Signaling 
To exclusively monitor Nodal signaling without inputs from other 
pathways, we generated a transgenic zebrafish Nodal reporter 
line, specific for Smad2-Smad4-Foxh1-mediated signaling. An 
eGFP reporter gene under the control of three Foxh1 and 
Smad binding sites, termed activin response elements (AREs) 
(Germain et al., 2000), was inserted into the zebrafish genome 
using Tol2-mediated transgenesis (Tg[ARE:eGFP]) (Figure 2A). 
We chose this reporter, which we have extensively characterized 
in a number of cell culture and developmental contexts (Germain 
et al., 2000; Inman and Hill, 2002; Randall et al., 2004), because 
Foxh1 is the primary transcription factor required for immediate 
early Nodal target gene expression (Pogoda et al., 2000; Slagle 
et al., 2011). In addition, Smad2 is the predominant receptor-
regulated Smad during blastula stages (Figure S2A), and indeed 
MZ deletion of Smad2 results in a phenotype identical to 
MZtdgf1 À/À embryos (Dubrulle et al., 2015). </p>



<p>In four independent Tg(ARE:eGFP) lines, WISH for eGFP 
mRNA revealed that the reporter was activated in identical do-
mains, excluding any effects caused by different integration sites 
of the transgene (Figures 2A and S2B). The eGFP expression do-
mains correspond to the expression domains of Nodal ligands 
(Schier, 2009) and include the embryonic margin at blastula 
stages, axial mesoderm during gastrulation, and the left lateral 
plate mesoderm during somitogenesis (Figures 2A and S3). Incu-
bation of developing Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos with SB-505124 
resulted in a strong reduction of eGFP staining (Figure 2B). 
This was also the case when foxh1 MOs were injected or when 
the Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos were bred into a tdgf1 À/À back-
ground (Figure 2B). The Tg(ARE:eGFP) reporter is therefore spe-
cific for Smad2-Smad4-Foxh1-mediated Nodal signaling during 
blastula stages. 
To confirm the inducibility of the reporter gene, we exposed 
dissociated cells from Tg(ARE:eGFP) blastula-stage embryos to 
increasing concentrations of recombinant NODAL and measured 
gene expression by qPCR. eGFP expression was induced at iden-
tical NODAL concentrations compared with ta, suggesting equal 
sensitivity of the reporter compared with this target gene (Fig-
ure 2C). Historically the sensitivity of Nodal target genes, such 
as ta and noto (flh), has been assessed by ectopically expressing 
Nodal ligands in the animal pole of blastula-stage embryos and 
using WISH to assay gene expression (Chen and Schier, 2001). </p>

<p>Using NODAL-coated beads in such an assay, we found that the 
reporter was induced in a domain of similar size to that of ta and 
noto (Figure 2D). Finally, we found no differences in the expression 
of downstream Nodal genes in 40%-50% epiboly embryos by 
qPCR and WISH when we compared WT and Tg(ARE:eGFP) em-
bryos, demonstrating that the introduction of the transgene had no 
impact on Nodal signaling (Figures S2C-S2E). In conclusion, the 
Tg(ARE:eGFP) zebrafish line is a specific and sensitive biosensor 
for early Nodal signaling. </p>

<p>Nodal Signaling Is Initiated by Both Maternal and Yolk 
Syncytial Layer-Derived Ligands 
We next used the Tg(ARE:eGFP) reporter line to determine 
how Nodal signaling is initiated in the embryo. At the 8-cell and 
1,000-cell stages, no eGFP mRNA could be detected (Figure 2E), 
indicating that eGFP mRNA is not maternally contributed. At 
sphere stage, however, signaling cells are detected as a local-
ized cluster of eGFP-positive cells (Figure 2F). From 30% epiboly 
until the onset of gastrulation, Nodal signaling is detected in 
the entire margin, with a shallow staining gradient running from 
dorsal to ventral (Figure 2F). As expected, the overall expression 
of eGFP correlated well with increasing levels of P-Smad2 
(Figure 2G). 
We compared the spatial and temporal activation of Nodal 
signaling in Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos with the expression of </p>

<p>B 
A 
C </p>

<p>u n t r e a t e d 
S U 
-5 4 0 2 </p>

<p>P-Erk </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>d n F g f R D </p>

<p>M 
S O </p>

<p>Erk </p>

<p>fscn1a 
ta </p>

<p>l 
o 
r 
t 
n 
o 
c </p>

<p>2 
0 
4 
5 
-
U 
S </p>

<p>lft1 
lft2 </p>

<p>R 
f 
g 
F 
n 
d </p>

<p>45/45 
84/84 
105/105 
41/42 </p>

<p>23/23 
44/44 
52/52 
13/13 </p>

<p>31/31 
46/48 
50/52 
36/36 </p>

<p>m 
o 
r 
f 
s 
r 
e 
i 
t 
l 
l 
e 
c n </p>

<p>i 
g 
r 
a 
m 
e 
h 
t 
D 
SU </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ta expression </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>S U 
-5 4 0 2 
D 
M 
S O 
S B -5 0 5 1 2 4 
P-Smad2 </p>

<p>Smad2 </p>

<p>Mcm6 </p>

<p>S U 
-5 4 0 2 
D </p>

<p>M 
S O 
S B -5 0 5 1 2 4 </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>P-Erk </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>4 
2 
1 
5 
0 
5 
-
B 
S </p>

<p>P-Erk 
DAPI 
overlay </p>

<p>ta 
fscn1a lft1 
lft2 </p>

<p>DMSO </p>

<p>a 
t </p>

<p>SU-5402 </p>

<p>D 
S U 
S B </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>5.0 
n 
o 
i 
s 
s 
e 
r 
p 
x 
e 
e 
v 
i 
t 
a 
l 
e 
r 
0 </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>D 
S U 
S B 
D 
S U 
S B 
D 
S U 
S B </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>Figure 1. Expression of ta and fscn1a in the 
Margin Is Regulated by Fgf Signaling </p>

<p>(A) Whole-mount immunofluorescence for phos-
phorylated Erk (P-Erk) in DMSO-and SB-505124-
treated 50% epiboly embryos. DAPI labels the 
nuclei. 
(B) Western blot for P-Erk in pooled 50% epiboly 
embryos treated with indicated compounds. Actin 
is a loading control. 
(C) Western blot for P-Erk and total Erk in pooled 
40%-50% embryos after control treatment or FgfR 
inhibition. Actin is a loading control. 
(D) WISH for ta, fscn1a, lft1, and lft2 in control 
embryos, embryos incubated with SU-5402, or 
embryos injected with mRNA encoding dnFgfR, at 
40%-50% epiboly. For fscn1a, animal views are 
shown. Red brackets outline the width of the WT ta 
expression domain. 
(E) qPCR for indicated Nodal target genes on 
pooled 50% epiboly embryos treated with DMSO 
(D), SB-505124 (SB), or SU-5402 (SU). Depicted is 
the mean expression ± SD normalized to eef1a1l1 
levels and compared with levels in DMSO-treated 
cells (*p &lt; 0.01, t test; n = 3). ns, not significant. 
(F) Western blot for P-Smad2 and Smad2 in pooled 
40%-50% embryos treated with the indicated 
compounds. Mcm6 is a loading control. 
(G) Sections of DMSO-and SU-5402-treated 
40%-50% epiboly embryos stained for ta. 
(H) Quantification of the number of cell tiers 
from the margin that express ta. Depicted is 
the mean ± SD (*p &lt; 0.01, Mann-Whitney U test; 
n &gt; 50). 
See also Figure S1. </p>

<p>Developmental Cell 35, 175-185, October 26, 2015 ª2015 The Authors 177 </p>

<p>core components of the pathway (Figure S3). The genes encod-
ing the receptor Acvr1ba, the co-receptor Tdgf1, and transcrip-
tion factors Smad2 and Foxh1 are ubiquitously expressed during 
blastula stages. The activation of signaling therefore depends 
exclusively on ligand expression (Figure S3). 
The discrete signaling domain at sphere stage likely corre-
sponds to the future dorsal side of the embryo, given the known 
dorsal localization of maternal ndr1 mRNA (Figures S3 and S4A) 
(Gore et al., 2005). We could show that ndr1 transcripts are 
polyadenylated before the maternal-to-zygotic transition (Fig-
ure S4B), suggesting that maternal ndr1 is translated and may 
signal during blastula stages. This was demonstrated by knock-
ing down the Mix-like transcription factor Mxtx2, which is 
required for zygotic ndr1 and ndr2 expression in the yolk syncy-
tial layer (YSL) (Fan et al., 2007; Hong et al., 2011; Xu et al., 2012). 
Tg(ARE:eGFP) mxtx2 morphants retained only a small, dorsal 
domain that expressed ndr1, ndr2, and eGFP (Figure S4C). 
Loss of the ventrolateral expression of ndr1/2 in the blastoderm 
in mxtx2 morphants suggested that this ndr1/2 expression was 
initiated by Nodal ligands secreted by the YSL and resulted 
from the ability of Ndr1/2 to induce their own expression. Indeed, 
embryos incubated with the Nodal inhibitor SB-505124 from the 
32-cell stage exhibited complete loss of expression of ndr1/2 in 
the blastoderm of 40% epiboly embryos, whereas expression of 
ndr1/2 in the YSL was not affected (Figure S4D) (Fan et al., 2007). </p>

<p>Thus, maternally provided Ndr1 activates Nodal signaling in 
dorsal-most embryonic cells before the initiation of signaling in 
the entire margin by Ndr1/2 synthesized in the YSL (Figure S4E). </p>

<p>Endogenous Nodal Signaling Extends up to Five or Six 
Cell Tiers from the Margin 
The Tg(ARE:eGFP) zebrafish line provides an ideal tool to inves-
tigate the dimensions of the Nodal signaling domain at the 
margin. To initially investigate whether there was any Nodal 
signaling beyond the ligand-expressing domain, we performed 
double fluorescent WISH for ndr2 and eGFP in 30% epiboly em-
bryos, when the Nodal signaling domain is expanding (Dubrulle 
et al., 2015; Harvey and Smith, 2009). Although individual 
signaling cells were occasionally observed directly adjacent to 
ndr2-expressing cells, no eGFP-positive cells were detected 
further beyond the ligand expression domain (Figure S5A). 
To determine the extent of Nodal signaling more rigorously, 
40%-50% epiboly Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos were stained for 
eGFP, ndr1, ndr2, lft1, and lft2 expression, sectioned, and quan-
titated (Figures 3A and 3B). The expression of eGFP, ndr1, ndr2, 
and lft1 was limited to an average of about five cell tiers, whereas 
lft2 expression was detected in only two to three cell tiers from 
the margin. To confirm that these findings were not due to a 
lack of sensitivity of the WISH, we analyzed the expression of 
sox3, which is repressed by Nodal signaling in the margin </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>Figure 2. The Tg(ARE:eGFP) Zebrafish Line 
Is a Sensitive and Specific In Vivo Nodal 
Reporter </p>

<p>(A) Top: schematic representation of the Nodal 
reporter gene construct. Bottom: WISH for eGFP in 
Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos at 50% epiboly (above, 
lateral view; below, animal view) and 22 somite 
stages. Dashed line indicates the midline. A, 
anterior; D, dorsal; lpm, lateral plate mesoderm; P, 
posterior; V, ventral. 
(B) WISH for eGFP in control-treated Tg(AR-
E:eGFP) embryos or after inhibition of Nodal 
signaling by SB-505124 from the 32-cell stage 
(left), injection of foxh1 MO (middle), or in a tdgf1 À/À 
background (right) at 50% or 30% epiboly. For the 
tdgf1 À/À experiment, a clutch of 16 embryos from a 
heterozygous incross was analyzed. Note that 
25% of embryos lack eGFP staining. 
(C) qPCR for eGFP, ta, and odc1 on dissociated 
blastula-stage Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryonic cells. De-
picted is the mean relative expression compared 
with untreated cells, normalized to eef1a1l1 levels 
from one representative experiment ± SD. 
(D) Polystyrene beads soaked in recombinant hu-
man NODAL were implanted into the animal pole of 
1000-cell Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos. Once the em-
bryos had reached ring stage, they were stained for 
the indicated genes. Animal views are shown. A red 
spot indicates the position of the bead. 
(E) eGFP expression at 8-cell and 1,000-cell stages. 
(F) eGFP expression in sphere, 30% and 50% 
epiboly Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos. Arrow indicates 
expression in dorsal cells. 
(G) Western blot for phosphorylated Smad2 (P-
Smad2) in blastula stage embryos treated with or 
without SB-505124. Mcm6 is a loading control. 
See also Figures S2-S4. </p>



<p>(Bennett et al., 2007). Significant repression was seen in up to six 
cell tiers from the margin (Figure 3A). Importantly, staining for all 
induced Nodal target genes, including eGFP, was consistently 
stronger in a cluster of cells directly proximal to the YSL, where 
signaling originates (Figure 3A). 
To corroborate the data obtained from the sections, we used a 
direct readout of the Nodal pathway, fluorescent immunostain-
ing of whole-mount 50% epiboly embryos with an antibody 
against P-Smad2. For comparison, we also stained for P-Erk. 
Nuclear P-Smad2 staining was observed exclusively in the 
margin and, as expected, in a smaller domain than the P-Erk 
staining (Figure 3C). To quantitate the size of the P-Smad2-
positive domain, we imaged the embryos at the margin, used 
<rs type="software">MetaMorph</rs> software to generate normalized nuclear staining in-
tensities, and measured the distance of each nucleus from the 
margin in control-and SB-505124-treated embryos. P-Smad2 
staining above background was found up to five to six cell tiers 
(80-90 mm) from the margin in a steep gradient, which was 
abolished in SB-505124-treated embryos (Figures 3D, 3E, and 
S5B-S5D). The staining was strongest in the nuclei of cells near-
est the YSL. Taken together with our observations from the 
Tg(ARE:eGFP) reporter line, these data demonstrate that Nodal 
signaling occurs in five to six cell tiers from the margin, closely 
mirroring the expression of the ligands. </p>

<p>Temporal Regulation of Lft1 Protein Translation during 
Early Blastula Stages 
Our data demonstrate that the Nodal ligands and antagonists are 
co-expressed at the margin of late blastula-stage embryos, and 
moreover, Nodal activity is restricted to these cells. This raised </p>

<p>two important questions. First, if the ligands and antagonists 
are co-expressed, how does signaling occur at all? Second, 
given that all cells are competent to signal at blastula stages 
and Nodal signaling induces the expression of the ligands, why 
does signaling not spread throughout the embryo? 
To address these questions, we first determined to what 
extent Lft1/2 regulate Nodal signaling in early and late blastula-
stage embryos. The Lft1/2 proteins are known to inhibit signaling 
by sequestering Tdgf1 and possibly also Nodal itself (Chen and 
Shen, 2004; Cheng et al., 2004). As expected, injection of lft1/2 
MOs led to an expansion of the Nodal signaling domain at 
50% epiboly, which was confirmed by qPCR (Figures 4A and 
4B). At dome stage, however, there was no increase in the size 
of the Nodal signaling domain, suggesting that Lft1/2 do not 
regulate Nodal signaling at early stages. Although there is an 
offset in the appearance of ndr1/2 and lft1/2 mRNA due to the 
presence of maternal ndr1 transcripts, the lack of an early role 
for Lft1/2 is not explained by an absence of lft1/2 mRNA at 
sphere and dome stages (Figures 4C and S3). We hypothesized 
therefore that a delay in translation of the Lft1/2 proteins could 
account for the inability of Lft1/2 to regulate Nodal signaling at 
dome stage. Both lft1 and lft2 transcripts were readily polyade-
nylated by sphere stage (Figure 4D), suggesting that lack of poly-
adenylation could not account for any delay in Lft1/2 translation. 
To measure endogenous protein levels directly, we raised 
polyclonal antibodies for Lft1 and Lft2 and thoroughly character-
ized them (Figure S6). Although both antibodies recognized their 
corresponding target protein when overexpressed (Figure S6B), 
only the Lft1 antibody was able to detect endogenous protein, so 
we focused on this family member. The major band detected by </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D 
E </p>

<p>Figure 3. Extent of Nodal Signaling and 
Target Gene Expression in Tg(ARE:eGFP) 
Embryos </p>

<p>(A) Sections of 40%-50% epiboly embryos, 
stained for eGFP, ndr1, ndr2, lft1, lft2, and sox3. 
Sections were counterstained with Nuclear Fast 
Red. The black line indicates the border of the YSL 
and blastoderm; arrowheads indicate five cell tiers. 
(B) Quantification of the number of cell tiers that 
express indicated Nodal target genes, calculated 
from the margin. Depicted is the mean number of 
cell tiers ± SD (n = 18). 
(C) Whole-mount immunofluorescence of 50% 
epiboly embryos for P-Smad2 and P-Erk. DAPI 
labels nuclei. Depicted is a single optical slice of a 
lateral view. 
(D) Immunofluorescence for P-Smad2 in DMSO-
and SB-505124-treated 50% embryos. Depicted is 
a Z-projection of a lateral view. The white dashed 
line indicates the border of the margin. 
(E) Quantification of P-Smad2 immunofluores-
cence normalized to background signal as a 
function of the number of cell tiers from the margin 
in DMSO-and SB-505124-treated embryos. Data 
were binned in 15 mm intervals to represent the 
average size of a cell in 50% epiboly embryo 
(Dubrulle et al., 2015). Depicted are means of each 
bin obtained from multiple optical slices ± SEM 
(*p &lt; 0.0, t test, n = 3, comparing DMSO-and SB-
505124-treated intensities for each cell tier). 
See also Figure S5. </p>

<p>Developmental Cell 35, 175-185, October 26, 2015 ª2015 The Authors 179 </p>

<p>western blot corresponding to endogenous Lft1 migrated by 
SDS-PAGE with a molecular weight of $40 kD (Figure S6C). 
Mutation analysis indicated that this product arose from cleav-
age at the first Furin cleavage site (marked as C1 in Figure S6A), 
and we could demonstrate that this product was active (Figures 
S6D-S6F). The same 40 kD band was also detected in embryos 
injected with ndr1 mRNA (Figure S6G). Levels of endogenous 
Lft1 were barely detectable by western blotting at dome stage 
and 30% epiboly but increased at 50% epiboly (Figures 4E 
and 4F). Thus, endogenous Lft1 protein levels remain low until 
50% epiboly, despite readily detectable mRNA levels at all these 
time points. This suggested that the lack of an early role for Lft1/2 
could be due to low protein abundance and led us to hypothesize 
that repressed Lft1/2 translation creates a window of opportunity 
for Nodal signaling to become established. </p>

<p>miR-430 Creates a Temporal Window for Nodal </p>

<p>Signaling by Regulating Lft1/2 Levels 
During blastula stages, the miR-430 family of miRNAs have been 
reported to block translation, without affecting polyadenylation 
(Bazzini et al., 2012; Choi et al., 2007). We reasoned therefore 
that the activity of miR-430 could be responsible for the re-
pressed translation of Lft1/2 proteins to create a temporal 
window for Nodal to activate signaling. miR-430 pri-miRNA is 
expressed in the nuclei of all cells in the blastoderm, immediately 
after activation of zygotic transcription (Figure 5A). We also 
confirmed a ubiquitous expression pattern for mature miR-
430a and miR-430b at 50% epiboly (Figure 5B) and demon-</p>

<p>dome 
50% epi </p>

<p>con MO </p>

<p>lft1/2 MOs </p>

<p>23/23 </p>

<p>24/24 </p>

<p>15/17 </p>

<p>9/9 </p>

<p>sphere dome </p>

<p>ndr1 
lft1 
lft2 </p>

<p>30% 
epi </p>

<p>50% 
epi 
-+ -+ -+ -+ </p>

<p>Lft1 -</p>

<p>P-Smad2 -</p>

<p>Mcm6 -</p>

<p>SB-505124 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>6 4 -c e l l h i g h 
s p h e r e d o m </p>

<p>e 
5 0 % </p>

<p>e p i </p>

<p>lft1 </p>

<p>lft2 
-total </p>

<p>-poly-A </p>

<p>total </p>

<p>poly-A 
1 -c e l l </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>% of maximal expression </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>MZT </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>eGFP </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Relative Lft1 protein 
expression </p>

<p>s p h e r e 
d o m </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 0 % </p>

<p>e p i </p>

<p>3 0 % </p>

<p>e p i </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>dome 
50% epi 
relative 
eGFP expression </p>

<p>con MO 
lft1/2 MO </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 
* </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 4 -c e l l 
h i g h 
s p h e r e 
d o m </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>5 0 % </p>

<p>e p i 
s h i e l d 
1 -c e l l </p>

<p>Figure 4. Delayed Translation of Lft1/2 
Levels during Early Blastula Stages </p>

<p>(A) WISH for eGFP in dome and 50% epiboly 
Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos, injected with control or 
lft1/2 MOs. Animal views are shown at left, and 
ventrolateral sections are shown at right. 
(B) qPCR for eGFP mRNA on pooled dome and 
50% epiboly embryos. Depicted are means ± SEM 
(*p &lt; 0.01, t test; n = 6). 
(C) qPCR for ndr1, lft1, and lft2 at different stages. 
The percentage of mean maximal expression ± SD 
from a representative experiment performed in 
triplicate is shown. 
(D) Extension poly-A test (ePAT) for lft1 and lft2 
mRNA. Silver stained non-denaturing poly-
acrylamide gels are shown indicating total and 
polyadenylated (poly-A) mRNA. 
(E) Western blot showing protein expression of 
endogenous Lft1 and phosphorylated Smad2 in 
pooled, blastula-stage embryos. Treatment with 
SB-505124 is shown to confirm the Lft1 band. 
Mcm6 is a loading control. 
(F) Quantification of Lft1 protein expression from 
sphere to 50% epiboly. Depicted are the average 
band intensities of three independent blots, 
normalized to levels at 50% epiboly ± SD (*p &lt; 
0.05, t test). 
See also Figure S6. </p>

<p>strated that mature miR-430a and miR-
430b are directly processed upon 
expression (Figure 5C). miR-430c was 
not detected by either WISH or northern 
blotting, but RNA sequencing data demonstrated that miR-
430c is much less abundant than miR-430a and miR-430b 
(unpublished data). Thus, the miR-430 family is abundant, ubiq-
uitously expressed, and readily processed during mid to late 
blastula stages. 
To determine the role of miR-430 in the regulation of Lft1/2 
protein translation, we designed three MOs that prevented pro-
cessing of mature miR-430a, miR-430b, and miR-430c. Injection 
of these MOs into one-cell-stage embryos resulted in a pheno-
type resembling MZ dicer mutants at 22 hpf (Figure S7A) (Giral-
dez et al., 2005). Furthermore, they abolished miR-430a staining 
at 50% epiboly and reduced miR-430a, miR-430b, and miR-
430c expression, as determined by qPCR, by 89% (Figures 
S7B and S7C). Co-injection of miR-430 MOs with a GFP reporter 
containing either three miR-430 binding sites or a GFP reporter 
with the lft2 3 0 UTR, which contains a single miR-430 binding 
site, resulted in increased translation compared to control MOs 
(Figure S7D). Together, these experiments demonstrate the effi-
cacy of the miR-430 MOs. 
We next injected equal amounts of control or miR-430 MOs 
and performed western blotting for P-Smad2 and Lft1 at several 
blastula stages. In control MO-injected embryos, Lft1 protein 
was not detectable until 30% epiboly and increased at 50% 
epiboly, as observed for Lft1 protein expression in WT embryos 
(compare Figure 4E with Figure 5D). Importantly, this was 
accompanied by a gradual increase of P-Smad2 over time. In 
contrast, injection of miR-430 MOs led to premature translation 
of Lft1 from dome stage, and this coincided with lower overall </p>

<p>180 Developmental Cell 35, 175-185, October 26, 2015 ª2015 The Authors </p>

<p>accumulation of P-Smad2 (Figure 5D). Interestingly, the level of 
Lft1 protein in dome-stage miR-430 morphants was similar to 
the maximal level of Lft1 protein measured at 50% epiboly in 
control MO-injected embryos, suggesting that there may be a 
threshold level of Lft1 that is inhibitory. 
To determine whether reduced signaling in the miR-430 mor-
phants was due to premature translation of Lft1/2 and to inves-
tigate the spatial consequences for Nodal signaling of the loss 
of miR-430, we injected miR-430 MOs and/or lft1/2 MOs into 
Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos and assayed Nodal activity (eGFP) 
and ndr1 levels at 30% epiboly. Injection of lft1/2 MOs alone re-
sulted in a modest increase in eGFP and ndr1 staining (Fig-
ure 5E), whereas injection of miR-430 MOs led to a reduction 
in eGFP staining in the blastoderm, consistent with the inhibi-
tion of the Nodal signaling pathway we observed using P-
Smad2 levels as a readout (Figure 5D). When lft1/2 MOs and 
miR-430 MOs were co-injected, signaling was activated in 
the entire blastoderm, and this was accompanied by a similar 
expansion of ndr1 expression (Figure 5E). Importantly, this 
spreading of eGFP staining in lft1/2 and miR-430 MO-co-in-
jected embryos was due to Nodal signaling, because it was 
completely blocked by incubating double morphants with SB-
505124 (Figure 5F). The further spreading of signaling following 
combined knockdown of lft1/2 and miR-430 is readily ex-
plained by the regulation of Ndr1 translation by miR-430 in 
the absence of Lft1/2 (see Figure 7A) (Choi et al., 2007). 
Together, these experiments demonstrate that miR-430 delays 
Lft1/2 translation to create a temporal window for Nodal to acti-
vate signaling. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>Figure 5. Temporal Regulation of Lft1/2 
Translation by miR-430s </p>

<p>(A) WISH for pri-miR-430 at indicated stages. 
(B) WISH using LNA probes for mature miR-430a 
and miR-430b at 50% epiboly. 
(C) Northern blot for miR-430a and miR-430b at 
indicated stages using the same probes as in (B). 
mat, mature miRNA; pre, pre-miRNA. 
(D) Western blot for endogenous Lft1 and P-
Smad2 in pooled, blastula-stage embryos injected 
with control or miR-430 MOs. Mcm6 is a loading 
control. epi, epiboly. 
(E) Lateral views of WISH for eGFP reporter and 
ndr1 in 30% epiboly, Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos in-
jected with MOs against lft1/2, miR-430 or both. 
(F) WISH for eGFP mRNA in 40% epiboly Tg(ARE: 
eGFP) embryos injected with control or combined 
lft1/2 and miR-430 MOs and treated with DMSO or 
SB-505124. Animal views are shown. 
See also Figure S7. </p>

<p>Duration of Ligand Exposure 
Translates Directly into Increasing 
Signaling Levels 
Our data demonstrate that a temporal 
window for Nodal signaling activation de-
termines the size of the Nodal signaling 
domain and predict that once Lft1/2 levels 
reach a certain threshold, Nodal signaling 
is unable to spread to adjacent cells. We 
therefore tested if blocking signaling acti-
vation by recombinant mouse LEFTY1 (mLEFTY1) is dose depen-
dent in dissociated embryonic cells. A 5-fold excess (calculated 
by mass) of mLEFTY1 over human recombinant NODAL led to 
a near complete inhibition of signaling activation as read out by 
western blotting for P-Smad2 and endogenous zebrafish Lft1, 
which monitors the transcriptional output of the pathway (Fig-
ure 6A). Thus, Lft1/2 proteins can reach an inhibitory concentra-
tion at which signaling can no longer be activated. 
Next we determined if duration of exposure to NODAL directly 
corresponds to increasing levels of signaling. When blastula-
stage cells were exposed to 50 ng/ml NODAL and then inhibited 
with a blocking concentration of 500 ng/ml mLEFTY1 at different 
time points, P-Smad2 and endogenous Lft1 levels were indeed 
proportional to the duration of ligand exposure (Figure 6B). 
Finally, we investigated how rapidly signaling is blocked when 
Lft1/2 levels reach inhibitory concentrations. This is a crucial 
issue, as we observe that Nodal signaling in vivo (as read out 
by eGFP, ndr1, ndr2, lft1, and lft2) is sustained in the margin 
for several hours after Lft1 levels reach an inhibitory concentra-
tion at around 50% epiboly (Figure S3). Dissociated embryonic 
cells were therefore exposed to NODAL for 1 hr, and then 
signaling was inhibited by addition of mLEFTY1 for 2 hr. We 
observed that P-Smad2 levels decreased slowly, compared 
with the rapid termination of signaling with SB-505124 (Fig-
ure 6C). This demonstrated that although signal activation is 
blocked by Lefty, Nodal signaling is sustained for some time, 
presumably because of continued signaling from internalized re-
ceptor complexes in early endosomes (Jullien and Gurdon, 
2005;  n et al., 2013). </p>

<p>Developmental Cell 35, 175-185, October 26, 2015 ª2015 The Authors 181 </p>

<p>In conclusion, our data show that activation of Nodal signaling 
in blastula-stage cells can occur until Lft1/2 levels reach inhibi-
tory concentrations. Moreover, the levels of P-Smad2, and as 
a result transcription, are proportional to the duration of signal 
activation. This can be maintained for some time after inhibitory 
Lft1/2 concentrations are reached, while no new signaling is 
activated. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>A Temporal Window of Signaling Activation Determines 
the Size and Shape of the Nodal Signaling Domain 
Here we describe a specific and sensitive Nodal reporter line 
that has enabled us to visualize endogenous Nodal signaling in 
developing zebrafish embryos, without overexpression of any 
pathway components. We show that signaling is initiated on 
the dorsal side because of maternally provided Ndr1. Ventral 
and lateral signaling arises as a result of Ndr1/2 expression in 
the YSL, which then spreads toward the animal pole as a result 
of autoregulation. Nodal signaling in the margin reaches a 
maximum of six cell tiers, which we demonstrate by P-Smad2 
immunostaining and reporter activity. We find no evidence of 
signaling beyond the cells that express the ligand, and moreover, 
these same cells additionally express the Nodal antagonists 
Lft1/2. Spreading of presumed long-range Nodal target genes, 
such as ta, that are activated beyond the ligand expression 
domain, is actually due to Fgf signaling, activated downstream 
of Nodal. Our data support a model whereby a temporal window 
for Nodal signaling activation dictates the dimensions of 
the Nodal signaling domain (Figure 7). Thus, temporal informa-
tion is translated into spatial information in the developing 
embryo. 
The crucial determinant of the temporal window is the de-
layed translation of the Lft1/2 proteins, which is mediated by 
miR-430. In addition, maternally provided ndr1 transcripts 
and the production of Ndr1/2 by the YSL allow Nodal signaling 
to be initiated in the blastoderm, before transcription of lft1/2 
(Figure 7C). ndr1/2 expression in the YSL activates signaling 
in adjacent cells in the blastoderm. Because of positive feed-</p>

<p>back, the blastoderm cells produce more Ndr1/2, while Lft1/2 
levels remain relatively low because of the ubiquitous synthesis 
of miR-430. In these conditions, Nodal signaling can be acti-
vated in neighboring cells until extracellular Lft1/2 levels reach 
inhibitory concentrations. Therefore, the duration for which 
Lft1/2 levels are repressed dictates the size of the Nodal 
signaling domain. How the repressive action of miR-430 is 
lifted at 50% epiboly to allow Lft1/2 translation is not yet known 
and requires further investigation. Although inhibitory Lft1/2 
levels prevent further activation of signaling, and hence addi-
tional spreading of Nodal signaling, cells already responding 
to Nodal will continue to signal for several hours, because 
this occurs from internalized receptors that are refractory to 
Lft1/2 inhibition. A consequence of our proposed mechanism 
is that cells directly adjacent to the YSL activate Nodal 
signaling for the longest duration. This likely explains the 
more intense P-Smad2 staining in these cells relative to those 
further from the margin. We therefore propose that Nodal 
signaling at the margin at blastula stages is dictated by an 
interplay among ligand, ligand antagonist, and a miRNA, with 
a differential in timing between ligand and antagonist produc-
tion being the key determining factor. 
The size and shape of the Nodal signaling gradient had previ-
ously been thought to be regulated by a reaction-diffusion sys-
tem (Meinhardt, 2009;  ller et al., 2012; Schier, 2009). Here 
we propose an alternative mechanism whereby the size of the 
domain is dictated by the delay in Lefty translation. Although 
the Nodal/Lefty ligand/antagonist pair has many features of a re-
action-diffusion system, we have uncovered one aspect that is 
incompatible. In reaction-diffusion models, which were originally 
conceived as pattern-forming chemical reactions, a homoge-
neous distribution of activator and inhibitor are unstable, and a 
local elevation of activator initiates formation of a gradient (Mein-
hardt, 2009). Integral to this model is the ability of the diffusing 
antagonist to immediately inhibit activator function at a distance. 
For Nodal and Lefty, this cannot happen, because once Nodal 
signaling is activated it occurs from internalized receptors and 
is therefore insensitive to Lefty inhibition, except over prolonged 
time frames. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 6. Nodal Signaling Dynamics </p>

<p>(A) Western blot for P-Smad2 and endogenous Lft1 
on dissociated blastula-stage embryonic cells. 
Cells were exposed to 100 ng/ml NODAL for 2 hr, 
with or without increasing doses of mLEFTY1. 
Actin is a loading control. Lft1 runs as two bands: 
the upper one is unprocessed, and the lower is the 
40 kD processed band. SB, SB-505124. 
(B) Cells were treated ± 10 mM SB-505124 or with 
50 ng/ml NODAL and then with 500 ng/ml 
mLEFTY1 at the indicated time points. All cells 
were collected at the 3 hr time point and western 
blotted as indicated. 
(C) Top: scheme of the experimental setup. Arrows 
denote addition of the indicated compound or 
recombinant protein. All cells were collected at the 
3-hr time point. Bottom: western blot using the 
indicated antibodies. Times (hours) of incubation 
with 10 mM SB-505124, NODAL, or mLEFTY1 are 
shown. </p>



<p>A Temporal Gradient of Nodal Signaling and Cell Fate 
Decisions 
Our data suggest that spatially graded activity of the Nodal 
signaling pathway is mainly the result of different durations of 
exposure to Ndr1/2 over time, as opposed to exposure to 
different concentrations. We observe two graded signaling do-
mains in Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos that are both explained by 
timing of ligand exposure. During blastula stages, a shallow 
signaling gradient runs from dorsal to ventral. This is readily ex-
plained by the fact that dorsal cells are exposed to Nodal for a 
longer period than ventrolateral cells, because maternally pro-
vided Ndr1 signals dorsally before Ndr1/2 produced in the YSL 
induces signaling in the blastoderm margin. In addition, we found 
a clear vegetal-to-animal gradient within the ligand-expression 
domain using P-Smad2 immunostaining in late blastula-stage 
embryos, and we also observed that cells directly adjacent to 
the YSL expressed higher levels of all Nodal target genes, 
including the eGFP reporter gene, reflecting higher levels of 
signaling. Again, cells directly adjacent to the YSL are exposed 
to Ndr1/2 for the longest period of time. The importance of dura-
tion of exposure is further supported by our ex vivo experiments 
with dissociated embryonic cells. The long-term functional con-
sequences of this were demonstrated in previously published 
work, which linked cell fates to the duration of exposure to Nodal 
signals (Hagos and Dougan, 2007). Thus, our model explains 
how concentration and duration of signaling can be translated 
into positional information. Finally, the importance of timing of </p>

<p>signaling activation also rationalizes the normal development 
of ndr1 mutants (Feldman et al., 1998; Heisenberg and  s-
slein-Volhard, 1997; Lim et al., 2013). Mesendoderm develop-
ment in these mutants is largely normal, although delayed. This 
is explained by the fact that Ndr2 compensates for the lack of 
Ndr1, but its expression is delayed, because there is no maternal 
Ndr2. 
From the sectioning of Tg(ARE:eGFP) embryos and immuno-
staining for P-Smad2, it is clear that Smad2-Smad4-Foxh1-
dependent Nodal signaling is confined to 5-6 cell tiers from the 
margin, which could imply that all mesendodermal cells arise 
from this domain. This finding seems to contradict lineage-
tracing studies that show that some mesodermal precursors 
are located up to 12 cell tiers away from the margin (e.g., see 
Dougan et al., 2003; Warga and  sslein-Volhard, 1999). 
Although these lineage-tracing studies have provided valuable 
insight into the overall spatial distribution of mesendoderm pre-
cursors, they cannot themselves determine the extent of Nodal 
signaling. This is because although Nodal signaling is required 
for mesendoderm formation, not all cells that become mesendo-
derm have necessarily experienced Nodal signaling directly. 
Our understanding of how morphogens activate graded sig-
naling in tissues has been dominated by the pre-molecular era 
assumption that secreted ligands diffuse from a source to form 
concentration gradients, and this assumption has naturally pro-
gressed into the formulation of models that include diffusion as 
a major determinant in patterning by morphogens. Although in </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 7. The Nodal Temporal Window Model </p>

<p>(A) Schematic showing how miR-430, Lft1/2, and ndr1/2 regulate one another. 
(B) Model of temporal window for Nodal signaling activation, controlled by miR-430 and Lft1/2. Ndr1/2 protein levels increase (dark blue line) over time because of 
autoregulation at low Lft1/2 concentrations (red line) until sufficient Lft1/2 is translated to inhibit signaling activation (pink shading) just before the onset of 
gastrulation. This process is controlled by miR-430s (green line, middle), which allows slow accumulation of signaling (light blue line, right). G, gastrulation; 1K, 
1,000-cell stage. 
(C) In vivo mesendoderm induction over time according to the Nodal temporal window model. YSL-expressing Ndr1/2 is shown in purple; cells responding to 
Nodal are in blue, with dark blue denoting those experiencing the longest signaling duration. Cells expressing miR-430 are denoted with green nuclei, and pink 
shading depicts cells in which Lft1/2 levels have reached an inhibitory threshold. Note that by 50% epiboly the cells beyond the Nodal signaling domain 
are responding to Fgf, and this accounts for expression of mesodermal genes such as ta and fscn1a in these cells. For details, see text. DC, deep cells; EVL, 
enveloping layer. </p>

<p>Developmental Cell 35, 175-185, October 26, 2015 ª2015 The Authors 183 </p>

<p>some contexts, such as the establishment of left-right asymme-
try, Nodal can act at long range (Shiratori and Hamada, 2014), 
the work presented here shows that the formation of the Nodal 
signaling domain at the blastula margin is explained by short-
range signaling activation, signaling dynamics, and transcrip-
tional/translational regulation. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>For detailed experimental procedures, see the Supplemental Information. </p>

<p>Recombinant Proteins and Inhibitors 
Human NODAL (3218-ND/CF; R&amp;D) was dissolved in 4 mM HCl at 100 mg/ml, 
aliquoted in non-stick tubes, and used at 40 ng/ml (unless stated otherwise) 
without freeze-thawing. Recombinant mLEFTY1 was dissolved according to 
the manufacturer's instructions (994-LF/CF; R&amp;D). The inhibitors SB-505124 
(3263; Tocris Bioscience) and SU-5402 (572631; Calbiochem) were dissolved 
in DMSO and used in embryos at 50 and 10 mM respectively. In dissociated 
embryonic cells, SB-505124 was used at 10 mM. </p>

<p>Dissociated Embryonic Cell Culture 
For blastula-stage cell cultures, up to 1,000 embryos were dechorionated us-
ing 2 mg/ml Pronase (11459643001; Roche) in 10 ml E3 medium. The dechor-
ionated embryos were washed extensively in E3 medium and once with 
calcium-free Ringers buffer to remove the Pronase (Link et al., 2006). The em-
bryos were manually disrupted in calcium-free Ringers buffer using a P200 
pipette in 6 cm bacterial dishes, collected by centrifugation at 1,000 3 g for 
5 min, and then resuspended at $50 embryos/ml in Leibovitz's L15 Medium 
(11415-064; GIBCO) supplemented with 3% fetal bovine serum (FBS). Cells 
were plated in 24-well tissue culture plates coated with poly-L lysine (P4707; 
Sigma) and allowed to attach for 30 min. These experiments were performed 
at 28 C using pre-warmed buffers in triplicate. The experiments were termi-
nated by aspirating the medium and freezing the plates at À80 C. </p>

<p>Whole-Mount Immunofluorescence and Quantification of P-Smad2 
Staining 
Embryos were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS overnight, dehydrated to 
100% methanol, and stored at À20 C until processing. For whole-mount 
immunofluorescence, embryos were rehydrated to PBS and incubated in 
cold acetone at À20 C for 20 min. Blocking and antibody incubations were 
performed in 10% FBS and 1% Triton X-100 in PBS, and washes were per-
formed in PBS/1% Triton. The following primary antibodies were used: a-P-
Smad2/3 (8828; Cell Signaling Technology) and a-P-Erk (M8159; Sigma). 
Note that because of the lack of Smad3 at blastula stages, we solely detect 
P-Smad2 with the a-P-Smad2/3 antibody. DAPI was used to stain nuclei, 
and images were acquired on a Zeiss LSM 780 confocal microscope. For 
quantification of P-Smad2 intensity in deep cells, <rs id="software-1" type="software">MetaMorph</rs> Software 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>) was used to generate P-Smad2 to DAPI ratios from at 
least three single optical slices per embryo, in three individual DMSO or SB-
505124 treated, 50% epiboly embryos. Care was taken not to select mitotic 
or overlapping nuclei or nuclei from the enveloping layer. To measure the dis-
tance of a nucleus to the margin, a line was drawn laterally at the vegetal edge 
of the margin, and the distance to the nucleus perpendicular to the margin was 
measured using the <rs type="software">MetaMorph</rs> Software. To normalize the staining intensity 
for each embryo, the average ratio of an area further than 11 cell tiers from the 
margin (&gt;165 mm) was subtracted from each measurement. The data were 
divided in 15 mm bins, representing the average size of a deep cell at 50% epib-
oly (unpublished data; Dubrulle et al., 2015). The averages of the binned data 
for each cell tier, comparing DMSO and SB-505124 treatment, were used for 
testing for statistical significant differences using paired t tests with a 95% 
confidence interval. </p>

<p>Animal Experimentation 
All the zebrafish work was carried out under a UK Home Office License under 
the Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986. The license underwent full ethical 
review and approval by the Cancer Research UK London Research Institute 
Animal Ethics Committee. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION </p>

<p>Supplemental Information includes Supplemental Experimental Procedures 
and seven figures and can be found with this article online at http://dx.doi. 
org/10.1016/j.devcel.2015.09.014. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS </p>

<p>A.L.v.B. and C.S.H. conceived the study. A.L.v.B., J.E.C., C.H., and M.-C.R. 
performed the experiments and analyzed the data with the help of R.K.S. 
A.L.v.B. and C.S.H. wrote the paper, with input from the other authors. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to thank E. Amaya, A. Giraldez, M. Hammerschmidt, S. Harvey, 
A. Meng, P.  ller, A. Lekven, S. Reichert, A. Schier, and S. Wilson for re-
agents. We are very grateful to D. Martin, C. Sergeant, and P. Taylor for fish 
maintenance, and we also thank the Francis Crick Institute Light Microscopy 
Facility and Equipment Park. We thank S. Horswell and M. Schaafsma for 
assistance with statistics. We thank members of the Hill lab, A. Economou, 
N. Tapon, B. Thompson, and J.P. Vincent, for discussions and insightful 
comments on the manuscript. This work was supported by Cancer Research 
UK and the European Commission Network of Excellence EpiGeneSys 
(HEALTH-F4-2010-257082). </p>

<p>Received: January 13, 2015 
Revised: August 11, 2015 
Accepted: September 23, 2015 
Published: October 26, 2015 </p>







<p>Developmental Cell 35, 175-185, October 26, 2015 ª2015 The Authors 185 </p>

</text></tei>