<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4918545" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Spinal cord injury (SCI) may result in skeletal 
muscle atrophy. Identifying diagnostic biomarkers and effec-
tive targets for treatment is an important challenge in clinical 
work. The aim of the present study is to elucidate potential 
biomarkers and therapeutic targets for SCI-induced muscle 
atrophy (SIMA) using proteomic and bioinformatic analyses. 
The protein samples from rat soleus muscle were collected at 
different time points following SCI injury and separated by 
two-dimensional gel electrophoresis and compared with the 
sham group. The identities of these protein spots were analyzed 
by mass spectrometry (MS). MS demonstrated that 20 proteins 
associated with muscle atrophy were differentially expressed. 
Bioinformatic analyses indicated that SIMA changed the 
expression of proteins associated with cellular, developmental, 
immune system and metabolic processes, biological adhe-
sion and localization. The results of the present study may 
be beneficial in understanding the molecular mechanisms of 
SIMA and elucidating potential biomarkers and targets for the 
treatment of muscle atrophy. </p>

<p>Spinal cord injury (SCI) is a serious central nervous system 
disorder. Sociological changes, and infrastructural and 
transport system development have resulted in an increased 
incidence of SCI (1). Patients with SCI experience irrevers-
ible sensory and motor dysfunction. In modern society, the 
length of time that patients with paralysis and SCI survive has 
increased, which results in a heavy financial burden for the 
families and society. </p>

<p>SCI commonly leads to muscle atrophy (2). Previous 
research has demonstrated that within the initial 6-18 months 
following SCI, 27 to 56% of the muscle fibers have atrophied (3). 
Currently, there is no clear consensus regarding classification 
of the type of atrophy that occurs following SCI, certain 
reports suggest disuse (4-7) and denervated atrophy (8,9). 
However, the atrophy induced by SCI is different from the 
aforementioned types of atrophy. Disuse models are based on 
variable degrees of unloading and inactivity, including ankle 
immobilization and hindlimb unloading. Disuse-induced 
muscle atrophy occurs when the central nervous system is 
intact. Another scenario is denervated atrophy, which is often 
induced by the model of peripheral axotomy (10,11). The 
central nervous system is not damaged in this type of muscle 
atrophy, as the injury is restricted to the axon of the dorsal 
root ganglion. The difference between SCI-induced muscle 
loss and the aforementioned types of atrophy is that in SCI the 
lower motor neurons remain intact and upper neurons cannot 
transmit information to the lower neurons. 
Due to the complexity of the central nervous system and the 
observed cases of spontaneous functional recovery (12,13), 
the present study hypothesizes that the SCI-induced muscle 
atrophy (SIMA) may be the result of a special pathological 
mechanism. To develop novel treatment strategies or find 
novel diagnostic markers, it is required to investigate the 
molecular mechanisms and signaling pathways that mediate 
SCI-induced muscle atrophy. Previous studies have demon-
strated the involvement of certain molecules and genes during 
this pathological process (14-16). However, the pathological 
mechanisms of SIMA are complex, thus, only investigating 
certain molecules is insufficient. Microarray data has 
provided some indication of the changes to mRNA expres-
sion levels that occur within the whole genome following 
SCI. However, the mRNA expression level does not always 
correlate with the protein expression level. Post-translational 
modifications and microRNAs may affect the protein expres-
sion levels (17). Thus, adopting a proteomics approach to 
analyze the global protein profile in SIMA may provide more 
accurate information that cannot be obtained from micro-
array analysis. 
To the best of our knowledge, there have been no system-
atic studies aimed at identifying the proteins associated with 
SIMA on a proteome scale. The present study compared 
normal soleus muscle samples with post-SCI soleus muscle 
samples by two-dimensional (2D) gel electrophoresis, </p>

<p>Proteomic and bioinformatic analyses of 
spinal cord injury-induced skeletal muscle atrophy in rats </p>

<p>ZHI-JIAN WEI 
* , XIAN-HU ZHOU 
* , BAO-YOU FAN, WEI LIN, YI-MING REN and SHI-QING FENG </p>

<p>Department of Orthopaedics, Tianjin Medical University General Hospital, Tianjin 300052, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received June 26, 2015; Accepted May 3, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/mmr.2016.5272 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Shi-Qing Feng, Department </p>

<p>of Orthopaedics, Tianjin Medical University General Hospital, 
154 Anshan Road, Heping, Tianjin 300052, P.R. China 
E-mail: fengsq321@126.com </p>

<p>* Contributed equally </p>

<p>Key words: spinal cord injury, proteomics, 14-3-3, APOBEC-2, </p>

<p>myosin regulatory light chain, biomarker </p>

<p>WEI et al: PROTEOMICS OF SCI-INDUCED MUSCLE ATROPHY </p>



<p>followed by matrix assisted laser desorption/ionization-time 
of flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) analysis and 
identified a number of specific proteins that demonstrated 
differential expression levels. It is important to accumulate 
basic data, and the results of the present study may improve 
diagnostic procedures and the design of future strategies to 
treat SIMA. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Animals and treatments. In the present study, female Wistar 
rats (n=30; weight, 220-250 g, age, 8 weeks; Tianjin Medical 
University, Tianjin, China) were used. Rats were single-housed 
in standard plastic cages in a room temperature (24±2˚C), 
relative humidity (50±10%), and light/dark conditions 
(12/12-h light/dark cycle) room with access to food and water 
ad libitum. The study was approved by the ethics committee 
of Tianjin Medical University General Hospital. All proce-
dures in the current study, including the use of experimental 
animals, followed the guidelines of the Animal Care and 
Research Committee of Tianjin Medical University. The rats 
were divided into a sham group and two injury groups (7 and 
14 days post-SCI; n=10/group). The contusion injury models 
were induced by the standard New York University (NYU) 
impactor, as described previously (18). Animals were anes-
thetized (3 ml/kg 10% chloral hydrate, intraperitoneally) and 
laminectomized to expose the T10 spinal cord. A moderate 
injury was generated by dropping a metal rod (10 g, 12.5 mm) 
onto the back side of the spinal cord. The compression force 
and velocity were controlled by a surveillance system to main-
tain uniformity between animals. These rats were manually 
treated with bladder emptying. Sham subjects underwent a 
T10 laminectomy without contusion. Locomotive behavior 
was assessed at 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12 and 14 days following 
injury using Basso, Beattie, and Bresnahan (BBB) score (19) to 
ensure that all subjects exhibited a normal curve of functional 
changes following SCI. 
After 7 and 14 days, rats were euthanized with pentobarbital 
anesthesia (100 mg/kg, intraperitoneally), and then perfused 
with phosphate buffered-saline (PBS). Following perfusion, 
the posterior hind limbs were sliced to retrieve soleus muscle 
samples. Initially, the gastrocnemius muscle was lifted by 
cutting the terminus of the Achilles tendon to expose the 
soleus muscle. The soleus muscle was carefully excised from 
the posterior limbs and all connective tissue was removed to 
reserve muscles. Prior to each operation, the body weight of 
the rats was measured and then the isolated soleus muscle was 
weighed following bilateral harvesting. Following the surgery, 
the ratio of muscle weight to body weight was calculated, then 
muscle samples were frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at 
-80˚C. Control group rats were sacrificed following the same 
protocol at 14 days post-injury. </p>

<p>Histological examination. Samples from each group (n=10) 
were fixed in 10% phosphate-buffered formaldehyde solution. 
Following the process of decalcification and dehydration, the 
muscles were embedded in paraffin, cut into 5-µm sections 
and stained using hematoxylin and eosin. Muscle fibers 
(≥100 in each group) were observed in bright-field using 
Nikon ECLIPSE TS100 light microscope (Tokyo, Japan) </p>

<p>and Nikon D7200 image acquisition system. Their diameters 
were measured using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Image J</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>, Bethesda, MD, USA). </p>

<p>Sample preparation and 2D gel electrophoresis. Muscles 
samples were washed twice with PBS, once with distilled water 
and then ground to a fine powder with a pestle in liquid nitrogen. 
Lysis buffer [8 M urea, 2 M thiourea, 2% (w:v) CHAPS, 1% 
dithiothreitol (DTT), 1 mM phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride 
(PMSF); 0.17 ml], 50 µg/ml DNase I and 1 mM PMSF was 
added to each sample. The samples were lysed by exposure 
to ultrasound for 30 sec (time interval 0.5 sec) repeated four 
times. The lysates were centrifuged at 12,000 x g for 30 min 
at 4˚C to obtain the supernatants. Protein concentration was 
determined using the Bradford method and samples were 
stored at -80˚C. 
For first-dimension isoelectric focusing, pH 3-10 non-linear 
range immobilized pH gradient (IPG) strips (18 cm) were 
rehydrated with solubilized protein samples (800 µg) for 12 h. 
Isoelectric focusing was performed Isoelectric focusing was 
performed using the Protean Ⅱ Xi cell electrophoresis system 
(Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc., Hercules, CA, USA) under 
the following voltage time program: 0-500 V for 1 h, 500 V 
for 5 h, 500-3500 V for 3.5 h, 3500 V for 14 h and finally 
3500-5000 V for 4 h. 
Immediately following focusing, the IPG strips were 
equilibrated for 15 min in equilibration buffer Ⅰ [50 mM 
Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 6 M urea, 30% glycerol, 2% sodium dodecyl 
sulfate (SDS), 2% DTT, 0.02% bromophenol blue], and then 
for 15 min in equilibration buffer Ⅱ (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 
6 M urea, 30% glycerol, 2% SDS, 2.5% iodoacetamide, 0.02% 
bromophenol blue). The second dimension separation was 
performed at 15˚C using a vertical electrophoresis system 
(Multiphor Ⅱ; GE Healthcare Life Sciences , Chalfont, UK) 
with 1-mm 12.5% acrylamide gels run at 20 mA/gel until the 
tracking dye reached the bottom of the gel. The 2D PAGE gel 
was then stained with Coomassie Blue. </p>

<p>Visualization of proteins and image analysis. Following 
electrophoresis, the 2D gels were subjected to staining with 
a solution of 10% ammonium sulfate, 10% phosphoric acid, 
0.12% G250 and 20% methanol overnight. 
The gels were washed with a destaining solution (3% 
glacial acetic acid) in horizontal rotators. Finally, the gels were 
washed with Milli-Q water for 30 min. Images were obtained 
by scanning the 2D gels with a PowerLook 2100XL scanner 
(UMAX Technologies, Inc., Dallas, TX, USA). 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">PDQuest</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v 8.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc.</rs>.) software was 
used to calculate the intensities of protein spots to identify 
differentially expressed proteins. To correct quantitative 
variations in the intensity of protein spots, spot volumes 
were normalized as a percentage of the total volume of all 
the spots present in a gel. Only spots that were consistently 
present in the gels from at least three rats in each group were 
analyzed to avoid spot differences that were due to gel-to-gel 
or biological variation inherent among the rats. The protein 
molecular weight, which ranged from 10 to 100 kDa, and 
the isoelectric point (pI), which ranged from 3 to 10, of each 
protein spot were calculated by the software using the distri-
butions of standard markers and pI positions, respectively. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 14: 165-174, 2016 </p>



<p>Analysis of variance (AVOVA) with Tukey's post-hoc multiple 
comparison tests were performed to analyze statistically 
different intensities among groups. P&lt;0.05 was considered to 
indicate a statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>In-gel tryptic digestion and MALDI-TOF-MS analysis. 
Selected protein spots were excised from the gel and cut 
into ~1 mm 
2 pieces. Samples were destained using 50% 
(vv) acetonitrile (ACN) and 25 mM ammonium bicarbonate 
(100 µl, pH 8.0) for 15 min, this was repeated three times until 
the destaining process was complete. The gel samples were 
dipped into 100% ACN (30 µl, pH 8.0) for 5 min until they 
turned white. They were dried at room temperature and the 
samples were then digested using trypsin (8 µl, 0.005 mg/ml) 
at 37˚C for 16 h. The digested proteins (0.3 µl) coupled with 
0.3 µl matrix were subjected to MALDI-TOF MS analysis 
using a 4700 Proteomics Analyzer (Applied Biosystems; 
Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) to obtain 
the peptide mass fingerprint (PMF) with 4,600 laser intensity. 
The peak list was generated by <rs id="software-2" type="software">GPS Explorer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">v3.5</rs> software 
(Applied Biosystems; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.</rs>.) and 
searched using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Mascot</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 2.1.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Matrix Science Ltd.</rs>., 
London, UK). The PMFs were processed by using the NCBI 
databases (www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov) and the fingerprinting 
method was applied allowing a maximum of one missed 
tryptic cleavage per protein. The protein score confidence 
calculated using the Mascot algorithm. Confidence score 
≥95% and P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate a statistically 
significant difference. </p>

<p>Classification of proteins. Identified proteins were submitted 
to the Protein Analysis Through Evolutionary Relationships 
(PANTHER) classification system (www.pantherdb.org) to 
determine their function via high-throughput analysis (20). 
Proteins were classified according to family and subfamily, 
molecular function, biological process and pathway. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Data are presented as the mean ± standard 
error of the mean. Significant differences were determined by 
ANOVA testing. <rs id="software-4" type="software">SPSS</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 22.0</rs> was used for data 
analysis (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). P&lt;0.05 was consid-
ered to indicate a statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>BBB score in rats post-SCI increased with recovery time. In 
the control group, all rats exhibited a BBB score of 21. In the 
injured groups, immediately following SCI, the motor func-
tion of rats' hind limbs was severely impaired leading to BBB 
scores of ~0. Subsequently, the score gradually increased and 
all injured subjects demonstrated a similar recovery process. 
SCI rats recovered to exhibit BBB scores of ~9 by 7 days 
post-injury. Scores reached 10 after 14 days. Rats in the control 
group exhibited BBB scores of 21 throughout the experiment 
(Fig. 1). </p>

<p>SCI reduces soleus muscle fiber diameter. The mean diam-
eter of the soleus muscle fiber was 94.4±10.8 µm in the 
control group. In the SCI groups, the mean diameters of the 
soleus muscle fiber were 76.7±10.0 µm and 66.2±8.2 µm at </p>

<p>7 and 14 days post-injury, respectively. The diameters in the 
SCI groups were significantly decreased compared with the 
control group (P&lt;0.01). The mean diameter of the soleus 
muscle fiber decreased gradually at different time points 
(Fig. 2). </p>

<p>SCI induced differential protein expression in soleus muscle 
samples. Differentially expressed proteins in the soleus muscle 
of injured and control rats were identified and analyzed using 
2D PAGE and MALDI TOF. Gel images of proteins isolated 
from the muscle of control, 7 and 14 days post-SCI groups 
were compared (Fig. 3). Per gel, &gt;500 protein spots were 
detected. The protein expression profile in the soleus muscle 
of SCI rats indicated that the expression levels of &gt;50 proteins 
were changed compared with the control group. Among 
altered proteins, 23 protein spots exhibited significant changes 
(Table I) and were quantitatively high enough to be identified 
by MALDI-TOF. MS data were analyzed using the Mascot 
search engine. The Mascot search identified 20 spots with high 
confidence (Table II). The confidence score of proteins was 
&gt;95%. 
To investigate the dynamic molecular mechanisms 
involved in SCI, the identified altered proteins were clas-
sified into 9 functional categories using the PANTHER 
database, including biological adhesion, cellular component 
organization or biogenesis, cellular processes, developmental 
processes, immune system processes, localization, metabolic 
processes, multicellular organism processes and response to 
stimulus (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Repeatable injuries are essential for assessing the severity of 
muscle atrophy in SCI animal models in original and repli-
cative studies. The current study used an NYU impactor to 
generate the SCI and verified that SCI animals shared similar 
recovery curves, which were in accordance with the results of 
Basso et al (21). Furthermore, the BBB recovery curves were 
identical for the experimental groups at 14 days post-injury. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Locomotor behavior analysis by BBB score. Following spinal 
cord injury, the BBB score gradually increased. Data points present the 
mean ± standard error of the mean. BBB, Basso, Beattie, and Bresnahan. </p>

<p>WEI et al: PROTEOMICS OF SCI-INDUCED MUSCLE ATROPHY </p>



<p>This indicates that the present study produced a consistent and 
reproducible contusion SCI model. 
Using 2D gels and MALDI-TOF MS analysis, the current 
study identified differentially expressed proteins in soleus 
muscle fibers of control and SCI model rats. In present study, 
it was demonstrated that this method is efficient for the 
identification of multiple proteins, a number of them at low 
abundance. Previous studies investigating muscle atrophy 
typically focus on the disuse and denervated animal models 
to simulate their corresponding clinical phenomenon. SIMA 
is often classified as one of these models of muscle atrophy 
or a combination of these models. However, the pathological 
process of SIMA involves multiple factors, including signal 
transduction, immunization, electrical conduction, stimuli 
and metabolism (22), which results in a complex condition 
that cannot be attributed to one molecular mechanisms or 
a simpler combination of a small number. Thus, the present 
study investigated the pathological changes that occur during </p>

<p>SIMA. Using 2D gels, numerous proteins were identified. 
Certain proteins exhibited a similar expression pattern as 
previously described (23), but others exhibited different 
curves or inconsistent ones (24). The potential importance 
and function of these proteins in SIMA is discussed further 
below. 
The 14-3-3 proteins, as conserved regulatory molecules, 
have been demonstrated to be involved in numerous 
intracellular processes, including cell cycle regulation, 
metabolic control, apoptosis, and the control of gene tran-
scription in almost all eukaryotic cells. Previous research 
demonstrated that 14-3-3 proteins are upregulated in the 
denervated tibialis anterior muscle of rats (25). However, 
other studies have observed that 14-3-3 was not increased 
in the skeletal muscles of patients with chronic obstruc-
tive pulmonary disease, which is a hypoxemic disease 
with similar characteristics to the early changes observed 
in the microenvironment during SCI (26). As a prognostic </p>

<p>Figure 2. The mean diameter of the soleus muscle fiber at different time points following SCI. Hematoxylin and eosin staining (magnification x400) of (A) the 
control group, (B) group 1 (7 days post-SCI) and (C) group 2 (14 days post-SCI). (D) Quantitative analyses were performed to confirm the morphological 
results. Data are presented as the mean ± standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 vs. control group. SCI, spinal cord injury. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Protein profiles of 2D gel electrophoresis. 2D gels representing proteins from (A) the control group, (B) group 1 (7 days post-SCI) and (C) group 2 
(14 days post-SCI). P&lt;0.05, n=3. SCI, spinal cord injury. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 14: 165-174, 2016 </p>



<p>indicator, early accumulation of the 14-3-3 protein in the 
cerebrospinal fluid of patients with acute transverse myelitis 
was perceived to have been associated with little or no 
recovery of neurological function (27). However, deficiencies 
have been noted regarding certain aspects of these previous 
studies. The limited number of subjects (n=4 per group) may 
influence the accuracy of results. Furthermore, a previous 
study (28) observed that 14-3-3 protein was only expressed 
in ~10% of the patients and concluded that 14-3-3 expres-
sion was, thus, not associated with a poor patient outcome. 
Therefore, the present study hypothesizes that 14-3-3 may be 
important for the prediction of recovery from muscle atrophy 
following SCI. Certain studies support this hypothesis. In 
the cerebrospinal fluid of SCI rats, severe injury induced a 
slight reduction in 14-3-3 protein expression compared with 
moderate injury (29). Another study with a contusion model 
demonstrated that the expression levels of three isoforms of 
the 14-3-3 protein family increased at the mid-stage of the 
recovery following the restoration of bladder function (30). 
Despite the possibility that elevated levels of 14-3-3 protein 
following SCI may reflect the process of neuronal damage (31), 
in the central system (32) or peripheral tissues (33), the 
present results demonstrate that 14-3-3 protein, coupled with 
functional recovery, was increased despite an early decrease, </p>

<p>which may be attributed to the slow reaction of the protein. 
Upregulation of 14-3-3 protein expression levels can activate 
downstream reaction of the phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bispho-
sphate 3-kinase-AKT signaling pathway, which may 
suppress apoptosis. An aim of future research will be to 
investigate that underlying mechanism that results in changes 
to 14-3-3 expression levels following SCI. Different severi-
ties of SCI and more time points will be useful to elucidate </p>

<p>Figure 4. Functional classification of identified proteins in the soleus muscle 
of rats with SCI. Pie chart demonstrates functional classifications depending 
on the biological process related to each protein using Protein Analysis 
Through Evolutionary Relationships. </p>

<p>Table I. Identification of differentially expressed proteins by MALDI-TOFMS in rat soleus muscle at different time points 
following SCI. </p>

<p>Fold-change protein expression 
------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
7 days 
14 days 
14 days post-SCI/ 
Protein name 
post-SCI/control 
post-SCI/control 
7 days post-SCI </p>

<p>Myosin regulatory light chain 2 
0.157911 
0.242524 
0.651114 
14-3-3 Protein ε 
2.198649 
1.282510 
1.714334 
Probable C&gt;U-editing enzyme APOBEC-2 
0.742312 
2.545599 
0.291606 
Tropomyosin β chain 
2.230306 
0.752411 
2.964213 
ATP synthase β subunit 
1.201723 
3.443378 
0.348995 
Myosin light chain 
0.247498 
0.156377 
1.582694 
Myosin light chain 3 
0.247498 
0.156377 
1.582694 </p>

<p>α-Actinin-2 </p>

<p>0.253011 
0.070115 
3.608539 
Chain A, crystal structure of the 70-kDa heat 
0.455156 
1.406490 
0.323611 
shock cognate protein 
Heat shock protein β 6 
0 
1.292586 
0 
Serum albumin precursor 
2.528853 
2.490987 
1.015201 
α B-crystallin 
+∞ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 
Troponin T class IIIb β 
+∞ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>+∞ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.326424 </p>

<p>β-Enolase </p>

<p>+∞ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>+∞ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.117352 
Creatine kinase M-type 
+∞ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>+∞ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2.717467 
Fibrinogen β chain precursor 
0.401764 
0.946549 
0.424452 
Fibrinogen α chain 
0.139896 
1.026677 
0.136261 
MMSDH 
0.127811 
0.816477 
0.156540 
Phosphoglycerate kinase 1 
0.081919 
0.458707 
0.178586 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The protein was only expressed post-SCI, thus the ratio between SCI and control is infinite. 
b The protein was not expressed at 14 days post-SCI 
or in the control. SCI, spinal cord injury; APOBEC-2, apolipoprotein B mRNA editing enzyme catalytic polypeptide like 2; MMSDH, aldehyde 
dehydrogenase 6 family member A1. </p>

<p>WEI et al: PROTEOMICS OF SCI-INDUCED MUSCLE ATROPHY </p>



<p>Table II. Identification of differentially expressed proteins by MALDI-TOF MS in rat soleus muscle samples at different time points following SCI. </p>

<p>Accession </p>

<p>Protein </p>

<p>Peptide </p>

<p>Potential participation </p>

<p>SSP </p>

<p>number </p>

<p>name </p>

<p>MWpI </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>count </p>

<p>Score </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>of signaling pathways </p>

<p>1108 </p>

<p>386869343 
Myosin regulatory light chain 2 </p>

<p>18868.394.86 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>100 
Focal adhesion, regulation of actin cytoskeleton </p>

<p>1306 </p>

<p>13928824 
14-3-3 Protein ε </p>

<p>29326.484.63 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>99.39 
Hippo, PI3K-Akt, p53 signaling </p>

<p>1407 </p>

<p>9507245 
14-3-3 Protein ε </p>

<p>28455.984.8 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>100 
Hippo, PI3K-Akt, p53 signaling </p>

<p>2102 </p>

<p>157822795 
Probable C&gt;U-editing enzyme APOBEC-2 </p>

<p>25871.964.75 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>100 
Not annotated </p>

<p>2209 </p>

<p>11875203 </p>

<p>Tropomyosin β </p>

<p>chain </p>

<p>32930.594.66 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>99.95 
Cardiac muscle contraction, adrenergic signaling in cardiomyocytes </p>

<p>2617 </p>

<p>1374715 
ATP synthase β </p>

<p>subunit </p>

<p>51170.654.92 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>100 
Not annotated </p>

<p>3501 </p>

<p>205474 
Myosin light chain </p>

<p>20948.594.99 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>100 
Focal adhesion, regulation of actin cytoskeleton </p>

<p>4108 </p>

<p>6981240 
Myosin light chain 3 </p>

<p>22256.135.03 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>100 
Focal adhesion, regulation of actin cytoskeleton </p>

<p>4406 </p>

<p>157951643 </p>

<p>α-Actinin-2 </p>

<p>104338.545.31 </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>100 
Not annotated </p>

<p>5112 </p>

<p>178847300 
Chain A, crystal structure of the 70-kDa </p>

<p>59894.935.91 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>100 
MAPK signaling pathway, heat shock cognate protein, endocytosis, 
protein processing in endoplasmic reticulum </p>

<p>5310 </p>

<p>20302069 
Heat shock protein β </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>17551.126.05 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>99.97 
Nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism </p>

<p>5406 </p>

<p>158138568 
Serum albumin precursor </p>

<p>70709.866.09 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>100 
Metabolic pathways, endocrine and other factor-regulated calcium 
reabsorption, Ras and Rap1 signaling </p>

<p>5525 </p>

<p>30387800 </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>B-crystallin </p>

<p>20155.446.84 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>100 
Protein processing in endoplasmic reticulum </p>

<p>6517 </p>

<p>207391 
Troponin T class IIIb β </p>

<p>28301.929.36 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>100 
Not annotated </p>

<p>6518 </p>

<p>126723393 </p>

<p>β-Enolase </p>

<p>47326.457.08 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>100 
Not annotated </p>

<p>6520 </p>

<p>6978661 
Creatine kinase M-type </p>

<p>43219.876.58 </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>100 
Not annotated </p>

<p>7303 </p>

<p>158186678 </p>

<p>Fibrinogen β 
chain precursor </p>

<p>54827.927.9 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>100 
Complement and coagulation cascades, platelet activation </p>

<p>1202 </p>

<p>144922622 </p>

<p>Fibrinogen α </p>

<p>chain </p>

<p>60980.867.11 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>100 
Endocytosis, complement and coagulation cascades, platelet 
activation </p>

<p>1205 </p>

<p>400269 </p>

<p>MMSDH </p>

<p>58226.748.47 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>100 
Not annotated </p>

<p>1206 </p>

<p>40254752 
Phosphoglycerate kinase 1 </p>

<p>44909.148.02 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>100 
Glycolysisgluconeogenesis, HIF-1 signaling </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values of MW and pI are from the database. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The sequence of matched peptide with the highest ion score and confidence interval %=100. MALDITOF MS, matrix-assisted laser desorptionionization </p>

<p>time-of-flight mass spectrometry; SCI, spinal cord injury; SSP, significantly expressed spot number; MW, molecular weight; pI, isoelectric point; PI3K, phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate 3-kinase; </p>

<p>Akt, v-akt 
murine thymoma viral oncogene; APOBEC-2, apolipoprotein B mRNA editing enzyme catalytic polypeptide like 2; MAPK, mitogen-activated protein kinase; Ras, rat sarcoma viral oncogene </p>

<p>homolog; Rap1, RAP1A, member of RAS oncogene family; MMSDH, aldehyde dehydrogenase 6 family member A1; HIF-1, hypoxia inducible factor 1. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 14: 165-174, 2016 </p>



<p>the biochemical and pathophysiological function of proteins 
differentially expressed in SIMA. 
αB-crystallin (CryAB) is a small heat shock protein 
involved in preventing protein aggregation (34). Dysfunc-
tion of CryAB may result in skeletal muscle disorders and 
enhancing the function of this protein is accepted as a poten-
tial therapeutic strategy (35). Previous studies indicate that 
CryAB is a protective protein that maintains the capability 
of satellite cells to regenerate skeletal muscle (34) and that 
it is important for muscle homeostasis (36). Denervated tibi-
alis anterior muscle exhibits increased expression of CryAB. 
CryAB can prevent apoptosis induced by a variety of stimuli, 
which may explain why fast-twitch anterior muscle exhibits 
reduced atrophy (25). In the present study, CryAB protein 
expression was upregulated at 7 days post-SCI and then 
reduced to the level as that of the control by day 14. This 
notable finding is contrary to previous research that demon-
strated that denervation decreased the expression levels 
of CryAB in slow muscle, particularly in the soleus (37). 
However, this discrepancy suggests that SIMA, which differs 
from denervation, has the potential for recovery at an early 
stage and that the upregulation of CryAB may be a marker of 
protection. This hypothesis is supported by indirect evidence 
demonstrating that expression of CryAB returned to the 
level observed in the normal controls following successful 
reinnervation (38). Together, the results of the present study 
indicate that, following SCI, there is a transient time window 
for the self-restoration of skeletal muscle, but ultimately 
the positive effect is suppressed by persistent disadvanta-
geous pathogenic factors. Thus, confirming the accurate time 
window and the upregulation of CryAB may be investigated 
as future therapeutic strategies. 
β-enolase is widely distributed in cells and involved 
in the glycolysis pathway (39). Increasing evidence has 
demonstrated that β-enolase may assist DNA transcription, 
replication and repair. Previous studies demonstrated that 
the expression of β-enolase is dependent on regular nerve 
activity (40) and its upregulation indicates regeneration of 
skeletal muscle (41). Research indicates that the expression 
of β-enolase following denervation remains at a low level 
in slow-twitch muscle, however, continues to decrease in 
the fast-twitch muscle (40,42). However, the present study 
demonstrated that the expression levels of β-enolase in 
SCI muscle increased steadily, which indicates that SIMA 
has the reverse effect on this protein. Previous evidence 
suggested that following reinnervation, the expression level 
of β-enolase in soleus muscle increased, which may support 
the hypothesis that the increase of β-enolase expression in 
the soleus muscle depends on the integrity of peripheral 
nerves. However, the functional recovery of SCI is limited 
and muscle atrophy is inevitable. In sum, the present study 
hypothesized that the role of β-enolase is altering the muscle 
types, as demonstrated in a previous study (43) that supports 
the current observations. In addition, a longer period of 
observation is required in future research. 
The bio-functions of apolipoprotein B mRNA editing 
enzyme catalytic polypeptide like 2 (APOBEC2) have been 
hypothesized to include mediation of the cytidine-to-uridine 
transcriptional editing of mRNA (44). Due to exclusive 
expression in skeletal and cardiac muscles, APOBEC2 was </p>

<p>suggested to be important in the physiological function of 
intramuscular development. However, APOBEC2 knockout 
mice did not exhibit a change in phenotype (45). This may 
indicate that APOBEC2 subtly regulates certain aspects of 
muscle function, including the response to damage stimuli. 
The results of the present study demonstrated that the protein 
expression levels of APOBEC2 in the soleus increased gradu-
ally following SCI, in contrast to the change in expression 
levels during denervation atrophy (24). This finding may be 
attributed to intact neurons that give priority to compensation 
of muscle function by switching the muscle types. A previous 
study demonstrated that APOBEC2-deficient mice exhibited a 
marked shift in muscle fiber type, from fast to slow (46). It is 
hypothesized that the increase of APOBEC2 expression levels 
may result in enhanced conversion of slow fibers to fast ones. 
Further evidence indicates that the ratio of slow to fast fibers in 
soleus muscle was decreased gradually following spinal cord 
transection (47). 
α-actinin-2 is a major Z-disk component, which is crucial 
for the crosslinking of actin and titin filaments (48,49). It is 
understood that α-actinin-2 is expressed in all types of muscle 
fibers, including slow and fast fibers (50). Previous studies 
demonstrated that α-actinin-2 can bond with calsarcin-2, a 
key inhibitor of calcineurin activation, to release calcineurin 
from calsarcin-2 and change the fast fibers to a slow pheno-
type (51-53). The present study demonstrated that following 
SCI, the expression of α-actinin-2 in the soleus dropped 
sharply over time. This decrease indicates that downregulation 
of α-actinin-2 may result in enhancement of calsarcin-2, which 
inhibits the activation of calcineurin signaling, and a shift in 
fiber type from slow to fast. The results of the current study are 
consistent with previous research and it is hypothesized that 
the shift of metabolic phenotype of muscle fibers following 
SCI preserves the energy metabolism and function of the 
muscle. 
Heat shock protein family A member 4 (Hsp70) is a highly 
conserved molecular chaperone protein that has been reported 
to regulate various processes associated with stress, damage 
or degeneration (54). The protective effects of Hsp70 in muscle 
atrophy have also been demonstrated in a number of previous 
studies (55-57). Upregulation of Hsp70 may prevent muscle 
atrophy as a result of denervation, aging or disuse (58-60). 
The present study observed that the expression of Hsp70 in the 
soleus muscle was slightly reduced at 7 days post-SCI and then 
increased sharply at 14 days to a level markedly higher than 
that of the control. This indicates that the muscle exhibited 
the potential for restoration following central nervous system 
injury. The slight reduction observed at the early stage of SCI 
may be attributed to a temporary disorder of energy metabo-
lism (61) or inhibition of glucocorticoid due to the stress 
response (62). However, it remains necessary to investigate 
why the protective effect of Hsp70 is too limited to prevent 
atrophy and whether the increased expression of this protein is 
also a transient phenomenon. 
Another notable finding from the present study is that the 
protein levels of certain myosin regulatory light chain (MLC) 
isoforms and enzymes involved in cellular and metabolic 
processes were decreased in the soleus muscle at early stages 
(7 days) post-SCI. Subsequently, the expression was increased 
at 14 days post-SCI, with certain isoforms almost at similar </p>

<p>WEI et al: PROTEOMICS OF SCI-INDUCED MUSCLE ATROPHY </p>



<p>levels to the control. The function of MLCs is associated with 
contractile force and velocity in muscle fibers (63). Multiple 
reports have demonstrated that the changes to MLCs were 
associated with fiber-type shift (8,64-66). Certain enzymes key 
in cellular and metabolic processes, including fibrinogen α and 
β chain, aldehyde dehydrogenase 6 family member A1 and 
phosphoglycerate kinase 1, participate in various biological 
processes and their normal function is for homeostasis of 
physiological and pathological metabolism (67-69). Fluctua-
tions in the expression levels of these proteins may indicate 
that skeletal muscle has been damaged by central nervous 
system injury, but with relatively integrated peripheral nervous 
control, will exhibit reduced function of multiple molecular 
processes at an early stage and subsequently adapt during the 
middle stage. The results of the current study are in accordance 
with a previous study that demonstrated that muscle appears to 
have plasticity and can adapt following moderate spinal cord 
contusion, which was similar to the present animal model (70). 
The data of the current study indicated that SCI-induced 
atrophic muscles exhibited limited molecular improvements, 
which may be associated with functional recovery. However 
these improvements cannot reverse the changes to the 
size of muscle fibers of the soleus muscles of SCI rats. It is 
accepted that following moderate contusion, rats will exhibit 
spontaneous recovery of motor function following a fixed 
pattern (71,72). Furthermore, previous findings indicated that 
the growth effects of muscle fibers may result in improvement 
of motor function (73-75), however, this does not mean that 
the size of the fibers is directly associated with BBB score. 
Notably, the results of the present study demonstrated that the 
extent of variation in the second week was reduced compared 
with the change in the first week, which may be attributed to 
the temporary molecular compensatory mechanisms. These 
mechanisms may be used as therapeutic targets to induce 
anti-atrophic effects or reverse the effects on skeletal muscle, 
potentially coupled with more observable improvement of 
motor function (34,62). However, in the current study, due 
to specific molecular improvements, the process of muscle 
atrophy slowed at a later stage, however, it may not be able 
to be stopped or reversed. In addition, the increases to 
BBB scores also slowed down at this stage. Concerning the 
delayed effects of molecules prior to phenotypic changes, it is 
concluded that the decreased extent of atrophic response was 
consistent with the sharp increase to motor function recovery 
at the early stage. Future studies are required to investigate 
prolonged observation over increased time points. 
In conclusion, the current study used a proteomics 
approach to identify differential expression of proteins in 
the soleus muscle at different time points following SCI. 
The identified proteins were associated with biological adhe-
sion, cellular processes, developmental processes, immune 
system processes, localization and metabolic processes. The 
results of the present study demonstrated that SIMA has 
characteristics different to disuse and denervated atrophy, 
or a combination of them. The present study may improve 
the understanding of the association between central nervous 
system injury and skeletal muscle atrophy. Furthermore, the 
results may provide insight into potential mechanisms or 
cellular pathways that may be adopted as biomarkers and 
targets for the treatment of SIMA. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was supported by the State Program of the National 
Natural Science Foundation of China (grant nos. 81330042 
and 81371957); the Special Program for Sino-Russian Joint 
Research Sponsored by the Ministry of Science and Technology, 
China (grant no. 2014DFR31210); the Key Program Sponsored 
by the Tianjin Science and Technology Committee, China 
(grant no/ 13RCGFSY19000); and the Program for Research 
Sponsored by the Health Authority of Binhai New Area of 
Tianjin, China (grant no. 2012BWKY028). </p>



<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 14: 165-174, 2016 </p>





<p>WEI et al: PROTEOMICS OF SCI-INDUCED MUSCLE ATROPHY </p>





</text></tei>