<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4787772" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Two-step PCR procedures are an efficient and well 
established way to generate amplicon libraries for 
NGS sequencing. However, there is a high risk 
of cross-contamination by carry-over of amplicons 
from first to second amplification rounds, potentially 
leading to severe misinterpretation of results. Here 
we describe a new method able to prevent and/or 
to identify carry-over contaminations by introduc-
ing the K-box, a series of three synergistically act-
ing short sequence elements. Our K-boxes are com-
posed of (i) K1 sequences for suppression of contam-
inations, (ii) K2 sequences for detection of possible 
residual contaminations and (iii) S sequences acting 
as separators to avoid amplification bias. In order 
to demonstrate the effectiveness of our method we 
analyzed two-step PCR NGS libraries derived from 
a multiplex PCR system for detection of T-cell re-
ceptor beta gene rearrangements. We used this sys-
tem since it is of high clinical relevance and may 
be affected by very low amounts of contaminations. 
Spike-in contaminations are effectively blocked by 
the K-box even at high rates as demonstrated by 
ultra-deep sequencing of the amplicons. Thus, we 
recommend implementation of the K-box in two-step 
PCR-based NGS systems for research and diagnos-
tic applications demanding high sensitivity and ac-
curacy. </p>

<p>Two-step polymerase chain reaction (PCR) strategies are a 
convenient approach to generate amplicon libraries suitable 
for next generation sequencing (NGS) (Figure 1). For this 
purpose, in the first amplification reaction the target nucleic 
acid sequence is amplified using specific primers flanked by </p>

<p>a tail sequence (e.g. a M13 or T7 tail). In the second ampli-
fication reaction, adaptor sequences required for NGS are 
introduced utilizing primers complementary at their 3 end 
to the tail sequence of the first amplification primers (1). In 
order to make this method more cost-efficient, multiplexing 
of several samples for NGS can be performed. To this end 
so-called barcodes are introduced within or close to the 5 
end of the second amplification primers (1). 
However, this highly efficient two-step amplification 
strategy harbors a considerable risk of cross-contamination 
during set-up of the second PCR especially by carry-over of 
amplicons from the first PCR to the second PCR due to the 
high number of amplicons generated in the first amplifica-
tion reaction (2,3). The risk of contamination is even higher 
if resulting PCR products are isolated by gel extraction or 
PCR purification kits. Furthermore, PCR products of a sec-
ond amplification may contaminate other second amplifi-
cation reactions. Other mistakes might occur by pipetting 
a first-step amplicon inadvertently into the wrong second 
PCR mix, which can be regarded as a 100% contamination. 
There are many applications which rely on two-step PCR 
strategies for NGS library generation (4-8). Here we fo-
cus on the analysis of genomic T-cell receptor beta (TCR␤) 
gene rearrangements since this application is very suitable 
to demonstrate the importance of contamination protection 
due to the inherent risk of detecting extremely low rates of 
contaminations and due to the clinical importance of de-
tecting very rare events. 
T-cells play a central role in cell-mediated immunity with 
95% of T-cells expressing T-cell receptors (TCR) consist-
ing of an alpha and beta chain as a heterodimer on their 
surfaces (9). TCR␤ chains are highly diverse and can be 
regarded as genomic fingerprint of each T-cell (10,11) The 
high diversity of the human T-cell repertoire is mainly gen-
erated by somatic recombination among the Variable (V), 
Diversity (D) and Joining (J) TCR␤ gene segments and 
the addition of random non-templated bases at recombi-
nation junctions (12). The hypervariable complementarity-
determining region 3 (CDR3) of the rearranged TCR␤ rec-</p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +49 30 8445 2734; Fax: +49 30 450 536106; Email: volkhard.seitz@charite.de 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Prof. Dr. Michael Hummel. Tel: +49 30 8445 2734; Fax: +49 30 450 536106; Email: michael.hummel@charite.de 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Dr. Steffen Hennig. Tel: +49 30 79786111/110; Fax: +49 30 79781731; Email: hennig@hsdiagnomics.de </p>

<p>C The Author(s) 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>e135 Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 20 </p>

<p>PAGE 2 OF 9 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Scheme of a standard two-step PCR approach. In a two-step PCR strategy (A) a PCR product is at first generated using specific primers flanked 
by a tail sequence and is then further amplified in the second reaction with primers that target only the tail sequence (blue color) introduced by the first 
amplification primers. Therefore, in the second amplification (B) contaminations from other first or second PCRs may be co-amplified. The barcodes (BC) 
allow barcoding for NGS multiplexing but cannot suppress cross-contaminations. </p>

<p>ognizes antigens bound to major histocompatibility com-
plex molecules (10). Therefore, the determination of T-cell 
repertoires are of interest for a wide range of research and 
clinical applications, e.g. (i) detection of T-cell clonality, (ii) 
minimal residual disease analysis in T-cell lymphoma pa-
tients, (iii) TCR␤ signatures as biomarkers in clinical vac-
cination studies or (iv) identification of common 'public 
TCRs' in autoimmune disease as therapeutic targets. 
Here we describe a novel contamination protection 
method for two-step PCRs ideally suited for NGS library 
preparations. By utilizing a synergistic combination of se-
quence elements denoted as K-box, this new method oper-
ates through both prevention of contaminations and iden-
tification of possible residual contaminations. Our method 
shows effective suppression of even high rates of artificial 
contaminations. Hence we recommend implementation of 
the K-box as an additional feature in two-step PCR-based 
NGS procedures for research and diagnostic applications, 
where high sensitivity and reliability is mandatory. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The K-box architecture </p>

<p>We developed a comprehensive method in order to handle 
inherent contamination problems in two-step PCR-based 
NGS library preparations. This new method is based on 
three synergistically acting sequence elements referred to 
as K-box. As outlined in Figure 2, the first amplification </p>

<p>primers comprise all three elements (k1, k2 and s in the 
forward primer and k1 , k2 and s in the reverse primer), 
whereas the forward and reverse primers of the second am-
plification contain only k1 and k1 , respectively. With the 
three K-box elements one single K-box is designed by bioin-
formatics methods and optimized not to form hybrids that 
might lead to mispriming under a multiplex experimental 
setup. 
The rationale behind the introduction of K1 elements is 
the prevention of carry-over contaminations from previous 
amplification reactions. As outlined in Figure 2 only match-
ing K1 sequences in the primers of the first and second PCR 
allow amplification of the respective PCR product. Since 
K1 sequences are individual for each sample, the amplifica-
tion of PCR cross-contaminations is suppressed in the sec-
ond PCR in case of non-concordant K1 elements. 
In our TCR␤ multiplex analyses K1 sequences comprise 
exemplary 7 nucleotides (see Table 1). The K1 elements are 
designed by a minimization procedure which selects the K1 
elements by (i) minimal global similarity to any other K1-
element, and (ii) a strong dissimilarity rule at the specific 
3 ends of the K1 elements. The resulting K-box sequences 
have a very low potential for hybrid formation. 
A further K-box element is the K2 sequence present only 
in the first amplification primers. While K1 elements lead to 
suppression of contaminations, the K2 elements serve to de-
tect possible remaining contaminations from previous am-
plification reactions. In our TCR␤ multiplex analyses we de-</p>

<p>PAGE 3 OF 9 </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 20 e135 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Scheme of the K-box method in two-step PCR. In the K-box method (A), three additional sequence elements (K1-, K2-and S-elements) are 
introduced by the first amplification primers. The combination of k1 and k1 (K1 elements) differ from sample to sample but are identical (matched) within 
a specific first and second amplification primer set. (B) A second amplification can only occur with matched K1 elements and therefore the amplification of 
contaminations from other first or second amplifications is suppressed. In Figure 2 mismatched K1 elements are indicated by different colors and marked 
by two flash symbols. The combination of k2 and k2`(K2 elements) serves as a bioinformatics indicator. Sequences in the PCR mix with unexpected 
K2 elements are identified as residual contaminations. Furthermore, s and s (S elements) are designed as mismatch with the template i.e. the respective 
genomic TCR␤ V-and J-segments. The S elements effectively separate the template matching part of the primers from their 5 -tail thereby reducing the 
risk of PCR bias. </p>

<p>Table 1. Sequences of k-and k -box elements for set 1-9 used for the two-
step PCR NGS library preparations </p>

<p>The sequences are listed in 5 -3 orientation as present in the forward and 
reverse primers. The three distinct k-boxes used in the forward primers are 
marked with green, yellow and red colors and the purple, blue and gray 
colors mark the three different k -boxes employed in the reverse primers. 
By using all possible k/k combinations of the 3 k-and 3 k -boxes 9 sets 
were generated. </p>

<p>signed K2 elements exemplarily with three sample-specific 
nucleotides (see Table 1). 
For a better understanding of first and second PCR 
primer matching we introduce here the term 'set' which de-
fines a unique k/k combination. Within an individual set 
a specific second primer pair is designed to work only to-
gether with a specific first primer pair. </p>

<p>Table 1 gives an example of 9 sets with K1 and K2 se-
quences used in the TCR␤ multiplex analyses. The 9 pos-
sible set combinations are formed by 3 distinct k-and k -
boxes in the forward and reverse primers. Basically with 10 
distinct k-and k -boxes 100 unique k/k sets can be gener-
ated. Therefore, with a linear increase in the effort of primer 
synthesis an exponential growth in the number of distinct 
sets is achieved. This makes this approach up-scalable with 
reasonable efforts. 
In principle, K1 and K2 elements can be of any con-
venient length. We typically use a length of 7 nucleotides 
for K1 and 3 nucleotides for K2 elements. Since the se-
quences of K1 and K2 elements are variable in a sample spe-
cific manner, certain variations may coincidentally match in 
their last nucleotides on the 3-end with the sequence of the 
target DNA next to the template. In that case the template 
hybridizing part of the first amplification primers would be 
elongated, possibly leading to higher annealing tempera-
tures and PCR bias. To circumvent this problem separator 
sequences (S elements) are introduced into the first ampli-
fication primers (Figure 2). They are designed as mismatch 
with the template i.e. the respective genomic TCR␤ V-and 
J-segments. The S elements effectively separate the template 
matching part of the primers from their 5 -tail thereby re-
ducing the risk of PCR bias. </p>

<p>e135 Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 20 </p>

<p>PAGE 4 OF 9 </p>

<p>It should be noted that every multiplex PCR assay needs 
a proper design for S elements, whereas the same K1 se-
quences and the respective second amplification primers 
can be used for different multiplex applications. Barcodes 
are introduced into the second amplification primers to al-
low multiplex sequencing of NGS libraries. Table 2 summa-
rizes the functions of the different K-box elements and the 
terminology used throughout the manuscript. </p>

<p>Design and description of target DNA samples </p>

<p>The K-box method was established in two-step PCR-based 
NGS library preparations with three different types of tem-
plates: </p>

<p>(1) Genomic DNA (gDNA) from the T-cell line Peer. PCRs 
were performed with a primer pair specific for the V-
and J-segments of the Peer TCR␤ gene rearrangement 
(Supplementary Figure S1). 
(2) Tonsillar gDNA which harbors a physiologically 
broad range of different TCR␤ gene rearrangements. 
TCR␤ multiplex PCRs were performed (Supplemen-
tary Methods). 
(3) A synthetic template with 616 TCR␤ V-J-combinations 
(Supplementary Figure S3). TCR␤ multiplex PCRs 
were performed (Supplementary Methods). </p>

<p>Determination of parameters for effective suppression of 
carry-over contamination </p>

<p>In order to optimize the sets of K-boxes for practical use in 
a laboratory, systematic variations of different parameters 
were tested with respect to their effects on contamination 
suppression. 
In standardized experiments 100 ng genomic DNA of the 
T-cell line Peer was used as template in the first amplifica-
tion reaction employing only primers specific for the Peer 
TCR␤ rearrangement. The product of this first PCR round 
was used as template for the second amplification. The PCR 
conditions are given as Supplementary Methods. With this 
two-step PCR workflow both matching and mismatching 
K1 elements were tested. Supplementary Table S1 illustrates 
the sequences of the 4 primer sets with matching K1 ele-
ments (sets A-D). Each set is characterized by a unique k/k 
combination. Supplementary Tables S4 and S6 explain the 
experimental set-up using primers with matching and mis-
matching K1 elements. Mismatching alterations of one and 
two base pairs (bp) were carried out and their gradual ef-
fects on contamination suppression were determined. 
Proofreading polymerases exhibit 3 -5 exonuclease activ-
ity and may remove K1 elements at the 3 -end of the second 
amplification primer. We examined therefore the protective 
effect of phosphorothioate (PT) bonds introduced at (i) the 
first, (ii) the first and second and at (iii) the first, second and 
third position from the 3 end of the second amplification 
primers (Supplementary Table S4). For comparison we per-
formed the second amplification with a non-proofreading 
polymerase and second amplification primers without PT-
bonds (Supplementary Table S6). 
PCR products were analyzed on 6% acrylamide gels and 
Tif images were generated with the Biorad Geldoc 2000 </p>

<p>(München, Germany) using default settings. PCR bands 
were quantified with the <rs id="software-0" type="software">FusionCapt Advance</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Vilber Lourmat</rs>, Eberhardzell, Germany). The mean and 
standard deviation of replicated experiments were deter-
mined to obtain statistically reliable results. 
The degree of contamination suppression was deter-
mined by quantifying the visible product of the second 
PCR. Complete contamination suppression was assumed 
when the second amplification yielded no visible PCR prod-
uct. </p>

<p>Testing of contamination protection by the K-box in multiplex 
two-step PCR analyses </p>

<p>To test the effectiveness of the K-box method in a multi-
plex TCR␤ analysis we first used two different experimen-
tal set-ups: (i) runs with matching K1 elements and (ii) runs 
with mismatching K1 elements simulating e.g. pipetting er-
rors. We used 400 ng tonsillar DNA as template to allow the 
amplification of high numbers of different TCR␤ gene rear-
rangements. The two-step PCR protocol employed is given 
as Supplementary Methods. PCR results were analyzed by 
gel electrophoresis. In the experiments with matching K1 
elements the 9 primer sets depicted in Table 1 were used. 
In line with the K-box principle these 9 sets were charac-
terized by unique k/k combinations between the sets and 
concordant k/k combinations within a set. The same two-
step PCR workflow was used also in a total of 15 experi-
ments with mismatching K1 elements simulating pipetting 
mistakes (Supplementary Table S2). To this end the first am-
plification product of a given set (e.g. set 1) was used as tem-
plate for amplification with second amplification primers 
from another (not matching) set (e.g. set 2). Such a simu-
lation of sample confusion can be regarded as 100% con-
tamination in the second PCR mix. 
Next, we applied NGS to evaluate the K-box method. We 
used again the 9 TCR␤ multiplex primer sets depicted in 
Table 1 and a synthetic template. Generation of the syn-
thetic template is illustrated in the Supplementary Meth-
ods in Figure S3. This synthetic template covered all TCR␤ 
V-J combinations (N = 616) relevant for binding of the 
44 V-and 14 J-segment specific TCR␤ primers. Using the 
aforementioned 9 primer sets (Table 1) 18 PCR assays were 
performed, 9 of which without and 9 assays with spike-in 
contaminations (see Supplementary Table S3 and Table 3). 
Spike-in contaminations are here defined as first amplifica-
tion products with not matching K-boxes to the second am-
plification primers employed. For example, a mix of eight 
first amplification products amplified with set 1-8 primers 
are spike-in contaminations if the second amplification is 
performed with set 9 primers. If the amplification of the 
spike-in contaminations is not completely suppressed by the 
K1 mismatches, residual contaminations can be detected by 
the unique k2/k2 combinations. The 9 assays with spike-in 
contaminations were assembled as follows: 60% represented 
the PCR product of the first amplification with matching 
K-box combination whereas the remaining 40% were de-
rived from the PCR products of the other 8 first amplifi-
cations (5% each) with mismatching K-box combinations 
(Supplementary Table S3). This first amplification mixture 
was diluted 1:100 and the second amplification assay was </p>

<p>PAGE 5 OF 9 </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 20 e135 </p>

<p>Table 2. Description of the K-box sequence elements </p>

<p>Abbreviation 
Description </p>

<p>K-box 
Comprises the sequence elements k1/k1 , k2/k2 , s/s . 
k-box 
K-box of the forward first and second amplification primers. 
k -box 
K-box of the reverse first and second amplification primers. 
k1/k1 (K1 elements) 
K-box elements of the first and second amplification primers for suppression of contaminations. 
k2/k2 (K2 elements) 
K-box elements of the first amplification primers. Their main purpose is the detection of 
contaminations in subsequent bioinformatics steps (NGS data analysis) 
s/s (S elements) 
S-elements are designed as mismatch with the template i.e. the respective genomic TCR␤ V-and 
J-segments. The S elements effectively separate the template matching part of the primers from their 
5 -tail thereby reducing the risk of PCR bias. </p>

<p>The typical lengths of K1, K2 and S-elements as used in our TCR␤ multiplex analyses are 7, 3 and 2 nucleotides, respectively. </p>

<p>processed as described in the Supplementary Methods. Spin 
column-purified PCR products were sequenced with MiSeq 
(Illumina, San Diego, USA) in paired-end mode (2 × 150 
bp). For multiplexing standard TruSeq barcodes and MiSeq 
sequencing default conditions were employed allowing 1 
mismatch in the barcode. </p>

<p>Bioinformatics analysis </p>

<p>Resulting reads were clustered and classified with respect to 
the K-box elements by employing a tailored algorithm: in 
step 1, reads delivered by the Illumina sequencer in paired-
end mode, were joined by an in-house developed optimal 
assembly procedure, which uses the phred-like quality val-
ues per base to deliver a proper consensus sequence per each 
read pair. The resulting joined read is (i) of higher quality 
than each of the single reads alone and (ii) is able to de-
liver effective read-length of &gt; 500 bp, if a current 2×300 bp 
MiSeq run is used (Supplementary Methods). These joined 
reads were used in step 2 to find the respective K-box ele-
ments by sequence comparison. 
In the following we used sequence analysis to quantify 
the rate of contamination suppression by determining the 
amount of contamination carried over between different 
sets. The principles to analyze the experiment outlined in 
Supplementary Table S3 are given below: </p>

<p>r The k2/k2 elements are identified in each read pair as </p>

<p>part of the respective K-box (V and J side). </p>

<p>r Since the correct k2/k2 elements are known, as well as </p>

<p>the potentially contaminating k2/k2 elements generated 
by spike-ins (see above), we are able to precisely deter-
mine the respective rates. </p>

<p>r In each experiment one set is given as correct, i.e. there </p>

<p>is one defined 'correct' k2 element on V and one correct 
k2 on J side. Other sets which are studied in parallel and 
which are also used as spike-in contaminations can be 
uniquely identified by their different K2 elements. The 
respective matches are counted and flagged as 'contami-
nated'. </p>

<p>r However, in addition to the methodologically introduced </p>

<p>K2 elements there are so-called random K2 elements, 
which can be caused e.g. by sequencing artifacts. These 
random K2 elements can be simply all possible triplets 
(61 on the V and 61 on the J side) except the 2×3 K2 el-
ements on the V or J side used in the 9 sets (see Table 1). 
The respective matches are counted and flagged as 'ran-
dom'. </p>

<p>r The random K2 elements are complicating the analysis. </p>

<p>To obtain a clear-cut read out for each of the experiments 
described in Supplementary Table S3, we measured the 
events with simultaneous occurrence of the 2 contami-
nating k2 elements on the V side and 2 contaminating 
k2 elements on the J side. This robust approach detects 
in each experiment 6 of the 8 spike-in contaminations. </p>

<p>r Furthermore, we united all reads containing random K2 </p>

<p>elements on the V and/or the J side and compared the 
rates in the experiments with and without spike-in con-
taminations by a standard two-sided t-test. The aim was 
to determine if the random error is equally distributed in 
both groups. </p>

<p>Comparison of the respective rates will allow a precise 
measurement of how efficient the K-boxes are in suppress-
ing carry-over contaminations. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Determination of parameters for effective suppression of 
carry-over contamination </p>

<p>In order to determine the factors needed for effective sup-
pression of carry-over contamination in two-step PCR 
analyses we analyzed (i) the impact of the number of base 
pairs of K1 mismatches and (ii) the effect of PT-bonds at the 
3 -end of second amplification primers using a proofreading 
polymerase. For this purpose we used DNA of the T-cell line 
Peer as a template and amplified in a non-multiplex setting 
specifically the Peer TCR␤ gene rearrangement (Supple-
mentary Figure S1). As visualized in Figure 3 the absence 
of K1 mismatches led--as expected--to strong amplifica-
tion products after second amplification (Lane 1) whereas a 
K1 mismatch of 1 bp was able to strongly reduce the PCR 
product intensity (Lanes 2 and 3). K1 mismatches of 2 bp 
(Lane 4) were sufficient to suppress the contaminating sec-
ond amplification products almost completely. As another 
important factor an increasing number of PT-bonds at the 
3 -end of second amplification primers resulted in improved 
contamination suppression (Figure 4). Details are given as 
Supplementary Table S4). 
Consequently, conditions for effective carry-over con-
tamination suppression should comprise k1/k1 mis-
matches of more than 2 nucleotides and the use of at least 2 
PT-bonds at the 3 -end of second amplification primers. 
For comparison to the experiments using a proofread-
ing polymerase and primers with PT-bonds in the sec-</p>

<p>e135 Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 20 </p>



<p>Table 3. 18 experiments were performed with or without spike-in contaminations as outlined in Supplementary Table S3 </p>

<p>Experiment 
number 
Set-ID </p>

<p>Spike-in 
contamination </p>

<p>Number of read 
pairs 
Correct reads (%) </p>

<p>Contamination 
reads (%) 
Random reads (%) </p>

<p>1 
set1 
No 
467378 
97,5 
0 
2,5 
2 
set2 
No 
514960 
98,4 
0 
1,6 
3 
set3 
No 
415902 
98,0 
0 
2,0 
4 
set4 
No 
447288 
98,0 
0 
1,9 
5 
set5 
No 
454124 
98,1 
0 
1,9 
6 
set6 
No 
415391 
98,0 
0 
1,9 
7 
set7 
No 
491452 
97,9 
0 
2,1 
8 
set8 
No 
540915 
98,2 
0 
1,8 
9 
set9 
No 
455199 
98,0 
0 
2,0 
10 
set1 
40% 
481099 
97,9 
0 
2,1 
11 
set2 
40% 
486962 
98,4 
0 
1,5 
12 
set3 
40% 
446743 
98,0 
0 
2,0 
13 
set4 
40% 
460226 
97,9 
0 
2,0 
14 
set5 
40% 
480041 
98,1 
0 
1,9 
15 
set6 
40% 
464568 
97,9 
0 
2,0 
16 
set7 
40% 
527910 
97,7 
0 
2,2 
17 
set8 
40% 
434073 
98,0 
0 
2,0 
18 
set9 
40% 
431367 
97,9 
0 
2,1 </p>

<p>The percentages of correct reads and of contaminations were determined according to the respective K2 sequences employed. A contamination rate of 0% 
indicates that no contaminating read was detectable. Furthermore, the percentage of random reads with unexpected K2-elements occurring stochastically 
on V/J-side is given. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effect of base pair length of K1 mismatches on contamination 
suppression. Gel electrophoresis results (Ethidium bromide staining) of 
two-step PCR demonstrate a positive correlation between length of K1 
mismatches and contamination suppression. Whilst under K1 matching 
conditions (0 bp) the expected prominent readout is achieved (Lane 1), K1 
mismatches of only 1 bp have already pronounced negative effects on the 
second amplification (Lanes 2 and 3). A K1 mismatch of 2 bp prevents 
almost completely the second amplification (Lane 4). In this experiment 
3 PT-bonds were used at the 3 end of the second amplification primers. 
PCR products of the first amplification were defined as 100% contamina-
tion and were used as template for the second amplification. The size of 
the gel ladder is given in base pairs. </p>

<p>ond amplification we performed experiments with a non-
proofreading polymerase in the second amplification and 
primers without PT-bonds. In both settings the k-box and 
k -box contamination suppression increases with an in-
creasing number of K1 mismatches. However, contamina-
tion suppression is less effective if non-proofreading poly-
merases are used (Supplementary Tables S5 and S7). A fur-
ther advantage of proofreading polymerases is their less 
error-prone DNA-synthesis. </p>

<p>Testing of contamination protection by the K-box in multiplex 
two-step PCR analyses </p>

<p>To test the impact of the K-box method for contamina-
tion protection in a multiplex TCR␤ analysis we utilized 
in a first experiment 9 primer sets in 9 match and 15 mis-
match settings. In these experiments tonsillar DNA was </p>

<p>used as a template. The length of K1 mismatches in the 
mismatch settings was 4-5 base pairs (Supplementary Table 
S2). As shown in Figure 5 and Supplementary Figure S4 
the matched settings led to the production of the expected 
PCR products. On the other hand the K1 mismatch settings 
between first and second amplification primers completely 
suppressed the amplification during the second PCR. 
In order to demonstrate the effectiveness of contamina-
tion protection by a highly sensitive NGS we investigated 
the 9 primer sets in 9 match settings and in 9 assays with 
matching sets plus spike-in contaminations (Supplementary 
Table S3). For these experiments an artificial template was 
used (Supplementary Figure S3). 
In total, 18 NGS libraries were prepared, which were 
tagged by standard Illumina barcodes. The libraries were 
sequenced on <rs type="software">Illumina</rs> MiSeq and demultiplexed by Illu-
mina software (default parameters). For 8.52 % of the reads 
the barcode could not be identified unambiguously. These 
reads were excluded from further analysis. Another qual-
ity filtering step was imposed by our read-joining algorithm 
which requires that both reads of each read pair exhibit sig-
nificant overlaps. 94.8% ± 1.81% of all read pairs could by 
joined successfully to one consensus sequence. Finally, the 
joined reads were classified and filtered again for occurrence 
of possible k1/k1 -boxes, which was the case for 90.6% ± 
2.4%. In the end, compared to the original raw read num-
bers, on average 83.5% ± 2.2% of reads were used for the 
data analysis, which was equivalent to around 8.5 million 
read pairs. 
Our observations are summarized in the following and in 
Table 3: </p>

<p>r Most importantly, evaluation of NGS results revealed </p>

<p>complete suppression of spike-in contaminations. </p>

<p>r We compared the percentages of random reads in the </p>

<p>runs without spike-ins to the ones with 40% effective con-
tamination by a standard two-sided t-test. The resulting </p>

<p>PAGE 7 OF 9 </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 20 e135 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Impact of K1 mismatch length and number of PT-bonds in the second amplification primer on contamination suppression. The base pair length 
of K1 mismatch sequences and the number of PT-bonds was varied in two-step PCR assays. The quantity of PCR products from the second PCR are 
shown as volume percent (Vol. %) which were determined as outlined in Supplementary Figure S2 and the results were statistically analyzed as shown in 
Supplementary Table S5. The base pair length of K1 mismatches and the number of PT-bonds positively correlate with suppression of contaminations. 
The mean for the NTCs (N = 16) and background (N = 16) measurements was 9.9 ± 1.9 Vol. % and 9.4 ± 2.3 Vol. % respectively. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Testing of contamination protection by the K-box in two-step 
PCR TCR␤ analyses. Results analyzed by gel electrophoresis (Ethidium 
bromide staining) for 3 match settings, 5 mismatch settings and 3 NTCs are 
shown. In the match setting the expected TCR␤ amplification product was 
observed whereas in the mismatch settings amplification was completely 
suppressed. The experimental setup for the PCR reactions 1-11 is given in 
Supplementary Table S2. The size of the gel ladder is given in base pairs. </p>

<p>P-value is not significant (P = 0.8) which means that the 
random errors occurred at equal rates in both groups. </p>

<p>r The design of our primer sets with integrated K-boxes </p>

<p>leads to a highly efficient reduction of contamination in 
the secondary PCR step, and, if necessary, allows de-
tection and of course computational removal of possi-
bly persisting minor contaminations by bioinformatics 
sequence analysis. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
PCR-based systems are known to be vulnerable to false 
positive results caused by contaminations with products 
from previous amplifications (2,3). Sources of contaminat-
ing DNA include assay reagents, equipment, operator han-
dling and aerosols (2,3). The rapid development of NGS 
technologies permits a much higher sensitivity than most 
of the previously established methods. However, this sensi-
tivity may lead to the detection of previously unrecognized 
cross-over contaminations from other samples. This is espe-
cially critical in the case of assays which require the reliable 
detection of just a few amplicons (e.g. minimal residual dis-</p>

<p>ease (MRD)). MRD is an important prognostic factor and 
has clinical impact (13-15). 
Two-step PCR NGS library preparations are used for 
various applications such as targeted re-sequencing of can-
cer genes, 16S microbiome analyses or the analysis of B-
and T-cell receptor genes (4-8). As described by Faham and 
Willis amplification bias may be decreased by reducing the 
number of amplification cycles in a first step using primers 
with tails non-complementary to the target sequences (16). 
These tails include primer binding sites that are added to 
the ends of the sequences of the primary amplicon and are 
specifically targeted in the second amplification step. By us-
ing only a single forward and a single reverse primer, the 
primary cause of amplification bias is confined (16). 
Here we introduce a novel method to effectively prevent 
contaminations in two-step PCR systems. This new ap-
proach sharply contrasts with previously described meth-
ods which are merely able to detect contaminations or to 
prevent first round PCR contaminations (17-21). Our ap-
proach is additionally capable to prevent contaminations in 
the second PCR (Table 4). Especially the most commonly 
used UTP/UNG system where dTTP is replaced by dUTP 
in the PCR mixture leading to degradation of unintention-
ally transferred DNAs into the samples is not able to detect 
or suppress contaminations present in the second PCR (17- 19). The reason is that the products from the first reaction 
would be cleaved by an UNG treatment in the second re-
action. This is especially true with bisulfite amplification / 
sequencing, where conversion to U precludes using UDG 
in the first place. 
An alternative method to detect amplicon cross-
contaminations is the use of NGS adaptor-specific primers 
(20,21). These primers anneal to NGS adaptor parts being 
present in the first and second PCR products (e.g. a M13 
tail). By this method, cross-contaminations from the first </p>

<p>e135 Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 20 </p>



<p>Table 4. Cross-contaminations and their possible prevention in two-step PCR settings for NGS library generation </p>

<p>Possible contamination site </p>

<p>Source of contamination 
First amplification PCR mix 
Second amplification PCR mix </p>

<p>Amplicon from the first PCR 
(A) 
(C) 
Prevention: UTP/UNG system 
Prevention and detection: 
Detection: PCR with first amplification 
tail-specific primers </p>

<p>K-box protection (this manuscript) </p>

<p>Amplicon from the second PCR 
(B) 
(D) 
Prevention: UTP/UNG system 
Prevention and detection: 
Detection: PCR with first or second 
amplification tail-or adaptor-specific primers </p>

<p>K-box protection (this manuscript) </p>

<p>A &amp; B: Contaminations of the first amplification by PCR products derived from another first or second amplification can be prevented by the UTP/UNG 
system and detected by tail-or adaptor-specific primers (19-21). C &amp; D: Contaminations of the second amplification by PCR products derived from 
another first or second amplification can be prevented and detected by the K-box protection method described in this manuscript. </p>

<p>or second PCR amplicons, either in the template or the 
PCR reagents, can be detected but not prevented. 
Our K-box method as described in this manuscript is a 
synergistic combination of suppression of carry-over con-
taminations and detection of possible residual contamina-
tions in the two-step PCR workflow. The design of the se-
quence elements of this K-box is sample-specific. Specific 
amplification is only possible in case of a perfect match of 
the K1 elements used for first and second amplification. K2 
sequences serve for detection of possible residual contami-
nations. 
We found that our method is most effective with a proof-
reading polymerase in the second amplification providing 
the additional advantage of amplification with lesser errors. 
In order to fully prevent cross-contaminations in the second 
PCR, mismatches between K1 sequence elements of more 
than 2 nucleotides should be used in addition to at least 
2 PT-bonds at the 3 -end of second amplification primers 
(Figures 3 and 4). 
Applying these K-box parameters we showed that in two 
step NGS library preparations a high contamination grade 
of up to 100% was completely suppressed (Figure 5, Table 
3 and Supplementary Figure S4). Thus, our method is not 
only able to prevent low level contaminations but also very 
high rates of contaminations which can be caused by con-
fusing samples. 
The suppression of contaminations is a much more ele-
gant approach as compared to mere detection of contam-
inations. The latter approach necessitates time-consuming 
repetition of the entire procedure whereas the K-box 
method is perfectly integrated in the two-step PCR work-
flow without additional time requirements. Especially for 
diagnostic amplicon-based NGS the avoidance of repetition 
represents an important advantage due to the time pressure 
associated with this type of analysis. 
Examples for distinct practical applications of the K-box 
method are (i) the analysis of consecutive samples from one 
patient in MRD diagnostics, (ii) targeted re-sequencing of 
cancer genes or (iii) 16S microbiome analyses. The K-box 
method can be adapted to high throughput formats, e.g. a 
two-step PCR performed in 96 well plates. Thereby, K2 ele-
ments are essential to detect possible remaining contamina-
tions from previous amplification reactions and thus certify 
the efficiency of contamination suppression by K1 elements. 
If the effective contamination suppression by K1 elements </p>

<p>is firmly established for the given primer sets, a reduction 
to a sole K1-S combination (without K2 elements) may be 
considered. 
In summary, we describe a new method capable of sup-
pressing contaminations and/or detecting residual contam-
inations in NGS library preparations employing a two-step 
PCR protocol. This new method is based on three syner-
gistically acting sequence elements referred to as K-box. 
The K-box method provides a significant improvement for 
NGS diagnostics in terms of accuracy, time requirement 
and costs. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>We thank Anke Seegebarth for her excellent technical assis-
tance, Julia Ritter for help with primer design and Rudolf 
Hammer for fruitful discussions in preparation of the 
manuscript. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Investitionsbank Berlin and the European Regional Devel-
opment Fund [10155447 and 10155355 to the Charité and 
HS Diagnomics, respectively]. 
Conflict of interest statement. S.H. is CEO as well as co-
founder of HS Diagnomics, and S.S., A.D. and V.S. are 
shareholders of HS Diagnomics. V.S., M.H., S.H. are inven-
tors of a patent (EP 2746405 A1) which describes the K-box 
system. D.L. has no conflict of interest to disclose. </p>



<p>PAGE 9 OF 9 </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 20 e135 </p>



</text></tei>