<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4586740" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cells rely on autophagy to survive diverse cellular insults such 
as nutrient depletion, accumulation of protein aggregates, dam-
aged mitochondria, or intracellular bacteria (Deretic et al., 2013). 
Autophagy describes different eukaryotic mechanisms of protein 
degradation, which result in the transfer to and the degradation 
of organelles or cytosolic material in the lysosomes (Hamasaki 
et al., 2013b). Macroautophagy (here referred as autophagy) is </p>

<p>controlled by specialized Atg factors that promote the genesis 
of autophagosomes, substrate recruitment, lysosome-autopha-
gosome fusion, and final degradation of autolysosome contents. 
One of the earliest steps of autophagy involves the activation of 
the ULK1-ATG13-FIP200 protein complex at the surface of 
the ER for recruitment of the class III phosphatidylinositol-3-
kinase vacuolar protein sorting 34 (VPS34), together with the 
Vps15-Beclin1-ATG14 complex (Mizushima, 2010). Phospha-
tidylinositol-3-phosphate (PtdIns(3)P) formation by VPS34 is 
absolutely required for autophagosome formation, and one of the 
major upstream regulators of this step is the mTORC1 complex, 
whose inactivation induces autophagic flux through ATG1/ULK1 
activation in response to metabolic changes, starvation, or rapa-
mycin treatment (Kim et al., 2011). 
Like other membrane trafficking steps, autophagy is reg-
ulated by Rab GTPases, soluble N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive </p>

<p>Autophagy is a key degradative pathway coordinated by external cues, including starvation, oxidative stress, or 
pathogen detection. Rare are the molecules known to contribute mechanistically to the regulation of autophagy and 
expressed specifically in particular environmental contexts or in distinct cell types. Here, we unravel the role of RUN 
and FYVE domain-containing protein 4 (RUFY4) as a positive molecular regulator of macroautophagy in primary 
dendritic cells (DCs). We show that exposure to interleukin-4 (IL-4) during DC differentiation enhances autophagy flux 
through mTORC1 regulation and RUFY4 induction, which in turn actively promote LC3 degradation, Syntaxin 17-
positive autophagosome formation, and lysosome tethering. Enhanced autophagy boosts endogenous antigen pre-
sentation by MHC II and allows host control of Brucella abortus replication in IL-4-treated DCs and in RUFY4-expressing 
cells. RUFY4 is therefore the first molecule characterized to date that promotes autophagy and influences endosome 
dynamics in a subset of immune cells. </p>

<p>RUN and FYVE domain-containing protein 4 
enhances autophagy and lysosome tethering in 
response to Interleukin-4 </p>

<p>Seigo Terawaki, 1 * Voahirana Camosseto, 1 * Francesca Prete, 1 * Till Wenger, 1 * Alexia Papadopoulos, 1 
Christiane Rondeau, 2 Alexis Combes, 1 Christian Rodriguez Rodrigues, 1 Thien-Phong Vu Manh, 1 Mathieu Fallet, 1 
Luc English, 2 Rodrigo Santamaria, 4 Ana R. Soares, 5,6 Tobias Weil, 5 Hamida Hammad, 7 Michel Desjardins, 2,3 
Jean-Pierre Gorvel, 1 Manuel A.S. Santos, 5,6 Evelina Gatti, 1,6 ** and Philippe Pierre 1,6 ** </p>

<p>1 Centre d'Immunologie de Marseille-Luminy, Aix Marseille Université UM2, Institut National de la Santé et de la Recherche Médicale U1104, Centre National de la 
Recherche Scientifique UMR7280, 13288 Marseille, France 
2 Département de pathologie et biologie cellulaire and 3 Département de microbiologie, infectiologie, et immunologie, Université de Montréal, Québec H3C 3J7, Canada 
4 Departamento de Informática y Automática, Universidad de Salamanca, 37008 Salamanca, Spain 
5 RNA Biology Laboratory, Department of Biology and Centre for Environmental and Marine Studies (CES AM) and 6 Institute for Research in Biomedicine (iBiMED), Aveiro 
Health Sciences Program, University of Aveiro, 3810-193 Aveiro, Portugal 
7 Laboratory of Immunoregulation and Mucosal Immunology, Department for Molecular Biomedical Research, VIB, Ghent 9050, Belgium </p>

<p>© 2015 Terawaki et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>*S. Terawaki, V. Camosseto, F. Prete, and T. Wenger contributed equally to 
this paper. </p>

<p>**E. Gatti and P. Pierre contributed equally to this paper. </p>

<p>Correspondence to Philippe Pierre: pierre@ciml.univ-mrs.fr; or Evelina Gatti: 
gatti@ciml.univ-mrs.fr </p>

<p>Abbreviations used in this paper: 3-MA, 3-methyl adenine; BCV, B. abortus-
containing vacuole; bmDC, bone marrow-derived DC; cDC, conventional DC; 
CFU, colony-forming unit; CQ, chloroquine; DAL IS, DC-aggresome-like induced 
structure; DC, dendritic cell; DEG, differentially expressed gene; DRiP, defective 
ribosomal protein; HDM, house dust mite; ICM, immunofluorescence confocal 
microscopy; iDC, immature DC; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; mDC, mature DC; 
MoDC, monocyte-derived DC; PCA, principal component analysis; PtdIns(3)P, 
phosphatidylinositol-3-phosphate; qPCR, quantitative PCR; ROS, reactive oxy-
gen species; RUFY, RUN and FYVE domain-containing protein; SNA RE, soluble 
N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor attachment protein receptor; TLR, Toll-like re-
ceptor; WT, wild type. </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
factor attachment protein receptors (SNA REs), and tethering 
complexes. The role of Rab7 in autophagosome-lysosome fu-
sion has been extensively studied (Tabata et al., 2010), whereas 
the Qa-SNA RE Syntaxin 17 (STX17) has been proposed to 
mediate both autophagosome formation and fusion with lyso-
somes by binding to its partners SNAP29 and VAMP8 (Itak-
ura et al., 2012; Hamasaki et al., 2013a). In their active form, 
GTPases and SNA REs are anchored to intracellular vesicles, 
subsequently regulating recruitment of various effector pro-
teins in cooperation with the accumulation of specific lipids 
like PtdIns(3)P. RUN and FYVE domain-containing proteins 
(RUFYs), which contain an N-terminal RUN domain, shown 
to interact with small GTPases (Callebaut et al., 2001), and a 
PtdIns(3)P-interacting C-terminal FYVE domain, are good 
candidate effectors capable of controlling endocytosis or au-
tophagy (Birkeland and Stenmark, 2004). A member of the 
RUFY family, the FYVE and coiled-coil domain containing 1 
(FYCO1) has been demonstrated to bind LC3/ATG8, PtdIns(3) 
P, and Rab7 (Pankiv et al., 2010), linking autophagosomes to 
microtubule plus end-directed molecular motors. 
Antigen presentation mostly consists of the direct pre-
sentation of proteasome-degraded cytosolic peptides by MHC 
class I and the presentation of internalized exogenous proteins 
by MHC class II. The closely related autophagy and endocytic 
degradative pathways are particularly important for the orches-
tration of immunity by dendritic cells (DCs) because MHC II-
restricted antigen presentation is heavily dependent on endo/ 
lysosomal proteolytic processing to achieve efficient peptide 
presentation to naive CD4 + T cells (Honey and Rudensky, 
2003). Interestingly, cytosolic proteins have also been shown 
to use autophagy to transit from the cytosol to endosomes and 
enter the MHC II-restricted presentation pathway (Schmid et 
al., 2007; Münz, 2012), whereas endosomal function and exog-
enous antigen MHC II presentation are altered in Atg-deficient 
DCs (Lee et al., 2010). DCs are activated through microbial pat-
tern recognition receptors such as Toll-like receptors (TLRs), 
which results in unmatched T cell priming capacities (Kawai 
and Akira, 2008). Autophagy functions in many aspects of 
innate immune signaling (Deretic et al., 2013) and can be en-
hanced by microbial stimulation, as shown for RAW264.7 mac-
rophages by lipopolysaccharide (LPS; Delgado et al., 2008; 
Levine et al., 2011). Thus, DCs exposed to microbial stimuli 
and various polarizing cytokines offer a unique model to study 
autophagy regulation and identify novel factors controlling this 
function in mammalian cells. 
We focus here on the regulation of autophagy in DCs re-
sponding to LPS and Interleukin-4 (IL-4) in vitro. We show that 
autophagy flux is reduced during the stimulation of primary 
DCs by LPS. This inhibition is a consequence of mTORC1 ac-
tivation after TLR stimulation and results in a clear reduction 
of endogenous MHC II-restricted antigen presentation and ac-
cumulation of neosynthetized misfolded proteins in DC-aggre-
some-like induced structures (DAL ISs). We further demonstrate 
that IL-4-mediated differentiation of DCs is able to consider-
ably augment basal autophagy flux, promoting endogenous an-
tigen presentation and reducing the ability of the intracellular 
pathogen Brucella abortus to replicate. IL-4 exerts this function 
by interfering with mTOR signaling but also via the induction 
of RUFY4, a previously uncharacterized RUFY family member 
(Ivan et al., 2012). RUFY4 expression increases autophagy and 
leads to the reorganization of late endosomal compartments, 
thereby changing the overall endosome membrane dynamic </p>

<p>during DC differentiation and revealing its functional role as 
a Rab7 effector and one of the few positive regulators of auto-
phagy identified to date. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>TLR stimulation activates mTOR and 
suppresses autophagy in DCs </p>

<p>Engagement of the TLR4 pathway by LPS induces in bone mar-
row-derived DCs (bmDCs) the phosphorylation of mTORC1 
targets, such as p70 ribosomal protein S6 kinase (p70S6K), ri-
bosomal protein S6, translation factor inhibitor 4E-BP1, and, 
importantly, AMB RA1 at residue Ser52 (Fig. 1, A and B), as 
well as ULK1 kinase at residue Ser757 (see Fig. 3 A). mTORC1 
inhibits autophagy through its recruitment into the Atg1/ULK1-
mAtg13-FIP200 autophagy initiation complex and subsequent 
Ser757 phosphorylation of ULK1 (Mizushima, 2010; Kim et 
al., 2011) and Ser52 phosphorylation of AMB RA1, which inter-
feres with ULK1 function (Nazio et al., 2013). LPS stimulation 
of mTORC1, in addition to enhancing global protein synthesis 
(Lelouard et al., 2007), likely reduces ULK1 activity and conse-
quently basal levels of autophagy in activated DCs. 
TLR-dependent inhibition of autophagy was confirmed by 
comparing nonactivated immature DCs (iDCs), which accumu-
lated the phosphatidylethanolamine-conjugated and autopha-
gosome-associated LC3II isoform (Kabeya et al., 2004), with 
LPS-activated mature DCs (mDCs), in which the nonlipidated 
LC3I precursor was stabilized, denoting a reduced autophagy 
flux (Fig. 1 C). Inhibition of lysosomal proteolysis with chloro-
quine (CQ) promoted accumulation of LC3II in iDCs but not in 
mDCs, confirming the LPS-dependent inhibition of autophagic 
flux (Fig. 1 C). In transfected DCs expressing mCherry-eGFP 
tandem-tagged LC3, similarly to bafilomycin, LPS treat-
ment increased the ratio of eGFP-versus mCherry-associated 
fluorescence, confirming a decrease in LC3 turnover (Fig. 1 D; 
Klionsky et al., 2012). In autophagy-active cells, GFP-LC3 fluo-
rescence was rapidly quenched upon autophagosome-lysosome 
fusion (Klionsky et al., 2012), as observed by cytometry in 
iDCs expressing GFP-LC3 (Fig. 1 E), in which only few and 
weakly fluorescent GFP-positive structures were detected by 
microscopy in absence of CQ treatment. Conversely, upon LPS 
stimulation, a rapid accumulation of GFP-LC3 in organelles 
reminiscent of stalled autophagosomes was observed together 
with increased LC3-associated fluorescence levels (Fig. 1 E). 
Electron microscopy revealed the presence of partially fused au-
tophagosomes with lysosomes containing undigested material 
in LPS-activated DCs, which is supportive of a globally reduced 
autophagic flux in mDCs (Fig. S1). Collectively, these results 
demonstrate that autophagy flux is reduced during DC activation 
and probably mediated by TLR-dependent mTORC1 activation. </p>

<p>Autophagy flux reduction leads to 
defective ribosomal protein (DRiP) 
accumulation in DAL ISs </p>

<p>Upon inhibition of autophagy in HeLa cells, neosynthetized 
DRiP processing is delayed, thereby promoting accumulation 
of these potential antigens in large ubiquitin-positive aggre-
gates, termed ALISs (Wenger et al., 2012), together with the 
autophagy adaptors p62/SQTM1 and Nbr1 (Johansen and La-
mark, 2011). We examined the distribution of p62 and NBR1 by 
confocal microscopy in mDCs and found that the two adaptors </p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>Figure 1. The mTOR pathway is activated and autophagy is inhibited in DCs upon LPS exposure. (A) WT or MyD88-and TRIF-deficient (KO) DCs were stim-
ulated with LPS as indicated, and S6 phosphorylation was analyzed by immunoblot. (B) DCs were stimulated with LPS and treated or not with rapamycin 
(4 h) as indicated. Cell lysates were analyzed by immunoblot for phosphorylation of p70-S6 kinase and S6 and total levels of p70, and S6 and actin served 
as controls (left). DCs were stimulated as indicated with LPS, and lysates were analyzed by immunoblot for phosphorylation of 4E-BP1 (Thr37/46; middle) 
and AMB RA1 (right; P-AMB RA1 is indicated by an arrowhead). Note the shift of 4-EBP1 from the nonphosphorylated γ form to the partially phosphorylated 
(hypophosphorylated) β and the hyperphosphorylated α forms (middle). (C) DCs were stimulated with LPS for the indicated time, and CQ was added for 
4 h where specified. Cell lysates were analyzed by immunoblot for LC3 and actin (left). LC3I, nonlipidated form; LC3II, lipidated form. The relative LC3II 
accumulation was quantified using <rs id="software-1" type="software">ImageJ</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>; right). The data shown are from a single representative experiment out of seven 
repeats. (D) DC maturation induces autophagy inhibition. DCs were transfected with mRNA encoding for mCherry-GFP-LC3 and incubated for 8 h in the 
presence of LPS or bafilomycin or starved in HBSS. GFP and mCherry fluorescence in CD11c + cells was assessed by FACS (left). Plotted is the ratio of GFP 
fluorescence (fold over control) versus mCherry fluorescence (fold over control; right). Mean and SEM from three independent experiments and p-values 
(Student's t test) are shown. (E) Autophagy inhibition is revealed by accumulation of GFP-LC3. DCs from GFP-LC3 transgenic mice were treated or not for 4 
or 20 h with LPS or for 4 h with CQ, stained for CD11c, and analyzed for GFP fluorescence (left). B6 WT DCs (histogram filled with gray) or GFP-LC3 DCs 
were stimulated (red) or not (green) with LPS for 20 h, and GFP fluorescence was analyzed in CD11c + cells by FACS (rightmost panel). The data shown 
are from a single representative experiment out of three repeats. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
accumulated in DAL ISs, together with LC3, polyubiquitinated 
proteins (FK2), and puromycin-tagged DRiPs (puro-DRiPs; 
Fig. 2 A and Fig. S2 A; Lelouard et al., 2004). Autophagic flux 
inhibition in mDCs could therefore contribute to DRiP aggre-
gation with p62 and LC3. Consistent with this hypothesis, the 
serine 403 phospho form of p62, which is increased upon au-
tophagy inhibition and has enhanced affinity for polyubiquiti-
nated proteins (Matsumoto et al., 2011), was found enriched 
in DAL ISs (Fig. S2 A). Pharmacological inhibition of autoph-
agy using 3-methyl adenine (3-MA) strongly promoted DAL 
IS formation in mDCs, whereas autophagy induction with the 
mTORC1 inhibitor rapamycin prevented p62 aggregation and 
DAL IS assembly (Fig. 2 B). As DAL IS formation requires 
active protein synthesis, we demonstrated that although the 
mRNA translation was reduced by 3-MA and rapamycin treat-
ment, the drugs did not interfere with LPS-dependent induc-
tion of protein synthesis, which remained active throughout 
the time of drug exposure (Fig. 2 C), further suggesting that, in 
addition to increased protein synthesis, autophagy inhibition is 
absolutely key for DAL IS formation. Polyubiquitinated protein 
aggregation and p62 expression have been linked to reactive ox-
ygen species (ROS) expression and NRF-2 activation (Fujita et 
al., 2011); however, treatment of DCs with N-acetyl-l-cysteine 
(NAC) did not prevent DAL IS formation in response to LPS 
(Fig. S2 B), indicating that ROS production is not required 
for TLR-driven aggregation of DRiPs with p62 in DCs. p62/ 
Nbr1/ubiquitin-positive aggregates and DAL ISs are therefore 
identical structures, are also detectable in splenic CD11c + DC 
subtypes purified from LPS-injected mice (Fig. S2 C), and are 
the likely manifestation of a reduced autophagic processing of 
neosynthetized proteins. </p>

<p>Autophagy reduction in maturing DCs 
decreases endogenous MHC II presentation </p>

<p>Professional antigen-presenting cells use autophagy to process 
and load endogenous cytosolic antigens on MHC II (Schmid 
et al., 2007). A model antigen (GFP-2OP) was created by 
fusing eGFP together with two different ovalbumin-derived 
peptides, the I-A d -restricted IR17 peptide (Ova 323-339) 
and the K b -restricted SL8 peptide (Ova 257-264, SII NFEKL; 
Fig. 2 D). MHC I presentation of GFP-2OP is highly dependent 
on neosynthesis, misfolding, and rapid proteasome degradation 
(Wenger et al., 2012). Interestingly, inhibition of autophagy 
in HeLa cells promotes the accumulation of similar antigens 
in ALISs (Wenger et al., 2012) and delays their degradation, 
suggesting that in professional APCs, GFP-2OP will be pro-
cessed and presented by MHC II molecules. GFP-2OP mRNA 
was electroporated in CB6F1 mouse DCs, resulting in strong 
antigen expression (GFP fluorescence) as well as MHC I K b / 
SL8 presentation (Fig. 2 D). eGFP-expressing DCs exhibited a 
mature surface phenotype with high levels of CD86 and MHC 
II, which could be enhanced, along with IL-12 production, by 
LPS (Fig. S2, D and E). In transfected CD11C + DCs, a portion 
of GFP was found aggregated together with p62 in DAL ISs, 
confirming the impact of DC activation on autophagic process-
ing (Fig. S2 F). MHC II-restricted GFP-2OP presentation lev-
els were quantified after IL-2 production by DO11.10 CD4 + T 
cells. Upon short-term autophagy inhibition by 3-MA or after 
LPS stimulation, a 50% reduction in IL-2 release by DO11.10 T 
cells was observed (Fig. 2 E), leaving both MHC I presentation 
of the same antigens and control MHC II presentation of exog-
enously added ovalbumin unaltered (Fig. 2 E). </p>

<p>IL-4 increases basal levels of 
autophagy in DCs </p>

<p>Circulating monocytes can give rise to DCs in steady state, but 
their contribution to the DC pool is by far greater under inflam-
matory conditions (Geissmann et al., 2010). The breadth and 
quality of the immune response is influenced by environmental 
cues, such as cytokine signals provided by neighboring tissues 
or cells. For example, in the context of allergic inflammation, 
exposure of macrophages or monocytes to the canonical Th2 
cytokines IL-4 and IL-13 induces characteristic markers (M2 
phenotype or alternative activation), along with changes in their 
metabolism, that enhance the synthesis of antiinflammatory 
factors (Van Dyken and Locksley, 2013). Human monocyte-de-
rived DCs (MoDCs) have been shown to efficiently present 
LC3-associated antigens to CD4 + T cells with little influence 
of LPS-mediated activation (Schmid et al., 2007). Moreover, 
LPS-activated MoDCs display little co-aggregation of p62 to-
gether with polyubiquitination (FK1) in DAL ISs (Fig. S2 G), 
suggesting that MoDCs, conversely to mouse bmDCs, do not 
significantly reduce their autophagy flux in response to micro-
bial activation. As the most relevant difference in the protocols 
used to differentiate MoDCs and bmDCs in vitro is the addition 
of IL-4 (Zhou and Tedder, 1996), we decided to compare auto-
phagy and antigen presentation levels in mouse DCs differenti-
ated in the presence of GM-CSF and IL-4, instead of GM-CSF 
alone (Wells et al., 2005). 
As expected, CD11c + DCs differentiated with GM-CSF 
and IL-4 (IL-4-DCs) exhibited slightly elevated CD86 and 
CD40 levels (Wells et al., 2005) but responded normally to 
LPS (Fig. S3 A). IL-4-DCs had a higher basal rate of protein 
synthesis, which was proportionally less augmented by LPS 
activation than in GM-CSF-DCs (Fig. 3 A). When phosphor-
ylation of AMB RA1 and ULK1 was monitored, little Ser52 
and Ser757 phosphorylation could be detected in LPS-activated 
IL-4-DCs (Fig. 3 A and Fig. S3 B). The same held true for rapa-
mycin-sensitive rS6 phosphorylation (Fig. S3 B), indicating 
that, conversely to conventional GM-CSF-differentiated DCs, 
mTORC1 activation in response to TLR4 triggering is inhibited 
by IL-4 and constitutive autophagy levels are likely to be pre-
served in IL-4-differentiated DCs. 
LC3 immunoblots indicated that autophagy flux was in-
creased in IL-4-DCs (Fig. 3 B). When the fate LC3-binding 
proteins and DAL ISs were monitored by microscopy (Fig. 3 C) 
and quantified using automated imaging software (Fig. 3 D), 
diminished levels in numbers and size of p62 aggregates con-
firmed that autophagy was far more active in LPS-treated 
IL-4-DCs. By electron microscopy, IL-4-DCs displayed au-
tophagosome populations with normal morphology, with a 
significant decrease in numbers of partially fused autophago-
somes found in GM-CSF mDCs (Fig. S1). Activated IL-4-DCs 
also displayed an increase in the number of electron-dense late 
endosomal structures found in the cytosol. Immunofluores-
cence microscopy confirmed this observation and revealed that 
LAMP2-positive late endosome/lysosome pericentriolar clus-
ters were increased in IL-4-DCs (Fig. 3 E), suggesting that both 
autophagosome and endosome dynamics are enhanced during 
differentiation with IL-4. </p>

<p>IL-4 facilitates the clearance of damaged 
mitochondria in mDCs </p>

<p>To avoid cellular damage, ROS-generating mitochondria are 
constantly removed by mitophagy, a specialized form of auto-</p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>Figure 2. Autophagy inhibition by DC activation leads to the aggregation of endogenous antigens in DAL ISs and down-regulation of MHC II presentation. 
(A) Immunofluorescence confocal microscopy (ICM) analysis for NBR1 and p62 was performed on LPS-stimulated DCs (left). LPS-stimulated DCs were given 
a 10-min pulse of 0.1 µg/µl puromycin (right) or left untreated (middle). 30 min later, cells were detergent extracted and fixed. Polyubiquitinylated proteins 
(polyUbi), p62, and puromycin-marked (Puro) proteins were analyzed by ICM. Arrowheads indicate the rapid localization of puromycin-labeled proteins 
with p62 in DAL ISs. (B) ICM analysis of polyubiquitinylated proteins and p62 was performed on LPS-stimulated (4 h) or control DCs, treated or not for 4 h 
with 3-MA or rapamycin. (A and B) Bars, 10 µm. (C) DCs were stimulated as indicated with LPS in the presence or absence of 3-MA or rapamycin and 
were given 1 µg/ml puromycin 10 min before harvesting and incorporation monitoring by immunoblot. Density quantification is shown on the right. The 
data shown are from a single representative experiment out of three repeats. (D) Schematic representation of the eGFP/double ovalbumin peptide (GFP-
2OP) model antigen, containing the I-A d -presented IR17 peptide (Ova 323-339) and the K b -presented SL8 peptide (Ova 257-264). Representative FACS 
analysis (n = 4) of GFP fluorescence and K b /SL8 antigen presentation (25D1 mAb) upon transfection of GFP or GFP-SL8 mRNA in CB6F1 DCs. (E, top left) </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
phagy. We speculated that inhibition of mitophagy should lead 
to the accumulation of ROS-producing mitochondria upon LPS 
activation of DCs and a reduction of these same mitochon-
dria in IL-4-DCs. We used mitochondria-specific fluorescent 
labels that distinguish respiring (MitoTracker deep red), total 
(MitoTracker green), and ROS-generating mitochondria (Mito-
SOX; Tal et al., 2009). Cytometry analysis (Fig. S3 C) showed 
that LPS exposure increased by 25% the number of cells con-
taining damaged mitochondria and by 30% the number of cells 
producing mitochondrial ROS (Fig. S3 D). IL-4 exposure con-
siderably decreased these proportions by augmenting damaged 
mitochondria clearance, as determined by the large cell fraction 
displaying reduced mitochondrial staining and the inhibition 
of this phenomenon in ATG5 flx/flx -CD11C-cre DCs (Fig. S3 C; 
Lee et al., 2010). Interestingly, the difference between LPS-ac-
tivated wild-type (WT) and ATG5 −/− GM-CSF DCs was mini-
mal, confirming the inhibitory effect of LPS on mitophagy in 
DCs. Therefore, LPS-and IL-4-mediated control of autophagy 
have important consequences on DC physiology, and IL-4 is 
also likely to exert its antiinflammatory role through enhanced 
mitophagy and an associated decrease in ROS production. </p>

<p>IL-4 differentiation facilitates T cell priming 
by endogenous antigen </p>

<p>Upon IL-4-driven DC differentiation, a larger flow of endog-
enous antigens should be available for MHC II presentation. 
DCs, derived from DOG mice that express hDTR-Ova 140-
386-eGFP, were used to present ovalbumin-derived peptides on 
H-2K b to OT-I and on I-A b to OT-II primary T cells (Hochweller 
et al., 2008). CFSE labeling dilution experiments indicated 
that OT-I CD8 + T cells were efficiently primed by DOG-DCs 
(Fig. 4 A), confirming the production of cytosolic ovalbumin 
peptides in these cells, which express this antigen in very low 
amounts difficult to visualize by other techniques (Hochweller 
et al., 2008). When MHC II presentation was investigated, GM-
CSF DOG-DCs did not efficiently stimulate CFSE-labeled CD4 + 
OT-II cells (Fig. 4 B), independently of their activation state. 
Conversely, and despite low levels of antigen expression, im-
mature IL-4-DOG-DCs weakly activated OT-II cells (Fig. 4 C), 
a phenomenon considerably enhanced by LPS stimulation and 
leading to CD4 + T cell divisions (Fig. 4 C). Exogenously added 
ovalbumin was only processed and presented efficiently upon 
LPS activation (Fig. 4 B), a situation also observed with Eα52-
68-specific H30 T cell hybridomas, which failed to be activated 
by either type of iDCs fed with necrotic A20 B cells (Fig. 4 D). </p>

<p>Short-term exposure to IL-4 does not 
impact autophagy in DCs </p>

<p>Short IL-4 exposure (2 h) inhibits starvation-induced autophagy 
in Raw and primary mouse macrophages (Harris et al., 2007). 
We therefore investigated whether the potentiation of autophagy 
in IL-4-DCs was the result of long-term differentiation and po-
tentially cell specific. DCs and macrophages were generated in 
parallel cultures of mouse bone marrow in the presence of GM-</p>

<p>CSF or M-CSF, to which IL-4 was added for 5 d or 2 h before 
LC3 processing analysis (Fig. S4 A). Interestingly, long-term 
IL-4 treatment enhanced autophagy in DCs much more than 
in macrophages, whereas short-term exposure had little effect 
on DCs and, as suggested previously, was moderately inhibi-
tory for macrophages (Harris et al., 2007). Similar experiments 
performed on RAW macrophages indicated that IL-4 inhibits 
minimally autophagic flux after short-term exposure and had 
no effect after 24 h of treatment. Thus, increased autophagy in 
IL-4-DCs is dependent on both long-term differentiation with 
IL-4 and cell culture specificity because DCs and macrophages 
differentiated in vitro have remarkably distinct behaviors. </p>

<p>Transcriptomics analysis of DCs 
differentiated with IL-4 </p>

<p>We initiated a comparative microarray-based genomic analysis 
of purified GM-CSF bm-CD11 + DCs differentiated or not in the 
presence of IL-4 to identify a transcriptional program capable of 
enhancing endosomes and/or autophagosomes dynamics. Prin-
cipal component (PC) analysis (PCA) showed a close proximity 
of replicates (Fig. 5 A) with a clear partitioning of each exper-
imental condition tested. PC1, corresponding to ''LPS versus 
nonactivated (con),'' represented 49% of the overall variability 
between microarrays. PC2, corresponding to ''IL-4 treatment,'' 
accounted for 22%, suggesting that LPS activation dominated 
the overall DC differential gene expression program. However, 
IL-4 treatment induced a specific response only moderately 
affected by LPS. Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were 
selected on statistical significance (P &lt; 0.1) and a fold change 
above 2 for up-regulated genes (Fig. 5 B) and below 0.33 for 
down-regulated genes (Fig. S5). After clustering and heat map 
representation of the top regulated genes, resistin-like-α, Ccl24, 
and arginase 1 were found to be the most up-regulated by 
IL-4, as previously described in macrophages (Van Dyken and 
Locksley, 2013). Venn diagrams showed that out of all probes 
tested, 187 DEGs defined a core IL-4 differential gene expres-
sion signature (Table S1). DEGs were submitted to two differ-
ent pathway analyses, <rs type="software">Voronto</rs> and <rs type="software">Ingenuity Pathway Analysis 
(IPA</rs>) softwares. <rs type="software">Voronto</rs> uses tessellation Voronoi diagrams to 
integrate expression data and hierarchical ontologies extracted 
from public databases (Santamaría and Pierre, 2012). The most 
significant pathways induced by IL-4 were linked to amino acid 
and lipid metabolisms as well as chemokine signaling. <rs type="software">IPA</rs> iden-
tified the IL-4 signature list as constituted of immunologically 
relevant genes because top pathways were identified as inflam-
matory or immunological diseases. IL-4 was identified as the 
top predicted upstream regulator followed closely by IL-13 and 
STAT6, confirming the pertinence of our analysis. This predic-
tion was mostly influenced by genes representing the hallmark 
of alternative versus classical macrophage activation, including 
Arginase 1 and anti-nematode and -fungal resistance genes such 
as chitinases (e.g., Chi3l4) and RNases (e.g., Ear11). When im-
munologically relevant genes were examined, mRNA levels of 
chemokines CCL24, CCL22, and IL-6 were all significantly </p>

<p>GFP mRNA-transfected CB6F1 DCs were incubated with 0.3 µg/ml ovalbumin (delivered as immune complexes) alone or together with LPS or 3-MA for 
8 h and used to stimulate DO.11 T cells. Mean and SEM from three independent experiments. (top right) CB6F1 DCs transfected for 8 h with eGFP or eGFP-
SL8-OT2P mRNA were used to stimulate DO.11 T cells for 24 h. T cell activation was determined by IL-2 dosage. Mean and SEM from four experiments 
and p-values (Student's t test) are shown. (bottom) CB6F1 DCs were transfected with GFP or with GFP-2OP mRNA and cultured for 8 h in the presence or 
absence of 3-MA or LPS, and antigen expression (% GFP positive) and K b /SL8 surface appearance (% K b /SL8 positive by 25D1 staining) were measured. 
Mean and SEM from three independent experiments. </p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>Figure 3. IL-4 differentiation promotes autophagy and prevents DALIS formation in DCs. (A) IL-4 and control DCs were stimulated as indicated with LPS 
and were given 1 µg/ml puromycin for 10 min (left) before harvesting. Puromycin incorporation (left) or ULK-1 phosphorylation (right) was monitored by 
immunoblot analysis, representative of n = 3. (B) cDCs or IL-4-DCs were stimulated with LPS for 16 h, and CQ was added as indicated. Cell lysates were 
analyzed by immunoblot for LC3 and actin (left). The ratio of LC3II/LC3I was determined by densitometry analysis (right). The data shown are from a single 
representative experiment out of six repeats. (C) DCs generated in the presence or absence of IL-4 were activated with LPS for 20 h, and then p62 and 
LC3 localization was analyzed by ICM. p62 and LC3 overlaps in DALIS are indicated by arrowheads. R = Pearson's correlation. (D) DCs generated in 
the presence or absence of IL-4 were activated with LPS for 8 h. The size of p62 aggregates (x axis) and the number of aggregates per cell (y axis) were 
quantified by automated video microscopy and plotted. The numbers of aggregate-negative cells (red) and total analyzed cell number (black) are shown 
at the origin of the plot (left). The proportion of cells with or without p62 aggregates is shown as bar graph (right). n = 350 and 372; mean and SEM 
from three independent experiments. **, P &lt; 0.01. (E) DCs generated in the absence or presence of IL-4 were stimulated with LPS as indicated. LAMP2 
localization, monitored by ICM analysis, revealed late endosome clustering in IL-4-DCs (arrowheads). (C and E) Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
augmented by IL-4, whereas levels of CD86 and CD40 were 
moderately up-regulated, as anticipated from cytometry (Fig. 
S3). As IL-4 shifts cellular resources away from the generation 
of molecules associated with proinflammatory cytokine and ni-
tric oxide (NO) production, we extracted by Venn diagrams a 
list of 112 genes (common; Fig. S5 B) that were significantly 
down-regulated by IL-4 in all conditions tested. A majority 
of these DEGs belonged to immunological-relevant pathways 
(Fig. S5 C, yellow delineation), among which cytokines, cy-
tokine receptors, and innate receptors were overrepresented. 
IL-1β and TNF, as well as TLR 1, 2, 6, and 7 and CD14 were 
down-modulated by IL-4 differentiation, confirming that IL-4 
induces a bias in the capacity of DCs to sense microbes and 
promote inflammation. In agreement with these observations, 
upstream regulators of majorly IL-4-down-regulated genes in-
cluded TNF, IL-6, and IL-1β. 
Up-regulated DEGs were compared with previously cu-
rated lists of IL-4-stimulated genes to identify novel IL-4-reg-
ulated genes. We restricted the comparison to the IPA and to a 
recently published analysis of the genes defining the core of al-
ternatively activated mouse and human macrophages (Martinez 
et al., 2013). We could only find 26 genes from our list that were 
present in either of these two databases (Fig. 5 C), confirm-
ing that despite the ontogenic proximity of macrophages and 
GM-CSF-derived DCs, IL-4 induces a great heterogeneity in </p>

<p>their respective gene expression program. When the IL-4-DC 
signature was compared with available monocyte/phagocyte 
gene signatures (Gautier et al., 2012), several genes defining the 
macrophage core signature were found to be down-regulated 
by IL-4, including CD64/FCG RI, emr1/F4/80, CD14, FCgRIII, 
Camk1, ARS, MR1, and the important macrophage differentia-
tion transcription factor MAFB, suggesting that IL-4 augments 
GM-CSF-dependent differentiation of monocytes into DCs, as 
suggested by up-regulation of the Batf3 and IRF4 transcription 
factors, which are involved in DC development, as well as in-
flammation (Murphy et al., 2013). In contrast, 14 DEGs specific 
for lung macrophages (out of 108 genes Gautier et al., 2012) were 
found up-regulated in IL-4-DCs (429 genes), including Rufy4, 
Net1, Ear2, Ear1, Ear10, Cldn1, Kynu, Chi3l3, Flt1, Cd69, 
Olr1, Siglec5, Cdh1, and Mtmr7, suggesting the existence of a 
lung-specific IL-4-dependent signature in these macrophages. 
Our analysis was primarily aimed at identifying mole-
cules controlling endocytosis and autophagy in DCs. Among 
the small number of up-regulated genes (six) annotated to mem-
brane traffic ontology, Rufy4, Gimap1, and Gimap5 stood out by 
their protein structural organization or anticipated function. The 
GTPases of the immunity-associated protein (GIM AP) family 
of putative GTPases function as nucleotide-regulated scaffolds 
on intracellular membranes (Saunders et al., 2010). RUFY4 
is predicted to have a FYVE domain in its C-terminal portion </p>

<p>Figure 4. Endogenous MHC II presentation in-
efficiently primes primary T cells but is strongly 
enhanced in matured IL-4-DCs. (A) Immature WT 
or DOG DCs were used to stimulate OT-I T cells. 
CFSE dilution was assayed after 3 d of co-culture 
(n = 3). (B and C) Immature or mature DOG DCs 
treated with (C) or without IL-4 (B) were used to 
stimulate OT-II cells. CFSE dilution in CD4 + T cells 
was assayed after 3 d of co-culture (top). WT DCs 
incubated with 10 µg/ml ovalbumin treated with 
or without IL-4 were used to stimulate OT-II cells 
as a control of exogenous antigen presentation 
(bottom). The data shown are from a single repre-
sentative experiment out of five repeats. (D) iDCs 
or mDCs generated in the presence or absence 
of IL-4 were harvested and incubated with freeze-
killed A20 (dA20) cells at a 1:4 ratio. After 8 h, 
the DCs were used to stimulate H30 T cells, and 
TCR stimulation was evaluated by IL-2 production 
from H30 cells. Mean and SEM from four indepen-
dent experiments are shown. </p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>Figure 5. In silico analysis of IL-4-driven genes in mouse bmDCs. (A) PCA from multiple samples of DCs treated or untreated with IL-4 and/or LPS. (B) 
Venn diagram representation of genes up-regulated by IL-4 stimulation more than twofold. (C) Clustered heat map representation (left) and <rs type="software">Voronto</rs> path-
way analysis (right) of IL-4-driven genes are shown. (bottom right) <rs type="software">IPA</rs> analysis of the top IL-4-induced genes organized by immune-relevant functions (fold 
change is indicated as Log Fc and genes mentioned in this paper are indicated in red), top biological functions, and upstream regulators are shown with 
the number of genes involved and associated p-value. A list of IL-4-induced genes found in common with previous studies from <rs type="software">IPA</rs> (Ing) or Martinez et al. 
(2013) (M2) is presented on the right. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
(Fig. 6 A and Fig. S5 D) that could mediate interaction with Pt-
dIns(3)P, separated by two coiled coil domains from its N-ter-
minal RUN domain (Fig. 6 A). RUFY4 is thus a particularly 
interesting candidate for our study because RUFY proteins have 
been shown to influence endosomal spatial distribution (Ivan et 
al., 2012) and the closest RUFY4 paralogue, FYCO1 (Fig. S5 
D), regulates autophagosome motility (Pankiv et al., 2010). </p>

<p>RUFY4 is induced in DCs differentiated 
in the presence of IL-4 both in vitro 
and in vivo </p>

<p>We next confirmed by quantitative PCR (qPCR) that Rufy4, 
Gimap1, and Gimap5 expression was induced by IL-4 in both 
mouse bmDCs and human MoDCs (Fig. 6 B). RUFY4 mRNA 
was induced 15-to 30-fold within the first days of IL-4 addition 
to the differentiation media (Fig. 6 C), whereas LPS treatment 
moderately decreased its expression. Given the difference in au-
tophagy levels among DCs and macrophages differentiated in 
the presence of IL-4, we monitored RUFY4 expression in these 
two cell types as well as in RAW macrophages grown in the 
presence of IL-4 (Fig. S4 B). Strikingly, RUFY4 mRNA could 
only be detected in IL-4-DCs and not in macrophages, nor after 
short-term IL-4 exposure, suggesting that RUFY4 expression, 
which coincides with increased autophagy, is linked to both 
long-term IL-4 exposure and GM-CSF-induced differentiation. 
Given this information, we explored in which physiolog-
ical situations RUFY4 expression could be detected in DCs. In 
addition to bridging innate and adaptive immunity, lung DCs 
can also mount Th2 immune responses to harmless allergens, 
such as house dust mite (HDM) allergen and, in this way, con-
tribute to immunopathology (Plantinga et al., 2013). Among 
DC subsets, CD11b + conventional DCs (cDCs) and MoDCs 
were identified as important players in the allergic cascade, with 
CD11b + cDCs being the principal subset inducing Th2 cell-me-
diated immunity characterized by the production of large quan-
tities of IL-4 (Plantinga et al., 2013). Repeated HDM allergen 
inhalations by mice, followed by lung DC subset isolation, were 
performed to analyze RUFY4 expression. Comparative qPCR 
performed on the different DC subsets isolated from control 
or allergic mice demonstrated that RUFY4 mRNA expression 
was strongly augmented in CD11b + cDCs of HDM-stimulated 
lungs (Fig. 6 D), whereas lower expression was detected in the 
CD103 + DC subset and allergic conditions did not augment 
RUFY4 mRNA expression in this cell type. Thus, in vivo, high 
RUFY4 expression correlates with Th2-related lung inflamma-
tion in the CD11b + DC subset, confirming its potential rele-
vance for DC-mediated physiopathology. </p>

<p>RUFY4, a novel positive regulator 
of autophagy </p>

<p>Ectopic expression of tagged RUFY4, GIM AP1, and GIM 
AP5 (Fig. 6 E) was performed before LC3 monitoring in cells 
treated with CQ for 4 h. RUFY4 expression promoted LC3II 
accumulation, contrasting with GIM AP1 and 5, which did not 
affect LC3 fate (Fig. 6 E and Fig. 7 A). We thus focused on 
RUFY4 expression and associated LC3 degradation by ex-
posing transfected HEK293 cells to autophagy-interfering 
drugs (Fig. 6 F). Wortmannin treatment clearly inhibited LC3 
processing and antagonized RUFY4 activity, suggesting that 
the putative PtdIns(3)P-binding FYVE domain of RUFY4 is 
functional. We generated a RUN-less and a FYVE-less form 
of RUFY4 (Fig. 6 A) to evaluate the importance of these do-</p>

<p>mains (Fig. 7, A and B). Enhanced LC3II accumulation was 
observed upon RUFY4 expression but not with the RUN-less 
or the FYVE-less mutants, suggesting that both domains are 
necessary to enhance autophagy. 
Ectopically expressed RUFY4 induced the aggregation 
of large membranous organelles, containing RUFY4 itself, and 
were either strongly positive for Stx17 (Fig. 6 G), the autopha-
gosomal SNA RE required for fusion with endosome/lysosome 
(Itakura et al., 2012; Takáts et al., 2013), or for LAMP1. 
EEA1-positive early endosomes remained unchanged by 
RUFY4 expression, which promoted the recruitment of Rab7 
on LAMP1-positive endosomes and their clustering together 
with Stx17-containing organelles (Fig. 6 H). Cotransfection of 
RUFY4 and LC3 confirmed that RUFY4-induced Stx17-posi-
tive organelles are autophagosomes that actively recruit LC3, 
a phenomenon strongly amplified by starvation and CQ treat-
ment (Fig. 6 I). The functionality of the RUN and FYVE do-
mains present in RUFY4 was examined by microscopy. In the 
absence of the RUN domain, little difference was found with 
control cells, confirming our biochemical data and indicating 
that the RUN domain is absolutely critical for RUFY4 func-
tion (Fig. 7, C and D). The FYVE-less mutant did not localize 
to autophagosomes, nor promote Stx17 and Rab7 recruitment, 
but still induced perinuclear localization of LAMP1-positive 
endosomes (Fig. 7, C and D). In many occurrences, high levels 
of FYVE-less expression also promoted the collapse of large 
tubular and vesicular membrane structures (Fig. 7 E), with no 
apparent codistribution with LAMP1 and RAB7. 
Given the active recruitment of RAB7 to RUFY4-posi-
tive organelles upon transfection, we investigated whether these 
two molecules could interact. Immunoprecipitation of trans-
fected myc-tagged RUFY4 followed by immunoblot detection 
demonstrated that RUFY4 is able to interact biochemically 
with Rab7 but not Rab9 (Fig. 7 F). In agreement with confocal 
microscopy, interaction with Rab7 was not detected with the 
functional mutants, confirming that RUFY4 mediates part, but 
not all, of its effects through RAB7. By electron microscopy, 
lysosome and late endosome clustering in response to RUFY4 
expression was detected in areas close to the nucleus (Fig. 8). 
These electron-dense organelles were found in juxtaposition to 
enlarged autophagosome-like organelles (Fig. 8), which were 
formed of an apparently continuous reticular network of dou-
ble membranes carrying ribosomes on their cytosolic side and 
sometimes round electron-dense structures internally, possi-
bly representing ferritin granules (Kishi-Itakura et al., 2014). 
The formation of these structures reached a paroxysm in 
FYVE-less mutant-transfected cells, in which giant reticulated 
"autophagosome-like" structures likely to be formed from ER 
membranes and containing different types of organelles and 
cytosolic material could be observed (Fig. 8). Thus, RUFY4 
exerts its function by regulating the membrane dynamic of au-
tophagosome growth, probably in liaison with Rab7 and other 
Rab activity. Moreover, RUFY4 also promotes the clustering 
and tethering of lysosomes, which could facilitate fusion with 
autophagosomes. Interestingly, this activity was not affected by 
nocodazole treatment (Fig. S4 D), suggesting that, differently 
from FYCO1, RUFY4 functions independently of the microtu-
bule network and its associated molecular motors. 
Production of PtdIns(3)P by the kinase Vps34 is key 
for autophagosome formation and recruitment of FYVE do-
main-bearing effectors, including Rubicon, DFcP1, and ALFY 
(Stein et al., 2003; Simonsen et al., 2004). The association of </p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>Figure 6. IL-4 drives the expression of Rufy4, a novel enhancer of autophagy. (A) Schematic representation of WT and RUN domain-less (ΔRUN) or FYVE 
domain-less (ΔFY VE) mutant of human Rufy4. Putative RUN/FYVE domains and coiled coil (CC) domains were calculated by using online prediction tools 
PRO SITE and COI LS server, respectively. (B) Induction of mouse GIM AP1, GIM AP5, and Rufy4 gene expression in IL-4-treated DCs was confirmed by qPCR 
(left). Rufy4 induction was also observed in human MoDCs, which was developed in the presence of GM-CSF and IL-4 (right). Mean and SEM from three 
independent experiments. (C) Time course of Rufy4 mRNA levels in mouse DCs generated in the presence or absence of IL-4. Rufy4 mRNA was monitored 
by qPCR at different days of culture (from day 0 to 6). The medium was replaced with fresh medium containing IL-4 on days 2 and 4. LPS was added on 
day 5 for 16 h. (D) Comparative qPCR for RUFY4 mRNA expression in different subsets of mouse lung DCs isolated from control and HDM-exposed ani-
mals. (C and D) The graphs show means ± SEM of triplicate determinations from one representative experiment. (E) HeLa cells were transfected with human </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
RUFY4 with PtdIns(3)P-containing organelles was monitored 
by confocal microscopy through its codistribution with over-
expressed GFP-2×FYVE, which specifically associates with 
PtdIns(3)P-enriched domains (Simonsen et al., 2004). In cells 
coexpressing the two proteins, a strong degree of colocaliza-
tion could be observed in most enlarged organelles (Fig. 9 A), 
confirming the enrichment in PtdIns(3)P of RUFY4-containing 
autophagosomes and late endosomes in vivo. WIPI2, an ortho-
logue of ATG18, is an effector of PtdIns(3)P and is recruited to 
early autophagosomal structures to promote the formation of 
LC3-positive autophagosomes (Fig. 9 B; Polson et al., 2010). 
Interestingly, like starvation, RUFY4 expression induced WIPI2 
punctae, which were found in direct vicinity with RUFY4-con-
taining endo/lysosomes (Fig. 9 C), confirming that RUFY4 pro-
motes autophagosome formation. 
Physiological RUFY4 expression together with appro-
priate intracellular signaling, such as mTOR inhibition, could 
thus considerably enhance the rate of autophagy flux, as ob-
served in IL-4-DCs. To verify this hypothesis, we established 
stable HeLa cell lines expressing near physiological lev-
els of a Cherry-tagged form of RUFY4. At steady state, the 
RUFY4-expressing line displayed no obvious difference in LC3 
processing nor endo/lysosome dynamic compared with control 
cells (Fig. 9 D). However, upon rapamycin treatment or a short 
2-h starvation period, enhanced LC3II processing and accumu-
lation of enlarged LAMP1-positive structure were observed in 
the presence of moderate levels of mCherry-RUFY4 (Fig. 9, 
D-F). Thus, similarly to IL-4-treated DCs, alteration of mTOR 
signaling together with enhanced RUFY4 expression consider-
ably increased autophagy and the endo/lysosomes dynamic. </p>

<p>RUFY4 silencing prevents Stx17 
association with autophagosomes </p>

<p>The impact of RUFY4 depletion in IL-4-DCs was monitored by 
examining the distribution of different autophagy markers and 
the processing of LC3 in the cells silenced for RUFY4 (Fig. 10). 
RUFY4 extinction was 70% complete 24 h after the introduction 
of relevant siRNA by nucleoporation, as established by qPCR 
and immunofluorescence (Fig. 10 A). RUFY4 is distributed in 
different subcellular locations, both in the cortical periphery 
of the cells and in more central locations, where it displayed a 
significant overlap with membrane-associated Stx17 (Pearson's 
coefficient r = 0.75 in confocal plane a) but not LAMP1 (r = 
0.42; Fig. 10 B). Upon Rufy4 silencing, late endosomes and 
lysosomes were more dispersed throughout the cell than their 
counterparts in IL-4-DCs (Fig. 10 A, arrowheads), whereas 
in the minority of activated control siRNA-treated IL-4-DCs 
displaying DAL ISs, Stx17 was found associated with P62 
and polyubiquitin (FK2) in punctate structures reminiscent of 
autophagosomes but distinct from LAMP1-positive vesicles </p>

<p>(Fig. 10 C). Stx17 association in clusters was only observed 
in IL-4-treated DCs, suggesting that enhanced autophago-
some formation driven by IL-4 and RUFY4 promotes a strong 
membrane recruitment of Stx17 (Fig. 10 D, arrowheads). This 
hypothesis was confirmed upon Rufy4 silencing, during which 
Stx17 association with membranes and punctae was lost, and its 
distribution appeared to be cytosolic (Fig. 10 C). LC3II/actin 
and LC3II/LC3I ratios were both decreased by Rufy4 silencing 
(Fig. 10 C), confirming the importance of RUFY4 to maintain 
active autophagy in IL-4-DCs. These observations are com-
pletely in line with the results obtained in transfected HeLa cells 
and suggest further that RUFY4 acts together with STX17 as a 
positive regulator of autophagy and late endosome clustering. </p>

<p>RUFY4 expression prevents B. abortus 
replication </p>

<p>Brucellosis is a zoonotic disease that results from direct contact 
with infected animals or ingestion of contaminated food prod-
ucts. B. abortus virulence is dependent on its ability to survive 
and replicate within host cells. Once internalized, B. abortus is 
found within a compartment, the B. abortus-containing vac-
uole (BCV) that transiently interacts with early endosomes 
(Salcedo et al., 2008). However, BCVs do not normally fuse 
with lysosomes and instead fuse with membranes of the ER to 
establish a vacuole suited for its replication. At late stages of 
the B. abortus intracellular cycle, a post-ER replication com-
partment is initiated at the ER and converts BCVs into vacuoles 
with autophagic features. Importantly, BCV conversion into 
these vacuoles completes the intracellular cycle of B. abortus 
and promotes cell to cell spread. Macrophages and placental 
trophoblasts are two key targets of B. abortus infection, but we 
have shown that HeLa cells and more importantly mouse DCs 
also support the replication of this pathogen in vitro (Salcedo 
et al., 2008). B. abortus is therefore ideal to test whether in-
creased classical autophagy flux and endosomal compartment 
reorganization upon DC differentiation in IL-4 or upon RUFY4 
expression could interfere with its replication. We first analyzed 
the survival of the WT B. abortus 2308 strain in murine bmDCs 
by enumerating the colony-forming units (CFUs) at different 
times after infection of GM-CSF and IL-4-DCs (Fig. 10 E and 
Fig. S4 E). As expected, we observed in GM-CSF DCs an in-
crease in the number of intracellular bacteria up to 48 h after 
inoculation, demonstrating that B. abortus is able to replicate 
within GM-CSF DCs. However, a completely different situa-
tion was observed with IL-4-DCs, which considerably reduced 
B. abortus replication at a late time of infection. As expected, 
this difference was not observed upon IL-4 addition at the time 
of infection (Fig. S4 E) and did not reflect the inability of IL-4-
DCs to internalize bacteria because equivalent CFU formation 
was found immediately after inoculation, indicating an equal </p>

<p>GIM AP1, GIM AP5, or Rufy4 expression vector for 24 h in duplicate before treatment with 50 µM CQ for the last 4 h. Cell lysates were immunoblotted for 
LC3 and actin. One representative blot is shown (left; n = 3). Relative LC3 accumulation (LC3II/actin) was determined by densitometry analysis (right). (F) 
HEK293 cells were transfected with Flag-tagged human Rufy4 construct for 24 h in the absence or presence of 50 nM wortmannin or 10 nM rapamycin for 
the last 4 h. To monitor the time course of LC3II accumulation, 50 µM CQ was added for each group as indicated. (G and H) HeLa cells were transfected 
to express WT myc-hRufy4 (24 h). After immunostaining for myc tag and the indicated antigens, the cells were analyzed by ICM. Insets are magnifications 
of boxed representative colocalization areas. Arrowheads indicate accumulation of RUFY4-positive organelles either codistributing with Stx17 (yellow) or 
LAMP1 (white). Pearson's coefficients (significant over 0.5) of colocalization among the indicated markers are plotted below the images. (I) HeLa cells were 
cotransfected with WT myc-hRufy4 and GFP-LC3 constructs (24 h), left untreated (top) or starved and treated with 50 µM CQ for the last 2 h (bottom). After 
pre-extraction in saponin, cells were fixed, permeabilized, and immunostained for myc tag and Stx17. Panels with enlarged views of the boxed regions 
in merged images are shown at the right. Pearson's coefficients (significant over 0.5) of colocalization among indicated markers are plotted next to the 
images. Mean and SEM from three experiments, n = 25. Bars: (G and I) 10 µm; (H) 25 µm. </p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>Figure 7. RUFY4 and mutant expression in HeLa cells. (A) HEK293 cells were transfected with myc-tagged WT or ΔRUN and ΔFYVE mutant constructs 
for 24 h and treated with CQ as indicated. An empty plasmid (mock) was used as a negative control. Cell lysates were analyzed by immunoblot for 
LC3, myc tag, and actin. (B) Graph shows LC3II quantification over actin, mean ± SEM of three independent experiments. Student's t test: *, P &lt; 0.05; 
**, P &lt; 0.01. (C-E) HeLa cells were transfected with myc-tagged WT, ΔRUN, or ΔFYVE mutant constructs for 24 h. Cells were subjected to pre-ex-
traction with saponin, before fixation and staining for myc, LAMP1, and STX17 (D), EEA1 (C), or Rab7 (E). Representative confocal images are shown. 
Pearson's coefficients (significant over 0.5) of colocalization among the indicated markers are plotted next to the images. Mean and SEM from three 
experiments, n = 25. Bars: (WT Rufy4) 10 µm; (ΔRUN and ΔFYVE) 25 µm. (D) Bar graphs indicate percentage of cells containing enlarged Stx17 + 
organelles among cells expressing (myc+) or not expressing (myc−) the exogenous Rufy4 proteins (n = 70). (F) Total lysate and immunoprecipitates of 
Myc-RUFY4 and mutants were submitted to immunoblot for myc, Rab7, and Rab9 detection. Rab7 was found to coimmunoprecipitate only with myc-
Rufy4 but not ΔRUN and ΔFYVE mutants. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
capacity to uptake B. abortus. To further evaluate the contribu-
tion of RUFY4 to prevent B. abortus replication, we transfected 
the different RUFY4 mutants in HeLa cells and monitored rep-
lication by microscopy at 6 h after infection. RUFY4 expression 
strongly prevented bacterial replication, whereas expression of 
the mutants did not (Fig. 10 F). In cells expressing the mutants, 
no difference in bacterial replication could be observed with 
control HeLa cells (Fig. 10 F), suggesting that the positive reg-
ulation of RUFY4 on autophagy is key in preventing infection. 
Therefore, IL-4 and RUFY4 have anti-intracellular bacteria 
activity, a situation that is likely to have a physiopathological 
relevance in different infection contexts. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Few studies have addressed how IL-4 changes DC functional 
specificity (Wells et al., 2005). Our work reveals that DCs dif-
ferentiated in the presence of IL-4 display considerable func-
tional differences with "traditional" GM-CSF-differentiated 
cells, both at the transcriptional level and, perhaps more impor-
tantly, at the posttranslational level. We showed that autophagy 
and associated functions are positively influenced by IL-4 with 
the consequence of augmenting the processing of endogenous 
antigens and their MHC II-restricted presentation, which is </p>

<p>normally decreased upon microbial sensing by DCs. Our data 
highlight that in addition to a reduction in mTOR activity, IL-4-
dependent transcriptional activation of several genes, including 
rufy4, is likely required for maintaining a relatively high basal 
autophagic flux in cells exposed to IL-4. Independently of its 
immunological relevance, our work reveals for the first time the 
implication of RUFY4 in augmenting autophagy flux, promot-
ing late endosomal and autophagosome membrane dynamic 
and preventing B. abortus replication in vitro. 
The ability of DCs to present the same antigens on both 
MHC I and MHC II molecules in the absence of costimulatory 
molecules could confer them with the ability to simultaneously 
anergize autoreactive CD8 + and CD4 + T cells in the periphery. 
Conversely, the reduction of autophagy-dependent MHC II pre-
sentation upon DC activation could focus presentation on cap-
tured exogenous antigens, while preventing untimely activation 
of autoreactive CD4 + T cells. The efficient autophagy-dependent 
MHC II presentation previously reported in human MoDCs 
(Schmid et al., 2007) can be explained by the presence of IL-4 
in the differentiation media and underlines the importance for 
monocytes of the nature of the cytokines and inflammatory me-
diators present at recruitment sites in vivo. Indeed, the presence 
or absence of Th2 cytokines will drive DC differentiation with 
relatively equivalent cell surface phenotypes but with very dif-
ferent cell biology and functional abilities, as observed in the 
lungs of asthmatic mice (Plantinga et al., 2013). 
The signal cascade responsible for IL-4 induction of au-
tophagy remains to be clarified, in particular in its capacity 
to prevent mTOR phosphorylation of ULK1 upon LPS de-
tection. Upon IL-4 ligation, IL-4Rα heterodimerizes with the 
gamma common chain (γc) and signals via the insulin recep-
tor substrate-1/2 (IRS-1/2) and STAT6 pathways (Heller et 
al., 2008). Although STAT6 is involved in IL-4-induced gene 
expression, IRS-1 signaling activates the type I PI3K pathway 
and subsequently the Akt/mTOR pathway, suggesting that IL-4, 
like LPS or other TLR agonists, could inhibit autophagy. How-
ever, Yamamoto et al. (2006) have reported that activation of 
IRS-2 leads to an autophagy-mediated clearance of accumu-
lated poly-Q proteins, which occurs despite the activation of 
mTOR. IRS-2 recruitment by IL-4Rα could promote autophagy 
and change the balance among different transduction cascades. 
It has also been recently reported that upon viral infection of 
DCs, a decrease of the intracellular concentration of free argi-
nine and a corresponding increase in citrulline occurs (Ravin-
dran et al., 2014), whereas the deacetylated tRNA-sensing 
eIF2α kinase GCN2 was proposed to control autophagy and to 
regulate DC function. As these results were obtained with cells 
differentiated with IL-4, it is tempting to speculate that mTOR 
reprogramming and autophagy induction could be linked to ar-
ginase-1 expression, which by decreasing cytosolic amino acids 
concentration could influence mTOR activity. 
The Rufy4 gene is located on chromosome 1 in mouse 
(Chr 2 in human), and its promotor region contains several po-
tential STAT6 consensus binding sites (TRA NSFAC database). 
Rufy4 is immediately adjacent to the CXCR2 gene, which is also 
strongly up-regulated by IL-4 treatment (Fig. 5 C), indicating 
that this area of the genome is transcriptionally active upon GM-
CSF-and IL-4-induced differentiation. Rufy4 has appeared rel-
atively late in evolution (reptile) and is clearly not part of the 
core autophagy machinery characterized in yeast (Deretic et al., 
2013). Together with Rab7, RUFY4 is likely part of a regulatory 
module required for the fine tuning of autophagy in specific im-</p>

<p>Figure 8. Electron microscopy analysis of Rufy4-overexpressing HeLa 
cells. HeLa cells were transfected with human Rufy4 or ΔFY VE Rufy4 con-
struct or with mock plasmid as control and were fixed with glutaraldehyde. 
Subcellular structures were analyzed by conventional electron microscopy. 
Boxed area is magnified on the right. Arrowheads indicate zones of lyso-
some clustering and tethering. Bars, 500 nm. </p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>Figure 9. Rufy4 colocalizes with PtdIns(3)P-enriched domains and promotes the formation of WIPI2 punctae. (A) HeLa cells were cotransfected with 
GFP-2×FYVE and mCherry-tagged human Rufy4 constructs for 24 h. The cells were fixed without permeabilization, and the cellular localization of 
these fluorescent proteins was monitored by confocal microscopy. (B) HeLa cells were transfected with GFP-tagged WIPI2 and monitored by confocal 
microscope. Punctate WIPI2 formation was observed upon autophagy induction by either starvation or 10 nM rapamycin treatment. (C) HeLa cells 
were cotransfected with GFP-tagged WIPI2 and control (top) or myc-tagged Rufy4 (bottom) constructs for 24 h. The cells were permeabilized with 
saponin-containing buffer and then stained for LAMP1. Representative ICM images are shown. (D) mCherry-tagged human Rufy4 constructs were stably 
transfected to HeLa cells. Bulk HeLa/mCherry-Rufy4 lines express moderate amounts of Rufy4, as shown by FACS analysis (bottom). mCherry-Rufy4-
expressing cells were cultured in the absence or presence of 10 nM rapamycin for 6 h before monitoring LC3II accumulation; 50 µM CQ was added 
as indicated. The cell lysates were immunoblotted with LC3 and actin antibodies (top left). Relative accumulation of the LC3II form was determined 
over actin levels by densitometry analysis (right). A single representative experiment is presented out of three repeats. (E and F) Immunofluorescence 
microscopy shows that after a short 2-h starvation in HBSS, accumulation of enlarged LAMP1-positive structures is promoted in two independent stably 
transfected clones expressing low levels of mCherry-Rufy4 (F) but not in the mock-transfected control cells (E). (A, C, and F) Insets are magnifications of 
boxed representative colocalization areas. Bars, 10 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 10. RUFY4 silencing influences STX17 distribution and inhibits autophagy and B. abortus replication. (A) IL-4-DCs treated with control (siIrr, top) 
or Rufy4-specific siRNA (siRUFY4, bottom) were grown in the presence of IL-4 and immunostained with anti-Rufy4 and anti-LAMP1 antibodies. Represen-
tative single confocal planes are shown. Late endosome clustering is indicated by arrowheads. The bar graph shows Rufy4 mRNA levels in control and 
Rufy4-silenced cells quantified by qPCR (means ± SEM of triplicate determinations from one representative experiment). (B) Control or Rufy4-silenced DCs 
were immunostained for Rufy4, LAMP1, and STX17. Two confocal imaging planes of the same cell are shown. (C) siIrr (left) and siRUFY4 (right) DCs were 
immunostained for STX17, p62, FK2, and LAMP1. Representative panels with enlarged views of the boxed region are shown. (bottom left) Graphical 
representation of the percentage of cells containing STX17-positive organelles in siRNA-treated DCs is shown. Bars show mean ± SEM of two independent 
experiments (n &gt; 50); Student's t test: **, P &lt; 0.01. (bottom right) Quantitative representation of LC3II/actin and LC3II/LCI protein ratios detected by </p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>mune cells. RUFY4 overexpression increases autophagic flux, 
probably by stimulating both autophagosome generation and fa-
cilitating tethering with lysosomes. The association of RUFY4 
with Rab7 and PtdIns(3)P-containing organelles is very similar 
to what is observed with Rubicon, whose overexpression leads 
to abnormal morphology of late endosomes. Rubicon mediates 
the simultaneous interaction between the Beclin 1-Vps34 and 
Rab7 (Tabata et al., 2010) and negatively regulates autophago-
some and late endosome fusion (Matsunaga et al., 2009). Thus, 
Rufy4 and Rubicon could compete for the same effectors, such 
as Rab7, and have opposite effects for the control of autophagy. 
Our in vitro experimental conditions mimic the differentia-
tion in DCs of monocytes exposed or not to IL-4 for a relatively 
long period. Cells grown in these conditions initiate transcription 
programs linked to their long-term functional differentiation and 
not to a rapid response to a cytokine stimulus. This difference 
is also illustrated by the strong expression of RUFY4 mRNA in 
lung macrophages and not in other tissue-resident macrophages 
or those differentiated in vitro with M-CSF. (Gautier et al., 2012), 
suggesting that long-term exposure to a particular combination 
of cytokines in a given tissue environment contextualizes the 
basal cellular functions of resident immunocytes (Ginhoux and 
Jung, 2014). This situation could increase resistance to intracel-
lular bacterial infection at potential sites of entry, as suggested by 
the relative protection conferred by RUFY4 against B. abortus 
infection. The reason of this inhibition remains to be established; 
however, the rapid kinetics of bacterial clearance suggests that 
exacerbated xenophagy could be key for this process. Our obser-
vations suggest the existence of a need for enhanced autophagy 
and endosome traffic in the frame of Th2 immune responses, 
including the MHC II presentation of cytosolic antigens and the 
regulation of metabolic homeostasis. Whether a deregulation of 
autophagy could contribute to the exacerbation of allergic dis-
eases, such as asthma, that are critically dependent on IL-4 and 
DCs will have to be investigated in the future. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Mice </p>

<p>Male C57BL/6 or CB6F1 mice 7-8 wk old were purchased from Charles 
River. C57BL/6J ATG5 flox/flox /CD11c-Cre (Lee et al., 2010) mice were 
obtained from A. Iwasaki (Yale School of Medicine, New Haven, CT). 
C57BL/6J MyD88/TRIF −/− mice were obtained from L. Alexopoulou 
(CIML, Marseille, France). C57BL/6JJcl mice transgenic for GFP-LC3 
under the MAP1 promotor were obtained from the RIK EN depository. 
C57BL/6J RAG2 −/− TCR transgenics OT-I and OT-II mice were bred 
at the CIML animal facilities. C57BL/6J CD11c.DOG (DTR-OVA-
eGFP) mice were from N. Garbi (DKFZ, Heidelberg, Germany). Ex-
periments were conducted in accordance with institutional guidelines 
for animal care and use. Protocols have been approved by the French 
Provence ethical committee (number 04/2005). </p>

<p>Cell culture </p>

<p>bmDCs were cultured as described previously (Lelouard et al., 2002). 
IL-4 (PeproTech) at 20 ng/ml was used from day 2 of DC culture on-
ward, where indicated. Bone marrow-derived macrophages and RAW 
cells were cultured as described previously (Harris et al., 2007), and 30 
ng/ml IL-4 was added for the indicated times. HeLa and HEK293 cells 
were maintained in DMEM (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% fetal 
calf serum (Hyclone, PER BIO), at 37°C and 5% CO 2 . IL-12 production 
was determined by ELI SA (eBioscience). Chemicals were used at the 
following concentrations: 10-50 nM rapamycin, 5 mM 3-MA, 100 ng/ 
ml LPS, 50 µM CQ, and 0.1 µg/ml puromycin (all from Sigma-Al-
drich). Lung DCs were purified from C57BL/6 mice exposed or not to 
HDM as described by Plantinga et al. (2013). </p>

<p>Antigen presentation experiments </p>

<p>Primary T cells were isolated from spleen and lymph nodes by mag-
netic depletion (Invitrogen), labeled with 2 µM CFSE where indicated, 
and co-cultured with 5,000 DCs at a 4:1 (T/DC) ratio. For T cell hybrid-
oma activation by endogenous presentation, transfected DCs were fixed 
mildly (0.25% PFA, 2 min, RT) and cultured at 2:1 (T/DC) ratio with 
DO11 or H30 T cells for 24 h. For exogenous presentation experiments, 
DCs were harvested and plated (at 1:4 DC/A20 ratio) with freeze-killed 
A20 cells (I-Eα-positive B cell line, source of Ea52-68 peptide) or with 
ovalbumin immune complexes (0.5 µg/ml Ova, 2 µg/ml rabbit anti-Ova 
final) and cultured at 2:1 (T/DC) ratio with DO11 (Ova 329-337) on 
I-A d -specific or H30 (Ea52-68) on I-A b -specific T cells for 24 h. IL-2 
production was determined by ELI SA (eBioscience). </p>

<p>Immunodetection and immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>25-50 µg Triton X-100 soluble material or total protein from 5 × 10 4 
cells (lysed directly in 2× reducing sample buffer, boiled, and homog-
enized using a 26-G needle) was separated by 3-15% gradient or 12% 
SDS-PAGE before immunoblotting and chemiluminescence detection 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific). Antibodies used in this study were rab-
bit polyclonal anti-p62, -phospho-S6, -S6, -p70S6k1, -4EBP1, and 
-phospho-Ulk1 (Ser 757) all from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.; 
and anti-Ulk1 (H240) and -ATG5 (N terminus) from Sigma-Aldrich. 
Mouse monoclonal anti-phospho-p70S6K1 (49D7), -phospho-4EBP1 
(236B4), -myc (9B11 and 71D10), and -Stx17 (I-14) were all from 
Cell Signaling Technology; and anti-actin (AC-15) and -Rab7 were 
from Sigma-Aldrich. Other mouse monoclonal antibodies were an-
ti-LC3 (2G6; nanoTools), -NBR1 (6B11; AbD Serotec), -polyubiquitin 
(FK2; Biomol), -SII NFEKL (IF10.2.2), -GFP (JL-8; Takara Bio Inc.), 
-CD11c (N418), and -puromycin (12D10; Schmidt et al., 2009); and 
brilliant violet 421 anti-LAMP1 (H4A3; BioLegend) and -EEA1 (BD). 
Rabbit polyclonal antibodies against AMB RA1 and phospho-AMB 
RA1 (ser52) were from EMD Millipore. Secondary antibodies were 
from Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Inc., Molecular Probes, 
and Cell Signaling Technology. For immunofluorescence, cells on cov-
erslips were fixed with 3.5% PFA and permeabilized with 0.1% Triton 
X-100. Where indicated, cells were permeabilized (0.2% Triton X-100, 
5 min, on ice) before fixation (3.5% PFA), alternatively pre-extracted </p>

<p>immunoblot in extracts from the same siRNA-treated cells processed for immunofluorescence (one representative experiment, n = 3). (D) Confocal immuno-
fluorescence of bmDCs generated in the presence or absence of IL-4 and stained for STX17, which accumulates in large punctate structures (arrowheads). 
(E) bmDCs were grown in the presence or absence of IL-4 and infected for different time points with B. abortus. Bar graph indicates bacteria replication 
assessed by CFUs; Student's t test: **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.001. Error bars indicate SEM (n &gt; 3). (F) HeLa cells were transfected with WT myc-hRufy4 or 
the myc-tagged mutants ΔRUN and ΔFY VE (24 h) and infected with B. abortus for 3 h. Confocal microscopy for B. abortus LPS (arrowheads), myc, and 
LAMP1 was performed (left) and quantified for infection levels (right). Graphs show the percentage of cells containing B. abortus among cells expressing 
(myc+) or not (myc−) RUFY4 constructs (top) and mean number of bacteria per cell (bottom). B. abortus-containing cells were assigned to one of the fol-
lowing categories: cells containing one bacterium, cells containing two bacteria, or cells containing more than two bacteria. n = 50 from two independent 
experiments; Student's t test: *, P &lt; 0.05. Error bars indicate SEM. Bars: (A and D) 25 µm; (B) 5 µm; (C) 7.5 µm; (F, WT) 10 µm; (F, mutants) 2 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
with 0.02% saponin in PBS (30 s, RT), fixed with 3.5% PFA (15 min, 
RT), and permeabilized with 0.1% Triton X-100 (15 min, RT) or cold 
methanol permeabilized for 2 min at −20°C after PFA fixation. Immu-
nofluorescence and confocal microscopy were performed at 20°C with 
a LSM580 (Carl Zeiss) or a TCS SPX5 (Leica) using a 40× and 63× 
objective and accompanying imaging software. Fluorochrome or bio-
tin directly coupled antibodies for FACS were CD8α (RM2201) from 
Invitrogen; I-A/I-E (M5/114.15.2), CD80 (16-10A1), CD4 (RM4-5), 
and DEC205 (205yekta) from eBioscience; and CD11c (N418), CD86 
(GL-1), CD40 (HM40-3), and H-2K b (HB-176) from BD. Anti-K b / 
SL8 25D1.16 (Porgador et al., 1997) was purified and fluorochrome 
coupled using the Alexa Fluor 647 protein labeling kit (Invitrogen). 
Data were acquired on a FACS LSR II or Canto II (BD) and analyzed 
using FlowJo (Tree Star). For immunoprecipitation, 0.4 × 10 6 HeLa 
cells were transfected with mock or the Myc-tagged hRUFY4 (WT 
and mutants) plasmids for 24 h. The cells were then lysed (RIPA) and 
subjected to immunoprecipitation using the Cross-link Magnetic IP/ 
Co-IP kit with anti-Myc (mouse IgG2a 9B11, 5 µg; Thermo Fisher Sci-
entific). Immunoprecipitates and input control were blotted with rabbit 
anti-Rab7 (D95F2; Cell Signaling Technologies) and mouse IgG1 an-
ti-Rab9 (Thermo Fisher Scientific). </p>

<p>DAL IS scoring </p>

<p>Cells on coverslips were pre-extracted with cold 0.1% Triton-X for 2 
min at 4°C before fixation with 3.5% PFA. Detection was performed 
with an anti-P62 (SQTM1; sc-25575; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, 
Inc.) and anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor A568 (A11011; Molecular Probes), 
mounted with Prolong Gold with DAPI (P-36931; Life Technologies). 
DAL IS quantification was performed by mosaic image acquisition with 
an Axioplan video microscope (Carl Zeiss). Images were then analyzed 
using a multiparameter protocol based on the Physiology Analyst mod-
ule of ASS AY Builder software (Carl Zeiss). This protocol allows the 
automatic recognition and characterization of the cell population and 
intensities, areas, and spot number in the cellular regions. </p>

<p>cDNA cloning, in vitro transcription, and gene transduction or 
silencing </p>

<p>All plasmids were generated using standard cloning, PCR, and fu-
sion PCR techniques and based on pcDNA3.1 backbone (Invitrogen). 
The H-2K b cDNA (gift from F. Momburg, DKFZ) was inserted into 
pcDNA3.1. The myc-tagged human GIM AP1 and GIM AP5 inserted 
in pCANmyc1 were gifts from G. Butcher (The Babraham Institute, 
Cambridge, England, UK). A plasmid for GFP-2OP in vitro transcrip-
tion was generated using eGFP cloned in pcDNA/Zeo, as described 
previously (Wenger et al., 2012). 4 × 10 6 DCs were transfected with 20 
µg mRNA using the mouse DC nucleofection kit (Amaxa). Total mRNA 
was purified using the RNeasy Mini kit (QIA GEN), and cDNAs were 
synthesized by SuperScript II system (Invitrogen) according to the man-
ufacturers' instruction. Mouse and human Rufy4 cDNA was amplified 
by nested-PCR using cDNA from MoDCs as template and then cloned 
to pcDNA3.1 vector with tagging with Flag (C terminus), myc (N ter-
minus), or mCherry (N terminus). The ΔRUN and ΔFY VE domain 
mutants were obtained by PCR. Human WIPI2 cDNA was also cloned 
from human MoDC cDNA by conventional PCR method and then fused 
to the GFP gene at its N terminus in the pcDNA3.1 vector. The plasmid 
DNAs were introduced to the cell lines with use of JetPrime regent 
(Polyplus). ONE-TAR GET plus siRNA targeting Rufy4 and ONE-TAR 
GETING plus nontargeting siRNA (Thermo Fisher Scientific) were 
used as specific Rufy4 siRNA and as control siRNA, respectively. 4 × 
10 6 IL-4-treated bmDCs were transfected at day 4 with 5 µM siRNA 
using the Nucleofector (Amaxa) according to the manufacturer's in-
structions. Cells were collected 48 h after transfection and analyzed. </p>

<p>qPCR </p>

<p>Total RNAs were extracted and purified using the RNeasy Mini kit. 100 
ng to 1 µg total RNA was subjected to reverse transcription using Super-
Script II. Each gene transcript was quantified by SYBR Green method 
with 7500Fast (Applied Biosystems). The relative amount of each tran-
script was determined by normalizing to internal housekeeping gene 
expression. Primer sets were as follows: mouse Rufy4, 5′-TGG CCCCT 
GGACA CTGCA TA-3′ and 5′-AGA GCAGG CGTGG CAAAC CA-3′; 
human Rufy4, 5′-TGC TCTCA ATGGG GTGGC CT-3′ and 5′-GGG 
TTTGG GTGGA ACTGG AGCA-3′; mouse GIM AP1, 5′-ATG CAGAG 
GCGCA CCAGG TT-3′ and 5′-TGG CCACA CCCAG GAAGA CA-3′; 
mouse cyclophilin B, 5′-ATG TGGTT TTCGG CAAAG TT-3′ and 5′-
TGA CATCC TTCAG TGGCT TG-3′; mouse GAP DH, 5′-GGG TGTGA 
ACCAC GAGAA ATA-3′ and 5′-CTT CCACA ATGCC AAAGT TGT-3′; 
and human GAP DH, 5′-CAA TGACC CCTTC ATTGA CC-3′ and 5′-
GAC AAGCT TCCCG TTCTC AG-3′. </p>

<p>Microarray and bioinformatics analyses </p>

<p>Equal amounts of RNA extract (500 ng) from each replicate were am-
plified and Cy3 labeled using the Low Input Quick Amp Labeling kit 
(Agilent Technologies). Hybridizations were performed according to 
the manufacturer's instructions for One-Color Microarray-Based Gene 
Expression Analysis using Whole Mouse Genome GE 4 × 44K v2 mi-
croarrays (Agilent Technologies). Images were scanned on an Agilent 
G2565AA microarray scanner, and raw images were quantified using the 
<rs id="software-13" type="software">Agilent Feature Extraction</rs> <rs corresp="#software-13" type="version-number">10.5.1.1</rs> software and the GE1_105_Dec08 
protocol. The signal intensity was aligned and normalized between 
microarrays by centering the median of the signal distribution using 
<rs id="software-14" type="software">BRB-ArrayTools</rs> <rs corresp="#software-14" type="version-number">v3.8.1</rs>. The microarray data have been submitted to 
the GEO database and can be accessed under accession no. GSE56929. 
Raw gene expression data obtained from the <rs type="software">Agilent Feature Extraction</rs> 
software were background corrected using the "normexp" method and 
quantile normalized, using the limma package through <rs type="software">Bioconductor</rs> in 
the <rs id="software-17" type="software">R</rs> statistical environment (<rs corresp="#software-17" type="version-number">version 2.15.0</rs>). Quality control of the ex-
pression data was assessed by boxplots of raw expression data, density 
plots of the normalized data, and calculation of the Pearson's correla-
tion coefficients between arrays. The <rs type="software">Cluster</rs> and <rs type="software">Treeview</rs> softwares 
were used to classify samples according to the similarity of their gene 
expression profiles as assessed by hierarchical clustering with average 
linkage as a clustering method and Pearson correlation as a metric 
distance, considering the genes having a minimal fold change of two 
across all samples. PCA was computed with the <rs type="software">MeV</rs> software across 
all probes, using the median-centered method and 10 neighbors for 
KNN imputation. The 3D plot was generated using the scatterplot3D 
package in the R statistical environment. Genes differentially expressed 
between each sample in a statistically significant manner were selected 
as having a fold change &gt;2× and an FDR (Benjamini-Hochberg correc-
tion) &lt;0.1 after empirical Bayes processing using the limma package. 
These gene lists were submitted to <rs type="software">Venn</rs> software for comparisons or 
uploaded into <rs type="software">IPA</rs> and <rs id="software-23" type="software">Voronto</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-23" type="creator">Santamaría and Pierre</rs>, 2012) to test for 
significant enrichment of functional annotations. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data representing multiple experiments are displayed as mean ± SEM. 
Paired Student's t test was used where indicated. </p>

<p>Bacterial infection and replication assays </p>

<p>Infections were performed with the smooth virulent B. abortus strain 
2308 at a multiplicity of infection of 20:1 for all experiments. Bacteria 
were centrifuged onto bmDCs or HeLa at 400 g for 10 min at 4°C and 
then incubated for 30 min at 37°C with 5% CO 2 atmosphere. Cells 
were gently washed twice with medium and then incubated for 1 h in </p>

<p>RUFY4 positively regulates autophagy • Terawaki et al. </p>



<p>medium supplemented with 100 µg/ml streptomycin to kill extracellu-
lar bacteria. Thereafter, the antibiotic concentration was decreased to 
20 µg/ml. Control samples were always performed by incubating cells 
with media only and following the exact same procedure for infection. 
To monitor bacterial intracellular survival, infected cells were lysed 
with 0.1% Triton X-100 in H 2 O and serial dilutions plated onto TSB 
agar to enumerated CFUs. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material </p>

<p>Fig. S1 shows comparative electron micrographs of GM-CSF-and 
IL-4-differentiated and LPS-activated DCs. Fig. S2 shows DAL IS 
formation in DCs exposed to different conditions. Fig. S3 shows that 
IL-4-induced signaling augments mitophagy and decreases mitochon-
drial ROS in DCs. Fig. S4 shows the consequences on macrophages of 
short-term IL-4 treatment and long-term differentiation. Fig. S5 shows 
in silico analysis of genes down-modulated by IL-4 differentiation. 
Table S1 is a list of up-regulated genes during IL-4-induced DC differ-
entiation. Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jcb. 
org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201501059/DC1. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The laboratory is supported by EU FP 7 Collaborative Project SYB ARIS 
grant agreement number 242220; the Equipe labelisée Ligue Natio-
nale Contre le Cancer; Agence Nationale de la Recherche grants 
ANR 10-BLAN-1236, ANR 10-BLAN-1308, ANR-12-BSV2-0025-01, 
and ANR-FCT 12-ISV3-0002-01; DCBiol Labex ANR-11-LAB EX-0043 
grant ANR-10-IDEX-0001-02 PSL*, and A*MID EX project ANR-11-
IDEX-0001-02 funded by the "Investissements d'Avenir" French gov-
ernment program. S. Terawaki is a Uehara Memorial Foundation 
fellow. S. Terawaki and F. Prete are Fondation de la Recherche Médi-
cale (FRM) fellows. T. Wenger is a von Humboldt foundation and Insti-
tut National du Cancer fellow. T.-P. Vu Manh was supported by the 
PhylogenDC ANR grant. We acknowledge support from no. ANR-10-
INBS-04-01 France Bio Imaging for advanced microscopy. Part of the 
research was also supported by FCT through the Institute for Biomedi-
cine-iBiMED contract UID/BIM/04501/2013 and PTDC/ 
IMI-IMU/3615/2014. </p>

<p>The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 15 January 2015 
Accepted: 18 August 2015 </p>



<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>