<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4727475" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Context: Despite the ongoing advances in surgical procedures and promising progress in bioengineering techniques, auricular 
reconstruction remains a significant challenge in plastic surgery. There are different causes for acquired auricular defects, including 
trauma, tumor ablation and burns. The management options for upper, middle and lower third auricular defects are briefly reviewed in 
the current paper. 
Evidence Acquisition: Original research papers investigating the plastic surgeons, otolaryngologists and maxillofacial surgeons in 
approaching the complicated issue of auricular reconstruction published from January 1995 to December 2014 were aggregated and used 
in the current study. 
Results: Utilizing autologous stem cell populations to treat craniofacial defects is a promising field of ongoing investigations. Studies 
show that cartilage stem/progenitor cells (CSPCs) are highly chondrogenic and can produce elastic reconstructive material with long-term 
tissue restoration. 
Conclusions: Auricular reconstruction surgery is a challenging plastic procedure that requires great expertise and expert knowledge 
of the various techniques available. Novel techniques in the fields of reconstructive bioengineering and regenerative medicine are 
promising but further research is required before widespread clinical application. </p>

<p>Ebrahimi A et al. </p>

<p>Trauma Mon. 2015;20(4):e28202 </p>

<p>
mentioned in an ancient Indian text (12). Currently, the 
ever-growing fields of biotechnology and bioengineer-
ing play a crucial role in introduction of novel therapeu-
tic options in ear reconstructive surgery; investigations 
on culturing and bioengineering ear cartilage are prom-
ising (13-16). The current article briefly reviewed recon-
structive surgery of the acquired external ear defects. The 
provided information may aid plastic surgeons, otolar-
yngologists and maxillofacial surgeons to approach the 
complicated issue of auricular reconstruction. </p>

<p>2. Evidence Acquisition </p>

<p>Original research papers investigating the plastic sur-
geons, otolaryngologists and maxillofacial surgeons in ap-
proaching the complicated issue of auricular reconstruc-
tion published from January 1995 to December 2014 were 
aggregated, coded, and used in the current study. The fol-
lowing libraries and online sources were searched: PubMed, 
MEDLINE, Wiley, EMBASE, ISI Web of Knowledge and Scopus. 
The terminologies that were used to identify these ar-
ticles included: plastic surgery, auricular defects, recon-
structions, ear trauma, bioengineering, facial surgery. The 
articles obtained from different databases into the bib-
liographic software package <rs type="software">EndNote</rs> were imported and 
merged into one complete database. Two review authors 
independently assessed the titles and abstracts of all ar-
ticles found by the searching method outlined above. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Acute Ear Trauma </p>

<p>Appropriate management of the acutely traumatized ear 
is of vital importance and improper treatment could lead 
to a cauliflower ear following auricular hematoma. Man-
agement of cauliflower ear is a challenging reconstructive 
procedure and requires reshaping of the auricle after exci-
sion of the deformed cartilage (17, 18). Moreover, the blunt-
ly traumatized auricle is vulnerable to infection, necrosis, 
and contracture. There was no consensus on the evidence-
based management of acute auricular hematoma and 
systematic reviews of the literature highlighted the need 
for further research before recommending the optimal 
management strategies (19). The current management 
of auricular hematoma mainly depends on its size; while 
smaller hematomas should be aspirated; larger ones re-
quire open surgical drainage. Further studies are required 
to elucidate the efficacy of post-drainage interventions 
including splinting or bandaging (19, 20). New techniques 
using fibrin glue and an 18-gauge catheter with a compres-
sion dressing are recently proposed. Cost-effectiveness 
and efficacy of these management options remain to be 
confirmed by further studies (20, 21).Use of local flaps in 
soft tissue defects, initial realigning of the helical rim and 
anatomical repair of ear lacerations should be considered 
in management of acute ear trauma. In cases of ear ampu-</p>

<p>tation, staged reconstruction or replantation techniques 
should be used (22). </p>

<p>3.2. Basic Surgical Principles and Classification of 
Auricular Defects </p>

<p>Based on the involved tissue, auricular defects are cat-
egorized into cutaneous and cutaneous-cartilaginous 
defects (23). Primary closure is usually applicable in cases 
of medial auricular cutaneous defects due to malleable 
nature of the tissues involved. However, primary closure 
is not usually possible for lateral cutaneous defects and 
skin grafts from the medial surface or the contralateral 
postauricular area are usually required (24-26). 
Lack of supporting structure and sophisticated anatomi-
cal alterations of the external ear make cutaneous-carti-
laginous defects more challenging to deal with. Depend-
ing on the extent of damage, primary repair, local flaps, 
skin grafts and regional flaps are used in the reconstruc-
tive procedures (27). A successful auricular reconstruction 
with satisfactory aesthetic results depends heavily on func-
tional vascular supplies and decreased tension at the site 
of reconstruction to ensure tissue vitality. Currently, tem-
poroparietal fascia flaps are widely used in regional flaps 
that provide a well-vascularized environment (28). Small 
defects could be reconstructed by excision and primary 
closure if decreased auricular height could be appropri-
ately managed to avoid cupping of external ear structures 
(3). Use of various alternative flaps including superior 
pedicle postauricular chondrocutaneous flaps and autolo-
gous contralateral conchal cartilage grafts are promising 
and are topics of ongoing research (29, 30). Reconstruc-
tion of the tragus can also be achieved with a preauricular 
cutaneous flap transposed to the defect and folded onto it. 
The flap can be based either inferiorly or superiorly. </p>

<p>3.3. The Upper Third Auricular Defects </p>

<p>There are several techniques to reconstruct the upper 
third defects; factors such as size of the defect and avail-
ability of skin grafts mainly determine the superior op-
tions in each case (31, 32). Fortunately, minor defects cause 
less cosmetic issues and hair may cover the site. For upper 
auricle defects, smaller than 2.8 cm, the helical advance-
ment technique is advantageous and complications are 
rare (33). A variation of this flap, which is detached from 
the anterior and posterior helical surfaces, maximizes 
mobility at the cost of threatening tissue viability (34). In 
another variation, first described by Anita and Buch more 
than forty years ago, flap viability is not jeopardized but 
movement is considerably limited as the posterior skin 
remains intact (35). Large upper third defects are often 
managed by contralateral cartilage grafts and postau-
ricular skin flaps and in case of insufficient graft donor 
sources, use of compound pedicle flaps is recommended 
(26, 36). Preauricular flaps, designed at the junction of 
the ear and face with the pedicle based superiorly or infe-
riorly, may cover some small antihelical defects. </p>

<p>Ebrahimi A et al. </p>



<p>Trauma Mon. 2015;20(4):e28202 </p>

<p>3.4. The Middle Third Auricular Defects </p>

<p>In contrast to the upper third auricle, middle auricular 
defects do not substantially disturb functions like support 
of eyeglasses. However, the retroauricular skin is thinner 
and the deformed structures are more visible (37). Based 
on the same principles, chondrocutaneous advancement 
flaps could be also used in approaching middle third au-
ricular defects (35). Good cosmetic results are reported by 
using superior pedicle postauricular chondrocutaneous 
flaps in management of full-thickness upper and middle 
third auricular defects (29). Reduced vertical height is a 
major problem if small middle third defects are repaired 
after turning the traumatized site into a wedge. Retroau-
ricular composite flaps and autogenous cartilage harvest-
ed from conchal cartilage are used to reconstruct larger 
defects. Use of small local flaps raised from the lobule is an 
effective alternative in patients with abundant lobular tis-
sue; recent studies highlight the simplicity and minimal 
anatomical deformity of this technique (38). </p>

<p>3.5. Lower Third Auricular Defects </p>

<p>Lower third auricular structures including lobule are 
more mobile and flexible; therefore, reconstruction of 
the defects at these locations is often less challenging. In 
addition, as mentioned earlier the lobule can act as a po-
tential source of advancement flaps. Various techniques 
are introduced in the literature to address traumatized 
earlobes. In cases of full-thickness major trauma that in-
volve a great proportion of the lobule, more burdensome 
techniques, using cartilage grafting, are often required. 
One famous technique is the double flap proposed by 
Preaux and modified by Brent who recommended the 
use of bipedicle chondrocutaneous flaps and contralat-
eral cartilage grafts (39, 40). Davis introduced another 
approach based on a mastoid flap for anterior earlobe 
reconstruction and a posterior flap turned over from the 
anterior helix surface (41). More easily implemented tech-
niques are also gaining acceptance and reconstruction 
of ear lobule through a one-stage procedure is reported 
with favorable aesthetic and symmetric outcomes. These 
techniques include the use of the Limberg-flap, a double-
over skin flap, two superiorly based flaps rotated towards 
the middle or a bilobed flap with an anterior base (42-44). </p>

<p>3.6. Large Defects of the Auricle </p>

<p>Reconstruction of defects larger than one-third auricu-
lar is a daunting task and requires great expertise. Larger 
ear defects present unique and complex challenges to 
plastic surgeons due to the delicate and intricate archi-
tecture of external ear structure that is difficult to dupli-
cate surgically. Despite complexities during reproduction 
of the intricate auricular anatomy, detailed information 
on landmarks, size and position could help the surgeon 
achieve satisfactory outcomes. Autogenous cartilage and 
skin grafting, temporoparietal flaps covering costal carti-</p>

<p>lage grafts and tubed-pedicle flaps from the retroauricu-
lar or supraclavicular sites can be used to manage large 
auricular defects (45-47). Tissue may be expanded in the 
retroauricular region for coverage in conjunction with 
grafts or reconstruction of large defects. 
Autologous rib cartilage is a widely employed tech-
nique for total reconstruction of the auricle. To restore 
the natural ear shape, rib cartilage frameworks should be 
appropriately sculpted and the skin should be carefully 
used to ensure successful reconstruction and reduced 
complications (48). Use of alloplastic material and bio-
engineered cartilage are areas of ongoing investigation. 
Porous polyethylene is currently considered the most 
favorable alloplastic framework and recent reviews of 
the literature underscore the benefits of its open porous 
structure and biocompatibility (49-51). In cases of total 
or nearly total defects, superficial temporal and poste-
rior auricular arteries play a crucial role in creating the 
required microvascular anastomosis for successful ear 
replantation (52). </p>

<p>3.7. Reconstruction of the Burned Ear </p>

<p>The external ear is highly susceptible to thermal inju-
ries and progressive deep burns due to its exposed ana-
tomical structure. Reconstruction of the burned auricle 
is a significant challenge for most plastic surgeons. Early 
debridement of ear burn wounds before occurrence of 
irreversible cartilage changes is highly recommended. 
Surgeons' preference and local tissue availability are the 
most important variables to consider before choosing 
the optimal modality for repair (53, 54). Integrity of the 
mastoid skin is considered a reliable prognostic factor 
in patients with burned auricles. Superficial temporal 
fascia or an indirect expansion could be used and in rare 
cases, free contralateral superficial temporal fascia may 
become necessary before placing a prosthesis (55). Use of 
postauricular advancement flaps and skin grafts to cover 
the helix and antihelix respectively are suggested as a 
straightforward technique with low complication rates 
to manage extensive ear burns acutely (56). In addition 
to postauricular skin and fascia, free radial forearm flaps 
and free lateral arm fascial flaps are also used to recon-
struct the burned auricle. These techniques may be lim-
ited by lack of viable local tissues or free flaps following 
extensive burns (57). Innovative techniques combining 
scalp tissue expansion with porous polyethylene recon-
struction is recently introduced, which use temporopa-
rietal fascia flaps and does not require costochondral 
grafting (58). Use of bone-anchored extraoral implants is 
also investigated in burn patients with lasting aesthetic 
results and low complications (59). </p>

<p>3.8. Prosthetic Reconstruction of the Auricle </p>

<p>In some cases of extensive auricular defects, especially 
in older patients, surgical procedures may not lead to 
satisfactory results and prosthetic reconstruction should </p>

<p>Ebrahimi A et al. </p>

<p>Trauma Mon. 2015;20(4):e28202 </p>

<p>
be used. From a historical perspective, ear prostheses 
are broadly used and various attachment techniques 
are tested since ancient times (60). In addition to the 
aesthetic concerns, perfect fitting of the prosthesis is of 
utmost importance. Titanium screw implants address is-
sues such as bone healing, vascular integrity and integra-
tion of foreign objects into patients' bodies (61). Studies 
confirmed reliability of auricular prostheses anchored 
to the extraoral bone-integrated implants and evidence 
is accumulating the patient satisfaction and rapid return 
to normal life following such procedures (62). </p>

<p>3.9. Novel Bioengineering Techniques in Auricular 
Reconstruction </p>

<p>Utilizing autologous stem cell populations to treat cranio-
facial defects is a promising field of ongoing investigations. 
Studies show that cartilage stem/progenitor cells (CSPCs) 
are highly chondrogenic and can produce elastic recon-
structive material with long-term tissue restoration. (63). 
Bioengineering absorbable materials that could serve as 
templates for cartilage healing are also a logical perspec-
tive currently studied to simplify reconstruction proce-
dures (64). Three dimensional templates made of biore-
sorbable and nonbioresorbable materials are tested but 
problems are encountered due to uneven biodegradation 
rates and further research is required before application of 
these novel techniques in the clinical setting (65, 66). </p>

<p>4. Conclusions </p>

<p>There are different causes for auricular defects includ-
ing tumor ablation, traumas and burns. Auricular recon-
struction surgery is a challenging plastic procedure that 
requires great expertise and expert knowledge of the var-
ious techniques available. Current techniques could be 
further modified with respect to their cost-effectiveness 
and simplicity. The reconstruction method is dependent 
on defect size and location. Novel techniques in the fields 
of reconstructive bioengineering and regenerative medi-
cine are promising but further research is requirred be-
fore widespread clinical application. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank the Trauma Research Center 
of Baqiyatallah University of Medical Sciences. </p>

<p>Footnote </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution:Study concept and design: Ali 
Ebrahimi, Alireza Kazemi, Hamid Reza Rasouli, Maryam 
Kazemi, Mohammad Hosein Kalantar Motamedi; ac-
quisition of data: Hamid Reza Rasouli, Maryam Kazemi, 
Mohammad Hosein Kalantar Motamedi; analysis and in-
terpretation of data: Ali Ebrahimi, Alireza Kazemi, Hamid 
Reza Rasouli, Maryam Kazemi, Mohammad Hosein Kalan-
tar Motamedi; drafting of the manuscript: Alireza Kaze-
mi, Hamid Reza Rasouli, Maryam Kazemi; administrative, </p>

<p>technical, and material support: Ali Ebrahimi, Alireza Ka-
zemi, Hamid Reza Rasouli, Maryam Kazemi Mohammad 
Hosein Kalantar Motamedi; study supervision: Ali Ebra-
himi and Mohammad Hosein Kalantar Motamedi. </p>



<p>Ebrahimi A et al. </p>





<p>Ebrahimi A et al. </p>

<p>Trauma Mon. 2015;20(4):e28202 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>