<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4271550" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT The core human gut microbiota contributes to the developmental origin of diseases by modifying metabolic path-
ways. To evaluate the predominant microbiota as an epigenetic modifier, we classified 8 pregnant women into two groups based 
on their dominant microbiota, i.e., Bacteroidetes, Firmicutes, and Proteobacteria. Deep sequencing of DNA methylomes revealed 
a clear association between bacterial predominance and epigenetic profiles. The genes with differentially methylated promoters 
in the group in which Firmicutes was dominant were linked to risk of disease, predominantly to cardiovascular disease and spe-
cifically to lipid metabolism, obesity, and the inflammatory response. This is one of the first studies that highlights the associa-
tion of the predominant bacterial phyla in the gut with methylation patterns. Further longitudinal and in-depth studies target-
ing individual microbial species or metabolites are recommended to give us a deeper insight into the molecular mechanism of 
such epigenetic modifications. </p>

<p>IMPORTANCE Epigenetics encompasses genomic modifications that are due to environmental factors and do not affect the nucle-
otide sequence. The gut microbiota has an important role in human metabolism and could be a significant environmental factor 
affecting our epigenome. To investigate the association of gut microbiota with epigenetic changes, we assessed pregnant women 
and selected the participants based on their predominant gut microbiota for a study on their postpartum methylation profile. 
Intriguingly, we found that blood DNA methylation patterns were associated with gut microbiota profiles. The gut microbiota 
profiles, with either Firmicutes or Bacteroidetes as a dominant group, correlated with differential methylation status of gene pro-
moters functionally associated with cardiovascular diseases. Furthermore, differential methylation of gene promoters linked to 
lipid metabolism and obesity was observed. For the first time, we report here a position of the predominant gut microbiota in 
epigenetic profiling, suggesting one potential mechanism in obesity with comorbidities, if proven in further in-depth studies. </p>

<p>ences in methylation pattern, and what are the major pathways 
associated epigenetically with patterns of microbial community 
structure? 
Selection of subjects. Eight pregnant women were selected 
from a cohort of 91 subjects previously described elsewhere (10). 
We selected mothers based on the relative abundances of the pre-
dominant phyla as previously reported (10). The HighBact group 
(n 4) exhibited a predominance of the Bacteroidetes (P 0.017) 
and Proteobacteria (P 0.013) phyla, whereas Firmicutes were 
predominant in the HighFirm group (n 4) mothers (P 0.020) 
(Fig. 1). Previously, it has been shown that Bacteroidetes and Fir-
micutes constitute the dominant core of gut microbiota, and a 
Firmicutes-dominant microbiota has been implicated in the devel-
opment of overweight, obesity, and metabolic syndrome (11-13). 
Additionally, the dietary and health characteristics of selected 
mothers in each group were similar, i.e., statistically insignificant 
(see Table S1 in the supplemental material). 
Correlation between DNA methylation profile and microbi-
ota composition. The two groups showed distinct methylation 
profiles (blood samples were collected 6 months after delivery), as 
illustrated by the clustering analysis in Fig. 2A. With a fold change 
cutoff of 1.5 and P value of 0.05, the promoters of a total of 568 
genes were more methylated and the promoter of 245 genes were 
less methylated in mothers with higher levels of Firmicutes (High-
Firm group) than in mothers with higher levels of Bacteroidetes 
and Proteobacteria (HighBact group) (see Table S2 in the supple-
mental material). 
Gut microbiota composition associates with promoter DNA 
methylation status of genes associated with lipid metabolism, 
obesity, and inflammation. Pathway analysis revealed that the 
most significant functional network altered in the HighBact group 
was linked to cardiovascular diseases, together with gene expres-
sion and cell morphology functions (score of 43; Fisher exact test, 
P 1 10 43 ) (see Table S2 in the supplemental material). In 
addition, differentially methylated genes were enriched in other 
functional networks, including the inflammatory response, met-
abolic pathways, and diseases like cancer, mostly affecting the gas-
trointestinal system (312 molecules, P 0.05). As the Bacte-
roidetes/Firmicutes ratio was associated with obesity-related 
comorbidities, the cardiovascular disease risk network was further 
expanded, and associations with lipid metabolism (72 genes), in-</p>

<p>flammatory response (85 altered genes), and obesity (23 altered 
genes) were found (Fig. 2B). Consistent with these results, the 
gene SCD5, which had the greatest difference between the two 
groups (fold change, 6.239; P 0.00005), encodes primate-
specific stearoyl-coenzyme A (CoA) desaturase, which has a key 
function in the catalysis of monounsaturated fatty acids from sat-
urated fatty acids. The promoter region of SCD5 was more meth-
ylated in the HighFirm group and had an undetectable methyl-
ation in the HighBact group. LPS (P 0.00208) was one of the 
upstream regulators of genes identified in the network (see Ta-
ble S3), which further strengthens the role of microbial molecules 
in epigenetic modifications. 
Some of the epigenetically regulated genes include the genes 
encoding USF1 (P 0.00805), ACOT7 (P 0.035), ASAH2 (P 
0.0367), TAC1 (P 0.00972), and LMNA (P 0.03081). USF1 is 
one of the key regulators of fatty acid synthase (FAS) and is also a 
key enzyme in lipogenesis (14). USF1 and LMNA have also been 
linked with the onset of coronary heart disease (15, 16). The ex-
pression of ACOT and microRNAs 103/107 was also found to be 
upregulated in obese rats and mice, respectively (17, 18). Simi-
larly, gut microbiota or its metabolites are directly linked to obe-
sity and associated metabolic pathways. However, the association 
with epigenetic regulation of these genes should be further con-
firmed by quantitative PCR (qPCR) and in vitro experiments. 
These findings are consistent with previous studies, which have 
linked higher levels of Firmicutes to the development of over-
weight, obesity, higher energy extraction, and metabolic func-
tions, including lipid metabolism. Additionally, deviant gut mi-
crobiota composition could also be one of the risk factors which 
may contribute to metabolic syndrome. Our findings are novel, 
but due to the small sample size, larger studies and interventions, 
and possibly animal experiments also, are required to assess the 
mechanisms. Nonetheless, this approach is intriguing and could 
offer a new basis for prevention and treatment strategies involving 
the gut microbiota and its impact on long-term genomic modifi-
cations. 
Microbial phylum comparisons. All the OTU tables were re-
trieved from our earlier study (10).The percentages of relative 
abundance for all phyla were used to compare the mothers (di-
vided into two groups). Statistical package <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> was used for the </p>

<p>FIG 1 Categorization of mothers into group HighBact and group HighFirm was based on their dominant bacterial phyla. Box plots show the relative abundance </p>

<p>(%) of the three major bacterial phyla, Bacteroidetes, Firmicutes, and Proteobacteria. There is a statistically significant difference between the groups (P 0.05) 
using t test analysis. </p>

<p>Kumar et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2014 Volume 5 Issue 6 e02113-14 </p>

<p>t test and to make box plots of the percentages of relative abun-
dance. 
DNA methylome analysis. The DNA methylome analysis was 
carried out from 5 g of genomic DNA that was extracted from 
EDTA blood with a QIAamp DNA blood maxikit (Qiagen) and 
fragmented into an average size of 150 bp with a Covaris S2 soni-
cator. Methylated DNA was enriched with a MethylMiner meth-
ylated DNA enrichment kit (Invitrogen) by following the high-salt 
(2 M NaCl), single-elution workflow. The sequencing libraries 
were prepared from 500 ng of enriched DNA with a SOLiD frag-
ment library construction kit (Life Technologies), and the SOLiD 
fragment library barcoding kit module 1-16 (Life Technologies) 
was used for multiplexing. The libraries were purified (AMPure 
XP beads; Agencourt) and size selected (150 to 300 bp) from 1% 
agarose gels (QIAquick gel extraction kit; Qiagen). The bead prep-
aration was carried out according to the SOLiD 4 System Tem-
plated Bead Preparation Guide. The SOLiDEZ bead system was 
used for automated templated bead preparation. The libraries 
were sequenced with a SOLiD 4 or SOLiD 5500XL sequencer (Life 
Technologies) by using 50-bp chemistry. 
Methylation sequencing data analysis. The raw sequence data 
were mapped to hg19 reference genome sequences with <rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Life Tech-nologies</rs> <rs id="software-5" type="software">Bioscope</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">version 2.0</rs>) software using the default param-
eters, yielding on average 56.7 M mapped reads per sample (stan-
dard deviation, 14.26 M reads). The read counts for proximal 
promoters (region between 1,000 bp upstream and 500 bp down-</p>

<p>stream from the transcription start site, coordinates derived from 
RefSeq gene annotations) were calculated using bedtools (version 
2.17.0). Statistical analysis for comparing differentially methyl-
ated promoters between sample groups was carried out using 
R/<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Bioconductor</rs> <rs id="software-3" type="software">limma</rs> package on TMM-normalized and voom-
transformed count values as suggested in the limma manual (19, 20). 
The promoters with absolute fold changes above 2 and P values 
below 0.05 were listed as significantly differentially methylated. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplemental material for this article may be found at http://mbio.asm.org/ 
lookup/suppl/doi:10.1128/mBio.02113-14/-/DCSupplemental. 
Table S1, DOC file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S2, XLS file, 0.3 MB. 
Table S3, XLS file, 0.1 MB. 
Table S4, PDF file, 2.1 MB. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Omry Koren for useful discussion on data analysis. We also 
thank the hospital nurses for their help in collecting the samples. 
This research project was funded by the Academy of Finland. 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>



<p>FIG 2 Association of gut microbiota with DNA methylation. (A) Clustering analysis of DNA methylome data revealed a clear correlation between the </p>

<p>whole-blood epigenetic profile and the composition of the gut microbial population of the mothers with a predominance of either Bacteroidetes and Proteobac-
teria (group HighBact) or Firmicutes (group HighFirm). Green indicates decreased and red indicates increased gene promoter methylation in group HighFirm 
compared to the promoter methylation in group HighBact. (B) Based on <rs id="software-2" type="software">Pathway Analysis</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Ingenuity Systems</rs>), the gut microbial composition affects the DNA 
methylation status of genes primarily linked to cardiac diseases, with associations to lipid metabolism, inflammatory response, and obesity. The affected genes 
linked to the particular functional or metabolic syndrome displayed in the network had fold changes of 3 in the promoter DNA methylation status between the 
HighBact group and the HighFirm group. The symbols and their colors are defined in Table S4 in the supplemental material. </p>

<p>Epigenetic Association of Gut Microbiota </p>

<p>November/December 2014 Volume 5 Issue 6 e02113-14 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 3 </p>





<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2014 Volume 5 Issue 6 e02113-14 </p>

</text></tei>