<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4548766" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: This study systematically compared the efficacy and safety of simultaneous </p>

<p>hepatectomy and splenectomy (HS) with hepatectomy (H) alone in patients with hepatocellular 
carcinoma (HCC) and hypersplenism. 
Methods: The PubMed, Web of Science, Science Direct, EMBASE, and Cochrane Library </p>

<p>databases were systematically searched by two independent researchers through to March 31, 
2015 to identify relevant studies. All the extracted literature were managed by Bibliographic 
citation management software. Quality assessment of the included studies was performed using 
a modified Newcastle-Ottawa Scale judgment. The data were analyzed using RevMan5.2 
software. 
Results: Eight studies including a total of 761 patients with HCC and hypersplenism (360 in </p>

<p>the HS group, 401 in the H group) were finally included in the analysis. Outcomes, including 
postoperative complications, perioperative mortality, operation time, 5-year survival rate, and 
need for blood transfusion did not differ significantly between the two groups. HS was associ-
ated with significantly more intraoperative bleeding (mean difference [MD] 57.15, 95% confi-
dence interval [CI] 18.83-95.46, P=0.003), and CD4/CD8 ratio (MD 0.69, 95% CI 0.61-0.77, 
P,0.00001), CD4 subset, platelet count (MD 213.06, 95% CI 202.59-223.53, P,0.0001), 
white blood cell count (MD 4.85, 95% CI 4.58-5.13, P,0.0001), interferon-gamma levels 
(MD 18.52, 95% CI 13.93-23.11, P,0.00001), and interleukin-2 levels (MD 20.73, 95% CI 
16.05-25.41, P,0.0001). In addition, lower CD8 subset (MD -7.85, 95% CI -9.07, -6.63, 
P,0.00001) and interleukin-10 levels (MD -18.56, 95% CI -22.61, -14.50, P,0.00001) were 
observed for HS. 
Conclusion: We identified that simultaneous HS do not increase postoperative complications, </p>

<p>operation time, or perioperative mortality in patients with HCC and hypersplenism. Simultane-
ous splenectomy can increase postoperative white blood cell and platelet counts significantly, 
improve blood coagulation, reduce the incidence of postoperative bleeding, and enhance immu-
nity. Therefore, HS is safe, effective, and feasible for patients with HCC and hypersplenism. 
Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is a common malignant tumor and the third leading 
cause of tumor-related death worldwide. 1 Hepatectomy is regarded as an effective 
treatment for HCC, which is often complicated by splenomegaly and hypersplenism. 
Hypersplenism results in pancytopenia, and hepatectomy in patients with hypersplenic </p>

<p>correspondence: shi-Qiang shen 
Department of general surgery, 
renmin hospital of Wuhan University, 
hubei Zhang road, Wuchang District 
no 99 Wuhan 430060, hubei Province, 
People's republic of china 
Tel +86 27 8804 1911 
Fax +86 27 8804 1911 
email shenshiqiang2014@hotmail.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
19 August 2015 </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2130 </p>

<p>li et al </p>

<p>thrombocytopenia may cause a perioperative bleeding 
episode and sometimes liver failure. 2 Therefore, many sur-
geons hesitate to perform hepatectomy for patients with HCC 
and hypersplenism. Splenectomy is perceived as a good man-
agement technique for hypersplenism, as it helps to improve 
thrombocytopenia and leukopenia and decrease pressure in 
the portal veins. 3,4 In addition, some studies suggest that 
splenectomy may help to improve liver function, 5-7 nutritional 
metabolism, 6 and Child-Pugh scores. 8 However, whether 
patients with HCC and hypersplenism should undergo 
hepatectomy and a concomitant splenectomy remains contro-
versial. To address these issues and provide more references 
on the treatment of HCC complicated by hypersplenism, we 
conducted an integrated quantitative evaluation using meta-
analysis to compare the efficacy and safety of simultaneous 
hepatectomy and splenectomy (HS) or hepatectomy (H) alone 
in patients with HCC and hypersplenism. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
search strategy </p>

<p>A systematic search was conducted in the PubMed, Web of 
Science, Science Direct, EMBASE, and Cochrane Library data-
bases until March 31, 2015, with no limits. The search strategies 
were based on combinations of the following keywords: hepa-
tocellular carcinoma, hypersplenism, liver resection, splenec-
tomy, comparative study, efficacy, liver cancer, primary liver 
carcinoma, and hepatectomy. In addition, we checked relevant 
reviews on the topic of interest. We traced the reference lists 
of selected articles and used Google Scholar to find potential 
studies. No approval was required from the Institutional Review 
Board regarding the approval for this study. </p>

<p>inclusion and exclusion criteria </p>

<p>Randomized controlled trials, clinical controlled studies, 
and case-control studies were identified. The inclusion cri-
teria were: a clear diagnosis of HCC (including computed 
tomography, magnetic resonance imaging, serum alpha-
fetoprotein levels, and pathology after surgery) and a diag-
nosis of hypersplenism (mild, white blood cell [WBC] count 
,3.5×10 9 /L and/or platelet count ,150×10 9 /L, severe, WBC 
count ,2.0×10 9 /L and/or platelet count ,75×10 9 /L, and sple-
nomegaly that was classified as greater than class I [spleen 
enlarged beyond left subcostal margin and palpable]); 9 com-
parison of HS with H; and available data for each surgical 
regimen. The exclusion criteria were: compared two surgical 
procedures in an animal model; only reported one surgical 
procedure (hepatectomy or splenectomy); data could not be 
used for statistical analysis; hepatectomy and splenectomy </p>

<p>was conducted step by step or by laparoscopic surgery; 
basic preoperative situation of the two groups was obviously 
different; and articles from the same author or institution that 
contained significant overlap of patient data. </p>

<p>Data extraction and quality assessment </p>

<p>Data on all variables and outcomes were extracted from eli-
gible studies by two reviewers independently. The extracted 
information included: baseline information on articles 
(authors, research areas, publication year, and grouping meth-
ods); general information (case numbers, operative methods, 
Child-Pugh classification, tumor size, mean age, sex ratio); 
treatment outcomes (eg, perioperative mortality, postopera-
tive complications [pleural effusion, upper gastrointestinal 
hemorrhage, bile leakage, pulmonary infection, abdominal 
cavity hemorrhage, incision infection, hyperbilirubinemia], 
CD4, CD8, CD4/CD8 ratio, interferon [IFN]-γ levels, inter-
leukin [IL]-2 levels, IL-10 levels, postoperative WBC and 
platelet counts, and 5-year survival rate). Disagreements 
were resolved by discussion or consulting experts. If neces-
sary, the primary authors were contacted to obtain missing 
data. A modification of the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale was 
used as an assessment tool for selection, comparability, and 
outcome assessment. </p>

<p>Outcome definition </p>

<p>Perioperative mortality was defined as death in hospital 
within 30 days following surgery. Complications included 
both hepatic and extrahepatic events. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>The data were analyzed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">RevMan</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">5.2</rs> software. We 
analyzed dichotomous variables using odds ratios (ORs) 
or risk differences along with 95% confidence intervals 
(CIs), and analyzed continuous data using mean differences 
(MDs) along with 95% CIs. The I 2 and P-value were used 
for evaluation of heterogeneity. A fixed-effects model was 
used when the heterogeneity test showed better homogeneity 
(P.0.1). 10,11 Otherwise, a random-effects model was used. 
With regard to outcomes when significant heterogeneity 
existed across studies, sensitivity analysis was conducted 
by respectively omitting each study to explore the influence 
of each individual study on the merged data. </p>

<p>assessment of publication bias </p>

<p>Publication bias is an important factor that affects the 
authenticity of the results of meta-analyses. For various 
reasons, the literature published in journals may differ from </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2131 </p>

<p>hs versus h for hcc with hypersplenism </p>

<p>unpublished studies. The existence of this type of bias can not 
be completely resolved by a meta-analysis itself. In this meta-
analysis, a funnel plot was drawn using the funnel plot com-
mand in the RevMan software (Figure 1), which indi cated no 
obvious publication bias in the studies included. </p>

<p>Results 
characteristics of pooled studies </p>

<p>A flow diagram of the search strategy for study selection and 
inclusion is shown in Figure 2. A total of 325 relevant abstracts 
were retrieved in the initial search based on the search strategy 
described above. A total of 291 studies were excluded for 
having irrelevant titles, and/or abstracts. Twenty-one studies 
were excluded for being reviews or updates, or containing 
data that were not able to be compared, three studies were 
excluded because they were published by the same authors 
and institutions and contained significant overlap of patient 
data which had already been published in other studies, 12-14 
and another two studies were excluded because the H groups 
were not complicated with hypersplenism. 15,16 Consequently, 
eight studies including a total of 761 patients comparing the 
outcomes of HS with H alone were included in this meta-
analysis. 17-24 The basic characteristics of all studies included 
in the meta-analysis are detailed in Table 1. </p>

<p>Quality judgments for studies </p>

<p>All the included studies were analyzed retrospectively. 
Due to the specificity and ethics, the surgeons could not 
randomly allocate patients into the two groups. Finally, 
eight retrospective case-control studies were included in the 
analysis. The quality of the literature was assessed using a 
modification of the Newcastle-Ottawa Scale. 25 The results of 
this assessment are shown in Table 2. Of the eight included </p>

<p>articles, three were published before 2005, and the other five 
were published after 2005. Studies given more than four 
stars were recognized as being moderate to high quality. </p>

<p>immunology results </p>

<p>With respect to immune function and cell count-related 
outcomes, eight endpoints, including CD4/CD8 ratio, CD4 
subset, CD8 subset, IFN-γ levels, IL-10 levels, IL-2 levels, 
and WBC and platelet counts, were analyzed. High IL-2 
levels, IFN-γ levels, CD4 subset, and CD4/CD8 ratio, and 
low IL-10 levels and CD8 subset in HS were highly sig-
nificant (P,0.00001-0.005). Moreover, in the quantitative 
analysis of WBC counts, HS was significantly superior to H 
(MD 4.85, 95% CI 4.58-5.13, P,0.00001) and platelet 
counts were higher in HS than that in H alone (MD 213.06, 
95% CI 202.59-223.53, P,0.00001; Table 3). </p>

<p>Operation-related results </p>

<p>With respect to operation-related outcomes, five endpoints, 
including postoperative complications, perioperative mortal-
ity, operation time, intraoperative blood loss, and need for 
blood transfusion were analyzed. Three studies reported peri-
operative mortality. 17,18,20 Overall, perioperative mortality did 
not differ significantly between the two surgical approaches 
(OR 0.48, 95% CI 0.09-2.50, P=0.38; Figure 3A). Seven 
studies reported postoperative complications. 17-22,24 Post-
operative complications were assessed with no significant 
difference between the two surgical approaches for patients 
with HCC and hypersplenism (OR 0.84, 95% CI 0.60-1.17, 
P=0.29; Figure 3B). Six studies reported intraoperative blood 
loss. 17-19,21,22,24 More intraoperative blood loss was found with 
simultaneous HS, which was highly significant (MD 57.15, 
95% CI 18.83-95.46, P=0.003; Figure 3C). Four studies 
reported operation time, 17-19,21 which was not significantly 
different between the two surgical approaches (MD 37.99, 
95% CI -11.75, 87.73, P=0.13; Figure 3D). Moreover, three 
studies reported blood transfusion, 17,19,24 which did not differ 
significantly between the two surgical approaches (OR 1, 
95% CI 0.58-1.71, P=0.99; Figure 3E). In terms of long-
term results, two studies were pooled for analysis 19,20 and 
no significant difference in 5-year overall survival rates was 
observed between the two surgical approaches for patients 
with HCC and hypersplenism (risk difference 0.08, 95% 
CI -0.03, 0.19, P=0.18; Figure 3F). </p>

<p>heterogeneity </p>

<p>High heterogeneity was detected for WBC counts (I 2 =91%, 
P,0.00001), platelet counts (I 2 =96%, P,0.00001), IL-10 </p>

















<p>
Figure 1 Funnel plot for publication bias tests. each point represents a separate 
study for the indicated association. Vertical line represents the mean effects size. 
Abbreviations: se, standard error; Or, odds ratio. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2132 </p>

<p>li et al </p>

<p>Table 1 Basic characteristics of all pooled studies in the meta-analysis </p>

<p>References 
Regions 
Groups 
Patients 
(n) </p>

<p>Child-Pugh 
classification </p>

<p>Type of liver tumor resection </p>

<p>A 
B 
Hepatic lobectomy 
Local excision </p>

<p>cao et al 23 
People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hs 
h </p>

<p>7 
9 </p>

<p>na 
na 
na 
na </p>

<p>Oh et al 18 
Korea 
hs 
h </p>

<p>12 
6 </p>

<p>6 
4 </p>

<p>6 
2 </p>

<p>11 
1 
4 
cai et al 20 
People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hs 
h </p>

<p>57 
45 </p>

<p>48 
42 </p>

<p>9 
3 </p>

<p>12 
9 </p>

<p>45 
36 
chen et al 19 
People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hs 
h </p>

<p>94 
110 </p>

<p>64 
61 </p>

<p>30 
49 </p>

<p>62 
74 </p>

<p>32 
36 
sugimachi et al 17 
Japan 
hs 
h </p>

<p>4 
11 </p>

<p>9 
6 
na 
na </p>

<p>Bi et al 21 
People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hs 
h </p>

<p>71 
106 </p>

<p>65 
96 </p>

<p>6 
10 </p>

<p>39 
56 </p>

<p>32 
50 
Wang et al 22 
People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hs 
h </p>

<p>31 
30 </p>

<p>26 
25 </p>

<p>5 
5 </p>

<p>na 
na </p>

<p>Zhang et al 24 
People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>hs 
h </p>

<p>84 
84 </p>

<p>84 
84 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>20 
32 </p>

<p>64 
52 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: hs, simultaneous hepatectomy and splenectomy; h, hepatectomy; na, not applicable. </p>









<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
 </p>







<p>Figure 2 Flow diagram summarizing the selection of eligible studies. </p>

<p>levels (I 2 =89%, P=0.002), IFN-γ levels (I 2 =81%, P=0.02), 
and operation time (I 2 =87%, P,0.0001). Sensitivity analysis 
was then conducted by omitting each single study. There were 
no changes in outcomes compared with primary outcomes. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In recent years, the 5-year survival rate has been reported 
to reach 50%-70% in strictly selected patients undergo-
ing liver resection, percutaneous radiofrequency ablation, 
or liver transplantation for the treatment of early HCC. 26 
Under current medical conditions, hepatectomy is still </p>

<p>the primary treatment for HCC. Splenectomy has been 
suggested for the treatment of secondary hypersplenism 
and thrombocytopenia. 27 Sugawara et al 28 recommended 
splenectomy as an aid to extend the patient selection criteria 
for hepatectomy to patients with HCC and hypersplenism. 
Hypersplenism can lead to decreased WBC and platelet 
counts, which can lower the body's resistance to infection 
and cause coagulopathy, which is traditionally considered as 
a contraindication to HS for patients with HCC and hyper-
splenism. However, some patients have good hepatic reserve, 
and improvements in preoperative preparation, surgical </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2133 </p>

<p>hs versus h for hcc with hypersplenism </p>

<p>Table 2 Quality assessment of studies in the meta-analysis based on modified Newcastle-Ottawa Scale judgment </p>

<p>References 
Selection 
Comparability 
Outcome assessment 
Quality judgment </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>cao et al 23 
 
 
 
 
Oh et al 18 
 
 
 
 
 
 
cai et al 20 
 
 
 
 
 
chen et al 19 
 
 
 
 
 
 
sugimachi et al 17 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Bi et al 21 
 
 
 
 
Wang et al 22 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Zhang et al 24 
 
 
 
 
 
 </p>

<p>Notes: Selection: 1. Is the subject definition adequate or described? (if yes, one star); 2. Was the subject representative of the total population? (one star, if truly or obviously; 
no stars if subjects were selected group or not described). Comparability: 3. Did the study show no differences between HS and H in patients with HCC and hypersplenism? 
Five main factors were considered: positive node of primary tumor, disease-free interval, number of liver metastases, presence of liver tumor, carcinoembryonic antigen 
level. Other four factors: age, sex, American Society of Anesthesiologists score, and preoperative and postoperative chemotherapy were comparative (if yes, two stars; one 
star if there were no other differences between the two groups even if one or more of these five characteristics was not reported; no star was assigned if the two groups 
differed). Outcome assessment: 5. Clearly defined outcome of interest (if yes, one star); 5. Adequacy of follow-up (one star if less than 20% of patients lost to follow-up, 
otherwise no stars). 
Abbreviations: hs, simultaneous hepatectomy and splenectomy; h, hepatectomy; hcc, hepatocellular carcinoma. </p>

<p>Table 3 Pooled outcomes of simultaneous hepatectomy and splenectomy versus hepatectomy alone in all studies </p>

<p>Outcomes 
Studies 
(n) </p>

<p>Participants 
MD/OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value for 
effect size </p>

<p>Test of heterogeneity Analysis 
model 
HS 
H 
I 2 (%) 
P-value </p>

<p>Postoperative cD4 + T-cell ratio 
2 
84 
74 
6.87 
,0.00001 
0 
0.52 
Fixed 
Postoperative cD8 + T-cell ratio 
2 
84 
74 
-7.85 
,0.00001 
28 
0.24 
Fixed 
Postoperative cD4 + T-cell/cD8 + T-cell ratio 
2 
84 
74 
0.69 
,0.00001 
0 
0.43 
Fixed 
Postoperative WBc count 
4 
280 
330 
4.90 
,0.00001 
91 
,0.00001 
random 
Postoperative platelet count 
5 
292 
336 
183.3 
,0.00001 
96 
,0.00001 
random 
Postoperative il-2 levels 
2 
84 
74 
20.73 
,0.00001 
0 
0.70 
Fixed 
Postoperative iFn-γ levels 
Postoperative il-10 levels </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>84 
84 </p>

<p>74 
74 </p>

<p>24 
-24.23 </p>

<p>0.005 
0.007 </p>

<p>81 
89 </p>

<p>0.02 
0.002 </p>

<p>random 
random </p>

<p>Abbreviations: iFn-γ, interferon-gamma; IL, interleukin; MD, mean difference; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; WBC, white blood cell; HS, simultaneous hepatectomy 
and splenectomy; h, hepatectomy. </p>

<p>techniques, and postoperative care can raise the ability to 
tolerate HS. Two-stage hepatectomy and splenectomy may 
lead to complications and inevitably prolongs the overall 
treatment time. Hepatectomy conducted after splenectomy 
when WBC and platelet counts return to normal may reduce 
the surgical risk, but may increase the risks of tumor recur-
rence and metastasis. Hepatectomy before splenectomy 
may result in uncontrolled intraoperative and postoperative 
oozing of blood from surgical wounds and lead to further 
severe liver damage, uncontrolled hemorrhagic shock, and 
multiple organ failure due to factors such as coagulation 
disorder and thrombocytopenia. Simultaneous splenectomy 
can increase postoperative WBC and platelet counts signifi-
cantly, improve blood coagulation, and reduce the incidence 
of postoperative bleeding. Therefore, some researchers 17-24 
have considered HS to be beneficial for patients with HCC 
and hypersplenism. However, their studies have been ret-
rospective in nature and have included limited numbers of 
cases. There has been no convincing evidence for the efficacy </p>

<p>and safety of simultaneous HS for patients with HCC and 
hypersplenism. The aim of this meta-analysis was to evalu-
ate the efficacy and safety of HS versus H alone in patients 
with HCC and hypersplenism by comparing the short-term 
and long-term results between the two groups. 
In addition to complications related to technical errors 
and perioperative evaluation, portal vein thrombosis and 
uncontrolled infection are known to be life-threatening 
complications after simultaneous HS. 29-31 The results of our 
meta-analysis indicate that there is no significant difference 
in terms of perioperative mortality between simultaneous HS 
and H alone for patients with HCC and hypersplenism, and 
HS does not increase the risk of postoperative complications. 
Overwhelming infection is a well-known and much feared 
complication after splenectomy. The incidence is low, with 
a higher death rate in children. The interval between sple-
nectomy and first infection ranges from 15 to 49.7 months. 
Theoretically, liver cirrhosis is an immunocompromised 
condition, but overwhelming sepsis has rarely been reported </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2134 </p>

<p>li et al </p>





































































































































<p>χ </p>



<p>χ </p>



<p>χ </p>







































































































































































<p>
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ 
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ 
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ 
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ 
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ 
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ </p>

























<p>
τ χ </p>





















































































































































































<p>χ </p>

<p>
χ </p>











































































<p>Figure 3 Meta-analysis of comparison between HS and H groups for (A) perioperative mortality, (B) postoperative complications, (C) intraoperative bleeding, (D) operation 
time, (E) blood transfusion, and (F) 5-year overall survival rates. 
Abbreviations: HS, simultaneous hepatectomy and splenectomy; H, hepatectomy; CI, confidence interval; M-H, Mantel-Haenszel test; IV, inverse variance; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2135 </p>

<p>hs versus h for hcc with hypersplenism </p>

<p>after splenectomy for hypersplenism in cirrhotic patients in 
other studies. 32,33 No overwhelming post splenectomy infec-
tion was reported over a long follow-up period in patients 
who underwent simultaneous HS in any of the included 
studies. Portal vein thrombosis refers to the complete or 
partial obstruction of blood flow in the portal vein due to the 
presence of a thrombus in the vasal lumen, and is a severe 
complication after splenectomy. In our study, only one patient 
was identified to have portal vein thrombus, which resolved 
on conservative treatment. Hepatectomy also raises the portal 
vein pressure, which increases the risk of upper gastrointesti-
nal hemorrhage. Splenectomy reduces the portal vein inflow 
by 20%-30%, consequently decreasing portal vein pressure 34 
and reducing the risk of upper gastrointestinal hemorrhage. 
In our meta-analysis, the incidence of upper gastrointestinal 
hemorrhage after simultaneous HS was 2.63 % (five of 190 
cases), whereas the incidence of upper gastrointestinal hem-
orrhage after H alone was 5% (ten of 200 cases). 
Acknowledging that the spleen normally plays a key role 
in preventing infection, the changes in immune function 
caused by splenectomy is another concern. The spleen in a 
patient with HCC and hypersplenism often shows negative 
immune function. In addition, research has shown that the 
spleen in a tumor-burdened host attracts a large number of 
inhibitory macrophages; these cells change the structure 
and function of the TCR-CD3 complex, thus inhibiting the 
immune function of T lymphocytes. 35 The cellular response 
plays a central role in anti-tumor immunity. CD4 T lym-
phocytes mainly produce cytokines to regulate anti-tumor 
immunity, and CD8 T lymphocyte cells produce immuno-
suppressive cytokines. So, to a certain extent, determination 
of T lymphocyte subsets could reflect the body's immune 
function. Th1 cells produce IL-2 and IFN-γ and promote a 
cellular immune response, so play an important role in anti-
tumor immunity, whereas Th2 cells mainly produce IL-4 
and IL-10 and inhibit secretion of Th1 cells. Splenectomy 
may reduce destruction and storage of platelets and WBCs 
in the spleen, and at the same time reduce platelet-related 
antibody levels in serum and increase platelet production by 
increasing the release of thrombopoietin. The results of our 
meta-analysis showed that after simultaneous HS, postopera-
tive WBC and platelet counts return to normal, and T lym-
phocyte subsets such as CD4 and CD4/CD8 and levels of 
Th1 lymphocyte cytokines such as IL-2 and IFN-γ increased, 
but T lymphocyte subsets such as CD8 and Th2 lymphocyte 
cytokines such as IL-10 decreased. These variations indicate, 
to some extent, that simultaneous HS reduced the risk of 
perioperative bleeding, avoided immunosuppression of the </p>

<p>spleen, and enhanced anti-tumor immunity. Moreover, it cre-
ated favorable conditions for subsequent transcatheter arterial 
chemoembolization and adjuvant chemotherapy, hopefully 
improving the prognosis for patients. 36 
The results of our meta-analysis indicate more intraop-
erative blood loss with simultaneous HS than with H alone. 
However, operation time and need for blood transfusion did 
not differ significantly between the two surgical approaches. 
Patients with HCC and hypersplenism often have severe 
cirrhosis, and simultaneous HS increased the surgical 
trauma. Therefore, reasonable perioperative management, 
and careful operation are helpful to decrease periopera-
tive bleeding and are the key to successful surgery and an 
uneventful postoperative recovery. 
Cumulative survival rates, disease-free survival rates, and 
tumor recurrence rates are important outcomes to evaluate the 
therapeutic effect of antitumor treatment. 37 It is reported that 
chemotherapy helps to prevent recurrence of HCC after liver 
resection. 38,39 HCC patients often have splenomegaly and 
hypersplenism, which will limit their ability to tolerate post-
operative chemotherapy. An increase in WBC and platelet 
counts after splenectomy will be favorable for postoperative 
chemotherapy. Unfortunately, the 5-year survival rates for the 
two treatment groups were not significantly different in our 
study; however, we could only find two relevant studies for 
inclusion in our meta-analysis, so more studies are needed 
in this area. The two studies 19,24 we identified had reported 
that 5-year relapse-free survival was better in patients who 
underwent simultaneous HS than in those who underwent 
H alone; however, we could not compare the relapse-free 
survival rate between the HS and H groups because only one 
study provided the data needed to do so. 
There are several limitations to this meta-analysis. First, 
the patient numbers included were small. Second, we did not 
include studies published in other languages (eg, German, 
French, Spanish), which may have resulted in a degree of 
selection bias. Third, a funnel plot analysis is valid only if 
more than ten trials are included, and we could only include 
eight studies. 
In conclusion, we identified that simultaneous HS does 
not increase postoperative complications, operation time, or 
operative mortality in patients with HCC and hypersplenism. 
Simultaneous HS can increase postoperative WBC and plate-
let counts significantly, improve blood coagulation, reduce 
the incidence of postoperative bleeding, and enhance immu-
nity. Therefore, HS is safe, effective, and feasible for patients 
with HCC and hypersplenism. We suggest simultaneous HS 
for patients with these two conditions. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2136 </p>

<p>li et al </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report that they have no financial and personal 
relationships with other people or organizations that could 
inappropriately influence their work, and no professional or 
other personal interest of any nature or kind in any product, 
service, and/or company that could be construed as influenc-
ing the position presented in this paper. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2015:8 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2137 </p>

<p>hs versus h for hcc with hypersplenism </p>

</text></tei>