<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4397380" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract The present study is the first report on the isolation of Penicillium menonorum from rhizosphere soil in Korea and its 
identification based on morphological characteristics and internal transcribed spacer gene sequence. The fungal isolate was 
named KNU-3 and was found to exhibit plant growth-promoting (PGP) activity through indole acetic acid (IAA) and siderophore 
production, as well as P solubilization. KNU-3 produced 9.7 mg/L IAA and solubilized 408 mg of Ca </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>PO </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>/L, and inoculation with 
the isolate significantly (p &lt; 0.05) increased the dry biomass of cucumber roots (57%) and shoots (52%). Chlorophyll, starch, 
protein, and P contents were increased by 16%, 45%, 22%, and 14%, respectively, compared to plants grown in uninoculated 
soil. The fungus also increased soil dehydrogenase (30%) and acid phosphatase (19%) activities. These results demonstrate that the 
isolate KNU-3 has potential PGP attributes, and therefore it can be considered as a new fungus to enhance soil fertility and 
promote plant growth. Moreover, the discovery of PGP ability and traits of this fungus will open new aspects of research and 
investigations. In this study, plant growth promotion by P. menonorum KNU-3 is reported for the first time in Korea after its 
original description. </p>

<p>50 Babu et al.   soil and marine habitats [6], and some were identified as 
harmful pathogens that can cause spoilage and decay of 
plant products [13]. Other species were characterized as 
plant growth promoters by producing secondary metabolites 
and colonizing plant roots and/or soils. In the present study, 
we report the isolation of Penicillium menonorum from 
crop field soil for the first time in Korea. Furthermore, we 
report its PGP attributes and its positive effect on the 
growth enhancement of cucumber plants. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Fungus isolation and identification. Soil samples were 
collected (0~15 cm depth) from crop field soil at Jeongseon 
(37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>22'45'' N, 128 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>39'53'' E), Gangwon-do, Korea. Fungi 
were isolated by conventional dilution and the growth 
medium was supplemented with 100 µg chloramphenicol 
(bacteriostat) per mL potato dextrose agar (PDA; Difco 
Laboratories, Detroit, MI, USA). After incubating the plates 
at 27 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 3~15 days, fungal isolates were tentatively 
identified based on the differing morphology upon sub-
culturing to the genus level based on taxonomic keys [14]. 
Pure cultures were maintained on PDA slants and stored at 
4 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. A pure culture of Penicillium sp. KNU-3 showing a 
definitive similarity match for P. menonorum was identified 
based on its morphological description provided by Peterson 
et al. [15], and selected for further internal transcribed 
spacer (ITS) gene sequence analysis. </p>

<p>Molecular identification. Genomic DNA of the strain 
KNU-3 was extracted using the DNeasy Plant Mini Kit 
(Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) following the manufacturer's 
instructions. The ITS regions, including the 5.8S, were 
amplified with the primers ITS1 and ITS4 [16]. The 
amplified PCR product (619 bp) was purified using a 
QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA, 
USA) following the manufacturer's recommendations. The 
PCR product was sequenced with an ABI Prism 3730 
DNA Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). 
The sequence was compared with reference ITS1~ITS4 
rDNA sequences in GenBank using <rs id="software-1" type="software">BLAST</rs> analysis (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http:// www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gob/blast</rs>). The nucleotide sequence 
reported here has been deposited at NCBI-GenBank (accession 
No. KJ921605). The sequences of closely related strains were 
aligned using <rs type="software">MultAlin</rs> program. Phylogenetic analysis was 
carried out by the neighbor-joining method using MEGA 
software [17] with the Kimura 2-parameter model. The 
robustness of the tree was evaluated by 1,000 bootstrap 
replications. </p>

<p>Screening for PGP properties. The fungus KNU-3 was 
further screened for PGP traits that could be associated 
with its ability to promote plant growth. Production of the 
phytohormone indoleacetic acid (IAA) in the presence of 
tryptophan was estimated as described by Babu et al. [18]. 
Briefly, plugs of the fungus with a diameter of 4 mm were </p>

<p>inoculated into potato dextrose broth (PDB; diluted 1 : 7) 
supplemented with 100 mg/L of filter-sterilized tryptophan 
(Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and incubated for 
7 days on a rotary shaker (170 rpm) at 28 ± 2 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. The 
supernatants were obtained by centrifugation at 12,000 
rpm for 10 min. One milliliter of the supernatant was mixed 
with 2 mL of Salkowsky's reagent (50 mL 35% perchloric 
acid, 1 mL 0.5 M FeCl 3 ), incubated at room temperature 
for 20 min, and the absorbance was read at 535 nm. IAA 
was estimated using a standard curve prepared by serial 
dilution of 100 µg/mL IAA solution in PDB (diluted 1 : 7). 
Fungal 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) 
deaminase activity was estimated [19]. Siderophore production 
was determined using modified Chrome azurol S (CAS) 
agar medium [20]. 
Quantitative estimation of phosphate solubilization 
was conducted in Pikovskya's broth [21]. One milliliter 
homogenized mycelium suspension grown for 7 days was 
inoculated to 100-mL broth in 250-mL conical flasks. Flasks 
were incubated on a rotary shaker at 130 rpm and 30 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 
8 days. Experiments were conducted in triplicate and the 
uninoculated broth served as the control. Samples were 
collected at prescribed time intervals (2, 4, 6, and 8 days) 
and the mixtures were centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 5 min. 
Five milliliters of supernatant were immediately filtered 
through a 0.2-µm membrane, and soluble P in the culture 
filtrate was determined [18]. Periodic pH estimation of the 
culture filtrate was performed using a digital pH meter. </p>

<p>Pot experiment. Effects of KNU-3 on cucumber growth 
were studied in earthen pots (50 cm diameter, 20 cm 
height) containing 2 kg of soil (60% field soil and 40% 
commercial soil, w/w). The dried soil had the following 
composition: loamy sand (78.3% sand, 7.2% silt, and 14.5% 
clay), 0.36% total organic C, 2.47 mg/kg available N, 0.97 
mg/kg available P, 8.9 mg/kg available K, and 8.27 mg/kg 
available Mg. The pH of the dry soil was 5.1. Cucumber 
(Cucumis sativus L.) seeds were disinfected by dipping in 
2% NaOCl solution for 5 min and then washed four times 
with sterile double-distilled water. Three seeds were sown 
(3.0 cm deep) in each pot with or without 10 g of fungus 
inoculum (10-mL fungus suspension mixed with 10 g 
autoclaved commercial soil). The fungus inoculum was 
applied near the seeds during seeding. Treatments were 
replicated 12 times in a completely randomized block 
design. After 1 wk, the seedlings were thinned to two per 
pot. Seedlings were grown in an open environment, using 
tap water to maintain 70% of soil water-holding capacity. 
After 4 wk, plants were removed from the pots; roots and 
shoots were separated, and repeatedly washed in deionized 
water. The leaf chlorophyll content was measured using a 
SPAD-502 chlorophyll meter (Konica Minolata, Tokyo, 
Japan). The total soluble protein content in the leaf was 
estimated according to the Bradford method [22] and 
starch was estimated by using phenol sulfuric acid reagent 
[23]. Shoot and root dry weights were measured after oven </p>

<p>First Report on Plant Growth-Promoting Penicillium menonorum from Korea 51 </p>

<p>drying at 60 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C to a constant weight. The P concentration in 
dried leaves (dried at 65 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C) was measured [24]. Soil available 
P [25] and the acid phosphatase [26] and dehydrogenase 
[27] enzyme activities were estimated. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Data were subjected to an analysis 
of variance (ANOVA) and means were compared using 
Tukey's test at p &lt; 0.05. Statistical analyses were performed 
using <rs id="software-4" type="software">SigmaPlot</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Systat Software Inc</rs>., San Jose, CA, 
USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Fungus isolation and identification. A large number 
of different microfungi were isolated and tentatively 
identified based on phenotypic data (data not shown). 
Among these fungi, the Penicillium sp. KNU-3 showed 
distinct morphology and was selected and studied in 
detail. The fungus colonies on PDA (Fig. 1A) attained 141 
8 mm (maximum, 20 mm) diameters after 7 days growth 
at 25 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. The vegetative hyphae were velutinous-silky, radially 
sulcate peripherally, and centrally raised by approximately 
2~3 mm. Sporulation was moderate, the central region 
was pale bluish to dark gray, the peripheral area was 
white, and a clear rosy exudate was observed in the center. 
No sclerotia or ascomata appeared. The colony reverse 
was yellow with a yellow-brown or reddish-brown center. 
Conidiophores (Fig. 1C) were simple, arising from basal and </p>

<p>aerial hyphae, smooth-walled, hyaline, 5~15 (~20) × 1.52 
.0 µm, nonvesiculate, with an apical whorl of (1~) 2~5 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Penicillium menonorum KNU-3. A, Colonies grown 7 
d at 25 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C on potato dextrose agar showing a pale blue-gray 
color in the central area where the fungus is sporulating; B, 
Colony showing white in reverse; C, Conidiophores, phialides, 
and conidia; D, Conidia (roughened conidia) (scale bars: C = 
15 µm, D = 2 µm). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Neighbor-joining phylogenetic analysis of the Penicillium menonorum partial 18S-ITS1-5.8S-ITS2-28S rDNA region 
sequence obtained from crop field soil in Korea. The sequence obtained in this study is shown in boldface. Numerical values on 
branches are the bootstrap values as percentage of bootstrap replication from 1,000 replicate analysis. The scale represents 
substitution per site. </p>

<p>52 Babu et al. </p>

<p>fields 5~7 (~9) by 2.5~3.5-µm-bearing conidia. Conidia 
were spherical to subspherical, (2~) 2.5~3.5 µm (Fig. 1D), 
with rugose surface. In order to confirm the morphological 
results, the isolate KNU-3 was further identified through 
analysis of the rDNA ITS region. </p>

<p>Molecular identification. The ITS sequence of the P. 
menonorum KNU-3 isolate was 100% identical to the 
culture collection NRRL: 50410 of P. menonorum S. W. 
Peterson sp. nov (GenBank accession No. HQ646591). The 
phylogenetic analysis of KNU-3 was carried out by 
distance tree construction. The ITS1 sequence of KNU-3 
was aligned with sequences of available P. menonorum 
strains and its nearest species through the <rs type="software">BLAST</rs> sequence 
using <rs type="software">MultAlin program</rs>, and a neighbor-joining tree was 
constructed from the aligned sequences. The phylogenetic 
analysis revealed that the isolate was grouped with a reference 
isolate of P. menonorum with 99% bootstrap value support 
(Fig. 2), and was distinct from other Penicillium spp., which 
were grouped in distinct clades. These results indicate that 
the isolate KNU-3 is closely related to P. menonorum. 
Based on morphological properties, sequence homology, 
and phylogenetic analysis, the isolate KNU-3 was thus 
identified as P. menonorum. </p>

<p>PGP traits. P. menonorum KNU-3 was able to produce 
siderophores in the plate-based assay as evidenced by the 
formation of a yellow zone on the CAS agar medium plate 
(Supplementary Fig. 1A). While the fungal isolate produced 
a significant amount of IAA (9.7 mg/L), no ACC deaminase 
activity was detected. As shown in Table 1, P-solubilization 
increased from day 2 to day 6 with a value ranging from 
198 to 408 mg/L (Supplementary Fig. 1B). The pH of the 
medium decreased up to 6 days ranging from 6.2 to 5.1 
with an increase of soluble P. After 5 days of incubation, 
soluble P decreased slowly with a concomitant slight pH 
increase of the medium (Table 1). </p>

<p>Plant growth promotion and soil enzyme activity. 
The isolate promoted root and shoot growth of cucumber 
plants, with a concomitant increase in the dry biomass of 
the shoots and roots compared with the uninoculated controls 
(Fig. 3A). Inoculation also resulted in a significantly higher 
total chlorophyll content (16%) (Fig. 3B) as well as an 
accumulation of total starch (45%) and protein content 
(22%) (Fig. 4). KNU-3 inoculation significantly increased 
the total P content (510 mg/L) in plant shoots compared to 
uninoculated controls (460 mg/L). Soil inoculation with 
KNU-3 resulted in significantly enhanced levels of organic </p>

<p>Table 1. Amount of P solubilization and change of pH in liquid culture medium supplemented with tri-calcium phosphate 
(TCP) and inoculated with Penicillium menonorum KNU-3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>Amount of available P (mg/L) and change of pH </p>

<p>2 days 
4 days 
6 days 
8 days </p>

<p>Soluble P 
pH 
Soluble P 
pH 
Soluble P 
pH 
Soluble P 
pH </p>

<p>Uninoculated </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>41 ± 1.4 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>6.8 ± 0.4* 
44 ± 1.1* 
6.6 ± 0.3* 
43 ± 0.3* 
6.7 ± 0.2* 
43 ± 1.4* 
6.7 ± 0.2* 
KNU-3 
198 ± 6.6* 
6.2 ± 0.6* 
369 ± 11.4* 5.5 ± 0.6* 
408 ± 28.0* 5.1 ± 0.7* 
373 ± 22.6* 5.3 ± 0.7* </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The experiment were performed twice with three replicates for each treatment. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Mean and standard deviation. An asterisk (*) indicates a significant difference between uninoculated liquid culture medium and liquid 
culture medium inoculated with KNU-3 (p &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Dry biomass (A) and leaf chlorophyll content (B) of cucumber plants grown in uninoculated soil and in soil inoculated 
with Penicillium menonorum KNU-3. Error bars indicate standard deviations of the means (n = 12). Bars with the same letter 
are not significantly different at p &lt; 0.05 according to Tukey's test. </p>

<p>First Report on Plant Growth-Promoting Penicillium menonorum from Korea 53 </p>

<p>carbon (3.9%) and available P (3.4 mg/L) of the soil compared 
to that of uninoculated soil organic carbon (4.6%) and 
available P (2.9 mg/L). The enzyme activity of dehydrogenase 
gives an indication of an active microbial population in the 
soil. Inoculation with KNU-3 induced a significant increase 
in dehydrogenase activity (30%) compared with uninoculated 
soil (Fig. 5A). In addition, a significant elevated acid 
phosphatase activity (19%) was observed in soil inoculated 
with KNU-3 compared to the uninoculated soil (Fig. 5B). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Numerous microfungi were isolated in the present study to 
investigate the fungal community in Jeongseon, Gangwon-
do, Korea. Among these isolates, one Penicillium sp. showed </p>

<p>definitive similarity matches with P. menonorum. In order 
to confirm the morphological results, molecular identification 
of the isolate was carried out based on ITS sequence 
analysis. The ITS sequence of the isolate was compared to 
the GenBank database sequences by using the NCBI-
<rs type="software">BLAST</rs> search program, and it was found to be identical to 
the type strain NRRL: 50410 of P. menonorum S.W. Peterson 
sp. nov. In addition, the phylogenetic tree revealed that the 
isolate was grouped in a distinct clade together with P. 
menonorum with bootstrap support value of 100% (Fig. 2). 
Morphological and molecular characteristics of the isolate 
were in agreement with the description by Peterson et al. 
[15]. P. menonorum S.W. Peterson sp. nov. is a phenotypically 
and genotypically broadly circumscribed new species that 
was first isolated from garden soil in southern California 
by Peterson et al. [15], and P. menonorum isolation from 
Panax ginseng has been reported in China [28]. Nevertheless, 
to our knowledge, this study presents the first record of P. 
menonorum in Korea. 
Many microbial-based agricultural techniques have 
been developed to exploit potential mechanisms for the 
enhancement of crop production in different soils. Although 
members of the genus Penicillium are common opportunistic 
pathogens in the soil environment, some Penicillium strains 
associated with the different plant rhizospheres are able to 
solubilize inorganic insoluble P salts and promote plant 
growth in the soil. Thus, the growth-promoting capacity of 
P. menonorum KNU-3 was evaluated by assaying for IAA 
and siderophore production, ACC deaminase activity, and 
P solubilization. IAA secreted by microorganisms promotes 
root growth through a direct stimulatory effect on plant 
cell elongation or cell division [29]. In the present study, 
P. menonorum KNU-3 was positive for both IAA and 
siderophore production. Other researchers have made 
similar observations for the IAA production by Penicillium 
sp. [11]. Siderophores are important metabolites released 
by the PGP microorganisms that directly alleviate iron </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Starch and protein content in leaves of cucumber 
plants grown in uninoculated soil and in soil inoculated with 
Penicillium menonorum KNU-3. Error bars indicate standard 
deviations of the means (n = 12). Bars with the same letter 
are not significantly different at p &lt; 0.05 according to Tukey's 
test. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Dehydrogenase (A) and acid phosphatase (B) activities in uninoculated soil and in soil inoculated with Penicillium 
menonorum KNU-3. Error bars indicate standard deviations of the means (n = 12). Bars with the same letter are not significantly 
different at p &lt; 0.05 according to Tukey's test. TPF, triphenylformazan. </p>



<p>deficiency by increasing the supply of iron to the plant and 
indirectly depriving fungal pathogens of iron [30, 31]. 
Kang et al. [32] reported that siderophores are also able to 
chelate Mg </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, and Al 
3+ from a soil solution. In this 
study, the isolate showed both IAA production and the 
presence of siderophores, which may provide an explanation 
for its PGP activity. Several studies have demonstrated that 
production of siderophores, other secondary metabolites, 
and lytic enzymes by Penicillium spp. were most effective 
in promoting plant growth and controlling plant root 
pathogens. 
The inoculation of P-solubilizing fungi in P-deficient 
soil has been reported to increase the available P content 
in the soil and the P uptake in plants. Thus, the efficiency 
of P. menonorum for its phosphate-solubilizing activity was 
quantitatively estimated at different time intervals in liquid 
medium during the in vitro study. The level of P availability 
in the culture filtrate was significantly increased by decreasing 
the pH of the medium up to the 5th day (Fig. 2). However, 
a significant drop in soluble P levels was observed on later 
days (Fig. 2). This could be due to the depletion of nutrients 
in the culture medium [32], limiting the availability of the 
soluble form of P, which has an inhibitory effect on further 
P solubilization [33]. In addition, the formation of an 
organo-phosphate compound induced by the release of 
organic metabolites might have reduced the amount of 
available P [34]. In this study, phosphate solubilization was 
accompanied by a decrease in the pH of the medium. The 
results of this study are in agreement with other studies on 
the effect of pH on the solubilization of the P source. 
The decrease in pH indicates the production of organic 
acids, which chelate cations through their carboxylic acid 
group and convert it into the soluble form. Nonetheless, 
phosphate-solubilizing microorganisms solubilize inorganic 
phosphates by several mechanisms, including the production 
of organic acids [35], polysaccharides [36], and phosphatase 
enzymes (mainly acid phosphatases) [37]. Periodic estimation 
of available P in the medium revealed the potential of the 
isolate to release P from insoluble phosphate sources from 
agricultural soil. In addition to P solubilization, KNU-3 
also produced other secondary metabolites such as IAA and 
siderophores. Evidence pointing to plant growth promotion 
by P-solubilizing microorganisms through the production 
of IAA and siderophores renders the P-solubilizing 
microorganisms more suitable as biofertilizers [29]. 
Based on plant growth promoting traits, a pot experiment 
was conducted to test the effect of KNU-3 inoculation on 
concurrent plant growth promotion in the cucumber 
plants. Soil inoculation with KNU-3 significantly increased 
the dry biomass by 53%. It is expected that inoculation 
with KNU-3 exhibiting PGP traits consequently promotes 
the growth promotion of the soil-plant system. Inoculation 
resulted in significantly higher chlorophyll contents of 
cucumber plants. Our results agree with a previous report 
of significant increases in chlorophyll content in leaves of 
pomegranate [3] after inoculation with P. pinophilum. </p>

<p>Rasouli-Sadaghiani et al. [38] suggested that the enhanced 
chlorophyll content may be correlated with higher iron 
acquisition, and that this can be considered as a marker of 
iron availability to the plant system. 
Both starch and protein contents are important 
measurements for plant health and fruit yield. In this 
study, the P. menonorum inoculation significantly increased 
the starch and protein contents of the plants compared 
with the control plants. The main mechanisms potentially 
involved are the mobilization of insoluble sources of P-
bearing minerals and subsequent enhancement of uptake 
and production of siderophores/plant growth regulators 
that enhance photosynthesis rate and plant growth, which 
results in higher starch and protein contents in cucumber 
plants. The beneficial effects of certain Penicillium spp. in 
terms of plant growth promotion and biological control have 
been reported by many researchers. Recently, Radhakrishnan 
et al. [11] reported enhancement of shoot length, root 
length, and fresh and dry seedling weight of sesame plants 
under salt stress when co-cultivated with Penicillium sp.. 
Soil inoculation with P. pinophilum was found to increase 
N, P, and K uptake, which resulted in improved growth, 
significantly higher leaf area index, and an elevated 
photosynthetic rate of pomegranate plant [3]. However, to the 
best of our knowledge, this is the first study to demonstrate 
that P. menonorum can increase chlorophyll, starch, and 
protein contents, as well as the yield of cucumber plants. 
The organic content in soil samples has been considered 
one of the key determinants driving the microbial community 
structure [39]. The increased amount of organic carbon in 
KNU-3-inoculated soil indicates decomposition of organic 
wastes, organic matter formation, and nutrient cycling by 
KNU-3 or other microorganisms in the rhizospheric soil. 
Because P in soil is likely to be fixed, it is usually present 
in trace amounts and is relatively unavailable to plants. 
The increase in P uptake by cucumber plants and higher 
concentrations of available P in soil reported in this study 
might be due to solubilization of insoluble P present in the 
soil by phosphate-solubilizing P. menonorum, thereby 
enhancing the P uptake. It has been reported that P-
solubilizing Penicillium spp. are capable of solubilizing 
the unavailable forms of P in P-bearing minerals in soil 
through the production and excretion of organic acids, 
phosphatase, and phytase enzymes [3, 40]. 
Soil enzymes are important catalyzers of several reactions 
required for life processes of microorganisms in soils and 
the stabilization of soil structure, the decomposition of 
organic wastes, organic matter formation, and nutrient 
cycling [41]. Among the soil enzymes, dehydrogenase and 
acid phosphatase play an important role in oxidative 
metabolism, and thus in determining the metabolic activity 
of microorganisms and P-mineralization in soils, respectively. 
In this study, dehydrogenase and acid phosphatase activities 
were increased in KNU-3-inoculated treatments compared 
with the non-inoculated control treatment. These results 
confirm earlier reports demonstrating greater P uptake by </p>

<p>First Report on Plant Growth-Promoting Penicillium menonorum from Korea 55 </p>

<p>plants, mobilization of insoluble P, dehydrogenase, and 
acid phosphatase activity in soil when inoculated with 
Penicillium pinophilum [3]. The enhanced enzymatic activities 
in soil is associated with an increase in the availability of 
nutrients to the plants, which in turn have a positive 
influence on soil fertility [42]. KNU-3 was capable of 
increasing the organic carbon, available P, and enzyme 
activities, which are all beneficial characteristics to improve 
crop productivity in sustainable agriculture. 
The present study has established that P. menonorum 
exhibits not only plant growth promoting attributes in 
vitro, but also has a positive effect on the growth of 
cucumber plants than the non-inoculated plants in in vivo. 
This is the first report of P. menonorum isolated from crop 
field soil in Korea. Furthermore, it is the first time we 
report plant growth promoting attributes of P. menonorum 
and its positive effect on the growth enhancement of 
cucumber plants in in vitro. Summarizing the discussion 
above, it can be concluded that the P. menonorum species 
can be used as a biofertilizer after the conduction of 
further extensive field trials. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Institute of 
Biological Resources (NIBR) under the Ministry of 
Environment, Republic of Korea, for the project on survey 
and excavation of Korean indigenous fungal species and 
University-Industry Cooperation Foundation of Kangwon 
National University, Korea. We would like to express our 
sincere thanks to Hongcheon Agriculture Technology Center 
for providing the soil sample. </p>

<p>ELECTRONIC SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplementary data including one figure can be found 
with this article online at http://www.mycobiology.or.kr/ 
src/sm/mb-43-49-s001.pdf. </p>



</text></tei>