<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4930280" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Endothelial dysfunction plays a central role in the devel-
opment and progression of vascular diseases. Endothelial 
progenitor cells (EPCs), which are mobilized from bone mar-
row to the vascular endothelium, are vital for endothelial re-
pair, functioning directly through differentiation and indirectly 
through paracrine effects. Oxidative stress caused by free 
radicals, oxygen anions and peroxides is closely associated 
with the initiation, development and progression of vascular 
diseases (Heitzer et al., 2001; Yoshii et al., 2006; Schleicher  and Friess, 2007; Cachofeiro et al., 2008; Battelli et al., 2014)  and has direct cytotoxic effects on the endothelium (Griendling  and FitzGerald, 2003; Harrison et al., 2003) and EPCs (Hung  et al., 2003; Urbich et al., 2005; Thum et al., 2006; Thum et al.,  2007; Watson et al., 2008). However, the specific mechanism 
of these effects is not clear, and the roles of calcium and cal-
cium signaling in this mechanism are undefined. 
Calcium is an important ion that regulates a variety of activi-
ties, including muscle contraction, skeleton formation, and cell 
proliferation, migration and apoptosis. Store-operated calcium 
channels (SOCs; also known as SOCCs) mediate store-op-
erated calcium entry (SOCE) and are expressed ubiquitously </p>

<p>in non-excitable cells, such as EPCs (Lewis, 2007). Previous 
studies have demonstrated that SOCE in embryonic fibro-
blasts is critical for the oxidative stress response (Henke et  al., 2012). Numerous studies have suggested that oxidative 
stress enhances the inward flow of calcium, leading to intra-
cellular calcium overload (Caron et al., 2007) and ultimately, 
cell apoptosis (Henke et al., 2013). Therefore, we hypothe-
sized that SOCE may play a significant role in oxidative stress-
induced apoptosis in EPCs. Inhibition of SOCE may protect 
EPCs from oxidative stress-induced apoptosis, thus making 
SOCE a potential target for the treatment of various vascular 
diseases. 
Stromal interaction molecule (STIM) proteins are localized 
to the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and act as sensors of ER 
calcium. These proteins play a direct role in the ER-plasma 
membrane (PM) junction (Rebecchi and Pentyala, 2000; Liou  et al., 2005). They regulate extracellular calcium via SOCE or 
capacitative calcium entry (Roos et al., 2005). Studies by our 
group have indicated that both shRNA (shSTIM1) and ML-9, 
an SOCE antagonist, protect EPCs from injuries induced by 
oxidative stress. Further work has suggested that this protec-
tion may involve interference with multiple factors associated 
with intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS), ER stress </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(4), 371-379 (2016) </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author </p>

<p>E-mail: huanglan260@126.com 
Tel: +86-02368755601, Fax: +86-02368755601 </p>

<p>Received Aug 17, 2015 Revised Nov 9, 2015 Accepted Nov 17, 2015 
Published Online Jul 1, 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2015.130 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 The Korean Society of Applied Pharmacology </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licens-
es/by-nc/4.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>Inhibition of Store-Operated Calcium Entry Protects Endothelial 
Progenitor Cells from H 2 O 2 -Induced Apoptosis </p>

<p>Yan-Wei Wang, Ji-Hang Zhang, Yang Yu, Jie Yu and Lan Huang* </p>

<p>Institute of Cardiovascular Diseases of PLA, Xinqiao Hospital, Third Military Medical University, Chongqing 400037, People's Republic of China </p>

<p>Store-operated calcium entry (SOCE), a major mode of extracellular calcium entry, plays roles in a variety of cell activities. Ac-
cumulating evidence indicates that the intracellular calcium ion concentration and calcium signaling are critical for the responses 
induced by oxidative stress. The present study was designed to investigate the potential effect of SOCE inhibition on H2O2-in-
duced apoptosis in endothelial progenitor cells (EPCs), which are the predominant cells involved in endothelial repair. The results 
showed that H2O2-induced EPC apoptosis was reversed by SOCE inhibition induced either using the SOCE antagonist ML-9 
or via silencing of stromal interaction molecule 1 (STIM1), a component of SOCE. Furthermore, SOCE inhibition repressed the 
increases in intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) levels and endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress and ameliorated the mito-
chondrial dysfunction caused by H2O2. Our findings provide evidence that SOCE inhibition exerts a protective effect on EPCs in 
response to oxidative stress induced by H2O2 and may serve as a potential therapeutic strategy against vascular endothelial injury. </p>

<p>Key Words: Endothelial progenitor cells, Oxidative stress, SOCE, STIM 1, ML-9 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2015.130 </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(4), 371-379 (2016) </p>

<p>and mitochondrial dysfunction. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cell culture and characterization of EPCs </p>

<p>Male Sprague-Dawley rats were sacrificed by injection of 
an overdose of sodium pentobarbital (100 mg/kg) into the peri-
toneal cavity (Zhao et al., 2008), according to the standards of 
the American Veterinary Medical Association Panel on Eutha-
nasia. Bone marrow-derived EPCs (BM-EPCs) were isolated 
from the femurs and tibias of rats through density-gradient 
centrifugation (Sigma-aldrich, St. Louis, USA) according to es-
tablished methods. Isolated EPCs were cultured in Dulbecco's 
modified Eagle's medium (Gibco, Grand Island, USA) at 37°C 
under 5% CO2 and 100% humidity. EPCs were cultured for 
7 days before being utilized in experiments. To confirm the 
identities of EPCs, cells were incubated with acLDL-DiI (10 
mg/ml) for 6 h and then fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 15 
min, incubated with fluorescein isothiocyanate-labeled lectin 
(UEA-1; 10 mg/ml) for 1 h and examined under a laser confo-
cal scanning microscope (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany) (Kuang et 
al., 2012). Cells that were double positive for acLDL-DiI and 
UEA-1 were identified as EPCs. Approximately 85% of cells 
were positive for both markers. </p>

<p>ShRNA transfection </p>

<p>STIM1 expression was silenced using a lentiviral vector 
carrying stromal interaction molecule 1 (STIM1) shRNA con-</p>

<p>structed by GenePharma (Shanghai, China). EPCs were cul-
tured in 6-well plates 2 days before transfection. Cells were 
infected with the lentiviral vector at a multiplicity of infection of 
100 for 48 h. The STIM1 shRNA sequence was GCGACTTCT-
GAAGAGTCTACC. The negative control shRNA sequence 
was TTCTCCGAACGTGTCACGT. The efficiency of shRNA 
transfection was confirmed by Western blot analysis. </p>

<p>Cell viability assay </p>

<p>A cell viability assay was performed using a Cell Counting 
Kit-8 (CCK-8) (Beyotime, Jiangsu, China) in accordance with 
the manufacturer's protocol. After 7 days of culturing, EPCs 
were trypsinized (HyClone, Utah, USA) and seeded into 96-
well plates (approximately 5,000 cells/well). Cell viability was 
quantified by measuring absorbance at 450 nm with a micro-
plate reader (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, USA) after cells 
were treated with processing factors and incubated with CCK-
8. The results were expressed as a percentage of the control 
group (Hou et al., 2007; Zhang and Sun, 2010). </p>

<p>Apoptosis assay </p>

<p>EPC apoptosis was evaluated with a FITC-Annexin V 
Apoptosis Detection Kit (Neo Bioscience, Beijing, China). 
After 7 days of culturing, EPCs were treated with process-
ing factors and then trypsinized and treated with Annexin V-
FITC and propidium iodide (PI). The treated cells were finally 
counted via flow cytometry (Beckman coulter, Indianapolis, 
USA) following the manufacturer's protocol. The results were 
expressed as the percentages of cells in the second quadrant </p>

<p>Fig. 1. H 2 O 2 -induced cytotoxicity and apoptotic cell death involve disruption of intracellular calcium homeostasis. After treatment with dif-</p>

<p>ferent concentrations of H 2 O 2 for 6 h, cell viability was measured using a CCK-8 kit (A). After pretreatment with BAPTA-AM (BA), cells were 
treated with H 2 O 2 for 6 h, and cell viability was measured (B). EPCs were pretreated with BAPTA-AM (BA) before exposure to H 2 O 2 for 6 h. 
The cells were then stained with Annexin V-FITC and propidium iodide (PI) and analyzed via flow cytometry (D). Quantitative data for An-
nexin V-FITC/PI staining is presented (C). *p&lt;0.05; 
# p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>BA </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 
BA </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Apoptosis rate (%) </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>BA </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 
BA </p>

<p>C 
A </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
2 0 0 
4 0 0 
6 0 0 
8 0 0 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 , 0 0 0 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>H O ( M) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>PI </p>

<p>AnnexinV-FITC </p>

<p>H O 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>H O 
2 2 +BA </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>BA </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>



<p>Wang et al. SOCE Inhibition Protects EPCs from H 2 O 2 -Induced Apoptosis </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>(early apoptosis) and third quadrant (late apoptosis). </p>

<p>Calcium imaging </p>

<p>Intracellular calcium concentration was measured with the 
Fluo-3AM calcium indicator. EPCs were pretreated with 50 μM 
ML-9 or shSTIM1, incubated with Fluo-3AM for 30 min in the 
dark, washed 3 times with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), 
incubated in medium for 30 min, washed with PBS three times 
and placed in a calcium-containing or calcium-free solution. 
The cells were then observed under a laser scanning confo-
cal microscope at an excitation wavelength of 488 nm and 
emission wavelengths alternating between 525 nm and 530 
nm. The results were analyzed with specific software (Li et  al., 2009). </p>

<p>Detection of ROS in EPCs </p>

<p>To detect intracellular ROS in EPCs, we used a Reactive 
Oxygen Species Assay Kit (Beyotime), which detects changes </p>

<p>in intracellular ROS using the DCFH-DA fluorescent probe. 
EPCs were treated with processing factors and then incubated 
with DCFH-DA and observed under a laser scanning confocal 
microscope at a 488 nm excitation wavelength and a 525 nm 
emission wavelength. The results were evaluated based on 
the intensity of the intracellular fluorescence (Jia et al., 2006). </p>

<p>Measurement of the mitochondrial membrane potential 
(MMP) </p>

<p>The MMP was measured using the fluorescent dye rhoda-
mine123 (Rh123) (Beyotime). Rh123 rapidly passes through 
the PM and is sequestered by active mitochondria within a 
few minutes. In our experiments, EPCs were cultured with 2 
μM Rh123 for 30 min at 37°C in the dark and then washed 
with PBS. The results were estimated by determining the gray 
values of the cells. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Inhibition of SOCE attenuates the detrimental effects of H 2 O 2 on EPCs. Representative immunoblots (top) and quantification (bot-</p>

<p>tom) of STIM1 expression 48 h after transfection (A). EPCs that had been cultured for 7 days were pretreated with ML-9 for 20 min or with 
STIM1 shRNA before the addition of H 2 O 2 for 6 h. Cell viability (B) and apoptosis (C) were then measured. The relative expression levels of 
caspase 12 (D) and caspase 9 (E) were measured by Western blot analysis. *p&lt;0.05; 
# p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -</p>

<p>1 
S t i m </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
Relative expression </p>

<p>of caspase12 (fold of control) </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>Caspase12 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
M 
L -9 
s h -</p>

<p>1 
S t i m 
C 
o n t r o l 
s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -</p>

<p>1 
S t i m </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
Relative expression </p>

<p>of caspase9 (fold of control) </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>Caspase9 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l M 
L -9 
s h -</p>

<p>1 
S t i m 
C 
o n t r o l 
s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -S T I M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 
Cell viability (%) </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 M 
L -9 C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -S T I M </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 
Apoptosis rate (%) </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 M 
L -9 C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -S t i m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
Relative expression of Stim1 
(fold of control) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Stim1 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l s h -S t i m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2015.130 </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(4), 371-379 (2016) </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>After the various treatments were performed, proteins were 
extracted from EPCs using a lysis buffer (RIPA) containing 
phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride (PMSF). Protein concentra-
tions were determined with a BCA protein assay kit. Equal 
amounts of protein (30 μg per lane) were separated via sodi-
um dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-</p>

<p>PAGE) and then transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) 
membranes. The membranes were blocked with 5% non-fat 
milk in Tris-buffered saline containing 0.5% Tween 20 and then 
incubated with specific primary antibodies. The membranes 
were subsequently incubated with appropriate secondary anti-
bodies and then visualized with a luminescent image analyzer 
(GE, Connecticut, USA). </p>

<p>[Ca ] Fluo-3AM F/F </p>

<p>2+ cyt 0 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>Time (sec) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>[Ca ] Fluo-3AM F/F </p>

<p>2+ cyt 0 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>Time (sec) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Free Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>with Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>with Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>Free Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>H O +ML-9 </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>[Ca ] Fluo-3AM F/F </p>

<p>2+ cyt 0 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>Time (sec) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 </p>

<p>H O +sh-Control </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O +sh-STIM1 </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Free Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>with Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Inhibition of SOCE restores intracellular calcium homeostasis. EPCs that had been cultured for 7 days were treated with thapsigar-</p>

<p>gin (TG) (A) or pretreated with ML-9 for 20 min (B) or with STIM1 shRNA (C) before exposure to H 2 O 2 in a calcium-free solution, followed by 
treatment with 2 mM CaCl 2 . The intracellular calcium concentration was then measured using Fluo-3AM, a calcium indicator. </p>

<p>Control 
H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O 
2 2 +ML-9 </p>

<p>Control 
H O 
2 2 +sh-Control 
H O 
2 2 +sh-Stim1 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Relative ROS level 
(fold of control) </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -S t i m </p>

<p>1 
M 
L -9 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p># 
# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Inhibition of SOCE prevents intracellular ROS accumulation. EPCs that had been cultured for 7 days were pretreated with ML-9 </p>

<p>for 20 min or with STIM1 shRNA before exposure to H 2 O 2 for 6 h, and intracellular ROS levels were evaluated using a fluorescence probe 
(DCFHDA). *p&lt;0.05; 
# p&lt;0.05. </p>



<p>Wang et al. SOCE Inhibition Protects EPCs from H 2 O 2 -Induced Apoptosis </p>



<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed, and the data were ex-
pressed as the mean ± standard deviation (SD) of five expe-
riments. <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">16.0</rs> was utilized for data analysis. The t-test 
was employed to compare two groups, and one-way analysis 
of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare multiple groups. A 
p-value&lt;0.05 was regarded as statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>H 2 O 2 -induced cytotoxicity and apoptotic cell death 
involve disruption of intracellular calcium homeostasis </p>

<p>EPCs (cultured for 7 days) were exposed to various con-
centrations (200, 400, 600, 800 and 1000 μM) of H2O2 for 6 h, 
and cytotoxicity was determined with a CCK-8 kit. As shown in 
Fig. 1A, H2O2 induced cytotoxicity in a dose-dependent man-
ner. When the H2O2 concentration was increased to 600 μM, 
cell viability was approximately 50%. This concentration was 
used in the following experiments. H2O2-induced apoptosis 
was detected via flow cytometry. To assess whether intracel-
lular calcium was involved in the H2O2-induced cytotoxicity 
and apoptosis of EPCs, we pretreated EPCs with BAPTA-AM 
(BA), an intracellular free calcium chelator (Fig. 1B-1D). The 
addition of BA (10 μM) attenuated the H2O2-induced injury of 
EPCs, suggesting that H2O2-induced injury may be related to 
disruption of intracellular calcium homeostasis. </p>

<p>Inhibition of SOCE attenuates the detrimental effects of 
H 2 O 2 on EPCs </p>

<p>To investigate the effects of SOCE inhibition, we utilized 
ML-9 (50 μM), an antagonist of SOCE, and silenced the ex-
pression of STIM1 by shRNA (Fig. 2A). This method was used 
for SOCE in the following experiments. As hypothesized, the 
H2O2-induced decrease in EPC viability and increase in EPC 
apoptosis were reversed by the inhibition of SOCE (Fig. 2B, 
2C). In addition, the H2O2-induced up-regulation of caspase 
12 , which is responsible for ER stress-induced apoptosis (Ra-
sheva and Domingos, 2009), and caspase 9, which is closely 
related to the mitochondrial apoptotic pathway, was signifi-
cantly attenuated by SOCE inhibition (Fig. 2D, 2E). </p>

<p>Inhibition of SOCE restores intracellular calcium 
homeostasis </p>

<p>Numerous data have demonstrated that calcium entry 
through SOCE channels is a common and ubiquitous mecha-
nism of regulating calcium entry and that SOCE is the main 
mode of calcium entry into EPCs. Thus, we performed calcium 
imaging to determine whether H2O2 affects calcium signaling in 
EPCs through SOCE. H2O2 stimulation of EPCs in a calcium-
free buffer led to an increase in cytosolic calcium due to calcium 
release from the ER (left peaks in Fig. 3B, 3C). The addition of 
calcium after cytosolic calcium level slowed down resulted in 
calcium influx through the PM (right peaks in Fig. 3B, 3C) due 
to the depletion of ER stores. These results were considered 
typical calcium imaging results for SOCE and were similar 
to thapsigargin (TG; 2 μM)-induced calcium fluxes (Fig. 3A). 
Therefore, H2O2-induced calcium changes potentially occur 
mainly through SOCE. Furthermore, the inhibition of SOCE 
resulted in a significant decrease in cytosolic calcium in re-
sponse to H2O2 insult (Fig. 3B, 3C). </p>

<p>Inhibition of SOCE prevents intracellular ROS accumulation </p>

<p>To investigate the role of ROS in the protective effects of 
SOCE inhibition, we used the fluorescent probe DCFH-DA to 
detect intracellular ROS production. Compared with the con-
trol group, the H2O2 treatment group exhibited significantly in-
creased ROS accumulation, and the inhibition of SOCE mark-
edly blunted this effect (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Inhibition of SOCE protects EPCs from ER stress </p>

<p>Many studies have demonstrated that ER stress is often ac-
companied by increased ROS production. To assess the pro-
tective effect of SOCE inhibition, we measured the expression 
of ER stress-related proteins. As shown in Fig. 5A, 5B, the 
expression levels of C/EBP homologous protein (CHOP) and </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -S t i m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 
Relative expression of (fold of control) </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>CHOP </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
M 
L -9 
s h -</p>

<p>1 
S t i m 
C 
o n t r o l 
s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -S t i m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
Relative expression of 
BIP (fold of control) </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>BIP </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
M 
L -9 
s h -</p>

<p>1 
S t i m 
C 
o n t r o l 
s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p># 
# </p>

<p># 
# </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Inhibition of SOCE protects EPCs from ER stress. EPCs </p>

<p>that had been cultured for 7 days were pretreated with ML-9 for 20 
min or with STIM1 shRNA before treatment with H 2 O 2 for 6 h. The 
expression of the ER stress-related proteins CHOP (A) and BIP (B) 
was evaluated by Western blot analysis. *p&lt;0.05; 
# p&lt;0.05. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2015.130 </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(4), 371-379 (2016) </p>

<p>CRP78/BIP were up-regulated by H2O2 stimulation compared 
with that of the control group. Moreover, the inhibition of SOCE 
suppressed the expression of ER stress-related proteins. </p>

<p>Inhibition of SOCE ameliorates H 2 O 2 -induced mitochon-
drial dysfunction </p>

<p>To demonstrate the effects of SOCE inhibition on the re-
pair of mitochondrial dysfunction, we measured the MMP by 
Rh123 staining. After incubation with H2O2, the MMP was re-
duced compared with that of the control group, and this effect 
was ameliorated by SOCE inhibition (Fig. 6B). Moreover, the 
results of Western blot analysis suggested that H2O2 treatment 
up-regulated the cytosolic cytochrome C level compared with 
that of the control group (Fig. 6A). As predicted, SOCE inhibi-
tion significantly reduced the detrimental effects induced by </p>

<p>H2O2. Furthermore, we observed the effects of SOCE inhibi-
tion on Bcl-2 family members, which play a vital role in the mi-
tochondrial pro-apoptotic signaling pathway. Exposure to H2O2 
led to a decrease in the Bcl-2/Bax ratio compared with that of 
the control group (Fig. 6C), and this decrease was amelio-
rated by SOCE inhibition. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study has shown for the first time that SOCE plays key 
roles in the H2O2-induced decrease in EPC cell viability and 
increase in EPC apoptosis. We have also demonstrated that 
SOCE inhibition attenuates H2O2-induced EPC cytotoxicity 
and apoptosis. First, H2O2 insult activated the process known </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -S t i m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
Relative expression </p>

<p>of cytochrome C 
(fold control) </p>

<p>of </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>Cytochrome C </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l M 
L -9 
s h -</p>

<p>1 
S t i m 
C 
o n t r o l 
s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l 
s h -S t i m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
Ratio of Bcl-2/Bax (fold of control) </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>Bcl-2 </p>

<p>Bax </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l M 
L -9 
s h -S </p>

<p>1 
t i m 
C 
o n t r o l 
s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p># 
# </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O 
2 2 +ML-9 
Control </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># 
# </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
Relative MMP level 
(fold of control) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>M 
L -9 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>s h -C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>H O 
2 2 +sh-Control 
H O 
2 2 +sh-Stim1 
Control </p>

<p>s h -S t i m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Inhibition of SOCE ameliorates H 2 O 2 -induced mitochondrial dysfunction. EPCs that had been cultured for 7 days were pretreated </p>

<p>with ML-9 for 20 min or with STIM1 shRNA before treatment with H 2 O 2 for 6 h. The release of cytochrome C into the cytoplasm (A) and the 
Bcl-2/Bax ratio were measured by Western blot analysis (C). The MMP was measured via rhodamine 123 staining (B). *p&lt;0.05; 
# p&lt;0.05. </p>



<p>Wang et al. SOCE Inhibition Protects EPCs from H 2 O 2 -Induced Apoptosis </p>



<p>as calcium release-activated calcium influx. Second, SOCE 
inhibition suppressed H2O2-induced calcium influx. Third, 
SOCE inhibition attenuated H2O2-induced EPC cytotoxicity 
and apoptosis. Finally, SOCE inhibition significantly reversed 
the H2O2-mediated induction of several key pro-apoptotic sig-
naling pathways mediated by ER stress and mitochondrial 
dysfunction. Taken together, our results demonstrate that 
SOCE inhibition protects EPCs from H2O2-induced apoptosis. 
It is generally recognized that H2O2 insult leads to calcium 
influx and disruption of intracellular calcium homeostasis, fol-
lowed by an increase in ROS production (Ohyama et al., 2012). 
These changes further activate downstream apoptotic signal-
ing pathways and ultimately result in cell death. Accumulating 
evidence suggests that oxidative stress-induced injuries might 
be attenuated by stabilizing intracellular calcium homeosta-
sis (Godfraind, 2005; Ohyama et al., 2012). Moreover, some 
studies have indicated that antioxidants diminish increases in 
intracellular calcium levels (Pieper and Dondlinger, 1998; Su  et al., 1999). Although the specific mechanism of the reduction 
of intracellular calcium following antioxidant application is still 
not clear, we hypothesized that the decrease in intracellular 
ROS production in response to antioxidant insult might lead 
to a change in the intracellular calcium level. In the present 
study, we demonstrated that H2O2 insult resulted in calcium 
influx and increase in intracellular ROS levels. In addition, we 
found that SOCE inhibition prevented intracellular ROS accu-
mulation. To date, there have been no reports of the effect of 
antioxidants on calcium regulation in EPCs. Thus we will pay 
more attention to this aspect in our future study. 
SOCE, which occurs ubiquitously in non-excitable cells, 
plays an essential role in the regulation of intracellular calcium 
homeostasis. Accumulating evidence has demonstrated that 
SOCE is involved in oxidative stress (Törnquist et al., 2000;  Martín-Romero et al., 2008; Henke et al., 2013; Plomaritas et  al., 2014). However, the effect of SOCE on oxidative stress 
remains to be elucidated. Several studies have demonstrat-
ed that H2O2 insult weakens SOCE (Törnquist et al., 2000;  Plomaritas et al., 2014). Other studies have shown that H2O2 
insult augments SOCE and the influx of calcium ions (Rao et  al., 2013). These contradictory results may be explained by 
the activation of different signaling pathways in response to 
oxidative stress in different cell types. For example, the oxida-
tive stress-induced changes in calcium influx and SOCE are 
mediated by the activation of protein kinase C (PKC) in thy-
roid FRTL-5 cells (Törnquist et al., 2000) and by regulation of 
STIM1 expression in the HT22 cells (Rao et al., 2013). In the 
present study, the H2O2 insult-induced disruption of intracel-
lular calcium homeostasis was attenuated by inhibiting SOCE 
using ML-9 or via STIM1 silencing. These findings suggest 
that SOCE plays a critical role in oxidative stress. 
Accumulating evidence supports the notion that calcium 
and calcium signaling are involved in ER and mitochondrial 
activities (Arnaudeau et al., 2001; Pizzo and Pozzan, 2007). 
The ER, a site of major calcium stores, plays a critical role in 
a variety of cellular activities, such as protein synthesis, post-
translational modifications, protein folding and apoptosis. A 
prolonged decrease in the ER calcium level (Hooper et al.,  2013) or accumulation of unfolded or misfolded proteins within 
the ER (Hammadi et al., 2013) leads to ER stress. Prolonged 
ER stress further promotes the expression of CHOP, a CEBP 
family transcription factor, and caspase 12, thereby activat-
ing downstream apoptotic pathways. Moreover, ER stress can </p>

<p>result in sustained mitochondrial calcium accumulation (De- niaud et al., 2008). The mitochondria, which are also important 
calcium-buffering organelles, are physically and functionally 
interconnected with the ER. Mitochondria are often located 
near calcium release sites in the ER or at calcium influx chan-
nels at the PM, where they buffer intracellular calcium changes 
by modulating the rate of capacitative calcium entry through 
calcium release-activated channels (CRACs) or the rate of 
calcium release by IP3 receptors (Arnaudeau et al., 2001). 
Disruption of mitochondrial calcium homeostasis may result in 
dysfunction of the mitochondria, resulting in up-regulation of 
caspase 9 expression and enhanced release of cytochrome c 
from the mitochondria into the cytoplasm. Cytochrome c and 
caspase 9 form apoptotic bodies through the multiple polym-
erization of apoptotic protease activating factor 1 (Apaf-1), 
thereby activating downstream apoptotic pathways (Hikita et  al., 2015). Several published reports have suggested that vari-
ous apoptotic pathways are involved in the cross-talk between 
the ER and mitochondria (Wang and El-Deiry, 2004; Pizzo and  Pozzan, 2007). Cytochrome c, which plays a vital role in this 
cross-talk, translocates to the ER to bind inositol 1,4,5-triphos-
phate receptors, leading to sustained calcium release. This 
calcium release in turn triggers the release of cytochrome c. 
Importantly, cytochrome c is involved in these apoptotic path-
ways. The present study demonstrated that SOCE inhibition 
restored intracellular calcium homeostasis and suppressed 
the pro-apoptotic effect by reducing ER stress and preserving 
mitochondrial function. Taken together, these data show that 
communication between the ER and mitochondria is involved 
in the protective effect of SOCE inhibition against H2O2 insult. 
In conclusion, these findings have confirmed the role of 
SOCE in oxidative stress. H2O2-induced EPC apoptosis was 
shown to be alleviated by SOCE inhibition. The probable 
underlying mechanisms may be related to intracellular ROS 
levels, ER stress and mitochondrial dysfunction. Therefore, 
SOCE inhibition may serve as a potential therapeutic strategy 
for EPC injury in oxidative stress. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China (grant 81370211). We would like to thank 
Prof. J.H.Z. and Prof. Y.Y. for the critical comments on this 
manuscript. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>All authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest. </p>









<p>Wang et al. SOCE Inhibition Protects EPCs from H 2 O 2 -Induced Apoptosis </p>



</text></tei>