<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4189225" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: Cilostazol overcomes high on-treatment </p>

<p>platelet reactivity (HTPR) and reduces adverse 
cardiovascular (CV) outcomes after percutaneous 
coronary intervention (PCI). However, the role for triple 
antiplatelet therapy (TAPT) with cilostazol in addition to 
aspirin and clopidogrel after PCI is not well defined. </p>

<p>Methods: We conducted a MEDLINE/EMBASE/ </p>

<p>CENTRAL search for randomised trials, until May 2014, 
evaluating TAPT compared with dual antiplatelet 
therapy (DAPT) of aspirin and clopidogrel alone in 
patients undergoing PCI and reporting platelet 
reactivity and/or CV outcomes. The primary platelet 
reactivity outcome was differences in platelet reactivity 
unit (PRU) with secondary outcomes of %platelet 
inhibition and rate of HTPR. The primary CV outcome 
was major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE), with 
secondary outcomes of death, cardiovascular death, 
myocardial infarction, stent thrombosis (ST), target 
lesion revascularisation (TLR) and target vessel 
revascularisation (TVR) as well as safety outcomes of 
bleeding and drug discontinuations. </p>

<p>Results: In 17 trials that evaluated platelet reactivity </p>

<p>outcomes, the mean PRU value was 47.73 units lower 
with TAPT versus DAPT (95% CI −61.41 to −34.04, 
p&lt;0.0001; mean PRU 182.90 vs 232.65). TAPT also 
increased platelet inhibition by 12.71% (95% CI 10.76 
to 14.67, p&lt;0.0001), and led to a 60% reduction in the 
risk of HTPR (relative risk=0.40; 95% CI 0.30 to 0.53) 
compared with DAPT. Moreover, among the 34 trials 
that evaluated CV outcomes, TAPT reduced the risk of 
MACE (incident rate ratio (IRR)=0.68; 95% CI 0.60 to 
0.78), TLR (IRR=0.57; 95% CI 0.44 to 0.73), TVR 
(IRR=0.69; 95% CI 0.59 to 0.81) and ST (IRR=0.63; 
95% CI 0.40 to 0.98) with no difference for other 
outcomes including bleeding, even in trials using drug-
eluting stents. Drug discontinuation due to adverse 
effects was, however, higher with TAPT vs DAPT 
(IRR=1.59; 95% CI 1.32 to 1.91). </p>

<p>Conclusions: In patients undergoing PCI, addition of </p>

<p>cilostazol to DAPT results in decreased platelet 
reactivity and a significant reduction in CV outcomes 
including ST, even in the drug-eluting stent era. </p>

<p>KEY MESSAGES </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject? 
▸ Cilostazol, a phosphodiesterase III inhibitor, 
exhibits antiplatelet effect and inhibits neointimal 
hyperplasia and smooth muscle proliferation. 
However, its role in addition to dual antiplatelet 
therapy (DAPT) of aspirin and clopidogrel in 
patients undergoing percutaneous coronary 
intervention (PCI) is not well defined. </p>

<p>What does this study add? 
▸ In patients undergoing PCI, addition of cilostazol 
to DAPT results in decreased platelet reactivity 
and a significant reduction in cardiovascular out-
comes including stent thrombosis, even in the 
drug-eluting stent era. </p>

<p>How might this impact on clinical practice? 
▸ The current study provides evidence to support 
use of cilostazol as an attractive and strong 
competitor for newer antiplatelet regimens and 
should be evaluated in future trials in patients 
undergoing PCI. </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>causing a subsequent increase in cAMP within platelets, 
and has been shown to augment platelet inhibition when 
it is added to aspirin and clopidogrel as part of a triple 
therapy regimen. 6 7 In addition, cilostazol inhibits neoin-
timal hyperplasia and smooth muscle proliferation, and 
has the potential to reduce the risk of restenosis after cor-
onary stent implantation. 8-11 Despite these pharmaco-
logic effects, clinical results from observational and small 
randomised trials have not shown a consistent clinical 
benefit. 
Our objective was to evaluate whether triple antiplate-
let therapy (TAPT) with cilostazol (in addition to aspirin 
and clopidogrel) decreases platelet reactivity and 
reduces adverse cardiovascular (CV) outcomes when 
compared with a dual antiplatelet (DAPT) regimen of 
aspirin and clopidogrel alone. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Eligibility criteria 
We conducted a MEDLINE, EMBASE and CENTRAL 
search using the MeSH terms 'cilostazol' and 'rando-
mised clinical trial'. We limited our search to trials 
involving human subjects through May 2014. The search 
terms were broad with no language restrictions imposed. 
We checked the reference lists of review articles and 
prior meta-analyses to assess for additional eligible 
studies. Corresponding authors of studies were con-
tacted for further information if relevant data were not 
reported. Trials in abstract format without a manuscript 
published were also included in the analysis. 
To be included for analysis, eligible trials had to fulfil 
the following criteria: (1) randomised clinical trials of 
TAPT (aspirin, clopidogrel and cilostazol) in compari-
son to DAPT (aspirin and clopidogrel); (2) enrolment 
of patients undergoing PCI with drug-eluting or bare 
metal stents and (3) follow-up of at least 2 weeks for 
trials reporting platelet reactivity outcomes and at least 
1 month for trials reporting cardiovascular outcomes. </p>

<p>Selection and quality assessment 
Three authors (AS, BT and SB) independently reviewed 
trial eligibility and quality. Disagreements were resolved 
by consensus. Risk of bias was assessed using criteria 
recommended by the Cochrane Collaboration, specific-
ally evaluating sequence generation of allocation; alloca-
tion concealment; blinding of participants, staff and 
outcome assessors; incomplete outcome data; selective 
outcome reporting; and other sources of bias. 12 Trials 
with high or unclear risk of bias for the first three cri-
teria were considered as high bias risk trials and the rest 
as low bias risk trials. </p>

<p>Data extraction and synthesis 
The primary platelet reactivity outcome was differences 
in platelet reactivity unit (PRU) after treatment in TAPT 
versus DAPT groups. Secondary outcomes were percent 
platelet inhibition and rate of HTPR. We used a cut-off </p>

<p>of PRU &gt;235 as the threshold for identifying patients 
with HTPR who may be at high risk for ischaemic or 
thrombotic events following PCI, as has been recom-
mended by a recent consensus document. 13 Of note, 
definition of HTPR differed by study. 
Our primary CV outcome was major adverse cardiovas-
cular events (MACE), defined as death, myocardial 
infarction (MI) or target lesion revascularisation (TLR). 
We evaluated secondary CV outcomes of death, cardio-
vascular death, MI, stent thrombosis, TLR and target 
vessel revascularisation (TVR). Safety outcomes of major 
bleeding, minor bleeding, any (major or minor) bleed-
ing and drug discontinuation due to adverse effects 
were also evaluated. The definitions of bleeding varied 
between the trials. Given the lack of consistent reporting 
of the Academic Research Consortium definitions of 
stent thrombosis from the studies, we used the individual 
trial protocol definitions of stent thrombosis. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
We performed an intention to treat meta-analysis in line 
with 
recommendations 
from 
the 
Cochrane 
Collaboration and the PRISMA Statement 14 15 and used 
standard software for statistical analysis (<rs id="software-0" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.9.0</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">STATA Corp.</rs>, Texas, USA). Heterogeneity was assessed 
using the I 2 statistic, defined as the proportion of total 
variation observed between the trials attributable to dif-
ferences between trials rather than sampling error 
(chance), with values &lt;25% considered as low and &gt;75% 
as high. 16 The pooled effect for each grouping of trials 
was derived from the point estimate for each separate 
trial weighted by the inverse of the variance (1/SE 2 ). 
Continuous variable outcomes (PRU, per cent platelet 
inhibition) between the groups were compared with 
both a fixed effect model using the inverse variance 
method and a random effects model using the 
DerSimonian and Laird method. For cardiovascular out-
comes, rates were expressed per patient-years to adjust 
for the varying duration of follow-up. Results were there-
fore reported as incident rate ratios (IRR) and 95% CIs 
with the use of both a fixed effect model using the 
method of Mantel and Haenszel and a random effects 
model using the method of DerSimonian and Laird, 
with the estimate of heterogeneity being taken from the 
Mantel-Haenszel model. Publication bias was estimated 
using the weighted regression tests of Begg and Egger. 12 
For platelet reactivity indices, analyses were stratified 
based on whether standard-dose (75 mg) or high-dose 
(150 mg) clopidogrel was used in the DAPT arm. In add-
ition, further sensitivity analyses were performed based 
on the cohort enrolled: (1) acute coronary syndrome 
(ACS) versus not; and (2) enrolment of patients with 
HTPR at baseline versus not. For cardiovascular out-
comes, analyses were stratified based on stent type-
drug eluting stent (DES) versus Bare metal stent (BMS). 
A p value of &lt;0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Study selection 
We identified 41 trials that satisfied the inclusion criteria 
(figure 1). Seventeen trials reported platelet reactivity 
outcomes of which 10 comparator arms used high dose 
(150 mg) of clopidogrel. A total of 34 trials reported CV 
outcomes, the majority (25 trials) of which used DES. </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics 
The baseline characteristics, inclusion criteria and 
quality assessment are summarised in tables 1-4. In 
order to quantify platelet reactivity outcomes, we evalu-
ated 17 trials with 20 comparator arms and 5056 
patients. The median follow-up was 30 days and 
although the definition of HTPR was heterogeneous, all 
trials used the VerifyNow P2Y12 assay to measure platelet 
reactivity. The analysis of cardiovascular outcomes 
included 34 trials with 14 119 patients. The mean age of 
study participants was between 56.3 and 67.5 years, 
37.9% of the patients had diabetes and the majority 
(77.6%) underwent PCI with DES. </p>

<p>Primary platelet reactivity outcomes 
Primary outcome: differences in PRU 
TAPT resulted in a mean PRU reduction of 47.73 (95% 
CI −61.41 to −34.04, p&lt;0.0001; mean PRU 182.90 vs 
232.65) compared with DAPT (figure 2A). There was a </p>

<p>larger mean difference between the TAPT and DAPT 
groups when the analysis was restricted to a DAPT group 
using standard-dose clopidogrel (mean PRU 189.54 vs 
255.83) where the PRU value was lower by a mean of 64.10 
(95% CI −84.35 to −43.85). Moreover, TAPT was associated 
with a lower PRU value even when compared with DAPT 
using high-dose clopidogrel (mean difference of 27.17) 
(mean PRU 176.27 vs 209.48) (figure 2A). The results 
were similar when stratified by ACS status (see web appen-
dix figure A1) or by baseline clopidogrel resistance status 
(see web appendix figure A2). There was moderate-to-high 
heterogeneity for the above analysis. However, the hetero-
geneity was reduced in subgroup analysis restricted to com-
parison with high-dose clopidogrel (figure 2A), in trials 
enrolling patients with baseline clopidogrel resistance (see 
web appendix figure A2 and in trials enrolling patients 
without ACS (see web appendix figure A1). 
In addition, the mean PRU values on treatment in the 
TAPT group in each of the trials were below a PRU of 
235, which has been cited in the literature as the sug-
gested threshold for defining HTPR. 13 </p>

<p>Secondary outcomes: percent platelet inhibition and high 
on-treatment platelet reactivity 
TAPT was associated with a 12.71% greater platelet 
inhibition compared to DAPT for the overall cohort </p>

<p>Figure 1 Study selection. </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>(95% CI 10.76 to 14.67, p&lt;0.0001) (figure 2B). TAPT 
was also associated with a greater platelet inhibition in 
comparison with DAPT using standard-dose clopidogrel 
(14.37% mean greater platelet inhibition) and remained 
significant even when compared with DAPT using high-
dose clopidogrel (9.07% mean greater platelet inhib-
ition) (figure 2B). There was moderate heterogeneity 
for the above analysis. The results were similar when 
stratified by ACS status (see web appendix figure A3) or 
by baseline clopidogrel resistance status (see web appen-
dix figure A4). </p>

<p>In addition, TAPT was associated with a 60% reduction in 
the risk of HTPR when compared with DAPT (figure 2C) 
(relative risk=0.40; 95% CI 0.30 to 0.53, p&lt;0.0001). When 
stratified by clopidogrel dose, TAPT was associated with a 
50% reduction in risk of HTPR compared to standard-dose 
DAPT and a 72% reduction compared to high-dose DAPT 
(figure 2C). Heterogeneity was moderate with no evidence 
for significant publication bias. The results were similar 
when stratified by ACS status (see web appendix figure A5) 
or by baseline clopidogrel resistance status (see web appen-
dix figure A6). </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics of included trials for platelet reactivity outcomes </p>

<p>Trial 
Year N 
Comparison </p>

<p>SD or HD 
(DAPT group) </p>

<p>Mean age 
(years) </p>

<p>Follow-up 
(days) </p>

<p>ACCEL-AMI 29 
2009 90 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>Both 
62 
30 </p>

<p>ACCEL-LOADING-ACS 30 
2012 218 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>SD 
63 
30 </p>

<p>ACCEL-POLYMORPHISM 31 2010 134 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>HD 
63 
30 </p>

<p>ACCEL-PPI 32 
2012 90 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>HD 
NR 
30 </p>

<p>ACCEL-RESISTANCE 33 
2009 60 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>HD 
63 
30 </p>

<p>CILON-T 34 
2011 716 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>SD 
64 
180 </p>

<p>Gao et al 35 
2013 428 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>SD 
56 
365 </p>

<p>Guan et al 36 
2012 840 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>SD 
60 
30 </p>

<p>HOST-ASSURE 37 
2013 1356 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>Both 
63 
30 </p>

<p>Jeong et al 38 
2014 275 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>Both 
NR 
30 </p>

<p>Jin et al 39 
2012 60 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>HD 
62 
30 </p>

<p>Kim et al 40 
2011 126 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>HD 
62 
30 </p>

<p>Kim et al 41 
2007 60 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>SD 
63 
30 </p>

<p>Kum et al 42 
2009 66 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>SD 
62 
14 </p>

<p>Lee et al 43 
2010 63 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>Both 
NR 
14 </p>

<p>PIANO-2 CKD 44 
2011 74 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>Both 
53 
14 </p>

<p>Shim et al 45 
2009 379 
Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>SD 
61 
14 </p>

<p>ACCEL-AMI, adjunctive Cilostazol versus High Maintenance Dose Clopidogrel in patients with AMI; ACCEL-LOADING-ACS, Multicentre 
Randomised Trial Evaluating Efficacy of Cilostazol on Platelet Aggregation, Inflammation and Myonecrosis in ACS Patients; 
ACCEL-POLYMORPHISM, Cytochrome 2C19 Polymorphism and Response to Adjunctive Cilostazol versus High Maintenance-Dose 
Clopidogrel in Patients Undergoing Percutaneous Coronary Intervention; ACCEL-PPI, Pharmacodynamics Effects of Adding Cilostazol versus 
Double-dose Clopidogrel in Patients with Acute Myocardial Infarction During Proton Pump Inhibitor Co-administration; ACCEL-RESISTANCE, 
Adjunctive Cilostazol Versus High Maintenance Dose Clopidogrel in Patients with Clopidogrel Resistance; CILON-T, Influence of 
Cilostazol-based Triple Antiplatelet Therapy on Ischaemic Complication After Drug-eluting Stent Implantation; HD, high-dose clopidogrel 
(150 mg); HOST-ASSURE, Harmonising Optimal Strategy for Treatment of Coronary Artery Stenosis-Safety and Effectiveness of 
Drug-Eluting Stents and Antiplatelet Regimen; NR, not reported; PIANO-2 CKD, Platelet Reactivity in Patients with Chronic Kidney Disease 
Receiving Adjunctive Cilostazol Compared with a High-Maintenance Dose of Clopidogrel; SD, Standard-dose clopidogrel (75 mg). </p>



<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>Cardiovascular outcomes 
Primary outcome 
TAPT was associated with a 32% reduction in the risk of 
MACE (IRR=0.68; 95% CI 0.60 to 0.78) when compared </p>

<p>with DAPT for the overall cohort (figure 3A). This 
effect was observed regardless of stent type (P interaction 
&gt;0.05) such that even in patients undergoing PCI with 
DES, TAPT resulted in a 36% reduction in MACE </p>

<p>Table 2 Inclusion criteria and study quality for platelet reactivity outcomes trials </p>

<p>Trial 
Cohort 
Definition of HTPR </p>

<p>Platelet 
reactivity 
assay </p>

<p>Quality of 
study* </p>

<p>ACCEL-AMI 29 
Patients with ACS undergoing 
PCI </p>

<p>5 and 20 μM ADP-induced 
maximal platelet aggregation 
&gt;50% </p>

<p>VerifyNow 
P2Y12; LTA </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>ACCEL-LOADING-ACS 30 
Patients with non-ST-elevation MI 
undergoing PCI </p>

<p>NR 
VerifyNow 
P2Y12 </p>

<p>±±± </p>

<p>ACCEL-POLYMORPHISM 31 Patients with high post-treatment 
platelet reactivity or diabetes 
undergoing PCI </p>

<p>5 μM ADP-induced maximal 
platelet aggregation &gt;50% </p>

<p>VerifyNow 
P2Y12; LTA </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>ACCEL-PPI 32 
Patients with acute MI 
undergoing PCI </p>

<p>20 μM ADP-induced 
maximal platelet aggregation 
&gt;59% </p>

<p>LTA 
±±± </p>

<p>ACCEL-RESISTANCE 33 
Patients with high on-treatment 
platelet reactivity undergoing PCI </p>

<p>5 μM ADP-induced maximal 
platelet aggregation &gt;50% </p>

<p>VerifyNow 
P2Y12; LTA </p>

<p>++± </p>

<p>CILON-T 34 
Patients with angina undergoing 
PCI </p>

<p>NR 
VerifyNow 
P2Y12 </p>

<p>++± </p>

<p>Gao et al 35 
Obese patients undergoing PCI 
Post-treatment platelet 
aggregation absolute 
difference 10% or less </p>

<p>LTA 
±±± </p>

<p>Guan et al 36 
Patients with ACS and high 
on-treatment platelet reactivity 
undergoing PCI </p>

<p>20 μM ADP-induced 
maximal platelet aggregation 
&gt;55% </p>

<p>LTA 
±±± </p>

<p>HOST-ASSURE 37 
All-comer patients undergoing 
PCI </p>

<p>NR 
VerifyNow 
P2Y12 </p>

<p>±±+ </p>

<p>Jeong et al 38 
Patients with ACS undergoing 
PCI </p>

<p>NR 
LTA 
±±± </p>

<p>Jin et al 39 
Patients undergoing PCI 
% platelet inhibition &lt;20 
VerifyNow 
P2Y12; LTA </p>

<p>±++ </p>

<p>Kim et al 40 
Patients with acute MI 
undergoing PCI </p>

<p>20 μM ADP-induced 
maximal platelet aggregation 
&gt;59% </p>

<p>VerifyNow 
P2Y12; LTA </p>

<p>++± </p>

<p>Kim et al 41 
Patients with ST-elevation MI 
undergoing PCI </p>

<p>% platelet inhibition &lt;20 
VerifyNow 
P2Y12; LTA </p>

<p>±±± </p>

<p>Kum et al 42 
Patients undergoing PCI 
NR 
VerifyNow 
P2Y12 </p>

<p>±±± </p>

<p>Lee et al 43 
Patients with high on-treatment 
platelet reactivity undergoing PCI </p>

<p>% platelet inhibition &lt;20 
VerifyNow 
P2Y12 </p>

<p>+±± </p>

<p>PIANO-2 CKD 44 
Patients with renal disease on 
haemodialysis undergoing PCI </p>

<p>5 μM ADP-induced maximal 
platelet aggregation &gt;50% </p>

<p>VerifyNow 
P2Y12; LTA </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Shim et al 45 
Patients undergoing PCI with 
DES </p>

<p>% platelet inhibition &lt;20 
VerifyNow 
P2Y12 </p>

<p>+±± </p>

<p>*Represents risk of bias based on: sequence generation of allocation; allocation concealment and blinding. '+' represents low bias risk, 
'−' high bias risk and '±' unclear bias risk. 
ACCEL-AMI, adjunctive Cilostazol versus High Maintenance Dose Clopidogrel in patients with AMI; ACCEL-LOADING-ACS, Multicentre 
Randomised Trial Evaluating Efficacy of Cilostazol on Platelet Aggregation, Inflammation and Myonecrosis in ACS Patients; 
ACCEL-POLYMORPHISM, Cytochrome 2C19 Polymorphism and Response to Adjunctive Cilostazol versus High Maintenance-Dose 
Clopidogrel in Patients Undergoing Percutaneous Coronary Intervention; ACCEL-PPI, Pharmacodynamics Effects of Adding Cilostazol versus 
Double-dose Clopidogrel in Patients with Acute Myocardial Infarction During Proton Pump Inhibitor Co-administration; ACCEL-RESISTANCE, 
Adjunctive Cilostazol Versus High Maintenance Dose Clopidogrel in Patients with Clopidogrel Resistance; ACS, acute coronary syndrome; 
CILON-T, Influence of Cilostazol-based Triple Antiplatelet Therapy on Ischaemic Complication After Drug-eluting Stent Implantation; HD, 
high-dose clopidogrel (150 mg); HOST-ASSURE, Harmonising Optimal Strategy for Treatment of Coronary Artery Stenosis-Safety and 
Effectiveness of Drug-Eluting Stents and Antiplatelet Regimen; LTA, light transmittance aggregometry; MI, myocardial infarction; NR, not 
reported; PIANO-2 CKD, Platelet Reactivity in Patients with Chronic Kidney Disease Receiving Adjunctive Cilostazol Compared with a 
High-Maintenance Dose of Clopidogrel; SD, Standard-dose clopidogrel (75 mg). </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>Table 3 Baseline characteristics of included trials for cardiovascular outcomes </p>

<p>Trial 
Year N 
Comparison </p>

<p>Follow-up 
(months) </p>

<p>Mean 
age 
(years) </p>

<p>DM 
(%) Stent type </p>

<p>DES 
(%) </p>

<p>ABCD 46 
2014 
630 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
65 
31 BES 
100 </p>

<p>ACCEL-AMI 29 
2010 
90 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
62 
21 PES&gt;SES&gt;ZES 
100 </p>

<p>ACCEL-
LOADING-
ACS 30 </p>

<p>2012 
218 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
63 
23 DES, BMS 
95 </p>

<p>ACCEL-
RESISTANCE 33 </p>

<p>2009 
60 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/high-dose 
clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
63 
23 DES 
100 </p>

<p>Ahn CM et al 47 
2011 
130 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>24 
64 
22 SES 
100 </p>

<p>Chen YD et al 48 2006 
120 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>9 
58 
30 BMS 
0 </p>

<p>CIDES 49 
2008 
280 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>6 
62 
100 PES, SES 
100 </p>

<p>CILON-T 34 
2011 
960 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>6 
64 
34 PES, ZES 
100 </p>

<p>CLEAR 50 
2011 
120 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>6 
66 
42 SES&gt;ZES&gt;PES&gt;EES 100 </p>

<p>CREST 51 
2005 
705 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>6 
60 
26 BMS 
0 </p>

<p>DECLARE-
DIABETES 52 53 </p>

<p>2008/ 
2010 </p>

<p>450 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>24 
61 
100 PES, SES 
100 </p>

<p>DECLARE-
LONG 53 54 </p>

<p>2007/ 
2010 </p>

<p>450 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>24 
61 
33 PES, SES 
100 </p>

<p>DECLARE-
LONG II 55 </p>

<p>2011 
499 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
62 
35 ZES 
100 </p>

<p>Gao et al 35 
2013 
428 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
56 
18 SES&gt;PES 
100 </p>

<p>Guan et al 36 
2012 
840 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
60 
NR DES 
100 </p>

<p>Han et al 56 
2009 1212 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
60 
22 BMS, DES 
52 </p>

<p>Han et al 57 
2006 
120 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>3 
61 
23 BMS, DES 
43 </p>

<p>HOST-
ASSURE 37 </p>

<p>2013 3755 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
63 
32 ZES-R&gt;EES-PtCr 
100 </p>

<p>Hu et al 58 
2013 
146 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
63 
NR NR 
NR </p>

<p>Jin et al 39 
2012 
60 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
62 
45 DES 
100 </p>

<p>Kim et al 59 
2008 
109 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>6 
68 
29 PES&gt;SES 
100 </p>

<p>Kim et al 41 
2007 
60 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
63 
29 SES&gt;PES&gt;others 
100 </p>

<p>Kum et al 42 
2009 
603 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>6 
62 
26 DES 
100 </p>

<p>Lee et al 60 
2007 
20 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
56 
25 NR 
100 </p>

<p>LONG-
DES-II 61 62 </p>

<p>2007 
500 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>9 
61 
33 PES, SES 
100 </p>

<p>Lu et al 63 
2006 
120 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>6-9 
71 
NR BMS 
0 </p>

<p>Lu et al 64 
2007 
402 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>6 
61 
44 BMS, DES 
85 </p>

<p>Continued </p>



<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>(IRR=0.64; 95% CI 0.55 to 0.75) when compared with 
DAPT alone (figure 3A). There was low heterogeneity in 
the analysis and no evidence for significant publication 
bias. </p>

<p>Secondary outcomes 
TAPT was associated with similar IRR for death 
(IRR=0.79; 95% CI 0.58 to 1.09) (figure 3B), cardiovas-
cular death (IRR=0.74; 95% CI 0.42 to 1.30) and MI 
(IRR=0.85; 95% CI 0.63 to 1.14) (figure 3C) for the 
overall cohort. The IRR was independent of stent type as 
TAPT showed benefit regardless whether BMS and DES 
was used (stent type, P interaction &gt;0.05). In the overall 
cohort, TAPT was associated with a 43% reduction in the 
risk of TLR (IRR=0.57; 95% CI 0.44 to 0.73) (figure 3D) 
and a 31% reduction in the risk of TVR (IRR=0.69; 95% 
CI 0.59 to 0.81) (figure 3E) compared with DAPT. TAPT 
efficacy for reducing TLR and TVR was present even 
when the analyses were restricted to studies using DES. 
In DES-treated patients, TAPT resulted in a 43% reduc-
tion in TLR (IRR=0.57; 95% CI 0.44 to 0.74) and a 35% 
reduction in TVR (IRR=0.65; 95% CI 0.54 to 0.79) with 
TAPT compared with DAPT. </p>

<p>TAPT was associated with significantly lower stent 
thrombosis rate when compared with DAPT (IRR=0.63; 
95% CI 0.40 to 0.98) (figure 3F). There was no hetero-
geneity (0%) in all of the above analyses and no evi-
dence for significant publication bias. </p>

<p>Safety outcomes 
TAPT was associated with a numerically increased risk of 
major (IRR=1.24; 95% CI 0.79 to 1.92) (figure 4A), 
minor (IRR=1.37; 95% CI 0.88 to 2.14) (figure 4B), or 
any bleeding (IRR=1.26; 95% CI 0.99 to 1.61) (figure 
4C) compared with DAPT, although these were not statis-
tically significant. TAPT was also associated with a 59% 
increase in drug discontinuation due to adverse events 
(IRR=1.59; 95% CI 1.32 to 1.91) (figure 4D) when com-
pared with DAPT. The most commonly listed causes for 
drug discontinuation were headache, skin rash and palpi-
tations/tachycardia. There was no-to-modest (for drug 
discontinuation outcomes) heterogeneity in all of the 
above analyses and no evidence for significant publica-
tion bias. </p>

<p>Table 3 Continued </p>

<p>Trial 
Year N 
Comparison </p>

<p>Follow-up 
(months) </p>

<p>Mean 
age 
(years) </p>

<p>DM 
(%) Stent type </p>

<p>DES 
(%) </p>

<p>Min et al 10 
2007 
59 Aspirin/clopidogrel or 
ticlopidine/cilostazol vs 
aspirin/clopidogrel or 
ticlopidine </p>

<p>6 
62 
26 BMS 
0 </p>

<p>OPTIMUS-2 6 
2008 
50 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>1 
64 
100 NR 
100 </p>

<p>Shen et al 65 
2010 
160 Aspirin/Clopidogrel/ 
Cilostazol vs Aspirin/ 
Clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
69 
100 DES 
100 </p>

<p>Suh et al 66 
2009 
143 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>25 
62 
100 PES&gt;SES 
100 </p>

<p>Wang et al 67 
2005 
193 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
62 
28 BMS 
0 </p>

<p>Wang et al 68 
2010 
164 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
68 
NR BMS, DES 
NR </p>

<p>Zang et al 69 
2008 
263 Aspirin/clopidogrel/cilostazol 
vs aspirin/clopidogrel </p>

<p>12 
59 
100 BMS, DES 
53 </p>

<p>ABCD, Evaluating Additional Benefit of Cilostazol to Dual Antiplatelet Therapy in Patients with Long or Multivessel Coronary Artery Disease 
underwent Biolimus-Eluting Stent Implantation; ACS, acute coronary syndrome; AMI, acute myocardial infarction; BES, biolimus-eluting stent; 
BMS, bare metal stent; CIDES, comparison of cilostazol versus clopidogrel after drug-eluting stenting in diabetic patients; CILON-T, Influence 
of Cilostazol-based Triple Antiplatelet Therapy on Ischaemic Complication After Drug-eluting Stent Implantation; CLEAR, The Cilostazol 
Administration Before Percutaneous Coronary Intervention for Reduction of Periprocedural Myonecrosis Trial; CREST, Coronary Stent 
Restenosis in Patients Treated with Cilostazol; DECLARE-LONG II: Triple Antiplatelet Therapy With Dual Antiplatelet Therapy to Reduce 
Restenosis After Drug-Eluting Stent Implantation in Long Coronary Lesions; DECLARE-DIABETES, A Randomised Comparison of Triple 
Antiplatelet Therapy with Dual Antiplatelet Therapy After Drug-Eluting Stent Implantation in Diabetic Patients; DECLARE-LONG, Drug-Eluting 
Stenting Followed by Cilostazol Treatment Reduces Late Restenosis in Patients with Long Coronary Lesions; DES, drug-eluting stent; DM, 
diabetes mellitus; EES, everolimus-eluting stent; EES-PtCr, everolimus-eluting platinum-chromium alloy stent; LONG-DES, Sirolimus-Eluting 
Stent Versus Paclitaxel-Eluting Stent for Patients With Long Coronary Artery Disease; OPTIMUS-2, Impact of Cilostazol on Platelet Function 
Profiles in Patients with Diabetes Mellitus and Coronary Artery Disease on Dual Antiplatelet Therapy; PES, Paclitaxel-eluting stent; SES, 
Sirolimus-eluting stent; ZES, Zotarolimus-eluting stent; ZES-R, Zotarolimus-eluting Resolute stent. 
Other trial expansions as in tables 1 and 2. </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In patients undergoing PCI, TAPT using cilostazol 
results in significant decrease in platelet reactivity and 
reduced risk of HTPR. TAPT resulted in significantly 
lower mean PRU, greater platelet inhibition and 
reduced risk of HTPR in the setting of DAPT with both 
standard-dose and high-dose clopidogrel. In addition, 
TAPT was associated with a significant reduction in CV </p>

<p>events, including reduction in MACE, driven largely by 
significant reductions in TLR and TVR. Most import-
antly, there was a significant lower stent thrombosis with 
TAPT versus DAPT. Moreover, the reduction of resten-
osis with TAPT remained even when the analysis was 
restricted to trials using DES. In addition, there was 
numerically higher bleeding with TAPT versus DAPT, 
although this did not reach statistical significant. </p>

<p>Table 4 Inclusion criteria and study quality of included cardiovascular outcomes trials </p>

<p>Trial 
Cohort 
Quality of study* </p>

<p>ABCD 46 
Patients with long or multivessel disease undergoing PCI 
++± 
ACCEL-AMI 29 
Patients with ACS undergoing PCI 
+++ 
ACCEL-LOADING-ACS 30 Patients with non-ST-elevation MI undergoing PCI 
±±± 
ACCEL-RESISTANCE 33 
Patients with high on-treatment platelet reactivity undergoing PCI 
++± 
Ahn et al 47 
Patient with ACS undergoing PCI 
±±+ 
Chen et al 48 
Patients with ACS undergoing PCI 
±++ 
CIDES 49 
Patients with diabetes undergoing PCI 
±±± 
CILON-T 34 
Patients with angina undergoing PCI 
++± 
CLEAR 50 
Patients with stable angina undergoing PCI 
±±± 
CREST 51 
Patients with ACS/known stenosis undergoing PCI 
+++ 
DECLARE-DIABETES 52 
Patients with ACS and diabetes undergoing PCI 
+±± 
DECLARE-LONG 54 
Patients with ACS and stenosis of long (&gt;25 mm) lesions undergoing PCI 
+±± 
DECLARE-LONG II 55 
Patients with ACS/known stenosis of long (&gt;25 mm) lesions undergoing PCI +++ 
Gao et al 35 
Obese patients undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Guan et al 36 
Patients with ACS and high on-treatment platelet reactivity undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Han et al 56 
Patients with ACS undergoing PCI 
++± 
Han et al 57 
Patients with ACS undergoing PCI 
±±± 
HOST-ASSURE 37 
All-comer patients undergoing PCI 
±±+ 
Hu et al 58 
Patients with ACS undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Jin et al 39 
Patients undergoing PCI 
±++ 
Kim et al 59 
Patients with ACS/known stenosis undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Kim et al 41 
Patients with ST-elevation MI undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Kum et al 42 
Patients with ACS/known stenosis undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Lee et al 60 
Patients undergoing elective PCI 
+±± 
LONG-DES-II 61 
Patients with stenosis of long lesions undergoing PCI 
++± 
Lu et al 70 
Patients undergoing PCI 
±±+ 
Lu et al 64 
Patients with ADP-induced platelet inhibition rates &lt;30% undergoing PCI 
+±± 
Min et al 10 
Patients with ACS/known stenosis undergoing elective PCI 
±+± 
OPTIMUS-2 6 
Patients with diabetes undergone PCI 
+++ 
Shen et al 65 
Patients with ACS undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Suh et al 66 
Patients with diabetes and chronic total occlusion undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Wang et al 67 
Patients with small vessel stenosis undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Wang et al 68 
Patients with non-ST-elevation MI undergoing PCI 
±±± 
Zang et al 69 
Patients with ACS undergoing PCI 
±±± </p>

<p>*Represents risk of bias based on: sequence generation of allocation; allocation concealment and blinding. '+' represents low bias risk, '−' 
high bias risk and '±' unclear bias risk. 
ABCD, Evaluating Additional Benefit of Cilostazol to Dual Antiplatelet Therapy in Patients with Long or Multivessel Coronary Artery Disease 
underwent Biolimus-Eluting Stent Implantation; ACS, acute coronary syndrome; AMI, acute myocardial infarction; BES, biolimus-eluting stent; 
BMS, bare metal stent; CIDES, comparison of cilostazol versus clopidogrel after drug-eluting stenting in diabetic patients; CILON-T, Influence 
of Cilostazol-based Triple Antiplatelet Therapy on Ischaemic Complication After Drug-eluting Stent Implantation; CLEAR, The Cilostazol 
Administration Before Percutaneous Coronary Intervention for Reduction of Periprocedural Myonecrosis Trial; CREST, Coronary Stent 
Restenosis in Patients Treated with Cilostazol; DECLARE-LONG II: Triple Antiplatelet Therapy With Dual Antiplatelet Therapy to Reduce 
Restenosis After Drug-Eluting Stent Implantation in Long Coronary Lesions; DECLARE-DIABETES, A Randomised Comparison of Triple 
Antiplatelet Therapy with Dual Antiplatelet Therapy After Drug-Eluting Stent Implantation in Diabetic Patients; DECLARE-LONG, Drug-Eluting 
Stenting Followed by Cilostazol Treatment Reduces Late Restenosis in Patients with Long Coronary Lesions; DES, drug-eluting stent; DM, 
diabetes mellitus; EES, everolimus-eluting stent; EES-PtCr, everolimus-eluting platinum-chromium alloy stent; LONG-DES, Sirolimus-Eluting 
Stent Versus Paclitaxel-Eluting Stent for Patients With Long Coronary Artery Disease; OPTIMUS-2, Impact of Cilostazol on Platelet Function 
Profiles in Patients with Diabetes Mellitus and Coronary Artery Disease on Dual Antiplatelet Therapy; PES, Paclitaxel-eluting stent; SES, 
Sirolimus-eluting stent; ZES, Zotarolimus-eluting stent; ZES-R, Zotarolimus-eluting Resolute stent. 
Other trial expansions as in tables 1 and 2. </p>



<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>However, there was a significant increase in the risk of 
drug discontinuation due to adverse effects when com-
pared with DAPT. </p>

<p>Platelet reactivity and outcomes 
Prior studies have shown a relationship between 
on-treatment platelet reactivity and adverse CV events in </p>

<p>Figure 2 (A) Primary platelet reactivity outcome: difference in platelet reactivity units (PRU) after treatment between triple 
antiplatelet therapy (TAPT) versus dual antiplatelet therapy (DAPT). (B) Secondary platelet reactivity outcome: difference in 
percent platelet inhibition after treatment between TAPT versus DAPT. (C) Secondary platelet reactivity outcome: risk of high 
on-treatment platelet reactivity (HTPR) after treatment between TAPT versus DAPT. </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>patients undergoing PCI. In an analysis of individual 
patient data from six studies with 3059 patients, for every 
10 U increase in PRU there was a 4% increase in 
primary endpoint rate of death, MI or stent thrombosis 
(HR 1.04; 95% CI 1.03 to 1.06; p&lt;0.0001). 17 A recent 
consensus statement recommended a cut-off of PRU 
&gt;235 U as the threshold for identifying patients with 
HTPR who may be at high risk for ischaemic or throm-
botic events following PCI. 13 Patients with HTPR have 
been shown to have an increased risk of death (110% 
increase), MI (104% increase) and stent thrombosis 
(211% increase). 17 18 
Although platelet reactivity is a surrogate marker, given 
the wide interindividual variability in clopidogrel-
induced platelet inhibition, 1-3 various strategies have 
been tested to improve platelet inhibition. These strat-
egies have utilised higher loading and maintenance 
doses of clopidogrel, or next-generation P2Y12 inhibitors 
such as prasugrel and ticagrelor, which are more potent 
that clopidogrel and have a more uniform antiplatelet 
effect. Doubling of the clopidogrel dose (150 mg) has 
been shown to significantly reduce PRU in patients with 
HTPR. 19-21 Similarly, data from the next-generation 
P2Y12 inhibitors such as prasugrel and ticagrelor have 
shown improved platelet reactivity indices when com-
pared with clopidogrel. 22 Although the newer agents pra-
sugrel and ticagrelor reduce MACE in randomised trials, 
these agents increase bleeding in patients with PCI and 
cost significantly more than generic clopidogrel. 23 24 
Cilostazol, a phosphodiesterase III inhibitor, exhibits 
antiplatelet effects by increasing cAMP within platelets, </p>

<p>and is available as a generic drug. Our results show a sig-
nificant benefit of TAPT with cilostazol in improving 
platelet reactivity indices in patients undergoing PCI, 
with lower PRU, greater platelet inhibition and a signifi-
cant reduction in the risk of HTPR regardless of compari-
son with either standard-dose or high-dose clopidogrel. 
In addition, these results were seen even in comparison 
with DAPT using high-dose clopidogrel. Given that 
generic clopidogrel is now available, many clinicians opt 
to prescribe high-dose clopidogrel to address HTPR in 
patients who cannot afford newer antiplatelet agents. 
The results of the present study show that TAPT with 
cilostazol is superior even to DAPT with high-dose clopi-
dogrel. Despite these promising results, a number of lim-
itations must be acknowledged. Although platelet 
reactivity is a risk factor/surrogate marker for adverse CV 
events, clinical studies have not yet demonstrated that a 
pharmacological treatment strategy based on platelet 
reactivity improves outcomes. 20 25 In the ARCTIC trial of 
2440 patients randomised to platelet-function monitoring 
and drug adjustment group versus conventional strategy 
of no monitoring and drug adjustment, there were no dif-
ferences in composite of death, MI, stent thrombosis, 
stroke, or urgent revascularisation at 1 year between the 
two groups, calling into question the utility of adjusting 
therapies based on platelet function monitoring. 25 
However, because cilostazol inhibits both platelet acti-
vation and smooth muscle proliferation, it has the poten-
tial to target two dreaded complications of PCI-stent 
thrombosis and restenosis. TAPT may reduce MACE by 
two or more cellular mechanisms. 8-11 Our study shows </p>

<p>Figure 2 Continued </p>



<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>significant reduction in both stent thrombosis and 
restenosis using TAPT with cilostazol, even in patients 
treated with DES. This is a potential advantage for this </p>

<p>agent, as no antiplatelet agent, including prasugrel or 
ticagrelor, has been shown to have any antirestenosis 
property. </p>

<p>Figure 3 (A) Primary cardiovascular outcome: risk of major adverse cardiovascular effects (MACE) between triple antiplatelet 
therapy (TAPT) versus dual antiplatelet therapy (DAPT). (B) Secondary cardiovascular outcome: risk of all-cause mortality 
between TAPT versus DAPT. (C) Secondary cardiovascular outcome: risk of myocardial infarction between TAPT versus DAPT. 
(D) Secondary cardiovascular outcome: risk of target lesion revascularisation (TLR) between TAPT versus DAPT. (E) Secondary 
cardiovascular outcome: risk of target vessel revascularisation (TVR) between TAPT versus DAPT. (F) Secondary cardiovascular 
outcome: risk of stent thrombosis between TAPT versus DAPT. </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>Therefore, a strategy of using TAPT with cilostazol has 
several advantages: (1) it improves the surrogate outcome 
of platelet reactivity relative to DAPT, including high-dose 
clopidogrel; (2) the antismooth muscle proliferative prop-
erties of cilostazol may make it an excellent agent to 
prevent restenosis resulting in reduced TVR even in 
patients treated with a DES; (3) the improvement in </p>

<p>platelet reactivity indices translate into significant reduc-
tion in stent thrombosis and (4) the medication is avail-
able generically and is therefore less expensive than newer 
antiplatelet therapy. Thus, when used following PCI, 
TAPT with cilostazol has the potential to be a cost-effective 
therapy to improve clinical outcomes by reducing throm-
botic events and restenosis. The results of this study </p>

<p>Figure 3 Continued </p>



<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>therefore call for a randomised trial comparing a strategy 
of TAPT with DAPT using newer antiplatelet agents. 
Our results differ from the studies of Jang et al 26 and 
Sakurai et al 27 in that these studies did not evaluate 
platelet reactivity outcomes and had far fewer trials 
than the current analysis. In our analysis, TAPT was </p>

<p>associated with significant increase in drug discontinu-
ation. The most commonly listed causes for drug dis-
continuation were headache, skin rash and 
palpitations/tachycardia. Sakurai et al 27 similarly found 
a significant increase in rash and gastrointestinal side 
effects with TAPT. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Continued </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>Study limitations 
As in other meta-analyses without individual patient 
data, we were unable to adjust for dosages of medication 
used or with compliance with assigned therapies. Given 
heterogeneity in the study protocols, clinically relevant </p>

<p>differences could have been missed and are best 
assessed in a meta-analysis of individual patient data. 
Stroke would have been interesting to examine, as there 
is some evidence that cilostazol reduces stroke. 28 All of 
the trials did not report all of the outcomes. The </p>

<p>Figure 4 (A) Safety outcome: risk of major bleeding between triple antiplatelet therapy (TAPT) versus dual antiplatelet therapy 
(DAPT). (B) Safety outcome: risk of minor bleeding between TAPT versus DAPT. (C) Safety outcome: risk of any bleeding 
between TAPT versus DAPT. (D) Safety outcome: risk of drug discontinuation due to adverse effects between TAPT versus 
DAPT. </p>



<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>subgroup analyses might suffer from multiple testing. In 
addition, the results need to be confirmed in an ethnic-
ally diverse population, as most of the trials were done 
in Asian populations. However, the CREST and the 
OPTIMUS-2 trials, performed mainly in a non-Asian 
population, showed similar efficacy of cilostazol when 
compared with controls. The individual trials did not </p>

<p>provide sufficient data to stratify analyses by early versus 
newer generation DES. </p>

<p>Conclusions 
In patients undergoing PCI, TAPT with cilostazol is 
associated with significantly improved platelet reactivity 
indices, even when compared with DAPT with high-</p>

<p>Figure 4 Continued </p>

<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>



<p>Coronary artery disease </p>

<p>dose clopidogrel, and is associated with significant 
reduction in CV events, including reduction in BMS 
and DES restenosis and stent thrombosis. The dual 
properties of antiplatelet and antiproliferative action, 
the availability as a generic medication combined with 
the above data makes TAPT with aspirin, clopidogrel 
and cilostazol an attractive and strong competitor for 
newer antiplatelet regimens and should be evaluated in 
future trials. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>New York University School of Medicine, New York, New York, USA </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Saint Luke's Mid America Heart Institute, Kansas City, Missouri </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Brigham and Women's Hospital, and Harvard Medical School, Boston, 
Massachusetts, USA </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Brigham and Women's Hospital Heart and Vascular Center and Harvard 
Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA </p>

<p>Contributors SB was involved in study concept and design, analysis and 
interpretation of the data, statistical analysis, and study supervision and 
also takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the 
data analysis. SB and AS were involved in acquisition of the data and drafting 
of the manuscript. SB, AS, JJD, KC, FF and DLB were involved in critical 
revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content. </p>

<p>Funding This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in 
the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. </p>

<p>Competing interests DLB: Advisory Board: Elsevier Practice Update 
Cardiology, Medscape Cardiology, Regado Biosciences; Board of Directors: 
Boston VA Research Institute, Society of Cardiovascular Patient Care; Chair: 
American Heart Association Get With The Guidelines Steering Committee; 
Data Monitoring Committees: Duke Clinical Research Institute, Harvard 
Clinical Research Institute, Mayo Clinic, Population Health Research Institute; 
Honoraria: American College of Cardiology (Editor, Clinical Trials, 
Cardiosource), Belvoir Publications (Editor in Chief, Harvard Heart Letter), 
Duke Clinical Research Institute (clinical trial steering committees), 
Harvard Clinical Research Institute (clinical trial steering committee), HMP 
Communications (Editor in Chief, Journal of Invasive Cardiology), Population 
Health Research Institute (clinical trial steering committee), Slack Publications 
(Chief Medical Editor, Cardiology Today's Intervention), WebMD (CME 
steering committees); Other: Clinical Cardiology (Deputy Editor), Journal of 
the American College of Cardiology (Section Editor, Pharmacology); Research 
Grants: Amarin, AstraZeneca, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Eisai, Ethicon, Medtronic, 
Roche, Sanofi Aventis, The Medicines Company; Unfunded Research: FlowCo, 
PLx Pharma, Takeda. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>





<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>





<p>Coronary artery disease </p>





<p>Bangalore S, Singh A, Toklu B, et al. Open Heart 2014;1:e000068. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2014-000068 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

</text></tei>