<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4384862" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Assessment of the energy expenditure of walking is fre-
quently performed to evaluate the effectiveness of walking 
systems (1). The standard method for estimating energy cost 
is the direct measurement of oxygen consumption (VO 2 ) but 
it is generally unavailable in the clinical setting. The Physi-
ological Cost Index (PCI) first was introduced by MacGregor </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>as method based on linear correlation between VO 2 and heart 
rate (HR) (2). It requires simply recording of HR at rest and 
while walking, measured by not expensive equipment. Mea-
suring the PCI has been the subject of many publications for 
patients with different locomotion disorders (3-6) and also in 
lower limb amputees walking with prosthesis (7-10). 
We undertook this study aiming to present the efficacy of 
rehabilitation program for subjects with lower limb amputa-
tion, for over ten years after the implementation of this pro-
gram in Kosovo (11, 12). Our aim was to assess energy cost 
and walking speed in two level amputation: transfemoral and 
transtibial amputation as most important determinants of ef-
ficacy of prosthetic walking respectively of prosthetic reha-
bilitation program. Also we aimed to analyze wherever the 
age and prosthetic walking supported with walking aids had 
impact on energy cost and walking speed. </p>

<p>2. METHODS </p>

<p>This was a prospective cross sectional study. The research 
covered the period from the first of January to the first of July, 
2012. </p>

<p>2.1. Subject population </p>

<p>A convenience sample of individuals with amputations was 
recruited among patients at the Department of Prosthetics 
and Orthotics at the University Clinical Center of Kosovo. 
Inclusion criteria were to have: 1) above 18 years of age; 
2) unilateral lower limb amputation, for reasons other than 
vascular disease; 3) at least one year experience of using pros-
thesis; 4) no cognitive disorders or other significant medical 
conditions. All gave informed consent. 
All trans-femoral amputees used modular (endoskeletal) 
prosthesis with quadrilateral socket, 4-bar linkage knee with 
mechanical swing phase control; or polycentric knee joint 
and SACH-foot. Transtibial amputees used a modular patellar 
tendon bearing socket and SACH-foot. 
The subjects wore their prostheses almost all day for ordi-
nary activities. </p>

<p>2.2. Measurements </p>

<p>PCI is calculated as the quotient of difference in working </p>

<p>ABSTRACT 
Background: The Physiological Cost Index (PCI) was introduced by MacGregor to estimate the energy cost in walking of healthy people, also it has been 
reported for persons with lower limb amputation, walking with prosthesis. Objective: To assess energy cost and walking speed in two level lower limb 
amputation: transfemoral and transtibial amputation and to determine if the age and prosthetic walking supported with walking aids have impact on energy 
cost and walking speed. Methods: A prospective cross sectional study was performed in two level lower limb amputees with no vascular disease who were 
rehabilitated at the Department of Prosthetics and Orthotics at the University Clinical Center of Kosovo. The Physiological Cost Index (PCI) was assessed 
by five minutes of continuous indoor walking at Comfort Walking Speed (CWS). Results: Eighty three lower limb amputees were recruited. It is shown 
relevant impact of level of amputation in PCI (t=6.8, p&lt;0.001) and CWS (T=487, p&lt;0.001). The great influence of using crutches during prosthetic walking 
in PCI (ANOVA F= 39.5 P &lt; 0.001) and CWS (ANOVA F=32.01, P &lt;0.001) has been shown by One Way ANOVA test . The correlation coefficient (R) showed a 
significant correlation of age with PCI and CWS in both groups of amputation. Conclusions: Walking with transfemoral prosthesis or using walking aids 
during prosthetic ambulation is matched with higher cost of energy and slower walking speed. Advanced age was shown with high impact on PCI and CWS 
in both groups of amputees. 
Key words: physiological cost index; comfort walking speed; amputation; crutches; age. </p>

<p>doi: 10.5455/aim.2015.23.12-17 </p>

<p>ACTA INFORM MED. 2015 FEB 23(1): 12-17 
Received: 21 December 2014 • Accepted: 12 February 2015 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL PAPER </p>

<p>© 2015 Teuta Osmani Vllasolli, Nikola Orovcanec, Beti Zafirova, Blerim 
Krasniqi, Ardiana Murtezani, Valbona Krasniqi, Bukurije Rama 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons. 
org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, 
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited. </p>

<p>Physiological Cost Index and Comfort Walking Speed in Two Level Lower Limb Amputees Having No Vascular Disease </p>

<p>ACTA INFORM MED. 2015 FEB 23(1): 12-17 / ORIGINAL PAPER </p>



<p>and resting heart rates and walking speed respectively self 
selected (comfort) walking speed. The PCI value reflects the 
increased heart rate required for walking and is expressed as 
heartbeats per meter by formula: 
PCI = [MeanHR at work -MeanHR at rest]/ Walking 
speed (m/min) 
Mean PCI values for healthy adults have been reported to 
be between 0.23 and 0.42 (1, 13-15. 
In the case of healthy persons, CWS has been reported to be 
between 60 and 100 m/min (16-18). </p>

<p>2.3. Testing procedure </p>

<p>PCI was assessed by five minutes of continuous indoor 
walking at CWS. The participant had an HR monitor (OXY-
100 Handheld Pulse Oximeter, 20060 Gessate (MI), Italy) 
attached around the chest and the receiver was attached in 
second finger of their hand. Before registering HR at rest, the 
participant was seated in silence for about five minutes and 
then it was recorded each minute for the following five min-
utes. Prior to the walking part of the test, a short distance was 
walked in order to warm up. The walking was conducted in-
doors, in a hallway with a regular floor surface. We chose a 
76-m-long quadratic-shaped track with gently rounded cor-
ners (36 x 2 x 36 x 2), marked every one meter. The patients 
were asked to walk at their self selected comfortable speed, 
with the aid they normally use for support if walking con-
tinuously for a few hundred meters. Walking was carried out 
for five minutes with the tester walking behind to read the 
HR at work every 30 seconds. A digital stopwatch was used 
to time subjects as they walked over a track while the investi-
gator recorded HR and walked distance. All the participants 
were instructed to avoid the intake of tobacco, coffee/tea or a 
large meal at least two hours prior to the test. </p>

<p>2.4. Statistical methods </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using statistical package 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">21.0</rs>. Descriptive statistics were calculated. To deter-
mine whether there were differences between the transfem-
oral and transtibial amputee groups in terms of distribution 
by gender and walking with crutches the Chi-square test or 
Fisher Exact test were used. T-test or Mann-Whitney Rank 
Sum Test was used for comparison of differences on PCI and 
CWS between two amputation groups. The one way analysis 
of variance (ANOVA) was used for comparison of differences 
between amputation groups and impact of using crutches on 
PCI and CWS. 
The correlation between the age and PCI or CWS by level 
of amputation was tested with simple linear regression anal-
ysis. </p>

<p>3. RESULTS </p>

<p>Eighty three lower limb amputees were recruited. There 
were twenty-two transfemoral and sixty-one transtibial am-
putees. The descriptive data are given in (Table 1). There were 
no important differences between groups according to distri-
bution of gender or age while there were significant differ-
ence in period of prosthetic use and walking with aids. 
Most frequent cause of amputation was firearm injuries (63 
cases). 
The mean value of PCI in transfemoral amputees was 0.57 </p>

<p>(SD=0.085) and in transtibial amputees it was 0.43 (SD=0.087) 
and the mean value of CWS 60.14 (SD=6.8) for transfemoral 
and 75.6 (SD=12.92) for transtibial amputees. It is shown rel-
evant impact of level of amputation in physiological deter-
minates. There was significant difference between the PCI 
in TF (0.57) vs. TT amputees (0.43) (t=6.8, P&lt;0.001) and be-
tween the CWS in TF amputees (median =60.5, lowest = 47.0, 
highest = 72.0, n=22) and TT amputees (median = 78.0, lowest 
= 53.0, highest = 94.0, n=61); Mann-Whitney Rank Sum Test, </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>Transfemoral 
amputees(TF) 
n=22 </p>

<p>Transtibial 
amputees(TT) 
n=61 </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>Male/Female (n) 
20/2 
52/9 
0.719* 
Age (years) mean (SD) 
min-max </p>

<p>40.6 (12.5) 
24-70 </p>

<p>39.7 (13.1) 
18-70 
0.78 † </p>

<p>Period of prosthetic use 
(years) 
Mean (SD) </p>

<p>17.1 (10.5) 
14.5 (7.5) 
0.423 ‡ </p>

<p>Cause of amputation (n) 
Firearm injuries 
Trauma (accidents) 
Anomalies </p>

<p>10 
9 
2 </p>

<p>47 
11 
3 </p>

<p>Walking with aids (n) 
One crutch 
Two crutches </p>

<p>8 
3 </p>

<p>5 
5 </p>

<p>0.387 § </p>

<p>Physiological Cost Index 
mean (SD) 
Comfort Walking Speed 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>0.57 (0.085) 
60.14 (6.8) </p>

<p>0.43 (0.087) 
75.6 (12.92) </p>

<p>&lt;0.001# 
&lt;0.0001‖ </p>

<p>Table 1. Descriptive characteristics of amputees (n=83) * Fisher Exact test 
(P = 0.719),  †T-test, t=0.28 (P = 0.78),  ‡ Mann-Whitney Rank Sum 
Test, U = 650, (P = 0.423) </p>

<p>Sample TF 
Sample TT 
Sample size 
20 
58 
Lowest value 
5.0 
1.5 
Highest value 
47.0 
41.0 
Median 
13.0 
13.0 
95% CI for the median 
12.0 to 22.66 
13.0 to 13.0 
Interquartile range 
12.0 to 22.5 
12.0 to 13.0 </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney test (independent samples) </p>

<p>Average rank of first group 
43 </p>

<p>Average rank of second group </p>

<p>38.29 </p>

<p>Large sample test statistic Z </p>

<p>0.801 </p>

<p>Two-tailed probability </p>

<p>P = 0.423 </p>

<p> § Fisher Exact test (P = 0.387), # T-test, t=6.8 (P&lt;0.001), ‖ Mann-
Whitney Rank Sum Test, U = 234, (P &lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>Sample TF 
Sample TT 
Sample size 
22 
61 
Lowest value 
47.0 
53.0 
Highest value 
72.0 
94.0 
Median 
60.5 
78.0 
95% CI for the median 
56.0 to 64.79 
70.0 to 82.96 
Interquartile range 
56.0 to 65.0 
61.75 to 87.0 </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney test (independent samples) </p>

<p>Average rank of first group 
22.1364 
Average rank of second group 
49.1639 
Large sample test statistic Z 
-4.50875 
Two-tailed probability 
P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Physiological Cost Index and Comfort Walking Speed in Two Level Lower Limb Amputees Having No Vascular Disease </p>

<p>ORIGINAL PAPER / ACTA INFORM MED. 2015 FEB 23(1): 12-17 </p>



<p>U = 234, (P&lt;0.0001) (Table 1). </p>

<p>The average values of PCI (ANOVA F= 39.5 P &lt; 0.001) 
and CWS (ANOVA F=32.01, P &lt; 0.001) significantly differed 
among the four analyzed groups, categorized by level of am-
putation and using of crutches (Table 2). 
In transfemoral group of amputation with increasing age 
energy expenditure significantly increased (r = 0.662, P = 
0.001) while walking speed significantly decreased [ r =-0.56, 
P = 0.007) (Graph 1 and 2). 
The correlation coefficient (R), in transtibial amputees also 
showed that age was in significant correlation with PCI of (r 
= 0.597, P &lt; 0.001) and CWS of (r =-0.673, P &lt; 0.001) (Graph 
3 and 4). 
Advanced age and using crutches during prosthetic walking 
were significant factors that affect the energy expenditure in 
transfemoral amputees. With every increase of age by one 
year increased the average PCI of 0.005 , while using crutches 
increased the mean value of PCI for (-0.094). Based on the 
values of the correlation coefficients, we could conclude that 
the greater impact on the value of PCI had age (R=0.662) 
(Table 3). 
The simple linear regression analysis also showed important 
impact of advanced age and using of crutches in PCI values in 
transtibial amputees. With every increase in age by one year 
increases the average PCI of 0.004, while using the crutches </p>

<p>increased it (-0.144). The values of the correlation coefficients 
R, showed the greater impact on energy expenditure had car-
rying crutches (R = 0.622) (Table 3). 
By simple linear regression analysis it was shown a great 
impact of age and crutches in walking speed in transfem-
oral group of amputees. With every increase of age by one 
year mean value of CWS decreased of (-0.306), while using 
crutches decreased the mean value of the CWS of 11.0. The 
greater impact on the value of a CWS had age (R=-0.56) 
(Table 3). 
In transtibial group of amputees these two variables also 
has been shown as significant factors that affect the walking 
speed. With every increase in age by one year, mean value of 
CWS decrease of (-0.666), while using crutches reduces the 
average value of the CWS in 20.82. The values of correlation 
coefficient R showed that there was approximately same im-
pact of these two factors in walking speed, in transtibial am-
putees (Table 3). </p>

<p>4. DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Prosthetic ambulation is a primary concern in the rehabili-
tation process of lower limb amputees, and it is primarily ad-
dressed in energy expenditure and walking speed. This im-
portance is in correlation with other measures of prosthetic 
ambulation (16-19). 
Measuring energy cost of walking in lower limb amputees 
is an established method mostly done by assessment of oxygen 
consumption (VO 2 ), but more suitable for clinical settings is 
measuring of PCI. The only equipment that is needed is a 
standard heart rate monitor and a stopwatch. 
The present study investigated the PCI and CWS both in 
transfemoral and transtibial amputees as well as the influence 
of walking aids and age on them. Reports in the literature 
showed that energy cost of walking was greater in the ampu-
tated individuals compared to healthy controls (10, 16, 19) and 
increased with a higher level of amputation (16, 20). 
In our study, the mean PCI value for transfemoral group 
was (0.57, SD= 0.085) and for transtibial group of amputees 
(0.43, SD=0.087 ) which were in accordance with mean value 
of PCI for transfemoral amputees in studies (7, 21) respec-
tively with transtibial amputees in study of Canadian authors 
(22). 
Energy consumption is usually measured by either a floor 
test or a treadmill test but we preferred the floor test because 
of possibility of using walking aids during the test and the pa-
tient's ability to select the most comfortable walking speed. 
CWS is considered to be a reliable measure highly correlated 
to other aspects of walking (23, 24). 
In our study, the mean CWS value for transfemoral ampu-
tees (60.14 m/min, SD=6.8) was close to the speed reported 
in other studies (16, 17, 21, 23). The mean value of CWS for 
transtibial amputees (76.5 m/min, SD= 12.8) was similar to 
other studies (19, 20) particularly with CWS (71 m/min.), re-
ported in Pagliarulo at al. (26) and Waters at al. (16) with trau-
matic transtibial amputees. 
In most of the studies, the included cases were selected as 
those with no pathological stump condition, a good socket 
fit and those with the ability to perform the test without the 
support of a walking with aids. However, we preferred to in-
clude cases which in daily life used crutches during prosthetic </p>

<p>Groups 
PCI*, mean±SD (min-
max) </p>

<p>CWS </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>, mean±SD 
(min-max) 
Transfemoral walking 
with aids (n=11) 
0.62±0.05 (0.57-0.75) 54.64±3.67 (47-61) </p>

<p>Transfemoral walking 
without aids (n=11) 
0.53±0.09 (0.37-0.66) 65.64±4.18 (60-72) </p>

<p>Transtibial walking with 
aids (n=10) 
0.55±0.09 (0.35-0.72) 58.2±2.62 (53-62) </p>

<p>Transtibial walking with-
out aids (n=51) 
0.40±0.06 (0.29-0.58) 79.02±11.26 (55-94) </p>

<p>Table 2. Differences of Physiological Cost Index (PCI) and Comfortable 
Walking Speed (CWS) in transfemoral and transtibial amputees in relation 
to using aids. * One Way ANOVA: F=39.5, P&lt;0.001,  † One Way 
ANOVA: F=32.01, P&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Comparison 
Diff of Means P value </p>

<p>TF with aids vs. TT without aids 
0.217 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>TF with aids vs. TF without aids 
0.0936 
0.012 </p>

<p>TF with aids vs. TT with aids 
0.073 
0.084 </p>

<p>TT with aids vs. TT without aids 
0.144 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>TT with aids vs. TF without aids 
0.0206 
0.905 </p>

<p>TF without aids vs. TT without aids 
0.124 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Transfemoral amputees(TF) 
(n=22) </p>

<p>Transtibial amputees(TT) 
(n=61) </p>

<p>Coefficient 
Multiple 
R 
P 
Coefficients 
Multiple 
R 
P </p>

<p>PCI </p>

<p>Intercept 
Age </p>

<p>0.389 
0.005 
0.662 
0.001 </p>

<p>0.269 
0.004 
0.597 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Intercept 
Crutches </p>

<p>0.714 
-0.094 
-0.569 
0.007 </p>

<p>0.691 
-0.144 
-0.622 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>CWS </p>

<p>Intercept 
Age </p>

<p>72,553 
-0.306 
-0.560 
0.007 
102.054 
-0.666 
-0.673 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Intercept 
Crutches </p>

<p>43,636 
11.000 
0.086 
&lt;0 
.001 </p>

<p>37.380 
20.820 
0.601 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Table 3. Simple Linear Regression-Impact of age and using crutches in PCI 
and CWS by level of amputation </p>

<p>Physiological Cost Index and Comfort Walking Speed in Two Level Lower Limb Amputees Having No Vascular Disease </p>

<p>ACTA INFORM MED. 2015 FEB 23(1): 12-17 / ORIGINAL PAPER </p>



<p>ambulation, so we tested them while they walked with as-
sisting devices. 
Energy cost significantly increased and walking speed sig-
nificantly decreased both in transfemoral and transtibial am-
putees in cases with prosthetic walking performed supported 
by aids. 
It was difficult to compare our findings with other au-
thors since no study analyzed the same occasion-walking 
with prosthesis and with crutches. In study, Walters at al., 
which analyzed difference between prosthetic walking and 
walking with crutches without prosthesis found that the rate 
of oxygen consumption, heart rate, and respiratory quotient </p>

<p>were significantly increased in all groups of amputees when 
walking with crutches but without a prosthesis (26). Also, the 
authors (27), which analyzed unilateral transtibial traumatic 
amputees, found that crutch walking requires more exertion 
than walking with prosthesis without crutches. In other side, 
there is the study of Trabaselli at al. which assessed energy 
consumption and self selected walking speed in amputees 
with vascular disease who were using walking aids during 
walking on the floor or a treadmill. They didn't analyzed the 
influence of walking aids on energy cost of walking, their aim 
was to measure the impact of walking surface-overground 
or treadmill walking. So, we couldn't compare their findings </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Graph. 1. Linear Regression -Transfemoral amputees 
y variable: PCI 
x variable: Age (year) </p>

<p>Age (year) </p>

<p>30 
40 
50 
60 
70 </p>

<p>PCI </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>y = 0.3892 + 0.0045x 
R 
2 =0.438, r= 0.662, (p=0.001) </p>

<p>Graph. 2. Linear Regression -Transfemoral amputees 
y variable: CWS 
x variable: Age (year) </p>

<p>Age (year) </p>

<p>30 
40 
50 
60 
70 </p>

<p>CWS (m/min.) </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>y = 72.55 -0.306*x 
R 
2 =0.314, r = -0.56, (p=0.007) </p>

<p>Graph. 3. Linear Regression -Transtibial amputees 
y variable: PCI 
x variable: Age (year) </p>

<p>Age (year) </p>

<p>20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 </p>

<p>PCI </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>y = 0.269 + 0.004x 
R 
2 =0.356, r= 0.597, (p&lt;0.001) </p>

<p>Graph. 4. Linear Regression -Transtibial amputees 
y variable: CWS 
x variable: Age (year) </p>

<p>Age (year) </p>

<p>20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 </p>

<p>CWS (m/min.) </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>y = 102.05 -0.666*x 
R 
2 =0.454, r = -0.673, (p&lt;0.001) </p>

<p>Plagiarism avoidance: </p>

<p>Physiological Cost Index and Comfort Walking Speed in Two Level Lower Limb Amputees Having No Vascular Disease </p>

<p>ORIGINAL PAPER / ACTA INFORM MED. 2015 FEB 23(1): 12-17 </p>



<p>with ours. 
Although our fi ndings provide evidence that prosthetic 
walking supported with aids was accompanied with more en-
ergy consumption and lower walking speed we concur with 
the suggestion of authors (27), that patients with lower limb 
amputations should rather prescribe prosthetic walk sup-
ported with crutches than crutch walk. 
Age was found as an important factor infl uencing the en-
ergy expenditure and walking speed in able bodied (16, 
28-30) and in lower limb amputees (16, 19). However, we 
thought it would be very interesting to shed more light on 
possible diff erences in prosthetic walking according to age. 
So, we analyzed its impact in our amputees and we found a 
great impact in both group of amputees on both physiological 
determinants. 
In other side, authors (31) in their study found that gender 
and height were correlated signifi cantly with gait speed but 
weight and age were not. Their explanation was because of 
restricted age range (50 -79) of subjects. 
We have to mention some limitations of this study that 
should be addressed in future studies. 
The fi rst one is having no control group. The eff ect of pros-
thetic components on energy consumption and measuring 
kinetic and kinematic properties of walking was beyond the 
scope of this study, although it would be desirable. Also, there 
were small number of cases with crutches especially when 
grouped by number of used crutches. </p>

<p>5. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>This study showed that walking with transfemoral pros-
thesis is matched with higher costs of energy and slower 
walking speed compared to transtibial prosthesis. Walking 
aids had a great impact in increasing of energy expenditure 
and reducing the walking speed while amputees were per-
forming prosthetic ambulation. Also, the age was shown as an 
important factor infl uencing the PCI and CWS in both group 
of amputees. 
Acknowledgments 
We thank Lulzim Geci-director of the OrthoProstetic 
Center of Kosovo, for the useful data to contacting the pa-
tients and Haki Krasniqi and Shaip Loshi orthoprosthetists in 
this center, for the technical support in realization of this re-
search. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST: NONE DECLARED </p>



<p>Physiological Cost Index and Comfort Walking Speed in Two Level Lower Limb Amputees Having No Vascular Disease </p>

<p>ACTA INFORM MED. 2015 FEB 23(1): 12-17 / ORIGINAL PAPER </p>





</text></tei>