<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4097343" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We propose a new sealed battery operating on a redox reaction between an oxide (O 22 ) and a peroxide (O 2 
22 ) 
with its theoretical specific energy of 2570 Wh kg 21 (897 mAh g 21 , 2.87 V) and demonstrate that a 
Co-doped Li 2 O cathode exhibits a reversible capacity over 190 mAh g 21 , a high rate capability, and a good 
cyclability with a superconcentrated lithium bis(fluorosulfonyl)amide electrolyte in acetonitrile. The 
reversible capacity is largely dominated by the O 22 /O 2 
22 redox reaction between oxide and peroxide with 
some contribution of the Co 21 /Co 31 redox reaction. </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>echargeable lithium ion batteries (LIBs) operating on shuttling of lithium between the negative and positive 
electrodes, both of which are composed of topotactic insertion hosts of lithium such as graphite and 
LiCoO 2 , are indispensable to our society as power sources for portable and large electronic appliances 
such as notebook computers and electric vehicles. However, their energy densities are rather modest; even the 
state-of-the-art LIBs do not exceed 250 Wh kg 21 . Therefore, various researches are being carried out to develop 
post-LIBs with much higher energy densities. 
One of the approaches is utilization of electrode materials operating on so-called conversion reactions and the 
theoretical specific capacity is 714 mAh g 21 for the reaction of CoO 1 2Li 1 1 2e 2 R Co 1 Li 2 O 1 , while the severe 
hysteresis in voltage between the charging and discharging processes generally limits the energy efficiency. 
Moreover, some metal oxides including CoO show surprisingly good cycling reversibility despite the highly 
destructive nature of the conversion reaction. However, such oxide materials can be used only for anodes, because 
their working potentials are typically in the range of 0-1 V (vs. Li/Li 1 ) and low. Recently, some fluorides such as 
BiF 3 
2 and FeF 2 (or FeF 3 ) 3 have been reported to operate at higher potentials (2.7-3.4 V), while their poor kinetics 
and reversibility are problems. 
Another approach is a development of a lithium-air (Li-O 2 ) battery by use of atmospheric O 2 with a theoretical 
specific energy of 3400 Wh kg 21 even including the weight of oxygen in the discharged product (Li 2 O 2 ). However, 
the actual capacity or the energy is dependent on the pore volumes of the cathode matrices where Li 2 O 2 is formed, 
the pores are clogged with solids, and the discharge is prohibited by the limitation of the oxygen supply. In 
addition, there are more serious inherent problems of the open device, suffering from the coexisting moisture and 
CO 2 , and safety for the application to electronic vehicles. The main discharge product for Li-O 2 batteries is Li 2 O 2 
according to the reaction (the equilibrium potential, Eu (vs. Li/Li 1 )) 4,5 , </p>

<p>O 2 z2Li z z2e { ?Li 2 O 2 E 0 
1 ~2:96 V 
À 
Á 
: 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>The subsequent reduction of Li 2 O 2 has recently been pointed out to take place to form Li 2 O during the deep 
discharge according to the reaction 6-9 , </p>

<p>Li 2 O 2 z2Li z z2e { ?2Li 2 O E 0 
2 ~2:87 V 
À 
Á 
: 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>However, there is no report on the repetition of the charge and 
discharge utilizing the reaction between Li 2 O (or O 22 ) and Li 2 O 2 
(or O 2 
22 ). The investigation on LIB cathodes such as LiCoO 2 and 
Li-rich layered oxides shows not only the charge compensation 
mechanism involving transition metal ions but also some contri-
bution of the reversible redox reaction of oxygen atoms 10-13 . 
Therefore, we have reached an idea that Li 2 O 2 would act as a 3 V-
level cathode utilizing the redox couple of oxide (O 22 )/peroxide 
(O 2 
22 ) [equation (2)]. In addition, a certain electrode catalyst or 
mediator would selectively accelerate the thermodynamically more 
favourable backward reaction of equation (2) instead of the back-
ward reaction of equation (1) and the following reaction, </p>

<p>Li 2 O?1=2O 2 z2Li z z2e { E 0 
3 ~2:91 V 
À 
Á 
: 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>Here, we propose a new sealed battery operating on a redox reaction 
between O 22 and O 2 
22 with its theoretical specific energy of 
2570 Wh kg 21 (897 mAh g 21 , 2.87 V, see the Supplementary 
Information) based on the reaction, </p>

<p>2LizLi 2 O 2 ?2Li 2 O, 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>and demonstrate that a Co-doped Li 2 O cathode exhibits a reversible 
capacity over 190 mAh g 21 , a high rate capability, and a good 
cyclability with a superconcentrated lithium bis(fluorosulfonyl)a-
mide (LiFSA) electrolyte in acetonitrile 14 . The reversible capacity is 
largely dominated by the reaction of equation (2) with some contri-
bution of the redox reaction of Co ions. </p>

<p>Results 
Preparation and Characterization of the Co-Doped Li 2 O Cathode. 
The powders (Co/Li 5 0.025-0.2) of Li 2 O and Co 3 O 4 were 
pulverized and the Co-doped Li 2 O were obtained. Among them, 
the Co-doped Li 2 O (Co/Li 5 0.1) showed the best charge-
discharge performance (Supplementary Figure S1a). The electronic 
conductivity of the Co-doped Li 2 O (Co/Li 5 0.1) powder compact 
was 5.3 3 10 2 kV cm, while Li 2 O is an insulator. Therefore, the 
resulting Co-doped Li 2 O (Co/Li 5 0.1) was hereafter used as a 
cathode and the specific capacity was calculated on the basis of the 
total weight of the Co-doped Li 2 O. Rh 2 O 3 and IrO 2 could also act 
similarly to Co 3 O 4 (Supplementary Figure S1b). 
In the X-ray diffraction (XRD) pattern of the Co-doped Li 2 O 
(Supplementary Figure S2), broad peaks of anti-fluorite-type Li 2 O 
and a weak peak at 44.8u of cubic LiCoO 2 
15 were observed, while 
peaks of spinel-type Co 3 O 4 were not observed. The peak intensity of 
the cubic LiCoO 2 increased upon increase in the Co/Li ratio. 
The Co K-edge X-ray absorption near edge structure (XANES) 
measurement of the Co-doped Li 2 O was carried out to investigate the 
oxidation states and coordination environments of the Co species 
(Supplementary Figure S3). The absorption edge position agreed 
with that of starting Co 3 O 4 , indicating that the average Co valence 
does not change under mechanical milling conditions. The pre-edge 
peak of the Co-doped Li 2 O was stronger than those of Co 3 O 4 and 
LiCoO 2 and as strong as that of the spinel CoAl 2 O 4 , in which every 
Co 21 ion is located at the tetrahedral site. This absorption represents 
the transition of the 1s electron to an unoccupied d orbital of Co ions, 
which is an electric dipole forbidden transition in an ideal octahedral 
symmetry, while the noncentrosymmetric tetrahedral environment 
allows the transition 16,17 . Thus, the intense pre-edge peak shows the 
presence of considerable amounts of tetrahedral Co. </p>

<p>Electrochemical Performance. The charge and discharge curves of 
the cell consisting of the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode, a Li metal anode, 
and a superconcentrated 4 M LiFSA electrolyte in acetonitrile 14 are 
shown in Figure 1. The charge voltage gradually increased and </p>

<p>reached approximately 3.2 V above 150 mAh g 21 . The discharge 
and charge curves from the first to 15th cycle almost unchanged 
with the constant coulombic efficiency of ca. 96% at 45 mA g 21 
(Figure 1a). The 1st discharge capacity reached 195 mAh g 21 at a 
low current density of 13.5 mA g 21 and the capacity of 133 mAh g 21 
can be discharged even at a very high current density of 1080 mA g 21 
at which the capacity of 200 mAh g 21 can be charged in 11 min 
(Figure 1b). </p>

<p>Co K-edge XANES Measurement of the Co-Doped Li 2 O Cathode 
during the Charge and Discharge Process. The Co K-edge XANES 
spectra were measured at various charge and discharge capacities 
(Figure 2). In the charge process from 0 to 54 mAh g 21 , the 
absorption edge position shifted to the higher photon energy, 
indicating the oxidation of Co 21 to Co 31 . By the further increase in 
the capacity the edge position of Co 31 did not change. In the discharge 
process after the charge to 270 mAh g 21 , the absorption edge position 
hardly changed in the range of 0-162 mAh g 21 and then returned to 
the initial position upon the discharge to 250 mAh g 21 . </p>

<p>Peroxide Analysis in the Co-Doped Li 2 O Cathode during the 
Charge and Discharge Process. We quantified O 2 
22 species in the 
Co-doped Li 2 O cathode at various charge and discharge capacities. 
Figure 3a shows the amounts of the O 2 
22 (detected as O 2 ) in the 
cathode at various charge capacities. In the range of 0-54 mAh 
g 21 , the amounts of the O 2 
22 were negligible. In the region 54-
216 mAh g 21 , the amounts of the O 2 
22 increased and the slope 
from 162 mAh g 21 to 216 mAh g 21 corresponded to 0.5 O 2 
22 /e 2 . 
In the final region of 216-270 mAh g 21 , the amounts of the O 2 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>more gradually increased. 
Figure 3d shows amounts of the O 2 
22 in the cathode at various 
discharge capacities after the charge to 270 mAh g 21 . In the region of 
0-162 mAh g 21 , the amounts of the O 2 
22 decreased and the slope 
from 0 mAh g 21 to 108 mAh g 21 corresponded to 0.5 O 2 
22 /e 2 . In the </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Electrochemical performances of the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode. </p>

<p>(a) Charge and discharge voltage curves in repeated charge/discharge 
cycles at 45 mA g 21 . (b) Charge and discharge voltage curves at various 
current densities (13.5-1080 mA g 21 ). Each testing cell was charged to 
200 mAh g 21 , and then discharged to the cut off voltage of 2.0 V at a 
constant current density. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5684 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05684 </p>

<p>
final region of 162-250 mAh g 21 , the O 2 
22 was hardly detected. We 
also quantified the O 2 
22 species in the cathode recharged to 270 mAh 
g 21 . The amount of the O 2 
22 was 2.31 mmol g 21 in approximate 
agreement with that for the first charge. </p>

<p>Observation and Analysis of the Cathode during the Charge. The 
in-situ gas phase analysis during the charge process was conducted. 
In Figure 4b, cumulative amounts (per weight of the Co-doped Li 2 O </p>

<p>cathode) of O 2 and CO 2 evolved are shown together with its charge 
curve (Figure 4a). In the range of 0-216 mAh g 21 , O 2 was hardly 
observed, and then the amount of O 2 evolution monotonically 
increased. The slope of O 2 evolution in the range of 324-594 mAh 
g 21 almost corresponded to 0.25 O 2 /e 2 . The XRD 111 peak intensity 
of the Co-doped Li 2 O was approximately linearly weakened with 
increase in the charge capacity from 0 to 324 mAh g 21 and was 
more slowly weakened at 540 and 580 mAh g 21 (Figure 4c and </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Co K-edge XANES spectra of the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode at various charge and discharge capacities. The current densities were 4.5 mA g 21 . </p>

<p>The insets show the absorption edge regions of the spectra. (a) Charge process. (b) Discharge process. </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Analysis of the Co-doped Li 2 O cathodes after the charge and the discharge. (a) and (d) Analytical peroxide amounts of the cathodes after the </p>

<p>charge (a) and discharge (d). (b) and (e) Co K-edge XANES absorption edge positions of the cathodes after the charge (b) and discharge (e). (c) and (f) 
Charge (c) and discharge (f) voltage curves at current density of 4.5 mA g 21 . </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5684 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05684 </p>

<p>
Supplementary Figure S4). The evolution of CO 2 was not observed in 
the whole range of the charge process. 
Direct observation of the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode charged to 
270 mAh g 21 was attempted with high resolution transmission elec-
tron microscopy (HRTEM). Figure 5 shows the HRTEM image and 
the fast Fourier transform (FFT) pattern. Since some spots in 
Figure 5b lie on the circles estimated with the Li 2 O 2 crystal structure, 
many fringe regions surrounded by red circles in Figure 5a are likely 
attributable to Li 2 O 2 . In contrast, for the starting cathode before the 
charge, since all spots (Supplementary Figure S5b) lie on the circles 
estimated with Li 2 O or cubic LiCoO 2 crystal structures, many fringe 
regions surrounded by red circles (Supplementary Figure S5a) are 
likely attributable to Li 2 O or cubic LiCoO 2 . </p>

<p>Discussion 
Upon increase in Co content above Co/Li 5 0.1, the discharge capa-
city decreased (Supplementary Figure S1a) and the XRD peak intens-
ity of cubic LiCoO 2 increased (Supplementary Figure S2), suggesting </p>

<p>that the resulting cubic LiCoO 2 is inactive for the charge and 
discharge reactions at the voltage of 2.0-3.2 V (vs. Li/Li 1 ) as has 
been reported in ref. (18). 
In the XRD pattern of the Co-doped Li 2 O (Supplementary Figure 
S2), broad peaks of anti-fluorite-type Li 2 O and a weak peak at 44.8u 
of cubic LiCoO 2 
15 were observed, while peaks of spinel-type Co 3 O 4 
were not observed. The volume fractions of Co-doped Li 2 O and cubic 
LiCoO 2 were estimated to be 0.9050.10 with the parameters of 111 
reflection of Co-doped Li 2 O and 200 one of cubic LiCoO 2 in 
Supplementary Table S1 (see the Supplementary Information). The 
Co K-edge XANES spectrum of the Co-doped Li 2 O shows the pres-
ence of considerable amounts of tetrahedral Co (Supplementary 
Figure S3). These results indicate that most of Co ions are substitu-
tionally doped in the tetrahedral Li sites of the anti-fluorite Li 2 O 
structure with formation of vacancies at the same sites due to charge 
compensation. Co 21 and Co 31 in the Co-doped Li 2 O would be ran-
domly distributed at the tetrahedral sites in a defective anti-fluorite 
structure, since the XRD pattern was not identical to that of the 
defective anti-fluorite structure, in which Co ions were ordered in 
the tetrahedral sites 19,20 . 
The Co-doped Li 2 O cathode, of which the theoretical specific 
capacity is calculated to be 556 mAh g 21 based on the weight of 
Li 2 O in the Co-doped Li 2 O (see the Supplementary Information), 
exhibited a reversible capacity over 190 mAh g 21 , a high rate cap-
ability, and a good cyclability (Figure 1). The electronic conductivity 
of the Co-doped Li 2 O powder compact was 5.3 3 10 2 kV cm and of 
the same level (5 3 10 2 kV cm) as that of LiMn 2 O 4 
21 , showing that 
the Co-doped Li 2 O can work as an electrode material. This conduc-
tivity is possibly explained by narrowing of the Li 2 O band gap by 
formation of the impurity state with the dope of Co or becoming 
metallic by the carrier dope. The coulombic efficiency of the present 
system is 96% and still below 100%. This is possibly explained by the 
progress of the side reaction of solid electrolyte interface formation 
during the charge other than CO 2 formation. 
To clarify the oxidation states of Co and the presence of O 2 
22 in the 
Co-doped Li 2 O cathode, the Co K-edge XANES measurement and </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Voltage, gas evolution, XRD peak intensity of the Co-doped </p>

<p>Li 2 O cathode in the charge process. (a) The voltage curve. (b) Cumulative 
amounts of O 2 and CO 2 evolved in the charge process at the current density 
of 4.5 mA g 21 . The slope of 0.25 O 2 /e 2 indicates theoretical rate of O 2 
evolution according to the reaction, 2O 22 R 4e 2 1 O 2 . (c) The XRD 111 
peak intensity of Co-doped Li 2 O. The peak intensity at 0 mAh g 21 was taken 
as a unity. The black line is a theoretical line of change in the peak intensity. </p>

<p>Figure 5 | HRTEM image and FFT pattern of the Co-doped Li 2 O. </p>

<p>(a) HRTEM image after the charge. The areas in red circles were obtained 
by the inverse Fourier transformation of the spots in the FFT pattern that 
are attributed to Li 2 O 2 . The periods of the fringe in the areas were 
confirmed to be equal to those in Li 2 O 2 . (b) FFT pattern of the HRTEM 
image. The white circles are on the basis of Li 2 O 2 . </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5684 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05684 </p>

<p>
quantification of O 2 
22 species were carried out at various charge and 
discharge capacities (Figures 2 and 3). In the charge process from 0 to 
54 mAh g 21 , the oxidation of Co 21 to Co 31 proceeds without the O 22 
oxidation (Figures 3a and 3b). The oxidation of Co 21 to Co 31 in the 
charge process is completed at the charge capacity #54 mAh g 21 in 
accord with the theoretical capacity (39 mAh g 21 ) of the cathode due 
to the oxidation of Co 21 to Co 31 . In the region of 54-216 mAh g 21 , 
the amounts of the O 2 
22 increased and the slope from 162 mAh g 21 
to 216 mAh g 21 corresponded to 0.5 O 2 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>/e 2 , suggesting the O 2 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>formation according to the backward reaction of equation (2) 
(Figure 3a). In the final region of 216-270 mAh g 21 , the amounts 
of the O 2 
22 more gradually increased. Considering the O 2 evolution 
curve (Figure 4b), both the O 2 
22 formation and O 2 evolution reac-
tions likely proceed in this region. 
In the discharge process from 0 to 162 mAh g 21 , the amounts of 
the O 2 
22 decreased and the slope from 0 mAh g 21 to 108 mAh g 21 
corresponded to 0.5 O 2 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>/e 2 , suggesting the consumption of the 
O 2 
22 according to equation (2) (Figure 3d). In the final region of 
162-250 mAh g 21 , the O 2 
22 was hardly detected, indicating that the 
discharge mostly consists of the reduction of Co 31 to Co 21 , in agree-
ment with the Co K-edge XANES results (Figures 2b and 3e). In the 
recharge process to 270 mAh g 21 , the amount of the O 2 
22 was 
2.31 mmol g 21 in approximate agreement with that for the first 
charge, suggesting reversible formation of O 2 
22 in the repeated 
cycles. 
It is essentially important for the present battery that no substan-
tial amount of O 2 is released in the charge process. Moreover, CO 2 
evolution accompanied by anodic side reactions between Li 2 O 2 and 
carbon additives or electrolytes has been pointed out as a problem of 
the Li-O 2 batteries 22-24 . In the range of 0-216 mAh g 21 , O 2 was 
hardly observed (Figure 4b), suggesting that the side reactions of 
O 2 evolution do not proceed and Co-doped Li 2 O is oxidized accord-
ing to the reaction, 2O 22 R O 2 
22 1 2e 2 , with some contribution of 
the oxidation of Co ions. The slope of 0.25 O 2 /e 2 in the range of 324-
594 mAh g 21 suggests that O 2 is formed according to the direct 
reaction (i) 2Li 2 O R O 2 1 4Li 1 1 4e 2 and/or the consecutive reac-
tion (ii) 2Li 2 O R Li 2 O 2 1 2Li 1 1 2e 2 R O 2 1 4Li 1 1 4e 2 (the 
overall reaction, 2O 22 R O 2 1 4e 2 ). The investigation on the mech-
anism of the O 2 evolution is in progress. The XRD 111 peak intensity 
of the Co-doped Li 2 O was approximately linearly weakened with 
increase in the charge capacity toward the theoretical capacity of 
556 mAh g 21 (Figure 4c and Supplementary Figure S4). The upper 
deviation from the linear line at 540 and 580 mAh g 21 is probably 
due to the O 2 evolution. While the HRTEM image shows fringe 
regions attributed to Li 2 O 2 (Figure 5), the XRD patterns of Co-doped 
Li 2 O upon charged to 270, 324 and 540 mAh g 21 showed no Li 2 O 2 
signal (Supplementary Figure S4) because of the small amount and 
poor crystallinity. The evolution of CO 2 was not observed in the 
whole range of the charge process, showing that the Co-doped 
Li 2 O cathode is free from side reactions to produce CO 2 and the 
superconcentrated LiFSA electrolyte in acetonitrile is stable under 
the present conditions. 
All results demonstrate that the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode is 
charged without the O 2 evolution in the region of 0-216 mAh g 21 
(Figure 4b) via the oxidation of Co 21 to Co 31 (0-54 mAh g 21 ) 
(Figure 2a) and the subsequent oxidation of O 22 to O 2 
22 (54-
216 mAh g 21 ) (Figure 3a) according to the reaction, 2Li 2 O R 
Li 2 O 2 1 2Li 1 1 2e 2 : Eu 5 2.87 V. In the higher capacity range, 
O 2 was evolved, suggesting the progress of reactions with the higher 
equilibrium potential, 2Li 2 O R O 2 1 4Li 1 1 4e 2 : Eu 5 2.91 V and/ 
or Li 2 O 2 R O 2 1 2Li 1 1 2e 2 : Eu 5 2.96 V as expected thermo-
dynamically. At the present stage, the reversible specific capacity of 
the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode was ca. 200 mAh g 21 and lower than its 
theoretical 556 mAh g 21 . 
In conclusion, we have proposed and demonstrated a new sealed 
and high-rate battery operating on a redox reaction between O 22 and </p>

<p>O 2 
22 with the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode and a superconcentrated 
LiFSA electrolyte in acetonitrile; a reversible capacity over 190 
mAh g 21 , a high rate capability, and a good cyclability. The reversible 
capacity was largely dominated by the reaction, O 2 
22 1 2e 2 « 2O 22 , 
with some contribution of the redox reaction of Co. The present 
specific capacity of the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode is still lower than 
its theoretical 556 mAh g 21 . The investigation of roles of Co in the 
redox reaction between O 22 and O 2 
22 and the state of the O 2 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>species in the Co-doped Li 2 O would lead to the improvement of 
the specific capacity. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Preparation of the Co-Doped Li 2 O. Accurately weighed powders of Li 2 O (Kojundo 
Chemical Laboratory co., ltd.) and Co 3 O 4 (Wako Pure Chemical Industry, ltd.) were 
loaded into a zirconia milling pot (45 mL) in an Ar-filled glove box (LABmaster SP, 
MBRAUN) at atomic ratio of Co/Li 5 0.1. The milling pot was fixed in a planetary 
ball mill machine (Pulverisette 7, Fritsch) and agitated with zirconia milling balls 
(10 mm diameter 3 25) at 600 rpm for 200 h. Then, the milling pot was opened in an 
Ar-filled glove box and a dark green powder was collected. The elemental analysis of 
the resulting powder was carried out by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission 
spectroscopy (ICP-AES); Li 28.7 wt%, Co 24.0 wt%, atomic ratio of Co/Li 5 0.099. </p>

<p>Electrochemical Measurements. The Co-doped Li 2 O cathode was prepared by 
blending the active material thoroughly with powder acetylene black and 
polytetrafluoroethylene at the weight ratio of 4555055. The material was then pressed 
on an Al mesh (100 mesh) current collector to form an electrode. The cathode, a Li 
anode pressed on a Cu foil current collector, a concentrated electrolyte solution of 
4 M LiFSA in acetonitrile 14 , and a glass fibre filter (GA-55, Toyo Roshi Kaisha, Ltd.) as 
a separator were assembled in two-electrode cells (HS Test Cell or CR2032 coin-type 
cell, Hosen Corp.). All these procedures were carried out in an Ar-filled glove box. 
The charge and discharge tests were conducted with a battery charge/discharge 
system HJ1001SD8 (Hokuto Denko Corporation). </p>

<p>Characterization of Materials. The elemental analysis of Li and Co was performed by 
ICP-AES with ICPS-8100 (Shimadzu). The Co-doped Li 2 O powder (11.37 mg) was 
weighed in an Ar-filled glove box and dissolved into 1 mL of an aqueous solution 
(6 M HCl). The solution was diluted in a volumetric flask to 100 mL and then 5 mL of 
the solution was diluted in a volumetric flask to 50 mL. The concentrations of Li and 
Co were quantified with standard solutions of Li and Co (0-4 ppm). 
Powder XRD patterns were measured using the monochromatized Cu-K a1 radi-
ation on a RIGAKU Smart-Lab system. Every sample was mounted in a gas-tight 
holder with a Be window filled with Ar. The charged or discharged Co-doped Li 2 O 
cathode was removed from the cell, washed three times with acetonitrile, and dried 
under vacuum. All procedures were carried out in an Ar-filled glove box. 
The oxidation states and coordination environments of Co in the cathode were 
observed with XANES measurements. The XANES measurements at the Co K-edge 
were carried out on the BL14B2 beamline at the SPring-8 synchrotron radiation 
facility (8 GeV, 100 mA) of the Japan Synchrotron Radiation Research Institute 
(JASRI) in Hyogo, Japan. A Si(111) two-crystal monochromator was used for the 
measurements of Co K-edge XANES spectra. Ion chambers filled with N 2 (100%) and 
N 2 (85%)/Ar (15%) were used for the I 0 /I detector. XANES spectra at Co K-edge were 
collected in a transmission mode, and the total acquisition time was 6 min per 
spectrum. Data reduction was performed by using the <rs type="software">REX2000</rs> program (Rigaku 
Co., Ltd.). 
The HRTEM measurements of the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode pristine and after 
charged to 270 mAh g 21 were carried out on a JEM-4010 microscope (JEOL, Japan) at 
an accelerating voltage of 400 kV. </p>

<p>Measurements of O 2 and CO 2 Evolution in the Charging Process. The Co-doped 
Li 2 O cathode (11.3 mg) was pressed on an Al mesh as a current collector. The 
negative electrode was a metallic Li foil pressed on a Cu mesh. These electrodes, a glass 
fibre filter separator, and a 4 M LiFSA electrolyte were assembled in a two electrode 
beaker cell. The resulting beaker cell, a circulation cylinder, and a 2-position 6-port 
valve with a sampling loop were assembled. All these procedures were carried out in 
an Ar-filled glove box. Then, the system was transferred outside and connected to the 
gas flow system directly connected to a quadrupole mass spectrometer (OmniStar 
GSD301, Pfeiffer Vacuum) (Supplementary Figure S6). The galvanostatic charging 
test was conducted at a rate of 4.5 mA g 21 (50.9 mA) for 168 h at room temperature 
(ca. 298 K) with SI 1287 (Solartron) potentio/galvanostat. The gases in the cell were 
transferred to the sampling loop by using the circulating cylinder and the analysis was 
conducted every 12 h with the mass spectrometer as follows: The gases in the 
sampling loop were purged with a carrier gas (He, 50 mL min 21 ) by switching the 
valve and transferred into the mass spectrometer. To remove a vapour of acetonitrile, 
the purged gases were passed through a cold trap (ca. 193 K). The concentrations of 
O 2 (m/z 5 32) and CO 2 (m/z 5 44) were determined with the integrated peak areas of 
O 2 and CO 2 (with respect to that of Ar (m/z 5 40)), respectively. </p>

<p>Analysis of Peroxide in Cathodes. The charged or discharged cathodes were 
removed from the coin-type cell, washed three times with acetonitrile, and dried </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5684 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05684 </p>

<p>
under vacuum. Then, the sample, 1 g of ice water in a small glass container frozen 
with liquid nitrogen at 77 K, and a small amount of Pt powder (,1 mg) were put into 
the beaker cell (Supplementary Figure S6) and the beaker cell was closed with a gas 
tight glass cap. The resulting beaker cell, a circulation cylinder, and a 2-position 6-
port valve with a sampling loop were assembled. All these procedures were carried out 
in an Ar-filled glove box. Then, the system was quickly transferred outside and 
connected to the gas flow system directly connected to a quadrupole mass 
spectrometer (OmniStar GSD301, Pfeiffer Vacuum) (Supplementary Figure S6). 
Before the ice melted, the background oxygen concentration in the cell was analysed 
with the quadrupole mass spectrometer. Then, the sample was dispersed in the ice 
melting water and O 2 was evolved in the presence of a Pt catalyst. The amount of O 2 
evolved was quantitatively estimated with the quadrupole mass spectrometer in the 
same way as that described in the section of measurements of O 2 and CO 2 evolution in 
the charging process. It was confirmed in a separate experiment that the amount of 
Li 2 O 2 is quantitatively estimated with the amount of O 2 evolved in the presence of the 
Pt catalyst according to the reaction, Li 2 O 2 R 0.5O 2 1 Li 2 O. To confirm the origin of 
oxygen atoms in the peroxide in the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode, the labelled experiment 
was carried out by using H 2 
18 O in an N 2 -filled glove box to prevent overlapping of the 
m/z value of 36 Ar with that of 18 O 2 . For the mass analysis of the Co-doped Li 2 O 
cathode charged to 270 mAh g 21 , a signal at m/z 5 32 was observed and those at m/z 
5 34 and 36 were not observed (Supplementary Figure S7). These results show that 
the oxygen atoms in the O 2 result from those in the Co-doped Li 2 O cathode. </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank T. Honma and H. Ofuchi (JASRI) for XANES measurements. This work is 
supported by the Japan Society of the Promotion of Science (JSPS) through its ''Funding 
Program for World-Leading Innovative R&amp;D on Science and Technology (FIRST 
Program)'' and Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Researches from the Ministry of Education, 
Culture, Sports, Science and Technology. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>N.M. conceived the project. S.O., H.O., K.Y. and Y.S. synthesized the material. S.O., Y.O. 
and Y.S. tested the battery, with direction from M.H., T.K., Y.Y., A.Y. and N.M. S.O. and 
Y.O. collected and analysed data for X-ray diffraction and X-ray absorption near edge 
structure measurements, with direction from M.H. and M.O. Y.O. designed and conducted 
experiments for gas phase analysis and peroxide analysis. E.T. collected and analysed data 
for electron microscopy, with direction from N.S. and Y.I. N.M. and T.K. supervised the 
project. S.O., Y.O., M.H., T.K. and N.M. wrote the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Okuoka, S.-i. et al. A New Sealed Lithium-Peroxide Battery with a 
Co-Doped Li 2 O Cathode in a Superconcentrated Lithium Bis(fluorosulfonyl)amide 
Electrolyte. Sci. Rep. 4, 5684; DOI:10.1038/srep05684 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in 
this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative 
Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder 
in order to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 5684 | DOI: 10.1038/srep05684 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>