<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4812504" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In 1989, Caffe et al. [1] published a method for organ 
culture in which the neuroretina was placed with the photore-
ceptor layer facing downward on rafts made of nitrocellulose 
filters and polyamide gauze grids. Since then, mammalian 
retinal organ cultures have been commonly used to research 
retinal physiology and pathobiology. Retinal cell dynamics 
have shown that organotypic models can be comparable with 
in vivo conditions, especially those of the outer retina [2]. 
Thus, retinal cultures are still used in electrophysiological 
studies to monitor drug effects on retinal cell functionality 
[3], to evaluate neurotrophic factors or physical tension on 
retinal cells [4], and to study the molecular basis of potential 
therapies for photoreceptor death [5]. Our group has previ-
ously used neuroretina explant cultures to evaluate modifi-
cations induced by exogenous cells such as blood-derived 
macrophages or by cytokines such as tumor necrosis factor 
alpha (TNF-α) that are implicated in the pathobiology of 
proliferative vitreoretinopathy [6,7]. We have explored the 
potential role of therapeutic agents such as TNF-α-blockers </p>

<p>[7]. We have also established a mixed coculture model 
composed of three cellular layers, the neuroretina, the RPE, 
and adipose tissue-derived stem cells, to evaluate the neuro-
protective effects of stem cells [8]. </p>

<p>There are some obvious limitations of these culture 
systems, such as the axotomy of ganglion cells as part of the 
dissection procedure and the absence of a blood supply. Thus, 
degenerative changes in retinal cells, especially at the inner 
retina, could differ from in vivo conditions [9]. In addition, 
a major limitation is the absence of the RPE. The RPE is 
a monolayer of pigmented, cuboidal epithelial cells that are 
closely associated with the photoreceptor outer segments. 
The most important functions of the RPE are the synthesis 
and maintenance of the interphotoreceptor matrix, photore-
ceptor membrane turnover, and retinoid metabolism [10]. The 
importance of the neuroretina-RPE association is supported 
by the fact that neuroretinas adjoined to RPE monolayer 
cultures have better-preserved tissue architecture in culture 
studies [11]. The RPE is also considered a key element in 
the development of some retinal diseases and, importantly, in 
the physiopathology of retinal detachment and central serous 
chorioretinopathy. In these pathologies, the neuroretina and 
the RPE become physically separated. Furthermore, the RPE 
secretes across the apical membrane neuroprotective factors </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; 
Purpose: To develop and standardize a novel organ culture model using porcine central neuroretina explants and RPE 
cells separated by a cell culture membrane. 
Methods: RPE cells were isolated from porcine eyes, expanded, and seeded on the bottom of cell culture inserts. 
Neuroretina explants were obtained from the area centralis and cultured alone (controls) on cell culture membranes or 
supplemented with RPE cells in the same wells but physically separated by the culture membrane. Finally, cellular and 
tissue specimens were processed for phase contrast, cyto-/histological, and immunochemical evaluation. Neuroretina 
thickness was also determined. 
Results: Compared to the neuroretinas cultured alone, the neuroretinas cocultured with RPE cells maintained better 
tissue structure and cellular organization, displayed better preservation of photoreceptors containing rhodopsin, lower 
levels of glial fibrillary acidic protein immunoexpression, and preservation of cellular retinaldehyde binding protein both 
markers of reactive gliosis. Neuroretina thickness was significantly greater in the cocultures. 
Conclusions: A coculture model of central porcine neuroretina and RPE cells was successfully developed and stan-
dardized. This model mimics a subretinal space and will be useful in studying interactions between the RPE and the 
neuroretina and to preclinically test potential therapies. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>that helps to maintain retinal homeostasis [10]. Thus, an 
adequate ex vivo tool for studying retinal degeneration and 
the importance of molecular signaling across the subretinal 
space after physical separation of the neuroretina and the 
RPE would be inherent to overcome the complexities that 
are inherent in vivo studies. </p>

<p>In this study, we developed and characterized a novel 
organotypic coculture system in which the central cone-
dominated porcine neuroretina was cocultured with RPE 
cells that were maintained physically separated from the 
neuroretina by the culture medium and a porous membrane. 
This arrangement prevented any physical contact between 
the cocultured cells but allowed signal molecules to pass 
between them. This model could be useful for studying in 
vitro the interactions between the neuroretina and the RPE 
when they lose their natural contact, as happens in several 
retinal diseases such as retinal detachment and central serous 
chorioretinopathy. Further, this ex vivo model will allow 
study of the role of RPE-secreted factors and the evaluation of 
potential therapies for reducing the progression of neuroretina 
degeneration. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Fifteen porcine eyes from animals aged 6-8 months were 
obtained from the local slaughterhouse and processed 
within 2 h of death. Immediately after enucleation, the eyes 
were immersed in ice-cold transport medium composed of 
Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) supplemented 
with a 10% antibiotic-antimycotic mixture containing peni-
cillin, streptomycin, and amphotericin B (Gibco, Invitrogen, 
Paisley, UK) and transported on ice to the laboratory. Under 
aseptic conditions in a laminar airflow hood, the eyes were 
dissected free from all periocular tissue. After full immersion 
of the eyeballs in 70% ethanol during 2 min, the eyes were 
washed in clean DMEM supplemented with 10% antibiotic-
antimycotic at room temperature. </p>

<p>RPE cell isolation and culture: RPE cells from the porcine 
eyes (n=5) were obtained as previously described [12]. 
Briefly, the eyes were dissected at the ora serrata to exclude 
the iris and lens. The vitreous was then removed from the 
posterior eyecup with cotton swabs, and then the neuroretina 
was detached and discarded. The remaining eye cup was 
covered with 0.05% trypsin-tetrasodium ethylene diamine 
tetra-acetate (Trypsin-EDTA, Gibco) for 30 min at 37 °C. 
RPE cells were removed by filling the eye cup with DMEM 
supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco) 
plus 1% antibiotic-antimycotic mixture (complete DMEM) 
and swabbing gently. The isolated cells were collected and 
centrifuged for 2 min at 6800 RCF. After resuspension in </p>

<p>complete DMEM, the cells were plated in 25 cm 
2 flasks 
(Nunc, Roskilde, Denmark). The RPE cells were maintained 
in complete DMEM under standard culture conditions 
of 37 °C in an atmosphere of 5% CO 2 with 95% humidity. 
The medium was renewed at 2-3 day intervals. RPE cell 
morphology was evaluated with a Nikon Eclipse TS100 
inverted-phase contrast microscope (Nikon Instruments 
Inc., Tokyo, Japan) during culture. Trypan blue exclusion 
assay (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) was used to determine 
viability and cell numbers. After reaching &gt;90% conflu-
ence, the cells were trypsinized with 0.05% trypsin-EDTA, 
washed, and resuspended in PBS (Gibco). </p>

<p>Passage 2 RPE cells were seeded (30,000 cells/cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) [8] 
on the bottom of Transwell 
® culture plates (Corning Inc., 
Corning, NY) and grown for 24 h in complete DMEM to 
allow cellular adhesion before coculturing with neuroretina 
explants. </p>

<p>Central neuroretina explant preparation and culture: Twenty 
neuroretina explants were obtained from ten eyes as previ-
ously described by our group [6]. The porcine cone-enriched 
visual streak was identified, as described by Hendrickson and 
Hicks [13], and two 5×5 mm adjacent explants from each eye 
were obtained with Castroviejo corneal scissors (John Weiss 
&amp; Son Ltd., Milton Keynes, UK) from the temporal area 1 mm 
superior to the optic disc (Figure 1). The neuroretina explants 
were laid over the Transwell 
® membranes (24-mm diameter 
with 0.4-µm pore polycarbonate membrane insert; Product 
#3412, Corning Inc.) with the photoreceptor layer facing 
the membrane. Nine neuroretina explants were cocultured 
with RPE cells but physically separated from them by the 
culture medium overlying the RPE cells and the Transwell </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>membrane (Figure 2). Another nine explants were cultured as 
controls without RPE cells. Cultures were maintained in 1:1 
Neurobasal-A/DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal bovine 
serum, 2% B-27 (Gibco), 1% L-glutamine (Sigma-Aldrich, 
St. Louis, MO), and 1% antibiotic-antimycotic mixture 
and maintained in standard culture conditions. The culture 
medium level (1.5 ml as suggested by the manufacturer) was 
maintained in contact with the support membrane beneath the 
explants and changed with freshly prepared, warmed medium 
every day. The explants were harvested for analysis after 9 
days of culture, as previously described by our group [14], 
and were cut into two halves for subsequent processing. Two 
fresh central neuroretina specimens were used as culture day 
0 samples and processed in parallel. </p>

<p>Histological and immunochemical processing: RPE cells that 
were cocultured with neuroretina explants for 9 days were 
fixed in the Transwell 
® culture plates with ice-cold methanol 
(Panreac Quimica S.A.U., Barcelona, Spain) for 15 min at </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>4 °C. The RPE cells were immunostained for phenotype-
specific marker proteins. Primary antibodies (Table 1) for 
zonula occludens protein 1 (ZO-1), RPE-specific 65 kDa 
protein (RPE65), and cellular retinaldehyde binding protein 
(CRALBP) were diluted in PBS containing 0.5% Triton 
X-100, 10% goat serum, and 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA; 
all Sigma-Aldrich). The antibodies were applied directly to 
the cultures and incubated overnight at 4 °C. After washing 
in PBS, the corresponding species-specific secondary anti-
bodies to immunoglobulin gamma conjugated to Alexa Fluor 
488 or 568 (green and red; Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR) 
were applied at a 1:200 dilution for 1 h. Nuclei were stained 
with 10 µg/ml 4',6-diamino-2-phenylindole dihydrochloride 
(DAPI, Molecular Probes). Finally, the cells were washed in 
PBS, mounted in fluorescent mounting medium (DakoCyto-
mation Inc., Carpinteria, CA), and coverslipped. </p>

<p>Neuroretina samples were fixed overnight in 1% para-
formaldehyde and 1% glutaraldehyde (both Panreac Quimica 
S.A.U.) in phosphate buffer (PB, Gibco). After gradual dehy-
dration in an ethanol series, the pieces were embedded in 
low-viscosity epoxy resin (Spurr, TAAB, Aldermaston, UK). 
Semithin sections (1 µm) were obtained with an ultramicro-
tome (LKB Bromma 8800 Ultratome III, Freiburg, Germany) 
and stained with 1% toluidine blue in 3% sodium tetraborate 
(both Panreac Quimica S.A.U.). </p>

<p>For immunohistochemistry, the other half of the samples 
were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde in PB, pH 7.4, for 2 h 
and then subjected to sucrose (Panreac Quimica S.A.U.) cryo-
protection [15]. On the following day, they were embedded 
in Tissue-Tek O.C.T. Compound (Sakura Finetek Europe 
B.V., Alphen, the Netherlands). Sections (5 µm) were cut 
on a cryostat (Leica Instruments, Nussloch, Germany) and 
mounted on glass slides (SuperFrost Plus; Menzel-Gläser, 
Braunschweig, Germany). The neuroretinas were immunos-
tained for the phenotype-specific markers (Table 1) rhodopsin 
(RHO), calbindin D-28K (CB), glial fibrillary acidic protein 
(GFAP), and CRALBP. Specific combinations of anti-
bodies were diluted in PBS containing 0.5% Triton X-100 
and incubated overnight at 4 °C. The next day, the sections 
were washed in PBS. Thereafter, the corresponding species-
specific secondary antibodies conjugated to Alexa Fluor 488 
and/or 568 were applied at a 1:200 dilution for 1 h. Nuclei 
were stained with 10 µg/ml DAPI. Finally, the sections were 
washed in PBS, mounted in fluorescent mounting medium, 
and coverslipped. </p>

<p>The primary antibodies used in this work have been 
used in previous studies and have been well characterized 
by our group and other authors regarding specific cell-
type immunostaining in whole fixed porcine eyes and in 
porcine neuroretina samples [6-8,16]. Furthermore, control 
samples in which primary antibodies were omitted were 
processed in parallel, and no immunoreactivity was found 
in any case. Samples were analyzed with a Leica DM4000B </p>

<p>Figure 1. Neuroretina explant tissue sampling in porcine globe. Two 
neuroretina explants (5×5 mm) were obtained from each eye at the 
porcine cone-enriched visual streak superotemporal to the optic 
disc. Scale bar=5 mm. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Schematic view of the 
coculture model of the porcine 
neuroretina explant and isolated 
RPE cells. The neuroretina explant 
was placed over a cell culture 
membrane, and the RPE cells 
were placed on the bottom of the 
cell culture insert and cocultured 
together in the same well. In this 
configuration, the cell culture membrane physically separated them, but signal molecules could pass through the porous membrane. This 
figure is not to scale. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>light microscope (Leica Microsystems, Wetzlar, Germany) 
equipped for epifluorescence, Leica HCX PL FLUOTAR PH2 
20x/0.50 and 40x/0.75 and Leica N PLAN 63x/0.8 objectives 
(Leica Microsystems) were used, and images were obtained 
with a Leica DFC490 digital camera (Leica Microsystems). 
Brightness and contrast were minimally adjusted and final 
figures composed with <rs id="software-1" type="software">Pixelmator 3.4 Twist</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Apple</rs>, Cuper-
tino, CA). </p>

<p>Neuroretina thickness quantification: The thickness of the 
neuroretina and the thickness of the outer nuclear layer (ONL) 
and the inner nuclear layer (INL) were measured on toluidine 
blue histological images with <rs id="software-2" type="software">Image J</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">1.47v</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">NIH Image</rs>, 
National Institute of Health, Bethesda, MD). Measurements 
were performed in representative serial sections. Neuroretina 
thickness was determined between the outer and the inner 
limiting membranes. In each case, six measurements were 
performed in 20X images from each of the neuroretina 
explants (n=20). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis: Statistical analysis was performed using 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">R Statistical Software</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 3.1.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Foundation for Statistical Computing</rs>, Vienna, Austria). The means and standard devia-
tions were calculated for continuous variables. The statistical 
significance level was set at 5%. </p>

<p>A Kruskal one-way ANOVA (ANOVA) was used to 
compare the mean thicknesses of freshly isolated neuroretinas 
and those cultured for 9 days alone or for 9 days in coculture 
with RPE cells. The homogeneity of variance assumption was 
checked with the robust Brown-Forsythe Levene-type test 
using the group medians as implemented in <rs type="software">R lawstat package</rs> 
[17]. When the homogeneity of variance was not validated, 
the Welch test was used for comparison of the mean values. </p>

<p>Pair-wise comparisons were performed with the Student t test 
with Bonferroni correction for multiple testing. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>RPE cells: Isolated porcine RPE cells started to adhere on 
culture day 1 and to form clusters of cells at day 4 in flasks 
(Figure 3A). These cells were polygonal and contained 
pigment. At day 7 of culture in flasks, the RPE cells were 
almost confluent in a monostratified epithelium, had a polyg-
onal shape, and had pigmented cytoplasmic granules (Figure 
3B). However, some cells had dedifferentiated morphology, 
with increased size and reduced pigment content (Figure 
3B, arrowheads). Cellular characteristics were maintained 
until passage 2, when the RPE cells were cocultured with 
neuroretina explants. At coculture day 9 (Figure 3C), the RPE 
cells formed a confluent monolayer in the bottom of the cell 
culture inserts, retained the polygonal shape, and still had 
some pigment content (Figure 3C, insert); some cells looked 
dedifferentiated (Figure 3C, arrowheads). </p>

<p>To assess preservation of the RPE morphology and 
phenotype during coculture with the neuroretina explants, 
the RPE cells were examined with antibodies against ZO-1, 
which is a peripheral adaptor protein of tight junction struc-
ture between RPE cells. The expression of the RPE65 protein, 
which is located in the cytoplasm and involved in the produc-
tion of 11-cis-retinal and in visual pigment regeneration, and 
CRALBP, a retinoid-binding protein implicated in vitamin A 
metabolism and found in the RPE apical microvilli, was also 
detected with immunohistochemistry. Nine days after cocul-
ture with the neuroretina explants, the RPE cells showed vari-
able ZO-1 immunoexpression at the polygonal cell periphery 
(Figure 3D) and maintained the expression of cytoplasmic </p>

<p>Table 1. Primary anTibodies used in This sTudy. </p>

<p>Molecular marker 
Antibody 
Source 
Working 
dilution </p>

<p>Zonula occludens protein 1 (ZO-1) 
Mouse monoclonal 
[ZO1-1A12] 
Invitrogen, #33-9100 (Camarillo, CA) 
1:50 </p>

<p>Retinal pigment epithelium-specific 
65 kDa protein (RPE65) 
Mouse monoclonal 
Novus Biologicals, #NB100-355 
(Cambridge, UK) 
1:50 </p>

<p>Cellular retinaldehyde-binding protein 
(CRALBP) 
Mouse monoclonal [B2] 
Abcamplc, #Ab15051 (Cambridge, UK) 
1:50 (RPE) 
1:1000 (NR) </p>

<p>Calbindin D-28K (CB) 
Rabbit polyclonal 
Swant, #CB-38a (Bellinzona, 
Switzerland) 
1:500 </p>

<p>Rhodopsin (RHO) 
Rabbit polyclonal 
Chemicon-Millipore, #AB9279 
(Temecula, CA) 
1:200 </p>

<p>Glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) 
Rabbit polyclonal 
DakoCytomation, Inc., #N1506 (Glos-
trup, Denmark) 
1:500 </p>

<p>RPE: retinal pigment epithelium cells; NR: neuroretina explant </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>RPE65 (Figure 3E). CRALBP was not detectable in the RPE 
coculture (Figure 3F). </p>

<p>Neuroretina explants: Neuroretina explants stained with 
toluidine blue showed the general overview of all layers of 
the porcine retina (Figure 4). In the freshly isolated neuro-
retina explants (Figure 4A,D), the characteristic neuroretina 
architecture was apparent, with the notable presence of cone 
photoreceptors corresponding to the porcine visual streak. 
The delicate structures of the photoreceptor outer and inner 
segments (OS and IS) were well preserved before culturing. 
In the absence of cocultured RPE cells, the retina structure 
at 9 days of culture (Figure 4B,E,F) was disorganized, and 
cellular vacuolization was present throughout the retina 
layers. Photoreceptor OS were lost while the remaining 
IS appeared shorter and swollen compared to the freshly 
isolated neuroretina explants. In the ONL, photoreceptor 
cell bodies were oriented to form degenerative rosette-like 
structures (Figure 4B,E, asterisks). The plexiform layers were 
partially disrupted and unstructured. The Müller cells were 
hypertrophied, the nuclei were translocated to the ONL, and 
cytoplasmic pigmented granules were present (Figure 4F, 
open arrow and open arrowheads). Furthermore, cellular </p>

<p>extensions of Müller cells covered the photoreceptor (Figure 
4B,F, arrows). At 9 days of coculture with RPE cells (Figure 
4C,G), the cellular architecture of the neuroretina explants 
was better preserved, and the retina layers were more easily 
discerned than those in the neuroretina explants cultured 
alone. Photoreceptor IS were condensed and swollen (Figure 
4G, arrowheads); no rosette-like formation was evident. The 
integrity of the plexiform layers and the INL were main-
tained. Cellular extensions over the photoreceptors were 
present (Figure 4C,G, arrows). </p>

<p>To further assess photoreceptor integrity and retina cell 
morphology during culture, the neuroretina explants were 
examined with antibodies against RHO, an opsin protein 
present in rod OS, and CB, a calcium-binding protein present 
in cone photoreceptors. Additionally, to assess the degree of 
glial cell activation, the neuroretina explants were immu-
nostained with antibodies against GFAP, an intermediate 
filament protein present in glial cells, and against CRALBP, 
found in Müller cells. </p>

<p>In the freshly fixed neuroretina explants, the rods main-
tained normal long and straight OS morphology expressing </p>

<p>Figure 3. Cellular morphology and immunochemistry of RPE cells during the culture and coculture period. At day 4 of culture in the flasks 
(A), the RPE cells formed clusters of pigmented, polygonal cells. At day 7 in the flasks (B), the RPE cells reached confluence and maintained 
morphological characteristics. Dedifferentiated cells were present (B, arrowheads). At 9 days of coculture with the neuroretina explants (C), 
the RPE cells in the cell culture inserts were confluent, monolayered, pigmented, and polygonal-shaped (C, insert). Dedifferentiated cells 
were still present (C, arrowheads). At 9 days of coculture, the RPE cells in the cell culture inserts showed variable ZO-1 immunoexpression 
at the cell periphery (D, green; nuclei, blue) and maintained cytoplasmic RPE65 (E, red; nuclei, blue). CRALBP was not detectable (F) 
Scale bars=100 μm (A-C) and 20 μm (D-F). </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>RHO (Figure 5A). At 9 days of culture without the RPE, 
partial displacement of RHO immunoexpression was detected 
at the swollen rod IS (Figure 5B). Additionally, photoreceptor 
nuclei were displaced to the IS region (Figure 5B asterisks). 
After 9 days of coculture with RPE, RHO expression (Figure 
5C) was evident at the ONL (Figure 5D arrows) and was 
displaced to shorter and swollen rod IS. </p>

<p>In the freshly fixed neuroretina explants, cones were 
immunoreactive for CB and had a normal morphology 
(Figure 5D). At 9 days of culture without the RPE, the CB 
immunostained cones showed markedly altered morphology </p>

<p>(Figure 5E). At 9 days of coculture with the RPE, the cones 
underwent morphological degenerative changes (Figure 5F). </p>

<p>In the freshly fixed neuroretina explants, CRALBP 
immunoexpression revealed Müller cells with normal 
morphology (Figure 5G). GFAP immunostaining was limited 
to the innermost layers of the neuroretinal tissue. At 9 days 
of culture without RPE, GFAP was clearly upregulated in 
the cytoplasm of the glial cells (Figure 5H). GFAP cellular 
processes extended outside the retinal tissue and formed 
layered structures (Figure 5H, arrows). At 9 days of cocul-
ture with RPE, CRALBP was scarcely present, and glial cell </p>

<p>Figure 4. Neuroretina morphology during the culture and coculture period. In the freshly isolated retina explants (A and D), the porcine 
central retina showed the characteristic highly organized layered structure. At 9 days of culture alone (B, E, and F), the retinal architecture 
was disorganized. Photoreceptor OS were lost, and the cell bodies formed degenerative rosette-like structures (B and E, asterisks). Müller 
cells were hypertrophied, with nuclei translocated to the outer nuclear layer (F, open arrow) and cell cytoplasm pigmented granules (F, open 
arrowheads). Cellular extensions over photoreceptors were also present (B and F, arrows). At 9 days of coculture with RPE cells (C and G), 
the layered retinal morphology was preserved with condensed photoreceptor IS still present (G, arrowheads). Cellular prolongations were 
observed over the photoreceptors (C and G, arrows). OS=outer segments; IS=inner segments; OLM=outer limiting membrane; ONL=outer 
nuclear layer; OPL=outer plexiform layer; INL=inner nuclear layer; IPL=inner plexiform layer; GCL=ganglion cell layer. Scale bars=20 µm. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>immunoexpression of GFAP was reduced compared with 
cultures without RPE (Figure 5I). GFAP processes were also 
present over the outer limiting membrane; the thickness of the 
cellular extensions was reduced (Figure 5I, arrows). </p>

<p>Neuroretina thickness quantification: The thickness of the 
neuroretina, the INL, and the ONL changed over time during 
the culture period (Figure 6). The thickness of freshly isolated 
neuroretinas (n=2) was 135.29±17.02 µm. After 9 days of 
culture alone, the thickness of the neuroretinas (n=9) was </p>

<p>Figure 5. Neuroretina immuno-
histochemistry during the culture 
and coculture period. In the freshly 
isolated retina explants (A), RHO 
immunoreactivity (green) showed 
the normal appearance of rod 
outer segments (OS). At 9 days of 
neuroretina explants culture alone 
(B), RHO was scarcely detected, 
and the inner segments (IS) were 
not discernable. Photoreceptor 
nuclei appeared at the IS region (B, 
arrowhead). At 9 days in coculture 
with RPE cells (C), RHO was 
displaced to the short and swollen 
rod IS and to the outer nuclear 
layer (arrows). In the freshly 
isolated retina explants (D), CB 
(red) showed cone photoreceptors 
with normal morphology. At 9 days 
of neuroretina culture alone (E), 
cone morphology was markedly 
altered as revealed with CB immu-
nostaining. At 9 days in coculture 
with the RPE (F), cone morphology 
underwent degeneration. In the 
freshly isolated retina explants (G), 
CRALBP (green) showed Müller 
cells with normal morphology. 
Reduced immunostaining for 
GFAP (red) was observed. At 9 
days of neuroretina culture alone 
(H), GFAP was upregulated at 
the cytoplasm of glial cells, and 
GFAP-positive extensions formed 
a layered-like structure outside 
the retinal tissue (arrows). At 9 
days in coculture with RPE (I), 
CRALBP was scarcely detected, 
and GFAP was reduced compared 
to explants cultured alone. GFAP-
positive processes were present 
over the outer limiting membrane (arrows). OS=outer segments; IS=inner segments; ONL=outer nuclear layer; INL=inner nuclear layer; 
GCL=ganglion cell layer. Scale bars=10 μm. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>92.28±14.94 µm, while that of the RPE-cocultured neuro-
retinas (n=9) was 109.35±4.25 µm (p&lt;0.0001). The ONL 
thickness of the freshly isolated samples was 34.64±1.43 µm. 
After 9 days of culture alone, the ONL thickness was 
21.7±3.57 µm, while that of the RPE-cocultured neuroretinas 
was 30.82±3.16 µm (p&lt;0.0001). The INL thickness of the 
freshly isolated samples was 35.54±1.81 µm. After 9 days of 
culture alone, the INL thickness was 21.89±2.68 µm, while 
that of the RPE-cocultured neuroretinas was 27.88±2.35 µm 
(p&lt;0.0001). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The present study described the development and charac-
terization of a novel coculture model of cone-dominated 
porcine central retina and RPE cells to closely simulate ex 
vivo the subretinal space microenvironment. Retinal degen-
eration is a common finding of many retinal diseases, and 
in some cases, such as retinal detachment and central serous 
chorioretinopathy, it is in part the consequence of physical 
separation between the neuroretina and the RPE. This separa-
tion starts a cascade of events that result in cellular changes 
throughout the retina. These events are in part responsible 
for the poor functional results that can occur even after 
successful reattachment surgery [18]. Currently, research in 
retinal degeneration is largely limited due to the difficulty in 
obtaining specimens from freshly detached human retinas 
and the limitations of experimental animal models [19]. In 
this sense, simple neuroretina cultures represent a useful tool </p>

<p>for studying retinal modifications. These models are inexpen-
sive and easy to develop. Importantly, they closely simulate in 
vivo retinal cellular and molecular dynamics and have been 
the source of improved knowledge of retinal physiopathology 
in recent decades [1]. Nevertheless, these previously reported 
culture models lack the influence of the RPE cells that are 
necessary for maintaining the viability and functionality of 
the outermost retinal layers [10]. Furthermore, RPE cells 
secrete various growth and trophic factors that act on the 
neuroretina and the choroidal endothelium [10]. The RPE also 
plays an important role in the retinal degeneration process 
and is considered a key element in retinal detachment phys-
iopathology [19]. </p>

<p>There are some obvious limitations of these culture 
systems, such as the absence of choroidal and retinal blood 
flow, the lack of vitreous, and the axotomy of ganglion 
cells, that may considerably limit the study of the inner 
retina modifications [9]. However, neuroretina organotypic 
cultures are still considered an adequate tool for improving 
knowledge of retinal physiopathology [3]. Other authors have 
previously described models in which RPE monolayers were 
cocultured in contact with the neuroretina [11]. Those models 
are complex to develop and do not adequately mimic a retinal 
pathology related to the separation between the neuroretina 
and the RPE. Our purpose was to study and characterize the 
differences between neuroretinas cultured alone and those 
cocultured with RPE cells while physically separated from 
each other. This novel model could be the basis for studying </p>

<p>Figure 6. Porcine neuroretina thick-
ness during the culture and cocul-
ture period. Neuroretina tissue 
thickness (A) on day 9 of culture 
and on day 9 of coculture with 
RPE was reduced compared to the 
freshly isolated tissue. The thick-
ness of the neuroretina cultures 
alone on day 9 was significantly 
less than that of the neuroretinas 
that had been cocultured with 
RPE. ONL (B) and INL (C) thick-
ness on day 9 of culture and on 
day 9 of coculture with RPE was 
reduced compared to the freshly 
isolated tissue. The ONL (B) and 
INL (C) thickness of the neuro-
retina cultures alone on day 9 was 
significantly less than that of the neuroretinas that had been cocultured with RPE. *p&lt;0.02 (n=20) and **p&lt;0.0001 (n=20). ONL=outer 
nuclear layer; INL=inner nuclear layer. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>the interaction between the neuroretina and RPE cells when 
they are separated in vivo because no such studies currently 
exist. In this model, neuroretina explants were cultured over 
cell culture membranes that physically separated the RPE 
cells cultured on the bottom of the cell culture inserts. Thus, 
the porous cell culture membranes inhibit RPE cell migra-
tion into the retinal tissue and direct contact with neuroretina 
cells; while molecular exchange among the different cell 
types can occur. In this scenario, RPE-secreted factors can 
diffuse through the cell culture membrane pores and influ-
ence neuroretina cell dynamics, thus recreating the subretinal 
space milieu. </p>

<p>The porcine retina possesses some characteristics that 
make this species particularly useful in retinal research, such 
as retinal extent, ultrastructure, and the lack of a tapetum [13]. 
The retinal parenchyma is quite similar to that of humans, 
with a double circulation system and a central zone, the visual 
streak. This zone is a broad horizontal retinal streak above 
the optic disc, with high cone density and without direct 
vascularization [13]. Unlike the human fovea, no depression 
is present throughout the pig area centralis [13]. The porcine 
retina has a rod density that is similar to that of humans, 
and the cellular dynamics after neuroretina-RPE separation 
are comparable in both species, especially those of key cells 
such as Müller and RPE cells [20]. Therefore, in the coculture 
model that we have developed, we used explants from the 
porcine cone-dominated area centralis because of the simi-
larity with the human central retina. </p>

<p>As shown with phase contrast microscopy, RPE cells 
largely maintained their morphological characteristics 
throughout the coculture period. Furthermore, these cells 
maintained the expression of ZO-1 outlining the polygonal 
shape of the RPE cells within the monolayer, and RPE65 
supporting the preservation of the RPE phenotype, without 
dedifferentiation to form other cell types or undergoing 
an epithelial-mesenchymal transition [21]. As previously 
described in primary RPE cell cultures, a few clusters of 
cells became partially dedifferentiated [22]. CRALBP 
immunoexpression was not observed in RPE cells cocultured 
with neuroretinas, probably due to the loss of normal cell 
polarization, especially seen as the disappearance of the 
apical microvilli [21]. The ability of RPE in culture to secrete 
neurotrophic factors has been described by other authors [23]. </p>

<p>In the cultures in the present study, the neuroretina 
explants without the RPE showed degenerative alterations 
in the tissue and retina cells as previously described [14]. 
However, the presence of degenerative rosette-like structures 
reported here were not observed by our group in previous work 
in which the central retina was not used [14]. Degenerative </p>

<p>rosettes commonly occur in abnormally developing retinas 
[24]. Our immunohistochemical studies revealed retinal cell 
degenerative modifications as we [6,7] and others previously 
described in organotypic porcine retina cultures [9]. Although 
RHO and CRALBP immunoexpression was better preserved 
and lower levels of GFAP were detected in the neuroretinas 
cocultured with RPE cells, we did not quantify the GFAP 
or CRALBP labeling, and this will be part of future experi-
ments. The thickness of the neuroretinas was greater in the 
cocultures. However, it is not clear if that is related to cellular 
swelling or to better cellular viability. In this sense, it will be 
useful to explore cell death and survival in future studies. In 
any case, the neuroretina explants cocultured with RPE cells 
maintained better preserved tissue and cellular characteristics 
and significantly better conserved tissue and nuclear layer 
thicknesses. These findings were consistent through the 
complete 5-mm neuroretina explants and were observed in 
all the experiments performed. </p>

<p>Based on the morphological and immunohistochemical 
results found in this study, neuroretina preservation in cocul-
tures with RPE cells may be partially linked to neuroprotec-
tive factors secreted by RPE cells. The secretion of neuro-
trophic/neuroprotective factors by RPE cells is stimulated 
during retinal damage [10]. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Our group has developed and standardized a 
novel coculture model of central cone-dominated porcine 
neuroretina that was supplemented with RPE cells main-
tained separately within the same culture wells. This cocul-
ture system mimics ex vivo the subretinal space that develops 
during retinal detachment (RD) and other disease conditions 
of the retina. Compared to the neuroretina explant cultures 
alone, the presence of cocultured RPE provided improved 
neuroretina architecture and thickness, better preservation of 
RHO and CRALBP immunoexpression, and lower levels of 
GFAP. These data suggest that the cocultured RPE, while not 
in direct contact with the neuroretina explant, had a neuro-
protective role. This effect may be linked to the beneficial 
effects of neurotrophic factors secreted or induced by RPE 
cells during coculture. Furthermore, the proposed model 
will be useful to better study interactions between the RPE 
and the neuroretina and to test neuroprotective and/or anti-
inflammatory drugs for retinal degenerative diseases. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>Authors thank the staff of Justino Gutierrez S. L. slaugh-
terhouse (Valladolid, Spain) for providing the porcine eye 
globes used in this work, and Itziar Fernandez (CIBER BBN-
IOBA, Spain) for expert advice in statistical analysis. This 
research has been partially supported by a grant from Junta </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>de Castilla y Leon (VA386A122). I. Fernandez-Bueno and G. 
K. Srivastava were supported by Centro en Red de Medicina 
Regenerativa y Terapia Celular de la Junta de Castilla y Leon, 
Spain. This study was presented in part at The Association 
for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology (ARVO) Annual 
Meeting, Orlando, FL, USA, May 2014 and Denver, CO, 
USA, May 2015, and at The European College of Veterinary 
Ophthalmologists (ECVO) Conference, London, UK, May 
2014. </p>



<p>Molecular Vision 2016; 22:243-253 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v22/243&gt; </p>

<p>© 2016 Molecular Vision </p>





</text></tei>