<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4561054" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background Simeprevir is a N3/4 protease inhibitor 
approved for the treatment of hepatitis C virus (HCV) 
infection. HCV prevalence is higher in patients with chronic 
kidney disease compared with the general population; safe 
and efficacious therapies in renal impairment are needed. 
Objectives To evaluate simeprevir renal excretion in 
healthy subjects and to compare the simeprevir steady-state 
pharmacokinetics between subjects with severe renal 
impairment and healthy subjects. 
Methods In the mass balance study, healthy adults 
received a single 200-mg dose of 
14 C-simeprevir; 
radioactivity in the urine and feces was quantified until 
concentrations were \2 % of the administered dose and 
seven or more stools were produced. In the pharmacoki-
netic study, non-HCV-infected adults with severe renal 
impairment (estimated glomerular filtration rate B29 mL/ 
min/1.73 m 
2 ) and matched healthy subjects (estimated 
glomerular filtration rate C80 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 ) received 
150 mg simeprevir for 7 days. Pharmacokinetic analysis 
was performed post-dose on Day 7. 
Results 
14 C-simeprevir recovery from the urine was low 
(0.009-0.138 % of total dose). The minimum plasma 
concentration, maximum plasma concentration, and area 
under the plasma concentration-time curve at 24 h were 71, </p>

<p>34, and 62 % higher, respectively, in subjects with severe 
renal impairment compared with healthy subjects. The 
mean fraction of simeprevir unbound to protein was 
\0.0001 (all subjects). Most adverse events were grade I or 
II; one subject with renal impairment who was receiving 
fenofibrate presented with grade 3 rhabdomyolysis. 
Conclusions Simeprevir plasma concentrations were 
mildly elevated in subjects with severe renal impairment. 
The results suggest that simeprevir may be administered 
without dose adjustment in patients with renal impairment. </p>

<p>Key points </p>

<p>Simeprevir concentrations were mildly elevated in 
subjects with severe renal impairment. </p>

<p>Simeprevir may be administered without dose 
adjustment in patients with renal impairment. </p>

<p>Hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection is estimated to affect 
approximately 3 % of the global population, or more than 
170 million people worldwide [1, 2]. The prevalence of 
HCV is higher in patients with chronic kidney disease 
(CKD), with reported prevalence rates ranging from 3 to 
68 % (region-and dialysis center-dependent) in patients 
receiving hemodialysis [3, 4], and between 10 and 49 % in 
renal transplant recipients [5]. Epidemiology studies in 
patients with CKD prior to dialysis or renal transplant are 
limited; however, the prevalence of HCV is likely also 
increased in this population [1, 6]. </p>

<p>&amp; Sivi Ouwerkerk-Mahadevan 
SOUWERKE@its.jnj.com </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Janssen Research &amp; Development, Turnhoutseweg 30, 
Beerse 2340, Belgium </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Janssen Infectious Diseases, Beerse, Belgium </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Consultant at Janssen Infectious Diseases, Beerse, Belgium </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Academic Center for General Practice, KU Leuven, Leuven, 
Belgium </p>

<p>Drugs R D (2015) 15:261-270 
DOI 10.1007/s40268-015-0101-0 </p>

<p>Two main factors contribute to the association between 
HCV and renal disease. First, HCV has been associated 
with the development of glomerular renal disease, most 
commonly membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis 
(with or without essential mixed cryoglobulinemia) and 
membranous glomerulonephritis [7]. Second, patients with 
CKD have an increased risk of exposure to HCV, with the 
potential for infection via blood transfusions (prior to 
standardized screening procedures), nosocomial transmis-
sion during dialysis, and renal transplantation [1, 7]. 
Increased morbidity and mortality and reduced long-
term graft survival in transplant recipients have been 
demonstrated in patients with CKD with coexisting HCV 
infection [8, 9]. Therefore, the Kidney Disease Improving 
Global Outcomes guidelines suggest that all patients with 
CKD and HCV infection be evaluated for antiviral treat-
ment [1]; however, treatment of HCV in patients with 
severe renal dysfunction can be challenging [10]. Renal 
catabolism and filtration are important in the clearance of 
both ribavirin and interferon [11], resulting in increased 
exposure to both agents in severe renal impairment [12-14]. 
Increased exposure may lead to reduced tolerance [higher 
dropout rates have been reported in subjects with end-stage 
renal disease (ESRD) treated with pegylated interferon] and 
an increased risk of ribavirin-associated hemolytic anemia, 
which is proportional to plasma concentration [15, 16]. As a 
result, dosing adjustment is required in patients with a 
creatinine clearance (CrCl) of B50 mL/min for ribavirin 
and pegylated interferon alfa-2b and a CrCl of\30 mL/min 
for pegylated interferon alfa-2a [13, 17-19]. Sustained 
virologic response (SVR) rates to interferon monotherapy 
are increased in patients with CKD (ESRD on hemodialy-
sis) compared with patients with normal renal function, 
likely secondary to increased exposure; however, they are 
lower than those reported for interferon and ribavirin 
combination therapy, which is often avoided in subjects 
with severe renal impairment [1, 20-22]. Sofosbuvir, a 
nucleotide NS5B polymerase inhibitor, is primarily elimi-
nated in the urine, and increased exposure in renal failure 
has been reported; the sofosbuvir package insert states that a 
dosing recommendation cannot be made for patients with 
severe renal impairment or ESRD [23]. 
In contrast, boceprevir and telaprevir, the first-genera-
tion NS3/4A protease inhibitors, are metabolized and 
excreted by the liver, and pharmacokinetic studies have 
demonstrated similar exposure in subjects with renal 
impairment compared with healthy subjects [24, 25]. In 
addition, the NS5A replication complex inhibitor dacla-
tasvir is also primarily excreted in the feces (\10 % renal 
excretion); although mildly increased daclatasvir exposures 
have been observed with renal impairment, daclatasvir may 
be administered for all degrees of renal impairment without 
dose adjustment [26, 27]. </p>

<p>Simeprevir is a once-daily oral HCV N3S/4A protease 
inhibitor for the treatment of chronic HCV genotype 1 
infection as a component of combination antiviral therapy 
[28, 29]. Combination therapy with simeprevir has demon-
strated high SVR rates in both phase II and III trials for 
patients with HCV genotype 1 with normal renal function 
[29-34]. In treatment-naïve patients, the phase III QUEST-1 
and QUEST-2 trials demonstrated SVR rates of 80 and 81 %, 
respectively, in subjects receiving simeprevir plus ribavirin 
and pegylated interferon, compared with a SVR rate of 50 % 
in subjects receiving pegylated interferon and ribavirin alone 
[33, 34]. In prior relapser patients, the phase III PROMISE 
trial demonstrated an SVR rate of 79.2 % in subjects 
receiving simeprevir, pegylated interferon, and ribavirin, 
compared with an SVR rate of 36.1 % in subjects receiving 
pegylated interferon and ribavirin alone [31]. Even higher 
SVR rates of 92-94 % were observed using combination 
therapy with simeprevir plus sofosbuvir with or without 
ribavirin in the phase II COSMOS trial [35]. Phase III trials 
have also demonstrated the efficacy of simeprevir in patients 
with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) coinfection and 
in patients with genotype 4 (simeprevir is approved for the 
treatment of genotype 4 in Europe and Australia) [36, 37]. 
The safety of simeprevir has been demonstrated in 
subjects without renal impairment in both phase II and III 
trials [28, 33-35]. In pooled results from the three phase III 
trials evaluating simeprevir in combination with pegylated 
interferon and ribavirin (QUEST-1, QUEST-2, and PRO-
MISE), similar rates of grade 3 and 4 adverse events (AEs) 
were observed with simeprevir combination therapy com-
pared with pegylated interferon and ribavirin alone [28, 33,  34]. In addition, the phase II COSMOS trial that evaluated 
simeprevir in combination with sofosbuvir demonstrated a 
\5 % rate of grade 3 and 4 AEs, excluding increased blood 
amylase levels [35]. 
Here, we report the results of two phase I, open-label 
studies of simeprevir relevant to the safety of simeprevir in 
subjects with renal impairment. Study 1, the mass balance 
study, characterizes the excretion of 
14 C-simeprevir in 
healthy subjects. Study 2 evaluates the steady-state phar-
macokinetics and short-term safety and tolerability of 
simeprevir in non-HCV-infected subjects with severe renal 
impairment in comparison with healthy subjects. </p>

<p>2 Materials and Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Study 1: 
14 C-Simeprevir Mass Balance Study </p>

<p>2.1.1 Subjects </p>

<p>Eligible subjects included healthy male individuals 
between 18 and 55 years of age with a body mass index </p>

<p> 
S. Ouwerkerk-Mahadevan et al. </p>

<p>(BMI) between 18.0 and 30.0 kg/m 
2 , a normal screening 
electrocardiogram, and a history of nonsmoking for at least 
3 months prior to enrollment. Pre-study health was based 
on medical history and pre-study physical examination, 
vital signs, and blood (biochemistry and hematology) and 
urine laboratory evaluations. Key exclusion criteria inclu-
ded: a history of hepatitis A, B, or C or HIV infection; 
active or underlying disease (including gastrointestinal, 
cardiovascular, nervous system, psychiatric, renal, hepatic, 
metabolic, respiratory, inflammatory, or infectious dis-
ease); a history of clinically significant cardiac arrhythmia; 
several episodes of constipation (less than one stool every 
3 days) or diarrhea (three or more stools per day) during 
the previous 2 months; and the use of medications (except 
for paracetamol or ibuprofen) within 14 days of study 
medication intake. </p>

<p>2.1.2 Study Design </p>

<p>All subjects received a single 200-mg dose of the oral 
formulation of simeprevir containing 
14 C-labeled and 
unlabeled simeprevir in polyethylene glycol 400 on study 
Day 1 in the fed condition; the total radioactivity dose 
was 1.85 MBq (equivalent to 50 lCi). Urine and feces 
were collected until at least Day 8 and until the 
radioactivity in the urine and feces combined was \2 % 
of the administered dose (over a period of 24 h) and the 
subject produced at least seven stools. Urine was col-
lected during the following intervals following dose 
administration: 0-8, 8-16, 16-24, 24-36, and 36-48 h; 
after 48 h, urine was collected every 24 h. All fecal 
output was collected (per stool). Total radioactivity was 
measured in the urine and feces using liquid scintigraphy; 
the lower limit of quantification was 0.002-0.093 % for 
urine and 0.027-0.185 % for feces. Safety evaluation 
included subject-reported AEs, laboratory analysis (he-
matology, biochemistry, and coagulation), urinalysis, and 
electrocardiogram. </p>

<p>2.1.3 Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The primary study endpoint was the total excretion of 
simeprevir-related radioactivity in the urine and feces. 
With a percentage coefficient of variation of approximately 
30 %, six subjects were included. Subjects who received 
the single dose of the study medication were included in 
the analysis (intention-to-treat population). The percentage 
of simeprevir-related radioactivity of the total administered 
dose was determined for urine and feces. Descriptive 
statistics were used for demographic characteristics and 
total radioactivity levels. </p>

<p>2.2 Study 2: Simeprevir in Subjects with Severe 
Renal Impairment </p>

<p>2.2.1 Subjects </p>

<p>Eligible subjects included non-HCV-infected male and 
post-menopausal or non-pregnant, non-lactating female 
subjects between 18 and 70 years of age with a BMI of 
18-35 kg/m 
2 and a history of light or nonsmoking for 
3 months prior to screening (B10 cigarettes or two cigars 
or pipes per day). Subjects in the severe renal impairment 
group were required to have an estimated glomerular fil-
tration rate (eGFR) of B29 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 (determined 
by the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease equation), 
stable renal disease (plasma creatinine within 25 % of the 
last value obtained within 6 months of the study) and 
treatment regimen (from 2 months prior to study initia-
tion); subjects could not be receiving dialysis or be 
expected to receive dialysis within the next 3 months. 
Subjects with diabetes mellitus were eligible, provided that 
the disease was controlled (defined as glycosylated hemo-
globin \7 %). Control subjects had to be healthy based on 
medical history and pre-study physical examination, vital 
signs, electrocardiogram, and blood (biochemistry, hema-
tology, coagulation) and urine laboratory evaluations 
(conducted at screening). They were also required to have 
normal renal function, defined as an eGFR of C80 mL/ 
min/1.73 m 
2 (determined by the Modification of Diet in 
Renal Disease equation), and be matched to a subject with 
severe renal impairment in sex, race, age (within 10 years), 
and BMI (within 20 %). 
Subjects in both groups were excluded for a history of 
hepatitis A, B, or C or HIV infection. Subjects in the severe 
renal impairment group were also excluded for a history of 
renal carcinoma (unless cancer free for C5 years) or 
transplant, hepatorenal syndrome, uncontrolled hyperten-
sion, the use of disallowed medications (statins), or other 
significant diseases. Healthy subjects were also excluded 
for a history of congenital or hereditary kidney disease, 
nephrectomy, renal transplant, nephrolithiasis, or the use of 
medications other than paracetamol or ibuprofen. </p>

<p>2.2.2 Study Design </p>

<p>All subjects received a 150-mg oral dose (capsule) of 
simeprevir daily in the fed condition for 7 days. Pharma-
cokinetic analysis began on Day 7 following a C10-h fast 
and a standardized breakfast. Venous blood sampling for 
simeprevir plasma concentrations was performed on Days 
5, 6, and 7; full pharmacokinetic profiling was performed 
on Day 7. Samples were drawn pre-dose on Days 5 and 6 
and pre-dose and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 9, 12, 16, 24, 48, </p>

<p>Simeprevir in Renal Impairment </p>

<p>
and 72 h post-dose on Day 7. Simeprevir plasma concen-
trations were determined using liquid chromatography-
mass spectrometry/mass spectrometry. Unbound simepre-
vir concentrations were determined from blood samples 
drawn pre-dose and 4 h post-dose using liquid scintillation 
counting of fortified 
3 H-simeprevir after dialysis. Safety 
evaluation included subject-reported AEs, laboratory 
analysis (hematology and biochemistry on Days 1, 3, 5, 7, 
and 8), urinalysis (Days 1 and 7), and electrocardiograms 
(Days 1 and 7). </p>

<p>2.2.3 Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The primary endpoint was comparison of steady-state 
pharmacokinetics of simeprevir between subjects with 
severe renal impairment and matched subjects with normal 
renal function. The secondary endpoint was short-term 
safety and tolerability. No formal sample size determina-
tion was performed; a sample size of eight subjects per 
group was considered sufficient for pharmacokinetic 
assessment. Subjects who received at least one dose of the 
study medication were included in the analysis (intention-
to-treat population). Noncompartmental pharmacokinetic 
analysis was conducted with <rs id="software-0" type="software">WinNonlin Professional</rs> </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Pharsight Corporation</rs>, Mountain View, CA, 
USA). Descriptive statistics (mean, standard deviation 
[SD]) were calculated for total and unbound plasma con-
centrations at each time point. For the full pharmacokinetic 
profile, the minimum plasma concentration (C min ), maxi-
mum plasma concentration (C max ), and area under the 
plasma concentration-time curve at 24 h (AUC 24 ) on the 
logarithmic scale were the primary pharmacokinetic 
parameters of interest. A linear mixed-effects model 
(controlling for renal function) was used to estimate the 
least-squares (LS) means for each of the parameters. A 
90 % confidence interval (CI) was created around the dif-
ference between the LS means in the renal impairment and 
control groups. The Wilcoxon rank sum test was used for 
the comparison of the time to maximal plasma concentra-
tion (T max ) between groups. No formal hypothesis testing 
was performed. </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>3.1 Study 1: 
14 C-Simeprevir Mass Balance Study </p>

<p>Six male subjects were enrolled between February 2008 
and April 2008; all subjects completed the study. Baseline 
demographics are shown in Table 1. Subjects were male, 
Caucasian, and nonsmoking. The median age was 
47.0 years. </p>

<p>The mean total recovery of simeprevir-related radioac-
tivity from the urine and feces combined was 91.18 % 
[standard deviation (SD), 16.00]. The total simeprevir-
related radioactivity recovered from the urine was low and 
ranged between 0.009 and 0.138 % of the total radioactive 
dose (Table 2). Of the radioactivity excreted in the urine, 
the majority was excreted within 16-24 h post-dose. The 
majority of the radioactivity was excreted in the feces, 
ranging between 59 and 101 % (101 % because of round-
ing in one subject with a recovery slightly [100 %) of the 
total radioactive dose. One of the six subjects had a low 
radioactivity recovery of 59 % from the feces (reasons 
unclear); however, recovery in the remaining subjects was 
93-100 %. The largest fraction of radioactivity was 
excreted in the feces within 3 and 4 days post-dose 
(Fig. 1). 
For the study period (including screening, treatment 
period, and follow-up), at least one AE was reported in five 
subjects; these included increased alanine aminotransferase 
(ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) levels (two 
subjects), prolonged activated partial thromboplastin time 
(aPTT; two subjects), and dry mouth (one subject). Two 
AEs (both prolonged aPTT) were considered by the 
investigator to be very likely related to simeprevir, and four 
AEs (increased AST and ALT) were considered by the 
investigator to be possibly related to simeprevir. No deaths 
or AEs resulting in permanent premature discontinuation 
from the study occurred. </p>

<p>3.2 Study 2: Simeprevir in Subjects with Severe 
Renal Impairment </p>

<p>Sixteen subjects, eight subjects with severe renal impair-
ment and eight matched healthy subjects were enrolled 
between August 2011 and December 2011; all subjects 
completed the study. Baseline and demographic data are 
shown in Table 1. A majority of subjects were male and 
Caucasian. The median age was similar among groups; 
55.0 years (range 36-67 years) for subjects with renal 
impairment and 57.0 years (range 37-61 years) for control 
subjects. The median (range) eGFR was 19.9 mL/min/ 
1.73 m 
2 (range 12-28 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 ) in the renal 
impairment group and 94.4 mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(range 
84-110 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 ) in the control group. 
Steady-state pharmacokinetics were reached prior to 
blood sampling on Day 7 for most subjects, although 
concentrations increased after Day 7 for some subjects 
in both groups. Mean plasma concentrations were higher 
for subjects in the renal impairment group when com-
pared with subjects in the control group on all measured 
study days (Table 3). Pharmacokinetic analysis on Day 
7 revealed no major differences in the shape of the </p>

<p> 
S. Ouwerkerk-Mahadevan et al. </p>

<p>plasma concentration-time curve between groups 
(Fig. 2). Based on the LS mean ratio, the key pharma-
cokinetic parameters C min , C max , and AUC 24h of 
simeprevir were approximately 71, 34, and 62 % higher, 
respectively, in subjects with severe renal impairment 
compared with matched healthy subjects (Table 4). 
Scatter plots (not shown) demonstrated no correlation 
between individual eGFR values and individual C max 
and AUC 24h values. 
The median T max was 6 h (range 4-9 h) in both groups. 
Simeprevir plasma concentration declined more slowly in 
subjects with renal impairment compared with healthy 
subjects (Fig. 3). In addition, the mean half-life was pro-
longed in subjects with renal impairment, which was 24 h 
compared with 16.7 h in healthy subjects. </p>

<p>The mean unbound plasma concentrations in subjects 
with renal impairment were 0.2892 (SD 0.4411) at pre-dose 
and 0.4216 (SD 0.3319) at 4 h, which were higher com-
pared with matched healthy subjects: (mean 0.1142, SD 
0.1567 at pre-dose, and mean 0.2714, SD 0.2574 at 4 h). 
The mean fraction of simeprevir unbound to protein (fu) 
was about 0.0001 in both groups. 
For the study period (including screening, treatment 
period, and follow-up), at least one AE was reported in four 
subjects (50 %) in the renal impairment group and three 
subjects (37.5 %) in the control group (Table 5). During 
the treatment phase, four subjects (50 %) in the renal 
impairment group had at least one AE compared with one 
subject (12.5 %) in the control group. Most AEs were 
grade 1 or 2 in severity; a grade 3 rhabdomyolysis was </p>

<p>Table 1 Subject demographics </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Study 1 
Study 2 </p>

<p>All subjects (n = 6) 
Renally impaired subjects (n = 8) 
Healthy controls (n = 8) </p>

<p>Median (range) eGFR (mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
NA 
19.9 (12-28) 
94.4 (84-110) </p>

<p>Median (range) age (years) 
47.0 (35.0-51.0) 
55.0 (36-67) 
57.0 (37-61) </p>

<p>Sex, n (%) </p>

<p>Male 
6 (100) 
7 (87.5) 
7 (87.5) </p>

<p>Female 
0 
1 (12.5) 
1 (12.5) </p>

<p>Race </p>

<p>Caucasian 
6 (100) 
8 (100) 
8 (100) 
Median (range) BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
23.9 (20.7-27.4) 
27.8 (24-32) 
25.7 (23-29) </p>

<p>Median (range) height (cm) 
171.5 (162.0-184.0) 
173.0 (161-187) 
177 (161-186) </p>

<p>Median (range) weight (kg) 
70.0 (61.0-81.0) 
83.5 (67-100) 
81.5 (68-93) </p>

<p>Type of smoker, n (%) </p>

<p>Light/nonsmoker 
6 (100) 
8 (100) 
8 (100) </p>

<p>BMI body mass index, eGFR estimated glomerular filtration rate, NA not available </p>

<p>Table 2 Percentage of total 
radioactivity dose recovered in 
the urine and feces for 
individual subjects </p>

<p>Collection interval (h) 
Total radioactivity in urine (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Subject 1 
Subject 2 
Subject 3 
Subject 4 
Subject 5 
Subject 6 </p>

<p>0 -8 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>8-16 
0 
0 
0.029 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>16-24 
0.019 
0.009 
0.058 
0.019 
0.010 
0.022 </p>

<p>24-36 
0.015 
0 
0.021 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>36-48 
0 
0 
0.030 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Total 
0.034 
0.009 
0.138 
0.019 
0.010 
0.022 </p>

<p>Collection interval (h) 
Total radioactivity in feces (%) </p>

<p>Subject 1 
Subject 2 
Subject 3 
Subject 4 
Subject 5 
Subject 6 </p>

<p>Total 
96 
99 
59 
93 
99 
101 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a Not quantifiable radioactivity was detected in the urine from 48 to 216 h of collection in any subject </p>

<p>b Subject 6 had a recovery slightly [100 %, which rounded to 101 % </p>

<p>Simeprevir in Renal Impairment </p>

<p>
observed in the renal impairment group. AEs during the 
treatment phase in the renal impairment group included: 
myalgia, rhabdomyolysis, hypertension, hyperbilirubine-
mia, and increased blood alkaline phosphatase; all were 
experienced by one subject (12.5 %) each. Hyperbiliru-
binemia was the only AE observed during the treatment 
phase in the control group. No deaths or AEs resulting in 
permanent premature discontinuation of simeprevir occur-
red. All AEs were considered by the investigator to be 
unrelated or doubtfully related to simeprevir, aside from 
rhabdomyolysis and myalgia, which were considered 
probably related to simeprevir. These were experienced by 
the same subject who was also taking high-dose fenofi-
brate. This subject experienced myalgia on Day 4 (recov-
ered 1 day later) and elevated AST, ALT, lactate </p>

<p>dehydrogenase, and bilirubin (direct and indirect) levels on 
Day 8; rhabdomyolysis was confirmed on Day 9 with a 
creatine kinase level of 96.76 lkat/L, creatine kinase 
muscle brain fraction levels of 20.84 and 19.45 lg/L, and 
myoglobin levels of 1200, 1475, and 1476 lg/L on Day 9. 
The subject was hospitalized for 3 days and received 
ademetionine; laboratory values gradually decreased over 
the following 30 days. </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>Given the increased prevalence of HCV in patients with 
CKD and the increased morbidity and mortality associated 
with HCV in this population, HCV therapies that are safe </p>

<p>0 
24 
48 
72 
96 
120 
144 
168 
192 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Post dosing time (h) 
Fecal excretion recovery (% of dose) </p>

<p>Subject 1 </p>

<p>Subject 2 </p>

<p>Subject 3 </p>

<p>Subject 4 </p>

<p>Subject 5 </p>

<p>Subject 6 </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Cumulative excretion of the radioactivity in feces as a 
function of time after a single oral administration of 200 mg of </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C-simeprevir </p>

<p>0 
4 
8 
1 2 
1 6 
2 0 
2 4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>5000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>7000 </p>

<p>8000 </p>

<p>9000 </p>

<p>Time (h) 
Simeprevir plasma concentration (ng/mL) </p>

<p>Subjects with several renal impairment (n = 8) </p>

<p>Matched healthy subjects (n = 8) </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Linear plasma concentration-time profiles of simeprevir in 
subjects with several renal impairment and controls </p>

<p>Table 3 Pharmacokinetics of simeprevir in subjects with severe renal impairment and healthy matched controls </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic parameters mean (SD) 
Renally impaired subjects (n = 8) 
Matched healthy controls (n = 8) </p>

<p>Day 5 </p>

<p>C 0h (ng/mL) 
1688 (1882) 
825.1 (1004) </p>

<p>Day 6 </p>

<p>C 0h 
1944 (2254) 
939.0 (1142) </p>

<p>Day 7 </p>

<p>C 0h (ng/mL) 
2220 (2696) 
1112 (1480) </p>

<p>C min (ng/mL) 
1707 (1741) 
961.3 (1191) </p>

<p>C max (ng/mL) 
4671 (3823) 
3378 (2636) </p>

<p>T max (h) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.0 (4.0-9.0) 
6.0 (4.0-9.0) </p>

<p>AUC 24h (ngÁh/mL) 
76,690 (71,740) 
44,380 (39,920) </p>

<p>AUC 24h area under the plasma concentration-time curve for 24 h post-dose, C 0h predose plasma concentration, C max maximum plasma con-
centration, C min minimum plasma concentration, SD standard deviation, T max time to reach C max 
a Values presented are the median (range) </p>

<p> 
S. Ouwerkerk-Mahadevan et al. </p>

<p>and effective in patients with CKD are needed. Simeprevir 
is a once-daily, oral HCV NS3/4A protease inhibitor for the 
treatment of chronic HCV genotype 1 infection, as a </p>

<p>component of combination antiviral therapy [28, 29]. In 
phase II and III studies, simeprevir has been demonstrated 
to be safe, with high SVR rates when used in combination 
with ribavirin and pegylated interferon or sofosbuvir [29- 34]. 
These two studies demonstrated that simeprevir has 
minimal renal excretion and that its pharmacokinetics are 
not altered to a clinically significant degree in patients with 
severe renal impairment, which suggests that simeprevir 
may be administered without dose adjustment in patients 
with mild, moderate, or severe renal impairment. 
The 
14 C-simeprevir mass balance study demonstrated a 
predominance of fecal excretion (59-101 %), with \2 % 
of 
14 C-simeprevir excreted in the urine. This suggests that 
simeprevir is primarily eliminated by biliary excretion with 
insignificant renal clearance. These results are consistent 
with preclinical studies that demonstrated that simeprevir 
was predominately distributed to the liver and intestines 
with low distribution (similar or less than plasma) to the 
kidneys [38, 39]. These results suggest that renal </p>

<p>0 
1 2 
2 4 
3 6 
4 8 
6 0 
7 2 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>10,000 </p>

<p>Time (h) 
Simeprevir plasma concentration (ng/mL) </p>

<p>Subjects with several renal impairment (n = 8) </p>

<p>Matched healthy subjects (n = 8) </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Semilogarithmic plasma concentration-time profiles of 
simeprevir in subjects with several renal impairment and controls </p>

<p>Table 5 Incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events </p>

<p>Adverse event, n (%) 
Renally impaired subjects 
Matched healthy controls </p>

<p>Treatment phase 
Follow-up 
Whole study </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Treatment phase 
Follow-up 
Whole study </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Any AE 
4 (50.0) 
1 (12.5) 
4 (50.0) 
1 (12.5) 
2 (25.0) 
3 (37.5) </p>

<p>Hyperbilirubinemia 
1 (12.5) 
0 
1 (12.5) 
1 (12.5) 
1 (12.5) 
2 (25.0) </p>

<p>Pneumonia 
0 
1 (12.5) 
1 (12.5) 
0 
0 
0 
Myalgia 
1 (12.5) 
0 
1 (12.5) 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Rhabdomyolysis 
1 (12.5) 
0 
1 (12.5) 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
1 (12.5) 
0 
1 (12.5) 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Investigations </p>

<p>Prolonged aPTT 
0 
1 (12.5) 
1 (12.5) 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Increased blood ALP 
1 (12.5) 
0 
1 (12.5) 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>Increased hepatic enzyme 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 (12.5) 
1 (12.5) </p>

<p>AE adverse event, ALP alkaline phosphatase, aPTT activated partial thromboplastin time 
a The whole study periods include screening, treatment phase, and follow-up </p>

<p>Table 4 Statistical evaluation of simeprevir pharmacokinetics </p>

<p>Parameter 
LS means 
LS means ratio 
90 % CI </p>

<p>Renally impaired subjects (n = 8) 
Matched healthy controls (n = 8) </p>

<p>C min (ng/mL) 
985.5 
577.5 
1.71 
0.65, 2.50 </p>

<p>C max (ng/mL) 
2588 
3459 
1.34 
0.66, 2.72 </p>

<p>AUC 24h , (ngÁh/mL) 
32,010 
51,710 
1.62 
0.73, 3.59 </p>

<p>T max (h) 
6.0 (4.0-9.0) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>6.0 (4.0-9.0) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0 
0.0, 0.2 </p>

<p>AUC 24h area under the plasma concentration-time curve for 24 h post-dose, CI confidence interval, C max maximum plasma concentration, C min 
minimum plasma concentration, LS least squares, T max time to reach C max 
a Values presented are the median (range) </p>

<p>Simeprevir in Renal Impairment </p>

<p>
impairment would be unlikely to affect the pharmacoki-
netics of simeprevir; however, given that severe renal 
impairment may affect pharmacokinetics through diverse 
mechanisms, such as alterations in cytochrome P450 
activity, conjugation reactions (glucuronidation and 
acetylation), and intestinal or hepatic transport, a pharma-
cokinetic study (Study 2) in subjects with severe renal 
impairment was also performed [40]. 
Pharmacokinetic studies of simeprevir in subjects with 
severe renal impairment demonstrated that most subjects 
with renal impairment reached steady state within 7 days; 
these results were comparable to subjects without renal 
impairment in both this study and in previous studies [28]. 
Slightly higher plasma concentrations of simeprevir were 
seen in subjects with severe renal impairment compared 
with healthy subjects with a C min , C max , and AUC 24h that 
were approximately 71, 34, and 62 % higher, respectively. 
The 90 % confidence intervals were wide because of the 
small sample size and high inter-subject variability. These 
mild increases in simeprevir plasma concentrations are 
unlikely to be clinically significant. In addition, the con-
centrations observed in this study (non-HCV-infected 
subjects with renal impairment) were within the range of 
concentrations observed in phase III studies (AUC 
4848-449,185 ngÁh/mL) in HCV-infected subjects without 
renal impairment [41]. It is important to note that subjects 
with HCV infection have been shown to have two-to three-
fold higher concentrations when compared with non-HCV-
infected subjects and, therefore, simeprevir concentrations 
in HCV-infected patients with renal impairment would be 
expected to be higher than those observed in this study 
[28]. 
In addition, the mean half-life of simeprevir was pro-
longed in subjects with severe renal impairment when 
compared with subjects with normal renal function (24 and 
16.7 h, respectively). Similar to simeprevir concentrations, 
differences in the half-life of simeprevir have also been 
observed between non-HCV-infected subjects and HCV-
infected subjects with normal renal function; the half-life 
of simeprevir is between 10 and 13 h in non-HCV-infected 
subjects and 41 h in HCV-infected subjects [28]. There-
fore, the half-life of simeprevir in HCV-infected subjects 
with renal impairment may be longer than that reported for 
non-HCV-infected subjects with renal impairment in this 
study. 
Simeprevir was well tolerated in subjects with renal 
impairment in this study; the majority of AEs were 
mild/moderate in severity. All AEs were considered by the 
investigator to be unrelated or doubtfully related to 
simeprevir, except for the serious AE rhabdomyolysis and 
the AE myalgia, which were considered probably related to 
simeprevir; these were experienced by the same patient 
who was also taking high-dose fenofibrate, which has been </p>

<p>associated with AST and ALT elevations, myopathy, and 
rhabdomyolysis [42]. 
The safety and efficacy of simeprevir has not been 
evaluated in patients with ESRD (eGFR \15 mL/min), 
including patients who require dialysis. Simeprevir is 
highly bound to plasma proteins (C99 %); therefore, 
simeprevir would not be expected to be removed by dial-
ysis. Further studies are needed to evaluate the efficacy and 
safety of simeprevir in patients with ESRD and in patients 
requiring dialysis. The results obtained in this study are 
consistent with those seen with other N3/4 protease inhi-
bitors used to treat HCV, such as boceprevir and telaprevir. 
These agents have similarly demonstrated minimal renal 
excretion and nonclinically significant pharmacokinetic 
alterations in subjects with renal impairment [18, 24, 25,  43-45]. 
The renal system plays an important role in the elimi-
nation of other HCV therapies, including ribavirin and 
pegylated interferon; the pharmacokinetics of these medi-
cations demonstrate greater alterations in patients with renal 
impairment [12, 18, 23]. For ribavirin, a </p>

<p>14   C-ribavirin 
excretion study demonstrated that 61 % of radioactivity was 
excreted in the urine following a 600-mg </p>

<p>14   C-ribavirin dose 
[12]. A study comparing the pharmacokinetics of ribavirin 
between 18 subjects with renal impairment (mild, moderate, 
or severe) and six healthy subjects demonstrated a decrease 
in apparent clearance of approximately 50-75 % and a two-
to three-fold increase in AUC in subjects with moderate to 
severe renal impairment following a single 400-mg dose 
[46]. For interferon-a 2b , a single-dose pharmacokinetic 
study of 20 subjects with renal impairment (all severities) 
and six healthy control subjects found decreases in apparent 
clearance of up to 45 % and a 90 % increase in AUC and 
C max in subjects with severe renal impairment compared 
with healthy subjects, following a 1-lg/kg subcutaneous 
dose [14]. The effects of renal impairment on the pharma-
cokinetics of interferon-a 2a may be less pronounced as it is 
largely metabolized by the liver; the package label reports a 
25-45 % reduction in clearance in ESRD on hemodialysis 
[13, 18]. 
In addition, the renal system is important for the elim-
ination of sofosbuvir, an NS5B protease inhibitor that is 
recommended in the American Association for the Study of 
Liver Disease/Infectious Diseases Society of America 
guidelines (as part of combination therapy) for the treat-
ment of all genotypes in patients with normal renal func-
tion who are initiating or who have relapsed following 
pegylated interferon/ribavirin therapy [19]. The package 
insert reports that 80 % of 
14 C-sofosbuvir was recovered 
from the urine following a 400-mg 
14 C-sofosbuvir dose 
[23]. In addition, pharmacokinetic studies in subjects with 
renal impairment have demonstrated increases in the area 
under the curve to infinity (AUC inf ) of 61, 107, and 171 % </p>

<p> 
S. Ouwerkerk-Mahadevan et al. </p>

<p>in subjects with mild, moderate, and severe renal impair-
ment, respectively, compared with subjects with normal 
renal function, following a single 400-mg dose [23]. 
Because the safety and efficacy of sofosbuvir have not been 
established in people with severe renal impairment (eGFR 
\30 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 ), no dose recommendations were 
given for these individuals [23]. Moreover, the use of 
simeprevir in combination with sofosbuvir in patients with 
renal impairment has not been studied. 
For daclatasvir, an NS5A replication complex inhibitor, 
a 
14 C-daclatasvir excretion study demonstrated that only 
6.6 % of the total radioactivity dose was eliminated in 
urine (88 % recovery from the feces) [26]. Pharmacoki-
netic studies have demonstrated only mild increases in the 
AUC inf of approximately 18, 39, and 51 % in subjects with 
moderate, severe, and ESRD, respectively [26, 27]; there-
fore, daclatasvir may be administered to patients with all 
degrees of renal impairment and in ESRD without dose 
adjustment [26]. </p>

<p>5 Conclusions </p>

<p>Simeprevir plasma concentrations were mildly increased 
in subjects with severe renal impairment. The results 
suggest that simeprevir may be administered without dose 
adjustment in patients with renal impairment, although 
caution should be exercised until more information is 
available regarding the safety of simeprevir in this 
population. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments Editorial support for the writing of this manu-
script was provided by Melissa Yuan, MD, of MedErgy, and was 
funded by Janssen. </p>

<p>Compliance with Ethical Standards </p>

<p>Funding These studies were sponsored by Janssen. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest S. O.-M., G. M., and I. W. are full-time 
employees of Janssen Research &amp; Development; M. B.-M., S. M., 
M. P., R. V., and A. S. are full-time employees of Janssen Infectious 
Diseases; and C. T. is a consultant at Janssen Infectious Diseases. </p>

<p>Ethical standards These studies were conducted in accordance 
with the principles of the Good Clinical Practice Guidelines and the 
Declaration of Helsinki. The final protocols were reviewed and 
approved by independent ethics committees, and all subjects provided 
written informed consent prior to study enrollment. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which per-
mits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original 
author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons 
license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p>Simeprevir in Renal Impairment </p>



<p>
 
S. Ouwerkerk-Mahadevan et al. </p>

</text></tei>