<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4939487" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Aims: This study aimed to evaluate the efficacy of computed tomog-
raphy (CT)-guided bone biopsy for the diagnosis of spinal infection and com-
pared the clinical outcomes between tuberculous and pyogenic spinal infections. 
Methods: The retrospective cohort study included patients who received CT-guid-
ed bone biopsy at a tertiary hospital over the 13 years. 
Results: Among 100 patients, 67 had pyogenic spondylitis and 33 had tuberculous 
spondylitis. Pathogens were isolated from bone specimens obtained by CT-guid-
ed biopsy in 42 cases, with diagnostic yields of 61% (20/33) for tuberculous spon-
dylitis and 33% (22/67) for pyogenic spondylitis. For 36 culture-proven pyogenic 
cases, Staphylococcus aureus was the most commonly isolated organism. Patients 
with pyogenic spondylitis more frequently presented with fever accompanied by 
an increase in inflammatory markers than did those with tuberculosis. Among 
all patients who underwent surgery, the incidence of late surgery performed one 
month after diagnosis was higher in patients with tuberculous infection (56.3%) 
than in those with pyogenic disease (23.3%, p = 0.026). 
Conclusions: Results obtained by CT-guided bone biopsy contributed to prompt 
diagnoses of spinal infections, especially those caused by tuberculosis. Despite 
administration of anti-tuberculous agents, patients with tuberculous spondylitis 
showed an increased tendency to undergo late surgery. </p>

<p>Keywords: Spondylitis; Computed tomography; Biopsy; Tuberculosis; Percutaneous </p>

<p>Diagnostic yield of computed tomography-guided 
bone biopsy and clinical outcomes of tuberculous 
and pyogenic spondylitis </p>

<p>Eun-Jeong Joo 1 , Joon-Sup Yeom 1 , Young Eun Ha 2 , So Yeon Park 3 , Chong-Suh Lee 4 , Eun-Sang Kim 5 , 
Cheol-In Kang 2 , Doo-Ryeon Chung 2 , Jae-Hoon Song 2 , and Kyong Ran Peck 2 </p>



<p>Joo EJ, et al. CT-guided bone biopsy in spinal infection </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2013.019 </p>

<p>of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) has improved the 
sensitivity and specificity of this disease entity, the diag-
nosis of spondylitis has been a challenge for physicians 
for many years [6]. 
Computed tomography (CT)-guided biopsy is a valu-
able tool in the diagnosis of musculoskeletal diseases. 
The value of this procedure in pyogenic spinal infection 
has been investigated in several studies, indicating a 
sensitivity range of 30% to 50% [7-9]. However, the diag-
nostic yield of CT-guided bone biopsy for spinal tuber-
culosis has rarely been exploited despite the recent ris-
ing prevalence of both tuberculous and pyogenic spinal 
infection [10,11]. 
To evaluate the roles of CT-guided biopsy in tuber-
culous and pyogenic spondylitis, we conducted a retro-
spective cohort study in patients who were diagnosed 
with spine infection and who received a CT-guided 
bone biopsy over a 13-year period. Among recipients of 
CT-guided bone biopsies, we also compared the clinical 
outcomes between tuberculous and pyogenic spondyli-
tis groups. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study population and patient selection </p>

<p>This retrospective cohort study was designed to iden-
tify the diagnostic yield of CT-guided bone biopsy and 
to evaluate the clinical outcomes in patients with spinal 
infection from March 1996 to March 2008 in a 1,900-
bed tertiary care university hospital. To search patients 
who have underwent CT-guided bone biopsy and di-
agnosed to have osteomyelitis, we screened cases in 
which "bone" specimen was obtained by "CT-guided 
procedure." Specimen code for "bone tissue" and pro-
cedure codes for "bone needle biopsy procedure" and 
"imaging guidance procedure" were used for screening 
cases. Electronic medical records were reviewed among 
screened individuals. From the medical records, we 
selected patients who had cultural and pathologic re-
ports and radiologic findings compatible with those of 
pyogenic and tuberculous spondylitis. Based on histo-
pathologic reports, cases proven to have malignancy or 
non-septic inflammatory discitis were excluded. Finally 
adults patients, who had underwent CT-guided bone bi-
opsy and been diagnosed to have infectious spondylitis </p>

<p>by the evidence of cultural, pathologic, and radiologi-
cal data and been treated with prolonged antimicrobial 
therapy, were enrolled in the study. </p>

<p>Definitions and data collection </p>

<p>Patients with tuberculous spondylitis were categorized 
into definite, probable and possible groups, whereas 
those with pyogenic one were categorized into definite 
and possible. The definite group referred to cases with 
microbiologic evidence of bacteria, fungus or tubercu-
losis. The presence of caseating granulomatosis or ac-
id-fast bacilli in Ziehl-Neelsen stained slides on histopa-
thology defined probable tuberculosis in cases without 
mycobacterial growing. Detection of tuberculosis by 
polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was also used to aid the 
probable diagnosis when microbiologic evidence was 
not given [12]. The possible group contained cases that 
were clinically diagnosed and treated with conventional 
antibacterial and anti-tuberculous agents by attending 
physicians, based on clinical presentation and mani-
festation when test results from cultures, histopathol-
ogy, and tuberculosis PCR failed to prove presumptive 
pathogen. Radiologic findings such as the patterns of 
destruction of vertebral end plates and signal-intensity 
changes of involved vertebrae, and presence of epidural, 
paravertebral, and dis-space abscess were also used to 
support a clinical diagnosis. 
The following patient data were collected using elec-
tronic medical and laboratory records: initial clinical 
presentation such as fever, constitutional symptoms, 
and back pain; underlying comorbidity; laboratory data 
including white blood cell count (WBC), erythrocyte 
sedimentation rate (ESR), and C-reactive protein (CRP) 
level; involved vertebra; radiologic findings suggesting 
tuberculosis or pyogenic spinal infections, the presence 
of paravertebral or epidural abscess; results of histopa-
thology; antibiotic regimen and duration of treatment; 
and performance of surgical intervention 
Clinical improvement was assessed at 4 weeks during 
the course of therapy. Lack of improvement referred to 
the cases with persistent or aggravated back pain, neces-
sity of abscess drainage, or development of neurologic 
deficit [13]. The patients were followed up for 6 months 
after completion of treatment. Clinical success was de-
fined as cases without recurrence at 6 months after fin-
ishing treatment, whereas clinical failure was as those </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 31, No. 4, July 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2013.019 </p>

<p>with death, relapse or repetitive surgery during the fol-
low-up period. 
The time of surgery was defined as days between the 
date of CT-guided bone biopsies and the date of sur-
gical intervention. Types of surgical intervention were 
further classified into early and late surgery. The late 
cases were designated as those performed 1 month after 
diagnosis. The number and percentage of late surger-
ies was also calculated to evaluate the efficacy of initial 
medical treatment. The decision to perform early or late 
surgery was made by the attending surgeon. The rea-
sons for late surgical approach were divided into two 
categories whether it was initially planned at the time 
of diagnosis when the early surgery was indicated or it 
was abruptly performed as the results of lack of clinical 
improvement. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Student t test was used to compare continuous variables, 
and Pearson chi-square test or Fisher exact test was used 
to compare categorical variable. Values of p &lt; 0.05 were 
considered statistically significant. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistics for 
Windows, PASW <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, 
USA), was used for all statistical analyses. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Diagnostic yield of CT-guided bone biopsy </p>

<p>During the study period between 1996 and 2008, a to-
tal of 1,027 cases were screened to have had undergone 
CT-guided bone biopsy. Of them, 927 were excluded; 
898 malignancy and non-septic discitis; 29 incomplete 
medical records. Only one hundred patients have been 
diagnosed and treated as infectious spondylitis among 
recipients of CT-guided bone biopsy over the 13 year-</p>

<p>study period. 
Of 100 patients, 67 were identified to have pyogenic 
spondylitis. Definite diagnosis for pyogenic spondylitis 
were made in 36 patients because bacterial and fungal 
growing was confirmed in those (32 and 4), whereas pos-
sible diagnosis were made in 31 patients who had been 
treated with antibacterial agents based on clinical and 
laboratory supports without microbiologic evidence. 
Thirty-three patients were diagnosed to have tubercu-
lous spondylitis. Definite growth of Mycobacterium tuber-
culosis was confirmed in 13 patients. Histopathological 
analyses of vertebral marrow showed granuloma with 
caseating necrosis in nine patients, suggesting probable 
tuberculosis. Eleven patients were treated with antitu-
berculous agents based on clinical diagnosis and re-
ferred to possible group. 
Microbiologic and pathologic yield of CT-guided 
bone biopsy for diagnosing definite and probable in-
fectious spondylitis was shown in Table 1. In pyogenic 
spondylitis group, of 36 confirmed cases, 22 micro-or-
ganisms were recovered from bone specimens obtained 
by biopsies and remaining 14 organisms were from 
blood and other tissues, which were not obtained from 
CT-guided biopsy. This resulted in 33% of diagnostic 
yield of CT-guided bone biopsy for pyogenic spondyli-
tis. Definite growth of M. tuberculosis in 13 patients was 
identified respectively from 11 bone specimens and two 
sputum cultures. Nine pathologic results from bone 
marrows had assisted to make a diagnosis for probable 
tuberculous spondylitis. Among a total of 33 tuberculo-
sis cases, 20 were identified by test results from bone 
specimens, which had yielded 61% of diagnosis of tu-
berculosis. </p>

<p>Table 1. Microbiologic and pathologic yield of computed tomography-guided bone biopsy </p>

<p>Infectious spondylitis 
Total no. (%) 
(n = 100) </p>

<p>No. of cases (%) </p>

<p>Pyogenic 
spondylitis (n = 67) </p>

<p>Tuberculous 
spondylitis (n = 33) </p>

<p>Definite and probable cases 
58 (58) 
36 (54) 
22 (67) </p>

<p>Proven by bone tissue obtained from CT-guided bone biopsy 
42 (42) 
22 (33) 
20 (61) </p>

<p>Proven by other tissues not obtained from CT-guided biopsy 
16 (16) 
14 (21) 
2 (6) </p>

<p>CT, computed tomography. </p>



<p>Joo EJ, et al. CT-guided bone biopsy in spinal infection </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2013.019 </p>

<p>Clinical characteristics of tuberculous and pyogenic 
groups </p>

<p>Clinical characteristics of patients with tuberculous and 
pyogenic spondylitis are compared in Table 2. The me-</p>

<p>dian age was 56 years and males were predominant in 
the pyogenic group (68.7%) compared with the tubercu-
lous group (45.5%, p = 0.044). Patients presented with spi -
nal disease (26%), diabetes (13%), and hypertension (13%). </p>

<p>Table 2. Clinical characteristics in groups of pyogenic and tuberculous spondylitis </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>No. of cases (%) 
p value 
Total 
(n = 100) </p>

<p>Pyogenic spondylitis 
(n = 67) </p>

<p>Tuberculous spondylitis 
(n = 33) </p>

<p>Age, yr 
56 (43-64) 
57 (42-66) 
54 (44-4) 
0.892 </p>

<p>Male sex 
61 (61) 
46 (68.7) 
15 (45.5) 
0.044 </p>

<p>Fever 
46 (46) 
35 (52.2) 
11 (33.3) 
0.038 </p>

<p>Underlying disease </p>

<p>Diabetes 
13 (13) 
7 (10.4) 
6 (18.2) 
0.360 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
13 (13) 
6 (9.0) 
7 (21.2) 
0.127 </p>

<p>Renal insufficiency 
6 (6) 
2 (3.0) 
4 (12.1) 
0.177 </p>

<p>Chronic liver disease 
4 (4) 
3 (4.5) 
1 (3.0) 
1.000 </p>

<p>Spinal disease 
26 (26) 
23 (34.3) 
3 (9.1) 
0.004 </p>

<p>Others 
25 (25) 
15 (22.4) 
10 (30.3) 
0.491 </p>

<p>Involved spines 
0.002 </p>

<p>Cervical thoracolumbar 
29 (29) 
12 (17.9) 
17 (51.5) </p>

<p>Cervical 
1 (1) 
0 
1 (3.0) </p>

<p>Thoracic 
19 (19) 
8 (11.9) 
11 (33.3) </p>

<p>Thoracolumbar 
9 (9) 
4 (6.0) 
5 (15.2) </p>

<p>Lumbar-sacral 
69 (69) 
53 (79.1) 
16 (48.5) </p>

<p>Lumbar 
56 (56) 
41 (61.2) 
15 (45.5) </p>

<p>Lumbosacral 
13 (13) 
12 (17.9) 
1 (3.0) </p>

<p>Extensive 
2 (2) 
2 (3.0) 
0 </p>

<p>Presence of abscess a 
49 (49) 
30 (44.8) 
19 (57.6) 
0.229 </p>

<p>Index of inflammation </p>

<p>WBC, × 1,000 cells/µL 
7,760 (6,300-10,020) 
8,050 (6,712-10,140) 
6,800 (5,670-9,075) 
0.016 </p>

<p>ESR, mm/hr 
58.00 (28.00-79.00) 
64.50 (42.25-88.50) 
52.00 (22.00-70.50) 
0.038 </p>

<p>CRP, mg/dL 
3.43 (0.97-7.61) 
4.07 (1.64-9.05) 
2.55 (0.71-5.01) 
0.179 </p>

<p>Surgical intervention 
46 (46) 
30 (44.8) 
16 (48.5) </p>

<p>Early (within 1 month) 
30 (30) 
23 (76.7) 
7 (43.8) </p>

<p>Late (after 1 month) 
16 (16) 
7 (23.3) 
9 (56.3) 
0.026 </p>

<p>30-Day mortality 
3 (3) 
2 (3.0) 
1 (3.0) </p>

<p>Repetitive surgery 
1 (1) 
0 
1 (3.0) </p>

<p>Unknown, follow-up loss 
12 (12) 
7 (10.4) 
5 (15.2) </p>

<p>Hospital stay 
32 (19-50) 
38 (24-52) 
21 (9-35) 
0.003 </p>

<p>Values are presented as median (interquartile range) or number (%). Characteristics of groups between pyogenic and tubercu-
lous spondylitis were compared in the analysis including definite, probable, and possible cases. 
WBC, white blood cell count; ESR, erythrocyte sedimentation rate; CRP, C-reactive protein. 
a Abscess at psoas muscles, epidural space, and paravertebral area. </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 31, No. 4, July 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2013.019 </p>

<p>The most commonly involved vertebrae were lumbar 
(56%), followed by thoracic (19%) and thoracolumbar 
(9%). Cervical thoracolumbar vertebrae were more com-
monly involved in the tuberculous group (51.5%) than in 
the pyogenic group (17.9%), with statistical significance 
(p = 0.002). More than three ranges of spines were exten-
sively involved in only in one case, which was caused by 
Pseudomonas aeruginosa. An abscess in the psoas muscles 
or in the epidural or paravertebral space was observed in 
49% of patients. Patients with pyogenic spondylitis more 
frequently presented with fever accompanied by an in-
crease in inflammatory markers than did those with tu-
berculosis. A total of 11 cases were identified to have surc -
gical site infection which occurred within 3 months after 
spine surgery in pyogenic spondylitis group. 
Surgical intervention was performed in 46% of spon-
dylitis cases. Sixteen patients (16%) underwent surgery 1 
month after diagnosis despite medical treatment: these 
included nine cases of tuberculous spondylitis and 
seven cases of pyogenic one (56.3% vs. 23.3%, p = 0.026). 
There were no differences between the two groups with 
respect to rates of 30-day mortality and repetitive sur-
gery. Patients with pyogenic spondylitis had stayed lon-
ger in hospital than had those with tuberculous spondy-
litis (38 days vs. 21 days, p = 0.003). </p>

<p>Microbiological data </p>

<p>Thirty-eight isolates were recovered in 36 patients of 
definite pyogenic groups. Mixed organisms were found 
in two patients with methicillin-susceptible Staphylococ-
cus aureus and Streptococcus viridans and methicillin-re-
sistant S. aureus and Enterococcus faecalis. S. aureus was the 
most commonly recovered isolate, accounting for 47% 
of cases with definite pyogenic spondylitis. Gram-neg-
ative organisms were cultivated in eight patients (21%). 
Fungus was recovered in four patients (11%), and all of 
these cases were related to surgical site infection. De-
tailed microbiological results are provided in Table 3. </p>

<p>Comparison between culture-positive and negative 
groups with bacterial infection </p>

<p>Characteristics of patients with positive culture results 
in definite bacterial infection group were compared 
with those who had negative culture results in possible 
group (Table 4). Four fungal cases were excluded in this 
analysis. The rates of prior antimicrobial treatment were </p>

<p>not different between the two groups. An increase in in-
flammatory markers was observed in the culture-posi-
tive group, in particular the WBC and CRP levels. Clini-
cal outcomes were not different between the two groups. </p>

<p>Late surgical intervention </p>

<p>A late surgical approach was attempted in 16 patients 
with nine cases of tuberculosis and seven cases of pyo-
genic spondylitis, including probable and possible di-
agnoses (Table 5). Five patients with spinal tuberculo-
sis had accompanying pulmonary infection. When we 
analysed the reasons for late surgery, most cases were 
related to lack of clinical improvement related to aggra-
vation of back pain, progression of abscess and neuro-
logic deficit. In four tuberculous spondylitis cases, de-
layed surgery was planned intentionally at the time of </p>

<p>Table 3. Isolated organisms </p>

<p>Isolated organism 
No. of isolates (%) 
(n = 38) </p>

<p>Gram-positive organisms 
26 (68.4) </p>

<p>Staphylococcus species 
21 (55.3) </p>

<p>Staphylococcus aureus 
18 (47.4) </p>

<p>Methicillin-susceptible a 
17 (44.7) </p>

<p>Methicillin-resistant b 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>Coagulase-negative staphylococcus 
3 (7.9) </p>

<p>Methicillin-susceptible 
2 (5.3) </p>

<p>Methicillin-resistant 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>Streptococcus species a 
2 (5.3) </p>

<p>Enterococcus species b 
2 (5.3) </p>

<p>Gram negative organisms 
8 (21.1) </p>

<p>Klebsiella pneumoniae 
2 (5.3) </p>

<p>Pseudomonas aeruginosa 
2 (5.3) </p>

<p>Escherichia coli 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>Alcaligenes xylosoxidans 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>Burkholderia cepacia 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>Salmonella Paratyphi A 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>Fungus 
4 (10.5) </p>

<p>Aspergillus fumigatus 
3 (7.9) </p>

<p>Candida albicans 
1 (2.6) </p>

<p>a Mixed organisms with methicillin-susceptible S. aureus and 
Streptococcus viridans in one patient. 
b Mixed organisms with methicillin-resistant S. aureus and 
Enterococcus faecalis in one patient. </p>



<p>Joo EJ, et al. CT-guided bone biopsy in spinal infection </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2013.019 </p>

<p>diagnosis even though patients presented with epidural 
and paravertebral abscesses. In these cases, attending 
physicians have decided to observe the response of anti-
tuberculosis treatment and delay the surgery for at least 
1 month, expecting the improvement of spondylitis by 
medical therapy. The size of the abscess in four patients, 
at the time of assessment of clinical response, was not 
improved despite antituberculous therapy, which had 
resulted in the late surgery. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study evaluated the diagnostic yield of CT-guid-
ed bone biopsy for infectious spondylitis in a country 
with a high prevalence of tuberculosis. Microbiological 
and pathologic data obtained by CT-guided bone biop-
sy contributed to the prompt diagnosis of spinal infec-
tion, especially in cases with tuberculosis, which showed 
a 60% diagnostic yield. The value of percutaneous bi-
opsy had been analysed in previous studies with yields 
ranging from 40% to 70% [7,10,11,14]. The 60% yield 
of CT-guided bone biopsy in diagnosing tuberculous 
spondylitis achieved in this study is in accordance with 
results from previous studies. Even though prior stud-</p>

<p>ies have already reported the high yield of percutaneous 
biopsy for the diagnosis of tuberculosis, these studies 
did not target subjects who underwent CT-guided bone 
biopsy. Most of the research issues associated with spi-
nal tuberculosis have been confined to the diagnostic 
modality of MRI and clinical outcomes [2,6,15]. In such 
a situation lacking the evidence provided by specimens 
obtained under the guidance of CT, our study has signif-
icance in having evaluated a large number of patients 
and provided a comprehensive conclusion. 
The utility of inflammatory markers for the differen-
tiation between tuberculous and bacterial etiology was 
previously investigated in community-acquired pneu-
monia. A marked increase in inflammatory markers was 
strongly associated with a bacterial etiology and disease 
severity in pneumonia [16,17]. Comparative studies of 
pyogenic and tuberculous spinal infections have investi-
gated the association between an increased ESR and py-
ogenic spondylitis, but the results were not sufficiently 
consistent to show a significant association [11,18]. The 
results of the present study showing a strong association 
between inflammatory markers and pyogenic spondy-
litis are expected to be valuable in discriminating the 
bacteria from tuberculosis. 
The culture-negative rate was approximately 50% for </p>

<p>Table 4. Clinical characteristics in patients with culture-positive and negative results in bacterial infection group </p>

<p>Variable 
No. of patients 
p value 
Culture-positive (n = 32) 
Culture-negative (n = 31) </p>

<p>Age, yr 
57 (42-69) 
55 (40-62) 
0.487 </p>

<p>Male sex 
23 (71.9) 
19 (61.3) 
0.373 </p>

<p>Underlying disease 
24 (75.0) 
18 (58.1) 
0.154 </p>

<p>Previous antibiotic-usage 
21 (65.6) 
14 (45.2) 
0.102 </p>

<p>Fever 
12 (37.5) 
13 (41.9) 
0.719 </p>

<p>Index of inflammation 
32 
30 </p>

<p>WBC, × 1,000 cells/µL 
8,290 (6,640-14,930) 
7,990 (6,700-9,360) 
0.011 </p>

<p>ESR, mm/hr 
66.5 (52.8-98.8) 
61.0 (31.8-84.8) 
0.075 </p>

<p>CRP, mg/dL 
6.95 (3.37-13.63) 
2.30 (0.68-4.24) 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Surgical intervention 
16 (50.0) 
11 (35.5) 
0.244 </p>

<p>Clinical improvement a 
28 (87.5) 
27 (87.1) 
0.263 </p>

<p>Hospital stay 
42 (28-55) 
31 (35-50) 
0.064 </p>

<p>Values are presented as median (interquartile range) or number (%). Characteristics between patients with definite and possi-
ble bacterial infections were compared. Four fungal cases were not introduced in this analysis. 
WBC, white blood cell count; ESR, erythrocyte sedimentation rate; CRP, C-reactive protein. 
a Assessment at at 4 weeks during the course of therapy. </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 31, No. 4, July 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2013.019 </p>

<p>all of bacterial spondylitis cases in this study. To iden-
tify factors associated with culture-negative results, we 
compared the culture-positive and -negative groups. 
Patients in the culture-negative group presented with a 
lower CRP and a lower ESR compared with those of the 
culture-positive group, and previous antimicrobial ther-</p>

<p>apy did not affect the negative results. In the previous 
study of evaluating the impact of prior antibiotic expo-
sure on the results of culture in patients with infectious 
spondylitis, the presence of paravertebral abscess, ele-
vated WBC, CRP levels were related to positive outcome, 
whereas longer duration of previous antibiotic expo-</p>

<p>Table 5. Late surgical attempts in 16 patients </p>

<p>No. Age Sex 
Clinical 
diagnosis 
Comorbidity 
Time of 
surgery 
Abscess 
Reasons for 
late surgery 
Level 
Treatment 
regimen </p>

<p>Duration, 
mon </p>

<p>1 
52 
F Tuberculous, 
possible </p>

<p>Pulmonary 
TB </p>

<p>72 
Yes 
Delayed 
surgery </p>

<p>T6-8 
HREZ 
18 </p>

<p>2 
50 
F Tuberculous, 
probable </p>

<p>No 
71 
Yes 
Progression 
of abscess </p>

<p>L3-4 
HREZ 
17 </p>

<p>3 
73 
M Tuberculous, 
possible </p>

<p>HTN 
54 
Yes 
Progression 
of abscess </p>

<p>T10-11 HREZ 
10 </p>

<p>4 
21 
M Pyogenic, 
definite </p>

<p>No 
126 
No 
Neurologic 
deficit </p>

<p>L4-5 
PIP/TAZ, CFTZ, 
SMX/TMP </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 
43 
M Tuberculous, 
definite </p>

<p>Pulmonary 
TB </p>

<p>38 
Yes 
Progression 
of abscess </p>

<p>T10-12 HREZ 
18 </p>

<p>6 
61 
F Tuberculous, 
definite </p>

<p>Pulmonary 
TB </p>

<p>56 
No 
Delayed 
surgery </p>

<p>L2-3 
HREZ 
14 </p>

<p>7 
54 
M Pyogenic, 
possible </p>

<p>HIVD 
48 
Yes 
Aggravation 
of back pain </p>

<p>L4-5 
CFZ, CIP, CLND 
2.5 </p>

<p>8 
47 
F Tuberculous, 
probable </p>

<p>Pulmonary 
TB </p>

<p>55 
Yes 
Delayed 
surgery </p>

<p>T12-L1 HREZ 
15 </p>

<p>9 
54 
M Pyogenic, 
definite </p>

<p>HIVD 
195 
Yes 
Relapsed 
infection </p>

<p>L4-5 
Fluconazole 
2 </p>

<p>10 
44 
M Tuberculous, 
probable </p>

<p>HIVD 
306 
No 
Neurologic 
deficit </p>

<p>L2-3 
HREZ 
12 </p>

<p>11 
22 
F Tuberculous, 
probable </p>

<p>Pulmonary 
TB </p>

<p>50 
Yes 
Progression 
of abscess </p>

<p>L1-2 
HREZ 
14 </p>

<p>12 
25 
M Pyogenic, 
possible </p>

<p>HIVD 
67 
No 
Neurologic 
deficit </p>

<p>L3-4 
CFZ→CIP, CLND 
2 </p>

<p>13 
60 
F Pyogenic, 
possible </p>

<p>Behcet 
81 
Yes 
Progression 
of abscess </p>

<p>L5 
CFZ→CIP, RFP 
12 </p>

<p>14 
78 
F Pyogenic, 
possible </p>

<p>HTN 
59 
No 
New abscess 
formation </p>

<p>L3-S 
CTRX, 
VANC→LFLX, 
RFP </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>15 
69 
M Pyogenic, 
definite </p>

<p>LC, CRF 
61 
Yes 
Progression 
of abscess </p>

<p>T11-12 
MERO 
2.5 </p>

<p>16 
57 
F Tuberculous, 
definite </p>

<p>HIVD 
102 
Yes 
Delayed 
surgery </p>

<p>C6-T3 
HREZ 
15 </p>

<p>TB, tuberculosis; HREZ, isoniazid + rifampicin + ethambutol + pyrazinamide; HTN, hypertension; PIP/TAZ, piperacillin/ 
tazobactam; CFTZ, ceftazidime; SMX/TMP, sufamethoxazole/trimethoprim; HIVD, herniated intervertebral disc; CFZ, ce-
fazolin; CIP, ciprofloxacin; CLND, clindamycin; RFP, rifampicin; CTRX, ceftriaxone; VANC, vancomycin; LFLX, levofloxacin; 
LC, liver cirrhosis; CRF, chronic renal failure; MERO, meropenem. </p>



<p>Joo EJ, et al. CT-guided bone biopsy in spinal infection </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2013.019 </p>

<p>sure, 4 or more days was related to negative outcome 
[19]. According to the results of this study, although we 
have investigated duration of previous antibiotic expo-
sure, we couldn't find the exact data for duration of an-
tibiotic exposure. These findings might reflect the fact 
that this study was conducted in a tertiary-care hospital 
to which most of the patients were referred during an-
timicrobial therapy, and data concerning prescriptions 
given outside of the hospital may be incorrect. Alterna-
tively, the negative culture result might be a reflection 
of a less extensive inflammatory process triggered by a 
low grade infection [20]. It is also possible that samples 
were collected at the site devoid of organisms, resulting 
in a false-negative result [21]. Given the concerns sur-
rounding a possible false-negative result, a repeat biop-
sy might be considered when the first biopsy is negative. 
In past decades, radical resection of the tuberculo-
sis-infected focus and bone grafting was suggested as a 
general approach for the treatment of spinal tubercu-
losis in patients with severe neurological deficits. With 
the advent of imaging modalities and effective treat-
ment regimens, a non-operative approach was subse-
quently introduced for those with spinal tuberculosis 
and neurologic deficits [22]. However, delayed surgery 
for late onset complications involves the risk of neural 
deterioration and vertebral destruction leading to severe 
kyphosis [23]. In our study, 16 patients underwent de-
layed operation after the lack of improvement by medi-
cal approaches; of these, late surgery had been originally 
planned for four cases. Upon further investigation into 
these cases of late surgery for spinal tuberculosis, disease 
progression including kyphosis and spinal instability 
was observed in a total of nine cases despite adminis-
tration of more effective antituberculous agents. These 
deteriorating outcomes in cases of delayed surgery raise 
concerns regarding trials that delay the initial surgical 
approach indicated at the time of diagnosis. According 
to a study that evaluated prognostic factors influencing 
the outcomes of patients with spinal tuberculosis, radi-
cal surgery was significantly related to a favourable out-
come and a large number of involved vertebrae was re-
lated to the progression of kyphosis [2,24]. Considering 
these outcomes of surgical treatment in spinal tubercu-
losis, it is important to cautiously select cases that are 
predicted to deteriorate during medical treatment for 
early-radical operation, especially those involving more </p>

<p>than two vertebrae and with expected kyphosis [2,24]. If 
it is not possible to undergo an early-radical approach 
in adversely predicted cases, it is mandatory to perform 
short-term follow-up for early recognition of impend-
ing neurologic deficits. 
This study has several limitations. First, it was a ret-
rospective design with a small sample size that was not 
sufficient to show statistical power. Because clinical data 
regarding initial presentations and outcomes were col-
lected retrospectively, initial clinical presentation and 
additional data that could be helpful to assess possible 
portals of entry in patients with spondylitis were not 
described precisely. A second limitation concerns the 
problems associated with a large single center study in 
a tertiary to which most of the patients were referred 
from other institutions. This might result in an inaccu-
rate assessment of previous antimicrobial usage outside 
of this hospital and may lead to a large number of neg-
ative-cultural reports; thus, underestimating the exact 
diagnostic yield of bone biopsy in pyogenic spondylitis. 
Finally, there is the possibility of inaccurate diagnoses 
in cases of possible spondylitis. Among antituberculous 
agents, rifampin, and fluoroquinolone are known to be 
active against staphylococcal infection. Many cases that 
were treated as possible tuberculosis might have been 
culture-negative pyogenic spondylitis. To adjust for 
possible misdiagnoses between tuberculosis and bacte-
rial etiologies, we classified cases into definite, probable, 
and possible groups. The clinical characteristics of tu-
berculous and pyogenic spondylitis infections showed 
consistent results even after adjusting for possible cases. 
In conclusion, microbiological and pathologic data 
obtained by CT-guided bone biopsy contributed to a 
prompt diagnosis of spinal infection, especially the 60% 
diagnostic yield caused by tuberculosis. Pyogenic spon-
dylitis was associated with fever more frequently than 
was tuberculous spondylitis. Despite early administra-
tion of antituberculous agents, patients with tuberculo-
sis tended to show progression of inflammatory and de-
structive processes, leading to late surgical intervention. 
With the current increasing prevalence of both tuber-
culous and pyogenic spinal infections, CT-guided bone 
biopsy is expected to serve as an effective modality for 
the prompt diagnosis and proper management of infec-
tious spondylitis. </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 31, No. 4, July 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2013.019 </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>



<p>KEY MESSAGE </p>

<p>1. Microbiological and pathologic data obtained 
by computed tomography (CT)-guided bone 
biopsy contributed to an effective diagnosis 
of spinal infection, especially the 60% diag-
nostic yield caused by tuberculosis. 
2. Despite early administration of anti-tubercu-
lous agents, patients with tuberculosis tended 
to show progression of inf lammatory and 
destructive processes, leading to late surgical 
intervention. 
3. CT-guided bone biopsy is expected to serve 
as an effective modality for the prompt diag-
nosis and proper management of infectious 
spondylitis. </p>



<p>Joo EJ, et al. CT-guided bone biopsy in spinal infection </p>



</text></tei>