<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4875560" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aims </p>

<p>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is associated with an increased risk of stroke, which is currently estimated by clinical character-
istics. The cardiac biomarkers N-terminal fragment B-type natriuretic peptide (NT-proBNP) and cardiac troponin high-
sensitivity (cTn-hs) are independently associated with risk of stroke in AF. Our objective was to develop and validate a 
new biomarker-based risk score to improve prognostication of stroke in patients with AF. </p>

<p>Methods 
and results </p>

<p>A new risk score was developed and internally validated in 14 701 patients with AF and biomarkers levels determined at 
baseline, median follow-up of 1.9 years. Biomarkers and clinical variables significantly contributing to predicting stroke 
or systemic embolism were assessed by Cox-regression and each variable obtained a weight proportional to the model 
coefficients. External validation was performed in 1400 patients with AF, median follow-up of 3.4 years. The most im-
portant predictors were prior stroke/transient ischaemic attack, NT-proBNP, cTn-hs, and age, which were included in 
the ABC (Age, Biomarkers, Clinical history) stroke risk score. The ABC-stroke score was well calibrated and yielded 
higher c-indices than the widely used CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score in both the derivation cohort (0.68 vs. 0.62, P , 0.001) 
and the external validation cohort (0.66 vs. 0.58, P , 0.001). Moreover, the ABC-stroke score consistently provided 
higher c-indices in several important subgroups. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>A novel biomarker-based risk score for predicting stroke in AF was successfully developed and internally validated in a 
large cohort of patients with AF and further externally validated in an independent AF cohort. The ABC-stroke score 
performed better than the presently used clinically based risk score and may provide improved decision support in AF. </p>

<p>ClinicalTrials. 
gov identifier </p>

<p>NCT00412984, NCT00799903. </p>

<p>---Atrial fibrillation (AF) is a common and treatable risk factor 
for stroke and systemic embolism. 
1,2 The AF population is </p>

<p>heterogeneous with a variable risk of stroke. 
3 Development of </p>

<p>risk stratification schemes in AF patients emerged in the 1990s 
and have thereafter been reconstructed and refined continuous-
ly. 
4 -7 Current guidelines recommend a risk-based approach to </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Tel: +46 18 611 95 07, Fax: +46 18 51 55 70, Email: ziad.hijazi@ucr.uu.se 
&amp; The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Society of Cardiology. </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals. 
permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>European Heart Journal (2016) 37, 1582-1590 
doi:10.1093/eurheartj/ehw054 </p>

<p>decisions on anticoagulation treatment in AF based on the CHA 2-
DS 2 -VASc score [which assigns 1 point each for a history of congest-
ive heart failure, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, vascular disease, 
age 65 -74 years, and sex category (female gender), and 2 points 
for age ≥75 years and, prior stroke/transient ischaemic attack 
(TIA)]. 
5 The CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc and other currently used risk scores </p>

<p>are all based solely on clinical variables. Recently, it was demon-
strated that biomarkers reflecting cardiac and renal dysfunction as 
well as inflammation and oxidative stress are related to the risk of 
stroke and other outcomes in patients with AF. 
8 We demonstrated </p>

<p>that cardiac troponin measured with high-sensitivity assays (cTn-hs), 
indicating myocardial injury, and N-terminal fragment B-type natri-
uretic peptide (NT-proBNP), indicating myocyte stress, contained 
more prognostic information than most clinical characteristics in pa-
tients with AF. 
9 -12 Based on these experiences, we aimed to improve </p>

<p>risk stratification of stroke in AF by developing and validating a risk 
score that included the prognostically most important biomarkers 
and clinical characteristics. The project was performed in accordance 
with the recent TRIPOD statement. 
13 The development cohort was </p>

<p>14 701 patients with AF with biomarkers measured at entry in the 
Apixaban for Reduction in Stroke and Other Thromboembolic 
Events in Atrial Fibrillation (ARISTOTLE) trial, and the validation 
cohort was 1400 participants with AF and biomarkers measured at 
entry in the STabilization of Atherosclerotic plaque By Initiation of 
darapLadIb TherapY (STABILITY) trial. </p>

<p>14 -17 </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study populations </p>

<p>The details of the ARISTOTLE trial (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: 
NCT00412984) have been published previously. 
14,15 Briefly, ARIS-</p>

<p>TOTLE was a double-blind, double-dummy, randomized clinical trial 
that enrolled 18 201 patients between December 2006 and April 
2010. Patients included had paroxysmal, persistent or permanent AF, 
or atrial flutter, and one or more of the following risk factors: age 
≥75 years, prior stroke, TIA, or systemic embolus, heart failure, dia-
betes mellitus, or hypertension requiring pharmacological treatment. 
Participants were randomized to warfarin (n ¼ 9081) or apixaban 
(n ¼ 9120). The primary endpoint was stroke or systemic embolism. 
The median length of follow-up was 1.9 years for the subset of patients 
with cardiac biomarkers available at randomization (n ¼ 14 701) after 
exclusion of 45 (0.3%) patients with missing variables. A total of 1056 
deaths occurred during follow-up. The median time in therapeutic range 
(TTR) in the warfarin-treated group was 66.1 calculated by the method 
of Rosendaal. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>The external validation cohort consisted of 1400 participants with AF 
or atrial flutter (689 on oral anticoagulation) and biomarkers available at 
entry in the STABILITY trial. The details of the STABILITY trial (Clinical-
Trials.gov identifier: NCT00799903) have been published previously. </p>

<p>16,17 </p>

<p>Briefly, STABILITY was a double-blind, international, multicentre, event-
driven trial that randomly assigned 15 828 patients with stable coronary 
heart disease to receive either once-daily darapladib or placebo between 
December 2008 and April 2010. Patients included had stable coronary 
heart disease and at least one of the following additional cardiovascular 
risk factors: age ≥60 years, diabetes, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol 
level of ,1.03 mmol/L, smoker of five or more cigarettes per day, mod-
erate renal dysfunction (≥30 and ≤59 mL/min), or polyvascular arterial 
disease. The primary endpoint was a composite of cardiovascular death, </p>

<p>myocardial infarction, or stroke, and median follow-up was 3.4 years in 
this external validation cohort. 
Ethics committee approval was obtained for all investigational sites, 
and all patients gave written informed consent. </p>

<p>Endpoints and outcome assessment </p>

<p>In both trials, all outcomes were adjudicated by the same international 
team of adjudicators blinded to treatment assignment. Stroke was 
defined as the sudden onset of a focal neurological deficit in a location 
consistent with the territory of a major cerebral artery and categorized 
as ischaemic, haemorrhagic, or unspecified. Haemorrhagic transform-
ation of ischaemic stroke was not considered to be haemorrhagic 
stroke. In the ARISTOTLE trial, systemic embolism was also adjudicated 
and defined as an acute vascular occlusion of an extremity or organ, 
documented by means of imaging, surgery, or autopsy. </p>

<p>Biochemical methods </p>

<p>In both trials, patients provided blood samples at study entry. Plasma 
was frozen in aliquots and stored until analysed centrally at the Uppsala 
Clinical Research Center (UCR) laboratory, Uppsala, Sweden. Plasma 
cardiac troponin-I levels (cTnI-hs) were determined with high-sensitivity 
sandwich immunoassays on the ARCHITECT i1000SR (Abbott Diag-
nostics) according to the instructions of the manufacturer, and 
NT-proBNP and troponin-T (cTnT-hs) levels in plasma were deter-
mined with high-sensitivity sandwich immunoassays on the Cobas </p>

<p>w </p>

<p>Analytics e601 Immunoanalyzers (Roche Diagnostics, Germany) ac-
cording to the instructions of the manufacturer. The limit of detection 
(LoD) and analytical range for these assays have been described 
previously. </p>

<p>10 -12 </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Derivation of the prediction model </p>

<p>All biomarkers were log-transformed and values below the reporting 
limit were set to half the limit. As a first step, a model including all can-
didate predictors (listed in Table 1) was fitted. Separate models were de-
rived for inclusion of cTnI-hs and cTnT-hs. Possible non-linearities were 
evaluated by transforming the continuous variables using restricted cu-
bic splines, each with four knots placed at the respective 5th, 35th, 65th, 
and 95th sample percentiles. To allow for different prediction models 
for subjects with and without a prior stroke, bivariate interactions be-
tween each variable and prior stroke were included. The global tests 
of any non-linearity or interaction were not statistically significant, 
wherefore the full prediction model included only main effects and lin-
ear terms. For a more parsimonious and clinically useful model, we ap-
proximated the full model by using a fast backward algorithm on an 
ordinary least squares model in which the estimated linear predictor 
from the full Cox model was the outcome and all candidate variables 
were entered in exactly the same manner as in the full Cox model. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Thus, in the first step R 
2 ¼ 1.0 by design and by removing variables in </p>

<p>a stepwise manner, the full model could be approximated to an arbitrary 
level. The final model approximated 96.5% of the full model while only 
including the four variables: age, cTnI-hs (or cTnT-hs), NT-proBNP, and 
prior stroke/TIA. The strong correlation between age and creatinine 
clearance entailed that one of these biomarkers could be excluded with-
out an effect on the outcome. Age was included as it is a readily available 
variable, and a required determinant for estimating creatinine clearance. 
As a sensitivity analysis, we fitted a competing risks model with stroke/ 
systemic embolism as the event of interest and death of any cause as a 
competing risk. </p>

<p>ABC-stroke risk score </p>



<p>Model validation </p>

<p>The model was internally validated using 300 bootstrap samples. Within 
each bootstrap sample, we refitted the model and compared the appar-
ent performance in the bootstrap sample with the test performance 
(applying the refitted model to the original data). The optimism was 
quantified as the mean difference of these performance estimates. To 
reduce the optimism of new predictions, we applied uniform shrinkage 
to the regression parameters by calculating the linear predictor for all 
subjects in the original sample using the estimated regression coeffi-
cients from the models fitted within each bootstrap sample followed 
by using the observed outcomes in the original sample, the slope 
for the linear predictor estimated using a Cox-regression model. The 
average of all slopes determined the shrinkage. External validation was 
conducted in 1400 patients from the STABILTY trial using the cTnT-hs 
model as cTnI-hs was not measured in the STABILITY trial. 
Discrimination was assessed by Harrell's c-index and graphically pre-
sented by plotting Kaplan-Meier curves for the predefined risk classes. 
Calibration was assessed graphically by comparing observed event rates 
with the predicted risk at 1, 2, and 3 years. 
The final prediction model was presented as a nomogram and its dis-
criminative ability was compared with the presently used CHA 2 DS 2 -
VASc score using 1000 bootstrap samples. ABC-stroke risk classes 
were defined as low (,1%), medium (1 -2%), and high (.2%) 1-year 
risk of stroke or systemic embolism according to established stroke 
risk categories. 
To illustrate the comparison with the CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score for risk 
stratification, the ABC-stroke risk classes were also based on treatment 
decision values for stroke risk adjusted for antithrombotic treatment 
according to 0 -0.3%, 0.3 -1%, 1 -2%, and .2% 1-year risk of stroke 
or systemic embolism. 
The final model was also evaluated for consistency in various sub-
groups, e.g. in warfarin-treated patients with low TTR, in whom anticoa-
gulation is sub-therapeutic. The analyses followed the framework for 
derivation and validation of prediction models proposed by Harrell, 
Steyerberg, and Steyerberg and Vergouwe. 
18 -20 The external validation </p>

<p>followed the principles and methods described by Royston and Altman 
and the reporting followed the recently published TRIPOD statement </p>

<p>(protocol checklist, Supplementary material online, Figure G). 
13,21 All </p>

<p>analyses were performed using R version 3.1 using the packages <rs type="software">rms</rs> 
and <rs type="software">Hmisc</rs>. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Baseline demographics and cardiac 
biomarkers in the derivation cohort </p>

<p>A total of 14 701 patients in the ARISTOTLE trial had plasma sam-
ples available for biomarker measurements at entry. Baseline demo-
graphics and biomarker levels are presented in Table 1. The median 
age was 70 (range 19 -97) years and 35.7% were women. Hyperten-
sion was the most common CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc risk factor (87.5%), fol-
lowed by age .65 years (69.9%), female sex (35.7%), heart failure 
(31.0%), diabetes mellitus (24.7%), prior stroke or TIA (18.8%), and 
vascular disease (24.8%). Cardiac troponin-I high-sensitivity was de-
tectable in 93.6% of patients and elevated in 9.2%, cTnT-hs was de-
tectable in 93.5% and elevated in 34.4%, and 75% had elevated 
NT-proBNP levels. </p>

<p>Development of a new biomarker-based 
risk score in atrial fibrillation in the 
derivation cohort </p>

<p>The development of the new risk score and selection of the prog-
nostically most important clinical variables and biomarkers was 
based on 27929 person-years of follow-up and of 391 stroke or 
systemic embolism events in the ARISTOTLE cohort. The most im-
portant predictors of stroke were prior stroke or TIA, NT-proBNP, 
cTnI-hs (or cTnT-hs), and age (Supplementary material online, Figure 
A). The remaining clinical variables or biomarkers did not add signifi-
cant information to the risk score. The final score was named ABC-
stroke score based on inclusion of Age, Biomarkers (cTnI-hs and 
NT-proBNP), and Clinical history (prior stroke/TIA) (Figure 1). </p>

<p>.... ............ ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ...... </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographics and baseline characteristics in the derivation and external validation cohorts </p>

<p>Variable 
Derivation 
(n 5 14 701) </p>

<p>External validation 
(n 5 1400) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
70.0 (19.0-97.0) 
69.0 (37.0-88.0) </p>

<p>Gender (female) 
35.7% (5255) 
14.4% (201) </p>

<p>Current smoker 
8.1% (1188) 
11.8% (165) 
Permanent or persistent AF 
84.8% (12 473) 
36.6% (512) </p>

<p>Heart failure 
31.0% (4555) 
31.2% (437) </p>

<p>Hypertension 
87.5% (12 868) 
75.4% (1055) 
Diabetes 
24.7% (3632) 
39.4% (552) </p>

<p>Prior stroke/TIA 
18.8% (2770) 
14.4% (201) </p>

<p>Vascular disease 
24.8% (3649) 
58.3% (816) 
Prior myocardial infarction 
12.8% (1884) 
54.1% (758) </p>

<p>Peripheral arterial disease 
4.9% (718) 
9.3% (130) </p>

<p>Troponin I high-sensitivity (ng/L) 
5.4 (,2.0-11 230.0) 
NA 
Troponin T high-sensitivity (ng/L) 
10.9 (,5.0-1580.0) 
12.2 (,5.0-156.0) </p>

<p>NT-proBNP (ng/L) 
713.0 (,5.0-31 309.0) 
399.0 (,5.0-25 770.0) </p>

<p>Renal function, eGFR (mL/min/m 
2 ) 
74.0 (18.3-345.0) 
67.9 (24.9-118.4) </p>

<p>AF, atrial fibrillation; TIA, transient ischaemic attack; NT-proBNP, N-terminal fragment B-type natriuretic peptide; eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate. </p>

<p>Z. Hijazi et al. </p>



<p>Internal validation of the ABC-stroke 
score and comparison with 
CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc </p>

<p>The ABC-stroke score that included cTnI-hs yielded a c-index of 
0.68 for stroke or systemic embolism (Table 2). The internal boot-
strap validation indicated only modest over-fitting (optimism-
corrected c-index of 0.67). The ABC-stroke score that included 
cTnT-hs provided similar results. The sensitivity analysis using 
a competing risks model showed similar results (Supplementary 
material online, Figure B) with a c-index of 0.67. 
For comparison, the widely used CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score achieved 
a c-index of 0.62 in this cohort (P , 0.001). The ABC-stroke score 
that included cTnI-hs consistently achieved higher c-indices when 
compared with the CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score in subgroups without 
prior stroke in order to assess the score performance in the primary 
prevention setting (0.66 vs. 0.59, P , 0.001). It also achieved well in 
patients with a low time (,65%) in therapeutic range (TTR) (0.67 
vs. 0.62, P ¼ 0.014) (Table 2). Also with cTnT-hs, the ABC-stroke 
score (nomogram in Supplementary material online, Figure C) con-
sistently achieved higher c-indices (P , 0.001) when compared with 
the CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score with c-index of 0.67 in the total cohort, 
c-index of 0.65 (P ¼ 0.006) in the subgroup without prior stroke, </p>

<p>and c-index of 0.67 (P ¼ 0.005) in patients with low TTR (Table 2). 
Within both low-and high-risk CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score cohorts, the 
ABC-stroke risk score was well calibrated and further stratified pa-
tients into subgroups with observed 1-year event rates close to the 
1-year predicted by the ABC-stroke score (Figure 2 and Supplemen-
tary material online, Table). 
There was no significant interaction between the ABC-stroke 
score and the relative reduction of stroke with apixaban when com-
pared with warfarin. The absolute difference in the rate of stroke or 
systemic embolism was larger in patients with a predicted annual 
risk .1% in the ABC-stroke score (Figure 3). </p>

<p>External validation of the ABC-stroke 
score and comparison with 
CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc </p>

<p>Baseline demographics and biomarker levels in the external validation 
cohort are presented in Table 1. In the external validation, based on 
4751 person-years of follow-up and 48 adjudicated stroke events, 
ABC-stroke score achieved a c-index of 0.66 in comparison with 
0.58 for the CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score (P , 0.001). The incidence rates 
(events per 100 person-years) were similar in the derivation and ex-
ternal validation data within each predefined risk class: 0.56 vs. 0.56 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Nomogram for the new biomarker-based risk score. For each predictor, read the points assigned on the 0-10 scale at the top and </p>

<p>then sum these points. Find the number on the 'Total Points' scale and then read the corresponding predictions of 1-and 3-year risk of stroke or 
systemic embolism below it. Continuous variables are represented from the 1st to the 99th percentiles. The prediction model is preferably used as 
a web-based calculator or app. Application of the nomogram is exemplified in Supplementary material online, Figures E and F. </p>

<p>ABC-stroke risk score </p>



<p>(low), 1.37 vs. 1.29 (medium), and 2.63 vs. 3.22 (high) (Table 3). The 
relative hazard ratios between the risk classes in the derivation and 
validation cohorts were similar (Table 3). Kaplan-Meier curves within 
risk classes for both the derivation and validation data illustrate that 
the ABC-stroke score was well calibrated with a good discriminative 
ability in different cohorts of patients with AF (Figure 4 and calibration 
plot in Supplementary material online, Figure D). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The ABC-stroke score is a novel biomarker-based risk score for 
predicting stroke or systemic embolism and was developed in 
a very large cohort of patients with AF treated with oral anticoagu-
lation. The score included two biomarkers-NT-proBNP and car-
diac troponin-hs-and two pieces of directly available clinical </p>

<p>.... ............ ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ...... </p>

<p>.... ............ ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ...... </p>

<p>Table 2 C-indices (95% confidence interval) for the ABC-stroke and CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc scores in the derivation (n 5 14 
701) and the validation cohort (n 5 1400) </p>

<p>Full cohort 
No prior stroke 
TTR &lt;65% </p>

<p>Derivation cohort 
ABC-stroke (troponin I) 
0.68 (0.65, 0.71) 
0.66 (0.62, 0.69) 
0.67 (0.62, 0.71) </p>

<p>ABC-stroke (troponin T) 
0.67 (0.65, 0.70) 
0.65 (0.61, 0.68) 
0.67 (0.63, 0.71) </p>

<p>CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc 
0.62 (0.60, 0.65) 
0.59 (0.55, 0.63) 
0.62 (0.57, 0.66) </p>

<p>Validation cohort 
ABC-stroke (troponin T) 
0.66 (0.58, 0.74) 
0.63 (0.54, 0.72) 
NA </p>

<p>CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc 
0.58 (0.49, 0.67) 
0.50 (0.40, 0.60) 
NA </p>

<p>TTR, time in therapeutic range (International normalized ratio 2.0 -3.0); ABC-stroke, Age, Biomarkers (cardiac troponin and NT-proBNP), Clinical history (prior stroke/transient 
ischaemic attack); CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc, assigns 1 point each for Congestive heart failure, Hypertension, Diabetes mellitus, Vascular disease, Age 65 -74 years, and Gender category 
(female gender), and 2 points for Age ≥75 years and, prior Stroke/transient ischaemic attack. </p>

<p>Figure 2 (A) Kaplan-Meier estimated cumulative event rate by four ABC-stroke risk classes for the CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score (panel): 0 -1, 2, 3, </p>

<p>4, and ≥5 points. (B) Kaplan -Meier estimated cumulative event rate by the CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score: 0 -1, 2, 3, 4, and ≥5 points for the three 
ABC-stroke risk classes (panel): 0 -0.3%, 0.3-1%, 1 -2, and .2%. </p>

<p>Z. Hijazi et al. </p>



<p>information-age and prior stroke. The ABC-stroke score consist-
ently predicted stroke or systemic embolism with a significantly 
higher accuracy than the guideline-recommended CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc 
risk model when validated internally using bootstrap samples and 
multiple subgroups. The ABC-stroke score was also found well 
calibrated and with consistent superiority over the clinical risk score 
in the external validation in a smaller cohort of patients with AF. The 
new biomarker-based ABC-stroke score was developed and vali-
dated in accordance with the recent TRIPOD statement and should 
therefore be acceptable for implementation in clinical care. 
The ABC-stroke score is simple, only encompassing four vari-
ables (Age, Biomarkers (troponin and NT-proBNP), and prior 
stroke or TIA as Clinical history). These four variables provided 
most of the prognostic information in multivariable models from 
the Cox analyses. When including the two biomarkers in the risk 
score model previously identified clinical risk factors, such as hyper-
tension, diabetes mellitus, congestive heart failure, and other </p>

<p>cardiovascular diseases or gender, no longer carried any important 
incremental prognostic information. The biomarkers appear to add 
important information concerning subclinical cardiovascular dys-
function and were better associated with vascular vulnerability 
than disease diagnosis. 
22 This might be explained by more informa-</p>

<p>tion is gained by biomarkers being more sensitive indicators of myo-
cardial stress and dysfunction. 
23 -25 In contrast to other scores, </p>

<p>using categorical irreversible risk factors, the proposed ABC-stroke 
score also contains continuous risk variables. The ABC-stroke score 
is dynamic with the opportunity to increase or decrease and would 
thereby be expected to allow monitoring of the patient's clinical 
condition and changes in risk of future events in either direction. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>A dynamic risk score may facilitate its use as a decision support tool 
for selection of treatment in different clinical settings, e.g. in relation 
to the profiles of new treatments such as dabigatran, rivaroxaban, 
and apixaban, when compared with warfarin. 
14,23,27 Risk stratifica-</p>

<p>tion with the ABC-stroke score indicated that the largest gain in </p>

<p>Figure 3 Kaplan -Meier estimated cumulative event rate by randomized treatment (colour) for the three ABC-stroke risk classes (panel): </p>

<p>low (,1%), medium (1 -2%), and high (.2%). </p>

<p>. ............ ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ......... </p>

<p>. ............ ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ......... </p>

<p>Table 3 Event rates and hazard ratios between ABC-stroke risk classes for the derivation and the validation cohorts </p>

<p>Risk class 
n 
Events 
Incidence rate </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Hazard ratio </p>

<p>Derivation cohort 
Low (,1%) 
4170 
46 
0.56 (0.41, 0.74) 
1.00 (ref) </p>

<p>Medium (1-2%) 
7154 
187 
1.37 (1.18, 1.58) 
2.45 (1.78, 3.38) </p>

<p>High (.2%) 
3377 
158 
2.63 (2.24, 3.08) 
4.67 (3.36, 6.48) </p>

<p>Validation cohort 
Low (,1%) 
820 
16 
0.56 (0.32, 0.90) 
1.00 (ref) </p>

<p>Medium (1-2%) 
448 
19 
1.29 (0.78, 2.02) 
2.34 (1.20, 4.55) </p>

<p>High (.2%) 
132 
13 
3.22 (1.71, 5.50) 
5.80 (2.79, 12.1) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Per 100 person-years. </p>

<p>ABC-stroke risk score </p>



<p>stroke or systemic embolism prevention with apixaban when 
compared with warfarin was obtained in high-risk patients. 
The ABC-stroke score includes two biomarkers, NT-proBNP 
and cardiac troponin-hs, both of which are readily available in 
most parts of the world. Even without a thorough understanding 
of the exact mechanisms, information on cardiac biomarker levels 
substantially improves the risk prediction in patients with AF. Other 
biomarkers, e.g. markers of inflammation (C-reactive protein, 
interleukin-6), oxidative stress (GDF-15), and coagulation (e.g. 
D-dimer), have in some studies shown associations with stroke in 
AF in addition to clinical risk factors. 
8,28 However, these biomarkers </p>

<p>were not included in the present evaluation, as they have not dis-
played independent associations with stroke in the presence of 
NT-proBNP and cardiac troponin, or are cumbersome to measure 
and assess in clinical practice. 
8,28 Furthermore, in our sensitivity </p>

<p>analyses (not shown), adding these biomarkers to the construction 
model did not add important prognostic information to the 
presented model. 
The ABC-stroke score was constructed using established statis-
tical methods for development of the clinical prediction models 
and adhered to the recently developed TRIPOD statement. 
13 The </p>

<p>model construction was based on an extensive clinical trial with 
standardized recording of clinical characteristics and careful long-
term follow-up of centrally adjudicated outcome events. The large 
number of events and the relatively simple model appears to have 
prevented over-fitting as shown by the internal bootstrap validation 
and the successful external validation in an independent cohort of 
patients with AF. The new ABC-risk score seemed robust, since it 
provided similar information when based on two different troponin 
assays. Although the ABC-stroke risk score yielded a modest 
c-index of 0.68, it consistently outperformed the current guidelines-
recommended stroke risk score. It was also well calibrated as pre-
dicted event rates were associated with the observed event rates </p>

<p>both in the derivation and validation cohorts. Evaluation of the score 
was also assessed in patients with ineffective and without anticoagu-
lant treatment. Warfarin-treated patients with AF and a TTR below 
58 -65% derive little or no net benefit from oral anticoagula-
tion. 
29,30 The consistent performance of the ABC-stroke score </p>

<p>was strengthened by the consistent results in the subgroup of 
warfarin-treated patients with TTR ,65% during follow-up in the 
derivation cohort. The robustness of the score was further con-
firmed by the similar results in the cohort of patients without oral 
anticoagulation in the smaller external validation cohort. As prior 
stroke was the strongest risk factor in the score, it was important 
that the ABC-stroke score's performance was verified also in the 
subgroup of patients without prior stroke, indicating its usefulness 
also in the primary prevention setting. Thus, in all subgroups of 
both the derivation and validation cohort, the ABC-stroke score 
consistently achieved better prediction than the currently used 
CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc, suggesting that this risk score may be an important 
step forward as decision support concerning stroke prevention 
in AF. 
Treatment of AF, as well as other cardiovascular diseases, is mov-
ing towards more individualized patient care in which biomarkers 
have an important role in increasing the understanding of patho-
physiology, improving risk stratification, and personalizing treat-
ment. 
8,27 In this aspect, the use of the proposed ABC-stroke </p>

<p>score seems appealing because of its simplicity and the possibility 
to apply across different healthcare settings. The implementation 
of the algorithm used in the score will either be based on the nomo-
gram or, preferably, based on an electronic tool integrated into 
electronic patient records or an online tool. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>A novel risk score for predicting stroke or systemic embolism using 
two biomarkers (NT-proBNP and cTn-hs) and information on age 
and prior stroke/TIA, named ABC-stroke score (Age, Biomarkers, 
Clinical history), was developed in a large cohort and validated in 
a smaller cohort of patients with AF. The ABC-stroke risk score 
consistently performed better than presently used clinically based 
risk scores in terms of risk prediction and risk stratification, and 
may provide improved decision support in patients with AF. </p>

<p>Supplementary material </p>

<p>Supplementary material is available at European Heart Journal online. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions </p>

<p>J.L. performed statistical analysis. All authors had full access to the 
data and were involved in study design, data analyses, and interpret-
ation. Lead authors (Z.H. and L.W.) and members of the Executive 
(J.H.A., M.H., E.M.H., C.B.G., L.W.), Clinical Events (C.H. and R.D.L.), 
and Biomarker Substudy (L.W., C.B.G., A.S., E.M.H., and M.H.) com-
mittees designed the ARISTOTLE trial and supervised the conduct, 
as previously published. Members of the Executive (H.D.W. and 
L.W.) and Executive Operations (C.H. and R.A.H.S.) committees 
designed the STABILITY trial and supervised the conduct, as previ-
ously published. The first draft of the manuscript was written by </p>

<p>Figure 4 Cumulative risk of stroke by predicted 1-year ABC-</p>

<p>stroke risk group (green ,1%, blue 1 -2%, and red .2%) for 
the derivation (solid lines, n ¼ 14 701) and the external validation 
(dashed lines, n ¼ 1400) data. </p>

<p>Z. Hijazi et al. </p>



<p>Z.H., which thereafter was revised by all co-authors until agreement 
to submit was reached. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Ebba Bergman, PhD, and Martina Tillberg, MSc, at Uppsala Clinical 
Research Center, Uppsala, Sweden, provided editorial assistance, 
by funds from Bristol-Myers Squibb and Pfizer Inc. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant from The Swedish Foundation for 
Strategic Research. The ARISTOTLE trial was funded by Bristol-Myers 
Squibb, Co., Princeton, NJ, USA and Pfizer Inc., New York, NY, USA, 
and coordinated by the Duke Clinical Research Institute, Durham, 
NC, USA and Uppsala Clinical Research Center (UCR), Uppsala, 
Sweden. The STABILITY trial was sponsored by GlaxoSmithKline, 
Philadelphia, PA, USA. Funding to pay the Open Access publication 
charges for this article was provided by Uppsala Clinical Research Cen-
ter (UCR). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest: Z.H.: institutional research grants from Boehrin-
ger Ingelheim and Bristol-Myers Squibb/Pfizer; lecture fees from Boeh-
ringer Ingelheim. J.L.: nothing to report. J.H.A.: institutional research 
grants from Bristol-Myers Squibb, Merck-Schering Plough, and Regado 
Biosciences; consulting fee/honoraria from Bristol-Myers Squibb, Pfizer, 
Merck-Schering Plough, AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, Ortho-
McNeil-Janssen, Polymedix, Regado Biosciences, and Bayer. M.H.: em-
ployee of Bristol-Myers Squibb. C.H.: institutional research grants 
from AstraZeneca, Merck, GlaxoSmithKline, Roche, and Bristol-Myers 
Squibb; advisory board fees and honoraria from AstraZeneca. E.M.H.: 
consulting fees, travel support, and adjudication committee membership 
for Bristol-Myers Squibb, Daiichi Sankyo, Merck, Ortho-McNeil, John-
son &amp; Johnson, and Pfizer; lecture fees from Boehringer Ingelheim. 
R.D.L.: grants and personal fees from Bristol-Myers Squibb; grants 
from GlaxoSmithKline; personal fees from Bayer, Boehringer Ingleheim, 
and Pfizer. J.O.: institutional grant, consulting and lecture fees from 
Boehringer Ingelheim; consulting and lecture fees from Bayer, 
Bristol-Myers Squibb, and Pfizer. A.S.: institutional research grants 
from AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingelheim, and Bristol-Myers Squibb. 
R.A.H.S.: grants and non-financial support from GlaxoSmithKline. 
H.D.W.: grants and personal fees from GlaxoSmithKline and AstraZe-
neca; grants from Sanofi-Aventis, Eli Lilly, National Institute of Health, 
Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme, and Daiichi Sankyo Pharma Development. 
C.B.G.: institutional research grants from Boehringer Ingelheim, 
Bristol-Myers Squibb, GlaxoSmithKline, Medtronic Foundation, Merck 
&amp; Co., Pfizer, Sanofi-Aventis, Takeda, and The Medicines Company; con-
sulting fees from Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers Squibb, GlaxoS-
mithKline, Hoffmann-La Roche, Novartis Pharmaceutical Company, 
Lilly, Pfizer, Sanofi-Aventis, Takeda, The Medicines Company, and Astra-
Zeneca. L.W.: research grants from Bristol-Myers Squibb, AstraZeneca, 
Boehringer Ingelheim, GlaxoSmithKline, Merck &amp; Co., and Pfizer Inc.; 
consulting fee/honoraria from Abbott, AstraZeneca, Boehringer Ingel-
heim, GlaxoSmithKline, Merck &amp; Co., and Regado Biosciences. </p>



<p>ABC-stroke risk score </p>





<p>Z. Hijazi et al. </p>



</text></tei>