<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4436784" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Most current superresolution (SR) microscope techniques surpass the diffraction 
limit at the expense of temporal resolution, compromising their applications to live-cell imag-
ing. Here we describe a new SR fluorescence microscope based on confocal microscope 
optics, which we name the spinning disk superresolution microscope (SDSRM). Theoretically, 
the SDSRM is equivalent to a structured illumination microscope (SIM) and achieves a spatial 
resolution of 120 nm, double that of the diffraction limit of wide-field fluorescence micros-
copy. However, the SDSRM is 10 times faster than a conventional SIM because SR signals are 
recovered by optical demodulation through the stripe pattern of the disk. Therefore a single 
SR image requires only a single averaged image through the rotating disk. On the basis of 
this theory, we modified a commercial spinning disk confocal microscope. The improved reso-
lution around 120 nm was confirmed with biological samples. The rapid dynamics of micro-
tubules, mitochondria, lysosomes, and endosomes were observed with temporal resolutions 
of 30-100 frames/s. Because our method requires only small optical modifications, it will en-
able an easy upgrade from an existing spinning disk confocal to a SR microscope for live-cell 
imaging. </p>

<p>Fluorescence microscopy is now an essential tool for the cell biolo-
gist. However, most subcellular structures are &lt;200 nm and blurred 
by diffraction (Abbe, 1873). Superresolution (SR) techniques, such as 
photoactivatable localization microscopy (PALM; Betzig et al., 2006), 
stochastic optical reconstruction microscopy (STORM; Rust et al., 
2006), and stimulated emission depletion microscopy (STED; Hell 
and Wichmann, 1994), can extend the resolution down to ≤50 nm, </p>

<p>but usually at the expense of image acquisition time. Therefore their 
applications are rather limited to fixed specimens. In living cells, 
some cellular structures, such as endosomes and other vesicles, 
move at velocities &gt;3 μm/s (Allen et al., 1982). Thus the image ac-
quisition time needs to be &lt;&lt;30 ms for 100-nm-resolution imaging. 
From this viewpoint, PALM and STORM are not suitable for ob-
serving the rapid dynamics of subcellular structures in living cells 
because they reconstruct a single SR image from at least thousands 
of raw images, requiring &gt;10 s of imaging for a single frame. STED 
can be accelerated, but faster image acquisition requires orders of 
magnitude stronger illumination than conventional imaging, which 
risks photodamage. As a result, the practical limit of STED image 
acquisition time is longer than a few microseconds/pixel, meaning 
10 s for a 1024 × 1024-pixel field of view (Huang et al., 2009). 
A third SR technique, structured illumination microscopy (SIM; 
Heintzmann and Cremer, 1999), can extend the resolution to 
120 nm, twice the resolving power of conventional wide-field (WF) 
microscopy. Although its resolution is worse than that of the other 
two techniques, SIM can achieve faster frame rates with little photo-
damage and relatively easy multicolor imaging. One study reported 
a frame rate up to 11 Hz (Kner et al., 2009). However, this may be the 
best achievable frame rate because SIM requires 9-15 raw images 
to reconstruct a single SR image. A related technique, multifocal </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Yu-Li Wang 
Carnegie Mellon University </p>

<p>Received: Aug 18, 2014 
Revised: Feb 12, 2015 
Accepted: Feb 18, 2015 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E14-08-1287) February 25, 2015. 
Address correspondence to: Yasushi Okada (y.okada@riken.jp). 
S.H. designed and built the microscope system through discussion with Y.O. 
Y.O. prepared the samples. Both authors did the experiments and wrote the 
manuscript. 
S.H. is an employee of Olympus Corporation, which holds a patent regarding this 
SR technique. Y.O. declares no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>© 2015 Hayashi and Okada. This article is distributed by The American Society for 
Cell Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is avail-
able to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported 
Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB ® ," "The American Society for Cell Biology ® ," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell ® " are registered trademarks of The American Society for Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used: CF, confocal; DSU, disk scanning unit; MSIM, multifocal 
structured illumination microscope; SDSRM, spinning disk superresolution micro-
scope; SIM, structured illumination microscope; SR, superresolution; WF, wide 
field. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>imaging (York et al., 2013) and is fast enough to image fine struc-
tures in living cells moving at up to 6 μm/s. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Principle of SDSRM </p>

<p>The basic principle of our SR method is illustrated in Figure 1 and 
fully discussed in Supplemental Text 1. Here we use a one-dimen-
sional model and omit the magnification of the imaging system for 
simplicity. In WF microscopy, the sample is illuminated homoge-
neously, and the image contains only the signals within the cut-off 
frequency of the optical system (f c ), which determines the diffraction 
limit of the resolution. In conventional SIM (Figure 1A), a raw image 
is taken with illumination modulated sinusoidally. SR signals-namely, 
the signals of the structure beyond f c -are overlaid as Moiré interfer-
ence patterns with a frequency shift by f 0 , the spatial frequency of the </p>

<p>structured illumination microscopy (MSIM; York et al., 2012), a paral-
lelized form of image scanning microscopy (Sheppard, 1988), gen-
erates an image with ∼150-nm resolution at ∼1-Hz frame rate. Re-
cently an improved implementation of MSIM, termed instant SIM, 
was reported (York et al., 2013). A 100-Hz frame rate with ∼150-nm 
resolution was achieved by using several optical elements, such as 
two sets of microlens array and pinhole array; however, expertise is 
required to align all these optical elements correctly. 
Here we report another implementation of SIM using spinning 
disk confocal microscope optics, which we named the spinning 
disk superresolution microscope (SDSRM). We demonstrate that 
the commercial spinning disk confocal microscope can be up-
graded into a SR microscope simply by replacing the disk. It can 
achieve the same resolution as SIM, 120 nm, but with a frame rate 
of 10 ms/frame. This is the fastest frame rate reported for SR </p>



























<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>SIM 
WF </p>

<p>CF </p>

<p>SDSRM </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Principles of SIM and SDSRM. (A, B) Schematic comparison of SIM and SDSRM. (C) Fourier transform of </p>

<p>the point spread function (PSF) of SIM, 
PSF SIM (green), is a weighted sum of </p>

<p>PSF WF (black) and its frequency (f 0 )-shifted 
SR components (red). Here f c denotes the cut-off frequency of conventional WF, and f 0 denotes the spatial frequency of 
the SIM illumination pattern. (D) Fourier transform of the PSF of CF, 
PSF CF (green), is a weighted sum of 
PSF WF (black) 
and its frequency (f 0 )-shifted components (red). Here f 0 denotes the basic spatial frequency of the mask pattern, and f c ′ 
denotes the apparent cut-off frequency of CF. (E) With SDSRM, the stripe pattern is designed to increase the SR 
component (red), and the digital high-pass filter (purple) further enhances the SR component (blue). See Supplemental 
Figures S1 and S2 for details. </p>

<p>Volume 26 May 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Ultrafast superresolution live imaging | 1745 </p>

<p>(p/w) sin 2 [(w/p)π] (Supplemental Text 1). Thus 
the effective cut-off frequency (f c ′) of CF is 
limited to ∼ f 
2 0, meaning only 2-fold in-
crease in resolution (Sheppard, 1988). SR 
signals between f c ′ and f c + f 0 are buried in 
the noise and need statistical estimation for 
recovery with an algorithm such as Richard-
son-Lucy deconvolution (York et al., 2012). 
Instead, we designed the stripe pattern as w 
= 80 nm and p = 270 nm on the sample 
plane to increase the SR signals. This para-
meter is close to the theoretical maximum 
(w/p = 0.35) and increases the SR signal 
more than five times the conventional CF 
stripe pattern. Furthermore, we designed a 
digital high-pass filter to further enhance the 
SR signals (Figure 1E, Supplemental Text 2, 
and Supplemental Figure S2). Thus we can 
recover an image with fully double the reso-
lution from a single raw image of line CF with 
the designed stripe pattern. </p>

<p>Instrumentation of SDSRM </p>

<p>On the basis of this principle, we modified a 
spinning disk microscope (Figure 2A). The 
disk, light source, projection lens, and camera 
were changed from the commercial system. 
For the scan head, we used the disk 
scanning unit (DSU; Olympus, Tokyo, 
Japan), whose disk is easy to replace. The 
stripe pattern of the disk was designed to 
match the condition discussed. Here w and 
p are 500 nm and 5 μm on the sample plane, 
respectively, with the commercial DSU for 
60×/numerical aperture (NA) 1.4 objectives. 
Both w and p were narrowed to 80 and 
270 nm on the sample plane when pro-
jected through a 60× objective (Figure 2, B 
and C). This custom-designed disk was 
made by using electron lithography on a 
low-reflection chrome coat that covered a 
fused silica substrate (DU-DSR1-SP; Proto-
type Development Division, Olympus). 
The Olympus DSU system normally uses a mercury lamp as the 
illumination, but the light throughput for the illumination is only 14% 
with our custom-designed disk mainly due to the opening ratio and 
the diffraction efficiency of the disk pattern. We therefore replaced 
the light source with a laser (488 nm, 500 mW; Sapphire 488HP; 
Coherent, Santa Clara, CA). The laser beam was expanded with a 
lens to fill the aperture, and the speckle noise was removed by a 
rotating diffuser (light stirrer; NANDN, Tokyo, Japan). 
The image was projected onto a charge-coupled device (CCD) 
camera (CoolSNAP HQ; Photometrics, Tucson, AZ) or an sCMOS 
camera (ORCA FLASH 4.0v2; Hamamatsu, Hamamatsu, Japan) via a 
magnifier to satisfy the Nyquist condition for up to 100-nm resolu-
tion. The SR components in the raw image were amplified by 
Fourier-space filtering using the Custom Filter command of <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> 
(National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD). The filter (Supplemen-
tal Figure S2E) was designed as discussed in Supplemental Text 2. 
The resolution of the system was confirmed using latex beads 
(Supplemental Figure S3). In our hands, a backilluminated electron-
multiplying CCD camera (iXon897; Andor, Belfast, United Kingdom) </p>

<p>sinusoidal illumination pattern. The SR signals are demodulated by 
digital processing using three raw images taken with illumination 
patterns phase shifted by 120° each. Thus the cut-off frequency of 
SIM is extended to f c + f 0 . Usually, the same objective lens is used for 
imaging and illumination, so that f 0 can be designed up to f c (f 0 ≤ f c ). 
Hence, f c + f 0 ≤ 2f c . Namely, at most twice-better resolution can be 
achieved with SIM (Figure1C and Supplemental Figure S1A). 
In SDSRM, a stripe pattern with opening width w and period p 
is used as a modulator for illumination and demodulator for detec-
tion (Figure 1B). The stripe pattern is shifted continuously, and the 
image is integrated on the camera. Thus the same confocal mask 
pattern serves as both modulator and demodulator, and frequency-
shifted SR signals are already returned to the original position 
optically. Although this optical configuration is the same as the con-
ventional line confocal (CF) microscope, the design of the stripe 
pattern is different. In conventional CF, p is much larger than w to 
minimize cross-talk (Shimozawa et al., 2013). Therefore the ampli-
tude of the SR signals is much weaker than the WF signal (Figure 1D 
and Supplemental Figure S1B) because it is proportional to </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Configurations for the SDSRM. (A) System diagram. Excitation light from a mercury 
lamp or a laser is introduced into the illumination port of a disk-scanning unit (IX2-DSU; Olympus) 
attached to a microscope base (IX81; Olympus). The disk-scanning unit has a retractable spinning 
disk and a six-position wheel for filter sets. The spinning disk is rotated at 1800 rpm. Slit patterns 
are drawn by electron lithography. The intermediate image that passes through the disk is 
projected onto the image sensor of the camera. (B, C) The pattern drawn on the spinning disk. 
The pattern has slit openings of width w and pitch p. The slit orientation is modified to avoid 
stripe pattern artifacts caused by overlap in the stripe orientation and disk rotation. </p>





<p>Laser </p>

<p>D isk </p>

<p>O bjective Lens </p>

<p>S am ple </p>

<p>C am era </p>

<p>Tube Lens </p>

<p>M otor </p>

<p>P rojection Lens 
Illum ination Lens </p>

<p>D ichroic M irror </p>

<p>B arrier Filter </p>

<p>IX 81 </p>

<p>N D Filter </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>R otating 
D iffuser </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>tive (Figure 3, A-C), CF with the same NA 0.5 objective followed 
by deconvolution (Figure 3, D-F), SDSRM with the same NA 0.5 
objective (Figure 3, G-I) and conventional WF with NA 0.95 objec-
tive (Figure 3, J-L). Here a mercury lamp was used for illumination, 
and the images were taken with a CCD camera (CoolSNAP HQ). 
Because the diffraction limit is proportional to the inverse of 
the NA (Abbe, 1873), the NA 0.95 objective yields an image with </p>

<p>failed to extend the resolution even after the digital filtering. The SR 
components seemed to be weakened through the potential cross-
talk between the adjacent pixels. </p>

<p>Proof-of-principle experiments with a low-NA objective </p>

<p>As a proof-of-principle experiment, we examined a microtubule 
sample under four conditions: conventional WF with NA 0.5 objec-</p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Proof-of-principle experiments for the SR effect by the SDSRM on microtubules in PtK2 cells. 
(A-C) Conventional WF image with an NA 0.5 objective (UPLFL20X; Olympus). (D-F) CF image with the 
NA 0.5 objective, followed by deconvolution with the Richardson-Lucy algorithm. See Supplemental Figure S4 
for results with other deconvolution algorithms. (G-I) SDSRM image with the NA 0.5 objective. (J-L) Conventional 
WF image with NA 0.95 objective (UPLSAPO40×2; Olympus). B, E, H, and K show higher-magnification views of 
A, D, G, and J for the areas inside the rectangle in A. Panels C, F, I, and L show pixel intensity across the microtubule 
bundle shown between the arrows in B, and the corresponding Gaussian fits with estimated full-width at half-maximum. 
Bars, 1 μm (A, D, G, J), 0.5 μm (B, E, H, K). </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>J </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>-1 -0.5 0 0.5 1 </p>

<p>-1 -0.5 0 0.5 1 </p>

<p>-1 -0.5 0 0.5 1 
Lateral position (µm) </p>

<p>Intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.63 µm </p>

<p>0.39 µm </p>

<p>0.40 µm </p>

<p>WF, NA0.5 </p>

<p>SDSRM, NA0.5 </p>

<p>WF, NA0.95 </p>

<p>D 
E 
F </p>

<p>CF+DC, NA0.5 </p>

<p>D 
E </p>

<p>CF+DC, NA0.5 </p>

<p>0.53 µm </p>

<p>-1 -0.5 0 0.5 1 </p>

<p>Volume 26 May 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Ultrafast superresolution live imaging | 1747 </p>

<p>Fast SR live imaging of endosomes </p>

<p>The initial experiments with the CCD camera described earlier 
confirmed that SDSRM can achieve ∼120-nm resolution, twice bet-
ter than with conventional WF microscopy, even with the live bio-
logical specimen. Next we tried a faster frame rate by replacing 
the camera with sCMOS camera (ORCA FLASH 4.0v2), which can 
achieve a frame rate up to 100 frames/s, faster than the video rate. 
A silicone oil immersion objective lens (UPLSAPO60XS, NA1.3; 
Olympus) was used to minimize the spherical aberrations by the 
refraction index mismatch. 
As the proof of principle of fast SR imaging, we chose endo-
somes and lysosomes, which are known to be highly dynamic. 
They often move at &gt;1 μm/s, and imaging at faster than the 
video rate is required for capturing their dynamics without 
motion blur. The dynamics of lysosomes was observed with 
lysosomal-associated membrane protein 1 (Lamp1)-EYFP. The 
images were taken with 20-ms exposure. A 100-ms-interval time 
series of two lysosomes is shown in Figure 5. They sometimes 
move at as fast as 10 μm/s; the lumen is still clearly visualized, 
demonstrating that the rapid frame rate enabled SR imaging 
without motion blur (Supplemental Movie S2). Similarly, the 
rapid dynamics of recycling endosomes including a fusion 
event was clearly visualized by 100-Hz SR live imaging (10-ms 
exposure) of Rab11a-venus (Figure 6 and Supplemental 
Movie S3). </p>

<p>1.9-times-higher resolution than the NA 0.5 objective. Nonethe-
less, the image obtained by the SDSRM with the NA 0.5 objective 
was essentially the same as the image obtained by conventional 
WF with the NA 0.95 objective, indicating that the SDSRM is a 
real SR, which improves resolution by a factor of ∼2 compared 
with conventional WF. Note that deconvolution of the CF image 
did improve resolution over WF but failed to achieve full 2× reso-
lution (Figure 3, D-F). We tried several different deconvolution 
software packages, but all gave similar results (Supplemental 
Figure S4). </p>

<p>SR live imaging of microtubules </p>

<p>We next examined whether our SDSRM can resolve biological 
structures &lt;200 nm with a high-NA objective (UPLSAPO60XO, 
NA1.35; Olympus) in living cells. Microtubules were stained by ex-
pressing enhanced yellow fluorescent protein (EYFP)-tagged β-
tubulin. The raw images were taken by a CCD camera (CoolSNAP 
HQ) at 5 frames/s with laser excitation 20 W/cm 2 at the sample. As 
shown in Figure 4, the width of a single microtubule image is blurred 
to 260 nm (full-width at half-maximum) in a conventional WF image, 
which is improved by a factor of 2 to 120 nm with the SDSRM 
(Figure 4C). A pair of microtubules with 250-nm distance was not 
separated in the conventional WF image but was clearly separated 
with the SDSRM (Figure 4D). Furthermore, the dynamics of microtu-
bules was recorded at 5 frames/s (Supplemental Movie S1). </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: SR live imaging of microtubules. (A) Conventional WF image of Vero cell expressing β-tubulin-EYFP. 
A 60× objective with NA 1.35 (UPLSAPO60XO; Olympus) was used for imaging. (B) SDSRM image of the same 
view field. The excitation laser power on the sample was 20 W/cm 2 . The exposure time was 200 ms with a 
conventional CCD camera (CoolSNAP HQ). The raw images were high-pass filtered to enhance the SR 
components. (C) Sectional plots of pixel intensities across a single microtubule (1 in A). (D) Sectional plots of 
pixel intensities across a microtubule doublet with an interval of 250 nm (2 in A). Bar, 2 μm. See Supplemental 
Movie S1. </p>

<p>120nm </p>

<p>260nm </p>

<p>conven onal </p>

<p>SDSRM </p>

<p>SDSRM </p>

<p>conven onal </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: SDSRM images of rapid dynamics of recycling endosomes 
stained with Rab11a-venus. The images were taken with a 60×/NA 1.3 
silicone oil immersion objective (UPLSAPO60XS). The excitation laser 
power on the sample was 100 W/cm 2 . The frame rate was 100 
frames/s with 10-ms exposure. The raw images were high-pass 
filtered to enhance the SR components, followed by deconvolution 
by the CMLE algorithm (Huygens) to reduce noise. Seven consecutive 
frames of the yellow region in A are shown in B, which shows the 
fusion and the following movement of recycling endosomes. Bars, 
5 μm (A), 0.5 μm (B). See Supplemental Movie S3. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>0 ms </p>

<p>10 ms </p>

<p>20 ms </p>

<p>30 ms </p>

<p>40 ms </p>

<p>50 ms </p>

<p>60 ms </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: SDSRM images of rapidly moving lysosomes stained with 
Lamp1-EYFP. Time-lapse images were taken with a 60×/NA 1.3 
silicone oil immersion objective (UPLSAPO60XS; Olympus) and a 
sCMOS camera (ORCA FLASH 4.0 v2). The excitation laser power on 
the sample was 100 W/cm 2 . The frame rate was 10 frames/s with 
20-ms exposure and 80-ms interval. The raw images were high-pass 
filtered to enhance the SR components, followed by deconvolution 
by the Classic Maximum Likelihood Estimation (CMLE) algorithm 
(Huygens, SVI, Hilversum, Netherlands) to reduce noise. The 
dynamics of two lysosomes are shown in the insets. Bars, 5 and 2 μm 
(insets). See Supplemental Movie S2. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 
4 5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>5 
4 </p>

<p>and branching. Sometimes a thin tubular vesicle was released from 
the protrusion (yellow arrowhead in Figure 8), which suggests that 
the protrusion would be pinched off to form MDVs. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we demonstrated that the spinning disk confocal mi-
croscope has potential as an alternative implementation of SIM. 
Conventional SIM requires several modulated images to retrieve SR 
components by demodulation in the Fourier space, but it has higher 
photon efficiency because the signal is retrieved without a mask. In 
contrast, the confocal aperture works as a mask to demodulate the 
SR components in the confocal microscope. To obtain stronger SR 
component signals, a smaller confocal aperture is required. How-
ever, this comes at the expense of signal intensity because with a 
smaller confocal aperture, most of the photons from the sample are 
rejected at the confocal aperture. Here we overcome this problem 
by specially designing the mask pattern on the disk. The opening 
was narrowed to λ/5 while keeping the aperture ratio as 30%. This 
aperture ratio is more than three times higher than for the conven-
tional spinning disk confocal, and this high light throughput enabled 
100-Hz SR imaging with moderate excitation power (20-40 W/cm 2 ). 
Owing to this high aperture ratio, however, the optical sectioning 
capability is compromised. The stray light from the out-of-the-focus 
specimen cannot be rejected efficiently, and the axial resolution is 
close to that of conventional WF imaging. The axial resolution can 
be enhanced by reducing the aperture ratio but at the expense of 
light throughput or signal intensity. A longer exposure time would 
be required. </p>

<p>SR imaging of mitochondrion-derived vesicles </p>

<p>Finally, we applied the SDSRM for the imaging of recently re-
ported but poorly characterized organelles, mitochondrion-
derived vesicles (MDVs). They are proposed to be formed by bud-
ding of the mitochondria outer membrane and to mediate the 
transport of damaged proteins from mitochondria to peroxisomes 
(Neuspiel et al., 2008). However, it has been difficult to examine 
the structure and dynamics of the outer membrane of mitochon-
dria due to the limited resolution of light microscopy. We there-
fore examined the mitochondrial outer membrane first by staining 
with anti-TOMM20 antibody (Figure 7). The lumen of the mito-
chondria is barely visible with conventional WF imaging but is 
clearly observed with SDSRM as well as STED (Figure 7D). Unex-
pectedly, the SR image of mitochondrial outer membrane showed 
that the size of the lumen of mitochondria is highly variable even 
in a single cell. We also found thin protrusions from thick mitochon-
dria. Only the outer membrane is apparently protruded, and the 
lumen is thin and unclear even with the STED SR image (Figure 7E). 
In addition to the mitochondria and the thin protrusions, many 
vesicular or tubular structures were also stained with TOMM20 an-
tibody. They would correspond to MDVs as reported previously 
(Neuspiel et al., 2008). 
We next expressed TOMM20-mEmerald and used the SDSRM 
with exposure 30 ms and excitation 20 W/cm 2 . The 120-nm-resolu-
tion live imaging at video rate with SDSRM enabled us to observe 
not only the mitochondrial fusion event, but also the rapid dynamics 
of MDVs (Figure 8 and Supplemental Movie S4). The protrusions of 
the outer membrane were highly dynamic: elongating, shrinking, </p>

<p>Volume 26 May 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Ultrafast superresolution live imaging | 1749 </p>

<p>first visualization of MDV formation from mitochondrial protrusions. 
The frame rate of our system is mainly limited by the rotation speed 
of the disk (1800 rpm), which would be possible to accelerate 
10 times to achieve a frame rate of 1 kHz. This would enable imag-
ing of rapid processes such as neurotransmitter release at the syn-
apse (Südhof, 2013) 
In summary, the spinning disk confocal-based implementation 
of SIM described here is easy to implement and robust to use. An 
existing spinning disk confocal can easily be upgraded. Thus we 
hope that this method will not only open the way for SR live-cell 
imaging with high temporal resolution, but also help to popularize 
SR microscopy. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Microscopy setup for SDSRM </p>

<p>The microscope setup for SDSRM (Figure 2A) is based on the disk-
scanning confocal microscope system, which includes an inverted 
microscope base (IX81; Olympus) and a disk-scanning unit (IX2-
DSU; Olympus). A combination of a cooled CCD (CoolSNAP HQ) 
and a mercury lamp with a light guide (U-HGLGPS, Olympus; not 
shown in Figure 2A) was used for the initial experiments (Figure 3 
and Supplemental Figure S3). The light source was then replaced 
with a laser (Sapphire488HP; Coherent, Santa Clara, CA) and a </p>

<p>Even with the high-light-throughput disk pattern, stronger excita-
tion light was required than for typical fluorescence live-cell imaging. 
Twice-better resolution in two dimensions means one-fourth signal 
intensity per pixel, and only 30% of the signal passes through the 
disk to reach the camera. Thus an at least 12-times stronger signal is 
required. Furthermore, even higher signal-to-noise ratio is required 
than for conventional WF imaging because the weak SR compo-
nents are enhanced by high-pass filtering, which can also enhance 
the noise. In this study, therefore, most of the images were acquired 
with excitation light intensity of 20-40 W/cm 2 , which is nearly 
100 times stronger than for typical fluorescence live-cell imaging 
(0.1-1 W/cm 2 ). Note, however, that this excitation beam light inten-
sity is comparable to that for typical SIM imaging and &gt;100 times 
weaker than for STED. Furthermore, the excitation light intensity can 
be further reduced for light-sensitive samples by elongating the ex-
posure time, although the temporal resolution is compromised. 
As applications of live-cell SR imaging, we observed the dynam-
ics of microtubules, lysosomes, recycling endosomes, and mito-
chondria. The short exposure time (&lt;30 ms) enabled SR live imag-
ing without motion blur, and the fine structures of rapidly moving 
organelles were captured, such as the fusion and fission events of 
the outer membrane of mitochondria and the rapid dynamics of 
mitochondrial protrusions and MDVs. To our knowledge, this is the </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: The outer membrane of mitochondria stained with anti-TOMM20 antibody. (A) Conventional WF image. 
(B) SDSRM image. (C) STED image. (D, E) Sectional plots of pixel intensities across a thick mitochondrial region (red, D) 
and a thin protrusion (yellow, E). Black, red, and blue curves show conventional WF, SDSRM, and STED, respectively. WF 
(A) and SDSRM (B) images were taken with a 60×/NA 1.3 silicone oil immersion objective (UPLSAPO60XS); STED images 
(C) were taken with a 100×/NA 1.40 objective (HC PL APO 100×/1.40 OIL STED WHITE; Leica). SDSRM and STED 
images were postprocessed by deconvolution (CMLE, Huygens) to reduce noise and enhance contrast. Bar, 5 μm. </p>

<p>WF 
SDSRM 
S TED </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>0 
500 
1000 
1500 
2000 
2500 </p>

<p>Position (nm) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>Intensity (au) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>Intensity (au) </p>

<p>Position (nm) </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1400 
1200 </p>

<p>E 
D </p>

<p>Protrusion (yellow) 
Mitochondria (red) </p>

<p>WF </p>

<p>STED </p>

<p>SDSRM M </p>

<p>WF </p>

<p>STED </p>

<p>SDSRM M </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>The disk-scanning unit has a spinning disk and a filter-set wheel 
changer. The spinning disk is put on the primary image plane for 
confocal imaging. The disk was made by using electron lithography 
on a low-reflection chrome coat that covered a fused silica substrate 
(DU-DSR1-SP; Olympus). The width and the pitch of the confocal slit 
apertures were 80 and 270 nm, respectively, as discussed in the 
main text. 
For comparisons with WF, the disk was removed and a neutral 
density filter with a transmission factor of 6% (ND6) was put into the 
illumination path to adjust the image brightness. The image was 
projected onto the camera via a 5× magnifier and taken by 2 × 2 
binning mode. Thus the pixel size of the specimen is 43 nm with a 
60× objective lens, satisfying the Nyquist condition for up to 100-nm 
resolution. The software package <rs id="software-1" type="software">MetaMorph</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>, 
Sunnyvale, CA) was used to control the system and for acquisition of 
the image. </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection </p>

<p>The cells were obtained from Health Science Research Resources 
Bank (Osaka, Japan) and maintained at 37°C in DMEM with 10% 
fetal bovine serum (Life Technologies; Thermo Fisher Scientific, 
Waltham, MA) at 5% CO 2 . The cells were grown on glass coverslips 
(No. 1S; Matsunami, Osaka, Japan) for immunofluorescence stain-
ing. For live imaging, cells were transfected with TransFectin (Bio-
Rad, Hercules, CA) and plated onto a glass-bottom dish (No. 1.5; 
MatTek, Ashland, MA). The medium was changed to L15 medium 
with 10% fetal bovine serum but without phenol red (Life Technolo-
gies) before imaging. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence staining </p>

<p>For microtubule staining (Figure 3), the cells were fixed with 2% 
paraformaldehyde and 0.1% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M cacodylate 
buffer and 4% sucrose, followed by permeabilization with 0.5% 
Triton X-100. Nonspecific binding was blocked with 2% bovine se-
rum albumin (BSA, Fraction V; Roche, Schweiz, Switzerland) before 
staining with anti-β-tubulin antibody (MAB3408; EMD-Millipore, 
Billerica, MA) and Alexa Fluor 488-labeled secondary antibody (Life 
Technologies). For mitochondrial staining (Figure 7), the cells were 
fixed with cold methanol (−20°C) and stained with anti-TOMM20 
antibody (ab56783; Abcam, Cambridge, MA), followed by Alexa 
Fluor 488-labeled secondary antibody. The stained cells were 
mounted with ProLong Gold (Life Technologies). </p>

<p>STED imaging </p>

<p>For confirmation of the subdiffraction structures, some samples 
were observed with an STED microscope system (SP8-STED 3X; 
Leica Microsystems, Wetzlar, Germany) with the following settings. 
The acousto-optic tunable filter was 3% for 480 nm (excitation) and 
95% for 592 nm (depletion). The gate for the detector was opened 
from 1.5 to 6 ns after the excitation pulse. The sample was scanned 
at 400 Hz with 8× line averaging. The pinhole was closed to 68 μm 
(0.5 Airy unit at 520 nm). </p>

<p>square-core fiber (ST175SQE(12); Mitsubishi Cable, Tokyo, Japan) 
with a vibrating motor (not shown in Figure 2A; used for images in 
Figure 4) or a single-mode fiber (kineFLEX; Qioptiq, Asslar, Germany) 
with a rotating diffuser (light stirrer; NANDN; used for images in 
Figures 5-8). Finally, the CCD camera was replaced with an sCMOS 
camera (ORCA FLASH 4.0v2) for faster frame rates (for Figures 5-8). </p>

<p>FIGURE 8: Time-lapse SDSRM images of the dynamics of the outer 
membrane of mitochondria stained with TOMM20-mEmelard. The 
lumen of mitochondria is clearly imaged during the fusion of two 
mitochondria (white arrow). The rapid dynamics of the outer 
membrane protrusion (red arrow) and tubular vesicles released from 
the outer membrane protrusion (yellow arrowhead) are also clearly 
recorded. The images were taken with a 60×/NA 1.3 silicone oil 
immersion objective (UPLSAPO60XS). The excitation laser power on 
the sample was 20 W/cm 2 . The frame rate was 10 frames/s with 30-ms 
exposure and 70-ms interval. The raw images were high-pass filtered 
to enhance the SR components, followed by deconvolution by the 
CMLE algorithm (Huygens) to reduce noise (Supplemental Figure S5). 
Bar, 2 μm. See Supplemental Movie S4. </p>

<p>0 ms </p>

<p>100 ms </p>

<p>200 ms </p>

<p>300 ms </p>

<p>400 ms </p>

<p>500 ms </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We are grateful to S. Niwa and N. Hirokawa (University of Tokyo, 
Tokyo, Japan) for the plasmids (tubulin, Lamp1, and Rab11a); M. 
Davidson for the plasmid mEmerald-TOMM20-N-10 (#54282; 
Addgene); K. Abe (Olympus) for discussion and assistance; S. Xu, 
J. Asada, M. Komeno, and M. Kakiuchi (Quantitative Biology Cen-
ter) for technical and secretarial assistance; and D. Priest (Quanti-
tative Biology Center) for editing the manuscript. Part of this work </p>

<p>Volume 26 May 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Ultrafast superresolution live imaging | 1751 </p>



</text></tei>