<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4849203" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 
License, which permits use and distribution in any 
medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the 
use is non-commercial and no modifications or 
adaptations are made. </p>

<p>Significant outcomes </p>

<p>• Patients with a relatively low symptom load appeared to be at an increased likelihood of having their </p>

<p>referrals for compulsory mental health care disallowed. </p>

<p>• Reported suicide risk and some less severe diagnostic groups were associated with above average dis-</p>

<p>allowance rates. </p>

<p>• The likelihood of disallowance seemed more dependent on patient and admission factors than on </p>

<p>referring agent competence. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>• Time lapse between referral and the specialist's assessment probably affected the outcome of several </p>

<p>compulsory referrals, but was not registered. </p>

<p>• Referring agent competence was specified by a variable with uncertain validity. </p>

<p>410 </p>

<p>Acta Psychiatr Scand 2016: 133: 410-418 
Compulsory mental health care has a long tradi-
tion in psychiatry. It is practised under the pre-
sumed ethical justification that the negative 
consequences of compulsory mental health care on 
autonomy, integrity and comfort are outweighed 
by the benefits of treatment or protection (1). 
There is considerable interdisciplinary agreement 
that under certain conditions involuntary measures 
are justifiable (2). However, there is yet no interna-
tional consensus on which conditions to apply, in 
spite of attempts to standardize the practice (3). 
The subject remains controversial. 
In several countries, compulsory mental health 
care may be established if a severely mentally ill 
person is at risk to himself or others or has a press-
ing need of treatment (4). In Norway, severely 
mentally ill patients may be placed under such care 
when voluntary treatment has either failed or been 
deemed futile. Two medical examinations are 
required. Both must conclude that the patient is (i) 
a danger to themselves and/or (ii) a danger to 
others and/or (iii) in a condition that is likely to 
worsen substantially, or their chance of recovery is 
reduced in the absence of treatment (5). The first 
examination often takes place in primary health 
care and is performed by a physician unaffiliated 
to the admitting institution (6). If the physician 
finds the requirements met, the patient is referred 
and admitted, by force if necessary. The second 
medical examination takes place at the admitting 
institution. Within 24 h after admission, a psychia-
trist or an authorized specialist in clinical psychol-
ogy, hereafter referred to as 'specialist', must 
decide whether to establish compulsory mental 
health care or not. This decision is based on the 
findings from the examination, in addition to 
information from observations in the ward, find-
ings from previous examinations and other avail-
able information. If the specialist decides not to 
establish it, the patient is admitted voluntarily or 
discharged (Norwegian underkjenning). Hereafter, 
such outcome will be referred to as 'disallowed 
referral' for compulsory mental health care or as 
'disallowance'. 
Two Norwegian studies have shown that 31-
45% of referrals for compulsory mental health care 
are disallowed (6, 7). These rates are considerably 
lower for referrals from the specialist psychiatric 
health service compared to, for example, emer-
gency primary healthcare clinics (6, 8). Similarly, 
mentally ill individuals, who on decision of ambu-
lance personnel were involuntarily transported to 
an Australian mental health facility for psychiatric 
assessment and treatment, had three times lower </p>

<p>odds of involuntary admission than patients 
detained by medical practitioners (9). The likeli-
hood of disallowance thus seems associated with 
features of the referring agent, among which aver-
age professional expertise appears to be of some 
importance. 
Although some conditions result in disallowance 
because they have a natural course of quick clinical 
improvement, reports of high disallowance rates 
that vary with referring agent raise suspicion that 
not all disallowed referrals are warranted. Knowl-
edge of factors associated with disallowance might 
therefore increase assessment proficiency. </p>

<p>Aims of the study </p>

<p>This study aimed to examine factors associated 
with disallowance of referrals for compulsory men-
tal health care. A particular focus was on discover-
ing relations between disallowance and referring 
agents. </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>A subset of data from the prospective, longitudinal 
cohort study 'Suicidality in Psychiatric Emergency 
Admissions' was retrieved for use in this study. 
'Suicidality in Psychiatric Emergency Admissions' 
was conducted at a 19-bed psychiatric emergency 
unit (6). The emergency unit was part of the Psychi-
atric Department of Haukeland University Hospi-
tal, a state-governed hospital in Bergen, Norway, 
with a catchment area of approximately 
400 000 inhabitants. The subset included data on 
admissions for compulsory mental health care that 
were conducted between 1 May 2005 and 30 April 
2008. Admissions of patients who were sentenced 
to civil commitment or transferred from other 
wards or institutions were excluded since disal-
lowance was not a possible outcome in those cases. 
In this time period, approximately 95% of all adult 
patients in the catchment area who were referred 
for emergency psychiatric admission were received 
at this psychiatric emergency unit (6). They were 
assessed and given emergency treatment at the unit 
before discharge or transfer to other wards for 
long-term treatment. The remaining 5% were well-
known patients who were directly admitted to open 
wards, without an initial stay at the emergency unit. </p>

<p>Measurements </p>

<p>Data on the following variables were retrieved 
from the complete data set: </p>



<p>Disallowance in compulsory mental care referrals </p>

<p>• Descriptive patient information and sociodemo-</p>

<p>graphic conditions: gender, age and ethnicity. </p>

<p>• Referral and admission: referring agent and </p>

<p>legal basis for in-patient stay. </p>

<p>• From assessments made upon admission to the </p>

<p>psychiatric emergency unit: «Global Assessment 
Scale Split version» for symptoms (GAF S), 
«Global Assessment Scale Split version» for 
function (GAF F) (10, 11), alcohol or drug 
intoxication and suicide risk as factor contribut-
ing to the admission. </p>

<p>• Diagnoses given upon discharge. </p>

<p>The split version of GAF is derived from the tra-
ditional GAF scale and consists of two dimen-
sions, GAF S and GAF F, which reflect subtle 
differences in clinical impairment (12). The split 
version is routinely used as initial assessment tool 
in all psychiatric hospital admissions in the Norwe-
gian mental health service. 
All patients were given an enrolment code on 
their first admission in the registration period. Any 
subsequent admission was numbered and linked to 
this enrolment code, which allowed tracing of 
patients' consecutive admissions. 
Diagnoses were given according to the ICD-10 
coding system (13). They were aggregated into 
groups, in accordance with existing ICD-10 groups: 
mental and behavioural disorders due to psychoac-
tive substance use (F10-F19), schizophrenia, schizo-
typal and delusional disorders (F20-F29), mood 
[affective] disorders (F30-F39), neurotic, stress-
related and somatoform disorders (F40-F48) and 
disorders of adult personality and behaviour (F60-
F69). The remaining diagnostic groups were clus-
tered into 'other psychiatric diagnoses'. 
Up to three diagnoses were given upon dis-
charge: primary, secondary and tertiary. Previous 
analyses on these data have shown that all of the 
diagnoses were potentially important to the admis-
sion (6). Therefore, diagnoses were dichotomized 
into 'given' or 'not given', for example 'no mood 
disorder' or 'mood disorder as primary, secondary 
or tertiary diagnose'. 
A variable, which represented the assessment 
competence of the referring agents, was necessary 
for allowing analysis on the impact of this feature 
on disallowance likelihood. Therefore, each refer-
ring agent was separately scored on three key fac-
tors and placed in succession according to their 
summarized score (Table 1). 
Previous knowledge of the patient was chosen as 
a key factor due to its assumed importance as a fac-
tor in assessing referrals for compulsory admission 
(6, 14). Additionally, the opportunity to ensure fol-
low-up of the patient, for example by observation </p>

<p>when in doubt, could affect the urgency of a final 
decision and was therefore also included as a key 
factor. Services that were expected to hold similar 
properties were merged to form single categories or 
competence levels, as shown under 'included ser-
vices' in Table 1. Emergency specialist psychiatric 
care was held apart from other specialist psychi-
atric services because, although holding the same 
level of expertise, clinicians in this service would 
normally have no or scarce previous knowledge of 
the patient and no opportunity for follow-up. 
Emergency primary health care was in many cases 
staffed by general practitioners, and Table 1 thus 
reflects a similar level of expertise in these two 
agents. However, the circumstances in the two ser-
vices differ substantially as previous knowledge of 
patient and follow-up availability is absent or 
scarce in emergency primary health care, whilst 
general practitioners mostly know and are obliged 
to follow up their enlisted patients. For the analy-
ses, the resulting table was applied as a scale vari-
able, hereafter referred to as 'referring agent 
competence' or simply 'competence'. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>IBM <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 22</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., 
Armonk, NY, USA), was used for descriptive 
statistics, including mean, standard deviation, fre-
quencies and cross-tabulation analyses with Pear-
son's chi-squared test. Mplus <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">7.2</rs> (Muth en &amp; 
Muth en, Los Angeles, CA, USA) was used for 
structural multilevel modelling, with logistic 
regression to estimate associations between the 
included predictors and the dichotomous outcome 
variable, disallowance. Admission-specific predic-
tors were analysed as level 1 variables, whilst level 
2 included static patient factors. Hence, at level 2, </p>

<p>Table 1. Referring agents placed in succession according to their expected average 
competence, based on expected psychiatric expertise, previous knowledge of 
patient and availability of follow-up </p>

<p>Referring agent </p>

<p>Included 
services </p>

<p>Psychiatric 
expertise </p>

<p>Previous 
knowledge 
of 
patient </p>

<p>Follow-up 
available </p>

<p>Specialist medical 
and surgical care </p>

<p>Hospital services 
Prison services </p>

<p>À 
À 
À </p>

<p>Emergency primary 
health care </p>

<p>+ 
À 
À </p>

<p>Emergency specialist 
psychiatric care </p>

<p>++ 
À 
À </p>

<p>Regular general 
practice </p>

<p>+ 
+ + 
+ </p>

<p>Specialist psychiatric 
care </p>

<p>Out-patient care 
In-patient care </p>

<p>++ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>À = below average; + = above average; ++ = considerably above average. </p>



<p>Fuglseth et al. </p>

<p>patient-dependent mean values for disallowance 
were used in the statistical analyses. Competence 
and GAF F were expected to be predicted by other 
variables and were therefore modelled as interme-
diating variables. The standardized and unstan-
dardized regression coefficients were reported as 
well as odds ratio values for the dichotomous dis-
allowance variable. Robust maximum likelihood 
estimator was used to adjust for deviations from 
normal distributions. 
By a linear regression function, GAF F was 
regressed on GAF S, admission count, suicide risk 
and diagnosis variables. The GAF variables were 
originally continuous variables ranging from 0 to 
100. Ahead of the multivariate analyses, the range 
in these variables was reduced by dividing by 10. 
Competence level was predicted by GAF F and 
GAF S, alcohol or drug intoxication, some diag-
nostic groups and cross-level interactions between 
gender and GAF scores. The main outcome vari-
able, disallowance, was predicted by competence, 
GAF S, diagnostic group variables, suicide risk 
and alcohol or drug intoxication. 
Gender-specific interaction terms were tested, 
such as age, competence, GAF F and GAF S to 
check whether associations were gender specific. In 
addition, interaction terms between suicide risk 
and the diagnostic group variables were estimated 
to investigate whether the statistical effect of suicide 
risk differed between diagnostic groups. At level 2, 
disallowance was predicted by gender and ethnic-
ity. Non-statistical parameter values were removed 
in a backward stepwise procedure, followed by re-
estimation until a model consisting of only statisti-
cally significant predictors was obtained. 
The project was approved by the Regional Com-
mittee for Medical and Health Research Ethics, 
the Norwegian Social Science Data Services and 
the Norwegian Directorate of Health. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In the study period, there were 2889 admissions of 
patients who were referred for compulsory mental 
health care, of which 2813 were eligible for disal-
lowance. Of these, 764 (27.2%) were disallowed. 
Mean age on admission was 41.2 years (range 17-
96, SD 16.5). Number of admissions per patient 
ranged from 1 to 31, with a median value of 1. The 
mean value of GAF S was 31.8 in non-disallowed 
admissions (range 3-80, SD 9.8) and 38.0 in admis-
sions that resulted in disallowance (range 5-80, SD 
11.4). GAF F had a mean value of 34.6 in non-dis-
allowed admissions (range 3-81, SD 11.0) and 40.1 
in admissions that resulted in disallowance (range 
1-91, SD 12.2). </p>

<p>The results presented in Table 2 show that 
disallowance rates differed between groups with 
regard to ethnicity, competence level, alcohol or 
drug intoxication, diagnostic group and suicide 
risk. Suicide risk, clinically apparent alcohol or 
drug intoxication and several diagnostic groups 
were associated with higher than average rates of 
disallowance. Non-Norwegian ethnicity and 
schizophrenia spectrum disorders, however, were 
associated with lower than average rates of disal-
lowance. The table showed a reduction in disal-
lowance frequency with each increase in referring 
agent competence level. 
Results from the multilevel analysis, presented 
in Fig. 1, show that the explained variance for dis-
allowance was 30% on the admission level and 
21% on the patient level. Low referring agent com-
petence, high GAF S score, observed alcohol or 
drug intoxication, reported suicide risk, the pres-
ence of neurotic, stress-related and somatoform 
disorders, personality disorders and other non-spe-
cified diagnoses were associated with above aver-
age disallowance rate. 
Schizophrenia spectrum diagnoses and affective 
disorders were associated with below average disal-
lowance rate. GAF F, with an explained variance 
of 37%, exerted no significant direct effect on dis-
allowance rate, whilst a diagnosis of substance use 
disorders exerted no significant effect at all. The 
association between suicide risk and disallowance 
was moderated by the personality disorder vari-
able. Hence, the magnitude of the association 
between suicide risk and disallowance was weaker 
in admissions of patients with personality disor-
ders than in admissions of patients without. The 
average disallowance rate was higher in admissions 
of male patients than female patients, and higher 
in admissions of Norwegian than non-Norwegian 
patients. 
Competence acted as an intermediating variable 
for several other variables on disallowance. Simi-
larly, GAF F was an intermediating variable for 
several effects on competence. However, the 
explained variance for competence was a modest 
7%, and given its limited total effect on disal-
lowance, each of the mediated effects represented 
negligible total effects on disallowance rate. 
Three cross-level interaction terms were found 
statistically significant: gender moderated the effect 
of GAF S on competence and GAF F. In admis-
sions of males, the correlation between GAF S and 
competence remained unaffected by the modera-
tion. However, in admissions of females, the mod-
eration exerted a positive effect, which resulted in a 
positive correlation. The gender variable also mod-
erated the effect of GAF F on competence. This </p>



<p>Disallowance in compulsory mental care referrals </p>

<p>correlation remained unaffected in admissions of 
males, but in admissions of females a negative 
moderating effect was exerted, which yielded an 
inverse correlation. The analyses uncovered no 
other interaction terms related to competence. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study showed that decreased symptom load, 
as expressed by GAF Symptom, was the strongest 
predictor of disallowance. Referring agent </p>

<p>competence was a significant, but modest predic-
tor. Other factors that predicted disallowance were 
suicide risk, alcohol or drug intoxication, personal-
ity disorders and neurotic, stress-related and 
somatoform disorders. 
According to the results, there was a substan-
tial association between GAF S score and likeli-
hood of disallowance. Oppositely, the association 
between GAF F score and disallowance, which 
was significant according to the bivariate analy-
ses, was non-significant according to the multiple </p>

<p>Table 2. Results from descriptive and bivariate analyses, depending on patient and admission factors. Descriptive results in the 'total' column. Results from bivariate analyses 
on disallowance rate in the two 'disallowance' columns </p>

<p>Total 
Disallowance </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>(n = 2813) </p>

<p>Yes 
No </p>

<p>(n = 764, 
27.2%) </p>

<p>(n = 2049, 
72.8%) </p>

<p>n 
% ( †) 
n 
% ( ‡) 
n 
% ( ‡) </p>

<p>Sex 
0.050 
Male 
1453 
51.8 
418 
28.7 
1036 
71.3 
Female 
1360 
48.2 
346 
25.5 
1013 
74.5 
Ethnicity 
&lt;0.001 
Norwegian 
2581 
91.8 
729 
28.2 
1852 
71.8 
Non-Norwegian 
232 
8.2 
35 
15.1 
197 
84.9 
Suicide risk 
&lt;0.001 
No known suicide risk 
1173 
47.5 
188 
16.0 
985 
84.0 
Suicide ideations, but no plan 
601 
24.3 
225 
37.4 
376 
62.6 
Suicide plans 
325 
13.2 
154 
47.4 
171 
52.6 
Self-harm 
370 
15.0 
150 
40.5 
220 
59.5 
Alcohol or drug intoxication (n = 2774)* 
&lt;0.001 
No signs 
2188 
78.9 
526 
24.0 
1662 
76.0 
Possibly influenced by alcohol or drugs 
361 
13.0 
103 
28.5 
258 
71.5 
Apparently influenced by alcohol or drugs 
225 
8.1 
122 
54.2 
103 
45.8 
Competence (n = 2469)* 
&lt;0.001 
Specialist medical and surgical services (hospital/prison) 
328 
11.7 
108 
32.9 
220 
67.1 
Emergency primary health care 
1436 
51.0 
447 
31.1 
989 
68.9 
Emergency specialist psychiatric care 
185 
6.6 
55 
29.7 
130 
70.3 
Regular general practice 
404 
14.4 
88 
21.8 
316 
78.2 
Specialist psychiatric care (out-/in-patient) 
460 
16.3 
66 
14.3 
394 
85.7 
Diagnostic group 
Mental and behavioural disorders due to psychoactive substance use (F10 -F19) 
&lt;0.001 
Yes 
682 
24.2 
273 
40.0 
409 
60.0 
No 
2131 
75.8 
491 
23.0 
1640 
77.0 
Schizophrenia, schizotypal and delusional disorders (F20-F29) 
&lt;0.001 
Yes 
1023 
36.4 
105 
10.3 
918 
89.7 
No 
1790 
63.6 
659 
36.8 
1131 
63.2 
Mood [affective] disorders (F30 -F39) 
0.060 
Yes 
806 
28.7 
239 
29.7 
567 
70.3 
No 
2007 
71.3 
525 
26.2 
1482 
73.8 
Neurotic, stress-related and somatoform disorders (F40 -F48) 
&lt;0.001 
Yes 
354 
12.6 
153 
43.2 
201 
56.8 
No 
2459 
87.4 
611 
24.8 
1848 
75.2 
Disorders of adult personality and behaviour (F60 -F69) 
&lt;0.001 
Yes 
380 
13.5 
151 
39.7 
229 
60.3 
No 
2433 
86.5 
613 
25.2 
1820 
74.8 
Other diagnoses (n = 2798)* 
&lt;0.001 
Yes 
399 
14.3 
148 
37.1 
251 
62.9 
No 
2399 
85.7 
611 
25.5 
1788 
74.5 </p>

<p>*Total amount is given for variables with missing data. 
 †Column percentages. 
 ‡Row percentages. </p>



<p>Fuglseth et al. </p>

<p>regression analyses. This was in large part due 
to the similarity between GAF F and GAF S 
(12), demonstrated in the results by a strong 
association between these two factors. The 
apparently inverse correlation between GAF S 
and disallowance was the most robust relation in 
the model. Correspondingly, GAF score was one 
of two significant predictors of a comparable 
outcome among African American youth (15). 
Furthermore, the results showed that when 
patients with diagnoses of neurotic, stress-related 
and somatoform disorders or personality disor-
ders were admitted, the likelihood of disal-
lowance was elevated. These diagnostic groups 
are associated with lower mean symptom load 
than, for example, schizophrenia disorders, bipo-
lar disorders and severe depression. In summary, 
several associations served to indicate that com-
pulsory referrals of individuals with relatively 
low symptom load were at increased likelihood 
of being disallowed. This could imply that more 
emphasis should be put on symptom load when </p>

<p>considering compulsory referrals of mentally ill 
patients. 
According to this study, the lower the compe-
tence level of the referring agent, the higher the like-
lihood of disallowance. Accordingly, referring 
agents that were given a low score on the key factors 
'knowledge of patients' and 'follow-up availability' 
had the highest rates of disallowance. This provides 
some support to the appeal that severely mentally ill 
patients should be referred through institutions 
where they are already known (14). In comparison, 
the third key factor, expertise, appeared to be of less 
impact on disallowance rate. This seems to differ 
from reports of substantial differences in assessment 
accuracy between healthcare personnel found in an 
Australian study, where professional expertise 
appeared to be an important factor (9). In our 
study, however, all referring clinicians were physi-
cians. Hence, the subtle impact of diverging psychi-
atric expertise on disallowance rate could have been 
a result of the physicians' communal general train-
ing. Perhaps, when the assessor possesses a certain </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Results from linear regression analysis showing estimated relations between patient and admission factors and disallowance 
of compulsory referrals. Includes direct and indirect relationships. </p>



<p>Disallowance in compulsory mental care referrals </p>

<p>level of training, a further increase in the quality of 
referral assessments could be achieved by improving 
judgement of specific patient traits, for example 
symptom load and suicidality (16). 
The magnitude of the association between com-
petence and disallowance was modest, compared 
to effects exerted by other variables. Hence, refer-
ring agent competence did not appear to have a 
substantial total effect on disallowance likelihood. 
Additionally, several factors acted as predictors of 
competence level and were thus indirectly related 
to disallowance via the competence level that was 
received. Thus, patient selection probably 
accounted for part of the variation in disallowance 
rate between competence levels. It seemed that 
although referring agents had different features, 
only a subtle part of the variation in disallowance 
likelihood was attributable to those differences. 
This appears contrary to previous reports where 
traits held by the referring agents significantly 
impacted the referral pattern. However, most other 
studies investigated general referrals for psychiatric 
care (17) or involuntary referrals, without investi-
gating eventual disallowance rates (14). Other 
studies with similar subjects were conducted in set-
tings that were not comparable with the Norwe-
gian system (18). 
When patients with reported suicidal ideations, 
suicide plans or self-harm were admitted, the likeli-
hood of disallowance appeared increased. This 
might reflect a natural progression in some of these 
cases, as admission to a safe environment and the 
passing of time might decrease the suicide risk (7). 
It could also be that patients considered to be at 
risk for suicide are compulsorily admitted due to 
the apprehension about adverse outcomes (8). This 
might be appropriate overtriage, preventing fatal 
outcomes. However, it could also reflect the clini-
cians' uncertainty in judging risk of suicide. Policy 
makers in institutions and individual clinicians 
alike should discuss the benefits of hedging against 
adverse outcomes vs. the risk of unwarranted com-
pulsory referrals. Additionally, training and appli-
cation of structured assessments could increase 
assessment confidence in healthcare professionals 
and contribute to preventing unwarranted referrals 
(16, 19). 
Observed alcohol or drug intoxication seemed to 
increase the likelihood of disallowance, an associa-
tion that seems to correspond with findings from a 
previous Norwegian study (8). This relation proba-
bly cancelled out any potentially significant effects 
of substance use disorders. The results from the 
regression analysis thus differed from the results of 
the bivariate analysis, which showed a significant 
association between substance use disorders and </p>

<p>disallowance. A considerable amount of the disal-
lowances associated with intoxication were proba-
bly due to rapid improvement from an acute drug-
or alcohol-induced mental crisis (7, 20). Hence, as 
with suicide risk, many of these disallowances were 
likely due to an actual change in a patient's condi-
tion. Nevertheless, clinicians could benefit from 
being aware of this association when considering 
compulsory referral of intoxicated patients. 
According to the results in this study, non-Nor-
wegians were at a significantly reduced probability 
of disallowance. This was an unexpected associa-
tion. Non-Norwegians are perhaps more severely 
ill at admission (21), in part because of delayed 
help seeking due to poor knowledge of available 
healthcare services (22). Accordingly, a decreased 
rate of disallowance was perhaps a natural conse-
quence of more severe illness at presentation. 
These findings appeared in line with the findings 
regarding symptom load in this study. Addition-
ally, communication problems can interfere with 
psychiatric assessments (23), necessitating compul-
sory observation, thus reducing the disallowance 
rate. Communication quality could therefore be a 
factor contributing to this finding. It was probably 
one of several confounding factors behind this 
finding. More research is needed to improve the 
understanding of this association. 
In conclusion, several factors were associated 
with disallowance. Among them, low symptom 
load was by far the strongest, whilst referring agent 
competence only modestly affected the outcome. 
More studies are warranted to improve the under-
standing of referrals for compulsory mental health 
care and disallowance, especially concerning rela-
tively healthy patients. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>The study population included in this study was 
limited to one region, which covered a tenth of the 
Norwegian population. It is uncertain whether 
these findings would have been replicated in a lar-
ger, cross-regional population. 
No significant structural changes were carried 
out during the inclusion period from 1 May 2005 
to 30 April 2008. After the inclusion period, there 
were comprehensive changes in the psychiatric 
healthcare organization in Norway. However, 
these changes did not impact handling of the 
patient group concerned in this study. Hence, the 
study is still relevant. 
Time lapse between referral and the special-
ist's assessment was not registered. However, it 
was probably a decisive factor in the outcome 
of conditions that potentially changed rapidly, </p>



<p>Fuglseth et al. </p>

<p>for example suicide risk and alcohol or drug 
intoxication, and should be recorded in future 
studies. 
Interpretation of the association between GAF 
S and disallowance was somewhat limited by the 
general nature of this scoring tool. Future studies 
could benefit from applying more extensive, 
detailed symptom assessment tools. 
Information regarding the characteristics of 
each individual referring physician was not avail-
able. Thus, the competence variable described a 
hypothetical mean for each referring agent. There 
were most likely substantial differences in expertise 
between clinicians, also within each of the referring 
groups. Future studies could increase the validity 
of a similar variable by gathering information on 
the expertise held by each individual referring 
physician. Also, additional situational factors, for 
example time available for assessment and assess-
ment environment, could be included to supple-
ment a similar variable in future studies (6, 7, 9, 
14). 
Although the results of this and other studies 
perhaps suggest that unwarranted referrals occur, 
the lack of present knowledge on the relationship 
between disallowed and unwarranted referrals 
restricted the discussion on the topic. Investigation 
of appropriate levels of overtriage and more 
research on factors affecting assessment quality 
might offer valuable contributions. Certainly, 
further research on the topic is warranted. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Funding for this study was provided by Uni Research Health, 
Division of Psychiatry, Haukeland University Hospital and a 
research grant from the Western Norway Regional Health 
Authority. The authors are thankful to Jill Bjarke, R.N., Geirr 
Fitje, B.B.A., Petter Jacobsen, R.N. and Marianne Langeland 
R.N. for their contribution to the high quality of the data. </p>

<p>Declaration of interest </p>

<p>No conflicting interests reported. </p>





<p>Disallowance in compulsory mental care referrals </p>





<p>Fuglseth et al. </p>

</text></tei>