<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4631805" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Linezolid is an oxazolidinone with potent activity against Mycobacterium tuberculosis. Linezolid toxicity in patients 
correlates with the dose and duration of therapy. These toxicities are attributable to the inhibition of mitochondrial protein syn-
thesis. Clinically relevant linezolid regimens were simulated in the in vitro hollow-fiber infection model (HFIM) system to iden-
tify the linezolid therapies that minimize toxicity, maximize antibacterial activity, and prevent drug resistance. Linezolid inhib-
ited mitochondrial proteins in an exposure-dependent manner, with toxicity being driven by trough concentrations. Once-daily 
linezolid killed M. tuberculosis in an exposure-dependent manner. Further, 300 mg linezolid given every 12 hours generated 
more bacterial kill but more toxicity than 600 mg linezolid given once daily. None of the regimens prevented linezolid resistance. 
These findings show that with linezolid monotherapy, a clear tradeoff exists between antibacterial activity and toxicity. By iden-
tifying the pharmacokinetic parameters linked with toxicity and antibacterial activity, these data can provide guidance for clini-
cal trials evaluating linezolid in multidrug antituberculosis regimens. </p>

<p>IMPORTANCE The emergence and spread of multidrug-resistant M. tuberculosis are a major threat to global public health. Lin-
ezolid is an oxazolidinone that is licensed for human use and has demonstrated potent activity against multidrug-resistant 
M. tuberculosis. However, long-term use of linezolid has shown to be toxic in patients, often resulting in thrombocytopenia. We 
examined therapeutic linezolid regimens in an in vitro model to characterize the exposure-toxicity relationship. The antibacte-
rial activity against M. tuberculosis was also assessed for these regimens, including the amplification or suppression of resistant 
mutant subpopulations by the chosen regimen. Higher exposures of linezolid resulted in greater antibacterial activity, but with 
more toxicity and, for some regimens, increased resistant mutant subpopulation amplification, illustrating the trade-off between 
activity and toxicity. These findings can provide valuable insight for designing optimal dosage regimens for linezolid that are 
part of the long combination courses used to treat multidrug-resistant M. tuberculosis. </p>

<p>Citation Brown AN, Drusano GL, Adams JR, Rodriquez JL, Jambunathan K, Baluya DL, Brown DL, Kwara A, Mirsalis JC, Hafner R, Louie A. 2015. Preclinical evaluations to identify 
optimal linezolid regimens for tuberculosis therapy. mBio 6(6):e01741-15. M </p>

<p>ultiply drug-resistant (MDR) and extensively drug-resistant 
(XDR) Mycobacterium tuberculosis strains represent major 
public health challenges and are causes of much morbidity and 
mortality (1-3). Because chemotherapy is nonoptimal for these 
pathogens and is poorly tolerated, failure rates are higher, treat-
ment courses are longer, and, consequently, failure and substan-
tial attendant drug-related morbidity are too frequently seen. 
Linezolid is an oxazolidinone antibiotic which has only re-
cently entered the clinician's therapeutic armamentarium for M. 
tuberculosis. This agent has been employed in the therapy of XDR 
M. tuberculosis as an add-on drug to "optimized background ther-
apy" for patients not responding to their current drug regimen 
(4). The results were surprisingly good, with 87% having a thera-
peutic response and only 4 therapeutic failures. These therapeutic 
outcomes were driven by an initial dose of 600 mg daily. The 
responses were also attended by frequent occurrence of possibly or </p>

<p>probably drug-related toxic events (82%). A number of toxicities 
have been associated with linezolid therapy, including gastroin-
testinal side effects and optic and peripheral neuropathies (4), but 
the earliest (and a frequent) toxicity is hematological toxicity, re-
sulting in reduced numbers of platelets. This effect has been dem-
onstrated to be related to mitochondrial toxicity (5, 6). However, 
drug-related toxicities observed in patients receiving 600 mg of 
linezolid daily were reduced in frequency after a reduction in dose 
to 300 mg daily (4). 
In order to obtain the maximal benefits of this antibiotic, un-
derstanding the relationships between drug exposure and M. tu-
berculosis kill, emergence of isolates resistant to linezolid, and tox-
icity is required. Our group has previously published work 
describing the relationships between drug exposure and M. tuber-
culosis kill and resistance suppression (7-9) in the hollow-fiber 
infection model (HFIM) system. Recently, our laboratory devel-</p>

<p>RESEARCH ARTICLE </p>

<p>crossmark </p>

<p>November/December 2015 Volume 6 Issue 6 e01741-15 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 1 </p>

<p>oped an approach to examining drug exposure and toxicity for 
oxazolidinones (10). A major objective of this current project was 
to characterize the exposure-mitochondrial toxicity relationship 
for linezolid. To that end, we employed a human myeloid leuke-
mia cell line with platelet properties (K562 cells) and exposed 
them to various concentrations of linezolid, simulating pharma-
cokinetic profiles that would be achieved in a patient receiving this 
antibiotic. K562 cells have been used previously to evaluate mito-
chondrial toxicity related to oxazolidinone therapy (6). K562 cells 
were then evaluated for mitochondrial toxicity by screening for 
known toxicity biomarkers, including synthesis of proteins in-
volved with energy metabolism, disruption of ATP production, </p>

<p>and altered apoptosis. These different uses of the HFIM give us the 
ability to relate exposure to both antimicrobial effect and drug 
concentration-driven mitochondrial toxicity. 
The aim of these experiments was to identify the optimal dose 
and dosing interval of linezolid as monotherapy to obtain optimal 
cell kill, minimize resistance emergence, and cause the least toxic-
ity for the patient. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Linezolid-associated mitochondrial toxicity of K562 cells in the 
HFIM system. K562 cells grew well in the HFIM system, reaching 
peak concentrations of approximately 10 13 live cells per hollow-
fiber cartridge by the end of the 16-day study in the no-treatment 
control arm (Fig. 1). Cell growth was similar among all treatment 
arms (Fig. 1), indicating that linezolid exposure had minimal ef-
fect on cellular proliferation in the HFIM system. 
Mitochondrial toxicity of K562 cells was evaluated by assessing 
two characterized mitochondrial toxicity biomarkers: energy me-
tabolism disruption and altered apoptosis. Disruption of cellular 
energy metabolism was determined by quantifying oxidative-
phosphorylation (OXPHOS) protein complexes 1, 3, 4, and 5 and 
measuring ATP production. Linezolid therapy had little effect on 
the protein synthesis of OXPHOS complex 1, 3, or 5 proteins 
(Fig. 2A, B, and D). In contrast, OXPHOS complex 4 proteins 
were markedly inhibited in the linezolid treatment arms relative to 
the no-treatment control, and protein levels were suppressed in a 
clearly exposure-dependent manner for the once-daily (q24h) 
regimens (Fig. 2C). At day 9 (when maximal protein inhibition 
was observed), complex 4 protein levels were 36.36% for the </p>

<p>FIG 1 Cell growth of K562 cells in the HFIMS system during linezolid ther-</p>

<p>apy. Linezolid exposure had a minimal effect on K562 cellular proliferation 
after 16 days in the HFIM system. At various time points, cells were harvested 
from the HFIM system, and live cells were enumerated using the trypan blue 
exclusion method. </p>

<p>FIG 2 OXPHOS mitochondrial protein levels for complexes 1, 3, 4, and 5 from K562 cells treated with linezolid in the HFIM system. The effects of linezolid on </p>

<p>the production of OXPHOS protein complexes 1 (A), 3 (B), 4 (C), and 5 (D) in K562 cells harvested from the HFIM system were assessed. Cell pellets were lysed, 
and OXPHOS mitochondrial protein levels were quantified by ELISA. </p>

<p>Brown et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2015 Volume 6 Issue 6 e01741-15 </p>

<p>342-mg q24h regimen, 33.33% for the 600-mg q24h regimen, 
15.15% for the 858-mg q24h regimen, and 9.09% for the 1,116-mg 
q24h regimen relative to the no-treatment control arm (Fig. 2C). 
Interestingly, the twice-daily regimen (300 mg q12h) resulted in 
the lowest levels of complex 4 proteins (6.06% relative to the no-
treatment control at day 9), indicating that mitochondrial protein 
synthesis is sensitive to linezolid dosing interval. Cellular ATP 
production was not influenced by linezolid, as an exposure-
response relationship was not observed over time for linezolid-
treated K562 cells (Fig. 3A). Finally, mitochondrial toxicity was 
evaluated by assessing the induction of apoptosis (a mitochon-
drial toxicity biomarker) in K562 cells treated with linezolid by 
measuring caspase 3 activation. Caspase 3 activity levels increased 
in all treatment arms throughout the duration of the 16-day study 
(Fig. 3B). The degree of apoptosis did not correlate with different 
exposures of linezolid (Fig. 3B), suggesting that linezolid-induced 
mitochondrial toxicity is not the result of altered apoptosis in 
treated K562 cells. 
Pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic (PK/PD) analysis of 
linezolid-associated mitochondrial toxicity. To identify the PD 
index for linezolid that is most closely linked with toxicity, we 
graphed the area under the OXPHOS complex 4 protein 
concentration-time curve (AUC OXPHOS4 ) from day 6 through day </p>

<p>16 (Fig. 2C) for each hollow-fiber treatment arm against the free-
drug linezolid 24-h AUC exposure and trough concentrations that 
were achieved in the HFIM system. An inhibitory sigmoid-E max 
effect model was fit to the data, and the results are shown in Fig. 4. 
The model fit the data well, resulting in r 2 values of 0.972 for 
linezolid 24-h AUC exposure and 0.992 for linezolid trough con-
centration. These data suggest that linezolid trough concentration 
is the PD index that is most closely linked with linezolid-
associated mitochondrial toxicity and that 0.19 mg/liter is the 
trough concentration associated with 50% maximal toxicity. 
Linezolid MICs and mutation frequencies for M. tuberculo-
sis. The linezolid MIC for the H37Rv M. tuberculosis strain used in 
these studies was 1 mg/liter. The frequency of mutation to resis-
tance in response to 2.5 mg/liter of linezolid for this organism was 
Ϫ7.4 log CFU. 
Antibacterial activity of linezolid against M. tuberculosis in 
the HFIM system. We evaluated the antibacterial activity of the 
same linezolid dosage regimens described above for the toxicity 
studies against the H37Rv strain of M. tuberculosis in the HFIM 
system to identify an optimal regimen that is the most effective 
and least toxic. The overall microbial kill for each regimen over 
time is displayed in Fig. 5A. Linezolid killed M. tuberculosis in an 
exposure-dependent manner, with the two highest exposures as-</p>

<p>FIG 3 ATP production and caspase 3 activation in K562 cells treated with linezolid in the HFIM system. The effects of linezolid exposure on the production of </p>

<p>ATP (A) and caspase 3 activation (B) in K562 cells harvested from the HFIM system were assessed. ATP levels were quantified using a colorimetric ATP assay, and 
caspase 3 activation was assessed via a colorimetric caspase 3 assay. </p>

<p>FIG 4 Influence of linezolid exposure (24-h AUC) and trough concentration on mitochondrial toxicity. The area under the OXPHOS protein complex 4-time </p>

<p>curve (AUC OXPHOS4 ) illustrated in Fig. 2C was calculated for all hollow-fiber arms and plotted against the linezolid 24-h AUC exposures and trough concen-
trations achieved for each regimen in the HFIM system. Black circles correspond to the q24h regimens, and red squares represent the q12h regimens. An 
inhibitory sigmoid-E max effect model was fitted to the data (blue line). </p>

<p>Linezolid for the Treatment of Tuberculosis </p>

<p>November/December 2015 Volume 6 Issue 6 e01741-15 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 3 </p>

<p>sociated with 858 mg q24h and 1,116 mg q24h, resulting in a 3-log 
reduction in bacterial burden at the end of the 3-week study 
(Fig. 5A). Conversely, the 342-mg q24h and 600-mg q24h regi-
mens yielded an overall bacterial decline of 0.5 and 1.7 logs, re-
spectively. The 300-mg q12h regimen provided the greatest 
amount of antibacterial activity and provided 3.3 logs of bacterial 
cell kill at the termination of the study (Fig. 5A). 
All therapeutic regimens of linezolid allowed the emergence of 
linezolid-resistant M. tuberculosis subpopulations (Fig. 5B). The 
number of drug-resistant mutants was heavily influenced by lin-
ezolid exposure (Fig. 5B and 6), with the 600-mg q24h regimen 
resulting in the highest number of mutants and the 1,116-mg q24h 
regimen resulting in the smallest mutant population after 3 weeks 
of therapy. The relationship between linezolid exposure and the 
bacterial burden of the resistant subpopulation resembles an in-
verted "U" (Fig. 6), a phenomenon that has been previously de-
scribed for resistance selection for other antibiotics (11). The 
emergence of resistant subpopulations allowed by the 300-mg 
q12h dosage regimen was similar to those reported for the 342-mg 
q24h and 858-mg q24h therapeutic arms. 
Mathematical model for antibacterial efficacy in the HFIM 
system. A large mathematical model was simultaneously fitted to 
the linezolid PK, the total bacterial M. tuberculosis burden, and the 
linezolid-resistant M. tuberculosis subpopulation burden data </p>

<p>generated by the studies performed in the HFIM system. The 
model fit all of the data well, resulting in precise and unbiased 
curve fits, as demonstrated by the predicted-versus-observed 
graphs (employing Bayesian posterior parameter values) for lin-
ezolid PK and bacterial burden (total population and resistant 
subpopulation [see Fig. S3 in the supplemental material]) as well 
as measures of bias and precision (mean weighted error; bias-
adjusted mean weighted squared error). The predicted-observed 
plots for the three system outputs yielded the following: for lin-
ezolid concentration, a slope of 1.125, an intercept of 0.598, and 
an r 2 of 0.941; for total bacterial burden, a slope of 1.030, an inter-
cept of Ϫ0.130, and an r 2 of 0.826; and for the less linezolid-
susceptible subpopulation, a slope of 1.056, an intercept of 
Ϫ0.133, and an r 2 of 0.949 (see Fig. S3). 
The means, medians, and standard deviations of the parameter 
values are displayed in Table 1. The pharmacokinetic parameter 
values of volume and clearance (CL) are for protein binding-</p>

<p>FIG 5 Antibacterial activity of linezolid on M. tuberculosis in the HFIM system. The antibacterial effect of linezolid on the total population of M. tuberculosis (A) </p>

<p>and the linezolid-resistant M. tuberculosis subpopulation (B) was determined. Hollow-fiber experiments were performed as two independent studies, and the 
data are the combined results of both experiments. The data points represent the mean values from both experiments, and the error bars correspond to the 
standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>FIG 6 Influence of linezolid exposure on the amplification of linezolid-</p>

<p>resistant bacterial mutants after 3 weeks of therapy. Hollow-fiber studies were 
performed twice as two independent experiments. The data points represent 
the geometric means from the two experiments for each linezolid exposure. </p>

<p>TABLE 1 Parameter values for the full model for estimation of 
linezolid impact on total MTB burden and the less linezolid-susceptible 
subpopulation a </p>

<p>Parameter (units) 
Mean 
Median 
SD </p>

<p>Vol (liters) 
65.2 
65.2 
1.21 
CL (liters/h) 
12.2 
13.2 
1.79 
K g,max-s (h Ϫ1 ) 
0.754 
0.699 
0.206 
K g,max-r (h Ϫ1 ) 
0.0208 
0.0210 
0.00518 
K k,max-s (h Ϫ1 ) 
3.25 
3.66 
0.624 
K k,max-r (h Ϫ1 ) 
1.21 
0.752 
0.885 
C 50,k-s (mg/liter) 
3.68 
3.74 
0.496 
C 50,k-r (mg/liter) 
18.7 
17.0 
2.873 
H k-s 
10.9 
14.3 
4.39 
H k-r 
13.8 
14.6 
10.1 
POPMAX (CFU/ml) 
3.72 ϫ 10 7 
4.84 ϫ 10 7 
1.50 ϫ 10 7 
Initcond_2 (CFU/ml) 
1.81 ϫ 10 7 
1.43 ϫ 10 7 
9.66 ϫ 10 6 
Initcond_3 (CFU/ml) 
5.90 
0.601 
8.35 </p>

<p>a Vol is the apparent volume of the central compartment; CL is the apparent plasma 
clearance; K g,max-s and K g,max-r are maximal growth rate constants for the susceptible 
and resistant populations; K k,max-s and K k,max-r are maximal kill rate constants for the 
respective populations; C 50,k-s and C 50,k-r are linezolid concentrations at which the kill 
rate is half maximal for the respective populations; H k-s and H k-r are Hill's constants for 
the respective populations; POPMAX is the population burden at which stationary 
phase is achieved; Initcond_2 is the initial total MTB population burden; Initcond_3 is 
the initial linezolid-resistant MTB burden. It was assumed that the initial linezolid 
concentration was 0.0. </p>

<p>Brown et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2015 Volume 6 Issue 6 e01741-15 </p>

<p>corrected free linezolid. The maximal growth rate constants for 
the susceptible and less-susceptible populations demonstrate that 
the less-susceptible population grows substantially less well. The 
maximal kill rate constants demonstrate that it is substantially 
more difficult to kill the less linezolid-susceptible subpopulation, 
leading to the difficulty in suppressing resistance amplification, 
even with higher exposures. Finally, the linezolid concentration at 
which the M. tuberculosis kill rate is 50% of the maximal rate is 
5-fold higher for the less-susceptible population. These are in line 
with expectations for these populations for linezolid. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>MDR and XDR TB pose substantial public health problems all 
around the world. Rates of response to antibiotic intervention are 
lower than we have come to expect in the chemotherapy of tuber-
culosis. Treatment courses are long and fraught with toxicities, 
which leads to decreased patient compliance. These difficulties are 
directly attributable to the fact that in both instances, our first-line 
agents isoniazid and rifampin have been rendered ineffective due 
to the emergence of resistance. There is a need for new agents that 
have good activity like isoniazid and rifampin. Linezolid and other 
oxazolidinones have the promise of being one of the new agents to 
fill this niche for the combination therapy of MDR and XDR M. 
tuberculosis infection. 
In order for linezolid to fulfill this promise, it is important that 
an optimized dose and dosing interval be chosen for therapy. The 
most appropriate dosage regimen will have a major impact on the 
burden of M. tuberculosis, will have a low probability of resistance 
emergence, and will be relatively nontoxic. In order to identify the 
optimal dose, understanding the relationships between drug ex-
posure and M. tuberculosis kill, resistance emergence, and the like-
lihood concentration-driven toxicities is necessary. Understand-
ing that a fixed drug dose will generate a distribution of exposures 
in a population of patients is also important. Consequently, these 
considerations must be factored into the design of experiments for 
both efficacy and toxicity so that not only a population mean 
exposure is studied, but also exposure equivalents corresponding 
to ϩ1, ϩ2, and Ϫ1 standard deviations from the mean exposure. 
In this set of experiments, we employed the hollow-fiber infec-
tion model (HFIM) to examine all of these issues. We used this 
model previously to examine the microbiological endpoints for 
M. tuberculosis therapy (7-9). In the current project, we developed 
an approach to link linezolid exposure to an in vitro measure of 
linezolid-associated toxic effect. One of the most common toxic 
effects of linezolid and other oxazolidinone therapy is the reduc-
tion of the number of hematological cells. In particular, thrombo-
cytopenia and anemia are major problems with long-term oxazo-
lidinone administration (12). 
Oxazolidinone toxicity is thought to be mediated by inhibiting 
mitochondrial protein synthesis (5, 6). Others have shown that 
OXPHOS complex 4 (cytochrome c oxidase) proteins are consis-
tently and significantly decreased in both in vitro and in vivo sys-
tems exposed to oxazolidinone therapy (5, 6, 13). Furthermore, 
OXPHOS complex 4 levels have been shown to be well below the 
normal range in patients treated with prolonged courses of lin-
ezolid (5, 13). These data identify protein complex 4 as a marker 
for oxazolidinone-related mitochondrial toxicity. To that end, we 
employed K562 cells, a human erythromyeloblastoid leukemia 
cell line, and exposed these cells to linezolid concentration-time 
profiles similar to that seen in humans using the HFIM system. We </p>

<p>sampled the system over time and assayed for OXPHOS protein 
complexes 1 (NADH dehydrogenase), 3 (cytochrome c reduc-
tase), 4 (cytochrome c oxidase), and 5 (ATP synthase). OXPHOS 
complex 2 proteins (succinate dehydrogenase) have been previ-
ously shown to not be altered in the presence of linezolid (5), as 
these protein subunits are mainly encoded by nuclear DNA (14). 
Thus, we did not assess OXPHOS complex 2 protein levels as part 
of this investigation. It was our hypothesis that only the complex 4 
proteins would yield a clear exposure-response relationship. In 
Fig. 2, it is obvious that only complex 4 demonstrates a definite 
exposure-response with a range of linezolid exposures. We calcu-
lated the AUC OXPHOS4 as an integrated measure of the toxic effect 
of linezolid. The results, seen in Fig. 4, indicate that an inhibitory 
sigmoid-E max model describes the data very well. We had em-
ployed two measures of exposure as the independent variable, the 
24-h AUC of linezolid and the linezolid trough concentration. In 
the experiment, we examined 5 linezolid exposures plus a no-
treatment control. Four of the 5 linezolid exposures were admin-
istered daily. For the daily exposures, we evaluated the mean ex-
posure from a 600-mg linezolid dose, as well as ϩ1 standard 
deviation (mean 24-h AUC exposure equivalent to 858 mg), ϩ2 
SD (1,116-mg equivalent), and Ϫ1 SD (342-mg equivalent). Ad-
ditionally, we examined two different dosing intervals for the 
mean exposure of a 600-mg daily dose, administered either once 
daily or as 300 mg q12h. As seen in Fig. 4A, when AUC is the 
independent variable, all the daily exposures are well described by 
the mathematical model, but the q12h administration results in 
more toxicity than suggested by the model. When trough concen-
trations are employed as the independent variable, the model is 
more predictive of the results. We conclude that the effect of lin-
ezolid on OXPHOS complex 4 proteins is most closely linked to 
trough concentrations. This finding has been seen in clinical trials 
as well (15, 16). 
If toxicity were the only issue, we would choose the lower ex-
posure and we would employ q24h or possibly less frequent dos-
ing to minimize adverse drug effects; however, in order for lin-
ezolid therapy to be most effective against M. tuberculosis 
clinically, it is imperative that a regimen result in major kill of the 
total M. tuberculosis population burden and also not amplify re-
sistant subpopulations. Linezolid's mechanism of action for M. 
tuberculosis kill and for toxicity is inhibition of protein synthesis, 
bacterial and mitochondrial, respectively. Consequently, as anti-
microbial activity increases, an increase in toxicity would be pre-
dicted to accompany it. 
In Fig. 5, we see the change over time in the total M. tuberculosis 
burden. The decline in M. tuberculosis total population reaches a 
maximum at about 2 weeks. Thereafter, the total burden increases 
due to resistance emergence. The two higher exposures (ϩ1 SD 
[858-mg equivalents] and ϩ2 SD [1,116-mg equivalents]) pro-
duce more overall kill than the two smaller exposures, with ϩ1 SD 
killing ca. 1.2 log 10 CFU/ml more, which rises to 1.36 
log 10 CFU/ml with the ϩ2 SD exposure, relative to the mean 
(600 mg). Conversely, the Ϫ1 SD (342-mg equivalents) kills sub-
stantially less (~1.1 log 10 CFU/ml) than the mean exposure (max-
imum kill of 0.7 log 10 CFU/ml for the Ϫ1 SD exposure compared 
to 1.8 log 10 CFU/ml for the mean exposure). Clearly, increasing 
exposure to increase antimicrobial activity has to be balanced for 
the concomitant increase in toxicity. 
We also examined half the mean exposure given every 12 h 
(q12h) to identify whether dosing interval influences M. tubercu-</p>

<p>Linezolid for the Treatment of Tuberculosis </p>

<p>November/December 2015 Volume 6 Issue 6 e01741-15 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 5 </p>

<p>losis cell kill. Somewhat to our surprise, the 300-mg-equivalent 
exposure given q12h resulted in significantly better M. tuberculosis 
kill than 600 mg daily, indicating that trough concentrations (rel-
ative to the MIC) were driving M. tuberculosis kill. A similar find-
ing was observed by Wallis et al. (17). As described above, how-
ever, the price is one of toxicity. This is important for design and 
interpretation of early bactericidal activity (EBA) trials for oxazo-
lidinones. A 14-day EBA study of linezolid may demonstrate max-
imal killing activity for a twice-daily regimen of linezolid com-
pared with daily dosing of the same total amount. Such a result 
must be balanced by the increased toxicity that will result from 
this dosing interval and the fact that the toxicity will not be evident 
clinically until after 14 days of treatment. We have noted in other 
studies evaluating oxazolidinone pharmacodynamics (18) that 
the improved bacterial kill with twice-daily dosing is seen only 
with monotherapy and that the advantage is abrogated in the face 
of adequate combination chemotherapy. Also, for the advantage 
of better patient adherence to regimen or ease of directly observed 
therapy, it is likely that a daily regimen will be optimal. 
Finally, what of resistance emergence? Figure 5B shows a some-
what surprising finding. The order of resistance emergence does 
not follow a simple exposure response. The mean exposure actu-
ally drives the greatest resistance emergence, followed by the Ϫ1 
SD exposure. The ϩ1 and ϩ2 SD exposures have considerably less 
resistant subpopulation amplification at the end of the third week, 
but both are still considerably above baseline. The reason for this is 
shown in Fig. 6. The data describe a nonmonotonic function, 
which our laboratory has described as an inverted "U" (11). At 
lower exposures, there is some, but not maximal, resistant sub-
population amplification. As greater pressure is exerted, there is 
more selective pressure, and the resistance amplification increases 
to a maximum. At yet-higher exposures, some control is exerted 
over the less-susceptible subpopulation, and its numbers decline 
from the maximum. In this instance, even the ϩ2-SD exposure 
did not fully control the less-susceptible subpopulation amplifi-
cation. Consequently, increasing exposure that would partially 
control the resistance amplification would result in considerable 
more toxicity with higher linezolid doses. In addition, linezolid 
(and other oxazolidinones) will be given as part of combination 
chemotherapy, where there will be a much greater likelihood of 
controlling resistance amplification, as long as there is sufficient 
consideration given to the exposures for the other drug(s) in the 
combination. 
These data and the analysis provide some guidance for clinical 
trials to study linezolid in clinical trials of M. tuberculosis-infected 
patients. The exposure-responses for M. tuberculosis kill and tox-
icity show a clear trade-off with increasing dosage. The magnitude 
of the M. tuberculosis kill for Ϫ1 SD exposure is likely to be sub-
optimal for many patients. The higher exposures (ϩ1 and ϩ2 SD) 
induce a rapid increase in the measure of toxicity examined here. 
Therefore, if linezolid is to be incorporated into a multidrug reg-
imen in a phase II study, doses slightly smaller and slightly larger 
than 600 mg (e.g., perhaps 450 and 900 mg) should be examined. 
However, no 450-mg dosing is available, so a 300-mg/day regimen 
might be considered. Several centers with experience in MDR 
treatment now initiate therapy with 300 mg/day. In addition, 
studies of initial dosing with 900 or 600 mg/day should allow dose 
reductions to be made when exposure-related toxicities are de-
tected. While the amplification of a less susceptible subpopulation 
is worrisome, if linezolid is included in a robust regimen (i.e., not </p>

<p>added as a single agent to a failing regimen), there is a high likeli-
hood of protection from resistance emergence. We are currently 
conducting studies evaluating q24h dosing intervals of linezolid in 
combination with moxifloxacin to determine relationships to tox-
icity and antimicrobial activity. 
These in vitro models can provide guidance and decision sup-
port for the choice of doses and schedules in phase II clinical trials 
to ultimately result in regimens that will have substantial M. tu-
berculosis kill with moderate toxic liability and which will (in com-
bination regimens) suppress emergence of resistance. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>K562 cells and bacterial strain. For the linezolid toxicity studies, human 
erythromyeloblastoid leukemia K562 (ATCC CCL-243) cells were used. 
Cells were maintained in RPMI 1640 medium (HyClone, Logan, UT) 
supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (HyClone) at 37°C and 5% 
CO 2 and were subcultured twice weekly. 
The H37Rv strain of M. tuberculosis was used for the linezolid antibac-
terial studies. Bacterial stocks were stored at Ϫ80°C and grown as previ-
ously described (7). 
Compound. Pharmaceutical-grade linezolid was purchased from 
CuraScript (Orlando, FL) as a solution for injection and stored at room 
temperature in the dark. Prior to experimental use, linezolid was diluted 
to the desired concentrations in sterile deionized water. 
Linezolid susceptibility. The susceptibility of the H37Rv strain to li-
nezolid was determined using the absolute serial dilution method as pre-
viously described (7, 9). Briefly, 10 4 CFU of H37Rv in log-phase growth 
was plated on Middlebrook 7H10 agar (Becton Dickinson Microbiology 
Systems, Sparks, MD) supplemented with 10% oleic acid, albumin, dex-
trose, and catalase (OADC; Becton Dickinson Microbiology Systems) 
containing 2-fold dilutions of linezolid. The cultures were incubated at 
37°C and 5% CO 2 . After 4 weeks of incubation, the MICs were determined 
by identifying the lowest drug concentration at which there was no bac-
terial growth on the agar plate. 
Mutation frequency determination. The mutation frequency of the 
H37Rv strain was evaluated using methods that are described elsewhere 
(7, 9). Briefly, H37Rv cultures in log-phase growth were inoculated onto 
plates containing Middlebrook 7H10 agar plus 10% Middlebrook OADC 
with linezolid at a concentration equivalent to 2.5ϫ the MIC. The muta-
tion frequency was identified after 4 weeks of incubation at 37°C and 5% 
CO 2 . 
Toxicity studies in the HFIM system. Drug-related toxicities associ-
ated with prolonged linezolid therapy were assessed in the HFIM system. 
A detailed description of the HFIM system is found elsewhere (7, 9, 10, 19, 
20). For these studies, the extracapillary space (ECS) of six polysulfone 
hollow-fiber cartridges (FiberCellSystems, Frederick, MD) were inocu-
lated with 5 ϫ 10 6 K562 cells. Linezolid was administered into five car-
tridges as a 1-h infusion via computer-controlled syringe pumps to sim-
ulate the free (non-protein-bound)-drug 24-h area under the 
concentration-time curve (AUC) that is associated with the mean free-
drug plasma AUC of linezolid at steady state after oral dosing at 600 mg 
daily (q24h), one standard deviation above the mean free 24-h-AUC ex-
posure (858-mg mean equivalent exposure q24h), two standard devia-
tions above the mean free 24-h-AUC exposure (1,116-mg mean equiva-
lent exposure q24h), and one standard deviation below the mean free 
24-h-AUC exposure (342-mg mean equivalent exposure q24h). The fifth 
cartridge received linezolid as the mean free 24-h AUC exposure for 
300 mg administered twice daily (q12h). Finally, one cartridge did not 
receive drug treatment and served as a no-treatment control. Linezolid 
containing medium was isovolumetrically replaced with drug-free me-
dium to simulate the mean clinical half-life of 4.26 h. Human pharmaco-
kinetic parameters for linezolid were obtained from the Zyvox package 
insert (21). 
Serial drug concentrations were collected from the HFIM system over 
the course of the study and quantified by liquid chromatography-tandem </p>

<p>Brown et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2015 Volume 6 Issue 6 e01741-15 </p>

<p>mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) (see below). Intensive PK sampling was 
conducted for the first 48 h of the study, followed by sparse PK sampling 
for the duration of the study. The measured linezolid concentrations in 
the HIFM system were within 10% of the targeted value at all time points, 
indicating that the desired PK profiles for linezolid were achieved in the 
HFIM system (see Fig. S1 in the supplemental material). 
Mitochondrial toxicity of K562 cells was evaluated at various time 
points over the course of the 16-day study. K562 cells were harvested from 
the HFIM system, enumerated, and assessed for viability via the trypan 
blue exclusion method. Cell pellets were collected on days 0, 6, 9, 12, and 
16 after linezolid exposure and were frozen at Ϫ80°C until the end of the 
study. Cell pellets were lysed using the cell extraction buffer provided with 
the cytochrome c oxidase (complex IV) human profiling enzyme-linked 
immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kit (Abcam, Cambridge, MA) according 
to the manufacturer's instructions, and total cellular protein concentra-
tion was determined for each sample using a Thermo Scientific Pierce 
bincinchoninic acid (BCA) protein assay kit (Life Technologies, Grand 
Island, NY). Cell lysates were assessed for energy metabolism disruption 
and altered apoptosis, two biomarkers of mitochondrial toxicity. Energy 
metabolism disruption was evaluated by quantifying oxidative phosphor-
ylation (OXPHOS) protein complexes using a NADH dehydrogenase 
(complex 1) human profiling ELISA kit (Abcam), a cytochrome c reduc-
tase (complex 3) human profiling ELISA kit (Abcam), a cytochrome c 
oxidase (complex 4) human profiling ELISA kit (Abcam), and an ATP 
synthase (complex 5) human profiling ELISA kit (Abcam). Because OX-
PHOS complex 2 (succinate dehydrogenase) protein subunits are en-
coded mainly by nuclear DNA (14) and have been shown to not be altered 
in the presence of linezolid (5), we did not assess these protein levels to 
conserve cell lysates for additional assays. Energy metabolism disruption 
of cell lysates was also evaluated by measuring total ATP production using 
a colorimetric ATP assay kit (Abcam). Finally, the mitochondrial toxicity 
marker of altered apoptosis was examined by measuring the increase in 
caspase 3 activation using a colorimetric assay (Abcam) as per the manu-
facturer's instructions. 
Assessment of antibacterial activity for linezolid against M. tuber-
culosis in the HFIM system. The same linezolid dosage regimens and 
pharmacokinetic profiles described above for the toxicity study were eval-
uated for antibacterial activity against M. tuberculosis in the HFIM system. 
The HFIM system for M. tuberculosis has been described elsewhere (9). 
Briefly, 10 ml of H37Rv M. tuberculosis was inoculated into the HFIM 
system (FiberCell Systems) at a concentration of 1 ϫ 10 7 CFU per ml. 
Linezolid was administered into cartridges as described above for the tox-
icity studies. Intensive PK sampling was conducted for the first 48 h of the 
study, followed by sparse PK sampling for the duration of the study (see 
Fig. S2 in the supplemental material). At various times throughout the 
3-week study, bacterial cultures were collected. The samples were washed 
by centrifugation (1,500 ϫ g for 5 min) to remove linezolid and then 
plated onto drug-free 7H10 OADC agar and agar supplemented with 
linezolid at 2.5ϫ the MIC for quantitative culture. After 28 days of incu-
bation, the colonies on each plate were enumerated, and the bacterial 
burden was calculated. Two independent hollow-fiber studies were per-
formed. 
Linezolid LC-MS/MS assay. Samples collected from the HFIM system 
experiments were diluted with water and analyzed by high-pressure liquid 
chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS; AB Sciex, Fos-
ter City, CA) for linezolid concentrations. The HPLC parameters were as 
follows: the column used was a Thermoscientific Hypersil Gold C 18 col-
umn, 150 by 4.6 mm, with a 5-m particle diameter, and mobile phases A 
and B were 5 mM ammonium formate adjusted to pH 3.00 using formic 
acid in water and acetonitrile, respectively, and ran in isocratic mode at 
34% B with a flow rate of 0.750 ml/min. Linezolid concentrations were 
measured using the MS/MS transition from m/z 338 to m/z 235. The 
analysis run time was 5 min, and the target concentration range was 0.125 
to 20.0 g/ml (r 2 Ͼ 0.997). Quality control samples (0.125, 2.50, and </p>

<p>20.0 g/ml) had coefficients of variation (CVs) ranging from 2.9 to 4.3% 
and accuracies (percent recovery) between 85 and 103%. 
Statistical analysis and mathematical modeling. The area under the 
OXPHOS protein complex 4-time curve (AUC OXPHOS4 ) from days 6 to 16 
was calculated for each hollow-fiber arm from the toxicity studies using 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">Prism</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 6.01</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc.</rs>., La Jolla, CA). The 
complex 4 AUC OXPHOS from days 6 to 16 was graphed against the lin-
ezolid free-drug 24-h AUC exposure and free-drug trough concentrations 
achieved for each regimen in the HFIM system. An inhibitory sigmoid-
E max effect model was fitted to the data using <rs id="software-3" type="software">ADAPT</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">V</rs> software. Param-
eter estimates were obtained employing maximum-likelihood estimation. 
The impact of linezolid on both the total M. tuberculosis burden and 
the less-susceptible subpopulation burden was analyzed in a population 
sense employing the program <rs id="software-4" type="software">BigNPAG</rs>, a nonparametric (for parameter 
distributions) adaptive grid program written by <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Leary et al. and Neely et al.</rs>. (22, 23). Starting weights were as estimates of the inverse of the obser-
vation variance for each of the three system outputs. The adaptive ␥ func-
tion in <rs type="software">BigNPAG</rs> was employed to optimize the weights so as to give the 
best approximation to the homoscedastic assumption. The three system 
outputs were (i) measurement of linezolid concentration-time profiles in 
each HFIM arm, (ii) measurement of total M. tuberculosis burden in each 
HFIM arm, and (iii) measurement of the less linezolid-susceptible sub-
population in each HFIM arm. 
The system of nonhomogeneous differential equations to describe this 
system was published previously (24). </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplemental material for this article may be found at http://mbio.asm.org/ 
lookup/suppl/doi:10.1128/mBio.01741-15/-/DCSupplemental. 
Figure S1, TIF file, 0.1 MB. 
Figure S2, TIF file, 0.1 MB. 
Figure S3, TIF file, 5.9 MB. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by a 2012 grant from the Lifespan/Tufts/Brown 
Center for AIDS Research (CFAR), an NIH/NIAID/Miriam Hospital 
funded program (P30-AI-042853) and also by the NIAID/DAIDS of the 
National Institutes of Health under contract award No. 
HHSN266200700043C and HHSN272201400006I. 
The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not 
necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health. 
We have no conflicts of interest to declare. </p>



<p>Linezolid for the Treatment of Tuberculosis </p>

<p>November/December 2015 Volume 6 Issue 6 e01741-15 </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 7 </p>



<p>Brown et al. </p>



<p>® </p>

<p>mbio.asm.org 
November/December 2015 Volume 6 Issue 6 e01741-15 </p>

</text></tei>