<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4632900" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background and aims. Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) are 
antidepressants increasingly prescribed for pregnancy and postpartum depression. 
However, these compounds can cross the placenta and also pass into breast milk, thus 
reaching the fetus and infant during critical developmental stages, potentially causing 
adverse effects. Fluoxetine, a widely used SSRI, has been shown to affect (neuro) 
endocrine signaling in various organisms, including humans. This compound can also 
interact with estrogen receptors in vitro and cause an estrogen-dependent uterotrophic 
response in rodents. Consequently, the aim of the present study was to assess if the 
active metabolite of fluoxetine, namely norfluoxetine (NFLX), shares the same capacity 
for estrogen receptor interaction. 
Methods. The in vitro (anti)estrogenic activity of norfluoxetine was assessed 
using a firefly luciferase reporter construct in the T47D-Kbluc breast cancer cell line. 
These cells express nuclear estrogen receptors (ERs) that can activate the transcription 
of the luciferase reporter gene upon binding of ER agonists. Light emission was 
monitored in case of cells exposed to norfluoxetine or mixtures of norfluoxetine-
estradiol. Cell viability was assessed using a resazurin-based assay. 
Results. During individual testing, NFLX was able to induce a significant 
increase in luciferase activity compared to control, but only at the highest concentration 
tested (10 µM). In binary mixtures with estradiol (30 pM constant concentration) a 
significant increase in luminescence was observed at low submicromolar norfluoxetine 
concentrations compared to estradiol alone. 
Conclusion. Norfluoxetine can induce estrogenic effects in vitro and can 
potentiate the activity of estradiol. However, further studies are needed to clarify 
if these observed estrogenic effects may have detrimental consequences for human 
exposure. </p>

<p>Keywords: norfluoxetine, estrogen receptors, in vitro </p>

<p>postpartum (range 6.5-12.9%), and in the past decade the 
use of SSRIs to treat depression during pregnancy and 
breast-feeding has increased considerably [2-4]. 
However, the use of SSRIs during gestation and 
postpartum may carry risks for the offspring, as these 
psychoactive drugs can cross the placenta and also pass 
into breast milk, thus reaching the fetus and infant during 
critical developmental stages [5,6]. In humans, studies </p>

<p>Background and aims </p>

<p>Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) 
are antidepressant drugs recommended as first-line 
pharmacotherapy for unipolar depression [1]. The 
prevalence of depression is high during pregnancy and </p>

<p>DOI: 10.15386/cjmed-476 </p>

<p>Manuscript received: 21.05.2015 
Received in revised form: 22.06.2015 
Accepted: 23.06.2015 
Address for correspondence: anca.pop@umfcluj.ro </p>



<p>Original Research </p>

<p>Clujul Medical 2015 Vol. 88 no. 3: 386-390 </p>

<p>regarding perinatal SSRI exposure and adverse outcomes 
in offspring have focused on risks of fetal malformations, 
birth weight, respiratory distress, neonatal convulsions and 
some neurodevelopmental effects such as psychomotor 
delays, behavioral changes and autism [5,7,8]. Endocrine-
related reproductive effects in children exposed in utero 
and/or through lactation have not received attention thus 
far. 
Fluoxetine (FLX), a major representative of 
SSRIs, has been linked to reproductive and/or (neuro) 
endocrine toxicity in aquatic organisms, rodents and 
humans [9-11]. Studies on fish showed that FLX can 
disrupt the physiological responses of the reproductive 
axis by interfering with the neuroendocrine regulation of 
steroidogenesis and gametogenesis. Furthermore, FLX can 
also disrupt estrogen signaling in the brain by reducing 
the expression of estrogen receptors in the hypothalamus 
[10]. In addition, a few studies on rodents suggested 
that FLX could interfere with sexual steroid signaling 
during development, as this compound was able to affect 
sexual brain differentiation, sexual behaviour, testicular 
development and sperm production in rat offspring 
exposed in utero and/or through lactation [12-16]. Finally, 
a study by Mueller et al. showed that FLX can activate 
estrogen receptors in vitro and can also induce an estrogen-
dependent uterotrophic response in rodents [17]. 
In vivo, fluoxetine is metabolized to norfluoxetine 
(NFLX), an active molecule for which there is no published 
data regarding its endocrine effects [18]. Consequently, this 
study aimed at assessing the capacity of NFLX to elicit 
estrogenic or antiestrogenic effects in vitro, using a firefly 
luciferase-reporter assay in an estrogen receptor (ER) 
positive cell line. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Chemicals and reagents 
Norfluoxetine (NFLX) was purchased from LGC 
Standards (Germany). Resazurin, 17β-estradiol (E 2 ), 
EDTA, tricine, dithiothreitol (DTT), ATP and Dulbecco's 
Modified Eagle's Medium F-12 (DMEM F-12) were 
obtained from Sigma Aldrich (Steinheim, Germany). 
Tris and 1,2-diaminocyclohexane-N,N,N',N'-tetraacetic 
acid (CDTA) were from Fluka (Buchs, Switzerland) 
and luciferin was from Roth (Karlsruhe, Germany). 
(MgCO 3 ) 4 Mg(OH) 2 .5H 2 O was purchased from Acros 
Organics (Geel, Belgium). Dulbecco's Phosphate Buffered 
Saline (PBS), trypsin, RPMI1640 + GlutaMAX culture 
medium and charcoal stripped Fetal Bovine Serum (FBS) 
and were purchased from Gibco (Paisley, UK). Fetal Bovine 
Serum (FBS) was from Sigma (Steinheim, Germany). 
Stock solutions 
NFLX and E 2 were prepared as stock solutions 
in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO, Riedel-de Haën, Seelze, 
Germany). Subsequent serial dilutions were prepared and 
then used to obtain the desired test concentration range for </p>

<p>NFLX and E 2 . 
Cell culture 
Estrogen receptor positive T47D-KBluc human 
breast cancer cells were obtained from American Type 
Culture Collection (ATCC, USA). The cells were 
maintained in 75 cm 2 flasks with RPMI1640 + GlutaMAX 
medium, supplemented with 10% FBS at 37°C in an 
atmosphere of 5% CO 2 , under saturating humidity. During 
every cell passage the cells were rinsed with PBS and were 
detached from plastic flasks using trypsin. 
Cell viability assay 
Cell viability was evaluated using a resazurin-
based assay. For this test, T47D-KBluc cells were seeded 
at 5x10 5 cells/mL (96 wells/plate) in RPMI1640 with 
GlutaMAX medium. Following a 24h incubation at 37°C, 
5% CO 2 , the cells were rinsed with 200 µL PBS and then 
exposed for 24h to NFLX in increasing concentrations 
or binary mixtures of NFLX in increasing concentrations 
and 30 pM E 2 (the lowest E 2 concentration that induced a 
maximum response in this cell line). The experiments were 
performed in triplicate. Viable cells are able to reduce the 
non-fluorescent resazurin reagent to a fluorescent product 
called resorufin. After exposure to test compounds or 
mixtures, the cells were rinsed with 200µL PBS and then 
incubated with 200 µL of a 100 µM resazurin solution, 
for 3h at 37°C, 5% CO 2 . Using a plate-reader (Synergy 2 
Multi-Mode Microplate Reader, BioTek), the fluorescence 
of resorufin in viable cells was measured at λ excitation =530/25; 
λ emission =590/35. 
Luciferase assay 
The luciferase assay was used as an indicator of 
(anti)estrogenic activity in T47D-KBluc breast cancer 
cells, which express ERs and carry a stably transfected 
firefly luciferase-reporter. The assay is performed by 
measuring the luminescence intensity produced when the 
ER-dependent luciferase is expressed and transforms its 
substrate. For this purpose, T47D-KBluc cells (8.5x10 6 
cells/mL) were seeded in 96-well plates and incubated 
24h at 37°C, in phenol red-free Dulbecco's Modified 
Eagle's Medium F-12 (DMEM F-12), containing 10% 
charcoal stripped FBS. After the 24h incubation, the 
medium was removed and the cells were rinsed with 
PBS and subsequently exposed to NFLX in increasing 
concentrations or binary mixtures of 30 pM E 2 and NFLX 
in increasing concentrations. The DMSO concentration in 
assay medium did not exceed 0.2%. A buffer containing 
10 mM Tris, 1.99 mM DTT and 2 mM CDTA was used to 
lyse the cells after the 24h exposure period. The plates were 
incubated at -20°C for 15-minutes, then frozen at -80°C for 
a minimum of 30 minutes. Following a thawing period on 
ice, the plates were shaken for 30 mins at room temperature. 
Luminescence was measured using a plate-reader (Synergy 
2 Multi-Mode Microplate Reader, BioTek) with automatic 
injection of 100 µL luciferin FlashMix [0.47 mM luciferin, 
20 mM tricine, 1.07 mM (MgCO 3 ) 4 Mg(OH) 2 .5H 2 O, 0.1 </p>



<p>Pharmacy </p>

<p>Clujul Medical 2015 Vol. 88 no. 3: 386-390 </p>

<p>mM EDTA, 2 mM DTT and 5 mM ATP, pH 7.8] in each 
well. Light emission was stopped with 50 µL NaOH 0.2 M. 
Data analysis and statistics 
Experiments were performed three times in 
triplicate. Data was expressed either as percentages of non-
treated controls (individual testing) or as percentages of the 
signal observed for 30 pM E 2 (testing mixtures NFLX-E 2 ). 
The normality of the distribution of data was tested with 
the Shapiro-Wilk test (p&lt;0.05). To compare data, 1-way 
ANOVA was applied to normally distributed data, followed 
by Dunnett's Multiple Comparison post hoc test. For 
data that were not normally distributed we used Kruskal-
Wallis test, followed by Dunnett's Multiple Comparison 
test. Differences in P values of &lt;0.05 were considered 
statistically significant. All statistical analyses and graphs 
were performed using <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5</rs>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Cell viability assay 
To assess cell viability in the presence of NFLX, 
T47D-Kbluc cells were exposed to NFLX in increasing 
concentrations (0.01, 0.03, 0.1, 0.3, 1, 3, 10, 15 and 20 
µM) for 24 hours. NFLX significantly decreased cell 
viability at 15 and 20 µM (data not shown) and therefore, 
these concentrations were excluded from further testing. 
Mixtures NFLX (increasing concentrations as stated 
above) and E 2 (constant concentration 30 pM) were also 
evaluated using the same assay and incubation time. Again, 
mixtures that contained NFLX in concentrations above 10 
µM significantly decreased cell viability (data not shown) 
and were excluded from further testing. </p>

<p>Luciferase assay 
To test for estrogenic effects of NFLX, T47D-Kbluc 
cells were incubated with increasing concentrations of 
NFLX (0.01, 0.03, 0.1, 0.3, 1, 3 and 10µM) for 24 hours. 
A significant increase in luciferase activity as compared 
to control was observed only at the highest concentration 
tested, 10 µM (Figure 1). This induction represents 10% of 
the E 2 response at 30 pM in T47D-Kbluc cells. 
At low concentrations, mixtures NFLX (increasing 
concentrations as mentioned above) and E 2 (constant 
concentration 30 pM) yielded a significant increase in 
luciferase activity as compared to E 2 , whereas the highest 
concentration tested induced a significant decrease in 
luciferase activity (Figure 2). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the light of the recent findings on FLX interactions 
with the nuclear estrogenic receptors (ERs), we aimed at 
assessing if the main metabolite, NFLX, shares the same 
capacity to interfere with estrogenic signaling [17]. As the 
parent compound, NFLX is highly lipophilic and crosses 
the blood-brain barrier to accumulate in the brain, where 
it acts as an antidepressant by selectively blocking the 
serotonin transporter [18]. However, the structural and 
functional similarities of the two compounds suggest that 
NFLX might also be an active ligand for nuclear ERs. 
Indeed, the results of the in vitro firefly-luciferase 
assay show that NFLX alone can induce estrogenic effects 
by activating the nuclear estrogenic receptors and thus 
affecting the ER-regulated gene expression. However, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Luciferase induction in T47D-Kbluc cells after 
exposure to NFLX. Results are expressed as % induction for 
the luciferase assay. Results represent the mean ± SEM of 3 
independent experiments. Significant results as compared to the 
negative control (DMSO treated cells) are marked with asterisks 
(*** for P-value &lt;0.001). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Luciferase induction in T47D-Kbluc cells after 
exposure to mixtures of NFLX (increasing concentrations) + 
E 2 (30 pM). Results are expressed as % induction for the luciferase 
assay. Results represent the mean ± SEM of 3 independent 
experiments. Significant results as compared to the control (E 2 30 
pM treated cells) are marked with asterisks (* for P-value &lt;0.05, 
** for P-value &lt;0.01). </p>



<p>Original Research </p>

<p>Clujul Medical 2015 Vol. 88 no. 3: 386-390 </p>

<p>the small magnitude of the observed effect (10% of E 2 
induction) suggests that NFLX is a weak ER agonist at high 
concentrations. 
We further tested mixtures of NFLX and E 2 to 
simulate the biological scenario where this compound 
would be present at the ERs alongside their natural 
ligand. In this case, NFLX caused an increase in the E 2 -
induced transcriptional activity at low (submicromolar) 
concentrations. Considering the fact that no effect was 
observed at these concentrations during individual testing, 
we hypothesize that NFLX can act in a synergistic manner 
with E 2 . Conversely, at 10 μM we observed a significant 
decrease in signal as compared to E 2 . This is in line with the 
previous finding from individual testing and suggests that 
NFLX can displace the natural ligand from the ERs, thus 
resulting in a decrease in signal due to the weak agonist 
properties of NFLX. 
These results may raise concern regarding the 
endocrine disruptive potential of NFLX, since the synergistic 
effect observed at submicromolar concentrations suggests 
that this compound may interfere with estrogenic signaling 
at therapeutic plasma concentrations, which are reported to 
be below 1 μM, with variations depending on FLX dose 
and CYP2D6/CYP2C9 genotype [19,20]. In the fetus and 
newborns, NFLX concentrations reach aproximately 70 
to 80% of the maternal plasma levels [21]. Also, during 
breastfeeding, the infants receive less than 1% of the 
maternal FLX dose through breast milk [21]. However, 
FLX, as well as NFLX are highly bound to plasma proteins 
(~95%) and therefore less compound may be available for 
receptor interaction in vivo compared to our in vitro studies 
[22,23]. Little is known about the level of FLX or NFLX 
protein binding and metabolism in the fetus and newborn 
[24]. Although higher concentrations can be achieved in 
brain tissue due to accumulation of FLX and NFLX, the 
biological significance of the observed effect of NFLX at 
10 μM remains unclear due to the fact that only total FLX-
NFLX concentrations have been reported for the human 
brain (~ 13 μM) [25]. Further in vitro and in vivo testing 
would be useful to understand the relevance of our present 
findings in the context of disrupted estrogenic signaling 
during development. 
A limitation of the present study lies in the fact 
that the observed interaction with the nuclear ERs was 
not confirmed through tests in the presence of total ER 
antagonists. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, this is the first study to report that 
NFLX has the potential to interfere with estrogenic 
signaling in vitro, either by increasing or decreasing the 
ER-mediated activity of 17β-estradiol. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>This paper was published under the frame of 
European Social Found, Human Resources Development 
Operational Programme 2007-2013, project no. 
POSDRU/159/1.5/136893. </p>







</text></tei>