<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4748904" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Several meta-analyses have shown no significant difference </p>

<p>in stent thrombosis (ST) between sirolimus eluting stents (SES) and 
paclitaxel eluting stents (PES). However, other meta-analyses have 
found SES to be superior to PES. Therefore, to solve this issue, we 
aim to compare the clinical outcomes between SES and PES during a 
follow-up period of about 1 or more years. 
We have searched Medline and EMBASE for randomized con-
trolled trials (RCTs) comparing SES with PES. These RCTs have been 
carefully analyzed and then different types of ST including ST defined 
by the Academic Research Consortium (ARC), acute ST, late and very 
late ST have all been considered as the clinical endpoints in this study. A 
follow-up period of about 1 year, between 1 and 2 years as well as a 
longer follow-up period between 1 and 5 years have been considered. 
Data were retrieved and combined by means of a fixed-effect model 
because of a lower heterogeneity observed among the results. Odd ratios 
(OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated and the pooled 
analyses were performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">RevMan</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.3</rs> software. 
Twenty-nine studies from 19 RCTs comprising of 16,724 patients 
(8115 patients in the SES group and 8609 patients in the PES group) 
satisfied the inclusion criteria and were included in this meta-analysis. 
No significant differences in ST have been observed between SES and 
PES. Results were as follow: definite ST with OR: 0.87; 95% CI: 0.64-
1.18, P ¼ 0.36; probable ST with OR:0.72; 95% CI: 0.42-1.21, 
P ¼ 0.21; definite, probable and/or possible ST with OR: 0.94; 95% 
CI: 0.75-1.17, P ¼ 0.57; acute ST with OR: 0.99; 95% CI: 0.38-2.56, 
P ¼ 0.98; subacute ST with OR: 0.72; 95% CI: 0.41-1.25, P ¼ 0.25; 
early ST with OR: 0.81; 95% CI: 0.53-1.25, P ¼ 0.34; late ST with OR: 
0.72; 95% CI: 0.39-1.34, P ¼ 0.30; very late ST with OR: 1.02; 95% CI: 
0.72-1.44, P ¼ 0.92; and any ST with OR: 0.86; 95% CI: 0.69-1.07, 
P ¼ 0.18. Long-term ST between 1 and 5 years with OR: 0.93; 95% CI: 
0.71-1.22, P ¼ 0.60 was also not significantly different. 
No significant difference in ST has been observed between patients 
treated with either SES or PES. Hence SES and PES can both be 
considered almost equally effective. </p>

<p>(Medicine 95(5):e2651) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CAD = coronary artery disease, DES = drug 
eluting stents, PES = paclitaxel eluting stents, SES = sirolimus 
eluting stents, ST = stent thrombosis. </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>tent thrombosis (ST) is a major concern for patients treated 
with drug eluting stents (DES). Sirolimus eluting stents 
(SES) and paclitaxel eluting stents (PES) have been the most 
commonly used first-generation DES. 
Several meta-analyses comparing SES with PES showed 
no significant difference in ST between these 2 types of stents. 
For example, the meta-analysis conducted by Gurm et al 
1 in 
2008, including 7455 patients, found no significant difference in 
ST between SES and PES. A similar result was reported in 
another meta-analysis of 6 randomized controlled trials (RCTs) 
including 1183 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. 
2 The 
result from the meta-analysis conducted by Zhang et al 
3 in 2010 
also showed no significant difference in ST among the 1173 
patients analyzed. Moreover, the meta-analysis conducted by 
Kastrati et al 
4 in 2005 including 3669 patients also showed a 
similar rate of ST between SES and PES in patients with 
coronary artery disease (CAD). Zhang et al's 
5 study which 
included both RCTs and observational studies, also did not find 
any significant difference in ST between these 2 groups among 
the patients from RCTs. 
However, ST was not always similar between SES and 
PES. The meta-analysis conducted by Schömig et al 
6 in 2007 
including 16 RCTs with 8695 patients surprisingly showed a 
significant reduction in ST with SES compared to PES. His 
study which included a large number of randomized patients 
could have had an effect on his results. 
Therefore, in order to solve this issue, we aim to combine 
old studies comparing SES and PES with new ones and conduct 
a meta-analysis with an even larger number of randomized 
patients (a total of 16,724 patients) to confirm whether a 
significant difference in ST between the use of SES and PES 
really exists or not. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Sources of Data and Search Strategy </p>

<p>We have searched Medline and EMBASE for RCTs by 
typing the words ''drug eluting stents/DES and percutaneous 
coronary intervention/PCI,'' and also replacing the word 
''DES'' by ''PES and/or SES'' or their full form ''paclitaxel 
eluting stents and sirolimus eluting stents.'' PES and SES have 
also been replaced by Taxus and Cypher, respectively. All </p>

<p>Editor: Ahmet Aykan. 
Received: October 15, 2015; revised: January 5, 2016; accepted: January 8, 
2016. 
From the Institute of Cardiovascular Diseases, the First Affiliated Hospital 
of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, Guangxi, P. R. China. 
Correspondence: Meng-Hua Chen, Institute of Cardiovascular Diseases, the 
First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, 
Guangxi 530027, P. R. China (e-mail: xyicucmh@sina.com). 
The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NoDerivatives License 4.0, which allows for redistribution, 
commercial and non-commercial, as long as it is passed along unchanged 
and in whole, with credit to the author. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000002651 </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>SYSTEMATIC REVIEW AND META-ANALYSIS </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>reference lists of related studies were also reviewed for relevant 
articles. No language restriction was applied. </p>

<p>Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria </p>

<p>Studies were included if: </p>

<p>(1) They were RCTs. 
(2) They compared sirolimus eluting stents (SES) with 
paclitaxel eluting stents (PES). 
(3) ST was reported among the clinical endpoints. </p>

<p>Studies were excluded if: </p>

<p>(1) They were non-RCTs (observational studies, reports, 
meta-analyses, letter to editors). 
(2) They did not compare SES with PES but instead, showed 
the effectiveness of SES and PES separately without 
comparison or compared SES or PES with another DES. 
(3) ST was not reported among the clinical endpoints. </p>

<p>Defining the Different Types of Stent 
Thromboses, Outcomes, and Follow-Up </p>

<p>Definite ST, probable ST, possible ST, acute, subacute, late 
and very late ST with a follow-up of 1 month, short-term follow-
up (1-12 months) and long-term follow-up (&gt;1 year) including 
a follow-up between 1 and 2 years, and 1 and 5 years were 
analyzed in this study. The different types of ST have been 
defined in Table 1. Table 2 shows the types of ST reported in 
each of the included trials. </p>

<p>Data Collection and Analysis </p>

<p>Study Selection </p>

<p>All titles and abstracts were independently screened by 2 
authors (PKB and ZW) and full papers of those studies which 
met the inclusion criteria were obtained for review. These 
studies were carefully checked. Disagreements were carefully 
discussed between these 2 authors, and if the authors could not 
reach a final decision, whether to include the study or not, 
disagreements were resolved by the help of the third author 
(MHC). </p>

<p>Data Extraction and Management </p>

<p>Data extraction was performed from full-text articles by 
the same 2 independent authors (PKB and ZW). Any disagree-
ment was resolved through discussion and consensus between 
these 2 authors. The following data were extracted from each of 
the trials: author identification, year of patient enrollment, year 
of publication, language of publication, study design, study 
population, patient characteristics, intervention and outcomes 
reported as well as the follow-up periods. </p>

<p>Assessment of Risk of Bias </p>

<p>The bias risk of the included trials was assessed with the 
components recommended by the Cochrane Collaboration. </p>

<p>7   Each of the included trials has been carefully assessed 
and a grade ranging from A to E has been allocated to specific 
trials depending on whether they satisfied all the components 
recommended by the Cochrane Collaboration. In other word, 
a grade between A to E was allocated to the trials depending 
on their risk of bias. Completely low risk of bias among all of 
these 6 components mentioned above corresponded to a grade 
A, whereas a grade E was given if this evaluation showed a 
high risk of bias among the data corresponding to 
these RCTs. 
Except for 1 trial which have been allocated a grade C, all 
the other trials have been allocated a grade B even if a few were 
almost on a range between an A and a B. </p>

<p>Methodological Quality and Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The selection of studies, collection and analysis of data, 
and reporting of the results obtained, followed the recommen-
dations of the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic 
Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) statement. The 
Cochrane Q-statistic and the I2-statistic tests were used to 
assess heterogeneity among the studies whereby P 0.05 
was considered statistically significant and P &gt; 0.05 was con-
sidered statistically insignificant. I2 described the total variation 
(due to heterogeneity rather than chance) across studies in terms 
of percentages whereby a value of 0% indicated no heterogen-
eity, and larger values especially from 50% and above indicated 
increasing heterogeneity. A fixed effect model was used if I2 
was &lt;50% and a random effect model was used if I2 was 
&gt;50%. Funnel plots were assessed for publication bias. Odd </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Definitions of the Different Types of Stent Thrombosis Reported in This Study </p>

<p>Types of Stent Thrombosis 
Definitions </p>

<p>Any stent thrombosis 
Defined as any type of stent thrombosis mentioned below (definite, probable, early, late, very late) 
Definite stent thrombosis 
Defined as thrombosis within the stent at autopsy or thrombectomy or angiographic confirmation by TIMI 
flow 0 with thrombus in the stent or the 5 mm edges or TIMI flow 1, 2, or 3 with thrombus and at least one 
of these within 48 hours: new onset resting angina, new ECG ischemic changes or typical rise and fall in 
cardiac biomarkers 
Probable stent thrombosis 
Any unexplained death within the first 30 days postprocedure. Any MI in the territory of implanted stent 
without angiographic confirmation and in the absence of any other obvious cause 
Possible stent thrombosis 
Defined as any unexplained death from 30 days after intracoronary stenting until the end of follow-up 
Acute stent thrombosis 
Occurring between 0 and 24 hours after stent implantation 
Subacute stent thrombosis 
Occurring between 24 hours and 30 days 
Early stent thrombosis 
Acute or subacute stent thrombosis can also be replaced by the term early stent thrombosis 
Late stent thrombosis 
Occurring between 30 days and 1 year 
Very sate stent thrombosis 
Occurring after 1 year </p>

<p>ECG ¼ electrocardiography, MI ¼ myocardial infarction, TIMI ¼ thrombolysis in myocardial Infarction. </p>

<p>Bundhun et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated 
for categorical variables. <rs id="software-1" type="software">RevMan</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5.3</rs> software was used for the 
statistical analysis. The authors had full access to and take full 
responsibility for the integrity of the data. All authors have read 
and agreed to the manuscript as written. Ethical approval was 
not required since this study is a systematic review and meta-
analysis of RCTs. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Figure 1 shows the flowchart of study selection. We 
identified 42 studies comparing SES with PES in patients with 
CAD. Thirteen studies were excluded (6 of them were meta-
analysis and 7 were observational studies). Finally, 29 studies 
from 19 RCTs that met the inclusion criteria comprising of 
16,724 patients (8115 patients in the SES group and 8609 </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Types of Stent Thrombosis Reported Among the Trials </p>

<p>Trial Name 
Outcome: Types of Stent Thromboses Reported </p>

<p>SIRTAX 
Any stent thrombosis, early, late, definite, probable, possible stent thromboses 
SORT OUT II 
Early, late, acute, subacute, definite, probable, possible stent thromboses 
CHINA 
Subacute stent thrombosis 
LIPSIA Yukon 
Definite, probable, possible stent thromboses 
TAXi 
Any stent thrombosis 
PROSIT 
Any stent thrombosis, acute, subacute, late, very late stent thromboses 
DiabeDES 
Definite, probable, possible stent thromboses 
ISRCTN90526229 
Subacute and late stent thromboses 
Long-DES 
Any stent thrombosis 
ISAR-DESIRE 2 
Definite stent thrombosis 
DES-DIABETES 
Acute, subacute, late and very late stent thromboses 
ZEST AMI 
Acute, subacute and late stent thromboses 
PASEO 
Definite, early, late and very late stent thromboses 
TAXUS 
Definite, probable, early, late, and very late stent thromboses 
ISAR-LEFT-MAIN 
Definite and probable stent thromboses 
REALITY 
Acute, subacute and late stent thromboses 
SINGLE KISS 
Any stent thrombosis 
J-DESsERT 
Definite and probable stent thromboses 
ZEST 
Definite, probable, acute, subacute, and late stent thromboses </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. The flow diagram for study selection. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 
Stent Thrombosis Between SES and PES </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>patients in the PES group) were included in this systematic 
review and meta-analysis. </p>

<p>General Characteristics of Included Trials </p>

<p>Table 3 reports the general features of all the 19 trials 
included in this meta-analysis. Features such as the number of 
participants involved in the SES group, number of participants 
involved in the PES group, the year of enrollment of patients for 
these trials, the follow-up periods as well as the Cochrane Bias 
Risk grade have been summarized in Table 3. </p>

<p>Baseline Characteristics of the Included Trials </p>

<p>Table 4 reports the baseline features of each of the included 
studies. Data from each study have been reported. The mean age 
of the patients, the percentage of male patients, the percentage 
of patients with hypertension, those patients who are current 
smokers and the percentage of patients who suffer from type 2 
diabetes mellitus have been listed in Table 4. 
No significant difference in age has been observed in 
patients from both groups. Almost all the studies reported 
similar number of male patients. Percentage of patients suffer-
ing from hypertension, smoking, and diabetes mellitus was 
almost similar in both groups. Overall, no significant differ-
ences have been observed in the baseline characteristics 
between these 2 groups. 
Baseline features for the studies 
14,19 have not been 
included since they were not made available by the authors 
in the original articles. </p>

<p>Main Results of This Meta-Analysis </p>

<p>The result for ST has been divided into several groups. 
Twelve thousand forty-five patients were analyzed for definite 
ST (5769 treated with SES and 6276 treated with PES), 11,415 
patients were analyzed for probable ST (5454 treated with SES 
and 5961 treated with PES), 11,545 patients were analyzed for </p>

<p>definite and probable/and or possible ST (5522 treated with SES 
and 6023 treated with PES), 6141 patients were analyzed for 
acute ST (3091 treated with SES and 3050 treated with PES), 
6536 patients were analyzed for subacute ST (3289 treated with 
SES and 3247 treated with PES), 9931 patients were analyzed 
for early ST (4722 treated with SES and 5209 treated with PES), 
8905 patients were analyzed for late ST (4204 treated with SES 
and 4696 treated with PES), 5788 patients were analyzed for 
very late ST (2646 treated with SES and 3142 treated with PES), 
and 16,724 patients were analyzed for any type of ST (8115 
treated with SES and 8609 treated with PES). 
The pooled analysis showed no significant difference 
between SES and PES in any category of ST. Since a lower 
heterogeneity has been observed, a fixed effect model has been 
used for the analysis. The results were as follow: definite ST 
with OR: 0.87; 95% CI: 0.64-1.18, P ¼ 0.36; probable ST with 
OR:0.72; 95% CI: 0.42-1.21, P ¼ 0.21; definite, probable and/ 
or possible ST with OR: 0.94; 95% CI: 0.75-1.17, P ¼ 0.57; 
acute ST with OR: 0.99; 95% CI: 0.38-2.56, P ¼ 0.98; subacute 
ST with OR: 0.72; 95% CI: 0.41-1.25, P ¼ 0.25; early ST with 
OR: 0.81; 95% CI: 0.53-1.25, P ¼ 0.34; late ST with OR: 0.72; 
95% CI: 0.39-1.34, P ¼ 0.30; very late ST with OR: 1.02; 95% 
CI: 0.72-1.44, P ¼ 0.92; and any ST with OR: 0.86; 95% CI: 
0.69-1.07, P ¼ 0.18. Table 5 summarizes the main result of this 
study and Figure 2A-C represents the detailed analysis of this 
meta-analysis. 
Excluding the trials with a follow-up period of 1 year or 
less, another analysis was carried out considering trials with a 
follow-up period between 1 and 2 years, and between 1 and 5 
years. However, even with these long-term follow-up periods, 
no significant differences in ST have been observed between 
SES and PES. Results were as follow: OR: 1.27; 95% CI: 0.83-
1.94, P ¼ 0.27 for a follow-up period between 1 and 2 years and 
OR: 0.93; 95% CI: 0.71-1.22, P ¼ 0.60 for a follow-up period 
between 1 and 5 years. These results have been illustrated in 
Figure 3. </p>

<p>TABLE 3. General Features of the Included Trials </p>

<p>TRIAL Name </p>

<p>Year of Patient 
Enrollment </p>

<p>number of patients in 
SES group (n) </p>

<p>number of patients 
in PES group (n) </p>

<p>Follow-Up 
(Months) </p>

<p>Cochrane 
Bias Score </p>

<p>SIRTAX 
2003-2004 
503 
509 
1, 9, 12, 24, 60 
B 
SORT OUT II 
2004-2006 
1065 
1033 
18, 60 
B 
CHINA 
2003-2004 
202 
196 
19 
C 
LIPSIA Yukon 
2006-2008 
118 
114 
9, 60 
B 
TAXi 
2003-2004 
102 
100 
&lt;1, 6 
B 
PROSIT 
2004-2006 
154 
154 
12, 36 
B 
DiabeDES 
2005-2006 
68 
62 
8 
B 
ISRCTN90526229 
2005-2007 
196 
201 
1, 9 
B 
Long-DES 
2004-2005 
250 
250 
1, 9 
B 
ISAR-DESIRE 2 
2007-2009 
225 
225 
12 
B 
DES-DIABETES 
2005-2006 
200 
200 
9, 48 
B 
ZEST AMI 
2006-2007 
110 
110 
12 
B 
PASEO 
2003-2005 
90 
90 
12, 24 
B 
TAXUS 
2001-2004 
878 
1400 
48 
B 
ISAR-LEFT-MAIN 
2005-2007 
305 
302 
1 
B 
REALITY 
2003-2004 
684 
669 
12 
B 
SINGLE KISS 
2007-2008 
380 
391 
12 
B 
J-DESsERT 
2008-2010 
1707 
1719 
12 
B 
ZEST 
2006-2008 
878 
884 
1, 12 
B </p>

<p>PES ¼ paclitaxel eluting stents, SES ¼ sirolimus eluting stents. </p>

<p>Bundhun et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>For all of the above analyses, sensitivity analyses yielded 
consistent results. Based on a visual inspection of the funnel 
plots, there has been no evidence of publication bias for the 
included studies that assessed these ST. The funnel plots have 
been illustrated in Figure 4A and B. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Many recently published meta-analyses showed no 
differences in ST associated with SES and PES. However, </p>

<p>the meta-analysis conducted by Schömig et al 
6 in 2007 surpris-
ingly showed a significant reduction in ST with the use of SES 
compared to PES. Compared to many previous studies, his 
study included a larger number of randomized patients. There-
fore, to confirm the existence or absence of any significant 
difference in ST between SES and PES, old and new studies 
were combined to conduct this meta-analysis. 
Among the 48.5% patients treated with SES, and the 51.5% 
patients treated with PES, no significant difference in ST has </p>

<p>TABLE 4. Baseline Features of the Included Studies </p>

<p>Trial Name 
Associated Studies 
Age (Years) 
Males (%) 
HT (%) 
Cs (%) 
DM (%) </p>

<p>SIRTAX 
SES/PES 
SES/PES 
SES/PES 
SES/PES 
SES/PES 
Billinger et al </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>-
73.6/75.9 
67.2/70.2 
31.8/28.5 
21.5/18.3 
Räber et al </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>62.0/62.0 
76.0/78.0 
60.0/57.0 
37.0/36.0 
22.0/18.0 
Togni et al </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>-
53.2/79.2 
63.6/63.2 
35.7/35.6 
24.4/18.5 
Windecker et al </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>62.0/62.0 
75.9/78.4 
60.0/62.3 
36.6/35.6 
21.5/18.3 
SORT OUT 
Bligaard et al </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>64.5/63.6 
74.1/75.5 
48.3/47.3 
39.4/39.2 
15.2/14.7 
Galløe et al </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>64.5/63.6 
74.1/75.5 
48.3/47.3 
39.4/39.2 
15.2/14.7 
CHINA 
Ling </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>-
-
-
-
-
LIPSIA Yukon 
Desch et al </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>67.0/67.3 
69.0/68.0 
98.0/97.0 
23.0/27.0 
100/100 
Stiermaier et al </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>67.0/67.3 
69.0/68.0 
98.0/97.0 
23.0/27.0 
100/100 
TAXi 
Goy et al </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>65.0/63.0 
77.5/83.0 
58.8/63.0 
25.5/26.0 
32.4/36.0 
PROSIT 
Lee et al </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>60.0/60.0 
76.0/76.6 
45.5/40.9 
61.7/55.8 
22.1/28.6 
Kim et al </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>-
-
-
-
-
DiabeDES 
Jensen et al </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>62.6/64.4 
83.8/79.0 
63.2/71.0 
38.2/25.8 
82.4/85.5 
Maeng et al </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>66.0/65.0 
84.0/74.0 
63.0/75.0 
38.0/23.0 
83.0/87.0 
ISRCTN90526229 
Juwana et al </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>61.0/61.0 
69.0/74.0 
27.0/33.0 
50.0/55.0 
10.7/6.5 
Long-DES 
Kim et al </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>61.4/60.7 
67.2/61.2 
55.2/54.8 
37.2/37.6 
32.8/33.6 
ISAR-DESIRE 2 
Kufner et al </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>66.6/66.8 
79.0/73.5 
73.5/72.0 
10.5/12.0 
38.2/33.8 
Mehilli et al </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>66.4/67.1 
79.2/74.3 
72.4/72.4 
11.6/12.4 
38.2/33.8 
DES-DIABETES 
Lee et al </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>61.1/60.7 
61.0/55.0 
57.0/62.0 
27.0/28.5 
100/100 
Lee et al </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>61.1/60.7 
61.0/55.0 
57.0/62.0 
27.0/28.5 
100/100 
ZEST AMI 
Lee et al </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>57.8/59.3 
86.4/82.7 
38.2/53.6 
56.4/61.8 
26.4/23.6 
PASEO 
Di Lorenzo et al </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>62.0/63.0 
71.1/68.9 
27.8/26.7 
24.4/24.4 
27.8/23.3 
TAXUS 
Mauri et al </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>61.9/62.8 
71.6/71.5 
63.8/72.1 
21.2/23.8 
22.2/25.4 
Stone et al </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>61.9/62.4 
71.6/72.4 
63.8/69.3 
21.2/23.7 
22.2/23.2 
ISAR-LEFT M 
Mehilli et al </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>69.3/68.8 
80.0/75.0 
69.0/70.0 
10.0/10.0 
28.0/30.0 
REALITY 
Morice et al </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>62.6/62.6 
74.1/72.0 
65.5/67.6 
20.2/22.0 
27.3/28.7 
SINGLE KISS 
Nasu et al </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>67.0/66.0 
79.0/80.0 
75.0/69.0 
29.0/26.0 
40.0/44.0 
J-DESsERT 
Otsuka et al </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>70.1/70.1 
72.7/72.0 
80.2/83.1 
18.0/18.3 
48.8/49.3 
ZEST 
Park et al </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>61.9/62.0 
67.3/65.8 
58.9/61.1 
29.2/27.5 
28.1/27.7 </p>

<p>Cs ¼ current smoker, DM ¼ diabetes mellitus, HT ¼ hypertension, PES ¼ paclitaxel eluting stents, SES ¼ sirolimus eluting stents. </p>

<p>TABLE 5. Summary of the Main Results of This Study </p>

<p>Outcomes 
Events in SES Group 
Events in PES Group 
OR With 95% CI 
P-Value 
I2 (%) </p>

<p>Definite ST 
76/5769 
93/6276 
0.87 [0.64-1.18] 
0.36 
3 
Probable ST 
22/5454 
33/5961 
0.72 [0.42-1.21] 
0.21 
0 
D/P or Po ST 
167/5522 
183/6023 
0.94 [0.75-1.17] 
0.57 
14 
Acute ST 
6/3091 
6/3050 
0.99 [0.38-2.56] 
0.98 
0 
Subacute ST 
21/3289 
29/3247 
0.72 [0.41-1.25] 
0.25 
0 
Early ST 
36/4722 
47/5209 
0.81 [0.53-1.25] 
0.34 
0 
Late ST 
16/4204 
24/4696 
0.72 [0.39-1.34] 
0.30 
0 
Very late ST 
65/2646 
67/3142 
1.02 [0.72-1.44] 
0.92 
0 
Any ST 
151/8115 
179/8609 
0.86 [0.69-1.07] 
0.18 
0 </p>

<p>CI ¼ confidence interval, OR ¼ odd ratio, PES ¼ paclitaxel eluting stents, SES ¼ sirolimus eluting stents, ST ¼ stent thrombosis. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 
Stent Thrombosis Between SES and PES </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>

<p>been observed between these 2 groups. 1.9% of the patients in 
the SES group and 2.08% of the patients in the PES group 
suffered ''any'' ST (meaning any kind of ST). However, this 
result was not statistically significant. The result was still not 
statistically significant during a follow-up between 1 and 2 
years as well as during a follow-up period between 1 and 
5 years. 
Despite of including a larger number of randomized 
patients in our study, our result was similar to the meta-analyses 
conducted by Gurm et al in 2008, 
1 Zhang et al in 2010 and 2014, 
Kufner et al in 2011 and Kastrati et al in 2005. 
2-5 These studies 
had a limited number of patients and 2 of these studies were </p>

<p>conducted on patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Despite 
these differences, our study also showed similar results. Even 
many retrospective studies as well as the observational studies 
with a very large number of consecutive patients comparing 
SES with PES showed an equal rate of ST between these 
2 groups. 
In this current Era, which can be considered as a ''win-
ning'' world for the DES, the use of bare-metal stents (BMS) is 
often only indicated when the use of DES is contraindicated. 
The use of DES clinically, has significantly lowered the inci-
dence of several major adverse cardiovascular events as well as 
reduced the incidence of restenosis after PCI compared to the </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Forest plot comparing stent thrombosis between SES and PES. </p>

<p>Bundhun et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 </p>

<p>6 | www.md-journal.com </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Continued </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 
Stent Thrombosis Between SES and PES </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 7 </p>

<p>use of BMS. However, the use of DES is still associated with a 
higher rate of ST. 
As shown in our results, and in the results of many other 
studies, the comparison of ST between the 2 first-generation 
DES has resulted in no significant difference in ST between SES 
and PES. However, it is a fact that most of the drugs which are 
currently approved to coat stents used in coronary angioplasty 
do not differentiate or simply do not recognize the difference 
between proliferative vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs) 
and endothelial cells (ECs). 
37 The specification of these anti-
proliferative drugs which is normally very important, is often 
lacking and therefore, the proliferation and migration of 
VSMCs and ECs in the vessel are affected. These antiproli-
ferative drugs also cause the inhibition of neointimal hyperpla-
sia and they also severely affect the endothelial regeneration 
which is very important for the healing of these injured vessels 
and finally resulting in an incomplete reendothelialization. 
Because of this insufficient reendothelialization, late/long-term 
ST often manifests. </p>

<p>38-39   Moreover, p27 is a component expressed by arteries. When 
arteries are injured, p27 is rapidly downregulated due to mech-
anisms initiated by activated VSMC triggering intimal hyper-
plasia which then results in arterial restenosis. Overexpression 
of exogenous p27 in VSMC results in mechanisms that led to the 
significant reduction in neointimal formation. Studies have 
shown sirolimus, which is the coating material of certain 
DES, would inhibit the breakdown of p27, as well as induce 
the increased production of p27 thus preventing the </p>

<p>proliferation and migration of VSMC and could therefore 
inhibit reendothelialization of vessels by this way. 
40-41 Also, 
overexpression of p27 without sparring ECs could prevent the 
normal physiological function of the injured blood vessels and 
this could further increase the risk of late ST among the 
several DES. 
Even though the use of DES is associated with a higher rate 
of ST, our study showed a similar rate of ST between SES and 
PES. However, to further minimize ST in similar patients with 
CAD, other researches have introduce the microRNA-based 
strategy in coating stents. 
42 MicroRNA has been described 
previously. 
43 This microRNA-based strategy can strictly reduce 
restenosis by selectively inhibiting the proliferation and 
migration of VSMC without disturbing or inhibiting reendothe-
lialization or causing impairment to the function of EC. Hence, 
incorporating the microRNA-based strategy in stents could 
increase the overexpression of p27 and at the same time protect 
ECs thus reducing ST in those patients treated with DES after 
PCI. Further studies should be conducted to confirm the effect 
of this microRNA-based strategy to make sure whether it truly 
protects ECs. 
42 This will be a revolution in the field of 
Interventional Cardiology. 
Our results showed SES and PES to have a similar rate of 
ST even during the long-term follow-up. However, a few 
studies also showed results which were different from our 
study. For example, the meta-analysis including 16 RCTs 
comparing SES with PES in patients with CAD published by 
Schömig et al 
6 in 2007 showed a completely different result </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Continued </p>

<p>Bundhun et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>from ours. His study surprisingly showed ST to be significantly 
lower in the SES group compared to the PES group. However, in 
his study, ST was not reported according to the Academic 
Research Consortium (ARC) criteria which defined ST as 
definite and probable ST. Also, data which the author had used 
in his meta-analysis were completely different from that of our 
study because majority of his data were directly obtained from 
unpublished articles whose abstracts were represented and 
discussed in international meetings or from principal investi-
gators. In our study, ST was reported according to ARC and we 
did not include data from unpublished articles. 
The study by Bangalore et al 
44 also showed different 
results from ours. His study which compared the effectiveness 
and safety between BMS and DES, performed a mixed treat-
ment comparison meta-analysis (MTC meta-analysis) com-
monly known as a network meta-analysis. ''An MTC meta-
analysis is slightly different in the way that it is an extension that 
allows data to be combined and compared directly and 
indirectly,'' which, are supposedly not considered as random-
ized data, but are ''observational findings across trials, which 
might result in more bias, for example due to confounding,'' 
even if they included high-quality RCTs. 
7 However, in our 
study, all data were strictly obtained directly from RCTs. 
Even if there is no novelty in our idea, our study satisfies 
all the requirements for a meta-analysis, in terms of low 
heterogeneity, absent publication bias, and sensitivity analysis, 
and provides robust scientific validity to our findings. Hence, it 
is believed to show better results. </p>

<p>LIMITATIONS </p>

<p>This study also has several limitations. First of all, as a 
general consideration, authors always consider their studies to 
have a limited number of patients. Hence, even if our study 
included more than 16,000 patients, it is always a fact that due 
to a small population of patients compared to other studies, 
this could have an effect on our results too. Most of the RCTs 
had a follow-up period of at least 1 year; however, several 
other RCTs had a follow-up period of less or more than 
1 year. Therefore, combing different follow-up periods 
that are almost of the same length, but not exactly the same, 
could affect the results in one way or the other. Moreover, our 
study included patients from different categories of 
diseases. For example, a few studies were conducted on 
the general population suffering from CAD; however, other 
studies were conducted on patients with long coronary 
lesions, ST elevated myocardial infarction or on patients 
suffering from type 2 diabetes mellitus. These patients have 
other abnormalities, for example patients with type 2 diabetes 
mellitus have platelet dysfunction which expose them to a 
higher possibility of ST after PCI. So, this could also be a 
limitation in our study. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Similar to many meta-analyses and RCTs, no significant 
difference in ST has been observed between SES and PES. 
Hence, both SES and PES are expected to be equally effective. </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Forest plot comparing long-term (1-2 years and 1-5 years) stent thrombosis between SES and PES. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 
Stent Thrombosis Between SES and PES </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 9 </p>



<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Funnel plots for sensitivity analyses. </p>

<p>Bundhun et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 5, February 2016 
Stent Thrombosis Between SES and PES </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 11 </p>

</text></tei>