<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4905837" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT. The purpose of this study was to investigate the anti-Newcastle disease virus (NDV) activities of baicalin from Scutellaria ba-
icalensis, a Traditional Chinese Medicine in vitro. Chicken embryo fibroblasts (CEFs) were infected with NDV, and quantitative analysis of 
apoptotic cells was performed using flow cytometry. Cytotoxicity and anti-viral activities of baicalin were studied using the MTT method. 
The results showed that the maximal safe concentrations of baicalin to CEFs was 1 × 2 −2 mg/ml. Baicalin could directly kill NDV, inhibit 
the infectivity of NDV to CEF and block intracellular NDV. It inhibited the apoptosis of NDV-infected CEFs and suppressed the spread of 
NDV. These results indicate that baicalin has strong anti-NDV activity and has the potential for use as components of an antiviral drug. 
KEY WORDS: apoptosis, Baicalin, newcastle disease virus (NDV), Virus inhibitory rate 
Y. JIA ET AL. </p>

<p>
was purchased from Thermo Fisher Scientific (Shanghai, 
China). The flow cytometry was purchased from BD Biosci-
ences (Shanghai, China). Unless otherwise stated, all other 
reagents were from Sigma-Aldrich (Shanghai, China). 
Cells and virus: The chicken embryo fibroblasts (CEFs) 
were prepared using 10-day-old specific pathogen free 
chicken embryos. The chick embryo was removed right after 
the eggshell was disinfected and opened. The head, extremi-
ties and viscera were removed, washed with phosphate buff-
ered solution (PBS), cut into 1-to 2-mm 3 pieces and washed 
three times with PBS. A 0.25% trypsin solution was added to 
the samples for 30 min at 37°C, and then, the samples were 
centrifuged. The precipitate was washed three times with 
PBS and filtered through a 4-tier gauze. Cells were counted 
and diluted into 1 × 10 6 ml −1 with 10% Dulbecco's modified 
Eagle's medium (DMEM) and inoculated in 96-well culture 
plates at 37°C in a humid atmosphere of 5% CO 2 for 12 hr. 
The strain of NDV (La Sota strain IV) propagated in the 
10-day-old specific pathogen-free chicken embryos, was 
obtained from the Poultry Research Laboratory of Sichuan 
Agricultural University. The virus was stored at −80°C until 
use. 
Virulence of NDV assay: The virulence of NDV was 
expressed as median tissue culture infective dose (TCID 50 ). 
NDV was prepared by 10-fold dilution (10 −1 -10 −8 ). Then, 
100 µl of viral solution was added to each well of 96-well 
plates containing CEF monolayers (four wells for each 
concentration). CEF, added to 100-µl DMEM basal medium 
with 2 µl/ml TPCK-trypsin, was used as the control. After 
2 hr of incubation at 37°C, 100 µl of DMEM basal medium 
with 2 µl/ml TPCK-trypsin was added to each well. After 
72 hr, the cytopathic effect was observed and recorded, and 
the TCID 50 value of NDV was calculated using the Reed-
Muench formula. 
Cytotoxicity analysis: Baicalin was diluted two-fold se-
rially from 2 mg/ml to eight concentrations with DMEM. 
CEFs were prepared and cultivated in 96-well plates. CEF 
monolayers in the 96-well plates were exposed to baicalin 
at a series of concentrations (four wells each concentration). 
After culture for 72 hr in a 37°C humid atmosphere of 5% 
CO 2 , 30 µl of MTT was added to each well and incubated 
for 4 hr. The supernatant was then removed and 100 µl of 
dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) was added to each well. The 
plates were shaken for 10 min to dissolve the crystals 
completely. The absorbance at 570 nm (A570 value) was 
measured using a microliter enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assay reader. Larger A570 values contribute to more live 
cells, since A570 values are correlated with the number of 
live cells. When the A570 values of the Chinese crude drug 
group were not significantly lower than that of the cells in 
the control group (indicating that the Chinese crude drugs 
had no cytotoxicity), the corresponding concentrations were 
considered a maximally safe concentration for CEFs. All 
experiments were carried out in triplicate [3]. 
Antiviral assay: According to the results of the cytotoxic-
ity analysis, baicalin at eight different concentrations, from 
250 to 1.953 µg/ml, was used for determination of anti-viral 
activity using the MTT method. When treating CEFs cul-</p>

<p>tured in monolayers, the two-fold serial dilutions of Chinese 
crude drugs and 100 TCID 50 NDV were added to the cell 
plates, respectively, using three different methods: 
Pre-addition of the drug: Baicalin solution was first added 
to CEFs at 100 µl per well (four wells per concentration). 
After incubation for 4 hr, the baicalin solution was removed, 
cells were washed twice with PBS, and 100 µl of the virus 
solution was added to each well. 
Post-addition of the drug: The virus solution was added 
to the CEFs first. After incubation for 2 hr, baicalin solu-
tion was removed, cells were washed twice with PBS, and 
baicalin solution was added to the wells (four wells each 
concentration). 
Simultaneous-addition of the drug and virus after mixing: 
Each concentration of baicalin solution was mixed with the 
virus solution, incubated for 2 hr at 37°C and then added to 
the CEFs (four wells for each concentration). At the same 
time, the NDV control group (virus only), cell control group 
(DMEM only) and the black group (no cells) were estab-
lished [32]. 
All CEF plates were placed in a 5% CO 2 incubator at 
37°C. After 72 hr when the NDV control group showed the 
appearance of cytopathic effect (CPE), the CEF viability 
was measured using the MTT assay [26]. The mean cellular 
A570 values were used as indices of anti-viral activity. Ba-
icalin was considered to have significant anti-viral activity 
when the A570 value of the Chinese crude drug group was 
significantly higher than that of the virus control group was 
[14]. 
The virus inhibitory rate was calculated based on the 
formula [10]: Virus inhibitory rate=(the highest Ā570 value 
of baicalin group −Ā570 value of the virus control group)/ 
(Ā570 value of the cell control group −Ā570 value of the 
virus control group)×100%. 
Flow cytometry analysis of apoptosis (FACS): The CEFs 
were inoculated in 6-well culture plates at 37°C in a hu-
mid atmosphere of 5% CO 2 until they were cultured into a 
monolayer. A 100 TCID 50 virus solution was added to the 
CEFs. After incubation for 2 hr at 37°C, the virus solution 
was removed, the cells were washed twice with PBS, and 
the maximal safe concentration of the baicalin solution was 
added (three wells for each concentration). At the same time, 
the NDV control group (virus only) and the cell control 
group (DMEM only) were established. All CEF plates were 
placed in a 5% CO 2 incubator at 37°C for 72 hr until the 
NDV control group had the appearance of CPE. 
Each group was collected by trypsinization, washed 
twice with PBS, resuspended in one time binding buffer at a 
concentration of 1 × 10 6 cells/ml and subjected to Annexin 
V-FITC/PI staining. The samples were analyzed by <rs type="software">FACS</rs> 
and <rs type="software">Cell Quest</rs> Research Software [4]. 
Statistical analysis: Data were expressed as mean± stan-
dard error (SE), and Duncan's multiple range test was used 
to analyze the difference among the Chinese crude drug and 
control groups. Differences between means were considered 
significant at P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>TRADITIONAL CHINESE MEDICINE </p>



<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The cytotoxicity of baicalin to CEFs: The A570 values of 
each group are listed in Table 1. The A570 values of baicalin 
in the 1 × 2 −2 mg/ml groups were not significantly lower than 
those of the corresponding cell control groups (P &gt;0.05). 
Therefore, these concentrations could be considered as the 
maximum safe concentrations. 
Antiviral activity of baicalin in CEF: 
(1) Antiviral activity of baicalin before addition of the 
drug 
The A570 values and the virus inhibition rates of each 
group are listed in Table 2. The A570 values of baicalin in the 
1 × 2 −9 -1 × 2 −2 mg/ml groups were significantly higher than 
the A570 values of the NDV control groups were (P&lt;0.05). 
The highest virus inhibitory rates of the baicalin groups were 
100%. 
(2) Antiviral activity of Baicalin in post-addition of the 
drug 
The A570 values and the virus inhibition rates of each 
group are listed in Table 2. The A570 values of baicalin in the 
1 × 2 −9 -1 × 2 −2 mg/ml groups were significantly higher than 
the A570 values of the NDV control groups were (P&lt;0.05). 
The highest virus inhibition rates of the baicalin groups were 
&gt;100%. 
(3) Antiviral activity of baicalin in simultaneous-addition 
of the drug and virus after mixing 
The A570 values and the virus neutralization rates of each 
group are listed in Table 2. The A570 values of baicalin in the 
1 × 2 −9 -1 × 2 −2 mg/ml groups were significantly higher than 
the A570 values of the NDV control groups were (P&lt;0.05). 
The highest virus neutralization rates of the baicalin groups 
were higher than 100%. 
Annexin V-FITC/PI staining: FACS was used in the quan-
titative analysis of apoptotic cells after NDV infection by 
staining cells with a combination of fluorescent Annexin 
V-FITC and PI (Table 3, Fig. 1). The early and late stage 
apoptosis rates of the cell control groups were 20.75% and 
27.37%, respectively. The early and late apoptosis rates of 
NDV control groups were 24.52% and 36.20%, respectively. 
The early and late apoptosis rates of the maximum concen-</p>

<p>tration for the baicalin groups were 18.17% and 27.33%, 
respectively. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The cell absorbance value (A570 value) is an index that 
reflects the number of living cells and is related to cell 
growth. A higher value of A570 indicates higher activity of 
CEF [19]. In this study, a high A570 value reflected good 
anti-viral activity of the Chinese crude drugs. The Chinese 
crude drugs were indicated to have no cytotoxicity when 
their A570 values were not significantly lower than those 
of control group were, and the corresponding concentration 
could be considered as the maximally safe concentration for 
CEFs. The results of the safe concentration indicated that 
at baicalin concentrations higher than 1 × 2 −2 mg/ml, cell 
growth was inhibited. Baicalin, within a certain range of 
concentrations, demonstrated cytotoxicity. 
The virus inhibitory rate directly reflects the antiviral 
potential of a drug [10]. The pre-addition of baicalin was 
thought to exert inhibitory action at a very early stage in 
the viral infection cycle as the virus adsorbs or penetrates 
into the host cell [25]. NDV infection is achieved via two 
envelope proteins, hemagglutinin-neuraminidase (HN) and 
the fusion protein (F) [7]. HN binds to sialic acid-containing </p>

<p>Table 1. The cytotoxicity of Baicalin to CEF 
(A570 value) </p>

<p>Concentration (mg/ml) 
Baicalin (A570) </p>

<p>1 × 2 
0.211 ± 0.007 d) 
1 × 2°0.347 ± 0.009 c) 
1 × 2 −1 
0.421 ± 0.007 b) 
1 × 2 −2 
0.472 ± 0.011 a) 
1 × 2 −3 
0.477 ± 0.015 a) 
1 × 2 −4 
0.481 ± 0.007 a) 
1 × 2 −5 
0.479 ± 0.004 a) 
1 × 2 −6 
0.477 ± 0.007 a) 
Cell control 
0.471 ± 0.007 a) 
Data are shown as the mean ± SE. a-d) Data within 
a column without the same superscripts P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Table 2. Effect of Baicalin on blocking, neutralizing and inhibiting NDV </p>

<p>Concentration 
(mg/ml) </p>

<p>Block 
Neutralize 
Inhibit </p>

<p>Baicalin (A570) Blocking rate Baicalin (A570) Neutralization rate Baicalin (A570) Inhibition rate </p>

<p>1 × 2 −2 
0.446 ± 0.005 a) 
100.00% 
0.447 ± 0.007 a) 
100.41% 
0.455 ± 0.006 a) 
103.70% 
1 × 2 −3 
0.443 ± 0.010 a) 
98.77% 
0.445 ± 0.006 a) 
99.59% 
0.450 ± 0.008 a, b) 
101.65% 
1 × 2 −4 
0.443 ± 0.007 a) 
98.77% 
0.437 ± 0.005 a, b) 
96.30% 
0.449 ± 0.006 a, b) 
101.23% 
1 × 2 −5 
0.430 ± 0.004 b) 
93.42% 
0.425 ± 0.007 b) 
91.36% 
0.447 ± 0.009 a, b) 
100.41% 
1 × 2 −6 
0.429 ± 0.008 b) 
93.00% 
0.412 ± 0.004 c) 
86.01% 
0.443 ± 0.005 a, b) 
98.77% 
1 × 2 −7 
0.406 ± 0.008 c) 
83.54% 
0.397 ± 0.005 d) 
79.84% 
0.444 ± 0.008 a, b) 
99.18% 
1 × 2 −8 
0.372 ± 0.011 d) 
69.55% 
0.381 ± 0.004 e) 
73.25% 
0.432 ± 0.009 b) 
94.24% 
1 × 2 −9 
0.345 ± 0.006 e) 
58.44% 
0.365 ± 0.007 f) 
66.67% 
0.422 ± 0.008 b) 
90.12% 
Cell control 
0.446 ± 0.008 a) 
-
0.446 ± 0.008 a) 
-
0.446 ± 0.008 a, b) 
-
NDV control 
0.203 ± 0.008 f) 
-
0.203 ± 0.008 g) 
-
0.203 ± 0.008 c) 
-
Data are shown as the mean ± SE. a-g) Data within a column without the same superscripts P&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Y. JIA ET AL. </p>

<p>
receptors, leading to virus adsorption, and promotes mem-
brane fusion causing virus penetration into host cells [8]. 
There are two sialic acid binding sites on the globular head 
region of HN [29]. Our results showed that the A570 values 
of all eight concentrations of the baicalin groups were sig-
nificantly higher than the A570 values of the corresponding 
virus control groups were, which indicated that they could 
prevent NDV infection. Baicalin could block HN binding to 
sialic acid-containing receptors and virus adsorption. 
The post-addition of Chinese crude drugs was thought 
to prevent viral protein synthesis. It may affect the trans-
membrane and intracellular signaling processes involved in 
regulating virus expression. These results were supported by 
previous findings that viral protein synthesis was prevented 
by carrageenan, as inhibition was observed only when the </p>

<p>compound was present during virus entry [23]. Damonte 
et al. reported that the few attempts had been made to find 
anti-viral substances by mainly focusing on the screening of 
probable ribonucleic acid (RNA) synthesis inhibitors, such 
as ribavirin and other nucleoside analogs [9]. In agreement 
with this idea, our results showed that the A570 values of 
all eight concentrations of the baicalin groups were sig-
nificantly higher than the A570 values of the corresponding 
virus control groups, which indicated that they could treat 
the NDV infection. Baicalin could inhibit viral protein or 
RNA synthesis. 
The mixed-addition of Chinese crude drugs and viruses 
was thought to cause direct inactivation of the viruses. Wang 
et al. reported that sulfated Lycium barbarum polysaccha-
ride at certain concentrations could directly kill NDV [27]. 
In agreement with this idea, our results showed that the A570 
values of all eight concentrations of the baicalin groups were 
significantly higher than the A570 values of the correspond-
ing virus control groups were, which indicated that they 
could directly kill NDV. 
The NDV inhibitory rate of baicalin decreased in a dose-
dependent manner. Both of the blocking rate and neutraliza-
tion rate are significantly decreased as the decrease of the 
baicalin concentrations, but the inhibition rate is slightly de-
creased as the decrease of the baicalin concentrations. High 
concentrations of baicalin in the all three methods of addi-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Flow cytometry analysis of Annexin V/PI assay. In the four quadrants for each image, the right 
lower quadrant is for the early apoptosis rate, and the right upper quadrant is for the late apoptosis rate. 
A: Cell control; B: NDV control; C: CEFs treated with the maximum safe concentration of baicalin 
and 100 pfu/well of NDV. </p>

<p>Table 3. The Apoptosis rates of treatment groups </p>

<p>Classification 
Apoptosis rates (%) </p>

<p>Early stage 
Late stage </p>

<p>Baicalin 
18.17 ± 0.61 c) 
27.33 ± 0.71 b) 
Cells control 
20.75 ± 0.74 b) 
27.37 ± 0.59 b) 
NDV control 
24.52 ± 0.72 a) 
36.2 ± 0.65 a) </p>

<p>Data are shown as the mean ± SE. a-c) Data within a column without 
the same superscripts P&lt;0.01. </p>

<p>TRADITIONAL CHINESE MEDICINE </p>



<p>tion, such as 1 × 2 −2 mg/ml, 1 × 2 −3 mg/ml and 1 × 2 −4 mg/ 
ml, had strong effects on NDV. However, low concentrations 
of baicalin in combination with the simultaneous-addition 
of the drug and virus after mixing, such as 1 × 2 −7 mg/ml, 1 
× 2 −8 mg/ml and 1 × 2 −9 mg/ml, had the strongest effect in 
directly killing NDV of the three methods of addition. 
The highest virus inhibitory rate directly reflected the 
anti-viral potency. The highest virus inhibition rates and the 
highest virus neutralization rates of the baicalin groups were 
both higher than 100%. Our results showed that baicalin 
could suppress NDV as well as lead to CEF growth and pro-
liferation. Zhao et al. reported that baicalin could promote 
CEF growth significantly [33]. This view is consistent with 
the results of our study. 
NDV can induce apoptosis of infected CEF. To investi-
gate the anti-viral mechanism of baicalin, we evaluated the 
apoptosis of CFE by flow cytometry (FCM) [6]. Our results 
showed that baicalin could inhibit NDV-infected CEF apop-
tosis in both early and late stages of the infection process. 
The stages of apoptosis can be categorized into early and 
late, and the sum of the stages represents the total apoptosis 
rate. NDV induces apoptosis in cells through caspase-and 
p38-MAPK-dependent pathways [2]. Baicalin may in-
hibit NDV-infected CEF apoptosis by blocking the signaling 
pathway and thus, reduce the release of NDV. 
In recent years, the inhibitory effect of some TCM 
against NDV has been studied. Zhang et al. reported that 
some flavone ingredients from TCM could inhibit NDV-
infected cells, such as baical skullcap root flavones, wild 
dendranthema flower flavones, epimedium flavones and 
sanchi flavones. However, their toxicity is higher than that 
of baicalin is, and only flavone prescriptions with suitable 
compatibility can show good anti-viral activity [31]. Some 
polysaccharides from TCM also could inhibit NDV infection 
of cells, such as Chuanmingshen violaceum polysaccharide, 
Auricularia auricula polysaccharide and Tremella polysac-
charide. Anti-viral activity of these polysaccharides is insuf-
ficient, but sulfation could increase their anti-NDV activity 
[21, 24, 32]. 
In conclusion, baicalin can suppress, neutralize and block 
NDV in vitro, as well inhibit NDV-infected CEF apoptosis, 
leading to the subsequent suppression of the spreading of 
NDV infection. The compound has potential for use as com-
ponents of future anti-viral regimens. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS. This research was partially sup-
ported by the Science and Technology Support Program of 
Sichuan Province (Grant No.2015SZ0201) and Veterinary 
herbal immune technology research and innovation team of 
Jiaxing Vocational and Technical College [No.Jiazhiyuan 
(2012) 74]. </p>



<p>Y. JIA ET AL. </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>