<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4128692" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>effects of annatto-derived tocotrienol 
supplementation on osteoporosis induced 
by testosterone deficiency in rats </p>

<p>Background: Previous animal models have demonstrated that tocotrienol is a potential treatment 
for postmenopausal osteoporosis. This study evaluated the antiosteoporotic effects of annatto-
derived tocotrienol (AnTT) using a testosterone-deficient osteoporotic rat model. 
Methods: Forty rats were divided randomly into baseline, sham, orchidectomized, AnTT, 
and testosterone groups. The baseline group was euthanized without undergoing any surgical 
treatment or intervention. The remaining groups underwent orchidectomy, with the exception 
of the sham group. AnTT 60 mg/kg/day was given orally to the AnTT group, while the testos-
terone group received testosterone enanthate 7 mg/kg per week intramuscularly for 8 weeks. 
Structural changes in trabecular bone at the proximal tibia were examined using microcomputed 
tomography. Structural and dynamic changes at the distal femur were examined using histo-
morphometric methods. Serum osteocalcin and C-terminal of type 1 collagen crosslinks were 
measured. Bone-related gene expression in the distal femur was examined. 
Results: There were significant degenerative changes in structural indices in the orchidectomized 
group (P0.05), but no significant changes in dynamic indices, bone remodeling markers, or </p>

<p>gene expression (P0.05) when compared with the sham group. The AnTT group showed 
significant improvement in structural indices at the femur (P0.05) and significantly increased 
expression of bone formation genes (P0.05). Testosterone was more effective than AnTT in 
preventing degeneration of bone structural indices in the femur and tibia (P0.05). 
Conclusion: AnTT supplementation improves bone health in testosterone-deficient rats by 
enhancing bone formation. Its potential should be evaluated further by varying the dosage and 
treatment duration. 
Although the prevalence of osteoporosis in men is lower than that in women, 
1 male 
osteoporosis is still regarded as a tremendous health problem. Men with osteoporo-
sis suffer from higher mortality after a fracture when compared with their female 
counterparts. 
2,3 Osteoporotic fractures also cause a substantial financial burden to 
society and decrease quality of life for patients, 
4,5 so should be prevented. The age-
related decrease in testosterone is a major risk factor for male osteoporosis. 
6,7 Several 
pharmacologic antiosteoporotic agents are available on the market, including bisphos-
phonates, teriparatide, and strontium ranelate, but are not free of side effects. 
8 Calcium 
supplementation with and without vitamin D is commonly prescribed, but has been 
associated with an increased risk of cardiovascular events. 
9 This has prompted a search 
for other agents with the potential to prevent osteoporosis. </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Interventions in Aging 
5 August 2014 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1248 </p>

<p>Chin and Ima-nirwana </p>

<p>Tocotrienol is a subset of the vitamin E family, derived 
from plant oils, and has been shown to have antiosteoporotic 
effects. 
10,11 Previous studies in animal models of osteoporosis 
have demonstrated that mixtures of tocotrienols can prevent 
degenerative changes in trabecular bone induced by estrogen 
deficiency, 
12-14 free radicals, 
15 and nicotine. 
16 Tocotrienols 
have also been shown to preserve bone mineral density 
and calcium content in rats with dexamethasone-induced 
osteoporosis. 
17,18 These studies have used palm tocotrienols, 
which contain a substantial amount of alpha-tocopherol 
(αTF). Fujita et al have shown that αTF promotes fusion 
of osteoclasts and increases bone resorption, 
19 which might 
interfere with the bone-protective effects of a tocotrienol 
mixture containing αTF. However, previous studies have not 
used molecular techniques, so the bone-protective mecha-
nism of tocotrienol remains unclear. 
Annatto-derived tocotrienol (AnTT) contains a high 
proportion of δTT and virtually no αTF, 
20 so provides an 
opportunity to study the antiosteoporotic effects of tocot-
rienol without the interference of αTF. Abdul-Majeed et al 
found that osteoporotic changes due to estrogen deficiency 
were prevented in ovariectomized rats supplemented with 
AnTT 60 mg/kg for 8 weeks. 
21 We hypothesized that AnTT at 
this dose would be able to prevent male osteoporosis induced 
by testosterone deficiency. 
In the current study, we evaluated the effects of AnTT 
on trabecular bone in orchidectomized rats with respect to 
changes in bone structural indices, remodeling, and gene 
expression. In addition to previously used bone histomor-
phometric methods, we used microcomputed tomography 
(μCT) for more accurate three-dimensional estimation of 
bone structural parameters. Expression of genes related to 
bone formation and resorption was quantified to provide a 
mechanistic overview of how AnTT could prevent degen-
erative changes in bone. The information generated by this 
study could be used to determine whether AnTT acts as a 
preventive agent in male osteoporosis caused by testosterone 
deficiency. It also serves as a basis for use of AnTT in future 
clinical trials in humans. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Materials </p>

<p>The AnTT used in this study was a generous gift from 
American River Nutrition (Hadley, MA, USA). It was com-
posed of approximately 90% δTT and 10% γTT, with no αTF. 
It was diluted in olive oil (Bartolini Emilio, Arrone Terni, Italy) 
and administered orally at a dose of 60 mg/kg body weight. 
Olive oil was used for dilution because it contains a low level of </p>

<p>vitamin E (51 ppm). 
22 Testosterone enanthate (Jesalis Pharma, 
Jena, Germany) was diluted with peanut oil (Sime Darby, 
Subang Jaya, Malaysia) and administered intramuscularly at a 
dose of 7 mg/kg body weight. Peanut oil was used for dilution 
because the formulation used contains peanut oil. </p>

<p>Treatment of animals </p>

<p>Forty 3-month-old intact Sprague-Dawley rats (250-300 g) 
were purchased from the Laboratory Animal Research Unit, 
Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. 
They were acclimatized at the local vivarium for one week 
(room temperature, 12-hour light/dark cycle). The rats were 
housed singly in plastic cages with free access to tap water and 
standard rat chow (Gold Coin, Port Klang, Malaysia). They 
were stratified into five groups using random numbers gener-
ated by statistical software. Orchidectomy was performed in 
the orchidectomized, AnTT, and testosterone groups. A sham-
operated group underwent similar surgical treatment but their 
testes were not removed. The baseline group was sacrificed 
without undergoing any surgical treatment or intervention. The 
AnTT group received AnTT daily (60 mg/kg body weight, 
oral gavage) for 8 weeks, while the other groups received 
an equal volume of the olive oil vehicle. The testosterone 
group received weekly testosterone enanthate injections 
(7 mg/kg body weight, intramuscularly) for 8 weeks while 
the other groups received an equal volume of the peanut oil 
vehicle. Treatment was initiated a week after orchidectomy. 
The weight of each rat was monitored weekly using a digital 
scale (Tanita Model 1,144, Tokyo, Japan) and recorded to the 
nearest 1 g. At the end of the treatment period, the rats were 
euthanized using diethyl ether (HmbG Chemicals </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Hamburg, 
Germany), after which their femoral and tibial bones were 
harvested. After the soft tissue was removed, the bones were 
either stored in 10% formalin solution for histomorphometric 
and μCT evaluation, or at -70°C for study of gene expression. 
The study protocol was reviewed and approved by the animal 
ethics committee at Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia (Code 
FP/FAR/2012/IMA/18-July/445-July-2012-April-2014). </p>

<p>MicroCT analysis </p>

<p>Trabecular parameters were investigated at the left proximal 
tibia using a μCT 40 scanner (Scanco Medical, Brüttisellen, 
Switzerland). A sample was placed in a holder and scanned 
in an upright position. The volume of interest (200 slices) 
selected started from 1.5 mm distal to the lowest point of the 
proximal growth plate and extended towards the distal end of 
the tibia. Images were acquired at 70 kVp and 114 μA with 
high resolution. The integration time was 200 msec. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1249 </p>

<p>effects of tocotrienol in male osteoporosis </p>

<p>Contouring was performed using a semiautomated 
method to select the trabecular region. Three-dimensional 
reconstruction and evaluation were performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Scanco</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Scanco Medical</rs>) to measure the following bone 
parameters: trabecular bone volume, trabecular number, 
trabecular separation, trabecular thickness, structural model 
index, and connectivity density. </p>

<p>Bone processing and histomorphometry </p>

<p>Fluorochrome labeling was performed using calcein (Sigma-
Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) 20 mg/kg body weight admin-
istered intraperitoneally on days 9 and 2 before the rats were 
euthanized. Undecalcified left rat femurs were embedded in 
polymethyl methacrylate (Sigma-Aldrich) and sectioned at a 
thickness of 9 μm using a microtome (Leica RM2235, Nuss-
loch, German). Sections to be used for evaluation of bone struc-
ture were stained using the Von Kossa method, while unstained 
sections were used for assessment of bone dynamics. 
The region assessed was the secondary spongiosa in 
the metaphyseal region, which is 3-7 mm from the lowest 
point of the growth plate and 1 mm from the lateral cortex. 
Structural parameters were investigated by an automated 
method using an image analyzer (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">MediaCybernetics</rs> <rs id="software-2" type="software">Image 
Pro-Plus</rs>, Rockville, MD, USA). Dynamic parameters were 
investigated using a fluorescence microscope (Nikon Eclipse 
80i, Tokyo, Japan) and measured manually using a Weibel 
grid. The structural parameters measured included trabecular 
bone volume, thickness, number, and separation. Dynamic 
parameters measured included single-labeled surface, 
double-labeled surface, mineralizing rate, mineral apposition 
rate, and bone formation rate. </p>

<p>Biochemical analysis </p>

<p>Blood was collected from the rats prior to euthanasia via 
the retro-orbital sinus. Serum was extracted immediately 
after centrifuging the blood at 3,000 rpm for 10 minutes. 
The serum was stored at -70°C until analysis. Osteocalcin 
and carboxy-terminal of type 1 collagen crosslinks were 
measured using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kit 
(Immunodiagnostic Systems, Tyne and Wear, UK). </p>

<p>gene expression analysis </p>

<p>A sample of trabecular bone was taken from the distal right 
femur and homogenized in buffer provided by the manu-
facturer using a high-speed homogenizer (Bead Ruptor 24, 
Omni, Kennesaw, GA, USA) and steel beads at 4°C. The 
tissue lysate was incubated at 65°C and centrifuged to pre-
cipitate the debris. </p>

<p>mRNA expression was quantified using the QuantiGene 
Plex 2.0 
® technique (Panomics/Affymetrix Inc, Santa Clara, 
CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Oligonucleotide probe sets for the genes of interest were 
designed by the manufacturer. The tissue lysate was pipetted 
into a 96-well plate preloaded with capture reagent and a 
probe set. After incubation overnight at 54°C, hybridization 
with the preamplifier, amplifier, and biotinylated label was 
carried out. Luminescence was measured using a Luminex </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>instrument (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA), and the mean 
fluorescence intensity specific for each gene (proportional to 
the mRNA captured by the bead) was generated. Expression 
of each gene was normalized to the expression of glyceral-
dehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase. The genes of interest 
are listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Distribution of the data was assessed using the Shapiro-Wilk 
test and all data were found to be normally distributed. One-
way analysis of variance, with either Tukey's or Dunnett's 
T3 as the post hoc test, was used to detect significant differ-
ences in the variables of interest between the study groups. 
All data are presented as the mean and standard error of the 
mean. P-values 0.05 were considered to be statistically 
significant. The statistical analysis was performed using 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">Statistical Package for Social Sciences</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 16.0</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>, Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Rats in all the treatment groups gained weight throughout 
the study period. The percent increase in body weight was 
significantly less in the testosterone group than in the sham 
and AnTT groups (P0.05, Figure 1A). 
Orchidectomy resulted in decreased bone quality, as indi-
cated by a significant reduction in trabecular bone volume, 
trabecular number, and connectivity density, and a significant 
increase in trabecular separation in the orchidectomized 
group when compared with the sham group using μCT at 
the proximal tibia (P0.05). Similar structural changes 
were observed at the distal femur, ie, the orchidectomized 
group showed significant reductions in trabecular bone vol-
ume, number, and thickness, and a significant increase in 
trabecular separation when compared with the sham group 
(P0.05). Treatment with testosterone was able to prevent 
these degenerative changes completely (P0.05), and treat-
ment with tocotrienol was able to prevent adverse changes at 
the distal femur (P0.05). Structural indices at the proximal 
tibia showed a trend towards improvement in the AnTT group </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1250 </p>

<p>Chin and Ima-nirwana </p>

<p>Table 1 genes of interest in this study </p>

<p>Gene 
NCBI accession number 
Name </p>

<p>Osteoblast-related 
ALPL 
nM_013059 
Alkaline phosphatase 
BGLAP 
nM_013414 
Osteocalcin or bone gamma-carboxyglutamate (gla) protein 
COL1A1 
nM_053304 
Collagen, type I, alpha 1 
CTNNB1 
nM_053357 
Catenin (cadherin associated protein), beta 1 
IBSP 
nM_012587 
Integrin-binding sialoprotein 
RUNX2 
nM_053470 
runt-related transcription factor 2 
SP7 
nM_181374 
sp7 transcription factor 
SPARC 
nM_012656 
Osteonectin or secreted protein, acidic, cysteine-rich 
OPG/TNFRSF11b 
nM_012870 
Osteoprotegerin/tumor necrosis factor receptor superfamily, member 11b 
Osteoclast-related 
ACP5 
nM_019144 
Acid phosphatase 5, tartrate resistant 
CTSK 
nM_031560 
Cathepsin K 
ITGB3 
nM_153720 
Integrin, beta 3 
NFATc1 
XM_001058445 
nuclear factor of activated T-cells, cytoplasmic, calcineurin-dependent 1 
SPP1 
nM_012881 
Osteopontin or secreted phosphoprotein 1 or Bone sialoprotein 1 
SRC 
nM_031977 
src v-src sarcoma (schmidt-ruppin A-2) viral oncogene homolog (avian) 
RANKL/TNFSF11 
nM_057149 
receptor activator of nuclear factor kappa-b/tumor necrosis factor 
(ligand) superfamily, member 11 
Others 
PPARG 
nM_001145366 
Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma, transcript variant 2 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Percentage changes in body weight, serum terminal-C type 1 collagen crosslinks, and osteocalcin levels in rats. The bar charts show the percentage change in body 
weight (A), serum terminal-C type 1 collagen crosslinks (B), and osteocalcin levels (C) before and after treatment. The data are shown as the mean with the standard error 
of the mean. 
Notes: 
b Significant difference versus the sham group; </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>significant difference versus the orchidectomized group; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>significant difference versus the AnTT group. The statistical 
significance value is set at P0.05. 
Abbreviations: AnTT, annatto tocotrienol-supplemented group; Bl, baseline group; CTX-1, terminal-C type 1 collagen crosslinks; OrX, orchidectomized group; sh, sham-
operated group; Te, testosterone enanthate-supplemented group. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Percentage change of body weight </p>

<p>% change </p>

<p>b,d </p>

<p>c,d </p>

<p>SH </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Percentage change of CTX-1 </p>

<p>Percentage change of osteocalcin </p>

<p>% change </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-30 </p>

<p>-40 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>-60 </p>

<p>-70 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>% change </p>

<p>SH </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>-80 </p>

<p>-60 </p>

<p>-40 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1251 </p>

<p>effects of tocotrienol in male osteoporosis </p>

<p>when compared with the orchidectomized group, but only 
values for trabecular separation reached statistical signifi-
cance (P0.05; Figure 2 and Figure 3A-D). 
Dynamic histomorphometric variables (single-labeled 
surface, double-labeled surface, mineralizing rate, mineral </p>

<p>apposition rate, and bone formation rate) were not sig-
nificantly different between the orchidectomized and sham 
groups (P0.05). Treatment with testosterone suppressed 
bone remodeling, as evidenced by a significant reduction 
in double-labeled surface and a significant increase in </p>

<p>Structural model index of proximal 
tibia </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>SMI 
Conn. D. </p>

<p>160.0 </p>

<p>140.0 </p>

<p>120.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>80.0 </p>

<p>60.0 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>Connectivity density of proximal tibia </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Bone volume of proximal tibia 
Trabecular number of proximal tibia </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>BV/TV (%) </p>

<p>Tb. N. (mm </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>a 
a,b,c </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Trabecular separation of proximal 
tibia </p>

<p>Trabecular thickness of proximal 
tibia </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Tb. Th. (mm) 
Tb. Sp. (mm) </p>

<p>0.09 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.00 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>0.70 </p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>a,c 
a,c </p>

<p>a 
a 
a </p>

<p>Figure 2 Bone structural indices in proximal tibia of rats evaluated using μCT. The bar charts (A-F) show bone structural indices at the proximal tibia evaluated using μCT. 
The data are shown as the mean and standard error of the mean. 
Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant difference versus the baseline group; 
b significant difference versus the sham group; </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>significant difference versus the orchidectomized group. The statistical 
significance value is set at P0.05. 
Abbreviations: AnTT, annatto tocotrienol-supplemented group; Bl, baseline group; OrX, orchidectomized group; sh, sham-operated group; Te, testosterone enanthate-
supplemented group; sMI, structural model index; Conn.D, connectivity density; BV/TV, bone volume over total volume; Tb. n., trabecular number; Tb. Th., trabecular 
thickness; Tb. sp., trabecular separation. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1252 </p>

<p>Chin and Ima-nirwana </p>

<p>Bone volume of distal femur 
T rabecular number of distal femur </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
B L 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>25.0 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>35.0 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>45.0 </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>0.0000 </p>

<p>0.0020 </p>

<p>0.0040 </p>

<p>0.0060 </p>

<p>0.0080 </p>

<p>0.0100 </p>

<p>0.0120 </p>

<p>0.0140 </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>c,d </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>a 
c </p>

<p>BV/TV (%) </p>

<p>Tb. N. (µm </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Trabecular thickness of distal femur 
T rabecular separation of distal femur </p>

<p>Tb. Th. (µm) 
Tb. Sp. (µm) </p>

<p>60.0 
200.0 </p>

<p>180.0 </p>

<p>160.0 </p>

<p>140.0 </p>

<p>120.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>80.0 </p>

<p>60.0 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>c 
c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>a,b,d </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>a,b,d </p>

<p>BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
B L 
S H 
O RX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>dLS (%) 
sLS (%) </p>

<p>60.0 
80.0 </p>

<p>70.0 </p>

<p>60.0 </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>50.0 </p>

<p>40.0 </p>

<p>30.0 </p>

<p>20.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>Double-labeled surface 
Single-labeled surface </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1253 </p>

<p>effects of tocotrienol in male osteoporosis </p>

<p>single-labeled surface in the testosterone group as compared 
with the sham and AnTT groups (P0.05). Supplementation 
with tocotrienol increased bone remodeling, as indicated by a 
significant increase in double-labeled surface and a significant 
decrease in single-labeled surface (P0.05; Figure 3E-I). 
The difference between treatment with testosterone and 
treatment with AnTT with regard to the bone remodeling 
process was further supported by the bone turnover marker 
results. The orchidectomized group showed a marginally 
higher osteocalcin level when compared with the sham group, 
but the difference was not statistically significant (P0.05). 
Treatment with testosterone significantly suppressed osteo-
calcin levels in comparison with the orchidectomized group 
(P0.05). The tocotrienol-treated group showed higher 
osteocalcin levels than the orchidectomized group, although 
the difference was not statistically significant (P0.05). There 
was no difference in C-terminal of type 1 collagen crosslink 
levels between the groups (P0.05; Figure 1B and C). </p>

<p>In general, gene expression was not significantly different 
between the sham and orchidectomized groups (P0.05). 
RANKL and PPARG gene expression was significantly lower 
in the testosterone group than in the orchidectomized group 
(P0.05). Treatment with tocotrienol significantly increased 
the expression of several bone formation genes, such as 
ALPL, when compared with the sham and orchidectomized 
groups (P0.05), COL1α1 when compared with the orchi-
dectomized group (P0.05), and CTNNB1 when compared 
with the sham group (P0.05). Tocotrienol also significantly 
suppressed expression of RANKL and PPARG mRNA 
when compared with the orchidectomized group (P0.05). 
Expression of RUNX-2 and SPARC was also higher, albeit 
not significantly so, in the AnTT group when compared with 
the sham and orchidectomized groups (P0.05). There was 
no significant difference in expression of osteoclast-related 
genes between the groups with and without AnTT treatment 
(P0.05; Figures 4 and 5). </p>

<p>MAR (µm/d) 
MS (%) </p>

<p>2.5 
8.0 </p>

<p>7.0 </p>

<p>6.0 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
BL 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>Mineralizing surface 
Mineral apposition rate </p>

<p>a 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>G 
H </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Bone formation rate </p>

<p>BL </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>1.8 </p>

<p>SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>BFR (mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/µm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/d) </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>a 
a 
a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Figure 3 Bone structural and dynamic indices at the distal femur in rats evaluated using the bone histomorphometry technique. The bar charts show the bone structural 
(A-D) and dynamic (E-I) indices at the distal femur evaluated using the bone histomorphometry technique. The data are shown as the mean and standard error of the mean. 
Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant difference versus the baseline group; 
b significant difference versus the sham group; </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>significant difference versus the orchidectomized group; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>significant 
difference versus the AnTT group. The statistical significance value is set at P0.05. 
Abbreviations: AnTT, annatto tocotrienol-supplemented group; Bl, baseline group; OrX, orchidectomized group; sh, sham-operated group; Te, testosterone enanthate-
supplemented group; BV/TV, bone volume over total volume; Tb.n., trabecular number; Tb. Th., trabecular thickness; Tb. sp., trabecular separation; dls, double-labeled 
surface; sls, single-labeled surface; MAr, mineral apposition rate; Ms, mineralizing surface; BFr, bone formation rate. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1254 </p>

<p>Chin and Ima-nirwana </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>ALPL expression 
BGLAP expression </p>

<p>0.070 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>0.600 </p>

<p>SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
S H 
O RX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>Relative MFI 
Relative MFI </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>COL1α1 expression 
CTNNB expression </p>

<p>1.100 </p>

<p>1.050 </p>

<p>1.000 </p>

<p>0.950 </p>

<p>0.900 </p>

<p>0.850 </p>

<p>0.800 
0.000 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.080 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.120 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.140 </p>

<p>SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
S H 
O RX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Relative MFI 
Relative MFI </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>RUNX-2 expression 
SP7 expression </p>

<p>SH </p>

<p>0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.150 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.250 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.350 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.450 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
S H 
O RX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>Relative MFI 
Relative MFI </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1255 </p>

<p>effects of tocotrienol in male osteoporosis </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study indicates that osteoporosis induced by 
testosterone deficiency is characterized by a decrease in bone 
structural indices, such as trabecular bone volume, number, 
and thickness, as well as an increase in trabecular separation. 
These changes subsequently led to increased bone porosity, 
as evidenced by decreased connectivity density. There were 
no dramatic differences in indices of bone dynamics or bone 
remodeling markers between the orchidectomized and sham 
groups, probably because the increase in remodeling favor-
able to net bone loss was transient and had slowed down after 
2 months. This also explains the lack of overt differences in 
gene expression profile between the orchidectomized and 
sham groups. 
In the current study, the tocotrienol and testosterone 
interventions were found to preserve bone health in rats 
via two distinct mechanisms. Testosterone inhibited both 
bone formation (as evidenced by a significant decrease in </p>

<p>double-labeled surface and serum osteocalcin level) and 
bone resorption (as evidenced by a significant decrease in 
RANKL mRNA expression), so bone remodeling was halted. 
Tocotrienol uncoupled bone remodeling by promoting bone 
formation (as evidenced by a significant increase in double-
labeled surface and expression of bone formation genes), 
with a negligible impact on bone resorption (as indicated by 
no significant changes in osteoclast-related gene expression). 
Differences between AnTT and testosterone with regard to 
the bone-protective mechanism have a significant clinical 
impact. We showed that testosterone was more effective 
than AnTT in preserving trabecular structure at the femur 
and tibia. However, inhibition of bone remodeling by testos-
terone could lead to accumulation of microfractures, thereby 
weakening the bone if not repaired via the normal remodeling 
process. On the other hand, AnTT activated bone formation 
but had negligible effects on bone resorption, resulting in a 
net gain of bone, which counteracted the loss of bone mass </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>SPARC expression 
IBSP expression </p>

<p>0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.150 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.250 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.350 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.450 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
S H 
O RX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>0.600 </p>

<p>Relative MFI 
Relative MFI </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>OPG expression </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c,d </p>

<p>SH </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.150 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.250 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.350 </p>

<p>ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>Relative MFI </p>

<p>Figure 4 relative expression of genes related to osteoblast differentiation/bone formation in rats. The bar charts (A-I) show the relative expression of genes related to 
osteoblast/bone formation. The data are shown as the mean with standard error of the mean. 
Notes: 
b Significant difference versus the sham group; </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>significant difference versus the orchidectomized group; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>significant difference versus the AnTT group. The statistical 
significance value is set at P0.05. 
Abbreviations: AnTT, annatto tocotrienol-supplemented group; Bl, baseline group; OrX, orchidectomized group; sh, sham-operated group; Te, testosterone enanthate-
supplemented group; MFI, mean fluorescence intensity. </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1256 </p>

<p>Chin and Ima-nirwana </p>

<p>Figure 5 relative expression of genes related to osteoclastogenesis/osteoclast function/bone resorption and PPARG in rats. The bar charts (A-H) show the relative expres-
sion of genes related to osteoclastogenesis/osteoclast function/bone resorption and PPARG. The data are shown as the mean and the standard error of the mean. 
Notes: 
b Significant differences versus the sham group; </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>significant differences versus the orchidectomized group; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>significant difference versus the AnTT group. The statistical 
significance value is set at P0.05. 
Abbreviations: AnTT, annatto tocotrienol-supplemented group; Bl, baseline group; OrX, orchidectomized group; sh, sham-operated group; Te, testosterone enanthate-
supplemented group; MFI, mean fluorescence intensity. </p>

<p>ACP5 expression 
CTSK expression </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>SH 
0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.045 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.080 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.120 </p>

<p>0.140 </p>

<p>0.160 </p>

<p>0.180 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
S H 
O RX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>Relative MFI 
Relative MFI </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0.070 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E </p>

<p>ITGB3 expression 
NFATC1 expression </p>

<p>Relative MFI 
Relative MFI </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>SPP1 expression 
SRC expression </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>0.250 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.150 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.080 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.120 </p>

<p>SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
S H 
O RX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>Relative MFI 
Relative MFI </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>G 
H </p>

<p>RANKL expression 
PPARG expression </p>

<p>0.140 </p>

<p>c 
c 
c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.120 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.080 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.150 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.250 </p>

<p>SH 
ORX 
A nTT 
T E 
S H 
O RX 
AnTT 
TE </p>

<p>Relative MFI 
Relative MFI </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1257 </p>

<p>effects of tocotrienol in male osteoporosis </p>

<p>due to testosterone deficiency. Since bone remodeling was 
not suppressed, AnTT would allow repair of microfractures. 
However, examination of microfractures was outside the 
scope of the present study. 
The use of a δTT-predominant AnTT mixture without any 
αTF is a novel approach in the prevention of male osteoporo-
sis, so no comparable studies are available. A previous study 
by Abdul-Majeed et al showed that supplementing ovariecto-
mized female rats with AnTT 60 mg/kg for 8 weeks prevented 
adverse changes in femoral trabecular bone due to estrogen 
deficiency, as evidenced by improvements in cellular and 
static bone parameters. 
21 Bone formation was increased and 
bone resorption was decreased in the AnTT-treated group 
in that study, 
21 whereas only bone formation was increased 
in the present study. This discrepancy might be due to sex 
differences in the response of bone to treatment with AnTT. 
Many studies had been performed previously using γTT-
predominant palm-derived tocotrienol mixtures containing 
20%-30% αTF to investigate the antiosteoporotic effects of 
tocotrienol. 
10 The majority of these studies found that palm-
derived tocotrienols at 60 mg/kg body weight were effective 
in preventing degenerative changes in structural, dynamic, 
cellular and static indices of bone in osteoporosis induced by 
estrogen deficiency, 
12-14 nicotine, 
16 and free radicals. 
15 In a 
study using normal rats, isomers of tocotrienol were found to 
have anabolic effects on bone as evaluated by biomechanical 
strength testing and histomorphometric evaluation. 
23 Hence, 
the current study showed that AnTT also exerted anabolic 
effects on bone in male rats with testosterone deficiency. 
Very few studies have explored the bone-protective 
mechanism of tocotrienols, and the antiosteoclastogenic 
effects of tocotrienols were given more emphasis in the avail-
able in vitro studies. In vitro studies by Brooks et al 
24 and 
Ha et al 
25 demonstrated that tocotrienol isomers were able to 
decrease the formation and differentiation of osteoclasts from 
human CD14+ cells and mouse bone marrow macrophages 
and the resorption activity of osteoclasts. Ha et al further 
demonstrated that the antiosteoclastogenic effects of αTT 
could be attributed to disruption of RANKL signaling. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>These observations were supported by several in vivo studies, 
in which eroded surface and osteoclast surface of trabecular 
bone were reduced in tocotrienol-supplemented female ani-
mals. 
21 The present research shows that AnTT supplementa-
tion significantly increases the expression of genes related to 
bone formation (ALPL, COL1α1, and CTNNB1) but does not 
have a significant influence on expression of genes related to 
osteoclasts. Although expression of RANKL was decreased 
in the AnTT group, expression of other genes related to </p>

<p>osteoclast function (ACP5, CTSK, and ITGB3) and signaling 
(NFATC1 and SRC) was not affected. Further, treatment with 
AnTT decreased expression of PPARG, which is responsible 
for differentiation of adipocytes, indicating that bone marrow 
mesenchymal cells were more committed to differentiate 
into osteoblasts (indicated by marginally higher but not sta-
tistically significant RUNX expression in the AnTT group) 
instead of adipocytes. In view of previous evidence regarding 
the antiosteoclastogenic effects of tocotrienols, we postu-
late that the dose used in the current study was sufficient 
to activate genes for bone formation but not those for bone 
resorption. It is also possible that the effect of the AnTT 
mixture on bone remodeling was different from that of single 
tocotrienol isomers and palm-derived tocotrienol mixtures, 
whereby the AnTT mixture exerted predominantly anabolic 
but not antiresorptive effects in bone. 
There are several advantages to using an αTF-free tocot-
rienol mixture. A study by Fujita et al showed that αTF stimu-
lated osteoclast fusion and increased bone resorption activity, 
but other vitamin E isomers did not. 
19 Alpha-TF was also 
shown to compete with other vitamin E isomers to bind with 
αTF transport protein, which secretes vitamin E isomers into 
the circulation, 
26 thus reducing the level of tocotrienol isomers 
beneficial to bone health. This was supported by intervention 
studies, in which αTF supplementation decreased circulat-
ing levels of other tocopherols and tocotrienols. 
27,28 These 
undesirable characteristics of αTF might interfere with the 
bone-protective effects of tocotrienols and subsequently 
reduce their efficacy. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>Several limitations need to be considered in interpreting 
the results of the present study. The affinity of αTF transport 
protein for δTT and γTT was very low. 
26 We did not deter-
mine the amount of tocotrienol that reached the circulation 
or bone. However, previous animal studies have shown that 
supplementation with tocotrienol 60 mg/kg improves bone 
quality. 
21 Trabecular bone was studied because it is metaboli-
cally active and provides a large surface to volume ratio for 
interaction between soluble factors and bone. 
30 Thus, trabe-
cular bone would show a more rapid response than cortical 
bone when studying compounds that could affect bone. The 
antiosteoporotic effects of AnTT could be further explored 
by varying the dose and treatment duration. The dosage and 
treatment period in the current study were based on those 
used in an earlier ovariectomized osteoporosis model. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>This study is novel because the effects of an AnTT mix-
ture with a unique composition of 90% δTT and 10% γTT 
have never been examined before in osteoporosis induced 
by testosterone deficiency. Previous studies have used </p>

<p>Clinical Interventions in Aging 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1258 </p>

<p>Chin and Ima-nirwana </p>

<p>palm-derived tocotrienol mixtures and focused on estrogen-
induced osteoporosis and other models. The absence of αTF 
in the mixture allows the effects of tocotrienols to be studied 
without undesirable interference. This study characterized 
the effects of AnTT on gene expression in bone, which 
has not been done by previous researchers. This allowed 
a better understanding of the mechanisms underlying the 
bone-protective action of AnTT. A gene expression study 
was performed using a multiplex platform that reduced 
errors due to sample processing, dilution, and amplification. 
The multiplex platform has been reported to have a lower 
coefficient of variation when compared with the traditional 
reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>AnTT 60 mg/kg showed promising antiosteoporotic effects 
in rats with osteoporosis induced by testosterone deficiency. 
These antiosteoporotic effects are attributed to an increase in 
bone formation activity brought about by increased expres-
sion of genes related to bone formation. AnTT protects bone 
via a different mechanism when compared with testosterone 
replacement, which inhibits the bone modeling process. 
Further research of AnTT should be conducted by varying 
the dose and treatment duration, when examining the antios-
teoporotic effects of AnTT in male osteoporosis induced by 
testosterone deficiency. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank the Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia for funding 
this study via a grant from Impak Perdana (DIP-2012-07). 
We also thank Dr Lim Fei Tieng from Hi-Tech Instruments 
Sdn. Bhd. for her assistance with the μCT measurements and 
Dr Thuan Bui from i-DNA Biotechnology Sdn. Bhd. for assis-
tance in using the QuantiGene 2.0. We are also grateful for 
the assistance provided by the technicians in the Department 
of Pharmacology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



</text></tei>