<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4093267" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The use of antibiotic growth promoters (AGP) has been 
widely practiced in animal production for decades 
worldwide. The benefits of AGP in improving production 
efficiency of broiler chickens are well established (Miles et 
al., 2006). However, AGP may also leave residue in animal 
products such as meat, milk and egg (Nisha, 2008). 
There is a growing interest in herbal plants as </p>

<p>alternatives to AGP. The benefits of herbal feed additives in 
improving growth performance and nutrient digestibility, 
and reducing pathogens have been reported (Zulkifli et al., 
2012). 
Garlic bulb, paste, oil, powder, husk and leaves may 
influence the performance of farm animals (Qureshi et al., 
1983). The functions of garlic are mainly attributed to the 
bioactive 
components, 
including 
sulfur-containing 
compounds such as alliin, diallylsulphides and allicin 
(Amagase et al., 2001). Allicin and its derivatives have been 
shown to be a larvicidal and bacteriostatic, active against 
both Gram positive or Gram negative organisms as well as 
fungi such as Candida albicans and viruses including 
influenza viruses (Chang and Cheong, 2008). Kumar and 
Berwal (1998) tested antibacterial activity of fresh garlic 
bulbs against the potent food pathogens; Staphylococcus 
aureus, Escherichia coli (E. coli), Salmonella typhi and 
Listeria monocytogenes. They found E. coli is the most </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. </p>

<p>Vol. 27, No. 3 : 375-382 March 2014 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5713/ajas.2013.13030 </p>

<p>www.ajas.info </p>

<p>pISSN 1011-2367 eISSN 1976-5517 </p>

<p>Effects of Two Herbal Extracts and Virginiamycin Supplementation on 
Growth Performance, Intestinal Microflora Population and 
Fatty Acid Composition in Broiler Chickens </p>

<p>Suriya Kumari Ramiah 
1 , Idrus Zulkifli 
1,2, *, Nordiana Asyikin Abdul Rahim 
2 , </p>

<p>Mahdi Ebrahimi </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, and Goh Yong Meng </p>

<p>1,3 </p>

<p>Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Universiti Putra Malaysia, 43400 UPM Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia </p>

<p>ABSTRACT: The competency of garlic and pennywort to improve broiler chicken growth and influence intestinal microbial </p>

<p>communities and fatty acid composition of breast meat were studied. Two hundred forty, "day-old" chicks were randomly allocated to 4 
treatment groups consisting of 6 replications of 10 chicks in each pen. The groups were assigned to receive treatment diets as follows: i) 
basal diet (control), ii) basal diet plus 0.5% garlic powder (GP), iii) basal diet plus 0.5% pennywort powder (PW) and iv) 0.002% 
virginiamycin (VM). Birds were killed at day 42 and intestinal samples were collected to assess for Lactobacillus and Escherichia coli. 
The pectoralis profundus from chicken breast samples was obtained from 10 birds from each treatment group on day 42 and frozen at 
20C for further analyses. Fatty acid profile of breast muscles was determined using gas liquid chromatography. Feed intake and 
weight gain of broilers fed with GP, PW, and VM were significantly higher (p&lt;0.05) compared to control. Feeding chicks GP, PW, and 
VM significantly reduced Escherichia coli count (p&lt;0.05) while Lactobacillus spp count were significantly higher (p&lt;0.05) in the gut 
when compared to control group on day 42. Supplemented diet containing pennywort increased the C18:3n-3 fatty acid composition of 
chickens' breast muscle. Garlic and pennywort may be useful in modulating broiler guts as they control the enteropathogens that help to 
utilize feed efficiently. This subsequently enhances the growth performances of broiler chickens. (Key Words: Broiler Chicken, Garlic, 
Pennywort, Growth Performances, Microbial Population, Fatty Acid Composition) </p>

<p>Copyright © 2014 by Asian-Australasian Journal of Animal Sciences </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author: Idrus Zulkifli. Tel: +60-3-89471042, 
Fax: +60-3-89381612, E-mail: zulidrus@upm.edu.my 
1 Institute of Tropical Agriculture, Universiti Putra Malaysia, 
43400 UPM Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia. 
2 Faculty of Agriculture, Universiti Putra Malaysia, 43400 UPM 
Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia. 
3 Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universiti Putra Malaysia, 
43400 UPM Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia. </p>

<p>Submitted Jan. 11, 2013; Accepted Aug. 19, 2013; Revised Oct. 23, 2013 </p>

<p>Ramiah et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:375-382 </p>

<p>
sensitive among all pathogen tested to the effect of garlic. 
Pennywort, Centella asiatica or pegaga, is closely 
related to the species Hyrocotyle (Hussin et al., 2007). It is 
known for its reputation as a wound healing agent and brain 
stimulant (Oyedeji et al., 2005). The chemical composition 
of pennywort has a very important role in medicinal and 
nutriceutical applications. These applications are most 
likely due to its biologically active constituents of 
triterpenes namely asiatic acid and asiaticoside (Inamdar et 
al., 1996). Noraharaini et al. (2011) reported that the 
bioactive compounds of pennywort have antibacterial 
properties against Helicobacter pylori, Staphyloccocus 
aurues, E. coli and Pseudomonas aeroginosa. 
Poultry meat has many desirable nutritional 
characteristics such as low lipid and relatively high 
concentration of polyunsaturated fatty acids (Bourre, 2005). 
Modification of meat fatty acid composition through 
feeding provided the best results in single-stomached 
poultry (Wood et al., 1999). Earlier study demonstrated that 
dietary supplementation of garlic could reduce serum 
cholesterol in broilers (Qureshi et al., 1983) and laying hens 
(Yalcin et al., 2007). To the authors' best knowledge, there 
is limited information on the effects of pennywort on the 
growth performance and fatty acid composition of broiler 
meat. 
This present study was designed to compare the effects 
of dietary supplementation of garlic, pennywort and 
virginiamycin on growth performance, gut microflora and 
meat fatty acid composition in commercial broiler chickens. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Animal welfare 
This study was undertaken following the guidelines of 
the Research Policy of the Universiti Putra Malaysia on 
animal ethics. </p>

<p>Source and preparation methods for diet 
Garlic bulbs and pennywort plant were purchased from 
a local wholesale market in Selangor, Malaysia. They were 
coarsely chopped and dried in an oven at 50C until 
constant weight. Dried materials were ground into powder 
using a Wiley mill through a 1-mm screen (Thomas Wiley 
Cutting Mill Model 4 Thomas Scientific, Swedeboro, NJ, 
USA) and stored at 4C until further use. </p>

<p>Experimental birds and diets 
A total of 240 day-old male broiler chicks (Cobb 500) 
were obtained from a local hatchery. Upon arrival, the 
chicks were individually wing-tagged, weighed and 
randomly assigned into four treatments group. Each 
treatment group had six replicates of 10 birds. The cages 
were three-tiered and each block consisted of six cages. The </p>

<p>cages were in a conventional open-sided house with cyclic 
temperatures (minimum, 24C; maximum, 34C). The 
relative humidity was between 80% to 90%. Feed and water 
were provided ad libitium and lighting was continuous. The 
chicks were vaccinated against Newcastle disease on day 7 
and 21. Commencing from day one, six replicate cages 
containing 10 chicks were assigned to each of the four 
dietary treatments, giving a total of 24 pens. The dietary 
treatments were: </p>

<p>i) Basal diet (Control) 
ii) Basal diet plus 0.5% garlic powder (GP) 
iii) Basal diet plus 0.5% pennywort powder (PW) and 
iv) Basal diet plus 0.002% virginiamycin (Pfizer, USA) 
(VM) </p>

<p>The chickens were fed starter and finisher diets from 
day 0 to 21 and day 22 to 42 respectively. The diets were in 
mash form. The composition of experimental diets was 
formulated to meet or exceed NRC (1994) 
recommendations (Table 1). Feed intake and BW were 
recorded weekly and feed conversion ratios (FCR) 
(feed/gain) were calculated. </p>

<p>Bacterial count 
On day 42, 10 birds from each treatment group were 
randomly selected (more than one bird were sampled from 
some replicate cages) and were slaughtered. Their small 
intestines (from the distal end of the duodenum to the 
ileocaecal junction) were removed immediately and placed 
in sterile. All the birds (including those not selected) 
appeared healthy at the point of sampling. One gram of 
faecal sample from each pen was then diluted with 9 mL of 
1% peptone broth (Becton, Dickinson and Co.) and 
homogenized. Viable counts of bacteria in the faecal 
samples were then conducted by plating serial 10-fold 
dilutions (in 1% peptone solution) onto MacConkey agar 
plates (Difco Laboratories, Detroit, MI, USA) and 
lactobacilli medium III agar plates (Medium 638; DSMZ, 
Braunschweig, Germany) to isolate Escherichia coli and 
Lactobacillus, "respectively". Escherichia coli was counted 
on the eosin-methylene blue (EMB) agar and incubated for 
24 h at 37C. Lactobacillus was counted on the Rogosa agar 
and incubated for 24 to 72 h at the same temperature. 
Colonies with green metallic colour considered as 
Escherichia coli while the white colour is Lactobacillus. 
The microbial counts were determined as colony forming 
units (cfu) per gram of samples. </p>

<p>Lipid extraction 
Pectoralis profundus of chicken breast samples were 
obtained from 10 birds (those that were used for bacterial 
count) randomly selected from each treatment group on day 
42 and frozen at 20C for further analyses. Total fatty acid </p>

<p>Ramiah et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:375-382 </p>



<p>from meat samples were extracted using a chloroform-
methanol as described by Folch et al. (1957) with some 
modification by Ebrahimi et al. (2012). The total fatty acid 
was dried under stream of N 2 gas and FAME was prepared 
by methylation of the fatty acids using methanolic KOH 
following boron trifuoride (BF 3 , 14% in methanol) after the 
initial KOH hydrolysis (Cruz et al., 2013). </p>

<p>Fatty acid analysis 
Fatty acid methyl esters were separated and quantified 
by gas-liquid chromatography (Model 7890A, Agilent </p>

<p>Technologies, USA) using a 30 m0.32 mm i.d. capillary 
column (SP-2330, Supelco, Inc., Bellefonte, PA, USA). The 
hydrogen was used as the carrier gas at 40 mL/min. The 
injector temperature was programmed at 240C and the 
detector temperature was 250C. The column temperature 
program started to run at 140C, for 2 min, warmed to 
158C at 1C/min, held for 28 min, warmed to 220C at 
1C/min and then held for 20 min to achieve satisfactory 
separation. The identification of the peaks was made by 
comparison of equivalent chain lengths with those of 
authentic fatty acid methyl esters (37 Component FAME 
mix, Supelco, Bellefonte, PA). Peak areas were determined 
automatically using the Agilent gas chromatography 
chemstation software (Agilent Technologies, USA). The 
fatty acid concentrations are expressed as percentage of the 
sum of total identified peaks measured in each sample. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All data presented in this paper are the actual 
untransformed data except log-transformed data used for 
bacterial count when necessary to best approximate the 
normal distribution. Except for mortality, all data were 
analysed using the one-way ANOVA. Mortality data were 
analysed by chi-square test. Significant means were then 
elucidated using the Duncan multiple range tests. All 
statistical tests were conducted at 95% confidence level 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> program (Version 6.0, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2003</rs>). 
The results were expressed as means with pooled of 
standard error of mean (SEM). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Mean BW, feed intake and feed efficiency are shown in 
Table 2. Diet had no significant effect (p&gt;0.05) on BW of 
chicks at 7 and 14 days of age. However, on days 21, 35, 
and 42, birds fed GP, PW, and VM had significantly greater 
(p&lt;0.05) BW than controls. On day 28, the BW of the 
control chickens were less than PW and VM but not 
significantly different (p = 0.008) from those of the GP. The 
ADG was not significantly different in any treatment diets 
(p = 0.419) at starter phase. However, data at the finisher 
phase and overall trial showed that the ADG of GP, PW and 
VW were significantly different higher (p&lt;0.05) compared 
to control group. Irrespective of diet, feed intake during the 
first 3 weeks was not significantly different (p&gt;0.05). 
Feeding birds with GP, PW and VA significantly increased 
(p&lt;0.05) the total feed intake compared to control group at 
22 to 42 days. Feed efficiency was not significantly affected 
(p = 0.891) by diet throughout the experimental period. 
The fatty acids composition of breast muscle is 
presented in Table 3. Chicken fed with pennywort diet had 
highest level of C18:3n-3 compared to other dietary 
treatments (p&lt;0.05). The ratio of n-6:n-3 was higher in VM </p>

<p>Table 1. Ingredient and nutrient composition of diets </p>

<p>Ingredient (%) </p>

<p>Experimental diets 
Starter 
(1 to 21 days) </p>

<p>Finisher 
(22 to 42 days) 
Corn (Crude protein: 8.5%) 
54.29 
58.25 
Soybean meal 
(Crude protein: 41.6%) </p>

<p>34.20 
28.86 </p>

<p>Fish oil 
5.35 
5.75 
Crude palm oil 
2.55 
4.05 
DiCalcium phosphate 
1.09 
0.89 
Limestone 
1.01 
0.84 
Fine salt 
0.39 
0.26 
Mineral premix </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.30 
0.30 
Vitamin premix </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.30 
0.30 
Lysine 
0.34 
0.33 
DL-methionine 
0.18 
0.17 
Analysed nutrient (%) 
Crude protein 
22 
20 
ME kcal/kg 
3,000 
3,150 
Crude fiber 
3.73 
3.42 
Crude fat 
5.39 
7.04 
Total saturated fat 
SFA </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>50.44 
52.03 
UFA </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>49.56 
47.97 
MUFA </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>36.85 
36.79 
PUFAn-3 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1.09 
0.42 
PUFAn-6 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>11.62 
10.76 
n-6:n-3 ratio </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>10.68 
25.66 
UFA:SFA 
0.98 
0.92 
PUFA:SFA ratio 
0.25 
0.21 </p>

<p>1 Premixes contributed the following nutrients per kilogram of complete 
feed: vitamin A, 2,300 IU; vitamin D3, 400 IU; vitamin E, 1.8 mg; 
vitamin B12, 3.5 mg; riboflavin, 1.4 mg; panthotenic acid, 2 mg; nicotinic 
acid, 7 mg; pyridoxine, 0.25 mg; folic acid, 0.15 mg; menadione, 0.3 mg; 
thiamin, 0.15 mg; manganese oxide, 35 mg; ferrous sulfate 35 mg; zinc 
oxide, 30 mg; copper sulfate, 60 mg; cobalt carbonate, 5 mg; potassium 
iodine, 0.6 mg; selenium vanadate, 0.09 mg. Based on NRC (1994) feed 
composition table. 
2 SFA = sum of C10:0+C12:0+C14:0+C15:0+C16:0+C17:0+C18:0. 
3 UFA = sum of C14:1+C16:1+C17:1+C18:1n-9+C18:2+C18:3. 
4 MUFA = sum of C14:1+C16:1+C17:1+C18:1n-9. 
5 PUFA n-3 = sum of C18:3n-3. 
6 PUFA n-6 = sum of C18:2n-6. 
7 n-6 : n-3 = sum of (C18:2n-6)/sum of (C18:3n-3). </p>

<p>Ramiah et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:375-382 </p>

<p>
group compared to PW (p&lt;0.05). Diet had no significant 
effect (p&gt;0.05) on the percentage of SFA, UFA and MUFA. 
The long chain 22-carbon n-3 and 18-carbon n-6 were the </p>

<p>major contributors to the overall PUFA (polyunsaturated 
fatty acid) of the breast muscle. 
Feeding chicks GP, PW, and VM significantly reduced </p>

<p>Table 3. Effect of dietary supplement on fatty acid composition in breast muscle of broiler chickens 
Fatty acids 
Control 
GP 
PW 
VM 
SEM 
p value 
C14:0 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>0.40 
0.51 
0.56 
0.62 
0.04 
0.312 
C16:0 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>23.60 
23.71 
23.44 
23.27 
1.05 
0.848 
C16:1 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>3.11 
3.48 
3.23 
4.01 
0.22 
0.276 
C18:0 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>11.25 
11.34 
10.44 
10.37 
0.54 
0.615 
C18:1 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>34.86 
33.25 
35.86 
34.00 
1.59 
0.426 
C18:2n-6 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>17.27 
17.52 
16.94 
17.26 
0.77 
0.764 
C18:3n-3 
0.58 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.05 
0.007 
C20:4n-6 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>6.11 
6.53 
5.50 
7.15 
0.40 
0.319 
C20:5n-3 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>0.66 
0.61 
0.80 
0.52 
0.05 
0.182 
C22:5n-3 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>0.93 
1.07 
0.91 
1.03 
0.07 
0.754 
C22:6n-3 </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>1.20 
1.34 
1.39 
1.23 
0.07 
0.607 
SFA </p>

<p>1,ns </p>

<p>35.25 
35.57 
34.46 
34.27 
1.55 
0.432 
UFA </p>

<p>2,ns </p>

<p>64.74 
64.42 
65.53 
65.72 
2.88 
0.432 
MUFA </p>

<p>3,ns </p>

<p>37.98 
36.73 
39.09 
38.01 
1.74 
0.629 
PUFA n-3 </p>

<p>4,ns </p>

<p>3.37 
3.63 
3.98 
3.29 
0.19 
0.205 
PUFA n-6 </p>

<p>5,ns </p>

<p>23.38 
24.05 
22.45 
24.41 
1.09 
0.315 
n-6:n-3 
7.20 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>6.79 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>5.83 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7.65 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.37 
0.046 
UFA:SFA </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>1.85 
1.81 
1.94 
1.92 
0.08 
0.459 
PUFA:SFA </p>

<p>ns </p>

<p>0.76 
0.78 
0.76 
0.81 
0.04 
0.590 </p>

<p>GP = Garlic powder. PW = Pennywort powder; VM = Virginiamycin. 
1 SFA = sum of C14:0+C16:0+C18:0. 
2 UFA = sum of C16:1+C18:1+C18:2n-6+C18:3n-3. 
3 MUFA = sum of C14:1+C16:1+C17:1+C18:1n-9. 
4 PUFA n-3 = sum of C18:3n-3. 
5 PUFA n-6 = sum of C18:2n-6. 
6 n-6:n-3 = sum of (C18:2n-6)/sum of (C18:3n-3). 
Data presented as means with pooled SEM (n = 10/treatment group). 
a,b Means within a row with no common superscript differ significantly (p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Table 2. Effect of dietary supplement on body weight, daily gain, feed intake and feed efficiency (gain:feed) in broiler chickens </p>

<p>Parameter 
Experimental diets 
SEM 
p value 
Control 
GP 
PW 
VM 
BW (g/bird) 
Day 0 
47.9 
48.9 
47.7 
47.2 
0.24 
0.081 </p>

<p>Day 7 
165.1 
165.4 
165.4 
169.4 
0.91 
0.272 
Day 14 
355.7 
360.7 
363.6 
366.1 
2.22 
0.377 
Day 21 
762.4 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>787.7 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>797.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>800.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>4.35 
0.008 
Day 28 
1,199.4 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1,235.1 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>1,246.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1245.8 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>7.43 
0.008 
Day 35 
1,649.2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1,709.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1,727.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1,725.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>9.52 
0.011 
Day 42 
2,147.7 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>2,236.8 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2,258.0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2,256.3 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>10.62 
0.0005 
Daily gain (g/d) 
Day 1-21 
34.02 
35.18 
34.90 
35.22 
0.29 
0.419 
Day 22-42 
45.15 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>47.70 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>48.17 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>48.12 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.36 
0.008 
Day 1-42 
49.99 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>52.09 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>52.63 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>52.59 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.25 
0.0005 
Feed intake (g/bird) 
Day 1-21 
364 
372 
376.3 
378.1 
6.97 
0.164 
Day 22-42 
893.67 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>945.73 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>956.73 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>954.96 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>12.67 
0.0005 
Day 1-42 
3,774.0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>3,953.5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3,999.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>3,999.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>14.06 
&lt;0.0001 
Gain:feed (g/g) 
Day 1-21 
0.82 
0.82 
0.82 
0.82 
0.02 
0.910 
Day 22-42 
0.59 
0.59 
0.59 
0.59 
0.02 
0.944 
Day 1-42 
0.57 
0.57 
0.57 
0.57 
0.01 
0.891 </p>

<p>GP = Garlic powder. PW = Pennywort powder; VM = Virginiamycin. Data presented as means with pooled SEM (n = 6/treatment group). 
a,b Means within a row with no common superscript differ significantly (p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Ramiah et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:375-382 </p>



<p>Escherichia coli count in the gut when compared to controls 
on day 42 (Figure 1). On day 42, the intestinal 
Lactobacillus spp counts of GP, PW and VM chicks were 
significantly higher (p = 0.007) than the control group 
(Figure 2). Diet had no significant effect (p = 0.841) on 
mortality rate (Figure 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>A number of studies have shown that inclusion of 
virginiamycin may improve growth performance of broiler 
chickens (Miles et al., 1984; Beelay et al., 1994). On the 
contrary, Proudfoot et al. (1990) showed that supplementing 
broiler chickens with virginiamycin had negligible effect on 
growth performance. Earlier report (Slyranda et al., 2011) 
suggested that the effect of garlic supplementation on 
growth performance in broilers is inconsistent. Demir et al. </p>

<p>(2003) and Pourali et al. (2010) reported that garlic 
supplementation at 0.2, 0.4, 0.6, and 1.0% had negligible 
influence on growth performance. On the contrary, Kumar 
et al. (2010) reported that supplementing broilers with 
garlic based growth promoter at 250 ppm improved BW 
and FCR. The present findings clearly suggested that birds 
fed diets supplemented garlic had higher feed intake and 
greater BW than controls. Improvement in BW could be 
due to flavouring compound in garlic which attributed the 
chickens to consume more, hence leading to higher body 
weight. According to Qureshi et al. (1983), inclusion of 
garlic more than 0.6% reduced feed intake and weight gain. 
It appears that the effectiveness of dietary garlic 
supplementation in improving growth is dose dependent. 
There is very little information available with regards to 
pennywort supplementation and growth performance in 
broilers. The only reported work on dietary pennywort 
supplementation and BW in broilers was by Pongmanee 
(2003). The author found that broilers supplemented with 
1.67 g/kg feed of crude powder and 0.40 g/kg of crude 
extract of Asiatic pennywort had significantly greater 
weight gains than those of controls on day 21 but not on 
day 42. The present work showed that supplementing diets 
with pennywort at 0.5% resulted in greater BW and higher 
feed intake than control birds on 22 to 42 days. The 
antimicrobial properties of pennywort have been 
demonstrated in in vitro studies. Oyedeji et al. (2005) 
reported that both crude and chromatographic extracts of 
pennywort showed antibacterial activity against the test 
isolates indicating the presence of bioactive ingredients for 
therapeutic purposes. 
Under conditions of the study, the growth performance 
data obtained in the present work are considered 
comparable with broilers raised under commercial setting. 
However, feeding broilers pelleted rations may further 
improve their FCR (Zulkifli and Ramlah, 1998). Based on </p>

<p>a 
b 
b 
b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>C 
GP 
PW VM </p>

<p>cfu/g </p>

<p>Figure 1. Effect of dietary supplement on intestinal Escherichia 
coli count in broiler chickens. Data presented as means with 
pooled SEM (0.25), n = 10/per treatment group. 
a,b Means within a 
row with no common superscript differ significantly (p = 0.046). 
C = Control, GP = Garlic powder. PW = Pennywort powder, VM 
= Virginiamycin. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>4.00 </p>

<p>6.00 </p>

<p>8.00 </p>

<p>10.00 </p>

<p>C 
GP PW VM </p>

<p>cfu/g </p>

<p>Figure 2. Effects of dietary supplement on Lactobacillus count in 
broiler chickens. Data presented as means with pooled SEM 
(0.007), n = 10/per treatment group. 
a,b Means within a row with 
no common superscript differ significantly (p = 0.003). C = 
Control, GP = Garlic powder. PW = Pennywort powder, VM = 
Virginiamycin. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C 
GP 
PW 
VM </p>

<p>Mortality </p>

<p>rate </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effect of dietary supplement on mortality rate. 
a,b Means 
within a row with no common superscript differ significantly (p = 
0.841). n = 60/per treatment group. C = Control, GP = Garlic 
powder. PW = Pennywort powder, VM = Virginiamycin. </p>

<p>Ramiah et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:375-382 </p>

<p>
the present findings, it appears that GP, PW and VM are 
equally effective in improving feed intake and weight gain 
of broilers. The FCR for GP, PW and VM were not 
significantly different (p&gt;0.05). This may suggested that the 
response of chickens to growth promoters could be related 
to genetic background (Miles et al., 1984; Butaye et al., 
2003) 
The microbial population in the gastrointestinal tract of 
poultry plays an important role in normal digestive 
processes and health maintenance (Woods et al., 1999). The 
present findings suggested that GP, PW and VM are able to 
reduce intestinal Escherichia coli counts in broilers. 
Similarly, Kumar et al. (2010) indicated that the inclusion 
of garlic at 250 ppm in the broiler diet reduced the count of 
Escherichia coli as well as reduction of Salmonella when 
compared to control group. In vitro studies suggested that 
the antibacterial property of garlic is attributed to allicin 
compound (Ankri and Mirelman, 1999; Willis and Reid, 
2003). The present study also demonstrated that dietary 
supplementation of pennywort may also reduce Escherichia 
coli count in the gut. According to Norzaharaini et al. 
(2011), the antibacterial effect of pennywort was derived 
from bioactive compound, asiaticoside. 
The benefits of lactic acid bacteria (LAB), such as 
Lactobacillus spp, in enhancing growth and immunity of 
poultry are well documented (Dang and Visek, 1960; Jin et 
al., 1996). The present findings showed that GP, PW, and 
VM can improve Lactobacillus count in the gut. The mode 
of action of LAB includes i) maintaining normal intestinal 
microflora by competitive exclusion and antagonism; ii) 
altering metabolism by increasing digestive enzyme activity 
and decreasing bacterial enzyme activity and ammonia 
production; iii) improving feed intake and digestion; and iv) 
neutralizing enterotoxins and stimulating the immune 
system (Dang and Visek, 1960). 
Earlier reports indicated that LAB was resistant to the 
antimicrobial effects of some herbal plants and spices 
(Zaika and Kissinger, 1979; Patterson and Burkholder, 
2003). In an in vitro study by Rees et al. (1993), suggested 
that lactic acid bacteria were unaffected by the presence of 
garlic because the production of lactic acid by LAB reduced 
the surrounding pH and subsequently killed Escherichia 
coli. Combination effect of garlic and pennywort effects 
could be exploited to maximize the antibacterial activity of 
herbs. It is known that the antimicrobial property of feed 
supplements is more obvious under less hygienic condition 
(Barrows, 1992). 
There is considerable evidence (Qureshi et al., 1983) 
suggesting that dietary garlic supplementation can reduce 
lower palmitic acid, SFA, serum and meat cholesterol 
content and increase unsaturated fatty acids (UFA) in 
chickens. Compounds such as allyl-disulfide or allyl-
sulfhydryl groups could be responsible for the inhibition of </p>

<p>cholesterol synthesis by garlic (Singh and Porter, 2006). 
In the present study, we have been using 0.5% of garlic 
of which it is reasonable to surmise that the inclusion of the 
garlic might have some beneficial effect on chickens' meat 
with increased level of garlic supplement in diet as showed 
by Onibi et al. (2009). Increasing level of garlic in diet may 
have influence on fatty acid profile in chickens' meat. 
Hussin et al. (2009) reported that pennywort-fed rats 
had elevated high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and decreased 
triglyceride level than those fed control diet. The increase in 
HDL will result in higher antiatherogenic index and HDL-
cholesterol/total cholesterol ratio. Hence, pennywort has the 
potential to control the formation of atherosclerosis and 
coronary heart disease in rats (Hussin et al., 2009). 
Nevertheless, pennywort contained high levels of omega-3 
fatty acid of fatty acid composition 3.98% compared to 
garlic which might increase the omega-3 fatty acid 
composition in meat by increasing the amount of 
supplementation. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This study demonstrated that dietary supplementation of 
garlic, and pennywort may improve the growth performance 
of broilers. Reduction of Escherichia coli and increase of 
Lactobacillus in the small intestine by adding garlic and 
pennywort in basal diet could be commercially interesting 
as it may have the potential to be an alternative to antibiotic 
growth promoter for broiler chickens. Hence, the beneficial 
effect of pennywort and garlic supplementation in 
improving growth performance of broiler chickens may be 
more obvious under floor pen system as compared to cages 
which are considered more hygienic. Further research is 
required to evaluate the effects of garlic and pennywort on 
fatty acid composition in chickens' meat. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>The research was supported by Universiti Putra 
Malaysia. A special thanks to Prof. Saleha Abdul Aziz, Ms. 
Krishnammah Kuppusamy and Ms. Fauziah Nordin for 
their technical assistance during the experimental period. </p>



<p>Ramiah et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:375-382 </p>





<p>Ramiah et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:375-382 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>