<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4582499" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Interstitial application of paraffin in plastic and reconstructive surgery 
is obsolete due to the development of permanent and extensive foreign </p>

<p>body granulomas at the site of application. These granulomas can cause 
severe physical impairment and develop their own prognostic worth. 
Furthermore, the disperse oil droplets are not a locally stable suspen-</p>

<p>1 Oral and Cranio-Maxillofacial 
Surgery, Eppendorf University </p>

<p>sion. Therefore, the desired aesthetic aspect can get lost in the course </p>

<p>Hospital, University of 
Hamburg, Germany </p>

<p>of a potential dislocation of the suspension. In addition, the interstitial 
confluence of non-resorbable droplets to larger oil drops causes palpable 
and sometimes visible indurations of the skin, the correlate of chronic </p>

<p>2 Gerhard-Domagk-Institute of 
Pathology, Westfälische </p>

<p>inflammation. This case report describes the efforts undertaken to re-</p>

<p>Wilhelms University, Münster, 
Germany </p>

<p>lease the patient at least temporarily from her paraffin granulomas and 
to improve her appearance. The relevant literature is briefly discussed. 
Furthermore, we present some immunohistochemical findings to specify 
the foreign body reaction associated with paraffin injections into con-
nective tissues. </p>

<p>A plethora of cosmetics are used to enhance the facial 
appearance of humans. In the Western world, facial cos-
metics are predominantly applied to emphasize facial 
parts in order to rejuvenate the physical appearance, to 
comply with current fashion trends, or to cover unattract-</p>

<p>ive skin regions. The application of cosmetics usually is 
externally, i.e. topical application, and thus, these sub-
stances should not to interfere with the body's structure 
or function and should be principally removable. Other 
aesthetic techniques to withstand the visual correlate of 
facial aging or to alter unwelcome facial details are intend-
ed for temporary or definite internal dermal augmentation </p>

<p>1/7 
GMS Interdisciplinary Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery DGPW 2014, Vol. 3, ISSN 2193-8091 </p>

<p>Review Article </p>

<p>OPEN ACCESS </p>

<p>of identified facial parts with substances showing varying 
degrees of three-dimensional stability. A large number of 
injectable dermal fillers are offered as augmentation 
materials, e.g. to contour the oral region [3], [22]. Some 
are used for perioral or lip augmentation, e.g. to flatten 
wrinkles or to support the projection of lips [10]. Concern-
ing the temporal efficacy of these fillers, these substances 
can be categorized as degradable (with large variations 
of degradation times) and permanent [3]. 
However, a variety of approved dermal fillers have the 
ability to cause foreign body reactions, irrespective of the 
intended duration of topic presence [6], [10], [11], [18], 
[23], [25], [26], [27], [32], [33], [37], [39]. In some 
products, the immune response of the material can be 
defined as part of the therapeutic action, because dense 
and stable scar formation in the course of inflammatory 
reaction can support augmentation and therefore can be 
desirable, at least to a certain extent [3], [23]. In other 
instances of aesthetic fillers, topical or systemic adverse 
reactions represent serious complications, because 
severe damage to the region of application or general 
impairment to health may occur [26]. 
Paraffin, a derivative of mineral oil [47], is a well-charac-
terized substance used in a variety of cosmetic products 
[5] and medical ointments [2]. Paraffin is used to preserve 
cosmetics, to stabilize mixtures, and to allow thin layers 
of make-up, to name just a few of these applications. All 
of these approved applications of paraffin as a cosmetic 
product are for external use only. 
The application of paraffin as a permanent filler in plastic 
surgery has been abandoned due to well-known undesir-
able effects [13]. However, the application of paraffin as 
an augmentation material has a long history in aesthetic 
and reconstructive surgery, with reports of initial success-
ful interstitial use dating back to the 19 
th century [13], 
[22]. The medical interstitial application of paraffin was 
abandoned due to the finding that soon after application 
paraffin coalesces, and these non-absorbable agglomer-
ates can become firm and unsightly swellings and can 
cause pain [13], [15], [16], [22], [38]. Histologically, the 
insufficient absorption and degradation of paraffin causes 
distinct foreign body reactions [45]. The distribution and 
disabled degeneration of paraffin inside the body can 
promote further adverse effects, such as migration of the 
material and embolization of vessels [22]. In rare in-
stances, paraffin can be associated with sudden death 
after injection [35] or cause ulcers that mimic cancer 
[41]. Paraffin deposits can even be found in topical asso-
ciation with cancer [21]. 
As a consequence of the elimination of paraffin as an 
augmentation material in all fields of plastic surgery, ad-
verse reactions to interstitial application of paraffin in the 
context of adverse reactions to dermal fillers were con-
sidered to be of historical interest only [33]. However, the 
individual misuse of paraffin as an augmentation mater-
ial is still of interest in surgical practice [7], [8], [9], [12], 
[17], [20], [21], [31], [33], [34], [35], [38], [46]. Further-
more, even some invasive medical procedures may incid-
entally cause interstitial deposition of paraffin, leading </p>

<p>to what is called 'oil granuloma' or the synonymous 'par-
affinoma' [1], [2], [19], [24]. Due to the many regions of 
potential application and the long-lasting harmful effects 
of paraffin, many surgical specialties with up-to-date 
competencies in plastic and reconstructive surgical 
techniques are required to solve physical and psycholo-
gical problems arising after intended or accidental imple-
mentation of paraffin-containing substances into various 
body regions, e.g. scalp [20], [21], eye lids and orbit [2], 
[12], [24], [28], cheek [31], [34], [42], [43], nose [1], 
[40], lips and perioral regions [6], [7], [38], neck [14], 
breast [17], [30], thorax [8], and genitalia [4], [9], [15], 
[41]. 
The aim of this report is to emphasize the special surgical 
problems resulting from misuse of paraffin containing 
oils as dermal filler in the region of the lips and oral mu-
cosa and to provide new findings illustrating the immune 
response to paraffin. </p>

<p>Case report </p>

<p>Medical history and surgical treatment </p>

<p>A 26-year-old female visited the outpatient clinic of the 
department of oral and maxillofacial surgery seeking help 
for her painfully swollen lips. About half a year before, 
she had agreed to have oil injected into her lips by a girl-
friend in order to accentuate her facial appearance with 
full lips. Initially, the result was satisfactory, but a few 
weeks later, the patient noticed painful indurations in 
those parts of the lips where the oil was injected into the 
connective tissues. Finally, she had decided to ask for 
surgical help both to remove these indurations and to 
restore her distorted lip shape (Figure 1A). 
Physical investigation and therapy. On admission, the 
patient showed very prominent and wide lips (Figure 1A). 
The voluminous lips appeared symmetrically designed 
when closed. However, during speaking the assumed 
regions of injection became visible as stationary glossy 
protrusions (Figure 1B). These regions were painful on 
palpation (Figure 1C). The patient reported impaired food 
intake and speaking due to the triggering of pain following 
lip movements. Repeated requests for the name of the 
product she had injected finally revealed a skin oil as the 
source of the lip augmentation material (Bi-Oil™). 
The patient was informed that surgical removal of the 
lesions rarely leads to complete elimination of the foreign 
material without severe mutilation of the lips due to the 
likely wide-spread diffusion of the material inside the lips 
and perioral region. Furthermore, the patient was in-
formed about the long-lasting confluence of finest fat 
droplets that could cause local recurrence of lip protru-
sions despite an initially sufficient debulking procedure. 
In general anaesthesia, a w-shaped incision was per-
formed in the labial mucosa of both lips lateral to the 
margins of the palpable masses (Figure 1D). Soon after 
incision, yellowish, scarred areas became visible inside 
the lip muscles. The masses extended completely through </p>

<p>2/7 
GMS Interdisciplinary Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery DGPW 2014, Vol. 3, ISSN 2193-8091 </p>

<p>Friedrich et al.: Paraffinoma of lips and oral mucosa: Case report and ... </p>

<p>Figure 1: (A) Photograph of the patient's bulky lips at the time of first attendance. (B) Deformity of the lips during lip movements 
caused by paraffin deposits. (C) Dystrophic areas of the integument are visible at the site of paraffin deposits. (D) Incision line 
for debulking of the augmented lips. (E) Whitish and firm tissues constitute the prominent lip masses adhering to the local 
connective tissues. (F) Sample of excised lip tissue. (D) Post-operative photographs demonstrate moderate reduction in lip 
volume. </p>

<p>the oral orbicularis muscle, with focal thickenings 
matching the palpable and visible lip masses (Figures 1E 
and 1F). After excision of the scar tissue, the wounds 
were closed by primary intention. Swelling of the lips 
lasted for about 2 weeks, and after 4 weeks the patient 
noticed a significant volume reduction of her lips. How-
ever, the lips remained swollen, and the patient com-
plained that the visual aspect of her lips still differed from 
her expectations. 
Half a year later, the patient visited the outpatient clinic 
again and complained about recurrence of the bulky and 
prominent lips. Meanwhile, she needed psychiatric 
treatment and was taking anti-depressant medication. 
The lips showed the similar swellings and hardenings 
similar to those that were present before the first inter-
vention. The debulking procedure was repeated. Intra-
operatively, scar-like masses were exposed that were 
identical to the prior findings in amount, distribution, and 
texture. Healing was uneventful. The lips appeared less 
voluminous than before, and the patient reported that 
her lips were now less painful during movement. After 
the first postsurgical follow-up (Figure 1G), she terminated 
further appointments. Two years later, the patient re-
turned to the outpatient department and asked for further </p>

<p>treatment. The lips looked similar to the situation 
presented at her first appointment. In order to achieve 
long-lasting removal of the fibrous tissues, a direct in-
cision over the hardened portions of the lips was chosen 
and extensive debulking was performed. The volume of 
the excised tissue was similar to the volumes excised in 
prior procedures. Healing was uneventful, but again the 
patient discontinued follow-up controls. </p>

<p>Histology </p>

<p>Immediately after the excision of the lip tissues, the 
samples were fixed in buffered formalin and sent to the 
pathology laboratory. After embedding in paraffin wax, 
4-µm-thick sections were stained with haematoxylin-
eosin. Representative sections were further examined 
using automated immunohistochemical systems. The 
freshly cut sections were loaded into a PT Link module 
(Dako, Glostrup, Denmark) and subjected to an antigen 
retrieval/de-waxing protocol with a Dako EnVision FLEX 
Target Retrieval Solution at high pH, and then transferred 
to the Dako Autostainer Link 48 instrument. Immunostain-
ing was performed using the primary antibodies to CD163 
(Novocastra, NCL-CD163, clone 10D6, dilution 1:10, </p>

<p>3/7 
GMS Interdisciplinary Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery DGPW 2014, Vol. 3, ISSN 2193-8091 </p>

<p>Friedrich et al.: Paraffinoma of lips and oral mucosa: Case report and ... </p>

<p>Figure 2: Paraffinoma (microscopic findings). (A) Under low-power magnification, numerous oil cysts and cellular infiltrations 
of soft tissue between the muscle fibres are apparent (haematoxylin and eosin; original magnification 100X). Under higher-power 
magnification, multinucleated giant cells, foamy macrophages, a few lymphocytes and eosinophilic leucocytes along with mast 
cells can be recognized within the interstitial infiltrate. The conventional histology findings were proven by immunohistochemistry 
for (B) CD163, (C) mast cell tryptase (D) CD3, and (E) CD20 (magnification (B-E) 200X). </p>

<p>Newcastle-upon-Tyne, UK), CD3 (Dako, IS503), CD20 
(Dako M0755, clone L26), mast cell tryptase (Dako 
IR640/IS640, clone AA1), and the Dako EnVision Flex 
detection system. Microscopic analyses were performed 
using a Zeiss microscope (Axiophot, Carl Zeiss, Jena, 
Germany) and representative microphotographs were 
taken using a digital camera (AxioCam MRc, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Carl Zeiss</rs>), 
and <rs id="software-0" type="software">AxioVision</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Rel. 4.8</rs>. imaging software (Carl Zeiss). 
The microscopic analysis of the tissue showed skeletal 
muscle fibres (Figure 2A) surrounded by numerous oil 
cysts rimmed by foamy macrophages and multinucleated 
giant cells as well. During the processing of the specimen 
the areas previously filled with oil appear as empty 
spaces. Minimal, thin fibrous fibres can also be recog-
nized between the oil cysts. Moreover, the interstitial tis-
sues contained many mononuclear macrophages with 
small oil droplets and foamy macrophages. There were 
no microscopic signs of a secondary infection; however, 
scattered lymphocytes, mast cells and eosinophilic 
leukocytes were found throughout the lesion. Under po-
larized light, neither birefringent particles nor crystals 
were found within the lesion. The dominant cell type 
within the interstitial tissues was the mature M2 macro-
phage, which showed characteristic expression of the 
CD163 antigen (Figure 2B). The low intra-lesional occur-
rence of the mast cells was proven by immunohistochem-
istry using the specific antibody against mast cell tryptase 
(Figure 2C). Furthermore, immunohistochemical analysis 
showed a slight dominance of CD3-positive T-lymphocytes 
(Figure 2D) over B-lymphocytes, which showed positive 
reaction to CD20 antibodies (Figure 2E). 
The microscopic aspect of the tissues was identical on 
all occasions. </p>

<p>Material </p>

<p>Bi-Oil™/Bio-Oil™ (Producer: delta pronatura/Dr. Krauss 
and Dr. Beckmann KG, Egelsbach, Germany) is a skin oil, 
with recommended use for external application only to 
improve the appearance of scars and stretch marks and 
to adjust uneven skin tones. Further recommended ex-
ternal applications are ageing and dehydrated skin. The 
producer's disclosure of contents emphasizes that Bi-
Oil™ is a formulation that is a combination of plant ex-
tracts and vitamins suspended in an oil base. The list of 
ingredients starts with paraffin liquidum and other oils, 
e.g. tri-isononanoin, cetearyl ethylhexonate, isopropyl 
myristate, and soja oil. The non-specified ingredient Pur-
Cellin Oil™ appears to influence the formulation's overall 
consistency and is likely a mixture of several products, 
such as plant extracts (lavender, rosemary, and chamo-
mile) and vitamins A and E. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This report details the diagnosis and treatment for lip 
paraffinoma with respect to some morphological findings 
associated with the oil deposits. The instillation of paraffin 
for plastic surgery purposes is obsolete [13]. In the 
presented case, the paraffin-containing oil was admin-
istered by a layperson. The content declaration of this 
product discloses other ingredients -in particular, oils 
that also may have contributed to the foreign body reac-
tion. Thus, the term 'oil granuloma' appears to be more 
appropriate to characterize the specific origin of this for-
eign body reaction. However, paraffin is usually the main 
component of these oils, and therefore, it is likely to 
constitute the majority of the dispersed oil. </p>

<p>4/7 
GMS Interdisciplinary Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery DGPW 2014, Vol. 3, ISSN 2193-8091 </p>

<p>Friedrich et al.: Paraffinoma of lips and oral mucosa: Case report and ... </p>

<p>Imaging of head and neck paraffinoma may show specific 
findings on computed tomograms [14]. Imaging should 
be considered in cases with application of paraffin to a 
wide region of the body or deep injection sides of the 
body [14]. 
Paraffin is a mixture of high-molecular-weight hydrocar-
bons with a colourless-to-white aspect [47]. Usually par-
affin is well tolerated after application onto skin or mu-
cosa. However, after accidental or intentional subcu-
taneous infiltration, a foreign body reaction develops; in 
some cases ulceration may even occur [36]. Adverse ef-
fects to paraffin injections are typically confined to the 
sites of application and adjacent regions. However, some 
reports detail the involvement of lymph nodes and lungs 
after paraffin injection. These complications are thought 
to reveal the spread of material via lymphatic or haema-
togenous routes and have occasionally been associated 
with fatalities [35]. 
In the context of adverse reactions to interstitial paraffin 
applications, it is noteworthy to emphasize that adverse 
reactions were also reported for approved dermal fillers 
[26]. However, these adverse reactions appear to be 
predominantly temporary [3], [10]. 
The latency period between injection and the growth of 
indurations or ulcers can take months to years [36]. In 
general, the slow tissue response to the oil was reported 
to achieve its maximum about three months after appli-
cation [13]. The degree of reaction appears to be propor-
tional to the amount of oil injected [13]. 
Initially, the paraffinoma was considered a sclerosing 
lipogranuloma arising after trauma and essentially con-
sisting of altered endogenous lipids. At a later point in 
time, evidence was presented for exogenous lipids in the 
vacuoles of paraffinomas, leading to the assumption that 
interstitial paraffin cannot be absorbed and dissolved in 
vivo [29]. 
Histologically, paraffinoma is a granulomatous foreign 
body reaction that results from the interstitial application 
of oily substances [4]. The microscopic characteristics of 
paraffinoma are already well characterized [17], [33], 
[45]. So-called oil cysts with empty centres and rims of 
foamy or multinucleated macrophages represent the 
typical lesion of the paraffinoma. Due to the process of 
tissue conservation (usually in paraffin) and preparation 
(dewaxing procedures), however, the oil is usually com-
pletely washed out from the slices, and the interstitial or 
even intracellular vacuoles represent the residues of the 
oil [19], [24]. These vacuoles are surrounded by giant 
cells, a variably dense, eosinophilic infiltrate of round 
cells and a marked fibrosis [15]. Our immunohistochem-
ical analysis of oil granuloma specified the cellular com-
ponents involved in the process of foreign body reaction, 
macrophages and lymphocytes. 
Complete surgical excision is considered to be the treat-
ment of choice. However, a complete excision is not al-
ways possible, e.g. due to the functional impairments 
after wide resection or the stark extent of paraffin distri-
bution [2], [30], [44]. A perilesional approach was suc-
cessfully applied to remove foreign body granulomas [31]. </p>

<p>In this case we also considered a hidden oral incision line 
somewhat distant from the palpable masses to be ad-
equate for approaching the oil granulomas. The w-shaped 
incision allowed the excision and retraction of the lip in 
the region of prominent granulomas. However, the scar 
tissue clearly adhered to the covering lip epithelia. Thus, 
only a partially excision was carried out below the red 
portion of the lips in order to maintain the characteristic 
lip epithelia. However, any surgical attempt to improve 
the appearance by removing the paraffinoma or other 
foreign bodies used as filler must take into account that 
the expectations of patients presumably will not fully be 
accomplished [40]. 
Paraffinoma can be the physical finding that indicates a 
body dysmorphic disorder and other severe psychiatric 
disorders [34]. Therefore, supportive psychological ther-
apy should be seriously considered in patients who are 
surgically treated for paraffinoma resulting from intention-
al injections into the body. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Interstitial application of paraffin-containing substances 
of any kind must be avoided in the fields of plastic and 
reconstructive surgery. Even with surgical therapy of so-
called paraffinomas, it is difficult to achieve long-lasting 
satisfactory results. </p>

<p>Notes </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no competing in-
terests. </p>



<p> 
GMS Interdisciplinary Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery DGPW 2014, Vol. 3, ISSN 2193-8091 </p>

<p>Friedrich et al.: Paraffinoma of lips and oral mucosa: Case report and ... </p>



<p> 
GMS Interdisciplinary Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery DGPW 2014, Vol. 3, ISSN 2193-8091 </p>

<p>Friedrich et al.: Paraffinoma of lips and oral mucosa: Case report and ... </p>



<p>Corresponding author: 
Prof. Reinhard E. Friedrich, MD, DMD, PhD, FEBOMFS 
Oral and Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery, Eppendorf 
University Hospital, University of Hamburg, 20246 
Hamburg, Germany, Phone: +49-(0)-741053259 
rfriedrich@uke.de </p>

<p>Please cite as 
Friedrich RE, Zustin J. Paraffinoma of lips and oral mucosa: Case report 
and brief review of the literature. GMS Interdiscip Plast Reconstr Surg 
DGPW. 2014;3:Doc05. 
DOI: 10.3205/iprs000046, URN: urn:nbn:de:0183-iprs0000467 </p>

<p>This article is freely available from 
http://www.egms.de/en/journals/iprs/2014-3/iprs000046.shtml </p>

<p>Published: 2014-05-15 </p>

<p>Copyright 
©2014 Friedrich et al. This is an Open Access article distributed under 
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/deed.en). You 
are free: to Share -to copy, distribute and transmit the work, provided 
the original author and source are credited. </p>

<p> 
GMS Interdisciplinary Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery DGPW 2014, Vol. 3, ISSN 2193-8091 </p>

<p>Friedrich et al.: Paraffinoma of lips and oral mucosa: Case report and ... </p>

</text></tei>