<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4376262" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Cell culture systems have proven to be crucial for the in vitro maintenance of primary </p>

<p>hepatocytes and the preservation of hepatic functional expression at a high level. A poly-(N-p-
vinylbenzyl-4-O-β-D-galactopyranosyl-D-gluconamide) matrix can recognize cells and promote 
liver function in a spheroid structure because of a specific galactose-asialoglycoprotein receptor 
interaction. Meanwhile, a fusion protein, E-cadherin-Fc, when incubated with various cells, has 
shown an enhancing effect on cellular viability and metabolism. Therefore, a hybrid substratum 
was developed for biomedical applications by using both of these materials to combine their 
advantages for primary hepatocyte cultures. The isolated cells showed a monolayer aggregate 
morphology on the coimmobilized surface and displayed higher functional expression than cells 
on traditional matrices. Furthermore, the hybrid system, in which the highest levels of cell adhe-
sion and hepatocellular metabolism were achieved with the addition of 1% fetal bovine serum, 
showed a lower serum dependency than the collagen/gelatin-coated surface. Accordingly, this 
substrate may attenuate the negative effects of serum and further contribute to establishing 
a defined culture system for primary hepatocytes. 
Hepatocytes, which compose the majority of the cellular mass in the liver, play many 
complex roles in the metabolism of living organisms; these functions include detoxifica-
tion, metabolism, bile secretion, immune defense, and protein synthesis. 1 The features 
of isolated hepatocytes from adult mammals during in vitro primary incubation may 
reflect the general properties of these cells in vivo. Accordingly, a valuable cellular 
model has been established for studies regarding the regulation of the functionality, 
senescence, and transformation of liver cells. Because of their easy access, the cells 
are widely utilized in clinical trials to investigate hepatic function, estimate xenobiotic 
metabolism, establish artificial organs in vitro, and further regenerate tissue in vivo. 2,3 
However, hepatocytes tend to lose their reproductive activity and specific liver function 
steadily after isolation. Meanwhile, attempts to replace primary cells by using permanent 
cells or even cancer cell lines have also encountered drawbacks because the substitute 
cells are not fully consistent with primary cells with regard to metabolism and func-
tionality. Therefore, the use of a primary culture of hepatocytes remains a significant 
challenge, and various techniques have been devised to promote cellular viability and 
functional expression; these methods include the development of extracellular matrix 
(ECM) substrata, soluble factor supplements, and coculture systems. 4,5 </p>

<p>correspondence: Xiumei Wang 
school of Materials science and 
engineering, Tsinghua University, Beijing 
100084, People's republic of china 
Tel +86 10 6278 2966 
email wxm@mail.tsinghua.edu.cn </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
23 March 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2314 </p>

<p>Meng et al </p>

<p>Appropriate modifications of physical and chemical 
methods for culture matrices may lead to the retention of 
the cellular replication capacity and differentiated func-
tions in hepatocytes. Cell-recognizable materials have 
become increasingly available for the construction of cell 
culture substrata, which can mimic the in vivo conditions to 
provide specific ECMs for specific cell lineages to induce 
functional differentiation. Among these materials, poly-(N-
p-vinylbenzyl-4-O-β-D-galactopyranosyl-D-gluconamide) 
(PVLA) possesses galactose termini on its side chains and 
can specifically recognize hepatocytes through an inter-
action between asialoglycoprotein receptors (ASGPRs) 
on the cellular membrane and the polymer. 6,7 ASGPR is a 
membrane receptor on liver cells, and its primary physio-
logical function is to internalize galactose from circulating 
blood. 8 It is further involved in the removal of apoptotic 
cells and acts as a carrier of low-density lipoprotein and as 
an entry point for hepatotropic viruses or DNA. 9 ASGPR, 
in association with PVLA, assists primary hepatocytes in 
forming a multilayered aggregate morphology on the matrix. 
The liver-specific functions of the incubated cells on the 
galactose-carrying polymer, including ammonia removal 
and albumin secretion, have been found to be enhanced 
over the long term. 10,11 Moreover, a chimeric protein, 
E-cadherin-Fc (EFC), composed of the E-cadherin extracel-
lular domain and the immunoglobulin G (IgG) Fc domain, 
is capable of enhancing the cellular viability of endodermal 
cells. 12 The protein-coated surface could further preserve 
the hepatocellular functions and metabolism of hepatic cell 
lineages. 12,13 This combination in the culture system can 
promote the hepatic induction of embryonic stem cells in 
the late stage of oriented differentiation. 14 
In addition, primary hepatocytes were incubated with 
serum in early experiments to promote cellular behaviors. 15 
However, it is possible that the presence of fetal bovine serum 
(FBS) in the culture medium may produce a nonimmuno-
suppressive condition and introduce xenobiotic substances 
into the system. The supplementation of the serum can 
increase the risk of disease transmission, including spongi-
form encephalitis, when the cells are expanded for clinical 
transplantation. Because of its instability in composition and 
quality, serum supplementation may further lead to a reduc-
tion in cellular metabolism. 16 In one experiment, cells were 
maintained in a hormonally defined medium because of their 
response to hepatotropic growth factors, including epidermal 
growth factor, transforming growth factor-α, and insulin, to 
stabilize the culture system and reduce the negative influence. 
Although the cost of the incubation system, especially for </p>

<p>massive cell culture, was increased, the cellular behaviors in 
this system were preserved or even promoted. Therefore, it 
is beneficial if the PVLA matrix does not require serum for 
hepatocyte maintenance and induction. 17,18 
In this study, isolated hepatocytes were seeded on a hybrid 
substrate of PVLA and EFC to achieve monolayer aggregate 
morphology in vitro. Increased functional and metabolic 
expression were observed in primary hepatocytes at both 
the gene and protein levels, unlike in the cells on collagen 
or gelatin surfaces. The effects of serum concentration (0%, 
1%, and 10%) on cellular attachment, maintenance, and 
hepatic marker expression were further analyzed, and a low 
serum dependency in the cell-recognizable system with dual 
components was revealed. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Preparation of cell-recognizable matrices </p>

<p>PVLA and EFC were prepared by previously described 
methods and filter sterilized after dissolution. 19,20 The hybrid 
substratum was produced by the sequential addition of EFC 
(2.5 μg/mL) and PVLA (50 μg/mL) solutions for 2 hours each 
to a nontreated polystyrene (PS) dish at 37°C. The control 
substrata were produced by adding PVLA (100 μg/mL) 
solution to a nontreated dish or adding gelatin (1 mg/mL) 
or collagen I (100 μg/mL) solutions to treated PS dishes at 
37°C for 2 hours each. The surfaces were rinsed thrice with 
phosphate buffered saline (PBS) and prepared for the future 
incubation of primary hepatocytes. </p>

<p>enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay 
(elIsa) for eFc adsorption </p>

<p>The sample solutions of EFC were prepared at different con-
centrations consisting of 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 15 and 30 μg/mL. 
Then, 50 μL of EFC solution at each concentration was 
maintained in a nontreated 96-well plate for 2 hours at 37°C. 
The surface was subsequently washed thrice with PBS and 
blocked by using 100 μL of Blocking One solution (Nacalai 
Tesque, Kyoto, Japan) for 30 minutes. After the liquid 
was completely removed, 50 μL of horseradish peroxi-
dase (HRP)-conjugated anti-mouse IgG antibody (Jackson 
ImmunoResearch Laboratories, West Grove, PA, USA) was 
added, and the plate was incubated for 1 hour at room tem-
perature. O-phenylenediamine dissolved in 100 μL of citric 
acid-phosphoric acid solution with H 2 O 2 was then added to 
the wells for 10 minutes at room temperature. Approximately 
20 μL of H 2 SO 4 solution (1 M) was added to the mixed solu-
tion to produce a pH value of 1.0. Finally, the optical density 
was measured at 492 nm by using a microplate reader. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2315 </p>

<p>low serum dependent hybrid substratum for hepatocyte culture </p>

<p>Quartz crystal microbalance (QcM) test 
for coimmobilization of eFc and PVla </p>

<p>The sequential adsorption of EFC and PVLA was confirmed 
by using the AFFINIX Q4 apparatus (Initium Co. Ltd., 
Tokyo, Japan) with a temperature controlling system. First, 
the electrodes of the QCM cells were cleaned and coated 
with a thin film of PS by using a high-speed spinning method. 
After the QCM instrument was stabilized for 2 hours, 500 μL 
of EFC solution (2.5 μg/mL) was added to the cell. The 
surface was washed with distilled water after the oscillation 
frequency was stabilized. Subsequently, 500 μL of PVLA 
solution (50 μg/mL) was added to the cell, which was then 
rinsed. The change of mass per unit area was calculated from 
the change in frequency by using the Sauerbrey Equation. 
A Langmuir adsorption curve was produced via double 
reciprocal data fitting. </p>

<p>Isolation and culture of mouse primary 
hepatocytes </p>

<p>The primary hepatocytes were obtained from the liver of 
anaesthetized male mice (6-7 weeks old) (Japan SLC Inc, 
Hamamatsu, Japan) by using a two-step hepatic portal vein 
perfusion method. 21,22 All procedures complied with the insti-
tutional ethical use protocol of the Animal Center in Tokyo 
Institute of Technology. After removal, the tissue was dis-
sected in Hank's solution and filtered through a 100 mm cell 
strainer. Then, the living hepatocytes were isolated and puri-
fied by using density gradient centrifugation. Subsequently, 
the cells were suspended in Gibco ® Dulbecco's Modified 
Eagle's Medium (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, 
USA) with FBS (volume/volume [v/v] 0%, 1%, or 10%) 
and antibiotics (50 μg/mL penicillin, 50 μg/mL streptomy-
cin, and 100 μg/mL neomycin). After the cellular viability 
was confirmed by using the Trypan Blue exclusion method 
(95%), the viable cells were seeded on previously coated 
PVLA, gelatin, collagen, and coimmobilized surfaces. The 
primary hepatocytes were incubated at 37°C in an atmosphere 
of 5% CO 2 during culture. The medium was changed after 
4 hours to remove the nonadherent and dead cells and was 
changed every day thereafter during culture. </p>

<p>Measurement of cell viability by using 
a cell adhesion assay </p>

<p>After washing with PBS, the hepatocytes incubated on vari-
ous coated surfaces in a 96-well plate were fixed with 4% 
formaldehyde (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd., Osaka, 
Japan) for 15 minutes and later stained with 0.1% (weight/ 
volume [w/v]) Crystal Violet for 10 minutes. The absorbency </p>

<p>at 570 nm was measured after adding 2% (v/v) sodium 
dodecyl sulfate solution for 30 minutes. Evaluations of cell 
attachment of the cultured cells were performed at 4 hours and 
subsequently every 2 days thereafter (days 1, 3, 5, 7, and 9) 
to estimate cell maintenance. The percentage of cultured 
cells that remained after 3, 5, 7, and 9 days relative to the 
original number of the cells on the first day was considered 
as the relative preservation of isolated hepatocytes in each 
culture system. </p>

<p>semiquantitative reverse transcription 
polymerase chain reaction </p>

<p>On days 1 and 5, RNA from the incubated hepatocytes in 
the hybrid systems with different serum concentrations 
was extracted from the cell lysates by using the TRIzol 
reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific) suspended in distilled 
water; later, the RNA was reverse transcribed into comple-
mentary DNA. Then, polymerase chain reaction (PCR) 
was performed, and the products were analyzed by using 
2% agarose gel electrophoresis and scanned by using a 
Molecular Dynamics Typhoon 8600 Imager. The rela-
tive intensities of the target genes (the genes for albumin, 
hepatocyte nuclear factor-4 alpha [HNF-4α], and ASGPR) 
were calculated with <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> image analysis software (Ver-
sion 1.48) and were compared to a housekeeping marker, 
glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase. The level of 
expression of these genes in cells on gelatin surfaces with 
10% FBS served as a control. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence analysis 
of hepatic markers </p>

<p>After 1 day and again after 5 days, PBS-rinsed primary hepato-
cytes in various systems were fixed with 8% formaldehyde for 
20 minutes and were made permeable with 0.2% Triton X-100 
(Nacalai Tesque) for 5 minutes. After blocking with Blocking 
One solution for 1 hour, the cells were incubated with primary 
antibodies to albumin (goat anti-mouse albumin; Abcam, Cam-
bridge, UK) or ASGPR (rabbit anti-human ASGPR1/2; Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology, Dallas, TX, USA) for 2 hours at room 
temperature. The cells were triple-rinsed with PBS and incu-
bated with the corresponding secondary antibodies (Alexa 555-
conjugated donkey anti-goat IgG, Thermo Fisher Scientific; 
Alexa 488-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG, Thermo Fisher 
Scientific) for 2 hours; the cells were then counterstained with 
4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, 
USA) to label the cell nuclei. After rinses with PBS, protein 
staining in the cells was examined with a fluorescent inverted 
microscope (Olympus Corporation, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2316 </p>

<p>Meng et al </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>After 1 day and again after 5 days, the cellular proteins were 
extracted from the primary hepatocytes cultured on coimmo-
bilized matrices with different serum concentrations. The cells 
cultured on gelatin with 10% FBS were used as the control 
group. Then, the proteins were separated by sodium dodecyl 
sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and transferred onto a 
polyvinylidene difluoride membrane (EMD Millipore, Billerica, 
MA, USA). The membrane was incubated with primary antibod-
ies to albumin (Abcam) and β-actin (Sigma), the latter of which 
was used as a housekeeping marker, for 2 hours. After the rinses, 
the membrane was further incubated with an HRP-conjugated 
secondary antibody (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories) 
for another 2 hours at room temperature. The HRP activity was 
assayed with Immobilon Western detection reagents (EMD Mil-
lipore) and observed under a fluorescent inverted microscope. </p>

<p>glycogen storage (periodic acid -schiff 
reaction) </p>

<p>After 3 days of culture, the primary hepatocytes were fixed 
with 8% formaldehyde for 10 minutes. After being rinsed 
with periodic acid -Schiff (PBS), the cells were oxidized 
in 1% periodic acid (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd.) 
for 5 minutes and then rinsed again. After the addition of the 
Schiff reagent (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd.) for 
10 minutes, the cells were washed and observed. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>The results are presented as the mean ± standard deviation and 
were compared by using a Student's t-test. A P-value 0.05 was 
considered statistically significant, and a P-value 0.01 was 
considered highly statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
The construction of a hybrid matrix </p>

<p>First, the EFC adsorption on the PS dish was confirmed 
by using the ELISA method, which indicated that the pro-
tein adsorption curve conformed to the Langmuir pattern. 
The lowest concentration of the protein solution to form a 
monolayer on PS surface was 10 μg/mL and was considered 
as the monolayer concentration (Figure 1A). Then, EFC and 
PVLA were successively added to a nontreated PS surface 
and evaluated by using the QCM method (Figure 1B). EFC 
with a concentration less than the monolayer concentration 
(2.5 μg/mL) was immobilized on a dish surface, and space 
was left for subsequent PVLA addition. Therefore, a hybrid 
matrix with two components was constructed for future 
applications in hepatocyte culture. </p>

<p>The attachment of hepatocytes 
to the hybrid matrix </p>

<p>The isolated hepatocytes maintained their spherical mor-
phology on PVLA-coated dishes after 4 hours (Figure 2A), 
whereas their morphology was more spread out on control 
matrices consisting of gelatin and collagen (Figure 2C and D). 
Meanwhile, the primary hepatocytes showed a dual pattern. 
Some cells contracted while other cells were spread out 
because of the presence of both PVLA and EFC in the culture 
system (Figure 2B). Moreover, the serum requirement for 
the cells to achieve the maximal adherence on each surface 
differed in accordance with the substrata. In particular, on 
the hybrid matrix and on the PVLA surface, the number of 
hepatocytes was higher for the cells supplied with 1% FBS 
than for the cells supplied with serum at other concentra-
tions (Figure 2E). The cells exhibited better attachment to </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 </p>

<p>Concentration of EFC (µg/mL) 
Adsorbance (492 nm) </p>

<p>15 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>Unit adsorption (ng/cm 2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Time (seconds) </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>900 </p>

<p>1,100 </p>

<p>Addition 
of EFC 
Addition 
of PVLA 
Rinse 
Rinse </p>

<p>0 
2 ,000 
3,000 
4,000 
1,000 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Figure 1 The adsorption of substrata on the Ps surface. 
Notes: The EFC adsorption of PS was confirmed by using the ELISA method, which revealed that 10 μg/ml was the monolayer concentration of eFc (A). The coimmobilization 
of eFc (red) and PVla (blue) is shown (B). 
Abbreviations: Ps, polystyrene; eFc, e-cadherin-Fc; elIsa, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; PVla, poly-(N-p-vinylbenzyl-4-O-β-D-galactopyranosyl-D-gluconamide). </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2317 </p>

<p>low serum dependent hybrid substratum for hepatocyte culture </p>

<p>traditional matrices, including collagen and gelatin, with a 
serum supply in the concentration range of approximately 
0%-10% (Figure 2E); further increases in serum concentra-
tion showed no additional beneficial influence. 23 Aside from 
the hepatocytes on PVLA-coated dishes, the differences in 
cell viability on the other three matrices are statistically sig-
nificant among the different FBS concentrations (0%, 1%, 
and 10%) supplied for the cultures. </p>

<p>The maintenance of hepatocytes 
on the hybrid matrix </p>

<p>The matrices continued to show effects on cell behavior 
during hepatocyte maintenance in culture. One day after 
seeding, the primary hepatocytes revealed a monolayer mor-
phology on coimmobilized (Figure 3A and G) and gelatin-
coated surfaces (Figure 3C and I), while they maintained a 
round shape on PVLA surfaces (Figure 3B and H). During </p>

<p>Gelatin </p>

<p>Scale bar: 50 µm </p>

<p>Hybrid matrix </p>

<p>PVLA </p>

<p>Collagen </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>Adhesion ratio of hepatocytes </p>

<p>(percentage of cells on gelatin without FBS) </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
0% FBS 
1% FBS 
10% FBS </p>

<p>Gelatin </p>

<p>Hybrid </p>

<p>PVLA </p>

<p>Collagen </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Figure 2 The attachment of primary hepatocytes in various systems (4 hours). 
Notes: The cell morphology on PVla with 1% FBs (A), the hybrid matrix with 1% FBs (B), gelatin with 10% FBs (C), and collagen with 10% FBs (D) is shown. The relative 
amount of attached hepatocytes was further determined by using the number of cells on the gelatin surface without FBs as the 100% value (E). The cell numbers on gelatin 
and on collagen increased when the serum concentration ranged from 0% to 10%, and they reached the highest level on the PVla-containing matrices in the medium with 
1% FBs. The hybrid matrix was made up of eFc and PVla. scale bar: 50 μm. 
Abbreviations: FBs, fetal bovine serum; PVla, poly-(N-p-vinylbenzyl-4-O-β-D-galactopyranosyl-D-gluconamide); eFc, e-cadherin-Fc. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2318 </p>

<p>Meng et al </p>

<p>continuous incubation, the hepatocytes clustered in the 
culture systems because of the presence of PVLA, whereas 
the cells spread out on the gelatin and other traditional 
matrices. Finally, the cells formed monolayer aggregates on 
the hybrid matrix (Figure 3D and J) and multilayer spheroid 
structures on PVLA-coated dishes (Figure 3E and K) after 
5 days in culture. Furthermore, the viability of the maintained 
cells reached the highest level at each time point (days 1, 3, 
5, 7, and 9) with a concentration of 1% FBS on the hybrid 
matrix and on PVLA (Figure 4A); however, a higher serum 
concentration could possibly enhance cell maintenance in 
the gelatin or collagen systems. The highest cell numbers, 
in ascending order for different time points, occurred on the 
following surfaces: PVLA  hybrid surface  gelatin and 
collagen, especially in the early culture period. The total num-
ber of cells gradually became smaller over time, and finally 
remained similar among these systems on days 7 and 9. 
Moreover, the number of remaining hepatocytes relative 
to the initial cell number during 1 week was higher on the 
surfaces with PVLA than on the other matrices supplemented 
with the optimal serum concentrations (Figure 4B). </p>

<p>The hepatic marker expression 
of hepatocytes on the hybrid matrix </p>

<p>The specific markers expressed in primary hepatocytes were 
measured at both the protein and the gene levels by using </p>

<p>various methods. Our results indicated that both the matrix 
and serum in the culture system may affect the cellular 
behavior of isolated hepatocytes. The immunofluorescence 
staining method revealed the expression of the proteins, 
including albumin and ASGPR, in primary hepatocytes. 
After 1 day, most of the isolated cells expressed albumin 
(red, Figure 3A-C) and ASGPR (green, Figure 3G-I), both 
in relatively high levels on various matrices, although dif-
ferent patterns were revealed that included both contracted 
and spread out morphology. The hepatocytes on the hybrid 
matrix and PVLA-coated dish further maintained albumin 
(red, Figure 3D and F) and ASGPR (green, Figure 3J and K) 
expression in large amounts after 5 days, whereas the amount 
of expression rapidly decreased on other matrices. 
After 1 day and again after 5 days, the hepatic genes 
responsible for the liver function in cells on the hybrid sub-
strate of PVLA and EFC were examined by PCR (Figure 5A). 
It has been reported that the cellular transcription markers can 
be regulated in complex environments, including ones that 
contain hormones, cytokines, xenobiotics, and ECMs. We 
found that the cells on the coimmobilized matrix of PVLA and 
EFC maintained expression of liver-specific genes, including 
those for albumin, HNF-4α, and ASGPR, for at least 5 days 
(Figure 5A). Among all the hybrid systems with various 
concentrations of serum, the coimmobilized matrix with 1% 
FBS exhibited an optimal performance in preserving hepatic </p>































































<p>
Figure 3 Immunofluorescence images of primary hepatocytes. 
Notes: The immunofluorescence images of primary hepatocytes cultured on EFC-PVLA hybrid matrix, PVLA, and gelatin after 1 day and after 5 days. The expression of 
albumin (red, A-F) and asgPr (green, G-L) is shown, and DaPI was used for nuclear staining (blue). scale bar: 50 μm. 
Abbreviations: FBs, fetal bovine serum; PVla, poly-(N-p-vinylbenzyl-4-O-β-D-galactopyranosyl-D-gluconamide); asgPr, asialoglycoprotein receptor; DaPI, 4′,6-diamidino-
2-phenylindole; eFc, e-cadherin-Fc. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2319 </p>

<p>low serum dependent hybrid substratum for hepatocyte culture </p>

<p>expression, especially after long-term incubation. Meanwhile, 
compared to the gelatin surface (10% FBS), the PVLA/EFC 
matrix (1% FBS) may have to a greater extent enhanced the 
expression levels of mature markers in primary hepatocytes, 
such as albumin (Figure 5B), HNF-4α (Figure 5C), and 
ASGPR (Figure 5D) at each time point. During the incuba-
tion, the isolated hepatocytes on the hybrid substratum showed 
no sharp declines in the expression of these genes, whereas 
the expression rapidly decreased on the control surface. The 
preservation effect was particularly evident in the markers, 
including HNF-4α (Figure 5C) and ASGPR (Figure 5D), that 
were expressed in highly mature hepatic cells. 
To further examine the serum effect, the albumin expres-
sion in hepatocytes at the same time points (days 1 and 5) 
was revealed by the Western blot method (Figure 6) and was </p>

<p>consistent with the immunochemistry results. On each matrix, 
albumin began to be secreted in abnormally high amounts 
after 1 day of incubation. The highest level of protein secre-
tion was exhibited in cells maintained on the hybrid matrix 
supplied with 1% FBS, whereas the amount of secretion was 
attenuated in the hepatocytes with other serum concentrations 
or on other surfaces. </p>

<p>The glycogen storage in hepatocytes 
on the hybrid matrix </p>

<p>In addition to their protein secreting capability, hepatocytes 
possess many other functionalities, such as the synthesis of 
biomolecules, transformation of carbohydrates, and formation 
of bile. Here, the functional expression of primary hepato-
cytes was revealed by their glycogen storage capability after </p>













































































<p>Figure 4 The maintenance of primary hepatocytes on the hybrid matrix after 1, 3, 5, 7, and 9 days. 
Notes: The relative ratios of attached cells in various systems were determined by using the number of cells on PVla without FBs as the 100% value. The number of primary 
hepatocytes on the hybrid matrix was higher in the medium with 1% FBs at every time point than the cells on the same surface without or with 10% FBs. The hepatocytes were 
viable on PVla (1% FBs), gelatin (10% FBs), and collagen (10% FBs), which was used as a control (A). The relative preservation of hepatocytes was determined by normalizing 
the cell numbers to the value after 1 day on each matrix (B). The hybrid matrix was made up of EFC and PVLA. The symbol * denotes statistical significance at P0.05. 
Abbreviations: FBs, fetal bovine serum; PVla, poly-(N-p-vinylbenzyl-4-O-β-D-galactopyranosyl-D-gluconamide); eFc, e-cadherin-Fc. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2320 </p>

<p>Meng et al </p>

<p>1 day (Figure 7). The hepatocytes showed an elevated level of 
stored glycogen (red color) on the PVLA surface (Figure 7A) and 
on the coimmobilized matrix (Figure 7B) with a cluster morphol-
ogy, in contrast to the spreading cells on the gelatin (Figure 7C) 
and on the collagen surface (Figure 7D). The amount of stored 
glycogen was highest in cells on the PVLA matrix, although 
the cell number there was the smallest. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>PVLA, which possesses galactose termini, plays an impor-
tant role in hepatocyte incubation and stimulation because 
of its specific ability to recognize ASGPRs on the cellular 
membrane. 24,25 The receptors may seize the galactose ends 
on the side chains of the glycopolymer and may tend to 
ingest them through cellular endocytosis. However, the 
hydrophobic interaction between the polymer backbone 
and PS can attach PVLA to the surface of nontreated cell 
culture dishes. Thus, the PVLA matrix possesses the capa-
bility to specifically adhere to the isolated hepatocytes and 
maintain the cellular expression of ASGPRs at a high level. 
The receptors commonly found on mature hepatocytes are 
believed to induce maturity of these cells. 26 The PVLA 
matrix is hence suitable for the culture of primary hepato-
cytes and the maintenance of their hepatic differentiation 
status after isolation. 27 Furthermore, a Ca 2+ dependent cell </p>





























<p>α </p>













<p>
α </p>

























































































<p>
Figure 5 The transcription markers of primary hepatocytes on the hybrid matrix with different concentrations of FBs on days 1 and 5. 
Notes: The expression of hepatic markers at the gene level was analyzed by using rT-Pcr (A). The relative expression levels of the markers alB (B), hNF-4α (C), and 
asgPr (D) were quantified by using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software and normalized to the GAPDH housekeeping gene. The primary hepatocytes cultured on gelatin with 10% FBS are used 
as a control. The expression level of each maker on gelatin after 1 day culture is considered as 100%. The hybrid matrix was made up of eFc and PVla. The symbols * and 
**denote statistical significance at P0.05 and at P0.01. 
Abbreviations: rT-Pcr, reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction; g, gelatin; FBs, fetal bovine serum; alB, albumin; hNF-4α, hepatocyte nuclear factor-4 alpha; asgPr, 
asialoglycoprotein receptor; gaPDh, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase; eFc, e-cadherin-Fc; PVla, poly-(N-p-vinylbenzyl-4-O-β-D-galactopyranosyl-D-gluconamide). </p>















<p>β </p>







<p>
Figure 6 The alB expression of hepatocytes after day 1 and after day 5. 
Notes: The ALB expression was confirmed using Western blot analysis and 
compared with the expression of the housekeeping β-actin. 
Abbreviations: alB, albumin; g, gelatin; FBs, fetal bovine serum. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2321 </p>

<p>low serum dependent hybrid substratum for hepatocyte culture </p>

<p>adhesion molecule, E-cadherin, also contributes to the for-
mation of aggregates in endoderm cell lineages and hence 
results in a prolongation of the cell survivability term and 
further enhancement of differentiation functionality. 14,28 A 
chimeric protein called EFC was developed with E-cadherin 
as a base by combining the extracellular domain of mouse 
E-cadherin and the Fc domain of IgG. The fusion protein 
was intended to be applied for cell recognition and incuba-
tion. The artificial substratum may selectively recognize 
endoderm cells and further determine the differentiation 
direction of stem cells in the endodermal system, includ-
ing cells of hepatic lineage. 12 Therefore, we combined the 
virtues of E-cadherin and galactose-carrying biomaterials 
in the hepatic culture. Specifically, the hybrid system for 
mouse primary hepatocytes was devised by immobilizing 
EFC molecules after PVLA addition onto a hydrophobic 
surface, and culture media without any cytokines but 
various concentrations (v/v 0%, 1%, and 10%) of FBS 
were used. The beneficial effects of the coimmobilized 
substratum on the cellular phenotype, serum dependency, 
and functional expression were revealed at both the gene 
and protein levels. 
First, the attachment of hepatocytes is significant in 
primary culture because further survival of the cells is </p>

<p>dependent on the initial attachment status. It is believed 
that cellular adhesion is mediated through the specific 
recognition of ECM molecules by receptors on the cellular 
membrane. The attachment of cells onto natural substrata 
depends on the competitive adsorption of proteins (includ-
ing the proteins that constitute the ECMs) that are added 
to the culture medium or secreted by cells. The bioactive 
compounds in serum have been confirmed to significantly 
affect the cellular behaviors on ECMs such as collagen, 
gelatin, and fibronectin. In addition to the action of cellular 
attachment, FBS also provides essential nutrients for cell 
growth. Therefore, increasing the serum amount within the 
environment may enhance the number of attached cells, 
and a concentration of 10% FBS may induce most of the 
viable cells to anchor to the traditional matrices. 
Second, our results regarding hepatocytes on the hybrid 
matrix and PVLA revealed a reduced need for serum to 
produce cell attachment (Figure 2). Consistent with nature, 
hepatocyte attachment on PVLA is not mediated by integrin, 
and anoikis is further suppressed in the system. 17,29 It has been 
reported that only the hepatocytes with a high maturity level can 
steadily attach to PVLA surfaces because of the large number 
of ASGPRs present on the cellular membrane. The selective 
effect of the polymer is the reason that cell attachment to the </p>













<p>
Figure 7 The storage of glycogen (red) in primary hepatocytes on various surfaces after 1 day in culture. 
Notes: The surfaces include a PVla-coated dish (A), the hybrid matrix (B), a gelatin-coated dish (C), and a collagen-coated dish (D). scale bar: 50 μm. 
Abbreviation: PVla, poly-(N-p-vinylbenzyl-4-O-β-D-galactopyranosyl-D-gluconamide). </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2322 </p>

<p>Meng et al </p>

<p>pure PVLA matrix is limited. Thus, the number of attached cells 
was less than the number of isolated liver cells, which consist 
of hepatocytes of both high and low maturity levels and non-
parenchymal cells. 30 The addition of E-cadherin to the system 
could attract more hepatocytes with an inadequate amount of 
ASGPRs to attach to the matrix because hepatocytes belong 
to the endoderm cell lineage. Thus, the limitation on cellular 
attachment was extended; however, among the hybrid systems 
with different FBS concentration, the largest amount of cell 
attachment was found on the matrix supplied with 1% FBS; 
this amount was still lower than the number of cells attached 
to the gelatin and collagen surfaces with 10% serum. 
Subsequently, the cell number decreased after the incu-
bation period because the isolated mouse hepatocytes lost 
their proliferating capability in vitro unless specific factors 
are added, such as spleen derived growth factor (but not the 
serum), 31 the transgenes of c-myc and transforming growth 
factor-α, 32 or coculture with feeder cells. 33 It has been reported 
that the addition of other bioactive molecules, such as epider-
mal growth factor, insulin, or serum, may delay cell apoptosis 
and promote the cell's functional expression. However, the 
application of serum can possibly introduce inhomogeneity 
and immunogenicity and raise the cost of the culture system. 
Therefore, it remains important to reduce the addition of 
serum during the incubation of primary hepatocytes after 
attachment. In this study, the PVLA surface could tightly 
immobilize the isolated hepatocytes after cell capture. The 
cadherin-mediated cellular adhesion on the coimmobilized 
matrix had the capability to enhance cell maintenance in the 
culture system without causing cell detachment and resulted in 
the morphological differences among the galactose-carrying 
matrices. Finally, after 1 week in culture or longer, the number 
of residual hepatocytes declined to a similar cellular density 
with scarcely any hepatic markers on each combination of 
substratum and FBS concentration (Figure 4). Therefore, the 
hybrid substratum exhibited an excellent capacity to maintain 
the cell number and low serum dependency as well. 
In the prolonged period of culture, the cells spread on 
gelatin-coated dishes gradually lost their abilities for hepatic 
expression at both the protein (Figure 3) and gene levels 
(Figure 5), whereas the hybrid system and PVLA matrix 
significantly promoted liver functionality. The preserva-
tion period of marker expression also supported the role of 
PVLA in forming aggregates and maintaining the hepatic 
functionality of cells. Meanwhile, the E-cadherin in the 
matrix helped to maintain the cells in a monolayer morphol-
ogy, which kept the cells in a homogeneous environment. 
Therefore, it was demonstrated that the cellular interactions 
inside the aggregates in both multilayers and monolayers, </p>

<p>which were promoted by PVLA and EFC, may bestow a 
remarkable regulating effect on the marker expression of 
hepatocytes. 34,35 Finally, the interaction between galactose 
and ASGPRs possibly ensured that hepatocytes with a high 
maturity level remained on the dish surface and functional 
expression was highly preserved (Figure 7). 
We also demonstrated that 1% may be the optimal FBS 
concentration to preserve protein secretion in hepatocyte 
culture on a hybrid matrix; the results from this combination 
were better than those for the general matrix consisting of a 
gelatin-coated culture dish (Figure 6). The highest expression 
level observed in the hybrid system with a small quantity of 
FBS in the medium was speculated to be the result of the 
initiating and nourishing effect of serum in a very low con-
centration. The ability of the hybrid system to maintain the 
hepatocytes under low-serum or serum-free conditions allows 
the elimination of the negative effects of animal products 
in clinical applications and establishment of a completely 
defined culture system for hepatocytes. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The coimmobilized matrix combined the advantages of 
PVLA for maintaining hepatic function and of EFC for 
enhancing cellular viability with a low requirement for FBS 
in vitro. For mouse primary hepatocytes, it provided the ideal 
culture conditions, which are able to support cell prolifera-
tion and differentiation and further prevent interference and 
infection of biological products. The hybrid system may be 
further applied in the induction of stem cells to hepatocytes 
and has the advantages of promoting the affinity of hepatic 
cells and allowing low dependency on serum. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by Grants-in-aid for Scientific 
Research from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, 
Science and Technology of Japan, Tsinghua University 
Initiative Scientific Research Program (20121087982), the 
National Basic Research Program of China (973 Program, 
2011CB606205) and China Postdoctoral Science Foundation 
(2013M540090). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>



</text></tei>