<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4210416" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. [Purpose] The aim of this study was to investigate the steady state of oxygen uptake (VO 2 ) at several 
standing up frequencies to clarify whether workload in the sit-to-stand exercise (STSE) is greater than the anaerobic 
threshold (AT). [Subjects] Ten healthy young subjects performed the STSE. [Methods] In the STSE, subjects stood 
up and sat down without using their arms to push-off from the chair at standing up frequencies of 6, 12, 18, 24, 
30, and 36 times per minutes. Subjects exercised for 5 minutes at each frequency with 5 minutes of rest between 
each consecutive frequency trial. The steady state of VO 2 was evaluated by the difference in the VO 2 between the 
3rd and 5th min at each frequency. The correlation between the VO 2 of the STSE and the standing up frequency 
was analyzed. [Results] At standing up frequencies greater than 24 times/min, the steady state of VO 2 could not 
be confirmed. The relationship between the standing up frequency (at less than 24 times/min) and VO 2 was strong 
(r=0.94). [Conclusion] The STSE may be a potentially useful test for determining AT and predicting the physical 
capacity of patients. 
Physical capacity is evaluated to assess the prognosis of 
cardiac patients, and to help determine the exercise inten-
sity for training in cardiac rehabilitation and for lifestyle 
related disease management 1, 2) . Physical capacity, such as 
maximal oxygen uptake (VO 2 max) and anaerobic thresh-
old (AT), is measured by cardiopulmonary exercise testing 
(CPX) using a cycle ergometer, and treadmill, or field tests 
such as the incremental shuttle walking test (ISWT) 2-5) . 
Laboratory assessment, such as CPX, is not widely avail-
able and is expensive. Furthermore, it may not be suitable 
for patients who cannot pedal or walk. Although the ISWT, 
which is a simple test and easily conducted, is often em-
ployed in clinical practice, it requires a large space and can-
not be conducted with patients who cannot walk safely 4, 5) . 
On the other hand, the sit-to-stand exercise (STSE) which 
is part of an individual's activity of daily living, and uses 
the repetitive motion of standing-up and siting down on a 
chair 6, 7) . The STSE, which requires only a chair and small 
space, can be performed by a large number of patients, and </p>

<p>the exercise load intensity can be easily adjusted by chang-
ing the standing up frequency 6, 7) . Although the STSE has 
been recommended as an estimate of leg muscular power by 
many previous studies, there are few studies that have eval-
uated the subjects' physical capacity during the STSE 6-9) . 
Kamimura 6) examined the relationship between standing 
up frequency and physiological workload, and indicated 
that oxygen uptake (VO 2 ) and heart rate increase linearly as 
the standing up frequency increases. Moreover, Kamimu-
ra 6) examined the relationship between VO 2 of STSE and 
the AT determined using a cycle ergometer, and estimated 
that the work rate at the standing up frequency of 30 times/ 
minute was greater than the AT, and at 24 times/min less 
than the AT. However, there has been no study has investi-
gated the relationship between the AT estimated by STSE 
and standing up frequency directly. 
The purpose of this study was to confirm the steady state 
of VO 2 at several standing up frequencies to clarify whether 
the STSE workload is greater than the AT. Additionally, this 
study investigated the relationship between physiological 
workload and the standing up frequencies. It is necessary to 
clarify the STSE physiological workload in order to develop 
the STSE as a method of measurement of physical capacity. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>An appropriate sample size was estimated based on 
the finding that the standing up speed is a predictor of the 
oxygen uptake 6, 7) . Assuming a standardized effect size for </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 
26: 1631-1633, 2014 </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Keisuke Nakamura (E-mail: 
keipons55@yahoo.co.jp) </p>

<p>©2014 The Society of Physical Therapy Science. Published by IPEC Inc. </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Cre-</p>

<p>ative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-</p>

<p>nd) License &lt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/&gt;. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 26, No. 10, 2014 </p>

<p>
Pearson's correlation of 0.80, to achieve a statistical power 
of 80% at an α level of 0.05 (two-tailed), we estimated that 
about 9 subjects were needed 10) . Therefore, a total of ten 
subjects were recruited for this study. The selection criteria 
were as follows: 1) 20-29 years old, 2) no history of bone, 
joint disease or cardiorespiratory disease that have affected 
the exercise, and 3) voluntarily gave consent to take par-
ticipation in the research. This research was conducted with 
the approval of the Shinshu University School of Medicine 
Ethics Committee and Matsumoto City Hospital Ethics 
Committee. All subjects gave their written consent to par-
ticipation in this study. 
The breath-by-breath gas analyzer used in this study was 
the AT1100 by ANIMA (Tokyo, Japan). The gas analyzer 
was carefully calibrated before the start of measurement. 
The height of the chair used for the STSE was adjusted 
to the level of the upper end of the fibula head. Subjects 
were asked to cross their arms in front of their chest during 
exercise to prevent trick motion by the arm. The feet were 
placed in a comfortable position and set apart at shoulder 
breadth. Accordingly, subjects had to touch each target in 
the upright position and sitting position in order to define 
the STSE motion. The standing up frequencies of the STSE 
were set at 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, and 36 times per minute, and 
subjects exercised for 5 minutes at each frequency with 5 
minutes of rest between each consecutive frequency trial. 
The frequency of standing up was controlled by audio sig-
nals given by a metronome. The criteria for the suspension 
of the test were as follows: 1) when it corresponded to gen-
eral discontinuance criteria for exercise tests 11) ; 2) when a 
heart rate reached 80% of the predicted maximum HR, or 3) 
if subjects missed the timing given by the audio signals for 
three times in a row 6) . When the steady state of VO 2 could 
not be confirmed after five minutes, the test was terminated. 
The steady state of VO 2 was evaluated by the difference in 
the VO 2 between the 3rd and 5th min (VO 2 5th − VO 2 3rd 
≤ 0) 12) . 
The measurement items were VO 2 , heart rate (HR), 
systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pres-
sure (DBP), and the Borg scale of rate of perceived exer-
tion (RPE) and fatigue of the leg. During testing, VO 2 , and 
HR were continuously measured. Respiratory gases were 
measured on a breath-by-breath basis. The breath-by-breath 
expired gas data were converted into time series data. The 
data sets were calculated using the gas analysis software of 
the AT1100, in which the variable moving average was per-
formed. The nine-point moving average of data was applied 
to the calculation for the respiratory gas parameters. The 
mean values of VO 2 and HR during the 30 seconds before 
the end of each standing up frequency were calculated. The 
rate of increase in HR at each standing up frequency to HR 
at rest (ΔHR) was calculated. After the exercise, BP and the 
Borg scale were measured. The temperature in the exercise 
room was maintained at between 21 °C and 24 °C. 
Statistical analysis was performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">11.0</rs> J for 
Windows software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) .The 
correlation between the standing up frequency and VO 2 of 
the STSE was analyzed using Pearson's product-moment 
correlation coefficient. Simple linear regression analysis </p>

<p>was used to determine the relationship of the standing up 
frequency to VO 2 . Significance was accepted for values of 
p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Seven males and three females participated in this study. 
Their average age was 22.3±2.2 (yr), their average height 
was 169.6±9.8 (cm), their average weight was 58.1±8.1 (kg), 
and the average height of chair was 43.5±1.8 (cm) (Table 1). 
The reason for having to termination of the STSE was an 
inability to confirm the steady state of VO 2 . There were no 
subjects who corresponded to the criteria for the premature 
suspension of the test at standing up frequencies up to 18 
times/min. However, the steady state of VO 2 could not be 
confirmed for some subjects at 3 frequencies as follows: at 
24 times/min (2 subjects out of 10), 30 times/min (6 subjects 
out of remaining 8), 36 times/min (2 subjects out of remain-
ing 2). Therefore, the eight subjects who had completed at 
least 24 times/min were included in the analysis. The rela-
tionship between the standing up frequency and VO 2 was 
strong (r=0.94, p&lt;0.05). It was represented by the regres-
sion equation (n=8): VO 2 (ml/min/kg) = 0.40 ×standing up 
frequency (times/min) + 5.23 (R 2 =0.88). The data revealed 
that as the frequency of standing up increased, each subject 
demonstrated a gradual increase in VO 2 , ΔHR, SBP, and 
Borg Scale (Table 2). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Because there weren't any subjects who corresponded 
to the discontinuance criteria of reaching 80% of predicted 
HR maximum, and Borg Scale of RPE and fatigue of the 
leg after exercise indicated moderate intensity, this protocol 
was considered to be of a safe physical workload. 
We demonstrated that the STSE workload at standing up 
frequencies from 24 times/min to 36 times/min was above 
the AT. In general, a steady state of VO 2 cannot be reached 
at the workloads above the AT 11) . Therefore, in our study, 
the steady state of VO 2 could not be verified at the work-
loads during standing up frequencies from 24 times/min to 
36 times/min. Kamimura 6) estimated that the standing up 
frequency of a work load, equal to the AT determined by 
cycle ergometer, was within the range from 24 times/min 
to 30 times/min, and the results of our study lend support 
to Kamimura's report 6) . This may be related to the resem-
blance of the exercise pattern, since both STSE and cycle 
ergometers used similar lower limb muscles and rhythmic </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of all subjects (n=10) </p>

<p>Mean±SD </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
22.3±2.2 
Height (cm) 
169.6±9.8 
Weight (kg) 
58.1±8.1 
Sitting height (cm) 
89.5±3.1 
Height of chair (cm) 
43.5±1.8 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
22.5±4.1 </p>



<p>motion 13-15) . 
This study demonstrated the relationship between VO 2 
and standing up frequency was strong, and VO 2 increased 
linearly with increase in standing up frequency. It is possi-
ble that the total muscle mass involved in the STSE increas-
es as the speed of standing up also increases, and a response 
from the cardiovascular-respiratory system is elicited by the 
increase in the total muscle mass 13) . However, Shiomi 7) in-
dicated VO 2 increases in a logarithmically function with in-
crease in standing up frequency. The difference between the 
two study methods is the setting of the height of the chair. 
In Shiomi's report 7) , the height of the chair was set at just 
41 cm, which is lower than that used in our study. A lower 
height of chair requires greater muscle activities in the legs, 
and causes greater fatigue in the leg muscles 14) . This fatigue 
may cause an inability to elicit a greater response from the 
cardiovascular-respiratory system. Thus, the setting height 
of the chair is important for a linear increase in VO 2 , and 
the setting in our study appears to be adequate. 
The incremental increases in VO 2 and other physiologi-
cal indexes confirm that the STSE test produces a gradual 
physiological response to exercise of increasing intensity, 
and these have been needed to determine the AT and es-
timate some sort of physical capacity 4, 5) . With regards to 
the ISWT, a strong relationship between walking distance 
(measured up to ability to maintain walking speed) and 
VO 2 max has been reported, and therefore, VO 2 max can be 
used to predict walking distance 4, 5) . In the STSE, elderly 
people may not be able to maintain the required speed when 
the activity at high frequencies is faster (e.g. greater than 
24 times/min). Similar to the ISWT, the STSE may also 
be a potentially useful measurement for the prediction of 
physical capacity such as VO 2 max from the standing up 
frequency. 
The results of our present study suggest workload (VO 2 , 
HR), adjusted by changing the standing up frequency, in the 
STSE can exceed the AT, but we did not determine whether 
the AT can be determined from the STSE directly, and this 
will need to be verified in future studies. Furthermore, the 
validity and reliability of the AT determined by the STSE 
will need to be investigated. 
Also, because knee pain may be provoked when elderly 
people conduct the STSE, the height of the chair will need 
further consideration. Moreover, using the arms to push off 
when standing up may decrease the knee pain, and the rela-
tionship between the physiological workload and standing 
speed with arm push-off will have to be examined. </p>

<p>In conclusion, the STSE is a simple test which varies 
only the frequency of standing up. We propose that the 
STSE could be conducted with a relatively low risk for 
healthy young adults. The physiological workload when the 
standing up frequency is greater than 24 times/min is great-
er than the AT. Therefore, the STSE may be a potentially 
useful test for determining AT and predicting the physical 
capacity of patients who are unable to perform the tasks 
used in other methods of evaluation. </p>



</text></tei>