<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4063356" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Choroidal neovascularization (CNV) is a major cause 
of severe central vision loss in patients with exudative, 
age-related macular degeneration (AMD) [1]. In patients 
with exudative AMD, choroidal blood vessels grow through 
Bruch's membrane into the subretinal space. This is followed 
by leakage and accumulation of serum or blood beneath the 
RPE, leading to retinal damage and rapid loss of vision [2]. </p>

<p>Human ocular neovascularization may be caused or 
facilitated by altered expression of integrins [3,4]. Integrins 
are heterodimeric, cell surface receptors found in nearly all 
metazoan cell types. These receptors are composed of non-
covalently linked α-and β-subunits [5,6]. In mammals, 18 
α-subunits and eight β-subunits have been identified [7]. The 
subunit composition of the heterodimer determines binding 
to specific ligands in the extracellular matrix (ECM). For 
example, α5β1 and αvβ3 integrins bind to their ligands fibro-
nectin (FN) and vitronectin (VN), respectively, which are 
strongly expressed around developing vasculature [5,8,9]. 
Therefore, α5β1 and αvβ3 integrins have been investigated 
the most as potential regulators of angiogenesis [10]. Integrin </p>

<p>αvβ3 was the first integrin associated with angiogenesis [11], 
and deletion of the α5 gene is embryonically lethal with 
vascular and cardiac defects [12]. These integrin-mediated 
interactions are also required for pathological processes such 
as angiogenesis [13], tumor survival, and metastasis [14]. </p>

<p>Laser irradiation encircling the optic nerve is widely used 
for inducing CNV in rodent [15] and primate [16] models of 
AMD. During experimental choroidal neovascularization, the 
binding of inhibitors to integrins α5 and αv is antiangiogenic. 
For example, systemic administration of α5β1 integrin antag-
onist causes CNV suppression and regression [17]. An αvβ3 
specific antagonist also inhibits laser-induced CNV in mice 
[18]. However, the expression of integrin α5 and αv subunits 
with time is limited in these models, and the localization of 
integrin ligands such as FN and VN has not been reported. 
Thus, the purposes of the present study in the laser-induced 
CNV model were as follows: 1) to identify integrin α chain-
positive cells and their ligands FN and VN and 2) to measure 
the binding of integrins to their ligand ECMs. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Animals: Twenty adult male Brown Norway rats (8-9 weeks-
old) were obtained from Charles River Laboratories (Yoko-
hama, Japan) and maintained under a 12 h:12 h light-dark </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:864-871 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/864&gt; 
Purpose: Inhibitors binding to integrins α5 and αv are antiangiogenic in models of choroidal neovascularization (CNV). 
However, a comprehensive understanding of the accumulation of integrin α isoform-positive cells, their ligands, and 
associations is limited. The purpose of the present study was to examine the localization of integrin α chain-positive 
cells and their extracellular matrix (ECM) ligands in the RPE/choroid after laser injury. 
Methods: CNV, observed with fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-labeled isolectin, was produced in Brown Norway 
rats with a 532 nm green laser. Localization of α5 and αv integrins and their ligands was performed with immunohisto-
chemistry in consecutive cryosections. To test the binding specificity between the integrin α chains and ECM ligands, 
an in vitro cell adhesion assay was performed using retinal endothelial cells and specific antibodies. 
Results: Angiogenesis was observed on day 7 after laser injury in choroidal flat mounts and cryosections. The number of 
integrin α5-and αv-positive cells markedly increased at day 3 and then gradually decreased, but was still elevated on day 
14. One day after laser treatment, α integrin ligands fibronectin (FN) and vitronectin (VN) were markedly increased, and 
localized closely to integrins in the laser-injured regions. FN decreased on day 7, but was still retained until 14 days. In 
contrast, VN disappeared. Cell adhesion assays showed specific association of integrin α5 to FN, and integrin αv to VN. 
Conclusions: Laser-induced choroidal injury increased FN and VN, followed by accumulation of integrin α5-and 
αv-positive cells. The interaction between integrin α chain-positive cells and their specific ligands FN and VN may be 
important steps leading to CNV. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:864-871 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/864&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>cycle. Senju follows the international IACUC animal research 
laws, policies and guidelines, and all experimental animals 
were handled in accordance with the Association for Research 
in Vision and Ophthalmology (ARVO) Statement for the Use 
of Animals in Ophthalmic and Vision Research and the NIH 
Guiding Principles in the Care and Use of Animals (DHEW 
Publication, NIH 80-23). </p>

<p>Laser-induced choroidal neovascularization model: Rats 
were anesthetized with a 1 ml/kg bodyweight intraperitoneal 
injection of a mixture containing ketamine hydrochloride 
(50 mg/ml; Daiichi Sankyo, Tokyo, Japan) and xylazine 
hydrochloride (10 mg/ml; Bayer, Tokyo, Japan). Pupils were 
dilated with topical tropicamide/phenylephrine (Midrin-P, 
Santen Pharmaceutical, Osaka, Japan). Visualization of the 
fundus was aided by placing a cover glass on the eye over 
hydroxyethylcellulose. A slit-lamp biomicroscope (NIDEK, 
Aichi, Japan) was used to encircle the optic nerve on the retina 
with six to seven laser spots (100 µm each, 532 nm, 150 mW, 
0.1 s). Breakage of Bruch's membrane was confirmed by 
bubble formation and used as an end point for treatment. 
Animals with severe hemorrhages in the retina were excluded 
from the study. Two rat eyes in the experimental group were 
choroidal flatmounted and subjected to immunohistochem-
istry as described below. </p>

<p>Choroidal flatmounts: After euthanasia on day 1, 3, 7, or 14 
following laser photocoagulation, the eyes were enucleated 
and prefixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (Nacalai tesque, 
Kyoto, Japan) for 30 min. Retina-RPE-choroid complexes 
were microsurgically isolated from the prefixed eyes and 
further fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 1 h. The retina </p>

<p>was removed from RPE-choroid complexes. The RPE-choroid 
complexes were then washed with PBS (1X; 137 mM NaCl, 
2.7 mM KCl, 8.1 mM Na 2 HPO 4 , 1.5 mM KH 2 PO 4 :Nacalai 
tesque) and incubated for 30 min with PBS blocking buffer 
containing 0.5% Triton X-100 (GE Healthcare UK, Bucking-
hamshire, UK) and 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA; Sigma-
Aldrich, St. Louis, MO). To visualize neovascularization, 
RPE-choroid complexes were incubated overnight at 4 °C 
with 0.01% fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-conjugated 
isolectin B4 derived from Griffonia (Bandeiraea) simplici-
folia agglutinin (Vector Laboratories, Peterborough, UK) 
diluted with PBS containing 0.5% Triton X-100. After the 
RPE-choroid complexes were washed with PBS and sealed 
with VECTASHIELD (Vector Laboratories), CNV was 
observed with a fluorescence microscope (IX71; Olympus, 
Tokyo, Japan). Note that FITC-labeled isolectin binds to 
microglial cells and macrophages as well as endothelial 
vascular cells [19]. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry for integrins and extracellular matrix: 
Enucleated eyes in embedding medium (Tissue-Tek OCT 
Compound; Sakura Finetek, Torrance, CA) were flash-frozen 
with liquid nitrogen. Serial sections (10 μm) were cut on a 
cryostat at −20 °C and collected with adhesive film (Cryofilm 
type 2C(9); SECTION-LAB, Hiroshima, Japan). The sections 
were fixed with 75% ethanol at −20 °C for 30 min, washed 
three times with Tris-Buffer Saline (TBS; 2 mM Tris, 50 
mM NaCl, pH7.4; BioRad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) for 
5 min each and dried for 30 min at room temperature. Dried 
sections were incubated in PBS blocking buffer containing 
0.3% Triton X-100 and 10% goat serum (Dako, Glostrup, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Representative flatmount 
images of macrophages and microg-
lial and endothelial cells labeled 
with green fluorescent antibody for 
isolectin in normal and laser-treated 
rat RPE-choroid preparations. The 
red arrow indicates macrophages 
and microglial and endothelial 
cells; the yellow arrows indicate 
new tubular structures. Scale bar = 
200 μm. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:864-871 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/864&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>Denmark) for 30 min and incubated overnight at 4 °C with 
primary antibody diluted with Can Get Signal Solution B 
(NKB-601, TOYOBO, Osaka, Japan) containing 10% goat 
serum. Dilution of the primary antibodies was as follows: 
rabbit anti-integrin α5 (1:50; H-104, Santa Cruz, Dallas, 
TX), rabbit anti-integrin αv (1:50; Q-20-R, Santa Cruz), 
anti-isolectin B4 (1:25; Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, 
CA), rabbit anti-vitronectin (1:50; Santa Cruz), rabbit anti-
laminin (1:50; Santa Cruz), and mouse anti-fibronectin (1:50; 
Santa Cruz). After washing with TBS for 5 min three times, 
the sections were incubated for 1 h with Alexa Fluor 546 
goat anti-rabbit immunoglobulin G (IgG; Life Technologies, 
Carlsbad, CA) or Alexa Fluor 488 goat anti-rabbit IgG (Life 
Technologies) diluted to 1:250 with Can Get Signal Solution 
B containing 10% goat serum. Sections were washed three 
times with TBS containing 0.3% Triton-X 100 and sealed 
with Fluoromount (Diagnostic BioSystems, Pleasanton, CA). 
As a negative control, normal rabbit IgG diluted to 1:3,750 
(Dako) was used in place of the primary antibody. Cellstain 
(DOJINDO, Kumamoto, Japan) diluted to 1:3,000 was used 
for nuclear staining. </p>

<p>Cell adhesion assay: To confirm the selectivity and speci-
ficity of the association between integrins and ECM ligands, 
a cell adhesion assay was performed using primary human </p>

<p>retinal endothelial cells (HRECs; Cell Systems, Kirkland, 
WA). Briefly, 75 μl vitronectin (5 μg/ml; BD, Franklin Lakes, 
NJ) or fibronectin (10 μg/ml, Sigma-Aldrich; concentrations 
showing best adhesion to HRECs) was incubated for 1 h at 
37 °C in 96-well microtiter plates. After excess ECM was 
removed from the wells, the uncoated area in the wells was 
blocked with 1% BSA. HRECs suspended at 10 
5 cells per ml 
in CSC medium (Cell Systems) containing 0.1% BSA were 
incubated for 30 min with antibodies for α5β1 (clone JBS5, 
EMD Millipore, Billerica, MA) or αvβ3 (LM609, Millipore). 
Ten-microliter cell suspensions were inoculated into the 
ECM-coated wells. After incubation for 10 min at 37 °C, the 
cells were fixed with 10% neutral formalin (Nacalai tesque) 
and stained with 0.1% crystal violet solution (Sigma-Aldrich). 
The statistical test and variance is stated in figure legend. 
The stained areas were quantified with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Image-Pro</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Media Cybernetics</rs>, Rockville, MD). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Neovascularization after laser treatment: Immunohisto-
chemistry with FITC-labeled isolectin as a marker for laser-
induced neovascularization in the RPE-choroid showed blood 
vessels in normal, non-laser treated rats (Figure 1, Normal), 
but only a few macrophages and microglial and endothelial </p>

<p>Figure 2. Fluorescence microscopy with red fluorescent antibody for integrin α5 in normal and laser-treated rat RPE-choroid. The red arrows 
show integrin α5 expression near normal blood vessels. The yellow arrows show positive red antibody binding for integrin α5 between the 
subretinal and suprachoroidal spaces with ruptured Bruch's membranes after laser treatment. The white arrow indicates isolectin binding in 
green macrophages and microglial and endothelial cells and near new tubular structures (green arrows). The blue arrows show colocalization 
of red integrin α5 with green macrophages and microglial and endothelial cells. Blue 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) nuclear stain 
highlights the disruption and wound healing in the inner and outer nuclear layers. Scale bar = 100 μm. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:864-871 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/864&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>cells stained 1 day after laser injury (day 1). Staining on day 
3 indicated early accumulation of mainly macrophages and 
microglial cells with some endothelial cells (red arrow). On 
days 7 and 14, macrophages and microglial cells decreased, 
and tubular structures were observed (Figure 1, yellow 
arrows), indicating active retinal neovascularization in this 
rat model. </p>

<p>Colocalization of integrin α5 and αv subunits with tubule 
formation: Fluorescence microscopy with red fluorescent 
labeling for the α5 subunit of integrin showed weak reactivity 
near blood vessels throughout the RPE-choroid of normal rats 
(Figure 2, red arrows). On day 1 after laser treatment, binding 
of the antibody for integrin α5 slightly increased; and on day 
3, integrin α5 markedly increased between the subretinal 
and suprachoroidal spaces with ruptured Bruch's membranes 
(row 1, yellow arrows). Integrin α5 remained visible for 14 
days. Macrophages and microglial and endothelial cells also 
accumulated around the laser spots on day 3 (row 2, white 
arrow), and angiogenic tubules (green arrows) were observed 
on days 7 and 14. Integrin α5 colocalized with macrophages 
and microglial and endothelial cells (row 3, blue arrows) on 
day 3 and endothelial cells on days 7 and 14. Another subunit 
of integrin, αv, was also observed in normal blood vessels and 
the RPE (Figure 3, red and orange arrows). The appearance </p>

<p>and accumulation of integrin αv after laser treatment (Figure 
3) were similar to those described for integrin α5. Nega-
tive controls using IgG in place of primary antibodies did 
not show significant binding (data not shown). Blue nuclear 
staining (row 4, Figure 2 and Figure 3) showed overall retinal 
disruption on day 1 followed by progressive healing over 
14 days, suggesting increased α5 and αv integrin subunit-
positive cells during retinal neovascularization. </p>

<p>Extracellular matrix components precede accumulation of 
integrin-positive cells: We found that FN and VN weakly 
localized around blood vessel in normal rats (Figure 4, red 
arrows) but markedly increased between the subretinal space 
and sclera with ruptured Bruch's membranes on day 1 after 
laser treatment (Figure 4, orange arrows). FN and VN anti-
body binding on day 3 was somewhat decreased but remained 
(yellow and blue arrows). On day 7 after laser injury, FN 
further decreased, but closely localized with tube-like struc-
tures (Figure 4, green arrows). In contrast, VN almost disap-
peared. Day 14 was similar in appearance to day 7. Binding 
of antibody for laminin, another extracellular matrix protein 
that binds to integrin [6], did not change after laser treatment 
(data not shown). These data suggested that specific binding 
ligands, such as FN and VN, may precede and possibly </p>

<p>Figure 3. Fluorescence microscopy with red fluorescent antibody for integrin αv in rat RPE-choroid. Non-treated retinas show positive 
antibody binding for integrin αv around the normal vessels (red arrows) and in the RPE (orange arrows). The yellow arrows show positive 
red antibody binding for integrin αv between the subretinal and suprachoroidal spaces after laser treatment. The white arrow indicates 
isolectin binding in green macrophages and microglial and endothelial cells and near the new tubular structures (green arrows). The blue 
arrows show colocalization of red integrin αv with green macrophages and microglial and endothelial cells. Scale bar = 100 μm. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:864-871 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/864&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>Figure 4. Fluorescence microscopy in normal and laser-treated rat RPE-choroid, triple labeled red for fibronectin (FN, row 2) and vitronectin 
(VN; row 4), green for isolectin, and blue for nuclear staining. The red arrows indicate normal blood vessels. The orange arrows indicate 
the antibody binding for FN and VN between the subretinal space and sclera after laser treatment. The yellow and blue arrows indicate the 
moderate decrease in FN and disappearance in VN, respectively; the green arrows show FN localization around forming tubules. Scale bar 
= 100 μm. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Cell adhesion assay of 
primary human retinal endothelial 
cells. Adherence of human retinal 
endothelial cells to (A) fibronectin 
(FN) and (B) vitronectin (VN)-
coated plates were conducted in 
the absence (PBS) and presence 
of antibodies to specific integrin 
subunit α5β1 and αvβ3. Data are 
means ± standard deviation (SD; 
n = 3). *p&lt;0.01 relative to PBS 
(Dunnett's test). </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:864-871 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/864&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>influence the accumulation of integrin α5-and αv-positive 
cells during retinal neovascularization. </p>

<p>Fibronectin and vitronectin matrix proteins bind to specific 
integrin subunits: An in vitro cell adherence-inhibition assay 
using HRECs showed that the antibody for integrin α5β1 
subunit significantly (p&lt;0.01) inhibits adhesion of HRECs 
onto FN-coated plates (Figure 5A). An integrin αvβ3 anti-
body had no effect. Conversely, the integrin αvβ3 antibody 
significantly inhibited adhesion of cells onto VN-coated 
plates, while the integrin α5β1 antibody had no effect (Figure 
5B). These data indicated that integrin α5 and αv bind specifi-
cally to FN and VN, respectively. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The major finding of the present studies was the sequence of 
molecular events that occur during the onset and development 
of neovascularization in the laser-induced CNV model in rats 
(Table 1). The first major event observed 1 day after laser 
treatment was the accumulation of FN and VN between the 
subretinal space and sclera around the injured areas (Figure 
4). mRNA specific for FN is transiently increased by the 
terminal complement proteins C5b-8 and C5b-9 in glomer-
ular mesangial cells [20]. VN also increases in complement-
stimulated human RPE cells [21]. The end product of comple-
ment activation, membrane attack complex (MAC), increases 
as early as 1 h after laser treatment [22]. Thus, complement 
activation could be a mechanism for the early expression of 
FN and VN in our laser model. </p>

<p>On day 3, binding of antibodies for integrins α5 and αv 
and for FITC-labeled isolectin (for macrophages and microg-
lial, perivascular, and endothelial cells) increased markedly 
(Table 1, Figure 1, Figure 2, Figure 3, and Figure 4). Increased 
chemokine, (C-C motif) ligand 2 (CCL2), causes migration 
and accumulation of microglia and macrophages for uptake 
of cell debris [22,23]. mRNA for CCL2 peaks at 12 h within 
laser-injury spots [22]. In addition, mRNA for vascular 
endothelial growth factor (VEGF) increases 2 days after laser </p>

<p>treatment [22], and VEGF is secreted from macrophages and 
microglial and RPE cells [24]. Specific adherence of retinal 
endothelial cells, where integrins α5 and αv were expressed 
(confirmed with western blotting, data not shown), to FN and 
VN through integrin α5 and αv was also observed (Figure 
5). These data suggest that under the influence of cytokines, 
such as CCL2 and VEGF, integrin α5-and αv-positive macro-
phages and microglial and endothelial cells migrated between 
the subretinal and suprachoroidal spaces with ruptured 
Bruch's membranes. This is also where FN and VN, the 
specific ligands for integrins α5 and αv, accumulated. These 
data suggest that the increased FN and VN in laser injury 
may be important for the accumulation of integrin α5-and 
αv-positive cells. This was followed by uptake of cell debris 
by the macrophages and microglia and neovascularization by 
the endothelial cells. </p>

<p>On day 7, FN was retained, tube-like structures formed, 
and VN disappeared (Table 1). These data suggest that VN 
was important for the onset of neovascularization, while FN 
was needed for onset and further vessel development during 
neovascularization. Interestingly, laminin, another extracel-
lular matrix protein found in the RPE basement membrane 
[25], did not increase after laser injury. These specific 
changes in ECM localization suggest that the association 
between integrin subunits and their specific ligands may be 
important for VEGF-induced proliferation and differentiation 
of endothelial progenitor cells for subsequent CNV. </p>

<p>Antagonists targeting single integrin subunits inhibit 
CNV [17,18,26,27]. However, our current data suggested that 
αv and α5 integrins are important for neovascularization. 
Blocking of multiple integrins thus may be useful for the 
therapy for AMD. Only limited data are available concerning 
the efficacy of using antagonists to block multiple integrin 
subunits [28]. Antagonism of multiple integrin subunits may 
also cause stronger side effects; further experiments testing 
multiple integrin antagonists are needed. </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of changeS in inTegrinS and Their ligand ecmS during neovaScularizaTion. </p>

<p>Post laser treatment, days 
Staining intensity* </p>

<p>1 
3 
7 
14 </p>

<p>Fibronectin 
+++ 
++ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Vitronectin 
+++ 
++ 
-/+ 
-/+ </p>

<p>α5 Integrin 
-/+ 
+++ 
++ 
+ </p>

<p>αv Integrin 
-/+ 
+++ 
++ 
+ </p>

<p>Neovascularization 
-
-/+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>* (-)=none, (-/+)=minimal, (+)=mild, (++)=moderate, (+++)=strong. </p>

<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:864-871 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/864&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>



<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>Authors' Disclosure Statement: These studies were 
completely funded by Senju Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. Dr. 
Shearer is a paid consultant for Senju Pharmaceutical Co., 
Ltd., a company that may have a commercial interest in the 
results of this research and technology. Drs. Azuma and 
Hirata are employees of Senju Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. These 
potential conflicts of interest were reviewed, and manage-
ment plans approved by the OHSU Conflict of Interest in 
Research Committee were implemented. </p>



<p>Molecular Vision 2014; 20:864-871 &lt;http://www.molvis.org/molvis/v20/864&gt; </p>

<p>© 2014 Molecular Vision </p>





<p>Articles are provided courtesy of Emory University and the Zhongshan Ophthalmic Center, Sun Yat-sen University, P.R. China. 
The print version of this article was created on 19 June 2014. This reflects all typographical corrections and errata to the article 
through that date. Details of any changes may be found in the online version of the article. </p>

</text></tei>