<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4093164" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Hanwoo (Korean Native Cattle; Bos taurus coreanae) 
had been used for transportation as well as farming for a 
long time in South Korea. It has been about 30 years since 
Hanwoo was improved in earnest for meat yield. 
Appearance traits such as body type and hair color were 
used for selecting Hanwoo to determine the breed before 
that time. In 1910, the predecessor agency of the National </p>

<p>Institute of Animal Science (NIAS) in Rural Development 
Administration (RDA) had established a judging guide 
including standard body type for Hanwoo, and had held 
seedstock fairs for each province every year. In the test 
guide for proven bulls set up in 1924, hair color had been 
defined as light brown in the Hanwoo judging guide of 
1938. The Livestock Protection Act that is a parent law of 
the current Livestock Industry Act (LIA) had been set up in 
1954 to protect the Hanwoo decreased drastically due to the 
Korean War emphasizing more in registration of Hanwoo 
and restriction of slaughtering them. In 1963, LIA had been 
set up to define selection objectives to improve Hanwoo as 
beef cattle, and a National Hanwoo Championship had been 
held in 1969 resulted in selecting 3 proven bulls. The </p>

<p>Asian-Aust. J. Anim. Sci. </p>

<p>Vol. 26, No. 2 : 151-156 February 2013 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5713/ajas.2012.12439 </p>

<p>www.ajas.info </p>

<p>pISSN 1011-2367 eISSN 1976-5517 </p>

<p>National Genetic Evaluation (System) of 
Hanwoo (Korean Native Cattle) </p>

<p>B. Park, T. Choi, S. Kim and S.-H. Oh 
1, * </p>

<p>National Institute of Animal Science, Cheonan, Korea </p>

<p>ABSTRACT: Hanwoo (Also known as Korean native cattle; Bos taurus coreanae) have been used for transportation and farming for a </p>

<p>long time in South Korea. It has been about 30 yrs since Hanwoo improvement began in earnest as beef cattle for meat yield. The 
purpose of this study was to determine the trend of improvement as well as to estimate genetic parameters of the traits being used for 
seedstock selection based on the data collected from the past. Hanwoo proven bulls in South Korea are currently selected through 
performance and progeny tests. National Hanwoo genetic evaluations are implemented with yearling weight (YW), carcass weight 
(CW), eye muscle area (EMA), backfat thickness (BF) and marbling score (MS). Yearling weights and MS are used for selecting young 
bulls, and EMA, BF, and MS are used for selecting proven bulls. One individual per testing room was used for performance tests, and 
five individuals per room for progeny tests. Individuals tested were not allowed to graze pasture, but there was enough space for them to 
move around in the testing room. Feeds including roughages and minerals were fed ad libitum, and concentrates were provided at the 
rate of about 1.8% of individual weight. Overall means of the traits were 352.838.56 kg, 335.0944.61 kg, 77.858.838 cm 
2 , 8.63.7 </p>

<p>mm and 3.2931.648 for YW, CW, EMA, BF and MS. Heritabilities estimated in this study were 0.30, 0.30, 0.42, 0.50 and 0.63 in YW, 
CW, EMA, BF and MS, respectively, which are similar to results from previous research. Yearling weight was 315.54 kg in 1998, and 
had increased to 355.06 kg in 2011, resulting in about 40 kg of improvement over 13 yrs. YW and CW have improved remarkably over 
the past 15 yrs. Breeding values between 1996 and 2000 decreased or did not change much, but have moved in a desirable direction 
since 2001. These improvements correspond with the substantial increase in use of animal models since the late 1990s in Korea. 
Hanwoo testing programs have practically contributed to the improvement in aspects of quality and quantity. In sum, the current 
selection system is good enough to accommodate circumstances where fewer sires are used on many more cows. Although progeny tests 
take longer and cost more, they seem to be appropriate under the circumstances of the domestic market with its higher requirement for 
better meat quality. Consequently, accumulative data collection, genetic evaluation model development, revision of selection indices, as 
well as cooperation among farms, associations, National Agricultural Cooperative Federation, universities, research institutes, and 
government agencies must be applied to the Hanwoo selection program. All these efforts will assist the domestic market to secure a 
competitive position against imported beef under Free Trade Agreement trade system and will provide farmers with higher profits as 
well as the public with a higher quality of beef. (Key Words: Hanwoo, Genetic, Trend, Parameter) </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author: S.-H. Oh. Tel: +1-336-334-7672, 
Fax: +1-336-334-7288, E-mail: soh@ncat.edu 
1 North Carolina A&amp;T State University, Greensboro, North 
Carolina, USA. </p>

<p>Submitted Aug. 14, 2012; Accepted Oct. 4, 2012; Revised Nov. 5, 2012 </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian-Aust. J. Anim. Sci. 26:151-156 </p>

<p>
Korean Animal Improvement Association (KAIA) had also 
been established, resulting in a surge of animal registration, 
and an Artificial Insemination (AI) program began to 
expand at the same time. In 1974, performance tests were 
implemented at the Koryungji test station to improve 
Hanwoo as beef cattle in earnest. A regional Hanwoo 
propagation project started in 1979 with 8 stations 
constructing the foundation of improving Hanwoo cow 
farms nationally, and performance tests were implemented 
at each station in all provinces from 1979. In 1980, a 
seedstock selection program through performance and 
progeny tests was introduced, preserving a pure line 
determined by the decision of the Genetic Improvement 
Committee (a subcommittee on Hanwoo beef cattle), thus 
resulting in the establishment of a Hanwoo improvement 
and development plan in 1982. With the plan, performance 
tests were implemented at both the National Institute of 
Animal Science (NIAS) and the Animal Genetic Resources 
Station (AGRS), and progeny tests were implemented at the 
Hanwoo Improvement Center (HIC). Ten Hanwoo proven 
bulls were selected in 1987 for the first time through the 
performance and progeny tests implemented in the program. 
In 1992, a comprehensive plan for livestock improvement 
was announced to make management efficiency better 
resulting in performance tests being implemented at HIC, 
and progeny tests at NIAS. From 2005, both tests began to 
be implemented at HIC. In 1995, the regional Hanwoo 
propagation project was expanded to 250 stations, and was 
changed to the Hanwoo breeding farm promotion project 
afterwards, and finally, the performance testing program for 
Hanwoo cow-calf operators in 2011. In 2005, the Hanwoo 
breeding farm program was established to enable farmers to 
produce proven bulls by themselves. There are lots of 
Hanwoo improvement programs being implemented 
currently, such as the Hanwoo bull testing program that 
provides semen through selecting proven bulls, a 
performance testing program for Hanwoo cow-calf 
operators to improve the Hanwoo cow, a Hanwoo breeding 
farm project to produce calves to be used for Hanwoo 
proven bulls at small farms, the Elite Hanwoo Cow Grant to 
preserve the genetic resource by supporting elite Hanwoo 
cow rearing, and the Hanwoo MOET control center to 
provide fertilized eggs produced from elite Hanwoo cows. 
The purpose of this study was to describe improvement 
trend and to estimate genetic parameters of the traits being 
used for seedstock selection based on the historical data. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Performance and progeny tests 
Hanwoo proven bulls in South Korea are currently 
selected through performance and progeny tests. </p>

<p>Nationwide, Hanwoo genetic evaluations are implemented 
with yearling weight (YW), eye muscle area (EMA), 
backfat thickness (BF) and marbling score (MS). Yearling 
weights and MS are used for selecting young bulls, and 
EMA, BF, and MS are used for selecting proven bulls. 
Performance tests mean testing calves that are produced by 
scheduled mating both at HIC and Hanwoo breeding farms, 
and that are from 6 to 12 months of age. Performance tests 
include semen and health tests for semen production, and 
evaluation for body type as well as weighing at 6, 9, and 12 
months of age. Performance tests are started in March or 
September each year, and terminated in September of the 
same year, or in March of the following year. After 
performance tests, young bulls are selected through genetic 
evaluations for weights with genetic parameter estimates of 
MS considering relatives, where weighting factors for YW 
and MS are 2:1. Young bulls selected through performance 
tests are marked for progeny tests. Semen collected from 
young bulls is provided to about 40 regional HICs that 
practice scheduled mating, and is inseminated in cows 
whose lineage is known to at least as far back as the 
grandparents. Young bulls selected in March produce semen 
around April to June, and then semen is distributed among 
cows in July or August. Semen of young bulls selected in 
September is distributed for insemination in January or 
February of the following year. About 150 doses per a 
young bull are distributed for insemination. Progeny testing 
individuals at HIC are weighed at 6, 12, 18 and 24 months 
of age, and harvested at 24 months of age to investigate 
carcass traits including CW, EMA, BF and MS. Body types 
are also collected at 12 and 24 months of age. </p>

<p>Test environments 
South Korea is geographically located in a temperate 
climate with four seasons; cold and dry in winter, hot and 
humid in summer, and clear and dry in spring and fall. 
Tested individuals were weaned at 90 d of age, on average. 
One individual was placed per testing room for performance 
tests, and five individuals per room for progeny tests. 
Individuals tested were not allowed to graze pasture, but 
there was enough space (2 m6 m) to move around in the 
testing rooms. 
Nutrient requirements of various production stages are 
shown in Table 2. Corn, wheat bran, soybean meal and salt 
were used for compound feed. Grass hay, wild grass hay, 
grass, whole barley haylage, corn silage, grass silage, 
pelleted rice straw, pelleted grass hay, untreated or 
ammonia-treated rice straw were listed as roughage sources. 
Feeds including roughages and minerals were fed ad 
libitum, and concentrates were provided at a rate of about 
1.8% of individual weights. The nutrient table from the feed 
manufacturer assigned to produce the test feed was used as </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian-Aust. J. Anim. Sci. 26:151-156 </p>



<p>the reference for the nutrient content of the concentrates, 
and the Korean standard feed table (1988) published by 
RDA was used for roughages. </p>

<p>Data 
Data consisted of two sets, including performance and 
progeny testing records from HIC, and performance testing 
records only from livestock research centers in each 
province. The number of animals in each trait by year is 
shown in Table 1. Yearling weights were collected from 
7,863 individuals, including steers. Carcass weights were 
recorded from 4,442 individuals (Table 3). Yearling weights 
were adjusted to weights (W t ) at the termination (t) of tests 
and previous weights (W t-1 ) at the time (t-1) before the 
termination (t). </p>

<p>Adjusted yearling weights 
= (W t -W t-1 )/(t-(t-1))(365-(t-1))+W t-1 </p>

<p>Carcass weight was collected at the end of refrigeration 
for 24 h after harvest. Eye muscle area was measured using 
a dot-grid with cross-sectional slice between the thoracic 
and the 1 
st lumber vertebrae perpendicular to the vertebral 
column, where backfat thickness was also measured. 
Marbling scores were classified with the naked eyes 
following guidelines into 7 levels until 2005, and 9 levels 
after that (Livestock Products Grading Guideline, 2011). </p>

<p>Statistical analyses 
Pedigree information was traced using Hanwoo 
registration records in KAIA as much as possible (54,158 
heads; Table 4). Repeated individuals were corrected or 
deleted using registration and birth records of KAIA 
database. 
The statistical model for YW was as follows. </p>

<p>Y ij = +C i +A j +e ij </p>

<p>where,  is overall mean, C i is the fixed effect of i </p>

<p>th </p>

<p>contemporary group that was defined as combinations of 
year, season, birth place and farm (652 levels), A j is the 
random additive genetic effect of j 
th animal, and e ij is </p>

<p>measurement error. 
The statistical model for carcass traits was as follows. </p>

<p>Y ij = +C i +d of age at harvest+A j +e ij </p>

<p>where,  is overall mean, C i is the fixed effect of i </p>

<p>th </p>

<p>contemporary group that was defined as combinations of 
year, season, testing place and harvest date (327 levels),  is 
the coefficient for linear regression on days of age at 
harvest, A j is the random additive genetic effect of j 
th animal, </p>

<p>and e ij is measurement error. 
Basic statistics were analyzed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.02</rs> (SAS 
institute, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2010</rs>), and genetic parameters were estimated with 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">ASReml</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Gilmour et al.</rs>., <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">1999</rs>). Selection indices for 
performance and progeny tests were as follows, respectively. </p>

<p>Selection index for performance test = 2BYW+BMS </p>

<p>Table 4. Structure of the Hanwoo pedigree </p>

<p>Item 
No. of animals </p>

<p>Animals in pedigree 
54,158 (100%) 
Sires 
1,152 (2.13%) 
Dams 
27,389 (50.6%) 
Animals with data 
9,660 (100%) 
One parent unknown 
21 (0.22%) 
Both parents unknown 
5 (0.05%) 
Both parents known 
9,634 (99.73%) </p>

<p>Table 1. Number of animals in each trait by year 
Year 
YW 
CW 
EMA 
BF 
MS9 
1998 
-
118 
118 
118 
-
1999 
-
366 
364 
355 
-
2000 
409 
351 
351 
349 
-
2001 
475 
282 
282 
281 
-
2002 
353 
246 
246 
245 
-
2003 
476 
309 
309 
307 
-
2004 
640 
289 
288 
289 
-
2005 
700 
288 
288 
288 
288 
2006 
745 
344 
343 
344 
344 
2007 
852 
356 
356 
356 
356 
2008 
884 
379 
379 
379 
379 
2009 
854 
383 
383 
383 
383 
2010 
831 
376 
376 
376 
376 
2011 
380 
355 
355 
355 
355 
2012 
264 
-
-
-
-</p>

<p>YW = Yearling weight; CW = Carcass weight; EMA = Eye muscle area; 
BF = Backfat thickness; MS9 = Marbling score with 9 levels. </p>

<p>Table 3. Number of records and average of each trait </p>

<p>Trait 
No. of 
record 
MeanSD 
Min 
Max </p>

<p>Yearling weight (kg) 7,863 352.838.56 
184.1 527.9 
Carcass weight (kg) 4,442 335.144.61 
183.0 488.0 
EMA (cm 
2 ) 
4,439 
77.858.838 
50.0 121.0 
Backfat (mm) 
4,428 
8.6393.678 
2.0 
35.0 
MS9 
2,481 
3.2931.648 
1 
9 </p>

<p>* EMA = Eye muscle area; MS9 = Marbling score with 9 levels. 
** SD = Standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 2. Nutrient requirements of various production stages </p>

<p>CP (%) 
TDN (%) </p>

<p>Performance tests (180 d) 
and progeny tests (first 180 d) </p>

<p>15 
71 </p>

<p>Progeny tests (mid 180 d) 
13 
72 
Progeny tests (last 180 d) 
11 
73 </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian-Aust. J. Anim. Sci. 26:151-156 </p>

<p>
Selection index for progeny test 
= BEMA-BBF+6BMS </p>

<p>where, BYW = Breeding value for YW; BMS = Breeding 
value for MS; BEMA = Breeding value for EMA; BBF = 
Breeding value for BF; and BMS = Breeding value for MS. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Overall means of the traits were 352.838.56 kg, 
335.0944.61 kg, 77.858.838 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 8.63.7 mm and 
3.2931.648 for YW, CW, EMA, BF and MS (Table 2). 
Yoon et al. (2002) had reported with 1,262 carcass records 
from 334 steer progeny of Hanwoo young bulls that overall 
means were 301.134.3 kg, 74.88.7 cm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 7.33.2 mm, and 
3.041.60 in CW, EMA, BF, and MS, respectively. Yearling 
weight is one of the traits used to select young bulls, where 
there is a positive correlation with BF, CW and EMA. It 
results in improvements in YW, CW and EMA, but negative 
effects in BF (Table 5). The marbling scoring system was 
changed from 7 levels to 9 levels since 2005, thus causing 
higher scores than the past. Son et al. (1997) have reported 
that least square mean of YW was estimated at 232.083.22 
kg in the Hanwoo cow population from 1989 to 1995. 
Although it was estimated in the cow population, about 
50% in YW has been improved for last two decades 
comparing to the result in this study (352.838.56 kg). 
Oikawa et al. (2000) have reported that means of EMA, BF 
and MS were 46.75.9 cm 
2 , 16.14.6 mm, 2.491.01, 
respectively, in Japanese Black (Wagyu) cattle population. </p>

<p>The EMA that they reported was smaller than the result in 
this study which may be because it was measured at the 6th 
to 7th rib section on the left side of the carcass. They had a 
5-level system in MS resulting in lower scores than the 
result in this study. 
Heritabilities estimated in this study (Table 5) were 0.30, 
0.30, 0.42, 0.50 and 0.63 in YW, CW, EMA, BF and MS, 
respectively, results which are similar to previous research 
(Yoon et al., 2002). Heritability of body weight at finish, 
and EMA, BF and MS in Japanese Wagyu was estimated at 
0.360.13, 0.020.04, 0.150.14 and 0.490.13, 
respectively. There were differences in EMA and BF except 
MS, which may be due to inconsistent harvest treatments in 
the testing procedure (Oikawa et al., 2000). 
Trends of phenotypic and breeding values in each trait 
are shown in Figure 1 to 5 by year, which are from 2000 to 
2011. The trends of some phenotypic values are not steady, 
which may be due to the individuals randomly chosen for 
progeny tests. In other words, it may be due to a small 
number to represent all the population, while most animals 
were included in the pedigree to estimate breeding values. 
Yearling weight was 315.54 kg in 1998, and increased to 
355.06 kg in 2011, resulting in about 40 kg of improvement 
over 13 yrs. Genetic responses were calculated with 
estimated heritabilities and generation intervals (Table 6). 
Many studies were reported on estimation of genetic 
parameters in Hanwoo, but few on trends of breeding values. 
Yang and Ohh (1990) have reported breeding values for 
body weights and girths in Hanwoo, but their trends were 
not included. </p>

<p>Table 5. Heritability (diagonal), genetic and environmental correlations (below and above diagonal) 
Traits 
Yearling weight 
Carcass weight 
EMA 
Backfat 
MS9 
Yearling weight (kg) 
0.300.04 
0.720.03 
0.330.05 
0.180.06 
0.130.11 
Carcass weight (kg) 
0.650.08 
0.300.05 
0.500.04 
0.360.06 
0.080.11 
EMA (cm 
2 ) 
0.120.11 
0.450.08 
0.420.06 
0.190.07 
0.110.12 
Backfat (mm) 
0.250.11 
0.250.09 
-0.200.10 
0.500.06 
0.190.13 
MS9 
-0.200.13 
0.200.12 
0.300.11 
-0.020.11 
0.630.09 </p>

<p>* EMA = Eye muscle area; MS9 = Marbling score with 9 levels. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Trends of phenotypic and breeding values in yearling 
weight (YW) by year. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Trends of phenotypic and breeding values in carcass 
weight (CW) by year. </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian-Aust. J. Anim. Sci. 26:151-156 </p>



<p>YW and CW have been improved remarkably over the 
past 15 yrs. Breeding values between 1996 and 2000 
decreased or did not change much, but have moved in a 
desirable direction since 2001. These improvements 
correspond with the substantial increase in use of animal 
models since the late 1990s in Korea. MacNeil et al. (2000) 
have reported that yearling weights showed a 20 kg increase, 
that is, 1.3 kg/yr on average, in a Hereford line from 1978 
to 1993. 
Hanwoo testing programs have practically contributed 
to the improvement in quality as well as quantity (Figure 6 
and Table 7). It can be verified in the results of other carcass 
data reported by the Korea Institute for Animal Products 
Qualify Evaluation (KAPE) that is the organization that 
ranks carcass and manages the data quality in South Korea. 
The statistics of the carcass collected by KAPE from 2001 
to 2010 shows the marketed live weights, CW, EMA and </p>

<p>MS in the past 10 yrs have been increased by 109 kg, 74 kg, 
9.1 cm 
2 and 1.8 (Table 7). The trend of Hanwoo 
improvement that HIC surveys every three years also shows 
the similar results. For instance, the 18-month weight in 
1974 was 289.2 kg on average, and was 552.8 kg in 2010; a 
91% increase over 36 yrs (Table 9). </p>

<p>IMPLICATIONS </p>

<p>The current selection system is good enough to 
accommodate circumstances that fewer bulls have a big 
impact on many more cows. Although progeny tests take 
longer and cost more, it seems to be appropriate under the 
circumstances of a domestic market that has a higher 
affinity for better meat quality (Oikawa et al., 2000). 
Selection objectives reflect social needs, therefore it is 
difficult to currently predict new goals in the future. 
However, they are to select Hanwoo proven bulls optimized 
under the varying environment in accordance with social 
and economic requirements for Hanwoo or changes in price </p>

<p>Table 6. Genetic responses in each trait by year </p>

<p>Trait 
Heritability 
Selection 
differential </p>

<p>Genetic 
response 
Yearling weight 
0.30 
1.32 
0.078 kg/yr 
Carcass weight 
0.30 
6.09 
0.35 kg/yr 
EMA 
0.42 
3.34 
0.27 cm 
2 /yr </p>

<p>Backfat 
0.50 
-1.04 
-0.01 mm/yr 
MS9 
0.63 
-0.31 
-0.037 /yr </p>

<p>* Average generation interval was estimated to 5.22 yr. 
** EMA = Eye muscle area; MS9 = Marbling score with 9 levels. </p>

<p>Table 7. Statistic for carcass traits 
2001 
2002 
2003 
2004 
2005 
2006 
2007 
2008 
2009 
2010 
Marketed weights (kg) 
586 
608 
617 
630 
632 
645 
655 
670 
683 
695 
Carcass weight (kg) 
345 
358 
365 
379 
378 
385 
394 
405 
413 
419 
EMA (cm 
2 ) 
79.6 
81.1 
82.2 
83.1 
81.5 
83.1 
84.2 
86.5 
88.0 
88.7 
MS 
3.4 
3.5 
3.9 
4.2 
4.9 
4.8 
4.8 
5.0 
5.3 
5.2 </p>

<p>* Published by Korea Institute for Animal Products Quality Evaluation. ** EMA = Eye muscle area; MS = Marbling score. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Trends of phenotypic and breeding values in backfat 
(BF) by year. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Trends of phenotypic and breeding values in marbling 
score (MS) by year. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Trends of phenotypic and breeding values in eye muscle 
area (EMA) by year. </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian-Aust. J. Anim. Sci. 26:151-156 </p>

<p>
structure. Technologies to be introduced in the future or 
under the present study for selection programs include feed 
efficiency measurements, ultrasound, and genomic selection 
and so on. The application of these techniques to a Hanwoo 
selection program would require several steps, such as 
accumulative data collection, genetic evaluation model 
development, revision of selection indices, as well as 
cooperation among farms, associations, the National 
Agricultural Cooperative Federation, universities, research 
institutes, and government agencies. All efforts will keep 
the domestic market from imported beef under Free Trade 
Agreement trade system to secure competitive position, 
provide farmers with higher profits as well as the public 
with higher quality of beef. </p>



<p>* Source: Hanwoo Improvement Center, National Agricultural Cooperative Federation. </p>

<p>KPN783 
KPN802 
KPN829 
KPN740 </p>

<p>Figure 6. Hanwoo proven bulls selected recently. </p>

</text></tei>