<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4976915" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Pain is a main symptom of herpes zoster (HZ), and postherpetic neuralgia 
(PHN) is a frequent complication occurring in 5% to 15% of cases, causing moderate to severe 
neuropathic pain. A population-based observational study was conducted to evaluate the treat-
ment patterns and economic burden of prescription drug treatment of HZ and PHN pain in the 
province of Manitoba (Canada) over a period of 15 years. 
Methods: Administrative health care data, including medical and hospital separation records, 
were examined to identify episodes of HZ using International Classification of Diseases-9/10 
codes between April 1, 1997 and March 31, 2014. Episodes of PHN were identified using medi-
cal and prescription claims. Incident use of analgesic, antidepressant, or anticonvulsant drugs 
was used to determine prescription pain costs. 
Results: The age-adjusted incidence of HZ increased from 4.7 episodes/1,000 person-years in 
1997/98 to 5.7/1,000 person-years in 2013/14. PHN occurred in 9.2% of HZ cases, a rate that 
did not change over the study period (P=0.57). The annual cost to treat HZ pain rose by 174% 
from 1997/98, reaching CAD $332,981 in 2011/12, 82.8% (95% confidence interval [CI] 81.2%, 
84.3%) of which was related to PHN. The per episode cost of HZ rose by 111% from $31.59 
(95% CI $25.35, $37.84) to $66.81 (95% CI $56.84, $76.78) and by 94% for PHN from $292 
(95% CI $225, $358) to $566 (95% CI $478, $655). These increases were driven by increasing 
use of anticonvulsants, primarily gabapentin, which accounted for 57% of the increase in cost. 
Conclusion: There has been an increase in the incidence of HZ and PHN and in the average 
cost associated with the prescription treatment of their resultant neuropathic pain. The primary 
driver of the increased episodic cost is the increased use of gabapentin. These changes have 
resulted in a substantial increase in the economic burden associated with HZ and PHN. 
Herpes zoster (HZ) is an infectious disease caused by reactivation of latent varicella 
zoster infection. This common viral disease afflicts between 20% and 30% of the 
population at some point in their lifetime; up to 50% of individuals over 80 years of 
age are affected. 
1,2 The dermatological symptoms of HZ are typically preceded by 
prodromal symptoms that range from a tingling or burning sensation to a sharp stab-
bing pain. This is followed by a raised, reddish rash and vesicular lesions, typically 
over the region of skin affected by prodromal symptoms, 2 to 3 days later. This rash 
typically affects singular dermatomes resulting in a unilateral, stripe-like appearance 
that is diagnostic of HZ. Lesions continue to erupt for several days before the rash 
crusts over, generally within 7 to 10 days. Symptoms then begin to subside and total </p>

<p>correspondence: shawn Bugden 
college of Pharmacy, Rady Faculty of 
health sciences, University of Manitoba, 
750 McDermot avenue, Winnipeg, MB, 
R3e 0T5, canada 
email shawn.bugden@umanitoba.ca </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Journal of Pain Research 
3 August 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>544 </p>

<p>Friesen et al </p>

<p>resolution generally occurs within 3 to 4 weeks. 
3 While HZ 
is generally self-limiting, longer lasting complications can 
occur. 
The most common complication of zoster is postherpetic 
neuralgia (PHN). PHN is defined as pain that persists after 
the resolution of the dermatological symptoms of HZ. It 
is caused by damage to sensory neurons sustained during 
the initial active infection with pain persisting even after 
the virus has returned to its dormant state. 
4 There is no single 
standard definition of PHN. Pain persisting at 30 to 120 days 
measured from onset of HZ or from healing of rash is used 
in the literature. 
5-7 Pain persisting at 90 days from initial HZ 
diagnosis is the most commonly used definition. </p>

<p>5-7 </p>

<p>The incidence of HZ is estimated at 3.5 to 7 cases per 
1,000 person-years (PY), with the incidence in females 
slightly higher than in males. 
8,9 The incidence of HZ increases 
steadily with age, rising to 6-7/1,000 PY by 60 years, and 
continuing to increase thereafter. 
2,10,11 The rate of conversion 
to PHN has been estimated at anywhere from 5% to 60% of 
HZ cases. 
7,11,12 This wide range is partially explained by the 
lack of standard diagnostic criteria. Studies that used pain 
persisting at 90 days to define PHN have a more conserva-
tive conversion rate with a narrower range of between 5% 
and 15%. </p>

<p>7-9,11-13 </p>

<p>PHN is a challenging condition to treat, and the effective-
ness of pharmacological therapy is limited. The Canadian 
Pain Society consensus statement on the treatment of neuro-
pathic pain recommends as first-line therapy for PHN one of 
the tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs), gabapentin, or pregaba-
lin. 
14 Opioids and topical lidocaine are listed as second-line 
alternatives. The European Federation of Neurological Soci-
eties 2010 treatment guidelines for neuropathic pain largely 
echo these recommendations. Opioids, while effective, are 
not recommended as first-line therapy due to side effects, 
development of tolerance, and risk of dependency. 
15 A variety 
of other drugs are also discussed in the literature, including 
those used for other forms of neuropathy, although their 
efficacy for PHN is disputed. These include valproic acid/ 
divalproex sodium, duloxetine, venlafaxine, carbamazepine, 
tramadol, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), 
and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors. </p>

<p>6,14-18 </p>

<p>While treatment of PHN remains difficult, it is possible to 
reduce the risk of HZ, and with it PHN, with the HZ vaccine 
(Zostavax II </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Merck &amp; Co., Inc., Kenilworth, NJ, USA). This 
vaccine has been shown to reduce the relative risk of HZ by 
51% and of PHN by almost 67%. Vaccines may decrease the 
chance of developing HZ, but HZ and the associated PHN </p>

<p>are expected to continue to result in a significant burden to 
society in the near future. 
To determine the incidence of HZ and rates of PHN, a ret-
rospective cohort study was conducted in Manitoba, Canada, 
over a period of 17 years. The objectives were to determine 
the burden of disease of zoster-related pain and to understand 
the major cost drivers in the changing cost of treating HZ. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>A population-based cohort study was conducted in Manitoba 
(Canada) using administrative health care data from Mani-
toba's universal public health care system gathered from April 
1, 1995 to March 31, 2014 in the course of providing routine 
medical care. These data were accessed via the Manitoba 
Centre for Health Policy Population Health Research Data 
Repository, a collection of databases containing records of 
contacts of Manitoba residents with the health care system. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Databases utilized included the Drug Program Information 
Network, which processes all community pharmacy-based 
prescriptions for insurance coverage and drug utilization 
review; the Medical Services database which contains records 
of all fee-for-service medical provider claims; hospital dis-
charge abstracts containing separations data for all hospital-
izations; and the Manitoba Health Registry which contains 
basic demographic information on all persons registered with 
Manitoba Health, Healthy Living and Seniors. All records are 
de-identified but contain a unique scrambled personal health 
number allowing for the cross-linkage of records over time 
and across data sets. 
Episodes of zoster were identified using diagnostic codes 
in medical claims and hospital separations. Individuals with 
one or more International Classification of Diseases-9 (ICD-
9) codes starting with 053 or ICD-10-Clinical Modification 
(ICD-10-CM) codes starting with B02 were considered as 
HZ cases, the date of the first being the episode start date. 
The use of ICD diagnostic codes to diagnose zoster was 
both highly selective (positive predictive value 93%) and 
sensitive (97.5%). 
20 Multiple episodes per individual were 
allowed if 2 years had elapsed between episodes. To ensure 
only incident episodes were included in the analysis, a 2-year 
washout period was used; thus, any episodes identified prior 
to 1997/98 were excluded. Episodes where individuals were 
under 20 years at diagnosis were excluded to avoid misclas-
sification of varicella zoster cases as HZ. Cases of PHN were 
identified by HZ pain drug treatment or medical claims with 
HZ ICD codes appearing past 90 days from diagnosis. Ongo-
ing treatment is defined in the following section. </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>545 </p>

<p>cost of treating herpes zoster pain and postherpetic neuralgia </p>

<p>Drug treatment was categorized using Anatomical Thera-
peutic Chemical classes. Prescriptions for opioids (Ana-
tomical Therapeutic Chemical codes starting with N02A), 
NSAIDs (M01), anticonvulsants (N03A), antidepressants 
(N06A), nabilone (A04AD), local anesthetics (D04A), 
glucocorticoids (H02AB), and acetylsalicylic acid and acet-
aminophen (N02B) associated with HZ episodes identified in 
the previous step were collected. Those dispensed between 
90 days pre-HZ diagnoses and 2 years postdiagnosis were 
evaluated against several criteria to assess if they were related 
to HZ-PHN or were only coincident. 
The use of each drug class was categorized as either 
incident or prevalent for that episode by evaluating prescrip-
tions in the 90 days preceding diagnosis. A drug class was 
categorized as prevalent if a person received a total of 30 
days' supply or more within those 90 days, and all within-
class prescriptions were excluded from the analysis for that 
episode. From the remaining incident class, all prescriptions 
from diagnosis to 1) 90 days postdiagnosis or 2) date of last 
HZ medical claim were classified as HZ-PHN treatment. 
Prescriptions with dispensation dates outside this window had 
to meet the continuous use criteria. A grace period of 100% 
of the prescription duration was added to its duration to create 
an end date. To be considered a continuous treatment, there 
should be no gaps between the end date of previous prescrip-
tions and receipt of the next. Discontinuity signaled the end 
of drug treatment and of that episode; all later prescriptions 
were removed from further analysis of this episode. 
Data were summarized by Manitoba Health fiscal years, 
which run from April 1 to March 31 for each year. Results 
are reported as occurring within the fiscal year of diagnosis. 
Incidence rates for HZ were calculated for 1997/98 through to 
2013/14, and age adjusted using the population of Manitoba 
in 1997 as our standard. As 2 years follow-up was required 
to capture all data related to episodes of HZ with PHN, only 
episodes diagnosed from 1997/98 to 2011/12 contributed 
to the PHN analysis. Regression analysis was conducted on 
rates of conversion from HZ to PHN across this interval. 
Drug costs were calculated directly from prescription 
records, included cost of both drug and dispensing fee, and were 
adjusted to 2013 Canadian dollars using Statistics Canada's 
consumer price index for prescription drug costs in Manitoba. 
Annual total prescription costs were tabulated for all HZ epi-
sodes, as well as within HZ episodes that converted to PHN 
(HZ-PHN). Prescription costs per episode were calculated, and 
t-tests were conducted to determine the significance of differ-
ences between mean costs in 1997/98 and 2011/12. Regression 
on the proportion of total cost due to HZ-PHN was used to look </p>

<p>for trends over time. The relationship between age at diagnosis 
and mean treatment cost was examined by regression analysis. 
Prescription data were stratified by drug class for HZ-
PHN episodes, looking at anticonvulsants, antidepressants, 
NSAIDs, and opioids. The number of treated episodes was 
determined for each year. Regressions on the number of class-
wise treated episodes were used to examine trends over time. 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, USA) 
was used for all data analysis. Approvals were granted by the 
University of Manitoba Health Research Ethics Board and the 
Manitoba Health Information Privacy Committee. Individual 
written consent from patients was not required by the ethics 
board or the privacy committee for this retrospective analysis 
using de-identified data. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Between April 1, 1997 and March 31, 2014, there were 
73,893 episodes of HZ diagnosed in Manitoba resulting in 
a mean of 4,347 (95% confidence interval [CI] 4,067, 4,626) 
episodes per year. There were 5,749 episodes of HZ diag-
nosed in 2013/14, a 50% increase from the 3,844 episodes 
diagnosed in 1997/98. The age-standardized incidence rate 
of HZ increased by 21%, from 4.70 episodes/1,000 PY in 
1997/98 to 5.70 episodes/1,000 PY in 2013/14. 
Total prescription costs for treating pain resulting from HZ 
and PHN are shown in Table 1. The annual cost of prescription 
drugs used to treat all HZ-related pain rose by over 174%, from 
CAD $121,438 in 1997/98 to $332,981 in 2011/12. The drug 
cost of HZ-PHN episodes rose by 191%, from $96,554 to 
$281,342. PHN accounted for a mean of 82.8% (95% CI 81.2%, 
84.3%) of drug costs. This percentage did not change signifi-
cantly over the course of the study period (P=0.57, R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.026). 
From 1997/98 through to 2011/12, the period for which 
full PHN results could be obtained, there were 6,038 episodes 
of HZ that met the study criteria for PHN, corresponding to 
a conversion rate of 9.6%. A linear regression analysis on 
conversion rates revealed no significant trend over this period 
of time (P=0.45, R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.046). However, the increase in the total 
number of HZ episodes resulted in a greater number of PHN 
cases over time, rising from 331 in 1997/98 to 497 in 2011/12. 
The mean cost of treating HZ-related pain increases lin-
early with age at diagnosis, each additional year increasing 
the mean episode cost by $1.04 (P&lt;0.0001, R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.65) (Figure 
1). The mean cost for persons aged 20 to 29 years was $24.15 
(95% CI $19.95, $28.34), while for persons aged 60 to 69 years 
the cost was 143% higher at $58.72 (95% CI $52.92, $64.53). 
The average cost of treating an episode of HZ, and sepa-
rately those episodes with PHN, increased over the study </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>546 </p>

<p>Friesen et al </p>

<p>period (Table 1). The mean cost per episodes to treat all HZ-
related pain rose significantly by 111% (t=5.369, P&lt;0.0001) 
from 1997/98 to 2011/12, and by 94% for HZ-PHN episodes 
(t=4.36, P&lt;0.0001). 
Changes in the treatment of HZ-PHN over time were 
examined by linear regression (Figure 2). Only anticonvulsant 
use changed significantly with a 212% increase in the number </p>

<p>of anticonvulsant-treated episodes from 1997/98 to 2011/12 
(P&lt;0.0001, R 
2 =0.92). 
The duration of treatment for HZ-PHN varied widely 
between drug classes (Figure 3). The median days supplied 
was highest for antidepressants (178 days) and anticonvul-
sants (134 days), with shorter durations for NSAIDs (50 days) 
and opioids (28 days). The median duration of anticonvulsant </p>

<p>Table 1 Total cost and cost per episode of treating herpes zoster-related pain by year </p>

<p>Herpes zoster episodes 
Herpes zoster with PHN </p>

<p>Year 
Episodes Rxs 
Total cost Mean cost (95% CI) 
Episodes Rxs 
Total cost 
Mean PHN cost (95% CI) </p>

<p>1997/1998 
3,844 
6,082 
$121,438 
$31.59 ($25.35, $37.84) 
331 
3,925 $96,555 
$291.71 ($225.45, $357.96) 
1998/1999 
3,781 
6,309 
$130,276 
$34.46 ($28.38, $40.53) 
349 
4,229 $107,007 
$306.61 ($248.06, $365.16) 
1999/2000 
3,941 
7,820 
$245,329 
$62.25 ($50.74, $73.76) 
367 
5,526 $215,149 
$586.24 ($475.95, $696.53) 
2000/2001 
3,954 
7,629 
$224,626 
$56.81 ($46.70, $66.92) 
399 
5,440 $192,830 
$483.28 ($393.34, $573.23) 
2001/2002 
4,060 
8,282 
$271,792 
$66.94 ($52.67, $81.22) 
429 
6,064 $236,570 
$551.45 ($425.20, $677.69) 
2002/2003 
4,126 
8,015 
$254,967 
$61.80 ($52.07, $71.52) 
410 
5,554 $215,795 
$526.33 ($440.91, $611.75) 
2003/2004 
4,070 
7,783 
$231,833 
$56.96 ($47.57, $66.35) 
375 
5,541 $191,562 
$510.83 ($421.55, $600.12) 
2004/2005 
4,087 
7,070 
$194,372 
$47.56 ($40.78, $54.34) 
379 
4,670 $153,891 
$406.05 ($343.97, $468.12) 
2005/2006 
4,131 
7,886 
$214,436 
$51.91 ($44.30, $59.51) 
432 
5,581 $172,052 
$398.27 ($334.80, $461.74) 
2006/2007 
4,143 
7,918 
$207,393 
$50.06 ($42.52, $57.60) 
377 
5,586 $165,257 
$438.35 ($366.84, $509.86) 
2007/2008 
4,207 
7,968 
$193,942 
$46.10 ($39.89, $52.31) 
377 
5,674 $152,928 
$405.64 ($348.23, $463.06) 
2008/2009 
4,295 
9,435 
$252,994 
$58.90 ($50.77, $67.04) 
440 
7,147 $209,013 
$475.03 ($407.32, $542.74) 
2009/2010 
4,584 
9,393 
$267,865 
$58.43 ($49.20, $67.67) 
427 
7,024 $222,968 
$522.17 ($434.64, $609.71) 
2010/2011 
4,622 
9,102 
$276,383 
$59.80 ($49.42, $70.17) 
449 
6,617 $230,827 
$514.09 ($416.88, $611.30) 
2011/2012 
4,984 
11,065 $332,981 
$66.81 ($56.84, $76.78) 
497 
8,398 $281,342 
$566.08 ($477.51, $654.66) </p>

<p>Notes: costs include all prescriptions from date of diagnosis to end of episode and include prescriptions for postherpetic neuralgia when present. The herpes zoster with 
Phn group includes only those cases of herpes zoster that converted to neuralgia and includes prescriptions from the start of the herpes zoster episode. costs are reported 
in 2013 canadian dollars. 
Abbreviations: PHN, postherpetic neuralgia; Rxs, prescriptions; CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Mean cost per episode of herpes zoster-associated pain treatment by age at diagnosis. Costs adjusted for inflation to 2013 Canadian dollars. </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 
40 
60 </p>

<p>Age at diagnosis (years) </p>

<p>Cost per episode (CAD $) </p>

<p>80 
100 </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>547 </p>

<p>cost of treating herpes zoster pain and postherpetic neuralgia </p>

<p>treatment increased from 55 to 141 days between 1997/98 and 
2011/12. There was much less change observed in the median 
treatment duration of other drug classes, with antidepressants 
increasing from 161 to 190 days, opioids remaining relatively 
stable with an increase from 26.5 to 27 days, and NSAIDs 
decreasing from 38.5 to 30 days. </p>

<p>The overall annual cost of opioid, NSAID, and anti-
depressant prescriptions underwent a moderate increase 
with antidepressants increasing by 91%, opioids by 67%, 
and NSAIDs by 35% (Table 2). However, these changes 
were small compared to the increase in anticonvulsant use, 
which underwent a 755% rise in class cost, increasing from </p>

<p>Figure 2 Treatment of postherpetic neuralgia episodes by drug class. 
Notes: numbers of episodes treated by drug class. a single episode can be treated with more than one class of drug, thus a single episode can contribute data to more 
than one category. 
Abbreviation: NSAID, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug. </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1997 
Number of treated episodes </p>

<p>1999 
2001 
2003 
2005 
2007 </p>

<p>Year 
Drug class 
Antidepressants </p>

<p>NSAIDs </p>

<p>Anticonvulsants </p>

<p>Opioids </p>

<p>2009 
2011 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Distribution of days of drug treatment per episode by class. 
Notes: Boxplot of the number of days of drug treatment per episode by drug class for herpes zoster with postherpetic neuralgia.  = mean. 
Abbreviation: NSAID, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug. </p>

<p>1,250 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>750 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>0 
Antidepressants Anticonvulsants 
NSAIDs 
Drug class 
Drug treatment duration per episode (days) </p>

<p>Opioids </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>548 </p>

<p>Friesen et al </p>

<p>$15,520 to $132,685. This increase accounts for 56% of the 
total increase in prescription spending for the treatment of 
all HZ-associated pain. 
The most frequently prescribed anticonvulsant drug for 
HZ-PHN also changed over time. In 1997, carbamazepine 
prescriptions accounted for 62% (260 prescriptions) of all 
anticonvulsant prescriptions, while gabapentin accounted for 
only 21% (89 prescriptions). In contrast, in 2011, only 3.2% 
(80 prescriptions) of all anticonvulsant prescriptions were 
for carbamazepine. Gabapentin accounted for 73% (1,798) 
of prescriptions, while pregabalin, which was not available 
in 1997, accounted for 9.2% (226). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The economic burden of treating HZ-associated pain, and 
PHN in particular, increased significantly from 1997/98 to 
2011/12 (Table 1). This increase is the combined result of 
increases in both the incidence of diagnosed HZ and in the 
mean episode cost of prescription drug treatment of pain. 
A dramatic increase in gabapentin was found to be a primary 
driver of mean episode cost. 
Over the 17-year period between 1997/98 and 2013/14, 
there has been a sustained increase in the incidence of HZ, 
with a resulting increase in the number of PHN cases. Changes 
in size and increasing age 
21 of the provincial population 
explain the majority of this increase. However, after taking 
both these factors into account, a significant increase of 21% in 
the age-adjusted incidence per thousand people was observed. 
As the rate of conversion from HZ to PHN did not change 
over the study period, the increased number of HZ episodes </p>

<p>resulted in an increase in the number of PHN cases. This 
increase in PHN cases is an important factor in determining 
the economic burden of HZ, as these cases were responsible 
for over 80% of HZ-related analgesic prescription costs. 
Not only were there more HZ and PHN cases, there 
was also a significant increase in the mean cost per episode 
related to the treatment of pain. This higher episode cost was 
driven by the increased use of anticonvulsant drugs, primarily 
gabapentin. While the number of users of anticonvulsants 
rose, the use of other classes of drugs remained relatively 
unchanged (Table 2). Not only did the number of persons 
using anticonvulsant drugs increased, the median duration 
of treatment increased with them as well. 
From an evidence-based perspective, this change might 
seem surprising. There is considerable debate on whether this 
increased expenditure is justified. There is limited evidence 
demonstrating superior efficacy and involves much greater 
cost compared to the other first-line therapies such as TCAs. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>In fact, one systematic review estimated the number needed to 
treat (NNT) for a 50% reduction of pain for gabapentin to be 
4.39 (95% CI 3.34, 6.07), while that for TCAs was 2.64 (95% CI 
2.1, 3.54). 
23 Gabapentin was introduced to the Canadian market 
in December 1994 when it was approved for the adjunctive 
treatment of partial seizures. 
24 It was aggressively marketed to 
physicians for a number of nonapproved indications, including 
PHN, by Parke Davis. This promotion eventually led to a US 
federal lawsuit against the company for off-label marketing in 
1996. 
25 It was not until 2004 that the US Food and Drug Admin-
istration (FDA) approved gabapentin for PHN, 
25 although it has 
never received this indication in Canada. Some of this promo-</p>

<p>Table 2 Treatment of herpes zoster-related pain by drug class </p>

<p>Antidepressants 
Anticonvulsants 
NSAIDs 
Opioids 
Miscellaneous </p>

<p>Year 
Users Cost (CAD) 
Users Cost (CAD) 
Users Cost (CAD) 
Users Cost (CAD) 
Users Cost (CAD) </p>



<p>Journal of Pain Research 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>549 </p>

<p>cost of treating herpes zoster pain and postherpetic neuralgia </p>

<p>tion suggested that TCA use for PHN was inappropriate in 
older patients from a safety perspective. 
22 However, gabapentin 
is not without its own adverse effects, and a systematic review 
suggests the number needed to harm (NNH) for major harms 
is actually similar for gabapentin (NNH=12.25, 95% CI 7.69, 
30.2) and TCAs (NNH=16.9, 95% CI 8.85, 178). </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Concerns have been raised about the use of opioids in 
noncancer pain. 
26 These include the risk of dependency, the 
development of tolerance, and the potential for abuse, and are 
part of the rationale for listing opioids as second-line PHN 
treatment options. 
15,27 However, opioids were used frequently 
to treat HZ-PHN episodes (Figure 2). While the high rate 
of use may be concerning, the median of duration of opioid 
treatment (Figure 3) reveals generally short-term use, pos-
sibly reflecting appropriate opioid stewardship. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>This study has a number of strengths and limitations. Popula-
tion level data from a universal single-payer health care system 
ensures virtually all contacts of residents with this health care 
system, and all prescription dispensations are captured in the 
study. These data sets also allow us to directly measure health 
system costs rather than inferring results from survey data or 
sampling, as it has been done in many previous studies. </p>

<p>12,28-30 </p>

<p>There are also several limitations to this study. We were unable 
to measure the true incidence of HZ in the population as 
only persons who sought medical treatment appeared in the 
administrative data. However, previous studies have reported 
that up to 95%-99% of persons with HZ will seek medical 
attention. 
8,28 Second, HZ diagnostic codes or prescription 
treatment past 90 days postdiagnosis were used as a proxy for 
a PHN diagnosis as we only had access to the first three digits 
of ICD codes in our data. Thus, rates reported are of HZ cases 
requiring ongoing medical management, sometimes referred 
to as clinically significant PHN. This methodology is com-
mon in administrative data studies looking at PHN. 
8 Finally, 
the use of nonprescription medications, including low-dose 
ibuprofen and naproxen, acetaminophen, acetylsalicylic acid, 
and topical treatments, is not captured. However, these costs 
are outside the scope of this study. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The total costs of treating pain associated with HZ and PHN 
rose by 174% between 1997/98 and 2011/12. There are two 
primary components to this increasing economic burden. 
The first is the increasing number of HZ cases. While some 
of this can be attributed to an aging population, the age-
standardized incidence of HZ has increased. The second </p>

<p>component is the increasing average cost of treating an 
episode of HZ-PHN driven by the use of higher cost anti-
convulsants for longer periods of time. Management of the 
economic burden of HZ-PHN analgesic treatment should 
include the use of evidence-based cost-effective therapies 
and measures such as vaccination that can help reduce the 
incidence of HZ. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors acknowledge the Manitoba Centre for Health 
Policy for use of data contained in the Population Health 
Research Data Repository under project #H2014:411 
(Health Information Privacy Committee # 2014/2015-35). 
The results and conclusions are those of the authors and 
no official endorsement by the Manitoba Centre for Health 
Policy, Manitoba Health, Healthy Living and Seniors, or 
other data providers is intended or should be inferred. Data 
used in this study are from the Population Health Research 
Data Repository housed at the Manitoba Centre for Health 
Policy, University of Manitoba, and were derived from data 
provided by Manitoba Health. The authors would also like 
to thank Heather Prior from the Manitoba Centre for Health 
Policy for her assistance and preliminary data extraction. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>This work was supported by a investigator-initiated grant 
grant from Merck Canada. The authors report no other con-
flicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Journal of Pain Research 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Journal of Pain Research </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/journal-of-pain-research-journal </p>

<p>The Journal of Pain Research is an international, peer reviewed, open 
access, online journal that welcomes laboratory and clinical findings 
in the fields of pain research and the prevention and management 
of pain. Original research, reviews, symposium reports, hypoth-
esis formation and commentaries are all considered for publication. </p>

<p>The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Friesen et al </p>



</text></tei>