<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4674517" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background Data on the prevalence of adverse drug 
event (ADE)-related emergency department (ED) visits in 
developing countries are limited. Malaysia is located in 
South-East Asia, and, to our knowledge, no information 
exists on ADE-related ED visits. 
Objective The objective of this study was to determine 
the prevalence, preventability, severity, and outcome of 
drug-related ED visits. 
Methodology A cross-sectional study was conducted in 
consenting patients who visited the ED of Hospital 
Universiti Sains Malaysia over a 6-week period. The ED 
physician on duty determined whether or not the visit was 
drug related according to set criteria. Other relevant 
information was extracted from the patient's medical folder 
by a clinical pharmacist. 
Results Of the 434 consenting patients, 133 (30.6 %; 95 % 
confidence interval [CI] 26-35 %) visits were determined to 
be ADE related; 55.5 % were considered preventable, 
11.3 % possibly preventable, and 33.1 % not preventable. 
Severity was classed as mild in 1.5 %, moderate in 67.7 %, 
and severe in 30.8 %. The most common ADEs reported 
were drug therapeutic failure (55.6 %) and adverse drug </p>

<p>reactions (32.3 %). The most frequently implicated drugs 
were antidiabetics (n = 31; 23.3 %), antihypertensives 
(n = 28; 21.1 %), antibiotics (n = 13; 9.8 %), and anti-
asthmatics (n = 11; 8.3 %). A total of 93 patients (69.9 %) 
were admitted to the ED for observation, 25 (18.8 %) were 
discharged immediately after consultation, and 15 (11.3 %) 
were admitted to the ward through the ED. 
Conclusion The prevalence of ADE-related ED visits was 
high; more than one-half of the events were considered 
preventable and one-third was classed as severe. As such, 
preventive measures will minimize future occurrences and 
increase patient safety. </p>

<p>Key Points </p>

<p>Three in ten patients seeking care at the emergency 
department of a teaching hospital in Malaysia were 
for events associated with drug use. </p>

<p>Drug therapeutic failure due to medication non-
adherence was the most commonly reported adverse 
drug event. </p>

<p>An adverse drug event (ADE) is ''any untoward medical 
occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation subject 
administered a pharmaceutical product and which does not 
necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this 
treatment'' [1]. ADEs have been identified as a major public 
health concern and are responsible for a high level of mor-
bidity and mortality worldwide [2]. In the USA, ADEs </p>

<p>&amp; Abubakar Ibrahim Jatau 
pharmjt@gmail.com </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Faculty of Health Sciences, Universiti Sultan Zainal Abidin, 
Kampus Gong Badak, Kuala Terengganu, Malaysia </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, 
Universiti Sultan Zainal Abidin, Kampus Kota, 
Kuala Terengganu, Malaysia </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Emergency Medicine, School of Medical 
Sciences, Universiti Sains Malaysia, Kota Bharu, Kelantan, 
Malaysia </p>

<p>Drugs -Real World Outcomes (2015) 2:387-395 
DOI 10.1007/s40801-015-0045-2 </p>

<p>accounted for 17 million emergency department (ED) visits 
and 8.7 million hospital admissions annually [3]. ADEs 
occur in all clinical settings and are responsible for 
0.77-37.6 % of ED visits [4-6]. They also contributed to an 
increase in healthcare cost, loss of productivity, increased 
hospital stay and time away from work, as well as lower 
patient satisfaction [7-9]. In Canada, ADEs were responsible 
for a total annual cost of $Can35.7 million in 2008 [10]. 
In Malaysia, over 2 million hospital admissions and 19 
million outpatient visits were documented in government 
hospitals in 2014 [11]. Similarly, over 8 million and 33 
million prescriptions were dispensed to in-patients and out-
patients, respectively [12]. Despite these figures, data on 
the prevalence of ADE-related hospitalizations in Malaysia 
are still scarce. Thus, it is necessary to identify the burden 
of ADEs in an ED to better understand the challenges faced 
by healthcare professionals in Malaysia. 
Many of the previous studies on ADE-related hospital-
izations focused on patients in ambulatory care units and 
those admitted to hospital wards, with relatively few 
evaluating the number of patients seeking care in the ED 
[13]. The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence 
of ADE-related ED visits at a teaching hospital in Malay-
sia. Our secondary objective was to determine the degree 
of severity, preventability, and outcome of these visits. </p>

<p>2 Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Settings </p>

<p>The study was conducted at the ED of Hospital Universiti 
Sains Malaysia (HUSM), Kelantan, Malaysia. HUSM is a 
767-bed tertiary hospital and was considered the largest 
referral centre in the east coast of Malaysia [14]. The ED 
receives approximately 65,000 patients per annum. </p>

<p>2.2 Patients </p>

<p>All patients coming to the HUSM ED during the period 
December 2014 to January 2015 were considered for this 
study. The exclusion criteria were (1) patients referred 
from another hospital, (2) patients on a scheduled visit to 
the ED, and (3) patients with medico-legal cases. The 
remainder of the patients was approached for consent. Only 
those who consented to participate were interviewed. 
Recruitment was halted when the required minimum 
number of patients was reached. </p>

<p>2.3 Design </p>

<p>A cross-sectional study was performed over a 6-week period. 
Patient interviews were conducted between 09:00 am and </p>

<p>05:00 pm, Sunday to Thursday. The ED physician determined 
whether or not the chief presenting complaints were related to 
drugs, based on the following criteria [15]: (1) known drug 
actions as described in drug monographs and/or literature, (2) 
the temporal relationship between the event and the time of 
drug use, and (3) the nature of the current underlying dis-
ease(s). Information regarding the patient's socio-demo-
graphic characteristics, current drug use, current use of any 
modality of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM), 
and history of visiting multiple prescribers or pharmacies in 
the last 14 days were collected. Patient medical and medica-
tion history, drug allergy, history of presenting illness, recent 
hospital admission, drugs dispensed at the ED, and outcome of 
the visits was also obtained. The categorization of the ADE, 
preventability, severity, and outcome of the visits were 
determined based on definitions adopted and modified from 
previous studies, as described in Sect. 2.4. </p>

<p>2.4 Definitions </p>

<p>An ED visit was considered ADE related when the chief 
presenting complaint was related to drug use [8]. If the patient 
had other symptoms related to drug use, and the chief pre-
senting complaint was not related to these, the ED visit was 
considered not ADE related. ADE-related ED visits were 
classified into the following five categories. (1) Adverse drug 
reaction (ADR)-a ''response to a drug that is noxious or 
unintended, and that occurs at doses normally used for the 
prophylaxis, diagnosis, or therapy of disease'' [9]. (2) Drug 
therapeutic failure (DTF)-an absence of therapeutic 
response (deterioration of disease state or condition) to a drug 
that could be linked causally either to a prescribed dose that 
was too low, medication non-adherence, recent dose reduction 
and interaction, or inadequate monitoring [16]. The visit was 
regarded as due to DTF when caused by medication non-
adherence where the patient's drug-taking behavior did not 
correspond with agreed recommendations from the healthcare 
provider, resulting in a disease or condition not stabilizing or 
symptoms worsening [17]. (3) Accidental drug overdose-
unintentional administration of a drug (set at an amount higher 
than the normal recommended therapeutic dose, that has the 
potential to cause harm, e.g., a young child or an adult with 
impaired mental abilities swallowing medication left within 
their grasp or an adult mistakenly taking an incorrect drug or 
dose) [3]. (4) Intentional drug overdose-deliberate admin-
istration of a drug at an amount higher than the normal rec-
ommended dose, that has the potential to cause harm (e.g., for 
the purpose of self-harm, suicide attempts, or to achieve 
euphoric state) [3]. (5) Untreated indication-when the chief 
presenting complaint is related to a disease or condition that 
requires a drug therapy and the patient did not seek or receive 
such therapy (possibly due to mental illness or ignorance of 
the disease condition) [3]. </p>

<p> 
A. I. Jatau et al. </p>

<p>Preventability was evaluated based on three categories 
[18]: (1) Preventable-the drug-related ED visit was the 
result of misuse of a drug, inappropriate discontinuation of 
treatment, non-adherence, or self-medication; (2) Possibly 
preventable-the visit was due to failure to monitor drug 
therapy or an error in prescribing, dispensing, or adminis-
tration; or (3) Not preventable-the ADE occurred during 
compliance with good drug utilization. 
The severity of drug-related ED visits was classified 
according to the following criteria [19]: (1) Mild-a lab-
oratory abnormality or the symptom did not require drug 
intervention, (2) Moderate-a laboratory abnormality or 
symptom that required drug intervention at the ED, (3) 
Severe-the symptom required hospital admission, was 
life-threatening, or resulted in permanent disability. 
The outcome of the drug-related ED visit was categorized 
into three groups: (1) discharged immediately after consulta-
tion with the ED physician, (2) admitted to the ED-observa-
tion ward for a maximum of 72 h, and (3) admitted to a 
hospital ward through the ED. Drug classification was per-
formed according to <rs id="software-3" type="software">MIMS</rs>.com Malaysia version <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">1.3.0</rs> [20]. </p>

<p>2.5 Sample Size Calculation </p>

<p>The sample size was calculated using a single proportion 
formula [21], adopting 38.0 % as the expected proportion 
of population with ADE-related ED visits, as per previous 
literature [22]; a 0.05 significance (alpha) level at a 95 % 
confidence interval (CI); and taking into consideration the 
20 % of included patients who would leave without seeing 
a physician. A sample size of 434 was calculated. </p>

<p>2.6 Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using statistical software (<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> ver-
sion <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">21</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). The prevalence of 
ADE-related ED visits was calculated by dividing the 
number of patients with ADE-related ED visits by the total 
sample size. Descriptive analysis of socio-demographic, 
clinical, and drug-related variables was conducted. Results 
were presented as frequency (percentage) for categorical 
variables and mean (standard deviation [SD]) for numerical 
variables. The Chi squared goodness-of-fit test was used to 
determine the distribution of cases in a single categorical 
variable at a 0.05 significance (alpha) level. </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>There was a total of 7530 ED visits over the 6-week period; 
3573 patients came to the ED between 09:00 am and 
05:00 pm Sunday to Thursday. Of the 1162 patients 
selected for the study, 728 were excluded, for the following </p>

<p>reasons: referral from other hospital (n = 714); scheduled 
visit (n = 8); declined to participate (n = 4); and medico-
legal cases (n = 2). Therefore, 434 eligible patients were 
interviewed. The number of ED physician-identified ADE-
related ED visits was 133 (30.6 %; 95 % CI 26-35 %). 
Table 1 illustrates the characteristics of the patients with an 
ADE-related ED visit. The mean (SD) age of the patients 
with an ADE-related ED visit was 41.0 (21.58) years. Of 
the 133 patients, 62 % were female and 96.0 % were of 
Malay ethnicity. The proportion of patients with formal 
education was 66.9 %, and 70 % of participants were 
married. A total of 110 patients (82.7 %) were currently 
taking medications at the time of the ED visit; 17 (12.8 %) 
claimed use of one or more different modalities of CAM. 
The most commonly reported chronic diseases among 
patients with an ADE-related visit were diabetes mellitus 
(DM) (n = 55; 41.4 %); hypertension (n = 54; 40.6 %); 
and asthma (n = 13; 9.7 %) (A person could have more 
than one chronic disease). 
Five categories of ADE were reported: (1) DTF 
(n = 74; 55.6 %), (2) ADR (n = 43; 32.3 %), (3) acci-
dental drug overdose (n = 7; 5.2 %), (4) intentional drug 
overdose (n = 6; 4.5 %), and (5) untreated indication 
(n = 3; 3.2 %). Female patients dominated in most of the 
ADE categories. The prevalence of DTF, ADR, and acci-
dental overdose was higher among the elderly population 
(C60 years). Medication non-adherence was found to be 
the major cause of DTF (81.1 %). Table 2 demonstrates 
the prevalence of different categories of ADE among sex 
and age categories. 
Of the 133 ADE-related ED visits, 74 (55.6 %) were 
considered preventable, with DTF due to medication non-
adherence accounting for 85.3 %. A total of 41 (30.8 %) of 
ADE-related ED visits were classed as severe, with DTF 
due to medication non-adherence responsible for 41.5 % of 
this level of severity. There was no report of permanent 
disability or death from these visits. Of the subjects, 25 
(18.8 %) were discharged immediately after consultation 
with the ED physician, 93 (69.9 %) were admitted to the 
ED-observation ward for a maximum of 72 h, and 15 
(11.3 %) were admitted to a hospital ward from the ED. 
Admission to the ED-observation ward was mainly due to 
hypoglycemia secondary to antidiabetic therapy (n = 10; 
10.8 %), uncontrolled DM (n = 10; 10.8 %), and hyper-
tensive urgency (n = 9; 9.7 %). Admission to the hospital 
ward was mostly due to uncontrolled DM (n = 2; 13.3 %). 
A total of 45 individual drugs and 18 drug combinations 
were involved in the 133 ADE-related ED visits. The most 
frequently implicated drugs were antidiabetics (n = 31; 
23.3 %), antihypertensives (n = 28; 21.1 %), antibiotics 
(n = 13; 9.8 %), anti-asthmatics (n = 11; 8.3 %), and 
diuretics (n = 8; 6.0 %). The most frequent single drugs 
reported were insulin (n = 13; 9.8 %), furosemide (n = 7; </p>

<p>Drug-Related ED Visits in Malaysia </p>

<p>
2.3 %), salbutamol (n = 6; 4.5 %), and gliclazide (n = 5; 
3.8 %). The drug combinations most involved were 
amoxicillin ? clavulanic acid (n = 4; 3.0 %) and 
rifampicin ? isoniazid (n = 3; 2.3 %). 
The most common complaints among patients with ADE-
related ED visits were fatigue, irritability, sweating, uncon-
sciousness, hypertension, skin reactions, upper gastroin-
testinal bleeding, palpitations, giddiness, shortness of breath, 
tarry stools, abnormal behavior, chest pain, convulsions, 
lethargy, edema, and Stevens-Johnson Syndrome (SJS). </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to determine the 
prevalence of ADE-related ED visits at a teaching hospital 
in Malaysia. A prevalence of 30.6 % (95 % CI 26-35) for 
ADE-related ED visits was determined within the 6-week 
period. More than one-half of the ADEs were determined 
to have been preventable, and almost one-third had a 
severe outcome. The prevalence rate found in the current 
study is consistent with results of previous studies </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographic 
characteristics of cases with 
adverse drug event-related 
emergency department visit </p>

<p>Patient characteristics 
Mean age (SD) 
Frequency (%), n = 133 
P value </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Age (years) </p>

<p>B9 
4 (3.0) 
\0.001 </p>

<p>10-19 
4 (3.0) </p>

<p>20-29 
18 (13.5) </p>

<p>30-39 
14 (10.5) </p>

<p>40-49 
20 (15.0) </p>

<p>50-59 
28 (21.1) </p>

<p>C60 
45 (33.8) </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Male 
44.45 (21.14) 
50 (38.0) 
0.015 </p>

<p>Female 
51.35 (16.50) 
83 (62.0) </p>

<p>Marital status </p>

<p>Single 
37 (28.0) 
0.003 </p>

<p>Married 
93 (70.0) </p>

<p>Divorced 
3 (2.0) 
Ethnicity </p>

<p>Malay 
128 (96.0) 
0.438 </p>

<p>Chinese 
5 (4.0) </p>

<p>Education status </p>

<p>None 
44 (33.1) 
0.001 </p>

<p>Yes 
89 (66.9) </p>

<p>Current drug use 
110 (82.7) 
0.522 </p>

<p>Male 
40 (36.4) </p>

<p>Female 
70 (63.6) </p>

<p>Preventability </p>

<p>Preventable 
74 (55.5) </p>

<p>Possibly preventable 
15 (11.3) </p>

<p>Not preventable 
44 (33.1) </p>

<p>Severity </p>

<p>Mild 
2 (1.5) </p>

<p>Moderate 
90 (67.7) 
Severe 
41 (30.8) </p>

<p>Outcome of the visit </p>

<p>Discharged immediately 
25 (18.8) </p>

<p>Admitted to ED 
93 (69.9) </p>

<p>Admitted to the ward 
15 (11.3) </p>

<p>ED emergency department, SD standard deviation 
a Chi square goodness of fit </p>

<p> 
A. I. Jatau et al. </p>

<p>conducted in Spain and the USA using a similar study 
design and population (28.1-33.2 %) [23-26]. In contrast, 
the prevalence rate was higher than in other studies per-
formed in England, Finland, Canada, and Taiwan, which 
were in the range of 0.77-4.0 % [24, 27-30]. In the current 
study, the rate of ADE-related admissions to the ward 
through the ED was 11.3 %, which is similar to rates found 
in a study conducted in Malaysia (12.7 %) [31]. The high 
prevalence rate found in this study may be due to a broader 
definition of ADE, eligibility criteria, and study population 
used. This was adopted to ensure a comprehensive 
knowledge of ADE-related hospitalization. Moreover, the 
high proportion of patients with DTF may also be 
responsible for the high prevalence rate. 
In the current study, the proportion of female patients 
found to be associated with ADE-related ED visits and 
currently receiving medications was higher than that of 
male patients. This was in agreement with previous studies 
[27, 32, 33]. The female sex has been identified as a risk 
factor associated with ADE-related ED visits [23, 25, 34,  35]. This is possibly due to the increased bioavailability of 
drugs, greater sensitivity of female target organs to drugs, 
and polypharmacy due to gender-specific treatments [36]. 
ADE-related complaints at the ED in the current study 
were higher among the elderly. This was consistent with 
findings of previous studies [4, 7, 24, 37]. This could 
possibly be because the body's ability to handle drugs 
diminishes with age, leading to changes in drug pharma-
cokinetics, altered organ responses, and homeostatic 
counter-regulation to drug effects [38]. More patients 
without formal education had ADE-related ED visits than </p>

<p>patients with higher education. Similar studies have shown 
that patients with a higher level of education have a better 
perception of the risks of ADEs [39]. A higher level of 
education brings a greater conscious awareness of the risks 
associated with drug use. Many previous studies on 
prevalence of ADEs did not evaluate marital status [13]. 
However, our study reveals a significant difference in ADE 
occurrence within married, divorced, and single patients, 
with a married population having a higher percentage of 
patients with ADE-related ED visits. Similarly, Chri-
schilles et al. [40, 41] and Hema et al. [40, 41] also found 
that a higher proportion of patients with ADE were mar-
ried. An explanation for this within the current study may 
be that over 40 % of the patients with ADEs were elderly 
and more than one-half were females, who were earlier 
found to have a higher incidence of ADE-related 
hospitalization. 
The ADE category with the highest prevalence rate in 
the current study was DTF, which accounted for more than 
one-half of ADE-related ED visits. This is consistent with a 
similar study conducted in a hospital ward in Malaysia 
[22]. In the current study, medication non-adherence was 
the major cause of DTF-related ED visits. The prevalence 
rate of DTF due to medication non-adherence reported was 
higher than that found in previous studies [8, 15, 42-44]. 
This variation may be due to more patients with chronic 
diseases visiting our ED with ADE-related complaints. 
However, patients with underlying chronic illness were 
found to have a higher chance of medication non-adher-
ence [43]. Another reason for the higher prevalence rate of 
DTF due to medication non-adherence may be associated </p>

<p>Table 2 Categories of adverse drug events among sex and age categories </p>

<p>Categories of adverse drug event, n (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P value </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>DTF 
ADR 
Accidental drug overdose 
Intentional drug overdose 
Untreated indication </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Male 
30 (40.5) 
12 (27.9) 
4 (57.1) 
4 (66.7) 
0 (0.0) 
0.160 </p>

<p>Female 
44 (59.5) 
31 (72.1) 
3 (42.1) 
2 (33.3) 
3 (100) </p>

<p>Age category (years) </p>

<p>B9 
3 (1.6) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (14.3) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
\0.001 </p>

<p>10-19 
1 (0.0) 
2 (4.7) 
1 (14.3) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (33.3) </p>

<p>20-29 
6 (9.5) 
8 (18.6) 
0 (0.0) 
3 (50.0) 
0 (0.0) 
30-39 
8 (11.1) 
5 (11.6) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (16.7) 
2 (66.7) </p>

<p>40-49 
7 (9.5) 
8 (18.6) 
1 (14.3) 
2 (33.3) 
0 (0.0) </p>

<p>50-59 
22 (31.7) 
5 (11.6) 
1 (14.3) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) </p>

<p>C60 
27 (36.5) 
15 (34.9) 
3 (42.9) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) </p>

<p>Prevalence </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>17.0 
9.9 
1.6 
1.4 
0.7 </p>

<p>ADR adverse drug reaction, DTF drug therapeutic failure 
a Frequency is calculated as the number of cases in 133 patients with adverse drug event-related emergency department visits </p>

<p>b Chi squared goodness of fit </p>

<p>c Prevalence is calculated as the percentage of cases with adverse drug events in the sample size (434) </p>

<p>Drug-Related ED Visits in Malaysia </p>

<p>
with the busy and overcrowded nature of some public 
hospitals in Malaysia, which may not allow adequate 
patient counseling, especially regarding medication 
adherence [45, 46]. Medication non-adherence has become 
a silent burden of healthcare [39, 44, 47]; thus, many 
intervention measures have been made to improve adher-
ence to increase patient safety. Such interventions include 
patient education via verbal and written instructions, 
illustrations, and audiovisuals by healthcare providers, and 
reminders such as medication calendars, medication 
schedule alerts, stickers, box alarms, and pill timers. In 
Malaysia, efforts have been made to improve medication 
adherence, including the use of short message alerts, called 
<rs type="software">MySMS</rs> 
Ò , in some hospitals [48] and the establishment of 
Medication Therapy Adherence Clinic (MTAC) services 
operated by pharmacists in some public hospitals. These 
services have resulted in significant improvements in 
medication adherence [49]. Studies have shown that 
pharmacist interventions have played a major role in 
improving medication adherence, especially among 
patients with chronic illness. The pharmacist is an expert 
on drugs and has the skills and expertise to improve 
medication adherence and potentially minimize the 
prevalence of DTF-related ED visits [50, 51]. More inter-
vention measures are needed to improve medication 
adherence. 
In the current study, ADRs account for one-third of the 
ADE-related ED visits. This rate is consistent with similar 
studies conducted in India [52] and in hospital wards in 
Malaysia and Germany [33, 38]. Hypoglycemia was the 
most common complaint associated with ADRs, mainly 
related to antidiabetic therapy (gliclazide and insulin). The 
high rate of ADRs in the current study may be explained by 
the poor ADR monitoring and reporting system in 
Malaysia. Despite the establishment of the Malaysian 
Adverse Drug Reaction Advisory Committee (MADRAC) 
in 1987 to receive and monitor ADR reporting, the 
response is still very low compared with other countries 
[53]. Reports have identified some of the factors associated 
with under-reporting of ADRs in Malaysia, including (1) 
lack of awareness on the importance of and the need for 
ADR monitoring and reporting, (2) uncertainty about 
whether or not the event was an ADR, (3) opinion that the 
reaction was too trivial or well known to report, (4) lack of 
knowledge on how to report, and (5) inadequate time for 
reporting [54]. If ADRs are not reported, then, predictably, 
the extent of the occurrence, the people at risk, and the 
drugs involved will not be well known. As such, preventive 
interventions will be hampered, leading to increasing 
numbers of ADRs. Another reason for the high ADR 
prevalence rate in our study may be related to the current 
treatment guidelines for DM and the poor glycemic control </p>

<p>associated with oral antidiabetic drugs. In Malaysia, 
prevalence of DM is high, at 20 % [55, 56], and the 
majority of patients have experienced sub-optimal gly-
cemic control with oral hypoglycemic drugs. Thus, early 
insulin therapy has been included in the current treatment 
guidelines for DM, and this has led to increased levels of 
insulin use [57, 58]. However, this may be responsible for 
the high prevalence of ADRs related to insulin-induced 
hypoglycemia in the current study. Healthcare providers 
should therefore discuss and monitor insulin therapy with 
their patient, with regards to possible ADRs and how to 
manage hypoglycemia associated with the therapy. 
More than one-half of the ADEs identified were pre-
ventable, with over 80 % contributed by DTF and 50 % by 
females. This is similar to results found in Saudi Arabia 
and Canada [12, 19, 59]. These findings signal the possi-
bility of preventing more ADEs by improving medication 
adherence and minimizing other preventable ADEs iden-
tified. Healthcare professionals and policy makers should 
therefore focus their attention, efforts, and resources to the 
identified preventable ADEs to improve patient safety [60]. 
In the current study, almost one-third and two-thirds of 
the ADE-related ED visits were severe and moderately 
severe, respectively; this is similar to findings in other 
studies [26, 61]. A high proportion of females experienced 
severe outcomes from ADEs due to ADRs and DTF, which 
is also consistent with previous studies [42, 62]. These 
findings have shown the healthcare challenges posed by 
DTF and ADRs, and hence, the urgent need for interven-
tions to prevent further occurrences. There were no reports 
of death or permanent disability within the current study, 
although two patients presented with SJS, involving oral 
cloxacillin and a topical skincare cream containing colla-
gen (Dnarz </p>

<p>Ò </p>

<p>). This is similar to a retrospective cohort 
study among patients of Asian descent, which found 
cloxacillin to be among the drugs causing SJS [63]. The 
pathogenesis of SJS was believed to be due to genetic 
susceptibility, therefore, more pharmacogenomics studies 
are needed to determine the drugs and groups of people at 
high risk of SJS [63]. 
In the current study, more than two-thirds of the cases 
were admitted to the ED-observation ward and experienced 
more severe ADEs. Most presented with hypoglycemic and 
hypertensive symptoms associated with anti-diabetic and 
antihypertensive use. Therefore, a need exists for a clinical 
pharmacist in the ED, for adequate detection, reporting, 
and preventing of ADEs. Pharmacists, as drug experts, 
specialize in recognizing ADEs in all clinical settings. 
Consequently, most physicians lack adequate knowledge 
and expertise to detect and report ADEs, and it has been 
reported that over 40 % of ADEs presented at EDs were 
misdiagnosed by ED physicians [64]. </p>

<p> 
A. I. Jatau et al. </p>

<p>The classes of drug most frequently implicated were 
anti-diabetics, cardiovascular system agents, central ner-
vous system agents, antibiotics, anti-asthmatics, and 
diuretics, similar to findings from other studies [15, 61, 65- 68]. This may be associated with the higher number of 
patients with chronic illness reported in the study. Insulin, 
furosemide, salbutamol, gliclazide, and amlodipine were 
the most commonly reported drugs. Similar studies have 
shown that these drugs have been associated with an 
increased likelihood of ADE-related ED visits [50, 69, 70]. 
Amphetamine was commonly associated with intentional 
drug overdose among male patients. This indicates a need 
for close monitoring and patient counseling when pre-
scribing and dispensing such drugs given their potential to 
cause ADEs leading to ED visits. 
Limitations of this study include that it was limited to 
one hospital, and the findings may not be generalized to a 
larger population in Malaysia. In addition, the study period, 
sample, and lack of internal validation of ADEs could 
further affect the results reported. </p>

<p>5 Conclusion </p>

<p>The prevalence of ADE-related ED visits in Malaysia is 
high. More than one-half of these visits were pre-
ventable and due to DTF. Medication non-adherence was 
the major cause of DTF and was responsible for the high 
percentage of severe ADEs admitted to the ED-observation 
ward. This indicates the need for an effective intervention 
strategy, such as patient education on drug utilization, 
engaging the services of a clinical pharmacist at the ED, 
and other measures targeted at preventable ADEs to 
improve patient safety. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments The authors would like to thank the physicians 
on duty at the HUSM ED during the period of study. The assistance of 
the nurses and other paramedics is gratefully acknowledged. </p>

<p>Compliance with Ethical Standards </p>

<p>The study was approved by the ethics committee of Universiti Sultan 
Zainal Abidin (UniSZA) and Universiti Sains Malaysia (USM) and 
has been performed in accordance with the ethical standards of the 
Declaration of Helsinki. Informed consent was obtained from all 
individual participants included in the study. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest Pharm Abubakar Ibrahim Jatau, Dr Myat Moe 
Thwe Aung, Dr Tuan Hairulnizam Tuan Kamauzan and Prof Ab 
Fatah Ab Rahman all declare that they have no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Funding No specific funding was received for this research. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which per-
mits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any </p>

<p>medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original 
author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons 
license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p>Drug-Related ED Visits in Malaysia </p>



<p>
 
A. I. Jatau et al. </p>



<p>Drug-Related ED Visits in Malaysia </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>