<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4925014" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Previous studies have revealed that a population of innate memory CD8 
+ T cells is generated in response to IL-4, first appearing 
in the thymus and bearing high expression levels of Eomesodermin (Eomes) but not T-bet. However, the antigen specificity and 
functional properties of these cells is poorly defined. In this study, we show that IL-4 regulates not only the frequency and 
function of innate memory CD8 
+ T cells, but also regulates Eomes expression levels and functional reactivity of naive CD8 
+ T 
cells. Lack of IL-4 responsiveness attenuates the capacity of CD8 
+ T cells to mount a robust response to lymphocytic chorio-
meningitis virus infection, with both quantitative and qualitative effects on effector and memory antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cells. 
Unexpectedly, we found that, although numerically rare, memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells in IL-4Rα-deficient mice exhibited 
enhanced reactivity after in vitro and in vivo stimulation. Importantly, our data revealed that these effects of IL-4 exposure 
occur before, not during, infection. Together, these data show that IL-4 influences the entire peripheral CD8 
+ T cell pool, in-
fluencing expression of T-box transcription factors, functional reactivity, and the capacity to respond to infection. These 
findings indicate that IL-4, a canonical Th2 cell cytokine, can sometimes promote rather than impair Th1 cell-type immune 
responses. </p>

<p>IL-4 responsiveness regulates CD8 
+ T cell function | Renkema et al. 
1320 </p>

<p>effector program, and in established memory CD8 
+ T cells, 
T-bet and Eomes cooperate to promote IL-2Rβ (CD122) 
expression, which is required for memory cell homeostasis 
(Kaech and Cui, 2012). However, the two transcription fac-
tors also have nonredundant roles and different expression 
profiles in short-lived effector cells (SLECs) versus memory 
precursor effector cells (MPECs): High expression levels of 
T-bet promotes terminal effector cell differentiation, whereas 
Eomes expression levels peak in memory CD8 
+ T cells, and 
Eomes is required for efficient production of central memory 
CD8 
+ T cells (Joshi et al., 2007; Banerjee et al., 2010; Rao et  al., 2010), as well as innate memory CD8 
+ T cells (Weinreich  et al., 2009; Sosinowski et al., 2013). 
Although the role of IL-4 in inducing innate memory 
CD8 
+ T cells in the thymus has been well studied, little is 
known about how the response to IL-4 shapes homeostasis 
and function of the peripheral CD8 
+ T cell pool. This is im-
portant to assess because some studies have shown that mem-
ory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells generated through homeostatic 
mechanisms act by inhibiting rather than enhancing the 
T cell immune response (Rifa'i et al., 2004; Lin et al., 2007;  Dai et al., 2010; Kim et al., 2010, 2011; Sakuraba et al., 2013). 
Here, we show that responsiveness to IL-4 during CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cell development and homeostasis leads to diverse changes 
in functional response and gene expression not only of mem-
ory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells, but also of naive CD8 
+ T cells. 
Although IL-4Rα-deficient memory phenotype CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells exhibited low Eomes expression, our data unex-
pectedly revealed that these cells had enhanced capacity to 
produce inflammatory cytokines in vitro and expand to lym-
phocytic choriomeningitis virus (LCMV) infection in vivo. 
These data suggest that a lack of IL-4 sensitivity chiefly com-
promises the numbers rather than intrinsic function of mem-
ory-like cells. Through adoptive transfer studies, we could also 
show that sensitivity to IL-4 encounter during the response 
to LCMV was not necessary to support an effective CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cell response, suggesting that the impact of IL-4 is pri-
marily through its effects on CD8 
+ T cell development and 
homeostasis. Collectively, our results indicate that IL-4 has 
diverse effects on the phenotype and function of the whole 
peripheral CD8 
+ T cell population and that IL-4 responsive-
ness enhances the CD8 
+ T cell response to pathogens. </p>

<p>RES ULTS 
IL-4 responsiveness dictates the frequency of innate 
memory CD8 
+ T cells in secondary lymphoid tissues 
Innate (bystander) memory CD8 
+ T cells are generated in 
the thymus of certain mouse strains in a process depen-
dent on IL-4 produced by NK T cells and IL-4 sensitivity 
by CD8 
+ T cells themselves (Weinreich et al., 2010; Lee et  al., 2013b). However, it is less clear whether and how IL-4 
reactivity affects the peripheral pool of memory phenotype 
CD8 
+ T cells. We initially compared the CD8 
+ T cell pools 
from spleen and lymph nodes of naive WT and IL-4Rα KO 
BALB/cByJ mice. Although the total numbers of lympho-</p>

<p>cytes were similar (Fig. 1 A), IL-4Rα KO mice exhibited 
a decreased frequency of CD8 
+ T cells (Fig. 1 B), leading 
to reduced numbers of CD8 
+ T cells (Fig. 1 C). Preliminary 
studies indicated total lymphocyte numbers in IL-4Rα KO 
mice were normalized by an increased frequency of B cells 
(not depicted). Using CD44 and CXCR3 surface expres-
sion as markers (Ventre et al., 2012), we differentiated the 
CD8 
+ T cell pool into three populations: naive phenotype 
(CD44 
lo CXR3 </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>), memory phenotype (CD44 
hi CXCR3 
hi ), 
and an intermediate phenotype (CD44 
hi CXCR3 </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>) popula-
tion (gating shown in Fig. 1 D). IL-4Rα KO mice had de-
creased frequencies of memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells in 
the periphery, with reciprocal increased frequencies of naive 
phenotype cells, compared with WT (Fig. 1 E). These differ-
ences resulted in a substantial decrease in memory phenotype 
CD8 
+ T cell numbers (and slightly fewer intermediate cells), 
whereas the number of naive CD8 
+ T cells increased in IL-
4Rα KO mice (Fig. 1 F). To determine whether the impact of 
IL-4 responsiveness was cell extrinsic or intrinsic, we gener-
ated mixed BM chimeras, in which congenically distinct IL-
4Rα KO and WT BM cells were coinjected to reconstitute 
lethally irradiated hosts. As in the intact mice, the frequency of 
memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells was significantly reduced in 
the IL-4Rα KO donor population, whereas naive phenotype 
CD8 
+ T cells frequencies were increased (Fig. 1 G), demon-
strating that these effects reflect a cell-intrinsic role for IL-
4Rα on CD8 
+ T cells (as was found for thymic IL-4-induced 
memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells [Weinreich et al., 2009]). 
It was possible that IL-4Rα deficiency caused a reduc-
tion in conventional rather than innate memory phenotype 
CD8 
+ T cells. We and others have shown that a significant 
fraction of C57BL/6 CD8 
+ T cells specific for varied for-
eign antigens exhibit a memory phenotype despite no pre-
vious exposure to those antigens; this population of innate 
memory cells has also been called virtual memory CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells (Haluszczak et al., 2009; La Gruta et al., 2010). This 
population was only modestly reduced in IL-4-or IL-4Rα-
deficient C57BL/6 mice (Akue et al., 2012; Sosinowski et al.,  2013), but it was unclear whether the much larger popula-
tion of IL-4-dependent memory-like cells in BALB/c mice 
included virtual memory cells. To address this, we performed 
tetramer enrichment assays to isolate antigen-specific CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cell populations in unimmunized WT and IL-4Rα KO 
BALB/c mice. Total numbers of CD8 
+ T cells specific for 
the L 
d -restricted LCMV nucleoprotein 118-126 (NP 118-126 ) 
epitope and the K 
d -restricted Listeria monocytogenes liste-
riolysin O 91-99 (LLO 91-99 ) epitope were modestly reduced 
in IL-4Rα-deficient BALB/c mice (Fig. 2, A and C). On 
resolution of phenotypic subsets, it became apparent that 
the numbers of foreign antigen-specific naive CD8 
+ T cells 
were not significantly changed in unimmunized WT and IL-
4Rα-deficient mice but that numbers of both memory and 
intermediate phenotype cells were reduced in the IL-4Rα 
KO animals (Fig. 2, B and D). Similar findings were observed 
when L 
d /NP 118-126 -specific CD8 
+ T cells were characterized </p>

<p> 
JEM Vol. 213, No. 7 </p>

<p>from the spleens of WT, IL-4Rα KO, and IL-4 KO animals 
(not depicted). These results indicate that our findings for the 
bulk CD8 
+ T cell pool also apply to precursors specific for 
unencountered antigens. Together, these results indicate that 
IL-4Rα expression by CD8 
+ T cells is important for the gen-
eration and/or maintenance of innate memory phenotype 
CD8 
+ T cells in peripheral tissues. </p>

<p>IL-4 receptor regulates Eomes expression in peripheral 
memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells 
The T-box transcription factors T-bet and Eomes play a cru-
cial role in activated CD8 
+ T cell fate and function. Antigen-
induced memory CD8 
+ T cells and innate memory CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells in C57BL/6 mice express both Eomes and T-bet (Lee  et al., 2013a). In contrast, the thymic innate memory popula-
tion in BALB/c mice is characterized by high Eomes expres-
sion and low T-bet expression (Weinreich et al., 2010). It is 
unclear, however, whether this Eomes 
hi , T-bet 
lo phenotype is 
a unique feature of thymic innate memory phenotype CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells and how IL-4 responsiveness impacts T-box factor ex-
pression by naive and memory phenotype peripheral CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells in BALB/c mice. Hence, we measured expression of 
Eomes and T-bet by CD8 
+ T cells from the spleen and lymph </p>

<p>nodes of WT and IL-4Rα KO BALB/cByJ mice (Fig. 3 A). As 
we reported for thymic innate memory CD8 
+ T cells (Wein-
reich et al., 2010), BALB/c peripheral memory phenotype 
CD8 
+ T cells were Eomes 
hi and T-bet </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>. In contrast, IL-4Rα 
deficiency resulted in reduced Eomes and elevated T-bet ex-
pression by memory phenotype cells. Unexpectedly, analysis 
of IL-4Rα KO mice also revealed reduced Eomes expression 
(and moderately increased T-bet expression) in the naive and 
intermediate phenotype CD8 
+ T cell populations (Fig. 3, B 
and C). This conclusion was supported when Eomes 
hi and Eo-
mes 
lo peaks were analyzed separately; Eomes expression levels 
were higher in WT versus IL-4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cells within 
these populations (not depicted). It was possible that IL-4Rα-
dependent Eomes expression by CD8 
+ T cell subsets was not 
caused by IL-4 sensitivity by CD8 
+ T cells themselves. Hence, 
we again examined mixed BM chimeras (as in Fig. 1) and 
found that Eomes expression was highly dependent on IL-
4Rα expression by CD8 
+ T cells (Fig. 3 D), indicating a CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cell-intrinsic role of IL-4 sensitivity. Again, measuring the 
Eomes expression level after gating on Eomes 
hi and Eomes </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>populations confirmed this conclusion (not depicted). In con-
trast, the elevated T-bet expression observed in CD8 
+ T cell 
subsets of intact IL-4Rα KO mice was not reliably observed in </p>

<p>Figure 1. IL-4Rα expression is required for genera-
tion/maintenance of bystander memory CD8 
+ T cells 
in the periphery. (A-C) Combined spleen and lymph 
node lymphocytes from age-matched WT BALB/cByJ and 
IL-4Rα KO BALB/cByJ were analyzed for total lymphocyte 
count (A), frequency (B), and total number of CD8 
+ T cells 
(C). (D-F) As shown in D, CD8 
+ T cells were segregated 
into three populations based on CD44 and CXCR3 expres-
sion. The frequency (E) and number (F) of CD44 
lo CXCR3 </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>, 
CD44 
hi CXCR3 </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>, and CD44 
hi CXCR3 
hi CD8 
+ T cells was de-
termined in WT and IL-4Rα KO BALB/cByJ mice. (G) Mixed 
BM chimeras were generated by introducing WT and IL-
4Rα KO BALB/cByJ donor BM into lethally irradiated WT 
BALB/cByJ hosts. Chimeric mice were bled 8 wk later, and 
the frequency of CD8 
+ T cells with the indicated CD44/ 
CXCR3 phenotype was determined for both donor popu-
lations. Error bars indicate mean ± SD. P-values are rep-
resented as *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.001; ****, P &lt; 
0.0001 by unpaired (A-C, E, and F) or paired (G) Student's 
t test for BM chimeras. (A-C) Data are combined from two 
separate experiments (n = 9 for WT, n = 8 for IL-4Rα KO) 
and are representative of five experiments. (D-F) n = 4 for 
WT and n = 4 for IL-4Rα KO, and data are representative 
of five experiments. (G) n = 7 for mixed BM chimeras, and 
data are representative of three experiments. </p>

<p>IL-4 responsiveness regulates CD8 
+ T cell function | Renkema et al. </p>

<p>
IL-4Rα-deficient cells from the mixed BM chimeras 
(Fig. 3 E), suggesting this effect was not cell autonomous. 
Together, these data show that IL-4 sensitivity is re-
quired for maximal Eomes expression not only by memory 
phenotype BALB/c CD8 
+ T cells, but also in naive (and 
intermediate) phenotype CD8 
+ T cells. These findings in-
dicate that IL-4 influences gene expression in the entire pe-
ripheral CD8 
+ T cell pool. </p>

<p>IL-4 responsiveness influences cytokine and effector 
molecule production by stimulated CD8 
+ T cells 
CD8 
+ T cells with high expression of Eomes and low expres-
sion of T-bet have been associated with not only differenti-
ation of functionally potent memory CD8 
+ T cells in acute 
infection models (Banerjee et al., 2010), but also with terminal 
differentiation of exhausted CD8 
+ T cells in chronic infection 
studies (Paley et al., 2012). Hence, the functional impact of 
altered Eomes and T-bet ratios observed in WT and IL-4Rα-
deficient BALB/c CD8 
+ T cells is difficult to predict. </p>

<p>To address this, we first measured cytokine produc-
tion after T cell activation in vitro. We and others previously 
showed that IL-4-induced memory phenotype cells in the 
thymus were capable of rapid IFN-γ production upon TCR 
stimulation; however, these studies entailed comparison with 
the response of IL-4 KO or IL-4Rα KO CD4 
− CD8 
+ thy-
mocytes, which are dominated by naive phenotype cells 
(Weinreich et al., 2010; Lai et al., 2011). A direct comparison 
between the responses of naive and memory CD8 
+ subsets in 
WT and IL-4Rα-deficient BALB/c mice has not been care-
fully investigated. First, we stimulated bulk CD8 
+ T cells from 
peripheral lymphoid tissues of WT and IL-4Rα KO mice 
with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 and assayed production of the 
inflammatory cytokines TNF and IFN-γ. Unexpectedly, de-
spite the increased frequency of memory phenotype CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells in WT animals, similar frequencies of WT and IL-
4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cells produced IFN-γ at 6-and 24-h time 
points, and a greater proportion of IL-4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cells 
expressed TNF at 6 h (a time point chosen because this cyto-
kine is produced early after stimulation; Fig. 4 A; Badovinac et 
al., 2000). These findings prompted us to study the responses 
of WT and IL-4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cell subpopulations. Hence, 
we next sorted the three CD8 
+ T cell subsets (see Fig. 1) and 
tested their individual responses to T cell activation (Fig. 4, 
B-D). Similar to the bulk populations (Fig. 4 A), IL-4Rα 
KO CD8 
+ T cells from all three subsets showed an increased 
frequency of TNF-producing cells compared with their WT 
counterparts (Fig. 4 B). Interestingly, at 24 h of stimulation, 
we observed increased percentages of IFN-γ-producing cells 
from all three subsets of CD8 
+ T cells derived from IL-4Rα 
KO animals relative to WT (Fig. 4 D). This result was not 
caused by altered kinetics of IFN-γ expression by WT ver-
sus IL-4Rα-deficient populations because a significantly 
higher fraction of IL-4Rα KO CD8 
+ memory phenotype 
T cells produced IFN-γ even at 6 h of stimulation (a time 
point at which very few CXCR3 </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>/CD44 
hi/lo populations 
expressed IFN-γ; Fig. 4 C). 
These data suggest that the reduced frequency of mem-
ory phenotype and Eomes 
hi CD8 
+ T cell populations in 
IL-4Rα-deficient mice may be partially offset by increased 
functional reactivity, at least in terms of inflammatory cyto-
kine production. Hence, we next sought to investigate the 
consequences of these differences by tracking the in vivo re-
sponse of WT and IL-4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cells to infection. </p>

<p>IL-4 sensitivity regulates the CD8 
+ T cell response 
to acute viral infection 
The role for IL-4 in regulating the CD8 
+ T cell response to 
infection is unclear. IL-4 reactivity was proposed to be import-
ant for optimal effector (Carvalho et al., 2002) and memory 
(Morrot et al., 2005) CD8 
+ T cell responses to a mouse model 
of malaria. However, IL-4 signaling may inhibit polyfunctional 
responses to viral infection (Wijesundara et al., 2013) and may 
reduce activation of memory CD8 
+ T cells after in vitro re-
stimulation (Ventre et al., 2012). To investigate whether IL-4 </p>

<p>Figure 2. IL-4Rα expression is required for normal numbers of anti-
gen-specific memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cell precursors. (A-D) Tetramer 
enrichment was performed on spleen and lymph nodes from individual 
age-matched WT BALB/cByJ and IL-4Rα KO BALB/cByJ using tetramers 
containing LCMV NP 118-126 /L 
d (labeled NP 118-126 Tet </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) and L. monocytogenes 
LLO 91-99 /K 
d (labeled LLO 91-99 Tet </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>). The total numbers of tetramer-binding 
cells (A and C) and the numbers of cells in the indicated phenotypic subsets 
(B and D) are indicated. Each data point represents cells recovered from 
an individual mouse. Error bars indicate mean ± SD. P-values are repre-
sented as *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ****, P &lt; 0.0001 by unpaired Student's 
t test. Data are combined from two separate experiments (experiment 1: 
n = 5 for WT, n = 4 for IL-4Rα KO; experiment 2: n = 4 for WT, n = 4 for 
IL-4Rα KO) and are representative of four experiments (n = 15 for WT, n = 
15 IL-4Rα KO in total). </p>

<p> 
JEM Vol. 213, No. 7 </p>

<p>sensitivity impacted the CD8 
+ T cell response to infection, 
we infected WT and IL-4Rα KO mice with an acute viral 
pathogen, LCMV Armstrong, and tracked the response of L 
d / 
NP 118-126 -specific CD8 
+ T cells, as well as the bulk CD8 
+ T cell 
pool. In part, we chose to follow the response to L 
d /NP 118-126 
because, in our hands, the total numbers of antigen-specific 
precursors were not substantially different between WT and 
IL-4Rα KO mice, whereas the numbers of nonnaive pheno-
type antigen-specific cells was significantly reduced (Fig. 2). 
WT and IL-4Rα KO mice had similar frequencies of NP 118-</p>

<p>126 -specific CD8 
+ T cells, as measured by tetramer binding 
(Fig. 5 A). However, we found significantly decreased numbers 
of total CD8 
+ T cells in the spleens of IL-4Rα KO mice 7 d 
after LCMV infection (Fig. 5 B), and accordingly, the abso-
lute numbers of antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cells were reduced 
in IL-4Rα animals (Fig. 5 C). It is worth noting that the fold 
difference in bulk and antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cell numbers 
between WT and IL-4Rα-deficient mice was more substantial </p>

<p>after LCMV infection (Fig. 5, B and C) than in unimmunized 
mice (Figs. 1 C and 2 A), e.g., the difference in bulk CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells before infection was 1.3-fold, whereas it was 2.2-fold 
after infection (Figs. 1 C and 5 B), indicating that the response 
to infection exacerbates the deficit in IL-4Rα KO CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells. Because we found that IL-4 sensitivity influenced 
Eomes and T-bet expression in unimmunized CD8 
+ T cell 
populations (Fig. 3), we next measured intracellular expression 
of these factors in the antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cells at the ef-
fector stage of the response to LCMV. We observed decreased 
frequency and numbers of Eomes-expressing CD8 
+ T cells in 
IL-4Rα KO mice (Fig. 5 D and not depicted). Although an in-
creased frequency of IL-4Rα KO antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cells 
was either T-bet single positive or expressed low levels of both 
transcription factors (Fig. 5 D), this did not translate into in-
creased absolute numbers of these populations (not depicted). 
It was possible that the differences we observed in 
the nature of the CD8 
+ T cell response to LCMV in WT </p>

<p>Figure 3. IL-4Rα regulates Eomes and T-bet ex-
pression by all CD8 
+ T cell subsets. (A) Cells were 
isolated from naive WT and IL-4Rα KO BALB/cByJ 
spleen and lymph nodes, and CD8 
+ T cells with the 
indicated CXCR3/CD44 phenotype were analyzed for 
Eomes and T-bet expression after intracellular stain-
ing. The black line (unfilled) represents naive CD4 T 
cells as a control. (B-E) The mean fluorescence inten-
sity (MFI) for expression of Eomes (B and D) and T-bet 
(C and E) was determined in CD8 
+ T cells from intact 
WT BALB/cByJ and IL-4Rα KO BALB/cByJ mice (B and 
C) and from mixed BM chimeras, generated as in Fig. 1 
(D and E). Error bars indicate mean ± SD. P-values are 
represented as *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.001; ***, P &lt; 0.001; 
****, P &lt; 0.0001 by unpaired (B and C) or paired (D and 
E) Student's t test. (B and C) n = 4 for WT and n = 4 
for IL-4Rα KO, and data are representative of four ex-
periments. (D and E) n = 7 for mixed BM chimeras, and 
data are representative of three experiments. </p>

<p>IL-4 responsiveness regulates CD8 
+ T cell function | Renkema et al. </p>

<p>
versus IL-4Rα KO animals reflected alterations in the re-
sponse of other IL-4-sensitive cells and/or aspects of viral 
control (e.g., viral clearance kinetics). To control for this, 
we conducted similar experiments in mixed BM chime-
ras, in which we could determine the intrinsic impact of 
IL-4Rα deficiency among the CD8 
+ T cell population. 
Those studies revealed that the differences in T-bet and 
Eomes expression held for WT and IL-4Rα KO cells 
responding to LCMV in the same host animals, arguing 
for a cell-autonomous role for IL-4Rα expression in this 
system (Fig. 5 E). Thus, the impact of IL-4 sensitivity on 
T-bet/Eomes expression is carried into the effector phase 
of the antiviral response. 
Elevated T-bet expression levels are required for effec-
tive generation of SLECs, identified in LCMV infections by a 
CD127 
lo KLRG1 
hi phenotype, whereas MPECs identified as 
CD127 
hi KLRG1 
lo are more likely to survive contraction and 
develop into long-lived memory cells (Kaech et al., 2003). 
Hence, we also investigated whether the frequency of SLEC 
and MPEC populations (and other CD127/KLRG1-defined 
subsets) differed in LCMV-infected WT and IL-4Rα KO 
mice. At an effector stage time point, we observed reduced 
frequencies of SLEC phenotype cells and a modest increase 
in the frequency of MPEC phenotype cells in IL-4Rα KO 
animals (Fig. 5 F), although all antigen-specific IL-4Rα KO 
subpopulations were decreased in absolute numbers com-
pared with WT (not depicted). The changes in KLRG1/ 
CD127 expression were, however, not well recapitulated in 
the BM chimeras (Fig. 5 G), suggesting effects of IL-4Rα 
expression on cells other than CD8 
+ T cells may influence 
these phenotypic differences. </p>

<p>We next extended these data to a memory time point. 
Antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cells were isolated by peptide-
MHC tetramer enrichment from spleen and lymph nodes 
of WT, IL-4Rα KO, and mixed BM chimeras infected with 
LCMV at least 45 d previously. Fewer antigen-specific cells 
were recovered from the IL-4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cell popu-
lation relative to WT cells (Fig. 5, H and I). Note that the 
BM chimera approach allowed us to normalize the ratio 
of IL-4Rα KO and WT cells in the preimmune popula-
tion (Fig. 5 I, first column); hence, the dominance of WT 
over IL-4Rα KO antigen-specific memory CD8 
+ T cells in 
this case suggests a qualitative rather than quantitative dif-
ference in the capacity of LCMV-induced IL-4Rα CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells to reach memory phase. 
These data suggest that differences in IL-4 sensitivity 
affect both the magnitude and quality of the CD8 
+ T cell 
immune response toward acute viral infection. </p>

<p>The impact of CD8 
+ T cell responsiveness to IL-4 
occurs before LCMV infection 
Although our data suggested that CD8 
+ T cell sensitivity to 
IL-4 was important for an optimal response to LCMV, it was 
not possible to determine whether this chiefly reflected a re-
quirement for IL-4 during the infection itself or whether the 
effects of IL-4 occurred before infection, by programming 
the preimmune CD8 
+ T cell population. 
To distinguish between these possibilities, we performed 
adoptive transfer experiments. Congenically distinct WT 
CD8 
+ T cells were transferred into either WT (IL-4 suffi-
cient) or IL-4 KO (IL-4 deficient) recipients. Engraftment 
was determined 1 d after adoptive transfer in some mice </p>

<p>Figure 4. Enhanced cytokine production by IL-4Rα KO 
CD8 
+ T cells. (A) Bulk CD8 
+ T cells from WT and IL-4Rα KO 
were stimulated with plate-immobilized anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 
for 6 or 24 h and stained for intracellular TNF or IFN-γ. 
(B-D) WT and IL-4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cells were sorted into the 
subsets indicated and then stimulated with anti-CD3 and an-
ti-CD28 for 6 (B and C) or 24 h (D) before intracellular staining 
for TNF (B) or IFN-γ (C and D). Error bars indicate mean ± SD. 
P-values are represented as *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ****, P &lt; 
0.0001 by unpaired Student's t test. n = 4 for WT and n = 4 
for IL-4Rα KO for each graph, and data are representative of 
three (A) or two (B-D) experiments. </p>

<p> 
JEM Vol. 213, No. 7 </p>

<p>(n = 3 for WT, n = 4 for IL-4 KO) and found to be equivalent 
in both recipients (not depicted). 7 d after LCMV infection, 
we observed similar numbers of total and antigen-specific 
donor CD8 
+ T cells in both the WT and IL-4 KO recipient 
groups (Fig. 6, A and B). Additionally, no statistical differences 
in Eomes (Fig. 6 C) and T-bet (Fig. 6 D) were observed in 
WT antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cells transferred to WT or IL-4 
KO recipients. These findings suggested that exposure to IL-4 
during the immune response to LCMV is not required for an 
effective CD8 
+ T cell response. 
We used a complementary approach to determine the 
impact of IL-4Rα deficiency on the response of memory phe-</p>

<p>notype CD8 
+ T cells. Because frequencies of naive and mem-
ory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells differ in WT and IL-4Rα KO 
mice (Fig. 1), we sorted congenically distinct WT and IL-4Rα 
KO CD8 
+ T cells into naive (CD44 
lo CXCR3 </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>) or mem-
ory phenotype (CD44 
hi CXCR3 </p>

<p>hi </p>

<p>) subsets before coadoptive 
transfer into WT host BALB/c mice that were subsequently 
infected with LCMV. The magnitude of the LCMV-specific 
response by both donor populations was determined 7 d after 
infection. Fig. 6 E shows the numbers of donor L 
d /NP 118-128 
tetramer-stained cells, whereas Fig. 6 F shows the response by 
each donor population as a percentage of the host response, 
which helps normalize interexperiment variability. These ex-</p>

<p>Figure 5. IL-4Rα deficiency compromises 
the antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cell response 
to LCMV. (A-G) Intact WT and IL-4Rα KO 
BALB/cByJ mice (A-D and F) or mixed BM chi-
meras containing WT and IL-4Rα KO donor 
cells (E and G) were infected with LCMV Arm-
strong, and spleens were analyzed on day 7 
after infection. (A-C) The frequency (A) and 
number (C) of NP 118-126 /L 
d tetramer-positive 
(Tet </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) CD8 
+ T cells were measured, as was the 
number of total CD8 
+ T cells (B). (D-G) The fre-
quency of NP 118-126 /L 
d tetramer-positive CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells expressing the indicated pattern of 
T-bet/Eomes expression (D and E) or KLRG-1/ 
CD127 expression (F and G) was determined in 
LCMV-infected WT and IL-4Rα KO mice (D and 
F) or mixed BM chimeras (E and G). (H and I) 
NP 118-126 /L 
d tetramer enrichment was used to 
enumerate the antigen-specific memory CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells in WT and IL-4Rα KO mice (H) and mixed 
BM chimeras (I) at least 45 d after infection 
with LCMV. Error bars indicate mean ± SD. 
P-values are represented as *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 
0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.001 by unpaired (A-D, F, and 
H) or paired (E and G) Student's t test. (A-D 
and F) Data (n = 5 for WT, n = 5 for IL-4Rα 
KO) are representative of two individual exper-
iments. (E and G) Data (n = 5 for mixed BM 
chimeras) are representative of two individ-
ual experiments. (H) Data are combined from 
two separate experiments (n = 6 for WT, n = 
6 for IL-4Rα KO). (I) Data are combined from 
two separate experiments (n = 6 for mixed 
BM chimeras) and are representative of three 
individual experiments. </p>

<p>IL-4 responsiveness regulates CD8 
+ T cell function | Renkema et al. </p>

<p>
periments revealed no significant difference in the magnitude 
of the response of antigen-specific WT and IL-4Rα KO naive 
CD8 
+ T cells, in contrast to what might be expected were 
reactivity to IL-4 critical for driving expansion of LCMV-spe-
cific CD8 
+ T cells. Interestingly, the expansion of memory 
phenotype IL-4Rα KO donor cells was at least as great as that 
of their WT counterparts, and in many cases, this IL-4Rα KO 
population responded more vigorously than the WT popula-
tion (Fig. 6, E and F). These findings reinforce the conclusion 
that IL-4Rα engagement during the response to LCMV is 
not required to induce a strong proliferative response. Further-
more, these results suggest that memory phenotype IL-4Rα 
KO CD8 
+ T cells are not intrinsically defective in their in vivo 
response to LCMV but that their scarcity limits the overall 
magnitude of the response in IL-4Rα-deficient mice. 
Combined, these results strongly suggest that it is IL-4 
exposure during development and homeostasis that shapes 
the subsequent CD8 
+ T cell response to LCMV infection and 
that IL-4 conditioning primarily increases the quantity but 
not the quality of memory-like CD8 
+ T cells that participate 
in the immune response to LCMV. </p>

<p>DIS CUS SION 
Our data indicate that, in BALB/c mice, the response to 
steady-state levels of IL-4 substantially alters the CD8 
+ T 
cell pool. IL-4Rα-deficient mice had reduced total CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cell numbers, chiefly arising because of a severe reduction 
in the frequency of memory phenotype cells (including vir-
tual memory cells specific for unencountered foreign anti-
gens). However, beyond these quantitative effects, qualitative 
changes in the CD8 
+ T cell pool were evident. Our previous 
study indicates that IL-4 exposure in the thymus resulted in 
high expression levels of the Eomes transcription factor (but 
not the related factor T-bet) in thymic memory phenotype 
CD8 
+ T cells (Weinreich et al., 2010). Peripheral memory 
phenotype CD8 
+ T cells in IL-4Rα KO mice were reduced 
in frequency and showed reduced Eomes expression. Surpris-
ingly, we also observed that IL-4 responsiveness correlated 
with heightened Eomes expression in all CD8 
+ T cells, in-
cluding phenotypically naive CD8 
+ T cells. A study by Carty 
et al. (2014) using C57BL/6 mice suggested that naive CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells do not up-regulate Eomes in response to IL-4 alone in 
vitro, but rather, Eomes could be induced by a combination </p>

<p>Figure 6. IL-4 exposure before but not 
during LCMV infection regulates the CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cell response. (A-D) WT BALB/cByJ (CD45.1) 
CD8 
+ T cells were transferred into WT BALB/ 
cByJ (CD45.2) or IL-4 KO BALB/cJ recipients 
(CD45.2), which were then infected with LCMV 
and analyzed 7 d after infection. The num-
bers of total splenic donor CD8 
+ T cells (A) 
and donor NP 118-126 /L 
d tetramer-binding CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells (B) were calculated for each recipient 
group. (C and D) Expression levels of Eomes (C) 
and T-bet (D) on antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cells 
in the indicated recipient animals. MFI, mean 
fluorescence intensity. (E and F) Naive (CD44 </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>CXCR3 </p>

<p>lo </p>

<p>) and memory phenotype (CD44 </p>

<p>hi </p>

<p>CXCR3 </p>

<p>hi </p>

<p>) CD8 
+ T cells were sorted from WT 
BALB/cByJ (CD45.1) and IL-4Rα KO BALB/cByJ 
(CD45.2) mice, and equal numbers of pheno-
type-matched WT and IL-4Rα KO cells were 
cotransferred into WT BALB/cByJ recipients 
(CD45.1/2). 1 d after adoptive transfer, recip-
ients were infected with LCMV. Total numbers 
of splenic NP 118-126 /L 
d tetramer-binding CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells (E) or the frequency of donor NP 118-126 /L </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tetramer-positive (Tet </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) cells (F) within the 
total tetramer-positive population was cal-
culated for each recipient. Error bars indicate 
mean ± SD. (A-D) P &gt; 0.05 (not significant [ns]) 
for all comparisons, using unpaired Student's t 
test. (E and F) P-values are represented as *, P &lt; 
0.05 by paired Student's t test. (A-D) Data (n = 
5 for WT, n = 5 for IL-4 KO recipients) are rep-
resentative of two experiments. (E and F) Data 
are combined from two separate experiments 
(n = 6 for naive phenotype recipients, n = 5 for 
memory phenotype recipients total). </p>

<p> 
JEM Vol. 213, No. 7 </p>

<p>of IL-4 together with weak TCR stimulation. In contrast, in 
vivo treatment of mice with IL-4 complexes (which induce 
a heightened response to IL-4) could provoke naive CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cell proliferation (Morris et al., 2009) and induce their 
acquisition of innate memory phenotype, including ele-
vated Eomes expression (Ventre et al., 2012). Hence, the 
elevated Eomes levels we observe in WT naive CD8 
+ T 
cells in BALB/c mice might arise because of sustained IL-
4Rα signals in the periphery or potentially be carried over 
from IL-4Rα stimulation during thymic differentiation; 
whether, in either case, basal TCR stimulation through self-
peptide-MHC interactions is required to preserve Eomes ex-
pression levels is unclear. 
Our experiments investigating the impact of IL-4Rα 
signals on functional responses of peripheral CD8 
+ T cell 
populations also led to unexpected findings. Although nu-
merically reduced, IL-4Rα-deficient memory phenotype 
CD8 
+ T cells showed significantly enhanced capacity to 
make IFN-γ and TNF compared with their WT counter-
parts. Furthermore, this functional superiority extended to 
the IL-4Rα-deficient naive and intermediate phenotype 
populations. On a per cell basis then, acute inflammatory cy-
tokine production is compromised rather than enhanced by 
developmental exposure to IL-4. This finding resonates with 
the long-established principle that IL-4Rα signals promote 
Th2 and impair Th1 cell differentiation. Likewise, we found 
that IL-4Rα-deficient memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells 
exhibited enhanced not diminished expansion in response 
to LCMV infection when their numbers were normalized 
with WT cells through adoptive transfer. Hence, IL-4 appears 
to act to both increase the number of memory-like CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T cells while also reducing their individual capacity to elicit 
inflammatory cytokines in vitro and mount a robust response 
to viral infection in vivo. 
Because these data suggest that IL-4 sensitivity has both 
positive and negative effects on the quantity/quality of the 
CD8 
+ T cell pool, they raise the question of whether de-
velopmental exposure to IL-4 would improve or diminish 
the CD8 
+ T cell response to pathogens. Previous studies have 
indicated that some homeostatic memory-like CD8 
+ T cell 
populations are regulatory cells, capable of restraining CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>and CD8 
+ T cell responses (Rifa'i et al., 2004; Lin et al., 2007;  Dai et al., 2010; Kim et al., 2010, 2011; Sakuraba et al., 2013). 
Published studies suggest loss of IL-4 sensitivity compromises 
the CD8 
+ T cell response to liver stage malaria (Carvalho et  al., 2002; Morrot et al., 2005). In our experiments, we found 
that loss of IL-4 sensitivity by the CD8 
+ T cell population led 
to diverse changes in the response to acute LCMV infection. 
The magnitude of the antigen-specific response was com-
promised in IL-4Rα-deficient mice, as was the production 
of effector cells expressing high levels of Eomes. Interpreting 
the basis for these changes in the intact IL-4Rα KO mice is 
complicated by the fact that these mice exhibit both slightly 
reduced numbers of preimmune CD8 
+ T cells and changes 
in gene expression and functional traits within the CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>population. However, similar conclusions were reached from 
studies using mixed BM chimeras, in which the numbers of 
preimmune WT and IL-4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cells were nor-
malized. Collectively with the data discussed in the previous 
paragraph on the robust reactivity of memory phenotype IL-
4Rα KO CD8 
+ T cells, our data suggest that the impaired 
LCMV-specific response observed in IL-4Rα KO mice is 
chiefly caused by a deficit in the numbers rather than the 
intrinsic quality of memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells. 
The chimera and adoptive transfer approaches also 
indicated that IL-4-dependent changes in the pre-and 
postimmune CD8 
+ T cell pool were dependent on IL-4 
sensitivity by the CD8 
+ T cell population itself. Further-
more, these data suggested that the effects of IL-4 reactivity 
occurred during T cell development or homeostasis, rather 
than during the response to pathogen infection, because we 
found no evidence for a role of IL-4 in supporting the re-
sponse to LCMV. Hence, our data are compatible with a 
model in which IL-4 induces altered thymic differentiation 
of CD8 
+ T cells, and these effects are maintained into the 
peripheral antigen-responsive pool. 
Collectively, our experiments suggest diverse effects of 
steady-state IL-4 exposure on CD8 
+ T cell subsets, gene ex-
pression, functional reactivity, and response to pathogens. Our 
findings indicate that IL-4 exposure may impair the intrinsic 
capacity of CD8 
+ T cells to rapidly produce IFN-γ and to 
mount a robust proliferative response to LCMV; yet, at the 
same time, IL-4 drives differentiation of significantly greater 
numbers of memory phenotype CD8 
+ T cells that participate 
effectively in Th1 responses. In this regard, our findings sug-
gest a need to reevaluate ways in which IL-4, the prototypical 
Th2 cell cytokine, may ironically improve rather than dimin-
ish proinflammatory immune responses. 
In this regard, a recent study (Lee et al., 2015) used 
distinct approaches to manipulate the frequency of IL-4-
induced memory-like cells in BALB/c mice and found 
that the presence of this population correlated with im-
proved control of LCMV cl13 (which can establish a 
chronic infection in mice). 
An important question is whether similar effects are 
mediated by IL-4 in humans. Populations of Eomes 
hi mem-
ory-like CD8 
+ T cells have been described in fetal humans 
(Min et al., 2011), and related subsets have been observed in 
adult humans (Jacomet et al., 2015). How variability in IL-4 
expression levels alters the frequency or characteristics of 
these CD8 
+ T cells is unclear. In a set of mouse strains, there 
was a correlation between the frequencies of IL-4-producing 
invariant NK T cells and thymic innate memory CD8 
+ T cells 
(Lee et al., 2013b). It is possible that humans with sustained 
elevated levels of IL-4 (e.g., individuals with atopic diseases 
or infection with pathogens inducing chronic Th2 responses) 
may undergo similar changes in the developing CD8 
+ T cell 
pool, which would promote balance in the immune system 
by increasing the numbers of cells competent to participate in 
type-1 immune responses. </p>

<p>IL-4 responsiveness regulates CD8 
+ T cell function | Renkema et al. </p>

<p>
MAT ERI ALS AND MET HODS 
Mice and virus. BALB/cByJ and IL-4 KO BALB/cJ mice 
were purchased from The Jackson Laboratory. IL-4Rα KO 
BALB/cByJ mice were generated by backcrossing IL-4Rα 
KO BALB/cJ (The Jackson Laboratory) with BALB/cByJ 
mice for at least five generations. All animal experiments were 
done with approved Institutional Animal Care and Use Com-
mittee protocols at the University of Minnesota. LCMV 
Armstrong was provided by D. Masopust (University of Min- nesota, Minneapolis, MN). Mice were infected with 2 × 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>plaque forming units i.p. </p>

<p>Mixed BM chimeras. BM was harvested from congenically 
distinct WT and IL-4Rα KO BALB/c mice. After T cell de-
pletion, BM was mixed at ∼45% WT and ∼55% IL-4Rα KO, 
as preliminary data showed disadvantaged engraftment of IL-
4Rα KO BM. Recipient congenic WT BALB/c mice were 
given 500 cGy (in a split dose) and reconstituted with 10 × 
10 
6 BM cells i.v. Chimeras were used &gt;8 wk after transplantation. </p>

<p>Peptide-MHC class I tetramer enrichment. Enrichment of 
antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cell precursors or LCMV-specific 
CD8 
+ T cells at memory time points was performed as previ-
ously described (Haluszczak et al., 2009). Combined spleen 
and lymph nodes or spleen only, as indicated, was digested 
with collagenase D. Cells were labeled with PE-or APC-
conjugated tetramers, followed by magnetic enrichment over 
columns using anti-PE or anti-APC magnetic beads (Miltenyi 
Biotec). Enriched samples were stained with surface antibod-
ies, and AccuCheck counting beads (Invitrogen) were used 
for calculating cell number. </p>

<p>Surface and intracellular flow cytometry. Single-cell suspen-
sions were generated from spleen and lymph nodes as desig-
nated. Cells were stained with the following extracellular 
antibodies: anti-CD4 (RM4-5), anti-CD8 (53-6.7), an-
ti-CD44 (IM7), anti-CXCR3 (CXCR3-173), anti-CD3ε 
(145-2C11), anti-CD45.1 (A20), anti-CD45.2 (104), an-
ti-KLRG1 (2F1), and anti-CD127 (A7R34). Antibodies were 
purchased from eBioscience, BD, or Tonbo. LCMV NP 118-126  and L. monocytogenes LLO 91-99 tetramers were provided by 
the National Institutes of Health Tetramer Facility. For intra-
cellular staining, cells were fixed with the FoxP3 Fix/Perm 
kit (eBioscience) and stained with the following antibodies: 
anti-Eomes (Dan11mag), anti-T-bet (4B10), anti-IFN-γ 
(XMG1.2), and anti-TNF (MP6-XT22). </p>

<p>In vitro stimulation. CD8 
+ T cells were enriched using nega-
tive magnetic isolation (Miltenyi Biotec) and cultured for 
bulk CD8 
+ T cell analysis or FACS sorted based on CD44 
and CXCR3 expression (Fig. 1 D). Cells were cultured at 5.0 
× 10 
4 cells per 200 µl in a flat-bottom 96-well plate with 
immobilized anti-CD3 (145-2C11) and anti-CD28 (37.51) 
for 6-24 h. GolgiPlug (BD) was added for the final 4 h, before 
antibody staining. Cells were prepared for flow cytometry as </p>

<p>described in the previous section, with the addition of fixable 
Live/Dead (Thermo Fisher Scientific) staining to exclude 
dead cells from analysis. </p>

<p>Adoptive transfers. CD8 
+ T cells were magnetically isolated 
as described in the previous section from congenic donors 
and either transferred as bulk CD8 
+ populations or first sub-
jected to FACS sorting to isolate CD44 
hi CXCR3 
hi and 
CD44 
lo CXCR3 
lo populations. In some experiments, 1.5-2 
× 10 
6 WT BALB/c CD8 
+ T cells were adoptively transferred 
into congenic WT and IL-4 KO BALB/c mice. In the com-
petitive adoptive transfer experiments, equal numbers of WT 
and IL-4 KO BALB/c CD8 
+ T cells (1.8-2.8 × 10 
6 cells total, 
depending on the population and experiment) were adop-
tively transferred i.v. into WT BALB/c congenic recipients. </p>

<p>Data analysis and statistics. Flow cytometry data were an-
alyzed using FlowJo (Tree Star). A two-tailed, unpaired or 
paired Student's t test was performed on log-transformed 
data using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad</rs> Software). P-values are rep-
resented as follows: *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; ***, P &lt; 
0.001; ****, P &lt; 0.0001. </p>

<p>ACK NOW LED GME NTS </p>

<p>We thank the members of the Jamequist Laboratory and the University of Minnesota 
Center for Immunology for critical input. 
This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health grants R21 
AI100088 and R01 AI075168 to S.C. Jameson and grant K99-AI114884 to Y.J. Lee and 
a postdoctoral fellowship from the University of Minnesota Cancer Biology Training 
Grant (T32 CA009138) to K.R. Renkema. 
The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 20 August 2015 </p>

<p>Accepted: 28 April 2016 </p>

<p>REfERENCES </p>

<p>Akue, A.D., J.Y. Lee, and S.C. Jameson. 2012. Derivation and maintenance of 
virtual memory CD8 T cells. J. Immunol. 188:2516-2523. http ://dx .doi 
.org /10 .4049 /jimmunol .1102213 </p>

<p>Badovinac, V.P., G.A. Corbin, and J.T. Harty. 2000. Cutting edge: OFF 
cycling of TNF production by antigen-specific CD8 
+ T cells is antigen 
independent. J. Immunol. 165:5387-5391. http ://dx .doi .org /10 .4049 / 
jimmunol .165 .10 .5387 </p>

<p>Banerjee, A., S.M. Gordon, A.M. Intlekofer, M.A. Paley, E.C. Mooney, 
T. Lindsten, E.J. Wherry, and S.L. Reiner. 2010. Cutting edge: The 
transcription factor eomesodermin enables CD8 
+ T cells to compete for 
the memory cell niche. J. Immunol. 185:4988-4992. http ://dx .doi .org 
/10 .4049 /jimmunol .1002042 </p>

<p>Carty, S.A., G.A. Koretzky, and M.S. Jordan. 2014. Interleukin-4 regulates 
eomesodermin in CD8 
+ T cell development and differentiation. PLoS 
One. 9:e106659. http ://dx .doi .org /10 .1371 /journal .pone .0106659 </p>

<p>Carvalho, L.H., G. Sano, J.C. Hafalla, A. Morrot, M.A. Curotto de Lafaille, 
and F. Zavala. 2002. IL-4-secreting CD4 
+ T cells are crucial to the 
development of CD8 
+ T-cell responses against malaria liver stages. Nat. 
Med. 8:166-170. http ://dx .doi .org /10 .1038 /nm0202 -166 </p>

<p>Dai, H., N. Wan, S. Zhang, Y. Moore, F. Wan, and Z. Dai. 2010. Cutting edge: 
programmed death-1 defines CD8 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>CD122 
+ T cells as regulatory versus 
memory T cells. J. Immunol. 185:803-807. http ://dx .doi .org /10 .4049 / 
jimmunol .1000661 </p>

<p> 
JEM Vol. 213, No. 7 </p>



</text></tei>