<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4664003" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>1 Paper extracted from master's thesis "Avaliação da cultura de segurança entre profissionais do centro cirúrgico de um hospital de porte </p>

<p>especial: elementos para a melhoria da qualidade do cuidado aos idosos submetidos a procedimentos cirúrgicos", presented to Fundação de </p>

<p>Ensino 1041 </p>

<p>Objective: to evaluate the perception of healthcare professionals about the safety culture in the </p>

<p>operating room of a public hospital, large-sized, according to the domains of the Safety Attitudes </p>

<p>Questionnaire (SAQ). Method: descriptive, cross-sectional and quantitative research, with the </p>

<p>application of the SAQ to 226 professionals. Descriptive data analysis, instrument consistency </p>

<p>and exploratory factor analysis. Results: participants were distributed homogeneously between </p>

<p>females (49.6%) and males (50.4%); mean age of 39.6 (SD±9.9) years and length of professional </p>

<p>experience of 9.9 (SD±9.2) years. And Cronbach's α of 0.84. It was identified six domains </p>

<p>proposed in the questionnaire: stress perception (74.5) and job satisfaction (70.7) showed </p>

<p>satisfactory results; teamwork environment (59.1) and climate of security (48.9) presented </p>

<p>scores below the minimum recommended (75); unit's management perceptions (44.5), hospital </p>

<p>management perceptions (34.9) and working conditions (41.9) presented the lowest averages. </p>

<p>Conclusions: the results showed that, from the perspective of the professionals, there is weakness </p>

<p>in the values, attitudes, skills and behaviors that determine the safety culture in a healthcare </p>

<p>organization. </p>

<p>The safety of the healthcare services took over an </p>

<p>important place in public healthcare policies since the </p>

<p>publication of the document entitled To err is human: </p>

<p>building a safer health system, published in 1999 by </p>

<p>the Institute of Medicine (IOM), of the United States of </p>

<p>America (USA). Security, considered a quality dimension </p>

<p>and recognition that healthcare services are complex </p>

<p>systems and that healthcare can be highly damaging and </p>

<p>lethal, sparked the search by experts and researchers for </p>

<p>continuous improvement strategies of work processes in </p>

<p>this area </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In Brazil, only in 2013, safety of healthcare </p>

<p>services was the subject of the National Patient Security </p>

<p>Programme of Ministry of Health (MH), as well as the </p>

<p>Resolution of Board of Directors (RDC) No. 36 of the </p>

<p>National Health Surveillance Agency (ANVISA), which </p>

<p>established specific guidelines and actions for patient </p>

<p>safety in the context of the Unified Health System (SUS). </p>

<p>The search for quality in the healthcare services </p>

<p>has increasingly found space in the national and </p>

<p>international agendas and discussions on healthcare </p>

<p>reform. It is a gradual and differentiated process </p>

<p>that involves the reconfiguration in the relationships </p>

<p>between professionals and patients, between demand </p>

<p>and healthcare supply, which can be affected also by the </p>

<p>variation in the levels of social healthcare inequality </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Strategies for improving the quality of healthcare </p>

<p>services require systematic evaluations. These go </p>

<p>beyond the methodological debates on the purpose and </p>

<p>utility of the evaluation in decision-making, recognition </p>

<p>of pluralism of values and distinct points of view of the </p>

<p>interest groups about the evaluation process </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>. Thus, </p>

<p>it is important that managers of healthcare services </p>

<p>disseminate an evaluative culture into organizations. </p>

<p>Surgical centers are considered high-risk scenarios </p>

<p>and extremely susceptible to errors. In this scenario, </p>

<p>work processes are complex and interdisciplinary </p>

<p>practices, with strong dependence on the individual </p>

<p>and team performance in environments dominated by </p>

<p>pressure and stress. Surgical complications account for </p>

<p>a large proportion of deaths and injuries (temporary </p>

<p>or permanent) caused by the care process, considered </p>

<p>preventable </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In this regard, to know the safety culture of the </p>

<p>environment, in which it is intended to operate, is an </p>

<p>essential aspect to effect improvements. According </p>

<p>to the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality </p>

<p>(AHRQ), the safety culture is "the individual or collective </p>

<p>product of values, attitudes, perceptions, competencies </p>

<p>and behavior patterns that determine the commitment, </p>

<p>style and competence of a healthcare organization in </p>

<p>safety promotion" </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>. In turn, the climate of security is a </p>

<p>measurable component of the safety culture and can be </p>

<p>assessed through the perception of professionals, since </p>

<p>the attitudes and values are more difficult to assess </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>To this end, the Safety Attitudes Questionnaire </p>

<p>(SAQ) is an instrument developed by researchers from </p>

<p>the University of Texas (USA) that measures the climate </p>

<p>of security perceived by the healthcare professionals. </p>

<p>It was designed based on the Intensive Care Unit </p>

<p>Management Attitudes Questionnaire, derived from the </p>

<p>traditional Flight Management Attitudes Questionnaire </p>

<p>(FMAQ), used for over 20 years by the commercial </p>

<p>aviation, to measure the safety perception of the flight </p>

<p>crews </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>. The items that comprise the SAQ were highly </p>

<p>sensitive for assessing the individual safety attitudes </p>

<p>and exploration of the relationship between the safety </p>

<p>environment scores and results of care provided to </p>

<p>patients. This instrument has been used to assess the </p>

<p>differences in the perception of proactive organizational </p>

<p>commitment to the safety of individuals working in </p>

<p>the operating rooms of high and medium complexity </p>

<p>institutions in different countries. It contributes to the </p>

<p>increase in the probability of successful implementation of </p>

<p>resource management tools and security improvement, </p>

<p>such as the World Health Organization Surgical Safety </p>

<p>Checklist </p>

<p>(6-8) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The hospital where the study was carried out is </p>

<p>characterized as a high complexity service in all areas, </p>

<p>especially in surgical procedures, in the public network </p>

<p>of the Federal District, a reference in the Central West </p>

<p>region. It is in the process of accreditation by the </p>

<p>Joint Commission International and in the process of </p>

<p>implementation of several strategies to patient safety, </p>

<p>among them is the implementation of the WHO Surgical </p>

<p>Safety Checklist. </p>

<p>This hospital was included, in 2012, in the </p>

<p>Public Hospitals Restructuring Project (RHP) of SUS </p>

<p>Institutional Development Programme (Proadi-SUS). </p>

<p>This action of the Ministry of Health addresses the </p>

<p>strengthening of SUS in partnership with philanthropic </p>

<p>hospitals of recognized quality through the training of </p>

<p>workers and professionals, supporting to certification </p>

<p>and accreditation processes, for the management </p>

<p>qualification of public hospitals. </p>



<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Carvalho PA, Göttems LBD, Pires MRGM, Oliveira MLC. </p>

<p>This study was guided by the question: what is the </p>

<p>safety culture perception among professionals working </p>

<p>in the operating room of this hospital, according to the </p>

<p>domains of the SAQ? The objective was to evaluate </p>

<p>the perception of healthcare professionals about the </p>

<p>safety culture in the operating room of a public hospital, </p>

<p>large-sized, according to the domains of the SAQ. </p>

<p>Method </p>

<p>A cross-sectional descriptive study with a </p>

<p>quantitative approach was carried out. It was used the </p>

<p>Safety Attitudes Questionnaire (SAQ), with the version </p>

<p>translated and validated to Brazil. This instrument </p>

<p>is composed of two parts: the first part contains 41 </p>

<p>questions on patient safety perception and the second </p>

<p>part contains questions about the professional category, </p>

<p>gender, age and length of professional experience </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The 41 items of the SAQ are grouped into six </p>

<p>domains: 1) Teamwork Environment (TWE): quality of </p>

<p>the relationship and collaboration between the members </p>

<p>of a team (items 1-6); 2); Climate of Security (CS): </p>

<p>professionals' perception about the organizational </p>

<p>commitment to patient safety (items 7-13); 3) Job </p>

<p>Satisfaction (JS): positive view of the workplace (items </p>

<p>15-19); 4) Stress Perception (SP): recognition of the </p>

<p>influence of stress factors in the performance of work </p>

<p>(items 20-23); 5) Unit's Management Perception (UMP) </p>

<p>and Hospital Management Perception (HMP), both </p>

<p>relating to the approval of management or administrative </p>

<p>actions (items 24-29); and 6) Working Conditions (WC): </p>

<p>perception of the work environment quality (items </p>

<p>30-32). The items 14 and 34-36 are not part of any </p>

<p>domain in the original instrument. </p>

<p>Each item of the SAQ follows a five-point Likert </p>

<p>scale, organized and scored as follows: totally disagree </p>

<p>(0 points), partially disagree (25 points), neutral (50 </p>

<p>points), partially agree (75 points) and strongly agree </p>

<p>(100 points ); the "not applicable" option does not score. </p>

<p>In the final score, 0 corresponds to the worst perception </p>

<p>of the climate of security and 100 to best perception. </p>

<p>The calculation is made by adding the answers of the </p>

<p>items of each domain and dividing the result by the </p>

<p>number of items of each domain </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>, after inversion of </p>

<p>reverse items. </p>

<p>The study was carried out in the Surgical Center </p>

<p>Core (NCC) of the Federal District Base Hospital (HBDF), </p>

<p>with a capacity of 855 beds, of which 482 are surgical </p>

<p>beds, according to the National Healthcare Facilities </p>

<p>Register. </p>

<p>The SAQ was answered by 226 professionals </p>

<p>(sample error of 0.05) working in the reporting unit, </p>

<p>including nurses, practical nurses, residents physicians </p>

<p>and physicians of surgical and anesthetic areas, </p>

<p>dentists, administrative and environmental support </p>

<p>professionals. Inclusion criteria were: professional </p>

<p>agreement to participate in the study and length of </p>

<p>professional experience in the service for more than </p>

<p>six months. Professionals away from the work activities </p>

<p>during the collection period were excluded. Participants </p>

<p>were recruited in their own working environment, when </p>

<p>they were asked to respond to the instrument. </p>

<p>Data were collected from May to September 2013, </p>

<p>in three shifts, by two scientific initiation students of </p>

<p>the final year of the nursing course and two nursing </p>

<p>residents of the surgical team of the hospital, trained </p>

<p>by the researcher, who has extensive experience in the </p>

<p>operating room. </p>

<p>It was used the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for Social Science (SPSS</rs>), <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20.0</rs> and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Rstudio</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">0.98.501</rs> software. </p>

<p>Descriptive analysis, exploratory factor analysis and </p>

<p>comparison between groups were carried out. The </p>

<p>descriptive analysis of the SAQ was carried out using the </p>

<p>mean, median and standard deviation (SD) of responses </p>

<p>to items, calculated for each domain, ranging from 0 </p>

<p>to 100. Values greater than 75 mean strong agreement </p>

<p>of the professionals on questions about patient safety. </p>

<p>The Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin Measure (KMO) evaluates how </p>

<p>the data adjust to the use of the factor analysis model, </p>

<p>which resulted 0.75, allowing the use of this analysis to </p>

<p>data interpretation. </p>

<p>Along with the results of the factor analysis, there </p>

<p>are the factor loadings that represent the covariance </p>

<p>between the items and factors studied, which allows to </p>

<p>identify which factor the item was linked. To estimate </p>

<p>the factors, it was used the Component Main method, </p>

<p>in order to reduce the scope of the data and preserve </p>

<p>the explanation of data variability. Subsequently, it </p>

<p>was carried out a rotation of factors to improve the </p>

<p>interpretation of results by means of the Promax oblique </p>

<p>rotation. </p>

<p>Cronbach's α coefficient was used to analyze the </p>

<p>internal consistency of the items also called instrument </p>

<p>reliability. The α value ranged from 0 to 1, however, to </p>

<p>prove the internal consistency, it must present a value </p>

<p>between 0.7 and 1.0. Results below 0.7 indicate that the </p>

<p>instrument cannot measure the construct. </p>

<p>1044 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem 2015 Nov.-Dec.;23(6):1041-8. </p>

<p>The research followed all ethical care foreseen in the </p>

<p>Resolution 466/12 of the National Health Council. The project </p>

<p>was approved by the Ethics Research Committee of the </p>

<p>Foundation of Education and Health Sciences, of the State </p>

<p>Office of Health of the Federal District (CEP/FEPECS/SES/ </p>

<p>GDF), on 11/12/2012, with the advice number 144.024. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The profile of participants was characterized </p>

<p>by a homogeneous distribution among females </p>

<p>(49.6%) and males (50.4%), according to Table 1. </p>

<p>Regarding the length of professional experience, most </p>

<p>respondents had between 1 and 2 years (26.1%) and </p>

<p>between 11 and 20 years (22.1%) of experience, </p>

<p>with a mean of 9.9 years (SD±9.2). Physicians are </p>

<p>professionals with the longest length of professional </p>

<p>experience, followed by nursing technicians. The </p>

<p>predominant age group was between 31 and 50 years </p>

<p>(63.3%), with a mean of 39.6 (SD±9.9). Physicians </p>

<p>were the professionals who most participated </p>

<p>(73; 33.6%), followed by nursing technicians </p>

<p>(65; 27.4%) and resident physicians (51; 22.6%). </p>

<p>The total score of the SAQ, in the investigated unit, </p>

<p>ranged from 34.5 to 74.9, per domain, with mean of 53.5 </p>

<p>(SD±13.9) and median of 52.4 (Table 2). The domains </p>

<p>of job satisfaction (0.76), stress perception (0.74) and </p>

<p>hospital management perception (0.77) had significant </p>

<p>internal consistency, with α value higher than 0.7 and, </p>

<p>therefore, ensuring the reliability of the construct. </p>

<p>However, the domains of teamwork environment (0.40), </p>

<p>climate of security (0.50), unit's management perception </p>

<p>(0.63) and working conditions (0.58) showed α value less </p>

<p>than 0.7, indicating low correlation amongst the items. </p>

<p>The scores also varied per occupational category, and </p>

<p>resident physicians presented the lowest mean (50.4), </p>

<p>followed by nurses (51.1) and physicians (51.6). The highest </p>

<p>averages were achieved by the administrative (74.6), </p>

<p>followed by the environmental support (62.9) (Table 3). </p>

<p>Table 1 -Frequency of participants regarding gender, </p>

<p>length of professional experience, age and job title. </p>

<p>Brasília, DF, Brazil, 2013 </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Frequency 
Percentage </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
114 
50.4 </p>

<p>Female 
112 
49.6 </p>

<p>Length of professional experience </p>

<p>6-11 months 
13 
5.8 </p>

<p>1-2 years 
59 
26.1 </p>

<p>3-4 years 
18 
8.0 </p>

<p>5-10 years 
45 
19.9 </p>

<p>11-20 years 
50 
22.1 </p>

<p>21-39 years 
37 
16.4 </p>

<p>Absents 
4 
1.8 </p>

<p>Age group </p>

<p>Up to 30 years 
43 
19.0 </p>

<p>31-40 years 
79 
35.0 </p>

<p>41-50 years 
64 
28.3 </p>

<p>51-60 years 
27 
11.9 </p>

<p>Over 60 years 
4 
1.8 </p>

<p>Absents 
9 
4.0 </p>

<p>Profession/occupation </p>

<p>Administrative 
5 
2.2 </p>

<p>Table 2 -Descriptive analysis and Cronbach's α, per </p>

<p>domain, of the Safety Attitudes Questionnaire, Brasília, </p>

<p>DF, Brazil, 2013 </p>

<p>Domains 
Cronbach's α 
Mean 
Median 
Standard 
Deviation </p>

<p>Teamwork 
environment </p>

<p>0.40 
59.1 
58 
18.5 </p>

<p>Climate of 
Security </p>

<p>0.50 
48.9 
50 
19.6 </p>

<p>Job 
satisfaction </p>

<p>0.76 
70.6 
75 
22.0 </p>

<p>Stress 
Perception </p>

<p>0.74 
74.9 
81 
25.6 </p>

<p>Unit's 
management 
perception </p>

<p>0.63 
44.5 
46 
21.6 </p>

<p>Hospital 
management 
perception </p>

<p>0.77 
34.5 
33 
22.3 </p>

<p>Work 
conditions </p>

<p>0.58 
41.9 
41 
25.9 </p>

<p>Total 
0.84 
53.5 
52.4 
13.9 </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Frequency 
Percentage </p>

<p>Nurse 
13 
5.8 </p>

<p>Physician 
73 
32.3 </p>

<p>Resident Physician 
51 
22.6 </p>

<p>Dentist 
11 
4.9 </p>

<p>Environmental support 
8 
3.5 </p>

<p>Nursing technician 
65 
28.8 </p>

<p>Total 
226 
100.0 </p>

<p>Table 1 -(continuation) </p>

<p>(continue...) </p>



<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Carvalho PA, Göttems LBD, Pires MRGM, Oliveira MLC. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Participants were distributed homogeneously </p>

<p>among females (49.6%) and males (50.4%). Females </p>

<p>predominated among the nursing professionals, </p>

<p>while males predominated amongst physicians. The </p>

<p>participation of physicians (32.3%), combined or </p>

<p>not with participation of resident physicians (22.6%) </p>

<p>reveals a singular characteristic of this research. In </p>

<p>studies with the application of the SAQ, the proportion </p>

<p>of physicians is lower compared to other healthcare </p>

<p>team members 
(10-11) . </p>

<p>Regarding the length of professional experience, it </p>

<p>was observed that professionals with over 5 years of </p>

<p>experience account for over 60% of participants, due </p>

<p>to the type of employment contract of the professionals </p>

<p>with the institution, which is a statutory contract. The job </p>

<p>stability of the professionals may contribute to changes </p>

<p>in the labor process, since the institution does not suffer </p>

<p>the consequences of high personal replacement rates </p>

<p>(turnover). </p>

<p>A study carried out in US healthcare services </p>

<p>showed that working conditions are associated with </p>

<p>injuries in patients and nurses. The registration of </p>

<p>nursing hours per patient/day showed a negative </p>

<p>association with the falls and pressure ulcers. On the </p>

<p>other hand, the increased turnover of the staff in the </p>

<p>unit has increased the risk of injury in nurses, while its </p>

<p>decrease has reduced the chances of patient falls </p>

<p>(12) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The SAQ, in the assessed scenario, presented </p>

<p>Cronbach's α of 0.84, similar to that found in the </p>

<p>instrument translation study for Brazil (α=0.89). This </p>

<p>value suggests that the instrument is suitable for </p>

<p>measuring the proposed construct. However, in the </p>

<p>analysis per domain, it was observed that Cronbach's </p>

<p>α ranged from 0.4 to 0.7. The TWE (0.4), CS (0.5) </p>

<p>and JS (0.5) domains showed α values far below the </p>

<p>recommended (0.7), indicating low correlation between </p>

<p>the items of these domains. This result indicates the </p>

<p>need for instrument application in other samples, for </p>

<p>greater reliability and validity of the instrument. </p>

<p>In a research carried out in Taiwan, the Cronbach's </p>

<p>α ranged from 0.79 to TWE, 0.81 to CS, 0.91 to JS, </p>

<p>0.87 to the management perception, and 0.78 to WC </p>

<p>(13) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In Australia </p>

<p>(14) </p>

<p>, Cronbach's α ranged from 0.65 to 0.81, </p>

<p>and in Norway </p>

<p>(11) </p>

<p>, the Cronbach's α ranged from 0.68 to </p>

<p>0.85, for the six domains that compose the instrument. </p>

<p>Research has shown that item/total correlations </p>

<p>between the domains were considered from moderate </p>

<p>to strong, with the exception of the SP domain </p>

<p>(13) </p>

<p>. This </p>

<p>domain has been poorly correlated with other domains </p>

<p>of the SAQ, thereby, some researchers 
(15) suggest </p>

<p>that this subscale should be omitted from the overall </p>

<p>calculation of the instrument and analyzed separately. </p>

<p>However, moderate correlations of this domain with </p>

<p>the other domains and the total SAQ were found in the </p>

<p>assessment of this healthcare unit. </p>

<p>The total score of the SAQ ranged from 34.4 to 74.8, </p>

<p>per domain, with average of 53.5. The average score </p>

<p>shows that the perception of the safety culture among </p>

<p>professionals is below international recommendations, </p>

<p>which is 75 for a good perception of safety culture. </p>

<p>Some research using this instrument in the national </p>

<p>and international contexts, suggest that scores above </p>

<p>80 indicate a strong consensus among professionals </p>

<p>on the safety environment. However, those below 60 </p>

<p>Table 3 -Score of the perceptions of professionals of the operating room, per job title, according to the domains and </p>

<p>total of the Security Attitudes Questionnaire. Brasília, DF, Brazil, 2013 </p>

<p>Job Title 
TWE ⃰ 
CS </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>JS </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>SP </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>UMP </p>

<p>|| </p>

<p>HMP </p>

<p> ¶ </p>

<p>WC** 
Total </p>

<p>Administrative 
82.5 
66.7 
94 
64.1 
77.6 
55 
77.5 
74.6 </p>

<p>Nurses 
59 
49.2 
77.7 
68.7 
63.4 
46.9 
22.9 
51.1 </p>

<p>Physicians 
58.8 
44.5 
63.7 
77.9 
41.4 
33 
41.3 
51.6 </p>

<p>Resident physicians 
56.3 
48.1 
64.8 
79.3 
37.4 
28.7 
38 
50.4 </p>

<p>Dentists 
56.5 
45.2 
67.7 
68.5 
46.2 
35.6 
44.7 
52.1 </p>

<p>Nursing technicians 
66.8 
47.5 
89.3 
70.8 
65.5 
54 
46.3 
55.9 </p>

<p>Environmental support 
59.5 
54 
78 
71.2 
46.1 
36.9 
45.5 
62.9 </p>

<p>Total 
59.1 
48.9 
70.6 
74.8 
44.5 
34.4 
41.9 
53.5 </p>

<p>* Teamwork environment </p>

<p> † Climate of security </p>

<p> ‡ Job satisfaction </p>

<p> § Stress perception </p>

<p>|| Unit's management perception </p>

<p> ¶ Hospital management perception 
** Work conditions </p>



<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem 2015 Nov.-Dec.;23(6):1041-8. </p>

<p>represent a warning sign for the institutions, since they </p>

<p>indicate the need for actions for implementing the safety </p>

<p>culture </p>

<p>(6,13) </p>

<p>. It is worth mentioning that a study carried </p>

<p>out in six public hospitals, in three regions of Brazil, with </p>

<p>1301 professionals of medical and surgical wards, had </p>

<p>an average of 61.5 </p>

<p>(13) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The perception of the professionals about the safety </p>

<p>culture varied in relation to the assessed domains. </p>

<p>The teamwork environment presented an average of </p>

<p>59.1, with a mean of 58.3 (SD=18.5), a reasonable </p>

<p>result when compared to the international literature. </p>

<p>Research carried out in Taiwan showed an average of </p>

<p>48.9% of positive attitudes regarding the teamwork </p>

<p>amongst hospital healthcare workers </p>

<p>(13) </p>

<p>and 37% </p>

<p>amongst respiratory therapists </p>

<p>(16) </p>

<p>. However, in Greece, </p>

<p>in 2011, it was found a score of 74.1 for this domain </p>

<p>(17) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A coordinated team, with good communication and </p>

<p>working cooperatively, yields a more humanized care </p>

<p>and avoid discontinuity and high-risk situations for the </p>

<p>patient. </p>

<p>Regarding the climate of security the average was </p>

<p>48.9 (SD±19.6). In Brazil, it was found an average of </p>

<p>69.4 </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>, while other studies using the same instrument in </p>

<p>Ireland 
(18) and in the United States of America 
(19) showed </p>

<p>results ranging from 65.9 to 79.7, respectively. In </p>

<p>Taiwan it was found an average of 21 for this domain </p>

<p>(16) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The results of the NCC reveal a need for initiatives to </p>

<p>promote patient safety in this environment. </p>

<p>The 
job 
satisfaction 
domain 
(mean=70.6, </p>

<p>SD±22.5) showed the second most favorable outcome </p>

<p>amongst NCC professionals, which is consistent with </p>

<p>the findings of another study, conducted in Brazilian </p>

<p>hospitals (mean=77.6, SD±27.8) </p>

<p>(13) </p>

<p>. By comparing with </p>

<p>international studies </p>

<p>(16-17,19) </p>

<p>, it is observed that in Brazil </p>

<p>the professionals are more satisfied with their work. </p>

<p>This is a quite favorably result, since the job satisfaction </p>

<p>directly influences the safety culture and is related to </p>

<p>fewer adverse events </p>

<p>(17) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The stress perception (mean 74.8; SD±25.64) is </p>

<p>slightly below the recommended, which is 75. However, </p>

<p>this domain was the one showing the best perception </p>

<p>by the professionals of the NCC. In the USA, a study </p>

<p>assessing the differences in the perceptions on patient </p>

<p>safety amongst professions revealed that stress </p>

<p>recognition and working conditions differ according to the </p>

<p>profile of caregivers and professionals. Anesthesiologists </p>

<p>had more favorable stress perception (mean=82) </p>

<p>than nurses (mean=69) and surgeons (mean=65). </p>

<p>In the operating room, the perceptions about working </p>

<p>conditions were less favorable among nurses (mean=57) </p>

<p>than among surgeons (mean=75) </p>

<p>(19) </p>

<p>. A research carried </p>

<p>out in Tehran, before and after a training course on </p>

<p>safety culture, in a teaching hospital, showed low stress </p>

<p>perception by the managers, with average ranging from </p>

<p>20.9 to 27.3 </p>

<p>(20) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The UMP (mean=44.5, SD±21.6) and HMP </p>

<p>(mean=34.4, SD±22.3) domains, related to the </p>

<p>management of the unit and the hospital, achieved the </p>

<p>lowest scores among all domains of the SAQ, followed by </p>

<p>working conditions (mean=41.9, SD±25.9). Low scores </p>

<p>regarding the perception of professionals about hospital </p>

<p>management indicate barriers between the nursing </p>

<p>staff and the hierarchical superiors with respect to the </p>

<p>dialogue on patient safety issues </p>

<p>(21) </p>

<p>. In the study carried </p>

<p>out to characterize the safety culture perceptions, in </p>

<p>a national sample of agencies of Emergency Medical </p>

<p>Services (EMS) in the USA and Canada, it was observed </p>

<p>a wide variation in the management perception </p>

<p>(mean=67.2), suggesting that this domain oscillates </p>

<p>according to the prevailing management model in the </p>

<p>assessed scenario </p>

<p>(22) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In relation to the working conditions, studies </p>

<p>carried out in Taiwan and Tehran obtained scores of 31.8 </p>

<p>and 59.1, respectively, among hospital workers </p>

<p>(13,16,20) </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>both considered low. In Tehran, this domain achieved </p>

<p>a higher score, after a process of education, increasing </p>

<p>the average from 59.1 to 84.5 </p>

<p>(20) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Low perception in relation to the unit's management, </p>

<p>hospital management and working conditions suggests </p>

<p>that professionals working in healthcare do not notice </p>

<p>any commitment from the institution's management </p>

<p>with the latent factors of safety culture. It also indicates </p>

<p>the need for interventions to change this culture, such </p>

<p>as continuing education processes. The SAQ results </p>

<p>showed that HMP and UMP domains presented low </p>

<p>correlation between the items that comprise them. </p>

<p>Healthcare organizations are highly complex </p>

<p>systems, and therefore, need to implement a </p>

<p>management model focused on patient safety. Studies </p>

<p>suggest that SAQ results may provide a useful starting </p>

<p>point by assessing the safety culture, because they </p>

<p>serve as a criterion to guide the needs and opportunities </p>

<p>for quality improvement and patient safety </p>

<p>(23) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Systematic monitoring of safety culture can </p>

<p>contribute to promoting teamwork and safe care </p>

<p>throughout the patient's stay in the service. It is </p>

<p>emphasized that, the interpretation and analysis of </p>

<p>results are essential, as the average score of the SAQ </p>

<p>demonstrates that all domains are equally important </p>

<p>and that poor performance in one domain (climate of </p>



<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Carvalho PA, Göttems LBD, Pires MRGM, Oliveira MLC. </p>

<p>security) can be compensated by a good performance in </p>

<p>other domain (job satisfaction) </p>

<p>(23) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In high reliability organizations, such as </p>

<p>commercial aviation and nuclear energy, climate of </p>

<p>safety is a proactive measure, which supplements </p>

<p>traditional retrospective metrics such as number of </p>

<p>deaths and accidents 
(24) . In this sense, measurement </p>

<p>of the climate of safety among healthcare professionals </p>

<p>supplements the retrospective metrics related to </p>

<p>patient safety, such as the number of adverse events, </p>

<p>allowing the recognition of the system's weaknesses, </p>

<p>as well as the dimensions in which the service needs </p>

<p>to invest more intensely. The development of an </p>

<p>organizational culture that prioritizes safety is critical </p>

<p>to the consolidation of strategies to improve the quality </p>

<p>of the patient safety 
(25) . </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The results of this study demonstrate, in the </p>

<p>perspective of the professionals, weakness in the </p>

<p>values, attitudes, skills, competencies and behaviors </p>

<p>that determine the safety culture in a healthcare </p>

<p>organization. It was observed a detachment from the </p>

<p>hospital management and the unit management, in </p>

<p>relation to professionals, poor working conditions and </p>

<p>negative safety culture. Consistent interventions in these </p>

<p>aspects are suggested to provide a safe environment for </p>

<p>both professionals and patients. These results may be </p>

<p>useful for the managers in the area, since they point </p>

<p>out directions and alternatives for promoting patient </p>

<p>safety, such as communication among their teams and </p>

<p>introduction of new tools, such as the WHO Surgical </p>

<p>Safety Checklist. </p>

<p>The limitations of this study include the use of </p>

<p>perceptions rather than personal behavior and lack of </p>

<p>use of assistance results. It is suggested that follow-</p>

<p>up surveys on safety culture are used to assess the </p>

<p>progress in the implementation of processes to improve </p>

<p>the surgical care and patient safety, as well as studies on </p>

<p>adverse events and incidents. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>To the professionals who participated in this study. </p>







</text></tei>