<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4407839" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Insects exhibit an elaborate repertoire of behaviors in 
response to environmental stimuli. The central complex 
plays a key role in combining various modalities of sen-
sory information with an insect's internal state and past 
experience to select appropriate responses. Progress 
has been made in understanding the broad spectrum of 
outputs from the central complex neuropils and circuits 
involved in numerous behaviors. Many resident neurons 
have also been identified. However, the specific roles 
of these intricate structures and the functional connec-
tions between them remain largely obscure. Significant 
gains rely on obtaining a comprehensive catalog of the 
neurons and associated GAL4 lines that arborize within 
these brain regions, and on mapping neuronal pathways 
connecting these structures. To this end, small popula-
tions of neurons in the Drosophila melanogaster central 
complex were stochastically labeled using the multi-</p>

<p>color flip-out technique and a catalog was created of 
the neurons, their morphologies, trajectories, relative 
arrangements, and corresponding GAL4 lines. This 
report focuses on one structure of the central complex, 
the protocerebral bridge, and identifies just 17 morpho-
logically distinct cell types that arborize in this struc-
ture. This work also provides new insights into the 
anatomical structure of the four components of the 
central complex and its accessory neuropils. Most strik-
ingly, we found that the protocerebral bridge contains 
18 glomeruli, not 16, as previously believed. Revised 
wiring diagrams that take into account this updated 
architectural design are presented. This updated map 
of the Drosophila central complex will facilitate a 
deeper behavioral and physiological dissection of this 
sophisticated set of structures. J. Comp. Neurol. 
523:997-1037, 2015. </p>

<p>angular reach in gap crossing (Triphan et al., 2010); 
sleep (Donlea et al., 2011; Donlea et al., 2014); sound 
production during courtship (Popov et al., 2003); gravi-
taxis (Baker et al., 2007); and in sun-compass naviga-
tion in the locust and monarch butterfly (Heinze and 
Homberg, 2007; Heinze and Reppert, 2011). 
The central complex is highly conserved across 
insect species, and while the degree of functional con-
servation remains largely unknown, structural conserva-
tion is strong, although there are conspicuous 
differences in the basic blueprint of this brain region. 
All insects examined to date have a protocerebral 
bridge (PB), a caudal neuropil that resembles mustache 
handlebars in shape (Fig. 1). The PB is vertically divided 
into distinct units called glomeruli (G). The noduli (NO) 
lie rostral to the PB and constitute the only paired neu-
ropil of the central complex structures (Fig. 1). Depend-
ing on the species, anywhere from two to four discrete </p>

<p>units precariously stacked on top of one another on 
each side of the midline constitute the noduli. While 
the stacked noduli have been referred to as (horizontal) 
layers, no vertical divisions have been reported for 
these structures. The anteriormost structure is the cen-
tral body (CB), which, in some insects, comprises an 
upper (CBU) and lower (CBL) half. In Diptera, the struc-
tures homologous to the CBU and CBL are called the 
fan-shaped body (FB) and ellipsoid body (EB), respec-
tively (Fig. 1). The FB is posterior to the EB and is the 
largest of the central complex neuropils. It is subdivided 
vertically into columns, known as segments in Drosoph-
ila (Hanesch et al., 1989) and staves in Musca (Straus-
feld, 1976). Along the anterior-posterior axis of the FB, 
Hanesch et al. (1989) observed four shells, delineated 
by the positions and extent to which arbors from small-
field neurons project into these FB domains. The most 
prominent subdivisions of the FB are the horizontal </p>

<p>Figure 1. Central complex. A: The central complex straddles the midline in the central brain (gray). Its four components are the protocere-
bral bridge (solid purple fill; posterior), fan-shaped body (green), ellipsoid body (orange; anterior); and noduli (solid blue fill). Accessory neu-
ropils that are arborized by PB neurons include the crepine (CRE, transparent blue), rubus (RUB, yellow), gall (GA, red), and lateral 
accessory lobe (LAL, transparent purple). Posterior (B), sagittal (C; anterior to the right), and dorsal (D) views of the central complex. 
Images A-D were generated using Fluorender (Wan et al., 2009, 2012). The four components of the central complex are shown immunola-
beled with anti-nc82: (E) PB, (F) FB, (G) EB, and (H) NO. Asterisks in F highlight the layers that can be distinguished by differences in syn-
aptic density, as measured by intensity of nc82 signal. Dorsal is up. Scale bars 5 20 lm in A-D; 10 lm in E-G; 11 lm in H. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>layers, evident in brains immunolabeled to reveal the 
density of synapses (Fig. 1F). The ventral half of the EB 
is the most anterior neuropil of the central complex; 
the EB is partially embedded in the FB and is tilted on 
its axis such that the dorsal half is oriented more pos-
teriorly. In Drosophila, the EB is shaped like a torus, 
whereas in other Diptera, as well as most other insects, 
its shape more closely resembles that of a kidney bean 
(Strausfeld, 1976). Similar to the FB, the EB is subdi-
vided on three axes but the EB terminology is inconsis-
tent with that used for equivalent axes in the FB. 
Divisions along the anterior-posterior axis (shells in the 
FB) are called rings in the EB (Hanesch et al., 1989). 
Concentric rings along the radius of the EB are called 
layers (Young and Armstrong, 2010b), deriving their 
name from the homologous and more obvious "layers" 
in the noncircular CBL and the more common arched or 
kidney-bean form of the EB in other, non-Drosophila dip-
terans. Finally, the vertical divisions analogous to the 
PB glomeruli are the wedge-shaped divisions along the 
radius of the toroid that resemble pieces of pie. The 
analogy to the PB glomeruli is evident if the torus is 
split at its base and the formerly joined ends stretched 
away from one another, thereby converting rings into 
layers. These divisions are called sectors or segments 
(Hanesch et al., 1989). 
Central complex structures communicate extensively 
with numerous associated regions in the central brain. 
Historically, the lateral accessory lobes (LAL; Fig. 1; 
also known as the ventral bodies) and the bulb (BU, 
commonly referred to as the lateral triangle) have been 
recognized as prominent association areas, although 
additional regions, such as the gall (GA; Fig. 1), also 
constitute key centers of communication. 
Coherent and in-depth functional studies on the cen-
tral complex and its associated regions require both a 
detailed and comprehensive anatomical map of the con-
stituent neurons of the central complex and its neigh-
boring accessory neuropils as well as a set of GAL4 
lines that targets these neurons. This map will need to 
1) provide a detailed description of the architectural 
framework in which these neurons reside, 2) define 
inputs and outputs to each of the substructures that 
integrates sensory input with behavioral output, and 3) 
illustrate the connections between these brain regions. 
The work presented here contributes to the generation 
of this map by refining the architecture of a subset of 
neuropils of the central brain, including the four compo-
nents of the central complex and some associated 
regions, and by illustrating the "wiring rules" used by 
neurons to connect these substructures of the central 
complex. The neurons described in this work focus 
almost exclusively on cells that arborize in the PB. We </p>

<p>expect that most PB cell types are reported here, 
although electron microscope (EM) reconstruction will 
be required to verify complete coverage. At least two 
cells are known to be excluded from this description: 
one cell type identified by Lin et al. (2013) that was 
not seen in this study, and one cell seen only twice in 
this study, and neither time in its entirety. When neces-
sary, cells that do not arborize in the PB are included in 
the analysis both to provide a more comprehensive 
description of the anatomy of central complex struc-
tures and to strengthen connectivity and architectural 
claims suggested by PB neurons. 
We present revised circuitry "rules" and anatomical 
maps of the four central complex regions and neuropils 
associated with the central complex. We also provide 
an atlas of the PB cells identified in this study and cor-
responding Drosophila GAL4 lines that identify these 
cells. These data provide a template for a full recon-
struction of the protocerebral bridge neurons at an EM 
level. The tools and reagents will also enable and facili-
tate a broad range of behavioral and physiological stud-
ies into the neural basis of spatial navigation, visual 
learning, and other complex behaviors involving the 
central complex. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Multicolor flip-out technique and reagents </p>

<p>Approximately 35 GAL4 lines were selected from a 
collection of 7,000 GAL4 lines (Jenett et al., 2012) 
based on their expression patterns in the central com-
plex. These lines were characterized using the multi-
color flip-out (MCFO) technique (Nern et al., in prep.), 
which generates stochastically labeled single cells in a 
spectrum of colors. This method employs a transcrip-
tion unit and a transcriptional stop signal. The ability of 
the transcription unit to produce a product is blocked 
by a transcriptional stop signal. The stop signal can be 
removed by the action of a site-specific recombinase, 
and the fraction of cells in which the stop signal is 
removed-and thus the density of immunolabeling-can 
be varied by adjusting the level of recombinase pro-
duced (Struhl and Basler, 1993). Briefly, UAS reporter 
constructs carrying Flag, VK5, and HA epitope tags 
(pJFRC206-5xUAS-IVS-myr::smGFP-FLAG in VK00005 and 
pJFRC200-10xUAS-IVS-myr::smGFP-HA in attP18, Viswa-
nathan et al., submitted) downstream of an FRT-flanked 
stop signal were excised by limited expression of FLP 
recombinase activity. The following Flp stocks were 
used. 
57C10-FlpPEST-&gt;su(Hw)attP8:HA_V5_FLAG_1; 57C10-
wtFlp-&gt;su(Hw)attP8:HA_V5_FLAG_1; 57C10-FlpL-&gt;attP18: 
HA_V5_FLAG_1;57C10-FlpLwt-&gt;su(Hw)attP8:HA_V5_FLAG_1. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>999 </p>

<p>GAL4 stocks are noted throughout the text. Flies were 
dissected anywhere from eclosion to 2 weeks to achieve 
the desired density of labeled cells. Tissue was subse-
quently labeled with epitope tag-specific antibodies. 
With one exception, exclusively female brains were ana-
lyzed in this study. In all, 17 of the known 18 cell types 
were identified within the set of 35 GAL4 lines. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>For a complete list of antibodies used in this study, 
refer to Table 1. Immunohistochemistry and mounting 
were performed according to the protocol developed by 
Nern et al. (in prep.). Brains were dissected in 
Schneider's medium and fixed in 2% paraformaldehyde 
(PFA) in Schneider's medium for 50 minutes at room 
temperature (RT, 22 
C). Samples were then rinsed 4 3 </p>

<p>10 minutes at RT in PAT3 (0.5% Triton X-100/0.5% 
bovine serum albumin [BSA] in phosphate-buffered 
saline [PBS]), followed with a blocking step in 3% nor-
mal goat serum (NGS) in PAT3 for 90 minutes at RT. 
Next, tissue was incubated in mouse anti-nc82, an anti-
body against Bruchpilot (1:30; Developmental Studies 
Hybridoma Bank, University of Iowa; RRID: AB_528108; 
Wagh et al., 2006; Hofbauer et al., 2009), rabbit anti-
HA (1:300; Cell Signaling Technology, Beverly, MA; 
RRID: AB_1549585), and rat anti-Flag (1:200; Novus 
Biologicals, Littleton, CO; RRID:AB_1625981) in 3% 
NGS/PAT3 for 4 hours at RT, then overnight at 4 
C. 
Tissue was brought to RT and washed 3 3 30 minutes 
at RT. Samples were then incubated in Alexafluor-488 
donkey antimouse (1:400; Jackson ImmunoResearch 
Laboratories, West Grove, PA), Alexafluor-594 donkey 
antirabbit (1:500; Jackson Labs), and Alexafluor-647 
donkey antirat (1:300; Jackson Labs) in 3% NGS/PAT3 
for 4-6 hours at RT and 3-5 days at 4 
C. Tissue was </p>

<p>brought to RT and rinsed 3 3 30 minutes in PAT3. 
Brains were then blocked in 5% normal mouse serum/ 
PAT3 for 1 hour at RT, then incubated in DyLight-549 
mouse anti-V5 (1:500; AbD Serotec; AB_915420) for 4-
6 hours at RT, then overnight at 4 
C. Following 3 3 30 
minutes washes in PAT3 at RT and one 15-minute wash </p>

<p>in PBS, tissue was fixed in 4% PFA in PBS at RT for 4 
hours, then rinsed once for 15 minutes at RT in PBS. 
Finally, tissue was rinsed 53 in PAT3 at RT for 10-15 
minutes per wash. Tissue was mounted within 3-5 days 
of final PAT3 washes. If tissue was mounted after more 
than 2 days, it was first washed once more in PAT3. </p>

<p>Antibody characterization </p>

<p>The specificity of nc82 against BRP protein has 
been demonstrated by: 1) the expression pattern of 
GFP-tagged bruchpilot driven under tissue-specific driv-
ers, which matches nc82 signals in wing discs and tra-
cheal cells, and is also targeted to the active zone of 
larval NMJ boutons (Wagh et al., 2006); 2) western 
blots of adult head extracts using nc82 (Wagh et al., 
2006); and 3) the loss of immune-expression in brp 
mutant neuromuscular junctions and rescue by expres-
sion of BRP in brp mutants (Kittel et al., 2006). nc82 
has been widely used to label synaptic sites in Dro-
sophila, based largely on the pattern of labeling dem-
onstrated at neuromuscular junctions and fly 
photoreceptor synapses (Hamanaka and Meinertzha-
gen, 2010), but reports of its specificity are mostly 
not complete for synapses of the CNS. In particular, 
nc82 labels the platform of the T-bar ribbon, and not 
only has nc82 not been shown to label the platforms 
at CNS synapses, but not all synapses in the CNS 
have such organelles (Butcher et al., 2012). 
The specificities of the three epitope-tagged antibod-
ies, rat anti-FLAG, rabbit anti-hemagglutinin (anti-HA), 
and mouse anti-V5, are validated by the internal con-
trols of the flip-out approach in that: 1) expression pat-
terns differ by GAL4 line and 2) the extent of labeling 
varies from no label to dense label even though the 
GAL4 drivers are reasonably broad. </p>

<p>Clearing and mounting </p>

<p>Tissue was dehydrated through an ethanol series, 10 
minutes each in 30%, 50%, 75%, and 95% EtOH and 
then placed on poly L-lysine-coated coverslips (No. 1) 
while immersed in 95% EtOH. Once mounted, samples 
were dehydrated 3 3 10 minutes in 100% EtOH in </p>

<p>TABLE 1. 
Primary Antibodies Used in This Study </p>

<p>Antibody 
Immunogen 
Source 
Dilution </p>

<p>Anti-Bruchpilot 
Amino acids 1105-1740 of Drosophila 
Bruchpilot C-terminus </p>

<p>DSHB, mouse, monoclonal, nc82, 
RRID: AB_528108 </p>

<p>1:30 </p>

<p>Anti-HA 
Influenza HA epitope YPYDVPDYA 
Cell Signaling Technology, 3724S, rabbit, 
monoclonal, RRID: AB_1549585 </p>

<p>1:300 </p>

<p>Anti-FLAG 
N-terminal DYKDDDDK-tagged ECD 
of mouse Langerin </p>

<p>Novus Biologicals, NBP1-06712, rat, 
monoclonal, RRID:AB_1625981 </p>

<p>1:200 </p>

<p>Anti-V5 
Paramyxovirus SV5 
AbD Serotec, MCA 1360D549, mouse, 
monoclonal, RRID: AB_915420 </p>

<p>1:500 </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>Coplin jars, and then 3 3 5 minutes in 100% xylene. 
Spacers (No. 2) were placed on the microscope slide, 
DPX (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) added to the 
coverslip-mounted tissue, and the coverslip placed on 
the spacers, tissue side down. Samples were dried for 
2 days at RT before imaging. </p>

<p>Image acquisition </p>

<p>Brains were imaged using a Zeiss LSM 780 confocal 
microscope and a Plan-Apochromat 633/1.4 oil immer-
sion objective. Images were scanned at a frame size of 
1024 3 1024 pixels, voxel size 5 0.19 3 0.19 3 0.38 
lm, zoom 0.8 and one frame average. </p>

<p>Image analysis </p>

<p>Confocal stacks were viewed and analyzed using the 
Janelia Workstation, image-viewing software being 
developed at Janelia Research Campus (Murphy et al., 
2014). The suite of tools available in the Workstation 
enables confocal stacks to be viewed in both two and 
three dimensions and to be annotated with a user-
generated ontology. The Workstation provides an effi-
cient, intuitive, and customized alternative to publicly 
available platforms such as FIJI. </p>

<p>Neuropil masks </p>

<p>Neuropil masks were generated using Fluorender, 
nc82-labeled brains obtained in this work, and a stand-
ard brain (JFRC2013). Details of methodology are avail-
able in Aso et al. (eLife, in press). </p>

<p>Figure preparation </p>

<p>Brightness and contrast were adjusted in the Janelia 
Workstation for improved visualization of neurons. 
<rs type="software">Adobe Photoshop</rs> (San Jose, CA) was occasionally used 
to hide nc82 immunolabeling or primary neurites of 
nonessential cells if they interfered with visualizing the 
relevant neurons in a figure. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
New naming convention </p>

<p>Naming conventions for neurons in the central com-
plex range from being too broad and ambiguous to 
accommodate the level of detail essential for the studies 
reported here to being too esoteric for one not well 
acquainted with the field. In an effort to simplify a 
compartment-rich structure with many regions, domains, 
and subdomains, we use a new convention that provides 
an intuitive description of each cell type discussed. 
In the nomenclature system used here, neurons are 
named based on their axonal paths-the domains in 
which they arborize-and, when possible, the predomi-</p>

<p>nant polarity of their arbors at each synaptic junction. 
Several examples of neuron names and accompanying 
tutorials on how to translate the names are provided in 
Figure 2 (see legend for details) and abbreviations for 
the terms in the names are presented in Table 2. 
This naming scheme provides a naive reader with suffi-
cient information both to correlate a cell with its name 
and to deduce with reasonable accuracy its morphology, </p>

<p>Figure 2. Nomenclature design. A: This generic schematic illus-
trates the nomenclature system. Three neuropils are shown. Neuro-
pil 1, the first neuropil in a neuron's "name," is the neuropil 
closest to the cell body. The subdomains (abbreviated sd in the fig-
ure) are included in the neuron's name to define the subregion/s 
of the neuropils in which the cell type arborizes. For example, 
there are several distinct volumes in the EB, so the volume that is 
specific to a given cell type is included in the name. The third com-
ponent of a cell's name is the predominant morphology of its 
arbors, abbreviated as either "s" for spines, or "b" for boutons. 
B,C: Two neurons are shown, accompanied by schematics to illus-
trate the cells' locations in the central complex, and by the neu-
ron's name, annotated to illustrate how the name is derived. 
Letters that are used in the neuron names are highlighted in color. 
Ovals in the schematics represent the cell bodies, solid and 
hatched fills denote spine and bouton arbor morphologies, respec-
tively. PB: protocerebral bridge; GA: gall; EB: ellipsoid body; cb: cell 
body; s: spines; b: boutons; FB: fan-shaped body; RUB: rubus. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>since the connectivity path and the morphological fea-
tures of arbors at each synaptic junction are unique for 
each cell type. Such a system also obviates the need for 
a historical knowledge of neuron nomenclature (for exam-
ple, a "P1" neuron). While some important morphological 
details are not included in the path, such as size and 
location of the soma and trajectory of the primary neu-
rite, inclusion of all details would be inordinately cumber-
some and unlikely to be essential to distinguish unique 
cell types. Established nomenclature, as described in Ito 
et al. (2014), is used when possible and when it was con-
sidered accurate and sufficient in light of the new find-
ings described here. Newly identified compartments are 
named in accordance with preexisting terms, when possi-
ble. (For example, two, not one, regions constitute the 
medial nodulus, or NO 2 , and are referred to here as the 
dorsal and ventral compartments of NO 2 .) When neces-
sary, "ipsilateral" ("i") and "contralateral" ("c") are 
included in the neuron's name; these designations are 
context-dependent. For example, in complex arborization 
patterns these designations provide geographic informa-
tion about the locations of the arbors. In cases in which 
the neuron does not arborize in the PB, the cell body 
serves as the reference point, as follows: If the arbor is </p>

<p>on the same side as the cell body, it is considered ipsilat-
eral. Finally, this naming scheme has the added advant-
age that additional detail can be incorporated as 
necessary or as it becomes available. For example, during 
the course of this study it became evident that neurons 
arborize in only a subset of the glomeruli of the PB, so 
the designation "G x-y " was incorporated to identify the 
specific glomeruli targeted by the cell type, where "x" 
refers to the number of the medial glomerulus and "y" 
refers to the lateral glomerulus. 
Information about the morphology of the neurites that 
constitute each arbor is indicated in the cell type's 
name. These designations are based on light-level analy-
sis and are intended to indicate only the more predomi-
nant type of terminal since: 1) morphological distinctions 
at this level are sometimes ambiguous and 2) many neu-
rons are not exclusively pre-or postsynaptic at a given 
site (I. Meinertzhagen, pers. comm.; Takemura et al., 
2008). Even with the use of polarity markers, discrimi-
nating between input and output can be difficult (Nicolai 
et al., 2010). Indeed, it will likely turn out to be the case 
that many of the terminals in the cells described here 
are mixed. Ultimately, EM-level analysis will be necessary 
to definitively resolve the fine details of an arbor's mor-
phology and the polarity of the cells' terminals. In the 
neuronal path nomenclature presented here, bleb-like or 
bouton terminals are designated "b" (for boutons), spiny 
or branch-like arbors are designated "s" (for spiny/ 
spines), and mixed terminals as "s.b." (Fig. 2). 
Polarity of neurons' terminals is often inferred from 
the morphology of their neurites. The terminals consist-
ing of boutons are considered to be presynaptic or out-
put, whereas the spiny terminals and are considered to 
be postsynaptic, dendritic, or input. The assignments 
provided here are largely consistent with those shown 
in Lin et al. (2013). 
Note that "left" and "right" are used throughout the 
text to refer to the left and right halves of the PB. 
These terms refer not to the fly's left and right, but 
rather, to the left and right sides of the figure, as seen 
by the reader. Given the bilateral symmetry of the PB, 
the distinction serves only as a point of reference to 
orient the reader to the figures. </p>

<p>Criteria used to define unique cell types </p>

<p>Since there is not a consensus for the definition of 
cell type, we used the following logic to define a cell 
type for the studies presented here: We assume that 
cells of a cohort that follow the same path and have 
identical morphology survey the environment for the 
same information and deliver the same information 
(albeit from different coordinates in the environment) to 
the same downstream centers. This line of logic suggests </p>

<p>TABLE 2. 
Abbreviations </p>

<p>PB 
protocerebral bridge 
FB 
fan-shaped body 
EB 
ellipsoid body 
NUB 
nubbin 
NO 1 
nodulus 1, dorsal nodulus 
NO 2 
nodulus 2, medial nodulus 
NO 3 
nodulus 3, ventral nodulus 
NO 2 D 
dorsal compartment of NO 2 
NO 2 V 
ventral compartment of NO 2 
NO 3 P 
posterior compartment of NO 3 
NO 3 M 
medial compartment of NO 3 
NO 3 A 
anterior compartment of NO 3 
LAL 
lateral accessory lobe 
GA 
gall 
GA-t 
gall tip 
GA-s 
gall surround 
CRE 
crepine 
RUB 
rubus 
PS 
posterior slope 
SPS 
superior posterior slope 
IB 
inferior bridge 
G 
glomerulus of PB 
G# 
subset of glomeruli designated by number/s 
' 
layer (of FB) 
EBw 
wedge (EB domain) 
EBt 
tile (EB domain) 
s 
spines/spiny 
b 
boutons 
D 
dorsal 
V 
ventral 
P 
posterior 
i 
ipsilateral 
c 
contralateral </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>these cells perform the same function and consequently 
should be considered to be members of the same cell 
type. Therefore, a cell's path was used to define its cell 
type, so each of the 17 PB cell types identified in this 
study follows a unique projection (Fig. 3, Table 3A). Lin 
et al. (2013) adopted a more conservative definition in 
which they define cells that are likely performing the 
same function for different points in space as different 
cell types (in other words, the same cell performing the 
same function in different glomeruli). </p>

<p>Multicolor flip-out technique as a tool for 
refined anatomical studies </p>

<p>The multicolor flip-out (MCFO) technique provides an 
opportunity to visualize neurons at high resolution, both 
singly and in small populations. This technique makes it 
possible to label neighboring cells in a spectrum of 
unique colors, providing a degree of precise spatial infor-
mation not accessible with techniques used previously. 
In addition, a much larger number of individual cells for 
analysis can be generated when using the MCFO tech-
nique. This larger and more spatially refined dataset of 
the relative positions of uniquely colored cells revealed 
new insights into the architecture and circuitry of the 
Drosophila central complex, as well as new cell types. 
Most of the cell types described here were not identified 
in Hanesch et al. (1989; Table 3B) but were identified in 
Lin et al. (2013), although there are notable differences 
between the Lin et al. and this account, which are pre-
sented in Table 3A. A summary of cell types and GAL4 
lines that identify them are presented in Table 4. The 
revised anatomical framework of the central complex 
and associated structures are presented first followed by 
the neuronal circuits between these structures. </p>

<p>Protocerebral bridge comprises 18 
functional glomeruli </p>

<p>The protocerebral bridges of Drosophila (Power, 1943; 
Strausfeld, 1976, 1999; Hanesch et al., 1989; Lin et al., 
2013), Musca (Strausfeld, 1976), Schistocerca (Williams, 
1975; Muller et al., 1997; Heinze and Homberg, 2008; 
Young and Armstrong, 2010b), honeybees (Mobbs, 
1985), and beetles (Wegerhoff et al., 1996) have all been 
extensively reported to comprise 16 distinct units, known 
as glomeruli. In addition to the aforementioned neopter-
ans, it is widely accepted that the division of the PB into 
16 units is a common theme among other neopterans, 
including the cockroach Periplaneta americana and the 
paper wasp Polistes castaniensis (Strausfeld, 1976). The 
work presented here reveals that there are in fact 18, 
rather than 16, glomeruli in the PB in Drosophila brains. 
There are nine glomeruli per hemisphere, abbreviated 
here as G1. . .G9. The more sophisticated genetic tools, </p>

<p>imaging methods, and versatile software programs used 
for this work enable unambiguous visualization of 18 glo-
meruli in both adult brains immunolabeled with nc82 
(which recognizes the synaptic protein, Bruchpilot) as 
well as in brains in which the MCFO strategy was used 
to label random subsets of cells, thereby highlighting 
each glomerulus in a distinct color from its neighbors 
(Movies 1 and 2). Eighteen glomeruli have been reliably 
counted in multiple GAL4 lines that label diverse cell 
types in the PB. Furthermore, this is not a sex-specific 
morphological phenomenon, since PBs from both male 
and female brains contain 18 glomeruli (Fig. 4). The parti-
tioning of the PB into 18 segments is also evident in the 
pupal brain, as can be seen in figure 6J from Young and 
Armstrong (2010a). In their figure, the two medial glomer-
uli, while evident, are not targeted in the enhancer trap 
line used. Although anatomy does not predict function, 
the data presented here strongly suggest that G1, the 
medial glomerulus, and the likely glomerulus to have 
been overlooked in previous studies, is most certainly a 
functional unit given that: 1) it is targeted by various cell 
types (e.g., PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b, PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/ 
Vgall.b, PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b), and 2) cells that 
arborize in the first glomerulus follow the same trajecto-
ries as do their siblings in neighboring glomeruli. G9 is 
also expected to be functional as it is also targeted by 
many cell types (e.g., PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b, PB G2-9 .s-
EBt.b-NO 1 .b, PB G2-9 .b-IB.s.SPS.s). 
Architecturally, the "addition" of a ninth glomerulus 
would be expected to affect the anatomical correspon-
dence and projection patterns between glomeruli in the 
PB and equivalent vertical partitions in the FB and EB, 
since the FB is reported to be divided into eight and 
the EB into 12-16 vertical divisions (Hanesch et al., 
1989; Young and Armstrong, 2010b; Lin et al., 2013). 
These features are discussed below. 
Following convention, G9 is the most lateral and the 
two G1s are the medial glomeruli. Most of the glomeruli 
closely approximate lima beans in shape, although 
those closest to the midline are more rectangular. The 
central two glomeruli (G1) occupy the smallest volumes. 
Unlike the equivalent vertical divisions in the FB (seg-
ments/columns) and EB (wedges and tiles, described 
below), the boundaries between the glomeruli are evi-
dent in nc82-labeled samples. In addition, they are gen-
erally more restrictive than the FB and EB vertical 
domains, in that individual PB cell arbors are predomi-
nantly, but not exclusively, confined within the bounda-
ries of these units (see below). </p>

<p>Segmentation of the FB </p>

<p>The FB, as well as its corresponding neuropil, the 
CBU, is divided into horizontal layers, vertical columns, </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>Figure 3. Protocerebral bridge neuron catalog. Confocal images of all neurons with arbors in the PB that were identified in this study are shown. 
Each image is accompanied by a sketch that illustrates the neuropils in which the neuron arborizes. A: This schematic illustrates all neuropils that 
are arborized by the PB neurons described here, except the inferior bridge (IB) and superior posterior slope (SPS), which were omitted to simplify 
the schematic. The IB and SPS are shown in Ito et al., 2014. The schematic illustrates the current understanding of the subvolumes that constitute 
each of the neuropils shown, which is derived from work presented here. The neuropils were traced from a single focal plane of nc82-
immunolabeled specimens, so they reflect the approximate shapes of their respective brain regions. The layout and relative sizes of the neuropils 
were modified to accommodate the two dimensionality of the schematic. The color scheme was chosen to best separate adjacent volumes and is 
not coordinated with volumes of similar color within this schematic, nor with any neurons or figures in the text. PB: protocerebral bridge. Numbers 
1-9 in the PB identify each of the glomeruli of this neuropil. FB: fan-shaped body. Layers 1-9 of the FB are indicated. The relative widths of each 
layer are accurate for the focal plane shown. The irregular line that demarcates layer 4 from layer 5 is intended to illustrate the gaps in nc82 label 
in this region. The serrated ventral boundary of layer 1 depicts the seven teeth of this layer, as described below. The gall comprises three regions: 
the gall tip (GT), dorsal gall (DG), and ventral gall (VG). LAL: lateral accessory lobe. EB: ellipsoid body. CRE: crepine. RUB: rubus. NO 1 : dorsal nodu-
lus. NO 2 D: dorsal subcompartment of medial nodulus. NO 2 V: ventral subcompartment of medial nodulus. NO 3 : ventral nodulus; individual subcom-
partments of this neuropil are not indicated in the schematic. B-U: Confocal images and sketches of neurons drawn on the template shown in A. 
Neuropils that are arborized by the neurons are highlighted in black, whereas regions that are not populated by a given neuron are shadowed in 
gray. In the sketches, spiny arbors are drawn as random scribbles and boutons are illustrated as dots. B: PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b. C: PB G2-9 .s-
FB'1.b-NO 3 M.b. D: PB G2-9 .s-FB'2.b-NO 3 A.b. E: PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 D.b. To more accurately depict the morphology of the arbor in layer 3 of the 
FB, it is shown extending into layer 4 in the drawing although in reality, the arbor is confined to layer 3. F: PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 V.b. The sense of 
depth conveyed by the maximum intensity projection of the confocal image is not conveyed in the 2-dimensional drawing. Consequently, the mor-
phology of the NO 2 V arbor appears different in the sketch compared to the confocal image. G: PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>

<p>and anterior-posterior layers called shells (Hanesch 
et al., 1989). The PB neurons characterized here fill the 
entire anterior-posterior depth of the structure, so 
shells will not be discussed further. The number of 
layers in the Drosophila FB has most recently been esti-
mated to be "roughly eight" (Young and Armstrong, 
2010b) or six (Lin et al., 2013). nc82 immunolabeling 
reveals a low-resolution "stratigraphic column" of seven 
distinct layers in the FB, based on quality, texture, and 
intensity of the immunoreactivity, which reflect the den-
sity of synapses (Fig. 5A). </p>

<p>Volumes defined by the profiles of MCFO-labeled cells 
that arborize in the FB provide a higher-resolution map 
of FB layers. This more detailed neuronal landscape 
reveals there are at least nine layers (Fig. 5; abbreviated 
'1-'9). A particularly informative example is a local 
interneuron that arborizes in only two layers of the FB 
(Fig. 5B, left inset). In the example shown in Fig. 5B, the 
arbor is spiny in FB'8 and has output terminals in the 
dorsalmost layer, the "cap" of the FB, currently assigned 
as layer 9. The bouton-rich arbor is clearly confined to 
the dorsal layer of the FB (Fig. 5B), which is not </p>

<p>Figure 3. H: PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b. I: PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b. J: PB G9 .b-EB.P.s-ga-t.b. K: PB.s-FB'6.b.'3.s-Vga-s.b (the ventral gall sur-
round, or Vga-s, is a region that appears to surround the ventral gall). L: PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b. M: PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b. N: 
PB.b-LAL.s-PS.s. Cell body is anterior, at the level of the anterior lobes. O: PB G6-8 .s G9 .b. (Continued). </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>revealed as a distinct layer in nc82-labeled specimens 
but instead blends with the next more ventral layer (Fig. 
5A). Furthermore, the arbor does not completely fill the 
dorsal cap, possibly indicating there is yet another, even 
more dorsal layer (Fig. 5B, right inset, arrow). 
A more subtle example is illustrated by a large field 
neuron with unilateral spiny branches in the superior 
protocerebrum (not shown) and a sparse apparently 
presynaptic arbor throughout a layer that resides 
between layers 1 and 2 of the FB (Fig. 5C, red, '1d/ </p>

<p>2v). While this cell may help define a new, narrow layer, 
alternatively it may occupy an upper substratum of 
layer 1 or, more likely, based on nc82 labeling, a lower 
substratum of layer 2. FB layers 2-5 are shown in Fig-
ure 5D. Another large field neuron arborizes along the 
dorsal margin of the synapse-dense layer, identified 
here as layer 6 (Fig. 5E1-E3). If this layer, FB'6d, and 
the previously mentioned FB'1d/2v, are ultimately 
determined to be separate layers, there would be at 
least 11 layers in the FB. </p>

<p>Figure 3. P: PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b. Q: PB18.s-9i1i8c.b. R: PB G1/2-9 .b-SPSi.s. S: PB G2-9 .b-IB.s.SPS.s, the ipsilateral version. Cell bodies for this 
neuron are posterior to the PB. Since the IB partially overlaps with the FB, the FB was excluded from this and the drawing in (T) to avoid 
inadvertently suggesting the neuron arborizes in the FB. T: PB G2-9 .b-IB.s.SPS.s, the contralateral version. U: PB.s-EBw.AMP.s-Dga-s.b (note 
this is likely a variant of the EBw.AMP.s-Dga-s.b cell). Scale bars 5 14 lm in B,C,D; 11 lm in E,L; 13 lm in F; 10 lm in G,H,I,K,O,P,S,T,U; 
6 lm in J,N,Q,R; 8 lm in M. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>TABLE 3A. 
Comparison of Cell Types I </p>

<p>Wolff et al. cell name 
Lin et al. cell name 
Wolff et al. features 
Lin et al. features </p>

<p>1 
P B G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b 
PB 1-glomerulus -&gt;FB f -No L4 
does not arborize in G1 
arborizes in all glomeruli 
arborizes in subcompartment 
of NO 3 </p>

<p>arborizes in separate 
nodulus: NO 4 
2 
P B G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 M.b 
NI 
does not arborize in G1 
3 
P B G2-9 .s-FB'2.b-NO 3 A.b 
PB 1-glomerulus -&gt;FB e -No L3 
does not arborize in G1 
arborizes in all glomeruli 
4 
P B G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 D.b 
PB 1-glomerulus -&gt;FB d -No L2 
does not arborize in G1 
arborizes in all glomeruli 
5 
P B G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 V.b 
NI 
does not arborize in G1 
6 
P B G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b 
PB 1-glomerulus -&gt;EB P -No R1 
does not arborize in G1 
arborizes in all glomeruli 
7 
P B G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b 
PB 1-glomerulus -&gt;EB C -IDFP DSB 
does not arborize in G9 
arborizes in all glomeruli 
odd G to D gall; even 
G to V gall </p>

<p>all glomeruli to D gall </p>

<p>glomerular tendrils 
respect "odd/even rule" 
8 
P B G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b 
EB C,O,P -&gt;EB C,O,P -
IDFP D/VSB -PB 1-glomerulus </p>

<p>does not arborize in G9 
arborizes in all glomeruli </p>

<p>considered same cell type as 
EB C,P -&gt;EB C,P -IDFP DSB -
PB 1-glomerulus 
odd G to D gall; even 
G to V gall </p>

<p>G1 to D or V gall; G3,5,7 to 
V gall; G2,4,6,8 to D gall 
1:1 PB:EB correspondence 
glomerular tendrils respect 
"odd/even rule" </p>

<p>3:1 PB:EB and 1:5 
PB:EB correspondence </p>

<p>evidence for mixed terminals 
mixed spiny and bouton terminals 
is ambiguous 
9 
P B G9 .s-EB.P.s-ga-t.b 
EB C,P -&gt;EB C,P -IDFP DSB -
PB 1-glomerulus </p>

<p>arborizes only in G9 
considered same cell type as 
EB C,O,P -&gt;EB C,O,P -IDFP D/VSB -
PB 1-glomerulus 
EB arbor is sparse but 
fills entire wedge </p>

<p>EB arbor fills half a wedge </p>

<p>arborizes in gall tip 
arborizes in dorsal gall 
10 
PB.s-FB'6.b.'3.s-Vga-s.b 
PB 1-glomerulus -FB b,d -IDFPDSB 
11 
PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b 
PB 1-glomerulus -FB c,d -&gt;IDFP RB 
G1 arbor projects 
ipsilaterally </p>

<p>G1 arbor projects either 
ipsilaterally or contralaterally 
arborizes in 3 FB layers 
arborizes in 2 FB layers 
12 
PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b 
PB 1-glomerulus -FB e -&gt;IDFP HB-lateral 
does not arborize in 
2 most lateral glomeruli </p>

<p>does not arborize in single 
most lateral glomerulus 
13 
PB.b-LAL.s-PS.s 
CVLP medial -IDFP HB-lateral -
VMP lateral -&gt;PB 16-glomeruli 
14 
PB G6-8 .s G9 .b 
PB 6-glomeruli 
15a 
PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b 
PB 15-glomeruli 
same cell type as 
PB18.s-9i1i8c.b </p>

<p>different cell type from 
PB16-glomeruli 
spiny arbor in all 
glomeruli </p>

<p>spiny arbor in all but 
one glomerulus 
bouton arbors spaced 
7 glomeruli apart </p>

<p>bouton arbors spaced 
5 glomeruli apart 
15b 
PB18.s-9i1i8c.b 
PB 16-glomeruli 
same cell type as 
PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b </p>

<p>different cell type from 
PB15-glomeruli 
presynaptic arbors 
spaced 7 glomeruli 
apart </p>

<p>presynaptic arbors spaced 
6 glomeruli apart </p>

<p>16 
PB G1/2-9 .b-SPSi.s 
NI </p>

<p>17 
PB G2-9 .b-IB.s.SPS.s 
CCP ventral -VMP dorsal -
&gt;PB 2-glomeruli </p>

<p>arborizes in 1 to 
several G, not </p>

<p>arborizes in 2 adjacent 
glomeruli 
necessarily adjacent 
does not arborize in G1 </p>

<p>18 
NI 
PB 1-glomerulus -FB c,d,e,f -
&gt;IDFP HB-medial </p>

<p>17 cell types 
14 cell types 
Net total: 18 PB cell types 
NI: not identified in this study </p>

<p>The actual number of layers in the FB will likely 
remain unresolved until two prerequisites are met. First, 
the features of what constitutes a layer need to be for-
mally defined. The two most likely options are to define 
them based on either function or anatomy, or perhaps 
as some combination of the two. Second, all neurons 
that arborize in the FB must be identified and consoli-
dated into a single, standard brain so that their relative 
volumes can be compared directly. 
Vertical striations evident in nc82-labeled FBs give 
the neuropil a columnar appearance. In addition, the 
arbors of small field neurons in the FB occupy horizon-
tally constrained domains in the layers in which they 
arborize, lending a columnar appearance to the FB in 
samples with labeled neurons. In at least some cases, 
the margins of arbors in the FB were used to determine 
the width and, by extrapolation, the number of columns, 
although there is not a consensus on the number of 
columns in the FB. In Drosophila, Hanesch et al. (1989) 
suggest there are either 8 or 16, while Lin et al. (2013) 
favor eight. Strausfeld (1976) describes 14 staves in 
Musca and Calliphora and 8, each with two subunits, in 
Drosophila (Strausfeld, 2012) compared with Heinze 
and Homberg (2008), who describe 16 columns in the 
CBU of Schistocerca. 
It has been assumed that the number of columns is 
identical in all layers. While a columnar architecture is 
evident in nc82-immunolabeled brains in all layers 
except the cap, the picture that is beginning to emerge 
from the work reported here is that neurons, including 
both PB-FB and FB neurons that do not have projections 
to the PB, do not organize themselves into columns in 
all layers of the FB. Rather, such a restricted pattern of 
arborization may be a phenomenon associated only with </p>

<p>layers 1 through 5. (The only instance of columnar 
arbors in layers 4 and 5 comes from the PB G1-8 .s-
FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b cell.) A more relaxed columnar 
arrangement is evident in layers 4 through 8 (with the 
exception of the PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b cell), in 
which the arbors of various cell types extend horizon-
tally across a greater width than in layers 1 through 3 
(e.g., PB.s-FB'6.b.'3.s-Vga-s.b; see Fig. 3, as well as 
several FB local interneurons). Furthermore, the diminu-
tive, dorsalmost layer, layer 9, which spans only approxi-
mately the medial sixth of the FB, is unlikely to have 
eight or more columns. Data analyzed here support this 
prediction: a columnar organization is not evident in 
layer 9 in nc82-labeled brains, and of the neurons ana-
lyzed to date, each neuron that arborizes in this layer 
has processes that extend throughout more than half of 
the layer. Even in layers 2 and 3, where a columnar 
organization is clearly evident, the boundaries are not 
restrictive, in that arbors from neighboring columns fre-
quently overlap. For example, the apparently presynap-
tic arbors of cells that arborize in FB'2 and FB'3, PB G2-</p>

<p>9 .s-FB'2.b-NO 3 A.b, PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 D.b and PB G2-
9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 V.b (Fig. 3), occupy a geographic space 
that corresponds roughly to the upstream PB glomerulus 
in which these cells also arborize, although these arbors 
can show extensive overlap with those from cells in 
adjacent glomeruli. Finally, no PB-FB cells were identi-
fied in this study that target layers 7-9. 
Published work has proposed either a one-to-one 
(Hanesch et al., 1989; Chiang et al., 2011) or two-to-
one (Lin et al., 2013) correspondence between glomer-
uli in the PB and columns in the FB. In order to distin-
guish between these two possibilities and to reevaluate 
the options with the knowledge that there are 18 glo-
meruli in the PB, it was necessary to determine the 
number of columns in the FB. This number is difficult to 
evaluate given that the arbors of neurons overlap with 
one another, sometimes extensively. However, we show 
that the morphology of layer one ('1) of the FB is 
unique compared to the other layers and therefore pro-
vides an unambiguous opportunity to count columns. 
All layers of the FB have smooth dorsal and ventral 
margins except FB'1 (and possibly the FB'4/FB'5 
boundary). The ventral margin of FB'1 is delineated by a 
total of seven distinct teeth resembling cogs, plus an 
additional two "cryptic teeth" that are elusive in that 
they are not evident in nc82-labeled samples, but only in 
specimens with the right combination of labeled cells. 
Five of the seven teeth are shown in the focal plane in 
Figure 6A; a cryptic tooth is seen in Figure 6B and Movie 
3. The FB is shaped like a negative meniscus, curved 
such that the center is posterior to the edges, as previ-
ously reported (Hanesch et al., 1989; Strausfeld, 2012). </p>

<p>TABLE 3B. 
Comparison of Cell Types II </p>

<p>Hanesch et al. (1989) 
Wolff et al. </p>

<p>1 
pb-fb-no 
PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b 
PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 M.b 
PB G2-9 .s-FB'2.b-NO 3 A.b 
PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 D.b 
PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 V.b 
2 
pb-eb-no 
PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b 
3 
pb-fb-eb 
NI 
4 
pb-fb/pb-fb-fb 
NI 
5 
pb-eb/pb-eb-eb 
NI 
6 
pb-no 
NI 
7 
pb-fb-vbo 
PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>8 
pb-eb-vbo 
PB.b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>9 
pb-eb-ltr 
PB.s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 
PB large field 
PB18.s.GxD7Gy.b </p>

<p>NI: not identified in this study. VBO is now called the LAL. LTR is now 
called the BU. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Likely equivalent to corresponding Hanesch et al. cell type. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>TABLE 4. </p>

<p>Protocerebral Bridge Cell Types </p>

<p>Neuron Cell Type </p>

<p>GAL4 Line # </p>

<p>Figure </p>

<p>Special features </p>

<p>PB 
G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO </p>

<p>3 P.b 
R15D05, R20C08, R26C04, R38G07, R44C06, R65B12, R85H06 </p>

<p>3B, 6, 16 </p>

<p>no G1 </p>

<p>PB 
G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO </p>

<p>3 M.b 
R15E12, R20C08, R65B12, R85H06 </p>

<p>3C, 16 </p>

<p>no G1 </p>

<p>PB 
G2-9 .s-FB'2.b-NO </p>

<p>3 A.b 
R16D01, R20C08, R26C04, R37A12, R41H08, R65B12 </p>

<p>3D, 16 </p>

<p>no G1 </p>

<p>PB 
G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO </p>

<p>2 D.b 
R16D01, R20A08, R38C04, R41G11, R44C06, R65B12, R65D07 </p>

<p>3E, 16 </p>

<p>no G1 </p>

<p>PB 
G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO </p>

<p>2 V.b 
R13D09, R26C04, R37F06, R38C04, R41G11 </p>

<p>3F, 16 </p>

<p>no G1 </p>

<p>PB 
G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO </p>

<p>1 .b 
R12D09, R13D05, R33A12, R37F06,R41G11, R41H08, R65B12 </p>

<p>3G, 4, 8, 11,14 </p>

<p>no G1 </p>

<p>PB 
G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b </p>

<p>R33A12 </p>

<p>2, 3H, 4, 7, 8, 10,13, 14, 17 
Even glomeruli to ventral gall; odd glomeruli to dor-
sal gall; no G9 </p>

<p>PB 
G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b 
R15C03, R19G02, R26B12, R26C04, R33A12, R60D05 </p>

<p>3I, 4, 7, 8, 9, 10,13, 15, 17 
Even glomeruli to ventral gall; odd glomeruli to dor-
sal gall; no G9 </p>

<p>PB 
G9 .b-EB.P.s-ga-t.b </p>

<p>R26B12, R27G06, R33A12 </p>

<p>3J, 13, 18 
G9 only; only PB cell that arborizes in gall tip </p>

<p>PB.s-FB'6.b.s.'3.s-Vga-s.b </p>

<p>R33A12, R38C04 </p>

<p>3K </p>

<p>PB arbor very minor </p>

<p>PB 
G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b </p>

<p>R27G06, R33A12, R41G11 </p>

<p>2, 3L, 21, 22 
no G9; G1 cell usually follows ipsilateral projection; 
G1i arbor resides lateral to G8c arbor in FB </p>

<p>PB 
G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b </p>

<p>R11B11, R13D09, R44C06 </p>

<p>3M, 19 
no G9, no G8; most G1 cells project ipsilaterally; 
LAL arbor comes in 3 lengths; PB arbors 
multiglomerular </p>

<p>PB.b-LAL.s-PS.s </p>

<p>R51B11 </p>

<p>3N </p>

<p>PB 
G6-8 .s 
G9 .b </p>

<p>R18G01, R41H08 </p>

<p>3O, 18 </p>

<p>PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>R12E10, R34E11, R38G07, R41H08 </p>

<p>3P, 18 
dendritic arbor in 18 glomeruli; 2 glomeruli --sepa-
rated by 7 glomeruli --have pre-synaptic clusters </p>

<p>PB18.s-9i1i8c.b </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>R12E10, R34E11, R33D11, R38G07, R41H08 </p>

<p>3Q 
3 presynaptic clusters at G9 and G1, both ipsi, and 
G8 on contralateral side; 7 empty glomeruli 
between each cluster </p>

<p>PB 
G1/2-9 .b-SPSi.s </p>

<p>R33D11 </p>

<p>3R, 18 </p>

<p>PB 
G2-9 .b-IB.s.SPS.s </p>

<p>R47G08, R50C12 </p>

<p>3S, 3T, 18 
no G1; one cell arborizes in generally 1-2 and up 
to 3 glomeruli; PB and IB/SPS arbors can both 
be ipsilateral, or PB ipsi-and IB/SPS 
contralateral </p>

<p>15D05: PB.s-FB'1.b-NO 
3 P.b cells seen only in odd glomeruli in line 15D05. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>These two cells are likely the same cell type. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>The central tooth is most posterior and flanked on each 
side by three prominent and increasingly anterior teeth. 
The most lateral two cryptic teeth are the smallest and 
lie ventral and anterior to their nearest neighbors (Fig. 
6B,D, Movie 3). The cell type PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b 
(Figs. 3, 6C) reveals a total of nine columns in '1 of the 
FB. These cells arborize in eight glomeruli (G2-G9) on </p>

<p>each side of the midline. Cells from two glomeruli, one 
ipsilateral and one contralateral, project to each of the 
seven distinct teeth. The lateralmost, cryptic teeth, how-
ever, receive input from just one contralateral glomeru-
lus each (Fig. 6D; the details of the wiring diagram are 
described below). PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b cells therefore 
reveal a total of nine columns in layer 1 of the FB. </p>

<p>Figure 4. The protocerebral bridge comprises 18 glomeruli. MCFO-labeled protocerebral bridge neurons highlight individual glomeruli in 
distinct colors. The PB is also immunolabeled with nc82, so glomeruli not containing stochastically labeled cells are gray (see lines and 
asterisks). The protocerebral bridges of both female (C,D,F-L) and male (A,B,E) brains each have 18 glomeruli. Brains from three GAL4 
lines are shown, although the presence of 18 glomeruli is universal among all lines. A-H: [R33A12], a mixture of PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b 
and PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b neurons; I,J: [R37F06], PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b neurons; K,L: [R60D05], PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b neurons; K: 
see also Movie 1; L: see also Movie 2. Movies 1 and 2: Each movie shows a different PB with MCFO-labeled cells in the glomeruli. 
Between zero and two cells arborize in each glomerulus. Numbers identify each glomerulus and are color-coded according to the color of 
the cells that arborize in the corresponding glomeruli. Scale bar 5 8 lm. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>A second example of column number for '1 is illustrated 
by the previously unreported cell type FB'1.b-NO 3 P.s-LAL.s.b-
cre.s.b, which has distinct tufts of boutons in FB'1 (Fig. 6E). 
In this cell, there are four tufts per side and two centrally 
located tufts (both of which occupy the larger, medial tooth). 
Each tuft stems from a separate branch, and each branch 
arises from the primary neurite; these branches help to distin-
guish the tufts. The arborization pattern of this large-field neu-
ron is consistent with the observation that there are a total 
of nine columns in FB'1. (One could argue that there are 10 
columns since the two medial tufts are distinct. However, </p>

<p>since the center tooth is a single, morphological unit, we 
opted to consider the center tooth a single column.) </p>

<p>Elaborate set of neuropil volumes partitions 
the ellipsoid body </p>

<p>The EB is shaped like a torus, or donut (Fig. 1). The 
arbors of neurons that innervate this central complex struc-
ture define multiple, distinct, but overlapping volumes 
within the EB. These arbors reveal a highly complex yet 
exquisitely well-organized tangle of synaptic inputs and </p>

<p>Figure 5. Layers of the FB. A: nc82-labeled adult FB. Asterisks identify layers discriminated by their synaptic density and distribution. B-
E: MCFO-labeled fan-shaped bodies. B: Layer 9 is the "cap" of the FB. A local interneuron that arborizes in two layers of the FB (left inset) 
terminates at sites presumed to be presynaptic at the top of the FB. It does not fill the entire cap (right inset, arrow); this unfilled tip may 
define yet another, more dorsal, layer. C: A red, large-field neuron arborizes in the FB between FB'1 and FB'2 (layer 1d/2v). This neuron 
defines either a separate layer or a sublayer of either FB'1 or FB'2. Layer 3 is not evident at this angle of orientation. D: MCFO of a brain 
from GAL4 line [R34E11] reveals a distinct, unlabeled layer 3 between layers 2 and 4, both of which are clearly delineated by MCFO-
labeled neurons. E1: The dorsal layers 9, 8, and 6 are highlighted by MCFO-labeled neurons; layer 7 appears as a gap labeled only with 
nc82. A large-field neuron arborizes throughout only the dorsal half of layer 6 (the ventral half is labeled with nc82, as shown in E2), per-
haps defining it as a separate layer. The exclusion of the red layer 8 neuron from layer 9 and the green layer 9 neuron from layer 8 sub-
stantiates the assignment of these domains as distinct layers [GAL4 line R34H05]. E2: High-magnification view of E1 with nc82 label 
included. Layers 5 and 7 are evident, as is the synapse-dense ventral region of layer 6 from which the green neuron in E1 is excluded. 
E3: Sagittal view of brain shown in panel E1 highlights the dorsal position of the green neuron in layer 6. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>outputs and hint at the sophisticated circuits of cells that 
target this structure. This work identifies new volumes and 
elaborates on previously defined volumes of the EB. </p>

<p>Layers/rings </p>

<p>The EB is partitioned along its radius into concentric 
annuli, or rings (Hanesch et al., 1989; Renn et al., 1999; 
Young and Armstrong, 2010b), of varying diameters. 
(Note that in other neuropterans the homologous subdivi-
sions are layers rather than rings since the EB and homol-
ogous upper division of the central body, or CBL, are not 
circular.) The striking arbors of the "ring neurons" form vir-
tually complete rings within the boundaries of the EB and 
help to accentuate these regions. The rings do not fill the 
anteroposterior depth of the torus (see below). The mor-
phology of the ring neurons has been described else-
where (Hanesch et al., 1989; Young and Armstrong, 
2010b). As discussed for layers of the FB, an accurate 
and complete catalog of the number of rings in the EB will 
only be possible with an exhaustive analysis of all neurons 
that form ring-like arbors in the EB. </p>

<p>Shells </p>

<p>The EB is layered on its anteroposterior axis. Hanesch 
et al. (1989) cited two such layers and named them the 
anterior and posterior rings; Young and Armstrong 
(2010b) observed four such rings. Since the term "shell" 
was used to define similar anteroposterior layers in the 
FB (Hanesch et al., 1989), we will refer to such antero-
posterior divisions of the EB as shells both to maintain a 
consistent terminology and so as to not confuse anterior 
and posterior rings with the concentric rings of the EB. 
The studies reported here reveal three distinct, com-
plete shells in the EB. The shells are evident in nc82-
immunolabeled preparations and are highlighted more 
clearly in brains with labeled cells, particularly brains in 
which the ring neurons are labeled (Fig. 7). EB arbors 
fill the entire volume of the shells they occupy. Some 
cell types fill just one shell (e.g., Fig. 7A,B), whereas 
others fill more than one (Fig. 7C,D). The arbor of one </p>

<p>Figure 6. Projection pattern between the PB and FB'1. A: nc82-
labeled FB. This focal plane illustrates the medial and two neigh-
boring teeth on each side of the midline. B: Distinction between 
the lateralmost and cryptic teeth of FB'1. The green arbor, con-
sisting of boutons, is in the lateralmost tooth and originates from 
a PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b neuron in G3L. The blue, bouton-rich 
arbor is in the cryptic tooth and arises from a PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-
NO 3 P.b neuron that arborizes in G2L [R65B12]. These FB'1 
domains are also illustrated in Movie 3. C: PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-
NO 3 P.b neuron. D: Schematic representation of PB:FB'1 circuitry 
of the PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b neuron. The glomeruli in which this 
neuron arborizes (G2-G9), the specific FB teeth they target and 
the lines connecting them, are similarly colored to more easily 
follow the projection pattern for this cell type. The numbers 
beneath each tooth of the FB refer to the glomeruli from which 
they receive input, and "i" and "c" refer to ipsilateral and contra-
lateral. The arbors from pairs of neurons that target the same 
teeth intermingle within the FB domains, although for clarity the 
colors are separated in the schematic. At the second junction, 
between the FB and NO, the primary neurites from G9-G6 cross 
the midline to arborize in the contralateral noduli (not shown). 
The remaining projections, from G5-G2, have already crossed the 
midline and therefore do not cross the midline again. E: Two 
examples of FB'l.b-NO 3 P.s-LAL.s.b-cre.s.b neurons [R44C06] high-
light FB'1 teeth with tufts of boutons. Each tuft is located in a 
separate tooth with the exception of the central tooth, which 
houses two tufts; asterisks identify the tufts. A clear distinction 
between the left, lateral two teeth in the red example (right 
panel) is obscured in this focal plane, although the individual neu-
rites leading to the tufts are evident and reveal the separate 
arbors. The two ventral tufts in both the green (left) and red 
(right) neurons that are not marked with asterisks arborize in the 
noduli. Movie 3 shows NO 1 , NO 2 and a small portion of the FB. 
The green cell originates from G2L in the PB and arborizes in the 
cryptic tooth of the FB (labeled C). The blue boutons are in the 
most lateral tooth and course from G9R in the PB. The more 
medial green arbor (not labeled) arises from G8R. Left scale 
bar 5 8 lm, right scale bar 5 10 lm in E. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>cell type, the EB.w.AMP.s-Dga-s.b cell (Fig. 7D), extends 
the entire depth of the EB, populating the anterior, 
medial, and posterior shells (AMP). (More specifically, 
this cell has spiny arbors in all three shells-anterior, 
medial, and posterior-of an EB wedge, and bouton-type 
terminals in an undefined region surrounding the dorsal 
gall, which we call the Dorsal gall-surround.) A previ-
ously uncharacterized R1-like neuron, EBR1.b-cre.s, also 
occupies the anterior shell (not shown). </p>

<p>Nubbin: a new anatomical feature of the EB </p>

<p>This work identifies a previously uncharacterized ana-
tomical feature of the EB: a protuberance on the dorsal 
anterior face of the EB (Fig. 7E, Movie 4). Since it is an 
anteroposterior volume, it could be considered a partial 
shell. We named this region the nubbin (nub) because 
it is a projection that appears stunted and undevel-
oped. The nubbin is evident in nc82-labeled brains and, 
as with other brain regions and subdomains, is defined </p>

<p>as a distinct volume in the EB by the arbors of a neu-
ron, the BU.s-EBnub.b cell, which specifically targets 
this region of the EB (Fig. 7E; [R41G11]). Notably, this 
volume is not targeted by any other neurons identified 
to date. </p>

<p>Wedges and tiles </p>

<p>Two morphologically and functionally distinct volumes 
partition the EB into periodic compartments: wedges 
and tiles. Wedges radially segment the EB, resembling 
slices of a pie. Wedges extend the full radius of the 
torus and, as demonstrated here, occupy either just the 
posterior and medial shells of the EB, or all three shells, 
depending on the cell type (see below). As described 
for columns in the FB, arbors in wedges in the EB also 
do not respect strict boundaries; rather, arbors from 
cells within neighboring wedges overlap to varying 
degrees (see below). These subdivisions are named 
"sectors" in Hanesch et al. (1989), but the term </p>

<p>Figure 7. EB shells and nubbin. A: Anterior (cyan and yellow) and medial (green) shells are highlighted with MCFO-labeled neurons whereas 
the posterior shell lacks signal (gray, nc82). Left panel is an off-axis frontal view to provide a sense of depth of the shells. Right panel is a 
sagittal view [R30F05]. B: Anterior (orange) and posterior (red) shells are highlighted by ring neurons; medial layer is unlabeled. Left panel 
is frontal view, right panel is sagittal view [R13D05]. C: Sagittal views of two EBs are shown. The EB arbors of tile cells, in this case PB G1-</p>

<p>8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells (green, top; yellow, bottom), fill just the posterior shell, whereas the PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cell (red, top and 
bottom) fills both the posterior and medial shells. Arrows identify the anterior shells, which lack labeled arbors. D: Two EBs are shown in 
sagittal view. The EB arbor of EBw.AMP.s-Dga-s.b cells (blue and green) fills all three shells: posterior, medial. and anterior. Arrows again 
identify the anterior shell. E: Frontal and side views of a BU.s-EBnub.b neuron. The EB arbor is restricted to the anterior protuberance of the 
EB [R41G11]. This cell is not a PB neuron, but is used to show the morphology of the nubbin. Scale bar 5 19 lm in E. See also Movie 4. 
Anterior is to the right for all side views. Movie 4: The red arbor of a BU.s-EBnub.b neuron fills the nubbin subregion of the EB. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>"wedge" is preferred over "sector" since it implies a 
sense of depth not suggested by sector. 
The second volume, the tile, has not been described 
previously. Tiles also segment the EB around the circum-
ference of the torus, but unlike wedges they are a sur-
face volume, restricted to the posterior shell of the EB. 
While all shells extend from the perimeter of the torus 
to the canal, this feature is not obvious in the posterior 
shell since the diameter of the canal is greater at the 
posterior than at the center of the torus. Consequently, 
in maximum intensity projections tile volumes do not 
appear to extend to the canal. As described for the FB 
and other EB volumes, a few boutons from cells in one 
tile can occupy a neighboring tile (see below). 
Wedges and tiles are functionally distinct. To date, 
the only cell type that has been identified that arborizes 
in the PB and in wedges is spiny in the EB (PB G1-8 .b-
EBw.s-D/Vgall.b; Figs. 3, 8A,C1,C2; note that Lin et al., </p>

<p>2013, characterize the EB arbor in this cell as mixed, 
comprising both dendritic and presynaptic endings, see 
below). A second cell that does not arborize in the PB 
but does arborize in wedges is also spiny in EB wedges 
(EB.w.AMP.s-Dga-s.b, described above). On the con-
trary, the only two cell types identified to date that 
arborize in the PB and occupy the tile domain are 
bouton-rich in the tile (PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b and 
PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b; Figs. 3, 8B,C1,C2,D1,D2). </p>

<p>There is a 1:1 correspondence between PB 
glomeruli and EB wedges for a given cell 
type </p>

<p>The circuitry that connects the structures of the cen-
tral complex and its accessory neuropils resembles an 
intricate labyrinth. A cell-type-by-cell-type analysis of 
the underlying circuits reveals that, despite the </p>

<p>Figure 8. Wedge and tile cells. A: PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-Vgall.b. B: PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-Dgall.b. C1: PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-Vgall.b (left) and PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-Vgall.b 
(right) cells. C2: Same cells as shown in C1 with nc82 for reference. PB in left panel; EB and gall in center panel; dorsal gall, right panel. D1: 
PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b cell. D2: Same cell as shown in D1 with nc82 for reference. PB shown in left panel and EB and NO 1 in right panel. Note 
that the profile of the FB is replaced by that of the EB in more anterior focal planes. In the plane shown here, the FB is just beginning to give 
way to the EB, so the EB arbor appears to reside in the FB. PB: protocerebral bridge; EB: ellipsoid body; GA: gall; NO: nodulus. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>apparent undecipherable confusion, cells for the most 
part adhere to a fundamental set of wiring rules. These 
are outlined in the sections that follow. 
As with the FB, there is thought to be a 1:1 corre-
spondence between PB and EB volumes. Hanesch et al. 
(1989) report between 12 and 16 sectors in the EB, </p>

<p>whereas Strausfeld (2012) and Lin et al. (2013) pro-
pose there are 16. If such a 1:1 correspondence exists, 
this work raises two questions: whether there are 16 or 
18 wedges and tiles, and, if there are 16, how the cir-
cuits are designed to accommodate the discrepancy. 
MCFO-labeled brains were used to glean insight into </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>the anatomical organization of the EB with respect to 
the PB and to identify the number of divisions, both 
wedges and tiles, in the EB. 
Of the PB-EB neurons analyzed to date, the maxi-
mum number of glomeruli targeted by a given small 
field PB-EB neuron is 16-no PB-EB small field neurons 
have been identified for which a single cell type tar-
gets each of the 18 glomeruli. Instead, those neurons 
that arborize in 16 glomeruli target either G1-G8 or 
G2-G9, leaving one glomerulus per side "empty," or 
without an arbor. Consequently, we expect either that: 
1) there are 18 volumes in the EB (both wedges and 
tiles), and two of the 18 lack arbors, or 2) there are 
16 volumes and there is a 1:1 correspondence 
between the PB and EB. 
PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cells (Figs. 3, 8A,C1,C2) rep-
resent the only cell type identified so far that arborizes 
in both the PB and in wedges in the EB. Although Lin 
et al. (2013) characterize the EB arbor of this cell as 
"mixed," comprising both pre-and postsynaptic domains, 
our analysis of the morphology and polarity (using anti-
synaptotagmin) of the transmission is inconclusive for 
presynaptic terminals in the EB. To determine the num-
ber of wedges in the EB, the MCFO technique was used 
to label PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cells at both low and 
high density (Fig. 9). Sparsely labeled brains were used 
to: 1) establish the number of wedges in the EB and 2) 
map the circuits between individual glomeruli and small 
increments-equivalent to half-hour increments on a 
clock face-of the EB. This "circuitry template" enabled a </p>

<p>"dissection" of the more complicated, densely labeled 
brains, which were effectively used to confirm the results 
of the sparsely labeled brains. 
The projections of PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cells in 
three densely labeled brains, each containing 13-14 
labeled glomeruli (of 16 possible, since G9 lacks an arbor 
from this cell type), were tracked from PB glomeruli to EB 
wedges (Fig. 9, Movies 5 and 6). When like-colored pri-
mary neurites from different glomeruli overlapped one 
another, the circuits established from sparsely labeled 
brains were used as a guide to "untangle" their intersect-
ing paths to their respective wedges in the EB. As neces-
sary, color channels were toggled on and off to create 
different combinations of colors for each cell so that the 
precise arborization domains for each cell could be deter-
mined. This strategy, in combination with the circuitry 
template, enabled the following five conclusions to be 
drawn. 1) There are 16 wedges, and arbors sometimes 
fill just half a wedge ("demi-wedges"). There is no dis-
cernible anatomical distinction between cells that occupy 
entire vs. demi-wedges, other than the boundaries of the 
wedge arbor. 2) When two cells are labeled in a single 
glomerulus, their arbors either overlap completely in a 
given volume of the EB, or they occupy adjacent demi-
wedges. Of the 41 glomeruli labeled in these three 
brains, most had one or two labeled cells in a single glo-
merulus and just two had three labeled cells. In both 
instances of glomeruli containing three labeled cells, the 
arbors of two of these cells overlapped, whereas the third 
occupied an adjacent volume; it is likely that the two </p>

<p>Figure 9. The EB comprises 16 wedges and 32 demi-wedges. A1-A3: Confocal images and schematics of MCFO-labeled protocerebral bridges 
and corresponding ellipsoid bodies from three densely labeled brains. Cell type: PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b. Colors used in the schematics do not 
necessarily correspond to the colors in the confocal images because of color redundancy in the data panels. Two of the 41 labeled glomeruli shown 
in these three brains had three labeled cells each: G4R and G8R in A1. Note that in A1, the green cell in G4R transitions to yellow in the EB due to 
ramping of the laser power during imaging. To minimize confusion, this cell is green in the schematic in both the PB and EB. Brains shown in A1 and 
A3 are from line [R60D05]; brain in A2 is from [R33A12]. B,C: Demi-wedges are illustrated in these high magnification confocal images of small por-
tions of two ellipsoid bodies. Two cells are labeled in the glomeruli (insets) corresponding to the wedges shown. For each example, three panels 
are shown. The first shows both cells (or both colors), followed by each color shown separately to illustrate the gap, or demi-wedge, occupied by 
the partner cell. The asterisks identify the two demi-wedges corresponding to a single wedge. Note that while there is some overlap between these 
EB arbors, there is a clear distinction between the two arbors that originate from the same glomerulus. B: An enlargement of a portion of the EB 
shown in A1; the region of interest is G4L, which contains a red and blue cell, shown in inset. See also Movie 5. C: The wedge labeled with blue and 
red arbors (9:00, red and yellow asterisks) exemplifies an instance in which the arbors from two cells from the same glomerulus both occupy the 
entire wedge. These cells arborize apparently presynaptically in G3R. The blue and green cells occupy adjacent demi-wedges of a single wedge 
and have their PB bouton arbors in G8L (inset). Brain shown in C is from line [R60D05] and is the same brain shown in Movie 6. Movie 5 The red 
and blue cells highlighted here with asterisks occupy adjacent demi-wedges of the same wedge. Cells both arborize in G4L of the PB (shown in Fig. 
9). The gaps that appear when the red and blue channels are turned off are the demi-wedges. Movie 6 illustrates two cells with bouton-type arbors 
in a single glomerulus, G8L (labeled G8), and postsynaptically in adjacent demi-wedges in the EB. One cell is green, the second is blue; they arbo-
rize in the EB at 8:00. The densest regions of the spiny arbors in the demi-wedges, the spines (as in backbones), are marked with the paired blue 
and green asterisks. There is a second green cell that arborizes at about 11:00 in the EB that does not arise from G8L (yellow asterisk). A second 
pair of cells, one red and one blue (paired red and blue asterisks), projects from G3R (glomerulus not shown). These cells arborize in the EB at 
10:00 and overlap extensively in either the same wedge or demi-wedge. The Z series of the blue cell illustrates the projection of the cell (orange 
arrow identifies primary neurite) that arborizes in G8 to the lower blue arbor in the EB (orange asterisk). Similarly, the Z series of the green cell 
shows the projection from G8 to the green demi-wedge in the EB (purple asterisk), although this path is more difficult to follow. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>volumes occupied by these three cells represent demi-
wedges of a single wedge. When only one cell was 
labeled in a glomerulus, it generally appeared to fill the 
entire wedge, although in some instances there was an 
unlabeled adjacent volume. There are likely to be more 
blank demi-wedges than can be discerned in these 
brains, but given the high density of labeled cells and the 
fact that spiny branches can spill into neighboring vol-
umes (see 4, below), unlabeled demi-wedges are difficult 
to detect. 3) There is a 1:1 correspondence between glo-
meruli and EB wedges: Wedges and demi-wedges receive </p>

<p>arbors exclusively from cells in a single glomerulus and 
arbors from a single glomerulus arborize in only one 
wedge or two paired demi-wedges. In other words, an 
arbor arising from a cell in one glomerulus has not been 
seen to share either a wedge or a demi-wedge with an 
arbor of a cell arising from a different glomerulus. (Note 
that this observation is primarily gathered from the 
sparsely labeled brains.) 4) Arbors from neighboring 
wedges can overlap at the edges of their arborizations 
domains, sometimes quite extensively (Fig. 10). 5) Arbors 
arising from cells that target G1 and G5 target wedges at </p>

<p>Figure 10. Arbors in EB wedge and tile domains are not confined within strict boundaries. A: Spiny arbors of three PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/ 
Vgall.b cells in three adjacent EB wedges are shown: The central green cell's arbor is bordered dorsally by the red cell and ventrally by 
the blue cell. The spiny arbors of PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cells in wedge domains are dense centrally, resembling a backbone, and 
become increasingly sparse peripherally. The lines identify the approximate extreme lateral limits of spiny arbors from adjacent wedges. 
While there is variability in the extent of the domains of arborizations, arbors do not extend beyond the adjacent EB domain. The degree 
of overlap of arbors in neighboring wedges is evident in the examples shown in which color channels were separated to illustrate the indi-
vidual neurons. B: Arbors consisting of boutons also extend into neighboring tile domains, illustrated in these five examples. Asterisks 
identify boutons from PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells that intrude into neighboring tile domains. C: Schematics illustrating the extension of 
spiny (top) and bouton (bottom) arbors into adjacent domains. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>clock positions 6:00 and midnight, respectively, with the 
left and right counterparts for each of these glomeruli 
falling on opposite sides of this midline (at approximately 
11:30-12:00/12:00 to 12:30 and 5:30-6:00/6:00-6:30; 
see below for projection map details). 
Two key conclusions can be drawn about wedges, at 
least for the only cell type so far identified to arborize 
in them, the PB G1-8 ps-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cell. First, there 
are 16 wedges in the EB, one for each glomerulus 
arborized by this cell type (G1-G8), and second, arbors 
of some cells occupy the entire wedge, whereas others 
occupy just half a wedge. Whether these cells-full 
wedge vs. demi-wedge-should be classified as distinct 
cell types or not is debatable; answering this question 
will require additional physiological and behavioral 
studies. 
Consistent with the results described above, cell 
counts of the total population of PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/ 
Vgall.b cells in three brains (n 45, 39, and 36) sug-
gest that between two and three cells target each of 
the 16 glomeruli (n divided by 16 glomeruli). It is not 
obvious how these two to three cells are distributed 
among the 16 glomeruli. The data shown in Figure 9 
reveal that the simplest scenario, in which there are 
three cells per glomerulus, one that occupies the full 
wedge, and one for each demi-wedge, cannot be the 
case. Since as many as three cells can arborize in a 
single glomerulus and its corresponding wedge, an 
alternative possibility is that certain glomeruli are 
always targeted by three cells, and others always by 
two cells. No more than three cells were seen to arbo-
rize in a single glomerulus in these studies, perhaps 
excluding yet more complex combinations. Finally, it is 
possible that the volume occupied by the arbors of a 
particular cell is determined by a stochastic develop-
mental event. </p>

<p>Eight tiles constitute the EB </p>

<p>As previously noted, the available evidence suggests 
that tiles are output domains in the EB, whereas 
wedges are input domains, and that tiles innervate just 
the posterior shell of the torus, whereas wedges arbo-
rize in both the posterior and medial shells, as well as 
the anterior shell in the case of the EB.w.AMP.s-Dga-s.b 
cell. A third significant difference between these two 
volumes is that tiles are targeted by cells from two glo-
meruli rather than just one. Consequently, there are 
eight tiles rather than 16, and tiles occupy a wider vol-
ume than do wedges (Fig. 11). 
Just two cell types have been identified that connect glo-
meruli in the PB to tile domains in the EB: PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-
D/Vgall.b (Figs. 3, 8B,C1,C2) and PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b 
(Figs. 3, 8D1,D2). As with the PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b </p>

<p>cells (Figs. 3, 8A,C1,C2), the two PB-EB tile cells are not 
represented in all glomeruli: PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells 
do not arborize in G9, and PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b cells do 
not target G1. The details of the connections between the 
PB and EB domains are described below. </p>

<p>Noduli are composed of subcompartments </p>

<p>nc82 labeling reveals three distinct noduli, each with 
a unique size and shape (Fig. 12) (Young and Arm-
strong, 2010b). The dorsalmost nodulus, "NO 1 ," is the 
smallest, triangular in shape in frontal sections, and is 
displaced anteriorly. NO 1 is also the brightest nodulus in 
nc82-labeled brains and, since nc82 is thought to label 
T-bar ribbons, this brighter signal may therefore reflect a 
greater density of presynaptic sites, suggesting that NO 1 
has the highest synaptic density of the three noduli. The 
medial nodulus, NO 2 , is somewhat rectangular in shape 
in a frontal view and protrudes slightly more anteriorly 
than NO 1 . The ventralmost nodulus, NO 3 , is more square 
than NO 2 and occupies the largest volume of the three. 
NO 2 and NO 3 have distinct subcompartments that are 
revealed by distinguishable texture, contrast, and inten-
sity in nc82-labeled samples and, more definitively, by 
arborization domains of cells that specifically target 
these subregions. NO 1 may also have subcompartments 
(see below). The nomenclature of "subcompartments" 
rather than separate noduli was chosen because these 
subregions are so tightly juxtaposed that there is no 
obvious break in nc82-labeling, and therefore no separa-
tion, between the units (Fig. 12B,D) as there is between 
NO 1 , NO 2 and NO 3 . Cell projections to these subcom-
partments are discussed below. </p>

<p>NO 1 </p>

<p>There appears to be a medial-lateral compartmentaliza-
tion of NO 1 , although this division is less compelling 
than are the subdivisions of NO 2 and NO 3 (described 
below). First, nc82 labeling is uniform across NO 1 , 
which is not the case with NO 2 and NO 3 . Second, just 
one cell type identified to date can arborize exclusively 
in either the medial or lateral half of a dorsal nodulus. 
Of the 35 GAL4 lines examined for this study, only 
two cell types arborize in NO 1 and only one has been 
identified that connects the PB to NO 1 (PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-
NO 1 .b). The arbors of 64% (28 of a total of 44) of 
observed cells of this type fill the entire nodulus. In 
30% (n 5 13) of cases, the arbor is restricted to the 
medial half of the nodulus (Fig. 12A1-A3). The arbors 
in the remaining 7% (n 5 3) filled only the lateral half of 
the nodulus (Fig. 12A4). 
Cells in each of the eight glomeruli associated with 
this cell type, G2-G9, produce arbors that can fill the </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>entire nodulus. However, it is intriguing that the cells that 
arborize only in the medial half of the nodulus arise from 
even glomeruli (with 8/13 arising from G6), and that the 
three cells that arborize only in the lateral NO 1 all arise 
from G5. While the significance of the predisposition for 
the medially arborizing subset of cells to arise from even 
glomeruli, with a majority from G6, and the laterally arbo-
rizing cells to arise from G5 is unclear, these observa-
tions suggest that at least in most cases communication 
from G5 and G6 is restricted to either the medial or lat-
eral half of NO 1 as part of a functional plan. 
In addition to this mediolateral compartmentalization 
of information within NO 1 , an unusual feature of this </p>

<p>nodulus adds further support to the argument that it is 
compartmentalized: nc82 signal in NO 1 sometimes 
appears divided into medial and lateral halves, a phe-
nomenon not seen in the other noduli (not shown). 
While the identification of additional cell types that 
show a medial-lateral preference within NO 1 is neces-
sary to confirm such compartmentalization of NO 1 , a 
selective distribution of information seems likely. </p>

<p>NO 2 </p>

<p>NO 2 comprises two subcompartments, a large dorsal 
(NO 2 D) and a smaller, ventral (NO 2 V) domain (Fig. 12B-
G, Movie 7). NO 2 V resembles a pancake-like pedestal </p>

<p>Figure 11. The EB comprises eight tiles. A-D: MCFO-labeled protocerebral bridges and corresponding ellipsoid bodies from four brains 
from line [R37F06]. The cell type labeled is PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b; the noduli are not shown. The unlabeled gap in the center of the PB 
reflects the fact that this cell type does not arborize in G1. Note that the colors in the PB are not always preserved for a given cell in the 
EB due to laser adjustment (ramping) through a confocal stack. For example, in B the cell that arborizes in G2R is purple in the PB and 
blue in the EB. In this same brain, G9L is pink in the PB due to the presence of two labeled cells, one green and one blue (see inset of 
PB, in which the green and blue channels were independently toggled off to demonstrate the presence of the two neurons); the bouton 
arbors from these two cells are clearly blue and green in the EB. The eight tile volumes are evident in the EB; the glomeruli from which 
they originate are indicated next to each EB tile. In panel A, the EB is shown twice, the second time with the green channel turned off to 
reveal arbors that are obscured by the green channel (i.e., the red arbor from 4R). </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>for NO 2 D in frontal sections (Fig. 12B-G). In rare cases, 
cells that arborize in NO 2 V also extend a thin flange 
anteriorly and dorsally, partially enwrapping NO 2 D (not </p>

<p>shown). NO 2 D is less intensely labeled with nc82 than 
NO 2 V, and so may contain less densely packed synap-
tic sites (Fig. 12B1,B2). </p>

<p>Figure 12. Anatomy of subcompartments of the noduli. A: Frontal view of NO 1 pairs illustrating the apparent subdivision of NO 1 into 
medial and lateral halves. Noduli are from [R65B12] (A1,A2) and [R12D09] (A3,A4). B: Frontal (B1,B3) and sagittal (B2) views of nc82-
labeled (B1,B2) and MCFO-labeled noduli (B3) illustrating the subcompartments of the noduli. B3 is from line [R65B12]. C: Frontal (C1) 
and sagittal (C2,C3) views of subcompartments of noduli. C2 shows the left set of noduli, C3 shows the right noduli of a brain from line 
[R34H05]. D: Sagittal views showing labeled neurons in NO 2 V from line [R37F06]. Black asterisk marks NO 1 . E-G: Sagittal views of 
MCFO-labeled subcompartments of noduli from [R65B12]. (Note that in panel E1 the brighter label in NO 3 P is bleed-through from the neu-
ron labeled in E2.) F,G: The distinction between the three subcompartments of NO 3 is illustrated using the MCFO technique. See accom-
panying Movie 7. Anterior is to the right for all sagittal views. Movie 7: NO 1 , the two subcompartments of NO 2 and the three 
subcompartments of NO 3 are clearly distinguished in this movie. Colored labels correspond to the colors of the cells that fill various com-
partments. NO 1 , NO 2 V, and NO 3 P are labeled only with nc82. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>NO 3 </p>

<p>NO 3 is composed of three domains: the largest, poste-
rior domain, NO 3 P; the smallest, medial domain, NO 3 M; 
and the most anterior domain, NO 3 A, which abuts </p>

<p>NO 3 V (Fig. 12B-G, Movie 7). NO 3 P and NO 3 A are unam-
biguously distinct domains, and even in nc82-labeled 
brains it is easy to distinguish them, with NO 3 A having 
less intense signal and probably therefore being the 
less synaptically dense subcompartment (Fig. 12B2). 
The distinction between NO 3 M and NO 3 P is less 
obvious since, qualitatively, the nc82 label is identical 
in these two subcompartments. However, the distinc-
tion is unambiguous in brains with labeled cells that tar-
get subsets of these compartments (Fig. 12E-G). (Note 
that Lin et al., 2013, describe four noduli. It is likely 
that their NO 3 and NO 4 correspond to what we 
describe as NO 3 A for NO 3 and NO 3 P1NO 3 M for NO 4 .) </p>

<p>Gall comprises three subcompartments </p>

<p>The gall (GA) is a distinct, paisley-shaped neuropil sit-
uated on the "shoulders" of the LAL (Figs. 1, 3). Ito 
et al. (2014) consider it a subregion of the LAL, but 
this work suggests it is an independent neuropil adja-
cent to the LAL. Our analysis of neurons that target 
both the PB and the gall reveal that the gall consists of 
three subdomains. Two large subdomains compose the 
bulk of the gall and were also described by Lin et al. 
(2013), a dorsal (D) and a ventral compartment (V; also 
the most anterior of the three subunits; Fig. 13). The 
previously undescribed minor subdomain is the most 
posterior volume and lies at the dorsal tip of the gall, 
earning it the name "gall tip" (Fig. 13). All three com-
partments are targeted in a cell type-dependent man-
ner. Cells that arborize in the dorsal gall are excluded 
from the gall tip. Only one cell type has been identified 
that targets the gall tip (see below). </p>

<p>Figure 13. Gall subcompartments. A: The three subcompartments 
of the gall are delineated by cells labeled with the MCFO tech-
nique. Subcompartments are labeled in each panel. T: gall tip. D: 
dorsal gall. V: ventral gall. The gall tip is identified by PB G9 .s-
EB.P.s-ga-t.b; the D and V gall are identified by PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-
D/Vgall.b and PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells. B1-B3: Adjacent 
glomeruli (top) and corresponding galls (bottom) containing cells 
labeled using MCFO. nc82 is gray channel in all panels. B1,B2: 
PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b (from line [R60D05]) and B3) PB G1-8 .s-
EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells (from line [R33A12]). B1: Orange cell is in 
G7 and arborizes in the dorsal gall; blue cell is in G6 and arbor-
izes in the ventral gall. B2: Blue cell is in G8 and the ventral gall; 
red cell is in G7 and the dorsal gall. The apparent gap between 
the red and blue cells in the glomeruli is not an intervening glo-
merulus, but is a consequence of both a slightly buckled PB 
between G7/G8 and the fact that the blue arbor does not com-
pletely fill G8. B3: Red cell is in G4 (top) and the ventral gall 
(middle, frontal view), blue cell arborizes in G3 (top) and the dor-
sal gall (middle). Lower panel is a side view of the gall to illus-
trate that the apparent overlap of the red and blue arbors in the 
frontal view is a consequence of the fact that the D and V 
domains are staggered on the D/V axis. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>Neuronal circuits between the protocerebral 
bridge and ellipsoid body </p>

<p>The various cell types that project between the PB 
and volumes in the EB follow the same general trajecto-
ries, although there are cell type-dependent differences 
in the details of the circuit diagrams, largely for two 
reasons. First, since there are 8 tiles and 16 wedges, 
the projection patterns between glomeruli and EB vol-
umes are necessarily distinct. Second, individual cell 
types project to different subsets of glomeruli (for 
example, G1-G8, G2-G9, or exclusively G9 in the case 
of the PB G9 .b-EB.P.s-ga-t.b cell, described below). Con-
sequently, while the overall projection pattern is pre-
served in these unique cell types, the precise 
correspondence between a given glomerulus and a spe-
cific geographic location in the EB differs. 
To map the circuits between the PB and the EB, the 
projections of all cell types that arborize in both the 
PB and EB were traced. For wedge cells, the projec-</p>

<p>tions from the PB to EB wedges were followed in doz-
ens of brains sparsely labeled for the PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-
D/Vgall.b cell type and in three densely labeled brains 
(per brain, 13-14 labeled glomeruli of 16 possible, 
since G9 is not targeted by this cell type) were traced. 
The circuitry template derived from more sparsely 
labeled brains was used as a scaffold to dissect the 
more dense, complex patterns. Brains in which PB G2-</p>

<p>9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b and PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells 
were labeled were used to map the circuits between 
the PB and EB tiles. 
The primary wiring principle is that the glomeruli of 
the PB effectively map linearly onto the EB. The projec-
tions from left to right and right to left are mirror sym-
metrical to one other (Figs. 14, 15). Each half of the PB 
completely enwraps the EB, with the left half wrapping 
clockwise and the right half wrapping counterclockwise 
around the EB. The alignment of the projection pattern 
from PB to EB can be most readily visualized if the EB 
is filleted at its antapex (6:00 on an analog clock face) 
and stretched flat to derive the ancestral, linear form of 
the EB characteristic of non-Drosophilids. For both 
wedge and tile cells, the most lateral glomerulus from 
the left half of the PB aligns to the volume that lies 
approximately between 7:00 and 8:00 on a clock face, 
whereas the most medial volume from the left half 
aligns with 6:00 (5:30-6:30; Figs. 14, 15). For the 
right half of the PB, the most lateral glomerulus aligns </p>

<p>Figure 14. Connectivity between the PB and EB tiles. Schematics 
illustrating the projection patterns between the PB and EB tiles 
for two cell types, each of which targets a different subset of glo-
meruli. Schematics were derived from MCFO-labeled brains. Top: 
PB, middle: EB; bottom: filleted EB, as described in text. Glomer-
uli and their target EB volumes are color-matched. The numbers 
below the PB identify each of the glomeruli, whereas the black 
text around the EB denotes coordinates of an analog clock for 
use as reference. A: This wiring scheme represents the cell type 
PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b, which does not arborize in G1 (gray in PB). 
Two cells, one ipsilateral and one contralateral, arborize in each 
tile. The three distal glomeruli project ipsilaterally in the EB, G6 
and G2 occupy the midline volumes (the zenith and nadir, respec-
tively), and G3-G5 project contralaterally in the EB. This linear 
projection pattern is readily seen by comparing the PB to the fil-
leted EB. B: Wiring scheme for PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells, 
which do not arborize in G9 (gray in PB; [R33A12]). The same 
basic circuitry scheme illustrated in A applies to this cell type, 
but the ipsilateral/contralateral split is shifted laterally by one 
glomerulus since EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells do not arborize in G9 but 
do arborize in G1. Therefore, the three most lateral glomeruli pro-
ject ipsilaterally, G5 and G1 arborize in the midline volumes (the 
apex and antapex, respectively), and G4-G2 project to the con-
tralateral EB. PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells in even-numbered glo-
meruli project to the ventral gall whereas odd-numbered 
glomeruli project to the dorsal gall (labeled D and V above each 
glomerulus of the PB). </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>to the volume approximately between 4:00 and 5:00 
and the most medial glomerulus aligns with 6:00. 
The second principle is collectively illustrated by 
PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cells (Fig. 15) in conjunction 
with the two tile cell types: PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b (Fig. 
14A) and PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b (Fig. 14B). The same 
strategy used to map the circuits of PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/ </p>

<p>Vgall.b cells, described above, was used to map the 
wiring diagrams for the tile cells. As previously noted, 
PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b cells are absent from G1, whereas 
both PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b and PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/ 
Vgall.b cells are not represented in G9. 
The second principle accommodates three features of 
the central complex: 1) There is a disparity between the </p>

<p>Figure 15. Connectivity between the PB and EB wedges. This schematic was constructed based on MCFO-labeled PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/ 
Vgall.b cells, which do not project to G9 (gray in PB). Schematics of the PB, EB, and filleted EB are shown. Between zero and three cells 
are labeled in each glomerulus. Alphanumeric labels on the EB and filleted EB indicate the glomeruli from which cells project to each vol-
ume; the number refers to the glomerulus number, R is shorthand for right, and L for left. Alternating wedges are filled with gray or white 
and demi-wedges are indicated by a solid line that divides each wedge. Various combinations of wedge and demi-wedge arbor fills are 
illustrated. For example, G8R illustrates an example with three labeled cells; the purple and yellow occupy one demi-segment in the EB, 
the green occupies the other demi-segment of the same wedge. G1R has two labeled cells, both of which fill the entire EB wedge that cor-
responds to G1R. G5L and G3R each have just one labeled cell, but G3R fills its entire corresponding wedge, whereas G5L fills just a 
demi-wedge. As with PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells (above), PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cells project to either the dorsal or ventral gall in 
the same glomerulus-specific fashion: even-numbered glomeruli project to the ventral gall whereas odd-numbered glomeruli project to the 
dorsal gall, as indicated by the D and V designations above the PB. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>number of volumes in the PB (18) and EB (16 wedges or 
8 tiles); 2) Information flow is evenly distributed between 
the two brain hemispheres, as the brain generally is bilat-
erally symmetric; 3) Most neurons cross the midline at 
some point in their trajectories; since cells of the central 
complex typically arborize in three structures, cells can 
remain ipsilateral between the first and second neuropils 
and cross the midline between the second and third neu-
ropils, or they can cross the midline between the first 
and second neuropils. To maintain a balanced distribu-
tion of information flow, the point of crossover for cells 
that stay ipsilateral between the first and second sub-
structures shifts by one glomerulus in cells that arborize 
in G1-G8 versus those that arborize in G2-G9 so that 
four glomeruli per side stay ipsilateral at the first junction 
and four cross contralaterally at the first junction. More 
specifically, for cells that arborize in G9-G2, G9-G6 stay 
ipsilateral at the first junction and G5-G2 cross the mid-
line at the first junction (PB-EB; Fig. 14A), whereas for 
cells that target G8-G1, G8-G5 remain ipsilateral at the 
first junction and G4-G1 cross the midline at the first 
junction (Figs. 14B, 15; note that for tiles, two volumes 
are situated on the midline, one at 12:00 and the other 
at 6:00). Therefore, a given glomerulus does not corre-
spond to one single volume in the EB. Rather, the corre-
spondence between each glomerulus and its target 
volume in the EB depends on the cell type. 
The circuits also differ slightly for cell types that arbo-
rize in the two types of EB volumes because there is a dif-
ference in the number of EB subdivisions: 16 wedges and 
8 tiles. The 2:1 correspondence between glomeruli and 
EB tiles results in one ipsilateral and one contralateral glo-
merulus contributing cells that arborize in the same EB 
tile. The arbors in a given EB tile are not segregated, but 
rather are intermingled (Figs. 10, 11, 14). In contrast, 
there is a 1:1 correspondence between glomeruli and EB 
wedges: Cells in each glomerulus target separate wedge 
volumes in the EB and, in some cases, two cells from a 
single glomerulus occupy separate demi-wedges of the 
same wedge. In the case of circuits for cell types that 
arborize in G1-G8, the EB tile and wedge regions that cor-
respond to specific glomeruli (wedges) or pairs of glomer-
uli (tiles) are identical. (For example, both G1 tile cells in 
Fig. 14B and G1 wedge cells in Fig. 15 target the 6:00 
region in the EB.) For cell types that occupy G2-G9, cor-
responding regions in the EB shift by one volume, but the 
correspondence is effectively the same (compare Figs. 
14B and 15 to Fig. 14A; in the G2-G9 cell type, it is the 
G2 cells, not the G1 cells mentioned above, that target 
the 6:00 region in the EB). In other words, although G8R 
and G2L (Fig. 14B) or the equivalent G9R and G3L (Fig. 
14A) for tile cells occupy a single volume (roughly corre-
sponding to clock position 4:00 to 5:00), the geometric </p>

<p>coordinates of this volume are the same as the combined 
volume occupied by the corresponding G8R and G2L 
wedge cells (4:00-5:00). Finally, whereas tile volumes 
straddle the midline (both 6:00 and 12:00), the wedge vol-
umes do not, but instead fall to either side of the midline. </p>

<p>Connectivity principles for the protocerebral 
bridge to the fan-shaped body parallel those 
between the protocerebral bridge and 
ellipsoid body </p>

<p>The unique, tooth-like morphology of FB'1 enabled 
the number of columns to be defined in this layer. It 
also helped reveal the connectivity between the PB and 
layer 1 of the FB by mapping the trajectories of PB G2-</p>

<p>9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b cells between the PB and FB'1. As 
with PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b cells, PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b 
cells are represented in all glomeruli except G1. 
Cells in G9, G8, and G7 map linearly and ipsilaterally 
onto the FB (Fig. 6D). The arbors of cells from G9 
occupy the lateralmost prominent tooth (not the cryptic 
tooth described above). Cells from G8 target the next, 
more medial neighbor, and cells from G7 project to the 
tooth adjacent to the central tooth. Both G6 cell arbors 
project to the large, central tooth, and those from G5, 
G4, and G3 arborize in progressively more lateral teeth 
on the contralateral side, with G3 cells occupying the 
most contralateral, prominent tooth. As a consequence 
of this projection pattern, the ipsilateral G9 cell arbors 
coarborize with the contralateral G3 cell arbors, the 
ipsilateral G8 cell pairs with the contralateral G4, and 
the ipsilateral G7 cell pairs with the contralateral G5. 
This wiring diagram is effectively identical to that seen 
between the PB and EB for PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b cells 
(Fig. 14A). In a wiring scheme that parallels that 
described for the PB-EB projections, the expectation is 
that the cells in G2 would project to the FB's equivalent 
geographic location of the antapex (i.e., the most lateral 
domains in the filleted EB and the cryptic teeth in 
FB'1)-and they do (Fig. 6D). However, unlike the other 
teeth of FB'1, which receive input from both an ipsilat-
eral and contralateral cell, the arbors that arise from 
cells in G2 appear to be the sole occupants of their 
FB'1 domains. These domains are not readily apparent 
in nc82-labeled brains, but can be distinguished in sam-
ples in which either or both of the contralateral G9 and 
ipsilateral G3 cells are labeled (Fig. 6B). The cryptic 
tooth is ventral and anterior to the volume occupied by 
G9 and G3 cells, although it is not clear if the cryptic 
tooth is a separate tooth or just a separate subdomain 
of the most lateral prominent tooth to which the cells 
of G9 and G3 project. Therefore, at least for the PB G2-</p>

<p>9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b cell type (Figs. 3, 6C), FB'1 </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>comprises either nine or seven columns, with cells of 
the most lateral cryptic teeth providing output from just 
one glomerulus and those of the remaining columns 
providing output from two glomeruli each (Fig. 6D). 
The projections for the PB-FB-NO neurons PB G2-9 .s-
FB'2.b-NO 3 A.b, PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 D.b, and PB G2-9 .s-
FB'3.b-NO 2 V.b are essentially identical to those shown 
in Figure 6 in that cells from the most lateral four glo-
meruli stay ipsilateral in their projections to the FB, 
whereas those from the most medial four glomeruli 
cross to the contralateral side of the FB. The projection 
map is less precise for layers 2 and 3 because the 
arbors of cells in these layers are not confined to 
defined domains as they are to the teeth of layer 1 (the 
PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO3 P .b cell in Fig. 6) and therefore 
overlap somewhat with one another. While we did not 
have a sufficient number of PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO3 M .b 
cells to perform a comprehensive analysis, the circuitry 
is consistent with the diagram derived for PB G2-9 .s-
FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b cells (Fig. 6D). 
The PB-FB-NO cells described above constitute the 
isomorphic set of neurons that give rise to the so-called 
vertical fiber system (Hanesch et al., 1989). The early 
Golgi-based account differs in two ways from the 
revised account provided here. First, the early descrip-
tion states that all cells maintain ipsilateral projections 
between the PB and the FB and do not cross the mid-
line until they course from the FB to the noduli. The 
revised, MCFO-based account described above instead 
indicates a more typical projection pattern in which 
only cells from the lateral four glomeruli remain ipsilat-
eral between the PB and FB. Second, the revised 
account reveals that the vertical fiber system does not 
include cells from G1, as none of the PB-FB-NO cells 
arborizes in G1. </p>

<p>PB-FB-NO circuits are highly restricted in 
the FB </p>

<p>Brains immunolabeled to visualize all neurons portray 
an image of absolute chaos with a dense network of 
connections coursing through the collective neuropils. 
An MCFO-based "dissection" of these connections 
reveals a surprisingly limited connectome between neu-
ropils. For example, there is a great deal of specificity 
in central complex regions that provide output to the 
noduli. As noted above, just one cell type has been 
identified that connects the PB to NO 1 (PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-
NO 1 .b; Figs. 3, 11, 14A). Of the cells identified to date, 
a similarly small number of cells connect the PB to NO 2 
and NO 3 . Furthermore, there is specificity in the con-
nections between certain layers of the FB and subcom-
partments of the noduli. </p>

<p>The common themes among the cell types that con-
nect the PB to NO 2 and NO 3 are: 1) the FB serves as 
the second synaptic junction; 2) the cells all have spiny 
arbors in the PB and bouton-type arbors in the FB and 
noduli; and 3) none of these cells is represented in G1, 
so, to date, no direct communication between G1, the 
FB, and the noduli (nor even between G1 and the noduli) 
has been identified. Of the PB neurons identified, those 
that arborize in both the dorsal and ventral compart-
ments of NO 2 communicate directly with only layer 3 of 
the FB via PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 D.b and PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-
NO 2 V.b (Figs. 3, 16A,C,D). NO 3 P and NO 3 M receive their 
input from the PB via layer 1 of the FB and the cell 
types PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 P.b (Figs. 3, 6C, 16A) and 
PB G2-9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 M.b (Figs. 3, 16A,E), while NO 3 A 
receives its input from the PB via layer 2 of the FB from </p>

<p>Figure 16. Connectivity between the FB and noduli. A: The sche-
matic illustrates the circuits between three layers of the FB-'1, 
'2, and '3-and the subcompartments of the noduli to which the 
cells from these layers project. For clarity in illustrating the FB-
NO connections, since the three NO 3 subcompartments are not 
visible in a frontal view, noduli are shown in the schematic in a 
sagittal view (as in Fig. 12E2); inset of NO is frontal view. Arrows 
indicate projections from the PB. NO 1 is not directly wired to the 
FB. B: PB G2-9 .s-FB'2.b-NO 3 A.b [R34H05]. C: PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-
NO 2 D.b [R44C06]. D: PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 V [R37F06]. E: PB G2-</p>

<p>9 .s-FB'1.b-NO 3 M.b [R85H06]. Scale bars 5 14 lm in B,E; 11 lm 
in C; 13 lm in D. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>the PB G2-9 .s-FB'2.b-NO 3 A.b cell (Figs. 3, 16A,B). In sum-
mary, G1 does not communicate directly with any of the 
noduli; the PB does not communicate directly with NO 1 
via the FB, but rather via the EB; NO 2 communicates 
directly with only layer 3 of the FB, NO 3 A only with layer 
2, and NO 3 P and NO 3 M with only layer 1. 
Such highly specific wiring between the PB and the 
noduli and their subcompartments, as well as between 
the layers of the intermediate neuropil (the FB) and the 
subcompartments of the noduli, typifies the specificity 
of the connections between neuropils of the brain. It 
also suggests a highly modular division of roles for the 
subregions of the Drosophila brain. </p>

<p>Neurons discriminate between various 
subsets of glomeruli </p>

<p>A ubiquitous theme throughout the development of 
nervous systems is target recognition, a key factor in 
synapse formation and neurite growth, particularly of 
the primary neurite. Both are essential events in estab-
lishing the proper circuits and, ultimately, the appropri-
ate behavioral responses for each individual cell type. 
The complexity of targeting is evident in the PB, where 
different classes of neurons arborize in unique but over-
lapping subsets of glomeruli. As noted earlier, several 
PB neurons discriminate between the G1-G8 and G2-
G9 subsets of glomeruli. Another neuron distinguishes 
G9 from the rest of the glomeruli (see below). Both 
apparently dendritic and presynaptic contacts exhibit 
specificity in the subregions of neuropils they target. 
A very striking and quite sophisticated example of 
targeted subsets of glomeruli is illustrated by two cell 
types. These cell types both arborize in G1-G8 and 
both follow the same path-PB-EB-gall-but they are 
effectively complementary in the likely direction of 
information flow. One exhibits boutons in the PB and 
spines in the EB (PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b; Figs. 3, 
8A,C), apparently carrying information from the EB to 
the PB. The reciprocal neuron has a spiny arbor in the 
PB and boutons in the EB (PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b; 
Figs. 3, 8B,C) and apparently carries information in the 
reverse direction, from the PB to the EB. Both neurons 
have boutons in the gall. 
Two subclasses comprise each of these cells types, 
and it is the subclasses that exhibit specificity for glomer-
ular subsets. The subclasses differ in two ways: 1) they 
arborize in different glomeruli, and 2) they target different 
regions of the gall. Both subclasses arborize in alternating 
glomeruli, but one targets the odd-numbered glomeruli 
(G1, G3, G5, G7) and the second targets the even-
numbered glomeruli (G2, G4, G6, G8; Fig. 17). Down-
stream, in the gall, information flow is further segregated: </p>

<p>for both cell types, the even-numbered population proj-
ects to the ventral gall (PB.s-EBt.b-Vgall.b, PB.b-EBw.s-
Vgall.b), whereas cells that arborize in the odd-numbered 
glomeruli project to the dorsal gall (PB.s-EBt.b-Dgall.b, 
PB.b-EBw.s-Dgall.b; Figs. 13B1-B3, 14B, 15, 17). Even the 
tendrils that the PB-EB-D/Vgall cells project into nearby 
glomeruli maintain exclusively odd-or even-numbered glo-
merular input or output by skipping adjacent glomeruli to 
reach their appropriate odd or even targets (Fig. 17). The 
significance of the discrimination between the dorsal and 
ventral domains on physiology and behavior is unclear, 
but it seems likely that tight regulation of this odd/even 
segregation is critical for circuit function and behavior. 
In summary, this pair of complementary cells is identi-
cal in all respects except one. They both 1) arborize in 
G1-8; 2) project to the same three neuropils (PB, EB, 
gall); 3) consist of two populations, one that arborizes in 
the odd-numbered glomeruli and the dorsal gall and one 
that arborizes in the even-numbered glomeruli and the 
ventral gall; and 4) tendrils from both cell types obey the 
even/odd mapping onto glomeruli. The only difference is 
that one carries information from the PB to the EB and 
the other transmits information from the EB to the PB. </p>

<p>PB cells are not exclusively uniglomerular </p>

<p>Most small-field neurons that arborize in the PB are 
"uniglomerular" in that their arbors appear to populate 
only a single glomerulus (e.g., PB G2-9 .s-EBt.b-NO 1 .b; 
PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 D.b). However, the branches of 
some small-field neurons infiltrate adjacent glomeruli or 
even glomeruli several units distant from the "primary" 
arborization site, where the primary glomerulus is the 
one that receives the most extensive arbor and is gen-
erally closest to the primary neurite. This multiglomeru-
lar pattern occurs in neurons with both spiny arbors 
and boutons in the PB (Fig. 18A, asterisks). Multiglo-
merular arbors usually extend unilaterally rather than 
bilaterally. There is no overall trend to spread either 
medially or laterally, although within a cell type there 
may be such a bias (e.g., see below for PB G1-7 .s-
FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b). Notably, these secondary arbors 
can also reach across the midline. This is most often 
seen in cells with a primary arbor in G1 (e.g., PB G1-8 .b-
EBw.s-D/Vgall.b), although it has also been observed 
for G2 and G3, albeit rarely. 
Features of the multiglomerular phenotype are not uni-
versal; instead, they are characteristic of specific cell 
types. For example, with rare exceptions the bi-glomerular 
arborizations of PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cells are 
restricted to G1. As mentioned above, in these rare excep-
tions the arbor skips the adjacent glomerulus to maintain 
the even/odd glomerulus pattern (e.g., primary arbor in 
G5, secondary in G7; Fig. 17); in one case, a G2 to G2 </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>jump necessitated that the neurite bypass the two inter-
vening G1 glomeruli. The secondary arbors for this cell 
type are minimal, containing as few as a single bouton. 
PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b cells also exhibit multi-
glomerular arbors. Thin, spiny tendrils frequently invade 
adjacent glomeruli. Secondary arbors for these cells are 
generally minimal, typically unilateral (most often 
extending medially rather than laterally), and usually 
only project a distance of one to two glomeruli. Some 
extend bilaterally, again most often for one to two glo-
meruli; the bilateral extensions account for most of the 
laterally extending arbors. They can also bypass the 
adjacent arbor and arborize in the next glomerulus (for 
example, with a primary arbor in G1 and a secondary 
arbor in the ipsilateral G3). These arbors can be quite 
extensive. In one instance, the bulk of an arbor was ela-</p>

<p>borated in G3, but additional neurites sprouted in three 
additional glomeruli, including the contralateral G1. In 
an extreme case, the primary arbor was in G6 and ten-
drils extended to all other ipsilateral glomeruli. </p>

<p>Unusual PB cell types 
Small-field neuron that has both ipsilateral and 
contralateral subtypes </p>

<p>A number of cell types were identified that are unusual in 
various respects. The PB G2-9 .b-IB.s-SPS.s cell elaborates 
a likely presynaptic arbor in the PB and an extensive, 
bifurcated, spiny arbor in the inferior bridge (IB) and supe-
rior posterior slope (SPS; Fig. 18A). As described for a 
subset of other cell types, PB G2-9 .b-IB.s-SPS.s cells some-
times arborize in multiple glomeruli, either adjacent or up </p>

<p>Figure 17. A segregated circuit connects the dorsal and ventral gall to distinct volumes in the EB and PB. Two cells, PB.s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b 
and PB.b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b, relay information between the PB, EB, and gall. Information is relayed from the even glomeruli to corresponding 
tiles in the EB (as described in Fig. 14) and to the ventral gall via the PB.s-EBt.b-Vgall.b cells (cell A). Similarly, information is relayed from 
the odd glomeruli to the odd-corresponding set of tiles in the EB (see also Fig. 14) and to the dorsal gall via the PB.s-EBt.b-Dgall.b cells 
(cell C). Information is transmitted from the EB to the PB and gall via the PB.b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cells. Cells in the wedges that correspond 
to the even glomeruli deliver information to the even glomeruli and to the ventral gall via the PB.b-EBw.s-Vgall.b cells (B) and from the 
odd-corresponding wedges to the odd glomeruli and dorsal gall via the PB.b-EBw.s-Dgall.b cells (D). Both cell types occasionally extend 
tendrils, skipping their adjacent neighbor to maintain the odd/even integrity of a cell. The green cell is an example of the cell type shown 
in D, where the primary bouton arbor is in G1 and a single bouton from the same cell extends to G3. The light blue cell is an example of 
the cell type shown in A with a primary arbor in G4 and secondary arbor in G6. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>to four glomeruli away (secondary arbors are medial, lat-
eral, and bilateral to the primary arbor; Fig. 18A, aster-
isks). PB G2-9 .b-IB.s-SPS.s cells exhibit bouton-type arbors 
in G2-9. This cell type is unique in that it comes in two 
classes, one in which both the bouton and spiny arbors 
are ipsilateral (Fig. 18A, blue, orange cells; notably, an 
occasional minor dendritic branch crosses to the contra-
lateral IB), and a second in which the primary neurite 
crosses contralaterally to arborize in the IB and SPS (Fig. 
18A, green cell). (Note that occasional cells of other cell 
types follow an ipsilateral projection. However, these pro-
jections are likely to be developmental errors since they </p>

<p>are anomalous for their cell types. For example, two 
PB G2-9 .s-EB.t.b-NO 1 .b cells from G9 stayed ipsilateral 
through their entire course, as did a PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-
NO 2 V.b cell, also from G9.) </p>

<p>PB local interneurons with stereotyped input 
and output features </p>

<p>Several PB local interneurons were also identified in 
this study. These were also identified in Lin et al. 
(2013), but interpretations differ between the two 
accounts (Table 3A). One, PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b, is unusual 
in that it has neurites that appear to both receive and </p>

<p>Figure 18. Unusual PB cell types. Confocal images of assorted atypical neuronal cell types. A: PB G2-9 .b-IB.s-SPS.s neurons (from left to 
right: contralateral, green; ipsilateral, blue and red). The green bouton arbor occupies three glomeruli in the PB (asterisks). B: 
PB18.s.GxD7Gy.b neurons. This arbor is primarily spiny in morphology with two clusters of boutons spaced seven glomeruli apart 
[R34E11]. C: The morphology of the PB G6-8 .s-G9 .b arbors resembles boutons in G9 and spines in G6-8 [R18G01]; four neurons are shown. 
D-F: PB G1/2-9 .b-SPSi.s cells. D1 and D2 are the same neuron, with and without the nc82 channel shown. E1: The left half of the PB is 
arborized by a pink example of PB G1/2-9 .b-SPSi.s and the right half is arborized by two PB G1/2-9 .b-SPSi.s cells, one orange and one blue. 
E2: A magnified portion of the right PB (boxed region in E1) is shown to illustrate the close proximity of the boutons from these two cells. 
F1: Each half of the PB is populated by two neurons. The close proximity of the boutons from two of these cells is shown (F2, [R33D11]). 
G: PB G9 .s-EB.P.s-ga-t.b cells. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>distribute information within the PB. This cell arborizes 
throughout the entire PB (PB18.s) and is predominantly 
spiny in morphology, but has two clusters of precisely 
spaced boutons. The arbor in the glomerulus distal to 
the cell body is often sparse and may appear to lack 
spiny terminals, but a complete absence of arbor was 
seen in only one instance. (Lin et al. state that this cell 
does not arborize in the distal glomerulus.) A distance 
of seven glomeruli separates these clusters (Gx is sepa-
rated by D7 glomeruli from Gy; Fig. 18B; Lin et al. note 
these output terminals are spaced five glomeruli apart). 
The PB18.s-9i1i8c.b cell exhibits the same features as 
PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b, except its initial cluster of boutons is 
in G9. With a bouton-type arbor at the lateral tip of the 
PB, this leaves sufficient glomeruli (2 3 D7) for a total 
of three arbors consisting of boutons: G9 and G1 from 
the same half of the PB (9i1i for G9 ipsilateral and G1 
ipsilateral) and G8 from the other half of the PB (8c for 
G8 contralateral). It is likely these both represent the 
same cell type (see Discussion). 
Similar to PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b cells, a second local inter-
neuron, PB G6-8 .s-G9 .b, also exhibits spatially restricted 
spiny and bouton-type terminals along the length of the 
PB. Based on their morphology, G9 terminals appear to 
consist exclusively of boutons and the remaining glomer-
uli in which this cell arborizes, G8, G7, and G6, are pre-
dominantly, if not exclusively, spiny (Fig. 18C). A third and 
somewhat similar neuron, although not a local inter-
neuron, is the PB G1/2-9 .b-SPSi.s cell (Figs. 3, 18D1,D2). 
The PB arbor of these cells appears to be exclusively pre-
synaptic and the boutons are sparse and evenly distrib-
uted as single boutons along just half the length of the 
PB. The number of boutons per neuron ranges from 25-
40. The arbor usually extends from G9i through G2i, 
although G1i is occasionally populated by a single bouton 
(therefore the designation "G1/2" in the neuron's name). 
In rare cases, the arbor extends across the midline into 
the contralateral half of the PB. One particularly curious 
feature of this cell is that the boutons from two cells that 
arborize in the same half of the PB predominantly overlap 
one another (Fig. 18E2,F2). The arbor is spiny in the SPS 
of the ipsilateral side. 
The PB.b-LAL.s-PS.s (Fig. 3N) cell is another cell that 
provides input to the PB. A dense arbor of boutons fills 
all 18 glomeruli of the PB, delivering information from 
an elaborate spiny arbor in the posterior slope (PS). </p>

<p>G9-specific cell </p>

<p>One cell type is exclusive to G9: PB G9 .b-EB.P.s-ga-t.b. 
This cell has boutons in G9 of the PB, a spiny arbor in 
the posterior shell of the EB (EB.P.s), and boutons in 
the dorsal tip of the gall (Fig. 18G). The arbor in the 
posterior shell of the EB is sparse, is located just lateral </p>

<p>to the ventral midline (i.e., 6:00), and is always ipsilat-
eral with respect to the G9 arbor (i.e., if the soma and 
G9 arbor are on the left, the EB arbor is to the left of 
the ventral midline, from 6:00 to 6:30). The cell termi-
nates in the contralateral gall. The nature of information 
collected by the EB and relayed to G9 and the gall is 
intriguing. (Lin et al. consider this cell as part of the 
PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cell type.) </p>

<p>G1-G7 cell type with ipsilateral G1 projections 
and three subtypes </p>

<p>The PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b cell type is highly 
unusual in both its anatomy and wiring and seems to con-
sist of several subtypes (Fig. 19). First, this cell type is 
noteworthy in that it arborizes exclusively in G1-G7 
(although dendrites from a primary arbor in G7 can extend 
into both G8 and G9). The wiring pattern may be the most 
unusual feature of this neuron. Whereas cells in G2-G7 
for the most part follow the stereotypical projection pat-
tern, G1 does not. In other cell types, and according to 
the projection pattern rules described above, cells that 
arborize in G1 cross the midline to project contralaterally. 
Unexpectedly, most G1-based PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-
cre.b cells follow an entirely ipsilateral tract: 13/17 such 
cells stay ipsilateral in the FB as well as the LAL and crep-
ine. A few of these G1 arbors infiltrate the contralateral 
G1, so by strict definition these cells do not follow abso-
lute ipsilateral trajectories. The remaining 4/17 project 
contralaterally, crossing the midline at the first junction 
(between the PB and FB). This ipsilateral G1 projection 
pattern is highly atypical and, consequently, the nature of 
the information relayed by this class of neurons, in partic-
ular by G1, and the significance of information flow from 
the center of the PB to the ipsilateral central brain, is 
intriguing. 
These G1 cells are even more unusual in that the pri-
mary neurite projects to the lateral margin of the ipsilat-
eral FB. In this sense, they behave more like cells in the 
G1 from the contralateral side of the PB, as the position 
they occupy in the FB is in the vicinity of where a typical 
G1-based arbor from the contralateral side would arbo-
rize. The partial projection pattern, from the lateral margin 
of the FB to the center, is therefore: G7i:G1i:G6i:G2c ("i" 
stands for ipsilateral and "c" for contralateral). 
A common wiring theme of cell types discussed pre-
viously is that they cross the midline before arborizing 
in the third neuropil, and as a general rule, cells that 
arborize in the most medial four glomeruli cross contral-
aterally at the first junction, whereas those that target 
the most lateral four glomeruli cross at the second 
junction. Certain PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b cells devi-
ate from this standard projection pattern. G1 cells pri-
marily remain ipsilateral altogether, as discussed above. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>As expected from previously described trajectory pat-
terns, cells from G7, G6, and G5 always remain ipsilat-
eral at the PB-FB junction (the first junction) and G2 
cells always course contralaterally. On the other hand, 
cells from G3 and G4 are less predictable. Cells projec-
ting from G4 either remain ipsilateral in the FB or their 
arbors straddle the midline, whereas G3 cells generally 
cross to the contralateral FB, although they can also 
straddle the midline or even remain ipsilateral in the 
FB. In all cases, except for the ipsilateral G1 tracts, </p>

<p>cells arborize in the contralateral LAL, as expected. 
This breakdown in a strict medial/lateral boundary and 
the resulting imbalance in distribution of information 
received from the left and right fields of the fly's envi-
ronment are atypical of PB neurons. 
PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b cells also exhibit different 
subtypes. First, the length of the apparently presynaptic 
arbor along the lateral margin of the LAL varies, falling 
into three distinct categories. The short and medium 
length arbors reside completely in the LAL, whereas the 
long subtype extends the length of the LAL and then 
continues on into the inferior ventrolateral protocere-
brum. The length of these "dangling arbors" is consist-
ent within subtypes. There is no correlation between 
subtype and specific subsets of glomeruli. In other 
words, it is not the case that, for example, only short 
arbors correlate with G1-3, medium from G4/G5, and 
long from G6/G7. Instead, cells arborizing in all seven 
glomeruli for this cell type have been seen to give rise 
to each of the three LAL arbor lengths. Whether these 
three subtypes constitute separate cell types or not is 
debatable. Since the three subtypes appear in each of 
the GAL4 lines in which the cell type has been seen, it 
seems less likely they are distinct cell types. Second, 
the bouton arbor does not always extend into the crep-
ine. (For simplicity, "crepine" is included in the cell's 
name.) This difference may have more to do with the 
somewhat arbitrary delineation of the boundaries of the 
LAL and crepine than with internal inconsistency with 
the cells' arborization patterns. Further complicating 
the projection pattern of this cell type, on rare occa-
sions a small spur reaches from the FB into the EB. 
The EB.w.AMP.s-Dga-s.b cell illustrates another exam-
ple of ambiguous distinction of cell types, but in this 
case the ambiguity is between cell types (or subclasses) 
and projection errors. Two variants of this cell type 
were seen multiple times (Fig. 20). In one variant, an 
additional spiny arbor projected to the PB, and in 
another a secondary neurite projected to a separate 
region of the EB where it sprouted a sparse spiny arbor 
in the anterior shell of the EB. These adventitious arbors 
to the PB and EB, although consistent in morphology, 
are likely to be morphogenetic errors. First, they occur 
rarely, and second, they have only been seen in GAL4 
lines that identify EB.w.AMP.s-Dga-s.b cells. Although 
errors were occasionally seen in other cell types, these 
were very rare and typically seen only once. </p>

<p>The "horizontal fiber system" cell exhibits a 
contralateral G8 projection but ipsilateral G1 
circuitry </p>

<p>The horizontal fiber system (HFS) is a set of isomorphic 
neurons that has historically been described as </p>

<p>Figure 19. Three subtypes of neuron PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b. 
Short, medium, and long LAL arbors for PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-
cre.b neurons are shown. Asterisks indicate where the "tails" of 
the arbors exit the LAL. A: Long (left, blue and red) and short 
(right, green) versions of the LAL tail. Both sides arborize dorsally 
in the crepine. B: Medium arbor (left, purple); note that the faint 
green arbor does exit the LAL but only three of its boutons lie 
outside the LAL. Both red and green arbors on the right are the 
long variety. Both left and right arbors also infiltrate the crepine 
[R11B11]. Scale bars 5 10 lm in A; 12 lm in B. </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>connecting the PB to layers 2 and 3 of the FB and to 
the LAL (Power, 1943; Williams, 1975; Hanesch et al., 
1989). The PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b cell type, which 
arborizes in G1-G8, appears to be the cell type that is 
the basis of the HFS. (Note that the terminals in the FB 
are mixed, and therefore carry both the .s and .b desig-
nations.) However, the circuits revealed here by the 
MCFO technique exhibit fundamental differences from 
the traditional wiring interpretation (Hanesch et al., 
1989). 
First, the most lateral projection, from G8, does not 
maintain an ipsilateral path. Rather, the cells from G8 
(as well as G7 and G6) remain ipsilateral at the first 
junction, the FB, and subsequently cross the midline to 
arborize in the contralateral rubus (Figs. 21A-C, 22). In 
other words, PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b cells that arbo-
rize in G8 follow the "standard" projection pattern. The 
rubus is a distinct, round, nc82-dense and therefore 
synaptic-rich structure at the anterior and lateral edge 
of the crepine. Note that Hanesch et al. indicate that 
this cell projects not to the rubus but to the LAL or 
VBO, which lies ventral to the rubus. Lin et al. correctly 
note that the cell from G8 projects contralaterally, 
although they refer to the rubus as the round body. </p>

<p>Second, G1 cells do not follow the standard G1 pro-
jection pattern, as they are reported to do in the tradi-
tional model of the HFS. Instead, more often than not 
they follow an exclusively ipsilateral projection (66% of 
the time, n 5 8 of 12 instances). Notably, PB G1-8 .s-
FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b cells represent one of only two cell 
types identified to date in which the G1 cell predomi-
nantly follows an ipsilateral path. (The other is the 
PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b cell, described above. Also, 
the ipsilateral variant of the PB G2-9 .b-IB.s-SPS.s cell 
maintains an entirely ipsilateral path, regardless of the 
glomerulus in which it arborizes.) Similar to the PB G1-</p>

<p>7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b cell type, PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-
rub.b G1 cells project to the lateral margin of the FB. 
However, unlike the PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b cell, 
the G1 arbor from PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b cells is 
the most lateral arbor in the FB, so it occupies an even 
more lateral volume than does the G8 contralateral pro-
jection. This is the volume that corresponds to that typ-
ically occupied by the contralateral G1 cell's arbor. G2, 
G3, and G4 cells project contralaterally, and cells from 
G5 are inconsistent in their projection patterns, always 
projecting close to the midline, but the arbors lie to 
either side of or on the midline. Furthermore, the </p>

<p>Figure 20. Variants of the EBw.AMP.s-Dga-s.b cell. The EB.w.AMP.s-Dga-s.b cell seems prone to errors since two variants of the cell were 
seen multiple times. A: In one variant (EBw.AMP.s-Dga-s.b-EBw.A.s; [R38C04]), a second, sparse, spiny arbor projects to the anterior shell 
of the EB (asterisks). B: There is just one EB arbor in the "wild-type" cell (EBw.AMP.s-Dga-s.b; found in [R38B06][R38C04][R41G11]). C: In 
the second variant (PB.s-EBw.AMP.s-Dga-s.b; [R38B06]), a small spiny arbor projects to the PB (asterisks). Scale bars: blue cell, 14 lm; 
orange cell, 10 lm in A; yellow cell, 10 lm; blue cell 24 lm in B; orange cell, 6 lm; green cell 18 lm in C. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>projection pattern described here is identical to that 
described for the PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cell (Fig. 
15, filleted EB). While this revised circuitry for the HFS 
necessitates reinterpretation of behavioral results for 
stimuli reaching the lateral PB, reinterpretation is prob-
ably not necessary for the revised ipsilateral G1 projec-
tion since the midline position of G1l and G1r probably 
means these cells receive the same visual input. None-
theless, it is unusual for G1 to follow an ipsilateral 
trajectory. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The work presented here builds on published studies 
by both defining previously unidentified anatomical fea-
tures of each of the four components of the central 
complex as well as updating wiring diagrams to accom-
modate these new anatomical insights. We also report 
new cells and new features of previously identified cells 
and the genetic reporter lines that reveal them, with 
the prospect that these will form an essential stepping 
stone both to synaptic studies at the electron micro-
scope level and to functional studies. The most signifi-
cant new insights from this work are summarized 
below. As noted earlier, the statements below are 
drawn from neurons that arborize in the PB. </p>

<p>Substructure of the central complex 
neuropils </p>

<p>The most surprising finding of this study is that the 
Drosophila protocerebral bridge comprises 18 glomeruli. 
This finding has an important impact on the wiring rela-
tionships between the glomeruli and their respective 
vertical units in the FB, the columns, and in the EB, the 
wedges and a new volume described here, the tiles. 
The longstanding belief regarding the correspondence 
between the PB and FB and PB and EB wedges was 
that there is a 1:1 relationship between the vertical 
subdomains of these structures. The finding that there 
are 18 glomeruli raised the possibility that the FB and 
EB also exhibit an octodecimal organization. However, 
we provide compelling evidence that there are just 16 
wedges in the EB and further show that some cells </p>

<p>Figure 21. Horizontal fiber system cells and projections. The pro-
jection patterns of HFS cells differ from published accounts only 
for cells that arborize in G1 and G8, so only examples for these 
glomeruli are shown. A-D: PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b cells. The 
PB arbor is sparse. It is likely that the FB arbor also has boutons 
in addition to the more obvious spines. Insets show glomeruli in 
which cells of interest arborize; nc82 highlights the bridge; spiny 
arbors are either green or blue. A: This cell arborizes in G8R (8), 
the ipsilateral FB (FB) and contralateral rubus (RUB). B: Two cells 
are labeled; one arborizes in G8L (8), the second in G7L (7). Both 
arborize in the ipsilateral FB (FB) and cross to the contralateral 
rubus (RUB). C: Two blue cells are labeled. One arborizes in G1L 
(1) and the second arborizes in G8R (8). The projection from G8R 
to the ipsilateral FB (right, FB 8) is evident. The primary neurite 
then courses from the FB to the contralateral rubus (8, RUB). The 
second blue cell arborizes in G1L (1), then courses to the ipsilat-
eral FB (FB 1), and finally to the ipsilateral rubus (1, RUB) where 
it joins the rubus arbor from G8R. Left inset illustrates the G1L 
cell arbor in the PB; right inset shows the G8R cell arbor in the 
PB, with G9 situated just below and G7 just above the labeled 
glomerulus. D: G1L (inset and noted with a "1" in panel D) proj-
ects to the ipsilateral FB (FB) and ipsilateral rubus (RUB). </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>arborize in just half a wedge, indicating the further divi-
sion of wedges into 32 demi-wedges. The observation 
that a simple 1:1 correspondence between the PB and 
EB wedges is lacking and, furthermore, that there are 
also demi-wedges, has implications for how the system 
is wired to accommodate this numerical discrepancy. 
Another unexpected finding from this work is the 
existence of a second EB volume that also partitions 
the EB around its circumference: the tile domain. Tiles 
are distinct from wedges in that there are half as many 
tiles as wedges (eight tiles), they are functionally dis-
tinct from the wedge (output versus input, respectively), 
and these two volumes survey different volumes of the 
EB since they extend to different depths of the EB. 
Only two PB cell types target the tile domain. 
Although a columnar morphology is apparent in layers 
1-8 of the FB in nc82-labeled samples, the organization 
of the cells that populate these layers is not universally 
columnar. We show that there is a minimum of nine layers 
in the FB, yet a columnar organization (i.e., vertical strati-
fication) of cell arbors is restricted to layers 1-5 for single 
column widths (where the columnar organization for 
layers 4 and 5 is revealed by the PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-
rub.b cell); wider, more loosely organized arbors occur in 
more dorsal layers. With the exception of arbors in layer 
1, the column borders are not rigid, as neighboring arbors 
overlap one another, sometimes extensively. The unique 
tooth-like structure of layer 1 of the FB definitively shows 
that there are nine columns in this layer. Due to the over-
lap of arbors, it is more difficult to count columns in the 
other layers, but layers 2 and 3, which exhibit a tighter 
columnar organization than more dorsal layers, likely have 
16 columns based on mapping data from the PB G2-9 .s-
FB'2.b-NO 3 A.b, PB G2-9 .s-FB'3.b-NO 2 D.b, and PB G2-9 .s-
FB'3.b-NO 2 V.b (not shown). This would be consistent 
with parallel divisions of the EB (wedges). 
We also describe other new anatomical features and 
subdomains. First, we show that each of the noduli has 
subcompartments. The dorsal noduli, NO 1 , have medial 
and lateral subcompartments. The medial noduli, NO 2 , 
consist of two distinct subcompartments, NO 2 D and 
NO 2 V; no PB cell type arborizes in either of these sub-
compartments. The ventral noduli, NO 3 , consist of three 
distinct subcompartments, NO 3 A, NO 3 M, and NO 3 P. The 
nubbin is a partial shell on the dorsal, anterior face of 
the EB, and the "gall tip" is a region at the dorsal tip of 
the gall. Finally, two undefined regions to which some 
cells project and that are not clearly demarcated are 
the dorsal and ventral gall surround (Dga-s and Vga-s). 
Even though the subdomains of the central complex 
structures can be distinguished from one another, they 
apparently do not function as isolated subunits. Rather, 
there is shared communication between most of these </p>

<p>Figure 22. Horizontal fiber system wiring diagram. Schematic of 
the revised projection pattern of the cell that is the basis of 
the HFS, the PB G1-8 .s-FB'3,4,5.s.b-rub.b cell. This cell does not 
arborize in G9. Top: PB; middle: FB (layers 1 through 5 are 
shown); circles: rubus; bottom: FB. The projections illustrated 
here differ in several key respects from the published HFS pro-
jection patterns: 1) Cells that arborize in G8 do cross the mid-
line; they do not follow an ipsilateral projection; 2) Cells that 
arborize in G1 remain ipsilateral; they do not cross the midline; 
3) G1, not G8, arbors occupy the most lateral column of the 
FB. Note that the arbors from G8-G6 remain ipsilateral in the 
FB and those from G4-G2 consistently project to the contralat-
eral FB, whereas arbors from G5 occupy a more loosely demar-
cated geographic volume: They course to the midline, but can 
arborize on either the ipsilateral or contralateral side of the 
midline or on the midline. Nonetheless, G5 arbors always termi-
nate in the contralateral rubus (dashed and solid yellow lines 
from G5 to FB to rubus). The composite outlined here was not 
constructed from densely labeled brains, as described for the 
PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/Vgall.b cell (Fig. 15), so not every cell was 
seen with direct relation to its nearest neighbors. One brain 
was documented to show the key spatial relationship between 
G1L and G8L in the FB; this relationship was confirmed in 
numerous other brains in which either G1 or G8 cells were 
labeled, as the most lateral two FB columns can be readily dis-
tinguished from one another. The relative positions of neighbor-
ing arbors in the FB were also confirmed (and in some cases 
determined) by comparing FB arbor positions in different brains. 
The relative positions, shown here, largely-but not completely-
resemble the projection pattern for the PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/ 
Vgall.b cell type. </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>subunits. At least for the neurons described here (i.e., 
those that arborize in the PB), both pre-and postsynaptic 
arbors in the glomeruli, EB tiles, wedges and shells, FB 
columns, and NO 1 (medial and lateral domains) can 
extend into neighboring domains. This sharing of informa-
tion is not obvious between NO 2 D and NO 2 V, nor between 
NO 3 A and NO 3 M. The boundary between NO 3 P and NO 3 M 
is too obscure to evaluate if arbors in these two domains 
are completely restricted or shared, although in the exam-
ples shown in Figure 12 they appear to be restricted. The 
frequency and degree to which arbors overlap in the vari-
ous subunits is cell type-dependent. While some arbors 
exhibit no or minimal intrusion into adjacent volumes, 
overlap between neighboring units could serve important 
circuit functions. </p>

<p>Cell types of the protocerebral bridge </p>

<p>This work identifies 17 unique cell types that arborize 
in the protocerebral bridge. These fall into four classes: 
cells that 1) are intrinsic to the PB (n 5 2), 2) are intrinsic 
to the central complex (an additional 6), 3) arborize in the 
FB, EB, or NO in addition to extra-central complex regions 
(e.g., the gall; n 5 6), and 4) arborize exclusively in the PB 
and regions outside the central complex (n 5 3). Cells 
that arborize in the PB receive their input from the EB, 
LAL, PS, IB, and also from within the PB. One cell previ-
ously identified in another study (Lin et al., 2013) was not 
targeted by any of the 35 lines analyzed in this work, 
the PB 1-glomerulus -FB c,d,e,f !IDFP HB-medial cell. Like the 
PB G2-9 .b-IB.s-SPS.s cell described above, the PB 1-glomeru-</p>

<p>lus -FB c,d,e,f !IDFP HB-medial cell also has two subtypes, one 
that arborizes in just one HB (the LAL) and a second that 
arborizes in both the right and left HBs/LALs. A cell that 
appears to be morphologically homologous to this PB-FB-
LAL cell has been characterized in the locust, and also 
has two subtypes, CPU1 (which arborizes in a single LAL) 
and CPU2 (which arborizes bilaterally in both LALs; 
Heinze and Homberg, 2008). To the extent that it is possi-
ble to construct wiring diagrams from the images shown 
in these two studies, it appears that the circuits for these 
cells are also identical between Drosophila and Schisto-
cerca. In addition, one cell type was identified in our study 
that was not characterized in Lin et al. (2013), the PB G1/ </p>

<p>2-9 .b-SPSi.s cell. 
The combined total from this work and Lin et al. 
(2013) brings the current number of identified cell types 
that arborize in the protocerebral bridge of Drosophila to 
18. A potential 19th cell type was seen just twice, and 
in neither case could the entire cell be traced. Its PB 
arbor is spiny and very sparse, and while it clearly arbor-
izes in the central brain, it is not clear if it arborizes else-
where within the central complex. It is also possible that 
this "cell type" only constitutes a variant, as described </p>

<p>for the EB.w.AMP.s-Dga-s.b cell. There will likely be addi-
tional cells identified that arborize in the PB, although 
this number is predicted to be small. A complete inven-
tory of all cells in the Drosophila brain awaits a full 
reconstruction at an electron microscope level. 
The distinction between what constitutes a unique cell 
type is vague in some cases. For example, the arbor in 
the LAL for the PB G1-7 .s-FB'2.s-LAL.b-cre.b comes in 
three discrete lengths: short, medium, and long. It would 
be simplest to conclude that the only difference between 
these three variants of a single cell type is the geographic 
range over which each distributes information within the 
LAL. Here these variants are classified as subtypes of the 
same class of neuron, as they are assumed to relay the 
same information based on connectivity and morphology. 
The GAL4 patterns are consistent with this classification 
in that all three subtypes occur in each GAL4 line that 
expresses this cell. Similarly, for the PB G1-8 .b-EBw.s-D/ 
Vgall.b and PB G1-8 .s-EBt.b-D/Vgall.b cells, the population 
of cells from odd-numbered glomeruli arborize in the dor-
sal gall, whereas those that populate the even-numbered 
glomeruli target the ventral gall. Since the information 
relayed by the populations of odd and even glomeruli-
targeted cells is likely the same in a qualitative sense, the 
difference being only that it is segregated in its delivery to 
the dorsal and ventral regions of the gall, we assigned 
these two categories to the same cell type. 
A difference between the PB18.s-9i1i8c.b and PB18.s-
GxD7Gy.b is less clear-cut. The difference between these 
two cells is the number of apparently presynaptic arbors 
in the PB: the PB18.s-9i1i8c.b cell has three clusters of 
boutons whereas the PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b has just two. 
However, they both follow the same rule: they project 
spiny terminals throughout the entire extent of the PB 
and bouton-type terminals spaced at intervals with seven 
intervening glomeruli separating the output terminals. 
When the "first" (i.e., most proximal to the cell body) clus-
ter of boutons occurs in G9, there are sufficient glomeruli 
remaining to accommodate two of these intervals of 
seven glomeruli (interval 1: D7 includes G8i to G2i and 
interval 2: D7 includes G1c to G7c) and three clusters of 
boutons (G9i, G1i, and G8c). Furthermore, no instance of 
the PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b cell has been seen with a cluster of 
boutons in just G9 and G1, which would represent the 
expected G9 (and also G1) version of this cell type. In 
addition, these two cell types are always coincident in the 
lines in which they have been observed, suggesting that 
they share many aspects of their genetic programming. 
While the PB18.s-GxD7Gy.b cell type may simply not 
arborize in G9 or G1, it seems more likely that PB18.s-
GxD7Gy.b and PB18.s-9i1i8c.b cells are representative of 
the same cell type, and the difference in arborization pat-
tern (three vs. two clusters of boutons) is simply a </p>

<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>

<p>consequence of the glomerulus in which the most proxi-
mal cluster occurs. Ultimately, behavior or physiology will 
determine whether these cells perform the same function, 
and transcript profiling will reveal whether they express 
the same genes and thus belong to the same class. </p>

<p>Wiring principles of protocerebral bridge 
neurons </p>

<p>The wiring diagrams described here differ from pub-
lished reports, in part due to the fact that previous 
authors were unaware of the existence of 18 glomeruli in 
the PB and therefore based their models on the historic 
interpretation that there are 16 glomeruli. This numerical 
revision and new insights into the anatomical substruc-
ture of the central complex components are the primary 
basis for revisions of existing circuit diagrams. 
Although there are 18 glomeruli, no small-field neuron 
arborizes in all 18 glomeruli. Instead, most cell types 
arborize in either G1-G8 or G2-G9. Each of these catego-
ries adheres to the following basic wiring principle: Cells 
that arborize in the lateral four glomeruli of each side of 
the PB stay ipsilateral in the second neuropil (either the 
FB or EB, depending on the neuron) and cross to the con-
tralateral side at the third neuropil, whereas cells that 
arborize in the medial four glomeruli cross to the contra-
lateral side in the second neuropil (also described by 
Hanesch et al., 1989, and others). Consequently, because 
there are two subsets of PB neurons, the glomerulus that 
targets a given column, wedge, or tile is shifted by one 
glomerulus, depending on the subset of cell type. Further-
more, the observation that no small-field neurons arborize 
in all 18 glomeruli suggests the number of columns in the 
FB and wedges in the EB would not need to exceed 16 in 
order to maintain a 1:1 correspondence between the PB 
and FB/EB. 
As described by Strausfeld (1999), arbors from cells 
that target the PB alternate with one another in the 
second neuropil such that arbors from the left glomeruli 
alternate with those from the right glomeruli. The PB 
wiring diagrams presented here differ somewhat from a 
recent account (Lin et al., 2013), as follows. The most 
lateral FB column (or EB wedge) is occupied not by the 
ipsilateral G9 (or G8 for the G1-G8 cells), as previously 
described, but instead by the contralateral G2 (or G1 
for the G1-G8 cells). This circuit therefore reverses the 
pattern in the second neuropil (FB or EB) from one in 
which the most lateral (L) glomeruli project to the most 
lateral columns (or wedge or tile) on the ipsilateral side 
to one in which the medial (M) glomeruli from the con-
tralateral half of the PB project to the most lateral col-
umns. In other words, previously published diagrams 
(Lin et al., 2013) indicate a pattern of LMLMLM from </p>

<p>lateral to medial in the second neuropil, whereas this 
report shows that pattern to be MLMLML. 
The projection map shown here for cells that connect 
the PB to layer 1 of the FB illustrates conclusively the 
projection pattern between these domains. Obtaining 
an accurate map between the PB and layers 2 and 3 is 
difficult given the greater overlap between arbors of 
cells in these two layers, but the projection patterns we 
observed between the PB and layers 2 and 3 of the FB 
are consistent with the PB:FB'1 map. 
As noted above, distribution of information is not 
always restricted to the subdomains of each central com-
plex structure. When information is shared between 
neighboring domains (or alternating domains, in the case 
of the cells that arborize in the dorsal or ventral gall), gen-
erally only a small portion of the arbor is shared. The func-
tional significance of these zones of overlap remains to be 
determined. 
Connections between central complex structures are 
remarkably restricted. For example, of those neurons that 
arborize in the PB and FB, only FB layers 1, 2, and 3 con-
nect to the noduli, and only to NO 2 and NO 3 . The only link 
between the PB and NO 1 is via the ellipsoid body, so 
whereas NO 2 and NO 3 can be considered to work in con-
junction with the FB to elicit a behavior based on output 
from the PB, NO 1 cooperates with the EB to elicit a behav-
ior based on output from the PB. In fact, communication 
is even more specific: layer 3 of the FB communicates 
directly only with NO 2 , layer 2 directly only with the ante-
rior subcompartment of NO 3 , and layer 1 directly only 
with NO 3 M and NO 3 P. Furthermore, the cells in G1 do not 
communicate directly with the noduli at all-neither via 
the FB nor via the EB. The absence of direct connections 
between the PB and upper layers of the FB is also note-
worthy. This streamlined and highly segregated network 
of connections within and between central complex struc-
tures suggests a high degree of regional specialization in 
function for the components of the central complex. 
The roles of central complex structures, their subdo-
mains, and related neuropils are poorly understood. While 
functions remain largely unknown, many circuits 
described here are informative in various other ways. For 
example, some identify commonalities in function 
between neuropil subregions, such as FB'2 and NO 3 A, 
which are both arborized by a common neuron. Other cir-
cuits reveal spatial segregation between neuropils. The 
most intriguing instance is the exclusive relay of informa-
tion between the ventral gall and even-numbered glomer-
uli and the dorsal gall and odd-numbered glomeruli, which 
demonstrates that both information and information flow 
can be spatially segregated from the glomeruli to the gall. 
It will be interesting to learn the functional role of the gall 
and why it segregates a portion of the information it </p>

<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>receives and sends, as well as what sort of behavioral 
response requires this rigidly alternating spatial distribu-
tion in the PB. Finally, the absence of connections 
between neuropils may prove informative in functional 
studies. For example, G1 is distinct from G2-G8 in that it 
lacks direct connections with the noduli, and NO 1 is dis-
tinct from NO 2 and NO 3 in that it communicates with the 
PB via the EB rather than the FB, raising the questions of 
what behaviors G1 does and does not contribute to, and 
what the differences are in behavioral outputs from NO 1 
and NO 2 /NO 3 . 
The observation that there are 18 glomeruli in the 
Drosophila PB has significant implications for both the 
architecture and evolution of the Drosophila brain with 
respect to the brains of other neopterans. Although the 
suite of genetic tools available in locusts, bees, beetles, 
and other insects does not yet include MCFO, improve-
ments in imaging and histology may prove sufficient to 
reevaluate the number of glomeruli in these species, 
given that glomeruli can be accurately counted in 
brains that are labeled only with nc82. Either some or 
all of these species also have 18 glomeruli, or an extra 
pair of glomeruli arose in Drosophila. The latter may be 
unlikely but would raise some intriguing possibilities 
about how the anatomical correspondence and circuitry 
between glomeruli in the PB and equivalent vertical par-
titions in the FB and EB PB circuits may differ between 
flies and other insects thought to have the same basic 
cellular composition and organization within the central 
complex, and how the geometric coordinates would 
then have had to shift along the axis of the PB to effect 
accurate behavioral responses. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Sean D. Murphy, Todd Safford, Chris-
topher M. Bruns, Konrad Rokicki, Yang Yu, Eric T. Trautman, 
Leslie L. Foster, and Donald J. Olbris, of the Janelia Scien-
tific Computing Software group, for their dedication, 
patience, and relentless efforts in creating the Janelia Work-
station, without which this work would not have been possi-
ble. The authors are deeply grateful to Aljoscha Nern for 
generously sharing critical reagents and protocols prior to 
publication and to Barret D. Pfeiffer for sharing unpublished 
molecular constructs. The authors thank Vivek Jayaraman 
for invaluable and insightful discussions; Ulrike Heberlein, 
Vivek Jayaraman, Nick Strausfeld, Wyatt Korff, and David 
Stern for critical comments on the article; and Sung Soo 
Kim for recognizing the extension of the spiny arbor of the 
PB G2-9 .b-IB.s-SPS.s cell into the SPS. The authors thank 
Joanna Hausenfluck, Gina DePasquale, Allison Sowell, and 
Adrianne Enos for assistance with immunohistochemistry 
(JH), brain dissections (GD, AS), and brain mounting (AE). 
T.W. thanks Arnim Jenett for his introductory tutorial on </p>

<p>central complex and central brain anatomy and Y. Aso for 
assistance with Fluorender and providing the masks for the 
gall and LAL. The authors also thank Don Ready and Elena 
Rivas for independently suggesting the term "tile" for the 
EB volume. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>ROLE OF AUTHORS </p>



<p>T. Wolff et al </p>



<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



<p>Drosophila central complex anatomy and neurons </p>

<p>The Journal of Comparative Neurology | Research in Systems Neuroscience </p>



</text></tei>