<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4780720" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: 5-Fluorouracil (5-FU) was loaded in hollow microspheres to improve its oral 
bioavailability. 5-FU hollow microspheres were developed by a solvent diffusion-evaporation 
method. The effect of Span 80 concentration, ether/ethanol volume ratio, and polyvinyl 
pyrrolidone/ethyl cellulose weight ratio on physicochemical characteristics, floating, and in vitro 
release behaviors of 5-FU hollow microspheres was investigated and optimized. The formulation 
and technology composed of Span 80 (1.5%, w/v), ether/ethanol (1.0:10.0, v/v), and polyvinyl 
pyrrolidone/ethyl cellulose (1.0:10.0, w/w) were employed to develop three batch samples, 
which showed an excellent reproducibility. The microspheres were spherical with a hollow 
structure with high drug loading amount (28.4%±0.5%) and production yield (74.2%±0.6%); they 
exhibited excellent floating and sustained release characteristics in simulated gastric and intes-
tinal fluid. Pharmacokinetic studies demonstrated that 5-FU hollow microspheres significantly 
enhanced oral bioavailability (area under curve, [AUC] (0−t) : 12.53±1.65 mg/L*h vs 7.80±0.83 
and 5.82±0.83 mg/L*h) with longer elimination half-life (t 1/2 ) (15.43±2.12 hours vs 2.25±0.22 
and 1.43±0.18 hours) and mean residence time (7.65±0.97 hours vs 3.61±0.41 and 
2.34±0.35 hours), in comparison with its solid microspheres and powder. In vivo distribution 
results from tumor-bearing nude mice demonstrated that the animals administered with 5-FU 
hollow microspheres had much higher drug content in tumor, plasma, and stomach at 1 and 
8 hours except for 0.5 hours sample collection time point in comparison with those adminis-
tered with 5-FU solid microspheres and its powder. These results suggested that the hollow 
microspheres would be a promising controlled drug delivery system for an oral chemotherapy 
agent like 5-FU. 
5-Fluorouracil (5-FU) belongs to a family of antimetabolite antitumor drugs and 
interferes with nucleic acid and DNA synthesis, resulting in cancer cell death. 
1-3 It is 
one of the most widely used antitumor drugs for the treatment of several solid tumors 
such as colorectal, breast, liver, brain, and pancreas cancer, either alone or in combina-
tion with other drugs. 
4-9 Because of the poor absorption of 5-FU from gastrointestinal 
tract and greatly variable oral bioavailability, it was commonly used intravenously 
in clinic. Patients have to be continually administered high drug doses because of 
the short biological half-life (10-20 minutes) of 5-FU. At present, to obtain an ideal 
therapeutic effect in patients, 5-FU injection is frequently administered every day by 
intravenous bolus injection for 5 days and this treatment procedure is repeated every </p>

<p>correspondence: ling Zhao 
Department of Pharmaceutical sciences, 
college of Pharmacy, sichuan Medical 
University, 3-319, Zhongshan road, 
Jiangyang Zone, luzhou, sichuan, 646000, 
People's republic of china 
Tel/fax +86 830 3162 291 
email zhaoling-998@163.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Drug Design, Development and Therapy 
3 March 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>998 </p>

<p>huang et al </p>

<p>28 days with three cycles. 
10 However, intravenous adminis-
tration is commonly associated with hematological, neural, 
and cardiac severe systemic adverse effects. Therefore, oral 
delivery systems containing 5-FU, including gelatin/chitosan 
microspheres, poly (dl-lactic-co-glycolic acid) nanopar-
ticles, alginate-chitosan/montmorillonite nanocomposite 
systems, and floating microspheres, have been developed 
in order to improve oral bioavailability with a continuous 
sustained release behavior. </p>

<p>11-14 </p>

<p>The oral sustained or controlled drug delivery system 
can release the drug slowly into the gastrointestinal tract and 
maintain a relative steady blood drug concentration for a 
longer time. However, such drug delivery systems have been 
affected by different gastric retention times resulting from 
gastric emptying. 
15 In general, an incomplete release and short 
residence time of the drug formulation in the upper gastroin-
testinal tract will result in lower oral bioavailability. Thus, it is 
particularly important to avoid these problems and prolong the 
gastric retention time of drug dosage forms, which contribute 
to retain the sustained or controlled drug delivery in stomach 
for a longer time and improve oral bioavailability of the drug 
which is preferentially absorbed in the upper site of the small 
intestine. During the past decades, many studies concerning 
the oral sustained or controlled release dosage forms possess-
ing prolonged gastric emptying time have been done, such as 
bioadhesive systems, swelling type dosage forms, high density 
drug preparations, and floating dosage forms. </p>

<p>16-24 </p>

<p>In order to improve the gastric retention time of the drug, 
floating dosage forms that are less dense than the gastric 
fluid (1.004 g/cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) have been extensively studied, including 
single-unit and multiunit dosage forms. The single-unit dos-
age forms, such as tablets, pills, and capsules, have a short-
coming in that drugs exhibit an "all-or-nothing" release in the 
emptying process. 
15,17 Hollow microspheres, as a multiunit 
floating drug delivery system, pass through the gastrointes-
tinal tract, avoid gastric emptying, and then release the drug 
more uniformly. Furthermore, compared with single-unit 
dosage forms, the more uniform the distribution of these 
multiunit drug dosage forms is in the gastrointestinal tract, 
the more reproducible drug absorption and the less local 
irritation will be obtained. </p>

<p>25-27 </p>

<p>The objective of the study was to develop and evaluate 
multiple-unit hollow microspheres containing 5-FU in 
order to prolong the release of the drug and improve oral 
bioavailability and biodistribution in a tumor-bearing 
model animal. On the basis of our previous studies, </p>

<p>25,26 </p>

<p>solvent diffusion-evaporation method was used to prepare 
5-FU hollow microspheres employing various ratios of </p>

<p>polyvinyl pyrrolidone (PVP) and ethyl cellulose (EC) as drug 
controlled-release polymer blends. The morphology, particle 
size distribution, drug loading amount, floating properties, 
and in vitro drug release behavior of 5-FU loaded hollow 
microspheres were investigated. In addition, the pharma-
cokinetic behavior in rabbits and biodistribution in a tumor-
bearing model animal of 5-FU hollow microspheres were 
compared with that of its nonfloating microspheres (solid 
microspheres) and its powder in rabbits to assess the useful-
ness of oral hollow microspheres drug delivery system. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
cells and animals </p>

<p>MCF-7 cells were provided from the Department of 
Oncology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Sichuan Medi-
cal University (Luzhou, People's Republic of China). The 
protocol for this study was approved by the ethics committee 
of Sichuan Medical University. 
Albino rabbits (average weight of 1.35±0.10 kg) were 
obtained from the Laboratory Animal Center of Sichuan 
Medical University. Balb/c nude mice (5-6 weeks of 
age, ~17 g) were supplied by Jianyang Dashuo Biology 
Technology Co, Ltd. (Luzhou, People's Republic of China). 
All animals used in this study were exposed to a 12-hour 
light/dark cycle and received food and water throughout 
the study. All the experimental procedures were approved 
(Approval number: 2013004) by the Sichuan Medical 
University Animal Ethical Experimentation Committee 
(Luzhou, People's Republic of China). </p>

<p>reagents </p>

<p>RPMI 1640 cell culture medium and fetal bovine serum 
were obtained from Luzhou Kelong Biology Technology 
Co. Ltd. (Luzhou, People's Republic of China). 5-FU was 
purchased from Chongqing Laimei Pharmaceuticals Com., 
Ltd. (Chongqing, People's Republic of China). PVP k-29/32 
was a gift sample from ISP Technologies, Inc. (New Jersey, 
USA). EC (10 cp) was provided by Shanghai Colorcon Coat-
ing Technology Co. Limited (Shanghai, People's Republic of 
China). Ethanol, ether, and other reagents (analytical grade) 
were purchased from Luzhou Juhe Chemical Regent Co. Ltd. 
(Luzhou, People's Republic of China). </p>

<p>Preparation of hollow microspheres </p>

<p>Hollow microspheres containing 5-FU were prepared by 
a solvent diffusion-evaporation method described in our 
previous studies. 
26,28,29 Briefly, 5-FU powder and polymer 
blends of EC and PVP were firstly dissolved or dispersed </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>999 </p>

<p>A 5-fluorouracil-loaded floating gastroretentive hollow microsphere </p>

<p>in ethanol at room temperature by ultrasonication, fol-
lowed by addition of ether. Under a constant stirring with 
a propeller type agitator at 300× g at 30°C in oil bath, the 
polymer-drug solution was introduced into liquid paraffin 
containing Span 80 (1.5%, w/v), forming an oil-in-oil (o/o) 
type emulsion. Then, the emulsion was constantly stirred 
until the evaporation of the solvent. After being filtered, 
washed with n-hexane, and dried overnight at 40°C, the 
hollow microsphere samples were stored in desiccators at 
room temperature. 
Preparation of nonfloating microspheres (solid micro-
spheres) was the same as the hollow microspheres and the 
formulation of organic solution was composed of 5-FU, EC, 
PVP, and ethanol. </p>

<p>scanning electron microscopic 
observation </p>

<p>Scanning electron microscopy (Hitachi S-3000N, Hitachi 
Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) was used to confirm the characteris-
tics of the hollow microspheres. Before scanning, hollow 
microspheres containing 5-FU were sputtered with gold to 
make the surface conductive. In addition, the microspheres 
were dissected with a knife to investigate the internal 
morphology. </p>

<p>Particle size distribution analysis </p>

<p>The particle size distribution of hollow microspheres 
containing 5-FU was measured by standard test sieves 
(Anping County Wire and Wire Mesh Factory, Hengshui, 
Hebei Province, People's Republic of China). Particles that 
passed through one sieve but were retained on the other were 
collected and accurately weighed, then evaluated on the basis 
of the weight fraction on each sieve. </p>

<p>Drug loading amount and production 
yield determination </p>

<p>Drug loading amount in hollow microspheres containing 
5-FU was performed by dissolving about 10 mg of hollow 
microsphere samples in 10 mL of ethanol at room temperature 
by ultrasonication. The drug concentration was determined 
using a UV-visible spectrophotometer (UV-2102; Shanghai 
Unico Instrument Co. Ltd, Shanghai, People's Republic of 
China) at 265 nm. 
The production yield of hollow microspheres contain-
ing 5-FU was calculated by dividing the weight of the dried 
microspheres by the weight of the drug and polymers. Drug 
loading amount and production yield of hollow microspheres 
were calculated as per Equations 1 and 2, respectively. </p>

<p>Drug loading </p>

<p>amount (%) </p>

<p>Amount of 5-FU in hollow 
microspher 
= 
e es 
Amount of hollow microspheres </p>

<p>containing 5-FU </p>

<p>×100 (1) </p>

<p>Production </p>

<p>yield (%) </p>

<p>Dried microspheres (mg) 
5-FU weight pol 
= 
+ 
y ymer weight 
×100 (2) </p>

<p>Buoyancy test </p>

<p>The buoyancy of 5-FU loaded microspheres was studied 
using the method described in previous literature. 
30 Briefly, 
100 microspheres were dispersed in 900 mL of enzyme-
free simulated gastric fluid (HCl/NaCl solution containing 
0.02% Tween-80; pH 1.2) or enzyme-free simulated 
intestinal fluid (KH 2 PO 4 /NaOH solution containing 0.02% 
Tween-80; pH 7.4) at 37°C±0.5°C. The dispersing medium 
was stirred at 100× g with standard paddle method of Chinese 
Pharmacopoeia appendix Xc. No 2. 
31 Buoyancy capacity was 
evaluated based on the number of microspheres that remained 
buoyant on the test medium. </p>

<p>in vitro dissolution studies </p>

<p>The in vitro release of 5-FU loaded microspheres was investi-
gated using rotating basket method of Chinese Pharmacopoeia 
appendix XC. No 1. 
31 An appropriate amount of microspheres 
that were equivalent to 10 mg of drug was placed in a rotating 
basket that had a smaller pore size than microspheres. Then 
the rotating basket containing 5-FU microspheres was soaked 
in 900 mL of enzyme-free simulated gastric fluid (HCl/NaCl 
solution containing 0.02% Tween-80; pH 1.2) or enzyme-free 
simulated intestinal fluid (KH 2 PO 4 /NaOH solution containing 
0.02% Tween-80; pH 7.4) at 37°C±0.5°C as the release 
medium at a stirring speed of 100× g. At appropriate time 
intervals, a 5 mL sample solution was taken from medium and 
replaced with the same volume of blank release medium at the 
same temperature after each sampling to maintain an original 
volume. The sample solution was analyzed by UV-visible 
spectrophotometer (UV-2102) at 265 nm and calculated with 
a standard cure (A=0.055C+0.058 for simulated gastric fluid, 
A=0.058C-0.007 for simulated gastric fluid). According to 
drug quality standard of Chinese Pharmacopoeia for the 
validation of analytical methods, 
31 the selectivity, linearity, 
accuracy, precision, recovery, and stability of UV analytical 
methods were validated. As shown in Figure 1, no interference 
of the excipients including PVP, EC, and Tween-80 used in 
hollow microspheres was observed and the λ max value related 
to the absorption peak of 5-FU in the medium was 265 nm. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>huang et al </p>

<p>Figure 1 Absorption spectra of 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) in enzyme-free simulated 
gastric fluid (SGF) and enzyme-free simulated intestinal fluid (SIF). 
Notes: (a) SGF; (b) SIF; (c) SGF spiked with excipients used for 5-FU hollow 
microspheres; (d) SIF spiked with excipients used for 5-FU hollow microspheres; 
(e) SGF spiked with 5-FU; and (f) SIF spiked with 5-FU. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic study </p>

<p>The rabbits used in the present study were fasted overnight 
for 12 hours with free access to water. 5-FU hollow micro-
spheres as test formulation and its solid microspheres and 
powder as controls in the sodium carboxymethy cellulose 
suspension (0.5%, w/w) form were respectively administered 
to six rabbits at a dose of 50 mg/kg body weight through the 
oral routes. An amount of 1.2 mL blood samples were col-
lected from the marginal ear vein before administration and at 
0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, and 24 hours after oral 
administration. Each blood sample was centrifuged immedi-
ately at 5,000× g for 10 minutes and the supernatant plasma 
was collected and kept at -20°C for further analysis. 
Frozen plasma sample was thawed at room tempera-
ture. Biosample was further carried out and analyzed by 
modification of our previous study. 
1 In brief, 0.5 mL of 
plasma sample was taken into a 5 mL centrifuge tube. And 
100 µL ammonium acetate buffer (pH 3.5; 0.01 M) and 
3 mL of isopropanol-ethyl acetate (15:85, v/v) were added. 
The mixture was vortexed for 3 minutes and centrifuged at 
10,000× g for 10 minutes. The supernatant was decanted 
and evaporated to dryness at 50°C using N 2 flow. The dry 
residues were reconstituted with 100 µL of mobile phase and 
centrifuged at 10,000× g for 10 minutes. Then, 20 µL sample 
of the clear supernatant was injected onto a high-performance 
liquid chromatography (HPLC) system. 
The amount of 5-FU in rabbit plasma sample was 
determined by the HPLC system, which consisted of Dionex </p>

<p>ultimate 3000 series including pump (LPG-3400SD), UV-vis 
detector (VWD-3100), auto injector (WPS-3000), and column 
oven (TCC-3000). Separation was performed on a reverse 
phase C18 column (Inertsil ODS-SP; 4.6×250 mm, 5 µm 
particle size, GL Sciences, Tokyo Japan) with a guard col-
umn (Phenomenex C18, 4.0 mm ×3.0 mm, 5 µm particle 
size, USA) at 25°C using a mobile phase of acetonitrile-
ammonium acetate buffer (pH 3.5; 0.01 M) (1.0:99.0 v/v) at 
the flow rate of 0.8 mL/min. The sample was analyzed at a 
detection wavelength of 265 nm and the injection volume was 
20 µL. According to the validation of bioanalytical methods 
of the US Food and Drug Administration guidelines, the 
method was validated in terms of selectivity, linearity, preci-
sion, accuracy, extraction efficiency, and stability in rabbit 
plasma. As shown in Figure 2, the HPLC assay resulted in 
good baseline resolution and rabbit plasma matrix compo-
nents did not interfere with the analysis of 5-FU. The method 
was linear over the range of 0.020-20.0 µg/mL (r 
2 =0.9986). 
The lower quantification limit was 0.020 µg/mL. The preci-
sion and accuracy for quality control plasma samples ranged 
from 4.57% to 8.87% and from 83.6% to 106.4%. Extrac-
tion efficiency at three concentrations was 91.5% to 96.4%. 
Therefore, the method was suitable for 5-FU quantification 
in rabbit plasma samples. </p>

<p>Biodistribution in tumor-bearing mice </p>

<p>Firstly, MCF-7 breast cancer cells were cultured in RPMI-
1640 medium (GE Healthcare Life Science, Uppsala, 
Sweden) with 10% fetal bovine serum (GE Healthcare Life 
Science) at 37°C with 5% CO 2 . Then the aforementioned 
cancer cells (5×10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>) were subcutaneously inoculated in the 
right flanks of Balb/c nude mice to obtain a tumor-bearing 
animal model. When the tumor reached about 100 mm 
3 in size, 
the tumor-bearing mice were randomized into three groups 
(nine mice per group) and were fasted overnight for 12 hours 
with free access to water. Each group was orally administered 
with 5-FU hollow microspheres as test formulation and its 
solid microspheres and powder as controls in the sodium 
carboxymethyl cellulose suspension (0.5%, w/w) form at a 
dose of 100 mg/kg body weight. At 0.5, 1, and 8 hours after 
oral drug administration, three mice were sacrificed. Blood, 
tumor, heart, liver, spleen, lung, kidney, and brain samples 
were immediately collected. Blood was separated by centri-
fuging at 5,000× g for 5 minutes to obtain plasma sample. 
Tissues samples were washed with ice-cold 0.9% saline and 
dried with filter paper. Then these tissues were homogenized 
with 0.9% saline in appropriate concentration (tumor and liver 
1:3; heart, spleen, lung, and brain 1:20; kidney 1:5, w/w). </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1001 </p>

<p>A 5-fluorouracil-loaded floating gastroretentive hollow microsphere </p>

<p>Figure 2 Representative HPLC chromatograms of 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) in rabbit plasma: (A) blank plasma; (B) blank plasma spiked with 5-FU; and (C) plasma sample after 
oral administration of 5-FU hollow microspheres. 
Abbreviation: hPlc, high-performance liquid chromatography. </p>

<p>Above 0.1 mL of plasma and tissue homogenates were 
mixed with 25 µL ammonium acetate buffer (pH 3.5; 0.01 M) 
and 1 mL of isopropanol-ethyl acetate (15:85, v/v). The mix-
tures were vortexed and extracted by ultrasonication, then 
centrifuged at 10,000× g for 10 minutes. After that, the organic 
layer was collected and evaporated to dryness under N 2 flow 
at 50°C. The dry residues were redissolved with 100 µL of 
mobile phase. Then, 20 µL sample of the clear supernatant 
was injected into the above-mentioned HPLC system. 
In order to investigate biodistribution in tumor-bearing 
mice after oral administration of 5-FU hollow microspheres 
as test formulation and its solid microspheres and powder 
as controls, the HPLC assay method was developed and 
validated through determination of specificity, linearity, 
quantification limit, precision, accuracy, recovery, and 
stability. The analysis method showed specificity since no 
significant interfering peaks at or near the retention time of 
5-FU were detected from endogenous substances by com-
paring chromatograms of blank mice tissue homogenate 
of the tumor as a representative sample, blank mice tumor 
homogenate spiked with 5-FU, and mice tumor sample col-
lected after oral administration of 5-FU hollow microspheres, 
respectively (Figure 3). The analysis method had proven to </p>

<p>be simple, specific, sensitive, accurate, and precise and was 
suitable for 5-FU quantification in biosamples in tumor-
bearing mice. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>The plasma drug concentration over time data was used to 
calculate pharmacokinetic parameters including the area under 
the plasma drug concentration-time curve up to 24 hours post-
administration, time to reach the maximum plasma drug con-
centration (T max ), maximum plasma drug concentration (C max ), 
t 1/2 , and MRT by <rs id="software-0" type="software">DAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.0</rs> pharmacokinetics software. 
Student's t-tests were used to evaluate the significant dif-
ferences between the pharmacokinetic data of 5-FU hollow 
microspheres as test formulation and its powder as control. 
Values were reported as mean ± standard deviation and 
P0.05 was considered the statistical significant difference. </p>

<p>Results and discussion 
effect of span 80 concentration on 
particle size, drug loading amount, and 
production yield </p>

<p>In the present study, the solvent diffusion-evaporation method 
was employed to develop 5-FU hollow microspheres as a </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1002 </p>

<p>huang et al </p>

<p>Figure 3 Representative HPLC chromatograms of 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) in tumor-bearing mice biosamples: (A) blank tumor; (B) blank tumor spiked with 5-FU; and (C) 
tumor sample after oral administration of 5-FU hollow microspheres. 
Abbreviation: hPlc, high-performance liquid chromatography. </p>

<p>floating drug delivery system. From our previous studies, </p>

<p>26,28,29 </p>

<p>the process of o/o type emulsification is very important to 
form hollow microspheres. Thus, when the other conditions 
were equal, the effect of Span 80 concentration in the liquid 
paraffin on particle size, drug loading amount, and produc-
tion yield of 5-FU hollow microspheres was investigated 
and the results are summarized in Table 1. It can be seen 
from particle size distribution that when Span 80 (as emulsi-
fier) concentration in the liquid paraffin was increased from 
0.5% (w/v) to 2.0% (w/v), the particle size of 5-FU hollow 
microspheres decreased, because of the decreasing interfacial 
tension between organic phase and liquid paraffin. In order </p>

<p>to stabilize o/o emulsion, the main function of Span 80 is to 
form a thin film around the droplets to prevent their coales-
cence. 
11 In fact, when the concentration of Span 80 was 1.5%, 
a more uniform particle size distribution of 5-FU hollow 
microspheres was obtained. In other words, the percentage 
of a 5-FU hollow microsphere ranged from 450 to 600 µm 
in diameter (67.5%±1.6%). As shown in Table 1, drug load-
ing amount and production yield increased with increasing 
concentration of the Span 80 up to 1.5%. However, when the 
concentration of the Span 80 was more than 1.5%, the drug 
loading amount and production yield decreased. Thus, 1.5% 
of Span 80 was chosen as an emulsifier for further study. </p>

<p>Table 1 The effect of Span 80 concentration in the liquid paraffin on particle size, drug loading amount, and production yield of 
5-fluorouracil hollow microspheres </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Span 80 
concentration (%) </p>

<p>Particle size distribution 
Drug 
loading (%) </p>

<p>Production 
yield (%) 
450 µm (%) 
450-600 µm (%) 
600 µm (%) </p>

<p>0.5 
9.1±0.4 
25.6±2.5 
63.3±3.6 
18.4±1.1 
38.9±1.0 
1.0 
14.2±0.7 
27.2±2.4 
58.6±2.9 
23.5±1.2 
48.4±1.3 
1.5 
19.5±0.5 
70.6±4.7 
9.9±1.0 
27.6±1.4 
67.5±1.6 
2.0 
58.1±3.8 
33.6±2.2 
8.3±0.6 
21.3±1.1 
60.2±1.9 </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1003 </p>

<p>A 5-fluorouracil-loaded floating gastroretentive hollow microsphere </p>

<p>effect of ether/ethanol volume ratio on 
particle size, drug loading amount, and 
production yield </p>

<p>As shown in Table 2, the formation of 5-FU hollow micro-
spheres was greatly affected by ether/ethanol volume ratio. 
When ethanol was employed alone as organic phase, no 
hollow microspheres were observed, except some non-
floating microspheres (solid microspheres). The reason 
was that ethanol cannot diffuse into the liquid paraffin: 
the polymer cannot aggregate between the continuation 
phase and dispersion phase. 
28,29 In comparison with ethanol 
alone, a mixture of ether and ethanol was used to obtain 
5-FU hollow microspheres. Interestingly, after emulsifica-
tion of about 5 minutes, the air bubble was observed in the 
microsphere droplets by using an optical microscope. This 
was because the ether can be quickly diffused into the liquid 
paraffin, resulting in polymer instantly solidifing into a thin 
film. When ether/ethanol volume ratio was increased from 
0.5:10.0 to 1.0:10.0, drug loading amount and production 
yield increased, too. However, when the concentration of the 
ether/ethanol volume ratio was more than 1.0:10.0, the drug 
loading amount and production yield decreased. In addition, 
there was no difference in particle size distribution among 
three samples prepared by ether/ethanol volume ratio that 
ranged from 0.5:10.0 to 1.5:10.0 (P0.05). Therefore, ether/ 
ethanol (1.0:10.0, v/v) was used for further study. </p>

<p>effect of PVP/ec weight ratio on particle 
size, drug loading amount, production 
yield, and floating and in vitro release 
behavior </p>

<p>On the basis of preliminary experiment, it was suggested 
that the drug release rate and cumulative release percentage 
of 5-FU hollow microspheres prepared by mixing polymer 
blends of hydrophilic PVP and hydrophobic EC were signifi-
cantly improved. 
26 Therefore, the effect of PVP/EC weight 
ratio on particle size, drug loading amount, production yield, 
and floating and in vitro release behavior was investigated. 
As shown in Table 3, the average diameter and drug loading 
amount increased with the increased PVP/EC weight ratio 
from 0:10 to 1.0:10.0. The reason was that a higher viscos-
ity of the internal phase with increasing PVP/EC weight 
ratio rendered a higher resistance to the shearing of emul-
sion, thereby increasing the particle size of 5-FU hollow 
microspheres. 
15 Another possibility is that the rapid polymer 
precipitation resulted in hardness avoiding further particle 
size reduction during solvent evaporation. 
26 Drug loading 
amount is usually associated with the particle size distribution 
of microspheres, and the larger the particle size, the higher 
the drug loading amount. In general, as the particle size of 
5-FU hollow microspheres was increased, the thickness of the 
wall of microspheres increased. The result was in agreement 
with the results reported in literature. 
27 In addition, when the </p>

<p>Table 2 The effect of ether/ethanol volume ratio on particle size, drug loading amount, and production yield of 5-fluorouracil hollow 
microspheres </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Ether/ethanol (v/v) 
Particle size distribution 
Drug 
loading (%) </p>

<p>Production 
yield (%) 
450 µm (%) 
450-600 µm (%) 
600 µm (%) </p>

<p>0:10.0 
-
-
-
-
0 
0.5:10.0 
19.5±2.1 
60.1±2.5 
20.4±2.1 
21.4±1.3 
58.4±1.5 
1.0:10.0 
18.1±1.6 
62.9±4.2 
19.0±1.7 
26.7±1.5 
71.1±2.3 
1.5:10.0 
20.0±2.4 
61.2±3.7 
18.8±1.9 
20.9±1.2 
32.2±1.2 </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviation: v, volume. </p>

<p>Table 3 The effect of PVP/EC weight ratio on particle size, drug loading amount, and production yield of 5-fluorouracil hollow 
microspheres </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>PVP/EC (w/w) 
Particle size distribution 
Drug loading 
amount (%) </p>

<p>Production 
yield (%) 
450 µm (%) 
450-600 µm (%) 
600 µm (%) </p>

<p>0.0:10.0 
18.1±1.6 
62.9±4.2 
19.0±1.7 
26.7±1.5 
71.1±2.3 
0.2:10.0 
17.5±2.1 
61.3±2.5 
21.2±1.3 
27.1±1.2 
70.3±2.6 
0.5:10.0 
15.1±1.6 
61.7±4.2 
23.2±1.8 
27.3±1.9 
69.8±2.7 
1.0:10.0 
13.2±1.1 
59.2±5.3 
27.6±0.8 
28.1±1.8 
72.2±2.3 
2.0:10.0 
10.1±1.1 
56.2±5.7 
33.7±0.8 
29.8±1.5 
60.5±3.4 </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: EC, ethyl cellulose; PVP, polyvinyl pyrrolidone; w, weight. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1004 </p>

<p>huang et al </p>

<p>Figure 4 Effect of PVP/EC weight ratio on floating behavior of 5-fluorouracil hollow microspheres in simulated gastric fluid (A) and simulated intestinal fluid (B). 
Note: Mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: EC, ethyl cellulose; PVP, polyvinyl pyrrolidone. </p>

<p>PVP/EC weight ratio was increased from 0:10.0 to 1.0:10.0, 
there was no significant difference in the production yield 
of 5-FU hollow microspheres (P0.05). However, as the 
PVP/EC weight ratio was increased to 2.0:10.0, production 
yield decreased. A possible reason is that the viscosity of 
drug-polymer solution at PVP/EC weight ratio of 2.0:10.0 
was too high to disperse in liquid paraffin containing Span 
80 (1.5%, w/v), forming an o/o type emulsion. 
As shown in Figure 4, 5-FU hollow microspheres in the 
case of PVP/EC weight ratio ranging from 0:10 to 1.0:10.0 
possessed good buoyancy in gastric fluid and intestinal fluid 
containing Tween-80 that simulates the surface tension of 
gastrointestinal fluids. 
24 More specifically, the buoyancy rate 
of these hollow microspheres after 12 hours was more than 
95%. Furthermore, no significant difference in the buoyancy </p>

<p>rate among these formulations was observed (P0.05). How-
ever, when 5-FU hollow microspheres were prepared using 
PVP/EC weight ratio of 2.0:10.0, the buoyancy rate decreased 
to 53.7%±2.9% and 51.5%±3.6% after 12 hours in simulated 
gastric fluid and intestinal fluid, respectively. The phenom-
enon could be explained in that the channels on the surface 
of 5-FU hollow microspheres, which resulted from PVP and 
5-FU dissolution, became too large to be penetrated into the 
hollow cavities by the release medium with an increasing of 
PVP/EC weight ratio up to 2.0:10.0. 
Drug release profiles from 5-FU hollow microspheres 
are presented in Figure 5. It was observed that drug release 
kinetics in simulated gastric fluid and intestinal fluid was 
significantly influenced by the PVP/EC weight ratio. 
Importantly, not only the slope but also the shape of the </p>

<p>Figure 5 Effect of PVP/EC weight ratio on in vitro release behavior of 5-fluorouracil hollow microspheres in simulated gastric fluid (A) and simulated intestinal fluid (B). 
Note: Mean ± standard deviation. 
Abbreviations: EC, ethyl cellulose; PVP, polyvinyl pyrrolidone. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1005 </p>

<p>A 5-fluorouracil-loaded floating gastroretentive hollow microsphere </p>

<p>release curves was affected, 
26 which showed differences in 
the underlying drug release mechanisms. However, there 
was no difference in release behaviors in both the release 
mediums. When PVP/EC (0:10.0) was used to prepare 5-FU 
hollow microspheres, at the end of 24 hours the cumulative 
drug release amount in simulated gastric fluid and intestinal 
fluid was only 62.5%±2.0% and 60.2%±2.9%, respectively. 
When the PVP/EC weight ratio was increased to 1.0:10.0, 
it was observed that the hollow microspheres containing 
5-FU slowly released the drug and at the end of 24 hours the 
cumulative drug release amount increased to 97.8%±3.4% 
and 96.9%±3.0%, respectively. In the case of PVP/EC weight 
ratio of 2.0:10.0, the hollow microspheres containing 5-FU 
released 100% of the drug within 8 hours. In order to prolong 
the release of 5-FU, the production yield and floating capa-
bility of 5-FU hollow microspheres with PVP/EC (2.0:10.0) 
were lower than those of the PVP/EC (1.0:10.0). Thus, PVP/ 
EC (1.0:10.0) was chosen for further study. </p>

<p>Preparation and in vitro evaluation of 
5-FU hollow microspheres </p>

<p>On the basis of the above experiments, when the amount of 
5-FU remained constant, the formulation and technology 
composed of Span 80 (1.5%, w/v), ether/ethanol (1.0:10.0, 
v/v), and PVP/EC (1.0:10.0) were employed to develop three 
batches (20120401, 20120402, and 20120403) of 5-FU hol-
low microspheres. The particle size, morphology, drug load-
ing amount, production yield, floating efficiency (12 hours), 
and in vitro release behavior of three batches samples were 
evaluated and the results are summarized in Table 4 and 
Figures 6 and 7. As shown in Table 4, there was no difference 
in particle size distribution, drug loading amount, production 
yield, and floating efficiency of 5-FU hollow microspheres. 
In vitro floating efficiency investigation indicated that, in 
spite of stirring the simulated gastric fluid for 12 hours, 
more than 95.0% 5-FU hollow microspheres still continued 
floating. As shown in Figure 4, 5-FU hollow microspheres 
were spherical with a cavity within a hard polymer shell 
and a lot of pores in internal walls of hollow microspheres, 
which resulted in lower density. It was suggested that </p>

<p>Table 4 The particle size, drug loading amount, and production yield and floating efficiency of 5-fluorouracil hollow microspheres </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Batch no 
Particle size distribution 
Drug 
loading (%) </p>

<p>Production 
yield (%) </p>

<p>Floating 
efficiency (%) 
450 µm (%) 
450-600 µm (%) 
600 µm (%) </p>

<p>20120401 
12.8±1.1 
58.1±4.6 
28.3±1.1 
28.8±1.2 
74.9±2.5 
96.6±2.9 
20120402 
13.1±1.3 
61.9±4.7 
25.0±1.1 
27.9±1.2 
73.8±2.5 
97.2±2.5 
20120403 
12.9±1.1 
63.6±4.6 
23.5±1.2 
28.6±1.2 
74.0±2.5 
95.7±2.0 </p>

<p>Note: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>5-FU hollow microspheres possessed an excellent floating 
effect. As shown in Figure 7, dissolution profiles of in vitro 
release patterns indicated that similar drug release behaviors 
among the three batches of 5-FU hollow microspheres were 
observed. Therefore, the formulation and technology used 
to develop 5-FU hollow microspheres in this study have a 
good reproducibility. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic evaluation </p>

<p>In order to investigate further whether 5-FU hollow micro-
spheres could enhance its oral bioavailability and improve 
pharmacokinetic behaviors, 5-FU hollow microspheres and 
its solid microspheres and powder as the control groups 
were orally administrated to rabbits at a dose of 50 mg/kg 
body weight. The mean plasma drug concentration-time 
curve is shown in Figure 8 and the relevant pharmacokinetic 
parameters calculated by <rs id="software-1" type="software">DAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2.0</rs> software are summarized 
in Table 5. As shown in Figure 8 and Table 5, 5-FU hol-
low microspheres demonstrated the greatest absorption 
and the slowest elimination after gavage administration in 
comparison with its solid microspheres and powder. The 
C max and T max of 5-FU solid microspheres and powder were 
2.25±0.22 mg/L and 1.00±0.15 hours, and 2.55±0.19 mg/L 
and 0.75±0.11 hours, respectively; the plasma drug con-
centration was detectable up to 12 and 8 hours, whereas the </p>

<p>Figure 6 Scanning electron microscopy photographs of 5-fluorouracil hollow 
microspheres (batch: 20120401). </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1006 </p>

<p>huang et al </p>

<p>Table 5 Pharmacokinetic parameters of 5-FU after oral administration of 5-FU hollow microspheres and its solid microspheres and 
powder to rabbits at a dose of 50 mg/kg body weight </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>AUC (0-t) (mg/L*hours) 
MRT (0-t) (hours) 
C max (mg/L) 
T max (hours) 
t 1/2 (hours) </p>

<p>5-FU hollow microspheres 
12.53±1.65* 
7.65±0.97* 
1.64±0.21* 
2.00±0.22* 
15.43±2.12* 
5-FU solid microspheres 
7.80±0.83 
3.61±0.41 
2.25±0.26 
1.00±0.15 
2.25±0.22 
5-FU powder 
5.82±0.83 
2.34±0.35 
2.55±0.19 
0.75±0.11 
1.43±0.18 </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean ± standard deviation. *P0.01 vs 5-FU solid microspheres and powder as the controls. 
Abbreviations: c max , maximum plasma drug concentration; 5-FU, 5-fluorouracil; MRT, mean residence time; T max , time to reach the maximum plasma drug concentration; 
t 1/2 , elimination half-life; AUC, area under curve. </p>

<p>Figure 7 Percentage cumulative release of three batches of 5-fluorouracil hollow microspheres in simulated gastric fluid (A) and simulated intestinal fluid (B). 
Note: Mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>C max and T max of hollow microspheres were 1.64±0.21 mg/L 
and 2.00±0.22 hours, respectively. At 24 hours after 
gavage administration of 5-FU hollow microspheres, the 
drug concentration in plasma was still detectable at about 
0.13±0.02 mg/L. These results suggested that 5-FU from 
hollow microspheres possessed slower drug release or 
absorption relatively. 
The t 1/2 and MRT of 5-FU hollow microspheres were 
15.43±2.12 hours and 7.65±0.97 hours, respectively, which 
were longer than those of its solid microspheres at t 1/2 of 
2.25±0.22 hours and MRT of 3.61±0.41 hours, and powder at 
t 1/2 of 1.43±0.18 hours and MRT of 2.34±0.35 hours, respec-
tively. Furthermore, it was worth noting that 5-FU hollow 
microspheres exhibited higher area under curve (AUC) (0−t) 
than its powder (12.53±1.65 mg/L*h vs 7.80±0.83 mg/L*h 
and 5.82±0.83 mg/L*h, P0.01). It was suggested that 5-FU 
hollow microspheres prolonged drug residence time in the 
gastrointestinal tract due to its good floating characteristic 
in gastric fluid, leading to a better and longer absorption 
effect. Li et al developed acyclovir-loaded spray-dried 
hollow microspheres and investigated its pharmacokinetic 
behavior in rabbits. The results showed it improved two to 
three folds in the oral bioavailability of acyclovir. 
32 Another 
study also indicated riboflavin-loaded microballoons as a </p>

<p>floating controlled drug delivery system were very useful for 
improving oral drug bioavailability in healthy humans. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Biodistribution evaluation in tumor-
bearing mice </p>

<p>There are many studies related to oral dosage forms of 
5-FU. 
11-14 However, there are very few studies on the 
biodistribution in a tumor-bearing animal model after oral 
administration. In the present study, drug biodistribution 
behaviors were carried out in tumor-bearing mice model 
to investigate the amount of 5-FU that is delivered to main 
organs and tumors. The content of 5-FU in tumor and main 
organs including heart, liver, spleen, lung, kidney, and stom-
ach at 0.5, 1, and 8 hours was measured by the HPLC method 
and illustrated in Figure 9 after oral administration of 5-FU 
hollow microspheres as a test formulation and its solid micro-
spheres and powder as controls in the sodium carboxymethyl 
cellulose suspension form at a dose of 72 mg/kg body weight. 
As shown in Figure 9, the elimination of 5-FU powder was 
the fastest among the three formulations in plasma, tumor, 
and main organs, while the drug concentration in biosamples 
at 8 hours after administration was not detectable. 5-FU hol-
low microspheres and its solid microspheres showed similar 
drug distribution trends in tumor-bearing mice. However, </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1007 </p>

<p>A 5-fluorouracil-loaded floating gastroretentive hollow microsphere </p>

<p>Figure 8 Plasma drug concentration-time curve after oral administration of 
5-fluorouracil (5-FU) hollow microspheres and its solid microspheres and powder 
to rabbits at a dose of 50 mg/kg body weight. 
Note: each point represents the mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>Figure 9 Drug distribution in plasma, tumor, and main tissues including heart, liver, 
spleen, lung, kidney, and stomach in tumor-bearing mice after oral administration 
of 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) hollow microspheres as a test formulation and its solid 
microspheres and powder as controls in the sodium carboxymethyl cellulose 
suspension form at a dose of 72 mg/kg body weight. 
Notes: These values are arithmetic mean ± standard deviation. Plasma, ng/mL; 
tumor and main tissues, ng/g. 
Abbreviation: h, hours. </p>

<p>on the one hand, the level of plasma drug concentration was 
found to be gentler in the case of 5-FU hollow microspheres 
than that of its solid microspheres, which indicated that 
5-FU hollow microspheres reduced rapid clearance from the 
circulation due to slower drug release rate. On the other, the 
animals administered with 5-FU hollow microspheres had 
a much higher drug content in tumor, plasma, and stomach </p>

<p>at 1 and 8 hours except for 0.5 hours sample collection time 
point in comparison with those administered with 5-FU 
solid microspheres. This result indicated that 5-FU hollow 
microspheres had improved tissue distribution characteristics 
of 5-FU to some extent. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In the present study, the effect of Span 80 concentration, 
ether/ethanol volume ratio, and PVP/EC weight ratio on 
physicochemical characteristics and floating and in vitro 
release behaviors was investigated and optimized. As a 
multiple-unit floating drug delivery system, 5-FU hollow 
microspheres were developed successfully by a solvent 
diffusion-evaporation method. An excellent reproducibility 
of formulation and technology was obtained. The micro-
spheres were spherical with hollow structures with high drug 
loading amount and production yield. 5-FU hollow micro-
spheres exhibited excellent floating and sustained release 
characteristics. Pharmacokinetic studies demonstrated that 
5-FU hollow microspheres showed significantly enhanced 
absorption and oral bioavailability with longer t 1/2 and MRT, 
which contributed to prolonging drug residence time in the 
gastrointestinal tract due to its good floating characteristic in 
gastric fluid. In vivo distribution results from tumor-bearing 
nude mice indicated that 5-FU hollow microspheres could 
improve tissue distribution characteristics of 5-FU to some 
extent. It could be concluded that the hollow microspheres 
would be a promising sustained and controlled drug delivery 
system for an oral delivery chemotherapy agent like 5-FU. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was financially supported by the National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (81101678 and 81341124), 
Science and Technology Support Project of Sichuan Province 
(2013SZZ006, 2014SZ0071 and 2014FZ0105), the Joint 
Fund of Sichuan Province, Luzhou City and Sichuan Medi-
cal University (14JC0134), the Key Program of the Scientific 
Research Foundation of the Education Department of Sichuan 
Province (12ZZ020; 12ZB066), the Scientific Research Foun-
dation of the Administration of Traditional Chinese Medicine 
of Sichuan Province (2012-F-026), the Scientific Research 
Foundation of the Health Bureau of Sichuan Province 
(130270 and 130269), and the Key Program of the Scientific 
Research Foundation of Bureau of Science and Technology 
of Luzhou City (2013LZLY-K80, 2013-S-47 [17/20]). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/drug-design-development-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal that spans the spectrum of drug design 
and development through to clinical applications. Clinical outcomes, 
patient safety, and programs for the development and effective, safe, 
and sustained use of medicines are a feature of the journal, which </p>

<p>has also been accepted for indexing on PubMed Central. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Drug Design, Development and Therapy 2016:10 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1008 </p>

<p>huang et al </p>



</text></tei>