<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4322207" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: Although successful airway management </p>

<p>is essential for emergency trauma care, comprehensive 
studies are limited. We sought to characterise current 
trauma care practice of airway management in the 
emergency departments (EDs) in Japan. </p>

<p>Design: Analysis of data from a prospective, </p>

<p>observational, multicentre registry-the Japanese 
Emergency Airway Network ( JEAN) registry. </p>

<p>Setting: 13 academic and community EDs from </p>

<p>different geographic regions across Japan. </p>

<p>Participants: 723 trauma patients who underwent </p>

<p>emergency intubation from March 2010 through 
August 2012. </p>

<p>Outcome measures: ED characteristics, patient and </p>

<p>operator demographics, methods of airway 
management, intubation success or failure at each 
attempt and adverse events. </p>

<p>Results: A total of 723 trauma patients who </p>

<p>underwent emergency intubation were eligible for the 
analysis. Traumatic cardiac arrest comprised 32.6% 
(95% CI 29.3% to 36.1%) of patients. Rapid sequence 
intubation (RSI) was the initial method chosen in 
23.9% (95% CI 21.0% to 27.2%) of all trauma patients 
and in 35.5% (95% CI 31.4% to 39.9%) of patients 
without cardiac arrest. Overall, intubation was 
successful in ≤3 attempts in 96% of patients (95% CI 
94.3% to 97.2%). There was a wide variation in the 
initial methods of intubation; RSI as the initial method 
was performed in 0-50.9% of all trauma patients 
among 12 EDs. Similarly, there was a wide variation in 
success rates and adverse event rates across the EDs. 
Success rates varied between 35.5% and 90.5% at the 
first attempt, and 85.1% and 100% within three 
attempts across the 12 EDs. </p>

<p>Conclusions: In this multicentre prospective study in </p>

<p>Japan, we observed a high overall success rate in 
airway management during trauma care. However, the 
methods of intubation and success rates were highly 
variable among hospitals. </p>

<p>and trauma care. Failure of emergency airway 
management is often associated with morbid-
ity and mortality in trauma patients. </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>Consequently, training in and understanding 
of airway management is a distinct discipline 
that is essential for successful trauma 
resuscitation. 
Evidence-based recommendations for airway 
management during trauma care exist within 
international and national guidelines in the 
USA. These guidelines indicate rapid 
sequence intubation (RSI) as the initial 
method of emergency airway management in 
most trauma patients. 
1 4 5 Recent studies 
reported that RSI is the most common airway 
management method in emergency depart-
ments (EDs) in North America and Europe. </p>

<p>6-9 </p>

<p>Despite the ubiquitous practice of emergency 
airway management in trauma patients, little is 
known about its current practice and perform-
ance in other industrialised nations. 
Therefore, we sought to describe the current 
practice of airway management for trauma 
patients in EDs in Japan. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design and setting 
We analysed the data of a prospective, observa-
tional, multicentre registry, the Japanese 
Emergency Airway Network registry. The study 
design, setting, methods of measurement and 
measured variables have been reported </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This is the first study to report disparities in 
trauma airway management based on multicen-
tre, prospective data. 
▪ Passive surveillance of data is subject to self-
reporting bias, leading to a possible underesti-
mation of failed intubations and adverse events. </p>

<p>Nakao S, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006623. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006623 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>elsewhere. 
10-13 Briefly, the registry is a consortium of 13 
academic and community EDs from different geographic 
regions across Japan. These EDs consist of 10 tertiary 
medical centres that have the capability of managing the 
most severe trauma patients and three secondary medical 
centres that are designated to treat moderately severe 
trauma patients. The participating EDs had a median ED 
census of 30 000 patient visits per year (range 9000-
67 000). The participating hospitals had a median trauma 
admission of 1000 per year (range 300-1500). 
14 All 13 EDs 
were staffed by attending emergency physicians, and 12 
had affiliations with emergency medicine residency train-
ing programmes. Each hospital maintained individual pro-
tocols, policies and procedures for emergency airway 
management. Intubations were performed by attending 
physicians or by resident physicians at the discretion of the 
ED's attending physician. The ethics committee of each 
participating centre approved the protocol, with waiver of 
informed consent before data collection. </p>

<p>Patients 
The registry prospectively collected information on con-
secutive patients who underwent airway management in 
the participating EDs during a 30-month period, from 
March 2010 to August 2012. All adult and paediatric 
trauma patients who underwent intubation were eligible 
for this analysis. We excluded an ED in which the 
number of trauma intubations was less than 10 from the 
current analysis. </p>

<p>Data collection 
Data collection was passive, relying on self-reports by the 
intubators on duty. After each intubation, the intubators 
completed a standardised data sheet, including the 
patient's age, sex, estimated weight, primary indication 
for intubation, methods used to facilitate intubation, 
intubator's level of training (emergency physicians, resi-
dent physicians and transitional-year residents) and spe-
cialty (emergency physician or not), number of 
attempts, success or failure, and intubation-related 
adverse events. Method was defined as the set of medica-
tions and devices used, such as RSI with a Macintosh 
laryngoscope. Transitional-year residents were postgradu-
ate year 1-2 physicians who rotate through the EDs. An 
intubation attempt was defined as a single insertion of 
the laryngoscope (or other device) past the teeth. </p>

<p>2 10-13 </p>

<p>For nasal intubations, an attempt was defined as a single 
insertion of a tracheal tube past the turbinates. An 
attempt was successful if it resulted in the tracheal tube 
being passed through the vocal cords. One or more 
methods could be used in each patient and each 
method could be attempted several times. 
Adverse events were recorded using a prespecified list, 
with the option to include additional comments, if 
necessary. Adverse events were defined as cardiac arrest, 
hypotension, hypoxaemia, dysrhythmia, vomiting, 
oesophageal intubation, mainstem bronchial intubation 
and airway traumas that are considered to be intubation </p>

<p>related. 
11 Cardiac arrest included asystole, bradycardia 
or dysrhythmia with non-measurable blood pressure and 
cardiopulmonary resuscitation during or after intub-
ation. Hypotension was defined as systolic blood pres-
sure less than 90 mm Hg. Hypoxaemia was defined as 
pulse oximetric saturation less than 90% during an 
intubation attempt, not a result of oesophageal intub-
ation. Pre-existing hypotension or hypoxaemia before an 
intubation attempt was not counted as an adverse event. 
Oesophageal intubation was defined as misplacement of 
the endotracheal tube in the upper oesophagus or hypo-
pharynx, with a lapse of time and desaturation ( pulse 
oximetric saturation &lt;90%) before the removal of the 
misplaced tube. We monitored compliance with data 
form completion by reviewing professional billing 
records. Where the data collection form was missing, the 
intubator was interviewed by one of the investigators 
within 2 weeks of the patient encounter, to fill out the 
data form. 
The outcomes of interest were the primary indication 
for intubation, initial method used for intubation, intub-
ation success rates (on the first attempt and within three 
attempts) and intubation-related adverse event rates. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
We performed all analyses with JMP <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.10</rs> software (SAS 
Institute Inc, Cary, North Carolina, USA). At the patient 
level, we described patient demographics, the primary 
indication for intubation, initial method of intubation, 
success rates and adverse event rates as proportions with 
95% CIs and medians with IQRs. Then, at the ED level, 
we described medians, IQR and ranges for each 
outcome for all trauma patients. We also repeated the 
analysis after stratifying by indication (non-cardiac arrest 
vs cardiac arrest) and specialty (emergency physicians vs 
non-emergency physicians). All p values were two-tailed, 
with p&lt;0.05 considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
During the 30-month study period, 4268 patients 
required emergency airway management. Of these, the 
registry recorded 4094 intubations (capture rate, 95.9%; 
figure 1), of which 3370 patients who underwent airway 
management for medical reasons were excluded from 
the analysis. One of the 13 hospitals, in which only one 
trauma patient required airway intervention during the 
study period, was excluded because the number of intu-
bations for trauma care was less than 10 during the study 
period. Hence, 723 patients with trauma were eligible 
for analysis. Emergency physicians, including emergency 
medicine residents, performed the first intubation 
attempts in 60% (95% CI 56.4% to 63.5%) of all trauma 
patients and 66.7% (95% CI 62.4% to 70.8%) of patients 
without cardiac arrest. Transitional-year residents ( post-
graduate years 1 and 2) performed the first intubation 
attempts in 31.4% (95% CI 28.1% to 34.9%) of all </p>



<p>Nakao S, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006623. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006623 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>trauma patients and 25.7% (95% CI 22.0% to 29.7%) of 
patients without cardiac arrest. 
Table 1 shows the baseline characteristics and primary 
indications in patients who required trauma airway man-
agement. Median age was 56 years; two-thirds of the 
patients were male. Traumatic cardiac arrest was the 
reason for intubation in 32.6% (95% CI 29.3% to 
36.1%) of all trauma patients, while head trauma 
accounted for 30.4% (95% CI 27.2% to 33.9%). Table 2 
shows the initial method of airway management in the 
trauma patients. RSI was the initial method chosen in 
23.9% (95% CI 21.0% to 27.2%) of all trauma patients 
and 35.5% (95% CI 31.4% to 39.9%) of patients without 
cardiac arrest. Cricothyrotomy was performed as the 
initial airway management strategy in 2.2% (95% CI 
1.4% to 3.6%) of all trauma patients and 0.4% (95% CI 
0.1% to 1.5%) of patients without cardiac arrest. The 
direct laryngoscope was used in most intubations 
(n=654, 90.5%) and the remaining were intubated using 
a video laryngoscope (n=30, 4.1%), a bronchoscope 
(n=17, 2.4%) or a lighted stylet (n=1, 0.1%), on the first 
attempt. </p>

<p>Table 3 summarises the intubation success rates and 
adverse event rates. Overall, intubation was successful in 
the first attempt in 63.8% (95% CI 60.2% to 67.2%) and 
within three attempts in 96% (95% CI 94.3% to 97.2%) of 
all trauma patients. In patients without cardiac arrest, 
intubation was successful in the first attempt in 60.2% 
(95% CI 55.8% to 64.4%) and within three attempts in 
94.5% (95% CI 92.1% to 96.2%) of patients. In patients 
with cardiac arrest, intubation was successful in the first 
attempt in 71.2% (95% CI 65.1% to 76.6%) and within 
three attempts in 99.2% (95% CI 97.0% to 99.8%) of the 
patients. In the stratified analysis by the specialty (ie, emer-
gency physicians (n=434) vs non-emergency physicians 
(n=289)), emergency physicians had a higher success at 
the first attempt (72.8% vs 50.2%, p&lt;0.001) compared to 
non-emergency physicians (including all transitional-year 
residents (n=237)). Intubation-associated adverse event 
rates were 10.8% (95% CI 8.7% to 13.3%) in overall 
trauma patients, 11.5% (95% CI 9.0% to 14.6%) in 
patients without cardiac arrest and 9.3% (95% CI 6.2% to 
13.7%) in patients with cardiac arrest. 
At the ED level, there was a wide variation in the 
methods of intubation across the 12 EDs (figure 2). 
For example, RSI as the initial intubation method was 
performed in 0-50.9% of all trauma patients and in 
0-87.5% of patients without cardiac arrest. Similarly, 
there was a wide variation in the success rates and 
adverse event rates across the EDs (figure 3). The range 
of overall success rates for intubation in the first attempt 
ranged from 35.5% to 90.5% and from 85.1% to 100% 
within three attempts. Likewise, overall adverse event 
rates varied widely (range 0-16.7%) across the EDs. 
These wide variations in intubation success rates and 
adverse event rates persisted across the non-cardiac 
arrest and cardiac arrest strata. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
In this prospective, multicentre, observational study in 
Japan, we observed an acceptable success rate of airway 
management in trauma patients in EDs. However, we 
also found a wide range of variation in the initial 
method of intubation, success rates and adverse event 
rates during trauma airway management across the EDs. 
Indeed, the overall success rates in the first intubation 
attempt ranged from 35.5% to 90.5%. 
We were struck by the high degree of variation in the 
methods of airway management in trauma cases across 
the 12 EDs. The reasons for the observed practice varia-
tions are unclear and are likely multifactorial. It is pos-
sible that non-RSI methods were attempted in patients 
who were predicted to have a difficult intubation. 
However, the difference in the patient population across 
the EDs cannot fully explain the observed threefold dif-
ference in the use of RSI. Therefore, some of the 
patients might have been inappropriately considered as 
'difficult intubation' and intubated with non-RSI 
methods. Alternatively, it is also plausible that non-RSI </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of the 723 trauma patients who 
required intubation </p>

<p>Patient characteristics 
Age (year), median (IQR) 
56 
(34 to 73) 
Male, % (95% CI) 
66.9 (63.4 to 70.3) 
Estimated weight (kg), median (IQR) 60 
(50 to 70) 
Indication for intubation, % (95% CI) 
Cardiac arrest 
32.6 (29.3 to 36.1) 
Head trauma 
30.4 (27.2 to 33.9) 
Shock 
16.6 (14.1 to 19.5) 
Facial/neck trauma 
8.4 (6.6 to 10.7) 
Airway burn 
6.8 (5.2 to 8.8) 
Others 
5.1 (3.3 to 8.0) </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval; IQR, interquartile range. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow chart showing inclusion of patients in this 
study. </p>

<p>Nakao S, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006623. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006623 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>methods were more frequently used in certain EDs 
because of the physician's preference, procedural 
experiences, training background or differences in ED 
staffing and institutional policies. 
Our study also demonstrated a high degree of varia-
tions in success and adverse event rates among the EDs. 
Particularly, the success rate at first attempt was highly 
variable. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first 
study to demonstrate such interhospital variations in 
success and adverse event rates in trauma airway man-
agement in different EDs. The reasons for the variations 
among the EDs are likely multifactorial; the potential 
explanations include interhospital differences in patient 
population, skills or education backgrounds of intuba-
tors, 
15 drug and device availability in the ED, or any 
combination of these factors. Alternatively, the observed 
wide variation in the intubation method may have led to 
these variations in success and adverse event rates. 
Furthermore, there are no requirements for procedural 
credentials to perform ED intubations in individuals as 
well as in institutions in Japan. 
10 This lack of procedural 
requirements would have contributed, at least partially, 
to the observed interhospital variations in the success </p>

<p>rates. Indeed, we observed that intubation success rates 
performed by non-emergency physicians were signifi-
cantly lower; this was, at least in part, explained by the 
intubation attempts by transitional-year residents. 
However, it is well documented in the literature that 
first-pass success is important in critically ill patients; </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>therefore, the observed lower success rate by these non-
skilled physicians cannot be justified. Our data under-
score the need for reinforcement of the Japanese meth-
odology of training for non-skilled physicians (eg, the 
use of simulators and training in a more controlled 
setting 
16-18 ) to improve their intubation skills, which 
will, in turn, improve patient outcomes. 
Although international and Japanese trauma care 
guidelines recommend the use of RSI as the initial 
method of emergency airway management in most 
trauma patients, 
1 4 5 the evidence for accurately predict-
ing patients in whom RSI should be avoided remains 
limited. 
19 20 It is, therefore, plausible that the scarcity of 
evidence may have contributed to the practice variations 
across the EDs. Our observations should facilitate 
further investigation of any barriers to the delivery of 
safer trauma care nationally. Additionally, building more </p>

<p>Table 3 Success rates and intubation-associated adverse events </p>

<p>All trauma patients </p>

<p>Patients without cardiac 
arrest 
Patients with cardiac arrest 
n 
Per cent 95% CI 
n 
Per cent 95% CI 
n 
Per cent 95% CI </p>

<p>Successful in 1st attempt 
461 63.8 
(60.2 to 67.2) 293 60.2 
(55.8 to 64.4) 168 71.2 
(65.1 to 76.6) 
Successful in ≤3rd attempts 
694 96.0 
(94.3 to 97.2) 460 94.5 
(92.1 to 96.2) 234 99.2 
(97.0 to 99.8) 
Adverse events 
78 10.8 
(8.7 to 13.3) 
56 11.5 
(9.0 to 14.6) 
22 9.3 
(6.2 to 13.7) 
Details of adverse events* 
Oesophageal intubation 
25 3.5 
(2.2 to 5.1) 
15 3.1 
(1.7 to 5.0) 
10 4.2 
(2.0 to 7.7) 
Mainstem bronchus intubation 18 2.5 
(1.5 to 3.9) 
9 1.8 
(0.8 to 3.5) 
9 3.8 
(1.7 to 7.1) 
Airway trauma 
17 2.4 
(1.4 to 3.7) 
14 2.9 
(1.6 to 4.8) 
3 1.3 
(0.3 to 3.7) 
Hypotension † 
8 1.1 
(0.5 to 2.2) 
8 1.6 
(0.7 to 3.2) 
Vomiting 
6 0.8 
(0.3 to 1.8) 
6 1.2 
(0.5 to 2.7) 
Hypoxia ‡ 
3 0.4 
(0.1 to 1.2) 
3 0.6 
(0.1 to 1.8) 
Cardiac arrest 
1 0.1 
(0.0 to 0.8) 
1 0.2 
(0.0 to 1.1) </p>

<p>*Patients may have more than 1 adverse event. 
 †Hypotension was defined as systolic blood pressure less than 90 mm Hg. 
 ‡Hypoxia was defined as pulse oximetric oxygen saturation of less than 90% during intubation attempts, not as a result of esophageal 
intubation. 
CI, confidence interval. </p>

<p>Table 2 Initial method of intubation </p>

<p>All trauma patients 
Patients without cardiac arrest 
n 
Per cent 
95% CI 
n 
Per cent 
95% CI </p>

<p>Rapid sequence intubation 
173 
23.9 
(21.0 to 27.2) 
173 
35.5 
(31.4 to 39.9) 
Sedation without paralysis 
153 
21.2 
(18.3 to 24.3) 
153 
31.4 
(27.5 to 35.7) 
Paralytics without sedation 
19 
2.6 
(1.7 to 4.1) 
19 
3.9 
(2.5 to 6.0) 
Oral without sedation 
349 
48.3 
(44.6 to 52.0) 
127 
26.1 
(22.4 to 30.2) 
Surgical 
16 
2.2 
(1.4 to 3.6) 
2 
0.4 
(0.1 to 1.5) 
Nasal intubation 
13 
1.8 
(1.1 to 3.1) 
13 
2.7 
(1.6 to 4.5) 
Total 
723 
100 
487 
100 </p>

<p>CI, confidence interval. </p>



<p>Nakao S, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006623. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006623 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>robust evidence on trauma airway management, coupled 
with improved dissemination of these findings, could 
decrease the variations in trauma care across the EDs in 
Japan. 
Our study has several potential limitations. First, this 
passive surveillance of the study data is subject to self-
reporting bias, leading to a possible underestimation of 
failed intubations and adverse events. However, active 
independent monitoring of ED intubations is difficult to 
accomplish. We did, however, use a self-reporting system 
with structured data forms, uniform definitions and a 
high capture rate. Second, we did not design this study 
to measure patient outcomes, such as long-term mortal-
ity or morbidity. A more detailed analysis of adverse 
events and outcomes requires following the patients for 
a longer period. Third, we did not account for several 
potential confounders, such as severities (the Injury 
Severity Score, the Revised Trauma Score, etc) of cases 
and training levels of physicians. However, these pro-
spective multicentre data reflect the current airway man-
agement in the natural setting of a 'real' population and 
current clinical practice, thereby enhancing the poten-
tial generalisability of the findings. Finally, all EDs in this 
study were designated as tertiary or academic general 
hospitals, and all but one of the EDs were affiliated with 
an emergency medicine residency programme in Japan. 
Therefore, our inferences may not be generalisable to 
trauma airway management in non-academic EDs or in 
other developed nations. These observations, however, </p>

<p>are highly relevant from a policy standpoint. As these 
EDs provide advanced care for trauma victims and train 
the majority of emergency physicians, they have a dispro-
portionate impact on current and future trauma care in 
EDs in general. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
In this multicentre prospective study of emergency 
airway management in Japan, we found an acceptable 
overall success rate in trauma airway management. 
However, we also found that the method of intubation, 
success rates and adverse event rates were highly variable 
among EDs. For researchers, our observations should 
facilitate further investigations to identify the reasons for 
the interhospital variations. Additionally, for policy-
makers and professional organisations, our findings 
suggest that development and dissemination of nation-
wide protocols are warranted to achieve safer airway 
management for trauma victims in Japan. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Interhospital variations in success rates and 
adverse event rates. Box plots of interhospital variations in 
success rates and adverse event rates. The line in the middle 
of the box represents the median, with the lower and upper 
limits of the box representing the 25th and 75th centiles. The 
whiskers from the box extend to the minimum and maximum 
values. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Interhospital variations in initial methods of 
intubation. Box plots of interhospital variations in the initial 
methods of intubation. The line in the middle of the box 
represents the median, with the lower and upper limits of the 
box representing the 25th and 75th centiles, respectively. The 
whiskers from the box extend to the minimum and maximum 
values. </p>

<p>Nakao S, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006623. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006623 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors acknowledge the following research 
personnel at the study hospitals for their assistance with this project: Fukui 
University Hospital (Hideya Nagai, MD, Hiroshi Morita, MD); Fukui Prefectural 
Hospital (Yukinori Kato, MD, Hidenori Higashi, MD); Japanese Red Cross 
Medical Center of Wakayama (Hiroshi Okamoto, MD); Kameda Medical Center 
(Kenzo Tanaka, MD); National Center for Global Health and Medicine (Taigo 
Sakamoto, MD, Shunichiro Nakao, MD); Nagoya Ekisaikai Hospital (Yukari 
Goto, MD); Niigata City General Hospital (Nobuhiro Sato, MD, MPH); Obama 
Municipal Hospital (Takuyo Chiba, MD); Okinawa Chubu Prefectural Hospital 
(Masashi Okubo, MD); Osaka Saiseikai Senri Hospital (Kazuaki Shigemitsu, 
MD); Shonan Kamakura General Hospital (Taichi Imamura, MD); Kurashiki 
Central Hospital (Hiroshi Okamoto, MD); and St. Marianna University School 
of Medicine Hospital (Yasuaki Koyama, MD). Finally, we are grateful to our 
many emergency physicians and residents for their perseverance in pursuing 
new knowledge about this vital resuscitative procedure. </p>

<p>Contributors KH designed the study, for which SN and YH contributed to the 
data collection and analysis. SN wrote the manuscript, which AK reviewed. </p>

<p>Funding This study was supported by a grant from St Luke's Life Science 
Institute and a grant from Massachusetts General Hospital and Brigham and 
Women's Hospital. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The ethics committee of each participating centre. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Nakao S, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006623. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006623 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>