<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4010924" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The ability to perturb individual genes in genome-wide experiments has been instrumental in unraveling 
cellular and disease properties. Here we introduce, describe the assembly, and demonstrate the use of 
comprehensive and versatile transcription activator-like effector (TALE) libraries. As a proof of principle, 
we built an 11-mer library that covers all possible combinations of the nucleotides that determine the 
TALE-DNA binding specificity. We demonstrate the versatility of the methodology by constructing a 
constraint library, customized to bind to a known p53 motif. To verify the functionality in assays, we applied 
the 11-mer library in yeast-one-hybrid screens to discover TALEs that activate human SCN9A and miR-34b 
respectively. Additionally, we performed a genome-wide screen using the complete 11-mer library to 
confirm known genes that confer cycloheximide resistance in yeast. Considering the highly modular nature 
of TALEs and the versatility and ease of constructing these libraries we envision broad implications for 
high-throughput genomic assays. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>ranscription activator-like effectors (TALEs) are proteins secreted by Xanthomonas bacteria to target 
specific DNA sequences </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>. TALE family members contain a highly conserved and repetitive region 
(Fig. 1a) and their DNA binding capacities are dependent on the amino acid positions 12 and 13 (i.e. repeat 
variable diresidue or RVD) of each modular repeat 
3,4 . Recent advances show that TALE proteins consist of a 
modular DNA-binding domain (DBD) that can be rapidly synthesized de novo 
5 . The ability to complement the 
DBD with a functional domain permits a wide range of applications that include gene activation, repression, and 
nucleotide deletion and insertion, in a variety of model organisms and cell types </p>

<p>6-10 </p>

<p>Results 
Assembly and verification of the libraries. To assemble our TALE 
libraries, we modified the Golden Gate protocol (Fig. 1b) </p>

<p>5,26 </p>

<p>. The 
enabling modification is the use of a predetermined mixture of the 
four building modules during the first step of the assembly (Fig. 1c). 
The flanking sequences of the four modules are identical. Therefore, 
during the enzyme-based digestion and ligase-based ligation 
reactions these modules have an equal probability in appearing in 
the final TALE construct (Methods and Supplementary Material). To 
test the library fidelity we subjected our 11-mer TALE mixture to 
standard Sanger sequencing using primers flanking the TALE DNA 
binding domain (Supplementary Table 1, P23 and P24). The se-
quencing results show that there are 6-nucleotide long repeats, 
spaced by 102 nucleotides, which have variable signature (Supple-
mentary Fig. 1a). This general profile perfectly matches the TALE 
tandem repeat structure which contains 102 nucleotides and has 
RVDs which are 6-nucleotides in length. Importantly the 
composition of different peaks within these 6-nucleotide noisy 
elements closely tracks the expected composition. In particular, 
when equal amounts of all four possible RVDs are used for all 
positions, the first nucleotide position should consist of 75% A and 
25% C (Supplementary Fig. 1b) and indeed the results have the 
expected sequencing profile (Supplementary Fig. 1c). Similarly, at 
position 2 of the RVD sequence, we should have only nucleotide A 
which was confirmed by sequencing (Supplementary Fig. 1c). The 
sequencing results confirm all positions. </p>

<p>The versatility of the proposed methodology of TALE library con-
struction, perhaps, can be best illustrated by the simplicity in gen-
erating specific variants, namely sequence or nucleotide-biased 
TALE libraries (Supplementary Fig. 2). A sequence-biased TALE 
library has constrained nucleotides, and is assembled to bind to a 
specific transcription factor motif, while a nucleotide-biased TALE 
library has a predetermined ratio of the building modules resulting in 
desired nucleotide distributions (e.g. GC-rich). 
As an example, we assembled a sequence-biased library to target a 
p53 motif. The p53-responsive element has been identified 
27 as two 
copies of the decamer motif 59-RRRCWWGYYY-39 (R5A or G, 
W5A or T, Y5C or T) separated by 0 to 13 random nucleotides. 
Accordingly, we prepared an 11-mer TALE library which targets 59-
RRRCWWGYYYN-39 (Methods and Supplementary Material). The 
validity of this library was again verified by Sanger sequencing, and 
the results closely match the desired RVD patterns (Supplemen-
tary Fig. 3). </p>

<p>TALE library-based yeast one-hybrid assay. We then explored the 
functional integrity of our complete 11-mer TALE library using a 
yeast one-hybrid assay (Methods, Yeast One-hybrid Assay). A VP16 
activation domain was added to the 11-mer library to enhance the 
transactivation activities. For the assay, we cloned part of the 
59untranslated region (UTR) and the open reading frame (ORF) of 
the human SCN9A gene (Supplementary Table 2) in front of an 
antibiotic resistance gene, Aureobasidin A (Aba) in yeast (bait), </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Construction of an 11-mer TALE-VP16 library. (a) Schematic illustration of a TALE protein depicting the tandem repeat domain and the </p>

<p>variable diresidues (RVDs). (b) Schematic illustration of a typical TALE assembling reaction. Corresponding RVDs were chosen for specific 
nucleotide targets (NI for A, HD for C, NG for T, and NN for G). (c) Schematic illustration of the TALE library assembling. For each position, equal 
amounts of all four building modules were used, which results in an 11-mer TALE library covering all possible 11-mer DNA targets. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4857 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04857 </p>

<p>
and applied our library (prey) (Fig. 2a). We used 50 (15 cm diameter) 
plates, which resulted to approximately 1 million individual TALE 
clones (Supplementary Material, Yeast one-hybrid). For assays that 
require comprehensive library coverage the protocol can be scaled up 
by increasing the number of plates. The positive clones were con-
firmed by re-streaking on Aba-containing agar plates (Supple-</p>

<p>mentary Fig. 4). Thirteen of the TALE-VP16 expression plasmids 
were then rescued and sequenced to extract the RVD sequences 
(Supplementary Table 3). 
Using <rs id="software-3" type="software">TALE-NT</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">2.0</rs> (TALE Effector Nucleotide Targeter 2.0) </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>, 
we were able to confirm that these positive clones are predicted to 
bind to either the plus or minus strand of three specific locations </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Isolation of TALE-VP16 fusions targeting the human SCN9A gene using the 11-mer TALE-VP16 library and the yeast one-hybrid assay. </p>

<p>(a) Schematic illustration of the yeast one-hybrid assay using the 11-mer TALE-VP16 library. A bait sequence was cloned in front of an antibiotic 
resistance gene (Aba resistance gene) in yeast. The 11-mer TALE-VP16 library was then transformed into this stable clone and a surviving assay was 
performed on -Leu plates containing 100 nM Aba. (b) The RVD sequences of isolated TALE-VP16 fusions and their targets within the human SCN9A bait 
sequence (scale not proportional). TALE-VP16 fusions were shown to bind to both the plus and the minus strands of the SCN9A bait sequence. (c) The 
isolated TALE-VP16 fusions induced overexpression of endogenous SCN9A in HEK293 cells and A431 cells. The mRNA levels of SCN9A were 
determined by quantitative RT-PCR. An empty vector (PEF-1) was used as the control. Columns 1-6: All TALE-VP16 fusions were able to effectively 
induce the overexpression of SCN9A in HEK293 cells (n55). Columns 11-16: All TALE-VP16 fusions effectively induced the overexpression of SCN9A in 
A431 cells (n53). Columns 7-10: All 4 TALEs designed according to <rs id="software-2" type="software">TALE-NT</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">2.0</rs> failed to induce the overexpression of SCN9A in HEK293 cells (n53). 
Inlet: Western blot shows that all TALE-VP16 fusions induced the overexpression of SCN9A protein in A431 cells (representative data of two independent 
experiments). (d) The RVD sequences of isolated TALE-VP16 fusions and their targets within the human miR-34b/c bait sequence (scale not 
proportional). (e) Confirmation of the binding between isolated TALE-VP16 fusion M1 and its predicted gene target within the human miR-34b/c bait 
sequence. The isolated clone M1 was predicted to target 59-TTTCTAGGTAT-39 within the miR-34b/c bait sequence. The full-length bait sequence 
(pAbAi-miR-34b/c) or bait with the predicted target site deleted (pAbAi-miR-34b/c (DTTTCTAGGTAT)) was stably integrated into yeast cells. TALE-
VP16 fusion clone M1 was then transformed into either cell line. Only cells which contained the intact bait sequence survived the 100 nM Aba selection. 
(f) The isolated TALE-VP16 fusion M1 effectively induced overexpression of miR-34b in a dose-dependent manner in both HEK293 and HeLa cells (n53 
for both cell lines). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4857 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04857 </p>

<p>
within the SCN9A bait sequence. Five of the TALE-VP16 clones are 
illustrated together with their corresponding position (Fig. 2b). To 
confirm these results, we first generated baits that exclude those 
predicted DNA target sites. For example, the positive clone T110 
induced the expression of Aba resistance gene when the bait 
sequence is intact (Supplementary Fig. 5a) but it failed to produce 
surviving clones when the specific DNA target site (59-GTTGC-
CTCCCC-39) was removed (Supplementary Fig. 5b). Subsequently, 
we cloned these TALE-VP16 fusions into a mammalian expression 
vector, transiently transfected the plasmids into human embryonic 
kidney cells (HEK293) and human squamous carcinoma cells 
(A431), and measured the expression level of SCN9A by quantitative 
RT-PCR (Methods, Quantitative reverse transcription-PCR). All 
fusions were able to effectively drive the overexpression of the 
SCN9A gene in both cell lines (up to 11-fold increase for HEK293 
cells and 8.5-fold increase for A431 cells) (Fig. 2c). 
In line with these results, the TALE-VP16 fusions also induced the 
overexpression of SCN9A protein in A431 cells (Fig. 2c, and 
Supplementary Fig. 6b). Interestingly, we were not able to detect 
SCN9A protein in HEK293 cell samples, including those transfected 
with the fusion constructs (Supplementary Fig. 6c). The discrepancy 
between the mRNA and protein measurements for HEK293 cells 
may be due to regulatory translational or post-translational mechan-
isms on the expression of SCN9A </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>. 
We also investigated whether the TALE fusions isolated from our 
screening were compatible with a virus-based delivery system for 
potential applications in primary cells. We prepared a TALE T34 
recombinant adeno-associated viral vector using the AAV helper-
free system (Agilent Technologies). This AAV viral stock was applied 
to HEK293 cells at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 400 and in-
duced the overexpression of the SCN9A gene by 2 fold (Supple-
mentary Fig. 7). 
Furthermore, we tested the performance of our TALE-based yeast 
one-hybrid screening approach for microRNA gene targets. Speci-
fically, we used part of the promoter sequence of the human miR-
34b/c gene as the bait sequence (Supplementary Table 2) and isolated 
four positive clones, which were confirmed by re-streaking on Aba-
containing plates (Supplementary Fig. 8). The RVD sequences of 
these four clones were extracted (Supplementary Table 3) and all 
are predicted to target the bait (Fig. 2d). Interestingly, two of the 
clones (M1, M17) target the same sequence within the miR-34b/c 
promoter (Fig. 2d). Again, we used two methods to confirm the 
results. We first generated a bait mutant which excludes the pre-
dicted target sequence for clone M1 (59-TTTCTAGGTAT-39) and 
prepared the according yeast stable cell line. As expected, in these 
yeast cells clone M1 failed to induce the expression of Aba resistance 
gene (Fig. 2e). Furthermore, the TALE M1 -VP16 cDNA was cloned 
into a mammalian expression vector and transiently transfected into 
HEK293 and HeLa cells. The TALE fusion effectively induced the 
overexpression of miR-34b in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 2f). 
Our results clearly demonstrate that the complete library can be 
used to isolate TALEs that bind to a desired DNA sequence. 
Importantly, we observed that TALE-VP16 can be designed to bind 
to the minus strand of a target sequence and in addition, can also be 
designed to target sequences within the ORF. We emphasize that one 
fundamental difference between our approach and all previous appli-
cations of TALEs is that our screening procedure does not rely on 
TALE-DNA binding prediction algorithms </p>

<p>28,30 </p>

<p>. This is a considerable 
advantage as available algorithms may not yet fully capture the 
dynamics of TALE-DNA interactions. Indeed, we designed four 
11-mer TALE-VP16 constructs for the same SCN9A bait sequence 
using the <rs id="software-4" type="software">TALE-NT</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">2.0</rs> program (Supplementary Table 3) and 
observed that all fusions, as well as combinations, failed to induce 
the overexpression of SCN9A mRNA levels in HEK293 (Fig. 2c, 
Supplementary Figs. 7 and 9). Additional insight can be gathered 
from recovered RVDs (Supplementary Table 3), as none of the iso-</p>

<p>lated positive TALE-VP16 clones contain RVD sequences exactly 
matching the canonical TALE-DNA binding code. As an example, 
for the target sequence 59-GTTGCCTCCCC-39, instead of the pre-
dicted canonical RVD sequence the four isolated clones contained at 
least one RVD difference. Therefore, the TALE-DNA binding 
information extracted from our library can be used in the future to 
refine the TALE-DNA binding algorithms. </p>

<p>TALE library-based benchmark genomic screen in yeast. We next 
applied our library to screen for TALE-VP16 fusion proteins which 
confer resistance to cycloheximide in yeast. The underlying mecha-
nisms of cycloheximide resistance are well-studied. For example, in 
yeast S. cerevisiae, overexpression of ATP-binding cassette (ABC) 
transporters such as Pdr5p has been shown to contribute to cyclohe-
ximide resistance </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>. In addition, the expression of the PDR5 gene is 
known to be positively regulated by two homologous zinc finger-
containing transcription regulators, Pdr1p and Pdr3p </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>. We first 
determined the lowest concentration cycloheximide (0.5 mg/ml) at 
which the wild-type yeast cells failed to grow (Supplementary Ma-
terial). We applied the complete TALE-VP16 library and isolated 
eighteen positive clones which tolerate cycloheximide (e.g., selected 
clones illustrated in Supplementary Fig. 10). Subsequently, we 
isolated the TALE-VP16 fusion plasmids and re-transformed them 
back to the wild-type cells for confirmation, as in the original screen 
natural mutations of the yeast genome (both gain-of-function 
33 and 
loss-of-function 
34 ) can artificially increase the resistance to cyclohe-
ximide. Five genuine positive clones were confirmed (Fig. 3a), 
isolated and sequenced to extract the TALE RVD sequences (Supple-
mentary Table 3). 
The sequencing results indicate that two clones (A8, A35) are 
predicted to target the promoter of the PDR3 gene and, in addition, 
A35 is also predicted to bind to the promoter of the PDR5 gene 
(Fig. 3a). Two methods were used to confirm the results. First, we 
cloned four copies of the predicted PDR3 and PDR5 promoter tar-
gets and their immediate adjacent sequences in front of a fluor-
escence reporter gene (mKate2) in yeast. We then transformed the 
yeast stable clones with plasmids carrying the TALEs. Indeed both 
clones induced the expression of mKate2 in cells containing the bait 
(Fig. 3b). Second, we prepared yeast cells transformed with TALE A8 -
VP16, TALE A35 -VP16 or empty vector and measured the expression 
levels of PDR3 and PDR5 by quantitative RT-PCR. Again, both 
clones were able to effectively induce the expression of PDR3 and 
PDR5 (Fig. 3c). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Here, we establish a methodology for the assembly of complete and 
biased TALE-based libraries. As proof-of-concept, we demonstrate 
that our methodology can be applied towards designing effective 
TALEs for any given DNA target (i.e. the yeast-one-hybrid experi-
ments) as well as for genome-wide phenotype screens in yeast. 
We show experimentally that the standard TALE design algorithm 
can fail to predict RVDs that bind to a desired target. Therefore, 
in the unforeseen cases where computational methods are not 
successful, the yeast-one-hybrid approach provides an algorithm-
independent alternative towards designing TALEs. 
A potential pitfall is that instead of the desired bait sequence a 
TALE may bind to the antibiotic resistance plasmid backbone 
sequence and induce the expression of the resistance gene. In our 
case, the negative control experiments (deletion of target) provide 
proof that the selected TALEs target exclusively the bait 
(Supplementary Fig. 5 and Fig. 2e). More generally, to avoid false-
positives in the TALE-based yeast-one-hybrid assays, we recom-
mend using bait sequences that are sufficiently long, ideally larger 
than 500 bp (Supplementary Material, Yeast-one-hybrid assay false-
positives). We also presume that multiple copies of the targets can be 
used in cases when the target sequence is short. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4857 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04857 </p>

<p>
An advantage of TALEs compared to other technologies (e.g., 
RNAi, CRISPR 
35-37 ) is that the size of the DNA target can be 
controlled. Increasing the DNA target size will result to superior 
specificity, albeit at the cost of increasing the library complexity 
and reducing the coverage in yeast screens. Therefore, a practical 
strategy towards eliminating off-target effects is to use a relatively 
short library (e.g., 11-mer) for screening purposes and a posteriori 
extend the DBDs of the screened TALEs to include flanking target 
sequences. 
An alternative approach towards increasing the size of the targets 
of the library, without introducing additional experimental burden 
or increasing the complexity, involves utilizing the RVD properties. </p>

<p>For example, it is known that the RVD NN can target both A and G. 
Therefore, only three modules (i.e. NN, NG and HD) can be used for 
the assembly of the complete TALE libraries. As an example, a 14-
mer TALE library with these three modules will result in a complex-
ity of 3 
14 54,782,969. The assembly of larger TALE libraries can be 
experimentally cumbersome and in some cases practically prohib-
itive without the use of automated assembly systems. 
One additional challenge lies in the fact that there is a certain 
degree of uncertainty in terms of deciphering the TALE-DNA bind-
ing given a RVD sequence, which may complicate the identification 
of potential target sequences in genome-wide assays. This issue can 
be resolved experimentally using ChIP-seq </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Genetic screen for cycloheximide resistance in yeast using the TALE-VP16 plasmid library. (a) Confirmation of the genuine positive yeast </p>

<p>clones conferring cycloheximide resistance. 18 positive clones were isolated from the cycloheximide resistance screening. Subsequently, these positive 
TALE-VP16 fusion plasmids were recovered and again re-transformed into the wild-type yeast cells. The transformed cells were then re-streaked onto 
-Leu plates containing 0.5 mg/ml of cycloheximide. After 3 days, cells transformed with genuine positive clones pGADT7-TALE-A8-VP16 and pGADT7-
TALE-A35-VP16 were able to grow robustly. In contrast, cells transformed with the false positive clone pGADT7-TALE-A12-VP16 or the control 
pGADT7 failed to grow. (b) The isolated TALE-VP16 fusion clones A8 and A35 bind to the promoters of the PDR3 and PDR5 genes. TALE-VP16 fusion 
clones A8 and A35 were isolated from cycloheximide resistance screening. Both A8 and A35 were predicted to bind to the promoter of PDR3 gene. In 
addition, A35 was predicted to target the promoter of the PDR5 gene. Four copies of the predicted PDR3/PDR5 promoter targets and their immediate 
adjacent sequences were cloned in front of a fluorescence reporter gene (mKATE2) in yeast (bait). These yeast stable clones were then transformed with 
corresponding pGADT7-TALE-A8-VP16, pGADT7-TALE-A35-VP16 or pGADT7 (control). TALE-VP16 fusion clones A35 or A8 potently induced the 
expression of mKATE2 in yeast cells containing the corresponding baits, while pGADT7 failed to do so (right). (c) The isolated TALE-VP16 fusions A8 
and A35 induced overexpression of endogenous PDR3 and PDR5 genes. Wild-type yeast cells were transformed with pGADT7-TALE-A8-VP16, 
pGADT7-TALE-A35-VP16 or pGADT7 (control). The expression levels of PDR3/PDR5 were measured by quantitative RT-PCR. Both clones were able to 
effectively induce the overexpression of PDR3 (n53) and PDR5 (n53). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4857 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04857 </p>

<p>
In summary, we have successfully established a methodology for 
the assembly of versatile TALE-based libraries and we demonstrated 
yeast-one-hybrid and genome-wide screens in yeast cells. We further 
emphasize that the TALE DBD can be fully customized to target any 
nucleotide content (e.g., GC-rich areas), nucleotide constraints (e.g., 
transcription factor motifs), or other modifications (e.g., methyla-
tions </p>

<p>39,40 </p>

<p>). For the latter, during the construction of the TALE library, 
one additional RVD building block can be included in the assembly, 
namely N*. The star indicates that the amino acids at position 13 of 
TALE repeats are missing, which has been shown 
39 to overcome the 
steric hindrance from the additional methyl moiety present at posi-
tion 5 of thymine and thus allow efficient recognition of 5-methy-
lated cytosine. 
The modularity of the functional domain allows for a range of 
targeted manipulations including, but not limited to, transactivators, 
transrepressors, methylases, demethylases, recombinases, and nu-
cleases </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>. More generally, with TALE libraries we have the ability 
to introduce multiple rounds of positive and negative screening, 
and even introduce a combination of positive and/or negative action 
to study synergistic effects. Finally, the TALE protein coding 
sequences can be easily isolated and sequenced, which can facilitate 
the rapid identification of their target genes. To conclude, consider-
ing the highly modular nature of TALEs, the ability to control their 
size and thus fine-tune their specificity, and the versatility and ease of 
constructing these libraries we foresee a broad range of applications 
in the future. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Library construction. A modified protocol based on the Golden Gate Assembly was 
used to construct the 11-mer TALE-VP16 library. First, a pFUS_A library containing 
all possible combinations of 10 tandem repeat (RVDs 1-10) and a pFUS_B library 
containing all combinations of 1 tandem repeat (RVD 11) were prepared as described 
in Cermak, T. et al. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, except that for each position in a standard 30 mL reaction, 
37.5 ng of each of the NN, NI, NG, and HD building blocks were mixed and included. 
Next, the pFUS_A and pFUS_B plasmid libraries were conjoined using the standard 
protocol. Similar procedures were used to prepare the p53-responsive element-
targeting TALE-VP16 libraries. For each position of the Golden Gate Assembly 
reactions, the amounts of the four building blocks were adjusted according to the 
desired nucleotide target. All libraries were then subjected to standard Sanger 
sequencing using the forward primer P23 and the reverse primer P24 (Supplementary 
Table 1). The sequencing profiles were then analyzed using <rs type="software">FinchTV</rs> (Geospiza). For 
full description, see Supplementary Material. </p>

<p>Yeast one-hybrid assay. The Matchmaker Gold Yeast One-Hybrid Screening System 
was used (Clontech, #630491). The TALE-VP16 library-based yeast one-hybrid assay 
was performed according to the protocol (Clontech, protocol #PT4087-1). The 
positive clones were screened by using SD/-Leu agar medium (Clontech, #630311) 
containing either 100 ng/ml Aureobasidin A (Clontech, #630466) or 0.5 mg/ml 
cycloheximide (Sigma-Aldrich, #C7698-1G). Subsequently, the positive clones were 
cultured in SD/-Leu broth (Clontech, #630310) and the pGADT7-TALE-VP16 
plasmids were then prepared using the PrepEase Yeast Plasmid Isolation Kit 
(Affymetrix, #79220). The plasmids were then rescued into XL10-Gold 
Ultracompetent cells (Agilent, #200315) and prepared using the Qiagen Plasmid Mini 
Kit (Qiagen, #12123). For full description, see Supplementary Material. </p>

<p>Prediction of target sequences. All rescued pGADT7-TALE-VP16 plasmids were 
subjected to standard Sanger sequencing using the forward primer P23 and the 
reverse primer P24 (Supplementary Table 1), which are flanking sequences of the 
DNA binding domain of TALE proteins. After extracting the RVD sequences, the 
TALE potential target sequences were determined by the Target Finder function of 
<rs id="software-6" type="software">TALE-NT</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">2.0</rs> 
28 using the setting ''upstream base T''. Since TALE-NT 2.0 only 
supports sequences which are between 12 and 31 RVDs, for each TALE we conducted 
four searches by adding one additional RVD (HD or NN or NI or NG) to the end of 
our RVD sequences. The lowest score from one of these four searches was defined as 
''the lowest possible score''. The targets were considered as potentially genuine only 
when the lowest possible score is less than 9, as lower scores indicate higher 
confidence of the bindings between TALE fusions and their predicted DNA target 
sequences. </p>

<p>Mammalian cell culture and transfection. All mammalian cells were maintained at 
37uC, 100% humidity and 5% CO 2 . HEK293, A431 and HeLa cells were grown in 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM, Invitrogen, #11965-1181) 
supplemented with 10% Fetal Bovine Serum (FBS, Atlanta Biologicals, #S11550), 
0.1 mM MEM non-essential amino acids (Invitrogen, #11140-050), 0.045 units/mL 
of Penicillin and 0.045 units/mL of Streptomycin (Penicillin-Streptomycin liquid, </p>

<p>Invitrogen, #15140). For transient transfection, ,300 thousand cells in 1 mL of 
complete medium were plated into each well of 12-well culture treated plastic plates 
(Griener Bio-One, #665180) and grown for 16-20 hours. For jetPRIME (Polyplus 
Transfection, #114-15) transfection, up to 1 mg of the plasmid was added to 75 mL of 
jetPRIME buffer and 1.75 mL of jetPRIME. Transfection solutions were mixed and 
incubated at room temperature for 10 min. The transfection mixture was then 
applied to the cells and mixed with the medium by gently shaking. </p>

<p>Preparation of recombinant AAV vectors. The AAV helper-free system was 
purchased from Agilent Technologies (#240071). HEK293 cells were seeded on 10-
cm cell culture treated petri dishes (Griener Bio-One, #664160). After reaching 
approximately 70-80% confluence, the cells were transfected with 3.3 mg of AAV-
SCN9A-T34, 3.3 mg of pHELPER plasmid and 3.3 mg of pAAV-RC plasmid using 
30 mL of jetPRIME. 72 hours post-transfection, the cells were scraped into the growth 
medium and pelleted by centrifugation at 1000 rpm for 5 min. The supernatant was 
then removed and the cell pellets were re-suspended in 1 mL of complete growth 
medium before being subjected to 4 rounds of freeze-thaw cycles between the dry ice-
ethanol bath and the 37uC water bath. Subsequently, the cellular debris was collected 
by centrifugation at 10,000 3 g for 10 min. The supernatant (primary recombinant 
AAV virus stock) was transferred into a fresh tube and stored at 280uC. The 
QuickTiter AAV Quantitation Kit (Cell Biolabs, #VPK-145-T) was used to determine 
the titers (genome copy/mL, GC/mL) of the recombinant AAV viral stocks. In brief, 
any free nucleic acids were first removed and the intact AAV viruses were captured 
using the QuickTiter AAV Capture Matrix. The captured viruses were then denatured 
to release the viral nucleic acids, which were subsequently labeled with fluorescence 
tags. The fluorescent intensities were measured using the FLUOstar Omega plate 
reader (BMG Labtech) with a 480/520 nm filter set. </p>

<p>Western blot assay. A431 or HEK293 cells were lysed in RIPA buffer (Sigma-Aldrich, 
#R0278) with protease inhibitors (Sigma-Aldrich, #P8340). Protein concentrations 
were measured using the Coomassie Plus Bradford assay kit (Thermo Scientific, 
#23236). For Western blot, 15 mg of whole cell lysates were mixed with loading buffer 
and boiled for 5 min, and then were run in 4-15% Mini-PROTEAN TGX 
polyacrylamide gel (Bio-Rad, #456-1083). After transferring, the nitrocellulose 
membranes were first blotted with 50 mM Tris, 150 mM NaCl and 0.1% Tween-20 
(TBS-T) with 5% nonfat milk for 30 min at room temperature. The membranes were 
then incubated with either anti-SCN9A monoclonal antibody (15500 dilution in 
TBS-T, Millipore, #MABN41) or anti-actin monoclonal antibody (155,000 dilution 
in TBS-T, Millipore, #MAB1501) at 4uC overnight. The membranes were then 
washed with TBS-T three times, each time for 10 min. Subsequently, the membranes 
were incubated with goat anti-mouse IgG (H1L) secondary antibody (1510,000 
dilution in TBS-T, Thermo Scientific, #31430) at room temperature for 45 min. The 
membranes were then washed with TBS-T four times, each time for 10 min. The 
membranes subsequently were incubated with ECL Western blotting substrates 
(Thermo Scientific, #32106) and then exposed to X-ray films (Sigma-Aldrich, 
#Z370398). </p>

<p>Quantitative reverse transcription-PCR (rtPCR). For measurement of mRNAs in 
mammalian cells, total RNA was extracted using the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, 
#74104) 48 hours post transfection. First strand synthesis was performed using the 
QuantiTect Reverse Transcription Kit (Qiagen, #205311). Quantitative PCR was 
performed using the KAPA SYBR FAST Universal qPCR Kit (KAPA Biosystems, 
#KK4601). GAPDH was used for normalization. For measurement of mRNAs in 
yeast cells, the same protocol was followed, except that total RNA was extracted using 
the MasterPure Yeast Purification Kit (Epicentre, #MPY80200), and yeast ACT1 was 
used for normalization. For measurement of miRNAs in mammalian cells, total RNA 
was extracted using the miRNeasy Micro Kit (Qiagen, #217084). First strand 
synthesis was performed using the miScript II RT Kit with HiSpec Buffer (Qiagen, 
#218161). Quantitative PCR was performed using miScript SYBR Green PCR Kit 
(Qiagen, #218073). RNU6 was used for normalization. The quantitative analysis was 
performed using the 2 
2DDCt method. The values of fold-change are reported as mean 
with standard deviation. For full description, see Supplementary Material. </p>

<p>Fluorescence microscopy. Bait yeast strains containing PDR3/PDR5 promoter target 
sequences were prepared as described in the yeast two-hybrid section. Subsequently, 
these yeast stable clones were transformed with corresponding pGADT7-TALE-
VP16 plasmids and then grown on SD/-Leu agar medium. Individual positive clones 
(diameter 2-3 mm) were re-suspended in 1 mL of 0.9% (w/v) NaCl solution and 
transferred into 12-well culture treated plastic plates. Cells were allowed to fully settle 
and then imaged using an Olympus IX81 microscope in a Precision Control 
environmental chamber. The images were captured using a Hamamatsu ORCA-03 
Cooled monochrome digital camera. The filter set (Chroma) for mKATE2 is ET560/ 
40x (excitation) and ET630/75m (emission). Data collection and processing was 
performed using the software package Slidebook 5.0. All images were collected with 
the same magnification (403) and exposure times and underwent identical 
processing. </p>

<p>1. Zhou, J. &amp; Chai, J. Plant pathogenic bacterial type III effectors subdue host 
responses. Curr Opin Microbiol 11, 179-185 (2008). 
2. Boch, J. &amp; Bonas, U. Xanthomonas AvrBs3 family-type III effectors: discovery and 
function. Annu Rev Phytopathol 48, 419-436 (2010). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4857 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04857 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was funded by the US National Institutes of Health (NIH) grants GM098984, 
GM096271, CA17001801, the US National Science Foundation (NSF) grant 
CBNET-1105524, and the University of Texas at Dallas. We would like to thank S. Baek, 
M.Guinn, S. Lin and S. Shah for technical support, and the Levene Lab for assistance with 
Western blot assays. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Y.L. and L.B. conceived the project and designed the experiments. Y.L. performed the 
majority of the experiments. K.E. performed <rs id="software-8" type="software">TALE-NT</rs><rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">2.0</rs> cloning and viral experiments. 
Y.L. and L.B. analyzed the data. Y.L., K.E., M.Z. and L.B. prepared the manuscript. L.B. 
supervised the project. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Li, Y., Ehrhardt, K., Zhang, M.Q. &amp; Bleris, L. Assembly and 
Validation of Versatile Transcription Activator-Like Effector Libraries. Sci. Rep. 4, 4857; 
DOI:10.1038/srep04857 (2014). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. The images in this article are included in the 
article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the image credit; 
if the image is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to 
obtain permission from the license holder in order to reproduce the image. To view a 
copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 4 : 4857 | DOI: 10.1038/srep04857 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>