<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4182354" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Purpose: This study aimed to investigate the effect of changing the kilovoltage peak (kVp) on the radiographic 
assessment of dental caries. 
Materials and Methods: Seventy-five extracted posterior teeth with proximal caries or apparently sound proximal 
surfaces were radiographed with conventional E-speed films and a photostimulable phosphor system using 60 kVp 
and 70 kVp for the caries assessment. The images were evaluated by three oral radiologists and compared with the 
results of the stereomicroscope analysis. 
Results: No statistically significant difference was found between 60 kVp and 70 kVp for the caries detection, 
determination of caries extension into dentin, and caries severity in either the conventional or the digital images. 
Good to very good inter-observer and intra-observer agreements were found for both kilovoltage values on the 
conventional and digital images. 
Conclusion: Changing the kilovoltage between 60 kVp and 70 kVp had no obvious effect on the detection of proxi-
mal caries or determination of its extension or severity. (Imaging Sci Dent 2014; 44: 199-205) </p>

<p>whether this validity is equal for digital images and con-
ventional radiographs. 
The aim of this study was to investigate the effect of 
changing tube voltage on caries assessment based on digi-
tal and conventional radiographs. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>This study was conducted on 150 proximal surfaces of 
75 human posterior teeth that were extracted for periodon-
tal or orthodontic reasons. The selected teeth were visually 
sound or with proximal caries without occlusal cavitation 
and without extended buccal or lingual/palatal caries. Sets 
of three teeth each were mounted in contact in a mold 
made of plaster of Paris (Gipsina, Giza, Egypt). The level 
of gypsum was adjusted to be below the cemento-enamel 
junction of the examined teeth by 1-3 mm. A small piece 
of lead foil was attached to the tube side of the mold to 
indicate the mesial side of each image. All teeth were 
radiographed twice by using an intraoral X-ray machine 
(Minray, Soredex, Tuusula, Finland) set once at 60 kVp 
and the other time at 70 kVp. The tube current was 7 mA. 
The focus-to-film distance as well as the tube angulation 
between the central rays and the image receptors was fixed 
by using a simple cylindrical device. Eight 1.5-mm-thick 
layers of pink wax, leading to a total thickness of 12 mm, 
were placed between the position-indicating device (PID) 
and the teeth to simulate the effect of soft tissues in the 
oral cavity. 
28 Two types of image receptors were used to </p>

<p>expose the investigated teeth in this study: E-speed films 
(CEA ID, Agfa Healthcare, Mortsel, Belgium) with a 
spatial resolution of 20 lp/mm, and a photostimulable 
phosphor plate (PSP) for a direct digital system (Digora </p>

<p>Optime, Soredex, Tuusula, Finland) with a spatial resolu-
tion of 12.5 lp/mm and 14-bit grayscale (Fig. 1). 
To choose the most appropriate exposure time, different 
exposure times were tested for each receptor. The shortest 
exposure times that produced high-quality images, as judg-
ed by three examiners, were included in the experiment. 
Conventional films were processed by an automatic pro-
cessor (Extra-X, Velopex, London, England). 
After being detached from their molds, the teeth were 
longitudinally separated (mesiodistally) at the middle of 
their proximal surfaces by using a water-cooled diamond 
saw. The separated crowns were examined under a stereo-
microscope (Leica S 8APO, Microsystem, Heerbrugg, 
Switzerland) (Fig. 2). 
All radiographic images were blindly assessed by three 
oral radiologists having more than five years of experience </p>

<p>─ 200 ─ </p>

<p>Effect of changing the kilovoltage peak on radiographic caries assessment in digital and conventional radiography </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Digital radiographic images show the teeth radiographed with 60 kVp (A) and 70 kVp (B). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Stereomicroscopic image (32× magnification) of sectioned 
tooth shows advanced caries in the proximal surface. </p>

<p>each, with a haphazard arrangement of the images. Each 
image was assessed twice with a period of two weeks 
between the two sessions. The radiographic images were 
evaluated inside a quiet room with dimmed light. A black 
cardboard with a customized window was placed on a 
viewer box to be used in the assessment of conventional 
radiographs, and the use of a magnifying lens (2× magni-
fication) was allowed. The digital images were evaluated 
in such a room by using the Digora for Windows 2.7 soft-
ware on an 18.5-inch monitor (SyncMaster B1930N, Sam-
sung, Seoul, South Korea) with a resolution of 1360×768. 
The examiners were not allowed to change the contrast 
and the brightness of the images. Every interpretation 
session was terminated after 30 min or upon request of 
any of the examiners because of eye fatigue. 
A five-point scoring system was used in the assessment 
of carious proximal surfaces as follows: 0: sound, 1: incip-
ient caries (less than half the enamel thickness), 2: mode-
rate (more than half the enamel thickness but does not 
reach the dentino-enamel junction), 3: advanced (less than 
half the dentin thickness), and 4: severe (more than half 
the dentin thickness). 
The results of radiographic images were compared with 
those yielded by a stereomicroscope as the gold standard in 
order to calculate the sensitivity, specificity, positive pre-
dictive value (+ +PV), and negative predictive value (-PV) 
of both the investigated kVp values in the conventional 
and the digital images. The receiver operating characteris-
tic (ROC) curve was used to evaluate the diagnostic accu-
racy measures of the different modalities. Areas under the 
ROC curve (AUCs) of the different tests were compared </p>

<p>using a z-statistic. Inter-and intra-observer agreements 
(reliability) were assessed using the kappa statistic. The 
ROC curve analysis and the reliability analysis were per-
formed with MedCalc <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 11.3</rs> for Windows (MedCalc 
Software BVBA, Ostend, Belgium). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Stereomicroscopic findings, the standard reference, 
revealed that 46.7% of the examined surfaces were carious, 
while the remaining 53.3% were sound. From the carious 
surfaces, 31.4% were confined to the enamel (14.3% inci-
pient caries and 17.1% moderate caries) and 68.6% extend-
ed into the dentin (25.7% advanced caries and 42.9% severe 
caries). 
With respect to the diagnostic accuracy measures and 
ROC curve analysis for caries detection using the two 
imaging modalities and the two kVp settings, convention-
al radiography (60 kVp) showed the highest sensitivity 
(74.3%), the highest -PV (77.8%), the highest diagnostic 
accuracy (77%), and the highest AUC (0.765). Conven-
tional radiography (70 kVp) showed the highest specificity 
(86.3%) and the highest + +PV (80%) (Table 1). 
Pair-wise comparisons between the AUC of different 
caries detection modalities revealed statistically non-sig-
nificant differences among all modalities. 
With respect to the diagnostic accuracy measures and 
ROC curve analysis for the determination of caries exten-
sion into the enamel or the dentin of different modalities, 
conventional radiography (60 kVp) showed the highest 
sensitivity (75%). Conventional radiography (70 kVp) </p>

<p>─ 201 ─ </p>

<p>Mohamed Khalifa Zayet et al </p>

<p>Table 1. Results of diagnostic accuracy measures of the four modalities used in the detection of caries </p>

<p>Modality 
Sensitivity % 
Specificity % 
+ +PV % -PV % 
Diagnostic 
accuracy % 
AUC 
SE 
95% CI </p>

<p>Conventional (60 kVp) 
74.3 
78.8 
75.4 
77.8 
77 
0.765 
0.039 
0.689-0.830 
Conventional (70 kVp) 
62.9 
86.3 
80 
72.6 
75 
0.746 
0.041 
0.668-0.813 
Digora (60 kVp) 
62.9 
82.5 
75.9 
71.7 
73 
0.727 
0.042 
0.648-0.796 
Digora (70 kVp) 
68.6 
85 
80 
75.6 
77 
0.768 
0.039 
0.692-0.833 </p>

<p>+ +PV: Positive Predictive Value, -PV: Negative Predictive Value, AUC: Area Under the Curve, SE: Standard Error, CI: Confidence Interval </p>

<p>Table 2. Results of diagnostic accuracy measures of the four modalities used in the detection of enamel and dentin caries </p>

<p>Modality 
Sensitivity % 
Specificity % 
+ +PV % -PV % 
Diagnostic 
accuracy % 
AUC 
SE 
95% CI </p>

<p>Conventional (60 kVp) 
75 
86.4 
92.3 
61.3 
81 
0.807 
0.052 
0.695-0.891 
Conventional (70 kVp) 
70.8 
95.5 
97.1 
60 
83 
0.831 
0.048 
0.723-0.910 
Digora (60 kVp) 
66.7 
90.9 
94.1 
55.6 
79 
0.788 
0.054 
0.674-0.877 
Digora (70 kVp) 
68.8 
86.4 
91.7 
55.9 
78 
0.776 
0.056 
0.660-0.867 </p>

<p>+ +PV: Positive Predictive Value, -PV: Negative Predictive Value, AUC: Area Under the Curve, SE: Standard Error, CI: Confidence Interval </p>

<p>showed the highest specificity (95.5%), the highest + +PV 
(97.1%), the highest diagnostic accuracy (83%), and the 
highest AUC (0.831) (Table 2). 
Pair-wise comparisons between the AUC of different 
modalities in the determination of the caries extension 
into the enamel or the dentin revealed statistically non-
significant differences between all modalities. 
With respect to the diagnostic accuracy measures and 
ROC curve analysis for the detection of incipient caries, 
all modalities showed the same sensitivity (90%). Digital 
radiography (70 kVp) showed the highest specificity (70%), 
the highest + +PV (33.3%), and the highest -PV (97.7%). 
Conventional radiography (60 kVp) showed the highest 
diagnostic accuracy (81%) and the highest AUC (0.805) 
(Table 3). 
With respect to the diagnostic accuracy measures and 
ROC curve analysis for the detection of moderate caries, 
conventional radiography (70 kVp) showed the highest 
sensitivity (91.7%), the highest -PV (97.6%), the highest 
diagnostic accuracy (83%), and the highest AUC (0.831). 
Digital radiography (70 kVp) showed the highest specifi-
city (77.6%) and the highest + +PV (40.9%) (Table 3). 
With respect to the diagnostic accuracy measures and 
ROC curve analysis for the detection of advanced caries, </p>

<p>all modalities showed a sensitivity of 100%. Digital radio-
graphy (60 kVp) showed the highest specificity (48.1%), 
the highest + +PV (40%), the highest diagnostic accuracy 
(69%), and the highest AUC (0.688). All modalities show-
ed the same -PV (100%) (Table 4). 
With respect to the diagnostic accuracy measures and 
ROC curve analysis for the detection of severe caries, 
conventional radiography (70 kVp) showed the highest 
sensitivity (96.7%), the highest -PV (97.1%), the highest 
diagnostic accuracy (96%), and the highest AUC (0.962). 
Conventional radiography (60 kVp), digital radiography 
(60 kVp), and digital radiography (70 kVp) showed the 
highest specificity (100%) and the highest + +PV (100%) 
(Table 4). 
Pair-wise comparisons between the AUC of different 
modalities in the determination of caries severity revealed 
statistically non-significant differences among all modali-
ties. 
The Kappa statistic showed an inter-observer agreement 
of 0.754, 0.780, 0.797, and 0771 for conventional radio-
graphy (60 kVp), conventional radiography (70 kVp), digi-
tal radiography (60 kVp), and digital radiography (70 kVp), 
respectively. Further, the intra-observer agreement ranged 
from 0.765 to 0.790 for conventional radiography (60 kVp), </p>

<p>─ 202 ─ </p>

<p>Effect of changing the kilovoltage peak on radiographic caries assessment in digital and conventional radiography </p>

<p>Table 3. Results of diagnostic accuracy measures of the four modalities used in the detection of incipient and moderate caries </p>

<p>Modality 
Sensitivity % Specificity % + +PV % -PV % 
Diagnostic 
accuracy % 
AUC 
SE 
95% CI </p>

<p>Incipient Conventional (60 kVp) 
90 
63.3 
29 
97.4 
81 
0.805 0.062 0.693-0.890 
caries 
Conventional (70 kVp) 
90 
66.7 
31 
97.6 
77 
0.772 0.068 0.656-0.864 
Digital (60 kVp) 
90 
55 
25 
97.1 
74 
0.737 0.074 0.619-0.835 
Digital (70 kVp) 
90 
70 
33.3 
97.7 
78 
0.783 0.066 0.669-0.873 </p>

<p>Moderate Conventional (60 kVp) 
83.3 
63.8 
32.3 
94.9 
78 
0.779 0.063 0.664-0.869 
caries 
Conventional (70 kVp) 
91.7 
69 
37.9 
97.6 
83 
0.831 0.054 0.723-0.910 
Digital (60 kVp) 
83.3 
72.4 
38.5 
95.5 
81 
0.811 0.057 0.700-0.895 
Digital (70 kVp) 
75 
77.6 
40.9 
93.7 
80 
0.801 0.059 0.688-0.887 </p>

<p>+ +PV: Positive Predictive Value, -PV: Negative Predictive Value, AUC: Area Under the Curve, SE: Standard Error, CI: Confidence Interval </p>

<p>Table 4. Results of diagnostic accuracy measures of the four modalities used in the detection of advanced and severe caries </p>

<p>Modality 
Sensitivity % Specificity % + +PV % -PV % 
Diagnostic 
accuracy % 
AUC 
SE 
95% CI </p>

<p>Advanced Conventional (60 kVp) 
100 
46.2 
39.1 
100 
68 
0.678 0.069 0.555-0.785 
caries 
Conventional (70 kVp) 
100 
44.2 
38.3 
100 
67 
0.672 0.069 0.549-0.780 
Digital (60 kVp) 
100 
48.1 
40 
100 
69 
0.688 0.068 0.566-0.793 
Digital (70 kVp) 
100 
44.2 
38.3 
100 
64 
0.639 0.072 0.516-0.751 </p>

<p>Severe 
Conventional (60 kVp) 
80 
100 
100 
87 
95 
0.953 0.028 0.874-0.989 
caries 
Conventional (70 kVp) 
96.7 
85 
82.9 
97.1 
96 
0.962 0.025 0.887-0.993 
Digital (60 kVp) 
83.3 
100 
100 
88.9 
95 
0.946 0.030 0.864-0.986 
Digital (70 kVp) 
76.7 
100 
100 
85.1 
93 
0.925 0.036 0.836-0.974 </p>

<p>+ +PV: Positive Predictive Value, -PV: Negative Predictive Value, AUC: Area Under the Curve, SE: Standard Error, CI: Confidence Interval </p>

<p>from 0.790 to 0.814 for conventional radiography (70 kVp), 
from 0.800 to 0.850 for digital radiography (60 kVp), and 
from 0.774 to 0.786 for digital radiography (70 kVp) 
(Table 5). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Upon analyzing the results of the current study, no sta-
tistically significant difference in the diagnostic accuracy 
for the assessment of dental caries in either conventional 
or digital images could be detected between 60 kVp and 
70 kVp. This finding is in contrast to the following state-
ment: "Images with a high contrast are more accurate in 
caries assessment than those with a low contrast." This 
concept, which is stated in textbooks, has been applied in 
many dental faculties where the oral radiology curricula 
are based on such textbooks. 
24-27 Moreover, some current </p>

<p>intraoral X-ray machines allow changing the kilovoltage 
peak between 60 kVp and 70 kVp, or even between 60 
kVp, 65 kVp, and 70 kVp; this option may be partially 
attributed to the previously mentioned statements about 
the relationship between short grayscale and caries detec-
tion. 
When dealing with the assessment of dental caries, sen-
sitivity and specificity as well as positive and negative 
predictive values have an equivalent diagnostic status. 
This is because it is important to detect carious lesions in 
affected teeth as well as to exclude caries in sound teeth. 
This diagnostic importance is attributed to the fact that 
false negative cases will lead to the progression of caries, 
particularly dentine caries, deeper in the tooth with a sub-
sequent more aggressive treatment. Moreover, false posi-
tive cases will lead to unrequired restorative intervention. 
Therefore, it is more practical to deal with the diagnostic 
accuracy as a whole than dealing with each measure sepa-
rately. 
The results of the current study revealed that the differ-
ence between the lower and the higher kilovoltage with 
respect to the diagnostic accuracy was minor and non-sta-
tistically significant. As for conventional radiography, the </p>

<p>use of 60 kVp revealed higher values in the detection of 
caries and the determination of caries severity in incipient 
and advanced caries, while the use of 70 kVp showed high-
er values in the determination of caries extension into the 
dentin and the determination of caries severity in the cases 
of moderate and severe caries. 
The insignificant importance of changing the kilovoltage 
values was also evident in digital images but in a different 
way. The use of 60 kVp showed higher values in the deter-
mination of caries extension as well as the severity of 
moderate, advanced, and severe caries, while the use of 
70 kVp aided in caries detection and the determination of 
its severity in the incipient cases. 
These fluctuating results of the high and the low kilo-
voltage in conventional and digital radiography reflect 
that changing the tube potential is no longer an influenc-
ing factor in caries assessment, the concept that was valid 
previously on the basis of old studies. 
29,30 This finding is </p>

<p>not confined to the detection of caries but extends to the 
determination of caries extension into the enamel and the 
dentin as well as the severity of the caries. 
The non-significant difference between both the investi-
gated kilovoltage peaks in the conventional radiographs 
may be attributed to the advances in the manufacturing of 
radiographic films, namely the production of films with a 
higher film latitude than that of the films produced in the 
previous decades. In the same manner, the wide dynamic 
range of digital systems, particularly that of photostimula-
ble phosphor systems, may be the cause for similar results, 
where a high film latitude and a wide dynamic range per-
mit obtaining diagnostically accepted images with a wide 
range of exposure time. Based on the fact that the expo-
sure time is the main factor that influences the image den-
sity, which will subsequently affect the final contrast of 
the image, the effect of changing the tube voltage as the 
master factor determining the image contrast may not be 
a crucial one. 
The results of the current study are consistent with those 
of Bottenberg et al, 
31 who used a charge-coupled device </p>

<p>(CCD) and a complementary metal-oxide semiconductor </p>

<p>─ 203 ─ </p>

<p>Mohamed Khalifa Zayet et al </p>

<p>Table 5. Inter-observer and intra-observer agreement results (Kappa statistic) </p>

<p>Modality 
Inter-observer 
Intra-observer 
Intra-observer 
Intra-observer 
agreement 
agreement (Observer 1) 
agreement (Observer 2) 
agreement (Observer 3) </p>

<p>Conventional (60 kVp) 
0.754 
0.790 
0.765 
0.772 
Conventional (70 kVp) 
0.780 
0.804 
0.814 
0.790 
Digital (60 kVp) 
0.797 
0.800 
0.850 
0.803 
Digital (70 kVp) 
0.771 
0.781 
0.786 
0.774 </p>

<p>(CMOS) instead of a PSP, which meant that the non-sig-
nificant difference in caries assessment between 60 kVp 
and 70 kVp was not confined only to PSP systems but was 
also observed in solid-state systems besides conventional 
radiography. 
30,32 The results of previous studies were </p>

<p>heterogonous to some extent either because of the use of 
a non-common kilovoltage 
33 or because of the use of the </p>

<p>kilovoltage that is not used in intraoral radiography any-
more. </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>Good-to-very good inter-observer and intra-observer 
agreements for 60 kVp and 70 kVp in both conventional 
and digital radiography reflected the comparable reliability 
of both the investigated potentials in the caries assess-
ment. Moreover, the small differences in agreement were 
not consistent among the study modalities. 
In conclusion, the difference between 60 kVp and 70 
kVp was not statistically significant with respect to the 
overall diagnostic accuracy in the dental caries assessment. 
Moreover, the sensitivity and the specificity as well as the 
positive predictive value and the negative predictive value 
in the considered cases were comparable and not constant 
for either of them in the detection of caries and the deter-
mination of its extension into the dentin or its severity. 
Therefore, from a clinical point of view, changing the tube 
voltage of intraoral X-ray machines between 60 kVp and 
70 kVp has no significant effect on the accuracy of the 
dental caries assessment, and this lack of effect could exist 
in both conventional and digital radiography. </p>



<p>─ 204 ─ </p>

<p>Effect of changing the kilovoltage peak on radiographic caries assessment in digital and conventional radiography </p>



<p>─ 205 ─ </p>

<p>Mohamed Khalifa Zayet et al </p>

</text></tei>