<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4579483" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Precise assessment of the prevalence of illicit drug use, face various methodological challenges. 
Objectives: The current study aimed to investigate the prevalence of illicit drug use among students studying at Universities in Shahroud 
(Northeast of Iran) through crosswise method. 
Patients and Methods: Participants of this cross-sectional study were 1646 students at Universities in Shahroud. The data collection 
instrument was a questionnaire designed based on crosswise model (CM). 
Results: The results of the study showed that 19% of students used at least one kind of illicit drug and 14.9% used opium residue once in 
their life. Moreover, 3.5% of students used drug and 3% used opium residue during the last month; 40.3% of the students admitted that they 
fully understood the instruction of the questionnaire; 9.6% said that did not comprehend the instruction at all, and 38.1% believed they 
partly understood the instruction. The result showed that 33.7% of the students fully trusted, 39.8% partly trusted, and 18.4% poorly trusted 
this method. There was a significant relationship between comprehension level and trust in CM (P &lt; 0.001). 
Conclusions: This method can be appropriate to estimate sensitive issues; however, lack of understanding the method or doubting the 
confidentiality of the responses can lead to bias in the results. That is to say, if the instructions are introduced better, the level of trusting 
the method will increase and accordingly more reliable responses can be obtained. More studies under controlled conditions are required 
to interpret the findings of the current study better. </p>

<p>Keywords: Drug Abuse; Illicit Drug; Iran </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-
Commercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial 
usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>One of the important information sources to help the 
authorities decide on the public health issues and their 
relation with other social issues is eliciting data from the 
target individuals and collecting their responses. Yet, di-
rect questions on the innermost private characteristics 
of people, their unacceptable social behaviors, illicit be-
haviors, etc., which are technically called sensitive issues, 
face various methodological challenges. Since different 
reasons such as disturbance, disclosure, susceptibil-
ity, and social acceptance people may avoid taking part 
in the study; or some people may participate in the study 
but skip sensitive items or provide inaccurate responses. 
Such errors may cause biases like social desirability bias 
and consequently desirable social behaviors such as us-
ing seatbelt, voting and exercise can be over reported and 
undesirable behaviors such as drug abuse, abortion, and 
high risk sex behavior can be prone to under reporting (1). 
There are different strategies, which aim to decrease such </p>

<p>measurement errors and biases and increase the reliabil-
ity of people responses. Randomized Response Technique 
(RRT) designed by Varner in 1965 can be viewed as the ear-
liest attempt to obtain valid information to estimate the 
proportion of a sensitive behavior in a population without 
revealing the true status of the respondents. Different ver-
sions of Randomized Response Technique are evolved and 
introduced through time (2-4). In all these procedures, in 
addition to the item on the sensitive behavior, an insensi-
tive item which is independent of the sensitive item is giv-
en to the respondent. Based on a randomized instrument, 
the distribution of which is known to the researcher, the 
respondent decides which item to answer. Therefore, the 
meaning of the responses depends on the results of the 
random instrument, which is unknown to the researcher 
and responding does not indicate anything about the true 
status of the sensitive behavior. 
Being aware of this anonymity, the respondent is ex-</p>

<p>Khosravi A et al. </p>

<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2015;4(2):e24388 </p>

<p>
pected to provide more honest responses to direct ques-
tions. Yet, all randomized response techniques depend 
on the randomized instrument used by the interviewer, 
understanding and performing some of the procedures 
are difficult and costly and not recursive or repeatable. To 
overcome some of the deficiencies in RRT, for a two status 
sensitive item, two non-randomized response techniques 
called crosswise (CW) and triangular procedures are re-
cently developed by Yu et al. (5), which should be appropri-
ate to solve some of the problems of randomized response 
models. As these authors maintain, these two models are 
appropriate both for face to face interviews and for self-
administered interviews. As these two models do not need 
any randomized instruments, their administration is eas-
ier than RRT models. Another advantage of these models 
is that none of the respondents directly answers the sen-
sitive items. However, in RRT models, at least some of the 
respondents should directly answer the sensitive items 
(5). Using prior knowledge of the population prevalence 
for an insensitive question led to the development of a 
number of competing techniques. In these models, the 
non-sensitive question is outside the researcher's control, 
independent of the research question but the population 
prevalence such as birth month or season, geographical lo-
cation for the person or a family member is already estab-
lished. Crosswise model uses a combination of sensitive 
and an insensitive questions with known population prev-
alence (5). Although Yu et al. (5), introduced the theoreti-
cal components and analysis of these models, the practical 
application of these two methods are not yet known, and 
to the best knowledge of the present study authors, these 
two methods are not tested in the domain of drug abuse. 
Drug abuse by university students worldwide, and alco-
hol use in Iran are regarded as sensitive issues and many 
researchers investigated the prevalence of drug abuse 
among students. However, as many of these researchers 
admit, due to the sensitivity of the issue and mistrust of 
the respondents, the prevalence of drug abuse is much 
higher than reported (6-13). Due to the anonymity which 
CW model entails for the participants, in the current study 
it was assumed that anonymity leads to an increase in the 
trust of the respondents and CW model can provide esti-
mates different from those of the direct methods. 
In this method, respondents receive two items with 
yes-no options. One item is sensitive and the other two 
option item is insensitive and independent of the sensi-
tive item. In this model, it is assumed that the probability 
of positive response to insensitive item is already known 
to the researcher. Of course the probability distribution 
should not be the same for the insensitive item. To re-
spond the items, the respondent is asked to choose "A" 
if the answers to both items are the same (both items 
yes or both no), and to choose "B" if the answers to both 
items are not the same (one answer is yes and the other is 
no). Assuming that the respondent honestly answers the 
items, an unbiased estimation of the prevalence of the 
sensitive trait is obtained as follows (Equation 1) (5): </p>

<p>λ = the proportion of those who choose A 
π = the proportion of those who have sensitive behavior. 
p = the probability of positive response to insensitive 
item p ≠ 0.5. </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>λ = pπ + (1 − p) (1 − π) </p>

<p>An orthogonal estimate is obtained through Equation 2: </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>π = </p>

<p>λ+ p−1 
2 p−1 </p>

<p>, ( p ̸ = 0.5) </p>

<p>The variance of π is calculated as follows (Equation 3). It 
should be noted that the second part of the equation is 
due to the insensitive item. </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>Var (π) = </p>

<p>π(1−π) 
n </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>p(1− p) 
n(2 p−1) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>The current study aimed to investigate the prevalence 
of drug abuse among students at Universities in Shah-
roud through CM and to evaluate the comprehension 
and trust levels of the participants in this method. The re-
sults can be helpful to improve the research methods in 
addiction studies, evaluate anti-drug programs, and plan 
for better tackling of drug related problems. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>The participants in this cross-sectional study were 1644 
students of Shahroud University of Medical Sciences, 
Shahroud University of Technology, Shahroud Islamic 
Azad and Payame Noor Universities. Fifty classes were 
selected from these Universities through stratified and 
cluster random sampling. Approximately 10% of the stu-
dents attending Shahroud universities were selected. All 
the students attending classroom sessions during De-
cember 2011 to January 2012 were asked to fill out a self-
administered questionnaire. Questionnaires were dis-
tributed at the beginning of each class after explanation 
about the CW model, and the students were given time to 
fill out the questionnaires. </p>

<p>3.1. Estimation of the sample size </p>

<p>The current study used the sample size formula intro-
duced by the developers of the model (Equation 4): </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>n = </p>

<p>Z α </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>L 0 (2p− 1) </p>

<p>Khosravi A et al. </p>



<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2015;4(2):e24388 </p>

<p>L 0 = 0.106 is the maximum confidence interval around 
the prevalence of the sensitive trait (π), which depends 
on the precision level intended by the researcher. 
P = 0.26 is the probability of positive response to the in-
sensitive items, which is already known to the research-
ers. The sample size was estimated to be 1650, according 
to the mentioned parameters. The Ethics Committee of 
Shahroud University of Medical Sciences approved the 
study protocol (No. 900.20). Oral informed consent was 
obtained after explaining the objectives of the study, and 
the people agreed to participate. </p>

<p>3.2. Instrument </p>

<p>The study instrument was designed based on crosswise 
model as follows. At the beginning of the questionnaire, 
instructions were provided on how to answer the items. 
Then there were the demographic items. It was tried to 
select items in a way which would produce the minimal 
sensitivity in the participants. These items were limited 
to asking about gender, place of residence, and marital 
status. The rest of the questionnaire included six pairs of 
items. The main results were last month and lifetime us-
ing one of the narcotic drugs and last month and lifetime 
using of opium or burned opium. Each sensitive item was 
accompanied by an insensitive item with a known proba-
bility distribution (Table 1). Assuming equal distribution 
of identical distribution of birth in seasons throughout a 
year, one of the items was on the date of birth. Moreover, 
according to a study which investigated the distribution 
of major blood types in different geographical areas and 
among different racial-ethic groups of Iran, 24.36% of 
people have blood group B (14). Therefore one insensitive </p>

<p>item was "Is your blood group B?" Moreover, assuming 
that the distribution of numbers (including 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 
6, 7, 8, 9) in ATM passwords, building numbers, telephone 
numbers and childbirth through year are equal, insensi-
tive items that were shown in the Table 1 were developed. 
In order to test the quality appraisal of the obtained re-
sponses, to examine the internal consistency and to ex-
perimentally compare the estimates of the model with 
the expected values, in one pair (No.2 in Table 1); both 
items were selected as insensitive with the expected 
probability distribution. Moreover, since lack of compre-
hension of the instruction to complete the questionnaire 
and the degree of trust were among major bias sources, 
the two items on these issues were put at the end of the 
questionnaire. </p>

<p>3.3. Data Analysis </p>

<p>The data were analyzed through the equations already 
introduced in this paper. To investigate the association 
between comprehending the instruction for crosswise 
model and the trust of respondents in it, Chi-square test 
was used. All calculations were performed through <rs type="software">Excel</rs> 
and <rs type="software">R-package</rs>. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>Out of 1644 participants, 49.5% (n = 814) were male and 
50.4% (n = 830) female. </p>

<p>4.1. Estimates Obtained Through Crosswise Model </p>

<p>Table 2 displays the prevalence and confidence interval 
for using each of the interrogated cases. </p>

<p>Table 1. Items in the Crosswise Model Questionnaire </p>

<p>Item 
Question </p>

<p>1 
Think of the password of one of your ATM cards, which you use more often. </p>

<p>Is the final figure of this password one of the numbers 5, 6, or 7? </p>

<p>Have you over the last month used one of the narcotic drugs (cannabis, opium, opium extract, crack, heroin, 
glass, ecstasy)? </p>

<p>2 
Is the final figure of your ID number 2, 4, or 6? </p>

<p>Were you born in summer? </p>

<p>3 
Think of the number of your father's or an acquaintance's house and do not change it. </p>

<p>Is the rightmost figure 2, 4, or 6? </p>

<p>Have you used opium during the last month? </p>

<p>4 
Think of a friend or acquaintance whom you know very well and know when exactly he was born. </p>

<p>Is his or her birthday between the first and the tenth day of the month? </p>

<p>Have you ever used any narcotic drug (cannabis, opium, opium extract, crack, heroin, glass, ecstasy)? </p>

<p>5 
Think of one of your friends that you know his/her mobile number. </p>

<p>Is the rightmost figure of his/her mobile number 2, 4 or 6? </p>

<p>Have you ever used opium or Burned opium? </p>

<p>Khosravi A et al. </p>

<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2015;4(2):e24388 </p>

<p>
Table 2. Estimation of the Drug Abuse Prevalence Based on Crosswise Model a </p>

<p>Items 
Male (N = 814) 
Female (N = 830) 
Total (N = 1644) </p>

<p>Use of illicit drugs throughout the lifetime 
21.4 (13.1 -29.8) 
16.9 (8.7 -25.1) 
19.0 (13.1 -24.8) </p>

<p>Use of illicit drugs during the last month 
6.1 (0 -14.1) 
0.9 (0 -8.7) 
3.5 (0 -9.1) </p>

<p>Use of opium or its burnt during the last month 
3.9 (0 -11.9) 
2.1 (0 -10.0) 
3.0 (0 -8.6) </p>

<p>Use of opium or its burnt throughout the lifetime 
18.9 (10.7 -27.3) 
11.4 (3.4 -19.5) 
14.9 (9.1 -20.7) </p>

<p>a Data are presented as % (95%CI). </p>

<p>Table 3. Experimental Estimation With Crosswise Model a </p>

<p>Total 
Male 
Female 
Expected Distribution </p>

<p>Item1: Was the person born in summer? 
27 (22 -33) 
25 (17 -33) 
30 (21 -38) 
25% </p>

<p>a Data are presented as % (95%CI). </p>

<p>The results of the study showed that 19% of the students 
used at least one kind of illicit drug and 14.9% used opi-
um residue (yen-shee) once over their life. There was no 
statistically significant difference between males and fe-
males in this regard. Moreover, 3.5% of the students used 
drugs and 3% used opium residue during the last month. 
There was no a statistically significant difference between 
males and females in this regard (P &lt; 0.05). 
Regarding the instruction comprehension, 40.27% of 
the students reported that they fully understood the 
questionnaire instructions, 38.09% reported partial un-
derstanding, and 12.02 % reported little understanding, 
and 9.59% reported no understanding of the instructions. 
With reference to the trust in the CM method, 33.71% of 
the students said they highly trusted the model, while 
39.85% moderately trusted, and 8.01% mistrusted the 
method. Moreover, there was a statistically significant 
relationship between understanding the method and 
trusting it; hence those who understood the method bet-
ter had more trust in it. 
The results of assessing of internal consistency of the 
questionnaires are displayed in Table 3. If the distribu-
tion estimate is the birth season of individuals (in case 
of asking about 2, 4, and 6 as the final figure of ID card is 
regarded as insensitive question), the model estimated it 
for the total population to be 27% (95% for CI: 22 -33), for 
females 30% (95%for CI: 21 -38) and for males 25% (95% for 
CI: 17 -33). </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>The current study aimed to evaluate the application of 
crosswise model in estimating the proportion of drug 
abuse. In general, it can be said that the results of the 
current study on narcotic drugs and burnt opium abuse 
over life and during the last month are consistent with 
the findings of other studies carried out among students 
of Iranian Universities with direct questionnaires (7, 8, 
10, 15). In the previous studies on drug abuse, the preva-
lence of drug abuse over life and during the last month 
was greater among males and showed a significant differ-
ence with that of females. However, although instant es-</p>

<p>timation of these prevalence figures in CWM was greater 
in males, the differences were not significant. Moreover, 
opium or burnt opium abuse over life was reported more 
among males, but there was no statistically significant dif-
ference with that of females. 
Since CWM requires a large sample size to provide con-
sistent estimates, and with regard to the high standard 
error in the two groups (especially males), the obtained 
result can be a matter of chance and due to small sam-
ple size in the two levels. On the other hand, since drug 
abuse by females is denounced more in the society than 
its abuse by males, it is possible that females trusted 
more in CWM and provided more accurate responses as 
compared to what other studies reported, and in fact it 
can be one of the advantages of CWM. Moreover, in the 
recent years there has been an increase in the students' 
tendency, especially females, towards narcotic drugs, 
smoking, and alcoholic drinks, which has led to concerns 
in student environments; it can also be one of the reasons 
for apparently incongruent results. 
Another result of the current study was the low confi-
dence interval for the prevalence of drug abuse during 
the last month (0.95 CI: 0-9.1). This can be by chancing or 
the respondents may not have correctly understood the 
instruction. In the insensitive item, which accompanied 
the item on drug abuse during the last month, it was as-
sumed that the final figure in ATM passwords is equally 
distributed. However, since people usually change their 
passwords, there may have been a preference for certain 
numbers for which the distribution was not equal and 
accordingly introduced error into the estimations. Esti-
mation of the lifetime opium or burnt opium abuse was 
based on the insensitive item for which the equal distri-
bution of the final figure in the mobile phone number 
was assumed. 
One of the indicators of the evaluation model was the 
level of comprehending the instructions as well as the 
level of the participants trust in crosswise model and the 
association between them; 40.27% of the students said 
that they had fully understood the instructions. The rea-
son for lack of understanding the instructions in 9.59% </p>

<p>Khosravi A et al. </p>



<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2015;4(2):e24388 </p>

<p>or partial understanding in 38.85% of the students can be 
the fatigue after some classes. 
Another important aspect of evaluating the success of 
this method was the number of participants who trusted 
that their personal information would be kept confiden-
tial. The results showed that 33.71% of the students highly 
trusted, 39.85% moderately trusted, 18.4% poorly trusted, 
and 8.01% distrusted this method. Since a significant rela-
tionship was found between understanding the method 
and trusting it, it can be said that improving the under-
standing of the instructions can result in an increase 
in the level of trust in the method and more accurate 
responses. It further indicates that the instructions pro-
vided by the researchers were not appropriate. 
In this method of responding, the respondent can-
not take a self-protection strategy and give a negative 
answer to a question. As a result, it reduces the self-pro-
tection bias. This is in fact one of the advantages of CW 
model over RRT techniques. Since in this method the es-
timations are based on peripheral techniques, and the 
normality of the data requires a large sample size, the 
present results indicated that for rare attributes with a 
skewed likelihood distribution, the method cannot pro-
vide consistent estimates. In these cases, Bayesian meth-
ods can be used. These findings were consistent with the 
findings of Ben John et al. on plagiarism (16). One limi-
tation in evaluating the model was the inaccessibility of 
findings on trust in a direct questionnaire, which can be 
compared with CWM. In this study six pairs of items were 
designed. It is possible that some students thought that 
some items were repetitious and the researchers intend-
ed to ultimately find an association between these items 
and detect their response and it influenced their trust. 
Therefore other studies with fewer pairs of items are 
suggested. Other studies with direct questionnaires and 
other NRR designs such as triangular and Hidden Sensi-
tivity (HS) models can be carried out and their results can 
be compared to one another. Other populations such as 
school students can also be studied using these designs. 
In this way, the results can be judged soundly. 
One of the most important and complicated parts of 
this model was selecting an insensitive item with a clear 
probability distribution appropriate for the population 
under study. In addition to meeting the conditions of the 
model, such items should be designed in a way which 
makes it impossible for the researcher to find their an-
swers and only the respondent himself should be aware 
of the answer. Since the insensitive items used in the 
study may not have corresponded to the assumptions, 
the results of the study may be distorted by this incon-
gruence. Moreover, high rate of lack of comprehension 
and distrust in the model showed that this model was 
not understandable to the students. This can also result 
from the complexity of the model or inaccuracy of the 
researchers to follow the instructions. Another issue was 
that this model proves inconsistent estimates for traits 
with almost zero prevalence, such as the prevalence of </p>

<p>drug abuse in females. In sum, more studies with other 
populations are required to better compare this model 
with the other models to detect its possible superiorities. 
The main limitation was lack of understanding the 
method or doubting the confidentiality of the respons-
es that can lead to bias in the results. The current study 
findings suggest that the CWM is a fruitful data collec-
tion method for sensitive topics such as drug abuse. Also 
the obtained results showed a good estimation for this 
method when two insensitive questions were used. Fur-
ther studies comparing the direct and indirect methods 
to estimate the prevalence of drug abuse in students are 
desirable. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We also wish to thank all of the students for their valu-
able collaboration with this study. </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions </p>

<p>Reza Chaman, Mansour Shamsipour, Seyed Abbas 
Mousavi and Ahmad Khosravi contributed to the study 
concept, design, data gathering, data analysis, interpre-
tation of data and drafting the manuscript. Mohammad 
Amiri and Faride Khosravi contributed to the data gather-
ing, and reviewing the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding/Supports </p>

<p>This study was supported by the Research council at 
Shahroud University of Medical Sciences, grant No 9005. </p>



<p>Khosravi A et al. </p>

<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2015;4(2):e24388 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>