<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4929210" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Physical inactivity is the third leading cause of the burden of disease for Australian Aboriginal adults. The neigh-
borhood environment and social support are known to influence physical activity (PA) participation. This study 
examined these factors in relation to achieving PA recommendations in Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal 
Australians. Cross-sectional data from the 2010 Social, Economic, and Environmental Factor (SEEF) Study in 
New South Wales, Australia were used to estimate adjusted odds ratios (OR) for Aboriginal versus non-
Aboriginal participants for PA-related attributes, including achieving PA recommendations. ORs for achieving 
PA recommendations were estimated in both groups. Overall, 63.1% of Aboriginal (n = 314) and 65.4% of non-
Aboriginal (n = 59,175) participants met PA recommendations. Odds of healthy sleep duration were lower, 
and receiving GP advice to be active was higher, among Aboriginal versus non-Aboriginal participants. Aboriginal 
respondents had higher odds of reporting that the crime rate made it unsafe to walk and that local public trans-
port was inaccessible. They had higher odds of disagreeing they have local shops, footpaths or free/low cost rec-
reation facilities. PA correlates were similar in both groups. The factors relating to PA were similar in Aboriginal 
and non-Aboriginal people. Neighborhood and social features were less PA-favorable for Aboriginal participants 
suggesting multiple possible avenues for increasing PA in this older population group. 
Preventive Medicine Reports </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / e e s . e l s e v i e r . c o m / p m e d r </p>

<p>(Koohsari et al., 2014). A review identified a positive relationship be-
tween parks and recreation settings and physical activity participation 
(Abercrombie et al., 2008). Fear of crime has also been found to lead 
to a decrease in time spent walking (Foster et al., 2014). </p>

<p>* The term 'Aboriginal' will be used to refer to participants of Aboriginal 
and/or Torres Strait Islander origin, in keeping with advice from the Ab-
original Health and Medical Research Council. </p>

<p>Identifying the factors associated with physical activity is important 
in devising strategies to increase levels of physical activity among Ab-
original people. There is little evidence regarding environmental corre-
lates of physical activity among Aboriginal Australians. Internationally, a 
study of Native American elders found that being closer to interesting 
places was a facilitator to walking (Sawchuk et al., 2011). However, an-
other Native American study found undesirable aspects of the built en-
vironment such as a lack of destinations for walking or public open 
space as barriers to walking for recreation and transport (Mathews 
et al., 2010). The majority of Aboriginal Australians live in urban loca-
tions (Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS), 2011). Therefore, these as-
pects of the neighborhood built environment may serve to influence 
their levels of physical activity. However, the impact of specific histori-
cal factors such as colonisation and displacement may be a determinant 
of the types and quality of neighborhoods where Aboriginal Australians 
currently reside. To our knowledge no study has yet examined the evi-
dence of the influence of the neighborhood built environment on phys-
ical activity levels among Australian Aboriginal people. 
Social support of family and friends has been identified as a positive 
correlate of physical activity across various population groups, including 
ethnic minorities and women (Harvey and Alexander, 2012; Wilcox 
et al., 2009), and specifically Native American women (Henderson 
and Ainsworth, 2003). However, cultural traditions of Aboriginal 
Australians such as kinship place great importance on family and com-
munity values. Family engagement and group activities have been 
found to be strong motivators of physical activity participation among 
Aboriginal Australians (Hunt et al., 2008). We hypothesize that social 
support would be associated with physical activity among Aboriginal 
adults. 
The aim of this study was to investigate the sociodemographic fac-
tors, attributes of the neighborhood built environment and social 
support associated with achieving the national physical activity recom-
mendations among Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal participants of a 
large Australian cohort study. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Participant recruitment </p>

<p>The Sax Institute's 45 and Up Study is a large-scale population-based 
cohort study of men and women aged 45 years and older residing in 
New South Wales (NSW), Australia (Collaborators, 2008). Participants 
were randomly sampled through the Medicare database, with 
oversampling in rural areas and among older adults (Collaborators, 
2008). Baseline self-administered postal questionnaires were distribut-
ed between 1 January 2006 and 31 December 2008. Joining the study in-
volved completing the baseline questionnaire and providing written 
consent. The Social, Economic, and Environmental Factor (SEEF) study 
is a subsequent sub-study of the 45 and Up Study which aims to identify 
how social, economic and environmental factors influence the health 
and wellbeing of middle aged and older Australians. In 2010 the SEEF 
questionnaire was distributed by mail to the first 100,000 participants 
to join the 45 and Up Study. A total of 60,404 participants returned 
a completed questionnaire and a signed consent form (response 
rate = 60.4%). 
The 45 and Up Study was granted ethical approval by the University 
of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee (Reference </p>

<p>050,035). The SEEF Study was granted ethical approval by the Universi-
ty of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee (Ref no.: 10-2009/ 
12,187). Ethical approval for the current study was also granted by the 
Aboriginal Health and Medical Research Council of New South Wales 
(reference 912/13). </p>

<p>Measures </p>

<p>Pilot testing of the SEEF questionnaire (n = 128) resulted in overall 
acceptable test-retest reliability intra-class coefficients (ICC) ranging 
from 0.33 to 0.84 and Cronbach's alpha coefficients ranging from 0.23 
to 0.96. Aboriginal status was self-identified in the 45 and Up Study 
with the following question: 'Are you of Aboriginal or Torres Strait Is-
lander Origin? and response options of: 1) No -non-Aboriginal; 
2) Yes -Aboriginal; and 3) Yes -Torres Strait Islander. Participants 
were able to identify as both Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander. 
Very few participants indicated they were exclusively of Torres Strait Is-
lander origin (n = 19) and for the purposes of these analyses this vari-
able was dichotomised into non-Aboriginal and Aboriginal and/or 
Torres Strait Islander, with the latter category referred to as 'Aboriginal'. </p>

<p>Physical activity </p>

<p>The main outcome variable, achieving the national physical activity 
recommendations, was calculated based on the Active Australia Survey 
(AIHW, 2003) which measures minutes of walking and other moderate 
and vigorous leisure-time physical activity in the past week, and has ac-
ceptable reliability (Brown et al., 2004a) and validity (Timperio et al., 
2003). The SEEF questionnaire included questions about the frequency 
and duration of their time spent doing walking, moderate and vigorous 
activities in the past week. Two different thresholds of at least 150 min 
per week and at least 300 min per week of MVPA were used, based on 
the upper and lower thresholds of the range advised in the national 
guidelines (Australian Government Department of Health, 2013). </p>

<p>Socio-demographic variables </p>

<p>Sociodemographic variables (age, sex and annual household in-
come) were derived from the SEEF questionnaire. Educational qualifica-
tions were derived from the baseline 45 &amp; Up Study questionnaire and 
dichotomised as (None/school/intermediate/High School Certificate 
(HSC); trade/apprenticeship/certificate/diploma/university). The Ac-
cessibility Remoteness Index of Australia Plus (ARIA+) score (AIHW, 
2004) and the measure of Socio-Economic Indices for Areas (SEIFA), 
the Index of Relative Socio-economic Disadvantage (IRSD) (Australian 
Bureau of Statistics (ABS), 2013b) were derived for each participant's 
postcode of residence at the time of recruitment to the 45 and Up 
Study, as recorded by Medicare Australia. These variables were 
dichotomised as: ARIA (Major City/Inner/Outer Regional; Remote/Very 
Remote) and SEIFA (Most disadvantaged quintiles 1, 2; Least disadvan-
taged quintiles 3, 4, 5). Other socio-economic variables were also 
dichotomised: sex (male; female); age (45-59 years; ≥ 60 years); in-
come (b$39,999; ≥$40,000). </p>

<p>Neighborhood built environment and social support variables </p>

<p>The SEEF questionnaire included six neighborhood built environ-
ment questions adapted from the Physical Activity Neighborhood Envi-
ronment Survey (PANES) (Sallis et al., 2010). These questions asked 
about access to shops/services, public transit and recreation facilities, 
presence of sidewalks and personal safety from crime (day and night). 
Responses option were dichotomised as: disagree (strongly disagree 
and somewhat disagree) and agree (strongly agree and somewhat 
agree). The two questions related to levels of crime were reverse scored. 
Cronbach's alpha coefficients and test-rests reliability ICCs were 0.64 </p>

<p> 
R. Macniven et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 3 (2016) 203-210 </p>

<p>and 0.56, respectively, for the two crime questions and 0.81 and 0.84 for 
the other neighborhood environment questions, respectively. 
Social and neighborhood connections were assessed using eight 
questions. Dichotomised 'yes/no' responses were sought for survey 
items about whether the respondent visits neighbors or family outside 
their local area, can give or receive help from friends and neighbors, is 
likely to see people they know in their local area, can trust most people 
in their neighborhood; and if the area has a reputation for being safe. 
Three further questions from the Duke Social Support Scale (Goodger 
et al., 1999) asked the respondent how many times per week they 
spend: time with friends or family they do not live with (dichotomised 
as 0-3, ≥ 4); at meetings of social clubs, religious/other groups 
(dichotomised as 0, ≥1); and how many people outside home, within 
1 h of travel they can depend on or feel very close to (dichotomised as 
0-3; ≥4). </p>

<p>Healthy lifestyle behaviors </p>

<p>Respondents were also asked whether they had been told by their 
General Practitioner (GP) to be more physically active in past 12 months 
(yes/no). Dichotomisation of hours per day spent in sedentary behav-
iors was based on cut points established from current evidence for un-
healthy levels of sitting at 8 + hours (Chau et al., 2013) and high 
levels of television viewing at 2 + hours (Hu et al., 2001). Hours per 
day spent sleeping were classified as healthy (7-9 h) or at risk (5-7 h 
or 9+ hours) Cappuccio, D'Elia (Cappuccio et al., 2010). </p>

<p>Analyses </p>

<p>Data analysis was carried out using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 21.0</rs>. Chi-squared 
tests were used to compare the sociodemographic profile of Aboriginal 
and non-Aboriginal participants. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence 
intervals (CIs) for Aboriginal versus non-Aboriginal participants for 
physical activity, sedentary behavior and sleep, neighborhood built en-
vironment and social support variables were estimated using forced 
entry binary logistic regression models, adjusting (where appropriate) 
for age and sex (Model 1). Models were further adjusted for remoteness 
of residence (Model 2) and education level (Model 3). 
Similar models examined the factors associated with meeting the 
physical activity recommendations, separately in Aboriginal and non-
Aboriginal participants. Effect modification of the relationship between 
each sociodemographic, behavioral, neighborhood built environment 
and social support factor and achieving the recommended physical ac-
tivity levels by Aboriginal status was also examined using interaction 
tests. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Participants without a valid age or date of entry into the study or a 
valid response to the question on Aboriginal origin (n = 910) were ex-
cluded from the analysis. Of the 60,404 respondents to the SEEF study a 
total of 59,489 (314 Aboriginal; 59,175 non-Aboriginal) participants 
were included in the analyses (98.5%). 
Compared to non-Aboriginal participants, Aboriginal adults were 
more likely to be younger, have lower levels of educational qualifica-
tions and income and live in a disadvantaged area. Aboriginal partici-
pants were less likely to live in a major city and be married/living 
with a partner (all p ≤ 0.001) (Table 1). </p>

<p>Physical activity and healthy lifestyle behaviors </p>

<p>Table 2 presents the proportion of participants meeting the 
upper threshold of the physical activity recommendations of 
N300mins/week, which was high in both Aboriginal (63.1%) and non-
Aboriginal respondents (65.4%). A greater propotion of respondents 
met the lower threshold of the physical activity recommendations of </p>

<p>N150mins/week (data not shown; 76.9% in Aboriginal and 80.4% in 
non-Aboriginal respondents, respectively p = 0.144). The odds of 
achieving the upper threshold of the physical activity recommendations 
did not differ according to Aboriginality, after adjustment for age, sex 
and ARIA/education. Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal participants 
did not differ significantly in terms of measures of sedentary behavior. 
Aboriginal participants had higher odds of being told to be more physi-
cally active by their GP in the past 12 months than non-Aboriginal 
participants in each model (age and sex adjusted OR = 1.90, 95% CI 
1.50-2.40; Table 2). Compared to non-Aboriginal participants, Aborigi-
nal participants also had a higher odds of unhealthy sleep duration in 
each model. </p>

<p>Neighborhood built environment and social support variables </p>

<p>Adjusting for age and sex, Aboriginal respondents had a higher odds 
of disagreeing that there were local shops within easy walking distance of 
home; public transport within a 10-15 min walk from home; footpaths on 
most of the streets in neighborhood or that the neighborhood has free or 
low cost recreation facilities AND HIGHER ODDS OF AGREEING or that 
the crime rate makes it unsafe to walk at both day and night; compared 
to non-Aboriginal respondents (Table 2). Adjustment for ARIA attenuat-
ed the association with accessibility to local shops, recreation facilities 
and footpaths. Aboriginal respondents had higher odds of indicating 
that they do not go outside local area to visit family, cannot get help 
from friends when need it; DO NOT agree most people in neighborhood 
can be trusted or DO NOT AGREE that their area has a reputation for 
being a safe place, compared to non-Aboriginal respondents. In the 
model adjusted for ARIA, Aboriginal respondents had a higher odds of 
reporting they cannot ask neighbor to help care for someone, compared 
to non-Aboriginal respondents. 
Aboriginal participants had higher odds of spending no time in the last 
week at meetings of social clubs or other group meetings (compared 
to 1 +) or having 0-3 people outside home that they can depend on 
(compared to 4 +) compared to non-Aboriginal participants. Other 
neighborhood built environment, neighborhood connections and social 
support variable responses were similar among Aboriginal and non-
Aboriginal participants. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Socio-demographic characteristics of Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal participants of the 
2010 SEEF study, New South Wales, Australia. </p>

<p>Aboriginal 
(N = 314)% </p>

<p>Non-Aboriginal 
(N = 59,175)% </p>

<p>p value </p>

<p>Sex 
Male 
40.4 
46.4 
0.034 
Female 
59.6 
53.6 
Age 
45-59 
63.4 
47.1 
b 0.001 
60+ years 
36.6 
52.9 
Education 
None/school/intermediate/HSC 
52.9 
40.3 
b 0.001 
Trade/apprenticeship/certificate/ 
diploma/uni </p>

<p>47.1 
59.7 </p>

<p>Marital status 
Single/divorced/separated/widowed 31.8 
24.0 
0.001 
Married/living with partner 
68.2 
76.0 
Income 
b$20,000-$39,000 
55.7 
40.3 
b 0.001 
$40,000+ 
44.3 
59.7 
Remoteness (ARIA+) 
Major City 
29.2 
43.4 
b 0.001 
Inner/outer regional/remote/ 
very remote </p>

<p>70.8 
56.6 </p>

<p>SEIFA 
Most disadvantaged quintiles 1, 2 
57.3 
40.1 
b 0.001 
Least disadvantaged quintiles 3, 4, 5 
42.7 
59.9 </p>

<p> 
R. Macniven et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 3 (2016) 203-210 </p>

<p>Correlates of meeting physical activity recommendations among Aboriginal 
and non-Aboriginal participants </p>

<p>Non-Aboriginal participants had a higher odds of meeting the phys-
ical activity recommendations if they were female, younger (b60 years), 
married/living with a partner, living in a major city, more educated and 
earning more income (≥$40,000; Table 3). Although associations were 
statistically significant among the non-Aboriginal participants only, 
the OR and 95% CI among the Aboriginal participants were consistent 
with those for non-Aboriginal participants and tests for statistical inter-
action according to Aboriginality were not significant. Repeating the 
models using the lower threshold of the 150 mins/week physical activ-
ity recommendations did not materially alter the findings regarding 
these associations (data not shown). 
In both Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal groups, those who were told 
to be more physically active by their GP in the past 12 months had a 
lower odds of meeting the physical activity recommendations (OR = 
0.35, 95% CI 0.20-0.60 and OR = 0.46, 95% CI 0.44-0.48, respectively; 
Table 3). Compared to those who sat for more than eight hours a day, 
only the non-Aboriginal respondents who spent less than eight hours 
a day sitting had a higher odds of meeting the physical activity recom-
mendations (OR = 1.75, 95% CI 1.67-1.83). Similarly, non-Aborginal re-
spondents with four or more people outside home that they can depend 
on also had a higher odds of meeting the physical activity recommenda-
tions compared to those with fewer social contacts (OR = 1.37, 95% CI 
1.32-1.42). 
In the non-Aboriginal group, those who disagreed that: they have 
easily accessible public transport, local footpaths and crime rate made 
it unsafe to go out (day or night) had a higher odds of meeting the </p>

<p>physical activity recommendations. Those who answered 'yes' to the 
seven questions relating to support from family, friends and neighbors 
and those who perceived their neighborhood as a safe place had a 
higher odds of meeting the physical activity recommendations. Partici-
pants who disagreed that there are local shops within easy walking dis-
tance of home had a lower odds of meeting the physical activity 
recommendations. Those who spent more time (≥ 4 vs 0-3) in the last 
week with friends, family they do not live with or any time at social clubs, 
other groups meetings had a higher odds of meeting the physical activity 
recommendations. Further adjustment for remoteness of residence did 
not materially alter the findings. After adjusting for education, the 
odds of meeting physical activity recommendations increased for 
those who spent less than eight hours a day sitting (OR = 1.86, 95% CI 
1.00-3.45) and also for those with four or more people outside home 
that they can depend on and physical activity (OR = 1.69, 95% CI 1.01-
2.83) increased (Supplementary Table). 
The relationship of each of the sociodemographic, behavioral, neigh-
borhood built environment and social support factors to meeting the 
physical activity recommendations did not vary significantly according 
to Aboriginality (p[interaction] ≥ 0.1). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>A large proportion of Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal participants 
met the upper threshold of the recommended levels of physical activity. 
Socio-demographic factors relating to higher levels of PA included fe-
male sex, younger age, higher educational qualifications, higher income, 
being married/partnered and residing in non-major city areas. Factors 
associated with achieving physical activity guidelines were similar </p>

<p>Table 2 
Physical activity (PA), healthy lifestyle behaviors, neighborhood characteristics and social support among Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal participants of the 2010 SEEF study, New South 
Wales, Australia. </p>

<p>Aboriginal 
N = 314% </p>

<p>Non-Aboriginal 
N = 59,175% </p>

<p>Odds Ratios for Aboriginal vs non-Aboriginal participants (reference 
group) </p>

<p>Model 1 adjusted 
for age, sex </p>

<p>Model 2 adjusted for 
age, sex and remoteness 
of residence </p>

<p>Model 3 adjusted for 
age, sex and education </p>

<p>PA, healthy lifestyle behaviors 
Meets PA recommendations N300 min/week (no) 
36.9 
34.6 
1.15 (0.89-1.47) 
1.18 (0.92-1.51) 
1.14 (0.89-1.47) 
8+ hours per day spent sitting 
36.4 
36.0 
1.06 (0.79-1.40) 
1.13 (0.85-1.51) 
1.08 (0.81-1.43) 
2+ hours per day spent watching TV 
57.2 
56.3 
1.07 (0.80-1.44) 
1.04 (0.77-1.40) 
0.99 (0.73-1.34) 
5-7/9+ hours per day spent sleeping 
34.7 
20.8 
2.10* (1.66-2.68) 
2.11* (1.66-2.69) 
2.03* (1.60-2.59) 
Told by GP to be more active, past 12 months 
35.6 
22.3 
1.90* (1.50-2.40) 
1.95* (1.54-2.48) 
1.81* (1.43-2.30) </p>

<p>Neighborhood built environment 
Local shops within easy walking distance of home (disagree) 
59.0 
53.5 
1.26* (1.01-1.59) 
1.12 (0.89-1.42) 
1.28* (1.01-1.61) 
Public transport within 10-15 min walk from home (disagree) 
38.2 
26.7 
1.67* (1.32-2.10) 
1.33* (1.03-1.71) 
1.63* (1.29-2.06) 
Footpaths on most streets in neighborhood (disagree) 
54.2 
43.9 
1.51* (1.21-1.89) 
1.24 (0.97-1.58) 
1.49* (1.19-1.87) 
Neighborhood has free/low cost recreation facilities (disagree) 
35.4 
26.2 
1.49* (1.18-1.88) 
1.25 (0.98-1.60) 
1.40* (1.10-1.78) 
Crime rate makes it unsafe to walk: NIGHT (agree) 
33.7 
26.6 
1.53* (1.20-1.95) 
1.58* (1.24-2.01) 
1.44* (1.13-1.84) 
Crime rate makes it unsafe to walk: DAY (agree) 
13.0 
4.6 
3.31* (2.36-4.63) 
3.41* (2.43-4.77) 
3.09* (2.20-4.33) </p>

<p>Neighborhood connections 
Go outside local area to visit family (no) 
20.5 
15.0 
1.53* (1.16-2.03) 
1.59* (1.21-2.11) 
1.45* (1.10-1.93) 
Can get help from friends when need it (no) 
11.1 
6.0 
1.88* (1.31-2.69) 
1.92* (1.34-2.75) 
1.77* (1.23-2.56) 
Can ask neighbor to help care for someone (no) 
49.8 
42.8 
1.23 (0.98-1.54) 
1.26* (1.00-1.58) 
1.23 (0.98-1.55) 
Visited neighbor in past week (no) 
47.7 
45.2 
1.00 (0.80-1.26) 
1.04 (0.83-1.31) 
1.02 (0.81-1.23) 
Likely to run into friends and acquaintances locally (no) 
12.3 
13.7 
0.85 (0.60-1.19) 
0.97 (0.69-1.37) 
0.89 (0.63-1.26) 
Done favor for sick neighbor in past 6 months (no) 
50.6 
54.7 
0.80 (0.63-1.00) 
0.83 (0.66-1.04) 
0.82 (0.65-1.02) 
Agree most people in neighborhood can be trusted (no) 
22.0 
12.1 
1.89* (1.43-2.49) 
1.99* (1.51-2.62) 
1.84* (1.39-2.43) 
Area has reputation for being a safe place (no) 
16.3 
8.4 
2.02* (1.48-2.74) 
2.18* (1.60-2.97) 
1.96* (1.44-2.68) </p>

<p>Social support 
0-3 vs 4+ Times last week with friends, family (do not live with) 
59.0 
59.0 
0.96 (0.76-1.21) 
0.97 (0.77-1.22) 
0.94 (0.75-1.19) 
0 vs 1 Times last week at social clubs, other groups meetings 
55.4 
44.7 
1.40* (1.11-1.78) 
1.41* (1.11-1.78) 
1.36* (1.07-1.72) 
0-3 vs 4+ People outside home, within 1 h travel can depend on 
44.1 
36.5 
1.35* (1.08-1.70) 
1.35* (1.08-1.70) 
1.31* (1.04-1.64) </p>

<p>Model 1: adjusted for age, sex. 
Model 2: adjusted for age, sex and ARIA where appropriate. 
Model 3: adjusted for age, sex and education where appropriate 
* Statistical significance p b 0.05. </p>

<p> 
R. Macniven et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 3 (2016) 203-210 </p>

<p>Table 3 
Socio-demographic, behavioral, neighborhood and social support correlates of meeting physical activity recommendations of N300 min/week in the, adjusted for age and sex. </p>

<p>Aboriginal 
N = 314 </p>

<p>Non-Aboriginal 
N = 59,175 </p>

<p>% meet PA 
Odds ratios 
% meet PA 
Odds ratios </p>

<p>Socio-demographic 
Sex 
Male 
62.6 
1.00 
64.1 
1.00 
Female 
63.4 
1.03 (0.62-1.71) 
66.4 
1.08 ⁎ (1.04-1.12) 
Age 
45-59 
66.5 
1.00 
67.4 
1.00 
60+ years 
55.8 
0.64 (0.38-1.08) 
54.4 
0.84 ⁎ (0.81-0.87) 
Education 
None/school/intermediate/HSC 
60.6 
1.00 
62.5 
1.00 
Trade/apprenticeship/certificate/diploma/uni 
64.6 
1.11 (0.67-1.86) 
67.4 
1.24 ⁎ (1.19-1.29) 
Marital status 
Single/divorced/separated/widowed 
60.8 
1.00 
60.8 
1.00 
Married/living with partner 
66.7 
1.05 (0.60-1.84) 
66.7 
1.29 ⁎ (1.24-1.35) 
Income 
b$20,000-$39,000 
55.7 
1.00 
63.0 
1.00 
$40,000+ 
68.6 
1.55 (0.88-2.76) 
67.8 
1.22 ⁎ (1.12-1.27) 
Remoteness (ARIA+) 
Major city 
59.0 
1.00 
63.8 
1.00 
Inner/outer regional/remote/very remote 
64.6 
1.24 (0.72-2.15) 
66.6 
1.13 ⁎ (1.09-1.17) 
SEIFA 
Most disadvantaged quintiles 1, 2 
63.3 
1.00 
65.2 
1.00 
Least disadvantaged quintiles 3, 4, 5 
62.7 
0.99 (0.60-1.64) 
65.4 
1.01 (0.97-1.05) </p>

<p>Healthy lifestyle behaviors 
Hours per day spent sitting 
Unhealthy 8+ hours 
50.0 
1.00 
55.8 
1.00 
Healthy b8 h 
64.8 
1.81 (0.98-3.35) 
68.1 
1.75 ⁎ (1.67-1.83) 
Hours per day spent watching TV 
High 2+ hours 
63.6 
1.00 
64.9 
1.00 
Low ≤2 h 
60.0 
0.84 (0.43-1.62) 
67.9 
1.11 ⁎ (1.06-1.17) 
Hours per day spent sleeping 
Unhealthy 5-7/9+ hours 
62.9 
1.00 
60.8 
1.00 
Healthy 7-9 h 
64.5 
1.05 (0.61-1.79) 
67.1 
1.30 ⁎ (1.25-1.36) 
Told by GP to be more active, past 12 months 
No 
71.8 
1.00 
69.7 
1.00 
Yes 
46.7 
0.35 ⁎ (0.20-0.59) 
51.3 
0.46 ⁎ (0.44-0.48) </p>

<p>Neighborhood built environment 
Local shops within easy walking distance of home 
Agree 
66.0 
1.00 
66.9 
1.00 
Disagree 
61.8 
0.83 (0.49-1.39) 
64.4 
0.90 ⁎ (0.87-0.93) 
Public transport within 10-15 min walk from home 
Agree 
64.8 
1.00 
64.9 
1.00 
Disagree 
61.4 
0.84 (0.50-1.43) 
67.2 
1.11 ⁎ (1.06-1.15) 
Footpaths on most of streets in neighborhood 
Agree 
64.4 
1.00 
64.0 
1.00 
Disagree 
62.8 
0.91 (0.55-1.51) 
67.4 
1.15 ⁎ (1.11-1.20) 
Neighborhood has free or low cost recreation facilities 
Agree 
64.1 
1.00 
65.7 
1.00 
Disagree 
62.5 
0.93 (0.55-1.57) 
65.0 
0.96 (0.92-1.00) 
Crime rate makes it unsafe to walk: NIGHT 
Agree 
55.3 
1.00 
60.0 
1.00 
Disagree 
67.0 
1.60 (0.93-2.75) 
67.4 
1.37 ⁎ (1.32-1.43) 
Crime rate makes it unsafe to walk: DAY 
Agree 
57.6 
1.00 
54.7 
1.00 
Disagree 
63.5 
1.18 (0.56-2.50) 
66.0 
1.59 ⁎ (1.46-1.73) </p>

<p>Neighborhood connections 
Go outside local area to visit family 
No 
62.7 
1.00 
57.7 
1.00 
Yes 
63.9 
1.09 (0.60-2.01) 
66.7 
1.46 ⁎ (1.38-1.53) 
Can get help from friends when need it 
No 
59.3 
1.00 
55.6 
1.00 
Yes 
64.7 
1.26 (0.56-2.85) 
66.1 
1.58 ⁎ (1.46-1.70) 
Could ask neighbor to help care for someone 
No 
59.8 
1.00 
63.2 
1.00 
Yes 
68.3 
1.57 (0.93-2.66) 
67.5 
1.25 ⁎ (1.20-1.29) 
Visited neighbor in past week 
No 
59.0 
1.00 
61.8 
1.00 
Yes 
68.2 
1.53 (0.92-2.54) 
68.6 
1.39 ⁎ (1.34-1.45) 
Likely to run into friends and acquaintances locally 
No 
63.9 
1.00 
58.4 
1.00 
Yes 
63.4 
0.96 (0.46-2.01) 
66.6 
1.44 ⁎ (1.37-1.52) </p>

<p>(continued on next page) </p>

<p> 
R. Macniven et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 3 (2016) 203-210 </p>

<p>between Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal participants. Neighborhood 
conditions such as low crime rate and greater social interaction/social 
support were associated with achieving the physical activity recom-
mendations. Despite less favorable neighborhood environments, the 
proportion of Aboriginal participants achieving the recommended 
physical activity recommendations was similar to the proportion of 
non-Aboriginal participants. 
Given these high proportions and the tendency for physical activity 
to be over reported when measured through self report (Brown et al., 
2004b), we focused on the results of the modeling of the upper thresh-
old of the recommendations. While these high levels of physical activity 
are encouraging, particularly among the Aborginal participants, they 
may in part be due to a 'healthy cohort effect' where participants in 
studies tend to be healthier than the overall population from which 
they are sampled (Struijk et al., 2015). 
The socio-demographic, neighborhood built environment and social 
support correlates of physical activity are largely consistent with 
existing literature (Saelens et al., 2003; Foster et al., 2014) in both Ab-
original and non-Aboriginal participants in our sample. An exception 
to this was our finding that females were more active than males. 
Males are typically more active than females in Australia (Australian 
Bureau of Statistics (ABS), 2013a) and internationally (Guthold et al., 
2008). However, in specific population sub groups, including ethnic mi-
norities and middle to older aged adults, females tend to be more active 
than males or rates are similar (Hawkins et al., 2009; Martin et al., 
2014). Our findings appear to reflect these differences according to gen-
der and across the life-course, both in the Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal 
sub groups. 
Factors that influence physical activity can be explained through the 
socio-ecological model which takes account of both individual and so-
cial environmental aspects (McLeroy et al., 1988). The model has been 
adapted to include specific factors influencing physical activity partici-
pation among Aboriginal Australians, such as colonisation (structural 
macro-social factor), feeling unsafe in a physical environment (structur-
al environmental factor) and family and community connections (social 
connections) (Nelson et al., 2010). While our findings highlight that 
Aborginal people experience less desirable neighborhood environ-
ments, as well as lower indicators of social support, similar levels of 
physical activity are achieved. This may be due to a cultural emphasis 
on, or acceptability of, physical activity and sport among Aboriginal peo-
ple (Thorpe et al., 2014). Other influencing factors could include a level </p>

<p>of resilience among the Aboriginal sample in our study where despite 
less than ideal conditions for health, reasonable health outcomes can 
be achieved. Evidence of links between resilience and Aboriginal health 
are emerging but appears to be positively associated with a strong tra-
ditional culture (Currie et al., 2013); therefore emphasising cultural 
connections is important. Other determinants of physical activity in Ab-
original populations may not yet be known or understood. Further, 
analyses of cohort studies including Aboriginal people, or qualitiative 
exploratory research may elucidate greater insights. 
Aboriginal participants were more likely to have unfavorable neigh-
borhoods compared to non-Aboriginal participants. However, following 
adjustment for remoteness of residence, some of these associations 
were attenuated which could be attributed to Aborginal Australians 
being more likely to live in rural/remote areas than non-Aboriginal 
Australians (Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS), 2011). The use of 
the adapted PANES, which was established to measure physical activity 
and neighborhood environment aspects in urban populations only 
(Sallis et al., 2010), may also in part explain these findings. The develop-
ment and validation of a corresponding measure for non-urban neigh-
borhoods is important for future investigation. Further, some of the 
findings where the direction of association differered between partici-
pant groups, such as distance from public transport and presence of 
footpaths, could be due to the use of the PANES in a cohort where 
ARIA differed according to Aboriginality. Regardless, these findings indi-
cate that for the majority of neighborhood built environment attributes, 
Aboriginal participants were more likely to experience or perceive a less 
satisfactory position, even after accounting for education, a commonly 
used indicator of (dis)advantage. 
Hence, these data show that features of the neighborhood environ-
ment are associated with physical activity levels and that Aboriginal 
people report less physical activity favorable neighborhood attributes. 
The findings suggest that addressing features of the neighborhood and 
environment, such as walkability, crime and amenities could specifically 
improve physical activity levels. They also provide general support for 
policy based on the social determinants of health, where financial re-
sources and the everyday conditions in which people live and work, 
such as the neighborhood environment, are targeted to reduce inequal-
ities that influence health (Friel and Marmot, 2011). Recent evidence 
highlights the role of neighborhood walkability and safety in mediating 
the association between education level and physical activity (Pratt 
et al., 2015) suggesting specific modifiable neighborhood features. </p>

<p>Table 3 (continued) </p>

<p>Aboriginal 
N = 314 </p>

<p>Non-Aboriginal 
N = 59,175 </p>

<p>% meet PA 
Odds ratios 
% meet PA 
Odds ratios </p>

<p>Done favor for sick neighbor in past 6 months 
No 
60.4 
1.00 
62.8 
1.00 
Yes 
66.9 
1.47 (0.87-2.48) 
68.8 
1.33 ⁎ (1.28-1.38) 
Agree most people in neighborhood can be trusted 
No 
56.1 
1.00 
60.9 
1.00 
Yes 
65.2 
1.49 (0.82-2.74) 
66.2 
1.29 ⁎ (1.22-1.37) 
Area has reputation as a safe place 
No 
60.0 
1.00 
60.4 
1.00 
Yes 
65.1 
1.20 (0.60-2.42) 
66.0 
1.30 ⁎ (1.22-1.38) </p>

<p>Social support 
Times last week with friends, family (do not live with) 
0-3 
63.2 
1.00 
62.0 
1.00 
4+ 
64.9 
1.05 (0.63-1.76) 
70.8 
1.51 ⁎ (1.46-1.57) 
Times last week at social clubs, other groups meetings 
0 
59.3 
1.00 
62.4 
1.00 
1+ 
68.4 
1.61 (0.95-2.73) 
68.1 
1.33 ⁎ (1.28-1.38) 
People outside home, within 1 h travel can depend on 
0-3 
57.9 
1.00 
61.0 
1.00 
4+ 
68.2 
1.62 (0.97-2.71) 
68.1 
1.37 ⁎ (1.32-1.42) </p>

<p>Test of interaction by Aboriginality of sociodemographic, behavioral, neighborhood built environment and social support variables and meeting the physical activity recommendations 
were not statistically significant. 
⁎ Statistical significance p b 0.05. </p>

<p> 
R. Macniven et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 3 (2016) 203-210 </p>

<p>This study found that those participants who were told to be more 
active by their GPs were those who were less likely to be achieving 
the physical activity recommendations suggesting that both Aboriginal 
and non-Aboriginal people are receiving the appropriate health advice. 
The effectiveness of GP advice to patients to be more physically active is 
well established (Orrow et al., 2012), but widespread implementation 
of such advice remains a public health challenge. A recent national sur-
vey demonstrated less than a fifth of participants had received advice 
from their GP to be active in the past year, but similar to our study, ad-
vice was more commonly given to those with poorer health (Short et al., 
2015). Further exploration of GP advice to be physical active longitudi-
nally would help understand how this strategy can be best utilised and 
establish whether the provision of such advice leads to behavior change 
over time. Specific training, protocols and resource provision for GPs 
may prove effective measures. 
Among non-Aboriginal people, those who spent less than eight 
hours a day sitting were significantly more likely to meet the physical 
activity recommendations. A similar, but non-significant, finding was 
also evident in Aboriginal people. This is consistent with the evidence 
for the health risks of lengthy time periods spent sitting that has been 
established in recent years in mainstream populations (Bennie et al., 
2013) and across sex and race groups in the U.S. (Staiano et al., 2014). 
Little is known of sitting time prevalence and associated health risks 
among Australian Aboriginal people although recent ABS data found 
Aboriginal adults in non-remote areas spent an average of 5.3 h per 
day in sedentary behavior, which was less than their non-Aboriginal 
counterparts (Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS), 2014b). These find-
ings provide emerging evidence of the association between physical 
activity and sitting time which should be examined in future epidemio-
logical studies of health behaviors in Aboriginal populations. 
This study showed that social support was correlated with achieving 
the physical activity recommendations. Having four or more people out-
side home to depend on was significantly associated with meeting the 
physical activity recommendations. Social support is an established cor-
relate of physical activity in the general population (Nieminen et al., 
2013) and given the holistic context of Aboriginal health, where physi-
cal, mental, social and spiritual aspects are interconnected, it could pos-
sibly have a stronger influence. However, given that we also found 
Aboriginal people were less likely to have four or more people outside 
home to depend on, as well as being less likely to spend time in the 
past week at social clubs; this seems to reflect an overall lower level of 
social connect within this Aboriginal sample. Yet it should be noted 
that the Duke Social Support Scale used in this study focuses on social 
contacts outside the home, which may not capture social support within 
the household or family; such household and family support may be of 
greater importance to Aboriginal people (Williamson et al., 2010). 
Strengths of the present study include the large sample of almost 
60,000 middle-older age adults and a relatively large sample of Aborig-
inal participants followed up in a cohort study. The SEEF study captures 
data on many indictors of the neighborhood built environment and so-
cial support together in a study of this magnitude. It provides data for 
the first time of these behavioral, social and environmental characteris-
tics together within a specific Australian Aboriginal population group 
and one of the first of any Indigenous populations internationally. The 
findings should be acknowledged within several limitations including 
the self-reported, cross-sectional nature of the study and the small 
number of Aboriginal, relative to non-Aboriginal, respondents. This led 
to a larger number of significant associations in the non-Aboriginal pop-
ulation. However, testing of interaction effects revealed no differences 
between the two groups. Therefore, the non-significant findings in Ab-
original people where the direction of associations and magnitude of 
ORs matched that of the non-Aboriginal participants can be attributed 
in part to the smaller Aboriginal sample size. However, with several 
hundred Aboriginal participants, this study is large relative to many 
other Aboriginal studies. Further, there may have been sample bias 
reflecting participants with higher levels of literacy and education </p>

<p>level than the general population, particularly among Aboriginal people 
who experience higher levels of disadvantage. In light of these strengths 
and limitations, it is important not to over-interpret non-significant 
findings in this context, and to not infer causality from the observed 
associations. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Despite unfavorable neighborhoods and reduced social support, Ab-
original participants in this cohort were as likely to be achieving the 
physical activity recommendations compared to non-Aboriginal partic-
ipants. Factors associated with achieving the recommendations were 
similar between Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal participants and includ-
ed younger age, higher education, higher income, greater social support 
and more favorable neighborhood conditions such as perceived low 
crime rates. Given that significant disparities in the neighborhood 
built environment and social support were found among Aboriginal 
compared to non-Aboriginal people; this is an important area for future 
research and public health policy and programs. 
Supplementary data to this article can be found online at http://dx. 
doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2016.01.006. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interests. </p>

<p>Transparency document </p>

<p>The Transparency document associated with this article can be 
found, in online version. </p>



<p> 
R. Macniven et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 3 (2016) 203-210 </p>



<p> 
R. Macniven et al. / Preventive Medicine Reports 3 (2016) 203-210 </p>

</text></tei>