<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4932580" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Meat quality is defined by those traits that consumers 
perceive as desirable, such as visual appearance, edibility 
and credence quality (van der Wal et al., 1997; Warner et al., 
2010; Lee et al., 2012). At the point of sale, visual traits 
such as color, leanness, amount and distribution of fat, and 
the absence of excess water in the tray influence consumer 
purchase decisions. At the point of consumption, consumer 
satisfaction is mainly determined by edibility (Becker, 2000; 
Glitsch, 2000). Consumer's eating satisfaction, which is 
primarily associated with tenderness, juiciness and flavor, 
subsequently influence the intention to repurchase (Maltin 
et al., 1997; Lee et al., 2012). In general, tenderness is 
considered the most important palatability trait (Warner et 
al., 2010). Many researchers have reported that the main </p>

<p>source of consumer complaints and/or the most common 
cause of failure to repurchase is variation in tenderness, in 
particular the presence of toughness (Jeremiah, 1982; 
Tarrant, 1998; Bindon and Jones, 2001; Maltin et al., 2003). 
By the same token, consumers are willing to pay a premium 
for the meat that is guaranteed to be tender (Boleman et al., 
1997). Thus, the production of consistently tender meat is 
of primary concern to meat science and the meat industry. 
There are various methods available to measure meat 
tenderness, including instrumental, histological, and 
chemical evaluation; however, sensory evaluation is 
considered the ultimate method (Larmond, 1976). Sensory 
evaluation is the result of scoring done by trained or 
consumer panelists (Wood et al., 2004). The use of trained 
panelists is useful for comparing differences or 
investigating particular characteristics, but usually cannot 
provide information regarding the acceptability of or 
preference for one kind of meat over another to consumers 
(Wheeler et al., 1997; Destefanis et al., 2008; Warriss, 
2010). On the other hand, sensory consumer opinion as </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. </p>

<p>Vol. 29, No. 7 : 1029-1036 July 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5713/ajas.15.0482 </p>

<p>www.ajas.info </p>

<p>pISSN 1011-2367 eISSN 1976-5517 </p>

<p>Estimation of Sensory Pork Loin Tenderness Using 
Warner-Bratzler Shear Force and Texture Profile Analysis Measurements </p>

<p>Jee-Hwan Choe </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, Mi-Hee Choi </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, Min-Suk Rhee, and Byoung-Chul Kim* 
Division of Food Bioscience and Technology, College of Life Sciences and Biotechnology, 
Korea University, Seoul 136-701, Korea </p>

<p>ABSTRACT: This study investigated the degree to which instrumental measurements explain the variation in pork loin tenderness as </p>

<p>assessed by the sensory evaluation of trained panelists. Warner-Bratzler shear force (WBS) had a significant relationship with the 
sensory tenderness variables, such as softness, initial tenderness, chewiness, and rate of breakdown. In a regression analysis, WBS could 
account variations in these sensory variables, though only to a limited proportion of variation. On the other hand, three parameters from 
texture profile analysis (TPA)-hardness, gumminess, and chewiness-were significantly correlated with all sensory evaluation 
variables. In particular, from the result of stepwise regression analysis, TPA hardness alone explained over 15% of variation in all 
sensory evaluation variables, with the exception of perceptible residue. Based on these results, TPA analysis was found to be better than 
WBS measurement, with the TPA parameter hardness likely to prove particularly useful, in terms of predicting pork loin tenderness as 
rated by trained panelists. However, sensory evaluation should be conducted to investigate practical pork tenderness perceived by 
consumer, because both instrumental measurements could explain only a small portion (less than 20%) of the variability in sensory 
evaluation. (Key Words: Warner-Bratzler Shear Force, Texture Profile Analysis, Sensory Evaluation, Pork Loin Tenderness) </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 by Asian-Australasian Journal of Animal Sciences </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author: Byoung-Chul Kim. Tel: +82-2-3290-
3488, Fax: +82-2-3290-4984, E-mail: bckim@korea.ac.kr </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally. </p>

<p>Submitted Jun. 2, 2015; Revised Aug. 10, 2015; Accepted Sept. 10, 2015 </p>

<p>Choe et al. (2016) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 29:1029-1036 </p>

<p>
measured by consumer panelists is a key factor in 
establishing the value of meat and predicting purchasing 
decisions (Destefanis et al., 2008). Despite its obvious 
benefit, sensory evaluation is expensive, difficult to 
organize, and time consuming, regardless of whether the 
panelists are trained professionals or consumers (Peachey et 
al., 2002; Platter et al., 2003; Destefanis et al., 2008). 
Consequently, many attempts have been made to develop 
instrumental methods that can accurately reflect the meat 
tenderness ratings generated by panels (Lawrie and 
Ledward, 2006; Destefanis et al., 2008). However, sensory 
evaluation and instrumental methods cannot measure the 
same physical properties of meat (Hansen et al., 2004). 
Sensory evaluation determine that meat tenderness is a 
result of the type and rate of deformation and the 
heterogeneity of the sample, whereas instrumental 
measured only a resistance of external physical force 
(Hansen et al., 2004). For instance, instrumental methods 
assess the force required to shear, compress, penetrate, bite, 
stretch, and mince the meat (Lawrie and Ledward, 2006). 
Warner-Bratzler shear force (WBS) is the most widely 
used estimator of sensory meat tenderness; it is in fact the 
only method used for raw meat and is suitable for 
commercial application (Culioli, 1995; Shackelford et al., 
1995; 1999; Wheeler et al., 1997; de Huidobro et al., 2005). 
However, the correlation between WBS and sensory 
tenderness is known to vary considerably (Culioli, 1995; 
Caine et al., 2003; Platter et al., 2003; de Huidobro et al., 
2005; Destefanis et al., 2008). Variability in the relationship 
between WBS and sensory tenderness depends in many 
factors including muscle type, sample preparation, cooking 
methods, shear apparatus, measurement procedure and 
panel type (Destefanis et al., 2008). Moreover, WBS 
measurement has a limitation to imitate fully the 
complexity of the chewing motion (Caine et al., 2003). 
Texture profile analysis (TPA) is another common method 
used to evaluate the texture of various food items, with one 
advantage to assess multiple variables at one time 
measurement. For meat, these variables include hardness, 
cohesiveness, springiness and chewiness (de Huidobro et al., 
2005). The relationship between sensory evaluation and 
various instrumental measurements of beef tenderness has 
been investigated in previous researches, and it has been 
reported that TPA is a superior indicator of the beef 
tenderness assessed by panelists compared to WBS (Caine 
et al., 2003; de Huidobro et al., 2005). However, few 
studies have investigated the relationship between sensory 
and instrumental evaluation of pork tenderness, even 
though tenderness is an important quality for this meat 
(Jeremiah, 1982; Hansen et al., 2004). Therefore, the 
purpose of this study is to investigate the degree to which 
the two common instrumental measurements, WBS and 
TPA, can explain variation in pork tenderness as assessed </p>

<p>by trained panelists. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Meat samples 
A total of 380 pork loin samples were taken at 24 h 
postmortem between the 9th and 15th thoracic vertebra on 
the right side of 380 female pigs (Landrace×Yorkshire× 
Duroc), which are raised in the same farm under the same 
condition including the same feed. The samples were 
immediately transferred to the laboratory and were further 
divided into three groups to assign one group for each 
analysis including sensory evaluation, WBS measurement, 
and TPA measurement (Figure 1). The samples were then 
vacuum packaged and stored at -20°C until testing. </p>

<p>Sensory evaluation 
For the sensory evaluation of the pork loin, 10 panelists 
were selected and trained in accordance with previous 
methods (AMSA, 1995; Peachey et al., 2002). The 
objective of the training was to ensure that panelists were 
capable of providing precise, consistent and reproducible 
sensory evaluation. During the final training sessions, 
significant differences between the trained panelists and the 
samples were not observed when the same sample was 
assessed by all panelists or the same samples were assessed 
by the same panelist, indicating that the panelists could 
provide consistent and reproducible sensory evaluation data. 
Each pork loin sample was evaluated twice. A total of 
95 testing sessions was performed, with 8 samples 
evaluated per session. Two steaks of 20 mm thickness were 
cut from each pork loin at 24 h postmortem without visible 
fat and connective tissue and stored at -20°C until 
evaluation. Samples were thawed overnight at 4°C, and 
then cooked at 180°C without salt or spices in a humid oven 
(Hauzen HS-XC364AB, Samsung, Gyeonggi, Korea). 
Samples were cooked until an internal temperature of 75°C 
was reached, as measured by a TES-1300 thermometer 
(TES Electrical Electronic Co., Taipei, Taiwan). The cooked </p>

<p>Figure 1. Diagram of sampling procedure in pork loin. T5 and 
T11: 5th and 11th thoracic vertebrae. Slight modification of de 
Huidobro et al. (2005). </p>

<p>Choe et al. (2016) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 29:1029-1036 </p>



<p>samples were immediately cut into 15 mm cubes (Figure 
2A), packaged with polyethylene bag, and submerged in a 
water bath (54°C) until served to the panelists. Each sample 
was served in a lidded cup labelled with a three-digit 
random code. There was a 5 min interval between the 
evaluations of each sample. Panelists were instructed to 
cleanse their palate with distilled water (30°C) and salt-free 
crackers between samples. Testing took place in individual 
booths under white light. 
The tenderness-related attributes of the pork loin were </p>

<p>evaluated using the method described by Fortin et al. (2005) 
with slight modification. The definitions and score 
distributions for each of these attributes are presented in 
Table 1. These parameters were assessed using 5 cm 
unstructured line scales, labelled with the anchors (1 on the 
left side and 5 on the right side) shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Warner-Bratzler shear force 
Pork loins were thawed overnight at 4°C, then cut into 
20 mm thick chops. Pork chops from each sample were </p>

<p>Table 1. Definitions and score distributions of sensory evaluation parameters for pork loin tenderness </p>

<p>Attributes 
Definition 
Anchor points 
Softness 
Force required to compress (biting across the fibers) the meat sample placed 
between molar teeth </p>

<p>1 = Very hard 
5 = Very soft 
Initial tenderness 
Force required to chew three times after the initial compression 
1 = Very tough 
5 = Very tender 
Chewiness 
Energy required to chew nine times for swallowing at a constant rate 
1 = Very chewy 
5 = Very tender 
Rate of breakdown 
Number of chews required for the sample to disintegrate during the mastication 
process in preparation for swallowing </p>

<p>1 = Very slow 
5 = Very fast 
Amount of perceptible residue Amount of perceptible residue remaining upon complete disintegration of the 
meat sample </p>

<p>1 = None 
5 = Abundant 
Juiciness 
Amount of moisture released after five chews 
1 = Not juicy 
5 = Extremely juicy 
Mouth coating 
Amount of oil/fat left on the mouth surface 
1 = None 
5 = Abundant </p>

<p>Modified from Fortin et al. (2005). </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Figure 2. Schematic representation of the sample preparation for sensory evaluation and texture profile analysis (A) and Warner Bratzler 
shear force (B). The samples for each measurement were cut parallel to the longitudinal orientation of the muscle fiber without cooked 
surface from each cooked pork loin chop. Then, 15 mm cube samples were obtained for sensory evaluation and texture profile analysis. 
The samples were measured perpendicular to the muscle fiber orientation. Slight modification of Hansen et al. (2004). </p>

<p>Choe et al. (2016) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 29:1029-1036 </p>

<p>
cooked to a final core temperature of 75°C in a 
continuously boiling water bath and then immediately 
immersed in ice water until equilibrated. After cooling, six 
cores (diameter 1.27 cm) without fat or connective tissue, 
parallel to the longitudinal orientation of the muscle fibers, 
were taken from each pork chop (Figure 2B). WBS was 
determined using an Instron Universal Testing Machine 
(Model Series IX; Instron Co., Norwood, MA, USA) with a 
Warner-Bratzler shearing device. Samples were sheared 
perpendicular to the long axis of the core, and WBS was 
taken to be the peak force of the curve (Honikel, 1998). </p>

<p>Texture profile analysis 
The pork chops used for TPA measurement were 
prepared in the same manner previously described for WBS 
measurement. After cooling, the cooked surface was 
removed and six 15 mm cubes were then cut from each 
pork chop (Figure 2A). The fiber axis of each cube was 
perpendicular to the direction of the probe. TPA 
measurement was performed using a texture analyzer (TA-
XT2i, Stable Micro System, Surrey, England). Cube 
samples were placed under a 10 mm diameter cylindrical 
probe. The probe moved downwards at a constant speed of 
3.0 mm/s (pre-test), 1.0 mm/s (test) and 3.0 mm/s (post-test). 
The probe continued downward until penetrating a pre-
determined percentage of the sample thickness (75%), 
retracted to the initial point of contact with the sample, and 
stopped for a set time period (2 s) before initiation of the 
second compression cycle. During the test, the force of the 
sample was recorded every 0.01 s and plotted on a force-
time plot (de Huidobro et al., 2005). The force-time data 
from each test were recorded, and at least 6 tests were used 
to calculate the mean values for the TPA parameters of each 
sample. Hardness, cohesiveness, springiness, gumminess 
and chewiness were calculated following the standard </p>

<p>procedure (Bourne, 1978; Honikel, 1998). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Statistical analysis was performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical 
Analysis System</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS</rs>, 2013). Descriptive statistics for the 
sensory evaluation, WBS, and TPA parameters were 
calculated using the MEAN procedure. The Pearson 
correlation coefficients between sensory evaluation and the 
instrumental measurements were determined using the 
CORR procedure. To establish regression models for 
sensory evaluation variables, the WBS and TPA parameters 
were used as independent variables in the REG procedure. 
A stepwise procedure was used to estimate the percentage 
of variation in sensory evaluation that was explained by the 
instrumental measurements. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Sensory evaluation and instrumental measurements of 
pork loin tenderness 
WBS had the highest coefficient of variation (31.48%) 
of all the variables measured (Table 2). For the sensory 
evaluation variables, variation ranged from 10.68% for the 
amount of perceptible residue to 23.60% for initial 
tenderness, while for the TPA parameters, hardness, 
gumminess, and chewiness had high coefficients of 
variation (18.19%, 24.80%, and 22.16%, respectively). 
Other studies have shown similar results for beef tenderness 
(Caine et al., 2003; de Huidobro et al., 2005), with high 
coefficients of variation for WBS and the TPA-hardness and 
chewiness. On the other hand, in the present study, the TPA-
cohesiveness and springiness had lower coefficients of 
variation compared to other variables, consistent with the 
results of the previous study (Caine et al., 2003). 
The overall feeling of tenderness on the palate involves </p>

<p>Table 2. Descriptive statistics for sensory evaluation and instrumental measurements of pork loin tenderness (n = 380) 
Mean±SD 
Minimum 
Maximum 
CV 
Sensory evaluation 
Softness 
2.89±0.60 
1.03 
4.70 
20.76 
Initial tenderness 
2.76±0.65 
1.00 
4.23 
23.60 
Chewiness 
2.88±0.59 
1.03 
4.48 
20.61 
Rate of breakdown 
2.78±0.52 
1.13 
4.17 
18.84 
Amount of perceptible residue 
3.27±0.35 
2.20 
4.21 
10.68 
Juiciness 
2.90±0.53 
1.50 
4.23 
18.29 
Mouth coating 
2.74±0.31 
1.83 
3.60 
11.17 
WBS (N) 
51.58±16.2 
22.47 
113.8 
31.48 
TPA parameters 
Hardness (N) 
29.54±5.37 
17.25 
46.45 
18.19 
Cohesiveness 
0.45±0.04 
0.26 
0.61 
9.16 
Springiness 
0.92±0.09 
0.55 
1.36 
9.68 
Gumminess 
13.56±3.36 
5.87 
24.20 
24.80 
Chewiness 
12.46±2.76 
5.82 
24.34 
22.16 </p>

<p>SD, standard deviation; CV, coefficient of variation; WBS, Warner-Bratzler shear force; TPA, texture profile analysis. </p>

<p>Choe et al. (2016) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 29:1029-1036 </p>



<p>three aspects: i) the initial ease of dental penetration of the 
meat, ii) the ease with which the meat breaks into fragments, 
and iii) the amount of residue remaining after chewing 
(Lawrie and Ledward, 2006). Of the sensory evaluation 
variables measured in this study, softness and initial 
tenderness were associated with the first aspect, chewiness 
and rate of breakdown with the second, and the amount of 
perceptible residue with the third. Juiciness and mouth 
coating were also assessed by the trained panelists, both of 
which could influence sensory tenderness by softening the 
meat during chewing (Aberle, 2001). In general, juiciness 
has two organoleptic components: i) the impression of 
wetness during initial chews due to the rapid release of meat 
fluid and ii) sustained juiciness due to the stimulatory effect 
of fat on salivation (Lawrie and Ledward, 2006). Thus, 
trained panelists scored pork loin tenderness both directly 
(softness, initial tenderness, chewiness, rate of breakdown, 
and amount of perceptible residue) and indirectly (juiciness 
and mouth coating) in the present study. </p>

<p>Relationship between sensory evaluation and 
instrumental measurements of pork loin 
WBS was significantly correlated with the sensory 
evaluation variables directly related to pork loin tenderness: 
softness, initial tenderness, chewiness, and rate of 
breakdown (Table 3). However, there was no significant 
correlation between WBS and juiciness or mouth coating, 
both indirect sensory measures of tenderness. In contrast, </p>

<p>the TPA-hardness, gumminess, and chewiness were 
significantly related to both the direct and indirect sensory 
evaluation variables of tenderness. However, the TPA-
springiness had no significant relationship with any sensory 
evaluation variable. Similar results have been observed in 
other research on beef (Caine et al., 2003; de Huidobro et 
al., 2005). For example, WBS and the TPA-hardness and 
chewiness were found to be significantly correlated with the 
sensory tenderness evaluation of beef rib steak, though not 
with juiciness or flavor (Caine et al., 2003). 
WBS produced significant regression models for the 
sensory variables softness, initial tenderness, chewiness and 
rate of breakdown (Table 4) but could not predict 
perceptible residue, juiciness or mouth coating. Although 
the regression models were significant, their regression 
coefficients were remarkably low (from 0.031 for sensory 
softness to 0.072 for sensory chewiness). Stepwise analysis 
using the TPA parameters resulted in significant regression 
models for all sensory evaluation variables (Table 5). The 
TPA-hardness, cohesiveness and springiness were selected 
to predict the sensory evaluation of pork loin tenderness; in 
particular, every regression model included hardness. These 
results were similar to the study on beef tenderness in 
which WBS predicted only those sensory variables directly 
related to beef tenderness (hardness and number of 
chewings), but TPA parameters predicted both the direct 
sensory tenderness variables and sensory juiciness (de 
Huidobro et al., 2005). </p>

<p>Table 3. Correlations between sensory evaluation and instrumental measurements of pork loin tenderness (n = 380) </p>

<p>WBS 
TPA 
Hardness 
Cohesiveness 
Springiness 
Gumminess 
Chewiness 
Softness 
-0.18*** 
-0.39*** 
-0.19*** 
0.07 
-0.36*** 
-0.36*** 
Initial tenderness 
-0.23*** 
-0.41*** 
-0.18*** 
0.04 
-0.37*** 
-0.38*** 
Chewiness 
-0.27*** 
-0.43*** 
-0.21*** 
0.10 
-0.40*** 
-0.39*** 
Rate of breakdown 
-0.26*** 
-0.39*** 
-0.21*** 
0.08 
-0.37*** 
-0.26*** 
Amount of perceptible residue 
-0.02 
0.26*** 
0.17** 
-0.10 
0.26*** 
0.24*** 
Juiciness 
0.10 
-0.15** 
0.01 
-0.07 
-0.12* 
-0.15** 
Mouth coating 
-0.02 
-0.23*** 
-0.05 
-0.02 
-0.19*** 
-0.22*** </p>

<p>WBS, Warner-Bratzler shear force; TPA, texture profile analysis. 
Levels of significance: * p&lt;0.05, ** p&lt;0.01, *** p&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>Table 4. Regression models of sensory evaluation for pork loin tenderness using WBS (n = 380) </p>

<p>Regression models 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Significance 
Softness = 3.226 (0.102)-0.007 (0.002)×WBS 
0.031 
*** 
Initial tenderness = 3.221 (0.109)-0.009 (0.002)×WBS 
0.051 
*** 
Chewiness = 3.390 (0.099)-0.010 (0.002)×WBS 
0.072 
*** 
Rate of breakdown = 3.221 (0.087)-0.008 (0.002)×WBS 
0.069 
*** 
Amount of perceptible residue = 3.225 (0.060)-0.000 (0.001)×WBS 
0.001 
NS 
Juiciness = 2.728 (0.091)+0.003 (0.002)×WBS 
0.010 
NS 
Mouth coating = 2.765 (0.053)-0.000 (0.000)×WBS 
0.000 
NS </p>

<p>WBS, Warner-Bratzler shear force. 
Values in parenthesis are the standard error of the estimate for the corresponding regression coefficients 
Levels of significance: NS, not significant; *** p&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>Choe et al. (2016) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 29:1029-1036 </p>

<p>
Stepwise regression analysis was also performed to 
estimate the proportion of variation in the sensory 
evaluation of pork loin tenderness explained by both WBS 
and TPA parameters (Table 6). The TPA-hardness was 
selected in all regression models, accounting for over 15% 
of the variation in sensory softness, initial tenderness, 
chewiness, and rate of breakdown. However, the WBS and 
TPA parameters explained less 10% of variation in the 
amount of perceptible residue, juiciness, and mouth coating. 
Other studies have reported much stronger coefficients of 
correlation and regression between sensory evaluation 
variables and instrumental measurements (Caine et al., 2003; 
de Huidobro et al., 2005). For instance, WBS explained 
approximately 36% of the variation in initial tenderness and 
overall tenderness, and the TPA-hardness and adhesiveness 
accounted for over 46% of the variability in the sensory 
tenderness of beef rib steak (Caine et al., 2003). In another 
study, WBS and TPA parameters explained approximately 
9% and 23%, respectively, of the variation in the sensory 
hardness of cooked beef loin, although the regression 
coefficients were relatively low (de Huidobro et al., 2005). 
The weak relationship between sensory evaluation and 
instrumental measurements of meat tenderness is generally 
accepted. There may be four possible reasons for this </p>

<p>observation (Warriss, 2010). The first is the lack of 
precision arising from the use of sensory panelists because 
of the subjective nature of the measurements, e.g., differing 
scales of perception for tenderness. In this study, pork loin 
tenderness was assessed by trained panelists capable of 
producing consistent and reproducible data, and thus there 
were no significant differences between panelists when the 
same samples were assessed by trained panelists, and 
between the same sample when the same sample was 
assessed by the same panelists. 
The second explanation is the confounding effect of 
juiciness on meat tenderness (Warriss, 2010). Perception of 
meat tenderness by consumers is a complex interaction of 
physical and sensory (e.g. juiciness) processing during 
mastication (Jeremiah, 1982; Caine et al., 2003; Warriss, 
2010). But juiciness, regardless of whether it is the result of 
the release of meat fluid during chewing or the stimulatory 
effect of fat on salivation, is difficult to measure using 
instrumental methods. Although TPA parameters were 
associated with sensory juiciness both in this study and in 
another study (de Huidobro et al., 2005), difficulty to 
measure effect of the juiciness on meat tenderness may be 
the reason for the weak relationship between the sensory 
evaluation and instrumental measurement of pork loin </p>

<p>Table 6. Proportion of variation in sensory evaluation of pork loin tenderness explained by WBS and TPA parameters using stepwise 
regression (n = 380) 
Sensory evaluation 
Soft 
IT 
Chew 
Break 
Residue 
Juiciness 
Coating 
WBS 
0.5 
1.2 
4.3 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>TPA parameters 
Hardness 
15.1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>*** 
16.9*** 
18.5*** 
15.6*** 
6.6*** 
2.4** 
5.2*** 
Cohesiveness 
0.5 
Springiness 
1.2 
1.3* 
1.0* 
Gumminess 
Chewiness 
Cumulative contribution 
15.1 
18.1 
18.5 
16.1 
7.8 
8.0 
7.9 </p>

<p>WBS, Warner-Bratzler shear force; TPA, Texture profile analysis; Soft, softness; IT, initial tenderness; Chew, chewiness; Break, rate of breakdown; 
Residue, amount of perceptible residue; Coating, mouth coating. 
1 Percentage of partial R 
2 . 
Levels of significance: * p&lt;0.05, ** p&lt;0.01, *** p&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>Table 5. Regression models of sensory evaluation for pork loin tenderness using TPA parameters (n = 380) </p>

<p>Regression models 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Significance 
Softness = 4.171 (0.160)-0.043 (0.005)×Hardness 
0.151 
*** 
Initial tenderness = 5.112 (0.425)-0.054 (0.006)×Hardness-0.822 (0.360)×Springiness 
0.180 
*** 
Chewiness = 4.287 (0.155)-0.048 (0.005)×Hardness 
0.185 
*** 
Rate of breakdown = 3.922 (0.139)-0.039 (0.005)×Hardness 
0.156 
*** 
Amount of perceptible residue = 2.774 (0.097)+0.017 (0.003)×Hardness 
0.066 
*** 
Juiciness = 3.644 (0.482)-0.025 (0.006)×Hardness+1.445 (0.787)×Cohesiveness 
-0.706 (0.320)×Springiness </p>

<p>0.048 
*** </p>

<p>Mouth coating = 3.252 (0.276)-0.018 (0.004)×Hardness+0.760 (0.450)×Cohesiveness 
-0.343 (0.183)×Springiness </p>

<p>0.070 
*** </p>

<p>TPA, texture profile analysis. Levels of significance: *** p&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>Choe et al. (2016) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 29:1029-1036 </p>



<p>tenderness. 
The third reason for the weak relationship between 
sensory evaluation and instrumental measurements could be 
related to variation in the cooking methods, cooking 
temperature, and holding temperature before testing 
(Warriss, 2010). In the present study, the samples used for 
sensory evaluation were cooked in a humid oven at 180°C, 
whereas samples for the instrumental measurements were 
cooked in boiling water. Cooking methods using water 
exhibit higher cooking loss and WBS values compared to 
the other cooking methods (Dzudie et al., 2000; Huff-
Lonergan et al., 2002; Obuz et al., 2003). Moreover, higher 
cooking temperatures are known to result in also higher 
cooking loss (less juiciness) and tougher meat (Aaslying et 
al., 2003; Obuz et al., 2003; Combes et al., 2004). In terms 
of holding temperature, it was reported that variation 
between sensory evaluation and objective measurements 
may be minimized if the instrumental measurements are 
performed immediately after cooking (Caine et al., 2003). 
For example, higher holding temperatures after cooking on 
a belt grill resulted in higher cooking loss and less tender 
beef (Obuz et al., 2003). That is, the cooking procedure may 
be related to the second explanation, with different cooking 
procedure resulting in different water loss and succulence. 
However, as mentioned above, instrumental methods cannot 
take into account succulence. This combine effect of 
cooking procedure and instrumental limitation may be 
account for low correlation between sensory and 
instrumental measurements in this study. 
Lastly, variation among longitudinal location of pork 
loin may be the reason of the weak correlations between 
sensory evaluation and instrumental measurements in this 
study. There were significant variation in sensory quality 
between the location of pork loin, with mid-loin part being 
suitable as reference for meat quality assessment (van 
Oeckel and Warnants, 2003). The other study also pointed 
out that variation between longitudinal location must be 
considered when designing sensory evaluation of pork loin 
(Hansen et al., 2004). In this study, samples for each 
measurements were taken from different longitudinal 
location of loin. This sampling procedure can minimize the 
variation between muscle samples, but the variation 
between different measurements in a muscle sample cannot 
be reduced. 
Although instrumental measurements accounted for 
only a small proportion of the variation in the sensory 
evaluation of pork loin tenderness in this study, it was found 
that the TPA parameters may have a more robust 
relationship with sensory tenderness evaluation than did 
WBS (Caine et al., 2003; de Huidobro et al., 2005). To 
imitate the mastication process, the probe halts and retracts 
prior to penetrating the last 25% of the sample thickness 
during TPA measurement (de Huidobro et al., 2005). 
However, the shear device used to measure WBS </p>

<p>completely severs each sample. That is why the data 
dispersion of the TPA parameters was lower than that of 
WBS, and similar to that of the sensory evaluation variables, 
an outcome that is in agreement with other studies (Caine et 
al., 2003; de Huidobro et al., 2005) and which may also 
explain the closer relationship between the TPA parameters 
and the sensory variables. 
Based on the results of this study, TPA measurement 
could be considered a better indicator of the sensory 
evaluation of pork loin tenderness compared to WBS 
measurement, with the TPA parameter hardness likely to 
prove particularly useful. However, neither WBS nor TPA 
measurements could explain a significant proportion of the 
variation in the sensory evaluation of pork loin tenderness. 
Therefore, sensory evaluation should be conducted to 
investigate practical pork tenderness perceived by consumer. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>We certify that there is no conflict of interest with any 
financial organization regarding the material discussed in 
the manuscript. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This research was supported by a grant from Korea 
University. The authors would like to appreciate the 
Institute of Biomedical Science and Food Safety, the Korea 
University Food Safety Hall, for providing equipment and 
facilities. </p>



<p>Choe et al. (2016) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 29:1029-1036 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>