<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4559775" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: To assess the value of applying MultiVane to liver T2-weighted imaging (T2WI) compared with conventional 
T2WIs with emphasis on detection of focal liver lesions. 
Materials and Methods: Seventy-eight patients (43 men and 35 women) with 86 hepatic lesions and 20 pancreatico-biliary 
diseases underwent MRI including T2WIs acquired using breath-hold (BH), respiratory-triggered (RT), and MultiVane 
technique at 3T. Two reviewers evaluated each T2WI with respect to artefacts, organ sharpness, and conspicuity of 
intrahepatic vessels, hilar duct, and main lesion using five-point scales, and made pairwise comparisons between T2WI 
sequences for these categories. Diagnostic accuracy (Az) and sensitivity for hepatic lesion detection were evaluated using 
alternative free-response receiver operating characteristic analysis. 
Results: MultiVane T2WI was significantly better than BH-T2WI or RT-T2WI for organ sharpness and conspicuity of 
intrahepatic vessels and main lesion in both separate reviews and pairwise comparisons (p &lt; 0.001). With regard to motion 
artefacts, MultiVane T2WI or BH-T2WI was better than RT-T2WI (p &lt; 0.001). Conspicuity of hilar duct was better with BH-
T2WI than with MultiVane T2WI (p = 0.030) or RT-T2WI (p &lt; 0.001). For detection of 86 hepatic lesions, sensitivity (mean, 
97.7%) of MultiVane T2WI was significantly higher than that of BH-T2WI (mean, 89.5%) (p = 0.008) or RT-T2WI (mean, 
84.9%) (p = 0.001). 
Conclusion: Applying the MultiVane technique to T2WI of the liver is a promising approach to improving image quality that 
results in increased detection of focal liver lesions compared with conventional T2WI. 
Liver magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) has an 
advantage over other liver imaging modalities because 
it provides multiparametric information by combining a 
variety of contrast agents such as conventional gadolinium 
chelates and tissue-targeted agents as well as baseline 
or novel sequences such as diffusion-weighted imaging. 
Although gadolinium-enhanced T1-weighted imaging 
(T1WI) has been a mainstay for liver MRI, T2-weighted 
imaging (T2WI) is still considered to be an essential </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3348/kjr.2015.16.5.1038 </p>

<p>pISSN 1229-6929 · eISSN 2005-8330 </p>

<p>Original Article | Gastrointestinal Imaging </p>

<p>Received October 27, 2014; accepted after revision May 22, 2015. 
Corresponding author: Young Kon Kim, MD, PhD, Department 
of Radiology and Center for Imaging Science, Samsung Medical 
Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, 81 Irwon-ro, 
Gangnam-gu, Seoul 06351, Korea. 
• Tel: (822) 3410-6438 • Fax: (822) 3410-0049 
• E-mail: jmyr@dreamwiz.com 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits 
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in 
any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>



<p>T2-Weighted Liver MRI </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 16(5), Sep/Oct 2015 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study Sample 
Our retrospective study had Institutional Review Board 
approval, and informed consent was waived. From July 2013 
to November 2013, 78 patients (43 men and 35 women; age 
range, 33-80 years; mean age, 57 years) with suspected 
pathology in the liver and pancreatico-biliary system 
based on clinical and laboratory findings underwent upper 
abdominal MRI including T2WI acquired using MultiVane 
technique. Of the 78 patients, 58 had focal liver lesions as 
follows: 23 had 35 hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) (size 
range, 0.8-9 cm), 15 had 18 hemangioma (size range, 0.6-
3.0 cm), 12 had 25 metastases from colorectal cancer (size 
range, 0.5-3.5 cm), four had four abscesses (size range, 
1.5-4.5 cm), three had three masses forming intrahepatic 
cholangiocarcinoma (size range, 3.5-5.5 cm), and one had 
focal nodular hyperplasia (size 10 cm). The remaining 20 
patients had pancreatic cystic lesions including intraductal 
papillary mucinous neoplasm (n = 12) and serous cystic 
neoplasm (n = 1), common bile duct stone (n = 4), and 
pancreatic ducal adenocarcinoma (n = 3). All 23 patients 
with HCCs and one patient with cholangiocarcinoma had 
liver cirrhosis or chronic hepatitis associated with viral 
hepatitis B (n = 21) and viral hepatitis C (n = 3). The 
remaining patients had no underlying chronic liver disease. 
The diagnosis of HCC was confirmed by histopathological 
findings of surgical specimens for seven patients (10 HCCs) 
and non-invasive criteria for HCC in the remaining HCCs as 
they showed arterial hypervascularization and early wash-
out on both four-phase computed tomography and MRI (18). 
The confirmation of liver metastases was based on surgical 
resection in four patients, or a combined interpretation of 
all imaging modalities including follow-up multidetector CT 
or MRI in the remaining eight. Three cholangiocarcinomas, 
four pancreatic adenocarcinomas, four pancreatic cystic 
tumours, and one focal nodular hyperplasia were diagnosed 
by surgery. The diagnosis of hemangioma and pancreatic 
cystic lesions were based on their typical imaging finding. </p>

<p>MR Examination 
All MRIs were acquired using a 3T whole-body MR system 
(Ingenia, Philips Healthcare, Best, the Netherlands) 
equipped with a dual-source parallel radiofrequency 
transmission system and quadrature body coil. The baseline 
MRIs included a T1-weighted turbo field-echo in-phase and 
opposed sequence (repetition time [TR]/first echo time </p>

<p>component of the liver MRI protocol because it is useful 
for differentiation between solid and non-solid masses, 
specific tumour diagnosis, and assessment of biliary disease 
(1-4). Technologic innovations, such as improved MRI 
gradient performance, multichannel surface receiver coils, 
parallel imaging techniques, and improved fat suppression 
schemes, have enabled high-quality T2WI of the liver to be 
obtained using breath-holding or respiratory triggering (5, 
6). Nevertheless, a limiting factor of liver T2WI is artefacts 
caused by respiratory motion or other patient motion, even 
during suspended respiration or respiratory triggering. 
The standard T2WI is based on a turbo-spin-echo (TSE) 
sequence with a Cartesian k-space sampling. For T2WI free 
from motion artefacts, modifications to the basic protocol 
may include the addition of free-breathing sequences, 
respiratory-gating, and motion correction techniques (i.e., 
BLADE, PROPELLER, or radial acquisition of k-space) (7-
14). Periodically rotated overlapping parallel lines with 
enhanced reconstruction (PROPELLER [General Electric 
Medical Systems, Milwaukee, WI, USA] or BLADE [Siemens 
Medical Systems, Erlangen, Germany]) or MultiVane (Philips 
Healthcare, Best, the Netherlands) is a technique that 
employs multiple data acquisition at the k-space center 
for the correction of in-plane motion by matching low-
resolution images reconstructed from each set of echo 
train segments (10, 13). MultiVane is a recently introduced 
motion correction technique that is similar to the 
PROPELLER technique (13) using rotating blades in the 
k-space, which makes it possible to detect in-plane motion 
that affects the low frequency in the center of k-space and 
correct in-plane motion for each blade to reduce motion 
effects in the images. 
Several prior studies have shown that application of the 
PROPELLER or BLADE technique to liver imaging at 1.5T or 
3T, resulted in improved image quality and lesion detection 
(15-17). However, no study with a large case series has 
proven sensitivity or accuracy with liver T2WI using such 
techniques superior to that of conventional T2WI at 3T 
for detection of focal liver lesions. Because applying the 
PROPELLER technique is time-consuming, determining its 
real benefits, including lesion detectability, compared to 
conventional techniques is clinically relevant. Therefore, we 
undertook this study to assess the value of MultiVane T2WI 
compared with conventional T2WIs in the evaluation of the 
liver with emphasis on detection of focal liver lesions. </p>



<p>Kang et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 16(5), Sep/Oct 2015 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>[TE], second TE, 3.5 msec/1.13 msec [in-phase], 2.3 msec 
[opposed-phase]; flip angle, 10°; matrix size, 256 x 194; 
bandwidth, 1785.7 Hz/pixel). The gadoxetic acid-enhanced 
imaging that consisted of unenhanced, arterial-phase (20-35 
seconds), portal-phase (60 seconds), 3-minute late-phase, 
and 20-minute hepatobiliary images were obtained using a 
T1-weighted three-dimensional turbo-field-echo sequence 
(enhanced T1 high-resolution isotropic volume examination; 
eTHRIVE, Philips Healthcare) (TR/TE, 3.1 msec/1.5 msec; 
flip angle, 10°; matrix size, 256 x 256; bandwidth, 724.1 
Hz/pixel; 2-mm section thickness). The contrast agent was 
automatically administered intravenously at a rate of 1 mL/ 
sec for a dose of 0.025 mmol/kg body weight using a power 
injector, followed by a 20-mL saline flush. 
Three T2WIs were successively acquired during the long 
interval between the dynamic phases and the 20-minute 
hepatobiliary phase images (at approximately 7 minutes 
after administration of the contrast agent) to shorten 
the image acquisition time. The T2WI protocol was as 
follows: 1) breath-hold multi-shot T2-weighted sequence 
(TR/TE, 1037 msec/80 msec; flip angle, 90°; matrix size, 
324 x 235; reconstructed matrix size, 384 x 384; TSE 
factor, 14; acceleration factor of 2; half scan factor, 0.6; 
maximum slices per breath hold, 10; acquisition time, 1 
minute 8 seconds); 2) a respiratory-triggered multi-shot 
T2-weighted sequence (TR/TE, 1037 msec/80 msec; flip 
angle, 90°; matrix size, 376 x 270; reconstructed matrix 
size, 382 x 378; TSE factor, 82; acceleration factor of 4; 
half scan factor, 0.6; acquisition time, 3 minutes); and 
3) MultiVane T2WI with respiratory triggering (TR/TE, 
1554 msec/103 msec; flip angle, 90°; matrix size, 304 x 
304; reconstructed matrix size, 319 x 319; TSE factor, 32; 
MultiVane percentage, 230%; acquisition time, 6 minutes 30 
seconds), with a 5-mm section thickness, no intersection 
gap, and a field of view of 32-38 cm. Since motion in the 
liver is expected to appear through plane motion in axial 
imaging, gross motion correction was not applied in order 
to shorten examination time. The fat suppression technique 
was a spectral attenuated inversion recovery technique for 
RT-T2WI and spectral presaturation with inversion recovery 
for BH-T2WI and MultiVane T2WI. </p>

<p>Image Analysis 
Assessments of all three T2WIs were performed in 
a blinded fashion by consensus of two readers with 4 
years and 14 years of experience in abdominal MRI. Both 
reviewers were unaware of the sequence parameters and </p>

<p>patient information. Adjustment of the window level and 
width was allowed during the qualitative assessment. At 
the first reading session, three T2WIs were reviewed by 
consensus of two reviewers with regard to respiratory 
motion artefact, anatomic sharpness of upper abdominal 
organ margin (liver, gallbladder, and pancreas), conspicuity 
of intrahepatic vessels (portal vein and hepatic vein) 
and hilar bile duct (first and second order branch), and 
conspicuity of main lesion on each patient using a five-
point evaluation scale system in which 1 = unacceptable, 
2 = poor, 3 = fair, 4 = good, and 5 = excellent. For patients 
with multiple lesions, the study coordinator, who was not 
involved in image interpretation, assigned the smallest 
lesion as the target lesion prior to image review. Each 
review was performed on three separate days separated by 
at least 2 weeks. 
After reviewing individual T2WIs, each reader 
independently reviewed T2WIs side-by-side for each patient 
for pairwise comparison followed by joint evaluation until 
a consensus was reached on the results. In total, 234 T2WI 
scans were classified into 156 pairs of MultiVane T2WI 
versus BH-T2WI or MultiVane T2WI versus RT-T2WI in which 
MultiVane T2WI was the control image. Two image sets 
were displayed side by side, and evaluation was performed 
by direct comparison. The readers assessed the image sets 
by considering five aspects: motion artefact, anatomic 
sharpness of organ margin, conspicuity of intrahepatic 
vessels, conspicuity of hilar bile duct, and conspicuity 
of main lesion. A semi-quantitative five-point scale (1 
= inferior [impairing diagnosis], 2 = slightly inferior [no 
influence on diagnosis], 3 = equal, 4 = slightly superior 
[no influence on diagnosis], and 5 = superior [easing 
diagnosis]) (19). In addition, in patients with focal liver 
lesions, the observers recorded the possibility of a hepatic 
lesion by assigning each lesion a confidence level, based 
on a 4-point scale as follows: 1 = probably not a lesion, 
2 = possibly not a lesion, 3 = probably a lesion, and 4 = 
definitely a lesion. Lesions not detected on MRI were given 
a rating of 0. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
Statistical analyses were performed using statistical 
software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, 
USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 9.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, 
USA). Subjective image ratings for each image were 
compared using the Friedman test. Dunn's multiple-
comparisons test was used as the post-hoc test. The </p>



<p>T2-Weighted Liver MRI </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 16(5), Sep/Oct 2015 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>pairwise comparisons were performed using the Wilcoxon 
test corrected for multiple comparisons according to the 
Bonferroni adjustment. The diagnostic accuracy of each 
pulse sequence for the detection of focal hepatic lesions 
was determined using an alternative free-response receiver 
operator characteristic (ROC) curve analysis on a lesion-by-
lesion basis. Considering the possible influence of lesion 
clustering on the diagnostic accuracy, nonparameric analysis 
of clustered ROC curve data was performed by using the 
method proposed by Obuchowski (20). The sensitivity for 
each set of images was evaluated according to the number 
of lesions assigned confidence levels of 3 or 4 from among 
the 86 liver lesions. We used our own method (21) for 
comparing sensitivity, specificity, and positive predictive 
value. A p value &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. The </p>

<p>kappa statistic for two observers was calculated to assess 
the inter-observer agreement regarding pairwise comparison 
between T2WIs. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Individual Analysis for Each T2WI 
Table 1 summarises the results of consensus review for 
motion artefact; anatomic sharpness of organs margin; and 
conspicuity of intrahepatic vessels, hilar bile duct, and 
main lesion for the three different T2WI sequences. There 
were significant differences among the three sequences for 
all categories (p &lt; 0.001). With regard to the severity of 
motion artefacts, MultiVane T2WI or BH-T2WI was better 
than RT-T2WI (p &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 1). The mean value for </p>

<p>Table 1. Results of Subjective Image Analysis Using Five-Point Evaluation Scale System for Each MRI Sequence </p>

<p>Artefact 
Organ Sharpness 
Vessel Conspicuity Hilar Duct Conspicuity Lesion Conspicuity 
BH-T2WI 
4.92 ± 0.31 
4.65 ± 0.66 
4.44 ± 0.68 
4.91 ± 0.37 
4.54 ± 0.99 
RT-T2WI 
4.08 ± 0.99 
4.33 ± 0.66 
4.62 ± 0.67 
4.42 ± 0.85 
4.58 ± 0.95 
MultiVane T2WI 
4.95 ± 0.22 
4.95 ± 0.22 
4.92 ± 0.27 
4.77 ± 0.45 
4.92 ± 0.48 
P value 
&lt; 0.001* , ‡ , 0.570  † 
&lt; 0.001* , †, ‡ 
0.070*, &lt; 0.001  †, ‡ 
&lt; 0.001* , ‡ , 0.030  † 
0.550*, 0.001  †, ‡ </p>

<p>Data represents mean values ± 1SD. *P values are BH-T2WI and RT-T2WI,  † BH-T2WI and MultiVane T2WI,  ‡ RT-T2WI and MultiVane T2WI. BH-
T2WI = breath-hold multi-shot T2-weighted image, RT-T2WI = respiratory-triggered multi-shot T2-weighted image, SD = standard deviation </p>

<p>Fig. 1. 57-year-old man diagnosed with colon cancer with liver metastasis. </p>

<p>Small two liver metastases (0.3−0.4 cm in diameter) are indistinct on breath-hold T2-weighted image (A) and respiratory-triggered T2-weighted 
image (B), but are clearly seen on MultiVane T2-weighted image (arrows) (C). Severe motion artefact is noted in (B). </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Breath-hold T2-weighted image (A), respiratory-triggered T2-weighted image (B), and MultiVane T2-weighted image (C) 
in 36-year-old man. Sharpness of pancreas margin was considered to be better with (C) than with (A) or (B). </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>



<p>Kang et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 16(5), Sep/Oct 2015 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>the subjective assignment of anatomic sharpness of upper 
abdominal organ margin was highest in MultiVane T2WI 
(4.95), followed by BH-T2WI (4.65) and RT-T2WI (4.33), 
with a significant difference among the sequences (p &lt; 
0.001). The conspicuity of intrahepatic vessels and the main 
lesion was significantly better with MultiVane T2WI than 
with BH-T2WI or RT-T2WI (p &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 2). Meanwhile, 
the mean value for conspicuity of hilar duct was highest 
in BH-T2WI (4.91), followed by MultiVane T2WI (4.77) and 
RT-T2WI (4.42), with a significant difference among the 
sequences (p &lt; 0.001 or p = 0.030). </p>

<p>Pairwise Comparison between MultiVane T2WI and BH-
or RT-T2WI 
In pairwise comparisons between MultiVane T2WI and 
BH-T2WI or RT-T2WI, the motion artefact of MultiVane T2WI 
was significantly lower than that of RT-T2WI (p &lt; 0.001) 
(Fig. 1), but there was no difference between MultiVane 
T2WI and BH-T2WI (p = 0.250) (Table 2). In terms of 
the anatomic sharpness of upper abdominal organs and 
conspicuity of intrahepatic vessels, MultiVane T2WI was 
significantly better than BH-T2WI or RT-T2WI (p &lt; 0.001) 
(Fig. 2). Similarly, for conspicuity of the main lesion, </p>

<p>MultiVane T2WI was significantly better than BH-T2WI 
or RT-T2WI (p &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 3). However, with regard to 
conspicuity of the hilar bile duct, BH-T2WI was significantly 
better than MultiVane T2WI (p = 0.005), and MultiVane 
T2WI was significantly better than RT-T2WI (p = 0.004). In 
pairwise comparison between MultiVane T2WI and BH-T2WI, 
two cases were judged as slightly inferior (score 2) with 
MultiVane T2WI compared with BH-T2WI for artefact, lesion 
conspicuity, and organ sharpness, and three cases had score 
2 for vessel conspicuity. In the remaining cases, MultiVane 
T2WI was judged as being better than or equivalent to 
BH-T2WI (score 3-5). In pairwise comparison between 
MultiVane T2WI and RT-T2WI, only one case was judged as 
slightly inferior (score 2) with MultiVane T2WI compared 
with RT-T2WI for organ sharpness and vessel conspicuity. 
For the remaining cases, MultiVane T2WI was judged as 
being better than or equivalent to RT-T2WI (score 3-5). </p>

<p>Hepatic Lesion Detection 
With regard to the detection of 86 hepatic lesions in 58 
patients, nonparametric analysis of clustered ROC data, 
sensitivity, and positive predictive value are summarised 
in Table 3. The Az value of MultiVane T2WI (mean, 0.977) </p>

<p>Table 2. Result of Pairwise Comparison among MRI Sequences </p>

<p>Artefact 
Organ Sharpness Vessel Conspicuity 
Hilar Duct 
Conspicuity 
Lesion Conspicuity </p>

<p>MultiVane T2WI 
-BH-T2WI </p>

<p>Mean 
3.06 
3.62 
3.46 
2.86 
3.31 
Median 
3.0 (2.0-5.00) 
4.0 (2.0-5.0) 
3.0 (2.0-5.0) 
3.0 (2.0-4.0) 
3.0 (2.0-5.0) 
P value 
0.250 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
0.005 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>MultiVane T2WI 
-RT-T2WI </p>

<p>Mean 
3.80 
3.46 
3.41 
3.13 
3.23 
Median 
3.0 (3.0-5.0) 
3.0 (2.0-5.0) 
3.0 (2.0-5.0) 
3.0 (3.0-5.0) 
3.0 (3.0-5.0) 
P value 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
&lt; 0.001 
0.004 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Numbers in parentheses represent range of scoring, respectively. BH-T2WI = breath-hold multi-shot T2-weighted image, RT-T2WI = 
respiratory-triggered multi-shot T2-weighted image </p>

<p>Fig. 3. 60-year-old man diagnosed with colon cancer with liver metastasis. </p>

<p>Small liver metastasis (0.3 cm in diameter) (arrows) is indistinct on breath-hold T2-weighted image (A) and respiratory-triggered T2-weighted 
image (B), however is clearly seen on MultiVane T2-weighted image (arrow) (C). Motion artefact is noted in (B). Conspicuity of intrahepatic 
portal vein and hepatic vein is better with (C) than with (A) or (B). </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>



<p>T2-Weighted Liver MRI </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 16(5), Sep/Oct 2015 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>was significantly higher than that of BH-T2WI (mean, 
0.570; p &lt; 0.001) for both observers. Among 86 focal liver 
lesions, MultiVane T2WI allowed detection of 85 lesions 
(98.8%) by observer 1 and 84 lesions (97.7%) by observer 2, 
whereas 78 (90.7%) and 77 lesions (89.5%) were detected 
with BH-T2WI, and 74 (86.1%) and 73 lesions (84.9%) 
were detected with RT-T2WI. Thus, in terms of sensitivity, 
MultiVane T2WI (mean, 97.7%) yielded a significantly </p>

<p>higher value than BH-T2WI (mean, 89.5%) (p = 0.008) or 
RT-T2WI (mean, 84.9%) (p = 0.001). One single HCC was 
not detected by all three T2WIs, even on retrospective 
reviewing. Seven lesions (2 HCCs and 5 metastases) were 
not verified by any observer on the BH-T2WI or RT-T2WI, 
but were clearly discerned on the MultiVane T2WI. One HCC 
(2.0 cm) and three metastases (0.5-1.0 cm) were not seen 
with BH-T2WI or RT-T2WI, even upon review (Fig. 4). Other </p>

<p>Table 3. Diagnostic Performance of Three T2-Weighted Images for Detection of 86 Focal Liver Lesions </p>

<p>BH-T2WI 
RT-T2WI 
MultiVane T2WI 
P </p>

<p>Az </p>

<p>Observer 1 
0.605 
0.861 
0.988 
0.305*, 0.128  † , &lt; 0.001  ‡ 
Observer 2 
0.570 
0.849 
0.977 
0.306*, 0.127  † , &lt; 0.001  ‡ 
Mean 
0.570 
0.849 
0.977 
0.306*, 0.127  † , &lt; 0.001  ‡ </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>Observer 1 
90.7% (78) 
86.0% (74) 
98.8% (85) 
0.045*, 0.008  † , 0.001  ‡ 
Observer 2 
89.5% (77) 
84.9% (73) 
97.7% (84) 
0.045*, 0.008  † , 0.001  ‡ 
Mean 
89.5% 
84.9% 
97.7% 
0.045*, 0.008  † , 0.001  ‡ </p>

<p>PPV </p>

<p>Observer 1 
98.7% [1] 
100.0% [0] 
100.0% [0] 
0.310*, 0.310  † 
Observer 2 
98.7% [1] 
100.0% [0] 
100.0% [0] 
0.310*, 0.310  † 
Mean 
98.7% 
100.0% 
100.0% 
0.310*, 0.310  † </p>

<p>P value was corrected by Bonferroni's method for multiple testing. Az values represent area under ROC curve. Numbers in parentheses and 
brackets represent number of true-and false-positive lesions, respectively. *P values are BH-T2WI and RT-T2WI,  † BH-T2WI and MultiVane 
T2WI,  ‡ RT-T2WI and MultiVane T2WI. BH-T2WI = breath-hold multi-shot T2-weighted image, PPV = positive predictive value, ROC = 
receiver operating characteristic, RT-T2WI = respiratory-triggered multi-shot T2-weighted image </p>

<p>Fig. 4. 59-year-old man with 2.2 cm-sized hepatocellular carcinoma. </p>

<p>Hepatic mass is not depicted on breath-hold T2-weighted image (A) and respiratory-triggered T2-weighted image (B), however is clearly seen as 
hyperintense (arrow) on MultiVane T2-weighted image (C). </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Table 4. Inter-Observer Agreements Regarding Pairwise Comparison between T2WIs </p>

<p>Category 
Pairwise Comparison 
Kappa Value </p>

<p>Motion artefact 
MultiVane T2WI vs. BH-T2WI 
0.731 
MultiVane T2WI vs. RT-T2WI 
0.870 </p>

<p>Anatomic sharpness of organs 
MultiVane T2WI vs. BH-T2WI 
0.874 
MultiVane T2WI vs. RT-T2WI 
0.654 </p>

<p>Conspicuity of intrahepatic vessels 
MultiVane T2WI vs. BH-T2WI 
0.729 
MultiVane T2WI vs. RT-T2WI 
0.672 </p>

<p>Conspicuity of hilar duct 
MultiVane T2WI vs. BH-T2WI 
0.842 
MultiVane T2WI vs. RT-T2WI 
0.899 </p>

<p>Conspicuity of main lesion 
MultiVane T2WI vs. BH-T2WI 
0.847 
MultiVane T2WI vs. RT-T2WI 
0.851 
BH-T2WI = breath-hold multi-shot T2-weighted image, RT-T2WI = respiratory-triggered multi-shot T2-weighted image </p>



<p>Kang et al. </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 16(5), Sep/Oct 2015 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>lesions were assigned as category 1 or 2 with BH-T2WI or 
RT-T2WI. There was one false positive lesion on BH-T2WI 
caused by motion artefact. 
The kappa values for two observers ranged from 0.654 
to 0.899 for the five MR categories, indicating good or 
excellent inter-observer agreement (Table 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>For the diagnosis of focal liver lesions, the two-fold 
requirement for liver imaging is to improve sensitivity for 
malignancy detection while maintaining high specificity by 
accurately characterising small hemangiomas or cysts that 
are frequently encountered in daily practice (4). As a result 
of this compelling need for high-quality T2WI, there has 
been a steady stream of investigations on T2WI sequences 
that show superiority in image quality and diagnostic 
performance for detecting focal liver lesions among various 
T2WIs (6, 7, 11, 12). 
Since single shot breath-hold techniques for liver T2WI 
has the disadvantage of relatively low spatial resolution 
and signal-to-noise ratio (SNR), we applied a multi-shot 
technique to BH-T2WI, resulting in an increased matrix 
size (324 x 235). Therefore, differences in matrix size were 
minimised among the three T2WIs for fair comparison. In 
the current study, MultiVane T2WI was significantly better 
than BH-T2WI with regard to anatomic sharpness of organ 
and conspicuity of intrahepatic vessels and main lesion in 
both separate reviews and pairwise comparison (p &lt; 0.05), 
although there was no significant difference in artefacts 
between the sequences. In pairwise comparison between 
MultiVane T2WI and BH-T2WI, only two cases were judged 
as slightly inferior (score 2) with MultiVane T2WI compared 
with BH-T2WI for artefact, lesion conspicuity, and organ 
sharpness and three cases were slightly inferior for vessel 
conspicuity. In the remaining cases, MultiVane T2WI was 
better than or equivalent to BH-T2WI. In comparison 
between MultiVane T2WI and RT-T2WI, MultiVane T2WI was 
significantly better than RT T2WI for all five categories, 
both in separate reviewing and pairwise comparison (p &lt; 
0.05). Only one case was judged as slightly inferior (score 
2) with MultiVane T2WI compared with RT-T2WI for organ 
sharpness and vessel conspicuity. In the remaining cases, 
MultiVane T2WI was better than or equivalent to RT-T2WI. 
Theoretical advantages of central k-space oversampling 
using BLADE, PROPELLER, or MultiVane is the reduction of 
artefacts associated with gross motion and a better SNR (8-</p>

<p>10, 13). However, motion of the upper abdomen is mainly 
through-plane motion from respiratory movement rather 
than in-plane motion that occurs in a rigid body such as the 
brain. Therefore, gross motion correction was not applied in 
our study. Nevertheless, our results showed the usefulness 
of applying MultiVane technique for high-quality liver T2WI, 
which are consistent with prior reports (8-10). 
Liver MRI is more vulnerable to artefacts than MRI 
for other organs because of the proximity of the liver to 
lung or the gastrointestinal tract, which hinders lesion 
detection. In addition, clear differentiation between tiny 
lesions and end-on views of vessels is problematic in T2WI 
with poor image quality. Thus, the results for qualitative 
analysis regarding liver lesion detection seem to be a 
more relevant indicator of image contrast and quality than 
quantitative analysis. With regard to the detection of 86 
hepatic lesions, the Az value and sensitivity of MultiVane 
T2WI were significantly higher than those of BH-T2WI or 
RT-T2WI for both observers (p &lt; 0.05). With the popular 
use of gadoxetic acid for liver MRI, the role of T2WI for 
lesion characterisation is being emphasised because early 
hepatocyte uptake of gadoxetic acid might cause false-
positive diagnosis of a small haemangioma as malignancy 
(22, 23). In this regard, our observations have clinical 
impact. In the aforementioned cases, BH-T2WI or RT-T2WI 
did not suffer from severe artefacts that hindered tumour 
detection. In addition to the benefit of artefact-free images 
in MultiVane T2WI, another possible reason for our findings 
is higher SNR and contrast-to-noise ratio (CNR) in MultiVane 
T2WI as a result of acquiring multiple data at the k-space 
centre, which is responsible for contrast resolution (15). 
However, we did not acquire quantitative results because 
there has been no perfect noise estimation given the use 
of parallel imaging for BH-or RT-T2WI and T2WIs were 
acquired after the administration of gadoxetic acid (24). 
With regard to the conspicuity of the hilar bile duct, 
BH-T2WI was significantly better than MultiVane T2WI 
(p = 0.005). Based on the above considerations, it is 
recommended to acquire both BH-T2WI, possibly as heavily 
T2WI, and MultiVane T2WI. However, the long acquisition 
time for MultiVane T2WI (mean, 6 minutes 30 seconds) may 
be a burden in a time-pressed environment. The MultiVane 
T2WI used in the current study was acquired with neither 
parallel imaging nor half scan and interleaved sampling. 
Further investigations with application of those techniques 
to MultiVane T2WI will be warranted to shorten image 
acquisition time while maintaining high image quality. In </p>



<p>T2-Weighted Liver MRI </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 16(5), Sep/Oct 2015 </p>

<p>kjronline.org </p>

<p>the gadoxetic acid-enhanced MRI protocol, introducing 
MultiVane T2WI during the long waiting time between early 
dynamic phases and the 20-minute hepatobiliary phase 
could be a reasonable approach to adopting a shortened 
protocol, because T2WIs acquired after administration 
of gadoxetic acid are reported to be comparable to pre-
contrast T2WIs in the detection and characterization of 
hepatic tumours (25-27). 
There are several limitations in our study that should be 
mentioned. First, owing to the retrospective study design, 
we acquired T2WIs during the interval between the dynamic 
images and the 20-minute hepatobiliary phase in order to 
shorten examination time. Given that signal intensity of 
the lesion or liver might be altered by T1-or T2 effects 
of administered gadoxetic acid (25, 28), a bias might 
be introduced to the conspicuity of the hepatic lesion. 
However, lesion-liver contrast on postcontrast T2WI is 
reportedly comparable to that on precontrast T2WI (25-28). 
Second, there was a minimal difference in matrix size among 
the three T2WIs. However, despite the fact that MultiVane 
T2WI had the lowest reconstructed matrix size, we achieved 
better results with MultiVane T2WI than the other two 
techniques. Third, although image review was performed in 
a blinded manner, an experienced on-site reviewer might 
recognize which technique was applied. Fourth, we did not 
attempt to adjust parameters to optimise MultiVane T2WI 
for the liver by multiple testing of MultiVane percentages to 
balance the trade-off between image quality and acquisition 
time. Fifth, as previously mentioned, we did not perform 
quantitative measurement for SNR and CNR because of 
variability in image acquisition techniques among the three 
T2WI sequences. In addition, as a result of the retrospective 
study design, we did not optimise conventional BH-T2WI or 
RT-T2WI to maximise SNR and CNR. 
In conclusion, application of the MultiVane technique 
to T2WI of the liver is a promising approach to improving 
image quality that leads to increased detection of focal 
liver lesions compared with conventional T2WIs. </p>







</text></tei>