<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4453642" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Controversy exists on whether urinary tract infection (UTI) is a risk factor for urinary bladder cancer (UBC). Here, the 
association is investigated using data from one of the largest bladder cancer case-control studies worldwide. </p>

<p>Methods: Information on (i) history and age at onset of regular cystitis ('regular low-UTI') and (ii) number and age at onset of UTI 
treated with antibiotics ('UTI-ab') from 1809 UBC patients and 4370 controls was analysed. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence 
intervals (CI) adjusted for age, education, smoking, and use of aspirin/ibuprofen were generated, for men and women separately. </p>

<p>Results: Regular low-UTI was associated with an increased UBC risk (men: OR (95% CI) 6.6 (4.2-11); women: 2.7 (2.0-3.5)), with 
stronger effects in muscle-invasive UBC. Statistically significant decreased risks (ORs B0.65) were observed for up to five UTI-ab, 
specifically in those who (had) smoked and experienced UTI-ab at a younger age. In women, UTI experienced after menopause 
was associated with a higher UBC risk, irrespective of the number of episodes. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Regular cystitis is positively associated with UBC risk. In contrast, a limited number of episodes of UTI treated with 
antibiotics is associated with decreased UBC risk, but not in never-smokers and postmenopausal women. </p>

<p>Urinary tract infections (UTIs) refer to the presence of microbial 
pathogens in the urethra or bladder (lower urinary tract), or ureter 
and pelvis of the kidney (upper urinary tract). In men, the prostate 
may be involved as well. UTIs are among the most prevalent 
infectious diseases with varying frequencies among sexes and age 
categories. About 80% of UTIs occur in women; it is estimated that 
40-50% of females experience at least one symptomatic UTI and 
that half of them will experience a recurrence within 1 year 
(Foxman, 2010; Salvatore et al, 2011). The majority of UTIs is </p>

<p>caused by E. coli and manifests as cystitis. Risk factors for 
(recurrent) UTI include obstruction of the urinary tract, use of a 
bladder catheter, a suppressed immune system, oestrogen defi-
ciency, a genetic predisposition, and sexual intercourse, and may 
differ between men and pre-and postmenopausal women 
(Foxman et al, 2000; Nicolle, 2002; Foxman, 2010; Salvatore 
et al, 2011). 
There is strong evidence linking infection of the bladder by 
Schistosoma haematobium, endemic in certain low-and middle-</p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr SH Vermeulen; E-mail: Sita.Vermeulen@radboudumc.nl </p>

<p>Received 25 July 2014; revised 27 October 2014; accepted 2 November 2014; published online 27 November 2014 </p>

<p>&amp; 2015 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/15 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: urinary bladder cancer; urothelial carcinoma; bladder infection; urinary tract infection </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2015) 112, 594-600 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2014.601 </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.601 </p>

<p>income countries but rare in high-income countries, and by spinal 
cord injury-related catheter use to squamous cell carcinoma of the 
bladder (IARC Working Group on the Evaluation of Carcinogenic 
Risks to Humans, 1994; Hess et al, 2003). However, whether 
common, recurrent UTIs are involved in the aetiology of urothelial 
carcinoma of the bladder remains unclear. Several epidemiological 
studies, most from the second half of the twentieth century and 
conducted in small populations, have investigated the association 
between episodes of (lower) UTI and the risk of urinary bladder 
cancer (UBC). The majority of these studies report increased UBC 
risks for any vs no UTI, in both men and women (Wynder et al, 
1963; Dunham et al, 1968; Howe et al, 1980; Kantor et al, 1984; 
Claude et al, 1986; La Vecchia et al, 1991; Kunze et al, 1992; 
Sturgeon et al, 1994; Jhamb et al 2007; Sun et al, 2013), whereas 
some do not support a positive association (Piper et al, 1986; Kjaer 
et al, 1989; González et al, 1991; Jiang et al, 2009). A few studies 
specifically address the number of UTI episodes or the duration 
between UTI and UBC diagnosis, the latter to prevent potential 
misclassification. Overall, positive associations tend to weaken as 
the time lag between UTI and UBC increases (González et al, 1991; 
La Vecchia et al, 1991; Sun et al, 2013) and the number of UTIs 
decreases (Kantor et al, 1984; La Vecchia et al, 1991). In contrast to 
these findings, Jhamb et al (2007) and Jiang et al (2009) report a 
decreased risk of UBC with an increasing number of kidney and 
bladder infections with the lowest risk for more than three episodes 
of infection. 
In this study, we analysed data of the Nijmegen Bladder 
Cancer Study (NBCS), one of the largest case-control studies for 
UBC worldwide, as to gain better insights into the role of 
recurrent infections of the (lower) urinary tract as a risk factor 
for UBC. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects and data extraction. Within the framework of the 
NBCS, UBC patients living in the catchment area of seven hospitals 
in the eastern part of the country were identified through the 
Netherlands Cancer Registry (NCR) held by the Comprehensive 
Cancer Centre the Netherlands (IKNL) (Kiemeney et al, 2008). 
Patients diagnosed in the periods 1995-2006, 2006-2007, 2007-2009, 
and 2009-2010 under the age of 76 years were batch-wise invited 
for participation. Participants were asked to fill out a questionnaire 
and donate a blood sample for DNA extraction. All patients had 
histologically confirmed carcinoma of the urinary bladder. Data on 
tumour characteristics were obtained via the NCR. The response 
rate to the questionnaire was 65%. 
Controls in the NBCS were individuals recruited for the 
Nijmegen Biomedical Study (NBS), a population-based survey 
that aimed to provide a generic reference group for case-control 
studies. The NBS was conducted by the Departments for Health 
Evidence and Clinical Chemistry of the Radboud University 
Medical Center, Nijmegen, The Netherlands. In 2002, 22 451 age-
and sex-stratified inhabitants were randomly selected from the 
demography registration of the municipality of Nijmegen and 
invited to fill out a questionnaire and donate a blood sample. The 
response rate to this first questionnaire was 43%, with a total of 
9350 participants (54% female). A second, third, and fourth 
questionnaire were sent out in 2005 (response rate 70%; n ¼ 5594), 
2008 (response rate 69%; n ¼ 5613), and 2012 (response rate 51%; 
n ¼ 3831), respectively. 
The study protocols of the NBCS and the NBS were approved by 
the Institutional Review Board of the Radboud University Medical 
Center, and all study subjects gave written informed consent 
(Kiemeney et al, 2008) (NBCS: http://icbc.cancer.gov/member-
ship.html; NBS: http://www.nijmegenbiomedischestudie.nl). </p>

<p>By means of the NBCS and NBS questionnaire(s), information 
on, among others, lifestyle, ethnicity, medical history, and family 
history, was collected from the patients and controls. Data on UTIs 
were retrieved via two questions: (i) Have you ever been diagnosed 
by a physician with regular bladder infections (for the remainder of 
this article abbreviated with regular low-UTI), and, if so, at what 
age? (ii) Have you ever had a urinary tract infection for which you 
were treated with antibiotics (abbreviated with UTI-ab) and, if so, 
how often (1-2, 3-5, 6-10, or 11 times or more) and at what age 
did you first have a UTI-ab? For patients, the latter question was 
specifically posed for the period up to 2 years prior to UBC 
diagnosis. For the NBS controls, data on regular low-UTI were 
obtained in 2005 and data on UTI-ab were obtained in 2008. We 
excluded those UTI-ab in controls that were reported to have 
occurred within 2 years prior to filling out the questionnaire. For 
regular low-UTI, those that occurred at or after age at UBC 
diagnosis for patients (and filling out the questionnaire for 
controls) were excluded. 
In addition, questionnaire data on highest education, ethnicity, 
smoking, and regular use during a minimum of 6 months of the 
non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs aspirin and ibuprofen/ 
brufen (prior to UBC diagnosis) were extracted. 
For this study, we selected UBC patients of self-reported 
Caucasian ethnicity and controls that filled out questionnaires 1-3 
(that contained information relevant for this study), had no prior 
history of bladder cancer at time of recruitment, and were of self-
reported Caucasian ethnicity. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Univariable and multivariable logistic regres-
sion analyses were used to evaluate the association between regular 
low-UTI and frequency of UTI-ab and bladder cancer risk. Odds 
ratios (ORs) and corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) 
were adjusted for the following, potentially confounding, factors: 
age at UBC diagnosis/at time of completing questionnaire (in 
years), smoking status (categorical variable: never smokers, former 
smokers, current smokers (i.e., those who had not stopped in the 
year prior to the year of UBC diagnosis (for patients) or filling out 
the questionnaire (for controls)), cumulative smoking exposure in 
terms of pack-years of cigarettes, use of aspirin and ibuprofen/ 
brufen (yes/no), and education (categorical variable). Additional 
analyses were conducted to determine whether the associations 
differed for non-muscle invasive and muscle-invasive bladder 
cancer, age at onset of UTI (below or above sex-specific median 
age), menopausal state at onset UTI (using a threshold of 51 years 
as proxy), and smoking status (never vs ever). All analyses were 
stratified for gender. A (two-sided) P-value of less than 0.05 was 
considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses were per-
formed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows</rs>, release <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0.0.1</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Characteristics of UBC patients and controls. This study 
included 1809 UBC patients (81% male) and 4370 controls (45% 
male). Average age of male patients and controls was 63 and 62 
years, respectively. Average age for female patients and controls 
was 61 and 57 years. Patients were less educated, were more likely 
to smoke, and more likely to have regularly used non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory drugs, as compared with controls. Among the 
patients, 83% of male and 75% of female cases were categorised as 
non-muscle invasive bladder cancer patients (stages Ta, T1, and 
CIS). Almost all patients were diagnosed with urothelial carcinoma 
(Table 1). 
The frequencies of regular low-UTI and UTI-ab in patients and 
controls are given in Table 2. As expected, these were higher in 
women compared with men. The overlap in reported regular low-</p>

<p>Recurrent urinary tract infection and bladder cancer risk 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.601 </p>

<p>
UTI and frequent UTI-ab by the study participants was 
considerable (Table 3). </p>

<p>Association between UTI and UBC. A positive history of regular 
low-UTI was associated with an increased risk of UBC in both 
men (OR adjusted (95% CI) 6.6 (4.2-11)) and women (OR adj 2.7 
(2.0-3.5)). In contrast, a positive history of UTI-ab was associated 
with a decreased UBC risk, again in both men (OR adj 0.76 
(0.61-0.94)) and women (OR adj 0.82 (0.64-1.1)). Stratification on 
frequency of UTI-ab revealed that the protective effect was only 
seen for up to five episodes of infection. An increased UBC risk was 
observed for men with more than 10 UTI-ab episodes (OR adj 6.0 
(1.2-30)) but numbers of male patients and controls in this 
stratum were low (Table 2). 
As the symptoms of bladder cancer may be confused with those 
of a UTI, we repeated the analyses while omitting those regular 
low-UTI or UTI-ab that took place within 5 years prior to the date 
of diagnosis of bladder cancer (for patients) or the questionnaire 
(for controls). Resulting risks were only slightly changed (Table 2) 
and for subsequent analyses, we did not take the time lag between 
UTI and UBC into account. 
The stratified analyses (Table 4) indicated that the UBC risk 
increase for regular low-UTI and multiple episodes of UTI-ab was 
more pronounced in muscle-invasive bladder cancer compared 
with non-muscle invasive bladder cancer. The UBC risk decrease 
for a low number of UTI-ab is specifically observed in those who 
(had) smoked and the group of subjects that experienced UTI at a 
younger age (i.e., below the sex-specific median age at onset UTI). 
For women, large differences in UTI-ab-associated risks for 
premenopausal (p51 years) vs postmenopausal (451 years) state 
were seen. The decrease of UBC risk for a limited number of UTI-
ab was only observed for premenopausal state UTI; a strong </p>

<p>increase in risk for UBC was observed for postmenopausal state 
UTI-ab, irrespective of the number of episodes. Omission of UTI-
ab that occurred within 5 years prior to UBC diagnosis/ 
questionnaire led to even higher risks (data not shown). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Infection of the urinary tract has been thought to play a role in 
urinary bladder carcinogenesis, but has only been particularly 
evidenced and widely accepted for the association between 
schistosomiasis and catheter use in spinal cord injury with 
squamous cell carcinoma (IARC Working Group on the 
Evaluation of Carcinogenic Risks to Humans, 1994; Hess et al, 
2003). We show in this case-control study that UTI in the form 
of regular cystitis is associated with an increased risk of 
carcinoma of the bladder and that a limited number of UTI 
treated with antibiotics (i.e., p5) is associated with decreased 
UBC risk. 
We analysed data on regular cystitis and the number of UTI 
treated with antibiotics. These two variables are both measures of 
recurrent UTI but do not reflect the exact same information. In 
addition to differential recall bias or misclassification, disparity 
between results for regular low-UTI and a high number of UTI-ab 
as observed in our study can be contributed to the distinctions 
between (i) regular and a high number of episodes, (ii) cystitis and 
UTIs, and (iii) use and no use of antibiotics. Indeed, disparate risks 
for bladder and kidney infections have been reported by Jiang et al 
(2009) and Jhamb et al (2007). Also, inhibition of cell proliferation 
and anti-cancer effects in transitional cell carcinoma cell lines for 
two of the most commonly used antibiotics in UTI in Dutch </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of the study population </p>

<p>Men (n ¼ 3437) 
Women (n ¼ 2742) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n ¼ 1974) </p>

<p>Patients 
(n ¼ 1463) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n ¼ 2396) </p>

<p>Patients 
(n ¼ 346) </p>

<p>Mean age in years (sd) 
61.8 (15.9) 
62.9 (9.3) 
56.5 (16.5) 
61.3 (10.6) </p>

<p>Highest education </p>

<p>Primary 
122 (6.2) 
213 (14.6) 
184 (7.7) 
70 (20.2) 
Lower vocational secondary 
305 (15.5) 
363 (24.8) 
307 (12.9) 
82 (23.7) 
Intermediate general secondary 
246 (12.5) 
202 (13.8) 
432 (18.1) 
87 (25.1) 
Intermediate vocational secondary 
296 (15.1) 
219 (15.0) 
277 (11.6) 
36 (10.4) 
Higher general secondary 
186 (9.5) 
84 (5.7) 
276 (11.6) 
13 (3.8) 
Higher vocational secondary 
379 (19.3) 
219 (15.0) 
580 (24.3) 
39 (11.3) 
University 
428 (21.8) 
113 (7.7) 
331 (13.9) 
5 (1.4) 
Other 
3 (0.2) 
49 (3.4) 
1 (0.0) 
14 (4.0) </p>

<p>Smoking status </p>

<p>Never 
483 (24.5) 
120 (8.2) 
1034 (43.3) 
88 (25.4) 
Former 
1170 (59.3) 
860 (58.8) 
996 (41.7) 
131 (37.9) 
Current 
319 (16.2) 
482 (33.0) 
358 (15.0) 
127 (36.7) 
Mean pack-years cigarettes (sd) 
19.1 (17.1) 
27.0 (19.2) 
14.1 (15.2) 
22.5 (16.0) </p>

<p>NSAIDS </p>

<p>Aspirin 
474 (24.0) 
524 (35.8) 
462 (19.3) 
126 (36.4) 
Ibuprofen/brufen 
232 (11.8) 
239 (16.3) 
503 (21.0) 
73 (21.1) </p>

<p>Tumour stage </p>

<p>NMIBC (Ta, T1, CIS) 
-
1220 (83.4) 
-
260 (75.1) 
MIBC (XT2) 
-
183 (12.5) 
-
70 (20.2) 
Missing 
-
60 (4.1) 
-
16 (4.6) </p>

<p>Tumour histology </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Urothelial carcinoma 
-
1440 (98.4) 
-
327 (94.5) 
Squamous cell carcinoma 
-
4 (0.3) 
-
11 (3.2) 
Adenocarcinoma 
-
5 (0.3) 
-
6 (1.7) 
Other 
-
14 (1.0) 
-
2 (0.6) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: NSAIDS ¼ non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs; NMIBC ¼ non-muscle invasive bladder cancer; MIBC ¼ muscle invasive bladder cancer; sd ¼ standard deviation. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>predominant histology according to the 1995 to 2000 ICD-O-2 and the 2000 to 2006 ICD-O-3. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Recurrent urinary tract infection and bladder cancer risk </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.601 </p>

<p>practice (i.e., nitrofurantoin and trimethoprim) have been 
described (Seay et al, 1996; Kamat and Lamm, 2004). However, 
as most UTIs manifest as cystitis and are treated with antibiotics, 
these latter two distinctions may not fully account for the observed 
disparity in effects. 
One possible explanation for the fact that regular cystitis 
associates positively with UBC is the mediating role of nitric oxide 
(NO). NO is produced during inflammation by the activation of 
inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) and may promote tumour 
growth and proliferation (Xu et al, 2002; Lin et al, 2003). Indeed, </p>

<p>studies have shown that iNOS-specific proteins and ribonucleic 
acid products are present in urothelial tumours of the bladder but 
not in control bladder tissue (Swana et al, 1999; Lin et al, 2003). In 
addition, UTIs are also associated with increased iNOS expression 
in animal models (Mysorekar et al, 2002; Poljakovic and Persson, 
2003) and nitrative DNA damage has been associated with bladder 
cancer induced by Schistosoma haematobium infection (Ma et al, 
2011), suggesting that repeated activation of iNOS and thus NO 
production in both recurrent UTI episodes and in UBC may be a 
common pathway involved in urothelial response. One may </p>

<p>Table 2. Associations between regular bladder infection (regular low-UTI) and UTI treated with antibiotics (UTI-ab) and urinary 
bladder cancer in men and women </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>Controls 
(n ¼ 1974) </p>

<p>Patients 
(n ¼ 1463) 
OR (95% CI) 
OR adjusted </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n ¼ 2396) </p>

<p>Patients 
(n ¼ 346) 
OR (95% CI) 
OR adjusted </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Regular low-UTI </p>

<p>No 
1950 (98.8) 
1327 (90.7) 
Ref 
Ref 
2039 (85.1) 
232 (67.1) 
Ref 
Ref 
Yes 
24 (1.2) 
136 (9.3) 
8.3 (5.4-13) 
6.6 (4.2-11) 
357 (14.9) 
114 (32.9) 
2.8 (2.2-3.6) 
2.7 (2.0-3.5) </p>

<p>Omission p5 years </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>No 
1959 (99.2) 
1387 (94.8) 
Ref 
Ref 
2110 (88.1) 
263 (76.0) 
Ref 
Ref 
Yes 
15 (0.8) 
76 (5.2) 
7.2 (4.1-13) 
5.5 (3.1-9.9) 
286 (11.9) 
83 (24.0) 
2.3 (1.8-3.1) 
2.2 (1.6-3.0) </p>

<p>UTI-ab </p>

<p>No 
1569 (82.9) 
1174 (85.9) 
Ref 
Ref 
1110 (48.4) 
169 (54.0) 
Ref 
Ref 
Yes 
324 (17.1) 
192 (14.1) 
0.79 (0.65-0.96) 
0.76 (0.61-0.94) 
1182 (51.6) 
144 (46.0) 
0.80 (0.63-1.0) 
0.82 (0.64-1.1) </p>

<p>Omission p5 years </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>No 
1623 (85.7) 
1231 (90.1) 
Ref 
Ref 
1224 (53.4) 
187 (59.7) 
Ref 
Ref 
Yes 
270 (14.3) 
135 (9.9) 
0.66 (0.53-0.82) 
0.63 (0.49-0.80) 
1068 (46.6) 
126 (40.3) 
0.77 (0.61-0.98) 0.72 (0.56-0.94) </p>

<p>Number of UTI-ab </p>

<p>0 
1569 (83.7) 
1174 (87.4) 
Ref 
Ref 
1110 (49.6) 
169 (58.5) 
Ref 
Ref 
1-2 
217 (11.6) 
103 (7.7) 
0.63 (0.50-0.81) 
0.63 (0.48-0.82) 
530 (23.7) 
43 (14.9) 
0.53 (0.38-0.76) 0.63 (0.43-0.91) 
3-5 
75 (4.0) 
42 (3.1) 
0.75 (0.51-1.1) 
0.82 (0.54-1.2) 
333 (14.9) 
32 (11.1) 
0.63 (0.42-0.94) 0.65 (0.43-1.0) 
6-10 
11 (0.6) 
14 (1.0) 
1.7 (0.77-3.8) 
1.2 (0.52-2.9) 
159 (7.1) 
22 (7.6) 
0.91 (0.57-1.5) 
1.1 (0.64-1.8) 
X11 
2 (0.1) 
11 (0.8) 
7.4 (1.6-33) 
6.0 (1.2-30) 
107 (4.8) 
23 (8.0) 
1.4 (0.88-2.3) 
1.1 (0.64-1.8) </p>

<p>Omission p5 years </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0 
1623 (86.6) 
1227 (91.3) 
Ref 
Ref 
1224 (54.6) 
186 (64.4) 
Ref 
Ref 
1-2 
173 (9.2) 
73 (5.4) 
0.56 (0.42-0.74) 
0.55 (0.41-0.75) 
450 (20.1) 
34 (11.8) 
0.50 (0.34-0.72) 0.56 (0.37-0.83) 
3-5 
66 (3.5) 
27 (2.0) 
0.54 (0.34-0.85) 
0.59 (0.36-0.97) 
311 (13.9) 
29 (10.0) 
0.61 (0.41-0.92) 0.60 (0.39-0.94) 
6-10 
11 (0.6) 
8 (0.6) 
0.96 (0.39-2.4) 
0.70 (0.26-1.9) 
149 (6.7) 
18 (6.2) 
0.80 (0.48-1.3) 
0.91 (0.53-1.6) 
X11 
1 (0.1) 
9 (0.7) 
11.9 (1.5-94) 
8.2 (0.9-73) 
107 (4.8) 
22 (7.6) 
1.4 (0.83-2.2) 
1.0 (0.59-1.7) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; OR ¼ odds ratio; UTI ¼ urinary tract infection; UTI-ab ¼ urinary tract infection treated with antibiotics. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OR adjusted for age (at diagnosis for patients and at filling out questionnaire for controls), highest education, smoking status (current, never, former), pack-years cigarettes, use of aspirin, use 
of ibuprofen/brufen. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Regular low-UTI for which the number of years between age of UTI and filling out questionnaire (controls)/age of UBC diagnosis (patients) was equal to or less than 5 years were set to zero. 
Among those who reported regular low-UTI, age at regular low-UTI was available in 15 (63%) male controls and 96 (71%) male patients and in 266 (75%) female controls and 89 (78%) female 
patients. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>UTI-ab for which the number of years between age of first UTI and filling out questionnaire (controls)/age of UBC diagnosis (patients) was 2-5 years were set to zero. Among those who 
reported UTI-ab, age at first UTI-ab was available in 243 (75%) male controls and 118 (62%) male patients and in 738 (62%) female controls and 90 (63%) female patients. </p>

<p>Table 3. Overlap in reported regular bladder infections (regular low-UTI) and episodes of UTI-ab for patients and controls and 
men and women separately </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>Controls N (%) 
Patients N (%) 
Controls N (%) 
Patients N (%) </p>

<p>Regular low-UTI 
No 
Yes 
No 
Yes 
No 
Yes 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>Number of UTI-ab </p>

<p>0 
1585 (99.8) 
3 (0.2) 
1112 (94.7) 
62 (5.3) 
1114 (97.5) 
29 (2.5) 
146 (86.4) 
23 (13.6) 
1-2 
199 (98.5) 
3 (1.5) 
86 (83.5) 
17 (16.5) 
474 (93.9) 
31 (6.1) 
34 (79.1) 
9 (20.9) 
3-5 
63 (88.7) 
8 (11.3) 
20 (47.6) 
22 (52.4) 
226 (69.1) 
101 (30.9) 
20 (62.5) 
12 (37.5) 
6-10 
5 (45.5) 
6 (54.5) 
3 (21.4) 
11 (78.6) 
67 (42.7) 
90 (57.3) 
4 (18.2) 
18 (81.8) 
X11 
1 (50.0) 
1 (50.0) 
5 (45.5) 
6 (54.5) 
27 (25.2) 
80 (74.8) 
0 (0.0) 
23 (100.0) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: UTI ¼ urinary tract infection; UTI-ab ¼ urinary tract infection treated with antibiotics. For controls, those UTI-ab episodes that were experienced after the questionnaire on regular 
low-UTI were omitted as to account for the time lag between the questionnaires on regular low-UTI and UTI-ab. </p>

<p>Recurrent urinary tract infection and bladder cancer risk 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.601 </p>

<p>
Table 4. Associations between regular bladder infection (regular low-UTI) and UTI-ab and urinary bladder cancer, stratified by 
stage of bladder cancer, median age at onset of infection, menopausal state at onset infection (i.e., older than 51 years of age or 
not), and smoking status (never vs ever) </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>Controls/ 
patients </p>

<p>OR adjusted </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Controls/ 
patients </p>

<p>OR adjusted </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Controls/ 
patients </p>

<p>OR adjusted </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Controls/ 
patients </p>

<p>OR adjusted </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Tumour stage 
NMIBC 
MIBC 
NMIBC 
MIBC </p>

<p>Regular low-UTI </p>

<p>No 
1950/1119 
Ref 
1950/153 
Ref 
2039/180 
Ref 
2039/40 
Ref 
Yes 
24/101 
5.7 (3.5-9.2) 
24/30 
14 (7.4-27) 
357/80 
2.4 (1.8-3.3) 
357/30 
4.4 (2.6-7.4) </p>

<p>UTI-ab </p>

<p>No 
1569/978 
Ref 
1569/148 
Ref 
1110/127 
Ref 
1110/32 
Ref 
Yes 
324/160 
0.74 (0.59-0.93) 
324/24 
0.80 (0.49-1.3) 
1182/108 
0.83 (0.62-1.1) 
1182/30 
0.86 (0.50-1.5) </p>

<p>Number of UTI-ab </p>

<p>0 
1569/978 
Ref 
1569/148 
Ref 
1110/127 
Ref 
1110/32 
Ref 
1-2 
217/86 
0.62 (0.47-0.82) 
217/12 
0.57 (0.30-1.1) 
530/36 
0.69 (0.46-1.0) 
530/6 
0.48 (0.19-1.2) 
3-5 
75/33 
0.75 (0.48-1.2) 
75/7 
1.2 (0.52-2.8) 
333/22 
0.61 (0.38-1.0) 
333/7 
0.65 (0.26-1.6) 
6-10 
11/12 
1.1 (0.47-2.7) 
11/1 
1.3 (0.16-11) 
159/18 
1.1 (0.66-2.0) 
159/4 
1.2 (0.39-3.4) 
X11 
2/10 
6.5 (1.3-32) 
2/1 
6.8 (0.50-92) 
107/15 
0.94 (0.51-1.7) 
107/7 
1.5 (0.59-3.8) </p>

<p>Age regular low-
UTI/UTI-ab </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>pmedian age 
4median age 
pmedian age 
4median age </p>

<p>Regular low-UTI </p>

<p>No 
1950/1327 
Ref 
1950/1327 
Ref 
2039/232 
Ref 
2039/232 
Ref 
Yes 
5/24 
8.0 (2.9-22) 
10/72 
7.8 (3.9-16) 
122/24 
2.2 (1.3-3.8) 
144/65 
3.6 (2.5-5.2) </p>

<p>UTI-ab </p>

<p>No 
1569/1174 
Ref 
1569/1174 
Ref 
1110/169 
Ref 
1110/169 
Ref 
Yes 
108/31 
0.38 (0.24-0.59) 
135/87 
0.84 (0.62-1.1) 
330/28 
0.69 (0.43-1.1) 
408/62 
1.0 (0.75-1.5) </p>

<p>Number of UTI-ab </p>

<p>0 
1569/1174 
Ref 
1569/1174 
Ref 
1110/169 
Ref 
1110/169 
Ref 
1-2 
78/18 
0.33 (0.19-0.58) 
93/47 
0.64 (0.43-0.94) 
123/8 
0.64 (0.28-1.4) 
236/24 
0.79 (0.49-1.3) 
3-5 
25/7 
0.35 (0.14-0.88) 
32/23 
1.1 (0.61-2.0) 
101/5 
0.43 (0.17-1.1) 
98/13 
0.86 (0.46-1.6) 
6-10 
3/3 
0.89 (0.14-5.6) 
4/6 
1.4 (0.37-5.3) 
53/4 
0.67 (0.23-2.0) 
43/12 
2.0 (0.99-4.2) 
X11 
0/3 
-
2/6 
4.8 (0.90-25) 
47/8 
0.89 (0.36-2.2) 
22/11 
2.1 (0.95-4.9) </p>

<p>Menopausal state 
Pre (p51 years) 
Post (451 years) </p>

<p>Regular low-UTI </p>

<p>No 
2039/232 
Ref 
2039/232 
Ref 
Yes 
211/57 
3.1 (2.1-4.5) 
55/32 
3.4 (2.1-5.7) </p>

<p>UTI-ab </p>

<p>No 
1110/169 
Ref 
1110/169 
Ref 
Yes 
632/68 
0.79 (0.57-1.1) 
106/74 
5.0 (3.4-7.4) </p>

<p>Number of UTI-ab </p>

<p>0 
1110/169 
Ref 
1110/169 
Ref 
1-2 
302/21 
0.59 (0.36-0.98) 
57/21 
2.6 (1.4-4.5) 
3-5 
173/13 
0.55 (0.30-1.0) 
26/19 
6.3 (3.2-12) 
6-10 
81/13 
1.3 (0.68-2.6) 
15/8 
4.0 (1.5-11) 
X11 
64/16 
1.2 (0.62-2.3) 
5/7 
10 (3.0-35) </p>

<p>Smoking status </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Never 
Ever 
Never 
Ever </p>

<p>Regular low-UTI </p>

<p>No 
478/110 
Ref 
1470/1216 
Ref 
867/56 
Ref 
1165/176 
Ref 
Yes 
5/10 
7.4 (3.0-24) 
19/126 
6.4 (3.9-11) 
167/32 
2.8 (1.7-4.6) 
189/82 
2.6 (1.9-3.7) </p>

<p>UTI-ab </p>

<p>No 
406/90 
Ref 
1161/1083 
Ref 
481/38 
Ref 
625/131 
Ref 
Yes 
59/18 
1.1 (0.61-2.1) 
265/174 
0.71 (0.57-0.88) 
498/43 
1.1 (0.67-1.7) 
680/101 
0.71 (0.52-0.96) </p>

<p>Number of UTI-ab </p>

<p>0 
406/90 
Ref 
1161/1083 
Ref 
481/38 
Ref 
625/131 
Ref 
1-2 
40/98 
0.87 (0.39-1.9) 
177/94 
0.58 (0.44-0.77) 
211/14 
0.98 (0.51-1.9) 
318/29 
0.51 (0.33-0.80) 
3-5 
16/5 
1.2 (0.39-3.5) 
59/37 
0.76 (0.48-1.2) 
144/14 
1.2 (0.60-2.3) 
188/18 
0.43 (0.25-0.76) 
6-10 
1/1 
3.3 (0.20-54) 
10/13 
1.1 (0.46-2.6) 
76/4 
0.67 (0.23-2.0) 
81/18 
1.2 (0.68-2.2) 
X11 
0/1 
-
2/10 
4.6 (0.93-22) 
45/7 
1.4 (0.56-3.5) 
62/16 
0.92 (0.49-1.7) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI ¼ confidence interval; MIBC ¼ muscle invasive bladder cancer; NMIBC ¼ non-muscle invasive bladder cancer; OR ¼ odds ratio; UTI ¼ urinary tract infection; UTI-ab ¼ urinary 
tract infection treated with antibiotics. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OR adjusted for age (at diagnosis for patients and at filling out questionnaire for controls), highest education, smoking status (current, never, former), pack-years cigarettes, use of aspirin, use 
of ibuprofen/brufen. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Median ages (in years) at onset UTI (with omission UTI o ¼ 5 years prior to age at UBC diagnosis/questionnaire): regular low-UTI males: 50.0; regular low-UTI females: 25; UTI-ab males: 42.0; 
UTI-ab females: 24.5 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>OR adjusted for age (at diagnosis for patients and at filling out questionnaire for controls), highest education, use of aspirin, pack-years cigarettes, use of ibuprofen/brufen. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Recurrent urinary tract infection and bladder cancer risk </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.601 </p>

<p>speculate that the protective effect of a limited number of UTI 
treated with antibiotics suggests that the beneficial anti-cancer 
effect of antibiotics as described by Seay et al (1996) and Kamat 
and Lamm (2004) outweighs the detrimental effects of (sporadic) 
infection and subsequent NO production. It is, however, unclear 
whether only a few short courses of antibiotics can decrease 
bladder cancer risk. Note that the decreased rate of UTI-ab in 
bladder cancer patients compared with controls was not seen for 
the few UBC patients in our population with squamous cell and 
adenocarcinoma but only for urothelial carcinoma (as predomi-
nant histology) (data not shown). 
Exact comparison between our findings and those from 
previous studies is hampered by the fact that only few studies 
have addressed the number, location, and treatment of the UTIs in 
detail. The observed increased UBC risk for regular cystitis 
confirms findings from Kantor et al (1984) and La Vecchia et al 
(1991) whose studies show that more than three episodes of cystitis 
increases UBC risk. The observed decreased risk of UBC for a 
limited number of UTI is in line with a recent study from Jiang 
et al (2009) in which one, two to three, and more than three 
episodes of cystitis were associated with reduced risk of UBC in 
women. Unfortunately, those women who experienced more than 
three episodes were combined in one category, thereby preventing 
us to evaluate the association for those with a higher number of 
episodes in more detail. Most studies, however, report a higher 
UBC risk for a patient-reported positive history of UTI (Wynder 
et al, 1963; Jhamb et al, 2007). 
A number of the previous studies into the association between 
UTI and UBC have described a decrease in the OR for UTI and 
bladder cancer risk after excluding those UTI that occurred within 
the years prior to UBC diagnosis (González et al, 1991; La Vecchia 
et al, 1991; Jhamb et al, 2007; Jiang et al, 2009; Sun et al, 2013). 
These findings support the existence of a diagnostic bias. This is 
underlined by studies that have described UTI diagnosis as a cause 
for delay in bladder cancer diagnosis (Henning et al, 2013; Cohn 
et al, 2014). The results of our study were, however, only 
marginally affected by omission of infections occurring within 5 
years prior to UBC diagnosis. 
We showed that our results for UTI-ab were similar for men 
and women; the increased UBC risk for regular cystitis was 
higher in men though. However, note that, in contrast to women, 
regular cystitis is rare among the male population. Further 
stratified analyses, more or less hampered by limited numbers in 
specific subcategories, did identify deviating findings in some 
subgroups. Timing of the onset of UTI was found to be of 
importance; the protective effect of a small number of UTI-ab 
was only found for those UTI that were experienced at a 
relatively young age (i.e., below the sex-specific median age) and 
the increase in UBC risk for recurrent cystitis was more 
pronounced for an older age of UTI-onset. Especially the 
increased risk of bladder cancer for history of UTI-ab, 
irrespective of frequency, in postmenopausal women was striking 
and warrants further research. It is notable that these subgroups 
that showed stronger increased UBC risk for recurrent cystitis, 
that is, men, those with UTI onset at an older age, and 
postmenopausal women, are also more likely to experience a 
complicated and recurrent (course of) UTI because of the 
presence of anatomical, functional, or metabolic conditions (e.g., 
prostatitis, diabetes, vaginal atrophy). Furthermore, the higher 
UBC risk for regular cystitis was much stronger in muscle-
invasive bladder cancer compared with non-muscle invasive 
bladder cancer, in line with Kantor et al (1984) and Sturgeon 
et al (1994). The protective effect of a small number of UTI-ab 
was only seen in (former) smokers; we could not confirm the 
positive interaction between smoking and history of cystitis on 
UBC risk as reported in earlier studies (Kantor et al, 1984; La 
Vecchia et al, 1991). </p>

<p>In conclusion, our study showed a protective effect on UBC risk 
for a small number (p5) of UTI episodes treated with antibiotics, 
specifically at a younger age of onset and in (former) smokers, and 
increased UBC risk for regular cystitis. We underline the 
importance of considering the total number of UTI, age at onset, 
location in the urinary tract, and use of antibiotics when 
considering the association of UTI with bladder cancer in future 
research as to allow for further unravelling of their separate effects. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Principal investigators of the Nijmegen Biomedical Study are 
LA Kiemeney, M den Heijer, ALM Verbeek, and DW Swinkels en 
B Franke. </p>



<p>Recurrent urinary tract infection and bladder cancer risk 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.601 </p>



<p>
This work is published under the standard license to publish agree-
ment. After 12 months the work will become freely available and 
the license terms will switch to a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Recurrent urinary tract infection and bladder cancer risk </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.601 </p>

</text></tei>