<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4776054" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background. Due to the unintended potential misclassifications of the World Health Organization (WHO) immunological fail-
ure criteria in predicting virological failure, limited availability of treatment options, poor laboratory infrastructure, and healthcare 
providers' confidence in making switches, physicians delay switching patients to second-line antiretroviral therapy (ART). Evaluating 
whether timely switching and delayed switching are associated with the risk of opportunistic infections (OI) among patients with 
unrecognized treatment failure is critical to improve patient outcomes. 
Methods. A retrospective review of 637 adolescents and adults meeting WHO immunological failure criteria was conducted. 
Timely and delayed switching to second-line ART were defined when switching happened at &lt;3 and ≥3 months, respectively, 
after failure diagnosis was made. Cox proportional hazard marginal structural models were used to assess the effect of switching 
to second-line ART on the risk of developing OI. 
Results. Of 637 patients meeting WHO immunological failure criteria, 396 (62.2%) switched to second-line ART. Of those 
switched, 230 (58.1%) were delayed. Switching to second-line ART reduced the risk of OI (adjusted hazards ratio [AHR], 0.4; 
95% CI, .2-.6). Compared with patients who received timely switch after failure diagnosis was made, those who delayed switching 
were more likely to develop OI (AHR, 2.2; 95% CI, 1.1-4.3). 
Conclusions. Delayed switching to second-line ART after failure diagnosis may increase the risk of OI. Serial immunological 
assessment for switching patients to second-line ART is critical to improve their outcomes. 
Diagnosis and treatment of patients failing first-line antiretroviral 
therapy (ART) in low-and middle-income countries (LMIC) re-
mains challenging [1, 2]. Because of the lack of routine viral load 
monitoring, the definition of treatment failure to a large extent de-
pends entirely on World Health Organization (WHO) clinical and 
immunological failure criteria [3-5]. Due to the potential misclas-
sification of treatment failure resulting from using these failure 
criteria [6-9] as well as limited availability of treatment options, 
poor laboratory infrastructure, low healthcare provider confidence 
in making switches, and high costs of second-line ART, physicians 
are often reluctant [3, 4, 10, 11] to switch. One consequence of </p>

<p>unrecognized treatment failures and/or delayed switches may be 
an increased risk of opportunistic infections (OI). 
Delayed switching to second-line ART in programs without 
routine viral load monitoring is common. A higher proportion 
of patients remain on a failed first-line regimen in programs 
without routine viral load monitoring, compared with those 
in programs with routine viral load monitoring [8]. Of patients 
meeting WHO immunological and clinical failure criteria, 
&lt;45% are switched to second-line ART [12, 13]. The rate of 
switch is higher in eastern Europe than in sub-Saharan Africa 
[14], and the difference in the rates of switch is attributed to 
the lack of routine viral load monitoring in African programs. 
A delay in switching is also indicated by the variation in switch-
ing times from diagnosis of failure [2, 14]. In addition, in 
resource-limited settings, switching happens earlier in programs 
with routine viral load monitoring than in those without [15]. 
Despite treatment success for many patients on second-line 
ART, mortality and virological failure rates are high [14, 16-19]. 
Virological failure is defined as increasing levels of detectable 
human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) RNA and is associated 
with multiple nucleoside/nucleotide resistance mutations </p>

<p>Received 13 November 2015; accepted 7 January 2016. 
Correspondence: H. O. Ramadhani, Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Center, P.O. Box 3010 
Moshi, Kilimanjaro, Tanzania (habibrama@gmail.com). </p>

<p>Open Forum Infectious Diseases </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>© The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Infectious Diseases 
Society of America. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc-nd/4.0/), which permits non-commercial reproduction and distribution of the work, in any 
medium, provided the original work is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work 
is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com. 
DOI: 10.1093/ofid/ofw018 </p>

<p>The Effect of Switching to Second-Line Antiretroviral Therapy • OFID • 1 </p>

<p>[20, 21]. Higher levels of HIV RNA pose the risk of OI. Other 
than medication nonadherence, high mortality and treatment 
failure may also be due to delayed switching among patients 
with unrecognized treatment failure. Compared with patients 
meeting clinical/immunological failure criteria and switched 
into second-line ART, those who met criteria and did not 
switch had poor survival [13]. 
Reports about the frequency of OI among patients failing 
first-line ART in LMIC are limited. Whether disproportionally 
higher OI are observed in patients remaining on failed first-line 
regimen compared with those who switched to second-line 
ART is not understood. We sought to evaluate the influence 
of switching and delayed switching to second-line ART on 
the risk of OI among patients meeting immunological failure 
criteria. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study Design and Population </p>

<p>We used a retrospective cohort study design to evaluate the 
effect of switching to second-line ART on the incidence of OI 
among patients infected with HIV in Northern Tanzania. Re-
cords of patients attending the Kilimanjaro Christian Medical 
Centre (KCMC), Mawenzi Regional Hospital (MRH), and 
Kibosho, Kilema, and Machame Hospitals between January 
2004 and August 2013 were reviewed. Patients who were &lt;13 
years old were excluded. According to the hierarchy of the 
health system in Tanzania, KCMC is a tertiary referral hospital, 
MRH is a regional hospital, and Kibosho, Kilema, and Ma-
chame are district hospitals. These care and treatment centers 
(CTCs) offer treatment according to the Tanzanian Ministry 
of Health treatment guidelines for the provision of ART. Ac-
cording to these guidelines, patients receive a fixed-dose combi-
nation of stavudine (D4T), lamivudine (3TC), and nevirapine 
(NVP) as first-line ART. Zidovudine (AZT) and efavirenz re 
used in place of D4T and NVP, respectively, depending upon 
toxicities and concurrent medications. Each patient is 
typically seen on a monthly basis and their prescriptions are re-
filled. At the time of this study, routine viral load monitoring 
was not available in these CTCs; therefore, patients were 
switched to second-line ART based on clinical and immunolog-
ical criteria according to the WHO guidelines (www.who.int/ 
hiv/pub/arv/adult2010) of a decline in CD4 
+ cell count to the </p>

<p>pretreatment value or below ≥50% decline from the peak value 
CD4 
+ cell count value while on treatment or persistent low CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cell count &lt;100 c/mm 
3 . The drugs used for second-line ART </p>

<p>included tenofovir, abacavir (ABC), and lopinavir/ritonavir 
(LPV/r); atazanavir/ritonavir was substituted for LPV/r as need-
ed. The second-line nucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitor 
choice for adolescents and adults depended on the first-line 
ART. For patients on AZT or D4T in first-line ART, the default 
second-line option was tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF) 
combined with 3TC or FTC and LPV/r. For those who had </p>

<p>received TDF in first-line, the second-line option was an AZT-
based regimen. For those who were on TDF during first-line 
because of intolerance to AZT or D4T, an alternative second-
line option was ABC combined with 3TC or FTC and LPV/r. </p>

<p>Data Collection </p>

<p>As part of routine HIV clinical care, all patient data including 
demographics, medication use, OI, adherence indicators 
(adherent = fewer than 2 missed days per month/nonadherent = 2 
or more missed days per month), and laboratory values were 
collected on standardized forms and entered into a database 
designed and funded by the Tanzanian National AIDS Control 
Program in collaboration with Elizabeth Glaser Pediatric AIDS 
Foundation. This database was searched for clinical data, and 
when information was missing, it was abstracted from their 
respective medical files. Treatment monitoring included clinical 
and immunological criteria; CD4 
+ cell counts were checked at </p>

<p>4-to 6-month intervals using flow cytometry. </p>

<p>Definition of Variables </p>

<p>The primary end point was the time from immunological failure 
to the first occurrence of OI (pulmonary tuberculosis [TB], pneu-
monia, Kaposi's sarcoma [KS], cryptococcal meningitis [CM], 
and herpes zoster [HZ]). All TB, KS, CM, and some pneumonia 
infections were confirmed by the laboratory, histopathology, 
or x-ray, whereas HZ infections were diagnosed clinically. We 
defined loss to follow-up as the absence of a documented clinic 
visit 6 months from date of the previous clinic visit. 
The exposure of interest was time until switching to second-
line ART. We defined switching to second-line as initiation of 
a boosted protease inhibitor-based regimen; otherwise, the 
patient was considered not switched. Furthermore, among 
those switched to second-line, we defined timely switching 
and delayed switching as switching occurring at &lt;3 months vs 
≥3 months after the diagnosis of immunological failure was 
made, respectively. A cutoff of 3 months was chosen because 
after a failure diagnosis, patients received 1 to 2 months of 
intensive adherence counseling before making the switch. 
Institutional review board approval was obtained from the 
University of North Carolina and KCMC. </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Analysis 
Software (SAS</rs>), <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC). 
The distribution of continuous variables was explored to 
guide categorization. Frequencies and distributions of sociode-
mographic and clinical characteristics were computed. 
Because switching to second-line ART is influenced by CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cell counts, confounding by indication is a potential problem 
such that patients with low CD4 
+ cell are more likely to be </p>

<p>switched to second-line than those without low CD4 
+ cell. </p>

<p>Time-varying covariate (CD4 cell) affects both time-varying ex-
posure (time to switching) and outcome (OI or death). In addi-
tion, switching history predicts future CD4 cell count. Because </p>

<p>2 • OFID • Ramadhani et al </p>

<p>of the existence of such scenarios, the use of marginal structural 
models (MSMs) is recommended. We assessed the effect of 
switching to second-line ART on the risk of OI using Cox pro-
portional hazards MSMs, which address confounding by indi-
cation. CD4 
+ cell count was considered as a time-varying </p>

<p>confounder. To ensure switching to second-line ART happened 
after a time-varying confounder, CD4 
+ cell count values at fail-</p>

<p>ure diagnosis were assigned to the preceding month. Other 
covariates included age, gender, adherence to first-line ART, ad-
herence to second-line ART, treatment sites, and duration spent 
on first-line ART. Patients began accumulating person time 
from the moment failure diagnosis was made, and they were 
observed until first occurrence of an opportunistic infection, 
death, lost to follow-up, or end of the study, whichever came 
first. All patients who died, were loss to follow-up, and did 
not experience OI were censored in the primary analysis. 
Marginal structural model analyses use inverse probability of 
exposure weights to control confounding by time-varying 
covariates that are also on the causal pathway from exposure to 
outcome. In this case, the persons were assigned weights in-
versely proportional to their probability of having the exposure, 
given their exposure and covariate histories. We used logistic 
regression models to compute the weights, and all weights were 
stabilized. After computation of the stabilized weights, we used 
Cox proportional hazards MSMs to estimate the associations. 
All associations were presented as adjusted hazard ratios 
(AHRs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Estimates whose 
CIs excluded 1 were regarded as statistically significant. 
Kaplan-Meier curves were used to assess the survival distri-
butions among those who were switched and those who were 
not switched to second-line ART. We used log-rank tests to 
compare the hazard functions for those switched against 
those not switched to second-line ART. Poisson regression 
models were used to compute the incidence rate of OI. Two 
sensitivity analyses were performed: the first defined time from 
failure diagnosis to death or first occurrence of OI used as the 
outcome, and the second used propensity scores weighting to as-
sess the effect of switching to second-line ART on the risk of OI. 
In the second case, the main exposure switching to second-line 
ART was considered as time fixed mimicking the design of 
a randomized controlled trial where every eligible patient 
would be assigned either to be switched or not at baseline. A re-
gression model to generate the scores included the following 
variables: age (&lt;30, 30-55, &gt;55), gender, months patient spent 
on first-line ART (&lt;36, 36-60, &gt;60), CD4 cell count (&lt;100, 
100-200, &gt;200), sites (tertiary hospital, regional hospital, district 
hospital), percentage adherence to first-line ART (&lt;90, ≥90), and 
percentage adherence to second-line ART (&lt;90, ≥90). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>From January 2004 through August 2013, we identified 637 ad-
olescent and adult patients at the 5 sites who met WHO </p>

<p>immunological failure criteria. Three hundred ninety-four 
(61.8%) patients were female, and the majority (454, 71.3%) 
of patients were aged between 30 and 55 years (Table 1). 
Most patients (476, 74.7%) had suboptimal adherence to first-
line ART, 360 (56.5%) patients spent &lt;36 months on first-line 
ART, and 174 (43.9%) patients had CD4 
+ cell count of &lt;100/ </p>

<p>mm 
3 at the time of switching to second-line ART. Three hun-</p>

<p>dred ninety-six (62.2%) patients switched to second-line ART, 
whereas 241 (37.8%) patients did not. Among those switched, 
233 (58.8%) switched within the first 3 months from the time 
failure diagnosis was made. 
Approximately one fifth (n = 115; 18.1%) experienced an op-
portunistic infection. The most common infections were pneumo-
nia (n = 46; 7.2%) and TB (n = 35; 5.5%). Other OI included CM, 
KS, or HZ (n = 34; 5.3%). </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of HIV-Infected 
Adolescents and Adults Meeting WHO Immunologic Failure Criteria at 5 
Infectious Disease Clinics in Kilimanjaro Region, Tanzania, 2004-2013 </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Overall 
(n = 637) </p>

<p>Switched to 
Second-Line 
(n = 396) </p>

<p>Did not Switch 
to Second-Line 
(n = 241) </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
243 (38.2) 
146 (36.9) 
97 (40.2) </p>

<p>Female 
394 (61.8) 
250 (63.1) 
144 (59.8) </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>&lt;30 y 
134 (21.0) 
97 (24.5) 
37 (15.3) </p>

<p>30-55 y 
454 (71.3) 
221 (68.4) 
123 (75.9) </p>

<p>&gt;55 y 
49 (7.7) 
28 (7.1) 
21 (8.7) </p>

<p>Duration on first-line ART </p>

<p>&lt;36 mo 
360 (56.5) 
222 (56.1) 
138 (57.3) </p>

<p>36-60 mo 
187 (29.4) 
146 (31.8) 
61 (25.3) </p>

<p>&gt;60 mo 
90 (14.1) 
28 (12.1) 
32 (17.4) </p>

<p>First-line adherence </p>

<p>Optimal 
161 (25.3) 
98 (24.8) 
63 (26.1) </p>

<p>Suboptimal 
476 (74.7) 
298 (75.2) 
178 (73.9) </p>

<p>Second-line adherence </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Optimal 
N/A 
260 (65.7) 
N/A </p>

<p>Suboptimal 
N/A 
136 (34.3) 
N/A </p>

<p>CD4 cells at time of switch </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>&lt;100 c/mm³ 
N/A 
174 (43.9) 
N/A </p>

<p>100-200 c/mm³ 
N/A 
166 (41.9) 
N/A </p>

<p>&gt;200 c/mm³ 
N/A 
56 (14.1) 
N/A </p>

<p>Sites </p>

<p>Tertiary hospital 
327 (51.3) 
244 (61.6) 
83 (34.5) </p>

<p>Regional Hospital 
167 (26.2) 
92 (23.2) 
75 (31.1) </p>

<p>District Hospital 
143 (22.5) 
60 (15.2) 
83 (34.4) </p>

<p>Infections </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Tuberculosis 
35 (5.5) 
14 (3.5) 
21 (8.7) </p>

<p>Pneumonias 
46 (7.2) 
12 (3.0) 
34 (14.1) </p>

<p>Meningitis 
1 (0.2) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (0.4) </p>

<p>Kaposis sarcoma 
8 (1.3) 
3 (0.8) 
5 (2.1) </p>

<p>Herpes zoster 
25 (3.9) 
9 (2.3) 
16 (6.6) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ART, antiretroviral therapy; HIV, human immunodeficiency virus; N/A, not 
applicable; WHO, World Health Organization. 
a Not measured in full 637. </p>

<p>The Effect of Switching to Second-Line Antiretroviral Therapy • OFID • 3 </p>

<p>Survival Distributions Among Those Switched and Those not Switched 
to Second-Line Antiretroviral Therapy </p>

<p>During the follow-up, 637 patients contributed 1181 person-
years with overall median of follow up of 1.4 (interquartile 
range [IQR], 0.7-2.7) years. Those who switched had a median 
follow up of 2.3 (IQR, 1.2-3.9) years, the corresponding median 
follow up among those who did not switch was 1.0 (IQR, 
0.5-1.4) years. Among those who switched, 38 experienced an 
opportunistic infection (incidence rate = 5.4 per 100 person-
years [95% CI, 4.0-7.5]), compared with 77 among those who 
did not switch (incidence rate = 15.9 per 100 person-years [95% 
CI, 12.7-19.9]) The difference in probabilities of developing OI 
among those switched and those who did not switch is apparent 
from the start of follow up (Figure 1). Kaplan-Meier curves 
showed a steep decline of OI free-survival during the first 16 
months among patients not switched to second-line. The 6-
and 12-month probabilities of having OI among those switched 
to second-line ART were 0.03 and 0.07, respectively, compared 
with 0.13 and 0.36 among those who did not switch (P &lt; .001, 
log-rank test). 
Compared with patients who met immunological failure cri-
teria and did not switch to second-line ART, those who met and 
switched were less likely to acquire OI (AHR, 0.4; 95% CI, .2-.6; 
Table 2). The models were adjusted for age, gender, duration on 
first-line ART, site of care, and adherence. 
Among those switched to second line ART, compared with 
patients who were timely switched after their failure diagnosis 
was made, those who were delayed to switch were more 
likely to acquire OI (AHR, 2.2; 95% CI, 1.1-4.3; Table 3). 
When the primary end point was defined as death or occur-
rence of the first opportunistic infection, compared with 
patients who met immunological failure criteria and did not 
switch to second-line ART, those who met and switched were 
less likely to die or acquire OI (AHR, 0.4; 95% CI, .2-.7; 
Table 4). </p>

<p>The logistic regression model used to estimate the propensity 
score yielded a c-statistic of 0.8. The mean propensity to receive 
second-line ART was 0.7 (standard deviation, 0.2) compared 
with 0.4 (standard deviation, 0.2) for those who did not receive 
second-line ART. The distribution of the propensity score for 
those switched to second-line ART was somewhat higher than 
those who did not switch to second-line; however, approximate-
ly 97.7% of the propensity scores overlapped between the 
2 groups. Using propensity scores analyses, compared with 
patients who met immunological failure criteria and did not 
switch to second-line ART, those who met and switched were 
less likely to acquire OI (AHR, 0.2; 95% CI, .1-.2; Table 5). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The study attempted to assess the association between switching 
to second-line ART and the risk of OI among HIV-infected pa-
tients meeting immunologic failure criteria from 5 CTCs in 
northern Tanzania. We demonstrated that switching to sec-
ond-line ART reduced the incidence of OI among patients 
meeting immunological failure criteria infections (AHR, 0.4; </p>

<p>Figure 1. Kaplan-Meier curves for 637 human immunodeficiency virus-infected 
adolescent and adult patients according to switching status. </p>

<p>Table 2. Risk Factors of Opportunistic Infections Among HIV-Infected 
Adolescents and Adults Switched and Those not Switched Into Second-
Line Antiretroviral Therapy at 5 Infectious Disease Clinics in Kilimanjaro 
Region, Moshi, Tanzania, 2004-2013 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Number of 
Infections </p>

<p>Person 
Years </p>

<p>Rate/ 
100 py </p>

<p>Adjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Switched </p>

<p>No 
77 
483.3 
15.9 
1 </p>

<p>Yes 
38 
697.3 
5.4 
0.4 (.2-.6) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
43 
489.1 
8.8 
1 </p>

<p>Female 
72 
691.5 
10.4 
1.2 (.8-1.7) </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>&lt;30 y 
27 
270.4 
10.0 
1 </p>

<p>30-55 y 
80 
827.0 
9.7 
0.9 (.5-1.5) </p>

<p>&gt;55 y 
8 
83.2 
9.6 
0.6 (.3-1.5) </p>

<p>Duration on first-line ART </p>

<p>&lt;36 mo 
76 
647.4 
11.7 
1 </p>

<p>36-60 mo 
29 
371.2 
7.8 
0.5 (.3-.8) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>&gt;60 mo 
10 
161.9 
6.2 
0.3 (.1-.6) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>First-line adherence </p>

<p>Optimal 
20 
357.2 
5.6 
1 </p>

<p>Suboptimal 
95 
823.4 
11.5 
1.5 (.9-2.4) </p>

<p>Second-line adherence </p>

<p>Optimal 
43 
686.3 
6.2 
1 </p>

<p>Suboptimal 
72 
494.3 
14.6 
1.3 (.8-1.9) </p>

<p>Sites </p>

<p>Tertiary Hospital 
54 
738.3 
7.3 
1 </p>

<p>Regional Hospital 
30 
251.8 
11.9 
1.1 (.7-1.8) </p>

<p>District Hospital 
31 
190.4 
16.3 
1.3 (.8-2.1) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ART, antiretroviral therapy; CI, confidence interval; HIV, human 
immunodeficiency virus; HR, hazards ratio; py, person years. 
a Hazards ratios are based on analysis of Cox proportional marginal structural models on 636 </p>

<p>patients. 
b Statistically significant. </p>

<p>4 • OFID • Ramadhani et al </p>

<p>95% CI, .2-.6). Furthermore, time of switching impacted the 
risk of OI with longer delays associated with approximately 2-
fold increase in risk relative to timely switching. 
In the absence of routine viral load testing for determining 
treatment failure, delayed switching is common in many low-
and middle-income countries [2, 14, 19]. In this study, only 
62% of those meeting immunological failure criteria switched 
at all, and the median time to switch from the time of immuno-
logical failure diagnosis was 5.1 months. Limited availability of 
the second-line medications, low sensitivity of the WHO immu-
nologic failure criteria in predicting virological failure, and low 
confidence of healthcare providers in making switches may 
have contributed to the delays in switching. In addition to 
these factors, delays in switching in this cohort could as also 
be explained by the low levels of adherence. Approximately 
75% of the patients had adherence levels below 90% before 
switch. Those with low levels of adherence may have been less 
likely to be switched. Similar delays in switching were docu-
mented in Haiti where the median time to switching to 
second-line ART was 7 months and patients with adherence </p>

<p>below 90% were less likely to be switched [13]. Substantial pro-
portions of patients who met immunological failure criteria in a 
study from Mali [3] did not switch to second-line ART, and the 
median duration of follow up from failure diagnosis was 5 
months. These observations suggest that delays in switching 
to second-line ART are a serious management concern across 
low-and middle-income countries. 
Among patients meeting immunological failure criteria, 
switching to second-line ART is associated with a 60% reduc-
tion in the risk of OI compared with those who remained on 
a failed first-line regimen. The association between immunolog-
ical failure and the incidence of HZ has been reported previous-
ly [22], in which the incidence of HZ was 6.2 episodes per 100 
person years. We observed a slightly lower incidence rate of 2.1 
episodes per 100 person years. The high incidence of OI is likely 
attributable to unrecognized treatment failure and relatively 
severe immunosuppression. Among those who switched, 
approximately half of the patients in our study had CD4 
+ cell </p>

<p>count &lt;100 c/mm 
3 at the time of switch. Severe immunosup-</p>

<p>pression defined by CD4 
+ cell &lt;100 c/mm 
3 is a clear risk factor </p>

<p>for OI such as TB and pneumonia [23, 24]. 
Our sensitivity analyses results were robust with the results 
from the main analysis. Using propensity scores, switching to 
second-line ART is associated with an 80% reduction in the 
risk of OI compared with those who remained on a failed </p>

<p>Table 3. Risk Factors of Opportunistic Infections Among HIV-Infected 
Adolescents and Adults Switched Into Second-Line Antiretroviral 
Therapy at 5 Infectious Disease Clinics in Kilimanjaro Region, Moshi, 
Tanzania 2004-2013 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Number of 
Infections </p>

<p>Person 
Years </p>

<p>Rate/ 
100 py </p>

<p>Adjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Timely switched </p>

<p>Yes 
11 
323.1 
3.4 
1 </p>

<p>No 
27 
374.2 
7.2 
2.2 (1.1-4.3) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
15 
277.6 
5.4 
1 </p>

<p>Female 
23 
419.6 
5.5 
1.1 (.5-2.1) </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>&lt;30 y 
12 
177.3 
6.8 
1 </p>

<p>30-55 y 
22 
486.2 
4.5 
0.5 (.2-1.3) </p>

<p>&gt;55 y 
4 
33.8 
11.8 
1.6 (.2-4.8) </p>

<p>Duration on first-line ART </p>

<p>&lt;36 mo 
22 
445.7 
4.9 
1 </p>

<p>36-60 mo 
11 
211.7 
5.2 
1.0 (.3-3.6) </p>

<p>&gt;60 mo 
5 
39.9 
12.5 
1.5 (.5-4.3) </p>

<p>First-line adherence </p>

<p>Optimal 
4 
219.4 
1.8 
1 </p>

<p>Suboptimal 
34 
477.9 
7.1 
4.1 (1.4-12.6) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Second-line adherence </p>

<p>Optimal 
23 
510.7 
4.5 
1 </p>

<p>Suboptimal 
15 
186.6 
8.0 
1.7 (.6-5.2) </p>

<p>Sites </p>

<p>Tertiary Hospital 
22 
516.7 
4.3 
1 </p>

<p>Regional Hospital 
11 
120.2 
9.2 
1.5 (.7-3.6) </p>

<p>District Hospital 
5 
60.4 
8.3 
1.5 (.5-4.5) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ART, antiretroviral therapy; CI, confidence interval; HIV, human 
immunodeficiency virus; HR, hazards ratio; py, person years. 
a Hazards ratios are based on analysis of Cox proportional marginal structural models on 396 </p>

<p>switched to second line ART. 
b Statistically significant. </p>

<p>Table 4. Analyses of the Effect of Switching to Second Line Antiretroviral 
Therapy on Risk of Opportunistic Infections or Deaths Among HIV-Infected 
Adolescents and Adults at 5 Infectious Disease Clinics in Kilimanjaro 
Region, Moshi, Tanzania 2004-2013 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Number of Infections/ 
Deaths </p>

<p>Person 
Years </p>

<p>Rate/100 
py </p>

<p>Adjusted HR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Switched </p>

<p>No 
77 
697.3 
4.6 
1 </p>

<p>Yes 
48 
483.3 
3.3 
0.4 (.2-.7) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; HIV, human immunodeficiency virus; HR, hazards 
ratio; py, person years. 
a Hazards ratios are based on analysis of Cox proportional marginal structural models on 396 </p>

<p>patients. 
b Statistically significant. </p>

<p>Table 5. Propensity Score Analyses of the Effect of Switching to Second-
Line Antiretroviral Therapy on Risk of Opportunistic Infections Among HIV-
Infected Adolescents and Adults at 5 Infectious Disease Clinics in 
Kilimanjaro Region, Moshi, Tanzania 2004-2013 </p>

<p>Variable 
Categories 
AHR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Switched 
No 
1 </p>

<p>Yes 
0.2 
(.1-.2) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AHR, adjusted hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; HIV, human 
immunodeficiency virus. 
a Statistically significant. </p>

<p>The Effect of Switching to Second-Line Antiretroviral Therapy • OFID • 5 </p>

<p>first-line regimen. The mean propensity among those switched 
to second line ART was higher than that of those who did not 
switch, indicating that those switched were at a greater need to 
receive second-line ART than those who did not. 
Combining deaths and OI as the end point, the effect of 
switching to second-line persisted; the risk of death or OI was 
less among those switched compared with those continued on 
the failed first-line regimen. Among those who died, 31% had 
OI before death. Others have previously shown that delayed 
switching is associated with an increased risk of mortality [13, 
25]. Although the causes of death were not ascertained in these 
studies, it is likely patients had life-threatening OI before their 
deaths. 
Many of the OI in this study were clinically diagnosed. Mis-
diagnosis might have overestimated the incidence of OI. Al-
though it is possible to misdiagnose pneumonia infections 
clinically, the dermatological manifestations of HZ are obvious 
and unlikely to be misdiagnosed in patients infected with HIV. 
Moreover, clinical diagnosis of HZ is common in many studies 
[22, 26, 27]. Although TB infections were confirmed by sputum 
examination, the presence of smear negative does not rule out 
TB, especially in patients infected with HIV. The timing of 
sputum collection and processing can also impact the diagnosis 
of TB. Variations in timing and processing from different 
laboratories might have underestimated the incidence of TB 
infections. 
The timing of diagnosis of OI could be measured with some 
errors in this study. Due to the factors related to patients, access 
to care, and healthcare systems in LMIC, diagnoses of TB and 
KS and other acquired immune deficiency syndrome-defining 
cancers are likely to be made late [28, 29]. All patients in this 
study were screened for TB at ART initiation, and patients 
were periodically evaluated for TB as they attended their 
CTCs. In addition, with monthly clinic visits and periodic eval-
uation, errors in the timing of diagnosis of OI are likely to be 
minimal. 
Because CD4 
+ cell counts were measured at intervals of 4-6 </p>

<p>months, the diagnosis of treatment failure was made late in 
most patients, especially those whose CD4 
+ cells were measured </p>

<p>at 6-month intervals. In our analyses, the most current CD4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>cell measurements were assigned to the previous month to 
account for possible late treatment failure diagnosis. 
We did not have HIV-RNA results for the patients, and there-
fore CD4 cell count were used to make failure diagnosis. It is like-
ly that some patients considered failed might not have failed and 
those with virological failure might have not been included into 
the study. Such misclassification of the failure diagnosis might 
have introduced selection bias. Moreover, practically, HIV 
RNA is known to influence both OI and physicians' decision 
in making switches. However, because physicians did not have 
the knowledge of the HIV-RNA results, it is unlikely that their 
decisions were directly influenced by the HIV RNA. High plasma </p>

<p>HIV-RNA leads to suppression of the patient's immunity, which 
is being reflected by the low CD4 cell count that was controlled 
for in this study. 
We compared switched versus not switched and timely 
switched versus delayed switched separately; however, compar-
ison of not switched versus timely switched and delayed 
switched in a single model is another alternative. Moreover, 
death could be a competing risk in a model assessing effects 
of switching and risk of OI or death, and therefore the resultant 
effect size could be biased. Furthermore, because patients who 
failed in 2004 would be much less likely to access second-line 
treatment than those in 2013, inclusion of the year of immuno-
logical failure in the estimation of the propensity score proba-
bilities would have slightly changed propensity score effects size. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The risk of OI and death is reduced among patients switched to 
second-line ART after a diagnosis of immunological failure is 
made. Furthermore, the risk of opportunistic infection is higher 
when the delay to switch is 3 months or longer from the time of 
failure. Delay in switching could mainly be due to uncertainties 
physicians have due to the relatively poor ability of the WHO 
immunological failure criteria to predict virological failure. If 
this theory is true, efforts should be made to invest in viral 
load testing equipment to improve the timing of failure diagno-
sis and manage patients accordingly. This process could be 
made possible by placing a central testing laboratory where pa-
tients' dry blood spots from different care and treatment centers 
could be evaluated. Dry blood spot is known to reduce logistic 
difficulties and the cost that is associated with the use of plasma. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank the management of the 5 care and treatment centers for invalu-
able assistance in conducting the study. We also thank study participants 
and other staff members for their assistance with this study. Moreover, we 
thank Haji M. Ally and Mariana A. Mallya for data extraction. 
Financial support. This work was supported by Duke Center for AIDS 
Research, a National Institutes of Health-funded program (P30 AI064518-06). 
Potential conflicts of interest. All authors: No reported conflicts. All 
authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Con-
flicts of Interest. </p>







<p>The Effect of Switching to Second-Line Antiretroviral Therapy • OFID • 7 </p>

</text></tei>