<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4004907" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Atherosclerosis begins in childhood. Protection from atherosclerosis is provided by high-
density lipoprotein (HDL), a heterogeneous particle, which includes several subclasses differing in size, 
density and apolipoprotein content. The objective of this study was to document the relevance of assessing 
HDL particle size as another feature of dyslipidemia related to the develpment of atheosclerosis during 
childhood. For that purpose, HDL particle size in 268 community-based children (137 boys and 131 girls), 
7-13 years old, was measured by gradient gel electrophoresis, and relationships of HDL particle size to 
plasma lipids parameters and the anthropometric indices were analyzed. There was no gender difference 
in HDL particle diameter. The results of analysis revealed significant positive correlations between HDL 
particle diameter and HDL-cholesterol level (r=0.363, p&lt;0.01), apolipoprotein AI level (r=0.310, r&lt;0.05) 
and low-density lipoprotein particle (LDL) size (r=0.290, p&lt;0.05), while there was an inverse correlation 
with atherogenic index (r=-0.316, p&lt;0.05). There was no significant correlation between HDL particle size 
and triglyceride levels in the overall analysis (n=268), however, when this relation was analyzed in the 
limited HDL size range below 11 nm, a significant inverse relation appeared between particle size and TG 
levels (r =-0.546, P&lt;0.01, n=75). These findings indicate that the general shift toward smaller HDL particle 
size was associated with dyslipidemia characterized by higher atherogenic index and triglyceride level, 
lower HDL-C level and smaller LDL particle size. Therefore, HDL size may represent another relevant 
marker of atherogenic lipid metabolism. </p>

<p>Numerous prospective epidemiological 
studies have firmly established that high-density 
lipoprotein (HDL), as assessed by its cholesterol </p>

<p>content, is inversely correlated with the incidence 
and prevalence of coronary heart disease due to 
atherosclerosis (1). The anti-atherogenic action of 
HDL is probably related to reverse cholesterol 
transport by which excess peripheral cholesterol is 
returned to the liver (2). However, HDL is 
heterogeneous, encompassing several subclasses 
differing in size, density and apolipoprotein 
content. Several approaches, such as 
ultracentrifugation, precipitation, immunoaffinity 
c hr o m a to gr a ph y, a nd v ar i o us t ype s o f </p>

<p>Received: October 23, 2003 
Accepted: December 9, 2003 
Correspondence: Dr. Osamu Arisaka, Department of 
Pediatrics, Dokkyo University School of Medicine, Mibu-
cho, Kitakobayashi 880, Tochigi-ken 321-0293, Japan 
E-mail: arisaka@dokkyomed.ac.jp </p>

<p>Numata 
2 
Vol.13 / No.1 </p>

<p>electrophoresis, have been used to isolate and 
characterize HDL subpopulations. As previous 
studies have shown, in agarose gel electrophoresis, 
most HDL has α-mobility, while some shown pre-β 
mobility. By gradient gel electrophoresis, pre β-
HDL can be further separated into pre β 1 -HDL, pre 
β 2 -HDL and pre β 3 -HDL, while α-HDL can be </p>

<p>separated into five distinct subpopulations, HDL 3c , 
HDL 3b , HDL 3a , HDL 2a and HDL 2b , according to 
increasing particle size (3, 4). 
During the past few years, several reports 
have indicated that patients with hyperlipidemia/ 
dyslipidemia often have altered HDL subclass 
distributions. Recent studies using this 
classification have found relationships between 
HDL subclasses and different metabolic and 
anthropometric parameters. That is, it has been 
demonstrated that patients with hyperlipidemia 
have increased concentrations of small HDL 
particles (HDL 3b and HDL 3c ) and decreased 
concentrations of large HDL particles (HDL 2b and 
H DL 2a ) ( 5 ) . Fu r th ermo re, it ha s b ee n 
demonstrated that there are positive correlations 
between increased body mass index (BMI) and 
higher levels of HDL 3b and lower levels of HDL 2b , 
and inverse correlerations between fasting plasma 
insulin concentrations and plasma HDL 3a , HDL 2a , 
and HDL 2b (6). A very recent report proposed that 
lipoprotein subclass parameters can be used to 
manage risk more effectively and prevent 
cardiovascular disease in patients with insulin 
resistance (7). It is widely recognized that the 
insulin resistant state is associated with 
dyslipidemia and increased cardiovascular disease 
risk (8, 9). 
The childhood origin of atherosclerosis is well 
recognized, as is the expression in childhood of 
characteristics that place individuals at increased 
risk for atherosclesois later in life. Atherosclerosis 
begins during childhood (10, 11). Although the 
relationships of low-density lipoprotein (LDL) 
particle subclass and particle size to the insulin 
resistant state or atherogenic metabolic state have 
received considerable attention even in children </p>

<p>(12-14), there have been relatively few studies 
regarding HDL subclass or particle size in children 
(15-19). 
This study was carried out to document the 
relevance of assessing HDL particle size as another 
feature of atherogenic dyslipidemia found in 
children, using a recently described method (20). 
The relationship between HDL particle size and 
various parameters was analyzed. Findings 
obtained in this study could provide additional 
information for understanding the pathogenesis of 
atherosclerosis in children. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Subjects 
The study subjects were 268 school children 
(137 boys and 131 girls) 7 to 13 yr of age, residing 
in S-cho, Chiba, Japan. Parents or guardians of all 
the children gave infor med consent for 
participation in the study. Children with diabetes 
mellitus, thyroid disease, chronic renal disease, or 
hepatobilliary disease were excluded from this 
study. 
After an overnight fast, morning venous blood 
samples were collected from the children at school. 
The obesity index was calculated as follows: 
Obesity index = [(body weight -ideal weight)/ideal 
weight)] × 100. Children whose obesity index was 
over 20% were considered to be obese. The body 
mass index (BMI) was also calculated from the 
weight and height. </p>

<p>Lipid measurements 
In regard to individual plasma lipid 
p ar am e t e r s , t o t a l c h o l e s t e r o l ( TC ) an d 
triglycerides (TG) were determined enzymaticaly. 
HDL-C was measured by precipitation of other 
lipoproteins using the phosphowolframic acid 
method. LDL-C was calculated using Friedewald's 
formula (21). Apolipoproteins (ApoA1 and ApoB) 
were quantified by turbidimetric immunoassay. 
The atherogenic index (AI) was calculated as 
follows: AI = [TC -HDL-C] ÷ HDL-C. An AI value </p>

<p>HDL Particle Size and Atherosclerosis </p>

<p> 
June 2004 </p>

<p>below 3 is considered normal (22). </p>

<p>Gradient gel electrophoresis of plasma samples 
The HDL particle diameter was determined 
according to the method described by Perusse et al 
(20), by gradient gel electrophoresis using 4 to 25% 
polyacrylamide. After the gels had been 
equilibrated at 120 V for 60 min, electrophoresis 
was performed for each gel containing the serum 
sample diluted 1:2 with sample buffer (consisting 
of 40% sucrose, 0.06% EDTA-2Na, and 0.01% BPP), 
to a volume of 20 µL. Each gel also contained 
thyroglobulin, ferritin, catalase, and lactate 
dehydrogenase as reference standards of known 
diameter. The gels were then electrophoresed at 
15 V for 15 min, followed by migration at 70 V for 
20 min, at 75 V for 16 h, and finally at 125 V for 8 
h. The gels were then stained for lipid overnight 
with Sudan Black, and for reference standards 
with Coomassie Brilliant Blue for 45 min. They 
were then decolorified with ethanol and kept 
immersed in acetic acid. The decolorified gels 
were then scanned with an image scanner (Epson 
GT-6500: Seiko Epson Corporation, Nagano, 
Japan) and analyzed using an image processing 
and analysis program for Macintosh (<rs id="software-0" type="software">NIH Image</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">1.61</rs>: <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>, United States). 
Migration distances were determined. The HDL 
particle diameter was then calculated by 
comparing the mobility of the sample with that of 
the three calibrated standards on each gel. A 
higher integrated HDL size indicated a greater 
proportion of "large" HDL particles, whereas a low 
HDL size suggested an increased prevalence of 
"small" HDL particles. Inter-and intra-assay 
coefficients of variation for the integrated HDL size 
assessed by this method were &lt; 3% (n=10) and &lt;2% 
(n=9), respectively. 
Low-density lipoprotein (LDL) particle size 
was also measured, using the present blood 
sampl es, according to t he gradi ent gel 
electrophoresis method reported by Krauss (23) 
and Arisaka (11); type of solutions, duration time 
of electrophoresis, electric voltage, type of lipid </p>

<p>staining, and reference standard substances 
differed from the present HDL electrophoresis. 
The data for LDL particle size has been reported 
elsewhere (14). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The relationships between HDL particle size 
and various parameters were analyzed. An 
unpaired Student's t-test was done to compare 
boys and gi rls for vari ous parameters. 
Relationships between HDL particle size and the 
individual parameters of the lipid profile were 
analyzed using Spearman's non parametric rank 
correlation. p&lt;0.05 was considered to denote a 
statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>1) Table 1 shows the characteristics of 
subjects' profiles by sex. There was no statistically 
significant difference regarding obesity index and 
various lipid levels between boys and girls. 
2) The HDL particle diameter was 11.4 (mean) 
± 0.61 (SD) nm in boys and 11.4 ± 0.50 nm in girls, </p>

<p>not a statistically significant difference. Even 
though particle size was analyzed by dividing 
children into two age groups, those above 10 yr old 
(11.8 ± 0.55 nm, n=162) and those below 10 yr 
(11.5 ± 0.62, n=122), there was no difference 
between boys and girls in either age group. 
3) Relationships between HDL particle 
diameter and known individual risk factors for 
atherosclerosis were evaluated for boys and girls 
combined, boys alone, and girls alone. There were 
no apparent gender differences. Therefore, we 
analyzed the data from boys and girls together 
(Table 2, Figs. 1-5). 
The HDL particle diameter showed a 
significant positive correlation with HDL-C 
(r=0.363, p&lt;0.001) and ApoA1 (r=0.310, p&lt;0.05), 
while it showed an inverse correlations with AI 
(r=-0.316, p&lt;0.05) and BMI (r=-0.138, p&lt;0.05). No 
statistically significant correlation was noted 
between HDL particle size and TC, LDL-C, ApoB, </p>

<p>Numata 
 
Vol.13 / No.1 </p>

<p>TG, obesity index or blood pressure. 
4) There was no significant correlation 
between HDL particle size and TG levels in the 
overall analysis (n=268), however, when this 
relation was analyzed in the limited HDL size range 
below 11 nm, a significant inverse relation 
appeared between particle size and TG levels (r= 
-0.546, p&lt;0.01, n=75) (Fig. 2). 
5) There was a statistically significant 
correlation between HDL particle size and LDL 
particle size (r=0.290, p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Changes in HDL particle size, in association 
with changes in HDL subclasses distribution are 
considered to reflect the metabolic process of 
uptake and transport of cholesterol by circulating 
HDL. Also, changes in HDL particle size may be 
related to altered lipid metabolism caused by 
insulin resistance, which is the background of 
atherosclerosis (24-26). 
Several factors regulating HDL particle size 
are considered. Lipoprotein lipase is the rate-
limiting enzyme in the clearance of TG-rich 
lipoproteins from plasma and is involved in the 
formation of HDL, whereas hepatic lipase plays a 
role in the catabolism of HDL. Therefore, 
abnormalities in the regulation of TG metabolism 
by lipoprotein lipase and hepatic lipase may 
reduce HDL levels. Furthermore, cholesteryl ester 
transfer protein (CETP) and phospholipid transfer 
protein (PLTP) are two other factors involved in 
the metabolism of HDL (26, 27). PLTP and CETP 
are released from adipose tissues and appear to 
directly modulate lipoprotein metabolism: 
enhanced PLTP activity results in a lower HDL-C 
fraction accompanied by a relative increase in 
small pre β-HDL. CETP also catalyzes the transfer 
of cholesteryl ester from HDL to TG-rich 
lipoprotein in exchange for TG and leads to an 
enrichment of HDL and LDL with TG. TG-enriched </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of subjects by sex </p>

<p>Boys (n=137) 
Girls (n=131) 
p value </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
11.79 ± 0.15 
11.87 ± 0.14 
NS 
Obesity Index (%) 
10.50 ± 0.83 
4.00 ± 0.27 
NS 
TC (mg/dl) 
182.00 ± 2.33 
156.83 ± 2.71 
NS 
LDL-C (mg/dl) 
100.40 ± 2.03 
102.75 ± 2.31 
NS 
HDL-C (mg/dl) 
63.38 ± 1.23 
62.40 ± 1.37 
NS 
TG (mg/dl) 
91.09 ± 3.86 
90.98 ± 3.94 
NS 
ApoA1 (mg/dl) 
152.46 ± 1.70 
150.69 ± 1.91 
NS 
ApoB (mg/dl) 
79.83 ± 1.35 
82.00 ± 1.61 
NS 
Atherogenic Index 
2.00 ± 0.06 
2.08 ± 0.07 
NS </p>

<p>Mean ± SE, NS: Not significant. </p>

<p>Table 2 Relationship between HDL particle size and 
individual lipid levels, anthropometric indi-
ces and blood pressure in 268 children </p>

<p>r 
p -v a l u e </p>

<p>Total cholesterol 
0.128 
NS 
LDL-cholesterol 
-0.015 
NS 
HDL-cholesterol 
0.363 
p&lt;0.01 
Triglyceride 
-0.112 
NS 
HDL≤11 nm 
-0.546 
p&lt;0.01 
ApoA1 
0.310 
p&lt;0.05 
ApoB 
-0.069 
NS 
LDL particle size 
0.290 
p&lt;0.05 
Atherogenic index 
-0.316 
p&lt;0.05 
Body mass index 
-0.138 
p&lt;0.05 
Obesity index 
-0.127 
NS 
Systolic blood pressure 
-0.102 
NS 
Diastolic blood pressure 
-0.04 
NS </p>

<p>NS: Not significant. </p>

<p>HDL Particle Size and Atherosclerosis </p>

<p> 
June 2004 </p>

<p>HDL and LDL particles can be subjected to further 
lipolysis by hepatic lipase, leading to the formation 
of small, dense HDL and LDL particles (28, 29). In 
obesity, increased synthesis of these lipid transfer 
proteins by the enlarged mass of adipose tissue 
occurs and it has been demonstrated that weight </p>

<p>reduction is associated with a decrease in plasma 
CETP activity (30-32). Factors that promote the 
conversion of HDL and LDL into populations of 
smaller particles is thought to be related to insulin 
resistance (19, 32). 
Relatively few studies have examined HDL </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Relationship between HDL particle diameter and HDL-cholesterol 
level. </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Relationship between HDL particle diameter (range below 11 nm) and 
triglycerides level. </p>

<p>Numata 
6 
Vol.13 / No.1 </p>

<p>particle size in children (15-19). In the present 
study, relationships among lipids, lipoproteins, 
anthropometric measures and HDL particle sizes 
in children were investigated. It was found that 
HDL particle size showed a general shift toward 
smaller size in association with decreased HDL-C 
and ApoA1, and increased atherogenic index, TG </p>

<p>and BMI, indicating the features of atherogenic 
metabolic triad. Although circulating HDL-C 
concentration is recognized for its inverse 
association with the occurrence of cardiovascular 
disease, HDL-C is only moderately predictive of 
disease (1, 2). This is exactly because circulating 
HDL, as assessed by its cholesterol content (HDL-</p>

<p>Fig. 3 Relationship between HDL particle diameter and ApoA1 level. </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Relationship between HDL particle diameter and the atherogenic index. </p>

<p>HDL Particle Size and Atherosclerosis </p>

<p> 
June 2004 </p>

<p>C), does not reflect the heterogeneity of HDL 
particles (HDL subfractions). Therefore, it is 
reasonable that HDL particle size and HDL-C level 
are not strongly correlated, as shown in the present 
study. These results favor the idea that the low 
cardiovascular disease risk may be due in part to 
their anti-atherogenic HDL pattern, rather than the 
HDL-C concentration. In addition, no significant 
correlation was found between HDL particle size 
and either TC or LDL-C,providing further support 
for the previously published notion that the 
measurement of TC or LDL-C alone does not allow 
proper identification of individuals who are 
carriers of atherogenic dyslipidemia. 
Regarding the relationship between HDL 
particle size and plasma TG levels, a tendency for an 
inverse relationship was recognized in the HDL size 
ranges below approximately 11 nm. However, in 
the diameter ranges above 11 nm, this association 
was not found. The association of reduced HDL 
particle size with elevated TG may be explained by 
the bidirectional exchange of TG between HDL and 
TG-rich lipoprotein: hypertriglyceridemia appears 
to promote TG transfer from TG-enriched 
lipoprotein to HDL particles under the action of 
CETP with a subsequent hydrolysis of TG-enriched 
HDL by hepatic lipase or lipoprotein lipase, </p>

<p>producing small HDL particles (4, 28, 32, 34). 
Although it is thought that TG is a critical 
component of lipoprotein particles and plasma TG 
level affects lipoprotein size, both TG level -related 
metabolic effect and TG level-independent genetic 
effect may be operated for determining HDL 
particle size (4, 35). 
We also noted a positive relationship between 
HDL particle size and LDL particle size, suggesting 
that the synergic reduction in the size of these two 
lipoproteins may be the consequence of a common 
metabolic alteration, probably related to insulin 
resistance (8, 9, 23, 24). Therefore, HDL size may 
represent another relevant marker of atherogenic 
dysmetabolism. 
In conclusion, although the mechanisms by 
which HDL size could affect cardiovascular disease 
risk remain to be further investigated, the results of 
this study imply that a general shift toward smaller 
HDL partic le size may be r elated to the 
pathogenesis of atherosclerosis in children. 
Therefore, HDL size may represent another 
relevant marker of atherogenic lipid metabolism. 
Prospective studies are clearly warranted to 
quantify the contribution of HDL particle size to 
the evaluation of the future risk of cardiovascular 
disease development. </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Relationship between HDL particle diameter and LDL particle diameter. </p>

<p>Numata 
8 
Vol.13 / No.1 </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>I wish to thank Professor Osamu Arisaka, MD 
for his tremendous support and enhancement of 
this study. Also, I wish to thank Yasuyo Kawai for 
her expert assistance with the laboratory studies. 
This study was supported by grants from Dokkyo 
University School of Medicine, along with a 
research encouragement prize and from Japan 
Study Group for Obesity and Related Metabolism 
in Childhood and Adolescence. A summary of this 
article was presented at the the 106th Annual 
Meeting of the Japanese Society of Pediatrics in 
2003 held in Fukuoka. </p>



<p>HDL Particle Size and Atherosclerosis </p>

<p> 
June 2004 </p>



</text></tei>