<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4626665" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT. Viable biocontrol agents for mosquito control are quite rare, therefore improving the efficacy of existing biological agents is 
an important study. We need to have a better understanding of the predation-risk behavioral responses toward prey. This research ex-
amined prey choices by Toxorhynchites splendens by monitoring the behavioral responses of Aedes aegypti, Aedes albopictus, and 
Anopheles sinensis larvae when exposed to the predator. The results show that Tx. splendens prefers to consume Ae. aegypti larvae. 
The larvae exhibited different behavioral responses when Tx. splendens was present which suggest vulnerability in the presence of 
predators. "Thrashing" and "browsing" activities were greater in Ae. aegypti larvae. Such active and risky movements could cause 
vulnerability for the Ae. aegypti larvae due to increasing of water disturbance. In contrast, Ae. albopictus and An. sinensis larvae 
exhibited passive, low-risk behaviors, spending most of the time on the "wall" position near the edges of the container. We postulated 
that Ae. aegypti has less ability to perceive cues from predation and could not successfully alter its behavior to reduce risk of predation 
risk compared with Ae. albopictus and An. sinensis. Our results suggest that Tx. splendens is a suitable biocontrol agent in controlling 
dengue hemorrhagic vector, Ae. aegypti. </p>

<p>predatory Tx. splendens larva and also its residual kairomones remnant. 
We emphasize on the behavior response of Ae. aegypti since the species 
is the main dengue vector threat in Malaysia. The inclusion of the other 
two species serves as a comparative factor. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Predator and Prey Colonies. Predatory mosquito (Tx. splendens) 
was obtained from Vector Control Research Unit (VCRU), Universiti 
Sains Malaysia. The strain originated from Penang Hill, Malaysia 
(5 
42'46" N, 100 
26'89" E) and has been maintained in the laboratory 
since 1980s. Tx. Splendens are unusually large mosquitoes; the wing-
span may exceed 12 mm, while the body length may exceed 7 mm. 
Larvae are generally dark brown or reddish in appearance, with very 
conspicuous hairs on the abdomen. The head capsule is quite thick and 
contains powerful mandibles. Fourth-instar larvae (sizes from 6 to 
9 mm) were used for the experiment. 
Late third-and early fourth-instar larvae of Ae. aegypti, Ae. albopic-
tus, and An. sinensis (VCRU strain) were utilized as prey. All of the 
mosquitoes prey strain have been cultured and maintained in VCRU 
laboratory since 1980s for more than 600 generations. Female mosqui-
toes were blood fed using mice. Aedes were fed for 2 h, starting from 
1900 to 2100 hours and Anopheles were fed from 2100 to 2300 hours 
(peak biting hour). After 2 d, we offered oviposition substrate and col-
lected the eggs from each species. Each species was reared separately in 
containers filled with aged tap water. The larvae were allowed to grow 
until late third and early fourth-instar larvae to be used in the experi-
ment. Aedes and Anopheles larvae were fed with 1 mg of fine powder of 
larval food daily. The larva food consists of a mixture of dog biscuit, 
beef liver, yeast, and milk powder. Larval food for Anopheles larvae 
consists of nestum, milk powder, yeast, oat, and wheat germ. 
Both predator and prey larvae culture were maintained in an insecta-
rium with temperature of 28 6 0.2 
C, 81 6 2.0% relative humidity 
(RH), and a photoperiod of 12:12 (L:D) h. 
Prey Preferences Test. The first experiment was to test the prey 
preferences of Tx. splendens toward the three different species of 
mosquito larvae. The experiment was conducted using a total of 20 
preys in 500 ml of seasoned or aged tap water in containers measur-
ing 6.5 Â 17.5 Â 11 cm (height Â length Â width). The ratios of mos-
quito larvae offered to a predator were 0:20; 3:17; 5:15; 7:13; 10:10; 
13:7; 15:5; 17:3; and 20:0 (Ae. aegypti:Ae. albopictus). A same ratio 
was also applied for Ae. aegypti:An. sinensis. We did not conduct a 
comparison between Ae. albopictus and An. sinensis since the main 
focus is more on Ae. aegypti. We specifically chose Anopheles spe-
cies due to its different feeding behavior from Aedes species. 
Anopheles species mostly feeds on suspended particles on water sur-
face (Ye-ebiyo et al. 2003), whereas Aedes species relies on sub-
merged feeding. The feeding is near or at the water surface (Merrit  et al. 1992). 
After 24 h of exposure, the Tx. splendens predator was removed 
from the container using a pipette, and the remaining number of prey 
was counted and identified to separate the species under a light micro-
scope. The experiment was conducted in laboratory conditions with 
temperature of 26 6 1 
C and 65-85% humidity. Each experiment was 
replicated six times. 
Prey preferences were determined by using Manly's a (Manly  1974) equation with Chesson's (1982) alteration to account for prey 
depletion (e.g., the comparison between Ae. aegypti against An. 
sinensis): </p>

<p>a ¼ 
lnðN Ae À C Ae Þ=N Ae 
lnððN Ae À C Ae Þ þ lnðN An À C An Þ=N An Þ 
(1) </p>

<p>where N is the initial number and C is the number of larvae consumed 
of Ae. aegypti (Ae) and An. sinensis (An). </p>

<p>We also can predict the preferences (a) of Tx. splendens predator 
with this multiplicative formula: </p>

<p>a a ¼ 
a Ae 
a Ae þ a An À ða Ae a An Þ 
(2) </p>

<p>Where a a is the predicted preference of Tx. splendens predator for 
Ae. aegypti, a Ae and a An are attack constants for Ae. aegypti and An. 
sinensis, respectively. 
Predator Avoidance Behavior. Three different treatments were 
applied: 1) control; without any predator; 2) prey alongside with a free 
roaming predator, and 3) when prey was placed in water which contains 
residual predator's kairomones but without the actual predators. 
Kairomones was defined by Nourdland and Lewis (1976) as a sub-
stance that is released, acquired, or produced by organism which, when 
it comes into contact with another species in natural context. This sub-
stance will evoke the behavioral and physiological reactions of the 
receiver but not the emitter. In this study, the emitter refers to Tx. splen-
dens larva, and the receivers are Aedes and Anopheles mosquito larvae. 
For residual kairomones preparation, a predator was released in 500 ml 
seasoned water and fed with 10 mosquito larvae for 24 h prior to the 
start of the treatment. Feeding is crucial to simulate the kairomones 
release by injured prey (Dodson et al. 1994, Kats and Dill 1998, Kusch  et al. 2004) and production of remnants exists from predation event 
(Kesavaraju and Juliano 2004). After 24 h, the predator and the remain-
ing prey were discarded using a pipette. We then proceeded to use the 
residual kairomone water (for treatment 3). 
For treatment 2, mosquito larva prey was placed in a plastic con-
tainer filled with 500 ml seasoned water. Seasoned water is tap water 
that has been left standing 24 h to reduce the chlorine content. After 
approximately 10-mins period of acclimation time, a Tx. splendens 
predator was added into the same container. The behaviors and posi-
tions of prey were recorded for 30 min or until it was captured. We cate-
gorized the behavior into four types of activity based on Juliano and  Reminger (1992): 1) resting-larva neither feeding nor moving; 2) 
browsing-larva propelled along the surface of the container by the 
movements of their mouthparts; 3) filtering-larva floating in the water 
column propelled by the movements of their mouthparts; and 4) thrash-
ing-vigorous lateral movements of the larval body, propelling them-
selves through the water. Four positions were also categorized as; 1) 
surface-spiracular siphon of the larva in contact of the water-air inter-
face; 2) bottom-larva within 1 mm of the bottom of the container; 3) 
wall-larva within 1 mm from any surface of the container walls; and 
4) middle-larva more than 1 mm from any surface of the container 
and not in contact with the water surface. All experiments were con-
ducted in laboratory conditions with temperature of 26 6 1 
C and 
65-85% humidity. All treatments were replicated six times. 
The behavioral data were analyzed using multinomial logistic regres-
sion in <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">20.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">2012</rs>). We recode the behavior categories from 1 
to 4 for activities and 5 to 8 for positions as follows: 1) resting; 2) brows-
ing; 3) filtering; 4) thrashing; 5) surface; 6) bottom; 7) wall; and 8) mid-
dle, which were then modeled as being dependent on prey species (Ae. 
aegypti, Ae. albopictus, and An. sinensis) and treatments (control, free-
roaming predator, and residual kairomones remnant). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Prey Preferences Study. Result shows that Tx. splendens consumed 
more Ae. aegypti larvae when varied ratios of Ae. aegypti and Ae. albo-
pictus were offered (Fig. 1). Similar result was also achieved, where 
Ae. aegypti were mostly consumed compared with An. sinensis (Fig. 2). 
This can be inferred by observing both of Figs. 1 and 2 where all the 
values of preference (a) lies above the broken line, a ¼ 0.667 which 
suggests that Tx. splendens preferred Ae. aegypti larvae over the other 
two species. The value of a ¼ 0.667 was calculated using Manly's </p>

<p> 
JOURNAL OF INSECT SCIENCE 
VOLUME 15 </p>

<p>preference selectivity index (a) for nonselective feeding (Manly 1974)  and value that lies on a ¼ 0.667 describe as no preferences toward cer-
tain species of prey. 
Predator Avoidance Behavior. The multinomial logistic likelihood 
ratio test shows significant effects (P &lt; 0.05) between species (x 
2 ¼ 49.36, 
df ¼ 2, P &lt; 0.0001), types of treatment (x 
2 ¼ 49.36, df ¼ 2, P &lt; 0.0001), 
and activities exhibit by larvae (x 
2 ¼ 219.54, df ¼ 7, P &lt; 0.0001). 
The most vulnerable larvae to Tx. splendens predation, Ae. aegypti 
showed high frequency of "thrashing" activity at the "wall" position 
when facing the predator. In the absence of predator (control treatment), 
more "resting" activity at "surface," "wall," and "middle" positions 
were exhibited. However, in residual kairomones treatment, Ae. aegypti 
exhibited more "browsing" activity (Fig. 3a). In contrast, Ae. albopictus 
displayed less activity and positioning in the presence of predator 
(Fig. 3b). An. sinensis exhibited safer, low-risk activity such as 
"resting" in presence of predator similar to control condition (Fig. 3c). 
The Cox and Snell's pseudo statistic showed that less than half of 
the variation in prey behavior was explained by the model (R 
2 ¼ 0.35). </p>

<p>Table 1 lists the parameter estimates from the model that shows each 
factor tested was compared with reference factor. Ae. aegypti, kairo-
mones treatment, filtering activity and middle position were served as 
reference factor. Based on the multinomial logistic regression, Ae. albo-
pictus prey was prone to display more "browsing" behavior (odds 
ratio ¼ 10.67, df ¼ 1, P ¼ 0.001) at the "bottom" odds ratio ¼ 17.50, 
df ¼ 1, P &lt; 0.0001) and "wall" positions (odds ratio ¼ 6.68, df ¼ 1, 
P ¼ 0.010) compared with reference category, Ae. aegypti. However, 
no significant differences were observed among all treatments for both 
Aedes species (P &gt; 0.05). 
In predator treatment, there was a significant difference in behavior 
between Ae. aegypti and An. sinensis (odds ratio ¼ 27. 95, df ¼ 1, 
P &lt; 0.0001), with An. sinensis larvae showed high frequency of 
"resting" (odds ratio ¼ 63.51, df ¼ 1, P &lt; 0.0001) at the "surface" 
(odds ratio ¼ 99.72, df ¼ 1, P &lt; 0.0001) and "wall" of the container 
(odds ratio ¼ 67.42, df ¼ 1, P &lt; 0.0001) in response toward predation 
risk posed by Tx. splendens. This low risk behavior by An. sinensis 
reduces the possibility of the larvae to be captured/eaten. </p>

<p>Discussions </p>

<p>Tx. splendens showed preference toward Ae. aegypti, even when 
Ae. albopictus and An. sinensis were offered together in this study. 
Tx. splendens preferred to attack Ae. aegypti even at a few number per-
ratio of the other two species. In our study, prey switching toward higher 
density of certain species did not occur, which means that Tx. splendens 
still prefers to consume Ae. aegypti. We suggest that Tx. splendens is a 
very effective predator and has a strong potential to control Ae. aegypti, 
the main vector of the dengue hemorrhagic fever in Malaysia. 
Ae. Aegyti and Ae. albopictus are two main vectors of dengue hem-
orrhagic fever and dengue fever, a mosquito-borne infectious disease 
that constitutes on a growing global threat especially in Asian countries. 
Domestic Ae. aegypti and Ae. Albopictus tend to have ubiquitous breed-
ing sites in artificial containers and natural sites close to human habita-
tions (Scott et al. 2000, Gubler 2012, Thavara et al. 2004, Dieng et al.  2010). Aedes species is associated with the presence of Tx. splendens 
predator because both species share the same breeding habitat. 
Tx. splendens is a container breeder and found in a wide variety of both 
artificial and natural containers (Steffan and Evenhuis 1981), whereas 
both Aedes prey was reported to coexisted together with the predator in 
bamboo stumps, rubber tires, earthen-ware jars, and cans (Trpis 1973,  Nyamah et al. 2011). However, shared breeding habitat does not occur 
between An. sinensis and Tx. splendens predator. This is due to different 
breeding habitat preference of Anopheles, which prefers clean and 
unpolluted water (Abu Hassan and Yap 2003) of running water 
(streams, irrigation, drainage, and slow running rivers) with dense of 
aquatic vegetations (Mattingly 1969). Therefore, as an initiative to con-
trol for Anopheles, Tx. splendens predator must first be introduced into 
the prey's natural breeding habitat. 
However, if the predator demonstrates a strong preference on one 
particular prey species, the prey is believed to be able to endure 
the highest level of predation (Bonsall and Hassell 1999). In our 
study, Ae. aegypti populations can be estimated by the existence of 
Tx. splendens predator. Ae. aegypti larvae are the preferred prey even at 
low density. Thus, when predation is more aggressive on the superior 
prey competitor, the inferior prey competitor may be able to coexist 
through a keystone predator effect (Paine 1966). 
Predator preference is predicted to shift according to prey density 
availability (Mauck and Coble 1971, Savino and Stein 1989) and 
thought to occur through mechanisms of density-dependent predation 
and switching behavior (Holling 1965, Murdoch and Oaten 1975,  Hassell and Comins 1978). Holt and Lawton (1994) pointed out that an 
apparent mutualism can occur between competing prey species when 
the presence of either one would lower the predation rates on the other. 
For example, selective predation of Corethrella appendiculata and </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The preference of Tx. splendens for Ae. aegypti larvae 
compared with Ae. albopictus larvae, indicated by (a) (6SE). The 
broken line indicates no preferences for either mosquito larvae, at 
a ¼ 0.667. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The preference of Tx. splendens for Ae. aegypti larvae 
compared with An. sinensis larvae, indicated by (a) (6SE). The 
broken line indicates no preferences for either mosquito larvae, at 
a ¼ 0.667. </p>

<p> 
ZUHARAH ET AL.: RISKY BEHAVIOR OF MOSQUITOES </p>

<p>
Toxorhynchites rutilus on Ae. albopictus may also reduce predation on 
Ae. triseriatus, thus enabling this species to propagate in numbers 
(Griswold and Lounibos 2005). However, in this study, Tx. splendens 
showed preference to consume Ae. aegypti even at a lower number per-
ratio compared with the Ae. albopictus and An. sinensis. Based on den-
sity-dependent theory, the low density population will remain safe and 
high population will be decimated to a minimum number. This turn of 
events allows the low density population to grow rapidly. However, we 
found no such evidence in our study to support this theory. We postulate 
that the predation interest by Tx. splendens is caused by the behavior 
and positioning of Ae. aegypti prey when confronted by the predator. 
The risky and active behavior and positioning attract predators making 
the prey to be more vulnerable. 
More than 70% of Ae. aegypti larvae captured by Toxorhynchites 
larvae occurred when the predaceous larvae were not in contact with </p>

<p>the water surface (Russo 1986) and were relatively motionless, waiting 
to ambush the prey (Steffan and Evenhuis 1981). Sometimes, Tx. splen-
dens larvae would swim toward a group of prey larvae, and the most 
attacks were on swimming prey larvae (Russo 1986, Linley and  Darling 1993, Griswold and Lounibos 2005). Generally, 
Toxorhynchites larvae spend most of their time immobile, with the 
degree of activity patterns varying according to species (Clements  1999). There are three different mechanisms of prey capture displayed 
by Toxorhynchites larvae depending on certain conditions: 1) staying 
inactive and waiting for sub-surface prey to approach within striking 
distance; 2) swimming toward a particular prey that was trapped on the 
water surface; and 3) illustrating continual prey-finding activity after 
grabbing a floating egg (Clements 1999). 
From our observation, Tx. splendens favored the first mechanism to 
capture the prey instead of swimming toward potential prey </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Behavior of three species of mosquito larvae (A) Ae. aegypti, (B) Ae. albopictus, and (C) An. sinensis in response to various treatments 
of control (absence of predator), with predator and predator's kairomones only. </p>

<p> 
JOURNAL OF INSECT SCIENCE 
VOLUME 15 </p>

<p>(mechanism 2) and predatory Tx. splendens larvae would lie motionless 
on the bottom of the container and wait for the prey to swim across and 
capture them. Because of the active "thrashing" behavior flaunted by 
Ae. aegypti in the water, preys failed to detect the presence of predator 
and become an easy target. This passive hunting mechanism is suitable 
for Toxorhynchites, which is a phytotelmata breeder, meaning that rig-
orous movement is not an option in a small and restricted space. 
According to Clements (1999), the characteristic of a striking behavior 
of Toxorhynchites larvae also differs according to the position of 
approaching prey. When prey is situated directly in front of 
Toxorhynchites larva's head, the strike movement involved a rapid dis-
placement of the head toward the prey though extension of the neck by 
over 1 mm. Alternatively, if the prey approaches Toxorhynchites larva 
from the side or behind, the strike took form of a rapid, lateral bending 
that moved the predator's head toward the prey. 
Both Ae. aegypti and Ae. albopictus larvae displayed almost similar 
frequency of behavioral activities. However, Ae. albopictus larvae dis-
played high occurrence at "wall" position in contrast to Ae. aegypti. 
This evidence suggests that prey situated near the edge of the container 
was less susceptible than any alternative prey species which is con-
stantly moving. Sih (1979) also stated that among all the larvae that 
were captured by the predators, 98% were positioned more than 38 mm 
from the edge of the container, meaning that preys can be found within 
the central of 70% of the surface area of the container. We observed the 
similar pattern in our study. Therefore, the vulnerability of Ae. aegypti 
larvae to predator could be due to the prey positions which were likely 
to be found at the middle, bottom, and surface of the container. 
Because of the risky behaviors exhibited by Ae. aegypti which com-
prise "thrashing" and constantly "browsing" for food sources at the 
"surface" and "middle" of the container, it was not a surprise that 
Tx. splendens preferred to consume more on Ae. aegypti larvae instead 
of An. sinensis that continually adopted a low-risk behavior of "resting" 
at the "surface" and "wall" positions. Zuharah and Lester (2011) found 
that Aedes notoscriptus appeared to be more visible and more attractive </p>

<p>to predators by exhibiting thrashing behavior because vigorous move-
ment attracted predators. According to a study conducted by Nyamah  et al. (2011), Ae. albopictus larvae were reported to be moving actively, 
contrary to Culex fuscocephala (Theobald) and these behavioral char-
acteristics cause Tx. splendens to prey on Ae. albopictus. In our study, 
when Ae. aegypti larva was placed with a free roaming Tx. splendens 
larva in predator treatment, Ae. aegypti larva exhibited "thrashing" 
behavior, thus making it more vulnerable toward predation. 
The dynamics in the behavior could be attributed to the "threat sen-
sitivity hypothesis" which stated that a particular prey species would 
change their avoidance reaction according to the degree of the threat 
(Helfman, 1989). An. sinensis definitely displays such reaction, where 
there were significant behaviors displayed between An. sinensis and 
Ae. aegypti larvae when they were placed with predatory Tx. splendens. 
An. sinenis larva was seen to be "resting" at the "surface" of the con-
tainer "wall." According to Juliano and Reminger (1992), this resting 
behavior was the least risky behavior in the presence of a potential pred-
ator. However, it is also possible that the "wall' position displayed by 
An. sinensis was also due to its natural larval behavior where Anopheles 
larvae were said to demonstrate negative thigmotaxis, a tendency to 
maintain bodily contact with solid object and its locomotion reduced 
(Clements 1999). For instance, larvae of Anopheles minimus and 
Anopheles maculatus, when placed in an experimental water flow chan-
nel, anchored themselves to the edge (Muirhead-Thomson 1940), and 
this ability is due to its dorsal brush setae modified to form hooks which 
can be used to cling to any solid objects (Lamborn 1921). 
Aquatic organisms usually received warning about prospective pre-
dation events by means of visual (Chivers et al. 2001) and chemical 
information known as kairomones, which can be released by injured 
prey (Dodson et al. 1994, Kats and Dill 1998, Kusch et al. 2004), preda-
tion events, predators (Kesavaraju et al. 2007) solid residues from pre-
dation events on either conspecifics or competing prey (Kesavaraju and  Juliano 2004), and feces from predator that fed on conspecifics (Brown  et al. 1955a,b, 1966). There is also an evidence suggests that mosquito 
larval contact with solid residues while foraging were able to provide 
signal to the presence of predation threat (Kesavaraju and Juliano  2010). However, predation risk cues in aquatic systems can degrade if 
they are not replenished by additional predation events, and prey thus 
may alter their reactions depending on the degradation level (Ferrari  et al. 2005). In our study, Ae. aegypti, Ae. albopictus, and An. sinensis 
seem to display risky behavior of "thrashing" and "browsing" activities 
in kairomones treatments. It is possible that the 24 h residual kairo-
mones from Tx. splendens is not strong enough to elicit their avoidance 
behavior toward possible predator threats. Therefore, these larvae were 
freely exhibiting their normal activities without any concern of predator 
presence. 
In conclusion, behavioral response and positioning of prey are two 
important factors that contribute to the success and effectiveness of 
Tx. splendens as biocontrol agent. This biocontrol agent has signifi-
cantly reduced Ae. aegypti vector, subsequently providing a possible 
chance to reduce the threat of dengue hemorrhagic fever. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We are grateful to the staff of School of Biological Sciences, 
Universiti Sains Malaysia and Vector Control Research Unit, 
Universiti Sains Malaysia for field assistance and mosquito culture. 
This project was partially supported by Fundamental Research Grant 
Scheme (FRGS) Ministry of Higher Education Malaysia (203/ 
PBIOLOGI/6711359) and Short Term grant Universiti Sains Malaysia 
(304/PBIOLOGI/6311043). </p>



<p>Table 1. Results from multinomial logistic regression showing nomi-
nal parameter estimates from the model </p>

<p>Behavioral display 
B 
SE 
Wald 
df 
Sig. </p>

<p>Ae. albopictus 
Treatments 
Control 
0.096 
0.144 
0.443 
1 
0.506 
Predator 
0.273 
0.184 
2.218 
1 
0.136 
Kairomones 
0 
-
-
0 
-
Activities 
Resting 
0.912 
0.338 
7.299 
1 
0.007 
Thrashing 
0.485 
0.237 
4.178 
1 
0.041 
Browsing 
0.726 
0.222 
10.667 
1 
0.001 
Filtering 
0.340 
-
-
1 
-
Position 
Surface 
0.458 
0.287 
2.542 
1 
0.111 
Bottom 
0.914 
0.219 
17.499 
1 
0.0001 
Wall 
0.508 
0.917 
6.679 
1 
0.010 
Middle 
0 
-
-
0 
-
An. sinensis 
Treatments 
Control 
0.282 
0.165 
2.940 
1 
0.086 
Predator 
1.016 
0.192 
27.946 
1 
0.0001 
Kairomones 
0 
-
-
0 
-
Activities 
Resting 
2.268 
0.285 
63.514 
1 
0.0001 
Thrashing 
0.860 
0.485 
3.145 
1 
0.076 
Browsing 
1.277 
0.634 
4.057 
1 
0.044 
Filtering 
24.986 
8,061.007 
0.000 
1 
0.998 
Position 
Surface 
2.783 
0.279 
99.717 
1 
0.0001 
Bottom 
0.833 
0.316 
6.940 
1 
0.008 
Wall 
2.110 
0.257 
67.415 
1 
0.0001 
Middle 
0 
-
-
0 
-
The references category is Ae. aegypti. Significant values are in bold. </p>

<p> 
ZUHARAH ET AL.: RISKY BEHAVIOR OF MOSQUITOES </p>



<p>
 
JOURNAL OF INSECT SCIENCE 
VOLUME 15 </p>



<p>Received 5 July 2015; accepted 30 August 2015. </p>

<p> 
ZUHARAH ET AL.: RISKY BEHAVIOR OF MOSQUITOES </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>