<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4589655" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aims </p>

<p>Permanent cardiac pacing is the only effective treatment for symptomatic bradycardia, but complications associated 
with conventional transvenous pacing systems are commonly related to the pacing lead and pocket. We describe 
the early performance of a novel self-contained miniaturized pacemaker. </p>

<p>Methods 
and results </p>

<p>Patients having Class I or II indication for VVI pacing underwent implantation of a Micra transcatheter pacing system, 
from the femoral vein and fixated in the right ventricle using four protractible nitinol tines. Prespecified objectives were 
.85% freedom from unanticipated serious adverse device events (safety) and ,2 V 3-month mean pacing capture 
threshold at 0.24 ms pulse width (efficacy). Patients were implanted (n ¼ 140) from 23 centres in 11 countries 
(61% male, age 77.0 + 10.2 years) for atrioventricular block (66%) or sinus node dysfunction (29%) indications. During 
mean follow-up of 1.9 + 1.8 months, the safety endpoint was met with no unanticipated serious adverse device events. 
Thirty adverse events related to the system or procedure occurred, mostly due to transient dysrhythmias or femoral 
access complications. One pericardial effusion without tamponade occurred after 18 device deployments. In 60 patients 
followed to 3 months, mean pacing threshold was 0.51 + 0.22 V, and no threshold was ≥2 V, meeting the efficacy 
endpoint (P , 0.001). Average R-wave was 16.1 + 5.2 mV and impedance was 650.7 + 130 ohms. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Early assessment shows the transcatheter pacemaker can safely and effectively be applied. Long-term safety and benefit 
of the pacemaker will further be evaluated in the trial. </p>

<p>Clinical Trial 
Registration </p>

<p>ClinicalTrials.gov ID NCT02004873. </p>

<p>Permanent cardiac pacing, the only effective treatment for symptom-
atic bradycardia, reduces symptoms and recurrence of syncope, and 
improves survival in high-risk populations. 
1 -3 Since their introduction </p>

<p>in the 1960s, pacemakers have shrunk in size and grown in sophistica-
tion, yet their basic function remains to be sustaining a normal heart 
rate. Conventional pacing systems consist of a pacemaker containing 
the electronics and battery typically implanted in a subcutaneous 
pocket in the chest. One or more leads threaded from the device 
pocket through veins into the heart conduct the pacing therapy to 
the desired pacing site. When veins cannot be used, a surgical proced-
ure includes implanting epicardial leads that link the heart to the 
device. Despite the reduction in complications due to technological 
advances, serious adverse events can still be encountered. These 
are reported to be 20% at 5 years, with highest contributions related 
to the pacing lead ( 11%) and pocket ( 8%), 
4 including pneumo/ </p>

<p>haemothorax after subclavian vein puncture, pocket haematoma, 
erosion or infection, vein stenosis or occlusion, endocarditis, tricuspid 
valve trauma, connection troubles, lead fractures, and other malfunc-
tions. 
5 -8 Micra 
TM transcatheter pacing system (TPS, Model </p>

<p>MC1VR01, Medtronic plc, Mounds View, MN, USA) is a miniaturized 
single-chamber pacemaker system that is delivered via catheter 
through the femoral vein and implanted directly inside the right 
ventricle (RV) of the heart. This new technology is feasible due to ad-
vances in miniaturization (high-density battery), low-power electron-
ics, catheter delivery systems, novel materials (nitinol), and electrodes 
being directly placed on the pacemaker capsule. This eliminates the 
need for a device pocket and insertion of a pacing lead, thereby 
eliminating an important source of complications associated with 
traditional pacing systems while providing similar benefits. 
The purpose of this report is to summarize the early performance 
of the TPS using pre-specified safety and efficacy objectives from the 
Micra Transcatheter Pacing System Study. These data are being used 
to support European regulatory submission. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study design and oversight </p>

<p>The trial is a prospective, multi-site, single-arm, worldwide clinical study 
evaluating the safety and efficacy of the TPS. Briefly, the study will im-
plant up to 720 patients at up to 70 centres worldwide. All participants 
must satisfy standard criteria for de novo pacemaker implantation with 
Class I or II indications and provide written informed consent. The trial 
design is described in detail elsewhere. 
9 The trial is sponsored by the </p>

<p>manufacturer, Medtronic. The protocol was approved by the Ethics 
Committee at each participating institution and associated national 
and local regulatory agencies. Data of this ongoing study are collected 
by trained centre personnel, and data integrity maintained via program-
matic edit checks and source data verification by the sponsor. Safety and 
trial conduct oversight are provided by an independent data monitoring 
committee. </p>

<p>Study device and implant procedure </p>

<p>The transcatheter pacing system is a 0.8 cc, 2.0 g, self-contained, her-
metically enclosed capsule, single-chamber ventricular pacemaker 
with functionality and features similar to existing ventricular pace-
makers, inclusive of rate responsive pacing and automated pacing cap-
ture threshold management. The device is 25.9 mm in length, with an 
outer diameter of 6.7 mm. A nominal pulse width duration of 0.24 ms 
was chosen since it is near the chronaxie of the strength duration 
curve. 
10 Utilizing a pulse width near the chronaxie should minimize pa-</p>

<p>cing energy and improve battery longevity. By design, it is conditionally 
safe for full body magnetic resonance imaging in 1.5 and 3.0 Tesla scan-
ners. The device is fixated via four electrically inactive protractible nit-
inol tines located on the distal end of the device (Figure 1). 
The TPS is tethered to and sits in a cup at the distal end of a steerable 
transfemoral catheter delivery system and placed through the femoral 
vein using a 23 French internal diameter/27 French outer diameter 
introducer (Figure 2). The introducer is advanced using a guide-wire 
and dilator into the right atrium. The guide-wire and dilator are then re-
moved, and the steerable delivery system catheter with TPS preloaded 
and tethered is then advanced into the RV. Transcatheter pacing system </p>

<p>Figure 1 Transcatheter pacing system single-chamber ventricular pacemaker. Illustration of transcatheter pacing system positioned in the </p>

<p>RV apex. RV, right ventricle. </p>

<p>TPS early performance </p>



<p>is deployed by retraction of the device-containing cup at the distal end of 
the delivery catheter positioned against the RV endocardium with fix-
ation into the myocardium by the associated protraction of the nitinol 
tines (Figure 3). The delivery catheter is then withdrawn several centi-
metres and the fixation confirmed by a 'pull and hold' test. The tether 
is pulled until counter movement of the heartbeats can be felt and the 
tine deflection can be observed fluoroscopically, with the tethering 
material still connected to the TPS. Although bench testing has shown 
a single tine engaged in tissue holds the device securely within the 
myocardium with a high margin of safety, it is recommended that two 
tines are engaged for further security of fixation. Therefore, investiga-
tors are requested to check fluoroscopically that at least two tines 
are engaged within the myocardium before releasing the device; other-
wise, the device should be retracted and repositioned to another pos-
ition within the RV. Once the device is placed in the RV and adequate 
device fixation verified, electrical measurements (pacing thresholds, pa-
cing impedance, R-wave amplitude) are checked. Inadequate fixation 
(e.g. device tines engage into the trabeculae rather than RV myocardial 
wall) will be apparent via unacceptable electrical measurements and 
possibly failed pull and hold test. In case of persistence of high thresholds 
after two to three deployments, investigators were advised to remove 
the transcatheter delivery system in order to check for thrombus cover-
ing the tip electrode, and, if found, to carefully remove the thrombus. 
No specific implant location is recommended as the device can be 
placed at various anatomical RV positions. However, it is suggested to 
avoid placement at the free wall to minimize risk of effusion. 
After adequate electrical measurements are obtained, the tether is 
cut and the delivery system is removed. Haemostasis is achieved via vari-
ous closure methods, determined by implanter. Post-procedural 
haemostasis and peri-procedural antibiotics and anticoagulation are at 
implanter discretion with the exception that intra-procedural hepari-
nized flushing of the introducer is recommended in all patients. </p>

<p>Therapy initiation and follow-up </p>

<p>Enrolled patients undergo system implant attempt and then are fol-
lowed, including adverse event and device evaluation, at implant, </p>

<p>hospital discharge, 1, 3, 6, and 12 months post-implant. Implanted pa-
tients are evaluated semi-annually until trial closure. Cardiovascular, 
procedure, and system-related adverse events are adjudicated by an 
independent clinical events committee. 
Initially, pacemaker-dependent patients were excluded. Twenty-five 
implanted patients underwent 24 h ambulatory ECG and device 
function (markers and EGMs) monitoring (Model ER220, Medtronic 
plc, Mounds View, MN, USA). After comprehensive review of the 
ambulatory ECG and safety data by the trial's independent data moni-
toring committee, allowance of pacemaker-dependent patients was 
determined. </p>

<p>Early performance objectives </p>

<p>Early performance objectives, the subject of this report, were assessed 
once the 60th patient completed the 3-month post-implant visit. At that 
point, 140 patients had been implanted (Figure 4). The safety objective 
was assessed in all 140 implanted patients, and the efficacy objective 
was assessed in the 60 subjects who had been followed through 3 
months. These early performance objectives were required to obtain 
CE mark: </p>

<p>(i) The early safety performance objective was to demonstrate that the 
freedom from unanticipated serious adverse device events 
(USADEs) was significantly .85% in all implanted patients once 
60 patients were followed through 3 months. The early safety per-
formance objective was assessed in all 140 implanted patients. 
USADEs are defined as serious adverse events related to the use 
of the TPS not previously identified in nature, severity, or degree 
of incidence. USADEs were selected for the early safety assessment 
endpoint since the risk profile of transvenous pacemaker lead 
systems has been well-established. Thus, the rate of USADEs was 
selected to characterize unforeseen risk associated with TPS. 
(ii) The early efficacy performance objective was to demonstrate that 
the mean pacing capture threshold at pulse duration of 0.24 ms 
was significantly lower than 2 V in the 60 patients who completed 
the 3-month follow-up visit. Meeting this objective ensures TPS 
would have battery longevity estimation as expected. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Transcatheter pacing system delivery system. Tools needed to deliver transcatheter pacing system, from bottom to top: needle and </p>

<p>guide-wire, introducer with dilator, delivery catheter with transcatheter pacing system retracted within the distal tube of the delivery system. In-
sert: transcatheter pacing system with Euro dollar to indicate scale. </p>

<p>P. Ritter et al. </p>



<p>In addition to the USADE early performance objective, all adverse 
events from the 140 implanted patients were carefully described and 
reviewed by the Data Monitoring Committee. </p>

<p>Statistical methods </p>

<p>A sample size of 60 patients successfully implanted with TPS and fol-
lowed for at least 3-months post-implant provided more than 90% 
power at a type I error level of 0.025 to test the null hypothesis asso-
ciated with the early performance efficacy objective assuming the true 
mean 3-month pacing capture thresholds is 1.0 V with a standard devi-
ation of 0.5 V. This sample size provided more than 90% power for test-
ing the early performance safety objective since all patients with an 
implant attempt at the time the 60th 3-month visit was accrued would 
be included in the analysis of the safety objective. 
The Kaplan -Meier method was pre-specified as the method for 
evaluating the safety objective so all patients with an implant attempt 
could be included in the analysis. However, since no USADEs were ob-
served, the exact binomial test comparing the observed 3-month 
USADE free rate to the null value of 85% was used to evaluate the safety 
objective and derive the lower 97.5% confidence interval (CI). A one-</p>

<p>sample t-test comparing the observed mean 3-month pacing capture 
threshold to the null value of 2.0 V was used to test the efficacy object-
ive. In addition, paired t-tests were used to compare electrical variables 
measured at implant and the 3-month visit. Statistical calculations were 
performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, USA) or R (www. 
r-project.org) and validated per the sponsor's operating procedures. 
The procedure duration was defined as the time from the insertion of 
the TPS introducer to removal. Time to hospital discharge was defined 
as the number of days from implant to hospital discharge. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patient recruitment began 5 December 2013 and the 60th 3-month 
visit accrued on 11 August 2014, triggering evaluation of the early 
performance objectives. At the time of database closure for this 
analysis, 140 patients had an attempted implant and all were 
successfully implanted. The TPS was implanted in these 140 patients 
in 23 study centres by 37 physicians in 11 countries and were fol-
lowed to an average of 1.9 + 1.8 months (range 0 -6.5 months). </p>

<p>Figure 3 Transcatheter pacing system deployment. Step 1, upper panel: the device is fully retracted within the delivery system. The distal end of </p>

<p>the catheter is placed at the targeted site of the RV. Step 2, middle panel: the device is deployed and its tines penetrate the myocardium. Step 3, 
lower panel: the delivery catheter is pulled back from the device, which is still retained by a tether. After fixation and electrical checks, the tether 
will be cut and removed, as will the delivery system be. RV, right ventricle. </p>

<p>TPS early performance </p>



<p>Patients were mostly male (60.7%), of mean age 77.0 + 10.2 years, 
height range 144 -190 cm, and weight range 41 -148 kg (Table 1). 
The most common primary indications for pacing were atrioven-
tricular (AV) block (66%, or 93 of 140 patients) and symptomatic si-
nus node dysfunction (29%, or 40 of 140 patients). Nine (6%) 
patients were not felt to be appropriate for implantation of conven-
tional transvenous lead pacing systems due to a variety of reasons 
such as compromised venous access, previous infection, and cancer 
with need for indwelling catheter. Confirmation of appropriate pace-
maker operation from the 24 h ambulatory ECG analysis by the trial's 
data monitoring committee was achieved 3 weeks prior to database 
closure, enabling pacemaker-dependent patient enrolment. Two 
pacemaker-dependent patients were subsequently implanted and in-
cluded in this analysis. 
Ninety-one (65%) of the 140 patients received a VVI pacemaker 
for bradycardia in conjunction with permanent or persistent atrial 
tachyarrhythmias. Of the remaining 49 patients, 22 had sinus node 
dysfunction, 19 had AV block, two had sinus node dysfunction 
plus AV block, and six had other reasons listed for choosing a 
ventricular pacemaker. In these 49 patients, the predominant reason 
for TPS selection was identified as 'infrequent pacing expected' 
(69%) and 'advanced age' (22%). Other reasons included sedentary 
lifestyle, anatomical limitations, or co-morbidities increasing compli-
cation risk. </p>

<p>Implant procedure results </p>

<p>The implant success rate was 100% (140/140). Type of anaesthesia, 
anticoagulation, and use of antibiotics were at the discretion of 
implanters. Sedation and/or local anaesthesia was applied in 93.6% 
of patients and general anaesthesia used in 6.4%. No systemic antic-
oagulation was applied in 36%, and various regimens were used in 
the other patients (40% received heparin and 24% received another </p>

<p>anticoagulation method). An anticoagulation antagonist was used to 
reverse anticoagulation effects in 16 patients (11%). The mean im-
plant time was 37 + 21 min (range: 11 -154 min) with an average 
fluoroscopy time of 9 + 7 min. The majority of attempts were suc-
cessful upon initial device positioning (59%) or two positioning 
(22.1%), but the maximum number of attempts in a single patient 
was 18 deployments (mean + SD, 2 + 2). A second device was 
used in two implants, due to unacceptable electrical measurements. 
In both cases, electrical measurements with the second device were 
similar to the measurements of the first device, although ultimately 
both cases were able to achieve a position with acceptable electrical 
measurements. While 107 of the 140 devices were placed at the RV 
apex (76.4%), 33 (24%) were implanted at the anterior septum, mid-
septum, or outflow tract (images available in Figure 5). Access site 
closure was predominantly performed using a suture method 
(76%), although other methods were observed (such as manual 
pressure or venotomy occlusion system). The average time to am-
bulation following the procedure was 13 + 8 h and the median days 
from procedure to hospital discharge was 1 day, although day to dis-
charge varied by geography (mean + SD, 2 + 2). </p>

<p>Early safety performance </p>

<p>There were no USADEs in the 140 patients, thus the safety objective 
was met with 100% freedom from USADEs at 3 months (95% 
confidence interval, 94.0-100%; P , 0.0001). Thirty adverse events 
occurred in 26 patients, all within 17 days of implant (Table 2). 
One pericardial effusion was observed in a 90-year-old female 
who had undergone 18 repositioning because of inappropriate elec-
trical measurements, the highest number of repositioning observed 
in the study. A pericardial drainage was performed to drain approxi-
mately 250 cc of blood, although no tamponade was diagnosed. The 
same patient experienced an acute myocardial infarction 3 days 
post-implant and angiography revealed three-vessel coronary artery 
disease. Transient complete AV block occurred in four patients and 
resolved within seconds to a few hours. Three cases of transient AV 
block required pacing via a temporary wire. The fourth resolved 
with immediate programming to active pacing after device deploy-
ment. Each of the four patients experiencing transient AV block 
had a history of LBBB or prolonged AV conduction (two had 
second-degree AV block, one had LBBB with first-degree AV block, 
and one had LBBB). Groin bleeding ('incision site haemorrhage') was 
observed in three of the 140 patients, and a haematoma in two. 
None of these events were considered serious, and all cases 
resolved without invasive intervention. There were two cases of 
arterial pseudoaneurysms. One of the two events was considered 
serious and required thrombin injection with prolonged hospitaliza-
tion. The other pseudoaneurysm was not considered serious and 
resolved without any invasive intervention. There was no apparent 
relationship to heparin use or closure method approach in the 
events which were observed at the groin puncture site. (There 
was a total of 11 events at the groin puncture site and intravenous 
heparin was administered in approximately half of the events. 
A suture method was used for closure in each of these 11 cases 
except one where only manual pressure was applied). One patient 
death occurred 139 days post-implant, was not cardiovascular 
related, and was determined to not be related to the procedure 
or system. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Flow diagram of patients analysed. Flow diagram from </p>

<p>patients implanted by 11 August 2014 and analysed for early per-
formance objectives. </p>

<p>P. Ritter et al. </p>



<p>Early efficacy performance </p>

<p>The mean pacing capture threshold at the 3-month visit for the 60 
patients measured at 0.24 ms was 0.51 V (95% CI, 0.45 -0.56; P , 
0.0001), meeting the efficacy objective. In these 60 patients, the 
mean electrical values for R-wave sensing amplitude, pacing </p>

<p>impedance, and pacing capture threshold at 0.24 ms were, respect-
ively: 11.7 + 4.5 mV, 719 + 226 ohm, 0.57 + 0.31 V at implant, 
15.6 + 4.8 mV, 662 + 133 ohm, 0.48 + 0.21 V at 1-month, 
and 16.1 + 5.2 mV, 651 + 130 ohm, 0.51 + 0.22 V at 3-months 
(Figure 6). All measurements at all visits were within expected </p>

<p>. ............ ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ......... </p>

<p>Table 1 Patient characteristics </p>

<p>Patient characteristics 
First 60 (n 5 60) 
Total (n 5 140) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age (years), mean + standard deviation 
76.8 + 9.9 
77.0 + 10.2 
0.84 </p>

<p>Male, n (%) 
37 (61.7) 
85 (60.7) 
0.86 
Pacing indication, n (%) </p>

<p>Symptomatic sinus node dysfunction 
20 (33.3) 
40 (28.6) 
0.35 </p>

<p>2nd-degree AV block 
4 (6.7) 
8 (5.7) 
0.72 
3rd-degree AV block 
6 (10.0) 
11 (7.9) 
0.53 </p>

<p>SND + AV block 
1 (1.7) 
2 (1.4) 
1.00 </p>

<p>AV block with persistent/permanent arrhythmias 
28 (46.7) 
72 (51.4) 
0.39 
Other indication 
1 (1.7) 
7 (5.0) 
0.24 </p>

<p>Reason for selecting single-chamber pacemaker, n (%) </p>

<p>Indications associated with persistent/permanent/chronic atrial tachyarrhythmias 
34 (56.7) 
82 (58.6) 
0.73 
Frequent pacing not expected 
21 (35.0) 
45 (32.1) 
0.59 </p>

<p>Patients advanced age 
5 (8.3) 
18 (12.9) 
0.21 </p>

<p>Significant co-morbities affecting survival and clinical outcome 
2 (3.3) 
3 (2.1) 
0.58 
Previous planned AV nodal ablation 
0 (0.0) 
2 (1.4) 
0.51 </p>

<p>Patients expected to be sedentary 
2 (3.3) 
5 (3.6) 
1.00 </p>

<p>Patient's anatomy precludes placement of atrial lead 
1 (1.7) 
2 (1.4) 
1.00 
Dual-chamber pacing complication risk deemed to high 
0 (0.0) 
1 (0.7) 
1.00 </p>

<p>Other reason 
2 (3.3) 
8 (5.7) 
0.24 </p>

<p>Cardiac disease, n (%) 
Cardiomyopathy, dilated/congestive + Cardiomyopathy, ischaemic 
5 (8.3) 
5 (3.5) 
0.01 </p>

<p>Coronary artery disease + Myocardial infarction 
20 (33.3) 
44 (31.4) 
0.72 </p>

<p>Pulmonary hypertension 
1 (1.7) 
7 (5.0) 
0.24 
Valve dysfunction, tricuspid 
10 (16.7) 
23 (16.4) 
1.00 </p>

<p>Hypertension 
46 (76.7) 
111 (79.3) 
0.53 </p>

<p>Symptoms, n (%) 
Congestive heart failure 
5 (8.3) 
13 (9.3) 
0.78 </p>

<p>Syncope 
23 (38.3) 
55 (39.3) 
0.86 </p>

<p>Comorbidities (%) 
Diabetes 
17 (28.3) 
34 (24.3) 
0.43 </p>

<p>Renal dysfunction 
10 (16.7) 
26 (18.6) 
0.67 </p>

<p>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) 
4 (6.7) 
14 (10.0) 
0.39 
Implant success rate (%) 
60 (100.0) 
140 (100.0) 
1.00 </p>

<p>Procedure duration (min) </p>

<p>Mean + standard deviation 
37.9 + 24.8 
36.7 + 20.7 
0.54 
Fluoroscopy duration (min) </p>

<p>Mean + standard deviation 
10.1 + 7.8 
9.1 + 7.0 
0.18 </p>

<p>Redeployments, n (%) 
0 
34 (56.7) 
82 (58.6) 
0.76 </p>

<p>1-4 
24 (40.0) 
52 (37.1) 
≥5 
2 (3.3) 
6 (4.3) 
Hours to ambulation following procedure </p>

<p>Mean + standard deviation 
14.7 + 7.6 
13.1 + 8.5 
0.10 </p>

<p>P-value is from the t-test (continuous variables) or Fisher Exact test (categorical variables) comparing those in the early performance cohort (first 60 implanted) to those implanted 
later. </p>

<p>TPS early performance </p>



<p>ranges. Paired comparison of the 60 patients from implant to 
3-month electrical values demonstrated an increase in R-wave amp-
litude (4.4 mV, P , 0.0001), a decrease in impedance (68 ohms, P ¼ 
0.006), and a non-significant decrease in pacing capture threshold 
(0.06 V, P ¼ 0.057). Rate response was programmed on in 54% 
(76 out of 140) of patients, programmed to VVIR where an initial 
testing showed effective rate adaptation to short walking test. On-
going evaluations in the study will confirm rate response operation 
via treadmill testing in a subset of subjects. </p>

<p>Ambulatory ECG evaluation </p>

<p>Examination of 24 h ambulatory surface ECG and device electro-
gram cycle by cycle at the 1-month visit from 25 patients indicated </p>

<p>that the device was pacing and sensing as expected. There were no 
pauses due to inappropriate TPS operation. Additionally, the daily 
capture threshold testing and hourly threshold confirmation tests 
were performing as expected. </p>

<p>Longevity estimation </p>

<p>In 60 patients followed to 3 months, cumulative percent pacing 
ranged from ,1 to .99% with a median of 49% (interquartile 
range, 10.2 -75.1%). Based on device use conditions (e.g. heart 
rate, pulse width, pacing amplitude, impedance) through 
3-months, battery longevity was estimated at an average 12.6 years 
(range 8.6 -14.4 years, Figure 7). This estimate does not include </p>

<p>Figure 5 X-rays of various device positions in RAO view. Left panel: apical device placement; Middle panel: mid-septal device placement; Right </p>

<p>panel: right-ventricular outflow tract (RVOT) device placement. </p>

<p>..... ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ............ ............ ........... ............ ...... </p>

<p>Table 2 Procedure or system-related adverse events from 140 implanted patients </p>

<p>30 total related adverse events 
Resulted in death, 
re-operation, or 
hospitalization? </p>

<p>Total event rate, n (%) </p>

<p>30 (26 patients, 18.6%) </p>

<p>Dysrhythmias 
Transient atrioventricular block 
No 
4 (4, 2.9) 
Right bundle branch block 
No 
2 (2, 1.4) 
Ventricular tachycardia 
No 
2 (2, 1.4) 
Ventricular fibrillation 
No 
1 (1, 0.7) 
Events at device placement site 
Pericardial effusion without tamponade 
1 hospitalization prolonged .48 h 
for both events in same patient </p>

<p>1 (1, 0.7) 
Acute myocardial infarction 
1 (1, 0.7) 
Pericarditis 
No 
2 (1, 0.7) 
Non-cardiac chest pain 
No 
1 (1, 0.7) 
Angina pectoris 
No 
2 (2, 1.4) </p>

<p>Events at groin puncture suite 
Arterial pseudoaneurysm 
1 hospitalization prolonged .48 h 
2 (2, 1.4) 
Incision site haemorrhage 
No 
3 (3, 2.1) 
Incision site haematoma 
No 
2 (2, 1.4) 
Incision site pain 
No 
1 (1, 0.7) 
Incisional drainage 
No 
1 (1, 0.7) 
Vaso-vagal presyncope 
No 
2 (2, 1.4) 
Other 
Dysuria following procedure 
No 
1 (1, 0.7) 
Osteoarthritis following procedure 
No 
1 (1, 0.7) 
Back pain during procedure 
No 
1 (1, 0.7) </p>

<p>P. Ritter et al. </p>



<p>pacemaker-dependent patients and assumes that thresholds remain 
stable for device lifetime. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This is the largest data set reported for any transcatheter pacing 
technology to date. Early results of this pacemaker are encouraging. 
The TPS demonstrated safety and efficacy through the acute phase 
by passing both of its early performance assessment objectives. One 
hundred and forty (100%) successful implants were achieved in a 
wide variety of patient demographics, cardiac conditions, and indica-
tions for pacing. This was accomplished by 37 physicians in 23 study 
centres in 11 countries. In two procedures, a second device was 
used due to unacceptable electrical measurements and decision 
to change the device was motivated by uncertainty due to early </p>

<p>experience of implanters. The majority of implants (81%) were 
successfully completed with one or two positionings. </p>

<p>Safety performance </p>

<p>USADE is an ISO standard for assessing primary risks to patient 
health when implementing a new medical device. The endpoint is of-
ten used for safety evaluation, 
11,12 but is uniquely different from the </p>

<p>study's primary objective. 
9 The trial had no USADEs after 266.4 </p>

<p>months of follow-up, far exceeding its primary safety objective. 
Thirty adverse events related to the procedure or system were 
identified in the 140 implanted patients, none of which were due 
to device dislodgement or infections. There were no deaths related 
to the procedure or system and no re-operations were required. 
Telemetry contact remained feasible in all patients. Adverse events 
did not differ substantially across patient sub-groups. 
One case of pericardial effusion occurred in the context of 18 
positionings due to undesirable electrical performance. In light of 
this observation, persistent repositioning should be avoided in order 
to limit the possible injury to the myocardium and surrounding 
vessels. In case of undesirable thresholds immediately after deploy-
ment, some waiting time should be considered before measuring 
electricals again. As is frequently observed in tined and helix-based 
pacemaker leads, 
13 thresholds may improve within minutes, thus </p>

<p>allowing release of the device. In all cases, consideration of the 
potential benefit of multiple repositioning vs. risk is warranted. 
Transient AV (in patients with LBBB or AV conduction abnormal-
ities) or right bundle branch block during navigation of the delivery 
tool was reported in a few cases, suggesting a mechanical trauma by 
the delivery system which bears consideration in crossing the tricus-
pid valve. Prevention of ventricular arrhythmias warrants a similar 
consideration. However, these events can occur with any right-
heart procedure. Temporary pacing is a preventive option and 
may be considered in patients with LBBB. 
The management of pre-and peri-operative anticoagulants was 
left to the discretion of the physician because of lack of experience 
with the implantation of the TPS. No specific recommendation was </p>

<p>Figure 6 Device electrical measures of first 60 patients. A, B, and </p>

<p>C display the mean + SD of the pacing threshold at 0.24 ms, 
R-wave amplitude, and impedance respectively for all data available 
from the 60 patients followed to 3 months. The P-value in A is for 
the comparison of the mean pacing capture threshold to the per-
formance goal of 2.0V. **Significantly different from implant value. </p>

<p>Figure 7 Distribution of expected transcatheter pacing system </p>

<p>battery longevity based on device use conditions (% pacing, heart 
rate, pacing capture thresholds) of first 60 patients through 
3 months. </p>

<p>TPS early performance </p>



<p>given to investigators who were free to define their own protocol 
with the condition that all catheters were flushed with heparinized 
saline, and that a heparinized drip was placed on the introducer to 
reduce clotting. A variety of approaches were used and minimal 
haematomas or bleeding were observed, without correlation to ap-
proach (40% received heparin and 36% did not receive any anticoa-
gulation; there were two haematomas and three events of minor 
groin bleeding). Therefore, no obvious advantages or disadvantages 
due to anticoagulation approach have become apparent, although a 
heparin bolus may reduce risk of clotting on the device and within 
the delivery tool. The risk of inadvertent arterial puncture (with 
possible subsequent complications such as pseudoaneurysms, AV 
fistulas, and haematomas) might be mitigated by using ultrasound 
techniques for venous access, although this has not been evaluated 
within this study. With regard to post-procedural closure/haemo-
stasis, investigators have successfully used various techniques as a 
pre-specified closure method was not mandated. The majority 
(46%) of closure methods utilized manual pressure with a suture 
method (Figure of 8, purse string). A suture method without manual 
pressure was used in 39% of cases. A vascular closure device was 
used in 11% of cases (with or without pressure or a suture), and 
manual pressure alone was used in 4% of cases. </p>

<p>Efficacy performance </p>

<p>Device functionality and efficacy was successfully demonstrated at 3 
months with a mean pacing threshold of 0.51 V at 0.24 ms pulse 
width; exceeding the intended goal of ,2.0 V. Further, ambulatory 
ECG monitoring in the first 25 patients at 1-month demonstrated 
the device was performing as expected. Pacing thresholds remained 
low and stable, with no measurements at or above 2.0 V at 3 months 
follow-up. This last observation is important because any program-
ming requiring high energy levels may result in a significant reduction 
in the life expectancy of the device. One patient had a pacing thresh-
old .2 V at implantation, though this decreased to ,1 V at 3 
months. Based on pacing conditions from the 60 patients followed 
to 3 months, mean device longevity was estimated at 12.6 years, 
with 95% of the patients over 10 years and shortest of 8.6 years. 
This longevity performance would be no worse than conventional 
pacing systems. 
14,15 The TPS uses a new capture management ap-</p>

<p>proach with automatic hourly 0.5 V safety margin confirmations 
to ensure pacing outputs remain at safe levels and to optimize bat-
tery longevity. </p>

<p>Alternate transcatheter pacemakers </p>

<p>While other manufacturers are developing transcatheter pace-
makers, it will be of importance to consider technical differences 
in the design and performance of the various technologies. In the 
LEADLESS Trial, the Nanostim 
TM leadless cardiac pacemaker (St </p>

<p>Jude Medical, St Paul, MN, USA) was successfully implanted in 32 
of 33 patients. 
16 One patient experienced a RV perforation and car-</p>

<p>diac tamponade during the procedure, and later died as a result of 
stroke. Two patients required device retrieval post-implantation, 
one for inadvertent left-ventricular placement and the other for de-
veloping an indication for an implantable cardioverter defibrillator. 
Compared with TPS, the Nanostim device is of similar size but long-
er (41.4 vs. 25.9 mm) and narrower in diameter (18 vs. 20 Fr). Rate 
response is controlled by RV blood temperature compared with an </p>

<p>accelerometer in TPS. Although the implant approach is also trans-
catheter delivered via the femoral vein, endocardium fixation is dif-
ferent. The TPS uses four protractible nitinol tines vs. a fixed helical 
coil with Nanostim. </p>

<p>Technology implications </p>

<p>Transvenous lead technology was developed in 1959 and with the 
introduction of implantable pacemakers in the 1960s, the implant 
technique has largely been unchanged. Today, it is estimated that 
600 000 pacemakers are implanted worldwide each year, </p>

<p>17   358 000 of which are in the USA. 
18 Compared with single-chamber </p>

<p>atrial-based systems and the more costly dual-chamber systems, VVI 
pacemaker utilization varies regionally with rates reported from 
trials of 8% in the USA 
19 and 25% in the Netherlands. 
4 VVI pace-</p>

<p>makers are guideline recommended for patients with permanent 
or persistent atrial arrhythmias and slow intrinsic heart rates. 
20 Fu-</p>

<p>ture developments of this technology may include AAI, VDD, DDD, 
or even biventricular pacing systems. However, in the meantime, 
mode selection may be influenced by the technological advantages 
of a miniaturized transcatheter pacemaker, advantages that include 
the absence of lead and pocket related risks and device implant 
cosmesis. Atrial and dual-chamber pacing modes have recently 
been preferred for bradyarrhythmia patients without permanent 
or persistent atrial tachyarrhythmia due to risks associated with 
AV dysynchrony, notably pacemaker syndrome. 
19 Over one-third </p>

<p>of the patients who received TPS in our trial were without history 
of permanent or persistent atrial tachyarrhythmia. Of these patients, 
the primary pacing indication was SND (45%) or AV block (39%). 
Physicians selected VVI pacing for reasons due to 'infrequent pacing 
expected' (69%), 'advanced age' (22%), and other reasons that in-
cluded sedentary lifestyle, anatomical limitations, or co-morbidities 
increasing risk of complication. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>This study is non-randomized and so the evaluation of benefit of this 
new technique over contemporary single-chamber or dual-chamber 
systems is indirect. This is the first report of early performance of 
the TPS in a multi-stage assessment protocol and there was limited 
representation of pacemaker-dependent patients in this cohort. The 
patient cohort is too small to determine any recommendation re-
garding anticoagulation management and post-procedural closure/ 
haemostasis. No devices have yet to be retrieved, thus retrievability 
remains uncertain. Also, performance with multiple or concomitant 
devices has not yet been observed. This is an ongoing study that may 
bring more precision regarding these issues. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Early performance assessment shows the TPS pacemaker can safely 
and effectively be applied. It is premature to draw definitive conclu-
sions about the benefits of this system. Long-term safety and benefit 
associated with the absence of a subcutaneous pulse generator and 
transvenous lead will further be evaluated in the trial. However, 
these early results meet and exceed initial pre-specified expecta-
tions. The fact that such data were obtained in a multicentre study 
involving 37 investigators at 23 different centres around the world 
with a variety of patients is encouraging. </p>

<p>P. Ritter et al. </p>



<p>Supplementary material </p>

<p>Supplementary material is available at European Heart Journal online. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We would like to thank the physicians who contributed to the early 
performance cohort as listed in the Supplementary material online. 
We would like to thank Eric Williams for his technical support and 
Harrison Hudnall for his editorial support in the preparation of this 
article. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by Medtronic plc as the sponsor of The Micra 
Transcatheter Pacing Study. Funding to pay the Open Access publication 
charges for this article was provided by Medtronic plc. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest: P.R.: consulting fees/ honoraria; G.Z.D.: consult-
ing fees/ honoraria; C.S.: consulting fees/ honoraria; K.S.: consulting fees/ 
honoraria; R.O.: consulting fees/ honoraria, speaker's bureau; L.M.: con-
sulting fees/ honoraria, speaker's bureau, research grants, and fellowship 
support; L.V.A.B.: consulting fees/ honoraria; R.E.K.: consulting fees/ 
honoraria; L.C.: consulting fees/ honoraria; S.Z.: consulting fees/ honor-
aria; C.N.: consulting fees/ honoraria; J.H.: consulting fees/ honoraria; 
M.L.: consulting fees/ honoraria; T.A.S.: consulting fees/ honoraria; 
A.V.: No disclosures; V.L.: Employment; Significant; Medtronic; K.S.: 
Employment; Significant; Medtronic; M.D.B.: Employment; Significant; 
Medtronic; T.J.S.: Employment; Significant; Medtronic; D.R.: consulting 
fees/honoraria, research grants. </p>



<p>TPS early performance </p>



</text></tei>