<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4542943" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>• Premise of the study: Phylogenetic inference is moving to large multilocus data sets, yet there remains uncertainty in the choice 
of marker and sequencing method at low taxonomic levels. To address this gap, we present a method for enriching long loci 
spanning intron-exon boundaries in the genus Heuchera . 
• Methods: Two hundred seventy-eight loci were designed using a splice-site prediction method combining transcriptomic 
and genomic data. Biotinylated probes were designed for enrichment of these loci. Reference-based assembly was per-
formed using genomic references; additionally, chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes were used as references for off-
target reads. The data were aligned and subjected to coalescent and concatenated phylogenetic analyses to demonstrate 
support for major relationships. 
• Results: Complete or nearly complete (&gt;99%) sequences were assembled from essentially all loci from all taxa. Aligned introns 
showed a fourfold increase in divergence as opposed to exons. Concatenated analysis gave decisive support to all nodes, and 
support was also high and relationships mostly similar in the coalescent analysis. Organellar phylogenies were also well-
supported and confl icted with the nuclear signal. 
• Discussion: Our approach shows promise for resolving a recent radiation. Enrichment for introns is highly successful with little 
or no sequencing dropout at low taxonomic levels despite higher substitution and indel frequencies, and should be exploited in 
studies of species complexes. </p>



<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 
Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>

<p>http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>for closely related species. While we were collecting these data, 
a study also including intron probes was published for Medicago 
L. ( de Sousa et al., 2014 ); these authors also point out the use of 
introns for lower-level taxonomic questions. However, this study 
only reports experimental statistics on entire loci-discussion 
and data on the effectiveness of intron enrichment are absent. Ad-
ditionally, their locus design methodology cannot be used on the 
majority of organisms that lack a high-quality annotated refer-
ence genome, underlining the need for broader methodologies 
and data exploration for use by the phylogenomic community. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Materials -The DNAs we used were primarily of high quality and prepared 
from cultivated material or quickly dried fi eld material. However, we also suc-
cessfully sequenced a herbarium specimen of H. acutifolia Rose, collected in 
1984; we have had further success with specimens collected as long ago as the 
1940s (unpublished). The same H. acutifolia sample that was successful for this 
study previously proved impossible to sequence for low-copy markers using a 
Sanger protocol ( Folk and Freudenstein, 2014 ; similar observations in Cronn  et al., 2012 ). As an initial test of our method, we present results from 15 indi-
viduals selected as taxonomically representative of the major sections of the 
genus (Appendix 1). </p>

<p>Genomic reference development -As a draft genomic reference, we used 
3.7 Gbp of short-read data (20,288,896 reads) from H. parvifl ora var. saurensis 
R. A. Folk. Paired-end sequencing was performed by The Ohio State University 
Molecular and Cellular Imaging Center in six multiplexed runs with samples 
from unrelated projects (fi ve Illumina MiSeq runs with 300-bp reads; one Illu-
mina HiSeq lane with 100-bp reads; all data uploaded to the Short Read 
Archive, accession SRP058301). This level of sequencing corresponds to ap-
proximately 7.5 × expected average nuclear genomic coverage using 2C values 
from Godsoe et al. (2013) . While over-sampling of high-copy loci will reduce 
the actual coverage of the single-copy portion of the genome, most nuclear 
contigs consistently showed 5-8 × coverage. These data were assembled in Vel-
vet ( Zerbino and Birney, 2008 ) using a kmer length of 64, expected insert length 
of 700 bp, standard deviation of insert length 100 bp, and minimum contig 
length of 1000, to develop reference contigs for the low-copy portion of the 
genome. This resulted in 18,344 contigs between 1000 and 7360 bp; a longer 
kmer length results in longer contigs, but these were not necessary for marker 
development. A BLAST search against organellar references confi rmed that 
organellar and rDNA sequences were not present in this batch of contigs. 
Because we wished to explore the possibility of off-target assembly of high-
copy loci, we used the skimming data from H. parvifl ora var. saurensis to assemble 
complete chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes (GenBank accessions KR478645 
and KR559021, respectively). The chloroplast genome was assembled by map-
ping all reads (trimmed with Geneious default settings) using the native Geneious 
assembler (version 7, Biomatters; available from http://www.geneious.com/ ) 
with medium sensitivity, using the chloroplast genome of H. sanguinea Engelm. 
(M. Moore, unpublished). The resultant contig was manually screened for 
regions of mis-mapped reads (always due to large indels in intergenic spacers); 
at these points the consensus sequence was broken into subsequences. These 
subsequences were subjected to iterative assembly in Geneious (25 iterations), 
repeated until all consensus sequences of these assemblies overlapped (by 
de novo assembly in Geneious with default settings) and could be combined 
into a single circle. The read mapping was repeated on this resultant genome 
draft, and the complete lack of mis-mapping regions was confi rmed. 
The mitochondrial assembly method was largely similar to that of the chlo-
roplast; however, a reasonably close reference mitochondrial genome was not 
available for the initial read-mapping. Geneious de novo assembly was per-
formed with default settings on the entire data set, divided into three approxi-
mately equal parts to reduce RAM requirements to feasible levels. Mitochondrial 
contigs were distinguished by BLAST searches against the Vitis vinifera L. 
mitochondrial genome ( Goremykin et al., 2008 ). This procedure was found to 
produce very long mitochondrial contigs compared to preliminary Velvet and 
SOAP ( Luo et al., 2012 ) assemblies, as long as 122,611 bp. Comparing the as-
semblies revealed that the Geneious contigs contained all of the mitochondrial 
sequence assembled by the other programs, but in fewer pieces. Consensus se-
quences of these contigs ( n = 39) were used in iterative assembly, circular 
reference construction, and assembly validation as above. </p>

<p>these systems that would help inform the design of new sequenc-
ing projects. The application of restriction-based protocols at 
taxonomic levels beyond that of populations, or perhaps sub-
specifi c taxa, entails a greater risk due to the possibility that 
many restriction sites may possess mutations in a subset of the 
study samples, resulting in frequent allele dropout and, at worst, 
data matrices consisting largely of missing data. Homology as-
sessment may also be more diffi cult if anonymous restriction-
based markers are to be used for phylogenetics. 
Targeted sequencing based on in-solution hybridization of 
DNA fragments to biotinylated RNA probes ( Gnirke et al., 2009 ) 
avoids these problems. Moreover, hybridization-based methods 
can be combined with genome-skimming techniques to obtain 
nontargeted high-copy loci (i.e., "Hyb-Seq"; Weitemier et al.,  2014 ), a benefi t that generally is not shared by other techniques. 
On the other hand, probe-hybridization-based techniques have 
typically targeted exonic regions that may be too conserved 
among closely related species where Sanger markers have failed 
to obtain resolution, resulting in large amounts of uninformative 
data and therefore wasted sequencing effort, even if some degree 
of off-target intron assembly is possible ( Weitemier et al., 2014 ). 
The performance of such a methodology in obtaining less con-
served nonexonic sequences (such as introns or intergenic regions) 
is currently poorly known, but comparative genomic data in the 
form of closely related genome and transcriptome sequences are 
becoming increasingly available to facilitate the identifi cation 
and use of such loci. 
The genus Heuchera L. (Saxifragaceae), with about 43 spe-
cies, appears to represent a recent, relatively rapid radiation for 
which these methodological decisions are especially critical. 
Deng et al. (2015) estimate the age of the " Heuchera group" (in-
cluding related genera such as Tiarella L. and Mitella L.) to be 
7.27 mya, a date recent enough to place the origin of many clades 
in Heuchera in the Pleistocene. Such recent divergence events 
are expected to leave few informative mutations for phylogenetic 
reconstruction, motivating the use of numerous and more quickly 
evolving regions. A recent study based on Sanger sequencing 
( Folk and Freudenstein, 2014 ) confi rms the diffi culty of resolv-
ing many of these relationships, particularly within taxonomic 
sections, reinforcing the need for careful marker choice. 
We therefore aimed to evaluate the RNA-probe-based tar-
geted sequencing of a panel of long, continuous loci containing 
both intron and exon sequences, using a combination of ge-
nomic and transcriptomic data. Because we were interested pri-
marily in phylogenetic confl ict, and therefore required resolved 
gene trees, we favored loci that were much longer than those 
typical in recent efforts. Using a Hyb-Seq approach ( Weitemier  et al., 2014 ), it is possible to obtain large amounts of organellar 
data from enrichment experiments, but the need for additional 
organellar genomes in the Saxifragaceae and other plant groups 
is acute given that there exists only one unpublished chloroplast 
genome for the family, and there is no mitochondrial genome 
available even for the Saxifragales. To develop further phylo-
genetic markers, we additionally sought to assemble organellar 
genomic resources for phylogenomics in the Saxifragaceae that 
should be of broad utility for related genera. 
Aspects of target enrichment relating to wet-laboratory meth-
ods, off-target genome assembly, and phylogenetic reconstruction 
are now well covered in exon-based enrichment methods ( Mandel  et al., 2014 ; Weitemier et al., 2014 ). Some recent studies have 
also included intronic probes (e.g., Govindarajulu et al., 2015 ); 
our work contributes to this publication series by focusing on the 
effectiveness of intron enrichment and long-target enrichment </p>

<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 </p>

<p>Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>

<p>3 of 10 
http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>enrichment pools, effi ciency of enrichment was evaluated using two relative 
qPCR assays (qPCR primers, thermocycler profi le, and other information in 
Appendix S1). Enriched samples that amplifi ed at least 10 cycles earlier than 
unenriched samples (&gt;1000-fold enrichment assuming 100% primer effi ciency) 
were considered successful. 
Target-enriched library pools were again pooled and diluted for sequencing 
on an Illumina MiSeq (W. Harry Feinstone Center for Genomic Research, 
University of Memphis, Tennessee; 500-cycle kit, Illumina V2 chemistry). The 
<rs type="software">MiSeq</rs> controller software was set to trim adapters and deconvolute barcodes; 
the raw output has been uploaded to the National Center for Biotechnology In-
formation (NCBI) Sequence Read Archive (accession SRP057104). Read end 
trimming was performed in Trimmomatic 0.33 ( Bolger et al., 2014 ) with a slid-
ing window of 20 bp and a quality score of Q20 or greater. </p>

<p>Low copy marker sequence assembly -Assembly of data for each species 
reused as a reference the initial 278 contigs of H. parvifl ora var. saurensis 
that were used for probe design. We reasoned that contigs that were suffi cient 
for designing effi cient enrichment probes should also be able to inform se-
quence assembly, avoiding the need for computationally demanding and often 
unsatisfactory de novo methods. We mapped reads to the 278 references us-
ing the relatively indel-tolerant BWA program (v. 0.7.12; Li and Durbin, 2009 ;  Li, 2013 ), with the default settings for paired-end data; fi nally, the resultant 
contigs were imported into Geneious. Consensus sequences were extracted 
from these contigs in Geneious using default settings, including trimming the 
consensus to the length of the reference sequence. Each locus was aligned 
individually using MAFFT 7.017 ( Katoh et al., 2009 ) with default settings. One 
of the loci (labeled Locus 4 in the probe panel, wherein loci are numbered in 
order of descending length; data available from the Dryad Digital Repository: 
http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.4cn66 [ Folk et al., 2015 ]) was found to yield 
only partial sequences from many taxa, resulting in large amounts of missing 
data (see Results); this has been excluded from the analyses, leaving 277 
effectively enriched loci. </p>

<p>Off-target sequence assembly -We repeated the reference-mapping in 
BWA with mitochondrial and chloroplastic references to attempt to construct 
chloroplast genomes and mitochondrial genomes from off-target reads. For the 
chloroplast assembly, we used fully assembled plastomes from H. parvifl ora 
var. saurensis , H. parishii Rydb. (below), and H. sanguinea (M. Moore, unpub-
lished data). The closest of these three references to each sample based on 
a preliminary Sanger chloroplast phylogeny (unpublished data) was used for 
reference-mapping to assist in assembling long, divergent intergenic regions. 
Development of a third plastome reference was necessary for the divergent in-
tergenic regions of H. parishii , H. elegans Abrams, and H. abramsii Rydb.; this 
was constructed by mapping the H. parishii reads to the H. parvifl ora var. sau-
rensis plastome in BWA and repeating the assembly refi nement methods used 
for the H. parvifl ora plastome assembly. Mitochondrial assembly used the fully 
assembled reference from H. parvifl ora var. saurensis . Because we desired 
purely mitochondrial signal for the mitochondrial phylogenetic analysis, this 
genome was blasted against the H. parvifl ora chloroplast genome and any hits 
were deleted from the mitochondrial assembly reference. Whole chloroplast 
genomes were aligned in MAFFT as with the single-copy markers; however, 
this was computationally infeasible for the much longer mitochondrial se-
quences. For these we used Mauve, setting an assumption of collinear genomes 
(which was enforced for our contigs by the read-mapping method) but other-
wise using default settings. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analysis -Because chloroplast capture is a well-known phe-
nomenon in the genus Heuchera ( Soltis et al., 1991 ; Soltis and Kuzoff, 1995 ;  Folk, Mandel, and Freudenstein, unpublished data), and organellar genomes in 
general are thought to be more prone to displaying phylogenetic discordance 
caused by hybridization ( Rieseberg and Soltis, 1991 ), we avoided including 
organellar genes in all multilocus analyses and instead present these sepa-
rately. We performed a concatenated analysis of the 277 low-copy nuclear loci 
in RAxML 8.1.3 ( Stamatakis, 2006 ), using an unpartitioned GTR-GAMMA 
model and with support quantifi ed by 5000 bootstrap replicates (matrices and 
tree fi les for the analyses of this paper available from the Dryad Digital Repository: 
http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.4cn66 [ Folk et al., 2015 ]). 
To examine the relative phylogenetic signal from exonic and intronic por-
tions of the sequences, we performed an exon-only analysis and an intron-only 
analysis by alternatively excluding intron and exon sites, respectively. Approx-
imately two thirds of our target sequence was intronic; hence analyzing this in 
its entirety would be an unfair comparison with the exonic matrix. Therefore, we </p>

<p>Organellar genome annotations were performed using Geneious, based on 
H. sanguinea (chloroplast) or V. vinifera (mitochondrion); synteny compari-
sons were performed using the Mauve plug-in ( Darling, 2004 ) in Geneious. </p>

<p>Locus design -To obtain putatively single-copy loci in the absence of com-
parative genomic data within Saxifragaceae, Velvet contigs ( n = 18,334) were 
searched against a panel of conserved single-copy sequences (hereafter "COS 
loci") from the Arabidopsis genome (Kozik et al., unpublished; but see http:// 
www.cgpdb.ucdavis.edu/COS_Arabidopsis/ ; also used in Mandel et al., 2014 ; 
n = 3714) using BLAST, yielding 3251 hits that were retained for RNA tran-
script queries. It is important to note that for these retained loci, we had two 
sources of assurance of their low-copy (likely single-copy) status: (a) they are 
single-copy in Arabidopsis , and (b) they had coverage consistent with single-
copy status in the H. parvifl ora Bartl. genome skimming work. This means that 
a fully or mostly assembled genome is not needed to identify low-copy targets, 
although such resources are useful when they are available ( Weitemier et al.,  2014 ). We used GeneSeqer ( Brendel et al., 2004 ) to identify intron-containing 
loci among these hits. GeneSeqer aligns transcriptome sequences to genomic 
sequences using several available splice-site models, evaluates putative align-
ments based both on sequence similarity and splice-site strength, and outputs 
gapped sequence alignments. In our experience, these alignments are more ac-
curate in the context of large indels (= introns) than those based on simple se-
quence alignment such as BLAST. The splice-site model we used was based on 
Arabidopsis thaliana (L.) Heynh. Our transcriptome sequences came from a 
SOAP assembly of H. sanguinea (courtesy of the 1KP project, D. Soltis, and 
G. Wong; assembly parameters available at https://pods.iplantcollaborative.org/ 
wiki/display/iptol/Access+to+OneKP+data+set ), and the genomic data were the 
set of H. parvifl ora Velvet contigs that matched the COS marker data set. 
All GeneSeqer alignments were evaluated by eye to verify acceptable exon 
sequence identity (i.e., no obvious paralogy or spurious alignment) between 
H. sanguinea and H. parvifl ora var. saurensis. We mostly favored loci with at 
least two introns &gt;100 bp long for locus development. A minority of chosen 
loci had a single longer intron, and two loci were included that were entirely 
exonic but appeared unusually variable based on alignment. We designed a 
278-locus panel, synthesized by MYcroarray (Ann Arbor, Michigan) as 8634 
120-bp oligomers tiled at 3 × coverage of the target loci. The mean locus length 
was 1362 bp (range 555-3672 bp), for a total targeted length of 378,553 bp. </p>

<p>Library preparation -Genomic DNAs were extracted as described previ-
ously ( Folk and Freudenstein, 2014 ). DNA was quantifi ed with a Qubit BR-
assay (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, California), and quality was evaluated 
using a Nanodrop 2000 (Thermo Scientifi c, Waltham, Massachusetts, USA). 
Problematic DNAs were cleaned with a QIAquick kit (QIAGEN , Valencia, 
California, USA); any DNAs too dilute for library preparation were concentrated 
by vacuum centrifugation. One microgram of clean genomic DNA in 60 μ L was 
sonicated using a Covaris machine (model S220; Covaris, Woburn, Massachusetts, 
USA), aiming for fragment size of 500-700 bp. Libraries were prepared with 
55.5 μ L of sonicated DNA, using a NEBNext Ultra kit (New England Biolabs, 
Ipswich, Massachusetts, USA), following the manufacturer's protocols with 
the following modifi cations: size selection aimed for a 500-700-bp range (i.e., 
30 μ L AM XP beads [Beckman Coulter, Brea, California, USA] for the fi rst 
size-selection step, and 15 μ L for the second step), and PCR amplification 
mostly used six cycles (eight cycles for the herbarium specimen). Libraries 
were barcoded using NEBNext Multiplex oligos (New England Biolabs). Li-
brary quality was verifi ed using an Agilent Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, 
Santa Clara, California, USA), and libraries were again quantifi ed by Qubit. 
Any libraries that were too dilute for sequence hybridization were concentrated 
in a vacuum centrifuge. </p>

<p>Probe-based target enrichment -Verifi ed libraries were used in a MYcroarray 
MyBaits in-solution hybridization protocol using our custom phylogenetic lo-
cus panel, following manufacturer protocols (version 2) with the following 
modifi cations: eight libraries were pooled per MyBaits reaction (60 ng each for 
480 ng total input DNA in 6 μ L) to reduce reagent cost and required input 
DNA, and hybridization was conducted for 36 h. PCR conditions used an 
annealing temperature of 60 ° C, an elongation time of 45 s, 15 total cycles, and 
10 μ L of template. Target-enriched library pools were verifi ed for size distribution 
on an Agilent Bioanalyzer, and quantifi ed with an Illumina library quantifi ca-
tion kit (KAPA, Wilmington, Massachusetts, USA). Because adapter dimers 
were problematic for one of the pools, all pools were cleaned following the 
paramagnetic bead-based cleaning procedure in the NEBNext protocol but with 
0.8 volumes of AMPure beads to 1 volume of enriched library. For all target </p>



<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 
Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>

<p>http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>TABLE </p>

<p>1. Statistics for the target enrichment experiment . a </p>

<p>Accession </p>

<p>Percent 
on-target </p>

<p>Mean ( 
± SD) </p>

<p>of low-copy 
locus coverage </p>

<p>Mean low-copy 
locus 
completeness (%) b </p>

<p>Mean exon 
completeness </p>

<p>(%) c </p>

<p>Mean intron 
completeness </p>

<p>(%) c </p>

<p>Percent 
chloroplast 
reads </p>

<p>Chloroplast 
coverage </p>

<p>Chloroplast 
completeness </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>Percent 
mitochondrial </p>

<p>reads </p>

<p>Mitochondrial 
coverage d </p>

<p>Mitochondrial 
completeness </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>Heuchera abramsii </p>

<p>54.7 </p>

<p>173.5 
× ( 
± 75.4 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.8 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>99.6 </p>

<p>7.8 </p>

<p>31.8 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>98.3 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>44.0 </p>

<p>H. acutifolia 
(herbarium specimen) </p>

<p>44.5 </p>

<p>206.0 
× ( 
± 76.5 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.8 </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>99.3 </p>

<p>3.8 </p>

<p>22.0 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>95.3 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>7.2 
× </p>

<p>66.3 </p>

<p>H. americana </p>

<p>var. americana </p>

<p>58.7 </p>

<p>178.9 
× ( 
± 52.5 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>99.5 </p>

<p>3.7 </p>

<p>14.8 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>96.6 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>3.7 
× </p>

<p>52.7 </p>

<p>H. elegans </p>

<p>54.8 </p>

<p>464.6 
× ( 
± 136.5 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>3.4 </p>

<p>38.6 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.7 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>4.7 
× </p>

<p>47.1 </p>

<p>H. grossulariifolia </p>

<p>var. </p>

<p>grossulariifolia </p>

<p>59.6 </p>

<p>262.3 
× ( 
± 70.3 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>99.7 </p>

<p>6.4 </p>

<p>36.9 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.4 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>58.5 </p>

<p>H. missouriensis </p>

<p>60.5 </p>

<p>586.1 
× ( 
± 112.1 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>99.8 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>4.2 </p>

<p>63.4 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>4.9 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>81.3 </p>

<p>H. parishii </p>

<p>47.3 </p>

<p>922.9 
× ( 
± 236.3 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>3.8 </p>

<p>99.8 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.8 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>8.2 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>64.2 </p>

<p>H. parvifl ora </p>

<p>var. parvifl ora </p>

<p>60.6 </p>

<p>1225.7 
× ( 
± 242.9 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>6.7 </p>

<p>220.2 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.7 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>17.8 
× </p>

<p>85.3 </p>

<p>H. parvifolia </p>

<p>var. nivalis </p>

<p>52.8 </p>

<p>714.9 
× ( 
± 168.1 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>51.8 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.7 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>9.4 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>84.7 </p>

<p>H. puberula </p>

<p>55.0 </p>

<p>440.4 
× ( 
± 93.5 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>47.3 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>6.6 
× </p>

<p>73.1 </p>

<p>H. pulchella </p>

<p>47.8 </p>

<p>1303.8 
× ( 
± 254.1 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>5.5 </p>

<p>219.3 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>13.1 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>90.8 </p>

<p>H. rubescens </p>

<p>var. versicolor </p>

<p>55.8 </p>

<p>321.3 
× ( 
± 79.6 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>2.4 </p>

<p>17.6 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>3.5 
× </p>

<p>42.6 </p>

<p>H. villosa </p>

<p>var. villosa </p>

<p>62.6 </p>

<p>361.9 
× ( 
± 76.6 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>100.0 </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>2.9 </p>

<p>24.7 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.1 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>61.4 </p>

<p>H. wootonii </p>

<p>55.7 </p>

<p>275.9 
× ( 
± 72.6 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.8 </p>

<p>99.9 </p>

<p>99.6 </p>

<p>2.8 </p>

<p>17.9 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>99.1 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>4.8 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>60.2 </p>

<p>Mitella pentandra </p>

<p>49.8 </p>

<p>238.9 
× ( 
± 91.7 </p>

<p>× ) </p>

<p>99.6 </p>

<p>99.6 </p>

<p>98.5 </p>

<p>7.2 </p>

<p>41.3 </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>98.6 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>6.6 
× </p>

<p>70.2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>For all calculations, locus four has been omitted. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Locus completeness is based on coverage of the reference sequences. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Region completeness fi gures are based on the percent of the H. parvifl ora </p>

<p>reference to which reads could be mapped. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Coverage of the mitochondrion only counts areas where reads could be mapped. If this calculation included the whole mitochondrion, it would be unfairly down-weighted by long regions (up </p>

<p>to tens of thousands of bases) of uncertain origin that are not shared across species. </p>

<p>arbitrarily excluded the last 49.3% of the intron matrix (introns of approximately 
loci 88-277) to yield a matrix of equivalent length to the exon matrix. Each 
of these two matrices was analyzed in RAxML with an unpartitioned GTR-
GAMMA model, with 1000 bootstrap replicates. 
The 277 gene alignments were also analyzed individually in RAxML to in-
fer gene trees, with the GTR-GAMMA model and 1000 bootstrap replicates. 
The optimal trees and bootstrap samples from each gene tree were analyzed 
using a gene tree-based coalescent approach in MP-EST ( Liu et al., 2010 ) and 
STAR ( Liu et al., 2009 ) using the STRAW server ( Shaw et al., 2013 ). 
Mitella pentandra Hook. was used as the outgroup for the nuclear analysis 
based on the results in Folk and Freudenstein (2014) . Rooting is not as straight-
forward for the chloroplast data set because Heuchera is known to be polyphy-
letic for chloroplast markers due to frequent hybridization with closely related 
genera such as Tiarella L. ( Soltis et al., 1991 ; Folk, Mandel, and Freudenstein,  unpublished data). If a supposed outgroup had captured a Heuchera chloroplast 
genome, this would result in incorrectly rooting the tree within Heuchera . 
While a mitochondrial analysis has never been undertaken for the Heuchera 
group of genera, these concerns could also apply to the mitochondrial data. 
To address these concerns, we repeated the chloroplast and mitochondrial 
read-mapping approach for publicly available short read data from Saxifraga 
granulata L. (one individual from Meer et al., 2014 ) to develop an appropriate 
outgroup sequence well outside the Heuchera group of genera. 
The low-coverage of mitochondrial DNA and the greater divergence from 
the reference resulted in a greater amount of missing data than in other data sets, 
especially in intergenic regions; this was addressed by deleting all columns 
with ≥ 75% missing data (a trial was also made of deleting columns with 50% 
missing data, but this resulted in lowered support values on an identical topol-
ogy; results not shown). Otherwise, the same phylogenetic analysis parameters 
from the low-copy nuclear markers were used for the mitochondrial and chlo-
roplast data sets. 
Any differences in support values between this analysis and the previous 
phylogenetic context of Folk and Freudenstein (2014) could be caused by re-
duced taxon sampling rather than a larger data set, as analyzing fewer taxa re-
duces the tree search space and may lengthen short branches that would have 
been broken up by intermediate taxa. To evaluate this possibility, we reana-
lyzed a reduced version of the earlier matrix, using only DNA characters and 
eliminating all taxa not sampled in this study. Heuchera acutifolia could not be 
sequenced for most markers in the earlier study, so we substituted the close 
relative H. longipetala Moc. ex Ser . For comparability, the matrix was run with 
an unpartitioned GTR-GAMMA model with 1000 bootstrap replicates. </p>

<p>Enrichment statistics -Percent on-target statistics ( Table 1 ) were calcu-
lated by mapping reads to the reference loci using the Geneious native assem-
bler (low sensitivity settings) and dividing the number of mapped reads by the 
total number of reads per each accession; the same method was used to deter-
mine read percentages for the chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes using the 
mitochondrial and chloroplast references. Other assembly statistics ( Table 1 ) 
were derived from the BWA assemblies used in downstream analyses, but also 
calculated in Geneious. Missing data, pairwise identity, and other alignment 
statistics ( Table 2 ) were derived in Geneious from the MAFFT alignments. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Target enrichment -Our target enrichment methodology re-
sulted in between 45% and 63% on-target sequences. This range 
is relatively high for interspecies target enrichment (e.g., compare 
Weitemier et al., 2014 ), and may result from the particularly low 
divergence among species of Heuchera , causing high comple-
mentarity between probes and target sequences. This resulted in 
relatively high coverage numbers for the study loci; although cov-
erage numbers were variable, all samples had greater than 100 × 
average coverage ( Table 1 ). Low coverage for target loci was ex-
tremely rare, other than for the excluded locus (see Methods). This 
locus appears to be a pseudogene; no well-matched short reads of 
this locus were obtained for about half of the samples. 
The clear explanation for the difference in coverage between 
samples is uneven pooling, rather than on-target sequence per-
centage, which did not vary particularly greatly between species. 
Hence the success of target enrichment was not markedly different </p>

<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 </p>

<p>Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>

<p>5 of 10 
http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>nodes (99% on one node in sect. Rhodoheuchera concerning 
the placement of H. rubescens Torr. var. versicolor (Greene) 
M. G. Stewart; otherwise 100%). Coalescent analyses in MP-
EST and STAR ( Fig. 2 ) likewise had primarily high support 
values. There was only one point of discord between these 
methods: coalescent methods found H. pulchella Wooton &amp;  Standl. and H. rubescens var. versicolor as sister to each other, 
whereas concatenation inferred these as successively sister to 
H. parishii , H. elegans , and H. abramsii. The phylogenetic 
analyses of organellar data (chloroplast, Fig. 3 ; mitochondrial, 
Fig. 4 ) likewise resulted in high support values, although these 
relationships differed greatly from those suggested by nuclear 
data. </p>

<p>Organellar reference genomes -The chloroplast genome 
of H. parvifl ora var. saurensis (154,696 bp; mean coverage 
1939.8 × ; no map shown) is conventional among angiosperms 
in terms of structure and size, with complete synteny shared 
with other members of the order. The H. parvifl ora var. sauren-
sis mitochondrial genome (541,954 bp; mean coverage 141.9 × , 
draft map in Fig. 5 ) is much less conserved in terms of struc-
ture, as is typical for plant mitochondrial genomes ( Sloan, 2013 ), 
with only a few very short regions of synteny and only short 
stretches of similar sequence preserved when compared to the 
closest reference, V. vinifera (Appendix S2). It has all func-
tional mitochondrial protein-coding genes that are present in Vitis , 
as well as numerous interspersed sequences of chloroplast origin. 
BLAST searches against the Marchantia polymorpha L. mitochon-
drial genome showed that all conserved mitochondrial genes 
absent in Vitis were also absent in Heuchera. Processes of intra-
molecular recombination and multiple conformations of the 
plant mitochondrial genome are thought to be mediated by moder-
ately long repeat regions ( Alverson et al., 2011 , and citations  therein), of which we found four. These repeat regions were in-
dependently supported by locally higher read coverage. Unusually , 
the smaller three repeat regions (6428 bp, 1196 bp, 550 bp) 
that we found overlap with the largest repeat (32,849 bp), but 
with a single copy of each elsewhere in the genome. The issue 
of multiple genome conformations is not critical for assem-
blies intended for analysis with phylogenetic methods. Using 
these two organellar references, we were able to infer resolved </p>

<p>between samples. Even for the outgroup Mitella pentandra , 
where slight signs of intron dropout are apparent (~1% lower 
assembly completeness, Table 1 ), it remained possible to as-
semble the vast majority of intronic sequences. 
Comparison with the proportion of on-target reads for the 
unenriched genome-skimming sample (0.057%, vs. average 
54.7% on target for enriched individuals) showed that the fold 
enrichment was very high (0.547/0.00057 ~960-fold enrich-
ment assuming constant background prevalence of target loci 
across samples), consistent with &gt;10 cycles increase in target 
concentration in the qPCR assays for all enriched individuals. 
Overall locus assembly completeness was also nearly 100% for 
all samples ( Table 1 ); this applies both to exons and introns, the 
latter of which had negligibly lower completeness. 
Percent pairwise identity calculations from the phylogenetic 
matrix ( Table 1 ) show that for Heuchera species, the percent diver-
gence of introns is fourfold that of exons. Similarly, introns had 
about four times the percent parsimony-informative characters. 
While nucleotide diversity is high in introns, as expected they are 
also quite rich in indel characters, &gt;40-fold more so than exons. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic inference -The concatenated nuclear tree 
( Fig. 1 ) was completely resolved with strong support on all </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Concatenated maximum likelihood (ML) tree based on 277 low-copy nuclear loci; branch lengths in the fi gure represent ML branch length 
estimates. Coloring of branches represents the taxonomic sections recognized in Folk and Freudenstein (2014) : orange = sect. Holochloa ; blue = sect. 
Heuchera ; green = sect. Bracteatae ; magenta = sect. Rhodoheuchera. Values plotted on branches are support values based on 5000 bootstrap replicates. 
Varietal assignments in sections Heuchera and Rhodoheuchera refl ect the taxonomy of the treatments by Rosendahl et al. (1936) and Wells (1984) ; taxon 
labels in sect. Holochloa refl ect Folk and Freudenstein (in press). </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Statistics for the phylogenetic alignments of low-copy nuclear 
loci. </p>

<p>Sequence statistic </p>

<p>Entire 
experiment 
Exons only Introns only </p>

<p>Percent pairwise identity 
(pairwise divergence) </p>

<p>96.4% (3.6%) 98.8% (1.2%) 95.2% (4.8%) </p>

<p>Number (percent) parsimony 
informative characters </p>

<p>17,691 (4.6%) 1830 (1.5%) 15,861 (6.1%) </p>

<p>Percent invariant characters 
82.90% 
93.40% 
77.80% 
Undetermined sequence (N or ?) 
0.20% 
0.10% 
0.30% 
Gap characters (-) 
3.00% 
0.10% 
4.30% 
Overall alignment length 
387,941 bp 
126,540 bp 
261,401 bp 
Average coverage per locus 
511.8 × 
Average locus length 
1362 bp 
Percent on-target reads for 
H. parvifl ora var. saurensis 
(unenriched genome 
skimming) </p>

<p>0.06% </p>



<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 
Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>

<p>http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>( Folk and Freudenstein, 2014 ); however, the increase in support 
was remarkable in several instances. The improvement in sup-
port over earlier work was most remarkable for section Rho-
doheuchera ( Fig. 1 , marked in magenta), the largest in the genus 
(~17 species). In Folk and Freudenstein (2014) , this section 
was the most problematic group for phylogenetic inference; 
there was weak or no support for all relationships in the sec-
tion, and at best moderate support for the monophyly of the 
section as a whole. The new data set confi dently confi rms the 
monophyly of sect. Rhodoheuchera and resolves relationships 
in this group. 
The analysis of the reduced Folk and Freudenstein (2014) 
matrix (Appendix S3) showed that higher support values were 
due to a mixture of reduced taxon sampling and more informa-
tive data. The average nodal bootstrap (BS) proportion was 
100% for the entire phylogenomic data set and 78.4% for the 
Sanger data set; several nodes in the Sanger data set were higher 
than in earlier work. Nevertheless, the improvement caused by 
greater locus sampling is apparent; the addition of further taxa 
would infl ate the tree search space, likely causing a greater dis-
parity between the two data sets. It is important to note that the 
Sanger tree was incongruent in several places with the phyloge-
nomic data set; particularly, section Heuchera (blue, Appendix 
S3) is sister to the rest of the genus (BS 76). Likewise, the posi-
tions of H. rubescens var. versicolor (BS 45) and H. parvifl ora 
var. parvifl ora (BS 99) differed. The position of section Heuchera </p>

<p>phylogenies with high support values as well (chloroplast, Fig. 4 ; 
mitochondrion, Fig. 5 ). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Low-copy locus design -Most eukaryotic nuclear genes 
have introns; this splice site structure is highly conserved ( The  Arabidopsis Initiative, 2000 ; Roy et al., 2003 ), making these 
regions a practically inexhaustible source of phylogenetic sig-
nal. Fully assembled genomes are not required for marker de-
velopment. At minimum, however, intronic locus design for 
targeted sequencing requires the researcher to obtain a large 
number of contigs at least as long as the desired marker length, 
as well as transcriptomic sequences to identify splice sites. Fi-
nally, some method must be used to select putative low-copy 
genes, such as curated genome drafts from the study organism 
( de Sousa et al., 2014 ; Weitemier et al., 2014 ) or, when this in-
formation is absent, panels of loci derived from model organ-
ism genomes ( Mandel et al., 2014 ; this study). In the latter case, 
if genome skimming data are available from one of the study 
organisms, coverage data are effective as an independent source 
of evidence for low-copy marker status. </p>

<p>Concatenated nuclear analysis -The relationships recovered 
were broadly congruent with results based on Sanger sequencing </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Maximum likelihood tree of the chloroplast data set. Branch proportions, coloring, and labeling follow Fig. 1 , except that the outgroup branch 
length is not to scale. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Coalescent tree estimated in MP-EST. Branch labels are bootstrap supports, based on 1000 bootstrap replicates per tree. The STAR result was 
topologically identical; where support values differed the two values are plotted as "MP-EST proportion/STAR proportion." Branch coloring follows the 
sectional taxonomy as in Fig. 1 ; branch lengths are not to scale. </p>

<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 </p>

<p>Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>

<p>7 of 10 
http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>practically complete; the few missing regions tend to corre-
spond to long A-T repeats and other types of microsatellite-like 
regions (total aligned length 158,903 bp; 1.8% missing data). 
This study serves as the fi rst sequence-based confi rmation of 
the discord between nuclear and chloroplast phylogenies (see 
Soltis et al., 1991 ; Soltis and Kuzoff, 1995 ) and uncovers new 
discord beyond what has previously been observed. The clade 
of Heuchera in this analysis that resolves as sister to Mitella 
pentandra corresponds to a clade hypothesized to have cap-
tured the Tiarella plastome ( Soltis et al., 1991 ), while the clade 
consisting of H. parvifolia , H. acutifolia , and H. pulchella cor-
responds to the clade hypothesized to possess the ancestral 
plastid genome. However, the position of H. parishii , H. ele-
gans , and H. abramsii (species unsampled in the earlier study) 
as a clade sister to the rest of the Heuchera group of genera 
represents a new lineage not uncovered previously. </p>

<p>Mitochondrial phylogeny -We acknowledge that, due to the 
lower coverage of the mitochondrial data in many samples 
(mostly caused by the lower background prevalence and larger 
size of mitochondrial genomes as compared to plastomes), our 
mitochondrial phylogeny should be viewed as experimental. The 
lack of conservation of basic structural features and even large 
stretches of sequence further hinders assembly. Nevertheless, 
it is remarkable that our mitochondrial analysis (total aligned 
length 421,260 bp; 43.9% missing data) resulted in a resolved 
topology, largely with strong support values, in a genus for which 
mitochondrial phylogenetics has never been performed. 
The mitochondrial phylogeny ( Fig. 5 ) shows a similar degree 
of confl ict with the nuclear topology as does the chloroplast 
tree. In fact, there are some parallel points of confl ict between 
the data sets. Particularly, the position of H. parishii , H. ele-
gans , and H. abramsii as sister to all other members of the Heu-
chera group of genera is exactly congruent with the chloroplast 
analysis, although the topology within this clade differs some-
what. Such mitochondrial skimming results have broad rele-
vance for plant systematists. Mitochondrial markers have been 
under-sampled in plant phylogenetics as compared to nuclear 
and chloroplast markers; in plants, mitochondrial loci have seen 
use mainly at higher levels (e.g., Chaw et al., 2000 ; Jian et al.,  2008 ), and among conifer species ( Gugerli et al., 2001 ), and 
only occasionally studied alone to infer mitochondrial trees. 
Some work has successfully used mitochondrial skimming </p>

<p>is congruent with the earlier study, while the positions of the 
other two were equivocal. The relatively high bootstraps for 
two of these anomalous Sanger relationships is unlikely to have 
been caused by reduced taxon sampling; it is more likely that 
the smaller data set inadequately sampled the genome for con-
fl icting phylogenetic signals for the positions of these taxa. 
Intron-and exon-only phylogenetic analyses (Appendices 
S4, S5) revealed further differences in these data types. Support 
values for the two analyses were only somewhat different (the 
intron-only analysis had 96.8% average nodal support; the 
exon-only analysis had 94.8% average support). However, only 
the intron-only analysis was congruent with the full data set 
result. For the exon-only analysis, H. rubescens var. versicolor 
and H. acutifolia exchanged topological positions (BS 78). Be-
cause the full analysis also addressed gene tree heterogeneity 
through coalescent analysis, the exon-only result does not ap-
pear to be optimal. </p>

<p>Coalescent nuclear analysis -While we are aware of the is-
sues associated with using long genetic loci with multispecies 
coalescent methods and the importance of incorporating gene 
tree estimation error ( Gatesy and Springer, 2014 ), nevertheless 
we contend that a coalescent analysis retains heuristic value, 
particularly in concert with the more standard concatenation 
methods. Especially when only well-supported nodes are con-
sidered, for this data set the difference between coalescent and 
concatenated estimates of the species tree is not particularly 
great. It is interesting that the only point of discord between 
concatenated and coalescent approaches was one of only two 
nodes in the coalescent analysis below 95% (= strong support; 
however, at 88% [MP-EST] or 78% [STAR] it is still moderate); 
Folk and Freudenstein (2014) also noted that points of discord 
between coalescence and concatenation estimates tend to be as-
sociated with lower nodal support in the coalescent tree. On the 
other hand, MP-EST and STAR were remarkably consistent 
with one another. </p>

<p>Chloroplast phylogeny -Heuchera is known as a particu-
larly dramatic example of chloroplast capture ( Soltis et al.,  1991 ), although in the time that has passed since this system 
was examined it has become possible to sequence essentially 
entire chloroplast genomes to explore this signal further. In the 
current analysis ( Fig. 4 ), the chloroplast genome assemblies are </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Maximum likelihood tree of the mitochondrial data set. Branch coloring and labeling follow Fig. 1 , except that the outgroup branch length is 
not to scale. </p>



<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 
Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>

<p>http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>independently resolve past hybridization events (see also 
Govindarajulu et al., 2015 ). The current paucity of good refer-
ence mitochondrial genomes among angiosperms may be among 
the major setbacks preventing resolved mitochondrial phyloge-
netic hypotheses in many plant groups. Given their unusual 
patterns of evolution, it will be interesting to explore whether </p>

<p>( Straub et al., 2012 ; Ripma et al., 2014 , Govindarajulu et al.,  2015 ), but this remains less common than the use of chloroplast 
data. Mitochondrial capture is well-known in animals ( Good  et al., 2008 , and citations therein); hence in plant groups, par-
ticularly those that are believed to have undergone chloro-
plast capture, mitochondrial phylogenies promise to further and </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Map of regions of interest in the mitochondrial genome of Heuchera parvifl ora var. saurensis , prepared using OrganellarGenomeDRAW 
( Lohse et al., 2013 ). The outer circle depicts protein-coding genes, rRNAs, and tRNAs; the inner circle depicts the large repeat regions. Genes annotated 
on the inner face of the circle indicate genes transcribed in a clockwise orientation, and genes on the outer face are transcribed counterclockwise. The 
orientation of the repeat regions is arbitrary; the green and blue regions are direct repeats, while the yellow and lavender regions exist both as direct repeats 
(where they overlap the green direct repeat) and inverted repeats (elsewhere). Annotated gene regions include both introns and exons. Plant mitochondrial 
genomes have several trans-spliced genes (e.g., nad5 ); only the cistronic portions are annotated to avoid overlap. </p>

<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 </p>

<p>Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
mitochondrial phylogenies show capture events as frequently 
as has been observed for chloroplast markers. </p>

<p>Conclusions -Even given large phylogenomic data sets, se-
quencing methods and marker choice must be no less carefully 
optimized for particular research questions. Recent radiations 
straddle the boundary of phylogenetic and population-level pro-
cesses, lending themselves to targeted enrichment of intronic 
markers. For these systems, where coalescent branch lengths are 
short and barriers to gene fl ow often poorly developed, gene tree 
discord is likely to be prevalent. Examining confl icting histories 
necessitates sequences long enough to infer resolved gene trees. 
The ability to assemble large amounts of off-target organellar 
data with such methods further results in a robust sampling of 
alternative genomic histories. Likewise, sequence divergence 
will usually be low in recent radiations, with the result that target-
ing more conserved portions of the genome may waste sequenc-
ing effort. Compounding these diffi culties for any inferential 
method is the effect of missing data; we have shown that this 
method results in essentially no missing data for targeted nuclear 
markers and chloroplast data (in contrast to a typical RNA-seq or 
RAD-seq experiment; see also Weitemier et al., 2014 ). 
In the increasingly data-rich fi eld of systematics, phyloge-
nomic confl ict is becoming the rule rather than the exception, 
with the result that reporting a single total-evidence tree with-
out examining the underlying data is becoming less satisfac-
tory. As systematists grapple with gene tree heterogeneity in 
the most diffi cult systems, targeted methods optimized for gene 
tree resolution are poised to address all of these concerns. Intron-
containing low-copy sequence markers, long-favored for Sanger 
sequencing ( Folk and Freudenstein, 2014 , and citations therein), 
will be increasingly important in genera and species complexes 
for a robust sampling not only for a total-evidence phylogeny, 
but more critically for individual gene histories. </p>

<p>LITERATURE CITED </p>





<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2015 3 ( 8 ): 1500039 
Folk et al.-Intron enrichment in Heuchera 
doi:10.3732/apps.1500039 </p>



<p>APPENDIX 1 . Voucher information for accessions used in this study . </p>

<p>Species </p>

<p>Herbarium voucher no. 
(Herbarium a ) 
Collection locality 
Geographic coordinates </p>

<p>Heuchera abramsii Rydb. 
Folk 45 (OS) 
Mount Baldy, CA, USA 
34 ° 17.423 ′ N, 117 ° 38.738 ′ W 
H. acutifolia Rose (herbarium specimen) 
Matus 14560 (TEX) 
Rancho Poza, VER, Mexico 
20 ° 32 ′ 10.38 ″ N, 98 ° 28 ′ 51.58 ″ W 
H. americana L. var. americana 
Folk 70 (OS) 
Berry Road, Wayne National Forest, OH, USA 
38 ° 36 ′ 9.11 ″ N, 82 ° 20 ′ 22.16 ″ W 
H. elegans Abrams 
Folk 44 (OS) 
Talus above road to Crystal Lake, 0.5 mi. from 
Hwy. 39, CA, USA </p>

<p>43 ° 18.940 ′ N, 117 ° 50.537 ′ W </p>

<p>H. grossulariifolia Rydb. var. 
grossulariifolia (tetraploid) </p>

<p>Folk 160 (OS) 
Cliff above roadside parking lot outside of Riggins, 
ID, USA </p>

<p>45 ° 24 ′ 40 ″ N, 116 ° 19 ′ 35 ″ W </p>

<p>H. missouriensis Rosend. 
Folk I-69 (OS) 
Little Grand Canyon near Carbondale, IL, USA 
37 ° 41 ′ 4.46 ″ N, 89 ° 24 ′ 38.92 ″ W 
H. parishii Rydb. 
Folk 43 (OS) 
Sugarloaf Mountain, CA, USA 
34 ° 12.003 ′ N, 116 ° 47.621 ′ W 
H. parvifl ora Bartl. var. parvifl ora 
Folk 72 (OS) 
Natural Bridge State Park, KY, USA 
37 ° 46 ′ 26.33 ″ N, 83 ° 40 ′ 51.39 ″ W 
H. parvifolia var. nivalis (Rosend., Butters &amp; 
Lakela) Á. Löve, D. Löve &amp; B. M. Kapoor </p>

<p>Folk 55 (OS) 
Along Rock Creek Hills Road, Lost Park, CO, USA 39 ° 20 ′ 59 ″ N, 105 ° 41 ′ 25 ″ W </p>

<p>H. puberula Mack. &amp; Bush 
Folk 69 (OS) 
Pea Vine Road near Big Springs, 
Ozark National Riverways, MO, USA </p>

<p>36.94794 ° N, 90.99215 ° W </p>

<p>H. pulchella Wooton &amp; Standl. 
Folk 20 (OS) 
Sandia Crest, NM, USA 
35 ° 12.662 ′ N, 106 ° 27.029 ′ W 
H. rubescens Torr. var. versicolor (Greene) 
M. G. Stewart </p>

<p>Folk 26 (OS) 
Outcrop above Hwy. 159, NM, USA 
33 ° 22 ′ 14 ″ N, 108 ° 41 ′ 34 ″ W </p>

<p>H. villosa Michx. var. villosa 
Folk I-1 (OS) 
Devil's Courthouse, NC, USA 
35 ° 18 ′ 9.44 ″ N, 82 ° 53 ′ 44.39 ″ W 
H. wootonii Rydb. 
Folk 22 (OS) 
Dry bank, Capitan Peak, NM, USA 
33 ° 36 ′ 45 ″ N, 105 ° 14 ′ 45 ″ W 
Mitella pentandra Hook. 
Folk 128 (OS) 
Pacifi c Crest Trail access from Hwy. 90, WA, USA 
47 25 ′ 40 ″ N, 121 24 ′ 48 ″ W </p>

<p>a OS = Ohio State University Herbarium; TEX = University of Texas at Austin Herbarium. </p>

</text></tei>