<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4292688" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>From the creation of the Unified Health System </p>

<p>(SUS) through to the present time, much has been </p>

<p>discussed about its advances -as well as about the </p>

<p>problems which are met. The creation of the SUS aimed </p>

<p>to change the situation of inequality in the health care </p>

<p>provided to the population, making public attendance for </p>

<p>any citizen obligatory, services being offered in primary, </p>

<p>secondary and tertiary care </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>However, "it is difficult to think about a universal </p>

<p>and fair Health System in a country like Brazil, where </p>

<p>many lack the conditions to survive (...). In this </p>

<p>regard, the 'necessary SUS', for us to have a more fair </p>

<p>society, is defined by its legal principles. In its turn, </p>

<p>the 'possible SUS', today, is that which is found in the </p>

<p>routine functioning of the health services. In spite of </p>

<p>the significant advances made since its beginning in </p>

<p>the 1990s, the 'possible SUS' and the 'necessary SUS' </p>

<p>remain far apart" </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Based on its principles, this system indicates a </p>

<p>widening of health professionals' actions, with the </p>

<p>objective of enabling them to ensure quality care for all, </p>

<p>with technical and humane competence and in line with </p>

<p>the system's guidelines, in addition to establishing links </p>

<p>with the service users, guaranteeing their participation in </p>

<p>decision-making in the health services. Such challenges </p>

<p>require the health professional to be in consonance with </p>

<p>the system's doctrinal and operational precepts, as well </p>

<p>as the symbolic constructions which support such actions. </p>

<p>These principles, in being used as a benchmark, </p>

<p>allow the recognition that the entire health institution </p>

<p>and its professionals have the commitment to meet </p>

<p>the service user's health needs with technical-scientific </p>

<p>quality, being able to resolve issues through access and </p>

<p>embracement </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In considering that the experiences within the </p>

<p>health services, and the information available define </p>

<p>psycho-social constructions which are shared by the </p>

<p>social group to which the individuals belong, these </p>

<p>therefore constitute socio-professional representations, </p>

<p>characterized by a hybrid construction between </p>

<p>conventional wisdom and reified knowledge </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In this regard, the social representations are </p>

<p>characterized by the knowledge of the common wisdom </p>

<p>which guides the decisions, the actions, the thoughts </p>

<p>and the attitudes of the groups and the people in their </p>

<p>routines </p>

<p>(3-4) </p>

<p>, but can also be used for analyzing the </p>

<p>technical-professional knowledge made up regarding a </p>

<p>given object of work </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In 
considering 
the 
symbolical 
dimensions </p>

<p>associated with the health system, especially taking </p>

<p>into account that thought and action establish important </p>

<p>relations, the following were defined as objectives for </p>

<p>this study: analyzing and comparing the incorporation </p>

<p>of the ethical-doctrinal and organizational principles in </p>

<p>the social representations on the SUS, among health </p>

<p>professionals in the city of Rio de Janeiro. </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>This is a qualitative and descriptive study, </p>

<p>grounded in the structural approach of the theory of </p>

<p>social representations </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>, undertaken in 2008, in eight </p>

<p>health institutions located in the city of Rio de Janeiro. </p>

<p>It was submitted to the Research Ethics Committee and </p>

<p>approved under protocol N. 196/08. </p>

<p>The population studied was made up of 125 health </p>

<p>professionals, of whom 55 (44%) were educated to </p>

<p>high school level and 70 (56%) had attended higher </p>

<p>education. The hypothesis behind the choice of the </p>

<p>subjects -and, especially, the inclusion of professionals </p>

<p>educated to high school level -is the existence of </p>

<p>different conceptions regarding the principles of the </p>

<p>SUS. For selecting the 125 subjects, the following were </p>

<p>considered as inclusion criteria: health professionals </p>

<p>who had worked in the public health service for over 20 </p>

<p>years, such that their professional experience dated to </p>

<p>before 1990. </p>

<p>The subjects answered an instrument which used </p>

<p>the technique of free word association, which seeks to </p>

<p>access the organization and internal structure of the </p>

<p>social representation analyzed. Based in this technique, </p>

<p>the subjects were requested to evoke five words which </p>

<p>immediately came to mind on hearing the word "SUS". </p>

<p>The words evoked were recorded by the researcher on </p>

<p>the data collection instrument. This technique is part of </p>

<p>the theory of the central nucleus or structural approach, </p>

<p>as a complementary approach of the theory of social </p>

<p>representations, used as a conceptual basis in the </p>

<p>analysis of the data from this research </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The data was analyzed using the <rs type="software">EVOC</rs> (Ensemble </p>

<p>de Programmes Permettant L´Analyse des Évocations) </p>

<p>(Group of Programs for the Analysis of Evoked </p>

<p>Responses) 2003 software, which allows one to achieve </p>

<p>the organization of the words based on the hierarchy </p>

<p>expressed through the frequency and the natural </p>

<p>order of the evocation, through the construction of the </p>

<p>Vergès matrix, where the evoked words are distributed, </p>

<p>considering the criteria of higher frequencies and mean </p>

<p>61 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Pontes APM, Oliveira DC, Gomes AMT. </p>

<p>order of evocation (MOE) </p>

<p>(6-7) </p>

<p>. This corresponds to four </p>

<p>quadrants, in which in the top left one may observe </p>

<p>the elements with a frequency which is higher than, or </p>

<p>equal to, the mean frequency, and with a lower mean </p>

<p>order of evocation (evoked more readily). In the top </p>

<p>right quadrant, one finds the more important peripheral </p>

<p>elements, due to their higher frequencies. In the bottom </p>

<p>right quadrant, one finds elements which are less </p>

<p>frequent and less-readily evoked, and in the bottom </p>

<p>left quadrant there are the elements which, in spite </p>

<p>of presenting low frequencies, are considered highly </p>

<p>important because of the privileged order of evocation </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Aiming for the detection of the degree of </p>

<p>connectivity of the elements identified as participants </p>

<p>of the social representation analyzed, the technique of </p>

<p>similitude analysis was adopted, proposed by Flament in </p>

<p>1986 </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>. This technique may be defined as being aimed </p>

<p>at the verification of the "quantity of links or connections </p>

<p>which a given element maintains with other elements of </p>

<p>the representation" </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>So as to undertake this analysis, the procedures </p>

<p>proposed by researchers who use the structural </p>

<p>approach of representations was followed </p>

<p>(5-8) </p>

<p>. After the </p>

<p>construction of the Vergès matrix, the co-occurrence of </p>

<p>the words which make up this picture was calculated, </p>

<p>considering only the subjects who evoked at least two </p>

<p>words, given that a relation of connectivity can only </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Vergès matrix for the inductive term "SUS" among health professionals in eight health institutions. Rio de </p>

<p>Janeiro, RJ, Brazil, 2009. (n=125) </p>

<p>exist between one term and another </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>. As the subjects </p>

<p>who did not evoke at least two words from the Vergès </p>

<p>matrix were excluded, therefore, 99 subjects remained </p>

<p>in the analysis of general similitude, 56 having higher </p>

<p>education, and 43 a high school education. </p>

<p>In order to calculate the rates, the table of co-</p>

<p>occurrence was produced, and the calculation of the </p>

<p>rate of similitude was undertaken for each pair of </p>

<p>words. Based on the set of rates calculated and their </p>

<p>connections, the maximum tree was configured, </p>

<p>which is characterized as a graphical representation </p>

<p>of the connections between the elements of one social </p>

<p>representation, without allowing the formation of cycles, </p>

<p>as only the biggest rates are maintained </p>

<p>(5-8) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In the interpretation of this tree, one considers the </p>

<p>hierarchy of the values of the links between the terms, </p>

<p>their neighbor relationship, and the connotation taken </p>

<p>on by each term, as a function of the others which link </p>

<p>to it </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In order to understand the results of the similitude </p>

<p>analysis, it is essential first to check the structure of the </p>

<p>social representation analyzed. Based on the application </p>

<p>of the technique of free word association, 569 words </p>

<p>were evoked by the 125 subjects, among which there </p>

<p>were 96 different ones. </p>

<p>Mean Order of Evocations (M.O.E.) </p>

<p>&lt;2.8 
≥2.8 </p>

<p>Average Freq. 
Term evoked 
Central Elements 
Freq. 
M.O.E. 
Term evoked 
1 
st Periphery 
Freq. 
M.O.E. </p>

<p>≥15 </p>

<p>Attendance 
27 
2.148 
Attends everybody 
22 
2.909 </p>

<p>Doesn't work 
25 
2.600 
Duty of the State 
18 
3.056 </p>

<p>Disorganization 
20 
2.500 
Idealism 
15 
3.067 </p>

<p>Attendance to the poor 
19 
2.737 </p>

<p>Unified Health System 
17 
1.765 </p>

<p>Health 
16 
2.563 </p>

<p>Average Freq. 
Term evoked 
Contrast Elements 
Freq. 
M.O.E. 
Term evoked 
2 
nd Periphery 
Freq. 
M.O.E. </p>

<p>&lt;15 </p>

<p>Fairness 
14 
2.357 
Access 
12 
3.583 </p>

<p>Unification 
13 
1.846 
Good attendance 
12 
3.250 </p>

<p>Difficulty 
12 
2.083 
Good 
12 
2.833 </p>

<p>Organization 
12 
2.583 
Inattention 
12 
3.583 </p>

<p>Bad 
11 
2.636 
Hierarchization 
12 
3.417 </p>

<p>Comprehensive care 
11 
3.364 </p>

<p>Professional work 
9 
3.667 </p>

<p>Training 
9 
4.000 </p>



<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem 2014 Jan.-Feb.;22(1):59-67. </p>

<p>In accordance with the Theory of the Central </p>

<p>Nucleus, the words located in the top left quadrant -</p>

<p>attendance, doesn't work, disorganization, attendance to </p>

<p>the poor, unified health system and health -characterize </p>

<p>the representation's possible central nucleus, as they </p>

<p>were evoked a greater number of times and more </p>

<p>readily. These elements characterize the hard part of </p>

<p>the representation, less sensitive to changes, due to the </p>

<p>subjects' external context or routine practices </p>

<p>(5,10) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In this analysis, it was possible to identify, in the </p>

<p>probable central nucleus of the representation, elements </p>

<p>which indicate different dimensions -pragmatic, </p>

<p>imagetic and evaluative of the SUS -with emphasis on </p>

<p>the functional character of the system. One can observe </p>

<p>a negative positioning on the part of the professionals, </p>

<p>in relation to its functionality, as the words which form </p>

<p>the possible central nucleus of the representation of </p>

<p>the SUS are predominantly of neutral and negative </p>

<p>meanings (doesn't work, disorganization, attendance to </p>

<p>the poor, health and unified health system). </p>

<p>The peripheral system of the social representation </p>

<p>is characterized by being organized around the central </p>

<p>nucleus, being constituted in the interface between </p>

<p>this nucleus and the concrete situation in which the </p>

<p>representation is constructed </p>

<p>(5,10) </p>

<p>. In the top right </p>

<p>quadrant -the first periphery -the lexicons attends </p>

<p>everybody, duty of the State, and idealism were </p>

<p>identified. In the bottom right quadrant -the second </p>

<p>periphery -one finds the terms access, good attendance, </p>

<p>good, inattention, hierarchization, comprehensive care, </p>

<p>professional work, and training. The elements present </p>

<p>in this quadrant are infrequent and are defined as less </p>

<p>important among the terms evoked </p>

<p>(5,9) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In the bottom left quadrant -contrast elements -it </p>

<p>may be perceived that these tend to be associated with </p>

<p>the meanings of the first periphery of the representation, </p>

<p>through the presence of positive elements and the </p>

<p>incorporation of the principles of the SUS, contrasting </p>

<p>with the central nucleus </p>

<p>(9,11) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In specific contexts, elements present in the </p>

<p>periphery of the representation may be considered </p>

<p>central, in the light of the high frequencies with which </p>

<p>they were evoked. However, in complementary fashion, </p>

<p>a second indicator of the centrality is admitted, based </p>

<p>on the large quantity of links which one element </p>

<p>maintains with others of the representation, besides </p>

<p>their salience </p>

<p>(5,12) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The analysis of the connectivity of the elements </p>

<p>evoked, presented in the maximum tree of Figure 2, </p>

<p>supports this hypothesis. </p>

<p>Bad </p>

<p>disorganization </p>

<p>inattention </p>

<p>doesn't work </p>

<p>idealism </p>

<p>attendance to the poor </p>

<p>difficulty </p>

<p>Attendance </p>

<p>Attends everybody </p>

<p>fairness </p>

<p>access </p>

<p>Duty of the State </p>

<p>Hierarchization </p>

<p>Comprehensive care </p>

<p>Good 
training </p>

<p>Professional work </p>

<p>good attendance </p>

<p>Unified Health System </p>

<p>training </p>

<p>health </p>

<p>organization 
unification </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,02 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,03 
,03 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,06 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>Figure 2 -Maximum similitude tree of the health professionals' evocations. Rio de Janeiro, </p>

<p>RJ, Brazil, 2009 (n=99) </p>

<p>The cognition which established the most </p>

<p>connections on the maximum tree was attendance, </p>

<p>already indicated as central in the Vergès matrix, </p>

<p>followed by attends everybody, which is found in the </p>

<p>first periphery in the structural analysis. As a result of </p>

<p>the possibility of the connectivity being considered as </p>

<p>a second criteria of centrality </p>

<p>(5,12) </p>

<p>, this lexicon may be </p>

<p>considered, hypothetically, as belonging to the central </p>

<p>nucleus of the representation of the SUS for health </p>

<p>professionals. </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Pontes APM, Oliveira DC, Gomes AMT. </p>

<p>Figure 3 -The maximum similitude tree of the evocations of the health professionals with </p>

<p>higher education. Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil, 2009 (n=56) </p>

<p>Among the elements which are connected with </p>

<p>attends everybody, the following stand out: training, </p>

<p>fairness, access, duty of the State, comprehensive care </p>

<p>and good. One may observe a positive attitude related </p>

<p>to this element, as all the terms linked to it have this </p>

<p>character. Another point of discussion is centered on the </p>

<p>fact that the other doctrinal principles which appear in </p>

<p>the analysis are associated with it. </p>

<p>Emphasis deserves to be given to the connection </p>

<p>established 
between 
comprehensive 
care 
and </p>

<p>hierarchization, as these establish the theoretical and </p>

<p>practical association of these two principles in the </p>

<p>health professionals' symbolic constructions, this being </p>

<p>confirmed by the schematic distribution on the similitude </p>

<p>tree, associated with the rates of connectivity. </p>

<p>The lexicon attendance associated with attends </p>

<p>everybody has the highest number of connections </p>

<p>among the terms evoked. In this regard, the various </p>

<p>facets taken on by attendance stand out, which in this </p>

<p>structure expresses a positive attitude, linked to elements </p>

<p>such as good attendance, health, unified health system, </p>

<p>professional work, attendance to the poor, and difficulty. </p>

<p>These connections reflect that, in spite of there existing </p>

<p>difficulties in the attendance process, the professionals </p>

<p>have a positive attitude related to the same, in addition </p>

<p>to re-affirming the characterization of the attendance as </p>

<p>the identity of the SUS. </p>

<p>It stands out that the principles of the SUS were </p>

<p>presented as integrated into the maximum tree, and the </p>

<p>negative elements -disorganization and doesn't work </p>

<p>-were shown as accessory elements to this structure, </p>

<p>permeated by attendance to the poor, through a weak </p>

<p>link characterized by the lowest rate of similitude, </p>

<p>among all the others. </p>

<p>Seeking better to understand the subgroup which </p>

<p>has a positive attitude associated with the SUS and the </p>

<p>incorporation of the principles into the representation, </p>

<p>a complementary comparative analysis was undertaken </p>

<p>among the professionals with high school education and </p>

<p>with higher education. </p>

<p>In accordance with the proposal of the structural </p>

<p>approach of the social representations, a social </p>

<p>representation may only be considered different if its </p>

<p>nucleus is too </p>

<p>(7,10) </p>

<p>. In analyzing the structure of the </p>

<p>social representation of the professionals with higher </p>

<p>education, the expression attends everybody and the </p>

<p>word fairness were present in the probable central </p>

<p>nucleus, allowing one to infer that this is the subgroup </p>

<p>responsible for the incorporation of the principles of </p>

<p>the SUS and for the positive attitude in relation to the </p>

<p>health system in the general representation of the group </p>

<p>studied, and which has a representation which is distinct </p>

<p>from that of the general group. </p>

<p>Another fact which corroborates this assertion is </p>

<p>the fact that lexicons exist relating to the principles </p>

<p>in all the quadrants of the representational structure, </p>

<p>which strengthens the proposal of representational </p>

<p>change, in which new elements are incorporated into the </p>

<p>periphery and the contrast zone, and later introduced </p>

<p>into the central nucleus of the representation, </p>

<p>transforming it. </p>

<p>The similitude tree shown in Figure 3 refers to the </p>

<p>maximum tree of higher education, in which 56 subjects </p>

<p>participated, and backs up the previous analysis. </p>

<p>Bad 
inattention </p>

<p>doesn't work </p>

<p>idealism </p>

<p>Attendance to the poor </p>

<p>Duty of the State </p>

<p>Attends everybody </p>

<p>access </p>

<p>Hierarchization </p>

<p>Comprehensive care </p>

<p>Unified Health System </p>

<p>Health </p>

<p>Disorganization </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>Integration 
Attendance </p>

<p>Good </p>

<p>Fairness 
Attendance </p>

<p>Training </p>

<p>Organization </p>

<p>difficulty </p>

<p>,04 
,04 
,04 </p>

<p>,07 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,07 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,04 </p>

<p>,04 
,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,04 
,04 </p>

<p>,04 
,04 </p>

<p>' </p>



<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem 2014 Jan.-Feb.;22(1):59-67. </p>

<p>It was the evocation duty of the State that most </p>

<p>established connections with the others, followed by </p>

<p>attends everybody and fairness, already supposedly </p>

<p>central. This data suggests that the professionals with </p>

<p>higher education have a different social representation </p>

<p>from the general group, as the term attendance is found </p>

<p>on the edge of the tree, while duty of the State and </p>

<p>attends everybody are central. It must be considered </p>

<p>that the SUS was a system created based on the principle </p>

<p>of the universality of care, in which health is taken as a </p>

<p>right of all, and a duty of the State </p>

<p>(13) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>It should be pointed out that all the lexicons </p>

<p>which establish connections with duty of the State </p>

<p>have positive meanings. The elements hierarchization, </p>

<p>integration and organization, associated with duty of </p>

<p>the State, indicate an administrative and organizational </p>

<p>dimension for which the State is responsible to provide </p>

<p>the conditions necessary for the system to function in </p>

<p>an integrated and hierarchized way, based on the three </p>

<p>levels of complexity, thus ensuring the political and </p>

<p>administrative organization of the health system, and </p>

<p>its full functioning. </p>

<p>As a similarity within the general analysis, we can </p>

<p>cite the integration of the principles of the SUS with the </p>

<p>tree and the presence of the negative elements of each </p>

<p>representation as accessories to this structure, these </p>

<p>being: disorganization, doesn't work, inattention and </p>

<p>bad. These elements are permeated by attendance to </p>

<p>the poor, as this establishes the connection between the </p>

<p>negative elements and the rest of the tree, forming a </p>

<p>scheme of thought. </p>

<p>Figure 4 refers to the maximum tree of the </p>

<p>professionals educated to high school level, in which </p>

<p>43 subjects participated, characterizing similar </p>

<p>representational structures between the professionals </p>

<p>with a high school education and the total set of </p>

<p>professionals, given that the term attendance remains </p>

<p>as the element which most establishes connections </p>

<p>with the others, as is expressed in the tree of the </p>

<p>general group. </p>

<p>Figure 4 -Maximum similitude tree of the evocations of health professionals educated to </p>

<p>high school level. Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil, 2009 (n=43) </p>

<p>Attendance </p>

<p>Assistance 
for the Retired </p>

<p>,10 </p>

<p>Duty of the State </p>

<p>Attends everybody 
G ood </p>

<p>Access 
Regionalization </p>

<p>Comprehensive Care 
Idealism </p>

<p>Unification 
Difficulty 
Attendance to the poor </p>

<p>doesn't work </p>

<p>Disorganization </p>

<p>Professional 
work 
Unified 
Health 
System </p>

<p>Health 
Education </p>

<p>Good attendance </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,03 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 
,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 
,05 </p>

<p>,05 
,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,05 </p>

<p>,10 </p>

<p>,10 </p>

<p>,08 </p>

<p>In this analysis, the various aspects attributed to </p>

<p>the attendance by the health professionals also call </p>

<p>attention. In this regard, this term is linked with the </p>

<p>duty of the State, education, assistance of the retired, </p>

<p>professional work, unified health system, health, good </p>

<p>attendance, good, attends everybody and difficulty. </p>

<p>One may observe a positive attitude related to the </p>

<p>attendance on the part of the health professionals </p>

<p>educated to high school level and the configuration </p>

<p>presented confirms the hypothesis that attendance is </p>

<p>characterized, by this group, as the identity of the SUS, </p>

<p>as shown in another study 
(11,14-15) . </p>

<p>In the analysis of similitude, emphasis is placed </p>

<p>on the importance that the lexicon professional work </p>

<p>takes on in the representational structure of the </p>

<p>professionals educated to high school level, as it has </p>



<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Pontes APM, Oliveira DC, Gomes AMT. </p>

<p>a higher rate of similitude of the tree (0.10), linked </p>

<p>to the word attendance, in addition to being situated </p>

<p>on the first periphery of the Vergès matrix, confirming </p>

<p>the striking presence of this symbolic construction </p>

<p>in these professionals' system of thought. This </p>

<p>relationship strengthens other findings in explaining </p>

<p>that the subjects stress as much their questions and </p>

<p>requirements as professionals inserted in the system, </p>

<p>as the questions and requirements of the population </p>

<p>observed in their routine 
(11-12,14-15) . </p>

<p>The lexicon difficulty appears connected to </p>

<p>attendance and attendance to the poor, forming a </p>

<p>ramification linked to all the other negative elements of </p>

<p>the representation (doesn't work and disorganization). </p>

<p>After the analysis of the three similitude trees, </p>

<p>(general, higher education and high school level) it is </p>

<p>possible to infer that the negative elements are found </p>

<p>as ramifications of these trees. At the same time, these </p>

<p>terms are associated with attendance to the poor which </p>

<p>emphasizes the negativity of this element in the health </p>

<p>professionals' representations. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Based on the analysis presented in the Vergès </p>

<p>matrix, one may observe the presence of a movement </p>

<p>of displacement of meanings occurring, in the direction </p>

<p>of the periphery and from the elements of contrast to </p>

<p>the Central Nucleus, with the incorporation of some </p>

<p>principles of the SUS and of positive elements to a </p>

<p>representation whose central nucleus does not cover </p>

<p>any technical-normative dimension, but only functional </p>

<p>and negative elements 
(4,15) . </p>

<p>The lexicons indicative of such principles -attends </p>

<p>everybody, duty of the State, comprehensive care and </p>

<p>hierarchization -are located on the periphery of the </p>

<p>representation and in its contrast zone. As a result, one </p>

<p>may infer that there is a more recent incorporation of </p>

<p>these principles into the symbolic universe of the group </p>

<p>of professionals, an incorporation which is ongoing. </p>

<p>On the other hand, the presence of such words in </p>

<p>different quadrants of the representational structure </p>

<p>points to their displacement, as proposed above. This </p>

<p>displacement and its direction (periphery -center) is </p>

<p>indicative of an ongoing process of representational </p>

<p>change 
(4,9,15) . </p>

<p>The functional and negative elements referred to, </p>

<p>in their turn, are expressed particularly in the words </p>

<p>attendance and doesn't work, as the most important </p>

<p>lexicons of the nucleus. The first term characterizes the </p>

<p>purpose of the health system and seems to define its </p>

<p>identity, as it incorporates into the representation of </p>

<p>the SUS its essential function of the assistance offered </p>

<p>to the population. In its turn, the second word adds to </p>

<p>the first, strengthening its negative dimension. </p>

<p>By contrast with the meanings expressed by </p>

<p>the central elements mentioned, only in the analysis </p>

<p>of similitude can one observe the centrality of the </p>

<p>principle of universality (attends everybody) and of </p>

<p>the responsibilization of the State (duty of the State), </p>

<p>through the large number of connections with other </p>

<p>elements and through the high rates of similitude which </p>

<p>are presented 
(8) , in consonance with the Organic Health </p>

<p>Law in which the SUS is characterized as a public </p>

<p>service, which provides attendance to the Brazilian </p>

<p>population, free of charge, universally, and fairly 
(16) . </p>

<p>It stands out that the principles of the SUS </p>

<p>mentioned are integrated into two of the three </p>

<p>maximum trees, presented as the principal irradiators </p>

<p>of other meanings, pointing to their centrality. Among </p>

<p>these other meanings, one finds the negative elements </p>

<p>present in the Central Nucleus -disorganization, doesn't </p>

<p>work, bad, attendance to the poor -which form their </p>

<p>own connections, characterizing an accessory frame for </p>

<p>this central structure, made up of the principles. </p>

<p>The health crisis is manifested based on certain </p>

<p>dimensions, namely: inefficiency, inefficacy, unfairness, </p>

<p>and dissatisfaction of public opinion. In the medical care </p>

<p>services, the crisis translates into the disorganization </p>

<p>of the hospitals and of the outpatient clinics, which </p>

<p>present characteristics such as waiting lines, deaths </p>

<p>and dehumanized attendance, among others 
(17) . </p>

<p>However, various historical contexts previous </p>

<p>to the implantation of the SUS contributed to the </p>

<p>incorporation of a negative perspective on the </p>

<p>construction of the social thinking regarding the health </p>

<p>system, namely: economic, political, communicational </p>

<p>and epidemiological. Thus, the association of the </p>

<p>previous contexts was an unfavorable basis for the </p>

<p>implantation of the SUS in Rio de Janeiro, being </p>

<p>responsible for some difficulties present in the system, </p>

<p>and which are present in the professionals' symbolic </p>

<p>constructions even today 
(17) . </p>

<p>The ethical-doctrinal principles 
(18) provide the SUS's </p>

<p>ideological basis, and are expressed in the care actions </p>

<p>in the routine of the professionals in the health units. </p>

<p>These principles are revealed in the analysis presented, </p>

<p>based on the connections in the maximum trees, with </p>

<p>characteristics related to the democratization of the </p>

<p>care, as the actions and the health services ceased to </p>



<p>www.eerp.usp.br/rlae </p>

<p>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem 2014 Jan.-Feb.;22(1):59-67. </p>

<p>be restricted and became universal and fair. This set </p>

<p>of meanings encompassing the SUS is present in the </p>

<p>representation analyzed, as the health professionals </p>

<p>constructed a web of knowledge and perceptions, in </p>

<p>which the connections established may not always </p>

<p>be observed in a single analysis, as shown in the </p>

<p>present text. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Based on the results observed in this study, it </p>

<p>may be concluded that the health professionals had </p>

<p>incorporated into their symbolic constructions -even </p>

<p>if partially -the principles which govern the Brazilian </p>

<p>health system. It should be emphasized that it was </p>

<p>possible to identify the different contents constituting </p>

<p>the social representation of the SUS among the health </p>

<p>professionals, as well as to identify the specific elements </p>

<p>in the comparison between the professionals with </p>

<p>distinct levels of education. Based on this comparison, </p>

<p>different representations were identified, confirmed by </p>

<p>the relations of connectedness established between the </p>

<p>central system and the periphery of the representation </p>

<p>analyzed through the technique of similitude. </p>

<p>In analyzing the structure of the social </p>

<p>representation of the professionals with higher </p>

<p>education, the expressions which reflect on the </p>

<p>principles of universality and fairness of the health </p>

<p>actions are present in the probable central nucleus, in </p>

<p>addition to other positive elements. This finding allows </p>

<p>the inference that this is the subgroup of professionals </p>

<p>responsible for the incorporation of the principles </p>

<p>of the SUS into the representation of the general </p>

<p>group, as well as for the positive attitude towards the </p>

<p>health system. Another characteristic present in this </p>

<p>subgroup's representation, and which corroborates this </p>

<p>assertion, is the fact that lexicons exist related to the </p>

<p>ethical and doctrinal principals of the SUS in all the </p>

<p>quadrants of the representational structure. </p>

<p>As discussed and demonstrated in the results </p>

<p>relating to the mobility of the elements in the </p>

<p>representational structure, it may be asserted that </p>

<p>there is an ongoing process of representational change </p>

<p>with the insertion into the representational structure </p>

<p>of new contents which are indicative of principles and </p>

<p>positive elements related to the SUS. </p>

<p>One can observe, in the analysis of the quadrants, </p>

<p>a representation anchored in the assistential role of </p>

<p>the State, associated with the image of disorganization </p>

<p>and non-functionality of the public services, focussed </p>

<p>on attendance and with negative meanings. In the </p>

<p>complementary analyses of similitude one may observe </p>

<p>a representation transforming, through a converging </p>

<p>movement, into a symbolic construction with positive </p>

<p>meanings, and anchored in the ethical-doctrinal </p>

<p>principles of the SUS. This proposal was further </p>

<p>strengthened by the presence of positive elements and </p>

<p>principles in the peripheral system of the representation </p>

<p>and in the contrast zone, as previously discussed. </p>







</text></tei>