<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4644012" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A 74-year-old man startled his dog and sustained a penetrating bite 
to his hand. The dog then licked the blood off the injured extremity. 
A few days later, the patient developed fever, chills and weakness, 
resulting in a fall. He presented to the emergency room for assess-
ment. Medical history and significant comorbidities included chronic 
obstructive pulmonary disease, hypertension, dyslipidemia and idio-
pathic dilated cardiomyopathy, Grade 3 left ventricle. No immuno-
compromising illnesses were present. Physical examination revealed 
a temperature of 40°C, with bronchial breath sounds and crackles 
heard in the left chest; the bite wound appeared improved. A chest 
x-ray revealed a left perihilar infiltrate. Peripheral white blood cell 
count was 15.<rs id="software-2" type="software">VITEK 2</rs><rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">06.01</rs><rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">BioMerieux</rs>Xiong et al </p>

<p>Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol Vol 26 No 5 September/October 2015 </p>

<p>
Biochemical profile 
Traditional biochemical testing was performed on the isolate and 
based on its profile was determined to be P dagmatis (2) (Table 2). 
Because this organism is not often encountered, alternate identifica-
tion methods were also used to ensure a correct identification. </p>

<p>16S rRNA gene PCR/sequencing 
16S rRNA gene PCR was performed at Public Health Ontario. 
A 736-base pair amplicon was generated (primers, for-
ward: 5'-AGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG-3'; Reverse: 5'-
GGACTACCAGGGTATCTAAT-3') and sequenced using routine 
methods (3). The sequence was analyzed using National Center 
for Biotechnology Information basic local alignment search tool 
(4) and results were interpreted using CLSI MM18-A guidelines 
(5). The PCR product was 99% similar to six deposits within the 
nr/nt database with 99% to 100% coverage. Sequences with high </p>

<p>levels of homology to the query sequence included the type strain 
of P dagmatis, ATCC 43325/CCUG 12397 (99%; NR_042883.1 and 
M75051.1) and the type strain of Pasteurella stomatis, CCUG 17979 
(99%; NR_042888.1). Based on CLSI MM18-A interpretation 
guidelines (5), due to the low level of demarcation of the sequence 
of the 16S rRNA gene between these species, the unknown bacteria 
may only be identified as P dagmatis or P stomatis. However, based on 
the biochemical profile (Table 2), this organism could not be P sto-
matis (which is urease and maltose negative, because the organism 
in question is urease and maltose positive); therefore, in the present 
case, the identification of the organism was P dagmatis. </p>

<p>MALDI-ToF MS 
Single colonies of fresh organisms grown overnight were prepared 
using a modified formic acid extraction procedure and analyzed using 
the Bruker MALDI BioTyper (Bruker Daltonics, Germany) in dupli-
cate using standard settings. The query spectra had a high level of 
similarity &gt;2.0 (≥2.0 is an acceptable score for species-level identifi-
cation) to P dagmatis spectra within the routine commercial data-
base. The top five matches were to spectra from different strains of 
P dagmatis within the commercial database. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION AND LITERATURE REVIEW </p>

<p>P dagmatis is a relatively new species for many clinicians. It is a 
Gram-negative coccobacillus belonging to the Pasteurellaceae family, 
which is fermentative, aerobic, nonmotile, oxidase positive and 
penicillin-sensitive. This organism has been isolated from both dogs 
and cats as normal flora, and also reported as a pathogen in human 
infections. It was previously labeled as Pasteurella "gas", Pasteurella 
new species 1 or P pneumotropica type Henriksen, and was eventually 
reclassified as P dagmatis (6). 
Bacteria from the Pasteurellaceae family cause zoonotic infections 
in humans, with P multocida and P canis being the most common 
Pasturella species reported in human infections (7,8). Infections 
caused by Pasteurella species are typically introduced by animals, 
particularly cat or dog bites, but also occasionally by other animals, 
and often manifest as skin or soft tissue infections (7-9). Sometimes, 
animal contact is not prominent in the initial patient history (10,11) 
(Table 3). The most probable route of transmission of P dagmatis 
infection in the present case was most likely the bite and licking of 
the patient's traumatized skin by his dog, as has been previously 
described (11,12). Continuous shedding of P dagmatis from asymp-
tomatic animals (eg, in dog urine [13]) and whether it can be an 
indirect route of infection to human remains to be investigated. </p>

<p>is, </p>

<p>ca </p>

<p>Table 1 
antibiotic susceptibility of Pasteurella dagmatis </p>

<p>antibiotic </p>

<p>Mininmum inhibitory 
concentration, mg/l Interpretation </p>

<p>Penicillin 
0.12 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Ampicillin 
≤2 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Pipercillin/tazobactum 
≤4 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Cefazolin 
≤4 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Ceftazidime/ceftriaxone 
≤1 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Meropenem 
≤0.25 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Gentamicin/tobramycin 
≤1 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Ciprofloxacin 
≤0.25 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Levofloxacin 
≤0.03 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Trimetoprim/sulfamethoxazole 
≤20 
Sensitive </p>

<p>Analysis performed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">VITEK 2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">BioMerieux</rs>, France) and agar dilution as 
per the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (1) </p>

<p>Table 2 
Key biochemical characteristics of Pasteurella dagmatis, 
P stomatis and P pneumotropica </p>

<p>P dagmatis P stomatis P pneumotropica </p>

<p>Dextrose 
+ 
+ 
n/a </p>

<p>Lactose 
-
-
-</p>

<p>Sucrose 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Xylose 
-
-
+ </p>

<p>Mannitol 
-
-
-</p>

<p>Maltose 
+ 
-
+ </p>

<p>Arabinose 
-
-
V </p>

<p>Sorbitol 
-
-
-</p>

<p>Trelose 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Dulcitol 
-
-
-</p>

<p>Catalase 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Oxidase 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>TSI slant/butt 
+/+ 
+/+ 
+/+ </p>

<p>Indole 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Urea activity 
+ 
-
+ </p>

<p>Nitrate to nitrite 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Motility 
-
-
-</p>

<p>Ornithine 
-
-
+ </p>

<p>Arginine 
-
-
n/a </p>

<p>Lysine 
-
-
V </p>

<p>Ortho-nitrophenyl-β-galactoside 
-
-
+ </p>

<p>Data presented as positive (+) or negative (-). Reactions refer to reference 2. 
n/a Not available; V Variable; </p>

<p>Table 3 
Summary of reports involving bacteremia in humans with 
Pasteuralla dagmatis in the english literature </p>

<p>Patient 
age, 
years/sex </p>

<p>animal 
bites Diagnosis </p>

<p>antibiotic 
Treatment 
Outcome Reference </p>

<p>78/male 
None Prosthetic valve 
endocarditis </p>

<p>Ceftriaxone 
Survived 
10 </p>

<p>66/male 
None Septicemia 
Penicillin 
Recovered 
11 </p>

<p>51/male 
Dog Septicemia, 
diabetic foot </p>

<p>Penicillin 
Resolved 
12 </p>

<p>55/female 
Cat Infectious endo-
carditis throm-
bocytopenia </p>

<p>Ceftriaxone 
Survived 
14 </p>

<p>77/male 
Cat Prosthetic valve 
endocarditis </p>

<p>Ceftriaxone, 
penicillin </p>

<p>Recovered 
15 </p>

<p>56/female 
Dog Peritonitis, 
septicemia, 
cirrhosis </p>

<p>Benzypenicillin, 
ciprofloxacin, 
metronidazole </p>

<p>Passed 
away 
within 
24 h </p>



<p>Pasteurella dagmatis bacteremia </p>

<p>Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol Vol 26 No 5 September/October 2015 </p>

<p>
While Pasteurella species are well recognized for causing skin or 
soft tissue infections, P dagmatis can also cause more serious disease, 
including infective and prosthetic valve endocarditis (10,14,15), 
septicemia (11,12,16), peritonitis (17), vertebral osteomyelitis 
(18,19), chronic bronchiectasis (20) and pneumonia (21), mainly in 
immunocompromised patients. A small number of case reports 
describing systemic human P dagmatis infections are listed in 
Table 3. Interestingly, while Pasturella species infrequently cause 
systemic infectious disease, in our review of the literature, when P 
dagmatis infections are reported, they appear to be frequently associ-
ated with severe disseminated infection including bacteremia. 
Coinfections of P dagmatis with another Pasturella species have also 
been observed (9,12,22); therefore, it is important for the laboratory 
to test multiple morphotypes from the plate to ensure that &gt;1 
Pasturella species is not present. 
Similar to other Pasturella species, P dagmatis is typically highly 
susceptible to many antibiotics, particularly, the beta-lactams 
(Table 1). Early suspicion and timely laboratory diagnosis of 
Pasturella infection are crucial for a favourable clinical outcome. 
Several reports have demonstrated that the VITEK 2 GN card 
misidentifies P dagmatis as P pneumotropica or P canis, despite an 
excellent identification probability (9,15,23,24). This is most likely 
because P dagmatis has not been included in the system database; 
as well, there has been a nomenclature change because P dagmatis 
was formerly grouped with P pneumotropica, type Henriksen. In a 
study that included 66 clinical Pasturella isolates and used sodA gene 
sequencing as a reference method, Zangenah et al (24) revealed that 
<rs type="software">VITEK 2</rs> only identified approximately 50% of Pasturella isolates 
correctly, while conventional biochemical tests and MALDI-ToF 
MS were able to correctly identify 94% and 89%, respectively. 
Interestingly, in the Zangenah et al (24) study, two P dagmatis isolates 
were not identified by VITEK MS MALDI-ToF (BioMerieux, France) 
and this limitation was also observed in our study (data not shown). 
The biological and genetic profiles among P dagmatis, P pneumotropica 
and P stomatis are very similar (Table 2); both a commercial biochem-
ical identification system and the sequence analysis of a portion of the 
16S rRNA gene were unable to differentiate between these species. </p>

<p>Correct identification was made using MALDI-ToF MS (MALDI 
Biotyper, Bruker, Germany) and was also supported by comparing 
the key biochemical characteristics among P dagmatis, P pneumo-
tropica and P stomatis (Table 2). It is probable that many clinical 
isolates of P dagmatis have been misidentified due to the limitation 
of commercial biochemical identification systems, such as <rs type="software">VITEK 
2</rs>. Misidentification may have contributed to an underestimation 
of the frequency of this organism in clinical samples; however, the 
growing use of MALDI-ToF MS systems for microorganism identifi-
cation in routine clinical microbiology laboratories may allow for a 
more accurate picture of how frequently P dagmatis causes infections. 
Correct identification is important for diagnosis and therapeutic 
management, and epidemiological monitoring of the transmission of 
Pasturella species, particularly for the systemic infections such as in 
the present case. Unfortunately, most routine methods available at 
hospital laboratories cannot identify the organism correctly. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>P dagmatis can cause severe animal-associated infections in humans, 
mainly in immunocompromised individuals. To our knowledge, this 
is the first systemic P dagmatis infection reported in Canada. Clinical 
outcomes rely on early accurate laboratory confirmation and timely 
administration of effective antibiotic treatment. Conventional iden-
tification of P dagmatis using <rs type="software">VITEK 2</rs> can be misleading, probably 
due to the absence of this organism from the database; 16S rRNA 
gene sequence analysis and MALDI-ToF MS systems represent excel-
lent options for identifying rarely encountered or difficult to identify 
organisms, such as members of the Pasturellaceae family. The present 
study re-emphasizes the need for continuously improving the data-
base of automatic microbial identification systems. </p>

<p>ACkNOWLEDGEMENTS: The authors thank the microbiology labo-</p>

<p>ratory staff from SJHC and PHOL for their help and support of this study. </p>

<p>DISCLOSURES: The authors have no financial relationships or conflicts </p>

<p>of interest to declare. </p>



<p>Xiong et al </p>

<p>Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol Vol 26 No 5 September/October 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>