<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4839839" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: The often cited need to achieve !95% (nearly perfect) </p>

<p>adherence to antiretroviral therapy (ART) for successful virologic 
outcomes in HIV may present a barrier to initiation of therapy in the 
early stages of HIV. 
This meta-analysis synthesized 43 studies (27,905 participants) 
performed across &gt;26 countries, to determine the relationship between 
cut-off point for optimal adherence to ART and virologic outcomes. 
Meta-analysis was performed using a random-effect model to 
calculate pooled odds ratios with corresponding 95% confidence intervals. 
The mean rate of patients reporting optimal adherence was 63.4%. 
Compared with suboptimal adherence, optimal adherence was associated 
with a lower risk of virologic failure (0.34; 95% CI: 0.26-0.44). There 
were no significant differences in the pooled odds ratios among different 
optimal adherence thresholds (!98-100%, !95%, !80-90%). Study 
design (randomized controlled trial vs observational study) (regression 
coefficient 0.74, 95% CI: 0.04-1.43, P &lt; 0.05) and study region (devel-
oping vs developed countries; regression coefficient 0.56, 95% CI: 0.01-
1.12, P &lt; 0.05) remained as independent predictors of between-study 
heterogeneity, with more patients with optimal adherence from devel-
oping countries or randomized controlled trials experiencing virologic 
failure. 
The threshold for optimal adherence to achieve better virologic 
outcomes appears to be wider than the commonly used cut-off point 
(!95% adherence). The cut-off point for optimal adherence could be 
redefined to a slightly lower level to encourage the prescribing ART at an 
early stage of HIV infection. </p>

<p>(Medicine 95(15):e3361) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AIDS = acquired immunodeficiency syndrome, 
ART = antiretroviral therapy, CAM = comprehensive meta-
Analysis, HDI = United Nations human development index, HIV 
= human immunodeficiency virus, MEMS = medication event 
monitoring system, NNRTIs = nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase </p>

<p>inhibitors, NRTIs = nucleoside/nucleotide reverse transcriptase 
inhibitors, PIs = protease inhibitors, PRISMA = preferred reporting 
items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses, RevMan = review 
manager, RNA = ribonucleic acid, SD = standard deviation. </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>IV/AIDS has been transformed into a manageable chronic 
disease with the advent of combination antiretroviral 
therapy (ART) initiated as the standard of care. 
1 Three classes 
of HIV medications have been widely used in combination-
nucleoside/nucleotide reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs), 
nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs), and 
protease inhibitors (PIs). 
1 Despite the availability of effective 
treatment options, suboptimal adherence to treatment can result 
in insufficient viral suppression and promote the emergence of 
drug-resistant viral strains, resulting in regimen failure, pro-
gression to AIDS, and death. 
2-4 Paterson et al suggested that at 
least 95% adherence to unboosted PIs was required for virologic 
suppression. 
5 This 95% adherence cut-off point, based on what 
is now obsolete therapy, has been widely used as the level of 
optimal adherence needed to be met by patients taking newer 
agents and their combinations. The concern that patients may 
not achieve a near-perfect adherence presents a barrier for 
initiation of therapy in the early stages of HIV. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>This meta-analysis integrated finding from observational 
studies on ART adherence with 2 objectives: (a) to critically 
evaluate the association between optimal adherence to ART and 
virologic outcomes, and (b) to use meta-regression to determine 
methodological, regimen, and population factors that could mod-
erate the relationship between adherence and virologic outcomes. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>We followed the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic 
Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) Statement in conduct-
ing this meta-analysis. 
7 Studies eligible for inclusion were 
randomized controlled trials, retrospective analyses of data 
from trials, and cohort studies measuring the relationship 
between medication adherence to ART and virologic failure. </p>

<p>Search Strategy </p>

<p>WB carried out systematic literature searches of the 
electronic databases MEDLINE via PubMed, Cochrane Clinical 
Trials, and EMBASE from their inception date to 17 April 2015. 
This search used combinations of the following key words: 
medication adherence, patient compliance, antiretroviral 
therapy, antiretroviral agent, antiretroviral treatment, protease 
inhibitors, non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors, vir-
ologic failure, and viral load. The reference lists of all articles 
included in this meta-analysis were also searched. Review 
articles, editorials, commentaries, government reports, and 
guidelines were excluded from this review. Titles and abstracts </p>

<p>Editor: Liang Shang. 
Received: November 23, 2015; revised: March 15, 2016; accepted: March 
16, 2016. 
From the Division of Pharmacy, School of Medicine, University of 
Tasmania, Tasmania, Australia. 
Correspondence: Woldesellassie M. Bezabhe, Division of Pharmacy, 
School of Medicine, University of Tasmania, Hobart TAS, Australia 
(e-mail: mwoldesellassie@yahoo.com; wbezabhe@utas.edu.au) 
Author contributions: WB, LC, LB, and GP conceived of and designed the 
meta-analysis. WB and YM reviewed abstracts and full articles. WB and 
YB extracted the data. WB performed the meta-analysis and wrote the 
first draft. All authors have read and approved the final draft. 
The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0, where it is 
permissible to download, share and reproduce the work in any medium, 
provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or 
used commercially. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000003361 </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>SYSTEMATIC REVIEW AND META-ANALYSIS </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>of potentially relevant articles were screened independently by 
WB and YM. Full articles of potentially appropriate citations 
were screened for inclusion in this review if they fulfilled the 
following criteria: original research, participants aged 16 years 
or older, having a clear definition of medication adherence 
measurement and clear cut-off points for optimal and subopti-
mal adherence, and virologic failure stratified by optimal and 
suboptimal medication adherence groups. Ethical approval was 
not required as this study was based on published data and had 
no direct access to patient information. </p>

<p>Data Collection and Outcome Measures </p>

<p>WB extracted data using standardized forms, with record-
ing of authors, year of publication, country of study, study type, 
regimen, method of adherence measurement, cut-off points for 
good adherence, and virologic failure. The data were verified by 
a second reviewer (YM). Disagreements between reviewers 
were resolved through discussion until a consensus was 
reached. Study authors' grouping of patients into optimal and 
suboptimal adherence using the most objective measure was 
used. When a study reported &gt;1 adherence measurement, 
the most reliable adherence measurement data was used, with 
reliability defined in following order: medication event 
monitoring system (MEMS) &gt; pill count &gt; pharmacy refill &gt; 
self-reported adherence in the past week &gt; self-reported adher-
ence in the past month. When the number of virologic failures 
within each adherence group was not reported, we calculated 
virologic failure from the information provided in the paper or 
contacted the corresponding author. Studies were excluded 
when it was not possible to obtain virologic failure data in 
each adherence group. The United Nations Human Develop-
ment Index (HDI) ranking was used to categories studies into 
low and high human development groups. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>The data were analyzed using Review Manager (RevMan) 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 5.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Cochrane Collaboration</rs>, The Nordic Cochrane 
Centre, Copenhagen, 2014) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Comprehensive Meta-Analysis</rs> 
(CAM) <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 3.3.070</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Biostat</rs>, Englewood, NJ). Each class of 
antiretroviral was considered in a separate analysis of the 
association between adherence and virologic failure in random-
ized clinical trials. Results are presented based on 9 categories, 
including study region, antiretroviral regimen, treatment experi-
ence, virologic failure cut-off points, adherence cut-off points, 
adherence measurement, study design, observation period, and 
year of publication. Adherence pooled odds ratios and 95% 
confidence intervals were calculated using a random effect 
model (DerSimonian and Lard) 
9 that accommodated the ran-
dom variation within studies and between-studies. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity between-studies were examined using the Q 
and I 
2 statistics. 
9,11 The odds ratio was plotted against the 
inverse of standard error to identify the risk of publication bias 
by visually assessing the symmetry of funnel plots. Statistical 
significance was confirmed using Egger's test, 
12 with a P value 
&lt;0.05 considered suggestive of publication bias. A meta-
regression was performed to examine major moderators of 
the between-studies heterogeneity. Results with P values 
&lt;0.1 from univariate analyses were included in the multivariate 
meta-regression model. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Overall, 1796 studies were identified, of which 1449 were 
excluded after review of the title and abstract (Figure 1). The </p>

<p>full text of the remaining 347 citations was screened, and 43 
studies with 27,905 participants met the inclusion criteria. The 
included studies had wide a variation in sample sizes 
(range ¼ 34-3607, mean ¼ 649, SD ¼ 805) and a slight 
majority of participants were men (57%). Twenty-five studies 
were prospective studies 
5,13-36 that reported virologic failure 
according to adherence group. The remaining studies were 
randomized controlled trials (11) 
37-47 and retrospective studies 
(7). 
48-54 Characteristics of the included studies are shown in 
Table 1. 
With respect to location, 14 studies were conducted in sub-
Saharan Africa; 9 in the US; 6 in Canada; 5 in Europe; 5 in Asia; 
1 in Australia; and 3 studies in several countries. Twenty-two 
(49%) studies included only treatment-naive patients and the 
remaining 21 studies included both treatment-naive and/or 
treatment-experienced patients. All studies reported cut-off 
points for optimal adherence and virologic failure. Thirty 
studies (70%) defined optimal adherence as !95%, with the 
remainder using 100%, 98%, 90%, 85%, and 80% as the cut-off 
points. Optimal adherence rates varied greatly across studies, 
partially due to the use of these different cut-off points and also 
different methods of measurement to assess adherence. The 
mean rate of achieving optimal adherence in adults was 63.4% 
(standard deviation [SD] ¼ 23.7, range 5% to 97%, n ¼ 43). </p>

<p>Meta-analysis and Meta-regression </p>

<p>Of a total 27,905 participants, 22,740 participants had a 
viral load and adherence measurement; 7056 (31%) had vir-
ologic failure. Overall, 3464 of 15,067 participants with optimal 
adherence to ART (23%), and 3592 of 7673 participants with 
suboptimal adherence (47%) participants had virologic failure 
(Figure 2). The pooled odds ratio for virologic failure for 
optimal adherence compared to suboptimal adherence was 
0.34 (95% CI: 0.26-0.44). A high degree of heterogeneity 
was found: Q statistic P &lt; 0.001 and I 
2 ¼ 90%. The funnel plot 
did not show asymmetry (Figure 3), and the result of Egger's 
test was not statistically significant (P ¼ 0.68). We conducted 
subgroup analyses to recalculate the pooled odds ratio accord-
ing to study design, HDI rank, regimen, treatment experience, 
viral load cut-off points, adherence measurement, and adher-
ence cut-off points (Table 2). 
The results of univariate meta-regression analyses for 
different moderators are shown in Table 3. Based on virologic 
failure cut-off points, studies were classified into three sets 
including: 100 copies/mL, 11 studies (N ¼ 5646); between 
100 copies/mL and 400 copies/mL, 17 studies (N ¼ 9351); 
and between 500 copies/mL and 1000 copies/mL, 14 studies 
(N ¼ 7383). The pooled odds ratio for virologic failure for 
optimal adherence compared to suboptimal adherence for the 
studies with the lowest virologic failure cut-off was higher 
(0.55; 95% CI: 0.41-0.74, I 
2 ¼ 56%) than for the studies with an 
intermediate virologic failure cut-off (0.37; 95% CI: 0.26-0.54, 
I 
2 ¼ 88%). The group using a virologic failure cut-off 
&gt;500 copies/mL had the lowest pooled odds ratio for virologic 
failure (0.25; 95% CI: 0.16-0.41, I 
2 ¼ 92%). Studies with the 
lowest virologic failure cut-off reported a significantly different 
pooled odds ratio compared with studies with a virologic failure 
cut-off &gt; 500 copies/mL (regression coefficient À0.75; 95% 
CI: À1.39 to À0.12, P ¼ 0.02). 
According to participants' treatment experience, studies 
were grouped into 3 sets: treatment-naive patients only, 22 
studies (N ¼ 17,010); treatment-experienced patients only, 12 
studies (N ¼ 4009), and both treatment-naive and experienced 
patients, 9 studies (N ¼ 1721). The pooled odds ratio for optimal </p>

<p>Bezabhe et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>adherence compared to suboptimal adherence for virologic 
failure for treatment-experienced patients was the highest 
(Table 2); however, no statistically significant difference in 
pooled odds ratio was found between the 3 groups. 
The relationship between adherence and virologic out-
comes varied with type of adherence measurement. The pooled 
odds ratio for the self-report adherence measure (0.45; 95% CI: 
0.37-0.55, I 
2 ¼ 31%) was higher than the pooled odds ratio for 
the pharmacy refill (0.29; 95% CI: 0.20-0.41, I 
2 ¼ 94%). The 
group using MEMS adherence measure had the lowest pooled 
odd ratio (0.15; 95% CI: 0.06-0.37, I 
2 ¼ 35%) for optimal 
adherence compared to suboptimal adherence for virologic 
failure. There was a trend toward significant difference across 
the odds of virologic failure between self-report and MEMS 
(regression coefficient À1.00; 95% CI: À2.05, 0.06, P ¼ 0.06), 
but not between self-report and pharmacy refill (regression 
coefficient À0.22; 95% CI: À0.78, 0.34, P ¼ 0.45). 
The pooled odds ratios were also estimated by grouping 
studies using cut-off points for optimal adherence studies with a 
cut-off point between 98% and 100%, 7 studies (N ¼ 3940); 
studies with a cut-off point of !95%, 30 studies (N ¼ 17,779); 
and studies with a cut-off point of 80% to 90%, 6 studies 
(N ¼ 1021). The pooled odds ratios for virologic failure for 
optimal adherence compared to suboptimal adherence for each </p>

<p>cut-off point were similar, with no statistically significant 
differences. 
The pooled odds ratio for optimal adherence compared to 
suboptimal adherence for observational studies was signifi-
cantly greater than randomized controlled studies (regression 
coefficient, 0.66; 95% CI: 0.10, 1.21, P ¼ 0.02). Studies were 
aggregated into three subgroups according to HIV-medication 
regimens: NNRTI-based, boosted PI-based, and unboosted PI-
based. The pooled odds ratio for virologic failure for optimal 
adherence compared to suboptimal adherence for patients tak-
ing NNRTI-containing regimens was the highest, but the differ-
ences in pooled odds ratios between the regimens were not 
statistically significant. 
Studies were subgrouped into 2 groups based on the HDI of 
the country in which the study was performed: very high HDI, 
21 studies (N ¼ 10,466); low HDI, 19 studies (N ¼ 9945). The 
pooled odds ratio for optimal adherence compared to subopti-
mal adherence for countries with low HDI (0.50; 95% CI: 0.35-
0.72) was significantly higher than countries with very high 
HDI (0.23; 95% CI: 0.15-0.33). 
A multivariate meta-regression model was built-in to 
examine the specific moderators of the between-study hetero-
geneity, including the following: study region, threshold used to 
define virologic failure, adherence measurement, study design, </p>

<p>Records idenƟfied through 
database searching 
(n =1723) </p>

<p>AddiƟonal records idenƟfied 
through other sources 
(n =114) </p>

<p>Records aŌer duplicates removed 
(n =1796) </p>

<p>Records screened 
(n =1796) </p>

<p>Records excluded 
(n =1449) </p>

<p>Full-text arƟcles assessed 
for eligibility 
(n =347) </p>

<p>Full-text arƟcles excluded, 
with reasons 
(n = 304) </p>

<p>Studies included in 
qualitaƟve synthesis 
(n =43) </p>

<p>Studies included in 
quanƟtaƟve synthesis 
(meta-analysis) 
(n =43) </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Flow diagram of study selection. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 
Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy and Virologic Failure </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>and year of publication. Study design (observational study 
versus randomized controlled trials; regression coefficient 
0.74, 95% CI: 0.04-1.43, P &lt; 0.05) and study region (devel-
oped versus developing countries; regression coefficient 0.56, 
95% CI: 0.01-1.12, P &lt; 0.05) remained as independent pre-
dictors of between-study heterogeneity. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This meta-analysis of 43 studies, involving 27,905 partici-
pants, addresses a gap in the current HIV treatment adherence 
literature with a quantitative evaluation of the association 
between level of adherence and virologic outcomes among </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Characteristics of Included Studies in Meta-Analysis of Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy and Virologic Failure </p>

<p>Study 
Country 
Study Type </p>

<p>Definition of 
Virologic Failure 
(Copies/mL) </p>

<p>Adherence 
Measures </p>

<p>Cut-off Point 
for Optimal 
Adherence % </p>

<p>Observation 
Period </p>

<p>Pasternak et al 2012 </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>Netherlands 
Randomized controlled trial 
!50 
MEMSÃ 
100 
9 months 
Okonjio et al 2012 </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>Kenya 
Randomized controlled trial 
!400 
Pill count 
!95 
24 weeks 
Murphy et al 2012 </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>South Africa 
Retrospective study 
!50 
Pharmacy refill 
&gt;90 
24 months 
Nolan et al 2011 </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>Canada 
Retrospective study 
!500 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
Median 51 months 
El-Khatib et al 2011b </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>South Africa 
Retrospective study 
&gt;50 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
Median 44 months 
Messou et al 2011 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Côte d'Ivoire 
Prospective study 
!300 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
12 months 
Lima et al 2010 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>Canada 
Retrospective study 
&gt;400 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
Median 2 years 
Ford et al 2010 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>South Africa 
Prospective study 
&gt;5000 
Self-report 
!95 
5 years 
Nellen et al 2009 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Netherlands 
Prospective study 
&gt;400 
Pharmacy refill 
!85 
2 years 
San et al 2008 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Mozambique 
Prospective study 
!1000 
Pill count 
&gt;95 
1 year 
Nachega et al 2007 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>South Africa 
Prospective study 
&gt;400 
Pharmacy refill 
100 
Median 2.2 years 
Gross et al 2006 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Canada 
Prospective study 
&gt;1000 
Pharmacy refill 
&gt;95 
Median 29 months 
Moore et al 2005 </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Canada 
Prospective study 
!500 
Pharmacy refill 
&gt;95 
Median 44.7 months 
Kitahata et al 2004 </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>USA 
Retrospective study 
&gt;500 
Pharmacy refill 
&gt;90 
Median 89 weeks 
Cahn et al 2004 </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>Argentina, Brazil, 
Mexico, Italy, 
Thailand, Canada </p>

<p>Randomized controlled trial 
!400 
Self-report 
!95 
48 weeks </p>

<p>Arnsten et al 2001 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>USA 
Prospective study 
&gt;500 
MEMS 
!90 
5.1 months 
McNabb et al 2001 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>USA 
Prospective study 
!400 
MEMS 
&gt;95 
3 months 
Parienti et al 2010 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>USA 
Prospective study 
!50 (400) 
MEMS 
&gt;95 
2 years 
Bangsberg et al 2000 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>USA 
Prospective study 
!400 
MEMS 
!98 
Median 9.4 weeks 
Paterson et al 2000 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>USA 
Prospective study 
!400 
MEMS 
!95 
Median 6 months 
Tuldra et al 2000 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Spain 
Randomized controlled trial 
&gt;400 
Self-report 
!95 
48 weeks 
Meresse et al 2013 </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>Cameroon 
Randomized controlled trial 
!40 
Self-report 
!80 
24 months 
Abah et al 2014 </p>

<p>53 </p>

<p>Nigeria 
Retrospective study 
&gt;1000 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
Median 12 months 
Neogi et al 2013 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>India 
Prospective study 
&gt;400 
Self-report 
100 
2 years 
Li et al 2012 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>USA 
Prospective study 
!200 
Self-report and 
Pill count </p>

<p>!95 
32 months </p>

<p>McMahon et al 2013 </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>India 
Retrospective study 
!200 
Pharmacy refill 
&gt;95 
12 months 
Ekstrand et al 2011 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>India 
Prospective study 
&gt;1000 
Self-report 
!95 
2 years 
Lower-Beer et al 2000 
27 Canada 
Prospective study 
&gt;500 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
Median 19 months 
Carr et al 2000 </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>Australia 
Randomized controlled trial 
!50 
Self-report 
100 
52 months 
Cohen et al 2013 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>21 countries 
Randomized controlled trial 
!50 
Self-report 
&gt;95 
96 weeks 
Haubrich et al 1999 </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>USA 
Randomized controlled trial 
&lt;500 
Self-report 
!95 
6 months 
Muyingo et al 2008 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>Uganda and 
Zimbabwe </p>

<p>Randomized controlled trial 
&gt;50 (400) 
Pharmacy refill 
100 
48 weeks </p>

<p>Anude et al 2013 </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Nigeria 
Prospective study 
!400 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
12 months 
Nelson et al 2010 </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>26 countries 
Randomized controlled trial 
!50 
Self-report 
&gt;95 
96 weeks 
Biswas et al 2014 </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>USA 
Prospective study 
!40 
Self-report 
&gt;95 
3 years 
Ti et al 2014 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Canada 
Prospective study 
!500 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
Median 32 months 
El-Khatib et al 2011b </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>South Africa 
Prospective study 
!400 
Pill count 
!95 
24 weeks 
Glass et al 2006 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>Switzerland 
Prospective study 
!50 (400) 
Self-report 
!95 
12 months 
Jordan et al 2009 </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Prospective study 
!1000 
Self-report 
!95 
16.65 months 
Goldman et al 2008 </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>Zambia 
Prospective study 
!400 
Pharmacy refill 
!95 
744 days 
Court et al 2014 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>South Africa 
Prospective study 
&gt;1000 
Pharmacy refill 
!90 
27 months 
Shet et al 2014 </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>India 
Randomized controlled trial 
&gt;400 
Pill count 
!95 
96 weeks 
Carrieri et al 2003 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>France 
Prospective study 
200, 400, and 500 Self-report 
100 
36 months </p>

<p>MEMS ¼ medication event monitoring system. </p>

<p>Bezabhe et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>adults taking ART. This study revealed that adherence levels as 
low as 80% to 90% may be adequate for viral suppression in 
patients taking newer antiretroviral drugs. Our data also showed 
that pooled odds ratios for virologic failure for optimal adher-
ence compared to suboptimal adherence were similar between 
NNRTI-based and boosted PI-based regimens. The effective-
ness of newer antiretroviral agents at the lower level of adher-
ence may encourage the prescribing of ART at an early stage of 
HIV infection. 
The findings indicated that the mean proportion of patients 
who were reported to demonstrate optimal adherence world-
wide was 63.4%, which is similar to a meta-analysis of 84 
studies that reported 62% of patients take !90% of their 
prescribed ART. 
55 The results of this study demonstrate that 
adherence is robustly associated with virologic outcomes across 
the various types of adherence measure, ART regimen, study 
population, and reporting. The odds of virologic failure were 
almost 3 times higher for participants with suboptimal adher-
ence compared with those with optimal adherence. This 
confirms that achieving long-term optimal adherence is indeed 
Achilles' heel of successful virologic outcomes. 
56 The need for </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Association between adherence to antiretroviral therapy and virologic failure. </p>

<p>-4 
-3 
-2 
-1 
0 
1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>Standard Error </p>

<p>Log odds ratio </p>

<p>Funnel Plot of Standard Error by Log odds ratio </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Funnel plot for the association between adherence to 
antiretroviral therapy and virologic failure (P ¼ 0.68 at Egger's test). </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 
Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy and Virologic Failure </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>

<p>clinicians to exert concerted efforts to maintain continuing 
optimal adherence to antiretroviral therapy is indisputable. 
Classifying patients according to various optimal adher-
ence thresholds (!98-100%, !95%, and 80-90%) did not 
result in statistically significant differences in the odds of 
virologic failure. This finding is consistent with a meta-analysis 
of 37 studies in children that reported no significant group 
differences in virologic outcomes between different thresholds 
of good adherence. 
57 This suggests that patients who achieved 
''perfect'' (100%) or ''near perfect'' (!95%) adherence did not 
necessarily have better virologic outcomes than patients who 
had achieved ''good enough'' (!80-90%) adherence. This 
finding has clinical importance and is in line with previous 
studies 
58,59 that indicated that although the need to maintain 
high levels of adherence to achieve long-term virologic sup-
pression is clear, the level of adherence behavior capable of 
sustaining viral suppression is broader than previously thought. 
Considerable variation in the relationship between adher-
ence and virologic outcomes was found based on the type of 
adherence measurement used in the studies we reviewed. For 
studies using self-reported adherence, the odds of virologic 
failure in participants with optimal adherence was about half 
that of participants with suboptimal adherence. The odds of 
virologic failure for optimal adherence were about one-third and 
one-seventh that of the participants with suboptimal adherence </p>

<p>using pharmacy refill and MEMS, respectively. Our meta-
analysis undermines the validity of using self-reported adher-
ence to distinguish virologic outcomes. A high proportion of 
patients with optimal self-reported adherence experienced vir-
ologic failure. Self-reported adherence is potentially con-
founded by social desirability and recall bias, which leads 
patients to overestimate their actual adherence; 
60 this method 
is inferior to MEMS in its ability to explain virologic outcomes. 
Despite the findings 
17,61 of previous studies suggesting the 
need for different levels of optimal adherence between anti-
retroviral regimens for achieving similar virologic outcomes, 
classifying patients based on regimen did not result in statisti-
cally significant differences in the odds of virologic outcomes in 
this meta-analysis. 
The pooled odds ratio for optimal adherence compared to 
suboptimal adherence for virologic failure for studies with 
virologic failure cut-offs &lt; 100 copies/mL were significantly 
higher than studies with virologic failure cut-offs between 
500 copies/mL and 1000 copies/mL. The rate of virologic fail-
ure detected in patients with good adherence increased when 
studies defined a virologic failure at a low level of HIV-1 
ribonucleic acid (RNA). The relationship between adherence 
and viral load improved when the level of detection of HIV-1 
RNA increased. The tighter the definition of virologic failure 
the more likely it is to unmask suboptimal adherence. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Subgroup Analysis Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy and Virologic Failure </p>

<p>Analysis Group 
No of Studies 
Pooled Odds Ratio (95% CI) </p>

<p>Tests for Heterogeneity </p>

<p>P Value (Q Statistic) 
I 
2 (%) </p>

<p>Study design 
Randomized controlled trial 
11 
0.55 (0.33-0.92) 
&lt;0.001 
85 
Observational study 
32 
0.29 (0.22-0.38) 
&lt;0.001 
90 
HDI rank 
High HDI 
21 
0.23 (0.15-0.33) 
&lt;0.001 
91 
Low HDI 
19 
0.50 (0.35-0.72) 
&lt;0.001 
87 
Regimen 
NNRTI-based 
17 
0.54 (0.38-0.77) 
&lt;0.001 
88 
Boosted PI-based 
4 
0.31 (0.14-0.71) 
0.06 
59 
Unboosted PI-based 
5 
0.25 (0.13-0.47) 
0.11 
47 
Treatment experience 
Naive 
22 
0.33 (0.23-0.47) 
&lt;0.001 
94 
Experienced 
12 
0.52 (0.41-0.66) 
0.36 
9 
Naive and experienced 
9 
0.28 (0.17-0.46) 
0.001 
69 
Threshold used to define virological failure 
100 copies/mL 
11 
0.55 (0.41-0.74) 
0.01 
56 
100-400 copies/mL 
17 
0.37 (0.26-0.54) 
&lt;0.001 
88 
!500 copies/mL 
14 
0.25 (0.16-0.41) 
&lt;0.001 
92 
Threshold used to define optimal adherence group 
!98-100% 
7 
0.54 (0.29-1.00) 
&lt;0.001 
85 
!95% 
30 
0.34 (0.24-0.47) 
&lt;0.001 
92 
!80-90% 
6 
0.34 (0.23-0.51) 
0.57 
0 
Measurement 
Self-report 
14 
0.45 (0.37-0.55) 
0.13 
31 
Pharmacy refill 
18 
0.29 (0.20-0.41) 
&lt;0.001 
94 
MEMS 
6 
0.15 (0.06-0.37) 
0.18 
35 
Pill count 
4 
0.80 (0.21-3.02) 
&lt;0.001 
93 </p>

<p>CI ¼ confidence interval, HDI ¼ United Nations human development index, MEMS ¼ medication event monitoring system, NNRTIs ¼ 
nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors, PIs ¼ protease inhibitors. </p>

<p>Bezabhe et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>The odds of virologic failure for optimal adherence were 
about half and one-third that of the patients with suboptimal 
adherence in countries with a low HDI and high HDI, respect-
ively. More patients with optimal adherence experienced vir-
ologic failure in countries with low HDI than in countries with 
high HDI. This review indicates that patients with equal or 
better levels of optimal adherence in developing countries 
compared to developed countries 
62 does not necessarily trans-
late into better virologic outcomes. This might be associated 
with the increase in pretreatment antiretroviral drug resistance </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>and unavailability of baseline HIV drug resistance testing 
before initiation of ART 
64 in resource-limited settings that have 
a potential to contribute to the increasing rates of virologic 
failure in optimally adherent patients. We support moves 
toward the use viral load monitoring at the point of care in 
resource-limited settings 
65 to improve treatment outcomes. 
Study design (observational study vs randomized con-
trolled trials) was an independent predictor of between-study 
heterogeneity. More patients with optimal adherence experi-
enced virologic failure in randomized controlled trials than in 
observational studies. Differences in estimated magnitude of 
treatment effect are very common between randomized con-
trolled trials and observational studies. 
66 This difference in 
virologic outcomes between study designs might be related 
with selection bias in observational studies 
67 and higher quality 
and rigor of randomized controlled trials. 
This meta-analysis shares the limitations intrinsic to meta-
analysis in general and with studies of adherence in particular. 
We only included studies published in English, so we may have 
missed studies that were relevant to our research question 
during the literature search. When the included studies were 
stratified and analyzed based on regimen, virologic failure cut-
off, adherence cut-off and type of adherence measurement, </p>

<p>heterogeneity between-studies remained high for most of the 
subgroups. Because of this high degree of heterogeneity, which 
was not entirely described either by subgroup analysis or by 
meta-regression, our pooled results need to be viewed with 
caution. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Irrespective of the cut-off point for optimal adherence, our 
findings support the tenet that optimal adherence to ART is 
associated with positive clinical outcomes. The threshold for 
optimal adherence to achieve better virologic outcomes appears 
to be wider than the commonly used cut-off point (!95% 
adherence). Though patients taking ART should be instructed 
to attain !95% adherence, apprehensions of slightly lower 
adherence should not deter prescribing ART regimens at an 
early stage of HIV infection. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
The authors would like to acknowledge Yihienew Mequa-
nint for his assistance in screening articles and verifying the 
extracted data, and all study authors who responded to inquiries 
about relevant papers. 
This meta-analysis was conducted in partial fulfillment of a 
PhD in Pharmacy at School of Medicine, University of Tasma-
nia. The authors received no specific funding for this research. </p>



<p>TABLE 3. Meta-Regression Analysis of Moderators for the Association Between Antiretroviral Adherence and Virologic Failure </p>

<p>Moderator 
Category 1 
Category 2 </p>

<p>Regression 
Coefficient (95%CI) P Value </p>

<p>I 
2 Inconsistency 
Q Statistic </p>

<p>Region 
Developing countries Developed countries 
0.79 (0.25, 1.32) 
0.004 
89.2%; 352.4 (38 df), P &lt; 0.001 
Regimen 
NNRTIs 
Boosted PIs 
0.58 (À0.42, 1.59) 
0.257 
88.8%; 349.11 (39 df), P &lt; 0.001 
Treatment experience 
Experienced 
Naive 
0.38 (À0.27, 1.04) 
0.250 
90.1%; 404.22 (40 df), P &lt; 0.001 
Threshold used to 
define virologic failure </p>

<p>100-400 copies/mL 
100 copies/mL 
À0.30 (À0.92, 0.33) 
0.353 
87.5%; 312.53 (39 df), P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>!500 copies/mL 
100 copies/mL 
À0.75 (À1.39, À0.12) 
0.020 
Threshold used to define 
optimal adherence group </p>

<p>!80-90% 
!98-100% 
À0.56 (À1.62, À0.51) 
0.304 
90.7%; 430.21 (40 df), P &lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>!95% 
!98-100% 
À0.54 (À1.31, 0.23) 
0.171 
Measurement 
Pharmacy refill 
Self-report 
À0.22 (À0.78, 0.34) 
0.446 
90.2%; 398.75 (df 39), P &lt; 0.001 
MEMS 
Self-report 
À1.00 (À2.05, 0.06) 
0.064 
Pill count 
Self-report 
0.17 (À0.89, 1.24) 
0.749 
Study design 
RCT 
Observational study 
0.66 (0.10, 1.21) 
0.020 
88.7%; 364.17 (41 df), P &lt; 0.001 
Observation period 
1 year 
&gt;1 year 
0.15 (À0.38, 0.69) 
0.574 
90.1%; 413.84 (31 df), P &lt; 0.001 
Year of publication 
!2005 
&lt;2005 
0.67 (0.07, 1.28) 
0.028 
89.6%; 394.36 (41 df), P &lt; 0.001 
Multivariate 
Region 
Developing countries 
Developed 
0.56 (0.01, 1.12) 
0.048 
82.6%; 172.5 (30 df), P &lt; 0.001 
Threshold used to define 
virologic failure </p>

<p>!500 copies/mL 
100 copies/mL 
À0.46 (À1.23, 0.30) 
0.238 </p>

<p>Measurement 
MEMS 
Self-report 
À0.50 (À1.58, 0.58) 
0.366 
Study design 
RCT 
Observational study 
0.74 (0.04, 1.43) 
0.038 
Year of publication 
!2005 
&lt;2005 
0.43 (À0.37, 1.23) 
0.291 </p>

<p>MEMS ¼ medication event monitoring system, NNRTIs ¼ nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors, PIs ¼ protease inhibitors. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 
Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy and Virologic Failure </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 7 </p>



<p>37. Pasternak AO, de Bruin M, Jurriaans S, et al. Modest nonadherence 
to antiretroviral therapy promotes residual HIV-1 replication in the </p>

<p>Bezabhe et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 15, April 2016 
Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy and Virologic Failure </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 9 </p>

</text></tei>