<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4307762" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>www.scielo.br/jaos 
http://dx.F </p>

<p>avorable results in the use of castor oil polyurethane (COP) as pulp capping, membrane 
material, sealer, mouthwash and in bone repair, associated with the fact that Ricinus 
communis is not derived from petroleum and it is abundant in Brazil, encourage researches </p>

<p>(FS) of a castor oil-containing dental luting agent with a weight percentage of 10% (wt%) 
of calcium carbonate (COP10) with RelyX ARC (RX) after mechanical cycling (MC) and 
distilled water storage. Material and Methods: Sixty-four specimens (25x2x2 mm) were 
fabricated and divided into two groups, COP10 and RX (control). Each group was divided 
into 4 subgroups (n=8) according to the storage time, 24 hours (24 h) or 60 days (60 
d), and the performance (MC+FS) or not (only FS) of the mechanical cycling test. The FS 
(10 kN; 0.5 mm/min) and MC tests (10,000 cycles, 5 Hz, 0.5 mm/min) were carried out 
using an MTS-810 machine. The data were analyzed using ANOVA (α=0.05). Results: The 
obtained FS (MPa) values were: COP10 24h-19.04±2.41; COP10 60d-17.92±3.54; RX 
24h-75.19±3.43; RX 60d-88.77±6.89. All the RX specimens submitted to MC fractured, 
while the values for COP10 after MC were as follows: COP10 24h-17.90±1.87 and COP10 
60d-18.60±1.60. Conclusions: A castor oil-containing dental luting agent with a weight 
percentage of 10% (wt%) of calcium carbonate is resistant to mechanical cycling without </p>

<p>Polymers are biocompatible materials of natural 
or synthetic origin that can be prepared by different 
methods 
34 . In dentistry, various polymers are 
used, such as silicone, methyl methacrylate and 
polyurethane. Currently, vegetable-polyurethane, 
which combines the versatility of polymer formulation 
while addressing the global concern towards 
producing new biomaterials from sustainable 
resources, has become one of the most studied 
biomaterials </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. The use of vegetable-polyurethane 
derived from castor oil (COP) in the health science 
fields has been studied, and COP has shown </p>

<p>favorable results in tests for biocompatibility 
22 . 
Castor oil is a new material that is globally available, 
and it has received much attention in recent years 
because of its availability on a large commercial 
scale </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>. 
The COP is a biocompatible, antimicrobial, 
osteointegrable and absorbable, osteoconductive 
and osteoinductive </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>. In dentistry, the use of this 
polymer has been studied in direct pulp capping </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, 
as a membrane material 
22 , as a sealer 
31 , as a 
mouthwash </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>, as bone prosthesis and in alveolar 
healing 
7 and bone reconstruction 
20 . In clinical 
research focusing on human dental alveoli, Jowett, 
et al. 
19 (1988) showed that this polyurethane has </p>

<p>2014;22(6):496-501 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 497 </p>

<p>good biocompatibility for use both in soft and hard 
tissue, has osteoinductive properties, and can be 
bactericidal and fungicidal when combined with 
calcium carbonate. 
The versatility of the polyurethane derived from 
castor oil as well as the aforementioned positive 
aspects support the study of COP as a dental luting 
agent. Although a wide range of dental luting agents 
is commercially available, the selection of a luting 
agent to be used for a given restoration should not 
be an arbitrary choice. It must be based on a basic 
knowledge of the materials available, the type of 
restoration to be placed, and the requirements 
17 based on the functional and 
biological needs 
2 of a particular clinical situation, 
including handling characteristics such as working 
time, setting time, consistency and ease of removal 
of excess material 
33 . As such, no single dental 
luting agent is considered ideal, and new products 
should be studied. It is important to characterize 
the mechanical, physical and biological properties of 
COP. When compared with zinc phosphate cement, 
the COP, with the addition of calcium carbonate, 
presented better diametral tensile strength values 
6 . 
The addition of calcium carbonate is responsible 
for conferring radiopacity to COP </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>. Moreover, this </p>

<p>ion exchange at the bone/resin matrix interface </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>margins. The COP dental luting agents are deemed 
strong enough to resist masticatory stresses and 
provide retention similar to that of zinc phosphate 
cement, a permanent cementation material </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>. 
In the oral cavity, the chewing forces applied to 
restorative materials result in cycles of mechanical 
impulses that lead to material fatigue and, 
consequently, fracture. These impulses can 
be simulated in the laboratory by performing 
mechanical cycling, which approaches the 
physiological conditions generated by the chewing 
cycle </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>. Fixed partial dentures are more likely to be 
subjected to bending forces than to other types of 
stress </p>

<p>10,25,26 </p>

<p>restorative material are more important than their 
tensile, shear and compressive strengths. Moreover, </p>

<p>appropriate for simulating the clinical situation of 
material fatigue 
4,32 because the concentration of </p>

<p>in the dental luting agent prior to the fracture or 
displacement of the restoration material 
11 . The 
mechanical properties of resinous materials are 
directly related to the quantity and type of inorganic 
particles </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>, degree of cure and percentage of silane-</p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>. 
Most current in vitro studies include cycling testing </p>

<p>of stress on the material </p>

<p>16,21 </p>

<p>. 
The aim of this study was to assess the behavior 
of COP under masticatory stress simulated by </p>

<p>with a weight percentage of 10% (wt%) of calcium 
carbonate was analyzed with and without the 
performance of the mechanical cycling test as well 
as with storage in distilled water. The results were 
compared with the results for RelyX ARC. The null 
hypothesis was that there is no difference between </p>

<p>ARC. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS </p>

<p>The procedure of the study is summarized in 
Figure 1. For the COP10 group, 32 specimens were 
fabricated with the castor oil-containing dental 
luting agent (Castor Oil Polyurethane -COP, Poliquil 
Araraquara, Chemical Polymers Ltd, Araraquara, SP, 
Brazil) with a weight percentage of 10% (wt%) of 
calcium carbonate (CaCO 3 ). For the control group, 
named RX, 32 specimens were fabricated with the 
resin cement RelyX ARC (3M ESPE, Sumaré, SP, 
Brazil). Each group was randomly divided into 4 
subgroups (n=8) according to the storage time 
in distilled water, 24 hours (24 h) or 60 days (60 
d), and the performance or not of the mechanical 
cycling (MC) test. 
The COP was provided in a sachet containing 
polyol, prepolymer and calcium carbonate 
6 . This 
polyurethane has the following highly reactive 
groups in the ricinoleic acid structure: a carbonyl 
group on the first carbon, a double bond (or 
unsaturation) on the ninth carbon and a hydroxyl 
group on the twelfth carbon. This combination of a 
hydroxyl group and unsaturation occurs exclusively 
in the castor oil molecule 
14 . Prepolymer was 
synthesized from methylene diphenyl diisocyanate 
(MDI) and was prepolymerized with the polyol while 
preserving 20% of free isocyanate. When these 
two components were mixed, the moisture-curing 
kinetics was determined by the polymerization 
reaction between the isocyanate and hydroxyl 
groups. The stoichiometric ratio between the polyol 
and the prepolymer was equal to 1:0.66. 
For the COP10 specimens, the material was 
manually mixed in the sachet for 2 minutes. It was </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>This apparatus was placed in a mechanical press 
under constant load and stored in saturated water 
vapor in a container lined with wet paper at 37°C 
for one hour </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>. 
For the RX group, the cement was manipulated </p>

<p>2014;22(6):496-501 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 498 </p>

<p>according to the instructions of the manufacturer, </p>

<p>cured with light at three points along its length on 
both sides for 40 seconds each </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>. The matrix was 
placed in a mechanical press under constant load 
and stored in saturated water vapor in a container 
lined with wet paper at 37°C for one hour </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>. 
After the initial storage period of 1 hour, all 
the samples were removed from the matrix and 
polished with 200 grit silicon carbide sandpaper 
(3M ESPE). Then, they were measured at three 
points using a digital caliper (500-144B, Mitutoyo 
Sul America Ltd, Suzano, SP, Brazil) to verify the 
width and thickness. A variance of ±0.2 mm was 
accepted. The samples were immersed in distilled </p>

<p>to the subgroups. 
All samples were subjected to 3-point bending </p>

<p>test, which was conducted in a universal testing 
machine (MTS 810, Material Test System, Eden 
Prairie, MN) equipped with the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Test Work</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4</rs> software, 
at a crosshead of 0.5 mm/min 
18 and with a 10 kN 
load cell. The FS values were calculated in MPa </p>

<p>point, I=distance between the supports, b=width 
of the samples, d=thickness of the samples). The 
MC procedure was carried out under conditions 
equivalent to those used for the FS test. Samples 
were submitted to 10,000 cycles at a frequency of 
5 Hz and a cross-head displacement of 0.5 mm. The 
initial load was 60% of the mean FS value previously 
obtained. After completing the MC, samples were 
submitted to FS. Normality distribution within each 
sample was done using Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, 
and the comparison between the experimental </p>

<p>COP10 
RX </p>

<p>24 hours 
60 days 
24 hours 
60 days </p>

<p>Without mechanical 
cycling </p>

<p>19.04±2.41 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>17.92±3.54 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>75.19±3.43 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>88.77±6.89 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>With mechanical 
cycling </p>

<p>17.90±1.87 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>18.60±1.60 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Table 1-
performance of mechanical cycling test </p>

<p>* Specimens did not resist the mechanical cycling </p>

<p>Figure 1-Flow chart of the study </p>

<p>DERCELI JR, FAIS LMG, PINELLI LAP </p>

<p>2014;22(6):496-501 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 499 </p>

<p>subgroups was performed using analysis of </p>

<p>5% (α=0.05). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The FS values are shown in Table 1. The COP10 
specimens had mean only about 25% of the RelyX 
ARC. The RX samples did not resist the mechanical 
cycling and fractured before the 10,000 cycles were 
completed. Two-way ANOVA among the subgroups </p>

<p>the FS values as a function of either the "mechanical 
cycling" (F 1,28 =0.068; p=.0795) or "storage time" 
(F 1,28 </p>

<p>of RelyX ARC storage (F 1,14 =24.860, p&lt;.0002); it </p>

<p>strength of the RX samples (Table 1). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, the null hypothesis was rejected </p>

<p>different from that of the RelyX ARC, a commercially 
available and most widely used resin cement. Two 
clinical situations were assessed using conditions 
designed to simulate the oral environment: aging 
was simulated by storage in aqueous medium </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>, 
and chewing forces were simulated by mechanical 
cycling </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>because previous studies have shown its ability 
to provide radiopacity to the COP and to supply 
bactericidal and fungicidal properties to the cement, 
properties that can be a key factor in the selection of 
a dental luting agent. The addition of 10% calcium 
carbonate showed good results regarding diametral </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>. 
The mechanical properties of resinous materials 
are directly related to the quantity and type 
(composition, shape, size and distribution) of the 
inorganic particles </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>, degree of cure and percentage </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>particles </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>. The results of this study showed that, </p>

<p>COP10 group was lower than that of the RelyX ARC 
group. This result can be explained by differences </p>

<p>cements. 
The RelyX ARC is composed of the following: 
1) an organic matrix composed of monomers, 
polymerization inhibitors, color modifiers and 
an initiator/activator system; 2) a zirconia/silica </p>

<p>3) organo-silane as a bonding agent between the </p>

<p>is composed of the following: 1) a matrix that </p>

<p>results from the polymerization of polyester from 
vegetable polyol with linear aliphatic diisocyanates; 
2) 10% (wt%) of calcium carbonate by weight as </p>

<p>of a bonding agent, which could result in the 
consequent failure in the linking-up of the inorganic 
particles with the resin matrix, could be a key </p>

<p>However, even though the FS mean for COP10 was 
only about 25% of that of RelyX ARC, the FS values 
were similar or slightly less than those found for 
luting agents such as zinc phosphate (18 MPa), 
glass ionomer cement (15-36 MPa) and resin-</p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. 
The specimens made from the resin cement 
RelyX ARC did not achieve the FS values reported </p>

<p>(86±6 -155±7 MPa) in 24 hours 
18 . However, 
after 60 days of storage in distilled water, this 
dental luting agent showed an 18% increase in 
FS in comparison with the values obtained after 
24 hours. It has been shown in the literature 
that mechanical resistance results can vary as a </p>

<p>cure and testing method used </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>. According some 
authors </p>

<p>10,12,26 </p>

<p>, increases in FS, even in the presence </p>

<p>or continued polymerization that may occur in dual-
cure cements. </p>

<p>strength of the COP10 specimens remained 
statistically similar to that observed after 24 
hours of storage. According to the manufactures 
of the COP, after 1 hour, the cement has acquired 
strength, although it can continue to present 
residual polymerization for up to 36 hours after 
the initial mixing, thought most of the isocyanate-
hydroxyl reaction is completed in 24 hours. As 
such, in this study, the residual polymerization 
that occurred between 24 and 36 hours of storage </p>

<p>values. Moreover, considering that the specimens 
were immersed in distilled water and that the 
free isocyanates may have reacted with water 
molecules, it was interesting that there was no 
decrease in FS, i.e., the long-term effect of water 
storage did not affect the FS of the COP10, similarly </p>

<p>deionized water </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>. 
The results of the MC test show that the RelyX </p>

<p>may be the result of the large amount of zirconia/ 
silica filler (67.5 wt%) incorporated into the 
matrix </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>the fracturing of the material without the occurrence 
of behaviour elastic. In comparison, the COP10 </p>

<p>2014;22(6):496-501 </p>

<p>J Appl Oral Sci. 500 </p>

<p>showed no change in FS after mechanical cycling, 
possibly due to the higher elasticity provided by the </p>

<p>failure potential of a cemented restoration under 
forces is related to the mechanical properties of the 
individual parts (periodontal ligament, tooth, luting 
agent and restoration) </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>. Despite reports of success 
of RelyX ARC </p>

<p>1,27 </p>

<p>, current literature shows that the 
comparisons based on adhesive properties and </p>

<p>partial dentures (FPD) cemented with RelyX ARC are 
still limited. Then, this in vitro study was carried out 
as a preliminary study to investigate and compare 
the behavior of the COP10 under tension, without </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>. Future studies </p>

<p>and fatigue) behavior of crowns or FPD cemented 
with these two materials in order to enhance the 
knowledge about COP10 and RelyX ARC. 
Despite the limitations inherent to an in vitro 
study as well as the lower FS values of the COP10 
that were observed, this dental luting agent can 
still be considered a promising material due to 
its characteristics related to biocompatibility, 
elasticity, mechanical strength and versatility </p>

<p>34 . 
Moreover, Ricinus communis is a plant easily found 
in Brazil with great potential in the manufacturing of 
products derived from its oil. As such, future studies 
should be conducted to assess COP containing 
higher concentrations of CaCO 3 and the addition </p>

<p>improve its mechanical resistance, causing it to 
have properties similar to those of commercially 
available resin cements. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>A castor oil-containing dental luting agent with a 
10% weight percentage (wt%) of calcium carbonate 
resisted mechanical cycling without decreases in </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank São Paulo Research Foundation </p>

<p>2006/02821-8). </p>



<p>DERCELI JR, FAIS LMG, PINELLI LAP </p>

<p>2014;22(6):496-501 </p>



<p>2014;22(6):496-501 </p>

</text></tei>