<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4303280" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: Using alendronate after spinal fusion is a controversial issue due to the inhibition of osteoclast mediated bone 
resorption. In addition, there are an increasing number of reports that the endplate degeneration influences the lumbar spinal 
fusion. The object of this retrospective controlled study was to evaluate how the endplate degeneration and the bisphospho-
nate medication influence the spinal fusion through radiographic evaluation. 
Methods: In this study, 44 patients who underwent single-level posterior lumbar interbody fusion (PLIF) using cage were 
examined from April 2007 to March 2009. All patients had been diagnosed as osteoporosis and would be recommended 
for alendronate medication. Endplate degeneration is categorized by the Modic changes. The solid fusion is defined if there 
was bridging bone between the vertebral bodies, either within or external to the cage on the plain X-ray and if there is 
less than 5° of angular difference in dynamic X-ray. 
Results: In alendronate group, fusion was achieved in 66.7% compared to 73.9% in control group (no medication). Alendronate 
did not influence the fusion rate of PLIF. However, there was the statistical difference of fusion rate between the endplate 
degeneration group and the group without endplate degeneration. A total of 52.4% of fusion rate was seen in the endplate 
degeneration group compared to 91.3% in the group without endplate degeneration. The endplate degeneration suppresses 
the fusion process of PLIF. 
Conclusion: Alendronate does not influence the fusion process in osteoporotic patients. The endplate degeneration decreases 
the fusion rate. </p>

<p>Alendronate medication has been the standard treatment for 
patients with osteoporosis </p>

<p>2,24) </p>

<p>. Alendronate binds to resorption 
surfaces of the bone and is locally released during acidification, 
and the rise in concentration stops resorption and membrane 
ruffling without destroying the osteoclasts </p>

<p>23) </p>

<p>. Alendronate alte-
red the density distributions, thereby decreasing the area with 
a high fracture risk, resulting in increased vertebral strength </p>

<p>7) </p>

<p>. 
Despite these good effects on treating osteoporosis, using alend-</p>

<p>ronate after spinal fusion is the controversial issue due to the </p>

<p>inhibition of osteoclast mediated bone resorption. Many in 
vitro studies show the negative effect of alendronate to the </p>

<p>lumbar spinal interbody fusion </p>

<p>6,9,13) </p>

<p>. However, recent prospec-
tive randomized control studies showed that alendronate over-
came its detrimental biological effect on the healing process 
of spinal fusion 18. The endplate degeneration of the lumbar 
spine has been thought as the source of back pain, but it also 
influenced the lumbar spinal fusion </p>

<p>12) </p>

<p>. Signal intensity changes 
of vertebral endplates and subchondral bone are often obser-
ved in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) in patients with spi-
nal degenerative diseases. In 1988, Modic et al. 
16,17) summari-
zed these changes and classified them into three types, and 
then Modic changes (MC), as a medical term, were used in the 
studies on spinal degenerative diseases. Although the etiology 
of MC remains poorly understood, some progress has been 
achieved in basic research during the past two decades, including 
studies of the prevalence and some clinical significance. 
What if there is the endplate degeneration at the fusion 
level, would activity of osteoclast increase or decrease to influ-
ence the fusion process? If the activity of osteoclast increase </p>

<p>Kim SM et al. </p>



<p>Fig. 1. (A) Plain static radiograph interpreted as a successful 
fusion. (B) Plain static radiograph interpreted as a non-fusion. </p>

<p>than is it reasonable to give alendronate to patient by expecting 
the inhibiting effect of osteoclast? If the activity of osteoclast 
decrease than is it harmful for giving alendronate to the patient? 
The object of this retrospective study was to evaluate how 
the endplate degeneration and the alendronate medication 
influence the fusion rate of osteoporotic patient through radio-
graphic evaluation. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>1. Patient Population </p>

<p>In this study, 44 patients who underwent single-level lumbar 
interbody fusion using cage were examined from April 2007 
to March 2009. Nine patients were male and thirty-five pa-
tients were female. The patients' mean age was 64.7 years (range 
60-74 years). The patients were diagnosed as degenerative 
spondylolisthesis, isthmic spondylolisthesis, severe intracanal 
stenosis, foraminal stenosis, and recurred herniated interverte-
bral disc (HIVD). The minimum X-ray follow up period was 
2 years (range 2-5 years) and the mean follow up period was 
33.8 months. 
All patients were diagnosed as osteoporosis using computed 
tomography (CT) bone densitometry and recommended for 
pharmacological treatment. The diagnosis of osteoporosis was 
made according to the World Health Organization. Patients 
were divided into the alendronate group (alendronate sodium 
[Fosamax] 35 mg/week) or the control group. The control group 
was classified as patients who were not taking alendronate 
for less than 1 week due to poor economic conditions and 
gastrointestinal trouble. Compared to the previous study </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>, 
we did not give vitamin D, calcium supplement, and any other 
medication for osteoporosis to the control group. The mean 
preoperative lumbar spine BMC and T-score were 63.76 mg/cc 
and -3.75 in the alendronate group, and 69.58 mg/cc and -3.98 
in the control group. There was no statistical difference between 
age and BMC, and between the control and alendronate group. </p>

<p>2. Radiographic Assessment </p>

<p>Endplate degeneration is categorized by the Modic classifi-
cation </p>

<p>16,17) </p>

<p>. Modic change type 1 [hypo-intense signal in 
T1-weighted imaging (T1WI) and hyperintense signal in T2-
weighted imaging (T2WI)] is corresponding to the vertebral 
body edema and hyper-vascularity. MC type 2 (hyperintense 
signal in T1WI and hyperintense signal in T2WI) is reflecting 
fatty replacements of the red bone marrow. MC type 3 
(hypointense signal in T1WI and hypointense signal in T2WI) 
was consisted of subchondral bone sclerosis. </p>

<p>The plain static radiographs were examined by two different 
neurosurgeons. They were interpreted as demonstrating the 
presence of fusion if there was a bridging bone between the 
vertebral bodies either within or external to the cage </p>

<p>22) </p>

<p>. Fig. 
1A shows a typical radiograph assessed as demonstrating a solid 
fusion. Fig. 1B shows the features of a pseudarthrosis with dis-
continuity in the bone graft and lucency adjacent to the cage. 
The flexion radiographs were taken with the patient in the 
standing position trying to bend forward as far as possible, 
whereas the extension radiographs were taken with the patient 
maximally arching his or her back. The spinal surgeon used 
the method advocated by Simmons </p>

<p>15) </p>

<p>, which involved identify-
ing two landmarks on the anterior portion of the superior and 
inferior vertebral bodies, drawing a line through these land-
marks, and measuring the angle subtended by the two resulting 
lines. An increase of 2° in the acute angle made by these two 
lines on extension views was considered to be a sign of non-
union. The apparent fusion rate was also determined using 
this same method, except that the 5° cutoff prescribed by the 
United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) was used. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The chi-square test was used to determine whether there 
is a significant difference between two groups in Fig. 2 to 6. 
The p value (&lt;0.01) was used to test statistical significance 
of evidence. The <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs>21(Statistical Package for the Social 
Sciences <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">21.0</rs>) was used to analyzed. Overall, 75% of fusion 
rate was seen and 25% of non-fusion rate was seen. In alend-
ronate group, fusion was achieved in 66.7% compared to 
73.9% in control group (no medication) (Fig. 2). There was 
no statistical difference between the two groups (p=0.599). 
Alendronate seems to have no effect on the fusion rate. 
The endplate degeneration was classified by Modic </p>

<p>16,17) </p>

<p>. A 
total of 52.4% of fusion rate was seen in the endplate degene-
ration group compared to 91.3% in the group without endplate </p>

<p>Medication for Osteoporosis cannot make Difference in the Lumbar Spinal Fusion </p>

<p>Korean J Spine 11(4) December 2014 223 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Fusion rate of the group with alendronate medication 
and the group with no-medication. In alendronate group, fusion 
was achieved in 66.7% compared to 73.9% in control group 
(no medication). There was no statistical difference between the 
two groups (p=0.599). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Fusion rate in the group with Modic changes and without 
Modic changes. 52.4% of fusion rate was seen in the Modic 
changes group compared to 91.3% in the group without Modic 
changes. There was a statistical difference between the two groups 
(p=0.004). </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Influence of Modic changes type to fusion rate. There was 
no statistical difference of fusion rate between Modic change types 
(p=0.293). </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Fusion rate of the group without Endplate degeneration 
(without Modic change). In alendronate group fusion was achieved 
in 92.3% of patients. In control group fusion was achieved in 90 
% of patients. There was no statistical difference between two 
groups (p=0.846). </p>

<p>degeneration (Fig. 3). There was a statistical difference of fusion 
rate between the endplate degeneration group and the group 
without endplate degeneration (p=0.599). Endplate degenera-
tion decreases the fusion rate in PLIF. However, subtypes of 
MC do not influence the fusion rate. There was no statistical 
difference of fusion rate between the MC types (p=0.293) (Fig. 4). 
Comparison of alendronate effect on patient without end-
plate degeneration shows in Fig. 5. In alendronate group fu-
sion was achieved in 92.3% of patients. In control group fu-
sion was achieved in 90% of patients. There was no statistical 
difference between two groups (p=0.846). Alendronate did 
not influence the fusion rate of patients without endplate dege-
neration. Among patients with endplate degeneration fusion 
was achieved in 37.5% of patients in alendronate group. In 
control group fusion was achieved in 61.5% of patients (Fig. </p>

<p>6). There was no statistical difference between two groups (p 
=0.284). Alendronate seems to have no effect on the fusion 
rate of the group with endplate degeneration. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The skeleton is a dynamic tissue that could remodel and 
repair the constant mirocracks that develop both in the can-
cellous bone and in the cortical bone for a lifetime </p>

<p>8) </p>

<p>. It had 
been assumed that the mechanisms of bone remodeling were 
likely to be different in cancellous versus cortical bone </p>

<p>8) </p>

<p>. Spe-
cifically, the assumption was that the cells needed for bone 
remodeling traveled directly from the red marrow to the bone 
surfaces in cancellous bone, whereas they accessed cortical </p>

<p>Kim SM et al. </p>



<p>Fig. 6. Fusion rate of the group with Endplate degeneration (with 
Modic change). In alendronate group fusion was achieved in 
37.5% of patients. In control group fusion was achieved in 61.5% of 
patients. There was no statistical difference between two groups 
(p=0.284). </p>

<p>bone via the vasculature </p>

<p>20) </p>

<p>. 
The successful spinal surgery is depending on gaining the 
long-stand spinal stability. Because of the spinal instrumentation 
gives short-term support, the solid bony fusion is necessary 
to obtain permanent stability. Coordination between bone 
formation and resorption is very important for spinal fusion. 
The evaluation of factors that influence the lumbar spinal 
interbody fusion is very difficult to assess due to the com-
plexity of biomechanics of each patient and difference in bone 
quality. Effects of spinal biomechanics are hard to quantify, 
whereas the bone quality can be easily measured by using bone 
densitometry and differentiated by using MRI according to 
Modic </p>

<p>16,17) </p>

<p>. Most of spine surgeons believe that osteoporosis-
related bone fragility is the primary reason for implant fixation 
failure </p>

<p>11) </p>

<p>, and it leads to fusion Failure </p>

<p>4,14) </p>

<p>. 
Both osteoporosis and MC related spinal fusion rate has 
been known to be low compared to normal or osteopenic 
patients </p>

<p>12,18) </p>

<p>. The only available human study shows osteopo-
rosis and alendronate influence the spinal fusion rate </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>. This 
study demonstrates a solid fusion was achieved in 95% of 
patients in the alendronate group, and 65% of those in the 
control group </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>. Most animal studies 
1,3,5,13,19,21,26-29) evaluating 
the impact of bisphosphonates on fusion rate have not found 
statistically significant changes with treatment, although this 
fact may be attributable to low statistical power. The animal 
literature does suggest that bisphosphonate therapy results in 
a less histologically mature fusion mass; however, the impact 
of these changes on fusion mass biomechanics is unclear. There 
are many studies about the endplate degeneration correlating 
with the symptoms, but few studies report a correlation 
between MC and spinal fusion. Kwon 
12) shows that the bony 
fusion rate was 97% in patients without degeneration and 
83% in patients with MC. The bony fusion rate in each group </p>

<p>was 81% in type 1, 84% in type 2, and 55% in type 3. The 
clinical success and fusion rates were significantly lower in 
patients with type 3 degeneration </p>

<p>12) </p>

<p>. 
Generally accepted fusion rate of lumbar spine is around 
85-95% </p>

<p>10) </p>

<p>. In our study, the overall fusion rate was 75%. 
Since half of the patients had MC in lumbar spine endplate, 
which could lower the fusion rate, fusion rate of our study 
could be acceptable. 
We reviewed the osteoporotic patients into two groups. 
The fusion rate of the alendronate group was 76.2% compared 
to 73.9% of the control group. There was no statistical differe-
nce between the alendronate group and the control group. 
This result refutes the previous prospective randomized con-
trolled study </p>

<p>18) </p>

<p>. From this result we could speculate that alen-
dronate does not alter fusion rate in osteoporotic patients. 
We reviewed the patients into endplate degeneration and 
without the degeneration groups. A total of 42.9% of non-fusion 
rate was seen in the endplate degeneration group, compared 
to 8.7% in the group without endplate degeneration. There 
was the statistical difference of fusion rate between the end-
plate degeneration group and the group without endplate 
degeneration. Endplate degeneration had potential to decrease 
the lumbar interbody fusion. We also compared the fusion 
rate of endplate degeneration by MC. There was no statistical 
difference of fusion rate between MC. The degeneration itself 
influenced the fusion rate, but there was no difference between 
fusion rates of the MC subtypes. Small sample size and surgical 
technique might influence the outcome. Most of the spinal 
surgeons use endplate decortications technique, a process of 
making microfracture of fusion bed, during lumbar interbody 
fusion. This process would eliminate the cortical bone and 
sclerotic endplate degeneration, such as MC type 3, to making 
bone marrow surface in fusion bed. However, endplate dege-
neration seems to influence the biological environment for 
those osteoclasts and osteoblasts. The limitation of this result 
is that the thickness of sclerotic endplate had not been mea-
sured. The thicker at the endplate sclerosis, the harder to make 
good fusion bed. 
We also put both factors, alendronate and endplate degene-
ration, together to see how these factors influence the fusion 
rate of the lumbar spine. The effects of alendronate on oste-
oporotic patient with and without MC show that alendronate 
did not influence the fusion rate of patients whether patients 
had a MC or not. 
The limitation of this study was that despite the wide use 
of flexion-extension radiography, the definition of a solid fu-
sion still remains controversial. In the radiologic assessment 
of interbody fusion using carbon fiber cages, the use of plain 
radiographs and flexion-extension radiographs produced much 
higher fusion rates than assessment with thin-section helical </p>

<p>Medication for Osteoporosis cannot make Difference in the Lumbar Spinal Fusion </p>

<p>Korean J Spine 11(4) December 2014 225 </p>

<p>computed tomography scans </p>

<p>25) </p>

<p>. The thin-section helical com-
puted tomography studies demonstrated the radiographic pre-
sence or absence of bridging bone, a property that was not 
seen with plain static radiographs or flexion-extension radio-
graphs </p>

<p>22) </p>

<p>. Another limitation is the biomechanical loads on 
fusion level that could not be measured in number due to 
different lifestyle of each patient, such as jobs. 
Finally, we still have several questions to be answered in 
future research: (1) How long should patients take bisphos-
phonates before and after spinal fusion surgery to improve 
the strength of vertebral bodies? (2) Could the current findings 
in a single-level posterior lumbar interbody fusion be applied 
to other situations, including multi-level spinal fusion, or 
correction of spinal deformities? (3) How will different types 
of spinal fusion, especially posterolateral lumbar fusion, affect 
the fusion process under alendronate medication? (4) Does 
bridging bone under alendronate treatment have sufficient 
mechanical properties and bone quality? </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>This study showed that alendronate does not influence the 
fusion process in osteoporotic patients. The endplate degene-
ration decreases the fusion rate, even though there was no 
difference in the MC subtypes. With the presence of endplate 
degeneration, alendronate does not influence the fusion rate 
in osteoporotic patients. 
The effect of alendronate medication after the single level 
PLIF still remained unknown. The decortication technique is 
more important than medication in endplate degeneration at 
the fusion site. </p>



<p>Kim SM et al. </p>





</text></tei>