<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4785322" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Introduction: Optic neuritis leads to degeneration of </p>

<p>retinal ganglion cells whose axons form the optic 
nerve. The standard treatment is a methylprednisolone 
pulse therapy. This treatment slightly shortens the time 
of recovery but does not prevent neurodegeneration 
and persistent visual impairment. In a phase II trial 
performed in preparation of this study, we have shown 
that erythropoietin protects global retinal nerve fibre 
layer thickness (RNFLT-G) in acute optic neuritis; 
however, the preparatory trial was not powered to 
show effects on visual function. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This study examines a potentially neuroprotective 
agent in optic neuritis, a disease with clearly 
defined kinetics of neurodegeneration. 
▪ We assess potential neuroprotective effects of 
erythropoietin by combining a multitude of com-
plementary morphological and functional 
measures. 
▪ Retinal nerve fibre layer degeneration correlates 
with general brain atrophy in multiple sclerosis; 
therefore, the results of the study are meaningful 
for multiple sclerosis in general. 
▪ The dosage of erythropoietin was chosen 
according to a prior phase II trial without having 
performed a proper dose-finding study. 
▪ In order to start treatment as soon as possible, 
we do not distinguish between possible subtypes 
of optic neuritis at the time of inclusion. </p>

<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Protocol </p>

<p>ON. Although it accelerates visual recovery, it does not 
influence visual outcome, lesion length or atrophy of 
the optic nerve. 
1 In an animal model of ON, methyl-
prednisolone even increased retinal ganglion cell degen-
eration by inhibition of a neurotrophin-dependent 
pathway. 
2 Data from animal models of ON indicate that 
the downstream mechanisms of neurodegeneration 
involve 
pathways 
regulated 
by 
neurotrophins. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Erythropoietin (EPO) has shown neurotrophin-like 
properties in models of ischaemia, trauma, epilepsy and 
MS. 
4 In contrast to 'classical' neurotrophins, EPO can 
be administered systemically. In an animal model of ON, 
EPO was particularly effective when given in combin-
ation with methylprednisolone. 
5 Encouraged by these 
results, a phase II pilot trial was conducted in patients 
presenting with ON as a first clinical event indicative of 
MS. 
6 In the EPO treatment group, a significant protec-
tion of the retinal nerve fibre layer (RNFL) was deter-
mined by optical coherence tomography (OCT). </p>

<p>Clinical evidence for optic nerve neuroprotection by EPO 
Diem et al 
6 have performed a pilot randomised clinical 
trial in preparation to this phase III trial (VISION 
PROTECT, NCT00355095): 40 patients were assigned to 
receive either 33 000 international units (IU) EPO or 
placebo intravenous injections per day for 3 days in add-
ition to methylprednisolone pulse therapy. Safety moni-
toring revealed no specific issues. Thirty-seven patients 
(20/17 EPO/placebo) were analysed for the primary 
end point change in retinal nerve fibre layer thickness 
(RNFLT) according to the intention-to-treat analysis. In 
patients treated with EPO, RNFLT decreased by a mean 
of 7.5 μm at week 16 compared to a mean of 16.0 μm in 
the placebo group ( p=0.03), measured with time-
domain OCT. Decrease in retrobulbar diameter of the 
optic nerve was smaller in the EPO group ( p=0.01), 
determined by MRI. Testing of visual functions revealed 
trends towards an improved outcome after EPO treat-
ment. The trial regimen chosen in TONE has been 
adapted from VISION PROTECT, which revealed that 
the general design is feasible and the chosen outcome 
measures are adequate. </p>

<p>Risk-benefit assessment 
In general, EPO will not be administered beyond 3 days 
because neuronal damage in ON is considered to be an 
acute event. In a schizophrenia trial, 40 000 IU of EPO 
were given weekly over 3 months resulting in a need for 
bloodlettings in 8 of 39 patients. 
7 In contrast, the treat-
ment over 3 days in the pilot trial VISION PROTECT 
did not lead to any clinically relevant increases in red 
blood cell counts. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>The majority of recorded adverse events in our pilot 
study 
6 consisted of side effects associated with methyl-
prednisolone such as hot flushes, facial flushing, mood 
changes or hyperglycaemia and did not occur more fre-
quently in EPO-treated patients. Five of 40 patients com-
plained of headache during the treatment period, 4 of </p>

<p>whom had received EPO. Four serious adverse events 
were recorded throughout the study but were judged as 
unrelated to the study medication. Haemoglobin values 
showed a transient slight increase in the EPO-treated 
group after 1 week. Blood pressure after treatment with 
EPO remained stable during the treatment period and 
did not differ from values after methylprednisolone 
administration alone. Possible additional side effects-
although not reported in the pilot study-include 
increases in red blood cell and thrombocyte counts, ele-
vations of blood pressure and thromboembolic compli-
cations. 
8 Since the risk of these events might especially 
be increased if EPO is combined with methylpredniso-
lone, we exclude patients with vascular risk factors. 
Other exclusion criteria of our study such as history of 
malignancy or epilepsy are also explained by the spec-
trum of undesired effects of EPO. 
8 Professional or semi-
professional sports activities belong to the exclusion 
criteria because EPO has been misused for doping, espe-
cially to enhance endurance of elite cyclists. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Additionally, pure red cell aplasia has been described as 
a rare but potentially fatal side effect of EPO. It is 
caused by neutralising antibodies induced by repetitive 
exposure to subcutaneous but eventually also intraven-
ous EPO formulations. 
10 For this reason, we included 
monitoring of antibodies against EPO into our safety 
assessment. </p>

<p>METHODS AND ANALYSIS 
Study design 
The study is designed as a prospective, double-blind, 
randomised controlled trial with participating depart-
ments located at German University Medical Centers. 
The trial has two parallel arms, one with an injection of 
33 000 IU human recombinant EPO per day for 3 con-
secutive days, and the other with placebo administered 
in an equal fashion. In both arms, patients will receive 
1000 mg of methylprednisolone intravenously per day 
for 3 days according to the standard of care. 
11 A 1:1 allo-
cation ratio is applied to ensure equally sized treatment 
groups. The trial is registered at http://www. 
clinicaltrials.gov (NCT01962571) and http://www. 
germanctr.de (DRKS00005298). </p>

<p>Primary objective 
Determination of the efficacy of EPO compared to 
placebo given as add-on to methylprednisolone (stand-
ard of care) as assessed by measurements of global 
RNFLT-G and low-contrast visual acuity (LCVA) in the 
affected eye 6 months after randomisation. </p>

<p>Setting 
Participating trial sites are the University Medical 
Centers in Berlin, Bonn, Düsseldorf, Erlangen, Essen, 
Freiburg, Göttingen, Hamburg, Hannover, Heidelberg, 
Mainz, Munich (LMU/TUM) and Tübingen. </p>



<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Population 
Patients with acute ON are going to be enrolled in this 
trial. For diagnosis of ON, the recent consensus diagnos-
tic flow chart published by Petzold et al 
12 is followed. 
Patients are only eligible if they provide written 
informed consent and if the investigator has verified 
that they meet all of the inclusion criteria and none of 
the exclusion criteria. Patients of both genders will be 
enrolled as the results of the preclinical and clinical 
studies did not indicate any gender effect on the trial 
treatment in terms of efficacy and safety. Inclusion and 
exclusion criteria are shown in box 1. </p>

<p>Treatment 
Experimental intervention 
A total of 33 000 IU human recombinant EPO given as a 
bolus injection (epoetin alfa, Hexal AG, Holzkirchen, 
Germany) per day intravenously on days 1, 2 and 3 in 
addition to standard methylprednisolone (1000 mg/day 
intravenously on days 1, 2 and 3). </p>

<p>Control intervention 
Placebo (0.9% saline) administered intravenously on 
days 1, 2 and 3 in addition to standard methylpredniso-
lone (1000 mg/day intravenously on days 1, 2 and 3). </p>

<p>Visit schedule 
Following randomisation and initiation of trial treatment 
(visit 1), the patient should be admitted to the ward at 
the trial site from days 1 to 3. If this is not possible for 
logistical reasons, assessments may be carried out on an 
outpatient basis at the discretion of the investigator. The 
following visits at weeks 1, 4, 16 and 26 and month 24 
will be performed in the outpatient setting. Table 1 
shows the schedule of visits. In case of pregnancy, 
regular follow-up visits will be performed if possible. If 
pregnancy occurs during the first 3 months after study 
medication, the treating gynaecologist will be informed 
to decide about an intensified pregnancy observation. </p>

<p>Outcome measures 
Primary end point 
TONE has two primary end points, which will be tested 
in a hierarchical manner. The first is the mean (global) 
RNFLT of all retinal segments along a circle of 12°, that 
is, 3.5 mm diameter (RNFLT-G-12) of the fellow eye at 
baseline minus RNFLT-G-12 of the affected eye 6 months 
after randomisation. 
13 RNFLT became a standard 
measure for neurodegeneration over the recent 
years. 
13 14 Using time-domain OCT, thinning of the 
RNFL from 100 to 78 µm (means, p=0.0001) was seen in 
the majority of ON patients (74%) within 6 months. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>RNFLT decline reaches a plateau around 4 months. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Several investigations have established that RNFLT meas-
urement by OCT is a robust tool for the quantification 
of optic nerve axons and the degree of optic nerve 
atrophy, especially after ON. 
16-19 The recent introduc-
tion of the spectral-domain OCT technique allows for </p>

<p>more precise quantification of the RNFL, in particular 
using the Spectralis system which incorporates eye track-
ing for better retest variability (variation coefficient of 
0.6% 
20 compared with 5% using time-domain OCT). </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>RNFLT will be determined along a ring of 3.5 mm 
(approximately 12°) diameter concentrically centred on 
the Bruch's membrane opening at the optic disc using 
the 
Spectralis 
OCT 
(Heidelberg 
Engineering, 
Heidelberg, Germany). RNFLT has been employed as a 
primary outcome measure in VISION PROTECT and in 
ongoing trials NCT01451593 and NCT01073813 and has 
been recommended as such in the literature. </p>

<p>13 17 </p>

<p>The second primary outcome measure is LCVA in 
the affected eye 6 months after randomisation. While 
high-contrast visual acuity (HCVA) recovers well after 
ON, 
11 LCVA is most likely to remain subnormal: 22% 
of cases with fully recovered HCVA revealed subnormal 
LCVA. 
22 LCVA correlates well with health-related 
quality of life 
23 and correlates significantly with 
RNFLT 
24 in patients with MS after previous ON. LCVA 
will be recorded by 2.5% low-contrast Sloan letter 
charts. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Secondary objectives and end points 
In addition to the primary objective, seven OCT analyses 
will be performed to increase the likelihood of captur-
ing neuroprotective properties: 
1. RNFLT 
in 
the 
papillomacular 
bundle 
(RNFLT-PMB-12) fellow eye at baseline minus 
RNFLT-PMB-12 of the affected eye 6 months after 
randomisation; 
2. RNFLT in the temporal quadrant (RNFLT-T-12) 
fellow eye at baseline minus RNFLT-T-12 of the 
affected eye 6 months after randomisation; 
3. RNFLT-G-12 of the affected eye 6 months after 
randomisation; 
4. RNFLT-PMB-12 of the affected eye 6 months after 
randomisation; 
5. RNFLT-T-12 of the affected eye 6 months after 
randomisation; 
6. Total macular volume (TMV) in the fellow eye at 
baseline minus TMV of the affected eye 6 months 
after randomisation; 
7. TMV of the affected eye 6 months after 
randomisation. 
In addition to these standardised OCT parameters, 
the Bern Photographic Reading Center will perform 
further analyses of manually segmented retinal layers 
(eg, thickness of RNFL plus inner nuclear layer). 
The functional end points HCVA and contrast sensitiv-
ity will be assessed using standard Early Treatment 
Diabetic Retinopathy Study charts (ETDRS charts) and 
Mars charts, respectively. 
25 The visual field will be 
recorded on automated, static perimeters (Octopus 900 
perimeter, Haag-Streit, Köniz, Switzerland) using the 
newly 
developed 
German 
Adaptive 
Threshold 
Estimation (GATE) strategy within the entire 30°visual 
field in a (fast) threshold determining manner 
26 and </p>

<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>analysed centrally by the Center of Competence 'Vision 
Research' of the Aalen University, Germany. 
Neurological examinations will be performed at each 
visit to assess the Extended Disability Status Score 
(EDSS), an international standard neurological 
symptom severity classification system. Amplitudes and 
latencies of visual evoked potentials will be measured by 
standard electrophysiological equipment in accordance 
with the recommendation of the International Society 
for Clinical Electrophysiology. Quality of life will be 
assessed using the validated German version of 25-item 
National Eye Institute Visual Functioning Questionnaire 
(Interviewer Version). 
27 Its overall score will be analysed. 
This questionnaire proved to be sensitive to chronic eye 
disease including ON. </p>

<p>23 24 </p>

<p>In addition, relapse rates of ON and/or MS will be 
documented and analysed. Safety will be evaluated in 
terms of adverse events, serious adverse events and 
laboratory data (haemoglobin, EPO antibodies). </p>

<p>Sample size 
Sample size calculations are based on RNFLT-G-12. For the 
second primary end point LCVA, power calculations with 
the resulting sample size have been performed. The 
primary analysis will be performed applying a linear 
regression model for the primary end point (RNFLT-G-12 
of the contralateral healthy eye at baseline minus 
RNFLT-G-12 in the affected eye 6 months after randomisa-
tion) with RNFLT-G-12 of the contralateral healthy eye at 
baseline as a covariate. The resulting treatment estimate is 
identical to the treatment estimate resulting from a linear 
regression model with the same covariates, but using 
RNFLT-G-12 in the affected eye 6 months after randomisa-
tion instead as the dependent variable. Therefore, the fol-
lowing calculations based on the end point RNFLT-G-12 in 
the affected eye 6 months after randomisation are valid 
considerations for the required sample size. The sample 
size revision planned after 50 patients will use the SD of 
the primary end point. </p>

<p>Box 1 Inclusion and exclusion criteria </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria 
1. Written informed consent obtained according to international guidelines and local laws 
2. Male and female patients aged ≥18 to ≤50 years 
3. Patients with optic neuritis (ON) 
4. First symptoms of ON ≤10 days prior to the first administration of investigational product 
5. High-contrast visual acuity (HCVA) of 0.5 (decimal system) corresponding to a minimum angle of resolution (MAR) of 2.0, a logMAR 
value of 0.3, or a Snellen equivalent of 6/12 (UK notation) and 20/40 (UK notation) </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>6. Adequate optical coherence tomography (OCT) measurements available (according to quality control by Bern Photographic Reading 
Center) 
Exclusion criteria 
1. Patient without legal capacity who is unable to understand the nature, significance and consequences of the trial 
2. Simultaneous participation in another interventional trial which could interfere with this trial and/or participation in a clinical trial within 
the last 3 months before enrolment in this trial 
3. Refractive anomalies: hyperopia &gt;5 dpt, myopia &lt;−7 dpt, astigmatism &gt;3 dpt 
4. Media opacity 
5. Severe papillitis 
6. Previous ON 
7. Any other optic nerve and retinal disease 
8. Pre-existing multiple sclerosis (MS) diagnosed according to the 2005 or 2010 McDonald criteria, 
35 36 or any other neurological disease 
9. Congenital diseases (thrombophilia, phenylketonuria) 
10. Acquired diseases (autoimmune diseases, cardiovascular diseases, diabetes mellitus, uncontrolled hypertension, any malignancy, epi-
lepsy, known tuberculosis with ongoing or unknown activity, acute gastrointestinal ulceration within the past 3 months prior to random-
isation, acute viral, bacterial or fungal infection, known infection with HIV, hepatitis B virus, or hepatitis C virus, history of colitis 
ulcerosa, diverticulitis, or acute enteroanastomosis, known osteoporosis, history of thromboembolic events, elevated haemoglobin level, 
polycythaemia, any other significant illness potentially interfering with any trial assessment or trial treatment) 
11. Performing semiprofessional or professional sporting activities or physical training 
12. Pretreatment with corticosteroids in the last 30 days prior to the onset of optic neuritis 
13. Pretreatment with erythropoietin (EPO) 
14. Known or persistent abuse of medication, drugs or alcohol 
15. Active immunisation within 2 weeks prior to randomisation 
16. Significant surgery within 4 weeks prior to randomisation 
17. Blood donation or bloodletting within 4 weeks prior to screening 
18. Pretreatment with immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory agents 
19. Persons who are in a relationship of dependence/employment with the sponsor or the investigator 
20. Female patients: pregnancy, planned pregnancy within the next 3 months or lactation period 
21. Female patients: inability or unwillingness to use two effective methods of contraception (barrier methods, hormonal methods or abstin-
ence) during the initial 3 months of the study </p>



<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Table 1 Visit schedule </p>

<p>Action </p>

<p>Screening/ 
baseline day 0 
(−3 days) </p>

<p>Therapy day 
1 </p>

<p>Therapy day 
2 </p>

<p>Therapy day 
3 </p>

<p>Week 1 
(±4 days) </p>

<p>Week 4 
(±4 days) </p>

<p>Week 16 
(±4 days) </p>

<p>Week 26 
(±7 days) </p>

<p>Month 24 
(±7 days) </p>

<p>Informed consent 
X 
Demographics 
X 
Inclusion/exclusion criteria X 
Medical history 
X 
Present complaints 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
MS relapse/ON 
recurrence </p>

<p>X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Concomitant medication 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Physical examination 
X* 
X* 
X* 
Vital signs † 
X 
3X 
3X 
3X 
X 
X 
Body weight 
X* 
X* 
X* 
ECG 
X* 
X* 
Routine laboratory ‡ 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Urinalysis (if clinically 
indicated) </p>

<p>X* 
(X*) 
(X*) 
(X*) 
(X*) </p>

<p>Pregnancy test 
X* 
EPO antibodies (analysis 
in central lab) </p>

<p>X 
X </p>

<p>Aquaporin 4 antibodies 
X 
Methylprednisolone 
therapy </p>

<p>X (standard 
of care) </p>

<p>X (standard 
of care) </p>

<p>X (standard 
of care) 
EPO/placebo 
administration </p>

<p>X 
X 
X </p>

<p>AE reporting 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X § 
Neurological examination, 
EDSS ¶ </p>

<p>X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Randomisation 
X 
Refraction 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
OCT 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
LCVA 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
HCVA 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Continued </p>

<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>

<p>5 
Open Access </p>

<p>Sample size calculation for RNFLT-G-12 
In order to determine the required sample size at a 
given significance level α by means of a two-sided t test, 
it is required to specify the clinically relevant difference 
between treatment groups for which a power of 80% is 
necessary, and assumptions on the SD of the primary 
end point. We have based these assumptions on the 
available studies published so far. For healthy or 
unaffected fellow eyes, the RNFLT-G-12 ranges around 
100 μm with a SD of less than 15 μm. 
13 16 28-31 After ON, 
the following data have been published (RNFLT-G-12 in 
micrometre with mean±SD, follow-up interval): 68.7 
±18.8, 3 years after clinically isolated syndrome (CIS); </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>85±17, &gt;1 month after MS; 
16 65±17; &lt;6 months after 
CIS; </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>84±12, 12 months after CIS </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>and 83±18, 
6 months after CIS. 
13 In the ON model, EPO reduced 
retinal ganglion cell loss by 50%. 
5 Adapted to the 
RNFLT-G-12, this effect would result in about 10 μm 
RNFLT-G-12 difference which is in exact agreement with 
the effect size observed in VISION PROTECT. 
6 These 
investigations are the basis of our assumptions: For 
patients with ON, a thinning of around 20% (15% to 
25%) can be assumed in the placebo group. The abso-
lute values in the cited studies ranged from 11 to 26 μm. 
In view of this range, a difference of 10 μm between 
treatment groups is considered to be clinically relevant. 
Our sample size calculation is based on the assumptions 
mentioned above with an SD of 17 μm and a clinically 
relevant difference between treatment groups (δ) of 
10 μm with an α of 5% and a power of 80%. No adjust-
ment for multiple testing (two primary end points) is 
necessary, as we are applying a hierarchical testing pro-
cedure. The resulting sample size is 47 per group and 
94 patients in total, based on the two-sided t test. Since 
the possibility of a proportion (5%) of non-evaluable 
patients must be considered, 100 patients will be 
randomised. </p>

<p>Sensitivity analysis of sample size calculation for 
RNFLT-G-12 
In the primary analysis, a regression model adjusting 
for baseline RNFLT-G-12 of the fellow eye and stratify-
ing factors (eg, study site) will be applied. Less vari-
ability and hence higher power can then be expected 
compared with the usual calculation via t test. 
Using the two-sided t test for the sample size calcula-
tion therefore provides a conservative strategy. Table 2 
provides sample size calculations for different 
scenarios. 
Table 2 displays resulting sample sizes per group 
depending on different δ, SDs and power values. First, 
we considered our assumptions of an expected differ-
ence of 10 μm with an SD of 17 μm as reasonable and 
calculated the power depending on the sample size (n, 
left table). Next, we varied the assumptions concerning 
the difference between treatment groups (middle table) 
and the SD assumptions (right table). Sample sizes per 
group are listed and denoted as n. </p>

<p>Table 1 Continued 
Action </p>

<p>Screening/ 
baseline day 0 </p>

<p>(−3 days) </p>

<p>Therapy day </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Therapy day </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Therapy day </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Week 1 
(±4 days) </p>

<p>Week 4 
(±4 days) </p>

<p>Week 16 
(±4 days) </p>

<p>Week 26 
(±7 days) </p>

<p>Month 24 
(±7 days) </p>

<p>CS </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Perimetry </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>NEI VFQ-25 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>VEP </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Routine MRI </p>

<p>X** </p>

<p>X † † </p>

<p>(X) </p>

<p>*Test to be performed, but not recorded on CRF. 
 †CRF: only blood pressure. 
 ‡CRF: only haemoglobin (Hb). 
 §(S)AE: to be reported only if related to investigational product. 
 ¶CRF: only EDSS. 
**Can be done after baseline as per local routine. 
 † †Recommended. </p>

<p>AE, adverse event; CS, contrast sensitivity; EDSS, Extended Disability Status Score; EPO, erythropoietin; HCVA, high-contrast visual acuity; LCVA, low-contrast visual acuity; MS, multiple 
sclerosis; NEI VFQ-25, National Eye Institute Visual Functioning Questionnaire 25; OCT, optical coherence tomography; ON, optic neuritis; VEP, visual evoked potentials. </p>



<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Sample size calculations by other authors have yielded 
n=100 
32 and n=116 considering only the affected eyes 
and n=72 considering the difference in RNFLT-G-12 
between follow-up of the affected eye and baseline of 
the fellow eye. 
13 All such calculations are based on time-
domain OCT data. Spectral-domain OCT, as used in this 
trial with higher spatial resolution, is likely to provide 
greater accuracy. 
When the primary end point measurements of 50 
patients are obtained, a blinded estimate of the SD will 
be performed (total variance ignoring treatment assign-
ment). 
33 A revised sample size calculation based on the 
new SD estimation will be obtained. No practically rele-
vant differences on the nominal significance level have 
been observed in the investigations of this procedure. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Power calculations for LCVA 
For LCVA as the other primary end point, less evidence 
from published data is available so far. However, sample 
size and power calculations have been performed for 
LCVA in analogy to RNFLT-G-12. In patients with MS 
and previous ON, mean LCVA &gt;3 months after onset of 
ON was 11.4 letters (SD 10.6) compared with 18.0 (SD 
9.6) in MS non-ON eyes and 24.8 (SD 7.4) in healthy 
controls. 
24 Median LCVA values of 15 in MS ON eyes, 24 
in MS non-ON eyes and 32 in healthy controls were 
reported in another publication. 
16 With 47 patients per 
arm, 80% power is achieved with an assumed SD of 10.6 
for a group difference of 6.2, corresponding to an 
expected LCVA of 11.4+6.2=17.6 in the EPO arm. 
Similarly, 47 patients per arm provide 70% power for δ 
of 5.5 and expected LCVA of 16.9 in the EPO arm. 
Therefore, the proposed sample size based on 
RNFLT-G-12 provides sufficient power for the second 
primary outcome as well. </p>

<p>Randomisation and blinding 
Blinding 
The study medication will be prepared in a non-blinded 
fashion by the pharmacy staff. The investigator who will 
remain blinded to the patient's assigned treatment 
group will forward a copy of the completed randomisa-
tion form to the pharmacist. By means of a randomisa-
tion list provided by the sponsor, the pharmacist will </p>

<p>prepare the investigational product (verum or placebo) 
according to the randomisation algorithm and will docu-
ment the corresponding patient number. </p>

<p>Randomisation methodology 
To allow for flexible randomisation independent of 
office hours, randomisation will be performed by using 
sealed envelopes provided by the sponsor, which are 
kept at the clinical trial sites. The randomisation code 
will be generated by the Clinical Trials Unit, Medical 
Center-University of Freiburg. Randomisation will be 
performed stratified by trial site, in blocks of variable 
size in a ratio of 1:1. Block size will be documented sep-
arately and will not be disclosed to the sites. The ran-
domisation code will be produced by validated 
programmes based on the Statistical Analysis System 
(<rs type="software">SAS</rs>). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
A detailed statistical analysis plan will be prepared. A 
blind review of the data will be performed after the end 
of the planned follow-up period without looking at the 
randomised treatment for each patient. If the statistical 
analysis plan contains any changes to the analyses out-
lined in the trial protocol, they will be marked as such, 
and reasons for amendments will be given. All statistical 
programming for analysis will be performed with the 
<rs type="software">SAS</rs>. </p>

<p>Definition of populations included in the analyses 
The primary efficacy analysis will be conducted accord-
ing to the intention-to-treat principle and will therefore 
be based on the full analysis set. It preserves the treat-
ment allocation provided by randomisation and will be 
as close as possible to the intention-to-treat ideal of 
including all randomised patients. Patients without any 
postrandomisation data will be excluded from the full 
analysis set. For patients with missing data for the 
primary end points, the last available outcome measure-
ment will be used for the calculation of the primary end 
point. 
The per-protocol population is a subset of the full ana-
lysis set and is defined as the group of patients who 
underwent the examinations required for the assessment </p>

<p>Table 2 Sample size calculations for different scenarios </p>

<p>n 
δ 
SD 
α 
Power 
n 
δ 
SD 
α 
Power 
n 
δ 
SD 
α 
Power </p>

<p>20 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.442 
72 
8 
17 
0.05 
0.801 
28 
10 
13 
0.05 
0.807 
30 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.610 
47 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.806 
32 
10 
14 
0.05 
0.803 
40 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.738 
33 
12 
17 
0.05 
0.806 
37 
10 
15 
0.05 
0.808 
50 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.830 
25 
14 
17 
0.05 
0.814 
42 
10 
16 
0.05 
0.808 
60 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.892 
19 
16 
17 
0.05 
0.806 
47 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.806 
70 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.933 
16 
18 
17 
0.05 
0.826 
52 
10 
18 
0.05 
0.801 
80 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.959 
13 
20 
17 
0.05 
0.821 
58 
10 
19 
0.05 
0.802 
90 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.975 
11 
22 
17 
0.05 
0.823 
64 
10 
20 
0.05 
0.801 
100 
10 
17 
0.05 
0.985 
9 
24 
17 
0.05 
0.803 
71 
10 
21 
0.05 
0.804 </p>

<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>of the end points at all times. Efficacy analyses will be 
performed in the per-protocol population for a sensitiv-
ity analysis. During the blind review of the data, it will be 
decided which patients belong to the per-protocol 
population. 
Safety analyses will be performed in the safety popula-
tion. Patients in the safety population are analysed as 
belonging to the treatment arm defined by treatment 
received. Patients are included in the respective treat-
ment arm, if they received at least one dose of trial 
treatment. </p>

<p>Primary end point 
As this study has two primary end points, a hierarchical 
testing procedure will be applied in order to preserve 
the type I error α=5%. RNFLT-G-12 will be tested first. 
Only in case a significant difference between treatment 
groups can be demonstrated, the test procedure for the 
end point LCVA will be carried out. To formalise the 
statistical approach, the following notation is used: 
τ EPO −τ PLA : RNFLT-G-12 difference after 6 months 
between EPO group and placebo group 
θ EPO −θ PLA : LCVA difference after 6 months between 
EPO group and placebo group. 
The following two null hypotheses are tested hierarch-
ically at 5% level: 
1. H 0 : τ EPO −τ PLA =0 vs H 1 : τ EPO −τ PLA ≠0, 
2. H 0 : θ EPO −θ PLA =0 vs H 1 : θ EPO −θ PLA ≠0. 
For both primary end points, the hypothesis will be 
tested within a linear regression model, using the 
outcome after 26 weeks as the dependent variable, and 
with treatment assignment, study site and baseline meas-
urement (RNFLT-G-12 and LCVA, respectively) constitut-
ing independent variables (CPMP/EWP/2863/99). 
RNFLT baseline measurements of the affected eye will 
be subject to additional variation caused by swelling of 
the optic disc. Therefore, baseline RNFLT-G-12 measure-
ments of the fellow eye will be used instead, as they are 
an adequate covariate to reduce variation of the treat-
ment effect estimate. The definition of the first primary 
end point in the linear regression model is RNFLT-G-12 
of the contralateral healthy eye at baseline minus 
RNFLT-G-12 in the affected eye 6 months after random-
isation. The resulting treatment estimate from this 
model is identical (apart from the sign) to the treatment 
estimate resulting from a linear regression model with 
the same covariates, but using RNFLT-G-12 in the 
affected eye 6 months after randomisation instead as the 
dependent variable. Within the linear regression model, 
the treatment effect will be estimated and presented 
with a two-sided 95% CI, and a two-sided test of the 
treatment difference will be performed at the 5% signifi-
cance level. 
For patients with missing data for the primary end 
points, the last available outcome measurement will be 
used for the calculation of the primary end point. This 
last-observation-carried-forward strategy seems reason-
able, as RNFLT deteriorates in the course of time and </p>

<p>95% of the expected RNFLT loss occurs at a mean of 
3 months after the onset of symptoms. 
13 Rates of adverse 
events leading to early termination of treatment are 
expected to be very low because study medication will 
only be given from days 1 to 3 of the trial. VISION 
PROTECT had no drop-outs due to adverse events or 
serious adverse events. 
6 As observations after 3 months 
can be expected to be similar to observations after 
6 months, it can be assumed that this procedure does 
not notably affect variance estimation. Sensitivity ana-
lyses will be conducted by using multiple imputation 
methods. The censoring distributions (time to drop-out) 
will be compared for the randomised treatment groups. 
Reasons for drop-out will be explored. </p>

<p>Secondary end points of efficacy 
The secondary end points will be analysed as the 
dependent variable in appropriate regression models. 
MS and ON relapse rates will be estimated by the 
Kaplan-Meier method, and Cox proportional hazards 
regression models will be applied. </p>

<p>Safety parameters 
All adverse events will be listed by trial site and patient and 
displayed in summary tables. The total number of adverse 
events, the minimum, maximum and mean number of 
adverse events per patient, the total number of follow-up 
days (number of days in the observation period), the 
number of adverse events per follow-up day (total number 
of adverse events divided by the total by the number of 
follow-up days), the number of patients who had at least 
one adverse event and the number of patients who 
stopped treatment due to adverse events will be given. </p>

<p>Interim analysis 
An interim analysis is planned for the time point when 
50 patients have been randomised and followed up for 
6 months. The interim report will describe patient 
recruitment, treatment compliance as well as safety for 
the patients in this period. Only blinded analyses will be 
conducted in the interim analysis, since no major safety 
problems are expected. 
Additionally, a blinded estimate of the SD of the 
primary end point will be calculated (total variance ignor-
ing treatment assignment). 
33 A revised sample size calcu-
lation based on the new SD estimation will be performed. 
The results of the interim analysis will be reported only to 
the independent data monitoring committee (DMC). 
The DMC will give advice to the coordinating investiga-
tors concerning the further conduct of the trial. </p>

<p>Data monitoring committee 
An independent DMC has been established. The func-
tion of the DMC is to monitor the course of the study 
and if necessary to give a recommendation to the coord-
inating investigator and sponsor of the trial for discon-
tinuation, modification or continuation of the study. </p>



<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Furthermore, the DMC may assist in the preparation of 
Development Safety Update Reports. </p>

<p>Study progress 
The recruitment period had started in September 2014 
with opening of first study centre. In March 2015, the 
last of the currently running 13 study centres was initia-
lised. As of 5 February 2016, we have included a total of 
51 patients. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
ON is currently not effectively treated because immuno-
therapies available so far have only limited neuroprotec-
tive properties. ON offers several advantages for testing 
neuroprotective agents as it represents a homogenous 
disease with rapid and predictable neurodegeneration. 
OCT allows for imaging of the proximal axon fibres of 
retinal ganglion cells, a subpopulation of central 
nervous system neurons, without the presence of con-
founding myelin sheaths. Additionally, visual dysfunction 
during and after ON can be precisely characterised by 
functional and electrophysiological measurements. This 
interdisciplinary study represents a conjoined effort of 
neurologists and ophthalmologists and is designed as a 
prospective, double-blind randomised clinical trial con-
ducted in different German University Medical Centers. 
It substantiates a recent pilot trial by R Diem, which 
showed a neuroprotective effect for EPO in ON. 
6 A posi-
tive outcome of TONE would not only improve the treat-
ment for ON but also have implications on therapy 
development in MS, since RNFL atrophy is a surrogate 
marker for neuronal degeneration in MS 
16 and corre-
lates with general brain atrophy. </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Neurology, Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, 
Germany </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Eye Center, Medical Center-University of Freiburg, Freiburg im Breisgau, 
Germany </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Ophthalmology, Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, 
Germany </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Department of Neurology and Neuroscience, Medical Center-University of 
Freiburg, Freiburg im Breisgau, Germany </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Clinic for Ophthalmology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Clinic for Neurology, Hannover Medical School, Hannover, Germany </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Department of Neurology, University Hospital Erlangen, Erlangen, Germany </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Department of Ophthalmology, University Hospital Erlangen, Erlangen, 
Germany </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Department of Neurology, Medical faculty, Heinrich Heine University, 
Düsseldorf, Germany </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Department of Ophthalmology, University Medical Center Hamburg-
Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Department of Ophthalmology, Medical Faculty, Heinrich Heine University, 
Düsseldorf, Germany </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>University Eye Hospital Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Department of Ophthalmology, University Hospital Munich LMU, Munich, 
Germany </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Department of Neurology, University Hospital Munich, Munich, Germany </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Department of Neurology, University Medical Center Göttingen, Göttingen, 
Germany </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Department of Ophthalmology, University Medical Center Göttingen, 
Göttingen, Germany </p>

<p>17 Clinical Trials Unit, Medical Center-University of Freiburg, Freiburg im 
Breisgau, Germany 
18 Competence Center "Vision Research", Study Course Ophthalmological 
Optics, Faculty of Optics and Mechatronics, University of Applied Sciences, 
Aalen, Germany 
19 Medical Service Center PD Dr. Volkmann and Colleges, Karlsruhe, Germany 
20 Department of Neurology, University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, 
Hamburg, Germany 
21 Center for Ophthalmology, Institute for Ophthalmic Research, University of 
Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany 
22 Department of Ophthalmology, Bern Photographic Reading Center, 
University Hospital and University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank Professor Bernhard Hemmer, 
Professor Danilo Fliser and Dr Thomas Bruckner, the members of the Data 
Monitoring Committee as well as Professor Hartmut Wekerle, Professor 
Wolfgang Brück and Professor Marius Üffing, the members of the Scientific 
Advisory Board. They acknowledge the support by the Pharmacy (PD Dr Hug) 
and the Clinical Trials Unit of the Medical Center-University of Freiburg, 
VISUS GmbH (Mr Moritz Fanti), Haag-Streit Deutschland (Mr Theurer) and 
Heidelberg Engineering (Dr Nahen, formerly Mr Lukas). Last but not least, the 
authors thank their patients and excellent study teams at each participating 
site. </p>

<p>Contributors WAL is coordinating investigator of the ophthalmological 
centres. He designed the trial and conducted it. RD is coordinating 
investigator of the neurological centres, co-designed and co-conducted the 
trial. Also, she conducted the pilot trial VISION PROTECT and assessed the 
preclinical data. GI participated in the design of the study, was responsible for 
the randomisation and performed the statistical analysis. BG and JM 
coordinate the trial and have been involved in drafting this publication. All 
other coauthors evaluated the feasibility of the TONE trial at their site, 
reviewed, commented and improved the study protocol and gave final 
approval of this manuscript to be published. </p>

<p>Funding This work is supported by the Federal Ministry of Education and 
Research (grant number 01KG1306). The authors also thank Freunde der 
Universitäts-Augenklinik Freiburg e.V. who made a donation to financially 
cosupport this trial. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Ethics Commission, University of Freiburg (194/14). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>





<p>Diem R, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010956. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010956 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>