<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4164721" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background/Aims: Protein disulfide isomerase (PDI) has been implicated in the </p>

<p>survival and progression of some cancer cells, by compensating for endoplasmic 
reticulum stress by upregulating the protein-folding capacity. However, its prog-
nostic role in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) has not been investi-
gated. 
Methods: We collected HCC tissues from 83 HCC patients who underwent sur-</p>

<p>gical resection for an immunohistochemical study of PDI. Overall survival (OS) 
was measured from the date of surgical resection until the date of death from any 
cause. Radiological progression was evaluated using the modified Response Eval-
uation Criteria in Solid Tumors in an independent radiological assessment. 
Results: PDI expression was found to be increased in human HCC compared to </p>

<p>adjacent nontumor tissues. Increased immunopositivity for PDI was associated 
with a high Edmondson-Steiner grade (p = 0.028). Univariate analysis of patients 
who had undergone surgical resection for HCC showed that tumor PDI upregula-
tion is a significant risk factor for poor OS (p = 0.016; hazard ratio [HR], 1.980) and 
time to progression (TTP; p = 0.007; HR, 1.971). Multivariate analyses revealed 
that high PDI expression was an independent predictor of a shorter TTP (p = 0.015; 
HR, 1.865) and poor OS (p = 0.012; HR, 2.069). 
Conclusions: Upregulated PDI expression is associated with aggressive clinico-</p>

<p>pathological features of HCC; thus, PDI might serve as an independent prognos-
tic factor and a potential therapeutic target for HCC patients. </p>

<p>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the fifth-leading 
cause of cancer-related death worldwide [1]. Curative 
resection is the primary therapeutic modality for HCC, 
except in advanced cases, but the prognosis of individ-</p>

<p>ual patients varies and several molecular markers of 
the prognosis of HCC have been identified [2]. Unfor-
tunately, few molecular markers for HCC are targetable 
by drugs and there is a pressing need to identify new 
molecular candidates to improve therapeutic strategies 
and predict the prognosis in the era of targeted an-</p>

<p>A novel prognostic factor for hepatocellular 
carcinoma: protein disulfide isomerase </p>

<p>Su Jong Yu 1,* 
, Jae-Kyung Won 2,3,4,* 
, Han Suk Ryu 4 
, Won-Mook Choi 1 
, Hyeki Cho 1 
, Eun-Ju Cho 1 
, 
Jeong-Hoon Lee 1 
, Yoon Jun Kim 1 
, Kyung-Suk Suh 5 
, Ja-June Jang 4 
, Chung Yong Kim 1 
, Hyo-Suk Lee 1 
, 
Jung-Hwan Yoon 1 
, and Kwang-Hyun Cho 2,3 </p>



<p>Yu SJ, et al. Protein disulfide isomerase for HCC </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.580 </p>

<p>ti-cancer therapy. 
Protein disulfide isomerase (PDI) is a 57-kDa dithi-
ol:disulfide oxidoreductase and molecular chaperone. 
It is one of the most abundant soluble proteins in the 
endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and plays a key role in 
maintaining cellular homeostasis by mediating oxida-
tive protein folding [3]. PDI expression is upregulated 
in some cancer types and involved in aggressive phe-
notypes of breast [4], brain [5], ovary [6], and prostate [7] 
cancers. Increasing evidence from functional studies 
indicates that PDI has an important role in tumor sur-
vival and cancer progression [3]. In human HCC cell 
lines, PDI was expressed in a hypoxia-inducible man-
ner [8]. However, the expression of PDI in human HCC 
tissues and its prognostic role in patients with HCC has 
not been determined. 
This study investigated whether PDI is expressed in 
human HCC tissues and evaluated the effect of PDI ex-
pression on the time to progression (TTP) and overall 
survival (OS) after surgical resection in patients with 
HCC. We found that PDI expression was upregulated 
in HCC samples and that high PDI expression was an 
independent predictor of a poor prognosis. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>Tissue specimens were collected from 83 patients with 
HCC resected between 2004 and 2012 at Seoul Nation-
al University Hospital (SNUH). The histopathological 
features were evaluated retrospectively from hema-
toxylin-and-eosin-stained slides, and clinical and fol-
low-up data were obtained from the medical records. 
Histological grade was scored according to the Edmon-
son-Steiner grading system [9], and pathological staging 
(pT stage) was determined according to the American 
Joint Committee on Cancer grading system (7th edi-
tion) [10]. The main clinical and pathological variables 
evaluated in this study are shown in Table 1. This study 
was conducted with the approval of the Institutional 
Review Board of SNUH, with waiver of the requirement 
for informed consent. </p>

<p>Tissue microarray construction </p>

<p>Previously stained hematoxylin and eosin slides were </p>

<p>reviewed retrospectively, and more than two representa-
tive formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded archival blocks 
were selected per case. Tissues from adjacent nontumor 
areas were also collected. The arrays were assembled 
by taking core tissue biopsies (5 mm in diameter) from 
specific locations in the existing formalin-fixed, paraf-
fin-embedded blocks (donor blocks) and re-embedding 
them in recipient paraffin blocks (tissue array blocks) 
using a trephine. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical staining </p>

<p>Immunohistochemical staining using an anti-PDI 
rabbit polyclonal antibody (Catalogue No. 2446, 1:100 
dilution, Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA) 
was performed on tissue array slides using the Ventana 
OptiView system (Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Ger-
many). </p>

<p>Evaluation of immunohistochemical staining </p>

<p>The immunohistochemical staining was analyzed inde-
pendently by two qualified pathologists. A semiquanti-
tative scoring system was used to evaluate PDI expres-
sion using both the intensity of cytoplasmic staining 
(3, strong; 2, intermediate; 1, weak) and percentage of 
positive cells (1, ≤ 25%; 2, 25% to 75%; 3, &gt; 75%). If there 
were differences in the initial evaluation, the slides 
were reviewed to achieve consensus. Cases with total 
scores of 2 to 4 and 5 to 6 were classified as the low-and 
high-expression groups, respectively. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Continuous variables were compared using Student t 
test and dichotomous variables using the chi-square 
test. Survival time was measured from the date of sur-
gical resection to the date of death or last contact. Con-
ventional clinical variables at the time of entry into the 
study and immunopositivity for PDI were analyzed to 
identify factors that influenced survival, as determined 
using the Kaplan-Meier method and compared using 
the log-rank test. Stepwise, univariate, and multivariate 
analyses were performed using the Cox proportional 
hazards model to identify factors that influenced sur-
vival. Variables found to be significantly associated with 
the outcome in the univariate analyses were included 
in the multivariate analysis. All statistical analyses were 
performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>., Armonk, </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 29, No. 5, September 2014 </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.580 </p>

<p>NY, USA), and p values &lt; 0.05 were considered to indi-
cate significance. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>PDI expression in HCC and nonneoplastic hepatic 
tissues </p>

<p>First, we investigated whether PDI expression is in-
creased in HCC compared to nontumor tissue. PDI 
protein expression was evaluated in tumor areas and 
adjacent nontumor areas in each patient in our study 
population. The immunohistochemical analysis of the 
83 HCC patients indicated that PDI expression was in-
creased in the tumor tissue of 51 cases (61.4%) compared 
to nearby nontumor tissue, whereas 11 cases (13.3%) 
showed a decrease in PDI expression compared to adja-
cent nontumor tissue (p &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Correlations between PDI expression status and 
clinicopathological variables </p>

<p>To determine the clinical significance of the PDI level 
in HCC, we assessed the correlation between PDI ex-
pression in the tumor and various clinicopathological 
variables (Table 1). Classifying the tumors into high-
and low-expression groups, high PDI expression was 
significantly correlated with a high Edmonson-Steiner 
grade (p = 0.028), but not with gender, age, etiology, 
α-fetoprotein (AFP) level, Child-Pugh class, tumor size, 
tumor multiplicity, vascular invasion, or lymph node 
metastasis (Table 1). </p>

<p>Prognostic significance of PDI expression in patients 
with HCC </p>

<p>To evaluate the prognostic significance of PDI expres-
sion, univariate analyses of TTP and OS were per-
formed. As shown in Fig. 2, the high-PDI-expression 
group had a significantly shorter TTP and poorer OS </p>

<p>Increase </p>

<p>Same </p>

<p>Decrease </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 </p>

<p>No. of patients </p>

<p>40 
50 
60 </p>

<p>PDI expression in HCC </p>

<p>(13.3%) </p>

<p>(25.3%) </p>

<p>(61.4%) </p>

<p>Figure 1. Protein disulfide isomerase (PDI) expression levels 
increased with the development of hepatocellular carcinoma 
(HCC). (A) Low expression in adjacent non-tumoral tissue 
(×100). (B) High expression in HCC tissue in the same 
patient (×100). (C) The proportion of the relative changes in 
PDI expression compared to adjacent non-tumoral tissue (p 
&lt; 0.0001). </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>



<p>Yu SJ, et al. Protein disulfide isomerase for HCC </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.580 </p>

<p>than the low-PDI-expression group (p = 0.007 and p = 
0.016, respectively). The AFP level, tumor size, and tu-
mor multiplicity also differed significantly for TTP (p = 
0.002, p = 0.001, and p = 0.025, respectively), while tumor 
size, tumor multiplicity, and Edmondson-Steiner his-
tological grade had prognostic significance for OS (p = 
0.024, p = 0.046, and p = 0.002, respectively) (Table 2). 
We performed a multivariate Cox regression analysis 
to investigate whether PDI expression was an indepen-
dent predictor of TTP and OS. PDI expression was an </p>

<p>independent predictor of tumor recurrence (p = 0.015). 
Large tumor size was also an independent predictor 
of TTP (p = 0.017) (Table 3). For OS, because histolog-
ical grade was associated with PDI expression in our 
correlation study, we included PDI expression in the 
multivariate analysis to avoid any bias caused by multi-
collinearity. Indeed, PDI expression was found to be an 
independent predictor of OS (p = 0.012) (Table 4). </p>

<p>Table 1. The correlation between PDI expression and clinicopathologic variables in this study </p>

<p>Clinicopathologic variable 
Number 
PDI high, n (%) 
PDI low, n (%) 
p value </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
71 
44 (86.3) 
27 (87.1) 
0.811 </p>

<p>Female 
12 
8 (13.7) 
4 (12.9) </p>

<p>Age, yr </p>

<p>≤ 55 
45 
27 (52.9) 
18 (56.2) 
0.768 </p>

<p>&gt; 55 
38 
24 (47.1) 
14 (43.8) </p>

<p>Etiology </p>

<p>Non-viral 
11 
9 (17.6) 
2 (6.2) 
0.190 </p>

<p>Viral 
72 
42 (82.4) 
30 (93.8) </p>

<p>AFP level, ng/mL </p>

<p>≤ 200 
45 
17 (54.8) 
28 (54.9) 
1.000 </p>

<p>&gt; 200 
38 
15 (45.2) 
23 (45.1) </p>

<p>Child-Pugh classification </p>

<p>A 
76 
47 (92.2) 
29 (90.6) 
1.000 </p>

<p>B&amp;C 
7 
4 (7.8) 
3 (9.4) </p>

<p>Tumor size, cm </p>

<p>≤ 5 
32 
22 (43.1) 
10 (31.2) 
0.279 </p>

<p>&gt; 5 
51 
29 (56.9) 
22 (68.8) </p>

<p>Tumor number </p>

<p>Single 
41 
26 (51.0) 
15 (46.9) 
0.716 </p>

<p>Multiple 
42 
25 (49.0) 
17 (53.1) </p>

<p>Edmondson grade (worst) </p>

<p>Grade 1-3 
38 
28 (56.0) 
10 (31.2) 
0.028 </p>

<p>Grade 4 
44 
22 (44.0) 
22 (68.8) </p>

<p>Vascular invasion </p>

<p>Absent 
31 
21 (41.2) 
10 (31.2) 
0.363 </p>

<p>Present 
52 
30 (58.8) 
22 (68.8) </p>

<p>Lymph node metastasis </p>

<p>Absent 
66 
41 (80.4) 
25 (78.1) 
0.803 </p>

<p>Present 
17 
10 (19.6) 
7 (21.9) </p>

<p>PDI, protein disulfide isomerase; AFP, α-fetoprotein. </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 29, No. 5, September 2014 </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.580 </p>

<p>PDI low </p>

<p>p = 0.007 
PDI high 
0 
20 
40 
60 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>Months after surgery </p>

<p>TTP rate 
OS rate </p>

<p>PDI low </p>

<p>p = 0.016 
PDI high </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>Months after surgery </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Protein disulfide isomerase (PDI) expression levels significantly associated with time to progression (TTP) and 
overall survival (OS). (A) TTP rate (p = 0.007). (B) OS rate between PDI low expression group and PDI high expression group (p 
= 0.016). </p>

<p>Table 2. Univariate analysis of time to progression and overall survival in this study population </p>

<p>Variable 
Number 
Time to progression 
Overall survival </p>

<p>HR (95% CI) 
p value 
HR (95% CI) 
p value </p>

<p>Etiology </p>

<p>Viral 
72 
0.618 (0.316-1.211) 
0.161 
0.936 (0.424-2.066) 
0.869 </p>

<p>AFP level, ng/mL </p>

<p>&gt; 200 
38 
2.089 (1.314-3.323) 
0.002 
1.540 (0.931-2.550) 
0.093 </p>

<p>Child-Pugh class </p>

<p>B&amp;C 
7 
0.795 (0.365-1.734) 
0.564 
1.679 (0.760-3.710) 
0.200 </p>

<p>Tumor size, cm </p>

<p>&gt; 5 
51 
2.403 (1.466-3.939) 
0.001 
1.840 (1.084-3.123) 
0.024 </p>

<p>Tumor multiplicity </p>

<p>Multiple 
42 
1.668 (1.066-2.612) 
0.025 
1.675 (1.008-2.782) 
0.046 </p>

<p>Histologic grade </p>

<p>Grade 4 
44 
1.050 (0.671-1.643) 
0.830 
2.368 (1.379-4.064) 
0.002 </p>

<p>Vascular invasion </p>

<p>Present 
52 
1.556 (0.976-2.749) 
0.063 
1.451 (0.859-2.449) 
0.164 </p>

<p>Lymph node metastasis </p>

<p>Present 
5 
1.206 (0.484-3.003) 
0.687 
1.868 (0.740-4.718) 
0.186 </p>

<p>PDI expression </p>

<p>High 
32 
1.971 (1.203-3.230) 
0.007 
1.980 (1.134-3.457) 
0.016 </p>

<p>HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; AFP, α-fetoprotein; PDI, protein disulfide isomerase. </p>



<p>Yu SJ, et al. Protein disulfide isomerase for HCC </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.580 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study found that the expression of PDI was in-
creased in HCC compared to nontumor tissue and that 
increased expression was associated with the aggressive 
clinicopathological features of HCC. Moreover, up-
regulated PDI expression in HCC tissues was an inde-
pendent risk factor for a poor OS and shorter TTP in 
patients with HCC. This is the first report that the level 
of PDI expression adversely affects the OS and pro-</p>

<p>gression of HCC patients who have undergone surgical 
resection. 
One can argue that the increased PDI level is a by-
product of cancer, such as the cellular environment, 
disease progression status, or degree of tumor differ-
entiation. However, recent studies indicate that PDI is 
important for tumor survival and progression, empha-
sizing its role as a tumor-promoting factor [5,11-13]. PDI 
expression seems to be associated with protection of 
cancer cells from proteotoxic stress and hypoxic dam-
age. Hypoxia can induce the accumulation of unfolded 
or misfolded proteins and lead to ER-stress-induced 
cell death [14]. Altered ER function results in ER stress 
and subsequent activation of the unfolded protein 
response (UPR), an important ER stress response that 
protects the cell by removing unfolded or misfolded 
proteins [15]. PDI proteins are key molecules in the 
UPR. Many ER-stress-response chaperones have PDI 
activity or PDI-like domains; therefore, blocking this 
activity might increase ER stress and enhance apoptosis 
[16]. 
Locally recurrent HCC nodules that survive hypoxic 
insults after transarterial chemoembolization some-
times have significantly shorter doubling times than 
those in neighboring nodules [17]. Moreover, HCC 
sometimes undergoes an infiltrating rather than a 
mass-forming growth pattern; these advanced in-
filtrative HCCs seldom show hypervascularity, grow 
more rapidly, and have a poorer prognosis than the 
mass-forming hypervascular types. These findings sug-
gest that hypoxia activates the signals that allow HCC 
cells to survive and proliferate [18] and that PDI con-
tributes to the survival and progression of these cancer 
cells. This explains the correlation between PDI expres-
sion and an aggressive cancer phenotype. 
The expression of PDI family proteins, an import-
ant arm of the UPR, correlates with cancer invasion, 
metastasis, and drug resistance in various tumor types, 
including melanomas and gliomas [5,11]. UPR, a pro-
survival pathway that is activated during hypoxia, which 
is a hallmark of solid tumors [19], is also an important 
mediator of metastasis in human cervical cancer [20]. 
UPR promoted the polarization of tumor-infiltrating 
myeloid cells toward an inflammatory/immunosup-
pressive phenotype, leading to T-cell dysfunction and, 
ultimately, to the evasion of tumor cells from immuno-</p>

<p>Table 3. Multivariate analysis of time to progression in this </p>

<p>study population </p>

<p>Variable 
Time to progression </p>

<p>HR (95% CI) 
p value </p>

<p>AFP level, ng/mL </p>

<p>&gt; 200 
1.440 (0.860-2.409) 
0.166 </p>

<p>Tumor size, cm </p>

<p>&gt; 5 
1.995 (1.130-3.522) 
0.017 </p>

<p>Tumor multiplicity </p>

<p>Multiple 
1.567 (0.990-2.480) 
0.055 </p>

<p>Vascular invasion </p>

<p>Present 
1.122 (0.681-1.847) 
0.651 </p>

<p>PDI expression </p>

<p>High 
1.865 (1.131-3.075) 
0.015 </p>

<p>HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; AFP, α-fetoprotein; 
PDI, protein disulfide isomerase. </p>

<p>Table 4. Multivariate analysis of overall survival in this </p>

<p>study population </p>

<p>Variable 
Overall survival </p>

<p>HR (95% CI) 
p value </p>

<p>AFP level, ng/mL </p>

<p>&gt; 200 
1.100 (0.620-1.952) 
0.745 </p>

<p>Tumor size, cm </p>

<p>&gt; 5 
1.595 (0.876-2.904) 
0.126 </p>

<p>Tumor multiplicity </p>

<p>Multiple 
1.494 (0.898-2.485) 
0.122 </p>

<p>PDI expression </p>

<p>High 
2.069 (1.172-3.651) 
0.012 </p>

<p>HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; AFP, α-fetoprotein; 
PDI, protein disulfide isomerase. </p>



<p>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine Vol. 29, No. 5, September 2014 </p>

<p>www.kjim.org </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3904/kjim.2014.29.5.580 </p>

<p>surveillance [21]. Therefore, we postulate that intratu-
moral hypoxia induces PDI expression as a component 
of the UPR, which leads to tumor evasion from immu-
nosurveillance via T-cell dysfunction. The escape from 
immunosurveillance contributes to cancer recurrence 
or metastasis [22]. 
In addition, PDI was reported to be associated with 
resistance to the growth-inhibitory effects of transform-
ing growth factor-β1 (TGF-β1), which frequently occurs 
in cancer cells. TGF-β1 downregulates PDI microRNA 
in TGF-β1-sensitive cells, but not in cells insensitive to 
the growth inhibitory effects of TGF-β1 [12]. Moreover, 
PDI protects cancer cells from apoptosis. In melanoma, 
the inhibition of PDI activity using bacitracin enhanced 
apoptosis triggered by fenretinide or velcade [13]. Al-
though PDI expression was reported to be increased 
in the stressful microenvironment of human HCC cell 
lines and in the serum of HCC patients [23,24], its func-
tional implications in HCC have not been elucidated 
fully. 
Previously, we observed that PDI was expressed in a 
human HCC cell line under hypoxic conditions. This 
suggests that PDI participates in the UPR to compen-
sate for the ER stress that occurs under innate intratu-
moral hypoxic conditions [8]. Indeed, the expression 
of PDI was increased in HCC compared to nontumor 
tissue, and the high PDI expression in HCC tissue ad-
versely affected the clinical outcome of HCC patients 
following surgical resection in our series. 
The development of robust PDI activity assays has 
led to the recent discovery of a series of novel PDI in-
hibitors, such as the irreversible inhibitors PACMA 
31, 16F16, and RB-11-ca, and the reversible inhibitors 
juniferdin and rutin [3]. Tumor cells require higher lev-
els of PDI to cope with marked ER stress and a global 
increase in protein synthesis to sustain rapid prolifera-
tion. Increased protein synthesis leads to an abundance 
of misfolded proteins in the ER that must be refolded 
by PDI. As such, tumor cells are more vulnerable to PDI 
inhibition than are normal cells. Therefore, PDI is an 
important target in the treatment of cancers. 
Together, these findings suggest that PDI expression 
is upregulated in HCC, tissues and is associated with 
the aggressive histological features of HCC. More im-
portantly, upregulated PDI expression in patients with 
HCC is predictive of poor OS after surgical resection </p>

<p>via frequent recurrence. Therefore, PDI can serve as a 
novel independent prognostic factor and may be a use-
ful therapeutic target in patients with HCC. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article 
was reported. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by National Research Foun-
dation of Korea grants funded by the Ministry of 
Science, ICT and Future Planning (2010-0017662 and 
2013M3A9A7046303). It was also supported by grants 
from the SNUH Research Fund (No. 04-2011-0660) and 
the Liver Research Foundation of Korea. </p>



<p>KEY MESSAGE </p>

<p>1. The expression of protein disulfide isomerase 
(PDI) was increased in hepatocellular carcinoma 
(HCC) tissues compared to adjacent nontumor 
tissues. 
2. The level of PDI expression was significantly as-
sociated with the Edmondson-Steiner grade. 
3. Univariate and multivariate analyses revealed 
that high PDI expression was an independent 
predictor of a shorter time to progression and 
poorer overall survival of HCC patients who un-
derwent surgical resection. </p>



<p>Yu SJ, et al. Protein disulfide isomerase for HCC </p>



</text></tei>