<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4481556" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Cellular and cardiovascular incidents are 
important aspects of ischemic injuries 
observed in stroke and other related cere-
brovascular disorders. 
1 Although oxygen 
deprivation at cellular level is associated 
with vascular occlusion and cyanide neu-
rotoxicity (mitochondrial poisoning), the 
symptoms exhibited in the patients differ to a certain ex-
tent. 
2,3 In vascular occlusion, the symptoms are usually rapid 
and severe; in most cases involving partial or full paralysis 
while cyanide toxicity causes neurological disorders (degen-
erative) over aperiod of time, depending on the dosage and </p>

<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Background: Recent studies have shown that endothelial proliferation and angiogenic response are char-
acteristic of degenerative events, such that the magnitude of endothelial activation is reflective of the 
progression of neurodegeneration. 
Purpose: This study sets out to, compare, the degenerative changes seen in the parietal cortex (PC) and 
periventricular zone (PVZ) after cyanide toxicity or vascular occlusion. 
Methods: Global vascular occlusion (VO) and cyanide toxicity (CN) were induced in separate sets of male 
adult wistar rats for 10 days (treatment phase). Subsequently, the treatment was discontinued for another 
10 days (withdrawal phase) (CN-I and VO-I). A separate group of control was maintained for 10 days and 
received normal saline for this duration. The animals were euthanized at day 10 (treatment and control) 
and day 20 (withdrawal) after which the tissue was processed for antigen retrieval immunohistochemis-
try to demonstrate; H&amp;E (general histology) CD31/PECAM 1(endothelial proliferation), CD45 (monocyte/ 
phagocyte), GFAP (glia), NSE (neuron), Ki-67 (cell proliferation) and NF (neurofilament). Total cell count, 
immunopositive cell counts, arterial wall thickness and lumen width were determined and plotted using 
ANOVA with significance set at P&lt;0.05*. 
Result: We observed an increase in endothelial proliferation (↑CD31), glia activation and a decrease in 
neuron count in vascular occlusion and cyanide toxicity after the treatment phase (degeneration). The 
neuron count increased (↑NSE) after withdrawal of cyanide treatment and vascular occlusion and was 
accompanied by a corresponding decrease in endothelial and glia activation (↓CD31/GFAP). Degenerative 
changes were more prominent in cyanide toxicity when compared with vascular occlusion. The increase in 
CD45 expression coupled with a reduced CD31/GFAP after the withdrawal phase was evident of vascular 
remodeling and neurosurvival. 
Conclusion: We conclude that neuronal degeneration in cyanide toxicity or vascular occlusion is de-
pendent on an increase in endothelial proliferation (↑CD31), glia activation (↑GFAP) and a decrease in 
monocyte expression (↓CD45); representing a pro-inflammatory response. Furthermore, cyanide toxicity 
induced more prominent degenerative changes when compared with the vascular occlusion due to a 
higher CD31/GFAP expression. Subsequent withdrawal of the ischemia facilitated a reduction in GFAP/ 
CD31 with a corresponding increase in monocytes (↑CD45) for vascular remodeling and neurosurvival. 
The VO-I showed a significant increase in vascular remodelling than the CN-I due to a more significant 
increase in monocytic expression (CD45) after the withdrawal of the occlusion. Generally, we found that 
degeneration was prominent in the parietal cortex and less in the periventricular zone for both forms 
of ischemia. 
www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>tributes blood to the neural tissue through its terminal "end 
arteries". 
7,8 The end arteries exist at the capillary level of ce-
rebral circulation and are single cell thick with an underly-
ing endothelium forming a structural part of the blood brain 
barrier (BBB) unit 
5,8 . Ultramicroscopic. 
5,8 Ultramicroscopic 
analysis of the structure of a single BBB unit reveals that the 
endothelial cells of the end arteries are linked via intercellular 
junctions to the ependymal astrocytes and tantacytes occupy-
ing the immediate surroundings of the arteries. 
9 arteryies. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>The matrix rich endothelium (charged molecules), surround-
ing astrocytes, neurons and blood cellsformthe structural, 
physiological and electrical barrier that controls the bi-direc-
tional movement of molecules across the blood-brain inter-
phase. 
4 The significance of such bi-directional flow has been 
described as regulatory as it is involved in homeostatic ef-
ficiency of regional circulation and metabolism in the central 
nervous system (CNS). </p>

<p>4,10 </p>

<p>The importance of the endothelium as an integral part of the 
BBB has been emphasized. Previous studies have shown, using 
high magnification microscopy, that endothelial cells provide 
structural and physiological barrier at the interphase of neu-
ron/glia and the circulating blood; such that toxins, nutrients, 
microbes, viruses and metabolitesin the blood come in contact 
with the endothelium before the cells of the nervous system. </p>

<p>11,8 </p>

<p>Proliferative or degenerative changes in the endothelium have 
been linked with the progression of most degenerative dis-
eases. This may involve changes in endothelial cells, adhesion 
molecules and matrix and is often the cause in brain infections, 
chemotoxicity and inflammation. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Recent studies have shown that bi-directional signals across 
the BBB actively modulate the pathophysiological process 
of degeneration in stroke, chemotoxicity and acute brain in-
juries. 
4,11,13 An example of such cellular signal is the "danger 
associated molecular pattern (DAMP)" associated with the re-
lease of chemokines and cytokines into the blood after trau-
matic brain injury. As a result, a more robust immune response, 
resulting in inflammation is activated. 
13,14 Interestingly, other 
studies have shown that the bi-directional communication be-
tween the ischemic or inflamed nervous system and the cells 
of the endothelium regulate the DAMP signal, and thus the 
progression of brain injuries. </p>

<p>10,15,16 </p>

<p>Differential cellular mechanisms are involved in the progression 
of endothelial and neural changes induced by chemotoxicity 
and vascular occlusion. 
17-20 Although acommon factor inthe 
progression of these models is oxidative stress, the pattern of 
endothelial/angiogenic response and how it affects the progres-
sion of degeneration and neurosurvival is yet to be elucidated. 
Generally, the induced oxidative stress has been described as 
a trigger of neuronal cell death, endothelial proliferation, glia 
activation, inflammation and in some cases proliferation in 
specific brain regions. 
15,16,21-24 In addition, our previous findings 
of glia activation, neuronal degeneration and proliferation in-
duced by differential oxidative stress has revealed that regional 
differences exists in stress response elicited in the brain; specifi-
cally across the plastic and non-plastic brain regions. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Consequently, we investigated the effects of cyanide toxicity and 
vascular occlusion on the endothelial (CD31/CD45), neuron (NSE) 
and glia (GFAP) cells using Immunohistochemistryand stereology 
in cortical slices. We compared the effect of cyanide toxicity and </p>

<p>vascular occlusion in the plastic periventricular zone (PVZ) and 
non-plastic parietal cortex (PC) in order to detect either prolifera-
tion (Ki-67) or degeneration (NF) relative to endothelial changes 
(CD31/CD45) after the treatment and withdrawal phases. Our 
findings demonstrate that endothelial changes are linked with 
glia activation, neuronal degeneration and proliferation. In addi-
tion, the observed changes vary for cyanide toxicity and vascular 
occlusion after the treatment and withdrawal periods. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>N = 30 male adult Wistar rats, weighing between (250-280 
gms) were used for this study. A group of n = 12 rats were 
treated with orally administered potassium cyanide (KCN) (30 
mg/Kg body weight (BW) for 10 days using a gavage (CN). </p>

<p>26-28 </p>

<p>A separate set of n = 12 animals was subjected to transient 
occlusion of carotid arteries, basilar artery and brachiocephalic 
vein using an elastic neck cuff. This was accompanied by a re-
duction of blood pressure above the neck cuff to 30 mmHg 
(VO). 
29-32 The control (CO; n = 6) received normal saline for the 
total duration of the treatment phase (10 days). At the end of 
the treatment phase, n = 6 animals were sacrificed in the VO, 
CN and CO groups. Cyanide treatment and vascular occlusion 
was discontinued in the remaining n = 6 animals, each in the 
CN and VO treatments for the next 10 days (day 20). This rep-
resents the withdrawal phase and these groups were renamed 
CN-I and VO-I respectively. Author completed the IACUC train-
ing on Animal Use and a protocol number was already assigned 
to group (ABU13/Neu/008). </p>

<p>Cerebral blood vessels </p>

<p>The animals were anaesthetized using intraperiotoneally ad-
ministered sodium pentobarbital (50 IP). The root of the neck 
was dissected to expose the ascending aorta following which 
the brain was perfused with artificial cerebrospinal fluid [ACSF 
composition (mM): KCl, 2.5; MgSO 4 , 1.0; NaH 2 PO 4 , 1.25; NaH-
CO 3 , 26; d-glucose, 20; ascorbic acid, 0.45; CaCl 2 , 2.0; and 
NaCl, 125 (osmolality, 290-310 mOsmol kg 
−1 ; pH 7.3-7.4)] at 
4 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>C. Subsequently, the tissues were perfused with freshly pre-
pared formolcalcium and fixed thereafter in formolcalcium for 
14 hours. </p>

<p>Tissue Preparation </p>

<p>The brain was dissected on a stereotaxic frame to obtain sagi-
tal and corona sections of the MCA, periventricular zone (PVZ) 
and parietal cortex (PC) using specific coordinates [2.5 mm lat-
eral to the median fissure (sagital) and 1.5mm anterior to the 
bregma (corona section)]. Later, the sections were post-fixed in 
formolcalcium in a separate chamber (6 hours) and processed 
into paraffin wax embedded tissue blocks. Leica Bond RX (Leica 
GmBH, Germany) automated tissue stainer was used for immu-
nohistochemical processing. All antibodies were procured from 
Novocastra (Leica Biosystems, Germany). Reagents and buffers 
used were molecular biology grade (99.9% pure) from Sigma-
Aldrich (Germany). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>7 µm thick serial sections were prepared using a microtome 
(Leica) and were mounted on a glass slide in preparation for </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>antigen retrieval immunohistochemistry. Sections were im-
mersed in urea overnight and transferred to a microwave for 
45 minutes to expose the antigens and proteins. Primary treat-
ment was done using bovine serum albumin (BSA) to block 
non-specific protein reaction in the tissue. Subsequent process-
ing involved the use of specific biotinylated secondary anti-
bodies (anti-CD31, anti-CD45 anti-NSE, anti-NF, anti-Ki-67 and 
anti-GFAP) diluted in PBS (a dilution of 1:200 was used for all 
secondary antibodies). The immunopositive reaction was de-
veloped using a polymer 3'3' Diaminobenzidine Tetrachloride 
(DAB; Sigma-Aldrich) with methenamine silver color intensifi-
cation. The sections were counterstained in haematoxylin and 
treated with 1% acid alcohol (freshly prepared) to reduce the 
counter-stain intensity. </p>

<p>Cell Count and Analysis </p>

<p>The images were acquired using an Optronics Digital Camera 
connected to a computer interface (<rs type="software">MagnaFire</rs>) and an Olym-
pus BX-51 research microscope. The general structure of the 
pyramidal cells of the PC and round neurogenic cells of the 
PVZ were characterized using inter-reader variability. The total 
cell count was determined using a 10 × 10 grid graticulate at 
400X magnification. For both the corona and sagital sections, 
n = 2 fields were captured to obtain n = 4 fields per section. 
Subsequently, the average count for n = 4 fields was deter-
mined as the representative value. 
33 Immunopositive cells in 
GFAP, NSE and Ki-67IHC were counted in Image J (NIH) and cal-
culated using the method described in the previous paragraph. 
NF, CD31 and CD45 were expressed as intensity of IHC reaction 
products (+/-). The lumen and arterial wall of the MCA branch 
were measured using Open Office Draw Suite (Sun Microsys-
tems) at a magnification of 100X. The data was plotted using 
a simple ANOVA (<rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 17.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">IBM</rs>) with significance set 
at P&lt;0.05*, P&lt;0.01** and P&lt;0.001*** for total and immu-
nopositive cell counts. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Histology of the MCA </p>

<p>The general morphology of the wall of the arteries was dem-
onstrated in a corona section through the whole brain at ap-
proximately 1.3 mm anterior to the bregma. Increase in thick-
ness of the wall of the arteries was characteristic of vascular 
occlusion (Figure 1-VO; 0.09 cm) and can be attributed in part 
to the mechanical stress induced by the cuffs for the treatment 
duration. The artery was also characterized by a narrower lu-
men (0.0028 cm), when compared with the control (0.036 cm) 
(Figure 1D). The effect of vascular occlusion in this group can 
be described anatomically as "induced vascular resistance" in 
the middle cerebral artery. The structural resistance observed 
in the global vascular occlusion treatment (VO) reduced af-
ter the withdrawal phase (VO-I). In the VO-I, the lumen/wall 
thickness ratio (LTR) increased significantly to 4.00 from the 
initial value (3.11) observed in the vascular occlusion treatment 
(Figure 1-VO-I). The increased LTR in this group corresponds to 
a reduction in wall thickness (0.008cm) and an increase in lu-
men width (0.032 cm; Figure 1D). </p>

<p>In cyanide treatment, a reduced LTR was seen (2.44) (Figure 1D); 
this was characterized by a prominent reduction in the lumen 
width (0.022 cm) and wall thickness (0.009cm) after the treat-
ment phase (Figure 1-CN). In the withdrawal group for CN treat-
ment, CN-I, the LTR value increased (3.00) when compared with </p>

<p>the control, indicating, a decreased resistance in the artery after 
the withdrawal. The increased LTRseen in CN-I was associated 
with an increase in the thickness of the tunica media (0.012 cm) 
and width of the lumen (0.036 cm) (Figure 1D). </p>

<p>CD31/CD45 (MCA) </p>

<p>CD31 and CD45 expression in the MCA (corona section) was 
determined to evaluate endothelial cell proliferation and the 
associated monocytic activity respectively. In VO (CD31 
++ ) 
and CN (CD31 
+++ ), the rate of endothelial cell proliferation 
increased (Figure 1; Table 1 and Figure 1D) when compared 
with the control after the treatment phase. This resulted in an 
increased intima-media layer thickness (CD31-endothelial acti-
vation) for CN and VO; although the expression of CD31 was 
higher in cyanide toxicity than vascular occlusion. However, 
after the withdrawal of cyanide treatment and vascular occlu-
sion, a significant decrease in CD31-endothelial thickening was 
observed in the VO-I (CD31 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) and CN-I (CD31 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>). Interestingly, 
we observed a decrease in monocytic-CD45 expression with an 
increase in endothelial-cell proliferation (↓CD45/↑CD31) after 
the treatment phase (Figure 1; Table 1). The same association 
was observed after the withdrawal phase as CD45 increased 
(CD45 
+++ ) with a corresponding decrease in CD31 expression 
(CD31 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) in the VO-I (Figure 1B and C) (↑CD45/↓CD31). In cya-
nide treatment, a similar inverse relationship was observed be-
tween CD31 and CD45. </p>

<p>Histology of the PC </p>

<p>The general morphology of the brain tissue was demonstrated 
by haematoxylin and eosin staining. Both CN and VO treatment 
groups showed degenerative changes in the parietal cortex 
(Figure 2A and Figure 2C) with a reduction in cell count per unit 
area (VO:16, CN:13) when compared to the control (24 cells 
per unit area) (Table 1; Figure 2F). Subsequently, an increase in 
cell count was observed after the withdrawal phase for both 
treatments such that CN-I recorded 16 and VO-I, 25 after this 
phase. In the VO-I, some cells showed features of resuscitation 
(Figure 2B) when compared with those of the CN-I (Figure 2C 
and 2D). Degenerative changes observed in the treatment 
groups include: vacuolated cytoplasm, loss of cellular projec-
tions, pale staining cell body, fragmented centrally placed nu-
clei and a diminished nucleoplasm. </p>

<p>Histology of the PVZ </p>

<p>Prominent cellular changes occurred in the PVZ of both mod-
els of ischemia after the treatment duration. The degenerative 
changes observed in the cells of the PVZ are similar to those 
of the cortical cells described above. It is important to note 
that the cells of PVZ often lack cellular projections; thus the 
adopted criteria for identifying degenerating cells in the PVZ 
excludes loss of cellular projections. The CN treatment group 
showed significant cell loss in the PVZ 
13 when compared with 
the control. 
24 The cell count increased in the withdrawal group 
for cyanide treatment (CN-I; 15) but was less than that seen 
in the control. Vascular occlusion (VO) induced minor degen-
erative changes in the PVZ with minimal cell loss 
16 after the 
treatment phase. However, in the vascular occlusion treatment, 
no significant change in cell count was observed after the with-
drawal phase (Table 1; Figure 2F). Generally, the distribution of 
degenerating neurogenic cells in vascular occlusion (Figure 2A) 
and cyanide treatment (Figure 2C) groups demonstrates the 
role of ischemia in induced degeneration in the plastic (PVZ) </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>Fig. 1: Coronal section of the brain showing a branch of the MCA close to the third ventricle (A) Microscopic anatomy of the artery demonstrated 
in haematoxylin and eosin staining (Magnification X100) to show the lumen and tunica media/intima in cyanide toxicity and vascular occlusion; after the 
treatment and withdrawal phases. An increase in the tunica media/intima thickness was observed in VO and was accompanied by a decrease in lumen 
width. In cyanide toxicity, degenerative changes were observed in the tunica media/intima; consequently, a decrease in wall thickness and lumen width 
was recorded in this group. A common set of event in the CN and VO is the decrease in lumen width and an increase in vascular resistance shown by 
the lumen width/wall thickness ratio (Figure 1D). After the withdrawal phase, regenerative changes such as increased lumen width, reduced vascular 
resistance and increased cell count were seen in the CN-I and VO-I. Degenerative changes were more pronounced in cyanide toxicity after the treatment 
phase with a LTR value of 2.44. Sequel After to the withdrawal of cyanide treatment in CN-I, the LTR value increased to 3.67 after the withdrawal phase, 
thus, a decreased vascular resistance (Figure 1D). Similarly, after vascular occlusion, vascular resistance increased in the artery (3.11) when compared with 
the control (4.55) and decreased after the withdrawal phase (VO-I; 4.00). This further supports the change in lumen width observed in histology after the 
treatment (↓lumen width and ↓LTR) and the improvement seen after the withdrawal phase (↑lumen width and ↑LTR). (B) CD31 immunohistochemistry to 
demonstrate endothelial adhesion molecule PECAM-1 during endothelial proliferation in cyanide toxicity and vascular occlusion induced oxidative stress. 
Endothelial proliferation (↑CD31) was observed in cyanide toxicity (CD31 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>) and vascular occlusion (CD31 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>) after the treatment phase. Similar to our 
observations in the LTR and histology (Figure 1A and 1D), a reduction in endothelial proliferation (↓wall thickness) was observed after the withdrawal 
phase. This was highly significant in CN-I (CD31 </p>

<p>--</p>

<p>) and was less significant in VO-I (CD31 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) (C) Blood monocytes and phagocytes (CD45) were demon-
strated around the artery to determine their role in pro-inflammation (treatment) and remodeling (withdrawal) during oxidative stress. Interestingly, 
VO (CD45 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) and CN (CD45 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>) showed a significant reduction in monocyte expression when compared with the control (CD45 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>) signifying the non-
involvement of these cells in pro-inflammatory response. However, after the withdrawal phase, the expression of CD45/monocytes increased significantly 
in VO-I (CD45 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>) and no significant change was observed in CN-I (CD45 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>). Subsequent analysis reveals that CD45/monocyte expression was associated 
with post-ischemia remodeling and not inflammatory response in oxidative stress. Furthermore, the magnitude of vascular remodeling was more signifi-
cant in vascular occlusion than cyanide toxicity (d) Pie chart representation of the wall thickness, the lumen width and the LTR. </p>

<p>Table 1: Cell counts in the PC and PVZ. The count represents the average of cell distribution in the sagital and corona sections. The 
NF, Cd31 and Cd45 were assigned +/-or + based on the intensity of immunoreaction colour deposits </p>

<p>Brain 
VO 
VO-I 
CN 
CN-I 
Control 
PVZ 
Total Cell Count 
GFAP 
NSE 
Ki-67 </p>

<p>16 
21 
14 
10 </p>

<p>25 
18 
11 
5 </p>

<p>13 
13 
5 
8 </p>

<p>15 
16 
29 
6 </p>

<p>17 
24 
14 
6 
PC 
Total Cell Count 
GFAP 
NSE 
Ki-67 
NF </p>

<p>16 
23 
3 
5 
++ </p>

<p>15 
27 
4 
9 
++++ </p>

<p>13 
35 
2 
5 
+/-</p>

<p>16 
17 
8 
4 
+ </p>

<p>24 
15 
10 
8 
+++ 
Blood Vessel 
CD31 
CD45 </p>

<p>++ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+++ </p>

<p>+++ 
++ </p>

<p>--
+ </p>

<p>++ 
+++ </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>Fig. 2: General morphology of the PC and PVZ for the treatment groups and the control (A) Degenerative changes are characteristic of vascu-
lar occlusion both in the PC and PVZ as the cell count reduced when compared to the control (B) In the withdrawal group for vascular occlusion; 
VO-I, the degeneration reduced and cell proliferation increased in the PVZ. Also, cell count and cell morphology gave scores similar to those of the 
control (Table 1) (C) Cyanide treatment induced aggressive degenerative changes ranging from reduced cell number, loss of cellular projections, 
pale staining cell bodies and vacuolar spaces around the neurons of the PC and PVZ (d) An improvement in cell count and structure (PC and PVZ) 
was observed in the CN-I following the withdrawal of cyanide treatment. Cell count increased in the PVZ of the CN-I, similar to what was observed 
in VO-I, but was less significant when compared versus the control and VO-I (E) Control; the structure of the PVZ is well defined with rounded cells 
organized into layers beside the highly vascularised third ventricle. The neurons of the PC are characterized by prominent neuronal projection, dark 
staining cell body and cell count was higher than those of the treatments (Magnification X400). (F) Bar chart representation of the total cell count 
in the PC and PVZ (Mean±SEM). </p>

<p>2A 
2B </p>

<p>2D 
2C </p>

<p>2F 
2E </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>and non-plastic (PC) brain areas. Interestingly, the results sug-
gest a differential rate of degeneration for these brain areas. 
Specifically, we observed a higher cell loss in the PC than the 
PVZ for the same threshold of assaultin cyanide toxicity and 
vascular occlusion. </p>

<p>GFAP PC </p>

<p>We next investigated the distribution of glia cells in the PC and 
PVZ after the treatment and withdrawal phases using specific 
antibody interaction to show the expression of type III inter-
mediate filament (GFAP) in astrocytes. Similar to our previous 
findings, 
25 we observed a variation in glia count for the PC and 
PVZ in cyanide treatment. In addition, this study has shown a 
similar trend exists for the PC and PVZ after vascular occlusion. </p>

<p>A significant increase in glia count was observed in the PC post 
cyanide treatment (35; Figure 3C and 3F) when compared with 
vascular occlusion (23; Figure 3A). From these results, it is evi-
dent that degeneration progressed faster in CN treatment than 
in VO, hence, the higher glia count in CN treatment after the 
treatment phase (Figure 3F; Table 1). In the withdrawal groups, 
glia activation was higher in the VO-I (27; Figure 3B) and lower 
in the CN-I (17; Figure 3D) when compared with the control. 
This suggests that in cyanide treatment degeneration pro-
ceeded faster during the treatment period and receded upon 
withdrawal -while the opposite occurred in case in vascular 
occlusion. </p>

<p>GFAP PVZ </p>

<p>The glia count decreased significantly in the PVZ after vascular 
occlusion was induced (21; Figure 3A) when compared with 
the control (24; Figure 3E). After the withdrawal phase, a fur-
ther decrease in glia count was observed in the VO-I (Figure 
3B-PVZ) having a score of 18 (Figure 3B). In the CN treatment, 
glia count increased significantly (30; Figure 3C) after the treat-
ment phase but decreased slightly in the withdrawal phase (25; 
Figure 3D). </p>

<p>NSE PC </p>

<p>The importance of neuronal metabolism in determining the 
significance of glia activation and other cellular changes associ-
ated with cyanide toxicity and vascular occlusion is important. 
Neuron specific enolase (NSE), a gamma enolase, expressed in 
immature neurons, early in neurogenesis, and adult neurons 
in oxidative stress was labelled in the PC to demonstrate neu-
ron specific oxidative stress, and to distinguish neurons from 
glia cells. We observed a decrease in NSE immunopositive cell 
count after the treatment phase [VO (3; Figure 4A) and CN 
(2; Figure 4C)] and an increase after the withdrawal phase 
(Figure 4B; Table 1). The most significant change in NSE expres-
sion was observed in the cyanide treatment group, such that 
the withdrawal (CN-I; 8) recorded NSE scores four times the 
treatment (CN; 2) (Figure 4C, 4D and 4F). All the treatments 
and withdrawal groups recorded NSE scores significantly 
lower than the control value (10; Figure 4 E). </p>

<p>NSE PVZ </p>

<p>In the neurogenic zone, the least NSE score was recorded in 
the CN treatment (Figure 4C). (However, withdrawal of cyanide 
treatment caused a significant increase in NSE count; from 14 in 
CN to 29 in CN-I (Figure 4F). This supports the previous findings 
that CN triggers a more rapid degeneration that reverses after 
withdrawal). Interestingly, in vascular occlusion, the NSE score </p>

<p>Fig. 3: distribution of GFAP in the PC and PVZ (A) mapping of astro-
cytes via IHC staining with anti-GFAP in the PC and PVZ of rats subjected to 
vascular occlusion. Increased immunoreaction depicts ependymal astro-
cyte proliferation around the blood vessels rich PVZ and glia activation in 
the parietal cortex (B) after the withdrawal phase, a reduction in astrocyte 
(GFAP) count was observed in the PVZ but increased in the PC (P&lt;0.05) 
when compared with the control (C) The most significant glia activa-
tion was observed after cyanide toxicity with a glia count of 35 in the 
PC (significant at P&lt;0.001 when compared with the control) (d) after 
the withdrawal phase, glia activation reduced in the PC and increased in 
the PVZ of cyanide treatment group (CN-I) (E) The control distribution of 
glia cells in the PC and PVZ (Magnification X100). (F) Bar chart represent-
ing the immunopositive glia cell counts in the PC and PVZ (Mean±SEM). </p>

<p>was higher in the treatment (14; Figure 4A and Figure 4F) and 
decreases after withdrawal (Figure 4B and Figure 4F). </p>

<p>Ki-67 PC </p>

<p>This is a cytoplasmic inclusion found in dividing mammalian 
cells, including neurons in early neurogenesis. Ki-67 was dem-
onstrated to determine the probable event of cell prolifera-</p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>Fig. 4: distribution of NSE in the PC and PVZ. The γ-enolase was 
shown in IHC using anti rat-NSE to demonstrate the metabolic switch 
from α-enolase in oxidative stress or neurogenesis in the PC and PVZ (A) 
a reduction in NSE (+) cell count was observed after the treatment phase 
in vascular occlusion (P&lt;0.001) when compared with the control (B) 
surprisingly, the withdrawal group of vascular occlusion (VO-I) showed 
no significant change in NSE (+) cell count in the PVZ and recorded a 
reduction in NSE (+) in the PC (P&lt;0.05) versus the control (d) Cyanide 
treatment withdrawal group showed a good yield in NSE (+) cell count 
both in the PC (8) and the PVZ (29) (P&lt;0.001) when compared with VO/ 
VO-I (E) Control group PVZ and PC showing the distribution of NSE posi-
tive cells in the molecular layer of the PC and the outer border of the PVZ 
(Magnification X400) (F) Bar chart representing the score for anti-NSE 
positive cell distribution in the PC and PVZ (Mean±SEM). </p>

<p>tion in the PC and (or) PVZ in the two models of ischemia. Cell 
proliferation was lower in the non-plastic PC when compared 
to the neurogenic PVZ. In vascular occlusion, Ki-67 immu-
nopositive cell count recorded a score of 5 (Figure 5A and 
Figure 5H); the appearance of these cells suggests they might 
be glia rather than neuronal. The rate of proliferation increased 
in the withdrawal for this category having a score of 9 in VO-I </p>

<p>(Figure 5B), similar to the trend observed in GFAP distribution. 
However, in cyanide toxicity, withdrawal had little effect on cell 
proliferation in this region increasing from 4 in CN (Figure 5C) 
to 5 in CN-I (Figure 5D and 5H). Cell proliferation was lower in 
CN and CN-I when compared with vascular occlusion and the 
control (Figure 5E and Figure 5H). </p>

<p>Ki-67 PVZ </p>

<p>Subsequent analysis of Ki-67 immunopositive cells showed a 
score of 10 in VO (10; Figure 5A) and 8 in CN (8; Figure 5C). 
These values were higher than those recorded in the withdraw-
al groups, that is CN-I (6; Figure 5D) and VO-I (5; Figure 5B). 
The results suggest that oxidative stress drives proliferation in 
the neurogenic PVZ. Severally dividing and migrating neurons 
in vivo stained positive in Ki-67as shown in Figure 5F and 5G. </p>

<p>Neurofilament </p>

<p>The immunoreactivity of NF demonstrates the extent of neuro-
nal process degeneration in the models of ischemia. Because 
the PVZ is void of cellular projections, NF was demonstrated 
only in the PC. The least NF deposition was found in cyanide 
treatment. This further supports the earlier findings in GFAP 
and NSE count which show that CN caused a more rapid de-
generation than VO for the treatment duration. Also, regenera-
tive changes occurred faster in vascular occlusion withdrawal 
group (VO-I: NF 
++++ ) as compared to the initial treatment (VO) 
group (NF 
++ ). In cyanide toxicity, degeneration of neurofila-
ment was observed (NF 
+/-in the CN) mostly in the fibrous layers 
of the cortex. These degenerative changes were reduced in the 
withdrawal group (CN-I), having a significant increase in depo-
sition of neurofilament (NF 
++ ) when compared with the control 
(Figure 6; Table 1). </p>

<p>discussion </p>

<p>Taken together, the results of this study have shown that endo-
thelial alteration accompanies neuron/glia change in vascular 
occlusion and cyanide toxicity. The observed morphological al-
teration involved an increase in endothelial activation (CD31) 
accompanied by a reduction in monocytic expression (CD45) 
after the treatment phase. Interestingly, this was reversed in 
the withdrawal phase as endothelial activation reduced and 
monocytic expression increased. We have also shown that the 
magnitude of endothelial proliferation determines the extent 
of PC/PVZ degeneration or PVZ proliferation in chemotoxicity 
and vascular occlusion. Ultimately, we attributed these changes 
to glia activation (↑GFAP), coupled with an increased neuronal 
metabolic demand (↓NSE) in the cortex and PVZ. Although the 
observed change in neuron/glia metabolism and microvascu-
lature of the brain during oxidative stress is believed to be a 
homeostatic response to balance oxygen supply and metabo-
lism, however, certain differences were observed in the stress 
response generated in vascular occlusion, cyanide toxicity and 
the corresponding withdrawal groups. </p>

<p>Vascular Occlusion </p>

<p>Vascular occlusion induced proliferative changes in the blood 
vessels, and degeneration in the PVZ and PC post treatment 
(Figure 1D). Subsequently, this was reversed after the with-
drawal period as the cell count increased in the PC, endothe-
lial proliferation reduced (CD31 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) and monocytic expression 
increased (CD45 
+++ ) (Figure 1B and Figure 1C). The observed 
changes were regarded as an inverse link between neurogenesis </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>Fig. 5: A-E. IHC demonstration of Ki-67 cytoplasmic inclusions in the PC and PVZ. (A) Cell proliferation was higher in the PVZ compared to the PC in 
VO after the treatment phase (B) After the withdrawal phase, increased cell proliferation was observed in the PC than in the PVZ of the VO-I treatment 
when compared with the VO and control (P&lt;0.01). However, the proliferating cells were glia (↑GFAP) rather than neuronal (NSE) (C) CN treatment 
caused a reduction in cell proliferation in the PC (↓Ki-67) when compared with the control. However, an increase in cell proliferation was observed in 
the PVZ (↑Ki-67) when compared with the control. This suggests that oxidative stress also drives cell proliferation in certain cells of the PVZ despite 
the cell loss observed in total cell count. Further analysis reveals astrocytic proliferation was more significant (↑GFAP) than neuronal proliferation (NSE) 
in the PVZ (P&lt;0.05). (d) Following the withdrawal of cyanide treatment, the rate of cell proliferation changed only slightly in the PC but significantly 
reduced in the PVZ of the CN-I group (P&lt;0.05). In furtherance, the decrease in Ki-67 corresponds to a decrease in astrocyte (↓GFAP) and monocyte 
(↓CD45) count after the withdrawal phase in this group (E) demonstration of Ki-67 positive cells in PC and PVZof the control group. 5F-H Pattern of 
cell division in the PVZ (F) several dividing neurons (stained positive to anti-Ki-67) showing polarity (or cytokinesis in vivo). The shape of these cells 
is unique and often has midline ring and 2 limbs adjoining these separating cells. Furthermore, our previous results (Ogundele et al., 2014) show that 
these cells are neuronal as they stained positive to NSE in IHC (Magnification X400). (G) The dividing cells are further illustrated using line graphics (H) 
Bar chart representing immunopositive cell count in Ki-67 IHC of the PC and PVZ (Mean±SEM). </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>and angiogenesis modulated through signaling pathways in-
volving angiogenic cells and immature neurons in remodeling 
post-ischemia. 
34-36 We next examined the distribution of Ki-67 
and NSE immunopositive cells in the PC and PVZ and observed 
active cell migration and metabolism in the PC and PVZ after 
the withdrawal phase. This is supported by the findings of Ros-
sell et al. (2013) where endothelial progenitors were used as 
stimulants for angio-neurogenesis post ischemia induced by 
MCA occlusion. 
37 In order to confirm neuronal cell prolifera-
tion, first we analyzed the distribution of neuron progenitors 
(NSE/Ki-67) in the PVZ and found that they were localized in the 
upper 2 or 3 layers of the PVZ. Subsequent analysis of the NSE/ 
Ki-67 progenitor cells show that further away from the PVZ, 
they assume a spindle shape and become polarized (Figure 5F 
and 5G). In addition, they separate along the midline with two 
(2) cellular processes adjoining the two daughter cells (Figure 
5G) with the upper cell extending towards the subcortical area 
and the lower cell directed towards the upper cell layer of the 
PVZ (Figure 5F). Interestingly, our previous study described 
such pattern of cell separation in neurogenesis using NSE im-
munolabeling to show proliferation in cells of the PVZ in vivo. It 
was observed that dividing neurogenic cells were characterized 
by two crus (limbs) around the separation ring and were ori-
ented in opposite directions. 
25 Since the neurogenic progenitor 
cells can divide to yield neuron and glia, we next distinguished 
gliogenesis from neurogenesis using the proposition by Robert-
son (2014). 
38 This involved statistical comparison of the GFAP/ 
NSE count in the PC and PVZ, followed by a direct correlation 
with the Ki-67 count. We observed an increase in cortical Ki-
67, most of which were restricted to the subcortical areas and </p>

<p>mostly coincided with the location of glia cells (GFAP) rather 
than neuron (NSE) (Table 2). </p>

<p>In addition to neurogenic cell division, histology of the PVZ re-
vealed a stratified arrangement of cells having 4-6 layers of 
rounded cells. Further characterization in IHC showed that the 
glia-progenitor cells (GFAP+) were closer to the blood vessels 
(lower 3 layers around the third ventricle) while the NSE posi-
tive cells (neuron progenitor) were sparsely located in the up-
per 2-3 layers close to the lower limit of the cortex (Figure 4E 
and 2E). We also observed an increased glia count around the 
blood vessels and degenerating cortical neurons. This was at-
tributed to rapid re-modelling of the BBB and a signal of neuro-
nal metabolic support/degeneration in the cortex. Consequent-
ly, repair was observed after the withdrawal phase as shown in 
the increased neurofilament (NF) deposition form NF 
++ in the 
VO to NF 
++++ in VO-I. </p>

<p>Chemotoxicity </p>

<p>In cyanide toxicity, the observed degenerative changes were 
widespread and severe when compared with the control and 
the vascular occlusion group. However, after the withdrawal 
phase, an increase in cell count was recorded in the PC and 
PVZ (Figure 2C and 2D). Endothelial activation was more sig-
nificant in cyanide treatment (CD31 
+++ ) and was accompanied 
by a reduction in monocytic expression (CD45 
++ ). A differ-
ence in angiogenic expression was observed for cyanide toxic-
ity when compared with the vascular occlusion treatment as 
degeneration was seen in the tunica media of the MCA for 
CN, and proliferation was seen in VO (Figure 1). In cyanide </p>

<p>Fig. 6: Neurofilament distribution and lamellation in the parietal cortex (A) Loss of NF immunodeposition in VO (NF 
++ ) indicates degeneration in 
the PC after the treatment phase when compared with the control (NF 
+++ ) (B) In the withdrawal group for vascular occlusion (VO-I), deposition of NF 
(NF 
++++ ) was observed in the PC around the neurons of the pyramidal cell layer. This indicates re-modelling of neuronal projections in this region after 
the ischemic injury (C) Cyanide toxicity induced degenerative changes characterized by heavy loss of neurofilament in the cortex (NF </p>

<p>-/+ </p>

<p>) when compared 
with the control (NF 
+++ ). (D) Similarly, an increase in NF was observed after the withdrawal phase (CN-I; NF 
+ ) but was less significant when compared 
with VO-I (E) distribution of neurofilament in the PC of the control. This shows a well-defined cellular and fibrous layer with filaments extending form 
one layer of the cortex to the next (Magnification X100). </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>toxicity, the expression of CD31 
+++ / CD45 
++ show that the en-
dothelial proliferation was rapid due to ROS and NO mediated 
pathways as previously described. 
39 In the withdrawal group, 
a shift in angiogenic expression was observed such that endo-
thelial proliferation was negative and monocytic activity also 
declined (CD31 
--/CD45 
+ ). The expression of CD31 
--/CD45 
+ in 
the CN-I indicates that endothelial proliferation and vasculo-
genesis occurred minimally post withdrawal; similarly, a low 
Ki-67 count was associated after cyanide withdrawal (Figure 4C, 
4D, 5C and 5D). </p>

<p>Glia activation was highest in cyanide treatment showing the 
more aggressive nature of this form of ischemia with a score of 
35 in the PC and 30 in the PVZ. This was also accompanied by a 
reduction in neuron count; with the most significant loss in the 
PC. However, a reduction in glia count was seen after the with-
drawal phase with a corresponding increase in NSE count. A 
major evidence of neuronal survival was seen in neurofilament 
deposition in the cortex, which increased significantly after the 
withdrawal phase (NF 
++++ ) (Figure 6). </p>

<p>Endothelial activation is characterized by an increase in CD31 
expression in induced oxidative stress. This is accompanied by 
a reduction in monocyte count (↓CD45) and an increase in glia 
count (↑GFAP). Both VO and CN induced these set of changes, 
although the extent of endothelial-glia activation was more 
significant in CN treatment. The magnitude of the endothelial 
activation also corresponded with the observed neuronal de-
generation, being more significant in cyanide treatment. After 
the withdrawal phase, a decrease in endothelial activation fa-
cilitated cell proliferation in the PVZ, thus suggesting an inverse 
relationship between neurogenesis and angiogenesis in stress. 
Ki-67/GFAP and Ki-67/NSE distribution suggests the prolifera-
tion was glial rather than neuronal. However, certain neuro-
genic cells divided after the induced stress (Figure 5F and 5G) 
while expressing NSE in the upper 2-3 layers of the PVZ. The 
observed degenerative changes were reversed after the with-
drawal phase for cyanide toxicity and vascular occlusion. </p>

<p>Angiogenesis in Ischemia </p>

<p>Previous studies have shown that inflammatory bacterial infec-
tion, chemotoxins, stroke/plaques, drug abuse can cause inju-
ries to the unit arrangement at micro-vessel level (environment) 
of the brain. 
38,40 A major cell type around the neurovascular 
structures is the CD45 
+ -Monocyte (phagocytes) which is acti-
vated in neurodegeneration and inflammation to remove de-
generating neurons and participate in remodeling of the blood 
vessels. The increase in the expression of these cells (CD45+) </p>

<p>demonstrates the activity of phagocytes in re-conditioning 
during oxidative stress, a similar role performed by microglia 
in stress. 
41,42 Our results revealed that ischemia induced pro-
inflammatory events which involved glia activation, increased 
in endothelial proliferation and decreased monocyte count. 
Furthermore, we observed a decrease in glia activation (↓GFAP) 
and endothelial proliferation (CD31) sequel to the withdrawal 
of the ischemic assault with a corresponding increase in mono-
cyte count. Consequently, it suggests the role of CD45 mono-
cytes in the recovery and remodeling of the neurovasculature 
rather than being a pro-inflammatory mediator; similar to the 
findings of Brambilla et al. (2014). </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>Astrocytic activation and NSE in stress </p>

<p>The relationship between the neuron (NSE) and astrocytes 
(GFAP) is deeply rooted in function, metabolism and structure. 
The expression level of GFAP and NSE has proven to be of clini-
cal significance, especially in diagnosis of degenerative diseases 
and progression of traumatic brain injury. 
43 The level of these 
proteins are usually elevated by several folds in the cerebrospi-
nal fluid and blood of neurosurvival patients (NSE/S100b by 
18.3 folds and GFAP by 4.6 folds). 
43,44 This suggests that GFAP/ 
NSE profile can add to the clinical assessment of the primary 
damage and predicting the outcome after some chemotoxicity 
or vascular occlusion. </p>

<p>Ischemic injury causes cellular activation and degeneration 
which often leads to the release of cell-type-specific pro-
teins. 
43-45 The GFAP/NSE profile is a reflection of cellular and 
sub-cellular events and differences between neuron and astro-
cytes under these conditions. 
46 Although NSE is expressed in 
neurogenesis and stress, our results suggest that NSE levels in 
neurogenesis are higher than that observed in stress, similar to 
the findings of Amorino and Parsons, (2004). 
47 Comparing the 
two models of ischemia, NSE level was higher in VO than CN, 
thus indicating the role of decreased endothelial cell prolifera-
tion (CD31) and angiogenesis in speeding up NSE activation 
(See also Table 1). The most predominant cell proliferation in 
the PC was astrocytic as seen by the GFAP/NSE ratio (Table 2). 
This trend also shows that oxidative stress reduced NSE in corti-
cal degeneration and increased glia presence in these degen-
erating brain regions. Comparing the GFAP/NSE ratios, in the 
VO and CN showed that glia activation was higher than NSE 
expression in both treatment groups (CN-17.5 and VO-7.67). 
A higher GFAP/NSE ratio in the CN treatment indicates a more 
rapid progression of ischemic assault when compared with VO 
and the control (with an index of 1.5). In addition, this index </p>

<p>Table 2: GFAP/NSE ratio for the treatments and control group. The GFAP/NSE ratio shows rate of glia activation compared with de-
generation in the PVZ and PC </p>

<p>PC </p>

<p>VO 
VO-I 
CN 
CN-I 
CO </p>

<p>GFAP 
NSE 
GRAP/NSE </p>

<p>23 
3 
7.67 </p>

<p>27 
4 
6.75 </p>

<p>35 
2 
17.5 </p>

<p>17 
8 
2.13 </p>

<p>15 
10 
1.5 </p>

<p>PVZ </p>

<p>GFAP 
NSE 
GRAP/NSE </p>

<p>21 
14 
1.5 </p>

<p>18 
11 
1.64 </p>

<p>30 
5 
6.0 </p>

<p>25 
29 
0.86 </p>

<p>18 
14 
1.28 </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>

<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>

<p>RES ARTICLE </p>

<p>showed that glia activation was more active in the PC than the 
PVZ. In the withdrawal groups, VO-I scored 6.75 in the PC and 
1.64 in the PVZ while CN-I scored 2.13 in the PC and 0.86 in the 
PVZ; this confirms reduction of glia activation and an increase 
in neuronal survival (NSE) in these groups. Other studies used a 
similar comparison in CSF assays as a predictor of progression 
of degeneration in traumatic brain injury patients. </p>

<p>43,48 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Cyanide toxicity and vascular occlusion can be described 
through the bidirectional model of the endotlelium-neuralen-
dothelium-neural tissue interphase (BBB). From these findings 
we hypothesise that cynaide toxicity induced the outward sig-
nal (neurodegeneration to vascular changes) while vascular oc-
clusion causes endothelial proliferation which precedes neuro-
degeneration (inward signal). </p>

<p>Vascular oclussion induced neuronal degeneration after endo-
thelial and glia activation caused by the mechanical stress and 
hypoxia. The endothelial activation was seen as an increased 
vascular resistance, probably associated with increased endo-
thelial nitric oxide which is associated with neuronal oxidative 
stress and degeneration after the treatment phase. </p>

<p>Cyanide diffused through the membrane to inhibit cytochrome 
C oxidase (CcOX) in the mitochondria. As a result, ROS and 
NO are released, signalling neuronal oxidative stress and glia 
activation. The interaction between ependymal glia and endo-
thelial cell is important in the associated endothelia activation 
which occur after onset neurodegeneration and glia activation. </p>

<p>We conclude that cyanide toxicity and vascular occlusion induced 
oxidative stress and neurodegeneration in the brain (↓NSE). This 
was associated with endothelial proliferation (↑CD31) and glia 
activation (↑GFAP) after the treatment phase, thus signifying 
degenerative and pro-inflammatory changes. However, the sig-
nificance of degeneration was pronounced in cyanide treatment 
when compared with vascular occlusion. Subsequently, with-
drawal of cyanide treatment and vascular occlusion induced a 
reduction in endothelial proliferation (↓CD31) and glia activa-
tion (↓GFAP). In addition, an increase in neuron count (↑NSE) 
and monocytic activity (↑CD45) was observed which is an indica-
tion of neurosurvival and vascular remodeling after this phase. 
Similarly, we recorded an increase in cell proliferation (↑Ki-67) 
and neurofilament deposition (↑NF) after the withdrawal phase. 
Degenerative changes were more significant in the PC than PVZ; 
also, PVZ showed an increase in cell proliferation after the with-
drawal phase. Finally, cyanide toxicity improved better than the 
vascular occlusion after the withdrawal period. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>NSE (neuron specific enolase; γ enolase), GFAP (glia fibrillary 
acidic protein; a type III intermediate filament), Ki-67 (cell pro-
liferation marker), NF (neurofilament), CD31 (PECAM-1; an en-
dothelial adhesion molecule), H&amp;E (heamatoxylin and eosin), 
CD45 (blood monocyte/phagocyte marker), LTR (lumen width/ 
wall thickness ratio), PC (parietal cortex, PVZ (periventricular 
zone), VO (vascular occlusion), VO-I (vascular occlusion with-
drawal), CN (cynaide toxicity), CN-I (cyanide toxicity withdrawal), 
BBB (blood brain barrier). </p>

<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>We acknowledge the contributions of the Anatomy technicians 
in maintaining and caring for the animals throughout the peri-</p>

<p>od of the study. Our sincere appreciation to Prof. Kirk Deitsch of 
the Weill Medical College of Cornell University, New York, USA, 
for giving us access to the Olympus BX 51 research Microscope 
and Optronics Camera for the image acquisition and analysis. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work is supported by the ISN-CAEN 1B of August, 2013 is-
sued by the International Society for Neurochemistry. Also, the 
Disease Model Mechanism Travelling Fellowship Grant TF476 
issued by the Company of Biologists LTD, Cambridge UK. Both 
grants are awarded to OOM. </p>

<p>Author Contribution </p>

<p>Ogundele O Michael: Initiated and designed the study, Ba-
logun W Gbolahan, Ansa E Cobham, Amin Abdulbasitand, 
Ishola Olakunle: All contributed in the implementation of the 
research, analysis of results and report writing. </p>

<p>This article complies with International Committee of Medical Journal edi-
tor's uniform requirements for manuscript. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: (COI) Statement: The Authors hereby declare there is no 
conflict of interest associated with this study or any of the procedures and 
materials used for the purpose of the study. </p>

<p>Received Date : 8 October 2014; Revised Date : 6 January 2015; 
Accepted Date : 6 February 2015 </p>



<p>www.annalsofneurosciences.org </p>

<p>ANNALS OF NEUROSCIENCES VOLUME 22 NUMBER 3 JULY 2015 </p>



<p>ANNALS </p>

<p>R E S A R T I C L E </p>

<p>A AN NN NA AL LS S </p>



</text></tei>