<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4775480" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Citation: Schwartsmann CR, Spinelli LF, Sotomayor MY, Yépez AK, Boschin LC, Silva MF. Bleeding of femoral head during total hip arthroplasty for osteoar-
throsis. Acta Ortop Bras. [online]. 2015;23(5):268-70. Available from ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: To evaluate the bleeding of the femoral head on hip 
osteoarthritis in patients who underwent total hip arthroplasty. 
Methods: One hundred and three hips affected by primary hip 
osteoarthritis were evaluated. After surgical dislocation, the fe-
moral head was divided into four quadrants, and micro perfora-
tions were made in order to observe and assess the presence 
of bleeding, as early type (EB), late type (LB) or without bleeding 
(WB). Results: We observed early bleeding (EB) in the upper 
quadrant in 16 hips (15.5%), late bleeding in 14 hips (13.6%) 
and no bleeding (WB) in 73 hips (70.9%). The anterior quadrant </p>

<p>showed EB in 24 hips (23.3%), LB in 7 hips (6.8%) and WB 
in 72 hips (69.9%). The lower quadrant presented EB in 40 
hips (38.8%), LB 14 hips (13.6%) and WB in 49 hips (47.6%). 
The posterior quadrant showed EB in 39 hips (37.9%), LB 19 
hips (18.4%) and WB in 45 hips (43.7%). Comparing BMI and 
gender, we found no association between these parameters 
(p&gt; 0.05). Conclusions: The inferior and posterior quadrant 
had the highest bleeding levels, following the path of the medial 
circumflex artery. Level of Evidence III, Therapeutic Study. </p>

<p>The pathophysiology responsible for the development of idio-
pathic osteoarthritis of the hip is not yet well understood. Hip 
osteoarthritis is a very common condition and affects most of 
the population. It gradually affects the activities of daily living, 
working and leisure activities. 
Regarding the vascular anatomy of the hip, the literature pre-
sents few studies showing vascular dissection of the pro-
ximal femur. Additionally, high definition imaging exams and 
Doppler vascular flow instruments have been used in anatomical 
description, as well as diagnostic and therapeutic procedures. 
The femoral head is infused primarily by the medial circumflex 
femoral artery (MCFA), through its deep branch, which also 
originates from 2-4 secondary branches. Among them, the 
upper and lower posterior branches are the most important. </p>

<p>1-11 </p>

<p>Observing the neck and femoral head medial side, the upper 
posterior branches can be identified among eleven and four-
teen hours and the anterior branches between seventeen and 
nineteen hours. The posterior branches are commonly present 
and are of variable size, although the upper posterior group is 
most consistent and represents the main source of epiphyseal 
vascular perfusion. 
11 The anterior vascular group is small and 
inconsistent. The piriformis branch of the inferior gluteal artery </p>

<p>is part of the main perfusion source in this region. On the other 
hand, the branches of the lateral circumflex artery, the obturator 
artery and the teres ligament represent a minimum contribution 
for the perfusion of the femoral head. </p>

<p>2-6,12-15 </p>

<p>Changes in the femoral head structure can be explained by 
intra and extraosseous vascular changes in the level of termi-
nal branches of the cervix and epiphysis. In hypertrophic and 
idiopathic coxarthrosis it has not yet been possible to determine 
its pathophysiology, but it is likely that the intraosseous vascular 
flow in the femoral head is fickle and minor compared to the 
extraosseous contribution of the retinacular network. The latter 
is responsible for maintaining the nutrition of the trabecular 
bone. There are reports of morphological changes in the fe-
moral head after injury of these retinacular vessels during the 
posterior approach. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to evaluate the bleeding from the femo-
ral head with osteoarthritis during total hip arthroplasty procedure. </p>

<p>MATERIAlS AND METhODS </p>

<p>In this study 103 arthritic hips without secondary pathologies 
undergoing total hip arthroplasty have been considered. Cases 
with previous surgery of the ipsilateral hip, avascular necro-
sis, rheumatoid arthritis or other rheumatic diseases, tumors, </p>

<p>Acta Ortop Bras. 2015;23(5):268-70 </p>



<p>history of hip disease in childhood or adolescence and peri-
pheral vascular disease have been excluded. No patient was 
using platelet aggregation inhibitors, coumarin derivate or was 
subjected to heparin prior to surgery. Anesthesia of patients was 
performed with lumbar spinal block, using heavy bupivacaine 
20 mg and 0.1 mg morphine. Patients were placed in contra-
lateral lateral position to perform a posterior-lateral approach. 
After opening the fascia lata and muscle and repair of tendons 
of the external rotator muscles of the hip, articular exposure 
with the opening of the posterior capsule was performed. The 
posterior hip dislocation with maximum flexion and internal ro-
tation exposes the femoral head for visualization of the four 
quadrants (anterior, posterior, superior and inferior). (Figure 1) 
After completion of the exposure of the joint surface, a puncture 
was performed in the middle of each quadrant with a 3.2 mm 
drill with a 10 mm depth lock. The bleeding was observed and 
qualified by registering it as early bleeding (EB: immediate to 
10 seconds), late bleeding (LB: after 10 seconds) or without 
bleeding (WB). (Figure 2) This study was approved by the Ins-
titutional Ethics Committee and the patients signed a Free and 
Informed Consent form. 
Among the variables analyzed, gender, age, laterality, body 
mass index (BMI), degree of osteoarthritis and bleeding 
according to the quadrant of the femoral head were included. 
Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18</rs>, with a 95% 
confidence interval. </p>

<p>RESUlTS </p>

<p>Forty eight male patients (47%) and 55 (53%) female patients, 
aged 34-89 years (mean 64±10 years old) were analyzed. The 
mean BMI of patients was 27±4 kg/m 
2 , ranging from 20 to 37. 
In 45% of patients, the right side was operated, and in 55% it 
was the left side. 
It was observed in the upper quadrant early bleeding (EB) in 16 
hips (15.5%), late bleeding in 14 hips (13.6%) and there was no 
bleeding (WB) in 73 hips (70.9%). in the anterior quadrant, EB 
in 24 hips (23.3%), LB in seven hips (6.8%) and WB in 72 hips 
(69.9%). In the lower quadrant, EB in 40 hips (38.8%), LB in 14 
hips (13.6%) and WB in 49 hips (47.6%). Finally, in the posterior 
quadrant, EB in 39 hips (37.9%), LB in 19 hips (18.4%) and WB 
in 45 hips (43.7%). When considered and compared BMI and 
gender, no association was found (p&gt; 0.05). (Table 1) </p>

<p>Figure 1. Exposure diagram of the quadrants of the femoral head in 
surgical hip dislocation. (A) anterior, (P) posterior, (S) superior and (I) 
inferior quadrants. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Exposure of the femoral head by the posterior way. Example of 
3.2mm micro-perforations in the posterior (P) quadrant. </p>

<p>Table 1. General incidence of bleeding in the different regions of the 
femoral head. </p>

<p>Bleeding 
Superior (S) Inferior (I) Anterior (A) Posterior (P) </p>

<p>Early Bleeding (EB) 
16 (15.5%) 40 (38.8%) 24 (23.3%) 39 (37.9%) </p>

<p>Late Bleeding (LB) 
14 (13.6%) 14 (13.6%) 
7 (6.8%) 
19 (18.4%) </p>

<p>No Bleeding (WB) 
73 (70.9%) 49 (47.6%) 72 (69.9%) 45 (43.7%) </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This study evaluated qualitatively bleeding from the femoral 
head in hip osteoarthritis regarding the four quadrants defined 
by the authors. Osteoarthritis is a disease that often deforms 
significantly the femoral head. Thus, it was expected that the 
disease caused a modification (interruption or decrease) in 
blood flow pattern around the neck and femoral head, particu-
larly to the region with the lowest degree of osteoarthritis. The 
absence of bleeding in the anterior and superior quadrants 
(±70%) could be related to a high incidence of osteoarthritis 
and/or bone remodeling in this region, responsible for pain and 
movement limitation. 
The intraosseous vascular anatomy of the proximal femur has 
been described in other studies. 
1-6,8,11,13,16 The main blood su-
pply of the femoral head is through the deep branch of the 
medial circumflex artery, which is constant in its extra capsular 
segment originating two to four superior retinacular vessels, and 
occasionally inferior retinacular vessels. 
17 However, the femoral 
head could be completely infused exclusively by its superiors 
retinacular vessels. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>On the other hand, among other minor sources, there are the 
medial epiphyseal artery, responsible for the parafoveal region, 
the metaphyseal artery branches and lateral femoral circumflex 
artery. Despite descriptions in the literature, the study of ana-
tomical dissection of the medial circumflex artery by Gautier 
et al. 
11 and Ganz et al., 
17 the authors found no anastomoses 
with the ascending branch of the lateral femoral circumflex ar-
tery in the femoral neck region. These anastomoses were pre-
sent only in patients under one year old. Thus, it is confirmed 
the little representation of the lateral femoral circumflex artery 
in the vascular supply of the femoral head. On the other hand, 
that study established a relative frequency of anastomosis 
between the medial femoral circumflex artery and a branch of 
the inferior gluteal artery along the piriformis muscle, responsible </p>

<p>Acta Ortop Bras. 2015;23(5):268-70 </p>



<p>for vascular compensation for any possible injury to the medial 
femoral circumflex artery. 
Despite the different degrees of macroscopic arthritis observed 
in different patients in the trans-operatory, this factor was not 
statistically significant in the qualitative assessment of bleeding 
from the femoral head per quadrants. Regardless of the degree 
of osteoarthritis, the vasculature to the femoral head seems to 
follow the path of the main artery. </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>The authors agree that this study has some limitations, mainly 
due to the fact of presenting bleeding subjectively rather than 
quantitatively. However, this research is the first in the literature 
that discusses the issue from this point of view and shows that 
the pattern of bleeding basically follows the medial circumflex </p>

<p>artery, without correlation with BMI, gender or type/degree of 
osteoarthritis. Osteoarthritis of the hip does not seem to modify 
the pattern of blood flow of the femoral head, and there is no 
evidence to support the fact that circulation in the femoral head 
decreases with aging. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>CONClUSIONS </p>

<p>Macroscopic and subjective assessment of bleeding from 
the femoral head with osteoarthritis in 103 hips submitted to 
total primary arthroplasty showed that the anterior and supe-
rior quadrant had the lowest bleeding after bone perforation, 
while the posterior and inferior quadrants recorded a higher 
early bleeding. </p>



<p>Acta Ortop Bras. 2015;23(5):268-70 </p>

</text></tei>