<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4073352" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT. Regulatory T cells (Tregs) suppress the immune system and maintain the homeostasis of the immune system in healthy dogs. In 
septic patients, the percentage of circulating Tregs is increasing, which may cause the sepsis-induced immunosuppression. This study was 
performed to investigate the changes of the percentage of Tregs in total lymphocytes of the peripheral blood in the experimental canine 
endotoxemia model. The animals injected with a high dose lipopolysaccharide (LPS) induced severe leukopenia followed by leukocytosis, 
but the total lymphocytes number was relatively consistent. As a result of flow cytometric analysis, the percentage of Tregs in total lym-
phocytes of the peripheral blood was 8.45 ± 1.30% (day 0), and it temporarily decreased 2.54 ± 1.16% (day 1) and increased continuously 
until the end of the experiment (14.34 ± 4.10% on day 3 and 25.70 ± 7.39% on day 7), respectively. This study provides basic information 
in physiologic and immunologic changes in Tregs in dogs with sepsis model. 
D. YU, J. KIM, C. PARK AND J. PARK </p>

<p>
cytes compared with CD4 (+)/CD25 (+)/isotype control (+) 
cells. Absolute numbers of lymphocytes were calculated by 
multiplying percentage of Tregs by absolute lymphocyte 
counts in CBC. Flow cytometry analysis was performed 
by a FACS Calibur flow cytometer (Becton Dickinson Im-
munocytometry Systems, San Jose, CA, U.S.A.). Data were 
acquired from a minimum of 10,000 events. Data analyses 
were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">FCS Express</rs> (FCS Express Version 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">De Novo Software</rs>). For statistics, data were analyzed by 
Student's t-test with Levene's test for equality of varience 
(parametric) or Mann-Whitney U test (non-parametric) after 
Shapiro-Wilk normalization test in <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, U.S.A.). Data are represented as mean ± 
S.D. A probability (P) value of &lt;0.05 was considered to be 
statistically significant. 
After high concentrations of LPS were injected into the 
blood vessels, dogs in the experimental group showed fever, 
vomiting and diarrhea within an hour, which are the com-</p>

<p>mon symptoms of canine endotoxemia [19, 23]. Before the 
LPS injection, the mean total white blood cell (WBC) counts 
of 8 male beagles were 8.56 ± 1.97 × 10 3 /µl. In the experi-
mental group, however, leukocytosis was observed one day 
after the LPS injection (WBC counts, 21.03 × 10 3 /µl, P&lt;0.05 
vs. control) (Fig. 2A). Total lymphocytes numbers on days 0, 
1, 3 and 7 were not significantly time dependently changed 
(0.95 ± 0.03, 0.85 ± 0.02, 0.88 ± 0.03 and 0.93 ± 0.02 × 10 3 / 
µl, respectively). 
In terms of Tregs population in this model, the percentage 
of Tregs was 8.45 ± 1.30% of total lymphocytes in peripheral 
blood before LPS injection (1.24 ± 0.43% of blood, absolute 
count of 75.2 ± 23.7/µl). This is similar Treg population 
result compared to a previous study (1.00% of peripheral 
blood from under 2 years of dogs) [14]. After LPS injection, 
the percentage of CD4 (+)/CD25 (+)/FoxP3 (+) T cells in 
total lymphocytes decreased on the first day after the LPS 
injection (LPS, 2.54 ± 1.16%; control, 8.54 ± 2.60; P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Identification of canine Tregs using CD4, CD25 and FoxP3 antibody. Lymphocytes were discriminated in terms of forward-and 
light-scatter (A) and CD4, CD25 double positive cells were recognized after gating lymphocytes (B) and then Foxp3 positive cells were 
calculated from the gated cells in B, compared with an irrelevant isotype-matched antibody (mouse IgG, control for FoxP3 staining, 
black line) (C). FoxP3 positive area was calculated including less than 1% of isotype-matched antibody stained cells. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Changes in total leukocyte counts (a) and absolute number of CD4 (+)/CD25 (+)/FoxP3 (+) T 
cells in total lymphocytes by flow cytometry analysis (b) during 7 days of LPS injection. Leukocytosis 
was presented at 1 day after LPS injection. The absolute number of CD4 (+)/CD25 (+)/FoxP3 (+) 
T cells was decreased in 1 day after LPS injection, but continuously increased until day 7. Data 
represent mean ± SD *P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01 versus control group at each time. </p>

<p>TREGS IN CANINE ENDOTOXEMIA </p>



<p>vs. control). And, after that, it increased gradually on day 3 
and day 7 after the LPS injection, respectively, compared 
with control group (14.34 ± 4.10%, P&lt;0.001 vs. control: 
7.27 ± 0.95) and 7 (25.70 ± 7.39%, P&lt;0.001 vs. control: 
7.40 ± 0.92) (Fig. 2B). The absolute numbers of Tregs in 
peripheral blood were 25.8 ± 10.2/µl (day 1, P&lt;0.001 vs. 
control: 106.4 ± 63.7), 132.2 ± 40.4/µl (day 3, P&lt;0.01 vs. 
control: 75.4 ± 35.7) and 258.9 ± 89.9/µl (day 7, P&lt;0.001 vs. 
control: 102.3 ± 39.3). 
In this study, we found transient decrease and persistent 
increment of Tregs in dogs after LPS stimulation. The idea 
of the whole study was to observe how much the percentage 
or numbers of Tregs would change in a canine endotoxemia 
model. Since CARS (compensatory anti-inflammatory re-
sponse syndrome) followed by profound pro-inflammatory 
state in septic crisis results in immunosuppressive state that 
cannot protect host from the primary infections of secondary 
nosocomial infections [2, 13], determining the host immune 
response whether it is up-regulated or down-regulated is 
very useful to predict the outcome of the sepsis. Specifically, 
Tregs, a subset of T lymphocytes, play an important role in 
maintaining the immune system and are essential for the ac-
tive suppression [1, 4, 13]. Transient diminished Tregs after 
one day of canine endotoxemia may be because of hyperin-
flammatory response in early stage of the sepsis. However, 
on days 3 and 7, there were significant continuous increase 
of percentages of Tregs. This can be explained the compen-
satory anti-inflammatory response in the later stage of sepsis 
[2]. Understanding kinetics of immune functional changes 
is an important clue to understand septic scenario and to 
predict the outcome. This kinetics of immune response is 
accordance with previous reports which revealed that the im-
mune failure could occur within the first week of the sepsis 
in a rodent model [11] and human septic patients [10]. This 
result can be used as a preliminary study to observe the ki-
netics of the canine immune status in sepsis. Further studies 
to investigate increased Tregs function should be performed 
in the future. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENT. This research was supported by 
Basic Science Research Program through the National Re-
search Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of 
Education, Science and Technology (KRF-2011-0011105). </p>



<p>D. YU, J. KIM, C. PARK AND J. PARK </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>