<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4551318" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Multiple angiogenic cues modulate phosphotyrosine signaling to promote vascu-
logenesis and angiogenesis. Despite its functional and clinical importance, how vascular cells 
integrate phosphotyrosine-dependent signaling to elicit cytoskeletal changes required for 
endothelial morphogenesis remains poorly understood. The family of Nck adaptors couples 
phosphotyrosine signals with actin dynamics and therefore is well positioned to orchestrate 
cellular processes required in vascular formation and remodeling. Culture of endothelial cells 
in three-dimensional collagen matrices in the presence of VEGF stimulation was combined 
with molecular genetics, optical imaging, and biochemistry to show that Nck-dependent ac-
tin remodeling promotes endothelial cell elongation and proper organization of VE-cadherin 
intercellular junctions. Major morphogenetic defects caused by abrogation of Nck signaling 
included loss of endothelial apical-basal polarity and impaired lumenization. Time-lapse imag-
ing using a Förster resonance energy transfer biosensor, immunostaining with phospho-
specific antibodies, and GST pull-down assays showed that Nck determines spatiotemporal 
patterns of Cdc42/aPKC activation during endothelial morphogenesis. Our results demon-
strate that Nck acts as an important hub integrating angiogenic cues with cytoskeletal chang-
es that enable endothelial apical-basal polarization and lumen formation. These findings 
point to Nck as an emergent target for effective antiangiogenic therapy. </p>

<p>The development of a functional vasculature involves the assembly 
of the primary capillary plexus, a process called vasculogenesis, and 
subsequent network expansion and remodeling through various 
mechanisms of angiogenesis (Carmeliet, 2003; Adams and Alitalo, 
2007). Vascular morphogenesis is orchestrated by multiple angio-
genic cues that elicit a coordinated response of endothelial cells, 
including proliferation, transitions in polarity states, directional mi-
gration, matrix remodeling, and lumenization (Adams and Alitalo, </p>

<p>2007; Iruela-Arispe and Davis, 2009; Davis et al., 2011). Cytoskeletal 
remodeling-in particular, actin dynamics-plays a key role in the 
regulation of vascular morphogenesis and homeostasis (Lamalice 
et al., 2007; Bayless and Johnson, 2011). Cytoskeletal remodeling 
also underlies the aberrant endothelial response leading to patho-
logical angiogenesis and vascular destabilization induced by an im-
balance in angiogenic cues (Weis and Cheresh, 2011). 
Signals that alter tyrosine phosphorylation are primarily involved 
in regulation of vascular morphogenesis and vessel stability (Jeltsch 
et al., 2013). Phosphorylation sites resulting from activation of tyro-
sine kinases provide a platform for the assembly of signaling com-
plexes through the recruitment of adaptor and scaffold proteins 
containing phosphotyrosine-binding modules (Machida and Mayer, 
2005). The family of noncatalytic regions of tyrosine kinase (Nck 
adaptor proteins; hereafter Nck), consisting of Nck1/α and Nck2/β, 
links tyrosine phosphorylation with downstream effectors that mod-
ulate cytoskeletal dynamics (Li et al., 2001; Buday et al., 2002). 
These modular adaptors, composed of three N-terminal Src homol-
ogy 3 (SH3) domains and one C-terminal SH2 domain, are required 
for the development of mesoderm-derived embryonic structures 
(Bladt et al., 2003), including the cardiovascular system (Clouthier 
et al., 2015). We and others have shown that Nck plays an important </p>

<p>Monitoring Editor 
Jonathan Chernoff 
Fox Chase Cancer Center </p>

<p>Received: Jun 4, 2015 
Revised: Jun 30, 2015 
Accepted: Jul 1, 2015 </p>

<p>This article was published online ahead of print in MBoC in Press (http://www 
.molbiolcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1091/mbc.E15-06-0338) on July 8, 2015. 
Address correspondence to: Gonzalo M. Rivera (grivera@cvm.tamu.edu). </p>

<p>© 2015 Chaki et al. This article is distributed by The American Society for Cell 
Biology under license from the author(s). Two months after publication it is avail-
able to the public under an Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unport-
ed Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc 
-sa/3.0). 
"ASCB </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," "The American Society for Cell Biology </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>," and "Molecular Biology of 
the Cell 
® " are registered trademarks of The American Society for Cell Biology. </p>

<p>Abbreviations used:aPKC, atypical protein kinase C; Cdc42, cell division control 
protein homologue 42; FRET, Förster resonance energy transfer; HUVEC, human 
umbilical vein endothelial cell; Nck, noncatalytic region of tyrosine kinase; 
N-WASp, neuronal Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein; PDXL, podocalyxin; 3D, 
three-dimensional; VE-cadherin, vascular endothelial cadherin; VEGF, vascular 
endothelial growth factor. </p>

<p>Sankar P. Chaki </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>, Rola Barhoumi </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>, and Gonzalo M. Rivera </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Department of Veterinary Pathobiology and </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Department of Veterinary Integrative Biosciences, Texas A&amp;M University, 
College Station, TX 77843-4467 </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>cells formed large tubes with well-defined lumens (Figure 2, A and 
B, left). In contrast, Nck-silenced cells exhibited a more-rounded ap-
pearance and far-less-extended cell-cell junctions, with inclusion of 
large cytoplasmic vacuoles and endocytic vesicles (Figure 2, A and 
B, right, and C). Typically, hollow structures formed by Nck-silenced 
cells showed intracellular or intercellular lumens of decreased diam-
eter (Figure 2C). Western blot analysis performed on cell extracts 
collected from 3D cultures showed a decrease in Nck levels in the 
silenced group (Figure 2D). Collectively these results point to an 
essential role of Nck adaptors in endothelial tubulogenesis. </p>

<p>Loss of Nck disrupts the cytoskeletal architecture 
and the distribution of vascular endothelial cadherin </p>

<p>Previous studies demonstrated an essential role of vascular endo-
thelial cadherin (VE-cadherin) and the organization of endothelial 
cell-to-cell adherens junctions in the establishment of endothelial 
polarity and vascular lumen formation (Strilic et al., 2009; 
Lampugnani et al., 2010). The phenotype exhibited by Nck-silenced 
endothelial cells in the present study (Figures 1 and 2) prompted us 
to investigate the role of Nck in the distribution of VE-cadherin and 
the organization of endothelial adherens junctions. First, we hy-
pothesized that Nck is enriched at VE-cadherin cell-cell junctions. 
Because commercially available anti-Nck antibodies are not suitable 
for immunofluorescence, we resorted to expression of fluorescently 
tagged Nck. Thus we prepared monolayers of endothelial cells ex-
pressing Nck-enhanced yellow fluorescent protein (EYFP) and per-
formed immunostaining of endogenous VE-cadherin and/or cortac-
tin, an Nck binding partner and regulator of junctional actin 
assembly (Han et al., 2014). Consistent with observations in epithe-
lial monolayers (Han et al., 2014), endogenous cortactin colocalized 
with junctional VE-cadherin (Supplemental Figure S2A, top). In sup-
port of our hypothesis, Nck-EYFP accumulated at VE-cadherin/cor-
tactin-rich cell-cell junctions (Supplemental Figure S2, A and B). 
In light of the foregoing findings, we hypothesized that Nck 
modulates junctional actin/VE-cadherin dynamics. To test this hy-
pothesis, serum-starved, confluent monolayers of human umbilical 
vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) were left untreated or subjected to 
a calcium switch assay (Zandy et al., 2007) followed by staining of 
endogenous VE-cadherin and F-actin. Results show that Nck deple-
tion disrupted the organization and dynamics of assembly of VE-
cadherin-based cell-cell junctions (Supplemental Figure S3). Con-
trol and, to a lesser extent, Nck-rescued cells presented robust 
localization of VE-cadherin staining at sites of cell-cell contact that 
displayed an organization resembling a trabecular meshwork (Sup-
plemental Figure S3A, top). In contrast, Nck-silenced cells exhibited 
decreased localization of VE-cadherin at sites of cell-cell contact 
and almost complete absence of the trabecular meshwork architec-
ture. In addition, calcium switch experiments revealed that Nck-
depleted cells had a slight but significant (p &lt; 0.05) delay in the re-
assembly of cell-cell contacts compared with control or Nck-rescued 
cells (Supplemental Figure S3, A and B). Of note, total levels of VE-
cadherin were similar in control, Nck-silenced, and Nck-rescued 
cells (Supplemental Figure S3C). 
Next we determined the distribution of endogenous VE-cad-
herin and the organization of cell-cell junctions in endothelial cells 
undergoing morphogenesis in 3D collagen matrices (Figure 3A and 
Supplemental Animation S1). Whereas control and rescued cells de-
veloped tubes displaying large, patent lumens and strong accumu-
lation of VE-cadherin at extended cell-cell contacts, Nck-depleted 
cells formed clusters that failed to develop into a tubular network 
and exhibited cytosolic accumulation and patchy distribution of VE-
cadherin at cell-cell contacts. In addition, control and rescued cells </p>

<p>role in angiogenic factor-stimulated cytoskeletal remodeling and 
directional migration of endothelial cells (Stoletov et al., 2001; 
Kiosses et al., 2002; Lamalice et al., 2006; Anselmi et al., 2012; 
Chaki et al., 2013). However, how Nck regulates molecular and 
cellular mechanisms enabling endothelial morphogenesis remains 
largely undetermined. Using a combination of molecular genetics 
and three-dimensional (3D) quantitative optical microscopy we now 
provide evidence that Nck regulates endothelial apical-basal polar-
ization and lumenization through the correct localization and activa-
tion of the cell division control protein homologue 42 (Cdc42)/ 
atypical protein kinase C (aPKC) polarity complex. These findings 
highlight Nck as a key molecular hub downstream of multiple 
angiogenic cues and potential target for the development of effec-
tive antiangiogenic therapies. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Nck is required for endothelial cord formation </p>

<p>Our previous findings showing that Nck silencing impairs front-back 
polarity and directional migration of endothelial cells in two dimen-
sions (Chaki et al., 2013) prompted us to examine the role of Nck in 
endothelial cell morphogenesis. The formation of solid cords on a 
planar growth factor-reduced matrix involves a cytoskeletal re-
sponse resembling that of capillary morphogenesis. To manipulate 
the cellular levels of Nck (Supplemental Figure S1C), we used a pre-
viously validated loss-of-function approach based on the expression 
of short hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) that consistently induced a &gt;50% 
decrease in Nck1/2 protein levels (Chaki et al., 2013). As a control, 
we used the same silencing vector (pSuper) not expressing shRNAs 
(empty vector). In addition, we rescued Nck1/2-silenced cells with 
retroviral particles harboring an shRNA-resistant mouse Nck2 cDNA 
that resulted in expression levels slightly above that of the endoge-
nous Nck (Chaki et al., 2013). Results show that control cells (empty 
vector), but not cells expressing short hairpins targeting Nck1 and 
Nck2 (shNck1 and 2), developed a robust and well-interconnected 
network of cords (Supplemental Figure S1A). Furthermore, reex-
pression of shRNA-resistant Nck in Nck1/2-silenced cells restored 
cord formation. Quantitative analysis showed a significant (p &lt; 0.01) 
decrease in cord length, number of branching points, and nodes 
in Nck-depleted (shNck1 and 2) versus control or rescued cells 
(Supplemental Figure S1B). </p>

<p>Nck is required for endothelial lumen formation </p>

<p>Lumenization is the process that transforms solid endothelial cords 
into vascular tubes, which is essential for the establishment of an 
efficient circulatory system. To determine more precisely how Nck 
regulates the program of endothelial cell morphogenesis, we per-
formed tube formation assays in 3D collagen I matrices in the pres-
ence of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) stimulation. Tube 
formation in 3D matrices entails matrix remodeling, endothelial cell 
invasion, polarization, and lumenization (Koh et al., 2008b). As 
shown in Figure 1A, control and Nck-rescued cells formed more ro-
bust networks of interconnected tubes in collagen than did Nck-si-
lenced cells. In addition, lumenization was only apparent in control 
and rescued cells, whereas mostly large intracellular vacuoles were 
observed in Nck-depleted cells. Quantitative image analysis dem-
onstrated a significant (p &lt; 0.001) reduction in the number of 
branching points (unpublished data), tube length, and lumen area 
(Figure 1B) in Nck-silenced versus control or rescued cells. 
To gain additional morphological insights, we performed trans-
mission electron microscopy of cells cultured in 3D collagen matri-
ces (Figure 2). By adopting an elongated squamous morphology 
and displaying extended, uninterrupted cell-cell contacts, control </p>

<p>Volume 26 September 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Nck regulates endothelial lumenization | 3049 </p>

<p>revealed that loss of Nck induced a signifi-
cant (p &lt; 0.001) disruption in the cytoskele-
tal organization, evidenced by a reduction 
in the intensity of F-actin bundles, and de-
creased VE-cadherin accumulation at sites 
of cell-cell contact (Figure 3, B and C). In 
addition, the length of cell-cell junctions 
was significantly (p &lt; 0.001) decreased in 
Nck-silenced versus control or rescued cells 
(Figure 3D, top). Total levels of VE-cadherin 
in cell extracts from 3D cultures were similar 
(p &gt; 0.05) in control, rescued, and Nck-si-
lenced cells (Figure 3D, bottom). </p>

<p>Perturbation of Nck signaling leads to 
loss of apical-basal endothelial polarity </p>

<p>Proposed mechanisms of the de novo 
endothelial lumen formation, that is, cord 
and cell hollowing, involve the vesicular de-
livery of fluids and membrane material to ar-
eas of cadherin-mediated cell-cell contacts 
(Sigurbjornsdottir et al., 2014). We hypothe-
sized that the altered junctional VE-cadherin 
and cytoskeletal organization resulting from 
abrogation of Nck signaling leads to defec-
tive cell polarization and, consequently, 
incomplete lumen formation/expansion. To 
test this prediction, we performed immunos-
taining of endogenous podocalyxin (PDXL), 
a highly sialylated transmembrane protein 
involved in lumen expansion that is re-
cruited to endothelial cell-cell contacts in 
a VE-cadherin-dependent manner (Strilic 
et al., 2009). In confluent monolayers of con-
trol and rescued HUVECs, PDXL colocalized 
with VE-cadherin at robust cell-cell contacts 
(Supplemental Figure S4A and Supplemental 
Animation S2). In contrast, monolayers of 
Nck-silenced cells showed a more diffused 
PDXL staining, with increased cytoplasmic 
and decreased junctional accumulation (Sup-
plemental Figure S4B, top and middle). In 
addition, Nck-depleted but not control or 
rescued cells had a decreased (p &lt; 0.01) 
junction-to-cytoplasmic PDXL ratio (Supple-
mental Figure S4B, bottom). Of note, the 
presence of PDXL/VE-cadherin-enriched cy-
toplasmic/membrane vesicles was readily 
apparent in confocal z-stacks from Nck-de-
pleted but not control or rescued monolayers 
(Supplemental Figure S4A and Supplemental 
Animation S2). The presence of PDXL-en-
riched vesicles/clusters in monolayers of Nck-
silenced cells was also confirmed by ground-
state depletion superresolution imaging 
(Supplemental Figure S4C). 
Next we determined the role of Nck in endothelial polarity in 3D 
environments. HUVECs undergoing morphogenesis in collagen I 
were fixed and stained with anti-PDXL, a luminal surface marker, and 
fluorescent phalloidin to visualize the actin cytoskeleton. In control 
and rescued groups, endogenous PDXL localized to luminal mem-
branes of endothelial cells that also displayed strong actin bundles </p>

<p>showed a robust cytoskeletal architecture that included long F-actin 
bundles delimiting extended lumens. Nck-silenced cells, in contrast, 
exhibited significant disruption of the cytoskeletal architecture, in-
cluding the presence of F-actin aggregates and short F-actin bun-
dles surrounding vacuolar and poorly developed hollow structures 
(Figure 3A and Supplemental Animation S1). Image analysis </p>

<p>FIGURE 1: Abrogation of Nck disrupts endothelial lumen formation in 3D collagen matrices. 
(A) Representative DIC images of fields (left; scale bar, 200 μm) and magnification of indicated 
ROIs (right; scale bar, 20 μm) from control, Nck-silenced (shNck1 and 2), and rescued cells. 
Arrows denote patent lumens, and arrowheads indicate intracellular vacuoles. (B) Lumen area 
(left) and tube length (right) in control, Nck-silenced, and rescued cells. Data derived from a total 
of 10 DIC fields from three independent experiments. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>endothelial cell-cell contacts. Quantitative 
image analysis showed a significant (p &lt; 
0.001) decrease in the average fluorescence 
intensity of luminal PDXL (Figure 4C). In ad-
dition, the extent of PDXL localization to lu-
minal region, quantified as percentage of 
the luminal perimeter decorated with PDXL 
staining, was significantly (p &lt; 0.001) re-
duced in Nck-silenced versus control or res-
cued cultures (Figure 4D). The loss of PDXL 
polarization induced by Nck silencing was 
accompanied by disorganization of the ar-
chitecture of actin filaments. Taken together, 
these findings suggest that changes in actin 
organization resulting from abrogation of 
Nck signaling contribute to loss of endothe-
lial cell apical-basal polarity and deficient 
lumen formation. </p>

<p>Nck drives endothelial polarity and 
lumen formation through activation 
of Cdc42 </p>

<p>To ascertain the mechanism by which Nck 
regulates endothelial polarity and tube mor-
phogenesis, we determined patterns of 
Cdc42 activation in cells undergoing mor-
phogenesis in 3D collagen matrices. First, 
the status of endogenous Cdc42 activation 
was ascertained using an antibody that rec-
ognizes the GTP-bound, active form of 
Cdc42 (Baschieri et al., 2014). In contrast to 
the strong luminal localization of endoge-
nous GTP-bound Cdc42 in control and res-
cued cells, active Cdc42 staining was greatly 
decreased and distributed diffusively 
through the cytoplasm in Nck silenced cells 
(Figure 5A and Supplemental Animation 
S4). Remarkably, small lumens occasionally 
formed by Nck-knockdown cells showed al-
most complete absence of active Cdc42. As 
previously noted, the loss of Nck lead to dis-
ruption of the architecture of actin filaments. 
Line scans across sections of 3D cultures 
showed unpolarized distribution and greatly 
decreased overall intensity of active Cdc42 
staining in Nck-silenced versus control/res-
cued cells (Figure 5B). Quantitative image 
analysis showed a significant (p &lt; 0.01) de-
crease in the average fluorescence intensity 
of luminal active Cdc42 (Figure 5C). To fur-
ther assess the role of Nck in the activation 
of Cdc42, we performed pull-down assays 
of endogenous GTP-bound Cdc42 in cell 
extracts obtained from 3D cultures (Koh et al., 2008b) using immo-
bilized Pak1 PBD domains (Benard and Bokoch, 2002). Consistent 
with the immunostaining findings, active/GTP-bound but not total 
Cdc42 was reduced (p &lt; 0.05) in cell extracts from Nck-silenced cells 
compared to control or rescued cells (Figure 5, D and E). 
To determine spatiotemporal patterns of Cdc42 activation in 
3D cultures, we performed time-lapse confocal imaging of endo-
thelial cells stably expressing the Raichu Cdc42 Förster resonance 
energy transfer (FRET) probe (Hirata et al., 2012). In contrast to </p>

<p>delimiting the abluminal surface of well-developed tubes (Figure 4A 
and Supplemental Animation S3). Line scans encompassing wall 
and lumens of control and rescued endothelial tubes clearly showed 
the polarized distribution of PDXL and actin bundles (Figure 4B). In 
contrast, within the small number of the 3D structures formed by 
Nck-silenced cells, the distribution of PDXL and the architecture of 
F-actin were profoundly disrupted (Figure 4, A and B). Consistent 
with findings in monolayers, Nck depletion led to diffuse cytoplas-
mic distribution and slight enrichment of PDXL in poorly developed </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Loss of Nck impairs endothelial cell morphology in cells cultured in 3D collagen 
matrices. (A) Phase contrast images of 3D structures formed by control and Nck-silenced cells. 
(B) High-power transmission electron micrographs of ROIs indicated in A. Areas marked by 
rectangles are shown in greater detail at bottom. (C) Low-power transmission electron 
micrograph of the 3D structure formed by Nck-silenced cells shown in A. The highlighted ROI 
correspond to images shown in B (right). Intracellular vacuoles (*) and small lumen delimited by 
two cells (**) are indicated. (D) Western blot showing Nck and β-actin (loading control) levels in 
cell extracts from 3D cultures. </p>

<p>Volume 26 September 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Nck regulates endothelial lumenization | 3051 </p>

<p>the robust activation of Cdc42 observed in 
cultures of control and rescued cells, the 
overall Cdc42 activation was significantly 
decreased in Nck-silenced cells (Figure 6, 
A and B). Compared to Nck-depleted 
cells, control and rescued cells showed 
more polarized Cdc42 activation, as evi-
denced by the progressive increase in 
FRET/teal fluorescent protein (TFP) signal 
from the abluminal to the luminal mem-
brane (Figure 6, A and C). A striking asso-
ciation between localized Cdc42 activa-
tion and lumen expansion was present in 
control and rescued but not Nck-silenced 
cells (Supplemental Movie S1). </p>

<p>Nck-dependent endothelial 
lumenization involves activation 
of aPKC </p>

<p>The aPKC isoforms PKCζ and PKCι/λ form a 
stable complex with Par6 and contribute to 
the establishment of polarity by binding 
Par3, which, in turn, interacts with proteins 
of the junctional complex (Rosse et al., 
2010). Previous studies showed that disrup-
tion of the Cdc42-Par3-Par6-aPKC polarity 
complex leads to impaired endothelial cell 
lumen and tube formation in 3D collagen 
matrices (Bayless and Davis, 2002; Koh 
et al., 2008a). Thus, to ascertain the contri-
bution of Nck to the spatial regulation of 
aPKC activation during endothelial mor-
phogenesis, we performed immunostaining 
of endogenous, phosphorylated aPKC 
(p-aPKC) using an antibody that recognizes 
phosphorylated aPKCζ (phospho-T410) and 
aPKCι/λ (phospho-T412). Consistent with 
spatial patterns of Cdc42 activation, 
strongly polarized p-aPKC staining was ob-
served in control and rescued endothelial 
tubes (Figure 7, A and B). As shown in Sup-
plemental Animation S5, control and res-
cued tubes typically displayed intense lumi-
nal p-aPKC signal along with well-organized 
abluminal F-actin bundles. In contrast, 
structures formed by Nck-silenced cells </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Silencing of Nck disrupts the organization of F-actin and the distribution of 
VE-cadherin in cells cultured in 3D collagen matrices. (A) Confocal images showing F-actin (red), 
endogenous VE-cadherin (green), and nuclei (blue). Lumens (L) are indicated. The ROIs (dotted </p>

<p>squares) were magnified and are shown to 
the right. (B) Surface plots showing pixel 
intensities for field images in A. (C) Actin and 
VE-cadherin accumulation at cell-cell 
contacts. Mean fluorescence intensity was 
quantified in 23-50 equal-size ROIs pooled 
from three independent experiments. 
(D) Quantitation of VE-cadherin cell-cell 
junctional lengths (top). Data represent mean 
junctional length (μm) determined in a total 
of 25-30 junctions pooled from three 
individual experiments. The Western blots 
(bottom) show the levels of VE-cadherin, Nck, 
and GAPDH (loading control) in cell extracts 
from 3D cultures. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>role for Nck in the establishment of endothelial apical-basal polarity 
and lumen formation through a mechanism that involves spatiotem-
poral regulation of the Cdc42/aPKC polarity complex. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The present study provides evidence that Nck, a family of multido-
main adaptors, plays an essential role in the coordination of key 
cellular behaviors during endothelial morphogenesis. We show that </p>

<p>showed diffuse (unpolarized) and significantly decreased overall p-
aPKC staining. Quantitative image analysis showed a significant 
decrease in the average fluorescence intensity of luminal p-aPKC in 
Nck-silencing versus control and rescued cells (Figure 7C). Consis-
tent with these findings, levels of phosphorylated (active) aPKC, 
determined by Western blotting, were significantly decreased in 
extracts from 3D cultures of Nck-silenced cells compared to control 
or rescued cells (Figure 7D). Collectively these results show a key </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Nck regulates endothelial polarity and lumen formation in cells cultured in 3D collagen matrices. 
(A) Confocal images showing the cytoskeletal architecture (F-actin; red), distribution of endogenous podocalyxin (PDXL; 
green), and nuclei (DNA; blue). Lumens (L) are indicated. The ROIs (dotted squares) were magnified and are shown to 
the right. (B) Line scans showing intensities along the solid white lines displayed in A. (C) Average luminal PDXL 
fluorescence intensity. From 35 to 50 luminal ROIs from images collected in three independent experiments were 
included in the analysis. (D) Percentage of the luminal perimeter decorated with PDXL staining. From 25 to 30 lumens 
from images collected in three independent experiments were analyzed. </p>

<p>Volume 26 September 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Nck regulates endothelial lumenization | 3053 </p>

<p>FIGURE 5: Loss of Nck disrupts activation of endogenous Cdc42 in cells cultured in 3D collagen matrices. (A) Confocal 
images showing the cytoskeletal architecture (F-actin; red), distribution of GTP-bound Cdc42 (Cdc42 </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>; green), and nuclei 
(DNA; blue). Lumens (L) are indicated. The ROIs (dotted squares) were magnified and are shown to the right. Scale bar, 15 
μm. (B) Line scans showing intensities along the solid white lines displayed in A. (C) Quantification of luminal Cdc42 
fluorescence intensity. Average pixel intensity was extracted from 35-50 ROIs from images acquired in three independent 
experiments. (D) Representative Western blots showing levels of GTP-bound Cdc42 (PBD 
Pak1 pull-down assays), total 
Cdc42, Nck, and GAPDH in cell extracts obtained from 3D cultures. (E) Quantification of active Cdc42. The intensity of 
bands corresponding to active Cdc42 (PBD 
Pak1 pull-down assays) was normalized by the intensity of bands corresponding 
to total Cdc42 in cell extracts and expressed as percentage of control cultures (n = 3 independent experiments). </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>effectors (Pawson, 2007; Good et al., 2011). The present findings 
support the hypothesis that Nck acts as a hub integrating signals 
driving endothelial morphogenesis. </p>

<p>Requirement of Nck in endothelial morphogenesis </p>

<p>Bladt et al. (2003) described profound developmental defects in 
mesoderm-derived tissues and embryonic lethality in mice caused 
by inactivation of Nck (both Nck1 and Nck2). Similarly, findings from 
a recent study showed that constitutive deletion of Nck in the endo-
thelium of mice results in impaired cardiovascular development and 
embryonic lethality (Clouthier et al., 2015). Although the study by </p>

<p>abrogation of Nck disrupts the architectural organization of the actin 
cytoskeleton and VE-cadherin junctions, resulting in loss of endo-
thelial apical-basal polarity and impaired lumen formation. Through 
the combination of 3D live-cell imaging and biochemistry, this study 
highlights new mechanistic insights by which Nck modulates the 
spatiotemporal activation of the Cdc42/aPKC polarity complex. 
These finding are consistent with current views that, rather than 
simple docking or molecular linkers, adaptor proteins integrate 
and specify the flow of information in signaling networks by dynami-
cally engaging distinct interaction partners at specific subcellular 
locations, promoting cooperative binding and clustering signaling </p>

<p>FIGURE 6: Nck modulates the spatiotemporal activation of Cdc42 in endothelial cells cultured in 3D collagen matrices. 
(A) FRET/TFP ratio images selected from time-lapse series of 3D cultures of HUVECs expressing the Raichu-Cdc42 FRET 
biosensor. The ROIs (dotted squares) were magnified and are shown to the right. The images represent FRET activity 
coded by the color scale (red, high activity; blue, low activity). (B) Activity of the Raichu-Cdc42 FRET probe (whole fields) 
from time-lapse sequences (n = 4-6 cells/condition from each of three independent experiments). (C) Line scans 
showing intensities along the solid white lines in the field images shown in A. </p>

<p>Volume 26 September 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Nck regulates endothelial lumenization | 3055 </p>

<p>FIGURE 7: Loss of Nck disrupts the activation of endogenous aPKC in cells cultured in 3D collagen matrices. 
(A) Confocal images showing the cytoskeletal architecture (F-actin; red), distribution of active aPKC (p-aPKC; green), 
and nuclei (DNA; blue). Lumens (L) are indicated. The ROIs (dotted squares) were magnified and are shown to the right. 
(B) Line scans showing intensities along the solid white lines displayed in A. (C) Quantification of luminal p-aPKC 
fluorescence intensity. Average pixel intensity was extracted from 35-50 ROIs from images acquired in three 
independent experiments. (D) Representative Western blots showing levels of p-aPKC, total aPKC, Nck, and GAPDH in 
cell extracts from 3D cultures. (E) Quantification of active aPKC. The intensity of bands corresponding to p-aPKC was 
normalized by the intensity of bands corresponding to total aPKC and expressed as percentage of control cultures 
(n = 3 independent experiments). a, b, p &lt; 0.05. </p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>

<p>formation (Davis and Camarillo, 1996; Kamei et al., 2006; Herbert 
et al., 2009; Strilic et al., 2009; Herwig et al., 2011). Nonetheless, 
the establishment of endothelial apical-basal polarity is believed to 
be a prerequisite for endothelial lumenization. Among various 
molecular players, β1 integrin (Zovein et al., 2010) and VE-cadherin 
(Lampugnani et al., 2010) have been identified as key drivers of en-
dothelial polarity and lumen formation. Both β1 integrin and VE-
cadherin coordinate the recruitment of actin filaments and apical 
proteins, including sialomucins, to the incipient endothelial lumen 
(Strilic et al., 2009; Zovein et al., 2010). Remarkably, the disruption 
of junctional VE-cadherin and F-actin organization induced by Nck 
silencing caused delocalization of the sialomucin PDXL and loss of 
apical-basal endothelial polarity. Accordingly, Nck silencing resulted 
in negligible luminal formation or the formation of intracellular vacu-
oles and intercellular luminal structures that failed to coalesce/ 
expand. Thus we propose that Nck promotes endothelial cell inter-
face elongation by a mechanism that involves localized actin polym-
erization/stabilization and, consequently, the organization of junc-
tional VE-cadherin. 
Coordination and interdependence of cadherin and integrin 
adhesions, the "adhesive cross-talk," is mediated by convergent 
signaling mediated by shared effectors, including adaptors/scaf-
folds and Rho GTPases (Weber et al., 2011). For example, a recent 
study showed that integrin β1 function is required for proper 
localization of VE-cadherin, endothelial cell-cell junction integrity, 
and the formation of stable, nonleaky blood vessels through a 
mechanism that involves RhoA and Rap1 activation (Yamamoto 
et al., 2015). Of interest, mouse embryos lacking endothelial Nck 
showed compromised vascular integrity, including increased 
edema and profuse hemorrhages (Clouthier et al., 2015). We 
showed previously that Nck modulates integrin α5β1-extracellular 
matrix adhesion force and endothelial cell stiffness by regulating 
the activation of RhoA (Chaki et al., 2013). Collectively these find-
ings suggest that Nck integrates signaling networks responsive to 
cell-cell and cell-matrix cues. </p>

<p>Nck drives endothelial polarity and lumenization 
through Cdc42/aPKC </p>

<p>The Rho GTPases-molecular switches that regulate cytoskeletal 
dynamics (Hall, 2012)-are major determinants of cell polarity 
(Roignot et al., 2013; Rodriguez-Boulan and Macara, 2014). 
In particular, Cdc42 (Bayless and Davis, 2002; Koh et al., 2008a; 
Qi et al., 2011; Jin et al., 2013; Liu et al., 2013) and its effector the 
Par3/Par6/aPKC complex (Kamei et al., 2006; Koh et al., 2008a; Qi 
et al., 2011) are required for endothelial lumen formation. Here we 
demonstrate that Nck specifies spatiotemporal patterns of Cdc42/ 
aPKC activation during endothelial morphogenesis. Previous stud-
ies documented the cooperation between Nck and Cdc42 in the 
activation of N-WASp-stimulated actin polymerization (Dart et al., 
2012; Humphries et al., 2014). Further, the Cdc42/Par6/aPKC 
polarity axis was shown to regulate adherens junction stability 
through modulation of N-WASp/Arp2/3-dependent actin remod-
eling (Georgiou et al., 2008). Because Nck stimulates N-WASp/ 
Arp2-3-dependent actin polymerization (Rivera et al., 2004; Ditlev 
et al., 2012), we postulate that Nck modulates morphogenesis by 
linking spatiotemporally restricted activation of Cdc42-dependent 
polarity signals, junctional actin polymerization, and VE-cadherin 
adhesion dynamics. Given its significant role in signaling down-
stream of integrin (Tu et al., 1998; Goicoechea et al., 2002; 
Vaynberg et al., 2005), VEGF (Stoletov et al., 2001; Lamalice et al., 
2006), and guidance receptors (Cheng et al., 2002; Li et al., 2002; 
Fan et al., 2003; Miura et al., 2009), the Nck hub appears uniquely </p>

<p>Clouthier et al. (2015) established that Nck is required for endothe-
lial tip cell sprouting, insights into the precise role of Nck in the regu-
lation of angiogenesis were limited by early embryonic lethality. 
We and others have shown that Nck plays an important role in 
angiogenic factor-stimulated cytoskeletal remodeling and directional 
migration of endothelial cells (Stoletov et al., 2001; Kiosses et al., 
2002; Lamalice et al., 2006; Chaki et al., 2013). However, the cellular 
mechanisms underlying Nck-regulated endothelial morphogenesis 
have remained largely unknown. Our present findings disclose new 
links between Nck-mediated actin remodeling and key cellular mech-
anisms necessary for endothelial lumen formation, including intercel-
lular junctional elongation and apical-basal polarization. Remarkably, 
Nck silencing suppressed lumen formation or resulted in intracellular 
vacuoles/small luminal structures that fail to coalesce and/or expand. 
We speculate that Nck contributes to endothelial lumenization 
through regulation of the fusogenic, adhesion, and matrix-remodel-
ing machineries of endothelial cells. </p>

<p>Loss of Nck disrupts actin and the organization 
of VE-cadherin cell-cell junctions </p>

<p>VE-cadherin cell-cell adhesion is required for vascular morphogen-
esis and stabilization (Montero-Balaguer et al., 2009). Dynamics of 
actin filaments and endothelial adherens junctions are reciprocally 
regulated (Abu Taha et al., 2014). Here we provide evidence that 
Nck silencing results in altered endothelial cell morphology, disor-
ganization of the actin cytoskeleton, and disruption of VE-cadherin 
cell-cell junctions. This is consistent with recent findings in zebrafish 
showing that VE-cadherin ablation impairs actin polymerization, 
stalk cell elongation, and the extension of the endothelial cell-cell 
interface (Sauteur et al., 2014). Given that pharmacological inhibi-
tion of actin polymerization phenocopies the junctional defects re-
sulting from VE-cadherin deletion (Sauteur et al., 2014), it is possible 
that localized actin polymerization stimulated by Nck promotes 
junction elongation. 
Arp2/3-dependent actin nucleation and filament stabilization are 
involved in the formation of cortical actin rings that support intercel-
lular junctional organization (Kovacs et al., 2011; Abu Taha et al., 
2014). Arp2/3-dependent actin polymerization at endothelial cell-
cell junctions is promoted by the nucleation-promoting factors neu-
ronal Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein (N-WASp; Rajput et al., 
2013) and cortactin (Boguslavsky et al., 2007; Han et al., 2014). In 
vitro, Nck forms a complex with cortactin and WIP/N-WASp that 
stimulates Arp2/3-dependent actin polymerization (Tehrani et al., 
2007). In living cells, we demonstrated that clustering of Nck stimu-
lates Arp2/3-stimulated actin polymerization through the activation 
of WIP/N-WASp (Rivera et al., 2004; Ditlev et al., 2012). Thus the 
present findings showing that Nck colocalizes with cortactin at VE-
cadherin cell-cell junctions support the hypothesis that Nck plays a 
key role in polymerization/stabilization of junctional actin filaments 
through the cortactin/N-WASp/Arp2/3 axis. Interestingly, zonula oc-
cludens (ZO-1), a protein that bridges the cadherin/catenin complex 
and junctional actin filaments (Itoh et al., 1997), is required for nor-
mal cadherin-dependent actin organization during development 
(Lockwood et al., 2008). Because ZO-1 is recruited to actin filaments 
induced by membrane-targeted Nck (Hanajima-Ozawa et al., 2007), 
it represents a plausible link between endothelial adherens junction 
dynamics and Nck-dependent actin remodeling. </p>

<p>Loss of Nck disrupts endothelial polarity 
and lumen formation </p>

<p>Depending on vessel type/cellular context, distinct cellular mecha-
nisms are used alternatively or in combination during vascular lumen </p>

<p>Volume 26 September 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Nck regulates endothelial lumenization | 3057 </p>

<p>scope. Confocal images were collected on a Zeiss LSM 510 Meta 
confocal microscope equipped with a Plan-Neofluar 40×/1.3 oil 
objective. Time-lapse series of HUVECs expressing the single-
chain Raichu/Cdc42 FRET probe (Aoki and Matsuda, 2009) were 
collected every 1 min for 30-60 min on a Zeiss LSM 780 confocal 
microscope equipped with Plan-Neofluar 40×/1.4 oil objective. 
Images were collected every minute for a total of 30-60 min. For 
ultrastructural analysis, collagen gels were prepared for trans-
mission electron microscopy (TEM). Briefly, gels were fixed with 
2.5% glutaraldehyde and 2% paraformaldehyde in 75 mM phos-
phate-buffered saline (PBS) for 3 h at 4°C, followed by overnight 
wash in 114 mM PBS. Gels were subsequently postfixed in 1% 
OsO 4 reduced with 1% K 4 [Fe(CN) 6 ] in 1 M cacodylate buffer for 
1 h at 4°C, washed twice in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer, and embed-
ded in Epon. Ultrathin sections were cut, mounted onto copper 
grids, and viewed with a Morgagni 268 transmission electron 
microscope (FEI). Digital images were acquired with a Mega-
ViewIII camera controlled with <rs id="software-0" type="software">iTEM</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Olympus Soft Imaging Systems</rs>, Germany) and then postprocessed using 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">ImageJ</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD</rs>) and <rs type="software">Adobe 
Illustrator</rs>. </p>

<p>Image processing and analysis </p>

<p><rs type="software">Fiji</rs> was used for image processing and extraction of quantitative 
data. For quantitative analysis of VE-cadherin, PDXL, active 
Cdc42, and p-aPKC, the average fluorescence intensity in regions 
of interest (ROIs) located in the luminal area was measured using 
<rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. A total of 35-50 ROIs from 3D images pooled 
from three independent experiments was analyzed. To determine 
VE-cadherin junctional length and the percentage of luminal pe-
rimeter coated with PDXL, the line scan function of <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> was 
used on 25-30 junctions/lumens from three independent experi-
ments. Images from FRET time-lapse series were processed with 
<rs type="software">Fiji</rs>. Briefly, a binary mask was derived from the YFP image and 
was multiplied separately with the TFP and FRET images. Then 
FRET images were divided by TFP images to obtain FRET/TFP 
ratio images. A rainbow color LUT was applied, and brightness 
and contrast were adjusted to display the ratio FRET images in an 
intensity-modulated manner by which red indicates high and blue 
indicates low FRET efficiency, respectively. For quantitative analy-
sis, YFP-masked FRET and TFP images were thresholded to 
measure pixel intensity of each individual image in the stack, and 
FRET/TFP intensity ratios were calculated as previously described 
(Chaki et al., 2013). For statistical purposes, time-lapse series 
were acquired from four to six cells/group. Experiments were 
repeated three times. </p>

<p>Calcium switch assay and immunofluorescence staining </p>

<p>HUVECs serum starved for 10 h in EBM2 (Lonza) starvation medium 
containing 0.2% fetal bovine serum were challenged with 4 mM eth-
ylene glycol tetraacetic acid (EGTA) for 30 min to chelate extracel-
lular calcium and disrupt Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-dependent intercellular junctions. 
After washing, cells were allowed to recover in calcium-containing 
EBM2 complete culture medium for various intervals. Cells were 
fixed and permeabilized with 3.7% paraformaldehyde and 0.25% 
Triton X-100 in cytoskeletal buffer (10 mM 2-(N-morpholino)ethane-
sulfonic acid, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM EGTA, 5 mM MgCl 2 , and 5 mM 
glucose (pH 6.1) for 10 min at room temperature and subsequently 
processed for immunofluorescence. 
Immune detection of endogenous proteins was performed as 
previously described (Rivera et al., 2004). After fixation and permea-
bilization, endothelial monolayers were blocked with 2% bovine </p>

<p>positioned to coordinate key cellular processes during vascular 
morphogenesis. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Reagents </p>

<p>HUVECs, EBM2/EGM2 culture medium, Hank's balanced salt solu-
tion, trypsin-EDTA, and trypsin neutralizing solution were purchased 
from Lonza (Walkersville, MD). Other reagents were purchased 
from the following sources: DAPI (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO), 
Hoechst33342 (Life Technologies, Eugene, OR), fibronectin (EMD 
Millipore, Billerica, MA), recombinant human VEGF 165 (R&amp;D 
Systems, Minneapolis, MN), Matrigel (BD Biosciences, Sparks, MD), 
Texas Red phalloidin (Life Technologies), lipofectamine 2000 (Life 
Tech nologies), DMEM (HyClone, Logan, UT), fetal bovine serum 
(Gemini Bio-Products, West Sacramento, CA), Alexa Fluor 488 pro-
tein labeling kit (Life Technologies), anti-pPKCzeta/lambda (Abcam, 
Cambridge, MA), anti-VE-Cadherin (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA), 
anti-active Cdc42 (NewEast Biosciences, Malvern, PA), and anti-
human podocalyxin (R&amp;D Systems), Collagen I (Corning, Discovery 
Labware, Bedford, MA). </p>

<p>Viral production </p>

<p>The production of viral particles harboring vectors for the expres-
sion of shRNA or cDNA was previously described (Chaki et al., 
2013). Briefly, retroviruses for the stable expression of shRNAs or 
cDNAs were generated in HEK293T cells by calcium phosphate 
precipitation. For protein silencing, the pSUPER retroviral vector 
carrying oligonucleotide sequences for the expression of shRNAs 
was used. The shRNA targeting sequences (Nck1: GAGAGAGAG-
GATGAATTAT; Nck2: AACTACGTGGTGGTCCTCAGT) were previ-
ously validated (Chaki et al., 2013). For protein expression, the 
pMSCV retroviral vector carrying cDNAs of interest with or without 
fluorescent marker was used. Retroviral vectors were cotransfected 
with pHCMV-G and pMD.gag.pol plasmids. Medium containing 
virus was harvested within 48 h of transfection and stored at −80°C 
in aliquots for later use. </p>

<p>Cord network formation </p>

<p>For endothelial cord network formation on laminin-rich matrices, we 
used serum-starved (6 h) HUVECs. Cells were resuspended in EBM2 
starvation medium supplemented with 50 ng/ml VEGF. Cells 
(2 × 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>) were seeded in 96-well plates coated with a thick layer 
(50 μl/well) of Matrigel and incubated for 16 h at 37°C. After fixation 
in paraformaldehyde (4% for 10 min) and staining in toluidine blue, 
cultures were subjected to bright-field imaging. </p>

<p>Three-dimensional, collagen-I-based vasculogenesis assay </p>

<p>Endothelial tube formation in 3D collagen matrices was per-
formed following a protocol previously described (Koh et al., 
2008b; Kim et al., 2013). Briefly, endothelial cells were mixed 
with 2-3.5 mg/ml type I collagen containing 16 nM phorbol-
12-myristate-13-acetate and 1.25 μM sphingosin-1-phosphate on 
ice. Subsequently, 50 μl of cell-collagen mixture was added on 
96-well glass-bottom plates and incubated at 37°C/CO 2 for 
45 min to allow gel formation. A total of 100 μl of EGM2 complete 
media supplemented with 50 ng/ml VEGF was added on top of 
the solidified collagen gel, and cultures were maintained in the 
incubator for 96 h. </p>

<p>Microscopy </p>

<p>Bright-field images and differential interference contrast (DIC) 
images were captured using an Olympus IX70 inverted micro-</p>



<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



<p>Cdc42 pull-down assay </p>

<p>Cells were cultured for 96 h in 3D collagen matrices, and GTP-
loaded Cdc42 from cell extracts was enriched by pull down with 
immobilized PBD domains from Pak1 (Kutys and Yamada, 2014). 
Briefly, endothelial cells were lysed by sonication in ice-cold lysis 
buffer containing 20 mM 4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piperazineethane-
sulfonic acid (HEPES), pH 7.6, 1% Triton X-100, 150 mM NaCl, 
5 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), Sigma-Aldrich protease 
and phosphatase inhibitor cocktail, and 5% glycerol. After high-
speed centrifugation for 10 min at 4°C, supernatants were col-
lected and protein concentration determined by the Bradford 
method. Next 500 μg of protein was incubated in the presence of 
40 μg of PBD Pak1 -glutathione S-transferase protein beads (Cyto-
skeleton) for 1 h at 4°C. Beads were washed twice with 500 μl of 
ice-cold wash buffer (25 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 30 mM MgCl 2 , 
40 mM NaCl, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride 
(PMSF), 5 μg/ml aprotinin, and 1 μg/ ml leupeptin) and boiled in 
sample buffer (40 μl of beads in wash buffer plus 10 μl of 5× sample 
buffer) for 5 min. Samples were resolved by SDS-PAGE, followed 
by Western blotting. Membranes were probed with an anti-Cdc42 
antibody (Abcam). </p>

<p>Western immunoblotting </p>

<p>Cells from two-dimensional cultures were harvested in ice-cold ki-
nase lysis buffer containing 25 mM Tris, pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 
5 mM EDTA, 10% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100, 10 mM β-
glycerophosphate, 1 mM sodium orthovanadate, 10 mM sodium 
pyrophosphate, 10 μg/ml aprotinin, and 1 mM PMSF. Cells from 3D 
collagen gels were harvested by brief sonication (5 s ×3) in ice-cold 
lysis buffer containing 20 mM HEPES, pH 7.6, 1% Triton X-100, 
150 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM DTT, and a protease and phos-
phatase inhibitor cocktail from Sigma-Aldrich. Supernatants were 
collected after high-speed centrifugation at 4°C. Sample protein 
concentration was determined using the Bradford assay (Bio-Rad), 
and equal amounts of protein (of 3-10 μg) were loaded and re-
solved by SDS-PAGE. All membranes were blocked in 0.5% nonfat 
dry milk (NFDM) dissolved in 1× Tris-buffered saline/Tween-20 
(TBST) except aPKC (5% BSA in TBST) for 1 h at room temperature 
before incubation with the appropriate primary antibody (see later </p>

<p>description). The secondary antibody (1:10,000) was diluted in 0.5% 
NFDM in 1× TBST except for PKC (5% BSA in TBST) and incubated 
for 1 h at room temperature. Secondary antibodies used were from 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology (sc-2054, goat anti-rabbit IgG-HRP; and 
#sc-2055, goat anti-mouse IgG-HRP). Signal from the chemilumi-
nescence substrate (NEL 100001EA; PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA) 
was captured using a Luminescent Image Analyzer. Membranes 
were incubated with primary antibody overnight at 4°C under the 
following conditions: anti-Nck (BD Transduction Laboratories, 
#610099, 1:5000; 0.5% NFDM/TBST, overnight, 4°C), anti-VE-cad-
herin (Bender Med System, #BMS158, 1:2500; 0.5% NFDM/TBST), 
anti-Cdc42 (Abcam, #ab64533, 1:250; 5% BSA/TBST), anti-aPKC 
(Cell Signaling, #9368, 1:500; 5% BSA/TBST), anti-phospho-aPKC 
(Cell Signaling, #9378, 1:1000; 0.5% NFDM/TBST), anti-glyceralde-
hyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH; Invitrogen, #437000, 
1:10,000; 0.5% NFDM/TBST), and β-actin (Sigma-Aldrich, #A1978, 
1:5000; 0.5% NFDM). </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Each experiment was replicated three times. Data were analyzed 
using analysis of variance, followed by Tukey's multiple-compari-
sons test. Bar diagrams represent mean ± SD. In box-and-whiskers 
plots, the central circle indicates the mean, the middle line indicates 
the median, and the top and bottom lines indicate the first and third 
quartiles, respectively. The whiskers extend up to 1.5 times the inter-
quartile range. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Michiyuki Matsuda (Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan) for the 
kind gift of the FRET Raichu-Cdc42 probe. We are indebted to 
Robert Burghardt, Director of the Image Analysis Laboratory (Texas 
A&amp;M University College of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical 
Sciences), for facilitating access to the imaging instrumentation. We 
thank Harold Ross Payne for performing transmission electron mi-
croscopy analysis. This investigation was supported by grants from 
the American Heart Association (12BGIA9030042 to G.M.R. and 
14POST18900045 to S.P.C.) and Texas A&amp;M University/AgriLife 
startup funds to G.M.R. The Image Analysis Laboratory is partly 
supported by the National Institutes of Health, National Center for 
Research Resources (1 S10 RR22532-01). </p>

<p>Volume 26 September 1, 2015 </p>

<p>Nck regulates endothelial lumenization | 3059 </p>





<p>Molecular Biology of the Cell </p>



</text></tei>