<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4183238" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>HOW TO CITE THIS ARTICLE </p>

<p>Macedo CSG, Alonso CS, Liporaci RF, Vieira F, Guirro RRJ. Cold water immersion of the ankle decreases neuromuscular 
response of lower limb after inversion movement. Braz J Phys Ther. 2014 Jan-Feb; 18(1):93-97. http://dx.Cryotherapy is indicated in the management 
of acute tissue injuries 1 . Its effectiveness is well 
established in pain relief, edema and inflammatory 
process control, and decreases in blood flow, 
metabolic rate, temperature, and intramuscular nerve 
conduction velocity 2 . In clinical practice, it is used 
in sports injuries of the ankle/foot and in injuries of 
physically active individuals during physical therapy 3 . 
Bleakley and Costello 2 pointed out that the 
application of topical cooling prior to exercise has 
become a popular method; however, the authors report 
that its benefits should compensate any deleterious 
physiological effects, considering that it has been 
associated with a significant decrease in nerve 
conduction velocity 4,5 in muscle contraction 6 and with 
possible effects on exercise and physical training 7 . 
Currently, studies 8-10 have shown different 
results related to the effects of local cooling on 
proprioception 11 , motor control 12 , joint position 3,9 , </p>

<p>and electromyographic (EMG) response 13 . Despite 
the frequent use of cryotherapy in the final stages of 
rehabilitation for foot and ankle injuries in athletes and 
the early return to sport, there is disagreement about 
the effect of cooling on peroneal muscle function 
during weight-bearing exercise 13 and on other muscles 
related to this joint and the lower limbs. It is assumed 
that, with the decrease in nerve conduction velocity 
and consequently less recruitment and muscle activity, 
the ankle is left vulnerable to injury. However, there 
is limited evidence on the effects of local cooling on 
motor control 8,10 , which reinforces the need for further 
studies on the subject. 
Therefore, the present study aimed to determine 
the effect of cold water immersion of the ankle on the 
amplitude of the EMG response of the corresponding 
lower limb muscles after ankle inversion, as well 
as to detect the possible changes 30 minutes 
post-immersion. </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>Braz J Phys Ther. 2014 Jan-Feb; 18(1):93-97 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S1413-35552012005000132 </p>

<p>Macedo CSG, Alonso CS, Liporaci RF, Vieira F, Guirro RRJ </p>

<p>Method </p>

<p>This study uses an analysis of repeated measures 
design to determine the peak RMS (Root Mean 
Square) values of the lateral gastrocnemius (LG), 
tibialis anterior (TA), fibularis longus (FL), rectus 
femoris (RF), and gluteus medius (GM) muscles, 
before (pre), immediately after (post), and 10, 20, 
and 30 minutes after cold water immersion. 
The study was approved by the Research Ethics 
Committee of Hospital das Clínicas, Faculdade de 
Medicina de Ribeirão Preto/Universidade de São 
Paulo (FMRP/USP), Ribeirão Preto, SP, Brazil 
protocol number 2968/2010, and all volunteers signed 
an informed consent form. The study was registered 
as a clinical trial (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: 
NCT01870414) and met the ethical standards in sport 
and exercise science research 14 . 
The volunteers were recruited by verbal invitation 
on the university campus and referred to evaluation 
and screening. The exclusion criteria were as follows: 
history of muscular or joint injury to the lower 
limbs in the last six months; diagnosis of metabolic, 
rheumatic or balance disorders; and cold or pain 
hypersensitivity during the tests. 
A convenience sample of 39 participants fulfilled 
the required criteria; however, 4 were excluded 
due to incompatible schedules. Our main focus 
was to evaluate healthy subjects for the integrity 
of the sensory and motor system, thus determining 
the results obtained exclusively from cold water 
immersion applied to the cooled and non-cooled 
lower limb muscles. 
For the EMG signals, the Myomonitor IV (Delsys, 
Boston, MA, USA) was used. This module has 
impedance of 10 9 Ohms, 16-bit resolution, input 
band of 1V, sampling frequency of 1000Hz, bandpass 
filters of 20 to 450Hz, Overall Channel Noise ≤1.2uV </p>

<p>RMS, with microcomputer connection and 1000x 
gain. The single differential surface sensors (Delsys, 
Boston, MA, USA) had 1-mm wide x 10-mm long 
silver-bar electrodes, 10 mm apart, Preamplifier Gain 
10 V/V±1%, CMRR -92 dB, and Input Impedance 
&gt;10 15 Ω //0.2pF. Data Acquisition Software was used 
(Delsys, Boston, MA, USA) for acquisition, storage, 
and analysis of data. 
For fixation of the electrodes, the volunteer 
was asked to stand up. After the skin was shaved 
and cleansed, the electrodes were fixed over the 
muscle bellies following the standards of the 
international protocol, Surface Electromyography for 
the Non-Invasive Assessment of Muscles. A reference 
electrode was positioned on the anterior, ipsilateral 
tibial tuberosity with double-sided adhesive and 
elastic bandage. 
The volunteer was in the orthostatic position on a 
tilt platform, eyes open and bare feet (Figure 1). The 
platform was synchronized with the electromyography 
equipment and activated by the computer. The device 
specifications and the inversion angle (30°) were 
based on a systematic review 15 . Each subject received 
instructions and was given the opportunity to feel 
the sudden inversion perturbation so this movement 
could be learned and recognized. The collection 
consisted of six tilts, three movements for each side, 
at random. For the data analysis, the mean value of 
the three collections was considered after the tilt of 
the platform for the dominant leg (defined as the leg 
that the subject would choose to kick a ball). 
Next, the subjects were placed in a seated position. 
The dominant leg was immersed for 20 minutes 13,16 
in cold water at a temperature of 4±2°C 17 and a depth 
of 20 cm, below the positioning of the electrodes; 
therefore, there was no need to remove those between 
trials. The water temperature was controlled using 
an infrared thermometer (MultTemp  , Porto Alegre, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Before (A) and after (B) 30° of ankle inversion movement, after the tilt of the platform. </p>

<p>94 Braz J Phys Ther. 2014 Jan-Feb; 18(1):93-97 </p>

<p>Cryotherapy of the ankle and inversion movement </p>

<p>RS, Brazil). The cold water was stirred during the 
procedure, and whenever necessary, some ice cubes 
were added to maintain the temperature. After 
immersion, the lower limb was dried with a towel. 
The skin surface temperature of the anterior ankle 
region was measured to confirm cooling. 
For the analysis, the peak RMS after the tilt of the 
inversion platform at 30° was considered. Similarly, 
Berg et al. considered that higher levels of RMS 
showed greater muscle activity 13 . For normalization 
of the peak RMS signal, pre-cold water immersion 
was considered as 100% because it is considered a 
dynamic activity 18,19 . 
Results were verified by applying the Shapiro-
Wilk test, repeated measures analysis, Bonferroni's 
post-hoc test, and linear regression analysis. The 
statistical analysis was performed using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical 
Package for Social Sciences</rs> (SPSS ® ), <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 15.0</rs>. 
The level of statistical significance was set at 5%. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Thirty-five male subjects, 21.6 (±3.2) yrs of age, 
177.9 (±7.9) cm tall, 82.8 (±19.3) Kg in weight 
and 25.9 (±4.8) Kg.m -2 of body mass index (BMI), 
were evaluated. Skin surface temperature before and 
after cold water immersion was 27.7(±3)°C and 7.1 
(±1)°C, respectively (p=0.0001). 
The results in Table 1 show that the peak 
RMS values were significantly lower for all post-
immersion times when compared to those obtained </p>

<p>Table 1. Electromyographic analysis of the peak RMS values of 
the dominant lower limb muscles after the tilt of the inversion 
platform at 30°. Mean values (SD) expressed as percentage of pre 
cold water immersion peak (%). n=35. </p>

<p>Moment analysis with 
cold water immersion </p>

<p>Muscles 
Pre Post 
Post 
10 min </p>

<p>Post 
20 min </p>

<p>Post 
30 min </p>

<p>Lateral 
gastrocnemius </p>

<p>100 
(0) </p>

<p>68.34* 
(31.30) </p>

<p>69.14* 
(30.22) </p>

<p>66.26* 
(29.87) </p>

<p>66.62* 
(29.83) </p>

<p>Tibialis anterior 
100 
(0) </p>

<p>53.73* 
(25.55) </p>

<p>55.78* 
(30.24) </p>

<p>63.74* 
(50.19) </p>

<p>50.19* 
(29.20) </p>

<p>Fibularis longus 
100 
(0) </p>

<p>73.65* 
(43.58) </p>

<p>74.91* 
(35.03) </p>

<p>73.29* 
(37.84) </p>

<p>71.10* 
(39.21) </p>

<p>Rectus femoris 
100 
(0) </p>

<p>73.22* 
(47.00) </p>

<p>62.77* 
(32.73) </p>

<p>65.28* 
(36.34) </p>

<p>64.78* 
(49.29) </p>

<p>Gluteus medius 
100 
(0) </p>

<p>86.21 
(31.90) </p>

<p>82.67* 
(25.02) </p>

<p>81.23* 
(24.05) </p>

<p>75.83* 
(30.43) </p>

<p>Mean values (SD) expressed as percentage of pre cold water 
immersion peak (%). *Statistically significant difference when 
compared to pre cold water immersion time (p&lt;0.05). Repeated 
measures analysis and Bonferroni's post-hoc test. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Behavior of the peak RMS values of the dominant lower limb muscles, after the tilt of the inversion platform at 30° pre and 
post cold water immersion. Trend line and R 2 . n=35. </p>

<p>pre-immersion for all muscles, except for immediate 
post-immersion for GM. 
Linear regression analysis was used to determine 
the decreasing patterns of the peak RMS values. It 
was observed that the non-cooled muscles (RF and 
GM) that were not related morphologically to the 
ankle/foot responded in a more uniform manner 
to the cooling over time, justifying the use of this 
experimental model (Figure 2). In contrast, the three </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>Braz J Phys Ther. 2014 Jan-Feb; 18(1):93-97 </p>

<p>Macedo CSG, Alonso CS, Liporaci RF, Vieira F, Guirro RRJ </p>

<p>other muscles that act on the ankle joint showed a very 
similar pattern after the cooling treatment. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Based on the results, cold water immersion for 20 
minutes at 4°C was effective in reducing skin surface 
temperature in agreement with Wolf and Basmajian 20 , 
who reported decreases in skin and intramuscular 
temperatures after a 5-minute intervention. These 
results are consistent with Rupp et al. 12 , who 
concluded that cold water immersion was more 
effective in significantly decreasing intramuscular 
temperatures in the gastrocnemius when compared 
to crushed-ice bag during treatment and 90 minutes 
post-treatment. 
Many studies have used electromyography 
to analyze ankle muscle response 10,15 and ankle 
inversion 13,21 . In addition, the present study 
evaluated the effects of cold water immersion on the 
electromyographic response of muscles that are not 
mechanically related to the cooled ankle joint. Thus, 
our study analyzed the RF and GM muscles, which 
showed a decrease in RMS immediately after the use 
of cold water immersion, with residual effect that 
lasted up to 30 min. 
The RF is a powerful knee extensor and the GM 
stabilizes the lateral movement of the pelvis, hip, 
and knee. Although the ankle inversion causes an 
anterolateral joint imbalance, consequently it triggers 
an ascending force to the pelvis, leading to a decrease 
in activation of the ankle muscles that can change the 
muscular responses around the hip and knee. This 
change could be explained in part by the existing 
modulation response coming from the skin, joint, and 
muscle receptors, while a reduction in distal afferents 
would cause an inhibitory effect of the proximal 
muscle activity. Thus, the cooling of the ankle had a 
direct reflection on the muscular activity of the non-
cooled muscle/joint complexes of the knee and hip. 
Following the same pattern, all muscles (LG, 
TA, and FL) mechanically related to the ankle that 
received cryotherapy showed significant reduction 
in RMS. These findings can be explained by the fact 
that cryotherapy causes a reduction in amplitude and 
an increase in latency of motor nerve conduction 5,22 , 
causing changes in the structures of the axon 
membrane and in the muscle conductivity of sodium 
and potassium channels, with a reduction in motor 
nerve conduction 22,23 , mainly of the sensorial nerves 5 . 
Moreover, Khanmohammadi et al. 3 suggested a linear 
relationship between the rate of muscle spindle 
discharge and reduced muscle temperature, which </p>

<p>can be confirmed by our findings. The results of 
these studies contrast with those of Berg et al. 13 and 
Cordova et al. 21 who observed no differences in FL 
amplitude or latency during inversion perturbation 
after cooling the ankle joint. Uchio et al. 24 reported 
some concern for the return of athletes to exercise 
after cryotherapy because the results from different 
studies are contradictory, justifying the need for 
further studies. 
There are some limitations that need to be 
acknowledged and addressed regarding the present 
study. The sample comprised active and healthy 
individuals as the authors understand that the tilt 
platform test could exacerbate pain and/or injury 
in individuals with ankle disorders. Additionally, 
the possibility of a control group being submitted 
to water immersion at room temperature or at rest 
should also be considered in order to ensure the 
effects of cold water immersion on ankle muscle 
activity. Further studies should include the analysis 
of the non-dominant lower limb that provides support 
during the tilting. 
The results of this study indicate a decrease in 
the EMG response of the LG, TA, FL, RF, and GM 
muscles to ankle inversion after the use of cold water 
immersion in healthy male subjects, with a residual 
effect that lasts up to 30 minutes. Therefore, after 
cold water immersion of the ankle, special care 
should be taken with activities that require greater 
neuromuscular control. </p>



<p>Correspondence </p>

<p>Rinaldo Roberto de Jesus Guirro 
Universidade de São Paulo 
Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto 
Av. Bandeirantes, 3900, Monte Alegre 
CEP 14049-900, Ribeirão Preto, SP, Brazil 
e-mail: rguirro@fmrp.usp.br </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>Braz J Phys Ther. 2014 Jan-Feb; 18(1):93-97 </p>

</text></tei>