<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4894081" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T03:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Hospitalized premature babies often undergo various painful procedures. Kangaroo mother care (KMC) and swad-
dling are two pain reduction methods. </p>

<p>Objectives: This study was undertaken to compare the effects of swaddling and KMC on pain during venous sampling in premature 
neonates. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods: This study was performed as a randomized clinical trial on 90 premature neonates. The neonates were 
divided into three groups using a random allocation block. The three groups were group A (swaddling), group B (KMC), and group 
C (control). In all three groups, the heart rate and arterial oxygen saturation were measured and recorded in time intervals of 30 
seconds before, during, and 30, 60, 90, and 120 seconds after blood sampling. The neonate's face was video recorded and assessed 
using the premature infant pain profile (PIPP) at time intervals of 30 seconds. The data was analyzed using the t-test, chi-square test, 
Repeated Measure analysis of variance (ANOVA), Kruskal-Wallis, Post-hoc, and Bonferroni test. </p>

<p>Results: The findings revealed that pain was reduced to a great extent in the swaddling and KMC methods compared to the control </p>

<p>group. However, there was no significant difference between KMC and swaddling (P ≥ 0.05). </p>

<p>Conclusions: The results of this study indicate that there is no meaningful difference between swaddling and KMC on physiological 
indexes and pain in neonates. Therefore, the swaddling method may be a good substitute for KMC. </p>

<p>Keywords: Infant, Premature, Neonate, Pain, Venipuncture, Kangaroo Mother Care </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>According to the international association of pain 
study, pain is an unpleasant feeling and an emotional ex-
perience following actual or potential tissue damage (1), 
which is created by a harmful stimulus, and its goal is 
essentially to defend and protect (2). Presently, it is ac-
cepted that neurons are formed during the embryonic pe-
riod and anatomically and functionally have the neces-
sary efficiency to conduct painful stimuli (3). Premature 
neonates are able to identify and react automatically to 
pain as early as 20 weeks of age (4). In addition, premature 
neonates are less able to reduce or inhibit painful stimuli 
because of descent neuron lines, which make them more 
sensitive to pain (3, 5). According to the world health or-
ganization (WHO), 15 million premature neonates are born 
globally each year, which is more than 0.1 of total neonate 
births (6). Premature neonates undergo many diagnostic 
and therapeutic procedures in the neonatal intensive care 
unit (NICU), which is reported to be more than 10 to 16 </p>

<p>interventions per day (7-9). Unfortunately, 40 to 90 per-
cent of neonates do not receive any preventative or ther-
apeutic actions to reduce the pain of these painful inter-
ventions (7, 8, 10). The most common intervention is blood 
sampling, or heel stick, to prepare laboratory samples (11). 
Continuous pain impulses by afferent nerves to specific ar-
eas of the brain cause atrophy of that part of the brain. 
The repeated pain of procedures leads to ventricular bleed-
ing in premature neonates, increases in brain plasticity of 
neonates, and reduction of subcortical white and gray mat-
ter, with subsequent increases in fluctuations inside the 
skull (12). Therefore, controlling the pain of harmful pro-
cedures, such as blood sampling, is of great importance, 
especially in premature babies, as it is proposed that the 
neonatal pain threshold is 30 to 50 percent less than in 
adults (3, 5). Moreover, uncontrolled pain can increase the 
risk of infection, the hospitalization period, and the death 
rate of neonates (13). Pain relief, which is among nursing 
interventions, can be done with or without medicine (14). 
Although the use of powerful medications for neonatal </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Iranian Red Crescent Medical Journal. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 
4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Dezhdar S et al. </p>

<p>surgeries is an accepted practice, using such medications 
in painful interventions such as blood sampling is not ap-
propriate (15). Fortunately, it has been proven that non-
medical interventions have greater impact on reducing 
pain caused by procedure (14). Swaddling and Kangaroo 
mother care (KMC) are two of the non-medical methods. 
KMC was innovated in 1979 in Colombia (16) and its pain 
controlling function can be justified with the neuromatrix 
theory of pain (17). The effect of KMC on neonate pain was 
first examined in 2000 with term neonates (18), then in 
2003, in preterm neonates (19), and after that, by many re-
searchers, with its effectiveness being established. Another 
pain controlling method for neonates is swaddling, which 
has advantages including improving sleep (20) improving 
neuromuscular growth, reducing pain and crying (21), and 
reducing the risk of sudden infant death syndrome (SIDS) 
(21, 22). </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Since diagnostic and therapeutic procedures are per-
formed throughout the day and night, and since the pres-
ence of the mother is not possible in the closed environ-
ment of the NICU, if swaddling is as effective as KMC, then 
it can be used as a substitute for KMC. Thus, this clinical 
trial study was undertaken for the first time in Iran in order 
to compare the effects of swaddling and KMC on venipunc-
ture pain in premature neonates. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>This is a parallel-group controlled trial. A total of 82 
premature neonates admitted to the NICU of Shohadaye-
Khalije-Fars hospital in 2014 were included in the study. It 
is a general-governmental referral and teaching hospital 
in Bushehr-Iran affiliated with the Bushehr University of 
Medical Sciences, with 200 beds and 13 hospital sections. 
The inclusion criteria were as follows: born at less than 37 
weeks of pregnancy; less than 2500 grams in weight; Apgar 
score higher than 6 in the first 5 minutes after delivery; be-
ing alive at least 24 hours after birth; and being awake and 
calm. The sampling was the first blood sample performed 
on a neonate on the same day as the delivery. Neonates 
who were fed within 30 minutes prior to the intervention, 
those who received any sedatives during the 24 hours prior 
to the study, and those who received vasodilators during 
their hospital stay, were excluded from the study. Other ex-
clusion criteria were as follows: presence of congenital, ge-
netic or neurological anomalies; intraventricular hemor-
rhage; seizures; undergoing any surgery; and any skin le-
sions in areas of skin contact in the mother or neonate. </p>

<p>The neonates who met the eligibility criteria were as-
signed into one of three intervention groups using a per-
muted block randomization method. Blocks of six were 
used for this purpose. </p>

<p>3.1. Data Collection 
Venous blood sampling was done under swaddling in 
group 1, KMC in group 2, and routine care in group 3 (con-
trol group). Blood sampling was a part of the diagnostic 
and therapeutic procedures of all neonates and no invasive 
intervention was added. The blue scalp vein set (number 
23) was used for all neonates. 
In the swaddling method, the bare neonate was 
wrapped in a thin sheet with a clean diaper by the re-
searcher, and using a stopwatch, 10 minutes after the swad-
dling began (23), the neonate's hand was taken from the 
swaddle and blood sampling was performed by the same 
skilled nurse. After a dressing was placed on the blood 
sampling site, the neonate's hand was placed back in the 
swaddle and the condition was kept for 2 minutes after 
blood sampling. Before blood sampling each neonate, the 
initial part of the tool was completed by the researcher, 
and this part included demographic and physiological in-
formation of the neonate (heart rate and arterial oxygen 
saturation). Physiologic information was obtained with a 
Saadat co. Arya brand monitoring machine that was cal-
ibrated by the medical equipment engineer in the hospi-
tal. In addition, the neonate's face was video recorded with 
a Canon camera for 2 minutes following the moment of 
blood sampling. In KMC, the neonate had only a clean di-
aper and socks and was placed in direct skin contact with 
the mother's chest, with the head at a 60 degree angle. In 
order to avoid lowering the neonate's body temperature, 
the neonate's back was covered with a thin blanket and the 
mother was asked to wrap her hands around the neonate's 
back, limit the neonate's movement, and avoid any addi-
tional actions, such as talking, caressing, moving, and feed-
ing the neonate. After 10 minutes (18) of KMC, blood sam-
pling was done on the neonate's hand and KMC was main-
tained for a further 2 minutes. The neonate's face was video 
recorded from the time of blood sampling until 2 minutes 
after. The videos were then coded and a single observer 
(an experienced research assistant that was unaware of the 
type of intervention) was asked to complete the prema-
ture infant pain profile (PIPP) tool for each video. In or-
der to measure physiological parameters, a pulse oximeter 
attached to the neonate's hand was used to measure the 
heart rate and arterial oxygen saturation. These parame-
ters were measured and recorded before, during, and after 
blood sampling. 
The PIPP tool was used to evaluate acute pain in the 
neonates. The validity and reliability of this tool have been </p>

<p> 
Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2016; 18(4):e29649. </p>

<p>Dezhdar S et al. </p>

<p>shown in many studies, and it has desirable validity and re-
liability of 0.93 -0.96 (24, 25); in a domestic study, the relia-
bility was reported as 0.88 (26). The PIPP includes seven in-
dexes as follows: three behavioral indexes, including brow 
bulge, eye squeeze, and nasolabial furrow; two physiologi-
cal indexes, including heart rate and arterial oxygen satu-
ration; and two indicators of age and behavioral state. Each 
of these indicators has a degree from zero to 3, which in to-
tal results in a value from 0 to 21. Values under 6 indicate 
lack of pain, values between 7 and 12 indicate mild to aver-
age pain, and values above 12 indicate severe pain. 
This trial was approved by the research ethical com-
mittee of Bushehr University of Medical Sciences on 
(DATE) 2014, with the reference number (B-93-16-1), and 
registered in the Iranian registry of clinical trials (IRCT: 
2014042212830N3R1). The study began after a written in-
formed consent letter was obtained from each mother. </p>

<p>3.2. Sample Size and Power </p>

<p>The sample size was calculated using <rs id="software-0" type="software">G power</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.1</rs> soft-
ware. Based on the information drawn from a study by Ak-
can et al. (27), the mean PIPP score was considered 10 with 
a standard deviation of 2. Assuming the equality of vari-
ances of PIPP scores in the intervention groups, alpha er-
ror of 5%, and statistical power of 80%, the required sample 
size to detect a difference of two scores between the groups 
was estimated to be 24. In order to increase the statistical 
power, and considering sample attrition, it was decided to 
include 30 neonates in each group. </p>

<p>3.3. Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Mean and standard deviation were used to describe 
quantitative variables and frequency and percentage were 
used to describe qualitative variables. 
The normality of the distribution of data was exam-
ined using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. According to the 
results of this test, the distributions of PIPP scores in the 
studied groups were not far from normality. Therefore, the 
mean PIPP score in each time point (30, 60, 90, and 120 
seconds), was compared by one-way analysis of variance 
(ANOVA) test. The Bonferroni correction was used to adjust 
for multiple comparison testing. 
Since the variables of heart rate, arterial oxygen satura-
tion, and face scale did not have normal distribution, the 
non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis test was used to compare 
these variables among groups at any point in time (0, 30, 
60, 90, and 120 seconds) after the sample was drawn. 
Repeated measure ANOVA was used to compare the ef-
fect of the interventions on PIPP score in repeated measure-
ments at 30, 60, 90, and 120 seconds. Tests of between-
subjects effects were used to examine the overall effect of </p>

<p>the interventions on the PIPP score. Post-hoc multiple com-
parison tests were used to compare pairwise comparisons 
between the groups. 
All statistical tests were carried out using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> statisti-
cal software, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 20</rs> and the graphs were drawn using 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">STATA</rs> statistical software <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 11</rs>. The significance level 
was considered 0.05 in all tests. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>A total of 90 neonates who met the eligibility crite-
ria were randomized into three groups, from which 82 
remained in the study and were analyzed. There were 
28 neonates (34.1%) in the swaddling group, 25 neonates 
(30.5%) in the KMC group, and 29 neonates (35.4%) in the 
control group. Figure 1 shows the flowchart of recruitment 
and follow-up of neonates during the study. 
Table 1 displays the baseline and demographic charac-
teristics of the neonates in the study. </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline and Demographic Characteristics of Neonates </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Swaddling (n = 
28) </p>

<p>Control (n = 
29) </p>

<p>KMC (n = 25) </p>

<p>Gestational 
age </p>

<p>32.61 ± 2.48 
33.21 ± 2.44 
34.6 ± 1.55 </p>

<p>Gender, male 
16 (57.10) 
14 (48.30) 
17 (68) </p>

<p>Weight, g </p>

<p>1694.64 ± </p>

<p>512.788 </p>

<p>1796.9 ± 571.202 
2138.2 ± 336.783 </p>

<p>APGAR score </p>

<p>9.07 ± 0.81 
9.1 ± 0.86 
9.64 ± 0.86 </p>

<p>Delivery type </p>

<p>Normal 
Vaginal 
Delivery </p>

<p>9 (32.10) 
10 (34.50) 
6 (24) </p>

<p>Cae-
sarean 
Section </p>

<p>19 (67.90) 
19 (65.50) 
19 (76) </p>

<p>Duration of 
sampling, s </p>

<p>18.39 ± 9.818 
22.14 ± 12.380 
14.2 ± 7.024 </p>

<p>Baseline heart 
rate, bpm </p>

<p>139.32 ± 17.053 
142.55 ± 14.022 
139.96 ± 18.959 </p>

<p>Baseline O2sat </p>

<p>96.89 ± 2.283 
96.07 ± 2.463 
98.26 ± 1.173 </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as mean ± SD or No. (%). </p>

<p>The demographic variables in the three groups of sam-
ples had no statistically significant differences except for 
mean weight between the KMC and swaddling groups (P = 
0.00), and between the KMC and control groups (P = 0.03) 
(Table 1). The control and swaddling groups did not show a 
statistically significant difference (P = 1.00). 
Tests of between-subjects effects of repeated measure 
ANOVA showed that mean PIPP scores were statistically </p>

<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2016; 18(4):e29649. 
3 </p>

<p>Dezhdar S et al. </p>

<p>Assessed for 
Eligibility = 102 </p>

<p>Refused to </p>

<p>Participate = 12 </p>

<p>Randomized = 90 </p>

<p>Allocated to Group </p>

<p>A (Swaddling) n = 30 </p>

<p>Allocated to Group </p>

<p>B (KMC) n = 30 </p>

<p>Allocated to Group </p>

<p>B (Control) n = 30 </p>

<p>Needle Stick More </p>

<p>than Once n = 2 </p>

<p>Needle Stick More than </p>

<p>Once n = 1 </p>

<p>Stop Video Recording n = 4 </p>

<p>Needle Stick More </p>

<p>than Once n = 1 </p>

<p>Swaddling (n = 28) 
KMC (n = 25) </p>

<p>Control (n = 29) </p>

<p>Subjects Included in the </p>

<p>Fnal Analysis n = 82 </p>

<p>Enrollment </p>

<p>Allocation </p>

<p>Follow -Up </p>

<p>Analysis </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flowchart of Recruitment and Follow-Up of Neonates During the Study </p>

<p>significantly different between the intervention groups F 
(2, 79) = 29.35, (P &lt; 0.001). Post-hoc pairwise comparison 
tests determined that mean PIPP scores were not statisti-
cally significantly different between the KMC and swad-
dling groups (P = 0.405). However, mean PIPP scores in 
both groups were statistically significantly lower than in 
the control group (Ps &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Mean PIPP scores were also statistically significantly 
different between the groups at seconds 30, 60, 90, and 120 </p>

<p>[F (2, 81) = 13.289, F (2, 81) = 18.555, F (2, 81) = 25.465, F (2, 81) 
= 48.446, respectively, (all Ps &lt; 0.001)]. Post-hoc pairwise 
comparisons determined that PIPP scores were not statis-
tically significantly different between the KMC and swad-
dling groups at any time-point. However, mean PIPP scores 
in both groups were statistically significantly lower than in 
the control group at all time-points (all Ps &lt; 0.01). Figure 2 
illustrates mean PIPP scores and their confidence intervals 
at all time-points. </p>

<p> 
Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2016; 18(4):e29649. </p>

<p>Dezhdar S et al. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>30 
60 
90 
120 
Mean PIPP Score </p>

<p>Time Points (second) </p>

<p>Swaddling 
KMC 
Control </p>

<p>Figure 2. Mean and 95% Confidence Intervals of Pain Intensity (PIPP Score) Measured at Different Time-Points by Intervention Group </p>

<p>Non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis test results showed 
that heart rates were not statistically significantly differ-
ent between the groups at the baseline, needling time, or 
30 seconds after the needling (P = 0.850, P = 0.072, and P 
= 0.057, respectively). However, the differences were sta-
tistically significantly different at 60, 90, and 120 seconds 
after the needling (P = 0.004, P &lt; 0.001, and P &lt; 0.001, re-
spectively). Pairwise comparisons showed that the signif-
icant differences were present between the heart rates of 
neonates in the swaddling or KMC group and the control 
group. There were no significant differences between the 
heart rates of neonates in the swaddling and KMC groups 
(all Ps &lt; 0.05) (Figure 3 and Table 2). </p>

<p>The Kruskal-Wallis test results showed that oxygen sat-
uration values differed significantly between the interven-
tion groups at different time-points (Figure 4). Unlike 
heart rate, baseline oxygen saturation values were statis-
tically, not clinically, significantly different between the 
groups. The differences were also statistically significant 
at all other time-points after the needling (all Ps &lt; 0.01). 
Pairwise comparisons determined that oxygen saturation 
values differed significantly between the KMC and control 
groups (all Ps &lt; 0.01) and also between the swaddling and 
control groups [all Ps &lt; 0.05 except for baseline (P = 0.254)]. 
Oxygen saturation values were also different significantly 
at the baseline (P = 0.022) and at the seconds 90 and 120 
after the needling, (P = 0.039 and P = 0.005, respectively); 
however, the values were not significantly different at the 
needling time (P = 0.181) and at the seconds 30 and 60 after </p>

<p>the needling (P = 0.167 and P = 0.422, respectively) (Table 3). 
Based on the Kruskal-Wallis test results, facial change 
scores were statistically significantly different between the 
KMC and control groups at 30, 60, 90, and 120 seconds af-
ter needling (P = 0.041, P = 0.006, P &lt; 0.001, and P &lt; 0.001, 
respectively). There were also significant differences be-
tween facial change scores in the swaddling and control 
groups at all time-points measured i.e. 30, 60, 90, and 
120 seconds after the needling (all Ps &lt; 0.001). However, 
there was no statistically significant difference between fa-
cial change scores in the KMC and swaddling groups at any 
time-point (Figure 5). </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>According to the findings of this study, the swaddling 
method reduces the pain of arterial blood sampling in 
neonates to a similar extent as the KMC method. The phys-
iological index differences in both groups of swaddling 
and KMC were more stable and less than the differences 
in the control group. The average pain comparison score 
in neonates with swaddling was less than in the control 
group. It is possible to justify the reduction of pain in 
swaddling using the Gate control theory of pain. Accord-
ing to this theory, stimulation of larger sensory fibers from 
touch receptors in areas of pain, or further ones, leads to 
pain signals weakening, therefore, it can be suggested that 
swaddling reduces pain by stimulating touch. One of the 
other effects of swaddling is warming the neonate. Heat </p>

<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2016; 18(4):e29649. 
5 </p>

<p>Dezhdar S et al. </p>

<p>Baseline 0" 
30" 
60" 
90" 
120" </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Heart Rate </p>

<p>Swaddling 
Control 
kmc </p>

<p>Figure 3. Box Plots of Heart Rate Values at Different Time-Points by Intervention Group </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of Average Heart Rate in Premature Neonates in Each Group </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Time 
Groups 
P Value </p>

<p>Swaddling 
KMC 
Control </p>

<p>Needling time </p>

<p>140.71 ± 16.64 
140.16 ± 19.90 
150.28 ± 15.02 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>Second 30 </p>

<p>148.75 ± 18.20 
145.80 ± 19.18 
157.62 ± 15.97 </p>

<p>0.052 </p>

<p>Second 60 </p>

<p>150.36 ± 17.70 
147.56 ± 20.35 
163.83 ± 15.13 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>Second 90 </p>

<p>144.86 ± 17.46 
143.28 ± 20.94 
162.41 ± 14.91 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Second 120 </p>

<p>141.25 ± 16.87 
139.36 ± 20.75 
159.31 ± 14.57 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as mean ± SD. </p>

<p>Table 3. Comparison of the Average Arterial Blood Oxygen Saturation (O2 sat) in Premature Neonates in Each Group </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Time 
Groups 
P Value </p>

<p>Swaddling 
KMC 
Control </p>

<p>Needling time </p>

<p>96.54 ± 2.61 
97.52 ± 1.98 
94.48 ± 2.55 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>Second 30 </p>

<p>94.64 ± 3.24 
95.72 ± 3.06 </p>

<p>92.41± 4.34 
0.003 </p>

<p>Second 60 </p>

<p>94.21 ± 3.84 
95.36 ± 2.78 </p>

<p>90.0± 5.29 
0.000 </p>

<p>Second 90 </p>

<p>94.04 ± 4.29 
96.36 ± 2.66 
90.76 ± 4.74 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>Second 120 </p>

<p>94.61 ± 3.64 </p>

<p>97.00± 2.50 
91.00± 4.06 
0.000 </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as mean ± SD. </p>

<p>increases blood flow and may reduce pain through excre-
tion of metabolic materials which cause pain. Another way </p>

<p>to reduce pain is muscle relaxation, which means mus-
cle slackness, and reduction of respiratory and heart rates. </p>

<p>6 
Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2016; 18(4):e29649. </p>

<p>Dezhdar S et al. </p>

<p>Baseline 0" 
30" 
60" 
90" 
120" </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>75 
O2 Saturation, % </p>

<p>Swaddling 
Control 
kmc </p>

<p>Figure 4. Box Plots of Oxygen Saturation Values at Different Time-Points by Intervention Group </p>

<p>30" 
60" 
90" 
120" </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
Facial Change Score </p>

<p>Swaddling 
Control 
kmc </p>

<p>Figure 5. Box Plots of Facial Change Score at Different Time-Points by Intervention Group </p>

<p>Swaddling may reduce pain by reducing the respiratory 
and heart rates. In a study by Huang, it was found that the 
pain score in the swaddling group was lower than in the 
containment group (28). Also, in a review study by Meek </p>

<p>in England, swaddling was identified as one of the effec-
tive nursing actions in reducing premature neonate pain 
(29). The findings of these two studies are consistent with 
the findings of the current research. In a review article </p>

<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2016; 18(4):e29649. 
7 </p>

<p>Dezhdar S et al. </p>

<p>in 2011 in Canada by Pilla Riddell et al. (30), it was sug-
gested that swaddling can inhibit pain but may not be as 
effective as KMC, which is not consistent with the findings 
of this clinical trial. It is possible that this contrast is be-
cause of the guesses based on results of two studies, one 
by Johnston et al. (31) and another by Huang et al. (28), 
as no clinical study was done to compare these two meth-
ods. According to results of the current study, swaddling as 
a multi-dimensional intervention can reduce a neonate's 
pain to a considerable degree. This study found that physi-
ological changes were less in the swaddling and KMC meth-
ods, and it was more stable compared to the control group. 
As was mentioned earlier, perhaps swaddling limits the 
neonate's movements and prohibits muscle stretch, caus-
ing muscle relaxation, and therefore improving respira-
tion, increasing oxygen saturation, and decreasing heart 
rate. A study by Ho and Ho not only showed that the av-
erage pain from blood sampling in swaddling had a signif-
icant reduction compared to the control group (P = 0.001), 
but it also showed that heart rate and oxygen saturation 
indexes reached the baseline in 2 minutes, whereas in the 
control group, 6 to 8 minutes were needed for the indexes 
to return to baseline (32). The findings of this study are 
in line with the present study. However, a study by Khod-
dam et al. concluded that neonate and mother skin con-
tact during intramuscular injection do not decrease physi-
ological indexes of pain and only cause less neonate crying 
(16), which is in contrast with the findings of the current 
research. This contrast may be because the insufficiency of 
the sample in Khoddam's study, which was only 15 in the in-
tervention group and 15 in the control group. It may be fur-
ther explained by the short period of hugging time, as in 
Khoddam's study the neonate was hugged just at the mo-
ment of blood sampling, whereas in this study the neonate 
was hugged for 10 minutes before blood sampling. Consid-
ering the results of the current study, swaddling, like KMC, 
is an effective way to stabilize the physiological indexes of 
the neonate. 
In the present study, it was shown that, in the two 
groups of swaddling and KMC, the physiological changes 
were similar to each other and less than in the control 
group. A systematic review which was done in 2007 on 
swaddling behavior stated that swaddling organizes the 
nervous behavior of the neonate well (21), which is in line 
with the findings of this study. Multiple studies refer to 
the effect of swaddling on neonate's sleep (33). It is possi-
ble that the improvement of neonate's sleep by swaddling 
is a reason which reduces the facial changes in response 
to pain. In the present research, it may be proposed that 
the neonates became sleepy when swaddled, and this re-
duced the changes in their face during the painful inter-
vention. Fernandes stated that the appearance reaction </p>

<p>can be a more practical observation than body movements 
and crying, and also can be more specific than physiologi-
cal changes which are the total response to stressful stim-
uli (1). Assuming that this is true, nurses can understand 
the neonate's pain experience without using any specific 
tool and only by observing the neonate's face. 
The average blood sampling time in the KMC group 
was 14.20 seconds, in swaddling it was 18.39 seconds, and in 
the control group it was 22.14 seconds. This difference was 
statistically significant (P = 0.020). The Bonferroni test re-
vealed that there was no significant difference between the 
swaddling and KMC groups (P = 0.407) and also between 
the swaddling and control groups (P = 0.498), but there 
was a significant difference between the KMC group and 
control group (P = 0.016). It was observed that the blood 
sampling time was less in the KMC group than the other 
two groups. A possible explanation may be the vertical po-
sition and gravity, which improves blood flow and there-
fore allows sampling to be done faster. This issue has been 
mentioned in Johnston's study as well (31). Considering 
these findings, sampling can be done in a shorter period 
of time in the KMC method. </p>

<p>5.1. Strengths and Limitations </p>

<p>The present research was performed for the first time 
in Iran with a suitable design (randomized control clini-
cal trial) and a strong performance. However, there are 
some limitations in this study. One of the major limita-
tions of the study is the validity limitation of the utilized 
instrument (PIPP) to measure intensity of pain in neonates. 
Considering the limitation of sample volume, some differ-
ences are seen in the basic value of some demographic fac-
tors, such as birth weight, which is possibly the cause of 
random error. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>All the researchers of this project would like to express 
their special thanks of gratitude to the research deputy of 
the Medical School of Bushehr for the approval of this re-
search project, and all the other people who cooperated 
with us in this project. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Funding/Support: This study was supported by the 
deputy of research in Bushehr University of Medical Sci-
ences. It should be mentioned that this article is taken 
from the thesis of master's students in nursing education. </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution: Shahin Dezhdar: sampling; 
Faezeh Jahanpour: corresponding author, adviser, and </p>

<p> 
Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2016; 18(4):e29649. </p>

<p>Dezhdar S et al. </p>

<p>draft review; Saeedeh Firouz Bakht: reviewer; Afshin Osto-
var: statistical analysis. </p>



<p>Iran Red Crescent Med J. 2016; 18(4):e29649. </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>