<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4895162" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Epitheliotropic intestinal T-cell lymphoma (EITL, also known as type II enteropathy-associated T-cell lymphoma) is an aggressive 
intestinal disease with poor prognosis and its molecular alterations have not been comprehensively characterized. We aimed to 
identify actionable easy-to-screen alterations that would allow better diagnostics and/or treatment of this deadly disease. By 
performing whole-exome sequencing of four EITL tumor-normal pairs, followed by amplicon deep sequencing of 42 tumor 
samples, frequent alterations of the JAK-STAT and G-protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) signaling pathways were discovered in a 
large portion of samples. Specifically, STAT5B was mutated in a remarkable 63% of cases, JAK3 in 35% and GNAI2 in 24%, with the 
majority occurring at known activating hotspots in key functional domains. Moreover, STAT5B locus carried copy-neutral loss of 
heterozygosity resulting in the duplication of the mutant copy, suggesting the importance of mutant STAT5B dosage for the 
development of EITL. Dysregulation of the JAK-STAT and GPCR pathways was also supported by gene expression profiling and 
further verified in patient tumor samples. In vitro overexpression of GNAI2 mutants led to the upregulation of pERK1/2, a member of 
MEK-ERK pathway. Notably, inhibitors of both JAK-STAT and MEK-ERK pathways effectively reduced viability of patient-derived 
primary EITL cells, indicating potential therapeutic strategies for this neoplasm with no effective treatment currently available. </p>

<p>celiac disease. 
9-12 Given the distinct clinicopathological features of 
type II EATL as described below and the lack of association with 
celiac disease, the term 'enteropathy-associated' in its nomencla-
ture is not appropriate and various names including mono-
morphic intestinal T-cell lymphoma 
11 and epitheliotropic intestinal 
T-cell lymphoma (EITL) 
13 have been proposed. In this study, we 
will refer to this neoplasm as EITL henceforth. 
EITL has an extremely poor prognosis with a median overall 
survival of only 7 months. 
13 No effective treatment or targeted 
therapies are currently available for this disease. A number of 
publications have focused on the clinical and pathological </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Lymphoma Genomic Translational Research Laboratory, Division of Medical Oncology, National Cancer Centre Singapore, Singapore, Singapore; 
2 Laboratory of Cancer 
Epigenome, Division of Medical Sciences, National Cancer Centre Singapore, Singapore, Singapore; 
3 Program in Cancer and Stem Cell Biology, Duke-NUS Medical School, </p>

<p>Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Centre for Computational Biology, Duke-NUS Medical School, Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Cancer Science Institute of Singapore, National University of 
Singapore, Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Duke University, Durham, NC, USA; </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Singapore General Hospital, Singapore, 
Singapore; </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Advanced Molecular Pathology Laboratory, Singapore Health Services, Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center, 
Guangzhou, China; </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Yong Loo Lin School of Medicine, National University 
of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore; 
12 Department of Pathology, National University Hospital, National University Health System, Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Department of 
Pathology, Chi Mei Medical Center, Tainan, Taiwan; </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Taipei Medical University and National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan; </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Department of 
Pathology, Guangdong General Hospital, Guangzhou, China; </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand; </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Samsung Medical Centre, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, South Korea; </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, University of Malaya, Kuala 
Lumpur, Malaysia; </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Hospital Raja Permaisuri Bainun, Ipoh, Malaysia; </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Department of Haematology-Oncology, National University Hospital, National 
University Health System, Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Division of Medical Oncology, National Cancer Centre Singapore, Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Genome Institute of Singapore, 
A*STAR, Singapore, Singapore; </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Institute of Molecular and Cell Biology, A*STAR, Singapore, Singapore and </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Office of Education, Duke-NUS Medical School, Singapore, 
Singapore. Correspondence: Associate Professor ST Lim or Dr CK Ong, Lymphoma Genomic Translational Research Laboratory, Division of Medical Oncology, National Cancer 
Centre Singapore, 11 Hospital Drive, Singapore 169610, Singapore or Associate Professor S-Y Tan, Department of Pathology, Singapore General Hospital, 20 College Road, 
Singapore 169856, Singapore. 
E-mail: dmolst@nccs.com.sg or cmrock@nccs.com.sg or drtansy@gmail.com </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. 
Received 15 July 2015; revised 7 January 2016; accepted 18 January 2016; accepted article preview online 8 February 2016; advance online publication, 1 March 2016 </p>

<p>Leukemia (2016) 30, 1311-1319 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 0887-6924/16 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/leu </p>

<p>characterization of EITL. Together with others, we have compre-
hensively described the histology of this complex disease. 
11,13 In 
short, EITL displays zonal variation featuring central invasive 
sheets of monomorphic neoplastic lymphocytes, a peripheral zone 
of mucosa infiltrated by morphologically atypical intraepithelial 
lymphocytes (IELs) and a distant zone featuring mucosa with 
normal villous architecture but increased number of morphologi-
cally normal IELs. The putative cell of origin is an intestinal IEL and 
clonality analyses have shown that the IELs in the distant mucosal 
zone share clonal relationship with the invasive lymphoma. </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>The CD8+ CD56+ phenotype and extensive nuclear expression of 
megakaryocyte-associated tyrosine kinase are features that are 
distinct from classical EATL, 
13,15 with the majority of neoplastic 
cells expressing CD8αα homodimers. 
13 Opinion is still divided 
whether these cells display mainly T-cell receptor (TCR) αβ or γδ 
phenotypes. </p>

<p>11,13 </p>

<p>Cytogenetic studies have demonstrated gains and transloca-
tions of MYC (8q24) 
10,13,16 in EITL, although they may also be seen 
in classical EATL. 
17 Conversely, gains of 1q32.2-q41 and 5q34-
q35.2 are more common in EATL compared with EITL, whereas 
9q31.3 gain and 16q21.1 loss can be observed in both classical 
EATL and EITL. 
1,3 Recently, it was reported that an activating 
STAT5B p.N642H mutation is common in T-cell lymphoma derived 
from γδ T-cells, including some cases of EITL. 
18 We used next-
generation sequencing techniques in a multicenter study to 
describe the frequent genetic changes in EITL. We provide here 
the first whole-exome sequencing (WES) study of this disease and, 
in the largest series published to date, demonstrate that STAT5B-
activating mutations are found in EITL tumors of both TCRαβ and 
TCRγδ origin. We present multiple lines of evidence that JAK-STAT 
and G-protein-coupled receptor (GPCR) signaling pathways are 
highly activated in EITL, and, most importantly, inhibition of these 
pathways by targeted therapy effectively reduces the viability of 
primary EITL cells. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS 
Patients and samples </p>

<p>EITL was defined as a primary intestinal T-cell lymphoma with 
characteristic morphology, typically with cytotoxic, CD3+ CD8+ CD56+ 
EBER − phenotype. Five snap frozen primary tumors and matched whole 
blood samples were obtained from the SingHealth Tissue Repository. The 
patients were recruited from 2010 to 2014 and all provided signed 
informed consent in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. An 
additional 41 archival formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded samples collected 
from 2003 to 2014 were obtained from the following centers: National 
Cancer Centre Singapore, Singapore General Hospital, National University 
Hospital and Tan Tock Seng Hospital in Singapore, Guangdong General 
Hospital and Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center in China, University of 
Malaya and Hospital Raja Permaisuri Bainun in Malaysia, Samsung Medical 
Centre in Korea, Chi Mei Medical Center in Taiwan and Mahidol University 
in Thailand. Fourteen of those were also used in our previous study with 
the same identifiers. 
13 Clinicopathological features are listed in 
Supplementary Table 1. Tumor cell content was assessed by hematoxylin 
and eosin staining. The study was approved by SingHealth Centralised 
Institutional Review Board (2004/407/F). </p>

<p>Sequencing and mutation analysis </p>

<p>Detailed methods are described in the Supplementary Information. Briefly, 
four tumor-normal pairs of EITL were whole-exome sequenced using 
SureSelectXT Human All Exon V4+UTRs capture (Agilent Technologies, 
Santa Clara, CA, USA) and HiSeq 2000 Sequencing System (Illumina, San 
Diego, CA, USA). All candidate variants were visually inspected in 
<rs type="software">Integrative Genomics Viewer</rs>. 
19,20 Only <rs type="software">Integrative Genomics Viewer</rs>-true 
mutations were considered somatic and variants with frequency ⩾ 15% 
were further validated by Sanger sequencing (Supplementary Table 2). 
Prevalence screening was performed for GNAI2, JAK3 and STAT5B genes 
in 42 tumor samples using amplicon deep sequencing. Only common 
hotspots reported in <rs id="software-7" type="software">COSMIC</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">v.72</rs> and regions identified through WES 
were sequenced for each gene (Supplementary Table 3). CREBBP mutation </p>

<p>frequency was determined in a partial prevalence cohort (16 cases) using 
Single Primer Enrichment Technology (NuGEN Technologies, San Carlos, 
CA, USA). </p>

<p>SNP genotyping array and allele-specific copy number analysis of 
tumors </p>

<p>Genomic DNA from four tumor-normal pairs was hybridized to Genome-
Wide Human Single-Nucleotide Polymorphism (SNP) Array 6.0 (Affymetrix, 
Santa Clara, CA, USA) chips. Allele-specific copy number analysis of tumors 
was performed as described previously. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Stable cell line construction and western blot </p>

<p>Full-length GNAI2 cDNA was amplified using AccuPrime Pfx DNA 
Polymerase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and cloned into retroviral 
vector MIGR1 (Addgene; plasmid no. 27490) 
22 at XhoI and EcoRI sites. 
GNAI2 mutations (c.535C4T for p.R179C and c.535C4A for p.R179S) were 
generated by QuikChange II XL Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Agilent 
Technologies) and confirmed by Sanger sequencing. 
HuT78 and Jurkat cell lines were from ATCC (Manassas, VA, USA) and 
maintained in Iscove's modified Dulbecco's medium (Invitrogen) supple-
mented with 20% fetal bovine serum (HyClone; GE Healthcare, Little 
Chalfont, UK) and RPMI-1640 (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% fetal 
bovine serum (HyClone; GE Healthcare), respectively. The cultures were 
routinely checked for mycoplasma contamination. Stable cell lines were 
generated by retroviral infection and sorting of green fluorescent protein-
positive cells using BD FACSAria III Cell Sorter (BD Biosciences, Franklin 
Lakes, NJ, USA). 
Protein extracts were prepared in RIPA cell lysis buffer (150 mM NaCl, 
50 mM Tris-HCl, 0.5% deoxychlorate sodium, 200 mM NaF, 200 mM PMSF, 
1% NP-40 and 1 mM EDTA) in the presence of freshly added protease 
inhibitor (Roche, Basel, Switzerland). HuT78 lines underwent serum 
starvation for 24 h before collection of protein lysates. Total protein 
extracts were separated on sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel and 
transferred to Trans-Blot Turbo Mini PVDF membranes (Bio-Rad, Hercules, 
CA, USA). The used antibodies are listed in Supplementary Table 4. Signals 
were visualized using ChemiDoc MP System (Bio-Rad). </p>

<p>Ex vivo cell viability assay in primary EITL cells </p>

<p>Primary EITL cells from patient 065T were subcutaneously injected into the 
NOD scid gamma (NSG) mouse (P1; The Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, 
ME, USA), followed by further passaging of the subcutaneously formed 
tumor cells by subcutaneous and intraperitoneal injection (P2). Eight-week-
old female animals were used in each passage. P2 mouse presented with 
highly swollen peritoneum, and intestinal and peritoneal tumors. All 
samples, including peritoneal fluid cells from P2, were histologically 
characterized by a senior hematopathologist (SYT) and diagnosed EITL. 
Owing to the consistent phenotype between patient's primary tumor and 
P2 peritoneal fluid cells, we will refer to the latter as primary EITL cells 
henceforth. Sanger sequencing confirmed the presence of all somatic 
mutations identified in the original tumor (Supplementary Table 5) also in 
the primary cells. Animal experiments were in compliance with ethical 
regulations of the SingHealth Institutional Animal Care and Use 
Committee. 
Primary EITL cells were maintained in RPMI-1640 (Invitrogen) supple-
mented with 10% human serum (Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO, USA) and 
500 IU/ml interleukin-2 (Miltenyi Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach, Germany). To 
test the feasibility of targeted therapy in EITL, 5 × 10 
3 cells were seeded in 
96-well plates in three technical replicates and treated with Stattic (CAS 
19983-44-9; Selleck Chemicals, Houston, TX, USA) and MEK inhibitor 
PD0325901 (CAS 391210-10-9; Axon Medchem, Groningen, The Nether-
lands) for 72 h, and Tofacitinib (CP 690550; Selleck Chemicals), Trametinib 
(GSK 1120212; Axon Medchem) and Gefitinib (ZD 1839; Axon Medchem) 
for 96 h at indicated concentrations. Cell viability was measured using the 
CellTiter-Glo Luminescent Cell Viability Assay (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). 
The efficacy of inhibitors was further evaluated by their effect on 
downstream targets using western blot. Cell lysates for PD0325901, 
Trametinib and Tofacitinib were collected 2 h and for Stattic 24 h post-
treatment. Dose-response curves were plotted using the Prism software 
(GraphPad, La Jolla, CA, USA). All drug treatment experiments were 
repeated at least two times with each inhibitor. </p>

<p>Molecular profiling of EITL 
M-L Nairismägi et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2016) 1311 -1319 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Accession numbers </p>

<p>Sequencing data from WES, Single Primer Enrichment Technology and 
amplicon deep sequencing has been deposited in the European 
Nucleotide Archive with the accession number PRJEB9720. The Affymetrix 
Genome-Wide Human SNP Array 6.0 and GeneChip Human Genome U133 
Plus 2.0 Array data are available in the Gene Expression Omnibus 
23 with 
the accession number GSE70654. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION 
Identification of somatic variants by WES 
To identify somatic mutations in EITL, we performed WES of four 
tumors with matching whole blood samples (Figure 1a). To 
maximize variant detection from a limited sample size, three 
different variant callers were applied-<rs type="software">Genome Analysis Toolkit</rs>, </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>MuTect 
25 and <rs type="software">Strelka</rs>. 
26 The mean depth of coverage was 126 × 
and on average 88% of targeted bases were covered by at least 20 
reads (Supplementary Table 6). Sanger validation of 296 candidate 
variants showed a false-positive rate of 3.72%. EITL samples 
presented a high mutation burden with an average of 85 
mutations per sample (range 59-137). A total of 340 nonsynon-
ymous somatic mutations were identified in 313 genes. Seven 
of those genes also harbored silent somatic mutations 
(Supplementary Table 5). The nonsynonymous variants comprised 
284 missense and 16 nonsense mutations, 13 frameshift indels, 25 
splice site mutations and 2 mutations resulting in loss of stop 
codon (Supplementary Figure 1a). As observed in most other </p>

<p>cancers, 
27,28 EITL mutation spectrum was characterized by the 
predominance of C4T transitions (Supplementary Figure 1b). 
A total of 14 genes were found recurrently mutated (Figure 1b 
and Supplementary Table 5). Among those were the calcium ion-
binding gene multiple EGF-like-domains 6 (MEGF6), regulator of cell 
size proline-rich 16 (PRR16) and the giant muscle protein Titin (TTN), 
genes with functions in neuronal migration, axon guidance and 
chemoattraction-Reelin (RELN), Roundabout 1 (ROBO1) and 
Semaphorin 3 A (SEMA3A)-and with functions in the movement 
and transportation of cilia-Dynein 9 (DNAH9) and Intraflagellar 
Transport 140 (IFT140). In addition, mutations were identified in 
the histone acetyltransferase CREB-binding protein (CREBBP) and 
two (putative) histone methyltransferases-additional sex comb-
like transcriptional regulator 3 (ASXL3) and SET domain-containing 2 
(SETD2)-suggesting that epigenetic dysregulation may have a 
role in EITL. 
Interestingly, three of the recurrently mutated genes presented 
with known activating hotspot variants. These included two key 
members of the JAK-STAT pathway, a central signaling cascade in 
immune cells-janus kinase 3 (JAK3) and signal transducer and 
activator of transcription 5B (STAT5B)-and G protein alpha 
inhibiting activity polypeptide 2 (GNAI2), a member of the family 
of Gα proteins. Remarkably, STAT5B was mutated in all four cases, 
suggesting a critical role in EITL formation. Three samples 
possessed the common p.N642H mutation, whereas the fourth 
harbored a complex substitution event in the beginning of exon 
17, resulting in two amino-acid changes-p.V712E and p.S715L </p>

<p>Figure 1. Graphical overview of the study, and mutation and subclonality profile of EITL tumors. (a) Types of analyses performed and the 
number of samples used for each experiment. Snap frozen cases are listed by their respective IDs. (b) Venn diagram illustrating the recurrent 
mutations in the discovery cohort. (c) The subclonal architecture of EITL sample 013T derived from <rs type="software">SciClone</rs> analysis. The upper plot 
demonstrates kernel density estimation and the lower one variant allele frequencies plotted against read depth (⩾20 × coverage) in copy-
neutral loss of heterozygosity-free regions. CNA, copy number analysis; FFPE, formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded; GEP, gene expression 
profiling. </p>

<p>Molecular profiling of EITL 
M-L Nairismägi et al </p>



<p>© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Leukemia (2016) 1311 -1319 </p>

<p>(see Supplementary Note and Supplementary Figure 2). Both JAK3 
and GNAI2 were mutated in a remarkable 2/4 cases. JAK3 
alterations occurred at two distinct activating positions (p.V674A 
and p.M511I), whereas GNAI2 was mutated in the same codon in 
both samples (p.R179C and p.R179S). 
To understand the clonal architecture of EITL tumors, we used 
SciClone 
29 to identify populations of cells containing specific 
mutations. All four discovery cohort samples demonstrated 
notable intratumor heterogeneity with five subclones present 
in each tumor sample (Figure 1c, Supplementary Figure 3 and 
Supplementary Table 7). As only copy-neutral loss of 
heterozygosity-free segments were analyzed, we were not able 
to determine whether the JAK3 and STAT5B mutations were 
located in different subclones. However, respective corrected 
variant allele frequencies do indicate that these mutations are 
located within two separate clones (Supplementary Table 5). </p>

<p>Prevalence screening of GNAI2, JAK3, STAT5B and CREBBP 
The high frequency of STAT5B, JAK3 and GNAI2 mutations in a 
small discovery cohort of only four samples was intriguing, 
prompting us to further analyze the prevalence of these mutations 
in a larger series of EITL samples. Forty-two additional EITL tumors 
(1 snap frozen and 41 archival samples) were screened for GNAI2, 
JAK3 and STAT5B mutations using amplicon deep sequencing. A 
total of 57 identified mutations were covered by an average of 
20 004 reads (range 104-175 515; Supplementary Table 8). As the 
amplicons covered only common mutation hotspots reported in 
<rs id="software-12" type="software">COSMIC</rs> <rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-number">v.72</rs> and positions identified in the discovery cohort, it is 
likely that our results are lower-bound estimates of the true 
mutation frequency of these three genes. 
Figure 2 summarizes the results from both the discovery and 
prevalence cohorts. STAT5B mutations were detected in 25/42 
(60%) cases, with 24/42 (57%) carrying known activating muta-
tions (p.N642H) in the Src homology 2 dimerization domain 
(Figure 2b). JAK3 was mutated in 14/42 (33%) samples with 13/42 
(31%) harboring activating mutations (p.M511I, p.A573V and 
p.V674A/F), the majority located in the pseudokinase domain 
(Figure 2c). We identified two samples carrying two separate JAK3-
activating mutations and a remarkable three activating mutations 
were identified in a third case indicating profound alteration of 
JAK3 function in these patients. Notably, none of these samples 
contained an activating STAT5B mutation (Figure 2a). Collectively, 
the JAK-STAT pathway was altered in 32/42 (76%) cases. It is 
remarkable that a large subset of tumors harbor co-occurring 
activating mutations in two members of the same pathway. A 
similar phenomenon was recently described for JAK1 and STAT3 in 
systemic ALK-negative anaplastic large T-cell lymphomas. 
30 More-
over, these mutants were demonstrated to act in synergy to 
constitutively activate downstream STAT3 signaling. Further 
studies for mutated JAK3 and STAT5B are thus warranted and 
might shed light on EITL tumorigenesis. 
GNAI2 mutations were observed in 9/42 (21%) samples. Two 
major hotspots were identified-p.R179 and p.T182-both 
located in the GTP-binding domain (Figure 2d) and are known 
activating variants. 
31-33 A single case was found to contain both 
mutations. Although exhibiting a lower mutation incidence 
compared with STAT5B and JAK3, it has been suggested that the 
lower frequencies for G protein α-subunits could be explained by 
mutations in receptors coupled to these G proteins. 
34 On that 
note, both the GNAI2 wild-type discovery cohort samples 
harbored somatic mutations in GPCRs (Supplementary Table 5). 
It would be therefore interesting to analyze the mutational 
prevalence of GPCRs and other members of Gα i signaling in a 
larger cohort to determine the frequency at which this cascade is 
altered in EITL. 
Alterations in all three genes were found to be not mutually 
exclusive (JAK3 vs STAT5B: P-value = 0.2527; GNAI2 vs STAT5B: </p>

<p>P-value = 0.5118; GNAI2 vs JAK3: P-value = 0.9998; one-sided Fish-
er's exact test by CoMEt 
35 ). Owing to the limited number of 
events, we were not able to analyze the subclonality of amplicon 
deep sequencing data; however, corrected variant allele frequen-
cies do suggest that multiple mutations in all three genes can be 
found both within the same as well as different subclones 
(Supplementary Table 8). 
We also analyzed the mutation frequency of CREBBP in a partial 
prevalence cohort of 16 samples. Mutations were identified in 
2/16 (13%) cases, and in total, CREBBP was mutated in 6/20 (30%) 
samples (Supplementary Figure 4 and Supplementary Table 9). 
Inactivating CREBBP mutations have been reported in a number of 
malignancies, including B-cell lymphomas, 
36,37 and the mutations 
have been described as early events associated with inferior 
outcome. 
38,39 Although in our series each identified variant was 
predicted to be disruptive, all mutations occurred in samples with 
coinciding STAT5B and/or JAK3 mutations, suggesting that CREBBP 
mutations might not be the major initiating event and further 
support the importance of activated JAK-STAT pathway in EITL. </p>

<p>Correlation of mutations with pathological features 
The identified STAT5B mutation frequency is nearly twice that of a 
previously published study of EITLs with TCRγδ expression. 
18 As 
the latter relied on Sanger sequencing, this difference may at least, 
in part, be explained by the lower sensitivity of Sanger 
sequencing. However, our observations do not support the 
hypothesis that STAT5B-activating mutations only occur in the 
TCRγδ lineage of EITLs as activating variants were equally 
identified in TCRαβ, TCRγδ, double-negative and aberrant 
double-positive cases (20%, 36%, 32% and 12% in each subset, 
respectively; Figure 2a and Supplementary Table 10). A similar 
observation was also made for the JAK3-and GNAI2-activating 
mutations. 
We further segregated the samples by the expression of CD8 
dimer. Activating mutations of each gene were present in tumors 
with CD8αα, CD8αβ and double-negative T-cells, with more than 
half of samples with STAT5B-activating variants being of the 
CD8αα type (61% CD8αα, 26% CD8αβ and 13% double negative; 
Supplementary Table 10). This is consistent with the notion that 
EITL is predominantly a tumor of CD8αα IELs. 
13 Importantly, there 
is no phenotypic variation between the mutant cases with 
different TCR and/or CD8 expression (Supplementary Figures 5 
and 6). </p>

<p>Copy number alterations in EITL 
To characterize the chromosomal abnormalities in EITL, we 
profiled all samples from the discovery cohort on a genome-
wide SNP array. All tumors were approximately diploid. We 
identified each of the previously reported frequent chromosomal 
change (loss of 16q12.1 and gains of 9q31.3 and 8q24) </p>

<p>1,3,10,13 </p>

<p>recurrently altered in 2/4 samples (Supplementary Table 11). This 
includes amplification of the MYC gene (four copies in two 
samples). Importantly, no gains of 1q32.2-q41 and 5q34-q35.5, 
alterations more common in classical EATL compared with EITL, 
were identified. Other recurrent losses included 8p, 11q and 12p, 
and gain of 7q (detailed regions in Supplementary Table 11). 
Remarkably, all four samples demonstrated copy-neutral loss of 
heterozygosity at chromosome 17q where STAT5B is located 
(Figures 3a and b). This phenomenon has previously been 
observed in JAK2 and JAK3 in other hematological 
neoplasms, 
40,41 and is thought to arise from somatic recombina-
tion events. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first time 
acquired uniparental disomy has been described for STAT5B and 
further indicates the pivotal role played by this gene in the 
development of EITL. Consistent with this, immunohistochemical 
analysis of samples with mutated STAT5B revealed noticeable 
upregulation of phosphorylated STAT5 (Supplementary Table 12), </p>

<p>Molecular profiling of EITL 
M-L Nairismägi et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2016) 1311 -1319 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>an example of which is shown in Figure 3c. It would be interesting 
to see whether there exists a transition from heterozygosity to 
homozygosity either histologically from distant mucosa to central 
tumor zone or clinically from primary diagnosis to relapse 
representing clonal evolution as observed in other tumors. </p>

<p>41,42 </p>

<p>We also identified two samples with amplification of the PIK3CG 
gene (five and four copies, respectively) that was also evident on 
protein level both for PIK3CG itself and downstream pAKT in one 
sample (Supplementary Figure 7). The prevalence of such 
amplification should be studied in a larger cohort as it might 
open up novel possibilities for targeted therapy. The first PI3K 
inhibitor is already in use for treatment of certain B-cell 
malignancies with many more currently in development. </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>Pathways and biological functions affected in EITL 
To identify key biological functions and signaling pathways 
affected in EITL, two different approaches were used-Ingenuity </p>

<p>Pathway Analysis (IPA) of mutated genes from WES and Gene Set 
Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) following gene expression profiling of 
EITL tumors. 
Among all mutated genes, major cellular functions such as cell 
death, survival, development, differentiation, homeostasis and 
proliferation were found significantly enriched (Supplementary 
Table 13), many of these affecting lymphocytes or T-cells 
specifically. In addition, mutated genes were also significantly 
associated with components involved in T-cell and intestine 
morphology and genes known to be involved in cancer and 
lymphoid malignancies. Importantly, enrichment of cell signaling 
and binding of DNA were also noted. All these suggest that key 
cellular functions are involved in the development of EITL and 
correlate well with the nature of this disease. 
Further supporting our genomic findings, canonical JAK-STAT 
and GPCR signaling were among the top-enriched IPA pathways 
(false discovery rate q-value = 0.24 and 0.03, respectively; 
Supplementary Table 14). In addition, several other aspects of </p>

<p>Figure 2. Frequently mutated genes in EITL identified by WES and amplicon deep sequencing. (a) Mutation frequencies of STAT5B, JAK3 and 
GNAI2 correlating to CD8 dimer and TCR type. Distribution of mutations in (b) STAT5B, (c) JAK3 and (d) GNAI2 genes. The frequency of each 
alteration is denoted within parentheses after its label. Filled circles indicate known mutation hotspots and empty circles mutations with 
unknown functional consequence. *A total of four nonsynonymous missense mutations identified resulting in the change of two amino acids. 
G, GTP-binding; ND, not done; SH2, Src Homology 2; TA, transcriptional activation domain; TCR, T-cell receptor. </p>

<p>Molecular profiling of EITL 
M-L Nairismägi et al </p>



<p>© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Leukemia (2016) 1311 -1319 </p>

<p>these cascades were also altered indicating the importance of 
GNAI2, JAK3 and STAT5B mutations described above. These include 
the role of JAK1 and JAK3 in γc cytokine signaling, Oncostatin M 
signaling, interleukin-2 and interleukin-9 signaling, cAMP-
mediated signaling and Gα i signaling. Molecular mechanisms 
of cancer was also found enriched, suggesting the involve-
ment of classical cancer genes in this disease. The latter is 
supported by the finding of at least one mutated tumor 
suppressor or oncogene in each case (Supplementary Table 5). 
Because IPA does not consider recurrence of gene alterations, 
we repeated the analysis with the list of recurrently mutated 
genes only. Importantly, all the above pathways, except 
Gα i signaling, were found significantly enriched in EITL 
(Supplementary Table 15). 
To verify the above by an unrelated approach, we performed 
gene expression profiling of four EITL tumors, two of CD8αα and 
two of CD8αβ origin. As EITL is suggested to arise from CD8+ 
IELs, 
13 we integrated our data with publicly available profile of 
CD8αα and CD8αβ T-cells from healthy donors. 
44 There was a total 
of 1760 genes significantly upregulated in EITL tumors (P o 0.05 
and fold change ⩾ 1.5; Supplementary Table 16). GSEA against 
Molecular Signatures Database gene sets 
45 was used to identify </p>

<p>deregulated pathways. The used gene sets and all statistics from 
GSEA are shown in Supplementary Table 17. It is noteworthy that 
GSEA independently confirmed the findings of IPA analysis using 
mutated genes from WES. Several aspects of GPCR signaling were 
found significantly enriched in EITL samples including GPCR ligand 
binding, signaling by GPCR and, importantly, Gα i signaling 
(Supplementary Figure 8). These clearly suggest a marked 
deregulation of Gα i signaling in EITL and further indicate the 
functional importance of discovered GNAI2 mutations. 
In addition, we also identified KEGG JAK-STAT signaling 
pathway as significantly enriched in EITLs. The higher side q-
value (Supplementary Table 17) is in this regard not surprising as 
the activation of JAK-STAT pathway is known to occur through 
protein phosphorylation and not increased expression of mRNA. 
More importantly, an outstanding association was identified with 
genes containing STAT5B binding sites in their promoters, both for 
the shorter and longer consensus motif. We further confirmed this 
by GSEA against publicly available gene set of STAT5 target 
genes. 
46 There was a significant enrichment between STAT5 
targets and genes upregulated in EITL (normalized enrichment 
score = 1.78, false discovery rate q-value o 0.001; Supplementary 
Figure 8d). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Acquired uniparental disomy in STAT5B locus. (a) Allele-specific copy number analysis of tumor (ASCAT) close-ups of two STAT5B 
mutant samples highlighting chromosome 17q. The upper panels demonstrate the raw (red) and segmented (green) B-allele frequencies 
(BAFs) of SNPs. The lower panels present allele-specific copy number profiles-red lines indicate the higher and green the lower copy number 
chromosomal haplotypes. The green line is at zero, which indicates loss of heterozygosity. (b) Sanger sequencing electropherograms 
demonstrating the presence of STAT5B somatic mutation in the same samples. (c) Representative images of pSTAT5 immunohistochemical 
staining in STAT5B wild-type and mutant cases. Magnification × 400. VAF, variant allele frequency from WES. </p>

<p>Molecular profiling of EITL 
M-L Nairismägi et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2016) 1311 -1319 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>

<p>Gene expression profiling data was validated by real-time PCR 
of randomly selected genes (Supplementary Table 18). The values 
from the two experiments were consistent, although the 
correlation was not statistically significant because of the small 
sample size (Supplementary Figure 9). In summary, JAK-STAT and 
GPCR signaling pathways were demonstrated as significantly 
enriched in EITL tumors using two different data sets and 
methodologies. </p>

<p>Targeted therapy inhibits viability of primary EITL cells 
While activating mutations in genes encoding α-subunits of G 
proteins occur in many human cancers, oncogenic alterations in 
the inhibitory subunits of G proteins exist at a much lower 
frequency. 
34 Oncogenic form of GNAI2 (GNAI2 p.R179C/H), 
referred to as gip2, 
32 was first identified in endocrine tumors of 
adrenal cortex and ovary, 
31 and p.T182A was thereafter also 
described as a constitutively activated mutant. 
33 Notably, gip2 was </p>

<p>demonstrated to constitutively activate mitogen-activated protein 
kinase, 
47 likely through inhibitory effect on intracellular cAMP 
levels. </p>

<p>48 </p>

<p>To better understand the above, we created stable cell lines 
overexpressing wild-type and mutant forms (p.R179C and 
p.R179S) of GNAI2. A strong upregulation of phosphorylated 
ERK1/2 level was detected in both mutant cells, whereas the total 
ERK1/2 protein levels remained unchanged (Figure 4a). The same 
observation was made in two independent cell lines. Consistent 
with this, immunohistochemical analysis of GNAI2 mutant 
cases also revealed upregulation of phosphorylated ERK1/2 
(Supplementary Table 12), examples of which are shown in 
Figure 4b, suggesting that the MEK-ERK signaling pathway is 
aberrantly activated in these EITL tumors. 
Notably, the identification of activated pathways in EITL offers 
novel treatment opportunities. JAK3 and STAT5B are both directly 
targetable by small-molecule inhibitors, and because mutant 
GNAI2 activates the MEK-ERK pathway, MEK inhibitors may be </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effective targeted therapy by JAK, STAT and MEK inhibitors in primary EITL cells. (a) Stable cell lines were created by overexpressing 
GNAI2 wild-type and mutants in HuT78 and Jurkat cells. The expression of relevant proteins was assessed by western blot. (b) Representative 
images of pERK1/2 immunohistochemical staining in GNAI2 wild-type and mutant tumors. Magnification × 400. (c) Representative ex vivo cell 
viability assay in primary EITL cells treated with PD0325901 and Stattic for 72 h, and Tofacitinib, Trametinib and Gefitinib for 96 h. All results are 
normalized to the control (dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO)) and presented as mean ± s.d. The experiment was repeated at least two times with 
each inhibitor. (d) Immunoblots of indicated proteins in primary EITL cells treated with PD0325901, Tofacitinib and Trametinib for two and 
Stattic for 24 h at indicated concentrations. </p>

<p>Molecular profiling of EITL 
M-L Nairismägi et al </p>



<p>© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Leukemia (2016) 1311 -1319 </p>

<p>effective for the treatment of EITL. To further confirm the 
involvement of JAK-STAT and GPCR signaling pathways in the 
survival of EITL, we evaluated the effect of two inhibitors of both 
pathways in primary EITL cells-Tofacitinib (pan-JAK inhibitor), 
Stattic (STAT3 inhibitor) and MEK inhibitors Trametinib and 
PD0325901. All four inhibitors reduced cell viability in a dose-
dependent manner compared with the vehicle-treated control 
(Figure 4c). Importantly, the primary cells were resistant to an 
inhibitor of a non-relevant pathway, the EGFR inhibitor Gefitinib, 
suggesting that the observed effect was not because of general 
cytotoxicity. Moreover, all four drugs clearly inhibited the down-
stream signaling cascades as demonstrated by suppression of 
STAT3, STAT5 and ERK1/2 phosphorylation (Figure 4d). 
These primary EITL cells harbor mutations in both JAK3 and 
downstream STAT5B, which may explain the inferior sensitivity of 
Tofacitinib compared with Stattic. Further supporting our data, 
JAK-STAT cascade inactivation either by knockdown of pathway 
members or targeted therapy also effectively reduces cell viability 
of cutaneous T-cell lymphoma cells that harbor an activating p. 
A573V JAK3 mutation. 
49-52 Despite the lack of GNAI2 mutation in 
the primary EITL cells, several other members of the GPCR 
pathway-the GPCRs HTR1F, GRM5, MRGPRX3 and GPR179, and 
protein tyrosine phosphatase DUSP4 (Supplementary Table 5)-
are all altered in these cells potentially leading to downstream 
activation of the GPCR pathway. Importantly, DUSP4 is known to 
inactivate ERK1/2. 
53 The p.R300W mutation identified in the 
primary EITL cells is positioned right in the middle of DUSP4 
catalytic dual-specificity phosphatase domain. As commonly 
observed for mutations within the functional domains of enzymes, 
it is likely that the identified p.R300W mutation causes inactivation 
of the DUSP4 protein that leads to the activation of ERK proteins 
and might explain the effectiveness of MEK inhibition in 
these cells. In addition, GPCR, Gα i and MEK-ERK pathways are 
all significantly enriched in the original tumor sample 
(Supplementary Figures 8a and c), further supporting the aberrant 
activation of these signaling pathways. Taken together, these 
results indicate that targeted therapy may be useful in the 
treatment of EITL patients. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
This is the first study to characterize comprehensively the 
molecular changes in EITL and provides novel insights into the 
pathogenesis of this disease. We have clearly demonstrated 
alterations in the JAK-STAT and GPCR signaling pathways on 
multiple levels, including mutations, chromosomal alterations and 
transcriptional upregulation. The high mutation frequency and 
location of mutations in key functional domains indicate the 
importance of these variants and notably may present novel 
opportunities for targeted therapies or better diagnostics. This is 
supported by our in vitro data demonstrating response of primary 
EITL cells to inhibitors of both pathways. Further studies are 
required to support these findings and to functionally evaluate 
them in a disease-specific model. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Medical Research Council of Singapore 
(TCR12DEC005), Tanoto Foundation as Professorship in Medical Oncology, New 
Century Foundation Limited, Ling Foundation and Singapore National Cancer Centre 
Research Fund. We thank Swe Swe Myint and Jia Liang Loh for help with sample 
preparation; Minghui Lee and Angie Tan from Duke-NUS Genome Biology Facility for 
gene expression profiling; Qian Qiao Tang, Alisa Noor Hidayah Sairi, Liang Kai Koh, 
Gerald Chua, Agnieszka Maliszewska and Beng Hooi Phang for logistic and technical </p>

<p>support, and all co-workers of Laboratory of Cancer Epigenome. We also thank 
SingHealth Flow Cytometry unit for cell sorting and the following surgeons for their 
generous contribution of patient samples: Associate Professor Foong Koon Cheah, 
Prof. Wai Keong Wong, Dr Peng Chung Cheow, Dr Yaw Chong Goh and Dr Weng 
Hoong Chan. </p>



<p>Molecular profiling of EITL 
M-L Nairismägi et al </p>



<p>Leukemia (2016) 1311 -1319 
© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or 
other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons 
license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under 
the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license 
holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on the Leukemia website (http://www.nature.com/leu) </p>

<p>Molecular profiling of EITL 
M-L Nairismägi et al </p>



<p>© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited 
Leukemia (2016) 1311 -1319 </p>

</text></tei>