<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4750616" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Objective: Unnecessary exposure of the abdomen, arms or head may lead to a substantial increase of the 
radiation dose in portable chest X-rays on the neonatal intensive care unit. The objective was to identify 
potential factors influencing inappropriate exposure of non-thoracic structures in two teaching hospitals. 
Methods: The study analysed 200 consecutive digital chest radiographs in 20 preterm neonates (mean 
gestation 25 ± 1 weeks). Demographical data, tube settings and exposure parameters were recorded. To 
grade the collimation, we used a scoring system with a maximum of 12 exposed non-thoracic structures. 
Length of gestation, age, the radiographer, years of experience in performing X-rays and the number of 
in situ catheters or lines, were correlated with collimation quality. 
Results: There was no significant difference between the rates of optimal images obtained in the two 
hospitals (0.32 vs 0.39, n.s.). Scores showed that most suboptimal images had only mildly reduced image 
quality (1.40 ± 1.38 vs 1.20 ± 1.43, n.s.). Length of gestation or presence of surgical drains, catheters and 
tubes had no obvious effects on the exposure of non-thoracic structures. Large intra-individual variation 
in optimal collimation (14-86%) was noted for the radiographers in both hospitals; this was unrelated to 
their respective years of experience. 
Conclusion: In our study, the only identifiable factor influencing the collimation of portable chest radio-
graphs in preterm infants was the radiographer's dedication and awareness. There were no apparent 
differences between the hospitals investigated. Exposure of non-thoracic structures was relatively fre-
quent and mainly involved the proximal humeri. 
Chest radiography is one of the most widely used diagnostic 
examinations in children [1-3]. In a special care baby unit, pre-
mature neonates have serious and life-threatening diseases that 
may require a large number of X-rays for diagnosis and treatment 
[4,5]. Increased neonatal radiosensitivity and longer life expectancy 
increase the risk of radiation-induced cancer, which emphasises the 
importance of minimising the dose while maintaining a clinically 
satisfactory image quality [6]. </p>

<p> *  Corresponding author at: Abteilung für Radiologie und Nuklearmedi-</p>

<p>zin, Klinikum Memmingen, Bismarckstr. 23, 87700 Memmingen, Germany. 
Fax: +49 0331 70 2852. 
E-mail address: jens.stollfuss@klinikum-memmingen.de (J. Stollfuss). </p>

<p>The radiation dose during bedside examinations can be 
increased without a visible change in the final image due to incor-
rect (free) exposure settings. It is therefore possible that different 
hospitals, using different image parameters, show a substantial 
variation in radiation dose [7-9]. 
However, inappropriate irradiation may be quite obvious when 
it comes to the incorrect collimation of the image field or incorrect 
positioning of the infant on the detector or film plate. Unnecessary 
exposure of the abdomen, arms or head can lead to a substantial 
increase of radiation dose, mainly due to the irradiation of red bone 
marrow or abdominal viscera [10]. Effects on the cumulative dose 
in preterm infants may be quite severe and independent of techni-
cal parameters. Reduction of the overall image quality with respect 
to the radiation dose could be influenced by multiple factors. Some 
of them may be specific to the infant, including weight, age and 
disease severity. Other intrinsic factors, such as the education and </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ejro.2015.07.002 
2352-0477/© 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4. 
0/). </p>

<p>J. Stollfuss et al. / European Journal of Radiology Open 2 (2015) 118-122 </p>



<p>awareness of the radiographer actually taking the X-ray on the 
intensive care unit, may also be relevant [10,11]. 
The aim of the present study was to compare radiation expo-
sure and image quality, in terms of the collimation, in two teaching 
hospitals. Our goal was to identify potential factors influencing 
inappropriate exposure of non-thoracic structures in portable chest 
X-rays on the intensive care unit. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>The study consisted of a retrospective analysis of 200 mobile 
digital AP chest X-rays (stored on phosphor plates) carried out on 
20 preterm neonates at two different hospitals, including patients 
with multiple X-rays (performed on separate occasions). One hun-
dred images were acquired from a university hospital (site 1) and 
another 100 images were obtain from a community teaching hos-
pital (site 2). We extracted demographical data from the case notes, 
including the length of gestation (weeks) and the age of the neonate 
on the date of the X-ray. Tube settings and exposure parame-
ters, including tube voltage, tube current and dose-area product 
(DAP) were recorded. The radiography systems used were a Philips 
Mobile Diagnost (Philips Healthcare, The Netherlands) at site 1, 
and a Siemens Mobilette (Siemens, Erlangen, Germany) at site 2. 
The radiographers were noted, as well as their years of experi-
ence in performing X-rays. In addition, we recorded the presence 
of tubes and catheters as a surrogate of disease severity. The data 
were anonymised before image evaluation. Radiographs used for 
the study were included sequentially and not preselected. We did 
not take the diagnosis into account. Both hospitals monitored the 
rate of repeat X-rays. Repeat images on neonates were not allowed 
without the permission of a consultant radiologist. All procedures 
performed in studies involving human participants were in accor-
dance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national 
research committee and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its 
later amendments or comparable ethical standards. For this type 
of study formal consent was not required. Informed consent was 
obtained from all individual participants included in the study. 
Two experienced radiologists (JCS and IK-S) evaluated the image 
quality, based on the exposure of non-thoracic structures. They 
determined the most superior and inferior parts of the body, as 
well as the lateral structures, which had been included within 
the boundaries of collimation on each chest X-ray. The readers 
performed their evaluations according to the European Guide-
lines on Quality Criteria for Diagnostic Radiographic Images in 
Paediatrics [12]. A grading system was used to measure image 
quality in terms of correct collimation. Inappropriate exposure of 
abdominal viscera was assumed when the caudal imaging field 
extended below the level of L1/2 (1 point). Exposure of the cra-
nial structures was considered inappropriate when the collimated 
field included more than the tip of the mandible (1 point). Inap-
propriate exposure of the arms was assumed when more than the 
diametaphyseal junction of the proximal humerus came within 
the field of view: part of the diaphyseal humerus (1 point); entire 
humerus (2 points); part of the forearm (1 point); entire forearm 
(2 points); hand (1 point). The maximum score was 12 points. The 
image quality in terms of correct collimation was graded arbitrar-
ily as follows: 0 points = optimal image quality; 1-2 points = slightly 
reduced; 3-4 = moderately reduced; 5-6 = markedly reduced; and 
&gt;7 points = severely reduced (Fig. 1). Rotation and tilting were also 
recorded. Radiographic errors were recorded on individual tick 
sheets and the information was captured in an <rs id="software-0" type="software">Excel</rs> spreadsheet 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs>, Redmond, WA). The readers resolved any differences by 
consensus. 
The exposure of non-thoracic structures was correlated with 
factors potentially influencing image quality. The chi 2 test (uncor-</p>

<p>Table 1 
Frequency and distribution of exposure of non-thoracic structures in two different 
hospitals. The number of structures and the points scored are shown for the two hos-
pitals. There was no significant difference ( 
* n.s.) between site 1 (university hospital) 
and site 2 (community teaching hospital). </p>

<p>Exposure of non-thoracic structures 
Site 1 
[n (points)] </p>

<p>Site 2 
[n (points)] </p>

<p>Head 
5/5 
7/7 
Right upper limb 
Part of upper arm 
32 (32) 
24 (24) 
Entire upper arm 
20 (40) 
12 (24) 
Part of forearm 
7 (7) 
4 (4) 
Entire forearm 
0 (0) 
1 (2) 
Hand 
1 (1) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Left upper limb 
Part of upper arm 
17 (17) 
28 (28) 
Entire upper arm 
19 (38) 
12 (24) 
Part of forearm 
4 (4) 
4 (4) 
Entire forearm 
1 (2) 
2 (4) 
Hand 
1 (1) 
2 (2) </p>

<p>Abdomen 
7 (7) 
8 (8) </p>

<p>Total 
114 (154) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>104 (131) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Table 2 
Comparison of image quality at the two institutions in terms of collimation. The chi </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>test showed no statistically significant difference in the number of correctly colli-
mated images ( 
* n.s.). The number of exposed non-thoracic parts (head, abdomen, 
arms and hands) in the suboptimal images is also given as a semiquantitative mea-
sure of image quality. </p>

<p>Image quality (collimation) 
Site 1 (%) 
Site 2 (%) </p>

<p>Optimal 
0.32 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Sub-optimal 
0.68 
0.61 
1-2 parts exposed 
Slightly reduced 
0.48 
0.49 
3-4 parts exposed 
Moderately reduced 
0.17 
0.08 
5-6 parts exposed 
Markedly reduced 
0.02 
0.04 
&gt;7 parts exposed 
Severely reduced 
0.01 
0.00 </p>

<p>rected for continuity) was used to calculate differences between the 
hospitals, as well as between optimal and suboptimal images with 
respect to age, gestation, number of tubes and catheters, radiog-
rapher, and the number of years' experience. Student's t test was 
used to calculate differences between DAPs. The Spearman rank 
correlation coefficient was used to analyse the correlation between 
the radiographer's experience in performing X-rays and collimation 
quality. A level of p &lt; 0.05 was regarded as statistically significant. 
Analyses were performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> statistical software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 9.1</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>All images were obtained with the neonate in a supine posi-
tion. Imaging parameters were 60 (60-62) kVp and 1.96 (1.6-2.5) 
mAs at the university hospital, and 72 (70-77) kVp and 0.71 
(0.56-0.80) mAs at the community hospital, with no grid and a 
20 × 25 cm image plate. The DAPs were 0.08 ± 0.04 cGy cm 2 and 
0.10 ± 0.05 cGy cm 2 , respectively (n.s.). The monitored repeat rates 
were low at both units. Only one repeat X-ray was recorded at site 
2 and none at site 1. 
Table 1 shows all exposed non-thoracic structures in both hospi-
tals. The upper arm was most commonly observed, while exposure 
of all other parts was relatively infrequent. The overall frequency 
and distribution were quite similar in the two hospitals (154 vs 131 
points, n.s.). Table 2 presents the number of images with optimal 
and suboptimal collimation. Evaluation shows a comparable rate of 
optimal images in the two hospitals with no significant difference 
(32% vs 39% for site 1 and 2, respectively). The majority of subopti-
mal radiographs demonstrated only 1-2 errors per film, accounting 
for 48% and 49% of the X-rays evaluated at sites 1 and 2, respectively. </p>



<p>J. Stollfuss et al. / European Journal of Radiology Open 2 (2015) 118-122 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Anterior-posterior portable digital radiographs, stored on phosphor plates. (a) (0 points): optimal collimation; (b) (1 point) and (c) (2 points): slightly reduced image 
quality due to exposure of the proximal marrow cavity of the left humerus; (d) (3 points) and (e) (4 points): moderately reduced image quality with exposure of the entire 
right humerus and part of the forerarm; (f) (5 points) and (g) (6 points): markedly reduced image quality in a case showing the entire humerus on both sides and part of left 
hand; (h) (7 points; and (i) (8 points): severely reduced quality observed in two cases that exposed multiple extra-thoracic structures. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Correlation of image quality and gestational age. Using the chi 
2 test, there was no statistically significant difference in mean gestation (weeks) between the two institutions 
( 
* n.s.). There is no obvious difference in image quality, in terms of exposed non-thoracic structures, due to the length of gestation. </p>

<p>Image quality (collimation) and length of gestation (in weeks) 
Site 1 [week ± SD] 
Site 2 [week ± SD] </p>

<p>Optimal images 
32 ± 3.2 
29 ± 3.7 
Sub-optimal images 
32 ± 3.3 
30 ± 3.9 </p>

<p>1-2 parts exposed 
Slightly reduced 
28 ± 3.4 
31 ± 4.2 
3-4 parts exposed 
Moderately reduced 
28 ± 3.7 
30 ± 2.1 
5-6 parts exposed 
Markedly reduced 
28 ± 0.7 
30 ± 1.6 
&gt;7 parts exposed 
Severely reduced 
30 ± 0.0 
-</p>

<p>Based on the number of points scored, therefore, the image quality 
in most of the suboptimal images was only mildly reduced. Table 3 
shows a correlation of collimation and gestation week, the latter 
serving as a surrogate of size and weight of the infants, as these 
data were not routinely recorded in the case notes. The length of 
gestation had no obvious influence on image quality. The same was 
true for the number of surgical drains, catheters, tubes, and central </p>

<p>lines taken as a surrogate of disease severity (Table 4). However, 
a large variation in the collimation could be seen when looking at 
the points scored by different radiographers. The rates of optimal 
images varied between 14% and 86%. The range of mean scores for 
each radiographer was 0.44-2.50 at site 1 and 0.14-2.50 at site 2. 
This phenomenon was not significantly related to the years of expe-
rience, as shown in Fig. 2. The mean collimation scores at site 1 and </p>

<p>J. Stollfuss et al. / European Journal of Radiology Open 2 (2015) 118-122 </p>



<p>Table 4 
Correlation of image quality and the number of surgical drains, catheters, tubes and central lines that may potentially hinder collimation. There is no statistically significant 
difference between the two institutions in the number of these devices inserted (chi 
2 test: 
* n.s.). There is no obvious difference in the number of insertions and image quality 
related to exposed non-thoracic structures. </p>

<p>Image quality (collimation) and number of surgical drains, catheters, tubes and central lines 
Site 1 [week ± SD] 
Site 2 [week ± SD] </p>

<p>Optimal images 
2.2 ± 0.9 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1.9 ± 0.8 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Suboptimal images 
2.2 ± 0.9 
1.9 ± 1.1 
1-2 parts exposed 
Slightly reduced 
2.1 ± 1.0 
1.6 ± 1.1 
3-4 parts exposed 
Moderately reduced 
2.4 ± 0.7 
2.3 ± 0.5 
5-6 parts exposed 
Markedly reduced 
1.5 ± 0.7 
2.3 ± 1.3 
&gt;7 parts exposed 
Severely reduced 
3.0 ± 0.0 
-</p>

<p>Fig. 2. Distribution of image collimation scores in the two institutions (site 1-university hospital; site 2-community teaching hospital). Large variation was observed in 
the scores, although there was neither a significant difference in the mean rate of correct collimation nor a correlation to the individual radiographer's years of experience 
in performing X-rays (Spearman rank correlation coefficient: r = 0.40; p = 0.15; n.s.). </p>

<p>site 2 were 1.40 ± 1.38 and 1.20 ± 1.43, respectively (n.s.). Signifi-
cant rotation and tilting was observed in 19% of the cases at site 1 
and 21% of those at site 2 (n.s.). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Numerous reports have suggested that infants and young chil-
dren are more sensitive to radiation exposure than older children 
and adults, so there is a greater potential for harmful side effects. 
Although radiographic imaging results in a relatively small dose 
compared with computed tomography, the vast number of X-rays 
taken represents an increased risk to the population as a whole [13]. 
In general, there are two major issues in radiography quality 
assurance: one that addresses the quality of the diagnostic X-ray 
equipment and the other that reviews the quality of the radiographs 
performed [7,14]. Numerous technical strategies to reduce patient 
dose have been discussed in the literature. The effects of parame-
ter settings, shielding, incorrect positioning, grid use, and exposure 
indicator targets have been extensively investigated [9,15]. 
However, independently of technical parameter settings, cor-
rect collimation is an important practical issue in radiography. 
Collimation reduces the volume of tissue irradiated and decreases 
patient exposure. It also reduces the amount of scatter radiation 
produced (although the effect in neonates is relatively small com-
pared to adults). However, reduction of scatter radiation reaching 
the image receptor increases image contrast and quality. Including 
extra-thoracic structures in the field does not usually provide any 
useful information on a chest X-ray but may result in a substantial 
increase in radiation exposure. </p>

<p>We compared the frequency of optimal imaging in two different 
hospitals and investigated potential factors influencing collimation. 
Our results indicate that the exposure of non-thoracic structures is 
a relatively frequent phenomenon. Complete or partial exposure 
of the upper arm was the most common finding. In the majority 
of cases, however, image quality in terms of collimation was only 
mildly reduced. The rates of optimal images were similar at the two 
hospitals, one of which has a dedicated paediatric imaging service 
(site 1). 
Recent reports found clear differences between paediatric and 
mixed-patient radiography services (as at site 2), with respect 
to image acquisition, image-quality assessment, and general 
emphasis on radiation dose reduction [16]. In a survey of 493 radio-
graphers, Morrison et al. found that patient motion is by far the 
most common reason for repeat exposures in all services. Other 
causes such as poor positioning, anatomical clipping, artefacts, and 
underexposure were much more commonly described in radiog-
raphy services not based in children's hospitals. They concluded 
that the risk of patient movement encourages many technologists 
to widen their collimation with infants and children, in order to 
capture all the necessary anatomy. The ease of repeating examina-
tions immediately with direct radiography may also contribute to 
an increased tendency to repeat less-than-perfect exposures [16]. 
However, compared with infants in general, motion was certainly 
a less important issue in the neonates investigated in our study 
and the repeat rates monitored were comparably low at the two 
institutions. 
The gestation age (as a surrogate of weight and size) and the 
number of external lines or catheters (as a surrogate of disease </p>



<p>J. Stollfuss et al. / European Journal of Radiology Open 2 (2015) 118-122 </p>

<p>severity) did not have any obvious effects on collimation. We 
found, somewhat unexpectedly, that the number of optimal images 
for each individual radiographer differed considerably. This phe-
nomenon was not, however, significantly correlated to the years 
of experience in performing X-rays. Other intrinsic factors, such 
as educational level and awareness of the radiographer, may be 
responsible for the large variation observed. However, while these 
factors are difficult to measure on an objective basis, our results 
support the idea of individualised training for radiographers, to 
improve image quality and decrease radiation doses in paediatric 
radiography. 
Morrisson et al. emphasised the need for better educational 
materials and training programmes for radiographers. They claim 
that broad commitment is required from manufacturers, educa-
tional institutions, speciality paediatric radiology organisations and 
individual imaging specialists [16]. In the study on the education of 
technologists, participants stressed the importance of immediate 
feedback on image quality and exposure, information about appro-
priate technical settings for paediatric patients, and more reliable 
measures of radiation exposure for patients in general. 
In a recent report, Hlabangana and Andronikou investigated 
the impact of short lectures for radiographers in conjunction with 
poster material showing technical errors in the image quality of 
paediatric chest X-rays. They observed a statistically significant 
improvement in the quality of radiographs performed immediately 
after the educational intervention and a statistically significant sub-
sequent decline in the quality of radiographs performed &gt;2 months 
afterwards [11]. The rate of poorly collimated images (5.4%) was 
lower than we found in our study. However, their evaluation did not 
include any portable X-rays in neonates. They concluded that con-
tinuing education is needed on a regular basis (e.g. every 2 months). 
To the best of our knowledge, no information is available regarding 
image quality for individual radiographers or individual responses 
to an educational intervention. 
Compared with the amount of literature addressing imaging 
parameters and other technical aspects in radiography, relatively 
few data are available on the individual (human) factors influencing 
radiation exposure in paediatric imaging. In view of the very large 
differences at baseline, we can conclude from our data that indi-
vidualised quality assurance, training and follow-up are necessary. 
Given the different distribution of red bone marrow in children 
(contained in a relatively small imaging field), every centimetre of 
incorrect collimation accounts for a substantial increase in the radi-
ation burden, whereas the effect on overall exposure in the adult is 
relatively small [17,18]. </p>

<p>5. Limitations </p>

<p>Our study is limited by its retrospective design, relatively small 
number of patients, and the lack of a control group. Despite 
these limitations, our results show that the individual education 
of radiographers remains an important factor in paediatric radia-
tion protection. The radiographer represents the last line of defence 
against the unnecessary irradiation of pre-term infants. </p>

<p>6. Conclusions </p>

<p>In our study, the only identifiable factor influencing the col-
limation of portable chest X-rays in preterm infants was the 
radiographer's dedication and awareness. There were no apparent 
differences between the hospitals investigated. In general, expo-
sure of non-thoracic structures was relatively frequent and mainly 
involved the proximal humeri. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Appendix A. Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data associated with this article can be found, in 
the online version, at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ejro.2015.07.002 </p>



</text></tei>