<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4620299" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>global burden of all diseases, which might turn into the sec-
ond most common global burden by the year 2020. </p>

<p>2,3 </p>

<p>Major depression contains five of the following symptoms, 
for at least 2 weeks: sad or blue, feeling depressed; increased 
or decreased sleeping; absence of interest or enjoyment; in-
creased or decreased appetite together with weight change; 
feeling of worthlessness or guilt; feeling agitated, feeling un-
settled or slowness; low energy; difficulty in concentration; 
and feeling that life is worthless or suicidal actions. 
4 The de-
pression risk factors are gender, family history of affective dis-
orders, socioeconomic status, no social support, drug abuse, 
childhood physical or sexual abuse history, parental loss be-
fore the age of 10, gonadotrophin stimulation for infertility </p>

<p>ObjectiveaaMajor depressive disorder is the leading cause of disability around the world. The relationship between depression and di-
etary patterns has been reported in a few studies but with controversial results. This study aimed to investigate this relationship in an 
Iranian population. 
MethodsaaIn our study, 330 depressed patients (cases) and healthy people (controls) (1:2) were individually matched according to age, 
sex and area of residence. New cases of depression were recruited from two psychiatric clinics in Tehran. Interviewers went to each pa-
tient's residential area, and invited qualified individuals to participate in the study as controls. Food intake over the past year was collected 
using a validated semi quantitative food frequency questionnaire. Dietary patterns were determined by the principal components method. 
Binary logistic regression was used to test the effect of dietary patterns on depression. 
ResultsaaWe identified two major dietary patterns by using factor analysis: the healthy and unhealthy dietary patterns. We categorized 
the scores of these patterns to quartiles. After adjusting for non-depression drug use, job, marital status, children number, and body mass 
index, the relations of depression and quartiles of two dietary patterns are significant (p=0.04 &amp; p=0.01, respectively). Compared with 
participants in the lowest quartile, those in the highest quartile had significantly lower odds ratio (OR) for depression in healthy dietary 
pattern, and higher OR for depression in unhealthy dietary pattern. 
ConclusionaaThis study indicates that healthy and unhealthy dietary patterns may be associated with the risk of depression. The results 
can be used for developing interventions that aim to promote healthy eating for the prevention of depression. </p>

<p>Psychiatry Investig 2015;12(4):434-442 </p>

<p>M Khosravi et al. </p>

<p>www.psychiatryinvestigation.org 435 </p>

<p>treatment in women, oral contraceptives use in women, stress, 
genetic backgrounds, medical illnesses such as vascular brain 
changes, cancer, diabetes, and malnutrition. </p>

<p>4,5   The rate of success for depression drug therapy of is esti-
mated at 60-80%. Moreover, maximum 25% of all depressed 
patients receive drug therapy. 
1 Due to poor medication com-
pliance in depressed patients, and high rate of recurrence, nu-
trition related factors might have an important role in the pre-
vention and treatment of major depression. </p>

<p>2   The relationship between depression and inadequate nu-
trient intake has been reported in many studies. 
2 For example, 
tryptophan, 
6 B vitamins group, 
7-9 magnesium, 
10,11 zinc, 
12 Ome-
ga 3 long chain polyunsaturated fatty acids. </p>

<p>13-15   The association between diseases and single or multiple 
nutrients is the main focus of traditional analyses in nutri-
tional epidemiology. This type of analysis is relatively valu-
able, but methodologically, it has several limitations. People do 
not consume one nutrient at a time. The various combina-
tions of nutrients in foods may have diminishing or exacer-
bating effects. Besides, the effect of a single nutrient may be 
hard to detect, while at the same time, the collective effects of 
some nutrients in a dietary pattern are easily measurable. More-
over, single nutrient analysis usually changes by the effect of 
dietary patterns. 
16 Furthermore, because of the interaction 
between dietary components, adjustment for these factors in 
multivariable analyses may not eliminate all their confound-
ing effects. </p>

<p>17   The main focus of this study is to investigate the relationship 
between depression and dietary patterns, rather than one or 
more specific nutrients. 
18 Among different countries, a few 
studies have shown an association of their diverse dietary pat-
terns with an increased risk of depression, 
19-21 but with con-
troversial results. 
19,20 Moreover, regarding the effects of racial, 
geographic, environmental, cultural, and social conditions on 
the relationship between dietary pattern and depression, it is 
crucial to perform these investigations in various countries. </p>

<p>22   Besides, advising people to follow a special dietary pattern 
seems more feasible than to intake a specific nutrient, such as 
vitamin D or folic acid. Therefore, in this study, we decided to 
compare dietary patterns between depressed and healthy 
people. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>We used a case-control observational design. Patients were 
diagnosed by psychiatrists as major depressive disorder, us-
ing the criteria of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of 
Mental Disorders, fourth edition (DSM-IV) </p>

<p>23   -standardized in 
Iran </p>

<p>24   -with no history of depression in the past year. We se-</p>

<p>lected the patients according to our inclusion and exclusion 
criteria, recruited from two psychiatric clinics in Tehran. For 
the control group, our criteria was the lack of major depres-
sion disorder, based on Beck Depression Inventory question-
naire (BDI-II), 
25 standardized in Iran. 
26 They should not have 
history of depression in the past year. Interviewers went to 
each patient's residential area, and invited qualified individu-
als to participate in the study. 
The matching of patients with controls was done individu-
ally, based on sex, age, and residential area. Each patient with 
depression was matched with two control people within 10-
year age categories. The inclusion criteria were people of 18-
65 years, residing in Tehran, with major depressive disorder 
in patients, and without depression in control group, maxi-
mum period of 3 month intervals from onset of five symptoms 
of depression to the beginning of the study. The exclusion cri-
teria were as follows: suffering from cognitive impairment or 
other psychotic illnesses diagnosed by a psychiatrist, severe 
depression or lacking ability to cooperate and answer the ques-
tions, starting any anti-depression drugs or treatments, suffer-
ing from hormonal disorders like Addison' s, Cushing' s disease, 
hyperthyroidism or hypothyroidism, and hyperparathyroid-
ism, suffering from chronic diseases like cancer, heart disease, 
diabetes, stroke, fibromyalgia, kidney or liver failure, multiple 
sclerosis and Parkinson disease, history of trauma, cuts, frac-
tures, bleeding, burns, accidents and other similar events in 
the past 3 months, that resulted in unconsciousness and hos-
pitalization, suffering from chronic and infectious diseases like 
HIV, mononucleosis, tuberculosis, viral hepatitis and pneu-
monia in the past 2 weeks, addiction to alcohol and drug at 
the time of the study or in the past 3 months, BMI ≥40 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 
pregnancy and lactation at the time of the study or in the past 
year, using any type of special diet in the past 2 months, and 
using any type of special diet for more than 2 months in the past 
year. 
Sample size was calculated as 110 depressed subjects and 
220 control subjects, using the software <rs type="software">open Epi</rs>, with two 
sided confidence. 
27,28 The investigators provided subjects with 
all related information, understandable to the subjects. A writ-
ten informed consent form was signed and dated by subjects 
and investigators. This study has been approved by the Ethics 
Committee of Tehran University of Medical Sciences. </p>

<p>Assessment of covariates </p>

<p>A general questionnaire was used for collecting general in-
formation, and data on medication use and some confound-
ers. Anthropometric measurements, including weight, height 
and BMI were done for all participants. Beck Anxiety Inven-
tory, standardized in Iran, 
29 was used for a quantitative mea-
sure of anxiety as a confounder. A classified physical activity </p>



<p>Dietary Patterns Are Related to Depression </p>

<p>questionnaire, based on the metabolic equivalent hours per 
day (MET-h/day), was utilized. This consists of nine levels of 
activity, from rest and sleep (MET=0.9) to vigorous activity 
(MET ≥6). The questionnaire has been prepared in previous 
studies in Europe and was validated with the daily physical ac-
tivity questionnaire and the CSA Accelerometer (Model 7164 
Ambulatory Monitor). 
30 Validity and reliability of the ques-
tionnaire have been confirmed in the study of Kelishadi et al. 
in Iran. 
31 A valid and reliable semi-quantitative food frequen-
cy questionnaire was applied to determine food intake in the 
previous 12 months. 
32 Data from the questionnaire was trans-
formed into actual food intake (g/day). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Simple logistic regression was used to examine the rela-
tionship between depression and the characteristics of indi-
viduals, such as physical activity, BMI, and other variables. Di-
etary patterns determined by exploratory factor analysis. We 
entered extracted food groups into the factor analysis and used 
a principal components method to determine number of fac-
tors or dietary patterns. We used orthogonal varimax rotation 
to identify major dietary patterns, based on number of food 
groups. To determine the number of dietary patterns, we used 
the eigenvalue and Scree plot. The Scree plot is a plot of the 
eigenvalues of derived factors and its value was equal to 1.5. 
The factor score for each pattern was calculated by summing 
intakes of food groups weighted by their factor score matrix. 
The derived factors (two dietary patterns) were labeled on 
the basis of our interpretation of the data and of the earlier 
literature. 
Since each participant received a factor score for each ex-
plored dietary pattern, we categorized participants into quar-
tiles of dietary pattern scores. To determine the associations 
of depression with quartile of dietary patterns, we used sim-</p>

<p>ple logistic regressions and estimated ORs. The first quartile 
of dietary patterns score was considered as a reference. Sub-
sequently, we developed multiple logistic regression model, 
and the relationships of dietary patterns to depression were 
adjusted by the confounders that had p values &lt;0.2 in simple 
logistic regression. We checked a goodness of fit by using 
Hosmer and Lemeshow Test, simultaneously. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In this study, we extracted two dietary patterns (healthy and 
unhealthy). We considered qualitative and quantitative vari-
ables, and potential risk factors as confounders. Age (p=0.9) 
and sex (p=0.8) were not different between two groups, be-
cause we matched cases and controls based on these variables. 
There was no significant difference between two groups, in 
family size, birth rank, years of education, smoking cigarettes 
and hookah per week, weight, height, marital and menopaus-
al status, roommate addicted to alcohol, depressed friend, and 
daily energy intake. However, other covariates were signifi-
cantly different among case and control groups (Table 1 and 
2). The mean of physical activity and years of education in 
patients were less than in healthy people, but the mean of pre-
vious depression morbidity and anxiety score in patients were 
more than in healthy people. The frequency of family history 
of depression, childhood history of traumatic events, history 
of evil events in the last 6 months, and non-depression drugs 
intake in patients were more than in healthy people. Depression 
risk is the least in the families with 2 children compared with 
families with 0, 1 and ≥3 children. In addition, this risk is the 
most in subjects with periods of unemployment more than 6 
months in the last 5 years, and in house workers and retired 
participants. Moreover, a decreased depression risk was found 
by increasing BMI. </p>

<p>Table 1. Simple logistic regression results for testing relation between depression and covariates </p>

<p>Quantitative variables 
No. 
Depressed patients 
Control peoples 
OR (95% CI) 
p-value 
Mean±SE 
Mean±SE </p>

<p>Physical activity (MET-h/day) 
325 
36.9±0.52 
38.6±0.33 
0.93 (0.89-0.98) 
0.007 </p>

<p>Previous depression morbidity 
330 
0.23±0.04 
0.09±0.02 
3.29 (1.93-5.62) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Anxiety score 
315 
20.6±0.96 
7.2±0.43 
1.21 (1.16-1.26) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Family size 
331 
3.7±0.15 
3.8±0.08 
0.96 (0.8-1.4) 
0.6 </p>

<p>Birth rank 
330 
3.07±0.19 
2.9±0.12 
1.05 (0.93-1.18) 
0.4 </p>

<p>Years of education 
327 
11.2±0.46 
12.2±0.3 
0.95 (0.9-1.004) 
0.07 </p>

<p>Cigarette use (No./week) 
330 
8.2±2.8 
2.6±1.6 
1.009 (0.99-1.02) 
0.09 </p>

<p>Hookah use (times/week) 
330 
0.4±0.22 
0.08±0.02 
1.3 (0.94-1.89) 
0.1 </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
329 
69.7±1.3 
70.1±0.96 
0.9 (0.98-1.02) 
0.8 </p>

<p>Height (cm) 
327 
162.8±0.79 
163.4±0.59 
0.9 (96-1.02) 
0.5 </p>

<p>MET-h/day: metabolic equivalent hours per day </p>

<p>M Khosravi et al. </p>

<p>www.psychiatryinvestigation.org 437 </p>

<p>BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
&lt;20 
3 (2.8) 
22 (10.3) 
1 (Reference) 
0.04 </p>

<p>20-24.9 
48 (44.9) 
76 (35.5) 
0.764 (0.47-1.23) </p>

<p>≥25 
56 (52.3) 
116 (54.2) 
0.216 (0.061-0.71) </p>

<p>Energy intake (kcal/day)* 
&lt;2169.3 
32 (29.1) 
78 (35.3) 
1 (Reference) 
0.2 </p>

<p>2169.3-2900 
35 (31.8) 
76 (34.4) 
0.63 (0.36-1.12) </p>

<p>&gt;2900 
43 (39.1) 
67 (30.3) 
0.72 (0.41-1.25) </p>

<p>*the respondents were categorized according to the cut-points of energy intake in tertile categories. BMI: Body Mass Index </p>

<p>Table 2. Simple logistic regression results for testing relation between depression and covariates </p>

<p>Quantitative variables 
No. 
Depressed patients Control peoples 
OR (95% CI) 
p-value 
No. (%) 
No. (%) </p>

<p>Marital status 
Single 
32 (29.1) 
67 (30.3) 
1 (Reference) 
0.2 </p>

<p>Married 
67 (60.9) 
143 (64.7) 
0.48 (0.19-1.2) </p>

<p>Divorced, 
widowed, living 
apart from spouse </p>

<p>11 (10) 
11 (5) 
0.47 (0.19-1.14) </p>

<p>Family history of depression 
No 
80 (73) 
196 (89) 
1 (Reference) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Yes 
30 (27) 
25 (11) 
2.94 (1.63-5.31) </p>

<p>Childhood history of traumatic events 
No 
70 (64) 
171 (77) 
1 (Reference) 
0.012 </p>

<p>Yes 
39 (36) 
50 (23) 
1.9 (1.15-3.15) </p>

<p>History of evil events in the last 6 months No 
40 (37) 
174 (79) 
1 (Reference) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Yes 
68 (63) 
47 (21) 
2.96 (1.8-4.86) </p>

<p>Non-depression drugs intake 
No 
85 (77) 
197 (89) 
1 (Reference) 
0.005 </p>

<p>Yes 
25 (23) 
24 (11) 
2.41 (1.3-4.4) </p>

<p>Menopausal status 
No 
16 (18.4) 
29 (16.4) 
1 (Reference) 
0.6 </p>

<p>Yes 
71 (81.6) 
148 (83.6) 
0.87 (0.44-1.7) </p>

<p>Having depressed friend 
No 
90 (81.8) 
194 (87.8) 
1 (Reference) 
0.1 </p>

<p>Yes 
20 (18.2) 
27 (12.2) 
1.6 (0.85-2.9) </p>

<p>Having alcoholic roommate 
No 
103 (93.6) 
212 (96.4) 
1 (Reference) 
0.2 </p>

<p>Yes 
7 (6.4) 
8 (3.6) 
1.8 (0.64-5.1) </p>

<p>Job 
Employee 
12 (11.3) 
42 (19.4) 
1 (Reference) 
0.02 </p>

<p>House worker &amp; 
retired </p>

<p>69 (65.1) 
104 (48.1) 
2.3 (1.14-4.7) </p>

<p>Self-employed 
16 (15.1) 
32 (14.8) 
1.75 (0.73-4.2) </p>

<p>Students 
9 (8.5) 
38 (17.6) 
0.83 (0.31-2.2) </p>

<p>Periods of unemployment 
House worker 
65 (59.1) 
98 (44.3) 
1 (Reference) 
0.008 </p>

<p>≤6 months in the 
last 5 years </p>

<p>32 (29.1) 
104 (47.1) 
0.46 (0.28-0.78) </p>

<p>More than 6 months 
in the last 5 years </p>

<p>13 (11.8) 
19 (8.6) 
1.03 (0.49-2.23) </p>

<p>Children number 
0 
40 (36.4) 
889 (39.8) 
1 (Reference) 
0.04 </p>

<p>1 
23 (20.9) 
44 (19.9) 
1.15 (0.61-2.15) </p>

<p>2 
20 (18.2) 
60 (27.2) 
0.73 (0.39-1.38) </p>

<p>≥3 
27 (24.5) 
29 (13.1) 
2.05 (1.08-3.9) </p>

<p>We defined 26 food groups (Table 3), and assigned each 
food item in these groups, on the basis of nutrients content 
similarities. By using factor analysis, we identified two major </p>

<p>dietary patterns: the healthy dietary pattern (high in fruits, 
cruciferous, yellow, green leafy and other vegetables, low fat 
dairy, whole grains, nuts, and olives) and unhealthy dietary </p>



<p>Dietary Patterns Are Related to Depression </p>

<p>Table 3. Food grouping used in the dietary pattern analyses </p>

<p>Food groups 
Food items </p>

<p>Refined grains and all kinds of breads 
Vermicelli, spaghetti and pasta, boiled potato, cooked rice, breads, Baguettes </p>

<p>Whole grains 
Corn and barely </p>

<p>Yellow vegetables 
Pumpkin, carrot, beet </p>

<p>Cruciferous vegetables 
Broccoli, all kinds of raw cabbages </p>

<p>Green vegetables 
Fresh and mixed vegetables (raw and cooked), lettuce, celery, green pea and beans, sweet pepper, 
spinach </p>

<p>Other vegetables 
Cucumber, squash, mushroom, garlic, onion (raw and cooked), turnip, tomato, eggplant </p>

<p>Fruits 
Cantaloupe melon, Honeydew melon, Water melon, pears, apricot, apple, peach, nectarine, 
greengage, fig (fresh and dried), grapes, kiwi, grapefruit, orange, persimmon, tangerine, date, 
Plum (red and yellow), mulberry, banana, Lemon(sweet and sour), sweet cherries, sour cherries, 
pomegranate, black berry, raspberries, bilberry, straw berry </p>

<p>Low fat dairy 
Low fat milk, low fat yogurt, cheese, dough </p>

<p>High fat dairy 
Chocolate milk, whole milk, whole yogurt, cream cheese, ice cream, curd </p>

<p>Red meats 
All kinds of red meats, heart, liver, kidney, tripe and rennet, tongue, brain, head sheep meat, 
leg sheep meat </p>

<p>Fishes 
Shrimp, trout, salmon, tuna, white fish and others </p>

<p>Poultry 
Chicken breast, chicken leg, chicken wings and neck, fried chicken, chicken heart, chicken liver </p>

<p>Processed meat 
Hamburger, pizza, sausage, hot dog </p>

<p>Legume 
Beans, lentils, peas, broad beans, soy protein, mung, split peas </p>

<p>Egg 
Eggs </p>

<p>Nuts 
Almond, peanut, walnut, pistachio, filbert </p>

<p>Seeds 
Sunflower, pumpkin, and other Seeds </p>

<p>Sweets 
Biscuit, cracker, cake, all kinds of dried sweets, all kinds of cream sweets, halva, hard candy, 
all kinds of chocolate, gaz, sohan, honey, sugar, jam </p>

<p>Pickle 
All kinds of pickle and salinity, red sauce </p>

<p>Snacks 
Fried potato, corn snack, potato chips </p>

<p>Soft drinks 
Non-alcoholic beverages </p>

<p>Caffeine 
Tea and coffee </p>

<p>Industrial fruits and juice 
Canned fruits, canned juice </p>

<p>Liquid oils 
Canola, soybean, sunflower, frying, and other liquid oils and mayonnaise </p>

<p>Olives 
Olive oil and green olives </p>

<p>Solid oils 
Cream, butter, animal oils, margarine, vegetable hydrogenated oil </p>

<p>pattern (high in refined grains and breads, high fat dairy, sol-
id oils, liquid oils and mayonnaise, pickle, snacks, soft drinks, 
industrial fruits and juice, red meats, poultry, processed meats, 
sweets). The factor-loading matrixes for these dietary patterns 
are shown in Table 4. 
Compared with participants in the lowest quartile, those in 
the highest quartile had significantly lower OR for depression 
in healthy dietary pattern, and higher OR for depression in 
unhealthy dietary pattern (Table 5). It should be noted that p 
trend for healthy and unhealthy dietary pattern quartiles are 
significant (p trend=0.010, OR=0.756, CI: 0.61-0.935 &amp; p 
trend=0.003, OR=1.382, CI: 1.116-1.71 respectively). 
All variables with p values&lt;0.2 in simple logistic regression </p>

<p>were comprised in multiple logistic regression models, in-
cluding physical activity, previous depression morbidity, anxi-
ety score, years of education, cigarette use, hookah use, previ-
ous history of depression, family history of depression, childhood 
history of traumatic events, history of evil events in the last 6 
months, non-depression drugs intake, having depressed friend, 
job, periods of unemployment, children number, body mass 
index, and marital status. This adjusted model remained sig-
nificant with five of these variables including non-depression 
drug use, job, BMI, children number, and marital status (Ta-
ble 5). Hosmer and Lemeshow tests were performed to check 
goodness of fit (p value=0.8). Moreover, the p trend was sig-
nificant for healthy and unhealthy dietary patterns, respectively </p>

<p>M Khosravi et al. </p>

<p>www.psychiatryinvestigation.org 439 </p>

<p>(p trend= 0.01, OR=0.73, CI: 0.571-0.940 and p trend=0.002, 
OR=1.479, CI: 1.149-1.905). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We detected two dietary patterns including "Healthy" and 
"Unhealthy" and studied the association between depression 
and dietary patterns. We found that the odds ratio of depres-
sion was decreased by adhering to healthy dietary patterns, 
and conversely increased by the consumption of unhealthy 
dietary patterns. 
The content of exploratory dietary patterns is close similar 
to the results of Rashidkhani study, 
33 and to some extent in 
parallel with dietary patterns obtained in other investigations 
in Iran. </p>

<p>32,34   In comparison with the investigations in other populations, 
there was a strong similarity between the content of dietary 
patterns in the current study and Mediterranean dietary pat-
terns, 
20,35 traditional and western dietary patterns, 
19 and also 
dietary patterns whole food and processed food. 
36 In the cross-
sectional study of Crawford 
37 and the study of Sanchez-Ville-
gas, 
38 more consumption of fast food was associated with the 
higher risk of depression. 
In spite of all the similarities, fish was not included in any 
of our dietary patterns, due to the low consumption of fish in 
our population. In our study, there were some unexpected 
food groups in each dietary pattern. For instance, since frying 
oils have high percentages of SFA, and almost all of our par-
ticipants consumed very high amount of these oils, this food 
group contains a greater amount of frying oils instead of oth-</p>

<p>Table 4. Factor loading matrix for major dietary patterns </p>

<p>Food groups 
Dietary patterns 
Food groups 
Dietary patterns </p>

<p>Healthy 
Unhealthy 
Healthy 
Unhealthy </p>

<p>Refined grains and all kinds of breads 
-
0.636 
Legume 
-
-</p>

<p>Whole grains 
0.403 
-
Egg 
-
-</p>

<p>Yellow vegetables 
0.615 
-
Nuts 
0.513 
-</p>

<p>Cruciferous vegetables 
0.643 
-
Seeds 
-
-</p>

<p>Green vegetables 
0.717 
-
Sweets 
-
0.364 </p>

<p>Other vegetables 
0.610 
-
Pickle 
-
0.301 </p>

<p>Fruits 
0.486 
-
Snacks 
-
0.375 </p>

<p>Low fat dairy 
0.305 
-
Soft drinks 
-
0.38 </p>

<p>High fat dairy 
-
0.387 
Caffeine 
-
-</p>

<p>Red meats 
-
0.407 
Industrial fruits and juice 
-
0.442 </p>

<p>Fishes 
-
-
Liquid oils 
-
0.516 </p>

<p>Poultry 
-
0.395 
Solid oils 
-
0.318 </p>

<p>Processed meat 
-
0.555 
Olives 
0.336 
-</p>

<p>Values &lt;0.30 were excluded. Bartlett's Test of Sphericity &lt;0.0001. Kaiser Meyer Olkin=0.671. Total variance=23.66% </p>

<p>Table 5. Results for testing the association between depression and quartiles of healthy and unhealthy dietary patterns </p>

<p>Variables 
OR 
95% CI 
p* 
OR 
95% CI 
p  † </p>

<p>Healthy pattern quartiles 
0.022 
0.047 </p>

<p>Quartile (1) 
1 
-
-
1 
-
-</p>

<p>Quartile (2) 
0.501 
0.261-0.962 
0.038 
0.464 
0.217-0.994 
0.048 </p>

<p>Quartile (3) 
0.393 
0.202-0.765 
0.006 
0.388 
0.181-0.834 
0.015 </p>

<p>Quartile (4) 
0.440 
0.227-0.852 
0.015 
0.383 
0.176-0.834 
0.016 </p>

<p>Unhealthy pattern quartiles 
0.017 
0.017 </p>

<p>Quartile (1) 
1 
-
-
1 
-
-</p>

<p>Quartile (2) 
1.393 
0.678-2.859 
0.367 
1.782 
0.794-3.999 
0.161 </p>

<p>Quartile (3) 
2.316 
1.157-4.636 
0.018 
2.404 
1.130-5.111 
0.023 </p>

<p>Quartile (4) 
2.714 
1.357-5.428 
0.005 
3.619 
1.593-8.220 
0.002 </p>

<p>*unadjusted binary logistic regression,  † adjusted binary logistic regression for non-depression drug use, job, BMI, children number, and mar-
ital status. BMI: Body Mass Index </p>



<p>Dietary Patterns Are Related to Depression </p>

<p>er beneficial kinds of liquid oils. Therefore, liquid oils food 
group was included in unhealthy dietary pattern. 
In addition, the presence of poultry food group in unhealthy 
dietary pattern does not mean that poultry are an unhealthy 
food group by itself. In fact, the individuals who adhere to the 
unhealthy dietary pattern, along with high intakes of unhealthy 
foods, eat higher amounts of poultry. </p>

<p>33   According to our results and Sanchez-Villegas et al., 
20 the 
red meat was placed in a dietary pattern which accompanied 
with higher odds of major depression. However, according to 
Jacka et al., 
19 the subjects with traditional diet, which includes 
red meat, had lower odds of major depression and anxiety as 
compared to those with the western diet. 
This comparison highlights that the interaction between 
diverse food and nutrients could manipulate the indepen-
dent effect of red meat. Consequently, this interaction is only 
observable in case of studying the dietary patterns, not nutri-
ents intake. It also could be the result of cultural, social, and eco-
nomic differences among people in different communities. </p>

<p>28   In the cohort study of Le Port et al., 
39 low fat dietary pattern 
was associated with the higher odds of depressive symptoms. 
This result is not in consistent with our results and other stud-
ies in terms of fat content of foods. 
19,36-38 In addition, the type 
of fat might be an important issue in low fat dietary pattern. 
Most of healthy dietary patterns with lower probability of de-
pressive symptoms contain olive oil. 
20,21 In Le Port et al. study, 
olive or olive oil was not considered as a food group. In one 
prospective study in 2011, there was a dose-dependent and 
converse significant relation between PUFA and MUFA intake 
and depression. Subjects with the highest Trans FA intake 
showed significantly highest risk for depression. 
40 Therefore, 
different types of oils should be considered to study the rela-
tion between depression and fat intake. 
In the cross-sectional studies of Nanri et al. 
41 and Suzuki et 
al. 
42 in Japan, healthy dietary pattern and balanced Japanese 
dietary pattern were associated with fewer depressive symp-
toms and depressive and anxiety disorders, respectively. 
The common point of the current study and others is the 
inverse relationship between depression and healthy dietary 
pattern. According to previous studies, a number of nutrients 
such as omega 3 fatty acids, vitamins D, E, B6, B12, and folate, 
magnesium, zinc, iron, copper, calcium, and tryptophan are 
important in the prevention and treatment of depression, and 
all of food groups in healthy dietary pattern including vege-
tables, fruits, dairy products, nuts, olive oil and green olive, fish, 
legumes and whole grains are rich in these nutrients 2. A spe-
cific mechanism is proposed for each nutrient, or a group of 
nutrients. For example, tryptophan, as a dietary amino acid, 
is the precursor of brain serotonin. The individuals with lower 
level of brain serotonin are considered to be vulnerable to af-</p>

<p>fective disorders, such as depression. Synthesis of serotonin is 
limited by the inaccessibility of tryptophan. </p>

<p>44   Omega 3 long chain polyunsaturated fatty acids produce 
anti-inflammatory eicosanoids, which reduce the levels of pro 
inflammatory cytokines in depressed patients. 
45 Also they 
have a role in brain functioning and serotonin neurotransmis-
sion (e.g., providing fluidity to neurons cell membrane). </p>

<p>39   The direct effect of nutritional factors on neural physiology 
is been discussed. In experimental studies, brain-derived neu-
rotrophic factor (BDNF) levels were lowered by an unhealthy 
diet within a short period of time. This effect was independent 
of obesity or nutritional deficits. BDNF is assumed to have a 
central role in depressive illness. It also protects neurons from 
oxidative stress and encourages the neurogenesis. Therefore, 
diet may influence psychiatric status through regulation of 
the BDNF expression. 
19 In conclusion, an inverse association 
between depression and healthy dietary patterns is largely 
expected. 
Regarding the relationship between depression and un-
healthy dietary pattern, a significant association has been ob-
served in this study and in several other studies, although with 
few exceptions. 
19,46 The latter might stem from the small amounts 
of unhealthy foods in these populations. 
Unhealthy dietary patterns with high consumption of soda, 
sweets, and saturated fatty acids and low consumption of veg-
etables and fruits usually have inadequate amount of folate, 
magnesium, and n-3 unsaturated fatty acids. These nutrients 
are beneficial against depression. Besides, these patterns ac-
company with high levels of trans and/or saturated fatty ac-
ids 
47 and very poor level of dietary fibers, 
48 which their nega-
tive effect is been proven on health. 
As the study limitations, like all case control studies, we 
could not determine the temporal relationship between di-
etary patterns and depression. Also, we exclude those who 
were addicted to alcohol. Moreover, due to the cultural limita-
tion, we did not question the rate of alcohol consumption in 
people with casual drinking. 
This study was the first case control study in which the re-
lationship between depression and dietary patterns was eval-
uated with a sufficient sample size, and adjusted for many 
confounders and depression risk factors in a developing coun-
try. We also recruited the controls from healthy population, 
instead of clinics or hospitals, and matched them by our pa-
tients. We also specified all inclusion and exclusion criteria 
very carefully. 
For future studies, we recommend to focus more on di-
etary patterns, rather than nutrients intake. In addition to our 
method, extraction of dietary patterns for future studies could 
be applied with other methods, such as Reduced Rank Regres-
sion (Triple R) and Latent Classification Analysis (LCA). </p>

<p>M Khosravi et al. </p>

<p>www.psychiatryinvestigation.org 441 </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research has been supported by Tehran University of Medical Scienc-
es &amp; health Services grant No. 19374-161-03-91. </p>





<p>Dietary Patterns Are Related to Depression </p>



</text></tei>