<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4478705" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Stratified sulfurous lakes are appropriate environments for studying the links between composition 
and functionality in microbial communities and are potentially modern analogs of anoxic conditions 
prevailing in the ancient ocean. We explored these aspects in the Lake Banyoles karstic area (NE 
Spain) through metagenomics and in silico reconstruction of carbon, nitrogen and sulfur metabolic 
pathways that were tightly coupled through a few bacterial groups. The potential for nitrogen 
fixation and denitrification was detected in both autotrophs and heterotrophs, with a major role for 
nitrogen and carbon fixations in Chlorobiaceae. Campylobacterales accounted for a large 
percentage of denitrification genes, while Gallionellales were putatively involved in denitrification, 
iron oxidation and carbon fixation and may have a major role in the biogeochemistry of the iron 
cycle. Bacteroidales were also abundant and showed potential for dissimilatory nitrate reduction to 
ammonium. The very low abundance of genes for nitrification, the minor presence of anammox 
genes, the high potential for nitrogen fixation and mineralization and the potential for chemotrophic 
CO 2 fixation and CO oxidation all provide potential clues on the anoxic zones functioning. We 
observed higher gene abundance of ammonia-oxidizing bacteria than ammonia-oxidizing archaea 
that may have a geochemical and evolutionary link related to the dominance of Fe in these 
environments. Overall, these results offer a more detailed perspective on the microbial ecology of 
anoxic environments and may help to develop new geochemical proxies to infer biology and 
chemistry interactions in ancient ecosystems. 
Linking microbial community composition and 
ecological processes such as carbon (CO 2 fixation 
and respiration), nitrogen (nitrification, denitrifica-
tion and N 2 fixation) and sulfur cycling (sulfur 
assimilation, anaerobic sulfate respiration and 
sulfide oxidation) is a primary goal for microbial 
ecologists. This information is needed to improve </p>

<p>our understanding on the structure and functioning 
of microbial communities, to properly guide experi-
mental research efforts, to promote our ability to 
understand fundamental mechanisms controlling 
microbial processes and interactions in situ 
(Prosser, 2012) and to approach the study of earlier 
interactions of biosphere-hydrosphere-geosphere 
(Severmann and Anbar, 2009). However, a detailed 
comprehension of biological interactions in highly 
complex systems is however difficult (Bascompte 
and Sole, 1995). 
Stratified lakes with euxinic (anoxic and sulfur-
ous) bottom waters are simplified study systems to 
explore current biodiversity-biogeochemistry inter-
actions because of their high activity, large biomass 
and low microbial diversity (Guerrero et al., 1985). 
Usually, oxic-anoxic interfaces contain conspi-
cuous blooms of photosynthetic bacteria that are 
often macroscopically visible because of the high </p>

<p>Correspondence: EO Casamayor, Integrative Freshwater Ecology 
Group, Center of Advanced Studies of Blanes-Spanish Council 
for Research (CEAB-CSIC),  Cala Sant Francesc, 14, Blanes, 
Girona 17300, Spain. 
E-mail: casamayor@ceab.csic.es 
or CL Dupont, Microbial and Environmental Genomics Group, 
J Craig Venter Institute, San Diego, CA 92037, USA. 
E-mail: cdupont@jcvi.org 
Received 19 March 2014; revised 17 November 2014; accepted 
24 November 2014; published online 9 January 2015 </p>

<p>The ISME Journal (2015) 9, 1648-1661 
&amp; 2015 International Society for Microbial Ecology All rights reserved 1751-7362/15 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/ismej </p>

<p>intracellular content of pigments, and additional 
microbial populations also tend to accumulate 
( s- and Guerrero, 1993). These blooms 
are, in fact, natural enrichment cultures that facil-
itate physiological studies in situ (Van Gemerden 
et al., 1985). At such interfaces fine gradients of 
physicochemical conditions are present and tight 
coupling between different biogeochemical cycles 
(mainly carbon, nitrogen and sulfur) are established. 
Microbes adapted to such gradients are difficult to 
culture because in situ conditions are very difficult 
to mimic in the laboratory, and their study has 
improved perceptibly by culture-independent meth-
ods (Casamayor et al., 2000). 
Stratified euxinic lake systems may also provide 
potential modern day analogue ecosystems for the 
oceans during long periods of Earth history. The 
planet was essentially anoxic until 2.7-2.4 billion 
years ago, with a ferruginous ocean (Anbar, 2008; 
Reinhard et al., 2013). With the advent of oxygenic 
photosynthesis, atmospheric oxygen began to rise, 
as did the oxygen content in the surface oceans. The 
deep oceans remained anoxic, but entered a period 
of temporal and spatial heterogeneity. Strong euxi-
nic conditions might be expected in ancient coastal 
areas, with merely anoxic conditions in the open 
ocean, although high Fe deep ocean conditions 
would have been maintained (Reinhard et al., 2013). 
In contrast, Fe is low in the deep waters of the 
modern ocean and, therefore, it is difficult to find 
appropriate ancient ocean analogue in the current 
marine realm. With this in mind, stratified aquatic 
systems with high Fe concentrations in deep waters 
could be more appropriate modern day analogues of 
the Proterozoic ocean. Karstic lacustrine systems 
with a gradient of organic carbon delivery and 
sulfide concentrations generated by sulfate reduc-
tion, and usually rich in iron, would provide 
reasonable biogeochemical analogues for ancient 
coastal to open ocean gradients. 
In this study, we explored the oxic-anoxic inter-
face (metalimnion) and bottom waters (hypolim-
nion) from two sulfurous lakes in the Banyoles 
karstic area (NE Spain) through shotgun metage-
nomics and in silico analysis of several metabolic 
pathways. In the framework of paleoreconstruction 
of anoxic conditions in ancient marine systems, one 
lake would be representative of strong euxinic 
conditions (Lake  ) and the other of low euxinia 
and an active iron cycle (basin III of Lake Banyoles). 
We explore the links between microbial composition 
and functionality for the carbon, nitrogen and sulfur 
cycling after phylogenetic and functional identifi-
cation. The taxonomic identity assigned to each 
functional step was determined by the closest match 
in databases, and the relative abundance and 
distribution of marker genes was comparatively 
analyzed among samples as a proxy of the potential 
in situ relevance of these pathways under the 
specific environmental conditions studied. Because 
of the lack of oxygen, large microbial biomass and </p>

<p>high contribution of deep dark fixation processes to 
overall CO 2 incorporation (Casamayor et al., 2008, 
2012; Casamayor, 2010), we hypothesized a high 
genetic potential for chemotrophic CO 2 fixation and 
a tight redox coupling between carbon, nitrogen and 
sulfur biogeochemical cycling. In addition, because 
of its euxinic nature we also expected a low 
contribution of both methanogens and ammonia 
oxidizers in the biogeochemical cycles prevailing in 
these environments. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Environment and samples collection 
Lake  and basin III of Lake Banyoles (Banyoles 
C-III) are in the Banyoles karstic area, northeastern 
Spain (4218'N, 2145'E), and the microbial commu-
nities inhabiting these water bodies have been 
extensively studied by limnologists and microbial 
ecologists (see, for example, Guerrero et al., 1980; 
Garcia-Gil and , 1992;  s- and 
Guerrero, 1993). The lakes were sampled on 8-9 
May 2010. Vertical profiles of temperature, conduc-
tivity, oxygen and redox potential were measured 
in situ with a multiparametric probe OTT-Hydrolab 
MS5 (Hatch Hydromet, Loveland, CO, USA). The 
different water compartments (oxic epilimnion, 
metalimnion with the oxic-anoxic interface and 
anoxic hypolimnion) were determined for each lake 
according to the physicochemical profiles recorded 
in situ (Figure 1). For sulfide analyses, 10 ml of 
subsamples were collected in screw-capped glass 
tubes and immediately alkalinized by adding 0.1 ml 
of 1 M NaOH and fixed by adding 0.1 ml of 1 M zinc 
acetate. Sulfide was analyzed in the laboratory 
according to  per and Schlegel (1964). For 
pigments, water samples were processed as 
described by Guerrero et al. (1985) and analyzed 
by HPLC as previously reported (Borrego et al., 
1999). Iron (Fe þ 2 ) concentrations were obtained 
from Garcia-Gil (1990). 
These lakes are stratified and have incoming 
sulfate-rich water seeping in through bottom 
springs, resulting in deep waters rich in reduced 
sulfur compounds. An oxic-anoxic interface, or 
redoxcline, is established in the water column 
where light and sulfide usually coexist. Lake 
Banyoles is a gypsum karst spring area consisting 
of six main basins covering a surface area of 1.1 km 2 . 
The basin III (C-III) is meromictic with a maximal 
depth of 32 m, and a redoxcline between 18 and 
21 m, depending on the season. Blooms of 
brown-colored photosynthetic green sulfur bacteria 
(Chlorobiaceae) and purple sulfur bacteria (Chro-
matiaceae) have been periodically reported 
(Garcia-Gil and , 1992). Lake  is a small 
monomictic lake (650 m 2 ), located 1 km away from 
Lake Banyoles with a maximum depth of 6.5 m. 
The thermocline is at 1.5 m, where different 
bacterial populations accumulate (Casamayor et al., 
2000). The presence of aerobic chemoautotrophic </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>sulfur-oxidizing bacteria and substantial fixation of 
CO 2 in the dark have been previously reported in 
sulfurous lakes (Casamayor, 2010). Lake  is a 
small eutrophic water body fully surrounded by 
trees that strongly limit the incident irradiance on 
the lake and provide continuous allochthonous 
organic matter inputs both by leaching from the 
littoral zone and submerged vegetal debris. The 
system is therefore prone to a dominance of aerobic 
respiration and mineralization in surface layers 
overlying sulfate respiration, fermentation and ana-
plerotic pathways at depth. In addition, the con-
spicuous presence of photosynthetic organisms and 
dissolved and particulate organic matter causes a 
strong light extinction and quality filtering in the 
first 2 m that severely limits the development of 
oxygenic and anoxygenic green phototrophs (Vila 
and , 1994). Conversely, the open-basin 
Banyoles C-III is oligotrophic, with lower influence 
of the littoral zone. The basin maintains a stable, 
sharp chemocline that oscillates in depth between 
19 and 21 m depending on the season, being 
shallower during summer. Active sulfate reduction 
occurring at the permanent anoxic monimolimnion 
causes sulfide accumulation below the chemocline, </p>

<p>usually reaching concentrations of up to 1 mM during 
summer and late fall. Lower sulfide concentrations 
are common however during spring. Light intensities 
reaching the O 2 /H 2 S interface are generally low 
(between 1% and 0.1% of surface incident light in 
winter and summer, respectively) despite the trans-
parency of the epilimnetic waters of Lake Banyoles. 
The brown-pigmented green sulfur bacteria are better 
adapted to low irradiances than the green-pigmented 
ones (Garcia-Gil and , 1992) and massively 
bloom in C-III. 
The oxic-anoxic metalimnion interface and the 
euxinic (anoxic and sulfurous) hypolimnion sam-
ples for metagenomic analyses were determined 
in situ according to the vertical physicochemical 
profiles. Samples were prefiltered in the field 
through a 200 mm nylon mesh and kept in the dark 
in 25 l polycarbonate carboys until further proces-
sing in the lab 2-4 h later. The plankton was 
collected using serial filtration onto 3.0, 0.8 and 
0.1 mm Supor 293 mm membrane disc filters (Pall 
Life Sciences, Port Washington, NY, USA) and 
stored in liquid nitrogen or À 80 1C until DNA 
extraction. DNA extraction and pyrosequencing 
was carried out at the J Craig Venter Institute in </p>

<p>Temperature (ºC) </p>

<p>10 
12 
14 
16 
18 
20 </p>

<p>Depth (m) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>1200 
1500 
1800 
2100 
2400 
2700 </p>

<p>Oxygen (mg l -1 ) 
Oxygen (mg l -1 ) </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
1 0 
1 2 </p>

<p>ORP (mV) </p>

<p>100 
200 
300 
400 
500 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>Temperature (ºC) </p>

<p>8 
1 0 
1 2 
1 4 
1 6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Conductivity (µS cm -1 ) 
Conductivity (µS cm -1 ) </p>

<p>2000 
2100 
2200 
2300 
2400 
2500 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1.0 </p>

<p>-200 -100 
0 
100 200 300 400 500 </p>

<p>ORP (mV) </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 </p>

<p>Basin C-III 
Lake Cisó </p>

<p>22.25 </p>

<p>24.0 </p>

<p>1.75 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>H 2 S (µM) 
H 2 S (µM) </p>

<p>Temp (°C) 
Cond. (µS cm -1 ) 
O 2 (mg l -1 ) 
ORP (mV) 
H 2 S (µM) </p>

<p>Figure 1 Vertical profiles of physicochemical data for Lake Banyoles basin C-III and Lake  . Metagenomic analyses were carried out 
at two selected depths (dotted lines): the oxic-anoxic interface (shadowed areas indicate the redoxcline zone) and the anoxic and 
sulfurous (euxinic) hypolimnia. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>Rockville, MD, USA as recently reported (Zeigler 
Allen et al., 2012). </p>

<p>DNA sequences analyses 
A shotgun metagenomics approach was applied on 
all three size fractions of four samples from Lakes 
 and Banyoles C-III. Identical reads were 
removed using CD-HIT (Li and Godzik, 2006). 
Annotation of metagenomic reads was conducted 
through the <rs type="software">JCVI</rs> prokaryotic annotation pipeline 
(Tanenbaum et al., 2010) using Uniref100, PFAM, 
TIGRfam and KEGG (Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes 
and Genomes) Orthologs (KO) databases for taxo-
nomic and functional annotation. <rs id="software-3" type="software">JCVI</rs> Metage-
nomics reports (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://jcvi.org/metarep</rs>) were used 
for analysis and comparative metagenomics (Goll 
et al., 2010). KO annotation was used for functional 
analysis and KO counts were normalized according 
to the length of the read and the length of the target 
gene (Sharon et al., 2009). The communities and 
functional profiles found in each size fraction were 
highly similar (Supplementary Figure S1) and, 
therefore, we pooled all reads after normalizing for 
sequencing depth for subsequent analyses, which 
allows for a better comparison of metagenomes. 
The functional analyses focused on the three main 
biogeochemical cycles for this type of lakes, that is, 
carbon (C), nitrogen (N) and sulfur (S) cycling. The 
genetic potential of the microbial community was 
analyzed following the C, N, and S marker genes 
(KOs) as reported by Lauro et al. (2011) with a few 
modifications. We amended this previous rubric by 
adding the anaerobic carbon fixation carried out 
through the Calvin cycle by Chromatiaceae, and 
additional genes for polysulfide reduction, nitrate 
reduction and nitrite oxidation. In addition, the 
genes pyruvate:ferredoxin oxidoreductase (porA/B) 
were not considered as marker genes for fermenta-
tion as in Lauro et al. (2011), because they are key 
genes in the reverse tricarboxylic acid cycle used for 
carbon fixation by Epsilonproteobacteria abundant 
in our study lakes (Campbell and Cary, 2004; Takai 
et al., 2005). Because both sulfide oxidation and 
dissimilatory sulfate reduction pathways are 
mediated by the same set of genes (aprA, aprB and 
dsrA) but are found in different families of bacteria, 
we assigned metagenomic reads to each pathway 
according to phylogeny, that is, sulfate reduction for 
Firmicutes and Deltaproteobacteria reads, and sul-
fide oxidation for Alphaproteobacteria, Betaproteo-
bacteria, Chlorobiaceae and Chromatiaceae. Finally, 
for the sulfur-oxidizing Epsilonproteobacteria of the 
order Campylobacterales we specifically searched 
for sox genes (coding for thiosulfate oxidation) not 
currently available in the KEGG database. Marker 
genes used in the present work are shown 
in Supplementary Table S1. Hierarchical clus-
tering and heatmap plots were generated with 
R (R Development Core Team, 2012) using the 
library '<rs type="software">seriation</rs>'. Metagenomic data have been </p>

<p>deposited at CAMERA (Sun et al., 2011) under 
accession number CAM_P_0001174. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Environmental parameters 
At the time of sampling (spring 2010), the water 
column was thermally stratified with thermoclines 
spanning from 1.5 to 3 m in Lake  , and 7-14 m in 
basin C-III (Figure 1). Chemical stratification was 
disconnected from thermal stratification in basin 
C-III, where a sharp chemocline was detected at 
21 m depth based on the higher conductivity of 
incoming sulfate-rich waters. The epilimnion of 
C-III showed oxygen concentrations of 46 mg l -1 , 
with rapid drawdowns in the hypolimnion, and the 
sharp oxic-anoxic interface caused an abrupt 
decrease in the redox potential and generation of a 
pronounced redoxcline (Figure 1, shaded area). In 
Lake  , the epilimnion (0-1.5 m depth) was 
oxygen deficient (0.2 À 1 mg l -1 ) and the water 
column became completely anoxic below 2 m depth. 
In this case, the redoxcline and the oxic-anoxic 
interface were located in a narrow water layer of 
0.5 m width (1.5-2 m depth). The concentration of 
nitrogen and sulfur species changed according to 
these physicochemical gradients with high concen-
trations of ammonia mainly in the hypolimnia (up to 
60 mM) and sulfide concentrations ranging between 
532 mM in Lake  and o1 mM in C-III in agreement 
with redox potential (Eh) measurements (Table 1, 
and Supplementary Figure S2). The concentration of 
Chl a measured in the lakes agreed with their 
traditional trophic status (oligotrophic for C-III and </p>

<p>Table 1 Biogeochemical data for Lake  and Banyoles basin </p>

<p>C-III </p>

<p> ML  HL C-III ML C-III HL </p>

<p>Depth (m) 
1.75 
4.5 
22.25 
24 
Temperature (1C) 
12.9 
10.6 
12.6 
12.6 
Conductivity (mS cm -1 ) 
2260 
2268 
2603 
2604 
Eh (mV) 
À 30 
À 86 
195 
145 
Oxygen (mg l À 1 ) 
0.10 
0 
0.25 
0 
H 2 S (mM) 
12.8 
531.9 
0.8 
3.6 
Light (% incident) 
1% 
o0.1% 
1% 
o0.1% 
TOC (mg l À 1 ) 
5 
3 
1.5 
3 
pH 
7.40 
7.23 
7.14 
7.15 
TDP (mM) 
1.05 
2.83 
0.33 
0.37 
NH 4 (mM) 
44.39 
50.99 
25.04 
37.52 
NO 2 (mM) 
0.75 
b.d.l. 
0.21 
0.00 
NO 3 (mM) 
2.20 
1.44 
6.20 
0.54 
Urea (mM) 
4.84 
0.17 
1.91 
1.08 
Si (mM) 
185.0 
168.1 
144.8 
114.5 
Chl a (mg l À 1 ) 
1.7 
22.5 
1.1 
0.8 
BChl a (mg l À 1 ) 
2.4 
123.7 
1.1 
1.6 
BChl c and d (mg l À 1 ) 
5.4 
39.3 
0 
0 
BChl e (mg l À 1 ) 
0.8 
13.6 
25.8 
40.6 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: BChl, bacteriochlorophyll; b.d.l., below detection 
limits; Chla, chlorophyll a; HL, hypolimnion; Eh, redox potential; 
ML, metalimnion; TOC, total organic carbon; TDP, total dissolved 
phosphorus. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>mesotrophic for Lake  ). Biomarker pigments for 
green sulfur (BChl c, d and e) and purple sulfur 
bacteria (BChl a) were detected in the metalimnion 
and hypolimnion of Lake  and basin C-III. 
Particularly, conspicuous concentrations of BChl e, 
the characteristic pigment of brown-colored species 
of Chlorobium, were measured between 22 and 24 m 
depth in basin C-III (Table 1). An active Fe 2 þ cycle 
has been previously reported in Lake Banyoles with 
concentrations of 8-10 mM in both the resurgence of 
groundwater (bottom spring) and water column of 
basin C-III, inflow velocity of 0.8 mmol total Fe per 
h, and concentrations of up to 8 mg total Fe per g of 
sediment (dw) (Garcia-Gil, 1990). Interestingly, 
we also observed substantial concentrations of 
nitrate in the bottom of the basin, coming from the 
groundwater, and high concentration in surface 
waters originated from the surrounding crop fields 
and farms (Supplementary Figure S2). </p>

<p>Taxonomic structure of the microbial communities 
The overall taxonomic breakdown of the commu-
nities was assessed using the phylogenetic annota-
tion of the metagenomic reads. The domain Bacteria 
numerically dominated the genetic composition of 
the microbial communities, both at the oxic-anoxic 
interfaces and at the anoxic hypolimnia (Table 2). 
More than 95% of all taxonomically assigned 
metagenomic reads matched bacteria, with a few 
representatives of archaea (range 0.7-3.5%), phages 
(0.8-4.0%) and eukaryotes (0.7-2.8%). Archaeal 
metagenomic reads were more abundant in the 
hypolimnion (2.67 ± 1.21% of total reads) than in 
the metalimnion (1.09±0.47%). Most of the 
archaeal metagenomics reads matched methano-
gens within Euryarchaeota (c. 88%), with a few 
additional representatives within Thermococci, 
Thermoplasmata, Archaeoglobi and Haloarchaea 
(Supplementary Figure S3). The 16S rRNA gene in 
the metagenomics data set agreed with the broad 
taxonomic picture provided by the functional genes 
(Table 2), that is, 98-100% of the 16S rRNA gene 
affiliated to Bacteria, whereas Archaea were a minor </p>

<p>component more abundant in the hypolimnion 
(1.4±0.7%) than in the metalimnion (0.2±0.2%). 
Interestingly, we observed higher proportion of 
functional reads affiliated to Crenarchaeota-
Thaumarchaeota at the oxic-anoxic interface 
(12.3 ± 0.4% of total archaeal reads) than at the 
anoxic and sulfurous bottom of the lakes 
(8.6±0.5%). Thaumarchaeota metagenomic reads 
putatively assigned to ammonia oxidizers were 
0.03% of total reads but were not detected in the 
16S rRNA pool. Conversely, ammonia-oxidizing 
bacteria (AOB, Nitrosomonadales-and Nitrosococ-
cus-like) and nitrite-oxidizing bacteria (Nitrospirae-
like) metagenomic reads were detected at 10 times 
higher concentration (0.3% of total reads). AOB 
were also detected in the 16S rRNA pool at similar 
concentrations (0.1% of total 16S rRNA gene). 
Overall, the most abundantly recovered 16S rRNA 
gene from the metagenomic data set matched 
Chlorobiales (green sulfur bacteria; 20%, range 
5-50%), Campylobacterales (Epsilonproteobacteria; 
14%, range 11-21%), Burkholderiales (Betaproteo-
bacteria; 12%, range 0.5-35%), OD1 (8%, range 
4-13%) and Frankiales (Actinobacteria; 5%, 
range 0.3-12%), among others (Figure 2, and 
Supplementary Table S2). These populations were 
differentially distributed between layers and lakes 
(Figure 2, and see details in Supplementary Table 
S2) and yielded a taxonomic clustering according to 
the redox potential, with samples with higher redox 
(4 À 30 mV) and lower sulfide concentrations (sul-
fide o13 mM) closer to each other than to the most 
euxinic sample (Lake  hypolimnion, sulfide 
4500 mM, redox À 86 mV; Table 1). </p>

<p>Functional structure of the microbial communities 
The metagenomic data set comprised four million 
reads of average length 377 bp and 54% of the 
metagenomic reads were taxonomically assigned 
based on the APIS or BLAST, whereas 22% could 
be assigned KO numbers and thus putative func-
tions (e-value 10 À 5 ). From the identified KOs, we 
selected marker genes related to C, N and S cycling </p>

<p>Table 2 Total number of metagenomic reads (averaged c. 1 million per sample) for Lake  and Banyoles basin C-III </p>

<p> ML 
 HL 
C-III ML 
C-III HL </p>

<p>Total number of reads 
869 947 
991 056 
1 071 206 
1 077 431 
Taxonomically assigned reads (%) 
46.7 
53.5 
54.2 
62.4 
Bacteria (%) 
92.5 
94.6 
91.9 
93.7 
Archaea (%) 
0.7 
3.5 
1.4 
1.7 
Eukarya (%) 
2.8 
1.1 
2.7 
0.7 
Viruses (%) 
4.0 
0.8 
4.0 
3.9 
16S rRNA genes in the metagenomic pool 
465 
578 
690 
787 
Bacteria (%) 
99.6 
97.9 
100 
99.4 
Archaea (%) 
0.4 
2.1 
0 
0.6 
Functionally assigned metagenomic reads (%) 
25.8 
27.5 
30.5 
32.6 
Reads of key genes in C, N and S cycles 
2392 
3574 
4773 
5162 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: HL, hypolimnion; ML, metalimnion. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>(Supplementary Table S1). Anaerobic C fixation, 
nitrogen fixation and assimilatory sulfate reduction 
genes accounted for a substantial percentage of 
annotated reads in the hypolimnia, whereas genes 
for aerobic respiration, nitrogen assimilation and 
sulfur mineralization were more abundant at the 
oxic-anoxic interfaces (Supplementary Table S3). 
Other less abundant metabolic pathways such as 
ammonification, anammox-SRAO (sulfate-reducing 
anaerobic ammonia oxidation; Rikmann et al., 2012) 
and dissimilatory sulfate reduction were detected, 
mostly in the hypolimnion of Lake  . Such 
differences were globally captured by a functional-
level (C, N and S pathways examined) hierarchical 
analysis that grouped the samples according to 
presence/absence of oxygen (Figure 3). This cluster-
ing analysis produced the same result using multi-
ple other functional annotations, including KEGG 
(EC), Gene Ontology terms and MetaCyc. Similarly, 
repeating this analysis with all size fractions as 
separate libraries (data not shown) and housekeep-
ing genes (Supplementary Figure S4) gave similar 
results, with redox being a more structuring factor 
than geographical distribution. 
As Bacteria and Archaea accounted for most of 
total metagenomic reads, we focused on the prokar-
yotes for a comparative study of the geochemistry 
of carbon (Figure 4), nitrogen (Figure 5) and sulfur 
(Figure 6) along the redoxcline. We used the relative 
abundance of the detected functional genes as a 
proxy of the potential relevance of each pathway 
in situ without considering the role of microscopic 
algae. For the C cycling, the main pathway detected 
in the oxic-anoxic interface was aerobic respiration 
by heterotrophic Actinomycetales and Burkholder-
iales in Lake  , and by Actinomycetales and 
Pelagibacterales (SAR11-like) in Lake Banyoles 
C-III. In the hypolimnion, the abundant pathways </p>

<p>were various forms of anaerobic carbon fixation: by 
Chromatiales (anoxygenic phototrophy by the 
Calvin cycle), Bacteroidales (probably anaplerotic) 
and sulfate-reducing bacteria (SRB) (probably the 
reductive citric acid cycle/Arnon pathway; Fuchs, 
2011) in Lake  , and Chlorobiales (anoxygenic 
phototrophy by the Arnon cycle) in Banyoles C-III 
(Table 3). Chemolithotrophic aerobic carbon fixation 
via the Calvin cycle, which was rare, was mostly 
related to Betaproteobacteria of the genus Hydro-
genophilales (Thiobacillus-like) and Gallionellales 
(Syderoxydans-like). Chemolithotrophic Epsilonpro-
teobacteria with genes for the Arnon cycle (Campy-
lobacterales on Figure 4) were found related to the 
genera Arcobacter, Sulfuricurvum and Sulfurimonas 
(Table 3). Carbon monoxide (CO) oxidation marker 
genes were also present (3-14% of those targeted 
marker genes selected for the carbon cycle, 
Supplementary Table S3) and related to hetero-
trophic bacteria. The potential for fermentation was 
mostly observed in Lake . Both methanogenesis 
and methane oxidation-specific marker genes had 
low abundances in all four environments, and even 
in those samples where such genes were not 
specifically detected (Figure 4, dotted lines) we 
found additional metagenomic reads taxonomically 
matching methanogens and methane oxidizers 
clades. 
For the nitrogen cycle, most of the detected 
marker genes catalyzed N assimilation and miner-
alization (Figure 5 and Supplementary Table S3). 
Denitrification was observed in low abundance in 
all the cases (c. 3% of the nitrogen functional reads 
selected), and the main taxa involved were 
Campylobacterales (autotrophic Sulfurimonas and 
Arcobacter), Oceanospirillales (heterotrophs) and 
Gallionellales (autotrophic Sideroxydans). Conver-
sely, the potential for nitrogen fixation (nif genes) </p>

<p>0 
25 
50 
75 
100 </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>CIII−Metalimnion </p>

<p>CIII−Hypolimnion </p>

<p>Cisó−Metalimnion </p>

<p>Cisó−Hypolimnion </p>

<p>0.52 0.50 0.48 0.46 0.44 0.42 </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l 
l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>Figure 2 Prokaryotic community structure (relative abundances at the Order level) of Lake Banyoles basin C-III and Lake  obtained 
from the 16S rRNA gene present in the metagenomic pool. See detailed information in Supplementary Table S2. Hierarchical clustering 
based on Bray-Curtis dissimilarity matrices. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>was observed in all the cases, although in higher 
abundance under euxinia (18±11%) than in the 
oxic-anoxic interfaces (4 ± 4%). The nif genes were 
most related to Chlorobium in Lake Banyoles, 
whereas in Lake  they were most similar to 
Syntrophobacterales. Under the most euxinic con-
ditions, c. 6% of the total nitrogen marker genes 
examined were the anammox catalyzing enzyme 
hydrazine oxidoreductase, although these were 
associated with Syntrophobacterales instead of the 
planctomycetales found in oceanic anoxic zones. 
Both aerobic ammonia oxidation and nitrification 
marker genes had very low abundance, and were 
only properly detected in Lake Banyoles C-III 
hypolimnion (amoC gene 97% identical to 
Nitrosospira multiformis). However, metagenomic 
reads matching Thaumarchaeota (ammonia-oxidiz-
ing archaea (AOA)), Nitrosomonadales and Nitroso-
coccus (AOB) and Nitrospirae nitrite-oxidizing </p>

<p>bacteria were detected in all lakes and water layers 
(Figure 5, dotted lines), pointing out that the genetic 
potential to close the nitrogen cycle was there, but 
at very low abundance as compared with other 
pathways in the cycle. 
Finally, in the S cycle (Figure 6 and 
Supplementary Table S3) the highest percentage of 
the reads matched assimilatory sulfate reduction 
(28±9% of those targeted sulfur marker genes) and 
sulfur mineralization (35 ± 25%), mostly driven by 
the predominant heterotrophic organisms found in 
each water layer (Actinomycetales and Burkholder-
iales). Most sulfide oxidation genes likely origi-
nated from Chlorobiales in Lake Banyoles C-III, 
and Chromatiales in Lake  , with further 
contributions from chemolithotrophs Gallionellales, 
Hydrogenophilales and Campylobacterales. The 
potential for planktonic sulfate reduction was 
only observed in strong euxinia (Lake  </p>

<p>Cis 
Metalimnion </p>

<p>CIII 
Metalimnion </p>

<p>CIII 
Hypolimnion </p>

<p>Cis 
Hypolimnion </p>

<p>Aerobic C fixation </p>

<p>Aerobic CH4 oxidation </p>

<p>Aerobic respiration </p>

<p>Anaerobic C fixation </p>

<p>CO oxidation </p>

<p>Fermentation </p>

<p>Methanogenesis </p>

<p>Ammonification </p>

<p>Anammox (SRAO) </p>

<p>Denitrification </p>

<p>Nitrification </p>

<p>Nitrogen assimilation </p>

<p>Nitrogen Fixation </p>

<p>Nitrogen Mineralization </p>

<p>Assimilatory sulfate reduction </p>

<p>Sulfur Mineralization </p>

<p>Sulfur oxidation </p>

<p>Dissimilatory sulfate reduction 
Sulfur </p>

<p>Nitrogen </p>

<p>Carbon </p>

<p>0 
0.02 0.04 0.06 0.08 </p>

<p>Normalized abundance </p>

<p>Color Key </p>

<p>Polysulfide reduction </p>

<p>Nitrate reduction + Nitrite oxidation </p>

<p>Nitrate reduction </p>

<p>Figure 3 Heatmap plot and functional clustering of the selected KEGG Orthologs for the predicted open reading frames (ORFs) from the 
metagenomic reads for Lake  and Banyoles basin C-III. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>hypolimnion, 16% of targeted sulfur reads as 
compared with 1.4 ± 1% in the remaining samples), 
with reads likely originating from Desulfobacterales 
and most probably Syntrophobacterales, although 
members of this group may carry out both reductive 
and oxidative parts of the sulfur cycle. Interestingly, 
we observed a high richness of sulfate-reducing 
bacteria genera (Table 3) with the potential to 
degrade a wide variety of carbon compounds to 
help to maintain the high sulfide concentrations 
found in Lake  . 
Although the metagenomic data set does not 
contain transcriptome or proteome data, and thus 
only indicates potential function, we observed a 
direct linear relationship between relative abun-
dance of dissimilatory sulfate reduction genes and 
in situ sulfide concentrations (r ¼ 0.998, P ¼ 0.002). 
Although this comparison should be carefully 
interpreted because of the low number of samples 
compared, it suggests a close link between both 
the abundance of planktonic SRB and sulfide </p>

<p>production. We also observed significant direct 
linear relationships between the relative abundance 
of anaerobic carbon fixation genes from bacterial 
chemotrophs and denitrification (r ¼ 0.958, P ¼ 0.042), 
suggesting a close link between chemoautotrophy 
and the nitrogen cycle. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Stratified planktonic environments with sharp che-
mical gradients and sulfide-rich bottom waters are 
valuable current windows on past Earth conditions. 
Anoxic and euxinic conditions were common but 
spatially and temporally heterogeneous in ancient 
oceans during Proterozoic (Reinhard et al., 2013; 
Lyons et al., 2014), and may have played an 
important role in mass extinctions during Phaner-
ozoic (Meyer and Kump, 2008). The presence of 
marker pigments for photosynthetic sulfur bacteria 
(that is, isorenieratene and okenone) have been often </p>

<p>Carbon cycle: 
CISÓ </p>

<p>ANAEROBIC 
AEROBIC 
FACULTATIVE </p>

<p>Calvin cycle carbon fixation </p>

<p>Anaerobic carbon fixation </p>

<p>Aerobic respiration </p>

<p>Fermentation </p>

<p>Methanogenesis </p>

<p>Aerobic methane oxidation </p>

<p>(Aerobic) 
CO oxidation </p>

<p>CO </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>METALIMNION </p>

<p>Organic matter 
(CH 2 O) </p>

<p>H 2 </p>

<p>CH 4 </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>CIII </p>

<p>ANAEROBIC 
AEROBIC 
FACULTATIVE </p>

<p>Calvin cycle carbon fixation </p>

<p>Anaerobic carbon fixation </p>

<p>Aerobic respiration </p>

<p>Fermentation </p>

<p>Methanogenesis </p>

<p>Aerobic methane oxidation </p>

<p>(Aerobic) 
CO oxidation </p>

<p>CO </p>

<p>CO 2 
Organic matter 
(CH 2 O) </p>

<p>H 2 </p>

<p>CH 4 </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>ANAEROBIC 
AEROBIC 
FACULTATIVE </p>

<p>Calvin cycle carbon fixation 
Anaerobic carbon fixation </p>

<p>Aerobic respiration </p>

<p>Fermentation </p>

<p>Methanogenesis </p>

<p>Aerobic methane oxidation </p>

<p>(Anaerobic) 
CO oxidation </p>

<p>CO </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>HYPOLIMNION </p>

<p>Organic matter 
(CH 2 O) </p>

<p>H 2 </p>

<p>CH 4 </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>ANAEROBIC 
AEROBIC 
FACULTATIVE </p>

<p>Calvin cycle carbon fixation </p>

<p>Anaerobic carbon fixation </p>

<p>Aerobic respiration </p>

<p>Fermentation </p>

<p>Methanogenesis </p>

<p>Aerobic methane oxidation </p>

<p>(Anaerobic) 
CO oxidation </p>

<p>CO </p>

<p>CO 2 
Organic matter 
(CH 2 O) </p>

<p>H 2 </p>

<p>CH 4 </p>

<p>CO 2 </p>

<p>Hydrogenophillales 24% 
*Chromatiales 3% </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 42% 
Burkholderiales 36% </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 48% 
Actinomycetales 21% </p>

<p>Methanomicrobiales 
Methanosarcinales </p>

<p>Rhodocyclales 
Burkholderia </p>

<p>Burkholderia 
Rhodocyclales </p>

<p>Rhodocyclales </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 50% </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 22% 
Sphingobacteriales 13% 
Campylobacterales12% </p>

<p>Acholeplasmatales 
Clostridiales 
Spirochaetales </p>

<p>Acholeplasmatales 
Bacillales 
Clostridiales </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 23% 
Spirochaetales 23% </p>

<p>Bacteroidales 12% 
Desulfarculales 12% 
Desulfobacterales 10% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 9% 
Clostridiales 5% 
Syntrophobacterales 4% </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 40% 
Rickettsiales (SAR11) 15% </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 26% </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 54% 
Actinomycetales 57% </p>

<p>Clostridiales 26% 
Syntrophobacterales 15% </p>

<p>Desulfuromonadales 
Thermotogales </p>

<p>*Chromatiales 21% </p>

<p>Gallionellales 29% 
Hydrogenophillales 8% </p>

<p>Gallionellales 78% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 78% 
Campylobacterales 4% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 70% 
Campylobacterales 3% </p>

<p>Figure 4 Genetic potential for several steps of the carbon cycle in Lake  and Banyoles basin C-III using a combination of normalized 
marker genes. Arrow size proportional to the potential flux of the carbon pathways (100% value, see Supplementary Table S3). Dotted 
lines: not detected marked genes but putative presence of the pathway (see main text). Relative abundances for the main microbes 
potentially driving each conversion step are shown (only for those that contributed 41% of the marker genes mixture). *Chromatiales: 
anoxygenic phototrophy through the Calvin cycle. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>reported as evidence of euxinic conditions in 
ancient oceans ( and  ster, 1998; Brocks 
et al., 2005). These conditions are not common 
nowadays, although persistent euxinia can be found 
in deep silled basins such as the Black Sea, Baltic 
Sea and Cariaco Basin (Millero, 1991; Stewart et al., 
2007). Future climate change scenarios predict, 
however, an increasing of euxinia phenomena, 
mainly in coastal marine ecosystems (Diaz and 
Rosenberg, 2008). The study of stratified sulfurous 
lakes has, therefore, an additional interest to predict 
biogeochemical functioning and microbial interac-
tions in such future scenarios. In the present study, 
we explored the community composition and func-
tional gene content along a gradient of redox 
conditions in a karstic sulfurous area. Continental 
systems are cheaper and easier to sample than 
marine basins, and a large variety of photo-and 
chemolithotrophs organisms, sulfide-oxidizing and 
sulfate-reducing bacteria, fermenters, denitrifying 
microbes, methanogens and methane oxidizers are 
expected to be found, among others, according to 
previous studies (see, for example, Casamayor et al., 
2000;  and Casamayor, 2011). The metabo-
lisms harbored by these microorganisms have the </p>

<p>potential to provide insights into the ecosystems 
operating in euxinic early stages of Earth. The strong 
euxinic conditions found in Lake  may match 
biogeochemistry in ancient coastal areas, whereas 
basin C-III in Lake Banyoles may represent the 
transition from euxinic coastal areas to merely 
anoxic and rich Fe conditions in the ancient open 
ocean (Figure 7). 
The very low abundance of genes for nitrification, 
the minor presence of anammox genes, the high 
potential for nitrogen fixation and mineralization 
and the potential for chemotrophic CO 2 fixation and 
CO oxidation all provide potential clues on the 
ancient oceanic anoxic zones functioning. The low 
abundance of ammonia oxidizers (AOA and AOB) 
agrees with the high ammonia accumulation in the 
anoxic bottom of the lakes, the lack of oxygen and 
presence of potentially toxic sulfide. We observed, 
however, a higher gene abundance of AOB relative 
to AOA in the metagenomic pool that may have a 
geochemical link related to the abundance of Fe in 
these environments. AOA have a highly copper-
dependent system for ammonia oxidation and 
electron transport (Walker et al., 2010), completely 
different from the iron-dependent system present in </p>

<p>METALIMNION </p>

<p>Nitrogen cycle: </p>

<p>CISÓ </p>

<p>NO 3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>NO 2 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>NH 4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>N 2 +N 2 O </p>

<p>Organic N </p>

<p>NO 3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>NO 2 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>NH 4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>N 2 +N 2 O </p>

<p>Organic N </p>

<p>CIII </p>

<p>HYPOLIMNION </p>

<p>NO 3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>NO 2 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>NH 4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>N 2 +N 2 O </p>

<p>Organic N </p>

<p>NO 3 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>NO 2 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>NH 4 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>N 2 +N 2 O </p>

<p>Organic N </p>

<p>Bacteroidales 57% </p>

<p>Bacteroidales </p>

<p>Bacteroidales </p>

<p>Bacteroidales 
Desulfuromonadales 
Campylobacterales </p>

<p>Campylobacterales 47% 
Syntrophobacteales 23% </p>

<p>Campylobacterales 35% 
Oceanospirillales 29% 
Campylobacterales 63% </p>

<p>Desulfovibrionales 56% 
Deferribacterales 16% </p>

<p>Campylobacterales 69% </p>

<p>Campylobacterales 85% </p>

<p>Campylobacterales 27% 
Oceanospirillales 19% 
Gallionellales 17% </p>

<p>Campylobacterales 39% 
Oceanospirillales 26% 
Gallionellales 16% </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 57% </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 23% </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 53% 
**Nitrospirae (NOB) </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 94% 
**Nitrospirae (NOB) </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 45% 
Burkholderiales 31% 
**Nitrospirae (NOB) </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 33% 
Rhodobacterales 33% 
**Nitrospirae (NOB) </p>

<p>**Nitrosomonadales 
**Nitrosococcus 
**Thaumarchaeota </p>

<p>**Nitrosomonadales 
**Nitrosococcus 
**Thaumarchaeota </p>

<p>**Nitrosomonadales 
**Nitrosococcus 
**Thaumarchaeota </p>

<p>**Nitrosomonadales 
**Nitrosococcus 
**Thaumarchaeota </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 12% 
Burkholderiales 9% </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 43% 
Chlorobiales 17% 
Rickettsiales 7% 
Campylobacterales 6% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 59% 
Campylobacterales 19% 
Gallionellales 4% </p>

<p>Syntrophobacterales 51% 
Chlorobiales 19% </p>

<p>Desulfovibrionales 
Syntrophobacterales 
Chlorobiales </p>

<p>Syntrophobacterales </p>

<p>Syntrophobacterales 
Desulfuromonadales </p>

<p>Syntrophobacterales 
Desulfobacterales </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 88% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 89% </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 13% </p>

<p>Bacteroidales 14% 
Clostridiales 8% </p>

<p>Thermotogales 11% 
Actinomycetales 9% 
Rickettsiales 8% </p>

<p>Campylobacterales 23% 
Chlorobiales 12% </p>

<p>Figure 5 Genetic potential for several steps of the nitrogen cycle in Lake  and Banyoles basin C-III using a combination of 
normalized marker genes. Arrow size proportional to the potential flux of the nitrogen pathways (100% value, see Supplementary Table 
S3). Dotted lines: not detected marked genes but putative presence of the pathway (see main text). Relative abundances for the main 
microbes potentially driving each conversion step are shown (only for those that contributed 41% of the marker genes mixture). 
**Presence of AOA, AOB and nitrite-oxidizing bacteria (NOB) reads in the metagenomic pool. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>Sulfur cycle: </p>

<p>CISÓ </p>

<p>METALIMNION </p>

<p>SO 4 </p>

<p>2-</p>

<p>H 2 S </p>

<p>Organic sulfur </p>

<p>CIII </p>

<p>SO 4 </p>

<p>2-</p>

<p>H 2 S </p>

<p>Organic sulfur </p>

<p>HYPOLIMNION </p>

<p>SO 4 </p>

<p>2-</p>

<p>H 2 S </p>

<p>Organic sulfur </p>

<p>RS N </p>

<p>RS N 
RS N </p>

<p>RS N </p>

<p>SO 4 </p>

<p>2-</p>

<p>H 2 S </p>

<p>Organic sulfur </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 64% 
Actinomycetales 9% 
Desulfuromonadales 9% </p>

<p>Rickettsilaes 33% 
Actinomycetales 23% 
Burkholderiales 17% 
Chlorobiales 15% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 63% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 
Hydrogenophilales 
**Campylobacterales </p>

<p>Chromatiales 54% 
Hydrogenophilales 23% 
**Campylobacterales </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 74% 
Gallionellales 19% 
Hydrogenophilales 4% 
**Campylobacterales </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 83% 
Gallionellales 14% 
Hydrogenophilales 2% 
**Campylobacterales </p>

<p>Syntrophobacterales 59% 
Desulfobacterales 27% 
Desulfarculales 10% </p>

<p>Desulfobacterales </p>

<p>Chlorobiales </p>

<p>Desulfovibrionales 33% 
Desulfobacterales 17% 
Selenomonadales 14% 
Chlorobiales 9% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 60% 
Desulfovibrionales 27% </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 56% 
Desulfobacterales 10% 
Desulfovibrionales 7% </p>

<p>Desulfobacterales </p>

<p>Syntrophobacterales 
Desulfobacterales </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 51% </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l 
l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l 
l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l 
l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l 
l </p>

<p>l 
l </p>

<p>Rhizobiales 10% </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 32% 
Bacteroidales 12% </p>

<p>Actinomycetales 21% 
Alteromonadales 9% 
Thizobiales 7% </p>

<p>Gallionellales 22% 
Bacteroidales 9% </p>

<p>Burkholderiales 43% 
Actinomycetales 36% </p>

<p>Figure 6 Genetic potential for several steps of the sulfur cycle in Lake  and Banyoles basin C-III using a combination of normalized 
marker genes. Arrow size proportional to the potential flux of the sulfur pathways (100% value, see Supplementary Table S3). Relative 
abundances for the main microbes potentially driving each conversion step are shown (only for those that contributed 41% of the 
marker genes mixture). **Campylobacteraceae contributed through sox genes not reported in KEGG database. </p>

<p>Table 3 Carbon fixation cycles and main metabolic traits of the C-fixing microorganisms found in this study </p>

<p>Taxa/phylogeny 
C-fixation 
pathway </p>

<p>Traits 
Main genera identified in Lakes  and C-III from 
the 16S rRNA gene present in the metagenomic pool </p>

<p>Gallionellales 
Betaproteobacteria </p>

<p>Calvin 
Facultative 
Chemolithoautotroph 
Energy sources: Fe(II)/sulfide 
Denitrification </p>

<p>Sideroxydans </p>

<p>Hydrogenophilales 
Betaproteobacteria </p>

<p>Calvin 
Chemolithoautotroph 
Sulfide oxidation </p>

<p>Campylobacterales 
Epsilonproteobacteria </p>

<p>Arnon a 
Chemolithoautotroph 
Denitrification 
Sulfide oxidation </p>

<p>Arcobacter, Sulfuricurvum, Sulfurimonas </p>

<p>Chromatiales 
Gammaproteobacteria </p>

<p>Calvin 
Photolithoautotroph Anaerobic 
Tolerates oxygen </p>

<p>Lamprocystis </p>

<p>Chlorobiales 
Chlorobi </p>

<p>Arnon a 
Photolithoautotroph 
Anaerobic (strict) 
N fixation </p>

<p>Chlorobium luteolum </p>

<p>Desulfobacterales 
Deltaproteobacteria </p>

<p>Arnon a 
Reductive 
acetyl-CoA b </p>

<p>Heterotroph 
Sulfate reducers </p>

<p>Desulfatiferula, Desulfobulbus, Desulfocapsa, 
Desulfosalsimonas </p>

<p>Syntrophobacterales 
Deltaproteobacteria </p>

<p>Arnon a 
Reductive 
acetyl-
CoA(?) b </p>

<p>Heterotroph 
Sulfate reducer/ 
sulfide oxidation 
SRAO </p>

<p>Desulfomonile </p>

<p>Desulfuromonadales 
Deltaproteobacteria </p>

<p>Reductive 
acetyl-CoA b </p>

<p>Nitrate dependent Fe(II) oxidation with 
production of ammonium (Weber et al., 
2006) </p>

<p>Abbreviation: SRAO, sulfate-reducing ammonium oxidation. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Also known as reverse Krebs cycle, reverse tricarboxylic acid cycle (rTCA) and reverse citric acid cycle. 
b Also known as Wood-Ljungdahl pathway. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>AOB. The tradeoff in Fe-vs Cu-rich ammonia 
oxidation enzymatic systems would suggest that 
AOA evolved relatively recently (o550 million 
years ago) and that the Proterozoic oceans, which 
would have been Fe rich, would have been AOB 
dominated. Interestingly, the evolutionary dynamics 
of the amoA gene cladogenesis events visualized 
using lineage through time plots displays a different 
scenario for AOA and AOB, with AOB showing a 
more constant cladogenesis through the evolution-
ary time, whereas AOA experienced two fast 
diversification events separated by a long steady-
state period (ndez-Guerra and Casamayor, 
2012). 
The potential for nitrogen fixation and denitrifica-
tion was detected in both autotroph and heterotroph 
microbial lineages, suggesting a diverse range of 
potential overlaps between carbon and nitrogen 
cycling in the ancient ocean, and an active nitrogen 
cycle in anoxic systems. Our results show a 
potential major contribution to nitrogen fixation by 
Chlorobiaceae under euxinic conditions. Chlorobia-
ceae were also the major contributors to carbon 
fixation in Banyoles C-III coupled to sulfide oxida-
tion through the Arnon cycle. Therefore, the 
reported presence of Chlorobiaceae in the ancient 
ocean ( and  ster, 1998; Brocks et al., 2005) 
would have been of major relevance not only for the 
carbon but also for the nitrogen cycling. Campylo-
bacterales (Epsilonproteobacteria) accounted for a 
large percentage of the denitrification genes in the 
anaerobic layers of both lakes, but were taxonomi-
cally segregated (Arcobacter dominated in  , 
Sulfurimonas was present in C-III). Both genera 
respire nitrate coupled to C fixation in the dark </p>

<p>through the reverse tricarboxylic acid cycle (Labrenz 
et al., 2005; Burgin and Hamilton, 2007; Grote et al., 
2012), being potentially able to couple denitrifica-
tion to sulfur oxidation (Ghosh and Dam, 2009). 
The other important group involved in denitrifica-
tion was the chemolithoautotrophic Gallionellales 
oxidizing sulfide or Fe 2 þ while respiring nitrate and 
producing NH 4 
þ or N 2 . The presence of Gallionel-
lales exclusively in C-III is probably because of their 
close relation with the iron cycle (Weber et al., 
2006), and by the fact that an active Fe 2 þ cycle has 
been previously detected in Lake Banyoles (Garcia-
Gil et al., 1990). The potential role of Gallionellales 
in ancient oceans with an active iron cycle is 
therefore of major interest. 
The case of Bacteroidales also deserves to be 
mentioned. Bacteroidales have been typically con-
sidered aerobic or microaerophilic chemoorganohe-
terotrophic bacteria (Reichenbach, 2006), and have 
been recurrently detected in the Banyoles area 
(Casamayor et al., 2000; Casamayor et al., 2002; 
Casamayor et al., 2012) and in the marine realm 
(- mez et al., 2013). However, their role 
in anaerobic, sulfide-rich layers was not elucidated. 
Here, we assigned Bacteroidales as potentially 
catalyzing DNRA (dissimilatory nitrate reduction 
to ammonium), coupling the electron flow from 
organic matter to the reduction of nitrate. Thus, we 
would expect a potential gradient of distribution for 
anaerobic Bacteroidales in the ancient ocean being 
more abundant in the organic carbon-and sulfide-
rich coastal zones (Figure 7) than in the anoxic and 
more oligotrophic open ocean. We also noticed the 
low abundance of key processes in the anaerobic 
carbon cycle such as CH 4 cycling, probably because </p>

<p>Organic carbon inputs </p>

<p>Lake Ciso: 
High C input, high sulfide 
Metaliminion (A) and 
Hypoliminion (B) </p>

<p>Lake Banyoles: 
Low C input, minimal sulfide 
Metaliminion (A) and 
Hypoliminion (B) </p>

<p>A 
B 
A 
B </p>

<p>Oxygen 
Fe (II) 
HS-</p>

<p>Continental Shelf 
Slope 
Open ocean </p>

<p>Modern Analog </p>

<p>Figure 7 Lake  and basin C-III of Lake Banyoles as modern analogs of anoxic conditions prevailing in the ancient ocean. The 
illustration shows the geochemical distributions of Fe, S, C and O 2 in depth profiles and along different oceanic regimes (shelf, slope, 
open ocean) during Proterozoic (Lyons et al., 2014). Lake  would be closer to coastal and continental shelf areas, whereas Banyoles 
C-III would be a more open ocean analogue. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p>in the presence of high levels of sulfate, methano-
gens are generally poor competitors with sulfate 
reducers in stratified natural environments (Raskin 
et al., 1996). Sulfate reduction normally occurs 
in fully anoxic sediments by SRB (Holmer and 
Storkholm, 2001). However, as shown here, a water 
column with euxinic conditions and a high avail-
ability of organic carbon is also suitable for the growth 
of an important community of planktonic SRB. 
Previous studies in Banyoles area measured 
unexpected high rates of dark carbon fixation at 
the oxic-anoxic interface and the hypolimnetic 
waters, accounting for 58% of total annual fixed 
carbon in Lake  (Garcia-Cantizano et al., 2005). 
It was proposed that photosynthetic bacteria could 
be partly carrying out dark carbon incorporation 
in situ (Casamayor et al., 2008), and Thiobacilli may 
actively fix CO 2 at certain depths (Casamayor, 2010). 
However, the ecological factors modulating the 
process and the microbial populations performing 
dark carbon fixation are still not well understood 
(Casamayor et al., 2012). In the present investiga-
tion, we detected the potential for chemotrophic 
CO 2 fixation mainly through the reverse tricar-
boxylic acid cycle (K00174, K00175 and K00244 
from KEGG Orthology) in Bacteroidales, Campylo-
bacterales and Desulfarculales. In addition, other 
SRB such as Desulfobacterales may also participate 
through the anaerobic C 1 -pathway (Wood-Ljung-
dahl pathway, K00194 and K00197) yielding formate 
assimilation and CO 2 fixation (Hugler et al., 2003; 
Sun et al., 2010; Fuchs, 2011). Interestingly, the 
diversity of taxa potentially participating in carbon 
fixation in the dark was larger in Lake  than in 
C-III, in agreement with in situ measurements 
carried out in former investigations (Garcia-
Cantizano et al., 2005; Casamayor, 2010). These 
findings would suggest an active carbon-fixing 
activity in ancient euxinic oceans beyond the 
euphotic zone that certainly deserves further 
investigations. 
In addition, the oxidation of CO generates adeno-
sine triphosphate and CO 2 that may be further 
processed through one of the reductive CO 2 fixation 
pathways to be used as C source (Ragsdale, 2004; 
King and Weber, 2007). Some studies indicate that 
organisms using CO as both energy and C source can 
be viewed as the extant survivors of early metabolic 
processes (Huber and , 1997). In the 
hypoxic layers we found that the heterotrophic 
group of Actinomycetales accounted for most of 
monooxygenase CO genes in agreement with their 
mixotrophic lifestyle (Schmidt and Conrad, 1993). 
More interestingly, in the anoxic depths of Lake  
we found that CO oxidation genes were mainly 
related to SRB from Deltaproteobacteria group 
(Geobacter and deltaproteobacterium NaphS2) and 
to Firmicutes (Carboxidothermus hydrogenofor-
mans, Moorella thermoacetica and Clostridium 
spp.). This finding suggests that the fate of the 
reducing equivalents from CO oxidation in </p>

<p>anaerobic conditions could be coupled to sulfate 
reduction (carried out by SRB) to produce sulfide, or 
to CO 2 reduction to produce acetate (SRB and 
Firmicutes) (Roberts et al., 2004; King and Weber, 
2007). To check whether CO oxidation could be 
coupled to CO 2 reduction to yield acetate (Ragsdale, 
2004; Roberts et al., 2004), we identified the 
phylogenetic affiliation of acetyl-CoA synthase 
genes (ACS, K14138), and found that Desulfobacter-
ales and Firmicutes had the potential to use the 
Wood-Ljungdahl pathway to obtain energy and fix 
carbon from CO in the hypolimnion of Lake  . 
However, although the CO-oxidizing genes were 
detected, we cannot assess their relevance in the 
lake or the ancient oceans because CO-oxidizing 
bacteria carry out a facultative mixotrophic metabo-
lism (Gadkari et al., 1990). 
Overall, the metagenomics approach unveiled the 
interrelationships between microbes and biogeo-
chemical cycling in a comparative framework of 
two lakes that are modern analogs of ancient ocean 
conditions. These results may also help to develop 
new geochemical proxies to infer ancient ocean 
biology and chemistry. A major pitfall in our 
metagenomic approach is the reliance on the 
assumption that the genes come from a particular 
bacteria or archaea according to phylogentic annota-
tion; lateral gene transfer would compromise the 
direct link of phylogeny to a metabolic pathway. In 
most of the cases we found the 16S rRNA gene 
counterpart present in the metagenomic data pool, 
giving additional support to such links. Obvious 
next steps include an experimental quantification of 
the energy and matter fluxes involved in each of the 
metabolic pathways to get a complete picture on the 
tight coupling between microbes and biogeochem-
ical cycling in anoxic ecosystems. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>JC Auguet, M  s, F Gich, FM Lauro and JM Gasol are 
acknowledged for field and lab assistance and ancillary 
data. We sincerely appreciate insightful comments and 
suggestions from anonymous reviewers and the editor. 
This research was funded by Grants GOS-LAKES 
CGL2009-08523-E and DARKNESS CGL2012-32747 to 
EOC from the Spanish Office of Science (MINECO), from 
financial support by the Beyster Family Fund of the San 
Diego Foundation and the Life Technologies Foundation 
to the J Craig Venter Institute, and the NASA Astrobiology 
Institute to CLD. </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>Anbar AD. (2008). Oceans elements and evolution. 
Science 322: 1481-1483. </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>

<p>1659 </p>

<p>The ISME Journal </p>

<p> A, Casamayor EO. (2011). Euxinic freshwater 
hypolimnia promote bacterial endemicity in continen-
tal areas. Microb Ecol 61: 465-472. 
Bascompte J, Sole RV. (1995). Rethinking complexity -
modeling spatiotemporal dynamics in ecology. Trends 
Ecol Evol 10: 361-366. 
Borrego CM, Baneras L, Garcia-Gil J. (1999). Temporal 
variability of Chlorobium phaeobacteroides antenna 
pigments in a meromictic karstic lake. Aquat Microb 
Ecol 17: 121-129. 
Brocks JJ, Love GD, Summons RE, Knoll AH, Logan GA, 
Bowden SA. (2005). Biomarker evidence for green and 
purple sulphur bacteria in a stratified Palaeoproter-
ozoic sea. Nature 437: 866-870. 
Burgin AJ, Hamilton SK. (2007). Have we overemphasized 
the role of denitrification in aquatic ecosystems? A 
review of nitrate removal pathways. Front Ecol 
Environ 5: 89-96. 
Campbell BJ, Cary SC. (2004). Abundance of reverse 
tricarboxylic acid cycle genes in free-living micro-
organisms at deep-sea hydrothermal vents. Appl 
Environ Microbiol 70: 6282-6289. 
Casamayor EO, Schafer H, Baneras L,  s- C, 
Muyzer G. (2000). Identification of and spatio-tem-
poral differences between microbial assemblages from 
two neighboring sulfurous lakes: comparison by 
microscopy and denaturing gradient gel electrophor-
esis. Appl Environ Microbiol 66: 499-508. 
Casamayor EO,  s- C, Muyzer G, Amann R. 
(2002). Microheterogeneity in 16S ribosomal DNA-
defined bacterial populations from a stratified plank-
tonic environment is related to temporal changes and 
to ecological adaptations. Appl Environ Microbiol 68: 
1706-1714. 
Casamayor EO, Garcia-Cantizano J,  s- C. (2008). 
Carbon dioxide fixation in the dark by photosynthetic 
bacteria in sulfide-rich stratified lakes with oxic-
anoxic interfaces. Limnol Oceanogr 53: 1193-1203. 
Casamayor EO. (2010). Vertical distribution of planktonic 
autotrophic thiobacilli and dark CO2 fixation rates in 
lakes with oxygen-sulfide interfaces. Aquat Microb 
Ecol 59: 217-228. 
Casamayor EO,  s M, Picazo A,  A, Borrego 
CM, Camacho A. (2012). Contribution of deep dark 
fixation processes to overall CO2 incorporation and 
large vertical changes of microbial populations in 
stratified karstic lakes. Aquat Sci 74: 61-75. 
 JSS,  J. (1998). A euxinic southern North 
Atlantic Ocean during the Cenomanian/Turonian ocea-
nic anoxic event. Earth Planet Sci Lett 158: 165-173. 
Diaz RJ, Rosenberg R. (2008). Spreading dead zones and 
consequences for marine ecosystems. Science 321: 
926-929. 
- mez B, Richter M,  ler M, Pinhassi J, 
Acinas SG,  JM et al. (2013). Ecology of 
marine Bacteroidetes: a comparative genomics 
approach. ISME J 7: 1026-1037. 
ndez-Guerra A, Casamayor EO. (2012). Habitat-
associated phylogenetic community patterns of micro-
bial ammonia oxidizers. PLoS One 7: e47330. 
Fuchs G. (2011). Alternative pathways of carbon dioxide 
fixation: insights into the early evolution of life? In: 
Gottesman S, Harwood CS (eds) Annual Review of 
Microbiology vol. 65. Annual Reviews: Palo Alto, 
p 631. 
Gadkari D, Schricker K, Acker G, Kroppenstedt RM, Meyer 
O. (1990). Streptomyces thermoautotrophicus sp. nov., </p>





<p>The ISME Journal </p>



<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on The ISME Journal website (http://www.nature.com/ismej) </p>

<p>Biodiversity and biogeochemistry in euxinic lakes 
T Llorens-s et al </p>



<p>The ISME Journal </p>

</text></tei>