<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4914536" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background Based on data of clinical trials, new agents 
are receiving approval to the pharmaceutical market, for 
which information concerning safety issues under real-life 
conditions is not yet available. 
Objectives The aim was to evaluate the tolerability of 
newer antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), such as topiramate, 
levetiracetam, zonisamide, pregabalin, extended-release 
oxcarbazepine, lacosamide and eslicarbazepine, under real-
life conditions by means of an assessment of routine clin-
ical data of inpatients. 
Method Over 2.75 years data of all inpatients receiving 
one of the newer AEDs were documented. Occurring 
adverse drug reactions (ADRs) were classified according to 
the WHO-UMC Causality Assessment concerning their 
likely relationship to the prescribed AEDs. For each AED, </p>

<p>the total number of patients without and with ADRs, 
assessed as at least possibly related to the particular drug, 
was calculated and corresponding incidences compared 
with reference data provided in the Summary of Product 
Characteristics (SmPC). For statistical evaluation Spear-
man correlation (r s ), estimated relative risk and logistic 
regression analysis were used. 
Results In total, the data of 562 patients were assessed, of 
which 90 % received up to six different AEDs. The pro-
portion of off-label use with regard to dosage varied 
between 6.4 and 64.7 %. Levetiracetam and oxcarbazepine 
as an extended-release formulation were most commonly 
used, and levetiracetam showed the best tolerance. By 
using logistic regression, the occurrence of ADRs was 
significantly associated with the number of AEDs 
(p \ 0.001) as well as the defined daily doses (p = 0.003). 
In total, ADRs of AEDs were documented for 318 patients 
(56.6 %). The most common referred to electrolyte 
imbalance, e.g., low sodium (n = 79, 14.1 %) and potas-
sium (n = 25, 4.4 %) levels, the central nervous system, 
including dizziness (n = 61, 10.9 %), disturbed vision 
(n = 47, 8.4 %), fatigue (n = 40, 7.1 %), nystagmus 
(n = 36, 6.4 %) and ataxia (n = 29, 5.2 %), or cognitive 
deficits, especially disturbance of speech (n = 37, 6.6 %), 
memory impairment (n = 36, 6.4 %) and mental slowing 
(n = 32, 5.7 %). By comparing the assessed ADR inci-
dences with specification data, for some ADRs, a probable 
underestimation by the SmPC of respective risk could be 
assumed. 
Conclusion During inpatient treatment, valuable data are 
generated, which are currently rarely utilized for pharma-
coepidemiologic or pharmacovigilance purposes. A sys-
tematic evaluation of these data can increase the 
probability of detecting ADRs and can promote real-life-
related drug surveillance. </p>

<p>Electronic supplementary material The online version of this 
article (Based on submitted quality, efficacy and safety data, doz-
ens of new agents are receiving approval to the pharma-
ceutical market every year. Despite their promising 
advantage to medical care, at the time of approval, there 
can be no certainty that these drugs are completely safe [1]. 
Information about specific population groups can fre-
quently be assumed to be missing as well as data about rare 
adverse drug reactions (ADRs) or drug interactions. It is 
therefore necessary to establish methods of large-scale 
post-marketing surveillance to gather real-life data espe-
cially with regard to safety issues. In most countries a 
spontaneous reporting system (SRS) for collecting data of 
suspected ADRs is used. Reported data are assessed by the 
responsible authority in a global database, which thus 
contains a vast data pool of ADRs relating to a wide range 
of drugs, in support of its main objective of generating 
signals of unknown, rare or serious ADRs [2-4]. This is a 
very cost-effective method. However, this kind of drug 
safety monitoring also has many limitations, the most 
frequently mentioned being the subject of underreporting. 
The mentioned reasons for this are manifold, including lack 
of time, large effort, fear of being prosecuted, unawareness 
of the requirement to report or the estimation that a par-
ticular ADR is not worth noting [3-5]. Also, SRSs are often 
believed to be exclusively designed for detecting rare and 
serious ADRs, but for general drug safety, the monitoring 
of all undesirable reactions is necessary [4]. For the most 
accurate relative risk (RR) assessment, exact data of 
application or drug utilization is required, which, however, 
is only available by approximation. Thus, an SRS has not 
got the impact to determine the prevalence rate of a specific 
ADR reliably and bears a risk of delay in signal detection. 
In the case of diseases requiring lifelong treatment, more 
detailed knowledge about the efficacy and tolerability of a </p>

<p>drug, attention to ADRs as well as awareness of patients' 
needs are necessary to achieve the best therapeutic out-
come. For epilepsy, as one of these diseases, the occurrence 
of ADRs has been shown to have an important influence on 
patients' quality of life [6-9]. Approximately 20 % of all 
patients with epilepsy, in the case of refractory epilepsy, 
even about 50 %, are on polytherapy, bearing an increased 
risk for ADRs and drug interactions [10-13]. Many of 
these patients have tried most of the available drugs and are 
therefore a target group for new treatment options aimed at 
reducing seizure frequency while maintaining or even 
optimizing tolerability. Especially in patients suffering 
from seizure recurrence, optimizing therapy can be a bal-
ancing act between increasing the drug dosage to maximize 
the therapeutic effect and running the risk of ADRs [14, 
15]. Over the past 25 years, more than 15 new antiepileptic 
drugs (AEDs) with modified acting mechanisms and/or 
side effect profiles have become available for epilepsy 
treatment, resulting in a major challenge for health pro-
fessionals and post-marketing surveillance in respect of 
specified knowledge about tolerability and drug interaction. 
Such a level of competence can hardly be generated by 
relying only upon a tool like an SRS for monitoring drug 
safety. In fact, long-term supervision of medicated patients, 
increased sensitivity towards recognizing accumulation of 
specific ADRs and deriving remedial measures from these 
observations are recommended as vital for a comprehen-
sive risk-benefit evaluation [14]. Accordingly, the sys-
tematic assessment and evaluation of routine inpatient data 
was assumed to be one way of obtaining this relevant 
knowledge and was therefore investigated in this survey. </p>

<p>2 Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Data Collection </p>

<p>Between May 2008 and December 2010, an in-house 
pharmacist attended the Consultants' ward round once a 
week on four different wards of the Bethel Epilepsy Centre, 
Bielefeld, Germany, a tertiary reference center for epi-
lepsy. All information taken as part of clinical routine 
during the ward round was documented in the patients' 
chart as usual and, for later digitalization, concurrently 
transcribed to an adjusted record form by the pharmacist. 
For every patient a new record form was used for each 
week. All inpatients receiving one of the newer AEDs, i.e., 
topiramate (TPM), levetiracetam (LEV), zonisamide 
(ZNS), pregabalin (PGB), extended-release oxcarbazepine 
[OXC(ER)], lacosamide (LCM) and eslicarbazepine (ESL), 
were included. Documented data comprised the specific 
drug, all AEDs in use, corresponding daily dosages and 
serum levels, if available, age, gender, concomitant </p>

<p> 
A. Hilgers, M. Schaefer </p>

<p>medication, patient and actual case number. In addition, all 
patient-reported and medically diagnosed ADRs were 
documented in an unstructured format, and for each one, 
the current causality concerning the administered AEDs 
was assessed by interprofessional exchange (i.e., physician, 
pharmacist, nursing staff). To this end, the temporal pattern 
of association between its occurrence and change of med-
ication and all available information concerning concomi-
tant disorders, diseases or medication were taken into 
account. For the classification of causality, the WHO-UMC 
Causality Categories were used (see the electronic sup-
plementary material, Online Resource 1) [16]. Any severe 
or unknown suspected ADRs were immediately reported 
via the SRS to the responsible regulatory authority. </p>

<p>2.2 Data Entry </p>

<p>All relevant data were recorded by the pharmacist in an 
internal database, using IBM <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> for Windows <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0</rs>. 
Patient data were documented by assigning an individual 
patient number, case number, gender, age and date of 
observation. In order to enable the evaluation, the initially 
documented ADRs were coded numerically according to 
the system organ classes (SOCs) of the MedDRA (Medical 
Dictionary for Regulatory Activities) terminology, and the 
specific symptom. Also, corresponding causality categories 
were entered numerically. For every documented ADR and 
week, a single data set containing patient details, medica-
tion, daily dosage and causality category for every given 
AED was generated. Where the same ADR was docu-
mented more than once for one patient, the first docu-
mented observation and accordingly the one with the 
lowest AED dosages was included for analysis only. For 
patients without ADRs, the highest AED dosage was 
considered. To rule out possible input errors, the data were 
entered twice at different times. Asserted discrepancies 
were clarified by re-checking the record forms. </p>

<p>2.3 Data Evaluation </p>

<p>Demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients 
were evaluated by using the first documented contact after 
hospitalization. For every newer AED, the total number of 
patients without and with ADRs, assessed with at least 
possible causality, and the corresponding dosages were 
calculated. Additionally, the same analysis was performed 
including only data sets of patients being treated off-label 
with regard to the maximum recommended daily dosage in 
the Summary of Product Characteristics (SmPC). In both 
analyses, every patient was included only once. Further-
more, for every AED, the incidence of the respective ADR 
was determined with reference to the number of patients 
experiencing this ADR while taking the particular AED </p>

<p>divided by the total number of patients where this AED 
was part of the therapy. All estimated incidence rates were 
compared with the respective data provided in the SmPC of 
each AED [17-23]. The correlation between the number of 
AEDs and the total drug load, calculated as sum of the 
defined daily doses (DDDs), was determined by Spearman 
correlation. For assessing the impact of number of AEDs 
and sum of DDDs on the occurrence of ADR, logistic 
regression was used. 
Concerning tolerability of each AED, the RR of ADR 
occurrence was calculated. For this purpose, the data of 
LEV were used as the reference, as being the most fre-
quently applied AED in this survey, the first recommended 
for treatment of focal epilepsy out of this selection and also 
proven as well tolerated [24-28]. </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>In total, data of 562 cases were assessed, which equals 
around one quarter of the total number of in-house 
patients on the attended wards in the same time period. 
The corresponding patients' characteristics, length of stay 
and number of AEDs in concomitant usage [mean, median 
and standard deviation (SD)] are summarized in Table 1. 
For further specification of the antiepileptic therapy, the 
number and percentage distribution of patients receiving 
antiepileptic monotherapy versus polytherapy of up to six 
different AEDs were evaluated on the basis of each ini-
tially documented observation per patient. Hence, 57 
patients (10.1 %) were on monotherapy, 192 patients 
(34.2 %) were treated with two different AEDs, 205 
patients (36.5 %) with three, 88 (15.7 %) with four, 19 
(3.4 %) with five and just one patient (0.2 %) with six. 
The number of AEDs correlated significantly with the 
total drug load as sum of DDDs (r s = 0.661, p \ 0.001). 
The mean drug load (± SD) per patient increased with an 
increasing number of AEDs from 1.15 ± 0.60 in patients 
on monotherapy to 2.42 ± 0.98 in patients on two con-
comitant AEDs, 3.33 ± 1.33 in those on three, 
4.50 ± 1.35 in those on four and 5.56 ± 1.28 in those on 
five or six. 
In monotherapy, as well as in a combination of two 
different AEDs, OXC(ER) and LEV were the ones most 
commonly used. This is the case for more than 40 % of the 
patients. For further information concerning the percentage 
of each AED in antiepileptic polytherapy see Fig. 1. LEV 
and OXC(ER) were further the most frequently used at all, 
with applications documented for 367 and 183 patients, 
respectively. For TPM and LCM, the data of 109 and 102 
patients were assessed, whereas ZNS (68 patients), PGB 
(61 patients) and ESL (17 patients) were a less frequently 
used component of the antiepileptic therapy. </p>

<p>Systematic ADR Monitoring in Epilepsy Therapy Using Routine Clinical Data </p>

<p>
In total, ADRs of AEDs were documented for 318 
patients (56.6 %). Logistic regression indicated that the 
occurrence of ADRs was significantly associated with the 
number of AEDs in polytherapy regime (p \ 0.001) as 
well as the total drug load as sum of DDDs (p = 0.003), 
whereas each predictor was analyzed separately. </p>

<p>For each of the focused AEDs, the number of cases 
without and with an ADR of at least possible causality and 
corresponding dosages are listed in Table 2. For none of 
these AEDs the sum of percentage of cases without and 
with possibly related ADRs achieved 100 %. The differ-
ences, ranging from 4 to 15 %, represent ADRs assessed as </p>

<p>Table 1 Patients' 
characteristics 
a of 562 in-house 
patients treated at the tertiary 
reference center for epilepsy 
who were receiving at least one 
of the newer AEDs </p>

<p>N 
Total (%) 
Mean 
Median 
SD 
Min. 
Max. </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
293 
52.1 </p>

<p>Female 
269 
47.9 </p>

<p>Epilepsy syndrome </p>

<p>Focal 
446 
79.4 </p>

<p>Generalized 
83 
14.8 </p>

<p>Focal ? generalized 
24 
4.3 </p>

<p>Non-epileptic disorder </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>9 
1.6 </p>

<p>Age (years) 
562 
37.2 
36.0 
14.6 
16.0 
89.0 </p>

<p>Length of stay (days) 
562 
60.6 
51.0 
38.7 
6.0 
238.0 </p>

<p>No. of AEDs per patient 
562 
2.64 
3.00 
1.00 
1.00 
6.00 </p>

<p>Drug load of AEDs (DDD) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>562 
3.14 
3.02 
1.53 
0.25 
10.82 </p>

<p>AED antiepileptic drug, DDD defined daily dose, SD standard deviation 
a Calculated by including every first documented observation of each patient </p>

<p>b Differential diagnosis of a paroxysmal non-epileptic disorder obtained during hospitalization </p>

<p>c Sum of DDD according to the WHO DDD list </p>

<p>0.71% </p>

<p>6.05% </p>

<p>0.18% </p>

<p>3.20% </p>

<p>5.16% </p>

<p>23.67% </p>

<p>1.96% </p>

<p>2.31% </p>

<p>10.85% </p>

<p>3.20% </p>

<p>0.53% </p>

<p>8.72% </p>

<p>22.95% </p>

<p>5.16% </p>

<p>5.16% </p>

<p>12.81% </p>

<p>9,08% </p>

<p>1.78% </p>

<p>3.56% </p>

<p>10.85% </p>

<p>4.27% </p>

<p>2.85% </p>

<p>4.63% </p>

<p>4.80% </p>

<p>0.71% </p>

<p>1.25% </p>

<p>2.31% </p>

<p>0.53% </p>

<p>0.18% </p>

<p>0.89% </p>

<p>0.89% </p>

<p>0.36% </p>

<p>0.18% </p>

<p>0.18% </p>

<p>0% 
5% 
10% 
15% 
20% 
25% 
30% 
35% 
40% 
45% 
50% 
55% 
60% 
65% 
70% </p>

<p>TPM </p>

<p>LEV </p>

<p>ZNS </p>

<p>PGB </p>

<p>OXC(ER) </p>

<p>LCM </p>

<p>ESL </p>

<p>1 AED </p>

<p>2 AED </p>

<p>3 AED </p>

<p>4 AED </p>

<p>5 AED </p>

<p>6 AED </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Percentage of patients treated with the respective AED, 
stratified by monotherapy and the different kinds of polytherapy (left 
to right). Total percentage of patients taking respective drug either as 
monotherapy or part of polytherapy: LEV 66.19 %, OXC(ER) 
32.38 %, TPM 19.4 %, LCM 18.15 %, ZNS 12.1 %, PGB 10.68 %, </p>

<p>and ESL 3.02 %. AED antiepileptic drug, ESL eslicarbazepine, LCM 
lacosamide, LEV levetiracetam, OXC(ER) oxcarbazepine extended-
release formulation, PGB pregabalin, TPM topiramate, ZNS 
zonisamide </p>

<p> 
A. Hilgers, M. Schaefer </p>

<p>unlikely, conditional or not causally linked to the particular 
AED. In the case of TPM, this applied to 13 patients, for 
LEV to 44, PGB to seven, ZNS to ten, OXC(ER) to 13, 
LCM to ten and ESL to just one patient. 
By referring exclusively to the overall tolerability, LEV 
emerged as best tolerated. The calculated RRs of ADR 
occurrence per AED compared with LEV, which was set as 
reference, ranged between 1.31 and 2.30, whereas again 
just the total number of possibly related ADRs was taken 
into account, not the clinical relevance of every single 
ADR nor other tolerability influencing factors. 
By means of the maximum applied dosages (Table 2), it 
becomes apparent that in some cases the maximum applied 
AED dosage exceeded the maximum permissible dosage 
according to the particular SmPC [17-23]. For LCM, that 
dosage was specified as 400 mg per day, for TPM and 
ZNS, as 500 mg/day each, and for PGB, as 600 mg/day; 
for ESL, OXC(ER) and LEV, the maximum approved 
dosage was determined as 1200, 2400 and 3000 mg/day, 
respectively. The proportion of off-label usage concerning </p>

<p>the maximum recommended daily dosage in the SmPC 
varied between 6.4 and 64.7 % with regard to the total 
number of patients the respective AED was part of therapy. 
For further differentiation, the corresponding data of every 
single AED, with and without ADR, is summarized in 
Table 3. Comparing the calculated RR for each AED used 
off-label to its application as recommended by the SmPC 
revealed no relevant risk change. Though, the number of 
patients for these evaluations was small. 
Concerning the documented ADRs, the most common 
were related to electrolyte imbalance, e.g., low sodium 
(n = 79, 14.1 %) and potassium (n = 25, 4.4 %) levels, 
the central nervous system, including dizziness (n = 61, 
10.9 %), disturbed vision (n = 47, 8.4 %), fatigue 
(n = 40, 7.1 %), nystagmus (n = 36, 6.4 %) and ataxia 
(n = 29, 5.2 %), or cognitive deficits, especially distur-
bance of speech (n = 37, 6.6 %), memory impairment 
(n = 36, 6.4 %) and mental slowing (n = 32, 5.7 %). In 24 
patients (4.3 %), the observed ADRs were considered as 
severe, rare, very distinctive or currently unknown and </p>

<p>Table 2 Patients without and 
with at least possibly related 
ADRs, stratified by the 
respective AEDs, including 
details of particular daily 
dosages </p>

<p>N 
Total 
a (%) RR </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>CI 
Daily dosage (mg) </p>

<p>Mean Median SD 
Min. Max. </p>

<p>LEV </p>

<p>Without ADR 
203 55.3 
[1.00] 
2596 3000 
1107 
250 6000 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 120 32.7 
2465 2500 
1096 
250 7000 </p>

<p>PGB </p>

<p>Without ADR 
26 42.6 
1.31 
0.89-1.93 
487 
600 
187 
75 
750 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
28 45.9 
321 
275 
194 
75 
750 </p>

<p>ZNS </p>

<p>Without ADR 
26 38.2 
1.40 
0.98-2.02 
256 
250 
164 
50 
600 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
32 47.1 
338 
300 
148 
100 
600 </p>

<p>OXC(ER) </p>

<p>Without ADR 
73 39.9 
1.57 
1.26-1.95 1715 1800 
677 
450 3850 
With possible ADR 
97 53.0 
1646 1800 
530 
450 3000 </p>

<p>LCM </p>

<p>Without ADR 
37 36.3 
1.63 
1.24-2.13 
326 
350 
144 
50 
600 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
55 53.9 
269 
250 
139 
50 
600 </p>

<p>TPM </p>

<p>Without ADR 
31 28.4 
1.97 
1.56-2.47 
223 
150 
203 
25 
800 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
65 59.6 
213 
200 
119 
50 
500 </p>

<p>ESL </p>

<p>Without ADR 
2 11.8 
2.30 
1.75-3.02 1800 1800 
849 1200 2400 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
14 82.4 
1514 1600 
501 
800 2400 </p>

<p>AED antiepileptic drug, ADR adverse drug reaction, CI confidence interval, ESL eslicarbazepine, LCM 
lacosamide, LEV levetiracetam, OXC(ER) oxcarbazepine extended-release formulation, PGB pregabalin, 
RR relative risk for the occurrence of possibly related ADRs compared with the occurrence of these under 
levetiracetam, SD standard deviation, TPM topiramate, ZNS zonisamide 
a For calculation, the total number of documented cases per AED was used; the missing percentage up to 
100 % fall upon ADRs assessed as unlikely, conditional or not causally linked to the particular AED 
b For calculation of RR, patients taking both of the specifically compared AEDs were excluded </p>

<p>Systematic ADR Monitoring in Epilepsy Therapy Using Routine Clinical Data </p>

<p>
therefore reported via the SRS to the responsible regulatory 
authority. Among these reports were one case of an 
arrhythmia absoluta under the combination of LCM and 
LEV as a potentially life-threatening ADR, three of suici-
dal ideation (two under LEV, one under the combination of 
OXC(ER)/LCM), three of myoklonia [two under 
OXC(ER), one under LEV], two of peripheral edema under 
OXC(ER), one of paresthesia under LEV, one of anorexia 
under TPM and one case of anxiety under LEV. 
For comparing the frequency of occurrence of particular 
ADRs in relation to the information mentioned in the 
SmPC, the incidence of the ADR was calculated for each </p>

<p>AED separately. The detailed results are shown in Table 4. 
Although, SmPC data express a very rough classification 
for ADR frequency by using categories differing by one 
power of ten only, e.g., C0.1 % for an uncommon 
and C10 % for a very common occurrence, for some reg-
istered ADRs probable underestimation was assumed. This, 
for example, was apparent in the case of cognitive 
impairment related to TPM and electrolyte imbalance 
concerning potassium under therapy with an carbonic 
anhydrase (CA) inhibitor (i.e., TPM, ZNS) or sodium level 
by application of dibenzazepine anticonvulsants (i.e., 
OXC, ESL). </p>

<p>Table 3 Patients under off-
label use concerning dose, 
without and with at least 
possibly related ADRs, stratified 
by the respective AEDs, 
including details of particular 
daily dosages </p>

<p>N 
Total 
a (%) RR 
CI 
Daily dosage (mg) </p>

<p>Mean Median SD 
Min. Max. </p>

<p>TPM </p>

<p>Off-label use 
7 
6.4 </p>

<p>Without ADR 
4 
3.7 
0.49 0.16-1.54 
638 
600 
111 
550 
800 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
2 
1.8 
650 
650 
71 
600 
700 </p>

<p>LCM </p>

<p>Off-label use 
18 17.6 </p>

<p>Without ADR 
8 
7.8 
0.84 0.50-1.40 
513 
500 
58 
450 
600 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
8 
7.8 
500 
500 
53 
450 
600 </p>

<p>LEV </p>

<p>Off-label use 
91 24.8 </p>

<p>Without ADR 
50 13.6 
0.95 0.68-1.33 3945 
4000 
408 3500 6000 
With possible ADR 27 
7.4 
4102 
4000 
701 3500 7000 </p>

<p>PGB </p>

<p>Off-label use 
6 
9.8 </p>

<p>Without ADR 
3 
4.9 
0.96 0.42-2.24 
725 
750 
43 
675 
750 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
3 
4.9 
708 
700 
38 
675 
750 </p>

<p>OXC(ER) </p>

<p>Off-label use 
20 10.9 </p>

<p>Without ADR 
8 
4.4 
1.02 0.68-1.52 2994 
3000 
401 2550 3850 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 11 
6.0 
2832 
2700 
316 2500 3600 </p>

<p>ESL </p>

<p>Off-label use 
11 64.7 </p>

<p>Without ADR 
1 
5.9 
1.03 0.78-1.36 2400 
2400 
2400 2400 </p>

<p>With possible ADR 
9 52.9 
1822 
1600 
353 1600 2400 </p>

<p>ZNS </p>

<p>Off-label use 
7 10.3 </p>

<p>Without ADR 
2 
2.9 
1.21 0.66-2.23 
600 
600 
0 
600 
600 
With possible ADR 
4 
5.9 
588 
600 
25 
550 
600 </p>

<p>AED antiepileptic drug, ADR adverse drug reaction, CI confidence interval, ESL eslicarbazepine, LCM 
lacosamide, LEV levetiracetam, OXC(ER) oxcarbazepine extended-release formulation, PGB pregabalin, 
RR relative risk for the occurrence of possibly related ADRs comparing off-label use concerning dose to the 
particular applications of the same drug used on-label, i.e., according to the recommended dosage by the 
Summary of Product Characteristics, SD standard deviation, TPM topiramate, ZNS zonisamide 
a For calculation, the total number of documented cases per AED was used </p>

<p> 
A. Hilgers, M. Schaefer </p>

<p>Table 4 Incidence rates of all ADRs, assessed as at least possibly related to the antiepileptic drug, compared with corresponding frequency data 
by the SmPC (nonexhaustive list; occurred ADRs mentioned only) </p>

<p>TPM 
LEV 
PGB 
ZNS 
OXC(ER) 
LCM 
ESL </p>

<p>Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC </p>

<p>Metabolism and nutrition disorders 
Weight gain 
N 
3 
7 
2 
% 
C1 
0.8 
C0.1 
11.3 
C1 
N/A 
1.1 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
Weight loss 
N 
9 
2 
3 
% 
8.2 
C10 
0.5 
C0.1 
C0.1 
4.5 
C1 
N/A 
N/A 
C0.1 
Decreased appetite/anorexia 
N 
5 
5 
3 
% 
4.5 
C1 
1.4 
C1 
N/A 
4.5 
C1 
N/A 
N/A 
C1 
Hypokalemia 
N 
11 
3 
9 
1 
3 
1 
% 
10.1 
C0.1 
0.8 
N/A 
C0.1 
13.2 
C0.1 
0.6 
N/A 
2.9 
N/A 
5.9 
N/A 
Hyponatremia 
N 
3 
1 
67 
3 
10 
% 
N/A 
0.8 
C0.01 
1.6 
N/A 
N/A 
37.0 
C1 
2.9 
N/A 
58.8 
C1 
Psychiatric disorders 
Sleep disturbance/insomnia 
N 
2 
1 
1 
1 
% 
C1 
0.5 
C1 
1.6 
C1 
1.5 
C1 
N/A 
C1 
5.9 
C1 
Nervousness/agitation 
N 
1 
5 
1 
1 
3 
4 
1 
% 
0.9 
C1 
1.4 
C1 
1.6 
C0.1 
1.5 
C10 
1.7 
C1 
3.9 
C0.1 
5.9 
C0.1 
Irritability 
N 
2 
1 0 
1 
% 
1.8 
C1 
2.7 
C1 
C1 
C10 
0.6 
N/A 
C1 
C0.1 
Aggressive reaction 
N 
2 
1 1 
1 
2 
2 
1 
% 
1.8 
C1 
3.0 
C1 
1.6 
C0.1 
3.0 
C0.1 
1.1 
N/A 
1.0 
C0.1 
N/A 
Anxiety 
N 
4 
1 
% 
C1 
1.1 
C1 
1.6 
N/A 
C1 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
Listlessness/apathy 
N 
2 
1 
1 
% 
C0.1 
0.5 
N/A 
1.6 
N/A 
N/A 
0.6 
C1 
N/A 
C0.1 
Mood swings/depressed mood 
N 
2 
8 
3 
1 
2 
% 
1.8 
C10 
2.2 
C1 
C0.1 
4.5 
C10 
0.6 
C1 
1.9 
C1 
C0.1 
Confusion 
N 
2 
1 
% 
C1 
0.5 
C0.1 
C1 
C10 
0.6 
C1 
C1 
C0.1 
Suicidal ideation 
N 
1 
4 
1 
1 
% 
0.9 
C0.1 
1.1 
C1 
N/A 
C0.1 
0.6 
N/A 
1.0 
C0.1 
N/A 
Nervous system disorders 
Fatigue/tiredness 
N 
5 
2 5 
5 
6 
1 2 
6 
2 
% 
4.5 
C10 
6.8 
C10 
8.1 
C10 
9.0 
C10 
6.6 
C10 
5.8 
C1 
11.8 
C10 
Dizziness 
N 
5 
2 3 
7 
5 
2 4 
2 5 
5 
% 
4.5 
C10 
6.3 
C1 
11.3 
C1 
7.5 
C10 
13.3 
C10 
24.3 
C10 
29.4 
C10 </p>

<p>Systematic ADR Monitoring in Epilepsy Therapy Using Routine Clinical Data </p>

<p>
Table 4 continued </p>

<p>TPM 
LEV 
PGB 
ZNS 
OXC(ER) 
LCM 
ESL </p>

<p>Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC </p>

<p>Nystagmus 
N 
4 
1 0 
5 
2 
1 3 
1 9 
4 
% 
3.6 
C1 
2.7 
N/A 
8.1 
C0.1 
3.0 
C1 
7.2 
C1 
18.4 
C1 
23.5 
C0.1 
Tremor 
N 
2 
1 7 
3 
2 
3 
8 
1 
% 
1.8 
C1 
4.6 
C1 
4.8 
C1 
3.0 
C1 
1.7 
C1 
7.8 
C1 
5.9 
C1 
Balance disorder/ataxia 
N 
3 
1 0 
2 
2 
1 2 
1 1 
2 
% 
2.7 
C1 
2.7 
C1 
3.2 
C1 
3.0 
C10 
6.6 
C1 
10.7 
C1 
11.8 
C1 
Disturbance in concentration/attention 
N 
16 
3 
2 
2 
1 
% 
14.7 
C1 
0.8 
C0.1 
C1 
3.0 
C1 
1.1 
C1 
1.0 
C1 
C1 
Memory impairment 
N 
25 
11 
2 
6 
3 
2 
% 
22.9 
C1 
3.0 
C0.1 
3.2 
C1 
9.0 
C10 
1.7 
C1 
1.9 
C1 
C0.1 
Disturbance of speech 
N 
31 
4 
3 
4 
2 
% 
28.4 
C1 
1.1 
N/A 
C0.1 
4.4 
C1 
2.2 
N/A 
1.9 
C1 
C0.1 
Mental slowing/bradyphrenia 
N 
17 
10 
1 
8 
4 
4 
% 
15.6 
C1 
2.7 
N/A 
1.6 
C0.1 
11.9 
C1 
2.2 
N/A 
3.9 
C1 
N/A 
Headache 
N 
1 
6 
1 
7 
4 
1 
% 
0.9 
N/A 
1.6 
C10 
1.6 
C10 
N/A 
3.9 
C10 
3.9 
C10 
5.9 
C1 
Dysgeusia 
N 
1 
1 
% 
C1 
0.3 
N/A 
1.6 
C0.1 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
Paresthesia 
N 
3 
2 
% 
2.7 
C10 
0.5 
N/A 
C1 
C1 
N/A 
C1 
C0.1 
Eye disorders 
Blurred vision/diplopia 
N 
6 
1 3 
5 
5 
2 3 
1 7 
4 
% 
5.5 
C1 
3.5 
C0.1 
8.1 
C1 
7.5 
C10 
12.6 
C10 
16.5 
C10 
23.5 
C1 
Ear and labyrinth disorders 
Tinnitus 
N 
1 
1 
% 
0.9 
C1 
0.3 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
C1 
C0.1 
Gastro-intestinal disorders 
Nausea/vomiting 
N 
3 
4 
1 
1 3 
1 5 
2 
% 
2.7 
C10 
1.1 
C1 
1.6 
C1 
C1 
7.2 
C10 
14.6 
C10 
11.8 
C1 
Diarrhea 
N 
1 
1 
1 
% 
0.9 
C10 
0.3 
C1 
C1 
C1 
C1 
1.0 
C1 
C1 
Obstipation 
N 
1 
1 
2 
4 
2 
% 
0.9 
C1 
N/A 
1.6 
C1 
3.0 
C1 
2.2 
C1 
1.9 
C1 
C0.1 
Flatulence 
N 
1 
4 
% 
C0.1 
N/A 
C1 
N/A 
0.6 
N/A 
3.9 
C1 
C0.1 </p>

<p> 
A. Hilgers, M. Schaefer </p>

<p>4 Discussion </p>

<p>4.1 AED Usage and ADR Incidence </p>

<p>Of the various AEDs of interest in this survey, OXC(ER) 
and LEV were most frequently used. To our knowledge, no 
study has so far investigated this selection of newer AEDs, 
but there are three different papers reporting on the nation-
wide prescription patterns of AEDs in Italy (data included 
until 2007), Norway (until 2009) and Germany (until 2010) 
[13, 29, 30]. Extracting the data related to the AEDs 
focused on in this survey also reveals the tendency towards 
LEV being the most frequently used, followed by 
OXC(ER), TPM, ZNS and PGB. LCM and ESL were the 
most recently approved AEDs, which is why no reliable 
data were available. 
With regard to every first documented observation per 
patient in this evaluation, almost 90 % were on polyther-
apy. Compared with the studies of Canevini et al. and 
Malerba et al. in which 22.5 and 21 %, respectively, of 
drug refractory patients were being managed on a single 
AED [30, 31], a proportion of 10.1 % is small. However, in 
our survey only patients recently admitted to in-house 
treatment were included, for whom, other than severe 
epilepsy, the need for a complex therapy management, </p>

<p>including administration of antiepileptic medication for 
acute use and the change in therapy by gradual cross-over 
of AEDs, can be assumed. By considering the calculated 
mean data for the length of stay, number of concomitant 
AEDs and AED load, defined as the sum of DDDs 
(Table 1), this assumption can be substantiated. 
It is still a matter of debate if antiepileptic polymedi-
cation compared with monotherapy is generally associated 
with more frequent ADRs. The correlation between AED 
toxicity and total drug load rather than the number of 
concomitant AEDs is also still under discussion [31-34]. In 
this survey, both factors were significantly associated with 
a more frequent occurrence of ADRs, whilst also both were 
strongly correlated with each other. However, in view of 
the numerical extent of association, the total number of 
AEDs seemed to be of greater impact. The reasons for this 
can be manifold, including the absence of a rigid dosing 
scheme, a gradual cross-over of AEDs, and the value of 
DDD as an imperfect measure of drug exposure itself [15, 
31, 35]. Testing for serum concentration-dependent toler-
ability was also considered for this survey, but ultimately 
rejected as therapeutic drug monitoring of the newer AEDs 
often was applied in selected cases only [36] and, therefore, 
corresponding serum concentrations were not available in 
every documented data set. </p>

<p>Table 4 continued </p>

<p>TPM 
LEV 
PGB 
ZNS 
OXC(ER) 
LCM 
ESL </p>

<p>Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC 
Obs. 
SmPC </p>

<p>Hepatobiliary disorders 
Increase in liver enzymes 
N 
6 
1 
2 
6 
2 
2 
% 
C0.1 
1.6 
C0.1 
1.6 
C0.1 
3.0 
C1 
3.3 
C0.1 
1.9 
C0.1 
11.8 
C0.1 
Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders 
Hypersensitivity/pruritus 
N 
2 
1 
1 
% 
C1 
0.5 
C0.01 
C0.1 
C1 
0.6 
C0.001 
1.0 
C1 
C0.1 
Alopecia 
N 
1 
2 
2 
1 
% 
0.9 
C1 
0.5 
C0.01 
N/A 
C1 
1.1 
C1 
1.0 
N/A 
C0.1 
Musculoskeletal disorders 
Myoclonia 
N 
1 
1 
2 
% 
C1 
0.3 
N/A 
C0.1 
1.5 
N/A 
1.1 
N/A 
C1 
N/A 
General disorders 
Peripheral edema 
N 
4 
2 
1 
% 
N/A 
N/A 
6.5 
C1 
C1 
1.1 
N/A 
N/A 
5.9 
C0.1 
Total 
N 
109 
367 
61 
68 
183 
102 
17 
% 
100 
100 
100 
100 
100 
100 
100 </p>

<p>ADR adverse drug reaction, ESL eslicarbazepine, LCM lacosamide, LEV levetiracetam, N/A not available, Obs. observed, OXC(ER) oxcarbazepine 
extended-release formulation, PGB pregabalin, SmPC Summary of Product Characteristics, TPM topiramate, ZNS zonisamide </p>

<p>Systematic ADR Monitoring in Epilepsy Therapy Using Routine Clinical Data </p>

<p>
The overall incidence of ADRs was calculated as 
56.6 %, based on 318 patients for whom adverse reactions 
were documented. With regard to the method of assessment 
and the investigated patient population, this result corre-
sponds well with that of other studies. Canevini et al., who 
also analyzed patients with drug-resistant epilepsy at ter-
tiary referral centers, identified ADRs in 36.5 % of 
patients, based on spontaneous reporting, compared with 
95.5 % when a validated screening questionnaire was used 
[31]; similar results were summarized in a review of Per-
ucca and Gilliam [37]. Considering that the detection of 
ADRs in clinical routine is derived from spontaneous 
reporting complemented by medical examination and lab 
diagnostics, and in view of the findings by Baker et al., 
which indicate a prevalence underestimation of ADRs 
when based on spontaneous reporting versus overestima-
tion when using checklists, the extent of prevalence in this 
survey can be considered plausible for a real-life hospital 
setting [38]. 
Concerning the overall tolerability, LEV emerged as best 
tolerated, which, similarly, was reported by Cramer et al. 
[28]. This may be a reason for it being first recommended 
and therefore frequently used, as also indicated by the high 
number of patients under LEV in this survey. The calculated 
RRs of ADR occurrence for each AED compared with LEV 
varied between 1.31 and 2.30. But these values should be 
treated with caution; for the evaluation, only the total 
number of possibly related ADRs was taken into account, 
and not the type nor the clinical relevance of the ADR, nor 
other tolerability influencing factors. The impact of associ-
ated ADRs can be very different, which is why by using this 
kind of RR calculation only the overall tolerability can be 
estimated and has to be reviewed in every single case [31, 
37]. Furthermore, all patients were preselected due to real-
life conditions, and the total number of patients treated with 
particular AEDs varied widely, which in itself may have had 
an impact on the estimated RR. 
An interesting finding of this survey was the rather high 
proportion of off-label use concerning maximum recom-
mended daily dosage (Table 3). So far, there are not many 
studies investigating off-label use by dose in drug resistant 
epilepsy. One study by Franco et al. focused on this 
question by means of a diagram, showing proportions of 
off-label use of between 0 and 25 % [39]. The values in our 
survey ranged from 6.4 % for TPM up to 64.7 % for ESL. 
By comparing the calculated RR for each AED used off-
label to its application as recommended by the SmPC, no 
considerable change of ADR occurrence was seen. How-
ever, the documented extent of off-label use showed an 
obvious relevance for clinical practice, indicating the need 
of further investigations on potential risks and benefits to 
alleviate physicians' and patients' uncertainty whilst using 
a drug out of its specification [39]. </p>

<p>As already mentioned, antiepileptic therapy often means 
a balancing act between optimizing therapeutic outcome 
and running the risk of ADRs [6-8, 14, 15, 31, 37, 40-42]. 
It is therefore important to be aware of the side effect 
profiles of every considered AED in order to choose the 
best therapy option for every patient. The comparison of 
incidences of ADRs with possible causality in relation to 
the information mentioned in the SmPC, which, to our 
knowledge, was first performed in this survey, is very 
valuable to provide a supplementary assessment of partic-
ular risk. Even though, SmPC data present a very rough 
estimate for ADR frequency by using categories differing 
by one power of ten only, e.g., C0.1 % for an uncommon 
and C10 % for a very common occurrence, for some of the 
documented ADRs, a probable underestimation was 
determined. For example, in the case of cognitive impair-
ment related to TPM or electrolyte imbalance under ther-
apy with a CA inhibitor (i.e., TPM, ZNS) or dibenzazepine 
anticonvulsants (i.e., OXC, ESL), the discrepancy was 
particularly apparent. 
It is a well known fact that the detection of specific 
ADRs can be influenced by physicians' expectations as to 
the likelihood of occurrence [8, 31]. Therefore, it cannot be 
excluded that applied targeted testing, such as close control 
of lab values, will cause a detection bias. 
TPM and ZNS are known as inhibitors of CA, which has 
a considerable share in regulating the acid-base balance 
and therefore influences the electrolyte status. In this sur-
vey, low potassium levels (\3.6 mEq/L) were assessed for 
11 and nine patients on TPM and ZNS (10.1 and 13.2 %), 
respectively, although the SmPC of both drugs mention this 
to be an uncommon occurrence (C0.1 and \1 %) [17, 20]. 
A similar result for TPM was found in a systematic review 
by Dell'Orto et al., indicating hypokalemia as concomitant 
with metabolic acidosis for 10 % of the cases [43]. To our 
knowledge, there are no comparable investigations refer-
ring to potassium levels under ZNS treatment, but a study 
by Mirza et al. indicated similar inhibitor potency to CA 
isoforms by TPM and ZNS, both inducing renal tubular 
acidosis [44]. Therefore, it seems plausible to detect an also 
increased frequency of hypokalemia under ZNS. Further 
investigations are definitely necessary to verify these 
results, but until then, the potential risk of CA inhibitors 
should be considered, particularly in patients with co-
morbidity or co-medication influencing electrolyte balance. 
The same applies to treatment regimes with OXC(ER) 
or ESL, for which a higher incidence of hyponatremia, 
compared with SmPC data, was documented [21, 23]. As 
possible reasons, the previously mentioned detection bias 
or other influencing factors, like vomiting, diuretic or 
psychotropic medication, heart or kidney insufficiency, 
etc., should be also taken into account. Furthermore, the 
varying reference values applied for the definition of </p>

<p> 
A. Hilgers, M. Schaefer </p>

<p>hyponatremia in different studies (here \135 mEq/L) and 
the highly selected patient population in this survey should 
be considered. Apart from this, there are many studies 
mentioning the frequency of decreased sodium serum 
levels in about 10-30 % of the patients under OXC treat-
ment, which in turn substantiates an assumed higher risk 
[45-50]. At the time of approval, ESL was promoted as 
bearing a lower hyponatremia risk compared with OXC. 
However, studies by Ley et al. and Gupta et al. could not 
substantiate this claim [51, 52]. In our survey, almost all 
patients with ESL stopped OXC(ER) because of decreased 
sodium levels prior. Therefore, the previous experience of 
hyponatremia could be an explanation for the high inci-
dence even under ESL. But interesting in this context, data 
concerning hyponatremia mentioned in the SmPC have, 
since approval, been adjusted to a common frequency (C1 
and \10 %), therefore, indicating the same risk as for 
OXC(ER), by now [23, 53]. 
With regard to cognitive impairment (e.g., psychomotor 
slowing, difficulty with concentration/attention, difficulty 
with memory, speech or language problems, particularly 
word-finding difficulties), this is a well described problem 
in patients on TPM [42, 54-59]. Being aware of that, 
neuropsychological testing and retesting (investigating 
cognitive processing, memory, language) are more often 
applied in conjunction with TPM therapy, as for example, 
recommended by Lee et al. [60]. This may have induced an 
overestimation of the particular risk in this survey, since 
cognitive impairment is also known to be influenced by 
seizure frequency and an increased number and dosage of 
AEDs [56]. However, a review by Mula, investigating the 
evidence of cognitive impairment under TPM, established 
that approximately 10 % of the patients experienced cog-
nitive problems [58]. Of these, as also confirmed in our 
survey, speech problems mainly concerning verbal fluency 
were the most prominent [58, 61], a fact, which should be 
considered in individual treatment plans, especially for 
patients actively working or studying. 
In conclusion, the results of this survey show that a sys-
tematic evaluation of inpatient data allows for even more 
information to be gained than could be extracted from clin-
ical trials or SRS. Therefore, this kind of surveillance can 
provide a decisive contribution to future adjustments of risk 
data, applied to align approval data with real-life experience, 
which is an ongoing process, as the comparison of SmPC 
data from 2011 and 2015 reflects [17-23, 53, 62-67]. </p>

<p>4.2 Methodological Considerations </p>

<p>Within this project, data were collected weekly by a phar-
macist as part of the Consultants' ward rounds. It cannot be 
excluded that short-stay patients were missed, which could 
have biased the selection of patients towards more complex </p>

<p>therapies. For this reason and to avoid time-consuming re-
documentation of paper notes, the implementation of elec-
tronic patient records is to be recommended. For ADR 
documentation, no standardized questionnaire was used in 
this survey, which may have underrated some ADR inci-
dences. However, by using this method, the ADR assessment 
remained as close to clinical routine as possible, and is 
therefore assumed to reflect the problems and concerns of 
practical relevance. A challenge, which is inherent in the 
system, is the real-life data assessment itself. Influencing 
factors, such as dose adjustment, change of therapy regime, 
co-morbidity or concomitant drug use, etc., do not follow a 
precise study plan under these conditions. Thus, the causality 
assessment and calculation of RRs concerning ADR are only 
methodical approaches to deal with these data, and the cor-
responding results should be judged in context and treated 
with caution. Due to this, not every pointed question of sci-
entific interest can be proven or rejected. Moreover, neither 
the applied method nor all of the results can be translated to 
patients treated at primary care level or those being well 
controlled concerning seizure frequency and tolerability. But 
by this approach, treatment issues relevant to all patients can 
be identified and used as guidance for further investigation. 
The major advantage of this method lies in the 
prospectively orientated full assessment of patients. It 
provides reliable application data, and the rather long-term 
observation period, the accumulation of medical informa-
tion and the opportunity of monitoring progress, encourage 
the evaluation of causal relations between ADRs and sus-
pected drugs. </p>

<p>5 Conclusion </p>

<p>For patients depending on lifelong treatment, optimized 
therapies adapted to individual needs are of great impor-
tance. For this purpose, established expertise in the 
advantages and disadvantages of each drug is indispens-
able. It has been shown that during inpatient treatment, 
valuable data are generated. A systematic assessment and 
continuous evaluation of these data can constitute a chance 
for perpetual risk and treatment evaluation under real-life 
conditions and therefore support individualized therapy 
management. Accordingly, even if this approach may need 
more methodological reasoning, it would certainly provide 
a new quality of drug surveillance. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments We would like to express our gratitude to Prof. 
T.W. May, Gesellschaft für Epilepsieforschung Bielefeld, for his 
encouragement and professional support with statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Author contributions Annika Hilgers was involved in the con-
ception of this study, collected all relevant data prospectively, 
developed the internal database, ran the analyses, and drafted the </p>

<p>Systematic ADR Monitoring in Epilepsy Therapy Using Routine Clinical Data </p>

<p>
manuscript. Marion Schaefer was involved in the conception of this 
study and reviewed and provided critical revisions to the manuscript. </p>

<p>Compliance with Ethical Standards </p>

<p>Ethical approvals For this type of study, ethical approval was not 
required. Data were collected as part of clinical routine and the use of 
patients' medical records was in accordance with the Gesundheits-
datenschutzgesetz (GDSG NRW, German law of healthcare data 
protection). The study was performed in accordance with the ethical 
standards of the Declaration of Helsinki. </p>

<p>Informed consent For this study, no informed consent was collected 
from the patients as all information was extracted from routine 
medical records and used anonymously. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest Annika Hilgers and Marion Schaefer have no 
conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Funding Annika Hilgers has received third-party funds within a 
Ph.D. project from the Bundesinstitut für Arzneimittel und Mediz-
inprodukte (BfArM), the German drug regulatory authority, between 
2008 and 2010, which enabled performance of the data collection 
prospectively. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which per-
mits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original 
author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons 
license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p> 
A. Hilgers, M. Schaefer </p>



<p>Systematic ADR Monitoring in Epilepsy Therapy Using Routine Clinical Data </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>