<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4764960" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: This study assessed the relationship between 
working memory capacity and auditory stream segregation by 
using the concurrent minimum audible angle in children with a 
diagnosed auditory processing disorder (APD). 
Methods: The participants in this cross-sectional, comparative 
study were 20 typically developing children and 15 children with 
a diagnosed APD (age, 9-11 years) according to the subtests 
of multiple-processing auditory assessment. Auditory stream 
segregation was investigated using the concurrent minimum 
audible angle. Working memory capacity was evaluated using the 
non-word repetition and forward and backward digit span tasks. 
Nonparametric statistics were utilized to compare the between-
group differences. The P earson correlation was employed to 
measure the degree of association between working memory 
capacity and the localization tests between the 2 groups. 
Results: The group with APD had significantly lower scores 
than did the typically developing subjects in auditory stream 
segregation and working memory capacity. There were significant 
negative correlations between working memory capacity and the 
concurrent minimum audible angle in the most frontal reference 
location (0° azimuth) and lower negative correlations in the most 
lateral reference location (60° azimuth) in the children with APD. 
Conclusion: The study revealed a relationship between working 
memory capacity and auditory stream segregation in children 
with APD. The research suggests that lower working memory 
capacity in children with APD may be the possible cause of the 
inability to segregate and group incoming information. </p>

<p>Please cite this article as: Lotfi Y, Mehrkian S, Moossavi A, Faghih Zadeh S, 
Sadjedi H. Relation between Working Memory Capacity and Auditory Stream 
Segregation in Children with Auditory Processing Disorder. Iran J Med Sci. 
2016;41(2):110-117. </p>

<p>Keywords • Auditory scene analysis • Stream segregation 
• Short-term memory • Auditory perceptual disorders • Child </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Auditory processing disorder (APD) is defined as difficulties in 
the processing of auditory information in the central nervous 
system 
1 and is characterized by the poor localization, separation, 
grouping, discrimination, or ordering of sounds. 
1,2 Children with 
APD have poor speech perception, especially in challenging 
environments. According to Jerger, 
3 one possible reason for poor 
performance in multisource environments is a deficit in auditory 
figure-ground discrimination, the ability to pick out important </p>

<p>What's Known </p>

<p>• 
Children with APD struggle to 
understand speech signals in the 
presence of noise. One possible reason 
for poor speech perception is a defi cit 
in auditory stream segregation. The 
spatial features of competing sounds 
affect the segregation of target sounds. 
• 
Stream segregation and extracting 
speech from competing noise is 
modulated cognitively by top-down 
mechanisms such as working memory. </p>

<p>What's New </p>

<p>• 
One possible reason for poor 
speech perception in children with 
APD is that they cannot benefi t from 
spatial cues to segregate talkers from 
competing sounds. 
• 
The present study showed the 
possible infl uence of working memory 
capacity on spatial cues and auditory 
stream segregation in children with 
APD. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Relation between working memory and auditory stream segregation </p>

<p>Iran J Med Sci March 2016; Vol 41 No 2 
111 </p>

<p>sounds from a noisy background. Figure-ground 
discrimination can be related to the perceptual 
concept of auditory stream segregation. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Sounds arriving at the ears usually come 
from different directions in space. Since all the 
surrounding sound signals arrive at the cochlea 
as a composite, a preliminary analysis of the 
incoming sound is required to divide the auditory 
input into distinct perceptual objects. 
5 The ability 
of a listener to segregate a single target from a 
group of distracting signals is due to a process 
of perceptual organization known as stream 
segregation. The process by which sound 
properties are segregated from the acoustic 
background (auditory segregation) and then 
integrate together as discrete perceptual entities 
(auditory object representation) is known as 
auditory scene analysis (ASA). 
5 Segregation and 
integration are 2 fundamental aspects of ASA. 
The ability to combine information from different 
sensory sources into unified concepts over time 
(integration processes) is a crucial part of ASA in 
that it allows the listener to understand speech. 
Working memory capacity plays a critical role 
in this process, especially because auditory 
processing relies on the temporal domain. 
In general, the interplay between bottom-up 
and top-down mechanisms mediates ASA. 
6,7 The 
separation between simultaneous sound events 
is based on numerous acoustic properties such as 
spectral, temporal, and spatial cues (bottom-up 
mechanisms). 
8 Also, stream segregation is a 
dynamic process that is modulated cognitively 
by top-down mechanisms, which involve the 
organization of acoustic components into 
perceptual object representations based on prior 
experiences 
9 or executive processes (especially 
working memory capacity and attention). 
Working memory capacity is defined as the ability 
to retain and manipulate information. Because 
speech perception requires the individual to 
follow, retain, and integrate a stream of auditory 
information, working memory capacity is likely to 
be a core component of speech perception. 
The effect of the spatial features of competing 
sound sources on the segregation of target 
sounds has been known for several decades. 
The intelligibility of speech in the presence of 
background noise is higher when the speech 
and noise come from different sources. Different 
natural sound sources usually come from 
different directions in space, and localization 
cues are extensively used for the segregation of 
different talkers. 
10 The ability to locate the spatial 
origin of a sound source requires the capacity 
of the central auditory nervous system to detect 
and compute a number of acoustic cues such as 
small differences in the arrival time and intensity </p>

<p>of signals reaching the 2 ears. The interaural 
time differences of the low-frequency (&lt;1.5 kHz) 
components of the sound provide a powerful 
cue for tracking speech signals on the horizontal 
plane (or azimuth). </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Previous studies have determined that 
extracting speech from competing noise requires 
working memory resources. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Their results 
suggest that competing auditory streams are 
less distracting to individuals with high working 
memory abilities; therefore, listeners with higher 
working memory capacity may be more adept 
at separating target signals from a complex 
situation. 
Despite the rich history of research into 
directional hearing, only a few studies have 
attempted to measure the spatial resolution of 
the auditory system for simultaneous stimuli, 
particularly in children. In the present study, 
we used a measure of directional hearing 
known as the concurrent minimum audible 
angle, which is an excellent tool for measuring 
auditory segregation mediated by the binaural 
system. The concurrent minimum audible 
angle is defined as a threshold separation 
angle required to distinguish 2 stimuli that are 
presented simultaneously. 
13 Perrott 
14 measured 
the concurrent minimum audible angle in adults 
and found that the threshold separation angle 
significantly increased with laterality. In addition, 
the concurrent minimum audible angle increased 
from 4° to 10° at the front (0° azimuth) to 30° to 45° 
at a lateral displacement of 67°. Currently, little 
information is available on auditory streaming in 
children. The poor performance of children with 
APD in multisource environments may stem 
from their inability to benefit from spatial cues 
so as to judge the location of a sound source 
and segregate talkers from competing sounds. 
However, this issue has not been thoroughly 
investigated. Moreover, there is a pauc ity of 
data on the effects of cognitive processing 
such as working memory capacity on auditory 
segregation in children with APD. Therefore, 
we sought to investigate specifically (a) working 
memory capacity and auditory segregation using 
pairs of concurrent auditory stimuli and (b) the 
possible influence of working memory capacity 
on auditory segregation in children with APD 
and subsequently compare them with those in 
healthy controls. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods </p>

<p>Participants 
The data on 15 right-handed children with 
APD (12 males and 3 females; mean age, 
9.1 years; SD, 0.35) and 20 healthy control </p>

<p>Lotfi Y, Mehrkian S, Moossavi A, Faghih Zadeh S, Sadjedi H </p>

<p> 
Iran J Med Sci March 2016; Vol 41 No 2 </p>

<p>children (13 males and 7 females; mean age, 
9.4 years; SD, 0.5) were included in this study. 
Children with APD were recruited from the 
audiology clinics of the University of Social 
Welfare and Rehabilitation. The subjects had 
a clinical diagnosis of APD according to the 
multiple-process ing 
auditory 
assessment 
subtests. (For reviews, see Ronald L., 2007.) </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Clinical diagnoses were established by 
experienced clinicians on the basis of a careful 
developmental history taking and a battery of 
tests, comprising the dichotic digit test, 
16 pitch 
pattern sequence test, and monaural selective 
auditory attention test. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>The dichotic digit test is composed of naturally 
spoken digits from 1 to 10 (except for the number 
4 in Farsi). The original formulation requires that 2 
number pairs be presented simultaneously to each 
ear of the listener, with the subject being required to 
repeat all 4 numbers. Forty patterns are presented 
in total. The outcome measure is the percentage of 
the correct responses for each ear. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>The pitch pattern sequence test reflects 
the temporal component of auditory pattern 
recognition. The test presents 3 tones of 
500 msec duration each and an interval of 
10 seconds. Two of the tones are the same 
and one varies, and the subject is required to 
declare the pattern to the tester (verbally, by 
humming or by pointing to a visual analogue). 
A total of 30 patterns are presented monaurally 
to each ear following a brief practice session. 
The outcome measure is the percentage of the 
correct responses. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>The monaural selective auditory attention test 
compares the ability of the patient to recognize 
monosyllabic words embedded in a background 
of competing high-interest speech. Both the 
target and the competition stimuli are recorded 
by the same speaker, thereby eliminating 
speaker recognition cues. This version utilizes 
only monaural stimulation, as a monaural low-
redundancy test. The outcome measure is the 
percentage of the correct responses for each 
ear. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>In order to assess relative homogeneity in 
children with APD, we included only children 
who displayed auditory deficits evidenced by 
poor performance on all 3 auditory tests in the 
study. 
All the participants had normal hearing 
(better than 15 dB HL at octave frequencies 
between 250 and 8000 in the audiometry 
test) 
18 and normal IQs (≥85 on the Wechsler 
Revised Intelligence Scale for children). 
19 The 
subjects underwent a comprehensive general 
audiological assessment in order to provide 
background data. The results of otoscopy, </p>

<p>tympanometry, and speech discrimination score 
were normal. None of the participants had 
a history of a neurological disease or injury. 
Subjects with a history of hearing impairment, 
ear diseases, and neurological difficulties were 
excluded from our study. All the subjects gave 
consent prior to participation in this research. 
This study was approved (#1429) by the local 
ethics committee of the University of Social 
Welfare and Rehabilitation. </p>

<p>Procedures 
Children who fulfilled the selection criteria 
were subjected to working memory capacity 
assessment and auditory stream segregation 
task. All the tests were performed under 
controlled test conditions in a sound-treated 
room with an ambient noise level &lt;30 dBA. 
Each child was evaluated individually in a single 
1-hour session. 
Working memory capacity is commonly 
assessed by determining the number of items 
(i.e., letters, words, or sentences) that a person 
can keep in mind simultaneously for a short 
period of time. Both the phonological loop and 
the central executive (components of working 
memory capacity) 
20 were assessed in this 
study. Two of the most reliable measures of the 
phonological loop and verbal working memory 
capacity that are widely used in studies are 
forward digit span and non-word repetition 
tasks. The central executive is assessed using 
backward digit span. 
21 Forward digit span 
assesses both attention and short-term memory 
capacity, whereas backward digit span measures 
working memory capacity. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Forward and backward digit spans were 
obtained using the digit span subtests of the 
Wechsler Intelligence Scale for children. 
23 In 
each case, digit span was measured for the 
forward and backward (reverse-order) recall of 
the digit sequences. The number of the digits was 
increased from 3 to 9 for forward digit span and 
from 2 to 8 for backward digit span, and 2 trials 
using different digit sets were presented at each 
increasing list length. Testing was ceased when 
the subject failed to accurately report either trial at 
1 sequence length or when the maximal list length 
was reached (9 digits forward and 8 backward). 
The validated Farsi non-word repetition 
task 
24 was used in this study. The test consisted 
of 40 non-words, which ranged in length from 
1 to 4 syllables. The subjects were instructed to 
repeat the non-word that they had just heard. 
Performance in this task was analyzed by counting 
the error percent for each non-word length. 
In this study, auditory stream segregation 
was assessed using a method described by </p>

<p>Relation between working memory and auditory stream segregation </p>

<p>Iran J Med Sci March 2016; Vol 41 No 2 </p>

<p>
Best 
13 (2004).In this method, a 2-trial forced-
choice procedure was employed. The subjects 
were presented with 2 simultaneous tones of 
different frequencies (i.e., 500 Hz and 800 Hz) 
and were asked to judge the relative location of 
the pair by indicating whether the higher tone was 
to the left or right of the lower tone, on the right 
hand side of the subjects (Figure 1). The subjects' 
head was positioned in the center. The subjects 
were instructed to keep their heads in this position 
for the duration of the recording process (about 
15 min). Testing took place using 3 reference 
locations on a horizontal plane: 0°, 30°, and 60°. 
For each reference location, 10 test locations were 
chosen on the basis of preliminary testing. In each 
trial, a pair of concurrent stimuli was presented. 
One stimulus corresponded to 1 of the reference 
locations, and the second stimulus was presented 
from 1 of the 10 test locations displaced in either 
azimuth. Prior to data acquisition, the subjects 
completed training blocks to ensure that they 
were able to detect the targets. Using a criterion 
of 75% correct in each test location, we measured 
the concurrent minimum audible angle. Stimuli 
were generated using <rs id="software-0" type="software">MATLAB</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">The MathWorks</rs>, 
Natick, MA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Sound Forge</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v.10</rs> by 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Sonic Foundry</rs>) with a sampling rate of 44.1 kHz. 
The stimuli were presented through headphones 
(TDH 39) via an audiometer, at 50 dB SL. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
All the analyses were conducted using 
Statistical Package for the Social Sciences 
(<rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs>), <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 16</rs>. Due to the relatively 
small group numbers in the study, the data did 
not meet normality assumptions in general. 
Therefore, nonparametric statistics (Mann-
Whitney U) were used to compare the between-
group differences. The Pearson correlation was 
employed to measure the degree of association 
between working memory capacity and the 
localization tests. The significance level adopted 
was 0.05 (5%), with confidence intervals of 95%. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Auditory Processing Tests 
The mean scores and SDs for the pitch 
pattern sequence test, dichotic digit test, and 
monaural selective auditory attention test for the 
children with APD and the typically developing 
children are shown in Figure 2. </p>

<p>Working Memory Capacity Tests 
The mean scores and SDs for the non-word 
repetition a nd forward and backward digit span 
tasks for the children with APD and the typically 
developing children are depicted in Figure 3. In </p>

<p>the non-word repetition task, the control group 
had near-ceiling scores, whereas the group </p>

<p>Figure 1: Schematic diagram of the reference positions around 
the head on the horizontal plane for the measurement of the 
concurrent minimum audible angle. The black dots illustrate 
the 3 reference locations examined: 0°, 30°, and 60° azimuth, 
all on the 0 ° elevation plane at the level of the ears. </p>

<p>Figure 2: Bar charts comparing the performance of the group 
with audio processing disorder (APD) with that of the control 
group on the 3 auditory processing tasks for each ear. </p>

<p>Figure 3: Means and SDs of the non-word repetition and 
forward and backward digit span tasks for the group with 
audio processing disorder (APD) and the control group. </p>

<p>Lotfi Y, Mehrkian S, Moossavi A, Faghih Zadeh S, Sadjedi H </p>

<p> 
Iran J Med Sci March 2016; Vol 41 No 2 </p>

<p>with APD had markedly lower scores. Both the 
forward and backward digit span scores were 
higher in the typically developing children than 
in the group with APD. The forward digit span 
scores were higher than were the backward digit 
span scores in both groups. Between-group 
comparisons revealed that the group with APD 
had a significantly lower score than did the 
control group in all the working memory capacity 
tests (P&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>Auditory System Segregation 
Table 1 shows the descriptive and inferential 
statistics of the concurrent minimum audible 
angle for the children with APD and the typically 
developing children. The concurrent minimum 
audible angle increased as a function of the 
laterality of the sources in both groups. Between-
group comparisons revealed that the group with 
APD had a significantly greater change for the 
separation of the concurrent stimuli than did the 
typically developing children on the 0° and 30° 
reference locations (P&lt;0.05). At the most lateral 
reference location in this study (i.e., 60° azimuth), 
there was no significant difference between the 2 
groups (P=0.538). </p>

<p>Correlations between Working Memory 
Capacity and the Concurrent Minimum Audible 
Angle 
Table 2 presents the correlations between 
the working memory capacity tasks (i.e., non-
word repetition task and forward and backward 
digit span tasks) and the concurrent minimum 
audible angle in the group with APD. The results 
in the children with APD showed higher negative 
correlations of the working memory capacity 
variables with the concurrent minimum audible 
angle results in the most frontal reference location 
(0° azimuth) and lower negative correlations in 
the most lateral reference location (60° azimuth). 
The results showed that the forward digit 
span task had significant correlations with the 
concurrent minimum audible angle in the 0° and 
30° reference positions (P=0.03 and P=0.05, 
respectively). The non-word repetition task had 
a significant correlation only with the concurrent 
minimum audible angle in the 0° reference 
position (P=0.04). There were no correlations 
between the working memory capacity tasks 
and the concurrent minimum audible angle in 
the 60° reference position (P&gt;0.05). 
Table 3 demonstrates the correlations 
between the working memory capacity tasks 
and the concurrent minimum audible angle in the 
control group. As can be seen, the correlations 
were different between the typically developing 
children and those with APD. The results for </p>

<p>the typically developing children showed that 
there were no significant correlations between 
the working memory capacity tasks and the 
concurrent minimum audible angle in all the 
reference positions (P&gt;0.05). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The findings of the current study revealed that 
the children with APD were significantly poorer 
than were the control group in both working 
memory capacity measures and auditory 
stream segregation according to the concurrent 
minimum audible angle. 
Working memory capacity deficits in children 
with APD have been reported in some studies. 
Maerlender et al. 
25 showed poor performance 
in forward and backward digit span tasks in 
children diagnosed with APD. In a different study, 
Iliadou and Bamiou 
26 found that the working 
memory capacity of their children with APD, as </p>

<p>Table 3: Correlations between the working memory 
capacity tasks and the concurrent minimum audible angle 
in the typically developing children </p>

<p>Typically 
developing 
group 
n, 20 </p>

<p>Concurrent minimum audible angle </p>

<p>0 ° (P value) 30 ° (P value) 60 ° (P value) </p>

<p>Non-word 
P value </p>

<p>−0.15 (0.53) −0.02 (0.90) −0.002 (0.99) </p>

<p>Forward digit 
P value </p>

<p>−0.34 (0.14) −0.11 (0.63) −0.13 (0.54) </p>

<p>Backward digit 
P value </p>

<p>−0.28 (0.23) −0.05 (0.81) −0.13 (0.58) </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Table 1: Means and SDs of the CMAA for the children 
with APD and the typically developing children </p>

<p>Variable 
Mean±SD 
P value </p>

<p>Children 
with APD 
n, 15 </p>

<p>Typically 
developing 
children 
n, 20 </p>

<p>CMAA 0°17.53±5.38 
13.35±2.84 
0.014 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CMAA 30°35.50±5.14 
20.75±3.8 
&lt;0.000 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CMAA 60°49.13±5.08 
45.87±4.39 
0.538 </p>

<p>a P&lt;0.05; CMAA: Concurrent minimum audible angle; 
APD: Audio processing disorder </p>

<p>Table 2: Correlations between the working memory 
capacity tasks and the concurrent minimum audible angle 
in the children with APD </p>

<p>Group with 
APD 
n, 15 </p>

<p>Concurrent minimum audible angle </p>

<p>0° (P value) 30° (P value) 60° (P value) </p>

<p>Non-word 
−0.57 (0.04) 
a −0.38 (0.16) −0.19 (0.50) </p>

<p>Forward digit −0.56 (0.03) 
a −0.51 (0.05) 
a −0.17 (0.57) </p>

<p>Backward digit −0.42 (0.12) −0.16 (0.56) −0.08 (0.77) </p>

<p>a P&lt;0.05; APD: Audio processing disorder </p>

<p>Relation between working memory and auditory stream segregation </p>

<p>Iran J Med Sci March 2016; Vol 41 No 2 </p>

<p>
measured by non-word repetition and forward 
and backward digit span tasks, was significantly 
poorer than that of their control group. These 
findings support our results indicating poor 
working memory capacity in children with APD 
by comparison with typically developing children. 
This finding is line with the hypothesis that APD 
cannot be defined as an exclusively modality-
specific perceptual dysfunction because the 
brain is non-modular and the auditory sensory 
processing in the central nervous system 
modulated by top-down mechanism influences 
working memory capacity. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Previous studies have shown that that 
performance in spatial discrimination tasks 
becomes poorer in the horizontal dimension 
as the azimuth increases. 
13,27 The results of 
the present study indicated that at a more 
lateral reference point (i.e., 60°), the angle 
of separation increased in both the typically 
developing children and the children with APD. 
These data are consistent with those reported 
by some previous studies which have shown 
that the concurrent minimum audible angle of 
tones increases in the lateral position. 
14 The 
findings of our study showed that the value of 
the concurrent minimum audible angle increased 
as the reference location was moved laterally 
(60° azimuth) in both groups; nonetheless, the 
children with APD required a greater change for 
the separation of concurrent stimuli than did the 
typically developing children in all the reference 
locations, especially in the 0° and 30° reference 
points. 
The results of the current study revealed 
significant differences between the 2 groups in 
the 0° and 30° reference positions, but there 
was no significant difference in the 60° azimuth 
reference point. This may be due to the fact that 
the concurrent minimum audible angle is most 
acute for sounds presented directly in front of 
the subject and least sensitive when the stimuli 
are presented from the lateral side. 
Currently, there is no information on the 
effects of cognitive processing such as working 
memory capacity on auditory segregation 
using the concurrent minimum audible angle in 
children with APD. We found significant negative 
correlations between working memory capacity 
and the concurrent minimum audible angle in the 
most frontal reference location (0° azimuth) and 
lower negative correlations in the most lateral 
reference location (60° azimuth) in our children 
with APD. This finding suggests that interventions 
designed to enhance the individual's cognitive 
strategies such as working memory capacity 
may confer better performance in the concurrent 
minimum audible angle in the frontal reference </p>

<p>locations. There were no significant correlations 
between the concurrent minimum audible angle 
and working memory capacity in the control 
group. The difference between the 2 groups may 
be explained by the notion that in children with 
lower working memory capacity, the top-down 
system must work harder and rely more on the 
bottom-up system to make sense of the acoustic 
information. This finding underscores the 
importance of a specific top-down rehabilitation 
program based on working memory capacity 
enhancement in children with APD. 
Conway et al. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>demonstrated that the 
subjects with high working memory capacity did 
better on the auditory processing task (dichotic 
listening) than did those with low working 
memory capacity in their study. The findings of 
the present study are in line with studies which 
have suggested that working memory capacity 
underlies the auditory processing performance. 
Previous investigations have demonstrated 
that accurate segregation can be impaired in 
a noisy environment because the non-target 
signals place a cognitive load on working 
memory capacity. 
29 Since working memory is a 
capacity-limited system and capacity comprises 
processing and storage components, any 
excessive load for processing due to difficult 
auditory task and noisy environment will 
decrease the share of storage component. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>The current study showed that potentially lower 
working memory capacity in the children with 
APD could be the reason for their inability to 
segregate and group information binaurally 
and presumably for their listening difficulties 
in multisource environments. The findings of 
the present study support the hypothesis that 
competing auditory streams are more distracting 
to individuals with low working memory abilities. 
There are some limitations in the current 
study. This study had a relatively small sample 
size, which suggests the need for further studies 
with larger samples. We could not match the 
intelligence factor between the 2 groups due 
to the small sample size, although there was 
no significant difference between the 2 groups 
(IQ range, 92 to 105). It should be noted that 
because APD can range in varying degrees 
of significance and may coexist with other 
disabilities, it may be difficult to diagnose "pure" 
APD correctly. Accordingly, the term "suspected 
APD" may be more appropriate for some cases 
of this research. Future studies using working 
memory capacity paradigms with incremental 
difficulty loads (e.g., white noise and speech 
noise) may enhance our understanding of the 
relationship between working memory capacity 
and auditory stream segregation. </p>

<p>Lotfi Y, Mehrkian S, Moossavi A, Faghih Zadeh S, Sadjedi H </p>

<p> 
Iran J Med Sci March 2016; Vol 41 No 2 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Working memory capacity was lower in the 
children with APD than in the age-matched, 
normal-hearing children in the present study. 
Moreover, the group with APD had poorer 
performance in the concurrent minimum audible 
angle skills for all 3 reference positions (i.e. 0°, 
30°, and 60°), especially in the more lateral 
position. The results of this study revealed 
significant negative correlations between 
working memory abilities and auditory stream 
segregation skills. Poor working memory 
capacity in children with APD may be the possible 
cause of poor performance in the segregating 
and grouping of incoming information and in turn 
poor speech perception in complex and noisy 
environments. Our findings suggest that higher-
order dysfunction or inadequate top-down factors 
such as working memory capacity in children with 
APD may have a negative effect on their ability 
to perform auditory stream segregation, not least 
in challenging environments. Since cognitive 
systems interact with auditory processing and 
speech comprehension, clinicians should employ 
multiple measures (bottom-up and top-down) for 
children with APD so that management may be 
beneficial for them. The findings of this study offer 
support for further research into the potential 
benefits of auditory working memory training to 
improve auditory stream segregation abilities in 
persons with APD. Individuals with APD require 
comprehensive assessment and an intervention 
program specifically for each individual's needs. 
Furthermore, clinicians should manage these 
children' specific behaviors and work on their 
weaknesses. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the 
participation of all research subjects in this study. 
This study was supported by the University of 
Social Welfare and Rehabilitation Sciences. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: None declared. </p>



</text></tei>