<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4492334" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Backgrounds/Aims: Recent studies have shown that pancreaticoduodenectomy (PD) can be performed quite safely. 
Critical pathway (CP) has been one of the key tools used to achieve excellent outcomes in high-quality, high-volume 
centers. This study was designed to evaluate the impact of CP implementation for PD patients. Methods: The important 
components of CP for PD patients include the early start of an oral diet and removal of the abdomen drain following 
follow-up computed tomography, with the intention of shortening the postoperative hospital stay. The study group (CP 
group) comprised of 88 patients who underwent pylorus-preserving or classical PD from January 2009 to December 
2010. The control group (pre-CP group) was 185 patients who underwent PD between January 2005 and December 
2008. Results: The two groups did not show significant differences in demographic profiles and the primary diagnosis. 
The incidences of overall postoperative complications such as delayed gastric emptying, fistula, and hemorrhage were 
similar or decreased in the CP group (54% vs. 40.9%). The incidence of clinically significant complications also showed 
a similar rate (5.4% vs. 4.5%) between the two groups. The nutritional status at discharge and re-admission rates 
were not different. The CP group showed a significantly shorter postoperative hospital stay (20.2±9.2 days vs. 14.9±5.1 
days, p＜0.001) and the total medical costs were also significantly reduced, by 15% (p＜0.001). Conclusions: The 
results of this study indicated that the implementation of CP for PD patients can decrease the length of hospital stay 
and reduce medial costs, with maintenance or improvement of patient outcomes. Further investigation is necessary 
to validate the actual impact of CP for PD through multi-center high-volume studies. (Korean J Hepatobiliary Pancreat 
Surg 2014;18:14-20) </p>

<p>Classical pancreaticoduodenectomy (PD) and pylorus-</p>

<p>preserving PD (PPPD) are complex procedures for peri-</p>

<p>ampullary disease. Because of the complexity as well as </p>

<p>the leak-prone nature of pancreatic anastomoses, this pro-</p>

<p>cedure was associated with significantly high incidences </p>

<p>of morbidity and mortality. Recent improvements in pan-</p>

<p>creatic surgery have led to a decrease in the mortality </p>

<p>rates, with the rates moving toward less than 5% in </p>

<p>high-volume centers, 1-3 and operative morbidity approach-</p>

<p>ing 30% to 40%, 
4-6 including the operative morbidities of </p>

<p>intra-abdominal abscess, sepsis, pancreatic fistula, and de-</p>

<p>layed gastric emptying. Recent studies have shown that </p>

<p>PPPD can be performed quite safely, especially in high </p>

<p>volume centers. 5,7 </p>

<p>Critical pathways (CP) are structured multidisciplinary </p>

<p>care plans that detail the essential steps in the care of pa-</p>

<p>tients with a specific clinical problem and describe the ex-</p>

<p>pected patient progress. 8 CP describes the tasks to be car-</p>

<p>ried out in time sequences and the discipline involved in </p>

<p>completing the tasks. CP may involve surgeons, nurses, </p>

<p>other health care professionals, patients, and families. </p>

<p>The implementation of CP was performed in many cat-</p>

<p>egories of diseases, resulting in improved efficacy, and re-</p>

<p>duction in the length of the hospital stay as well as </p>

<p>costs. 9-14 These CPs have been one of the key tools used </p>

<p>to achieve excellent outcomes in high-quality, high-vol-</p>

<p>ume centers. Initially, CP was used in relatively simple </p>

<p>procedures, but recently, CP has begun to be employed </p>

<p>Hyoung-Eun Kim, et al. Critical pathway for pancreaticoduodenectomy 15 </p>

<p>Table 1. Critical pathway for pancreaticoduodenectomy </p>

<p>Procedures 
Diet 
Drug 
Examination </p>

<p>Pre-operation 
Operation day </p>

<p>POD #1 </p>

<p>POD #2 
POD #3 
POD #4 </p>

<p>POD #5 </p>

<p>POD #6 
POD #7-8 </p>

<p>POD #10-11 </p>

<p>-Bowel preparation 
-Anti-embolic device 
-Central line and nasogastric 
tube insertion at operation 
room 
-Abdominal JP drains x3 </p>

<p>-Remove nasogastric tube 
-Ward ambulation </p>

<p>-Remove Foley catheter </p>

<p>-Remove central line </p>

<p>-Remove JP if OK 
-Remove JP if OK 
-Oncology consult 
-Discharge 
-Outpatient follow-up 2-3 
week later </p>

<p>-NPO after lunch 
-NPO </p>

<p>-NPO 
-Central total paren-
teral nutrition 
-NPO 
-Sips of water 
-Liquid diet 
-Peripheral fluid 
-Soft diet 
-Nutritionist interview 
-Stop intravenous fluid 
-Regular diet </p>

<p>-Antibiotics 
-Low molecular weight 
heparin 
-Patient-controlled analgesia 
-Proton pump inhibitor 
medication </p>

<p>-Stop heparin 
-Oral drug medication </p>

<p>-Oral analgesics 
-Oral antiacid 
-Digestives </p>

<p>-JP amylase/lipase </p>

<p>-JP amylase/lipase 
-JP amylase/lipase 
-JP amylase/lipase </p>

<p>-JP amylase/lipase 
-CT scan 
-JP amylase/lipase 
-JP amylase/lipase </p>

<p>NPO, nil per os; POD, post-operative day; CT, computed tomography; JP, jackson-pratt drain </p>

<p>in complex procedures. But the evidence to support their </p>

<p>use for complex procedures is limited, especially for com-</p>

<p>plex pancreatic surgery. 
9,13 This study was intended to </p>

<p>evaluate the impact of clinical pathway implementation </p>

<p>for PPPD patients. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Patient selection 
The study population was patients undergoing PD or </p>

<p>PPPD. Between January 2005 and December 2010, 273 </p>

<p>patients underwent PPPD or PD at our institution by a sin-</p>

<p>gle surgeon (SC Kim). A critical pathway for PD was im-</p>

<p>plemented from January 2009. Thus, 185 patients who un-</p>

<p>derwent surgery during a 48-month period before the im-</p>

<p>plementation of CP were allocated as the pre-CP group </p>

<p>(control group), and 88 patients who underwent surgery </p>

<p>during a 24-month period after CP implementation be-</p>

<p>came the CP group (the study group). Patients who re-</p>

<p>ceived additional vascular resection-anastomoses were in-</p>

<p>cluded as they were treated according to CP. To avoid </p>

<p>bias, the patients undergoing laparoscopic PPPD were ex-</p>

<p>cluded because they usually had a shorter hospital stay </p>

<p>compared with those who received an open procedure. </p>

<p>Peri-and post-operative parameters were analyzed retro-</p>

<p>spectively through a medical record review. This retro-</p>

<p>spective study protocol was approved by the institutional </p>

<p>review board of our institution. </p>

<p>Component of the critical pathway 
This CP protocol for PD and PPPD (Table 1) was de-</p>

<p>veloped by one surgeon (SC Kim) and a clinical nurse </p>

<p>practitioner. The CP was applied to patients if there was </p>

<p>no clinically significant postoperative complication after </p>

<p>the surgery. Templates were generated for a set-order sys-</p>

<p>tem in the hospital's electric medical record (EMR) system. </p>

<p>CP application began at admission for the operation, </p>

<p>with education of the patient and families using a guide </p>

<p>in booklet form which had been developed for PD/PPPD </p>

<p>patients. Specific aspects of CP included the management </p>

<p>of the abdominal drains and tubes, medications, diet, and </p>

<p>a special study for patients. </p>

<p>Details of the CP for PD and PPPD are as follows </p>

<p>(Table 1): on the day before surgery, all patients were or-</p>

<p>dered to fast after lunch, as well undergo a mild bowel </p>

<p>preparation. In the operation room, a sequential com-</p>

<p>pression device was applied and continued till the morn-</p>

<p>ing of the second postoperative day. Subcutaneous low-</p>



<p>Table 2. Nutritional status assessment by simplified mini nutrition assessment </p>

<p>S c o r e 
3 
2 
1 
0 </p>

<p>PIBW 
Serum albumin 
TLC </p>

<p>＜70 
＜2.1 
＜800 </p>

<p>≥70, ＜80 
≥2.1, ＜2.7 
≥800, ＜1,199 </p>

<p>≥80, ＜90 
≥2.7, ＜3.0 
≥1,200, ＜1,500 </p>

<p>＞90 
＞3.0 
＞1,500 </p>

<p>Percentage of ideal body weight (PIBW)=(current weight/ideal body weight)×100. Total lymphocyte count (TLC)=leucocyte 
count×proportion of lymphocytes (%)/100 
Determination of nutritional status: Score sum ranges from 0-3: Adequate nutritional status. Score sum ranges from 4-6: Level 
1 (low risk of malnutrition). Score sum ranges from 7-9: Level 2 (moderate risk of malnutrition) </p>

<p>molecular weight heparin was used for 4 days from the </p>

<p>operation day for prevention of deep vein thrombosis. All </p>

<p>patients received an intravenous infusion of proton pump </p>

<p>inhibitors and prophylactic antibiotics. For postoperative </p>

<p>pain control, a patient-controlled analgesia device and ad-</p>

<p>ditional on-demand narcotics or a non-steroidal anti-in-</p>

<p>flammatory drug were used. At the first postoperative day, </p>

<p>patients were encouraged to have ward ambulation and </p>

<p>the nasogastric tube was removed. Patients started sips of </p>

<p>water on the third postoperative day, with reduction of in-</p>

<p>travenous fluids, and a liquid diet was commenced on the </p>

<p>fourth day, and a soft diet on the fifth day, with pancreatic </p>

<p>enzyme supplementation. In most patients, initiation of a </p>

<p>regular diet began around the seventh postoperative day. </p>

<p>An interview with a nutritionist after a soft diet was start-</p>

<p>ed was included in this CP. Amylase and lipase levels of </p>

<p>the fluid in the abdominal drains were measured every </p>

<p>day, and postoperative abdomen computed tomography </p>

<p>(CT) was performed on the fifth day. The abdominal </p>

<p>drains were removed on the eighth postoperative day if </p>

<p>no clinically significant pancreatic fistula or fluid collec-</p>

<p>tion was identified. Discharge medications included an </p>

<p>antacid, analgesics, and a pancreatic enzyme supplement </p>

<p>in addition to the baseline medications. A follow-up visit </p>

<p>was scheduled 2-3 weeks after discharge with a visit to </p>

<p>the concurrent oncologist clinic scheduled on the same day. </p>

<p>Surgical procedure and definition of complica-
tions 
The procedures on all patients were performed by a sin-</p>

<p>gle surgeon. When doing the PPPD, the pancreaticojeju-</p>

<p>nostomy was performed in end-to-side fashion using the </p>

<p>duct-to-mucosa technique. Pancreaticogastrostomy was </p>

<p>not performed at all. Braun anastomosis (side-to-side jeju-</p>

<p>nojejunostomy) was routinely performed. </p>

<p>The complications after surgery were graded by the </p>

<p>International Study Group of Pancreatic Surgery (ISGPS) </p>

<p>definitions. 
15-17 Clinically significant complications were </p>

<p>defined as delayed gastric emptying (DGE) grade B or C, </p>

<p>post-pancreatectomy hemorrhage (PPF) grade B or C, </p>

<p>postoperative pancreatic fistula (POPF) grade B or C, </p>

<p>wound infection or other complications which needed an </p>

<p>intervention. All of these can influence patient outcomes </p>

<p>or the length of hospital stay. </p>

<p>Nutritional state evaluation 
Mini Nutrition Assessment (MNA) has been commonly </p>

<p>used for grading the nutritional status and the risk of mal-</p>

<p>nutrition in hospitalized patients. 
18,19 Key components of </p>

<p>the MNA are the body weight, serum protein, and lym-</p>

<p>phocyte count. 20 To perform the nutritional status assess-</p>

<p>ment more effectively, we developed a simplified MNA </p>

<p>(sMNA). Our sMNA comprised of 3 components includ-</p>

<p>ing the weight as a percentage of the ideal body weight, </p>

<p>serum albumin concentration, and a total lymphocyte </p>

<p>count. We calculated a score for each item according to </p>

<p>the definition, and then determined the nutritional status </p>

<p>by summation (Table 2). The nutritional status was de-</p>

<p>termined to be adequate if the summed score ranged from </p>

<p>0-3, level 1 if the score ranged from 4-6, and level 2 if </p>

<p>the score ranged from 7-9. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Categorical variables were analyzed using the chi-square </p>

<p>test, and when applicable, Fisher's exact test. Continuous </p>

<p>variables were analyzed using Student's t-test. Numeric </p>

<p>variables were expressed as the mean±standard deviation </p>

<p>or as a percentage. A p-value of less than 0.05 was con-</p>

<p>sidered to be statistically significant. All statistical analy-</p>

<p>ses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version18.0</rs>; </p>

<p>Hyoung-Eun Kim, et al. Critical pathway for pancreaticoduodenectomy 17 </p>

<p>Table 3. Patient demographics and preoperative parameters </p>

<p>Pre-CP group 
CP group 
p-value </p>

<p>Patient number (n) 
Surgical volume per month (n) 
Age (yrs) 
Male gender (n) 
Co-morbidity (n) 
All 
DM 
HTN 
DM＋HTN 
Pathological malignancy (n) 
Classical PD cases (n) </p>

<p>185 
6.5 
61.8±11.1 
108 (58.4%) </p>

<p>66 (35.7%) 
24 (13%) 
33 (19%) 
9 (4.9%) 
130 (70.3%) 
47 (25.4%) </p>

<p>88 
7.5 
60.3±10.5 
50 (56.8%) </p>

<p>40 (45.5%) 
10 (11.4%) 
19 (21.6%) 
11 (12.5%) 
72 (81.8%) 
21 (23.9%) </p>

<p>0.65 
0.81 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>0.042 
0.78 </p>

<p>DM, diabetes mellitus; HTN, hypertension; PD, pancreaticoduodenectomy </p>

<p>Table 4. Postoperative parameters </p>

<p>Pre-CP group (n=185) 
CP group (n=88) 
p-value </p>

<p>Mortality 
Complication* (n) All 
DGE 
PPH 
POPF 
Wound problem 
Others </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Clinically significant complication (n) 
Nutritional status at discharge (n) 
Adequate 
Level 1 
Level 2 
Postoperative hospital stay (days) 
Total hospital stay (days) 
Total medical cost (US$) 
Re-admission within 30 days (n) </p>

<p>0 
98 (53%) 
26 (14.1%) 
6 (3.2%) 
54 (29.2%) 
16 (8.6%) 
27 (14.6%) 
10 (5.4%) </p>

<p>163 (88.1%) 
22 (11.9%) 
0 
20.2±9.2 
29.2±11.1 
15,755±4,595 
5 (2.7%) </p>

<p>0 
36 (40.9%) 
4 (4.5%) 
2 (2.3%) 
23 (26.1%) 
2 (2.3%) 
15 (17.0%) 
4 (4.5%) </p>

<p>73 (83.0%) 
13 (14.8%) 
2 (2.3%) 
14.9±5.1 
19.4±7.7 
13,578±3,136 
4 (4.5%) </p>

<p>NS 
0.06 
0.02 
0.66 
0.60 
0.05 
0.60 
0.51 
0.10 </p>

<p>＜0.001 
＜0.001 
＜0.001 
0.43 </p>

<p>DGE, delayed gastric emptying; PPH, post-pancreatectomy hemorrhage; POPF, postoperative pancreatic fistula 
*All are according to the ISGPS definition (International Study Group of Pancreatic Surgery). 
 † Including fluid collection with 
or without intervention, chylous drainage, ileus, diarrhea, abdominal pain, pulmonary embolism, urinary tract infection, chol-
edochojejunostomy stricture, symptomatic portal vein narrowing, and fever of unknown origin </p>

<p>SPSS, Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Comparison of patient demographics and 
operative parameters 
The demographic features were similar between the two </p>

<p>groups (Table 3). The mean age and distribution of gender </p>

<p>were not significantly different. The incidence of co-mor-</p>

<p>bidity was similar when comparing diabetes and hyper-</p>

<p>tension, but patients with diabetes and hypertension were </p>

<p>more frequent in the CP group (p=0.02). The proportion </p>

<p>of classical PD was very similar in the two groups (25.4% </p>

<p>vs. 23.9%, p=0.78). The rate of primary pathologic diag-</p>

<p>noses of the malignancy was different between the groups, </p>

<p>with 70.3% in the pre-CP group and 81.8% in the CP </p>

<p>group (p=0.042). </p>

<p>Comparison of postoperative complications 
There was no case of in-hospital mortality in the two </p>

<p>groups. The peri-operative complication rate was similar </p>

<p>or decreased with the implementation of CP. The overall </p>

<p>complication rate was 53% before implementation of the </p>

<p>CP and 40.9% after CP implementation (p=0.06). The </p>

<p>clinically significant complication rate was not different, </p>

<p>showing 5.4% in the pre-CP group and 4.5% in the CP </p>



<p>group (p=0.51) (Table 4). </p>

<p>The rates of specific complications such as post-pan-</p>

<p>createctomy hemorrhage (3.2% in the pre-CP group vs. </p>

<p>2.3% in the CP group), and postoperative pancreatic fistu-</p>

<p>la (29.2% in the pre-CP group vs. 26.1% in the CP group) </p>

<p>were similar as well. In contrast, delayed gastric emptying </p>

<p>(14.1% in the pre-CP group vs. 4.5% in the CP group) </p>

<p>and wound complications (8.6% in the pre-CP group vs. </p>

<p>2.3% in the CP group) were significantly reduced. Other </p>

<p>less serious or less frequent complications such as fluid </p>

<p>collection, diarrhea, prolonged pain, pulmonary embolism, </p>

<p>urinary tract infection, and chylous drainage also showed </p>

<p>similar rates between the two groups (14.6% in the pre-CP </p>

<p>group vs. 17.0% in the CP group). </p>

<p>Comparison of postoperative nutritional status 
The nutritional status according to the sMNA score was </p>

<p>similar between the two groups. The re-admission rate </p>

<p>within 30 days after discharge was similar as well, show-</p>

<p>ing 2.7% in the pre-CP group vs. 4.5% in the CP group </p>

<p>(Table 3). </p>

<p>Comparison of postoperative hospital stay and 
medical costs 
In comparison with the pre-CP group, the CP group </p>

<p>showed a significantly shorter period of mean post-</p>

<p>operative hospital stay (20.2±9.2 days in the pre-CP group </p>

<p>vs. 14.9±5.1 days in the CP group, p＜0.001) and lower </p>

<p>total medical costs (US$ 15,755±4,595 in the pre-CP </p>

<p>group vs. US$ 13,578±3,136 in the CP group, p＜0.001) </p>

<p>(Table 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>CPs are care plans that detail the essential steps in the </p>

<p>care of patients with a specific clinical problem. 8 Although </p>

<p>their use in clinical medicine was initially focused on use </p>

<p>by nurses and other non-physician medical staff, physi-</p>

<p>cian-driven and -directed clinical pathways have gained </p>

<p>popularity over the past decades as an effort to improve </p>

<p>the efficiency and effectiveness of clinical medical services. </p>

<p>Previous studies have demonstrated that the implemen-</p>

<p>tation of CP decreases the length of hospital stay, total </p>

<p>costs, or both, following various gastrointestinal surgical </p>

<p>procedures. 11,12 More recently, even in the case of more </p>

<p>complex surgeries such as pancreas head resection, and </p>

<p>distal pancreatectomy, shorter hospital stays and reduced </p>

<p>hospital charges were observed after implementation of </p>

<p>CP. 
13,14 The results of this study also demonstrated that </p>

<p>the hospital stay and costs were significantly reduced after </p>

<p>implementation of CP in 88 patients who underwent </p>

<p>PPPD or PD, with patients showing maintenance or im-</p>

<p>provement of clinical outcomes. </p>

<p>When considering the effect of CP on postoperative </p>

<p>hospital stay, the early start of an oral diet might contrib-</p>

<p>ute to the shortening of the postoperative hospital stay, </p>

<p>but other factors must be related to this effect. In this </p>

<p>study, CP implementation advanced the start of an oral </p>

<p>diet by 3.5 days, but hospital discharge was increased by </p>

<p>5.3 days, which was a difference of 1.8 days. </p>

<p>Although there is no doubt that significant indirect </p>

<p>costs to both the patients and society exist in the patient </p>

<p>population undergoing PD or PPPD, a comparative assess-</p>

<p>ment of the medical costs was confined to the direct hos-</p>

<p>pital costs in this study because of the limitations of the </p>

<p>study's retrospective design. It is important to note that </p>

<p>many parts of the medical costs occurring during the peri-</p>

<p>operative period were incorporated and rather fixed (i.e., </p>

<p>anesthesia management, specific operative treatment, and </p>

<p>pathologic examination), and thus, these portions were not </p>

<p>influenced by CP implementation. It is possible to hy-</p>

<p>pothesize that the reduced costs observed in CP patients </p>

<p>were not primarily due to the CP implementation, but </p>

<p>were simply a consequence of the substantial difference </p>

<p>between the room cost and boarding costs, including the </p>

<p>special medical staff care fee. The results of this study </p>

<p>revealed that the total cost difference before and after CP </p>

<p>implementation was greater than the difference that origi-</p>

<p>nated from room and board costs. Such a remarkable re-</p>

<p>duction of the total medical costs seems to be associated </p>

<p>with integrated efforts toward maximizing cost-effective-</p>

<p>ness in every part of perioperative medical care, without </p>

<p>sacrificing patient safety. </p>

<p>The fact that a patient is "on the pathway" may result </p>

<p>in more of a push from health care providers for the pa-</p>

<p>tient to recover, unrelated to any specific component of </p>

<p>the pathway, the so-called Hawthorne effect. 21 We also </p>

<p>think that this Hawthorne effect might, at least in part, </p>

<p>be responsible for some of the differences observed in this </p>

<p>study. However, considering the relatively long length of </p>

<p>Hyoung-Eun Kim, et al. Critical pathway for pancreaticoduodenectomy 19 </p>

<p>the study period of 2 years, we do not think that a tempo-</p>

<p>rary phenomenon such as the Hawthorne effect was one </p>

<p>of the main components of the enhanced cost-effectiveness. </p>

<p>There are several important points to emphasize when </p>

<p>implementing CP as follows: CP leads to standardization </p>

<p>of medical care; all persons engaged in the treatment in-</p>

<p>cluding charge doctors, nurses, paramedical and the pa-</p>

<p>tients themselves share the same knowledge; patients can </p>

<p>anticipate the recovery pathways; it leads to maximal uti-</p>

<p>lization of medical resources; it serves as a care map for </p>

<p>doctors' training; and it may provide baseline information </p>

<p>for improving the CP protocol. </p>

<p>We do not think that our current CP protocol is suffi-</p>

<p>ciently cost-effective and patient safety-oriented. If some </p>

<p>unexpected complication happens, we are ready to revise </p>

<p>the CP protocol toward maximizing patient safety. The re-</p>

<p>sults of this study revealed that CP as a fast-tracking pro-</p>

<p>tocol plays an important role in patient care, in max-</p>

<p>imizing resources, and in resident and fellow training. </p>

<p>Therefore, without even mentioning the improvement in </p>

<p>the quality of medical care, implementation of CP is a </p>

<p>means of providing cost effective care and decreasing the </p>

<p>use of hospital resources. </p>

<p>One non-negligible limitation of this study was that the </p>

<p>study design included a historical control group. The sur-</p>

<p>geon's experience may have affected the complications, </p>

<p>especially following complex surgery such as PD and </p>

<p>PPPD, although the surgical volume was similar between </p>

<p>the study group and control group (7.5 cases/month and </p>

<p>6.5 cases/month). Several studies have demonstrated the </p>

<p>importance of the surgeon and institutional surgical vol-</p>

<p>ume in reducing the morbidity and mortality associated </p>

<p>with PD. There are several other limitations regarding this </p>

<p>study. There was no comparison data with other medical </p>

<p>centers. In addition, the number of the study groups was </p>

<p>rather small, thus increasing type II error. Finally, this </p>

<p>study lacked a patient satisfaction survey. </p>

<p>In conclusion, despite the complexity of PD and PPPD </p>

<p>procedures, the implementation of CP significantly re-</p>

<p>duced medical costs and enhanced resource utilization </p>

<p>without any detrimental effects on the quality of patient </p>

<p>care, and it even showed improved outcomes. These re-</p>

<p>sults support the idea that CP can be safely applied to </p>

<p>complex surgical situations if reasonably developed CP </p>

<p>protocols are established. Further investigation through </p>

<p>multi-center high-volume studies is necessary to validate </p>

<p>the actual impact of CP for PD and PPPD. </p>



</text></tei>