<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4960374" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Acute coronary syndrome is well known to be caused by the 
rupture of vulnerable atheromatous plaques, resulting in in-
sufficient perfusion of the myocardium. 
1 Human autopsy stud-
ies have indicated that vulnerable plaques are typically associ-
ated with a thin, inflamed fibrous cap overlaying a lipid core, 
increased neovascularization, medial and adventitial changes, 
intraplaque hemorrhage, inflammation, and positive vascular 
remodeling. 
2-4 In eroded plaques, which is another form of ad-
vanced plaque, thrombus occurs over the intima-deficient en-</p>

<p>Development of Advanced Atherosclerotic Plaque 
by Injection of Inflammatory Proteins 
in a Rabbit Iliac Artery Model </p>

<p>Jung-Sun Kim 
1,2,3 *, Seul-Gee Lee 
4 *, Jaewon Oh </p>

<p>1,3 </p>

<p>, Sungha Park </p>

<p>1,3 </p>

<p>, Se-Il Park </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, Sung-Yu Hong </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, Sehoon Kim </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>, 
Sang-Hak Lee </p>

<p>1,3 </p>

<p>, Young-Guk Ko </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>, Donghoon Choi </p>

<p>1,2,3 </p>

<p>, Myeong-Ki Hong </p>

<p>1,2,3,6 </p>

<p>, and Yangsoo Jang </p>

<p>1,2,3,6 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Cardiology Division, Severance Cardiovascular Hospital, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cardiovascular Product Evaluation Center, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul; </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Cardiovascular Research Institute, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul; </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Graduate Program in Science for Aging, Yonsei University, Seoul; </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Department of Pathology, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul; </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Severance Biomedical Science Institute, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea. </p>

<p>Purpose: Appropriate animal models of atherosclerotic plaque are crucial to investigating the pathophysiology of atherosclerosis, 
as well as for the evaluation of the efficacy and safety of vascular devices. We aimed to develop a novel animal model that would be 
suitable for the study of advanced atherosclerotic lesions in vivo. 
Materials and Methods: Atherosclerotic plaque was induced in 24 iliac arteries from 12 rabbits by combining a high cholesterol 
diet, endothelial denudation, and injection into the vessel wall with either saline (n=5), olive oil (n=6), or inflammatory proteins 
[n=13, high-mobility group protein B1 (HMGB1) n=8 and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α n=5] using a Cricket 
TM Micro-infusion 
catheter. Optical coherence tomography (OCT) was performed to detect plaque characteristics after 4 weeks, and all tissues were 
harvested for histological evaluation. 
Results: Advanced plaque was more frequently observed in the group injected with inflammatory proteins. Macrophage infiltra-
tion was present to a higher degree in the HMGB1 and TNF-α groups, compared to the oil or saline group (82.1±5.1% and 94.6± 
2.2% compared to 49.6±14.0% and 46.5±9.6%, p-value&lt;0.001), using RAM11 antibody staining. On OCT, lipid rich plaques were more 
frequently detected in the inflammatory protein group [saline group: 2/5 (40%), oil group: 3/5 (50%), HMGB1 group: 6/8 (75%), 
and TNF-α group: 5/5 (100%)]. 
Conclusion: These data indicate that this rabbit model of atherosclerotic lesion formation via direct injection of pro-inflammatory 
proteins into the vessel wall is useful for in vivo studies investigating atherosclerosis. </p>

<p>Key Words: Rabbit model, atherosclerosis, balloon injury, inflammatory protein </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>pISSN: 0513-5796 · eISSN: 1976-2437 </p>

<p>Received: December 7, 2015 Revised: February 9, 2016 
Accepted: March 3, 2016 
Corresponding author: Dr. Sungha Park, Division of Cardiology, Severance Car-
diovascular Hospital, Yonsei University College of Medicine, 50-1 Yonsei-ro, Seo-
deamun-gu, Seoul 03722, Korea. 
Tel: 82-2-2228-8460, Fax: 82-2-393-2041, E-mail: shpark0530@yuhs.ac </p>

<p>*Jung-Sun Kim and Seul-Gee Lee contributed equally to this work. 
•The authors have no financial conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>© Copyright: Yonsei University College of Medicine 2016 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and repro-
duction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J 2016 Sep;57(5):1095-1105 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.5.1095 </p>



<p>Advanced Atherosclerotic Rabbit Model </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.5.1095 </p>

<p>dothelium with thick fibroatheroma. 
2,4 The formation of vulner-
able plaques and the development of sudden thrombus have 
been observed in postmortem humans with cardiovascular 
disease. </p>

<p>3   Due to the lack of adequate animal models, pre-thrombotic 
pathophysiology and plaque vulnerability have been difficult 
to investigate in vivo. Several large animal models of vulnera-
ble atherosclerosis and plaque rupture have been proposed. </p>

<p>5-8   Using a high cholesterol diet and balloon injury, followed by 
pharmacological triggering, a rabbit model of induced athero-
sclerotic plaque and atherothrombosis has been developed. </p>

<p>6,8   However, these models show difficulties in developing consis-
tent advanced atherosclerotic plaques, thereby limiting their 
usefulness to clinical researchers. To overcome these limita-
tions, a reproducible porcine model of atherosclerosis, which 
utilized the direct injection of complex lipids into the vascular 
wall, 
9 was developed. Additionally, this approach resulted in 
focal lesions that were located in positively remodeled vessels 
that have increased neovascularization, as well as the release 
of pro-inflammatory chemokines. </p>

<p>10   Atherosclerosis is a complex inflammatory and immune re-
sponse disease, and plaque vulnerability is linked with in-
creased levels of inflammation. 
11 As such, the direct injection of 
pro-inflammatory proteins into the vessel wall may trigger a 
more potent inflammatory response and consistently augment 
the atherosclerotic process within a short period of time. To 
date, no study has investigated the effects of injecting pro-in-
flammatory proteins directly into the vascular wall on inflam-
mation and atherosclerosis. In this study, we selected the pro-in-
flammatory proteins high-mobility group protein B1 (HMGB1) 
and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α, because both of these che-
mokines are well known to promote the inflammatory process 
and mediate atherosclerosis. This study was designed to inves-
tigate the effect of injecting pro-inflammatory proteins into the 
vessel wall on the development of advanced plaques and inflam-
mation. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Experimental animal model </p>

<p>A total of 16 male New Zealand white rabbits (12 months old, 
weighing 3.0-4.0 kg) were used in the study. Four rabbits did 
not complete the protocol. Finally, 12 rabbits were included in 
this study. The experimental protocol is shown in Fig. 1. 
All rabbits were given a high cholesterol diet (2% cholesterol, 
Scientific Animal Food &amp; Engineering, Augy, France) 1 week 
prior to and 4 weeks after the balloon injury and intramuscu-
lar injection. After premedication with antibiotics and analge-
sics, anesthesia was induced by intramuscular injection with 
an appropriate mixture of tiletamine-zolazepam (10 mg/kg, 
Zoletil </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Virvac, Fort Worth, TX, USA) and xylazine (0.5 mg/kg , 
Rompun </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Bayer, Leverkusen, Germany), then maintained with </p>

<p>1-2% of isoflurane (Forane </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, JW Pharm, Seoul, Korea) and ox-
ygen. Access to the iliac artery was obtained via the carotid ar-
tery, using a sterile surgical technique. Heparin (150 units/kg) 
was injected to maintain an activated clotting time &gt;250 s be-
fore catheterization. Based on quantitative angiography (QA), 
an oversized balloon inflation with a 1.3:1.0 (balloon:artery ra-
tio) was applied two times for 30 seconds within both iliac ar-
teries using a 15-mm-length balloon. Following balloon inju-
ry, oil, inflammatory proteins+oil, or saline was delivered to 
each iliac artery using a Cricket 
TM Micro-Infusion catheter 
(Mercator Medsystems, San Leandro, CA, USA) over a guide-
wire under fluoroscopic guidance. Following the compound 
delivery, angiography and OCT examination were performed. 
All animals received 40 mg aspirin (~10 mg/kg) and clopido-
grel (75 mg/daily) after the procedure. The animals were eu-
thanized 4-weeks post-procedure, and the iliac arteries were 
harvested. 
The study protocol was approved by the local institutional an-
imal care and use committee (Medi Kinetics, MK-IACUC: 
111027-001 and Cardiovascular Production Evaluation Center, 
Yonsei University College of Medicine). All animals received 
humane care in compliance with the Animal Welfare Act and 
the "Principles of Laboratory Animal Care" formulated by the 
Institute of Laboratory Animal Resources (National Research 
Council, NIH Publication No. 85-23, revised 1996). </p>

<p>Intramural vascular injection </p>

<p>A total of 32 iliac arteries from 16 rabbits were randomly as-
signed into four groups: saline injection group (Daihan Pharm 
Co., Seoul, Korea, n=8), olive oil injection group (Sigma Aldrich, 
St. Louis, MO, USA, n=8), HMGB1 (A&amp;RT, Daejeon, Korea)+oil 
injection (n=8), and the TNF-α (Prospec, Ness-Ziona, Israel)+oil 
group (n=8). The operator was blinded to each artery material 
that was randomly selected and injected differently to both 
sides of iliac arteries. Immediately after the balloon injury, en-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. Experimental protocol. Schematic view of study timeline. Upon ar-
rival to the animal facility, rabbits were started on a daily high cholesterol 
diet for 5 weeks. One week later, balloon injury was induced, and inflam-
matory proteins were injected. Body weight and serums were assessed 
before the high cholesterol diet and before the sacrifice at 5 weeks. OCT 
was assessed at the beginning and end of the study. Animals were euth-
anized 4 weeks after the injection procedure, and iliac arteries were har-
vested at that time. OCT, optical coherence tomography. </p>

<p>Blood collection for 
cholesterol measurements </p>

<p>New Zealand white 
rabbits </p>

<p>Angiographic and 
OCT examination 
Euthanasia and 
tissue harvest </p>

<p>Balloon injury 
Oil or protein 
injection 
Angiographic 
and OCT 
examination </p>

<p>5 weeks 
1 week </p>

<p>2% Chol 
2% Chol </p>

<p>Study duration </p>

<p>v 
v 
v </p>



<p>Jung-Sun Kim, et al. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.5.1095 </p>

<p>dovascular intramural injection using a Cricket 
TM Micro-Infu-
sion catheter was performed. The infusion catheter is designed 
to deliver the material to the adventitia of the vessel wall via 
needle injection. The Cricket 
TM Micro-Infusion catheter was 
placed within the balloon-injured site, and the balloon was in-
flated. The vessel wall was penetrated by the needle. Complete 
occlusion after balloon inflation and shape of needle were 
confirmed by angiography. The infusion catheter system de-
livered 200 μL of saline, oil, HMGB1, or TNF-α (inflammatory 
proteins, 20 ug/200 uL dilution into saline) into the vessel wall. 
Each animal received two treatments within each iliac artery. 
The circumferential injection of solutions was repeated four 
times within the injured vessel segment to achieve a total of 1 cc 
of the target dose. Angiography and optical coherence tomog-
raphy (OCT) were performed twice: immediately post-procedure 
and 4-weeks post-procedure. After the autopsy, 15 mm of vessel 
was dissected into three equal parts (5 mm each) and stored. </p>

<p>Blood analysis </p>

<p>Plasma levels of total cholesterol (TC), triglyceride (TG), and 
high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) were measured 
by DRI-CHEM 4000i (Fujifilm, Tokyo, Japan) (TCHO-P, TG-P, 
HDL-C-PD) in blood samples before, 1 week, and 5 weeks af-
ter the introduction of the high cholesterol diet. Blood samples 
were collected from the carotid arteries of the rabbits. </p>

<p>Histological analysis </p>

<p>Under anesthesia, all animals were euthanized immediately 
after the follow-up imaging was complete. Iliac vessels (5 mm 
in length) were fixed by continued perfusion with 10% normal 
buffered formalin. To assure the proper identification, right il-
iac arteries were marked at the distal end with a 4-0 silk suture, 
and then both arteries were carefully cut and immersion-fixed 
overnight before the histological processing. For paraffin em-
bedding, 4 mm in length of vessel was placed intact into a sin-
gle cassette, and processed through a graded series of alcohols 
and xylenes. After processing, the specimen was embedded 
as a single paraffin block. Paraffin sections were cut on a mi-
crotome at 4 microns, mounted on microscope slides (Super-
frost Plus, Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), and stained 
with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) staining, Masson's trichrome 
staining, Movat's pentachrome staining, and Sirius red stain 
for collagens. Frozen sections were cut on a microtome at 10 
microns, and mounted a 1 mm length of vessel for Oil red O lip-
id staining. 
In addition, the induction of inflammation and the expres-
sion of HMGB1 and TNF-α were evaluated in arterial samples 
using a mouse monoclonal anti-rabbit macrophage antibody 
(RAM11, DAKO, Santa Clara, CA, USA), the anti-body for HMGB1 
(NOVUS, Littleton, CO, USA), TNF-α (ABCAM, Cambridge, 
MA, USA), and the receptor for advanced glycation end prod-
ucts (RAGE, LSBio, Seattle, WA, USA). Changes in smooth mus-
cle acting (SMA) were also evaluated with the anti-SMA (AB-</p>

<p>CAM, Cambridge, MA, USA), using a general immunohistoche-
mistry (IHC) protocol (Supplementary Method 1, only online). 
Atherosclerotic plaques types were classified into early (type 
II, fatty streak, and type III, pre-atheroma) and advanced (type 
IV, atheroma; type V, fibroatheroma) plaques according to the 
American Heart Association (AHA) criteria. 
12 All pathologic 
slides were reviewed by one pathologist (S.H.K.) to determine 
the histomorphometric analysis and AHA classification. 
The cross-sectional areas [external elastic lamina (EEL), in-
ternal elastic lamina (IEL) stenosis and lumen] were measured 
on stained slides using digital morphological analysis. Digital 
images of the vessels were scanned using a Leica SCN400 (Wet-
zlar, Germany) and histomorphometry was performed using 
Leica Application Suite (LAS) 4.2 (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany). 
1) Media=EEL-IEL 
2) Intima area=IEL-Lumen 
3) Plaque area=media+intima area </p>

<p>Reverse transcription-PCR analysis </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated from the iliac vessels (5 mm length) 
using a tissue grinder motor (Bel-Art Products, Wayne, NJ, USA) 
and QIAzol lysis reagent (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany). The 
concentration of RNA was measured by Nanodrop 2000/2000c 
(Thermo Scientific, Long Beach, NY, USA). Complementary 
DNA (cDNA) was synthesized using Quantitect Reverse Tran-
scription (QIAGEN) and PCR using the AccuPower PCR Pre-
mix (Bioneer, Daejeon, Korea). All PCR products were sepa-
rated by electrophoresis on 2% agarose gels diluted in TAE. 
Sizes were compared to an included 100 bp DNA ladder (DYNE 
Bio, Seongnam, Korea), and PCR products were visualized us-
ing Loading STAR (DYNE Bio, Seongnam, Korea). 
The rabbit gene primer sequences used for PCR were: RAGE, 
forward 5'-ATGGTCACCCTCAGATCA-3' and reverse 5'-CT 
GAAGAGAACCTGGGAG-3'; HMGB1, forward 5'-GTTCTGAG 
TATCGCCCCAAA-3' and reverse 5'-TCCTCCTCATCCTCTTC 
GTC-3'; TNF-α, forward 5'-ATGGTCACCCTCAGATCA-3' and 
reverse 5'-CTGAAGAGAACCTGGGAG-3'; GAPDH, forward 
5'-AGGTCATCCACGACCACTTC-3' and reverse 5'-GTGAGTT 
TCCCGTTCAGCTC-3' . Relative mRNA levels were determined 
by comparison to the GAPDH mRNA. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Iliac vessels (5 mm length) were homogenized using Tissue 
Grinder Motor (Bel-Art Products, Wayne, NJ, USA) and lysed 
with RIPA buffer (Biosesang, Seongnam, Korea) containing a 
cOmplete Mini, ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA)-free 
protease inhibitor cocktail 
® (Roche, Basel, Switzerland). The 
protein concentrations were measured by bicinchoninic acid 
protein assay. Iliac artery lysates were loaded and separated 
on 12% SDS-PAGE gels and transferred onto Immuno-Blot </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>PVDF Membrane (BIO-RAD, Hercules, CA, USA). Membranes 
were blocked by a 5% skim milk (Noble Bio, Hwaseong, Ko-
rea) dilution in Tris-Buffered Saline and Tween 20 (TBS-T) at </p>



<p>Advanced Atherosclerotic Rabbit Model </p>



<p>room temperature for 1 hour, and were subsequently washed 
three times in TBS-T. Membranes were incubated in TBS-T 
with primary antibodies against HMGB1, TNF-α, and RAGE 
(all 1:1000 in 5% BSA, Biosesang, Seongnam, Korea) overnight 
at 4°C. Membranes were washed three times in TBS-T and in-
cubated with horseradish peroxidase conjugated secondary 
antibody at room temperature for 1 hour. All blots were probed 
using GAPDH as a loading control. Densitometry analysis was 
performed with <rs id="software-1" type="software">Image J</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>, 
Bethesda, MD, USA). </p>

<p>Quantitative coronary angiography </p>

<p>Quantitative coronary angiography analysis was performed 
immediately before the procedure and 4-weeks post-procedure 
using an off-line quantitative coronary angiographic system 
(CAAS System; Pie Medical Instruments, Maastricht, the Neth-
erlands) in an independent core laboratory (Cardiovascular 
Research Center, Seoul, Korea). Using the guiding catheter for 
magnification-calibration, the reference vessel diameter (RD) 
and minimum luminal diameter (MLD) were measured from 
diastolic frames in a single, matched view showing the smallest 
MLD. Percent diameter of stenosis was calculated according 
to the following formula: percent diameter stenosis=[(mean 
RD-MLD)/mean RD]×100, mean RD=(proximal RD+distal ves-
sel diameter)/2. </p>

<p>Optical coherence tomography imaging and 
matching with histology </p>

<p>OCT was performed using the C7-XR imaging systems (Light-
Lab Imaging, Inc., St. Jude Medical, St. Paul, MN, USA). The 
OCT catheter was pulled back at 20 mm/s, and OCT images 
were generated at 100 frames/s. Contrast media were contin-
uously flushed through a guiding catheter at a rate of 4-5 mL/s 
for 3-4 seconds. Images were continuously acquired and stored 
digitally for subsequent analyses. All OCT images were ana-
lyzed at a core laboratory (Cardiovascular Research Center, Seoul, 
Korea) by analysts who were blinded to procedural informa-
tion. The histological images were compared to their corre-
sponding OCT pullback lesion segments until the best and 
closest visual match was found (Fig. 2). This match was per-
formed with the consideration to the anatomical features (lu-
minal shape, neointimal thickness, presence of neovascular-
ization, etc.), the proximity to side branches, and the length 
from the balloon injury edge to the location of the histology 
samples (provided by the histological laboratory). Plaques 
were classified as 1) fibrous (homogeneous, high backscatter-
ing region) or 2) lipid (low-signal region with diffuse border). </p>

<p>13   Macrophage infiltration within the lesion was characterized 
by increased signal intensity within the lesion accompanied 
by the heterogeneous backward shadows. </p>

<p>14   Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> v<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">20.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). All data are expressed as mean±SEM. 
Continuous variables were compared using t-test (comparison 
of two groups) and ANOVA (comparison of 3 or more groups). 
If data distributions were skewed, a non-parametric test was 
used for comparison. A p-value of &lt;0.05 was considered sta-
tistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Animal condition and serum cholesterol evaluation </p>

<p>Two animals died immediately post-procedure due to cardiac 
arrhythmia, and two others of saline group 1 site and TNF-α 
group 3 sites died due to liver failure before evaluation of le-
sions within 5 weeks. These could have stemmed from com-
plications resulting from the high cholesterol diet. Thus, 24 
target lesions within 24 iliac arteries were harvested from 12 
rabbits after 5 weeks [saline (n=5), oil (n=6), HMGB1 (n=8), 
and TNF-α (n=5)]. 
The mean TC level for all animals was 26.4±7.0 mg/dL at 
baseline. This significantly increased to 874±63 mg/dL 5 weeks 
after the initiation of the 2% cholesterol diet (1 week before the 
procedure and 4 weeks after the procedure, p&lt;0.001). Low-den-
sity lipoprotein cholesterol, TG, and HDL-C were 743±60 mg/dL, 
182±32 mg/dL, and 96±6 mg/dL, respectively, at 5 weeks after 
the cholesterol diet was initiated. </p>

<p>Quantitative imaging evaluation </p>

<p>Five weeks after the initiation of the high cholesterol diet, min-
imal lumen diameter was similar in all groups (saline group: 
0.89±0.09 mm, oil group: 0.93±0.07 mm, HMGB1 group: 0.90± 
0.10 mm, and TNF-α group: 1.01±0.08 mm, p-value by ANO-
VA=0.546) (Table 1). The percentage of diameter stenosis was 
also not significantly different among all groups (saline group: 
35.82±2.35%, oil group: 36.93±4.23%, HMGB1 group: 39.73± 
3.13%, and TNF-α group: 34.55±2.74%, p-value by ANOVA= 
0.813) (Table 1). </p>

<p>Histomorphometric analysis </p>

<p>Atherosclerotic plaques developed in all the injected segments. 
A representative histologic image is shown in Fig. 2. The ad-
vanced plaque type (III, VI, and V by AHA criteria) was more 
frequently observed in the pro-inflammatory protein injected 
group, compared to all other groups (Fig. 2). Plaque area tend-
ed to be higher in oil, HMGB+oil, and TNF-α+oil groups, com-
pared to the saline group (saline group: 1.22±0.17 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, oil 
group: 1.64±0.33 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, HMGB1 group: 1.62±0.19 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, and TNF-α 
group: 1.55±0.26 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, p-value by ANOVA=0.696) (Table 1). </p>

<p>Altered expression of inflammatory markers within a 
plaque </p>

<p>IHC demonstrated that percent area stained positive for RAGE, 
HMGB1, and TNF-α tended to be higher in the oil or pro-in-</p>



<p>Jung-Sun Kim, et al. </p>



<p>flammatory proteins group, compared with the saline group. 
Macrophage infiltration within the plaques was significantly 
higher in the HMGB1 and TNF-α groups, compared to both </p>

<p>the oil and the saline groups (82.1±5.1% and 94.6±2.2% com-
pared to 49.6±14.0% and 46.5±9.6%, p-value by ANOVA=0.014) 
(Fig. 3). RT-PCR showed that the expression of RAGE mRNA </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Morphologic changes of rabbit iliac artery analysis. Tissue staining of induced atherosclerosis iliac artery plaques in four groups of rabbits. The lip-
id content of the plaques is indicated by Oil red O staining; the SMA content of the plaques is detected by immunohistochemical staining of α-SMA; the 
collagen content of the plaques is represented by Sirius red staining visualized under polarized light. Representative examples of H&amp;E [a-d (amplification 
×30), A-D], Masson's trichrome (E-H), Masson's pentachrome (I-L), α-SMA (M-P), Sirius red (Q-T), Oil red O (U: saline injection plaque, V: oil injection 
plaque, W: HMGB1 injection plaque, X: TNF-α injection plaque) in the rabbit iliac (amplification ×100). a: Saline injection plaque A, E, I, M, Q: higher magni-
fication taken from the black box in a. b: Oil injection plaque B, F, J, N, R: higher magnification taken from the black box in b. c: HMGB1 injection plaque C, 
G, K, O, S: higher magnification taken from the black box in c. d: TNF-α injection plaque D, H, L, P, T: higher magnification taken from the black box in d 
(scale bars=100 µm). SMA, smooth muscle actin; HMGB1, high-mobility group protein B1; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; H&amp;E, hematoxylin and eosin. </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>H&amp;E </p>

<p>Trichrome </p>

<p>Pentachrome </p>

<p>α-SMA </p>

<p>Sirius red </p>

<p>Oil red O </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>Q </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>J </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>V </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>W </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>X </p>



<p>Advanced Atherosclerotic Rabbit Model </p>



<p>was significantly higher in the HMGB1 group, compared to 
the saline group, and tended to be higher in the TNF-α group 
than the saline group (p=0.054). The TNF-α group had a sig-
nificantly higher expression of HMGB1 and TNF-α mRNA ex-</p>

<p>pression, compared to the saline and oil groups (Fig. 4). RAGE 
protein expression was significantly higher in the HMGB1 
group than the saline, oil, and TNF-α groups, as assessed by 
the western blot (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Morphologic changes of rabbit iliac artery analysis according to immunohistochemistry. Tissue staining of induced atherosclerosis iliac artery 
plaques in four groups of rabbits. The inflammation content of the plaques is detected by immunohistochemical staining for RAGE, HMGB1, and TNF-α; 
the macrophage content of the plaques is detected by immunohistochemical staining for the anti-rabbit macrophage clone RAM11. Representative ex-
amples of immunohistochemical stain of RAGE (A-D), HMGB1 (E-H), TNF-α (I-L), and RAM11 (M-P) in the rabbit iliac (amplification ×100) (scale bars=100 
µm). Lesions of macrophage were markedly less for saline group and oil group, which showed significant differences in the total percent area in compar-
ison to the HMGB1 group and TNF-α group on RAM11 immunohistochemical staining. *p&lt;0.05, compared with the Saline group, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, compared with 
the Oil group. RAGE, receptor for advanced glycation end products; HMGB1, high-mobility group protein B1; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α. </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>RAGE </p>

<p>HMGB1 </p>

<p>TNF-α </p>

<p>RAM11 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>J </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>IHC area (I/P* 100, %) RAGE </p>

<p>IHC area (I/P* 100, %) TNF-α </p>

<p>IHC area (I/P* 100, %) HMGB1 </p>

<p>IHC area (I/P* 100, %) RAM11 </p>

<p>Table 1. Morphological Parameters in QA, OCT, and Histology </p>

<p>Saline (n=5) 
Oil (n=6) 
HMGB1 (n=8) 
TNF-α (n=5) 
QA 
RD, mm 
1.49±0.23 
1.84±0.15 
1.50±0.14 
1.54±0.07 
MLD, mm 
0.95±0.14 
1.17±0.14 
0.90±0.10 
1.01±0.08 
DS, % 
35.82±2.35 
36.93±4.23 
39.7±3.13 
34.6±2.74 
OCT 
Vessel area, mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4.79±0.62 
6.26±0.18 
6.25±0.71 
7.48±1.10 
Lumen area, mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.91±0.46 
3.50±0.42 
3.54±0.50 
4.21±0.87 
Plaque, mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.88±0.24 
2.34±0.17 
2.71±0.28 
3.27±0.29* 
Area stenosis, % 
40.5±3.8 
44.1±6.9 
44.3±3.3 
45.9±3.8 
Lipid rich plaque, % 
2/5 (40%) 
3/6 (50%) 
6/8 (75%) 
5/5 (100%) 
Histology 
Media, mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.72±0.06 
0.75±0.01 
0.84±0.08 
0.86±0.06 
Intima, mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.66±0.15 
0.89±0.30 
0.89±0.22 
0.86±0.24 
Plaque, mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1.22±0.17 
1.64±0.33 
1.62±0.19 
1.55±0.26 
I/P (%) 
47.5±7.0 
50.9±7.7 
47.4±7.2 
47.4±6.0 
QA, quantitative angiography; RD, reference diameter; MLD, minimal luminal diameter; DS, diameter stenosis; I/P, intimal plaque ratio; OCT, optical coherence 
tomography; HMGB1, high-mobility group protein B1; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α. 
Values are n (%) or mean±SEM. 
*p&lt;0.05, compared with the Saline group. </p>



<p>Jung-Sun Kim, et al. </p>



<p>OCT evaluation comparing histology </p>

<p>Figs. 6 and 7 displays representative histological and OCT im-
ages for comparison. The 24 histologic lesions included in this 
study yielded a total of 24 OCT histology co-registrations. The 
lumen area, plaque area, and percent area stenosis were not 
significantly different among the four groups. However, the 
plaque area tended to increase in the HMGB1 and TNF-α 
groups (saline group: 1.88±0.24 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, oil group: 2.34±0.17 mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, 
HMGB1 group: 2.71±0.29 mm </p>

<p>2   , and TNF-α group: 3.27±0.29 
mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, p-value by ANOVA=0.065). 
By qualitative analysis, all the lipid rich plaques assessed by 
OCT were well-matched with histologic findings. The propor-
tion of plaques found to be lipid rich was different among the 
groups. Fig. 6E demonstrates the breakdown of plaque classi-
fication by group [saline group: 2/5 (40%), oil group: 3/5 (50%), 
HMGB1 group: 6/8 (75%), and TNF-α group: 5/5 (100%)]. 
Plaques determined to be class III-V were classified as lipid rich. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>There are two key findings from this study. First, our data sug-
gest that the induction of inflammation via direct injection of 
pro-inflammatory proteins, such as HMGB1 or TNF-α, into the 
iliac artery increases macrophage infiltration and accelerates 
inflammation within the vessel wall. Second, advanced ather-
omatous plaques, including lipid rich plaques, were more fre-
quently induced by the injection of pro-inflammatory pro-
teins, compared to the controls. The current study may provide 
a useful in vivo modality for developing advanced atheroma-
tous plaques by direct injection of pro-inflammatory proteins. 
A rabbit model of atherosclerosis has been proposed to eas-
ily induce foam cell-rich plaques, because of its unique sensi-
tivity to hypercholesterolemia. 
6 The iliac artery or aorta of the 
rabbit is frequently used as a model for preclinical cardiovas-
cular research studies due to its similar morphology with the 
coronary artery of humans. 
8 However, its use is limited by in-
ter-individual variations in plasma cholesterol levels and le-
sion characteristics in response to a cholesterol diet. Further-</p>

<p>Fig. 4. The relative mRNA levels in induced atherosclerosis of rabbit iliac artery. Reverse transcription (RT)-PCR analysis of RAGE, HMGB1, and TNF-α 
mRNA expression in iliac arteries from four groups of rabbits A. Representative data showing the mRNA expressions of RAGE, HMGB1, and TNF-α in iliac 
arteries from four groups of rabbits (normalized with GAPDH as the house keeping gene) B, C, and D. The data in the bar graph are quantified ratios of the 
signal for RAGE, HMGB1, and TNF-α to that for GAPDH set at fold increase. Data are presented as the mean±SEM. *p&lt;0.05, compared with the Saline 
group, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, compared with the Oil group. RAGE, receptor for advanced glycation end products; HMGB1, high-mobility group protein B1; TNF-α, tumor 
necrosis factor-α; GAPDH, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase; SEM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C 
D </p>

<p>1.8 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.8 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1.8 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>RAGE </p>

<p>HMGB1 </p>

<p>TNF-α </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α 
Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α 
Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>RAGE/GAPDH (fold increase) 
HMGB1/GAPDH (fold increase) 
TNF-α/GAPDH (fold increase) </p>



<p>Advanced Atherosclerotic Rabbit Model </p>



<p>more, this model has a risk of lipid toxicity resulting from a 
prolonged exposure to a high cholesterol diet. 
6 In addition, bal-
loon injury followed by a high cholesterol diet usually results 
in the induction of early stage atherosclerotic plaques rather 
than advanced plaques. In this study, in order to overcome this 
variability of developed atheromatous plaque, we modified 
the existing protocols in animal models. Previously, Granada, 
et al. 
9 proposed a method for inducing atherosclerotic plaques 
by combining balloon injury and the vascular wall injection of 
lipidic substances in a swine model. In their study, atheroscle-
rotic lesions containing inflammatory cells, positive remodel-
ing, and neovascularization all developed and resembled the 
early stages of human atherosclerosis. 
5 Furthermore, the intra-
mural injection of complex lipids into the coronary arteries in-
duced an increased expression of vascular endothelial grow fac-
tor (VEGF) and monocyte chemoattractant protein 1 (MCP-1). </p>

<p>10   However, to the best of our knowledge, no study has investi-
gated the induction of an atherosclerotic plaque in a rabbit 
model by the direct injection of a lipidic substance or pro-in-
flammatory proteins into the vessel wall. We observed the de-</p>

<p>veloped plaque area to be similar among the groups injected 
with either saline, lipid, or lipid+pro-inflammatory protein. 
However, macrophage accumulation was more prominent in 
the pro-inflammatory injected groups. Furthermore, the pro-
inflammatory groups had an increased expression of TNF-α 
and HMGB1 within the intima and media of the vessel, com-
pared with either the saline or oil injected groups. This finding 
suggests that direct tissue injection of pro-inflammatory pro-
teins may induce potent inflammation and promote the devel-
opment of an advanced atheromatous plaque. 
We applied two pro-inflammatory proteins in this study, 
TNF-α and HMGB1. TNF-α is a well-known potent pro-inflam-
matory cytokine involved in the pathogenesis of arteriosclero-
sis. It promotes the inflammatory response, which causes many 
of the clinical problems associated with autoimmune disor-
ders, such as inflammatory disease. 
11,15 HMGB1 is a potent pro-
inflammatory protein ligand that mediates inflammation by 
activating innate immunity receptors, such as toll-like receptor 
(TLR) and RAGE. 
16 HMGB1 passively diffuses out of necrotic 
or apoptotic cells. It works as a pro-inflammatory mediator </p>

<p>Fig. 5. The relative protein levels in induced atherosclerosis of rabbit iliac artery. Western blot analysis of RAGE, HMGB1 and TNF-α mRNA expressions in 
iliac artery from four groups of rabbits A. Representative data showing the protein expressions of RAGE, HMGB1 and TNF-α levels in iliac arteries from 
four groups of rabbits (normalized with GAPDH as the house keeping gene) B, C, and D. The data in the bar graph are quantified ratios of the signal for 
RAGE, HMGB1, and TNF-α to that for GAPDH set at fold increase. Data were presented as the mean±SEM. *p&lt;0.05, compared with the Saline group, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, compared with the Oil group, </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, compared with the TNF-α group. RAGE, receptor for advanced glycation end products; HMGB1, high-mo-
bility group protein B1; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α; GAPDH, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase; SEM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C 
D </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p> † ‡ </p>

<p>RAGE </p>

<p>HMGB1 </p>

<p>TNF-α </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α 
Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α 
Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α </p>

<p>RAGE/GAPDH (fold increase) 
HMGB1/GAPDH (fold increase) 
TNF-α/GAPDH (fold increase) </p>



<p>Jung-Sun Kim, et al. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.3349/ymj.2016.57.5.1095 </p>

<p>that activates immune competent cells, which in turn augment 
the inflammatory responses through the discharge of pro-in-
flammatory cytokines. 
17 Studies have shown that HMGB1 is 
highly expressed in the human carotid endarterectomy speci-
mens. 
18 In this study, injection of HMGB1 into the vessel wall 
was associated with increased expression of RAGE and with 
increased recruitment of macrophages to the lesion. These 
data suggest that the HMBG1 injection may induce an upreg-
ulation of RAGE expression and activation, resulting in an in-
creased recruitment of macrophages through the expression 
of cytokines and cell adhesion molecules. </p>

<p>16   OCT is a well-established, accurate imaging modality with a 
high resolution, capable of evaluating the characteristics of ath-
eromatous plaques in clinical situations. 
13,16,19 Here, using OCT, 
we were able to show that HMGB1 and TNF-α groups had a 
higher incidence of lipid rich plaques, compared to both the 
oil or saline groups. This finding confirmed histological stud-
ies that showed HMGB1 and TNF-α groups have more ad-</p>

<p>vanced plaques, compared to the saline and oil groups. OCT 
indicated that the diameter and area of the stenosis were not 
different between the four groups. 
The main limitation of this study was its short duration, 
which did not allow for the development of an established ne-
crotic core, intra-plaque hemorrhage, or calcified plaques. Fur-
thermore, plaque rupture or thrombus, which is the main pa-
thogenic mechanism of acute coronary syndrome, was not 
observed in this experimental model. However, these limita-
tions do not detract from the central merit of this work, which 
shows that a consistent model of advanced atherosclerosis has 
been developed. Therefore, our study seems as a cost-effective 
and short-time method that induces atherosclerotic lesions in 
rabbit. The lack of adequate medium to large sized animal 
models for atherosclerosis has been a major limitation for ani-
mal research in the cardiovascular field. We believe this mod-
el may be useful for further study investigating the pathogen-
esis and treatment of atherosclerosis. Also, it could be useful </p>

<p>E 100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>V 
IV 
III 
II 
I </p>

<p>Saline 
Oil 
HMGB1 
TNF-α 
AHA classification (%) </p>

<p>Fig. 6. OCT images of matched rabbit iliac artery histologic sections and histologic classification based on AHA criteria. OCT images obtained in vivo were 
matched with histological sections. Saline group A; Oil group B; HMGB1 group C; TNF-α group D. Histologic classification by AHA criteria E. Plaque char-
acteristics were categorized into early (type II, fatty streak, and type III, pre-atheroma) and advanced (type IV, atheroma; type Va, fibroatheroma; type Vc, 
fibrotic; and type VI, complicated). AHA, American Heart Association; OCT, optical coherence tomography; HMGB1, high-mobility group protein B1; 
TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D </p>



<p>Advanced Atherosclerotic Rabbit Model </p>



<p>for evaluations of device or screening therapeutic substances 
for treatment cardiovascular disease in the atherosclerosis re-
search field. Another limitation of our study is that we could 
not compare the vascular remodeling process after injection, 
because we did not measure vascular structure before injection 
in our experiment. However, we can assume that there may be 
some positive remodeling process in inflammatory protein-
injected group, considering increased in plaque volume in 
these groups. 
In conclusion, direct injection of inflammatory proteins 
into the iliac artery wall significantly increased macrophage 
infiltration, and induced the formation of a lipid rich plaque. 
Our data indicate that the rabbit model developed here may 
be useful for in vivo studies investigating atherosclerosis. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by a faculty research grant of Yonsei 
University College of Medicine for 2012 (6-2012-0131), by Ba-
sic Science Research Program through the National Research 
Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Educa-
tion (NRF-2014R1A1A2055584), by a grant from the Korea He-
althcare Technology R&amp;D Project, Severance Integrative Re-
search Institute for Cerebral &amp; Cardiovascular Diseases, Mini-</p>

<p>stry for Health &amp; Welfare Affairs, Republic of Korea (HI08C2149) 
and the Cardiovascular Research Center, Seoul, Korea. </p>



<p>Fig. 7. OCT matching with histomorphometry for macrophage infiltration. OCT images obtained in vivo were matched with histomorphological section of 
rabbit models for macrophage infiltration. Tissue staining of induced atherosclerosis iliac artery plaques in 4 groups of rabbits. The macrophage content 
of the plaques is detected by immunohistochemical staining for the anti-rabbit macrophage clone RAM11 and CD68 (arrows). Saline group A; Oil group B; 
HMGB1 group C; TNF-α group D. OCT, optical coherence tomography; HMGB1, high-mobility group protein B1; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D </p>

<p>RAM11 </p>

<p>CD68 </p>



<p>Jung-Sun Kim, et al. </p>



</text></tei>