<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4832946" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Postoperative preablative stimulated thyroglobulin (ps-Tg) has been evaluated in predicting prognosis and success of ablation 
regarding differentiated thyroid cancer (DTC); however, its relationship with recurrence risk and radioiodine decision-making remains 
uncertain, especially in Chinese DTC patients. We aimed to evaluate the association between ps-Tg and recurrence risk stratification in 
DTC, to provide incremental values for ps-Tg in postoperative assessment and radioiodine management. 
Methods: Seven hundred and seven patients with DTC were included; low-risk (L; n = 90), intermediate-risk (I; n = 283), and high-risk 
(H; n = 334, 117 with distant metastasis [M1]) patients were divided according to recurrence risk stratification. The M1 group was further 
analyzed regarding evidence of metastasis. Cut-off values of ps-Tg were obtained using receiver operating characteristic analysis. 
Results: Patients with more advanced disease at initial risk stratification were more likely to have higher ps-Tg levels (I vs. L: P &lt; 0.05; 
H vs. I: P &lt; 0.001; H vs. L: P &lt; 0.001). The corresponding cut-off value of ps-Tg for distinguishing sensitivity and specificity in each 
of the two groups was 2.95 ng/ml (I vs. L: 61.5%, 63.3%), 29.5 ng/ml (H vs. I: 41.9%, 92.6%), 47.1 ng/ml (M1 vs. M0 in the H group: 
79.5%, 88.9%) and 47.1 ng/ml (M1 vs. M0 in all patients: 79.5%, 93.7%). With the cut-off value at 47.1 ng/ml, ps-Tg was the only 
factor that could be used to identify distant metastases, and consequently if measured before radioiodine therapy would prevent 10.26% 
of patients with M1 from undertreatment. 
Conclusions: Ps-Tg, as an ongoing reassessment marker, favors differential recurrence risk grading and provides incremental values for 
radioiodine treatment decision-making. </p>

<p>Key words: Ablation; Differentiated Thyroid Carcinoma; Radioiodine Therapy; Recurrence Risk Stratification; Thyroglobulin </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Dr. Yan-Song Lin, 
Department of Nuclear Medicine, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, 
Beijing 100730, China 
E-Mail: linys@pumch.cn </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.155086 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>



<p>have argued that the preablative stimulated Tg (ps-Tg) 
level may be influenced by postoperative thyroid tissue 
remnants, 
[11] and that it would take at least 1-year for Tg to 
become undetectable. 
[12-13] Thus, the specific value and the 
significance of ps-Tg regarding decision-making require 
further investigation. </p>

<p>At present in China, surgical techniques such as cervical 
lymph node dissection are incongruently assigned to patients, 
and the time interval between surgery and treatment using 
nuclear medicine varies from a few days to a few years. 
Therefore, a marker that could reflect ongoing disease status 
is urgently needed, rather than static pathological findings 
during surgery. There is evidence to indicate that ps-Tg 
measured just before radioiodine treatment may have a role 
as such a marker. </p>

<p>[8,9,14,15] </p>

<p>To date, very few data regarding the relationship between 
ps-Tg and the three recurrence risk categories of ATA have 
been reported. In this study, we introduced the ps-Tg level 
into ongoing postoperative reassessment to explore the 
correlation between ps-Tg level and ATA recurrence risk 
stratification; the objective was to provide evidence-based 
support for Chinese patients for the role of ps-Tg in 
postoperative reassessment and radioiodine treatment 
decision-making. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Peking 
Union Medical College Hospital. </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>In this retrospective study, 985 patients with DTC received 
total thyroidectomy followed by radioiodine treatment 
from 2007 to 2013. A total 278 of these patients were 
excluded from the study; 177 had high Tg antibody (TgAb) 
levels (&gt;46 IU/ml) 
[16] and the other 101 had missing data 
regarding ps-Tg or TgAb levels. Therefore, 707 patients 
were finally enrolled in the study, including 482 females 
and 225 males with a mean age of 42.7 (range, 4-77) years. 
Histologically, 685 patients were diagnosed with PTC and 
22 with FTC. All patients underwent total thyroidectomy 
performed by experienced surgeons, with no macroscopic 
thyroid remnants remaining; seven of these patients with 
papillary thyroid microcarcinoma (tumor size ≤1 cm) 
did not undergo cervical lymph node dissection. Patients 
received I-131 at a dose that varied from 30 mCi (1.1 GBq) 
to 200 mCi (7.4 GBq) according to their ATA recurrence risk 
stratification 
[6] within 3 months after surgery; they underwent 
levothyroxine (LT4) withdrawal or no replacement treatment 
and a low-iodine diet for at least 2-6 weeks when serum 
TSH levels were &gt;30 μIU/ml. </p>

<p>Measurements and tests </p>

<p>Levels of ps-Tg, TgAb and TSH were measured before the first 
I-131 remnant ablation after thyroxine hormone withdrawal, 
and the TSH level had risen (TSH &gt; 30 μIU/ml). Tg and TgAb 
levels were determined using electrochemiluminescence 
immunoassay (Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, </p>

<p>Germany), and the TSH level was determined using 
chemiluminescence immunoassay (Siemens Healthcare 
Diagnostics Inc., New York, NY, USA) in the same 
laboratory. Patient characteristics were compiled including 
age, sex, histology subtypes, tumor invasion, cervical 
lymph node metastasis, distant metastasis, remnant uptake 
on I-131-WBS, TSH, and ps-Tg and TgAb levels. Patients 
were divided into three groups according to the ATA 
recurrence risk stratification: 
[6] Low-risk (L; n = 90), 
intermediate-risk (I; n = 283) and high-risk (H; n = 334). 
The H group was further subdivided into two subgroups, 
one with distant metastasis (M1; n = 117) and the other 
without distant metastasis (M0; n = 217). Additionally, 
while assigning patients to H group, we did not take the 
ps-Tg level into account, because the predictive cut-off 
value was not specified in the ATA Guidelines. 
[6] Patients 
with at least one of the following characteristics, according 
to ATA and the National Comprehensive Cancer Network 
guidelines, 
[6,17-19] were considered for subsequent radioiodine 
therapy: Male; age &gt;45 years; tumor size &gt;1 cm; multiple 
lesions (&gt;1 lesion); and molecular characteristics such as 
the BRAF 
V600E mutation. Because increased TSH stimulates 
ps-Tg during the LT4 withdraw period, indicating that Tg 
release is TSH-dependent, 
[20-22] we introduced the parameter 
ps-Tg/TSH. The associations between ps-Tg, ps-Tg/TSH and 
three recurrence risk groups were analyzed. The M1 group was 
further analyzed in terms of metastatic evidence such as chest 
computed tomography, bone scan, postradioiodine-therapy 
WBS (RxWBS) combined with a suspicious high ps-Tg level. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Rank sum and F tests were used for the comparison of 
ps-Tg and ps-Tg/TSH values. The Kruskal-Wallis and 
F tests were used for comparisons among the three groups; 
the Mann-Whitney U and F tests were used to compare any 
two groups. The most sensitive and specific ps-Tg values 
for distinguishing each of the two group comparisons were 
obtained using receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves. 
Gender (female or male), age (&lt;45 years or ≥45 years), tumor 
size (maximum diameter ≤1 cm or &gt;1 cm), multifocality 
(single lesion or multiple lesions) and ps-Tg level 
(&lt;corresponding cut-off value or ≥corresponding cut-off 
value) were involved as independent variables of recurrence 
and distant metastasis. These factors were further analyzed 
using logistic regression analysis to identify if ps-Tg was 
an independent predictive factor for discerning different 
recurrence risk groups, and if distant metastases existed. 
A P &lt; 0.05 was considered as statistically significant. All 
of these statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 17.0</rs>, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">R 
project</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 2.15.1</rs>). </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Comparisons of preablative stimulated thyroglobulin in 
different recurrence risk groups </p>

<p>The descriptive characteristics of the 707 patients are given 
in Table 1. The ratio of females to males was 2.14:1, 96.89% </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>

<p>
of patients had PTC and the preablative TSH level was 
91.36 ± 35.57 μU/ml. Analysis of the three risk classification 
groups of L, I and H revealed that the more advanced the 
stratification, the greater the likelihood of a higher ps-Tg 
level. This trend could also be seen when comparing the 
L, I and H groups with the M0 and M1 groups [Figure 1]. 
Especially, in the case of the H group, it was found that the 
subgroup with distant metastasis was accompanied by the 
highest ps-Tg level [Figure 1]. </p>

<p>The mean ps-Tg level for the L, I and H groups was 5.278, 
11.588 and 159.939 ng/ml, respectively. The corresponding 
standard deviation varied greatly between the three recurrence 
risk groups [Table 2]. The median ps-Tg level for the L, I 
and H groups was 1.7, 4.4 and 14.7 ng/ml, respectively, 
and the corresponding 25-75% quartile was 0.3-5.4 ng/ml, 
1.2-13.3 ng/ml and 2.2-137.2 ng/ml, respectively [Table 2]. </p>

<p>When comparing the ps-Tg level among the three recurrence 
risk groups, significant differences could be found both using 
the F test (P &lt; 0.001; F = 48.254) and the Kruskal-Wallis </p>

<p>test (P &lt; 0.001;  
2 = 61.388) [Table 2]. Further comparisons 
between groups also revealed a similar trend using both 
the F test (L vs. I, P = 0.014, F = 6.107; H vs. I, P &lt; 0.001, 
F = 24.905; H vs. L, P &lt; 0.001, F = 71.783) and the 
Mann-Whitney U-test (L vs. I, P &lt; 0.001, z = −3.986; H vs. I, 
P &lt; 0.001, z = −7.367; H vs. L, P &lt; 0.001, z = −7.645) [Table 2]. </p>

<p>Receiver operating characteristic analysis of preablative 
stimulated thyroglobulin level </p>

<p>Receiver operating characteristic curves used for evaluating 
the most sensitive and specific ps-Tg values for distinguishing 
each of the two group comparisons are shown in Figure 2. 
The area under the ROC curve for the ps-Tg level used 
for distinguishing the groups was 0.631 (L vs. I), 0.668 
(I vs. H), 0.913 (M0 vs. M1 in the H group) and 0.931 
(M0 vs. M1 in all patients). Two definite cut-off values of 
ps-Tg, namely 2.95 ng/ml and 29.5 ng/ml, were obtained for 
differentiating the L from the I group as well as the I from the H 
group; these values might be used as indicators to distinguish 
each recurrence risk group [Figure 2]. In addition, when only </p>

<p>Table 1: Characteristics of study subjects </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Low risk 
Intermediate risk 
High risk 
Total </p>

<p>Number 
90 
283 
334 
707 
Gender, n (%) 
Male 
19 (21.11) 
94 (33.22) 
112 (33.53) 
225 (31.82) 
Female 
71 (78.89) 
189 (66.78) 
222 (66.47) 
482 (68.18) 
Age 
Mean ± SD (years) 
45.63 ± 12.14 
40.23 ± 11.72 
44.09 ± 13.69 
42.74 ± 12.89 
Histologic subtypes, n (%) 
Papillary 
90 (100) 
277 (97.88) 
318 (95.21) 
685 (96.89) 
Follicular 
0 (0) 
6 (2.12) 
16 (4.79) 
22 (3.11) 
TSH 
Mean ± SD (μIU/ml) 
85.85 ± 28.50 
92.02 ± 35.33 
92.28 ± 37.40 
91.36 ± 35.57 
Surgical methods, n (%) 
Total thyroidectomy + cervical lymph node dissection 
83 (92.22) 
283 (100) 
334 (100) 
700 (99.01) 
Total thyroidectomy only 
7 (7.78) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
7 (0.99) 
n: Number of patients; SD: Standard deviation; TSH: Thyroid stimulating hormone. </p>

<p>Figure 1: Scatter plot of ps-Tg in different groups. (a) Scatter plot of ps-Tg in three recurrence risk groups of low-risk(L), intermediate-risk(I) 
and high-risk(H). (b) Scatter plot of ps-Tg in four groups of L, I, H without distant metastasis(M1) and M1. </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>



<p>comparing patients in the H group, the cut-off ps-Tg value 
in discriminating M1 from M0 was 47.1 ng/ml (sensitivity: 
79.5%; specificity: 88.9%). In addition, when dividing all 
patients into two groups according to whether or not distant 
metastasis was present, the specificity of the cut-off ps-Tg 
value (47.1 ng/ml; sensitivity: 79.5%; specificity: 93.7%) 
became even higher than that in high-risk patients [Figure 2]. </p>

<p>Univariate and multivariate logistic analyses </p>

<p>Gender (female or male), age (&lt;45 years, or ≥45 years), 
tumor size (maximum diameter ≤1 cm or &gt;1 cm), 
multifocality (single lesion or multiple lesions) and ps-Tg 
level (&lt;corresponding cut-off value or ≥corresponding 
cut-off value) were analyzed as independent variables using 
logistic regression analysis. </p>

<p>Table 2: Comparison of ps-Tg and ps-Tg/TSH among different recurrence risk groups </p>

<p>Factors 
Low risk 
Intermediate risk 
High risk 
F test 
Kruskal-Wallis test </p>

<p>F 
χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ps-Tg (ng/ml) 
Mean ± SD 
5.278 ± 8.987 
11.588 ± 23.667 
159.939 ± 293.717 
48.254* 
61.388 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Median 
1.7 
4.4 
14.7 
ps-Tg/TSH (ng/μIU) 
Mean ± SD 
0.061 ± 0.097 
0.171 ± 0.426 
2.423 ± 5.611 
30.582* 
50.010 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Median 
0.022 
0.051 
0.195 
*P&lt;0.001, P values were all &lt;0.05 in further pairwise comparisons of ps-Tg and ps-Tg/TSH values among the three risk groups using the 
F test; 
 † P&lt;0.001, P values were all &lt;0.05 in further pairwise comparisons of ps-Tg and ps-Tg/TSH values among the three risk groups using the 
Mann-Whitney U-test. SD: Standard deviation; ps-Tg: Preablative stimulated thyroglobulin; ps-Tg/TSH: Preablative stimulated thyroglobulin/thyroid 
stimulating hormone. </p>

<p>Figure 2: ROC of serum ps-Tg and ps-Tg/TSH level. (a) ROC in distinguishing low from intermediate recurrence risk groups; (b) ROC in distinguishing 
intermediate from high recurrence risk groups; (c) ROC in distinguishing M1 from M0 in the high recurrence risk group; (d) ROC in distinguishing 
M1 from M0 in all patients. ROC: Receiver operating characteristic curve; AUC: Area under the curve; ps-Tg: Preablative stimulated thyroglobulin; 
ps-Tg/TSH: Preablative stimulated thyroglobulin/thyroid stimulating hormone; M1: Distant metastasis; M0: No distant metastasis. </p>

<p>d 
c </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>

<p>
In univariate logistic regression analysis, the role of 
ps-Tg was significant in distinguishing between I and 
L groups (odds ratio [OR]: 2.757; 95% confidence 
interval [CI]: 1.687-4.506; P &lt; 0.001), as well as between 
H and I groups (OR: 9.490; 95% CI: 5.733-15.707; 
P &lt; 0.001). Even higher OR values could be obtained 
in comparing both the M1 and M0 subgroups in the 
H group (OR: 31.161; 95% CI: 16.805-57.784; P &lt; 0.001) 
and between the M1 and M0 subgroup in all patients 
(OR: 57.916; 95% CI: 33.125-101.260; P &lt; 0.001), which 
further confirmed the high accuracy and predictive value 
of ps-Tg [Table 3]. </p>

<p>In further multivariate logistic regression analyses, except 
for the interference of other factors, ps-Tg was confirmed 
to be an independent prediction factor for differentiating the 
various groups (H vs. I, OR: 8.021, 95% CI: 4.771-13.486, 
P &lt; 0.001; M1 vs. M0 in the H group, OR: 31.977, 95% 
CI: 16.575-61.688, P &lt; 0.001; M1 vs. M0 in all study 
patients, OR: 52.141, 95% CI: 28.581-95.122, P &lt; 0.001). In 
spite of relative low efficacy (area under the curve, 0.631) of 
ps-Tg in discerning the L and I groups using ROC analysis, 
the OR (OR: 2.541, 95% CI: 1.529-4.223, P &lt; 0.001) was 
high enough to validate that ps-Tg could be defined as an 
independent predictive factor [Table 3]. </p>

<p>Analysis of preablative stimulated thyroglobulin thyroid 
stimulating hormone </p>

<p>The parameter Ps-Tg/TSH displayed similar trends to the 
ps-Tg in value comparisons and ROC analysis [Table 2 and 
Figure 2], implying that both the thyroid remnant and TSH 
had little influence on the ps-Tg level in this study. </p>

<p>Patients with distant metastasis </p>

<p>As stated above, the cut-off ps-Tg value of 47.1 ng/ml was 
found to be a good predictive index in discriminating the 
M1 from M0 subgroup. Utilizing this cut-off value, 10.26% 
of patients could be identified before radioiodine treatment 
as M1 patients in this study, without any other evidence of 
distant metastasis; however, they were finally confirmed to 
harbor distant metastases using imaging involving RxWBS 
after radioiodine treatment [Table 4]. Hence, the ps-Tg level 
could be the only evidence available for those patients who 
would benefit from modified high-dose radioiodine treatment 
based upon ongoing preablative reassessment. </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>Previous studies have suggested that the predictive value of 
ps-Tg regarding both the success of ablation and prognosis 
was highly informative. One study showed that the 10-year </p>

<p>Table 3: Logistic regression analysis of recurrence risk and distant metastasis status according to clinicopathologic 
factors </p>

<p>Factors 
Univariate logistic regression 
Multivariate logistic regression </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
P 
OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p>Low risk versus intermediate risk 
ps-Tg* 
2.757 (1.687-4.506) 
&lt;0.001 
2.541 (1.529-4.223) 
&lt;0.001 
Gender 
1.859 (1.058-3.265) 
0.031 
1.587 (0.882-2.853) 
0.123 
Age </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.464 (0.286-0.750) 
0.002 
0.490 (0.297-0.810) 
0.005 
Tumor size </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1.479 (0.916-2.388) 
0.109 
1.210 (0.728-2.011) 
0.461 
Multifocality </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1.073 (0.662-1.740) 
0.776 
1.181 (0.711-1.963) 
0.520 
Intermediate risk versus high risk 
ps-Tg* 
9.490 (5.733-15.707) 
&lt;0.001 
8.021 (4.771-13.486) 
&lt;0.001 
Gender 
1.014 (0.725-1.419) 
0.934 
0.962 (0.654-1.415) 
0.843 
Age </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1.865 (1.347-2.583) 
&lt;0.001 
2.239 (1.546-3.242) 
&lt;0.001 
Tumor size </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>3.141 (2.222-4.440) 
&lt;0.001 
2.620 (1.785-3.846) 
&lt;0.001 
Multifocality </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1.113 (0.808-1.532) 
0.513 
1.156 (0.804-1.661) 
0.434 
M0 versus M1 in high-risk 
ps-Tg* 
31.161 (16.805-57.784) 
&lt;0.001 
31.977 (16.575-61.688) 
&lt;0.001 
Gender 
1.663 (1.039-2.661) 
0.034 
1.667 (0.858-3.237) 
0.131 
Age </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1.162 (0.741-1.822) 
0.513 
1.603 (0.831-3.090) 
0.159 
Tumor size </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>4.677 (2.300-9.510) 
&lt;0.001 
5.225 (2.055-13.281) 
&lt;0.001 
Multifocality </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1.008 (0.641-1.585) 
0.971 
0.777 (0.405-1.492) 
0.449 
M0 versus M1 in all patients 
ps-Tg* 
57.916 (33.125-101.260) 
&lt;0.001 
52.141 (28.581-95.122) 
&lt;0.001 
Gender 
1.623 (1.079-2.442) 
0.020 
1.611 (0.878-2.958) 
0.124 
Age </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1.471 (0.988-2.190) 
0.057 
2.670 (1.441-4.946) 
0.002 
Tumor size </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>8.089 (4.146-15.780) 
&lt;0.001 
6.384 (2.770-14.713) 
&lt;0.001 
Multifocality </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>1.088 (0.730-1.622) 
0.679 
0.886 (0.492-1.596) 
0.687 
*The cut-off values for ps-Tg based status dichotomy were 2.95 ng/ml, 29.5 ng/ml, 47.1 ng/ml and 47.1 ng/ml while distinguishing between low-risk 
and intermediate-risk, intermediate-risk and high-risk, without and with distant metastasis in the high-risk group, and without and with distant 
metastasis in all patients; 
 † The dichotomy values were age 45 years, 1 cm and one lesion for age, tumor size and multifocality, respectively. 
M0: No distant metastasis; M1: Distant metastasis; CI: Confidence interval; OR: Odds ratio; ps-Tg: Preablative stimulated thyroglobulin. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>



<p>disease-free survival rate of DTC patients was 100% when 
the ps-Tg level was &lt;23 ng/ml, and decreased to 68.3% if 
the ps-Tg level exceeded this limit. 
[8] A recent meta-analysis 
implied that ps-Tg testing was a readily available and 
inexpensive tool with a high negative predictive value (NPV) 
regarding future disease-free status. A low ps-Tg level 
could be considered as a favorable prognostic factor for 
patients with DTC. 
[9] Kendler et al. 
[10] reported that the level 
of ps-Tg was the only independent predictor of ablation 
success (P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Recently, considerable attention has been focused on ps-Tg; 
however, this parameter has not been incorporated into 
radioiodine decision-making, partly owing to its insensitivity 
and nonspecificity caused by the probable influence 
of residual thyroid after surgery. 
[11] Some studies have 
utilized ROC curves to evaluate the cut-off value of ps-Tg 
as a predictor of the ablation success rate and prognosis. 
A Korean study reported that a cut-off value for the ps-Tg 
level of 27.5 μg/L was confirmed for predicting disease-free 
remission, with an NPV as high as 98%. 
[23] Another Korean 
study found that the optimal cut-off value regarding the ps-Tg 
level for successful ablation was 10 ng/ml with a sensitivity 
and specificity of 85.7% and 83.6%, respectively. 
[24] In our 
previous studies, we found that ps-Tg might be considered 
as a predictive marker for distant metastasis from DTC; </p>

<p>[25-26] </p>

<p>these two studies mainly focused on the association between 
Tg values and occult distant metastasis. According to the 
above-mentioned findings, and the recently published 
Chinese Management Guidelines for Patients with Thyroid 
Nodules and Differentiated Thyroid Cancer, 
[27] a high 
ps-Tg level was introduced as an important reassessment 
marker and regarded as a high recurrence risk index before 
radioiodine treatment. A high ps-Tg level was recommended 
for high-dose I-131 treatment, although without a definite 
cut-off value. This consideration is superior to the proposal 
that the ps-Tg level is disproportionate to the RxWBS 
findings in high recurrence risk stratum, as stipulated in the 
ATA guidelines and ignoring the predictive value of ps-Tg 
in radioiodine dose decision-making. </p>

<p>[6] </p>

<p>In the present study, we considered ps-Tg as one of the 
ongoing postoperative reassessment factors, correlating 
the ps-Tg level with the newly developed recurrence risk 
staging system, and provided relevant data from Chinese 
patients. Our findings suggested that a higher ps-Tg 
level indicated a more advanced stage of recurrence risk. 
Significant differences in ps-Tg levels have been found both 
among the three recurrence risk groups and between each 
two pairwise groups, indicating a remarkable difference 
in ps-Tg levels in different recurrence risk groups. ROC 
analysis was conducted to define a certain cut-off value 
between each two pairwise groups. Logistic analysis was 
also used to determine the OR values in verifying if ps-Tg 
could be regarded as an independent predictive factor 
regarding the risk of recurrence. Two definite cut-off values 
for ps-Tg level, 2.95 ng/ml and 29.5 ng/ml, were obtained for 
differentiating between the L and I and between the I and H 
groups, respectively; these cut-off values might be candidate 
indicators for different recurrence risk stratifications. In 
addition, in the H group, we found that the ps-Tg cut-off 
value (47.1 ng/ml) had a high sensitivity and specificity in 
distinguishing patients with distant metastasis from those 
with no metastasis. In addition, a high specificity (93.7%) 
and remarkably high OR (42.492) regarding the ps-Tg cut-off 
value (47.1 ng/ml) have been identified while discriminating 
distant metastasis in all patients; this finding might offer a 
specific cut-off value to further determine distant metastasis 
in high-risk patients in the absence of additional preablative 
metastatic evidence. Although the ps-Tg level has shown 
relatively lower accuracy in distinguishing both the L from 
the I and the I from the H groups relative to that achieved 
in differentiating the M1 from M0 subgroup, it still has a 
meaningful predictive value with OR values of 2.712 and 
31.801, respectively. All of these results indicated that 
the ps-Tg level might be an independent postoperative 
assessment factor and provide ongoing serologic evidence 
for the recurrence risk stratification system. </p>

<p>In addition, from our findings, it is noteworthy that ps-Tg 
might be the only indicator available for the identification of 
distant metastases, and thus if measured prior to radioiodine 
therapy would prevent 10.26% of patients with M1 from 
undertreatment. Therefore, the ps-Tg level could be used 
in conjunction with other ATA recurrence risk stratification 
indexes to improve the prediction of recurrence risk and 
dictate the most appropriate therapy. </p>

<p>As it is well-established, TSH can stimulate Tg release 
from the residual thyroid tissue or metastatic carcinoma 
tissue, indicating that Tg release is TSH-dependent. </p>

<p>[20-22] </p>

<p>Consequently, we took TSH as a correction factor, and the 
ps-Tg/TSH parameter was used in the present study to exclude 
the influence of postsurgical residual thyroid tissue. Similar 
results were obtained using ps-Tg/TSH and ps-Tg, both in the 
comparison of different recurrence risk groups and in the ROC 
analyses; this reflected the fact that TSH had no significant 
influence on ps-Tg in the current study and also suggested 
that the patients had undergone complete thyroid resection. </p>

<p>Table 4: Evidence of distant metastasis in patients in 
the M1 subgroup (n = 117) </p>

<p>CT* 
ps-Tg ≥47.1 ng/ml </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>RxWBS* 
Patient number (%) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>(−) 
(+) 
(+) 
12 (10.26) 
(−) 
(−) 
(+) 
7 (5.98) 
(+) 
(+) 
(−) 
5 (4.27) 
(+) 
(−) 
(−) 
4 (3.42) 
(+) 
(+) 
(+) 
83 (70.94) 
(+) 
(−) 
(+) 
6 (5.13) 
*Finding of distant metastatic lesions is defined as (+), and finding of 
no distant metastatic lesions is defined as (−) in the first and the third 
column; 
 † ps-Tg ≥47.1 ng/ml is defined as (+), and ps-Tg &lt;47.1 ng/ml 
is defined as (−) in the second column; 
 ‡ Three patients suffered from 
both pulmonary and bone metastases confirmed by both RxWBS 
and bone scintigraphy. M1: Distant metastasis; CT: Computed 
tomography; RxWBS: Postradioiodine-therapy whole-body scanning; 
ps-Tg: Preablative stimulated thyroglobulin. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>

<p>
A limitation of our study was that the follow-up outcomes 
were not available. Further studies are warranted to 
follow-up patients in the three risk recurrence categories after 
total thyroidectomy and radioiodine treatment. In addition, 
therapy response would need to be evaluated by means of 
physical examination, neck ultrasound scans, imaging and 
Tg serial values. </p>

<p>In summary, the ps-Tg level was found to be related to the 
risk of recurrence, and the corresponding cut-off value was 
obtained for discriminating different risks of recurrence 
with meaningful ORs and relatively high specificity. Ps-Tg 
could be considered as a convenient and reliable ongoing 
marker in indicating different risks of recurrence. It might 
be the only indicator that can be used to identify distant 
metastases, and thus if measured before radioiodine therapy 
would prevent more than 10% of patients with M1 from 
undertreatment. In addition, it could provide incremental 
value for both recurrence risk stratification and radioiodine 
decision-making. </p>

<p>references </p>



<p>Received: 13-12-2014 Edited by: Li-Min Chen 
How to cite this article: Yang X, Liang J, Li TJ, Yang K, Liang DQ, 
Yu Z, Lin YS. Postoperative Stimulated Thyroglobulin Level and 
Recurrence Risk Stratification in Differentiated Thyroid Cancer. Chin 
Med J 2015;128:1058-64. </p>

<p>Source of Support: This study was supported by grants from the National 
Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 30970850) and the Ministry 
of Health Industry Special Scientific Research Project (No. 201202012). 
Conflict of Interest: None declared. </p>

</text></tei>