<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4977069" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Although exergaming has been used as a physical activity modality among various </p>

<p>populations, the evidence regarding its effectiveness on health-related outcomes in overweight/ 
obese individuals remains unclear. The current study systematically reviewed literature and 
summarized findings of exergame-based interventions in overweight/obese populations with the 
goal of clarifying the current perspectives on exergaming and obesity. The initial search yielded 
202 articles from six databases; 12 studies were included after evaluating for inclusion criteria 
and removing duplicates. Among these studies, seven were randomized controlled trials, two 
were control trials, and three were comparison studies. Overall, exergaming has the potential 
to attenuate weight gain and shows promise when used for physical activity and physical fit-
ness promotion. Further, exergame play is positively associated with psychological well-being, 
but its effects on physiological outcomes are inconclusive. Finally, effects of exergaming on 
energy intake are not clear. Existing evidence supports that exergaming may elicit some health 
benefits in people who are overweight or/and obese. The limited number of available random-
ized controlled trials, however, restrict the ability to draw a conclusion that exergaming can 
trigger a change in all health-related outcomes. More research is warranted to make definitive 
conclusions regarding the effects of exergaming on health-related outcomes in such populations. 
Over the past few decades, overweight and obesity have become a global public health 
issue. According to the World Health Organization, worldwide, obesity has more than 
doubled in children and quadrupled in adolescents since 1980. 1 In fact, more than 
one-third of children and adolescents were overweight or obese in 2012, and an esti-
mated 39% (more than 1.9 billion) of adults aged 18 years and over were overweight 
and at least 13% (over 600 million) were obese in 2014. 2 Overweight and obesity are 
operationally defined as ''abnormal or excessive fat accumulations that may impair 
health''. 1 Specifically, overweight refers to having excess body weight for a particular 
height from muscle, fat, bone, water, or a combination of these factors, while obesity 
means having excess body fat. 3,4 In general, overweight and obesity typically result 
from overeating (especially unhealthy diets) and lack of sufficient physical activity, 
which facilitate the development of several comorbidities such as cardiovascular dis-
ease, type 2 diabetes, and various types of cancer. 2,3 
The traditional treatments for overweight and obesity include nutritional education 
such as eating healthy foods and change in lifestyles by increasing physical activity </p>

<p>Correspondence: Zan Gao 
College of education and Human 
Development, School of Kinesiology, 
University of Minnesota, 207 Cooke Hall, 
1900 University Avenue Se, Minneapolis, 
MN 55455, USA 
Tel +1 612 626 4639 
Fax +1 612 626 7700 
email gaoz@umn.edu </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of General Medicine 
4 August 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>276 </p>

<p>Zeng and Gao </p>

<p>and decreasing sedentary behaviors. Among these traditional 
treatments, promoting physical activity is often considered an 
effective avenue in treating overweight and obesity because 
it not only helps manage weight but also produces health 
benefits such as strengthening bones and muscles, promoting 
better sleep, improving mental health and mood, and reducing 
the risk of cardiovascular diseases. 2 As a result, various physi-
cal activities have been introduced and used to help lose and 
maintain weight (eg, running, hiking, swimming, bicycling). 
One of the most popular physical activities is exergaming (aka 
active video games). Exergaming is an emerging technology 
that uses interactive games to increase exercise behavior, 
which requires the players to physically interact with on-
screen avatars through a variety of body movements such as 
jumping, kicking, punching, and ducking while providing 
players the opportunity of being physically active, thereby 
increasing players' physical activity levels and promoting 
their overall health. 5 Given the fact that increased physical 
activity has been proven a viable approach in preventing or 
lessening the risk of overweight and obesity, 2 exergaming 
may represent a good alternative in prompting physical 
activity participation and managing weight. Indeed, the posi-
tive effects of exergaming on health-related outcomes have 
been reported among various populations. 6-8 More recently, 
however, exergaming has received considerable attention 
from researchers as a strategic tool to solve the epidemic of 
childhood obesity within a generation. 
A number of reviews with regard to exergaming have 
been published recently. Yet those systematic reviews 
on exergaming were mainly focused on physical activity 
and health promotion among healthy children and young 
adults. 9-14 However, none of them aimed at the overweight 
or/and obese populations. Without directly observing such 
populations, it is difficult to draw a conclusion concerning 
the effectiveness of exergaming on obesity. In other words, 
all the conclusions from previous reviews only illustrated the 
effects of this physical activity modality on preventing the 
risk of obesity instead of lessening the rate of overweight and 
obesity. To our knowledge, no known systematic review has 
specifically addressed the effects of exergaming on health-
related outcomes among overweight or/and obese individuals. 
Given that exergaming has been prevalent among children 
and adults, it is necessary to synthesize research findings in 
relation to the effects of exergaming among overweight or/ 
and obese populations with the goal of clarifying the current 
perspectives on exergaming and obesity, as well as providing 
meaningful practical implications for future research. There-
fore, the purpose of this study was to systematically review </p>

<p>and synthesize the exergame-based research that targets 
overweight or/and obese individuals as well as to discuss 
the effectiveness of exergaming on health-related outcomes 
in this population. More specifically, this review described 
the benefits of exergame playing for overweight or/and obese 
individuals and ultimately illuminated current perspectives 
on the topic of exergaming and obesity. </p>

<p>Methods 
Study inclusion criteria </p>

<p>To be included in this review, the following inclusion criteria 
were used for each selected study: 1) published in English 
between January 2010 and May 2016 as peer-reviewed 
empirical research, 2) employed the use of at least one 
exergame (eg, Xbox Kinect, Wii, Dance Dance Revolution 
[DDR]), 3) sample comprised overweight/obese individuals, 
and 4) used quantitative measures in the assessment of at least 
one relevant health or behavioral outcome. </p>

<p>Study exclusion criteria </p>

<p>Due to feasibility of conducting such review, studies in 
languages other than English were excluded. Additionally, 
studies were excluded if the participants were underweight 
(body mass index [BMI] ≤18.5 kg /m 2 ), normal weight 
(BMI =18.5-24.9 kg /m 2 ), and with chronic diseases and/ 
or physical impairments (eg, Parkinson's, impaired balance, 
poststroke); if the study looked at only passive exergames; 
if the study involved more than one intervention that may 
have confounded the results (eg, an intervention consisted of 
both exergaming and diet components); and if the outcome 
of interest was measured by qualitative approach. </p>

<p>Search strategy </p>

<p>To ensure inclusion of relevant literature, a comprehensive 
electronic search was conducted. The following databases 
were searched: 1) Academic Search Complete, 2) Com-
munication and Mass Media Complete, 3) ERIC, 4) Psy-
cINFO, 5) SportDiscus, and 6) Medline. Search terms used 
in combination were ("exergam" OR "active video gam*" 
OR "interactive video gam*" OR "wii" OR "Nintendo" OR 
"Xbox Kinect" OR "Playstation") and ("overweight" OR 
"obes*"). Titles and abstracts of potentially relevant studies 
were further screened by two independent reviewers (NZ and 
ZG). Full-text copies of studies satisfying the eligibility crite-
ria were obtained, while relevant studies were further identi-
fied through cross-referencing the bibliographies of selected 
articles. Any discrepancies were discussed and resolved by 
the two reviewers to secure a high agreement for inclusion. </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>277 </p>

<p>exergaming and obesity </p>

<p>Data extraction and analysis </p>

<p>Data extraction was completed by one reviewer (NZ) and 
checked by the other (ZG) for accuracy. One reviewer (NZ) 
independently screened the included articles and extracted 
data including 1) year of publication and country of origin, 
2) methodological details (eg, study design, sample charac-
teristics, exergaming types, outcome measures, and dose of 
exergaming intervention), and 3) key findings with respect 
to the effectiveness of exergaming on prompting health-
related outcomes among overweight or/and obese populations 
(eg, improved functional fitness, decreased BMI, reported 
changes in self-efficacy, heart rate, maximum volume of 
oxygen). The reviewers were not blinded to the journal titles 
and author names when extracting data. </p>

<p>Results 
Study selection </p>

<p>The initial search yielded 202 articles. After removing 
duplicates, titles and abstracts of the remaining papers were 
screened against the inclusion criteria. Following a thorough 
review of the remaining papers, 12 studies were included in </p>

<p>this review (Figure 1). A high inter-rater agreement (ie, 95%) 
was obtained between the researchers for the articles included. </p>

<p>Study characteristics </p>

<p>The characteristics of the included studies are shown in 
Table 1. In general, the US was the primary location for 
exergame-based intervention studies, 15-20 followed by three 
studies conducted in Canada 21-23 and one study each in New 
Zealand, 24 South Africa, 25 and Spain. 26 Among the 12 studies, 
seven were randomized controlled trials (RCTs), 17-21,23,24 two 
were control trials (CTs; quasi-experimental pretest-posttest 
design without randomization), 22,25 and three were one-group 
pretest-posttest design studies (pre-experimental design with 
pretest-posttest among same participants). 15,16,26 Notably, 
all the studies aimed at children and adolescents aged 8-19 
years, indicating the extent to which the prevalence of obe-
sity is currently increasing among youth; thus, childhood 
obesity should be paid substantial attention by researchers 
and policymakers. In addition, relatively large variability 
was seen for sample size across the studies. Specifically, the 
sample size varied from 13 to 332, and intervention length 
ranged from 6 to 24 weeks. With regard to game type, all </p>

<p>Records identified via database searching 
(n=202) 
Identification </p>

<p>Screening </p>

<p>Eligibility </p>

<p>Included </p>

<p>Records after duplicates removed 
(n=184) </p>

<p>Records screened 
(n=184) </p>

<p>Full-text studies evaluated for 
eligibility 
(n=31) </p>

<p>Full-text studies 
excluded with reasons* 
(n=19) </p>

<p>Studies included in systematic review 
(n=12) </p>

<p>Records excluded 
(n=153) </p>

<p>Figure 1 Flow diagram of studies through the review process. 
Notes: *Reasons for study exclusion included ineligible age, ineligible populations, ineligible exergaming types, and ineligible outcomes. Many studies were excluded for 
multiple reasons. </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>278 </p>

<p>Zeng and Gao </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary of exergaming studies </p>

<p>Study description 
Sample and 
design </p>

<p>Types of 
AVGs </p>

<p>Outcomes 
Dose 
Findings </p>

<p>To evaluate the 
physiologic cost, 
relative reinforcing 
value, and liking of 
playing wii versus a 
traditional sedentary 
video game in lean 
and overweight/obese 
children (USA) 15 </p>

<p>Children aged 
8-12 years 
(overweight/obese 
participants, n=11; 
lean participants, 
n=13); comparison 
design </p>

<p>wii Sports 
Boxing 
HR, vO 2 , liking, 
and relative 
reinforcing value </p>

<p>All children completed 
four 10 min activity 
conditions: resting, 
treadmill walking, 
traditional SvG 
play, and physically 
interactive video game 
play </p>

<p>Average HR, vO 2 , and liking were 
significantly greater for Nintendo 
wii than all other conditions. 
Lean children displayed a greater 
peak responding for access to wii 
relative to SvG, while overweight/ 
obese children did not. </p>

<p>To evaluate the 
efficacy and feasibility 
of a multifaceted, 
community-based 
weight intervention 
program for children 
using exergaming 
technology (USA) 16 </p>

<p>40 overweight or 
obese children aged 
8-16 years; pre-
post test </p>

<p>DDR, 
Nintendo 
wii tennis 
and boxing, 
PlayStation 2, 
etc. </p>

<p>BMI, 
psychological 
and behavioral 
outcomes </p>

<p>120 minutes per week 
×10 weeks </p>

<p>The average BMI significantly 
decreased; the average Global 
Self-worth score improved; screen 
time and soda intake reduced; and 
exercise hours per week increased 
after intervention. </p>

<p>To examine whether 
a 20-week exergame 
(ie, videogame that 
requires gross motor 
activity) intervention 
can produce weight 
loss and improve 
psychosocial 
outcomes (USA) 17 </p>

<p>African-American 
adolescents aged 
15-19 years 
(competitive 
exergame, n=19; 
cooperative 
exergame, n=19; 
control, n=16); 
RCT </p>

<p>Nintendo wii weight, peer 
support, self-
efficacy, and 
self-esteem </p>

<p>30-60 minutes per 
school day ×20 weeks </p>

<p>Cooperative exergame players lost 
significantly more weight than the 
control group, which did not lose 
weight. The competitive exergame 
players did not differ significantly 
from the other groups. Self-
efficacy of cooperative exergame 
players also significantly increased 
compared to the control group, 
and peer support also increased 
significantly in both the exergame 
groups compared to the control 
group. 
To examine 
the influence of 
exergaming on 
adolescent girls' body 
composition and 
cardiovascular risk 
factors (USA) 18 </p>

<p>Obese girls aged 
14-18 years (dance 
exergaming group, 
n=21; self-directed 
care control group, 
n=20); RCT </p>

<p>Xbox Kinect 
(<rs type="software">Just Dance</rs> 
and <rs type="software">Dance 
Central</rs>) </p>

<p>Body size and 
composition, 
blood pressure, 
cholesterol, 
triglycerides, 
glucose, and 
insulin </p>

<p>60 minutes per session 
×3 times per week 
×12 weeks </p>

<p>Per protocol (attended &gt;75%), 
abdominal subcutaneous adiposity 
decreased significantly and 
trunk and spine BMD increased 
in the intervention group. Per 
protocol (&gt;2600 steps/session), 
leg percentage of fat decreased 
significantly and abdominal 
subcutaneous and total adiposity 
decreased in the intervention 
group. 
To evaluate the 
effects of exergaming 
on physical activity 
and weight loss in 
overweight and obese 
children (USA) 19 </p>

<p>Overweight and 
obese children 
aged 8-12 years 
(exergame + weight 
management group, 
n=31; weight 
management group, 
n=38); RCT </p>

<p>Xbox Kinect 
(<rs type="software">Kinect 
Adventures</rs> 
and <rs type="software">Kinect 
Sports</rs>) </p>

<p>Physical activity 
levels, percentage 
overweight, and 
BMI </p>

<p>60 minutes per day 
×16 weeks </p>

<p>Participants in the program and 
active gaming group exhibited 
significant increases in moderate-
to-vigorous and vigorous physical 
activity at week 16. In the 
program-only group, a decline or 
no change was observed in the 
moderate-to-vigorous and vigorous 
physical activity. Participants 
in both the groups exhibited 
significant reductions in percentage 
overweight and BMI at week 16. 
However, the program and active 
gaming group exhibited significantly 
greater reductions in percentage 
overweight and BMI. </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>279 </p>

<p>exergaming and obesity </p>

<p>Study description 
Sample and 
design </p>

<p>Types of 
AVGs </p>

<p>Outcomes 
Dose 
Findings </p>

<p>To investigate the 
impact of dance-
based exergaming on 
a diverse sample of 
obese adolescents' 
perceived competence 
to exercise, 
psychological 
adjustment, and BMI 
(USA) 20 </p>

<p>Obese adolescents 
aged 12-18 years 
(exergame group, 
n=20; control 
group, n=20); RCT </p>

<p>DDR 
BMI, 
psychological 
adjustment, 
and perceived 
competence to 
exercise </p>

<p>3 times a week for 40 
minutes in the first 
session and 75 min in 
subsequent sessions 
×10 weeks </p>

<p>Compared with controls, 
participants in the dance-based 
exergaming group exhibited 
significant increase in self-reported 
perceived competence to exercise 
regularly and reported significant 
improvement in relationship with 
parents from baseline to end-of-
treatment. Mothers of adolescents 
in the exergaming group reported 
significant reductions in both 
composite scores of internalizing 
and externalizing symptomatology. 
No pre-post differences in BMI 
were seen within or between 
groups. 
To examine the 
efficacy of interactive 
video game stationary 
cycling in comparison 
with stationary 
cycling to music 
on adherence, 
energy expenditure 
measures, submaximal 
aerobic fitness, 
body composition, 
and cardiovascular 
disease risk markers 
in overweight and 
obese adolescents 
(Canada) 21 </p>

<p>Overweight or 
obese adolescents 
aged 12-17 years 
(interactive video 
game cycling group, 
n=13; stationary 
bike music group, 
n=13); RCT </p>

<p>Sony 
PlayStation 2 </p>

<p>exercise 
adherence, body 
composition, 
aerobic fitness, 
and exercise 
behavior </p>

<p>Twice per week for 60 
minutes per session 
×10 weeks </p>

<p>The music group had a higher 
percentage of attendance. There 
were no significant differences in 
peak HR, peak workload, time 
to exhaustion, body weight, BMI, 
fat mass, fat-free mass, waist 
circumference, and blood work 
parameters. </p>

<p>To examine the 
effects of 1-hour 
AvG play on lean and 
obese adolescents' 
energy expenditure 
(Canada) 22 </p>

<p>Adolescent boys 
aged 12-15 years 
(exergame group, 
n=19 obese; 
control group; 
n=12 lean); CT </p>

<p>XBOX 360 
Kinect Sport 
Boxing </p>

<p>Body weight, 
BMI, BF, ee, HR, 
MeTs </p>

<p>60 minutes 
Body weight, BMI, and body 
fat were significantly higher in 
obese adolescents. Absolute 
EE was significantly higher in 
obese adolescents but not when 
corrected for body composition. 
Maximal HR reached during AvG 
was significantly higher in lean 
adolescents. Time spent between 
three and six MeTs was not 
different between the groups but 
time spent above six MeTs was 
higher in lean adolescents. 
To evaluate the 
effects of stationary 
cycling to music 
versus interactive 
video game cycling 
on psychosocial 
functioning in 
obese adolescents 
(Canada) 23 </p>

<p>Overweight or 
obese adolescents 
aged 12-17 years 
(interactive video 
game cycling group, 
n=13; stationary 
bike music group, 
n=13); RCT </p>

<p>Sony 
PlayStation 2 </p>

<p>Scholastic 
competence, 
social 
competence, 
athletic 
competence, 
body image, self-
esteem, aerobic 
fitness, and body 
composition </p>

<p>Twice per week for 60 
minutes per session 
×10 weeks </p>

<p>Although no differences emerged 
between the exercise groups 
over time, when collapsed across 
exercise modality, significant 
pre-post improvements were 
found for body image, perceived 
scholastic competence, and social 
competence. Changes in aerobic 
fitness, but not body composition, 
were positively associated with 
psychosocial functioning. </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>280 </p>

<p>Zeng and Gao </p>

<p>Study description 
Sample and 
design </p>

<p>Types of 
AVGs </p>

<p>Outcomes 
Dose 
Findings </p>

<p>To evaluate the 
effects of active video 
games over a 6-month 
period on weight, 
body composition, 
physical activity, and 
physical fitness (New 
Zealand) 24 </p>

<p>Overweight and 
obese children 
aged 10-14 years 
(exergame group, 
n=160; control 
group, n=162); 
RCT </p>

<p>Sony 
PlayStation 
eyeToy </p>

<p>BMI, BF, 
physical activity, 
cardiorespiratory 
fitness, video 
game play, and 
food snacking </p>

<p>60 minutes of 
moderate-to-vigorous 
PA on most days of the 
week ×24 weeks </p>

<p>The treatment effect on BMI 
favored the intervention group. 
BMI increased in the control group 
but remained the same in the 
intervention group. There was also 
evidence of a reduction in BF in the 
intervention group. The change in 
daily time spent playing active video 
games at 24 weeks increased in the 
intervention group accompanied by 
a reduction in the change in daily 
time spent playing non-active video 
games. 
To investigate the 
effects of exergaming 
on overweight and 
obese children's 
functional fitness 
(South Africa) 25 </p>

<p>Overweight and 
obese children 
aged 9-12 years 
(exergame group, 
n=11; control 
group A, n=10; 
control group B, 
n=10); CT </p>

<p>Nintendo wii Functional fitness 
(ie, agility, speed, 
balance, reaction 
time, and 
coordination) </p>

<p>3 days per week for 
30 minutes per session 
×6 weeks </p>

<p>The exergame group showed 
significant improvement in 
their level of functional fitness. 
Specifically, coordination, reaction 
time, and speed and agility 
increased by magnitudes of 28%, 
94%, and 37% respectively. </p>

<p>To investigate 
the effects of an 
exergaming platform 
on perceived 
exertion, self-efficacy, 
positive expectations, 
and satisfaction 
in overweight/ 
obese children 
and adolescents 
as compared with 
normal-weight 
children (Spain) 26 </p>

<p>Children and 
adolescents aged 
6-16 years (walking 
on a treadmill 
with the support 
of the videogame 
platform group, 
n=21; walking on 
a treadmill group, 
n=21); comparison 
design </p>

<p>wii Fit 
Satisfaction, self-
efficacy, positive 
expectations, 
RPe, HR, vO 2 , 
MeT </p>

<p>In both the conditions, 
the treadmill program 
was 4 minutes in 
duration at a fixed 
speed of 4.2 km/h, with 
4 additional minutes at 
5.7 km/h (brisk walking 
speed). </p>

<p>The obese children scored 
significantly higher in expectations 
and satisfaction in the exergame 
condition but not in self-efficacy, 
perceived exertion, or physiological 
measures. </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AvG, active video game; BF, body fat; BMD, bone mineral density; BMI, body mass index; CT, control trial; DDR, Dance Dance Revolution; ee, energy 
expenditure; HR, heart rate; MeT, metabolic equivalent task; PA, physical activity; RCT, randomized controlled trial; RPe, rate of perceived exertion; SvG, sedentary 
video game; vO 2 , maximal oxygen consumption. </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>the studies employed commercially available exergames 
including, but not limited to, Nintendo Wii, Xbox Kinect, 
and DDR. </p>

<p>Data synthesis </p>

<p>Studies were grouped depending on if they examined, 1) 
adiposity outcomes (ie, if exergaming was associated with 
decreased BMI, percentage body fat, change in skin fold 
thickness, waist circumference and waist-to-hip ratio, bio-
impedance, body composition), 2) physical outcomes (ie, 
if exergame play promoted skill-related fitness or changed 
habitual physical activity), 3) physiological outcomes (ie, if 
exergaming impacted energy expenditure, heart rate, meta-
bolic equivalent task [MET], blood pressure, cholesterol, tri-
glycerides, glucose, and insulin), 4) psychological outcomes </p>

<p>(ie, if exergaming changed self-efficacy, self-esteem, body 
image, perceived competence, scholastic competence, social 
competence, athletic competence), and 5) energy intake (ie, 
if exergaming changed dietary behavior). </p>

<p>Adiposity outcomes </p>

<p>Seven RCTs and one comparison study examined the rela-
tionship between exergaming and adiposity. The majority 
of the RCTs (n=4) reported that exergaming intervention 
had a positive effect on BMI, body composition, or body 
fat. 17-19,24 In detail, Staiano et al 17 indicated that cooperative 
exergame players lost significantly more weight than the 
control group (participants performed usual daily activi-
ties such as socializing with friends, tutoring, and sports 
team practice), who did not lose weight after a 20-week </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>281 </p>

<p>exergaming and obesity </p>

<p>(30-60 minutes per school day) Nintendo Wii intervention. 
Staiano et al 18 also revealed decreases in leg fat percentage, 
abdominal subcutaneous adiposity, and total adiposity in 
the exergame group after a 12-week (60 minute per session 
×3 times per week) dance-based intervention compared to </p>

<p>a self-directed care control condition. Trost et al 19 suggested 
that participants in a weight management and exergaming 
group exhibited significantly greater reductions in percent-
age overweight and BMI over 16 weeks (60 minute per day), 
although the non-exergame group (weight management 
only) showed a decrease as well. Maddison et al 24 reported 
decrease in body fat in the exergame group after a 24-week, 
60 minutes of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity on 
most days of the week intervention, compared to the control 
group who played normal video games. 
The remaining RCTs (n=3) indicated that exergaming 
did not have a significant effect on adiposity outcomes. 20,21,23 
Specifically, Wagener et al 20 suggested that no pre-post dif-
ferences in BMI were seen after a 10-week (three times per 
week, 40 minutes for the first session and 75 minutes for 
subsequent sessions) DDR intervention in obese adolescents. 
Adamo et al 21 and Goldfield et al 23 found no significant dif-
ferences in body weight, BMI, fat mass, fat-free mass, waist 
circumference, or body composition between children who 
were given exergaming or those who were given a traditional 
exercise (stationary bike) after a 10-week exercise session 
(twice per week and 60 minutes per session). Finally, one 
comparison study 16 reported that children's average BMI 
significantly decreased after 10 weeks (120 minutes per week) 
of exergame-based intervention. </p>

<p>Physical outcomes </p>

<p>This review identified two RCTs and one CT examining the 
effects of exergaming on physical outcomes among over-
weight or/and obese children (eg, habitual physical activity 
and functional fitness). One RCT reported that participants 
in the exergaming group showed significant increases in 
moderate-to-vigorous physical activity at week 16; 19 another 
RCT found an increase in daily time spent playing exer-
gaming at week 24, indicating exergame play may increase 
children's physical activity thereby decreasing sedentary 
behavior. 24 In addition, one CT revealed that children in the 
exergaming group showed significant improvement in their 
levels of functional fitness, including coordination, reaction 
time, speed, and agility after a 6-week (30 minutes ×3 days 
per week) exergame-based intervention in comparison with 
control group (participants played traditional video games 
and continued with their everyday life activities). 25 </p>

<p>Physiological outcomes </p>

<p>Seven studies assessed whether exergaming affects one's physi-
ological health, such as heart rate, maximal oxygen consump-
tion, aerobic fitness, METs, and cardiovascular risk factors. Of 
the four RCTS, three reported that exergaming had no effect on 
physiological outcomes. Specifically, Staiano et al 18 found no 
significant changes in cardiovascular risk variables including 
blood pressure, cholesterol, triglycerides, glucose, and insulin, 
but significant increases in trunk and spine bone mineral den-
sity were seen in overweight and obese girls after intervention. 
Adamo et al 21 reported that there were no significant differences 
in peak heart rate, peak workload, time to exhaustion, and blood 
work parameters, suggesting exergaming may not help obese 
children improve aerobic fitness. Maddison et al 24 revealed that 
cardiovascular fitness (maximal oxygen consumption) changed 
but did not reach statistical significance after exergame play. 
On the other hand, one RCT by Goldfield et al 23 indicated 
that exergaming had a positive effect on aerobic fitness for 
participants in the exergaming group as shown by a significant 
decrease in peak heart rate and rate of perceived exertion after 
a 10-week exergame-based intervention (60 minutes × twice 
per week ×10 weeks) in comparison with stationary cycling to 
music group (non-exergaming group). In addition, one CT 22 
reported that absolute energy expenditure was significantly 
higher in obese children but maximal heart rate was lower in 
comparison with lean participants during exergaming. Nota-
bly, time spent between three and six METs was not different 
between obese and lean groups but time spent above six METs 
was lower in obese adolescents. Finally, a comparison study 15 
displayed that average heart rate and maximal oxygen consump-
tion were significantly greater in Nintendo Wii condition than 
in treadmill walking and traditional sedentary video game; one 
study found no improvements in any physiological measures 
including heart rate, rate of perceived exertion, maximal oxygen 
consumption, and MET. 26 </p>

<p>Psychological outcomes </p>

<p>This review included three RCTs and two comparison studies 
looking at the psychological effects of exergaming. Staiano 
et al 17 reported that self-efficacy of cooperative exergame 
players significantly increased, and both cooperative and 
competitive exergame groups exhibited more peer support 
compared to control group after 20 weeks. Wagener et al 20 
found that self-reported perceived competence to exercise 
regularly significantly increased in participants in dance-based 
exergaming condition. Goldfield et al 23 suggested that sig-
nificant pre-post improvements were found for body image, 
perceived scholastic competence, and social competence </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>282 </p>

<p>Zeng and Gao </p>

<p>after exergame-based intervention. Moreover, a comparison 
study indicated that improvement was seen in global self-
worth, but not in scholastic competence, social acceptance, 
athletic competence, and physical appearance. 16 Another study 
suggested that obese children scored significantly higher in 
expectations and satisfaction in the exergame condition but 
not in self-efficacy and rate of perceived exertion. 26 </p>

<p>energy intake </p>

<p>Three studies investigated energy intake during exergam-
ing. One of the RCTs reported that average self-reported 
daily total energy consumed from snack food decreased in 
the exergaming group (567±684 kcal/day) over a 24-week 
PlayStation EyeToy intervention compared to normal video 
game play control group (708±948 kcal/day), but such change 
was not statistically significant. 24 Another RCT showed no 
dietary changes (ie, overall energy intake or macronutrient 
intake) over the course of exergame-based intervention. 21 
Finally, one comparison study suggested that children's soda 
intake significantly reduced from an average of 4.27 to 2.75 
servings per day, but fast food intake did not change after a 
10-week exergame play (120 minutes per week). 16 </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Given that the worldwide prevalence of obesity has increased 
rapidly over the past decade while exergaming is becoming 
an increasingly popular activity in which both children and 
adults are engaging, it is necessary to review and synthesize 
research findings in relation to exergaming and obesity. 
Therefore, this review synthesized the current evidence 
regarding the effects of exergaming on health-related out-
comes among overweight or/and obese individuals, with 
the goal of stating the current viewpoints on the topic of 
exergaming and obesity as well as providing meaningful 
practical implications for future research. Twelve studies meet 
the basic eligibility criteria and were included for review. 
This systematic review is the first to provide a comprehen-
sive understanding of the influence of exergaming on multiple 
health and behavioral outcomes in overweight or/and obese 
populations. Overall, evidence concerning the effects of exer-
gaming on adiposity outcomes is inconclusive as four RCTs 
indicated positive effects and three RCTs did not. However, 
existing evidence suggests that exergaming has the potential 
to attenuate weight gain for overweight or/and obese children 
and youth. Two RCTs that examined exergaming and physical 
activity levels showed that exergaming may make a significant 
contribution to enable children and youth to meet guidelines 
of 60 minutes of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity on a </p>

<p>daily basis, as well as positively change one's exercise habits 
by increasing daily time spent on physical activity. In other 
words, exergaming shows promise as a tool to motivate and 
engage children and adolescents in physical activity. Also, 
there is evidence suggesting that exergaming can be beneficial 
to improve children's skill-related physical fitness. Nonethe-
less, evidence for exergaming and physiological outcomes is 
unclear as only one out of the four RCTs reported positive 
effects. Although literature demonstrated that exergaming 
alone may not be enough to stimulate physiological changes 
(eg, heart rate, maximal oxygen consumption, blood pressure, 
cholesterol) and reduce the risk of cardiovascular disease, 
exergame play is able to increase trunk and spine bone min-
eral density of overweight and obese girls. Further, all the 
RCTs suggest that exergaming has a positive effect on one's 
psychological outcomes including self-efficacy, body image, 
perceived scholastic competence, and social competence. 
Finally, evidence for energy intake from two RCTs shows 
that exergaming may affect one's dietary behavior, but did 
not reach statistical significance. 
The main strength of this study is the use of high stan-
dards of developing and conducting a systematic review, 
which helps limit potential bias throughout the review. All 
the steps of the review (ie, inclusion criteria, exclusion cri-
teria, and data extraction) were completed in duplicate to 
minimize error; the review focused on multiple health-related 
outcomes with the hope of giving a thorough understanding 
of the relationship between exergaming and health among 
overweight or/and obese populations. Although the current 
study provides the first known synthesis of the effects of 
exergame-based intervention in overweight or/and obese 
children and adolescents in a systematic manner, the study 
is not without limitations. To begin with, the current review 
is limited by the inclusion of only English language publica-
tions and peer-reviewed full-text despite the fact that other 
unpublished and non-English work may be available on the 
topic. Second, most studies had small sample sizes, mak-
ing it difficult to illustrate the true effects of exergaming 
on health-related outcomes, and the relatively low quality 
of studies may limit the generality of findings. Since some 
studies were underpowered, the findings were not statistically 
significant, although many of them displayed a trend toward 
significance. Furthermore, the variety of exergames employed 
in intervention studies limited the ability to discern which 
specific games, and which aspects of those games, are most 
useful for overweight or/and obese individuals. 
Previous literature that aimed at different populations 
showed similar results to ours in that some exergames: 1) can </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>exergaming and obesity </p>

<p>be considered a highly relevant strategic tool for the adoption 
of an active and healthy lifestyle, and may be useful in pre-
venting and lessening the risk of childhood obesity, 27 2) have 
a positive effect on psychological well-being, 28-30 (3) have the 
potential to improve individual functional fitness, 31,32 and (4) 
acutely increase light-to moderate-intensity physical activity 
but are unable to elicit high-intensity physical activity. 33-35 
Therefore, more high-quality RCT should be designed, and 
well-powered studies are warranted to compare exergames 
versus traditional physical activity, as well as contrast different 
types of video game consoles. Future research should aim to 
use larger sample sizes and diverse populations to avoid being 
statistically underpowered. Moreover, multiple follow-up 
measurements over longer time periods are required so the lon-
gitudinal effects of exergaming use can be better understood. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The current review supports that exergaming, as a physical 
activity modality, leads to a more active lifestyle by pro-
moting physical activity, psychological well-being, motor 
competence, energy expenditure, and cardiorespiratory 
fitness and by reducing body fat and sedentary behaviors in 
overweight or/and obese children and youth. Nevertheless, 
the limited number of available RCTs and concerns with 
design quality of other non-RCT studies restrict the ability to 
discern whether, or the circumstances under which, playing 
an exergame results in sustained changes in weight status and 
physiological responses, and for how long the change occurs. 
High-quality research is needed, to determine how different 
exergames may relate to the initiation and maintenance of 
some health benefits and understand the effects of exergaming 
on health-related outcomes, to resolve such discrepancies. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: https://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-general-medicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of General Medicine is an international, 
peer-reviewed open-access journal that focuses on general and internal 
medicine, pathogenesis, epidemiology, diagnosis, monitoring and treat-
ment protocols. The journal is characterized by the rapid reporting of 
reviews, original research and clinical studies across all disease areas. </p>

<p>The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>284 </p>

<p>Zeng and Gao </p>



</text></tei>