<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4094575" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Prostacyclin analogues are standard therapeutic options for vasoconstrictive diseases, 
including pulmonary hypertension and Raynaud's phenomenon. Although effective, these treat-
ment strategies are expensive and have several side effects. To improve drug efficiency, we tested 
liposomal nanoparticles as carrier systems. In this study, we synthesized liposomal nanoparticles 
tailored for the prostacyclin analogue iloprost and evaluated their pharmacologic efficacy on 
mouse intrapulmonary arteries, using a wire myograph. The use of cationic lipids, stearylamine, 
or 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane (DOTAP) in liposomes promoted 
iloprost encapsulation to at least 50%. The addition of cholesterol modestly reduced iloprost 
encapsulation. The liposomal nanoparticle formulations were tested for toxicity and pharma-
cologic efficacy in vivo and ex vivo, respectively. The liposomes did not affect the viability of 
human pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells. Compared with an equivalent concentration of 
free iloprost, four out of the six polymer-coated liposomal formulations exhibited significantly 
enhanced vasodilation of mouse pulmonary arteries. Iloprost that was encapsulated in liposomes 
containing the polymer polyethylene glycol exhibited concentration-dependent relaxation of 
arteries. Strikingly, half the concentration of iloprost in liposomes elicited similar pharmacologic 
efficacy as nonencapsulated iloprost. Cationic liposomes can encapsulate iloprost with high 
efficacy and can serve as potential iloprost carriers to improve its therapeutic efficacy. 
Prostacyclin and its analogues are potent vasorelaxing agents that have been exten-
sively used in the treatment of several diseases, such as pulmonary hypertension 
(PH), peripheral vascular disease, and Raynaud's phenomenon. 
1-4 The first synthetic 
prostacyclin used in the treatment of PH was intravenous epoprostenol. 
5,6 Since then, 
more stable prostacyclin analogues, such as iloprost and treprostinil, have become a 
mainstay in PH treatment. 
1,7,8 However, side effects are also apparent, which include 
flushing, cough, and flu-like symptoms. To improve the pharmacological profile of the 
drug, we investigated the use of liposomal nanoparticles as carrier systems. 
Over the last few years, liposomal nanoparticles have gained increased interest 
as drug delivery systems. Liposomal drug encapsulation can minimize drug-related 
side effects, reduce local irritation, and also increase therapeutic effects via sustained 
release. 
9,10 Modification of the liposome's surface chemistry by the addition of poly-
mers can improve stability. 
11,12 To date, several liposomal drugs have been approved for 
clinical use, including encapsulated doxorubicin and amphotericin B, for the treatment 
of cancer and fungal infections, respectively. 
13-15 Approved intravenous liposomal 
formulations for doxorubicin contain neutral lipids or lipids conjugated to the polymer </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
7 July 2014 </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3250 </p>

<p>Jain et al </p>

<p>polyethylene glycol (PEG), and cholesterol. 
14,16 In contrast, 
liposomal vincristine contains sphingomyelin and choles-
terol as main lipid components. 
17,18 The liposomal vincris-
tine formulation, Marqibo 
® (Talon Therapeutics, Inc, San 
Mateo, CA, USA), was approved for the therapy of leukemia 
only recently. 
17,18 In addition to intravenous application, 
other drug administration routes, including inhalation 
therapy have become the focus of interest for liposomal 
delivery systems. For inhalation purpose, neutral lipids, like 
phosphatidylcholines, and anionic lipids, like phosphatidylg-
lycerols, were used for encapsulation of beclomethasone, </p>

<p>19,20   fasudil, 
21 and vasoactive intestinal peptide (VIP), 
22 respec-
tively. None of these formulations has yet attained clinical 
status; however, many more liposomal formulations are in 
the pipeline. </p>

<p>13   Previously, Kleemann et al described liposomal 
encapsulation of the vasodilator iloprost, using conven-
tional liposomes composed of phosphatidylcholine and 
cholesterol, and also sterically stabilized liposomes, using 
PEG. 
23 However, their study was limited by low encapsula-
tion efficiencies. Here, we investigated the feasibility of 
tailoring liposomal formulations to improve the encapsula-
tion efficiency of iloprost and enhance its pharmacologic 
efficacy. Since iloprost chemically possesses negative 
charge at pH 7.4, we examined the possibility of using 
cationic lipids to promote encapsulation. We developed 
and characterized several novel liposomal formulations 
that were optimized for the delivery of iloprost, and we 
tested their effects on cell viability and their pharmaco-
logic efficacy on mouse intrapulmonary arteries, using a 
wire myograph. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Materials </p>

<p>Lipids, dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine (DPPC), 1-palm-
itoyl-2oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (POPC), 
cholesterol, [methoxy (polyethyleneglycol)-2000]-dipalmi-
toyl-phosphatidylethanolamine (DPPE-PEG 2000 ), and 1,2-di-
(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane 
(DOTAP), were purchased from Avanti Polar Lipids (Ala-
baster, AL, USA). Stearylamine (SA) was purchased from 
Sigma-Aldrich Corp (St Louis, MO, USA). Polyvinylpyr-
rolidone (PVP) was a kind gift from BASF (Ludwigshafen, 
Germany). U-46619 was purchased from Enzo Life sciences 
(Farmingdale, NY, USA) and dissolved in 99% dimethylsul-
foxide (DMSO). Anhydrous iloprost was a generous gift from 
Bayer AG (Leverkusen, Germany). Iloprost was prepared as 
a stock solution of 500 µg/mL in chloroform:methanol (C/M) 
2:1, volume/volume (v/v). </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Preparation of liposomes </p>

<p>Liposomes were prepared by the thin film rehydration meth-
od. 
24 Briefly, anhydrous iloprost (50 µg), lipids (6 mg), and, if 
appropriate, PVP were dissolved in C/M and mixed. Organic 
solvents were then evaporated under inert nitrogen to form a 
lipid film. The lipid film was rehydrated with 1 mL 10 mM Tris/ 
HCl, 154 mM sodium chloride pH 7 at room temperature (RT), 
with repeated vortexing, for 1 hour, and this was followed by six 
freeze and thaw cycles. Liposomes were then extruded through 
Whatman 200 nm polycarbonate filters (Avanti Polar Lipids) 
using an Avanti 
® Mini-Extruder (Avanti Polar Lipids). </p>

<p>separation of nonencapsulated iloprost 
from liposomes </p>

<p>Nonencapsulated iloprost was separated from liposomes by 
centrifugation, for 10 minutes at 4,000× g, using an Amicon </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>Ultra-4 centrifugal filter unit with Ultracel 100 membrane 
UFC810096 (Merck KGaA, Darmstadt Germany). Iloprost-
loaded liposomes were retained in the upper compartment. 
Nonencapsulated iloprost was absorbed by the cellulose 
membrane of the filter device and was eluted with 70% 
ethanol. The filter was washed twice with rehydration buffer, 
and then the liposomes were overlaid with argon and stored 
at 4°C until further analysis. </p>

<p>Determination of encapsulation efficiency 
of iloprost in liposomes </p>

<p>We developed a simple and rapid chromatographic method to 
estimate iloprost encapsulation in the liposomes. The amount 
of iloprost in the liposomes was determined by semiquantitative 
thin-layer chromatography (TLC). Iloprost-loaded liposomes 
were first subjected to phospholipid Folch extraction. </p>

<p>25   Briefly, the lipids were extracted in C/M 2:1 (v/v) using 
20 times the liposome. For phase separation, 0.2 volumes of 
0.034% magnesium chloride were added. The mixture was 
centrifuged at 1125× g for 5 minutes at RT. The lower organic 
phase, containing lipids and iloprost, was subjected to evapora-
tion under inert nitrogen, to obtain dried lipid extracts. The lipids 
were resolved in small quantities of C/M (2:1 v/v) and applied to 
a precoated silica TLC plate (TLC Silica Gel 60; Merck KGaA). 
The mobile phase consisted of chloroform:methanol:ammonia 
(65:35:1.5, v/v/v). For visualization of the lipid bands, the dry 
plate was dipped in 20% copper sulfate solution containing 9% 
phosphoric acid, and heated at 190°C. Iloprost was applied as a 
reference. Liquid chromatography tandem mass spectroscopy 
(LC-MS/MS) (4000 QTRAP </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, AB SCIEX, Framingham, MA, 
USA) was used for accurate quantification of iloprost (range 
of detection 5 ng -5 µg). </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3251 </p>

<p>encapsulated iloprost exhibits enhanced vasodilation </p>

<p>liposome particle size </p>

<p>Average particle size and polydispersity index (PDI) were 
measured by photon correlation spectroscopy, using a Zeta-
sizer 3000HS (Malvern Instruments, Malvern, UK). Empty 
and iloprost-loaded liposomes were measured after dilution 
to a lipid concentration of 0.03 mg/mL with ultrapure water. 
Particle size was analyzed by calculating the auto correla-
tion function of the detected intensity. The PDI value of 
liposome preparations was obtained from the width of the 
size distribution. </p>

<p>liposome zeta (ζ) potential </p>

<p>The ζ-potential was determined by laser doppler electro-
phoresis using a Zetasizer Nano ZS ZEN3600 (Malvern 
Instruments). All measurements were performed at RT, using 
samples diluted to a lipid concentration of 0.3 mg/mL with 
Tris/HCl buffer (10 mM Tris/Cl, pH 7.0, 2 mM CsCl), and 
were carried out in triplicates of at least ten runs. </p>

<p>Negative staining transmission electron microscopy </p>

<p>Next, 4.5 µL of pure (empty) and iloprost-loaded liposomes 
(0.6 mg/mL) were placed on carbon-coated copper grids. 
After a 1-minute incubation, the excess sample was blot-
ted off and replaced by the staining reagent (1% aqueous 
uranyl acetate). This treatment was repeated twice, each 
with 30 seconds incubation times. Samples were visual-
ized using an FEI Tecnai 
® G 
2 20 Transmission Electron 
Microscope (FEI Co, Hillsboro, OR, USA) at 120 kV as 
acceleration voltage, with the help of a Gatan Ultrascan </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>1000 CCD camera (Gatan, Inc., Pleasanton, CA, USA) at 
2 k×2 k resolution. </p>

<p>Freeze-fracture transmission electron microscopy </p>

<p>Pure and iloprost-loaded liposomes (6 mg/mL) were mixed 
with 30% glycerol and were frozen in liquid propane. 
Samples were fractured in a Balzers BAF 400D freeze-
fracture apparatus (Oerlikon Balzers Coating AG, Balzers, 
Liechtenstein) at pressures around 1.3×10 
-5 Pa, and replicas 
were made. The replicas were cleaned by introducing them 
into a 12% sodium hypochlorite solution for approximately 
3 hours, with further overnight storage in 50% NaOH. The 
replicas were then washed three times with double-distilled 
water before loading them on uncoated copper grids. The 
samples were visualized as previously described in the 
last section. </p>

<p>cell viability </p>

<p>Human pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells (hPASMCs) 
were isolated from pulmonary arteries from nontransplanted </p>

<p>donor lungs, as previously described elsewhere. 
26 A549 cells 
were purchased from Cell Lines Service, Eppelheim, 
Germany. The effect of liposomes on cell viability was 
evaluated using an MTS assay, according to the manufac-
turer's instructions (CellTiter 96 
® Aqueous One Solution 
Cell Proliferation Assay; Promega Corp, Fitchburg, WI, 
USA). A549 cells were cultured in Gibco 
® Dulbecco's 
Modified Eagle's Medium Nutrient Mixture F-12 (DMEM/ 
F12) medium (Life Technologies Corp, Carlsbad, CA, USA) 
containing glutamine and 10% fetal calf serum (A549), 
and hPASMC were cultured in VascuLife 
® SMC medium 
(Lifeline Cell Technology, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and seeded 
on 96-well plates, at a density of 4×10 
4 cells (hPASMC) and 
2×10 
4 cells (A549), respectively, per well. The cells were 
incubated with either 0.2 µM or 1 µM of free or liposomal 
iloprost, respectively, for 24 hours. Control liposomes 
(with lipid concentration of 6 mg/mL) were added at the 
same dilution factor as their respective liposomes. Sodium 
dodecyl sulfate, at 0.1% and 0.5% weight/volume, was 
used as a positive control for the hPASMC and A549 cells, 
respectively. Postincubation, MTS/phenazine methosulfate 
was added with further incubation for 2 hours. Absorbance 
of the produced formazan was recorded at 490 nm, using 
a 96-well plate reader (GloMax 
® -Multi Detection System; 
Promega Corp). </p>

<p>Isolation of tertiary pulmonary arteries </p>

<p>BALB/c mice (male or female), 20-25 weeks old, were used 
in the study. The mice were preanesthetized with isoflurane 
and euthanized with an intraperitoneal injection of ketamine 
(500 mg/kg) and xylazine (70 mg/kg), according to the European 
guidelines 2010/63/EU. The heart and lungs were removed 
and the tertiary intrapulmonary arteries isolated with help of 
a stereo zoom microscope SZX7 (Olympus Corp, Tokyo, 
Japan) (Figure S1). The arteries were cleaned of surrounding 
adipose and connective tissue and cut into segments 3-4 mm in 
length, for use in isometric tension measurements (myograph 
studies). All tissues were preserved in an ice-cold physi-
ologic salt solution of 140.5 mM NaCl, 5.5 mM KCl, 1.5 mM 
CaCl 2 , 1 mM MgCl 2 , 10 mM glucose, 0.5 mM Na 2 HPO 4 , 
0.5 mM KH 2 PO 4 , and 10 mM HEPES (4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-
1-piperazineethanesulfonic acid) solution pH 7.4, throughout 
the dissection procedure. </p>

<p>Isometric tension measurements 
in pulmonary arteries </p>

<p>The pulmonary arteries were positioned between jaws with 
the help of tungsten wires, in myograph chambers (Multi 
Wire Myograph System-620M; Danish MyoTechnology A/S, </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Jain et al </p>

<p>Aarhus, Denmark) containing physio logic salt solution and 
continuously aerated with 21% O 2 , 5% CO 2 , and balanced 
N 2 , at 37°C. The myograph chambers were connected to force 
transducers for isometric measurements (PowerLab 
® 8/35; 
ADInstruments, Dunedin, New Zealand). The pulmonary arter-
ies were incubated at 37°C, and a basal tension of 2 mN was 
applied. The arteries were allowed to stabilize for 45 minutes. 
Physiologic salt solution containing 120 mM KCl was used to 
determine viability and adequate contractility of the tissues. 
The arteries were stimulated three times, using 120 mM KCl to 
obtain reproducible contractions. Arteries that did not respond 
to these repeated stimuli were not included in the study. </p>

<p>Preparation of iloprost for wire myograph </p>

<p>Iloprost dissolved in C/M was dried by evaporation and 
dissolved in 96% ethanol, and diluted 1:1000 with physi-
ologic salt solution. The final concentration of ethanol was 
0.096 vol%. </p>

<p>Iloprost-induced relaxation of preconstricted 
pulmonary arteries </p>

<p>Initially, a concentration-response curve for mouse pulmo-
nary arteries was established by adding cumulative doses 
of the thromboxane analogue, U-46619 (0.001-3 µM). For 
subsequent experiments, the arteries were contracted with 
the half-maximal effective concentration (EC 50 ), 0.03 µM, 
of U-46619. Following stable contraction (~30 minutes 
postaddition of U-46619), the arteries were challenged with 
one concentration of free iloprost (1 µM, 3 µM, 10 µM, and 
30 µM), liposomal iloprost, or control (empty) liposomal for-
mulations, as indicated. The control liposomes were added to 
give the same final lipid concentration as their corresponding 
encapsulated formulation. In a subset of experiments, sodium 
nitroprusside (10 µM) was added 60 minutes post-iloprost 
addition to confirm vessel relaxation viability. </p>

<p>rNa isolation and real-time polymerase chain 
reaction (Pcr) measurements </p>

<p>Total RNA was isolated, using the RNeasy Mini kit 
(Peqlab, Erlangen, Germany), from the mouse pulmo-
nary arterial sections. Total RNA was reverse transcribed 
using the iScript 
™ cDNA Synthesis kit for RT-qPCR 
(Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA), according to 
manufacturer's instructions. Real-time PCR was performed 
using a LightCycler 
® 480 System (F. Hoffman-La Roche, 
Basel, Switzerland). The PCR reactions were set up using 
a QuantiFast 
® SYBR 
® Green PCR kit (Qiagen, Venlo, 
the Netherlands). The cycling conditions were as follows: </p>

<p>5 minutes at 95°C, (5 seconds at 95°C, 5 seconds at 60°C, 
and 10 seconds at 72°C) ×45. Due to the nonselective double-
strand DNA binding of the SYBR 
® Green I dye, melting 
curve analysis and gel electrophoresis were performed to 
confirm the specific amplification of the expected PCR 
product. PBGD and B2M were used as the reference genes. 
The difference in threshold cycle (Ct) values for each target 
gene were calculated as </p>

<p>ΔCt = Ct reference gene -Ct target gene. 
(1) </p>

<p>The primer sequences were as follows (5′-3′) EP1 GAA 
CCT CAG TCC TTG GCG GG, CAC CCC ATG CAT GTC 
TGC TC; EP2, ATA CTT AGG CCA CCG GTC CT, GGC 
ACT GGA CTG GGT AGA AC; EP3, ATT GCA GTT CGC 
CTG GCT TC, TTC AGG TTG TTC ATC ATC TGG C; 
EP4, CAC ACC GGG CTC CTA ACC C, GTT GAC TCC 
GGG GAT GGA CA; IP, CTA TCT TGG GGA ACT GCG 
CT, AAG CAT GCC TGT GAA GTC CT; TP, GAC TGC 
GAG GTG GAG ATG ATG, AGG TGG TGT CTG CAA 
CAA AGT; PBGD, GGT ACA AGG CTT TCA GCA TCG 
C; ATG TCC GGT AAC GGC GGC; B2M. CGG CCT GTA 
TGC TAT CCA GAA AAC C, TGT GAG GCG GGT GGA 
ACT GTG. The amplicons for all prostacyclin receptors were 
between 107-111 bp. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>Results were expressed as mean ± standard error of the mean 
(SEM), and n indicated the number of arteries. The concen-
tration curve for U-46619 was expressed as percentages of 
contraction relative to 120 mM KCl. Relaxation values were 
expressed as the percentage change from the U-46619-induced 
contraction. To obtain relaxation values for the encapsulated 
formulations, the relaxation values of empty liposomes were 
subtracted from the respective liposomal iloprost formulation. 
Multigroup comparisons were performed with a one-way 
analysis of variance (ANOVA), with either Tukey's or Dun-
nett's (for comparisons to a control group) post hoc test, as 
appropriate. Comparison between two groups was performed 
with a Student's t-test. <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc</rs>, La Jolla, CA, USA) was used. Values of P0.05 were 
considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
Encapsulation efficiency of iloprost 
in liposomal nanoparticles </p>

<p>We first developed a semiquantitative method for the rapid 
and easy determination of iloprost concentration using TLC </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3253 </p>

<p>encapsulated iloprost exhibits enhanced vasodilation </p>

<p>(Figure 1A). Nonencapsulated iloprost was removed from 
liposomal formulations via adherence to cellulose membranes 
(Figure 1B). Comparison of the encapsulation efficiency 
derived by TLC to that determined by mass spectroscopy 
revealed similar encapsulation rates (Figure 1C). 
Initially, we prepared conventional liposomes composed 
of DPPC and cholesterol. Hydration of the lipid film with 
10 µg/mL aqueous iloprost (Ventavis </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>; Bayer AG) resulted 
in a very low encapsulation efficiency of ~4% (data not 
shown). In order to improve encapsulation, we incorporated 
anhydrous iloprost into the lipid film during liposome prepa-
ration process. We used 10 mol% SA as the lipid component; 
the polymers PEG 2000 and PVP (liposomal formulations 
LI-1 and LI-2, respectively) were also included to impart 
stability. These modifications resulted in an encapsulation 
efficiency 60%. The inclusion of cholesterol in the lipid 
bilayer reduced the encapsulation to ~48% (LI-3) and ~53% </p>

<p>(LI-5). Replacement of SA with the cationic lipid DOTAP 
(LI-4 and LI-6) did not further improve encapsulation effi-
ciency (Table 1). 
The six individual formulations were then characterized 
for particle size, PDI, and ζ-potential. Table 1 depicts the 
characteristics of the pure and iloprost-loaded liposomes. 
All liposomal formulations were 168-178 nm postextru-
sion; the incorporation of iloprost did not affect liposome 
size. Following separation of the encapsulated and non-
encapsulated drug, no changes in size or aggregation were 
observed (data not shown). All formulations exhibited a 
PDI between 0.05 and 0.15, suggesting a homogeneous 
size distribution. Characterization of the liposomes' surface 
charge (ζ-potential) revealed that liposomes containing the 
polymer PVP showed the highest ζ-potential (35-40 mV), 
while liposomes containing the polymer PEG possessed 
lower ζ-potential (8-12 mV). The morphology of one </p>

<p>Figure 1 representative Tlc for detection of iloprost. (A) Detection limit for iloprost on TLC, after derivatization with copper sulfate, followed by quantification of the area 
occupied by the band. (B) evaluation of iloprost (2 µg) encapsulation into liposomes by Tlc; nonencapsulated iloprost was removed via absorption by a cellulose membrane. 
lane 1= iloprost reference (2 µg); lane 2= encapsulated iloprost; and lane 3= nonencapsulated iloprost eluted from the cellulose membrane. Iloprost bands on Tlc are 
indicated by arrows. (C) comparison of encapsulation of iloprost in liposomes via semiquantitative Tlc and Ms. 
Abbreviations: Ms, mass spectroscopy; NS, not significant; TLC, thin-layer chromatography. </p>

<p>0.25 0.5 1 
2 
4 
Iloprost (µg) </p>

<p>Iloprost </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>% iloprost encapsulation </p>

<p>Iloprost µg 
Peak area (au) </p>

<p>12,000 </p>

<p>9,000 </p>

<p>6,000 </p>

<p>3,000 </p>

<p>0 
0.25 0.5 1 
2 
4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>TLC </p>

<p>0 
MS </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>Table 1 characterization of pure (control) liposomal formulations (-iloprost) and iloprost-loaded liposomes (+ iloprost) </p>

<p>Liposome 
formulation </p>

<p>Composition (molar ratios) 
Iloprost 
Encapsulation 
efficiency (%) </p>

<p>Size 
(nm) </p>

<p>Polydispersity 
index </p>

<p>Zeta potential 
(mV) </p>

<p>lI-1 
POPc:sa:DPPe-Peg 2000 (87:10:3) 
-
+ </p>

<p>-
64.7±4.4 </p>

<p>168.9±6.1 
168±1.6 </p>

<p>0.12±0.02 
0.1±0.0 </p>

<p>10.9±0.2 
12.8±0.2 
lI-2 
POPc:sa:PVP (87:10:3) 
-
+ </p>

<p>-
59.6±3.3 </p>

<p>171.7±3.3 
169±3.6 </p>

<p>0.11±0.01 
0.1±0.0 </p>

<p>35.6±0.2 
36.2±0.4 
lI-3 
POPc:sa:DPPe-Peg 2000 :cholesterol 
(75.6:8.7:2.5:13) </p>

<p>-
+ </p>

<p>-
47.7±4.3 </p>

<p>174±6.9 
173.2±4.1 </p>

<p>0.07±0.0 
0.08±0.01 </p>

<p>11.4±0.3 
8.8±0.1 
lI-4 
POPc:DOTaP:DPPe-Peg 2000 
(87:10:3) </p>

<p>-
+ </p>

<p>-
66.2±6.4 </p>

<p>167.7±4 
167.8±2.7 </p>

<p>0.12±0.02 
0.1±0.01 </p>

<p>8.3±0.7 
9.6±0.0 
lI-5 
POPc:sa:PVP:cholesterol 
(73.2:8.5:2.5:15.6) </p>

<p>-
+ </p>

<p>-
53.2±7.7 </p>

<p>176.9±3.6 
178.3±4.4 </p>

<p>0.05±0.0 
0.09±0.01 </p>

<p>33.9±0.8 
38.6±0.2 
lI-6 
POPc:DOTaP:PVP (87:10:3) 
-
+ </p>

<p>-
60.6±5.7 </p>

<p>173.8±8 
175±7.5 </p>

<p>0.05±0.01 
0.09±0.01 </p>

<p>37.1±1 
33.5±1.3 </p>

<p>Note: Data represent mean ± seM. 
Abbreviations: DOTaP, 1,2-di-(9Z-octadecenoyl)-3-trimethylammonium-propane; DPPe-Peg 2000 , [methoxy (polyethyleneglycol)-2000]-dipalmitoyl-phosphatidylethano-
lamine; POPc,1-palmitoyl-2oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine; PVP, polyvinylpyrrolidone; sa, stearylamine; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3254 </p>

<p>Jain et al </p>

<p>Figure 2 Transmission electron micrographs of two liposomal formulations, lI-4 and lI-6, using negative staining (A) and freeze fracture (B) of iloprost-loaded liposomes 
(left panels) and pure (empty) liposomes (right panels). 
Note: Magnification is ×19,000. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>LI-4 </p>

<p>LI-6 </p>

<p>LI-4 </p>

<p>LI-6 </p>

<p>100 nm 
100 nm 
100 nm 
100 nm </p>

<p>100 nm 
100 nm 
100 nm 
100 nm </p>

<p>Figure 3 Viability studies of liposomes containing (A) 0.2 µM or (B) 1 µM iloprost, on the viability of human pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells for 24 hours, n=3. 
Notes: Data represent mean ± SEM. One-way ANOVA, followed by Dunnett's multiple comparison test, was performed to calculate statistical significance. 
Abbreviations: ANOVA, analysis of variance; NS, not significant; SDS, sodium dodecyl sulfate; SEM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>% viability (compared 
with control) </p>

<p>% viability (compared 
with control) </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Liposomal formulations (LI-) 
Liposomal formulations (LI-) </p>

<p>1 2 
3 
4 
5 6 </p>

<p>− + − + − + − + − + − + </p>

<p>1 2 
3 
4 
5 6 </p>

<p>− + − + − + − + − + − + 
Iloprost 
I loprost 
S D S 
c o n t r o l 
i l o p r o s t </p>

<p>S D S 
c o n t r o l 
i l o p r o s t </p>

<p>NS 
NS </p>

<p>PEG (LI-6)-and one PVP (LI-4)-containing liposome, 
respectively, was then studied using transmission electron 
microscopy. Negative staining revealed that the liposomes 
possessed almost spherical particles Figure 2A. The average 
size of the liposomal nanoparticles was found to be between 
100 and 200 nm. The freeze-fracture image clearly depicted 
that all liposomes exhibited a spherical shape without show-
ing any tendency for aggregation (Figure 2B). After 2 months 
of storage at 4°C, iloprost encapsulation was similar to that 
observed of freshly prepared liposomes (Figure S2). Taken 
together, six different liposomal formulations that encapsu-
lated large amounts of iloprost, at a drug to lipid molar ratio 
of 0.01, were successfully developed. </p>

<p>cell viability </p>

<p>The effect of the liposomal formulation on cell viability was 
determined by an MTS assay. Primary hPASMCs and the 
human alveolar epithelial cell line, A549, were treated with 
liposomal iloprost (0.2 µM or 1 µM iloprost concentration). 
None of the formulations exhibited any adverse effects on 
hPASMC (Figure 3) or A549 cell (data not shown) viability 
after 24 hours of incubation. </p>

<p>effect of iloprost on vasorelaxation 
of mouse pulmonary arteries </p>

<p>Pharmacological testing of encapsulated iloprost and free 
iloprost was determined by measuring changes in the </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3255 </p>

<p>encapsulated iloprost exhibits enhanced vasodilation </p>

<p>vascular tone of mouse intrapulmonary arteries, using a 
wire myograph. Cumulative concentrations of the throm-
boxane analogue, U-46619 (0.01-3 µM), produced a 
concentration-dependent contraction (Figure 4A). The 
EC 50 of U-46619 was determined to be 0.03 µM. At this 
concentration, a stable constriction was maintained for up to 
2 hours (Figure S3A). For all subsequent experiments, this 
EC 50 dose of U-46619 was used to precontract the arteries. 
Following precontraction, addition of iloprost produced a 
rapid and sustained vasodilation (Figure S3B). The viability 
and smooth muscle induced relaxation was confirmed by 
the addition of the nitric oxide donor sodium nitroprusside 
(Figure S3B). Upon noncumulative applications, iloprost 
exhibited a nonlinear concentration-dependent relaxation 
(Figure 4B). Maximal relaxation was observed with 10 µM 
of iloprost, with no further increase at higher concentrations. 
Therefore, we chose half of this concentration (5 µM) for 
all further experiments. Together, these results confirm the 
validity of the test system and that iloprost acted as a potent 
vasodilator on mouse pulmonary arteries. 
As the binding of iloprost to different prostanoid receptors 
produces different vasoactive effects, we next investigated 
the expression levels of the prostanoid receptors in isolated 
mouse pulmonary arteries, using real-time PCR. The highest 
expression was observed for the EP1 together with the TP 
receptor, followed by the IP receptor. The complete expres-
sion levels were as follows EP1 = TP  IP  EP4 = EP3  
EP2 (Figure 4C). 
To compare the pharmacologic efficacy of free and encap-
sulated iloprost, mouse pulmonary arteries were initially 
preconstricted with 0.03 µM U-46619 and treated with either 
free or encapsulated iloprost. Free iloprost exhibited 16% </p>

<p>maximal relaxation within 18 minutes, which was maintained 
for 1 hour. The pure liposomes (without iloprost) produced a 
slight vasorelaxation after 20 minutes (Figure S4). Liposomal 
iloprost formulations LI-1 and LI-2 exhibited a nonsignifi-
cant increase in vasodilation (~25%) as compared with free 
iloprost (Figure 5A, B, and G). Integration of cholesterol 
(LI-3 and LI-5) or DOTAP (LI-4 and LI-6) in the liposomal 
formulations significantly enhanced the maximum vasodila-
tion by up to ~29% (Figure 5C-G). No significant differences 
in time to maximal relaxation were observed (Figure 5H). 
The same relaxation curve of free iloprost is depicted in all 
figures, to enable direct comparison between free iloprost 
and encapsulated iloprost (Figure 5A-F). </p>

<p>concentration dependency </p>

<p>We then selected one formulation that demonstrated an 
enhanced effect, for further analysis. At 1 µM, both free 
and encapsulated iloprost (LI-4) produced similar levels of 
relaxation (Figure 6A). At 2.5 µM and 5 µM, encapsulated 
iloprost significantly increased the maximal relaxation when 
compared with free iloprost (Figure 6B and C). In order to 
provide direct comparison between the effects of different 
iloprost and LI-4 doses, the data from Figure 5D is presented 
again in Figure 6C. Strikingly, liposomal iloprost required 
half the concentration of iloprost to achieve similar levels of 
vasodilation as 5 µM free iloprost. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The rationale for this study was to create liposomal nanoparti-
cles tailored for the prostacyclin analogue iloprost and to deter-
mine their pharmacologic efficacy ex vivo. Previous reports 
have described very low (~4%) encapsulation efficiencies of </p>

<p>Figure 4 (A) concentration-dependent contraction of mouse intrapulmonary arteries in response to U-46619 compared with 120 mM potassium chloride, n=8. 
(B) Iloprost induced maximum relaxation upon contraction with half-maximal effective concentration 0.03 µM of U-46619 on mouse intrapulmonary arteries, n=5-7. 
(C) real-time Pcr analysis of prostanoid receptor expression in isolated mouse pulmonary arteries. 
Notes: (B) Data represent mean ± seM, ***P0.001 compared with 10 µM iloprost; </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>P0.01, </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>P0.001 compared with 30 µM iloprost. One-way aNOVa, followed by 
Tukey's multiple comparison test, was performed to calculate statistical significance. (C) lines indicate median. 
Abbreviations: aNOVa, analysis of variance; ec 50 , half-maximal concentration; Pcr, polymerase chain reaction; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>% contraction to 120 mM K+ 
% max relaxation </p>

<p>∆Ct </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
1 
3 
10 
30 
0.0001 0.001 
0 .01 
0 .1 
1 
1 0 </p>

<p>U-46619 (µM) 
Iloprost (µM) 
Prostanoid receptor </p>

<p>EP1 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>−8 </p>

<p>−6 </p>

<p>−4 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>EP2 
EP3 
EP4 
IP 
TP </p>

<p>EC 50 : 0.03 µM </p>

<p>*** ## </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3256 </p>

<p>Jain et al </p>

<p>Figure 6 Direct comparison of the relaxation kinetics of lI-4 compared with free iloprost on U-46619 preconstricted mouse pulmonary arteries. (A) 1 µM iloprost, 
(B) 2.5 µM iloprost, and (C) 5 µM iloprost. 
Notes: Data represent mean ± seM. *P0.05, ***P0.001. Unpaired t-test was used to calculate statistical significance. 
Abbreviations: NS, not significant; SEM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>LI-4 (n=10) 
Iloprost (n=7) </p>

<p>LI-4 (n=8) 
Free iloprost (n=8) </p>

<p>LI-4 (n=10) 
Iloprost (n=7) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 
20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>0 
40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>% relaxation </p>

<p>% relaxation </p>

<p>% max relaxation 
% max relaxation </p>

<p>% max relaxation </p>

<p>% relaxation </p>

<p>Time (minute) </p>

<p>Time (minute) </p>

<p>Time (minute) </p>

<p>Iloprost 
Ll-4 
I loprost </p>

<p>Iloprost </p>

<p>Ll-4 </p>

<p>Ll-4 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>1 µM </p>

<p>5 µM </p>

<p>2.5 µM </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>1 µM 
2.5 µM </p>

<p>5 µM </p>

<p>Figure 5 relaxation kinetics of free and different encapsulated iloprost (5 µM) formulations on isolated mouse pulmonary arteries, following U-46619 preconstriction. 
(A) lI-1, (B) lI-2, (C) lI-3, (D) lI-4, (E) lI-5, (F) lI-6 (black symbols) compared with free iloprost (grey symbols). (G) Percentage change from U-46619 induced contraction. 
(H) Time to maximum relaxation. 
Notes: For easy comparison, the same relaxation curve of free iloprost is depicted in all figures. Data represent mean ± seM. **P0.01. One-way aNOVa with Dunnett's 
multiple comparison test was used to determine degree of significance between the free and encapsulated iloprost. 
Abbreviations: ANOVA, analysis of variance; NS, not significant; SEM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>LI-1 
LI-2 
LI-3 </p>

<p>Time (minute) 
Time (minute) 
Time (minute) </p>

<p>40 
0 10 20 30 40 50 60 
0 10 20 30 40 50 60 
0 10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>% relaxation </p>

<p>LI-1 (n=8) 
Iloprost (n=8) </p>

<p>LI-2 (n=7) 
Iloprost (n=8) </p>

<p>LI-3 (n=7) 
Iloprost (n=8) </p>

<p>% relaxation 
% relaxation </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>LI-4 </p>

<p>Time (minute) </p>

<p>40 
0 10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>LI-4 (n=8) 
Iloprost (n=8) </p>

<p>% relaxation </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>LI-5 
LI-6 </p>

<p>Time (minute) 
Time (minute) </p>

<p>40 
0 10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 
0 10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>LI-5 (n=8) 
Iloprost (n=8) 
LI-6 (n=7) 
Iloprost (n=8) </p>

<p>% relaxation 
% relaxation </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>% max relaxation </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>NS NS ** ** ** ** </p>

<p>I lo 
p r o s t L I -1 L I -2 L I -3 L I -4 L I -5 L I -6 </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Time to max relaxation </p>

<p>(minute) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>I lo 
p r o s t L I -1 L I -2 L I -3 L I -4 L I -5 L I -6 </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3257 </p>

<p>encapsulated iloprost exhibits enhanced vasodilation </p>

<p>iloprost. 
23 This low encapsulation may be a limiting step for 
the creation of novel therapeutic strategies. Here we have 
developed several different liposomal formulations that 
exhibited very high encapsulation efficiencies (50%-65%) 
(Table 1). Our data indicate that cationic excipients are 
prerequisite for successful and efficient iloprost encapsula-
tion. Four of six iloprost-liposomal formulations exhibited 
enhanced relaxation efficacy of preconstricted mouse intra-
pulmonary arteries. 
To date, the use of cationic liposomes has been mostly 
limited to the encapsulation of negatively charged nucleic 
acids or oligonucleotides molecules for gene delivery. 
Recently Bai et al used cationic liposomes to encapsulate 
low-molecular weight heparin at higher efficiencies 
27 than 
that reported for neutral liposomes. 
28 We here used SA and 
the cationic phospholipid DOTAP as the positively charged 
constituents in our formulations. Differences in the liposome 
surface charge (ζ-potential) were dependent on the presence 
of PVP (LI-2, -5, and -6) or PEG (LI-1, -3, and -4), with 
PVP-liposomes possessing higher ζ-potential (Table 1). 
Liposomes containing SA or DOTAP exhibited similar 
ζ-potential. The higher ζ-potential in the PVP-liposomes 
presumably originates from the nitrogen-bearing pyrrolidone 
ring in PVP. The lower ζ-potential of the PEG liposomes 
(LI-1, -3, and -4) may be due to charge neutralization by the 
ethoxylate chain present in DPPE-PEG 2000 . 
The presence of charged lipids presumably increases the 
electrostatic interaction between negatively charged iloprost 
and the liposome, thereby promoting drug encapsulation. 
Furthermore, the encapsulation efficiency for iloprost was 
greatly affected by the choice of phospholipid. Saturated 
phospholipids, like DPPC, form densely packed bilayer 
structures, which mean very limited void volumes between 
the acyl chains. In contrast, unsaturated phospholipids, such 
as POPC, possess higher void volumes and could therefore 
intercalate more amphiphilic drug within the bilayer, and 
therefore, could be beneficial for iloprost encapsulation. Cho-
lesterol has been reported to induce a conformational change 
in the lipid bilayer, imparting cohesive strength to the bilayer 
and reducing leakiness from liposomes. 
29 Furthermore, cho-
lesterol can increase liposome membrane rigidity and may 
improve stability in vitro and in vivo. 
30 The incorporation of 
cholesterol (~15 mole %) in two of our SA-containing formu-
lations resulted in reduced iloprost encapsulation. This result 
leads us to speculate that a part of iloprost is preferentially 
intercalated within the liposome bilayer and to propose that 
the cholesterol in LI-3 and LI-5 may have acted as a bilayer 
stiffener, which reduced iloprost capture. </p>

<p>To further promote liposome stability, we modified 
the surface of liposomes by integrating polymers (PVP) or 
polymer-conjugated phospholipids (DPPE-PEG 2000 ). The 
presence of DPPE-PEG 2000 has been described to provide an 
external shield, thereby promoting steric stabilization. 
29 PVP 
has been used to coat liposomes and has been reported as an 
effective steric protector for liposomes in vivo. 
31-33 Incorpora-
tion of PVP within a DPPC lipid film promotes interaction 
with the DPPC acyl chains and consequently, liposome 
incorporation. 
34 Therefore, we speculate that a similar 
interaction occurred, with POPC integrating PVP within our 
liposomes. Thus, the chosen polymers may help to maintain 
the structural conformation of liposomal nanoparticles and 
may improve stability. 
At both lower and higher iloprost concentrations (0.2 µM 
and 1 µM iloprost), the liposomal formulations exhibited no 
adverse effects on cell viability (Figure 3). This is in line with 
previous study, which reported that instillation of cationic 
liposomes loaded with low molecular weight heparin did not 
significantly elevate lung injury markers. </p>

<p>27   Due to the difficulty in obtaining human material, we 
analyzed the pharmacologic efficacy of the liposomal for-
mulations on mouse pulmonary arteries. The thromboxane 
analogue U-46619 was chosen as the preconstrictor since 
elevated levels of thromboxane have been reported in PH 
patients. 
35 At 10 and 30 µM concentration, iloprost produced 
similar relaxation kinetics, which indicates ~10 µM as the 
maximal effective concentration; therefore, experiments 
directly comparing free and encapsulated iloprost were 
performed at 5 µM. The iloprost-induced relaxation of pre-
constricted arteries (maximum 40%) can be attributable to 
several factors: in mice and humans, iloprost preferentially 
binds the IP receptor, thereby evoking vasodilation, but also 
possesses high affinity for the vasoconstrictive EP1 and 
EP3 receptors. 
36-38 In murine pulmonary arteries, we observed 
highest expression of the EP1 receptor, followed by IP then 
EP3 (Figure 4). It is possible that human pulmonary arter-
ies may have different expression levels of these receptors, 
which may alter the response to iloprost. Our expression data, 
together with the receptor binding affinity of iloprost, indi-
cates that the strong vasodilative response induced by IP is 
attenuated by activation of the EP1 and/or EP3 receptors. 
One of our major findings was that the pharmacologic 
efficacy of 5 µM free iloprost was equipotent to half the 
concentration of liposomal encapsulated iloprost (2.5 µM) 
(Figure 6). Studies from Woo et al demonstrated that liposomal 
encapsulation of deguelin enhanced the antitumor efficacy by 
reducing the required dose from 4 mg/kg to 0.4 mg/kg and </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Jain et al </p>

<p>thus, may prevent potential side effects. 
39 The exact mecha-
nism whereby liposomal iloprost possesses higher activity is 
currently unclear; however, this may arise from a combination 
of factors, like shielding the drug from degradation, docking of 
liposomes to the pulmonary artery, or presentation of iloprost 
in an orientation that facilitates IP receptor binding. Based 
on our findings, we propose that liposomal iloprost formula-
tions can enhance the pharmacologic efficacy of iloprost and 
therefore, may reduce the therapeutic dose. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Cationic lipids in liposomes promote the encapsulation of 
the prostacyclin analogue iloprost. Iloprost-loaded cationic 
liposomes show enhanced vasodilation in comparison with 
free iloprost. This improved pharmacologic efficacy could 
be interesting with respect to minimizing the associated 
manufacturing costs and may be advantageous in terms of 
systemic side effects. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Gebhard Schratter for excellent technical assis-
tance, and Elisabeth Bock and Elisabeth Pritz for their 
excellent technical assistance with the electron microscopy. 
We also thank Akos Heinemann for the scientific review and 
Harald Köfeler, Astrid Knopf, and Birgit Reiter of the Core 
Facility for Mass Spectrometry, Centre for Medical Research, 
Medical University of Graz, for the iloprost quantification. 
The study was funded by the Ludwig Boltzmann Institute 
for Lung Vascular Research, Graz, Austria. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3259 </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3260 </p>

<p>Jain et al </p>

<p>Figure S1 steps involved in the preparation of mouse intrapulmonary arteries. 
Notes: (A) heart and lungs were removed en bloc. (B) removal of the adipose tissue surrounding aorta (arrow). (C) cutting the aorta exposed the pulmonary artery 
(arrow). (D) removal of lung parenchyma exposed further bifurcations (arrow). (E) Further removal of the lung parenchyma freed the pulmonary artery (arrow). (F) Fully 
exposed pulmonary arteries (arrow). </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E 
F </p>

<p>Figure S2 effects of storage on iloprost encapsulation. liposomes were stored for 2 months at 4°c and encapsulation was then analyzed by thin layer chromatography. 
(A) lI-1 and (B) lI-2. 
Notes: Band for 2 µg iloprost applied as reference (R), bands for liposomal encapsulated iloprost (L), fractions of the obtained flow through (filtrates) containing no iloprost 
from amicon 
® filter unit (Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany) (F1, F2), bands of nonencapsulated iloprost (N) eluted from the filter unit via an ethanol wash. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Months 
Months </p>

<p>R 
R </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>L 
L </p>

<p>LI-1 
LI-2 </p>

<p>F1 
F2 
N 
N </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure S3 representative real-time curve, from isometric tension measurements using a wire myograph. 
Notes: (A) Duration of vasoconstriction following 0.03 µM U-46619-induced vasoconstriction. (B) Vasorelaxation induced by addition of free iloprost (5 µM) and the nitric 
oxide donor, sodium nitroprusside (10 µM), on U-46619-induced preconstricted mouse pulmonary arteries. </p>

<p>Time (minute) 
Time (minute) </p>

<p>Force (mN) 
Force (mN) </p>

<p>0 
2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>2 
0 
3 0 
6 0 
9 0 
120 
120 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>30 
60 
90 </p>

<p>U-46619 
U-46619 
Iloprost </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Sodium nitroprusside </p>

<p>Supplementary materials </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nanomedicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nanomedicine is an international, peer-
reviewed journal focusing on the application of nanotechnology 
in diagnostics, therapeutics, and drug delivery systems throughout 
the biomedical field. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, CAS, SciSearch®, Current Contents®/Clinical Medicine, </p>

<p>Journal Citation Reports/Science Edition, EMBase, Scopus and the 
Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>3261 </p>

<p>encapsulated iloprost exhibits enhanced vasodilation </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>LI-1 (n=8) 
Empty (n=5) </p>

<p>Time (minutes) 
% max relaxation </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 
50 60 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>LI-2 (n=7) 
Empty (n=4) </p>

<p>Time (minutes) 
% max relaxation </p>

<p>0 
10 20 30 40 50 
60 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>LI-3 (n=7) 
Empty (n=4) </p>

<p>Time (minutes) 
% max relaxation </p>

<p>0 10 
20 30 40 50 
60 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>LI-4 (n=8) 
Empty (n=5) </p>

<p>Time (minutes) 
% max relaxation </p>

<p>0 
10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>LI-5 (n=8) 
Empty (n=5) </p>

<p>Time (minutes) 
% max relaxation </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>LI-6 (n=7) 
Empty (n=5) </p>

<p>Time (minutes) 
% max relaxation </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>Figure S4 relaxation kinetics of liposomes (empty) and encapsulated iloprost (5 µM iloprost) on isolated mouse pulmonary arteries, following U-46619 preconstriction. 
(A) lI-1, (B) lI-2, (C) lI-3, (D) lI-4, (E) lI-5, and (F) lI-6. 
Notes: relaxation values obtained by empty liposomes were subtracted from the respective liposomal iloprost formulation to determine the relative relaxation for each 
formulation. Data represent mean ± seM. 
Abbreviation: seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

</text></tei>