<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4615111" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Preserving the integrity of the genome and preventing cell 
division in the presence of DNA damage are critical tasks for 
cell and organism survival. Consequently, eukaryotic cells pos-
sess complex networks for surveillance of DNA integrity, 
checkpoint activation, and DNA repair. Upon a DNA damage 
insult the DDR kinases ATM, ATR and DNA-PK are acti-
vated. Early on, the downstream activated effector kinases 
MK2, Chk1 and Chk2 mediate a checkpoint response that 
converges in inactivation of Cdc25s, which results in persistent 
inhibitory phosphorylation of Cdks. 
1-3 In addition, the DDR 
kinases target p53 and Mdm2, resulting in the activation of a 
p53-dependent transcriptional program including the upregu-
lation of the Cdk inhibitor p21 and the p53-dependent </p>

<p>transcriptional repression of cell cycle-promoting factors. </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>Together these pathways enforce a checkpoint that allows time 
for repair and eventual reentry into the cell cycle. However, 
not all cells recover from a DNA damage arrest, but instead 
terminally exit the cell cycle. 
Terminal cell cycle exit is presumably a mean to prevent prop-
agation of mutations when damage cannot be repaired. In G2 
phase it strictly depends on p53-and p21-dependent APC/C </p>

<p>Cdh1 </p>

<p>activation and subsequent degradation of cell cycle proteins. </p>

<p>6-11 </p>

<p>A key target for APC/C 
Cdh1 is Cyclin B1, which in complex with 
Cdk1 acts as a master regulator of mitotic entry in an unper-
turbed cell cycle. 
12,13 Indeed, we have previously found that 
upon DNA damage the levels of Cyclin B1 function as a marker 
for whether G2 cells are still competent to resume cell division. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Interestingly, in cancer cell lines with compromised p21 function </p>

<p>© Erik M€ ullers, Helena Silva Cascales, Himjyot Jaiswal, Adrian T Saurin, and Arne Lindqvist 
*Correspondence to: Arne Lindqvist; Email: arne.lindqvist@ki.se 
Submitted: 05/27/2014; Accepted: 06/09/2014 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4161/15384101.2015.945831 </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The 
moral rights of the named author(s) have been asserted. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
2733 
Cell Cycle </p>

<p>Cell Cycle 13:17, 2733--2743; September 1, 2014; Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC </p>

<p>REPORT </p>

<p>APC/C-dependent degradation pathways are activated, but cells 
avoid degradation of Cyclin B1 as well as other mitotic proteins 
and do not terminally exit the cell cycle. </p>

<p>9,15 </p>

<p>Traditionally, DNA damage checkpoint activation and DNA 
repair were seen as a molecular cascade directly activated down-
stream of the recognition of DNA damage. Recently however, a 
growing number of studies indicate that DNA-damage signaling 
and checkpoint activation have more integrated roles that rely not 
only on the type of damage, but also on the region in the genome </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>and the cell cycle phase 
17 when the damage occurs. However, the 
timing and coordination of the checkpoint response and terminal 
cell cycle exit could not be conclusively addressed, as available 
studies depend largely on population averages and cell synchroni-
zation. How single cells decide between checkpoint recovery and 
terminal cell cycle exit remains currently unclear. 
We have set up a system that allows us to study Cyclin B1 
dynamics in single untransformed cells and to assess the resulting 
cell fate decisions during a DNA damage checkpoint response. 
We find that terminal cell cycle exit is temporally decoupled 
from the DNA damage insult in a manner that depends on the 
cell cycle position. Moreover, we find that nuclear translocation 
of Cyclin B1 marks a restriction point for terminal cell cycle exit. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Gene-targeted Cyclin B1 as a novel setup to study the DNA-
damage checkpoint response 
We wanted to set up a system to study permanent cell cycle exit 
in individual untransformed cells. We first analyzed an ongoing 
DNA-damage checkpoint response in hTERT-immortalized RPE 
cells and compared it to transformed U2OS cells. When continu-
ously exposed to low concentration of the topoisomerase II-inhibi-
tor Etoposide, U2OS cells retain expression of G2 specific markers, 
with the exception of Plk1. 
15 In contrast, RPE cells lose the expres-
sion of Cyclin A2, Cyclin B1, Plk1, Cdk1, and Cdk2, all key regu-
lators of S and G2 phase, indicating a cell cycle exit (Fig. 1A). 
6 We 
next established a U2OS 
18 and an RPE (Fig. S1A) cell line encod-
ing a Cyclin B1-eYFP fusion protein at the endogenous CCNB1 
locus, which allowed us to directly monitor Cyclin B1 protein 
dynamics in single live cells. We have previously shown that expres-
sion levels of Cyclin B1, a key regulator of mitotic entry, correlate 
closely with the competence to recover from a DNA damage check-
point. 
14 Furthermore, the decrease in Cyclin B1 levels after DNA 
damage correlates with cellular senescence. </p>

<p>19,20 </p>

<p>We monitored Cyclin B1-eYFP levels using time-lapse 
microscopy (Fig. 1B) and quantified the total fluorescence of 
multiple positions after careful subtraction of background fluo-
rescence (materials and methods), allowing a time-resolved read-
out of Cyclin B1-eYFP levels in a population. At the same time, 
we monitored a checkpoint arrest by scoring whether cells could 
enter mitosis. We find that Cyclin B1-eYFP levels increase over a 
range of Etoposide and NCS concentrations in U2OS cells 
(Fig. 1C and E). In fact, the increase in Cyclin B1-eYFP levels is 
more pronounced at Etoposide and NCS concentrations that 
block mitotic entry. In accordance, FACS analysis shows an </p>

<p>accumulation of 4n U2OS cells containing high levels of Cyclin 
B1 (Fig. 1G). Thus, U2OS cells block in G2 phase without 
impairing the ability to retain Cyclin B1. 
In contrast, Cyclin B1-eYFP levels start decreasing in RPE 
cells 3 to 4 hours after addition of Etoposide or NCS at concen-
trations where there is an apparent cell cycle arrest (Fig. 1D 
and F). The loss of Cyclin B1 does not depend on checkpoint 
slippage or an enforced G1/S checkpoint, as a large proportion of 
the Cyclin B1 eYFP-negative cells contain 4n DNA content 
(Fig. 1G). This shows that there is a correlation between a cell 
cycle block and the loss of Cyclin B1 in RPE cells. </p>

<p>Cyclin B1 is degraded in a p21-, p53-and APC/C </p>

<p>Cdh1 </p>

<p>-
dependent manner 
It has been reported that Cyclin B1 is actively degraded in an 
APC/C 
Cdh1 -dependent manner in untransformed cells after 
DNA damage. 
6,21 While Cyclin B1 and other APC/C 
Cdh1 targets 
are also regulated at the mRNA level late after DNA damage, 
timely destruction relies on APC/C 
Cdh1 -dependent degrada-
tion. 
6,19 In line, we find that addition of the proteasome inhibi-
tor MG-132 leads to sustained Cyclin B1-eYFP presence in RPE 
cells, whereas it has no effect on U2OS cells (Fig. 2A). Moreover, 
siRNA-mediated depletion of Cdh1, but not of Cdc20, NIPA, 
or b-TrCP, stabilized Cyclin B1-eYFP after Etoposide addition 
in a similar way as the APC/C inhibitor proTAME (Fig. 2B and 
C). This indicates that in RPE cells APC/C 
Cdh1 targets Cyclin 
B1-eYFP for degradation after DNA damage. 
APC/C 
Cdh1 activation during DNA damage was suggested to 
depend on p53 and p21. 
6,9,11 Indeed, siRNA-mediated depletion 
of p53 or p21 led to sustained Cyclin B1-eYFP levels (Fig. 2D). 
Thus, our live-cell setup recapitulates that Cyclin B1-eYFP is 
degraded in a p53-, p21-, and APC/C </p>

<p>Cdh1 </p>

<p>-dependent manner in 
RPE cells apparent 3 to 4 hours after induction of DNA damage. </p>

<p>Cyclin B1 degradation requires nuclear translocation 
Cyclin B1 is predominantly cytoplasmic in interphase, but 
can translocate to the nucleus upon p21 induction, although the 
relevance of this translocation remains unclear. 
7 When we fol-
lowed the levels of Cyclin B1-eYFP in U2OS and RPE cells we 
observed obvious differences in the intracellular localization. 
Whereas Cyclin B1-eYFP stays almost exclusively cytoplasmic in 
U2OS cells, the majority of RPE cells translocate Cyclin B1-
eYFP to the cell nucleus 1 to 2 hours before degradation com-
mences (Fig. 3A and B). In fact, we found that nuclear transloca-
tion of Cyclin B1-eYFP in RPE cells appeared to be highly 
predictive for the initiation of Cyclin B1-eYFP degradation 
(Fig. 3C). Nuclear translocation of Cyclin B1-eYFP is not depen-
dent on active APC/C 
Cdh1 , as addition of MG-132, proTAME, 
or depletion of Cdh1 rather increased the amount of cells with 
nuclear Cyclin B1-eYFP. However, siRNA-mediated knockdown 
of p53 or p21 abolished both nuclear translocation and degrada-
tion of Cyclin B1-eYFP (Fig. 3D). This suggests that although 
controlled by the same pathways, nuclear translocation of Cyclin 
B1 is independent of its degradation. </p>

<p>2734 
Volume 13 Issue 17 
Cell Cycle </p>

<p>As APC/C 
Cdh1 is predominantly active in the nucleus in G1 
phase in an unperturbed cell cycle, 
22 we reasoned that the 
observed nuclear translocation of Cyclin B1 in RPE cells during 
a DDR might be required for APC/C </p>

<p>Cdh1 </p>

<p>-mediated ubiquitina-
tion. Indeed, we find that addition of the Exportin 1 inhibitor 
LMB to Etoposide-treated U2OS cells leads to nuclear accumula-
tion of Cyclin B1-eYFP and subsequent degradation in more 
than half of the cells (Fig. 3E, G and H). Interestingly, addition </p>

<p>of LMB also induced mitotic entry in a subset of cells (Fig. 3F 
and H). However, in a small fraction of RPE cells Cyclin B1-
eYFP degradation occurred without an apparent nuclear translo-
cation (Fig. 3C), indicating either that ubiquitination and degra-
dation can also occur in the cytoplasm, or that nuclear 
translocation is rate-limiting in some cells. We therefore added 
Importazole, an inhibitor of Importin b to Etoposide-treated 
cells. 
23 Addition of Importazole effectively blocked nuclear </p>

<p>Figure 1. Gene-targeted Cyclin B1 as a novel setup to study checkpoint recovery competence. (A) U2OS or RPE cells were treated with 1 or 5 mM Etopo-
side for the indicated time periods and subjected to immunoblotting with the indicated antibodies. (C) Untreated control. (B) Representative images of 
U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP and RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cell populations during ongoing Etoposide treatment. Scale bar: 50 mm. (C-F) Equal amounts of U2OS 
Cyclin B1-eYFP cells (C and E) and RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells (D and F) were treated with Etoposide (C and D) or NCS (E and F) at time point 0, and fol-
lowed by time-lapse microscopy. Average Cyclin B1-eYFP signal was quantified and passage through mitosis was determined. (G) U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP 
and RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells were treated with 1 mM Etoposide for 5, 10 or 15 h, and subsequently cellular DNA content and eYFP positivity were 
assessed by flow cytometry. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
 
Cell Cycle </p>

<p>translocation, indicating that Cyclin B1 translocation during a 
DDR depends on active transport by Importin b (Fig. 3I). Strik-
ingly, when tracking single cells most cells did not show signs of 
Cyclin B1-eYFP degradation and only one cell lost Cyclin B1-
eYFP during the time-course of the experiment (Fig. 3I and J). 
This indicates that nuclear import is crucial for effective Cyclin 
B1 degradation after DNA-damage checkpoint activation. </p>

<p>Cyclin B1 nuclear translocation marks the restriction point 
for terminal cell cycle exit 
DNA damage-dependent activation of APC/C 
Cdh1 was shown 
to promote permanent cell cycle exit in untransformed cells. </p>

<p>6-9 </p>

<p>Similarly, Kikuchi and colleagues found that the loss of Cyclin 
B1 after DNA damage is associated with a concurrent increase in 
cellular senescence. 
19 In line with these findings, we never 
observed a single cell that regained expression of Cyclin B1-eYFP 
once having degraded it. Furthermore, we never detected recur-
rence of Cyclin B1-eYFP expression or mitosis when following 
cells for up to 5 d after damage (Fig. 4A). Moreover, whereas the 
G2 population of U2OS cells retains both Cyclin B1-eYFP and 
checkpoint recovery competence, RPE cells lose Cyclin B1-eYFP 
over time and do not enter mitosis after combined treatment 
with the checkpoint kinase inhibitors KU60019 and UCN-01 
once Cyclin B1-eYFP is degraded (Fig. 4B). Taken together, this </p>

<p>shows that RPE cells have lost the competence to resume cell 
division after APC/C 
Cdh1 activation. 
To assess when single cells become determined to perma-
nently exit the cell cycle we monitored live cells and blocked 
ATM and ATR kinase activity by addition of caffeine at different 
time points after Etoposide addition. Addition of caffeine shortly 
after damage stimulated mitotic entry and sustained Cyclin B1-
eYFP expression over time. In contrast, caffeine had limited effect 
on both Cyclin B1-eYFP levels and forced mitotic entry when 
added 6 hours after Etoposide (Fig. 4C and D). When analyzing 
single cells we found that addition of caffeine 1 hour after Etopo-
side had a dramatic effect on both mitotic entry and timing of 
Cyclin B1-eYFP degradation, showing that ATM/ATR activity 
initiates these events (Fig. 4E). However, when added 4 or 
6 hours after Etoposide, at a time when nuclear translocation of 
Cyclin B1-eYFP had occurred in most cells, forced mitotic entry 
was only apparent in cells where no signs of nuclear translocation 
or degradation of Cyclin B1-eYFP were present (Fig. 4E and F). 
Moreover, we never observed mitotic entry for cells that had 
already translocated Cyclin B1-eYFP to the nucleus at the time 
of caffeine addition (Fig. 4G). 
Thus, although DNA damage-dependent cell cycle exit 
requires APC/C 
Cdh1 activation, it is only ATM/ATR-dependent 
until nuclear translocation of Cyclin B1. Therefore, Cyclin B1 
nuclear translocation marks the restriction point for losing </p>

<p>Figure 2. Degradation of Cyclin B1 during ongoing DNA damage is p53-, p21-and APC/C </p>

<p>Cdh1 </p>

<p>-dependent. (A) Time-lapse microscopy quantification of 
populations of RPE and U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP cells. Cells were treated with 1 mM Etoposide from time point '¡1 h'. At 0 h cells were treated with MG-
132 (inhibitor of the proteasome) or mock treated. (B-D) Time-lapse microscopy quantifications of RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells in different conditions. Cells 
were transfected with the indicated siRNA 48 h and 24 h prior to Etoposide addition. Etoposide was added at a concentration of 1 mM at the '¡1 h' 
time point. At 0 h cells were treated with MG-132, proTAME, or DMSO as indicated. The error bars represent standard error of the mean signal of at least 
8 positions. </p>

<p> 
Volume 13 Issue 17 
Cell Cycle </p>

<p>Figure 3. Nuclear translocation is required for Cyclin B1 degradation. (A) Representative images of RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP and U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP cells 
during ongoing Etoposide treatment. Scale bar: 20 mm. (B) RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells were treated with 1 mM Etoposide and the time between Cyclin B1-
eYFP nuclear translocation and onset of degradation was determined for 67 individual cells. The average time  § standard deviation is indicated. (C) RPE 
Cyclin B1-eYFP cells were treated with 1 mM Etoposide, and Cyclin B1-eYFP nuclear translocation and degradation was assessed for 85 individual cells. 
(D) RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells were transfected with siRNA 48 h and 24 h prior to Etoposide addition, or treated with MG-132 or proTAME as indicated. 
Intracellular localization of Cyclin B1-eYFP was assessed in single cells at different time points after treatment with 1 mM Etoposide ('¡1 h' time point). 
Inhibitors were added at the '0 h' time point. (E) Representative images of U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP cells treated as indicated. Scale bar: 20 mm. (F) Mitotic 
entry was assessed for Cyclin B1-eYFP-positive cells treated as in (E). Data are mean and standard deviation of 3 independent experiments. (G) Time-
lapse quantification of cells treated as in (E). The error bars represent standard error of the mean signal of at least 8 positions. (H) The time point of 
nuclear translocation and the onset of degradation of Cyclin B1-eYFP were determined in single U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP cells. Each line represents a single 
cell. Inhibitors were added 1 h after Etoposide treatment. (I) Representative images of RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells treated with 1 mM Etoposide from time 
point '¡1 h'. After 1 h cells were treated as indicated. Scale bar: 20 mm. (J) The time point of nuclear translocation and the onset of degradation of Cyclin 
B1-eYFP were determined in single RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells. Each line represents a single cell. Inhibitors were added 1 h after Etoposide treatment. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>
checkpoint recovery competence and for subsequent APC/C 
Cdh1 -
dependent permanent cell cycle exit in G2 phase. </p>

<p>APC/C 
Cdh1 activation is temporally decoupled from 
checkpoint activation 
Although the DDR is activated within minutes in all cells, we 
observed large differences between the times of onset of Cyclin 
B1-eYFP nuclear translocation and degradation in individual 
cells, suggesting that Cyclin B1 degradation may depend on the 
cell cycle phase (Fig. 5A). As Cyclin B1-eYFP levels are a direct 
readout of cell cycle progression, we grew cells on fibronectin-</p>

<p>coated micropatterns, which enabled us to accurately quantify 
fluorescence in single U2OS or RPE cells over long periods of 
time. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Whereas on Western blot, U2OS cells reach a steady state of 
Cyclin B1 after DNA damage, Cyclin B1-eYFP levels vary dra-
matically over time in individual cells (Fig. 5B and C). In fact, a 
majority of U2OS cells continuously increase Cyclin B1-eYFP to 
protein levels that are higher compared to what is observed dur-
ing unperturbed growth. Similar to U2OS cells, no RPE cell sus-
tains a steady-state of Cyclin B1-eYFP over time (Fig. 5C). After 
an initial increase, RPE cells degrade Cyclin B1-eYFP over a 
15-hour time-period. Interestingly, the time point of degradation </p>

<p>Figure 4. Single RPE cells are not able to recover after Cyclin B1 nuclear translocation. (A) Representative montage of an RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cell growing 
on a fibronectin-coated micropattern treated with 1 mM Etoposide for 48 h and followed for an additional 114 h after Etoposide was washed out. Scale 
bar: 50 mm. (B) RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells and U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP cells were treated for 5, 10 or, 15 h with 1 mM Etoposide or mock treated. Subse-
quently, damaged cells were forced into mitosis using KU60019 and UCN-01. Nocodazole was added to block cells in mitosis. The percentage of Cyclin 
B1-eYFP positive cells and the percentage of mitotic cells were determined by flow cytometry. The graphs denote averages of 3 independent experi-
ments. Error bars represent standard errors. (C) Time-lapse microscopy quantifications of RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells treated with 1 mM Etoposide at time 
point 0 and caffeine addition at the indicated time points. The error bars represent standard error of the mean signal of at least 8 positions. (D) The per-
centage of Cyclin B1-eYFP-positive cells passing through mitosis was assessed from (C). (E) The time point of nuclear translocation and the onset of deg-
radation of Cyclin B1-eYFP were determined in single cells treated as in (C). Each line represents a single cell. The dotted lines indicate presence of 
caffeine. (F) Representative images of cells in (C) treated with Caffeine. Mitotic cell is marked by asterisk. (G) RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells were treated with 
1 mM Etoposide and caffeine was added after 4 h. Cyclin B1-eYFP intracellular localization and cell fate was assessed for 96 individual cells. </p>

<p> 
Volume 13 Issue 17 
Cell Cycle </p>

<p>Figure 5. The time point of Cyclin B1 degradation is decoupled from DDR activation. (A) RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells were treated with 1 mM Etoposide and 
the time point of onset of Cyclin B1-eYFP degradation was assessed. The red bar indicates cells that did not initiate degradation during the time of the 
experiment. (B) Representative montages of single U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP and RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells on fibronectin-coated micropatterns during an 
unperturbed cell cycle (control) and during treatment with 1 mM Etoposide (damage). Time between images is 1 h. Scale bar: 50 mm. (C) Single-cell 
quantifications of time-lapse images as in (B) for U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP cells and RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells under treatment with 1 mM Etoposide from 
time point '0 h'. The green track indicates a cell undergoing mitosis. The dashed orange lines denote the average of the displayed cells. (D) RPE Cyclin 
B1-eYFP cells were grown on fibronectin-coated micropatterns and treated with 1 mM Etoposide. The Cyclin B1-eYFP levels at the time of Etoposide addi-
tion are plotted versus the time point of maximum Cyclin B1-eYFP levels ('time point of Cyclin B1-eYFP degradation'). (E and H) In silico synchronizations 
of single-cell quantifications as in (C) in unperturbed conditions (E) or under treatment with 1 mM Etoposide (H). Data are from a single experiment in 
parallel wells, allowing for direct comparison of fluorescence levels. Cells in (E) are synchronized in silico to mitosis. Graphs (H) show tracks of cells with 
near-background levels at the time of Etoposide addition. RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells were synchronized in silico for to the maximum level of Cyclin B1-
eYFP reached. (F) The time point of apparent nuclear translocation of Cyclin B1-eYFP before mitosis was assessed in RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP and U2OS Cyclin 
B1-eYFP cells. (G) Time-lapse microscopy quantifications of the nuclear to cytoplasm ratio of single RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP and U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP cells. 
Cells were treated with 1 mM Etoposide or mock treated with DMSO at time point '¡1 h'. LMB was added at time point '0 h'. Mean and standard error of 
at least 15 cells per condition are depicted. (I) Quantification of DNA content (DAPI) vs. estimated time. Cells were sorted for DAPI levels and the predom-
inant localization of Cyclin B1 was assessed for each cell. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
 
Cell Cycle </p>

<p>correlates with the Cyclin B1-eYFP level at the time point of the 
DNA damage insult, that is cells with high Cyclin B1-eYFP level 
initiate degradation earlier than cells with low Cyclin B1-eYFP 
level (Fig. 5D). As a consequence, Cyclin B1-eYFP levels are pre-
vented from exceeding the levels observed during mitotic entry. 
Thus, Cyclin B1-eYFP degradation is temporally decoupled 
from initiation of the DDR in a manner that correlates with the 
initial levels of Cyclin B1-eYFP, indicating a cell cycle-dependent 
control of Cyclin B1 degradation. 
To allow better comparison between individual cells, we 
next synchronized cells from a single experiment containing 
both unperturbed and Etoposide-treated RPE and U2OS cells 
in silico. When synchronizing unperturbed cells in mitosis, 
both RPE and U2OS cells showed similar dynamics and similar 
levels of Cyclin B1-eYFP (Fig. 5E). However, in U2OS cells 
Cyclin B1-eYFP accumulation starts earlier and with larger var-
iability between individual cells (Fig. 5E), and we note that 
nuclear translocation of Cyclin B1-eYFP is less apparent com-
pared to RPE cells both in unperturbed and DNA damage con-
ditions (Fig. 5F and G). We next focused on cells with a low 
level of Cyclin B1-eYFP at the time of Etoposide addition. 
U2OS cells required approximately 30 hours before reaching 
similar Cyclin B1-eYFP level as during unperturbed mitotic 
entry, suggesting that Cyclin B1 accumulation is slower after 
initiation of a DDR (Fig. 5H). When synchronizing RPE cells 
with initially low levels of Cyclin B1-eYFP at their maximal 
level of fluorescence, we note that degradation is initiated at 
similar Cyclin B1-eYFP levels in all cells (Fig. 5H). Thus, 
indicating that in RPE cells Cyclin B1 is allowed to accumu-
late up to a distinct threshold before degradation is initiated. 
As this threshold corresponds to Cyclin B1 levels at the S/G2 
transition in unperturbed growth (Fig. 5E and H) we reasoned 
that Cyclin B1 degradation is initiated when cells exit S phase. 
To test this hypothesis, we assessed the cell cycle timing of 
Cyclin B1 nuclear translocation during DNA damage by sort-
ing single RPE cells according to their DNA content and 
determined Cyclin B1 localization by immunofluorescence. 
Strikingly, we find that Cyclin B1 nuclear localization occurs 
only in cells in G2 phase (Fig. 5I). Thus, Cyclin B1 accumula-
tion continues after DNA damage and Cyclin B1 nuclear 
translocation and subsequent degradation is only initiated 
when Cyclin B1 has reached a distinct threshold level in G2 
phase. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Terminal cell cycle exit is decoupled from DDR activation 
In principle, DNA repair should be initiated as soon as a 
lesion is recognized, whereas a cell cycle block only needs to be 
activated late in interphase to prevent mitotic entry. By examin-
ing Cyclin B1 dynamics in single RPE cells we show that APC/ 
C 
Cdh1 activation is temporally decoupled from the DNA dam-
age insult. While at a population level Cyclin B1 expression 
remains stable during the first hours after DNA damage, we 
find that no single cell maintains steady Cyclin B1 levels over </p>

<p>time. Rather Cyclin B1 levels continue to rise and degradation 
is only initiated once a certain threshold is reached. Cells con-
taining very low levels of Cyclin B1-eYFP initially accumulate 
it to levels indicative of entering G2 phase. At the same time, 
only cells with 4n DNA content initiate Cyclin B1 degradation, 
showing that terminal cell cycle exit occurs in G2 phase, but 
not in S phase. 
Similarly, the higher the Cyclin B1-eYFP content the more 
rapidly degradation is initiated. Thus, cells late in G2 phase 
exit the cell cycle faster than cells in early G2 phase, suggesting 
that G2 activities directly feed into the decision for cell cycle 
exit. As terminal cell cycle exit can be seen as a last resort of the 
DDR to avoid mitotic entry and thereby propagation of muta-
tions, incorporation of G2 activities in the decision process sug-
gests an elegant mechanism for timely cell cycle exit only when 
necessary. </p>

<p>Nuclear translocation of Cyclin B1 marks a restriction point 
for terminal cell cycle exit 
Upon successful repair of damaged DNA, cells should be 
allowed to resume cell division. However, not all cells will reen-
ter the cell cycle. Several studies show that this permanent cell 
cycle exit depends on APC/C 
Cdh1 activation. 
6-9 Indeed, chicken 
DT40 Cdh1 
¡/¡ cells fail to maintain a DNA damage-induced 
G2 arrest. 
24 However, we find that the actual point-of-no-
return occurs already earlier. Once all damaged DNA is 
repaired, the upstream ATM and ATR kinases lose their acti-
vating stimuli, which will lead to their eventual inactivation. 
We show that simulating repair by blocking ATM/ATR activity 
can induce recovery only in cells that had not previously trans-
located Cyclin B1 to the cell nucleus. Thus, after Cyclin B1 
nuclear translocation, cell cycle exit is no longer dependent on 
the presence of DNA damage signaling. As a consequence, 
depending on its initial cell cycle state, a cell has a set time to 
repair damaged DNA, before Cyclin B1 nuclear translocation 
in G2 phase marks the restriction point for terminal cell cycle 
exit. 
Interestingly, both Cyclin B1 nuclear localization and APC/ 
C 
Cdh1 activation have to be tightly connected to prevent check-
point override. APC/C 
Cdh1 activation and Cyclin B1 degrada-
tion were reported to be dependent on p21. 
6 In contrast, APC/ 
C 
Cdh1 activation appears to be a general response to DNA dam-
age that also occurs in cells that do not terminally exit the cell 
cycle due to a defective p21 response. 
9,15 Our data resolves this 
discrepancy as it suggests that a critical role of p21 is to seques-
ter Cyclin B1 in the nucleus, 
7 which then, in turn, is required 
for Cyclin B1 degradation. In fact, transformed cells exclude 
Cyclin B1 from the nucleus 
26 and accumulate it to high levels 
during ongoing DNA damage. 
27 Under these conditions forced 
nuclear translocation of Cyclin B1 actually induces checkpoint 
override or Cyclin B1 degradation. 
8 Notably, this data high-
lights an intriguing analogy to the unperturbed cell cycle, where 
Cyclin B1 nuclear translocation leads to a restriction point for 
mitotic entry. 
28-30 Thus, Cyclin B1 nuclear translocation marks 
a decision point -leading to mitosis or terminal cell cycle exit. </p>

<p> 
Volume 13 Issue 17 
Cell Cycle </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>We suggest that cell cycle exit is decoupled from the initiation 
of the DDR in a manner that depends on a cell's initial cell cycle 
phase and, thus, correlates to its Cyclin B1 levels. Once a certain 
threshold level is reached in G2 phase Cyclin B1 nuclear translo-
cation occurs and cell fate becomes determined toward perma-
nent cell cycle exit. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Cell culture 
U2OS cell lines were cultured in Dulbecco's modified eagle 
medium (DMEM) C GlutaMAX (Invitrogen) supplemented 
with 6% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS, HyClone) 
and 1% Penicillin/Streptomycin (HyClone). RPE cell lines were 
cultured in DMEM/Nutrient mixture F-12 (DMEM/F-12) C 
GlutaMAX (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% 
Penicillin/Streptomycin. HEK293T cells for viral particle pro-
duction were cultured in DMEM C GlutaMAX (Invitrogen) 
supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% Penicillin/Streptomycin. 
All cell lines were cultured in an ambient-controlled incubator at 
37 
C with 5% CO 2 . For live-cell imaging experiments, cells 
were cultured in Leibowitz's L-15 medium (Invitrogen) supple-
mented with 10% FBS and 1% Penicillin/Streptomycin. </p>

<p>RNAi 
For RNA interference experiments SMARTpool ON-TAR-
GET plus siRNAs targeting CDKN1A (p21), TP53 (p53), 
FRZ1 (Cdh1), CDC20 (Cdc20), BTRC (b-TrCP), ZC3HC1 
(NIPA), or CCNB1 (Cyclin B1) were purchased from Dhar-
macon. Cells were seeded at a density of 45000 cells/ml and 
transfected with siRNA using HiPerFect (Qiagen) and Opti-
MEM (Invitrogen) at 48 h and 24 h before analysis of pheno-
types. siRNAs were employed at a final concentration of 
20 nM. </p>

<p>Inhibitors and plasmids 
The inhibitors used in this study were employed at the follow-
ing concentrations: MG-132 at 10 mM (Sigma Aldrich), pro-
Tame at 15 mM (R&amp;D systems), Leptomycin B at 10 ng/ml 
(Sigma Aldrich), Importazole at 66 mM (Sigma Aldrich), UCN-
01 at 300 nM (Sigma Aldrich), KU60019 at 10 mM (Tocris 
Bioscience), Nocodazole at 250 ng/ml (Sigma Aldrich), S-Trityl-
L-cysteine (STLC) at 10 mM (Tocris Bioscience), caffeine at 
5 mM (Sigma Aldrich), Etoposide at 0.125 to 8 mM (Sigma 
Aldrich), and Neocarzinostatin (NCS) at 0.125 to 8 nM (Sigma 
Aldrich). Based on our titrations, 1 mM Etoposide was sufficient 
to induce damage to cells at all cell cycle stages and it was the 
lowest concentration where both U2OS and RPE cells displayed 
a robust checkpoint arrest (Fig. 1C and D; Fig. S1B). Therefore, 
we used 1 mM Etoposide in our experiments. </p>

<p>Live-cell microscopy and micropatterns 
For live-cell imaging of cell populations, 18000 cells were 
seeded in 96-well imaging plates (BD Falcon) 16 h before imag-
ing on either a DeltaVision Spectris imaging system (Applied 
Precision) using a 20£, NA 0.7 objective, or on a ImageXpress 
system (Molecular Devices) using a 20£, NA 0.45 objective. 
For experiments involving micropatterns, cells were detached 
using PBS containing 0.2% EDTA and seeded on fibronectin-
coated micropatterns (CYTOO) at a density of 60000 cells/ml 
5 h before starting the experiment. After 30 min cover slips were 
washed with PBS to remove unattached cells. 
Images were processed and analyzed using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs>. For time-
lapse microscopy quantification of populations the background 
was subtracted for every image series using rolling ball back-
ground subtraction. Furthermore, the image series were manually 
screened and series with fluorescent aggregates were excluded 
from the analysis. Subsequently, integrated fluorescent intensities 
were calculated and values were normalized for each series on the 
time point before inhibitor addition. Mean values of at least 8 
individual positions per condition were calculated. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence 
Cells were grown in 96-well imaging plates (BD Falcon), fixed 
using 3.7% formaldehyde (Sigma Aldrich) for 5 min at room 
temperature, permeabilized by ice-cold methanol for 2 min, 
blocked with 2% bovine serum albumin (Sigma Aldrich) in PBS 
supplemented with 0.1% Tween-20 (PBST) and incubated with 
primary antibodies for 2 h at room temperature. After washing 
with PBST, the cells were incubated with AlexaFluor-conjugated 
secondary antibodies for 1 h. DNA was stained with DAPI 
(0.5 mg/ml; Sigma Aldrich). The following antibodies were used: 
Cyclin B1 V152 (1:400; #4135 Cell Signaling), ɣH2AX (1:400; 
#9781 Cell Signaling). Images were acquired on an ImageXpress 
system (Molecular Devices) using a 40£ NA 0.6 or a 60£ NA 
0.7 objective. </p>

<p>Immunoblotting 
For Western blot analysis 1.5 £ 10 
6 U2OS or RPE cells were 
cultured in 10-cm dishes. DNA damage was induced using Eto-
poside (1 mM and 5 mM) and samples were collected 4 h, 8 h, 
24 h and 48 h after damage. Cells were washed using PBS and 
lysed in 500 ml of sample buffer (BioRad). 15 ml of each sample 
were loaded, run on 4-15% polyacrylamide gels (BioRad) and 
transferred to a PVDF membrane (BioRad) for immunoblotting. 
The following antibodies were used: Cyclin B1 GNS-1 (1:500; 
sc-245 Santa Cruz), Cyclin B1 V152 (1:1000; #4135 Cell Signal-
ing), Cyclin A2 H-432 (1:1000; sc-751 Santa Cruz), Plk1 F-8 
(1:500; sc-17783 Santa Cruz), Cdk1 POH1 (1:1000; #9116 Cell 
Signaling), Cdk2 78B2 (1:1000; #2564 Cell Signaling), p21 
12D1 (1:1000; #2947 Cell Signaling), p53 DO-1 (1:500; sc-126 
Santa Cruz), b-tubulin 9F3 (1:1000; #2128S Cell Signaling), 
GAPDH (1:25000; G9545 Sigma Aldrich), GFP (1:1000; 
ab290 abcam). Secondary antibodies conjugated to horseradish 
peroxidase (GE Healthcare) were diluted at 1:5000. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>
Generation of cell lines 
The U2OS Cyclin B1-eYFP and RPE Cyclin B1-eYFP cells 
were generated as previously described. 
18,31 Briefly, the open 
reading frame of eYFP lacking the start codon was inserted into 
the CCNB1 locus by adeno-associated virus-mediated homolo-
gous recombination. The targeting construct was designed to 
contain 959 bp of homology with the CCNB1 locus in the 5 
0 of 
the STOP codon and 1253 bp 3 
0 of the STOP codon. The con-
struct was cloned into a rAAV backbone and the resulting clones 
were verified by test digest prior to transfection of HEK293T 
cells to produce viral particles. Transduced and control U2OS 
and RPE cells were harvested with trypsin/EDTA 96 h after 
transduction, washed, resuspended in PBS, and filtered through 
a cell strainer to avoid cell aggregates (BD Falcon). Positive 
clones were obtained by sorting cells in a FACSAria III (Becton 
Dickinson) sorter as described previously by Mata and 
colleagues. </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>Flow cytometry 
Cells were harvested with trypsin/EDTA, resuspended and 
fixed with 70% ethanol. After fixation, cells were incubated with 
an antibody against Histone H3 pS10 (1:200; #3377 Cell Signal-
ing) and a secondary antibody conjugated to AlexaFluor647 </p>

<p>(Invitrogen). Finally, nucleic acids were stained using 40 mg/ml 
propidium iodide. Cells were analyzed on a FACSCanto II 
(Becton Dickinson). </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Camilla Sj€ ogren and Nico Dantuma for critical 
comments on the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was financed by the Swedish research council, the 
Swedish foundation for strategic research, the Swedish cancer 
society and the Swedish childhood cancer foundation. </p>

<p>Supplemental Material </p>

<p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed on the 
publisher's website. </p>



<p> 
Volume 13 Issue 17 
Cell Cycle </p>



<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>