<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4475471" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background &amp; Aims-Rapid induction of β-PDGF receptor (β-PDGFR) is a core feature of 
hepatic stellate cell activation, but its cellular impact in vivo is not well characterized. We 
explored the contribution of β-PDGFR-mediated pathway activation to hepatic stellate cell </p>

<p>© 2015 European Association for the Study of the Liver. Published by Elsevier B.V. </p>

<p>This manuscript version is made available under the CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 license. </p>

<p>Corresponding author Scott L. Friedman, M.D., Division of Liver Diseases, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, 1425 
Madison Ave., Box 1123, Room 11-70C, New York, NY 10029-6574, Tel +1 212 659 9501, Fax +1 212 849 2574, 
scott.friedman@mssm.edu. 
4 Current address: Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Department of Medicine, University of Illinois at Chicago, Chicago, 
IL, USA </p>

<p>Publisher's Disclaimer: This is a PDF file of an unedited manuscript that has been accepted for publication. As a service to our 
customers we are providing this early version of the manuscript. The manuscript will undergo copyediting, typesetting, and review of 
the resulting proof before it is published in its final citable form. Please note that during the production process errors may be 
discovered which could affect the content, and all legal disclaimers that apply to the journal pertain. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest: 
The authors disclose no conflicts. </p>

<p>Author contributions 
P.K. co-designed research plan, performed experiments, analyzed data, generated figures and drafted manuscript, A.L. and Y.A.L. 
performed experiments, analyzed data and performed validation of gene array results, A.D. performed flow-cytometric analysis, X.S. 
performed statistical analysis on data generated through gene array, M.I.F.: performed histological grading, S.T. performed 
histological grading, C.A. designed and supervised flow-cytometric analysis, P.S. generated original genetic mouse models, designed 
experiments, interpreted data, Y.H. provided statistical analysis and advice on gene array data, performed bioinformatic analysis and 
interpretation of data, S.L.F. co-designed research plan, reviewed and edited manuscript </p>

<p>HHS Public Access </p>

<p>Author manuscript </p>

<p>J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Published in final edited form as: 
J Hepatol. 2015 July ; 63(1): 141-147. doi:10.1016/j.jhep.2015.01.036. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>responses in liver injury, fibrogenesis, and carcinogenesis in vivo using genetic models with 
divergent β-PDGFR activity, and assessed its prognostic implications in human cirrhosis. </p>

<p>Methods-The impact of either loss or constitutive activation of β-PDGFR in stellate cells on 
fibrosis was assessed following carbon tetrachloride (CCl 4 ) or bile duct ligation. 
Hepatocarcinogenesis in fibrotic liver was tracked after a single dose of diethylnitrosamine (DEN) 
followed by repeated injections of CCl 4 . Genome-wide expression profiling was performed from 
isolated stellate cells that expressed or lacked β-PDGFR to determine deregulated pathways and 
evaluate their association with prognostic gene signatures in human cirrhosis. </p>

<p>Results-Depletion of β-PDGFR in hepatic stellate cells decreased injury and fibrosis in vivo, 
while its auto-activation accelerated fibrosis. However, there was no difference in development of 
DEN-induced pre-neoplastic foci. Genomic profiling revealed ERK, AKT, and NF-kB pathways 
and a subset of a previously identified 186-gene prognostic signature in hepatitis C virus (HCV)-
related cirrhosis as downstream of β-PDGFR in stellate cells. In the human cohort, the β-PDGFR 
signature was not associated with HCC development, but was significantly associated with a 
poorer outcome in HCV cirrhosis. </p>

<p>Conclusions-β-PDGFR is a key mediator of hepatic injury and fibrogenesis in vivo and 
contributes to the poor prognosis of human cirrhosis, but not by increasing HCC development. </p>

<p>Keywords </p>

<p>HCC; cirrhosis; receptor tyrosine kinase; gene expression signatures; pathway analysis </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Among mitogenic pathways in stellate cells, signaling by the beta platelet-derived growth 
factor receptor (β-PDGFR) is the most potent [1, 2]. Expression of PDGF receptors is low in 
healthy liver, but dramatically increases in stellate cells during injury [2, 3]. In both mice 
and humans, the PDGF signaling network is comprised of four ligands, PDGF A-D, which 
transduce their signals through dimeric transmembrane receptors α-and β-PDGFR, which 
can form hetero-and homodimers [4]. Upon ligand binding, receptor dimerization provokes 
phosphorylation of the tyrosine residues within the intracellular domain, leading to 
activation of the Fas-MAPK pathway, signaling through the PI3K-AKT/PKB pathway and 
activation of PKC family members [5]. </p>

<p>Antagonism of β-PDGFR has been an appealing target to treat hepatic fibrosis. Indeed, our 
previous study and those of others [6-8] have demonstrated that the RTK inhibitor imatinib 
mesylate (Gleevec®) whose targets include β-PDGFR, inhibits stellate cell activation and 
reduces fibrosis. </p>

<p>Recent evidence links the behavior of stromal cells, especially driven by the ligand PDGF-
B, not only to the pathogenesis of fibrosis, but also to inflammation, regeneration and cancer 
[9]. Sorafenib (Nexavar®), a multi-receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor whose targets include 
β-PDGFR, remains the only drug approved for treatment of advanced, non-resectable HCC </p>

<p>[10]. </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. 
Page 2 </p>

<p>J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Despite the suggestion that promotion of fibrosis by β-PDGFR can accelerate HCC 
development, this important question has not been addressed experimentally. Here we have 
specifically explored the contribution of β-PDGFR signaling by activated hepatic stellate 
cells to injury, fibrosis and cancer by exploiting complementary genetic models using a Cre-
Lox strategy, one in which the receptor was deleted in stellate cells, or another in which it 
was auto-activated. Importantly, we have examined whether β-PDGFR signaling in hepatic 
stellate cells is linked in human cirrhosis to overall prognosis. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>For detailed description of methods see Supplementary Methods. </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>β-PDGFR fl/fl mice, as previously described [11], (on the 129S4/SvJaeSor background) were </p>

<p>crossed with a transgenic FVB line expressing Cre-recombinase under control of the human 
glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) promoter to generate β-PDGFR fl/fl GFAP-Cre mice 
with a deletion of β-PDGFR in stellate cells -this GFAP promoter has been successfully 
validated in prior studies as active in hepatic stellate cells [12, 13]. To create animals with 
constitutively activated β-PDGFR in stellate cells, β-PDGFR betaJ/+ mice, as previously 
described [14], (on the 129S4/B6 background) were also crossed with a transgenic GFAP-
Cre line to generate β-PDGFR betaJ/+ GFAP-Cre mice. These animals harbor hepatic stellate 
cells with autoactivation of β-PDGFR, owing to an activating mutation knocked into the β-
PDGFR locus, plus addition of a lox-stop-lox cassette between the splice acceptor and the 
initiating codon of the cDNA [14]. </p>

<p>Models of Murine Liver injury and Fibrosis </p>

<p>Liver fibrosis was induced either by ligation of the common bile duct (BDL) [15] or by 
intraperitoneal (i.p.) injections of carbon tetrachloride (CCl 4 , Sigma, St. Louis, MO) [16]. 
For acute CCl 4 injury studies, mice received a total of 3 i.p. injections (alternating days) of 
either corn oil or 10% CCl 4 (diluted in corn oil) at a dose of 0.5 µl/g body weight. For the 
chronic injury model, mice received i.p. injections of CCl 4 3 times per week for a total of 6 
weeks. </p>

<p>Induction of Carcinogenesis </p>

<p>Mice received a single dose of diethylnitrosamine (DEN, Sigma, St. Louis, MO) (25µg/g bw 
i.p.) at day 15 post-partum. Starting two weeks after DEN, mice received a total of 22 
injections of CCl 4 (0.5µl/g bw i.p., 1 injection/week) [17]. Mice were sacrificed 48 hours 
following the last CCl 4 injection. Nodule number and size was documented as described by 
counting and measuring the diameter of each lesion using a caliper. </p>

<p>Primary Hepatic Stellate cell Isolation and Cell Culture </p>

<p>Mouse hepatic stellate cells were isolated from β-PDGFR fl/fl GFAP-Cre negative and β-
PDGFR fl/fl GFAP-Cre positive mice by enzymatic pronase and collagenase digestion and 
density gradient centrifugation as previously described [18]. Cells were cultured with 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium (DMEM) containing 10% fetal bovine serum. Cells </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>were either treated with or without PDGF-B [10 ng/ml] (Peprotech, Princeton, NJ) diluted in 
albumin (vehicle) containing serum-free media (DMEM). </p>

<p>Histologic and Immunohistochemical Studies </p>

<p>Liver samples were formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded, sectioned at 4 µm, and processed 
routinely for H&amp;E staining. Sirius Red, combined with morphometry, was used to quantify 
collagen using <rs id="software-4" type="software">Bioquant image analysis software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Bioquant Image Analysis Corporation</rs>, 
Nashville, TN). Immunohistochemical staining of αSMA and desmin was performed on 
formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded liver sections with a rabbit polyclonal antibody (Abcam, 
Cambridge, England). A pathologist blindly scored 5 random areas per slide for necrosis, 
inflammation and dysplasia. </p>

<p>Genome-wide expression profiling </p>

<p>Genome-wide gene expression profiling of mouse primary hepatic stellate cells was 
performed, in triplicate, by using MouseWG-6 v2.0 Expression BeadChip (Illumina) 
according to the manufacturer's protocol. Raw scanned data were normalized by using cubic 
spine algorithm implemented in the <rs id="software-0" type="software">GenePattern</rs> genomic analysis toolkit 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">www.broadinstitute.org/genepattern</rs>) [19]. Probe-level expression data were collapsed into 
gene-level by calculating the median of multiple probes, and converted to human genes 
based on an orthologous mapping table provided by the Jackson laboratory 
(www.informatics.jax.org). The dataset (GSE#52253) is available at NCBI Gene Expression 
Omnibus database (www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo). </p>

<p>Bioinformatics and Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Enrichment of molecular pathways was evaluated by Gene Set Enrichment Analysis 
(GSEA) [20] on a comprehensive gene set collection in Molecular Signatures Database (see 
Supplementary Methods). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>β-PDGFR Expression is Induced Upon Liver Injury In Vivo and In Vitro </p>

<p>We generated a mouse line in which the expression of β-PDGFR was deleted in hepatic 
stellate cells by crossing β-PDGFR fl/fl mice with animals expressing Cre-recombinase under 
the human glial fibrillary acidic protein promoter (GFAP-Cre) (Suppl. Fig. 1A) [13, 21]. </p>

<p>To first confirm the induction of β-PDGFR following acute injury, β-PDGFR fl/fl GFAP-Cre 
negative animals were treated with CCl 4 in three doses in one week. Whole liver lysates 
contained increased β-PDGFR expression and phosphorylation, as well as up-regulation of 
αSMA (Fig. 1A). </p>

<p>We next analyzed isolated hepatic stellate cells from β-PDGFR fl/fl Cre negative mice (β-
PDGFR) as well as their β-PDGFR fl/fl Cre expressing littermates (Δβ-PDGFR) (Fig. 1B, C). 
Isolated stellate cells were maintained in primary culture for six days following isolation. To 
first validate the knock down and diminished activation of β-PDGFR in the Cre expressing 
population, cell lysates were analyzed via immunoblot after incubation with either vehicle or </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>PDGF-BB (Fig. 1B). Stellate cells from Δβ-PDGFR mice displayed attenuated receptor 
expression and lack of activation at baseline and after 30 minutes of ligand exposure. Next, 
the expression of collagen I and αSMA were compared in primary stellate cells of the two 
groups. Stellate cells isolated and cultured for 6 days displayed significant knock down of 
the receptor in the Δβ-PDGFR group, with substantially reduced expression levels of 
collagen I and αSMA compared to stellate cells from β-PDGFR animals (Fig. 1C). β-
PDGFR expression was upregulated during hepatic injury and correlates with stellate cell 
activation in vitro. </p>

<p>Deletion of β-PDGFR in Stellate Cells Attenuates Liver Fibrosis In Vivo </p>

<p>Since mice responded to acute liver injury with up-regulation of β-PDGFR on stellate cells 
associated with fibrogenic markers, we analyzed control and Δβ-PDGFR animals (Suppl. 
Fig. 1A) following acute (1 week) and chronic (6 weeks) liver injury. To do so, we injected 
both groups with either oil or CCl 4 (3 i.p. injections weekly). </p>

<p>Macroscopically, there were no differences in the livers between control and Δβ-PDGFR 
littermates after treatment (Suppl. Fig. 1B, C), but less necrosis was present at the early time 
point (Suppl. Fig. 2A, B). Although there was a trend in reduced inflammation in the livers 
of Δβ-PDGFR mice after one week of injections (Suppl. Fig. 2B), comprehensive flow 
cytometry did not confirm any differences in the numbers or subsets of lymphocytes at 
baseline or after injury between wild type and Δβ-PDGFR littermates (data not shown). β-
PDGFR-deficiency led to significantly decreased collagen deposition after chronic hepatic 
injury as assessed by Sirius Red morphometry and hydroxyproline assay (Fig. 2 A, B, C). 
Serum transaminase levels (AST and ALT) were increased, especially after 6 weeks (Fig. 
2D). As expected, livers with β-PDGFR deletion in stellate cells expressed less αSMA and 
significantly less collagen α1(I) mRNAs (Fig. 2E). In order to validate the effect of 
diminished β-PDGFR expression on the expansion of activated HSCs following CCl 4 
treatment, we quantified the αSMA-positive tissue area in both groups (Suppl. Fig. 3A). 
Both after a short-term, and more strikingly, after long-term injury, mice of the Δβ-PDGFR 
group had reduced expansion of activated HSCs versus controls. This finding was further 
validated using whole liver lysates of livers after 6 weeks of CCl 4 treatment (Suppl. Fig. 
3B). Here, the decreased expression of β-PDGFR resulted in a diminished expression of 
αSMA. As an additional marker for HSCs and to measure the expansion of HSCs during </p>

<p>injury within the liver, desmin staining was performed on tissue sections following 1 week 
of CCl 4 treatment (Suppl. Fig. 4). In these mice, there was a significant decrease in desmin-
positive tissue quantification in Δβ-PDGFR mice versus controls. </p>

<p>Similar but less striking results were apparent in the bile duct ligation model (see Suppl. Fig. 
5). </p>

<p>Loss of β-PDGFR in Stellate Cells Diminishes Their Proliferative Response In Vivo </p>

<p>To determine whether increased fibrosis upon hepatic injury was due to β-PDGFR mediated 
stellate cell proliferation, we performed in vivo labeling of dividing stellate cells. Mice of 
both groups received a total of three i.p. injections of CCl 4 every 48 hours; 44 hours after the 
last injection, mice received a single i.p. injection of BrdU (1.5mg/150µl PBS), and cells </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>were isolated four hours thereafter. Isolated cells were stained for CD45 and BrdU and then 
analyzed by flow cytometry. UV autofluorescence was used to distinguish stellate cells from 
non-fluorescent cells, while the expression of CD45 was used to discriminate CD45 − stellate 
cells from other non-parenchymal cells (Suppl. Fig. 6A). Based on this analysis, 44.3% of 
stellate cells from β-PDGFR mice had incorporated nuclear BrdU compared to 16.3% in Δβ-
PDGFR cells (Suppl. Fig. 6B), indicating that β-PDGFR expression of stellate cells 
correlates with significantly increased proliferation during hepatic injury. </p>

<p>Constitutively Activated β-PDGFR in Stellate Cells Amplifies Liver Fibrosis In Vivo </p>

<p>To confirm the vital role of β-PDGFR during hepatic fibrosis, we analyzed a mouse line in 
which the expression of a β-PDGFR auto-activating mutant was induced in hepatic stellate 
cells by crossing β-PDGFR betaJ/+ mice with GFAP-Cre transgenic animals (Suppl. Fig. 7A). 
We compared PDGFR betaJ/+ Cre negative (β-PDGFR) and their PDGFR betaJ/+ Cre positive 
(βJ) littermates following three weekly i.p. injections of either corn oil or CCl 4 (0.5 µl/g 
body weight) over one (acute) or six (chronic) weeks (Fig. 3). The auto-activating βJ group 
displayed differences in fibrotic tissue area versus control animals upon oil injections (Fig. 
3A, B, C). Differences were also significant following 6 weeks of CCl 4 , with βJ mice 
displaying significantly increased collagen deposition (Fig. 3A, B, C). Consistent with these 
findings, mutant βJ expression on stellate cells led to significantly more collagen α1(I) and 
αSMA mRNA expression upon CCl 4 treatment (Fig. 3D). </p>

<p>There were no macroscopic differences between control and mutant βJ littermates before or 
after treatment (Suppl. Fig. 7B) but there was an increase in liver to body weight ratio in 
both treatment groups after 1 and 6 weeks (Suppl. Fig. 7C). Serum transaminase levels 
increased proportionate to treatment duration, without differences between β-PDGFR and βJ 
littermates (Suppl. Fig. 7D). Both groups displayed increased inflammation and necrosis 
(Suppl. Fig. 8A, B). </p>

<p>We quantified the desmin-positive area, as a reflection of stellate cell expansion (Fig. 3E). 
Using this approach, mice with auto-activating β-PDGFR displayed increased desmin-
positive tissue area upon acute injury (Fig. 3F). The auto-activating mutation of β-PDGFR 
led to increased stellate cell proliferation and hepatic fibrosis upon acute and chronic injury. </p>

<p>β-PDGFR Deficiency in Stellate Cells has no Impact on the Carcinogenic Response </p>

<p>Since the majority of HCCs develop within cirrhotic livers, we assessed the contribution of 
β-PDGFR signaling in stellate cells to the development of dysplastic nodules following DEN </p>

<p>plus CCl 4 (Suppl. Fig. 9A) [17]. This regimen reportedly mimics the permissive 
environment from which regenerative nodules and ultimately HCCs arise [12, 17]. </p>

<p>After long-term treatment with both a carcinogen as well as CCl 4 , Δβ-PDGFR accumulated 
less collagen as assessed by Sirius Red morphometry (Fig. 4A, B), associated with reduced 
collagen α1(I) mRNA (Suppl. Fig. 9G). However, loss of Δβ-PDGFR had no impact on the 
total number of lesions, the maximal nodule size, or the liver weight to body weight ratio 
(Suppl. Fig. 9B, C, D, E). Of note, careful expert analysis revealed the lesions to be 
dysplastic nodules, not true HCCs. Histologically, liver sections showed a similar </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>appearance of dysplastic nodules between both β-PDGFR and Δβ-PDGFR mice as assessed 
by a blinded pathologist (Suppl. Fig. 9F). </p>

<p>These data indicate that the lack of β-PDGFR expression by stellate cells attenuates fibrosis 
progression in chronic injury from CCl 4 , but does not protect against the development of 
dysplastic nodules when combined with a carcinogen. </p>

<p>Constitutively Activation of β-PDGFR in Stellate Cells does not lead to an Increased 
Carcinogenic Response </p>

<p>To further reflect these findings, we used βJ mice and their control littermates to assess their 
response towards the combined treatment with DEN and CCl 4 (Suppl. Fig. 10). 
Macroscopically, there was no difference in overall quantification of dysplastic nodule 
formation (Suppl. Fig. 10), regarding tumor number, the largest tumor diameter and overall 
liver weight to body weight ratio (Suppl. Fig. 10B, C, D, E). Histologically, the grade of 
dysplasia was not different among βJ and control mice (Suppl. Fig. 10F). Overall, the 
activation level of β-PDGFR did not correlate with formation of dysplastic nodules in this 
murine model. </p>

<p>Prognostic Relevance of β-PDGFR-mediated Signaling in Human Cirrhosis </p>

<p>We previously identified and validated a 186-gene signature in liver that predicts prognosis 
of patients with liver cirrhosis [22, 23]. The signature is assumed to reflect signals of 
molecular deregulation from multiple cell types in the cirrhotic tissue microenvironment that 
drive disease progression. We hypothesized that activation of β-PDGFR signaling in stellate 
cells contributes at least a part of the prognostic gene signature. Using this dataset, we 
examined whether the stellate cell-derived β-PDGFR or Δβ-PDGFR gene signature was 
present in the human cirrhosis cohort and determined its prognostic association. To do so, 
we performed Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) to evaluate induction of the 186-gene 
signature in isolated stellate cells from our β-PDGFR-wild-type and knockout mice. Of note, 
we observed a statistically significant enrichment of poor-prognosis-and good-prognosis-
correlated signature genes in the wild-type and knockout stellate cells, respectively (false 
discovery rate &lt;0.25) (Fig. 4C a, b). Genes up-regulated in the β-PDGFR knockout cells 
(i.e., genes suppressed by β-PDGFR pathway activation) (Supplementary Table 2), were 
associated with a good prognosis (Fig. 4C a). Likewise, genes up-regulated by β-PDGFR 
activation showed an association with a high overall risk of mortality in HCV cirrhotic 
patients (Fig. 4C b), suggesting that the pathway activation itself is partially linked to the 
risk of liver disease and fibrosis progression. Genes involved in inflammation and cell 
survival such as NFKB2, IER3, IFI30, and BCL2 contributed to the enrichment within the 
poor prognosis signature (Table 1). However, genes previously implicated in 
hepatocarcinogenesis such as EGF [24] were not involved in the enrichment, suggesting that 
β-PDGFR signaling in stellate cells is not directly involved in the process of </p>

<p>hepatocarcinogenesis. We verified the expression levels of the top five differentially 
regulated genes of β-PDGFR-wild-type and knockout mice as selected by DNA microarray 
using quantitative real-time PCR (Fig. 4D). These data provide evidence for a strong 
correlation between microarray data as well as PCR from hepatic stellate cells isolated from 
mice of both groups. For Ingenuity Pathway Analysis of the 186-gene signature within </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>hepatic stellate cells of β-PDGFR control compared to knockout mice, see Suppl. Table 2. 
Collectively, these results suggest that activation of β-PDGFR signaling in stellate cells has 
downstream consequences that drive disease progression and poor prognosis of human 
cirrhosis, but not through increased risk of HCC development. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the current study, we established two divergent genetic mouse models, by using a 
knockout or auto-activation of β-PDGFR, to assess the impact of titrating β-PDGFR 
expression on stellate cell and its contribution to liver injury and fibrosis. Deleting β-
PDGFR on hepatic stellate cells impairs their fibrogenic potential in vivo, leading to 
decreased expression of αSMA and collagen α1(I), and reducing their proliferation upon 
injury. Although previous studies have not directly linked β-PDGFR to collagen expression, 
here we demonstrate that the lack of β-PDGFR on primary hepatic stellate cells leads to 
decreased expression of collagen I after treatment with PDGF-B. Our data establish that β-
PDGFR activation increases fibrosis accumulation at least in part through increased stellate 
cell numbers based on BrdU incorporation in stellate cells in vivo and subsequent FACS 
analysis. We also emphasize that while specificity of human GFAP-Cre expression has been 
questioned [25], both this study and separate reports [12, 13] underscore its utility to drive 
stellate cell cre expression. Moreover, it has been shown that β-PDGFR is only expressed in 
activated hepatic stellate cells and some vascular endothelial cells in liver thereby 
minimizing potential hepatic off-target effects of the GFAP-Cre expression since only 
stellate cells will be affected by deletion of β-PDGFR. One major issue is that differences in 
the recombination of different floxed alleles or Cre reporters cannot be ruled out completely. </p>

<p>Our data begin to define nuanced and very specific links between some pathways of stellate 
cell activation, and prognosis of cirrhosis or incidence of HCC, but not others. For example, 
recent studies strongly implicate EGFR signaling and clinical outcomes in human HCC [24, 
26, 27], yet in contrast to a previous report [28] our findings do not establish a similar link 
for β-PDGFR signaling, despite its clear contribution to fibrosis. EGF was not among the 14 
genes that lead to an enrichment of the phenotype for poor prognosis in GSEA downstream 
of β-PDGFR signaling (Table 1, Suppl. Table 2). Although sorafenib, which is the only 
approved molecular therapy for HCC, targets multiple receptor tyrosine kinases, including 
β-PDGFR, our data suggest that the antineoplastic benefit of sorafenib may not be due to its </p>

<p>impact on β-PDGFR signaling alone, but rather on other RTK pathways, especially Ras/Raf 
kinase, HGF and VEGF signaling [29]. We also emphasize that expert histologic assessment 
failed to confirm the presence of true HCCs but rather only preneoplastic, dysplastic 
nodules, undermining the potential value of this model in generating true HCCs, in contrast 
to what has been previously proposed [28]. </p>

<p>β-PDGFR activity in stellate cells clearly contributes to progressive disease during chronic </p>

<p>liver injury, consistent with the finding that the β-PDGFR gene signature in primary hepatic 
stellate cells correlates with poor overall outcome in our human cohort. However, the β-
PDGFR-related difference in human outcomes is not due to enhanced tumor development, 
consistent with the findings in our murine model. Thus, β-PDGFR signaling may contribute 
to poor outcomes in HCV cirrhosis through its impact on fibrosis but not on carcinogenesis. </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>These findings indicate that while β-PDGFR is an attractive anti-fibrotic target, it may not 
be a suitable direct target to inhibit the development of neoplasia in cirrhotic liver, in 
contrast to other RTK pathways, especially EGFR signaling [30], where prophylactic 
receptor antagonism is a viable strategy for reducing the risk of cancer more directly. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Refer to Web version on PubMed Central for supplementary material. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank Dr. Marie Berres (Oncological Sciences, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai) and Hsin 
Chou for technical support. RNA seq and DNA microarray experiments were performed by the Genomics Core, 
preprocessing was performed by Dr. Ke Hao and Dr. Antonio Fabio Di Narzo (Genetics and Genomic Science, 
Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai). </p>

<p>Financial Support </p>

<p>This work has been supported by grants from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) (KO 4086/1-1 to P.K, 
LE 2794/1-1 to Y.A.L.), The Levine Family Foundation (to A. D.), as well as the NIH DK56621 and AA020709 (to 
S.L.F.), and the NIH DK099558 and European Commission 7th Framework Programme FP7-Health 2010 
(Heptromic) (to Y.H.). </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>β-PDGFR 
beta platelet-derived growth factor receptor </p>

<p>HCV 
hepatitis C virus </p>

<p>CCl 4 
carbon tetrachloride </p>

<p>DEN 
diethyl nitrosamine </p>

<p>GFAP 
glial fibrillary acidic protein </p>

<p>BDL 
bile duct ligation </p>

<p>bw 
body weight </p>

<p>AST 
aspartate aminotransferase </p>

<p>ALT 
alanine aminotransferase </p>

<p>mRNA 
messenger ribonucleic acid </p>

<p>PCR 
polymerase chain reaction </p>

<p>GAPDH 
glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase </p>

<p>αSMA 
alpha smooth muscle actin </p>

<p>H&amp;E 
hematoxylin and eosin </p>

<p>BrdU 
5-bromo-2'-deoxyuridine </p>

<p>CD45 
cluster of differentiation 45 </p>

<p>UV 
ultraviolet </p>

<p>PBS 
phosphate buffered saline </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. 
Page 9 </p>

<p>J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>HCC </p>

<p>hepatocellular carcinoma </p>

<p>IL1R 
interleukin 1 receptor </p>

<p>GSEA 
gene set enrichment analysis </p>

<p>FACS 
fluorescence-activated cell sorting </p>

<p>VEGF 
vascular endothelial growth factor </p>

<p>HGF 
hepatocyte growth factor </p>

<p>RTK 
receptor tyrosine kinase </p>

<p>EGFR 
epidermal growth factor receptor </p>

<p>NES 
normalized enrichment score </p>

<p>FDR 
false discovery rate </p>



<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Fig. 1. β-PDGFR expression correlates with activation of mouse hepatic stellate cells in vivo and 
in vitro </p>

<p>(A) Mice were injected three times with either oil or CCl 4 to induce acute liver injury and 
were sacrificed two days after the last injection. Immunoblot of whole liver lysates 
demonstrating increased expression of β-PDGFR, phospho-β-PDGFR and αSMA upon 
injury. 
(B, C) Δβ-PDGFR mice and control littermates were injected once with CCl 4 followed by 
isolation of HSCs 48 hours thereafter. Primary HSCs were kept in culture for 6 days. 
(B) Immunoblot demonstrates phosphorylation of the receptor in control animals upon 
ligand exposure and lack of receptor activation in HSCs of Δβ-PDGFR animals. 
(C) Immunoblot showing decreased HSC activation of Δβ-PDGFR mice in culture compared 
to wild type β-PDGFR mice, with reduced expression of Collagen I and αSMA. Graph 
indicating densitometric analysis of each band, verifying significant knock down of β-
PDGFR in primary HSCs of Δβ-PDGFR mice and decreased expression of HSC activation 
markers. 
Data represent the mean value of at least 3 separate experiments (*p&lt;0.05, error bars 
indicate SEM). 3 animals per condition were used in each experiment. Protein ratios 
(normalized to calnexin) were used to quantify the fold change relative to control, and are 
shown below each blot. </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Loss of β-PDGFR on HSCs leads to decreased collagen deposition in vivo </p>

<p>(A-E) Δβ-PDGFR and control mice were injected with CCl 4 over either one or six weeks to 
induce acute or chronic liver injury. 
(A) Sirius Red staining of paraffin embedded liver sections following acute or chronic liver 
injury depicts significantly lower collagen deposition after chronic injury (magnification 
200×). 
(B) Graph displays the percentage of liver area positive for Sirius Red staining measured by 
morphometric analysis. The area of fibrotic tissue is significantly reduced within Δβ-PDGFR 
animals compared to controls. 
(C) Measurement of hydroxyproline content per gram of whole liver after 6 weeks of CCl 4 
reflects reduced hydroxyproline content in livers of Δβ-PDGFR versus controls. 
(D) Levels of serum AST and ALT during acute and chronic injury. 
(E) Whole liver mRNA expression of Collagen α1(I), αSMA, β-PDGFR after 6 weeks of 
CCl 4 treatment confirm increased expression of stellate cell activation genes within control 
animals upon injury, as well as lack of increase within the Δβ-PDGFR group. 
All figures represent the mean of at least n=3 animals per experimental group. mRNA is 
expressed normalized to Gapdh (*p &lt; 0.05, **p&lt; 0.001; error bars indicate SEM). </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. 
Page 13 </p>

<p>J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The 'βJ' constitutively activating mutant of β-PDGFR on stellate cells leads to increased 
collagen deposition upon injury in vivo </p>

<p>(A-D) βJ and control mice were injected with CCl 4 over either one or six weeks to induce 
acute or chronic liver injury. 
(A) Sirius Red staining of paraffin embedded liver sections following acute or chronic liver 
injury depicts significantly higher collagen deposition after acute and chronic injury 
(magnification 200×). 
(B) Graph shows the percentage of liver area positive for Sirius Red staining measured by 
morphometry. The area of fibrotic tissue is significantly increased in livers of βJ animals 
compared to controls. 
(C) Increased hydroxyproline content per gram of whole liver after 6 weeks of CCl 4 in livers 
of βJ mice compared to controls. 
(D) Whole liver mRNA expression of αSMA and Collagen α1(I) after 6 weeks of CCl 4 
treatment confirms increased expression of stellate cell activation genes in βJ animals upon 
liver injury. 
(E) Desmin staining of paraffin embedded liver sections following acute liver injury depicts 
increased stellate cell expansion within livers of βJ mice versus controls. </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>(F) Graph shows percentage of tissue area positive for desmin measured by morphometry. 
All figures represent the mean of at least n=5 animals per experimental group. mRNA is 
expressed normalized to Gapdh (*p &lt; 0.05, **p&lt; 0.001; error bars indicate SEM). </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Deletion of β-PDGFR reduces fibrosis but not tumor burden in mice treated with DEN 
and chronic CCl 4 , and is linked to better outcome in patients with cirrhosis </p>

<p>Mice were treated with a single dose of DEN at day 15, followed by weekly injections with 
CCl 4 and sacrificed 48h after the last of 22 injections with CCl 4 . 
(A) Paraffin embedded liver sections were stained with Sirius Red to assess fibrotic tissue 
content (magnification 200×). 
(B) Decreased collagen area measured by morphometry in livers of Δβ-PDGFR mice. The 
bar graph represents the mean of n=5 animals per experimental group. (**p&lt; 0.001; error 
bars indicate SEM). 
(C) GSEA plots demonstrate β-PDGFR-dependent association with gene signatures for 
either a good or poor prognosis in an HCV cirrhotic patient cohort. 
Gene array samples of primary hepatic stellate cells isolated from either β-PDGFRfl/fl 
GFAP-Cre negative (indicated as WT) or β-PDGFRfl/fl GFAP-Cre positive (indicated as 
KO) mice were correlated with gene signatures for good or poor overall prognosis of a 
human HCV cirrhosis cohort. 
(a) Association of the β-PGDFR-knockout gene signature with a good outcome in liver 
cirrhosis. Enrichment of the β-PGDFR-knockout gene signature was evaluated in association 
with the risk of overall mortality in 216 HCV-related cirrhosis patients with early-stage 
cirrhosis (n=216). NES=−1.14, nominal p=0.21, FDR=0.22. 
(b) Association of the β-PGDFR gene signature with a poor outcome in HCV cirrhosis. 
Enrichment of the β-PGDFR gene signature was evaluated in association with the risk of </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
Table 1 </p>

<p>Induction of 186-gene human prognostic gene signature in primary stellate cells from wild-type and β-Pdgfr 
knockout mice. </p>

<p>a) Poor-prognosis-associated genes induced in wild-type mouse stellate cells </p>

<p>Human gene symbol 
Mouse gene symbol 
t-statistic </p>

<p>DAB2 
Dab2 
1,35 </p>

<p>LPP 
Lpp 
1,28 </p>

<p>ANXA1 
Anxa1 
1,28 </p>

<p>NFKB2 
Nfkb2 
0,96 </p>

<p>EPM2AIP1 
Epm2aip1 
0,90 </p>

<p>SERPINB2 
Serpinb2 
0,90 </p>

<p>ITGA9 
Itga9 
0,83 </p>

<p>IQGAP1 
Iqgap1 
0,81 </p>

<p>IER3 
Ier3 
0,74 </p>

<p>CCDC6 
Ccdc6 
0,54 </p>

<p>COL4A1 
Col4a1 
0,53 </p>

<p>IFI30 
Ifi30 
0,46 </p>

<p>ANXA3 
Anxa3 
0,44 </p>

<p>BCL2 
Bcl2 
0,40 </p>

<p>SERPINB8 
Serpinb8 
0,37 </p>

<p>b) Good-prognosis-associated genes induced in Pdgfrb-knockout mouse stellate cells </p>

<p>Human gene symbol 
Mouse gene symbol 
t-statistic </p>

<p>DAD1 
Dad1 
−0,30 </p>

<p>VPS41 
Vps41 
−0,30 </p>

<p>ERCC5 
Ercc5 
−0,32 </p>

<p>RRM1 
Rrm1 
−0,32 </p>

<p>ACOT2 
Acot2 
−0,35 </p>

<p>GCGR 
Gcgr 
−0,38 </p>

<p>RFC2 
Rfc2 
−0,40 </p>

<p>TIMM8A 
Timm8a1 
−0,40 </p>

<p>TXN2 
Txn2 
−0,51 </p>

<p>GGCX 
Ggcx 
−0,53 </p>

<p>ZNF185 
Zfp185 
−0,54 </p>

<p>HSPE1 
Hspe1 
−0,55 </p>

<p>FAM129A 
Fam129a 
−0,56 </p>

<p>F9 
F9 
−0,58 </p>

<p>PSMB3 
Psmb3 
−0,60 </p>

<p>MSH6 
Msh6 
−0,61 </p>

<p>XPA 
Xpa 
−0,67 </p>

<p>ZER1 
Zer1 
−0,69 </p>

<p>GHR 
Ghr 
−0,80 </p>

<p>J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Kocabayoglu et al. </p>

<p>
b) Good-prognosis-associated genes induced in Pdgfrb-knockout mouse stellate cells </p>

<p>Human gene symbol 
Mouse gene symbol 
t-statistic </p>

<p>ATP5D 
Atp5d 
−0,88 </p>

<p>PMM1 
Pmm1 
−0,90 </p>

<p>NENF 
Nenf 
−0,94 </p>

<p>t-statistic indicates degree of differential expression between wild-type and Pdgfrb-knockout mouse stellate cells. Positive values indicate up-
regulation in wild-type and negative values indicate up-regulation in knockout. </p>

<p>J Hepatol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 July 01. </p>

</text></tei>