<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4908911" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: To identify consumer information needs </p>

<p>about paracetamol, the most commonly used analgesic 
and antipyretic worldwide. </p>

<p>Design: Retrospective analysis of medicines questions </p>

<p>from the public. </p>

<p>Main outcome measures: Enquiry profile: </p>

<p>demographics, enquiry type and concurrent medicines 
included in paracetamol calls; question themes derived 
from subset of call narratives. </p>

<p>Results: Paracetamol comprised part of the enquiry in </p>

<p>5.2% of calls (n=6367). The caller age distribution for 
paracetamol calls was skewed towards a younger cohort, 
with 45.2% made by those aged 25-44 vs 37.5% in 'rest 
of calls'. Significantly more paracetamol-related calls 
were made for a child (23.7%) compared with 'rest of 
calls' (12.7%, p&lt;0.001). The most frequent concurrently 
asked about medicines were codeine (11%, n=1521) and 
ibuprofen (6.4%, n=884). Questions underpinned by 
paracetamol risk (interaction, use in pregnancy/lactation 
or other safety concerns) predominated (55.8%). When 
individual paracetamol enquiry types were compared with 
'rest of calls', efficacy was most frequent (24.9% vs 
22.8%); however, interaction (21.5% vs 14.8%), 
administration (15.5% vs 11%) and pregnancy/lactation 
(13.8% vs 8.3%) categories were more prevalent for 
paracetamol calls (all p&lt;0.001). Enquiry type frequency 
also varied by patient age group, with questions about 
administration more common in younger groups and 
efficacy dominating in those over 45. Narrative analysis of 
over-represented paracetamol enquiry types showed 
specific concerns relevant to life stages: young children, 
those of reproductive age and the elderly. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Consumers have many concerns about </p>

<p>the use of paracetamol that may be under-recognised by 
healthcare providers, with the nature of enquiries 
differing across life stages. These concerns are not 
adequately addressed by available consumer information. 
Improving access to targeted information about 
paracetamol would promote the safe and effective use of 
this common medicine. </p>

<p>widely available over the counter (OTC) in 
the UK and Australia. 
1 2 Although its mech-
anism of action is poorly understood, para-
cetamol remains popular due to tolerability 
and safety when taken at recommended 
doses. However, in an overdose-whether by 
a large single dose or repeated suprathera-
peutic dosing-
3 irreversible hepatotoxicity 
represents a global source of morbidity. </p>

<p>4-7 </p>

<p>The serious health ramifications of the 
potential and proven misuse of paracetamol 
demonstrates an opportunity for improve-
ment in the provision of consumer-oriented 
resources and justifies research into con-
sumer information needs. 
Despite its widespread use, consumer infor-
mation needs about paracetamol have not 
been well characterised in the literature. This 
is highlighted by a recent British Medical 
Journal (BMJ) editorial stating that 'import-
ant questions remain unanswered'. 
2 While 
the editorial sought to address three general-
ised questions about this common medicine, 
paracetamol is used by distinct populations 
spanning across life stages, who have varying 
information-seeking priorities. These include 
young children, 
8 pregnant women 
9 and the 
elderly. 
10 For instance, since paracetamol is 
commonly administered to infants, queries </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Our database of over 100 000 calls made over 
eight consecutive years by the Australian help-
seeking public represents an untapped resource 
for identifying consumer medicines information 
gaps and concerns. 
▪ The large sample size of paracetamol calls 
enabled unique questions for various patient life 
stages to be identified. 
▪ Collected data permitted both quantitative and 
narrative analysis, giving detailed insight into 
consumer concerns, particularly in the areas of 
interaction and administration of paracetamol. 
▪ Limitations include sampling bias; people who 
contact medicines call centres may have different 
information needs from the wider population. </p>

<p>Lau SM, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010860. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010860 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>from parents may differ in nature from those from the 
general population. 
11 Additionally, paracetamol is avail-
able in various combination formulations such as 
codeine for acute pain, with proven analgesic syner-
gism. 
12 The diverse side effect profiles and indications 
for combination products may result in unidentified dif-
ferences in consumers' information needs. 
Consumers may seek information about medicines 
from a variety of sources, 
6 including medical practi-
tioners, pharmacists, the internet, medicines labelling 
and information leaflets. For paracetamol, written infor-
mation plays a significant role due to its OTC availability. 
Health and medicines call centres are also used as a 
resource in Australia 
13 and internationally. 
14-16 Studies 
of queries handled by such helplines represent a largely 
untapped repository for researching consumer medi-
cines information gaps or concerns. This study aimed to 
characterise consumer information needs about para-
cetamol through analysis of medicines call centre data. 
This may serve to guide the practice of health profes-
sionals when prescribing or providing information about 
this frequently used medicine, to promote its safe and 
effective use. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Data collection 
We used data from the National Prescribing Service 
(NPS) MedicineWise (formerly NPS Medicines Line), 
operated by clinical pharmacists of Mater Health 
Services, Brisbane, between September 2002 and June 
2010. This call centre was available to consumers 
Australia-wide for medicine-related questions. Since data 
from our observational study were originally routinely 
collected as part of a health service without specific a 
priori research goals, research was conducted and 
reported in accordance with the REporting of studies 
Conducted using Observational Routinely-collected 
health Data (RECORD) guideline, 
17 an extension of the 
STrengthening the Reporting of OBservational studies 
in Epidemiology (STROBE) guidelines. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Details of each call were captured on a standardised 
form and entered into a <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Access</rs> database. 
These included demographics, enquiry type, relation-
ship of caller to patient and motivation for calling. For 
each call, up to three generic medicines relating to the 
question were recorded and categorised by the 
Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) classification 
system of medicines. 
19 Of the five ATC levels, we exam-
ined medicine classes at the ATC3 level, which labels 
medicines according to their pharmacological subgroup 
(eg, antihistamines-systemic), as well as at the ATC5 
level, which identifies the chemical substance (eg, chlor-
pheniramine). Caller location was identified by postal 
code and grouped by state/territory and Accessibility/ 
Remoteness Index of Australia (ARIA), a measure of the 
remoteness of areas from service centres. 
20 The relative 
population ratio was determined by dividing percentage </p>

<p>of paracetamol calls from each ARIA category by per-
centage of population living in each ARIA category. 
Narrative for calls between January 2009 and June 2010 
were also recorded electronically. Calls involving para-
cetamol in the question were extracted for analysis. 
Remaining calls were classified as 'rest of calls'. We 
excluded calls that only involved a voicemail request for 
Consumer Medicines Information (CMI) leaflets. </p>

<p>Quantitative analysis 
We conducted a retrospective quantitative analysis on all 
paracetamol-related calls. Comparisons between paraceta-
mol and 'rest of calls' were performed using a χ 
2 test for 
categorical data. Each call was originally coded for 1 of 25 
enquiry types. These were collapsed into seven question 
categories: 'efficacy' (indications for use, medicine com-
parisons, effectiveness for specific conditions or symp-
toms); 'interaction'; 'other safety' (side effects or cautions 
for use), 'administration' (dose, administration, formula-
tion or storage issues); safety in 'pregnancy and/or lacta-
tion'; 'logistics' (availability or cost) and 'miscellaneous'. 
Enquiry types were compared by patient age groups and 
other life stages, for example, during pregnancy or breast 
feeding. Concurrent medicines included in paracetamol 
calls were also compared by age groups and a special 
population, pregnant women. A two-sided p-value &lt;0.05 
was considered significant. The data were exported to 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">V.21</rs> for analysis (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corp.</rs>. SPSS Statistics 
for Windows, 23 edn. New York: IBM Corp, 2015). </p>

<p>Narrative analysis 
Three highly ranked enquiry types where paracetamol 
calls were over-represented compared with 'rest of calls' 
('interaction', 'administration' and 'pregnancy/lacta-
tion') were selected for narrative analysis. Two investiga-
tors (SML and TMM) independently coded the content 
of questions within each data set and created categories, 
grouped under higher order headings or themes. 
Coding differences were resolved through discussion 
until consensus was reached. Themes for interaction 
and administration calls were compared by age group. 
Interactions were further explored based on whether 
the call was: (1) directed towards a specific indication 
( pain, cough and cold, etc); (2) sourcing information 
on potential interactions for their medicines list includ-
ing paracetamol or (3) incidental, where paracetamol 
was not part of the enquiry. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
A total of 123 217 calls were available for analysis. Of 
these, 5.2% (n=6367) had paracetamol recorded as a 
medicine directly relating to the question. Whether 
paracetamol statistics were compared with 'rest of calls' 
longitudinally (annually) or collectively for the 8-year 
period, enquiry demographics were remarkably consist-
ent. Calls originated from all Australian states and terri-
tories, with metropolitan, rural and remote dwellers all </p>



<p>Lau SM, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010860. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010860 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>well represented (relative population ratio living in each 
ARIA category ranged between 0.6 and 1.09). The 
majority of paracetamol calls were from females 
(80.5%), which was not significantly greater than for 
'rest of calls' (76.5%, p=0.05). There was a bimodal dis-
tribution for caller age, with peaks at 30 and 70 years. 
Contrastingly, patient age distribution was trimodal, with 
an additional peak at &lt;1 year. Compared with 'rest of 
calls', the distribution of caller age for paracetamol calls 
was skewed towards a younger cohort, with 45.2% made 
by the 25-44 age group versus 37.5% in 'rest of calls'. 
Paracetamol calls were significantly more often for 
patients aged 14 and under (22.1%) versus 'rest of calls' 
(10.3%, p&lt;0.001). Correspondingly, significantly more 
paracetamol-related calls were made for a child (23.7%) 
compared with 'rest of calls' (12.7%, p&lt;0.001). Within 
calls made about paracetamol, callers for children were 
much more likely to be female (92.1%) than calls made 
for themselves or others (76.8%, p&lt;0.001). Over 90% of 
paracetamol calls were prompted by one of three 
reasons: inadequate information (47.9%), second 
opinion (27.2%) or a worrying symptom (15%). 
Compared with '\rest of calls', more calls were made for 
a second opinion (27.2% vs 23.3%, p&lt;0.001). 
The most frequent concurrently asked about medi-
cines (ATC5) in paracetamol calls were codeine (11%, 
n=1521) and ibuprofen (6.4%, n=884), with the remain-
der of concurrent medicines each comprising &lt;2% of 
paracetamol calls (in rank order: tramadol, dextropro-
poxyphene, oxycodone, pseudoephedrine, meloxicam, 
diclofenac, celecoxib, aspirin). Of the top 10 medicines, 
9 are indicated for analgesia, with pseudoephedrine (a 
decongestant) the only exception. Codeine and ibupro-
fen were ranked first or second across all life stages 
except in those aged 65 years or older, where tramadol 
ranked second (table 1). 
The most common pharmacological classes (ATC3) 
included in paracetamol calls were non-steroidal anti-
inflammatory and antirheumatic medicines (12.8%, 
n=1778), followed by cough suppressants (11.4%, 
n=1578) (table 2). These were in the top three ATC3 
classes across all patient age groups. The third ranked 
class in the younger age groups (&lt;1, 1-4, 5-24 years) was 
antihistamines, with opioids ranking in the top three for 
older groups. 
Overall, enquiry types underpinned by paracetamol 
risk predominated (interaction, use in pregnancy and/ 
or lactation or other safety concerns), constituting 
55.8% of calls (table 3). When individual paracetamol 
enquiry types were compared with 'rest of calls', 
although efficacy was most frequent (24.9% vs 22.8%), 
interaction (21.5% vs 14.8%), administration (15.5% vs 
11%) and pregnancy/lactation (13.8% vs 8.3%) calls 
occurred significantly more frequently for paracetamol 
calls (all p&lt;0.001). 
The frequency of enquiry types also varied when com-
pared by age groups. Administration enquiries were 
more common in younger groups, comprising </p>

<p>Table 1 
Top five Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) fifth-level medicines included in paracetamol calls by age group </p>

<p>&lt;1 Year </p>

<p>1-4 Years </p>

<p>5-24 Years </p>

<p>25-44 Years </p>

<p>45-64 Years </p>

<p>65+ Years </p>

<p>Pregnancy/lactation </p>

<p>Codeine 
Ibuprofen 
Pseudoephedrine 
Oxymetazoline 
Chlorpheniramine </p>

<p>Ibuprofen 
Codeine 
Amoxicillin 
Brompheniramine 
Chlorpheniramine </p>

<p>Codeine 
Ibuprofen 
Promethazine 
Pseudoephedrine 
Dextropropoxyphene </p>

<p>Codeine 
Ibuprofen 
Pseudoephedrine </p>

<p>Doxylamine 
Tramadol </p>

<p>Codeine 
Ibuprofen 
Oxycodone 
Meloxicam 
Dextropropoxyphene </p>

<p>Codeine 
Tramadol 
Celecoxib 
Meloxicam 
Glucosamine </p>

<p>Codeine 
Ibuprofen 
Pseudoephedrine </p>

<p>Doxylamine 
Oxymetazoline </p>

<p>Lau SM, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010860. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010860 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>approximately one-quarter of calls for patients aged 
under 24 years (table 3). Conversely, efficacy predomi-
nated in older age groups, at nearly one-third of enqui-
ries in those over 45. Logistics questions were more 
common in this group, comprising 4.3-5.4% of enqui-
ries in the over 45s vs 1.1-2.9% in younger groups. Calls 
about safety also increased in incidence with age. 
Enquiries about pregnancy and lactation were frequent 
in age groups 0-4 and 25-44, most likely representing 
infant and mother patient groups. 
There were some differences in the call profile for 
questions involving paracetamol alone versus those 
involving a concurrently enquired about analgesic 
(codeine or ibuprofen). Female callers predominated 
for questions about efficacy, interactions or safety. For 
paracetamol and ibuprofen calls, the caller was com-
monly of reproductive age (25-44 years) and asking on 
behalf of a child in 39.0% of calls, which was signifi-
cantly greater than for paracetamol calls without </p>

<p>ibuprofen (21.3%, p&lt;0.001). In contrast, paracetamol 
and codeine questions were more evenly distributed 
across caller age range and were less frequently made on 
behalf of a child (17.3% vs 22.9% for paracetamol calls 
without codeine). </p>

<p>Narrative analysis 
The enquiry types 'interaction', 'administration' and 
'pregnancy/lactation' were selected for narrative ana-
lysis, with 65%, 58.7% and 57.5% of calls, respectively, 
available for exploration of themes. A summary of narra-
tive themes and question examples by life stage is pro-
vided in the online supplementary appendix tables 1 
and 2. </p>

<p>Interaction calls 
Fifteen themes were identified from 895 interaction 
calls. The major theme was safety (85.1%, n=762), with a 
small percentage addressing therapeutic strategy (6.1%, </p>

<p>Table 2 Top three Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) third levels included in paracetamol calls by age group </p>

<p>&lt;1 Year 
1-4 Years 
5-24 Years 
25-44 Years 
45-64 Years 
65+ Years </p>

<p>Cough 
suppressants 
Non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory 
and antirheumatics 
Antihistamines-
systemic </p>

<p>Non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory 
and antirheumatics 
Cough 
suppressants 
Antihistamines-
systemic </p>

<p>Cough 
suppressants 
Non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory 
and antirheumatics 
Antihistamines-
systemic </p>

<p>Cough 
suppressants 
Non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory 
and antirheumatics 
Opioids </p>

<p>Non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory 
and antirheumatics 
Cough 
suppressants 
Opioids </p>

<p>Non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory 
and antirheumatics 
Opioids 
Cough 
suppressants </p>

<p>Table 3 Frequencies of enquiry types for paracetamol and 'rest of calls' and enquiry types by age groups for paracetamol 
calls </p>

<p>Paracetamol calls vs 'rest of calls' </p>

<p>Enquiry type </p>

<p>Paracetamol calls (%) 
n=6367 </p>

<p>'Rest of calls' (%) 
n=116 850 
p Value* </p>

<p>Efficacy 
24.9 
22.8 
&lt;0.001 
Interaction † 
21.5 
14.8 
&lt;0.001 
Other safety † 
20.6 
32.6 
&lt;0.001 
Administration 
15.5 
11.0 
&lt;0.001 
Pregnancy/lactation † 
13.7 
8.3 
&lt;0.001 
Logistics 
3.3 
5.8 
&lt;0.001 
Miscellaneous 
0.5 
4.4 
&lt;0.001 
Missing 
0 
0.3 </p>

<p>Paracetamol calls by age groups (years) (n=6367) 
Enquiry type 
&lt;1 (%) 
1-4 (%) 
5-24 (%) 
25-44 (%) 
45-64 (%) 
65+ (%) </p>

<p>Efficacy 
15.8 
24.1 
19.6 
17.7 
31.9 
31.3 
Interaction 
10.5 
28.2 
29.3 
22.2 
21.7 
20.0 
Other safety 
9.3 
9.5 
15.3 
17.2 
27.4 
27.7 
Administration 
17.5 
29.4 
24.6 
9.0 
13.8 
14.7 
Pregnancy/lactation 
45.3 
7.9 
8.3 
31.6 
0.2 
0.4 
Logistics 
1.5 
0.7 
2.9 
1.7 
4.3 
5.4 
Miscellaneous 
0.2 
0.2 
0 
0.6 
0.6 
0.5 </p>

<p>*All statistical comparisons between paracetamol-related calls and 'rest of calls' used χ 
2 analyses. 
 †Enquiry types related to safety. </p>



<p>Lau SM, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010860. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010860 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>n=55). The remainder did not primarily address para-
cetamol interactions. Across all age groups, the most 
common objective was minimising medication risk, 
asking about the safety of prospectively administering 
paracetamol with another medicine (Can I take Panadol 
with Mobic?). This comprised 73.6% of all interaction 
enquiries (n=659). Another question common to all age 
groups was whether paracetamol could be used shortly 
after taking another medicine (Can I take paracetamol if I 
had tramadol 50 mg 6 hours ago?) (6.9%, n=62). While 
there was no specific theme identified for patients 
&lt;1 year, callers for the 1-4-year group were concerned 
about combining medicines prior to administration 
(Can I combine Dimetapp Elixir and Panadol to give to my 
two year old?). Calls for patients aged 5-24 concerned 
potential interactions with lifestyle products, such as 
alcohol or supplements (Can I drink alcohol after taking 
Phenergan and Panadol?). For groups aged 25-44, 45-64 
and 65+, a common theme was the appropriate choice 
of medicine for a particular purpose, based on current 
medication (What analgesics are safe to take with Zoloft and 
Xanax?). Finally, both the 25-44 and 65+ groups asked 
about the potential for a worrying symptom being 
caused by a medicine interaction (Could paracetamol and 
esomeprazole have caused stomach cramps?). 
When interaction calls were further categorised, 
enquiries directed towards a specific indication com-
prised the majority in the &lt;1 and 1-4 age groups 
(59.0-64.6%). For all other age groups, calls sourcing 
information on potential interactions for a medicines 
list, including paracetamol, dominated. </p>

<p>Administration calls 
For the 582 administration enquiries, 22 themes were 
identified. They could be broadly grouped as enquiries 
relating to dose (37.6%, n=219), therapeutic strategy 
(21.2%, n=124), medicine constituents (10.1%, n=59) 
and safety concerns (9.6%, n=56), with the remainder 
not targeting paracetamol as the primary medicine or 
addressing issues such as pharmacokinetics. Common 
dose-related questions asked across all age groups were 
the appropriate amount or volume (45.7% of dose ques-
tions, n=100) (What dose can I give of Panadol for my son?) 
and a safety check of a proposed dose (14.2%, n=31) (Is 
it okay to take 4-6 tablets of paracetamol per day?). 
Two age-specific themes in the &lt;1 year group were 
related to therapeutic strategy, specifically where callers 
sought to achieve the best therapeutic outcome. First, 
callers sought to verify the appropriateness of adminis-
tration in a specific setting, usually for a specified age 
(Can I give children's Panadol to my 10-month-old baby?) or 
indication (Can I give children's Panadol 500 mg tablets for 
fever to my 3 years old?). Second, management of redosing 
paracetamol after vomiting or diarrhoea was a common 
concern (Can I give my child another dose of Panadol if she 
immediately vomited it up after I administered it?). These two 
themes were replicated in the 1-4 age group. In add-
ition, callers for those aged 1-4 asked about paracetamol </p>

<p>administration with food or drink (Can Painstop be given 
with juice?) and the action to take or outcomes after an 
unintentional overdose (My 1 year old has swallowed at 
least 1/2 a paracetamol tablet-will she be okay?). 
Age-specific themes identified for patients aged 5-
24 years were largely dose related. These included dose 
calculation (Should you dose paracetamol by weight or age in 
children?), verifying dose timing (Is it okay to give my 
5-year-old 9.5 mL of Panadol syrup every 4 hours for a fever?) 
and repeating a dose (Can I repeat the dose of Panadol from 
my child's fever after the last dose 5 hours ago?). As for the 
0-4 age group, outcome after an unintentional overdose 
was also a common theme (Have I given too much Painstop 
to my 10-year-old child?). 
In the 25-44 age group, use of multiple paracetamol-
containing medicines was a focus (Can I take Mersyndol 
1 hour after taking 1000 mg of Panamax?). In contrast, 
callers aged 45-64 were interested in alternative anal-
gesic options (Is it okay to take Panadeine Forte instead of 
Endone?) and medicine constituents, whether excipient 
or active (Can you tell me the gluten content for Panamax, 
Tramal and Mobic?). 
Several age-specific themes were identified in the 65+ 
group. Medicine constituent questions predominated, 
with callers commonly asking for a direct comparison 
between medicines (What is the difference between Panadol 
and Panadol Osteo?). Enquiries about the maximum per-
missible dose were prevalent (What is the maximum dose of 
paracetamol that I can take for osteoarthritis pain?). The con-
comitant use of a second paracetamol medicine was 
another common theme, as with the 25-44 age group. 
The final theme related to safety, where callers had a 
specific health concern about paracetamol (Will taking 
four paracetamol a day harm my liver?). </p>

<p>Pregnancy/lactation calls 
There were broadly two types of questions related to 
paracetamol in pregnancy or breast feeding. Callers, 
usually the patient themselves, were either seeking 
reassurance of safety after exposure to paracetamol (Will 
it matter if I have taken Di-Gesic while breast feeding?) or 
trying to minimise risk prior to medicine exposure. Risk 
aversion questions included safety of use at a particular 
gestation or while breast feeding (Can I take paracetamol 
if I am [a specified number of weeks] pregnant/breast 
feeding?) or seeking to quantify medication risk (What are 
the effects of paracetamol on my baby when breast feeding?). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
We found that consumers have many unanswered ques-
tions about paracetamol. The nature of their concerns 
varied with patient age or life stage. Safety was the major 
area of enquiry across ages, with interest in interaction 
and side effect risk increasing with age. Effectiveness of 
the medicine was an issue for all, but especially for pre-
school children and older adults. Pregnancy or lactation 
questions focused on minimising paracetamol risk prior </p>

<p>Lau SM, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010860. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010860 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>to maternal, fetal or infant exposure or seeking a risk 
management strategy after inadvertent exposure, while 
administration was an issue in young patients where 
dosing can be difficult. 
Previous research has investigated patient, carer and/ 
or health professional knowledge and attitudes about 
the use (dosing and unintentional risks) of paraceta-
mol. 
21-23 These studies identified paracetamol knowl-
edge gaps for many consumers, as well as healthcare 
providers having varied knowledge of appropriate use. 
However, it was difficult to identify a question pattern 
about paracetamol use from these publications due to 
diversity in study design. Participants were commonly 
recruited from a general practice waiting room where 
they generally responded to questions constructed by 
the investigators. This is not the same sample frame as 
our database of spontaneous calls. In general, misinfor-
mation about risks was a recurring theme; and this is 
what our paper also shows. While 'greater education of 
health care workers is required in order to provide fam-
ilies with appropriate information' 
23 was recommended, 
little research has addressed health professional 
responses to the information gaps consumers have 
about paracetamol. Generally, healthcare providers 
underestimate consumer concerns about medication 
risk 
24-26 and do not adequately acknowledge these con-
cerns. 
25 27 28 This mismatch was also highlighted in the 
recent BMJ editorial 
2 that addressed only three broad 
questions as important to paracetamol consumers (effi-
cacy, adverse effects and dose). Our study provides the 
consumer perspective to this issue. 
The primary prompt for paracetamol calls was inad-
equate information, which highlights the lack of infor-
mation provided with OTC medicines. In the UK, 
general sales list medicines, 
29 which are freely available 
in supermarkets, thus come without advice from health 
professionals. Mandatory information supplied with 
OTC 
medicines 
varies 
between 
countries. 
Pharmaceutical companies in the UK must supply 
approved Patient Information Leaflets with all medicines 
unless all necessary information specified by the 
Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory Agency 
(including indications, contraindications, general dosing 
instructions and side effects) is included on the label. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>The electronic Medicines Compendium, 
31 targeted at 
health professionals, provides additional Summaries of 
Product Characteristics. The equivalent Australian docu-
ments are CMI leaflets and Product Information, 
neither of which is mandatory for OTC medicines. Aside 
from Panamax, 
32 there are no accessible CMI for 
common paracetamol-only formulations. Importantly, 
none of these consumer resources provide strategies to 
prevent or reduce risk from common occurrences such 
as redosing after vomiting or reassurance, where appro-
priate, when planned or inadvertent exposure to para-
cetamol occurs. Addressing consumer OTC medicine 
concerns requires information in CMI (or equivalent) to 
be comprehensible and actionable, targeted for life </p>

<p>stage. Improving these aspects for paracetamol should 
be a focus of future research. 
While written information is available to varying stan-
dards in the UK and Australia, medical professionals 
remain the most trusted information source. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Consumers are, however, unlikely to consult their 
general practitioner about OTC medicine use. </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>Furthermore, research shows that healthcare profes-
sionals tend to drive and dominate communication 
about medicines in consultations, rendering it critical 
for deficiencies in patient knowledge to be brought to 
the forefront of health professional awareness. </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>Pharmacists may therefore play a pivotal role in provid-
ing information as the first and potentially only 
face-to-face contact. 
36 Australian research has shown that 
the majority of OTC medicines for children are still 
sourced from pharmacies rather than supermarkets, </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>with many considering pharmacists medicines experts 
and preferring spoken over written information. </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>Consideration could also be given to changing the OTC 
status to pharmacist-only or prescription status, as has 
been called for in research and the media. </p>

<p>38 39 </p>

<p>Medicines most commonly enquired about in combin-
ation with paracetamol were analgesics, especially 
codeine and ibuprofen, despite concomitant use in 
adults being safe and effective for additive analgesia at 
recommended doses. 
40 41 The differing caller and ques-
tion profile for concurrent analgesia involving paraceta-
mol is important for clinicians to know. Health 
professionals should also be aware that parents are con-
cerned about interactions between the various medicines, 
including paracetamol, antihistamines and ibuprofen. 
While both the UK and Australian written medicines 
information contain limited details about medicines with 
potential for interactions; 
25 27 consideration to include a 
similar list of safe medications would provide reassurance 
where there is common concurrent use. 
This study has several strengths. A large number of 
calls made to Medicines Line were available over eight 
consecutive years. Paracetamol call distribution 
approached relative population frequency. The data also 
permitted both quantitative and narrative analysis, giving 
detailed insight into consumer concerns. Age groups 
were well represented in the enquiry type subsets for 
interaction and administration, so they can be consid-
ered a representative sample for thematic analysis by 
age. Limitations include sampling bias; people who 
contact medicines call centres may have different infor-
mation needs from the wider population. This study 
highlighted those consumers who had sufficient con-
cerns about paracetamol use to seek information, but 
fails to capture the reverse-consumers who assume that 
paracetamol is safe due to its OTC status. 
42 The calls are 
also from an Australian population and may not accur-
ately reflect concerns held by consumers in other 
countries. 
Consumers have many concerns about paracetamol 
use that are likely to be under-recognised by healthcare </p>



<p>Lau SM, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010860. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010860 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>providers, with different patient age groups and life 
stages having unique questions that should be consid-
ered when targeting information towards patients. 
Therapeutic strategies to minimise paracetamol risk are 
not adequately addressed by available information. 
Improving information may be challenging due to the 
OTC status of paracetamol and the diversity of commer-
cial brands. Strategies such as increasing pharmacist 
involvement with paracetamol supply may be useful, but 
may necessitate a change in its unrestricted availability 
in other places such as supermarkets. Ultimately, the 
accessibility of information that the public wants to know 
needs to be targeted to optimise the safe and effective 
use of paracetamol. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors would like to acknowledge NPS 
MedicineWise (formerly National Prescribing Service, Australia), funder of 
NPS Medicines Line and service provider since July 2010. They would also 
like to thank Mater Health Services for providing the raw service data from 
September 2002 to 30 June 2010. </p>

<p>Contributors TMM and MLvD provided supervision, and conceived and 
designed the study. SML conducted the literature review and data analysis. 
SML, TMM and MLvD interpreted the data, and drafted and critically revised 
the manuscript. SML, TMM and MLvD as guarantors accept full responsibility 
for the work and/or the conduct of the study; they had access to the data and 
controlled the decision to publish. </p>

<p>Funding This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in 
the public, commercial or not-for-profit sector. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval This study was approved by Mater Health Services Brisbane, 
Human Research Ethics Committee (LNR submission 2012-68) and University 
of Queensland School of Medicine Low Risk Ethical Review Committee 
(2014-SOMILRE-0098). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Lau SM, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010860. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010860 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>





<p>Lau SM, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010860. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010860 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>