<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4809187" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: In this manuscript, we estimate the </p>

<p>incidence and identify risk factors for sudden 
unexpected death in a socioeconomically and racially 
diverse population in one county in North Carolina. 
Estimates of the incidence and risk factors contributing 
to sudden death vary widely. The Sudden Unexpected 
Death in North Carolina (SUDDEN) project is a 
population-based investigation of the incidence and 
potential causes of sudden death. </p>

<p>out-of-hospital deaths in Wake County, North Carolina, 
were screened to identify presumed sudden 
unexpected death among free-living residents between 
the ages of 18 and 64 years. Death certificate, public 
and medical records were reviewed and adjudicated to 
confirm sudden unexpected death cases. </p>

<p>Results: Following adjudication, 190 sudden </p>

<p>unexpected deaths including 122 men and 68 women 
were identified. Estimated incidence was 32.1 per 
100 000 person-years overall: 42.7 among men and 
22.4 among women. The majority of victims were 
white, unmarried men over age 55 years, with 
unwitnessed deaths at home. Hypertension and 
dyslipidaemia were common in men and women. 
African-American women dying from sudden 
unexpected death were over-represented. Women who 
were under age 55 years with coronary disease 
accounted for over half of female participants with 
coronary artery disease. </p>

<p>Conclusions: The overall estimated incidence of </p>

<p>sudden unexpected death may account for 
approximately 10% of all deaths classified as 'natural'. 
Women have a lower estimated incidence of sudden 
unexpected death than men. However, we found no 
major differences in age or comorbidities between men 
and women. African-Americans and young women 
with coronary disease are at risk for sudden 
unexpected death. </p>

<p>deaths in populations, particularly for deaths 
that occur earlier than expected, allows 
health officials to establish disease preven-
tion goals, priorities, and strategies' </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-CDC 
MMWR, 2 May 2014. 
The Sudden Unexpected Death in North 
Carolina (SUDDEN) project is a population-
based investigation of the incidence and 
causes of all out-of-hospital natural, unex-
pected deaths within defined populations. </p>

<p>3   KEY QUESTIONS </p>

<p>What is already known about this subject? </p>

<p>▸ Sudden death is the leading cause of deaths in 
adults in the Western world, but current esti-
mates of annual incidence vary widely. A family 
history of sudden death, depressed left ventricu-
lar function, coronary heart disease, hyperten-
sion and diabetes mellitus is one of the most 
important risk factors for sudden death. </p>

<p>What does this study add? </p>

<p>▸ Previous cohort studies of sudden death victims 
have been performed on middle-class and 
largely Caucasian populations. A requirement for 
known timing of death since last seen alive and 
free of apparent symptoms may lead to under-
reporting of cases among socioeconomically 
diverse populations and minorities. The Sudden 
Unexpected Death in North Carolina (SUDDEN) 
project aims to increase our understanding of 
the causes of sudden death and identify high-
risk populations by utilising a prospective, 
population-based methodology in diverse popu-
lations. No time-limiting criteria are required, but 
deaths must be naturally occurring and unex-
pected. The results from year 1 of the SUDDEN 
project show that African-American women and 
young women with coronary disease are at risk 
for sudden unexpected death. </p>

<p>How might this impact on clinical practice? </p>

<p>▸ By identifying vulnerable populations at risk for 
sudden death, such as African-Americans and 
young women with coronary disease, clinicians 
and policymakers will be able to develop appro-
priate prevention programmes. </p>

<p>Lewis ME, Lin F-C, Nanavati P, et al. Open Heart 2016;3:e000321. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000321 </p>



<p>Arrhythmias and sudden death </p>

<p>Cases are recorded regardless of known timing of death 
or symptom onset, meaning the incidence and causes of 
sudden death are not prejudged by case selection cri-
teria. 
4-6 Description of significant conditions at the time 
of death allows for identification of risk factors for 
sudden death, may lead to policy changes to improve 
the accuracy of death certificates and other death 
records and may lead to focused strategies to prevent 
sudden death. 
7-10 3 In the USA and many other indus-
trialised countries, women outlive men and experience 
fewer cardiovascular events, but the reasons for this 
enhanced survival are not clear. </p>

<p>11 12   In this report, we describe differences in incidence 
and significant conditions by gender over 1 year in one 
county in North Carolina. </p>

<p>METHODS 
The detailed design and methods of the SUDDEN 
project have been described previously. 
6 From 3 March 
2013 to 2 March 2014, all deaths identified by emer-
gency medical services (EMS) in Wake County, North 
Carolina, of persons between ages 18 and 64 years were 
screened to identify presumed sudden unexpected 
death (SUD) victims. We excluded those who survived to 
hospital, experienced an expected death or traumatic </p>

<p>death or who were not residents of Wake County, North 
Carolina (figure 1). 
A committee of 3 cardiologists unaffiliated with the 
study, selected for each case at random from a panel of 
10 cardiologists, adjudicated 190 participants into the 
SUDDEN cohort based on available EMS narrative, 
medical records (hospital or physician records within 
5 years of death), medical examiner documents and 
death certificates. 
The panel of cardiologists adjudicated presumed cases 
by excluding subjects who were terminally ill, had a 
'do-not-resuscitate' order, resided in a nursing facility or 
had a lethal toxicology report. Victims were not 
excluded if they had traumatic injuries secondary to a 
cardiac aetiology or had a non-lethal toxicology report. 
There was substantial agreement between the three adju-
dicators (κ value=0.68). Data and inclusions were veri-
fied by standard quality assurance protocols. 
Electronic death certificates as well as a copy of 
the original death certificate from the register 
of deeds were obtained for all 190 participants, half of 
which were signed medical examiner cases. Medical 
records were acquired for 68% of participants (table 1). 
There were no significant differences by gender in 
medical record retrieval rates or in the medical exam-
iner cases (table 1). </p>

<p>Figure 1 Excluded and 
adjudicated male and female 
referrals-living and deceased 
participants were referred to the 
Sudden Unexpected Death in 
North Carolina (SUDDEN) project 
by emergency medical services 
(EMS) based on the search 
criteria 'presumed cardiac 
etiology'. Referrals were screened 
by exclusion criteria, leaving 211 
males and 99 females presumed 
sudden unexpected deaths 
(SUDs). About 26% of men and 
37% of women were screened 
out because they were over the 
age of 65 years. After medical 
records and death certificates 
were obtained for each 
participant, a committee of three 
cardiologists adjudicated 122 
men (64%) and 68 women (36%) 
into the SUD in North Carolina 
(SUDDEN) cohort. </p>



<p>Lewis ME, Lin F-C, Nanavati P, et al. Open Heart 2016;3:e000321. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000321 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>Clinical notes were used to determine sudden death 
risk factors and significant conditions. Age, race, marital 
status, educational attainment, cause of death and 
address were noted from North Carolina death certifi-
cate data. Location at death and death-witnessed status 
were obtained from EMS records. Socioeconomic status 
was estimated by matching the primary residence 
address to 2010 US Census tract data. Medical records 
were considered available if the participant had either 
hospital or physician records within 5 years of death. 
Medical records were requested for all patients and were 
provided at the discretion of the collaborating institu-
tions, hospitals or medical practices. </p>

<p>Statistical methods 
Demographics and clinical characteristics of participants 
are reported in frequency and proportions for categor-
ical variables, and means and SDs for continuous vari-
ables. Gender difference in these variables was assessed 
using Fisher exact tests, χ 
2 tests or two-sample t tests 
when appropriate. The same approach compared 
female participants between SUDDEN victims and total 
deceased in Wake County and in the living population 
of Wake County. EMS reports, clinical risk factors and 
cause of death on death certificate were compared 
between male and female SUDDEN subjects and 
reported as ORs with 95% CIs. Subgroup analysis, strati-
fied by coronary disease as the cause of death, was con-
ducted to explore the difference in death age between 
males and females. All of the analyses were conducted 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>). We consider two-
sided p value &lt;0.05 statistically significant. 
Prior to the analysis, a power analysis determined a 
total number of 170 participants (85 males and 85 
females), assuming an OR of females as 2.5%, and 40% 
among those participants with a positive outcome are 
males, under 0.05 type I error probability and 0.8 statis-
tical power. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Case selection and demographics 
Excluded subjects had more non-natural causes of death 
and included subjects had more cardiac causes of death. 
Nearly 90% of excluded subjects were medical examiner 
cases. Compared with excluded subjects, included sub-
jects were older, more commonly female and 
African-American, and were more likely to have died 
from non-cardiac natural causes (data not shown). </p>

<p>Main outcome measures 
Figure 2 shows the age distribution of participants by 
gender and ethnicity, and table 2 compares participants 
to all decedents and living Wake County residents. 
Combining the SUDDEN cohort and living Wake 
County cohort data, the estimated incidence of SUD in 
the 18-64 age group was 32.1/100 000 of the population 
and was significantly different between men and women 
(42.7/100 000 among men and 22.4/100 000 among 
women, OR=0.53, p&lt;0.001, 95% CI 0.39 to 0.72). 
Within the cohort, the average age was 53; 118 partici-
pants (62%) were Caucasian, 66 (35%) were 
African-American, 62 (33%) were married and 128 
(85%) had graduated high school (table 2). Overall, 
there were significantly more African-Americans com-
pared to the living Wake County population (35% vs 
21%, p&lt;0.001), which is accounted for primarily by a sig-
nificant excess of African-American women (43% vs 
23%, p&lt;0.001) and to a lesser extent by an excess of 
African-American men (29% vs 20%, p=0.006). Among 
participants, 122 (64%) were men and 68 (36%) were 
women, significantly different from the proportions of 
living men and women in Wake County but not different 
from 2013 decedents of Wake County. 
There was no difference in average age by gender or 
the proportion of white men and women experiencing 
SUD (table 2). Figure 2, however, shows that African-
American men and women were especially over-
represented in the &gt;55 age group and under-represented 
in the 46-55 age group. There is no difference between </p>

<p>Table 1 Available medical data for SUDDEN men and 
women </p>

<p>Both 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>p 
Value </p>

<p>Death 
certificate </p>

<p>190 (100%) 122 (100%) 68 (100%) 1.000 </p>

<p>Physician 
signed </p>

<p>93 (49%) 
56 (46%) 
37 (54%) 
0.291 </p>

<p>Medical 
examiner 
report </p>

<p>97 (51%) 
66 (54%) 
31 (46%) 
0.291 </p>

<p>Medical 
records </p>

<p>129 (68%) 
80 (66%) 
49 (72%) 
0.419 </p>

<p>Death certificates are signed by either the participant's physician 
or the state medical examiner. Medical records were considered 
available if the participant had either hospital or physician records. 
SUDDEN, Sudden Unexpected Death in North Carolina project. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Sudden Unexpected Death in North Carolina 
(SUDDEN) Gender and Ethnicity by Age-the majority of the 
cohort is over age 55 years, especially black men but with 
exception of white women. Each bar represents the 
percentage of its respective group in each age category. For 
example, the percentage of white men younger than 35 years 
constituted 8% of all white men. </p>

<p>Lewis ME, Lin F-C, Nanavati P, et al. Open Heart 2016;3:e000321. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000321 </p>



<p>Arrhythmias and sudden death </p>

<p>SUDDEN men and women by marital status, annual 
income below $50 000 (data not shown) or educational 
attainment (table 2). Men and women were significantly 
less likely to be married compared to deceased or living 
Wake County residents (table 2, 33% vs 46%, p=0.018, vs 
53%, p&lt;0.001). Men and women were less likely to have 
graduated high school compared to living Wake County 
residents (table 2, 84% vs 90%, p=0.008). </p>

<p>Risk factors in men and women 
Table 3 shows that most participants had hypertension. 
Other common risk factors included dyslipidaemia, 
smoking and body mass index (BMI) &gt;30 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. 
Diabetes, cardiomyopathy and coronary artery disease 
(CAD) are less prevalent in the cohort. There is no stat-
istically significant difference in risk factors between 
men and women (table 3). 
As shown in table 4, 92% of the cohort was dead on 
EMS arrival and in 94% of cases, deaths were unwit-
nessed. More women than men (99% vs 91%) had 
unwitnessed deaths. Only three married participants (all 
men) had a witnessed death. Only 32% of victims were 
last seen alive within 24 h of death. In the remainder, 
the time last seen alive was either unknown or more 
than 24 h. 
The majority had a cardiac cause listed as the immedi-
ate ( primary) cause of death on their death certificate 
(table 5). About 37% had a non-cardiac natural cause 
listed as their primary cause of death; 4% were listed as 
unknown cause of death. There were no cases of sub-
stance abuse listed on the death certificate for this 
cohort. However, medical examiner reports show 29 par-
ticipants (31%) had positive but non-lethal blood or 
urine levels of one or two of the following: cocaine, 
opiates, 
opioids, 
ethanol, 
benzodiazepines 
or 
amphetamines. 
Fewer women had a cardiac cause listed as the 
primary cause of death on their death certificate, and 
more women had an unknown cause of death compared 
with men (table 5). There was no significant difference 
between the proportions of men and women with a non-
cardiac natural cause of death listed as the primary 
cause of death on their death certificate (table 5). 
Death certificates were more likely to attribute older 
men's and women's deaths to CAD, especially for older 
women. However, medical records and medical exam-
iner reports suggest that younger women were more 
likely to have CAD as a risk factor than men of the same 
age (figure 3). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
We have developed an ongoing, population-based case 
registry of SUD in the adult &lt;65 population over 
12 months in a single North Carolina county. At 1 year 
of assessment of such victims, we find that the majority 
of such deaths were unwitnessed and occurred in white, 
unmarried, hypertensive men with an average age of </p>

<p>Table 2 
Demographics of SUDDEN subjects, Wake County decedents and living Wake County residents by gender </p>

<p>SUDDEN </p>

<p>Dead Wake County </p>

<p>Living Wake County </p>

<p>Both </p>

<p>Men (1) </p>

<p>Women (2) </p>

<p>p Value 
(1 vs 2) </p>

<p>Men </p>

<p>Women (3) </p>

<p>p Value 
(2 vs 3) </p>

<p>Men </p>

<p>Women (4) </p>

<p>p Value 
(2 vs 4) </p>

<p>Total # </p>

<p>190 </p>

<p>122 (64%) 
68 (36%) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>796 (61%) </p>

<p>504 (39%) </p>

<p>0.472 
287 151 (49%) 302 680 (51%) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Average age (SD) </p>

<p>53 (9) </p>

<p>53 (9) </p>

<p>53 (9) </p>

<p>0.682 </p>

<p>50.7 (12) </p>

<p>52.7 (10) </p>

<p>0.833 </p>

<p>37.0 (14) </p>

<p>37.4 (14) </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>White </p>

<p>118 (62%) </p>

<p>79 (65%) </p>

<p>39 (57%) </p>

<p>0.351 
497 (63%) </p>

<p>291 (58%) </p>

<p>1.000 
188 837 (66%) 193 366 (64%) </p>

<p>0.259 </p>

<p>Black </p>

<p>66 (35%) </p>

<p>37 (29%) </p>

<p>29 (43%) </p>

<p>0.084 
253 (32%) </p>

<p>186 (37%) </p>

<p>0.344 
56 566 (20%) 
70 149 (23%) &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Married </p>

<p>62 (33%) </p>

<p>40 (33%) </p>

<p>22 (32%) </p>

<p>1.000 
353 (46%) </p>

<p>222 (45%) </p>

<p>0.048 
154 924 (53%) 161 589 (52%) </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>High school graduate 128/150 (85%) 75/89 (84%) 53/61 (87%) </p>

<p>0.815 
627 (82%) </p>

<p>440 (89%) </p>

<p>0.664 
265 374 (90%) 291 044 (93%) </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>Bolded p value signifies a significant difference (p&lt;0.05). All demographics are based on annual incidence for people aged 18-64 years. Data for SUDDEN subjects were gathered from 3 
March 2013 to 3 March 2014. Wake County death statistics were gathered from the NC Department of Health Statistics for 2013. Wake County statistics for living residents were gathered from 
census demographics by the American Community Survey for 2009-2013. 
SUDDEN, Sudden Unexpected Death in North Carolina project. </p>



<p>Lewis ME, Lin F-C, Nanavati P, et al. Open Heart 2016;3:e000321. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000321 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>53 years. In comparison with the general population, 
women were significantly under-represented, and inci-
dence in African-Americans was higher than expected. 
Younger women with coronary disease were more likely 
to die of SUD than men. </p>

<p>Demographics 
Our estimate of the incidence of sudden death is 42.4/ 
100 000 among male residents and 22.4/100 000 among 
female residents between the ages of 18 and 64 years. 
Only 1.5% of participants were both married and had a 
witnessed death, and there were significantly fewer 
married participants compared to all Wake County resi-
dents deceased in 2013 (33% vs 44%, p&lt;0.01). This sup-
ports the observation that marriage is a protective factor 
from sudden death. 
The association between marriage and sudden death 
has been described previously, specifically that marriage 
had beneficial health effects for unemployed women 
by providing an alternative source of financial 
resources and social support. 
13 Within our cohort, 
African-Americans, especially males, accounted for a 
higher proportion of the study population over the age 
of 55 years; whites, especially women, accounted for a 
higher proportion of the population aged 55 years and 
under. Different racial make-up of older and younger 
age groups within our sample suggests that older age as 
a predictor for sudden death may be modified by race. 
African-Americans were over-represented in the cohort </p>

<p>compared to the living population in Wake County 
(35% vs 21%), which is partially accounted for by a sig-
nificant excess of African-American women compared to 
living Wake County residents (43% vs 23%, p&lt;0.001). 
Most participants had hypertension, with dyslipidaemia, 
smoking and BMI &gt;30 kg/m 
2 , and diabetes was also 
present in more than 30% of the cohort. 
Cardiomyopathy and CAD were less prevalent than 
expected. 
There was a significant difference in estimated sudden 
death incidence between men and women in the 
cohort, but there was no difference in age at death or 
comorbidities such as hypertension or CAD. The cardio-
protective effects of oestrogen may lead to less plaque 
and coronary disease. 
14 15 However, the average age of 
men and women was 53, despite the presumed protect-
ive effect of oestrogen. The similarity of average age 
between men and women may be explained by the age 
of the cohort. The average age at menopause is 51 years, 
when women lose a substantial amount of oestrogen, </p>

<p>11   and the average age of the women in our cohort is 53. </p>

<p>Strength of no timing criteria 
Our understanding of the aetiology and risk factors for 
sudden death is limited compared with other acute car-
diovascular events such as myocardial infarction and 
stroke. Overlapping definitions of sudden death have 
contributed to variability in reported incidence rates 
and have impeded the study of sudden death aetiology </p>

<p>Table 3 Risk factors for men and women from clinical notes of SUDDEN subjects with available medical information </p>

<p>Both 
Men 
Women 
OR (95% CI) 
p Value </p>

<p>Available medical information 
181/190 (95) 
116/122 (95) 
65/68 (96) 
1.121 (0.238 to 5.877) 
1.000 
Hypertension 
105 (58) 
65 (56) 
40 (62) 
1.255 (0.645 to 2.447) 
0.531 
Dyslipidaemia 
78 (43) 
48 (41) 
30 (46) 
1.214 (0.629 to 2.344) 
0.534 
Smoker 
68 (38) 
45 (39) 
23 (35) 
0.864 (0.438 to 1.701) 
0.749 
BMI &gt; 30 
59 (33) 
35 (30) 
24 (38) 
1.355 (0.679 to 2.702) 
0.353 
Diabetes 
56 (31) 
32 (28) 
24 (37) 
1.537 (0.764 to 3.089) 
0.241 
Cardiomyopathy 
46 (25) 
27 (23) 
19 (29) 
1.362 (0.648 to 2.856) 
0.380 
CAD 
41 (22) 
27 (23) 
14 (22) 
0.905 (0.408 to 1.992) 
0.855 </p>

<p>The values are given as n (%). The listed comorbidities were identified as potential sudden unexpected death risk factors by the Oregon 
study. Medical information was considered available if participants had records from hospital, physician or medical examiner sources. 
BMI, body mass index; CAD, coronary artery disease; SUDDEN, Sudden Unexpected Death in North Carolina project. </p>

<p>Table 4 EMS reports of SUDDEN men and women </p>

<p>Both 
Men 
Women 
OR (95% CI) 
p Value </p>

<p>Dead on EMS arrival 
174 (92) 
111 (91) 
63 (93) 
1.249 (0.378 to 4.344) 
0.791 
Death at primary residence 
166 (87) 
102 (84) 
64 (94) 
3.137 (0.953 to 11.403) 
0.041 
Death in public area 
18 (9) 
16 (13) 
2 (3) 
0.203 (0.031 to 0.964) 
0.022 
Death unwitnessed 
178 (94) 
111 (91) 
67 (99) 
6.640 (0.856 to 140.672) 
0.059 
Last seen alive over 24 h before death 
20 (11) 
15 (12) 
5 (7) 
0.571 (0.172 to 1.788) 
0.335 
Last seen alive less than 24 h before death 
61 (32) 
40 (33) 
21 (31) 
0.927 (0.466 to 1.839) 
0.872 
Unknown hours since last seen alive 
109 (57) 
67 (55) 
42 (62) 
1.326 (0.693 to 2.543) 
0.444 </p>

<p>Bolded p value signifies a significant difference (p&lt;0.05). The values are given as n (%). 
EMS, emergency medical services; SUDDEN, Sudden Unexpected Death in North Carolina project. </p>

<p>Lewis ME, Lin F-C, Nanavati P, et al. Open Heart 2016;3:e000321. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000321 </p>



<p>Arrhythmias and sudden death </p>

<p>and risk factors. 
16 17 The WHO's definition of sudden 
death focuses on sudden cardiac death, sudden cardiac 
arrest and SUD. Their definition describes sudden death 
as a witnessed sudden, unexpected death within 1 h of 
symptom onset or within 24 h of having been observed 
alive and symptom free. 
18 Although this definition is 
broad in defining the circumstances of death, studies that 
use the full definition, including the time restrictions, are 
prone to systematic exclusion of many victims. It may be 
'more meaningful to define the specific characteristics 
surrounding cardiac arrest, and register and collect data 
in a standardised way, than to try to define the word 
'sudden' in the context of death'. </p>

<p>6 18   Previous studies may have underestimated the inci-
dence of SUD by systematic exclusion of people likely to 
die an unwitnessed death at an unknown time at home. </p>

<p>They have also tended to study racially homogeneous 
cohorts and so have missed, for example, the excess mor-
tality in African-American women we have identified. We 
found more women dying of sudden death compared to 
previous studies. This might be explained by differences 
in case ascertainment and selection methods. </p>

<p>19 20   Death certificate data inconsistent with medical records 
We found frequent and important discrepancies in the 
death certificates compared to medical records. For 
example, there were no cases of substance abuse listed 
on the death certificate. However, toxicology screens 
were positive in 31% of medical examiner cases. CAD 
seemed over-represented in older particiapants. Coding 
inconsistencies are important issues as they can signifi-
cantly impact estimates of disease incidence and 
resource allocation. </p>

<p>21   In the Framingham Heart Study, 26-year follow-up of 
men and women aged 35-84 years indicated that CAD 
morbidity was twice as high in men as in women, and 
60% of coronary events occurred in men. 
22 The onset of 
symptomatic CAD is typically about 10 years earlier in 
men, but CAD incidence in women increases rapidly at 
menopause. 
22 Analysis by age and coronary disease using 
medical records and medical examiner data in our 
cohort shows that women under age 55 years have more 
coronary disease than men of the same age. Most men 
with coronary disease were over the age of 55 years. This 
finding is inconsistent with previous research showing a 
growing risk of cardiovascular disease in older women. </p>

<p>23   This suggests that coronary disease is a risk factor for 
SUD in younger women. However, the opposite result is 
seen when using death certificate data. As previously dis-
cussed, this may suggest inaccuracy in documentation on 
death certificates. Sudden death is not just a disease of 
men but may have great impact on younger women. </p>

<p>Limitations 
The overall limitations of SUDDEN have been outlined 
previously. 
6 Our methodology created a comprehensive 
medical database, exemplified by acquisition of hospital 
or physician medical records on 68% of participants and 
death certificates for all 190 participants. </p>

<p>Table 5 Cause of death on death certificate for SUDDEN men and women </p>

<p>Both 
Men 
Women 
OR (95% CI) 
p Value </p>

<p>Cardiac cause 
100 (53) 
72 (59) 
28 (41) 
0.496 (0.260 to 0.945) 
0.024 
Non-cardiac natural cause 
71 (37) 
41 (34) 
30 (44) 
1.560 (0.811 to 3.000) 
0.162 
Non-natural cause 
11 (6) 
8 (7) 
3 (4) 
0.663 (0.134 to 2.882) 
0.749 
Unknown cause 
8 (4) 
1 (1) 
7 (10) 
14.000 (1.671 to 309.710) 
0.003 
Substance abuse 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
NaN 
NaN </p>

<p>Immediate (primary) cause of death was determined using Death Certificate ICD-10 codes: Cardiac code I, Non-cardiac natural codes A-H, 
J-R94, Non-natural codes V-Y, Unknown code R95-R99, Substance abuse codes T51-65. Cause of death on death certificate is preliminary 
and is considered incomplete until a year after the date of death. Bolded p value signifies a significant difference (p&lt;0.05). The values are 
given as n (%). 
NaN, not a number; SUDDEN, Sudden Unexpected Death in North Carolina project. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Proportion of Sudden Unexpected Death in North 
Carolina (SUDDEN) men and women with coronary artery 
disease (CAD) aged 56-64 years by source of medical data-
medical record (MR) or medical examiner (ME) data. Death 
certificate data show that CAD is more likely to occur in older 
participants, especially older women. However, MR and ME 
data for the same participants show less CAD in older 
women. About 181 (95%) of participants, 116 (95%) men and 
65 (96%) women, had medical information available from 
hospital, physician or ME sources. All SUDDEN subjects had 
death certificates available. Cause of death by CAD on death 
certificates was determined using ICD-10 codes I 25.0, 25.1, 
25.8 and 25.9. p Values are calculated based on age groups 
18-55 vs 56-64. </p>



<p>Lewis ME, Lin F-C, Nanavati P, et al. Open Heart 2016;3:e000321. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000321 </p>

<p>Open Heart </p>

<p>We do not include all out-of-hospital victims. We do 
not include individuals who survived to the hospital or 
who died in the hospital, institutionalised patients, non-
residents of North Carolina, minors and anyone over 
the age of 65 years. However, survival from sudden death 
is low and the number of these sudden death cases 
should be low. 
SUDDEN subjects are restricted to under age 65 years, 
which limits the study of sudden death in postmenopau-
sal women. Given that the focus of our project is to 
assess preventable SUD, the age restriction may be 
understandable. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS 
Using an epidemiological approach, we have identified 
the majority of sudden death victims are white unmar-
ried men, with an unwitnessed death at home, and are 
over age 55 years with hypertension. 
There was a significant difference in estimated inci-
dence by gender but no difference in age or comorbid-
ities. African-Americans and young women with CAD 
are at risk for sudden death. </p>

<p>Contributors MEL assisted with conception and design, analysis and 
interpretation of data, drafting of the manuscript, revising it critically for 
important intellectual content and final approval of the manuscript 
submitted. F-CL assisted with analysis and interpretation of data, revising 
the manuscript critically for important intellectual content and final approval 
of the manuscript submitted. PN assisted with conception and design, 
revising the manuscript critically for important intellectual content and final 
approval of the manuscript submitted. NM assisted with analysis and 
interpretation of data, revising the manuscript critically for important 
intellectual content. LM assisted with analysis and interpretation of data. 
AN assisted with analysis and interpretation of data. IP, EHC, JPM and 
RJSJr assisted with conception and design, revising the manuscript 
critically for important intellectual content and final approval of the 
manuscript submitted. </p>

<p>Funding The SUDDEN project is funded by individual, private donations, The 
Heart and Vascular Division of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 
and NC TraCS (National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS), 
National Institutes of Health (NIH), grant award number 1UL1TR001111). </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval The SUDDEN project was reviewed by the Office of Human 
Research Ethics at UNC. The study was reviewed in accordance with federal 
regulations governing human subjects research (45 CFR 46, 45 CFR 164 
(HPIAA), 21 CFR 50 and 56 (FDA) and 40 CFR 26 (EPA)) and has been 
approved by the UNC IRB (study # 14-2036). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement All data from the SUDDEN project are stored in an 
online database, REDCap. For access, please contact the study coordinator, 
IP, at irion_pursell@med.unc.edu, or the principal investigator, RJS, at 
ross_simpson@med.unc.edu. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Lewis ME, Lin F-C, Nanavati P, et al. Open Heart 2016;3:e000321. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000321 </p>



<p>Arrhythmias and sudden death </p>

</text></tei>