<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4683424" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Frontoparietal white matter supports information transfer between brain areas involved in complex haptic tasks 
such as somatosensory discrimination. The purpose of this study was to gain an understanding of the relationship 
between microstructural integrity of frontoparietal network white matter and haptic performance in persons 
with chronic stroke and to compare frontoparietal network integrity in participants with stroke and age matched 
control participants. Nineteen individuals with stroke and 16 controls participated. Haptic performance was 
quantified using the Hand Active Sensation Test (HASTe), an 18-item match-to-sample test of weight and texture 
discrimination. Three tesla MRI was used to obtain diffusion-weighted and high-resolution anatomical images 
of the whole brain. Probabilistic tractography was used to define 10 frontoparietal tracts total; Four 
intrahemispheric tracts measured bilaterally 1) thalamus to primary somatosensory cortex (T-S1), 2) thalamus 
to primary motor cortex (T-M1), 3) primary to secondary somatosensory cortex (S1 to SII) and 4) primary 
somatosensory cortex to middle frontal gyrus (S1 to MFG) and, 2 interhemispheric tracts; S1-S1 and precuneus 
interhemispheric. A control tract outside the network, the cuneus interhemispheric tract, was also examined. The 
diffusion metrics fractional anisotropy (FA), mean diffusivity (MD), axial (AD) and radial diffusivity (RD) were 
quantified for each tract. Diminished FA and elevated MD values are associated with poorer white matter 
integrity in chronic stroke. Nine of 10 tracts quantified in the frontoparietal network had diminished structural 
integrity poststroke compared to the controls. The precuneus interhemispheric tract was not significantly different 
between groups. Principle component analysis across all frontoparietal white matter tract MD values indicated a 
single factor explained 47% and 57% of the variance in tract mean diffusivity in stroke and control groups respective-
ly. Age strongly correlated with the shared variance across tracts in the control, but not in the poststroke participants. 
A moderate to good relationship was found between ipsilesional T-M1 MD and affected hand HASTe score 
(r = −0.62, p = 0.006) and less affected hand HASTe score (r = −0.53, p = 0.022). Regression analysis revealed 
approximately 90% of the variance in affected hand HASTe score was predicted by the white matter integrity in the 
frontoparietal network (as indexed by MD) in poststroke participants while 87% of the variance in HASTe score was 
predicted in control participants. This study demonstrates the importance of frontoparietal white matter in 
mediating haptic performance and specifically identifies that T-M1 and precuneus interhemispheric tracts may 
be appropriate targets for piloting rehabilitation interventions, such as noninvasive brain stimulation, when the 
goal is to improve poststroke haptic performance. 
Active sensation or haptic touch is the ability to use movement of the 
hand and arm to solicit somatosensory information from the </p>

<p>environment (Lederman and Klatzky, 1997). Haptic impairment is a com-
mon result of stroke identified in 31-89% of cases (Kim and Choi-Kwon, 
1996; Gaubert and Mockett, 2000; Connell et al., 2008; Carey and Matyas, 
2011; Borstad et al., 2012a). The functional consequence of 
haptic impairment can be conceptualized in two ways. First, there is the 
loss of the hand's natural role as the primary somatosensory receptor of 
the environment (Lederman and Klatzky, 1998). Second, there is reduced 
somatosensory afferent information that is particularly important for </p>

<p>NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>⁎ Corresponding author. </p>

<p>E-mail addresses: Borstad.2@osu.edu (A.L. Borstad), seongjin.choi@nih.gov (S. Choi), 
Schmalbrock.1@osu.edu (P. Schmalbrock), Larsen.64@osu.edu (D.S. Nichols-Larsen). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nicl.2015.11.007 
2213-1582/© 2015 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>NeuroImage: Clinical </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / y n i c l </p>

<p>dexterous movements (Classen et al., 2000). Hence, haptics and manual 
dexterity are co-dependent aspects of sensorimotor performance. 
Stroke mainly affects subcortical structures and white matter 
(Corbetta et al., 2015). Several studies in stroke describe the 
relationship between white matter integrity and poststroke motor per-
formance; however, the extent to which the integrity of white matter 
within the frontoparietal network is related to haptic performance is 
largely unknown. Constituent regions of the frontoparietal network as-
sociated with haptic performance have been identified using functional 
MRI; they are widely distributed and include primary and secondary so-
matosensory cortices, the premotor cortex, the posterior parietal cortex 
and the cerebellum (Stoeckel et al., 2003; Harada et al., 2004; Carey 
et al., 2011; Borstad et al., 2012a; Van de Winckel et al., 2005, 2012). Ef-
ficient information processing between brain areas is requisite to func-
tion and dependent upon the integrity of their white matter 
connections (Seidl, 2014). Because stroke results in diminished integrity 
both local to and distant from the lesion (Crofts et al., 2011; Borich et al., 
2012; Auriat et al., 2015; Lindberg et al., 2007, 2011; Yin et al., 2013; Lim 
et al., 2012; Carter et al., 2012), diminished integrity in the distributed 
network that supports somatosensation may explain, in part, why 
somatosensation was found to be impaired in both the affected and 
less affected upper extremity after stroke (Borstad et al., 2012a; Kim 
and Choi-Kwon, 1996; Connell et al., 2008; Carey and Matyas, 2011). 
Parts of the frontoparietal network have been examined in chronic 
stroke for their relationship to sensorimotor performance. In a previous 
study we found that integrity of the sensory aspect of the superior tha-
lamic radiation, which includes all afferent connections to S1 (Wakana 
et al., 2004), was related to haptic performance (Borstad et al., 2012a). 
Buch and colleagues showed the structural connectivity in the superior 
longitudinal fascicles II and III between frontal and parietal regions were 
associated with better sensorimotor rhythm modulation skill in severe 
chronic hemiparesis (Buch et al., 2012). Borich and colleagues reported 
integrity of the sensory region of the CC was reduced following chronic 
stroke but was not correlated with manual dexterity as measured by the 
Box and Blocks Test. A somatosensory measure was not included in 
their assessment (Borich et al., 2012). 
Quantitative diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) allows calculation and 
visualization of parameters that are sensitive to intrinsic features of 
brain tissue at the macromolecular, cellular, and tissue level, similar to 
histological stains; thus, DTI parameters are said to reflect tissue micro-
structural integrity (Basser and Pierpaoli, 1996). The two most fre-
quently used diffusion metrics are fractional anisotropy (FA) and 
mean diffusivity (MD) (Vos et al., 2012). FA quantifies the degree of di-
rectional dependence of diffusion while MD reflects the overall amount 
of isotropic diffusion. The diffusion signal can be further reduced to in-
dividual components that include: axial diffusivity (AD) largest eigen-
value, presumed to be along the length of the axons and radial 
diffusivity (RD) refers to the average of the next two smaller eigen-
values, which are presumed to be perpendicular to the axon. Elevated 
MD and diminished FA are associated with poorer white matter micro-
structural integrity in chronic stroke (Schlaug et al., 1997). 
Because there is limited knowledge of the extent to which stroke 
affects white matter structural integrity in the distributed frontoparietal 
network, in the present study, we compared frontoparietal network mi-
crostructural integrity in participants with stroke to age-matched con-
trol participants. We also examined the extent to which frontoparietal 
network microstructural integrity related to haptic performance as 
measured by the Hand Active Sensation Test (HASTe) (Borstad et al., 
2015; Williams et al., 2006). The goals were to 1) identify frontoparietal 
network tracts in which poststroke participants had diminished integri-
ty compared to controls and 2) determine if the microstructural integri-
ty of frontoparietal tracts was related to haptic performance. We 
hypothesized that there would be significant differences between 
poststroke and control participants in frontoparietal tract integrity and 
that diminished tract integrity would correlate with haptic performance 
of the stroke affected upper extremity. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Subjects </p>

<p>Nineteen individuals with stroke and sixteen age-matched controls 
participated. Inclusion criteria: a single stroke (ischemic or hemorrhag-
ic) diagnosed greater than 3 months prior to enrollment, 10° of active 
finger extension in the affected hand (required to complete haptic test-
ing), communication in English sufficient to provide informed consent 
and follow study instructions. Exclusion criteria: Mini Mental Status 
Exam score ≤ 24, severe spatial or visual neglect (a positive Albert's 
Test), apraxia or hemianopsia (informal assessment during screening), 
other diagnosed neurologic or sensory disorder, claustrophobia, and fer-
rous implants. Control participants met the criteria when they had no 
history of stroke or other neurologic condition, and no focal abnormality 
on MRI. The University Biomedical Sciences Institutional Review Board 
approved this study and written informed consent was obtained prior 
to participation. </p>

<p>2.2. Clinical evaluation </p>

<p>Haptic performance was quantified using the Hand Active Sensation 
Test (HASTe), an 18-trial test of weight and texture discrimination, valid 
and reliable for measurement of haptic performance in healthy individ-
uals and persons poststroke (Williams et al., 2006; Borstad et al., 2015). 
To complete the test, for each trial, participants manually explore one 
test object and three sample objects that vary by weight or texture with-
out using vision. Participants are asked to indicate which sample object 
is a match to the test object without discussing the properties of the ob-
jects. The accuracy score out of 18 is recorded for each hand; 13 or great-
er out of 18 possible has been considered the cut off for normal 
performance (Williams et al., 2006). Because of the match-to-sample 
design 6/18 could be considered a chance score. HASTe scores for con-
trol and poststroke participants were normally distributed and are re-
ported in Table 1. The 6-item Wolf Motor function Test was used to 
quantify motor performance (Bogard et al., 2009). The 6 items included: 
hand to table (front), hand to box (front), reach and retrieve, lift can, lift 
pencil, and fold towel. Pre-stroke handedness was determined using the 
Edinburgh inventory (Oldfield, 1971). Clinical evaluation and MRI took 
place on the same day for each participant. Demographic, neurologic, 
and sensory descriptors are given in Table 1. </p>

<p>2.3. MRI acquisition </p>

<p>A 3 Tesla MR scanner (Philips, Best, The Netherlands) with a body 
transmit and 8-channel receiver coil was used. High-resolution 3D T1-
weighted Magnetization Prepared Rapid Acquired Gradient Echo 
(MRRAGE) anatomical images with an isotropic voxel size of 1 mm 3 
were acquired for spatial normalization to a standard atlas. T2 weighted 
Fluid Attenuated Inversion Recovery (FLAIR) images were acquired in 
the axial plane with a voxel size of 2 × 2.5 × 2 mm for calculation of le-
sion volume. Diffusion-weighted images were acquired in the axial 
plane with parameters: TR/TE = 9750/92 ms, FOV = 256 × 256 mm 2 , 
Matrix = 128 × 128, isotropic voxel size 2 mm 3 , gap = 0.0 mm, two 
b-values 0 and 1000 s/mm 2 , diffusion-weighting gradient 
directions = 32, SENSE reduction factor of 2.2, scan time of 6 min. The 
signal-to-noise ratio (SNR, 25.6 for the entire white matter region) 
was calculated from a representative control participant. SNR with sen-
sitivity encoding (SENSE) reconstruction was determined from a mini-
mally diffusion-weighted image (b = 0 s/mm 2 ) and a noise image 
with radio frequency field off (Choi et al., 2011). </p>

<p>2.4. Lesion analysis </p>

<p>Two different methods were used to characterize the stroke lesions 
in participants. First, for visualization purposes only lesion masks were </p>

<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>created by manually drawing the lesion in the individuals T1-weighted 
image (Fig. 1) (Rorden and Brett, 2000). For quantification, stroke lesion 
volume was determined from T2 weighted FLAIR images by manually 
outlining signal abnormality slice-by slice in the axial plane (Bazin 
et al., 2007; Orrison, 2008). </p>

<p>2.5. Brain volume measurement </p>

<p>Gray and white matter volumes were calculated using each 
participant's T1 image. Stroke lesions were nulled to prevent misclassi-
fication of voxels prior to quantification; therefore, nulled voxels are not 
included in the regional or normalized brain volumes. All participant 
images were oriented, cropped to exclude non-brain/skull data 
(Smith, 2002) and analyzed using <rs id="software-5" type="software">SIENAX</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">2.6</rs> (Smith et al., 
2001, 2002). Next, affine registration was used to register the brain 
image to standard space (Montreal Neurologic Institute 152) (Jenkinson 
et al., 2002; Jenkinson and Smith, 2001). Skull dimensions were used to 
determine the registration scaling in order to normalize brain 
volume to head size. Tissue-type segmentation was carried out 
with partial volume estimation in order to quantify brain volume 
(gray matter + white matter) (Zhang et al., 2001), with N 99% accuracy </p>

<p>(Smith et al., 2002). Visual inspection of whole brain segmentation 
verified results. </p>

<p>2.6. Diffusion tensor imaging </p>

<p>The following objective approach was used to delineate tracts of 
interest in this study. Diffusion tensor image analysis was performed 
using <rs type="software">FMRIB Diffusion Toolbox</rs> (FDT) included in <rs type="software">Functional MRI of 
the Brain Software Library</rs> (FSL) (Analysis Group, FMRIB, Oxford, UK) 
(Smith et al., 2004). Image artifacts due to eddy currents and bulk 
head motion were minimized including b-matrix rotation during 
motion correction (Smith et al., 2004). Non-brain tissue was removed 
(Smith et al., 2002). Scalar maps for mean tract FA, MD, AD and RD 
were generated. Because the component diffusion metrics may provide 
more specific information about the underling tissue properties they 
were included in our analysis (Budde et al., 2007; Song et al., 2003). 
For poststroke participants, high-resolution anatomical images were 
masked to null voxels in the region of their lesion to minimize lesion 
related structural changes from affecting the registration. Affine (12 
degrees-of-freedom) registration was used to obtain transformation 
matrices first between the diffusion and anatomical space and then 
between the anatomical and standard space (Montreal Neurologic </p>

<p>Table 1 
Clinical details of participants. </p>

<p>ID 
Age 
Sex 
Dom. 
hand </p>

<p>More affected 
hand </p>

<p>Chronicity 
(months) </p>

<p>HASTe (less affected/more 
affected) </p>

<p>6-item Wolf 
(rate/60s) </p>

<p>Lesion volume 
(cm 3 ) </p>

<p>Brain volume 
(cm 3 ) </p>

<p>Poststroke 
002 
75 
M 
R 
L 
12 
7/8 
22.5 
14.3 
1424 
003 
62 
F 
R 
R 
9 
15/14 
27.9 
2.1 
1459 
004 
55 
F 
R 
L 
24 
10/7 
27.3 
20.1 
1393 
005 
46 
F 
R 
R 
96 
10/4 
38.7 
9.9 
1394 
007 
30 
M 
R 
L 
60 
16/12 
23.1 
37.5 
1390 
008 
84 
F 
R 
R 
11 
8/13 
26.1 
0.6 
1356 
009 
71 
M 
R 
R 
10 
12/11 
41.1 
1.9 
1431 
011 
64 
M 
R 
R 
20 
11/10 
19.8 
2.6 
1344 
012 
62 
M 
R 
L 
16 
9/11 
35.6 
8.0 
1320 
013 
39 
F 
L 
R 
4 
12/8 
18.3 
3.9 
1438 
014 
61 
F 
R 
L 
24 
13/13 
33.9 
6.0 
1298 
015 
77 
F 
R 
R 
8 
8/9 
41.9 
1.3 
1376 
016 
70 
M 
R 
L 
21 
14/15 
53.9 
.87 
1346 
017 
60 
F 
R 
L 
94 
8/6 
23.0 
110.1 
1454 
018 
85 
F 
R 
L 
38 
13/9 
42.8 
.056 
1269 
019 
65 
M 
R 
L 
41 
10/7 
24.2 
3.35 
1471 
020 
71 
F 
R 
L 
8 
10/7 
38.5 
49.4 
1350 
021 
69 
M 
R 
R 
9 
10/10 
2.0 
54.3 
1402 
022 
48 
F 
R 
R 
13 
16/13 
27.0 
4.1 
1412 
Mean 
62.8 
8M/11F 
18R/1L 
9R/10L 
13 (24) 
11.5/9.9 
29.9 (11.6) 
17.4 (27.9) 
1386 
Control 
(R/L) 
A 
53 
F 
L 
NA 
NA 
12/12 
NT 
NA 
1394 
B 
38 
F 
L 
16/16 
1522 
C 
41 
F 
R 
14/11 
1498 
D 
72 
M 
R 
10/10 
1432 
E 
85 
F 
R 
11/7 
1391 
F 
60 
F 
R 
12/11 
1481 
G 
69 
M 
R 
8/8 
1387 
H 
64 
M 
R 
13/13 
1113 
I 
58 
F 
R 
16/14 
1500 
J 
63 
M 
R 
11/11 
1475 
K 
69 
F 
R 
16/16 
1463 
L 
47 
F 
R 
14/17 
1518 
M 
68 
M 
R 
9/12 
1347 
N 
74 
F 
R 
12/13 
1279 
O 
40 
M 
R 
1215 
1476 
P 
46 
M 
R 
16/14 
1379 
Mean 
59.2 
7M/9F 
14R/2L 
12.6/12.5 
1432 
T-test 
p = 0.45 
p = 0.11/p = 0.01 
p = 0.33 </p>

<p>NA, not applicable; Dom., dominant, R, right; L, left; NT, not tested; t-test, two-tailed t-test; HASTe, Hand Active Sensation Test; the majority of participants were right hand so HASTe scores 
from the less affected upper extremity of the poststroke participants were compared to the right hand of the control participants, scores from the more affected upper extremity were 
compared to the left hand of control participants. </p>

<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>Institute 152) (Jenkinson and Smith, 2001). Binarized white matter 
masks (Zhang et al., 2001) were realigned into diffusion space and 
used to constrain probabilistic tracking. </p>

<p>Based on previous fMRI studies (Harada et al., 2004; Borstad et al., 
2012a; Carey et al., 2011; Tunik et al., 2007), 10 white matter tracts of 
interest in the somatosensory discrimination network were identified; </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Lesion in poststroke participants on T1 image (radiologic convention). The axial slice of with the largest lesion volume is shown. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Example 3D renderings of frontoparietal network tracts generated using probabilistic tractography. Four intrahemispheric (S1 to S2, thalamus to S1, S1 to MFG and thalamus to M1) 
measured bilaterally and, 2 interhemispheric tracts (S1-S1 and precuneus interhemispheric) were modeled. A control tract outside the network, the cuneus interhemispheric is not 
shown. Descriptions of the standard space seed, target, exclusion and termination masks can be found in the Appendix. </p>

<p>132 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>2 were interhemispheric and 4 were intrahemispheric (Fig. 2). The in-
terhemispheric tracts were: S1 to S1, and Precuneus interhemispheric. 
The intrahemispheric tracts measured in both hemispheres were 
thalamus to primary somatosensory cortex (S1), thalamus to primary 
motor cortex (M1), S1 to middle frontal gyrus (MFG), S1 to secondary 
somatosensory cortex (SII). Previously the T-S1 tract was related to 
poststroke haptic performance, it includes all sensory afferents to the 
S1 cortex (Borstad et al., 2012a). Thalamus to M1 includes efferent path-
ways from the frontoparietal network. These 10 tracts were successfully 
modeled with probabilistic tractography using a two-ROI approach 
(Heiervang et al., 2006). A minimum FA threshold of 0.2 was used to 
constrain probabilistic tracking. Our attempt to model a tract between 
left S1 and right SII (and right S1 and left SII) was unsuccessful in a series 
of 5 control subjects so was discontinued. We hypothesize this was due 
to the accumulation of uncertainty in the probabilistic algorithm caused 
by distance and curves in the tracts (Jbabdi and Johansen-Berg, 2011). 
To establish that the adjacent thalamocortical tracts studied here were 
independent (set a priori at b 10% overlap), the extent of overlap was 
calculated in each participant. The mean amount of overlap in voxels 
in stroke and control participants was 7.76% and 7.88% respectively. To 
provide a basis for comparison to frontoparietal network tracts studied 
here we also quantified the interhemispheric tract between right and 
left cuneus cortices. Circulation for the cuneus cortex comes from the 
posterior cerebral artery. As no participants in this study had posterior 
cerebral artery distribution stroke this tract was selected for control-
comparison purposes. Standard space masks used for probabilistic 
tracking met reproducible criteria (and are detailed in Supporting 
Information-end of this document). The position of tracts of interest 
was confirmed visually in each participant. As indices of tract integrity, 
mean tract FA, MD, AD and RD were then calculated. All voxels through 
which a probabilistic streamline passed were used to calculate means. </p>

<p>2.7. Statistics </p>

<p>Differences between the stroke and control group for HASTe score, 
brain volume, and age were determined using the two-sample t-test; 
p-Values ≤ 0.05 were considered significant (Table 1). Because our 
stroke an control groups were closely matched for handedness, to 
determine the effect of group (control, right hemisphere stroke, left 
hemisphere stroke) for each tract, we decided to compare right and 
left hemispheres directly, rather than comparing lesioned hemisphere 
to non-dominant hemisphere, two-sample t-tests were used for this 
comparison. The results were corrected for multiple comparisons 
using false discovery rate (FDR) correction (Benjamini and Hochberg, 
1995). Corrected p-values were considered statistically significant at 
p ≤ 0.03 (Table 2). 
Fractional anisotropy and mean diffusivity are known to reflect 
white matter integrity following stroke. Of the two metrics, in 
our data, MD had the lowest coefficient of variation across the 10 
frontoparietal network tracts we quantified in both the poststroke 
and control groups, therefore it was used for the following three 
analyses: 1) to explain frontoparietal network variance principal 
components' analysis (PCA) was conducted on the correlations 
across the 10-frontoparietal tract mean MD values (Table 3). 2) To 
evaluate the relationship between haptic performance of the affected 
hand and network integrity we examined the relationship between 
ipsilesional and interhemispheric tract MD and HASTe scores using 
Pearson correlation coefficient. Bonferroni correction for 6 comparisons 
resulted in an adjusted alpha of p b 0.008 (Table 3). 3) To evaluate how 
well frontoparietal white matter integrity and other variables (age, 
brain volume and lesion volume) predicted HASTe scores of the affected 
and less affected hand we used forward stepwise multiple regression. 
Statistical analyses were performed in <rs id="software-3" type="software">JMP® Pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">11.0.0</rs>. These data 
have been made publically available, to request access please contact 
the corresponding author. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Haptic performance </p>

<p>HASTe scores for both hands of all participants are shown in Table 1. 
Poststroke participants exhibited a wide range of haptic ability. HASTe 
scores ranged from 4 to 16 for the right hand and 6 to 16 for the left 
hand and were normally distributed. A moderate to good correlation 
was identified between less affected and more affected hand HASTe 
scores (r = 0.58, p = 0.009). Control participants also exhibited a 
range of haptic ability. Scores ranged from 8 to 16 for the right hand 
and 7 to 16 for the left hand. Control participant right and left hand 
HASTe scores were also correlated (r = 0.72, p = 0.001). There was a 
significant difference between stroke and control group means on the 
HASTe for comparison between the more affected hand of poststroke 
participants and the left hand of controls (p = 0.01) (Table 1). </p>

<p>3.2. Brain lesion volume </p>

<p>Gray, white and total brain volumes were not statistically different 
between groups. Average brain volume for poststroke/control 
participants was 1386/1415 cm 3 . The average cerebral spinal fluid, 
gray, and white matter volumes for poststroke/control participants 
were 27/26 cm 3 , 703/722 cm 3 , and 675/693 cm 3 respectively. 
Stroke lesion volume was 17.4 cm 3 on average. Mean (SD) lesion 
volume for left hemisphere participants (n = 9) was 8.9 (17) cm 3 , for 
right hemisphere stroke participants (n = 10) was 24.9 (34) cm 3 , 
they were not statistically different (p = 0.21). A lesion plot is shown 
in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>3.3. Tract quantification </p>

<p>Eleven tracts in 35 participants for a total of 385 tracts were 
modeled. Probabilistic tracts were not established in 37 instances 
(10%), similar to recent probabilistic tractography studies reporting 
11% (De Weijer et al., 2010) and 18% (Yang et al., 2009) error rates. 
These 'missing' tracts were divided into two categories: 1) biological, 
in which visible white matter changes (stroke lesion in tract, white 
matter disease or corpus callosum thinning) were evident; 2) technical, 
in which no structural explanation was evident. The technical error rate 
was 6% for controls and 5% for strokes. The biological error rate was 0.5% 
for controls and 7% for strokes. As different causes resulted in missing 
tracts, no single method of data imputation could be applied; therefore, 
only tracts that could be established were included in the analysis. The 
number of tracts analyzed for each group is given in Table 2. 
The right hemisphere stroke group differed from controls on at least 
one diffusion metric in 8 of 10 tracts in the network. The left hemisphere 
poststroke differed from controls in 7 of 10 tracts in the network. 
Neither group differed from controls for the precuneus interhemispheric. 
Both groups differed from controls for the cuneus interhemispheric 
(control) tract AD but not MD or FA (Table 2). 
To explain frontoparietal network variance we used principal 
component analyses (PCA) across all 10 white matter tracts for 
mean MD. PCA was run separately for stroke and control groups. In 
the control group the PCA results indicated a clear one-factor solution, 
with the first principal component (PC1) explaining 57% of the variance 
(Table 3). 
In controls, age was strongly correlated with PC1 (r = 0.95, p b 
0.0001) (Fig. 3a). For the stroke group PC1 explained 47% of the 
variance. Unlike the controls, PC1 for the poststroke participants did 
not have a statistically significant correlation with age (r = 0.20, p = 
0.42) (Fig. 3b). We then examined other factors for correlation with 
PC1 in the poststroke group. Brain volume was not correlated (r = 
0.13, p = 0.59), chronicity (r = 0.42, p = 0.07) and lesion volume 
(r = 0.41, p = 0.07) had fair relationships at trend level of significance. </p>

<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>3.4. Diffusion parameters and haptic performance </p>

<p>To explore the relationship between tract diffusion parameters and 
haptic performance in the control participants we conducted Pearson's 
correlations of left and interhemispheric frontoparietal tracts and right 
hand HASTe score. We chose the right hand, as it was the dominant 
hand in the majority of participants. After correction for multiple com-
parisons a moderate to good relationship was found between right 
HASTe score and Precuneus MD (and AD) and left S1-MFG AD (Table 4). 
To explore the relationship between tract diffusion parameters and 
haptic performance in the poststroke participants we conducted bivariate 
Pearson's correlations of iplslesional and interhemispheric frontoparietal </p>

<p>tracts and affected hand HASTe score (Table 5). After correction for 
multiple comparisons a moderate to good relationship was found 
between ipsilesional T-M1 MD (and RD) and affected hand HASTe 
score (r = − 0.62, p = 0.006) (Fig. 3). Because haptic performance 
measured by the HASTe requires somatosensory perception and motor 
manipulation we wished to discern whether the positive relationship 
between thalamus-M1 integrity and HASTe score was a function of bet-
ter motor performance in our participants. To do so we completed a post-
hoc correlation between thalamus-M1 MD and the 6-item Wolf Motor 
function Test (r = 0.08, p = 0.92) and between the 6-item Wolf and 
HASTe score (r = 0.14, p = 0.57) and no statistically significant correla-
tion was identified (Fig. 4). </p>

<p>Table 2 
Comparison of tract diffusion metrics by group. </p>

<p>Measures 
Control 
R stroke 
L stroke 
Control vs. R stroke 
Control vs. L stroke </p>

<p>Mean 
CV 
Mean 
CV 
Mean 
CV 
t 
p 
t 
p </p>

<p>R T-S1 
n = 15 
n = 9 
n = 9 
FA 
0.45 
6.9 
0.38 
19.7 
0.43 
8.2 
3.05 
0.0059 
1.13 
0.2726 
MD 
7.8 
7.0 
10.1 
22.1 
8.4 
11.4 
3.84 
0.0009 
2.19 
0.0391 
AD 
11.7 
11.7 
13.9 
14.3 
12.4 
8.5 
4.13 
0.0004 
2.15 
0.0431 
RD 
5.9 
15.7 
8.2 
29.4 
6.5 
14.8 
3.11 
0.0051 
1.19 
0.2456 
L T-S1 
n = 16 
n = 8 
n = 9 
FA 
0.46 
6.6 
0.43 
12.1 
0.42 
5.9 
2.22 
0.0363 
3.56 
0.0019 
MD 
7.7 
6.7 
8.5 
10.1 
8.8 
7.6 
3.07 
0.0052 
4.45 
0.0002 
AD 
11.8 
5.1 
12.5 
6.5 
12.9 
5.8 
2.61 
0.0154 
3.85 
0.0009 
RD 
5.7 
9.5 
6.6 
14.6 
6.8 
9.9 
3.01 
0.0060 
4.39 
0.0003 
R T-M1 
n = 15 
n = 9 
n = 9 
FA 
0.45 
6.2 
0.38 
8.3 
0.44 
9.3 
6.25 
b.0001 
1.03 
0.3119 
MD 
7.5 
7.4 
9.5 
9.3 
8.2 
8.3 
6.54 
b.0001 
2.45 
0.0229 
AD 
11.4 
6.2 
13.2 
8.3 
11.7 
14.0 
4.82 
b.0001 
0.62 
0.5416 
RD 
5.6 
9.4 
7.6 
11.2 
6.2 
13.3 
7.13 
b.0001 
2.32 
0.0301 
L T-M1 
n = 15 
n = 9 
n = 10 
FA 
0.47 
7.2 
0.44 
9.1 
0.39 
11.7 
2.10 
0.0468 
5.18 
b.0001 </p>

<p>MD 
7.5 
7.8 
8.6 
8.6 
9.1 
16.2 
3.38 
0.0026 
3.88 
0.0008 
AD 
11.5 
5.9 
12.8 
6.5 
12.4 
12.1 
3.05 
0.0056 
2.80 
0.0105 
RD 
5.5 
10.7 
6.3 
11.7 
7.3 
20.2 
3.25 
0.0035 
4.30 
0.0003 
R S1-SII 
n = 15 
n = 8 
n = 9 
FA 
0.38 
10.0 
0.32 
24.5 
0.35 
6.5 
2.44 
0.0235 
2.19 
0.0399 
MD 
8.1 
5.4 
10.1 
17.0 
8.9 
9.7 
4.30 
0.0003 
3.20 
0.0043 
AD 
11.1 
4.3 
13.1 
9.3 
12.1 
7.6 
5.29 
b.0001 
2.85 
0.0096 
RD 
6.6 
8.1 
8.6 
23.4 
7.4 
11.9 
3.78 
0.0010 
3.02 
0.0065 
L S1-SII 
n = 16 
n = 8 
n = 9 
FA 
0.38 
14.8 
0.35 
16.9 
0.35 
17.8 
1.40 
0.1750 
1.23 
0.2303 
MD 
8.0 
9.2 
8.6 
10.5 
9.0 
15.5 
2.10 
0.0474 
2.49 
0.0208 
AD 
11.0 
5.4 
11.6 
7.1 
12.1 
10.8 
1.92 
0.0672 
2.76 
0.0114 
RD 
6.4 
13.8 
7.2 
14.8 
7.5 
19.8 
1.95 
0.0632 
2.23 
0.0361 
R S1-MFG 
n = 14 
n = 9 
n = 9 
FA 
0.35 
11.8 
0.27 
9.6 
0.35 
12.1 
5.11 
b.0001 
0.35 
0.7298 
MD 
8.5 
12.5 
10.4 
12.6 
9.0 
10.5 
3.80 
0.0010 
1.01 
0.3211 
AD 
11.2 
11.2 
13.0 
11.1 
12.0 
7.1 
3.13 
0.0051 
1.71 
0.1025 
RD 
7.1 
16.2 
9.2 
11.2 
7.5 
13.9 
4.00 
0.0006 
0.71 
0.4823 
L S1-MFG 
n = 15 
n = 8 
n = 9 
FA 
0.36 
9.4 
0.33 
10.3 
0.32 
10.0 
2.11 
0.0467 
2.88 
0.0089 
MD 
8.4 
9.5 
9.2 
9.5 
9.4 
8.8 
2.46 
0.0222 
2.92 
0.0081 
AD 
11.2 
6.1 
12.0 
6.7 
12.2 
6.8 
2.56 
0.0180 
3.05 
0.0060 
RD 
7.0 
12.6 
7.9 
11.8 
8.2 
10.7 
2.37 
0.0270 
2.78 
0.0111 
S1-S1 
n = 15 
n = 8 
n = 8 
FA 
0.48 
5.9 
0.41 
17.0 
0.45 
7.1 
3.40 
0.0027 
2.02 
0.0567 
MD 
8.4 
5.0 
10.1 
16.1 
9.0 
9.0 
3.98 
0.0007 
2.46 
0.0225 
AD 
13.0 
3.6 
14.5 
9.5 
13.7 
8.2 
3.76 
0.0011 
2.09 
0.0492 
RD 
5.9 
10.0 
7.9 
23.0 
6.7 
10.3 
3.86 
0.0009 
2.64 
0.0154 
Precuneus 
n = 15 
n = 8 
n = 8 
FA 
0.40 
7.1 
0.39 
10.8 
0.38 
10.6 
0.93 
0.3640 
1.31 
0.2058 
MD 
9.1 
5.8 
9.7 
13.0 
9.5 
8.1 
1.54 
0.1378 
1.60 
0.1244 
AD 
12.9 
5.0 
13.6 
9.5 
13.3 
7.0 
1.70 
0.1038 
1.23 
0.2325 
RD 
7.1 
8.1 
7.7 
16.7 
7.6 
10.8 
1.33 
0.1993 
1.53 
0.1405 
Cuneus 
n = 11 
n = 5 
n = 8 
FA 
0.46 
9.3 
0.47 
10.8 
0.51 
10.5 
0.28 
0.7852 
2.05 
0.0598 
MD 
9.3 
5.2 
10.0 
8.9 
9.3 
7.7 
2.30 
0.0342 
0.10 
0.9275 
AD 
14.1 
3.4 
15.2 
5.9 
15.0 
5.9 
3.22 
0.0050 
2.55 
0.0230 
RD 
6.8 
10.2 
7.4 
13.7 
6.5 
13.6 
1.51 
0.1491 
0.93 
0.3675 </p>

<p>Bold, significant at 5% FDR (corrected p = 0.03); CV, coefficient of variation; FA, fractional anisotropy; MD, mean diffusivity; AD, axial diffusivity; RD, radial diffusivity; MD, AD, 
RD units: ×10 −4 mm. </p>

<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>The interpretation of bivariate correlations is limited given they do 
not account for the possible influence of other variables. Therefore we 
used forward stepwise multiple regression analysis to evaluate how 
well frontoparietal network white matter and other variables (age, 
brain volume and lesion volume) predicted HASTe scores. The combina-
tion of ipsilesional T-M1 and T-S1, Precuneus and S1-S1 resulted in the 
strongest model (F (4, 6) = 12.08, p = 0.004) for predicting affected 
hand HASTe scores. The multiple correlation coefficient (r 2 ) was 0.90, 
indicating that approximately 90% of the variability in affected hand 
HASTe score was predicted by the white matter integrity of these four 
tracts (as indexed by MD). Beta weights for the individual tracts were 
precuneus (β = 1.1, t = 5.9, p = 0.001), S1-S1 (β = 1.0, t = 3.5, p = 
0.01), and ipsilesional T-S1 (β = 0.9, t = 2.8, p = 0.03), and ipsilesional 
T-M1 (β = 0.74, t = 2.2, p = 0.06) indicating that precuneus tract 
integrity was the most important variable for predicting affected 
HASTe score. Age, brain volume and lesion volume were not retained 
in the model. To predict the less affected hand HASTe score, a single 
tract, the ipsilesional thalamus-M1 MD and age resulted in the stron-
gest model [F (2, 15) = 4.6, p = 0.028]. The correlation coefficient 
was 0.38 indicating that approximately 38% of the variance in less af-
fected hand HASTe score was predicted by white matter in the 
ipsilesional T-M1 tract and age. Beta weights for ipsilesional T-M1 
(β = 0.54, t = 2.6, p = 0.02) and age (β = 0.30, t = 1.5, p = 0.15) in-
dicate ipsilesional T-M1 was most important for predicting HASTe score 
for the less affected hand. 
To predict the right hand HASTe score for the control participants the 
4 left intrahemispheric and two interhemispheric tracts resulted in the 
strongest model (F (6, 12) = 6.48, p = 0.02). The multiple correlation </p>

<p>coefficient was 0.87 indicating that approximately 87% of the variability 
in right hand HASTe score was predicted by the white matter integrity 
of these 6 tracts (as indexed by MD). Beta weights for the individual tracts 
from strongest to weakest were precuneus (β = 1.5, t = 4.2, p = 0.005), 
left S1-SII (β = 1.0, t = 3.1, p = 0.02), left T-S1 (β = 0.92, t = 2.7, p = 
0.04), left T-M1 (β = 0.82, t = 2.0, p = 0.09), S1-S1 (β = 0.49, t = 2.4, 
p = 0.05), and left S1-MFG (β = 0.26, t = 1.1, p = 0.30). Age and brain 
volume were not retained in this model. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>This study had three main findings; first, we demonstrated that the 
microstructural integrity of the frontoparietal network is diminished 
both ipsilesionally and contralesionally in chronic stroke with a single 
factor accounting for nearly half of the shared variance across the 10 
tracts studied in this network. Second, frontoparietal network integrity 
predicted nearly 90% of the variance haptic performance in both 
poststroke and control participants. Third, multivariate regression 
analysis suggests that the strongest predictor haptic performance in 
both poststroke and control models was the precuneus interhemispheric 
tract integrity. The significance of these findings is discussed below. </p>

<p>4.1. Haptic performance is diminished in the affected hand in chronic stroke </p>

<p>Mean HASTe scores for poststroke and control participants were 
statistically different when comparing the more affected upper extremity 
to the left upper extremity of controls and were normally distributed 
enabling analysis of relationship to white matter integrity using paramet-
ric statistics. While the HASTe was sensitive to between group differences 
in this study, it did not perform as reported by Williams and colleagues in 
that some control participants (50% with the left and 56% with the right 
hand) studied here scored lower than the suggested cut off of 13/18 
correct matches for normal performance. This cut off was suggested 
based on the fact that in their control sample (n = 28, mean age 60 
(14) years) no participants scored less than 13/18. The mean/range in 
age of their participants was similar to ours so this difference seems 
unlikely to be related to age. A possible cause for the difference is control 
participant scores is that a different HASTe kit was used for this study. The 
HASTe is not commercially produced; therefore subtle differences in 
construction of the test objects could affect scores. Important to the inter-
pretation of the current studies data is that the same test kit, tester and 
method of administration was used across both participant groups. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Principal components analysis factor loadings by group. </p>

<p>Stroke 
Control </p>

<p>R T-S1 MD 
0.83925 
0.86289 
L T-S1 MD 
0.35606 
0.74688 
R T-M1 MD 
0.83581 
0.81729 
L T-M1 MD 
0.22083 
0.62672 
R S1-SII MD 
0.87726 
0.63451 
L S1-SII MD 
0.44177 
0.56079 
R S1-MFG MD 
0.76003 
0.81662 
L S1-MFG MD 
0.54763 
0.79244 
S1-S1 MD 
0.77120 
0.82337 
Precuneus MD 
0.84081 
0.62672 
Variance explained by PC1 
47% 
57% 
Mean between tract r 
0.38 
0.50 </p>

<p>PC1 = first principal component. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Thalamocortical white matter mean diffusivity related to haptic performance. One white matter tract in the ipsilesional hemisphere, the thalamus to M1 cortex, had a significant 
relationship with haptic performance of the affected hand across the poststroke participants (r = 0.62, p = 0.006). The same tract also had the strongest relationship with less affected 
hand haptic performance (r = 0.53, p = 0.022). </p>

<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>4.2. Microstructural integrity of frontoparietal network white matter is 
diminished in chronic stroke </p>

<p>Nine of 10 tracts quantified in the frontoparietal network had 
diminished integrity poststroke compared to the controls as evidenced 
by diminished FA or increased MD, AD or RD. Only the precuneus inter-
hemispheric tract was not significantly different between groups. The 
cuneus interhemispheric tract, chosen as a control tract, was also not 
statistically different between groups for FA or MD, though it was 
different for AD. These results are consistent with and extend findings 
from other diffusion imaging studies that have shown that poststroke 
microstructure is diminished in ipsilesional and contralesional CST 
(Schaechter et al., 2009), in areas surrounding the lesions and homolo-
gous locations in the contralesional hemisphere (Crofts et al., 2011). By 
quantifying stroke-control variations in white matter integrity the 
science is progressing toward an understanding of the biological process-
es, which follow stroke and are associated with recovery (Johansen-Berg 
and Behrens, 2009). Mechanisms associated with increases in diffusivity 
local to the lesion include axonal degeneration and gliosis (Pierpaoli 
et al., 1996; Werring et al., 2000); less frequently reported contralesional 
hemisphere changes have been referred to as transhemispheric diaschisis 
(Andrews, 1991). 
White matter disturbances occur with aging (Kohama et al., 2012). 
In particular prefrontal and PLIC areas have been shown to have age-
related degeneration (Salat et al., 2005). In our control data, age was 
strongly correlated with the shared variance in white matter integrity 
across frontoparietal tracts (r = 0.95, p b 0.0001). Conversely, the 
shared variance in white matter integrity between tracts in our stroke 
participants did not correlate with age (r = 0.20, p = 0.42). We believe 
this is because disruptions to white matter integrity due to stroke super-
sede those due to aging. This is supported by trends in our data between 
shared variance for the poststroke participants and chronicity (r = 0.42, 
p = 0.07) and lesion volume (r = 0.41, p = 0.07). Taken together, 
diminished integrity in both ipsilesional and contralesional hemispheres, 
and the large shared variance across the network in stroke participants, 
which is not correlated with age, suggest that there is a general stroke-
related factor affecting the frontoparietal network white matter integrity. 
This finding has important implications for interpreting quantitative 
white matter studies in stroke. First, reporting diffusion metrics as a </p>

<p>proportion of the same structure in the contralesional hemisphere may 
be biased by contralesional microstructural changes. Second, in light of 
network wide changes, single tract studies are at risk of over simplifying 
the relationship between white matter structure and behavior. </p>

<p>4.3. Tract integrity has a positive correlation with haptic performance </p>

<p>For the analysis of the relationship between haptic performance 
of the affected hand poststroke and integrity of individual tracts we 
prioritized ipsilesional and interhemispheric tracts because others 
have shown that areas of the most reduced structural connectivity are 
found in the ipsilesional hemisphere (Crofts et al., 2011), and the 
ipsilesional hemisphere would receive primary afferent input. In the 
poststroke participants a good relationship between ipsilesional 
thalamus-M1 integrity and haptic performance was identified. When 
thinking about the axons that travel between thalamus and M1 cortex 
it is tempting to assume the data reflect primarily efferent pathways. 
Of course, an important limitation of probabilistic tractography is the 
inability to distinguish between afferent and efferent tracts. One possible 
mechanism by which thalamus-M1 white matter integrity may support 
haptic performance is through facillatory drive to M1 from the dentate 
nucleus via the dentato-thalamo-cortical pathway. The dentate nucleus 
puts forth facilitation into the contralateral M1 through synaptic relay 
in the ventral lateral thalamus (Middleton and Strick, 2000; Dum 
et al., 2002); Ramnani, 2006). A second possible mechanism by which 
thalamus-M1 white matter may support haptic performance is through 
afferent input directly to M1. Some experiments have shown that the 
M1 hand area receives input from peripheral receptors (Friedman and 
Jones, 1981; Darian-Smith and Darian-Smith, 1993). There is still a 
question whether M1 receives direct afferents or only input through 
S1 (Reis et al., 2008). 
Previous studies have related the integrity of the descending fibers 
from M1 to handgrip (Schulz et al., 2012), motor skill (Schaechter 
et al., 2009; Lindenberg et al., 2010), and potential for recovery 
(Stinear et al., 2007; Lindenberg et al., 2012; Newton et al., 2006; 
Werring et al., 2000). When the M1-peduncular tract, which includes 
the CST, is generated with diffusion tractography, at the level of the 
internal capsule, it is located in the posterior limb of the internal capsule 
(PLIC) between the posterior putamen and the thalamus (Newton et al., </p>

<p>Table 4 
Pearson's correlation of tract diffusion parameters in control participants by right hand HASTe score. </p>

<p>Mean FA 
Mean MD 
Mean AD 
Mean RD </p>

<p>r 
p-Value 
r 
p-Value 
r 
p-Value 
r 
p-Value </p>

<p>Right HASTe 
Left T-S1 
0.03 
0.907 
−0.53 
0.036 
−0.60 
0.014 
−0.43 
0.097 
Left T-M1 
0.01 
0.953 
−0.15 
0.592 
−0.20 
0.469 
−0.10 
0.711 
Left S1-MFG 
0.14 
0.590 
−0.55 
0.033 
−0.66 
0.008* 
−0.50 
0.060 
Left S1-SII 
0.27 
0.308 
−0.08 
0.741 
−0.46 
0.072 
−0.03 
0.871 
S1-S1 
0.27 
0.324 
−0.59 
0.018 
−0.56 
0.031 
−0.35 
0.195 
Precuneus 
0.05 
0.846 
−0.68 
0.005* 
−0.72 
0.002* 
−0.53 
0.042 </p>

<p>With Bonferroni correction p-values are considered significant at p ≤ 0.008. Statistically significant correlations are indicated by an *. </p>

<p>Table 5 
Pearson's correlation of tract diffusion parameters by affected hand HASTe score. </p>

<p>Mean FA 
Mean MD 
Mean AD 
Mean RD </p>

<p>r 
p-Value 
r 
p-Value 
r 
p-Value 
r 
p-Value </p>

<p>Affected HASTe 
Ipsilesional T-S1 
0.18 
0.498 
−0.10 
0.238 
−0.33 
0.207 
−0.30 
0.265 
Ipsilesional T-M1 
0.46 
0.054 
−0.62 
0.006* 
−0.56 
0.163 
−0.62 
0.006* 
Ipsilesional S1-MFG 
0.29 
0.259 
−0.10 
0.760 
−0.03 
0.888 
−0.09 
0.715 
Ipsilesional S1-SII 
0.49 
0.047 
−0.46 
0.062 
−0.37 
0.138 
−0.48 
0.049 
S1-S1 
0.47 
0.063 
−0.42 
0.106 
−0.31 
0.234 
−0.42 
0.101 
Precuneus 
0.18 
0.510 
−0.09 
0.735 
−0.11 
0.673 
−0.07 
0.777 </p>

<p>After Bonferroni correction p-values are considered significant at p ≤ 0.008, statistically significant correlations are indicated by an *. </p>

<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>2006). Therefore, the CST is closely adjacent to the thalamus-M1 tract 
quantified here; it is possible there was overlap. Because haptic perfor-
mance measured by the HASTe is a somatosensory task, which is in part 
dependent upon motor manipulation, we wished to discern whether 
the positive relationship between thalamus-M1 integrity and HASTe 
score was a function of better motor performance. In post-hoc analyses 
we found no relationship between motor performance, measured by 
the 6-item Wolf and thalamus-M1 integrity. Nor was there a relationship 
between 6-item Wolf scores and haptic performance. These findings 
support the idea of a unique role of thalamus-M1 integrity to haptic 
performance in chronic stroke. 
The T-S1 tract integrity should reflect all afferent axons to the prima-
ry somatosensory cortex. In two participants, one with right and one with 
left hemisphere stroke we were unable to generate a T-S1 tract due to 
the lesion being within the tract. Both of these participants had HASTe 
scores so low they could have been attributed to chance (4/18 and 
7/18). Given we did not find a correlation between poststroke ipsilesional 
T-S1 integrity and affected HASTe scores, and T-S1 was not retained in 
the regression model, it suggest T-S1 tract is necessary but not sufficient 
for good haptic performance. 
Precuneus interhemispheric white matter integrity had the strongest 
relationship to haptic performance in the control participants. This finding 
echoes other studies in healthy adults, which relate precuneus function to 
sensory discrimination. Van de Winckel et al., found the precuneus was 
activated bilaterally in unfamiliar but not during familiar shape and length 
discrimination (Van de Winckel et al., 2012). Pellijeff and colleagues 
found precuneus activation related to the updating of limb posture 
(Pellijeff et al., 2006). When transcranial magnetic stimulation was used 
to inhibit the precuneus, impaired performance on grating orientation, a 
measure of tactile spatial acuity resulted (Zangaladze et al., 1999). The 
role of precuneus cortex in the sensorimotor transformations associated 
with goal directed movements, such as haptic exploration, is also the 
subject of a review (Cavanna and Trimble, 2006). </p>

<p>4.4. Frontoparietal network integrity predicts poststroke haptic performance </p>

<p>When a multivariate approach, which accounts for the influence of 
all variables, including age, was used to predict HASTe scores, 90% of 
the variability in affected hand scores poststroke and 87% of the vari-
ability in right hand scores in control participants could be attributed 
to network white matter integrity. Age was not a predictor in either 
model. The strongest predictor in both poststroke and control models 
was the precuneus interhemispheric tract. This finding is aligned with 
data from a previous study in which we found precuneus cortex fMRI 
activation correlated with HASTe scores in individuals with chronic 
left hemisphere stroke (Borstad et al., 2012b). Precuneus functional 
MRI activation has also been associated with length but not shape 
discrimination in a study of individuals with chronic left hemisphere </p>

<p>subcortical stroke (Van de Winckel et al., 2012). In the broad context 
of the relationship between poststroke white matter integrity and 
sensory-motor behavior, this studies findings parallel a recent large 
study of acute stroke in which a large percentage of sensory-motor 
deficit was explained by white matter damage (Corbetta et al., 2015) 
and exemplify the idea that neurologic disorders are due to problems 
of network function (Stam, 2014). 
A few limitations should be considered when interpreting this data. 
We used 32 diffusion-weighting gradient directions diffusion data, 
which may not be as robust to issues of complex intra-voxel fiber archi-
tecture and partial volume effects as acquisitions with a greater number 
of gradient directions or tensor-free approaches. It is possible that the 
high variability in FA found in our S1-SII tract is related to the tracts' 
smaller, peripheral, and more acute path (Heiervang et al., 2006), there-
fore we feel care should be taken in interpretation of S1-SII diffusion 
parameter values. The dense intra-cortical connections between S1 
and M1 are known to be important to sensorimotor processes (see 
recent review by Borich) (Borich et al., 2015), however, they were not 
quantified in this study because accurate tracking in the network of 
horizontal intra-cortical white matter is a limitation of probabilistic 
tractography (Jbabdi and Johansen-Berg, 2011). They should be included 
in future efforts to quantify this network. Regardless of our efforts to 
check the position of each tract of interest in each participant, subtle mis-
registration between participant data and the standard space masks may 
have resulted in small differences in tracts generated and the diffusion 
metrics derived. By having an age matched control group and applying 
the same rigorous registration and analysis process across groups we 
attempted to mitigate this effect. Diffusion metrics may have been 
underestimated in poststroke participants as a minimum FA threshold 
of 0.2 was used to constrain probabilistic tracking. We chose conservative 
thresholding to reduce sensitivity to noise and partial volume effects 
making false positives less likely (Behrens et al., 2003). However, this 
may have resulted in smaller samples in degraded tracts (Johansen-
Berg and Behrens, 2009). In spite of this we identified many differences 
in tract integrity between poststroke and control participants and statis-
tically significant and plausible relationships with behavior, which lend 
support to our approach. The poststroke participants in this study had 
heterogeneous lesion locations. While lesions were masked to avoid 
contribution to registration error, the lack of strict anatomical criteria 
for lesions of the participants included here likely contributed to variabil-
ity, decreasing the sensitivity of this study, however, variable lesion size 
and location is reflective of the clinical population with stroke and likely 
improves generalizability of our findings. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>This study is contributes to the growing body of literature that seeks 
to use neuroimaging information to predict functional potential and to </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Shared variance across 10 frontoparietal tract MD values correlates with age in control participants. The first principal component (PC1) accounting for the variance across tracts was 
strongly correlated with age in the control participants (r = 0.95, p b 0.0001) but not in the poststroke participants (r = 0.20, p = 0.42). </p>

<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

<p>target rehabilitation interventions (Riley et al., 2011; Gauthier et al., 
2012; Stinear and Ward, 2013). We demonstrated the importance of 
frontoparietal white matter in mediating haptic performance and 
specifically identified that T-M1 and precuneus interhemispheric tracts 
may be appropriate targets for piloting rehabilitation interventions, 
such as noninvasive brain stimulation, when the goal is to improve 
haptic performance of the affected hand in chronic stroke. The relative 
strength of these findings is good given the sample was heterogeneous 
and moderately sized, and a reliable white matter quantification 
approach was employed. Future studies may increase power to identify 
neural correlates of poststroke sensorimotor performance by combining 
functional connectivity and tensor-free structural measurement into 
one analysis (Calamante et al., 2013). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by a PODS I scholarship from the 
Foundation for Physical Therapy, Inc.; also The Ohio State University Neu-
roscience Signature Program and The OSU Center for Clinical and Transla-
tional Research award number TL RR025753 from the National Center for 
Research Resources, funded by the Office of the Director, National 
Institutes of Health and supported by the NIH Road map for Medical 
Research. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and 
does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Center 
for Research Resources or the National Institutes of Health. </p>

<p>Appendix A. Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at http://dx. 
doi.org/10.1016/j.nicl.2015.11.007. </p>



<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>



<p> 
A.L. Borstad et al. / NeuroImage: Clinical 10 (2016) 129-139 </p>

</text></tei>