<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4567233" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: To investigate the reactivation of the hepatitis B virus (HBV) following transarterial </p>

<p>chemoembolization (TACE) in Chinese hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) patients with low 
serum HBV DNA level, and to analyze the factors related to HBV reactivation in HCC patients 
with low serum HBV DNA level. 
Methods: From November 2011 to January 2014, 109 patients newly diagnosed with HCC </p>

<p>with an HBV DNA level less than 2,000 IU/mL were enrolled in the study. These patients 
underwent at least two TACE procedures and were followed-up for at least 3 months to assess 
the reactivation of HBV DNA. Ten variables were compared in patients with and without HBV 
reactivation to evaluate the factors related to HBV reactivation in HCC patients with low serum 
HBV DNA level. 
Results: Of 109 HCC patients with low level HBV DNA, nine patients were HBeAg-positive, the </p>

<p>other 100 patients were HBeAg-negative. Twenty-three of 109 (21.1%) patients developed HBV 
reactivation after TACE. Of nine HBeAg-positive patients, 55.6% (5/9) developed HBV reacti-
vation, while in 100 HBeAg-negative patients, the rate of HBV reactivation was 18% (18/100) 
(P=0.019). Of ten variables of patients with low level HBV DNA, the levels of AFP and HBeAg 
status were found to be significantly correlated with HBV reactivation. Nevertheless, on binary 
logistic regression analysis, only HBeAg-positive status was the independent predictor of HBV 
reactivation in HCC patients with low serum HBV DNA level (odds ratio, 7.41; P=0.013). 
Conclusion: HCC patients with low serum HBV DNA level still remain associated with risk </p>

<p>of viral reactivation after TACE, and HBeAg-positive HCC patients have a higher risk than 
patients with HBeAg-negative status. 
Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the seventh most common cancer and third leading 
cause of cancer-related deaths in the world according to the GloboCan 2008. 1 Most of 
the cases arise in Asia and Africa, and the People's Republic of China alone accounts 
for 55% of cases of HCC worldwide. 2 The major risk factor for HCC in the People's 
Republic of China is chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection. 3 Compared with patients 
with hepatitis C virus, patients with HBV tend to have less surveillance and more 
advanced stages of HCC, 4 which often precludes surgical options with curative intent 
such as resection and transplantation. Accordingly, transarterial chemoembolization 
(TACE) currently is considered as the mainstay of therapy for nonsurgical HCC. 5 </p>

<p>Correspondence: Jinlong song 
Department of surgical Oncology 
(interventional Therapy), shandong 
Cancer hospital and institute, shandong 
academy of Medical sciences, 440 Jiyan 
Road, Jinan, shandong, 250117, 
People's Republic of China 
Tel +86 531 6762 6412 
Fax +86 531 8798 4079 
email songjlmd@gmail.com </p>

<p>Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Therapeutics and Clinical Risk Management 
7 September 2015 </p>

<p>Therapeutics and Clinical Risk Management 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1368 </p>

<p>shao et al </p>

<p>Transarterial chemotherapy can reactivate HBV 
replication in patients with HBV-related HCC. 6-8 Pre-emptive 
antiviral therapy should be considered in HCC patients with 
high-level viremia. 8 The Asian-Pacific Association for 
the Study of Liver recommends that pre-emptive antiviral 
therapy should be initiated in all HCC patients who are to 
undergo TACE. 9 However, universal application of this 
strategy is costly and burdensome, especially as antiviral 
therapy for carriers of inactive HBV is not reimbursed 
by health insurance in the People's Republic of China, so 
pre-emptive antiviral therapy is often used in patients with 
serum HBV DNA level more than 2,000 IU/mL, and not 
widely used for patients with low level serum HBV DNA. 
To date, the data on viral reactivation following TACE in 
Chinese HBV-related HCC patients with low serum HBV 
DNA level are limited. 
In this study, we aimed to investigate the reactivation of 
the HBV following TACE in HCC patients with low serum 
HBV DNA level. The factors related to HBV reactivation 
in HCC patients with low serum HBV DNA level were also 
evaluated. </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>This is a retrospective study and was approved by the Institu-
tional Review Board of Shandong Cancer Hospital and Insti-
tute. Informed consent was waived. A total of 302 patients 
were newly diagnosed with unresectable HBV-related HCC 
from November 2011 to January 2014 at our unit (the Depart-
ment of Interventional therapy, Shandong Cancer Hospital 
and Institute). All 302 patients were tested for HBV DNA 
levels and Hepatitis B serology including HBeAg and anti-
HBe at the time of the diagnosis of HCC. Among these, 168 
patients with HBV DNA level less than 2,000 IU/mL were 
enrolled in the study. Of these 168 patients, 59 were excluded 
from analysis due to follow-up loss within 3 months after the 
first TACE session; the remaining 109 patients underwent at 
least two TACE procedures and were followed-up for at least 
3 months to assess the reactivation of HBV DNA. 
The diagnosis of HCC was made according to the updated 
standards for the diagnosis and treatment of primary liver 
cancer from the Chinese Society of Liver Cancer/Chinese 
Society of Clinical Oncology/Chinese Medical Association 
branch of Hepatology. 10 HBV DNA was measured using 
an HBVquantitative Kit (Shanghai kehua bio-engineering 
company limited, Shanghai, People's Republic of China) 
with a detection limit of 500 IU/mL. Hepatitis B serology was 
measured by commercial electrochemiluminescence immu-
noassay (Hoffman-La Roche Ltd., Basel, Switzerland). </p>

<p>TACE was performed according to traditional method. 
The chemotherapeutic regimens used for TACE were deter-
mined by the interventional radiologist. One or two kinds of 
pharmaceutical agents including fluorouracil glycosides (750-
1,000 mg), oxaliplatin (100-200 mg), or cisplatin (40-60 mg) 
were infused into feeding arteries of tumor, then 5-20 mL 
Lipiodol mixed with epirubicin (30 mg) was infused into feeding 
arteries at a rate of 1 mL/min until stasis flow in tumor vascular-
ity was achieved. The need for gelatin sponger was determined 
by the interventional radiologist. TACE was performed at 1 to 
2 monthly intervals. The duration of the patient's follow-up was 
at least 3 months from the time of the first TACE. 
The serum HBV DNA levels were measured before 
TACE and followed-up after TACE at 1 or 2 monthly inter-
vals. Low level serum HBV DNA was defined as less than 
2,000 IU/mL. 11 HBV reactivation was defined as reappear-
ance or an increase more than tenfold in serum HBV DNA 
compared to the baseline level. 6 To evaluate the factors 
related to HBV reactivation in HCC patients with low serum 
HBV DNA level, ten variables were compared in patients 
with and without HBV reactivation. 
Patients with HBV DNA level ,2,000 IU/mL were 
divided into two groups for further analysis. One group 
included patients who had antiviral history before HCC was 
developed and were on antiviral therapy at the time of HCC 
diagnosis, and the other group included patients who had no 
antiviral history before HCC diagnosis. Patients with antiviral 
history remained on their antiviral agents. For patients with-
out antiviral history, antiviral therapy was given to patients 
with HBV DNA level between 500-2,000 IU/mL; no anti-
viral therapy was commenced for patients with HBV DNA 
level ,500 mL until HBV reactivation was identified. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">statistical 
program for social sciences</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). 
Categorical variables were analyzed using chi-squared test 
and Fisher's exact test when appropriate. Continues variables 
were analyzed using Student's t-test. Binary logistic regres-
sion analysis was performed to identify the independent 
predictors of HBV reactivation. A P-value of ,0.05 was 
considered statically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Of the 109 patients, nine were HBeAg-positive, and the 
remaining 100 patients were HBeAg-negative. Twenty-three 
of 109 (21.1%) developed HBV reactivation during the 
follow-up period. For HBeAg-positive patients, 55.6% (5/9) </p>

<p>Therapeutics and Clinical Risk Management 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1369 </p>

<p>The hepatitis B virus reactivation after transarterial chemoembolization </p>

<p>developed HBV reactivation, while for HBeAg-negative 
patients, the rate of HBV reactivation was 18% (18/100). 
HBV reactivation developed more frequently in HBeAg-
positive patients (P=0.019). 
Among the ten variables compared in patients with and 
without HBV reactivation, the level of AFP and HBeAg status 
were found to be significantly correlated with HBV reacti-
vation. Nevertheless, on binary logistic regression analysis, 
only positive HBeAg status was the independent predictor 
of HBV reactivation in HCC patients with low serum HBV 
DNA level (odds ratio, 7.41; P=0.013) (Table 1). 
Of the 109 patients, 35 patients had antiviral history 
before the development of HCC, and antiviral therapy was 
continued in these patients; the other 74 patients had no anti-
viral history and no antiviral therapy was commenced after 
TACE. For patients with antiviral history and with antiviral 
therapy, five (14.3%, 5/35) experienced HBV reactivation; 
while for patients without antiviral history and without 
antiviral treatment, 18 (24.3%, 18/74) experienced HBV 
reactivation. However, there was no significant difference 
between the two groups (P=0.18). 
Of the 109 patients with HBV DNA ,2,000 IU/mL, 
95 patients had HBV DNA ,500 IU/mL, the other 14 patients 
had HBV DNA between 500-2,000 IU/mL. Of the 95 patients 
with HBV DNA ,500 IU/mL, 18 (18.9%, 18/95) experi-
enced HBV reactivation, while of the 14 patients with HBV 
DNA 500-2,000 IU/mL, five (35.7%, 5/14) experienced 
HBV reactivation. However, there were no significant dif-
ferences between the two groups (P=0.15). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>TACE is the standard treatment for intermediate-stage 
HCC according to the Barcelona clinic liver cancer staging </p>

<p>classification. In Asia, the role of TACE is further extended 
to include the treatment of advanced HCC. TACE currently 
is considered as the mainstay of therapy for nonsurgical 
HCC. It is now well-known that transarterial chemotherapy 
can reactivate HBV replication in HBV-related HCC patients 
with high baseline HBV DNA level. However, before 2004, 
studies on HBV reactivation in HCC patients receiving tran-
sarterial chemotherapy were lacking. 6 In the last decade, a 
series of studies on HBV reactivation in patients with HCC 
following TACE was published. 6-8 The risk of HBV reac-
tivation in transarterial therapy was reportedly 22%-40%. 
HBeAg-positive and a baseline HBV DNA level of more 
than 2,000 IU/mL were regarded as independent predictors 
of HBV reactivation. 7,8 In the present study, HBV reactiva-
tion after TACE in HCC patients with HBV DNA level of 
less than 2,000 IU/mL was investigated. Twenty-three of 
109 (21.1%) HCC patients with HBV DNA ,2,000 IU/mL 
developed HBV reactivation after TACE. This implies that 
HBV reactivation should not be overlooked in patients with 
low levels of viremia. Furthermore, in the present study, 
HBeAg-positive status was found to be the only indepen-
dent predictor of HBV reactivation, and 55.6% (5/9) of 
HBeAg-positive patients experienced HBV reactivation. This 
demonstrates that pre-emptive antiviral therapy is urgently 
needed for HBeAg-positive patients with low serum HBV 
DNA levels. 
Another finding of our present study is that five (14.3%, 
5/35) patients who were receiving antiviral therapy experi-
enced HBV reactivation. The incidence of HBV reactivation 
in patients who had antiviral history and were on antiviral 
therapy in our study was higher than those who had no 
antiviral history but were using pre-emptive antiviral agents 
reported in a previous study. This was a puzzling finding </p>

<p>Table 1 Factors related to hBV reactivation </p>

<p>Univariate analysis 
Multivariate analysis </p>

<p>Patients with HBV 
reactivation (n=23) </p>

<p>Patients without HBV 
reactivation (n=86) </p>

<p>P-value 
OR (95% CI) 
P-value </p>

<p>age (years) 
52.9±1.7 
56.3±1.0 
0.122 
0.95 (0.89-1.00) 
0.90 
sex (M:F) 
21:2 
71:15 
0.518 
0.36 (0.05-2.43) 
0.292 
hBeag (positive:negative) 
5:18 
4:82 
0.019 
7.41 (1.53-35.91) 
0.013 
aFP (ng/ml) 
3,238.1±2,605 
583.9±113.2 
0.001 
1.00 (1.00-1.00) 
0.522 
alT (iU/l) 
52.8±8.2 
38.0±3.5 
0.2 
1.02 (0.99-1.05) 
0.098 
asT (iU/l) 
59.2±10.3 
62.5±14.5 
0.807 
0.99 (0.97-1.01) 
0.365 
alB (g/l) 
48.8±0.9 
41.9±0.7 
0.383 
0.96 (0.88-1.04) 
0.277 </p>

<p>Tbil (µmol/l) 
21.0±2.6 
19.8±1.0 
0.086 
0.99 (0.95-1.04) 
0.773 
alP (iU/l) 
113.9±9.8 
119.5±7.3 
0.195 
0.99 (0.98-1.00) 
0.581 
ggT (iU/l) 
143.6±34.8 
123.4±16.8 
0.728 
1.00 (0.99-1.00) 
0.896 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: HBV, hepatitis B virus; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval; M, male; F, female; Tbil, total bilirubin; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AFP, α-fetoprotein; 
asT, aspertate aminotransferase; alB, albumin; alP, alkaline phosphatase; ggT, glutamine transpeptidase; hBeag, hepatitis B e antigen. </p>

<p>Therapeutics and Clinical Risk Management </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/therapeutics-and-clinical-risk-management-journal </p>

<p>Therapeutics and Clinical Risk Management is an international, peer-
reviewed journal of clinical therapeutics and risk management, focusing 
on concise rapid reporting of clinical studies in all therapeutic areas, 
outcomes, safety, and programs for the effective, safe, and sustained 
use of medicines. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, CAS, </p>

<p>EMBase, Scopus and the Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The 
manuscript management system is completely online and includes a 
very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>Therapeutics and Clinical Risk Management 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>1370 </p>

<p>shao et al </p>

<p>because a previous study had reported excellent efficacy of 
pre-emptive lamivudine therapy in HCC patients undergoing 
chemo-lipiodolization. 7 The reason for this finding may be 
the emergence of viral resistance. Unfortunately, no analy-
sis on viral resistance was done in our present study, so the 
hypothesis could not be proved. 
There are some limitations in our study. Firstly, the time 
of follow-up on HBV reactivation after TACE is short, so 
some cases of HBV reactivation caused by repeated TACE 
procedures may have been excluded. Secondly, the propor-
tion of patients who were excluded from analysis due to 
follow-up loss within 3 months after the first TACE proce-
dure was high (35.1%, 59/168); only 109 patients were left 
for HBV reactivation analysis and only nine patients were 
HBeAg-positive for subgroup analysis, which may lead to 
bias because of the small group. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, this study highlights that HCC patients with 
low serum HBV DNA level are still associated with more 
than 20% risk of viral reactivation. HBeAg-positive status 
was the only independent predictor of HBV reactivation in 
HCC patients with low serum HBV DNA level. Special atten-
tion should be paid to patients who have antiviral history 
with lamivudine, because viral reactivation could still occur 
in those patients. Study results suggest that pre-emptive 
antiviral therapy is necessary for HCC patients with low 
serum HBV DNA level. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>All authors contributed toward data analysis, drafting and 
revising the paper and agree to be accountable for all aspects 
of the work. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>

<p>References </p>



</text></tei>