<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4998785" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Due to the neurotoxicity effects of general anesthesia (GA) </p>

<p>and sedatives found in animal studies, there is a general recommen-
dation to avoid nonurgent surgical procedures requiring anesthesia in 
children younger than 3 years of age. The aim of this study was to 
determine the incidence of anesthesia-related postoperative cognitive 
dysfunction (POCD) on the first day (Day 1) and at 6 weeks after 
elective noncardiac surgery in school-age children. 
This was a prospective cohort study of 118 children undergoing GA 
and 126 age-matched controls of school children aged 5 to 12 years. All 
children were given a panel of 4 neuropsychological assessments (Hong 
Kong List Learning for verbal memory, Visual Matching for processing 
speed, Visual Memory, and General Comprehension Skill from the 
Hong Kong Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children). The primary 
outcome was the incidence of POCD on Day 1 and at 6 weeks after 
surgery. POCD was defined as when at least 2 of the 4 cognitive function </p>

<p>tests showed individual Z-scores À1.96 or a combined Z-score 
À1.96. 
Using the combined Z-score definition, the incidence of POCD in 
the GA group on Day 1 and at 6 weeks were 5.1% (95% confidence 
interval [CI]: 2.1-10.3) and 3.4% (95% CI: 1.1-8.0), respectively. No 
POCD was found using the other definition. The incidences of decline 
and improvement in neuropsychological tests were similar between 
groups over time except for a higher risk in visual matching impairment 
in the anesthesia group (11.9%) versus control group (1.6%) on Day 1 
(P &lt; 0.01). The adjusted relative risk ratio of postoperative cognitive 
decline to improvement between groups on Day 1 and at 6 weeks were 
0.85 (95% CI: 0.10-7.05) and 0.45 (95% CI: 0.04-4.84), respectively. 
The observed risk of POCD is assumed to apply to current drugs and 
techniques used in GA. 
In conclusion, the incidence of POCD was low. GA was associated 
with a transient effect on visual matching. When using the widely 
accepted Z-score definitions and relative risk ratio methodology, we 
found no anesthesia-related POCD per se in school-age children. </p>

<p>(Medicine 95(14):e3250) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: 95% CI = 95% confidence interval, CrI = credible 
interval, GA = general anesthesia, HKLL = Hong Kong List 
Learning, HK-WISC = Hong Kong Wechsler Intelligence Scale 
for Children, IQ = intelligence quotient, IQR = interquartile range, 
OR = odds ratio, POCD = postoperative cognitive dysfunction, 
POCI = postoperative cognitive improvement, RRR = relative risk 
ratio, SD = standard deviation, VAS = visual analog scale. </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>any children require anesthesia for surgical procedures 
and investigations each year, with approximately 450,000 
children undergoing in-patient surgery each year in the United 
States. 
1 A common parental concern is whether general anesthe-
sia (GA) has potentially deleterious effects on children's cog-
nitive and academic development. A consensus statement by the 
US Food and Drug Administration, SmartTots, and the Amer-
ican Academy of Pediatrics 
2 recommends avoiding nonurgent 
surgical procedures requiring anesthesia in children younger 
than 3 years of age because of the neurotoxicity and neuro-
plasticity effects of GA and sedatives shown in animal studies. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Postoperative cognitive dysfunction (POCD) has been 
defined as a subtle impairment of memory, concentration, and 
speed of information processing after surgery. 
4 While the epi-
demiology of POCD in adults after cardiac 
5 and noncardiac 
surgery 
6,7 has been well established, most existing pediatric 
studies have focused on the long-term neurodevelopmental out-
comes after GA exposure before the age of 4 years. 
8,9 Current </p>

<p>Editor: Kazuo Hanaoka. 
Received: January 18, 2016; revised: March 7, 2016; accepted: March 9, 
2016. 
From the Departments of Anaesthesia and Intensive Care (CSTA, AL, 
ASCL, RCKC, TG), Psychology (CM), Psychiatry (KYCL), and Surgery 
(CKY), The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shatin, New Territories, 
Hong Kong. 
Correspondence: Anna Lee, Department of Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, 
The Chinese University of Hong Kong, 4 F/L Main Clinical Block and 
Trauma Centre, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, New Territories, 
Hong Kong (e-mail: annalee@cuhk.edu.hk). 
RCKC is currently at the Department of Rehabilitation Sciences, The Hong 
Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Hong Kong. 
Designed the study, interpreted the data and revised the manuscript for 
important intellectual content (CSTA, CM). Reanalyzed and interpreted 
the data, drafted the manuscript and revised the manuscript for important 
intellectual content (AL). Acquisition of data and revised the manuscript 
for important intellectual content (ASCL, RCKC). Designed the study 
and revised the manuscript for important intellectual content (CKY, 
KYCL, TG). 
Part of this work was previously presented at the joint meeting of the Society 
of Pediatric Anesthesia and Japanese Society of Pediatric Anesthesiol-
ogy in San Francisco (October 10, 2003) and The 13th World Congress of 
Anaesthsiologists in Paris (April 18-23, 2004). 
The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necess-
arily represent the official views of the Hong Kong Research Grants 
Council or the Hospital Authority of Hong Kong. 
This research work was fully funded by a grant from the Research Grants 
Council of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, China 
(Project reference: CUHK4002/01M). 
The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0, where it is 
permissible to download, share and reproduce the work in any medium, 
provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or 
used commercially. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000003250 </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OBSERVATIONAL STUDY </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 14, April 2016 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>evidence suggests that early exposure to anesthesia is associated 
with an increased risk of neurodevelopmental deficits (odds ratio 
1.9, 95% credible interval 1.2-3.0). 
8 However, the risk of 
language and abstract reasoning deficits at age 10 after an initial 
exposure to anesthesia in children over 3 years old was similar to 
other children with no exposure to anesthesia. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>There is a paucity of studies on the short-term effects of 
anesthesia on cognitive function performance in school-age 
children. A randomized controlled trial of propofol versus 
isoflurane in 58 children aged between 5 and 14 years showed 
that both groups had visual memory deficits at 24 h after dental 
surgery. 
11 Compared with sevoflurane, children given propofol 
had visual memory deficits at 1 week, but recovered at 3 
months, after elective hernia surgery. 
12 In contrast, there was 
no effect of halothane-nitrous oxide GA on reasoning, motor or 
memory functions at 24 h after myringotomy in children aged 
between 5 and 8 years when compared with a control group (no 
anesthesia). 
13 These findings highlight the heterogeneity in 
study designs, type of neuropsychological tests, POCD defi-
nition, and timing of POCD used. 
Therefore, the effects of GA on early postoperative cog-
nitive function in school-age children undergoing noncardiac 
surgery are not well understood. We hypothesized that GA has 
no effect on short-term postoperative cognitive function. To 
control for the practice learning effects of serial neuropsycho-
logical tests, we included a control group of students of similar 
ages from a local school in this prospective cohort study to 
determine the incidence of anesthesia-related POCD on the first 
day (Day 1) and at 6 weeks after elective noncardiac surgery. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study Design, Setting, and Participants </p>

<p>Ethical approval for this study (CRE-2000.063) was pro-
vided by the Chinese University of Hong Kong Faculty of 
Medicine Clinical Research Ethics Committee, Hong Kong, 
on March 28, 2001. After parents gave written informed con-
sent, we recruited children with American Society of Anesthe-
siologists physical status class I or II, aged 5 to 12 years old 
undergoing elective general, urologic or orthopedic surgery of at 
least 60 min duration from April 2001 to January 2005. Patients 
were assessed a day before surgery (baseline), a day after 
surgery (Day 1), and 6 weeks afterwards. While it is ideal to 
perform the first follow-up at 1 week, for logistical reasons, we 
chose 1 day after surgery. The control group included students 
of similar ages from a local school. We recruited them from July 
2001 to November 2002 after we obtained the school approval 
and written informed parental consents. Children in the control 
group were followed up at their school at the same time intervals 
described in the anesthesia group. 
All participants undertook an intelligence screening test 
which consisted of the Vocabulary and Digit Span subtests from 
the Hong Kong Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children (HK-
WISC). 
14 Exclusion criteria included subjects with intelligence 
screening test below 70, inability to perform cognitive function 
tests during the perioperative period due to uncooperativeness, 
inability to understand instructions, presence of a visual or 
auditory impairment, or expected need for postoperative 
intensive care. </p>

<p>Anesthesia Management </p>

<p>EMLA cream (lidocaine 2.5% and prilocaine 2.5%) and 
oral midazolam 0.5 mg/kg up to a maximum of 15 mg were </p>

<p>given as premedication. Anesthesia was induced with intrave-
nous agents, thiopentone or propofol. In cases with difficult 
venous access, sevoflurane inhalation was used. All patients 
were intubated using a nondepolarizing neuromuscular block-
ing agent. Anesthesia was maintained with isoflurane or sevo-
flurane, nitrous oxide and oxygen, and mechanical ventilation. 
At the end of surgery, the residual paralysis was reversed with 
atropine and neostigmine. The choice of intraoperative and 
postoperative analgesics was at the discretion of the attending 
anesthesiologist. Pulse oximetry, noninvasive blood pressure, 
electrocardiography, core temperature, end tidal carbon dioxide, 
and anesthetic concentrations were monitored. Normothermia 
and normocapnia were maintained. The anesthetic depth was 
adjusted clinically by the attending anesthesiologist. The Bis-
pectral Index (BIS), not revealed to the anesthesiologists, was 
continuously monitored and recorded using the A-2000 BIS 
monitoring system (Aspect Medical Systems, Inc., Newton, 
MA) and a standard adult (Zipprep) electrode. All the 
parameters monitored were downloaded using software devel-
oped in our department. Any episode of desaturation (SpO 2 
90% for 30 s or more) or hypotension (systolic blood pressure 
&lt;80 mm Hg for 3 min) after excluding the effect of artifacts, 
were recorded for data analysis. Pain scores on the first day after 
surgery and at 6 weeks were recorded using the visual analog 
scores (VAS). The pain levels were categorized as mild (VAS 5-
44 mm), moderate (VAS 45-74 mm), and severe (VAS ! 
75 mm). </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Cognitive Function Assessments </p>

<p>The research staff was trained in the administration of 
neuropsychological tests and interview techniques for this 
study. To familiarize the children with the cognitive function 
assessments, we gave an explanation of the tests and ran a brief 
trial with all participants. In the anesthesia group, the baseline 
tests were administered, after the preoperative visit by the 
anesthesiologists a day before surgery, in an isolation room 
in the ward or a corner in the ward with least traffic. Post-
operative cognitive function assessments were conducted in the 
ward or at the patient's home. All children in the control group 
undertook all tests in a quiet room at their school. If the child 
was unable to do the assessment at the scheduled time, a nearest 
possible time was arranged. 
The panel of 4 cognitive function tests included: </p>

<p>1. Hong Kong List Learning (HKLL) test, 
16 a verbal memory 
test consisting of a list of 16 items (words) that was read to 
the child in Cantonese. The child was then asked to recall 
these words in any order immediately. This was repeated a 
second time. Finally, the child was asked to recall from the 
list as many items as possible after a 10-min period of 
distraction. For data analysis, we used the scores obtained 
for the correct items in the final recall. The test has been 
validated and local normative data are available. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>2. Visual Matching test from the Woodcock-Johnson tests of 
cognitive ability. 
18 This test measured the speed of 
processing and consisted of rows of figures that were 
presented to each child. Each row comprised of 6 numbers. 
The child was asked to circle the 2 numbers that were the 
same in each row over 3 min. We used the age standardized 
scores for analysis. The test yielded a test-retest reliability 
in American participants aged 6 and 9 years of 0.73 and 
0.78, respectively. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>3. Visual Memory test from the Gardner Test of Visual-
Perceptual Skills Revised (1996). 
19 This test consisted of 16 </p>

<p>Aun et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 14, April 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>two-dimensional line pictures to memorize. Each of these 
pictures was presented to the child for 5 s. The page was 
then turned to a next page containing 5 similar pictures with 
minor variations. The child was to identify the 1 that was 
presented earlier. Testing was discontinued if incorrect 
identification was made for 4 consecutive pictures. We used 
the age standardized scores for correct pictures for analysis. 
The split-half reliability of this task for American children 
was 0.80. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>4. General Comprehension subtest from the HK-WISC </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>measured the social comprehension and practical judgment 
and consisted of 30 orally administered questions that was 
given to each child. Each answer was allotted a rating from 
0 to 2 points, based on the quality of the answer given. This 
test was terminated once the child scored 0 on 5 consecutive 
questions. Age standardized scores were used for 
data analysis. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The mean and standard deviation (SD) or median and 
interquartile range (IQR) were reported as appropriate for 
continuous data after checking data for normality using the 
Shapiro-Wilk test. Independent sample t test, Mann-Whitney 
U test, or x 
2 tests were used to compare perioperative differ-
ences between groups. Pearson correlation analysis was used to 
assess the test-retest reliability of the cognitive function tests 
between baseline and follow-up sessions. 
20 We modeled indi-
vidual serial changes in cognitive function tests using mixed-
effects linear regressions by assuming different random inter-
cepts for each participant and adjusted for baseline intelligence 
quotient (IQ), age, gender, and any previous exposure to 
anesthesia. List-wise deletion was used to deal with missing 
completely at random follow-up data; it has been recommended 
that tests with missing data should not be used for evaluation of 
cognitive function. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>The primary outcome was incidence of POCD. This was 
estimated from the Z-scores methodology that requires data 
from the control group outlined by Rasmussen et al. 
21 We used 2 
criteria to define the direction of change (either decline or 
improvement) in the postoperative cognitive function in each 
child. POCD was defined as either at least 2 of the 4 cognitive 
functions tests with an individual Z-score À1.96 or a com-
bined Z-score of À1.96. Similarly, postoperative cognitive 
improvement (POCI) was defined as either at least 2 of the 4 
cognitive functions tests with an individual Z-score !1.96 or a 
combined Z-score of !1.96. To identify whether the post-
operative cognitive decline in performance in these children </p>

<p>represented a true deterioration or random variation, we used 
multinominal logistic regression to estimate the relative risk 
ratio of POCD to POCI between groups (POCD/POCI-RRR) </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>after adjusting for IQ, age, and gender. All analyses were 
performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">14.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">StataCorp</rs>, College Station, 
TX). The level of significance was set at P &lt; 0.05. 
Based on pilot data of 7 subjects (3 controls and 4 patients), 
a repeated measures analysis of variance design of 2 groups 
(control and anesthesia) measured at 3 times, we calculated that 
110 subjects in each group (total n ¼ 220) would be required to 
detect a difference of a small effect size of 0.20 at 90% power 
with correlation between repeated measures of 0.70 at 5% 
significance level (<rs id="software-2" type="software">nQuery Advisor</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">4.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Janet D Elashoff</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-date">2000</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Of the 289 participants screened, 276 were recruited but 32 
were lost to follow-up (11.6%), leaving 244 for analysis 
(Figure 1). The refusal rate of follow-up cognitive tests was 
similar between anesthesia (9.9%) and control (6.7%) groups 
(P ¼ 0.34). The demographic characteristics were comparable 
between groups, except for gender (Table 1). The median time 
to the second follow-up was similar between anesthesia (42.5 
days, IQR 40.0-46.0) and control (42.0 days, IQR 42.0-43.0) 
groups (P ¼ 0.59). 
Among the 118 patients, 114 (96.6%) received midazolam 
premedication. Intravenous anesthetics for induction were 
given in 106 (89.8%); 99 (83.8%) had thiopentone (median </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Flow of participants in the cohort study. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Comparison of Baseline Characteristics of Children by Group </p>

<p>Anesthesia (n ¼ 118) 
Controls (n ¼ 126) 
P Value </p>

<p>Median (IQR) age, y 
8.0 (6.7-9.9) 
8.4 (6.8-10.9) 
0.290 
Males, % 
86 (72.9) 
66 (52.4) 
0.001 
Median (IQR) body weight, kg 
26.5 (21.0-36.1) 
28.1 (24.0-35.0) 
0.188 
Median (IQR) IQ 
115 (95-140) 
120 (100-135) 
0.430 
Median (IQR) vocabulary test score </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>13 (10-17) 
12 (10-14) 
0.120 
Median (IQR) digit span test score </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>11 (9-13) 
11 (9-13) 
0.406 
Previous anesthesia exposure, % 
10 (8.5) 
7 (5.6) 
0.371 </p>

<p>IQ ¼ intelligence quotient, IQR ¼ interquartile range. 
Ã Scaled score. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 14, April 2016 
Cognitive Effects After General Anesthesia in Children </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>dose 4.4 mg/kg, IQR 3.9-4.9) and 7 (5.9%) had propofol 
(median dose 2.6 mg/kg, IQR 2.2-3.3). Eighteen (15.3%) 
patients were given sevoflurane. The majority of patients 
(n ¼ 116, 98.3%) had isoflurane for maintenance. Nitrous oxide 
was used in 91 (77.1%) patients while the rest had an air and 
oxygen mixture. All patients had atropine and neostigmine for 
reversal of residual paralysis. The median duration of anesthesia 
was 122 min (IQR 76-193). The median time to obeying 
commands was 15 min (IQR 7-33). In the 107 children with 
recorded BIS values, the mean (SD) was 54.1 (7.4). 
Most patients (98.3%) had intraoperative opioids (fentanyl 
and/or morphine). In the postoperative period, 31 (26.3%) had 
opioids, 71 (60.2%) had paracetamol, 7 (5.9%) nonsteroidal 
anti-inflammatory drugs, and 70 (59.3%) had regional anesthe-
sia for analgesia. Of the 110 patients with recorded pain scores 
on Day 1, 43 (39.1%), 37 (33.6%), and 10 (9.1%) children 
experienced mild, moderate, and severe pain, respectively. At 6 
weeks, 20 (17.7%) of 113 patients with pain assessments 
reported experiencing some pain. 
The test-retest reliability was high (r &gt; 0.7) for HKLL, 
visual matching, and general comprehension and was accep-
table (0.4 &lt; r &lt; 0.6) for visual memory over the 3 time points. 
The serial changes in the cognitive function test scores are 
shown in Figure 2. Despite adjustment for confounders, the 
baselines' scores were significantly lower in the anesthesia 
group than the control group for HKLL (mean difference 
À1.0, 95% confidence interval [CI]: À0.3 to À1.7) and visual 
matching (mean difference À9.3, 95% CI: À5.1 to À13.5). 
There was a significant group-time interaction for visual 
matching (P &lt; 0.01) and visual memory (P ¼ 0.03). Compared 
with the control group, children undergoing anesthesia had 
significantly lower overall group means for HKLL 
(P ¼ 0.001), visual matching (P &lt; 0.001), visual memory 
(P &lt; 0.01), and general comprehension (P ¼ 0.01). 
The incidences of cognitive function decline and improve-
ment between groups at the 2 follow-up times are shown in </p>

<p>Table 2. Compared with the control group, the risk of a decline 
in visual matching was higher in the anesthesia group on Day 1 
(P ¼ 0.001; risk difference 10.3%, 95% CI: 3.2-17.3). In a post 
hoc analysis of visual matching data on Day 1, the crude and 
adjusted POCD/POCI-RRR was 10.50 (95% CI: 1.02-107.66, 
P ¼ 0.048) and 6.82 (95% CI: 0.76-60.82, P ¼ 0.09), respect-
ively. Using the combined Z-scores, the crude and adjusted 
POCD/POCI-RRR on Day 1 were 1.20 (95% CI: 0.12-11.92, 
P ¼ 0.88) and 0.85 (95% CI: 0.10-7.05, P ¼ 0.88), respectively. 
The corresponding estimates at 6 weeks were 0.53 (95% CI: 
0.06-4.93, P ¼ 0.58) and 0.45 (95% CI: 0.04-4.84, 
P ¼ 0.51), respectively. 
In children undergoing anesthesia, the mean BIS were 
similar between those who had POCD (53 AE 8, n ¼ 6) and those 
with no POCD (54 AE 7, n ¼ 103) on Day 1 (P ¼ 0.75). Similar 
mean BIS were found between those who had POCD (58 AE 10, 
n ¼ 3) and those with no POCD (54 AE 7, n ¼ 106) at 6 weeks 
(P ¼ 0.37). Of the 12 desaturations, 2 occurred in children with 
POCD on Day 1 and none at 6 weeks. Hypotension did not occur 
in children with POCD at both follow-up times. There was no 
difference in pain scores between children with no change in 
cognitive function, POCD or POCI on Day 1 (P ¼ 0.31) and at 6 
weeks (P ¼ 0.29). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This prospective cohort of Hong Kong children aged 5 to 
12 years undergoing GA showed the risk of POCD on Day 1 and 
at 6 weeks after surgery were 1 in 20 and 1 in 30, respectively. It 
should be noted that there were similar low incidences (&lt;10%) 
of cognitive impairment and improvement for all tests in both 
groups at each time point except visual matching in the 
anesthesia group on Day 1. When using the criterion of at least 
2 tests with 2 SD decline, there was no association between GA 
and POCD. However, the results were imprecise when the 
combined Z-score criterion was adopted, with the POCD </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Incidence (%, 95% CI) of Cognitive Decline and Improvement by Group Over Time </p>

<p>Day 1 
6 wk </p>

<p>Cognitive Function Tests 
Anesthesia (n ¼ 118) 
Control (n ¼ 126) 
Anesthesia (n ¼ 118) 
Control (n ¼ 126) </p>



<p>Aun et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 14, April 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>identified in the few children likely to be random variation than 
true deterioration. Measurement errors are unlikely to bias these 
results as our choice of cognitive function tests had an accep-
table to high level of test-retest reliabilities. Pain score, depth 
of anesthesia, desaturation, and hypotensive episodes were not 
associated with POCD. 
Our study provides weak evidence for the association 
between GA and visual matching, a measure of processing 
speed, on Day 1. For every 10 children undergoing GA, a 
decline in visual matching will occur in 1 in the early post-
operative period. This is likely related to general discomfort 
from surgery, postoperative analgesic effects and the residual 
effects of longer GA. A post hoc analysis showed that children 
with a decline in visual matching scores had longer GA (median 
159 min, IQR 130-288) than those with no decline (median 116 
min, IQR 71-187) (P ¼ 0.03). All children with visual match-
ing impairment recovered before the 6-week follow-up assess-
ment. In other studies, reaction time returned to baseline levels 
at 24 to 48 h after midazolam premedication, propofol, isoflur-
ane, or sevoflurane-nitrous oxide anesthesia for dental pro-
cedures. 
11,22,23 Compared with sevoflurane, propofol was 
associated with visual memory impairment at 1 week, but 
not at 3 months, after elective hernia surgery but the study 
did not control for a practice learning effect. 
12 Taking all these 
results together, it appears that GA is associated with transient 
subtle effects on cognitive function in school-age children. 
Our age appropriate panel of neuropsychological tests took 
15 to 20 min to complete. Although more tests, such as those 
measuring executive function, would cover other areas of 
cognitive functions, too large a test battery would increase 
the rate of patient withdrawal because of fatigue. Our noncom-
pliance rate of follow-up tests was acceptable and similar </p>

<p>between groups, suggesting that attrition bias was small and 
unlikely to affect the results. There is no consensus on the 
optimum size of a panel of neuropsychological tests. 
7 Our focus 
on basic processes of memory, speed of processing, and com-
prehension covered several major areas of particular concern 
among parents of children undergoing GA. 
Compared with previous studies in school-age children 
with a control group, 
13,22,24 our study is the largest with the 
longest duration of anesthesia and follow-up data. While the use 
of a control group helped adjust for improved performance from 
learning and extraneous variables, 
7 we found significant base-
line differences between groups in half the panel of neuropsy-
chological tests undertaken. This suggests that some selection 
bias was present despite comparable baseline characteristics 
described in Table 1. As children undergoing surgery were more 
likely to be anxious in an unfamiliar hospital environment than 
at school, this may have affected their baseline tests perform-
ance. Nevertheless, our results are generally consistent with a 
previous study showing no effect of halothane-nitrous oxide 
GA on reasoning, motor or memory functions at 24 h after 
myringotomy in children aged between 5 and 8 years old. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>There are several limitations in this study. Our study 
included children with relatively high IQs; the mean IQ in 
another Hong Kong study of similar age children was estimated 
to be 115. 
17 The results have some generalizability to current 
pediatric anesthesia practice even if our data are old and the type 
of GA was not always standardized between anesthesiologists. 
Apart from intravenous thiopentone induction, our GA used 
current anesthetic agents namely midazolam premedication, 
propofol or sevoflurane induction, maintenance with nitrous 
oxide, oxygen, sevoflurane or isoflurane, neuromuscular block-
ade, and mechanical ventilation. Nevertheless, we believe that </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Adjusted serial changes in mean scores (95% confidence interval) of the 4 cognitive function tests: Hong Kong List Learning 
(HKLL), Visual Matching, Visual Memory, and General Comprehension (GC). The control group is represented by blue circle with solid 
lines and the anesthesia group is represented by magenta triangle with long dash lines. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 95, Number 14, April 2016 
Cognitive Effects After General Anesthesia in Children </p>

<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>

<p>the publication of this data may give further assurance to parents 
on the safety of GA in this patient age group. 
In conclusion, this prospective cohort study with an age-
matched control group of school children found weak evidence 
to support an association between GA and visual matching 
impairment on the first day of surgery. The incidences of POCD 
on Day 1 and at 6 weeks after surgery were low. We found no 
anesthesia-related POCD per se when using the widely accepted 
Z-score definition and relative risk ratio methodology. Any 
POCD found on Day 1 was likely to be a random event that 
resolved before the follow-up assessment at 6 weeks. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
We thank the children and parents for their participation, 
and the Chi Hong School in Shatin for their support and 
assistance in the study. </p>



<p>Aun et al 
Medicine Volume 95, Number 14, April 2016 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

</text></tei>