<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4675898" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Phosphorylation and dephosphorylation events play an 
important role in the transmission of the ABA signal. 
Although SnRK2 
[sucrose non-fermenting1-related 
kinase2] protein kinases and group A protein phosphatase 
type 2C (PP2C)-type phosphatases constitute the core ABA 
pathway, mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) path-
ways are also involved in plant response to ABA. However, 
little is known about the interplay between MAPKs and 
PP2Cs or SnRK2 in the regulation of ABA pathways. In this 
study, an effort was made to elucidate the role of MAP 
kinase kinase kinase18 (MKKK18) in relation to ABA signal-
ing and response. The MKKK18 knockout lines showed more 
vigorous root growth, decreased abaxial stomatal index and 
increased stomatal aperture under normal growth condi-
tions, compared with the control wild-type Columbia line. 
In addition to transcriptional regulation of the MKKK18 
promoter by ABA, we demonstrated using in vitro and 
in vivo kinase assays that the kinase activity of MKKK18 was 
regulated by ABA. Analysis of the cellular localization of 
MKKK18 showed that the active kinase was targeted specific-
ally to the nucleus. Notably, we identified abscisic acid insensi-
tive 1 (ABI1) PP2C as a MKKK18-interacting protein, and 
demonstrated that ABI1 inhibited its activity. Using a cell-
free degradation assay, we also established that MKKK18 was 
unstable and was degraded by the proteasome pathway. The 
rate of MKKK18 degradation was delayed in the ABI1 knockout 
line. Overall, we provide evidence that ABI1 regulates the ac-
tivity and promotes proteasomal degradation of MKKK18. </p>

<p>The phytohormone ABA recruits many diverse elements for the 
generation and transmission of endogenous signals (Xiong et al. 
2002, Mane et al. 2007, Fujita et al. 2009, Geiger et al. 2009, 
Ludwików et al. 2009, Nishimura et al. 2009, Santiago et al. 2009, 
Yoshida et al. 2010). Protein kinases and protein phosphatases 
are proteins that lead to rearrangements in the network of ABA 
signal transduction (Ohta et al. 2003, Zhu et al. 2007, Ma et al. 
2009, Nakashima et al. 2009, Park et al. 2009, Santiago et al. 
2009, Umezawa et al. 2009, Nishimura et al. 2010, Szostkiewicz 
et al. 2010, Dupeux et al. 2011a, Dupeux et al. 2011b). Both 
protein kinases and protein phosphatases are obligatory for 
ABA signal transduction. Sucrose non-fermenting 1 (SNF1)-
related protein kinases 2 (SnRK2s), Ca 
2+ -dependent protein 
kinases (CDPKs) and calcineurin B-like calcium sensor (CBL)-
interacting protein kinases (CIPKs) are all known for their 
involvement in ABA signaling and stress tolerance, and are 
identified as interacting partners with particular protein phos-
phatases type 2C (PP2Cs) (Ohta et al. 2003, Zhu et al. 2007, 
Umezawa et al. 2009). Key players of ABA signaling such as 
abscisic acid insensitive 1 (ABI1), abscisic acid insensitive 2 </p>

<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146, Advance Access publication on 6 October 2015, 
available online at www.pcp.oxfordjournals.org 
! The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Japanese Society of Plant Physiologists. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For 
commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Regular Paper </p>

<p>(ABI2) and Hypersensitive to Abscisic acid 1 (HAB1) have been 
shown to interact with RCAR/PYR/PYL (RCAR, 
Regulatory Component of ABA Receptor/PYR1, Pyrabactin 
Resistance 1/PYL, PYR1-like), putative ABA receptors that regu-
late SnRK kinases (Umezawa et al. 2009). ABI1 and ABI2, along 
with CIPK20, CIPK8, CIPK14 and CIPK15, manage protein-
protein interactions and regulate ABA signaling, gene expres-
sion and stress response (Guo et al. 2002, Ohta et al. 2003, 
Ludwików et al. 2013, Babula-Skowrońska et al. 2015). Other 
PP2C-interacting partners include transcription factors 
(Himmelbach et al. 2002), antioxidant enzymes (Miao et. al., 
2006), constituents of the chromatin remodeling complex (Saez 
et al. 2008) and components of the ethylene biosynthetic path-
way (Ludwików et al. 2014), which have likewise been identified 
as important to the ABA signaling network. 
Despite studies indicating that mitogen-activated protein 
kinase (MAPK) cascades are important for ABA signaling, 
little is known about the interplay between MAPKs and 
PP2Cs in this pathway. A MAPK cascade is a conserved 
module comprised of at least three elements: MKKKs, MKKs 
and MAPKs. A group of MKKKKs have also been identified 
(Jonak et al. 2002, Yoon et al. 2010). MKKKs link upstream 
receptors with downstream MKKs. MKKKs (as dual specificity 
kinases) phosphorylate MKKs on Ser/Thr residues in conserved 
S/T-X3-5-S/T motifs localized in an activation loop (T-loop). 
Once activated, the MKKs phosphorylate MAPKs at the TxY 
motif located in their T-loop. Upon activation, the MAPKs 
phosphorylate downstream substrates, thereby initiating vari-
ous cellular responses. Among the MAPKs, MPK6 is known to 
interact with ABI1 PP2C. Both ABI1 and MPK6 are involved in 
the regulation of biotic and abiotic stress responses (Leung et al. 
2006). In addition, MPK3, MPK6, MPK9 and MPK12 have been 
identified as regulators of ABA signaling in guard cells (Lampard 
et al. 2009, Brock et al. 2010, Jammes et al. 2011, Salam et al. 
2013). MKK1-MPK6 were found to be transiently activated by 
ABA treatment, to affect downstream generation of H 2 O 2 and 
to regulate guard cell aperture (Xing et al. 2008). Other kinases, 
such as MPK9 and MPK12, act upstream of anion channels in 
guard cell ABA signaling (Jammes et al. 2009). In addition, 
MKK7 and MKK9 are known to act as regulators during sto-
matal development (Lampard et al. 2009). 
Because MKKKs constitute the largest and most complex 
group of MAP cascade kinases, only a few MPK modules have 
been recognized and documented. Reaactive oxygen species 
(ROS) signaling in plants involves the MEKK1-MKK2-MPK4 
phosphorylation pathway (Colcombet and Hirt 2008, Pitzschke 
et al. 2009). In apple, the cascade MdMKK1-MdMPK1 is acti-
vated by ABA (Wang et al. 2010). In Arabidopsis, an unknown 
MKKK-MKK4/5-MPK3/6 module, and MEKK1-MKK1/2-
MPK4, are two MAPK cascades that govern flg22-dependent 
gene expression (Suarez-Rodriguez et al. 2007, Qiu et al. 2008, 
Nicaise et al. 2009, Boudsocq et al. 2010, Kong et al. 2012). 
Another MAPK cascade consists of YODA activating MKK4/ 
5-MKK7/MKK9 and MPK3/6: the YODA module is an import-
ant protein complex that regulates stomatal development 
and affects inflorescence architecture by promoting cell 
proliferation (Wang et al. 2007, Lampard et al. 2009, </p>

<p>Meng et al. 2012). Very recently, a MAPK cascade, MAP3K17/ 
18-MKK3-MPK1/2/7/14, was found to play a role in ABA stress 
signaling (Danquah et al. 2015) and senescence (Matsuoka et al. 
2015). 
In this study, we investigated the role of MKKK18 in ABA 
signaling and response. We find that MKKK18 is regulated by 
both ABI1 PP2C and the proteasome pathway. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>MKKK18 expression is induced by ABA </p>

<p>Previous studies have shown that MKKK18 expression is 
increased in response to wounding (Taki et al. 2005), pathogen 
attack (de Torres-Zabala et al. 2007), ozone, mannitol, NaCl and 
ABA treatment (Hoth et al. 2002, Leonhardt et al. 2004, 
Ludwików et al. 2009, Danquah et al. 2015). The responsiveness 
of the MKKK18 promoter to ABA, quinabactin (a sulfonamide 
ABA agonist) and ASn compounds (ABA analogs) was also 
demonstrated (Okamoto et al. 2013, Takeuchi et al. 2014). In 
addition, MKKK18 expression was found to be deregulated in 
abi1-1 and abi1td mutants (Hoth et al. 2002, Ludwików et al. 
2009). The expression of MKKK18 was diminished in abi1td 
(Ludwików et al. 2009), and abolished in ABA-insensitive 
abi1-1 (Hoth et al. 2002), quadruple pyr1pyl1pyl2pyr4 and 
the hab1 
G246D mutants (Danquah et al. 2015), suggesting that 
the proper transcription of MKKK18 requires regular ABA 
signaling. 
To gain a more detailed insight into the MKKK18 gene 
expression profile, we analyzed public transcriptome data 
compiled by Genevestigator and eFP Browser. The results 
indicated that MKKK18 exhibits low level expression in a 
range of plant tissues, with the exception of anthers. A rela-
tively high level of expression was observed in root cells, 
including the epidermis, endodermis, stele, cortex and lateral 
root cap. A significant increase in MKKK18 gene expression 
was observed in guard cells and mesophyll cells in response to 
ABA treatment. 
To verify the ABA responsiveness of MKKK18, we studied 
promoter activity in the 1,622 bp upstream region of the 
MKKK18 gene in transgenic plants carrying promoters fused 
to the b-glucuronidase (GUS) reporter genes. A de novo 
search for cis-acting elements using the PLACE program re-
vealed that the MKKK18 promoter contained a number of 
cis-regulatory elements. These elements included ABRE (PyAC 
GTGGC) and DRE elements (TACCGACAT) (Yamaguchi-
Shinozaki et al. 2005), an ASF1 regulatory sequence 
(Krawczyk et al. 2002), POLLENLELAT52 (Bate and Twell, 
1998), a W-box (Yamasaki et al. 2012) and a TAAAG element 
required for guard cell-specific gene expression (Plesch et al, 
2001). At 24 h after the ABA treatment, a full-length 
ProMKKK18:GUS construct delivered strong GUS expression 
in the flowers, leaves and root tissues (Fig. 1). In developing 
flowers, MKKK18 promoter activity was observed in sepals, 
anther filaments, ovaries and meristem tissues (Fig. 1C-F). 
GUS staining was visible in root meristem tissues and in areas 
of lateral root formation (Fig. 1G). ProMKKK18:GUS staining </p>



<p>F. Mitula et al. | MKKK18 is regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome pathway </p>

<p>was observed in guard cells and trichomes (Fig. 1H, I). 
Our results demonstrate that a 1.6 kb upstream sequence was 
sufficient for MKKK18 regulation by ABA. </p>

<p>Active MKKK18 is localized in the nucleus </p>

<p>To determine MKKK18 protein localization in vivo, C-terminal 
green fluorescent protein (GFP) fusions were generated and 
transiently expressed under the control of the 35S promoter 
in Arabidopsis thaliana protoplasts. MKKK18-GFP was pre-
dominantly localized in the nucleus, whereas, as expected, an 
empty vector control did not show background fluorescence in 
any cellular compartment (Fig. 2A). Next, we addressed 
whether kinase activity affected MKKK18 localization. By multi-
sequence alignment of Arabidopsis MAPKKK, we identified </p>

<p>conserved residues important for the activity of MKKK18. 
Based on this analysis, a kinase-inactive allele (K32M) and a 
permanently active form of MKKK18 (T161E) were generated. 
The K32M version of the protein is modified in its ATP-binding 
loop, while the permanently active, T161E form of MKKK18 is 
modified in the kinase domain. All versions of MKKK18 were 
fused to GFP and were again expressed in Arabidopsis 
protoplasts. Interestingly, the K32M version retained barely 
detectable kinase activity and was localized outside the 
nucleus. However, the fluorescent signal of the permanently 
active T161E version of MKKK18-GFP clearly accumulated 
in the nucleus of Arabidopsis protoplasts, suggesting a role in 
mediating the signaling function of MKKK18 in this 
compartment (Fig. 2A). Immunoblot analysis confirmed </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Analysis of the activity of the MKKK18 promoter in transgenic plants expressing the ProMKKK18:GUS construct. (A) Schematic map of the 
MKKK18 promoter used for transformation and tissue-specific expression of MKKK18. (B) The ProMKKK18:GUS seedlings were germinated and 
grown on half-strength MS medium. Five-week-old plants were treated with either 0.1% methanol (mock) or 100 mM ABA. One representative of 
five independent lines is shown. (A) No changes in GUS activity after mock treatment. The scale bar represents 2,000 mm. (B-J) Plant samples 
24 h after ABA treatment. GUS activity is visible in rosette leaves (B), flower buds and sepals (C), meristem tissues (D), pistils (E), anther filaments 
(F), lateral roots (G), trichomes (H), leaf guard cells (I) and hydathodes (J). </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146 </p>

<p>the presence of full-length fusion proteins in protoplasts 
(Fig. 2B). </p>

<p>MKKK18-overexpressing lines show ABA-related 
phenotypes at the level of germination and root 
growth </p>

<p>To investigate the functions of MKKK18, six independent 
MKKK18-overexpressor 
lines 
(Col-0/35S:MKKK18-GFP; </p>

<p>MKKK18oe1-MKKK18oe6) were generated and two T-DNA in-
sertion lines of MKKK18 in the Columbia (Col-0) background 
were selected from the SALK and GABI-Kat collections. These 
knockout lines were designated mkkk18-1 (SALK_087047) and 
mkkk18-2 (GK-244G02). Homozygous mkkk18-1 and mkkk18-2 
plants were identified by PCR-based genotyping, and the inser-
tion site was confirmed by PCR using T-DNA-specific and gene-
specific primers (Fig. 3A, B). A quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Subcellular localization of the MKKK18 protein in Arabidopsis protoplasts. Active MKKK18 is localized in the nucleus. (A) Microscopy 
images show nuclear localization of the MKKK18-GFP fusions in Arabidopsis protoplasts. Hoechst H33342 was used as nuclear localization 
marker. Scale bars are calibrated to 20 mm. (B) MKKK18 protein expression and activity were analyzed by immunoprecipitation using protein-
specific anti-MKKK18 antibodies and immunocomplex kinase assay with MBP as a substrate. The immunocomplex assay confirmed residual 
kinase activity of the MKKK18K32M-GFP allele. Western blot detection using anti-GFP antibodies corroborates the presence of MKKK18-GFP 
fusion proteins. Coomassie Brilliant Blue (CBB) staining confirmed equal loading. </p>



<p>F. Mitula et al. | MKKK18 is regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome pathway </p>

<p>(qPCR) analysis confirmed that expression of MKKK18 was 
abolished in both mkkk18-1 and mkkk18-2 (Fig. 3C). 
Previous reports showed that MKKK18 is an ABA-activated 
kinase (Danquah et al. 2015, Matsuoka et al. 2015). To monitor 
the activation of ABA signaling in the leaves of the knockouts 
and MKKK18-oe lines at the molecular level, the expression of </p>

<p>the ABA-induced genes RD29B and RAB18 was examined by 
qPCR (Fig. 3D). In response to treatment with ABA, RD29B and 
RAB18 expression was significantly down-regulated in both 
MKKK18 knockout lines compared with MKKK18oe and wild-
type (WT) plants (P &lt; 0.001), suggesting that ABA-mediated 
induction of these genes is regulated by MKKK18. </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Germination and root growth assays. (A and B) T-DNA insertion sites derived from the sequencing of genomic DNA isolated from 
mkkk18-1 and mkkk18-2 mutant lines. Black boxes represent an open reading frame. Homozygous knockout mutants were verified by PCR-based 
genotyping using the following primers: MKKK18LP plus MKKK18RP plus LBb1 for mkkk18-1 analysis (product size for the WT, 960 bp; product 
for homozygous lines, 750 bp); MEK18F plus GKatTDNA (product for homozygous lines, 850 bp) and GwMK18F plus GwMK18R (product for the 
WT, 1,001 bp) for mkkk18-2 genotyping. Primer sequences are indicated in Supplementary Table S1. (C) qPCR analysis confirmed a lack of 
MKKK18 expression in homozygous lines. Each quantification was repeated twice with similar results. The results are given as log 2 of the relative 
MKKK18/18S rDNA expression ratio ± SE (n = 6). (D) RD29B and RAB18 transcript levels in MKKK18 mutants. RD29B and RAB18 expression levels 
were determined using three biological replicates and were normalized against 18S rDNA. Each quantification was repeated twice on separate 
plates. The results are displayed as mean log 2 fold change ± SE (n = 9) of three independent experiments with consistent results. (E and F) 
Germination and root growth assays. ABA-mediated inhibition of germination (E) and primary root growth (F) in WT Col-0, MKKK18oe and 
MKKK18 knockout lines. Both MKKK18oe #1 and #2 lines showed similar results. Values are mean ± SE for three independent experiments 
(n = 30). *P &lt; 0.01; **P &lt; 0.001; ***P &lt; 0.0001 with respect to the control WT Col-0 line. </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146 </p>

<p>In the search for ABA-related phenotypes in the MKKK18 
mutants, we first analyzed whether seed germination and root 
growth were affected by ABA. Seeds of MKKK18oe lines and 
mkkk18 knockouts were sown on Murashige and Skoog (MS) 
medium supplemented with ABA, and the germination rate was 
analyzed and compared with that of WT seeds. As indicated in 
Fig. 3E, both knockout lines showed similar growth rates to WT 
Col-0 in the presence of low concentrations of ABA. In contrast, 
Col-0/35S:MKKK18-GFP germinated better than the WT Col-0 
control, which was supported by the t-test results (P &lt; 0.001) 
between the WT and independent MKKK18oe lines. This obser-
vation indicated that the 35S:MKKK18-GFP-overexpressing line dis-
played insensitivity towards ABA at the level of germination, 
suggesting that MKKK18 was required for germination. Next, in 
the search for ABA-related phenotypes, we analyzed ABA-
mediated inhibition of root expansion. In the presence of 2 mM 
ABA, root elongation in seedlings expressing 35S:MKKK18-GFP was 
reduced by 15% compared with the WT Col-0 control seedlings 
(n = 46; P &lt; 0.0001). At the same ABA level, the mkkk18-1 and 
mkkk18-2 knockout lines showed improved root growth (40% and 
20%, respectively) compared with the WT Col-0 line (Fig. 3F). </p>

<p>MKKK18 affects stomatal development and 
function </p>

<p>MAPKs are important elements of signaling cascades that affect 
stomatal development (Wang et al. 2007, Lampard et al. 2009, 
Tanaka et al. 2013). Therefore, we compared the number and 
density of stomata in 6-and 10-day-old seedlings of both 
MKKK18-oe lines and MKKK18 knockout lines (Fig. 4A). In 
the cotyledons, the stomatal index (SI) was significantly 
reduced, by 19% and 26%, in mkkk18-1 (P &lt; 0.001) and 
mkkk18-2 (P &lt; 0.0001), respectively. Consistent with this 
trend in SI, the abaxial SI for MKKK18oe lines was 7% higher 
than that for WT lines. Because GUS expression driven by the 
MKKK18 promoter was detected in guard cells, we analyzed 
whether MKKK18 was involved in the regulation of stomatal 
aperture. Compared with leaves from the WT, leaves from both 
knockout lines showed increased stomatal aperture under 
normal growth conditions. However, this effect was more pro-
nounced in the mkkk18-2 mutant (Fig. 4B). Measurements of 
stomatal aperture in response to ABA revealed that stomata 
from the knockout lines were again significantly more open 
than in the WT. Accordingly, MKKK18oe lines were hypersen-
sitive to ABA-induced stomatal closure (Fig. 4C). Next, we 
analyzed whether MKKK18 acted downstream of responses 
to CaCl 2 or H 2 O 2 in guard cell ABA signaling. Compared with 
WT Col-0, the knockout lines were significantly, if only slightly, 
impaired in H 2 O 2 -induced stomatal closure but not in response 
to CaCl 2 (Fig. 4C) . </p>

<p>MKKK18 is activated by ABA in tobacco </p>

<p>To test the mechanism of MKKK18 activation in response to 
ABA, we generated a peptide-specific antibody against 
MKKK18. Using alignment tools, we found a unique N-terminal 
sequence of MKKK18 with no obvious similarity to any other 
Arabidopsis protein, including MAPKs of any type. To test the </p>

<p>specificity of the generated antibodies, we performed immuno-
precipitation of recombinant MKKK18-glutathione S-
transferase (GST) with and without an epitope-mimicking pep-
tide. We found that the generated antibody recognized recom-
binant MKKK18-GST (Fig. 5A, B), while pre-incubation of anti-
MKKK18-coupled beads with the peptide blocked immunopre-
cipitation of MKKK18 (Fig. 5A). We then tested the antibody in 
Arabidopsis extracts, but were unable to detect the MKKK18 
protein directly, either by immunoblot analysis of the total 
protein extract or in the immunoprecipitates from WT Col-0 
and knockout lines. Nevertheless, MKKK18 immunocomplex 
activity was detectable in ABA-treated WT Col-0, although 
not in ABA-treated knockout lines (Fig. 5C), demonstrating 
that both knockout lines are deficient in MKKK18 activity. 
Overall, these results clearly demonstrate the specificity of 
the antibody for MKKK18. 
To analyze the time course of MKKK18 activation in re-
sponse to ABA, we again performed the kinase immunocom-
plex assay using myelin basic protein (MBP) as a substrate. 
Nicotiana benthamiana plants were generated that transiently 
expressed the 35S:MKKK18-GFP construct, and the MKKK18-
GFP protein was immunoprecipitated using the MKKK18-
specific antibody (Fig. 5D). As expected, treatment with 
1 mM ABA caused an increase in the activity of MKKK18, 
which was observed within 60 min of treatment. Importantly, 
before ABA treatment we did not observe MKKK18-GFP kinase 
activity on MBP. Overall, our results demonstrate that MKKK18 
activity is indeed regulated by ABA. </p>

<p>ABI1 PP2C interacts with MKKK18 and affects its 
activation by ABA </p>

<p>Our previous results showed that MKKK18 expression was sig-
nificantly affected in the abi1td mutant (Ludwików et al. 2009). 
Because MKKK18 is also ABA responsive, and ABI1 is known to 
be a negative regulator of ABA signaling, we then asked whether 
ABI1 would affect MKKK18 function. We transformed abi1td 
protoplasts with WT and mutated forms of MKKK18 fused to 
GFP, and examined their subcellular localization. We observed 
that the distribution of the various forms of MKKK18-GFP in 
abi1td mesophyll protoplasts was similar to that in WT proto-
plasts, suggesting that ABI1 did not affect MKKK18 localization 
(Supplementary Fig. S1). 
We next tested whether ABI1 would interact with MKKK18 
using yeast two-hybrid, GST pull-down and bimolecular fluores-
cence complementation (BiFC) assays. Full-length ABI1 (and 
homologous ABI2 PP2C as a control) and MKKK18 cDNA were 
fused to either the binding domain (BD) or the activation 
domain (AD) for yeast two-hybrid analysis and double-
transformed yeast lines were generated. Positive results, indicat-
ing interaction, were seen only for the ABI1-MKKK18 pair (Fig. 
6A, B; Supplementary Fig. S2). The binding of ABI1 to MKKK18 
was then analyzed using pull-down assays. Streptag-ABI1, and 
Streptag-ABI2 as a control, were purified from plant extracts 
and incubated with recombinant MKKK18-GST and His-
MKKK18, respectively. Again, only ABI1 was capable of binding 
MKKK18, indicating substrate specificity of ABI1 PP2Cs for </p>



<p>F. Mitula et al. | MKKK18 is regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome pathway </p>

<p>interaction with MKKK18 (Fig. 6C, D). This result was further 
confirmed by BiFC experiments using ABI1 (or ABI2 as a control) 
with MKKK18, which also revealed that ABI1 and MKKK18 were 
capable of interacting (Fig. 6E, F; Supplementary Fig. S3). 
Consequently, we analyzed the effect of ABI1 PP2C activity 
on MKKK18 activation. Arabidopsis mesophyll protoplasts 
were transfected with 35S:MKKK18-GFP constructs, and immu-
nocomplex MKKK18 activity was determined by in vitro kinase 
assays in the presence of recombinant ABI1 or ABI2 proteins 
(Fig. 7A, B). ABI1 but not ABI2 inhibited MKKK18 kinase ac-
tivity. As a control treatment, the activities of both PP2Cs were </p>

<p>assessed using a non-radioactive phosphatase assay (Fig. 7A). 
Previous studies revealed that ABI1 can inhibit the autoactivation 
of SnRK2 kinases (Ng et al. 2011). To test the mechanism of 
MKKK18 activation and the role of ABI1 in this process, we 
purified recombinant GST-MKKK18 and analyzed the kinase 
activity in vitro in the presence of the downstream in vivo sub-
strate, MKK3 (Danquah et al. 2015, Matsuoka et al. 2015), and an 
artificial substrate, MBP. As a positive control for the kinase ac-
tivity assay, SnRK2.6 was used (Fig. 7C). Interestingly, we 
observed no autophosphorylation activity of MKKK18 and as a 
consequence no phosphorylation of the substrates. These results </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Stomatal development and movement in MKKK18 knockouts and the MKKK18-overexpressing line. (A) Stomatal development is 
enhanced in the MKKK18-overexpressing lines. Representative line drawings show the abaxial surface of cotyledons at day 10. Change in 
stomatal index and the number of guard cells (GCs) and pavement cells (PCs) per cotyledon in WT Col-0, MKKK18oe and MKKK18 knockouts. 
Data represent the mean ± SD (n = 300) of three independent experiments. Scale bar = 50 mm. (B) Increased stomatal aperture of mkkk18-1 and 
mkkk18-2 knockouts compared with the WT in standard conditions (three independent experiments, 60-80 stomatal apertures at each data 
point). (C) The mkkk18-1 and mkkk18-2 knockouts are insensitive to ABA-and H 2 O 2 -induced stomatal closure (two independent experiments, 
80 stomatal apertures at each data point). MKKK18oe lines were hypersensitive to ABA-, CaCl 2 -and H 2 O 2 -induced stomatal closure (two 
independent experiments, 100 stomatal apertures at each data point). </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146 </p>

<p>indicate that MKKK18 activity is precisely controlled and that 
ABI1 does not regulate autoactivation of MKKK18. 
Finally, to confirm the role of ABI1 in the regulation of 
MKKK18 activity, we examined MKKK18 activation in WT 
Col-0 and abi1td after ABA treatment. Previously, it was re-
ported that MKKK18 expression is absent in the ABA receptor 
quadruple pyr1pyl1pyl2pyl4 mutant (Danquah et al. 2015). 
Therefore, SnRK2.6 kinase, another crucial element of the 
ABA pathway, was also included in this analysis. Under the 
conditions indicated, we observed a stronger induction of 
MKKK18 activity in the abi1td mutant than in the WT Col-0 </p>

<p>plants after 90 min of ABA treatment (Fig. 8A, B). Under the 
same conditions, ABA-induced MKKK18 activation was abol-
ished in the snrk2.6 mutant. These experiments demonstrated 
that both ABI1 PP2C and SnRK2.6 affect functional activation of 
MKKK18 in response to ABA treatment. </p>

<p>MKKK18 accumulation is regulated by ABI1 and 
the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway </p>

<p>The MKKK18 protein was found to be in low abundance and, 
indeed, undetectable in total protein extracts from WT Col-0 
plants. This feature of MKKK18 resembles other short-lived </p>

<p>Fig. 5 ABA induces rapid MKKK18 activation in tobacco. (A-C) Generation of MKKK18-specific antibodies. (A) MKKK18 peptide competition assay. 
Recombinant GST-MKKK18 protein was incubated with anti-MKKK18 with and without 45 mg of blocking peptide. A single band of approximatley 
65 kDa specific to GST-MKKK18 is absent in the immunoprecipitates containing the blocking peptide. Immunodetection was performed using anti-
MKKK18 antibody. (B) MKKK18-GFP protein immunoprecipitated from tobacco total protein extracts using increasing amounts of anti-MKKK18 and 
anti-GFP antibodies. The MKKK18-GFP protein was precipitated by 3 ml (lane 1) or 10 ml (lane 2) of MKKK18 antiserum and 0.6 mg (lane 3) or 1.2 mg 
(lane 4) of anti-GFP antibody, respectively. Immunoblotting with anti-MKKK18 antibodies confirmed the presence of MKKK18-GFP fusion protein. 
Arrows/Ab indicate anti-MKKK18 antibodies (visible as a band in lane 2) where excess anti-MKKK18 antibody was used in the immunoprecipitation 
reaction. The 65 kDa band represents MKKK18-GFP protein. (C) Analysis of MKKK18 activity in the mkkk18 knockout lines. MKKK18 protein was 
immunoprecipitated from 600 mg of total protein extract isolated from ABA-treated WT Col-0, mkkk18-1, mkkk18-2 and MKKK18oe using specific anti-
MKKK18 antibodies. Immunocomplex activity was determined using MBP (2 mg) as a substrate. Coomassie Brilliant Blue (CBB) staining of MBP 
confirmed equal loading. (D) Tobacco plants infiltrated with Agrobacterium strain C58C1 harboring 35S:MKKK18-GFP and 35S:p19 constructs for 
transient expression. Four to five days after infiltration, the tobacco plants were treated with ABA and tissue samples were collected at the indicated 
time points. MKKK18 activity was assessed by the immunocomplex assay using anti-MKKK18 antibody and MBP as a substrate. MKKK18-GFP was 
detected with anti-GFP antibody. CBB staining of MBP confirmed equal loading. The above experiments were repeated several times with similar results. </p>



<p>F. Mitula et al. | MKKK18 is regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome pathway </p>

<p>proteins, such as aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid syn-
thases (ACC synthases) 2 and 6, whose degradation is mediated 
by the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway (Liu and Zhang 2004, 
Joo et al. 2008). Recently, we demonstrated that ABI1 controls 
turnover of ACC synthase 6 (Ludwików et al. 2014, Ludwików, 
2015); therefore, we hypothesize that ABI1 might also be </p>

<p>involved in the regulation of MKKK18 stability. To test this 
hypothesis, we first examined MKKK18 transcript levels in 
WT plants and two independent ABI1 knockout lines, abi1td 
(Ludwikow et al. 2009) and abi1-2 (Saez et al. 2006). 
Importantly, in response to 90 min of 50 mM ABA treatment, 
MKKK18 expression was significantly lower in both ABI1 </p>

<p>Fig. 6 MKKK18 interacts with the ABI1 protein phosphatase. (A) Yeast two-hybrid analysis of the interaction between MKKK18 and ABI1/2 
PP2Cs. Diploid yeast colonies were grown on double (DDO-SD medium without Leu and Trp) or quadruple selective medium (QDO-SD medium 
without Leu, Trp, His or Ade) with or without supplemented X-a-Gal and aureobasidin. The bait (MKKK18) did not autoactivate the reporter 
genes in yeast. (B) Detection of ABI1/2 and MKKK18 expression in diploid yeast strains. Expression of BD and AD fusion proteins in yeast was 
determined by immunoblotting using specific anti-ABI1, anti-ABI2 and anti-MKKK18 antibodies. (C and D) Pull-down assays to verify the 
interaction of ABI1/2 with MKKK18. Input lines represent 100% of the ABI1/2. Recombinant GST-MKKK18 or His-MKKK18 was pre-coupled to 
glutathione-Sepharose, and incubated with StrepTag-ABI1 or StrepTag-ABI2, respectively. Pulled-down StrepTagged ABI1 protein was detected 
(IB) with the epitope tag antibody. The presence of recombinant protein was confirmed using anti-MKKK18 antibody. (E and F) ABI1-MKKK18 
interaction occurs within the nucleus. BiFC analysis in Arabidopsis protoplasts expressing full-length ABI1/2 and MKKK18 fused to cECFP or 
nVenus, respectively. RFP (E) was used as a transformation control. CFP-CBP20 (cyan fluorescent protein-Cap Binding Protein 20) (F) was used 
as a marker of nuclear localization. </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146 </p>

<p>knockout lines compared with WT plants (P &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. 
9A). Because the decrease in MKKK18 transcript accumulation 
does not explain the increased MKKK18 kinase activity in the 
ABI1 knockout, we examined the turnover of MKKK18. Cell-
free degradation assays showed that recombinant GST-
MKKK18 was degraded more slowly in abi1td than in WT cell 
extracts (Fig. 9B). The degradation was blocked by MG132 (a 
proteasome inhibitor) in both abi1td and WT plant extracts. 
The half-life of GST-MKKK18 in the assay was substantially 
longer in abi1td protein extracts compared with WT protein 
extracts (Fig. 9C, D). Overall, these results demonstrate that 
ABI1 PP2C regulates MKKK18 turnover. 
Next, we investigated MKKK18-GFP abundance in 
Arabidopsis protoplasts transiently expressing 35S:MKKK18-
GFP. Under such conditions, the degradation rate of MKKK18 
could be affected by its increased synthesis; therefore, to distin-
guish between translational or post-translational effects, we </p>

<p>used a protein synthesis inhibitor, cycloheximide (CHX) (Fig. 
9E). As expected, CHX treatment significantly reduced the ac-
cumulation of MKKK18 protein. Notably, simultaneous CHX 
and MG132 treatment prevents a reduction in MKKK18 pro-
tein levels, demonstrating that MKKK18 is degraded by the 
proteasome pathway. 
Because both MKKK18 transcript level and kinase activity 
are regulated by ABA, we asked whether ABA affects the 
MKKK18 protein level. Again, the cell-free degradation 
assay was performed to test whether MKKK18 stability is 
affected by ABA. GST-MKKK18 recombinant protein was 
incubated with protein extracts prepared from WT proto-
plasts treated with 50 mM ABA or mock treated. GST-
MKKK18 was rapidly degraded when incubated with WT 
protein extracts and this degradation was blocked by ABA 
(Fig. 9F). These results indicate that ABA regulates MKKK18 
protein stability. </p>

<p>Fig. 7 ABI1 inhibits MKKK18 activity. (A) Phosphatase activity of recombinant ABI1 and ABI2 proteins. The enzyme reactions were performed in 
a 50 ml final volume containing 3-5 mg pf GST-ABI1 or GST-ABI2. The results presented are the means from three independent biological 
replicates. (B) ABI1 inactivates MKKK18. The MKKK18-GFP immunocomplex was incubated with 3 mg of GST-ABI1 and GST-ABI2 (as a 
negative control), after which the kinase activity was determined with MBP as a substrate. Equal loading was confirmed by Coomassie Brilliant 
Blue (CBB) staining of MBP. The 
32 P-labeled MBP bands were quantified and then normalized against the intensity of the corresponding control 
band using ImageJ software. Data are means ± SD of the relative band intensities from three independent experiments. An asterisk (*) indicates 
statistically significant changes determined using Student's t-test. (C) Recombinant MKKK18 has no autophosphorylation activity in vitro. GST-
MKKK18 was incubated with MBP or/and MKK3, without or in the presence of [ </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P]ATP. Bands of GST-MKKK18, MKK3-GST and GST-
SnRK2.6 are indicated by a filled circle, a triangle and an arrow, respectively. Protein loading was confirmed by CBB staining. The blots shown are 
representative of three independent trials. </p>



<p>F. Mitula et al. | MKKK18 is regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome pathway </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Previously it was shown that ABA activates several MAPKs to 
perform various functions in the cell (Danquah et al. 2014, 
Danquah et al. 2015). In this study, we demonstrate that 
MKKK18 is also an element of the ABA response pathway 
and that it is specifically expressed in guard cells (Fig. 1I) and 
root meristem tissues (Fig. 1G). Interestingly, active MKKK18 is 
targeted specifically to the nucleus. We also show that MKKK18 
kinase activity is increased by ABA treatment. Consistent with 
this, we show that MKKK18 is involved in ABA-related re-
sponses including stomatal development (Fig. 4), stomatal 
movement (Fig. 4), ABA inhibition of germination and root 
growth (Fig. 3). Notably, we identify ABI1 PP2C as an 
MKKK18-interacting protein (Fig. 6) and we demonstrate 
that ABI1 inhibits MKKK18 activity (Fig. 7B). We also establish 
that MKKK18 is unstable and is degraded by the 26S prote-
asome, providing evidence that ABI1 promotes proteasomal 
degradation of MKKK18 (Fig. 9). 
ABA plays a major role in various aspects of plant growth 
and development, and is pivotal in stomatal function (Cai et al. 
2014, Danquah et al. 2014, Smekalova et al. 2014). In this study, 
we show that loss of MKKK18 function leads to impaired sto-
matal development and a constitutive phenotype with more 
open stomata. As previously documented, ABA inhibits initi-
ation of stomatal development (Tanaka et al. 2013), reducing 
the number of stomata per leaf and decreasing the SI (Franks </p>

<p>and Farquhar 2001, Tanaka et al. 2013). Our results show that 
the SI of the MKKK18oe lines is significantly higher than in the 
WT Col-0 line (Fig. 4). Accordingly, the SIs of both MKKK18 
knockouts are significantly lower (Fig. 4), suggesting that 
MKKK18 acts as a positive regulator of stomatal development. 
Interestingly, another MKKK, YODA, which fine-tunes this pro-
cess, acts as a negative regulator in the early stages, but acts as a 
positive regulator in the final step, of stomatal development 
(Wang et al. 2007, Lampard et al. 2009). According to Danquah 
et al. (2015) and Matsuoka et al. (2015), the MKKK17/18 kinase 
cascade recruits MKK3-MPK1/2/7/14. YODA activates the 
MKK4/5-MKK7/MKK9 and MPK3/6 pathways during stomatal 
development. Thus we may hypothesize that the MKKK18 
pathway is largely independent of YODA, although it may 
co-operate in the final stages of stomatal development. 
The involvement of different MAPK cascades in the same pro-
cess was reviewed recently (Danquah et al. 2014), while partici-
pation of the same cascades in different processes has also been 
reported (Wang et al. 2007, Meng et al. 2012). 
As is clear from the phenotypes described in this study, 
MKKK18oe lines show different responses to ABA stimulus de-
pending on developmental stage and cell type. For example, ger-
minating MKKK18oe seedlings exhibit a weak ABA-
insensitive phenotype (Fig. 3E), while overexpression of MKKK18 
also causes ABA-hypersensitive stomatal closing and root growth 
(Figs. 3C, 4F). This suggests that similar MKKK18-based signaling 
pathways may operate in these processes, but the opposite </p>

<p>Fig. 8 MKKK18 activity increases in the abi1td mutant in response to ABA treatment. (A) Seedlings of WT Col-0 and the abi1td and snrk2.6 
mutants were treated with 100 mM ABA for the indicated times. A 600 mg aliquot of total protein was used for the immune complex MKKK18 
activity assay using anti-MKKK18 antibody. Coomassie Brilliant Blue (CBB) staining of MBP confirmed equal loading. Due to low abundance, the 
endogenous MKKK18 protein was not detectable by immunoblot analysis. The results shown are representative of three independent experi-
ments (n = 9) with consistent results. (B) </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-labeled MBP bands were quantified using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software and normalized by taking the radio-
activity of the band in the absence of ABA as 1. Data are means ± SD of the relative band intensities from three independent experiments (n = 9). </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146 </p>

<p>phenotypic responses to ABA stimulus may also be observed, 
indicating that MKKK18 signaling integrates various pathways. 
Protein kinase autoactivation, via phosphorylation of the ac-
tivation loop, is a common regulatory mechanism that switches 
the status of the signaling cascades to standby. Very recently, it 
was shown that recombinant GST-MKKK18 is able to autopho-
sphorylate in vitro (Matsuoka et al. 2015). Our data appear to </p>

<p>contradict this result. Compared with a positive control, SnRK2.6 
kinase (Ng et al. 2011), we conclude that MKKK18 does not 
undergo autoactivation (Fig. 7). In our hands, GST-MKKK18 
autophosphorylates neither during production in bacterial cells 
nor in in vitro kinase assays (Fig. 7C). Our results suggest, there-
fore, that MKKK18 must be activated by an upstream kinase 
(possibly a receptor kinase or another type of protein kinase) </p>

<p>Fig. 9 Proteasome-dependent degradation of MKKK18 is ABA-dependent and regulated by ABI1. (A) qPCR analysis of MKKK18 transcript 
accumulation in response to treatment with 50 mM ABA for 90 min in WT Col-0, MKKK18oe, abi1td and abi1-2 strains. MKKK18 expression levels 
were determined using three biological replicates and were normalized against 18S rDNA. The results are displayed as mean log 2 fold change ± SE 
(n = 9) of three independent experiments with consistent results. (B) MKKK18 stability in the cell-free degradation assay. GST-MKKK18 was 
incubated with 100 mg of protein extract from either WT Col-0 or abi1td protoplasts incubated with or without 100 mM MG132 for 6 h in the 
dark. GST-MKKK18 protein levels at the indicated time points were determined by immunoblotting using anti-GST antibodies. Ponceau S 
staining confirmed equal loading. (C and D) Half-life plot for cell-free degradation of MKKK18 in WT Col-0 (C) and abi1td (D) extracts. 
Immunoblot images from each experiment were recorded simultaneously using a G:BOX Chemi XR5 fluorescence and chemiluminescence 
imaging system (Syngene), and the results were quantified using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software. (E) CHX treatment suppresses accumulation of MKKK18. 
Arabidopsis protoplasts expressing 35S:MKKK18-GFP were treated with 3 mM CHX, 3 mM CHX and 100 mM MG132, or given a mock treatment. 
The blot is representative of four experiments. MKKK18-GFP protein levels were determined by immunoblotting using anti-GFP antibodies. 
Ponceau S staining confirmed equal loading. MKKK18 protein bands were quantified using <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software and normalized to the control 
(mock) band (set as 1). (F) MKKK18 protein levels are modified by ABA. GST-MKKK18 was incubated with 100 mg of total protein extract 
isolated from WT Col-0 incubated with or without 50 mM ABA for 3 h in the dark. GST-MKKK18 protein levels at the indicated time points were 
determined by immunoblotting using GST antibodies. Ponceau S staining confirmed equal loading. MKKK18 protein bands were quantified using 
<rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> software and normalized to the control band (set as 1). </p>



<p>F. Mitula et al. | MKKK18 is regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome pathway </p>

<p>in response to ABA. Future studies are necessary to determine 
specific sites of regulatory significance in MKKK18. 
To determine the exact mechanism underlying MKKK18 
regulation, we tested the interaction between MKKK18 and 
the homologous phosphatases ABI1 and ABI2 (Fig. 6). ABI1/2 
are known to be negative regulators of ABA signaling that 
interact with the ABA receptors RCAR/PYR/PYL and SnRK2s 
(Ma et al. 2009, Park et al. 2009, Umezawa et al. 2009, Vlad et al. 
2009). Importantly, ABA-induced MKKK18 kinase activity is 
significantly increased in the ABI1 knockout (Fig. 8), while 
MKKK18 transcript levels were significantly reduced (Fig. 9A) 
compared with the WT. Our results suggest that the ABI1 pro-
tein phosphatase is needed for down-regulation of the pathway 
mediated by MKKK18. Interaction between MKKK18 and ABI1 
supports the notion that the MKKK18 cascade operates down-
stream of the core ABA signaling pathway. 
In addition, functional activation of the MKKK18 pathway is 
also constrained at the transcriptional level. MKKK18 expres-
sion is nearly abolished in ABA-insensitive abi1-1 (Hoth et al. 
2002), hab1 
G246D and quadruple pyr1pyl1pyl2pyr4 ABA recep-
tor mutants (Danaquah et al. 2015). Importantly, the hab1 </p>

<p>G246D </p>

<p>mutant confers an equivalent hypermorphic mutation to abi1-
1 (abi1G180D). Consistent with this, we observed that MKKK18 
activity is abolished in the snrk2.6 mutant and another 
ABA-insensitive mutant (Fig. 8). Because SnRK2.6 activity is 
abolished or nearly abolished in snrk2.6, abi1-1 and pyr1pyl1-
pyl2pyr4 mutants, it is most likely that MKKK18 transcription is 
controlled by SnRK2.6. In the abi1td mutant, decreased 
MKKK18 transcription compensates for its increased stability. 
Overall, we may conclude that components of the core ABA 
pathway regulate MKKK18 function at multiple levels. 
Another element of kinase activity regulation, especially in 
signal transduction pathways, is protein degradation via the 
proteasome pathway (Coulombe et al. 2003, Wang and 
Dohlman 2006, Peng et al. 2008, Fragoso et al. 2009, Lyzenga 
et al. 2013). Ubiquitinated proteins are present at low abun-
dance and are unstable: in mammalian cells, MEKK1 and several 
isoforms of extracellular signal-regulated kinases (ERKs) are 
degraded via the proteasome pathway, leading to inactivation 
of ERK1/2 and c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) pathways 
mediated by MEKK1 (Wang and Dohlman 2006). In 
Arabidopsis, well-documented examples of protein kinase deg-
radation include SnRK1.1, SnRK1.2, GSK3-like kinase and 
CIPK26 (Peng et al. 2008, Fragoso et al. 2009, Lyzenga et al. 
2013). Here we demonstrate that the interaction between 
ABI1 and MKKK18 is necessary for the destruction of the 
MKKK18 kinase (Fig. 9B-D). As shown recently, ABI1 promotes 
the degradation of ACS6 protein (Ludwików et al. 2014). This 
new role of ABI1 phosphatase is not restricted to a single pro-
tein, but also extends to the regulation of MKKK18 activity. We 
show that ABI1 inhibits MKKK18 activity (Fig. 7B) and, using a 
cell-free assay, we reveal that ABI1 promotes its degradation 
(Fig. 9B-D). Consistent with this, we also show that ABA 
treatment increases MKKK18 stability in cell-free assays 
(Fig. 9F), presumably due to inhibition of the ABI1 PP2C by 
ABA. However, it is possible that other mechanisms also 
regulate MKKK18 turnover. For example, the accumulation </p>

<p>of the ABA-responsive transcription factor abscisic acid 
insensitive5 (ABI5) is achieved by ABA-dependent regulation 
of KEG E3 ligase turnover (Liu and Stone 2010). In conclu-
sion, our results suggest that ABI1 PP2C can be considered 
a key player in the ABA-dependent feedback mechanism for 
resetting various signaling pathways to pre-stimulatory status. 
In summary, an important aspect of the current research is 
the identification of key regulators of the ABA response and 
their signaling networks. Our current findings demonstrate that 
phosphorylation and dephosphorylation events play an 
important role in the transmission of the ABA signal. 
Although the SnRK2 protein kinases and group A PP2C-type 
phosphatases constitute a core ABA signaling pathway, the in-
volvement of other groups of proteins, including MAP cascade 
kinases, has been recognized and documented in earlier studies 
(for the most recent review, see Danquah et al. 2014). The 
critical outstanding questions facing researchers are: which 
MAPKs are involved in ABA signal transduction, and what 
are the molecular details of the response to this signal? The 
analyses presented here demonstrate that MKKK18 is an ABA-
activated kinase regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome. Based 
on the results presented in this study and on previously pub-
lished data (Irigoyen et al. 2014), we propose a schematic model 
(Fig. 10) to describe the effect of ABI1 regulation on MKKK18. 
Further analysis will help to elucidate novel regulatory mech-
anisms involving MKKK18. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Plant growth and treatment </p>

<p>Arabidopsis thaliana Col-0 seeds were surface sterilized by treatment with 70% 
ethanol for 10 min, followed by four washes with sterile distilled water. The 
seeds were germinated on half-strength MS medium including 1% sucrose. 
After a 3 d stratification at 4 
C, the seeds were transferred to a growth chamber 
and grown as described in Ludwików et al. (2009). Seeds of mkkk18-1 and 
mkkk18-2 were obtained from the Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre. 
The T-DNA insertion line for abi1td was described previously (Ludwików 
et al. 2009). </p>

<p>Plasmid construction </p>

<p>For protein interaction analysis in yeasts, full-length ABI1 BD constructs and the 
PP2C catalytic domain (ÁN-ABI1) were used as described in Ludwików et al. 
(2009) and Ludwików et al. (2014), respectively. MKKK18 AD constructs were 
PCR-amplified using specific primer pairs (MKKK18fEcoRI and MKKK18rSacI), 
cloned into the pGEM-T Easy vector (Promega), excised as EcoRI-SacI restric-
tion fragments, and ligated into the pACT2-AD vector. To generate the 
MKKK18 BD construct, a pUNI clone for MKKK18 (U18652) was recombined 
with the pACT2 vector using Cre recombinase (Liu et al. 1998). To generate 
the pENTR 
TM /SD/D-TOPO 
Õ vector for facilitating the generation of C-or 
N-terminal in-frame MKKK18 fusions, cDNA for MKKK18 was amplified 
using Pfu polymerase, cloned into pENTR and then sequenced. To generate 
the recombinant GST-or His-tagged vectors, the pENTR-MKKK18 constructs 
were recombined with the Gateway 
Õ pDEST 
TM 15, Gateway 
Õ pDEST 
TM 17 or 
Gateway 
Õ pDEST 
TM 24 vectors using Gateway 
Õ LR Clonase 
Õ II Enzyme Mix 
(Invitrogen). For the BiFC assay, cDNAs for ABI1, ABI2 and MKKK18 were 
amplified using Pfu polymerase and then cloned into the pENTR/SD/D-
TOPO vector (Invitrogen) (see Supplementary Methods S1 for details on 
the construction of the BiFC vector). The clones generated were digested 
with MluI, and the cDNA-containing restriction fragments were recombined 
with the pSAT3-cCFP-DEST and the pSAT5-DEST-nVenus vectors using 
Gateway 
Õ LR Clonase 
Õ II Enzyme Mix (Invitrogen), resulting in ncECFP-</p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146 </p>

<p>ABI1/2 and cnVenus-MKKK18 constructs, respectively. The DNA construct for 
MKKK18 localization and plant transformation (35S:MKKK18-GFP) was pre-
pared in pEarleyGate 103 (Earley et al. 2006) using Gateway technology. Two 
out of six independent Col-0/35S:MKKK18-GFP transgenic lines were tested: #1 
and #2. Site-directed mutagenesis of MKKK18 was performed using a 
QuikChange II XL Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Agilent) according to the 
manufacturer's protocol, and using the following oligonucleotides: K32M For 
5 
0 -CACTCGCCGTAATGTCCGCCGAGT-3 
0 and Rev 5 
0 -ACTCGGCGGACATTA 
CGGCGAGTG-3 
0 ; and T161E For 5 
0 -GGTTGAACCGGAAATAGAGGAACCGGT 
TAGAGGAAC-3 
0 and Rev 5 
0 -GTTCCTCTAACCGGTTCCTCTATTTCCGGTTCA 
ACC-3 
0 . </p>

<p>Construction of the MKKK18 promoter-GUS 
vector </p>

<p>The 1,622 bp MKKK18 promoter region was generated from genomic Arabidopsis 
DNA by PCR amplification using the primers indicated in Supplementary Table 
S1. The promoter sequence was verified by sequencing. BLAST analysis confirmed 
that isolated fragments had 99% identity with the known MKKK18 promoter 
region deposited in the TAIR database. To produce the 1,622 bp MKKK18 pro-
moter region (the D::GUS construct), the PCR products were cloned into the 
pGEM T-Easy vector system (Promega), sequenced and cloned into the KpnI-
PstI sites of the pBI101 vector. The promoter-reporter fusion construct was trans-
formed into Agrobacterium tumefaciens strain LBA4404 and used for A. thaliana 
(Col-0) plant transformations using the floral dip method (Clough and Bent 1998). 
More than five independent transgenic lines were produced and tested for re-
sponsiveness by GUS histochemical assays. Three representative lines were </p>

<p>selected for detailed characterization and showed the same expression pattern 
under all conditions tested. </p>

<p>Histochemical localization of GUS expression </p>

<p>For histochemical analysis of GUS expression, T 2 seeds of Col-0/ 
ProMKKK18:GUS were grown as described and exposed to 1 mM ABA for 
24 h. Tissue samples were immersed in staining buffer [100 mM sodium phos-
phate, pH 7.0, 10 mM EDTA, 0.5 mM K 4 Fe(CN) 6 , 0.5 mM K 3 Fe(CN) 6 , 0.1% Triton 
X-100 and 1 mM X-gluc], and incubated overnight at 37 
C. After the GUS 
reaction, plant samples were incubated in 80% ethanol to remove chlorophyll 
from the green tissues. GUS staining patterns were recorded using a Zeiss Stereo 
Lumar V12 microscope. </p>

<p>Analyses of the mkkk18-1 and mkkk18-2 T-DNA 
insertion lines </p>

<p>The mkkk18-1 and the mkkk18-2 T-DNA insertion lines were isolated from 
SALK insertion lines (SALK_087047) and from the GABI-Kat collection 
(GK-244G02), respectively. The qPCR analyses were performed as described 
in Ludwików et al. (2009). </p>

<p>Stomatal index and stomatal aperture </p>

<p>The SI was calculated based on the method described in Tanaka et al. (2013). 
Counts of stomata and pavement cells were performed on five areas of each 
cotyledon from 10 separate seedlings, giving 100 measurements per experi-
ment, using a Nikon Eclipse Ti microscope with a Nikon Digital Sight DS-Fi1c </p>

<p>Fig. 10 Regulation of MKKK18 activity and stability by ABI1 PP2C. Under standard conditions, active ABI1 protein phosphatase inhibits MKKK18 
kinase activity and protein stability. ABA receptors and dephosphorylated MKKK18 are directed for degradation via the proteasome pathway. In 
the presence of ABA, ABI1 PP2C activity is restrained by binding of ABI1 to the ABA-PYL complex (ABA signaling is turned on). Active MKKK18 
activates the downstream cascade. ABA inhibits the degradation of ABA receptors by limiting their polyubiquitination. </p>



<p>F. Mitula et al. | MKKK18 is regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome pathway </p>

<p>camera. The SI was calculated individually for each cotyledon using the formula: 
SI = [number of stomata/(number of other epidermal cells + number of sto-
mata)]. For statistical analysis, Student's t-test was performed. For guard cell 
aperture measurements, rosette leaves of 5-week-old plants were floated in 
opening buffer (10 mM KCl, 7.5 mM EGTA, 10 mM MES-KOH, at pH 6.15) 
and incubated at 20 
C under light conditions for 2 h to open the stomata. 
Subsequently, the same opening buffer was supplemented with either 15 mM 
ABA, 1 mM H 2 O 2 or 1 mM CaCl 2 , and the leaves were incubated for another 2 h. 
The stomatal apertures (width divided by length) along three different epider-
mal transects were measured using a Nikon Eclipse Ti (with Nikon Digital Sight 
DS-Fi1c digital camera) and <rs type="software">Nikon NIS Elements AR</rs> software. No less than 60 
mature stomata were analyzed per transect. </p>

<p>Protoplast isolation, transformation and transient 
expression assays </p>

<p>Transient expression assays were performed using protoplasts from Arabidopsis 
mesophyll cells. Protoplast isolation, transformation and transient expression 
assays were performed based on methods described in Ludwików et al. (2014). 
Protoplasts were transiently transformed with 5 mg of plasmid, collected by 
centrifugation and resuspended in lysis buffer for further analysis. Transient 
protein expression in tobacco leaves was performed as described in Voinnet 
et al. (2003). Agrobacterium tumefaciens C58C1 cells with different MKKK18 
constructs were mixed with an equal volume of Agrobacterium C58C1 (pCH32 
35S:p19) expressing the silencing suppressor p19. The bacteria were injected 
into fully expanded leaves of tobacco plants, and were examined after 5 days. </p>

<p>Kinase activity assays </p>

<p>For the in vitro kinase assays, the MKKK18 immunocomplex assay was per-
formed based on methods described in Ludwików et al. (2014). Briefly, tissue 
extracts containing 500 mg of total protein were immunoprecipitated for 1 h at 
4 
C with 5 mg of anti-GFP or anti-MKKK18 antibody pre-coupled to Dynabeads 
Protein-A (Invitrogen). This mixture was washed three times with wash buffer I 
(20 mM Tris-HCl, 5 mM EDTA, 100 mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-100), once with the 
same buffer but containing 1 M NaCl, and once with kinase buffer [20 mM 
HEPES, pH 7.5, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT)]. A half-aliquot of 
MKKK18 was used to phosphorylate 5 mg of substrate (MBP; Sigma) in kinase 
buffer containing 25 mM ATP and [g-
32 P]ATP (2 mCi per reaction) at 30 
C. 
Another half-aliquot of activated MKKK18 was assayed under the same con-
ditions without radioactive ATP. The reactions were stopped by the addition of 
SDS-loading buffer after 60 min. SDS-PAGE reaction products were analyzed 
using autoradiography or Western blotting. </p>

<p>Immunoblotting </p>

<p>Proteins were separated by 10% SDS-PAGE (BioRad) and were transferred onto 
Immobilon-P membranes (Millipore). The membranes were blocked for 1 h in PBS-
T containing a 3% blocking solution, washed three times and incubated for 1 h with 
rabbit anti-GFP (1 : 200; sc-8334, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), StrepMAB-Classic 
(1 : 3,000; IBA BioTAGnology), anti-GST-Tag (1 : 5,000; Sigma), anti-MKKK18 anti-
body (AS13 2673, Agrisera), anti-ABI1 (AS12 1861, Agrisera) and anti-ABI2 (AS12 
1871, Agrisera). After washing three times, the membranes were incubated for 1 h 
with the appropriate secondary antibody. Detection was performed with ECL 
(Thermo Scientific) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </p>

<p>GST-tagged protein overexpression, purification, 
pull-down and cell-free degradation assays </p>

<p>Escherichia coli BL21(DE3) competent cells were transformed with recombinant 
MKKK18-GST, GST-ABI1 and GST-ABI2 expression constructs. Bacterial growth, 
isolation of recombinant GST fusion proteins, pull-down assays and cell-free deg-
radation assays were conducted according to Ludwików et al. (2014). The abun-
dance of MKKK18-GST was determined using anti-GST antibodies. </p>

<p>Bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BIFC) 
in Arabidopsis protoplasts </p>

<p>For the BiFC analysis, various combinations of plasmids encoding cECFP, 
nVenus fusion proteins and red fluorescent proteins (RFPs) as an internal </p>

<p>control were mixed at a 1 : 1 : 1 (w/w) ratio, and the mixture of plasmid DNA 
was used for polyethylene glycol-mediated transformation as described by 
Ludwików et al. (2014). </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at PCP online. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Dean of the Faculty of Biology 
['Grants for Interdisciplinary Grants' No. GIWB-02/2011]; the 
National Science Centre [grants No. DEC-2012/05/B/NZ3/ 
00352 to A.L. and DEC-2011/03/N/NZ3/01796 to M.M.]; 
KNOW Poznan RNA Centre [01/KNOW2/2014]. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank David Baulcombe for providing the p19 vector con-
struct and the Agrobacterium C58C1 strain, Olga Sztatelman for 
providing seeds of the snrk2.6 mutant, and Hanna Korcz-
Szatkowska for excellent technical assistance. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. </p>





<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146 </p>





<p>F. Mitula et al. | MKKK18 is regulated by ABI1 and the proteasome pathway </p>





<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 56(12): 2351-2367 (2015) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcv146 </p>

</text></tei>