<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4407761" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background. The live attenuated influenza vaccine (LAIV) is the preferred vaccine for children, but the mech-
anisms behind protective immune responses are unclear, and the duration of immunity remains to be elucidated. 
This study reports on the longevity of B-cell and T-cell responses elicited by the LAIV. 
Methods. Thirty-eight children (3-17 years old) were administered seasonal LAIV. Blood samples were collected be-
fore vaccination with sequential sampling up to 1 year after vaccination. Humoral responses were evaluated by a hemagglu-
tination inhibition assay, and memory B-cell responses were evaluated by an enzyme-linked immunosorbent spot assay 
(ELISpot). T-cell responses were evaluated by interferon γ (IFN-γ) ELISpot analysis, and intracellular cytokine staining of 
CD4 
+ T cells for detection of IFN-γ, interleukin 2, and tumor necrosis factor α was performed using flow cytometry. 
Results. LAIV induced significant increases in B-cell and T-cell responses, which were sustained at least 1 year after 
vaccination. Strain variations were observed, in which the B strain elicited stronger responses. IFN-γ-expressing T cell 
counts increased significantly, and remained higher than prevaccination levels 1 year later. Expression of T-helper type 1 
intracellular cytokines (interleukin 2, IFN-γ, and tumor necrosis factor α) increased after 1 dose and were boosted after the 
second dose. Hemagglutination inhibition titers were sustained for 1 year. Vaccine-induced memory B cell counts were 
significantly increased, and the response persisted for one year. 
Conclusions. LAIV elicited B-cell and T-cell responses that persisted for at least 1 year in children. This is a novel 
finding that will aid future vaccine policy. </p>

<p>Keywords. influenza; LAIV; humoral; T-cellular; longevity; pediatric; IFN-γ. </p>

<p>Annually, influenza virus infection has a large socioeco-
nomic burden on society, with 500 000 fatal cases glob-
ally [1-3]. The World Health Organization estimates </p>

<p>that 20% of children are infected with influenza virus 
each year, and they are the main source of spread of 
the virus and have a high burden of the disease [4]. Vac-
cination is the cornerstone of prophylaxis and is recom-
mended for high-risk patients. The trivalent inactivated 
influenza vaccine (TIV) is safe and provides protection 
but may not be the optimal vaccine for young children, 
owing to their lack of previous infection. Since 2003, 
the cold-adapted live attenuated influenza vaccine 
(LAIV), administered as a nasal spray, has been ap-
proved in the United States for individuals aged 2-49 
years. The vaccine was licensed in Europe in 2012 
(for individuals aged 2-17 years) and was implemented 
in the British childhood vaccination campaign, begin-
ning in 2013 [5]. In June 2014, the Advisory Committee 
on Immunization Practices preferentially recommended 
LAIV in healthy children 2-8 years old when it is imme-
diately available [6]. </p>

<p>Received 13 September 2014; accepted 11 November 2014; electronically pub-
lished 25 November 2014. 
Presented in part: Options for the Control of Influenza VIII Conference, Cape 
Town, South Africa, September 2013; Fifth European Scientific Working Group on 
Influenza Conference, Riga, Latvia, September 2014, 
Correspondence: Kristin G.-I. Mohn, MD, Influenza Center, Universitiy of Bergen, 
Haukeland University Hospital, Laboratory Bldg, 5th Fl, Jonas Lies vei 20, Bergen 
5021, Norway (kristin.mohn@k2.uib.no). </p>

<p>The Journal of Infectious Diseases 
® 2015;211:1541-9 
© The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Infectious 
Diseases Societyof America. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms 
of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/), which permits non-commercial 
reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work 
is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For 
commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com. 
DOI: 10.1093/infdis/jiu654 </p>

<p>LAIV Longevity Response • JID 2015:211 (15 May) • 1541 </p>

<p>Despite many years on the market, there are no established 
correlates of protection for LAIV. Efficacy studies and observa-
tional data suggest that the LAIV provides higher levels of pro-
tection than TIV in children [7-11]. The hemagglutination 
inhibition (HI) titer is widely used as a surrogate correlate of pro-
tection after TIV receipt; however, the cutoff titer of 1:40 is based 
on adult trials. There is debate on both the protective HI level in 
children and the fact that an HI titer underestimates the protec-
tion obtained by LAIV [12-14]. Cellular immunity may be a bet-
ter measure of protective immunity after LAIV in children [15]. 
CD4 
+ T cells have the ability to act as effector cells and to direct </p>

<p>and generate specific memory CD4 
+ and CD8 
+ T-cell subsets </p>

<p>with diverse functions [16-18]. Animal and human studies 
have demonstrated protective cellular immunity after LAIV 
[10, 19-21]. Therefore, the duration and quality of the immune 
response in humans after LAIV needs to be studied. 
We conducted a pediatric clinical trial to elucidate the immu-
nological mechanisms induced by LAIV, with emphasis on the 
long-term, strain-specific cellular immune responses. Our study 
is unique, as we obtained sequential blood samples from young 
children up to 1 year after vaccination, allowing us to compare 
and analyze serum and cellular responses in the same child. Our 
results indicate that LAIV induces long-term humoral and 
cellular immune responses in children and that priming is 
important in determining the magnitude of the response. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients and Study Design </p>

<p>Thirty-eight healthy children, consisting of 20 boys and 18 girls 
aged 3-17 years old, were recruited at Haukeland University 
Hospital (HUH) in Norway. From October 2012 to January 
2013, children were immunized with the trivalent seasonal LAIV </p>

<p>(Fluenz, Astra Zeneca, Birmingham, United Kingdom). Fluenz 
contained 10 
7.0 fluorescent focus units of attenuated reassortant </p>

<p>of A/California/7/2009(H1N1)pdm09-like, A/Victoria/361/ 
2011(H3N2)-like, and B/Wisconsin/1/2010 strains. The vaccine 
was administered intranasally as 0.1 mL per nostril. Children 3-
9 years old received 2 doses at a 4-week interval, and children 
≥10 years old received a single dose of vaccine as recommended 
by the manufacturer. The study was approved by the Regional 
Ethical Committee of Western Norway and the Norwegian 
Medicines Agency and was monitored by HUH (clinical trials 
registration, NCT01866540; EUDRACT registration 2012-
002848-24). 
Upon enrollment, parents and children aged ≥12 years pro-
vided voluntary, written informed consent. We collected data 
on baseline demographic characteristics, medical and influenza 
vaccination history, and risk factors for influenza virus infec-
tion. All procedures were conducted at the pediatric trial unit 
at HUH. Children with mild-to-moderate asthma (clinically 
stable with daily use of inhalators) or who had received prior 
influenza vaccination were included. Exclusion criteria are listed 
in Figure 1. A self-reported questionnaire of local and systemic 
side effects was completed after each vaccination. </p>

<p>Samples </p>

<p>Blood samples (volume, 8 mL) were collected after vaccination 
(Figure 1). Fresh peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) 
were isolated using Cell Preparation Tubes (BD, New Jersey) 
[22]. Plasma samples were aliquoted and stored at −80°C before 
use in the HI assay. </p>

<p>HI Assay </p>

<p>Plasma samples from each individual were tested in duplicate by 
means of an HI assay, using 8 hemagglutination units of the </p>

<p>Figure 1. Study design. Healthy children scheduled for elective tonsillectomy were recruited from the Ear, Nose, and Throat Department, Haukeland 
University Hospital (HUH), Bergen, Norway. Thirty-eight children received live attenuated influenza vaccine (LAIV), and 29 children (all &lt;10 years old) re-
ceived a second dose. Blood samples were collected before vaccination and at 4 time points after vaccination. The number of subjects providing samples at 
each time point is shown. Not all children provided blood samples at all visits, owing to difficulty in obtaining blood samples with a sufficient volume (ie, 8 
mL). Exclusion criteria were as follows: serious, chronic medical conditions; serious asthma; recent influenza; fever; pregnancy; use of acetyl salicylic acid 
(ASA) or immunosuppressive therapy; allergy to the vaccine components or earlier complications to vaccination; or under governmental custody. </p>

<p>1542 • JID 2015:211 (15 May) • Mohn et al </p>

<p>homologous H1N1 and H3N2 vaccine strains and 0.7% turkey 
red blood cells [23]. HI titers were defined as the reciprocal of 
the dilution causing 50% HI. Negative titers were assigned a 
value of 5 for calculation purposes. </p>

<p>Interferon γ (IFN-γ) Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Spot 
(ELISpot) Assay </p>

<p>IFN-γ-precoated 96-well plates were used according to 
the manufacturer's instructions (Mabtech, Sweden). PBMCs 
(400 000 cells/well) in Roswell Park Memorial Institute medium 
plus 10% fetal calf serum were added to wells, along with nega-
tive control (medium alone) or influenza virus antigens (5 µg/mL 
of split virus vaccine of each strain; H1N1, H3N2, B). Plates were 
incubated overnight (37°C, 5% CO 2 ) and developed the following 
day. The plates were read using the Immunoscan reader and as-
sociated software (<rs type="software">CTL-Europe</rs>). The negative control was sub-
tracted from the influenza virus-specific response. </p>

<p>Intracellular Cytokine Staining (ICS) of CD4 
+ T Cells </p>

<p>Expression of the influenza virus-specific T-helper type 1 (Th1) 
cytokines (IFN-γ, interleukin 2 [IL-2], and tumor necrosis factor 
α {TNF-α}) were measured using ICS of CD4 
+ T-cells. PBMCs </p>

<p>were stimulated overnight with a mixture of the 3 split-virus an-
tigens in the vaccine (H1N1, H3N2 and B; 2.5 µg/mL of each 
protein) in the presence of brefeldin A, monensin, and anti-
CD28 and anti-CD49 antibodies (BD Bioscience, San Jose). 
After overnight stimulation, cells were stained and analyzed 
on a BD LSR II flow cytometer for the expression of IFN-γ, 
IL-2, and TNF-α, as described earlier [24]. The antibodies 
used are provided in Supplementary Table 1, and the gating 
strategy is specified in Supplementary Figure 2. </p>

<p>Memory B-Cell Response, Determined by ELISpot </p>

<p>The antigen-specific immunoglobulin G (IgG), immunoglobulin 
A (IgA), and immunoglobulin M (IgM) memory B-cell responses 
after vaccination were quantified by ELISpot, as described by Pa-
thirana et al [25] and Crotty et al [26]. Influenza virus-specific im-
munoglobulin-secreting cells per million PBMCs are presented as 
percentages of the total IgG, IgA, and IgM responses, respectively. </p>

<p>Statistics </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed in <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs>, version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">17</rs>, and 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs>, version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version">5</rs> for Mac (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, San 
Diego, California). For all statistical tests, a P value of &lt; .05 was 
considered significant. ICS results were compared using t test. 
For the remaining results, analysis of variance (by the Kruskal-
Wallis test) with multiple comparisons testing was used. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Study Subjects </p>

<p>Thirty-eight healthy children, including 6 with asthma, received 
the LAIV (median age, 4 years). Ten children did not receive a </p>

<p>second dose owing to an age of ≥10 years (n = 8), concurrent 
illness at the time of vaccination (n = 1), and withdrawal from 
the study (n = 1). Samples were collected before and after vacci-
nation with sampling points as indicated in Figure 1. </p>

<p>Safety and Side Effects </p>

<p>The vaccine was easy to administer and well tolerated. Adverse 
events were solicited by questionnaires during the initial 7 days 
after vaccination, and 46% of children reported no side effects 
after the first dose. Reported side effects were mild and mostly 
local. Seven children (18%) reported runny/congested nose, and 
4 (11%) reported systemic side effects (Supplementary Figure 1). 
Six children had mild or moderate asthma (clinically stable with 
daily use of local steroids and β2 agonists), of whom 5 reported no 
side effects after vaccination and 1 reported transient local side 
effects. Parents of the asthmatic children did not report asthma 
exacerbation during the trial. In general, reactions often started 
2 days after vaccination and mainly lasted 1-3 days (data not 
shown). One severe adverse event required consultation but not 
treatment; this occurred in a healthy 17-year-old girl with non-
typical influenza-like illness symptoms of arthralgia. After the 
second dose, 26 children (90%) reported no side effects, and 3 
(10%) reported mostly local side effects (Supplementary 
Figure 1). </p>

<p>HI Antibody Response Against Influenza Virus A Strains 
Persists for 1 Year </p>

<p>Figure 2A and 2B show the HI response to the H1N1 and H3N2 
strains before and after LAIV receipt. An HI titer of ≥40 was 
considered a protective response. 
Before vaccination, the majority of children (25 [66%]) had 
protective antibody titers toward H1N1 (geometric mean titer 
[GMT], 71; 95% confidence interval {CI}, 40-125). Thirteen 
children did not have protective HI titers, of whom 9 had no 
detectable antibody (HI titer, &lt; 10) to the H1N1 virus. An in-
crease in HI titer occurred after the first dose (day 28; GMT, 95; 
95% CI, 55-164) and after the second dose (day 56; GMT, 111; 
95% CI, 64-194), when 27 subjects (84%) had a protective an-
tibody titer (9% seroconverted). Eighteen subjects had HI titers 
of ≥40 to the H1N1 virus at 180 days, and 6 subjects had no 
detectable antibodies. At day 360, 11 of 14 children (79%) 
had a protective HI level (≥40), of whom 3 seroconverted, but 
2 of these children had high prevaccination levels. Two children 
had no detectable antibodies. Four children without prevaccina-
tion antibodies remained seronegative throughout the study. 
For the H3N2 strain, 14 (37%) of the 18 children (47%) with an 
HI titer of &lt; 40 were seronegative (HI titer, 5; GMT, 37; 95% CI, 
20-68; Figure 2). After the first dose, there was a significant in-
crease in HI titers (P &lt; .0001) in all children except 2, reaching 
protective HI levels (GMT, 286; 95% CI, 203-401). The increase 
observed after the second dose was significant, compared with the 
titer on day 0 (P &lt; .001), as well as the titer on day 180 (P &lt; .01), </p>

<p>LAIV Longevity Response • JID 2015:211 (15 May) • 1543 </p>

<p>and 47% of the children seroconverted. One 4-year-old child had 
an HI titer of 40 after 2 doses but had no detectable titers at other 
time points. The antibody titers remained elevated 180 days after 
vaccination, with 96% of subjects (n =23) having protective HI ti-
ters (GMT, 229; 95% CI, 147-357). At day 360, 12 subjects (86%) 
had sustained a protective HI antibody response (GMT, 169; 95% 
CI, 69-410), while the titer in only 2 children remained &lt;40. Of 
the 14 children evaluated at day 360, 8 (57%) seroconverted. 
There was no significant difference in the durability of the HI 
response for either strain in children receiving 1 or 2 doses of 
vaccine (Supplementary Figure 3). </p>

<p>Long-term Increased IFN-γ Response </p>

<p>We measured the IFN-γ response by using an ELIspot, and we 
observed interstrain variations. The highest numbers of specific 
IFN-γ-secreting cells after vaccination were towards the B 
strain, followed by the H3N2 strain, and the lowest numbers was 
to the H1N1 strain. Before vaccination, the majority of children 
(77%) had levels of IFN-γ-secreting T-cells of ≥100 spot-form-
ing cells (SFCs)/10 
6 PBMCs that were specific to H1N1, which </p>

<p>is a suggested level of protection against influenza (Figure 3A) 
[15]. There was a significant increase in IFN-γ-secreting cells 28 
days after the first dose (P &lt; .05) and a further increase after the </p>

<p>Figure 2. Hemagglutination inhibition (HI) antibody titers after vaccination. Children were intranasally vaccinated with 1 (for those aged ≥10 years) or 2 
(for those aged &lt;10 years; doses were administered at a 28-day interval) doses of live attenuated influenza vaccine. HI antibody titers to H1N1 (A) and H3N2 
(B) were measured at the following time points: day 0 (before vaccination), day 28 (after the first dose), day 56 (after the second dose), and days 180 and 360 
after vaccination. Each symbol represents the HI response of 1 child, with bold horizontal lines and whiskers denoting geometric mean titers and 95% 
confidence intervals, respectively. The dotted line represents an HI titer of 40, considered the protective level [27]. The statistical significance of differences 
from prevaccination levels was determined by analysis of variance, using the nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis test. **P &lt; .01, ***P &lt; .001, and ****P &lt; .0001. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Long-term interferon γ (IFN-γ) immune response in blood after live attenuated influenza vaccination (LAIV). The long-term immune response 
was evaluated by measuring the number of IFN-γ-producing T cells, measured as spot-forming cells (SFCs)/10 
6 peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) 
after LAIV, using the IFN-γ enzyme-linked immunosorbent spot assay. Children were intranasally vaccinated with 1 (for those aged &lt;10 years) or 2 (for those 
aged ≥10 years; doses were administered at a 28-day interval) doses of LAIV. Blood samples were collected at 0, 28, 56, 180, and 360 days after vac-
cination. Each symbol represents the influenza virus-specific SFCs/10 
6 PBMCs for each child for each influenza strain in the vaccine (A, B, C), with bold 
horizontal lines and whiskers denoting mean values and standard errors of the mean, respectively. The dotted line represents 100 SFCs/10 
6 PBMCs, con-
sidered the protective level [15]. The statistical significance of differences from prevaccination levels was determined by analysis of variance, using the 
nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis test. *P &lt; .05, **P &lt; .01, ***P &lt; .001, and ****P &lt; .0001. </p>

<p>1544 • JID 2015:211 (15 May) • Mohn et al </p>

<p>second dose (P &lt; .001). The levels declined toward day 180, de-
creasing below the proposed protective level at day 360 after 
vaccination, but the mean value remained higher than prevac-
cination levels, although the difference was not significant. Six 
of the 7 children with ≥100 SFCs before vaccination had re-
ceived the Pandemrix vaccine. 
For the H3N2 strain (Figure 3B), 20 subjects (65%) had &lt;100 
SFCs/10 
6 PBMCs before vaccination, and the numbers of H3N2-</p>

<p>specific IFN-γ-secreting cells increased significantly after the first 
(P &lt; .05) and second (P = .01) doses. Levels declined toward day 
180 and increased slightly again by day 360, remaining above the 
suggested protective level of 100 SFCs/10 
6 PBMCs, although the </p>

<p>difference from prevaccination levels was not significant. Nine of 
the 11 children with ≥100 SFCs/10 
6 PBMCs before vaccination </p>

<p>had received the Pandemrix vaccine. There was no significant dif-
ference in IFN-γ response in children receiving 1 or 2 doses (Sup-
plementary Figure 4) 
The response was highest toward the B strain, with 25 sub-
jects (80%) exhibiting &lt;100 SFCs/10 
6 PBMCs before vacc-</p>

<p>ination, but it increased significantly after the first dose 
(P &lt; .0001), with a subsequent boost after the second dose 
(P &lt; .0001). By days 180 and 360, the levels declined, but the 
mean levels remained above the protective level and were signif-
icantly higher than at day 0 (P &lt; .001 and P &lt; .05, respectively). 
The IFN-γ response at each time point after vaccination was 
plotted against the HI response at day 0 (the prevaccination ef-
fect) and day 28 (the postvaccination effect) after immuniza-
tion. There was a significant correlation between the fold 
increase in HI titer for H1N1 and the fold increase in IFN-γ se-
cretion (Spearman r = 0.438; P = .036), but the correlation was 
not observed for H3N2 (data not shown). 
Further analysis of the 5 children who remained seronegative 
(HI titer, 5) to the H1N1 strain after vaccination (2 doses) found 
a significant increase in influenza virus-specific IFN-γ respons-
es after vaccination (P = .029). </p>

<p>Increased Multifunctional CD4 
+ T-Cell Response After LAIV </p>

<p>Receipt </p>

<p>Figure 4A shows that the frequency of Th1 CD4 
+ T cells that </p>

<p>express a single cytokine (IFN-γ, IL-2, or TNF-α) increased 
after the first dose and was significantly higher after the second 
immunization, compared with prevaccination levels. Similarly, 
the percentage of multifunctional CD4 
+ T cells expressing </p>

<p>either 2 (IFN-γ and IL-2, or IL-2 and TNF-α) or 3 (IFN-γ, 
IL-2, and TNF-α) cytokines increased after the first dose and 
significantly increased after the second dose, compared with 
prevaccination levels (Figure 4B). </p>

<p>Increased Long-term Memory B-Cell Response After LAIV 
Receipt </p>

<p>We evaluated the long-term influenza virus-specific memory B-
cell response (IgG </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, IgA </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, and IgM </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) after LAIV receipt (Figure 5). </p>

<p>Overall, the highest frequencies were measured toward the B 
strain, and the lowest were observed toward the H1N1 strain. 
The levels of H1N1-specific IgG 
+ memory B cells were high </p>

<p>before vaccination and remained elevated at all sampling points 
after vaccination. The IgM 
+ memory B-cell frequencies to </p>

<p>H1N1 increased significantly at all time points after vaccination 
(P &lt; .01), whereas the IgA 
+ memory B-cell response was only </p>

<p>significantly higher on day 360 (P &lt; .01). 
For the H3N2 strain, IgG 
+ memory B cells increased after the </p>

<p>first dose of vaccine, with a significant boost (P &lt; .001) after the 
second dose. The frequencies of H3N2-specific IgG 
+ memory B </p>

<p>Figure 4. The CD4 
+ T cell cytokine (T-helper type 1 [Th1]) response be-
fore and after vaccination. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells obtained 
before vaccination (day 0) and 28 and 56 days after vaccination were sim-
ulated overnight with split-virus antigen from a mixture of the 3 virus 
strains in the vaccine (H1N1, H3N2, and B). The percentage of CD4 
+ T 
cells secreting either single (A) or multiple (B) Th1 cytokines was measured 
by multiparametric flow cytometry. *P &lt; .05, by the Student t test, compared 
with the CD4 
+ T-cell response before vaccination (day 0). Abbreviations: 
IFN-γ, interferon γ; IL-2, interleukin 2; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor α. </p>

<p>LAIV Longevity Response • JID 2015:211 (15 May) • 1545 </p>

<p>cells were maintained at day 180 (P &lt; .01) and decreased at day 
360, although they remained higher than at day 0. We did not 
detect increased levels of IgA 
+ memory B cells to H3N2 at any </p>

<p>time point after vaccination; in contrast, IgM 
+ memory B cells </p>

<p>increased significantly at all time points (P &lt; .01). </p>

<p>For influenza B, the frequencies of all immunoglobulin 
classes of memory B cells increased significantly after 1 dose 
of vaccine, with P values of &lt;.05 for IgG and IgA and &lt;.001 
for IgM, for which the highest numbers were observed. After 
the second immunization, both the IgG 
+ and IgM 
+ memory B </p>

<p>Figure 5. Long-term memory B-cell (MBC) responses after live attenuated influenza vaccination (LAIV). The frequencies of influenza virus-specific im-
munoglobulin G (IgG), immunoglobulin A (IgA), and immunoglobulin M (IgM)-expressing MBCs before and after LAIV receipt. MBCs were stimulated to 
proliferate and differentiate into antibody-secreting cells by mitogens in vitro, and levels were subsequently measured by an enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
spot assay. The y-axis shows the percentage of influenza virus-specific MBCs. IgG </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, IgM 
+ , and IgA 
+ MBCs were measured against the 3 influenza virus 
strains in the vaccine. Data are represented as the percentage of antigen-specific IgG </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, IgA 
+ , and IgM 
+ MBCs among all IgG 
+ , IgA 
+ , and IgM 
+ MBCs, 
respectively. Each symbol represents 1 child. IgA 
+ and IgM 
+ MBC frequencies for day 180 were not determined because of laboratory constraints. The 
lines represent mean values ± standard errors of the mean. The statistical significance of differences from prevaccination levels was determined by analysis 
of variance, using the nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis test. *P &lt; .05, **P &lt; .01, ***P &lt; .001, and ****P &lt; .0001. </p>

<p>1546 • JID 2015:211 (15 May) • Mohn et al </p>

<p>cells increased significantly (P &lt; .01). At day 360, the frequencies 
remained higher than those observed before vaccination for all 3 
immunoglobulins. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Clinical pediatric trials with LAIV generally focus on short-
term responses after 1 or 2 doses or on efficacy studies per-
formed during influenza seasons [9, 28, 29]. Less is known 
about the long-term immunological responses, but there are 
studies reporting the durability of serum and local antibodies 
and the efficacy of LAIV [30, 31]. The aim of this study was 
to evaluate the longevity of the humoral and cellular immune 
responses elicited by LAIV in young children, with a focus on 
the effect of priming. To our knowledge, our study is unique in 
reporting the long-term immune responses to LAIV in children, 
including those with asthma. We found that the vaccine was safe 
and easy to administer, with mild side effects after the first dose 
and even fewer side effects after the second dose (Supplementa-
ry Figure 1). 
This study was conducted during a postpandemic period, 
when the H1N1 strain dominated. In general, the highest im-
mune response was against the B strain, followed by the 
H3N2 strain, with the lowest response against the H1N1 strain. 
The total levels of serum IgG, IgA, and IgM were stable 
throughout the study period [32]. The serological response to 
LAIV was evaluated by an HI assay, with differences observed 
in the response to the H1N1 and H3N2 strains. Before vaccina-
tion, the majority of the children had protective antibody titers 
(HI titer, ≥40) against the H1N1 strain, which did not increase 
after vaccination but remained elevated 1 year after vaccination. 
This may be because H1N1 was a dominant circulating influen-
za A strain in 2009 and 2010. Hence, most of the children were 
primed, either by natural infection or pandemic vaccination 
[33]. As LAIV must replicate to elicit an immune response, 
the presence of preexisting antibodies or cross-reactive T cells 
in primed children could inhibit virus infection and replication, 
resulting in lower HI responses. In contrast, the H3N2 strain 
circulated to a much lesser degree in Norway; hence, most 
children were unprimed against this strain [33]. The B strain 
had limited circulation in the prior seasons, except during 
2010-2011; it is therefore possible that most children were 
naive to this strain, consistent with the observation that 
LAIVs elicit stronger immune responses in unprimed children 
[34]. Apart from priming, differences in infectivity among the 
vaccine strains could also impact the subsequent immune 
response. We saw no difference in durability of the immune 
response after 1 or 2 doses of vaccine (Supplementary Figures 3 
and 4). 
Induction of long-term immunological memory is the ulti-
mate goal of vaccination. In this study, levels of influenza 
virus-specific memory B cells increased after vaccination and </p>

<p>were maintained for 1 year. Memory B cells can rapidly differ-
entiate into antibody-secreting plasmablasts upon antigen reen-
counter. They may possess broad cross-reactivity and the ability 
to go through secondary affinity maturation to altered antigenic 
epitopes [35, 36]. The IgG 
+ and IgA 
+ memory B-cell responses </p>

<p>in our study were strain dependent. When we divided the chil-
dren according to a protective HI titer of 40, we observed that, 
in influenza virus-primed children, the levels of memory B cells 
were not boosted upon vaccination (data not shown). The lack 
of a boosting response after vaccination in B cells in primed in-
dividuals has previously been described in adults [37, 38]. In 
contrast to the IgG 
+ and IgA 
+ memory B-cell responses, the </p>

<p>IgM 
+ memory B-cell response increased significantly against </p>

<p>all 3 influenza virus strains. Recent research suggests that iso-
type-switched, affinity-matured memory B cells dominate the 
antibody-secreting cell response on antigen recall, while the ma-
jority of IgM 
+ memory B cells contain less somatic hypermuta-</p>

<p>tions and dominate the formation of new germinal centers [38, 
39]. Furthermore, it has been suggested that IgM 
+ memory B </p>

<p>cells live longer than their isotype-switched counterparts [39]. 
Thus, the influenza virus-specific IgM 
+ memory B cells may </p>

<p>contain a population with the potential to respond to novel an-
tigenic variants (eg, drifted influenza viruses). The observed 
strain variations may indicate a biological threshold for memory 
B-cell responses in children with preexisting memory B cells 
due to previous influenza virus exposure. 
LAIV mimics natural infection and activates the innate im-
mune system, as well as both humoral and T-cell responses, 
which play a key role in cross-reactive anti-influenza virus re-
sponses [10, 21]. T cells depend on major histocompatibility 
complex presentation of viral antigens and, hence, cannot pre-
vent infection per se. Human studies have shown naturally ac-
quired CD4 
+ and CD8 
+ T cells to be important in limiting </p>

<p>disease and may provide heterosubtypic immunity, which 
may influence the influenza A (H1N1 and H3N2) response 
[40, 41]. T cells respond to conserved epitopes, which is why 
the response to influenza A viruses is interlinked. Importan-
tly, cross-reactive T cells elicited by LAIV have the potential 
to protect against drifted strains and shifted pandemic strains. 
This has been demonstrated in animal models [42, 43]. LAIV-
induced cross-reactive antibodies have been found in humans, 
but it has yet to be determined whether LAIV induces cross-
protective T cells in humans. 
Using a direct ELISpot assay, we determined the IFN-γ T-cell 
response following LAIV immunization. This ELISpot assay is 
more sensitive than serum antibody responses in determining 
the influenza virus-specific memory immune response with 
an arbitrary number of 100 SFC/10 
6 PBMCs suggested as a pro-</p>

<p>tective level against clinical influenza after LAIV in a trial of 
&gt;2000 children [15]. Interestingly, 5 subjects in our study 
who, on the basis of HI assays, did not seroconvert to H1N1 
had a significant increase in their IFN-γ response after 2 vaccine </p>

<p>LAIV Longevity Response • JID 2015:211 (15 May) • 1547 </p>

<p>doses, which may provide clinical protection. In fact, HI titers 
are known to underestimate the protective effect achieved by the 
LAIV in children, and clinical efficacy studies on LAIV have 
shown high levels of protection against laboratory-confirmed 
influenza despite low HI titers [7, 44, 45]. Studies in adults 
have found that LAIV elicits higher CD4 
+ T-cell responses </p>

<p>than TIV to the variant region of hemagglutinin, suggesting 
that antigenically distinct mutants that escape antibody re-
sponses may still be recognized by T cells [21]. 
Recent studies suggest that CD4 
+ T cells that simultaneously </p>

<p>secrete IFN-γ, IL-2, or TNF-α (multifunctional T cells) are 
functionally superior than single cytokine producers at induc-
ing anti-influenza virus immunity [46]. In this study, we have 
shown that LAIV induces a significant increase in both sin-
gle-cytokine and multifunctional Th1 responses in children. 
The magnitude of the Th1 cytokine responses induced after 
LAIV receipt was lower than observed in adult subjects after in-
tramuscular vaccination with candidate pandemic vaccines [25,  47]. Differences in the route of administration (intramuscular or 
intranasal) and formulation with the adjuvant in immunologi-
cally naive subjects could partly explain the superiority of the 
parenteral vaccine at inducing a Th1 response in peripheral 
blood. However, in children, LAIV has been shown to be a bet-
ter inducer of T-cell responses than TIV [10, 48, 49]. This may 
explain, at least in part, the higher efficacy of LAIV, compared 
with TIV, in children during head-to-head clinical trials [29]. 
Nonetheless, vaccine-induced long-lived memory CD4 
+ T </p>

<p>cells may provide broader protection and should be a goal of 
novel vaccines [18]. With respect to cytotoxic T cells, we did 
not detect an increase in antigen-specific CD8 
+ T-cell responses </p>

<p>at any time point after LAIV receipt. This is most likely due to 
the use of split virus proteins for in vitro PBMC stimulation, re-
sulting in inefficient antigen cross-presentation to stimulate a 
CD8 
+ T-cell response. </p>

<p>Here, we have demonstrated that LAIV elicits elevated and 
sustained humoral and T-cell responses in young children at 
least 1 year after vaccination and that there is great interstrain 
variation in responses. This was recently addressed by the Ad-
visory Committee on Immunization Practices, which noted that 
the LAIV gave less protection than TIV against the H1N1 strain 
alone [6]. This study provides support to public health officials 
in determining the benefit of their childhood vaccine programs 
when considering safety and obtaining long-lasting immune re-
sponses toward influenza virus. </p>

<p>Supplementary Data </p>

<p>Supplementary materials are available at The Journal of Infectious Diseases 
online (http://jid.oxfordjournals.org). Supplementary materials consist of 
data provided by the author that are published to benefit the reader. The 
posted materials are not copyedited. The contents of all supplementary 
data are the sole responsibility of the authors. Questions or messages regard-
ing errors should be addressed to the author. </p>

<p>Notes </p>

<p>Acknowledgments. We thank the children and parents who participat-
ed in the study; staff at the Ear, Nose, and Throat Department, Haukeland 
University Hospital, Dr Lorentz Sandvik, Dr Ole Gamlemshaug, Dr Per 
Anders Hunderi, Hildegunn Grimstad, Wendela Mathisen, Nina Haugland, 
staff at the Haukeland University Hospital Pediatric Trial Unit (specifically 
Hildur Grindheim, Renate Håpoldøy, Anne Marthe Østerbø, and Marianne 
Heradstveit), and staff at the University of Bergen Influenza Center, for assis-
tance with the clinical trial; Emilia Lohndal, Jane Kristin Nøstbakken, Steinar 
Sørnes and Dagny Ann Sandness for invaluable technical and logistical assis-
tance; and GlaxoSmithKline, for kindly providing the split virus antigen. 
Financial support. This work was supported by the Influenza Center at 
the University of Bergen and the Bergen Clinical Vaccine Consortium. The 
Influenza Center is funded by the Ministry of Health and Care Services, 
Norway, the Norwegian Research Council Globvac program (220670/ 
H10), the European Union (Univax 601738), Helse Vest, and the 
K. G. Jebsen Center for Influenza Vaccines. 
Potential conflicts of interest. All authors: No reported conflicts. 
All authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential 
Conflicts of Interest. Conflicts that the editors consider relevant to the con-
tent of the manuscript have been disclosed. </p>



<p>LAIV Longevity Response • JID 2015:211 (15 May) • 1549 </p>

</text></tei>