<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4950899" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Bone defects are frequently observed and are a significant 
issue in clinical practice. The repair of a bone with extensive 
defects is a complex procedure. Massive bone defects there-
fore constitute a major challenge in reconstructive surgery. 
Currently, methods used to repair bone defects include bone 
autografts, allografts and external fixation (1). 
Although there are several ways to repair articular cartilage 
defects, damage caused by degeneration of articular cartilage, 
trauma and sport-associated injuries does not regenerate (2). 
The rapid development of tissue engineering techniques has 
enabled cartilage and bone regeneration using scaffold mate-
rial and stem cells. A previous study has focused on the role of 
single growth factors in bone tissue engineering (3). However, 
the synergistic effects between various growth factors have 
rarely been reported (4). 
In the present study, beagle bone marrow mesenchymal 
stem cells (BMSCs) were used as seed cells. Once induced, 
BMSCs differentiate into osteoblasts and chondroblasts (5). 
BMSCs were first identified by Fridenshtein (6) and are 
considered to be optimal stem cells for the clinical treat-
ment of bone and cartilage defects, and have received 
widespread attention due to their abundance, ease of access, 
vigorous growth and multi-lineage differentiation (7). The 
present study used platelet-rich plasma (PRP) as a source of 
growth factors. PRP was generated by the resuspension of 
platelets derived from autologous blood at a high concentra-
tion in a low volume of plasma. The platelet count in PRP 
varies according to the preparation technique, ranging from 
two-to several-fold increases above physiological levels (8). 
Activation of platelets in PRP by an agonist, such as thrombin, 
leads to the release of numerous growth factors and other </p>

<p>Use of a biological reactor and platelet-rich plasma 
for the construction of tissue-engineered bone 
to repair articular cartilage defects </p>

<p>HUIBO LI 1 , SHUI SUN 2 , HAILI LIU 2 , HUA CHEN 1 , XIN RONG 1 , JIGANG LOU 1 , 
YUNBEI YANG 1 , YI YANG 1 and HAO LIU 1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Orthopedics, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, Sichuan 610041; </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Orthopedics, Shandong Provincial Hospital Affiliated to Shandong University, 
Jinan, Shandong 250021, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received May 25, 2015; Accepted April 14, 2016 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/etm.2016.3380 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Hao Liu, Department of </p>

<p>Orthopedics, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, 
37 Guoxue Road, Chengdu, Sichuan 610041, P.R. China 
E-mail: liuhao6304@163.com </p>

<p>Key words: bone repair, bone tissue engineering, bone regeneration, </p>

<p>bioreactor, platelet-rich plasma </p>

<p>LI et al: CONSTRUCTION OF TISSUE-ENGINEERED BONE USING A BIOREACTOR AND PLATELET-RICH PLASMA </p>



<p>important proteins, including basic fibroblast growth factor, 
fibronectin, insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1), osteocalcin, 
platelet-derived growth factor, serotonin, transforming growth 
factor-b1, thrombospondin-1, vascular endothelial growth 
factor and Von-Willebrand factor (9). A previous study 
revealed that the application of a single growth factor was not 
sufficient to achieve the desired effect on BMSCs (10). The 
aforementioned proteins and growth factors have confirmed 
efficacy in the osteogenic induction in BMSCs (11). Several 
of these proteins are involved in wound healing and tissue 
regeneration (12-15). 
Tissue engineering scaffolds are 3D substrates that provide 
the structural microenvironment required for the cultivation 
of BMSCs (14). Additionally, tissue engineering scaffolds are 
used in drug delivery, absorbable sutures, surgical orthopedic 
devices and cell tissue engineering applications (15). Porous 
bioceramics, such as β-tricalcium phosphate (β-TCP), are 
excellent scaffolds for tissue engineering; they are easy to 
combine with BMSCs, and are suitable for the repair of bone 
defects in articular cartilage injury (16). In the present study, 
BMSCs and β-TCP scaffolds were used in a perfusion biore-
actor to simulate in vivo conditions that promote cell adhesion, 
proliferation and differentiation. The current study may present 
a novel platform for the generation of tissue-engineered bone 
that is suitable in bone-repair applications. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Animal studies. All animal experimental protocols were 
approved by the local Institutional Animal Care and Use 
Committee of Shandong University (Jinan, China) in compli-
ance with the ̔Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory 
Animals̓ published by the National Academy Press (NIH 
Publication No. 85-23, revised 1996). Male beagles (n=10; 
4-10 months of age), weighing between 8 and 10 kg, were 
obtained from the Experimental Animal Center of Shandong 
Province (Jinan, China) and used in the present study. Animals 
were kept in separate cages with an ambient temperature of 
24˚C and 45% humidity, with a 14 h light/dark cycle, were fed 
a standard diet with ad libitum access to food and water, and 
were allowed to move freely during the study. </p>

<p>Isolation and cultivation of beagle BMSCs. Following the 
administration of 3% pentobarbital sodium (1 ml/kg; Solarbio 
Science &amp; Technology Co., Ltd., Beijing, China), the tibia was 
shaved and treated with 1% povidone iodine solution (Shandong 
Luxi Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd., Heze, China). Bone marrow 
(5 ml) was aspirated with a sterile bone marrow aspiration 
needle attached to a 10 ml syringe containing 1 ml heparin 
solution (Shandong Lukang Pharmaceutical Group, Jining, 
China). Following the addition of an equal volume (5 ml) of 
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) to the bone marrow serum, 
the mixture was homogenized. The aspirate was centrifuged 
at a speed of 168 x g for 5 min at 20˚C. The supernatant was 
removed and the precipitate mixed with an equal volume of 
PBS (5 ml) and homogenized again. The mixture was then 
centrifuged at a speed of 1,048 x g for 20 min at 20˚C and the 
cloudy coat in the centre of the centrifuge tube was harvested. 
This was combined with 5 ml PBS in a centrifuge tube and 
separated at a speed of 2,500 rpm for 5 min. Subsequently, </p>

<p>BMSCs were harvested from the bottom of the centrifuge 
tube. The primary BMSCs were cultured in Dulbecco's 
Modified Eagle's Medium (DMEM; HyClone, Rockford, IL, 
USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco; 
Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., Waltham, MA, USA) at 37˚C, 
in a humidified incubator containing 5% CO 2 . After three 
passages, the BMSCs were divided into osteoblast-and 
chondroblast-induced groups. The osteoblast-induced group 
was cultured in osteogenic differentiation medium containing 
DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 
10 nM dexamethasone, 50 mg/l ascorbic acid and 10 mM 
β-glycerophosphate (Wuhan Boster Biological Technology 
Co., Ltd., Wuhan, China). The chondroblast-induced group 
was cultured in chondrogenesis medium containing TGF-β1 
(10 ng/ml), IGF-1 (50 g/l) and dexamethasone (40 g/l). </p>

<p>Cell identification. Cells were observed using a light 
microscope for morphology and growth status daily. In the 
chondroblast-induced group, type II collagen was detected 
by immunohistochemistry. Antibodies were purchased 
from Wuhan Boster Biological Technology Co., Ltd.. The 
cells were fixed with 3% paraformaldehyde for 10 min and 
rinsed with Tris buffer, pH 7.4, at room temperature for 
5 min. The cells were then incubation with serum (1:20 in 
Tris buffer) at room temperature for 10 min, incubated with 
primary antibodies (anti-collagen II; cat. no. BA0533) in a 
moist chamber overnight at 4˚C, washed with PBS and incu-
bated with biotinylated goat anti-rabbit immunoglobulin G 
secondary antibody (1:50 in Tris buffer; cat. no. BA1003) 
at room temperature for 30 min, washed with PBS and 
incubated with dual system bridge antibodies (1:50 in Tris 
buffer; cat. no. BA1003) for 30 min at room temperature. 
The cells were then washed with PBS and fuscin (Wuhan 
Boster Biological Technology Co., Ltd.) was used for 
staining for 30 min at room temperature. Subsequently, the 
specimens were washed with PBS and dried, covered with 
glycerin/gelatin and examined under a light microscope. In 
the osteoblast-induced group, cells were identified with alka-
line phosphatase (ALP) staining and Alizarin red staining 
(Wuhan Boster Biological Technology Co., Ltd.) to observe 
the activity of ALP and the number of mineral nodules. </p>

<p>3D scaffolds. β-TCP is a porous bio-ceramic 3D scaffold 
purchased from Shanghai Bio-lu Biomaterials Co., Ltd. 
(Shanghai, China). The diameter of the spherical pores was 
500-600 µm and the porosity was 75±10% with &gt;80% of the 
pores being spherical in shape. Using a mold, a cylinder of 
β-TCP 5 mm in diameter and 5 mm in height was constructed. 
The surface of the cylinder was smooth and was sterilized 
using ethylene oxide. </p>

<p>Perfusion bioreactor. The perfusion bioreactor (Fig. 1) was 
designed by the East China University of Science and Tech-
nology (Shanghai, China). The system consists of a peristaltic 
pump, a device which pulls culture media through silicone 
tubes, a perfusion column in which the cell-scaffold composite 
can be implanted, two silicone tubes, an air filter and a flask 
filled with cell culture media. The function of the two silicone 
tubes is to enable the flow of culture media into a peristaltic 
pump via the silicone tubes when the peristaltic pump begins </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL AND THERAPEUTIC MEDICINE 12: 711-719, 2016 </p>



<p>to rotate. This creates a circulatory flow to provide mechanical 
stimulation to the cells. 
PRP was prepared according to a two-step centrifugation 
method as previously described (13). The standard protocol 
involves the preparation of PRP from autologous blood by 
a two-step centrifugation process; a separation step and a 
concentration step (17,18). For the preparation of PRP, ~10 ml 
of blood was obtained from the femoral veins of 10 anes-
thetized (3% pentobarbital sodium) beagles. The blood was 
collected in sterilized tubes containing 1 ml of sodium citrate 
used as an anticoagulant. The blood was then centrifuged 
twice; initially at 20 x g for 16 min at 20˚C to remove red blood 
cells, and then at 1,500 x g for 12 min at 20˚C to obtain the 
platelet pellet (19). The pellet was resuspended in platelet-poor 
plasma and the PRP from the 10 beagles was mixed and stored 
at -80˚C until required, and consequently allogenic PRP was 
used in the subsequent experiments. The PRP was combined 
with 1 ml coagulant (composed of 1 ml 10% CaCl 2 and 
1,000 U thrombin) and homogenized. Platelet-rich plasma gel, 
a jelly-like substance (Fig. 2), was then harvested. </p>

<p>Tissue-engineered bone building. Once the cells had been 
passaged three times, BMSC cell suspensions were prepared 
by trypsin (Wuhan Boster Biological Technology Co., Ltd.) 
digestion prior to the addition to the β-TCP scaffolds. One 
scaffold was prepared with an osteoblast-induced suspension 
and another with a chondroblast-induced suspension. Subse-
quently, 3 ml cell culture media was added to each cultivation 
orifice plate. The BMSC-TCP composites were placed in an 
incubator for 2 days at 37˚C in an atmosphere containing 
5% CO 2 (Fig. 3). The composites were then placed in the 
culture chamber of a perfusion bioreactor with a flow rate of 
3.5 ml/min for 3 weeks using culture media in the presence 
or absence of PRP. The culture medium was changed every 
2-3 days. Adhesion, proliferation and growth of the BMSCs in 
the β-TCP scaffold were examined under a scanning electron 
microscope (SEM). The composites were divided into five 
groups as follows: i) Group A, composite cultured with PRP 
in the bioreactor; ii) Group B, composite cultured with PRP 
without the bioreactor; iii) Group C, composite cultured in 
the bioreactor without PRP; iv) Group D, composite cultured 
without PRP and the bioreactor and v) Group E, β-TCP scaf-
fold only (negative control group). </p>

<p>Surgical procedure. Models of arthrodial cartilage defects 
were established in 20 joints of 10 beagles, with five defects in 
each joint. The beagles were anesthetized with an intravenous 
injection of 3% pentobarbital sodium. A median incision of 
3 cm was made over the knee joints, soft tissues were dissected 
and the bone was exposed by gentle retraction of the muscles. 
Five defects with a depth of 10 mm and a width of 5 mm were 
created in the distal femoral articular surface with a hand 
brace. </p>

<p>Composite implantation. Once the defects had been irrigated 
with sterile physiological saline solution, the BMSC-TCP 
composites were implanted into the defects and press-fitted. 
The osteoblast-induced BMSC-TCP composite (diameter, 
5 mm; height, 5 mm) was implanted into the innermost 
region of the bone defect, and the chondroblast-induced </p>

<p>BMSC-TCP composite of the same dimensions was implanted 
into the remaining shallow region of the bone defect. The 
osteoblast-induced BMSC-TCP composite was mechanically 
forced into contact with the chondroblast-induced composite. 
Following this, muscles, fascia and skin were separately closed </p>

<p>Figure 1. Perfusion bioreactor design used in the present study. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Preparation of platelet-rich plasma. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Cell-scaffold placement into the bioreactor. </p>

<p>LI et al: CONSTRUCTION OF TISSUE-ENGINEERED BONE USING A BIOREACTOR AND PLATELET-RICH PLASMA </p>



<p>over the regions of the defects using 4-0 sterile sutures. The 
animals were kept in standard conditions and were intramus-
cularly injected with 800,000 U penicillin (Wuhan Boster 
Biological Technology Co., Ltd.) each day for 3 consecutive 
days following the surgical procedure. The animals were 
then humanely sacrificed by anesthetic overdose (100 mg/kg) 
with pentobarbital sodium 3 months following the surgical 
procedure and the composites with tissue cells nearby were 
removed in order to perform reverse transcription-quantitative 
polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) and histological 
analysis. </p>

<p>Detection of ALP and BGLAP expression levels using 
RT-qPCR. Template RNA used was from the total RNA of the 
BMSC-TCP composites. Total RNA was isolated using TRIzol 
reagent (Invitrogen; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.), according 
to the manufacturer's instructions. The concentration of RNA 
was determined using an ultraviolet spectrophotometer. 
QIAGEN RNase-Free DNAse was purchased from Cyagen 
Biosciences (Santa Clara, CA, USA). The cDNA sample was 
generated using the RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis 
kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.). Primers sequences used 
in RT-qPCR were as follows: Forward, 5'-TGT GCG GGG 
TCA AGG CTAAC-3'; reverse, 5'-GGC GTC CGA GTA CCA 
GTTGC-3' for ALP; forward, 5'-CTC CTT ACC CGG ATC 
CCCTG3'; reverse, 5'-GTA GAA GCG CTG GTA GGCGT3' 
for BGLAP2. Reaction Buffer, RiboLock RNase Inhibitor, 
dNTP Mix, RevertAid M-MuLV Reverse Transcriptase were 
provided by Cyagen Biosciences Inc.. A negative control was 
included. Quantitative RT-PCR was performed using SYBR 
Green Realtime PCR Master mix (Toyobo, Osaka, Japan) in an 
Applied Biosystems AB7500 real-time PCR system (Applied 
Biosystems; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc.). Amplification was 
performed under the following thermal cycling conditions: 
95˚C for 60 sec followed by 40 cycles at 95˚C for 15 sec and 
60˚C for 60 sec. GADPH was used as a reference gene, and 
the 2 -ΔΔCq method was used (20). RT-qPCR was performed in 
triplicate and the mean ± standard deviation was calculated. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Data are presented as the mean ± standard 
deviation and were analyzed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20.0</rs> 
statistical software package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM SPSS, Armonk, NY, USA</rs>). 
One-way analysis of variance or paired Student's t-tests were 
used for comparisons between groups. P&lt;0.05 was considered 
to indicate a statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Cell culture observation. BMSCs from beagle bone marrow 
were harvested and characterized microscopically in a cell 
culture. Following a culture period of 3 days (Fig. 4A), a 
small number of spindle-shaped primary cells were observed 
growing against the wall of the cell culture flask. Cell colo-
nies formed after 7 days of culture (Fig. 4B). After 7 days of 
culture, the cells gathered into swirl-shaped colonies (Fig. 4C). </p>

<p>Characterization of BMSCs. BMSCs were induced to differen-
tiate into chondroblasts for 7 days. The cells displayed brownish 
yellow cytoplasmic granules following type II collagen immu-
nohistochemical staining (Fig. 5A). Subsequent to 7 days of </p>

<p>osteoblastic differentiation, alkaline phosphatase and Alizarin 
red staining revealed a large quantity of gray-black granules 
or black deposits (Fig. 5B). The aforementioned observations 
are consistent with the initial stem cell phenotype, which 
was further confirmed by the expression of CD29 and CD44 
following differentiation. Alizarin red staining revealed a 
large number of mineral nodes in the osteoblast-induced group 
(Fig. 5C and D). </p>

<p>Examination of composites by SEM. Differentiated BMSCs 
were deposited on β-TCP scaffolds and allowed to grow for 
21 days. SEM revealed that cells adhered to the scaffold and 
were widely distributed, secreting abundant extracellular 
matrix onto the scaffold (Fig. 6). Cell proliferation and a 
stretched, extended morphology was also observed, suggesting 
that the β-TCP scaffold is a good substrate for BMSC growth 
(Fig. 6). </p>

<p>Histological analyses of cartilage regeneration in vivo. Once 
the BMSCs had been cultured for 3 weeks in the bioreactor, 
BMSC scaffolds (Group A) or controls (Groups B-E) were 
implanted into an arthrodial cartilage defect model in beagles 
as described in the Materials and methods section. Histolog-
ical examination demonstrated that several of the implanted 
BMSC scaffolds regenerated cartilage tissue, and filled the 
defective area. Numerous newly differentiated chondrocytes, 
in addition to abundant bone formation, were observed with 
many chondrocytes and osteoblasts present. Osteotylus was 
also observed and this was regularly arranged and dispersed 
throughout the site of the defect (Fig. 7A). 
Several controls (bioreactor, PRP and BMSCs) were 
performed to investigate the importance of each component 
of the culture system. Implantation of BMSCs cultured on 
scaffolds without the bioreactor led to the formation of high 
levels of hyaline chondrocytes and cartilage lacunae, with the 
new cartilage integrating with the existing articular cartilage. 
Conversely, in Group A, new bone was not evenly distributed 
and the quantity of hyaline chondrocytes was reduced (Fig. 7B). 
In Group C, in which BMSCs were cultured in the absence 
of PRP, irregular, newly-formed osteotylus was present in the 
defect, and chondrocytes and osteoblasts were randomly and 
loosely arranged (Fig. 7C). In the absence of both PRP and 
the bioreactor (Group D), a small number of newly-generated 
chondrocytes and osteoblasts were detected in the defect. New 
bone formation was minimal, with abundant fibrous tissues 
infiltrating the damaged area (Fig. 7D). In the negative control 
with no BMSCs (Group E), several fibroblasts were observed 
to adhere to adjacent tissue on the defect border, resulting in 
the proliferation of fibrous and scar tissue (Fig. 7E). </p>

<p>Expression levels of osteogenic differentiation markers in 
BMSC implants. The expression levels of osteogenic differ-
entiation markers, ALP and BGLAP, in BMSC implants was 
determined by RT-qPCR (Fig. 8). In experimental Groups A, 
B, C and D, the expression levels of ALP and BGLAP were 
significantly higher compared with the negative control 
group (Group E; P&lt;0.05). The expression levels of ALP and 
BGLAP were significantly higher in Group A compared with 
Group C (P&lt;0.05) and in Group B compared with Group D 
(P&lt;0.05). These results therefore suggested that the presence </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL AND THERAPEUTIC MEDICINE 12: 711-719, 2016 </p>



<p>of PRP promotes bone regeneration. The expression levels of 
ALP were not significantly higher in Group A compared with 
Group B, or in Group C compared with Group D, (Group A </p>

<p>compared with Group B, t=0.169, P&gt;0.05; Group C compared 
with Group D, t=0.646, P&gt;0.05). The present data supports the 
hypothesis of an osteogenic promoting effect of the bioreactor. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Bone marrow stem cells from beagle bone marrow (A) 3 days after seeding, (B) primary cells cultured for 7 days, and (C) 7 days following subculture 
(magnification, x100). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Type II collagen immunohistochemical staining. (A) In the chondroblast-induced group, the cells displayed brownish yellow granules in the cyto-
plasm following type II collagen immunohistochemical staining (magnification, x200). (B) In the osteoblast-induced group (magnification, x200), gray-black 
granules or black deposit were observed in the (C) cytoplasm (magnification, x200) and (D) Alizarin red staining revealed a large number of mineral nodes in 
the osteoblast-induced group (magnification, x400). </p>

<p>Figure 6. (A) Scanning electron microscopy showed the structure of the β-tricalcium phosphate scaffold. (B) Scanning electron microscopy revealed good 
adhesion and distribution of beagle bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells on the β-tricalcium phosphate scaffold. (magnification, x5,000). </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>LI et al: CONSTRUCTION OF TISSUE-ENGINEERED BONE USING A BIOREACTOR AND PLATELET-RICH PLASMA </p>



<p>Figure 7. Histological staining revealing cartilage defects following implantation of BMSC scaffolds. The tissue samples were sectioned and stained with 
hematoxylin and eosin. (A) BMSCs cultured on scaffolds in the presence of PRP in a bioreactor. (B) BMSCs cultured on scaffolds without the use of the 
bioreactor. (C) BMSCs cultured in the bioreactor without PRP. (D) BMSCs cultured in the absence of the bioreactor or PRP. (E) Negative controls: Scaffold 
with no BMSCs. BMSCs, bone marrow stem cells; PRP, platelet-rich plasma. </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Figure 8. Gene expression levels of (A) ALP and (B) BGLAP2 were detected in the various experimental groups using reverse transcription-quantitative 
polymerase chain reaction. * P&lt;0.05 vs. control group (group E); # P&lt;0.05. Group A, BMSCs cultured with PRP in the bioreactor; Group B, BMSCs cultured 
with PRP without the use of the bioreactor; Group C, BMSCs cultured in the bioreactor without PRP; Group D, BMSCs cultured without PRP or use of the 
bioreactor; Group E, β-tricalcium phosphate scaffold only. ALP, alkaline phosphatase; BGLAP2, bone γ-carboxyglutamate protein 2; ALP, alkaline phospha-
tase; BGLAP2, bone γ-carboxyglutamate protein; BMSC, bone marrow stem cell; PRP, platelet-rich plasma. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL AND THERAPEUTIC MEDICINE 12: 711-719, 2016 </p>



<p>Consequently, a novel method for the efficient generation of 
tissue-engineered cells for the repair of bone defects has been 
developed in the present study. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, we proposed that addition PRP and use 
of a bioreactor for the generation of BMSCs on scaffolds 
would enhance the healing process of osteochondral defects. 
Tissue-engineered bone was constructed by co-culturing 
BMSCs and β-TCP scaffolds in a 3D perfusion bioreactor. The 
present study revealed that BMSCs, PRP, β-TCP scaffolds and 
the use of a bioreactor had positive effects on bone formation 
and were able to enhance the healing of osteochondral defects. 
In the present study, autologous PRP was used as a cyto-
kine source to promote bone formation. PRP is a concentrate 
of platelets in a small volume of plasma. Once activated by an 
agonist, growth factors contained in platelets may be released 
and exert their biological functions. The initial clinical study 
using PRP for bone reconstruction therapy was performed by 
Marx et al (17). In this randomized study, 88 patients with 
mandibular defects were treated with autogenous cancellous 
bone grafts with or without the addition of activated PRP. 
Both the radiographic and the histomorphometric evaluation 
revealed a significantly greater percentage of bone gener-
ated in the presence of PRP (17). PRP therefore appears to 
exert a positive effect in the early phase of bone healing in 
combination with autogenous cancellous bone grafts (21-23), 
and in diabetic fracture healing (24). Other studies support 
the hypothesis that PRP has the ability to promote bone 
healing (25,26) and strongly advocate its use in bone regen-
erative therapy (27,28). The identification of the potential of 
PRP in the promotion of bone regeneration in recent years 
has generated a novel field of research in orthopedics. The 
effect of PRP in the treatment of periodontal intrabony defects 
in humans has also been investigated (29) and its beneficial 
effects in both periodontal and cosmetic surgical procedures 
have been suggested (30-32). In vitro studies have demonstrated 
the effects of platelet concentration on the proliferation and 
differentiation of primary osteoblasts and fibroblasts (33,34). 
In two other in vivo studies (35,36), goat PRP was prepared 
and activated with bovine thrombin and calcium chloride. 
PRP is currently used clinically in several countries and cura-
tive effects have been achieved (36). In addition, it has been 
demonstrated that PRP may enhance the healing of osteo-
chondral defects and that the benefits may be detected at early 
stages of the healing process (37,38). Froum et al (39) observed 
histomorphometric differences in bone regeneration among 
the samples of three surgical cases. Another study examining 
human PRP demonstrated upregulation of collagen synthesis 
in osteoblasts (39). Growth factors and BMSCs attract other 
progenitor cells or osteoclasts, and therefore initiate bone 
remodeling (40,41). It is accepted that, subsequent to a bone 
injury, growth factors and host precursors are released (42). 
In addition, cell adhesion to extracellular matrices is essential 
in the development, maintenance and remodeling of osseous 
tissues (42,43). The extracellular matrix component released 
by platelets is fibronectin, and the latter mediates adhesive 
interactions and has a central role in osteoblast survival, 
proliferation, differentiation and matrix mineralization, in </p>

<p>addition to bone formation (44-46). The degranulation of 
PRP and release of growth factors may be achieved by the 
addition of thrombin in the presence of calcium chloride or 
by thawing the platelets (47). Studies have demonstrated that, 
in this combination, calcium sulfate acts as an activator of 
platelets and also as a delivery system for the platelet-released 
growth factors (48,49). Therefore, it may be concluded that the 
endogenous growth factors released by platelets promote the 
healing process. 
In a previous study performed by the authors (50), BMSCs 
were used as seed cells and β-TCP was used as a scaffold 
material, and a tissue-engineered osteochondral composite 
was successfully constructed in a perfusion bioreactor. This 
composite was used in the repair of osteochondral defects in 
beagles. It was found that certain grafts did not completely 
integrate into the areas of bone cartilage defects, indicating 
that the constructed osteochondral composite was not 
completely vascularized. In the present study, in the process 
of bone construction in the three-dimensional perfusion 
bioreactor, autologous PRP was used as a cytokine source 
to promote bone formation and vascularization. Autologous 
PRP is a convenient, economical and sustainable source of 
high-quality cytokines. The novel method for constructing 
tissue-engineered bone using BMSCs, β-TCP scaffolds and 
PRP can construct efficient tissue-engineered bone for carti-
lage repair. 
A porous bio-ceramic 3D scaffold constructed of β-TCP 
was used in the present study for its favorable mechanical 
strength, high porosity ratio and ease of processing and 
molding. SEM displayed good adhesion and distribution of 
BMSCs on the β-TCP scaffold. Concurrently, extracellular 
matrix secretion was observed on the scaffold. Favorable cell 
proliferation and morphology was also detected using SEM, 
suggesting that the β-TCP scaffold has a high affinity for 
BMSCs. In brief, β-TCP scaffolds display several benefits in 
tissue engineering which as as follows: i) The β-TCP scaffold 
is able to provide a 3D space that may support BMSC growth, 
expose cells to shear force and improve unit expansion rate, 
thus promoting the differentiation of cartilage and bone; ii) a 
3D structure may improve the biocompatibility of scaffolds 
and promote adhesion of BMSCs; iii) bone inducing growth 
factors will be gradually released by β-TCP in the process of 
cell culture due to the characteristics of the material. Overall, 
the β-TCP scaffold may be able to synchronously improve all 
three of the basic components required for bone and cartilage 
engineering. However, although the present study indicates 
that the β-TCP scaffold is an efficient biomaterial for BMSC 
adhesion and chondrogenic and osteogenic differentiation, 
further animal experiments are necessary to fully assess the 
scaffolds. 
The present study indicated that the use of a bioreactor 
and PRP was able to synergistically enhance cell prolifera-
tion and biosynthetic responses on scaffolds. Cell behavior is 
influenced by shear stress, tension and hydrostatic pressure 
stimulation. The continuous mechanical stimulation provided 
by the bioreactor, including shear stress stimulation, tension 
stimulation and hydrostatic pressure stimulation has effects on 
the morphology and function of BMSCs (51,52). In the present 
study, BMSCs were cultured on a 3D scaffold in a perfusion 
bioreactor, a culture model that possesses several advantages </p>

<p>LI et al: CONSTRUCTION OF TISSUE-ENGINEERED BONE USING A BIOREACTOR AND PLATELET-RICH PLASMA </p>



<p>compared with traditional planar 2D culture models. Firstly, it 
may provide mechanical stimulation to the BMSCs promoting 
their functionality. Secondly, the use of a bioreactor improves 
the distribution of nutrients within the scaffold. In addition, 
using the bioreactor provided a 3D growth environment, which 
promotes cell adhesion, growth and differentiation simultane-
ously, thereby reducing the effect of contact inhibition between 
the cells. Furthermore, the culture medium in a 3D bioreactor 
does not need to be replaced frequently, while the medium in a 
traditional 2D cell culture model requires intermittent replace-
ment. The predominant advantage of the system is a result of 
the mechanical stimulation provided by the flowing fluid that 
may synergistically enhance cell proliferation and biosynthetic 
response on scaffolds, which is able to simulate a cell stress 
environment highly similar to that observed in vivo (51-53). 
In addition, cells may be fully combined with, or adhered to, 
the scaffold materials in the bioreactor, making cell culture 
closer to physiologic 3D growth (54,55). The fluid shear stress 
provided by the bioreactor has a range of effects on cellular 
morphological and functional organization. It has previously 
been established that the fluid shear stress provided by a 
bioreactor is able to enhance the proliferation of MSCs (56). 
Notably, in the present study, it was revealed that PRP and the 
application of mechanical stimulation resulted in a greater 
number of cells and total collagen present on scaffolds after 
21 days, compared with the use of PRP alone. The aforemen-
tioned findings suggested that mechanical stimulation is able 
to synergistically enhance cell proliferation and biosynthetic 
response on scaffolds. In addition, mechanical stimulation 
maintained the expression levels of ALP and BGLAP, the 
most important indicators of osteogenic differentiation (57). 
ALP has a critical role in the calcification process and has 
been used as a conventional marker of early osteoblast differ-
entiation. BGLAP predominately appears in the mineralized 
formation as an indicator of osteoblast maturation. The expres-
sion levels of ALP and BGLAP therefore reflect the process of 
bone formation. 
In conclusion, BMSCs, PRP, β-TCP scaffolds and the 
use of a bioreactor all had positive effects on bone forma-
tion. In the present study, a novel method for constructing 
tissue-engineered bone using BMSCs, β-TCP scaffolds and 
PRP was assessed. The tissue-engineered bone constructed 
using this method displayed active biologic characteristics in 
morphology and in function, and may therefore provide an 
improved approach for the repair of osteochondral defects. 
The novel method for constructing tissue-engineered 
bone using BMSCs, β-TCP scaffolds and PRP detailed in the 
present study, will initiate the design and building of increas-
ingly efficient tissue-engineered bone for cartilage repair. </p>



<p>EXPERIMENTAL AND THERAPEUTIC MEDICINE 12: 711-719, 2016 </p>





</text></tei>