<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4103605" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:32+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>• Premise of the study: Microsatellite primers were developed for the cardon, a giant columnar cactus ( Pachycereus pringlei ) 
of the Sonoran Desert, to investigate intraspecifi c genetic patterns of diversity and population structure. 
• Methods and Results: Using 454 GS-FLX technology and bioinformatics tools, microsatellite primers were successfully identi-
fi ed on 282 reads, including di-, tri-, tetra-, penta-, and hexanucleotides. A set of 10 primers were characterized on 80 individu-
als collected in two areas of the Baja California peninsula, Mexico. All 10 loci were polymorphic, with a mean of 6.3 alleles 
per locus and overall levels of observed and expected heterozygosities ranging from 0.41 to 0.59 and from 0.40 to 0.57, respectively. 
Alleles per individual plant ranged from one to four, suggesting a polyploidal genome. 
• Conclusions: These loci should be useful for future investigations of population structure, genetic diversity, and gene fl ow in 
the cardon cactus. </p>



<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2014 2 ( 2 ): 1300066 
Gutiérrez Flores et al.-Pachycereus pringlei microsatellites 
doi:10.3732/apps.1300066 </p>

<p>http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>Favoring larger motif (repetition numbers) and lower melting temperature 
differences between pairs of primers, we selected 38 loci for PCR amplifi cation 
and a banding pattern of 10 cacti samples collected at El Comitán near La Paz 
(23.985 ° N, 110.187 ° W). Total DNA was extracted from cortex tissue, using the 
modifi ed CTAB procedure mentioned earlier. PCR reactions were performed in 
10-μ L volumes using a thermocycler (ICycler, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, 
California, USA). Each reaction contained 50 ng of DNA, 0.2 mM of each 
dNTP (no. 18427-088, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California, USA), 0.4 μ M of each 
primer (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, California, USA), 1 × PCR buffer 
(20 mM Tris-HCl, 50 mM KCl [pH 8.4]), 1-2.5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.4 U Taq DNA 
polymerase (no. 11615-010, Invitrogen), and 0.1 mg mL −1 of bovine serum albu-
min (BSA; no. B90015, New England Biolabs, Ipswich, Massachusetts, USA). 
Cycling conditions included initial denaturation at 94 ° C for 5 min, 30 cycles at 
94 ° C for 1 min each, 45 s at the locus-specifi c annealing temperature (see Table 1 
and Appendix S1), extension at 72 ° C for 1 min, and a fi nal extension at 72 ° C for 
25 min. PCR products were visualized by silver staining in 6% polyacrylamide 
(Bio-Rad Laboratories), 7.5 M urea, and a 10-bp ladder (Invitrogen). Results of 
PCR amplifi cation of the 38 pairs of primers are given in Appendix S1. 
Ten of the 38 primer pairs yielded distinct bands in the expected size range; 
consistent amplifi cation patterns and fewer stutter bands were selected for char-
acterization in 40 individuals that were sampled at El Comitán and 40 that were </p>

<p>sequenced using 454 pyrosequencing with the GS-FLX titanium platform 
(Roche Diagnostics, Basel, Switzerland), along with seven other species. The 
alignments were run according to the barcode plate strategy, as outlined in the 
GS-FLX Shotgun DNA Library Preparation Method Manual (supplied by 
Roche Diagnostics, Roche Applied Science, Mannheim, Germany). 
All 454 reads were fi rst converted from fl owgrams to FASTA and FASTA-
qual fi les without 454 adapters, using the <rs id="software-7" type="software">sff_extract</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="url">http://bioinf.comav.upv.es/sff_extract/index.html</rs>). We found 398,286 sequence reads with 
an average read length of 274 bp from two independent runs. MSATCOM-
MANDER software ( Faircloth, 2008 ) was used to identify perfect microsatel-
lites containing at least fi ve repeat units for dinucleotides and four for tri-, 
tetra-, penta-, and hexanuclotides. Perfect microsatellite motifs were found in 
10,685 (2.6%) reads, of which dinucleotide repeats were most abundant (62%), 
followed by trinucleotide repeats (31%), and tetranucleotide repeats (6%). 
Using <rs id="software-9" type="software">Primer</rs><rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">3</rs> software ( <rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Rozen and Skaletsky</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-date">2000</rs> ) embedded in the <rs id="software-10" type="software">QDD</rs> 
software ( <rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Meglécz et al.</rs>., <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-date">2010</rs> ), primer design was possible in 282 reads, with 
the following parameters: (1) melting temperatures 50-70 ° C, (2) PCR product 
between 90 and 320 bp, (3) GC content &gt;40%, (4) primer length between 17 
and 27 nucleotides, (5) primer self-complementarities and complement between 
them fulfi ll the quality criteria used as default parameters in the Primer3 
software. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Characteristics of 10 microsatellite loci developed for the cardon cactus, Pachycereus pringlei . </p>

<p>Locus 
Primer sequences (5 ′ -3 ′ ) 
Repeat motif 
T a ( ° C) 
Size range (bp) 
GenBank accession no. </p>

<p>Ppri01 
F: GCGAGGGTGTCTCAAATGAT 
(CT) 12 
58 
202-223 
KC349892 
R: TAATCCCCTCCCACCTAACC 
Ppri02 
F: TTCCATCGTCCCCTCACTTA 
(AG) 11 
66 
115-119 
KC349893 
R: CATTCACCACCGTGAACACT 
Ppri03 
F: GGTGTTCCTCGCTCTCATTC 
(CT) 11 
65 
133-155 
KC349894 
R: CTCGCAAATCCAAGCAAAAT 
Ppri04 
F: TTCAAATCATTCAATAAAACAAGAGC 
(TC) 13 
63 
96-112 
KC349895 
R: ATGGAGGTCGAGGATCAAGA 
Ppri05 
F: AAACTGCAGGTGTTTCAGGG 
(GTTT) 8 
61 
166-186 
KC349896 
R: AATGAAGCGAAAGGAAGCAA 
Ppri06 
F: GCTCACGTTGGCAGATTTGT 
(AAAT) 6 
50 
138-146 
KC349897 
R: GGTGATGACAAAAGGTTTTGC 
Ppri07 
F: TGGACTTCCAAGGGATAATGA 
(AAAT) 8 
59 
127-143 
KC349898 
R: TCAACTCAAAGTGTCAGTGCTG 
Ppri08 
F: AATAGCGCATGCCTCAAAGG 
(CT) 8 (CTTT) 2 
66 
109-126 
KC349899 
R: CAATAGTCCAGAAATAGGTCAGGTCA 
Ppri09 
F: AAGAGACAGGCCCTGAGACA 
(TC) 10 
68 
119-140 
KC349900 
R: TCGTAGGTTCCATCACCACA 
Ppri10 
F: TTCTCGAAGCCCCGCTTAC 
(GATA) 6 (GACA) 3 
64 
79-107 
KC349901 
R: GCACGTCAAAGATGCAAGCA </p>

<p>Note : T a = annealing temperature. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Genetic diversity of the 10 microsatellite loci developed from the cardon cactus, Pachycereus pringlei . a </p>

<p>El Comitán ( n = 40) 
Punta Prieta ( n = 40) 
Both areas ( n = 80) </p>

<p>Locus 
A 
A I 
H o 
H e 
A 
A I 
H o 
H e 
A </p>

<p>Ppri01 
7 
1-4 
0.67 
0.68 
3 
1-3 
0.38 
0.35 
9 
Ppri02 
2 
1-2 
0.13 
0.39 
3 
1-3 
0.85 
0.63 
3 
Ppri03 
10 
1-4 
0.78 
0.77 
5 
1-4 
0.67 
0.72 
11 
Ppri04 
9 
1-4 
0.77 
0.77 
7 
1-4 
0.74 
0.68 
9 
Ppri05 
5 
1-3 
0.43 
0.57 
3 
1-3 
0.31 
0.35 
6 
Ppri06 
3 
1-2 
0.73 
0.45 
2 
1-2 
0.03 
0.03 
3 
Ppri07 
4 
1-2 
0.75 
0.48 
3 
1-3 
0.68 
0.58 
5 
Ppri08 
4 
1-2 
0.35 
0.37 
2 
1-2 
0.03 
0.03 
5 
Ppri09 
5 
1-3 
0.51 
0.61 
3 
1-2 
0.05 
0.05 
5 
Ppri10 
5 
1-3 
0.74 
0.65 
6 
1-4 
0.40 
0.54 
7 
Mean 
5.5 
0.59 
0.57 
3.7 
0.41 
0.40 
6.3 </p>

<p>Note : A = number of alleles per locus; A I = number of alleles per locus in an individual plant; H e = expected heterozygosity; H o = observed heterozygosity; 
n = number of individuals sampled. 
a Locality information for populations: El Comitán, Baja California Sur, Mexico (23.985 ° N, 110.187 ° W); Punta Prieta, Ensenada, Baja California, 
Mexico (29.063 ° N, 114.155 ° W). </p>

<p>Applications in Plant Sciences 2014 2 ( 2 ): 1300066 </p>

<p>Gutiérrez Flores et al.-Pachycereus pringlei microsatellites 
doi:10.3732/apps.1300066 </p>

<p> 
http://www.bioone.org/loi/apps </p>

<p>sampled at Punta Prieta, Ensenada, Baja California (29.063 ° N, 114.155 ° W). 
Duplicate samples of each individual were stored in 96% ethanol at the Labo-
ratorio de Genética para la Conservación at CIBNOR . PCR reactions were 
performed, as described above, using optimized primer-specifi c annealing 
temperatures ( Table 1 ), magnesium chloride, and forward-labeled primers 
(5 ′ end-labeled with FAM, NED, PET, and VIC; Applied Biosystems). Individu-
als were genotyped by assessing allele size on a genetic analyzer (model 310, 
Applied Biosystems), using the GeneScan 600 LIZ Size Standard (<rs corresp="#software-12" type="creator">Applied Biosystems</rs>) and <rs id="software-12" type="software">GeneMapper</rs> <rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-number">4.1</rs> software (Applied Biosystems). 
Locus designation, primer sequences, repeat motifs, annealing temperatures, 
PCR product sizes, and GenBank accession numbers are listed in Table 1 . All 
10 loci were polymorphic, exhibiting two to 10 alleles per locus (mean A = 5.5) 
among cacti from El Comitán, and two to seven alleles per locus (mean A = 3.7) 
among cacti from Punta Prieta. Alleles per individual plant ranged from one to 
four in both populations, suggesting a polyploidal genome ( Table 2 ) . 
Observed heterozygosity was estimated in <rs type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> (Microsoft Cor-
poration, Redmond, Washington, USA). Expected heterozygosity was esti-
mated in <rs type="software">ATETRA</rs> software for tetraploid species that account for all possible 
combinations of allele copy numbers in populations with partial heterozygotes 
( Van Puyvelde et al., 2010 ). Genetic diversity in terms of heterozygosity varied 
from low to high across loci in both populations. Observed heterozygosity 
ranged from 0.13 to 0.78 (mean H o = 0.59) and expected heterozygosity ranged 
from 0.37 to 0.77 (mean H e = 0.57) at El Comitán. At Punta Prieta, observed 
heterozygosity ranged from 0.03 to 0.85 (mean H o = 0.41) and expected 
heterozygosity ranged from 0.03 to 0.72 (mean H e = 0.40) ( Table 2 ). For this 
study, we assumed tetraploidy in both populations because we observed as 
many as four alleles per locus in individual plants. Our results are also consis-
tent with a tetrasomic pattern of inheritance previously suggested in P. pringlei , 
based on an allozymatic study ( Murawski et al., 1994 ) and a chromosome 
counting study ( Pinkava et al., 1973 ). </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The 10 microsatellites are the fi rst to be developed for the 
cardon cactus, P. pringlei , and the genus Pachycereus . These 
polymorphic loci will be useful in studies of genetic diversity 
and genetic population differentiation and provide valuable in-
formation to understand the importance of biotic and abiotic 
factors involved in geographic variation in the genetic pool of 
this widespread cactus of the Sonoran Desert. </p>

<p>LITERATURE CITED </p>



</text></tei>