<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4642173" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A B S T R A C T </p>

<p>In this article, a novel derivative-free (DF) surrogate-based trust region optimization approach 
is proposed. In the proposed approach, quadratic surrogate models are constructed and succes-
sively updated. The generated surrogate model is then optimized instead of the underlined 
objective function over trust regions. Truncated conjugate gradients are employed to find the 
optimal point within each trust region. The approach constructs the initial quadratic surrogate 
model using few data points of order O(n), where n is the number of design variables. The pro-
posed approach adopts weighted least squares fitting for updating the surrogate model instead 
of interpolation which is commonly used in DF optimization. This makes the approach more 
suitable for stochastic optimization and for functions subject to numerical error. The weights 
are assigned to give more emphasis to points close to the current center point. The accuracy 
and efficiency of the proposed approach are demonstrated by applying it to a set of classical 
bench-mark test problems. It is also employed to find the optimal design of RF cavity linear 
accelerator with a comparison analysis with a recent optimization technique. 
ª 2014 Production and hosting by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of Cairo University. </p>

<p>In general, engineering systems are characterized by some 
designable parameters and some performance measures. The 
desired performance of a system (design specifications) is 
described by specifying bounds on the performance measures </p>

<p>of the system which is set by the designer. The conventional 
system design aims at finding values of the system designable 
parameters that merely satisfy the design specifications. In gen-
eral, there will be a multitude of acceptable designs. However, 
for contemporary engineering design, other criterion (objective 
function) can be chosen for comparing the different alternative 
acceptable designs (optimization problem) and for selecting 
the best one (optimal system design). Naturally, system perfor-
mance measures and the objective functions are functions of 
system parameters values and evaluated through system simu-
lations. For intensive CPU engineering systems, the high 
expense of the required system simulations may obstruct the 
optimization process. </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Tel.: +20 1001518506. 
E-mail address: aashiry@ieee.org (A.S.A. Mohamed). 
Peer review under responsibility of Cairo University. </p>

<p>Production and hosting by Elsevier </p>

<p>Journal of Advanced Research (2015) 6, 915-924 </p>

<p>Cairo University </p>

<p>Journal of Advanced Research </p>

<p>2090-1232 ª 2014 Production and hosting by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of Cairo University. 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jare.2014.08.009 </p>

<p>In practice, robust optimization methods that utilize the 
fewest possible number of function evaluations are greatly 
required [1,2]. Another difficulty is the absence of any gradient 
information as the required simulations cost in evaluating the 
gradient information is prohibitive in practice [3]. Attempting 
to approximate the function gradients using the finite differ-
ence approach requires much more function evaluations, 
which highly increase the computational cost. Another objec-
tion in estimating the gradients by finite differencing is that 
the estimated function values are usually contaminated by 
some numerical noise due to estimation uncertainty. Hence, 
gradient-based optimization methods cannot be applied here. 
For such optimization problems, only derivative free opti-
mization (DFO) methods can be applicable [1,4-7]. Further, 
the derivative free trust region methods usually handle such 
problems more efficiently as the trust region framework consti-
tutes one of the most important globally convergent optimiza-
tion methods, which has the ability to converge to a solution 
starting from any arbitrary initial point [8]. In addition, these 
methods use computationally cheap surrogate-based models 
that can be constructed by using function evaluations at some 
selected points. These surrogate models may be response sur-
faces, radial basis method, neural networks, kriging, etc. 
The majority of the existing derivative-free trust region 
techniques have the following features: </p>

<p>They require a relatively large number of function evalua-
tions, O(n 
2 ) (where n is the number of system design 
variables) to construct the initial quadratic model. 
The quadratic surrogate models are constructed via interpo-
lating the objective function at a constant number of points; 
when a point is obtained a previous point is dropped. In 
addition, these algorithms usually ignore the valuable infor-
mation contained in all previously evaluated expensive 
function values. </p>

<p>The work presented in this article introduces a new deriva-
tive free trust region approach that neither require nor approx-
imate the gradients of the objective function. It implements a 
non-derivative optimization method that combine a trust 
region framework with quadratic fitting surrogates for the 
objective function [4,5]. The principal operation of the method 
relies on building, successively updating and optimizing qua-
dratic surrogate models of the objective function over trust 
regions. The quadratic surrogate models reasonably reflect 
the local behavior of the objective function in a trust region 
around the current iterate and they are optimized instead of 
the objective function over trust regions. 
Truncated conjugate gradient method by Steihaug [9] is 
used to find the optimal point within each trust region. The 
approach constructs the initial quadratic surrogate model 
using few data points of order O(n). In each iteration of the 
proposed approach, the surrogate model is updated using a 
weighted least squares fitting. The weights are assigned to give 
more emphasis to points close to the current center point. The 
accuracy and efficiency of the proposed approach are demon-
strated by applying it on a set of classical benchmark test prob-
lems and comparisons with a recent optimization technique [6] 
are also included. 
The linear accelerators (LINACS) provide beams of high 
quality and high energy in which charged particles move on 
a linear path and are accelerated by electromagnetic fields. </p>

<p>The modern LINAC typically consists of sections of specially 
designed waveguides that are excited by RF electromagnetic 
fields, usually in the very high frequency (VHF) range. The 
accelerating structures are tuned to resonance and are driven 
by external, high-power RF power tubes, such as klystrons. 
The accelerating structures must efficiently transfer the electro-
magnetic energy to the beam, and this is accomplished through 
an optimized configuration of the internal geometry, so that 
the structure can concentrate the electric field along the trajec-
tory of the beam promoting maximal energy transfer, by add-
ing nose cones to create a region of more concentrated axial 
electric field as shown in Fig. 1. RF cavity analysis and design 
brought researchers and engineers' attention due to its exten-
sive applications [10-17]. Applications include: medicinal pur-
poses in radiation therapy, food sterilization and transmute 
nuclear fuel waste, etc. Design tools include: the computer 
code SUPERFISH [18], 3-D code MAFIA [19] and CST 
Studio Suite [20]. 
Design of accelerator RF cavities may include optimization 
of some of cavity parameters. Among the parameters charac-
terizing the operation of the RF cavities are, the average accel-
erating field Eacc, peak fields to accelerating field (Epk/Eacc, 
Hpk/Eacc), quality factor, and cavity shunt impedance R-shunt 
[21]. The parameters considered for optimization depend on the 
power level fed to the cavity, which limit the average accelerat-
ing field, where the constraints on these parameters are imposed 
by the application. For low power level feed, optimization may 
focus on maximizing shunt impedance, however for high power 
operation, limiting the peak fields inside is of concern in order 
to minimize multipacting [22]. In this work we will focus on the 
low power fed cavities, where maximizing the shunt impedance 
is of main concern and will be treated through our new optimi-
zation approach. 
The new proposed trust region (TR) optimization approach 
is capable of solving the design problems with either 2D or 3D 
simulators. It is expected to work as well if a 3D simulator was 
employed with the expense of more computational time. Most 
of the accelerators use body of revolution cavity structure 
which can be solved as 2D structure, saving the computational 
resources. However, the proposed approach was successfully 
employed in microwave filter design utilizing 3D full-wave 
EM solver [23]. </p>

<p>The new trust region approach </p>

<p>The computationally expensive objective function is locally 
approximated around a current iterate x k by a computation-
ally cheaper quadratic surrogate model M(x) which can be 
placed in the form: </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Cross section of the cavity with nose cones and spherical 
outer walls. </p>

<p> 
A.S.O. Hassan et al. </p>

<p>MðxÞ ¼ a þ b 
T ðx À x k Þ þ 
1 
2 
ðx À x k Þ 
T Bðx À x k Þ; 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where a 2 R, the vector b 2 R 
n , and the symmetric matrix 
B 2 R 
nÂn are the unknown parameters of M(x). The total num-
ber of the model parameters is q = (n + 1)(n + 2)/2. These 
parameters can be evaluated by interpolating the objective 
function at q points. </p>

<p>Initial model </p>

<p>Let x 0 be the initial point that is provided by the user. Initially, 
assuming that B is a diagonal matrix, then the number of 
points required to construct the initial model is m = 2n + 1 
[7]. The initial m points x i , i = 1, 2, . . ., m, can be chosen as 
follows [6,24] </p>

<p>x 1 ¼ x 0 and 
x iþ1 ¼ x 0 þ D 1 e i ; 
i ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; n 
x iþnþ1 ¼ x 0 À D 1 e i ; i ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; m À n À 1 </p>



<p>; </p>

<p>ð2Þ </p>

<p>where D 1 is the initial trust region radius that is provided by 
the user, and e i is the ith coordinate vector in R 
n . 
The initial quadratic model M </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(x) will have the parame-
ters a </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>, the vector b 
(1) , and the n diagonal elements of the 
model Hessian matrix B 
(1) . These parameters are computed 
by requiring that the initial model interpolates the objective 
function f(x) at the initial m points given in (2). Therefore 
the initial model parameters are obtained by satisfying the 
matching conditions: </p>

<p>M 
ð1Þ ðx i Þ ¼ fðx i Þ; i ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; m: 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>Model optimization </p>

<p>At the kth iteration, assume that x k is the current solution 
point. The model M </p>

<p>(k) </p>

<p>(x) is then minimized, in place of the 
objective function, over the current trust region and a new 
point is produced by solving the trust region sub-problem: </p>

<p>min s M 
ðkÞ ðsÞ; subject to ksk D k ; 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>where s = x À x k , D k is the current trust region radius, and k Á k 
throughout is the l 2 -norm. This problem is solved by the method 
of truncated conjugate gradient by Steihaug [9]. It is identical as 
the standard conjugate gradient method as long as the iterates 
are inside the trust region. If the conjugate gradient method ter-
minates at a point within the trust region, this point is a global 
minimizer of the objective function. If the new iterate is outside 
the trust region, a truncated step which is on the region bound-
ary is considered. Also, the method treats the case where the 
minimum is in the opposite direction of the conjugate direction 
which is due to the non convexity of the model [9]. One good 
property of this method is that the solution computed has a suf-
ficient reduction property, which was proved by Bandler and 
Abdel-Malek [25]. 
Let s 
* denotes the solution of (4), and then a new point 
x n = x k + s 
* is obtained. The achieved actual reduction in the 
objective function is compared to that predicted reduction using 
the model by computing the reduction ratio which is given by: </p>

<p>r k ¼ 
actual reduction 
predicted reduction 
¼ 
fðx k Þ À fðx n Þ 
M 
ðkÞ ðx k Þ À M 
ðkÞ ðx n Þ 
: 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>This ratio reflects how much the surrogate model agrees 
with the objective function within the trust region. The trust 
region radius and the current iterate will be updated such that, 
if r k is sufficiently high, i.e., r k P 0.7, there is a good agreement 
between the model and the objective function over this step. 
Hence, it is beneficial to expand the trust region for the next 
iteration, and to use x n as the new center of the trust region. 
If r k is positive but not close to 1, i.e., 0.1 6 r k &lt; 0.7, the trust 
region radius is not altered. On the other hand, if r k is smaller 
than a certain threshold, r k &lt; 0.1, the trust region radius is 
reduced. The updating formula used for updating D k and x k 
can be expressed as follows: </p>

<p>r k </p>

<p>r k &lt; 0:1 : 
D kþ1 ¼ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>D k 
0:1 6 r k 6 0:7 : D kþ1 ¼ D k </p>

<p>r k P 0:7 
ks 
Ã k &lt; D k : D kþ1 ¼ D k </p>

<p>ks 
Ã k P D k : D kþ1 ¼ 1:5 Ã D k </p>



<p>8 
&gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; </p>

<p>&gt; &gt; &gt; : 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>x kþ1 ¼ 
x k þ s 
Ã ; if r k &gt; 0 </p>

<p>x k ; 
otherwise </p>



<p>: 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>It is to be mentioned that the current center is the point of 
least function value achieved so far. </p>

<p>Model update </p>

<p>When a new point is available, the current quadratic model 
M 
(k) (x) is updated so that the point of lowest objective func-
tion value x k is now the center of the kth trust region. The 
model will take the form: </p>

<p>M 
ðkÞ ðsÞ ¼ a 
ðkÞ þ s 
T b 
ðkÞ þ 
1 
2 
s 
T B 
ðkÞ s; s ¼ x À x k and s 2 R 
n : ð8Þ </p>

<p>The parameters: a 
(k) , b 
(k) and B 
(k) are evaluated employing 
the parameter values of the previous model M </p>

<p>kÀ1 </p>

<p>(x) in addi-
tion to all available function values. The constant a 
(k) is 
assigned the value of f(x) k , i.e., a 
(k) = f(x) k . The model will 
be updated in two steps. First, the vector b 
(k) is updated then 
the Hessian matrix B 
(k) is updated as follows: </p>

<p>Step1: Updating the vector b </p>

<p>(k) </p>

<p>The vector b 
(k) can be obtained using only n points. How-
ever, using the n recent points may result in ill-conditioned sys-
tem of linear equations. In order to avoid this, it is proposed to 
use the least squares approximation with the most recent 2n 
points. So, the vector b 
(k) is evaluated such that the model 
M 
k (x) fits the last 2n points obtained, x i , i = 1, 2, . . ., 2n, i.e., 
the following condition should be satisfied: </p>

<p>M 
ðkÞ ðs i Þ ¼ fðs i Þ; where s i ¼ x i À x k and i ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; 2n: 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>When computing the vector b </p>

<p>(k) </p>

<p>, the matrix B 
(k) is assigned 
temporarily the value of the previous model Hessian matrix, 
B 
(kÀ1) , hence the vector b 
(k) is obtained by solving the follow-
ing system of linear equations: </p>

<p>Ab 
ðkÞ ¼ v; 
ð10Þ </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>A novel derivative-free surrogate model </p>

<p>
A ¼ </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T 
1 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T 
2 </p>

<p>. . 
. </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T 
2n </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
5 
and v ¼ </p>

<p>fðs 1 Þ À a 
ðkÞ À </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 B 
ðkÀ1Þ s 1 </p>

<p>fðs 2 Þ À a 
ðkÞ À </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 B 
ðkÀ1Þ s 2 </p>

<p>. . 
. </p>

<p>fðs 2n Þ À a 
ðkÞ À </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2n B 
ðkÀ1Þ s 2n </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>: 
ð11Þ </p>

<p>The previous system is an over-determined system. The 
least squares approximation for b 
(k) is </p>

<p>b 
ðkÞ ¼ ðA 
T AÞ 
À1 A 
T v: 
ð12Þ </p>

<p>Step2: Updating the matrix B </p>

<p>(k) </p>

<p>The model Hessian matrix B 
(k) is evaluated using the fol-
lowing updating formula: </p>

<p>B 
ðkÞ ¼ cB 
ðkÀ1Þ þ qp 
T ; 
ð13Þ </p>

<p>where c is a positive constant, 0.5 &lt; c &lt; 1, and the vector 
p 2 R 
n , </p>

<p>q ¼ ½signðdiagðB 
ðkÀ1Þ ÞÞ Ã 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 
ð1 À cÞ Ã jdiagðB 
ðkÀ1Þ Þj 
q 
: 
ð14Þ </p>

<p>This choice of q, ensures that changes in B 
(k) occur gradually. 
The vector p is evaluated such that the model M 
(k) (x) tries to fit 
all the available m points obtained so far, x i , i = 1, 2, . . ., m, i.e., 
the following condition should be satisfied </p>

<p>M 
ðkÞ ðs i Þ ¼ fðs i Þ; where s i ¼ x i À x k and i ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; m; 
ð15Þ </p>

<p>i.e., the vector p is obtained by solving the weighted system of 
linear equations </p>

<p>Ap ¼ v; 
ð16Þ </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>A ¼ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 qs </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 w 1 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 qs </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 w 2 
. . 
. </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>m qs </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>m w m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>; v ¼ </p>

<p>w 1 Ã ðfðs 1 Þ À a 
ðkÞ À s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 b 
ðkÞ À </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 cB 
ðkÀ1Þ s 1 Þ </p>

<p>w 2 Ã ðfðs 2 Þ À a 
ðkÞ À s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 b 
ðkÞ À </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 cB 
ðkÀ1Þ s 2 Þ </p>

<p>. . 
. </p>

<p>w m Ã ðfðs m Þ À a 
ðkÞ À s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>m b 
ðkÞ À </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>m cB 
ðkÀ1Þ s m Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>ð17Þ </p>

<p>To obtain more accurate model in the neighborhood of the 
current center, the available points are assigned different 
weights w i , i = 1, 2, . . ., m according to their distances from 
the trust region center. In the proposed approach the weight 
w i , associated with each equation, takes the form: </p>

<p>w i ¼ </p>

<p>1 
ifks i k 6 c 1 D </p>

<p>c 1 D 
ksik </p>

<p>if ks i k &gt; c 1 D 
; </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>i ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; m; 
ð18Þ </p>

<p>where c 1 is a positive constant, c 1 P 1. 
The previous system in (16) is an over-determined system 
(m &gt; n). The least squares approximation for p is </p>

<p>p ¼ ðA 
T AÞ 
À1 A 
T v: 
ð19Þ </p>

<p>After getting the vector p, the term qp 
T is calculated and the 
matrix is made symmetric by resetting the off-diagonal ele-
ments to their average values, i.e., b ij = b ji ‹ (b ij + b ji )/2, then 
the new Hessian matrix B 
(k) is updated according to Eq. (13). 
The model can be improved by generating a new point 
s new = x new À x k , which is chosen to be on the boundary of 
the trust region so that it improves the distribution of points 
around the center of the trust region. A suggested solution 
to find s new is to solve the following problem: </p>

<p>max s p ¼ 
X ns </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>ðs </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>i sÞ 
2 ; such that s </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>i s &lt; 0 8 i and ksk 6 D; 
ð20Þ </p>

<p>where s new is selected to maximize the sum of squares of the 
projections of the vector s new on the other s i , i = 1, 2, . . .n s 
vectors, where n s is the available set of points. After generating 
s new , the function value f(x new ) is computed. If f(x new ) is found 
to be less than f(x k ), then x new will be considered as the new 
trust region center of the subsequent iteration, otherwise, 
x new will just be added to the available set of points. </p>

<p>Algorithm </p>

<p>A complete algorithm for the proposed method is given below 
(see also an illustrative flowchart in Fig. 2). </p>

<p>1. Set N = 0 (the number of function evaluations), given 
x 0 2 R 
n ; D 1 &gt; 0; 0:5 &lt; c &lt; 1; c 1 P 1; N max ; d (a termination 
criterion). 
2. Find the initial m points using (2), letting x 1 be the initial trust 
region center, then construct the initial quadratic model using (3), 
Set k = 1. 
3. Solve the trust region sub-problem (4) using the truncated 
conjugate gradient method to obtain s 
* = x n À x k of the model 
M </p>

<p>(k) </p>

<p>(x) over the trust region. 
4. Evaluate f(x n ) and compute the reduction ratio by substituting in 
(5). 
5. Update the trust region radius to obtain D k+1 using (6). 
6. Determine the trust region center of the next iteration x k+1 based 
on x k and r k using (7). If ||f(x k+1 ) À f(x k )|| 6 d, the algorithm will 
be terminated with x opt = x k+1 and f opt = f(x k+1 ). If for two 
successive iterations, r k is negative go to Step 9, else continue. 
7. Add the point x n to the set of available points S, if the number of 
points in S exceeds N max , remove the farthest point from x k+1 . 
Comment. To avoid severe computational and storage overhead, a 
bound N max is put to limit the uncontrollable increase in the 
number of stored points. Specifically, when the number of available 
points reaches N max the farthest point from the trust region center is 
removed. 
8. Construct the quadratic model M </p>

<p>(k+1) </p>

<p>(x) around x k+1 based on 
M </p>

<p>(k) </p>

<p>(x) and the set of available points S using the updating 
procedures in Eqs. (9)-(19), then set k = k + 1 and go to Step 3. 
9. Generate a new point s new using (20), add it to the set of points S, 
then go to Step 8. </p>

<p>Examples </p>

<p>The effectiveness of the proposed algorithm is demonstrated 
through two benchmark examples. All results are compared 
with those obtained by NEWUOA (NEW Unconstrained 
Optimization Algorithm) by Powell [6]. The performance is 
measured by the number of function evaluations N required 
to reach the optimal solution. </p>

<p>The 2D Beale function </p>

<p>The function is by [26]: </p>

<p>fðxÞ ¼ 
X 3 </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>½a i À x 1 ð1 À x </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>2 Þ 
2 ; 
ð21Þ </p>

<p>where a 1 = 1.5, a 2 = 2.25, and a 3 = 2.625. This function has a 
valley approaching the line x 2 = 1, and has a minimum of 0 at 
(3 0.5) 
T . The initial values used for x 0 and D 1 are (0.1 0.1) 
T and </p>

<p> 
A.S.O. Hassan et al. </p>

<p>0.8, respectively. The results in Table 1 and Fig. 3 compare the 
optimal value obtained by applying the proposed technique 
versus NEWUOA with the same number of function evalua-
tion N. 
It is to be noticed, that starting from the same initial 
point and after only 11 iterations; the proposed algorithm 
gives a function value of 0.8065 while NEWUOA gives 
14.2031. </p>

<p>The 3D Box function </p>

<p>The function was proposed by [27]: </p>

<p>fðxÞ ¼ 
X i¼10 </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>exp 
Àix 1 
10 </p>



<p>À exp 
Àix 2 
10 </p>



<p>À x 3 exp 
Ài 
10 </p>

<p>
À expðÀiÞ </p>



<p>
2 </p>

<p>ð22Þ </p>

<p>This function has a minima at (1 10 1) 
T , and also along the 
line{(a a 0) 
T } with value 0. The initial values used for x 0 and </p>

<p>Fig. 2 A flowchart for the proposed optimization algorithm. </p>

<p>A novel derivative-free surrogate model </p>

<p>
D 1 are (0 10 2) 
T and 9.9, respectively. Table 2 shows a compar-
ison of the optimal value obtained after N function evaluations 
using the proposed algorithm versus NEWUOA (see also 
Fig. 4). 
In the above numerical examples, it is to be noticed that at 
the beginning of the optimization process, the proposed algo-
rithm is much faster than NEWUOA. However, as the optimi-
zation gets closer to the optimum, the methods based on 
interpolation will be more accurate as expected. This explains 
why the proposed algorithm is well suited for objective func-
tions that have some uncertainty in their values or subject to 
statistical variations. This may occur for design of systems 
whose parameter values are subject to known but unavoidable 
statistical fluctuations [1,28]. Also, the algorithm may be useful 
for surrogate-based system design [2,29]. These surrogates are </p>

<p>updated during the optimization process, and a few iterations 
in the optimization process will be sufficient at the beginning. 
In this case the new technique will produce a significant reduc-
tion in few iterations. </p>

<p>Optimized design of RF cavity </p>

<p>The RF cavity is a major component of linear accelerators 
[30,31]. The structure of RF cavity must efficiently transfer 
the electromagnetic energy to the charged particles beam. This 
can be accomplished through an optimized configuration of its 
internal geometry, by adding nose cones to create a region of 
more concentrated axial electric field along the path of the 
electron beam, as shown in Fig. 1. 
The most useful figure of merit for high field concentration 
along the beam axis and low ohmic power loss in the cavity 
walls is the effective shunt impedance per unit length ZT </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>where T is the transient-time factor (a measure of the energy 
gain reduction caused by the sinusoidal time variation of the 
field in the cavity, [32]). 
One of the main objectives in cavity design is to choose 
geometry to maximize effective shunt impedance per unit 
length. This indicates increasing the energy delivered to the 
beam compared to that thermally lost in the cavity walls. 
The effective shunt impedance per unit length is usually 
expressed in mega ohms per meter and is defined by </p>

<p>ZT 
2 ¼ 
ðV 0 TÞ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>PL 
; 
ð23Þ </p>

<p>where P is the thermal power losses in the walls of the cavity, 
V 0 = ò E(z)dz = E 0 L, and E 0 is the average axial electric field 
along the cavity axis with length L. 
The technique is applied to an RF cavity with resonance 
frequency 9.4 GHz, shown in Fig. 5. The objective is to maxi-
mize effective shunt impedance per unit length. In order to do 
that, we optimize the axial z positions of ten points that 
describe the cavity curvature through a spline curve. The axial 
positions z = (z 1 , z 2 ,. . ., z 10 ) 
T in the z-direction are taken as 
the design parameters. The radial positions of these points 
are chosen on a logarithmic scale along r-direction. It is to 
be noted that during the variation of the curvature, the </p>

<p>Table 1 Results of the 2D Beale function compared with 
NEWUOA. </p>

<p>N 
Proposed algorithm 
NEWUOA </p>

<p>11 
0.8065 
14.2031 
21 
0.1083 
0.91702 
31 
0.0033 
0.034386 
43 
2.3335eÀ5 
1.7965eÀ4 
55 
2.6973eÀ6 
6.5829eÀ11 
67 
2.5790eÀ7 
6.4829eÀ11 </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Results of the 2D Beale function. </p>

<p>Table 2 Results of the 3D Box function compared with 
NEWUOA. </p>

<p>N 
Proposed algorithm 
NEWUOA </p>

<p>10 
0.2413 
0.59732 
17 
5.2048eÀ3 
0.18785 
25 
2.3149eÀ3 
0.11451 
38 
4.2472eÀ4 
0.26465eÀ1 
48 
4.1820eÀ5 
0.24613eÀ1 
62 
4.1771eÀ6 
0.21593eÀ2 
87 
1.9203eÀ6 
6.975eÀ5 </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Results of the 3D Box function. </p>

<p> 
A.S.O. Hassan et al. </p>

<p>resonance frequency is always kept at 9.4 GHz. The initial 
values used for the ten radial positions z 0 are all set to 
0.6 cm and D 1 is set to 0.02 cm. 
Cavity design generally requires electromagnetic field-solver 
that solves Maxwell equations numerically for the specified 
boundary conditions. In the simulations, POISSON and 
SUPERFISH are used as the main solver programs in a collec-
tion of programs from LANL [18,33]. The solver is used to cal-
culate the static magnetic and electric fields and radio-frequency 
electromagnetic fields for either 2-D Cartesian coordinates or 
axially symmetric cylindrical coordinates. The code SUPER-
FISH is used to solve for axisymmetric TM0nl modes, for the 
field components Hphi, Er and Ez. The solution is obtained 
through solving Hemholtz equation using finite element method 
FEM over a triangular mesh subject to the proper boundary 
conditions and symmetries imposed [34]. 
Design algorithm shown in Fig. 6 is implemented in MAT-
LAB code, where an initial case is chosen corresponding to ten 
z positions of points with cavity curvature is described with 
spline curve (step 2). Then the spline interpolated curve is sam-
pled at 100 points, where those sampled points are considered 
connected with piecewise linear, approximating the cavity cur-
vature. This piece wise linear description is fed to <rs type="software">AUTO-
MESH</rs> program to generate mesh (step 3). The solution of 
lowest TM mode of the cavity is made at step 4 by calling 
SUPERFISH, and the obtained frequency in step 5 is used 
to scale the cavity dimensions to keep the resonance frequency 
at 9.4 GH (step 6). The corresponding scaling is reflected on 
the obtained cavity shunt impedance (step 7), where this value 
is fed to the optimizer algorithm to determine the new ten 
points positions. Then the process is repeated starting from 
step 2. 
The results of the effective shunt impedance per unit length 
for RF cavity in mega ohm per meter after N function evalu-
ations for both the proposed algorithm and NEWUOA are 
shown in Table 3. 
It is to be mentioned that starting from the same initial 
point, the convergence of the proposed algorithm is as best 
as NEWUOA. However, the advantage of the proposed 
algorithm is its easy implementation and accessibility for 
update and modification. </p>

<p>The figures of optimal cavity using the proposed algorithm 
and the NEWUOA are shown in Figs. 7 and 8 respectively. 
It worth mentioning that one could criticize the proposed 
optimized structure, that it contains sharp edge nose, which 
is difficult to manufacture and is a point of field singularity 
that causes breakdown. One way to override that problem is 
to add some curvature to the nose sharp tip, which would 
slightly reduce the realized shunt impedance. </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Structure of radio frequency (RF) cavity. </p>

<p>Fig. 6 The Poisson Superfish Solver within the proposed 
optimization (design) loop. </p>

<p>Table 3 Results of the RF cavity design compared with 
NEWUOA. </p>

<p>N 
Proposed algorithm 
NEWUOA </p>

<p>50 
111.771 
112.587 
75 
115.207 
116.833 
90 
117.183 
119.316 
120 
119.01 
120.511 
160 
120.5 
120.910 
200 
121.01 
121.211 
260 
121.301 
121.521 </p>

<p>A novel derivative-free surrogate model </p>

<p>
Fig. 7 The optimized cavity using the proposed algorithm. Effective Shunt impedance per unit length = 121.301 MOhm/m. </p>

<p>Fig. 8 The optimized cavity using NEWUOA. Effective Shunt impedance per unit length = 121.521 MOhm/m. </p>

<p> 
A.S.O. Hassan et al. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>In this article, a new trust region optimization method that 
does not require any derivative information has been pro-
posed. In this method, the objective function is approximated 
via quadratic surrogates, and using few number of initial data 
points than the exact number of surrogate parameters. 
Classical benchmark test problems were used to demonstrate 
the accuracy and efficiency of the proposed method. The 
results obtained showed the ability of the proposed method 
to rapidly converge to the final region containing the optimum 
solution when only a limited number of function evaluations is 
permissible and when a high accuracy is not really necessary. 
Least-squares fitting is used instead of interpolation which 
explains the inaccurate solution in case of explicit objective 
functions. Thus, the proposed method is suitable for stochastic 
optimization or objectives that suffer from numerical inaccu-
racy. In addition, the proposed method has been used to 
obtain the optimal design for the structure of RF cavity which 
is the major part of any linear accelerator. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors have declared no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Compliance with Ethics Requirements </p>

<p>This article does not contain any studies with human or animal 
subjects. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The authors deeply thank Dr. Sami Tantawi from SLAC 
National Accelerator Laboratory for the fruitful discussion 
on the optimization of the RF cavity resonators. </p>



<p>A novel derivative-free surrogate model </p>



<p>
 
A.S.O. Hassan et al. </p>

</text></tei>