<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4054524" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Amenorrhea is a common adverse effect of treatment with antipsychotic medications that influences both 
fertility and adherence to medication regimens. Most research suggests that medication-induced prolactinemia is the main 
cause of amenorrhea but few prospective studies have assessed this hypothesis. </p>

<p>Aim: Identify risk factors for amenorrhea following treatment with antipsychotic medication. </p>

<p>Methods: The study used a prospective, nested case-control design. First-episode, drug naïve female patients with 
schizophrenia who were in the middle of their menstrual cycle at the time of admission were enrolled. Serum levels of six 
reproductive hormones were assessed before and after a 12-week course of treatment with risperidone: progesterone, 
estradiol, prolactin, follicular stimulating hormone, luteinizing hormone, and testosterone. The hormone levels of 31 
patients who had no menstruation during the entire 12 weeks of treatment (the amenorrhea group) were compared to 
those of 31 age-matched subjects who had normal menstrual periods over the 12 weeks of treatment (the control group). </p>

<p>Results: We found a dramatic 4-fold increase in prolactin levels in women of childbearing age treated with risperidone, but 
the pretreatment and posttreatment levels of prolactin were not different between patients who did and did not develop 
amenorrhea with treatment. However, there were significantly lower pretreatment levels of estradiol and progesterone 
in patients who subsequently developed amenorrhea with risperidone treatment than in patients who did not develop 
amenorrhea. A conditional logistic regression analysis found that pretreatment levels of estradiol remained significantly 
associated with the development of amenorrhea during treatment even when adjusting for the pretreatment levels of the 
other five reproductive hormones assessed. </p>

<p>Conclusion: These findings do not support the suggestion that amenorrhea associated with the use of antipsychotic 
medication is the result of hyperprolactinemia. If our finding of the predictive power of pretreatment levels of estradiol is 
confirmed in larger studies, this information would be of use to clinicians in selecting antipsychotic medications for female 
patients with schizophrenia; patients at highest risk of developing amenorrhea could be preferentially treated with the 
medications that are at lowest risk of inducing amenorrhea. </p>

<p>Amenorrhea is a common side effect of treatment 
with antipsychotic medication that can affect both 
the fertility and compliance of female patients with 
schizophrenia. 
[1-6] Defining amenorrhea as three months 
or longer without menstrual periods in individuals who 
previously had regular menstrual cycles, a study in China 
reported amenorrhea in 11 to 35% of female patients 
being treated with various antipsychotic medications </p>

<p>and found that risperidone was associated with higher 
rates of amenorrhea than other antipsychotics. </p>

<p>[7]   Amenorrhea is presumed to be caused by medication-
induced hyperprolactinemia, but only a minority of 
antipsychotic-treated patients with hyperprolactinemia 
develop amenorrhea. 
[1,2,8-10] Other reports find that 
some female patients with schizophrenia have low 
levels of estrogen (estradiol), another potential cause of 
amenorrhea. </p>

<p>[8,11,12] </p>



<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2013, Vol.25, No.1 </p>

<p>The risk factors and protective factors that increase 
or decrease the likelihood of amenorrhea in females 
treated with antipsychotic medications remain 
unknown. Identifying high-risk patients prior to the 
selection of an antipsychotic would help clinicians 
avoid the use of medications that are most likely to 
result in amenorrhea. Information about risk status for 
amenorrhea would also be useful in deciding whether 
or not to provide concurrent treatment with metformin, 
which has recently been proven to be effective in the 
treatment of antipsychotic-induced amenorrhea. </p>

<p>[13]   The current study uses a nested case-control design to 
compare pretreatment levels of reproductive hormones 
in first-episode, drug-naïve female patients (with 
regular menses) with schizophrenia who do and do </p>

<p>not subsequently develop amenorrhea during an initial 
12-week course of treatment with risperidone. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1 Patient enrollment </p>

<p>The enrollment of patients is shown in Figure 1. 
Females admitted to the inpatient service at the Third 
People's Hospital of Huzhou City from July 2009 to 
October 2011 who met ICD-10 criteria for schizophrenia, 
who were in the first episode of illness (i.e., duration of 
illness of 3 to 12 months) and who had never received 
antipsychotic medication were potential subjects for 
the study. Inclusion and exclusion criteria included the 
following: Han nationality, 20 to 40 years of age, regular </p>

<p>Figure 1. Patient enrollment and follow-up </p>



<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2013, Vol.25, No.1 </p>

<p>menstrual cycles of 28 to 30 days for the six months 
prior to admission, most recent menstrual cycle 7 to 
14 days prior to admission (i.e., in the endometrial 
proliferation phase of the menstrual cycle), total score 
of the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) </p>

<p>[14]   ≥ 60 on admission, no significant physical diseases, no 
history of substance abuse, no history of allergies, no 
history of menstrual abnormalities (including polycystic 
ovary syndrome), and no abnormalities on routine 
admission laboratory examinations (including routine 
blood chemistry, urinalysis, thyroid function tests, and 
abdominal ultrasound). </p>

<p>All patients and their guardians signed informed 
consent forms to participate in the study. The study was 
approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of the Third 
People's Hospital of Huzhou City. </p>

<p>2.2 Intervention and assessment </p>

<p>Among all 1215 first-episode female patients with 
schizophrenia, 652 (54%) were enrolled in the study. 
Most of the 563 (46.3%) excluded patients were 
excluded because they were not in the middle of their 
menstrual cycle at the time of admission (i.e., last 
menstrual period was less than 7 days or more than 14 
days from admission) but some were excluded because 
they did not meet other inclusion or exclusion criteria. 
Almost all first-episode patients with schizophrenia 
were initially treated with risperidone, the most 
widely used antipsychotic medication in China. Initial 
doses of risperidone were gradually increased to 
therapeutic levels (2-6mg/d) over the first two weeks 
of treatment (based on the judgment of the treating 
clinician). The occurrence of side effects was assessed 
monthly using the Treatment Emergent Symptom Scale 
(TESS). 
[15] If necessary, adjunctive non-antipsychotic 
medication were administered: clonazepam for serious 
sleep problems, propranolol for tachycardia, and 
trihexyphenidyl for parkinsonian side effects. </p>

<p>As shown in Figure 1, 493 of the 652 patients 
(75.6%) completed the initial 12 weeks of treatment 
with risperidone. The main reasons for drop-out were 
loss to follow-up after hospital discharge, withdrawal 
of consent, and lack of efficacy of risperidone. The time 
of each menstrual period in the subjects was regularly 
recorded during the 12-week period. Based on this 
information, patients who completed the 12-week 
course of treatment with risperidone were categorized 
into three groups: 31 patients (6.3%) had no menstrual 
periods over the entire 12-week treatment period and, 
thus, met criteria for amenorrhea 
[6] (the amenorrhea 
group); 198 patients (40.2%) had regular menses (no 
more than 6 days early or late) during the 12-week 
period; and 264 patients (53.5%) had irregular menses 
over the 12-week period (i.e., at least one menstrual 
period that was either 7 or more days early or 7 or more 
days late). </p>

<p>Fasting venous blood samples (taken at 7am) 
were obtained from all patients before the initiation 
of treatment with risperidone and from those who 
completed 12 weeks of treatment with risperidone. 
(For all subjects, the pretreatment blood sample was 
taken during the endometrial proliferation phase of 
patients' menstrual cycles, but this was only the case 
for the post-treatment blood samples of subjects who 
continued to have normal menstrual cycles.) In addition 
to the routine tests of blood sugar and of liver, renal and 
thyroid function, the levels of the following reproductive 
hormones were assayed: progesterone, estradiol, 
prolactin, luteinizing hormone, follicular stimulating 
hormone, and testosterone. These assays were 
conducted using the ACCESS automatic microparticle 
chemiluminescence immunoassay system and the 
associated reagent kits (American Beckman Coulter 
Ltd.). The intra and inter coefficients of variation for the 
assessments were 5% and 8%. </p>

<p>2.3 Statistical methods </p>

<p>The analysis used a nested case-control design. For 
each of the 31 cases in the amenorrhea group a control 
subject was selected from among patients of the same 
age (within 3 years) who had had normal menstrual 
periods over the 12 weeks of treatment. These 31 
individuals constituted the control group. </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> statistic software. 
The results for several of the hormone measurements 
were not normally distributed, so both paired t-tests and 
Wilcoxon's signed ranked test (for matched data) were 
used in the univariate analyses. Univariate analyses 
included: a) assessment of the before versus after 
changes in the measures of reproductive hormones in 
the amenorrhea group and, separately, in the control 
group; b) comparison of baseline values between 
cases and controls; c) comparison of post-treatment 
values for cases and controls; and d) comparison of the 
magnitude of the before versus after change in values 
in cases versus controls. Multivariate conditional logistic 
regression was used to determine whether or not any of 
the pre-treatment measures of reproductive hormones 
was associated with the occurrence of amenorrhea 
during treatment. The two-tailed level of significance 
was set at 0.05. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1 Characteristics of cases and controls </p>

<p>The 31 patients in the amenorrhea group had a mean 
(sd) age of 26.3 (5.6) years. At the time of admission 
their mean duration of illness was 5 (2) months (range, 
3 to 10 months); 22 of them were married; 17 had 
borne children; and the mean total PANSS score was 
81.6 (16.3). Their mean duration of inpatient treatment 
was 47.5 (16.3) days. Their mean therapeutic dose of </p>



<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2013, Vol.25, No.1 </p>

<p>risperidone was 3.3 (0.4) mg/d (range, 2 to 5 mg/d). Their 
use of adjunctive treatments was as follows: 5 patients 
used 1 to 2 mg/d of clonazepam for 2 to 6 weeks; 6 
patients used 20 mg/d of propranolol for 5 weeks; and 
12 patients used 4 mg/d of trihexyphenidyl for 6 weeks. </p>

<p>The 31 patients in the control group had a mean 
age of 26.6 (6.2) years. At the time of admission their 
mean duration of illness was 5 (2) months (range, 3 to 
10 months); 24 of them were married; 19 had borne 
children; and the mean total PANSS score was 80.8 
(18.5). Their mean duration of inpatient treatment 
was 44.8 (17.6) days. Their mean therapeutic dose of 
risperidone was 3.3 (0.4) mg/d (range, 2 to 5 mg/d). 
Their use of adjunctive treatments was as follows: 7 
patients used 1 to 2 mg/d of clonazepam for 2 to 7 
weeks; 5 patients used 20 to 30 mg/d of propranolol for 
5 weeks; and 10 patients used 4 mg/d of trihexyphenidyl 
for 6 weeks. </p>

<p>There were no statistically significant differences 
between the two groups in any of these measures. </p>

<p>3.2 Comparison of reproductive hormone levels 
between patients who do and do not develop 
amenorrhea with risperidone treatment </p>

<p>As shown in Table 1, prior to treatment the levels of 
estradiol and progesterone in patients who subsequently 
developed amenorrhea when treated with risperdone 
were significantly lower than in patients who did not 
develop amenorrhea with antipsychotic treatment. 
After 12 weeks of treatment the estradiol level remained 
lower in the amenorrhea group but the difference was 
no longer statistically significant. After 12 weeks of 
treatment the progesterone level in the amenorrhea 
group and the control group was similar. The baseline 
and post-treatment levels of prolactin, follicular stimu-
lating hormone, luteinizing hormone, and testosterone </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of reproductive hormone concentrations (mean [sd]) between 31 first-episode female patients with 
schizophrenia who develop amenorrhea during 12 weeks of treatment with risperidone and 31 age-matched patients 
who do not develop amenorrhea during treatment </p>

<p>progesterone 
(nmol/L) </p>

<p>estradiol 
(pmol/L) </p>

<p>prolactin 
(ugl/L) </p>

<p>follicular 
stimulating 
hormone 
(U/L) </p>

<p>luteinizing 
hormone 
(U/L) </p>

<p>testosterone 
(nmol/L) </p>

<p>Baseline 
(before using medication) 
Amenorrhea group 
9.1 (12.4) 
225.1 (126.8) 
19.9 (5.3) 
9.0 (4.5) 
5.0 (5.7) 
2.4 (1.3) 
Control group 
13.2 (15.7) 
329.7 (116.0) 
21.3 (5.2) 
9.0 (4.6) 
4.9 (4.9) 
2.2 (0.8) </p>

<p>paired t-test (p-value) 
1.23 (0.228) 
3.35 (0.002) 
1.05 (0.302) 
0.03 (0.976) 
0.06 (0.953) 
0.53 (0.598) 
Wilcoxon Z (p-value) 
2.15 (0.032) 
2.92 (0.004) 
0.82 (0.410) 
0.02 (0.984) 
0.23 (0.822) 
0.10 (0.922) </p>

<p>End of 12 
th week of 
using medication 
Amenorrhea group 
4.4 (7.6) 
118.5 (103.5) 
80.9 (34.3) 
6.3 (6.5) 
6.8 (6.7) 
2.6 (1.8) 
Control group 
3.5 (5.4) 
179.9 (163.3) 
80.3 (40.0) 
5.7 (2.5) 
5.6 (4.0) 
2.2 (1.0) </p>

<p>paired t-test (p-value) 
0.51 (0.611) 
1.67 (0.105) 
0.06 (0.957) 
0.51 (0.617) 
0.82 (0.418) 
1.22 (0.233) 
Wilcoxon Z (p-value) 
0.67 (0.504) 
1.55 (0.122) 
0.06 (0.953) 
0.35 (0.724) 
0.08 (0.938) 
0.70 (0.487) </p>

<p>Change in concentration 
with treatment 
Amenorrhea group 
-4.7 (13.5) 
-106.5 (111.6) 
61.0 (32.8) 
-2.7 (6.6) 
-1.8 (7.2) 
-0.2 (1.4) 
paired t-test (p-value) 
1.95 (0.061) 
5.31 (&lt;0.001) 
10.35 (&lt;0.001) 
2.25 (0.032) 
1.40 (0.171) 
0.95 (0.352) 
Wilcoxon Z (p-value) 
2.21 (0.027) 
4.17 (&lt;0.001) 
4.86 (&lt;0.001) 
2.96 (0.003) 
1.02 (0.308) 
0.33 (0.742) </p>

<p>Control group 
-9.7 (15.6) 
-149.8 (178.6) 
59.1 (40.9) 
-3.3 (5.6) 
0.7 (6.4) 
-0.01 (1.0) </p>

<p>paired t-test (p-value) 
3.46 (0.002) 
4.67 (&lt;0.001) 
8.04 (&lt;0.001) 
3.29 (0.003) 
0.65 (0.523) 
0.38 (0.848) 
Wilcoxon Z (p-value) 
3.90 (&lt;0.001) 
3.60 (&lt;0.001) 
4.86 (&lt;0.001) 
2.85 (0.004) 
0.96 (0.337) 
0.24 (0.711) </p>

<p>Comparison of changes in the 
two groups with treatment 
Mean difference in 
change scores </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>5.0 (19.5) 
43.3 (229.5) 
1.9 (61.6) 
0.6 (9.5) 
1.1 (8.7) 
0.3 (1.8) </p>

<p>paired t-test (p-value) 
1.41 (0.168) 
1.05 (0.302) 
0.18 (0.862) 
0.37 (0.714) 
0.69 (0.498) 
0.92 (0.368) 
Wilcoxon Z (p-value) 
2.14 (0.033) 
1.88 (0.060) 
0.14 (0.891) 
0.14 (0.891) 
0.10 (0.922) 
0.77 (0.439) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>For each pair of patients the difference in the change scores is computed as the before versus after treatment change for the amenorrhea group 
patient minus the before versus after treatment change for the control group patient. </p>



<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2013, Vol.25, No.1 </p>

<p>were not significantly different between patients who 
did and did not developed amenorrhea during treatment 
with risperidone. </p>

<p>In both the amenorrhea group and the control 
group, 12 weeks of treatment with risperdone was 
associated with statistically significant drops in the levels 
of progesterone, estradiol and follicular stimulating 
hormone, and with a 4-fold increase in the levels 
of prolactin. The levels of luteinizing hormone and 
testosterone did not change significantly with treatment. </p>

<p>The drop in the level of progesterone with treatment 
was significantly smaller in the amenorrhea group than 
in the control group (4.7 v. 9.7 nmol/L, respectively) 
and the proportional change from baseline was also 
much smaller in the amenorrhea group (52% v. 73%, 
respectively). There was also a trend (p=0.060) of a </p>

<p>smaller drop in the level of estradiol with treatment in 
the amenorrhea group than in the control group (107 
v. 150 pmol/L) but the proportional drop from baseline 
(47% v. 45%, respectively) was similar in the two groups. 
There were no between-group differences in the 
magnitude of the changes with treatment of prolactin, 
follicular stimulating hormone, luteinizing hormone or 
testosterone. </p>

<p>The conditional logistic regression analysis that 
simultaneously considered the pre-treatment levels 
of all six reproductive hormones found that after 
adjustment for the levels of the other reproductive 
hormones, low pre-treatment estradiol levels were 
significantly associated with the subsequent occurrence 
of amenorrhea during treatment with risperidone. 
(Table 2) </p>

<p>Table 2. Results of conditional logistic regression of the association of pre-treatment levels of reproductive hormones with 
the subsequent occurrence of amenorrhea during 12 weeks of treatment with risperidone in first-episode female 
patients with schizophrenia (31 cases and 31 age-matched controls) </p>

<p>Reproductive hormone 
Wald value 
p-value 
odds ratio 
95% confidence interval </p>

<p>Progesterone 
&lt;0.01 
0.966 
0.999 
0.936-1.065 
Estradiol 
4.68 
0.031 
0.992 
0.985-0.999 
Prolactin 
1.03 
0.310 
0.928 
0.804-1.072 
Luteinizing hormone 
0.40 
0.526 
0.957 
0.836-1.096 
Follicular stimulating hormone 
0.01 
0.914 
0.994 
0.885-1.115 
Testosterone 
0.18 
0.674 
1.147 
0.606-2.171 </p>

<p>Nagelkerke R 
2 for the full model is 0.416. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>4.1 Main findings </p>

<p>Similar to the findings from other studies 
[16-18] we 
found a dramatic increase in prolactin levels in women 
of childbearing age treated with risperidone, but the 
pre-treatment and post-treatment levels of prolactin 
were not different between patients who did and did 
not develop amenorrhea with treatment. These findings 
do not support the suggestion that amenorrhea 
associated with the use of antipsychotic medication is 
the result of hyperprolactinemia. </p>

<p>[8-10]   The most dramatic finding was the significantly lower 
pre-treatment level of estradiol in the patients who 
subsequently develop amenorrhea with risperidone 
treatment. This was a robust finding that persisted 
even when the pre-treatment levels of the other five 
reproductive hormones assessed were adjusted for in 
a conditional logistic regression model. We matched 
cases with controls by age, and had selected subjects 
without prior menstrual problems (specifically excluding 
those with polycystic ovarian syndrome who may have 
irregular menses </p>

<p>[19]   ) who had regular menses for at least 
six months prior to admission and who were all in the </p>

<p>endometrial proliferation phase of their cycle, so it is 
unlikely that our results are confounded by differences 
in the menstrual history or menstrual phase of the 
subjects. </p>

<p>We also found significantly lower pre-treatment 
levels of progesterone in patients who subsequently 
developed amenorrhea and the drop in the level 
of this hormone with treatment was significantly 
smaller in individuals who developed amenorrhea 
than in those who did not develop amenorrhea. 
However, after adjustment for the other hormone 
levels in the multivariate analysis, pre-treatment level 
of progesterone was not an independent predictor of 
subsequent amenorrhea. </p>

<p>The post-treatment levels of the six reproductive 
hormones assessed were not significantly different in 
patients who did and did not develop amenorrhea with 
treatment. Moreover, with the exception of the change 
in progesterone levels, the magnitude of the before 
versus after change in the levels of the hormones was 
not related to the development of amenorrhea. But the 
sample was relatively small, so the failure to identify 
significant relationships may be due to low power to 
detect clinically important differences between the </p>



<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2013, Vol.25, No.1 </p>

<p>groups. Further study with larger samples would be 
needed to assess the interaction effects of estradiol, 
progesterone, prolactin and the other hormones in 
the onset and persistence of medication-induced 
amenorrhea. </p>

<p>4.2 Limitations </p>

<p>There are several factors that need to be considered 
when assessing these results. a) In choosing a first-
onset, drug naïve sample we avoided the complication 
of prior use of antipsychotic medication, but we found 
a much lower prevalence of amenorrhea than reported 
in other studies (only 6.3% after 12 weeks of treatment) 
so it is possible that the 31 subjects with amenorrhea 
we identified are not representative of all subjects 
who would eventually develop amenorrhea after long-
term treatment with antipsychotic medication. b) We 
compared subjects with amenorrhea to those who 
continued to have normal menstrual periods during 12 
weeks of treatment, excluding from the analysis patients 
who had irregular menses following treatment with 
risperidone but did not meet criteria for amenorrhea 
-53.5% of the total sample. c) Risperidone is reported 
to result in a higher prevalence of amenorrhea than 
other antipsychotic medication, 
[6] so our results may not 
hold true for other antipsychotic medications. d) Some 
potential risk factors for amenorrhea (including family 
history of menstrual abnormalities, diet, BMI, exercise, 
etc.) were not considered. e) The small sample size made 
it impossible to interpret some negative findings (e.g., 
lack of relationship between changes in hormone levels 
with amenorrhea) because they could be due to Type II 
errors. f) No comparison was made between those who 
were and were not enrolled and between those who 
were enrolled but did or did not complete the 12 weeks 
of treatment with risperidone; it is, therefore, difficult to 
be certain about how representative these results would 
be for all female patients with schizophrenia. </p>

<p>4.3 Significance </p>

<p>Amenorrhea is a common adverse reaction to the 
use of antipsychotic medications. Previous research 
has implicated medication-induced prolactin as the 
main cause of amenorrhea in patients treated with 
antipsychotic medication, but in this sample of first-
episode drug naïve patients we found that pre-treatment 
prolactin levels or the magnitude of the increase in 
prolactin with antipsychotic treatment was not related to 
treatment-induced amenorrhea. However, pre-treatment 
levels of estradiol were predictive of subsequent 
amenorrhea during treatment with risperidone. </p>

<p>Some antipsychotic medications have a greater risk 
of inducing amenorrhea than others. If our finding of the 
predictive power of pre-treatment levels of estradiol is 
confirmed in larger studies, this information would be of </p>

<p>use to clinicians in selecting antipsychotic medications for 
female patients with schizophrenia; patients at highest 
risk of developing amenorrhea would be preferentially 
treated with the medications that are at lowest risk of 
inducing amenorrhea. Alternatively, patients at highest 
risk of developing amenorrhea could be concurrently 
treated with agents such as metformin that have been 
shown to decrease the risk of medication-induced 
amenorrhea. </p>

<p>Further work is needed to clarify the complex 
relationships between antipsychotic medications, 
reproductive hormones, protective agents and 
amenorrhea; but this current study is part of a growing 
corpus of work that is gradually helping clinicians 
individualize their selection of treatments for patients 
with schizophrenia. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>The authors declare that they have no competing 
interests. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant from the 2011 
Huzhou City Program for Science and Technology 
(No.2011YS28). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Professor Chunsheng Wang from the 
Huzhou Teachers College for his assistance with the 
design of the study and the analysis of the data. </p>





<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2013, Vol.25, No.1 </p>





<p>Shanghai Archives of Psychiatry, 2013, Vol.25, No.1 </p>

<p>• 论著 • </p>

<p>汉族女性精神分裂症首发患者利培酮 
治疗所致闭经的危险因素 </p>

<p>陈海支 钱敏才 * 沈鑫华 杨胜良 杨剑虹 宋娟芬 费小聪 陶百平 宋宝华 任丽华 沈仲夏 </p>

<p>湖州市第三人民医院 浙江湖州 
*通信作者：qmc@hzsy.com </p>

<p>摘要 </p>

<p>背景 闭经是抗精神病药治疗时常见的不良反应。这一不良反应不仅会影响生育，还会影响患者对药物治疗方案 </p>

<p>的依从性。多数研究提示药物所致高泌乳素血症是闭经的主要原因，但是极少有前瞻性研究评估这一假设。 </p>

<p>目的 找出抗精神病药治疗后出现闭经的危险因素。 </p>

<p>方法 研究采用前瞻性巢式病例-对照设计。将入院时处于月经周期的中间时段、未接受抗精神病药治疗的首发 </p>

<p>精神分裂症患者纳入研究。分别在利培酮治疗前和治疗 12 周后测定血清中 6 种生殖激素的水平，即孕酮、雌二 </p>

<p>醇、泌乳素、促卵泡激素、促黄体生成素以及睾酮水平。将利培酮治疗 12 周内未来月经的 31 例患者(闭经组) </p>

<p>与年龄匹配、月经仍然规律的 31 例患者(对照组)对照，比较上述激素水平。 </p>

<p>结果 我们发现育龄妇女利培酮治疗后泌乳素水平升高 4 倍，但无论治疗前还是治疗后闭经组和对照组之间的泌 </p>

<p>乳素水平差异不明显。然而，治疗前闭经组的雌二醇及孕酮水平均显著低于对照组。条件Logistic回归分析发现， </p>

<p>在校正了治疗前其他 5 种生殖激素水平后，治疗前雌二醇水平仍然与治疗期间出现闭经显著相关。 </p>

<p>结论 本研究结果不支持高泌乳素血症导致抗精神病药物治疗相关的闭经这一观点。如果本研究结果中雌二醇水 </p>

<p>平的预测作用能够得到大样本研究的证实，那么临床医师可以利用这一信息为女性精神分裂症患者选择合适的抗 </p>

<p>精神病药物，对易发生闭经的高风险患者而言可以优先选用导致闭经风险低的药物治疗。 </p>

</text></tei>