<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4214812" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>and Hungary, just about half 
of them are members of the EU. We examined the following variables: socio-organizational indicators, health and educational indicators and 
health indicators. The data used refer to 2002 and as a source of data are used official data from reference WebPages of family medicine doctors 
associations, WONCA website (EURACT, EQuiP, EGPRN), WebPages of Bureau of Statistics of the countries where the research was con-
ducted as well as the Ministries of Health. Results: Results indicates that the failures and shortcomings of health care organizations in Southeast 
Europe. Lack of money hinders the implementation of health care reform in all mentioned countries, the most of them that is more oriented to 
Bismarck financing system. Problems in the political, legal and economic levels are obstacles for efficient a problem reconstructing health care 
system toward family medicine and primary prevention interventions. The population is not enough educated for complicated enforcement for 
and prevention of diseases that have a heavy burden on the budget. Health insurance and payment of health services is often a problem, because 
the patients must be treated regardless of their insurance coverage and financial situation. The decrease in production and economic growth, as 
well as low gross national income in the countries with economic crisis, lead to the inability of treatment for a large number of the population. 
Such situation a system leads to additional debts and loans to healthcare system. Measures implemented for provision of acute curative care largely 
did not lead to improvements in the health status of the population. Educational and preventive measures, as well as higher standards for quality 
and accessibility of health care services for entire population in each country, especially those struggling are bound to joining the European Union 
and their implementation must start. The most A large number of medical institutions are is inefficient in health education and health promotion 
and must work to educate patients and families and increase the quality of preventive health services. Modernization of health care delivery and 
joining the European Union by increasing overall economic stability of countries is one of the primary goals of all countries in Southeast Europe. 
discipline; 
■ The first contact with the health care system; 
■ Provides comprehensive services to all family members, 
regardless of the type of problem, age, sex; 
■ Provides continuous care over time and in different en-
vironments; 
■ Has its own specific epidemiology and uses a specific </p>

<p>DOI: 10.5455/msm.2014.26.277-286 </p>

<p>Received: 16 March 2014; Accepted: 28 June 2014 
© AVICENA 2014 </p>

<p>CASE STUDY </p>

<p>Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 </p>

<p>Published online: 26/08/2014 
Published print: 
08/2014 </p>

<p>CASE STUDY • Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>



<p>process in making decisions; 
■ Deals with health problems in their physical, psychologi-
cal, social and cultural dimensions; 
■ Provides access to the care that is oriented towards the 
patient and which is characterized by creating a close re-
lationship, over time, between doctor and patient; 
■ Promote good health and well-being through appropriate, 
safe and effective interventions; 
■ Makes effective and safe use of resources through coor-
dination of care, management and referral of patients by 
establishing contact with other professionals. 
Over the past two decades in the Southeast European 
countries there has been a great change. In addition to the 
economic, political, geographic we also saw a changes on the 
healthcare plan. 
Countries in transition after the collapse of socialism are 
faced with problems of the citizens insurance, reduced employ-
ment, reduced number of jobs, outdated equipment and a small 
number of health care institutions (2). Experts are searching for 
an effective and feasible way of financing health care through a 
variety of funds, in order to provide relief to courtiers budgets. 
In addition to the disintegration of socialism, war events that 
occurred in the former Yugoslavia setback also a healthcare sys-
tem. Additionally began the privatization of health systems, the 
opening of private health funds modeled on the Western system 
and the introduction of family medicine among the population. 
Before the collapse of the communist bloc in Eastern Eu-
rope, began the reforms that were visible in the early '80s in 
the United Kingdom during the reign of Margaret Thatcher 
(2). Many of these ideas are still not implemented. On the ter-
ritory of Yugoslavia the reason was war, while in Bulgaria and 
Romania the reason was political turmoil and lack of majority 
of votes in the government (2). </p>

<p>1.1. Healthcare in Bulgaria </p>

<p>In Bulgaria, the first health law, which came into practice 
was written 1918 (3). In 1924 the government has enacted the 
first law on health insurance which covered all the people em-
ployed in the private and state companies. In 1925 is adopted the 
Act on the Protection of persons who are unemployed. In the 
period from 1945 up to 1990 was passed several laws related to 
health care of the population. After the collapse of communism, 
it was obvious that the health system is in complete collapse. 
World Bank for development and the European Union have 
initiated various actions and programs for the reconstruction 
of the healthcare system. Besides this, the acts are passed for 
privatization of the health sector. 
Bulgaria health care reform began in 1989 (4). In addition 
to the decentralization of the healthcare system in the system 
is included also the private sector. Financing of healthcare re-
mained the responsibility of the state until the 1998 when was 
passed the law on financing whose application started in 2000. 
HIF was established that coordinates the work of 28 institutes 
across the country. The HIF is funded by revenues from insur-
ance of the employees, while also the self-employed have to pay 
for health insurance. The HIF provides a basic set of health 
insurance in the state or private institutions. 
Primary health care is paid by capitation and the principle 
of payment for services (4). Primary health care is the guardian 
of the passage of patients to specialized branches in hospitals, 
although patients themselves can immediately go to a special-</p>

<p>ist hospital. Vulnerable groups of patients are entitled to a basic 
set of free healthcare. Still, the system itself is not as effective 
and work must be done to improve it. Financing of health care 
institutions is provided by the Ministry of Health. Almost 
92% of Bulgaria's population is covered by compulsory health 
insurance. </p>

<p>1.2. Healthcare in Romania </p>

<p>Romania until 1960 had a system that was based on the Eu-
ropean health care systems. Since 1960 until 1990 the health 
care system started to stagnate. Emphasis is on 1990 and major 
changes that have led to unemployment and poor health care. 
After joining the European Union started new reforms to im-
prove the health care system (4). 
Romania has started the health care reform and decentral-
ization over law on healthcare reform from 1991 (4), when was 
formed 42 departments that are taking care about the health 
care. The reforms that have been implemented in the 1990s 
were financed by the World Bank under the leadership of the 
United Kingdom. After the reform the family medicine doc-
tors are working in their offices completely separate from the 
system of the private sector. Social health burden is growing 
constantly with 64.6% in 1998 to 82.7% of the total health 
services costs in 2004. 
The source of payment is a capitation, payment for services as 
well as bonuses that realize the doctors (4). After adjusting laws 
were in 1997 districts were reformed and they are required to 
control the financing of primary health care. Health Insurance 
is mandatory for a basic set of health care and the protection 
of affected populations. Privatization included pharmaceutical 
activity and dentists while most of the other medical care are 
in the public sector, while the private sector is less represented. </p>

<p>1.3. Healthcare in Albania </p>

<p>Albania before World War II had a small number of doctors. 
Also, the number of institutions in Albania was small. Apart 
from doctors also religious representatives had their own hospi-
tals. Between 1945 and in 1960 the doctors were educated in the 
Soviet Union as well as in some European countries (5). Between 
the 1960 and 1970 begins the reform. In 1980 comes the law on 
health insurance of the population. In 1990 the progress still 
did not occurred due to poor nutrition, poor health system, etc 
(5). Due to the breakup of Yugoslavia, the collapse of the com-
munist system in Albania condition was bad. In 2000 was given 
160 million US$ to improve the health system in Albania (5). 
Financing of health care in Albania before in 1990 was dis-
creet. Each province was paying for health care services through 
employee salaries. In political sense health was separated from 
the rest of the state funding. Hospital managers had to go to 
the Minister of Health regarding the salaries, employment of 
personnel, etc. Today, the health ministry has set aside a special 
fund for the payment of health workers and the maintenance 
of health facilities. Each province fund health institutions in 
their region. 
In Albania HIF was established in 1995 (4). The system is 
managed by social insurance for primary health care, hospital 
care as part of the essential drugs list. Data from 2008 say that 
80% of people is still not covered by health insurance in Albania, 
while 60% paid health insurance by themselves (4). Primary 
health care is provided to endangered part of population, such 
as the unemployed, pensioners, children, etc. </p>



<p>Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 • CASE STUDY </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>1.4. Healthcare in the former Yugoslavia </p>

<p>The health system of Yugoslavia was created before World 
War II. It is made by the Ministry of Health under the direc-
tion of Andrija Stampar. It was based on health centers and 
staff working within them. In addition to GPs also worked 
specialists of different professions as well as secondary medical 
personnel (6). 
Specialization in family medicine was introduced in 1960. 
Still an increasing role in the treatment of patients except for 
specialists of various profiles were family doctors. The system 
was centralized until 1974 when it was transformed into a de-
centralized system. The main executive bodies of the state con-
trolled the operation of all other bodies or managers of primary, 
secondary and tertiary health care (7). Since 1974 the governing 
body is elected at the local government level, state or commu-
nity. Since 1980 in Slovenia and Croatia began implementation 
of a system of state-private ownerships. The idea was that each 
patient can choose a private practice or doctor for their medi-
cal treatment and diagnostics, while the health insurance fund 
refunded and paid to private practice. With the arrival of the 
reforms and the war this type of health care has never come to 
life in its fullest extent. 
Slovenia 
Slovenia is one of the states of the former Yugoslavia. The first 
specialization in family medicine was started in 1960, although 
then called primary health care. Among the first was granted 
independence and first admitted to the European Union. 
Slovenia's population is about 2 millions (8). In 1991 after the 
dissolution and separation from Yugoslavia, there have been 
major political changes as well as changes in the health system 
of the state. In 1992 the health care system is changed to a de-
centralized system (9, 10). At the end of 2006 Slovenia has had 
29 hospitals that were mostly built in the 1970s, but have been 
renovated. Number of beds has increased by 33% between the 
1980 and 2007. Number of hospital days decreased from 10.4 
days in 1995 to 6.8 days in 2007. Number of health centers has 
increased since 1990 and now within 20km there are health 
centers throughout the territory of the Republic of Slovenia (10). 
The main role still has the Ministry of Health which coor-
dinates the operation and development of the health sector. 
Institute for health care system is one and it insures all residents. 
Only the units of health care such as hospitals and clinics are lo-
cated partly in the private sector. Health Insurance Fund covers 
80% of all claims for payment for medical services (10). At the 
present time the biggest problem is the gap between private and 
public property. Regulation of payment in these two institutions 
has not yet been agreed with the government and the Ministry 
of Health. In July 2008 is adopted the Act on the Reform and 
Objectives of Health Care and Care for the period 2008-2013. 
Nowadays, after health care reform there are two depart-
ments of family medicine at Medical Faculties in Ljubljana 
and Maribor. Educators in primary care today numbering over 
2000 trained and certified doctors that pass their knowledge to 
new generations. The family doctor has an obligation to provide 
medical care within 24 hours. 
Croatia 
In Croatia, the development of health care and insurance 
for the population reaches to the 1922 when appeared the first 
private insurance companies modeled on European regula-
tions. The period between the 1920 and 1930 was marked by </p>

<p>professor Andrija Stampar which is one of the pioneers of fam-
ily medicine in Yugoslavia (11). In Croatia during 1968 there 
were 960 GPs. Their scope of action was majority epidemiology 
and preventive medicine. 
After the breakup of Yugoslavia, there was a formation of 
a new organization of the health system. In 1993 the Act is 
designed to address the health care system under the guidance 
and control of the Croatian Ministry of Health. Among other 
things, the Act prescribes medications that are on the essential 
list and surgical procedures covered by the health insurance 
fund. 
The primary responsibility for financing and payment have 
Institute for Insurance. The funding is almost normal practice 
in case of vulnerable populations (children, old population, 
the unemployed, war veterans) covered by the health insurance 
fund. In addition to this there is an additional service package 
of health insurance for those who want to improve their basic 
care. From 2002 the benefit to the new health insurance law 
that changes some of the principles of health insurance and 
introduces some new things (4). In 2005 the amendment was 
placed on the law from the 2002. By this amendment every pa-
tient, unless patients under 18 years of age or over 80% disabled 
people with a disability, have to pay 0.83 U.S.$ or 1.66 U.S.$ to 
obtain the required services in health institutions. In addition 
to this part of the law was added and part of the participation of 
patients during transport and during funeral services by whose 
decree reducing the proportion that is required to pay the HIF. 
Bosnia and Herzegovina 
Historical development of health care goes back in 1879 
during the Austro-Hungarian rule. The first law was passed in 
1888. Organization of health care was like in other parts of the 
world under the rule of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. After the 
arrival of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia in 1918 was enacted sev-
eral laws on health care. The health care was developed equally 
throughout the territory of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia (12). 
Regional Hospital in Sarajevo, opened on the July 1st 1894, 
and was the largest hospital facility in the region and had four 
department (204 beds) (13). The network of health institutions 
and ratio of medical staffs per 1000 inhabitants at the end of 
First World War in B&amp;H was very confort. From 1923 in B&amp;H 
opened a lot of health centers and dispensaries for providing 
primary health care with concept of health promotion, home 
care and polyvalent patronage based on the ideas of professor 
Andrija Stampar as well as the entire territory of Yugoslavia. 
From 1976 in Sarajevo, Mostar and Banja Luka till 1990 was 
organized Family Practice Health Care Units with model of 
providing family practice at home -home care, paliative care, 
health promotion, polyvalent patronage and health education 
of patients at home, schools, work place. Concept was based on 
motto: "whole family with all members at one place of health 
care protection" and "all medical data about family members 
on one family registration card/medical record linkage" (13). 
In Bosnia and Herzegovina affected by the war in 1992-1995 
there was a specific organization of the health system after the 
breakup of Yugoslavia. Each ethnic group in their area had a 
specially designed health care system. 
After the signing of the Dayton Agreement established are 
the two Entities and the Brcko District which together form the 
Bosnia and Herzegovina. In the Federation of Bosnia and Her-
zegovina has been proposed health care system modeled on the </p>

<p>CASE STUDY • Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>



<p>British system while the money to enable the implementation 
provided the World Bank development fund (4). Health Care 
Act and the Law on health insurance is adopted in 1997. Each of 
the 10 cantons has its own health insurance fund, which is filled 
by tax revenues and contributions from employed population. 
The fund is filled by contributions of the employed population 
in the state sector, the private sector, employed as farmers as 
well as payment of certain services. 
Primary health care, which included one doctor and one 
nurse was made in 2001, and payment on the principle of capi-
tation in 2005 brought a reform which covered the majority of 
the population. 
Serbia 
The health care system in Serbia after the changes in 1990 
suffered great stagnation and degradation. After integration in 
2000 is adopted a set of laws and regulations for health sector 
reform. Health Care Act and the Health Insurance Act was 
adopted in 2005. 
The mere reform of family medicine involved the selection 
of doctors for each person individually in their health center. 
Ownership and financing is decentralized to the municipali-
ties. However, if the reform itself well designed and financed 
by the European Agency for the Development of reform itself 
was not accepted by the best medical specialists of different 
profiles. The law protecting endangered population as well as 
the principle of capitation payment. For the majority of the 
population is needed additional payment for medical services. 
Health Insurance does not cover the full scope of costs. For 
primary health care is spent 24.6% and 19.1% of the budget is 
spent on health centers (14). The local community participates 
with 4.4% and 0.2% from donations. Another 11.6% is earned 
by commission from other services such as-provision of services 
and renting space. From this 70% is spent on salaries, 14.5% on 
training and services while the medicines, equipment and other 
supplies consumed 15%. 
In 2009 is published plan for the development of the medical 
sector in which it concluded that today's health care system is 
too large, inefficient, outdated, out of control medical, person-
nel and other resources and the need to urgently launch reforms 
for its improvement (14). 
Montenegro 
The health system of Montenegro was incorporated into 
the system of Serbia until the 2006 (4). After the separation 
the system is based on the free choice of family medicine doc-
tors and dentists in a region that Health Center covers where 
patients live. There are four types of selection for the popula-
tion (4) doctors for children up to 15 years (pediatric), women 
health (gynecologists), doctors and dentists for adults. The 
higher health care is possible in health centers. The system 
of payment is provided in part through capitation and partly 
through performance-related payment (4). 
System of insurance relies on the Health Insurance Fund of 
Montenegro which covers around 97% of the population (4). 
After obtaining the funds from the European Development 
Fund started the further modernization of health care system. 
FYR Macedonia 
Health care reforms were needed in the Republic of Mace-
donia from early phase of transition. Immediately after political 
changes in 1991, the Government initiated a program for health 
care reforms by adopting new Health Care Law and establishing </p>

<p>a single, centralized Health Insurance Fund within the newly 
created Ministry of Health (15-20). Ministry of Health asked 
the World Bank for assistance for further implementation of the 
reform, and Macedonia became a member of the World Bank in 
December 1993. In 1996, a comprehensive health care reform 
was undertaken when the World Bank awarded the Ministry of 
Health a loan of US$19.4 million in order to achieve universal 
access to high quality health care through developing a capita-
tion plan for primary health care (PHC) providers and concept 
of family medicine in PHC, as well as to establish cost effective 
finance and delivery systems (16, 17). The Health Insurance Law 
was adopted in March 2000 and the Health Insurance Fund 
(HIF) was established as an independent institution outside 
of the Ministry of Health. PHC reform has increased patient 
choice through patient enrolment and capitation-based pay-
ment to physicians. The capitation is calculated on the basis of 
numbers of insured persons that have chosen a certain physician 
as their own primary care physician, the determined number of 
points for each category of population group and the determined 
value of each point. Additional incentive is provided for physi-
cians' practices that are located in remote rural areas. 
The paradigm of family medicine offers effective, efficient and 
financially sustainable primary health care. The first initiatives 
for introducing family medicine concept in R. Macedonia ap-
peared in mid 1990s. The Government of Macedonia in 2007 
adopted a document "Health Strategy of R. Macedonia by 2020 
with decision for introducing specialized family physicians as 
the leading team members ("team leaders") that provide health 
services at the PHC (19, 20). Currently different profiles of 
doctors are working at the PHC level (general practitioners, 
specialists in general medicine, pediatricians, school medicine 
specialists, occupational medicine specialists, gynecologists), 
whose qualifications are also different, which might be an ob-
stacle to providing a comprehensive and holistic health care to 
the population (19). The decision of the Government to intro-
duce highly trained specialists in family medicine in primary 
health care is in compliance with the global policies for achieving 
quality standards for offering a good, equal and quality health 
care to the whole population, in accordance with the WHO 
Strategy "Health for All in 21st Century" and toward the inte-
gration process of R. Macedonia for reaching the standards of 
the European Union. According to these standards, all medical 
practitioners should have undergone appropriate postgraduate 
training before they would be allowed to practice family medi-
cine independently. Two crucial elements in this regard need 
to be emphasized: 
-Specialization in family medicine was introduced in Octo-
ber 2009 and, until the end of 2012, 82 physicians passed the 
final exam and become specialist in family medicine (19, 20); 
-Additional education, i.e. additional training for doctors 
working at the PHC level to achieve level of specialists in fam-
ily medicine, started from the mid 2010 through the Center 
of Family Medicine within the Faculty of Medicine in Sko-
pje. Duration of the training is from 3-12 months. Training 
consists of three different categories and locations (Center for 
continuous medical education, hospitals and outpatient doctors' 
offices). The Center was supplied with appropriate equipment 
by the Ministry of Health of Macedonia and the expert and 
educational support was provided by the Department of Family 
Medicine at the Faculty of Medicine in Ljubljana. A Working </p>



<p>Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 • CASE STUDY </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Group of selected experts from the Faculty of Medicine and 
from university clinics in Skopje created clinical guidelines and 
protocols (clinical pathways) in nine priority fields for practicing 
evidence based medicine at PHC level. Until the end of 2012 
more than 130 doctors completed additional training in family 
medicine (19, 20). 
In November 2013 the strategy of the HIF from 2014 to 
2015 was presented publicly. The area that concerns doctors 
of choice at the PHC level is called "More health services at 
one door" with goal to introduce family doctors in the health 
system in Macedonia in 2015 with broadening the scope of 
health services to be available at PHC level (echo diagnostics, 
measurement of blood sugar, lung capacity, some services from 
the general surgery i.e. placing cannulas, replacement of stoma 
bags and litter, removing suture-threads, as well as eyesight 
measurement, examination of the skin, removing foreign bod-
ies from ears, taking microbiological samples etc.). In addition, 
HIF promoted some incentive measures for doctors and teams 
during the first 18 months of their practice and, especially for 
doctors practicing in rural areas. Introducing electronic diary, 
electronic health card and abolishing health books by replacing 
them with electronic health record at the PHC level was pro-
moted as project entitled "Less administration-more time for 
patients". HIF announced to start a campaign to promote health 
in cooperation with all stakeholders in the health system and 
non-governmental organizations which aims to raise awareness 
about certain good habits such as proper diet, physical exercise 
and healthy lifestyle, and to combat harmful habits (smoking, 
overweight etc.) and their impact on health (20). 
Kosovo 
Health care reform in Kosovo was conducted by UNMIK 
after the war in 1999. The new health care system started from 
"scratch" by a committee appointed by the WHO. The system 
itself is based on the European model of health care system (21). 
This way of ensuring health care consists of family medicine 
doctor that serve as entry into system to further treatment and 
care for the patient. The problem is the dualism between Alba-
nians and Serbs living in the same area (22). The private sector 
is legalized in Kosovo, and in the absence of the state sector in 
some parts it replaces functioning of health care (4). The World 
Bank has given the money as part of the reconstruction program. 
In addition to prevent fraud has signed agreements with some 
institutions for primary health care. </p>

<p>1.5. Healthcare in Hungary </p>

<p>Hungary has a long tradition of health care that originated 
from the 11th century. Ambulances were led by monks. The first 
hospital was built in Selmec 1422. The first act on the health care 
system was passed in the 1876. In 1840 the act was passed on 
health insurance of workers and farmers. By the 1940 the health 
care system is carried out through the private sector, as well as 
through some state hospitals. In 1949 the communist system 
brings about the health care law, which says that the health of 
national concern. During 1950's, 60's and 70's the system has 
had great difficulty with the payment and the maintenance of 
health care (23). 
After the fall of communism was established the new govern-
ment. The law that they voted is based on the reconstruction of 
health care from 1990 to 1994 (23). The model has allowed the 
differentiation of local government of the state, authority over 
hospitals, clinics and health centers. During the period from </p>

<p>1990 until 1994 the emphasis is given to primary health care 
as the first contact of the patient and the doctor, the principle 
of capitation payment, choosing a family doctor. In 2001 the 
Law was introduced on the basic package of health insurance 
for every citizen. In the period until 2011 was introduced a 
new reorganization of the health system, which is a image of 
the system in the European Union. </p>

<p>1.6. Healthcare in the Czech Republic </p>

<p>Czech health care system until 1990 was organized by the 
communist system according to Semashko. Czech Republic 
after the breakup met with a number of problems of payment 
for services, outdated systems and little trained personnel (24). 
Such a system demanded reforms that began in 1990. Payment 
of health care services differed depending on whether person 
is an employee or employer, and depending on whether they 
allocated money for health care. Since 1992 begins the work 
of a small private health insurance companied. Their number 
until 1995 increased to 27. Due to the impossibility of payment 
most of them are closed. In order to prevent such events has been 
established insurance fund. 
Health care reform began implementation during the 2005 
and 2006. In addition to hospitals, reform cover also primary 
health care. In January 2009 reform have been completed (24). </p>

<p>1.7. Healthcare in Slovakia </p>

<p>Slovakia during 1990s passed turbulent years after the col-
lapse of communism in that country. Besides Bismarck system 
began the privatization of hospitals. Due to the high corrup-
tion and malfeasance system was brought to the bankruptcy. 
Between the 2002 and 2006 there have been significant reforms. 
In 2007 year began reforms and projects related to health educa-
tion and promotion of healthy lifestyles (25). 
According to international statistics Slovakia has a progres-
sive gross national income. Indirect taxes and paying out of 
pocket increased in the period 2002-2005. The reforms that have 
been implemented have improved the health care system and its 
financing (25). After the elections in 2010 have been adopted 
a new decision on further upgrading the health care system in 
Slovakia as a standard diagnostic entering the basic insurance, 
new directions in medicine based on evidence, accreditation of 
health institutions, supervision of medical institutions, as well 
as prescribing medications and providing basic medicines to 
those who are not insured (25). </p>

<p>2. GOAL 
The Goal of this study is to present the role and importance 
of family medicine, or where is family today in the 21st Century 
since the beginning of development in these countries. </p>

<p>3. MATERIAL AND METHODS 
The study was designed as a descriptive epidemiological study 
with data from 10 countries of the former Communist bloc: 
Slovenia, Croatia, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Serbia, Montene-
gro, Macedonia, Kosovo, Albania, Bulgaria, Romania, Hungary, 
Czech Republic and Slovakia. 
The following variables were observed: (1) Economic and 
organizational data, (2) health and educational indicators (3) 
Health indicators. 
The data used refer to the period 2002-2012, and as a source 
of data were used official data from reference web pages of 
associations of family medicine doctors, WONCA website </p>

<p>CASE STUDY • Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>



<p>(EURACT, EQuiP, EGPRN), web page of the Bureau of Sta-
tistics of the countries where the research was conducted as well 
as the Ministries of Health (21). 
Data collected in the above manner were then entered in </p>

<p>a purpose-created database. The data were analyzed by using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Microsoft Office</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2010</rs> (8). </p>

<p>4. RESULTS 
Economic and organizational indicators </p>

<p>Of the total number of observed countries of South Eastern Europe (n=12), the highest gross </p>

<p>domestic product (GDP) per capita has Croatia ($ 9,000), followed by Slovenia ($ 8,400), </p>

<p>Serbia ($ 8,200), while the countries with the lowest GDP are: Albania ($ 3.700), Bulgaria ($ </p>

<p>4800) and Slovakia ($ 5,700). Bosnia and Herzegovina is located in the middle of the table, </p>

<p>with its GDP per capita of $ 7,500 (Figure 1) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Figure 1. GDP per capita in countries of SE Europe </p>

<p>Figure 2. Total expenditure per capita in the countries of SE Europe </p>

<p>The highest total expenditure per capita has Slovenia (821%), Czech Republic (407%) and </p>

<p>Croatia (394%), while Serbia has the lowest (7%), Albania (48%) and Bulgaria (81%). </p>

<p>3700 </p>

<p>4800 </p>

<p>5700 </p>

<p>6500 </p>

<p>6800 </p>

<p>6800 </p>

<p>7400 </p>

<p>7500 </p>

<p>7800 </p>

<p>8200 </p>

<p>8400 </p>

<p>9000 </p>

<p>0 1000 2000 3000 4000 5000 6000 7000 8000 9000 10000 </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>GDP ($) per capita </p>

<p>7,0% </p>

<p>48,0% </p>

<p>81,0% </p>

<p>85,0% </p>

<p>115,0% </p>

<p>117,0% </p>

<p>120,3% </p>

<p>216,0% </p>

<p>345,0% </p>

<p>394,0% </p>

<p>407,0% </p>

<p>821,0% </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 300 
400 
500 600 
700 
800 900 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Figure 1. GDP per capita in countries of SE Europe </p>

<p>Of the total number of observed countries of South Eastern Europe (n=12), the highest gross </p>

<p>domestic product (GDP) per capita has Croatia ($ 9,000), followed by Slovenia ($ 8,400), </p>

<p>Serbia ($ 8,200), while the countries with the lowest GDP are: Albania ($ 3.700), Bulgaria ($ </p>

<p>4800) and Slovakia ($ 5,700). Bosnia and Herzegovina is located in the middle of the table, </p>

<p>with its GDP per capita of $ 7,500 (Figure 1) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Figure 1. GDP per capita in countries of SE Europe </p>

<p>Figure 2. Total expenditure per capita in the countries of SE Europe </p>

<p>The highest total expenditure per capita has Slovenia (821%), Czech Republic (407%) and </p>

<p>Croatia (394%), while Serbia has the lowest (7%), Albania (48%) and Bulgaria (81%). </p>

<p>3700 </p>

<p>4800 </p>

<p>5700 </p>

<p>6500 </p>

<p>6800 </p>

<p>6800 </p>

<p>7400 </p>

<p>7500 </p>

<p>7800 </p>

<p>8200 </p>

<p>8400 </p>

<p>9000 </p>

<p>0 1000 2000 3000 4000 5000 6000 7000 8000 9000 10000 </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>GDP ($) per capita </p>

<p>7,0% </p>

<p>48,0% </p>

<p>81,0% </p>

<p>85,0% </p>

<p>115,0% </p>

<p>117,0% </p>

<p>120,3% </p>

<p>216,0% </p>

<p>345,0% </p>

<p>394,0% </p>

<p>407,0% </p>

<p>821,0% </p>

<p>0 
100 200 300 400 
500 600 
700 
800 900 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Figure 2. Total expenditure per capita in the countries of SE Europe </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina is located in the middle of the bottom part of the table with 85% </p>

<p>(Figure 2) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>The largest expenditures for health care by U.S. dollar exchange rate has Slovenia, Czech </p>

<p>Republic and Hungary, while the lowest have: Serbia, Albania and Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>(Figure 3) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Health expenditures per U.S. dollar exchange rate in the countries of SE Europe </p>

<p>Figure 4. Claims for health per capita per U.S. dollar exchange rate in the countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>26,0 </p>

<p>150,0 </p>

<p>268,0 </p>

<p>303,0 </p>

<p>331,0 </p>

<p>460,0 </p>

<p>582,2 </p>

<p>681,0 </p>

<p>726,0 </p>

<p>914,0 </p>

<p>1290,0 </p>

<p>1545,0 </p>

<p>0 
200 400 600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>16,0 </p>

<p>16,9 </p>

<p>97,0 </p>

<p>99,0 </p>

<p>248,0 </p>

<p>281,0 </p>

<p>365,0 </p>

<p>593,0 </p>

<p>608,0 </p>

<p>686,0 </p>

<p>1031,0 </p>

<p>1157,0 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
1400 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Figure 3. Health expenditures per U.S. dollar exchange rate in the countries 
of SE Europe </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina is located in the middle of the bottom part of the table with 85% </p>

<p>(Figure 2) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>The largest expenditures for health care by U.S. dollar exchange rate has Slovenia, Czech </p>

<p>Republic and Hungary, while the lowest have: Serbia, Albania and Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>(Figure 3) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Health expenditures per U.S. dollar exchange rate in the countries of SE Europe </p>

<p>Figure 4. Claims for health per capita per U.S. dollar exchange rate in the countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>26,0 </p>

<p>150,0 </p>

<p>268,0 </p>

<p>303,0 </p>

<p>331,0 </p>

<p>460,0 </p>

<p>582,2 </p>

<p>681,0 </p>

<p>726,0 </p>

<p>914,0 </p>

<p>1290,0 </p>

<p>1545,0 </p>

<p>0 
200 400 600 800 1000 1200 1400 1600 1800 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>16,0 </p>

<p>16,9 </p>

<p>97,0 </p>

<p>99,0 </p>

<p>248,0 </p>

<p>281,0 </p>

<p>365,0 </p>

<p>593,0 </p>

<p>608,0 </p>

<p>686,0 </p>

<p>1031,0 </p>

<p>1157,0 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
1400 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Figure 4. Claims for health per capita per U.S. dollar exchange rate in the 
countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Of the total number of observed countries of Southeast Europe (n=12), Bosnia and </p>

<p>Herzegovina has the highest claims for health care in the private sector (63.2%), followed by </p>

<p>Albania (35.4%), Slovenia (25.1%) and Hungary (25.0%), while the lowest claims in the </p>

<p>private sector have the Czech Republic (8.6%) and Slovakia (10.7%) (Figure 5) </p>

<p>(22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Claims for health care from state and the private sector in the countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Figure 6. Number of health facilities by type of sector in the countries of South Eastern 
Europe </p>

<p>91,4 </p>

<p>89,3 </p>

<p>84,9 </p>

<p>82,1 </p>

<p>81,8 </p>

<p>79,2 </p>

<p>79,2 </p>

<p>75,4 </p>

<p>75,0 </p>

<p>74,9 </p>

<p>64,6 </p>

<p>36,8 </p>

<p>8,6 </p>

<p>10,7 </p>

<p>15,1 </p>

<p>17,9 </p>

<p>18,2 </p>

<p>20,8 </p>

<p>20,8 </p>

<p>24,6 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>25,1 </p>

<p>35,4 </p>

<p>63,2 </p>

<p>0% 10% 20% 30% 40% 50% 60% 70% 80% 90% 100% </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>General governmental claims for health care 
Private claims for health care </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>158 </p>

<p>415 </p>

<p>577 </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>177 </p>

<p>1477 </p>

<p>23886 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>158 </p>

<p>415 </p>

<p>577 </p>

<p>1610 </p>

<p>24063 </p>

<p>1 
10 
100 
1000 
10000 
100000 </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Logarithmic scale </p>

<p>Total number of registered heath institutions </p>

<p>Number of registered private institutions </p>

<p>Number of state owned health institutions </p>

<p>Figure 5. Claims for health care from state and the private sector in the 
countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>The highest claims for health care per capita per U.S. dollar exchange rate have: Slovenia </p>

<p>and the Czech Republic, while the lowest has: Serbia and Montenegro. Bosnia and </p>

<p>Herzegovina is located in the lower part of the table (Figure 4) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Of the total number of observed countries of Southeast Europe (n=12), Bosnia and </p>

<p>Herzegovina has the highest claims for health care in the private sector (63.2%), followed by </p>

<p>Albania (35.4%), Slovenia (25.1%) and Hungary (25.0%), while the lowest claims in the </p>

<p>private sector have the Czech Republic (8.6%) and Slovakia (10.7%) (Figure 5) </p>

<p>(22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Claims for health care from state and the private sector in the countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Figure 6. Number of health facilities by type of sector in the countries of South Eastern 
Europe </p>

<p>91,4 </p>

<p>89,3 </p>

<p>84,9 </p>

<p>82,1 </p>

<p>81,8 </p>

<p>79,2 </p>

<p>79,2 </p>

<p>75,4 </p>

<p>75,0 </p>

<p>74,9 </p>

<p>64,6 </p>

<p>36,8 </p>

<p>8,6 </p>

<p>10,7 </p>

<p>15,1 </p>

<p>17,9 </p>

<p>18,2 </p>

<p>20,8 </p>

<p>20,8 </p>

<p>24,6 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>25,1 </p>

<p>35,4 </p>

<p>63,2 </p>

<p>0% 10% 20% 30% 40% 50% 60% 70% 80% 90% 100% </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>General governmental claims for health care 
Private claims for health care </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>158 </p>

<p>415 </p>

<p>577 </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>177 </p>

<p>1477 </p>

<p>23886 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>158 </p>

<p>415 </p>

<p>577 </p>

<p>1610 </p>

<p>24063 </p>

<p>1 
10 
100 
1000 
10000 
100000 </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Logarithmic scale </p>

<p>Total number of registered heath institutions </p>

<p>Number of registered private institutions </p>

<p>Number of state owned health institutions </p>

<p>Figure 6. Number of health facilities by type of sector in the countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>The largest number of state owned health institutions was recorded in Hungary (n=577) and </p>

<p>Albania (n=415), while the data for the registered private institutions was available only for </p>

<p>the Czech Republic (n=23,886) and Bosnia and Herzegovina (n=1477) (Figure 6) </p>

<p>(22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>The highest density of health facilities per 100,000 citizens is found in the Czech Republic </p>

<p>(232.1), followed by: Bosnia and Herzegovina (42.7) and Albania (13.2), while countries </p>

<p>such as Romania (0.02), Slovakia (0, 29) and Croatia (0.82) are the countries with the lowest </p>

<p>density. Data for other countries covered by the study were not available (Figure 7) </p>

<p>(22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Figure 7. The density of health facilities per 100,000 inhabitants in countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>2. Health and educational indicators </p>

<p>The countries with the highest number of public medical faculties are: Romania (n=12), </p>

<p>Bulgaria (n=8) and Czech Republic (n=7). Following, Bosnia and Herzegovina (n=5), </p>

<p>Albania, Hungary, Croatia and Serbia (n=4), Slovakia and Macedonia (n=3), Slovenia has </p>

<p>two medical faculties and Montenegro has one medical school (Figure 8) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>0,0188 </p>

<p>0,2960 </p>

<p>0,8152 </p>

<p>2,1286 </p>

<p>3,1681 </p>

<p>5,7742 </p>

<p>13,1526 </p>

<p>42,7444 </p>

<p>232,0679 </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 
150 
200 
250 </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Figure 7. The density of health facilities per 100,000 inhabitants in countries 
of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Figure 8. The number of medical faculties in the states of SE Europe </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
10 
12 
14 </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Number of medical faculties </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>816 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>115 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Figure 8. The number of medical faculties in the states of SE Europe </p>



<p>Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 • CASE STUDY </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Of the total number of observed countries of South Eastern 
Europe (n=12), the highest gross domestic product (GDP) per 
capita has Croatia ($ 9,000), followed by Slovenia ($ 8,400), 
Serbia ($ 8,200), while the countries with the lowest GDP are: 
Albania ($ 3.700), Bulgaria ($ 4800) and Slovakia ($ 5,700). 
Bosnia and Herzegovina is located in the middle of the table, 
with its GDP per capita of $ 7,500 (Figure 1) (22,23,24,53). 
The highest total expenditure per capita has Slovenia (821%), 
Czech Republic (407%) and Croatia (394%), while Serbia has 
the lowest (7%), Albania (48%) and Bulgaria (81%). Bosnia and 
Herzegovina is located in the middle of the bottom part of the 
table with 85% (Figure 2) (22,23,24,53). 
The largest expenditures for health care by U.S. dollar ex-
change rate has Slovenia, Czech Republic and Hungary, while 
the lowest have: Serbia, Albania and Bosnia and Herzegovina 
(Figure 3) (22,23,24,53). 
The highest claims for health care per capita per U.S. dollar 
exchange rate have: Slovenia and the Czech Republic, while the 
lowest has: Serbia and Montenegro. Bosnia and Herzegovina is 
located in the lower part of the table (Figure 4) (22,23,24,53). 
Of the total number of observed countries of Southeast Eu-
rope (n=12), Bosnia and Herzegovina has the highest claims for 
health care in the private sector (63.2%), followed by Albania 
(35.4%), Slovenia (25.1%) and Hungary (25.0%), while the low-
est claims in the private sector have the Czech Republic (8.6%) 
and Slovakia (10.7%) (Figure 5) (22,23,24,53). 
The largest number of state owned health institutions was 
recorded in Hungary (n=577) and Albania (n=415), while the 
data for the registered private institutions was available only for 
the Czech Republic (n=23,886) and Bosnia and Herzegovina 
(n=1477) (Figure 6) (22,23,24,53). 
The highest density of health facilities per 100,000 citizens 
is found in the Czech Republic (232.1), followed by: Bosnia 
and Herzegovina (42.7) and Albania (13.2), while countries 
such as Romania (0.02), Slovakia (0, 29) and Croatia (0.82) are 
the countries with the lowest density. Data for other countries 
covered by the study were not available (Figure 7) (22,23,24,53). 
Health and educational indicators 
The countries with the highest number of public medical fac-
ulties are: Romania (n=12), Bulgaria (n=8) and Czech Republic 
(n=7). Following, Bosnia and Herzegovina (n=5), Albania, 
Hungary, Croatia and Serbia (n=4), Slovakia and Macedonia 
(n=3), Slovenia has two medical faculties and Montenegro has 
one medical school (Figure 8) (22,23,24,53). 
In Macedonia, Albania, Croatia, Hungary and Slovakia all 
students who begin training in family medicine complete the 
specialization. Of the total number of participants in the edu-
cation in family medicine in Bosnia and Herzegovina (n=126), 
115 of them or 91.3% complete residency in family medicine. 
Of the total number of participants at the beginning of special-
ization in the Czech Republic a total of 90% of them complete 
the specialization, in Slovenia and Serbia 83.3% and 73.5% in 
Romania (Figure 9) (22,23,24,53). 
In Montenegro, Serbia, Croatia and Slovenia specialization 
in family medicine lasts four years, unlike Slovakia, where 
specialization is 3.5 years. In the Czech Republic, Romania, 
Bulgaria, Hungary, Macedonia and Bosnia and Herzegovina 
specialization lasts three years, but only in Albania last two 
years (Chart 10) (22,23,24,53). 
Health indicators </p>

<p>The lowest mortality rate in the age group &lt;5 years for males 
have Slovenia and the Czech Republic (5.0/100,000), while 
the highest mortality rates in this age group for males is in Al-</p>

<p>Figure 8. The number of medical faculties in the states of SE Europe </p>

<p>Figure 9. The number of participants and of those who completed residency in family 
medicine in the countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>In Macedonia, Albania, Croatia, Hungary and Slovakia all students who begin training in </p>

<p>family medicine complete the specialization. Of the total number of participants in the </p>

<p>education in family medicine in Bosnia and Herzegovina (n=126), 115 of them or 91.3% </p>

<p>complete residency in family medicine. Of the total number of participants at the beginning </p>

<p>of specialization in the Czech Republic a total of 90% of them complete the specialization, in </p>

<p>Slovenia and Serbia 83.3% and 73.5% in Romania (Figure 9) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 
10 
12 
14 </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Number of medical faculties </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>126 </p>

<p>816 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>115 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Number of residents 
Number of persons who started residency in family medicine </p>

<p>Number of residents who completed education in family medicine </p>

<p>Figure 9. The number of participants and of those who completed residency in 
family medicine in the countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>In Montenegro, Serbia, Croatia and Slovenia specialization in family medicine lasts four </p>

<p>years, unlike Slovakia, where specialization is 3.5 years. In the Czech Republic, Romania, </p>

<p>Bulgaria, Hungary, Macedonia and Bosnia and Herzegovina specialization lasts three years, </p>

<p>but only in Albania last two years (Chart 10) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Figure 10. Duration of residency (years) in family medicine in the countries of South Eastern 
Europe </p>

<p>3. Health indicators </p>

<p>The lowest mortality rate in the age group &lt;5 years for males have Slovenia and the Czech </p>

<p>Republic (5.0/100,000), while the highest mortality rates in this age group for males is in </p>

<p>Albania (27/100.000) and Romania (22.0/100,000) and Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>(20.0/100,000). The lowest mortality rate in the age group &lt;5 years for females also have </p>

<p>Slovenia and the Czech Republic (4.0/100,000), while the highest mortality rates in this age </p>

<p>group is in Albania (23/100.000) and Romania (19.0/100.000), and Bosnia and Herzegovina, </p>

<p>Macedonia and Bulgaria (15.0/100,000) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>2,0 </p>

<p>3,0 </p>

<p>3,0 </p>

<p>3,0 </p>

<p>3,0 </p>

<p>3,0 </p>

<p>3,0 </p>

<p>3,5 </p>

<p>4,0 </p>

<p>4,0 </p>

<p>4,0 </p>

<p>4,0 </p>

<p>0 
0,5 
1 
1,5 
2 
2,5 
3 
3,5 
4 
4,5 </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Duration of residency (years) </p>

<p>Figure 10. Duration of residency (years) in family medicine in the countries 
of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Figure 11. Mortality by the age groups per 100.0000 inhabitants in countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>The lowest mortality rate in the age group 15-59 years for males is in Montenegro </p>

<p>(132.0/100,000), Slovenia and the Czech Republic (163.0/100,000), while the highest </p>

<p>mortality rates in this age group for males are in: Hungary (259/100,000), Romania </p>

<p>(235/100,000) and Bulgaria (218.0/100,000). The lowest mortality rate in the age group 15-</p>

<p>59 years for females, too, have Montenegro (68.0/100,000), Slovenia (71.0/100,000), Czech </p>

<p>Republic and Croatia (72.0/100,000), while the highest mortality rates in this age group for is </p>

<p>in Hungary (110/100.000) and Romania (108.0/100,000) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>In percent, the highest mortality in the population above 60 years of age was observed in </p>

<p>Bulgaria and Croatia (27.1%), while the lowest in Albania (9.5%) and Bosnia and </p>

<p>Herzegovina (15.3%) (Figure 12) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>5 
8 </p>

<p>20 
17 
14 
17 
10 </p>

<p>27 
17 
22 </p>

<p>5 
11 
4 
7 </p>

<p>15 
13 
10 
15 
9 </p>

<p>23 
15 
19 </p>

<p>4 
9 </p>

<p>163 
178 
192 
186 </p>

<p>132 </p>

<p>195 </p>

<p>259 </p>

<p>167 </p>

<p>218 
235 </p>

<p>163 </p>

<p>206 </p>

<p>71 
72 </p>

<p>90 
98 </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>110 </p>

<p>94 
94 </p>

<p>108 </p>

<p>72 
79 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>SLO 
CRO 
BIH 
SRB 
MNE MKD HUN 
ALB 
BGR 
ROU 
CZE 
SVK </p>

<p>Mortality per 100,000 inhabitantns </p>

<p>&lt;5 yrs. Male 
&lt;5 yrs. Female 
15-59 yrs. Male 
15-59 yrs. Female </p>

<p>Figure 11. Mortality by the age groups per 100.0000 inhabitants in countries 
of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Figure 12. Mortality in age group over 60 years in countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>In all the countries of SE Europe, the most common are cardiovascular diseases, with the </p>

<p>highest rate of incidence in Bulgaria (4.478/100.000), Hungary (4.193/100.000) and Bosnia </p>

<p>and Herzegovina (4.016/100.000). The lowest rate of developing cardiovascular disease are </p>

<p>in Slovenia (1.602/100.000) and Croatia (2.373/100.000). The highest incidence rate of </p>

<p>developing respiratory diseases is in Hungary (695.0/100,000) and Czech Republic </p>

<p>(639.0/100,000) , while the lowest rates are in Bulgaria (320.0/100,000) and Romania </p>

<p>9,5% </p>

<p>15,3% </p>

<p>15,5% </p>

<p>17,6% </p>

<p>18,4% </p>

<p>18,6% </p>

<p>18,8% </p>

<p>18,9% </p>

<p>19,8% </p>

<p>20,0% </p>

<p>21,7% </p>

<p>21,7% </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Montenegro </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Mortality in age group &gt;60 years </p>

<p>Figure 12. Mortality in age group over 60 years in countries of South Eastern 
Europe </p>

<p>CASE STUDY • Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>



<p>bania (27/100.000) and Romania (22.0/100,000) and Bosnia 
and Herzegovina (20.0/100,000). The lowest mortality rate in 
the age group &lt;5 years for females also have Slovenia and the 
Czech Republic (4.0/100,000), while the highest mortality 
rates in this age group is in Albania (23/100.000) and Romania 
(19.0/100.000), and Bosnia and Herzegovina, Macedonia and 
Bulgaria (15.0/100,000) (22,23,24,53). 
The lowest mortality rate in the age group 15-59 years for 
males is in Montenegro (132.0/100,000), Slovenia and the 
Czech Republic (163.0/100,000), while the highest mortality 
rates in this age group for males are in: Hungary (259/100,000), 
Romania (235/100,000) and Bulgaria (218.0/100,000). The 
lowest mortality rate in the age group 15-59 years for females, 
too, have Montenegro (68.0/100,000), Slovenia (71.0/100,000), 
Czech Republic and Croatia (72.0/100,000), while the highest 
mortality rates in this age group for is in Hungary (110/100.000) 
and Romania (108.0/100,000) (22,23,24,53). 
In percent, the highest mortality in the population above 
60 years of age was observed in Bulgaria and Croatia (27.1%), 
while the lowest in Albania (9.5%) and Bosnia and Herzegovina 
(15.3%) (Figure 12) (26, 27, 28). 
In all the countries of SE Europe, the most common are car-
diovascular diseases, with the highest rate of incidence in Bul-
garia (4.478/100.000), Hungary (4.193/100.000) and Bosnia 
and Herzegovina (4.016/100.000). The lowest rate of develop-
ing cardiovascular disease are in Slovenia (1.602/100.000) and 
Croatia (2.373/100.000). The highest incidence rate of devel-
oping respiratory diseases is in Hungary (695.0/100,000) and </p>

<p>Czech Republic (639.0/100,000) , while the lowest rates are in 
Bulgaria (320.0/100,000) and Romania (368.0/100,000). The 
highest incidence rate of developing malignancies have Hun-
gary (3,044.0/100,000), Czech Republic (2,571.0/100,000) 
and Slovakia (2.144/100.00), while the lowest rate are in 
Bosnia and Herzegovina (1,429.0/100,000) and Bulgaria 
(1540.0/100,000). The highest incidence rate of developing 
genitourinary diseases have Macedonia (196.0/100,000 ) and 
Albania (195.0/100,000), while the lowest rates are in Slove-
nia (58.0/100,000) and Croatia (76.0/100,000). The highest 
incidence rate of developing diabetes mellitus have Hungary 
(369.0/100,000) and Bulgaria (349.0/100,000), while the 
lowest rates are in Croatia (172.0/100,000) and Albania 
(177.0/100,000) (26, 27, 28, 32, 33). 
The highest incidence rate of developing musculoskel-
etal disorders are in Hungary (760.0/100,000), and Slova-
kia (753.0/100,000), while the lowest rates are in Croatia 
(396.0/100,000) and Slovenia (402.0/100,000) (26, 27, 28). 
Best coverage of immunization against rubella among 
children &lt;1 year of age have Slovakia and Hungary (99.0%), 
while the lowest coverage is in Bulgaria (90%), Serbia (90%) 
and Bosnia and Herzegovina (92%) (Figure 14). The highest 
rate of maternal mortality are in Romania (58.0/100,000) 
and Albania (55.0/100,000), while the lowest mortality rates 
have Serbia and the Czech Republic (9.0/100,000), as well as 
Croatia and Slovakia (10.0/100,000). Bosnia and Herzegovina 
is located in the middle of the table with a maternal mortality 
rate of 31.0/100,000 (Figure 15) (26, 27, 28, 32, 33). 
The highest prevalence of TB has Romania (189.0/100,000) 
and Bosnia and Herzegovina (76.0/100,000), while the lowest </p>

<p>Figure 13. The most common diseases in the population at 100,000 inhabitants in the 
countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Figure 14. The coverage of immunization of children against rubella aged &lt;1 year in the 
countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Best coverage of immunization against rubella among children &lt;1 year of age have Slovakia </p>

<p>and Hungary (99.0%), while the lowest coverage is in Bulgaria (90%), Serbia (90%) and </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina (92%) (Figure 14). The highest rate of maternal mortality are in </p>

<p>1602 </p>

<p>2373 </p>

<p>3358 </p>

<p>3422 </p>

<p>3481 </p>

<p>2615 </p>

<p>3696 </p>

<p>3836 </p>

<p>4016 </p>

<p>4193 </p>

<p>4478 </p>

<p>528 </p>

<p>596 
639 401 </p>

<p>368 </p>

<p>416 </p>

<p>386 </p>

<p>466 </p>

<p>431 </p>

<p>695 </p>

<p>320 </p>

<p>1699 </p>

<p>1761 </p>

<p>2571 </p>

<p>2144 </p>

<p>1640 </p>

<p>1922 </p>

<p>1665 
1826 1429 </p>

<p>3044 </p>

<p>1540 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>129 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>101 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>195 </p>

<p>196 </p>

<p>168 </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>129 </p>

<p>234 </p>

<p>172 </p>

<p>269 </p>

<p>301 </p>

<p>258 </p>

<p>287 </p>

<p>177 </p>

<p>289 </p>

<p>223 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>349 </p>

<p>402 </p>

<p>396 </p>

<p>507 </p>

<p>753 </p>

<p>666 </p>

<p>675 </p>

<p>677 </p>

<p>665 </p>

<p>666 </p>

<p>760 </p>

<p>666 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
2000 
3000 
4000 
5000 
6000 
7000 
8000 
9000 
10000 </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>FYR Macedonia </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Number per 100,000 inhabitants </p>

<p>Cardiovascular diseases 
Respiratory diseases 
Malignant diseases </p>

<p>Genitourinary diseases 
Diabetes mellitus 
Musculoskeletal diseases </p>

<p>90,0% </p>

<p>90,0% </p>

<p>92,0% </p>

<p>92,0% </p>

<p>94,0% </p>

<p>94,0% </p>

<p>95,0% </p>

<p>97,0% </p>

<p>98,0% </p>

<p>99,0% </p>

<p>99,0% </p>

<p>84 
86 
88 
90 
92 
94 
96 
98 
100 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Figure 13. The most common diseases in the population at 100,000 
inhabitants in the countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Figure 13. The most common diseases in the population at 100,000 inhabitants in the 
countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Figure 14. The coverage of immunization of children against rubella aged &lt;1 year in the 
countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Best coverage of immunization against rubella among children &lt;1 year of age have Slovakia </p>

<p>and Hungary (99.0%), while the lowest coverage is in Bulgaria (90%), Serbia (90%) and </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina (92%) (Figure 14). The highest rate of maternal mortality are in </p>

<p>1602 </p>

<p>2373 </p>

<p>3358 </p>

<p>3422 </p>

<p>3481 </p>

<p>2615 </p>

<p>3696 </p>

<p>3836 </p>

<p>4016 </p>

<p>4193 </p>

<p>4478 </p>

<p>528 </p>

<p>596 
639 401 </p>

<p>368 </p>

<p>416 </p>

<p>386 </p>

<p>466 </p>

<p>431 </p>

<p>695 </p>

<p>320 </p>

<p>1699 </p>

<p>1761 </p>

<p>2571 </p>

<p>2144 </p>

<p>1640 </p>

<p>1922 </p>

<p>1665 
1826 1429 </p>

<p>3044 </p>

<p>1540 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>129 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>101 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>195 </p>

<p>196 </p>

<p>168 </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>129 </p>

<p>234 </p>

<p>172 </p>

<p>269 </p>

<p>301 </p>

<p>258 </p>

<p>287 </p>

<p>177 </p>

<p>289 </p>

<p>223 </p>

<p>369 </p>

<p>349 </p>

<p>402 </p>

<p>396 </p>

<p>507 </p>

<p>753 </p>

<p>666 </p>

<p>675 </p>

<p>677 </p>

<p>665 </p>

<p>666 </p>

<p>760 </p>

<p>666 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
2000 
3000 
4000 
5000 
6000 
7000 
8000 
9000 
10000 </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>FYR Macedonia </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Number per 100,000 inhabitants </p>

<p>Cardiovascular diseases 
Respiratory diseases 
Malignant diseases </p>

<p>Genitourinary diseases 
Diabetes mellitus 
Musculoskeletal diseases </p>

<p>90,0% </p>

<p>90,0% </p>

<p>92,0% </p>

<p>92,0% </p>

<p>94,0% </p>

<p>94,0% </p>

<p>95,0% </p>

<p>97,0% </p>

<p>98,0% </p>

<p>99,0% </p>

<p>99,0% </p>

<p>84 
86 
88 
90 
92 
94 
96 
98 
100 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Figure 14. The coverage of immunization of children against rubella aged &lt;1 
year in the countries of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Romania (58.0/100,000) and Albania (55.0/100,000), while the lowest mortality rates have </p>

<p>Serbia and the Czech Republic (9.0/100,000), as well as Croatia and Slovakia </p>

<p>(10.0/100,000). Bosnia and Herzegovina is located in the middle of the table with a maternal </p>

<p>mortality rate of 31.0/100,000 (Figure 15) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Graph 15. Maternal mortality rate per 100,000 inhabitants in the countries of South Eastern 
Europe </p>

<p>The highest prevalence of TB has Romania (189.0/100,000) and Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>(76.0/100,000), while the lowest rates are in the Czech Republic (13.0/100,000) and Slovenia </p>

<p>(23.0/100,000) (Figure 16) (22,23,24,25). </p>

<p>Figure 16. The prevalence of tuberculosis per 100,000 inhabitants in countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Maternal deaths per 100,000 inhabitants </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>189 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 100 120 140 160 180 200 </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Number of TBC peatients per 100,000 inhabitants </p>

<p>Graph 15. Maternal mortality rate per 100,000 inhabitants in the countries 
of South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>Serbia and the Czech Republic (9.0/100,000), as well as Croatia and Slovakia </p>

<p>(10.0/100,000). Bosnia and Herzegovina is located in the middle of the table with a maternal </p>

<p>mortality rate of 31.0/100,000 (Figure 15) (22,23,24,53). </p>

<p>Graph 15. Maternal mortality rate per 100,000 inhabitants in the countries of South Eastern 
Europe </p>

<p>The highest prevalence of TB has Romania (189.0/100,000) and Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>(76.0/100,000), while the lowest rates are in the Czech Republic (13.0/100,000) and Slovenia </p>

<p>(23.0/100,000) (Figure 16) (22,23,24,25). </p>

<p>Figure 16. The prevalence of tuberculosis per 100,000 inhabitants in countries of South 
Eastern Europe </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>58 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Maternal deaths per 100,000 inhabitants </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>65 </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>189 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 100 120 140 160 180 200 </p>

<p>Check Republic </p>

<p>Slovenia </p>

<p>Albania </p>

<p>Hungary </p>

<p>Slovakia </p>

<p>Serbia </p>

<p>Bulgaria </p>

<p>FYR of Macedonica </p>

<p>Croatia </p>

<p>Bosnia and Herzegovina </p>

<p>Romania </p>

<p>Number of TBC peatients per 100,000 inhabitants </p>

<p>Figure 16. The prevalence of tuberculosis per 100,000 inhabitants in 
countries of South Eastern Europe. </p>



<p>Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 • CASE STUDY </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>

<p>rates are in the Czech Republic (13.0/100,000) and Slovenia 
(23.0/100,000) (Figure 16) (26, 27, 28). </p>

<p>5. DISCUSSION 
Overview of the development of family medicine in the 
countries of Southeast Europe provides the possibility of under-
standing also the development of health care in these countries. 
Comparison of the system of education in undergraduate and 
postgraduate studies, the number of illnesses and the state of 
the global population health in areas that have been investigated 
also allow the comparison that is the basis for health care the 
system. Cross-section of the results provides insight into the 
further development of family medicine and the problems that 
should be focused. 
The highest gross national income of the countries in the 
region has Croatia, followed by Slovenia, Serbia, Bosnia and 
Herzegovina which is located in the middle of the scale. Croatia 
unlike Bosnia and Herzegovina has developed summer tourism, 
which contributes to filling the budget, and thus more payments 
in the health sector. Croatia is the only country that is after the 
breakup of Yugoslavia held the growth of tourism (29, 30, 31). 
Slovenia unlike the Croatia, by entering the European Union 
has lost markets and regulation that had before. Albania, Bul-
garia and Romania are the countries affected by the transition 
after, the collapse of communism. Weak growth of production 
and investment have led to a low GDP. 
When talking about the expenditure, the highest are in Slo-
venia, followed by Czech Republic and then Croatia. The prepa-
rations for Slovenia's entry into the European Union have led to 
the need for alignment of regulations with European standards 
in healthcare (11). Croatia also due to the aspirations for the 
European Union have a need to improve its health care system. 
Czech Republic, which is in the European Union prepares its 
health insurance system compatible with Europe. Serbia, Al-
bania and Bosnia and Herzegovina as a countries in which the 
reconstruction of health system has not yet been completed, as 
well as harmonization of standards with EU standards has the 
lowest cost for health care in the region (32-35). 
Demand for health services is highest in Slovenia, the Czech 
Republic and Hungary. European funds and education of the 
population have led to an increase in demand of the population 
for health services (12). Bosnia and Herzegovina is located on 
the bottom. The reason for these results lies in the fact that the 
majority of citizens is uninsured and only in emergencies seek 
doctor's help. 
The largest number of medical institutions is registered in 
the Czech Republic, Bosnia and Herzegovina and Hungary. The 
reason for these results is the large number of private funds in 
the Czech Republic, unregulated market of health services in 
Bosnia and Herzegovina, insufficient investment in the health 
sector in Bosnia and Herzegovina, as well as a lack of person-
nel (24). Moreover big problem is the failure to report the exact 
number of visits to private institutions in order to reduce the 
tax on services. 
The highest density of medical institutions is located in 
the territory of the Czech Republic, Bosnia and Herzegovina 
and Albania. The number of medical institutions in Bosnia 
and Herzegovina and Albania is inversely proportional to the 
number of quality health services and customer satisfaction 
with these services. </p>

<p>The largest number of educational medical institutions is 
in Romania, Bulgaria and the Czech Republic. Bosnia and 
Herzegovina is located at the 4 place. The number of students 
who choose to specialize in family medicine is the largest in 
Romania, Bosnia and Herzegovina and the Czech Republic. 
The reason for these results lies in the fact that the number of 
physician specialists in deficit and that a larger number of new 
family medicine doctor (12). 
Period of residency in family medicine varies depending on 
state in which residency takes place. 
The mortality rate of children under 5 years is highest in 
Albania, Romania and Bosnia and Herzegovina and the lowest 
mortality rate is in Slovenia and Croatia. The reason for these 
results is associated with improper parenting, lack of parents 
education as well as poor health care. The lowest mortality in 
the group of 15-59 years has Montenegro and Slovenia. The 
reason for this is a good standard, health promotion, as well as 
regular health check-ups in health care institutions. The highest 
mortality rate in this age group have Romania and Serbia. The 
reason for this situation are factors such as population migra-
tion, poorly monitored and planned pregnancies, poor health 
care, poor health and safety, etc (30). The population that has 
the highest mortality rate is over 60 years old and most are 
represented in Bulgaria and Croatia. Factors that are the most 
common causes of death are obesity, cardiovascular disorders, 
cancers. 
The most common diseases are cardiovascular diseases, and 
their number is proportionate in all the neighboring coun-
tries. Has the highest rate of Bulgaria, Hungary and Bosnia 
and Herzegovina. The reason for this is Improper diet, lack of 
enforcement and poor prevention of cardiovascular disease as 
well as a little sports. Countries that have been developed such 
as Croatia, Slovenia and the Czech Republic have the lowest 
rate of cardiovascular disease. 
The highest rate of respiratory diseases has Croatia and 
Slovenia. The reason is that these are developing countries and 
the air pollutants are increased. Countries in transition such as 
Bulgaria and Romania have the lowest rate, due to the regulated 
production and reduced factors that lead to respiratory diseases. 
Injuries of the musculoskeletal system are most present in 
Albania and Serbia. The reason lies in the reduced road and 
workplace safety because the work equipment is outdated and 
poorly inspection of safety at work (16). 
Immunization against rubella is the best in Slovakia and 
Hungary. The reason for this lies in the fact that they imple-
mented numerous educations of the population under the 
auspices of the European Union (12). The minimum coverage 
is in Bulgaria, Serbia and Bosnia and Herzegovina. The rate of 
maternal mortality is the highest in Romania and Albania, while 
it is lowest in Serbia, the Czech Republic, Slovakia and Croatia. 
The reasons for reduced mortality is prevention and education 
as well as births in hospitals (24). 
The prevalence of TB is highest in Romania and Bosnia and 
Herzegovina. A large number of Roma citizens is not insured. 
Poor living conditions have led to an increased number of pa-
tients suffering from tuberculosis (24). Slovenia and the Czech 
Republic have the lowest incidence of tuberculosis (26, 27, 30). 
The prevention, inspections and standard of living have led to 
a small number of patients. </p>

<p>CASE STUDY • Mater Sociomed. 2014 Aug; 26(4): 277-286 </p>

<p>Public Health Aspects of the Family Medicine Concepts in South Eastern Europe </p>



<p>6. CONCLUSION 
Results indicate the failures and shortcomings of health care 
organizations in Southeast Europe. Example of the most com-
mon diseases, quality of care, the number of health facilities 
and the number of doctors who are located in a particular area 
of the country compared to the rest of the region. The number 
of health facilities in the area would have to be reduced to the 
norms of the European Union as in Croatia and Slovenia. The 
biggest stumbling block is the funding and low gross national 
income. Terms of payment, insurance and levels of health care 
have to be in accordance with European standards and thus 
to economic development of the country to improve health 
care. Number of family medicine doctor must be increased 
and provide an incentive for choosing specialization in family 
medicine. The introduction of new technologies to diagnose 
diseases is necessary to promptly diagnose the disease and reduce 
the inflow of patients to secondary and tertiary levels of health 
care. In this way the savings in the budget will be increased. 
The modernization of information systems and connectivity in 
a single whole would reduce the number of patients waiting as 
well as the issuance of findings. Prevention of diseases that are 
most common is the most important item, since chronic disease 
are one of the major problems of family medicine. Networking 
of doctors and pharmacies will facilitate prescribing a sufficient 
number of recipes would improve the management of chronic 
diseases. Education of patients suffering from chronic diseases 
is very important because the proper lifestyle can reduce the 
consumption of medications and thus lead to a decrease in cost. 
The 24 hours operation at the level of family medicine would 
lead to a reduction in spending on secondary and tertiary levels 
and significantly improve the level of health care and citizen 
satisfaction . </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST: NONE DECLARED. </p>



</text></tei>