<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4930282" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Sepsis, a systemic inflammatory response syndrome by in-
fection, is life-threatening disease with high mortality and mo-
bidity (Singhal et al., 2013). Severe sepsis is a leading cause 
of death in intensive care units and results in aggregate health 
care cost (Lagu et al., 2012). Despite continuous effort and 
research, effective pharmacologic agent for sepsis has not 
been developed. The complicated and ambiguous pathologi-
cal mechanism of sepsis is one of the main causes of failure 
in management (Zhao et al., 2013). An uncontrolled hyper-
inflammatory response and improper cytokine response 
during sepsis have been proposed as the cause of multiple 
organ failure, which is most lethal complication of sepsis (Ri-
edemann et al., 2003). Given the large abundance of resident 
macrophages and their extensive endothelial surfaces, the 
liver plays a prominent role in the host immune response to 
infection (Chen et al., 1996). Moreover, the liver is believed to </p>

<p>be a vulnerable organ responsible for the initiation of multiple 
organ dysfunction syndrome, which is the most lethal compli-
cation of sepsis (Bone, 1991). 
Histone deacetylase (HDAC) regulates gene expression 
through chromatin remodeling (Wu and Grunstein, 2000). 
HDAC catalyzes the hydrolytic removal of the acetyl group of 
histone resulting in chromatin condensation and transcription-
al silencing (Johnstone, 2002). Given the role in their potent 
efficacy in modulating the gene expression, HDAC inhibitors 
have been developed as anti-cancer agents (Pan et al., 2007). 
Accumulating evidences revealed that HDAC inhibitors pos-
sess anti-inflammatory properties (Kim et al., 2001; Tong et 
al., 2004). Trichostatin A (TSA), a representative HDAC inhibi-
tor, improved the hepatic injury by decreasing interleukin (IL)-
6 production in septic mice (Zhang et al., 2009). 
Toll-like receptors (TLRs), crucial family of pattern recogni-
tion receptors, are the first line of defense system against mi-
crobial infection. Complex TLRs signaling and its associated </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(4), 387-394 (2016) </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author </p>

<p>E-mail: sunmee@skku.edu 
Tel: +82-31-290-7712, Fax: +82-31-292-8800 </p>

<p>Received Oct 30, 2015 Revised Nov 26, 2015 Accepted Dec 2, 2015 
Published Online Jul 1, 2016 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2015.176 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 The Korean Society of Applied Pharmacology </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Com-
mons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licens-
es/by-nc/4.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>Trichostatin A Protects Liver against Septic Injury through 
Inhibiting Toll-Like Receptor Signaling </p>

<p>So-Jin Kim, Jin-Sook Park, Do-Won Lee and Sun-Mee Lee* </p>

<p>School of Pharmacy, Sungkyunkwan University, Suwon 16419, Republic of Korea </p>

<p>Sepsis, a serious clinical problem, is characterized by a systemic inflammatory response to infection and leads to organ failure. 
Toll-like receptor (TLR) signaling is intimately implicated in hyper-inflammatory responses and tissue injury during sepsis. Histone 
deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors have been reported to exhibit anti-inflammatory properties. The aim of this study was to investigate 
the hepatoprotective mechanisms of trichostatin A (TSA), a HDAC inhibitor, associated with TLR signaling pathway during sepsis. 
The anti-inflammatory properties of TSA were assayed in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated RAW264.7 cells. Polymicrobial 
sepsis was induced in mice by cecal ligation and puncture (CLP), a clinically relevant model of sepsis. The mice were intraperito-
neally received TSA (1, 2 or 5 mg/kg) 30 min before CLP. The serum and liver samples were collected 6 and 24-h after CLP. TSA 
inhibited the increased production of tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α and interleukin (IL)-6 in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells. TSA 
improved sepsis-induced mortality, attenuated liver injury and decreased serum TNF-α and IL-6 levels. CLP increased the levels 
of TLR4, TLR2 and myeloid differentiation primary response protein 88 (MyD88) protein expression and association of MyD88 with 
TLR4 and TLR2, which were attenuated by TSA. CLP increased nuclear translocation of nuclear factor kappa B and decreased 
cytosolic inhibitor of kappa B (IκB) protein expression, which were attenuated by TSA. Moreover, CLP decreased acetylation of 
IκB kinase (IKK) and increased association of IKK with IκB and TSA attenuated these alterations. Our findings suggest that TSA 
attenuates liver injury by inhibiting TLR-mediated inflammatory response during sepsis. </p>

<p>Key Words: Histone deacetylase inhibitor, Nuclear factor kappa B, Sepsis, Toll-like receptor, Trichostatin A </p>

<p>Abstract </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2015.176 </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(4), 387-394 (2016) </p>

<p>downstream regulators involved in pathogenesis and devel-
opment of sepsis. In polymicrobial sepsis, hepatic TLR4 and 
TLR2 mRNA expression increased compared with that in sh-
am-operated mice (Williams et al., 2003) and TAK-242, a TLR4 
inhibitor, improved survival in a murine model of sepsis (Sha 
et al., 2011). Moreover, TLR protein expression upregulated 
in septic patients compared with healthy individuals. Activa-
tion of TLRs rapidly recruits adaptor molecules and triggers in-
flammatory gene expression through downstream pathways. 
Recently, HDAC inhibitors have been reported to regulate 
diverse signaling pathways through post-translational modifi-
cation of non-histone proteins. TSA inhibited up-regulation of 
myeloid differentiation primary response protein 88 (MyD88) 
gene expression in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced bone 
marrow-derived dendritic cells (Roger et al., 2011) and su-
beroylanilide hydroxamic acid suppressed mitogen-activated 
protein kinase (MAPK) signaling pathway through acetylation 
of MAPK phosphatase-1 (Finkelstein et al., 2010). 
Therefore, the present study was undertaken to elucidate 
the molecular mechanisms involved in the hepatoprotective 
effects of TSA, a HDAC inhibitor, in cecal ligation and puncture 
(CLP)-induced sepsis, particularly focusing on TLR signaling 
pathway. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM), fetal bovine 
serum (FBS) and penicillin/streptomycin (10,000 U/mL and 
10,000 μg/mL, respectively) were purchased from Gibco Life 
Technologies (Grand Island, NY, USA). LPS (Escherichia coli 
serotype O111:B4), tetrazolium bromide (MTT), and all other 
materials required for culturing cells were purchased from Sig-
ma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). All other chemicals used in 
this study were of reagent grade. </p>

<p>Cell viability </p>

<p>Mouse macrophage cell line RAW264.7 cells were pur-
chased from the American Type Culture Collection (Manas-
sas, VA, USA). RAW264.7 cells were seeded in 96-well plates, 
incubated for 24-h in 10% FBS and 1% penicillin/streptomy-
cin-contained DMEM. The cells were treated with vehicle 
(phosphate-buffered saline; PBS) or TSA (12.5, 25, 50, 100 
or 200 nM) for 24-h, and then 100 μL of MTT solution (5 mg/ 
mL in PBS) was added to each well. After 3-h incubation, the 
medium was removed, and subsequently 100 μL of dimethyl 
sulfoxide was added to each well to solubilize any deposited 
formazan. The optical density of each well was measured at 
450 nm using a microplate reader (Molecular Devices, Sunny-
vale, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Cell culture and treatment </p>

<p>RAW264.7 cells were cultured in 10% FBS and 1% peni-
cillin/streptomycin contained-DMEM, and maintained at 37°C 
in an atmosphere of 5% CO2. After 6-h incubation, the cells 
were starved with 0.5% FBS and 1% penicillin/streptomycin 
contained-DMEM. After 18-h starvation, the cells were treated 
with vehicle (PBS) or TSA (12.5, 25 or 50 nM) for another 1-h 
and then treated with LPS (1 μg/mL). After 24-h incubation, 
the culture media were harvested for assay. </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Male C57BL/6 mice weighing 23-25 g (8 weeks old) were 
supplied by Orient Bio (Seongnam, Korea). The animals were 
housed in cages located in temperature-controlled rooms with 
a 12-h light-dark cycle and received water and food ad libi-
tum. All animal procedures were approved by the Sungkyunk-
wan University Animal Care Committee and were performed 
in accordance with the guidelines of the National Institutes of 
Health (NIH publication No. 86-23, revised 1985). </p>

<p>CLP </p>

<p>Polymicrobial sepsis was induced by CLP as described 
by Chaudry et al (1979). Mice were anesthetized with an 
intramuscular injection of ketamine (100 mg/kg; Yuhan Cor-
poration, Seoul, Korea) and xylazine (10 mg/kg; Boehringer 
Ingelheim, St. Joseph, MO, USA). Anesthestized mice were 
then opened with a 1-cm midline incision of the abdomen and 
the cecum was carefully exposed. The cecum was ligated 
just distal to the ileocecal valve to avoid intestinal obstruction 
and punctured twice using a 20-gauge needle. The punctured 
cecum was squeezed to extract feces and returned to the 
abdominal position. The abdominal incision was closed with 
two layers of running suture. After the operation, all animals 
subcutaneously received 1 mL normal saline injection for fluid 
resuscitation. Sham-operated mice were operated to lapa-
rotomy and intestinal manipulation, however, the cecum was 
neither ligated nor punctured. </p>

<p>Administration of TSA and experimental design </p>

<p>In survival experiments, mice intraperitoneally received 
vehicle (normal saline) or TSA (1, 2 or 5 mg/kg) 30 min be-
fore CLP. The dose and time point of TSA administration were 
selected based on a previously published report (Zhang et 
al., 2009) and our preliminary study. Animals were randomly 
divided to the following 6 groups (each group, n=6-10): (a) 
vehicle-treated sham (sham), (b) TSA (2 mg/kg)-treated sham 
(TSA), (c) vehicle-treated CLP (CLP), (d) TSA 1 mg/kg-treated 
CLP (TSA 1 mg/kg+CLP), (e) TSA 2 mg/kg-treated CLP (TSA 
2 mg/kg+CLP) and (f) TSA 5 mg/kg-treated CLP (TSA 5 mg/ 
kg+CLP). Mortality was recorded for up to 10 days after CLP 
and survivors were monitored for further 3 weeks to ensure 
that no late mortalities occurred (each group, n=10). On the 
basis of a survival test, a dose of 2 mg/kg was chosen for 
further biochemical studies. Under anesthesia, blood samples 
from the inferior vena cava and liver tissues were collected 6 
and 24-h after CLP. The serum were isolated by centrifugation 
at 10,000×g for 10 min at 4°C. </p>

<p>Cytokine levels </p>

<p>The tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α and IL-6 production 
in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells and the serum levels of 
TNF-α and IL-6 were measured 6-h after CLP using commer-
cially available enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kits (BD 
Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA) according to the manufac-
turer's instructions. </p>

<p>Total RNA extraction and real-time reverse transcription 
polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted from liver tissues using RNAiso 
Plus (Takara Bio Inc., Shiga, Japan) and the first strand of 
cDNA was synthesized via reverse transcription (EcoDry 
cDNA Synthesis Premix; Takara Bio, Inc.). The cDNA was am-</p>



<p>Kim et al. Trichostatin A Attenuates Septic Injury </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>plified with primers and SYBR green (Roche Applied Science, 
Mannheim, Germany) using a thermocycler (Lightcycler Nano; 
Roche Applied Science). Gene specific primers used for cDNA 
amplification were 5′-AGCCCACGTCGTAGCAAACCACCAA-3′ 
(sense) and 5′-ACACCCATTCCCTTCACAGAGCAAT-3′ (anti-
sense) for TNF-α; 5′-GAAAGTCAACTCCATCTGCC-3′ (sense) 
and 5′-CATAGCACACTACGTTTGCC-3′ (anti ense) for IL-6; and 
5′-GGCTGTATTCCCCTCCATCG-3′ (sense) and 5′-CCAG-
TTGGTAACAATGCCATGT-3′ (antisense) for β-actin. Real-
time RT-PCR was performed with an specific amplification 
cycling conditions as follows: 35 cycles of 30 s at 94°C, 30 
s at 65°C and 30 s at 72°C for TNF-α; 35 cycles of 30 s at 
94°C, 45 s at 58°C and 30 s at 72°C for IL-6; and 35 cycles 
of 30 s at 94°C, 30 s at 55°C and 30 s at 72°C for β-actin. 
The levels of mRNA expression were normalized to that of the 
β-actin mRNA expression and reported relative to the average 
of all ∆cycle threshold (Ct)-values in each sample using the Ct 
method. All samples were carried out in duplicate to ensure 
amplification integrity. </p>

<p>Serum aminotransferase level </p>

<p>The serum levels of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and 
aspartate aminotransferase (AST) were measured 6 and 24-h 
after CLP with ChemiLab ALT and AST assay kits (IVDLab 
Co., Uiwang, Korea) using a Hitachi 7600 automatic analyzer 
(Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Histological analysis </p>

<p>The liver tissue collected 24-h after CLP was fixed with 10% 
neutral buffered formalin. The sample was embedded in par-
affin, sliced into 5-μm sections, and stained with hematoxylin 
and eosin (H&amp;E). Histological changes were evaluated in ran-
dom and nonconsecutive fields at x200 magnification (Olym-
pus BX51/Olympus DP71, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Total, cytosolic and nuclear protein extraction </p>

<p>The liver tissue collected 6-h after CLP was homogenized 
in PRO-PREP 
TM Protein Extraction Solution (iNtRON Biotech-
nology, Seongnam, Korea) for total protein samples or in NE-
PER 
® (Pierce Biotechnology, Rockford, IL, USA) for nuclear/ 
cytosolic proteins according to the manufacturers' instruc-
tions. The levels of protein concentration were determined us-</p>

<p>ing BCA Protein Assay kit (Pierce Biotechnology). </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Protein samples (16-20 μg) were loaded on 7.5-15% poly-
acrylamide gels, separated by sodium dodecyl sulphate/poly-
acrylamide gel electrophoresis and transferred to polyvinyli-
dene fluoride membranes (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA) using 
the Semi-Dry Trans-Blot Cell (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, 
CA, USA). After the transfer, the membranes were blocked for 
1-h with 5% (w/v) skim milk or bovine serum albumin powder 
in Tris-buffered saline with 0.1% Tween-20 at room tempera-
ture. Blots were incubated with primary antibodies overnight at 
4°C. Primary antibodies against MyD88, TIR-domain-contain-
ing adapter-inducing interferon-β (TRIF), nuclear factor kappa 
B (NF-κB), inhibitor of kappa B (IκB)-α, acetylated-lysine (Ac-
K; Cell Signaling Technology, Berverly, MA, USA), TLR4 and 
TLR2 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA, USA) were 
used. On the following day, the blots were incubated with ap-
propriate secondary antibodies for 1-h at room temperature. 
Bands were detected using an ECL detection system (iNtRON 
Biotechnology) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
The intensities of immunoreactive bands were evaluated 
using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Total-Lab TL120</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Nonlinear Dynamics</rs>, New-
castle, UK). Signals were standardized to that of β-actin (Sig-
ma-Aldrich) and lamin B1 (Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) for 
whole/cytosolic lysate and nuclear fraction, respectively. </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>To assess the protein association, liver lysates were immu-
noprecipitated with anti-TLR4, anti-TLR2 and IκB kinase (IKK) 
antibodies (Santa Cruz Biotechnology). The mixture was incu-
bated for 3-h at 4°C and beads were pelleted by centrifugation 
at 12,000×g for 30 s. The pelleted beads were washed five 
times in cold PBS, resuspended in loading buffer and heated 
at 95°C for 7 min before analysis by immunoblotting. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Survival data was prescribed by the Kaplan-Meier curve 
and analyzed by log-rank test. All other data were analyzed 
by the one-way analysis of the variance and the Bonferroni 
test was used for post-hoc comparisons. Statistical differenc-
es between the groups were considered significant at p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>12.5 25 50 100 200 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 
Viability (%) </p>

<p>TSA (nM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>12.5 25 50 </p>

<p>12,000 </p>

<p>10,000 </p>

<p>8,000 </p>

<p>6,000 </p>

<p>4,000 </p>

<p>2,000 
TNF-(pg/ml) 
a </p>

<p>TSA (nM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>V e h i c l e 
C 
o n t r o l </p>

<p>12.5 25 50 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 
IL-6 (pg/mL) </p>

<p>TSA (nM) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>V e h i c l e </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>LPS (1 g/ml) 
m </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>LPS (1 g/ml) 
m </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Effect of TSA on TNF-α and IL-6 release in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells. For the cellular toxicity assay, RAW264.7 cells were </p>

<p>treated with vehicle (PBS) or various concentrations of TSA for 24-h (A). To measure cytokine release, RAW264.7 cells were treated with 
various concentrations of TSA for 1-h before LPS (1 μg/mL) stimulation. Twenty-four hours after LPS stimulation, release of TNF-α (B) and 
IL-6 (C) was measured. The results are presented as mean ± SEM of three independent experiments. **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001 versus control 
group. 
 † † † p&lt;0.001 versus LPS group. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2015.176 </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(4), 387-394 (2016) </p>

<p>Results are presented as mean ± standard error of the mean 
(SEM). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>TSA suppresses inflammatory cytokine release in 
LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells </p>

<p>To evaluate the anti-inflammatory properties of TSA, the 
levels of released cytokines were determined in LPS-stimu-
lated RAW264.7 cells. TSA did not have any cytotoxicity on 
RAW264.7 cells at concentrations up to 50 nM (Fig. 1A). LPS 
significantly increased TNF-α and IL-6 release to 54.6-and 
26.4-fold, respectively, than those in the control group. These 
increases were inhibited by TSA in a concentration-dependent 
manner (Fig. 1B, 1C). </p>

<p>TSA protects mice against sepsis-induced lethality </p>

<p>In the CLP group, the survival rate on the first day was 80% 
and stabilized at 30% on the fifth day after CLP. Log-rank 
analysis of 10-day survival demonstrated that 2 mg/kg TSA 
significantly improved survival rate compared with CLP group 
(p=0.0498; Fig. 2). </p>

<p>TSA attenuates serum levels and hepatic mRNA 
expressions of inflammatory cytokines in septic mice </p>

<p>The serum levels of TNF-α and IL-6 in the sham group 
were 186.0 ± 30.1 and 90.7 ± 3.2 pg/mL, respectively. CLP 
significantly increased TNF-α and IL-6 levels to 1.5-and 31.5-
fold than those in the sham group, respectively, 6-h after CLP. 
These increases were attenuated by TSA (Fig. 3A, 3B). The 
hepatic TNF-α and IL-6 mRNA expression exhibited a marked 
increase to 2.8-and 1.5-fold than those in the sham group, re-
spectively. Consistent with observation of serum cytokine lev-
els, TSA attenuated the increases in TNF-α and IL-6 mRNA 
expression (Fig. 3C, 3D). </p>

<p>TSA attenuates hepatic injury in septic mice </p>

<p>The serum levels of ALT were 23.3 ± 0.9 and 28.5 ± 1.5 U/L, 
respectively, 6 and 24-h after sham operation. CLP significant-
ly increased these values to 2.5-and 10.4-fold than those in 
the sham group, respectively. These increases were attenu-</p>

<p>ated by TSA (Fig. 4A). The serum levels of AST were 43.7 ± 
3.7 and 45.3 ± 3.3 U/L, respectively, 6 and 24-h after sham 
operation. CLP significantly increased these values to 3.3-
and 7.4-fold than those in sham group, respectively, which 
were attenuated by TSA (Fig. 4B). According to histological 
analysis, there were marked pathological changes including 
inflammatory cell infiltration and necrosis in the liver that was 
evaluated at 24-h after CLP. These histological changes were 
ameliorated by TSA (Fig. 4C). </p>

<p>TSA decreases TLR4 and TLR2 signaling pathway in 
septic mice </p>

<p>To determine the effect of TSA on TLR signaling pathway, 
we first determined the TLR4 and TLR2 protein expression. 
CLP significantly increased TLR4 and TLR2 protein expres-
sion to 1.9-and 1.8-fold, respectively, than those in the sham 
group 6-h after CLP. These increases were attenuated by TSA 
(Fig. 5A, 5B). CLP significantly increased MyD88 and TRIF 
protein expression to 1.7-and 1.5-fold, respectively, than 
those in the sham group 6-h after CLP. TSA attenuated in-
crease in MyD88 protein expression, not TRIF (Fig. 5C, 5D). 
CLP significantly increased association of MyD88 with TLR4 
and TLR2 to 1.5-and 1.6-fold than those in the sham group, 
respectively. These increases were attenuated by TSA (Fig. </p>

<p>Survival rate (%) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Days after CLP (d) </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
6 
8 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Sham 
CLP 
TSA 1 mg/kg+CLP 
TSA 2 mg/kg+CLP 
TSA 5 mg/kg+CLP </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effect of TSA on CLP-induced lethality. Mice were intraperi-</p>

<p>toneally injected with vehicle (normal saline) or TSA (1, 2 or 5 mg/ 
kg) 30 min before CLP (n=10 per group). Animals were monitored 
for 10 days after CLP. *p&lt;0.05 versus CLP group. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A C 
L P </p>

<p>T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 
TNF-(pg/ml) 
a </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A C 
L P </p>

<p>T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>4,000 </p>

<p>3,000 </p>

<p>2,000 </p>

<p>1,000 
IL-6 (pg/ml) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A C 
L P </p>

<p>T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
TNF-a mRNA expression (Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A C 
L P </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
IL-6 mRNA expression (Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effect of TSA on serum levels and hepatic mRNA expres-</p>

<p>sions of TNF-α and IL-6 in sepsis. Mice were intraperitoneally 
administered vehicle (normal saline) or 2 mg/kg TSA 30 min before 
CLP. The blood samples were collected from the inferior vena cava 
6-h after CLP and then serum levels of TNF-α (A) and IL-6 (B) 
were determined. The liver tissues were collected 6-h after CLP 
and then hepatic mRNA expressions of TNF-α (C) and IL-6 (D) 
were determined. The results are presented as mean ± SEM (n=6-
8 per group). *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001 versus sham group. 
 † p&lt;0.05, 
 † † p&lt;0.01 versus CLP group. </p>



<p>Kim et al. Trichostatin A Attenuates Septic Injury </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>5E, 5F). CLP significantly increased association of TRIF with 
TLR4 to 1.8-fold than that in the sham group. TSA did not af-
fect this increase (Fig. 5G). </p>

<p>TSA decreases NF-κB signaling pathway in septic mice </p>

<p>To determine the effect of TSA on NF-κB signaling pathway, 
we first determined the NF-κB and IκB protein expression. 
CLP significantly increased nuclear NF-κB protein expression 
to 5.1-fold than that in the sham group 6-h after CLP. This 
increase was attenuated by TSA (Fig. 6A). CLP significantly 
decreased cytosolic IκB protein expression to 70% of that in 
the sham group, which was attenuated by TSA (Fig. 6B). CLP 
significantly decreased Ac-IKK protein expression to 38% of 
that in the sham group, which was attenuated by TSA (Fig. 
6C). CLP significantly increased association of IκB with IKK </p>

<p>protein expression to 2.0-fold than that in the sham group. 
This increase was attenuated by TSA (Fig. 6D). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Numerous evidences indicate that epigenetic modifica-
tion is the master regulator for gene expression and plays 
an important role in inflammatory and host defense response 
(Roger et al., 2011). Acetylation is an essential epigenetic 
modification that determines the amplitude of immune sys-
tem by controlling the chromatin structure, transcription factor 
activity and subsequent gene expression. Accumulating evi-
dences imply that HDAC inhibitors possess anti-inflammatory 
properties. Inhibition of histone acetylation attenuates syno-</p>

<p>* </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>6 h 
24 h </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 
ALT (U/L) </p>

<p>0 
6 h 
24 h </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>100 
ALT (U/L) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Sham 
TSA </p>

<p>CLP 
TSA+CLP </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>Sham 
TSA 
CLP 
TSA+CLP </p>

<p>Sham 
TSA 
CLP 
TSA+CLP </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Effect of TSA on hepatocellular damages in sepsis. Mice were intraperitoneally administered vehicle or 2 mg/kg TSA 30 min before </p>

<p>CLP. The blood samples were collected from the inferior vena cava 6 and 24-h after CLP and then serum levels of ALT (A) and AST (B) 
were determined. Tissues were isolated and stained with H&amp;E 24-h after CLP (magnification ×200). The arrow indicates neutrophilic infiltra-
tion and asterisk indicates necrosis. The results are presented as mean ± SEM (n=6-8 per group). *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001 versus 
sham group. 
 † p&lt;0.05, 
 † † † p&lt;0.001 versus CLP group. </p>



<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4062/biomolther.2015.176 </p>

<p>Biomol Ther 24(4), 387-394 (2016) </p>

<p>vial inflammation in collagen-induced arthritis mouse model 
(Nasu et al., 2008) and allergen-induced airway inflammation 
in mouse asthma model (Choi et al., 2005). Moreover, HDAC 
inhibitors relate to sepsis that is caused by an uncontrolled 
hyper-inflammation. TSA suppressed myeloperoxidase activ-
ity in septic mice (Zhang et al., 2010) and attenuated endotox-
emia-induced acute lung injury (Zhang et al., 2009). Moreover, 
it is reported that sepsis is characterized by upregulation of 
HDAC activity, which influences the acetylation status, and 
that the imbalance can be corrected by HDAC inhibitor (Li and 
Alam, 2011). 
In the present study, administration of TSA improved CLP-
induced mortality. A standardized septic animal model is criti-
cal to elucidate the pathophysiological process in sepsis. The 
CLP model has been extensively used in the research for 
sepsis and believed gold-standard model to closely resemble 
characteristics of human sepsis (Toscano et al., 2011). Severe 
sepsis causes lethal organ failure, which leads to septic shock 
and death. Among them, liver failure significantly relates to 
the high mortality in septic patients (Hebert et al., 1993). Liver 
performs important role through engaging in inflammation re-
sponse. Interestingly, the liver also acts as a victim that suf-
fers from the inflammatory responses (Nesseler et al., 2012). </p>

<p>In the present study, CLP significantly increased the serum 
levels of ALT and AST. Importantly, histology analysis sup-
ported hepatic injury during sepsis. TSA not only decreased 
serum markers of liver damage but also attenuated pathologi-
cal changes in liver. These results suggest that TSA improves 
hepatic injury during sepsis. 
Excessive and uncontrolled inflammatory response contrib-
utes to pathophysiological progress of sepsis. Indeed, previ-
ous studies have demonstrated that inflammatory cytokines 
such as TNF-α and IL-6 peak at early phase of sepsis and 
are strongly associated with disease progress (Takala et al., 
2002). In the present study, CLP significantly increased the 
serum levels of TNF-α and IL-6, which were attenuated by 
TSA. Moreover, TSA attenuated increases in hepatic TNF-α 
and IL-6 mRNA expression in septic mice. This result sug-
gests that TSA suppresses cytokine production at the tran-
scriptional level. 
TLRs play a critical role in the pathogenesis of sepsis as 
critical upstream mediators of excessive inflammation. In par-
ticular, TLR4 and TLR2 recognize gram-positive bacteria and 
gram-negative bacteria, respectively, which are main patho-
gens of sepsis. The levels of TLR4 and TLR2 protein expres-
sion increased in liver, lung and spleen in septic model and </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>* 
* 
** </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>*** 
** ** 
** </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
TLR4 protein expression 
(Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>TLR4 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0.5 
TLR2 protein expression (Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>TLR2 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P 
T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
MyD88 protein expression (Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>MyD88 </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
TRIF protein expression (Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>TRIF </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P 
T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
MyD88-TLR4/total TLR4 </p>

<p>(Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>IB: MyD88 </p>

<p>IB: TLR4 </p>

<p>T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>MyD88-TLR2/total TLR2 </p>

<p>(Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>IB: TLR2 </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P 
T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>TRIF-TLR4/total TLR4 
(Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>IB: MyD88 </p>

<p>IB: TLR4 </p>

<p>IB: TRIF </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>IP: TLR4 
IP: TLR2 
IP: TLR4 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Effect of TSA on TLR signaling pathway in septic liver. Mice were intraperitoneally administered vehicle or 2 mg/kg TSA 30 min </p>

<p>before CLP. The liver tissues were collected 6-h after CLP and then TLR4 (A), TLR2 (B), MyD88 (C) and TRIF (D) protein expression were 
determined. Liver lysates were immunoprecipitated with anti-TLR4 and anti-TLR2 antibodies and precipitated proteins were immunoblot-
ted using anti-MyD88 (E-F) and anti-TRIF (G) antibodies. The results are presented as mean ± SEM (n=6-8 per group) *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, 
***p&lt;0.001 versus sham group. 
 † p&lt;0.05 versus CLP group. </p>



<p>Kim et al. Trichostatin A Attenuates Septic Injury </p>

<p>www.biomolther.org </p>

<p>these increases correlate with mortality (Williams et al., 2003). 
Previous studies showed that eritoran, a TLR4 antagonist, 
attenuated cardiac dysfunction via inhibiting cytokine expres-
sion in endotoxemia model (Ehrentraut et al., 2011). TLR2-
deficient mice exhibited increased survival rates compared to 
wild type mice during sepsis (Bergt et al., 2013). Moreover, 
TSA inhibited the up-regulation of TLR2 mRNA expression in 
LPS-stimulated bone marrow derived macrophage (Roger et 
al., 2011). In the present study, the hepatic TLR4 and TLR2 
protein expression significantly increased after CLP and TSA 
attenuated these increases. 
TLRs rapidly recruit adaptor molecules and trigger down-
stream signaling pathway after activation. Upon stimulation, 
adaptor molecules such as MyD88 and TRIF are recruited and 
subsequently lead to the activation of NF-κB signaling. Defi-
ciency of MyD88 suppressed inflammatory cytokines and pro-
tected mice in polymicrobial sepsis (Kawai et al., 1999). More-
over, TAK-242 inhibited increases in serum cytokine levels by 
blocking interactions between TLR4 and its adaptor protein in 
endotoxemia model (Takashima et al., 2009). In the present </p>

<p>study, CLP significantly increased MyD88 and TRIF protein 
expression. TSA attenuated increase in MyD88. Moreover, the 
association of MyD88 with TLR4 and TLR2, and TRIF with 
TLR4 increased after CLP. TSA attenuated the association of 
MyD88 with TLR4 and TLR2, not TRIF with TLR4. In previous 
report, TSA inhibited the up-regulation of MyD88 mRNA ex-
pression in LPS-stimulated bone marrow derived macrophage 
but did not affect TRIF mRNA expression (Roger et al., 2011). 
Our result suggests that TSA suppresses MyD88-dependent 
TLR signaling pathway. 
Activation of TLR leads to a multistep signaling process, 
which leads to NF-κB signaling activation. NF-κB plays a cru-
cial role in pathophysiological process in sepsis via inducing 
the transcription of numerous inflammatory-related genes 
(Baldwin, 1996). Upon activation, IκB is phosphorylated by 
the IKK and subsequently degraded by the proteasome result-
ing in NF-κB activation (Beg et al., 1993). In septic patients, 
increased nuclear NF-κB expression is associated with high-
er rates of mortality and worse clinical outcome (Abraham, 
2003). Recently, HDAC inhibitors have been reported to inter-
fere with the activation of NF-κB signaling pathways. TSA in-
hibited the NF-κB signaling via suppressing proteosomal deg-
radation of IκB (Chakravortty et al., 2000). Butyrate, a HDAC 
inhibitor, inhibited TNF-α-stimulated IκB phosphorylation and 
degradation in the adenocarcinoma cells (Lührs et al., 2001). 
Moreover, YopJ, a Yeersinia outer protein, suppressed kinase 
activity of IKK by acetylation of the active loop of IKK, result-
ing in suppression of IκB degradation (Mittal et al., 2006). It 
is interesting to note that in some instances, HDAC inhibitors 
have been reported to activate NF-κB pathway. Acetylation at 
lysine 221 of p65 subunit of NF-κB enhanced nuclear import of 
NF-κB (Chen et al., 2002). In our study, CLP increased nucle-
ar translocation of NF-κB and TSA attenuated this increase. 
TSA attenuated decrease in cytosolic IκB protein expression 
in septic mice. Moreover, CLP decreased IKK acetylation and 
increased association of IKK with IκB. These alterations were 
attenuated by TSA. These results suggest that TSA inhibits 
translocation of NF-κB to nucleus via enhancing IKK acetyla-
tion. 
In conclusion, TSA protects against sepsis-induced hepatic 
injury by inhibiting TLR signaling pathways. Thus, we propose 
that TSA might be useful as a potential therapeutic interven-
tion for sepsis treatment. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by a National Research Founda-
tion of Korea (NRF) grant funded by the Korean government 
(MEST; 2012R1A5A2A28671860). So-Jin Kim (2013034472; 
NRF-2013H1A2A1034472) received 'Global Ph.D. Fellowship 
Program' support from the NRF funded by the MEST. </p>



<p>** </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>NF-B protein expression 
(Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>NF-B 
k </p>

<p>Lamin B </p>

<p>T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>I B protein expression (Arbitrary unit) 
k 
0 </p>

<p>I B 
k </p>

<p>b-actin </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P 
T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 
Ac-k-IKK/total IKK 
(Arbitrary unit) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>IB: Ac-K </p>

<p>IB: IKK </p>

<p>T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>I B (Arbitrary unit) 
k -IKK/total IKK </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>IB: I B 
k </p>

<p>IB: IKK </p>

<p>S h a m 
T S A + C </p>

<p>L P 
T S A 
C 
L P </p>

<p>IP: IKK 
IP: IKK </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Effect of TSA on NF-κB signaling pathway in septic liver. </p>

<p>Mice were intraperitoneally administered vehicle or 2 mg/kg TSA 
30 min before CLP. The liver tissues were collected 6-h after CLP 
and then nuclear NF-κB (A) and cytosolic IκB (B) protein expres-
sion were determined. Liver lysates were immunoprecipitated with 
anti-IKK antibody and precipitated proteins were immunoblotted 
using anti-Ac-K (C) and anti-IκB (D) antibodies. The results are 
presented as mean ± SEM (n=6-8 per group) *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01 
versus sham group. 
 † p&lt;0.05, 
 † † p&lt;0.01 versus CLP group. </p>





</text></tei>