<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4792857" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Tibetan is a valuable Himalayan sheep breed classified as endangered. Knowledge of the level and distribution of 
genetic diversity in Tibetan sheep is important for designing conservation strategies for their sustainable survival 
and to preserve their evolutionary potential. Thus, for the first time, genetic variability in the Tibetan population 
was accessed with twenty five inter-simple sequence repeat markers. All the microsatellites were polymorphic 
and a total of 148 alleles were detected across these loci. The observed number of alleles across all the loci was 
more than the effective number of alleles and ranged from 3 (BM6506) to 11 (BM6526) with 5.920 ± 0.387 
mean number of alleles per locus. The average observed heterozygosity was less than the expected heterozygos-
ity. The observed and expected heterozygosity values ranged from 0.150 (BM1314) to 0.9 (OarCP20) with an 
overall mean of 0.473 ± 0.044 and from 0.329 (BM8125) to 0.885 (BM6526) with an overall mean 0.672 ± 
0.030, respectively. The lower heterozygosity pointed towards diminished genetic diversity in the population. 
Thirteen microsatellite loci exhibited significant (P b 0.05) departures from the Hardy-Weinberg proportions in 
the population. The estimate of heterozygote deficiency varied from −0.443 (OarCP20) to 0.668 (OarFCB128) 
with a mean positive value of 0.302 ± 0.057. A normal 'L' shaped distribution of mode-shift test and non-
significant heterozygote excess on the basis of different models suggested absence of recent bottleneck in the 
existing Tibetan population. In view of the declining population of Tibetan sheep (less than 250) in the breeding 
tract, need of the hour is immediate scientific management of the population so as to increase the population 
hand in hand with retaining the founder alleles to the maximum possible extent. 
Sheep biodiversity in India is characterized by high degree of 
endemism as variations in agro climatic conditions have led to the de-
velopment of more than 40 breeds (Acharya, 1982). This vast ovine bio-
diversity is being eroded rapidly with more than 50% of sheep breeds 
currently under threat (Bhatia and Arora, 2005). Sheep provides em-
ployment and income to the socially and economically disadvantageous 
sections of the society being reared by the landless laborers and margin-
al farmers. Indigenous breeds must be considered as important reser-
voirs of non-exploited resources due to the presence of potentially 
unrecognized beneficial genetic variation. Moreover, autochthones 
breeds are the cultural properties due to their role in the agriculture ten-
ures and in the social life of rural populations. Tibetan sheep is one such 
important breed of Indian North temperate Himalayan region. The </p>

<p>sheep migrated to India with the Tibetan traders who used them as 
beasts of burden for transporting various merchandise besides wool 
(Government of Bengal, 1864). Independence of India in 1947 led to po-
litical and economic changes with concomitant cessation of their migra-
tion in the country. 
Tibetan animals are of medium size, mostly white with black or 
brown face and brown and white spots on the body. The fleece is rela-
tively fine and is among the best obtained from native ovine breeds 
of Indian subcontinent (Banerjee, 2009). The animals are unique being 
adapted to the harsh temperate climate and difficult terrains of 
Himalayas and survive even in the open housing system. Tibetan is 
regarded as one of the most rustic sheep breeds which thrives in condi-
tions of extreme harshness and deprivation while providing meat and 
down for the people. They are the only source of livelihood in the area 
since agriculture is not suitable due to the geo-climatic characteristics. 
However, population of Tibetan sheep has been decreasing drastically 
in recent past (Banerjee, 2009) due to lack of regulated market, trans-
port linkage, shrinkage of pasture land, increased inbreeding and occur-
rence of diseases. Population has gone down from 30,000 (Acharya, </p>

<p>Meta Gene 8 (2016) 14-20 </p>

<p>⁎ Corresponding author at: Core Lab, NBAGR, India. 
E-mail address: rekvik@gmail.com (R. Sharma). </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.mgene.2016.01.002 
2214-5400/© 2016 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Meta Gene </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / m g e n e </p>

<p>1982) to less than 250 in Sikkim (Livestock Census, 2012; Kumar, 2015). 
Therefore, urgent specific management and conservation measures are 
required not only for the restoration of depleted natural population due 
to endangered status but also for its biological and economical relevance 
and ecological importance. Knowledge of genetic variability is very 
important for establishing any conservation and management program. 
The use of highly variable molecular genetic markers, such as micro-
satellites, is one of the most powerful means for studying genetic diver-
sity because of their high degree of polymorphism, abundance, random 
distribution across the genome, co-dominant inheritance and neutrality 
with respect to selection (Barcaccia et al., 2013; Putman and Carbone, 
2014). These are being used to estimate the diversity of autochthonous 
sheep breeds all over the world (Ghazyl et al., 2013; Ceccobelli et al., 
2015) including India (Bhatia and Arora, 2005; Sharma et al., 2010). 
Unfortunately, no study has been undertaken so far to investigate the 
genetic characteristics of Tibetan sheep using molecular biology tech-
niques. This is critical as urgent conservation efforts are required to con-
serve and utilize the Tibetan sheep genetic resource. 
Hence, the aim of the present study was firstly to estimate the genet-
ic intra-breed variability of Tibetan sheep using 25 microsatellite 
markers and secondly to detect population bottleneck, if any. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Sample collection and polymerase chain reaction </p>

<p>The breeding tract of Tibetan sheep is now confined to the dry alpine 
zone, North District of Sikkim state in India (Fig. 1). Population is 
confined into six flocks only which are located in the Phalung valley 
(4697 m, latitude 27°56′ longitude 88°35′). Blood samples were ac-
quired from twenty Tibetan sheep (about 10% of existing population) 
from the breeding region (Fig. 1) following the guidelines of MoDAD 
(Measurement of Domestic Animal Diversity) program (FAO, 2004). 
The native sheep were evaluated for their phenotypic breed character-
istics as per the breed descriptor and individuals from each flock were 
sampled. Owners were questioned in detail to minimize the sampling 
of closely related individuals. Blood samples (5-6 ml) were collected 
in vacutainer containing Ethylene diamine tetra acetic acid (0.5 mM, 
pH 8.0). Genomic DNA was extracted from whole blood using phenol-
chloroform protocol (Sambrook et al., 1989). </p>

<p>2.2. Microsatellite genotyping </p>

<p>A panel consisting of 25 microsatellite markers was selected for the 
diversity analysis of Tibetan sheep population. These were chosen from 
literature related with sheep diversity studies aiming to analyze highly 
polymorphic markers spread across the genome. These markers also 
adhere to the guidelines of International Society for Animal Genetics 
and FAO (http://dad.fao.org/en/refer/library/guidelin/marker.pdf). 
Detailed information on primers is presented in Table 1. Forward primer 
of each marker was 5′ labeled with fluorescent dye, i.e. FAM, NED, PET 
and VIC. PCR amplification was performed in a reaction volume of 
25 μl on i-cycler. Reaction mixture consisted of 50-100 ng of genomic 
DNA, 200 μM of each dNTP, 50 pM of each primer and 0.5 units of Taq 
DNA polymerase. The amplification was carried out using a Touchdown 
program for all microsatellite loci, which consists of initial denaturation 
of 95°C for 1 min; 3 cycles of 95°C for 45 s and 60°C for 1 min, 3 cycle of 
95°C for 45 s and 57°C for 1 min; 3 cycles of 95°C for 45 s and 54°C for 
1 min, 3 cycles of 95°C for 45 s and 51°C for 1 min and 20 cycles of 95°C 
for 45 s and 48°C for 1 min. The PCR amplification was confirmed by 
electrophoresing the products in 1.8% agarose gel followed by staining 
with ethidium bromide (0.5 mg/ml). PCR products were multiplexed 
(Table 1) and genotyping was carried out on an automated ABI-3100 
DNA sequencer (Applied Biosystems, USA) using LIZ 500 as the 
internal size standard (Applied Biosystems, USA). Allele sizing was 
done using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GeneMapper™</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v 3.7</rs>. Stutter related scoring 
error, often seen in dinucleotide repeats, was absent and alleles could 
be scored unambiguously. </p>

<p>2.3. Data analysis </p>

<p>Basic genetic parameters including allele frequencies, observed (No) 
and effective number of alleles (Ne), observed (Ho) and expected 
heterozygosity (He) and heterozygote deficit (F IS ) in the whole popula-
tion were calculated by analyzing the genetic data with GenAlEx 6.2 
software (Peakall and Smouse, 2008). Tests of Hardy-Weinberg equilib-
rium and Ewens-Watterson Neutrality were applied using <rs id="software-1" type="software">POPGENE</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1.31 version</rs> (Yeh et al., <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">1999</rs>). Bottleneck events in the population 
were tested by three methods. The first method consisted of three ex-
cess heterozygosity tests developed by Cornuet and Luikart (1996): 
(i) Sign test, (ii) Standardized differences test, and (iii) a Wilcoxon </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Distribution of Tibetan sheep in Sikkim (India). </p>

<p> 
R. Sharma et al. / Meta Gene 8 (2016) 14-20 </p>

<p>sign-rank test. The probability distribution was established using 1000 
simulations under three models-Infinite allele model (IAM), stepwise 
mutation model (SMM) and two-phase model of mutation (TPM). The 
second method was the graphical representation of the mode-shift 
indicator originally proposed by Luikart et al. (1998). Loss of rare alleles 
in bottlenecked populations is detected when one or more of the com-
mon allele classes have a higher number of alleles than the rare allele 
class (Luikart et al., 1998). These two methods were applied using Bot-
tleneck v1.2.02 (http://www.ensam.inra.fr/URLB). </p>

<p>3. Results and discussion </p>

<p>Maintenance of genetic diversity is the major objective in conserva-
tion programs, so that population can face environmental challenges 
in the future and can respond to long term selection, either natural or 
artificial for traits of economic and cultural interest. Thus in this study, 
we characterized genetics of the Tibetan sheep based on 25 microsatel-
lite loci in order to generate information for their conservation. Of 
course, it is better to obtain as many individual data as possible to </p>

<p>understand the current status of the population in terms of genetic 
diversity. However, in case of Tibetan sheep, only 215 animals are left 
(Kumar, 2015) which are reared in quite inaccessible region, the higher 
reaches of the North District of Sikkim state. Thus genomic data on 
twenty animals may be considered sufficient to evaluate genetic diver-
sity of highly endangered sheep breed. </p>

<p>3.1. Genetic variability of microsatellite loci </p>

<p>All the markers were polymorphic and a total of 148 alleles were 
detected across the 25 loci. An exact test for genotypic linkage disequi-
librium yielded no significant P values across the population, and 
therefore independent assortment of all the loci was assumed. Reason-
able amount of polymorphism in Tibetan sheep breed was evident from 
the allele frequency data (available on request) with the mean number 
of alleles (MNA) of 5.920 ± 0.387 (Table 2). BM6526 showed the 
highest number of observed alleles per locus (11) while BM8125, 
OarVH72 and BM6506 showed the lowest (3). Expected number of 
alleles varied from 1.490 (BM8125) to 8.667 (BM6526) with the mean </p>

<p>Table 1 
Sequence and characteristics of the 25 primers used for diversity estimation of Tibetan sheep. </p>

<p>Microsatellite 
locus </p>

<p>Primer sequence (5′ → 3′) 
Set 
Chromosome 
location </p>

<p>Dye 
Allele size 
range (bp) </p>

<p>BM0757 
F -tgg aaa caa tgt aaa cct ggg 
R -ttg agc cac caa gga acc </p>

<p>1 
9 
FAM 
182-198 </p>

<p>BM8125 
F -ctc tat ctg tgg aaa agg tgg g 
R -ggg ggt tag act tca aca tac g </p>

<p>1 
17 
FAM 
111-115 </p>

<p>OarCP49 
F -cag aca cgg ctt agc aac taa acg c 
R -gtg ggg atg aat att cct tca taa gg </p>

<p>1 
17 
NED 
80-112 </p>

<p>BM0827 
F -ggg ctg gtc gta tgc tga g 
R -gtt gga ctt gct gaa gtg acc </p>

<p>1 
3 
NED 
202-220 </p>

<p>OarHH47 
F -ttt att gac aaa ctc tct tcc taa ctc cac c 
R -gta gtt att taa aaa aat atc ata cct ctt aag g </p>

<p>1 
18 
VIC 
124-136 </p>

<p>CSSM47 
F -tct ctg tct cta tca cta tat ggc 
R -ctg ggc acc tga aac tat cat cat </p>

<p>2 
2 
VIC 
124-150 </p>

<p>MAF214 
F -aat gca gga gat ctg agg cag gga cg 
R -ggg tga tct tag gga ggt ttt gga gg </p>

<p>2 
16 
PET 
187-273 </p>

<p>OarCP20 
F -gat ccc ctg gag gag gaa acg g 
R -ggc att tca tgg ctt tag cag g </p>

<p>2 
21 
PET 
65-79 </p>

<p>OarHH41 
F -tcc aca ggc tta aat cta tat agc aac c 
R -cca gct aaa gat aaa aga tga tgt ggg ag </p>

<p>2 
10 
NED 
120-130 </p>

<p>OarVH72 
F -ctc tag agg atc tgg aat gca aag ctc 
R -ggc ctc tca agg ggc aag agc agg </p>

<p>2 
25 
FAM 
123-127 </p>

<p>INRA63 
F -gac cac aaa ggg att tgc aca agc 
R -aaa cca cag aaa tgc ttg gaa g </p>

<p>3 
14 
FAM 
169-193 </p>

<p>OarAE129 
F -aat cca gtg tgt gaa aga cta atc cag 
R -gta gat caa gat ata gaa tat ttt tca aca cc </p>

<p>3 
5 
NED 
147-159 </p>

<p>OarCP34 
F -gct gaa caa tgt gat atg ttc agg 
R -ggg aca ata ctg tct tag atg ctg c </p>

<p>3 
3 
FAM 
102-122 </p>

<p>OarFCB128 
F -cag ctg agc aac taa gac ata cat gcg 
R -att aaa gca tct tct ctt tat ttc ctc gc </p>

<p>3 
2 
PET 
91-121 </p>

<p>OarHH35 
F -aat tgc att cag tat ctt taa cat ctg gc 
R -atg aaa ata taa aga gaa tga acc aca cgg </p>

<p>4 
4 
NED 
117-133 </p>

<p>OarHH64 
F -cgt tcc ctc act atg gaa agt tat ata tgc 
R -cac tct att gta aga att tga atg aga gc </p>

<p>4 
4 
PET 
118-136 </p>

<p>OarJMP029 
F -gta tac acg tgg aca ccg ctt tgt ac 
R -gaa gtg gca aga ttc aga ggg gaa g </p>

<p>4 
24 
FAM 
98-144 </p>

<p>OarJMP08 
F -cgg gat gat ctt ctg tcc aaa tat gc 
R -cat ttg ctt tgg ctt cag aac cag ag </p>

<p>4 
6 
VIC 
115-131 </p>

<p>BM1314 
F-ttc ctc ctc ttc tct cca aac 
R -atc tca aac gcc agt gtg g </p>

<p>5 
22 
NED 
157-173 </p>

<p>BM6506 
F -gca cgt ggt aaa gag atg gc 
R -agc aac ttg agc atg gca c </p>

<p>5 
1 
FAM 
187-201 </p>

<p>CSRD247 
F -gga ctt gcc aga act ctg caa t 
R -cac tgt ggt ttg tat tag tca gg </p>

<p>5 
14 
NED 
215-239 </p>

<p>CSSM31 
F -cca agt tta gta ctt gta agt aga 
R -gac tct cta gca ctt tat ctg tgt </p>

<p>5 
9 
FAM 
144-166 </p>

<p>OarFCB48 
F -gag tta gta caa gga tga caa gag gca c 
R -gac tct aga gga tcg caa aga acc ag </p>

<p>5 
17 
PET 
144-164 </p>

<p>HSC 
F -ctg cca atg cag aga cac aag a 
R -gtc tgt ctc ctg tct tgt cat c </p>

<p>6 
X 
FAM 
267-293 </p>

<p>BM6526 
F -cat gcc aaa caa tat cca gc 
R -tga agg tag aga gca agc agc </p>

<p>6 
26 
VIC 
142-170 </p>

<p> 
R. Sharma et al. / Meta Gene 8 (2016) 14-20 </p>

<p>of 3.70 (Table 2). Thus selection of microsatellites with a range of 
polymorphism reduced the risk of overestimating genetic variability, 
which might occur with the selective use of highly polymorphic loci. A 
microsatellite preferably should have at least 4 alleles to be useful for 
the evaluation of genetic diversity as per the standard selection of 
microsatellites loci (Barker, 1994). However, 3 alleles per locus have 
also been used to evaluate genetic diversity (Li et al., 2010). Therefore 
all the 25 microsatellites were retained for further analysis. 
Allelic diversity (mean number of observed alleles per locus) 
higher than that observed in Tibetan sheep has been reported in 
some of the Indian sheep breeds (Arora et al., 2008; Kumarasamy 
et al., 2009; Radha et al., 2011; Sharma et al., 2010). However, MNA 
in Tibetan breed is higher than that observed in several other 
Indian sheep breeds viz. 4.94 in Madras Red sheep (Prema et al., 
2008), 5.0 in Nilagiri (Girish et al., 2007), 5.04 in Muzaffarnagari 
(Arora and Bhatia, 2004), 5.3 in Kheri (Bhatia and Arora, 2008), 5.6 
in Shahabadi (Pandey et al., 2009), 5.7 in Magra (Arora and Bhatia, 
2006) and 5.88 in Vembur (Pramod et al., 2009).Thus it can be concluded 
that sufficient genetic variability exists in Tibetan sheep despite its 
decreasing population trend. 
The polymorphic information content (PIC) of a marker reveals 
its usefulness in diversity analysis of a breed. Following the criteria 
of Botstein et al. (1980), 84% of the investigated markers were observed 
to be highly informative (PIC N0.5), 12% as reasonably informa-
tive (0.25 b PIC b 0.5) and only 4% were slightly informative 
(PIC b 0.25) across Tibetan breed (Table 2). An average value of 0.63 for 
the PIC once again indicated abundant genetic diversity in this population. 
The higher PIC further indicated the utility of these markers for popula-
tion assignment (MacHugh et al., 1997) as well as genome mapping 
(Kayang et al., 2002) studies in addition to genetic diversity analysis. </p>

<p>3.2. Heterozygosity and Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium </p>

<p>Genetic variability is also measured as the amount of actual or 
potential heterozygosity, which is presented in Table 2. Expected 
heterozygosity was higher than the observed heterozygosity at all the 
loci. The observed and expected heterozygosity values ranged from 
0.150 (BM1314) to 0.842 (CSSM31) and from 0.329 (BM8125) to 0.885 
(BM6526) with an overall mean of 0.473 ± 0.044 and 0.672 ± 0.030, 
respectively. Genetic variation of similar magnitude (0.46-0.55) has also 
been reported in the endangered Namaqua Afrikaner sheep indigenous 
to South Africa (Qwabe et al., 2015). Whereas, higher heterozygosity 
has been reported in the two endangered Spanish breeds, Churra tensina 
(0.659) and Churra lebrijana (0.674) despite their small population size 
(Calvo et al., 2011). Most of the Indian sheep breeds with sufficient 
population exhibit higher heterozygosity (Ho) than the Tibetan sheep 
(Arora et al., 2011). Tibetan belongs to the sheep breeds of North temper-
ate region of India. It has the least diversity estimates among the breeds of 
North temperate region also (Table 3). Similarly, much higher </p>

<p>Table 2 
Observed and effective number of alleles, information index, observed and expected heterozygosity, F IS and average estimates of polymorphic microsatellite loci in Tibetan sheep. </p>

<p>Locus 
Na 
Ne 
I 
Ho 
He 
uHe 
F IS 
PIC 
χ 
2 value </p>

<p>BM0757 
4 
2.926 
1.215 
0.625 
0.658 
0.679 
0.050 
0.609 
8.907 
BM8125 
3 
1.490 
0.609 
0.167 
0.329 
0.338 
0.493 
0.301 
19.583 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>BM0827 
6 
2.586 
1.249 
0.400 
0.613 
0.634 
0.348 
0.570 
22.960 
CSSM47 
4 
1.800 
0.855 
0.222 
0.444 
0.471 
0.500 
0.411 
21.130 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>MAF214 
6 
4.800 
1.651 
0.250 
0.792 
0.826 
0.684 
0.760 
36.078 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OarCP49 
8 
3.587 
1.621 
0.750 
0.721 
0.740 
−0.040 
0.695 
35.075 
OarCP20 
5 
2.658 
1.198 
0.900 
0.624 
0.640 
−0.443 
0.576 
13.388 
OarHH41 
5 
2.855 
1.237 
0.500 
0.650 
0.668 
0.230 
0.598 
7.036 
OarHH47 
6 
4.781 
1.662 
0.421 
0.791 
0.812 
0.468 
0.762 
45.735 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OarVH72 
3 
2.067 
0.785 
0.250 
0.516 
0.529 
0.516 
0.406 
7.418 
BM6526 
11 
8.667 
2.269 
0.462 
0.885 
0.920 
0.478 
0.863 
79.387 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>INRA63 
7 
5.635 
1.800 
0.667 
0.823 
0.846 
0.189 
0.800 
27.088 
OarAE129 
4 
2.941 
1.221 
0.600 
0.660 
0.733 
0.091 
0.610 
6.800 
OarCP34 
7 
5.505 
1.829 
0.563 
0.818 
0.845 
0.313 
0.800 
31.813 
OarFCB128 
7 
4.966 
1.736 
0.250 
0.799 
0.833 
0.687 
0.772 
40.245 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>HSC 
5 
3.375 
1.353 
0.722 
0.704 
0.724 
−0.026 
0.654 
28.439 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OarHH35 
6 
3.879 
1.575 
0.250 
0.742 
0.792 
0.663 
0.715 
31.020 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OarHH64 
6 
4.346 
1.578 
0.412 
0.770 
0.793 
0.465 
0.732 
42.689 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OarJMP029 
9 
5.333 
1.871 
0.750 
0.813 
0.833 
0.077 
0.788 
59.949 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>OarJMP08 
7 
4.042 
1.607 
0.412 
0.753 
0.775 
0.453 
0.716 
33.819 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>BM1314 
5 
1.681 
0.797 
0.150 
0.405 
0.415 
0.630 
0.368 
20.497 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>BM6506 
3 
1.629 
0.644 
0.250 
0.386 
0.396 
0.353 
0.329 
5.788 
CSRD247 
6 
2.676 
1.192 
0.650 
0.626 
0.642 
−0.038 
0.557 
28.553 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CSSM31 
8 
5.348 
1.818 
0.842 
0.813 
0.835 
−0.036 
0.787 
20.559 
OarFCB48 
7 
2.935 
1.383 
0.368 
0.659 
0.677 
0.441 
0.620 
27.125 
Mean 
5.920 
3.700 
1.390 
0.473 
0.672 
0.696 
0.302 
0.632 
SE 
0.387 
0.334 
0.085 
0.044 
0.030 
0.032 
0.057 
0.032 </p>

<p>Na = No. of different alleles. 
Ne = No. of effective alleles = 1/(Sum pi^2). 
I = Shannon's Information Index = −1  *  Sum (pi  *  Ln (pi)). 
Ho = observed heterozygosity = no. of Hets/N. 
He = expected heterozygosity = 1 − Sum pi^2. 
uHe = unbiased expected heterozygosity = (2 N/(2 N − 1))  *  He. 
FIS = Fixation Index = (He − Ho)/He = 1 − (Ho/He). 
Pi is the frequency of the ith allele for the population &amp; Sum pi^2 is the sum of the squared population allele frequencies. 
PIC = polymorphism information content. 
a Significant deviation from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (P b 0.05). </p>

<p>Table 3 
Genetic diversity indices across sheep breeds of Northern temperate region of India. </p>

<p>Breed 
No. of alleles 
Heterozygosity 
Reference </p>

<p>Observed Effective Observed Expected </p>

<p>Rampur Bushair 6.000 
3.471 
0.515 
0.675 
Pandey et al. (2008) 
Gurej 
6.280 
3.340 
0.490 
0.660 
Gupta et al. (2007) 
Karnah 
6.830 
3.960 
0.530 
0.680 
Gupta and Gannai 
(2007) 
Changthangi 
8.760 
4.539 
0.691 
0.716 
Sharma et al. (2010) 
Tibetan 
5.920 
3.700 
0.473 
0.672 
Present study </p>

<p> 
R. Sharma et al. / Meta Gene 8 (2016) 14-20 </p>

<p>heterozygosity has been reported in several exotic sheep viz. Balearic 
sheep breeds (0.62, Pons and Landi, 2015), 12 sheep breeds of Croatia, 
Bosnia and Herzegovina (0.643-0.743, Salamon et al., 2014) and 
Turkish sheep breeds (0.66, Yilmaz and Sezenler, 2015). However, in 
assessing diversity estimates from different studies, it should be 
mentioned that the values are not directly comparable, as different micro-
satellite sets have been used by different workers. These values have only 
suggestive indication of diversity in the population. 
Observed heterozygosity was lower than the expected showing 
a departure from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) and possibil-
ity of inbreeding. Significant deviation from HWE was observed in 13 
out of 25 loci at P b 0.05 (Table 2). Departures from HWE of the sim-
ilar magnitude were also reported in the endangered Spanish sheep 
breeds (Calvo et al., 2011), Italian (Ceccobelli et al., 2015), Turkish 
(Yilmaz and Sezenler, 2015) and in various Indian sheep breeds 
(Radha et al., 2011). Various factors can contribute towards excess 
of homozygotes. First, the locus is under selection. Second, 'null al-
leles' may be present which are leading to a false observation of ex-
cess homozygotes. Third, inbreeding may be common in the 
population. Fourth, the presence of population substructure may 
lead to Wahlunds' effect. (Nei, 1987; Peter et al., 2007). 
Distinguishing among these is generally difficult (Christiansen 
et al., 1974). The likelihood of each of these explanations must be 
assessed from additional data, such as demographic information, 
i.e. population distribution. Null alleles are most unlikely to be segre-
gating at all the loci. Similarly possible Wahlunds' effects may not ac-
count significantly to the observed heterozygote deficit, as all the six 
flocks were at the same location. Ewens-Watterson Test for Neutral-
ity revealed that all the microsatellite except OarHH47 and INRA63 
(Table S1, observed F values lie outside of the upper and lower limits 
of 95% confidence region of the expected F values) were neutral. 
Since 92% loci were neutral, selection as a cause of the decrease in 
observed heterozygosity was ruled out. Thus the difference between 
the observed and expected heterozygosity can be attributed to the 
non-random mating among the individuals of the population. This 
was also reflected in the positive F IS value (0.302 ± 0.057) which 
ranged from − 0.443 to 0.687. Similar to our assumptions, the high 
F IS value (0.143) in the Spanish mouflon was considered as the 
major cause of the Hardy-Weinberg disequilibrium in that popula-
tion (Calvo et al., 2011). 
Higher heterozygote deficiency is generally observed in Indian 
sheep breeds; Magra (16%, Arora and Bhatia, 2006); Shahabadi (21.5%, 
Pandey et al., 2009); Rampur Bushair (22.7%, Pandey et al., 2008), and 
sheep breeds of Rajasthan-Nali (28.4%) and Chokla (28.6%) (Sodhi 
et al., 2006). However, Tibetan sheep (30.2%) exhibited the highest 
heterozygote deficiency among the Indian breeds, investigated so 
far. Authors agree that the major factor contributing towards the 
observed heterozygote deficiency in Tibetan sheep may be inbreeding 
due to extremely small population (b250) and ignorance of sheep 
owners about the scientific management. Under field condition, only 
natural mating is being practiced where the dominant male gen-
erally excludes subordinate males, and presumably sires most of the 
offspring. The general breeding practice in the region was to castrate 
most of the males. This lead to reduced effective population size/or 
mating between relatives and consequent genetic drift. The consan-
guinity produced by mating between relatives can be one of the princi-
pal causes for loss of heterozygotes, but has to be evaluated with 
caution, as inbreeding with significant deficit of heterozygote affect all 
or most of the loci in a similar way. Since eighty percent of loci depicted 
heterozygote deficit (Table 2), therefore we might consider consanguin-
ity as the foremost cause of heterozygote deficiency. Salamon et al. 
(2014) have also concluded that breeding practice lead to the higher 
F IS value in the study involving 12 eastern Adriatic and western Dinaric 
native sheep breeds. Such a high level of inbreeding is risky as it could 
lead to genetic diseases and moreover can adversely affect animal 
fitness. </p>

<p>3.3. Genetic bottleneck analysis </p>

<p>Bottleneck influences the distribution of genetic variation within and 
among populations. Population of Tibetan sheep has gone down drasti-
cally, which indicates the possibility of demographic bottleneck. In re-
cently bottlenecked populations, the majority of loci will exhibit an 
excess of heterozygotes, exceeding the heterozygosity expected in a pop-
ulation at mutation drift equilibrium. To estimate the excess of such het-
erozygosity Sign, Standardized differences and Wilcoxon sign rank tests 
were utilized. The actual mutation model of evolution followed by our 
microsatellites is not known, thus all the three models (IAM, TPM and 
SMM) were selected for running the Bottleneck program. The values of 
average heterozygosity (He) and their probabilities (H N He) in the 
Sign test, under three models of microsatellite evolution were calculated 
and used to measure the expected number of loci with heterozygosity 
excess (Table 4). The expected numbers of loci with heterozygosity ex-
cess were 14.77, 14.94 and 14.62 in IAM, TPM and SMM with probabili-
ties of 0.13211, 0.10276 and 0.39403 respectively, meaning that the null 
hypothesis was accepted when using the Sign test. These results indicate 
that, due to mutation-drift equilibrium, the Tibetan population has not 
undergone a recent genetic bottleneck. The standardized difference test 
provided the T2 statistics equal to 2.252, 0.269 and − 2.667 for the 
IAM, TPM and SMM models, respectively. The probability values were 
less than 0.05 for IAM and SMM, thus hypothesis of mutation-drift equi-
librium was accepted under TPM only. Using the Wilcoxon rank test 
(a non-parametric test) the probability values were 0.00441 (IAM), 
0.28009 (TPM) and 0.91775 (SMM) under these three models, indicating 
that the null hypothesis is accepted under TPM and SMM and thus the 
population under study has not undergone a recent bottleneck. It has 
been considered that the most useful markers for bottleneck detection 
are those evolving under IAM, and they provide guidelines for selecting 
sample sizes of individuals and loci (Cornuet and Luikart, 1996; Di 
Rienzo et al., 1994; Spencer et al., 2000); meanwhile, the TPM is thought 
to more closely simulate microsatellite mutation (Estoup and Cornuet, 
2000). Unlike the SMM, which predicts all mutations corresponding 
to the increment or decrement of a single base-pair repeat, the TPM 
predicts the occurrence of an occasional multiple base-pair repeat 
(Di Rienzo et al., 1994). The strict SMM is obviously the most conserva-
tive model for testing for a significant heterozygosity excess caused by 
bottlenecks, because in some conditions it can produce a heterozygosity 
deficiency, and due to the heterozygosity excess it is always lower than 
other mutation models. Thus we have considered results from all the 
three tests together and it is clear that serious demographic bottlenecks 
have most probably not occurred in this breed. 
The Mode-shift indicator test was also utilized as a second method 
to detect potential bottlenecks, as the non-bottleneck populations 
that are near mutation-drift equilibrium are expected to have a large 
proportion of alleles with low frequency. This test discriminates many 
bottlenecked populations from stable populations (Luikart, 1997; 
Luikart and Cornuet, 1997). A graphical representation utilizing allelic 
class and proportion of alleles showed a normal 'L' shaped distribution 
(Fig. 2). The L shaped curve indicated the abundance of low frequency 
(b 0.10) alleles. This finding suggested the absence of any detectably 
large, recent genetic bottleneck (last 40-80 generations) in declining </p>

<p>Table 4 
Population bottleneck analysis under three microsatellite evolution models. </p>

<p>Test/model 
I.A.M. 
T.P.M. 
S.M.M. </p>

<p>Sign test (number of loci with 
heterozygosity excess) </p>

<p>Exp 
14.77 
14.94 
14.62 
Obs 
18 
15 
11 
P-value 
0.13211 
0.10276 
0.39403 
Standardized differences test 
T2 value 
2.252 
0.269 
−2.667 
P-value 
0.01216 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.39403 
0.00382 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Wilcoxon rank test (one tail 
for heterozygosity excess) </p>

<p>P-value 
0.00441 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.28009 
0.91775 </p>

<p>a Bottleneck (rejection of null hypothesis of mutation drift equilibrium). </p>

<p> 
R. Sharma et al. / Meta Gene 8 (2016) 14-20 </p>

<p>population, where the probability of low frequency allele's loss was very 
high. Taken together all the results indicate the absence of bottleneck 
events in the recent past history of this breed. 
Shrinkage of pasture, inbreeding, absence of scientific animal hus-
bandry practices and management in very harsh climate have resulted 
in diminished profits for the Tibetan sheep herders. As a result, sheep 
rearing has failed to attract younger generations. Additionally, lack of 
proper policy is leading to rapid decline of Tibetan sheep population 
which are less than two hundred and fifty at present. Therefore, timely in-
tervention is required to prevent extinction of this valuable breed of 
sheep, which helps in sustaining the livelihood of highlanders and the 
fragile agro-ecosystem. The information reported here is important for 
sheep breeders for the establishment of conservation strategies. </p>

<p>4. Conclusions </p>

<p>The present work for the first time generated the knowledge of 
existing genetic diversity in the endangered Tibetan sheep based on mi-
crosatellite analysis. It is a unique gene pool with good adaptation to the 
extremely cold and low oxygen conditions. Genetic parameters show a 
high value of inbreeding and therefore this breed should be monitored 
due to very low number of individuals that compose it. Still there is 
scope for reviving the breed because of high allele diversity which sug-
gests that unique alleles present in this breed may not have been lost 
and the absence of bottleneck. 
Supplementary data to this article can be found online at http://dx. 
doi.org/10.1016/j.mgene.2016.01.002. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was financially supported by the Network Project on 
Animal Genetic Resources (ICAR). </p>



<p> 
R. Sharma et al. / Meta Gene 8 (2016) 14-20 </p>



<p> 
R. Sharma et al. / Meta Gene 8 (2016) 14-20 </p>

</text></tei>