<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4181735" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: We aimed to evaluate the intestinal anti-inflammatory properties of silk fibroin 
nanoparticles, around 100 nm in size, when loaded with the stilbene compound resveratrol, in 
an experimental model of rat colitis. 
Methods: Nanoparticles were loaded with resveratrol by adsorption. The biological effects 
of the resveratrol-loaded nanoparticles were tested both in vitro, in a cell culture of RAW 
264.7 cells (mouse macrophages), and in vivo, in the trinitrobenzenesulfonic acid model of rat 
colitis, when administered intracolonically. 
Results: The resveratrol liberation in 1× phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; pH 7.4) was charac-
terized by fast liberation, reaching the solubility limit in 3 hours, which was maintained over a 
period of 80 hours. The in vitro assays revealed immunomodulatory properties exerted by these 
resveratrol-loaded nanoparticles since they promoted macrophage activity in basal conditions 
and inhibited this activity when stimulated with lipopolysaccharide. The in vivo experiments 
showed that after evaluation of the macroscopic symptoms, inflammatory markers, and intestinal 
barrier function, the fibroin nanoparticles loaded with resveratrol had a better effect than the 
single treatments, being similar to that produced by the glucocorticoid dexamethasone. 
Conclusion: Silk fibroin nanoparticles constitute an attractive strategy for the controlled release of 
resveratrol, showing immunomodulatory properties and intestinal anti-inflammatory effects. 
Chronic human inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) is characterized by chronic diarrhea, 
abdominal pain, and bleeding, due to ulceration of the inner lining of the colon and/or 
rectum. The aims of treatment are the remission of the symptoms during the acute flare 
(acute treatment) and control of the chronic inflammation to avoid or delay the occur-
rence of new flares (maintenance treatment). Although the etiology of IBD remains 
unclear, it is generally accepted that it occurs in genetically susceptible subjects, who 
develop an exaggerated immune response in the digestive tract against intestinal 
bacteria, which leads to chronic intestinal inflammation. 
1 In consequence, control 
of the inflammation is the main target of the drugs used nowadays in the therapy of 
IBD, including aminosalicylates, immunosuppressants (glucocorticoids, azathioprine, 
metothrexate, and cyclosporine A), and biologicals (infliximab and adalimumab). 
However, adverse effects, an inconvenient dosing schedule and prohibitive price, </p>

<p>Correspondence: Julio Gálvez 
Department of Pharmacology, ibs 
Granada, Center for Biomedical 
Research, University of Granada, 
Avenida del Cocimiento s/n, 
18100-Armilla, Granada, Spain 
Tel +34 95 824 1793 
Fax +34 95 824 8964 
email jgalvez@ugr.es </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
23 September 2014 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4508 </p>

<p>Lozano-Pérez et al </p>

<p>in some cases, limit their long-term use. 
2 For this reason, 
the development of new immunomodulatory therapies that 
combine efficacy, convenient dosing, and lesser side effects 
is an important goal in human IBD therapy. 
Among the different approaches available for the therapy 
of IBD, one that has received considerable attention is the 
delivery of anti-inflammatory drugs in the affected colonic 
area through the use of nanoparticles. Different studies 
have indicated that nanomedicines are more beneficial than 
conventional medications regarding inflammation because 
nanoparticles have an increased ability to adhere to inflamed 
tissues compared with healthy ones, allowing better avail-
ability of drugs at lower concentrations and minimizing the 
risks of systemic action and adverse effects, with a general 
improvement of the efficacy. 
3 Similar observations have also 
been made in the management of colon cancer. 
4,5 In fact, the 
deposition and adherence of fluorescent polystyrene particles 
were greater in the ulcerated regions of the inflamed tissue 
than in nonulcerated control tissue in experimental models 
of rodent colitis; this adhesion was size-dependent, the 
best results being obtained with particle sizes ranging from 
25 to 100 nm. 
3 Based on this paradigm, different groups 
have developed the delivery of several drugs, such as tac-
rolimus and rolipram, delivered on poly(lactic-co-glycolic 
acid) nanoparticles; dexamethasone on poly(d-lactide) 
particles; 
3 or fluticasone propionate on hydroxypropyl 
betacyclodextrin. </p>

<p>6   Currently, there are many biomaterials available for 
the fabrication of nanoparticles for drug delivery. Among 
them, fibroin, a polymeric protein present in the silk of the 
lepidopteran insect Bombyx mori L., has shown a set of 
remarkable properties, such as biocompatibility and a simple 
processing technology, which makes it adequate for this 
application. Fibroin has experienced an outstanding develop-
ment in tissue engineering research as it can adopt a great 
diversity of configurations in the shape of films, hydrogels, 
sponges, and electrospun mats and fibers. 
7 In addition, fibroin 
can be elaborated as micro-and nanoparticles, with excellent 
properties as vectors for drug delivery. 
8-10 Many compounds 
can be encapsulated in fibroin particles, such as proteins, like 
insulin; 
11 antitumorals, like paclitaxel; 
12 and curcumin. 
13 In 
addition, fibroin is highly biocompatible, and its degradation 
products from the action of proteases are peptides that are 
easily reabsorbed by the tissues. As a consequence, neither 
fibroin nor its byproducts produce an inflammatory reaction 
or an adverse effect. </p>

<p>14   Besides, fibroin is not only an inert drug carrier. The 
peptides resulting from its hydrolysis have shown therapeutic </p>

<p>potential, for instance, in the stimulation of glucose transport 
in normal and insulin-resistant 3T3-L1 adipocytes 
15 or in the 
proliferation of fibroblasts in wound healing models. 
11 Kim 
et al also reported the anti-inflammatory activity of fibroin 
peptides in a mice edema model of inflammation. 
16 These 
effects were associated with the decrease of cyclooxyge-
nase-2, interleukin (IL)-6, IL-1β, and tumor necrosis fac-
tor (TNF)-α levels in the inflamed tissue. In addition, silk 
fibroin has also shown beneficial effects on wound healing 
in vivo, 
17 through upregulation and phosphorylation of c-Jun, 
a protein responsible for the migration of keratinocytes in 
wound healing models. </p>

<p>18   The aim of the present study was to test the intestinal 
anti-inflammatory effects of fibroin nanoparticles (FNPs) 
loaded with resveratrol on the trinitrobenzene sulphonic acid 
(TNBS) experimental model of rat colitis, which resembles 
human IBD. 
19 The combination of the good qualities of 
fibroin as a delivery vector and the anti-inflammatory and 
healing effects of its peptides could enhance the therapeu-
tic action of the drug. Resveratrol is a stilbene compound, 
present in many plant species, with excellent antioxidant, 
anti-inflammatory, antiviral, and antitumor properties 
20,21 but 
with a low bioavailability, which could be improved by 
nanoparticle delivery. We tested the anti-inflammatory 
effects of FNPs, either unloaded or loaded with resveratrol, 
and compared them with a widely used anti-inflammatory 
drug, the glucocorticoid dexamethasone. Special attention 
was paid to their effects on the expression of some of the 
mediators involved in the inflammatory response, such as 
proinflammatory cytokines (IL-1β, TNF-α, IL-6, and IL-12), 
chemokines (cytokine-induced neutrophil chemoattractant 
[CINC]-1 and monocyte chemoattractant protein [MCP]-1), 
and adhesion molecules (intercellular adhesion molecule 
[ICAM]-1), as well as different markers of epithelial integ-
rity in the mucosa, like the mucins MUC-2 and MUC-3, and 
the proteins trefoil factor (TFF)-3 and villin. In addition, 
the effects of resveratrol-loaded FNPs (RL-FNPs) were 
tested in vitro in RAW 264.7 cells (mouse macrophages). 
RL-FNPs showed immunomodulatory properties and had a 
better intestinal anti-inflammatory effect than the single treat-
ments, being similar to that obtained with the glucocorticoid 
dexamethasone. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Materials </p>

<p>Silk fibroin was obtained from silkworms reared in the 
sericulture facilities of the Instituto Murciano de Investi-
gación y Desarrollo Agrario y Alimentario (Murcia, Spain). </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4509 </p>

<p>Resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticles in TNBS rat colitis </p>

<p>All reagents, including resveratrol (99% purity, fine 
crystalline powder), were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich 
Corp (St Louis, MO, USA). </p>

<p>Preparation of reconstituted 
liquid silk fibroin </p>

<p>Cocoons were boiled twice for 45 minutes in aqueous 0.02 N 
Na 2 CO 3 and then rinsed thoroughly with water to extract the 
glue-like sericin proteins. The raw silk fibroin was then dried 
at room temperature for 72 hours before being dissolved 
at 10% (w/v) in Ajisawa's reagent 
22 -composed of CaCl 2 / 
ethanol/H 2 O (1:2:8, molar ratio) -for 6 hours at 70°C (avoid-
ing boiling). The silk solution was dialyzed for 48 hours 
against distilled water, to remove CaCl 2 , smaller molecules, 
and some impurities, using a cellulose semipermeable mem-
brane (cutoff 12 kD). </p>

<p>Preparation of silk FNPs </p>

<p>FNPs were prepared by nanoprecipitation in MeOH. 
10 Briefly, 
10 mL of 4% (w/v) silk fibroin aqueous solution was 
dropped into 90 mL of cold MeOH with gentle stirring. The 
resulting suspension of nanospheres was stirred for 2 hours. 
Then, nanoparticles were recovered by centrifugation at 
18,500 g for 15 minutes at 4°C (Eppendorf Centrifuge 5810R, 
equipped with a F-34-6-38 rotor; Eppendorf AG, Hamburg, 
Germany), washed with water, and lyophilized. They were 
stored at room temperature in a desiccator until use. </p>

<p>Preparation and characterization 
of RL-FNPs </p>

<p>RL-FNPs were prepared by an incubation method. Briefly, 
25 mg of lyophilized FNPs were added to 1 mL of resveratrol 
solution in ethanol, in Eppendorf tubes, and gently agitated 
for 24 hours, protected from the light. Loaded particles were 
collected by centrifugation at 18,000 g for 15 minutes at 4°C, 
washed with MilliQ water to remove unloaded resveratrol, 
and dried under reduced pressure in a Concentrator plus™ 
(Eppendorf AG) at room temperature for further character-
ization and utilization. Blank nanoparticles were prepared 
in a similar manner, omitting the drug. All batches were 
prepared in triplicate. The RL-FNPs were diluted to the 
desired concentration immediately before use, according to 
the equivalent dose of resveratrol. 
The mean diameter and size distribution of the nano-
particles were measured by dynamic light scattering (DLS) 
using a Malvern Mastersizer 2000E instrument (Malvern 
Instruments, Malvern, UK). All measurements were per-
formed in purified water at 25°C. Calculation of the size </p>

<p>and polydispersity index was achieved by the software 
provided by the manufacturer. The mean diameter values 
were calculated from the measurements performed, at least, 
in triplicate. Morphological examination of the nanoparticles 
was conducted using a JEOL-JSM-6060 (JEOL Ltd, Tokyo, 
Japan) scanning electron microscope (SEM). One drop of 
nanoparticle suspension was fixed on an aluminum stub, 
coated with gold (under vacuum, by an auto fine coater), and 
examined at different magnifications. 
The infrared (IR) spectra of pure resveratrol, unloaded 
FNPs, and RL-FNPs were compared by Fourier transform 
IR (FTIR) spectroscopy. For this purpose, an FTIR spectro-
meter (Perkin-Elmer Spectrum 100 Series; PerkinElmer Inc., 
Waltham, MA, USA), controlled with Spectrum Software 
version 6.1.0.0038, was used. Samples (~2 mg) were mixed 
with ~198 mg of KBr (Sigma-Aldrich Corp) and ground 
into a fine powder using a mortar and pestle, before being 
compressed into a disk (Perkin Elmer 15.011; PerkinElmer 
Inc.). Each spectrum was acquired in transmittance mode 
(ten scans) with a resolution of 4 cm 
-1 and spectral range 
of 4,000-500 cm 
-1 . The analysis was finally focused in the 
range of 2,000-500 cm 
-1 as the most informative for the IR 
spectra of silk fibroin for these assays. 
For the drug-loading content (DLC) and encapsulation 
efficiency (EE) experiments, the concentration of resveratrol 
in the loading solution varied from 1 to 25 mg/mL in etha-
nol. The quantity of loaded resveratrol was determined by a 
direct method, in a Synergy MX ultraviolet visible ( UV-Vis) 
spectrometer (Bio Tek Instruments Inc; Winooski, VT, 
USA). The amount of resveratrol loaded was determined at 
a wavelength of 320 nm, after extraction in ethanol, by refer-
ence to a calibration curve (0.5-25 μg/mL). Briefly, 25 mg of 
dried RL-FNPs were extracted with 1 mL of fresh ethanol in 
an Eppendorf tube. After 1 hour of gentle shaking, they were 
centrifuged at 18,000 g to remove FNPs, and their resveratrol 
concentration was then measured. The DLC and EE were 
represented by the equations (1) and (2), respectively: </p>

<p>DLC 
Weight of the drug in nanoparticles 
Weight of the nanopartic 
(%) = 
l les 
×100 (1) </p>

<p>EE 
Weight of the drug in nanoparticles 
Weight of the feeding drug 
(%) = 
s s 
×100 (2) </p>

<p>For further confirmation, resveratrol loading was also 
determined by an indirect method. The amount of resvera-
trol lost in the loading solution was assayed spectropho-
tometrically. The amount of drug loaded was calculated </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4510 </p>

<p>Lozano-Pérez et al </p>

<p>as the difference between the drug added in the loading 
solution and the drug content remaining in solution after 
incubation with FNPs. All experiments were performed 
in triplicate. 
The release rate of resveratrol from the silk FNPs in 
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) was also evaluated. Briefly, 
25 mg of dried RL-FNPs were dispersed in 25 mL of PBS 1× 
(pH 7.4) in a 50 mL Falcon™ tube and then maintained at 
37°C with gentle agitation. At different times of incubation, 
samples were centrifuged until the supernatants were clear, 
and then aliquots of 150 μL of supernatant were withdrawn 
from the incubation medium, centrifuged at 18,000 g to 
remove residual FNPs, and measured for resveratrol con-
centration as described above. Samples were diluted to the 
calibration range (0.5-25 μg/mL) with ethanol (ethanol/PBS 
9:1). Each assay was performed in triplicate, including a 
negative control of PBS without RL-FNPs. After sampling, 
an equal volume of fresh PBS was immediately added to 
the incubation medium. The amount of resveratrol released 
from the nanoparticles was expressed as a percentage of the 
total resveratrol loaded in the nanoparticles and was plotted 
as a function of time. </p>

<p>Bioactivity of RL-FNPs in RAW 264.7 cells </p>

<p>RAW 264.7 cells (mouse macrophage cells) were obtained 
from the Cell Culture Unit of the University of Granada 
(Granada, Spain) and cultured in Dulbecco's Modified 
Eagle's Medium (DMEM), supplemented with 10% fetal 
bovine serum (FBS) and 2 mM L-glutamine, in a humidified 
5% CO 2 atmosphere at 37°C. The RAW 264.7 cells were 
seeded onto 96-well plates, at a density of 5×10 
5 cells per 
well, and grown until confluence. They were cultured for 
2 hours with each concentration of the nanoparticles (100, 
250, and 500 μg/mL) (alone or loaded with resveratrol) and 
then stimulated with lipopolysaccharide (LPS) (100 ng/mL); 
similarly, positive and negative controls were also used, 
including three concentrations of resveratrol (12, 20, and 
60 μg/mL) -which correspond to the maximal release that 
could be obtained with each concentration of the RL-FNPs 
assayed. After 20 hours, the supernatants were collected 
and centrifuged at 10,000 g for 5 minutes: the nitrite levels, 
as an indirect marker of inducible nitric oxide synthase 
(iNOS) activity, were measured using the Griess assay. 
23 Cell 
viability was examined using the cell cytotoxicity 3-(4,5-
dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide 
(MTT) assay kit test (CellTiter 96 
® AQueous One Solution 
Cell Proliferation Assay; Promega Corporation, Madison, 
WI, USA) as described elsewhere. </p>

<p>24   In vivo evaluation of the bioactivity 
of RL-FNPs in the TNBS model of rat 
colitis </p>

<p>This study was carried out in accordance with the "Guide for 
the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals", as promulgated by 
the US National Institutes of Health (NIH), and the protocols 
were approved by the Ethics Committee of Laboratory Ani-
mals of the University of Granada (Spain) (reference number 
CEEA-2010-286). Female Wistar rats (180-200 g) obtained 
from Janvier Labs (St Berthevin, France) were housed in 
Makrolon 
® cages and maintained in an air-conditioned 
atmosphere with a 12/12 hour light-dark cycle, and they 
were provided with free access to tap water and food. The 
rats were randomly assigned to seven groups (n=10). An 
untreated TNBS control group and a noncolitic group were 
included for reference: they received only the vehicle used to 
administer the test compounds. The treatments tested were: 
a) unloaded FNPs, at the dose of 8 mg/rat; b) resveratrol, at 
the dose of 1 mg/rat; c) resveratrol encapsulated in FNPs 
(RL-FNPs), at the ratio of 1 mg in 8 mg nanoparticles/rat; 
and d) dexamethasone, at the dose of 0.1 mg/rat. All the treat-
ments were incorporated in carboxymethylcellulose (0.5% 
w/v) in water and administered intrarectally. 
Colonic inflammation was induced in the control and 
treated groups as previously described. 
25 Briefly, rats were 
fasted overnight, anesthetized with halothane, and given 
10 mg of TNBS dissolved in 0.25 mL of 50% ethanol (v/v), 
by means of a Teflon cannula inserted 8 cm through the anus. 
During and after TNBS administration, the rats were kept in a 
head-down position until they recovered from the anesthesia 
and were then returned to their cages. Rats from the non-
colitic group were administered, intracolonically, 0.25 mL of 
PBS, instead of TNBS. The four treatments described were 
administered from the day following the colitis induction 
until the day before the death of the rats, which took place 
8 days after the induction of the colonic damage. All the rats 
were killed with an overdose of halothane. The animal body 
weights, occurrence of diarrhea, and water and food intake 
were recorded daily throughout all the experiments. Once the 
animals had been killed, the colon was removed aseptically, 
placed on an ice-cooled plate, opened longitudinally, and 
cleaned of its luminal contents with cold saline. Afterwards, 
the colonic segment was weighed and its length measured. 
Each colon was scored for macroscopically visible damage, 
on a 0-10 scale, by two observers unaware of the treatment, 
according to the criteria previously reported. 
25 Then, the 
colonic samples were sectioned in different longitudinal frag-
ments to be used for biochemical determinations or for RNA </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4511 </p>

<p>Resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticles in TNBS rat colitis </p>

<p>isolation. Myeloperoxidase (MPO) activity was measured 
according to the technique described by Krawisz et al and 
the results were expressed as MPO units per gram of wet tis-
sue; one unit of MPO activity was defined as that degrading 
1 μmol hydrogen peroxide/min at 25°C. 
26 The total glutathione 
content was quantified with the recycling assay described by 
Anderson, and the results were expressed as nmol/g wet tis-
sue. 
27 For the analysis of gene expression in colonic samples by 
reverse-transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction 
(RT-qPCR), the total RNA from colonic samples was isolated 
using Trizol 
® , following the manufacturer's protocol. All 
RNA samples were quantified with a Thermo Scientific Nano-
Drop™ 2000 Spectrophoto meter (Thermo Fisher Scientific 
Inc, Waltham, MA, USA), and 2 μg of RNA was reverse-tran-
scribed using Oligo (dT) Primers (Promega Corp). Real-time 
quantitative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification 
and detection were performed on optical grade, 48-well plates 
in an Eco™ Real-Time PCR System (Illumina, Inc., San 
Diego, CA, USA), with 20 ng of complementary (c)DNA, the 
KAPA SYBR 
® FAST qPCR Master Mix (Kapa Biosystems, 
Inc., Wilmington, MA, USA), and specific primers at their 
annealing temperature (Table 1). To normalize messenger (m) 
RNA expression, the expression of the housekeeping gene, </p>

<p>glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was 
measured. The mRNA relative quantitation was calculated 
using the comparative CT (∆∆Ct) method. </p>

<p>28   statistics </p>

<p>All results are expressed as the mean ± standard error of the 
mean (SEM). Differences between means were tested for 
statistical significance using a one-way analysis of variance 
(ANOVA) and post hoc least significance tests. Differences 
between proportions were analyzed with the chi-squared test. 
All statistical analyses were carried out with <rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> 
version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">5.0</rs> (La Jolla, CA, USA), with statistical significance 
set at P0.05. </p>

<p>Results 
Particle size and shape </p>

<p>The DLS measurements showed that 80% of the FNPs had a 
diameter between 35 and 122 nm, with a median diameter of 
64 nm. The RL-FNP diameter (median diameter of 68 nm) 
was slightly bigger than that of unloaded silk FNPs (Figure 1). 
The RL-FNPs were found to have lower values of specific 
surface area than the FNPs (Table 2). These results are 
concordant with the effect of the saturation of the pores in </p>

<p>Table 1 Primer sequences used in real-time PCR assays in colonic tissue </p>

<p>Gene 
Sequence 5′-3′ 
Annealing T (°C) </p>

<p>GAPDH 
FW: CCATCACCATCTTCCAGGAG 
60 
rV: ccTgcTTcaccaccTTcTTg 
IL-1β 
FW: GATCTTTGAAGAAGAGCCCG 
59 
rV: aacTaTgTcccgaccaTTgc 
IL-6 
FW: CTTCCAGCCAGTTGCCTTCTTG 
60 
rV: TggTcTgTTgTgggTggTaTcc 
IL-12 
FW: ACGCTACCTCCTCTTCTTG 
60 
rV: aTgTcgTccgTggTcTTc 
TNF-α 
FW: GTCTTTGAGATCCATGCCATTG 
57 
rV: agacccTcacacTcagaTca 
CINC-1 
FW: CCGAAGTCATAGCCACACTCAAG 
60 
rV: TcaccagacagacgccaTcg 
ICAM-1 
FW: GTGAACTGCTCTTCCTCTTG 
60 
rV: agTggTcTgcTgTcTTcc 
MCP-1 
FW: TCTTCCTCCACCACTATGC 
60 
rV: TcTccagccgacTcFaTTg 
Villin 
FW: TGCTACCTGCTGCTCTATACCTAC 
59 
rV: cTggcTcgTcgTTgTacTTcTg 
TFF-3 
FW: ATGGAGACCAGAGCCTTCTG 
60 
rV: acagccTTgTgcTgacTgTa 
MUC-2 
FW: ACCACCATTACCACCACCTCAG 
60 
rV: cgaTcaccaccaTTgccacTg 
MUC-3 
FW: CACAAAGGCAAGAGTCCAGA 
60 
rV: acTgTccTTggTgcTgcTgaaTg </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CINC, cytokine-induced neutrophil chemoattractant; FW, forward; GADPH, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; ICAM, intercellular 
adhesion molecule; IL, interleukin; MCP, monocyte chemoattractant protein; MUC, mucin; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; RV, reverse; T, temperature; TFF, trefoil 
factor; TNF, tumor necrosis factor. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4512 </p>

<p>Lozano-Pérez et al </p>

<p>the particle surface by the resveratrol adsorbed in the FNPs. 
The SEM images show nanoparticles as discrete particles 
and RL-FNPs as aggregates (Figure 2). Resveratrol crystals 
were found over the surface of the aggregates as an artefact 
of sample preparation for SEM capture. </p>

<p>FTIR spectroscopy </p>

<p>IR spectra of the different FNPs were recorded in order to 
confirm that resveratrol was successfully incorporated into 
the nanoparticles and the structural conformations of the 
protein. The analysis was focused in the region ranging 
from 2,000-500 cm 
-1 (Figure 3), the most useful for detec-
tion of the characteristic absorption peaks of the aromatic 
rings of resveratrol and the silk fibroin amides. The FTIR 
confirmed that resveratrol was successfully incorporated 
onto the nanoparticles since its characteristic peaks (at 
~1,000 and ~1,300 cm 
-1 ) could be differentiated from the 
background of nanoparticles (Figure 3). Amide regions 
showed the characteristic peaks of the β-sheet conforma-
tion, as reported by Zhang et al 
10 denoting a water-insoluble 
protein in these cases. </p>

<p>Dlc and ee </p>

<p>The DLC varied, depending on the feeding ratio. By vary-
ing the feeding ratio of FNPs and resveratrol, the highest </p>

<p>DLC and EE of resveratrol in the nanoparticles were 
11.6%±0.2% (2.89 mg of resveratrol loaded in 25 mg of 
FNPs) and 33.3%±0.2%, respectively. The DLC obtained is 
similar to that found by Shao et al 
29 in a polyethyleneglycol-
polycaprolactone copolymer (PEG/PCL), mPEG4k-PCL20k, 
with a loading content of resveratrol near to 20%, but the 
EE in our study was far below their value (more than 90%). 
Although it is difficult to compare the properties of differ-
ent materials, such as silk and PEG/PCL copolymer, this 
low efficiency reached by the FNPs is probably due to the 
hydrophobicity of resveratrol. 
29 The amount of resveratrol 
loaded in the particles was a function of its concentration in 
the incubation solution, the maximum loading being reached 
at a concentration of 25 mg/mL in ethanol. </p>

<p>Release of resveratrol from RL-FNPs </p>

<p>Resveratrol has very low solubility (0.11-0.3 mg/L) in aque-
ous media (simulated intestinal fluid or PBS). 
30 Our RL-FNPs 
showed curves of liberation with an initial burst, reaching 
resveratrol saturation of the aqueous medium in 3-4 hours 
and maintaining a resveratrol concentration higher than 
15 mg/L in PBS medium over a period of 80 hours. Con-
sidering a volume of 25 mL of PBS, 0.5 mg of resveratrol 
was released initially until medium saturation was reached. 
Taking into account that the DLC of FNPs is about 12%, 
less than 20% of the loaded resveratrol was released in the 
initial burst. Adsorbed resveratrol was stable upon degrada-
tion, and the RL-FNPs showed a prolonged release over 
80 hours (Figure 4). </p>

<p>Bioactivity of RL-FNPs in RAW 264.7 cells </p>

<p>In this assay, we aimed to characterize the immunomodu-
latory properties of RL-FNPs in an in vitro model of cells 
involved in the immune response: the RAW 264.7 cell line 
of mouse macrophages. It is interesting to note that cell 
viability was not affected by any of the treatments used (not 
shown). In the absence of LPS stimulation, the treatment of 
these cells with the different concentrations of the nanopar-
ticles resulted in a progressive increase in the production of 
nitrite (Figure 5A). Similarly, the RL-FNPs also promoted 
the release of nitrite in the cell culture, although to a lesser </p>

<p>Particle size (µm) 
Number of particles (%) </p>

<p>0.01 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>0.1 
1 
10 </p>

<p>FNPs 
RL-FNPs </p>

<p>Figure 1 Particle size distribution (%) of FNPs and RL-FNPs. 
Abbreviations: FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk 
fibroin nanoparticle. </p>

<p>Table 2 Morphological characteristics of silk fibroin particles obtained by DLS </p>

<p>Particles 
Specific surface area (m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/g) 
D(0.1) (nm) 
D(0.5) (nm) 
D(0.9) (nm) </p>

<p>FNPs 
42.90 
0.035 
0.064 
0.122 
RL-FNPs 
11.20 
0.036 
0.068 
0.139 </p>

<p>Notes: D(0.1), D(0.5), and D(0.9) are standard percentile readings from the analysis. D(0.1) (nm) is the size of particle below which 10% of the sample lies; D(0.5) (nm) is 
the size in microns at which 50% of the sample is smaller, and 50% is larger. This value is also known as the mass median diameter (MMD); D(0.9) (nm) is the size of particle 
below which 90% of the sample lies. 
Abbreviations: DLS, dynamic light scattering; FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticle. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4513 </p>

<p>Resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticles in TNBS rat colitis </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>5 µm 
10 µm </p>

<p>3 µm 
10 µm </p>

<p>Figure 2 SEM images of: (A) FNPs (magnification 15,000×); (B) RL-FNPs (5,000×); (C) RL-FNPs (15,000×); and (D) detail of resveratrol crystals (5,000×) grown on the 
surface of aggregated RL-FNPs during sample deposition for SEM capture. 
Abbreviations: FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticle; SEM, scanning electron microscope. </p>

<p>Wavenumber (cm 
-1 ) </p>

<p>T % </p>

<p>4,000 3,500 3,000 2,500 2,000 
1,500 
1,000 
500 </p>

<p>RES </p>

<p>RL-FNPs </p>

<p>FNPs </p>

<p>Figure 3 Comparative FTIR spectra of resveratrol (top), RL-FNPs (middle), and 
FNPs (bottom). 
Abbreviations: FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; FTIR, Fourier transform infrared; RES, 
resveratrol; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticle; T, transmittance. </p>

<p>Time (hours) </p>

<p>RES released (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>20 
40 
60 
80 
0 </p>

<p>Figure 4 Release of resveratrol from RL-FNPs in 25 mL of PBS 1× (pH 7.4) over a 
period of 80 hours. 
Abbreviations: PBS, phosphate-buffered saline; RES, resveratrol; RL-FNP, 
resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticle. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4514 </p>

<p>Lozano-Pérez et al </p>

<p>extent than with the nanoparticles alone. In addition, res-
veratrol was also able to significantly increase the nitrite 
production in basal conditions, when compared with the 
corresponding control, although no concentration-dependent 
effect was obtained. When RAW 264.7 macrophages were 
incubated with LPS, enhanced production of nitrite took 
place, as well as its accumulation in the culture media, due 
to increased expression of iNOS in these cells (Figure 5B). 
The pretreatment with resveratrol-unloaded nanoparticles 
did not significantly modify nitrite levels in comparison with 
control conditions, whereas RL-FNPs, at concentrations of 
250 and 500 μg/mL, were able to reduce nitrite production. 
This inhibition was similar to that obtained when resveratrol 
was assayed at the lowest concentration studied but lower 
than those achieved when the macrophages were incubated 
with higher concentrations of resveratrol (Figure 5B). </p>

<p>In vivo evaluation of the bioactivity 
of RL-FNPs in the TNBS model 
of rat colitis </p>

<p>The aim of this experiment was to verify whether the incor-
poration of resveratrol (1 mg) in the nanoparticles of fibroin 
(8 mg) had an additional anti-inflammatory effect in vivo, 
in comparison with the administration of nanoparticles or 
resveratrol alone. Also, the effects were compared to those 
obtained after intracolonic administration of the glucocorti-
coid dexamethasone (0.1 mg), one of the standard therapies 
in human IBD. 
The macroscopic evaluation of the colonic specimens 
revealed that most of the experimental groups showed an </p>

<p>intestinal anti-inflammatory effect, the exception being those 
colitic animals that received resveratrol alone. This beneficial 
effect was evidenced by a significant reduction of the colonic 
weight/length ratio in comparison with the nontreated group, 
which indicates an improvement of the edema associated with 
the inflamed tissue (Table 3). At the same time, a significant 
reduction in the length of the inflamed/ulcerated colonic tis-
sue was observed 8 days after the administration of TNBS, 
with lower values in the macroscopic score (Table 3). It is 
interesting to note that the effect of the FNPs, alone or loaded 
with resveratrol, was similar to that obtained with the intra-
colonic administration of dexamethasone (Table 3). 
The beneficial effect shown macroscopically was 
also evident in the evaluation of the different biochemi-
cal parameters in the colonic tissue. The treatment of the 
colitic animals with the nanoparticles, alone or resveratrol-
loaded, was associated with a significant reduction of 
the activity of the colonic MPO, probably due to a lesser 
infiltration of leukocytes into the inflamed tissue (Table 3). 
However, it is important to note that the reduction was sig-
nificantly higher when the nanoparticles were loaded with 
resveratrol, showing a similar activity to dexamethasone 
(Table 3). At the same time, the treatment with the RL-
FNPs significantly increased the glutathione content, which 
indicates an improvement of the altered oxidative state that 
was the result of the inflammatory process induced by the 
TNBS, showing significant differences from the group of 
animals that received the unloaded nanoparticles. Again, 
this effect was similar to that observed in the group of rats 
that received dexamethasone (Table 3). </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Nitrite (µM) 
Nitrite (µM) </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>B a s a l 
2 5 0 
1 0 0 
5 0 0 
1 0 0 
2 5 0 
5 0 0 
1 2 
2 0 
6 0 
2 5 0 
1 0 0 
5 0 0 
1 0 0 
2 5 0 
5 0 0 
1 2 
2 0 
6 0 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>FNPs 
(µg/mL) </p>

<p>RL-FNPs 
(µg/mL) </p>

<p>Resveratrol 
(µg/mL) </p>

<p>FNPs 
(µg/mL) </p>

<p>RL-FNPs 
(µg/mL) </p>

<p>Resveratrol 
(µg/mL) </p>

<p>L P S </p>

<p>Figure 5 Production of nitrite in RAW 264.7 cells after exposure to different doses of resveratrol, RL-FNPs, and unloaded FNPs. (A) Reaction without exposure of cells 
to LPS. (B) Reaction with exposure of cells to LPS. 
Abbreviations: FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticle. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4515 </p>

<p>Resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticles in TNBS rat colitis </p>

<p>The analysis of the markers related to the alteration of 
the immune response (and associated with the intestinal 
inflammatory process) showed that the treatment of the 
colitic animals with the RL-FNPs significantly reduced the 
expression of IL-1β, TNF-α, IL-6, and IL-12, with an efficacy 
similar to that of the group receiving dexamethasone, except 
for IL-12 (Figure 6). The administration of unloaded nano-
particles significantly inhibited the expression of IL-6 and 
IL-12, whereas resveratrol alone only had a significant effect 
on the expression of TNF-α (Figure 6). 
Similarly, the administration of the RL-FNPs to the rats 
suffering the intestinal inflammation was associated with a 
significant reduction of the expression of the chemokines 
CINC-1 and MCP-1, this inhibition being similar to that 
achieved when resveratrol was administered. Unloaded 
nanoparticles were only able to reduce significantly the 
expression of MCP-1, whereas dexamethasone did not inhibit 
the expression of either of the two chemokines evaluated 
(Figure 7). On the other hand, the expression of the adhesion 
molecule ICAM-1 was also inhibited after treatment with the 
RL-FNPs, resveratrol, or dexamethasone; however, unloaded 
nanoparticles were devoid of any significant inhibitory effect 
on this proinflammatory marker (Figure 7). 
Finally, the evaluation of the markers related to the pre-
servation of the barrier function of the intestinal epithelium, 
like the mucins MUC-2 and MUC-3, as well as TFF-3 and 
villin, showed that only the treatment with RL-FNPs was 
associated with a significant increment in their expression, 
in comparison with the untreated colitic group, similar to the 
effects observed with dexamethasone (Figure 8). However, 
unloaded nanoparticles or resveratrol did not significantly 
modify the expression of these proteins, in comparison 
with control colitic rats. The recovery of the function of the </p>

<p>epithelial barrier was observed also in the group of colitic 
animals treated with the glucocorticoid dexamethasone, 
supporting the similar intestinal anti-inflammatory effect 
obtained with both treatments (Figure 8). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The results described in the present study indicate that it is 
possible to encapsulate the stilbene resveratrol in nanopar-
ticles made from silk fibroin. This encapsulation results from 
the adsorption of the drug onto the surface of the particles. 
Given that resveratrol has a small charge, the EE of about 
13% is quite low in comparison with other encapsulation 
approaches and materials for this compound. 
31 However, 
even at this low level of encapsulation, the loaded nanopar-
ticles showed a significant and remarkable biological effect -
both in vitro, in a macrophage cell line, and in vivo, in a rat 
model of experimental colitis. The in vitro assays revealed 
the immunomodulatory properties of the FNPs when they 
contained resveratrol, since only in this case were they able 
to both promote the macrophage activity when the cells were 
in basal conditions, and inhibit it when stimulated with LPS. 
These effects are similar to those found when resveratrol 
was tested alone in these in vitro assays. In fact, previous 
studies have reported that resveratrol, although slightly 
enhancing iNOS mRNA in a concentration-dependent man-
ner, decreased nitric oxide production in activated RAW 
264.7 macrophages. </p>

<p>32   The in vivo experiments show that the daily intracolonic 
administration of 1 mg of resveratrol encapsulated in 8 mg 
of FNPs per rat had an intestinal anti-inflammatory effect in 
the experimental model of rat colitis induced by the intraco-
lonic administration of the hapten TNBS, this effect being 
similar to that obtained with the intrarectal administration </p>

<p>Table 3 Effects of resveratrol, resveratrol-loaded fibroin nanoparticles, and unloaded fibroin nanoparticles on colonic macroscopic 
damage score, weight/length ratio, myeloperoxidase activity, and glutathione content, in TNBS experimental rat colitis </p>

<p>Group (n=10) 
Damage score 
(0-10) </p>

<p>Weight/Length 
(mg/cm) </p>

<p>MPO 
(mU/g tissue) </p>

<p>GSH 
(nmol/g tissue) </p>

<p>Noncolitic 
0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>65.8±3.4 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>15.3±1.7 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2,230±202 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>TNBS control 
7.2±0.2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>153.6±15.8 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>119.6±24.5 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1,114±80 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>FNPs (8 mg/rat) 
6.2±0.4 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>117.9±10.7 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>64.9±13.1 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>1,236±44 </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>RL-FNPs 
(1+8 mg/rat) </p>

<p># </p>

<p>5.5±0.3 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>109.8±10.0 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>33.9±9.8 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>1,477±105 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>resveratrol 
(1 mg/rat) </p>

<p>6.4±0.2 </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>128.2±12.7 </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>76.7±21.2 </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>1,320±131 </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>Dexamethasone 
(0.1 mg/rat) </p>

<p>5.8±0.4 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>105.4±9.4 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>35.5±8.3 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>1,497±154 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Notes: Data are expressed as mean ± SEM. Groups with a different letter (a-d) differ statistically (P0.05). </p>

<p># </p>

<p>8 mg of RL-FNPs, loaded with 1 mg of resveratol. 
Abbreviations: FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; GSH, glutathione; MPO, myeloperoxidase; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticle; SEM, standard error of the 
mean; TNBS, trinitrobenzene sulphonic acid. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4516 </p>

<p>Lozano-Pérez et al </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Fold increase 
Fold increase </p>

<p>Fold increase 
Fold increase </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>IL-1β 
IL-6 </p>

<p>TNF-α 
IL-12 </p>

<p>Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs Resv RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex 
Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs Resv RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex </p>

<p>Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs Resv RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex 
Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs Resv RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b,c 
a,b 
a,b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>a 
a 
a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a,c 
a,c </p>

<p>a,d </p>

<p>c,d 
c,d </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>Figure 6 Effects of unloaded FNPs, resveratrol, RL-FNPs, and dexamethasone on colonic gene expression, in TNBS rat colitis, of the cytokines (A) IL-1β, (B) IL-6, (C) 
TNF-α, and (D) IL-12, analyzed by real-time PCR. 
Notes: Pcr data are expressed as mean ± SEM (n=10). Groups with a different letter (a-d) differ statistically (P0.05). 
Abbreviations: Dex, dexamethasone; FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; IL, interleukin; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; Resv, resveratrol; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk 
fibroin nanoparticle; SEM, standard error of the mean; TNBS, trinitrobenzene sulphonic acid; TNF, tumor necrosis factor. </p>

<p>of dexamethasone -a glucocorticoid used as a positive 
control, and one of the therapies available for the treatment 
of human IBD. 
33 Previous study has reported the intestinal 
anti-inflammatory effect of resveratrol in this experimental 
model of rat colitis. 
21 However, our study reveals that the 
incorporation of this compound into FNPs resulted in an 
improvement of its biological properties because the effect 
observed with RL-FNPs was greater than that obtained when 
the resveratrol or the nanoparticles were administered alone, 
suggesting a synergistic action in the encapsulated product. It 
is important to note that the FNPs cannot be considered as an 
inert carrier in experimental colitis since they had an intestinal 
anti-inflammatory effect, thus confirming previous observa-
tions with this biomaterial, both in vivo and in vitro. </p>

<p>16,18   The synergistic effect obtained in the RL-FNPs was evi-
denced macroscopically since the lowest damage score was 
obtained in this group of colitic rats. It is noteworthy that the 
intestinal anti-inflammatory effects were related to the better </p>

<p>recovery of the colonic tissue produced by the treatments in 
comparison with the colitic control; this ruled out a preventa-
tive effect of the treatments since the administration of the 
different test compounds only started once the damage had 
been induced. The higher efficacy obtained with RL-FNPs 
was also demonstrated biochemically as a significantly lower 
reduction in colonic MPO activity in comparison with the 
colitic groups receiving resveratrol or the nanoparticles alone, 
probably related to a reduction of neutrophil infiltration and 
thus demonstrating the superior intestinal anti-inflammatory 
effect of the treatment. </p>

<p>34   Moreover, it is precisely in this group of animals where 
the anti-inflammatory effects were associated with a sig-
nificant improvement in most of the markers related to 
the alteration of the immune response resulting from the 
intestinal injury induced by the TNBS. 
35 In fact, RL-FNP 
administration was the only treatment able to significantly 
inhibit the expression of all the cytokines evaluated, namely </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4517 </p>

<p>Resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticles in TNBS rat colitis </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Fold increase 
Fold increase </p>

<p>Fold increase </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs Resv RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex 
Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs Resv 
RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex </p>

<p>Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs Resv RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex </p>

<p>a,b 
b,c </p>

<p>a,c 
a,c </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>a,c 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>b,c 
b </p>

<p>a,c 
a,c </p>

<p>b 
b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a 
a </p>

<p>CINC-1 
M CP-1 </p>

<p>ICAM-1 </p>

<p>Figure 7 Effects of unloaded FNPs, resveratrol, RL-FNPs, and dexamethasone on colonic gene expression, in TNBS rat colitis, of the chemokines (A) CINC-1, (B) MCP-1, 
and (C) the adhesion molecule ICAM-1, analyzed by real-time PCR. 
Notes: Data are expressed as mean ± SEM (n=10). Groups with a different letter (a-c) differ statistically (P0.05). 
Abbreviations: cINc, cytokine-induced neutrophil chemoattractant; Dex, dexamethasone; FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; ICAM, intercellular adhesion molecule; MCP, 
monocyte chemoattractant protein; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; Resv, resveratrol; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticle; SEM, standard error of the 
mean; TNBS, trinitrobenzene sulphonic acid. </p>

<p>TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and IL-12. This may be relevant since 
the expression of these proinflammatory cytokines has been 
reported to be increased in human IBD, and the effect of 
these cytokines on the intestine has been directly related to 
the induction of tissue injury and/or destruction. 
36 Closely 
associated with the improvement in the immune response 
produced by the different treatments are their effects on the 
chemokines CINC-1 and MCP-1 as well as on the adhesion 
molecule ICAM-1, which could be responsible for the lower 
neutrophil infiltration (which in turn, coincided consistently 
with the lower activity of colonic MPO obtained with the 
treatments) and the decline in monocytes/macrophages in the 
inflamed tissue. This could play a key role in the intestinal 
anti-inflammatory effect because it has been well described 
that in the first steps of the gut inflammation, margination 
and extravasation of circulating leukocytes probably result 
in the perpetuation of the inflammatory process. </p>

<p>37   Also of note is the significant effect of the more active 
treatments, RL-FNPs and dexamethasone, on the improve-
ment of the intestinal epithelium barrier function, as evi-
denced by increased expression of the mucins MUC-2 and 
MUC-3, the primary constituents of the colonic mucus 
layer, 
38 and of TFF-3 and villin, the bioactive peptides 
involved in epithelial protection and repair. 
39,40 This can 
be key to explaining the greater anti-inflammatory effect 
obtained with RL-FNP treatment in comparison with free 
resveratrol and unloaded nanoparticles -this could be one 
of the mechanisms that promotes the mucus-secreting layer 
that covers the epithelium and acts as a physical barrier, pro-
tecting its integrity and making possible a faster recovery of 
the injured colonic tissue. Epithelial barrier function impair-
ment is considered as one of the initial steps in intestinal 
inflammation that facilitates the access of antigens from the 
intestinal lumen and hence, generates an exacerbated immune </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4518 </p>

<p>Lozano-Pérez et al </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>MUC-2 
M UC-3 </p>

<p>TFF-3 
V illin </p>

<p>Fold increase 
Fold increase </p>

<p>Fold increase 
Fold increase </p>

<p>Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs 
Resv 
RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex 
Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs 
Resv 
RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex </p>

<p>Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs 
Resv 
RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex 
Non 
colitic </p>

<p>Colitic 
control </p>

<p>FNPs 
Resv 
RL-
FNPs </p>

<p>Dex </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>a,b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a,c </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>b,c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b,c 
c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b 
b </p>

<p>a 
a </p>

<p>a 
a </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>Figure 8 Effects of unloaded FNPs, resveratrol, RL-FNPs, and dexamethasone on colonic gene expression, in TNBS rat colitis, of the mucins (A) MUC-2 and (B) MUC-3, as 
well as of (C) TFF-3 and (D) villin, analyzed by real-time PCR. 
Notes: Data are expressed as mean ± SEM (n=10). Groups with a different letter (a-c) differ statistically (P0.05). 
Abbreviations: Dex, dexamethasone; FNP, silk fibroin nanoparticle; MUC, mucin; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; Resv, resveratrol; RL-FNP, resveratrol-loaded silk 
fibroin nanoparticle; SEM, standard error of the mean; TFF, trefoil factor; TNBS, trinitrobenzene sulphonic acid. </p>

<p>response. This effect seems to be of special relevance since 
it has been stated recently that mucosal healing is a key 
prognostic parameter in the management of IBD; in fact, 
mucosal healing has emerged as a key treatment goal in IBD 
that predicts sustained clinical remission. </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Silk FNPs constitute an attractive strategy for the controlled 
release of resveratrol. This is even more the case when one 
considers first the low bioavailability of resveratrol, both in 
animals and humans, and second, its low water solubility, 
which hinders its administration since it would need the 
use of an organic solvent (ie, dimethyl sulfoxide, acetone, 
or ethanol) that is not suitable for drug delivery. However, 
further studies, to improve its stability during gastric passage </p>

<p>and to delay drug release to the distal intestine, are needed in 
order to allow the oral administration of this nanoparticulate 
formulation. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Spanish Ministry of Sci-
ence and Innovation (grant number SAF2011-29648) 
with funds from the European Union, and by the Junta de 
Andalucia (grant numbers AGR-6826 and CTS 164). Parts 
of the experiments were financed by funds of the European 
Regional Development Fund (ERDF) Operative Program 
of the Region of Murcia 2007-2013. The research contract 
of Dr A Abel Lozano-Pérez was partially supported (at 
80%) by the FEDER Operative Program of the Region of 
Murcia 2007-2013. F Algieri is a predoctoral fellow of the </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4519 </p>

<p>Resveratrol-loaded silk fibroin nanoparticles in TNBS rat colitis </p>

<p>Junta de Andalucia; J Garrido-Mesa is a predoctoral fellow 
of the Spanish Ministry of Education, Culture and Sport; 
N Garrido-Mesa is a postdoctoral fellow of the Ramon Areces 
Foundation; ME Rodríguez-Cabezas is a postdoctoral fellow 
of Centro de Investigaciones Biomédicas en Red -Enferme-
dades Hepáticas y Digest (CIBER-EHD), which is funded 
by the Instituto de Salud Carlos III. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nanomedicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nanomedicine is an international, peer-
reviewed journal focusing on the application of nanotechnology 
in diagnostics, therapeutics, and drug delivery systems throughout 
the biomedical field. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, CAS, SciSearch®, Current Contents®/Clinical Medicine, </p>

<p>Journal Citation Reports/Science Edition, EMBase, Scopus and the 
Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2014:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>4520 </p>

<p>Lozano-Pérez et al </p>

<p>40. Wang Y, Srinivasan K, Siddiqui MR, George SP, Tomar A, Khurana S. 
A novel role for villin in intestinal epithelial cell survival and homeo-
stasis. J Biol Chem. 2008;283(14):9454-9464. </p>

<p>41. Neurath MF, Travis SP. Mucosal healing in inflammatory bowel dis-
eases: a systematic review. Gut. 2012;61(11):1619-1635. </p>

</text></tei>