<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4916592" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objective: The aims of this point-prevalence study </p>

<p>were to investigate a representative inpatient 
population to determine the prevalence of people 
admitted to hospital for the reason of a foot-related 
condition, and identify associated independent 
factors. </p>

<p>Methods: Participants were adult inpatients in 5 </p>

<p>different representative hospitals, admitted for any 
reason on the day of data collection. Maternity, 
mental health and cognitively impaired inpatients 
were excluded. Participants were surveyed on a 
range of self-reported demographic, social 
determinant, medical history, foot disease history, 
self-care, footwear, past foot treatment prior to 
hospitalisation and reason for admission variables. 
Physical examinations were performed to clinically 
diagnose a range of foot disease and foot risk factor 
variables. Independent factors associated with being 
admitted to hospital for the primary or secondary 
reason of a foot-related condition were analysed 
using multivariate logistic regression. </p>

<p>Results: Overall, 733 participants were included; </p>

<p>mean (SD) age 62 (19) years, male 55.8%. Foot-
related conditions were the primary reason for 
admission in 54 participants (7.4% (95% CI 5.7% to 
9.5%)); 36 for foot disease (4.9%), 15 foot trauma 
(2.1%). Being admitted for the primary reason of a 
foot-related condition was independently associated 
with foot infection, critical peripheral arterial 
disease, foot trauma and past foot treatment by a 
general practitioner and surgeon ( p&lt;0.01). Foot-
related conditions were a secondary reason for 
admission in 28 participants (3.8% (2.6% to 5.6%)), 
and were independently associated with diabetes and 
current foot ulcer ( p&lt;0.01). </p>

<p>Conclusions: This study, the first in a </p>

<p>representative inpatient population, suggests the 
direct inpatient burden caused by foot-related 
conditions is significantly higher than previously 
appreciated. Findings indicate 1 in every 13 
inpatients was primarily admitted because of a foot-
related condition with most due to foot disease or 
foot trauma. Future strategies are recommended to 
investigate and intervene in the considerable 
inpatient burden caused by foot-related conditions. </p>

<p>1-10   Foot disease typically refers collectively to 
ulcers, infections, ischaemia and Charcot foot 
and is usually precipitated by the foot risk 
factors of peripheral arterial disease (PAD), 
neuropathy and deformity. </p>

<p>1-4  10-12   Foot 
trauma typically refers to limb-threatening 
injuries to the foot caused by high energy 
trauma. </p>

<p>8 9   Foot-related conditions have been reported 
to be present in considerable proportions of 
specific inpatient populations. 
1-7 Yet, recent 
reviews conclude the direct foot-related 
inpatient burden has yet to be studied; that 
is, the total prevalence of all hospitalisations 
caused by any foot-related condition within 
a representative inpatient population. </p>

<p>1 2   One large retrospective study of a national 
hospital discharge data set reported that 
1.2% of all hospitalisations were caused by </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ This is the first study to investigate the preva-
lence of people admitted to hospital because of 
any foot-related condition within a representative 
inpatient population. 
▪ This study investigated inpatients from five dif-
ferent hospitals considered to be representative 
of inpatient populations in Australia. 
▪ Data collectors had specific training and high 
accuracy in collecting standard self-reported 
medical history and clinically diagnosed 
foot-related condition variables. 
▪ As a point-prevalence study, findings are reliant 
on the days surveyed being representative of 
standard activity and are unable to determine 
causal relationships. </p>

<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>foot disease; however, it did not report foot trauma. </p>

<p>5   Therefore, there is a distinct gap in information to quan-
tify the direct inpatient burden caused by foot-related 
conditions. 
1 2 Without this information, it is difficult for 
clinicians, researchers and policymakers to comprehend, 
compare and address a burden of disease. </p>

<p>13   Thus, the primary aim of this point-prevalence study 
was to investigate a representative inpatient population 
to determine the prevalence of people admitted to hos-
pital for the primary or secondary reason of a foot-related 
condition. A secondary aim was to investigate the inde-
pendent factors associated with being admitted to hos-
pital for the reason of a foot-related condition. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Study design 
This study was the first in the Foot Disease in Inpatients 
Study (FDIS) research project. The main objective of 
FDIS was to investigate the prevalence, and associated 
factors, of different foot disease disorders and foot risk 
factors in a representative inpatient population. This was 
a multisite observational point-prevalence cross-sectional 
study set in five public hospitals in Queensland, 
Australia. The authors have adhered to the STROBE 
reporting checklist for cross-sectional studies (see online 
supplementary table S1). Site-specific authority was also 
obtained from each hospital, and written informed 
consent was voluntarily obtained from all participants. </p>

<p>Settings 
Five public hospitals made up the sites for this study: (1) 
a major metropolitan hospital (&gt;500 beds) with a catch-
ment population of 900 000 in south Queensland; (2)  major metropolitan specialty (&gt;500 beds) with a catch-
ment population of 900 000 in south Queensland; (3) 
major regional (200-500 beds) with a catchment popula-
tion of 220 000 in central Queensland; (4) large metro-
politan (200-500 beds) with a catchment population of 
250 000 in south Queensland and (5) large regional hos-
pital (50-99 beds) with a catchment population of 30 000 
in north Queensland. These hospitals were purposively 
selected by the authors to maximise the population-based 
generalisability of any findings by representing each of 
the different defined categories of peer group hospitals in 
Australia according to the National Health Performance 
Authority: 
14 major metropolitan, major regional, large 
metropolitan, large regional and medium hospitals. </p>

<p>14   Specialist hospitals are unable to be defined into these 
peer groups; 
14 thus, the authors decided to include a 
major metropolitan specialist hospital instead of a 
medium hospital to further maximise generalisability. 
As a point-prevalence study, each hospital had data 
collected on one day. Practical resource implications 
meant the same day could not be chosen for all hospi-
tals. After consultation with senior hospital manage-
ment, a mid-week day (Tuesday to Thursday) was 
considered to be most representative of standard </p>

<p>hospital activity. The designated day for each hospital 
was decided by the authors according to resource, travel 
and data collector availability. Data collection days for 
hospitals in similar regions were separated by 2 months 
to minimise the possibility of the same participant 
admission being captured twice. Data collection days 
were in 2013: major metropolitan (September), major 
metropolitan specialty ( July), major regional ( June), 
large metropolitan (December) and large regional hos-
pital ( June). </p>

<p>Participants 
Eligible participants were all adult inpatients (&gt;18 years) 
present between 8:00 and 17:00 in the hospital on the 
designated data collection day. An inpatient was defined 
as a person admitted for at least one night of hospital 
care for any reason, either the night prior or the night 
of the designated data collection day as confirmed by 
the treating medical officer. Exclusion criteria included 
those &lt;18 years of age; those with a cognitive deficit as 
determined by the Nurse Unit Manager; or those in a 
paediatric, maternity or psychiatric ward. These criteria 
are typical of point-prevalence inpatient studies. </p>

<p>15-18   Sample size calculation 
An inpatient prevalence of 4.6% was chosen as the basis 
for the sample size calculation. 
1 This was chosen as a 
recent systematic review reported that foot wounds had 
been the most investigated of all inpatient foot-related 
conditions and 4.6% was the reported pooled preva-
lence estimate for inpatient foot wounds from this 
review. 
1 Therefore, a sample size of 750 participants was 
calculated for this study based on an inpatient preva-
lence of 4.6%, a 95% CI of 3.1% to 6.1%, and an α level 
of 0.05. </p>

<p>Data collection instrument 
A Queensland Foot Disease Form (QFDF) data collec-
tion instrument was used to collect all variables 
(figure 1). The QFDF was modified from a similar vali-
dated data collection instrument, the Queensland High 
Risk Foot Form (QHRFF). 
19 In brief, the QHRFF col-
lects 46 items via self-reported history and clinical diag-
noses of foot-related conditions. 
19 20 Modifications to 
the QHRFF to develop the QFDF included enacting any 
changes recommended by its original authors; 
19 remov-
ing variables not applicable to this study and adding vari-
ables identified from recent systematic reviews to be 
applicable to foot-related conditions in inpatients </p>

<p>1 2 21   such as reason for admission. 
1 5 22 The 57-item QFDF 
contained 36 (78%) of the 46 items that were extensively 
tested for reliability and validity in the QHRFF. 
19 The 
authors decided to further test the QFDF by testing the 
accuracy of data collectors using the QFDF against simu-
lated cases, and testing the concurrent validity of a sub-
sample of study data collected using the QFDF 
compared with medical records audited for the same 
data. Both testing procedures are described below. </p>



<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Variables collected 
Table 1 outlines the criteria, definitions and support-
ing citations 
5 8-11 19-39 used for each individual vari-
able collected by the QFDF in this study. Patient 
explanatory variables were self-reported and grouped 
into ward, demographic, social determinant, medical 
condition history, self-care ability, past foot treatment 
and foot disease history variables. Foot explanatory 
variables were clinically diagnosed and grouped into 
foot risk factors, foot disease and foot risk status. The </p>

<p>outcome variable of interest for this study was the self-
reported identification of a foot-related condition as 
the participant's primary or secondary reason for 
admission. From those participants reporting a 
foot-related condition as a reason for admission, the 
foot explanatory variable considered to most likely 
have caused the admission was identified and termed 
the predominant foot-related condition causing ad-
mission. Trained data collectors administered all 
variables. </p>

<p>Figure 1 QFDF data collection 
instrument. CKD, chronic kidney 
disease; CVA, cardiovascular 
accident; ESKD, end-stage 
kidney disease; GP, general 
practitioner; HbA1c, glycated 
haemoglobin; MI, myocardial 
infarct; PAD, peripheral arterial 
disease; QFDF, Queensland Foot 
Disease Form; UTWCS, 
University of Texas Wound 
Classification System. </p>

<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Table 1 Definitions for each item of the QFDF </p>

<p>QFDF item 
Definition </p>

<p>Ward 
Surgical ward 
Participant is in a ward for the purpose of a surgical procedure </p>

<p>23   Medical ward 
Participant is in a ward not for the purpose of a surgical procedure </p>

<p>23   Demographics 
Age 
Participant's age in whole years at time of data collection </p>

<p>19 21 23 24   Sex 
Participant is male, female or other </p>

<p>19 21 23 24   Social determinants 
Socioeconomic status 
Participant's postcode of usual residence was used to determine Australian Index of Relative 
Social Disadvantage status </p>

<p>21 25   Geographical remoteness 
Participant's postcode of usual residence was used to determine Accessibility/Remoteness 
Index of Australia status </p>

<p>21 26   Highest education level 
achieved </p>

<p>What is the highest education qualification level you have achieved? </p>

<p>21 24 27   Born overseas 
In which country were you born? </p>

<p>24 27   Indigenous status 
Are you of Aboriginal or Torres Strait Islander origin? </p>

<p>19 23 24   Medical condition history 
Diabetes 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had diabetes? (Should have 
lasted or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19 21 24 27 28   Diabetes type 
If yes to diabetes, which type of diabetes do you have: type 1 or type 2? </p>

<p>19 21 24 28   Hypertension 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had hypertension or high blood 
pressure? (Should have lasted or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19 24 27   Dyslipidaemia 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had dyslipidaemia or high 
cholesterol? (Should have lasted or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19 24   MI 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had MI or heart attack? (Should 
have lasted or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19 21 24   CVA 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had cardiovascular attack or 
stroke? (Should have lasted or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19 21 24 27   CKD 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had CKD? (Should have lasted 
or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19 21   ESKD 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had kidney failure or do you 
need dialysis? (Should have lasted or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19   Cancer 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had cancer? (Should have lasted 
or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>21 27   Arthritis 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had arthritis? (Should have 
lasted or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>27   Depression 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had depression? (Should have 
lasted or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>24 27   Acute foot trauma 
Have you had major trauma to your feet that resulted in a fracture, burn, wound or infection 
that required hospital treatment? </p>

<p>8 9   Smoker 
Are you a current smoker? </p>

<p>19 21 24 27   Ex-smoker 
If no to smoker, did you ever smoke? </p>

<p>19 21 24 27   Self-care ability 
Mobility impairment 
Are you able to walk without the help of an aide? </p>

<p>11 21   Vision impairment 
Are you able to read a newspaper (with glasses if needed) </p>

<p>11 21   Footwear worn: inside 
From a sheet displaying 16 different types of footwear: What is the type of shoes you have 
worn most inside the house over the past 12 months? </p>

<p>21 29 30   Footwear worn: outside 
From a sheet displaying 16 different types of footwear: What is the type of shoes you have 
worn most outside the house over the past 12 months? </p>

<p>21 29 30   Low-risk footwear 
Participant identified picture of walking shoe, runner, oxford shoe, boot or bespoke footwear 
as footwear worn most </p>

<p>29 30   Moderate-risk footwear 
Participant identified picture of moccasin, ugg boot, slipper or backless slipper as footwear 
worn most </p>

<p>29 30   High-risk footwear 
Participant identified picture of high heels, flip flop, court shoe, mule or sandal as footwear 
worn most </p>

<p>29 30   No footwear worn 
Participant identified picture of socks only or barefoot as footwear worn most </p>

<p>29 30   Continued </p>



<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Table 1 Continued </p>

<p>QFDF item 
Definition </p>

<p>Past foot treatment 
Yes 
Have you been treated for a foot problem in the past 12 months? (Excluding in the current 
admission) </p>

<p>19 31   Podiatry 
Have you been treated for a foot problem by a podiatrist in the past 12 months? (Excluding in 
the current admission) </p>

<p>19 31   GP 
Have you been treated for a foot problem by a GP in the past 12 months? (Excluding in the 
current admission) </p>

<p>19 31   Physician 
Have you been treated for a foot problem by another medical physician in the past 
12 months? (Excluding in the current admission) </p>

<p>19 31   Surgeon 
Have you been treated for a foot problem by a surgeon in the past 12 months? (Excluding in 
the current admission) </p>

<p>19 31   Nurse 
Have you been treated for a foot problem by a nurse in the past 12 months? (Excluding in the 
current admission) </p>

<p>19 31   Orthotist 
Have you been treated for a foot problem by an orthotist in the past 12 months? (Excluding in 
the current admission) </p>

<p>19 31   Other 
Have you been treated for a foot problem by any other health professional/s in the past 
12 months? (Excluding in the current admission) </p>

<p>19 31   Foot disease history 
Previous PN 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had PN? (Should have lasted or 
likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19   Previous PAD 
Have you ever been told by a doctor or nurse that you have had PAD? (Should have lasted 
or likely to last for 6+ months) </p>

<p>19 21   Previous foot ulcer 
Have you ever had a foot ulcer that has healed? </p>

<p>19 21   Previous amputation 
Have you ever had an amputation? Plus, a clinical examination to verify previous healed 
lower extremity amputation site </p>

<p>19 21   Foot risk factors 
PN 
A lack of protective sensation to a 10 g monofilament on at least 2 of 3 plantar forefoot 
locations on at least one foot </p>

<p>11 19 28 32 33   PAD 
Absence of at least one palpable foot pulse and a toe systolic pressure &lt;70 mm Hg on at 
least one foot </p>

<p>10 19 33-35   Mild PAD 
Toe systolic pressure=51-70 mm Hg </p>

<p>10 19 33-35   Moderate PAD 
Toe systolic pressure=31-50 mm Hg </p>

<p>10 19 35 36   Critical PAD (ischaemia) 
Toe systolic pressure=&lt;30 mm Hg </p>

<p>10 19 33 35   Foot deformity 
A score of at least 3 using the 6-point foot deformity score on at least one foot (1 point each 
allocated for small muscle wastage, bony prominence, prominent metatarsal heads, hammer/ 
claw toes, limited joint mobility and Charcot deformity) </p>

<p>19 29 32   Foot disease 
Acute Charcot 
A red, hot, swollen, unilateral neuropathic foot without a local foot wound on at least one 
foot </p>

<p>19 28 32   Current foot ulcer 
Do you have a current foot ulcer or sore? Plus, a clinical examination to verify a full thickness 
wound beneath the ankle </p>

<p>19 37   Current foot infection 
At least 2 manifestations of inflammation beneath the ankle (purulence, erythema, pain, 
tenderness, warmth or induration) </p>

<p>19 33 38 39   Foot risk status 
Low risk 
Nil foot disease history or clinical diagnosis of current foot disease, PN or PAD identified 
during the clinical examination </p>

<p>19 32   At risk 
Clinical diagnosis of PN and/or PAD (excluding critical PAD) identified during the clinical 
examination </p>

<p>19 32   High risk 
Clinical diagnosis of critical PAD, or, foot deformity with PN and/or PAD, or, self-reported 
previous foot ulcer or amputation </p>

<p>19 32   Acute 
Current foot wound or acute Charcot </p>

<p>19 32   Foot-related condition admission 
Primary reason for 
admission </p>

<p>Is a foot condition the main reason for your hospital admission? </p>

<p>5 20 22 23   Secondary reason for 
admission </p>

<p>Is a foot condition another reason for your hospital admission? </p>

<p>5 22 23 </p>

<p>CKD, chronic kidney disease; CVA, cardiovascular accident; ESKD, end-stage kidney disease; GP, general practitioner; MI, myocardial infarct; 
PAD, peripheral arterial disease; PN, peripheral neuropathy; QFDF,Queensland Foot Disease Form. </p>

<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Data collection procedure 
Data collector training 
Data collectors were 27 publicly employed podiatrists 
who routinely used the QHRFF in their existing clinical 
practice. Data collectors were assisted by 25 final year 
undergraduate podiatry students and 4 publicly 
employed other staff. The role of the assistants was to 
help the data collectors with administering the consent-
ing and self-reported history processes only. All data col-
lectors and assistants participated in a 3-hour training 
session &lt;1 month prior to their designated data collec-
tion day. </p>

<p>Data collector testing 
All data collectors were tested on their use of the 
57-item QFDF, using simulated cases to assess their data 
collection accuracy immediately pretraining and post-
training session. A minimum of 80% accuracy on the 
57-item simulated cases was required to be endorsed as 
a data collector and differences in pretraining and post-
training scores were analysed. </p>

<p>Data collection 
Data collection occurred between 8:00 and 17:00 on the 
designated day. Data collection teams of up to eight 
people were allocated up to five wards of potentially eli-
gible participants for data collection. After completing 
the voluntary consenting procedure, included partici-
pants were questioned to determine their self-report 
history variables. Participants were then shown a foot-
wear form (modified with permission from Barton 
et al 
30 ) containing 16 footwear styles to identify their 
main footwear worn inside and outside the house in the 
previous 12 months. All participants then underwent a 
non-invasive physical examination by a data collector to 
determine their clinically diagnosed variables. All partici-
pant data were recorded on the QFDF and all com-
pleted QFDF data collection forms were checked at the 
conclusion of each hospital data collection day by the 
authors for errors or omissions. Any missing data or 
potential data errors were clarified with the data col-
lector concerned. </p>

<p>Data collector audit 
As aforementioned, a subsample of data collected from 
participants (study data) was tested for concurrent valid-
ity with the participants' medical records (medical 
records). As the study was conducted in different 
regions, a random sample was unable to be tested due 
to resource constraints. Therefore, to be representative 
of the different wards and hospitals in the study, a sub-
sample (∼5% of the required study sample size) was 
taken from one general medical and one general surgi-
cal ward located in the large metropolitan hospital, 
which was the third largest (middle-sized) hospital. The 
process for the audit involved first collecting the study 
data from the subsample of participants as per the data 
collection procedure. The hospital medical records of </p>

<p>those participants included in the subsample were then 
audited on the same day by two authors who were 
blinded to the subsample study data collected. The 
authors were instructed to review the medical record 
and complete all applicable variables if noted anywhere 
in the medical record using a QFDF. The applicable vari-
ables recorded from the medical records were then com-
pared with the study data collected for agreement. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All data were analysed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> V.<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">22.0</rs> for Windows 
(SPSS, Chicago, Illinois, USA) or <rs type="software">GraphPad Software</rs>. 
Descriptive statistics were used to display all variables, 
using means and SDs for continuous variables or propor-
tions for categorical variables. Prevalence with 95% CIs 
were calculated using a modified Wald method for 
outcome variables. 
40 χ 
2 or Kruskal-Wallis tests were used 
to test differences between hospitals for categorical vari-
ables and t-tests or analysis of variance to test differences 
between hospitals for continuous variables. 
41 Univariate 
logistic regression analyses were undertaken to test for 
crude associations with the outcomes. </p>

<p>41-43   Multivariate logistic regression was used to analyse for 
independent associations. 
42 43 As this study was investi-
gating a new field, a data-driven backwards stepwise 
method was chosen. 
42 43 All variables achieving crude 
associations ( p&lt;0.2), except those deemed illogical, were 
entered into the backwards stepwise model, non-
significant variables ( p&gt;0.05) were removed at each step, 
until only variables achieving statistical significance 
remained ( p&lt;0.05) and their ORs reported (unadjusted 
model). 
42 43 This model method was consistent with 
similar foot-related studies. 
31 36 44-46 Collinearity was 
tested for all models using correlation matrix (&gt;0.9), tol-
erance (&lt;0.1) and variance inflation factor (&gt;10). 
42 43 If 
collinearity was identified, the variable with the lowest 
OR in the univariate analysis was removed. The Hosmer 
and Lemeshow goodness of fit, Omnibus and 
Negelkerke pseudo R 
2 tests were used at each step of all 
models to indicate goodness of fit, significance, parsi-
mony and potential variance of the outcome variable 
explained by the model, respectively. 
42 43 The final 
unadjusted model was then tested for confounding by 
re-entering in each non-included explanatory variable to 
see if it confounded the independent explanatory vari-
ables in the unadjusted model. 
42 43 A confounder was 
defined, and remained in the model, as changing the β 
effect estimates of at least one unadjusted independent 
explanatory variables by &gt;20% (adjusted model). 
42 Two 
different multivariate models were assessed for each 
outcome variable. The first used all available explanatory 
variables, except the summarised foot risk status variable 
(model 1). The second used the summarised foot risk 
status variable, instead of foot disease history, foot risk 
factors and foot disease explanatory variables (model 2). 
Missing data were treated by excluding cases with 
missing data as missing data were minimal (&lt;5% in all 
models). </p>

<p>42 </p>



<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Lastly, κ for dichotomous variables, weighted κ (wK) 
for ordinal variables and intraclass correlation (ICC; 
models 2 and 1) for continuous variables were used to 
test for measures of agreement for the data collector 
testing and audit. 
41 47 48 κ and wK (SEs ) strengths were 
categorised as: no agreement &lt;0; slight agreement=0-0.20; 
fair agreement=0.21-0.40; moderate agreement=0.41-0.6; 
substantial agreement=0.61-0.8 and near-perfect agree-
ment=0.81-1.0. 
41 47 48 ICC (SD) strengths were cate-
gorised as: weak-moderate agreement &lt;0.75 and strong 
agreement &gt;0.75. </p>

<p>41   RESULTS 
Characteristics 
Online supplementary table S2 reports the demographic 
characteristics of the 1146 total inpatients present 
during the study. Of these, 263 (23%) patients were 
non-eligible and excluded: 248 due to cognitive impair-
ment and 15 for other reasons (including children, 
non-English speaking or unavailable). Non-eligible 
patients were older ( p&lt;0.001) with no differences in sex 
( p=0.717). Of the 883 eligible patients, 733 (83%) con-
sented. There were no differences in age ( p=0.187) 
or sex ( p=0.198) between those consenting and 
non-consenting. 
Table 2 reports the characteristics of the 733 included 
participants. Overall, mean age (SD) was 62.0 (18.6) 
years and 55.8% were males. Differences were evident 
between hospitals for demographic, social determinant, 
medical history, self-care ability, past foot treatment, foot 
disease history and foot risk status variables ( p&lt;0.05). 
No differences between hospitals were recorded for foot 
risk factor and foot disease variables ( p&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Prevalence 
Primary reason for admission for foot-related conditions 
were identified in 54 participants (7.4% (95% CI 5.7% 
to 9.5%)) and 15 of those had diabetes (2.0% (1.2% to 
3.4%); table 2). The predominant causes of these were 
foot disease in 36 participants (4.9% (3.6% to 6.7%); 17 
foot infection, 13 critical PAD, 6 foot ulcer), foot trauma 
in 15 participants (2.1% (1.2% to 3.4%)) and 3 others 
were unable to be determined with the variables col-
lected. Higher proportions of primary foot-related 
admissions existed in the major regional (12.2%) and 
major metropolitan general hospitals (10.7%) as com-
pared with the other hospitals ( p&lt;0.05). 
Secondary reason for admission for foot-related condi-
tions were identified in 28 participants (3.8% (2.6% to 
5.5%)) and 19 of those had diabetes (2.6% (1.6% to 
4.0%); table 2). The predominant causes of these were 
foot disease in 13 participants (1.8% (1.0% to 3.0%); 9 
foot ulcers, 3 foot infections, 1 critical PAD), foot 
trauma in 1 (0.1% (0% to 0.8%)) and 14 others were 
unable to be determined. No differences in proportions 
of secondary foot-related admissions between hospitals 
were identified. </p>

<p>Independent associated factors 
Table 3 reports unadjusted and adjusted OR (95% CIs) 
for variables achieving significance for primary reason 
for admission for foot-related conditions. Univariate ana-
lyses ( p&lt;0.2) identified 20 variables eligible for model 1 
and 12 for model 2 (see online supplementary table 
S3). Current foot ulcer was excluded as collinearity was 
identified with current foot infection. Model 1 identified 
six unadjusted independent associated factors: critical 
PAD, current foot infection, acute foot trauma, past 
surgeon treatment, past general practitioner (GP) treat-
ment and myocardial infarct (MI) history (all p&lt;0.05). 
Identified confounders were: socioeconomic status, dia-
betes, chronic kidney disease (CKD) and dyslipidaemia. 
After adjusting, all factors remained significant (all 
p&lt;0.01), except MI ( p&gt;0.2). Model 2 identified four 
unadjusted independent associated factors: acute foot 
risk status, high foot risk status, past surgeon treatment 
and past GP treatment (all p&lt;0.05). Identified confoun-
ders were: diabetes, MI, CKD, acute foot trauma and 
past podiatry treatment. After adjusting, all factors 
remained significant (all p&lt;0.001). 
Table 4 reports unadjusted and adjusted OR (95% 
CIs) for variables achieving significance for secondary 
reason for admission for foot-related conditions. 
Univariate analyses ( p&lt;0.2) identified 16 variables eli-
gible for model 1 and 10 for model 2 (see online 
supplementary table S3). Current foot infection was 
excluded as collinearity was identified with current foot 
ulcer. Model 1 identified two unadjusted independent 
associated factors: diabetes and current foot ulcer (both 
p&lt;0.001). Identified confounders were: mobility impair-
ment and previous foot ulcer. After adjusting, both factors 
remained significant (both p&lt;0.01). Model 2 identified 
two unadjusted independent associated factors: diabetes 
and acute foot risk status (both p&lt;0.001). No adjustment 
was performed as no confounders were identified. </p>

<p>Data collector testing and audit results 
Online supplementary table S4 reports an improvement 
in the data collectors post-training scores compared with 
pretraining scores ( p&lt;0.001). All participants scored 
&gt;90% in the post-test. Online supplementary table S5 
reports the strengths of agreement between the study 
data and medical records data for the 44 eligible and 28 
consenting participants in the subsample. Of the 19 
applicable variables tested, 12 (63%) had near-perfect/ 
strong, 2 (11%) substantial, 3 (16%) moderate and 2 
(11%) had fair agreement. In variables reporting less 
than near-perfect/strong agreement, study data identi-
fied more cases than medical records. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Principal findings 
We believe this is the first study to investigate the direct 
inpatient burden caused by all foot-related conditions 
within a representative inpatient population. Our </p>

<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Table 2 Participant characteristics for each hospital site (number (%) unless otherwise stated) </p>

<p>n 
Total </p>

<p>Large 
regional </p>

<p>Major 
regional 
Large Metro </p>

<p>Major Metro 
specialty </p>

<p>Major Metro. 
general 
p Value </p>

<p>Participants 
733 
733 
21 
82 
90 
232 
308 
Ward 
Medical 
733 459 (62.6%) 
16 (76.2%) 
49 (59.8%) 
57 (63.3%) 171 (73.7%) 
166 (53.9%) 
Surgical 
733 274 (37.4%) 
5 (23.8%) 
33 (40.2%) 
33 (36.7%) 
61 (26.3%) 
142 (46.1%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Demographics 
Age (SD) years 
731 62.0 (18.6) 
50.0 (18.0)* 
63.5 (19.1) 
63.2 (18.3) 
65.5 (18.3) 
59.5 (18.3)* 
&lt;0.001* 
Age range years 
731 18-99 
20-85 
18-91 
21-96 
18-99 
18-94 
Age groups 
731 
18-40 years 
110 (15.0%) 
6 (28.6%) 
12 (14.6%) 
12 (13.3%) 
28 (12.1%) 
52 (16.9%) 
41-60 years 
188 (25.7%) 
8 (38.1%) 
20 (24.4%) 
23 (25.6%) 
54 (23.4%) 
83 (27.0%) 
61-80 years 
316 (43.2%) 
6 (28.6%) 
36 (43.9%) 
37 (41.1%) 
94 (40.7%) 
143 (46.6%) 
81+ years 
117 (16.0%) 
1 (4.8%) 
14 (17.1%) 
18 (20.0%) 
55 (23.8%) 
29 (9.4%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Male sex 
731 408 (55.8%) 
13 (61.9%) 
52 (63.4%) 
46 (51.1%) 127 (54.7%) 
170 (55.6%) 
0.531 
Social determinants 
Socioeconomic status 
711 
Most disadvantaged 
102 (14.3%) 
6 (28.6%) 
4 (5.1%) 
30 (34.1%) 
23 (10.2%) 
39 (13.1%) 
Second most disadvantaged 
159 (22.4%) 
2 (9.5%) 
41 (51.9%) 
40 (45.5%) 
27 (11.9%) 
49 (16.5%) 
Middle 
98 (13.8%) 
12 (57.1%) 
27 (34.2%) 
10 (11.4%) 
22 (9.7%) 
27 (9.1%) 
Second least disadvantaged 
240 (33.8%) 
1 (4.8%) 
5 (6.3%) 
8 (9.1%) 
131 (58.0%) 
95 (32.0%) 
Least disadvantaged 
112 (15.8%) 
0 
2 (2.5%) 
0 
23 (10.2%) 
87 (29.3%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Geographic remoteness 
711 
Major city 
435 (61.2%) 
1 (4.8%) 
1 (1.3%) 
54 (61.4%) 179 (79.2%) 
200 (67.3%) 
Inner regional area 
153 (21.5%) 
0 
40 (50.6%) 
26 (29.5%) 
36 (15.9%) 
51 (17.2%) 
Outer regional area 
66 (9.3%) 
1 (4.8%) 
21 (26.6%) 
8 (9.1%) 
5 (2.2%) 
31 (10.4%) 
Remote area 
30 (4.2%) 
2 (9.5%) 
13 (16.5%) 
0 
5 (2.2%) 
10 (2.4%) 
Very remote area 
27 (3.8%) 
17 (81.0%) 
4 (5.1%) 
0 
1 (0.4%) 
5 (1.7%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Highest education level 
731 
21 
82 
90 
230 
308 
Year 10 and under 
395 (54.0%) 
14 (66.7%) 
58 (70.7%) 
54 (60.0%) 124 (53.9%) 
145 (47.1%) 
Year 12 
132 (18.1%) 
3 (14.3%) 
9 (11.0%) 
18 (20.0%) 
38 (16.5%) 
64 (20.8%) 
Certificate in trade or 
business </p>

<p>74 (10.1%) 
2 (9.5%) 
9 (11.0%) 
10 (11.1%) 
25 (10.9%) 
28 (9.1%) </p>

<p>Diploma or associate degree 
46 (6.3%) 
0 
5 (6.1%) 
5 (5.6%) 
17 (7.4%) 
19 (6.2%) 
Bachelor degree 
48 (6.6%) 
0 
0 
1 (1.1%) 
12 (5.2%) 
35 (11.4%) 
Graduate diploma or 
certificate </p>

<p>15 (2.1%) 
1 (4.8%) 
0 
2 (2.2%) 
6 (2.6%) 
6 (1.9%) </p>

<p>Postgraduate degree 
18 (2.5%) 
1 (4.8%) 
1 (1.2%) 
0 
7 (3.0%) 
9 (2.9%) 
Other 
3 (0.4%) 
0 
0 
0 
1 (0.4%) 
2 (0.6%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Born overseas 
731 161 (22.0%) 
2 (9.5%) 
11 (13.4%) 
20 (22.5%) 
53 (22.8%) 
75 (24.4%) 
0.159 
Indigenous 
732 
34 (4.6%) 
10 (47.6%) 
5 (6.1%) 
3 (3.4%) 
8 (3.4%) 
8 (2.6%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Continued </p>



<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Table 2 Continued </p>

<p>n 
Total </p>

<p>Large 
regional </p>

<p>Major 
regional 
Large Metro </p>

<p>Major Metro 
specialty </p>

<p>Major Metro. 
general 
p Value </p>

<p>Medical condition history 
Diabetes 
733 172 (23.5%) 
6 (28.6%) 
20 (24.4%) 
18 (20.0%) 
66 (28.4%) 
62 (20.1%) 
0.195 
Type 2 diabetes † 
162 (22.1%) 
6 (28.6%) 
20 (24.4%) 
18 (20.0%) 
59 (25.4%) 
59 (19.2%) 
0.139 
Hypertension 
733 359 (49.0%) 
11 (52.4%) 
40 (48.8%) 
52 (57.8%) 129 (55.6%) 
127 (41.2%) 
0.006* 
Dyslipidaemia 
733 234 (31.9%) 
6 (28.6%) 
30 (36.6%) 
34 (37.8%) 
91 (39.2%) 
73 (23.7%) 
0.001* 
Myocardial infarct 
733 146 (19.9%) 
4 (19.0%) 
10 (12.2%) 
18 (20.0%) 
67 (28.9%) 
47 (15.3%) 
0.001* 
Cerebrovascular accident 
733 
85 (11.6%) 
1 (4.8%) 
10 (12.2%) 
10 (11.1%) 
36 (15.5%) 
28 (9.1%) 
0.173 
Chronic kidney disease 
733 
89 (12.1%) 
1 (4.8%) 
9 (11.0%) 
15 (16.7%) 
31 (13.4%) 
33 (10.7%) 
0.431 
End-stage kidney disease † 
733 
9 (1.2%) 
0 
3 (3.7%) 
1 (1.1%) 
0 
5 (1.6%) 
NA 
Cancer 
733 174 (23.7%) 
1 (4.8%) 
19 (23.2%) 
26 (28.9%) 
43 (18.5%) 
85 (27.6%) 
0.021* 
Arthritis 
733 274 (37.4%) 
5 (23.8%) 
36 (44.4%) 
40 (44.4%) 
91 (39.2%) 
102 (33.1%) 
0.100 
Depression 
733 191 (26.1%) 
2 (9.5%) 
29 (35.4%) 
28 (31.1%) 
55 (23.7%) 
77 (25.0%) 
0.069 
Acute foot trauma 
733 
26 (3.5%) 
1 (4.8%) 
4 (4.9%) 
6 (6.7%) 
2 (0.9%) 
13 (4.2%) 
0.079 
Smoker 
733 104 (14.2%) 
7 (33.3%) 
18 (22.0%) 
17 (18.9%) 
12 (5.2%) 
50 (16.2%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Ex-smoker 
733 304 (41.5%) 
10 (47.6%) 
34 (41.5%) 
35 (38.9%) 109 (47.0%) 
116 (37.7%) 
0.256 
Self-care ability 
Mobility impairment 
729 242 (33.2%) 
4 (19.0%) 
36 (43.9%) 
37 (41.1%) 
78 (33.8%) 
87 (28.5%) 
0.020* 
Vision impairment 
730 110 (15.1%) 
2 (9.5%) 
10 (12.2%) 
12 (13.5%) 
41 (17.7%) 
45 (14.7%) 
0.637 
Footwear worn: inside 
728 
Low-risk footwear 
81 (11.1%) 
0 
9 (11.0%) 
5 (5.6%) 
29 (12.7%) 
38 (12.4%) 
Moderate-risk footwear 
263 (36.1%) 
2 (9.5%) 
35 (42.7%) 
28 (31.1%) 108 (47.2%) 
90 (29.4%) 
High-risk footwear 
139 (19.1%) 
11 (52.4%) 
12 (14.6%) 
17 (18.9%) 
33 (14.4%) 
66 (21.6%) 
No footwear worn 
245 (33.7%) 
8 (38.1%) 
26 (31.7%) 
40 (44.4%) 
59 (25.8%) 
112 (36.6%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Footwear worn: outside 
726 
Low-risk footwear 
386 (53.2%) 
12 (57.1%) 
46 (56.1%) 
50 (55.6%) 118 (51.5%) 
160 (52.6%) 
Moderate-risk footwear 
75 (10.3%) 
1 (4.8%) 
8 (9.8%) 
10 (11.1%) 
34 (14.8%) 
22 (7.2%) 
High-risk footwear 
250 (34.4%) 
8 (38.1%) 
26 (31.7%) 
29 (32.2%) 
74 (32.3%) 
113 (37.2%) 
No footwear worn 
15 (2.1%) 
0 
2 (2.4%) 
1 (1.1%) 
3 (1.3%) 
9 (3.0%) 
0.405 
Past foot treatment 
733 
Yes 
256 (34.9%) 
6 (28.6%) 
38 (46.3) 
31 (34.4%) 
83 (35.8%) 
98 (31.8%) 
0.167 
Podiatrist 
180 (24.6%) 
4 (19.0%) 
21 (25.6%) 
23 (25.6%) 
70 (30.2%) 
62 (20.1%) 
0.105 
GP 
93 (12.7%) 
3 (14.3%) 
22 (26.8%) 
8 (8.9%) 
19 (8.2%) 
41 (13.3%) 
&lt;0.001* 
Surgeon 
36 (4.9%) 
0 
6 (7.3%) 
2 (2.2%) 
6 (2.6%) 
22 (7.1%) 
0.050 
Physician 
21 (2.9%) 
2 (9.5%) 
7 (8.5%) 
0 
4 (1.7%) 
8 (2.6%) 
0.002* 
Nurse 
20 (2.7%) 
1 (4.8%) 
3 (3.7%) 
0 
6 (2.6%) 
10 (3.2%) 
0.486 
Orthotist 
4 (0.5%) 
0 
1 (1.2%) 
1 (1.1%) 
0 
2 (0.6%) 
NA 
Other 
9 (1.2%) 
3 (14) 
0 
1 (1.1%) 
0 
5 (1.6%) 
NA 
Foot disease history 
Previous peripheral 
neuropathy </p>

<p>728 
99 (13.6%) 
0 
9 (11.0%) 
13 (14.4%) 
20 (8.7%) 
57 (18.8%) 
0.004* </p>

<p>Previous PAD 
728 
97 (13.3%) 
1 (4.8%) 
7 (8.5%) 
13 (14.4%) 
17 (7.4%) 
59 (19.4%) 
0.001* 
Continued </p>

<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>

<p>9 
Open Access </p>

<p>Table 2 Continued </p>

<p>n 
Total </p>

<p>Large 
regional </p>

<p>Major 
regional 
Large Metro </p>

<p>Major Metro 
specialty </p>

<p>Major Metro. 
general 
p Value </p>

<p>Previous foot ulcer 
731 
72 (9.8%) 
1 (4.8%) 
6 (7.3%) 
9 (10.0%) 
17 (7.4%) 
39 (12.7%) 
0.228 
Previous amputation 
731 
30 (4.1%) 
0 
2 (2.4%) 
3 (3.3%) 
6 (2.6%) 
19 (6.2%) 
0.181 
Foot risk factors 
Peripheral neuropathy 
728 160 (22.0%) 
3 (14.3%) 
24 (29.6%) 
16 (17.8%) 
58 (25.1%) 
59 (19.3%) 
0.137 
PAD 
728 
Mild PAD 
69 (9.5%) 
2 (9.5%) 
7 (8.5%) 
8 (8.9%) 
25 (10.8%) 
27 (8.9%) 
Moderate PAD 
51 (7.0%) 
0 
5 (6.1%) 
7 (7.8%) 
18 (7.8%) 
21 (6.9%) 
Critical PAD 
33 (4.5%) 
1 (4.8%) 
2 (2.4%) 
3 (3.3%) 
8 (3.5%) 
19 (6.3%) 
0.887 
Foot deformity 
706 158 (22.4%) 
2 (9.5%) 
13 (16.0%) 
20 (22.7%) 
51 (22.5%) 
72 (24.9%) 
0.293 
Foot disease 
Acute Charcot 
730 
2 (0.3%) 
0 
0 
0 
2 (0.9%) 
0 
NA 
Current foot ulcer 
732 
46 (6.3%) 
0 
6 (7.3%) 
5 (5.6%) 
10 (4.3%) 
25 (8.1%) 
0.298 
Current foot infection 
723 
24 (3.3%) 
0 
5 (6.2%) 
3 (3.3%) 
5 (2.2%) 
11 (3.6%) 
0.405 
Foot risk status 
731 
Low risk 
445 (60.9%) 
15 (71.4%) 
43 (52.4%) 
59 (65.6%) 132 (57.1%) 
196 (63.8%) 
At risk 
111 (15.2%) 
1 (4.8%) 
20 (24.4%) 
9 (10.0%) 
50 (21.6%) 
31 (10.1%) 
High risk 
109 (14.9%) 
4 (19.0%) 
8 (9.8%) 
16 (17.8%) 
37 (16.0%) 
44 (14.4%) 
Acute 
66 (9.0%) 
1 (4.8%) 
11 (13.4%) 
6 (6.7%) 
12 (5.2%) 
36 (11.7%) 
0.001* 
Foot-related condition admission 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>732 
82 (11.2%) (9.1 to 13.7) 
1 (4.8%) 
13 (15.9%) 
6 (6.7%) 
14 (6.0%) 
48 (15.6%) 
0.002* </p>

<p>Primary reason (95% CI) 
732 
54 (7.4%) (5.7 to 9.5) 
1 (4.8%) 
10 (12.2%) 
5 (5.6%) 
5 (2.2%) 
33 (10.7%) 
0.002* 
Secondary reason (95% CI) 
732 
28 (3.8%) (2.6 to 5.5) 
0 
3 (3.7%) 
1 (1.1%) 
9 (3.9%) 
15 (4.9%) 
NA </p>

<p>*p Value of &lt;0.05. 
 †Numbers also included in overall condition. GP, general practitioner; Metro, metropolitan; NA, not applicable to test as the assumption of χ 
2 test is violated as two cells had expected count &lt;5; 
PAD, peripheral arterial disease. </p>



<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>findings indicate 7.4% of all inpatients were hospitalised 
for the primary reason of a foot-related condition, 
including 4.9% for foot disease and 2.1% foot trauma. 
Interestingly, only 28% of those had diabetes. An add-
itional 3.8% were hospitalised with a foot-related condi-
tion as a secondary reason for admission, including 
1.8% for foot disease and 0.1% for foot trauma. Being 
admitted for the primary reason of a foot-related condi-
tion was independently associated with having critical 
PAD, foot infection, foot trauma or past foot treatment 
by a surgeon or GP. Whereas, being admitted for a sec-
ondary reason of a foot-related condition was inde-
pendently associated with having diabetes or a current 
foot ulcer. Overall, these findings suggest the direct 
inpatient burden caused by foot-related conditions is 
significantly higher than previously reported, affecting 
1 in 13 inpatients with the majority not related to 
diabetes. </p>

<p>Interpretations of findings 
The large disparity between our 7.4% direct foot-related 
inpatient burden finding and the 1.2% in the only previ-
ous similar study 
5 may be explained by a number of 
methodological differences. The previous study retro-
spectively investigated foot disease codes only from a 
standard hospital discharge data set to identify patients, </p>

<p>5   compared with our study which prospectively examined </p>

<p>for all possible foot-related conditions. Yet, our study still 
reported a much higher rate for those hospitalised for 
foot disease (4.9%) compared with the previous study 
(1.2%). 
5 Retrospective analyses compared with prospect-
ive examinations have been found to under-report 
foot-related admissions in the same Australian inpatient 
population by threefold. 
12 Additionally, the previous 
study investigated hospital admissions, 
5 whereas our 
study investigated a one occupied hospital bed day 
period. Foot-related admissions use threefold the 
number of bed days than average hospital admissions in 
Australia. 
3 6 These methodological improvements com-
pared with the previous study suggest our findings are 
plausible and much higher than previously reported. 
We found only 28% of foot-related hospitalisations 
were in people with diabetes which was similar to the 
15% reported in the previous study. 
5 This suggests the 
majority of the inpatient foot-related burden may not be 
caused by diabetes as has been traditionally considered. </p>

<p>3 4   Our findings equate to 2.0% of all inpatients, on a given 
day, being in hospital because of diabetes-related foot 
disease in Queensland. Considering a recent retrospect-
ive study of the Queensland hospital discharge data set 
identified that 0.9% of all hospital bed days in 
Queensland were primarily used to manage diabetes-
related foot disease, 
6 and the under-reporting in retro-
spective studies, 
12 our findings again seem plausible. Our </p>

<p>Table 3 Independent associated factors for primary admissions for foot-related conditions using multivariate logistical 
regression (ORs (95% CI)) </p>

<p>Risk factor 
Unadjusted 
p Value 
Adjusted 
p Value </p>

<p>Model 1 
Myocardial infarct 
0.15 (0.03 to 0.70) 
0.016* 
0.34 (0.06 to 1.90) 
0.219 
Acute foot trauma 
29.49 (7.28 to 119.48) 
&lt;0.001* 
73.32 (15.86 to 338.92) 
&lt;0.001* 
PAD 
&lt;0.001* 
&lt;0.001* 
Nil PAD 
Referent 
Referent 
Mild PAD 
0 
NA 
0 
NA 
Moderate PAD 
2.37 (0.62 to 9.04) 
0.207 
5.45 (1.05 to 28.23) 
0.044 
Critical PAD 
53.60 (16.82 to 170.84) 
&lt;0.001* 
140.56 (30.82 to 641.04) &lt;0.001* 
Current foot infection 
29.39 (7.52 to 114.83) 
&lt;0.001* 
53.11 (9.89 to 285.17) 
&lt;0.001* 
Past GP treatment 
4.65 (1.64 to 13.20) 
0.004* 
7.61 (2.30 to 25.19) 
0.001* 
Past surgeon treatment 5.88 (1.66 to 20.81) 
0.006* 
6.98 (1.91 to 25.54) 
0.003* 
Model 1 results: 
Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>: 0.602; 
Omnibus: df=8, p=&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Missing: 14 (1.9%); 
H&amp;L: p=0.013 </p>

<p>Pseudo R 
2 : 0.657; 
Omnibus: df=15, 
p=&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Missing: 36 (4.9%); 
H&amp;L: p=0.880 </p>

<p>Model 2 
+ Past foot treatment 
Foot risk status 
&lt;0.001* 
&lt;0.001* 
Low risk 
Referent 
Referent 
At risk 
1.66 (0.15 to 18.76) 
0.682 
2.01 (0.18 to 23.16) 
0.574 
High risk 
23.12 (5.05 to 105.95) 
&lt;0.001* 
39.57 (8.15 to 192.05) 
&lt;0.001* 
Acute 
181.44 (40.52 to 812.51) 
&lt;0.001* 
158.63 (30.34 to 829.51) &lt;0.001* 
Past GP treatment 
2.70 (1.17 to 6.25) 
0.020* 
6.40 (2.36 to 17.40) 
&lt;0.001* 
Past surgeon treatment 4.31 (1.49 to 12.44) 
0.007* 
11.62 (3.46 to 39.03) 
&lt;0.001* 
Model 2 results: 
Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>: 0.582; 
Omnibus: df=5, p=&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Missing: 2 (0.3%); 
H&amp;L: p=0.861 </p>

<p>Pseudo R 
2 : 0.638; 
Omnibus: df=10, 
p=&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Missing: 2 (0.3%); 
H&amp;L: p=0.954 </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05.df, degrees of freedom; H&amp;L, Hosmer and Lemeshow test; missing, excluded missing cases; NA, not applicable; Omnibus, Omnibus 
tests of model coefficients; Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, Nagelkerke R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>; GP, general practitioner; PAD, peripheral arterial disease. </p>

<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>findings also appear generalisable when interpreting dia-
betes rate trends between ours and other regions. The 
23.5% inpatient diabetes prevalence found in our 
Queensland study is similar to the 24.7% reported in 
Victoria (Australia), 
17 26.2% in the USA, 
49 50 but higher 
than 15.8% in the UK. 
51 The diagnosed diabetes popula-
tion prevalence in Queensland is 4.5% and 5.0% in 
Victoria; 
52 while the estimated national diabetes popula-
tion prevalence for Australia is 7.8%, 9.2% in the USA 
and 4.9% in the UK. 
53 Also diabetes-related amputation 
rates, often used as a surrogate measure of the foot 
disease burden, showed similar trends with 15 per 
100 000 people reported in Queensland, 
6 18 in Australia, 
36 in the USA and 9 in the UK. 
54 55 These interpretations 
suggest our findings are plausible and potentially gener-
alisable to other regions. 
Our study also found that nearly all those primarily hos-
pitalised for a foot-related condition were due to foot 
disease (67%) or foot trauma (28%). These findings were 
supported by our multivariate models reporting they were 
independantly associated with a foot disease disorder (crit-
ical PAD, foot infection or foot ulceration), foot trauma or 
had previous foot treatment from a GP or surgeon. These 
same independent associates have been consistently identi-
fied in diabetes inpatient populations; 
10 11 37 38 however, 
our findings adjusted for diabetes in a representative 
inpatient population. Furthermore, after adjustment, inpa-
tients classified with acute foot risk status were much more 
likely to be in hospital for the primary reason of a 
foot-related condition than those of lower foot risk status. 
This suggests, regardless of diabetes, that using a diabetes 
foot risk status system 
19 32 may be useful to identify people 
highly likely to be admitted to hospital because of a 
foot-related condition. 
In addition to those primarily hospitalised for a 
foot-related condition, 3.8% of participants reported a </p>

<p>foot-related condition as a secondary reason for their 
admission. This meant the participant had been primar-
ily admitted for another health condition, yet also 
required treatment in hospital to manage a foot-related 
condition. 
23 To the best of the authors' knowledge, no 
study has investigated the prevalence of secondary 
foot-related admissions. Participants with a secondary 
foot-related condition were more likely to have diabetes 
or a current foot ulcer. This is not surprising considering 
people with diabetes have very high rates of foot-related 
conditions compared with other disease processes in the 
population. 
1 5 7 Furthermore, those with a current foot 
ulcer typically require frequent wound dressing 
changes 
4 32 within the average length of hospital admis-
sion. 
3 5 6 Overall, the primary and secondary reason for 
admission findings indicate that 11.2% of all inpatients 
need treatment for a foot-related condition during their 
hospitalisation. 
The type of hospital and ward also appeared to impact 
on the prevalence of people admitted due to a 
foot-related condition. Our findings indicate major 
general hospitals have higher prevalences of people 
admitted with a foot-related condition than other hos-
pital types. Those admitted with a foot-related condition 
as the primary reason were also more likely to be in a 
surgical ward, whereas those admitted as a secondary 
reason were mostly found in a medical ward. These find-
ings may be explained by major general hospitals 
housing more of the necessary surgical disciplines 
needed to effectively manage complex foot-related con-
ditions, 
9-12 32-34 and thus more of these patients being 
transferred to these hospitals. Although this study has 
focused on inpatient explanations, the impact of avail-
able outpatient services cannot be discounted. 
6 This is 
especially the case considering recent significant reduc-
tions in diabetes-related foot disease admissions in </p>

<p>Table 4 Independent associated factors for secondary admissions for foot-related conditions using multivariate logistical 
regression (ORs (95% CI)) </p>

<p>Risk factor 
Unadjusted 
p Value 
Adjusted 
p Value </p>

<p>Model 1 
Diabetes 
5.46 (2.33 to 12.78) 
&lt;0.001* 
4.89 (2.07 to 11.57) 
&lt;0.001* 
Current foot ulcer 9.84 (4.13 to 23.45) 
&lt;0.001* 
4.94 (2.12 to 16.67) 
0.001* 
Model 1 results: 
Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>: 0.233; 
Omnibus: df=2, p=&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Missing: 1 (0.1%); 
H&amp;L: p=0.755 </p>

<p>Pseudo R 
2 : 0.259; 
Omnibus: df=4, p=&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Missing: 5 (0.7%); 
H&amp;L: p=0.425 
Model 2 
Diabetes 
5.27 (2.23 to 12.45) 
&lt;0.001* 
No confounders identified 
Foot risk status 
&lt;0.001* 
Low risk 
Referent 
At risk 
2.19 (0.56 to 8.55) 
0.258 
High risk 
2.81 (0.78 to 10.18) 
0.116 
Acute 
16.12 (5.40 to 48.11) 
&lt;0.001* 
Model 2 results: 
Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>: 0.261; 
Omnibus: df=4, p=&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Missing: 2 (0.3%); 
H&amp;L: p=0.680 </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05. 
df, degrees of freedom; H&amp;L, Hosmer and Lemeshow test; missing, excluded missing cases; NA, not applicable; Omnibus, Omnibus tests of 
model coefficients; Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, Nagelkerke R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. </p>



<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Queensland were reportedly associated with improved 
outpatient multidisciplinary foot services. </p>

<p>6   Implications for policymakers, clinicians and researchers 
Our findings have significant potential implications for 
policymakers. To contextualise these finding, an 
'average' 600-bed hospital could expect to manage 44 
inpatients each night for the primary reason of a 
foot-related condition, including 29 for foot disease and 
13 for foot trauma. This equates to an annual direct cost 
of $A15.6 million for an average hospital if assuming 
$A971 (2015) per Australian hospital bed day. </p>

<p>56   Forecasting this across Australia's 49 153 public hospital 
beds 
57 suggests Australia would need 3637 hospital beds 
each night, or 1.33 million beds each year, at an annual 
cost of $A1.29 billion to primarily manage foot-related 
conditions. Assuming a conservative 13-day average 
length of stay for foot-related conditions 
2-6 indicates 
Australia has over 102 000 annual primary admissions 
for foot-related conditions, including 67 600 for foot 
disease and 27 600 for foot trauma. With cellulitis 
ranked as the 10th leading cause of Australian public hos-
pital admissions with 35 248 admissions, 
58 these figures 
would place foot-related conditions in the top 10 causes 
of hospital admission in Australia. Interestingly, two-thirds 
of these reported cellulitis admissions were infections in 
the lower leg and foot. 
58 These figures are likely to be 
conservative as they do not account for private hospitals, 
surgical procedures, secondary foot-related admissions 
and any other foot-related inpatient management. 
These findings also suggest clinicians should focus 
their inpatient foot-related strategies on foot disease and 
foot trauma, regardless of diabetes. First, we recommend 
using a simple foot risk screening tool, 
19 32 or foot ulcer 
visual inspection, as admission triage strategies to 
improve identification of inpatient foot-related condi-
tions. Like recent amputation prediction tools, 
10 these 
tools could also be enhanced by including critical PAD 
in the acute foot category to further improve identifica-
tion. Second, our findings indicate those people hospita-
lised for a foot-related condition had not previously 
attended the recommended outpatient multidisciplinary 
foot team members. 
4 6 11 32 Thus, we recommended all 
people with foot-related conditions have access to out-
patient multidisciplinary foot teams, regardless of dia-
betes status. Third, our findings support other authors 
recommending episodes of foot-related hospitalisation 
should be an opportunity to triage inpatients into multi-
disciplinary foot teams for best practice care. 
22 28 59 Last, 
it is suggested strategies already demonstrated to reduce 
the inpatient diabetic foot burden should be considered 
for all inpatients admitted for foot-related conditions, 
such as triaging foot-related admissions into specialist 
multidisciplinary foot wards. </p>

<p>4 11 28 59 </p>

<p>Our findings also support further research. First, to 
confirm the findings of this study, we recommend imple-
menting methodologically similar research in other 
regions. </p>

<p>1  11  59   Second, our findings support </p>

<p>recommendations that hospital discharge data coders 
are trained to more accurately identify and code 
foot-related condition admissions to enable more effect-
ive monitoring of standard hospital discharge data 
sets. 
1 12 Third, we recommend reporting the use of 
occupied hospital bed days, rather than whole admis-
sions, to more specifically measure the burden of hospi-
talisation. Fourth, the foot disease and foot trauma 
factors identified in this study should be investigated for 
'up stream' factors that may predict these foot-related 
hospitalisations. Last, it is recommended that clinical 
trials implementing strategies demonstrated to reduce 
the inpatient diabetic foot disease burden should be 
evaluated on all inpatients admitted for foot-related 
conditions. </p>

<p>Strengths and weaknesses 
This study has several strengths. First, the study's find-
ings are generalisable as we purposively investigated rep-
resentative hospitals that reported very similar 
demographic, social determinant and medical history 
characteristics to those reported in other large inpatient 
studies. 
17 58 Second, this study recruited total participant 
numbers &lt;3% of the original sample size calculated, 
reported a robust consent rate &gt;80%, 
18 and no differ-
ences in demographic characteristics between consent-
ing and non-consenting inpatients. Third, the study 
used a data collection instrument modified from a very 
similar valid and reliable data collection instrument that 
captured a range of standard self-reported or clinically 
diagnosed foot-related variables. 
19 Fourth, data collec-
tors had previous similar data collection experience, 
further specific training and reported high accuracy and 
validity when tested against simulated cases and medical 
records. Last, the multivariate models used in this study 
were recommended to identify independent associated 
factors after adjusting for identified confounders and 
the sample size was large enough to account for over 50 
variables. </p>

<p>42 43   This study also had a number of limitations. First, the 
study was cross-sectional and can only report on asso-
ciated factors and not causal relationships. 
41 Second, as 
a point-prevalence study, it relies on the day of data col-
lection being representative of standard inpatient activ-
ity. </p>

<p>18   Third, while excluding cognitively impaired 
patients is standard, 
15-18 this may have introduced a 
selection bias towards under-reporting foot-related con-
ditions as excluded patients were mostly older cognitively 
impaired patients that have higher foot disease rates 
than cognitively intact patients. 
60 Fourth, although 
standard self-reported medical history and clinically 
diagnosed foot-related variables were used, these were 
not gold standard biomedical criteria and may under-
report medical conditions. 
10 17 34 Fifth, while the study 
used a data collection instrument modified from an 
existing valid and reliable instrument, it was only 
retested against simulated cases and medical records, 
which limits our knowledge on its validity and reliability </p>

<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>for capturing these data. 
41 Last, as this study used over 
100 statistical tests, there is the likelihood of a type 1 stat-
istical error. </p>

<p>41-43   CONCLUSIONS 
This is the first study to investigate the burden caused by 
people admitted to hospital because of foot-related con-
ditions within a representative inpatient population. 
Findings indicate the burden is significantly higher than 
previously reported with 1 in every 13 inpatients in hos-
pital for the primary reason of a foot-related condition. 
These patients were mostly affected by foot disease or 
foot trauma, in major general hospitals and most did 
not have diabetes. It is recommended that serious con-
sideration be given to future strategies to investigate and 
intervene in this considerable, yet historically underap-
preciated, inpatient burden. </p>

<p>Author affiliations </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>School of Clinical Sciences, Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, 
Queensland, Australia </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation, Queensland University of 
Technology, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Allied Health Research Collaborative, Metro North Hospital &amp; Health Service, 
Brisbane, Queensland, Australia </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Department of Podiatry, Metro North Hospital &amp; Health Service, Queensland 
Health, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Wound Management Innovation Cooperative Research Centre, Brisbane, 
Queensland, Australia </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>School of Physiotherapy, Australian Catholic University, Banyo, Queensland, 
Australia </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Department of Podiatry, North West Hospital &amp; Health Service, Mount Isa, 
Queensland, Australia </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Department of Podiatry, West Moreton Hospital &amp; Health Service, 
Queensland Health, Ipswich, Queensland, Australia </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes, Royal Brisbane and Women's 
Hospital, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>School of Medicine, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Queensland, 
Australia </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors wish to warmly acknowledge the tireless 
work of the multiple data collectors from Queensland Health and Queensland 
University of Technology. Without their enthusiasm this study would not have 
been possible. The authors also wish to recognise the ongoing support 
provided to this work by Queensland Health, Wound Management Innovation 
Cooperative Research Centre, the Australian Government's Cooperative 
Research Centres Program and Queensland University of Technology. </p>

<p>Contributors PAL conceived, designed, collected data, analysed data, 
wrote and reviewed/edited the manuscript. SEH, SSK, MCK and LR 
conceived, designed, collected data and reviewed/edited the manuscript. 
VN, CT, SJ, EMK, MCdE designed, collected data and reviewed/edited the 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This work was supported by grant funding from Queensland Health 
(Queensland Government, Australia) and the Wound Management Innovation 
Cooperative Research Centre (Australia). </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval This study received ethical approval from two Human 
Research Ethics Committee (HREC): The Prince Charles Hospital HREC 
(Ethics No. HREC/13/QPCH/5) and the Queensland University of Technology 
HREC (Ethics No. 1300000367). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>



<p>Lazzarini PA, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010811. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010811 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>