<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4453845" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Key challenges of biopsy-based determination of prostate cancer aggressiveness include tumour heterogeneity, 
biopsy-sampling error, and variations in biopsy interpretation. The resulting uncertainty in risk assessment leads to significant 
overtreatment, with associated costs and morbidity. We developed a performance-based strategy to identify protein biomarkers 
predictive of prostate cancer aggressiveness and lethality regardless of biopsy-sampling variation. </p>

<p>Methods: Prostatectomy samples from a large patient cohort with long follow-up were blindly assessed by expert pathologists 
who identified the tissue regions with the highest and lowest Gleason grade from each patient. To simulate biopsy-sampling error, 
a core from a high-and a low-Gleason area from each patient sample was used to generate a 'high' and a 'low' tumour microarray, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Results: Using a quantitative proteomics approach, we identified from 160 candidates 12 biomarkers that predicted prostate 
cancer aggressiveness (surgical Gleason and TNM stage) and lethal outcome robustly in both high-and low-Gleason areas. 
Conversely, a previously reported lethal outcome-predictive marker signature for prostatectomy tissue was unable to perform 
under circumstances of maximal sampling error. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Our results have important implications for cancer biomarker discovery in general and development of a sampling 
error-resistant clinical biopsy test for prediction of prostate cancer aggressiveness. </p>

<p>Prostate cancer accounts for 27% of incident cancer diagnosed 
in men in the USA. The American Cancer Society estimates that, 
nationally, 233 000 new diagnoses of prostate cancer will be 
made in 2014 (Siegel et al, 2014). Of all men newly diagnosed 
with prostate cancer, only about one in seven will progress to 
metastatic disease over a lifetime, whereas approximately half of </p>

<p>them will have localised disease that has a very low risk of 
progression (Carter et al, 2012; Siegel et al, 2014). Despite this 
low risk, as many as 90% of these low-risk prostate cancer 
patients in the United States undergo radical treatment, usually 
radical prostatectomy (RP) or ablative radiation therapy 
(Cooperberg et al, 2010). Such treatments for low-risk patients </p>

<p>*Correspondence: Dr P Blume-Jensen; E-mail: pblumejensen@metamarkgenetics.com or Dr DM Berman; E-mail: Bermand@queensu.ca 
5 Present address: Atreca Inc., San Carlos, CA 94070, USA. 
6 Present address: Karyopharm Therapeutics, Natick, MA 01760, USA. </p>

<p>Received 16 April 2014; revised 16 June 2014; accepted 20 June 2014; published online 17 July 2014 </p>

<p>&amp; 2014 Cancer Research UK. All rights reserved 0007 -0920/14 </p>

<p>FULL PAPER </p>

<p>Keywords: prostate cancer; biopsy; biomarkers; prognosis; sampling error; tumour heterogeneity </p>

<p>British Journal of Cancer (2014) 111, 1201-1212 | doi: 10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>
may be excessive and often result in long-term adverse 
events, including urinary incontinence and erectile and bowel 
dysfunction (Wilt et al, 2008; Moyer and U.S. Preventative  Services Task Force, 2012; Loeb et al, 2014). 
Current guidance and accepted standards of care for the diagnosis 
and management of prostate cancer recommend the use of clinical 
and pathological parameters to assess the disease grade and stage on 
biopsy (NCCN, 2012a; NCCN, 2012b). Pathological evaluation of 
tissue obtained by needle biopsy is essential both to confirm a 
prostate cancer diagnosis and to grade the cancer. Tumour grade, as 
determined by the biopsy Gleason score (GS) is the most important 
predictor of outcome, and considered the most informative 
parameter for guiding management decisions. The GS is comprised 
of two Gleason patterns, with the more prevalent pattern specified 
first. The two are summed to determine the GS. According to a 2005 
consensus on Gleason scoring, only three patterns (3, 4, and 5) are 
typically recognised on biopsy (Epstein et al, 2005). The accepted 
prognostic categories of GS are 3 þ 3 ¼ 6, 3 þ 4 ¼ 7, 4 þ 3 ¼ 7, 8, 
and 9-10. Importantly, although 3 þ 4 ¼ 7 and 4þ 3 ¼ 7 have 
equivalent Gleason sums, the latter has significantly worse prognosis 
based on a higher amount of pattern 4 (Goodman et al, 2012; Reese  et al, 2012). Approximately 80-85% of all prostate cancer biopsies 
have a GS of 3 þ 3 ¼ 6 or 3 þ 4 ¼ 7, representing a spectrum of cases 
with low to intermediate to high risk of progression (Epstein et al,  2012). Patients deemed to have indolent disease are candidates for 
active surveillance (AS) (Mohler et al, 2012; NCCN, 2012a; NCCN,  2012b). However, current methods of biopsy evaluation are often 
unable to place individual patients accurately along this spectrum 
(Cooperberg et al, 2010; Epstein et al, 2012). 
Two recognised factors affect the accuracy of biopsy-based 
Gleason scoring: one is sampling variation (i.e., failing to sample 
the area with the highest Gleason grade), and the second is 
pathologist discordance in Gleason scoring (Porten et al, 2011;  Corcoran et al, 2012; Epstein et al, 2012). Despite the current 
standard practice of multicore biopsy sampling, the most 
aggressive area of the tumour is frequently under-represented or 
over-represented (Corcoran et al, 2012; Bjurlin and Taneja, 2014). 
Indeed, 25-50% of cases of prostate cancer need to be either 
upgraded or downgraded from their initial biopsy score to a more 
accurate surgical GS after analysis and grading of prostatectomy 
tissue (Kvale et al, 2009; Davies et al, 2011; Epstein et al, 2012). 
Discordance between pathologists in Gleason grading can be as 
high as 30%, adding significantly to the difficulty of ensuring 
uniform and accurate prognostication (McKenney et al, 2011;  Goodman et al, 2012). 
Several clinical and pathological risk stratification systems have 
been developed to improve prediction of prostate cancer aggres-
siveness, including the D'Amico classification system, the Cancer 
of the Prostate Risk Assessment score, and the National 
Comprehensive Cancer Network guidelines (Cooperberg et al,  2005; D'Amico et al, 1998; NCCN, 2012a; Vellekoop et al, 2014). In 
addition, clinical nomogram systems such as the widely adopted 
systems described by Kattan and Steyerberg have been developed 
to predict indolent prostate cancer and prostate cancer out-
come(Steyerberg et al, 2007). All such systems recognise the biopsy 
GS as the single most powerful variable in risk assessment. 
Importantly, all of the risk stratification systems used to guide 
clinical management depend on effective and consistent Gleason 
scoring and are therefore vulnerable to sampling variation and 
discordant scoring by pathologists. 
Enhanced biopsy strategies have been proposed as one means to 
overcome sampling variation and errors. Among these, increasing 
the number or density of sampled cores might ensure more 
representative capture of tumour tissue. However, this could 
potentially increase the risk of adverse events from oversampling, 
and there is little evidence that it improves pathological 
classification (Eichler et al, 2006; Delongchamps et al, 2009). </p>

<p>There has also been interest in novel forms of image-guided biopsy. 
Currently, MRI-guided biopsy appears to improve detection of 
aggressive cancers, but long-term studies will be needed to 
determine whether it can improve patient selection for AS 
(Robertson et al, 2013). 
Using a quantitative multiplex proteomics in situ imaging 
system, which enables accurate biomarker measurements from the 
intact tumour epithelium (Shipitsin et al, 2014), we here report the 
identification and evaluation of 12 biomarkers that are able to 
predict prostate cancer aggressiveness and lethal outcome. 
Importantly, the markers were specifically selected to be robust 
to sampling error. The study was designed to simulate biased 
biopsy-sampling error based on coring from areas of high and low 
GS on prostatectomy tissue from each patient to generate 'high' 
(H) and 'low' (L) tissue microarrays (TMAs), respectively. 
Biomarkers were then selected based on their ability to reflect 
true prostate pathology and lethal outcome, regardless of whether 
they were measured on cores with high or low GS. This 
performance-based approach not only identified novel biomarkers, 
but also confirmed known biomarkers predictive of prostate cancer 
aggressiveness and lethal outcome. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Reagents and antibodies. All antibodies and reagents used in this 
study were procured from commercially available sources 
as described in Supplementary Table S4. Anti-fluorescein 
isothiocyanate MAb-Alexa 568, anti-CK8-Alexa 488, anti-
CK18-Alexa 488, anti-CK5-Alexa 555, and anti-Trim29-Alexa 
555 were conjugated with Alexa dyes using the appropriate protein 
conjugation kits (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, USA). </p>

<p>Slide processing and staining protocol. From TMA blocks, 5-mm 
sections were cut, placed on Histogrip (Life Technologies)-coated 
slides, and processed as described previously (Supplementary 
Materials). Briefly, after deparaffinisation, antigen retrieval was 
performed in 0.05% citraconic anhydride solution for 45 min at 
95 1C using a Lab Vision PT module (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, 
MA, USA). Staining was performed either manually or in automated 
fashion with an Autostainer 360 or 720 (Thermo Scientific). 
The quantitative multiplex immunofluorescence (QMIF) stain-
ing procedure that combined two anti-biomarker antibodies with 
region-of-interest markers was performed as previously described 
(see Supplementary Materials and Methods). </p>

<p>Acquisition, processing, quality control, and annotation of 
FFPE prostate cancer tissue blocks. A set of FFPE human 
prostate cancer tissue blocks with clinical annotations and long-
term patient outcome information was acquired from Folio 
Biosciences (Powell, OH, USA). Information about prostate 
cancer-specific deaths was obtained from either patient records 
or death certificates. Samples had been collected with appropriate 
institutional review board approval and all patient records were de-
identified. For evaluation of candidate biomarker antibodies, FFPE 
human prostate cancer tissue blocks with limited clinical annota-
tion were acquired from other commercial sources. 
A series of 5-mm sections was cut from each FFPE block. For 
annotation, a 5-mm section that was the last to be cut from each 
FFPE block was stained with haematoxylin and eosin and scanned 
using a ScanScope XT system (Aperio, Buffalo Grove, IL, USA). 
The scanned images were remotely reviewed and annotated for GS 
in a blinded manner by expert clinical board-certified anatomical 
pathologists. Circles corresponding to 1-mm diameter cores were 
placed over four areas of highest and two areas of lowest Gleason 
patterns (see Figure 1, top). </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>Generation of TMA blocks. TMA blocks were prepared using 
a modified agarose block procedure (Yan et al, 2007). See 
Supplementary Materials for further details. </p>

<p>Biomarker selection. To identify biomarkers for prostate cancer 
aggressiveness, we developed a selection and evaluation process 
that could be broadly applicable across diseases and conditions. 
The process, shown in Figure 2, had biological, technical, 
performance, and validation stages. See Supplementary Methods 
for further details. </p>

<p>Image acquisition. Two Vectra Intelligent Slide Analysis Systems 
(PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA, USA) were used for automated 
image acquisition as described (Supplementary Materials and 
Methods). Multispectral images were processed into images for 
each separate fluorophore signal and sent for analysis with 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Definiens Developer</rs> script (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Definiens AG</rs>, München, Germany). </p>

<p>Definiens automated image analysis. We developed an auto-
mated image analysis algorithm using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Definiens Developer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">XD</rs> for 
tumour identification and biomarker quantification as described in 
Supplementary Materials. </p>

<p>Data stratification and end points in the analysis. Expression of 
39 biomarkers was examined for correlation with tumour 
aggressiveness and lethality using the H and L TMAs. Disease 
aggressiveness was defined based on prostate pathology (aggressive 
disease ¼ surgical Gleason X3 þ 4 or T3b, N þ , or M þ ). For 
aggressiveness analyses, we examined marker correlation based on 
measurements in both L TMA samples with core Gleason p3 þ 4 
and the corresponding, matched H TMA samples. 
For lethal outcome analyses, we created two different sample 
sets: (1) all cores with an observed GS p3 þ 4; and (2) all cores. </p>

<p>Cohort composition. Table 1a presents the cohort composition. 
Only those samples that had a complete set of clinical information 
were included. When performing an analysis using a certain set of 
biomarkers, only samples with values for those markers were 
considered. Hence, the numbers in the table are upper bounds. </p>

<p>Univariate analysis of aggressiveness and lethality. Our objec-
tives for univariate analysis were two-fold: to characterise 
univariate behaviour as a performance assessment for potential 
inclusion in the final marker set, and to provide a reduced set of 
markers for exhaustive multivariable model exploration. See 
Supplementary Materials for details. </p>

<p>GS 4+3=7 </p>

<p>GS 4+4=8 </p>

<p>4+4 </p>

<p>4+4 
4+4 </p>

<p>3+3 </p>

<p>4+4 </p>

<p>3+3 </p>

<p>GS 3+3=6 </p>

<p>H TMA 
L TMA </p>

<p>Figure 1. Creation of biopsy simulation tissue microarrays (TMAs). A 
tissue block from a prostatectomy sample was annotated with all visible 
Gleason patterns (top). The example shown is from a patient with an 
overall Gleason score (GS) of 4 þ 3 ¼ 7. As shown in a higher-
magnification view (middle), patterns within the same block can be 
highly diverse. Two 1-mm cores were taken from each tissue block. 
One was taken from an area with the highest GS (4 þ 4 ¼ 8) and 
embedded into agarose/paraffin along with high-scoring cores from 
other blocks to create the H TMA (bottom left). The other was taken 
from an area with the lowest GS (3 þ 3 ¼ 6) and embedded into 
agarose/paraffin along with low-scoring cores from other blocks to 
create the L TMA (bottom right). </p>

<p>Initial list: 160 biomarker candidates </p>

<p>Step 1: 
Biological 
criteria </p>

<p>Step 2: 
Technical 
criteria </p>

<p>Step 3: 
Performance-
based criteria </p>

<p>Prioritised list: 120 candidates </p>

<p>Technical validation: 62 candidates </p>

<p>39 Ab candidates tested 
Univariate performance, multivariate performance </p>

<p>Biomarker selection on H&amp;L TMAs cohort </p>

<p>Final selection </p>

<p>12 Markers identified 
Biological relevance, published literature, univariate 
and multivariate analysis, technical considerations </p>

<p>DAB: specificity, signal intensity 
IF: specificity, signal intensity, dynamic range, 
epitope stability, staining uniformity </p>

<p>1. Biological relevance for cancer 
2. In silico analysis 
3. Human protein atlas 
4. Monoclonal Ab availability </p>

<p>Figure 2. Biomarker selection strategy. Three types of criteria were 
used to select 12 final biomarkers. (DAB: Ab specificity assessed based 
on chromogenic tissue staining with diamino benzidine (DAB); IF: Ab 
specificity and performance based on immunofluorescent tissue 
staining). </p>

<p>Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>
Biomarker ranking for aggressiveness via exhaustive search of 
multimarker models. We sought to rank the biomarkers by 
importance in multimarker models; 31 biomarkers, refined from 
the original set of 39 to improve technical performance further, 
were used in an exhaustive biomarker search. We considered all 
combinations of up to five biomarkers from the 31 biomarkers 
tested in the L TMA in the H and L TMA analysis. See 
Supplementary Materials for further details. </p>

<p>Biomarker ranking for lethality via exhaustive search of 
multimarker models. The same model-building approach done </p>

<p>for aggressiveness was followed for the biomarker ranking for 
prediction of lethality. Supplementary Table S3 shows frequency of 
biomarker utilisation (top 5%) for lethality. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Biopsy simulation. Our first goal was to develop a biopsy-
sampling model to simulate and exaggerate the biopsy sample 
variation observed in clinical practice. For this purpose, we </p>

<p>Table 1b. Clinical features of the cohort used to create L and H TMAs. The distribution of H TMA core Gleason scores and surgical Gleason scores among 
the 301 patients with L TMA core Gleason of 3 þ 3 or 3 þ 4 </p>

<p>Core Gleason score 
L TMA: n of patients 
Core Gleason score 
H TMA: n of patients 
Surgical Gleason score n of patients </p>

<p>3 þ 3 ¼ 6 
233 
3 þ 3 ¼ 6 
1 4 9 
3 þ 3 ¼ 6 
9 3 </p>

<p>3 þ 4 ¼ 7 
5 8 
3 þ 4 ¼ 7 
1 1 2 </p>

<p>X 4 þ 3 ¼ 7 
2 6 
X 4 þ 3 ¼ 7 
3 0 </p>

<p>3 þ 4 ¼ 7 
6 8 
3 þ 3 ¼ 6 
2 3 
3 þ 3 ¼ 6 
1 4 </p>

<p>3 þ 4 ¼ 7 
2 7 
3 þ 4 ¼ 7 
3 2 </p>

<p>X4 þ 3 ¼ 7 
1 8 
X 4 þ 3 ¼ 7 
2 2 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: H TMA ¼ high-grade tissue microarray; L TMA ¼ low-grade tissue microarray. </p>

<p>Table 1a. Clinical features of the cohort used to create L and H TMAs. A single cohort of 380 patients provided samples for the two TMAs </p>

<p>L TMA 
H TMA </p>

<p>Patients with survival and biomarker information 
360 of 380 
363 of 380 </p>

<p>Mean age (s.d.), years 
62.2 (6.76) 
62.1 (6.83) </p>

<p>Lethal events, n (%) 
60 (16.67) 
59 (16.25) </p>

<p>Mean length of follow-up (s.d.), years 
11.55 (3.96) 
11.52 (3.98) </p>

<p>Pathological tumour stage, n (%) </p>

<p>T2 
244 (67.8) 
250 (68.9) 
T3 
112 (31.1) 
109 (20.0) 
T4 
2 (0.56) 
2 (0.55) 
Missing 
2 (0.56) 
2 (0.55) </p>

<p>Core Gleason score, n (%) </p>

<p>p 6 
233 (64.7) 
177 (48.8) 
3 þ 4 
68 (18.9) 
98 (27.0) 
4 þ 3 
15 (4.2) 
31 (8.5) 
8-10 
27 (7.4) 
47 (13) 
Total 
343 (95) 
353 (97) </p>

<p>Surgical Gleason score, n (%) </p>

<p>p6 
108 (30) 
112 (31) 
3 þ 4 
169 (47) 
138 (46) 
4 þ 3 
30 (8.3) 
30 (8.3) 
8-10 
53 (15) 
53 (15) 
Total 
360 (100) 
363 (100) </p>

<p>Deaths stratified by surgical Gleason score, n (% of disease deaths, % of Gleason stratun) </p>

<p>p6 
2 (3.3, 1.9) 
3 (5.1, 2.7) 
3 þ 4 
20 (33.3, 11.8) 
17 (28.8, 10.1) 
4 þ 3 
9 (15, 30) 
10 (17, 33.3) 
8-10 
29 (48.3, 54.7) 
29 (49.1, 54.7) 
Total 
60 
59 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: H TMA ¼ high-grade tissue microarray; L TMA ¼ low-grade tissue microarray; TMA ¼ tissue microarray. For technical reasons, only 360 samples on the L TMA and 363 samples on 
the H TMA were usable. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>embedded cores from annotated prostatectomy tissue into TMAs. 
On the basis of centralised Gleason grading by expert urologic 
pathologists, a core was taken for each patient from the area with 
the least aggressive tumour (low GS) to generate a low-grade TMA 
(L TMA); in parallel, a core was taken from the area with the most 
aggressive tumour based on Gleason grading (high GS) to generate 
a high-grade TMA (H TMA) (Figure 1). Thus, we developed paired 
tissue TMAs with samples simulating biopsies biased in two 
directions, representing both more and less aggressive tumour 
areas from each patient. 
Table 1a describes the clinical features for the multi-institution 
cohort of 380 patients for whom paired TMAs were prepared. 
Table 1b describes the subset of 301 cases with core Gleason of 
3 þ 3 or 3 þ 4 on L TMA along with their corresponding core 
Gleason on H TMA and their surgical (prostatectomy) Gleason. 
Sampling for the L TMA was specifically designed to under-
estimate disease severity. As shown in Tables 1a and b, 64.7% of L 
TMA samples had a core GS p6, whereas only 30% of these L 
TMA samples came from patients with a surgical GS p6. The 
probability of upgrade (Table 1b) for samples in the L TMA from 
cases with core GS of p3 þ 4 to a higher surgical GS was 0.64 (95% 
Wilson confidence interval (CI): 0.59-0.69). This probability of 
upgrade is higher than that seen in clinical practice (Porten et al,  2011), as expected from the sampling method and patient cohort 
used. Thus, by exaggerating sample variation expected in clinical 
practice, this biopsy simulation procedure provided a useful model 
to identify biomarkers that reliably predict prostate cancer 
aggressiveness, regardless of sample variation. </p>

<p>Effect of sampling error on known biomarker model performance. 
Prior studies have demonstrated that RP GS of seven or higher 
and extension of prostate cancer beyond the prostate gland are 
significant predictors of metastasis and prostate cancer-specific 
mortality (Ross et al, 2012; Shikanov and Eggener, 2012; Brimo  et al, 2013). Accordingly, we defined 'aggressive disease' based on 
the prostate pathology as surgical GS of at least 3 þ 4 or pT3b 
(seminal vesicle invasion), N þ , or M þ . We tested the four-
biomarker model (SMAD4, CCND1, SPP1, and PTEN) previously 
reported by Ding et al (2011) for its ability to predict both disease-
specific death and disease aggressiveness in our sampling variation 
TMA cohort. Using logistic regression analysis on the patient cores 
in the L and H TMAs, marker coefficients and AUC were 
estimated on the testing set. As shown in Table 2, when measured 
on H TMA patient cores, the four-marker signature was able to 
predict disease-specific death with a median test AUC of 0.65 (95% 
CI of 0.59-0.74). However, when measured on L TMA, represent-
ing biased underestimation of the surgical GS, the four-marker 
model showed a non-significant median test AUC of 0.49 (95% CI 
of 0.42-0.58). Moreover, the four-marker signature was unable to 
predict aggressive disease in either H or L TMA (median test AUC 
of 0.56 (95% CI of 0.44-0.64) and of 0.56 (95% CI of 0.46-0.65), </p>

<p>respectively). These results demonstrate the impact of sampling 
error on prognostic marker performance, and support the necessity 
of identifying alternative biomarker combinations that can predict 
outcomes accurately regardless of sampling variation. </p>

<p>Biomarker identification. We next embarked on identifying 
biomarkers that would robustly predict cancer aggressiveness in 
spite of biopsy-sampling variation. The stepwise approach 
involved: (1) identification of candidate biomarkers, (2) evaluation 
of their biological and technical suitability, and (3) analysis of 
performance in H and L TMA cohorts (Figure 2). 
From a search of published literature and publicly available gene 
expression data sets, we identified 160 biomarker candidates based 
on biological relevance for prostate cancer (Lapointe et al, 2004;  True et al, 2006; Lapointe et al, 2007; Tomlins et al, 2007; Cheville  et al, 2008; Nakagawa et al, 2008; Graff et al, 2009; Makarov et al,  2009; Pressinotti et al, 2009; Gorlov et al, 2010; Taylor et al, 2010;  Chen et al, 2011; Cima et al, 2011; Ding et al, 2011; Markert et al,  2011; Ross et al, 2011; Swanson and Quinn, 2011; Ding et al, 2012;  Kristiansen, 2012). We further prioritised 120 of these markers 
based on availability of appropriate monoclonal antibodies (MAbs) 
(see Supplementary Table S1 for a comprehensive biomarker 
candidate list). Our candidate list included well-characterised 
markers relevant for prostate cancer aggressiveness, such as EZH2, 
MTDH, FOXA1 (Hu et al, 2009; Yang and Yu, 2013; Mills, 2014), 
as well as the markers PTEN, SMAD4, Cyclin D1, SPP1, phospho-
PRAS40-T246 (pPRAS40), and phospho-S6-Ser235/236 (pS6) 
previously identified as predictive of lethal outcome on prosta-
tectomy tissue (Ding et al, 2011; Shipitsin et al, 2014). 
We next procured MAbs against these 120 prioritised 
candidates and tested them for specificity and suitability for the 
QMIF assay. Candidate MAbs were further selected on the basis of 
signal intensity and specific immunofluorescence-staining patterns, 
as described (Shipitsin et al, 2014; Supplementary Materials). 
Candidate biomarker antibodies were selected based on signals that 
were more stable relative to those of epithelial markers. 
Subsequently, we tested the 62 MAbs that passed the previous 
steps and determined their dynamic range as well as their 
predictive performance. Using a small test TMA designed to 
represent the least aggressive areas from prostate tumours with 
high and low overall GSs, biomarkers were selected based on 
correlation of signal intensity with surgical GS. Specifically, we 
required minimally a three-fold difference of signals between 
lowest and highest expression values, in addition to the demon-
strated difference in signal value distributions between nonaggres-
sive and aggressive cases. The final 39 candidate MAbs that 
fulfilled these criteria were tested on the clinical cohort represented 
by H and L TMA blocks described above. </p>

<p>Univariate analysis. Each of the 39 biomarkers were tested for 
their ability to predict disease aggressiveness (surgical GS X3 þ 4 </p>

<p>Table 2. Sampling variation reduces the performance of an established lethal outcome-predictive biomarker signature </p>

<p>Markers: PTEN, SMAD4, CCND1, SPP1 
Mean AIC 
(2.5%, 97.5%) </p>

<p>Median train AUC 
(2.5%, 97.5%) </p>

<p>Median test AUC 
(2.5%, 97.5%) </p>

<p>H TMA lethal 
282.2 (275.9, 293.2) 
0.67 (0.64, 0.70) 
0.65 (0.59, 0.74) </p>

<p>L TMA lethal 
301.3 (288.6, 316.8) 
0.6 (0.58, 0.63) 
0.49 (0.42, 0.58) </p>

<p>H TMA aggressiveness 
350.1 (330.4, 367.4) 
0.62 (0.56, 0.68) 
0.56 (0.44, 0.64) </p>

<p>L TMA aggressiveness 
381.6 (353.0, 400.7) 
0.61 (0.55, 0.68) 
0.56 (0.46, 0.65) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: AIC ¼ Akaike information criterion; ROC ¼ receiver-operating characteristic curve; TMA ¼ tissue microarray. The combination PTEN þ SMAD4 þ CCND1 þ SPP1 has previously 
been shown to be prognostic for lethal outcome when measured on prostatectomy tissue. We confirmed that these markers are indeed predictive of lethal outcome when measured in the 
high-Gleason biopsy simulation tissue (H TMA). However, these markers are unable to predict lethality in the low-Gleason simulation biopsy (L TMA). The markers do not show statistically 
significant predictive performance for aggressive disease regardless of whether they were measured in high-(H TMA) or low (L TMA)-Gleason tissue areas. C statistic, area under ROC curve. </p>

<p>Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>
or pathological stage pT3b, and/or N þ or M þ ) and death from 
disease (survival analysis) when measured in either low-or high-
Gleason areas (Figure 3). Markers shown in red text demonstrated 
predictive value (Po0.1) for aggressive disease or death from 
prostate cancer based on either an increased or decreased 
expression in both low-and high-Gleason areas. This result 
suggests that these markers are resistant to varying degrees of 
sampling error. There were two markers that were predictive of 
aggressiveness and three markers of lethal outcome when 
measured in high, but not in low-Gleason areas, indicating that 
these markers are not robust to sampling error. Conversely, no 
markers were identified that had predictive performance only in 
low, but not in high-Gleason areas. Interestingly, out of the 14 
markers with significant univariate performance for aggressiveness, 
12 markers also exhibited significant univariate performance for 
lethal outcome, consistent with a strong correlation between 
aggressive disease and lethal outcome. Our performance-based </p>

<p>biomarker selection approach also confirmed correlation between 
lethal outcome and expression of three known prostate cancer 
progression markers, EZH2, HoxB13, and MTDH2, as previously 
reported (Hu et al, 2009; Yang and Yu, 2013; Mills, 2014). </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis: biomarker combinations predicting 
tumour aggressiveness. To explore the best multivariate biomar-
ker combinations to predict disease aggressiveness, we exhaustively 
searched all possible models with combinations up to and 
including five biomarkers (Figure 4A). We focused on 31 
biomarkers, further refined from the original set of 39 based on 
technical criteria (see Materials and Methods). Initially, an 
'extreme' model approach was used for the multivariate analysis, 
which included removal of 'intermediate' samples (GS ¼ 3 þ 4, 
pT3a and N0) for the model building and testing. We separated 
patient cores in the L TMA into independent training and test sets, 
and tested the resulting models on both L and H TMAs for </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>FUS 
PDSS2 
DERL1 </p>

<p>FAK1 </p>

<p>MTDH2 </p>

<p>PXN </p>

<p>YBX1 
LMO7 
DEC1 
pS6 
StAR 
FKBP5 
CD75 
PTEN 
SMAD4 
ACTN1 </p>

<p>HSPA9 
MAOA 
PLAG1 
EZH2 
DIABLO 
HOXB13 
AGK 
SMAD2 
GRIP1 
VDAC1 </p>

<p>NCOA2 
HSD17B4 
LATS2 
MAP3K5 
pPRAS40 
CUL2 </p>

<p>CCND1 
SPP1 
AKAP8 
CDKN1B </p>

<p>Biomarkers </p>

<p>COX6C 
EIF3H </p>

<p>AGPAT6 </p>

<p>FUS 
PDSS2 
DERL1 </p>

<p>FAK1 </p>

<p>MTDH2 </p>

<p>PXN </p>

<p>YBX1 
LMO7 
DEC1 
pS6 
StAR 
FKBP5 
CD75 
PTEN 
SMAD4 
ACTN1 </p>

<p>HSPA9 
MAOA 
PLAG1 
EZH2 
DIABLO 
HOXB13 
AGK 
SMAD2 
GRIP1 
VDAC1 </p>

<p>NCOA2 
HSD17B4 
LATS2 
MAP3K5 
pPRAS40 
CUL2 </p>

<p>CCND1 
SPP1 
AKAP8 
CDKN1B 
COX6C 
EIF3H </p>

<p>AGPAT6 </p>

<p>Odds ratio 
(per 1 s.d. change in biomarkers) </p>

<p>0.25 0.50 0.75 1.00 1.25 1.50 1.75 2.00 
Hazard ratio 
(per 1 s.d. change in biomarkers) </p>

<p>0.25 0.50 0.75 1.00 1.25 1.50 1.75 2.00 </p>

<p>L TMA 
H TMA </p>

<p>Biomarkers </p>

<p>Figure 3. Univariate performance of 39 biomarkers measured in both low-(L TMA; black bars) and high-(H TMA; brown bars) Gleason areas for 
disease aggressiveness and disease-specific mortality. (A) The odds ratio (OR) for predicting severe disease pathology (aggressiveness) was 
calculated for each marker. Markers with an OR to the left of the vertical line are negatively correlated with the severity of the disease as assessed 
by pathology. Those to the right of the line are positively correlated. The markers were ranked based on OR when measured in L TMA. (B) The 
hazard ratio for death from disease (lethality) was calculated for each marker and plotted as described for A. Biomarkers in red indicate statistical 
significance at the 0.1 level in both L and H TMAs. Biomarkers in blue indicate statistical significance in only H TMA, but not L TMA. Note the large 
overlap of biomarkers with statistically significant univariate performance for both aggressive disease and death from disease. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>multivariate performance across sampling variation. For this 
purpose, we used logistic regression models to estimate biomarker 
coefficients using the training data set, estimated AUC from the 
resulting ROC in the testing set, and then repeated the process for 
another sampling. 
In each case, the most frequently occurring biomarkers in 
the top 5 or 1% of the models, sorted by AIC (Akaike information 
criterion) (Lindsey and Jones, 1998) and test-set AUC, 
were determined. A final tally was generated encompassing 
ranking by test, ranking by AIC, and by both test and AIC 
(see Figure 4B for a representative example of a five-biomarker 
model ranked by AIC and test). Intriguingly, we observed a high 
degree of conservation of biomarker order in the top-performing 
biomarker models (see Figure 4C; Supplementary Table S2). The 
following biomarkers appeared among the top markers in at least 
50% of the ranked lists: ACTN1, FUS, SMAD2, DERL1, YBX1, </p>

<p>DEC1, pS6, HSPA9, HOXB13, PDSS2, SMAD4, and CD75. 
In addition, CUL2 was present in a number of highly ranked 
models (see Supplementary Table S2 for further details of the 
ranking results). </p>

<p>Multivariate analysis: biomarkers predicting lethal outcome. A 
similar modelling analysis to that applied to predict aggressiveness 
was performed for lethal outcome (Supplementary Table S3). 
Biomarkers appearing among top markers in at least 50% of the 
ranked lists included: MTDH2, ACTN1, COX6C, YBX1, SMAD2, 
DERL1, CD75, FUS, LMO7, PDSS2, FAK1, SMAD4, and DEC1 (see 
Supplementary Table S3 for further details of the ranking results). </p>

<p>Final biomarker set predictive of prostate cancer aggressiveness 
and lethality. We chose a final set of 12 biomarkers based on 
careful integration of univariate and multivariate performance, and 
analytical considerations, including minimally a three-fold </p>

<p>Selection of 39 markers out of 160 based on technical considerations </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>39 Markers further reduced to 31 based on exploratory analyses </p>

<p>Unbiased train/test of all combinations of up to 5 markers </p>

<p>Sort combinations by train AUC, AIC and test AUC </p>

<p>Determine marker utilisation frequency in top 1% and top 5% of sorted combinations </p>

<p>Ranking 
(L TMA) </p>

<p>Marker utilisation frequency (%) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
ACTN1 
FUS 
SMAD2 
CUL2 
DIABLO 
HSPA9 
PLAG1 
DERL1 
PDSS2 
AKAP8 
VDAC1 
HOXB13 
CD75 
LATS2 
HSD17B4 
DEC1 
LMO7 
YBX1 
MTDH2 
CDKN1B 
PXN 
SMAD4 
EIF3H 
CCND1 
COX6C 
pS6 
FKBP5 
pPRAS40 
MAOA 
MAP3K5 
FAK1 </p>

<p>AIC 
ACTN1, CUL2, DERL1, 
SMAD2, YBX1 </p>

<p>112.33 
(86.22, 135.58) </p>

<p>124.95 
(98.61, 150.52) </p>

<p>0.873 
(0.756, 0.954) </p>

<p>0.892 
(0.796, 0.956) </p>

<p>0.813 
(0.596, 0.958) </p>

<p>0.856 
(0.676, 0.965) </p>

<p>0.762 
(0.582, 0.905) </p>

<p>0.798 
(0.649, 0.912) </p>

<p>ACTN1, FUS, PLAG1, 
SMAD2, SMAD4 </p>

<p>Test </p>

<p>Markers </p>

<p>Biomarker </p>

<p>AIC median 
(2.5%, 97.5%) 
(L TMA) </p>

<p>Train median AUC 
(2.5%, 97.5%) 
(L TMA) </p>

<p>Test median AUC 
(2.5%, 97.5%) 
(L TMA) </p>

<p>Test median AUC 
(2.5%, 97.5%) 
(H TMA) </p>

<p>Figure 4. Performance-based biomarker selection process for disease aggressiveness. (A) The bioinformatics workflow selected the most 
frequently utilised biomarkers from all combinations of up to five markers from a set of 31. (B) Example of performance of top-ranked five-marker 
models, including comparison with training on L TMA and then testing on independent samples from L TMA and H TMA. Note that the test 
performances on L TMA and H TMA are consistent, with substantial overlap in confidence intervals. (C) Combinations were generated allowing a 
maximum of three, four, or five biomarkers. The figure shows the proteins most frequently included when five-biomarker models were used to 
predict aggressive disease, ranked by test. </p>

<p>Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>
dynamic signal intensity range across tumour samples for all 
antibodies. Figure 5A shows the estimated odds ratios (ORs) 
associated with these 12 biomarkers for univariate prediction of 
aggressiveness, and Figure 5B provides a biological summary of the 
selected biomarkers. The final biomarker set was comprised of: 
FUS, PDSS2, DERL1, HSPA9, PLAG1, SMAD2, VDAC1, CUL2, 
YXB1, pS6, SMAD4, and ACTN1. 
Each of the 12 marker antibodies was rigorously validated by 
specificity analyses including western blotting and an </p>

<p>immunohistochemistry assay before and after target-specific 
knockdown, as shown in Supplementary Figure S1. 
Finally, we assessed the predictive potential of the final 12-
biomarker set for both disease aggressiveness and disease-specific 
death on the entire patient cohort through logistic regression 
analyses as described (see Materials and Methods). As shown in 
Figure 5C, this resulted in an L TMA test AUC of 0.72 (95% CI: 
0.64-0.79) and a corresponding OR for aggressive disease of 20 per 
unit change in risk score (95% CI: 4.3-257). To confirm the ability </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Odds ratio </p>

<p>FUS 
PDSS2 
DERL1 
HSPA9 
PLAG1 
SMAD2 
VDAC1 
CUL2 
YBX1 </p>

<p>Biomarker </p>

<p>pS6 
SMAD4 
ACTN1 </p>

<p>FUS </p>

<p>Biomarker 
Univariate 
agressiveness </p>

<p>Univariate 
lethality </p>

<p>Multivariate 
aggresiveness </p>

<p>Multivariate 
lethality </p>

<p>PDSS2 
DERL1 
HSPA9 
PLAG1 
SMAD2 
VDAC1 
CUL2 
YBX1 
pS6 
SMAD4 
ACTN1 </p>

<p>× 
× 
× 
-
-
-
-
-
× 
× 
× 
× </p>

<p>× 
× 
× 
× 
× 
× 
-
-
× 
× 
× 
× </p>

<p>× 
× 
× 
× 
× 
× 
× 
× 
× 
-
-
× </p>

<p>× 
× 
× 
-
× 
-
-
× 
-
-
× 
× 
0.25 0.50 0.75 1.00 1.25 1.50 1.75 2.00 </p>

<p>Marker 
abbreviation </p>

<p>Full name 
Biological significance </p>

<p>ACTN1 </p>

<p>CUL2 </p>

<p>DERL1 </p>

<p>FUS </p>

<p>HSPA9 
(Mortalin) </p>

<p>PDSS2 </p>

<p>PLAG1 </p>

<p>pS6 </p>

<p>SMAD2 </p>

<p>SMAD4 </p>

<p>VDAC1 </p>

<p>YBX1 </p>

<p>Actinin, Alpha 1 </p>

<p>Cullin 2 </p>

<p>Derlin 1 </p>

<p>Fused in sarcoma </p>

<p>Heat Shock 70 kDa protein 9 
(Mortalin) </p>

<p>Prenyl (Decaprenyl) diphosphate 
synthase, subunit 2 </p>

<p>Pleiomorphic adenoma gene 1 </p>

<p>Phospho-S6 ribosomal protein </p>

<p>SMAD family member 2 </p>

<p>SMAD family member 4 </p>

<p>Voltage-dependent anion channel 1 </p>

<p>Y Box-binding protein 1 </p>

<p>A bundling protein that anchors actin to a variety of intracellular structures </p>

<p>A component of E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase complex involved in ubiquitination of 
target proteins </p>

<p>A protein involved in endoplasmic reticulum degradation of misfolded 
lumen proteins </p>

<p>A component of the heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein complex involved in 
pre-mRNA splicing and the export of fully processed RNA into the cytoplasm </p>

<p>A member of the heat shock protein 70 family involved in cell proliferation, stress 
response and the maintenance of the mitochondria </p>

<p>An enzyme that synthesizes the prenyl side-chain of coenzyme Q, a key element in 
the respiratory chain </p>

<p>A transcription factor involved in cell proliferation and transformaiton </p>

<p>A component of the 40S ribosome subunit involved in protein synthesis. Its 
phosphorylation reflects the PI3K and core MAPK pathway signaling activity </p>

<p>A component of the transforming growth factor-β signaling pathway involved in the 
regulation of cell proliferation, apoptosis and differentiation </p>

<p>A component of the transforming growth factor-β signaling pathway involved in the 
regulation of cell proliferation, apoptosis and differentiation </p>

<p>A voltage-dependent anion channel protein in the outer membrane of the mitochondria </p>

<p>A cytoplasmic mRNA-binding protein involved in pre-mRNA alternative splicing </p>

<p>Test L TMA </p>

<p>0.72 (0.64-0.79) </p>

<p>20 (4.3-257) </p>

<p>0.72 (0.60-0.83) </p>

<p>66 (5.1-6756) </p>

<p>0.7 (0.62-0.77) </p>

<p>21 (4.7-179) </p>

<p>0.71 (0.61-0.81) </p>

<p>36 (3.3-2889) </p>

<p>AUC aggressiveness (95% CI) </p>

<p>OR aggressiveness (95% CI) </p>

<p>AUC lethal outcome (95% CI) </p>

<p>HR lethal outcome (95% CI) </p>

<p>Test H TMA </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 5. Final biomarker set and selection criteria. (A) Twelve biomarkers were selected based on univariate performance for aggressiveness 
(shown as OR on left) and lethality as well as frequency of appearance in multivariate models for disease aggressiveness or lethal outcome 
(table on right) (B) The biomarker set comprises proteins known to function in the regulation of cell proliferation, cell survival, and metabolism. 
(C) A multivariate 12-marker model for disease aggressiveness was developed based on logistic regression. The resulting AUC and OR are shown. 
Subsequently, the risk scores generated by the aggressiveness model for all patients were correlated with lethal outcome. The resulting AUC and 
HR are shown. </p>

<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>to generalise across sampling error, the model derived from the L 
TMA-training set was also tested on H TMA for prediction of 
aggressive disease with consistent results (Figure 5C). Without any 
further changes to the aggressiveness model, we examined its 
performance on lethal outcome prediction by correlating the 
aggressiveness risk scores with death from disease. Of note, we 
found a similar AUC for lethal outcome as for aggressiveness on 
both L and H TMA of 0.72 (95% CI: 0.60-0.83) and 0.71 (95% CI: 
0.61-0.81), respectively. The corresponding HRs for lethal outcome 
on L and H TMAs were 66 per unit change (95% CI: 5.1-6756) and 
36 (95% CI: 3.3-2889), respectively. We conclude that the 12 
identified biomarkers are robust to sampling error and predictive 
of both disease aggressiveness and lethal outcome. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>There is a continuing clinical need to assess prostate cancer 
aggressiveness more accurately at the time of initial diagnosis as well 
as for follow-up of patients, both those under active patient 
surveillance and those receiving active treatment (Bangma and  Roobol, 2012; Carter et al, 2012; Brimo et al, 2013). Currently, in 
men with early disease, a biopsy GS of 3 þ 4 ¼ 7 or more is one of the 
prognostic determinants for active treatment (NCCN, 2012a;  Heidenreich et al, 2014). However, biopsy-sampling error resulting 
from tumour heterogeneity and discordant Gleason scoring can 
significantly affect the accuracy and reliability of assessing a patient's 
risk of cancer progression, aggressiveness, and lethality. This 
uncertainty in prognostication has contributed to significant over-
treatment of patients with biopsies of Gleason grade 3 þ 3 or 3 þ 4 
(Boorjian et al, 2009; Cooperberg et al, 2010; Bangma and Roobol,  2012; Epstein et al, 2012; Sandhu and Andriole, 2012; Loeb et al, 2014). </p>

<p>Biomarkers predictive of prostate cancer aggressiveness and 
lethality. In this manuscript, we describe the successful develop-
ment of a performance-based strategy to identify and evaluate 
biomarkers predictive of prostate cancer aggressiveness and lethal 
outcome, even under circumstances of extreme sampling variation, 
an issue typically encountered during prostate biopsy taking. Using 
a large cohort (N ¼ 380) of annotated clinical prostatectomy 
samples with long-term follow-up, the areas of highest and lowest 
GS on each prostatectomy tissue were cored to generate paired 
TMAs (H and L TMAs) representing the entire cohort, thereby 
simulating biopsies with sampling error for each patient. Using 
these paired TMAs, we evaluated a large number of biomarker 
candidates for the ability to predict aggressive prostate pathology 
and lethal outcome when measured in either low-or high-grade 
cancer regions from each patient. We first selected biomarkers with 
performance against aggressiveness and lethal outcome when 
measured in L TMA tissue, to identify those most robust to 
extreme sampling error. For this purpose, we only included L TMA 
samples with core Gleason p3 þ 4 as clinically relevant, as biopsies 
with GS 4 þ 3 or higher inevitably will be aggressive therapy 
candidates. Most of the identified biomarkers from univariate 
analyses were predictive of both disease aggressiveness and prostate 
cancer-specific mortality regardless of whether they were measured 
in L or H TMA tissue samples, and hence robust to sampling 
variation (Figure 3). Moreover, performance of some well-
established prostate cancer biomarkers predictive of progression 
risk and lethal outcome (SMAD4, EZH2, MTDH2, HoxB13, and 
PTEN) corroborated the validity of the approach. 
As part of specificity validation of our antibodies, we learned 
through target knockdown analyses and mass spectrometry-based 
protein sequencing analysis that a MAb sold as anti-DCC actually 
recognised the unrelated protein HSPA9, or Mortalin. We found 
that HSPA9 was predictive as part of multivariate models and 
hence was included in the final 12-marker set. Our functional </p>

<p>analyses revealed the involvement of HSPA9 in clonogenic colony 
formation and cell proliferation, consistent with previously 
reported data (see Supplementary Figure 2 and Flachbartova  and Kovacech, 2013). This further validates our unbiased, 
performance-based marker selection approach. 
On the basis of univariate performance as well as frequency of 
marker appearance in multivariate models for disease aggressive-
ness and lethal outcome, 12 biomarkers were selected (Figure 5A). 
A multivariate model based on these 12 markers showed similar 
predictive performance for aggressiveness across tissue-sampling 
variation (Figure 5C). Interestingly, the risk scores generated based 
on the 12-marker aggressiveness model were equally predictive for 
the separate end point of lethal outcome across tissue-sampling 
variation (Figure 5C). This indicates a clear linkage between 
aggressive features on surgical pathology and lethality, and, 
importantly, validates the usage of our pathologic end point for 
building our biomarker panel as relevant for long-term patient 
outcome. We conclude that the 12 identified biomarkers are 
relevant for prediction of tumour behaviour and could serve as the 
starting point for development of a clinical, evidence-based 
multivariate biopsy test for evaluating prostate cancer aggressive-
ness as a critical aid in early decision-making steps in patient 
management (NCCN, 2012a; NCCN, 2012b). </p>

<p>Biomarkers robust to sampling error. A key objective for our 
study was to identify and select markers that are highly robust to 
sampling error. One of the key reasons for biopsy-sampling error is 
the heterogeneity of prostate cancer. The inability to consistently 
acquire tissue from the most aggressive parts of the tumour leads to 
frequent underestimation of tumour aggressiveness and progres-
sion risk. By coring into the highest and lowest Gleason area from 
each patient, we generated paired TMAs of the entire cohort study 
designed to simulate two biopsies from each patient, one with 
'maximal' sampling error (L TMA), and the other with minimal 
sampling error (H TMA). We focused on L TMAs with core 
Gleason p3 þ 4, as these represent the clinically relevant cases 
where standard of care is insufficient for accurate prognosis. We 
found that B54% of these L TMA cases were upgraded to a higher 
surgical GS, which is higher than observed in clinical practice 
(Porten et al, 2011), confirming that our approach provided a 
biased sampling error model. 
The need for identification of biomarkers that are resistant to 
sampling error was underscored by examining a well-established 
four-marker signature based on Cyclin D1, SMAD4, PTEN, and 
SPP1 previously reported to be predictive of lethal outcome based 
on prostatectomy cohorts (Ding et al, 2011). Although we 
confirmed that the model was predictive for lethal outcome in H 
TMA, representing a situation of minimal sampling error, the 
model was not lethal outcome-predictive at all in our L TMA tissue 
cores, representing maximal sampling error (Table 2). This finding 
is consistent with a recent report that the four-marker signature is 
unable to predict lethal outcome in low-GS prostate tumours 
(Irshad et al, 2013). 
On the basis of univariate marker analyses, we identified 14 and 
18 markers with sampling error-robust performance across L and 
H TMA samples for disease aggressiveness and lethal outcome, 
respectively (markers with red font in Figure 4). Most of these 
univariately selected markers were predictive of both indications 
across sampling variation, supporting a correlation between disease 
aggressiveness and lethal outcome. Interestingly, although all 
markers that showed univariate performance for both indications 
on L TMA also were predictive on H TMA, two markers (PXN and 
MTDH2) and three markers (NCOA2, CCND1 (Cyclin D1), and 
AKAP8) (Sattler et al, 2000; Xu and Li, 2003; Hu et al, 2009; Ding  et al, 2011; Canton and Scott, 2013) were predictive of aggressive 
disease and lethal outcome, respectively, only when measured on H 
TMA, but not on L TMA (Figure 3). This suggests that these </p>

<p>Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

<p>
markers are predictive primarily in situations of minimal sampling 
error. Indeed, all these five markers have been shown as important 
regulators of cellular proliferation, migration, and oncogenesis (see 
e.g., Sattler et al, 2000; Xu and Li, 2003; Hu et al, 2009; Ding et al,  2011; Canton and Scott, 2013). The observation that Cyclin D1 is 
predictive of lethal outcome only in H TMA, but not L TMA, is 
consistent with the finding that the four-marker signature reported 
by Ding et al (2011) was not predictive of lethal outcome in our L 
TMA tissue, as well as on low-grade prostate cancer samples 
(Irshad et al, 2013). The fact that no markers were predictive for 
aggressive disease or lethal outcome on only L TMA, but not H 
TMA, is interesting given that we primarily selected for markers 
that can predict either aggressiveness or lethal outcome in L TMA, 
to reflect maximal sampling error robustness. This suggests that 
the identified markers likely reflect field effects from more 
aggressive tumour regions, consistent with their similar perfor-
mance in L and H TMA tissue samples. </p>

<p>Genetic and proteomic approaches. An extensive search to find 
better prostate cancer biomarkers has led to the identification of 
possible genetic markers for clinical risk prognostication (Lapointe  et al, 2004; Lapointe et al, 2007; Tomlins et al, 2007; Cheville et al,  2008; Cuzick et al, 2011; Scher et al, 2013). However, there are 
conflicting results regarding the reliability of many such markers in 
disease prognosis. For example, although TMPRSS2-ERG gene 
fusions are reported to be associated with high-risk tumours, more 
recent studies with large cohorts report no strong correlation 
between these fusions and patient outcome (Gopalan et al, 2009). 
A multivariate gene expression-based test has recently been 
reported to predict metastatic disease and lethal outcome based 
on a conservatively managed cohort of patients from the United 
Kingdom (Cuzick et al, 2012), as well as biochemical recurrence 
after treatment in actively managed cohorts in the United States 
(Cooperberg et al, 2013; Bishoff et al, 2014). The influence of 
sampling variation on this test has yet to be determined. 
The results of this study suggest that taking a proteomic 
approach, which measures proteins from only the tumour region of 
intact tissue, can possibly improve accurate risk classification at the 
biopsy stage. The rationale for this idea is two-fold. First, because 
prostate cancer is a heterogeneous, multifocal disease, biopsies 
frequently contain only lower-grade components, and pathologists 
may classify them as low-risk cancers. However, higher-grade 
molecular features, not reflected morphologically, have been 
reported to extend throughout the cancer (Boyd et al, 2012;  Sowalsky et al, 2013), and therefore are measurable in seemingly 
lower-grade-containing biopsies. It is possible to accurately and 
sensitively assess such high-grade molecular features in situ from 
tumour regions using a proteomic approach, even in tissue samples 
with variable amounts of tumour and benign components. This is 
an advantage over gene expression-based technologies requiring 
tissue homogenisation, resulting in variable dilution of the higher-
grade molecular features depending on the amount of intermixed 
benign tissue. Second, Gleason grading on biopsy is subjective, 
with expert pathologists disagreeing on up to 30% of cases 
(McKenney et al, 2011; Goodman et al, 2012). Molecular features 
that can be objectively measured should improve risk classification. </p>

<p>Limitations to the study. The fact that the biomarkers were 
analysed in multiple ways for univariate and multivariate 
performance on a single, large cohort increases the potential risk 
that the results are over-fitted to patients included in this study. 
Also, we simulated prostate cancer biopsies by taking 1-mm 
diameter cores from prostate tissue blocks to generate TMA blocks. 
Protein measurements made from cross-sections of these cores 
may perform differently if measured in 20 Â 1-mm biopsy sections, 
as typically encountered in routine pathology practice. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>There is an urgent need for a reliable and accurate prognostic test 
for patients with prostate cancer, given the difficulties of predicting 
survival outcomes for patients diagnosed with early-stage cancer 
and the resulting overtreatment. Further investigation of the 12 
biomarkers identified in this study will enable development of an 
objective clinical biopsy test based on multiplex proteomics in situ 
imaging. The next step is to identify the optimal biomarker 
subset algorithm from these 12 biomarkers, and to validate this in a 
large clinical cohort of Gleason-and TNM-annotated biopsy 
samples with matched prostatectomy and pathological specimens. 
These studies are currently under way. 
We propose that the identification strategy for protein 
biomarkers described herein is likely to be applicable to other 
tumour types, and may serve as a model for performance-based 
selection of biomarkers that can be used to develop prognostic or 
predictive tests for other tumours where histological assessment is 
pivotal to risk stratification and prognostication. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to thank Drs Raju Kucherlapati, Ronald DePinho, 
Lynda Chin, Philip Kantoff, and collaborators at Metamark for 
insightful comments and suggestions. We thank Rowena Hughes 
and Winnie McFadzean from Oxford PharmaGenesis Ltd for 
editorial support in collating comments from authors and 
finalisation of the manuscript for submission. Research support: 
this project was funded by Metamark Genetics Inc. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>DLR is a paid consultant and equity holder in Metamark. DMB 
and ML are paid consultants to Metamark. All other authors are 
paid employees of Metamark. </p>



<p>BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>



<p>Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error 
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER </p>

<p>www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>



<p>
BRITISH JOURNAL OF CANCER 
Prostate cancer biomarkers robust to sampling error </p>

<p> 
www.bjcancer.com | DOI:10.1038/bjc.2014.396 </p>

</text></tei>