<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4809623" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cytoplasmic citrate serves as an important regulator of gluconeogenesis and carbon source for de novo lipogenesis in the 
liver. For this reason, the sodium-coupled citrate transporter (NaCT), a plasma membrane transporter that governs hepatic 
influx of plasma citrate in human, is being explored as a potential therapeutic target for metabolic disorders. As cytoplasmic 
citrate also originates from intracellular mitochondria, the relative contribution of these two pathways represents critical 
information necessary to underwrite confidence in this target. In this work, hepatic influx of plasma citrate was quantified via 
pharmacokinetic modeling of published clinical data. The influx was then compared to independent literature estimates of 
intracellular citrate flux in human liver. The results indicate that, under normal conditions, &lt;10% of hepatic citrate originates 
from plasma. Similar estimates were determined experimentally in mice and rats. This suggests that NaCT inhibition will have 
a limited impact on hepatic citrate concentrations across species. 
WHAT IS THE CURRENT KNOWLEDGE ON THE TOPIC? þ NaCT has been proposed as a therapeutic target for obe-
sity and diabetes. However, no study identified the relative contribution of plasma citrate to hepatic citrate. • WHAT 
QUESTIONS DID THIS STUDY ADDRESS? þ What is the hepatic influx of plasma citrate in humans? What is the rela-
tive contribution of plasma citrate to hepatic citrate in humans, mice, and rats? Is plasma citrate a reasonable biomarker 
for NaCT inhibition? • WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS TO OUR KNOWLEDGE þ Under normal conditions, &lt;10% of hepatic 
citrate originates from plasma in humans, mice, and rats. Liver is the major organ that clears citrate from plasma in 
humans. Plasma citrate could serve as a biomarker for NaCT inhibition in humans. • HOW THIS MIGHT CHANGE CLIN-
ICAL PHARMACOLOGY AND THERAPEUTICS þ Future studies should determine the effect of NaCT inhibition on 
hepatic citrate (preferably cytoplasmic citrate) concentrations, and their quantitative relationship to efficacy endpoints 
(e.g., glucose and lipid lowering) as means of evaluating confidence in rationale prior to efficacy-based trials. </p>

<p>The sodium-coupled citrate transporter (NaCT) has been 
proposed as a therapeutic target for obesity and diabetes. </p>

<p>then compared to intracellular citrate flux in the liver 
reported in the literature. The modeling results suggest 
that, in humans, although hepatic influx largely determines 
the rate of citrate clearance from the plasma (i.e., 85%), 
the rate is small relative to the intracellular flux occurring 
from the mitochondria as a consequence of the TCA cycle. 
In order to more directly understand how much plasma 
citrate contributes to liver citrate levels, preclinical hepatic 
citrate enrichment studies were conducted in mice and rats. 
One study using mice infused with </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C-citrate showed 25% 
13 C-citrate enrichment in plasma at steady state, yet only 
0.7% </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C-citrate enrichment was found in the liver. Another 
study using fasting rats treated with 
14 C-citrate demon-
strated that fewer </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C radiolabels were incorporated into lip-
ids extracted from liver than those from kidney or testes. 
Given that liver is the major organ synthesizing lipids, and 
lipogenesis occurs in the cytoplasm, the findings suggest 
that flux of citrate from plasma to the liver contributes mini-
mally to the bulk production of lipids in the liver of fasting 
rats. 
Overall, these results suggest that NaCT inhibition will 
marginally affect hepatic citrate concentrations and there-
fore cast uncertainty on the rationale supporting their devel-
opment to treat metabolic disorders and translation of the 
observed metabolic benefits in rodents to humans. As 
such, future studies should explicitly determine the effect of 
such inhibitors on hepatic citrate (preferably cytoplasmic 
citrate) concentrations, efficacy endpoints (e.g., glucose 
and lipid lowering), and flux analysis as a means of evaluat-
ing confidence in rationale prior to efficacy-based trials. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Literature search results 
Five articles that describe the clinical PK of citrate in 
healthy subjects were identified and used in this analy-
sis. 
11-15 The means of longitudinal plasma citrate measure-
ments, corresponding study size (n), and standard </p>

<p>deviations (SD) were read from tables or digitized from fig-
ures (with <rs type="software">PlotDigitizer</rs>.exe) to use in this modeling. 
Five additional articles reporting intracellular citrate flux 
in the liver of healthy subjects were also identified and 
included in this study. 
16-20 The articles report in vivo intra-
cellular citrate flux as estimates determined via noninvasive 
technologies, such as in vivo nuclear magnetic resonance 
(NMR) combined with </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C-labeling technology, 
1 H, 
2 H, 
13 C 
magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS), or sampling glu-
tamine through urine phenylacetylglutamine (PAGN) and 
apolipoproteinB-100 (apoB-100). The reported mean values 
of hepatic citrate flux with SD as well as n were utilized in 
this analysis. </p>

<p>Model-based analysis of citrate PK in healthy humans 
Citrate PK profiles in healthy subjects following i.v. and p.o. 
doses of citrate were analyzed simultaneously using classic 
compartment models (Eqs. 1, 2) in NONMEM 7.2. NON-
MEM code and the data file are provided in Supporting 
Information I &amp; II. </p>

<p>d A 1 
ð Þ 
dt 
52k abs 3A 1 
(1) </p>

<p>d C p 
À Á </p>

<p>dt 
5 
CL elim 3C p 0 </p>

<p>ð Þ </p>

<p>V d 
1 
k abs 3A 1 
V d 
2 
CL elim 3C p 
V d 
(2) </p>

<p>To account for the difference of subject numbers and 
endpoint variance in each study, the model fitting was 
weighted using ͱn/SD. In the formula, n is the number of 
subjects and SD is the standard deviation from the litera-
ture. With this setting, more weight was given to studies 
with larger sample populations and smaller variance. This 
analysis provided information on citrate clearance (CL elim ), 
volume of distribution (V d ), baseline plasma citrate concen-
tration (C p(0) ), and bioavailability of oral citrate (F) in healthy 
subjects. 
Diagnostic plots of predicted vs. measured values were 
used to evaluate how well the models were able to fit 
the data. Furthermore, conditionally weighted residuals 
(CWRES) were plotted against predicted values and time 
to examine any potential bias of the model. A histogram of 
CWRES was used to evaluate if the errors are normally 
distributed. Simulated temporal and dose-response curves 
with observed data 6 SD were overlaid to evaluate model 
performance. 
Based on the calibrated parameters, the basal turnover of 
plasma citrate (TO citratet ) was calculated using Eq. 3: </p>

<p>TO citrate 5CL elim 3C p 0 </p>

<p>ð Þ </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>Hepatic clearance of citrate (CL h ) was calculated using 
Eq. 4, where Q h is hepatic blood flow and f p is the volume 
fraction of plasma in whole blood. Consistent with literature 
reports, the equation assumes a citrate absorption of 
97% 
15 and negligible metabolism in the lung and intestine. 
As citrate does not bind plasma proteins 
7 nor traverse the 
plasma membrane of red blood cells, 
21 it is concluded that 
citrate is only localized to plasma as unbound molecules. 
The value of Q h assumed in this calculation is 20 mL/min/ </p>

<p>Figure 1 Schematic depiction of the biological pathways that 
involve citrate and the role of NaCT in supplying citrate for 
hepatic biosynthesis. Plasma and mitochondrial citrate can be 
transported into hepatic cytoplasm by NaCT and another citrate 
transporter located on the mitochondrial membrane. Cytoplasmic 
citrate from both sources can inhibit PFK, activate F-1, 6-BP, and 
ACC, and/or be broken down to form acetyl-CoA, an important 
precursor in biosynthesis reactions. </p>

<p>Plasma Citrate Flux Into the Liver 
Li et al. </p>



<p>www.wileyonlinelibrary/psp4 </p>

<p>kg, 
22 and f p is 55%. F is the fractional oral bioavailability of 
citrate estimated using Eqs. 1 and 2: </p>

<p>CL h 5Q h 3f p 3 0:972F 
ð 
Þ 
(4) </p>

<p>The basal hepatic flux of citrate from plasma was calcu-
lated using Eq. 5: </p>

<p>Flux p!h 5CL h 3C p 0 
ð Þ 
(5) </p>

<p>Literature-based analysis of hepatic citrate flux 
in human 
Both fixed and random effect approaches were used to esti-
mate the weighted mean of hepatic citrate flux in humans 
using R 3.0.2 with meta-analysis library (<rs type="software">metafor</rs>). The data 
from the literature and R code are provided in Supporting 
Information III &amp; IV. The fixed effect approach assumed 
that the true mean was the same in all studies; as such, 
the flux from each study was weighted by sampling errors 
within the study only. In contrast, the random effect 
approach assumed that heterogeneity existed among the 
studies, and sampling errors of both within and between 
studies were used for weighting. Means and 95% confi-
dence intervals (CIs) of the estimated values, combined 
with individual reported values, were included in one forest 
plot for visualization. </p>

<p>Preclinical evaluation of the contribution of plasma 
citrate to hepatic citrate levels 
All procedures performed on animals minimized their suffer-
ing, complied with regulations and established guidelines, 
and were approved by a Pfizer Institutional Animal Care 
and Use Committee. </p>

<p>Mice 
13 C-citrate infusion study. Male B6/C57 DIO mice 
(n 5 8) from Jackson Laboratories (Bar Harbor, ME) arrived 
at 17 weeks of age following 12 weeks of high-fat diet 
(HFD, D12459i with 60% calories from fat). After an addi-
tional 3-week HFD acclimation period, the mice were 
implanted with a jugular vein cannula and allowed 4 days to 
recover. On day 4, all mice were fasted beginning at 5:00 PM. 
On day 5, after the overnight fast, mice were reconnected 
to jugular vein tubing in a disposable cage. U-[ </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C]-citrate 
was infused at 1.5 mmol/kg/hr for 5 minutes, followed by 
0.15 mmol/kg/hr for 115 minutes. Blood samples were col-
lected at 0, 5, 60, 90, and 120-minute timepoints (n 5 8 at 
each timepoint). All mice were euthanized at 120 minutes 
(n 5 8) and livers were immediately harvested. The percen-
tages of </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C-citrate enrichment were analyzed in both blood 
and liver samples using mass spectrum. </p>

<p>Incorporation of radioactivity of 
14 C-citrate into lipids using 
rats. Male Sprague-Dawley (SD) rats (n 5 8) at 8 weeks of 
age and fed a normal chow diet were used in this study. 
The rats were i.v. dosed with 0.4 mL of 50 mCi/mL 1, 5-
[ 
14 C]-citrate on the morning of the experimental day. Twenty 
minutes after the dosing, rats were sacrificed using a lethal 
dose of pentobarbital. Liver, kidney, and testes were har-
vested to analyze the amount of radioactivity per gram of 
tissue using Bligh and Dryer extraction. 
23 Plasma radioac-
tivity was quantified by measuring radioactivity in 10 mL of </p>

<p>plasma added to 5 mL of Optiphase Supermix on a stand-
ard scintillation counter. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Clearance and turnover of plasma citrate in healthy 
humans 
Human PK data were well described by the proposed model, 
yielding well-defined parameters (Table 1, Figure 2). Diag-
nostic plots revealed a good concordance between model 
predicted and observed plasma citrate concentrations. There 
was not any obvious trend of model residues vs. time, nor 
prediction. The distribution of residues appeared to be nor-
mal. Diagnostic plots are provided in Supporting Informa-
tion V. 
In healthy subjects, citrate clearance was estimated to be 
7.79 mL/min/kg with a 95% CI of [5.70-10.45]. The base-
line plasma citrate concentration was estimated to be 
0.13 mM with a 95% CI of [0.11-0.14]. Using Eq. 3, the 
turnover of plasma citrate in healthy subjects was deter-
mined to be 20 g/day. 
In healthy subjects, hepatic citrate clearance was calcu-
lated to be 6.60 mL/min/kg (Eq. 4), accounting for 85% of 
total citrate clearance. With sequential measurements of 
plasma citrate in healthy subjects following i.v. and p.o. 
doses of citrate, the fraction of bioavailability was calibrated 
to 0.37 with a 95% CI of [0.20-0.64]. Given the assumed 
fractional absorption of 97%, 
15 the oral, first-pass hepatic 
extraction of citrate is estimated to be 60% (with a 95% CI 
of [0.33-0.77]). 
Based on the hepatic clearance and plasma concentra-
tion of citrate, the hepatic influx of plasma citrate was cal-
culated maximally to be 17 g/day with a 95% CI of [9-20] 
(Eq. 5). </p>

<p>Local citrate production in the liver of healthy humans 
Analysis of reported hepatic citrate synthesis rates indi-
cates that the rate of endogenous citrate production greatly 
exceeds the rate of flux from the plasma citrate. Using the 
five literature reported hepatic citrate synthesis rates, the 
fixed effect estimate of the intracellular citrate flux in the 
liver of healthy subjects was 222 g/day with a 95% CI of 
[202-242]. When the heterogeneity of the studies was 
taken into consideration, the mixed effect estimate was 
approximated to 303 g/day with a 95% CI of [119-487] 
(Figure 3). These results suggest that plasma citrate con-
tributes no more than 10% of local citrate flux in the liver of 
healthy humans. </p>

<p>Table 1 Citrate pharmacokinetic parameter estimates derived from healthy 
subjects </p>

<p>Parameters 
Description 
Value 
95%CI 
Unit </p>

<p>C p (0) 
Baseline plasma citrate 
0.13 [0.11-0.14] 
mM </p>

<p>k abs 
Absorption rate 
0.02 [0.01-0.04] 
min </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>CL elim 
Elimination clearance 
7.79 [5.70-10.45] mL/min/kg </p>

<p>V d 
Central distribution volume 
259 
[242-281] 
mL/kg </p>

<p>F 
Fractional bioavailability 
0.37 [0.20-0.64] 
Unit-less </p>

<p>Plasma Citrate Flux Into the Liver 
Li et al. </p>



<p>CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology </p>

<p>13 C-citrate infusion study using mice 
Plasma citrate clearance in mice was determined to be 
50 ml/min/kg. At steady state, the plasma citrate concentra-
tion increased by approximately one-third over the endoge-
nous level (i.e., from 0.15 mM to 0.2 mM). Given the 
maintenance infusion rate of 0.15 mmol/kg/hour in this 
study, the mice had a plasma citrate clearance (50 ml/min/ 
kg) considerably higher than that in healthy humans 
(7.2 ml/min/kg). 
The plasma enrichment of 
13 C-citrate from the mice was 
plotted as a function of time in Figure 4a. At the end of the 
infusion, when the animals were sacrificed and tissue sam-
ples were analyzed, 25 6 1% of citrate measured in the 
plasma was associated with the 
13 C label (n 5 8). In com-
parison, only 0.7 6 0.3% of citrate measured in the liver 
was associated with the 
13 C label (n 5 8) (Figure 4b). </p>

<p>Incorporation of 
14 C-citrate into lipids using 
fasting rats 
Twenty minutes after dosing rats with 
14 C-labeled citrate, 
radioactivity of </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C was found to be the highest in the lipids 
extracted from kidney (2,072 6 643 dpm/mg tissue, n 5 8), 
followed by the testes (1,090 6 230 dpm/mg tissue, n 5 8). 
Lipids extracted from liver displayed the least radioactivity 
at 450 6 394 dpm/mg liver tissue (n 5 8) (Figure 5a). In the 
plasma, the radioactivity levels declined quickly, suggesting 
a short half-life of plasma citrate in rats (Figure 5b). At 20 
minutes after i.v. 
14 C-citrate infusion, the density of radioac-
tivity reduced to half of that observed at 10 minutes after 
dosing. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Citrate PK and hepatic flux in humans 
In this study, whole body plasma citrate clearance in 
healthy humans was estimated to be 7.79 mL/min/kg, with 
a baseline citrate concentration of 0.13 mM. These two 
parameters combine to give a citrate turnover rate of 20 g/ 
day, which is consistent with independent literature reports </p>

<p>Figure 3 Forest plot of hepatic citrate flux in healthy humans. 
Intracellular citrate flux in the liver of healthy subjects from five 
articles were included in this analysis. Both fixed and random 
effect estimates with 95% CI are reported in the plot. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Fitting results of citrate PK profiles in healthy humans. Data were obtained from five independent studies, as labeled on the 
top of each panel. Citrate was i.v. infused at 0.5 mmol/kg/hr, 0.34 mmol/kg/hr, and 0.33 mmol/kg/hr for 120, 120, and 220 minutes as 
described in Kramer et al., 2003, 
11 Apsner et al., 1997, 
12 and Bauer et al., 2005, 
13 respectively. Citrate was p.o. dosed at 0.26 mmol/ 
kg and 0.19 mmol/kg as in Rudman et al., 1980 
14 and Fegan et al., 1992, 
15 respectively. </p>

<p>Plasma Citrate Flux Into the Liver 
Li et al. </p>



<p>www.wileyonlinelibrary/psp4 </p>

<p>of 10 g/day determined by Nielsen. 
7 As 1 g of citric acid 
contains 2.5 calories, 
24 a turnover of 20 g/day of citrate cor-
responds to 50 calories daily, indicating a limited calorie 
exclusion resulting from a complete inhibition of plasma 
citrate utilization. The citrate intake from a typical diet is 
less than 10 g per day. 
7,25 As such, a significant amount of 
the citrate found in plasma is provided via endogenous pro-
duction. The tissues that are known to release citrate 
include muscle, bone, and prostate. </p>

<p>7,26 </p>

<p>Hepatic citrate clearance was found to be 6.6 mL/min/kg, 
indicating that liver is the predominant organ that metabo-
lizes plasma citrate (i.e., 85% of total clearance). This 
aligns with prior knowledge that the liver is an important 
organ involved in citrate metabolism, 
27 and with the fact 
that plasma citrate clearance is substantially decreased in 
subjects with impaired liver function. 
11,12 A portion of the 
remaining 15% of plasma citrate clearance is likely due, at 
least in part, to the kidney. This is consistent with the 
understanding that the kidney also plays a role in citrate 
homeostasis. 
28-30 For example, in healthy humans the glo-
merular filtrate rate of citrate is 4 g per day, with 70-90% 
reabsorbed at the proximal tubule by active citrate trans-
porters (SLC13A2 and SLC13A3) and only 10-30% 
remaining in the urine. 
31 As a result, the urine excretion of 
citrate is 0.4-1.2 g/day (i.e., 2-6% of daily citrate turn-
over). 
32,33 However, depending on the metabolic capacity of </p>

<p>the kidney, the reabsorbed citrate may or may not circulate 
back into plasma. If citrate is renally metabolized, it could 
lead to a net elimination of up to 4 g of citrate daily (20% of 
daily citrate turnover). Consistent with the physiologic case 
for the relatively minor role of kidney in human citrate clear-
ance, the pharmacokinetics of citrate are unaffected by 
impairments in renal function. </p>

<p>13,15 </p>

<p>Assuming that NaCT is entirely responsible for the 
hepatic clearance of citrate, an inhibitor of NaCT is 
expected to significantly affect circulating citrate concentra-
tions. Simulations from the derived PK model indicate that 
the assumed level of inhibition will affect both the magni-
tude and time-course citrate elevations. Maximum steady-
state elevations are expected to be approximately seven-
fold, with a twofold increase at 87% NaCT inhibition Eq. 6, 
where fCL NaCT and fi NaCT are the fractional clearance 
through NaCT and fractional inhibition of NaCT, 
respectively): </p>

<p>Citrate inhibited 
Citrate basal 
5 
1 
12 fCL NaCT 3fi NaCT 
ð 
Þ 
(6) </p>

<p>In addition, the time to reach a new steady-state citrate con-
centration will increase with inhibition, since inhibition affects 
the half-life of citrate (e.g., baseline of 23 minutes 
3,7 and up to 
2.7 hours with complete NaCT inhibition, Figure 6a,b). As </p>

<p>Figure 4 Plasma and hepatic enrichment of </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C-citrate in mice i.v. infused with 
13 C-citrate. (a) Plasma citrate enrichment was illus-
trated as a time sequential profile (red). (b) In the liver, the enrichment was a timepoint measurement (blue) taken 120 minutes after 
the infusion, when steady state was reached. For all the measurements, both mean and SD values are shown on the plots. </p>

<p>Figure 5 The radioactivity density of lipids and plasma from rats with i.v. 
14 C-citrate bolus targeting 20 mCi/rat. (a) Radioactivity density 
of the lipids extracted from liver, kidney, and testes of SD rats at 20 minutes after dosing </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C-citrate. (b) Radioactivity density of the 
plasma at 10 and 20 minutes after the dosing of 
14 C-citrate. Error bars represent SD. </p>

<p>Plasma Citrate Flux Into the Liver 
Li et al. </p>



<p>CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology </p>

<p>such, elevations in plasma citrate are expected to represent an 
excellent biomarker of NaCT activity upon administration of an 
inhibitor, particularly when examined within the context of a PK 
model. However, such elevations in plasma citrate are expected 
to partially offset the effect of inhibition on flux and associated 
steady-state hepatic citrate concentrations. For example, 50% 
inhibition of NaCT is expected to decrease flux by only 13% and 
near maximal inhibition (i.e., 87%) is expected to decrease flux 
by only 50%: </p>

<p>flux inhibited 
flux basal 
5 
12fi NACT 
12 fCL NaCT 3fi NaCT 
ð 
Þ 
(7) </p>

<p>While these results suggest that NaCT inhibition will mar-
ginally affect hepatic citrate concentrations, an even greater 
limitation is indicated by the estimated basal intracellular 
flux of 200-300 g/day. This suggests that the plasma citrate 
influx pathway in which NaCT is involved (i.e., 17 g/day) is 
a relatively minor contributor (i.e., &lt;10%) to the overall flux 
of citrate within the liver. 
Of course, this assessment is indirect in that it involves 
two independent, complex, and unique approaches to esti-
mate the two flux pathways (e.g., pharmacokinetic analysis 
for extracellular flux and noninvasive imaging for the intra-
cellular flux). The pharmacokinetic analysis also involves 
certain assumptions (e.g., negligible gut and lung metabo-
lism), which, if invalid, would overestimate the hepatic 
citrate clearance. In addition, the accuracy of technologies 
used in the estimation of in vivo hepatic citrate flux (e.g., in 
vivo NMR combined with </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C-labeling technology, 
1 H, </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>H, 
13 C MRS, or sampling glutamine through urine PAGN and </p>

<p>apoB-100) are still under evaluation. These estimates of in 
vivo intracellular flux are also determined at the level of 
whole liver, with no distinction as to subcellular compart-
mentalization (e.g., cytoplasm vs. mitochondria) which, if 
available, might lead to a different assessment of the rela-
tive importance of the two pathways. In order to get a more 
direct estimate of the contribution of citrate flux from 
plasma to the net hepatic citrate concentration, preclinical 
studies were conducted whereby hepatic enrichment of 
labeled citrate could be assessed. </p>

<p>Citrate PK in mice and rats 
Using fasting mice, we were able to demonstrate that the 
hepatic influx of plasma citrate was very low compared to 
intracellular citrate pools within the liver. In our studies, 
hepatic </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C-citrate enrichment is only 2.8% of that 
observed in the plasma (i.e., 0.7% in liver vs. 25% in 
plasma) at steady state. Consistent with our conclusions for 
human, these results suggest that inhibition of plasma 
citrate flux would marginally affect hepatic citrate concentra-
tions in mice, as most hepatic citrate seemingly originates 
from the TCA cycle. Unfortunately, an orthogonal assess-
ment through inhibition of plasma citrate flux is precluded 
by the lack of selective inhibitors for the predominate 
hepatic citrate transporters expressed in mice (i.e., 
SLC13A2 and A3). Furthermore, since NaCT is a relatively 
minor citrate transporter in mice, the use of specific NaCT 
inhibitors in mice will likely underestimate the potential 
effects in humans. 
Using fasting rats, we demonstrated that the flux of 
plasma citrate also minimally contributes to liver citrate. </p>

<p>Figure 6 Simulation of plasma citrate and hepatic influx of plasma citrate in response to NaCT inhibition. (a) Time sequential profiles 
of plasma citrate in response to inhibition. (b) Time-dependence of plasma citrate elevations across a range of NaCT inhibition. (c) 
Time sequential profiles of hepatic influx of plasma citrate in response to inhibition. (d) Time-dependence of hepatic citrate influx 
across a range of NaCT inhibition. </p>

<p>Plasma Citrate Flux Into the Liver 
Li et al. </p>

<p>137 </p>

<p>www.wileyonlinelibrary/psp4 </p>

<p>The total lipids extracted from rat liver contained a lower 
density of </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C radioactivity than those from kidney and 
testes. It is known that liver is the major organ synthesizing 
total lipids in rats, and its contribution is 37%. 
34 In contrast, 
kidneys contribute only 0.7%, and testes 0.1%. 
34 After taking 
tissue weight into consideration, liver should still contribute 
about 10-fold more radioactivity than the kidney (3.7%/g liver 
vs. 0.38%/g kidney in rats). The old numbers were based on 
human liver and kidney weight (1470 and 308 g, respec-
tively). As we are discussing rat physiology, the numbers are 
now updated based on rat liver and kidney weight (10 and 
1.825 g, respectively). However, in this study the density of 
radioactivity in liver lipids is only 22% of that in kidney lipids. 
This finding again suggests that there is a large local pool of 
citrate in the liver that significantly dilutes the radioactivity 
from </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C-citrate. In addition, since lipid synthesis mainly 
occurs in the cytoplasm, it is highly likely that the influx of 
plasma citrate contributed minimally to the citrate level in the 
cytoplasm of rat hepatocytes. 
Here it is worth noting that the current study designs uti-
lized fasted rodents and that circadian rhythms in citrate 
homeostasis associated with feeding might provide slightly 
different results. For example, after meals, plasma citrate 
concentrations have been reported to increase about 20% 
compared to that in fasting humans. 
35 In addition, it has 
been reported that glucagon stimulates citrate uptake by 
upregulating NaCT expression in rats. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Hepatic cytoplasmic citric acid is an important biochemical 
precursor and physiological regulator that is associated 
with potential therapeutic implications. Understanding the 
kinetics of plasma citrate is generally useful in evaluating 
the potential effects of pharmacological perturbations in 
citrate flux. 
From this work, we conclude that the liver is the major 
organ of citrate clearance in humans. We also conclude 
that plasma citrate could serve as a potential biomarker for 
NaCT inhibition, but that elevations in plasma citrate will 
partially offset the desired effect of inhibition at the level of 
flux. In addition, both modeling results in humans and 
experimental data in rodents indicate that influx of plasma 
citrate contributes marginally (relative to intracellular flux 
via the TCA cycle) to hepatic citrate concentrations. The 
specific molecular mechanism behind the metabolic bene-
fits observed in NaCT knockout mice is unclear and further 
investigations are necessary to determine if the physiologi-
cal effects can be explained by their exquisite sensitivity to 
cytoplasmic citrate concentrations. As such, future develop-
ment of NaCT inhibitors should, at a minimum, focus on 
developing the quantitative relationship between NaCT 
function, cytoplasmic citrate concentrations, and down-
stream physiology (e.g., glycolysis, gluconeogenesis, and 
de novo lipogenesis). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments. We thank James Gosset, Gianluca Nucci, 
Fatema Abdurrob, Yimin Zhu, and Qingyun Yan for their advice and assis-
tance with these studies. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest. The authors declare no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Author Contributions. Z.L., T.S.M., and D.M.E. wrote the article; 
Z.L. and T.S.M. designed the research; Z.L. and D.M.E. performed the 
research; Z.L. analyzed and modeled the data; D.M.E. contributed new 
reagents and analytical tools. </p>



<p>Plasma Citrate Flux Into the Liver 
Li et al. </p>



<p>CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology </p>



<p>V C 2016 The Authors CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems 
Pharmacology published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on 
behalf of American Society for Clinical Pharmacology and 
Therapeutics. This is an open access article under the 
terms 
of 
the 
Creative 
Commons 
Attribution-
NonCommercial License, which permits use, distribution 
and reproduction in any medium, provided the original 
work is properly cited and is not used for commercial 
purposes. </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper on the CPT: Pharmacometrics &amp; Systems Pharmacology website 
(http://www.wileyonlinelibrary.com/psp4) </p>

<p>Plasma Citrate Flux Into the Liver 
Li et al. </p>



<p>www.wileyonlinelibrary/psp4 </p>

</text></tei>