<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4820668" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: after the great east Japan earthquake and tsunami 
in March 2011, radioactive elements were released from the Fuku-
shima Daiichi nuclear Power Plant. Based on prior knowledge, con-
cern emerged about whether an increased incidence of thyroid cancer 
among exposed residents would occur as a result. 
Methods: after the release, Fukushima Prefecture performed ultra-
sound thyroid screening on all residents ages ≤18 years. the first 
round of screening included 298,577 examinees, and a second round 
began in april 2014. We analyzed the prefecture results from the first 
and second round up to December 31, 2014, in comparison with the 
Japanese annual incidence and the incidence within a reference area 
in Fukushima Prefecture. 
Results: the highest incidence rate ratio, using a latency period of 4 
years, was observed in the central middle district of the prefecture com-
pared with the Japanese annual incidence (incidence rate ratio = 50; 95% 
confidence interval [ci] = 25, 90). the prevalence of thyroid cancer was 
605 per million examinees (95% ci = 302, 1,082) and the prevalence 
odds ratio compared with the reference district in Fukushima Prefecture 
was 2.6 (95% ci = 0.99, 7.0). in the second screening round, even under </p>

<p>the assumption that the rest of examinees were disease free, an incidence 
rate ratio of 12 has already been observed (95% ci = 5.1, 23). 
Conclusions: an excess of thyroid cancer has been detected by 
ultrasound among children and adolescents in Fukushima Prefecture 
within 4 years of the release, and is unlikely to be explained by a 
screening surge. </p>

<p>(Epidemiology 2016;27: 316-322) </p>

<p>T he Fukushima Daiichi nuclear Power Plant released radio-</p>

<p>active elements after the great east Japan earthquake and 
tsunami on March 11, 2011. as the wind shifted direction over 
time, 131 i, 134 cs, and 137 cs, in addition to other radionuclides, were 
released to both the northwest and the south of the plant. 1 the rela-
tive amounts of radioactive material released were estimated to be 
9.1% 131 i, 17.5% 137 cs, and 38.5% 134 cs. compared with cher-
nobyl where one reactor melted down, at Fukushima three reac-
tors melted down. 2 radiation released into the atmosphere from 
the Fukushima accident was estimated to be approximately 900 
petabecquerel ( 131 i: 500 petabecquerel, 137 cs: 10 petabecquerel). 
the radiologic equivalence to 131 i international nuclear event 
Scale was approximately one-sixth of the 5,200 petabecquerel 
calculated to have been released by the chernobyl accident. 3 
in its health risk assessment, the World Health Organi-
zation predicted that an excess of thyroid cancer cases would 
result from radiation-exposed children based on a prelimi-
nary dose assessment. 4,5 When the World Health Organization 
reported a preliminary dose estimation in 2012, it estimated 
the mean population dose for the more-affected locations 
within Fukushima Prefecture (excluding areas less than 20 km 
from the plant, which were immediately evacuated 4 ), the less-
affected remainder of Fukushima Prefecture, neighboring 
Japanese prefectures, the rest of Japan, neighboring countries, 
and the rest of the world. 4 a map of the three variously exposed 
areas within Fukushima Prefecture is shown in Figure. 
the World Health Organization estimated the thyroid 
equivalent doses in 2011 to be 100-200 millisieverts (mSv) in 
the more affected areas and 10-100 mSv in the rest of Fukushima 
Prefecture as delivered by inhalation, external exposure from 
ground shine, and ingestion. 4 in the most contaminated areas 
just outside 20 km from the plant, the proportion of exposure by </p>

<p>copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, inc. all rights reserved. this is an 
open-access article distributed under the terms of the creative commons attri-
bution-non commercial-no Derivatives license 4.0 (ccBY-nc-nD), where it 
is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. the 
work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially. 
iSSn: 1044-3983/16/2703-0316 
DOi: 10.1097/eDe.0000000000000385 </p>

<p>Editors' Note: A commentary on this article appears on page 323. 
Editors' Note: Letters to the Editor regarding this article can be found on the 
epidemiology website in the May 2016 issue at http://journals.lww.com/ 
epidem/pages/default.aspx 
Submitted 25 January 2015; accepted 10 august 2015. 
From the a Department of Human ecology, graduate School of environmental 
and life Science, Okayama University, Okayama, Japan; b Department of 
epidemiology, graduate School of Medicine, Dentistry and Pharmaceu-
tical Sciences, Okayama University, Okayama, Japan; and c Department 
of information Science, Faculty of informatics, Okayama University of 
Science, Okayama, Japan. 
Presented earlier aspects of this research at conferences of the international Soci-
ety for environmental epidemiology in Basel (2013) and Seattle (2014). 
the authors report no conflicts of interest. 
Supplemental digital content is available through direct Url citations 
in the HtMl and PDF versions of this article (www.epidem.com). 
this content is not peer-reviewed or copy-edited; it is the sole respon-
sibility of the authors. 
correspondence: toshihide tsuda, Department of Human ecology, graduate 
School of environmental and life Science, Okayama University, 3-1-1 
tsushima-naka, Kita-ku, Okayama, 700-8530, Japan. e-mail: tsudatos@ 
md.okayama-u.ac.jp. </p>

<p>Thyroid Cancer Detection by Ultrasound Among 
Residents Ages 18 Years and Younger in Fukushima, 
Japan: 2011 to 2014 </p>

<p>Toshihide Tsuda, a Akiko Tokinobu, b Eiji Yamamoto, c and Etsuji Suzuki b </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>Epidemiology • Volume 27, Number 3, May 2016 
Thyroid Cancer Among Young People in Fukushima </p>

<p>© 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
www.epidem.com | 317 </p>

<p>inhalation was the highest among all estimated radiation doses 
to the thyroid, ground shine was the second highest, and inges-
tion was the lowest. the report indicated that the proportion of 
exposure via ground shine increased as time advanced. 
aside from the screening in Fukushima Prefecture that is 
the subject of this study, Watanobe et al. 6 conducted a screening 
exercise from 2012 to 2013 including thyroid ultrasonography for 
1,137 Fukushima residents ages 18 years and younger at the time 
of the accident. no thyroid cancer was detected in this screening. 
in regions of Japan other than Fukushima, the Japanese Minis-
try of environment conducted thyroid screening of 4,365 chil-
dren and adolescents ages 3-18 years living in three prefectures 
(aomori, Yamanashi, and nagasaki) using ultrasound in the 2012 
fiscal year 7 ; one thyroid cancer case was detected. 8 We summa-
rize previously collected data on thyroid screening including that 
in chernobyl in the etable 1 (http://links.lww.com/eDe/a968). 
three years and 10 months after the accident, the main 
objective of this study was to establish accurate and quantita-
tive estimates from the Fukushima experience and to plan for 
the future public health needs of the population. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Exposure Estimation </p>

<p>exposure information on 131 i from the Fukushima 
release has been uncertain because of the 8-day half-life of </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>i and the destruction of monitoring sites as a result of the 
event. to explain differences in the regional distributions of 
estimated internal exposures (through inhalation and inges-
tion, for example, of 131 i) and external exposures (for example </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>cs and 137 cs), torii et al. 1 suggested that the differences </p>

<p>were due to substantial 131 i concentrations in the south area of 
the plant, together with exposure differences between radioac-
tive iodine and the total air dose rate. 
in addition to Japanese sources 9-11 that were cited by the 
World Health Organization, 4 Unno et al. 12 reported chrono-
logical changes in 131 i radioactivity levels in fallout per day 
in various cities; in 131 i radioactivity levels in spinach, cow's 
milk, and chicken eggs; and in tap water pollution with 131 i 
from March to May of 2011 in various areas of east Japan. 
they did not consider radioiodine exposure through inhala-
tion. they also measured radioiodine concentrations in breast 
milk from 119 volunteer lactating women residing within 250 
km of the Fukushima nuclear power plant between april 24 
and May 31, 2011. Seven of 23 women who were examined 
in april secreted a detectable level of 131 i in their breast milk. 
the national institute of radiological Sciences esti-
mated equivalent doses in mothers and infants from the data 
of Unno et al., 12,13 based on an acute ingestion model. 14 these 
estimated doses ranged from 119 to 432 mSv among mothers 
and from 330 to 1,190 mSv in their infants for those living 45 to 
220 km south or southwest, including iwaki city in the Fuku-
shima Prefecture, ibaragi Prefecture, and chiba Prefecture. 
However, nagataki et al. 15 reported that thyroid radia-
tion doses in children in the evacuation and deliberate evacu-
ation areas were estimated to be 10 mSv in 95.7% of children 
(maximum: 35 mSv) among 1,083 by screening and intake 
scenario. the timing of evacuations from heavily contami-
nated areas within 20 km, and from additional contaminated 
areas mainly northwest of the Fukushima plant, occurred 
between March 12 and mid-June 2011. 3 Many residents were 
evacuated to areas within Fukushima Prefecture, especially to </p>

<p>FIGURE. Map of Fukushima Prefecture 
and screening areas for the first round of 
screening from 2011 to 2013 fiscal years. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>Tsuda et al. 
Epidemiology • Volume 27, Number 3, May 2016 </p>

<p> 
© 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>the middle area, defined in "Subjects and their Screening," 
for reasons of convenience. therefore, such evacuees contin-
ued to be exposed much like the residents in the middle area. 
although several studies independently estimated dose-
response relationships between radioiodine and thyroid cancer 
incidence in chernobyl, 16-18 precise doses for cumulative radi-
ation have not yet been established. Because there is no precise 
measurement of external and internal radiation exposure in 
Fukushima, we used the residential addresses of the subjects in 
March 2011 categorized into each administrative district as a 
surrogate for individual radiation exposure measurement. </p>

<p>Subjects and Their Screening </p>

<p>the screening program for all residents born in Fukushima 
Prefecture from april 2, 1992, to april 1, 2011, was planned 
and conducted by the Fukushima Prefectural government, and 
labeled the "first round" hereafter. 19 all residents 18 years old 
and younger in March 2011 were screened by ultrasound dur-
ing the 2011-2013 fiscal years: the "nearest area" in 2011; the 
"middle area" in 2012; and the "least contaminated area" in 
2013 as shown in table 1. the institutional review Board of 
Fukushima Medical University approved the screening using 
ultrasound on September 22, 2011 (approval no. 1318; research 
representative: Vice-President Masafumi abe). regarding the 
analysis of the data described in this paper, the thyroid cancer 
surveillance dataset was deidentified and publicly available, so 
no further human subjects review was required. 
the "nearest area" to the Fukushima plant, mostly within 50 
km (47,768 subjects) was the most contaminated area, as indicated 
by dark grey in Figure. this area includes the main evacuation </p>

<p>areas situated less than 20 km from the plant; the World Health 
Organization has not estimated doses in these areas. 4 
the "middle area" shown by light contrasting grays in Fig-
ure (50-80 km from the Fukushima power plant, with 161,135 
residents of ages 18 years and younger in 2011) has a relatively 
large population. these areas mostly correspond to the "more 
affected locations" in the World Health Organization report. 4 
We divided the middle area into four districts: the north middle 
district, the central middle district, the Koriyama city district, 
and the south middle district. the central middle district had the 
highest air dose rate among the four districts in the middle area. 
We assigned the rest of Fukushima Prefecture (the "least 
contaminated area" in the World Health Organization report; 
158,784 subjects), indicated in white in Figure, to four districts: 
the western least contaminated district, the southeastern least 
contaminated district, the iwaki city district, and the northeast-
ern least contaminated district. the first three of these mostly 
correspond to less affected locations in the World Health Orga-
nization report. 4 
therefore, we divided Fukushima Prefecture into nine 
districts (Figure). the residence of each subject in March 2011 
was used to assign membership to the districts. information 
about major cities in each district was indicated in an online 
data table including outdoor air dose rates from about noon on 
March 30, 2011, which was summarized in etable 2 (http:// 
links.lww.com/eDe/a968). 11 Subjects in areas with higher 
air dose rate levels were screened earlier. the rank order of 
the screening was the nearest, the middle, and the least con-
taminated areas. 19 On the other hand, the order of length 
of time from the accident to screening was the reverse: the </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Demographic Data of the Analysis: Population 18 Years Old and Younger on March 11, 2011, Numbers of First 
Examinees, Positives in First Examination, Second Examinees, and Detected Cancer Cases in Each Area or District up to 
December 31, 2014 </p>

<p>Areas and Districts (1) to (9) </p>

<p>Population 
&lt;19 Years a 
1st Examinees </p>

<p>Positives in 1st 
Examinees </p>

<p>2nd 
Examinees 
Cancer Cases </p>

<p>N 
A (A/N, %) 
B (B/A, %) 
C (C/B, %) </p>

<p>D (No. Operated 
Cases) </p>

<p>nearest area (1) (2011 fiscal year) 
47,768 
41,810 (88) 
221 (0.53) 
199 (90) 
15 (15) b 
Middle area (2012 fiscal year) 
161,135 
139,339 (86) 
988 (0.71) 
919 (93) 
56 (50) 
north middle district (2) 
57,212 
50,618 (88) 
312 (0.62) 
297 (95) 
12 (na) 
central middle district (3) 
21,052 
18,194 (86) 
115 (0.63) 
111 (97) 
11 (na) 
Koriyama city district (4) 
64,383 
54,063 (84) 
458 (0.85) 
415 (91) 
25 (na) 
South middle district (5) 
18,488 
16,464 (89) 
103 (0.63) 
96 (93) 
8 (na) 
least contaminated area (2013 fiscal year) 
158,784 
117,428 (74) 
1,042 (0.89) 
949 (91) 
39 (22) 
iwaki city district (6) 
62,289 
48,810 (78) 
436 (0.89) 
401 (92) 
22 (na) 
Southeastern least contaminated district (7) 
38,321 
29,656 (77) 
230 (0.78) 
210 (91) 
7 (na) 
Western least contaminated district (8) 
49,927 
32,760 (66) 
323 (0.99) 
289 (89) 
10 (na) 
northeastern least contaminated district (9) 
8,247 
6,202 (75) 
53 (0.86) 
49 (93) 
0 (0) 
total 
367,687 
298,577 (81) 
2,251 (0.75) 
2,067 (92) 
110 (87) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>On March 11, 2011. 
b One operated case was diagnosed as a benign tumor by histology, but the case was assessed as cancer in this study according to cytology results. 
na indicates not available. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>Epidemiology • Volume 27, Number 3, May 2016 
Thyroid Cancer Among Young People in Fukushima </p>

<p>© 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
www.epidem.com | 319 </p>

<p>least contaminated, the middle, and the nearest. this results 
in underestimation of the prevalence odds ratios (POrs) by 
interarea comparison when a district in the least contaminated 
area was used as a reference. Within the middle and least con-
taminated areas, the rough screening order for the first round 
was north middle and central middle, south middle, Koriyama 
city, northeastern least contaminated, iwaki city and south-
eastern least contaminated, and western least contaminated 
districts. therefore, even within the same area, almost 1 year 
passed between screening of the first screened and the last 
screened districts. results from the first round of screening 
were released approximately every 3 months. 
the second round of screening began in april 2014, 
with the addition of all residents born in Fukushima Prefecture 
from april 2, 2011, to april 1, 2012. 20 the screening ("second 
round" hereafter) will be completed in March 2016; the near-
est and the middle areas were screened in the first fiscal year 
and the rest will be screened in the second fiscal year. Within 
2 years, the second round will cover all residents 18 years old 
and younger, including those who were in utero in 2011. 
Subjects with positive findings received a secondary 
examination, and if necessary, underwent fine needle aspira-
tion. 19 When cancer cells were detected, the patient was fol-
lowed and operated on at an appropriate time. the excised 
thyroid tissue was examined histologically. explanations 
about medical decisions, such as timing of fine needle aspi-
ration and surgery, were not made publicly available by the 
prefecture. in addition to the progressive course of the disease, 
a patient's school schedule was also considered in the timing 
of procedures because of the need for hospitalization. Based 
on information from Fukushima Prefecture, most fine needle 
aspirations and surgeries were performed by doctors from 
Fukushima Medical University. </p>

<p>Analysis </p>

<p>We defined thyroid cancer cases detected by fine needle 
aspiration cytology in the secondary examination as cases of 
"thyroid cancer" because the number of cancer cases oper-
ated in individual cities and towns was not released by the 
prefecture. among 87 cases operated, 86 cases (99%) were 
confirmed as malignancies by histological examination. 
We made two comparisons of thyroid cancer occur-
rence: one internal and one external. For the internal 
comparison, we used the southeastern least contaminated 
district as a reference, and estimated POrs and 95% con-
fidence intervals (cis) for thyroid cancer in the remaining 
eight districts. For the external comparison, we used the 
Japanese mean annual incidence rate estimates for thyroid 
cancer among persons ages 19 years old and younger (i.e., 
two per 1,000,000) and 5-24 years old (6.5 per 1,000,000) 
from 2001 to 2008 reported by the Japanese national can-
cer center, 21 then employed three per 1,000,000 as the ref-
erence incidence and estimated incidence rate ratios (irrs) 
and 95% cis in the nine districts. in doing so, we divided </p>

<p>the prevalence by the latent duration of disease. 22 note that 
"latent duration" denotes the time from the date when thy-
roid cancer became detectable by screening and cytology to 
the date when it could be diagnosed in clinical settings with-
out screening or the date of operation. Here, we assumed 
4 years for a latent duration of childhood thyroid cancer, 
corresponding to the time between the Fukushima accident 
and thyroid cancer detection, for which the maximum dura-
tion was 3 years and 10 months. 
We calculated 95% cis for the POr using the maximum 
likelihood odds ratio with mid-P using <rs type="software">Statcalc</rs> in epi info 7 
and for irr based on the Poisson distribution indicated in the 
geigy scientific tables. 23 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>table 1 shows the number of subjects in the first round of 
screening, those actually screened ("1st examinees"), those who 
screened positive as indicated by referral to the secondary exami-
nation, those who actually underwent the secondary examination 
("2nd examinees"), detected thyroid cancer cases by cytology, 
and cancer cases as indicated by the number of surgeries. 
among 367,687 residents 18 years old and younger 
in 2011, 298,577 (81%) underwent the first round screening 
by the end of December 2014. the proportion of residents 
who underwent screening decreased year by year: 88% in 
the 2011 fiscal year; 87% in the 2012 fiscal year; and 74% 
in the 2013 fiscal year. this trend was mainly induced by 
a lower proportion of 16-to 18-year-old examinees in the 
least contaminated districts, which were screened last. Pro-
portions of examinees among subjects in the 16-18 years 
old stratum were 74% in the nearest, 63% in the middle, and 
34% in the least contaminated areas. in Japanese society, 
residents 18 years and older tend to leave their hometown 
for work or study, so some members of this group at the 
time of the accident had already left by the time the screen-
ing program reached their districts. 
among 2,251 ultrasound screen-positive cases by the 
end of December 2014, 2,067 cases were examined in sec-
ondary examinations, which detected 110 thyroid cancer 
cases, as indicated by the presence of cancer cells by cytol-
ogy after fine needle aspiration. among the 110 cases, 87 
cases were operated by the end of December 2014: 86 cases 
were histologically confirmed (83 papillary carcinomas and 
three poorly differentiated carcinomas), and one case was 
diagnosed as a benign tumor. 
table 2 shows the results of both the internal and exter-
nal comparisons. the results of external comparisons indicate 
an excess in irrs in all three areas, except for the northeast-
ern least contaminated district in which no thyroid cancer 
cases were detected. 
When based on histologically confirmed cases that were 
operated on, the irrs for external comparisons using a latent 
duration of 4 years were 28 (95% ci = 15, 47) in the nearest 
area (excluding one benign case), 30 (95% ci = 22, 39) in the </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>Tsuda et al. 
Epidemiology • Volume 27, Number 3, May 2016 </p>

<p> 
© 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>middle area, and 16 (95% ci = 10, 24) in the least contami-
nated area for which the secondary examination of cytology-
positive cases is incomplete. 
the highest irr in the external comparisons was 
observed in the central middle district of the prefecture, 50 to 
60 km west from the Fukushima power plant, where residents 
were not evacuated (irr based on positive cytology was 50; 
95% ci = 25, 90). Prevalence in the district was 605 cases per 
million examinees (95% ci = 302, 1,082), and the POr com-
pared with the southeastern least contaminated district was 
2.6 (95% ci = 0.99, 7.0). 
although the second round of screening that began in 
the 2014 fiscal year was not included in the tables, the num-
bers of subjects were as follows: total subjects, 218,397; actu-
ally screened, 106,068 (49%); among them, for 75,311 (71%), 
it had already been decided whether the secondary exami-
nation was necessary or not; positives in the screening, 611 
(0.8%); examined in the secondary examination, 377 (62% of 
the positives); finally diagnosed by the secondary examina-
tion, 262 (70%); examined by fine needle aspiration, 22 (8%), 
and detected eight new thyroid cancer cases by cytology up to 
December 31, 2014. all of the eight cancer cases (four males 
and four females with ages at the accident ranging from 6 to 
17 years at the time of the accident in 2011) underwent the 
first round screening. in three among the eight cases, a ≤5.0-
mm nodule and/or a ≤20.0-mm cyst were detected in the first 
round. the one cancer case was already operated on (histo-
logical type was papillary carcinoma). Mean age of the cases 
in 2011 was 12.1 ± 3.4 years in the second round, whereas it 
was 14.8 ± 2.6 years in the first round. even under the assump-
tion that the remaining 75,303 (75,311 minus 8 cancer cases) 
are disease free, an excess irr for external comparison with 3 
years as a latent duration which was maximum time since the 
first round was observed (12, 95% ci = 5.1, 23). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>although precise measurements of both external and 
internal radiation exposure in Fukushima were not obtained, 
in external comparison, we observed an approximately 30-fold 
increase in the number of thyroid cancer cases among children 
and adolescents using the area/district of residence to provide 
a surrogate for exposure information (table 2). in the early 
reports on excess thyroid cancer from chernobyl, place and 
time were also used as a proxy for exposure information. 24-26 
excesses of thyroid cancer in the central middle district by 
both external and internal comparison were observed, although 
the POrs were relatively lower. the finding that southernmost 
districts within the middle and the least contaminated areas 
had higher irrs than the northernmost districts was consistent 
with the flow of 131 i being primarily in a southern direction 
from the Fukushima release. 
By considering the prevalence (detected cases per 
1,000,000), irrs in table 2, and years between the accident and 
screening-4 to16 years in chernobyl and less than 4 years in 
Fukushima-we could infer that the incidence of thyroid cancer 
in Fukushima rose more rapidly than expected based on the cumu-
lative attributable thyroid cancer risk over 15 years as estimated 
by the World Health Organization. 5 the radiation burden to the 
thyroid in Fukushima Prefecture might have been considerably 
higher than estimated, 4 as suggested by other measurements. 12 
the variability of prevalence in chernobyl may also result from 
variability in years between the accident and screening. 
One concern is that the approximately 30-fold increase 
observed in the number of thyroid cancer cases in external 
comparison might be the result of a screening effect. this con-
cern is based on the potential presence of silent thyroid cancer 
among children and adolescents in the unscreened regions of 
Japan. However, the magnitude of the irrs was too large to 
be explained only by this bias. Furthermore, according to the </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Prevalence, Prevalence Odds Ratios (POR), and Incidence Rate Ratios (IRR) in Each District up to December 31, 2014 </p>

<p>Areas and Districts (1) to (9) </p>

<p>Prevalence of Thyroid Cancer 
Cases per 10 6 (95% CI) </p>

<p>Internal Comparison External Comparison </p>

<p>POR (95% CI) 
IRR a (95% CI) </p>

<p>nearest area (1) (2011 fiscal year) 
359 (201, 592) 
1.5 (0.63, 4.0) 
30 (17, 49) 
Middle area (2012 fiscal year) 
402 (304, 522) 
1.7 (0.81, 4.1) 
33 (25, 43) 
north middle district (2) 
237 (123, 414) 
1.0 (0.40, 2.7) 
20 (10, 35) 
central middle district (3) 
605 (302, 1,082) 
2.6 (0.99, 7.0) 
50 (25, 90) 
Koriyama city district (4) 
462 (299, 683) 
2.0 (0.87, 4.9) 
39 (25, 57) 
South middle district (5) 
486 (210, 957) 
2.1 (0.7, 6.0) 
40 (17, 80) 
least contaminated area (2013 fiscal year) 
332 (236, 454) 
-
28 (20, 38) 
iwaki city district (6) 
451 (282, 682) 
1.9 (0.84, 4.8) 
38 (24, 57) 
Southeastern least contaminated district (7) 
236 (95, 486) 
1 (reference) 
20 (7.9, 41) 
Western least contaminated district (8) 
305 (146, 561) 
1.3 (0.49, 3.6) 
25 (12, 47) 
northeastern least contaminated district (9) 
0 (0, 595) 
0.00 (0.0, 2.6) 
0.00 (0.0, 50) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>the irrs were based on diagnosis by cytology. When based on histologically confirmed cases that were operated on, the irrs for external comparisons using a latent duration of 
4 years were 28 (95% ci = 15, 47) in the nearest area (excluding one benign case), 30 (95% ci = 22, 39) in the middle area, and 16 (95% ci = 10, 24) in the least contaminated area 
for which the secondary examination of cytology positive cases is incomplete. </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>Epidemiology • Volume 27, Number 3, May 2016 
Thyroid Cancer Among Young People in Fukushima </p>

<p>© 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
www.epidem.com | 321 </p>

<p>data reported by Fukushima Prefecture, 27 positive lymph node 
metastases were observed in 40 of 54 cases (74%) operated 
at the Fukushima Medical University Hospital. this finding 
indicates that cancers detected by screening were not at a 
particularly early stage. 
in addition, a likely underestimated but clear increase 
(eight cases: irr = 12 with 3 years as a latent duration) of 
thyroid cancer incidence was observed in the second round 
screening among cases who were screened and cancer free in 
the first round. 20 this result cannot be explained by the screen-
ing effect because most occult thyroid cancer cases would 
have been harvested in the first round screening. 
another concern about attributing a causal effect of the 
Fukushima accident to increased thyroid cancer incidence is 
that the excess within 4 years of the accident is too soon for 
radiation exposure to have induced thyroid cancer. in cher-
nobyl, however, small excesses of thyroid cancer incidence 
were observed in both Belarus and Ukraine during 1987-
1989, within 3 years after the accident in 1986. 28,29 Further-
more, during 1987-1989, no screening was conducted around 
chernobyl. 30 the minimum empirical induction time for 
thyroid cancer is 2.5 years for adults and 1 year for children, 
according to the US centers for Disease control and Preven-
tion. 31 therefore, we considered it possible to detect thyroid 
cancer related to the accident by screening using ultrasound 
even within the 2011 fiscal year. 
Several limitations of this study should be mentioned. 
First, coverage of the screening program and secondary exami-
nation did not include all eligible residents of Fukushima at the 
time of the 2011 accident, as indicated in table 1. the screened 
population may not be fully representative of the exposed pop-
ulation. the proportion of examinees among eligible persons 
gradually declined in the 2012 and 2013 fiscal years, mainly 
in the stratum of those age 16-18 years in 2011, and half of 
the cancer cases (55 of 110) were detected in this stratum. We 
could not adjust for this decline because age-and municipal-
ity (city, town, and village)-specific number of detected cancer 
cases was not reported by the prefecture. therefore, this may 
induce overestimation in internal comparisons when preva-
lence of the 2013 fiscal year districts was used as a reference. 
Second, the effect of the length of time elapsed between 
the accident and timing of screening should be considered 
further. Using later screened areas or districts as a reference 
induces further underestimation when comparing each area/ 
district due to different empirical induction time. We underes-
timated the POrs because we used the southeastern least con-
taminated district as a reference where the screening program 
was conducted in the 2013 fiscal year. Furthermore, internal 
comparisons were intrinsically underestimated compared with 
external comparisons because the reference of internal compar-
isons was also influenced by the exposure. in particular, among 
seven cancer cases observed in the reference district (Figure), 
four were observed in Sukagawa city, which is usually included 
in the middle area as half of the city had a high air dose rate. if </p>

<p>we excluded Sukagawa city from the reference, prevalence of 
the reference decreased to 170 per million. Using a 4-year latent 
duration in estimating irrs in the external comparison in the 
first round and 3-year latent duration in the external compari-
son of the second round of screening might also underestimate 
irrs because they were longer than the actual durations. 
third, we employed areas and districts as a surrogate 
for exposure estimation, which could have introduced nondif-
ferential exposure misclassification that can bias the effect 
estimates toward the null. the known etiologic factors for 
thyroid cancer that are possible confounders, other than radia-
tion, include inherited genetic alterations, which are unlikely 
to explain regional excesses. there is little potential for spatial 
confounding both in Japan and within Fukushima Prefecture 
because the subjects in this study are all residents 18 years old 
and younger, as noted below. Furthermore, before the acci-
dent, no evidence existed that natural radiation was higher in 
Fukushima Prefecture than in the rest of Japan. 
Fourth, we defined thyroid cancer cases based on positive 
results of fine needle aspiration cytology. However, the propor-
tion of histologically confirmed cases among those operated was 
99%, so disease misclassification seems to be negligible. 
in conclusion, among those ages 18 years and younger in 
2011 in Fukushima Prefecture, approximately 30-fold excesses 
in external comparisons and variability in internal comparisons 
on thyroid cancer detection were observed in Fukushima Pre-
fecture within as few as 4 years after the Fukushima power 
plant accident. the result was unlikely to be fully explained 
by the screening effect. in chernobyl, excesses of thyroid can-
cer became more remarkable 4 or 5 years after the accident in 
Belarus and Ukraine, so the observed excess alerts us to pre-
pare for more potential cases within a few years. Furthermore, 
we could infer a possibility that exposure doses for residents 
were higher than the official report or the dose estimation by 
the World Health Organization, 4 because the number of thyroid 
cancer cases grew faster than predicted in the World Health 
Organization's health assessment report. 5 
Note added in editing: additional new data were released 
from Fukushima Prefecture on May 18, 2015, and two thyroid 
cancer cases from the first round of screening and seven cases 
from the second round of screening were added to the results 
presented in this article. the irr of external comparison with 
a 3-year latency in the second round of screening increased to 
13.7 (95% ci = 7.7, 23). We provide this information in the 
etable 3, etable 4, and the text of the eappendix (http://links. 
lww.com/eDe/a968). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to Colin L. Soskolne, PhD, 
Martin Tondel, MD, PhD, Erik R. Svendsen, PhD, Gaston 
Meskens, MSc, and Wael Al-Delaimy, MD, PhD, for their 
thoughtful suggestions and constructive discussions on 
cancer-related issues relating to the 2011 nuclear accident in 
Fukushima, Japan, and for constructive editorial assistance </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited. </p>

<p>Tsuda et al. 
Epidemiology • Volume 27, Number 3, May 2016 </p>

<p>322 | www.epidem.com 
© 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>through earlier drafts of this article. The authors also thank 
Tetsuji Imanaka, MSc, Keiji Hayashi, MD, and Okujou Iwami 
MD, PhD, for providing important references. </p>



</text></tei>