<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4853588" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Background While electroacupuncture (EA) 
pretreatment has been found to ameliorate 
migraine-like symptoms, the underlying 
mechanisms remain poorly understood. 
Emerging evidence suggests that the brainstem 
descending pain modulatory system, comprising 
the periaqueductal grey (PAG), raphe magnus 
nucleus (RMg), and trigeminal nucleus caudalis 
(TNC), may be involved in migraine 
pathophysiology. We hypothesised that EA 
would ameliorate migraine-like symptoms via 
modulation of this descending system. 
Methods We used a conscious rat model of 
migraine induced by repeated electrical 
stimulation of the dura. Forty male Sprague-
Dawley rats were randomly assigned to one of 
four groups: an EA group, which received EA at 
GB20 following dural stimulation; a sham 
acupuncture (SA) group, which received manual 
acupuncture at a non-acupuncture point 
following dural stimulation; a Model group, 
which received dural stimulation but no 
acupuncture; and a Control group, which 
received neither dural stimulation nor 
acupuncture (electrode implantation only). 
<rs type="software">HomeCageScan</rs> was used to measure effects on 
behaviour, and immunofluorescence staining was 
used to examine neural activation (c-Fos 
immunoreactivity) in the PAG, RMg, and TNC. 
Results Compared to the Model group, rats in 
the EA group showed a significant increase in 
exploratory, locomotor and eating/drinking 
behaviour ( p&lt;0.01) and a significant decrease in 
freezing-like resting and grooming behaviour 
( p&lt;0.05). There was a significant increase in the 
mean number of c-Fos neurons in the PAG, 
RMg, and TNC in Model versus Control groups 
( p&lt;0.001); however, this was significantly 
attenuated by EA treatment ( p&lt;0.001). There 
were no significant differences between the SA </p>

<p>and Model groups in behaviour or c-Fos 
immunoreactivity. 
Conclusions EA pretreatment ameliorates 
behavioural changes in a rat model of recurrent 
migraine, possibly via modulation of the 
brainstem descending pathways. </p>

<p>INTRODUCTION 
Migraine is a debilitating neurological 
disease that affects millions worldwide, 
including up to 12% of American and 
9.3% of Chinese people. 1 2 It is charac-
terised by recurrent attacks of unilateral 
headache that can be aggravated by 
routine physical activity, 3 resulting in 
reduced function. 4 The brainstem des-
cending pain modulatory system has been 
shown to play a vital role in migraine 
pathophysiology via effects on trigemino-
vascular nociceptive information trans-
mission and central sensitisation. 5 
Current drug treatments include 
migraine-specific medications (ergota-
mine, 5-HT 1B/1D/1F receptor agonists) 
and prophylactic treatments including 
antiepileptic drugs, lisuride, β-blockers, 
and ergot derivatives. However, these 
pharmacological agents have been asso-
ciated with suboptimal efficacy, poor 
adherence and side effects, and have 
many contraindications. 6 7 Overall, an 
efficacious clinical treatment for migraine 
is lacking, particularly for prophylaxis 
and to delay progression of recurrent to 
chronic migraine. 
A recent review has shown that acu-
puncture is effective for the treatment of 
migraine, especially prophylaxis. 8 Indeed, 
we have also found that acupuncture 
pretreatment is effective at decreasing 
the frequency of migraine attacks. 9 </p>

<p>Open Access 
Scan to access more 
free content </p>

<p>Original paper </p>

<p>Pei P, et al. Acupunct Med 2016;34:127-135. doi:10.1136/acupmed-2015-010840 </p>



<p>Moreover, Gao and colleagues found that electroacu-
puncture (EA) is able to regulate the peripheral excita-
tory neurotransmitter glutamate in plasma. 10 
Nevertheless, the exact mechanisms underlying the 
analgesic effect of acupuncture (including pretreat-
ment) on migraine have not yet been determined. 
We hypothesised that acupuncture pretreatment 
would ameliorate migraine-like symptoms in recurrent 
migraine via modulation of the brainstem descending 
pain modulatory system: the periaqueductal grey 
(PAG), raphe magnus nucleus (RMg), and trigeminal 
nucleus caudalis (TNC). To test this hypothesis we 
chose a rat model of recurrent migraine induced by 
repeated electrical stimulation of the dura surrounding 
the superior sagittal sinus (SSS), which is an estab-
lished paradigm of migraine-associated pain. 11 12 The 
aim of the present study was to examine the effect of 
EA on behaviour (using <rs type="software">HomeCageScan</rs> technology) 
and neuronal activation in the PAG, RMg, and TNC 
(by immunofluorescence staining). </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Ethics statement </p>

<p>All experiments were performed in accordance with 
the International Association for the Study of Pain 
guidelines and Guideline for the Care and Use of 
Laboratory Animals (State Council of China, 2013). 
The study was approved by the Beijing Institutional 
Review Board for Animal Experiments (Use 
Committee of Capital Medical University, Beijing, ref-
erence number AEEI 2015-075). All surgeries were 
performed under anaesthesia, and every possible 
effort was made to reduce suffering. </p>

<p>Animals </p>

<p>Male, Sprague-Dawley rats weighing 210±10 g were 
purchased from Vital River Laboratories. They were 
individually housed in a controlled environment 
(room temperature 23±2°C, humidity 50±10%, 12 h 
light-dark cycle with the lights turned on at 08:00) 
with food and water freely available. After 1 week of 
habituation, rats underwent brain surgery to establish 
the migraine model. </p>

<p>Surgical procedures 
Exposure of dura mater </p>

<p>Rats were anaesthetised with 60 mg/kg intraperitoneal 
sodium pentobarbitone (Sigma-Aldrich) and placed 
into a stereotactic frame. To access the dura mater, the 
parietal bone was exposed and two cranial windows 
(4 mm anterior and 6 mm posterior to the bregma on 
the midline suture, 1 mm in diameter) were carefully 
made using a saline-cooled drill (78001, RWD Life 
Science, Shenzhen, China). The cranial windows were 
then opened to expose the dura mater adjacent to the 
SSS, as previously described. 13 </p>

<p>Electrode fixation </p>

<p>A pair of tailored electrode fixtures (Beijing JiAnDeEr 
Ltd, China), each composed of a bipolar electrode 
(1.9-2.1 mm in length, 0.8 mm in diameter), a plastic 
holder with two screw holes and an obturator cap, 
were inserted into the cranial windows so that they 
touched the surface of the dura mater surrounding the 
SSS. Two stainless steel screws (M1.4×2.8 mm) were 
then placed into the screw holes as anchors for the 
dental cement (Shanghai New Century Dental 
Materials Co, Ltd, Shanghai, China) that was then 
used to stabilise the electrode fixtures. Finally the 
obturator cap was placed over the external stimuli line 
interface to prevent clogging. All surgery was per-
formed under direct visual control using an operating 
microscope. Finally, penicillin (0.04 million IU/100 g, 
Harbin Pharmaceutical Group Co, Ltd, China) was 
applied to the lesion in order to prevent infection. All 
rats were allowed to recover for 7 days before experi-
ments began. </p>

<p>Experimental design </p>

<p>After recovering from surgery, 40 animals were ran-
domly divided into four groups: an EA group, which 
received EA at GB20 (Fengchi) following electrical 
stimulation of the dura; a sham acupuncture (SA) 
group, which received acupuncture (manual not EA) 
at a distant non-acupuncture point following electrical 
stimulation of the dura; a Model group, which 
received electrical dural stimulation but no EA; and a 
Control group, which received neither electrical dural 
stimulation nor EA (only electrode implantation). The 
EA, SA, and Model groups received repeated electrical 
stimulation using a stimulator (YC-2 stimulator 
Chengdu) every other day for a total of three sessions 
(day 1, 3, and 5). Before electrical stimulation, the EA 
group received EA at GB20 once a day from day 0 to 
day 5 for a total of six sessions. The number of rats 
used was based on the power calculation of a previous 
study. 10 A schematic representation of the experimen-
tal protocol is given in figure 1. </p>

<p>EA at GB20 </p>

<p>Before dural stimulation, the EA and SA group 
received EA/SA pretreatment from days 0 to 5, for a 
total of six sessions. Conscious rats were placed into 
tailored fixtures that exposed their heads and necks. 
GB20 is a commonly used acupuncture point for the 
treatment of migraine. 9 Its anatomical location in rats 
is similar to the human, being 3 mm lateral to the 
centre of a line joining the two ears at the back of the 
head. 14 In the EA group, two stainless steel acupunc-
ture needles (diameter 0.25 mm; length 25 mm; 
Suzhou Medical Appliance Factory, Suzhou, China) 
were inserted bilaterally at GB20 to a depth of 2-
3 mm in the direction of the opposite eye. The needle 
handle was then connected to an electrical stimulator 
(Han's 
acupuncture 
point 
nerve 
stimulator </p>

<p>Original paper </p>



<p>Pei P, et al. Acupunct Med 2016;34:127-135. doi:10.1136/acupmed-2015-010840 </p>

<p>HNAS-200, Nanjing) between 08:00 and 10:00 for 
15 min/day. EA was given at 2/15 Hz frequency 
(amplitude-modulated wave) 15 and 0.5-1.0 mA inten-
sity (depending on the reaction of the rat). In the SA 
group, needles were placed bilaterally at distant non-
acupuncture points (about 10 mm above the iliac 
crest), 16 but no stimulation was given. Animals in the 
Control and Model groups were similarly placed into 
fixtures for 20 min, but no acupuncture was provided. </p>

<p>Repeated electrical stimulation of the dura </p>

<p>Before electrical stimulation, rats were individually 
placed into an observation cage (40 cm diameter, 
17.5 cm height) and habituated for 20 min to minim-
ise stress. The obturator cap was then removed from 
the electrode fixtures and an internal delivery elec-
trode tip was inserted, which was connected to the 
current external output port of an electrical stimulator 
(YC-2 stimulator, Chengdu). Based on previous 
studies 12 and our own optimisation of the stimulation 
parameters, effective dural stimuli consisted of mono-
phasic square-wave pulses with a 0.5 ms pulse dur-
ation at 1.8-2.0 mA intensity and 20 Hz frequency, 
and were administered for a 15 min period every 
other day for a total of three sessions for rats in the 
EA, SA, and Model groups. Rats in the Control group 
were also connected to the stimulator but received no 
electrical stimulation. </p>

<p>Behavioural analysis by <rs type="software">HomeCageScan</rs> </p>

<p>Spontaneous behaviour was monitored by the auto-
mated behavioural acquisition and analysis software 
'<rs id="software-0" type="software">HomeCageScan</rs>' (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Clever Systems Inc.</rs>, Reston, 
Virginia, USA). Before real/sham electrical dural 
stimulation, rats were acclimatised for 20 min in an 
individual transparent acrylic observation cage with an 
automatic real-time video surveillance and image ana-
lysis system, which was lit to model daytime condi-
tions. Subsequently, animals received electrical dural 
stimulation for 15 min in another cage before being 
individually placed back into the observation cage for 
a 1 h recording. 
The observation cage was cleaned with 10% 
ethanol between sessions to eliminate odour traces. 
Behaviours were analysed by identifying body parts </p>

<p>such as the mouth, head, tail, forelimb, hindlimb, 
upper/lower back and abdomen, and using sequence 
data to recognise and analyse movements automatic-
ally. During the test, rats had free access to food and 
water. 
According to previously described classifica-
tions, 17 18 we divided behaviours into the following 
six categories: </p>

<p>1. Exploratory behaviour: rearing up and sniffing 
2. Locomotor behaviour: turning, stretching, walking, 
jumping and walking slowly 
3. Freezing-like behaviour (frozen, immobile posture): 
twitching, 'remaining low' 
4. Resting behaviour: sleeping (head rested on flexed fore-
paws with eyes open/closed) 
5. Eating and drinking behaviour 
6. Grooming behaviour: face and body grooming. </p>

<p>All behaviours were verified and calibrated before 
recording and analysis. </p>

<p>c-Fos immunofluorescence and image analysis </p>

<p>After the last <rs type="software">HomeCageScan</rs> recording session, 
animals were anaesthetised with 10% chloral hydrate 
(15 ml/kg, intraperitoneally) and transcardially per-
fused through the ascending aorta with 100 ml 0.1 M 
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), followed by 500 mL 
of 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in PBS. Brains were 
removed and postfixed overnight at 4°C in 4% PFA/ 
PBS, then transferred to 30% sucrose/PBS for 72 h 
for cryopreservation. Coronal sections (25 mm thick) 
through the PAG, RMg, and TNC were cut using a 
cryostat (Leica CM3050S, Leica Inc, Wetzlar, 
Germany), incubated with rabbit anti-c-Fos antiserum 
(sc-52, 1:200, Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc, USA) 
overnight at 4°C, and then treated with Cy3 goat anti-
rabbit secondary antibodies (111-165-003, 1:500, 
Jackson 
ImmunoResearch 
Laboratories 
Inc, 
Pennsylvania, USA) for 2 h at room temperature 
before being mounted, dehydrated, and cover-slipped 
in anti-fade reagent (AR1109, Boster Bioengineering 
Inc, Wuhan, China). 
Section images were captured using a Leica semi-
automatic light microscope (Leica DM5500 B), and 
cells were counted in squares at 20× magnification. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Schematic representation of the experimental protocol. One week after surgery to implant electrodes, rats received 
electrical dural stimulation (or no stimulation in the case of the Control group) every 2 days from day 1 to day 5 (on days 1, 3, and 5). 
Electroacupuncture (or sham acupuncture) pretreatment was performed daily from day 0 to day 5 (on days 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5) in 
subgroups of rats. Behavioural analysis was carried out using <rs type="software">HomeCageScan</rs> immediately after dural stimulation on days 1, 3, and 
5. c-Fos immunofluorescence was measured in brain tissues prepared following necropsy on day 5. </p>

<p>Original paper </p>

<p>Pei P, et al. Acupunct Med 2016;34:127-135. doi:10.1136/acupmed-2015-010840 </p>



<p>Cell density in the PAG, RMg, and TNC was calcu-
lated by a blinded assessor using Image J software. 
Anatomical boundaries were determined according to 
a rat brain atlas. 19 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean±SD. Groups were com-
pared by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) using 
the <rs id="software-7" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs> Software 
(SPSS) <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">V.12.0</rs> (SPSS Inc, Chicago, Illinois, USA). 
Post-hoc testing was performed using Bonferroni 
(homogeneity of variance) or Tamhane (heterogeneity 
of variance) tests. Statistical significance was defined 
as p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Behavioural analysis </p>

<p>The results at baseline and following establishment of 
the recurrent migraine model ±EA/SA treatment are 
shown in table 1. Before dural stimulation, during the 
acclimatisation period (20 min), there were no signifi-
cant differences between groups in any of the analysed 
behaviours (all p&gt;0.05). </p>

<p>Exploratory behaviour, locomotor behaviour and eating/drinking 
behaviour </p>

<p>Across all subsequent time periods (D1-D5), rats in 
the Model group spent less time in exploratory beha-
viours (rearing up and sniffing), locomotor behaviours 
(turning, stretching, walking, and jumping) and 
eating/drinking behaviours than the Control group 
( p&lt;0.001-0.011). However, by day 5, these effects 
were all attenuated by pretreatment with EA 
( p&lt;0.001-0.006). There were no statistically signifi-
cant differences between groups in the 'walking 
slowly' behaviour. There were very few significant dif-
ferences between the Model and SA groups for any 
parameter, except for turning (D5) and walking (D1 
and D5), where a greater amount of time was spent 
on these activities in the SA group ( p=0.024, 
p=0.027 and p=0.001, respectively). </p>

<p>Freezing-like behaviour, resting behaviour, and grooming behaviour </p>

<p>Across all three time periods, freezing-like (twitching 
and remaining low) and resting (sleep) behaviours 
were significantly increased in the Model group com-
pared to the Control group ( p&lt;0.001-0.002). 
Grooming behaviour was similarly increased on D3 
and D5 ( p&lt;0.001 and p=0.005, respectively) but not 
D1 ( p=0.887). These effects were also mitigated on 
D3 and D5 (but not D1) for freezing-like behaviour 
( p&lt;0.001-0.047 and p=0.085-1, respectively) and at 
all time points for sleeping ( p&lt;0.001-0.011). Rats in 
the EA group spent less time grooming on D1 and D3 
( p=0.042 and p=0.018, respectively) and tended to 
spend less time grooming on D5 ( p=0.079) compared 
to the Model group. By contrast, there were no sig-
nificant differences between the Model and SA groups 
for any of these parameters ( p&gt;0.05). </p>

<p>c-Fos immunofluorescence analysis </p>

<p>Representative images and the density of 
c-Fos-immunoreactive cells in the PAG, RMg, and 
TNC are shown in figures 2-4, respectively. Rats in 
the Model group showed greater c-Fos neuron expres-
sion than that the Control group within the PAG (all 
p&lt;0.001). In the EA group, the mean number of 
c-Fos positive neurons was significantly reduced in all 
three brain regions compared to the Model group 
( p&lt;0.001), while SA had no significant effect on 
dural stimulation-induced c-Fos activation compared 
to the Model group (PAG/RMg: p=1.0; TNC: 
p=0.64). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The results of the present study suggest that acupunc-
ture pretreatment at GB20 can ameliorate behavioural 
responses to electrical stimulation of the dura in rats, 
and that the positive effects may, at least in part, result 
from modulation of brainstem descending pathways in 
this model. </p>

<p>Acupuncture pretreatment can ameliorate the behavioural 
responses to migraine </p>

<p>The rat model of migraine used herein was developed 
to mimic clinical pain conditions experienced by 
migraineurs, based upon clinical diagnostic criteria 
from the International Classification of Headache 
Disorders (ICHD)-II and ICHD-IIIβ classification 
including a decrease in physical activity during 
migraine attacks. 3 20 Analysis of behavioural changes 
using <rs type="software">HomeCageScan</rs> offers a new way to study 
migraine. 18 However, it should be remembered that 
there are clear differences in pathophysiology between 
this model and the human condition, which may limit 
the ability to extrapolate our results. 
Similar to previous studies, 17 18 we found that 
repeated stimulation of the dura produced an increase 
in nociceptive behaviour, such as freezing and resting. 
There was also a decrease in exploratory, locomotor 
and eating/drinking behaviour. Collectively, these 
reflect the clinical symptoms of migraine attacks, 
which includes a reduction in routine physical activity, 
loss of motivation, and decreased intake of food and 
drink. 3 4 21 Interestingly, these behavioural changes 
were reversed by EA pretreatment, as the EA group 
exhibited decreased nociceptive behaviour and 
increased exploratory, locomotor and eating/drinking 
behaviour. 
It has been suggested that grooming in rats may 
reflect the cutaneous allodynia that migraineurs often 
suffer during an episode. 18 Cutaneous allodynia arises 
as a consequence of central sensitisation of the TNC 
and higher structures, such as the thalamus, PAG, and 
RMg. 5 22 It is an independent predictor of migraine 
progression and is closely related with imbalances in 
the brainstem descending pain modulatory system. 22 
In the current study, EA pretreatment significantly </p>

<p>Original paper </p>



<p>Pei P, et al. Acupunct Med 2016;34:127-135. doi:10.1136/acupmed-2015-010840 </p>

<p>Table 1 Behavioural analysis results by group at baseline and on days 1-5 </p>

<p>EA 
SA 
Model 
Control 
p Value </p>

<p>Rearing up 
Baseline 
3.2±0.61 
3.4±1.06 
3.8±1.05 
3.0±0.51 
0.195 
D1 
2.4±0.21 a 
2.0±0.10 a 
2.0±0.25 a 
4.0±1.02 b 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
1.8±0.34 a 
1.4±0.13 a 
1.2±0.35 a 
4.0±1.14 b 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
2.3±0.35 a 
1.3±0.26 b 
1.0±0.37 b 
3.6±0.35 c 
&lt;0.001 
Sniffing 
Baseline 
490.7±124.17 
518.8±93.98 
522.0±120.27 
527.5±125.92 
0.898 
D1 
589.5±36.74 a 
306.4±20.87 b 
247.2±39.57 b 
1211.3±93.22 c 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
482.9±30.93 a 
197.6±16.68 bc 
179.9±28.42 b 
1074.9±102.94 c 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
501.9±34.56 a 
145.0±10.39 b 
129.4±17.74 b 
1096.1±123.87 a 
&lt;0.001 
Turning 
Baseline 
24.3±4.96 
22.6±5.62 
29.8±6.08 
22.9±7.13 
0.039 
D1 
50.7±5.04 a 
25.9±4.77 b 
25.8±4.69 b 
66.2±9.2 c 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
27.2±4.55 a 
15.7±1.93 b 
11.1±1.43 b 
64.1±8.83 c 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
22.7±3.47 a 
13.4±2.13 b 
7.0±0.96 c 
50.7±6.07 d 
&lt;0.001 
Stretching 
Baseline 
45.5±9.74 
42.0±5.20 
43.5±7.64 
38.4±5.06 
0.178 
D1 
59.3±3.2 a 
56.5±5.76 a 
50.4±9.48 a 
99.2±10.21 b 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
61.9±6.71 a 
50.6±5.01 ab 
43.6±8.75 b 
100.1±10.92 c 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
60.4±9.04 a 
47.6±4.71 ab 
41.2±7.8 b 
107.9±13.48 c 
&lt;0.001 
Walking 
Baseline 
34.1±9.37 
39.1±9.08 
37.0±10.11 
37.0±8.65 
0.699 
D1 
50.3±7.53 a 
36.4±4.1 b 
27.7±4.16 c 
87.5±13.12 d 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
48.8±4.08 a 
22.6±4.4 b 
22.4±4.36 b 
89.0±8.03 c 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
31±4.15 a 
23.9±3.67 a 
17.0±3.5 b 
72.1±9.09 c 
&lt;0.001 
Jumping 
Baseline 
10.1±2.23 
10.6±3.36 
11.8±3.89 
10.0±3.43 
0.593 
D1 
16.1±2.45 a 
12.6±2.41 a 
11.9±2.65 a 
20.9±1.85 b 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
18.3±3.7 a 
12.5±1.93 b 
10.8±1.95 b 
21.2±1.51 a 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
16.8±2.83 a 
10.1±1.09 b 
8.1±1.53 b 
22.8±5.04 c 
&lt;0.001 
Walking slow 
Baseline 
21.1±3.70 
19.5±5.73 
17.1±5.30 
18.0±4.51 
0.776 
D1 
51.1±6.96 
49.1±5.76 
46.5±9.2 
55.3±4.9 
0.3 
D3 
48.2±7.05 
45.9±5.01 
44.7±9.14 
53.0±6.22 
0.33 
D5 
48±6.49 
45.1±5.39 
43.7±5.71 
52.2±7.01 
0.179 
Twitching 
Baseline 
15.0±3.01 
17.4±2.91 
14.8±1.85 
15.6±2.62 
0.150 
D1 
51.9±6.91 ab 
61.1±8.22 a 
64.6±7.77 a 
40.1±9.82 b 
0.001 
D3 
47.8±9.08 a 
68.0±5.66 b 
73.9±7.51 b 
36.0±5.04 a 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
36±5.84 a 
101.7±15.62 b 
106.2±11.28 b 
26.8±5.42 a 
&lt;0.001 
Remaining low 
Baseline 
49.0±13.75 
56.7±17.93 
56.9±16.92 
53.1±19.21 
0.698 
D1 
399.8±20.09 a 
418.7±54.11 a 
421.9±58.2 a 
181.0±49.88 b 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
351.8±50.97 a 
423.6±42.77 ab 
438.3±31.89 b 
175.6±42.9 c 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
398.9±30.84 a 
471.1±65.86 ab 
492.3±67.89 b 
229.5±32.04 c 
&lt;0.001 
Sleeping 
Baseline 
87.6±14.77 
78.3±7.31 
82.8±13.57 
83.4±13.99 
0.456 
D1 
699.8±102.83 ac 
1101.5±271.2 ab 
1215.2±357.9 b 
509.7±64.79 c 
0.001 
D3 
719.7±148.45 a 
1366.2±209.97 b 
1466.5±210.69 b 
486.2±65.56 a 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
937.0±95.41 a 
1303.8±206.5 b 
1496.5±202.86 b 
624.9±117.77 a 
&lt;0.001 
Drinking 
Baseline 
6.7±2.35 
5.8±1.56 
6.0±2.16 
7.6±2.99 
0.288 </p>

<p>Continued </p>

<p>Original paper </p>

<p>Pei P, et al. Acupunct Med 2016;34:127-135. doi:10.1136/acupmed-2015-010840 </p>



<p>decreased grooming behaviour, which suggests that 
cutaneous allodynia and central sensitisation were 
attenuated. </p>

<p>A possible mechanism underlying the effects of EA 
pretreatment </p>

<p>We found that EA at GB20 reversed c-Fos immunor-
eactivity changes in migraine-related brain areas (com-
pared to the Model group). These results provide </p>

<p>neurophysiological support for the assertion that the 
effects of acupuncture pretreatment are mediated via 
the regulation of imbalances in the descending pain 
modulatory system. 
c-Fos is a protein marker of neuronal activation that 
has been used in diverse nociception research, includ-
ing migraine. 23 The TNC, which receives input from 
peripheral sensory nerves, is the second-order neuron 
of the trigeminovascular system. Activation of the </p>

<p>Table 1 Continued </p>

<p>EA 
SA 
Model 
Control 
p Value </p>

<p>D1 
50.3±4.86 a 
49.0±5.75 a 
48.1±3.89 a 
97.5±8.25 b 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
39.3±4.9 a 
37.8±4.41 a 
33.7±3.83 a 
96.5±7.45 b 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
43.8±3.24 a 
27.1±3.56 b 
24.6±3.08 b 
108.9±13.28 c 
&lt;0.001 
Eating 
Baseline 
2.2±1.52 
2.7±1.97 
2.7±1.71 
2.8±1.79 
0.879 
D1 
2.9±0.57 a 
1.7±0.35 b 
1.4±0.34 b 
4.2±0.94 c 
&lt;0.001 
D3 
2.3±0.31 a 
1.7±0.36 ab 
1.5±0.31 b 
5.2±0.71 a 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
2.2±0.22 a 
1.0±0.2 b 
0.8±0.09 b 
4.5±0.48 c 
&lt;0.001 
Grooming 
Baseline 
79.9±12.56 
73.0±16.46 
69.2±17.65 
77.7±15.4 
0.413 
D1 
899.8±63.37 a 
1054.8±121.15 ab 
1083.7±128.2 b 
797.6±85.31 b 
0.001 
D3 
896±47.72 ac 
1036.9±108.54 ab 
1077.9±121.86 b 
775.1±49.01 c 
&lt;0.001 
D5 
910.9±94.07 ab 
1041.1±152.53 a 
1115.4±161.76 a 
783.9±50.06 b 
0.004 
Data are time spent per behaviour per hour (s/h) and are expressed as mean±SD. 
Overall p values are for overall (one-way) analysis of variance comparing across the four groups at each individual time point. Mean values within a row 
with unlike superscripts (a, b and c) are significantly different (p&lt;0.05) on post-hoc testing using Bonferroni/Tanhame tests. 
EA, electroacupuncture; SA, sham acupuncture. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Immunocytochemical distribution of c-Fos positive cells in the periaqueductal grey (PAG) region (A) and numbers of 
positive cells per 100 μm 2 (B) in 40 rats that underwent implantation of electrodes followed by no stimulation (Control group, n=10) 
or repeated electrical dural stimulation (n=30) with no treatment (Model group, n=10), electroacupuncture pretreatment (EA group, 
n=10) or sham acupuncture pretreatment (SA group, n=10). Representative images show relatively sparse c-Fos labelling in the 
Control group (C) and EA group (F) and relatively intense c-Fos labelling in the SA group (D) and Model group (E). Scale bar=200 μm. 
Data are presented as mean±SD. ***p&lt;0.001 vs Control group. ### p&lt;0.001 vs Model group. ++ p&lt;0.01 vs SA group. Aq, 
aqueduct (Sylvius); Dk: nucleus of Darkschewitsch.; dlf, dorsal longitudinal fasciculus. </p>

<p>Original paper </p>



<p>Pei P, et al. Acupunct Med 2016;34:127-135. doi:10.1136/acupmed-2015-010840 </p>

<p>TNC is regarded as a standard for activation and sen-
sitisation of the trigeminovascular system and a reli-
able marker for the successful establishment of </p>

<p>experimental models of headache. 23-25 Meanwhile, 
TNC inhibition has proven to be predictive of thera-
peutic anti-migraine efficacy. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Immunocytochemical distribution of c-Fos positive cells in the raphe magnus nucleus (RMg) region (A) and numbers of 
positive cells per 100 μm 2 (B) in 40 rats that underwent implantation of electrodes followed by no stimulation (Control group, n=10) 
or repeated electrical dural stimulation (n=30) with no treatment (Model group, n=10), electroacupuncture pretreatment (EA group, 
n=10) or sham acupuncture pretreatment (SA group, n=10). Representative images show relatively sparse c-Fos labelling in the 
Control group (C) and EA group (F) and relatively intense c-Fos labelling in the SA group (D) and Model group (E). Scale bar=200 μm. 
Data are presented as mean±SD. *p&lt;0.05 vs Control group. ###p&lt;0.001 vs Model group. +++p&lt;0.001 vs SA group. py, pyramidal 
cell layer of the hippocampus; RP, raphe pallidus nucleus. </p>

<p>Figure 4 Immunocytochemical distribution of c-Fos positive cells in the trigeminal nucleus caudalis (TNC) region (A) and numbers of 
positive cells per 100 μm 2 (B) in 40 rats that underwent implantation of electrodes followed by no stimulation (Control group, n=10) or 
repeated electrical dural stimulation (n=30) with no treatment (Model group, n=10), electroacupuncture pretreatment (EA group, n=10) or 
sham acupuncture pretreatment (SA group, n=10). Representative images show relatively sparse c-Fos labelling in the Control group (C) 
and EA group (F) and relatively intense c-Fos labelling in the SA group (D) and Model group (E). Scale bar=200 μm. Data are presented as 
mean±SD. ***p&lt;0.001, versus Control group. ###p&lt;0.001 vs Model group. +p&lt;0.05 vs SA group. pyx, pyramidal decussation. </p>

<p>Original paper </p>

<p>Pei P, et al. Acupunct Med 2016;34:127-135. doi:10.1136/acupmed-2015-010840 </p>



<p>Numerous investigations over the past half-century 
have established that the descending pain modulatory 
system arises in the brainstem from the PAG-rostral 
ventrolateral medulla (RVM) circuit to the spinal and 
medullary dorsal horn, and can exert bidirectional 
effects leading to both inhibition and facilitation of 
pain. 22 26 Electrophysiological studies by Fields and 
colleagues 27 have demonstrated that there are two dis-
tinct groups of RVM neurons producing opposite 
pain modulatory effects: (1) 'on'-cells mediating inhib-
ition; and (2) 'off '-cells mediating facilitation. 
On-cells and off-cells form the neural basis for bidir-
ectional control by the RVM and imbalance between 
these two cells types is implicated in the pathogenesis 
and progression of pain disorders, including migraine. 
For migraine, the descending pain modulatory 
pathway that is mainly involved is believed to be the 
PAG-RMg circuit to the TNC. The RMg is one of the 
important pain modulatory nuclei in the RVM region. 
On-cells and off-cells of the RMg project descending 
fibres to the TNC, suppressing or enhancing transmis-
sion of peripheral nociceptive information to the 
higher brain structures. 5 22 
In agreement with previous studies, 25 28 our results 
showed significant increases in c-Fos immunoreactivity 
within the PAG, RMg, and TNC after repeated dural 
stimulation, supporting the notion that activation of 
the PAG-RMg pathway in the descending pain modu-
latory system contributes to migraine pathophysiology 
through impaired descending inhibition and/or 
enhanced descending facilitation. 22 Pretreatment with 
EA strikingly decreased c-Fos immunoreactivity within 
these structures. The alterations in c-Fos expression 
and positive behavioural changes in the EA group may 
reflect either an improvement of impaired descending 
inhibition 
and 
an 
enhancement 
of 
anti-
nociception─that is, decreased descending pain facili-
tation (through inhibition of off-cells) and/or 
increased descending pain inhibition (through facilita-
tion of on-cells). This supports previous experimental 
work suggesting that acupuncture analgesia is 
mediated in part by the descending pain modulatory 
system. 29 </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
Our study has shown that EA pretreatment at GB20 
can attenuate behavioural responses to electrical 
stimulation of the dura in a rat model of recurrent 
migraine and can mitigate the increased expression of 
c-Fos neurons within the PAG, RMg, and TNC that is 
characteristic of this model. Overall, this evidence 
supports the idea that EA pretreatment can ameliorate 
migraine-like symptoms by altering the descending 
pain modulatory system; however, further molecular 
and electrophysiological studies are required to better 
understand the central mechanisms of EA treatment 
of migraine. </p>

<p>Contributors PP and LPZ conducted the experiments. PP and 
LL interpreted the data and wrote the manuscript. YXC and 
ZYQ revised the manuscript. LPW supervised the research 
programme and contributed to integration of the research team. 
All authors have read and approved the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This study was supported by the Ministry of Science 
and Technology of the People's Republic of China (grant 
number: Major State Basic Research Development Program 
2014CB543203), Beijing Natural Science Foundation 
(7154205) and Beijing Municipal Administration of Hospitals 
Clinical Medicine Development of Special Funding Support 
(ZYLX201412). </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally 
peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in 
accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non 
Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to 
distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different 
terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use 
is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/4.0/ </p>



<p>Original paper </p>



<p>Pei P, et al. Acupunct Med 2016;34:127-135. doi:10.1136/acupmed-2015-010840 </p>





</text></tei>