<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4093824" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Poultry industry, in the process of rapid industrialization, 
developed commercial chicken strains from a small number 
of breeds. To increase the productivity of native chickens, 
they were bred for economic traits. Although this process 
resulted in higher productivity, at the same time it decreased 
genetic diversity (Tadano et al., 2007). In recent years, it 
has become increasingly important to protect national 
endemic genetic resources and use local breeds to create 
commercial strains that can adapt to the changing 
environment. 
In Korea, the National Institute of Animal Science 
(NIAS) has been studying the process of indigenization of 
foreign breeds in to Korea and methods to restore Korean 
native chicken breeds. Korean native chickens (KNCs) as 
defined by NIAS in 2008 are chickens that have been bred 
true for at least seven generations. The commercial KNC 
called Woorimatdag (WR CC) was developed by crossing 
three native chicken breeds (Heo et al., 2011). </p>

<p>Woorimatdag has contributed to the industrialization of 
KNCs because of its rapid growth and the texture of the 
meat in comparison to the native chickens (Park, 2010). 
However, the use KNC H strain in the paternal line to create 
Woorimatdag has led to the decrease in plumage uniformity. 
Unlike typical white broilers, KNCs usually have colored 
feathers and various pigmentation patterns. Plumage color 
is an important factor that is used by consumers to 
distinguish between KNC strains. Although plumage color 
is easily observed, the genetics behind the feather coloration 
is governed by both qualitative and quantitative features 
(Klungland and Vage, 2000). In chickens, mutations in 
MC1R and TYR genes have been shown to be associated 
with feather pigmentation (Kerje et al., 2003; Liu et al., 
2010). However, there is a lack of research on the genetics 
of plumage coloration in Korean chicken at the genome-
wide scale. The purpose of this study is to characterize the 
genetic polymorphism underlying different plumage color 
using the chicken 60K SNP chip through GWAS (genome-
wide association study) and to increase plumage color 
uniformity of Woorimatdag. The results will also be used 
for selecting and breeding KNC H strain. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Sample and phenotype collection, and genotyping 
A total of 274 samples from four KNC strains were 
collected from NIAS. It comprised of 245 KNC H strains </p>

<p>Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. </p>

<p>Vol. 26, No. 11 : 1523-1528 November 2013 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5713/ajas.2013.13413 </p>

<p>www.ajas.info </p>

<p>pISSN 1011-2367 eISSN 1976-5517 </p>

<p>Genome-wide Association Study of Chicken Plumage Pigmentation </p>

<p>Mi Na Park, Jin Ae Choi, Kyung-Tai Lee, Hyun-Jeong Lee, Bong-Hwan Choi, Heebal Kim 1 , 
Tae-Hun Kim, Seoae Cho 2 , and Taeheon Lee 1, * 
Division of Animal Genomics and Bioinformatics, National Institute of Animal Science, 
Rural Development Administration, Suwon, Korea </p>

<p>ABSTRACT: To increase plumage color uniformity and understand the genetic background of Korean chickens, we performed a </p>

<p>genome-wide association study of different plumage color in Korean native chickens. We analyzed 60K SNP chips on 279 chickens with 
GEMMA methods for GWAS and estimated the genetic heritability for plumage color. The estimated heritability suggests that plumage 
coloration is a polygenic trait. We found new loci associated with feather pigmentation at the genome-wide level and from the results 
infer that there are additional genetic effect for plumage color. The results will be used for selecting and breeding chicken for plumage 
color uniformity. (Key Words: Chicken, Plumage Pigmentation, Genome-wide Association Study) </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author: Taeheon Lee. Tel: +82-2-880-4822, 
Fax: +82-2-883-8812, E-mail: taeheon@snu.ac.kr 
1 Department of Agricultural Biotechnology, Animal Biotechnology 
Major, and Research Institute for Agriculture and Life Sciences, 
Seoul National University, Seoul 151-742, Korea. 
2 C&amp;K genomics, Seoul National University Research Park, Seoul 
151-919, Korea. </p>

<p>Submitted Jul. 10, 2013; Accepted Sept. 4, 2013; Revised Oct. 10, 2013 </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 26:1523-1528 </p>

<p>
(KNCH), 9 KNC S stains (KNCS), 9 KNC R stains 
(KNCR), and 11 KNC L strains (KNCL). The plumage 
colors of these strains range from black, black with brown, 
brown, red-brown, and black. KNC H strain chickens can 
have black to black and brown plumage and the individuals 
were classified into seven categories according to the 
number of body parts it exhibited brown plumage. Plumage 
color was scored for six specific body parts: head, neck, 
breast, back, wings, and tail. If the individual only had 
black feather, it was given a score of zero, however, if an 
individual showed brown plumage, for every body part it 
had brown it received 1 point. This classified the 
individuals into seven categories, ranging from all black to 
brown in all scored body parts. Blood samples were 
collected in EDTA tubes and DNA was extracted using 
Wizard genomic DNA purification kit (Promega, USA) 
according to the manufacturer's instruction. The genomic 
DNA samples were genotyped using the 60K SNP Illumina 
iSelect chicken array (Illumina Inc., USA). </p>

<p>Genome-wide association test 
The 60K SNP Illumina iSelect chicken array contains 
57,637 SNPs that are distributed across the chicken genome. 
SNPs were excluded if it had a missing rate of &gt;5%, a 
minor allele frequency (MAF) of &lt;0.01, or a Hardy-
Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) test p-value of &lt;10 -6 using 
PLINK 1.07 (Purcell et al., 2007). After the quality control, 
53,257 SNPs were retained for further analysis. GWAS 
analyses on plumage coloration of whole body and the body 
parts traits were performed using mixed model of <rs id="software-5" type="software">GEMMA</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">v0.93</rs>) (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Zhou and Stephens</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-date">2012</rs>), which accounts for 
population stratification and sample structure. </p>

<p>y = W+x+u+, 
u~MVN n (0, -1 K), ~MVNn (0, -1 I n ) </p>

<p>Where y is an n-vector of traits (plumage coloration) for 
n individuals; W = (w 1 , w 2 , … ,w c ) is an nc matrix of 
covariates (fixed effects) including a column of 1s;  is a c-
vector of the corresponding coefficients including the 
intercept; x is an n-vector of marker genotypes;  is the 
effect size of the marker; u is an n-vector of random effects; 
 is an n-vector of errors;  -1 is the variance of the residual </p>

<p>errors;  is the ratio between the two variance components; 
K is a known nn relatedness matrix and I n is an nn 
identity matrix. MVN n denotes the n-dimensional 
multivariate normal distribution. Relatedness matrix K was 
calculated as following: </p>

<p>T 
i 
n 
i </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>i 
n 
i </p>

<p>x 
x 
x 
x 
p 
) 
1 
)( 
1 
( 
1 
K </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p>  </p>

<p> </p>

<p>x i as its ith column representing genotypes of ith SNP, </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>x as the sample mean, and 1 n as a n1 vector of 1's. </p>

<p><rs type="software">GEMMA</rs> tests the alternative hypothesis H 1 :0 against the 
null hypothesis H 0 : = 0 for each SNP. To correct for 
multiple hypothesis testing, we obtained adjusted p values 
by using the Benjamini and Hochberg false discovery rate 
procedure (Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995), adjusted 
p-value 0.2 significance level is used. An overview of the 
test results was shown as a Manhattan plot constructed by 
the statistical package R. Base pair position of SNP markers 
were given based on the chicken genome assembly build 
WASHUC2. Inflation factor was calculated by the R 
package <rs id="software-3" type="software">GenABEL</rs> with "median" option (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Aulchenko et al.</rs>., </p>

<p>2007). </p>

<p>Estimating genetic variance 
We estimated the genetic variance of plumage by using 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">GCTA</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Yang et al.</rs>., <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2011</rs>). After calculating the genetic 
relationship matrix (GRM) between all pairs of samples 
using all the autosomal SNPs, we estimated the genetic 
component, or heritability, for each trait by REML analysis 
of an Mixed Linear Model y = X+g G +, where y is a 
vector of phenotypes,  is a vector of fixed effect such as 
sex, age with its incidence matrix X, g G is a vector of 
aggregate SNP effects as random effect with </p>

<p>2 
G 
G 
G </p>

<p>A 
= 
) 
(g 
Var </p>

<p> , and A G is the GRM estimated from all </p>

<p>autosomal SNPs. We defined heritability or the proportion 
of variance explained by all autosomal SNPs as </p>

<p>2 
P </p>

<p>2 
G </p>

<p>2 
G </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
h 
. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Plumage color of KNC H strain 
Each of the 245 KNC (H strain) was investigated 
individually for plumage coloration (Figure 1). The 
predominant plumage color of KNC H strain chickens was 
black, but 88 out of 245 had brown feathers in addition to 
the black. This mixing of brown plumage causes the 
uniformity of Woorimatdag to decrease. Plumage color was 
investigated in six body-parts: head, neck, breast, back, 
wings and tail. One point was given for each body part that 
showed brown plumage (Table 1). Out of the 207 KNC H 
strain hens, 157 hens only had black plumage color, while 
41 hens had brown plumage on the neck and 9 hens had 
brown plumage on both the head and neck. None of the 38 
KNC H strain roosters were pure black. 
Roosters and hens, respectively, have ZZ and ZW sex 
chromosome, which may be the cause of the differential 
plumage color between sexes. Sex-linked silver locus have 
been shown to control silver and wild type/gold color and 
interfere with the coloration of red (Gunnarsson et al., </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 26:1523-1528 </p>



<p>2007). This result is estimated to be associated with the 
difference in the color of the hen and rooster. It is possible 
that the sex-linked plumage coloration is related to the fact 
that rooster with colorful plumage has an advantage when it 
comes to mating success (Brawner III et al., 2000). </p>

<p>The SNPs associated with feather pigmentation 
The genome-wide association study revealed 12 
significantly associated SNPs that surpassed the 
significance level (Figure 2, Table 2). As genomic inflation 
factor is 0.987, it can be concluded that the GWAS result is 
not inflated by considering relatedness using <rs type="software">GEMMA</rs> 
(Figure 3). Among the significant SNPs, we identified 4 
susceptibility SNPs: rs14339964 (Gga3:36327458, p = 4.07 
10 -9 ), GGaluGA344987 (Gga3:705798, p = 1.1210 -6 ), </p>

<p>rs14641648 (Gga8:12987908, p = 2.0610 -6 ), and </p>

<p>GGaluGA193591 (Gga24:5696828, p = 2.3810 -6 ) in the 
population (Table 2). SNP rs14339964 at Gga3:36327458 is 
located in an intron region of AKT3 which is known to be 
regulators of cell signaling in response to insulin and 
growth factors and involved in a wide variety of biological 
processes. AKT3 is one of the key genes in the formation of 
melanoma cells (Tsao et al., 2012). Previous studies 
reported that through gene-environment interactions 
pigmentation pathways can contribute to the formation for 
melanoma and tumours (Gudbjartsson et al., 2008; Ibarrola-
Villava et al., 2012). Thus, we indirectly infer that AKT3 
mutations may be related to plumage pigmentation. Both 
SNPs, GGaluGA344987 at Gga3:705798 and rs14641648 at 
Gga8:12987908, are located in an intergenic region around 
KRT7 and PAP2 which are associated with pigmentation. 
PAP2 is another name of LPPR5 which has been found to </p>

<p>Table 1. Plumage color pattern of KNC H strain 
Feather color 
Point 
Number of chickens 
Head 
Neck 
Back 
Breast 
Wings 
Tail 
---------------------------------------------------Male --------------------------------------------
0 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 
3 
0 
1 
1 
0 
0 
0 
2 
2 
1 
1 
0 
0 
1 
0 
3 
9 
1 
1 
1 
0 
0 
0 
3 
1 
1 
1 
1 
0 
1 
0 
4 
14 
1 
1 
1 
0 
1 
0 
4 
4 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
0 
5 
5 
-----------------------------------------------------Female ------------------------------------------
Shank color 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
157 
0 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
41 
1 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
9 </p>

<p>Feather color: 0 = black, 1 = black+brown. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Example of plumage coloring in chicken. (a) (b) female, (c) (d) male. </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 26:1523-1528 </p>

<p>
increase pigmentation (Shan et al., 2009). KRT7 is a 
member of the keratin gene family and is related with 
melanocytic tumors (Blum et al., 2010). DDX6 encodes a 
member of the DEAD box protein family, which has 
multiple functions including translation suppression and 
mRNA degradation (Weston and Sommerville, 2006). 
DDX6 is a previously confirmed gene for vitiligo which is a 
disease related with pigmentation of skin (Tang et al., 2012). 
Interestingly, although rs15175679 (Gga20: 8397089, p = 
3.9110 -6 ) is not significant, the variant exits in gga-mir-
668 which is a region that harbors a small RNA. Previous 
studies of chicken embryogenesis has shown that this small 
RNA regulates developmental signaling pathways (Shao et 
al., 2012). The results of GWAS of head plumage, wing 
plumage, breast plumage, back plumage, neck plumage and </p>

<p>tail plumage traits, separately identified the same SNPs: 
rs14339964 and rs15616451 (near gene: AKT3, 
ENSGALG00000020136) as the result of GWAS with the 
whole body trait. Through the concordant result, we infer 
that quantitative analysis of whole body plumage is not a 
simple trait (Table 3). 
The feather pigmentation related genes including MC1R, 
TYR, PMEL, MLPH, ASIP, SOX10, and SLC34A2 are well 
known. However, the related loci of these genes were not 
found in this study. The chicken 60K SNP chip does not 
contain SNPs of the MC1R region, and so we could not 
identify the effects of MC1R in this study. The results of 
this study are nevertheless meaningful in that novel loci 
affecting pigmentation at genome-wide level were found. 
Estimated genetic heritability was 18.2%, but estimated </p>

<p>Table 2. Top SNPs associated with plumage coloration </p>

<p>rs 
CHR 
Position 
Min 
/Maj 1 
Freq 
Beta 
SE 
p value 
Q value* gG SNP** 
Gene 
Location </p>

<p>rs15304667 
1 
70248953 
G/A 
0.0623 1.221 
0.230 
2.66E-07 
0.014 
0.143 
STK38L 
Intron 
rs15408789 
1 
125252900 
G/A 
0.115 
0.548 
0.116 
3.58E-06 
0.186 
0.112 
AP1S2 
Intergenic 
GGaluGA172731 
2 
149522175 
G/A 
0.421 
1.180 
0.244 
2.43E-06 
0.126 
0.575 
ENSGALG000 
00018081 </p>

<p>Intergenic </p>

<p>rs14339964 
3 
36327458 
A/C 
0.210 
1.186 
0.194 
4.70E-09 
0.000 
0.394 
AKT3 
Intron 
GGaluGA239670 
3 
110847381 
G/A 
0.206 
1.366 
0.241 
4.50E-08 
0.002 
0.447 
TFAP2B 
Intergenic 
rs15616451 
4 
75015502 
A/G 
0.053 
0.597 
0.125 
3.30E-06 
0.171 
0.060 
ENSGALG000 
00020136 </p>

<p>Intergenic </p>

<p>rs16445392 
4 
85858579 
A/C 
0.025 
0.908 
0.186 
1.85E-06 
0.096 
0.044 
MXD4 
Intron 
rs15790835 
6 
19031740 
A/C 
0.132 
1.087 
0.227 
2.89E-06 
0.150 
0.249 
ENSGALG000 
00005969 </p>

<p>Intergenic </p>

<p>rs14641648 
8 
12987908 
A/G 
0.115 
1.165 
0.239 
2.06E-06 
0.107 
0.237 
PAP2 
Intron 
rs15047928 
19 
5092926 
A/G 
0.329 
1.325 
0.251 
2.87E-07 
0.015 
0.585 
FAM211A 
Intron 
GGaluGA193591 
24 
5696828 
G/A 
0.121 
1.162 
0.240 
2.38E-06 
0.123 
0.247 
DDX6 
Intron 
GGaluGA344987 
E22C19 
W28 </p>

<p>705798 
G/A 
0.287 
1.110 
0.222 
1.12E-06 
0.058 
0.454 
KRT7 
Intergenic </p>

<p>1 Minor allele/Major allele. * Adjusted p value. ** Estimated variance. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Manhattan plot of GWAS result. GWAS for the integrated phenotypes using Illumina chicken 60K SNP BeadChip of 274 
samples. The x-axis of the Manhattan plot shows the genomic position, the y-axis represents the log10 base transformed p-values, 
Benjamini and Hochberg false discovery rate procedure (Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995), the dashed line show significance level of 
adjusted p&lt;0.2. </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 26:1523-1528 </p>



<p>genetic heritability of significant SNPs was 3.1%. The 
results support a polygenic effect in feather pigmentation. 
This means previously reported genes MC1R, TYR, PMEL, 
MLPH, ASIP, SOX10, and SLC34A2 as well as the reported 
loci in this study are important in plumage coloration. The 
results may contribute to selecting and breeding of KNC H 
for plumage color uniformity. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The work was supported by a grant from the AGENDA </p>

<p>project (No. PJ907057) in the National Institute of Animal 
Science, Rural Development Administration (RDA), 
Republic of Korea. </p>



<p>Table 3. Top SNPs associated with plumage coloration by each part </p>

<p>Plumage 
part 
rs ID 
CHR 
Position 
Min 
/Maj 1 
Freq 
Beta 
SE 
p value 
Q value* 
Gene 
Location </p>

<p>Head 
rs14398623 
3 
97933258 
A/G 
0.115 
-0.149 
0.030 
1.56E-06 
0.081 
RNF144A 
Intron 
rs318020030 
7 
19055437 
A/G 
0.350 
0.220 
0.045 
1.79E-06 
0.093 
PPP1R9B 
Intron 
rs16669242 
9 
14516013 
A/C 
0.296 
0.235 
0.041 
2.74E-08 
0.001 
FGF12 
Intergenic 
GGaluGA105119 
14 
14228307 
G/A 
0.321 
0.154 
0.032 
2.76E-06 
0.144 
ENSGALG000 
00023628 </p>

<p>Intergenic </p>

<p>rs14112979 
18 
7210201 
G/A 
0.341 
0.219 
0.042 
3.26E-07 
0.017 
HELZ 
Intron 
Wing 
rs13982792 
1 
1.83E+08 
A/G 
0.463 
0.153 
0.033 
3.48E-06 
0.181 
XPO4 
Intron 
rs14131527 
2 
4895894 
A/G 
0.346 
0.114 
0.022 
4.14E-07 
0.022 
XIRP1 
Intron 
rs14188826 
2 
59639362 
A/G 
0.058 
0.163 
0.034 
2.70E-06 
0.140 
PRL 
Intergenic 
rs14339964 
3 
36327458 
A/C 
0.210 
0.146 
0.029 
1.19E-06 
0.062 
AKT3 
Intron 
rs14404313 
3 
103537929 
C/A 
0.146 
0.203 
0.036 
3.75E-08 
0.002 
NT5C1B 
Intergenic 
GGaluGA110134 
15 
9605683 
G/A 
0.333 
0.175 
0.037 
3.52E-06 
0.184 
MSI1 
Intron 
rs15027075 
17 
10503821 
A/G 
0.357 
0.111 
0.023 
2.70E-06 
0.141 
PBX3 
Intron 
Breast 
rs14316836 
3 
7925459 
G/A 
0.293 
0.062 
0.013 
2.49E-06 
0.129 
LCLAT1 
Intron 
Back 
rs14401050 
3 
100155987 
A/G 
0.204 
0.174 
0.036 
2.23E-06 
0.116 
E2F6 
Intergenic 
rs15616451 
4 
75015502 
A/G 
0.053 
0.118 
0.024 
1.71E-06 
0.089 
ENSGALG000 
00020136 </p>

<p>Intergenic </p>

<p>GGaluGA287070 
5 
49185847 
G/A 
0.393 
0.198 
0.038 
4.53E-07 
0.024 
VRK1 
Intergenic 
GGaluGA095084 
13 
11601056 
G/A 
0.082 
0.175 
0.033 
1.81E-07 
0.009 
SGCD 
Intron 
rs15022353 
15 
7826821 
A/G 
0.216 
0.178 
0.029 
1.84E-09 
9.56E-05 TTC28 
Intron 
1 Minor allele/Major allele. * Adjusted p value. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Quantile-Quantile plot of GWAS result Inflation factor (lambda) = 0.9877269. </p>

<p>Park et al. (2013) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 26:1523-1528 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>