<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4213536" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>cc This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Nationwide Survey of Patient Knowledge in Parkinson's Disease 
KMDS, et al. </p>

<p>www.e-jmd.org 85 </p>

<p>been used in an attempt to modify the natural his-
tory of PD. In addition to medications, stem cell 
therapy, complementary and alternative medicine 
(CAM), and physical exercise have been studied. 5-7 
Acupuncture is the most common non-pharmaco-
logical CAM that is used in PD. 8-12 Bee venom has 
been suggested as a potential neuroprotective agent 
based on its anti-inflammatory properties. 13,14 Fol-
lowing a clinical trial of bee venom acupuncture, 5 it 
has become a well-recognized experimental treat-
ment among PD patients and caregivers in Korea. 
Although clinical trials using stem cell therapy or 
bee venom acupuncture in PD have been per-
formed, well-designed controlled trials sufficient 
enough to reach the standards set by EBM are lack-
ing. 5,15-18 Despite the great interest in stem cell ther-
apy and the expectations for the widespread use of 
CAM in PD, 8-12,19 data on patient knowledge and 
attitudes towards experimental treatments are lack-
ing in the literature. Given that a majority of pa-
tients obtain information on experimental treat-
ments from the media or the internet rather than 
healthcare providers, 20,21 it is critical to understand 
the current level of understanding of experimental 
PD therapy in PD patients and their care givers. This 
information will aid in developing educational pro-
grams for patients and in guiding them toward evi-
dence-based practices. Therefore, we conducted a 
nationwide survey to study PD patients' understand-</p>

<p>ing of the safety, efficacy and evidence-based prac-
tice with regard to stem cell therapy or bee venom 
acupuncture and to gauge their willingness to re-
ceive experimental treatments. We also analyzed 
factors influencing their correct understanding of 
the current status of the above experimental treat-
ments. </p>

<p>MATERIALS &amp; METHODS </p>

<p>Since 2006, the Korean Movement Disorders So-
ciety (KMDS) has held annual nationwide cam-
paigns and lectures regarding PD ("Red Tulip Cam-
paign") to educate PD patients and caregivers in 
KMDS member hospitals. A survey of 1230 partici-
pants (PD patients and caregivers), organized by 
the KMDS, was performed at 44 sites from 48 sec-
ondary-or tertiary-referral hospitals in Korea from 
April 2, 2013 to June 14, 2013. No specific inclusion 
or exclusion criteria were applied, except that the 
patients were required to participate voluntarily 
and to be capable of answering the questionnaire. 
Trained interviewers collected demographic data 
from patients or caregivers and administered the 
12-item questionnaire in face-to-face interviews 
with the participants at each site. Participants an-
swered all questions with one of three answers (Yes, 
No, and Unknown). Demographic data included 
age, gender, PD duration, diagnosis of parkinsonian </p>

<p>Table 1. A questionnaire used to examine Parkinson's disease patient knowledge of and attitudes towards stem cell treatment and bee 
venom acupuncture </p>

<p>Item 
Questions </p>

<p>1 
Parkinson's disease is caused by a reduction in dopamine-producing neurons </p>

<p>2 
Parkinson's disease is the same disorder as Alzheimer's disease </p>

<p>3 
Parkinson's disease patients are improved by medical treatment including levodopa </p>

<p>4 
Late complications of Parkinson's disease can be improved by the surgical treatment deep brain stimulation </p>

<p>5 
Stem cell treatment for Parkinson's disease has been proven safe </p>

<p>6 
Stem cell treatment for Parkinson's disease has been proven efficacious </p>

<p>7 
Stem cell treatment for Parkinson's disease has been proven globally, and it is currently used as a standard therapy 
for Parkinson's disease </p>

<p>8 
Although stem cell treatment for Parkinson's disease is an experimental treatment without proof of safety and efficacy, 
I am willing to receive this experimental treatment if there is a chance </p>

<p>9 
Acupuncture with bee venom for the treatment of Parkinson's disease has been proven safe </p>

<p>10 
Acupuncture with bee venom for the treatment of Parkinson's disease has been proven efficacious </p>

<p>11 
Acupuncture with bee venom for the treatment of Parkinson's disease has been proven globally, and it is currently used as 
a standard therapy for Parkinson's disease </p>

<p>12 
Although acupuncture with bee venom for the treatment of Parkinson's disease is an experimental treatment without proof 
of safety and efficacy, I am willing to receive this experimental treatment if there is a chance </p>



<p>J Mov Disord 2014;7(2):84-91 </p>

<p>JMD </p>

<p>disorders, years of education, and the most disabling 
symptoms. Survey questionnaires developed by the 
executive committee of the KMDS was comprised 
of three parts (Table 1). The first section of the ques-
tionnaire (4 questions) was designed to estimate the 
participant's knowledge of the pathogenesis and the 
medical and surgical treatments available for PD. 
The second section (3 questions) covered the safety 
and efficacy of stem cell therapy, and whether stem 
cell therapy was used worldwide as an evidence-
based practice. Questions in the final section were 
similar to those in the second section, except that 
the questions referred to bee venom acupuncture 
treatment rather than stem cell therapy. Two ques-
tions asked the participants whether they were will-
ing to receive stem cell therapy or bee venom acu-
puncture treatment despite the fact that they were 
not safe, effective or acknowledged as a standard 
treatment around the world. For all questions, par-
ticipants answered using the responses yes, no, or 
unknown. Other demographic data, such as age 
upon participation in the survey, gender, duration 
of PD, years of education, category of PD diagnosis 
and the most disabling symptom, were also collect-
ed in parallel. The categories of PD diagnosis com-
prised PD, Parkinson plus syndrome, and an un-
known diagnostic parkinsonism category. The most 
disabling symptoms included tremor, rigidity, bra-
dykinesia, postural instability (falls), gait distur-
bance, and others. 
Statistical analyses were performed after convert-
ing participant responses into correct, incorrect, </p>

<p>and unknown responses. The degree of accuracy of 
the understanding of PD between patients and care-
givers was compared using chi-squared tests. Fac-
tors affecting an accurate understanding of PD 
treatment were analyzed using univariate logistic 
regression analyses. All statistical analyses were per-
formed using the <rs type="software">SAS program</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The demographic data are summarized in Table 2. 
Nine hundred and sixty three parkinsonian patients 
and 267 caregivers responded. Of the patients, 91.3% 
had PD, 4.5% had Parkinson plus syndrome, and 
4.3% did not know whether they had PD or PD plus 
syndrome. The mean age of the patients was 69.8 ± 
7.9 years, and the mean duration of PD was 4.4 ± 4.2 
years. The mean duration of education was 11.1 
years. In approximately two-thirds of patients, 
tremor or postural instability and gait disturbances 
were the most disabling symptoms. Other non-mo-
tor symptoms including memory decline, dizziness/ 
giddiness, and musculoskeletal issues, such as back 
pain, anxiety or depressive mood, were considered 
the most disabling symptoms in 17.1% of patients. 
The mean number of correct answers in the first 
section of the survey questionnaire, which collected 
information regarding the participants' general 
knowledge of Parkinson's disease, was 2.3 ± 1.2 for 
PD patients and 2.5 ± 1.2 for caregivers. The per-
cent of correct answers was highest for questions on 
dopamine deficits in PD, medical treatment of PD 
using dopaminergic drugs, discrimination of PD 
from Alzheimer's disease and surgical treatment of 
PD. The proportion of correct, incorrect and un-
known responses was similar between PD patients 
and caregivers for questions 1-3 (Figure 1). Howev-
er, more caregivers answered the question on surgi-
cal treatment of PD correctly than PD patients (p &lt; 
0.01, chi-squared test). Factors predicting correct 
answers for Q1-4 are summarized in Supplement 
Table 1 (in the online-only Data Supplement). 
Younger age-at-onset, higher levels of education, 
and a longer duration of disease were significant, 
independent predictors of correct answers for Q1, 
Q2, and Q4 but not for Q3. Logistic regression anal-
yses demonstrated that younger age-at-onset, longer 
periods of education and a longer duration of dis-
ease were significant, independent predictors of </p>

<p>Table 2. Demographic and clinical characteristics of the survey participants </p>

<p>Patient 
Caregiver </p>

<p>Survey participants, n (%) 
963 (78.4) 
267 (21.6) </p>

<p>Gender (M:F) 
580:383 
143:124 </p>

<p>Age (years), mean (SD) 
69.8 (7.9) 
64.9 (13.6) </p>

<p>PD duration (years), mean (SD) 
4.4 (4.2) </p>

<p>Diagnosis (PD:PD plus:unknown) 
879:43:41 </p>

<p>Education (year), mean (SD) 
11.1 (4.3) 
12.7 (4.7) </p>

<p>Most-disabling symptom* </p>

<p>Tremor, n (%) 
298 (30.9) </p>

<p>Gait disturbances/falls, n (%) 
325 (33.7) </p>

<p>Rigidity, n (%) 
111 (11.5) </p>

<p>Bradykinesia, n (%) 
182 (18.9) 
Others, n (%) 
165 (17.1) </p>

<p>*one hundred and thirty four patients responded with multiple answers that were the 
most-disabling symptom. PD: Parkinson's disease, SD: standard deviation. </p>

<p>Nationwide Survey of Patient Knowledge in Parkinson's Disease 
KMDS, et al. </p>

<p>www.e-jmd.org 87 </p>

<p>correct answers for all questions except question #3. 
A clinical diagnosis of atypical parkinsonism (Par-
kinson plus syndrome or unknown diagnostic cate-
gory of parkinsonism) was a significant predictor of 
incorrect answers for levodopa responsiveness in 
PD. Table 2 summarizes the logistic regression re-
sults of the factors predicting correct answers. 
With regard to questions on the safety and effica-
cy of treatment with stem cells or acupuncture with 
bee venom, 18.9-37.8% of PD patients answered 
correctly and 5.1-17.7% answered incorrectly. In-
triguingly, more than half of PD patients responded 
with "unknown". Despite the fact that the safety and 
efficacy have not been established, 55.5% of PD pa-
tients were willing to receive experimental treat-
ments with stem cells (Figure 2). PD patients showed 
a similar tendency of interest in experimental treat-
ments with acupuncture using bee venom. PD pa-
tients who were interested in stem cell therapy were 
also interested in receiving acupuncture treatment 
with bee venom (p &lt; 0.0001, odds ratio = 5.226, 95% 
confidence interval 3.919-6.969). 
We analyzed the factors associated with an accu-
rate understanding of experimental treatments by 
performing univariate logistic regression analyses of 
question items 5-12 (Table 3). Older age was associ-
ated with an incorrect understanding of experimen-
tal treatment with stem cells or bee venom acupunc-
ture. A higher level of education was associated with 
a correct understanding of the safety and efficacy of 
stem cell therapy. More PD plus patients answered 
questions on the efficacy of stem cell treatment in-
correctly than PD patients. A longer duration of PD 
was also associated with an improved understand-</p>

<p>ing of the safety of stem cell therapy, and whether it 
was an acknowledged treatment. This trend for an 
association between a correct understanding and 
higher education or longer duration of PD was sim-
ilar for questions regarding bee venom acupuncture 
treatment; however, statistical significance was found 
only for the associations between a safety question 
(Questions #9) and education and PD duration, and 
the acknowledgment of the experimental nature of 
stem cell therapy (Questions #11) and PD duration. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Bar graphs showing categories of answers to questions on the pathogenesis and treatment of Parkinson's disease in parkinso-
nian patients (A) and caregivers (B). Q1, Q2, Q3, and Q4 refer to the question items. Q1: Parkinson's disease is caused by a reduction in 
dopamine-producing neurons. Q2: Parkinson's disease is the same disorder as Alzheimer's disease. Q3: Parkinson's disease patients are 
improved by medical treatments including levodopa. Q4: Late complications of Parkinson's disease can be improved by surgical treatment 
via deep brain stimulation. </p>

<p>Correct </p>

<p>Incorrect </p>

<p>Unknown </p>

<p>Correct </p>

<p>Incorrect </p>

<p>Unknown 
72.9 </p>

<p>Q1 </p>

<p>2.2 </p>

<p>24.9 </p>

<p>Q1 </p>

<p>78.9 </p>

<p>1.9 
19.2 </p>

<p>(%) 
100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(%) 
100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
Q2 </p>

<p>55.5 </p>

<p>28.0 </p>

<p>16.5 </p>

<p>Q2 </p>

<p>62.4 </p>

<p>24.8 </p>

<p>12.8 </p>

<p>Q3 </p>

<p>66.6 </p>

<p>19.4 </p>

<p>14.0 </p>

<p>Q3 </p>

<p>65.1 </p>

<p>19.9 </p>

<p>15.0 </p>

<p>Q4 </p>

<p>35.2 </p>

<p>17.8 </p>

<p>47.0 </p>

<p>Q4 </p>

<p>45.5 </p>

<p>16.9 </p>

<p>37.6 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Figure 2. Bar graphs showing the categories of answers to questions on Par-
kinson's disease patient knowledge and attitude towards experimental treat-
ments. Q5 to Q12 refer to question items. Q5-8 focused on stem cell treatment, 
and Q9-12 focused on acupuncture using bee venom. Questions regarding 
safety (Q5 and Q9), efficacy (Q6 and Q10) and whether these treatments are 
used in evidence-based practice (Q7 and Q11) were also included. For Q8 and 
Q12, patients were asked whether they were interested in receiving experimen-
tal treatments despite a lack of evidence of the safety and efficacy for the given 
experimental treatment. </p>

<p>Yes 
No 
Unknown </p>

<p>Q5 </p>

<p>Q6 </p>

<p>Q7 </p>

<p>Q8 </p>

<p>Q9 </p>

<p>Q10 </p>

<p>Q11 </p>

<p>Q12 </p>

<p>0% 
20% 
40% 
60% 
80% 
100% </p>

<p>11.3 
27.6 
61.1 </p>

<p>17.7 
18.9 
63.4 </p>

<p>11.2 
24.2 
64.6 </p>

<p>55.3 
27.7 
17.0 </p>

<p>9.0 
37.8 
53.2 </p>

<p>7.8 
34.2 
58.0 </p>

<p>5.1 
34.6 
60.3 </p>

<p>42.0 
42.0 
16.0 </p>



<p>J Mov Disord 2014;7(2):84-91 </p>

<p>JMD </p>

<p>Patients with a longer duration of PD were more 
willing to receive stem cell therapy, but this associa-
tion was not found for acupuncture therapy with bee 
venom. Patients who complained that postural insta-
bility and gait disturbance and falls (PIGD) was the 
most disabling symptom were more willing to re-
ceive stem cell therapy. In contrast, only older age 
was associated with a willingness to be treated with 
acupuncture using bee venom. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, this study is the 
first to examine patient knowledge and attitudes to-
wards experimental treatments, specifically in a PD 
population. One can argue that, given the existence 
of several articles that support the safety and efficacy </p>

<p>of experimental treatments with stem cells or bee 
venom, the decision to judge answers as correct vs. 
incorrect might be misleading. However, we do not 
think that this approach was inappropriate because 
current evidence-based practice guidelines do not 
support the safety and efficacy of these experimen-
tal treatments. 1,2 
In our nationwide survey of PD patients and care-
givers, we observed that only approximately 10% of 
PD patients understood incorrectly that experimen-
tal treatments using stem cells or bee venom acu-
puncture were safe, efficacious or acknowledged as 
evidence-based treatments worldwide. However, 
more than half of patients responded to these ques-
tions with the term "unknown". Still, 55.3% and 42% 
of patients answered that they were willing to re-
ceive experimental treatments with stem cells or bee </p>

<p>Table 3. Factors associated with correct answers on questions of experimental PD treatments for patients with PD </p>

<p>Stem cell treatment 
Acupuncture with bee venom </p>

<p>Q5 
Q6 
Q7 
Q8 
Q9 
Q10 
Q11 
Q12 </p>

<p>Age 
0.95*** 
(0.94-0.97) </p>

<p>0.97** 
(0.95-0.99) </p>

<p>0.95*** 
(0.93-0.97) </p>

<p>0.98* 
(0.96-0.99) </p>

<p>0.97** 
(0.96-0.99) </p>

<p>0.98* 
(0.97-1.00) </p>

<p>0.98* 
(0.97-1.00) </p>

<p>0.97** 
(0.96-0.99) </p>

<p>Gender 
0.85 
(0.63-1.13) </p>

<p>0.99 
(0.71-1.38) </p>

<p>0.88 
(0.65-1.20) </p>

<p>0.95 
(0.73-1.24) </p>

<p>1.00 
(0.77-1.30) </p>

<p>1.05 
(0.81-1.37) </p>

<p>0.92 
(0.71-1.20) </p>

<p>0.93 
(0.71-1.21) </p>

<p>Education 
1.09*** 
(1.05-1.13) </p>

<p>1.07** 
(1.03-1.11) </p>

<p>1.12*** 
(1.08-1.17) </p>

<p>0.99 
(0.96-1.02) </p>

<p>1.05** 
(1.02-1.08) </p>

<p>1.02 
(0.99-1.05) </p>

<p>1.03 
(1.00-1.06) </p>

<p>1.01 
(0.98-1.04) </p>

<p>Diagnosis </p>

<p>PD plus vs. PD 
1.12 
(0.57-2.17) </p>

<p>0.30*** 
(0.09-0.99) </p>

<p>0.49 
(0.20-1.17) </p>

<p>1.23 
(0.66-2.30) </p>

<p>0.88 
(0.47-1.62) </p>

<p>0.65 
(0.34-1.24) </p>

<p>0.57 
(0.29-1.12) </p>

<p>1.06 
(0.57-1.97) </p>

<p>Unknown PDism 
vs. PD </p>

<p>0.39 
(0.15-1.01) </p>

<p>0.61 
(0.24-1.60) </p>

<p>0.68 
(0.29-1.56) </p>

<p>0.72 
(0.38-1.39) </p>

<p>0.65 
(0.33-1.27) </p>

<p>0.62 
(0.31-1.24) </p>

<p>0.76 
(0.38-1.51) </p>

<p>0.48 
(0.23-1.00) </p>

<p>PD duration 
1.05*** 
(1.01-1.08) </p>

<p>1.02 
(0.99-1.06) </p>

<p>1.06** 
(1.03-1.10) </p>

<p>1.06** 
(1.03-1.10) </p>

<p>1.06** 
(1.03-1.10) </p>

<p>1.03 
(1.00-1.06) </p>

<p>1.04* 
(1.01-1.08) </p>

<p>1.00 
(0.97-1.03) </p>

<p>Most-disabling symptom </p>

<p>Tremor 
0.95 
(0.69-1.29) </p>

<p>0.81 
(0.57-1.17) </p>

<p>0.85 
(0.61-1.17) </p>

<p>0.93 
(0.71-1.23) </p>

<p>0.93 
(0.71-1.23) </p>

<p>0.96 
(0.73-1.27) </p>

<p>0.92 
(0.69-1.22) </p>

<p>0.90 
(0.69-1.19) </p>

<p>Rigidity 
1.49 
(0.98-2.27) </p>

<p>1.14 
(0.70-1.86) </p>

<p>1.52 
(0.99-2.34) </p>

<p>0.95 
(0.64-1.41) </p>

<p>1.04 
(0.70-1.55) </p>

<p>1.15 
(0.78-1.72) </p>

<p>1.13 
(0.76-1.69) </p>

<p>0.82 
(0.55-1.24) </p>

<p>Bradykinesia 
1.17 
(0.82-1.67) </p>

<p>1.49* 
(1.01-2.19) </p>

<p>1.11 
(0.77-1.61) </p>

<p>1.07 
(0.77-1.48) </p>

<p>1.11 
(0.80-1.53) </p>

<p>1.05 
(0.76-1.45) </p>

<p>0.89 
(0.64-1.24) </p>

<p>0.99 
(0.71-1.37) </p>

<p>PIGD 
0.89 
(0.66-1.21) </p>

<p>0.99 
(0.70-1.39) </p>

<p>1.14 
(0.84-1.56) </p>

<p>1.48* 
(1.12-1.94) </p>

<p>0.98 
(0.75-1.28) </p>

<p>0.90 
(0.69-1.18) </p>

<p>0.93 
(0.71-1.22) </p>

<p>1.25 
(0.95-1.63) </p>

<p>Others 
0.63 
(0.42-0.95) </p>

<p>0.69 
(0.43-1.10) </p>

<p>0.62* 
(0.40-0.96) </p>

<p>0.64* 
(0.46-0.90) </p>

<p>0.76 
(0.54-1.07) </p>

<p>0.94 
(0.67-1.32) </p>

<p>0.99 
(0.70-1.39) </p>

<p>0.91 
(0.65-1.28) </p>

<p>Q5 to Q12 refer to question items. Q5-8 focused on stem cell treatments, and Q9-12 focused on acupuncture using bee venom. Briefly, questions 
were focused on safety (Q5 and Q9), efficacy (Q6 and Q10) and whether the experimental treatments were used in evidence-based practice (Q7 and 
Q11). In Q8 and Q12, patients were asked whether they were interested in receiving experimental treatments despite the lack of evidence of safety and 
efficacy of the given experimental treatment. Values are odds ratio with 95% confidence intervals in parenthesis. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.005, ***p &lt; 0.0001. 
PD: Parkinson's disease, Unknown PDism: diagnostic category of parkinsonism unknown, PIGD: postural instability and gait disturbance and falls, 
Others: other non-motor symptoms. </p>

<p>Nationwide Survey of Patient Knowledge in Parkinson's Disease 
KMDS, et al. </p>

<p>www.e-jmd.org 89 </p>

<p>venom acupuncture, respectively. This result can be 
compared to a recent study in which 46% of chronic 
ischemic stroke patients desired stem cell therapy 
despite its unknown side effects. 21 In our study, there 
was a high concordance in patients' willingness to 
receive either of the experimental treatments. In a 
cross-sectional study, Valadas et al. 22 noted that in 
PD, the primary motivation to participate in a clini-
cal trial was to advance science and gain access to 
better treatments. The major concern while partici-
pating in clinical trials was adverse events. In an-
other study, reasons to seek CAM included man-
agement of PD motor symptom (57.6%), fatigue 
(19.6%), pain (4.3%), constipation (5.4%), or no spe-
cific reason (13%). 8 These data suggest that a sizable 
proportion of patients with a chronic nervous sys-
tem disease wish to receive experimental treatments, 
even with the risk of adverse events. In this study, a 
younger age, higher education and a longer dura-
tion of PD were in general associated with a more 
accurate understanding of experimental treatments. 
These trends were also true for questions on PD eti-
ology and standard PD treatments. Education level 
was inversely associated with the use of CAM. 8,9 It 
was intriguing that although our patients with a 
longer duration of PD understood the safety issues 
surrounding stem cell therapy more accurately and 
whether it was an evidence-based practice, they were 
more willing to participate in clinical trials using 
stem cells. This finding is consistent with previous 
studies in chronic stroke patients in which a longer 
duration of disease was associated with patients' 
willingness to receive stem cell therapy and to use 
complementary and alternative medicine more fre-
quently. 8,21 This finding may be due to the failure of 
current symptomatic treatments to meet the patient's 
need to control motor or non-motor symptoms that 
may be resistant to levodopa in advanced PD. Addi-
tional contributing factors may also be the level of 
dissatisfaction with health-related quality of life or 
the lack of availability of disease-modifying treat-
ments. The fact that in our study, patients with dis-
abling PIGD were more interested in receiving ex-
perimental stem cell treatment supports this theory 
of unmet needs. Given the high expectations for ex-
perimental treatments with stem cells or bee venom 
acupuncture, it is critical to expect a substantial pla-
cebo effect when interpreting the results of a clinical 
trial evaluating a new therapeutic intervention for </p>

<p>PD. 23 In studying the neuroprotective effects of a 
pharmacological agent, considerable progress has 
been made in improving study designs to overcome 
symptomatic effects. 24,25 However, for clinical trials 
of non-pharmacological interventions, study de-
signs and the interpretation of results may be com-
plicated by many confounding variables, such as 
outcome measures, the appropriateness of the in-
tervention, control intervention or cultural back-
ground. 7,26,27 As suggested, strict guidelines encom-
passing ethical issues, regulatory control, study 
design, outcome measures, and specific analyses for 
clinical trials of non-pharmacological interventions 
are required for PD. 28 
There are limitations to this study. First, demo-
graphic and clinical data were collected from pa-
tients and not from physicians. This may have led to 
a coding bias, particularly in the diagnostic category. 
Secondly, our study may include a selection bias be-
cause data were collected from patients who attend-
ed KMDS PD educational campaigns. The high lev-
el of education in our participants reflects this factor. 
The small number of questions and our cross-sec-
tional design cannot explain why PD patients have 
false expectations of experimental treatments. More-
over, our questionnaire did not include questions 
about PD-related quality of life and level of satisfac-
tion with current treatment options, which are im-
portant when considering patients' decisions to seek 
therapeutic interventions. 
In conclusion, a small number of PD patients un-
derstand the safety and efficacy of stem cell treat-
ment or bee venom acupuncture and that it is not 
used as an evidence-based practice. Approximately 
half of the PD patients wished to participate in a 
clinical trial of an experimental treatment, despite 
having no data on the safety or efficacy of the thera-
py. We hope that our data will be used to educate or 
plan educational programs for PD patients and care-
givers. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>

<p>The online-only Data Supplement is available with 
this article at http://dx.doi.org/10.14802/jmd.14012. </p>

<p>KMDS Red Tulip Survey Participants </p>

<p>Dr. Tae-Beom Ahn (Kyunghee University Medical Center) 
Dr. Sang Myung Cheon (Dong-A University Hospital) </p>



<p>J Mov Disord 2014;7(2):84-91 </p>



<p>The authors have no financial conflicts of interest. </p>



</text></tei>