<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4700408" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The nucleotide-oligomerization domain (NOD) is an im-
portant molecule involved in host defense against bacterial 
infection. To study the role of NODs in the host response to 
Mycobacterium leprae, we measured the mRNA levels of 
NODs and related genes in infected mouse tissues. The 
mRNA expression of NOD1, NOD2, caspase-1 and ASC 
was increased in mouse footpads. Whereas NOD2 ex-
pression in macrophages was increased at 2 and 24 h 
post-infection with M. leprae, there was no expression of 
NOD1 at these time points. An increase in caspase-1 ex-
pression was observed at 2 h and continued at 24 h. 
However, the expression of ASC was increased only at the 
early time point. The expression of caspase-1 is regulated 
by NOD2-dependent pathway in established HEK 293. 
Our results suggest NOD2, rather than NOD1, may be as-
sociated with the host response to M. leprae and that cas-
pase-1 activation is essential for the host response. 
[Immune Network 2015;15(6):319-324] </p>

<p>Mycobacterium leprae is an intracellular pathogen that re-</p>

<p>sides and replicates in phagocytes such as macrophages. 
M. leprae can induce phagocytes to produce inflammatory 
cytokines, such as TNF-α and IL-12, which are involved 
in the control of bacterial replication and the coordination 
of adaptive immune responses (1,2). 
Pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) are essential com-
ponents for probing pathogen infection and evoking pro-
duction of pro-inflammatory cytokines in the innate im-
mune system. PRRs include toll-like receptors (TLRs), ret-
inoic acid-inducible gene I (RIG-I)-like receptors (RLRs) 
and nucleotide-binding and oligomerization domain (NOD)-
like receptors (NLRs) (3). NLRs are cytosolic receptors 
that are involved in manifold biological processes, includ-
ing host defense against pathogens (4,5). 
NOD1 and NOD2 are a subfamily of NLRs and their 
stimulation leads to activation of the nuclear transcription 
factor (NF)-κB, extracellular signal-regulated kinase 
(ERK) and Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK), which are known 
to be triggered by mycobacteria (6,7). This activation re-
sults in the expression of pro-inflammatory molecules that 
induce both innate and adaptive immune responses. NOD2 
also induces caspase-1 activation (8), which mediates the 
maturation of pro-IL-1β to its active form, IL-1β (9). 
NODs recognize bacterial molecules produced during 
the synthesis and degradation of peptidoglycan. In partic-</p>

<p>The Role of NOD2 in M. leprae Infection 
Tae Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 6: 319-324, December, 2015 </p>

<p>
ular, NOD2 is activated by muramyl dipeptide (MDP), a 
component of peptidoglycan (PGN) (10-12). NOD2 has al-
so been implicated in sensing intracellular pathogens such 
as Listeria monocytogenes (6) and M. tuberculosis (13). 
However, despite their importance, the role of NODs in 
M. leprae infection has not been elucidated. 
The inflammasome is a protein complex consisting of 
a nucleotide-binding domain, a leucine-rich repeats-con-
taining family, a pyrin domain-containing (NLRP), apop-
totic speck protein containing a caspase recruitment do-
main (ASC) PYCARD and caspase-1, and is a component 
of the innate immune system. The inflammasome promotes 
maturation of the inflammatory cytokine IL-1β and is re-
sponsible for activation of an inflammatory reaction 
(14,15). 
To date, many studies of NODs have focused on the se-
cretion of pro-inflammatory cytokine such as IL-1β 
through binding of their ligands, but there is no such evi-
dence for their role in mycobacterial disease, particularly 
in leprosy. In this study, we assess the role of NODs in 
the host response to M. leprae infection by measuring the 
mRNA levels of NODs and related genes in infected 
mouse tissues. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Mycobacterium leprae isolation 
The use of M. leprae-infected mice for the preparation of 
M. leprae was approved by the Department of Laboratory 
Animal IACUC in Songeui Campus. M. leprae was pre-
pared from the foot-pads of M. leprae-infected BALB/c 
nude mice. Foot-pads were treated with Potadine solution 
and washed with ice-cold DPBS to remove exogenous 
contamination. To isolate M. leprae, the foot-pads were 
excised, cut into small pieces, and ground with a MACs 
isolator (Miltenyl biotec. Germany). The extract was fil-
tered using a Cell strainer (BD Falcon, Durham, NC, USA) 
to remove tissue debris and centrifuged for 20 min at 4 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. 
The pellet was resuspended in 1 ml of ice-cold DPBS, and 
treated with 2N sodium hydroxide for 5 min to remove 
tissue-derived cells. The reaction was neutralized by add-
ing 13 ml of ice-cold DPBS. After centrifugation and re-
suspension, acid-fast staining was performed, and bacteria 
were counted under light microscopy (1,000×oil-lens) us-
ing the procedure of Shepard and McRae (16). </p>

<p>Cell culture and treatment with M. leprae 
The human embryonic kidney HEK 293 and murine RAW 
264.7 cell lines were purchased from the American Type 
Culture Collection. The cell lines were cultured in DMEM 
(Hyclone, Logan, UT, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal 
bovine serum (Hyclone) and antibiotics (Gibco, Grand 
Island, NY, USA). The cells were infected with M. leprae 
at a multiplicity-of-infection (MOI) of 10. RAW cells were 
also stimulated with LPS (derived from E. coli O111:B4, 
Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, USA). In some experiments, the 
cells were incubated with caspase-1 inhibitor (Ac-
YVAD-CMK, Calbiochem, Darmstadt, Germany) 1 h be-
fore infection. </p>

<p>ELISA for IL-1βand caspase-1 assay 
Culture supernatants were assayed for mouse IL-1β by 
ELISA (DuoSet, R&amp;D, Minneapolis, MN, USA) according 
to manufacturer protocols. Using this assay, the lower limit 
of detection of IL-1β was 3.9 pg/ml. Cell lysates were 
centrifuged at 10,000 g for 5 min at 4 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C and caspase-1 
activity assay was performed using a caspase-1 assay kit 
(Calbiochem) as previously described (17,18). The total in-
crease in the optical density at 405 nm versus that of the 
sample alone was calculated. Caspase-1 activity was ex-
pressed as: (maximum OD405/microgram protein)×10,000. </p>

<p>Transfection 
Human embryonic kidney (HEK) 293T cells were plated 
into 12-well plates (BD Falcon) at 2×10 
5 cells/well and in-</p>

<p>cubated overnight in a CO 2 incubator. The cells were 
co-transfected with varying amounts of pcDNA3-NOD1, 
pcDNA3-NOD2, or pcDNA3-NOD1-NOD2. The trans-
fection was performed with transfection reagent (FuGENE 
HD, Roche, Switzerland) according to the manufacturer's 
instruction. The transfected cells were washed and placed 
in serum-free DMEM and stimulated with M. leprae (MOI 
of 10). </p>

<p>Quantitative RT-PCR 
Total RNA from M. leprae-infected or non-infected tissues 
and cells was prepared using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, 
Waltham, MA, USA) and treated with DNase I (Qiagen, 
Valencia, CA, USA) to remove any contaminating ge-
nomic DNA. The amount of total RNA was quantified 
with spectrophotometer. cDNA was synthesized using a 
SuperScript cDNA synthesis III kit (Invitrogen) according </p>

<p>The Role of NOD2 in M. leprae Infection 
Tae Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 6: 319-324, December, 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 1. Caspase-1 activation and IL-1β production in RAW264.7 cells infected with M. leprae. Macrophages (10 
6 ) were incubated 
with caspase-1 inhibitor (Ac-YVAD-CMK) for 1 h and then treated with LPS (100 ng/ml) and M. leprae (MOI of 10) for 18 h, and the 
supernatants and cell lysates were assayed for caspase-1 activity (A) and IL-1β (B), respectively. Data are representative of at least three 
independent experiments, each performed in triplicate. **p＜0.01. </p>

<p>Table I. Primers used in this study </p>

<p>Gene 
Primer sequence </p>

<p>NOD1 
(mouse) 
Sense: 5'-AGCTGCAGCCTTGCTTTAGCC-3' 
Anti-sense: 5'-TCAGCCATAAATGCCGTAGCG-3' 
NOD2 
(mouse) 
Sense: 5'-CCGAAGCCCTAGCACTGATGC-3' 
Anti-sense: 5'-CAACCATCACGACTCCTCGGG-3' 
ASC 
(mouse) 
Sense: 5'-AGACATGGGCTTACAGGA-3' 
Anti-sense: 5'-CTCCCTCATCTTGTCTTGG-3' 
Caspase-1 
(mouse) 
Sense: 5'-TGAAAGAGGTGAAAGAATT-3' 
Anti-sense: 5'-TCTCCAAGACACATTATCT-3' 
Caspase-1 
(human) 
Sense: 5'-GAAGAGAAAGCTGTTTATCCG-3' 
Anti-sense: 5'-AATCGAACCTTGCGGAAA-3' </p>

<p>to manufacturer instructions. 
Quantitative RT-PCR was used to detect Caspase-1, 
Nod1, Nod2 and ASC transcripts in mouse footpads and 
RAW264.7 cells. β2M was used as an endogenous control. 
PCR amplification was performed with 2×QantiTect 
SYBR Green PCR Master mix (Qiagen) with validated pri-
mers (Qiagen) according to manufacturer protocols. The 
PCR conditions were as follows: 95 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 15 min, fol-
lowed by 40 cycles of 95 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 15 s, 55 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C (Caspase1, 
Nod1, Nod2, ASC, and β2M) for 30 s and 72 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 30 
s. Levels of mRNA were measured using Chromo 4 (MJ 
Research, Waltham, MA, USA). For relative quantifica-
tion, the expression of each gene was normalized to the 
expression of β2M in the cells relative to a calibrator. The 
amount of target was represented as 2 </p>

<p>−ΔΔCt </p>

<p>. The primers 
used in this study are shown in Table I. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
Statistical analyses were carried out using <rs type="software">SigmaStat</rs>, ver-
sion 3.1, by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) or 
Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA, depending on the data. The sig-
nificance was further confirmed by the Tukey test. 
Differences were considered significant when p was less 
than 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our previous report showed that M. leprae induced cas-
pase-1 activation and IL-1β production in peritoneal cells 
from C57BL6 mice (19). In the present study, RAW 264.7 
cells (a macrophage cell line) were exposed to M. leprae </p>

<p>overnight, and the levels of IL-1β production and cas-
pase-1 activity were measured. Consistent with our pre-
vious results, M. leprae bacilli induced caspase-1 activa-
tion and a low level of IL-1β production in RAW cells 
(Fig. 1). In contrast, LPS induced higher levels of IL-1β 
production under the same conditions, suggesting that the 
low level of IL-1β production was due to the doubling 
time of M. leprae. To determine whether caspase-1 is es-
sential for IL-1β secretion in M. leprae infection, RAW 
cells were incubated with the caspase-1 inhibitor 
Ac-YVAD-CMK for 1 h before infection, and then cas-
pase-1 activity and IL-1β secretion were measured. The 
M. leprae-induced IL-1β secretion was blocked in cells 
that lacked caspase-1 (Fig. 1A and B), suggesting that cas-
pase-1 activity is necessary for IL-1β secretion in re-
sponse to M. leprae infection. 
Previous reports have shown that NOD2 induces cas-
pase-1 activation, and that NOD signaling has a dual effect </p>

<p>The Role of NOD2 in M. leprae Infection 
Tae Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 6: 319-324, December, 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 3. The expression of NOD-related genes (A; NOD1, B; NOD2, C; caspase-1, D; ASC) in RAW 264.7 cells infected with M. leprae 
determined by real-time PCR. Data are representative of at least three independent experiments, each performed in triplicate. *p＜0.05; 
**p＜0.01 vs. no stimulation. </p>

<p>Figure 2. The expression of NOD-related genes in mouse footpads infected with M. leprae by determined by real-time PCR. Data are 
representative of at least three independent experiments, each performed in triplicate. *p＜0.05; **p＜0.01 vs. no stimulation. </p>

<p>by activating proIL-1β mRNA transcription and inducing 
the release of bioactive IL-1β (8). To assess the role of 
NODs in the host response to M. leprae infection, we ex-
amined the expression of NODs and related genes in 
mouse tissues infected with M. leprae, and compared that 
to non-infected tissues. We first measured the mRNA ex-
pression of NOD1, NOD2, caspase-1 and ASC in footpads 
from nude mice infected with M. leprae for 18 months. </p>

<p>M. leprae infection increased the expression of both NOD1 
and NOD2 mRNA. The mRNA expression of caspase-1 
and ASC, which are components of the inflammasome, 
was also induced by M. leprae infection (Fig. 2). 
Next, we investigated NOD expression in RAW 264.7 
cells after M. leprae infection. Compared to uninfected 
cells, mRNA levels for NOD1 and NOD2 were increased 
at 1 h after infection with M. leprae. Whereas NOD2 ex-</p>

<p>The Role of NOD2 in M. leprae Infection 
Tae Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 6: 319-324, December, 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 4. Caspase-1 expression in HEK cells transfected with 
NOD1 and NOD2. HEK cells were transfected with NOD1 or 
NOD2, or co-transfected with both NODs and stimulated for 24 
hours with viable M. leprae at 10.0 MOI. Data are representative 
of at least three independent experiments, each performed in 
triplicate. *p＜0.05; **p＜0.01 vs. empty vector. </p>

<p>pression was increased at 2 and 24 h post-infection with 
M. leprae, while the expression of NOD1 was not affected 
at 2 and 24 h post-infection (Fig. 3A and B). Increased 
caspase-1 expression was observed at 2 h and continued 
at 24 h (Fig. 3C). However, Fig. 3D shows that the ex-
pression of ASC, a major adaptor protein involved in the 
inflammasome, was increased only at the early time points 
(1 and 2 h). 
To investigate the role of NODs in the response of the 
host cell against M. leprae, the expression of caspase-1 in 
the HEK cells transfected with NOD1 or NOD2 expression 
plasmid was examined. Caspase-1 expression was in-
creased in cells transfected with NOD2 (Fig. 4), not 
NOD1, suggesting that caspase-1-mediated IL-1β pro-
duction was dependent on NOD2 signaling. 
IL-1β is a pro-inflammatory cytokines that has a critical 
role in the prevention of intracellular pathogens, including 
Bacillus anthracis and Francisella (17,20). Our results 
from the current study showed that M. leprae also induced 
caspase-1-mediated IL-1 secretion in RAW 274.7 cells 
(Fig. 1). NLRs, one of the two major classes of PRR in 
the innate immune system, provide a crucial interface be-
tween invading bacterial pathogens and the host immune 
system. Activation of NLRs by bacterial products can 
stimulate the NF-κB pathway, a key regulator of the 
pro-inflammatory response, activating genes that are in-</p>

<p>volved in immune responses to stimuli. Two NLRs, NOD1 
and NOD2, induce caspase-1 activation and IL-1β ex-
pression via large protein complexes named inflam-
masomes. 
In order to more clearly define the roles of NOD1 and 
NOD2, we transfected HEK 293T cells with NOD1, 
NOD2 or both NODs. There was low response to M. lep-
rae in NOD1-transfected cells, but a higher response in 
NOD2-transfected cells in caspase-1 expression (Fig. 4). 
We expected that HEK 293T cells transfected with both 
receptors (NODs) to have a significantly higher response 
than cells transfected with either one alone. However, 
there was no synergistic effect between NOD1 and NOD2 
in the response to M. leprae (Fig. 4). Therefore, our results 
suggest that NOD2, rather than NOD1, is associated with 
the host response to M. leprae infection. The future study 
will examine the role of NODs in host infected with M. 
leprae using siRNA and knock-out mice. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Sahmyook University 
Research Fund. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors have no financial conflict of interest. </p>



<p>The Role of NOD2 in M. leprae Infection 
Tae Hoon Kim, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 6: 319-324, December, 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>