<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4049090" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)-sponsored 10-day Genomics and Proteomics 
Hands-on Workshop held at National Jewish Health (NJH) and the University of Colorado School 
of Medicine (UCD). The course content included comprehensive lectures and laboratories in mass 
spectrometry and genomics technologies, extensive hands-on experience with instrumentation and 
software, video demonstrations, optional workshops, online sessions, invited keynote speakers, 
and local and national guest faculty. Here we describe the detailed curriculum and present the 
results of short-and long-term evaluations from course attendees. Our educational program consis-
tently received positive reviews from participants and had a substantial impact on grant writing and 
review, manuscript submissions and publications. </p>

<p>In recent years, genomics and proteomics have emerged as key 
technologies in biomedical research programs. These types of 
analyses are now critical to performing effective clinical re-
search aimed at developing a better understanding of disease 
pathology, as well as designing new approaches for clinical 
treatment [1]. For example, as genomic technologies have ma-
tured, so have a growing number of examples of genomic pro-
files directly being used to create individualized treatment 
plans [2]. These include the use of relatively simple single 
nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) genotyping for determining 
an appropriate treatment plan or for predicting the chemother-
apeutic regimen most likely to benefit a breast cancer patient 
[3-5]. In addition, mass spectrometry, metabolomics and pro-
teomics are becoming essential for providing sensitive methods 
of characterizing and analyzing both small molecules and pro-
teins [6-12]. Both genomics and proteomics have proven so 
successful in these regards that demand has far exceeded the 
supply of trained personnel equipped to exploit the available 
technologies. This has resulted in a surge of interest in training 
by investigators keen to utilize these technologies in their re-
search. The need for researchers trained in omics technologies 
has been described by several groups, including working 
groups from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) [13]. In 
our own experience, the demand for training has been demon-
strated at local, national and international levels. For example, 
in the past 8 years, previously established hands-on workshops 
in Metabolomics and Proteomics at National Jewish Health 
(NJH) and the University of Colorado School of Medicine 
(UCD) have been attended by over 400 individuals from 
around the world. 
To support technology-dependent clinical research studies, 
at least two types of training in omics technologies can be 
envisioned: (1) immediate short-term training in the form of 
workshops and (2) long-term instruction in the form of gradu-
ate education and visiting science programs. We aimed to fill 
the former need by providing an intensive and comprehensive 
hands-on training course in genomics, proteomics and 
bioinformatics in a coherent experimentally-based framework. 
Information gleaned from former participants' surveys 
enabled us to determine that there is still a large need for intro-
ductory courses which focus on biomedical research such as 
the one described herein. 
Several recent publications have focused on the need for 
experimental standards in omics research, especially when ap-
plied to human disease [14-17] and education is one means of 
lessening experimental error. To be of maximum benefit, edu-
cation should ideally occur before experimental planning has 
begun, in order to decrease the possibility that the wrong </p>

<p>platform, technology, experimental design or data analysis is 
chosen. For example, a first step toward utilizing omics 
technologies is the development of a well-defined hypothesis 
which clearly outlines the research question under investiga-
tion. If a researcher is interested in global expression patterns 
and/or biomarkers, he/she will need to determine if genomics, 
metabolomics or proteomics is more appropriate. Alterna-
tively, an investigator may determine that a combination of 
approaches is necessary. Even after determining a general 
approach, the researcher must choose which specific platform 
and sample preparation strategies to utilize and this requires 
an understanding of the technologies available and the 
strengths and weaknesses of each approach. Given the pleth-
ora of equipment and protocols currently available, a new 
investigator could conceivably become overwhelmed by alter-
natives and subsequently make a poor choice that could lead 
to downstream difficulties in data analysis and interpretation. 
After determining an appropriate platform in which to test the 
hypothesis, careful experimental design and quality control 
measures are also critical to the success of the project as well 
as for interpreting the results. Given the large datasets gener-
ated by these technologies, knowledge of data analysis work-
flows and options, biostatistics and bioinformatics are vital 
and these are areas in which many investigators require addi-
tional training, specifically in the context of omics research. Fi-
nally, interpretation of omics results is dependent on a broad 
understanding of biochemistry and molecular biology, often 
presented within a knowledge-based pathway framework. 
Our training course exposed participants to each of these areas 
and, more specifically, enabled them to make informed deci-
sions regarding the critical choice of platform for their partic-
ular research question. 
To this end, we assembled a group of educators and scien-
tists who understand the need for training and have experience 
in omics technologies and hands-on workshops. NJH is a pre-
mier hospital and research institution with a reputation for 
high quality clinical and basic research, effective professional 
education and extensive collaborations. The mass spectrome-
try facility is well established and supports over 100 national 
investigators involved in NIH-funded research in lung and 
immune diseases, diabetes, nutrition/obesity and others 
[18-25]. Similarly, the Program Directors at Colorado State 
University (CSU) and UCD have established genomics and 
proteomics research and support projects in pulmonary 
diseases, cancer and women's health, and have programs in 
nutrition, environmental and microbial science [26-38]. The 
Directors of the workshop have developed and taught courses 
and workshops covering the subjects of metabolomics, genomics, 
proteomics, bioinformatics and biostatistics. In general, we 
accomplished the following: (1) built a curriculum focusing </p>

<p>Reisdorph N et al / Omics Hands-on Workshop </p>

<p>
on outcome-structured learning in genomics, proteomics and 
bioinformatics technologies, which enabled investigators to 
immediately apply their knowledge to existing research studies; 
(2) provided novel, multidisciplinary training experiences using 
hands-on techniques and an established model by experienced 
investigators and educators; (3) disseminated educational 
materials such that knowledge and information could be used 
to benefit a wide variety of audiences; and (4) provided a portal 
for collaborative opportunities for both young and established 
investigators, thereby encouraging formation of interdisciplin-
ary teams. 
The intensive course schedule covered 10 consecutive days 
and was offered annually from 2007 to 2010 in the summer 
months. The NHLBI provided funding through a T15 award 
(N. Reisdorph, Principal Investigator) which covered faculty 
salary, invited keynote speakers, transportation between insti-
tutions and hotels, administrative support and laboratory 
module consumables. One salient feature of the course was 
the inclusion of over 20 faculty members with an array of expe-
rience spanning genomics, proteomics, bioinformatics, biosta-
tistics, mass spectrometry, genetics, molecular biology, 
biochemistry, lung and heart disease, clinical studies, human 
research, and mouse and cell models. In addition, a number 
of vendors (Agilent Technologies, Affymetrix, Biorad and 
Pierce) provided laboratory module consumables as well as 
beverages, lunches and keynote speaker dinners for partici-
pants. Participants paid for their travel and housing expenses 
and a moderate $1000 tuition fee was charged to cover items 
not covered through the T15 award, including catering and 
keynote receptions. Scholarships were available each year to 
cover all costs for up to four participants. </p>

<p>Course details </p>

<p>The genomics and proteomics workshop structure combined 
hands-on training with lecture-based learning. It was carefully 
designed to allow students to experience an application-based 
workflow from sample preparation to data analysis. Classes 
were composed of no more than 22 students, who were split 
into 2 groups. Following an introductory session on the day 
of arrival, Group 1 attended proteomics training for days 
2-4, then optional workshops for day 5, then genomics train-
ing for days 6-8 and finally bioinformatics for days 8-10 
(Table 1 showing general schedule). Conversely, Group 2 
attended genomics training for days 2-4, then optional work-
shops for day 5, then proteomics training for days 6-8 and 
finally bioinformatics for days 8-10. This allowed for small 
class size and one-on-one contact during instruction, while 
enabling all participants to interact with each other. Individual 
curricula for genomics, proteomics, bioinformatics and 
optional workshops are described below and detailed sched-
ules are included in the online supplementary information. 
Information on group events is also described. </p>

<p>Proteomics curriculum </p>

<p>A copy of the course curriculum is included in the supplemen-
tary information (Supplementary File 1), with proteomics 
spanning days 2-4. The proteomics curriculum was carefully 
designed to maximize the retention of information and mini-
mize student fatigue. Training material was presented in both </p>

<p>lecture and laboratory session modules. Lectures and labora-
tory sessions were strategically interspersed throughout the 
3 day period. Thus student training time consistently alter-
nated between lecture and hands-on activities, thereby reduc-
ing mental fatigue and helping to keep students engaged. 
Lectures and laboratory sessions were ordered logically to re-
flect a typical workflow, i.e., sample preparation &gt; data acqui-
sition &gt; data analysis. Lecture topics included introduction to 
mass spectrometry and database searching, quantitative pro-
teomics, advanced technologies and clinical proteomics. Dur-
ing hands-on lab sections, students were divided into groups 
of three, making the student-to-instructor ratio 3:1. The com-
position of these groups was predetermined by experience level 
and remained the same throughout the entire course. This pro-
vided an element of consistency that helped students feel com-
fortable with the learning environment. It also enabled the 
laboratory instructor to tailor the session to meet the needs 
of the individual participants. For example, the instructor 
may spend additional time describing the individual compo-
nents of a mass spectrometer to one group, but may discuss 
specific method parameters with another more experienced 
group. Laboratory sessions were divided into three stations 
and organized in a rotation-based format. Each group of three 
students spent 60-75 min per rotation at the following stations: 
sample preparation, instrumentation, informatics and data 
analysis. Over the course of the workshop, students returned 
several times to specific lab stations to continue and complete 
various aspects of sample preparation and instruction on mass 
spectrometry instruments and software. This rotation style for-
mat exposes students to a wide variety of proteomics and mass 
spectrometry concepts, while maintaining the continuity re-
quired to effectively experience an application-based workflow 
from sample preparation to data analysis. 
During laboratories, students were taken through typical 
proteomics work flows from sample preparation to data acqui-
sition and from data analysis to protein identification. Each 
student was responsible for preparing their own digested pro-
tein sample and students contributed to creating mass spec-
trometry data acquisition methods. Students identified the 
protein(s) in their sample during the database search labora-
tory session, which was the final session of the 3-day proteo-
mics course. In the days leading up to this final session, 
students were reminded that they would discover the identity 
of the protein(s) in their sample and there was a friendly com-
petition to see who would have the highest search result score. 
This was designed to build anticipation and help keep students 
engaged. </p>

<p>Genomics curriculum </p>

<p>A copy of the course curriculum is included in the Supplemen-
tary File 1, with genomics spanning days 6-8. The genomics 
curriculum schedule interweaved hands-on bench work with 
lectures and demonstration videos. For the hands-on section, 
the participants in 5 groups of 2 converted total RNA into 
biotinylated cDNA using the standard protocol for running 
on an Affymetrix gene expression microarray. Quality control 
of the intermediate and final products was assessed using the 
Agilent Bioanalyzer. During incubation times, lectures and 
demonstration videos were presented. The lecture topics 
included: principles and applications of DNA microarray </p>

<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics 11 (2013) 368-377 </p>

<p>technology, a comparison of multiple gene expression 
platforms, genomic DNA SNP analysis using microarrays, 
epigenetic applications, application of microarray technology 
to advancing medicine and translational research, using 
publicly available datasets in your own research projects, 
troubleshooting quality control issues and data analysis, and 
integrating proteomic and gene expression datasets. In the final 
year's course offering (2010), lectures in next-generation 
sequencing methods and applications were expanded. Various 
hands-on components typically completed by genomic core 
personnel were presented by video demonstrations, including 
microarray sample loading, washing, staining and scanning. </p>

<p>Bioinformatics curriculum </p>

<p>A copy of the course curriculum is included in the Supplemen-
tary File 1, with bioinformatics spanning days 8-10. All bioin-
formatics instructions were provided in the computational lab 
and synchronized with the laboratory sessions for a unique 
hands-on approach. Lecture topics included experimental de-
sign, power analysis, data pre-processing, quality control, 
exploratory data analysis, class discovery, differential expres-
sion and class prediction. The <rs type="software">BRB-Array Tools</rs> software, 
based on an <rs type="software">Excel</rs> interface of <rs type="software">R BioConductor</rs> packages, 
was used for demonstrations by the instructors ollowed by 
hands-on sessions by the participants. This software was se-
lected since it allowed participants with a diverse computa-
tional background to learn the fundamental data analysis 
steps in a user-friendly environment. Additional bioinformat-
ics instruction was provided on the final days of the workshop 
and covered additional online resources such as Genome 
Browsers, Gene Set Enrichment Analysis, Promoter Analysis, 
Gene Ontology Analysis, Database Resources for Genetic 
Variations and Disorders and in later years, an introduction 
to Next-generation Sequencing Data Analysis. </p>

<p>Keynote and special lectures, optional workshops and 
on-line training </p>

<p>In addition to the genomics, proteomics and informatics 
curricula, the course consisted of 4 keynote lectures, one 
half-day of optional workshops, and pre-and post-course 
online training. Table 2 lists keynote lecturers and their affili-
ations. Special lectures that were presented by local speakers 
are also listed in Table 2. 
Optional workshops varied each year depending on 
participants' interest. Optional workshops were held on 
Sunday morning and included the following topics: Additional 
Hands-on Experience with Mass Spectrometers, Two-dimensional 
Gel Electrophoresis, Introduction to Grant Writing, Biostatistics, 
Alternate Microarray Platform, Bioinformatics, MicroRNA 
Analysis and Literature Reviews. 
Online training was held via live and recorded sessions and 
consisted of introductory material for the proteomics sessions. 
A schedule with topics is listed in Supplementary File 2. In 
addition, a 4-session online workshop was held in January 
2012 to provide updated information to participants (Supple-
mentary File 3). The fields of genomics, proteomics and 
bioinformatics are constantly changing and one challenge of 
omics training is consistently providing updated and relevant </p>

<p>Table 1 General course layout </p>

<p>Note: 
Group 1 attended proteomics training for days 2-4, then optional workshops for day 5, then genomics training for days 6-8 and finally bioinformatics for days 8-10. Conversely, Group 2 </p>

<p>attended genomics training for days 2-4, then optional workshops for day 5, then proteomics training for days 6-8 and finally bioinformatics for days 8-10. </p>

<p>Group </p>

<p>Wednesday </p>

<p>(Day 1) </p>

<p>Thursday </p>

<p>(Day 2) </p>

<p>Friday 
(Day 3) </p>

<p>Saturday </p>

<p>(Day 4) </p>

<p>Sunday 
(Day 5) </p>

<p>Monday </p>

<p>(Day 6) </p>

<p>Tuesday </p>

<p>(Day 7) </p>

<p>Wednesday </p>

<p>(Day 8) </p>

<p>Thursday </p>

<p>(Day 9) </p>

<p>Friday 
(Day 10) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Arrive </p>

<p>Proteomics </p>

<p>Proteomics </p>

<p>Proteomics 
Morning </p>

<p>Genomics </p>

<p>Genomics </p>

<p>Genomics 
Morning </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Arrive </p>

<p>Genomics </p>

<p>Genomics </p>

<p>Genomics 
Morning </p>

<p>Proteomics </p>

<p>Proteomics </p>

<p>Proteomics 
Morning </p>

<p>1 and 2 
combined </p>

<p>Introductory </p>

<p>topics </p>

<p>Joint 
lecture 
Afternoon </p>

<p>Optional 
workshops </p>

<p>Bioinformatics </p>

<p>Afternoon </p>

<p>Bioinformatics </p>

<p>All day </p>

<p>Bioinformatics </p>

<p>Morning </p>

<p>Evening 
activities 
Keynote lecture Free time </p>

<p>Lecture by 
guest faculty </p>

<p>Free time </p>

<p>Free time </p>

<p>Free time </p>

<p>Lecture by 
guest faculty </p>

<p>Free time </p>

<p>Lecture by 
guest faculty </p>

<p>Dismissal 
Afternoon </p>

<p>Reisdorph N et al / Omics Hands-on Workshop </p>

<p>
information. This was accomplished both through annual 
review and revision of material, and through the final online 
session. All sessions were recorded and are available by con-
tacting the corresponding author. </p>

<p>Participant demographics and statistics </p>

<p>The workshop was aimed at junior and senior investigators 
but was also open to postdoctoral and clinical fellows and 
senior graduate students. In all, we provided hands-on 
and web-based training to 87 individuals from 55 institu-
tions, all of whom rated the training they received as out-
standing at the end of the course. Over 120 individuals 
applied for training and, as the course was NIH-NHLBI 
funded, priority was given to individuals with funding in 
an area related to heart, lung or blood diseases. Participants 
were chosen based on recommendations from a selection 
committee composed of course directors, instructors and 
advisors. Educational experience of participants from the 
four annual course offerings included: BS/BA (13%), 
PhD (33%), MD (48%) and MD/PhD (6%) (Figure 1A). 
Participants were primarily (48% of total) faculty members 
including Assistant Professor (26%), Associate Professor 
(6%), Professor (7%), Research Assistant Professor (3%) 
and Instructor (3%), although postdocs and fellows made </p>

<p>Table 2 Keynote and special lecturers </p>

<p>Speaker </p>

<p>Institution/affiliation </p>

<p>Title </p>

<p>Year(s) presented </p>

<p>Natalie Ahn, PhD </p>

<p>University of Colorado, Boulder </p>

<p>Phosphoproteomics </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>Keith Baggerly, PhD </p>

<p>MD Anderson Cancer Center </p>

<p>Evolution of forensic bioinformatics </p>

<p>2009, 2010 </p>

<p>Pierre Chaurand, PhD </p>

<p>University of Montreal </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry imaging </p>

<p>2009 </p>

<p>David Erle, MD </p>

<p>University of California, San Francisco </p>

<p>Microarray pearls and pitfalls </p>

<p>2007-2010 </p>

<p>Leroy Hood, MD/PhD </p>

<p>Institute for Systems Biology </p>

<p>Systems biology and systems medicine </p>

<p>2007 </p>

<p>Alexy Nesvizhskii, PhD </p>

<p>University of Michigan 
Bioinformatics in proteomic applications of heart, lung and blood disorders </p>

<p>2007-2010 </p>

<p>Kevin Schey, PhD </p>

<p>Vanderbilt University 
Spatially-resolved proteomics: MALDI tissue imaging and beyond </p>

<p>2007, 2008, 2010 </p>

<p>David Schwartz, MD </p>

<p>National Jewish Health </p>

<p>Environmental genomics and human health </p>

<p>2008 </p>

<p>Michael Edwards, PhD </p>

<p>University of Colorado, AMC 
Integrating publicly-available microarray data into your analysis </p>

<p>2007-2010 </p>

<p>Mark Geraci, PhD </p>

<p>University of Colorado, AMC 
Advancing translational medicine with DNA microarrays </p>

<p>2007-2010 </p>

<p>Kirk Hansen, PhD </p>

<p>University of Colorado, AMC 
Practical proteomics and spectral interpretation </p>

<p>2007-2010 </p>

<p>Sonia Leach, PhD </p>

<p>National Jewish Health 
SNP analysis with F-SNP, VarioWatch and SequenceVariantAnalyzer </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>David Riches, PhD </p>

<p>National Jewish Health </p>

<p>Introduction to model systems </p>

<p>2008-2010 </p>

<p>Ivana Yang, PhD </p>

<p>University of Colorado, AMC 
Genomic studies of DNA methylation patterns </p>

<p>2009, 2010 </p>

<p>Note: 
Keynote speakers are highlighted in bold. </p>

<p>30% </p>

<p>7% </p>

<p>8% 
4% 
3% </p>

<p>16% </p>

<p>14% </p>

<p>12% </p>

<p>2% 2% 2% </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Asst Professor </p>

<p>Assoc Professor </p>

<p>Professor </p>

<p>Research Asst Professor </p>

<p>Instructor </p>

<p>Postdoc </p>

<p>Fellow </p>

<p>Graduate Student </p>

<p>Core Manager </p>

<p>Technician </p>

<p>Other/Unknown </p>

<p>48% </p>

<p>6% </p>

<p>33% </p>

<p>13% </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>MD </p>

<p>MD/PhD </p>

<p>PhD </p>

<p>BS/BA </p>

<p>Figure 1 Participant demographics 
Shown are professional positions (A) and educational background 
(B) of course participants. Participants were mainly PhDs and 
MDs with faculty positions and included 2 proteomics core facility 
managers. </p>

<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics 11 (2013) 368-377 </p>

<p>up 30% of the participants (Figure 1B). Just over 10% of par-
ticipants were graduate students and 2 proteomics core manag-
ers attended the course. Generally speaking, only 5% of the 
participants stated that they had significant training in omics 
and considered themselves experts, with the vast majority 
not having any prior training. Information gleaned from these 
participants' statistics enabled us to determine that there is still 
a large need for introductory courses which focus on biomed-
ical research. While advanced course work is certainly neces-
sary, our course filled the significant niche for introductory 
and mid-level investigators. </p>

<p>Short-term evaluations </p>

<p>Following each section, participants were asked to fill out a 
web-based evaluation form which was developed in collabora-
tion with Dr. Carol Hodgson, an Associate Dean for Curricu-
lum and Evaluation and Director of the Educational 
Development and Research Office at the University of Colo-
rado, Denver. The form required rating various aspects of 
the workshop from poor, fair, good, very good and excellent, 
with corresponding numerical scores of 1 (poor)-5 (excellent). 
Median scores were tabulated for each laboratory and lecture 
and for administrative and overall course ratings. Composite 
scores for courses are shown in Figure 2. Scores for ''overall 
quality'' of the workshops in 2007, 2008, 2009 and 2010 were 
4.76, 4.80, 4.84 and 4.63, respectively (far right of bar graph). 
Course evaluations were taken seriously and were critical to 
shaping and improving the following years' offering. For 
example, a number of participants suggested video demonstra-
tions to replace hands-on genomics sample preparation, which 
was implemented in 2008. In addition, bioinformatics sessions 
originally spanned entire days; however these were split into 
half-days and interspersed with hands-on laboratory sessions 
after participant feedback suggested there were too many 
hours spent in the computer lab. Lectures and labs that re-
ceived relatively poor ratings (greater than 10% fair ratings </p>

<p>or that had less than 40% excellent ratings) were revised where 
possible in subsequent years. </p>

<p>Long-term evaluations </p>

<p>Approximately 3 months following the 2010 course, a follow-
up evaluation was distributed to former NHLBI 10-day 
omics course attendees. Supplementary File 4 lists the ques-
tions that were asked to participants. Of particular note is 
that of the 49 responders, 98% rated the course very good 
to excellent and 100% indicated that they would recommend 
the course to others. Ninety-eight percent of responders rated 
the quality of the workshop as very good to excellent. 
Impressively, 44% said that the workshop had had high im-
pact on their research. As shown in Figure 3, responders who 
were frequently using specific techniques in their own labora-
tories, or through a core facility, more than quadrupled fol-
lowing the course. For example, only 10% frequently used 
genomics informatics techniques prior to the course, but over 
50% frequently used these techniques following the course. 
This could indicate that education helped overcome a signif-
icant barrier in learning by exposing individuals to the tech-
niques in a hands-on fashion. In addition to increased 
utilization of techniques, training apparently helped partici-
pants in other aspects of their work. Figure 4 shows the re-
sults to the question ''please indicate if you have used 
knowledge gained in the course in any of the following sce-
narios''. Almost all participants indicated that they had used 
knowledge gained in the workshop in reading journal articles 
(96%) and attending scientific meetings/seminars (94%). An 
impressive 76% indicated that the course had benefited them 
in terms of manuscript review, and almost half indicated the 
course had helped with non-NIH grant review and thesis re-
view. This indicates that the course not only helped with re-
search programs, but the knowledge gained was applied in a 
myriad of other ways, all of which have a direct positive im-
pact on NIH-funded omics research. </p>

<p>3.80 
4.00 
4.20 
4.40 
4.60 
4.80 
5.00 </p>

<p>Keynote lectures </p>

<p>Proteomics lectures </p>

<p>Proteomics labs </p>

<p>Genomics lectures </p>

<p>Genomics labs </p>

<p>Bioinformaacs </p>

<p>Oponal workshops </p>

<p>Course organizaaon </p>

<p>Overall quality </p>

<p>Average score </p>

<p>Category 
2007 </p>

<p>2008 </p>

<p>2009 </p>

<p>2010 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Composite scores 
Scores are shown for courses held in 2007-2010. The numbers indicate average scores for all lectures and laboratories within a category. </p>

<p>Reisdorph N et al / Omics Hands-on Workshop </p>

<p>
0% </p>

<p>10% 
20% 
30% 
40% 
50% 
60% </p>

<p>Proteomics sample preparaaon </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry </p>

<p>Quanntaave proteomics </p>

<p>2D gels </p>

<p>Database searching </p>

<p>Proteomics data analysis </p>

<p>Gene expression arrays </p>

<p>Array CGH </p>

<p>SNP </p>

<p>MicroRNA </p>

<p>NextGen sequencing </p>

<p>Genomic informaacs </p>

<p>Gene and protein annotaaon </p>

<p>Promoter analysis </p>

<p>Pathway analysis </p>

<p>Gene funccon and ontology </p>

<p>Database resources </p>

<p>Responders using the indicated technique before and aaer workshop </p>

<p>Technique 
Before workshop, in own lab </p>

<p>AAer workshop, in own lab </p>

<p>Before workshop, through core </p>

<p>AAer workshop, through core </p>

<p>Figure 3 Usage of techniques 
The percentage of responders who frequently use a technique in their own laboratory (green bars) or through a core facility (blue bars) is 
shown. A total of 49 individuals responded to this series of questions. In all cases the number of individuals using a specific technique 
increased following participation in the course. Percentage of participants utilized the listed techniques in their own lab before the 
workshop and after the workshop was indicated in light green bars and dark green bars, respectively, while percentage of participants 
utilized the listed techniques through core facility before the workshop and after the workshop was indicated in light blue bars and dark 
blue bars, respectively. </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>40% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>NIH grant review Non-NIH grant 
review </p>

<p>Manuscript 
review </p>

<p>Thesis review Reading journal 
arcles </p>

<p>AAending 
seminars/ 
scienfic 
meengs 
Responders using knowledge gained in course </p>

<p>Scenario </p>

<p>Figure 4 Value of workshop beyond research 
Respondents' answers to the question ''please indicate if you have used knowledge gained in the NHLBI omics course in any of the 
following scenarios'' were analyzed. This chart demonstrates the utility of hands-on training beyond direct usage in research projects. </p>

<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics 11 (2013) 368-377 </p>

<p>Participant comments </p>

<p>In addition to ranking specific course elements, participants 
were asked to provide written feedback regarding the course. 
This enabled participants to make specific requests regarding 
the curriculum. For example, in the first year the curriculum 
included a ''mock grant proposal'' which entailed working in 
groups to develop short grant proposals that included genom-
ics and proteomics experiments. Groups were balanced to in-
clude junior and senior scientists and were given time for 2 
group discussions and 1 presentation. In addition to the dis-
cussion periods, participants were also encouraged to discuss 
the mock proposals during non-workshop hours as a means 
of facilitating collaborations after the workshop. While over 
half of the participants rated the mock grant proposal modules 
as very good to excellent, their written comments demon-
strated that the inclusion of this module was too time-consum-
ing and challenging and it was thus eliminated in subsequent 
workshops. 
Participant feedback also resulted in developing videos to 
complement the genomics modules, including alternate genom-
ics strategies (SNP, next-generation sequencing), including 
more proteomics informatics sessions, expanding quantitative 
proteomics sessions and decreasing the amount of material 
covered in the bioinformatics sessions. A short compilation 
of written comments submitted by workshop attendees is in-
cluded in Supplementary File 5. </p>

<p>Technical details and additional information </p>

<p>A search of PubMed and educational journals demonstrated a 
lack of publications related to omics-based education, in spite 
of the availability of several courses at educational and indus-
trial institutions. To our knowledge, the described course con-
stituted the only hands-on multi-omics course of its kind. As 
mentioned, the NHLBI provided significant funding to enable 
the presentation of the courses from 2007 to 2010 and hence no 
further courses are currently being held. Therefore, we have in-
cluded additional information that could be of use to others in 
the field of omics education and training. </p>

<p>Advertising </p>

<p>The course was advertised through several portals including lo-
cal institutions, institutions with primarily-underserved mem-
bers, vendor contact lists, proteomics and genomics core 
laboratories and websites. Scientists receiving funding from 
NHLBI for proteomics or genomics research were identified 
through the NIH Research Portfolio Online Reporting Tools 
(RePORT) website and contacted through email. Course bro-
chures were also sent to prospective and previous participants 
and course instructors for distribution. </p>

<p>Course demand </p>

<p>In the first year 43 individuals applied and 22 were admitted. 
In the second year, there were 48 applicants and 23 were 
admitted. In the third year, 27 applied and 20 were admitted 
into the course. In the fourth year, 28 applied and 22 were 
admitted. Due to the hands-on nature of the course, the course </p>

<p>directors determined that 20-22 participants allowed individu-
als to receive experience on instrumentation while providing 
substantial one-on-one time with instructors. While lecture-
only based courses could conceivably reach a larger audience, 
by definition they lack hands-on experience. The drop in de-
mand from the last 2 years was attributed to several circum-
stances including a declining national economy that resulted 
in a decrease in overall scientific budgets. In addition, the 
course necessarily recruited investigators whose research fo-
cused on heart, lung and blood studies and our applicant pool 
was therefore limited. Members of industry were also not al-
lowed to attend the course. Based on the number of inquiries 
between 2007 and 2010 from non-NHLBI investigators, and 
based on full capacity for current metabolomics and proteo-
mics courses at NJH and UCD, it is the opinion of the authors 
that there is still a high demand for these types of hands-on 
courses. </p>

<p>Summary and accessing course material </p>

<p>Course evaluations and participant comments have shown that 
our intensive hands-on workshop formats are an effective 
model for presenting essential lecture and laboratory informa-
tion in a relatively short amount of time. This curriculum 
could be the framework for long-term training strategies and 
can be conducted in any number of laboratories. While inten-
sive, 10 days seemed an appropriate length of time for the 
course and allowed full-time researchers, physician-scientists, 
post-docs and graduate students to attend. For copies of the 
videotaped lectures, copies of course evaluations or access to 
the web-based introductory material, please contact the corre-
sponding author. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions </p>

<p>NR was responsible for the overall development of the work-
shop, directing the proteomics modules, managing the grant, 
compiling evaluations and for the production of the manu-
script. CC and RS were responsible for the genomics mod-
ules, NR, RR and JP were responsible for proteomics 
modules including instructing and curriculum development, 
while KK and TLP were responsible for the bioinformatics 
modules. DJE, KS, AN and MG assisted with curriculum 
development, participant selection and presented lectures in 
the workshop. TLP prepared figures for the manuscript. All 
authors reviewed the manuscript, read and approved the final 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Competing interests </p>

<p>None of the authors has any competing interests to declare. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant through the National 
Institutes of Health, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Insti-
tute to Dr. Nichole Reisdorph (Grant No. T15HL086386). </p>

<p>Reisdorph N et al / Omics Hands-on Workshop </p>

<p>
Supplementary material </p>

<p>Supplementary data associated with this article can be found, 
in the online version, at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gpb.2013. 
10.002. </p>



<p> 
Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics 11 (2013) 368-377 </p>



<p>Reisdorph N et al / Omics Hands-on Workshop </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>