<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4494636" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t </p>

<p>Purpose: To determine the prevalence of premature ejaculation (PE) among adult Asian males presented 
with lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) and characterize its association with other clinical factors. 
Methods: A cross-sectional study was conducted at a tertiary medical center to determine the preva-
lence of PE among adult male participants with LUTS during the Annual National Prostate Health 
Awareness Day. Basic demographic data of the participants were collected. All participants were assessed 
for the presence and severity of LUTS using the International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS), and for the 
presence of PE using the PE diagnostic tool. Digital rectal examination was performed by urologists to 
obtain prostate size. LUTS was further categorized into severity, storage symptoms (frequency, urgency, 
and nocturia), and voiding symptoms (weak stream, intermittency, straining, and incomplete emptying) 
to determine their association with PE. Data were analyzed by comparing the participants with PE (PE 
diagnostic tool score !11) versus those without PE, using the independent t test for continuous data, 
ManneWhitney U test for ordinal data, and Chi-square test for nominal data. The statistical significance 
was set at P &lt; 0.05. 
Results: A total of 101 male participants with a mean ± standard deviation age of 60.75 ± 10.32 years 
were included. Among the participants, 33% had moderate LUTS, and 7% severe LUTS. The most common 
LUTS was nocturia (33%). The overall prevalence of PE was 27%. There was no significant difference 
among participants with PE versus those without PE in terms of age, marital status, prostate size, or total 
IPSS score. However, significant difference between groups was noted on the level of education (Mann </p>

<p>eWhitney U, z ¼ À1.993, P ¼ 0.046) where high educational status was noted among participants with 
PE. Likewise, participants with PE were noted to have more prominent weak stream (ManneWhitney U, 
z ¼ À2.126, P ¼ 0.033). 
Conclusions: Among the participants consulted with LUTS, 27% have concomitant PE. Educational status 
seems to have an impact in the self-reporting of PE, which may be due to a higher awareness of par-
ticipants with higher educational attainment. A significant association between PE and weak stream that 
was not related to prostate size suggests a neuropathologic association. 
Every year, the Philippine Urological Association (PUA) cele-
brates Prostate Health Awareness Month with National Digital 
Rectal Exam (DRE) Day. This is a nationwide effort to promote 
awareness in men regarding prostate diseases such as benign 
prostatic hyperplasia and prostate cancer. This is conducted by </p>

<p>urologists in several participating institutions. Most of the partici-
pants come in for consultation due to lower urinary tract symptoms 
(LUTS). Out of 925 participants in 2013, more than half (61%) were 
identified as cases of LUTS, with 57% reported to have moderate to 
severe LUTS. 1 
LUTS are common in men and have been shown to have 
increased frequency and severity with age. 2 Symptoms of male 
sexual dysfunction, including erectile dysfunction, ejaculatory 
dysfunction, and hypoactive desire were previously assumed to be 
only natural consequences of aging. 3 However, the latest evidence 
from epidemiological studies suggests that these symptoms are 
actually associated with LUTS. 2 Several community-based studies </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Institute of Urology, St. Luke's Medical Center, 279 E. </p>

<p>Rodriguez Sr. Boulevard, Quezon City, 1112, Philippines. 
E-mail address: jmsilangcruz@gmail.com (J.M.A. Silangcruz). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>Prostate International </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / p -i n t e r n a t i o n a l . o r g . </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.prnil.2015.03.001 
p2287-8882 e2287-903X/© 2015 Published by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of Prostate International. </p>

<p>Prostate International 3 (2015) 65e69 </p>

<p>have also shown strong correlations between the prevalence of 
sexual dysfunction, especially erectile dysfunction, and the severity 
of LUTS with increasing age. 4 
Premature ejaculation (PE), one of the components of male 
sexual dysfunction, is also seen in the elderly as a primary or sec-
ondary condition. 4 Although several studies have already defined 
the association between male sexual dysfunction (specifically 
erectile dysfunction) and LUTS, only few correlations have been 
made between premature ejaculation alone and LUTS. Common 
causes for this are poor detection of this symptom and under-
reporting of cases. 5 This study therefore aims to determine the 
prevalence of PE among adult Asian males and characterize its as-
sociation with LUTS and other clinical factors. </p>

<p>2. Methods </p>

<p>2.1. Data gathering </p>

<p>This is a descriptive cross-sectional study that included all male 
participants during the Annual National DRE Day in the Philippines 
conducted in June 2014 at St. Luke's Medical Center (Quezon City, 
Philippines). Demographic data obtained were age, marital status, 
educational attainment, and occupation including comorbidities 
such as hypertension and diabetes mellitus. All participants were 
assessed by urologists for the presence of LUTS using the Interna-
tional Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS), and PE using the PE Diag-
nostic Tool (PEDT). A PEDT score !11 was categorized as PE. The 
IPSS was further categorized into total score (IPSS sum), storage 
symptom domains (FUN: frequency, urgency, and nocturia), and 
voiding symptom domains (WISR: weak stream, intermittency, 
straining, and residual urine). DRE was also performed to obtain 
prostate size estimates. </p>

<p>2.2. Data analysis </p>

<p>Data gathered were encoded in a <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Excel</rs> spreadsheet 
and data analysis was performed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> for Windows, version 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">21.0</rs> (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Demographic data of the participants 
were summarized. The clinical characteristics differences among 
LUTS participants with PE versus without PE were statistically 
analyzed. The independent t test was used for analyzing continuous 
data such as age, IPSS sum, storage symptom score, and voiding 
symptom score. The ManneWhitney U test was applied to analyze 
ordinal data with a Likert scale 1e5 of individual IPSS symptom 
domains, prostate size range of 20e60 g, and educational attain-
ment (Table 1) from primary school to doctorate degree. The Chi-
square test was done to analyze nominal data such as the </p>

<p>presence or absence of comorbidity (hypertension and diabetes 
mellitus) and marital status. The statistical significance was set at 
P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>A total of 101 male participants attended the Annual National 
DRE Day conducted at our medical center, all of which were 
included in the study. The mean age of the participants was 61 
years ranging from 36 years to 86 years. Most (78.2%) of the par-
ticipants were married; 54% of the participants had graduated 
college and 63% were retired; 74.3% had comorbidity of hyperten-
sion, and 20.8% had diabetes mellitus. The demographic profile is 
summarized in Table 1. 
The mean ± standard deviation IPSS was 5.79 ± 6.59; 60.40% had 
a score &lt;8, which is categorized as mild LUTS; 32.67% scored 8e19, 
categorized as moderate LUTS; and only 6.93% had severe LUTS 
with a score of &gt;19. Distribution of LUTS severity is illustrated in 
Fig. 1. Among the participants, 13.9% (n ¼ 14) scored !3 in fre-
quency, 4% (n ¼ 4) scored !3 in urgency, 32.7% (n ¼ 33) scored !3 
in nocturia, 12% (n ¼ 12) scored !3 in weak stream, 10% (n ¼ 10) 
scored !3 in intermittency, 7.9% (n ¼ 8) scored !3 in straining, and 
13.9% (n ¼ 14) scored !3 in residual urine. In clustering the LUTS 
score, 50.6% of the participants had storage symptoms whereas 
43.8% had voiding symptoms. Distributions of individual LUTS do-
mains are described in Fig. 2. The mean age of participants with an 
approximate 20-g prostate size by DRE was 56.38 years, ~30 g was 
62.16 years, ~40 g was 63.96 years, ~50 g was 62.5 years, and ~60 g 
was 61.25 years (Table 2). 
According to the PEDT assessments of the participants, 26.7% 
(27) of the participants scored !11, which signifies the presence of 
PE, whereas 16.8% (17) scored 9e10 indicating that PE is probably 
present. Independent t test, used to determine the difference 
among participants with PE versus without PE, showed no signif-
icant differences in terms of age, IPSS sum, storage symptom score, 
or voiding symptom score (Table 3). ManneWhitney U analysis 
showed that educational attainment has significant association 
with the presence of PE, where higher educational status was noted 
among participants with PE (ManneWhitney U, z ¼ À1.993, 
P ¼ 0.046). Likewise, participants with PE were noted to have more 
prominent weak stream (ManneWhitney U, z ¼ À2.126, P ¼ 0.033); 
however, PE was not associated with prostate size (Table 4). There 
was no significant between group difference noted in the Chi-</p>

<p>Table 1 
Demographic profile of participants. </p>

<p>No. of patients ¼ 101 
Count (%) </p>

<p>Marital status 
Single 
10 (9.9) 
Married 
79 (78.2) 
Separated 
5 (5) 
Widowed 
7 (6.9) 
Occupation 
Retired 
63 (62.4) 
Employed 
38 (37.6) 
Education 
Primary 
7 (6.9) 
Secondary 
33 (32.7) 
College 
54 (53.5) 
Postgraduate 
3 (3) 
Master 
4 (4) 
Doctorate 
0 
Comorbid illness 
Hypertension 
75 (74.3) 
Diabetes mellitus 
21 (20.8) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Severity of lower urinary tract symptoms of participants. </p>

<p>J.M.A. Silangcruz et al. / Prostate International 3 (2015) 65e69 </p>

<p>
square analysis on comorbidity (hypertension, diabetes) and 
marital status (Table 5). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>In 2014, the PUA celebrated prostate health awareness month 
with the theme Ikaw na MAN (You're the MAN) focusing not only on 
prostate diseases but also urinary tract and sexual related prob-
lems. During the Annual National DRE Day 2014, more men 
participated in our medical center than in the previous yeard101 
participants compared with 59 participants in 2013. 1 This shows 
that the PUA was successful in promoting prostate health aware-
ness and more men are now becoming concerned about their 
health. 
Based on our study, the mean age of participants was 61 years, 
which is comparable to other studies in that over one third of men 
aged 50 years or more are living with moderate to severe LUTS. 2 
Voiding symptoms are most common in men with LUTS, but are 
generally less bothersome than storage symptoms, which are 
typically the reason for men seeking medical advice. 2 This is in 
contrast with our study where 50.6% of the participants present 
with storage symptoms, whereas voiding symptoms show only 
43.8%. Nocturia is the most common symptom reported (32.7%) 
together with frequency (13.9%) and residual urine (13.9%). A study 
described that an isolated nocturia can be common, particularly in 
aging men, with a recent meta-analysis estimating a prevalence of 
30e60% in men aged &gt;70 years. 6 
The most common prostate size in the mean age of 62.16 years is 
30 g whereas 40-g prostate sizes were seen in the mean age of 
63.96 years. This relates that the prostate enlarges with aging. In 
addition, although LUTS are sometimes associated with urinary 
flow and prostate size, there is substantial evidence that men can 
have symptoms even in the absence of enlarged prostate on 
physical examination. 6 This is partly because lower urinary tract 
symptoms can be caused by multiple mechanisms, including 
prostate, bladder smooth muscle tone and contractility. 6 
PE was first described a century ago; however, its definition has 
been debatable since then due to its ambiguity. 7 The fifth edition of 
the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5 </p>

<p>2013) has defined PE using the parameter of approximately 1-min 
intravaginal ejaculatory latency time. The DSM-5 also listed po-
tential exclusionary conditions to include nonsexual mental dis-
orders, severe relationship distress or other significant stressors, 
and substance/medication use or other medical disorders, which 
may result in early ejaculations. These criteria were intended to 
eliminate cases of premature ejaculation resulting secondarily from 
psychological and/or medical factors. 7,8 The International Society 
for Sexual Medicine (ISSM) in 2013 developed a definition groun-
ded in clearly definable scientific criteria. The committee proposed 
an evidence-based unified definition of both lifelong PE and ac-
quired PE. 9 The ISSM described three current questionnaires used 
in the diagnosis of PE; the PEDT has a modest database, and is 
readily available for clinical use. 5 Several studies have established 
the validity and reliability of PEDT that correlate well with the 
objective assessment by intravaginal ejaculatory latency time 10,11 ; 
due to its simplicity and availability, our study utilized this tool to 
screen the presence of PE among the participants. 
The prevalence of PE among participants with a complaint of 
LUTS in our study was 26.7% (n ¼ 27) whereas 16.8% (n ¼ 17) had 
probable PE. This is comparable with a study in Korea, where PEDT 
have diagnosed PE in 12.1% (35/290) and probable PE in an addi-
tional 11.7% (34/290). 4 It is clear that PE is highly prevalent and, 
globally, approximately 30% of all men can be considered to have 
the condition regardless of age group. 12 Similar to our study, the PE 
Perceptions and Attitudes Study reported that many countries did 
not show an increased prevalence of PE with increasing age. 13 
However, according to the data of the Korean Society for Sexual 
Medicine and Andrology, their study demonstrated an increased PE 
prevalence with increasing age. 4 The same Korean study also 
described that there is significant correlation between LUTS and PE 
particularly among the age 60e79 years group (r ¼ 0.292, 
P ¼ 0.007) 4 ; however, the PEDT score among the age 40e59 years 
group was not correlated with storage symptoms (r ¼ 0.327, 
P ¼ 0.077) or voiding symptoms (r ¼ 0.223, P ¼ 0.235). 4 In 
congruence, our study results also showed that the storage symp-
toms and PE has no association (P ¼ 0.600), as well as voiding 
symptoms and PE (P ¼ 0.108). 
The educational level of the participants correlates well with the 
presence or absence of PE. In particular, high education was asso-
ciated with increased incidence of PE showing a significant asso-
ciation (ManneWhitney U, z ¼ À1.993, P ¼ 0.046). Our study has 
demonstrated that educational status seems to have an impact in 
the self-reporting of PE of the participants, which may be due to 
higher awareness with higher educational attainment. It suggests 
that participants who are aware about the condition PE are more 
likely to volunteer PE symptoms. It is recommended that clinicians 
should always utilize the screening questions for PE to give the 
appropriate treatment, 5 because participants are often unwilling to 
volunteer their symptoms on PE. 14 
The mechanism of PE requires emission that involves deposition 
fluid from the ampullary vas deferens, seminal vesicles, and pros-
tate gland into the posterior urethra 15 ; and expulsion phase that 
involves closure of the bladder neck, followed by the rhythmic 
contractions of the urethra by pelviceperineal and bulbospongio-
sus muscles, and intermittent relaxation of the external urethral 
sphincters. 16 Sympathetic motor neurons control the emission 
phase of ejaculation reflex, and expulsion phase is executed by 
somatic and autonomic motor neurons. These motor neurons are 
located in the thoracolumbar and lumbosacral spinal cord and are 
activated in a coordinated manner when sufficient sensory input to 
reach the ejaculatory threshold has entered the central nervous 
system. 17,18 
Our study showed a significant association between PE and 
weak stream (ManneWhitney U, z ¼ À2.126, P ¼ 0.033) that was </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Distribution of individual lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) symptom 
domains. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Prostate size by digital rectal examination (DRE) distribution with age means. </p>

<p>Mean age (y) </p>

<p>Prostate size by DRE (g) 
20 
56.38 
30 
62.16 
40 
63.96 
50 
62.50 
60 
61.25 </p>

<p>J.M.A. Silangcruz et al. / Prostate International 3 (2015) 65e69 </p>

<p>
not related to prostate size (ManneWhitney U, z ¼ À0.479, 
P ¼ 0.632), which may suggest a neuropathologic association. A 
recent study by Choi et al., 19 although statistically not significant, 
also showed a lower maximum voiding flow velocity, and average 
flow velocity among their LUTS patients with PE as compared to 
patients with LUTS only (12.68 ± 3.96 vs. 17.51 ± 7.99, P ¼ 0.07; 
6.50 ± 2.27 vs. 9.00 ± 3.86, P ¼ 0.06, respectively). 
It may be possible that a neurologic problem causing weak 
bladder contraction such as neurogenic bladder may also cause PE 
because autonomic motor neurons for bladder contraction and 
ejaculation are located in the same area. A study described the 
possible cause of the link between LUTS, erectile dysfunction, and 
PE is overactivation of the autonomic nervous system and increased 
sympathetic nervous system activity. According to this hypothesis, 
LUTS could result from sympathetic nervous system tone, which 
induces the occurrence of urinary storage symptoms owing to the 
contraction of smooth muscles in the prostate gland and urinary 
bladder. Erectile dysfunction occurs as a result of smooth muscle 
contraction in the corpus cavernosum, whereas PE occurs as a 
result of smooth muscle contraction in the prostate, seminal 
vesicle, vas deferens, and epididymis. 4 
This study was limited to a clinical based single session 
assessment of participants. No follow up or additional objective </p>

<p>diagnostic examination such as a urodynamic study with sphinteric 
activity assessment were done to confirm the presence of and as-
sociation between PE and LUTS. Therefore, a larger-scale study with 
follow up of participants with objective assessment and additional 
risk factor identification (such as body mass index, smoking status, 
and psychological factors) is recommended for future studies to 
confirm our findings and additional analyses. </p>

<p>5. Conclusion </p>

<p>Among the participants consulted with LUTS, 27% have 
concomitant PE. Educational status seems to have an impact in the 
self-reporting of PE, which may be due to higher awareness of 
participants with higher educational attainment. A significant as-
sociation between PE and weak stream that was not related to 
prostate size, suggests a neuropathologic association. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>All contributing authors declare no conflicts of interest. </p>



<p>Table 3 
Independent t test analysis between participants with premature ejaculation (PE) versus without PE in terms of age, International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) sum, storage 
symptom score (FUN), and voiding symptom score (WISR). </p>

<p>Continuous variables 
Without PE (n ¼ 74), mean ± SD 
With PE (n ¼ 27), mean ± SD 
95% confidence interval 
P </p>

<p>Age (y) 
60.1 ± 10 
62.6 ± 11 
À7.1e2.14 
0.29 
IPSS sum 
5.3 ± 6 
7.1 ± 7 
À4.7e1.14 
0.23 
FUN 
2.9 ± 3 
3.3 ± 3 
À1.8e1.01 
0.6 
WISR 
2.4 ± 4 
3.9 ± 5 
À3.18e3.18 
0.11 </p>

<p>FUN, frequency, urgency, and nocturia; WISR, weak stream, intermittency, straining, and residual urine. </p>

<p>Table 4 
ManneWhitney U test between participants with premature ejaculation (PE) and 
without PE in terms of individual International Prostate Symptom Score, prostate 
size, and education. </p>

<p>Ordinal variables 
Without PE (n ¼ 74), 
mean rank </p>

<p>With PE (n ¼ 27), 
mean rank </p>

<p>z 
p </p>

<p>Education 
47.84 
59.67 
À1.993 0.046 </p>

<p>Quality of life score 49.23 
55.85 
À1.165 0.244 </p>

<p>Frequency 
50.51 
52.35 
À0.302 0.763 </p>

<p>Urgency 
51.46 
49.74 
À0.369 0.712 </p>

<p>Nocturia 
49.03 
56.39 
À1.149 0.251 </p>

<p>Weak stream 
47.78 
59.83 
À2.126 0.033 </p>

<p>Intermittency 
50.13 
53.39 
À0.637 0.524 </p>

<p>Straining 
49.63 
54.76 
À0.991 0.322 </p>

<p>Residual 
50.12 
53.41 
À0.554 0.579 </p>

<p>Prostate size 
50.19 
53.22 
À0.479 0.632 </p>

<p>Table 5 
Chi-square analysis between participants with premature ejaculation (PE) and 
without PE in terms of participants with comorbidity and marital status. </p>

<p>Nominal variables 
Without PE 
With PE 
Chi-square 
p </p>

<p>Hypertension 
Without 
18 
6 
0.048 
0.83 
With 
56 
21 
Diabetes mellitus 
Without 
59 
21 
0.046 
0.83 
With 
15 
6 
Marital status 
Single 
6 
4 
4.365 
0.23 
Married 
61 
18 
Separated 
2 
3 
Widowed 
5 
2 </p>

<p>J.M.A. Silangcruz et al. / Prostate International 3 (2015) 65e69 </p>



<p>
J.M.A. Silangcruz et al. / Prostate International 3 (2015) 65e69 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>