<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4853138" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>People's republic 
of china </p>

<p>Purpose: Currently, serum biomarkers that are sufficiently sensitive and specific for early 
detection and risk classification of gastric adenocarcinomas are not known. In this study, ten serum 
markers were assessed using the Luminex system and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay for 
the diagnosis of gastric cancer and analysis of the relation between prognosis and metastases. 
Patients and methods: A training set consisting of 228 gastric adenocarcinoma and 190 
control samples was examined. A Luminex multiplex panel with nine biomarkers, consisting 
of three proteins discovered through our previous studies and six proteins previously reported 
to be cancer-associated, was constructed. One additional biomarker was detected using a com-
mercial kit containing EDTA. Logistic regression, random forest (RF), and support vector 
machine (SVM) were used to identify the panel of discriminatory biomarkers in the training 
set. After selecting five proteins as candidate biomarkers, multivariate classification analyses 
were used to identify algorithms for diagnostic biomarker combinations. These algorithms were 
independently validated using a set of 57 gastric adenocarcinoma and 48 control samples. 
Results: Serum pepsinogen I, serum pepsinogen II, A Disintegrin And Metalloproteinase 
domain-containing protein 8 (ADAM8), vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), and serum 
IgG to Helicobacter pylori were selected as classifiers in the three algorithms. These algorithms 
differentiated between the majority of gastric adenocarcinoma and control serum samples in 
the training/test set with high accuracy (RF 79.0%, SVM 83.8%, logistic regression 76.2%). 
These algorithms also differentiated the samples in the validation set (accuracy: RF 82.5%, 
SVM 86.1%, logistic regression 78.7%). 
Conclusion: A panel of combinatorial biomarkers comprising VEGF, ADAM8, IgG to 
H. pylori, serum pepsinogen I, and pepsinogen II were developed. The use of biomarkers is a 
less invasive method for the diagnosis of gastric adenocarcinoma. They may supplement clini-
cal gastroscopic evaluation of symptomatic gastric cancer patients and enhance the diagnostic 
accuracy. 
Gastric adenocarcinoma accounts for 40% of all new gastric cancer cases worldwide. 
It is the fifth most common cancer globally and the third most common cause of cancer-
related deaths (estimated 723,000 deaths, 8.8% of the total in 2012), 
1 mainly because 
of a late diagnosis. The disease is particularly prevalent in Far Eastern countries. 
Gastric adenocarcinoma is the most common malignancy in the People's Republic 
of China, and was the second leading cause of death by malignancy (14.33%) in 
2012. 
2 Gastric cancer patients have considerably lower survival rates than those with 
other gastroenterological tract cancers, except for cancer of the esophagus. Five-year 
survival rates of patients with localized disease (stages I, II, N0) (63.2%) decreased </p>

<p>correspondence: Jian suo 
Department of gastrointestinal surgery, 
The First hospital, Jilin University, 71 
Xinmin street, changchun, Jilin 130021, 
People's republic of china 
email suojian0066@126.com </p>

<p>David Y Zhang 
Department of Pathology, icahn school 
of Medicine at Mount sinai, icahn 
(east) Building Floor 9th room 9-52, 
1425 Madison avenue, new York, 
nY 10029, Usa 
email david.zhang@mssm.edu </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
OncoTargets and Therapy 
26 April 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2456 </p>

<p>Tong et al </p>

<p>to 28.4% after the cancer spread to regional lymph nodes 
(stages II, III, N1-N3), and to 3.9% following the detection 
of distant metastases (stage IV). </p>

<p>3   An early diagnosis coupled with good treatment strategy 
for gastric cancer can significantly improve the survival rates. 
Esophagogastroduodenoscopy is the most reliable method 
for diagnosis of gastric adenocarcinoma. It is used broadly in 
gastroscopy in the People's Republic of China, South Korea, 
and Japan because of the high incidence of gastric adenocar-
cinoma in these countries. South Korea and Japan are the only 
two countries that provide a government-sponsored screening 
program for gastric cancer. These resulted in low mortality-
to-incidence ratio (0.43 in Japan, 0.35 in South Korea), 
indicating the benefits of population-based screening in high-
prevalence regions. 
1 The screening programs run in these 
countries include gastroscopy and serology tests. However, the 
feasibility and effectiveness of gastroscopy is questionable for 
the countries with low incidence rates for gastric cancers. 
Hence, serum biomarkers that identify patients with high 
risk for gastric adenocarcinoma would increase the effective-
ness of endoscopy and improve the early diagnosis rate. In past 
decades, studies have revealed several serum biomarkers for 
gastric cancer which comprise carcinoembryonic antigen, cancer 
antigen (CA) 19-9, and CA 72-4, among others. However, the 
sensitivity of these serum biomarkers used during diagnosis of 
gastric adenocarcinoma (20%-30%) is lower as compared to 
other cancers. 
4-6 Resent proteomic-based research identified sev-
eral significantly more selective and specific biomarkers. 
7 Also, 
miRNAs are emerging as a new potentially important tool in 
diagnostics of gastric cancer. 
8 These new approaches, however, 
often require specific technique and expensive instrumentation 
and cannot be used for routine screening tests. 
Traditionally, the detection of serum markers was done 
using the enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). 
However, the disadvantage of this method is that it requires 
larger volumes of sample and incurs high costs compared 
to the recent method of multiplex detection. The Luminex </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>xMAP 
® technology enables the large numbers of biological 
tests to be conducted and analyzed quickly, cost-effectively, 
and accurately as compared to the ELISA tests. 
In this study, we developed a diagnostic serum biomarker 
panel using Luminex multiplex technology and validated 
its performance by differentiating the patients with gastric 
adenocarcinoma from the healthy controls. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Patient samples </p>

<p>During 2008-2010, serum samples were collected from 
patients (n=285) with newly diagnosed primary gastric </p>

<p>adenocarcinoma without the presence of other cancers at 
The First Hospital of Jilin University, Changchun, People's 
Republic of China. All gastric cancer patients underwent radi-
cal tumor resection with histologically confirmed diagnosis of 
gastric adenocarcinoma. Control samples (n=238) were col-
lected from attendees of the health check-up program from the 
same hospital between 2008 and 2010. Patients from the con-
trol group had no history of cancer. All participants underwent: 
1) routine medical history and physical examination; 2) rou-
tine blood and Helicobacter pylori IgG tests; 3) chest X-ray; 
4) abdominal ultrasound investigation or computed tomog-
raphy scan; 5) gastroduodenoscopy; and 6) mammography 
in women. Two hundred and thirty-eight control samples 
without inflammatory conditions, or confirmed or suspected 
cancer that needed medical treatment, were included. All 
blood samples were collected before any medical treatment in 
the early morning. Peripheral blood was collected and stored 
in SST II tubes (BD, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA) at room tem-
perature for 1 hour, then centrifuged at 3,000× g for 5 minutes. 
Supernatants were collected, separated in aliquots, and stored 
at −80°C. All participants signed an informed consent form. 
The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board 
at The First Hospital of Jilin University. 
Clinical data on demographics and pathological charac-
teristics were available for all patients whose serum samples 
were used for this study (Table 1). The T status, N status, 
and TNM stage of each tumor were classified according to 
the seventh edition of the AJCC classification. </p>

<p>9   Samples were randomly divided into two datasets. Serum 
samples from 228 patients with gastric adenocarcinoma and 
190 control serum samples were grouped as a training set. 
Serum samples from 48 patients with gastric adenocarcinoma 
and 47 control serum samples were grouped as an indepen-
dent validation set. Patient demographics and clinical profiles 
are presented in Table 2. </p>

<p>construction of 9-plex bead array panel </p>

<p>The xMAP bead-based technology (Luminex Corp., Austin, 
TX, USA) permits simultaneous analysis of multiple analytes 
in a single run. It is an antibody-based microarray, with high 
sensitivity and high throughput advantage, which has been 
used extensively in clinical diagnosis and research work. 
Among the nine target proteins (Table 3) chosen for this proj-
ect, COX2, ADAM8, and beta-catenin were identified in our 
previous studies. 
10,11 There was difference in the expression 
of beta-catenin between the gastric cancer tissue and normal 
gastric mucosa tissue. COX2 and ADAM8 were higher in 
the gastric cancer tissues with lymph node metastases than 
in those without metastasis. Serum pepsinogen I (PGI) and </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2457 </p>

<p>Biomarkers for gastric cancer diagnostics </p>

<p>PGI/PGII ratios in the serum or plasma are indicators of 
atrophic gastritis, which is linked to elevated risk of gastric 
cancer. 
12-15 H. pylori and gastric atrophy have both been iden-
tified as etiological factors for gastric cancer. H. pylori was 
declared as a class I carcinogen by the International Agency 
for Research on Cancer in 1994. 
16 Epidemiological surveys 
support a positive association between H. pylori infection 
and the development of gastric cancer. 
17-19 In this study, all 
patients and health controls had been tested for H. pylori 
IgG with ELISA kit (Biohit ELISA kit; Biohit, Helsinki, 
Finland). Intercellular cell adhesion molecule (ICAM), 
vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), epidermal 
growth factor receptor (EGFR), and hemoglobin were also 
associated with gastric cancer development and metastasis 
in previous studies. </p>

<p>20-26   All antibodies have been validated in ELISA and were 
used according to the manufacturer's instructions. The anti-
gen protein has been validated for ELISA too. We developed 
all kits for Luminex according to The Luminex Cookbook. </p>

<p>27   All nine protein kits were divided into a 5-plex panel and two 
2-plex panels with different dilution rates for each patients' 
samples. All samples were randomly divided into different 
plates to perform the Luminex test. The random number allo-
cation and grouping was done using <rs id="software-1" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">12</rs> software. </p>

<p>Multiplex assay procedure </p>

<p>Multiplex assay was performed on a COSTAR™ 96-well 
round bottom plate (Corning Incorporated, Corning, NY, 
USA). Standard curve samples and prediluted patient 
samples (50 µL) were dispensed into the wells. Capture 
antibody-beads mixtures (50 µL) were added into each well 
and incubated at room temperature for 2 hours. Next, mag-
netic beads were suspended in 50 µL of 1% bovine serum 
albumin (BSA) in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), then 
50 µL of detection antibodies with biotin were added to each 
well and the mixtures incubated at room temperature for 
2 hours. Finally, 100 µL of streptavidin-phycoerythrin </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographic data and pathological characteristics of 
patients with gastric cancer and healthy controls </p>

<p>Gastric adenocarcinoma, 
n=285 </p>

<p>Control, 
n=238 </p>

<p>age, years 
59.89±11.499 
59.14±9.33 
sex 
Males 
204 
157 
Females 
81 
81 
stage 
i 
66 (23.1%) 
ii 
93 (32.6%) 
iii 
126 (44.2%) 
alcohol and smoking history 
alcohol 
86 −199 
smoking 
130 −155 
early stage 
48 
advanced stage 
237 
Differentiation type 
high 
7 
Medium 
120 
low 
158 
Tumor 
T1 
48 
T2 
55 
T3 
3 
T4 
179 
lymph node 
n0 
120 
n1 
40 
n2 
47 
n3 
78 
Tumor #2 cm 
52 </p>

<p>Tumor .2 cm 
233 
Tumor position 
antrum 
188 
Body 
65 
cardia 
32 </p>

<p>Table 2 Patients' demographic data and clinical profiles in training and validation groups </p>

<p>Training group 
Validation group </p>

<p>Gastric carcinoma 
(228) </p>

<p>Control 
(190) </p>

<p>Gastric carcinoma 
(57) </p>

<p>Control 
(48) </p>

<p>age, years 
59.82±11. 32 
59.15±9.27 
60.14±10.73 
59.11±7.93 
sex 
Male 
164 
120 
40 
36 
Female 
64 
70 
17 
12 
stage 
i 
47 
19 
ii 
78 
15 
iii 
103 
23 </p>

<p>serum pepsinogen II (PGII), as well as PGI/PGII ratio were 
used in the screening of gastric cancer in the countries with 
high and moderate incidence rates, such as the People's 
Republic of China, Japan, and South Korea. Most studies 
have demonstrated that low concentrations of PGI and low </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2458 </p>

<p>Tong et al </p>

<p>(4 µg/mL) were added and the mixtures incubated at room 
temperature for 30 minutes. Each step was followed by a 
double washing step using 1% BSA in PBS (Sigma-Aldrich 
Co., St Louis, MO, USA) on the magnetic plate (Alpaqua 
Engineering, LLC, Beverly, MA, USA). All incubations were 
done using the Digene Hybrid Capture System at 800 rpm. 
Subsequent to the final washing step, samples were resus-
pended in 100 µL of 1% BSA in PBS and read using Luminex-
200™ (Luminex Corp.). The standard curve was constructed 
using a seven-parametric-curve fitting, and the results were 
calculated using Xponent 3.1 (Luminex Inc.). Markers were 
grouped together according to the dilution factor after the 
cross-reactivity was checked across all analytes. During the 
experiment, intra-assay precision ranged from 2% to 16%, and 
interassay precision ranged from 6% to 19%. The acceptance 
criteria for each individual run followed the Westgard rule. </p>

<p>28   statistical analysis </p>

<p>The raw data of biomarkers from Luminex combined with the 
H. pylori IgG concentrations were analyzed by comparison 
between the gastric cancer patients group and the control 
group using χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, the z-statistic, and the Student's t-test. Further, 
the univariate and multivariate logistic regression analysis 
and correlations between biomarkers were analyzed. The 
analysis of correlations between biomarkers was performed 
as well. For the identification of algorithms distinguishing 
controls from patients with gastric carcinoma, three classifi-
cation analysis methods -random forest (RF), support vector </p>

<p>machine (SVM), and logistic regression -were performed 
with the R program package. The <rs id="software-3" type="software">R</rs> project of statistical 
computing (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Wirtschaftsuniversität</rs>, Wien, Austria) was used 
for classification analysis to develop the algorithms. 
The RF ensemble learning method, proposed by Breiman, 
is a combination of tree predictors where each tree depends 
on the values of a random vector sampled independently and 
with the same distribution for all trees in the forest. 
29 The 
idea behind SVMs is to construct a separating hyperplane 
or set of hyperplanes in a high or infinite dimensional space 
for classification. 
30 After obtaining results with the training 
set, each classification algorithm with different groups of 
classifiers was cross-validated with the validation set. The 
prediction performances with accuracy (number of patients or 
controls identical to the result of the classification/examined 
total number), sensitivity, and specificity were analyzed. The 
receiver operating characteristic curves were constructed and 
the areas under the curves were calculated. A P-value of 0.05 
was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The results of nine Luminex test biomarkers and the ELISA 
result of IgG to H. pylori are listed in Table 4 for the gastric 
cancer group and the control group. With the exception 
of EGFR (P=0.1951) and ICAM (P=0.2627), there were 
significant statistical differences in the biomarkers' levels 
(P,0.05). The levels of eight markers were higher in the 
gastric cancer group compared to the control group. 
The correlation analysis for ten biomarkers showed that 
there were significant correlations between beta-catenin, 
COX2, and VEGF (r.0.7 for all three pairs, Table 5). 
Since ten proteins are too many to run a single algorithm, 
the feature selection process was performed using RF. This 
function shows the cross-validated prediction performance 
of models with sequentially reduced numbers of predictors 
(ranked by variable importance) via a nested cross-validation 
procedure (Figure 1). The figure shows that five proteins (IgG to 
H. pylori, ADAM8, PGI, PGII, VEGF) are the best for the 
prediction. Biomarker selection is shown in Table 6, and 
the important scores are plotted in Figure 2. The results for 
three classification analysis methods -RF, SVM, and logistic 
regression -are shown in Table 7. The receiver operating 
characteristics of RF, SVM, and logistic regression algorithm 
of the five biomarkers are shown in Figure 3. In the test 
group, the accuracy of the RF and SVM algorithms for this 
five-biomarker panel was 82.5% and 86.1%, respectively, 
which was higher than the accuracy of logistic regression 
(78.7%). </p>

<p>Table 3 list of markers </p>

<p>Biomarker 
Antigen 
Capture 
antibody </p>

<p>Detection 
antibody </p>

<p>growth/angiogenic factor 
VegF 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
egFr 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
coagulation/thrombosis 
hemoglobin 
sigma-aldrich 
Pierce 
Pierce 
adhesion 
aDaM8 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
Beta-catenin 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
sicaM-1 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
Inflammation 
cOX2 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
r&amp;D system 
Pepsinogen 
Pepsinogen-i 
r&amp;D system 
abcam 
abcam 
Pepsinogen-ii 
Biohit 
nOVUs 
nOVUs </p>

<p>Notes: r&amp;D system: r&amp;D system inc., Minneapolis, Mn, Usa; sigma-aldrich: 
sigma-aldrich co., st louis, MO, Usa; Pierce: ; Biohit: Biohit, helsinki, Finland; 
abcam: abcam, Ma, Usa; nOVUs: novus Biologicals, littleton, cO, Usa. 
Abbreviations: icaM, intercellular cell adhesion molecule; VegF, vascular 
endothelial growth factor; egFr, epidermal growth factor receptor; aDaM8, a 
Disintegrin and Metalloproteinase domain-containing protein 8. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2459 </p>

<p>Biomarkers for gastric cancer diagnostics </p>

<p>The Cox model was used to model the relationship between 
the survival time, disease stage, and covariates, including the 
five proteins identified earlier. Conditional censoring distribu-
tion bootstrapping was used to construct the 95% confidence 
interval. The data show that proteins have no effect on survival 
time, while pathology N stage pN and pathology T stage pT 
had significant effect on survival (Table 8). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study used Luminex and ELISA methods to identify 
ten serum biomarkers to distinguish between gastric cancer </p>

<p>patients and healthy controls. Among the biomarkers included 
in the panel, eight biomarkers demonstrated statistically sig-
nificant differences between the gastric cancer group and the 
healthy control group. Additionally, in this study we tested 
three proteins that we have earlier reported to have higher 
expression in the gastric cancer tissue compared to the normal 
gastric mucosa (beta-catenin), or higher expression in the 
gastric cancer tissue with metastases compared to the gastric 
cancer tissue without metastases (COX2, ADAM8). 
10,11 The </p>

<p>levels of these three proteins were higher in the gastric cancer 
patients' serum than in the healthy controls. The proteomics 
studies provide the basics for high-sensitivity tests like the 
Luminex. In this study, using the computing algorithm com-
bined with high-throughput method, we identified five bio-
markers for gastric cancer among the ten selected proteins. 
A number of research studies have been aimed toward 
identifying the early diagnostic biomarkers for gastric cancers </p>

<p>Table 4 The description of variables in gastric cancer patients and controls </p>

<p>Variable 
-
Control (N=238) 
Gastric cancer (N=285) 
Statistic 
P-value </p>

<p>igg to Helicobacter 
pylori </p>

<p>Mean ± sD 
35.14±37.98 
66.96±42.19 
z=8.90 
,0.0001 </p>

<p>M (Q1-Q3) 
16.67 (6.31-60.64) 
66.44 (27.94-107.41) 
Min-Max 
0.46-142.71 
0.60-155.67 
Pgi 
Mean ± sD 
101.15±36.49 
4,740.89±22,768.80 
z=4.59 
,0.0001 
M (Q1-Q3) 
94.05 (77.37-120.19) 
116.66 (74.28-211.51) 
Min-Max 
13.54-286.47 
0.24-197,160.00 
Pgii 
Mean ± sD 
13.96±9.98 
3,422.14±10,146.89 
z=9.12 
,0.0001 
M (Q1-Q3) 
10.91 (7.38-17.38) 
21.66 (12.13-38.19) 
Min-Max 
1.60-66.94 
0.14-90,759.61 
Pgi/Pgii 
Mean ± sD 
9.13±4.07 
5.71±4.07 
z=10.26 
,0.0001 
M (Q1-Q3) 
8.56 (6.26-10.93) 
5.23 (3.03-7.61) 
Min-Max 
2.22-36.76 
0.04-24.49 
Beta-catenin 
Mean ± sD 
409.20±473.89 
767.73±854.38 
z=6.88 
,0.0001 
M (Q1-Q3) 
269.98 (135.91-460.89) 
483.61 (263.08-883.18) 
Min-Max 
1.00-3,210.81 
1.00-5,456.21 
cOX2 
Mean ± sD 
190.31±210.51 
308.00±320.50 
z=4.95 
,0.0001 
M (Q1-Q3) 
146.60 (38.79-260.89) 
221.51 (97.94-422.12) 
Min-Max 
0.34-1,325.78 
1.00-2,481.92 
aDaM8 
Mean ± sD 
500.78±492.02 
1,146.98±1,161.13 
z=10.11 
,0.0001 
M (Q1-Q3) 
337.12 (199.81-627.00) 
803.82 (466.89-1,467.16) 
Min-Max 
2.65-3,168.90 
1.00-9,645.67 
VegF 
Mean ± sD 
242.79±277.96 
548.92±490.40 
z=10.23 
,0.0001 
M (Q1-Q3) 
164.49 (77.28-290.32) 
416.47 (236.06-707.36) 
Min-Max 
1.00-1,962.88 
1.00-3,653.43 
egFr 
Mean ± sD 
9,308.89±4,302.37 
9,837.98±5,024.02 
t=1.30 
0.1951 
M (Q1-Q3) 
8,211.83 (6,565.46-10,832.58) 
9,029.69 (6,786.17-11,484.39) 
Min-Max 
3,897.56-41,378.60 
1.00-47,739.98 
icaM 
Mean ± sD 
174,870.10±86,585.45 
165,658.82±95,597.97 
t=1.15 
0.2527 
M (Q1-Q3) 
151,346.57 (119,159.57-213,194.11) 
144,412.52 (107,495.51-200,256.92) 
Min-Max 
56,918.07-627,365.84 
1.00-1,101,730.81 
hB 
Mean ± sD 
369,038.51±470,630.63 
939,135.01±3,663,960.29 
z=2.42 
0.0157 
M (Q1-Q3) 
235,096.52 (135,491.09-417,276.58) 
268,581.00 (144,175.20-724,694.68) 
Min-Max 
31,780.94-5,466,994.12 
1.00-50,057,376.68 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: hB, hemoglobin; M (Q1-Q3), median and interquartile range; Min-Max, minimum to maximum; Pgi, serum pepsinogen i; Pgii, serum pepsinogen ii; 
sD, standard deviation; icaM, intercellular cell adhesion molecule; VegF, vascular endothelial growth factor; egFr, epidermal growth factor receptor; aDaM8, a Disintegrin 
and Metalloproteinase domain-containing protein 8. </p>

<p>Table 5 The results of correlation analysis for three variables </p>

<p>Beta-catenin 
COX2 
VEGF </p>

<p>Beta-catenin 
1.0000 
cOX2 
0.8370* 
1.0000 
VegF 
0.7893* 
0.7291* 
1.0000 </p>

<p>Note: *The correlation is statistically significant. 
Abbreviation: VegF, vascular endothelial growth factor. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2460 </p>

<p>Tong et al </p>

<p>in blood serum, gastric juice, and even in the exhalants from 
the lungs. 
31-33 However, to date, there is no single known 
biomarker unique for diagnosis of gastric cancer. The tradi-
tional biomarkers such as carcinoembryonic antigen, CA 19-9, 
CA 12-5, and CA 7-24 are more sensitive in the diagnostics 
of other gastroenterological cancers rather than for gastric 
cancer. 
4-6 For this reason, they were excluded from this study. 
Instead, we tried to test other proteins that are known to be 
associated with tumorigenesis and development of gastric 
cancer. We used three algorithms to combine five biomarkers 
(IgG to H. pylori, ADAM8, PGI, PGII, and VEGF) in a 
panel cross-validated in a training group of 418 samples 
and a test group of 105 samples. SVM and RF resulted in 
higher accuracy and sensitivity compared to the logistic 
regression method. For SVM, the accuracy, sensitivity, and 
specificity in the test group were 86.1%, 88.6%, and 83.2%, 
respectively. Both PGI and PGII are being used in the gastric </p>

<p>cancer screening in the countries with high incidence of this 
disease. H. pylori infection is known to be a major cause 
of peptic ulcer development and, eventually, gastric cancer 
development in Asian countries. The infection rate and the 
carrier rate are higher in Asian populations than elsewhere in 
the world. With the H. pylori infection, gastric mucosa cells 
can produce more COX2, and beta-catenin is known to be 
involved in this process. In turn, COX2 and beta-catenin direct 
the production of VEGF. We detected significant correlation 
between protein levels of beta-catenin, COX2, and VEGF in 
our analysis. Moreover, VEGF and ADAM8 were associated 
with tumor metastases. Thus, the five selected biomarkers 
have a significant role to play during gastric carcinogenesis. 
In this study, SVM algorithm demonstrated the best 
performance. It had the highest accuracy, sensitivity, and 
specificity as compared to RF and logistic regression analysis. 
The five selected biomarkers were not associated with the 
prognosis of gastric cancer patients. In addition, the overall </p>

<p>Figure 1 random forest cross-validation for feature selection. 
Abbreviation: cV, cross-validation. </p>

<p>Table 6 Biomarker selection in the training group </p>

<p>Marker 
Avg.imp </p>

<p>aDaM8 
42.6065 
Pgi 
38.7232 
Pgii 
37.7563 
VegF 
35.1600 
igg to Helicobacter pylori 
34.7993 
egFr 
10.8508 
Beta-catenin 
10.3391 
hB 
8.4268 
icaM 
6.8035 
cOX2 
2.1472 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: hB, hemoglobin; icaM, intercellular cell adhesion molecule; 
VegF, vascular endothelial growth factor; egFr, epidermal growth factor receptor; 
aDaM8, a Disintegrin and Metalloproteinase domain-containing protein 8; Pgi, 
serum pepsinogen i; Pgii, serum pepsinogen ii. </p>

<p>Figure 2 importance scores of biomarkers in random forest. 
Abbreviations: icaM, intercellular cell adhesion molecule; VegF, vascular 
endothelial growth factor; egFr, epidermal growth factor receptor; aDaM8, 
a Disintegrin and Metalloproteinase domain-containing protein 8; hB, hemoglobin; 
igg, immunoglobulin g; Pgii, serum pepsinogen ii; Pgi, serum pepsinogen i. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2461 </p>

<p>Biomarkers for gastric cancer diagnostics </p>

<p>Table 7 Diagnostic performance of classification algorithms with five-biomarker panel </p>

<p>Training group 
Test group </p>

<p>Accuracy 
Sensitivity 
Specificity 
Accuracy 
Sensitivity 
Specificity </p>

<p>rF 
0.790 
0.842 
0.729 
0.825 
0.860 
0.784 
sVM 
0.838 
0.877 
0.792 
0.861 
0.886 
0.832 
logistic 
0.762 
0.807 
0.708 
0.787 
0.829 
0.737 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: logistic, logistic regression; rF, random forest; sVM, support vector machine. </p>

<p>Figure 3 The ROC of five biomarkers. 
Notes: (A) rF. (B) sVM. (C) logistic regression. 
Abbreviations: AUC, area under the curve; CI, confidence interval; ROC, receiver operating characteristic; RF, random forest; SVM, support vector machine. </p>

<p>sensitivity was sustained regardless of TNM stage and 
tumor size. Although none of the individual markers showed 
sufficient diagnostic power independently, the biomarker 
panel identified in this study performed well. SVM algo-
rithm demonstrated the best performance in this study. The </p>

<p>concentrations of proteins that we identified in this study 
are much higher than the concentrations of other cytokines 
and low level biomarkers that are usually detected with 
mass spectroscopy in serum samples. Therefore, the panel 
of biomarkers may have clinical applications and can be </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2462 </p>

<p>Tong et al </p>

<p>particularly useful for the preliminary diagnostics in patients 
with reported symptoms. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Using three diagnostic algorithms -RF, SVM, and logistic 
regression -we created and validated a panel of biomarkers 
that might prove useful in the clinical diagnostics and/or 
screening of gastric cancer. The panel includes five biomarkers: 
IgG to H. pylori, ADAM8, PGI, PGII, and VEGF. Among the 
diagnostic algorithms, SVM out-performed the others regard-
less of TNM stage or tumor size. In future, the developed panel 
of biomarkers may supplement clinical gastroscopic evaluation 
of symptomatic patients and enhance diagnostic accuracy. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Table 8 Cox model coefficients and 95% confidence interval </p>

<p>OR 
2.5% OR 
97.5% OR </p>

<p>aDaM8 
1.118 
0.754 
1.591 
Pgi 
0.935 
0.640 
1.444 
Pgii 
1.035 
0.733 
1.392 
VegF 
1.077 
0.795 
1.541 
igg to Helicobacter pylori 
1.170 
0.937 
1.544 
n1 
0.726 
0.000 
2.086 
n2 
3.817 
1.841 
10.506 
n3 
5.998 
3.110 
15.813 
T1 
1.365 
0.180 
38,189,896.926 
T2 
15.098 
0.000 
789,835,105.698 
T3 
5.680 
1.800 
141,247,321.593 
T4 
11.395 
2.777 
391,254,179.091 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: Or, odds ratio; Pgi, serum pepsinogen i; Pgii, serum pepsinogen ii; 
VegF, vascular endothelial growth factor; aDaM8, a Disintegrin and Metalloproteinase 
domain-containing protein 8. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/oncotargets-and-therapy-journal </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal focusing on the pathological basis of all cancers, potential 
targets for therapy and treatment protocols employed to improve the 
management of cancer patients. The journal also focuses on the impact 
of management programs and new therapeutic agents and protocols on </p>

<p>patient perspectives such as quality of life, adherence and satisfaction. 
The manuscript management system is completely online and includes 
a very quick and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. Visit 
http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real quotes from 
published authors. </p>

<p>OncoTargets and Therapy 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2463 </p>

<p>Biomarkers for gastric cancer diagnostics </p>



</text></tei>