<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4501418" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Hepatitis C virus (HCV) envelope protein 2 (E2) is involved in viral binding to host cells. The aim of this work was 
to produce recombinant E2B and E2Y HCV proteins in Escherichia coli and Pichia pastoris, respectively, and to study 
their interactions with low-density lipoprotein receptor (LDLr) and CD81 in human umbilical vein endothelial cells 
(HUVEC) and the ECV304 bladder carcinoma cell line. To investigate the effects of human LDL and differences in 
protein structure (glycosylated or not) on binding efficiency, the recombinant proteins were either associated or not 
associated with lipoproteins before being assayed. The immunoreactivity of the recombinant proteins was analysed 
using pooled serum samples that were either positive or negative for hepatitis C. The cells were immunophenotyped 
by LDLr and CD81 using flow cytometry. Binding and binding inhibition assays were performed in the presence of 
LDL, foetal bovine serum (FCS) and specific antibodies. The results revealed that binding was reduced in the ab-
sence of FCS, but that the addition of human LDL rescued and increased binding capacity. In HUVEC cells, the use 
of antibodies to block LDLr led to a significant reduction in the binding of E2B and E2Y. CD81 antibodies did not 
affect E2B and E2Y binding. In ECV304 cells, blocking LDLr and CD81 produced similar effects, but they were not as 
marked as those that were observed in HUVEC cells. In conclusion, recombinant HCV E2 is dependent on LDL for 
its ability to bind to LDLr in HUVEC and ECV304 cells. These findings are relevant because E2 acts to anchor HCV 
to host cells; therefore, high blood levels of LDL could enhance viral infectivity in chronic hepatitis C patients. </p>

<p>HCV-E2 protein and LDL/CD81 receptor • Ana Carolina Urbaczek et al. </p>



<p>ducted by Albecka et al. (2012) investigated the role of 
LDLr in the HCV life cycle by comparing virus entry to a 
process of lipoprotein uptake and showed that HCV par-
ticles can interact with LDLr. However, this interaction 
does not necessarily lead to a productive infection, but 
rather indicates a role for LDLr as a lipid-providing recep-
tor, which modulates viral RNA replication. 
Vascular changes in the cirrhotic livers of patients 
with chronic hepatitis C have attracted increasing inter-
est because little is known about the relationship of HCV 
with endothelial cells. As this pathology is associated 
with major complications and prognostic implications, 
the necessity of acquiring a more detailed characterisa-
tion of the interactions between HCV and cells during 
infection is required. Previous studies using hepatoma 
cell lines, lymphocyte cell lines and nonhuman cell lines 
have already demonstrated that the E2 protein can bind 
to these cells. In the current study, we tested E2 binding 
to human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVEC) and 
ECV304 cells, both of which are endothelial cell mod-
els. Therefore, we aimed to study the binding interac-
tions between recombinant E2 proteins and LDLr and 
CD81, two well known binding partners of E2, in two 
different endothelial cell lines: HUVEC, which have a 
high concentration of LDLr but no CD81 receptors, and 
ECV304 cells, which are a derivative of the human uri-
nary bladder carcinoma T24 cell line and possess a high 
concentration of LDLr and a low concentration of CD81. 
To investigate how human LDL and differences in pro-
tein structure (glycosylated or not) affected binding ef-
ficiency, we examined recombinant proteins that were 
either associated or not associated with lipoproteins. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Strains, cell lines and media -The DH5α Escherichia 
coli strain (Invitrogen, USA) was used for general prop-
agation of plasmids and the E. coli Rosetta (DE3) strain 
was used to express the E2 protein. The KM71H 
(Mut s ) Pi-
chia pastoris strain (Invitrogen) was used as an expres-
sion host. HUVEC (ATCC 
® CRL-2873™) and ECV304 
cells (ATCC 
® CRL-1998 
TM ) were used to analyse viral 
binding to host receptors. All cell lines were grown ac-
cording to Urbaczek et al. (2014). </p>

<p>Cloning, expression and purification of E2 protein 
-HCV cDNA was obtained from viral RNA that was ex-
tracted with a QIAamp Viral RNA Mini Kit (QIAGEN, 
USA) using sera that was collected and pooled from in-
dividuals with HCV genotype 1a. E. coli and P. pastoris 
were used to express E2 proteins. The E2B protein was 
expressed in E. coli and the E2Y protein was expressed 
in P. pastoris. Cloning, expression and purification were 
performed according to Urbaczek et al. (2014). </p>

<p>Immunoreactivity of recombinant proteins -Recom-
binant E2 proteins were transferred to polyvinylidene 
difluoride (PVDF) membranes. Pooled sera from HCV 
positive patients was diluted 1:100 and added to the 
membrane for 1 h. As a negative control, pooled sera that 
tested negative for HCV and select other infectious dis-
eases (Chagas, syphilis, hepatitis B, human immunode-
ficiency virus-1/2 and human T-lymphotropic virus) was </p>

<p>used at a dilution of 1:10. The reaction was visualised 
using biotinylated human immunoglobulin G (IgG) di-
luted 1:1000, avidin-peroxidase and chromogenic sub-
strate 3,3',5,5'-tetramethylbenzidine/hydrogen peroxide. </p>

<p>Immunophenotyping -HUVEC and ECV304 [culti-
vated with and without foetal bovine serum (FCS)] cells 
were suspended at a concentration of 1 x 10 
6 cells/mL 
and immunophenotyped for CD81 (TAPA-1) and LDLr 
cell surface receptors following the addition of anti-
CD81 mouse monoclonal antibody (MAb), IgG1-fluo-
rescein isothiocyanate (FITC) conjugate and anti-LDLr 
mouse MAb IgG1-phycoerythrin (PE)-conjugated; cells 
were incubated with the indicated immunoglobulins for 
30 min at 4ºC. The cells were analysed by flow cytom-
etry (FACS Canto BD Biosciences and FACSDiva soft-
ware v.6.1.3). In total, 30,000 cells were analysed. All 
experiments were repeated on at least three different oc-
casions and their results were combined. The results are 
expressed as average percentage fluorescence. </p>

<p>Binding assay -HUVEC and ECV304 cells were 
grown in media with and without the addition of FCS and 
were then washed twice in phosphate buffered saline, pH 
7.2. Following this, the cultures were suspended at a con-
centration of 1 x 10 
6 cells/mL and incubated at 37°C for 45 
min with 5 µg/mL untreated E2 protein (E2B or E2Y) or 
5 µg/mL E2 protein pre-incubated with 10 µg/mL human 
LDL. For these assays, human LDL was obtained from 
pooled sera taken from individuals who were HCV nega-
tive and who exhibited high concentrations of LDL (val-
ues above the normal reference). The cells were incubated 
with an anti-His mouse MAb IgG1-Allophycocyanin 
(APC) conjugate for 30 min at 4ºC and were then analysed 
by flow cytometry. A total of 30,000 cells were analysed 
for each experiment and all experiments were repeated a 
minimum of three times. The proportions of cells bound 
to the proteins were measured and pooled and the mean 
was calculated. A total of 10 experiments were performed 
to calculate the means and standard deviation (SD). </p>

<p>Binding inhibition -To inhibit the binding of E2 re-
combinant proteins to HUVEC and ECV304 cell surface 
receptors, cell cultures were grown to 1 x 10 
6 cells/mL 
(grown in medium with and without FCS) and LDLr and 
CD81 receptors on the cell surface were blocked through 
the addition of anti-LDLr and anti-CD81. The blocked 
cells were then incubated at 37ºC for 45 min with 5 µg/mL 
E2 protein (E2B or E2Y) or 5 µg/mL E2 protein pre-incu-
bated with 10 µg/mL human LDL (obtained from pooled 
sera taken from HCV negative patients that exhibited high 
concentrations of LDL) at 37ºC for 1 h. After washing, an 
IgG1-APC anti-His mouse MAb conjugate was added and 
the cells were incubated at 4ºC for 30 min. The cells were 
analysed by flow cytometry. A total of 30,000 cells were 
analysed for each experiment and all experiments were 
repeated a minimum of three times. A total of 10 experi-
ments were performed to calculate the means and SD. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis -All statistical analyses were per-
formed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc (USA)</rs>). 
All sample comparisons were made using ANOVA and 
Tukey tests to compare percentage fluorescence. Values 
of p &lt; 0.05 were considered significant. </p>



<p>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz, Rio de Janeiro, Vol. 110(4), June 2015 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Sequence amplification and correspondence to E2 
recombinant proteins -A sequence was amplified that 
corresponded to an E2 protein without a transmembrane 
domain (GenBank accession AF009606); when including 
restriction sites, this resulted in an 852-bp-long sequence. 
A recombinant pET-42a vector was sequenced and analy-
sed using BLAST by alignment with the HCV subtype-
1a genome sequence (GenBank accession M67463). The 
recombinant E2 proteins corresponded to the native form 
of E2 but without the transmembrane domain (amino acid 
residues from 384-661), which increased their solubility. </p>

<p>Expression analysis and immunoreactivity of E2 
recombinant proteins -Protein expression levels were 
confirmed by their corresponding electrophoretic bands. 
The protein that was produced in E. coli and fused to a 
glutathione-S-transferase protein (GST) and 6x His tag 
was found to be 63.5 kDa (E2B) (Fig. 1). The protein 
that was produced in P. pastoris and fused to a 6x His-
tag was found to be 50 kDa (E2Y) (Fig. 2) because of 
N-glycosylation. Molecular weight differences were re-
lated to the different fusion proteins that were employed 
and to the varying post-translational modifications that 
were imparted by different organisms. These results are </p>

<p>Fig. 1A-C: protein size markers. Expression and reactivity of the envelope 2 (E2) protein produced in Escherichia coli (E2B). A: sodium dodecyl 
sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis stained with Coomassie blue [2 in A: supernatant of the induced bacterial culture; 3 in A: recombi-
nant E2 protein fused to glutathione-S-transferase protein (GST) and 6x His tag (63.5 kDa) after purification in the GST column]; B: polyvi-
nylidene difluoride (PVDF) membrane transferred with the E2 recombinant protein [2 in B: recombinant E2 protein localised by anti-His tag 
primary antibody and alkaline phosphatase anti-immunoglobulin G (IgG) secondary antibody; 3 in B: negative control and alkaline phosphatase 
anti-IgG secondary antibody]; C: PVDF membrane transferred with the E2 recombinant protein for test of reactivity with human serum [2 in C: 
reactivity of the E2 recombinant protein with a pool of hepatitis C virus (HCV) (+) human serum (diluted 1:100); 3 in C: no reactivity of protein 
with a pool of HCV (-) human serum (diluted 1:10)]. </p>

<p>Fig. 2A-C: protein size markers. Expression and reactivity of the envelope 2 (E2) protein produced in Pichia pastoris (E2Y). A: sodium dodecyl 
sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis stained with Coomassie blue [2 in A: recombinant E2 protein fused to glutathione-S-transferase 
protein (GST) and 6x His tag (50 kDa) after purification in the GST column]; B: polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membrane transferred with 
the E2 recombinant protein [2 in B: recombinant E2 protein localised by anti-His tag primary antibody and alkaline phosphatase anti-immuno-
globulin G (IgG) secondary antibody; 3 in B: no reactivity of the E2 recombinant protein with primary antibody (anti-core) -negative control 
and alkaline phosphatase anti-IgG secondary antibody]; C: PVDF membrane transferred with the E2 recombinant protein for test of reactivity 
with human serum [2 in C: reactivity of the E2 recombinant protein with a pool of hepatitis C virus (HCV) (+) human serum (diluted 1:100); 3 
in C: no reactivity of protein with a pool of HCV (-) human serum (diluted 1:10)]. </p>

<p>HCV-E2 protein and LDL/CD81 receptor • Ana Carolina Urbaczek et al. </p>



<p>in agreement with previous publications that evaluated 
the same organisms and gene sequences (Yurkova et al. 
2004, Martinez-Donato et al. 2006). 
The antigenicity of each recombinant protein was 
tested using serum samples taken from chronic hepatitis 
C carriers. We found that human anti-IgG demonstrated 
a specific recognition of E2 proteins [Figs 1 (2 in C), 2 
(2 in C)]. As a control, a PVDF membrane that had been 
incubated with E2 proteins was tested against a pool of 
HCV negative serum; no interactions were found [Figs 1 
(3 in C), 2 (3 in C)]. No immunoreactivity was observed 
with respect to 6x His-tag and GST fusion proteins in 
HCV-negative and positive serum pools. </p>

<p>Cellular immunophenotyping -LDLr and CD81 (TA-
PA-1) surface receptors were characterised in HUVEC 
and ECV304 cells by flow cytometry and representative 
histograms that were obtained using FITC-conjugated 
anti-CD81 and PE-conjugated anti-LDLr are shown in 
Fig. 3. In HUVEC, 93% were positive for LDLr, whereas 
no significant fluorescence was found with respect to 
CD81 (approximately 1%). In ECV304 cells, 15% were 
positive for CD81 and 98% were positive for LDLr. The 
presence or absence of FCS in culture medium did not 
significantly alter the expression of receptors. </p>

<p>Binding of E2 recombinant proteins to LDLr and 
CD81 receptors -Assessing the binding of the recombi-</p>

<p>nant E2 proteins to HUVEC and ECV304 cells revealed 
that E2 proteins could bind to receptors without having 
to form a heterodimer with E1. In HUVEC, binding ca-
pacity was found to be totally dependent on the presence 
of FCS, as the percentage of binding was reduced for 
both E2 proteins when FCS was removed from culture 
media (Fig. 4). However, the addition of human LDL to 
the media both rescued and increased the binding capac-
ity of both E2 for all combinations studied and regard-
less of the presence or absence of FCS (Fig. 4). It is no-
table that in HUVEC, these recombinant proteins were 
only found to bind to LDLr because this cell line did not 
present significant amounts of CD81 receptors under the 
experimental conditions that were used in this work. 
With respect to ECV304 cells, the presence of FCS 
was important for the binding efficiency of both recom-
binant E2 proteins. However, these results differed from 
those obtained with HUVECs, which, in the absence of 
LDL, were totally dependent on the presence of FCS in 
culture media. Similar to the results obtained using HU-
VEC, in ECV304 cells, the addition of human LDL led 
to a significant increase in binding in all of the experi-
mental conditions that were tested (Fig. 5). 
Furthermore, we also observed more significant 
binding (p &lt; 0.01) of E2Y vs. E2B in both cell types in 
the presence of LDL or FCS. </p>

<p>Fig. 3: immunophenotyping assay of the low-density lipoprotein receptor (LDLr) and CD81 surface receptors in ECV304 and human umbili-
cal vein endothelial cells (HUVEC). Blank peak indicates isotype control used for calibration of the flow cytometer. Black peak indicates the 
fluorescence. FITC: fluorescein isothiocyanate; PE: phycoerythrin. </p>



<p>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz, Rio de Janeiro, Vol. 110(4), June 2015 </p>

<p>Inhibiting recombinant E2 proteins from binding to 
cell receptors -In HUVEC, blocking LDLr led to a sig-
nificant reduction in E2B and E29 binding both in the 
presence and absence of FCS and/or LDL in the media 
(Fig. 6). Blocking the CD81 receptor produced a mark-
edly different result, as both the binding and the effects 
produced by FCS and/or LDL were similar to the results 
that were obtained in experiments that did not include the 
CD81 inhibitory antibody (Fig. 7). In another set of ex-
periments, both LDLr and CD81 receptors were blocked 
and only a small amount of fluorescence was detected 
(Fig. 8), suggesting that these proteins might be binding 
to other receptors that are also able to bind E2 proteins, 
such as SR-BI, CLDN1, OCLN and TfR1. We also can-
not rule out the possibility that LDL might modify E2 
(e.g., conformation) and alter its interactions with CD81 
or other cellular receptors in the absence of LDLr. Nev-
ertheless, these results suggest that E2 proteins primar-
ily bound to LDLr and not to another cell receptor. In 
ECV304 cells, blocking LDLr also led to a decrease in 
the binding of both recombinant proteins under all of 
the experimental conditions that were tested. However, 
this effect was not as intense as that which was observed 
in HUVEC. In Fig. 9, it can be observed that blocking 
LDLr could not completely eliminate binding. This may 
indicate that both CD81 and other E2 receptors that are 
present in this cell line, such as SR-BI, CLDN1, OCLN 
and TfR1, represent alternative binding sites, which may 
be more relevant in the context of E2Y than E2B. When 
blocking CD81, a small but significant decrease in bind-
ing capacity was also observed under all of the experi-
mental conditions that were tested in ECV304 cells (Fig. 
10). These results confirm that CD81 is also relevant to the 
binding of E2 recombinant proteins to ECV304 cells and 
they differ from what was observed in HUVEC, which 
were practically insensitive to blockage of this receptor. 
Finally, the simultaneous blockage of both receptors (Fig. 
11) reduced the binding of E2 proteins to ECV304 cells, 
similarly to what was observed in HUVECs. </p>

<p>Fig. 4: binding of recombinant E2B and E2Y to human umbilical vein 
endothelial cells (HUVEC) -effect of the addition of low-density li-
poprotein (LDL) and foetal bovine serum (FCS). The results are mean 
and standard deviation. **: p &lt; 0.01; ***: p &lt; 0.001 (ANOVA and 
Tukey's multiple comparison test). </p>

<p>Fig. 5: binding of recombinant E2B and E2Y to ECV304 -effect of the 
addition of low-density lipoprotein (LDL) and foetal bovine serum 
(FCS). The results are mean and standard deviation. ** p &lt; 0.01; ***: 
p &lt; 0.001 (ANOVA and Tukey's multiple comparison test). </p>

<p>Fig. 6: binding of recombinant E2B and E2Y to human umbilical vein 
endothelial cells (HUVEC) with blocked low-density lipoprotein re-
ceptor (LDLr) -effect of the addition of LDL and foetal bovine serum 
(FCS). The results are mean and standard deviation. ***: p &lt; 0.001 
(ANOVA and Tukey's multiple comparison test). </p>

<p>Fig. 7: binding of recombinant E2B and E2Y to human umbilical vein 
endothelial cells (HUVEC) with blocked CD81 -effect of the addition 
of low-density lipoprotein (LDL) and foetal bovine serum (FCS). The 
results are mean and standard deviation. **: p &lt; 0.01; ***: p &lt; 0.001 
(ANOVA and Tukey's multiple comparison test). </p>

<p>HCV-E2 protein and LDL/CD81 receptor • Ana Carolina Urbaczek et al. </p>



<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Many details of HCV receptors in host cells are not 
completely understood; however, there is evidence that 
E2 is the main protein responsible for the initial events 
that occur during the coupling of the virus to host cells 
(Zibert et al. 1995, Farci et al. 1996). Moreover, LDL and 
CD81 receptors are believed to mediate this process (Scar-
selli et al. 2002, Voisset &amp; Dubuisson 2004). The absence 
of significant fluorescence that was noted with respect to 
CD81 is an indication that this receptor is not constitu-
tively expressed in HUVEC under physiological condi-
tions. Consistent with this, the expression of CD81 has 
previously been found to be reduced in endothelial cells 
in the absence of inflammation (Rohlena et al. 2009). In 
ECV304 cells, fluorescence was low but significant, which 
is an indication that the CD81 receptor was expressed. 
This result can be explained by the fact that ECV304 is 
a hybrid cell line that was created from endothelial cells 
that were contaminated with epithelial cells from bladder 
carcinoma (T24/83) (Brown et al. 2000). We believe that 
this might explain the very low but constitutive expres-
sion of CD81 in this cell line. However, we cannot rule out 
that the low percentage of ECV304 cells expressing CD81 
may be related to a particular cell cycle phase. 
The binding capacity of the recombinant E2 proteins to 
surface receptors in ECV304 cells was dependent on the 
presence of FCS and/or LDL in the culture media. These 
results suggest that E2 proteins are binding to CD81, as 
this receptor was present in a lower percentage of cells 
than was LDLr. Moreover, an absence of LDL in the cul-
ture media impeded the binding of E2 to LDLr, which was 
found to be present in a higher percentage of cells. 
The presence of human LDL was also critical to the 
binding of both proteins to HUVEC when FCS was ab-
sent from the medium. This is an indication that the virus 
primarily bound to LDLr. Coupled with the absence of 
CD81 in HUVEC, this finding suggests that, in both of 
the cell types that were used in this study, the interaction 
of E2 with LDLr seems to be at least partially mediated 
by LDL. Consistent with our findings, experiments that </p>

<p>Fig. 8: binding of recombinant E2B and E2Y to human umbilical vein 
endothelial cells (HUVEC) with blocked low-density lipoprotein re-
ceptor (LDLr) and CD81 -effect of the addition of LDL and foetal 
bovine serum (FCS). The results are mean and standard deviation. 
***: p &lt; 0.001 (ANOVA and Tukey's multiple comparison test). </p>

<p>Fig. 9: binding of recombinant E2B and E2Y to ECV304 with blocked 
low-density lipoprotein receptor (LDLr) -effect of the addition of LDL 
and foetal bovine serum (FCS). The results are mean and standard devi-
ation. ***: p &lt; 0.001 (ANOVA and Tukey's multiple comparison test). </p>

<p>Fig. 10: binding of recombinant E2B and E2Y to ECV304 with blocked 
CD81 -effect of the addition of low-density lipoprotein (LDL) and foetal 
bovine serum (FCS). The results are mean and standard deviation. **: p &lt; 
0.01; ***: p &lt; 0.001 (ANOVA and Tukey's multiple comparison test). </p>

<p>Fig. 11: binding of recombinant E2B and E2Y to ECV304 with 
blocked low-density lipoprotein receptor (LDLr) and CD81 -ef-
fect of the addition of LDL and foetal bovine serum (FCS). The re-
sults are mean and standard deviation. ***: p &lt; 0.001 (ANOVA and 
Tukey's multiple comparison test). </p>



<p>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz, Rio de Janeiro, Vol. 110(4), June 2015 </p>

<p>were performed to assess the binding properties of E2 
proteins that were expressed in Chinese Hamster Ovar-
ian cells revealed that binding was increased in a human 
acute lymphoblastic leukaemia cell line (MOLT-4) when 
using media that contained both LDL and FCS (Wün-
schmann et al. 2006). It is notable that several studies have 
used HCV particles that were produced in vitro (Barto-
sch et al. 2003, Zhong et al. 2005), which are structurally 
different from each other and from particles produced in 
vivo (André et al. 2002). In this study, we tested the re-
combinant proteins in two different organisms and found 
effects that were similar to previously reported findings. 
When HUVEC were blocked against CD81 and cul-
tured in media that lacked FCS, neither of the recombi-
nant proteins was able to significantly bind to the cells 
until after the addition of LDL. Additionally, when cells 
were incubated with anti-LDLr, the binding of E2 pro-
teins was not significant, suggesting that the binding of 
E2 proteins to cells occurs completely via LDLr. Alto-
gether, these results suggest that LDLr is the primary 
target of both proteins under conditions in which they 
are associated with LDL. In agreement with these find-
ings, CD81-deficient cells have previously been demon-
strated to internalise HCV after it binds to LDL and uses 
LDLr (Agnello et al. 1999). Additionally, LDLr-deficient 
cells are less susceptive to HCV infection (Hishiki et al. 
2010). Indeed, LDLr has long been considered HCV's 
route of entry into host cells (Wünschmann et al. 2000, 
Seipp et al. 1997). LDLr has also been shown to be rel-
evant for the cell entry of various members of the Flavi-
virus genus (Wünschmann et al. 2000). 
Another important finding was the verification that 
E2Y always exhibited a greater binding capacity than 
E2B. The primary difference between these two proteins 
is the glycosylation of E2Y. These results are in agreement 
with previous reports in which glycosylation was found 
to be indispensable for the global folding and conforma-
tion of this viral envelope protein (Goffard &amp; Dubuisson 
2003, Voisset &amp; Dubuisson 2004, Bian et al. 2009, Lin et 
al. 2009). Moreover, glycosylation is also important for 
the ability of E2Y to bind to LDL and to other receptors 
of host cells, thereby enabling the coupling and entry of 
HCV into cells (Dubuisson &amp; Rice 1996, Goffard et al. 
2005, Tello et al. 2010). A previous report by Yurkova et 
al. (2004) found that glycosylation was not important for 
the binding of E2 to CD81. This finding was not corrobo-
rated by our experiments, as we found that E2Y more 
efficiently bound to both CD81 and LDLr than did E2B. 
In vivo assays have shown the presence of HCV RNA-
containing particles in low-density fractions of plasma, 
a finding that has been associated with high infectivity. 
However, the nature of circulating HCV particles and 
their association with immunoglobulins or lipoproteins, 
as well as the details of their cell entry mechanisms, 
have all been subject to conflicting reports (André et al. 
2002). Nevertheless, the importance of HCV's associa-
tion with LDL during viral entry through LDLr has been 
observed both in vivo and in vitro. 
In conclusion, we have observed that the recombinant 
E2 HCV protein is dependent on LDL for its ability to 
bind to LDLr in HUVEC and ECV304 cell lines. The as-</p>

<p>sociation between E2 and LDL during the coupling of E2 
to host cells has been demonstrated elsewhere (Thomssen 
et al. 1992, Nahmias et al. 2006); hence, the major contri-
bution of this work is the demonstration that endothelial 
cells are also a potential target for this association. This 
may be related to the initial inflammation that is caused 
by HCV in endothelial cells of the hepatic portal vein, 
which may contribute to HCV-mediated cirrhosis. 
This finding is very relevant because E2 serves as an 
anchor protein during the binding of HCV to host cells 
and high blood levels of LDL might enhance viral infec-
tivity in chronic hepatitis C patients. In fact, LDL has 
been shown to promote an increase in HCV infectivity 
in several previous studies (Lavillette et al. 2005, Meu-
nier et al. 2005, Nahmias et al. 2006, Siagris et al. 2006, 
Hishiki et al. 2010). The glycosylation of E2 is of critical 
importance for enabling the virus to anchor to LDLr. Ad-
ditionally, although many studies have indicated that the 
E1E2 heterodimer is necessary for viral association with 
host cell receptors, we demonstrated here that the E2 
protein is able to independently bind to these receptors. 
Finally, the putative mechanism of cellular infection in-
volving E2, LDL, CD81 and LDLr could offer potential 
new targets for the development of novel antiviral thera-
pies. Moreover, controlling serum LDL levels might also 
be helpful for the treatment of chronic hepatitis C. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>To Prof Iracilda Zeppone Carlos (School of Pharmaceu-
tical Sciences/UNESP), Prof Dulcinéia Saes Parra Abdalla 
(School of Pharmaceutical Sciences/USP), Prof Marcelo 
Dias Baruffi (School of Pharmaceutical Sciences of Ribeirão 
Preto/USP), Marisa Polezi Placeres, Felipe Fortino Verdan 
da Silva, Lívia Carolina de Abreu Ribeiro, Thalita Athiê Néo 
and Thaís Ferreira Isabel (School of Pharmaceutical Sciences 
of Araraquara/UNESP. </p>



<p>HCV-E2 protein and LDL/CD81 receptor • Ana Carolina Urbaczek et al. </p>







<p>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz, Rio de Janeiro, Vol. 110(4), June 2015 </p>



</text></tei>