<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4473108" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Keywords. elimination; epidemiology; measles; vaccine. </p>

<p>In 1994, Canada committed to the objective of measles 
elimination by 2000 [1]. In Canada, a single dose of the 
live-attenuated measles vaccine administered at the age 
of 12 months had been recommended since the early 
1970s [2]. Despite good vaccine coverage, large epidem-
ics in mostly vaccinated children occurred between 
1989 and 1994 [3-7]. Because immunogenicity studies 
had also shown that a second dose administered to chil-
dren who did not respond to a first dose mounted a 
good response [8-10], the National Consensus Confer-
ence on Measles in 1993 and the National Advisory 
Committee on Immunization in 1996 recommended 
the routine administration of a second dose and </p>

<p>catch-up programs to administer a second dose to all 
children and adolescents previously vaccinated under 
the 1-dose program [11, 12]. 
Between 1996 and 1998, provinces implemented rou-
tine 2-dose vaccination programs and catch-up cam-
paigns targeting school-age children and adolescents 
[1]. A review of the measles epidemiology in Canada be-
tween 1996 and 2001 demonstrated that despite a few 
importations and 12 to 199 cases annually, endemic 
transmission had been interrupted since 1997 [1]. With 
elimination defined as the interruption of endemic mea-
sles virus transmission for a period ≥12 months in pres-
ence of high-quality surveillance, Canada (1) showed that 
all reported clusters lasted ≤26 weeks and (2) demonstra-
ted that elimination had been maintained between 2002 
and 2011 [13]. This article presents the epidemiology of 
measles in Canada between 2002 and 2013 and discusses 
the implications for sustaining measles elimination. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Surveillance and Data Collection </p>

<p>Measles has been a reportable disease in Canada since 
1924. As recommended by the Pan American Health </p>

<p>Received 24 November 2014; accepted 09 April 2015. 
Correspondence: Gaston De Serres, MD, PhD, Institut National de Santé Publique 
du Québec, Québec, PQ Canada G1E 7G9 (gaston.deserres@inspq.qc.ca). </p>

<p>Open Forum Infectious Diseases 
© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Infectious 
Diseases Societyof America. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms 
of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/), which permits non-commercial 
reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work 
is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For 
commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com. 
DOI: 10.1093/ofid/ofv048 </p>

<p>Measles in Canada Between 2002 and 2013 • OFID • 1 </p>

<p>Organization, Canada initiated a national enhanced measles 
surveillance program in 1998. Integration with rubella and con-
genital rubella syndrome/infection occurred in 2006 and 2007, 
respectively, with addition of these diseases to the national sur-
veillance system. Each case reported through the Canadian 
Measles and Rubella Surveillance System is reviewed, and 
only confirmed cases are added to the national database (see 
below). Data include information on clinical description, age, 
any epidemiologic link to confirmed cases, travel history, vacci-
nation status, and measles genotype. </p>

<p>Case Definition </p>

<p>Measles cases were defined as either laboratory-confirmed or 
clinically confirmed [13]. Laboratory-confirmed cases were 
characterized by either isolation of measles virus from an appro-
priate clinical specimen, detection of measles virus RNA, a 
4-fold or greater rise in measles-specific antibody titer between 
acute and convalescent sera, or positive serologic test for 
measles immunoglobulin (Ig)M antibody using a recommend-
ed assay. Clinically confirmed cases were defined by fever 
(≥38.3°C), a generalized maculopapular rash for at least 3 
days, and either cough, coryza, or conjunctivitis and must be ep-
idemiologically linked to a laboratory-confirmed case. Potential 
cases with recent immunization with a measles-containing vac-
cine (MCV) were excluded. </p>

<p>Measles Virus Genotyping </p>

<p>Measles virus genotyping was performed at the National Micro-
biology Laboratory (NML), Public Health Agency of Canada 
(PHAC) on appropriate clinical specimens (respiratory speci-
mens, urines, and viral isolates) collected from suspect measles 
cases. RNA was extracted using either the RNeasy Mini kit 
(Qiagen), QIAamp Viral RNA kit (Qiagen), or the MPLC 
Total Nucleic Acid Isolation Kit -High Performance (Roche) 
automated on the MagNA Pure LC 2.0 (Roche). The World 
Health Organization (WHO) standardized genotyping region 
[14], and the 450 nucleotides encoding the carboxyl-terminus 
of the measles nucleoprotein was amplified by one-step reverse 
transcription-polymerase chain reaction ([RT-PCR] OneStep 
RT-PCR kit; Qiagen). Amplicons were purified and sequenced 
by the Genomics Core Services section at the NML. Contigs 
were prepared using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SeqMan Pro</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">DNASTAR</rs>) software. The 
resulting sequences were aligned with WHO genotype reference 
sequences [15] using <rs id="software-1" type="software">MegAlign</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">DNASTAR</rs>) software and ge-
notypes determined by highest homology. </p>

<p>Importation Status </p>

<p>Imported measles cases were defined as persons exposed outside 
Canada during the 7 to 21 days before disease onset. Import-
linked cases had a documented epidemiologic link to an imported 
case. With measles elimination, all cases are either imported or a 
secondary spread. Cases were grouped into chains of transmission </p>

<p>(which sometimes included only the imported case) on the basis 
of epidemiological investigations. Chains with no known epide-
miologic link to importation and no genotype information were 
most likely due to secondary spread from imported measles cases 
through an undetected link or chain of transmission. To correct 
for this bias, we assumed that for each of these chains, only the 
imported case was missed by surveillance. </p>

<p>Vaccination Status 
Where available, vaccination status was assessed from registries. 
Otherwise, it was obtained from written documentation (vacci-
nation booklet) presented by cases and was sometimes con-
firmed by providers on an ad hoc basis. The vaccination </p>

<p>status variable was derived based on age at onset and current 
Canadian immunization recommendations [16]. To be valid, 
the first dose had to be administered at ≥12 months of age 
and the second at least 1 month later. Cases with 1 reported 
MCV dose were considered up-to-date if they were between 
the ages of 12 months and 6 years (the second MCV dose is rec-
ommended between 18 months and before school entry [6 
years]). Cases &lt;1 year of age were considered too young for 
their first dose, and those born before 1970 were assumed to 
be naturally immune and not recommended to be vaccinated. </p>

<p>Descriptive and Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Associations between categorical variables were calculated with 
χ 2 or Fisher exact tests. To gain insight on the status of measles </p>

<p>elimination in Canada, we estimated the effective reproduction 
number (R) using the proportion of imported cases and the dis-
tribution of the size of the chains of transmission [17]. Approx-
imate 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated by use of 
the profile likelihood. For the calculations based on the propor-
tion of imported cases, the CIs were truncated at a value of 1, 
because the method is conditional on outbreaks becoming ex-
tinct. Cases were grouped into chains of transmission on the 
basis of links found during the investigations. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Measles in Canada Between 2002 and 2013 </p>

<p>Between 2002 and 2013, 1171 confirmed cases of measles were 
reported to PHAC for an overall incidence of 0.29 cases per 
100 000 population (Table 1). The annual number of cases var-
ied between 6 and 752, and the incidence ranged from 0.02 to 
2.19 per 100 000 population (median, 0.05 per 100 000) (Fig-
ure 1). There were fewer cases between 2002 and 2006 (&lt;20 
cases/year) compared with 2007 and 2013 (&gt;60 cases annually 
in 5 of the 7 years). Half of the cases were laboratory confirmed, 
and the other half were clinical cases with an epidemiological link 
to a laboratory-confirmed case (Table 1). Males were slightly 
more affected than females (53% vs 47%). Measles affected 8 of 
the 10 provinces and none of the 3 territories. The median age </p>

<p>2 • OFID • De Serres et al </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of Confirmed Measles Cases in Canada 2002-2013 (n = 1171) </p>

<p>Total 
Hospitalized a 
2002 
2003 
2004 
2005 
2006 
2007 
2008 
2009 
2010 
2011 
2012 
2013 
N( % ) 
N( % ) 
N 
N 
N 
N 
N 
N 
N 
N 
N 
N 
N 
N 
Total 
1171 
151 (13%) 
7 
16 
8 
6 
13 
102 
62 
14 
99 
752 
9 
83 </p>

<p>Diagnosis Type b 
Laboratory confirmed 
583 (50%) 
118 (78%) 
7 
12 
8 
5 
9 
52 
34 
6 
82 
306 
9 
53 </p>

<p>Epi-linked 
584 (50%) 
33 (22%) 
0 
0 
0 
1 
4 
50 
28 
8 
17 
446 
0 
30 </p>

<p>Sex c 
Male 
624 (53%) 
79 (52%) 
3 
6 
1 
0 
7 
51 
37 
9 
50 
412 
3 
45 </p>

<p>Female 
545 (47%) 
72 (48%) 
4 
8 
7 
6 
6 
51 
25 
5 
49 
340 
6 
38 </p>

<p>Age group (years) 
&lt; 1 
5 6( 5 % ) 
1 3( 2 3 % ) 
0 
3 
2 
1 
4 
0 
4 
0 
1 1 
2 6 
1 
4 </p>

<p>1-4 
128 (11%) 
22 (19%) 
2 
3 
4 
1 
3 
14 
6 
1 
12 
63 
2 
17 </p>

<p>5-9 
127 (11%) 
8 (6%) 
1 
1 
0 
0 
1 
35 
9 
3 
6 
61 
1 
9 
10-14 
320 (27%) 
19 (6%) 
0 
0 
0 
2 
0 
25 
9 
2 
5 
260 
0 
17 </p>

<p>15-1 9 
2 7 1( 2 3 % ) 
2 9( 1 1 % ) 
0 
1 
0 
1 
2 
6 
4 
7 
1 1 
2 2 7 
1 
1 1 </p>

<p>20-2 9 
9 4( 8 % ) 
1 6( 1 7 % ) 
2 
3 
0 
0 
1 
7 
6 
0 
1 8 
4 0 
2 
1 5 
30-39 
125 (11%) 
29 (23%) 
1 
3 
2 
1 
1 
13 
16 
1 
22 
57 
2 
6 </p>

<p>4 0a n du p 
5 0( 4 % ) 
1 5( 3 0 % ) 
1 
2 
0 
0 
1 
2 
8 
0 
1 4 
1 8 
0 
4 </p>

<p>Hospitalization a 
Yes 
151 (13%) 
151 (13%) 
1 
4 
2 
2 
2 
13 
6 
2 
19 
90 
2 
8 </p>

<p>No 
967 (83%) 
Not applicable 
6 
5 
6 
4 
10 
86 
54 
12 
74 
632 
6 
74 </p>

<p>Vaccination status 
Unvaccinated 
740 (63%) 
98 (13%) 
3 
8 
6 
5 
8 
72 
36 
10 
43 
477 
5 
67 </p>

<p>1 dose 
98 (8%) 
13 (13%) 
0 
0 
0 
0 
2 
12 
1 
0 
14 
64 
2 
3 </p>

<p>2d o s e s 
1 0 9( 9 % ) 
4( 4 % ) 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
5 
0 
0 
7 
9 3 
0 
4 
Unknown 
224 (19%) 
36 (16%) 
4 
8 
2 
1 
3 
13 
25 
4 
35 
118 
2 
9 </p>

<p>Importation Status </p>

<p>Imported 
99 (9%) 
31 (21%) 
4 
9 
5 
3 
5 
5 
6 
4 
1 0 
2 9 
7 
1 2 
All others 
1072 (92%) 
120 (79%) 
3 
7 
3 
3 
8 
97 
56 
10 
89 
723 
2 
71 </p>

<p>a Hospitalization information is missing for 55 cases (7 in 2003; 1 in 2006; 3 in 2007; 2 in 2008; 6 in 2010; 30 in 2011; 1 for 2012; and 1 for 2013). </p>

<p>b Diagnosis type is missing for 4 cases in 2003. </p>

<p>c Sex is missing for 2 cases in 2003. </p>

<p>Measles in Canada Between 2002 and 2013 • OFID • 3 </p>

<p>of cases was 14.4 years (range, &lt;1 to 63 years) globally and 14 
years when excluding the 2011 outbreak in Quebec where 68% 
of the 678 cases were 10 to 19 years old [18]. With the exclusion 
of this outbreak, the incidence during the study period was high-
est in infants (1.0 per 100 000), lower but fairly similar between 1 
and 19 years of age (0.2 to 0.4 per 100 000), and there was a sub-
stantial decline between 20 and 39 years of age (0.1 per 100 000) 
(Table 2). Only 4% (50) of cases were adults born before 1970. 
Among the 1171 cases, 63% (n = 740) were unvaccinated, 
19% (n = 224) had an unknown vaccination status, 8% 
(n = 98) had received only 1 dose, and 9% (n = 108) had re-
ceived 2 doses (Table 2). Among the 740 unvaccinated cases, 
70 (9%) were not eligible for vaccination either because they 
were &lt;12 months of age (49 cases [7%]) or because they were 
born before 1970 and considered naturally immune (21 cases 
[3%]). Among the 98 cases who had received only 1 dose of vac-
cine, 22% were adults (n = 22) born after 1983 but before the 
implementation of the 2-dose program in 1996-1997, and an-
other 17% [17] were between 1 and 6 years of age and may have 
been too young to have received their second dose. 
Overall, 13% of cases were hospitalized (Tables 1 and 2). Out-
come data are not collected through national measles surveil-
lance, so specific information on severity of illness is not 
known. There was a significant association between age group 
and hospitalization status (P &lt; .001). Cases in the youngest 
and older age groups were more likely to be hospitalized: 22% </p>

<p>of adults 20 years and older and 19% of children &lt;5 years were 
hospitalized, compared with 8% among children 5 to 19 years. 
The risk of hospitalization was significantly lower (P &lt; .05) 
among cases who received 2 doses (3.7%) than those who 
were unimmunized (13%), those who received 1 dose (13%), 
or those with unknown immunization history (16%) (Table 2). 
Laboratory-confirmed cases were more likely than epi-linked 
cases to have unknown immunization history (25% vs 13%) but 
less likely to have received 2 doses (6% vs 13%) (Table 2). The 
distribution of immunization status was similar between male 
and female cases. Among cases younger than 20 years old, 
12% had an unknown immunization status compared with 
42% in adults 20-39 years old (P &lt; .001). The percentage of 
cases who had received 2 doses increased from 4% in those 
aged 1-4 years and 6% in those 5-9 years to 13% in 10-14 
years and 18% in those 15-19 years old. The percentage of un-
immunized cases was similar among imported and not import-
ed cases (67% vs 63%), but 2-dose recipients were less frequent 
(3% vs 10%, respectively), and cases with unknown immuniza-
tion status were more frequent (24% vs 19%). </p>

<p>Chains of Transmission and the Effective Reproductive Number </p>

<p>Between 2002 and 2013, there were 130 chains of transmission 
(Table 3). The imported case was identified in 93 (72%) of the 
chains but was missing for 37 chains. Because these 37 chains 
occurred in areas of the country or periods with no known </p>

<p>Figure 1. Number of confirmed measles cases by year, Canada, 1924-2013. Measles was not nationally notifiable between 1959 and 1968. </p>

<p>4 • OFID • De Serres et al </p>

<p>Table 2. Characteristics of Measles Cases by Vaccination Status, Canada 2002-2013 </p>

<p>Number of Doses 
Total </p>

<p>Unvaccinated 
N = 740 n (Row%) </p>

<p>1 Dose N = 98 
n (Row%) </p>

<p>2 Doses N = 109 
n (Row %) </p>

<p>Unknown N = 224 
n (Row %) </p>

<p>All a N = 1171 n 
(Incidence) </p>

<p>Excl. QC2011 a 
N = 493 n (Incidence) </p>

<p>Diagnosis Type b </p>

<p>Laboratory 
confirmed </p>

<p>338 (58) 
61 (10) 
36 (6) 
148 (25) 
583 (0.15) 
334 (0.08) </p>

<p>Epi-linked 
400 (68) 
37 (6) 
73 (13) 
74 (13) 
584 (0.15) 
155 (0.04) </p>

<p>Sex c 
Male 
382 (61) 
45 (7) 
67 (11) 
130 (21) 
624 (0.32) 
244 (0.12) </p>

<p>Female 
356 (65) 
53 (10) 
42 (8) 
94 (17) 
545 (0.27) 
247 (0.12) </p>

<p>Age (years) 
&lt;1 
49 (88) 
2 (4) 
0 (0) 
5 (9) 
56 (1.30) 
44 (1.02) </p>

<p>1-4 
92 (72) 
18 (14) 
5 (4) 
13 (10) 
128 (0.74) 
71 (0.41) </p>

<p>5-9 
109 (86) 
5 (4) 
7 (6) 
6 (5) 
127 (0.57) 
70 (0.31) 
10-14 
235 (73) 
9 (3) 
41 (13) 
35 (11) 
320 (1.31) 
72 (0.30) </p>

<p>15-19 
160 (59) 
14 (5) 
48 (18) 
49 (18) 
271(1.03) 
55 (0.21) </p>

<p>20-29 
48 (51) 
10 (11) 
7 (7) 
29 (31) 
94 (0.17) 
65 (0.12) 
30-39 
25 (20) 
35 (28) 
1 (1) 
64 (51) 
125 (0.23) 
76 (0.14) </p>

<p>40 and up 
22 (44) 
5 (10) 
0 (0) 
23 (46) 
50 (0.0.3) 
40 (0.02) </p>

<p>Importation status 
Imported 
66 (67) 
6 (6) 
3 (3) 
24 (24) 
99 (0.02) 
98 (0.02) </p>

<p>All others 
674 (63) 
92 (9) 
106 (10) 
200 (19) 
1072 (0.27) 
395 (0.10) </p>

<p>Hospitalized 
98 (65) 
13 (9) 
4 (3) 
36 (24) 
151 (0.04) 
72 (0.02) </p>

<p>a For all cases or excluding the 678 cases of the 2011 outbreak in Quebec (Excl.QC 2011). Incidence per 100 000. </p>

<p>b Diagnosis type is missing for 4 cases in 2003. </p>

<p>c Sex is missing for 2 cases in 2003. </p>

<p>Table 3. Distribution of Outbreak Size for Measles in Canada Between 2002 and 2013 and Estimates of the Reproduction Number (R) 
According to the Proportion of Imported Cases and Outbreak Size </p>

<p>Outbreak Size </p>

<p>Number of 
Cases 
% of Imported Cases 
Effective R </p>

<p>1 Case 
Total (NL) a </p>

<p>2 Cases 
Total (NL) a </p>

<p>≥3 Cases 
Total (NL) a </p>

<p>All Total 
(NL) a 
Total (NL) a Crude % (n/N) </p>

<p>Corrected a % 
(n/N) </p>

<p>From Corrected b 
% Imported </p>

<p>From Corrected b 
Outbreak Size </p>

<p>2002 
7 (3) 
7 (3) 
7 (3) 
57% (4/7) 
70% (7/10) 
0.30 (0.07-0.78) 
0 (0-0.19) </p>

<p>2003 
8 (1) 
2 (1) 
10 (2) 
16 (5) 
50% (8/16) 
56% (10/18) 
0.44 (0.20-0.83) 
0.11 (0.02-0.34) </p>

<p>2004 
5 (1) 
1 
6 (1) 
8 (1) 
63% (5/8) 
67% (6/9) 
0.33 (0.08-0.86) 
0.22 (0.04-0.69) 
2005 
4 (2) 
1 
5 (2) 
6 (2) 
50% (3/6) 
63% (5/8) 
0.37 (0.09-0.97) 
0.12 (0.01-0.55) </p>

<p>2006 
3 
3 (1) 
1 (1) 
7 (2) 
13 (6) 
38% (5/13) 
47% (7/15) 
0.53 (0.24-0.99) 
0.40 (0.16-0.81) </p>

<p>2007 
3 (1) 
2 (1) 
5 (2) 
102 (97) 
3% (3/102) 
5% (5/104) 
0.95 (0.78-1.0) 
0.93 (0.76-1.13) 
2008 
5 (1) 
2 
1 (1) 
8 (2) 
62 (54) 
10% (6/62) 
13% (8/64) 
0.87 (0.67-1.0) 
0.84 (0.64-1.09) </p>

<p>2009 
2 
2 
4 
14 
29% (4/14) 
29% (4/14) 
0.71 (0.36-1.0) 
0.71 (0.36-1.25) </p>

<p>2010 
11 (3) 
1 (1) 
3 (2) 
15 (6) 
99 (85) 
9% (9/99) 
14% (15/105) 
0.86 (0.69-1.0) 
0.80 (0.64-0.98) 
2011 
25 (1) 
4 (3) 
5 (2) 
34 (6) 
752 (20) 
4% (28/752) 
4% (34/758) 
0.96 (0.89-1.0) 
0.95 (0.88-1.02) </p>

<p>2012 
7 (1) 
1 
8 (1) 
9 (1) 
78% (7/9) 
80% (8/10) 
0.20 (0.03-0.62) 
0.10 (0.01-0.44) </p>

<p>2013 
12 (5) 
2 
7 (5) 
21 (10) 
83 (26) 
13% (11/83) 
23% (21/93) 
0.77 (0.61-0.97) 
0.67 (0.51-0.85) 
Total 
92 (19) 
14 (5) 
24 (13) 
130 (37) 1171 (300) 
8% (93/1171) 11% (130/1208) 0.89 (0.84-0.95) 
0.86 (0.81-0.92) </p>

<p>a Total (NL): Total number of outbreaks (outbreaks not linked to an imported case). </p>

<p>b Corrected for outbreaks not linked with an imported case. We assumed that for each of these outbreaks, only the imported case was missed, and we added these 
missed cases to both the numerator and denominator. </p>

<p>Measles in Canada Between 2002 and 2013 • OFID • 5 </p>

<p>measles activity, they are not the result of endemic transmission 
but from an undetected importation. Assuming therefore that 
each chain originated from a different importation, there were 
on average 11 importations per year (range, 4-34) with ≤10 im-
portations per year between 2002 and 2009, 15 in 2010, 34 in 
2011, 8 in 2012, and 21 in 2013 (χ 2 for trend for the study pe-
riod P &lt; .001). Among the 130 chains, 73 (54%) included only 
the identified imported cases and caused no secondary trans-
mission. There were 24 chains with ≥3 cases including 5 with 
&gt;30 cases, which accounted for 81% of all cases and were de-
scribed in detail elsewhere [13, 18-20]. These chains occurred 
in 2007 (Quebec: 94 cases, duration 24 weeks), 2008 (Ontario: 
53 cases, 11 weeks), 2010 (British Columbia: 82 cases, 7 weeks), 
2011 (Quebec: 678 cases, 26 weeks), and 2013 (Alberta: 42 cases, 
6 weeks). The source of importation was not identified for the 
first 3 of these chains but was for the latter 2. </p>

<p>The 99 imported cases (93 chains because some chains had 2 
coprimary imported cases) represent 8% (99 of 1171) of all re-
ported cases. This result underestimates the real proportion of 
imported cases because 37 other chains had no source of impor-
tation detected. To correct for this bias, we assumed that for 
each of these chains, only the imported case was missed by sur-
veillance, and we added these missed imported cases both to the 
numerator and denominator. The corrected proportion of im-
ported cases is 11% [(99 imported cases detected + 37 imported 
cases undetected)/(1171 detected + 37 imported cases undetect-
ed)]. The effective R would be estimated at 0.92 for the uncor-
rected proportion and 0.89 (CI, 95% .84-.95) for the corrected 
proportion. When using the distribution of the size of all chains 
and again adding 1 imported case to chains with no identified 
imported cases, R was 0.86 (CI, 95% .81-.92) (Table 3). </p>

<p>Measles Virus Genotypes 
Between 2002 and 2013, the genotype of 349 measles viruses 
were identified. Genotype D4 was the most prevalent (177 of 
349 [51%]), but 67% (119 of 177) of these were isolated during 
the 2011 outbreak in Quebec and were similar to a strain circu-
lating in Europe that year. In other years, the D4 strains were 
imported from Europe, Pakistan, India, the United States, Ban-
gladesh, or New Zealand. Genotypes D8 (n = 87, 25%) and H1 
(n = 41, 12%) were the second most frequent: D8 was associated 
with the 2008 Ontario outbreak and the 2013 Alberta outbreak, 
whereas H1 was associated with the 2010 Vancouver outbreak. 
The other genotypes identified were B2 [1], B3 [21], D3 [1], D5 
[6], D6 [1], D9 [11], and G3 [1]. The country of origin of im-
portations was known for 96 of 99 imported cases (Table 4). 
Measles was most frequently imported from Europe (37.4% 
overall, 19.2% from France), followed by Southeast Asia (30% 
overall, 12% from Pakistan, and 11% from India). There were 
7 importations from the United States, and 3 or fewer cases 
were imported from 19 other countries or regions (Table 4). </p>

<p>Table 4. Country of Importation in the 93 Importations (99 Cases) 
With an Identified Imported Case </p>

<p>WHO Region/Country </p>

<p>Total Number 
of Imported 
Cases (%) </p>

<p>Number of 
Cases With 
Genotype 
Identified 
Genotype(s) </p>

<p>Total 
99 (100) 
63 </p>

<p>Africa 
5 (5.1) 
2 </p>

<p>Africa, 
unspecified </p>

<p>1 (1.0) 
0 </p>

<p>Ethiopia 
1 (1.0) 
0 </p>

<p>Morocco 
1 (1.0) 
1 
D8 
Uganda 
1 (1.0) 
1 
B3 </p>

<p>Zambia 
1 (1.0) 
0 </p>

<p>Americas 
10 (10.1) 
8 
United States 
7 (7.1) 
1, 2, 1, 1 
B3, D4, D8, 
D9 </p>

<p>Mexico 
2 (2.0) 
2 
D8 a 
Cuba 
1 (1.0) 
1 
D4 b </p>

<p>Eastern 
Mediterranean </p>

<p>1 (1.0) 
0 </p>

<p>Somalia 
1 (1.0) 
0 
Europe 
37 (37.4) 
24 </p>

<p>Europe, 
unspecified </p>

<p>9 (9.1) 
3, 2, 1 
D4, D8, G3 </p>

<p>Belgium 
1 (1.0) 
1 
D4 </p>

<p>England 
1 (1.0) 
1 
D9 </p>

<p>France 
19 (19.2) 
9, 1 
D4, D5 
Israel 
1 (1.0) 
0 </p>

<p>Italy 
1 (1.0) 
0 </p>

<p>The Netherlands 
3 (3.0) 
4 
D8 
Switzerland 
1 (1.0) 
1 
D5 </p>

<p>United Kingdom 
1 (1.0) 
1 
B3 </p>

<p>South East Asia 
30 (30.3) 
20 
Afghanistan 
2 (2.0) 
2 
B3 </p>

<p>Bangladesh 
2 (2.0) 
1, 1 
D4, D8 </p>

<p>India 
11 (11.1) 
2, 3 
D4, D8, 
Pakistan 
12 (12.1) 
4, 4 
B3, D4 </p>

<p>Sri Lanka 
1 (1.0) 
1 
B3 </p>

<p>Thailand 
2 (2.0) 
2 
D8 
Western Pacific 
15 (15.2) 
8 </p>

<p>Western Pacific, 
unspecified </p>

<p>2 (2.0) 
1, 1 
D5, H1 </p>

<p>China 
2 (2.0) 
1 
H1 </p>

<p>Japan 
3 (3.0) 
1, 1 
D5, H1 </p>

<p>Malaysia 
1 (1.0) 
0 
New Zealand 
1 (1.0) 
1 
D4 </p>

<p>Vietnam 
3 (3.0) 
0 </p>

<p>Philippines 
3 (3.0) 
1, 1 
B3, D9 
Region/country 
unknown </p>

<p>3 (3.0) 
1 
B3 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: UK, United Kingdom; WHO, World Health Organization. 
a The traveler was exposed to a confirmed measles case who was a resident of 
the UK, where there was a documented increase in measles cases. 
b The traveler was returning from the Caribbean but likely acquired measles at 
the Montreal airport [18]. </p>

<p>6 • OFID • De Serres et al </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Between 2002 and 2013, a total of 1171 cases of measles have 
occurred in Canada for an overall incidence rate of 0.29 cases 
per 100 000 population. The maximum number of cases per 
year ranged from 6 to 752, with a trend towards higher number 
of cases and importations from 2007 onwards. The majority of 
cases were unvaccinated (63%) or had an unknown vaccination 
status (19%). There was a significant trend towards a greater an-
nual number of importations over the period, with the exclusion 
of the 2011 Quebec outbreak, which affected mostly adoles-
cents. The incidence was highest in infants (1.0 per 100 000) 
and lower but fairly similar between 1 and 19 years of age 
(0.2 to 0.4 per 100 000), suggesting a similar proportion of un-
vaccinated children in the numerous birth cohorts over the past 
20-30 years. Although no transmission lasted ≥12 months, the 
effective reproductive number was estimated at 0.86 (0.81-0.92) 
for the entire period but at 0.95 for 2011. 
The key elements needed to maintain elimination status in-
clude reaching high immunization coverage, minimizing vac-
cine failures, and effective public health management of cases 
and outbreaks in case of importations. It is estimated that at 
least 93% of the population needs to be immune to provide 
enough herd immunity to eliminate measles [21]. Heterogeneity 
and clustering of susceptibility narrow the margin between the 
level of immunity required to maintain elimination and that 
which allows sustained transmission. Among our cases, 63% 
were unimmunized and 19% had an unknown vaccination sta-
tus, which is similar to the 65% and 20%, respectively, observed 
in the United States between 2001 and 2011 [22]. Despite 
representing a small proportion of the population, most un-
vaccinated individuals do so on religious grounds or for 
philosophical reasons and therefore often cluster, adding to 
the risk of large size outbreaks. Although the need to reduce 
the proportion of unvaccinated individuals in Canada is obvi-
ous, given the strong beliefs of these individuals or their family, 
it has been a difficult task. As an example, after the large 2011 
outbreak in Quebec, a measles vaccination campaign was con-
ducted in all schools of the province. Despite parents being 
advised that unvaccinated children would be excluded from 
school during outbreaks, 2.2% of students chose to remain un-
vaccinated (compared with 3.2% before the campaign) [23]. 
New strategies to address this group of parents need to be 
developed. 
Overall, 17% of cases were known to be vaccinated (8% with 1 
dose and 9% with 2 doses). Therefore, the contribution of 
vaccine failures to the vulnerability of the population has been 
limited during that period. However the accumulation of vacci-
nated but yet unprotected individuals over the years diminishes 
the margin of safety to maintain elimination. Ensuring the ad-
ministration of the second dose is currently the most important 
intervention to minimize vaccine failures. </p>

<p>Importations are going to continue to occur until significant 
headway is made towards elimination in other jurisdictions. 
The genotype was identified for 349 cases. D4 was the most 
prevalent, but the majority of these cases occurred during the 
2011 outbreak in Quebec and were genotypically linked to the 
virus causing the large epidemic in France at the same period 
[18, 24]. Genotypes D8 and H1 were the next most commonly 
reported. The genotype pattern seen in Canada reflects geno-
types circulating in other endemic countries with no single 
genotype consistently seen in Canada. This lends further indi-
cation that elimination has been maintained between 2002 and 
2013. The increased number of importation events since 2010 
may be explained by the increase in epidemic measles activities 
in other parts of the world and particularly in Europe [24, 25]. 
Although Canadian travelers to developing countries often seek 
pretravel advice, very few would seek travel advice before trav-
eling to Europe. Ensuring proper vaccination of travelers against 
measles to minimize the number of importations is necessary 
but will be challenging. 
Among the estimated 130 distinct importations (93 where the 
imported cases were identified and 37 chains of transmission 
where it was not), half resulted in no secondary transmission, 
but 5 triggered outbreaks with &gt;30 cases, causing 81% of all 
cases. In the United States, between 2001 and 2013, 477 import-
ed cases were reported, and many others had virological evi-
dence of importation or had an unknown source [22, 26]. 
With approximately 5 times more importations than Canada, 
there were approximately the same total number of cases 
(1153 vs 1171), 83% resulted in no secondary spread [19], 
and only 3 outbreaks had 30 cases or more (Indiana 2005, 34 
cases; Illinois 2008, 30 cases; New York 2013, 58 cases) [27-
29]. The estimates of the effective reproductive number in the 
United States range between 0.62 and 0.66 [26, 30], substantially 
lower than the 0.86 found in Canada. All of these observations 
suggest a higher level of immunity and/or more efficient 
control measures in the United States. The effective R expresses 
the epidemic potential in a specific population and combines 
the contagiousness of the disease (duration of shedding and 
capacity to infect), the proportion of susceptible individuals, 
and the mixing patterns in the population. Outbreak 
control measures such as school exclusion, vaccination of ex-
posed contacts, or quarantine of contacts without evidence of 
immunity do not reduce the risk of importation but can reduce 
R and the length of chains of transmission. An R hovering </p>

<p>approximately 0.86 does not indicate that endemic transmission 
will resume in Canada in the short term, but 10% of im-
portations are expected to result in outbreaks involving 25 
cases or more [17]. In contrast, with an R = 0.65, &lt;1% of impor-
tations in the United States are expected to trigger outbreaks of 
this size. 
An important limitation of this study is its reliance on passive 
surveillance, which is known to underestimate the number of </p>

<p>Measles in Canada Between 2002 and 2013 • OFID • 7 </p>

<p>cases, and despite great efforts since 1998, there is evidence of 
imperfect sensitivity of measles surveillance. For 37 (28%) of the 
130 chains of transmission measles cases, the imported case was 
not identified, indicating that surveillance missed several cases. 
This could be due to initial cases of measles not presenting to 
healthcare personnel, cases being misdiagnosed because front-
line physicians have little experience with measles or because of 
attenuated disease in individuals who are immunized or partial-
ly immunized. The underreporting is likely more substantial for 
vaccinated cases (imported or indigenous) because these cases 
can present with attenuated disease. Based on data gathered 
during the 2011 outbreak in Quebec, active investigation for 
cases and vaccination status in the most affected school found 
43% more cases than reported to the passive surveillance system 
(110 vs 77), with a significant difference according to vaccina-
tion status: there was a 21% increase in unvaccinated cases but a 
130% increase in fully vaccinated individuals [18]. Vaccinated 
cases may also remain IgM negative and, without an epidemio-
logical link to a laboratory-confirmed case, would not be in-
cluded in national case counts, if no other test (PCR, culture, 
or IgG) confirms a measles infection. In addition, visitors to 
Canada may not readily consult a Canadian physician when 
sick with measles. The diagnosis may be missed in mild cases, 
those consulting before rash onset, or even in cases with typical 
symptoms occurring outside an outbreak. To minimize the 
number of undiagnosed measles cases, it is essential to maintain 
a high suspicion index for frontline physicians and ensure their 
use of appropriate confirmatory tests. Another limitation of our 
current study is the absence of data at the national level, which 
would have allowed us to determine the proportion of cases due 
to visitors or those related to Canadians traveling. This variable 
has been added to the national surveillance system since 2011 
and will be available in the future. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Canada has successfully maintained elimination of measles be-
tween 2002 and 2013. Although more effective control measures 
coupled with better identification of imported cases may limit 
the size of outbreaks, it is the vulnerability of the population 
(reflected by the R) that poses the long-term challenge. Each 
year will add to the number and proportion of unprotected 
individuals in the entire population, slowly pushing the country 
towards the epidemic threshold. Maintaining elimination will 
require concerted efforts. For the public, this means getting 
immunized and seeking medical care when ill. Frontline 
providers will need (1) to maintain ongoing clinical suspicion 
to make the diagnosis and collect appropriate specimens and 
(2) to offer immunization to Canadians. For public health, 
the priorities will be to identify and vaccinate pockets of under-
immunized individuals and to rapidly and adequately respond 
to new cases. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Potential conflicts of interest. GDS has received research funds from 
GSK and has received travel fees reimbursement to attend an ad hoc advi-
sory board for GSK. No other authors reported conflicts. 
All authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential 
Conflicts of Interest. 
Funding. This work has been supported by the Public Health Agency of 
Canada. </p>







<p>Measles in Canada Between 2002 and 2013 • OFID • 9 </p>

</text></tei>