<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4386214" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Aims: The aim of this study was to develop and </p>

<p>implement guidelines for sedation and analgesia 
management in the paediatric intensive care unit 
(PICU) and evaluate the impact, feasibility and 
acceptability of these as part of a programme of 
research in this area and as a prelude to future trial 
work. </p>

<p>Method: This pilot study used a pre-post design </p>

<p>using a historical control. </p>

<p>Setting: Two PICUs at different hospitals in an </p>

<p>Australian metropolitan city. </p>

<p>Participants: Patients admitted to the PICU and </p>

<p>ventilated for ≥24 h, aged more than 1 month and not 
admitted for seizure management or terminal care. </p>

<p>Intervention: Guidelines for sedation and analgesia </p>

<p>management for critically ill children including 
algorithm and assessment tools. </p>

<p>Outcome variables: In addition to key outcome </p>

<p>variables (ventilation time, medication dose and 
duration, length of stay), feasibility outcomes data 
(recruitment, data collection, safety) were evaluated. 
Guideline adherence was assessed through chart audit 
and staff were surveyed about merit and the use of 
guidelines. </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Detailed outline of the guideline development 
process based on the consensus paper and 
available evidence. 
▪ Original dual site feasibility ( pilot) study testing 
the impact of guidelines on patient, quality and 
practice outcomes. 
▪ Generation of clinical and trial process data to 
inform future trial work. 
▪ No firm evidence or 'cause and effect' can be 
concluded due to the pre/post study design and 
small sample size. </p>

<p>Keogh SJ, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006428. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006428 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>being as well as healthcare costs. 7-9 These risks are poten-
tially amplified in the critically ill child in the paediatric 
ICU (PICU) due to the developing brain. 10 11 The aim of 
this study was to develop and implement guidelines for 
sedation and analgesia management in the PICU and 
evaluate the impact, feasibility and acceptability of these 
as a part of programme of research in this area and as a 
prelude to future trial work. </p>

<p>BACKGROUND 
The 2006 consensus guidelines on sedation and anal-
gesia in critically ill children established a standard for 
clinical practice in PICUs. 12 The guidelines' key recom-
mendations include advice on a loading dose and 
administration for analgesia and sedation medication, 
the use of validated pain and sedation assessment tools, 
withdrawal assessment, and the inclusion of non-
pharmacological interventions. Surveys of sedation and 
analgesia management in PICUs have identified a lack 
of specific protocols for sedation and analgesia manage-
ment. 13-15 This research has also highlighted wide 
variations in physician practice, nursing assessment, 
pharmacological agents, as well as administrative 
methods and doses. Limited use of assessment tools has 
also been reported, and there were no measurements or 
guidelines for withdrawal of drugs. 
A number of studies have attempted to evaluate the 
impact of sedation and analgesia guidelines in PICU; 
however, the results have been varied. 16-20 Each of the 
studies successively added to our knowledge and under-
standing of sedation and analgesia management in crit-
ically ill children. However, differences in guideline 
specifics, models of care and study design may have con-
tributed to the varied outcomes observed in the studies 
and limited their ability to inform best clinical practice. 
The aim of this study was to develop sedation and anal-
gesia management guidelines based on the 2006 consen-
sus recommendation and test their impact on patient 
outcomes as well as feasibility and acceptability in prac-
tice as a prelude to rigorous trial evaluation of guide-
lines in practice. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Aims and objectives of study 
The aim of this study was to develop and implement 
guidelines for sedation and analgesia management in 
the PICU and, following this, evaluate the impact, and 
acceptability and feasibility of their use in the clinical 
setting. </p>

<p>Study design 
This dual site study used a pragmatic pretest and post-test 
design to examine the feasibility and impact of the guide-
lines on patient and practice outcomes. A chart audit was 
used to assess the implementation fidelity and a 
(nursing) staff survey was conducted to ascertain staff </p>

<p>perceptions of guideline utility and acceptability in prac-
tice. The requirement for consent was waived. </p>

<p>Setting 
The study units were two eight-bed, mixed medical-sur-
gical (not cardiac surgery) PICUs located at tertiary 
referral children's hospitals admitting patients from 0 to 
16 years of age. Postregistration qualifications in either 
paediatrics, ICU or PICU, were held by approximately 
48% of the nursing staff. </p>

<p>Sample and participants 
The target population was all patients ventilated for 
≥24 h within the PICU, aged more than 1 month and 
not admitted for seizure management or terminal care. 
All eligible patients were consecutively enrolled into the 
study. As the main aim of the study was feasibility and 
acceptability of guidelines rather than hypothesis testing, 
the statistical power of the sample was of reduced 
importance at this stage. Charts of patients in the post-
implementation phase were the focus of the audit. All 
nursing staff were invited to participate in the survey 
gauging staff perceptions and use of the guidelines in 
practice. </p>

<p>Guideline development 
The sedation and analgesia guidelines for this study 
were developed around an algorithm for each of the 
identified phases of sedation (see online supplementary 
appendix 1). The key recommendations of the guide-
lines developed and tested in this study were based on 
the key recommendations in the 2006 consensus paper 
which are summarised in table 1. 12 
A range of non-pharmacological strategies to minimise 
patient stress and pain and optimise comfort are sup-
ported by varying levels of evidence ranging from case 
studies to Cochrane systematic reviews. These were not 
new strategies, but it was important to incorporate them 
into the guidelines to promote a holistic approach to 
pain and sedation management and reflect the recom-
mendations of the consensus guidelines. Strategies 
recommended were aimed at moderating the PICU 
environment where possible (ie, minimising high-
intensity light and noise, ensuring rest periods); 21 22 
minimising discomfort of invasive devices; regular repo-
sitioning and limb support with pillows, pressure reliev-
ing devices or swaddling; 23 24 monitoring and optimising 
hydration, nutrition and essential cares (eg, oral and eye 
care); supporting parental visitation and reassurance as 
well as therapeutic (non-technical) touch. 25 26 
New assessment scales for behavioural state, pain and 
withdrawal assessment were integral to the guidelines. 
These included the State Behaviour Scale (SBS), 27 28 
the Multidisciplinary Assessment of Pain Scale 
(MAPS) 29-32 
and 
the 
Opioid 
Benzodiazepine 
Withdrawal Assessment Scale (WAS). 33 34 
The three phases of sedation (acute, plateau and 
weaning) management were derived from patterns </p>



<p>Keogh SJ, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006428. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006428 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>observed in a retrospective audit conducted earlier by 
the research team 35 36 and from the literature. 9 12 37-39 
The guidelines reflect the dynamic nature of a PICU 
patient's admission and allow for movement between 
and within phases according to the patient's need, 
response and condition. 
As the main aim of the guidelines was to improve con-
sistency in medication practices, it was vital to get a con-
sensus on prescribing practices within the study units. 
Even the authors of the consensus guidelines noted that 
there was limited evidence to draw on and the recom-
mendations were based on knowledge of drug pharma-
cokinetics, case study reports, expert opinion and also 
the understanding of pain management, drug tolerance 
and withdrawal medicine. Morphine and midazolam are 
the most common analgesic and sedative agents used in 
PICUs 3 14 35 40 and the drugs of choice in the study 
units. They are typically used in combination as together 
they have a synergistic effect that often allows for use of 
lower doses. Midazolam doses can be reduced as much 
as 30-50% when combined with an opioid. 41 
Nonetheless, prolonged and/or heavy sedation persists 
in critical care units, and as a result tolerance and with-
drawal syndrome complicate recovery. </p>

<p>In the acute phase, the guidelines proposed a signifi-
cant loading dose to achieve the desired analgesia and 
sedation goals, followed by regular patient assessment 
and incremental medication changes to achieve and 
maintain these goals. If the maximum dose allowed was 
reached (ie, 300 μg/kg/h for the past 4 h), then use of 
adjunct or alternative drugs was recommended (ie, clo-
nidine, fentanyl). 'Drug cycling' has been reported to 
be helpful in the UK, where 25% of PICUs surveyed 
reported rotation of sedatives to minimise tolerance. 3 In 
another paper, consultant intensivists conducted 
biweekly chart reviews of each patient in the ICU and 
regularly changed their sedation regimens. 42 Although 
these authors imply success with drug tolerance, no 
numerical data was offered in support. 
Once in the plateau phase, the key change in practice 
was the recommended conversion from intravenous to 
long-acting enteral agents. This approach is based on 
the principles of narcotic withdrawal where withdrawal 
syndrome is managed by conversion to an orally active 
drug with a longer half-life (such as methadone or 
diazepam) that has a more steady state serum concentra-
tion, more readily facilitating a slow tapering of the drug 
and minimising the severity of withdrawal symptoms or </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary of 2006 consensus paper recommendations for sedation management of critically ill children </p>

<p>1. Non-pharmacological interventions 
i. Any correctable environmental and physical factors causing discomfort should 
be addressed alongside the introduction of pharmacological agents 
ii. A normal pattern of sleep should be encouraged. Attention should be paid to 
lighting, environmental noise and temporal orientation of patients 
2. Pain assessment and analgesic 
management </p>

<p>i. All critically ill children have the right to adequate relief of their pain. Local and 
regional anaesthetic techniques should be considered. A patient controlled 
analgesia (PCA) device may be useful in older children 
ii. Pain assessment should be performed regularly by using a scale appropriate to 
the age of the patient and routinely documented. The level of pain reported by 
the patient must be considered the current standard of analgesia. Patients who 
cannot communicate should be assessed for the presence of pain-related 
behaviours and physiological indicators of pain. A therapeutic plan for analgesia 
should be established for each patient and regularly reviewed 
iii. Recommended pharmacological agents for analgesia include opioids (eg, 
morphine, fentanyl) for the relief of severe pain, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory 
drugs (NSAIDs) for moderately severe pain, and paracetamol for mild to 
moderate pain 
3. Sedation assessment and 
recommended or commonly used 
sedative agents </p>

<p>i. Adequate analgesia should be provided to all critically ill children regardless of 
the need for sedation. The use of clinical guidelines for sedation is 
recommended 
ii. The level of sedation should be regularly assessed and documented using a 
validated and age-appropriate sedation assessment scale. The desired level of 
sedation should be identified for each patient and regularly reassessed. Doses 
of sedative agents should be titrated to produce the desired level of sedation 
iii. Recommended pharmacological agents for sedation include midazolam or 
clonidine. Early use of enteral sedative agents (eg, chloral hydrate, 
promethazine) is recommended. Propofol should not be used to provide 
continuous sedation in critically ill children 
4. Withdrawal syndrome assessment, 
prevention and management </p>

<p>i. The potential for opioid and benzodiazepine withdrawal syndrome should be 
considered after 7 days of continuous therapy 
ii. When subsequently discontinued, the doses of these agents may need to be 
routinely tapered </p>

<p>Keogh SJ, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006428. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006428 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>even development of the withdrawal syndrome. 43-46 The 
advantages of methadone are an oral bioavailability of 
75-80%, allowing for oral administration, and a pro-
longed half-life of 12-24 h, allowing twice daily adminis-
tration (ibid). There is a general reluctance to use 
diazepam for critically ill patients because of its long 
elimination and concerns about excessive and pro-
longed sedation. However, similar to methadone, diaze-
pam's long-acting active metabolites theoretically should 
result in small changes in serum drug concentrations 
and may decrease fluctuations in sedation state and 
therefore be a more appropriate agent for long-term 
sedated patients. 39 
The formal acknowledgement of a sedation weaning 
phase with a dedicated assessment tool and tapering 
regime was new practice for the study units. No validated 
opioid or benzodiazepine weaning schedule was found; 
however, a consensus of opinion across the literature 
supports a daily reduction of 5-10% or an initial reduc-
tion of 20-40%, followed by a 10% reduction once or 
twice daily, depending on the patient response. 39 47 The 
protocol for sedation weaning incorporated into these 
guidelines approximated these recommendations. </p>

<p>Guideline implementation 
The guidelines encompassed many changes in practice: 
new assessment scales, standardisation of practice, con-
version to oral agents, algorithms and a discreet weaning 
pathway. In the interest of maximising staff understand-
ing and uptake of the tools, a phased implementation 
process was adopted with the gradual introduction of 
each tool into the units, followed by orientation and 
implementation of the algorithm phases and medication 
administration. Staff in-services introducing the study 
and guidelines were held over an initial fortnight with 
phased introduction and implementation of each assess-
ment tool over the following months. These were 
further supported by bedside education on tool use and 
supplemented by information and teaching aids on the 
units' computer system. 
In practice, the PICU team set sedation and analgesia 
goals as part of the daily patient review and staff at the 
bedside (usually nurses) used the guidelines to achieve 
the set goals. </p>

<p>Outcome variables 
Data were collected from all eligible patients over 
24 months (12 months historical control and 12 months 
post-implementation), plus a break to allow for the 
implementation period. In addition to the main study 
outcomes, the pilot study collected outcomes to establish 
feasibility of the protocol and processes. The main study 
outcomes measured included total ventilation time 
(TVT), sedation doses and duration, LOS in the PICU, 
plus quality indicators, such as accidental extubation 
and readmission rates. It was important to establish that 
the outcomes were not adversely affected by the guide-
lines before considering larger and more extensive trial </p>

<p>work. Feasibility data outcomes included the success of 
screening and recruitment strategies; data collection and 
entry processes; confirmation of Research Nurse time 
and cost, and produced further estimates of ventilation 
times and medication dosing, which can be used to 
finalise sample size requirements for the larger trial, and 
inform funding applications for same. Potentially con-
founding variables collected included patient age, 
gender, diagnosis and the Paediatric Index of Mortality 
(PIM2) as a measure of acuity. Nurses in the study 
setting routinely collect and record standard demo-
graphic and biophysiological patient measurements on 
the local computerised information system. The revised 
PIM2 is a simple model of mortality in PICU based on 
admission data and uses 10 explanatory variables. 48 
Post-implementation compliance/fidelity was assessed by 
chart review using an audit tool based on the 19 key 
components of the guidelines. Adherence to 75% of the 
key components overall and then within each phase was 
nominally chosen as the minimum acceptable value for 
fidelity at this stage. However, the results whatever they 
were would inform any future implementation processes 
and trial work. Nursing staff perceptions of the guide-
lines were ascertained through administration of a 
researcher-developed survey with questions on ease of 
use, impact on practice, perceived benefit, facilitation of 
team management and promotion of nurse autonomy at 
the bedside. Staff members were also given the oppor-
tunity to comment on strengths and limitations of the 
guidelines. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Data were analysed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">PASW</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">V.18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>.). 
Descriptive statistics were used for demographic data. 
Continuous values reported were medians and ranges 
due to the large spread of the data. Categorical variables 
were 
reported 
as 
counts 
and 
percentages. 
Non-parametric Mann-Whitney or Cross tabulation and 
Pearson's χ 2 were performed to compare groups. The 
probability of remaining ventilated between groups was 
analysed using survival analysis. Adherence to guidelines 
was reported in counts and percentages. The influence 
of diagnostic group on guideline adherence was ana-
lysed using Pearson's correlation and comparison of 
means using Student t test. Survey responses were 
reported in counts and percentages as well as significant 
themes derived from qualitative data. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
During the two study periods (12 months each), 173 
and 235 patients were ventilated in the respective pregui-
deline and postguideline implementation periods. After 
screening for eligibility, 75 and 70 patients were enrolled 
into the pre and post groups. Seven patients were lost to 
the study in the post-test group because of deviation 
from research protocol (n=5), one group of parents did 
not consent to use the drugs, and one was transferred to </p>



<p>Keogh SJ, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006428. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006428 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>another hospital. Ultimately, there were 75 in the 
control group and 63 in the post-implementation group. 
Data were analysed on a per-protocol basis. Figure 1 
demonstrates the sampling framework and exclusion 
criteria. 
Table 2 shows the main characteristics measured for 
each sample. Both groups were comparable with no sig-
nificant differences between age, weight, sex or reason 
for admission. There were also no differences identified 
between the TVT and LOS for each group. There were 
no incidents of accidental extubation or readmission 
within 48 h for participants in either group for the study. 
Table 3 shows the different drug characteristics 
between groups, demonstrating a greater variance in </p>

<p>drug usage. The decrease of 19 h in the median infusion 
time of morphine between groups approached signifi-
cance (87 vs 68 h, p=0.059). There were changes in the 
median minimum and maximum morphine doses, 
though not significantly. A reduction of 11 h was identi-
fied with median infusion of midazolam between groups; 
however, this difference was not significant. Significant 
changes in the median minimum and maximum doses of 
midazolam were observed (minimum 10 vs 17 μg/kg/h, 
p&lt;0.001 and maximum 120 vs 180 μg/kg/h, p&lt;0.001). 
Applying the Kaplan-Meier curve of risk to the prob-
ability of remaining ventilated to each group demon-
strated that the post-test group did not have an 
increased risk of remaining ventilated (see figure 2). </p>

<p>Figure 1 Sample framework (adm, admission; excl, exclusion; incl, inclusion). </p>

<p>Table 2 Baseline characteristics in the study groups </p>

<p>Pre, n=75 
Post, n=63 
Statistic </p>

<p>Age (years), median (IQR) 
2.08 (5.6) 
1.75 (4.5) 
NS 
Mann-Whitney 
Weight (kg), median (IQR) 
11.5 (15.62) 
12 (11) 
NS 
Mann-Whitney 
Sex, N (%) 
Male, 45 (60%) 
Male, 38 (60%) 
NS 
χ 2 
Primary diagnosis, N (%) 
Resp, 29 (39%) 
Resp, 21 (33%) 
NS 
χ 2 
PIM, median (IQR) 
5.00 (9) 
5.20 (5.3) 
NS 
Mann-Whitney 
TVT (days), median (IQR) 
4.02 (5.36) 
3.12 (7.68) 
NS 
Mann-Whitney 
LOS (days), median (IQR) 
6.3 (6.76) 
5.8 (7.90) 
NS 
Mann-Whitney </p>

<p>NS=not statistically significant, that is, p≥0.05. 
LOS, length of stay; PIM, Paediatric Index of Mortality; TVT, total ventilation time. </p>

<p>Keogh SJ, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006428. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006428 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>The probability of remaining ventilated was reduced in 
the post-test group (by just less than a day at 21 h); 
however, this was not statistically significant. 
Other observed changes in practice were the greater 
use of adjunctive and alternative medication, in particu-
lar methadone. Results showed that, prior to the guide-
line implementation, there was limited use of alternative 
medications (1-2 alternative medications or even none). 
Post-guideline implementation the numbers of alterna-
tive medications used increased. A more detailed ana-
lysis revealed a significant difference with the use of 
methadone pre 3%-post 33%, p&lt;0.001; diazepam pre 
5%-post 25%, p=0.001; chloral hydrate pre 32%-post 
58%, p=0.002; propofol pre 60%-post 20%, p&lt;0.001; 
and neuromuscular blockade agents pre 60%-post 
47.6%, not significant. </p>

<p>Implementation fidelity (chart audit) 
Sixty-three charts from the post-implementation period 
were reviewed to identify the level of staff adherence to 
the 19 key components of the guidelines and quantify 
the level of assessment and scoring. Overall adoption 
was achieved in 23 (36%) of the charts audited. 
Separate analysis within each of the phases demon-
strated that adoption was achieved in 30 (47.6%) in the 
acute phase, 23 (36.5%) in the plateau phase and 25 
(39.7%) in the weaning phase. Pain and sedation scores 
were assessed and documented in 95% (n=60) of charts 
in the acute and plateau phases, and in 85% (n=54) of 
charts in the weaning phase. The withdrawal score was 
assessed and documented appropriately in 75% (n=47) 
of charts. </p>

<p>Staff survey 
The response rate was 49% (n=54). Participants' 
responses were divided into four categories: awareness/ 
use, strengths, limitations and suggestions for improve-
ment. Fifty-two (96%) respondents stated they regularly 
referred to the guideline to assist with decision-making 
and to provide prompts and cues. There appeared to be 
some confusion as to who was primarily responsible for 
the initiation of the guidelines, with 12 (23%) suggest-
ing that it is was the consultant's responsibility and 32 
(60%) stating that it was the responsibility of the bedside 
nurse. Table 4 outlines further responses. 
The perceived strengths of the tool included the struc-
tured nature of the guidelines, promotion of consistency 
in practice and the resulting increased awareness regard-
ing sedation management. Conversely, the perceived lim-
itations included the perceived complexity of algorithm, 
confusion with delineation and movement between 
phases, and the lack of accommodation of increased 
drug tolerance with long-term patients. Staff suggested 
simplifying the algorithm and using larger print, incorp-
orating recommendations for short-term patients and 
providing clinical example as guides. Box 1 provides a 
sample of staff comments on the perceived strengths 
and weaknesses of the guidelines. Overall, four major 
themes were expressed by study participants (see box 1): 
(1) a knowledge deficit about some aspects of the </p>

<p>Table 3 Outcome variable comparison between study groups </p>

<p>Pre, n=75 
Median (IQR) </p>

<p>Post, n=63 
Median (IQR) 
Difference and statistic </p>

<p>Morphine 
Infusion duration (h) 
87 (136.5) 
68 (78) 
−19 h p=0.059 
Minimum dose (μg/kg/h) 
10 (11) 
17 (10) 
+7 μg /kg/h NS 
Maximum dose (μg/kg/h) 
120 (102.25) 
97.5 (52.75) 
−22.5 μg /kg/h NS 
Midazolam 
Infusion duration (h) 
71 (154) 
60 (90) 
−11 h NS 
Minimum dose (μg /kg/h) 
10 (12) 
24 (20) 
+14 μg/kg/h p&lt;0.001 
Maximum dose (μg/kg/h) 
120 (101.75) 
180 (143.25) 
+60 μg/kg/h p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>NS=not statistically significant, that is, p≥0.05. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Kaplan-Meier curve of risk of remaining ventilated 
between groups. </p>



<p>Keogh SJ, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006428. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006428 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>guidelines, (2) high value placed on individualised 
patient care, (3) perceived ineffectiveness of the guide-
lines for some patients and (4) disagreement between 
doctors and nurses on responsibilities. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
This pragmatic pilot study demonstrated the use of 
guideline-directed sedation and analgesia management 
was not associated with increased ventilation times or 
PICU LOS. The results of the study also showed that the 
guidelines were generally feasible and acceptable in clin-
ical practice with predominantly positive feedback from 
nursing staff using them. Full adoption of all aspects of 
guidelines was not realised, but results demonstrated 
improved levels of patient assessment and increased use of 
enteral agents (in line with guideline recommendations). 
The observed increases in median minimum and 
maximum doses of morphine and midazolam do not 
appear to be associated with an increase in patient TVT 
or LOS, and in fact the duration of each infusion was 
reduced. Similar changes in medication administration 
have been observed in other PICU guideline studies. 16-20 
The results of the Kaplan-Meier Risk analysis indicate 
that there was potentially a reduced risk of remaining venti-
lated in the post-test group (though this was not statistically 
significant). However, a median difference of 21 h between 
groups may be viewed as 'clinically significant' as this time 
difference in the clinical setting could translate to earlier 
extubation and/or discharge. Larger randomised trial 
studies are warranted to allow firm conclusions to be made. 
Only a small proportion of participants were ultimately 
eligible for the study (43% and 31%, respectively), 
which has implications for the projected timeline, 
research assistant time and costs and data collection for 
a larger multisite trial. The results also revealed the 
huge spread of the clinical data and the challenge this 
posed for researchers. Follow-on studies would possibly 
need to consider subcategories of patients, that is, short-
term, medium-term and long-term ventilated, and 
analyse them within these categories. 
The guidelines and implementation process in this 
study also appear to have increased the awareness and 
usage of alternative medications to complement or 
replace morphine/midazolam. This was particularly 
evident with the use of methadone and diazepam. Use 
of methadone rose from 3% pretest to 33% post-test. 
Use of diazepam rose from 5% pretest to 25% post-test. 
One of the key recommendations to emerge from the 
literature, and therefore included in the guidelines, was 
the transition from continuous intravenous analgesia 
and sedation to regular oral agents. Prolonged adminis-
tration of opioids and benzodiazepines may result in the 
development of drug tolerance and then withdrawal syn-
drome if these agents are abruptly discontinued. 9 38 49 50 
Research has shown that this can be prevented by slowly 
tapering the intravenous administration of the drug or 
switching from intravenous morphine and midazolam to 
orally active drugs with a longer half-life, such as metha-
done and diazepam. 44 46 In general, the increased use 
of adjunct medication was evidence of the clinician's use 
of guideline recommendations. 
Sedation, Pain and Withdrawal scores were all cap-
tured but difficult to summarise meaningfully as a </p>

<p>Table 4 Staff perceptions of sedation guidelines in 
practice </p>

<p>Questions </p>

<p>Yes 
response 
n=54 (%) </p>

<p>The sedation guidelines and flow chart are 
easy to follow </p>

<p>58.5 </p>

<p>The flow chart facilitates the sedation 
management process </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>Patients benefit from having a constructive 
escalation programme </p>

<p>96.3 </p>

<p>Patients benefit from having a constructive 
titration programme </p>

<p>94.3 </p>

<p>Patients benefit from having a constructive 
weaning programme </p>

<p>96.2 </p>

<p>A multidisciplinary approach enhances 
sedation management </p>

<p>96.3 </p>

<p>The guidelines give me more autonomy in 
managing sedation </p>

<p>68.5 </p>

<p>The guidelines improve overall sedation 
management </p>

<p>88.5 </p>

<p>Box 1 Staff perceptions of strengths and limitations of 
sedation guidelines </p>

<p>Strengths 
▸ The bedside nurse 'knows' the patient and their requirements, 
can initiate changes, use objective data on the screen, see 
changes and ask for a review if needed 
▸ It is a clinical tool to justify an increase or decrease in sed-
ation. Allows for uniform/consistent decision-making 
▸ Empowers and rationalises nursing changes in sedation 
▸ Everyone using the same guide should translate to more con-
sistent care. There is more autonomy for nurses, particularly 
with less experienced registrars. It potentially irons out varia-
tions in individual consultant preferences 
▸ It has increased the awareness among staff and prompts 
discussion 
▸ It places importance on sedation and assists nurses to provide 
better sedation. Patients more comfortable equals parents 
more comfortable 
Limitations 
▸ Can be complicated because of the amount of detail 
▸ Needs definitions and differential diagnoses for each of the 
phases 
▸ Not all patients fit the guidelines or respond as predicted 
▸ Requires full concentration with attention to detail and practice 
to become familiar 
▸ Lack of medical leadership/ownership shared 
▸ Difficult to continue in ward, particularly with weaning 
▸ Have trouble with some long-term patients following the 
guidelines and keeping them comfortable </p>

<p>Keogh SJ, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006428. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006428 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>research variable. We recommended that a useful vari-
able for follow-up in studies would be to calculate the 
percentage of time each patient spent in a designated 
'zone' and determining the appropriateness and 
success/failure of management accordingly. 
The audit of implementation fidelity demonstrated 
that the assessment and documentation of patient's pain 
and sedation was well recorded, reflecting sound staff 
understanding and uptake of the new assessment tools. 
The adoption score for the withdrawal phase was the 
lowest of the three phases, which may have resulted from 
less familiarity and knowledge with the tool and phase. 
This is consistent with findings found in a review of 
similar studies. 51 Suggested reasons for non-adherence 
included complexity of the guideline or algorithm, staff 
not valuing or understanding the goal of the guideline 
and perceived redundancy of the guideline if the staff 
were already competent practitioners in this area (ibid). 
Potential solutions to these issues included ongoing staff 
education and timely feedback related to the guideline to 
continuously reinforce importance, ease of use and 
troubleshoot issues. 52 In addition to surveying staff 
opinion, it is also important to conduct periodic chart 
audits to quantify guideline fidelity. This will help minim-
ise self-report bias as was reflected somewhat in this 
study. 53 Staff perceptions of guideline principles and use 
were positive, although the level of adherence was vari-
able. So the full impact of the guidelines was not realised. 
In conjunction with the audit, a survey of nursing staff 
perceptions and attitudes was undertaken to establish if 
these influenced adoption of the guidelines. In line with 
other similar studies, nurses were largely positive and 
constructive in their feedback. 18 16 54 All feedback has 
been utilised to improve the guidelines. Involving staff 
and providing feedback during the process of proced-
ural change is a vital step in optimising follow trial 
success and ultimately translation to practice. Follow-on 
trials should also build in mechanisms to capture multi-
disciplinary staff experience and feedback. 
The importance of the findings of this study is that 
they indicate that collaborative guidelines can be used to 
manage the PICU patient's comfort and pain without 
compromising quality of care (TVT, LOS, quality indica-
tors). The results are similar to those in the adult popu-
lation where guideline or protocol-driven sedation has 
been linked to a reduction in duration of continuous 
intravenous sedation, ventilation time and associated 
healthcare costs. 55-59 Evaluation of feasibility outcomes 
has aided in the development of a realistic plan regard-
ing participant recruitment, staff education to optimise 
guideline fidelity, safety of guidelines in clinical practice 
and collection of key outcome variables. </p>

<p>IMPLICATIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS 
No definitive causal effect can be attributed to the guide-
lines on outcomes due to the pre-post study design and 
small sample size. Full adoption of all phases and tools in </p>

<p>the guidelines was not realised and this has implications 
for ongoing implementation and larger trial work. 
Additionally, the small response rate and selective popula-
tion for the survey may introduce some bias in the 
current understanding of staff acceptance of the guide-
lines. A more inclusive (medical and nursing) survey 
population is recommended for follow-up research. 
Conducting the study in two units assists with the general-
isability of the study and its results. Some specifics of the 
guidelines and algorithm, however, might need modifica-
tion to reflect local practice, for example, use of different 
drugs (fentanyl instead of morphine) and different 
patient populations ( post cardiothoracic surgery). 
The study results are most useful in informing the 
structure and outcome measures for a follow-on clinical 
trial in this area. 
Results from the study, audit and survey have informed 
changes and modifications to optimise staff understand-
ing and use of sedation guidelines in practice. Weaning 
from sedation agents and the concept of withdrawal 
appear to be areas of practice that need more attention. 
The researchers went on to trial and evaluate a revised 
withdrawal assessment tool and a study comparing the 
outcomes of dexmedetomidine versus midazolam is 
about to start. The study units plan to continue to use 
the guidelines and tools in their modified form pending 
the results of a larger trial work recently completed 
in the USA. The modern ICU is an important focus for 
quality improvement efforts. Guidelines cannot automat-
ically guarantee improved quality of care; however, they 
do direct the clinician in the pursuit of this objective, 
particularly when supported by high-level evidence. </p>

<p>Funding This study was funded by a Queensland Health Nursing Research 
Grant. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Royal Children's Hospitals Human Research and Ethics 
Committee (HREC/05/QRCH/19). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement A copy of the guidelines is supplied as an appendix 
or can be made available by emailing Debbie.Long2@health.qld.gov.au. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Keogh SJ, et al. BMJ Open 2015;5:e006428. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006428 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>





<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>