<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4472590" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Study Design: A cross-sectional, descriptive study. 
Purpose: This study aimed to investigate the relationship between kyphosis and lordosis measured by using a flexible ruler and mus-
culoskeletal pain in students of Hamadan University of Medical Sciences. 
Overview of Literature: The spine supports the body during different activities by maintaining appropriate body alignment and pos-
ture. Normal alignment of the spine depends on its structural, muscular, bony, and articular performance. 
Methods: Two hundred forty-one students participated in this study. A single examiner evaluated the angles of lumbar lordosis and 
thoracic kyphosis by using a flexible ruler. To determine the severity and frequency of pain in low-back and inter-scapular regions, a 
tailor-made questionnaire with visual analog scale was used. Finally, using the Kendall correlation coefficient, the data were statisti-
cally analyzed. 
Results: The mean value of lumbar lordosis was 34.46°±12.61° in female students and 22.46°±9.9° in male students. The mean value 
of lumbar lordosis significantly differed between female and male students (p&lt;0.001). However, there was no difference in the level 
of the thoracic curve (p=0.288). Relationship between kyphosis measured by using a flexible ruler and inter-scapular pain in male and 
female students was not significant (p=0.946). However, the relationship between lumbar lordosis and low back pain was statistically 
significant (p=0.006). Also, no significant relationship was observed between abnormal kyphosis and frequency of inter-scapular pain, 
and between lumbar lordosis and low back pain. 
Conclusions: Lumbar lordosis contributes to low back pain. The causes of musculoskeletal pain could be muscle imbalance and 
muscle and ligament strain. </p>

<p>Clinical Study </p>

<p>Asian Spine J 2015;9(3):416-422 • http://dx.Spine with a lateral S-shaped curve is an important com-</p>

<p>ponent of the body skeleton. This structure supports the 
body during different activities by maintaining appropri-
ate body alignment and posture [1,2]. </p>

<p>Relationship between kyphosis and lordosis and thoracic and lumbar pain </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>Normal alignment of the spine depends on its structur-
al, muscular, bony, and articular performance; therefore, 
weakness of the spinal muscles can lead to static and dy-
namic imbalances of the body which are generally called 
positional abnormalities [2]. Skeletal abnormalities result 
from lack of motion and inappropriate movement pat-
terns, which have undesirable effects on the psychological, 
social, and physiological function [3]. 
Hyperkyphosis or postural round back is a common 
spinal deformity with a prevalence of 15.3% in Western 
societies [3] and 13.2% in Iranian high school students 
[4]. Congenital anomalies, neuro-muscular disorders, 
Scheuermann disease, and positional difficulties play an 
important role in causing thoracic kyphosis. Increasing 
the arch of the thoracic spine known as kyphosis along 
with the shortening of the thoracic muscles and weakness 
of the respiratory muscles affect the pulmonary system by 
decreasing the thoracic volume and lung volume [5]. 
Thoracic pain is one of the common conditions found 
in all of the societies and nowadays its prevalence is in-
creasing following a decrease in mobility, an increase in 
weight of the trunk, inappropriate positioning of the spine 
during daily activities, and increasing use of computers [6]. 
Physical activities, extensor exercises, and constant con-
trol of kyphosis by orthopedic surgeons are the examples 
of related treatments [7]. If kyphosis is progressive, a 
brace needs to be applied [8]. In that case, ongoing assess-
ment of kyphosis is essential to control the thoracic curve 
and to evaluate the outcomes of the treatment. 
Lumbar lordosis is the ventral curvature of the spine 
formed by wedging of the lumbar vertebrae and interver-
tebral discs [9]. Several studies have indicated the clinical 
and functional importance of lumbar lordosis [10]. Lum-
bar lordosis is a key component in maintaining the sagittal 
balance. According to some studies as lordosis increases, 
thoracic kyphosis also increases; however, some studies 
have indicated that an increase in lordosis is accompanied 
by a decrease in kyphosis [11,12]. The abnormal lumbar 
curvature can lead to imbalance in the standing position 
[2]. 
Medical examinations have shown that lumbar pain 
rarely has pathophysiological causes [13]. Pain intensifies 
at night following muscular weakness and in the morning 
and decreases after daily activities [14]. 
Assessment of kyphosis is usually performed via lateral 
radiography of the spine imposed on an X-ray [15]. Con-
tinuous radiography is expensive and also potentially life-</p>

<p>threatening [16]; hence, researchers have attempted to 
perform this assessment via non-invasive techniques [15]. 
The use of a flexible ruler as a means of non-invasive 
measurement of kyphosis and lordosis is cheap and ac-
cessible with a simple application [16]. Therefore, the 
goal of the present study was to evaluate the kyphosis and 
lordosis angles by using a flexible ruler and their relation-
ship with pain severity and frequency in male and female 
students. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>In this observational, cross-sectional, descriptive study, 
241 (157 females and 84 males) students of Hamadan 
University of Medical Sciences were enrolled. 
Sample size was calculated based on the number of 
newly entered students to the above mentioned university 
(650 female students, 350 male students) and the popula-
tion ratio (p) of 68% from previous studies. The present 
study was ethically approved by the related committee of 
Hamadan University of medical sciences. All participants 
took part in the study with full awareness and voluntarily. 
Students who had experienced rheumatologic or neuro-
logical pain and orthopedic diseases such as idiopathic 
scoliosis and difference in leg length discrepancy were ex-
cluded [1]. A pain questionnaire was used to examine the 
severity and frequency of the lumbar and inter-scapular 
pain. Pain severity was assessed via a visual numerical 
scale from 0 to 10. 
Pain frequency was measured as follows: never or 
rarely (perceived pain, once a month or less), sometimes 
(perceived pain, twice or three times a month), and often 
(perceived pain, once to three times a week or more) [1]. 
A flexible ruler was used to examine the thoracic and 
lumbar curvature. Validity and reliability studies for the 
flexible ruler and non-radiographic method have been 
performed previously [17]. 
The amount of lordosis and kyphosis was measured 
three times by a single examiner using a flexible ruler and 
the average value was reported. Also, the inter-observer 
correlation coefficient was 0.87 with a measurement error 
of 0.006. 
To assess the curvatures by using a flexible ruler, partic-
ipants were asked to stand in the normal anatomical posi-
tion with the examiner standing at the back. First lumbar 
(L 1 ) and second sacral (S 2 ) vertebrae were considered as 
markers for evaluating the lumbar curvature. In order to </p>

<p>Sedigheh-Sadat Mirbagheri et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2015;9(3):416-422 </p>

<p>identify S 2, the posterior superior iliac spine (PSIS) was 
marked. The midpoint between the two PSISs, according 
to Gray's Anatomy, was considered as the spinous process 
of the S 2 . 
To identify L 1 , the examiner pressed the lower back 
above the iliac crest in order to move the soft tissue later-
ally where the two thumbs reach horizontally together 
on the L 4 spinous process. By counting up the vertebrae, 
the L 1 spinous process was identified. Then, the flexible 
ruler was placed on L 1 and S 2 while a hand pressed on it 
to eliminate the gap between the ruler and the skin. The 
ruler was put on a sheet and the lumbar curve was drawn 
afterwards [18]. 
Measurement of the thoracic curvature was performed 
in a similar manner to that of the lumbar curvature. The 
only difference was that C7 and the junction of T12 and 
L1 were marked in order to measure the thoracic curva-
ture [19]. The thoracic curve was drawn by using a flex-
ible ruler. Two ends of the curve reached together, and 
a L line was drawn whose midline vertically reached the 
middle of the curve through the h line. The lengths of h 
and L lines were calculated and the aforementioned angle 
was obtained. The line was drawn from the side of the 
ruler which touched the skin. 
θ=4 arc tan 2 h/L 
Using descriptive statistics, mean values of kyphotic 
and lordotic angles and their prevalence based on gender 
were reported. 
Because of the misfit of the data to normal hypothesis, 
non-parametric tests such as the Mann-Whitney U test 
and non-parametric correlation tests of Gamma and 
Kendall were applied. Data processing was carried out via 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 16</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Mean values of lordotic and kyphotic angles are shown in 
Table 1. Mean value of the lumbar arch was 34.46°±12.61° </p>

<p>and 22.46°±9.9° in female students and male students, 
respectively. Lumbar lordosis showed a significant dif-
ference between the two student groups (p&lt;0.001), while 
there was no difference in the thoracic curvature (p=0.288) 
(Table 1). 
Table 2 indicates the prevalence of kyphosis accord-
ing to gender and angles of &lt;20, &gt;20 &amp; &lt;40, and &gt;40. In 
brief, 36.9% and 67.9% kyphotic angles of &lt;20, 16.8% and 
67.9% kyphotic angles of &gt;20 &amp; &lt;40, and 1.3% and 2.4% 
kyphotic angles of &gt;40, were identified in female students 
and male students, respectively (Table 2). 
Prevalence of lordosis based on gender and angles clas-
sified as &lt;30, &gt;30 &amp; &lt;50, and &gt;50 is presented in Table 3. 
In brief, 37.6% and 71.4 % &lt;30 lordosis, 49.7% and 
27.4% &gt;30 &amp; &lt;50 lordosis, and 12.7% and 1.2% &gt;50 lor-
dosis, were found in female students and male students, 
respectively (Table 3). 
Table 4 indicates the relationship between kyphosis and 
interscapular pain severity in male students, female stu-</p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison of the mean of lordotic and kyphotic angles in females and males </p>

<p>Female (n=157) 
Male (n=84) 
p-value 
Mean (SD) 
Min 
Max 
Mean (SD) 
Min 
Max </p>

<p>Measurement of lumbar curve (°) 
34.46 (12.61) 
5.73 
73.74 
22.46 (9.9) 
5.91 
50.12 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Measurement of thoracic curve (°) 
22.57 (7.08) 
5.73 
53.44 
23.56 (6.57) 
9.16 
42.16 
0.288 </p>

<p>SD, standard deviation; Min, minimum; Max, maximum. </p>

<p>Table 2. Prevalence of the kyphosis according to the gender (°) </p>

<p>Degree </p>

<p>Frequency (%) </p>

<p>Female 
Male 
Total </p>

<p>&lt;20 
58 (36.9) 
25 (29.8) 
83 (34.43) </p>

<p>&gt;20 &amp; &lt;40 
97 (61.8) 
57 (67.9) 
154 (63.9) </p>

<p>&gt;40 
2 (1.3) 
2 (2.4) 
4 (1.66) </p>

<p>Table 3. Prevalence of the lordosis according to the gender (°) </p>

<p>Degree </p>

<p>Frequency (%) </p>

<p>Female 
Male 
Total </p>

<p>&lt;30 
59 (37.6) 
60 (71.4) 
119 (49.83) </p>

<p>&gt;30 &amp; &lt;50 
78 (49.7) 
23 (27.4) 
101 (41.9) </p>

<p>&gt;50 
20 (12.7) 
1 (1.2) 
21 (8.71) </p>

<p>Relationship between kyphosis and lordosis and thoracic and lumbar pain </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>



<p>dents, and both, as well as the relationship between lordo-
sis and lumbar pain severity. 
No significant relationship was observed between ky-
phosis measured by using a flexible ruler and inter-scap-
ular pain in both student groups (p=0.946), whereas the 
relationship between lordosis and lumbar pain severity in 
the whole study sample was significant (p=0.006). 
There was no relationship between kyphosis and inter-
scapular pain frequency in male students and female stu-
dents and also in the whole study sample (p=0.068) (Table 
5). 
No significant relationship was found between kyphosis 
and lordosis in the whole study sample based on gender 
(p=0.331, Table 6). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The goal of this study was to investigate the prevalence 
of kyphosis and lordosis by using a flexible ruler and also 
of musculoskeletal pain and their relationship with pain 
severity and frequency in male and female students of 
Hamadan University of Medical Sciences. 
According to the results, the mean values of lordosis </p>

<p>and kyphosis were 34.46°±12.61° and 22.57°±7.08° in fe-
male students and 22.46°±9.9° and 23.56°±6.57° in male 
students, respectively. 
Many studies have proved the validity and reliability of 
using flexicurve in comparison with radiographic data. 
A systematic review of validity and reliability of the non-
radiographic method showed high to very high levels 
of reliability of the Flexicurve. This study suggested that 
flexicurve is an easy to use, hand-held tool, and it could 
replace radiography in evaluating lumbar lordosis [17]. 
However, with respect to cervical lordosis, there are some 
studies that showed that the flexicurve sagittal skin con-
tour measurement has poor concurrent validity compared 
to radiographic measurements [20]. It seems that postural 
or X-ray positioning and radiographic analysis lead to 
appearance of confounding variables, which affects the 
results. Also, obesity, muscular development, previous 
trauma, and biomechanical complexities of the cervical 
spine could result in some differences in the measurement 
of surface contour compared to lateral radiographs [20]. 
According to previous research, the flexicurve kyphosis 
angle provides strong validity and reliability. Furthermore, 
it is inexpensive and can be easily used by the entry-level 
research staff, requires short measurement time, and does 
not expose the patients to high radiation risk. It seems 
that the use of this measurement method for detection 
of spine abnormalities and examination of the posture in 
healthy subjects is quite beneficial [21]. 
On the other hand, postural age-related changes include 
a forward head, rounded shoulders, increased thoracic 
kyphosis, decreased lumbar lordosis, and flexed hips and </p>

<p>Table 4. Results of Kendall correlation test for investigating the relationship of kyphasis and lordosis with lumbar and inter-scapular pain in the 
whole sample </p>

<p>Inter-scapular pain (p-value) 
Back pain (p-value) </p>

<p>Female (n=157) Male (n=84) Total (n=241) 
Female (n=157) Male (n=84) Total (n=241) </p>

<p>Kyphosis 
0.799 
0.283 
0.946 
Lordosis 
0.808 
0.508 
0.006 </p>

<p>Table 5. Results of the Kendall correlation test for investigating the relationship of kyphosis and lordosis with frequency of the lumber and inter-
scapular pain in the whole sample </p>

<p>Inter-scapular pain frequency (p-value) 
Back pain frequency (p-value) </p>

<p>Female (n=157) Male (n=84) Total (n=241) 
Female (n=157) Male (n=84) Total (n=241) </p>

<p>Kyphosis 
0.798 
-
0.572 
Lordosis 
0.872 
-
0.068 </p>

<p>Table 6. Results of the Kendall correlation test for investigating the 
relationship of kyphosis and lordosis </p>

<p>Kyphosis (p-value) </p>

<p>Female (n=157) Male (n=84) Total (n=241) </p>

<p>Lordosis 
0.416 
0.101 
0.331 </p>

<p>Sedigheh-Sadat Mirbagheri et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2015;9(3):416-422 </p>

<p>knees [22]. With age, a progressive change occurs in the 
kyphotic angle in both genders [23]. However, there are 
limited evidences to illustrate the causes of age-related 
lumbar lordosis, and further research is required to de-
termine the influence of age on lordosis [22]. Therefore, 
in the present study, as all participants were young (aged 
between 19 to 21 years), we did not aim to evaluate the ef-
fect of age on the amount of kyphosis and lordosis. 
Lumbar lordosis showed a significant difference be-
tween both genders (p&lt;0.001); however, no difference was 
seen in the thoracic curve (p=0.288). In other words, the 
mean value of lordosis was higher in female students than 
in male students. The mean value of kyphosis was higher 
in male students than in female students, although this 
difference was not significant. 
Altogether, the lumbar curve was greater in female stu-
dents compared to male students in this study. Although 
some studies showed that lumbar lordosis is not different 
between females and males [24], results of the present 
study support the finding that lumbar curve is greater in 
females than in males [22]. 
The prevalence of abnormal kyphosis was 2.4% and 
1.2% in male students and female students, respectively. 
Therefore, abnormal kyphosis was more common in 
male students compared with female students. Abnormal 
lordosis was more common in female students than in 
male students (12.7% in female students and 1.2% in male 
students).The prevalence of kyphosis and lordosis beyond 
the normal range in students of Hamadan University of 
Medical Sciences was 1.66% and 8.71%, respectively. 
There was no significant relationship between kypho-
sis and inter-scapular pain in male students and female 
students and the whole study sample; while, they were 
significantly related in the study by Griegel-Morris et al. 
[1]. This difference in the result was most likely due to the 
different methods of measurement. In the present study, 
kyphosis was measured by using a flexible ruler which 
is more valid and subtle than observational assessment 
which could consider kyphosis of 20°-40° as an abnor-
mality. 
A significant relationship was observed between lumbar 
pain and lordosis in the whole study sample, although 
it was not significant according to gender. Therefore, it 
could be said that gender had no effect on the relationship 
between pain and severity of the abnormalities, which 
was probably due to the homogeneity of male and female 
students with respect to abnormality and pain. Several </p>

<p>factors are involved in causing low back pain such as disc 
degeneration, muscle stretch, age, and occupation [25]. 
Clinical observations indicate the role of postural anoma-
lies in low back pain [13]. In this study, lordosis in the stu-
dents was significantly related to low back pain, and this 
finding corresponded with that in the study by McKenzie 
[26] which showed that low back pain occurred as a result 
of long and inaccurate over-stretching of the soft tissue 
in an abnormal posture. That is, as the extensor muscles 
become overloaded during lordosis, low back pain may 
emerge. 
There was no significant relationship between the ab-
normality and pain frequency, which corresponded with 
the results of the study carried out in younger and older 
adults [1]. 
Since cervical, thoracic, and lumbar spinal regions are 
biomechanically related, any change in each arch might be 
due to the postural alteration in other arches [27]. In the 
present study, the relationship between lordosis and ky-
phosis was not significant. Perhaps, increasing the sample 
size could help in demonstrating a significant relationship 
between lordosis and kyphosis. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>According to the results, lordosis may play a key role in 
low back pain, which might result from muscular imbal-
ance and overstretching of the muscles and ligaments. 
Low back pain may also be caused by psychological fac-
tors, which usually cannot be controlled by the researcher 
in most studies. It could be concluded that through a 
simple examination of the spine, such abnormalities can 
be identified as well as chronic spinal pain can be pre-
vented. 
Findings of this study indicate the importance of pos-
tural evaluation in youth, in which chronic pain is rarely 
related to other diseases, and hence, the pain could be 
considered to occur as a result of inappropriate posture 
and can be managed by performing corrective exercises. 
Involvement of a team of professionals in occupational 
therapy, physical therapy, ergonomics, and orthopedic 
surgery is recommended in order to provide information 
to individuals about the anatomy and biomechanics of 
the spine, risk factors that contribute to abnormalities, 
accurate positions for sitting, standing, lying, carrying 
objects, and using instruments, and performing exercises 
to strengthen the weak muscles and correct the abnormal </p>

<p>Relationship between kyphosis and lordosis and thoracic and lumbar pain </p>

<p>Asian Spine Journal 
Asian Spine Journal </p>





<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>



<p>Sedigheh-Sadat Mirbagheri et al. 
 
Asian Spine J 2015;9(3):416-422 </p>



</text></tei>