<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4633460" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T03:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective(s): N-myc downstream regulated gene 2 (NDRG2) is a candidate gene for tumor suppression. 
The expression of NDRG2 is down-regulated in several tumors including lung cancer. The aim of this 
study was to explore the effect of NDRG2 overexpression on invasion, migration, and enzymatic 
activity of matrix metalloproteinase-2 (MMP-2) and -9 (MMP-9) in human lung adenocarcinoma A549 
cells. 
Materials and Methods: A recombinant plasmid encoding green fluorescent protein (GFP)-tagged 
NDRG2 (pCMV6-AC-NDRG2-GFP) was used to overexpress GFP-tagged NDRG2 in A549 cells. The cells 
in the experimental group and those in the control group were transfected with pCMV6-AC-NDRG2-
GFP and a control plasmid without NDRG2 (pCMV6-AC-GFP), respectively. Fluorescent microscopy and 
flowcytometry analysis of GFP expression were used to evaluate the cellular expression of GFP-tagged 
NDRG2 and the efficiency of transfection. The effects of NDRG2 expression on cell invasion and 
migration were evaluated using transwell filter migration assay. The gelatinase activity of secreted 
MMP-2 and MMP-9 was measured by gelatin zymography. 
Results: Our results demonstrated the expression of GFP-tagged NDRG2 in the cytoplasm and nucleus 
of A549 cells. The findings of transwell assay showed that NDRG2 overexpression reduced migration 
and invasion of A549 cells compared to control cells. Gelatin zymography analyses revealed that 
NDRG2 overexpression decreased the gelatinase activity of secreted MMP-2 and MMP-9. 
Conclusion: These findings suggest that NDRG2 may be a new anti-invasion factor in lung cancer that 
inhibits MMPs activities. </p>

<p>Lung cancer is one of the major causes of cancer 
related death in the world (1). The incidence and 
mortality rate of this malignancy is increasing 
annually. Lung cancer is often diagnosed in the 
late stages, when the tumor cells have been 
metastasized (2, 3). Currently, platin-based cytotoxic 
chemotherapy and removal of metastatic tumors by 
surgery are available therapeutic options. Resistance 
to chemotherapy and recurrence of metastatic 
tumors are major limitations of these treatments. 
Metastasis is a complex and multistep process which 
includes degradation of the extracellular matrix, 
migration of tumor cells into blood or lymph 
circulation, and invasion to other tissues (4). 
Understanding the molecular mechanisms involved 
in these processes is very crucial because it could 
lead to development of new therapeutic strategies. </p>

<p>N-myc downstream regulated gene 2 (NDRG2) 
belongs to NDRG family and encodes a 41KD 
cytoplasmic protein (5). It is normally expressed in 
several tissues and involved in multiple biological 
processes, including cell growth, differentiation, and 
apoptosis (5-7). Increasing evidence indicates the 
role of NDRG2 as a tumor suppressor in the control 
of cell growth and metastasis of tumor cells (5, 8, 9). 
Reduced expression of NDRG2 has been shown in 
several cancers including breast (10), colon (11), 
renal cell carcinoma (12), glioblastom (13), liver 
(14), and lung (15). On the other hand, over-
expression of NDRG2 leads to inhibition of 
proliferation, invasion, and metastasis of tumor cell 
lines (16-19). Li et al (15) has recently reported 
down-regulation of NDRG2 gene in human lung 
cancer which was negatively correlated with the 
stage of tumor and survival time of the patients. </p>

<p>*Corresponding author: Mohammad Ali Takhshid. Diagnostic Laboratory Sciences and Technology Research Center, School of Paramedical Sciences, Shiraz 
University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran. Tel/fax: +98-711-2270301; email: takhshid2001@yahoo.co.uk </p>

<p>Faraji et al </p>

<p>NDRG2 suppresses invasion of A549 cell line </p>

<p>Iran J Basic Med Sci, Vol. 18, No. 8, Aug 2015 </p>

<p>
However, the effects of NDRG2 overexpression on 
the migration and invasion of lung tumor cells 
remain unknown. Matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) 
are a large family of zinc-dependent peptidases 
involved in metastasis of various tumors through 
degradation of the extracellular matrix proteins (20). 
MMP-2 (gelatinase A) and MMP-9 (gelatinase B) are 
among the most important MMPs highly expressed in 
the lung tumor cells and their expression is 
correlated with invasiveness of these cells (5, 20). 
In the current study, the effects of NDRG2 
overexpression on the invasion and migration of 
A549 cell line were investigated. Furthermore, the 
effects of NDRG2 overexpression on the enzymatic 
activities of MMP-2 and -9 were also evaluated. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Cell culture and reagents 
The human lung adenocarcinoma cell lines A549 
was purchased from Pasteur Institute of Iran (NCBI 
code: C137). The cells were grown in RPMI 
(Gibco/Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) supplemented with 
10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum and 100 
units/ml penicillin-streptomycin (Gibco/Invitrogen, 
Carlsbad, CA) at 37 °C in a humidified 5% CO 2 
incubator. Lipofectamine™ 2000 and Plasmid Filter 
Purification Kit were from Invitrogen. </p>

<p>Plasmid amplification and purification 
A plasmid encoding C-terminal green fluorescent 
protein (GFP)-tagged NDRG2 (pCMV6-AC-GFP-
NDRG2) and a negative control pCMV6-AC-GFP 
plasmid without NDRG2 (mock plasmid) were 
purchased from OriGene (OriGene, USA). The 
competent Escherichia coli strains DH5α were used 
for proliferation of plasmid constructs. For each 
transformation, 100 ng of DNA was added to 25 μl of 
competent cells and incubated on ice for 30 min, 
followed by heat shock at 42 °C for 2 min and 
incubation on ice for 2 min. The cells were allowed to 
recover in 1 ml Luria-Bertani (LB) broth and then 
incubated for 60 min at 37 °C with shaking. Cells 
were plated on LB-agar plate containing 100 μg/ml 
ampicillin (plasmids encoded ampicillin resistance) 
and incubated at 37 °C overnight to select the 
transformants. After overnight culture, one colony of 
each plasmid was transferred to 3 ml of LB broth 
supplemented with ampicillin (50 μg/ml) for 5 hr 
of pre-culture at 37 °C before transfer to 500 ml LB 
broth for a further overnight of incubation in a rotating 
incubator. The overnight culture was centrifuged at 
5000 g for 10 min, and the resulting pellet was used to 
extract plasmid DNA using PureLink™ HiPure plasmid 
filter Purification Kit (Invitrogen, UK) as per 
manufacturer's instructions. The concentration of the 
DNA extracted was measured using the NanoDrop ND-
100 spectrophotometer. </p>

<p>Overexpression of the NDRG2 gene in A549 cells 
A549 cells were transfected with NDRG2 plasmid or 
mock plasmid using lipofectamine™ 2000 (Invitrogen, 
Carlsbad, CA) according to the manufacturer's 
instruction. After 48 hr, the transfected cells were 
detached with EDTA (10 mM in PBS), washed, and 
resuspended in cold PBS buffer. Fluorescent 
microscopy and flowcytometry analysis were then used 
to monitor the cellular expression of GFP-tagged 
NDRG2 and to measure the efficiency of transfection. 
Fluorescence microscopy was performed on an 
inverted microscope (Hund, Germany) with filter sets 
designed for GFP. 
Flowcytometric analysis was conducted using 
FACSAria flowcytometer (BD Biosciences, USA) 
equipped with a water cooled 488 nm argon-ion 
laser. Green fluorescence (FL1 detector) was 
detected using 530/30 filter. The data were analyzed 
with Cell Quest software (BD Biosciences, USA). For 
each sample, 20,000 events were collected. </p>

<p>Migration and invasion assays 
Invasion and migration assays were performed 
using a 24 well transwell insert (8 µm pore filters, 
BD Bioscience, Bedford, MA) with and without 
matrigel-coated membrane, respectively. Briefly, for 
migration assays, after filling the lower part of the 
transwell with RPMI plus 10% FBS, A549 cells 
(5×10 3 ) suspended in serum-free RPMI were added 
to the upper part of the transwell, and incubated for 
6 hr at 37 °C . The cells were allowed to migrate to 
the bottom of the membrane. After incubation, the 
cells migrated to the lower surface of the transwell 
were fixed with methanol for 5 min and stained with 
0.1% crystal violet. For invasion assays, the transwell 
was coated with 100 µl (1 mg/ml) matrigel (BD 
Bioscience, Bedford, MA). A549 cells (5×10 3 ) were 
plated onto the upper part of the matrigel-coated 
transwell chamber and incubated for 24 hr. The 
invaded cells were then fixed with methanol, stained 
and counted. The number of invading or migrating 
cells was determined by counting five high-power 
fields (400) on each membrane and was calculated 
as the mean number of cells per field (21). </p>

<p>Determination of MMP-2 and MMP-9 activities by 
gelatin zymography 
The enzymatic activities of MMP-2 and MMP -9 
were analyzed by gelatin zymography. Briefly, 
serum-free culture supernatant fractions were 
collected and mixed at a 1:1 ratio with non-reducing 
sample buffer (2% sodium dodecyl sulfate, 50 mM 
Tris-HCl (PH 6.8), 10% glycerol, and 0.001% 
bromophenol blue for preparing samples. The 
samples were electrophoresed on a 10% sodium 
dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis 
(SDS-PAGE) containing 0.1% gelatin. After separation 
of proteins, the gel was washed twice with washing </p>

<p>NDRG2 suppresses invasion of A549 cell line </p>

<p>Faraji et al </p>

<p>Iran J Basic Med Sci, Vol. 18, No. 8, Aug 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 1. Overexpression of GFP-tagged N-myc downstream 
regulated gene 2 in the A549 cells 
Green fluorescence represented the successful transfection and 
overexpression of GFP-tagged NDRG2. The exogenously introduced 
NDRG2 was localized in the cytoplasm of the A549 cells </p>

<p>buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl at pH 7.5, 100 mM NaCl, and 
2.5% triton X-100) and then treated with incubation 
buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl at PH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM 
CaCl 2 , and 0.02% NaN 3 ) at 37 °C for 24 hr. After 
incubation, the gels were stained (0.5% coomassie blue, 
10% metanol, and 5% acetic acid) and then destained 
(20% methanol and 10% acetic acid). MMPs were 
detected as a clear zone on the blue background. The 
gels were scanned using a densitometer (Bio-Rad GS-
800) and the density of the bands was measured using 
Image J software (National Institutes of Health, 
Bethesda, MD, USA) (22-24). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All statistical analyses were performed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">(version	 15.0</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS,	 Inc.,	 Chicago, IL,	 USA</rs>). The normal distribution of variables was 
assessed using the Shapiro Wilk test (P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Comparisons of variables between NDRG2 group and 
the control group were made using two-tailed 
Students t-test (for normally distributed invasion 
assay data) or Mann-Whitney U-test (for non-
normally distributed migration assay data). All data 
are represented by the mean±standard deviation of 
at least three independent experiments. P-value&lt; 
0.05 was considered as the significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Overexpression of NDRG2 in A549 cells 
For overexpression of NDRG2 in A549 cells, the 
cells were transfected with a plasmid encoding C-
terminal GFP-tagged NDRG2. The expression of GFP-
tagged NDRG2 was confirmed by fluorescence 
microscopy (Figure 1). NDRG2 was localized in the 
cytoplasm and nucleus of the cells. Flowcytometry 
analysis showed that the efficiency of transfection 
was more than 60% (Figure 2). </p>

<p>NDRG2 gene inhibits the invasion and migration of 
human lung cancer cells in vitro 
To evaluate the effect of NDRG2 overexpression 
on metastatic activity, we performed in vitro 
transwell migration assays and matrigel coated 
transwell invasion assays with human lung cancer 
cell line A549. Representative micrographs (Figure 
3) were taken from the lower surface of the 
transwell filter, and the cells that migrated or 
invaded were counted. As shown in Figure 3, the 
number of migrated cells was considerably reduced 
in NDRG2 overexpressing cells compared to the 
control cells (P&lt;0.02). Furthermore, overexpression 
of NDRG2 in the cells significantly decreased the 
number of invaded cells compared to the controls 
(P&lt;0.02; Figure 4). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Determination of transfection efficiency of pCMV6-AC-GFP vector using flowcytometry. Right: detection of transfection efficiency 
by flowcytometry. Transfection efficiency was maintained at 60%, 48 hr post-transfection. Left: dot blot flowcytometry after 48 hr. High 
efficiency of transfection with fluorescent GFP (green) in A549 cells was easily identified for 48 hr post-transfection (×100). Green 
fluorescence intensities (FL1-H) are indicated on the x axis, and cell counts are indicated on the y axis. The cytometric analysis was 
performed for 2 × 10 4 events </p>

<p>Faraji et al </p>

<p>NDRG2 suppresses invasion of A549 cell line </p>

<p>Iran J Basic Med Sci, Vol. 18, No. 8, Aug 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 3. Effects of NDRG2 overexpression on the migration of A549 cells in an in vitro assay. A fixed number of cells were plated onto the 
upper part of the transwell chamber. After incubation for 6 hr, invasive cells were counted at the lower part of transwell filter. 
Representative micrographs from the lower surface of the transwell filter. Overexpression of NDRG2 significantly suppressed their 
migration through the transwell. *P&lt; 0.001 (values are compared with control cells) </p>

<p>NDRG2 transfection suppresses the expression of 
MMP-2, MMP-9 in A549 cells 
Gelatin zymography was used to evaluate the 
effects of NDRG2 overexpression on MMP-2 and 
MMP-9 activity. As can be seen in Figure 5 A, A549 
control cells express and secret MMP-2 and MMP-9. 
Both MMP-2 and MMP-9 were represented as pro-</p>

<p>and active forms in the gel. Analysis of the gel for the 
effect of NDRG2 overexpression on MMP-2 and 
MMP-9 activity showed that both pro-and active 
forms of MMP-2 and MMP-9 significantly were 
reduced in NDRG2-transfected cells compared to the 
control cells (Figure 5 B). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effects of N-myc downstream regulated gene 2 overexpression on the invasion of A549 cells. A fixed number of cells were plated 
onto the upper part of the matrigel-coated transwell chamber. After incubation for 24 hr, invasive cells were counted at the lower part of 
transwell. *P&lt;0.002 compared with control cells </p>

<p>NDRG2 suppresses invasion of A549 cell line </p>

<p>Faraji et al </p>

<p>Iran J Basic Med Sci, Vol. 18, No. 8, Aug 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 5. Effects of N-myc downstream regulated gene 2 
overexpression on matrix metaloproteinase-2 and -9 activities. (A) 
A representative gelatin zymograph showing MMP-2 and MMP-9 
from cell culture supernatant of A549 control cells (lane 1), 
NDRG2 overexpressing A549 cells (lane 2). A serum sample 
(contain secreted MMP-2 and -9) was used as the positive control 
(lane 3). (B) The density of MMP-2 and -9 bands obtained in 
gelatin-zymographic gel (10% SDS-PAGE containing 0.1% gelatin). 
The activities of MMP-2 and MMP-9 were decreased in NDRG2 
overexpressed cells compared to the control cells. **P&lt; 0.01 and 
*P&lt; 0.05 vs. control </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>A growing body of evidence has documented the 
role of human NDRG2 gene as a tumor suppressor in 
a variety of cancers (5, 8, 9). However, the anti-
invasion effect of NDRG2 in the lung tumor cells was 
unclear. In this study, GFP-tagged human NDRG2 
gene was overexpressed in a highly invasive A549 
lung tumor cell line to investigate its effect on cell 
invasion. Our data showed that NDRG2 was 
increased significantly in the nucleus and cytoplasm 
of the cells. In vitro invasion and migration assays 
showed that NDRG2 inhibited migration and 
invasion of A549 cells. Moreover, the activities of the 
secreted form of MMP-2 and MMP-9 were decreased, 
upon overexpression of NDRG2. To the best of our 
knowledge, it is the first study about the effect of 
NDRG2 on invasion of the lung tumor cell line, 
suggesting that NDRG2 may act as an anti-invasion 
factor in lung cancer. 
It has been demonstrated that under basal 
condition the expression of NDRG2 is low and it is 
mainly localized in the cytoplasm of cells (7). When 
the cells are activated by stimulation factors, such as 
ischemia or hypoxia, NDRG2 is overexpressed and 
translocated to the nucleus. Thus, it appears that 
nucleolar localization of NDRG2 observed in our </p>

<p>study may be related to the overexpression of 
NDRG2. This finding is consistent with the results of 
previous studies which showed the presence of 
NDRG2 in the cytoplasm and nucleus of other cells 
(7, 12). The presence of nuclear localization signal 
(NLS) sequence is required for translocation of many 
proteins to the nucleus. NLS sequence has not been 
shown in the primary structure of NDRG2 and it has 
been suggested that helix α6 in the structure of 
NDRG2 may be responsible for its translocation to 
the nucleus (5). 
Tumor progression and metastasis are dependent 
on the ability of tumor cells to invade the surrounding 
tissues. The findings of our study revealed that NDRG2 
significantly suppressed migration and invasion of 
A549 cells. Similar results have been reported about the 
effects of NDRG2 on invasion and migration of prostate 
(16), breast (25), and hepatocarcinoma (19) cancer cell 
lines, suggesting the role of NDRG2 as an anti-invasion 
factor. Degradation of the extracellular matrix by MMPs 
is required for cancer cell invasion. MMP-2 and MMP-9 
are among the most important MMPs which are highly 
expressed in the lung tumor cells and its expression is 
correlated with invasiveness of these cells (20). The 
synthesis and secretion of MMP-2 and MMP-9 from 
A549 cells have been previously reported (18). We 
used SDS-PAGE gelatin zymography to measure the 
activities of MMP-9 and MMP-2. This technique is based 
on degradation of gelatin by MMP-9 and MMP-2. It is a 
repeatable and sensitive method that can detect 
picogram levels of MMP-9 and MMP-2. Furthermore, it 
can discriminate between MMP-2 and MMP-9 and their 
respective pro-enzymes (pro-MMP-2 and pro-MMP-9). 
Here, we showed a decreased level of MMP-2 and MMP-
9 activities upon NDRG2 overexpression, suggesting 
that NDRG2 probably affects cell invasion via inhibition 
of MMP-2 and MMP-9. The activities of MMPs can be 
influenced by several factors including the rate of their 
expression. We did not evaluate the effect of NDRG2 on 
MMPs gene expression. It is a limitation of our study; 
thus, our results should be reconfirmed in studies 
employing real time PCR in order to define the effect of 
NDRG2 on MMPs gene expression. Despite this 
limitation, our results indicate that NDRG2 inhibited the 
invasion and reduced the activities of MMP-2 and -9. 
The exact molecular mechanisms that are behind 
the NDRG2 effects in A549 cells have remained 
unknown. Up-regulation of TGF-b1 (9), nuclear 
factor kappa B (NF-kB) (5), and IL-8 (26) are among 
mechanisms previously suggested for the effects of 
NDRG2 on other cells. Further studies are required 
to explore the role of these pathways in the 
mechanism of NDRG2 effects in A549 cells. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In summary, our data support the view that 
overexpression of NDRG2 inhibits migration and 
invasion of A549 cells. The findings also showed the </p>

<p>Faraji et al </p>

<p>NDRG2 suppresses invasion of A549 cell line </p>

<p>Iran J Basic Med Sci, Vol. 18, No. 8, Aug 2015 </p>

<p>
inhibition of MMP-2 and MMP-9 activities upon 
NDRG2 overexpression. It may be a molecular 
mechanism for anti-invasion effects of NDRG2. 
However, further studies are needed to explore the 
potential mechanisms through which NDRG2 inhibits 
invasion of A549 cells. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The results described in this paper were part of 
MSc thesis of Seyed Nooredin Faraji and was 
supported by grant number 90-5971 from the Vice-
Chancellor for research affairs of Shiraz University of 
Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran. We are also grateful to 
all staff of Diagnostic Laboratory Sciences and 
Technology Research Center and Shiraz Institute for 
Cancer Research Center for technical assistance in 
this work. </p>



<p>NDRG2 suppresses invasion of A549 cell line </p>

<p>Faraji et al </p>

<p>Iran J Basic Med Sci, Vol. 18, No. 8, Aug 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>