<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4770866" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Mesenchymal stem cell (MSC), a widely used adult stem cell candidate for regenerative medicine, has been 
shown to exert some of its therapeutic effects through the secretion of extracellular vesicles (EVs). These 
homogenously sized EVs of 100Á150 hm exhibited many exosome-like biophysical and biochemical properties 
and carry both proteins and RNAs. Recently, exosome-associated proteins in this MSC EV preparation were 
found to segregate primarily to those EVs that bind cholera toxin B chain (CTB), a GM1 ganglioside-specific 
ligand, and pulse-chase experiments demonstrated that these EVs have endosomal origin and carried many of 
the exosome-associated markers. Here, we report that only a fraction of the MSC EV proteome was found in 
CTB-bound EVs. Using Annexin V (AV) and Shiga toxin B subunit (ST) with affinities for phosphatidylserine 
and globotriaosylceramide, respectively, AV-and a ST-binding EV were identified. CTB-, AV-and 
STÁbinding EVs all carried actin. However, the AV-binding EVs carried low or undetectable levels of the 
exosome-associated proteins. Only the ST-binding EVs carried RNA and EDA-containing fibronectin. 
Proteins in AV-binding EVs were also different from those released by apoptotic MSCs. CTB-and AV-binding 
activities were localized to the plasma membrane and cytoplasm of MSCs, while ST-binding activity was 
localized to the nucleus. Together, this study demonstrates that cells secrete many types of EVs. Specifically, 
MSCs secrete at least 3 types. They can be differentially isolated based on their affinities for membrane lipid-
binding ligands. As the subcellular sites of the binding activities of these ligands and cargo load are different 
for each EV type, they are likely to have a different biogenesis pathway and possibly different functions. </p>

<p>injury (2) and that the therapeutic agents in the condi-
tioned medium were homogenously sized particles with 
a hydrodynamic radius of 55Á65 hm and a flotation 
density in sucrose of 1.10Á1.18 g/mL (3). They carried 
exosome-associated proteins such as the tetraspanin pro-
teins CD9 and CD81, ALIX, TSG101 and RNAs of less 
than 300 nt (4). Based on these characteristics, these par-
ticles were identified as exosomes, a specific type of 
extracellular vesicle (EV). Subsequent analysis including 
pulse-chase experiments confirmed that the tetraspanin 
proteins CD9 and CD81, and endosomal markers ALIX 
and TSG101, were associated primarily with EVs that 
bind cholera toxin B chain (CTB), and that these CTB-
binding EVs were derived from endosomes. They were 
also enriched in GM1 gangliosides, which are the endo-
genous receptors for CTB (5). 
In this follow up, we observed that only a fraction 
of the proteins and none of the RNAs present in our 
so-called exosome preparation were found in MSC 
CTB-EVs. This suggests that the exosome preparation 
may contain other EV types. For clarity, our previously 
reported MSC exosome preparation will be referred to 
as an MSC EV preparation in this report. To isolate other 
EVs, we determined whether other membrane lipid-
binding ligands could extract the remaining EVs from 
MSC secretion, and whether these extracted EVs contain 
unique cargos of proteins and RNA. The rationale for 
using lipid-binding ligands for EV isolation is that the 
lipid membrane is the defining and physically delimit-
ing feature of EVs (6). By targeting membrane lipids, 
this isolation approach not only enriches for lipid 
membrane-bound entities, but also eliminates contam-
inating macromolecules. 
Here, we tested Annexin V (AV) and Shiga Toxin (ST), 
2 proteins known to bind phosphatidylserine and globo-
triaosylceramide, respectively, for EV extraction. The 
protein and RNA contents of CTB-, AV-and ST-binding 
EVs (CTB-EVs, AV-EVs and ST-EVs) were determined 
and compared. These EVs were visualized by electron 
microscopy. The subcellular localization of CTB-, AV-
and ST-binding activity was determined by confocal 
microscopy. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>MSC culture 
Immortalized E1-MYC 16.3 human ESC-derived MSCs 
were cultured in DMEM with 10% foetal calf serum 
as previously described (7). For EV preparation, the 
cells were grown in a chemically defined medium (NCM) 
for 3 days and the conditioned medium (CM) was 
harvested and 0.22 mm filtered as previously described 
(3,8,9). The CM was concentrated 100) for EVs by 
tangential flow filtration (TFF) (Sartorius, Gottingen, 
Germany, MWCO 100 kDa). The EV preparation was </p>

<p>filtered with a 0.22 mm filter (Merck Millipore, Billerica, 
MA) and stored in (208C freezer until use. The EVs 
were assayed for protein concentration using Coomassie 
Plus 
TM (Bradford) Assay (Thermo Fisher Scientific, 
Waltham, MA), as per manufacturer's instruction. </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry analysis of protein 
The MSC EV preparation described above was extracted 
with CTB to isolate the CTB-binding EVs as described 
below. The remaining EV preparation after CTB extrac-
tion was collected as CTB-depleted MSC EV. Proteins 
(250 mg) from each of the 2 fractions were analysed by 
LC-MS/MS. Briefly, the samples were reduced by DTT, 
alkylated with IAA, digested by trypsin and analysed 
with LC-MS/MS as described (10). For each sample, all 
MS/MS spectra of each of the 3 independent prepara-
tions were extracted by ProteomeDiscovere 1.4 (Thermo 
Scientific, Bremen, Germany) and combined into a single 
mascot generic file by a hand-written program. Protein 
identification was achieved by searching the combined 
data against the Uniprot human protein database (down-
load 22 Jan 2014; 88479 sequences, 35079223 residues) 
via an in-house Mascot server (Version 2.4.1Matrix 
Science, UK). The search parameters were a maximum of 
2 missed cleavages using trypsin; fixed modification was 
carbamidomethylation of cysteine, and variable modifi-
cations were oxidation of methionine and deamidation of 
asparagine and glutamine. The mass tolerances were set 
to 10 ppm and 0.8 Da for peptide precursor and fragment 
ions, respectively. Protein identification was accepted as 
true positive if 2 different peptides were found to have 
scores greater than the homology or identity scores. </p>

<p>EV extraction with CTB, AV and ST 
CTB (SBL Vaccin AB, Sweden), AV (Biovision, San 
Francisco, USA) and ST (Sigma, St Louis, USA) were 
biotinylated using Sulfo-NHS Biotin (Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Waltham, MA) as per manufacturer's instruc-
tion; 20 mg MSC EVs prepared as described above were 
incubated with 0.25 mg biotinylated CTB, AV or ST in 
binding buffer (100 mM Hepes, 2.5 mM CaCl 2 , 140 mM 
NaCl, PBS pH7.4), at a final volume of 100 mL for 
30 minutes with rotation. The CTB, AV or ST reaction 
mix was added to 30 mL equivalent of Dynabeads M280 
Streptavidin (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) 
that were pre-washed as per manufacturer's instruction. 
The reaction mix and beads were incubated at 378C with 
shaking at 800 rpm for 30 minutes. The beads were 
immobilized with a magnet and the supernatant was 
collected as the ''unbound'' fraction. The beads were then 
washed twice with 100 mL wash buffer (0.1% BSA in PBS) 
and the supernatants were collected as ''wash 1'' and 
''wash 2,'' respectively. The beads were re-suspended in 
100 mL PBS as the ''bound'' fraction. The equivalent of 
20% of the starting samples (input) and each of their 
respective ''unbound,'' ''wash 1,'' ''wash 2'' and ''bound'' </p>

<p>Ruenn Chai Lai et al. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>

<p>fractions were loaded on a 4Á12% SDS-polyacrylamide 
gel for silver staining or western blot hybridization. </p>

<p>CTB or AV coupled CD81 ELISA 
Ten mg of MSC EV was extracted first with 0.25 mg 
biotinylated CTB or AV, and the remaining supernatant 
was then extracted with 0.25 mg biotinylated AV or CTB, 
respectively. Each extraction was performed as described 
above in a binding buffer at a final volume of 100 mL 
for 30 minutes, followed by immobilization using 30 mL 
equivalent of pre-washed Dynabeads M280 Streptavidin. 
The beads were then washed twice with 100 mL wash 
buffer (0.1% BSA in PBS), incubated with 100 mL 
of 1:500 diluted anti-CD81 antibodies (Santa Cruz, 
CA), washed and incubated again with 1:5,000 diluted 
HRP-conjugated goat anti-mouse secondary antibodies. 
HRP activity was determined using Amplex Red Sub-
strate (Life Technology, Grand Island, NY) as per 
manufacturer's protocol. </p>

<p>Isolation and detection of RNA 
CTB-, AV-or ST-binding EVs were each isolated from 
200 mg MSC EV using 1.5 mg biotinylated CTB, AV or ST, 
respectively, in a final volume of 200 mL and the equiv-
alent of 150 mL pre-washed Dynabeads M280 Streptavidin 
as described above. The isolated EVs were resuspended 
in 100 mL of PBS and extracted for RNA using 3 volumes 
of Trizol LS (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) 
according to the manufacturer's protocol. After extrac-
tion, the pellet was re-suspended in 50 mL RNase-free 
water. The pellet was assayed for RNA using Quanti-
TTM RiboGreen RNA Assay Kit (Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Waltham, MA); 10 mL of each resuspended 
pellet was resolved on a 15% Novex Tris-borate-EDTA 
(TBE)-urea gels (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, 
MA) before staining with ethidium bromide. </p>

<p>Nanoparticle Tracking Analysis 
The size distribution of exosome was measured using 
NanoSight LM10 coupled with a 405-nm laser (Malvern, 
Worcestershire, UK) and analysed by <rs id="software-1" type="software">Nanoparticle Tracking Analysis</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2.3</rs> software (Malvern, Worcestershire, 
UK). MSC-EV preparation was diluted to 2 mg/mL with 
0.22 mm filtered PBS and loaded using the NanoSight 
syringe pump and script control system set at 100 arbitrary 
units as recommended by NanoSight. Three 30-second 
videos were recorded at an ambient temperature of 20Á 
218C with a 10-second delay between recordings. The 
minimal expected particle size, minimum track length 
and blur setting were set to the automatic default setting. 
Camera shutter speed was fixed at 30.00 ms, camera gain 
at 500, and camera sensitivity and detection threshold at 
10. The size and number of particles of the exosome was 
calculated as the average of 3 replicate recordings. </p>

<p>Electron microscopy 
MSC EV (100 mg) preparation was incubated with 
1.25 mg biotinylated CTB, AV, ST or without ligand in 
binding buffer described previously at a final volume of 
100 mL for 30 minutes with rotation; 50 mL streptavidin-
coated polystyrene particles (Spherotech, Lake Forest, 
IL) that were pre-washed as per manufacturer's instruc-
tion were added to the CTB, AV or ST reaction mix and 
incubated with shaking at 800 rpm for 30 minutes. The 
beads were then washed twice with 100 mL PBS and 
resuspended in 100 mL PBS; 20 mL of each of the bead 
extracts were spotted directly onto carbon tape on 
aluminium stubs, and left to dry at 408C. The stubs 
were sputter coated with 2 hm of gold coating (Leica 
Biosystems Wetzlar, Germany) and imaged in a Jeol 
6701FESEM. </p>

<p>Confocal microscopy 
Cells were cultured on 20 )20 mm glass coverslips. At 
80% confluence, they were fixed with 4% paraformalde-
hyde for 15 minutes and then permeabilized with 0.5% 
Tween 20 for 10 minutes. To reduce background signals 
from endogenous biotin and other non-specific binding 
sites, the cells were treated with Endogenous Biotin-
Blocking Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA), 
according to the manufacturer's instructions, followed by 
StartingBlock T20 (PBS) Blocking Buffer (Thermo Fisher 
Scientific, Waltham, MA) for 15 minutes. They were then 
incubated with 5 mg/mL of biotinylated CTB, AV or ST, 
together with 1:100 diluted anti-CD81 mouse mono-
clonal IgG 1 antibodies (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Dallas, 
TX) at 48C overnight. Cells were subsequently washed and 
incubated with 1:50 diluted Streptavidin-Cy3 (Thermo 
Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) with 1:500 diluted Alexa 
Fluor 488-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG antibodies 
(Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) for 1 hour at 
room temperature. They were then washed, counter-
stained with Hoechst 33342, mounted and visualized 
using a Zeiss LSM 510 laser scanning confocal micro-
scope (Carl Zeiss, Inc., Oberkochen, Germany). </p>

<p>Small RNA sequencing 
ST-EV was prepared from 200 mg MSC EV as described 
above using Trizol LS (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, 
MA) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The 
extracted RNAs were quantitated using Quanti-TTM 
RiboGreen RNA Assay Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, 
Waltham, MA). One mg RNA each from unfractionated 
MSC EV preparation and ST-EVs was used for library 
construction. The library for high-throughput sequencing 
was constructed using TruSeq Small RNA Library Prep 
Kit (Cat. #RS-200-0024) and applied to an Illumina 
High Seq 2000 sequencing system (Illumina, USA) for 
101-nt single-end sequencing. The reads obtained were 
trimmed of their ligation adaptors and reads shorter than 
18 nts were discarded. The remaining reads were mapped </p>

<p>MSC secretes at least 3 EV types </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>against a collection of human rRNA sequences to filter 
out ribosomal RNA-like reads. The unmapped reads were 
subsequently mapped to Reference genome hg19 from 
the UCSC genome browser (www.genome.ucsc.edu/). 
The <rs type="software">ENSEMBL</rs> gene annotation (GRCh37) was used 
to annotate the mapped reads based on its genomic 
location. For details of the analysis method, please refer 
to ''Supplementary Material and Method.'' </p>

<p>Western blot hybridization 
Western blot hybridization was performed using standard 
protocols. Briefly, proteins were denatured, separated on 
4Á12% polyacrylamide gels, electroblotted onto a nitro-
cellulose membrane and probed with a primary antibody 
followed by horseradish peroxidase-coupled secondary 
antibodies against the primary antibody. The primary anti-
bodies used in this study were mouse anti-human CD9, 
CD81, ALIX, TSG101, CD59, b-ACTIN (Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology, Dallas, TX) and EDA-containing FN1 
(Abcam, Cambridge, MA). After incubating with the 
appropriate horseradish peroxidase-coupled secondary 
antibodies, the blot was then incubated with a chemilu-
minescent HRP substrate to detect bound primary anti-
body, and therefore the presence of the antigen. </p>

<p>Staurosporine-treated MSC culture 
10 
5 E1-MYC 16.3 cells were plated into each well of a 6-
well culture plate. After 72 hours incubation, the cells were 
incubated in serum-free chemically defined medium (9)  with or without 1 mM staurosporine (Sigma, St Louis, 
USA) for 3 hours. The culture medium was then harvested 
and concentrated using a 30 kDa MWCO filter (Merck 
Millipore, Billerica, MA); 50 mg of the concentrated 
medium was extracted with AV and the extracts were 
analysed by western blotting for CD9 and b-ACTIN. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Proteome analysis of CTB-EVs 
We have previously described the presence of CTB-EVs 
in our MSC EV preparation. These EVs were shown by 
pulse-chase experiments to be derived from endosomes 
and were therefore bona fide exosomes (5). In addition, 
CTB could be used to extract endosome-derived MSC EVs 
from an MSC-conditioned medium. These CTB-EVs 
carried exosome-associated proteins and had a flotation 
density of 1.09Á1.17 g/mL. In our extraction protocol, 
CTB effectively extracts at least 96% of CD81 in the 
conditioned medium (5). Here, we determine the proteome 
of these CTB-EVs and CTB-EV depleted MSC EV 
preparation by mass spectrometry as previously described 
(10). 1,806 proteins were detected in the CTB-bound 
fraction and 1,547 were present in the CTB-depleted 
fraction (Supplementary File 1). 987 proteins were found 
in both fractions, suggesting that these 987 proteins 
are likely proteins commonly found in most EVs. The </p>

<p>observation that 819 and 560 proteins were detected only in 
either CTB-bound or -depleted fraction respectively in-
dicated that CTB-EVs represent a distinct class of EVs 
and that there were possibly other EV types beside the 
CTB-bound EVs (Fig. 1a). The proteins in the CTB-bound 
fraction and CTB-depleted fraction were functionally 
clustered into biological process, molecular functions 
and pathways by the Ingenuity Pathway Analysis platform 
(Ingenuity Systems, Mountain View, CA). From the 
analysis of the CTB-bound fraction and CTB-depleted 
fraction, we respectively selected a set of 20 pathways that 
had the least likelihood of the clustered proteins being 
associated with a pathway due to random chance, that is, 
the lowest p value. There were many shared pathways in 
these 2 sets. There were also pathways that were unique to 
either the CTB-bound or depleted fractions (Fig. 1b). 
Among the top 20 pathways for the CTB-bound 
fraction, 4 were endocytic or exocytic processes, namely 
Caveolar-mediated Endocytosis Signaling, Virus Entry 
via Endocytic Pathways, Mechanisms of Viral Exit from 
Host Cells and Clathrin-mediated Endocytosis Signaling. 
As these pathways essentially function to facilitate 
endocytosis, endosome-associated activities or exocytosis, 
their presence were consistent with our previous report 
that CTB-binding EVs from MSCs have an endosomal 
origin and were thus exosomes (5). Since endocytosis 
also plays a critical role in cell adhesion regulation by 
degrading and recycling cell adhesion molecules such 
as integrins (11) or ephrins (12), the dominance of cell-
adhesion regulatory pathways such as Remodeling of 
Epithelial Adherens Junctions, Epithelial Adherens Junc-
tion Signaling, Germ Cell-Sertoli Cell Junction Signaling, 
Sertoli Cell-Sertoli Cell Junction Signaling, Ephrin 
Receptor Signaling and Integrin Signaling could be a 
coincidental presence in the proteome of endosome-
derived CTB-EVs (13Á15). However, we postulate that 
the dominating presence of both endocytosis-and cell-
adhesion-associated pathways is not coincidental but 
rather integral to the biogenesis of exosome. Consistent 
with this hypothesis, many pathways regulating cytoske-
letal biomechanics, which is critical to the membrane 
restructuring and intracellular membrane vesicle traffick-
ing during endocytosis and cell adhesion, are also 
dominant in the proteome of CTB-EVs their significant 
clustering in Actin Cytoskeleton Signaling, and Actin 
Nucleation by ARP-WASP Complex pathways. Axonal 
Guidance Signaling, which involves cytoskeleton rear-
rangement and the modulation of cell-adhesion mole-
cules (17), is also implicated by the CTB-EV proteome. 
Also, consistent with the central role of endocytosis in the 
biogenesis of exosomes, several of the cell signal trans-
duction pathways featured in the functional clustering of 
the CTB-EV proteome shared a common regulatory 
function in endocytosis, namely 14-3-3-mediated Signal-
ing, PI3K/AKT Signaling, Paxillin Signaling (18,19). </p>

<p>Ruenn Chai Lai et al. </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>

<p>Another prominent cluster of pathways consists of EIF2 
Signaling, Regulation of eIF4 and p70S6K Signaling, 
mTOR Signaling and Protein Ubiquitination Pathway, 
which are highly important pathways in protein synthesis, 
post-translational modifications and translocations that 
span several subcellular compartments, such as endoplas-
mic reticulum (ER), Golgi cisternae, the trans-Golgi 
network (TGN), various types of secretory vesicle and 
the plasma membrane (20,21). These pathways are con-
sistent with the role of endosomes in protein synthesis and 
secretion (22,23). 
Although the proteome of the MSC CTB-EVs func-
tionally clustered in pathways that could be linked to the 
endosomal biogenesis of exosomes, many of these links are 
hypothetical and will have to be validated. It is possible 
that many of the pathways implicated in the biogenesis 
also contribute to the biological potency of the EV cargo. </p>

<p>Comparative proteomic analysis of MSC CTB-, 
AV-and ST-EVs 
As the proteomic analysis of MSC CTB-EVs suggested 
the presence of other EV types, the MSC EV preparation 
was test extracted with known and commercially available 
membrane lipid-binding proteins or antibodies. Several </p>

<p>ligands were tested, but only AV and ST extract EV types 
that were different from each other and from CTB-EVs. 
The extracts were resolved by SDS-PAGE and the gel was 
stained for proteins (Fig. 2a). Despite the low resolu-
tion of the 1D gels, differences among CTB, AV and ST 
extracts were discernible. These protein differences among 
the 3 extracts signified that each of the membrane lipid-
binding ligands extracted lipids that are complexed with a 
different cargo of proteins. 
To confirm that CTB, AV and ST were extracting 
EVs, MSC EVs were extracted with each of the 3 ligands. 
The extracts were then immobilized on streptavidin-
conjugated polystyrene beads and visualized by scanning 
electron microscopy (EM) (Fig. 2c). All 3 EV types were 
spherical and have approximate sizes of 50Á100 hm. This 
was consistent with the Nanoparticle Tracking Analysis 
(NTA) of the EV preparation prior to the ligand 
extraction. The modal size of EVs in MSC EV prepara-
tion was 10294.8 hm (Fig. 2b). The spherical shape of 
the EVs was likely distorted by their immobilization on 
surfaces with relatively deep crevices and the sample 
preparation processes. Additionally, their sizes were 
probably underestimated because the samples had to be 
dehydrated during preparation for EM analysis. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (a) Proteomic distribution of CTB-EVs and CTB-EV depleted MSC EV preparation by mass spectrometry. 1,806 proteins were 
detected in the CTB-bound fraction and 1,547 were present in the CTB-depleted fraction. 987 proteins were found in both fractions. (b) 
Functional clustering of the proteins in the CTB-bound fraction and CTB-depleted fraction. </p>

<p>MSC secretes at least 3 EV types </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. (a) SDS-PAGE analysis of MSC EVs extracted with membrane lipid-binding ligands, CTB, AV and ST, respectively. MSC CM 
was incubated with CTB, AV or ST followed by incubation with Dynabeads conjugated with Streptavidin. The beads were immobilized 
with a magnet and the supernatant was collected as the ''unbound'' fraction. The beads were then washed twice and the wash solutions 
were collected as ''wash 1'' and ''wash 2,'' respectively. The beads were re-suspended in PBS as the ''bound'' fraction. The equivalent of 
20% of the starting samples (input) and each of their respective ''unbound,'' ''wash 1,'' ''wash 2'' and ''bound'' fractions were resolved 
onto polyacrylamide gels and the gels were stained with silver. (b) Size distribution of MSC EVs by NanoSight. MSC EVs were diluted 
1,000) with 0.22 mm filtered PBS. The size distribution of exosome was then measured using NanoSight LM10 and analysed by 
<rs type="software">Nanoparticles Tracking Analysis</rs> software according to the manufacturer's protocol. (c) SEM analysis of MSC EVs that were extracted 
with CTB, AV and ST. MSC EV preparation was incubated with biotinylated CTB, AV, ST or without ligand and then streptavidin-
coated polystyrene particles. The beads were then washed twice with PBS and resuspended in PBS before being spotted and left to dry 
onto carbon tape on aluminium stubs at 408C. The stubs were sputter coated with 2 hm of gold coating (Leica Biosystems) and imaged 
in a Jeol 6701FESEM. Scale bar 0100 hm. </p>

<p>Ruenn Chai Lai et al. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>

<p>Western blot analysis of the 3 different extracts re-
vealed the presence of actin in all 3 extracts (Fig. 3a). 
As actin is the most ubiquitous protein in mammalian 
EVs (24), it is presently the best possible candidate 
reference protein for comparing relative protein levels 
among different EVs and was used in this study to 
compare relative protein levels among the 3 EV types. 
Exosome-associated proteins such as CD81, CD9, 
ALIX, and TSG101 were present in the CTB extracts 
as previously reported (5). Relative to actin, the level of 
these proteins was very low or not detected in the AV 
extracts and ST extracts, respectively. To determine </p>

<p>whether the low level of exosome-associated proteins in 
AV-EVs was due to a contamination of CTB-EVs, MSC 
EVs were first extracted with either CTB or AV and then 
further extracted with AV or CTB, respectively. The 
extracted EVs were then assayed for the presence of 
CD81 by ELISA as previously described (5) (Fig. 3b). 
The level of CD81 in either CTB-or AV-EVs before and 
after extraction with AV or CTB, respectively, was not 
changed, demonstrating that CTB and AV extraction of 
EVs were mutually exclusive. 
Unlike CTB and AV extracts, ST extracts carried detect-
able level of EDA-containing fibronectin and RNA </p>

<p>Fig. 3. (a) Western blot analysis of CTB-, AV-and ST-bound MSC EVs. MSC CM was incubated with CTB, AV or ST followed by 
incubation with Dynabeads conjugated with Streptavidin. The beads were immobilised with a magnet, washed, denatured and resolved 
onto polyacrylamide gels before electroblotting onto a nitrocellulose membrane. The membrane was probed with a primary antibody 
followed by horseradish peroxidase-coupled secondary antibodies against the primary antibody. The blot was then incubated with a 
chemiluminescent HRP substrate to detect bound primary antibody. (b) 10 mg MSC EV was extracted sequentially with biotinylated 
CTB and then biotinylated AV or vice versa. After each extraction, the ligand-bound vesicles were removed with Dynabeads 
 † MyOne 
Streptavidin T1 and assayed for CD81 by ELISA. The relative level of CD81 in CTB-vesicles before and after extraction with AV, and 
that in AV-vesicles before and after extraction with CTB were normalized to that in AV-vesicles before CTB extraction. (c) RNA 
analysis of CTB-, AV-and ST-EVs. CTB-, AV-or ST-binding EVs were isolated as described above and extracted for RNA using Trizol. 
The pellet in each of extracts was re-suspended in 50 mL of RNase-free water. 10 mL of each RNA solution was resolved on a 15% 
Novex Tris-borate-EDTA(TBE)-urea gel before staining with ethidium bromide. </p>

<p>MSC secretes at least 3 EV types </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>(Fig. 3a and c). To confirm the relative RNA distribution 
in the 3 extracts, the RNA concentration in each extract 
was assayed by RiboGreen, an RNA fluorescent assay. 
ST extract had about 53% of the total MSC EV RNA, 
while both CTB and AV extracts each had less than 0.5% 
of the total MSC EV RNA. </p>

<p>RNA analysis of ST-binding MSC EVs 
To characterize the RNAs in the ST-EVs, RNAs in un-
fractionated MSC EVs and ST-EVs were sequenced. Two 
small RNA libraries were generated using RNAs from 
the unfractionated MSC EVs and ST-EVs. Both libraries 
generated 204.15 million reads each. After adaptor trim-
ming and the elimination of reads with B18 nts, 117.76 
million and 151.13 million reads remained for the ST-EV 
and unfractionated MSC EVs, respectively. Most of the 
reads were less than 100 nts, with most reads being less 
than 40 nt. These reads were then filtered to remove 
ribosomal RNA-like sequences before mapping to hg19 
human genome; 19.9 million of the 35.71 million reads 
in ST-EV and 17.8 million of the 46.05 million reads 
in unfractionated MSC EVs were miscellaneous RNAs, 
that is, non-coding RNAs that cannot be categorized 
by ENSEMBL. The vast majority of miscellaneous RNA 
identified are a small non-coding RNA component of 
soluble ribonucleoproteins (RNPs) (Supplementary File 3). 
The top 5 expressed misc_RNA in both unfractionated 
MSC EVs and ST-EVs were Y RNAs. According to 
NCBI (www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/6084), Y RNAs are 
small non-coding RNAs that are the RNA component of 
soluble RNPs known as Ro RNPs. Ro RNPs have been 
associated with rheumatic diseases such as systemic lupus 
erythematosus and Sjogren syndrome. Qualitatively, the 
RNAs in ST-EV were different from those in unfractio-
nated MSC EVs. The majority of RNAs in both ST-EV 
and the unfractionated MSC EVs is ribosomal RNAs. 
For the rest, the 5 most abundant classes of RNA in 
the ST-EVs were Y RNA, snRNA, miRNA, lincRNA 
and protein-coding RNA (Fig. 4a), while the 5 most 
abundant classes of RNA in the unfractionated MSC 
EVs were Y RNA, snoRNA, protein-coding RNA, snRNA 
and processed transcript (Fig. 4b). The top 5 most 
abundant miRNAs in both preparation are mir-191, mir-
181, mir-22, mir-92 and mir-221 (Supplementary Fig. 1, 
The TPM (tags per million) of miRNAs can be found in 
Supplementary File 2). Therefore, it is possible that ST-
EVs are not the only RNA-containing EVs in the MSC 
EV preparation. </p>

<p>Steady-state AV-EVs are different from AV-EVs 
produced during apoptosis 
As AV-EVs must have exposed phosphatidylserines to 
bind AV, there is a good possibility that they might be 
derived from apoptotic cells. We tested this by inducing 
apoptosis in our MSC culture with staurosporine. In 
healthy MSC culture, most of the CD9 was associated </p>

<p>with CTB-EVs, while AV-EVs contained low or unde-
tectable levels of CD9. However, during apoptosis, the 
level of CD9 relative to actin was elevated by 3.8 fold 
(Fig. 5), suggesting that the composition of AV-EVs 
produced by healthy MSCs was different from that by 
apoptotic MSCs, and more exosome-associated markers 
were being secreted in AV-EVs during apoptosis. As such, 
CTB may be a more stable ligand for extracting exosomes 
than exosome-associated markers such as CD9. </p>

<p>Candidate cellular origin of CTB-, AV-and ST-EVs 
The different membrane lipid affinities and cargos of 
CTB-, AV-and ST-EVs indicated that they were likely to 
be different EV types derived from either different 
domains of the plasma membrane or different membrane 
organelles. To identify the candidate membrane sources 
of these EVs, MSCs were stained with fluorescence-
labelled CTB, AV and ST. CTB binding activity was 
localized to the discrete domains on the plasma mem-
brane and cytoplasm, AV binding activity was diffused 
throughout the cytoplasm, and ST binding activity was 
diffused throughout the nuclei (Fig. 6). To ascertain 
whether the staining pattern by CTB, AV and ST was 
specific to MSC or a more general cellular phenomenon, 
immortalized human keratinocytes (25) and myc-immor-
talized human myoblasts were tested and found to have 
similar staining patterns (Fig. 7). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this report, we investigated the EV types present in 
our previously described MSC exosome preparation (2). 
This MSC exosome preparation was purified from a 
chemically defined medium that had been conditioned 
by MSCs for 3 days and then size-fractionated (3). As 
described in the ''Introduction,'' we had previously des-
cribed this preparation as an exosome preparation based 
on the presence of exosome-associated parameters and 
properties. We also subsequently demonstrated through 
pulse-chase experiments that this preparation contained 
CTB-binding EVs that were derived from endosomes (5). 
Here, we report that these CTB-EVs had a proteome 
enriched in proteins that were functionally important in 
the cellular process of endocytosis. However, this elucida-
tion of the proteome of CTB-EVs by mass spectrometry 
also revealed that this proteome constituted only part 
of the MSC EV proteome, suggesting the presence of 
other EV types. As such, the previously described MSC 
exosome preparation was incorrect and should be des-
cribed as an EV preparation. 
To identify the other EV types in MSC EV preparation, 
2 ligands, AV and ST known to bind membrane lipids, 
phosphatidylserine and globotriaosylceramide, respec-
tively, were tested to see whether they would extract the 
remaining proteins. The rationale for using such ligands 
was to ensure that the extracted proteins are in a </p>

<p>Ruenn Chai Lai et al. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>

<p>membrane lipid complex. EM visualization of 50Á100 
hm vesicle-like structures in each of the extracts indicated 
that the membrane lipid complexes are vesicles. Like 
CTB, both AV and ST also extracted proteins. Signifi-
cantly, CTB and AV extracts contained membrane proteins 
such as CD9, CD81 and CD59. This property has been 
highlighted as an important characteristic of membrane 
vesicles in a position paper by the International Society of 
Extracellular Vesicles (6). 
Visual inspection of proteins extracted by all 3 ligands 
using low-resolution 1D protein gels revealed discernible 
differences. Western blot confirmed these differences. 
Actin, the protein most often found in mammalian EVs 
(24), was present in all 3 extracts and, as such, was used 
here as a normalization reference for our experiments. 
As expected of exosome as EVs with an endosomal 
biogenesis, CTB extracts had all the known endosomal </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Sequencing of RNA from MSC EV and ST-EV. 1 mg extracted RNA from the unfractionated MSC EV preparation and ST-EVs 
was used to construct libraries for sequencing on an Illumina High Seq 2000 sequencing system (Illumina, USA). The ligation adaptors 
of the reads generated were trimmed. Those reads shorter than 18 nts and ribosomal RNA-like reads were filtered off. The remaining 
reads were mapped back to genome hg19. The mapped reads were annotated by the <rs type="software">ENSEMBL</rs> gene annotation (GRCh37). The 
distribution of the mapped reads across the different RNA types were tabulated for mapped RNA of (a) ST-EV and (b) unfractionated 
MSC -EVs. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. EVs from steady state versus apoptotic MSC cultures. 
MSC was cultured in chemically defined medium for 72 hours 
and then treated with or without 1 mM staurosporine for 3 
hours. The media were then harvested and extracted with CTB 
or AV, and the extracts analysed for CD9 and actin by western 
blot. The CD9 and actin signals were scanned and the CD9 
signal in each extract was normalized to actin. </p>

<p>MSC secretes at least 3 EV types </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>exosome-associated proteins. Although AV-EVs also con-
tained very low levels of exosome-associated proteins, 
prior extraction with either CTB or AV did not reduce the 
level of exosome-associated CD81 in AV-or CTB-EVs, 
respectively. Therefore, AV-EVs cannot be extracted by 
CTB and vice versa, and AV and CTB extraction are 
mutually exclusive. In treating permeabilized MSCs with 
fluorescence-labelled CTB, the CTB-binding activity in 
MSCs was either confined to specific domains in the 
plasma membrane or in punctate cytoplasmic distribution 
in co-localization with CD81 (26), consistent with the 
biogenesis of endosomes. This cellular distribution of CTB-
binding activity could be attributed to the cellular receptor 
for CTB, namely GM1 ganglioside. GM1 gangliosides are 
known to be enriched in lipid rafts, which are sites of active 
endocytosis, and are thus enriched in endosomes as well. 
In contrast to CTB-binding activity, AV-binding activity 
was concentrated mainly in the cytoplasm and did </p>

<p>not co-localize with CD81, suggesting that AV-EVs were 
derived from membrane organelles in the cytoplasm. In the 
presence of Ca 
2 ' , AV is known to have a high specific 
affinity for phosphatidylserine but in the absence of Ca 
2 ' , 
AV binds phosphatidylcholine (27). Therefore, the staining 
of the cytoplasm and not the phosphatidylcholine-rich 
plasma membrane by AV is not an artefact caused by a lack 
of Ca </p>

<p>2 ' </p>

<p>. Although phosphatidylserine is better known as 
an extracellular cell surface marker for apoptosis, its main 
subcellular locations and functions are intracellular (re-
view (28)). The organelles known to be most enriched in 
phosphatidylserine are the plasma membrane, endosomes 
and secretory vesicles. This subcellular distribution of PS is 
thus different from our observed subcellular locations of 
AV-binding activities. We postulate that one possible 
reason for this discrepancy is the context-dependent AV 
binding of PS, that is, the presence of other phospholipids, 
such as phosphatidylethanolamine, could affect the binding </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Visualization of CTB-, AV-and ST-binding in E1-MYC 16.3 cells. Cells were fixed and co-stained with anti-CD81 antibody (green) 
and labelled CTB, AV or ST (red). They were then counterstained with Hoechst 33342 to visualize the nuclei (blue). Scale bars, 10 mm. </p>

<p>Ruenn Chai Lai et al. </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>

<p>of PS by AV (29). Hence, a low abundance PS in the right 
context may bind AV more efficiently than a high 
abundance PS in a poor context. Another possible reason 
is that unlike antibodies, all 3 ligands, that is, CTB, AV and 
ST, bind multiple copies of their lipid ligands. One AV 
molecule binds 4Á8 PS molecule (30,31), while both CTB 
and ST are pentamers in which one CTB monomer binds 
one GM1 (32), and one ST monomer binds one or more 
GB3 (33). As such, the cellular locations of CTB, AV and 
ST binding activity highlight only those locations in which 
their lipid ligands are highly enriched in sufficiently close 
physical proximity for polyvalent binding. As such, the 
efficacy or efficiency of CTB, AVor ST in extracting EVs is 
highly dependent on the spacing and density of their lipid 
ligands. It cannot be predicted simply by the presence or 
absence of the lipids in the EV membrane. Based on the 
cytoplasmic distribution of AV-binding sites, the biogen-
esis pathway of AV-EVs is likely to either physically or 
biochemically intersect with that of CTB-EVs, which would 
provide a rationale for some of the proteomic intersect of 
AV-and CTB-EVs, as evidenced by the low level of CD9, 
CD81, Alix Tsg101 and CD59 relative to actin 
Of the 3 EVs, ST-EVs were uniquely different not only in 
their cargo of RNA and EDA-fibronectin but also in the 
cellular distribution of their binding activity, which was 
restricted to the nucleus. We had previously reported that 
RNAs secreted by MSC were less than 300 nts and were 
encapsulated in cholesterol-rich phospholipid vesicles (4). 
These RNAs were susceptible to RNAse activity only after 
pre-treatment with detergent, phospholipase A2 or cyclo-
dextrin a chelator of cholesterol. They also have a low EV-
like buoyant density of 1.1 g/mL and this buoyant density 
could be increased towards a more RNA-like buoyant 
density by treatment with a combination of phospholipase 
A2 and cyclodextrin (1.13Á1.16 g/mL) or an SDS-based lysis 
buffer (1.15Á1.18 g/mL). This increase in apparent RNA </p>

<p>density by lipid extraction treatments demonstrates that 
the RNA is in a lipid complex such that the removal of less 
dense lipids increase their apparent density. Until now, 
there are no evidence to suggest that RNA-containing EVs 
from MSCs were physically different from other EVs. ST-
EVs carry at least 50% of the total MSC EV RNA, while 
both CTB-and AV-EVs each carry less than 0.5%. There-
fore, any EV RNA-mediated biological activity is likely to 
reside with ST-EVs, and not CTB-and AV-EVs. Although 
this nuclear location of the binding site could provide a 
rationale for its RNA cargo, the biogenesis and the 
biological significance of ST-EVs, its cargo of relatively 
short and seemingly non-functional RNAs, and its cargo 
of fibronectin, an extracellular protein, are enigmatic from 
our present perspective of EV biogenesis and functions. To 
date, biogenesis of EVs from the nucleus has not been 
described and no currently known biological process or 
processes could provide a mechanistic model for the 
biogenesis of EVs that involves both nuclear materials 
and extracellular matrix proteins. 
In summary, MSC produces at least 3 distinct 100 hm 
EV types, CTB-, AV-and ST-EVs, that could be dis-
tinguished by their membrane lipid composition, their 
proteome and RNA cargo. The unique presence of RNA 
and fibronectin in ST-EVs and the mutually exclusive EV 
binding activity of CTB and AV demonstrate that these 
3 EV types are unique entities. Based on the different 
subcellular location of CTB-, AV-and ST-binding activ-
ities in MSCs and other cell types, these EV types are likely 
to have a different biogenesis. However, the biological 
significance and functions of these different EV types 
remains to be elucidated. Nevertheless, the identification 
of these diverse EV types provides the initial key in 
stratifying and clarifying the diverse and often disparate 
biological functions that had been attributed to EVs in 
general. </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Visualization of CTB-, AV-and ST-binding in immortalized human skeletal myoblasts and keratinocytes. Cells were fixed and 
stained with labelled CTB, AV or ST (green), and counterstained with Hoechst 33342 to visualize the nuclei (blue). Scale bars, 10 mm. </p>

<p>MSC secretes at least 3 EV types </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We gratefully acknowledge Jayanthi Padmanabhan (BTI) for the 
preparation of the conditioned medium and purification of the 
exosomes and Dr Adrian Hui Kuang Boey (IMB-IMCB Joint 
Electron Microscopy Suite, A*STAR Singapore) for assistance in 
preparing and imaging specimens for this research. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest and funding </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest and have not 
received any funding or benefits from industry or any for 
profit organization for this work. </p>



<p>Ruenn Chai Lai et al. </p>



<p>(page number not for citation purpose) </p>

<p>Citation: Journal of Extracellular Vesicles 2016, 5: 29828 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jev.v5.29828 </p>

</text></tei>