<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4614601" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Introduction: Motion artifacts are a common problem in pediatric radiographic studies and are a common indica-
tion for pediatric procedural sedation. This study aimed to compare the combination of oral midazolam and keta-
mine (OMK) with oral midazolam alone (OM) as procedural sedatives among children undergoing computed to-
mography (CT) imaging. Methods: The study population was comprised of six-month to six-year old patients with 
medium-risk minor head trauma, who were scheduled to undergo brain CT imaging. Patients were randomly allo-
cated to two groups: one group received 0.5 mg/kg midazolam (OM group; n = 33) orally and the other one received 
0.2 mg/kg midazolam and 5 mg/kg ketamine orally (OMK group; n=33). The vital signs were monitored and rec-
orded at regular intervals. The primary outcome measure was the success rate of each drug in achieving adequate 
sedation. Secondary outcome measures were the time to achieve adequate sedation, time to discharge from radiol-
ogy department, and the incidence of adverse events. Results: Adequate sedation was achieved in five patients 
(15.2%) in OM group and 15 patients (45.5%) in OMK group, which showed a statistically significant difference 
between the groups (p = 0.015). No significant difference was noted between OM and OMK groups with respect to 
the time of achieving adequate sedation (33.80 ± 7.56 and 32.87 ± 10.18 minutes, respectively; p = 0.854) and the 
time of discharging from radiology department (89.60 ± 30.22 and 105.27 ± 21.98 minutes, respectively; p=0.223). 
The complications were minor and similar among patients of both groups. Conclusion: This study demonstrated 
that in comparison with OM, OMK was more effective in producing a satisfactory level of sedation in children un-
dergoing CT examinations without additional complications; however, none of these two regimens fulfilled clinical 
needs for procedural sedation. 
self-maintenance of a patent airway, minimal effects on 
respiration or hemodynamics, and rapid recovery (6). 
Over the last few years, researchers have shown a special 
interest in finding effective, nonparenteral, sedative 
agents that do not have injection problems (3). Ketamine 
is a noncompetitive antagonist of the N-methyl-D-aspar-
tate receptor (NMDAR), which is used for premedication, 
sedation, and induction as well as maintenance of gen-
eral anesthesia. Quick onset, short duration of action, 
and maintenance of laryngeal reflexes have made it a 
popular sedative choice for pediatric patients in the 
emergency department (7). Although ketamine is known 
as a parenteral agent, some researchers have success-
fully used it as an oral sedative drug (8, 9). Midazolam is </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>This open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 3.0 License (CC BY-NC 3.0). 
Copyright © 2015 Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences. All rights reserved. Downloaded from: www.jemerg.com </p>

<p>65 Emergency (2015); 3 (2): 64-69 </p>

<p>a potent benzodiazepine with rapid onset and offset ef-
fects as well as anxiolytic and amnestic properties, which 
can be administered through different routes (i.e. oral, 
intravenous, intramuscular, rectal, sublingual, and in-
tranasal). Oral midazolam (OM) is a safe and effective 
choice for sedation in children (10). In previous studies, 
the authors have used a combination of oral midazolam 
and ketamine (OMK) as premedication and sedative reg-
imens; besides, some studies reported that combination 
therapy has higher efficacy without any additional ad-
verse effects in comparison to the methods using each 
drug alone (11, 12). To the best of our knowledge, lim-
ited number of studies have reported the use of OM dur-
ing imaging, which had reported lower effectiveness rate 
in comparison with chloral hydrate (13, 14); however, 
OMK has not been used for this purpose, yet. Therefore, 
this study was conducted to compare the effects of OMK 
with OM as procedural sedatives in pediatric patients 
undergoing CT imaging. 
Methods: 
Study design and setting 
This randomized, double-blinded, clinical trial was con-
ducted from November 2012 to November 2013 in two 
teaching hospitals (Ayatollah Kashani Hospital and Alza-
hara Hospital) affiliated to Isfahan University of Medical 
Sciences, Isfahan, Iran. The study protocol was approved 
by Ethics Committee of the Isfahan University of Medical 
Sciences. All parents or guardians were informed of the 
study's protocol, risks, and benefits and were asked to 
sign an informed written consent. 
Participants 
We included six-month to six-year old children with me-
dium-risk minor head trauma who were scheduled to 
undergo brain CT scan (15). Medium-risk minor head 
trauma was defined as initial Glasgow coma scale score 
of 15 with any history of brief loss of consciousness, 
posttraumatic amnesia, vomiting, headache, or intoxica-
tion. All of these patients were classified as status I or II 
according to American Society of Anesthesiologists 
(ASA) physical status classification. Children with neuro-
logical disorders, anomalies of the cardiovascular sys-
tem, known allergy to midazolam, gastritis, any serious 
systemic diseases, those on long-term treatment with 
hepatic enzyme-inducing drugs or those receiving eryth-
romycin concurrently (due to drug interaction), and pa-
tients who had received medication within the preceding 
48 hours were excluded. 
Procedure 
Patients were randomly allocated to two groups; OM 
Group received 0.5 mg/kg midazolam (produced by; 
Tehran Shimi, Tehran, Iran) orally and OMK Group re-
ceived 0.2 mg/kg midazolam and 5 mg/kg ketamine 
(produced by; Rotexmedica, Trittau, Germany) orally. 
Randomization was conducted using a computer-gener-</p>

<p>ated sequence and block randomization protocol. Demo-
graphic and basic characteristics such as age, height, 
gender, weight, body mass index (BMI), and history of 
any medical condition were recorded before administra-
tion of study drugs. Then a nurse, who was blinded to the 
study, mixed both of the medications with 5 mL of sugar 
syrup to make it palatable. The parents gave the pre-
pared syrup to the children under the researchers' su-
pervision. Pulse rate and oxygen saturation (SaO2) were 
continuously monitored by a portable pulse oximeter. 
Blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, and SaO2 
were recorded at baseline (just before drug administra-
tion) and every 30 minutes until the patient was dis-
charged from the radiology department. The level of se-
dation of patients after drug administration was as-
sessed using Ramsay sedation scale (RSS) (16). RSS of 
four was considered as adequate sedation depth to tol-
erate diagnostic imaging studies. Patients who did not 
show satisfactory response to the sedative drugs within 
40 minutes and those who were awakened or moved 
during the imaging were excluded from further analysis. 
The interval between administration of sedative drugs 
and achieving RSS of four was considered as the time to 
achieve adequate sedation. Once the patients achieved 
adequate sedation, they were transferred to a scanner 
room and the imaging was performed according to the 
protocol. After the scan, the patients were transferred to 
another room in the radiology department to monitor 
and observe their conditions. The time to discharge from 
radiology department was defined as the interval be-
tween the start of sedative administration and return to 
the baseline alertness and spontaneous breathing. 
Statistical analyses 
All statistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). The categorical data 
were analyzed using Fisher's exact test. Parametric data 
were analyzed using the student's t-test. Descriptive sta-
tistics were expressed as mean ± standard deviation or 
number (percentage). Statistical significance was set at 
p &lt; 0.05. Two-way ANOVA was used to compare changes 
of vital signs during 180 minutes after drug administra-
tion between two groups. 
Results: 
66 participants were enrolled. Figure 1 shows the CON-
SORT flow diagram of study. The mean age of partici-
pants was 2.8 ± 1.6 years (range: 6 months to 6 years) 
and 54.5% of the participants were male. Table 1 shows 
the basic characteristics of patients. There was no signif-
icant difference between the two groups in age, height, 
weight, and male to female ratio (Table 1). Table 2 com-
pares outcomes between two groups. Adequate sedation 
(RSS of 4) was achieved in five patients (15.2%) in the 
OM group and 15 patients (45.5%) in the OMK group, 
which showed a statistically significant difference (p = 
0.015). No significant difference was found between the </p>

<p>This open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 3.0 License (CC BY-NC 3.0). 
Copyright © 2015 Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences. All rights reserved. Downloaded from: www.jemerg.com </p>

<p>Majidinejad et al </p>

<p>
groups in time of achieving adequate sedation (p = 
0.854) and the time of discharging from radiology de-
partment (p = 0.223). Adverse effects observed in two 
patients (one with nausea and another with vomiting) in 
the OM group and three patients (two with nausea and </p>

<p>one patient with vomiting) in the OMK group. Complica-
tions were minor and transient and did not differ be-
tween study groups (p &gt; 0.05). No serious adverse 
events were seen in the study participant. Systolic blood 
pressure, SaO2 level, pulse rate, and respiratory rate </p>

<p>Figure 1: CONSORT flow diagram of study </p>

<p>Table 1: Demographic characteristics of the participants a 
Characteristics 
Midazolam 
Midazolam-Ketamine 
P Value 
Height (centimeter) 
101 ± 19 
103 ± 20 
0.147 
Weight (kilogram) 
15.7 ± 4.8 
17.5 ± 14.6 
0.234 
Age (year) 
3.0 ± 1.6 
2.6 ± 1.6 
0.369 
Male to Female ratio 
17:16 
19:14 
0.805 </p>

<p>a , Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 2: The outcomes of patients in Midazolam and Midazolam-Ketamine groups 
Outcome 
OM Group 
OMK Group 
P Value 
Adequately Sedated 1 
5 (15.2%) 
15 (45.5%) 
0.015 
Time 2 to Become Adequately Sedated 
33.80 ± 7.56 
32.87 ± 10.18 
0.854 
Time 2 to Discharge From RD 
89.60 ± 30.22 
105.27 ± 21.98 
0.223 </p>

<p>OM: Oral midazolam; OMK: Combination of oral midazolam-ketamine; RD: Radiology department. 1 , Number (%); 2 , Mean ± standard devia-
tion (minute) </p>

<p>This open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 3.0 License (CC BY-NC 3.0). 
Copyright © 2015 Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences. All rights reserved. Downloaded from: www.jemerg.com </p>

<p>67 Emergency (2015); 3 (2): 64-69 </p>

<p>showed no significant inter-group differences at base-
line and at various time points after administration of 
the drugs (for all analysis: df = 18, p &gt; 0.05, Figure 2). 
Discussion: 
Our investigation showed that in comparison to OM, 
OMK successfully induced sedation in 45% of the pa-
tients. OM failed to sedate the patient in 85% of the cases 
and led to administration of additional medication and 
longer time to obtain the scan. 
Ketamine is used for premedication, sedation, and induc-
tion as well as maintenance of general anesthesia with 
minimal effect on respiration and tendency to preserve 
autonomic reflexes (7). Oral ketamine (OK) has been </p>

<p>used for pediatric sedation in previous studies. It has 
been reported that 10 mg/kg of ketamine provides effec-
tive sedation and analgesia in young children undergo-
ing wound repair processes (9). Moreover, 6 mg/kg of 
OK was reported to be effective in sedation for outpa-
tient pediatric dental surgeries (10). OM is the most com-
monly used premedication in the United States (18), 
which has been used as a safe and effective sedative in 
pediatrics, mainly in pediatric dentistry (10, 17); how-
ever, intravenous midazolam has been found to induce 
more sedation (18). Intravenous or nasal midazolam has 
gained widespread popularity as a sedative for children 
undergoing radiographic studies such as CT scan (19-</p>

<p>Figure: Inter-group differences of vital signs at baseline and at various time points after administration of mid-
azolam and combination of midazolam-ketamine (df: 18, p &gt; 0.05 for all comparisons). </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>110 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>Heart </p>

<p>rate(beat/minute) </p>

<p>Time (minute) </p>

<p>Midazolam 
Midazolam/Ketamine </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>Respiratory </p>

<p>rate(per </p>

<p>minute) </p>

<p>Time (minute) </p>

<p>Midazolam 
Midazolam/Ketamine </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>85 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>110 </p>

<p>115 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>Systolic </p>

<p>blood </p>

<p>presure(mm </p>

<p>Hg) </p>

<p>Time (minute) </p>

<p>Midazolam 
Midazolam/Ketamine </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>98 </p>

<p>99 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>SaO 2 </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>Time (minute) </p>

<p>Midazolam 
Midazolam/Ketamine </p>

<p>This open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 3.0 License (CC BY-NC 3.0). 
Copyright © 2015 Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences. All rights reserved. Downloaded from: www.jemerg.com </p>

<p>Majidinejad et al </p>

<p>
21). The OMK and OM alone are safe, effective, and prac-
tical approach to manage children for minor dental pro-
cedures (22, 23). The efficacy of OM and ketamine, alone 
or in combination has been studied in pediatric dentistry 
sedation and premedication (24-26). Younge et al. re-
ported better sedative effects during suturing lacera-
tions with OK (10 mg/kg) in comparison to OM (0.7 
mg/kg) (27). Although our study was consistent with the 
previous studies regarding the higher efficacy of OMK in 
comparison to OM, most of the previous studies reported 
success rates of 60% to 90% for OM (11, 17, 28) and 46% 
to 95% for OMK (11, 22). Barkan et al. showed that the 
combination of oral midazolam (0.5 mg/kg) and keta-
mine (5 mg/kg) led to deeper sedation in comparison 
with OM (0.5 mg/kg) alone in children requiring lacera-
tion repair. In addition, 27% of patients in the OM group 
and 6% in the OMK group needed further intravenous 
sedation (11). Moriera et al. (12) compared the efficacy 
of OM (1 mg/kg) and the OMK (midazolam, 0.5 mg/kg; 
and ketamine, 3 mg/kg) for guiding the behavior of chil-
dren undergoing dental treatment and reported higher 
efficacy of OMK. On the other hand, there are several 
studies reporting lower success rate, which are similar 
to our findings. Moro-Sutherland et al. (6) compared the 
sedative effects of intravenous midazolam with pento-
barbital during brain CT imaging in children aged six 
months to six years. They administered pentobarbital to 
29 patients (53%) and midazolam (mean dose, 0.2 ± 0.03 
mg/kg) to 26 patients (47%). In the midazolam group, 
only five patients (19%) were successfully scanned with 
midazolam alone and the remaining 21 patients (81%) 
required additional medication and took a longer time to 
scan. Another investigation reported a failure rate of 
60% in administrating intranasal midazolam (0.2 
mg/kg) for sedation of children undergoing CT scan (3). 
Molter et al. (29) used 0.4 mg/kg of OM 20 minutes be-
fore the induction of general anesthesia and reported a 
mild or no sedative effect in 76% to 84% of patients. In 
this study, the onset time of adequate sedation was 33 
minutes in OM group and 32 minutes in OMK group. 
Younge et al. (27) reported an onset time of 20 minutes 
for OK and 43 minutes for OM. Other studies reported 
that the time to reach optimal sedation level would be 15 
minutes for OM (10, 17). Studies, which used OM (0.5-1 
mg/kg) as premedication reported that the best time for 
optimal preoperative sedation would be 30 to 45 
minutes before scan (30). This time for ketamine is 25 to 
45 minutes (9, 31). Barkan observed that the needed 
time to achieve adequate sedation was 17 minutes for 
OM and 14 minutes for OMK. The patients' blood pres-
sure, respiratory rate, pulse rate, and SaO2 levels did not 
show any significant changes during the sedation. Alt-
hough ketamine and midazolam affect the respiratory 
and hemodynamics responses (11), our results were in 
line with the findings of previous studies that reported </p>

<p>minimal effects of low-dose OM and OK on these param-
eters (17, 31). Although further studies are needed to 
confirm or refute our results and attention to the phar-
macological aspects is necessary, lower efficacy of OM in 
this study could be explained as follows: 
First, we used these drugs for CT imaging that needs a 
deeper level of sedation in comparison with some other 
studies that used those drugs in other settings as pre-
medication. Second, in the previous studies, intravenous 
forms of these drugs were used, which might bring about 
unexpected results; the same drugs in different studies 
should be compared with caution. Third, the ethnic dif-
ferences in response to these sedative agents might af-
fect the results. Variability of drug response is an im-
portant consideration in clinical medicine. A major cause 
of variations in drug responses is hepatic cytochrome 
P450 oxidase (CYP450)-mediated drug metabolism (29). 
Distribution volumes and metabolism determine the 
pharmacokinetics of midazolam. Midazolam is almost 
exclusively metabolized by CYP450 3A (CYP3A) isoen-
zymes (32). There are several limitations to this study. 
First, we could not purchase the oral form of drugs. Alt-
hough previous studies have shown that these paren-
teral forms can be used orally, the oral form of drugs 
might bring about results that are more precise. Second, 
the number of participants who were included in the fi-
nal analysis (as sedated patients) was small. 
Conclusion: 
This study demonstrated that in comparison with OM, 
OMK was more effective in producing a satisfactory level 
of sedation in children undergoing CT examinations 
without additional complications; however, none of 
these two regimens fulfilled clinical needs for procedural 
sedation. 
Acknowledgments: 
The authors appreciate the insightful cooperation of staff 
of the Emergency Department. 
Conflict of interest: 
None 
Funding support: 
None 
Authors' contributions: 
All authors passed four criteria for authorship contribu-
tion based on recommendations of the International 
Committee of Medical Journal Editors. 
References: </p>



<p>This open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 3.0 License (CC BY-NC 3.0). 
Copyright © 2015 Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences. All rights reserved. Downloaded from: www.jemerg.com </p>

<p>69 Emergency (2015); 3 (2): 64-69 </p>



</text></tei>