<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4623144" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Inhibins are members of the TGFβ superfamily and act as suppressors of follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) 
secretion from pituitary glands via a negative feedback mechanism to regulate folliculogenesis. In this study, the INHBB gene 
was knocked down by three RNAi-Ready pSIREN-RetroQ-ZsGreen vector-mediated recombinant plasmids to explore the 
effects of INHBB silencing on granulosa cell (GC) cell cycle, apoptosis and steroid production in vitro. Quantitative real-time 
polymerase chain reaction, Western blot, flow cytometry and ELISA were performed to evaluate the role of INHBB in the mouse 
GC cell cycle, apoptosis and steroid production in vitro. The results showed that the relative mRNA and protein expression of 
INHBB in mouse GCs can be significantly reduced by RNAi with pshRNA-B1, pshRNA-B2 and pshRNA-B3 plasmids, with 
pshRNA-B3 having the best knockdown efficiency. Downregulation of the expression of INHBB significantly arrests cells 
in the G1 phase of the cell cycle and increases the apoptosis rate in GCs. This was further confirmed by downregulation of 
the protein expressions of Cyclin D1, Cyclin E and Bcl2, while the protein expression of Bax was upregulated. In addition, 
specific downregulation of INHBB markedly decreased the concentration of estradiol and progesterone, which was further 
validated by the decrease in the mRNA levels of CYP19A1and CYP11A1. These findings suggest that inhibin βB is important 
in the regulation of apoptosis and cell cycle progression in granulosa cells. Furthermore, the inhibin βB subunit has a role in the 
regulation of steroid hormone biosynthesis. Evidence is accumulating to support the concept that inhibin βB is physiologically 
essential for early folliculogenesis in the mouse. 
GCs transfected with different RNAi vectors were harvested at 48 
h post transfection, washed with PBS, fixed in ice-cold 70% ethanol 
overnight at 4 C, washed again in PBS and stained using propidium 
iodide/RNase A solution at 37 C in a dark chamber for 30 min. 
Flow cytometric analysis was conducted using a BD FACSCalibur 
(Becton, Dickinson and Company, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA) and 
the <rs id="software-0" type="software">ModFit LT</rs> for Mac V<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.0</rs> software. For each sample, a minimum 
of 20,000 cells was analyzed. All experiments were repeated three 
times independently. </p>

<p>Apoptosis analysis </p>

<p>After transfection, GCs were washed with PBS and then har-
vested by digestion with trypsin without EDTA at 37 C for 5 min. 
Cell apoptosis was probed with Annexin V-APC/7-AAD and later 
detected by flow cytometry (BD FACSCalibur, Becton, Dickinson 
and Company) according to the manufacturer's instruction (Apoptosis 
Detection Kit, KeyGEN, Nanjing, PR China). To confirm the role of 
INHBB silencing in apoptosis, the protein expressions of BCL-2 and </p>

<p>BAX were quantified by Western blot. Experiments were repeated 
three times independently. </p>

<p>Hormone analysis by ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent 
assay) </p>

<p>Mouse GCs were cultured (2 × 10 4 viable cells in 200 µl medium) 
in a 96-well plate. After transfection with the respective vectors for 
48 h, the culture medium was collected, and the concentrations of 
estradiol (E2) and progesterone (P4) were measured by mouse ELISA 
kits (Wuhan ColorfulGene Biological Technology, PR China). The 
sensitivities of the estradiol and progesterone ELISA kits were 2-50 
ng/l and 40-2400 pmol/l, respectively. 
To elucidate the role of INHBB in steroidogenesis, we quantified 
the mRNA expression of CYP19A1 and CYP11A1 genes 48 h after 
transfection between pshRNA-B3 and pshRNA-negative vectors, 
respectively. Experiments were repeated three times independently. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The data are presented as the means ± SD from three replicate 
experiments. Differences were evaluated using the Student's t test 
following one-way ANOVA with the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">16.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS</rs>, 
Chicago, IL, USA). P &lt; 0.05 was regarded as statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The INHBB gene was efficiently knocked down by 
pshRNA-B3 </p>

<p>The expression of GFP was first observed under fluorescent 
microscopy beginning 24 h after transfection (Fig. 1), and then the 
mRNA and protein levels of INHBB were detected by real-time PCR 
and Western blot, respectively. The results showed that all three 
plasmids were able to knockdown the mRNA expression of INHBB, 
with pshRNA-B3 having the greatest effect (~58%) when compared 
with the other recombinant RNAi vectors (Fig. 2). However, after 
INHBB silencing, only two plasmids (pshRNA-B2 and pshRNA-B3) 
were able to downregulate the protein expression of INHBB (Fig. 3). 
These results permitted us to select the plasmid named pshRNA-B3 
as the best recombinant RNAi vector for further experiments. </p>

<p>Effects of INHBB gene silencing on the cell cycle </p>

<p>Cell cycle distribution was determined by measuring the cellular 
DNA content by flow cytometry. The results showed that INHBB 
silencing significantly induced (P &lt; 0.05) G1 phase arrest of the cell 
cycle (Figs. 4 A and B). In addition, to further confirm these results, 
the protein levels of cell cycle factors (Cyclin D1 and Cyclin E) 
were determined by Western blot. The results showed a significant 
decrease in protein levels of Cyclin D1 and Cyclin E (P &lt; 0.05) after </p>

<p>Table 2. Sequences of primer pairs for quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>Gene name 
Forward primer sequences (5'→3') 
Reverse primer sequences (5'→3') </p>

<p>GAPDH 
GGCAAATTCAACGGCACAGT 
TAGGGCCTCTCTTGCTCAGT 
INHBB 
CGCGTCTCCGAGATCATCAG 
AGCTGGCTGGTCCTCACAG 
CYP19A1 
GCACAGTCACTACATCTCCCGA 
CACACAAACTTCCACCATTCGA 
CYP11A1 
ACACTGAGACTCCACCCCAT 
CTCGACCCATGGCAAAGCTA </p>

<p>M'BAYE et al. </p>

<p>
INHBB RNAi (Fig. 5A). These results demonstrated that INHBB had 
a crucial role in the proliferation of mouse GCs. </p>

<p>Effects of INHBB gene silencing on apoptosis </p>

<p>To elucidate the role of INHBB in GC apoptosis, double staining 
with Annexin V-APC/7-AAD was used after transfection. The results 
indicated a significant increase in apoptotic cells (P &lt; 0.05) (Table 3). 
To further reveal the effects of INHBB knockdown on apoptosis, we 
quantified the protein expressions of BCL-2 and BAX. The results 
demonstrated that INHBB RNAi significantly reduced the protein 
level of BCL-2 but increased the protein level of BAX (Fig. 5B). 
These results revealed that INHBB is a strong apoptotic inhibitor 
during the development of mouse granulosa cells. </p>

<p>Effects of INHBB gene silencing on hormones levels </p>

<p>To assess the effects of INHBB silencing on hormones levels, 
we measured the concentrations of estradiol and progesterone in 
culture medium 48 h post transfection. The results showed that 
the concentrations of estradiol and progesterone were significantly 
decreased in GCs transfected with pshRNA-B3 (P &lt; 0.05) compared 
with those transfected with pshRNA-negative (Table 4). 
To further elucidate the role of INHBB in steroidogenesis, we 
quantified the mRNA expressions of CYP19A1 and CYP11A1 genes 
48 h post transfection. The results showed that the relative mRNA 
levels of CYP19A1 and CYP11A1 were significantly decreased (P </p>

<p>&lt; 0.05) in GCs transfected with pshRNA-B3 compared with those 
transfected with pshRNA-negative (Figs. 6A and B). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The aim of the present study was to investigate the effects of 
INHBB gene silencing on the cell cycle, apoptosis and steroidogenesis 
in mouse granulosa cells. We transiently knocked down INHBB 
gene in primary mouse granulosa cells, which highly expresses 
INHBB. The results demonstrated that knockdown of the INHBB 
gene by RNAi vectors downregulated both the mRNA and protein 
expression of INHBB in mouse granulosa cells. This result indicates 
that INHBB RNAi expression plasmids were successfully constructed 
and transfected into mouse granulosa cells. 
To investigate the role of INHBB in cell cycle regulation, we 
detected different phases of the cell cycle in GCs after INHBB 
knockdown. The results showed that the G1 phase of the cell cycle 
was significantly arrested compared with the control. In the present </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Transfection and knockdown efficiency of INHBB RNAi vectors. 
Three (3) groups of INHBB RNAi recombinant plasmids were 
transfected in mouse GCs named as pshRNA-B1, pshRNA-B2, 
pshRNA-B3 and pshRNA-negative. After 48 h, the expression of 
GFP in the recombinant plasmids were shown, which implied that 
INHBB recombinant plasmids could be high efficiently expressed 
in mouse GCs. The best efficient RNAi vector (pshRNA-B3) was 
selected for further investigation. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Expression of INHBB in transfected GCs. The mRNA level 
of INHBB in mouse GCs was detected after transfection with 
INHBB knockdown vectors, respectively. The ratio is relative to 
the pshRNA-negative control group. All silencing vectors could 
efficiently knockdown the expression of INHBB with pshRNA-B3 
having the best silencing efficiency, which was chosen for further 
study. Values are presented as the mean ± SEM (n = 3 in each 
group). Bars with different letters indicate significantly different 
at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Fig. 3. INHBB protein levels in transfected GCs. INHBB protein 
levels were detected by western blot in mouse GCs 48 h after 
transfection. Lanes 1 to 4 represent the pshRNA-B1, pshRNA-B2, 
pshRNA-B3, and pshRNA-negative, respectively. Normalized 
ratios of INHBB band intensities were calculated by dividing 
the mean signal intensity for 3 biological replicates by the mean 
signal intensity with GAPDH. Values are presented as the mean ± 
SEM. Different letters (a, b) indicate significantly different at P &lt; 
0.05. </p>

<p>INHBB KNOCKDOWN IN MOUSE GRANULOSA CELLS </p>



<p>study, GCs after INHBB knockdown showed decreased protein levels 
of cyclin D1 and Cyclin E, which are the key regulators of the cell 
cycle progression from the G0/G1 phase to S phase [33, 34]. We 
believe that INHBB has the potential to affect GC development by 
regulating the cell cycle progression from G1 phase to S phase to </p>

<p>modulate ovarian function. In a previous study, INHA was also found 
to be involved in Sertoli cell progression in the mouse [27]. Taken 
together, these results indicate that INHBB is important in control 
of the cell cycle in mouse GCs. 
Folliculogenesis in mammals includes follicular growth and 
follicular atresia. Follicular growth involves proliferation, cell cycle 
control and differentiation of GCs. However, only a few follicles 
reach the ovulation stage, and most follicles are lost before ovulation 
due to atresia. This degenerative process is initiated or caused by 
apoptosis of granulosa cells. It is well established that the cross 
talk between cell death and survival signals is very important for 
follicular development, and whether the follicle ultimately ovulates or 
undergoes degeneration is dependent on the multiple ovarian factors 
that regulate cell proliferation, differentiation and apoptosis. Previous 
studies in rat have demonstrated that INHA increases apoptosis in early 
ovarian antral follicles treated with diethylstilbestrol [35]. Recently, 
it was found that miR-34a plays an important role in granulosa cell 
apoptosis by targeting the INHBB gene in the porcine ovary [36]. 
Based on these studies, we predicted that INHBB knockdown might 
reduce cell survivability by increasing apoptosis in mouse GCs. In 
support of this, our results showed that INHBB knockdown induced 
apoptosis in mouse GCs. Moreover, we found an increase in protein 
level of BAX and a decrease in protein level of BCL-2 after INHBB 
downregulation. Members of the BCL-2 gene family, such as BAX 
and BCL-2, play key roles in regulating apoptosis, which is the 
process of self-destruction of cells under physiological conditions 
[37]. In the female gonads the roles of the BCL-2 family members 
and BAX in apoptosis have been extensively studied, and they are </p>

<p>Fig. 4. DNA-content of transfected mouse GCs by flow cytometry. 
Following a 48-h transfection with pshRNA-B3 and pshRNA-
negative respectively, GCs were treated for DNA content by 
propidium iodide. (A) Histogram showing the proportions of cells 
that are in the three phases of the cell cycle using flow cytometry 
to measure their relative DNA content. G0/G1-phase cells are 
diploid (2N) and express half the DNA content of tetraploid G2/M 
phase cells (4N). S phase cells contain varying amounts of DNA 
between the G1 and G2 phases. (B) A graph presenting the % 
of GCs in each of the cell cycle phases. Values are presented as 
means ± SEM (n = 3 in each group). An asterisk (*) indicates 
significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Protein levels of related genes in transfected GCs. The protein 
levels of Cyclin D1, Cyclin E, BCL-2 and BAX were detected 
by western blot 48 h after transfection with the pshRNA-B3 and 
pshRNA-negative plasmids, respectively. The normalized ratio 
for each protein was calculated by dividing the mean signal 
intensity from 3 biological replicates by the mean signal intensity 
with GAPDH. Values are presented as the mean ± SEM (n = 3 in 
each group). Different letters (a, b) indicate significantly different 
at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>Table 3. Effects of INHBB silencing on apoptosis in mouse GCs (n=3) </p>

<p>Groups 
Live cells (%) 
Apoptotic cells (%) </p>

<p>pshRNA-B3 
77.80 ± 0.30 
22.68 ± 1.58 * 
pshRNA-Negative 
83.71 ± 0.66 
15.90 ± 2.23 </p>

<p>Values represent the mean ± SEM (n = 3). All results were evaluated 
by one-way ANOVA. An asterisk (*) indicates the level of significance 
within columns (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Table 4. Effects of INHBB silencing on the levels of estradiol and 
progesterone (n=3) </p>

<p>Groups 
Estradiol (ng/l) 
Progesterone (pmol/l) </p>

<p>pshRNA-B3 
9.86 ± 1.34 ** 
2124.24 ± 1.66 * 
pshRNA-Negative 
28.05 ± 1.27 
2306.17 ± 1.44 </p>

<p>Values represent the mean ± SEM (n = 3). Asterisks (** and *) indicate the 
level of significance within columns P &lt; 0.01 and P &lt;0.05, respectively. </p>

<p>M'BAYE et al. </p>

<p>
regarded as key factors in initiating or preventing apoptosis in female 
germ cells [38]. Overexpression of BAX accelerates the apoptotic 
death response to death signals [39]. These findings confirmed that 
INHBB knockdown increased the apoptosis rate in mouse GCs. 
The major functions of granulosa cells include the production of 
sex steroids as well as a myriad of growth factors thought to interact 
with the oocyte during its development. The sex steroid production 
consists of FSH stimulating granulosa cells to convert androgens 
(coming from the thecal cells) to estradiol by aromatase during 
the follicular phase of the menstrual cycle [40]. Therefore, culture 
of ovarian GCs is an essential model for studying the molecular 
mechanisms of gene regulation during folliculogenesis. Follicular 
development is a complex biological process regulated by various 
intrinsic factors, especially estradiol (E2) and progesterone (P4). 
In our culture system, INHBB silencing significantly reduced the 
concentrations of estradiol and progesterone in the culture medium of </p>

<p>the pshRNA-B3 group compared with the control group. The lower 
levels of these two hormones might be due to the lower mRNA level 
of CYP11A1 caused by INHBB knockdown, which is responsible 
for initiation of the steroidogenesis cascade in the ovary [41] and 
the decrease in CYP19A1 mRNA level, the enzyme responsible for 
androgen aromatization to estrogen [42]. 
In conclusion, our results demonstrate that RNA interference can 
be used to significantly reduce INHBB expression in mouse granulosa 
cells in vitro. The data provide evidence that inhibin/activin βB is 
important in the regulation of apoptosis and cell cycle progression 
in granulosa cells. This was further confirmed by the associative 
apoptotic and cell cycle factors. Furthermore, the inhibin βB subunit 
has a role in the regulation of steroid hormone biosynthesis. Evidence 
is accumulating to support the concept that inhibin/activin βB is 
physiologically essential for early folliculogenesis in the mouse. </p>

<p>This study was supported by both the Earmarked fund for Mod-
ern Agro-industry Technology Research System (grant number 
CARS-37-05B) and National Natural Science Foundation of China 
(No. 31272446 and No. 31001007). </p>



<p>Fig. 6. Expression of CYP19A1 and CYP11A1 in transfected GCs. 
The mRNA levels of CYP19A1 and CYP11A1 genes in GCs 
transfected with pshRNA-B3 and pshRNA-negative respectively 
were determined 48 h after transfection by q-PCR. The results 
showed that the mRNA level of CYP19A1 (P &lt; 0.05) (A) and 
CYP11A1 (P &lt; 0.05) (B) were significantly downregulated in 
pshRNA-B3 group compared with pshRNA-negative group. 
Values are presented as the mean ± SEM, n = 3 in each group. Bars 
with different mark indicate significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>INHBB KNOCKDOWN IN MOUSE GRANULOSA CELLS </p>





</text></tei>