<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4455856" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Decentralization and task shifting has significantly improved access to 
antiretroviral therapy (ART). Many studies conducted to determine the attrition rate in Ethiopia 
have not compared attrition rates between hospitals and health centers in a relatively recent 
cohort of patients. This study compared death and loss to follow-up (LTFU) rates among ART 
patients in hospitals and health centers in south Ethiopia. 
Methods: Data routinely collected from patients aged older than 15 years who started ART 
between July 2011 and August 2012 in 20 selected health facilities (12 being hospitals) were 
analyzed. The outcomes of interest were LTFU and death. The data were entered, cleaned, and 
analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20.0</rs> and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 12.0</rs>. 
Competing-risk regression models were used. 
Results: The service years of the facilities were similar (median 8 and 7.5 for hospitals and health 
centers, respectively). The mean patient age was 33.7±9.6 years. The median baseline CD4 count 
was 179 (interquartile range 93-263) cells/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. A total of 2,356 person-years of observation 
were made with a median follow-up duration of 28 (interquartile range 22-31) months; 24.6% 
were either dead or LTFU, resulting in a retention rate of 75.4%. The death rates were 3.0 and 
1.5 and the LTFU rate were 9.0 and 10.9 per 100 person-years of observation in health centers 
and hospitals, respectively. The competing-risk regression model showed that the gap between 
testing and initiation of ART, body mass index, World Health Organization clinical stage, 
isoniazid prophylaxis, age, facility type, and educational status were independently associated 
with LTFU. Moreover, baseline tuberculous disease, poor functional status, and follow-up at a 
health center were associated with an elevated probability of death. 
Conclusion: We observed a higher death rate and a lower LTFU rate in health centers than in 
hospitals. Most of the associated variables were also previously documented. Higher LTFU was 
noticed for patients with a smaller gap between testing and initiation of treatment. 
The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that approximately 35.0 million 
people were living with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) at the end of 2013, 
with 2.1 million people becoming newly infected with HIV in 2013 globally. In 2013, 
12.9 million people living with HIV were receiving antiretroviral therapy (ART) glob-
ally, of which 11.7 million were receiving ART in low-income and middle-income 
countries. The 11.7 million people on ART represent 36% of the 32.6 million people 
living with HIV in low-income and middle-income countries. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care 
28 May 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>168 </p>

<p>Teshome et al </p>

<p>The Southern Nations Nationalities and Peoples' Regional 
State is the third largest administrative region in Ethiopia 
and represents about 20% of the country's population. The 
prevalence of HIV in the region was estimated at 1.5%. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>According to the 2013 health performance report of the 
regional heath bureau, 35,271 patients had ever started on 
ART, while 24,900 patients were currently on ART, up from 
14,493 in 2010. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>As the number of patients on ART continues to increase, 
it will be of paramount importance to give due focus to the 
quality of care, to ensure optimal viral suppression and to 
improve quality of life for people living with HIV/acquired 
immune deficiency syndrome. One of these is to ensure that 
patients are retained in care that will have both individual 
and societal benefit. 
4 A higher attrition rate has been linked 
to poorer viral suppression and increased morbidity and 
mortality, among many other undesirable outcomes, both at 
the community and individual level. 
5-11 Systematic reviews 
conducted previously indicate that rates of attrition from 
ART care are prevailing problems in sub-Saharan Africa. </p>

<p>12-14 </p>

<p>Previous studies in Ethiopia have shown a high attrition rate, 
although most were single facility-based studies and were 
conducted in relatively previous cohorts. 
9,15,16 Estimates 
of retention/attrition rates at the region level for relatively 
recent cohorts and comparisons of the rates in hospitals and 
health centers have not been done. Therefore, in this study, 
we estimated the attrition rate of HIV patients on ART in the 
region and attempted to identify predictors of such attrition, 
including facility type, which has not been studied previously. 
The findings will be used to identify interventions to improve 
retention in ART care. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Setting and HIV service delivery approach </p>

<p>The study was conducted in the Southern Nations Nationalities 
and Peoples' Regional State, Ethiopia. In the region, there are 
179 health facilities that are actively providing HIV-related 
services including ART. When disaggregated by facility type, 
there are 22 hospitals and 157 health centers. 
17 These facilities 
also provide a wide range of HIV prevention, treatment, care, 
and support services. HIV care in Ethiopia is delivered by a 
multidisciplinary team. The composition of the team depends 
on the facility type. The team normally consists of a clinician 
(medical doctor, nurse, or health officer), pharmacy person-
nel, and counselors for support with adherence. The team 
leader is a medical doctor if in the hospital setting or a health 
officer if in a health center. There is a formal referral and 
linkage system between hospitals and health centers. </p>

<p>18,19 </p>

<p>Study design and population </p>

<p>We collected data for the cohort of patients initiated on ART 
between July 2011 and August 2012 in 20 selected health 
facilities. Data collection ended in the last week of July, 
2014. Considering the available resources, we selected 20 
health facilities based on their share of the case load in the 
region. 
Next, we prepared the sample universe for hospitals and 
health centers separately. In order to avoid too much travel 
for few card reviews, we decided to include only facilities 
with a total case load of more than 100 patients. Accordingly, 
25 health centers and 22 hospitals were included in the 
sampling universe. Finally, a total of eight health centers 
and 12 hospitals were randomly selected, reflecting the fact 
that hospitals have higher patient loads than health centers. 
Random selection was done using a random number genera-
tor in Excel. </p>

<p>Data collection procedure and data 
collectors </p>

<p>A structured data abstraction format was used to extract the 
data from patient cards and corresponding registers. The 
format was developed using the standardized patient moni-
toring formats and registers employed by the ART clinics. 
Initially, ART registers were used to identify the cohort of 
interest. Then, using the unique ART number from the reg-
ister, other patient data that were not available on the register 
were retrieved from other formats, ie, the patient follow-up 
form and the patient intake form. Some questions were also 
included to capture the characteristics of the facility. 
The data collectors were already ART-trained health 
professionals who were actively working in ART care clinics 
in the region. They were trained for 3 days. The training ses-
sions included the purpose of the research and pilot testing 
of the data collection tools and processes. The format and 
other technical features were amended as deemed necessary 
after pretesting. All members of the research team acted as 
supervisors during the entire data collection period. </p>

<p>Data management and analysis </p>

<p>Data were entered, cleaned, and analyzed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Statistical 
Package for the Social Sciences</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 20.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY, USA). Each questionnaire was 
given a unique identification number for entry to simplify 
data cleaning. Tables, graphs, and different statistical sum-
mary measures were calculated based on the nature of the 
variables and their distribution. The time-to-event method 
was used to investigate predictors of loss to follow-up (LTFU) </p>

<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>169 </p>

<p>lTFU and death rates from ART in ethiopia </p>

<p>or death after initiation of ART across independent variables. 
Because of the competing outcomes of death and LTFU, the 
cause-specific Cox models commonly used for time-to-event 
analysis would yield biased estimates. Therefore, the multi-
variate analysis and estimation of the cumulative incidence 
of LTFU and mortality were performed using competing 
risk regression models taking the other events of interest as 
the competing event. The data were entered into <rs type="software">Statistical 
Package for the Social Sciences</rs> software, saved as <rs id="software-4" type="software">Stata</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 8SE</rs>, and exported to Stata statistical software (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Stata Corporation</rs>, Release 12, College Station, TX, USA). The 
regression analysis and cumulative incidence of LTFU or 
death was conducted using <rs id="software-5" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">version 12.0</rs>. We decided a 
priori to include selected variables in the multivariate model. 
Missing data for each factor was modeled as a separate cat-
egory. For all statistical tests, the level of significance was 
set at a type I error of 0.05. </p>

<p>Definitions of terms used </p>

<p>loss to follow-up </p>

<p>A patient was labeled as LTFU if he or she failed to visit the 
health facility for more than 3 months after the last appoint-
ment date. For the time-to-event analysis, the event date for 
LTFU was the last appointment date plus 91 days using the 
Gregorian calendar. </p>

<p>Functional status </p>

<p>Functional status was routinely assessed each time the patient 
came to the ART clinic for any purpose. A patient was catego-
rized as "working" if their daily activities were not altered due 
to illness, "ambulatory" if the patient was not fully working 
but was able to do minor tasks at home, and "bed ridden" 
when the patient remained in bed most of the time. </p>

<p>ethical considerations </p>

<p>Ethical clearance was obtained from the institutional 
review board of the Southern Nations Nationalities and 
Peoples' Regional State Health Bureau. In Ethiopia, patient 
consent is not required for use of data already existing 
within health facilities. The ethics statement from the 
regional health bureau waived the requirement for written 
consent from the study participants. Direct patient identi-
fiers, like names, were not collected during the research. 
All the data obtained during the course of the study were 
held securely in hard and soft copy form in the computer 
files. Patient records were anonymized and deidentified 
prior to analysis. The data were analyzed as group data 
and not as individual data. </p>

<p>Results 
Facility characteristics </p>

<p>The card reviews were conducted in 20 health facilities, 
comprising 12 hospitals and eight health centers. The 
selected facilities had a median HIV-related service of 8.0 
(interquartile range [IQR] 7-8) years. The median years of 
service for the selected hospitals was 8 (IQR 7.25-8) years 
and for the selected health centers was 7.5 (IQR 6.25-8.0) 
years. In the 20 facilities studied, a total of 17,476 patients 
were currently actively on treatment at the time of data 
collection. The selected facilities had 70.2% of the total 
patient load in the region. </p>

<p>Characteristics of study participants </p>

<p>A total of 1,173 patients were included in the study. Their mean 
age was 33.7±9.6 years. The majority were aged 26-39 years. 
Around 40% of the patients were initiated on treatment in the 
same month as learning of their HIV infection status. More than 
half (52.2%) did not have their height and/or weight recorded in 
any of the registers, so body mass index could not be calculated. 
Median CD4 count was 179 (IQR 93-263) cells/mm 
3 at initia-
tion of treatment. Around two-thirds of the hospital patients 
were included for chart review. Slightly more than half (53.6%) 
were in the early WHO clinical stage, while 12.6% were diag-
nosed with tuberculosis at baseline. Other demographic and 
clinical characteristics are shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Follow-up duration and outcome </p>

<p>A total of 2,356 person-years of observation (PYO) were 
available with a median follow-up duration until occurrence 
of any of the events or end of data collection time of 28 (IQR 
22-31) months. The cumulative outcome was death, LTFU, 
or transfers out in 4.0%, 20.6%, and 9.4%, respectively. The 
remaining 66.0% were actively on treatment when data col-
lection ended. When the analysis was performed separately 
for facility types, the cumulative incidence of death was 6.1% 
in health centers and 3.0% in hospitals, respectively, while 
the cumulative incidence of LTFU was 18.5% and 21.7% at 
health centers and hospitals. The incidence rate also showed 
a similar pattern. The death rate was 3.0 per 100 PYO in 
health centers and 1.5 per 100 PYO in hospitals. Figure 1 
shows the overall incidence of the different outcomes and 
stratified by facility type. </p>

<p>Cumulative incidence of death and lTFU 
stratified by facility type </p>

<p>The cumulative incidence of death was higher in health 
centers than in hospitals while the cumulative incidence of </p>

<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>170 </p>

<p>Teshome et al </p>

<p>initiation of treatment, relatively older age, and secondary or 
higher educational status protected against LTFU. In contrast, 
not starting isoniazid preventive therapy, late WHO clinical 
stage, being in hospital-based care, and poor functional 
status at initiation of treatment increased the risk of LTFU 
from ART. Sex of the patient and other variables were not 
associated with LTFU from ART. 
Moreover, analysis for the event of death showed that 
poor functional status at initiation of treatment, diagnosis of 
tuberculosis at treatment initiation, and being followed up in a 
health center rather than a hospital increased the risk of death 
in the study cohort. Although there is a decrease in the hazard 
of experiencing death as the CD4 increases, the association 
was not statistically significant. The other variables failed to 
reach statistical significance. Table 2 shows the multivariate 
Cox regression analysis results for LTFU and death. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, one quarter of patients were LTFU or had 
died after a median follow-up of 28 months. Another study 
conducted in two hospitals in the Oromia region, Ethiopia, 
documented a 10.3% death rate and an 18.0% LTFU rate 
over 2 years of follow-up. 
16 The higher death rate in the study 
from Oromia might be attributable to the fact that 85% of the 
study participants had a baseline CD4 count ,200 cells/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, 
whereas this figure was 52.6% in our study. Similarly, 70.9% 
of the Oromia study participants were late-stage presenters, 
while in the current study only 44.1% presented late. Another 
study from south Ethiopia, in which the majority (62.5%) 
of patients were late presenters, reported a death rate of 
11.3%. 
9 Such differences could be because of two reasons. 
First, patients may be presenting earlier in the course of the 
disease, and second, the shift in eligibility criteria to higher 
CD4 counts may also be contributing to early initiation of 
ART. This clearly indicates the public return in terms of lives 
saved because of early presentation and/or early treatment 
initiation for HIV. 
Our attrition rate was higher than reports of 18% from 
rural Zimbabwe, 
20 18% after 5 years of follow-up in Thai-
land, 
21 16% after 2 years of follow-up in the People's Republic 
of China, 
22 and 10.7% after 2 years of follow-up in Rwanda. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>However, other studies have reported a comparable attrition 
rate. A study from rural Malawi reported an attrition rate of 
23% 
20 and another study from South Africa also reported an 
attrition rate of 26.4% among health facility based adherence 
support group, which is a similar context with our study. 
24 The 
current attrition rate is also similar to that in the 2003-2007 
cohort in south Ethiopia. 
19 The sensitivity analysis of a sys-
tematic review conducted to estimate patient retention in </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline demographic and clinical characteristics of the 
study cohort, south ethiopia </p>

<p>Variable 
n 
% </p>

<p>Sex 
Male 
524 
44.7 
gap between testing and treatment initiation 
Same month 
1-6 months </p>

<p>468 
39.9 
349 
29.8 
.6 months 
356 
30.3 
Marital status at enrolment (n=1,131) 
not married during enrolment 
Married at enrolment </p>

<p>478 
40.8 
653 
55.7 
Family size (n=1,052) 
living alone 
2-5 members </p>

<p>178 
15.2 
734 
62.6 
.5 members 
140 
11.9 
Body mass index (n=561) 
,18.5 
$18.5 </p>

<p>181 
15.4 
380 
32.4 
Facility type 
Hospital 
Health center </p>

<p>778 
66.3 
395 
33.7 
CD4, cells/mm 
3 (n=1,082) 
#100 
293 
25.0 
.100 
789 
67.3 
Age (years) at month 0 
15-25 
26-39 </p>

<p>228 
19.4 
631 
53.8 
$40 
314 
26.8 
Isoniazid prophylaxis 
Yes 
105 
9.0 
Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis 
Yes 
1,085 
92.5 
Side effects 
Yes 
42 
3.6 
Functional status (n=1,128) 
Working 
846 
72.1 
Ambulatory 
232 
19.8 
Bed ridden 
50 
4.3 
Disclosure (n=806) 
Disclosed 
not disclosed </p>

<p>763 
65.1 
43 
3.7 
educational status (n=1,133) 
no education 
323 
27.5 
Primary education 
493 
42.0 
Secondary or higher 
317 
27.0 
TB treatment, month 0 
Yes 
148 
12.6 
WHO clinical stage (n=1,146) 
early (stage I/II) 
629 
53.6 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: TB, tuberculosis; WHO, World Health Organization. </p>

<p>LTFU was higher in hospitals than in health centers. Figure 2 
shows the cumulative incidences of death and LTFU using 
competing risk analysis and stratified by facility type. </p>

<p>Factors associated with lTFU and death </p>

<p>Multivariate competing-risk regression analysis showed that 
longer time gap between knowing one's HIV infection status 
and treatment initiation, higher body mass index score at </p>

<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care 2015:7 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>0.2 
Hospital </p>

<p>Hospital </p>

<p>Health center </p>

<p>Health center 
0.15 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 
0.0 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 </p>

<p>Follow-up (months) 
Follow-up (months) 
Cumulative incidence 
Cumulative incidence </p>

<p>30 
40 
0 
1 0 
2 0 
30 
40 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Cumulative incidence curves using competing risk analyses for lTFU (A) and death (B) by facility type. 
Abbreviation: lTFU, loss to follow-up. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>171 </p>

<p>lTFU and death rates from ART in ethiopia </p>

<p>sub-Saharan Africa estimated that the retention rate ranged 
from 24% in the worst case to 77% in the best case at the 
end of 2 years of follow-up. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Death rate calculations might be influenced by other 
external conditions. Health facilities may not accurately cap-
ture the death event. This implies that some patients classified 
as "lost" may have actually died if there is no strong tracing 
system to record the final outcome for such patients. In line 
with this, several studies have shown that most individuals 
who are LTFU have in fact died but are not detected by the 
health system. Previous studies conducted in south Ethiopia 
and Malawi have shown that around half of patients who are 
LTFU are found to be dead when traced by health facilities. </p>

<p>9-11 </p>

<p>Also, in the current study, the poor clinical condition, as 
measured in terms of WHO clinical stage, of patients who 
are LTFU suggests that these patients might have died of the 
disease, unbeknownst to the health system. </p>

<p>The overall death or LTFU rate of 12.4 per 100 PYO 
was much lower than that in a study from rural Malawi 
which reported attrition rates of 33 and 36 per 100 PYO 
in hospitals and health centers, respectively. 
25 This Malawi 
study also documented a significant reduction in incidence 
of LTFU and a higher death rate in health centers when 
compared with hospitals, similar to our findings. Higher 
death rates in health centers were also reported from other 
studies conducted in Malawi. 
20,25 In our study, we observed 
that patients who had a short time interval between learn-
ing of their HIV infection status and initiation of treatment 
were more likely to be LTFU when compared with their 
counterparts. This indicates that acceptance of disease 
status and long-term willingness to stay in care depends 
partly on to what level patients are psychologically accept-
ing and managing the early denial stage of their HIV test 
result. Indepth counseling may be needed for patients </p>

<p>TO </p>

<p>Death </p>

<p>LTFU </p>

<p>0.0 
2.0 
4.0 
6.0 </p>

<p>Incidence rate (per 100 PYO) </p>

<p>8.0 
10.0 </p>

<p>9.0 </p>

<p>10.9 </p>

<p>10.3 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 
Overall Hospital Health center </p>

<p>4.7 </p>

<p>5.7 </p>

<p>2.7 </p>

<p>12.0 </p>

<p>Figure 1 Overall incidence rates of LTFU and death stratified by facility type. 
Abbreviations: lTFU, loss to follow-up; PYO, person-years of observation; TO, transfer out. </p>

<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>172 </p>

<p>Teshome et al </p>

<p>who start treatment relatively soon after learning of their 
HIV-positive status. 
Other risk factors for an elevated risk of LTFU were low 
body mass index at treatment initiation, being in a young 
age group (#25 years), not starting isoniazid prophylaxis, 
being cared for in hospital rather than in a health center, not 
attending formal education, and late WHO clinical stage at 
initiation of treatment. Most of these findings are in agree-
ment with those of several previous studies, 
9,10,15,22,23,26-32 Even 
though our point estimate for risk of LTFU or death showed 
males to be at increased risk, the association failed to reach 
statistical significance. However, other studies have found 
this relationship to be significant. </p>

<p>22,26,28,31 </p>

<p>The multivariate analysis showed that risk factors for 
death included being cared for in a health center rather 
than in a hospital, a diagnosis of tuberculosis at initiation 
of treatment, and poor functional status. These findings 
are similar to those of previous studies conducted in 
Ethiopia and elsewhere. 
9,16,27,28,31,33 The mortality excess 
is more than twice in health centers when compared with 
hospitals. This might be because of differences in the 
quality of care in terms of availability of facilities and 
high-level health workers to manage complicated cases. 
This calls for a careful analysis of the referral and link-
age system in place to ensure an equitable distribution of 
health care services. 
Finally, the study has some limitations inherent to the 
study design and the nature of the data collected. The find-
ings are only for patients who were initiated on treatment and 
do not address retention over the continuum of HIV care. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Missing values for some variables like body mass index 
were very large and may have resulted in bias or calculation 
errors. The possible outcomes might not have been accurately 
captured as patients who were classified as LTFU might 
have actually died or been cared for in other facilities. The 
competing-risk regression may partly solve the problem but 
the real final treatment outcome of the clients still remain 
undetermined. </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In this study, we noted that after a median follow-up of 28 
months, one quarter of patients were either LTFU or had 
died. Compared with previous studies in similar settings, 
patients are now started on treatment at a relatively earlier 
stage. The LTFU rate was higher in hospitals than in health 
centers; however, there is an excess death rate among patients 
being followed up in health centers. We recommend further 
studies to explore why this is happening. </p>

<p>Table 2 Adjusted hazard ratios for lTFU and death using the 
competing-risk regression model, south ethiopia </p>

<p>Variable 
LTUF, AHR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Death, AHR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Sex 
Female versus male 
0.91 (0.69-1.20) 
0.65 (0.31-1.36) 
gap between testing and treatment initiation 
Same month 
1-6 months 
.6 months </p>

<p>Reference category 
Reference category 
0.86 (0.63-1.17) 
0.89 (0.41-1.95) 
0.57 (0.40-0.81)* 
1.33 (0.55-3.20) 
Marital status at enrolment 
no during enrolment 
Married at enrolment </p>

<p>Reference category 
Reference category 
0.81 (0.61-1.12) 
0.73 (0.34-1.55) 
nR 
0.65 (0.29-1.44) 
1.91 (0.40-9.09) 
Family size 
living alone 
2-5 </p>

<p>Reference category 
Reference category 
0.80 (0.55-1.17) 
0.70 (0.31-1.59) 
.5 members 
0.67 (0.39-1.15) 
0.87 (0.29-2.63) 
nR 
0.90 (0.53-1.54) 
0.91 (0.29-2.91) 
Body mass index 
,18.5 
$18.5 </p>

<p>Reference category 
Reference category 
0.58 (0.38-0.91)* 
0.71 (0.23-2.17) 
nR 
1.27 (0.86-1.88) 
1.77 (0.67-4.69) 
Facility type 
HC versus hospital 
0.65 (0.47-0.91)* 
2.80 (1.40-5.61)* 
CD4, cells/mm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>#100 
Reference category 
Reference category </p>

<p>.100 
0.92 (0.67-1.26) 
0.55 (0.28-1.08) 
nR 
1.27 (0.73-2.23) 
0.94 (0.30-2.95) 
Age (years), at month 0 
15-25 
26-39 </p>

<p>Reference category 
Reference category 
0.59 (0.42-0.83)* 
1.50 (0.59-3.83) 
$40 
0.73 (0.50-1.07) 
1.57 (0.54-4.53) 
Isoniazid prophylaxis 
no versus yes 
1.90 (1.10-3.23)* 
0.74 (0.22-2.46) 
Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis 
no versus yes 
1.07 (0.64-1.79) 
1.44 (0.36-5.80) 
Side effects 
no versus yes 
0.82 (0.44-1.54) 
0.50 (0.19-1.34) 
Functional status 
Working 
Reference category 
Reference category 
Ambulatory 
1.18 (0.83-1.68) 
2.71 (1.05-6.95)* 
Bed ridden 
1.35 (0.69-2.62) 
5.35 (1.67-17.1)* 
nR 
1.71 (0.77-3.76) 
1.75 (0.33-9.16) 
Disclosure 
Disclosed 
not disclosed </p>

<p>Reference category 
Reference 
1.67 (0.85-3.28) 
0.30 (0.03-3.17) 
not documented 
0.96 (0.70-1.31) 
1.36 (0.65-3.87) 
educational status 
no education 
Reference category 
Reference category 
Primary education 
0.81 (0.59-1.11) 
0.60 (0.28-1.31) 
Secondary or higher 
0.58 (0.39-0.67)* 
0.71 (0.29-1.74) 
nR 
0.55 (0.22-1.36) 
1.06 (0.20-5.65) 
TB at baseline 
no versus yes 
1.22 (0.78-1.91) 
0.38 (0.16-0.88)* 
WHO stage 
late versus early 
1.39 (1.03-1.88)* 
0.85 (0.38-1.88) </p>

<p>Note: *Statistically significant. 
Abbreviations: AHR, adjusted hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; HC, health 
center; lTFU, loss to follow-up; nR, not recorded; TB, tuberculosis; WHO, World 
Health Organization. </p>

<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>173 </p>

<p>lTFU and death rates from ART in ethiopia </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The study was funded by the Federal HIV/AIDS Prevention 
and Control Office. We are grateful to the data collectors who 
extracted data from the registers, the data clerks in all the 
study facilities, and the heads of these health facilities. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/hivaids---research-and-palliative-care-journal </p>

<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care is an international, peer-
reviewed open-access journal focusing on advances in research in HIV, 
its clinical progression and management options including antiviral 
treatment, palliative care and public healthcare policies to control 
viral spread. The journal welcomes original research, basic science, </p>

<p>clinical &amp; epidemiological studies, reviews &amp; evaluations, expert 
opinion &amp; commentary, case reports &amp; extended reports. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>HIV/AIDS -Research and Palliative Care 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>174 </p>

<p>Teshome et al </p>

</text></tei>