<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4898329" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background. The metabolic syndrome is associated with modest but independent and additive 
risk of new onset chronic kidney disease (CKD) in several studies. The purpose of our study was to 
determine whether metabolic syndrome and other cardiovascular risk factors (hyperuricaemia 
and smoking) are associated with the progression of IgA nephropathy (IgAN). 
Methods. Two hundred and twenty three IgAN patients (107 with and 116 without metabolic 
syndrome) were examined. The primary renal end point was doubling of serum creatinine; sec-
ondary end points were reaching eGFR of ≤ 60 ml/min/1,73m 
2 or eGFR of ≤30 ml/min/1.73 m 
2 , 
and end-stage renal disease, ESRD (the composite of serum creatinine ≥500 µmol/l, initiation of 
dialysis treatment or transplantation). The association of metabolic syndrome with renal end 
points was examined using the Kaplan-Meier method and Cox models. 
Results. Metabolic syndrome established at the diagnosis or during follow-up of IgAN patients 
was significantly associated with the primary renal end point (unadjusted hazard ratio of dou-
bling of serum creatinine, 95% confidence interval: 1.96 (1.17-1.33, p = 0.011). The association 
remained significant after adjustment for confounders: 1.70 (1.02-3.83, p = 0.040). Results were 
similar for secondary end points except ESRD which was not associated with the presence of 
metabolic syndrome. Hyperuricaemia and smoking were independent risk factors of progression. 
Survival curves stratified on metabolic syndrome status showed significant differences for the end 
points ( p = 0.017-0.001) except for ESRD. 
Conclusions. Early diagnosis and treatment of metabolic syndrome, hyperuricaemia and smoking 
may be an additional cost-effective strategy for preventing the progression of IgAN. </p>

<p>The term metabolic syndrome is commonly used to de-
scribe the clustering of cardiovascular risk factors, namely 
central obesity, hypertension, impaired glucose metabolism 
and dyslipidaemia. Metabolic syndrome is found in over 
25% of adults in the USA and in several other industrialized 
countries, and there appears to be an increasing preva-
lence in higher age groups [1]. Individuals with metabolic 
syndrome are at increased risk for cardiovascular diseases 
as well as cardiovascular and all-cause mortality [2]. 
The recent interest of nephrologists in metabolic syn-
drome increased after the publication of Chen et al. [3], 
demonstrating in a cross-sectional study that metabolic 
syndrome was associated with a 2.26-fold higher risk 
(1.68-4.03) of chronic kidney disease (CKD) in a sample 
representative of the US population. Other cross-sectional 
studies have also demonstrated a link between metabolic </p>

<p>syndrome and CKD (see later). In the only longitudinal 
study, Kurella et al. [4] demonstrated a significantly in-
creased risk of incident CKD in non-diabetic adults with 
metabolic syndrome. However, the effects of metabolic 
syndrome on the progression of CKD beyond the contri-
bution of impaired glucose metabolism and hypertension 
are far from being established with certainty. 
IgA nephropathy (IgAN) is the most common primary 
glomerulonephritis and is an important cause of end-
stage renal disease (ESRD) worldwide [5]. Long-term 
observation in many countries has shown that IgAN 
causes ESRD in as many as 40% of patients within 
20 years after diagnosis [6, 7]. Clinical presentation is 
usually with haematuria and with variable degrees of 
proteinuria. Pathologically, IgAN is characterized by the 
glomerular deposition of polymeric IgA1 mainly in the 
mesangium accompanied by mesangial hypercellularity, 
mesangial matrix expansion, and varying degrees of </p>

<p>© The Author 2012. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of ERA-EDTA. All rights reserved. 
For permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com. </p>

<p>Clin Kidney J (2013) 6: 395-401 
doi: 10.1093/ckj/sfs131 
Advance Access publication 2 November 2012 </p>

<p>glomerulosclerosis and interstitial fibrosis. Adverse prog-
nostic indicators include the presence of heavy proteinur-
ia and hypertension, a significant reduction in glomerular 
filtration rate (GFR) at the time of renal biopsy and 
the extent of glomerulosclerosis and tubulointerstitial 
fibrosis on renal pathology [7, 8]. In addition to these 
known risk factors, other cardiovascular risk factors, such 
as hypertriglyceridaemia, hyperuricaemia, excessive body 
weight or cigarette smoking have also been associated 
with the progression of IgAN in recent studies [9-11]. 
However, there are no data about the prevalence of 
metabolic syndrome in IgAN patients, and there have not 
been any reports of an association between metabolic 
syndrome and the progression of IgAN. 
The purpose of the present study was to determine 
whether there are differences in the progression of IgAN 
according to the presence of metabolic syndrome and 
other cardiovascular risk factors at the time of diagnosis 
and during the course of IgAN. We emphasized that the 
clustering of cardiovascular risk factors is associated with 
a more severe progression of IgAN. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>We examined 240 biopsy-proven IgAN patients with 
normal or mild to moderately decreased renal function 
(CKD Stage 1-3) at the time of the diagnosis of IgAN. All 
of the patients were diagnosed in the Nephrology Center, 
Medical Faculty, University of Pécs, Hungary and fol-
lowed-up in 3-to 6-month intervals by the same two ne-
phrologists, TK and JN. Seventeen patients were not 
included in the statistical analyses of this study because 
of insufficient clinical data at the time of the diagnosis of 
IgAN. Further exclusion criteria were: secondary IgAN 
cases, rapidly progressive crescentic patients, patients 
with nephrotic syndrome and immunosuppressive treat-
ment. The analysed cohort included 223 patients. </p>

<p>Definition of metabolic syndrome </p>

<p>All IgAN patients were analysed to determine whether 
criteria for metabolic syndrome were met by using a 
modified NCEP ATP III (National Cholesterol Education 
Programme-Adult Treatment Panel III) definition of 
metabolic syndrome [12]. Metabolic syndrome was 
defined as any three or more of the following criteria: (i) 
fasting plasma glucose level of 5.6 mmol/L or higher or 
impaired glucose tolerance; (ii) triglyceride level of 1.7 
mmol/L or higher or lipid-lowering drug treatment; (iii) 
high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol level &lt;1.0 
mmol/L for men and &lt;1.3 mmol/L for women or drug 
treatment; (iv) body mass index (BMI) ≥30 kg/m 
2 ; (v) hy-
pertension with blood pressure ≥130/85 mmHg or antihy-
pertensive treatment. </p>

<p>Study measurements </p>

<p>Demographic, anthropometric and laboratory data as 
well as information about lifestyle habits were collected 
on all participants at the time of diagnosis and at each 
follow-up visit. Blood was collected by venepuncture after 
an overnight fast of at least 10 h at all follow-up examin-
ations. The Central Laboratory of Medical Faculty, Univer-
sity of Pécs measured all serum chemistry levels in fresh </p>

<p>samples with commercially available reagents. The glo-
merular filtration rate (eGFR; mL/min/1.73 m 
2 ) was esti-
mated with the Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology 
Collaboration equation [13]. BMI was calculated as 
weight in kilograms divided by the square of the height in 
metres. </p>

<p>Definition of progression of IgAN </p>

<p>The primary renal outcome was the doubling of serum 
creatinine, secondary renal outcomes were the decrease 
of eGFR to ≤60 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 , or to ≤30 mL/min/1.73 
m 
2 or reaching ESRD (defined as the composite of a 
serum creatinine ≥500 µmol/L or the initiation of dialysis 
treatment or transplantation). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data analysis was performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> software 
program version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Con-
tinuous variables with normal distribution were expressed 
as mean ± standard deviation and were compared by 
using Student's t-tests. Variables with non-normal distri-
bution were compared by the Mann-Whitney U-test, and 
categorical variables were expressed as percentage and 
compared by the χ 
2 test. The mean renal survival time 
until the selected end points was calculated using the 
Kaplan-Meier method. Differences between the calcu-
lated mean renal survival times were compared using the 
log-rank test. The effect of confounders was assessed by 
Cox regression analysis. 
Confounders were determined a priori based on theor-
etical considerations and by examining baseline covariate 
associations with metabolic syndrome and with the renal 
end points [14]. Multivariate models were constructed 
with sequential adjustments for age and gender as well 
as for age, gender, uric acid, eGFR, smoking and angioten-
sin-converting enzyme inhibitors/angiotensin II receptor 
blocker (ACEis/ARB). A value of P &lt; 0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Baseline clinical data </p>

<p>The mean age of the 223 participants included in the 
analytic cohort was 36.4 ± 13.0 years, 72% were male 
and 28% were female. Metabolic syndrome was already 
present in 17% of participants (38 patients) at the diag-
nosis of IgAN and was diagnosed de novo in a further 
31% of participants (69 patients) during the follow-up 
period. Analysing all (n = 223) IgAN patients together at 
the end of the follow-up period, the prevalence of zero, 
one, two, three and four parameters of the metabolic 
syndrome was 15 (7%), 48 (22%), 53 (24%), 91 (41%) 
and 16 (7%), respectively (Figure 2). Sixty-eight (31%) 
patients were obese and impaired carbohydrate metab-
olism [impaired glucose tolerance (IGT), impaired fasting 
glucose (IFG) or diabetes mellitus] was present in 77 
(35%) patients, HDL cholesterol was low in 108 (48%) 
patients, hypertriglyceridaemia was present in 133 (60%) 
patients and elevated blood pressure or antihypertensive 
treatment was present in 195 (87%) patients at the end 
of the follow-up period. Analysing together hypertrigly-
ceridaemia, lower HDL cholesterol and statin treatment, 
151 (68%) patients were dyslipidaemic. </p>

<p>396  T. Kovács et al. </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics of IgAN patients with and 
without metabolic syndrome are summarized in Table 1. 
There were no significant differences in the age, sex, 
follow-up time or number of smokers between the two 
groups. Patients with metabolic syndrome had higher uric 
acid levels in addition to the expected higher values for 
BMI, triglyceride, glucose and lower HDL cholesterol level 
that define metabolic syndrome. At the time of the diagno-
sis of IgAN, the eGFR of patients with metabolic syndrome 
was lower (73.6 ± 31.8 versus 82.2 ± 27.7 mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>in patients without metabolic syndrome, P &lt; 0.05). 
However, at the end of the follow-up period, the difference 
between the eGFR of the two groups was more substantial 
(46.8 ± 31.6 versus 67.4 ± 35.3 mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, P &lt; 0.001). 
The systolic and diastolic blood pressures of patients with 
metabolic syndrome were significantly higher (Table 1), 
and significantly more patients were treated with ACEi/ARB 
in the metabolic syndrome group (P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Association of metabolic syndrome with progression 
of IgAN </p>

<p>Survival curves stratified on metabolic syndrome status 
showed statistically significant differences in the time to 
reach three different end points for the renal outcome: 
the doubling of serum creatinine (P = 0.009, Figure 1A), 
eGFR ≤60 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 (P = 0.001, Figure 1B) and 
eGFR ≤30 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 (P = 0.017, Figure 1C). The </p>

<p>difference in time to reach the composite end point of 
ESRD (defined as the composite of a serum creatinine 
≥500 µmol/L or the initiation of dialysis treatment or 
transplantation) was not significant (P = 0.2). 
Metabolic syndrome was significantly associated with 
the progression of IgAN in unadjusted Cox models for 
three different renal end points eGFR ≤60 mL/min/1.73 
m 
2 , eGFR ≤30/mL/min/1.73 m 
2 and the doubling of 
serum creatinine (Table 2). The association remained sig-
nificant after adjustment for confounders (Table 2). The 
association, however, was not significant for the end 
points of ESRD in neither unadjusted nor adjusted Cox 
models (Table 2). At the analysis of the effect of single 
traits of metabolic syndrome: obesity (yes/no, Y/N), hy-
pertension (Y/N), dyslipidaemia (Y/N), dysglycaemia (Y/N) 
and complete metabolic syndrome on the prognosis of 
IgAN hypertension and complete metabolic syndrome 
were the two strongest influencing parameters (Table 3). 
In Cox regression analysis, higher uric acid level was 
also an independent risk factor for three different renal 
end points: </p>

<p>(i) eGFR ≤60 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 [hazard ratio (HR) associ-
ated with a 1 mmol/L higher serum uric acid level: 
1.003; 95% confidence interval (95% CI) 1.001-
1.005]. 
(ii) eGFR ≤30 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 (HR 1.002; 95% CI 1.001-
1.005) and 
(iii) ESRD (HR 1.004; 95% CI 1.001-1.006). </p>

<p>Smoking was significantly associated with ESRD (HR 
2.024; 95% CI 1.046-3.920). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our study showed that metabolic syndrome established 
at the time of diagnosis or during the follow-up of IgAN 
was significantly associated with the primary renal end 
point and remained significant after adjustment for con-
founders. Results were similar for the secondary end 
points except for ESRD. Hyperuricaemia was also an inde-
pendent risk factor for all secondary end points, 
and smoking was an independent risk factor for ESRD. 
Survival curves stratified on metabolic syndrome status 
showed significant differences for the association with 
the various end points except for ESRD. 
The criteria for metabolic syndrome diagnosis were 
set-up originally to identify those individuals most likely 
to develop cardiovascular diseases [15]. There is no 
doubt nowadays that the patients with metabolic syn-
drome are at significantly higher risk for CKD too, as sum-
marized by a number of review articles and by the recent 
meta-analysis of Thomas et al. [16-22]. Most of the 
observational studies discussed in these papers found a 
significant association between metabolic syndrome and 
CKD. The odds ratios for CKD in the different studies were: 
2.60 in the National Health And Nutrition Examination 
Survey III (NHANES III) database [3], 1.43 in the Athero-
sclerosis Risk in Communities study [4], 1.3 in American 
Indians [23], 1.54 in Japanese adults [24], 1.88 in the 
Tehran Lipid and Glucose Study [25], 1.64 in the Inter-
Asia study [26], 1.31 in hypertensive African Americans 
[27], 1.31 in the Hong-Kong Diabetes Registry [28], 1.77 
in Korean adults [29], 1.74 [30] and 1.42 [31] in Chinese 
adults as well as 1.30 in non-diabetic Taiwanese adults 
[32]. However, the majority of the studies were cross-sec-
tional and, as such, unable to establish a cause-effect </p>

<p>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of patients with and without metabolic 
syndrome </p>

<p>Metabolic 
syndrome 
(n = 107) </p>

<p>No metabolic 
syndrome 
(n = 116) 
P-value </p>

<p>Age 
37.9 ± 13.8 
34.9 ± 12.2 
0.089 
Follow-up (months) 
146.6 ± 112.5 
146.1 ± 99.4 
0.589 
Sex (M/F) 
81 (76%)/26 
(24%) </p>

<p>80 (69%)/36 
(31%) </p>

<p>0.296 </p>

<p>Parameters of metabolic syndrome 
BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
30.8 ± 4.8 
24.9 ± 3.4 
&lt;0.001 
Systolic BP (Hgmm) 
143 ± 20 
136 ± 19 
0.005 
Diastolic BP (Hgmm) 89 ± 12 
85 ± 12 
0.014 
Hypertension (Y/N) 
105 (98%)/2 
(2%) </p>

<p>90 (78%)/26 
(22%) </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Triglyceride 
(mmol/L) </p>

<p>2.18 ± 1.21 
1.59 ± 1.55 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>HDL (mmol/L) 
1.21 ± 0.48 
1.39 ± 0.39 
&lt;0.001 
Blood sugar 
(mmol/L) </p>

<p>6.32 ± 1.44 
5.10 ± 0.81 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Uric acid (mmol/L) 
390 ± 124 
351 ± 118 
0.006 
Smoking (Y/N) 
27 (25%)/79 
(75%) </p>

<p>30 (26%)/83 
(74%) </p>

<p>0.879 </p>

<p>Renal function 
eGFR at the 
diagnosis 
(mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>73.6 ± 31.8 
82.2 ± 27.7 
&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>eGFR at the end of 
follow-up (mL/min/ 
1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>46.8 ± 31.6 
67.4 ± 35.3 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Drugs 
ACEi/ARB (Y/N) 
92 (86%)/15 
(14%) </p>

<p>73 (63%)/43 
(37%) </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Statins (Y/N) 
48 (45%)/59 
(55%) </p>

<p>19 (16%)/97 
(84%) </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Data expressed as mean ± standard deviations and number of participants 
(for categorical variables). 
BMI, body mass index; BP, blood pressure; HDL, high-density lipoprotein; 
eGFR, estimated glomerular filtration rate; ACEi, angiotensin-converting 
enzyme inhibitor; ARB, angiotensin II receptor blocker. Comparisons were 
made by t-tests or χ 
2 tests. </p>

<p>Metabolic syndrome and progression of IgA nephropathy </p>

<p>
relationship between metabolic syndrome and the 
reduction in kidney function, and also unable to deter-
mine if metabolic syndrome is associated with longitudi-
nal changes in kidney function. In this study, we 
detected a significant association between metabolic 
syndrome and the progressive loss of kidney function 
except in ESRD, suggesting a potential effect of metabolic 
syndrome on the early progression of IgAN. The lower 
eGFR level of patients with metabolic syndrome seen at 
the time of diagnosis of IgAN suggests a potential effect 
of metabolic syndrome on the incidence of the renal 
disease too. Our observation that metabolic syndrome 
did not associate with the progression of IgAN in the 
end-stage of IgAN is in agreement with the results of the 
study of Lee et al. [33] on CKD patients participating in 
the CKD prevention programme regulated by the Public 
Health Bureau of Taiwan. 
Among the components of metabolic syndrome, dia-
betic and hypertensive injuries, the two major aetiologies 
of CKD worldwide, have been well studied and described. 
Concerning the association between IgAN and diabetes, 
Fliser et al. [34] published that insulin resistance and hy-
perinsulinaemia are already present in patients with inci-
pient renal disease, among others in IgAN patients. In our 
present study, we found impaired glucose regulation (IGT, 
IFG or diabetes mellitus) in 77 (35%) patients. It is known 
that IgAN can also be superimposed on diabetic nephro-
pathy or can be the only renal abnormality of diabetic 
patients. The association between IgAN and diabetes 
may not be coincidental, because the intraglomerular hy-
pertension and hyperfiltration as well as biochemical </p>

<p>alterations in the glomeruli of diabetic patients may facili-
tate the deposition of IgA1 immune complexes or aggre-
gates. Furthermore, the abnormalities of the IgA immune 
system are common in Type 2 diabetes [35]. 
Hypertension is common in CKD patients and, similar to 
the general population, it predicts cardiovascular morbidity 
and mortality. Hypertensive CKD patients with metabolic 
syndrome have an excess cardiovascular risk. The relation-
ship between blood pressure and mortality is U-shaped; 
low mean and diastolic blood pressure predicts early mor-
tality [36]. As we already mentioned in the introduction, 
the progression in IgAN is more severe in the presence of 
hypertension and strict blood-pressure control portents 
renal protection in IgAN [37]. In our study, among the par-
ameters of metabolic syndrome, hypertension had the 
greatest influence on the prognosis of IgAN. 
Obesity has been associated with an increased risk for 
the incidence of CKD and for ESRD in several epidemiologi-
cal studies [38-41]. In the examined populations, obesity 
as indicated by the elevated BMI was associated with de-
creased renal function and ESRD independent of the pres-
ence of hypertension and diabetes. Weight loss has a 
protective effect against the progression of CKD [40]. Higher 
BMI shows a seemingly paradoxical association with better 
survival in advanced CKD and in ESRD, which could be 
related to a better nutritional status in patients with elev-
ated BMI [42].Concerning IgAN patients, obesity was a pre-
dictive factor not only for the development of hypertension, 
but also for chronic renal failure and obese patients have 
glomerular enlargement and ultrastructural modification of 
the glomerular basement membrane [9, 43]. 
Dyslipidaemia, in particular atherogenic dyslipidaemia 
(high triglyceride and low HDL cholesterol), has been 
recognized as an independent risk factor for the develop-
ment and progression of CKD in observational studies 
and in meta-analyses [44, 45]. Furthermore, the progress-
ive decline in renal function may engender inflammation 
and oxidative stress, which could in turn induce various 
metabolic alterations, such as insulin resistance and dia-
betes, elevation of arterial blood pressure and hypertri-
glyceridaemia, leading to potential vicious cycles. In the 
study of Syrjänen et al. [10], elevated triglyceride levels 
were associated with progressive IgAN. 
Recent epidemiologic and experimental evidence 
suggests a role for hyperuricaemia not only as a marker 
of reduced kidney function but also as a causal risk factor 
for the development and progression of renal disease 
[46, 47]. Serum uric acid was a GFR-independent long-
term predictor of acute and chronic renal insufficiency in 
the Jerusalem Lipid Research Clinic cohort study [48]. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Time to reach the different end points (Kaplan-Meier analysis). (A) Time to doubling of serum creatinine (months). (B) Time to reach eGFR ≤60 
mL/min/1.73 m 
2 (months). (C) Time to reach eGFR ≤30 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 (months). </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Frequency of metabolic syndrome components at the end of follow-up. </p>

<p>398 
T. Kovács et al. </p>

<p>There is a close connection between hypertension and 
hyperuricaemia and at the re-evaluation of metabolic 
syndrome; Reaven [15] suggested to include hyperuricae-
mia among the criteria of metabolic syndrome. In the 
only previous study on IgAN patients, hyperuricaemia 
was found to be a predictor of poor prognosis similarly to 
our investigation [10]. 
An association between smoking and CKD has been 
found in various studies, including in lupus patients, poly-
cystic kidney disease, primary glomerular diseases and 
diabetic nephropathy [49-52]. In the present study, 
smoking was significantly associated with the progression 
to ESRD, similar to the study by Yamamoto et al. [11] who, 
however, examined the smoking status only at time of di-
agnosis of IgAN. 
Our study is notable for the well-characterized nature 
of the study population and the long follow-up of the 
patients by the same two nephrologists. Our study also 
has a number of limitations that have to be considered 
when interpreting the findings. This was a single-centre 
study hence the external validity of our findings may be 
limited. We lacked measurements of waist circumference 
as a better measure of abdominal obesity. Instead, we 
used BMI which is an acceptable alternative used in the 
World Health Organization classification of metabolic 
syndrome. This modification of the NCEP ATP III classifi-
cation of metabolic syndrome we used was also used by 
Lea et al. examining the metabolic syndrome and the risk 
of progressive CKD in hypertensive African Americans 
[27]. Our study did not involve and discuss proteinuria as 
a predictor of the progression of CKD, because proteinuria 
could be a clinical characteristic of IgAN and also a 
consequence of metabolic syndrome. 
This is the first study describing the frequent preva-
lence of metabolic syndrome at the time of diagnosis </p>

<p>and during the follow-up of IgAN patients, and support-
ing the role of metabolic syndrome in the progression of 
IgAN. Hyperuricaemia and smoking seem to also be 
important risk factors of progression in IgAN. In con-
clusion, the early diagnosis and treatment of metabolic 
syndrome and hyperuricaemia, and cessation of smoking 
could be an added beneficial cost-effective strategy in 
the prevention of the progression of IgAN and in the 
prevention of the development of cardiovascular dis-
eases, on the basis of the close connection between the 
progression of CKD and cardiovascular diseases. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements. Part of this material was presented at the 
American Society of Nephrology Kidney Week 2011 November 
10-13, Philadelphia, PA, USA. Dr Kovesdy is an employee of the 
US Department of Veterans Affairs. The opinions expressed in 
this paper are those of the authors' and they do not necessarily 
reflect the opinions of the US Department of Veterans Affairs. 
Funding. This study was supported by SROP-4.2.2/B-10/1/2010-
0029 Supporting Scientific Training of Talented Youth at the Uni-
versity of Pécs. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Table 3. Crude hazard ratios (95% CI) of various end points associated with the presence of single metabolic syndrome components and metabolic 
syndrome itself </p>

<p>Doubling of serum creatinine </p>

<p>GFR </p>

<p>Composite of ESRD 
≤60 mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>≤30 mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Obesity (Y/N) 
0.95 (0.54-1.66) 
1.52 (1.05-2.20) 
1.29 (0.77-2.15) 
1.25 (0.67-2.32) 
P = 0.852 
P = 0.026 
P = 0.334 
P = 0.484 
Hypertension (Y/N) 
5.73 (1.40-23.46) 
4.50 (1.83-11.02) 
5.93 (1.45-24,24) 
3.89 (0.94-16.07) 
P = 0.015 
P = 0.001 
P = 0.013 
P = 0.061 
Dyslipidaemia (Y/N) 
1.65 (0.94-2.92) 
1.44 (0.97-2.14) 
1.64 (0.95-2.85) 
1.32 (0.69-2.53) 
P = 0.082 
P = 0.073 
P = 0.077 
P = 0.395 
Dysglicaemia (Y/N) 
0.67 (0.41-1.10) 
0.60 (0.42-0.86) 
0.67 (0.42-1.09) 
0.88 (0.49-1.60) 
P = 0.116 
P = 0.005 
P = 0.110 
P = 0.680 
Metabolic syndrome (Y/N) 
1.87 (1.12-3.12) 
2.04 (1.42-2.93) 
1.98 (1.20-3.25) 
1.470 (0.81-2.66) 
P = 0.016 
P &lt; 0.001 
P = 0.007 
P = 0.207 </p>

<p>Table 2. Crude and adjusted hazard ratios (95% CIs) of various renal end points associated with the presence of metabolic syndrome </p>

<p>Doubling of serum 
creatinine </p>

<p>GFR </p>

<p>Composite of ESRD 
≤60 mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>≤30 mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Unadjusted 
1.95 (1.16-3.28) 
2.04 (1.30-3.10) 
1.90 (1.11-3.24) 
1.46 (0.80-2.66) 
P = 0.011 
P = 0.002 
P = 0.019 
P = 0.207 
Adjusted for age, gender 
1.85 (1.10-3.11) 
2.15 (1.37-3.37) 
1.84 (1.07-3.14) 
1.41 (0.78-2.57) 
P = 0.019 
P = 0.001 
P = 0.025 
P = 0.251 
Adjusted for age, gender, uric acid, eGFR, smoking 
1.81 (1.07-3.08) 
2.04 (1.28-3.26) 
1.81 (1.05-3.13) 
1.36 (0.74-2.50) 
P = 0.027 
P = 0.003 
P = 0.033 
P = 0.320 
Adjusted for age, gender, uric acid, eGFR, smoking, ACEi/ARB 1.70 (1.02-2.83) 
2.11 (1.31-3.40) 
1.64 (0.94-2.87) 
1.29 (0.69-2.41) 
P = 0.040 
P = 0.002 
P = 0.081 
P = 0.419 </p>

<p>Metabolic syndrome and progression of IgA nephropathy </p>



<p>
 
T. Kovács et al. </p>



<p>Metabolic syndrome and progression of IgA nephropathy </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>