<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4012704" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Context: Junior doctors are reported to make most of the prescribing errors in the hospital setting. 
Aims: The aim of the following study is to determine the knowledge intern doctors have about prescribing errors 
and circumstances contributing to making them. 
Settings and Design: A structured questionnaire was distributed to intern doctors in National Hospital Abuja 
Nigeria. 
Subjects and Methods: Respondents gave information about their experience with prescribing medicines, 
the extent to which they agreed with the definition of a clinically meaningful prescribing error and events that 
constituted such. Their experience with prescribing certain categories of medicines was also sought. 
Statistical Analysis Used: Data was analyzed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS</rs>) software 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 17</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc Chicago</rs>, Ill, USA). Chi-squared analysis contrasted differences in proportions; P &lt; 0.05 was 
considered to be statistically significant. 
Results: The response rate was 90.9% and 27 (90%) had &lt;1 year of prescribing experience. 17 (56.7%) 
respondents totally agreed with the definition of a clinically meaningful prescribing error. Most common reasons 
for prescribing mistakes were a failure to check prescriptions with a reference source (14, 25.5%) and failure 
to check for adverse drug interactions (14, 25.5%). Omitting some essential information such as duration of 
therapy (13, 20%), patient age (14, 21.5%) and dosage errors (14, 21.5%) were the most common types of 
prescribing errors made. Respondents considered workload (23, 76.7%), multitasking (19, 63.3%), rushing 
(18, 60.0%) and tiredness/stress (16, 53.3%) as important factors contributing to prescribing errors. Interns 
were least confident prescribing antibiotics (12, 25.5%), opioid analgesics (12, 25.5%) cytotoxics (10, 21.3%) 
and antipsychotics (9, 19.1%) unsupervised. 
Conclusions: Respondents seemed to have a low awareness of making prescribing errors. Principles of rational 
prescribing and events that constitute prescribing errors should be taught in the practice setting. </p>

<p>The essence of good prescription writing is to ensure that 
the pharmacist knows exactly, which drug formulation 
and dosage to dispense and the patient has clear written 
instruction for self-administration of the prescribed drug. </p>

<p>[1] </p>

<p>A prescription is a legal document that carries regulations </p>

<p>to ensure safe use and to comply with governmental 
regulations. </p>

<p>Aronson 
[2] has noted that the writing of a prescription is 
preceded by four steps in the prescribing process viz. making </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Website: </p>

<p>www.jbclinpharm.org </p>

<p>Quick Response Code </p>

<p>DOI: </p>

<p>10.4103/0976-0105.128244 </p>

<p>Ajemigbitse, et al.: Intern doctors' knowledge of prescribing errors </p>

<p>Journal of Basic and Clinical Pharmacy 
Vol. 5 | Issue 1 | December-February 2014 
 8  </p>

<p>an accurate diagnosis; assessing the balance of benefit to 
harm; selecting the right drug among a range of alternatives 
and the right dosing regimen and discussion with the patient 
about the proposed treatment, potential beneficial and 
adverse effects. World-wide, prescribing errors in clinical 
practice are common. 
[3-6] These errors can affect the safety 
of patients either hospitalized or ambulatory. Studies have 
shown that in about half of hospital admissions, physicians 
may make one prescribing error or the other. 
[7] Errors are more 
likely to occur with junior doctors 
[7-9] but are still prevalent in 
other senior categories of doctors. 
[7,10] Errors in prescribing 
can be attributed to a variety of factors including individual, 
environmental and organizational such as lack of knowledge, 
insufficient training, workload and communication. </p>

<p>[7,9,11,12] </p>

<p>They are difficult to quantify due to problems with available 
data, error definition and study design. 
[13] Using the Delphi 
technique, Dean et al. 
[14] developed a general definition of 
a clinically meaningful prescribing error which has been 
widely adopted in literature to measure baseline incidence of 
prescribing errors in the UK and elsewhere. </p>

<p>Some researchers 
[15] have reported that foundation (intern) 
year doctors lack confidence in prescribing several groups of 
medicines with the majority of them feeling that undergraduate 
education in clinical pharmacology and therapeutics had not 
prepared them adequately for prescribing duties. </p>

<p>The broad aims of medical school training are to lay the 
foundation for a medical career and to provide junior doctors 
with appropriate knowledge and skills for the first stage 
of their post-qualification career. 
[16] Although diversity of 
curriculum approaches in medical schools is encouraged, the 
Medical and Dental Council of Nigeria is responsible for the 
design and regulation of undergraduate medical education in 
Nigeria. 
[17] Medical training in Nigeria spans a minimum of 
6 years but it is in the 4 
th year onward that clinical training 
begins. This is the period where undergraduate pharmacology 
courses including topics in basic and clinical pharmacology as 
well as therapeutics are taught. </p>

<p>Conventionally, all newly graduated doctors are required to 
undergo internship in accredited hospitals for a year before 
full registration to practice. Internship is a period of medical 
apprenticeship under the supervision of a consultant. The 
intern is expected to learn clinical skills, perform some clinical 
procedures and demonstrate good clinical judgment to arrive 
at patient management decisions. Interns are consequently the 
most junior doctors in a tertiary hospital. The first experience 
of unsupervised prescribing begins during the internship year. 
Junior doctors are the most frequent prescribers in the hospital 
setting and are reported to make most of the prescribing errors. 
[7,8,18] Knowing what drug to prescribe to which patient does 
not necessarily translate to a good prescription. Considering 
the fact that the majority of prescription-related errors in 
the hospital environment are made by junior doctors, it is 
necessary to educate the interns and develop interventions 
that will improve the prescribing qualities. </p>

<p>Previous studies carried out in the Nigeria hospital setting 
reported that prescribing errors were common though may 
not always result in actual adverse outcomes for patients. </p>

<p>[19,20] </p>

<p>In the few studies examining the quality of prescribing by 
Nigerian medical practitioners, there appears to be a need to 
improve prescribing quality. However, it is not easy to change 
the prescribing habits of experienced doctors, thus there is 
the hope that educating junior doctors to prescribe according 
to a standard guideline may be a more effective intervention. 
This study was therefore aimed to determine the knowledge 
junior doctors have about prescribing errors, their perception 
of events that constitute a prescribing error, factors that 
contribute to prescribing errors, medicines less confidently 
prescribed and circumstances in which they were prone to 
making prescribing errors. </p>

<p>Subjects and Methods </p>

<p>This study was carried out in National Hospital Abuja (NHA) 
located in the Federal Capital Territory (FCT) of Nigeria. 
Nigeria is made up of 36 states and the FCT, an area 
situated in the geographic center of Nigeria. Being a Federal 
Government-Funded Hospital, NHA is accredited for medical 
internship training. Accredited hospitals for an internship in 
Nigeria include all the teaching hospitals affiliated to medical 
schools, military hospitals, some general (secondary care) 
hospitals and a few private hospitals. NHA along with the 
University of Abuja Teaching Hospital (UATH) are the only 
two tertiary hospitals situated in the FCT. Tertiary hospitals, 
apart from providing referral services to the numerous primary 
and secondary health care facilities within their territories 
and beyond, also serve as institutions for training of health 
personnel offering undergraduate, graduate, post-graduate 
and residency programs. Currently, a 200-bed tertiary 
hospital, NHA plays a key role in the provision of health 
services to the residents of Abuja, a cosmopolitan multi-ethnic, 
multi-cultural urban city with high socio-economic disparity. </p>

<p>A structured questionnaire modified from the work of Dean 
et al. 
[14] was the instrument of study. It was constructed based 
on the definition of and events that represented prescribing 
errors obtained from a consensus agreement of a wide range 
of health care professionals [Appendix]. The questionnaire 
sought information from the junior doctors about their 
demographics, undergraduate training, qualification, 
present posting, whether they agreed with the definition of 
prescribing error and the events that represented such, their 
experience and confidence with prescribing certain drug 
categories and circumstances under which they were likely 
to make a prescribing error. Prescribing errors are common 
among prescribers in Nigeria. 
[18-20] This problem coupled with 
a low self-awareness of making prescribing errors, prompted 
our inclusion of interns perception of prescribing errors in the 
parameters assessed. The questionnaire included a 5-point 
Likert scale ranging from totally agree to totally disagree 
to determine respondents' level of agreement with events 
that constitute a prescribing error [Appendix]. Most of the 
questions required selecting from a multiple of suggested 
options. The questionnaire was initially piloted at the UATH, 
FCT and was excluded from the study. </p>

<p>A total of 33 copies of the questionnaire were randomly 
distributed to house officers (HO) who were undergoing </p>

<p>Ajemigbitse, et al.: Intern doctors' knowledge of prescribing errors </p>

<p>Vol. 5 | Issue 1 | December-February 2014 
Journal of Basic and Clinical Pharmacy 
 9  </p>

<p>internship at the hospital during November 2011 and January 
2012. These junior doctors are admitted in two batches of 
6 months spread and undergo 3 months clerkship/rotation 
in the four major clinical specialties: Medicine, Surgery, 
Pediatrics and Obstetrics and Gynecology Departments. HO 
who were willing to voluntarily participate in the study were 
given the questionnaires to fill individually. Confidentiality 
of information tendered was assured to the participants. The 
ethics committee of the hospital approved the study. </p>

<p>Each questionnaire used in this study was coded for 
easy reference. The data obtained was analyzed with 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 17</rs> in terms of demographic characteristics, 
qualification, current and previous posting and prescribing 
experience using frequencies and percentages as appropriate. 
Chi-square test was adopted in estimating possible differences 
in proportions. At a confidence interval of 95%, a 2-tailed 
P &lt; 0.05 was considered to be significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Demographics 
Of the 33 questionnaires distributed to the junior doctors, 30 
were duly filled and returned giving a response rate of 90.9%. 
The respondents were predominantly males (19, 63.3%) 
thus a statistical gender balance was not achieved ( 
2 = 0.54, 
P = 0.524). A majority of the respondents (23, 76.7%) 
were between 25 and 35 years. Only 7 (13.3%) were below 
25 years. All but one graduated from a Nigeria medical 
school and all respondents had the bachelor of medicine 
and bachelor of Surgery degree only. 18 (60%) respondents 
had rotated through two major clinical postings (medicine, 
pediatrics), 4 (13.3%) through surgery, medicine. obstetrics 
and gynecology and 3 (10%) through the four major postings. 
5 (16.7%) respondents were presently in their first posting in 
the medicine department. </p>

<p>Prescribing experience 
Twenty seven (90%) of the respondents had &lt;1 year of 
prescribing experience. When asked of the frequency at which 
they prescribed medicines at the hospital, 22 (73%) claimed 
to prescribe medicines "every day or more," another 7 (23.3%) 
prescribed medicines 2-6 times a week while only 1 (3.3%) 
admitted to prescribing once a week. </p>

<p>Knowledge and self-awareness of prescribing errors 
Eleven (36.7%) respondents each admitted to "rarely" (&lt;5% of 
time) and "seldom" (5-10% of time) made prescription errors 
respectively. Six (20%) agreed to making prescribing errors 
sometimes (10-20% of time) while two (6.7%) denied ever 
making a prescribing error (0%). When asked the frequency 
at which a fellow clinician (doctor, pharmacist or nurse) 
had called the attention of the respondent to a prescription 
written by the respondent and that resulted to an alteration of 
such, 13 (43.3%) respondent claimed they had "rarely" (&lt;5% 
of time) been called to such while 9 (30%) assented to have 
"seldom" (5-10% of time) been alerted this way, 3 (10%) 
asserted to "sometimes" (10-20% of time) and 5 (16.7%) 
respondents declared to have "never" (0%) been alerted on 
account of a written prescription necessitating an alteration. </p>

<p>Assessment of the definition of a prescribing error 
and types of events 
Seventeen (56.7%) respondents totally agreed with the Dean 
et al. definition of a clinically meaningful prescribing error. 
Eight (26.7%) partially agreed with the definition while 
1 (3.3%) respondent each neither agreed nor disagreed, 
partially disagreed and totally disagreed respectively. 
2 (6.6%) respondents gave no response. Furthermore, the 
study solicited that respondents indicate the extent to which 
they agreed that a prescribing error had occurred in the 20 
scenarios described. The responses are presented in Table 1 
below. Overall, of the events described, there was a 53% 
total agreement by respondents that a prescribing error 
had occurred, 18.3% partially agreement and a 10% totally 
disagreement that a prescribing error had occurred. </p>

<p>Reasons for prescribing lapses 
It is expected that rules for correct prescribing be followed 
at all times. The responses on reasons for prescribing errors 
commonly made and types encountered in practice by 
respondents are given in Tables 2 and 3. </p>

<p>Factors contributing to prescribing errors 
Factors that could contribute to the possibility of prescribing 
errors occurring in the practice environment were 
sought. Respondents considered workload (23, 76.7%), 
multitasking (19, 63.3%), rushing (18, 60%) and tiredness or 
stress (16, 53.3%) as important contributory factors. Other 
factors mentioned were distraction (11, 36.7%), low morale (9, 
30%), unfamiliar patient, busyness and no senior support (8, 
26.7%) each, being nervous or confused (5, 16.7%) and time in 
the day (2, 6.7%). </p>

<p>Prescription writing confidence 
In order to assess the extent of clinical exposure on 
prescribing confidence, respondents were asked to rate their 
level of confidence when prescribing unsupervised, from a 
specified list of drugs. Table 4 shows the list of drugs they felt 
least confident prescribing when not supervised. Antibiotics/ 
Antimicrobials, analgesics (opioids/non-opioids), cytotoxics 
and antipsychotics ranked highest amongst the drugs rated. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>All the interns reported to have had experience writing 
prescriptions with a majority claiming to be involved in 
prescribing medicines every day or more. Thus, they were 
already familiar with prescription writing process as a result 
of their clinical exposure to patient care. However, knowing 
what drug to prescribe to a patient did not necessarily 
translate to a good prescription. </p>

<p>Responses from these interns indicated a low self-awareness 
of making prescription errors. Up to 80% of the respondents 
felt they seldom or rarely made a prescription error which is 
contrary to reports of studies that focused on prescribing by 
junior doctors. 
[12,13,15] This suggests that their knowledge of 
what constitutes a prescribing error needs to be updated, thus 
highlighting an educational gap. They may have perceived 
themselves sufficiently prepared to prescribe rationally. </p>

<p>Ajemigbitse, et al.: Intern doctors' knowledge of prescribing errors </p>

<p>Journal of Basic and Clinical Pharmacy 
Vol. 5 | Issue 1 | December-February 2014 
 10  </p>

<p>However, this perception did not correlate with the high 
proportion who did not totally agree with the definition of a 
clinically important prescribing error as presented by Dean 
et al. 
[14] Previous studies have shown that the prescribing 
knowledge of new graduates of medical schools in Nigeria 
did not correlate with their prescribing skills. 
[21] Practical 
prescribing and regular assessment of prescribing skills are 
rarely practiced during undergraduate teaching. 
[22,23] Only </p>

<p>the theoretical knowledge of clinical pharmacology and 
therapeutics are imparted in medical teaching. </p>

<p>A close look at the respondents' self-rating of extents to which 
they agreed that a prescribing error had occurred reveal that 
about half (53%) partially agreed that prescribing medicines 
outside the hospital formulary constituted a prescribing 
error [Table 1]. Failure to crosscheck prescriptions with a </p>

<p>Table 1: Extent to which respondents agreed that a prescribing error had occurred </p>

<p>Description 
Totally 
agree </p>

<p>Partially 
agree </p>

<p>Neither agree 
nor disagree </p>

<p>Partially 
disagree </p>

<p>Totally 
disagree </p>

<p>No 
response </p>

<p>Prescribing medicines outside the hospital formulary 
3 
16 
1 
2 
4 
4 
Prescribing medicines by brand name rather than generic 
13 
8 
4 
2 
2 
1 
Prescribing for a child whose body weight is not documented 
22 
3 
2 
0 
2 
1 
Prescribing a medication without sufficient education of the patient on its 
proper uses and effects </p>

<p>18 
8 
1 
0 
2 
1 </p>

<p>Prescribing "one tablet" of a drug that is available in more than one strength 
17 
5 
2 
1 
2 
3 
Failure to adhere to prescribing guidelines 
18 
5 
1 
3 
2 
1 
Omission of the prescriber's signature 
13 
1 
3 
6 
5 
2 
Writing illegibly 
16 
7 
2 
3 
1 
1 
Prescribing a drug and not taking account of a potentially significant drug 
interaction </p>

<p>19 
6 
2 
0 
2 
1 </p>

<p>Writing a drug's name using a non-standard nomenclature/abbreviation 
16 
6 
2 
1 
3 
2 
Forgetting to write prescriptions for CD in the required manner 
12 
6 
3 
2 
3 
4 
Omission of the route of admission for a drug that can be given by more 
than one route </p>

<p>16 
4 
3 
3 
3 
1 </p>

<p>Prescribing a drug to which the patient has a documented clinically 
significant allergy (e.g., allergy to penicillins) </p>

<p>19 
2 
0 
4 
4 
1 </p>

<p>Continuing a prescription for a longer duration than necessary 
20 
4 
2 
1 
3 
0 
Prescribing a drug to be infused through an IV peripheral line without 
indicating frequency or duration </p>

<p>20 
3 
1 
1 
4 
1 </p>

<p>Prescribing a drug for which there is no evidence of efficacy just because 
the patient wishes it </p>

<p>16 
7 
1 
0 
5 
1 </p>

<p>Misspelling a drug name (major misspelling that lead to ambiguity or more 
than one possible meaning) </p>

<p>16 
3 
2 
4 
3 
2 </p>

<p>Failure to communicate essential information 
14 
5 
5 
3 
2 
1 
Prescribing a drug that should be given at specific times in relation to meals 
without specifying this information on the prescription </p>

<p>15 
5 
4 
0 
4 
2 </p>

<p>Forgetting to put a stop date on IV infusions 
15 
6 
2 
1 
4 
2 
Total 
318 
110 
43 
37 
60 
32 
Percentage 
53 
18.3 
7.2 
6.2 
10.0 
5.3 </p>

<p>CD: Controlled drug </p>

<p>Table 2: Most common reasons for types of mistakes encountered or self-made </p>

<p>Description 
Female 
Percentage 
Male 
Percentage 
Total 
Percentage </p>

<p>Failure to check your prescription with a reference source 
4 
7.3 
10 
18.2 
14 
25.5 
Failure to check your prescription with another member of staff 
0 
0 
1 
1.8 
1 
1.8 
Failure to check if the drug prescribed was contraindicated for 
patient's clinical condition </p>

<p>0 
0 
3 
5.5 
3 
5.5 </p>

<p>Failure to check if the drug prescribed adversely interacted with 
another drug the patient is taking </p>

<p>2 
3.6 
12 
21.8 
14 
25.5 </p>

<p>Lack of knowledge of drug indication 
0 
0 
3 
5.5 
3 
5.5 
Lack of knowledge of drug dose 
2 
3.6 
4 
7.3 
6 
10.9 
Lack of knowledge of the different formulations of drug prescribed 
4 
7.3 
3 
5.5 
7 
12.7 
Failure to follow-up on patient's status with regards to adverse 
reaction to the prescribed medicine </p>

<p>2 
3.6 
5 
9.1 
7 
12.7 </p>

<p>Total 
14 
25.5 
41 
74.5 
55 
100.0 </p>

<p>Ajemigbitse, et al.: Intern doctors' knowledge of prescribing errors </p>

<p>Vol. 5 | Issue 1 | December-February 2014 
Journal of Basic and Clinical Pharmacy 
 11  </p>

<p>reference source was also highly rated as a common reason for 
prescribing mistakes [Table 2]. Referring to reference sources/ 
drug formularies for prescribing information has been reported 
as an important step to preventing adverse drug reactions. 
[24] It 
is of concern that interns do not consider prescribing medicines 
within the hospital formulary as important. Related to this is 
that less than half of respondents totally agreed that prescribing 
medicines by brand names rather than generics constituted 
a prescribing error. The formulary provides a reference 
standard to the hospital's prescribers toward ensuring safe 
and good quality supply management of medicines procured 
by the pharmacy department, at a minimum/affordable cost 
to individuals and is drawn from the national essential drug 
list. The implication is that respondents are likely to prescribe 
drugs that are locally unavailable and are more expensive. This 
contradicts the World Health Organizations' principles for 
rational prescribing. </p>

<p>[25] </p>

<p>From respondents' extent of agreement to the 20 listed 
scenarios [Table 1], it is difficult to recommend all the 
standards for application at a given hospital even though more 
than 50% of the events received total agreement. It may be 
argued that practice situations, pattern of disease, approach 
to disease management, medicine administration processes, 
medication utilization and prescribing pattern vary from one 
country to another and may not all be applicable to a local 
setting. This observation however underscores the importance 
of standardizing the prescription writing process in Nigeria. </p>

<p>Although, the Nigeria standard treatment guideline </p>

<p>[26] </p>

<p>enumerates the essential elements of a prescription order to 
include identity of prescriber and patient in full, it is interesting </p>

<p>to note that only 43% of the respondents agreed that omitting 
the prescriber's signature on a prescription order constituted 
a prescribing error. This underscores the need for education 
as it highlights the low perception of the importance of 
this requirement. Studies have reported the tendency of 
prescribers to omit such important details in prescription 
orders written in the hospital setting. 
[4,19] Internship is a 
period of medical apprenticeship, under the supervision by 
senior doctors. During this training, it is expected that interns 
would pick up some prescribing habits and skills through 
informal association with other doctors. A culture of omitting 
prescriber signature or name on orders is inappropriate and 
suggests that observing such in the practice environment 
may have led interns to believe this is of low importance. It is 
essential to correct this notion. </p>

<p>Writing prescriptions for controlled drugs (CD) in the 
required manner is another issue of concern. In the Nigeria 
setting, because pharmacists generally have not been 
assertive in ensuring that the proper protocols are adhered 
to, many irregularities abound in prescription orders for these 
categories of medicines. If the protocols for CD prescribing are 
not strictly adhered to and taught, little wonder if interns do 
not see the value of this. Furthermore, this study has revealed 
the need for standardization of how drugs are prescribed and 
documented in the hospital setting as a way to mitigate errors 
arising from poor prescription writing. </p>

<p>Workload was cited as the major factor contributing to 
prescribing errors. Other closely related factors were 
multitasking and rushing. Similar findings have been reported 
by other researchers. 
[7,10-12,27] Lack of knowledge of the drug </p>

<p>Table 3: Most common types of errors made by respondents </p>

<p>Description 
Female 
Percentage 
Male 
Percentage 
Total 
Percentage </p>

<p>Dosage errors 
5 
7.7 
9 
13.8 
14 
21.5 
Drug-disease interaction errors 
0 
0.0 
1 
1.5 
1 
1.5 
Incorrect regimen 
0 
0.0 
3 
4.6 
3 
4.6 
Omitting duration of drug 
7 
10.8 
6 
9.2 
13 
20.0 
Omission of patient's age 
6 
9.2 
8 
12.3 
14 
21.5 
Drug-drug interaction 
1 
1.5 
5 
7.7 
6 
9.2 
Duplication of therapy 
1 
1.5 
0 
0.0 
1 
1.5 
Incorrect formulation 
1 
1.5 
3 
4.6 
4 
6.2 
Poor or illegible handwriting 
1 
1.5 
5 
7.7 
6 
9.2 
Omission of name/signature 
2 
3.1 
1 
1.5 
3 
4.6 
Total 
24 
36.9 
41 
63.1 
65 
100.0 </p>

<p>Table 4: List of drugs that respondents were least confident prescribing </p>

<p>Medicines 
Female 
Percentage 
Male 
Percentage 
Total 
Percentage </p>

<p>Antibiotics/anti-microbials 
6 
12.8 
6 
12.8 
12 
25.5 
Cytotoxic drugs 
1 
2.1 
9 
19.1 
10 
21.3 
Antipsychotic medicines 
2 
4.3 
7 
14.9 
9 
19.1 
CV drugs and related disease 
1 
2.1 
0 
0.0 
1 
2.1 
Anti infectives 
2 
4.3 
1 
2.1 
3 
6.4 
Analgesics (opioids) 
2 
4.3 
10 
21.3 
12 
25.5 
Total 
14 
29.8 
33 
70.2 
47 
100.0 </p>

<p>CV: Cardiovascular </p>

<p>Ajemigbitse, et al.: Intern doctors' knowledge of prescribing errors </p>

<p>Journal of Basic and Clinical Pharmacy 
Vol. 5 | Issue 1 | December-February 2014 
 12  </p>

<p>was not a major reason for prescribing errors. Common 
reasons encountered or made by respondents were a failure 
to check prescriptions with a reference source or to check if 
the drug prescribed adversely interacted with other medicines 
the patient is taking. It can be overwhelming for these 
inexperienced doctors to have the in-depth pharmacologic 
knowledge required to treat patients along with identifying 
and preventing the opportunities for drug-drug interactions, 
drug-disease incompatibilities and allergies. </p>

<p>[28] </p>

<p>Dosage errors and omitting to write patient's age topped 
the list of common types of prescribing errors made by 
respondents [Table 3]. This was followed by omitting to 
give a duration or length of time for taking a prescribed 
drug. These lapses are common in the hospital setting in 
Nigeria. 
[4,18,19] Junior doctors feel incompetent to write duration 
on prescribed medicines in the hospitalized patient because 
the conventional practice was to review patient's progress 
during the daily medical rounds. This however encourages 
unintended extension of administration due to the possibility 
of forgetting to stop the prescribed drug. Interestingly, 
duplication of therapy (prescribing two or more drugs from 
the same therapeutic class) and drug-disease interaction were 
the least common types of prescribing errors by respondents. </p>

<p>Respondents were least confident to prescribe antibiotics/ 
antimicrobials, opioid analgesics and cytotoxics [Table 4]. 
This tended to reflect the pattern of ailment they had not yet 
been exposed to and possibly on their knowledge of potential 
adverse effects of these drugs when prescribed in error. It 
is interesting that antimicrobials are included in this list 
considering the high rate of use of this drug category in the 
study hospital 
[19] and society at large 
[29] prudence and caution 
in prescribing antibiotics is appropriate. </p>

<p>Confident prescribing apparently will depend on clinical 
exposure during the intern year. The more the number of 
clinical rotations, the more confident the respondents will be 
expected to be at prescribing. Confidence in prescribing comes 
with practice, responsibility and familiarity with frequently 
used drugs on the ward and adequate supervision by senior 
colleagues. </p>

<p>[30] </p>

<p>The need for a standardized approach to what constitutes 
an acceptable prescription in the Nigeria setting cannot be 
over-emphasized. Such a framework will be designed to 
be acceptable to our prescribers and to which they can be 
meaningfully evaluated. Good quality prescribing will not 
be achieved if individual prescribers are allowed to define 
what correct prescribing is on their own. The involvement of 
pharmacists and other health care professionals in developing 
practice standards for good quality prescribing to which 
prescribers can adhere and upon which they can be evaluated 
is pertinent. </p>

<p>This study considered a good spread of intern doctors in 
the different specialties of rotation but results cannot be 
generalized as the views of all interns trained in Nigeria. 
Although, a statistically significant gender balance was not 
achieved in the study sample, it is unlikely that the result 
obtained would change significantly if a gender balance was </p>

<p>achieved. The study relied on self-assessment by respondents 
which may be subject to systematic bias. Possible skewing 
may have resulted from using the 20 clinical scenarios. 
Nevertheless, this study gives some insight into the knowledge 
and attitude of intern doctors to prescribing errors and offers 
openings for further research in this area. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>This study has shown the gaps in the knowledge that intern 
doctors have about prescription errors. Inadequate knowledge 
or competence and incomplete information about clinical 
characteristics of individual patients can result in prescribing 
faults, including the use of potentially unfamiliar medications. 
Interns have a low self-awareness of prescribing errors and 
would likely benefit from theoretical and practical teaching 
on what constitutes a properly written prescription with 
frequent assessment of knowledge and skills acquired. This 
would likely improve their confidence in rational medication 
prescribing during and after their internship training. An 
unsafe working environment and inadequate supervision 
have also been identified as important underlying factors that 
contribute to prescription errors. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to all the intern doctors who participated in 
this study. </p>



<p>Ajemigbitse, et al.: Intern doctors' knowledge of prescribing errors </p>

<p>Vol. 5 | Issue 1 | December-February 2014 
Journal of Basic and Clinical Pharmacy 
 13  </p>



<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Events that constitute a prescribing error 
(Dean et al., 2000) </p>

<p>Errors in decision making 
1. Prescription inappropriate for the patient concerned 
• Prescribing a drug for a patient for whom, as a 
result of a co-existing clinical condition, that drug 
is contraindicated e.g., metformin for a patient with 
CrCl &lt; 60 mL/min; Beta adrenergic -blocker to 
asthma patients 
• Prescribing a drug to which the patient has a 
documented clinically significant allergy e.g., 
amoxiclav for a patient with penicillin allergy 
• Prescribing a drug and not taking into account 
a potentially significant drug-interaction e.g., 
Concomitant 
administration 
of 
artemether/ 
lumefantrine and azithromycin (a macrolide 
antibiotic) =&gt; Q-wave elongation, a hazardous 
interaction; Warfarin + diclofenac (NSAIDs) =&gt; 
increased risk of bleeding 
• Prescribing a drug in a dose which is inappropriate 
for the patient's renal function e.g., clarithromycin, 
imipenem, ceftazidime-dose reduction required in 
renal impairment 
• Prescribing a drug in a dose below that recommended 
for the patient's clinical condition e.g., amoxiclav </p>



<p>625 mg b.d instead of 8 hourly in respiratory tract 
infections (RTI) 
• Prescribing a drug with a narrow therapeutic index, 
in a dose predicted to give serum levels significantly 
above the desired therapeutic range e.g., theophylline; 
plasma -theophylline concentration for optimum 
response is 10-20 mg/L 
• Prescribing 2 drugs for the same indication when only 
one drug is necessary e.g., amoxicillin and cefuroxime 
concurrently for RTI when one would be adequate 
• Prescribing a drug for which there is no indication for 
that patient e.g., antibiotics for viral infections 
• Not altering the dose following steady state serum 
levels significantly outside the therapeutic range 
e.g., digoxin dose should state concentration has 
been reached 
• Continuing a drug in the event of a clinically 
significant ADR e.g., statins and muscle effects </p>

<p>2. Pharmaceutical issues 
• Prescribing a drug to be given by IV infusion in a 
diluent that is incompatible with the drug prescribed 
e.g., nitrofrusside injection administered in a plastic 
IV container 
• Prescribing a drug to be infused via an IV 
peripheral line, in a concentration greater than that 
recommended for peripheral administration. </p>

<p>Ajemigbitse, et al.: Intern doctors' knowledge of prescribing errors </p>

<p>Journal of Basic and Clinical Pharmacy 
Vol. 5 | Issue 1 | December-February 2014 
 14  </p>

<p>Errors in prescription writing 
1. Failure to communicate essential information 
• Prescribing a drug, dose or route that is not that 
intended 
• Prescribing a medicine and omitting the dose, 
frequency, route or duration of use 
• Writing illegibly 
• Writing a drug's name using abbreviations or other 
non-standard nomenclature 
• Writing an ambiguous medication order 
• Prescribing 'one tablet' of a drug that is available in 
more than one strength of a tablet 
• Omission of the route of administration for a drug 
that can be given by more than one route 
• Prescribing a drug to be given by intermittent IV 
infusion, without specifying the duration over which 
it is to be infused 
• Omission of prescriber's identity (name/signature) </p>

<p>2. Transcription errors 
• On admission to hospital, unintentionally not 
prescribing a drug that the patient was taking prior 
to their admission 
• Transcribing a medication order incorrectly when 
re-writing a patient's drug chart 
• Continuing another doctor's prescribing error 
when writing a patient's drug chart on admission to 
hospital 
• Writing 'miligrams' when 'micrograms' was intended 
(or vice-versa) 
• Writing a prescription for discharge medication 
that un-intentionally deviates from the medication 
prescribed on the in-patient drug chart </p>

<p>Situations that may be considered prescribing 
errors, depending on individual clinical situation 
• Prescribing a drug in a dose above the maximum 
dose recommended in the BNF or other reference 
book or guideline 
• Misspelling a drug name (major misspellings that 
lead to ambiguity) 
• Prescribing a drug that cannot readily be administered 
using the dosage forms available 
• Prescribing a dose regimen (dose/frequency) that is 
not recommended for the formulation prescribed 
• Continuing a prescription for a longer duration that 
necessary 
• Prescribing a drug that should be given at specific 
times in relation to meals without specifying this 
information on the prescription 
• Unintentionally not prescribing a drug for a clinical 
condition for which medication is indicated. </p>

<p>Situations that should be excluded as prescribing 
errors 
• Prescribing by brand name (as opposed to generic 
name) 
• Prescribing a drug without informing the patient of 
its uses and potential side effects 
• Prescribing a drug for which there is no evidence of 
efficacy, because the patient wishes it 
• Prescribing a drug not in the hospital formulary 
• Prescribing contrary to hospital treatment guidelines 
• Prescribing contrary to national treatment guidelines 
• Prescribing for an indication that is not a drug's 
product license </p>

</text></tei>