<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4411514" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Herpes simplex virus (HSV) is a common causative agent of 
genital ulceration and can lead to subsequent neurological 
disease in some cases. Here, using a genital infection model, 
we tested the efficacy of vinegar-processed flos of Daphne 
genkwa (vp-genkwa) to modulate vaginal inflammation 
caused by HSV-1 infection. Our data revealed that treatment 
with optimal doses of vp-genkwa after, but not before, HSV-1 
infection provided enhanced resistance against HSV-1 in-
fection, as corroborated by reduced mortality and clinical 
signs. Consistent with these results, treatment with vp-gen-
kwa after HSV-1 infection reduced viral replication in the 
vaginal tract. Furthermore, somewhat intriguingly, treatment 
of vp-genkwa after HSV-1 infection increased the frequency 
and absolute number of CD3 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>NK1.1 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>NKp46 
＋ natural killer 
(NK) cells producing interferon (IFN)-γ and granyzme B, 
which indicates that vp-genkwa treatment induces the acti-
vation of NK cells. Supportively, secreted IFN-γ was de-
tected at an increased level in vaginal lavages of mice treat-
ed with vp-genkwa after HSV-1 infection. These results in-
dicate that enhanced resistance to HSV-1 infection by treat-
ment with vp-genkwa is associated with NK cell activation. 
Therefore, our data provide a valuable insight into the use of 
vp-genkwa to control clinical severity in HSV infection 
through NK cell activation. 
[Immune Network 2015;15(2):91-99] </p>

<p>A and B comprised water with 0.1% formic acid and acetoni-
trile with 0.1% formic acid, respectively. The gradient dura-
tion program was as follows: 0 min, 20% B; 0∼1 min, 20% 
B; 1∼6 min, 20∼80% B; 6∼8 min, 80∼98% B; 1-min wash 
with 98% B; and a 2-min recycle time. The flow rate was 
0.4 ml/min. </p>

<p>Cells and viruses </p>

<p>The HSV-1 McKrae strain was propagated in Vero cells </p>

<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>

<p>
(CCL81; ATCC, Manassas, VA, USA) using DMEM supple-
mented with 2.5% FBS, penicillin (100 U/ml), and streptomy-
cin (100 U/ml). The Vero cells were infected with HSV-1 at 
a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 0.01, and then incubated 
in a humidified CO2 incubator for 1 h at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. After absorp-
tion, the inoculums were removed, and 10 mL of main-
tenance medium containing 2.5% FBS was added. 
Approximately 48∼72 h after infection, a culture of host cells 
that showed an 80∼90% cytopathic effect was harvested. The 
virus stocks were then concentrated by centrifugation at 
50,000×g, titrated using a plaque assay, and stored in ali-
quots at −80 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C until needed. </p>

<p>Animal infection </p>

<p>The mice were treated with progesterone to synchronize their 
estrous cycles (31) prior to intravaginal (i.vag.) infection with 
the HSV-1 McKrae strain. Briefly, BALB/c mice were injected 
subcutaneously (s.c.) with Depo-Provera (DP) (Upjohn Co., 
Kalamazoo, MI, USA) at 2 mg per mouse. Five days following 
DP injection, the mice were i.vag. infected with 10 
6 PFU of </p>

<p>HSV-1 McKrae strain (20 μl) per mouse. The infected mice 
were examined daily for vaginal inflammation, neurological 
illness, and death, as described previously (31). They were 
scored from 1 to 5 depending on clinical disease severity (0, 
no inflammation; 1, mild inflammation; 2, moderate in-
flammation; 3, severe inflammation; 4, paralysis; 5, death). </p>

<p>Viral titration in vaginal lavages </p>

<p>Vaginal lavage fluid was obtained by introducing 100 μl of 
PBS (pH 7.2) into the vaginal canals and then recovering it 
with a micropipette. The samples were stored at −80 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C until 
used. Individual subsamples (50 μl from each sample) were 
further diluted, and viral titers were determined by a plaque 
assay performed on Vero cells as described elsewhere (31). </p>

<p>FACS analysis of NK cell activity </p>

<p>The mice were treated with vp-genkwa before and after 
HSV-1 infection, and the splenocytes were prepared from in-
fected mice 3 days post-infection (dpi). NK cells were enum-
erated by FACS staining using a cocktail of CD3 (145-2C11), 
NK1.1 (PK136), and NKp46 (29A1.4.9) antibodies 
(eBioscience, San Diego, CA, USA). To determine the activity 
of NK cells, we used intracellular staining for IFN-γ and gran-
zyme B (GrB) in response to stimulation of PMA (750 ng/ml; 
Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) plus ionomycin (50 
ng/ml; Sigma-Aldrich). Briefly, prepared splenocytes were </p>

<p>cultured with PMA and ionomycin in the presence of mon-
ensin (2 μM; Sigma-Aldrich) for 2 h for IFN-γ and 4 h for 
GrB. Cells were harvested and labeled with CD3, NK1.1, and 
NKp46 antibodies, and subsequently stained with intracellular 
IFN-γ and GrB after fixation and permeabilization. All sam-
ples were acquired on FACS Calibur (BD Bioscience, 
Mountain View, CA, USA), and analyzed by <rs id="software-0" type="software">FlowJo</rs> software 
(ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">7.6.5</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Tree Star</rs>, San Carlos, CA, USA). Forward scatter 
and side scatter were used to identify lymphocytes, which 
were further used to define NK cell and intracellular ex-
pression of IFN-γ and GrB. </p>

<p>Determination of vaginal IFN-γ secretion </p>

<p>Vaginal lavage fluid for IFN-γ secretion was collected 3 dpi 
by introducing 100 μl of PBS (pH 7.2) into the vaginal canal 
and then recovering it with a micropipette following infection 
of synchronized mice with the HSV-1 McKrae strain. The vag-
inal mucus was subsequently removed from the fluid by cen-
trifugation at 10,000 rpm for 1 min. IFN-γ levels in vaginal 
lavages were determined by ELISA using IFN-γ anti-mouse 
Ab (R4-6A2) and biotinylated IFN-γ Ab (XMG1.2). The ELISA 
plates were washed and incubated with peroxidase-con-
jugated streptavidin for 1 h, and then the color was 
developed. The IFN-γ concentration was calculated with an 
automated ELISA reader. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All data were expressed as the average±standard deviation, 
and statistically significant differences between groups were 
analyzed by unpaired two-tailed Student's t-test. Kaplan-
Meier survival curves were analyzed by the log-rank test. A 
p-value≤0.05 was considered significant. All data were ana-
lyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Prism</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPadPrism4</rs>, San Diego, CA, 
USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Reduction of mortality and clinical signs by treatment 
of vp-genkwa after HSV-1 infection </p>

<p>In order to assess the effect of vp-genkwa on the mortality 
and clinical signs associated with mucosal HSV-1 infection, 
we orally administered 10 and 50 mg/kg (mpk) vp-genkwa 
twice prior to HSV-1 infection. Subsequently, we examined 
infected mice daily until 15 dpi. Our results revealed that 
pre-treatment of vp-genkwa had no effect on mortality and 
clinical signs, compared to the group treated with vehicle </p>

<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 1. Vp-genkwa treatment 
following mucosal HSV-1 infection 
reduces mortality and ameliorates 
clinical signs. (A and B) Effect of 
vp-genkwa treatment prior to HSV-1 
infection. Groups of BALB/c mice 
received oral vp-genkwa twice, and 
were infected i.vag. with HSV-1 the 
next day. The infected mice were 
then examined daily until 15 dpi for 
survival (A) and for vaginal inflam-
mation, neurological illness, and 
death (B). (C and D) Effect of 
vp-genkwa treatment after HSV-1 
infection. Groups of BALB/c mice 
were infected i.vag. with HSV-1 and 
treated orally with vp-genkwa twice 
with a 1-day interval. The infected 
mice were examined daily until 15 
dpi to assess survival (C), and 
vaginal inflammation, neurological 
illness, and death (D). Kaplan-Meiers 
survival curves were computed and 
analyzed using the chi-square test. 
Clinical severity was graded as 
follows: 0, no inflammation; 1, mild 
inflammation; 2, moderate swelling; 
3, severe inflammation; 4, paralysis; 
5, death. The graph of clinical scores 
represents the average clinical score 
of 10 mice per group. </p>

<p>(Fig. 1A and B). However, somewhat intriguingly, mice that 
were treated with vp-genkwa (10 mpk) after HSV-1 infection 
showed enhanced resistance (p=0.0605), as well as alleviated 
clinical signs, compared to mice that received vehicle (Fig. 
1C and D). Furthermore, higher doses of vp-genkwa (50 
mpk) did not provide increased protection against mucosal 
HSV-1 infection, indicating that enhanced protective immunity 
against HSV-1 infection may be achieved with treatment of 
vp-genkwa at optimal doses after infection. Therefore, these 
results suggest that treatment of vp-genkwa at an optimal 
dose after HSV-1 infection provides enhanced protection, </p>

<p>while pre-treatment of vp-genkwa before HSV-1 infection 
does not affect the associated mortality and clinical signs. </p>

<p>Treatment of vp-genkwa reduces viral burden 
following HSV-1 infection </p>

<p>Because treatment of vp-genkwa (10 mpk) after infection of-
fered increased protection against mucosal HSV-1 infection, 
we examined viral secretion in vaginal lavages of mice that 
received vp-genkwa (10 mpk) before and after HSV-1 
infection. Consistent with the previous results, vp-genkwa 
treatment before HSV-1 infection showed no regulatory role </p>

<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 2. Treatment with vp-genkwa 
after HSV-1 infection reduces viral 
replication. (A) Effect of vp-genkwa 
pretreatment on HSV-1 replication. 
(B) Effect of vp-genkwa post-
treatment on HSV-1 replication. 
Groups of BALB/c mice (n=5) were 
infected i.vag. with HSV-1 after (A) 
and before (B) oral administration of 
vp-genkwa (10 mpk). Viral titers in 
vaginal lavages collected at 2 and 4 
dpi were determined by plaque 
assay. </p>

<p>in the control of viral secretion in vaginal lavages, whereas 
vp-genkwa treatment after HSV-1 infection reduced viral titers 
in vaginal lavages (Fig. 2). Thus, this result indicates that 
vp-genkwa treatment after HSV-1 infection might control 
HSV-1 replication in the vaginal tract. </p>

<p>Increased NK cell activity in vp-genkwa-treated 
mice following HSV-1 infection </p>

<p>Vaginal infiltration of innate leukocytes, such as granulocytes 
and monocytes/macrophages, are thought to contribute to 
HSV infection resistance via direct and indirect mechanisms 
(10,11). Moreover, NK cells reportedly play a crucial role in 
regulating vaginal inflammation caused by HSV-1 infection 
(4,5). Thus, we decided to explore the regulatory role of 
vp-genkwa treatment on NK cell activity. First, we determined 
the frequency and absolute number of CD3 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>NK1.1 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>NKp46 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>NK cells in the spleen of mice treated with vp-genkwa before 
and after HSV-1 infection 3 dpi. In spite of vp-genkwa treat-
ment before and after HSV-1 infection, our results did not in-
dicate any changes in the frequency or absolute number of 
NK cells, except that vp-genkwa treatment before HSV-1 in-
fection slightly increased the percentage of NK cells in the 
spleen (Fig. 3A). However, intriguingly, vp-genkwa treatment 
after HSV-1 infection increased the frequency and absolute 
number of IFN-γ-and granzyme B-producing NK cells, 
whereas pre-treatment with vp-genkwa before HSV-1 in-
fection did not affect the frequency or absolute number of 
IFN-γ-and granzyme B-producing NK cells (Fig. 3B and C). </p>

<p>These data indicate that vp-genkwa treatment after HSV-1 in-
fection increases NK cell activity because IFN-γ and gran-
zyme B expressed on activated NK cells are involved in erad-
icating virions and killing virus-infected cells. Supportively, 
secreted IFN-γ was detected at higher levels in vaginal lav-
ages of mice treated with vp-genkwa after HSV-1 infection, 
compared to that of mice treated with vehicle and vp-genkwa 
before HSV-1 infection (Fig. 4). Collectively, these results in-
dicate that the enhanced resistance of mice treated with 
vp-genkwa after HSV-1 infection is closely associated with in-
creased NK cell activity. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Examination of genital HSV infection using a murine model 
has significantly contributed to our understanding of the role 
of innate and adaptive immune cells during vaginal in-
flammation and CNS-invasion. In the present study, we dem-
onstrated using a murine infection model that treatment with 
vp-genkwa at optimal doses after, but not before, HSV-1 in-
fection provides enhanced resistance, as reflected by reduced 
mortality and clinical severity. Further, the reduction in viral 
secretion in vaginal lavages of mice treated with vp-genkwa 
after infection supported the observed decrease in the clinical 
signs caused by mucosal HSV-1 infection. Interestingly, the 
reduction in mortality and clinical signs in mice treated with 
vp-genkwa after viral infection was closely associated with 
enhanced NK cell activation, which indicates the involvement </p>

<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>

<p>
Figure 3. Enhancement of NK cell activity in vp-genkwa-treated mice 
following HSV-1 infection. (A) The frequency and absolute number 
of NK cells in the spleen of mice treated with vp-genkwa. The 
splenocytes were prepared from mice that were pre-and post-treated 
with vp-genkwa (10 mpk) 3 dpi, and used to enumerate NK cells 
(CD3 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>NK1.1 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>NKp46 </p>

<p>＋ </p>

<p>) using FACS analysis. The left graph denotes 
the average percentage of NK cells in the spleen, and the right graph 
shows the absolute number of NK cells in the spleens of four mice 
per group. (B and C) The frequency and absolute number of NK cells 
producing IFN-γ and granzyme B. The splenocytes were prepared 
from mice pre-and post-treated with vp-genkwa 3 dpi and stimulated 
with PMA plus ionomycin. The frequency and absolute number of 
IFN-γ-(B) and granzyme B (C; GrB)-producing cells in NK cells (CD3 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>NK1.This study was supported by a National Research Foundation 
of Korea (NRF) grant, funded by the Korea Government 
(MISP) (2012R1A2A1A03670284). The funder had no role in 
study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, 
or preparation of manuscript. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors have no financial conflict of interest. </p>



<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>

<p>
J. Bozzola, and E. L. Parr. 1994. A mouse model for studies 
of mucosal immunity to vaginal infection by herpes simplex </p>

<p>virus type 2. Lab. Invest. 70: 369-380. </p>

<p>11. Uyangaa, E., A. M. Patil, and S. K. Eo. 2014. Prophylactic 
and therapeutic modulation of innate and adaptive immunity </p>

<p>against mucosal infection of herpes simplex virus. Immune 
Netw. 14: 187-200. </p>



<p>Anti-herpes Activity of Vp-genkwa by NK Cell Activation 
Erdenebileg Uyangaa, et al. </p>

<p>IMMUNE NETWORK Vol. 15, No. 2: 91-99, April, 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>