<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4820195" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Keywords: 
Sickness presence, health 
care professionals, disabled 
workers </p>

<p>Objectives. The aim of the article is to investigate the differences in sickness present and non-sickness 
present in the group of disabled health care professionals. </p>

<p>Methods. Data were gathered from all disabled health care professionals suffering from invalidity of category 
II or III who were identified in the research among all health care professionals at the University Medical 
Centre Ljubljana and who were employed there in the period between 1 January 2010 and 31 December 
2010. Each employee obtained a questionnaire composed of three standardized international questionnaires. </p>

<p>Results. There were 248 disabled workers of the II. and III. category of invalidity among the participants. 
Disabled sickness present reported to have more chronic diseases than disabled non-sickness present (OR = 
57.0; 95% CI = 24.4-133.2), lower salary when on sick leave (OR = 13.1; 95% CI = 5.7-30.2) and poor self-rated 
health (OR = 5.8; 95% CI = 2.7-12.3). </p>

<p>Conclusions. The prerequisite for sickness presence among disabled workers is their chronic bad health. It 
is also formally recognized with the degree of disability. Economic factors are among the most important to 
direct disabled workers towards sickness presence. The results indicate that workplaces are not adapted to 
disabled workers in regard to their limitations. </p>

<p>IZVLEČEK </p>

<p>Ključne besede: 
prezentizem, zdravstveni 
delavci, invalidi </p>

<p>Namen. Osnovni namen članka je raziskati razlike med prezentisti in neprezentisti znotraj skupine zdra-
vstvenih delavcev invalidov. </p>

<p>Metode. V raziskavi so sodelovali vsi invalidi II. in III. kategorije, ki so zaposleni v Univerzitetnem kliničnem 
centru Ljubljana in ki smo jih identificirali v raziskavi, ki je zajela vse zaposlene zdravstvene delavce UKC 
Ljubljana v obdobju med 1.1. 2010 in 31.12.2010. Izpolnili so vprašalnik, sestavljen iz treh standardiziranih 
mednarodnih vprašalnikov. </p>

<p>Rezultati. Med preiskovanci je bilo 248 invalidov II. in III. kategorije. Invalidi prezentisti so navajali več kro-
ničnih bolezni kot invalidi neprezentisti (RO = 57.0; 95 % IZ = 24.4-133.2), nižji osebni dohodek ob bolniškem 
staležu (RO = 13.1; 95 % IZ = 5.7-30.2) in slabšo samooceno zdravstvenega stanja (RO = 5.8; 95 % IZ = 2.7-12.3). </p>

<p>Zaključek. Osnova za prezentizem pri delovnih invalidih je kronična okvara njihovega zdravja, ki je tudi 
formalno priznana s stopnjo invalidnosti. Ekonomski dejavniki so poleg bolezni najpomembnejši dejavniki 
tveganja za prezentizem pri invalidih. Iz rezultatov je mogoče sklepati, da delovna mesta invalidnim delav-
cem niso prilagojena v tolikšni meri, da bi povsem ustrezala njihovim omejitvam zaradi bolezni. </p>

<p>The assessment of workers' health is usually carried out 
by the following indicators: injuries at work, occupational 
diseases, sick leave and disability. Most frequently, sick 
leave is used, which represents temporary absence from 
work due to disease and/or injury (1). However, in 2000 
a new phenomenon defined as sickness presence started 
to be researched. Sickness presence is the presence of 
workers at work when they feel so sick that they could 
be on sick leave (2-6). The data on sick leave show that 
30-40% of employees were not on sick leave during a one-
-year period observed (7, 8). A varied group ranging from 
employees who are actually healthy and do not have any 
health-related problems to those who feel sick but work 
nevertheless belong to this group. The latter are supposed 
to have a lower social status, fixed-term employment or 
are threatened with dismissal from work, more demanding 
and responsible work, can arrange work by themselves and 
those who have low possibility of replacement at work (2,  3, 6, 8-11). The researchers estimate that there are hig-
her odds for sickness presence in educational and medical 
institutions (2, 8). It is described that the level of sickness 
presence among health care professionals is associated 
with time pressure (8, 9, 12, 13), lack of personnel or 
the inability to replace a co-worker at work (8, 12), work 
experience and (dis)satisfaction with work (13). </p>

<p>Permanent damage to health and the resulting inability 
to work are called work-related disability (hereafter re-
ferred to as disability), which is recognized by law if the 
chances of the insured person to get or retain his/her 
workplace and to advance professionally are decreased 
due to the changes in his/her health status that cannot be 
reversed by means of treatment or medical rehabilitation 
(14). If the worker was classified into disability category 
II or III in the process of establishing disability, the rema-
ining workability was assessed, which means that he/she 
can be employed in another workplace that suits his/her 
level of education or he/she can undergo the process of 
occupational rehabilitation resulting in full-time work in 
another workplace or else he/she can do particular work 
at least part-time (14). Formally, the law protects disabled 
workers and requires that the employer is obliged to adapt 
the workplace to suit the limitations of the disabled in 
order to prevent further damage to their health (15, 16). 
There are no data on how successful the return of wor-
kers to a suitably adapted working environment is and to 
what extent such relocations of disabled people actually 
prevent damage to their health. </p>

<p>The available literature does not provide data on the 
extent of sickness presence among the disabled, which 
would indirectly show the suitability of the workplaces 
adapted for the disabled. Therefore, aiming at providing 
scientific evidence for focused preventive occupational 
medicine actions in the sub-population of disabled wor-
kers, the objective of our study was to assess the preva-
lence of sickness presence among disabled workers at the 
University Medical Centre Ljubljana (UMC Ljubljana). </p>

<p>2 METHODS </p>

<p>The study was designed as a cross-sectional study. </p>

<p>2.1 Participants </p>

<p>Out of 5865 health care professionals who were in a con-
tinuous employment relationship at the UMC Ljubljana in 
the period between 1 January 2010 and 31 December 2010, 
the following employees were excluded: those who were 
on sick leave and/or maternity leave for more than six 
months, all those who were employed at the UMC Ljublja-
na for fewer than twelve months in the observed period 
and those employed in technical services. In the remaining 
group of health care professionals, all the disabled workers 
were selected, totaling 389. </p>

<p>The study included the following groups of employees clas-
sified as being disabled: employees who were assessed by 
the Invalidity Committee of the Pension and Disability Insu-
rance Institute of the Republic of Slovenia as "the disabled 
of category II" if their workability for their occupation was 
decreased by 50% or more or as "the disabled of category 
III" if they were no longer able to work full-time with or 
without prior occupational rehabilitation but could carry 
out certain work at least part-time or if their workability 
for their occupation was decreased by less than 50% or if 
they could still work in their profession full-time but were 
not capable of working in the workplace to which they 
were assigned (14). </p>

<p>2.2 Observed phenomenon </p>

<p>The observed phenomenon was sickness presence. In our 
study, the sickness present were defined as the disabled 
workers who were present at work at least two or more 
times in 2010 when they felt sick and the non-sickness 
present were defined as the disabled workers who were 
never or who were present at work at most once when 
they felt sick (2). </p>

<p>2.3 Research tools and course of study </p>

<p>For the purpose of our study, a questionnaire was prepared 
consisting of 57 questions taken from three international 
standardized and validated questionnaires (2, 17-20). The 
questionnaire contained questions related to demographic 
factors (sex, age, education, children, smoking, recreati-
on, net salary, some important life events such as death 
of next of kin or friend, independence of a child, disease 
of next of kin, change in the workplace, change in the 
employment status of a partner, loan, change of a flat, ho-
lidays), factors connected with work (workplace, psychical 
and physical workload, shift work), psycho-social factors 
(creativity, possibility of education, influence on work or-
ganization, superiors' and co-workers' support, time pres-
sure, possibility of replacement, lower salary when on sick 
leave), factors that describe health status (diseases by 
groups by organ systems) and factors that describe one's 
own assessment of workability (sickness absence, barriers </p>



<p>Zdrav Var 2014; 53(4): 277-282 
doi 10.2478/sjph-2014-0030 </p>

<p>and work impairment, anticipated certainty about one's 
own workability in the following year). </p>

<p>The questionnaires were distributed to all disabled wor-
kers at the UMC Ljubljana in the second half of January 
2011 with the help of senior nursing officers. We enclosed 
an envelope for the answer and a cover letter. The que-
stionnaires were numbered by means of codes. Informed 
consent was signed by all participants who answered the 
questionnaire. Sealed envelopes with answered questio-
nnaires were collected in special boxes by senior nursing 
officers and the couriers took them to the Clinical Institute 
of Occupational, Traffic and Sports Medicine (CIOTSM). The 
participants could also return them by themselves to the 
CIOTSM. The Organ of the UMC Ljubljana, No. 2, 2011, pu-
blished an article describing the study and its aims in order 
to additionally encourage employees to answer the que-
stionnaire. All those whose answers had not been received 
by the end of April 2011 were sent the questionnaires once 
again in May 2011 together with a request to answer them. </p>

<p>2.4 Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Besides descriptive statistical methods, the statistical 
analysis also used the methods for the analysis of the as-
sociation of sickness presence with the selected risk fac-
tors for sickness presence: sex (male, female), age (50 
years or more, less than 50 years), education (secondary 
or less, higher or university), children (no, yes), smokers 
(no, yes), net salary &lt; EUR 1000 (no, yes), death of next 
of kin or friend (no, yes), disease of next of kin (no, yes), 
work (health care professionals, managerial or administra-
tive work), working life (20 years or more, fewer than 20 
years), high psychical workload (no, yes), high physical 
workload (no, yes), night work (no, yes), no possibility of 
education (no, yes), low superiors' support (no, yes), low 
co-workers' support (no, yes), time pressure (no, yes), dis-
satisfaction at work (no, yes), poor self-rated health (no, 
yes), musculoskeletal disorders (no, yes), cardiovascular </p>

<p>diseases (no, yes), respiratory diseases (no, yes), mental 
and behavioral disorders (no, yes), gastrointestinal disea-
ses (no, yes), endocrine diseases (no, yes), chronic disea-
ses (no, yes), no possibility of replacement (no, yes), lower 
salary when on sick leave (no, yes), on sick leave &gt; twice 
(no, yes), work impairment (no, yes) and not sure about 
workability next year (no, yes). Logistic regression was 
chosen as univariate as well as multivariate analysis. The 
multivariate model included all the variables that were in 
a statistically significant association with the dependent 
variable in the univariate model and that were considered 
the most sensible to be included in the multivariate model 
from a professional perspective. </p>

<p>The <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> program, version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0</rs>, was used to perform the 
statistical analysis, which was carried out at the CIOTSM. </p>

<p>2.5 Ethical aspects of the study </p>

<p>The study was approved by the National Medical Ethics 
Committee of the Republic of Slovenia on 11 January 2011. </p>

<p>3 RESULTS </p>

<p>The questionnaire was answered in full by 248 health care 
professionals -disabled workers out of the total number 
of 389 disabled workers employed at the UMC Ljubljana 
(63.8%). </p>

<p>Among the 248 disabled workers, 183 were sickness pre-
sent (73.8%) and 65 were non-sickness present (26.2%). 
Among the selected risk factors that were included in the 
univariate logistic regression, there was the strongest as-
sociation between sickness presence and the presence of 
chronic disease and lower salary when on sick leave (Table 
1). </p>

<p>Risk factor 
Category 
N SP 
(%) 
OR 
95 % CI limits 
p </p>

<p>Lower 
Upper </p>

<p>Sex 
Male 
Female </p>

<p>9/16 
174/232 </p>

<p>56.3 
75.0 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.33 
0.82 
6.55 
0.107 </p>

<p>Age 
50 years or more 
Less than 50 years </p>

<p>84/115 
99/133 </p>

<p>73.0 
74.4 </p>

<p>1.00 
1.10 
0.61 
1.89 
0.804 </p>

<p>Education 
Higher or university 
Secondary or less </p>

<p>43/65 
145/183 </p>

<p>66.1 
79.2 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.77 
1.48 
4.99 
0.001 </p>

<p>Children 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>22/43 
161/205 </p>

<p>51.2 
78.5 </p>

<p>1.00 
3.49 
1.76 
6.93 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Smokers 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>119/170 
64/78 </p>

<p>70.0 
82.1 </p>

<p>1.00 
1.96 
1.01 
3.81 
0.047 </p>

<p>Net salary &lt; 1000 EUR 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>35/58 
148/190 </p>

<p>60.3 
77.9 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.32 
2.36 
4.34 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Death of next of kin or friend 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>124/177 
59/71 </p>

<p>70.1 
83.1 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.10 
1.05 
4.22 
0.037 </p>

<p>Table 1. Estimates of sickness presence according to the selected risk factors among 248 disabled workers at the University Medical Centre 
Ljubljana, 2010, and the results of the univariate logistic regression. </p>



<p>doi 10.2478/sjph-2014-0030 </p>

<p>Risk factor 
Category 
N SP 
(%) 
OR 
95 % CI limits 
p </p>

<p>Lower 
Upper </p>

<p>Disease of next of kin 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>155/216 
28/32 </p>

<p>71.8 
87.5 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.76 
0.93 
8.18 
0.068 </p>

<p>Work 
Managerial or 
administrative work 
Health care professionals </p>

<p>5/14 </p>

<p>60/169 </p>

<p>35.7 </p>

<p>35.5 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.01 
0.35 
2.92 
0.991 </p>

<p>Working life 
Fewer than 20 years 
20 years or more </p>

<p>165/216 
18/32 </p>

<p>76.4 
56.3 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.50 
1.16 
5.56 
0.018 </p>

<p>High psychical workload 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>94/137 
89/111 </p>

<p>68.6 
80.2 </p>

<p>1.00 
1.85 
1.03 
2.70 
0.041 </p>

<p>High physical workload 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>123/177 
60/71 </p>

<p>69.5 
84.5 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.40 
1.17 
4.91 
0.017 </p>

<p>Night work 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>170/231 
13/17 </p>

<p>73.6 
76.5 </p>

<p>1.00 
1.16 
0.37 
3.71 
0.795 </p>

<p>No possibility of education 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>94/139 
89/109 </p>

<p>67.6 
81.7 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.13 
1.17 
3.89 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Low superiors' support 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>124/176 
59/72 </p>

<p>70.5 
81.9 </p>

<p>1.00 
1.90 
0.96 
3.77 
0.064 </p>

<p>Low co-workers' support 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>145/203 
38/45 </p>

<p>71.4 
84.4 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.17 
0.92 
5.14 
0.078 </p>

<p>Time pressure 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>49/68 
134/180 </p>

<p>72.1 
74.4 </p>

<p>1.00 
1.14 
0.60 
2.13 
0.703 </p>

<p>Dissatisfaction at work 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>123/180 
60/68 </p>

<p>68.3 
88.2 </p>

<p>1.00 
3.48 
1.56 
7.75 
0.002 </p>

<p>Poor self-rated health 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>95/151 
88/97 </p>

<p>62.9 
90.7 </p>

<p>1.00 
5.76 
2.69 
12.34 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Musculoskeletal disorders 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>34/70 
149/178 </p>

<p>48.6 
83.7 </p>

<p>1.00 
5.44 
2.12 
10.01 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Cardiovascular diseases 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>95/149 
88/99 </p>

<p>63.8 
88.9 </p>

<p>1.00 
4.55 
2.24 
9.25 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Respiratory diseases 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>119/173 
64/75 </p>

<p>68.8 
85.3 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.64 
1.29 
5.40 
0.008 </p>

<p>Mental and behavioural disorders 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>40/81 
143/167 </p>

<p>49.4 
85.6 </p>

<p>1.00 
6.11 
3.31 
11.28 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal diseases 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>123/175 
60/73 </p>

<p>70.3 
82.2 </p>

<p>1.00 
1.95 
0.98 
3.86 
0.055 </p>

<p>Endocrine diseases 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>115/169 
68/79 </p>

<p>68.0 
86.1 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.90 
1.42 
5.93 
0.003 </p>

<p>Chronic disease 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>11/62 
172/186 </p>

<p>17.7 
92.5 </p>

<p>1.00 
56.96 
24.36 
133.17 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>No possibility of replacement 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>92/138 
91/110 </p>

<p>66.7 
82.7 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.40 
1.30 
4.40 
0.005 </p>

<p>Lower salary when on sick leave 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>71/129 
112/119 </p>

<p>55.0 
94.1 </p>

<p>1.00 
13.07 
5.65 
30.24 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>On sick leave &gt; twice 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>91/135 
92/113 </p>

<p>67.4 
81.4 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.12 
1.17 
3.84 
0.013 </p>

<p>Work impairment 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>38/62 
145/186 </p>

<p>61.3 
78.0 </p>

<p>1.00 
2.23 
1.21 
4.14 
0.011 </p>

<p>Not sure about work ability next year 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>84/135 
99/113 </p>

<p>62.2 
87.6 </p>

<p>1.00 
4.29 
2.22 
8.30 
&lt; 0.001 </p>

<p>Legend: N SP = number of the disabled sickness present in the group; N cat = number of the disabled in the category 
Abbreviations: OR -odds ratio; CI -confidence interval </p>

<p>Zdrav Var 2014; 53(4): 277-282 </p>



<p>doi 10.2478/sjph-2014-0030 </p>

<p>The results of the multivariate analysis are similar to those 
of the univariate analysis. The variables that had been 
statistically significant in the univariate analysis were also 
statistically significant in the multivariate analysis, namely 
chronic diseases (OR = 31.0, 95% CI 11.0-87.2; p &lt; 0.001), 
lower salary when on sick leave (OR = 7.0, 95% CI 2.1-22.8; 
p = 0.001) and poor self-rated health (OR = 4.2, 95% CI 
1.1-15.9; p = 0.035). </p>

<p>4 DISCUSSION </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to deal with sic-
kness presence in the disabled. The response of the disa-
bled workers was higher than that of all health care pro-
fessionals, amounting to 57.6% (21). The share of sickness 
present disabled workers was larger than we could have 
expected in comparison to the results of the studies among 
health care professionals and among public employees, 
where the share of sickness present ranges between 18% 
and 65% (2-5, 12, 21). The share was higher than expec-
ted especially because the operative part of the decision 
of the invalidity commission that relieves the workers of 
some of the work enables the disabled to carry out work 
in accordance with their remaining psychophysical abilities 
and consequently they are not supposed to "work when 
sick". The observed groups of the disabled of invalidity 
categories II and III, including both sickness present and 
non-sickness present, do not differ in terms of sex and age, 
but they do differ in the following characteristics: disabled 
workers -sickness present with chronic diseases have hig-
her odds for sickness presence in comparison with disabled 
workers -non-sickness present. They primarily suffer from 
mental and behavioral as well as musculoskeletal disor-
ders. When they are really sick, people start to behave dif-
ferently due to the following reasons: the changed econo-
mic circumstances together with the economic crisis after 
2009 and a decreased likelihood of permanent employment 
with the possibility of dismissal and a decrease in salary 
during sick leave. A significant decrease in sick leave was 
observed in the area of mental and behavioral disorders 
at the level of the entire state, and we believe that it is 
this decrease that indicates sickness presence (22). Mental 
and behavioral disorders have also been presented in other 
studies as one of the main causes of sickness presence (23,  24). Disabled workers -sickness present enumerate more 
medical conditions than disabled workers -non-sickness 
present, and, consequently, they experience their health 
as poor and they are on sick leave more often. Despite 
the fact that the disabled workers should be assigned to 
a suitable workplace due to chronic damage to health, 
they often say they work while sick. Indirectly, a question 
can be posed whether the workplace is really suitable as 
regards the disability assessment (25). A new workplace 
should suit the worker's remaining psychophysical abilities. 
Sickness present disabled workers report higher physical 
and psychical workloads than disabled workers -non-sic-
kness present. Contrary to expectations, they also have 
to replace their co-workers more often than disabled wor-
kers -non-sickness present, although their invalidity status 
prohibits that explicitly. </p>

<p>Disabled workers -sickness present belong to the socially 
weaker class with a lower level of education and lower 
salaries, and they are mostly smokers. Besides chronic di-
seases among disabled workers -sickness present, fear of 
lower salary shows the highest odds for sickness presence. 
They perceive themselves as being dissatisfied with work. 
Since they are dissatisfied with work, their availability for 
work is low and consequently their productivity decreases 
(26). Disabled workers -sickness present are supported 
neither by their superiors nor by their co-workers. Disa-
bled workers -sickness present claim that their chances 
for education are slimmer. Since they have a lower level 
of education than disabled workers -non-sickness present, 
additional education for them means at best secondary 
education, which is sufficient only for physically deman-
ding work in the health sector. Disabled workers -sickness 
present mostly suffer from musculoskeletal disorders, whi-
ch is why physical work is not suitable for them, and, con-
sequently, such additional education does not represent a 
solution to this problem. We should, however, not ignore 
the fact that disabled workers -sickness present assess 
their health as poor, which is an additional reason why they 
do not have motivation for additional education (25, 27). </p>

<p>Despite the fact that the responsiveness of the participants 
was good and comparable to other studies on sickness pre-
sence, this study has its limitations. The test subjects took 
part in research on a voluntary basis, which is why not all 
the disabled workers were included, but their response 
was better than that of all health care professionals. It is 
possible that they have problems and as is generally well-
known, people with problems respond more often than 
those without problems. As regards the circumstances in 
Slovenia, the response was good, and we cannot find any 
reason why less than 40% of the non-respondents could 
be considered so different from the respondents that the 
results of this study cannot be evaluated as reliable. </p>

<p>This study is important for occupational medicine, because 
it poses two questions and expects occupational medicine 
to answer them. The first question concerns the importan-
ce of sickness presence as the possible new indicator of 
workers' health, and the second question concerns the sui-
tability of the workplaces that have already been adapted; 
the second more indirect question addresses the suitability 
of determining workability in the course of the invalidity 
procedure. Further research should be aimed at the que-
stion of what kind of risk sickness presence represents for 
future health and disability. </p>

<p>5 CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Disabled workers represent a large group among emplo-
yed health care professionals. Among them, the sickness 
present represents the majority despite the fact that all 
disabled workers with a formal invalidity decision are re-
lieved of some work in accordance with their diagnosis. 
It is obvious that besides chronic diseases, economic risk 
factors represent the greatest risk for sickness presence 
among disabled workers. It would therefore be sensible 
to invest money in work-oriented rehabilitation and re-</p>

<p>Zdrav Var 2014; 53(4): 277-282 </p>



<p>doi 10.2478/sjph-2014-0030 </p>

<p>training of the disabled in such a way as to increase their 
chances of employment in a suitable workplace that would 
be adapted to their specific needs. This is how their eco-
nomic vulnerability would be decreased. Presently, the 
disabled workers as well as employers are not particu-
larly motivated towards education. Disabled workers of 
category II or III frequently become disabled workers of 
category I and thus a burden on the Pension and Disability 
Insurance Institute; they can even become unemployed, 
which represents an even greater risk for the deterioration 
of their health status. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>The authors declare that no conflict of interest exist. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>As a tertiary project, the study was co-financed by 
the Health Insurance Institute of Slovenia (Project No. 
20110043). </p>

<p>ETHICAL APPROVAL </p>

<p>Received from the National Medical Ethics Committee of the 
Republic of Slovenia on 24 January 2011. </p>



<p>Zdrav Var 2014; 53(4): 277-282 </p>

</text></tei>