<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4668168" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. [Purpose] To observe motor and functional progress of children with cerebral palsy during 2 years. 
[Subjects and Methods] Pediatric cerebral palsy patients aged 3-15 years (n = 35/69) with 24-month follow-up at 
our outpatient cerebral palsy clinic were evaluated retrospectively. The distribution of cerebral palsy types was as 
follows: diplegia (n = 19), hemiplegia (n = 4), and quadriplegia (n = 12). Participants were divided into 3 groups 
according to their Gross Motor Functional Classification System scores (i.e., mild, moderate, and severe). All par-
ticipants were evaluated initially and at the final assessment 2 years later. During this time, patients were treated 3 
times/week. Changes in motor and functional abilities were assessed based on Gross Motor Function Measure-88 
and Wee Functional Independence Measure. [Results] Significant improvements were observed in Gross Motor 
Function Measure-88 and Wee Functional Independence Measure results in all 35 patients at the end of 2 years. The 
Gross Motor Function Measure-88 scores correlated with Wee Functional Independence Measure Scores. Marked 
increases in motor and functional capabilities in mild and moderate cerebral palsy patients were observed in the 
subgroup assessments, but not in those with severe cerebral palsy. [Conclusion] Rehabilitation may greatly help 
mild and moderate cerebral palsy patients achieve their full potential. 
Cerebral palsy (CP) covers the broadest spectrum of 
childhood posture and movement disorders. CP patients 
have static brain lesions and clinical manifestations that 
change over time during growth and development of the 
affected individual. The wide range of problems associated 
with CP poses difficulties in patient assessment and achiev-
ing rehabilitation targets 1, 2) . Rehabilitation of CP requires 
a multidisciplinary approach. The family and team of spe-
cialists should establish the most appropriate approach after 
determining the treatment goal. Although there are several 
treatment modalities, scientific evidence regarding the basis 
for treatment decisions is limited. The heterogeneity of CP 
and the absence of controls and results of disease specific 
measures are responsible for the lack of evidence 1) . 
The goal of rehabilitation of CP is to reduce secondary 
musculoskeletal deformity rather than treating the primary 
central neurological deficit. Medical management may also 
be required in addition to physical, occupational, and speech </p>

<p>therapy. Different management approaches are utilized in 
different institutions 2) . Most physical therapies are based 
on the principles of neuroplasticity, patterning, postural 
balance, and muscle strengthening or stretching. In addition, 
there are conductive education therapies, which include 
integrated education programs 3, 4) . However, there is no 
scientific evidence for the superiority of one treatment over 
another. Healthcare providers often use these therapeutic 
approaches in combination with functionally based thera-
pies. The ideal duration and frequency of these therapies 
have not been established 1) . The superiority of intermittent 
high-frequency treatments has not yet been successfully 
demonstrated in controlled studies 5, 6) . 
CP has a reported global prevalence of 2-3.5 per 1,000 
live births 7, 8) and 4.4 per 1,000 live births in Turkey 9) . 
Special education and rehabilitation centers exist in Tur-
key for children with CP covered by social security. These 
centers usually utilize a combination of therapeutic methods 
that are tailored to the needs of each child. In this study, we 
aimed to review long-term outcomes of rehabilitation in 
children undergoing such therapies. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>We conducted a retrospective review of medical records 
in 65 pediatric patients with CP who were followed-up for 
2 years from 2011 to 2013 at the CP outpatient clinic of 
Istanbul Medeniyet University, Goztepe Training and Re-</p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. 
27: 3211-3214, 2015 </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. Erkan Mesci (E-mail: erkanmesci@ 
hotmail.com) </p>

<p>©2015 The Society of Physical Therapy Science. Published by IPEC Inc. 
This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Cre-
ative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-
nd) License &lt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/&gt;. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 27, No. 10, 2015 </p>

<p>
search Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey. The approval to conduct 
this study was obtained from the The Institutional Board and 
local ethics committee at Istanbul Medeniyet University, 
Goztepe Trainig and Research Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey. 
Written informed consent provided from the parents/guard-
ian of the children prior to enrolling in the study. Eleven 
children with CP were excluded due to a change in address 
leading to discontinuation of therapy; 19 children met the 
study exclusion criteria (i.e., priorly received botulinum 
toxin injection or had major surgery performed within the 
last 6 months). The study was completed by 35 CP patients 
who received continuous physical therapy for 24 months and 
were followed-up by our team. All patients were diagnosed 
with CP by a pediatric neurologist. 
At the time of treatment initiation, children were enrolled 
in treatment programs at special rehabilitation centers after 
being examined by a physiatrist with expertise in CP and 
a physiotherapist working at our clinic. Patients received 
physiotherapy 3 times/week, which included traditional 
physiotherapy approaches and neurodevelopmental therapy. 
Depending on individual needs, patients were administered 
botulinum toxin injections, and assistance and orthosis were 
provided. Those patients who required surgical operation 
were referred for orthopedic intervention. Their caregiv-
ers were instructed to perform home-based exercises. All 
children were reexamined at the end of the 2 year treatment 
program by the same medical team. 
Children with CP were classified according to the number 
of limbs affected as follows: quadriplegic, an impairment of 
the trunk and 4 limbs; diplegic, involvement of the lower 
extremities; and hemiplegic, only one side of the body was 
affected. Patients were evaluated using a locomotor system 
examination, Gross Motor Function Classification System 
(GMFCS), Gross Motor Function Measure-88 (GMFM-88), 
and Wee Functional Independence Measure (WeeFIM). 
The GMFCS, commonly used in cerebral palsy studies, 
is a reliable and valid scale, which is based on self-initiated 
movement with a particular emphasis on sitting (truncal 
control) and walking 10) . The GMFCS consists of 5 levels; 
level 1 indicates independent mobility and level 5 indicates 
full dependency 11) . The reliability of the Turkish version of 
this scale was previously demonstrated 12) . 
Harries et al. have investigated changes in gross motor 
function during 6 months in children with CP aged 3-8 years 
who were classified using the GMFCS as mild, moderate, or 
severe 13) . In the present study, we also used the same classifi-
cation for patient assessment. GMFCS level 1 and 2 patients 
walk without and with limitations, respectively. GMFCS 
levels 1 and 2 were classified together as mild. GMFCS level 
3 patients walk with adaptive equipment assistance and were 
classified as moderate; level 4 and 5 patients who had no 
self-mobility were classified as severe. Based on this clas-
sification, the mild and moderate groups both contained 12 
patients and the severe group had 11 patients. 
The GMFM-88 is a valuable standardized test designed 
to examine the achievements and limitations of gross mo-
tor function in children with CP, monitor progress of the 
individual child, and evaluate the treatment outcomes of 
programs for this population 14) . The GMFM-88 is very 
reliable for assessing the mobility and functional ability of </p>

<p>children with CP 15) . GMFM-88 consists of 88 items, which 
are scored as 0-3 points based on how well each of the 
following 5 activities are performed: lying and rolling (A), 
sitting (B), crawling and kneeling (C), standing (D), and 
walking, running, and jumping (E). 
The WeeFIM was used to evaluate the health of the pa-
tients, their developmental condition, educational level, and 
degree of local sociality. Items of the WeeFIM are scored 
as 1-7, where 1 indicates total assistance and 7 indicates 
complete independence. The lowest and highest possible 
score is 18 and 126, respectively 16) . The reliability and 
validity of the Turkish version of the WeeFIM for assessing 
the functional status in Turkish children with CP have been 
demonstrated 17, 18) . 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for Social Sciences</rs> (SPSS) for Win-
dows 19.0 software package (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>, New York, USA) was 
used for statistical analyses of study findings. Study data 
were analyzed using statistical methods (i.e., median and 
minimum-maximum) and Wilcoxon signed rank test was 
used for intragroup comparisons of quantitative parameters 
that did not follow a normal distribution. The associations 
between GMFM-88 and WeeFIM scores were analyzed 
using Spearman correlation analysis. Results were reported 
with 95% confidence intervals and a p-value &lt;0.05 was 
considered significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The age range of the 35 children with CP was 3-15 years 
(median, 6 years). All CP patients had spastic type CP and 
most of them were boys with a diplegic predominance. Two 
children with athetoid form of CP and 4-limb involvement 
were included in the quadriplegic group. The characteristics 
of the study participants are illustrated in Table 1. A highly 
significant increase in GMFM-88 scores was observed after 
24 months of treatment compared to baseline when all chil-
dren were evaluated together (n = 35; p = 0.000). In addition, 
A highly statistically significant increase in WeeFIM values 
of the whole group was observed at the end of 24 months (p 
= 0.000; Table 2). 
Significant increases were observed in gross motor 
function (Table 3) and functional measure scores (Table 4) 
following treatment among patients with mild and moder-
ate disease. However, the reduction in GMFM-88 scores </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of the study participants </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Value </p>

<p>Age (years) 
3-15 (median 6) 
Treatment course (sessions) 
312 
Duration of treatment (months) 
24 
Gender 
Male 
23 (65.7%) 
Female 
12 (34.3%) 
Type of involvement 
Diplegic 
19 (54.3%) 
Hemiplegic 
4 (11.4%) 
Quadriplegic 
12 (34.3%) </p>



<p>observed among the severe group was not statistically 
significance. In addition, post-treatment changes in WeeFIM 
scores were not statistically significant in patients in the 
severe groups. 
An increase, decrease, and no change in GMFM scores 
was observed in 26, 8, and 1 patient(s), respectively, accord-
ing to the GMFM-88 evaluation after 24 months of treat-
ment (Table 5). However, WeeFIM scores were increased, 
decreased, and unchanged in 26, 5, and 4 patients, respec-
tively (Table 5). There was a significant correlation between 
baseline GMFM-88 and WeeFIM scores and post-treatment 
GMFM-88 and WeeFIM scores (p = 0.000). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Significant improvements in gross motor function 
were found when all (n = 35) pediatric CP patients were 
assessed together after 2 years. Individual evaluation of 
groups showed significant increases in both GMFM-88 
and WeeFIM scores for mild and moderate groups. Yi et al. 
observed a marked improvement in gross motor function 
in 45 children with CP after 6 months of rehabilitation and 
attributed this improvement to a longer treatment duration, 
baseline GMFM-88 scores, and absence of a concomitant 
disorder. GMFM-88 scores were increased in both groups 
in this previous study, including diplegic and quadriplegic 
patients. A greater improvement was observed in diplegic 
patients compared to severely affected patients, albeit not 
statistically significant 19) . In contrast, a statistically signifi-
cant change was not observed in GMFM-88 scores among 
our severely affected patients. Treatment was provided twice 
daily for 5 days/week in the study by Tae et al., which was 
different compared to our study. 
Improvements in GMFM-88 scores were observed in all 
3 groups (i.e., hemiplegic, diplegic, and quadriplegic) in a 
study with different types of CP patients after 8 months of 
treatment. According to that study, although a substantial </p>

<p>improvement in motor performance was detected during 
the first 4 months in hemiplegic and quadriplegic children, 
the trend was not maintained in the succeeding 4 months. 
However, diplegic children displayed an improving trend 
during the succeeding 4 months. Average GMFC scores of 
quadriplegic children were found to be lower compared to 
those of other groups 20) . 
In a retrospective study by Harries et al., 106 children 
with CP were evaluated after 7 years of follow-up using 
GMFM-88, and an increase in GMFM-88 scores was ob-
served among mild, moderate and severe CP groups. While 
the speed of improvement varied according to the severity of 
motor disability, both mild and severe groups reached their 
maximum gross motor function within the 7 year follow-
up 13) . 
The developmental patterns of children with spastic diple-
gic (SD) and spastic quadriplegic (SQ) CP were compared 
in the study by Chen et al. In that study, it was observed 
that children with SQ had lower development quotients in 
all developmental functions compared to SD children 21) . In 
a similar study, gross motor functions and developmental 
patterns improved with age and were correlated with the 
degree of ambulatory function in diplegic children; however, 
these results were not observed among SQ children 22) . These 
findings corroborate our results of quadriplegic patients (i.e., 
severe group). 
We found that the gross motor function and WeeFIM 
scores of children were correlated prior to treatment and 
following 24 months of rehabilitation. In our study, chil-
dren with mild and moderate CP had higher post-treatment 
WeeFIM scores compared to baseline, which were consis-
tent with their improved gross motor function, but there 
was no significant change in children with severe CP. In a 
study by Damiano and Abel, children with CP who achieved 
highest functional ambulation scores had higher GMFM-88 
scores 23) . Beckung and Hagberg have stated that gross motor 
functions of children with CP are crucial for their physical 
independence and mobility 24) . The pre-treatment and post-
treatment GMFM-88 and WeeFIM scores were determined </p>

<p>Table 2. Gross Motor Function Measure-88 and 
Wee Functional Independence Measure 
results of patients with cerebral palsy 
(n = 35) </p>

<p>Initial (median) Final (median) </p>

<p>GMFM-88 
125 
176* 
WeeFIM 
46 
71* </p>

<p>*p &lt; 0.001, Wilcoxon signed rank test; GMFM-88: 
Gross Motor Function Measure-88; WeeFIM: Wee 
Functional Independence Measure </p>

<p>Table 3. Changes in the Gross Motor Function Mea-
sure-88 scores (pre-treatment-post-treatment) </p>

<p>n Initial (median) Final (median) </p>

<p>Mild 
12 
218.5 
247.5** 
Moderate 
12 
123 
175** 
Severe 
11 
25 
15 </p>

<p>**p &lt; 0.01, Wilcoxon signed rank test </p>

<p>Table 4. Changes in the Wee Functional Independence 
Measure scores (pre-treatment − post-treatment) </p>

<p>n 
Initial (median) Final (median) </p>

<p>Mild 
12 
79 
112*** 
Moderate 
12 
47.5 
68** 
Severe 
11 
18 
19* </p>

<p>*p &gt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.05, ***p &lt; 0.01, Wilcoxon signed rank 
test </p>

<p>Table 5. Changes observed in Gross Motor Function 
Measure-88 and Wee Functional Independence 
Measure scores at the end of 2 years </p>

<p>Increased 
Decreased 
No change </p>

<p>GMFM-88 
26 
8 
1 
WeeFIM 
26 
5 
4 </p>

<p>GMFM-88: Gross Motor Function Measure-88, WeeFIM: 
Wee Functional Independence Measure </p>

<p>J. Phys. Ther. Sci. Vol. 27, No. 10, 2015 </p>

<p>
to be correlated in a study involving children with CP after 
1 year rehabilitation 25) . However, no correlation was found 
between GMFM-88 and WeeFIM scores of children with CP 
in a contrasting study 26) . 
Major limitations of our study included the fact that 
patients were treated at different centers and a small sample 
size. While a non-intensive (i.e., 3 times/week) rehabilita-
tion program provided marked motor improvement and in-
creased functional capacity at the end of 2 years in children 
with mild and moderate CP, which helped them reach their 
full potential, there was no such improvement in patients 
with severe CP. Our findings are comparable to several 
previous studies in this area. Identification and anticipation 
of problems experienced by children with severe disability 
would help patients and their families prepare better for the 
future. </p>



</text></tei>