<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4832950" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Ovarian cancer is a leading gynecological malignancy. We investigated the prognostic value of programmed cell death 
5 (PDCD5) in patients with ovarian cancer. 
Methods: Expression levels of PDCD5 mRNA and protein were examined in six ovarian cancer cell lines (SKOV3, CAOV3, ES2, OV1, 
3AO, and HOC1A) and one normal ovarian epithelial cell line (T29) using reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction, Western blotting, 
and flow cytometry. After inducing PDCD5 induction in SKOV3 cells or treating this cell line with taxol or doxorubicin (either alone or 
combined), apoptosis was measured by Annexin V-FITC/propidium iodide staining. Correlations between PDCD5 protein expression 
and pathological features, histological grade, FIGO stage, effective cytoreductive surgery, and serum cancer antigen-125 values were 
evaluated in patients with ovarian cancer. 
Results: PDCD5 mRNA and protein expression were downregulated in ovarian cancer cells. Recombinant human PDCD5 increased 
doxorubicin-induced apoptosis in SKOV3 cells (15.96 ± 2.07%, vs. 3.17 ± 1.45% in controls). In patients with ovarian cancer, PDCD5 
expression was inversely correlated with FIGO stage, pathological grade, and patient survival (P &lt; 0.05, R = 0.7139 for survival). 
Conclusions: PDCD5 expression is negatively correlated with disease progression and stage in ovarian cancer. Therefore, measuring 
PDCD5 expression may be a good method of determining the prognosis of ovarian cancer patients. </p>

<p>Key words: Ovarian Cancer; Poor Prognosis; Programmed Cell Death 5 </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Prof. Xiao-Hong Chang, 
Gynecolog Oncology Center, Peking University People's Hospital, 
Beijing 100044, China 
E-Mail: changxiaohong@pkuph.edu.cn </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.155100 </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>



<p>whether PDCD5 overexpression enhances apoptosis induced 
by chemotherapeutic regimens in ovarian cancer. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Ethics statement </p>

<p>This study was carried out in accordance with the Declaration 
of Helsinki of the World Medical Association. It was 
approved by Peking University People's Hospital (Beijing, 
China). All patients provided informed written consents. </p>

<p>Cell lines and cell culture </p>

<p>The human serous cystadenocarcinoma cell line SKOV3 
was kindly provided by the Memorial Sloan Kettering 
Cancer Center. CAOV3 ovarian serous cystadenocarcinoma 
samples were purchased from the China Military Science 
Center. HOC1A cells (immortalized ovarian cancer cells) 
were derived in our laboratory from metastatic nodules 
of the left abdominal wall of ovarian cancer patients. 
OV1 cells, a low-grade ovarian adenocarcinoma cell line, 
were kindly provided by Peking University Oncology 
Institution. The 3AO low-grade ovarian mucinous cell line 
was purchased from the China Science and Technology 
Cell Bank. The ES-2 human low-grade clear-cell line was 
a gift from Dr. You-Ji Feng at Fudan University. The T29 
human immortalized ovarian epithelial cell line was a gift 
from Dr. Jin-Song Liu at the MD Anderson Cancer Center. </p>

<p>All cells were cultured at 37°C in an atmosphere containing 
5% CO 2 . SKOV3, ES-2, 3AO, OV1, and OV2 cells were 
cultured in RPMI1640 medium containing 15% fetal calf 
serum. T29 and HOC1A cells were cultured in MCDB 
medium containing M199 plus 15% fetal calf serum. 
CAOV3 cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified 
Eagle's medium containing 15% fetal calf serum. All media 
contained 1% penicillin and streptomycin. </p>

<p>Tissue samples </p>

<p>A total of 127 ovarian cancer samples, 48 ovarian benign 
tumors, and 33 normal ovarian tissue samples were obtained 
during surgical procedures at the Department of Gynecology, 
Peking University People's Hospital from January 2000 to 
March 2006. All samples were examined by two pathologists 
to confirm patient diagnoses before experiments were 
performed. None of the patients had received neoadjuvant 
therapy, such as radiation or chemotherapy, prior to surgery. </p>

<p>Real-time reverse transcription polymerase chain 
reaction </p>

<p>Samples were frozen at −80°C in liquid nitrogen. RNA was 
extracted from 24 samples (5 normal ovarian tissues, 8 benign 
tumors, and 11 ovarian cancer tissues) using a modified 
TRIzol one-step extraction method. RNA concentrations were 
determined by their absorbance at 260 nm. Total RNA (3 μg) 
was reverse transcribed to cDNA using oligo-dT primers 
and M-MLV transcriptase (Promega, USA). Real-time 
polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed using a 
SYBR Green Master Mix (Toyobo, Japan) and primers specific 
to PDCD5 (sense: 5'-GTGATGCGGCCCAACAG-3', </p>

<p>antisense: 5'-GTGATGCGGCCCAACAG-3') and GAPDH 
(sense: 5'-TGCACCACCAACTGCTTAGC-3', antisense: 
5'-GGCATGGACTGTGGTCATGAG-3'). The PCR 
protocol comprised of 30 cycles at 94°C for 30 s, 58°C for 
30 s, and 72°C for 30 s; followed by a final extension at 
72°C for 7 min. Human GAPDH was used as an internal 
control. Samples were analyzed in triplicate in three 
independent experiments using Bio-Rad MJ Mini and 
MiniOpticon (Bio-Rad, USA). PDCD5 expression was 
calculated using the 2 
ΔΔCt method. </p>

<p>Western blotting </p>

<p>Tissue samples and ovarian cell lines were treated with 
RIPA lysis buffer (pH 7.4) containing ×1 protease inhibitor 
cocktail (M221; Amresco, Solon, OH, USA). After 
centrifugation for 15 min at 12,000 r/min, the supernatant 
was used for the whole protein lysate samples. Protein 
concentrations were determined using the BCA standard 
method. Protein extracts were diluted in loading buffer 
(1 mmol/L Tris-HCl, 3% sodium dodecyl sulfate [SDS], 
60% glycerol, and 75 mmol/L dithiothreitol), and samples 
were analyzed by SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis) 
using 15% gels, followed by transfer to polyvinylidene 
fluoride membranes. Membranes were then incubated 
with mouse anti-human PDCD5 (1:1000 dilution; Beijing 
University Human Disease Center, Beijing, China) 
or rabbit anti-human GAPDH (1:2000 dilution; Cell 
Signaling Technology Company, USA) antibodies at 
room temperature overnight. This was followed by 
incubation with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated 
secondary antibodies (1:10,000 dilution; ZB-2301, 
Zhongshan Golden Bridge Biotechnology, Beijing, China). 
Immunoreactive bands were visualized using the enhanced 
chemiluminescence method according to the manufacturer's 
instructions (Applygen Technologies, Beijing, China). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissue sections from 
normal ovary tissue and serous tumors were cut into 
4-6-μm sections and transferred to slides. Samples were 
deparaffinized in xylene and rehydrated via an ethanol 
gradient (100%, 95% ×2, 85%, 75% ×2, 50%, and distilled 
water). Slides were then washed, endogenous peroxidase 
activity was blocked by incubation in 3% H 2 O 2 , and samples 
were preincubated with 10% goat serum, and then with 
monoclonal mouse anti-PDCD5 antibody (1:1000) for 1 h at 
room temperature in a humid chamber. Secondary staining 
with HRP-conjugated anti-mouse IgG (Zhongshan Golden 
Bridge Biotechnology, Beijing, China) was performed 
using a DAB peroxidase substrate kit (Zhongshan Golden 
Bridge Biotechnology, Beijing, China). Nuclei were 
counterstained with hematoxylin. In negative controls, the 
primary antibody was replaced with an isotype control. All 
staining was evaluated using the <rs type="software">Leica Q550CW</rs> software 
system (Germany) and <rs type="software">Qwin</rs> image analysis software. We 
randomly selected five independent fields from each slide; 
the average density of positive cells these five fields was 
calculated as the PDCD5 expression level. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>

<p>
Annexin v-FITC/propidium iodide staining and flow 
cytometry </p>

<p>SKOV3 cells were centrifuged, resuspended in 1× binding 
buffer at a density of 4.0 × 10 
5 cells/ml and transferred to a 
12-well dish (1 ml suspension/well). Cells were incubated 
in triplicate with PBS (control), 20 μg/ml recombinant 
human PDCD5 (rhPDCD5; P20; Beijing University 
Human Disease Center, Beijing, China), 0.1 μg/ml 
taxol (T0.1), 0.5 μg/ml doxorubicin (A0.5), or P20 plus 
T0.1 or A0.5. After 24 h, cells were collected, centrifuged, 
and incubated with conjugated Annexin V (2.5 μl; 
Pharmingen) and 1 μl propidium iodide (Pharmingen) for 
15 min at room temperature in the dark. Next, 400 μl ×1 
Annexin binding buffer was added to each cell sample, 
and the cells were analyzed by flow cytometry (BD 
Influx, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Becton Dickinson</rs>) using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Cell Quest Research Software</rs> (Becton Dickinson). </p>

<p>Survival time and follow-up </p>

<p>The mean follow-up period for patients was 49.6 months 
(range: 6-133 months; median: 45.5 months). The survival 
time of ovarian cancer patients enrolled in this study was 
defined as the time from primary surgery to death or last 
follow-up. Of the 94 patients at Stages III and IV, 22 were 
lost to follow-up before the time of death could be recorded. 
Therefore, only 72 patients were included in the survival 
analysis. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>We used χ 
2 and Fisher's exact tests to determine 
correlations between PDCD5 levels and clinical parameters. 
The cumulative survival time was calculated by the 
Kaplan-Meier method and analyzed using the log-rank test. 
Cox proportional hazard regression was used to calculate 
hazard ratios (HRs) with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) 
between groups in univariate and multivariate settings. 
A P &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. All calculations 
were performed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">17.0</rs> statistical software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., USA). </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Human ovarian epithelial cells and cancer cell lines had 
different programmed cell death 5 mRNA and protein 
expression levels </p>

<p>Programmed cell death 5 mRNA and protein expression 
levels were analyzed in T29 cells and various ovarian 
cancer cell lines using real-time PCR and western blotting, 
respectively. PDCD5 mRNA levels were highest in normal 
ovarian epithelial cells (T29). Among the ovarian cancer cell 
lines examined, PDCD5 mRNA expression was highest in 
CAOV3 cells, moderately expressed in OV1 and 3AO cells, 
and lowest in HOC1A, SKOV3, and ES2 cells [Figure 1a]. 
The pattern of PDCD5 protein expression in these 
cell lines, as analyzed by western blotting [Figure 1b] 
and flow cytometry [Figure 1c], reflected their mRNA 
expression (i.e., T29 &gt; CAOV3 &gt; 3AO = OV1 &gt; 
Hoc1A = SKOV3 = ES2). </p>

<p>PDCD5 mRNA and protein expression in human ovarian 
tissues </p>

<p>We next determined PDCD5 mRNA and protein expression 
levels in tumor tissues and compared them with levels 
in normal ovarian tissue. Benign ovarian tumor samples 
were used as controls. Reverse transcription-PCR showed 
that PDCD5 mRNA expression was less in epithelial 
malignancies (n = 11) than in normal tissue (n = 5) or benign 
ovarian tumors (n = 8). Immunohistochemical analysis 
showed PDCD5 protein expression in these tissues was 
consistent with their mRNA expression. Similarly, PDCD5 
expression was lowest in epithelial cancer tissues (n = 127), 
higher in benign ovarian tumor tissue (n = 48), and highest 
in normal ovarian tissue (n = 33; Table 1 and Figure 2). 
Compared with normal ovaries, the expression of PDCD5 
mRNA and protein in benign ovarian tumors and epithelial 
malignancies are significantly decreased [Table 1]. </p>

<p>Effects of recombinant programmed cell death 5 on 
apoptosis in skov3 cells </p>

<p>We next analyzed the effect of recombinant PDCD5 on 
apoptosis. Treatment of SKOV3 cells with 20 μg/ml 
recombinant PDCD5 (P20) did not alter basal apoptosis 
compared with controls (3.6 ± 0.7% vs. 3.2 ± 1.5%, 
respectively). However, PDCD5 did enhance taxol-and 
doxorubicin-induced apoptosis. Treatment with 0.1 μg/ml 
taxol increased apoptosis (11.1 ± 0.8%) compared with 
buffer control and P20-treated controls. However, treatment 
with P20 + 0.1 μg/ml taxol resulted in even higher levels of 
apoptosis (21.9 ± 1.9%). Similarly, P20 treatment enhanced 
doxorubicin-induced apoptosis (16.0 ± 2.1%; Figure 3). </p>

<p>Study participants </p>

<p>Baseline demographic and disease characteristics of the 
127 patients are shown in Table 2. Their median age was 
52 years (range: 24-72 years). Their ovarian cancer types 
included serous (84; 66.14%), mucinous (13; 10.24%), 
endometrioid (14; 11.02%), clear cell (9; 7.08%), and other 
types (7; 5.51%). Of the 127 patients, 62 (48.82%) had cancer 
antigen-125 (CA-125) expression levels &gt;500 IU/ml, while 
the remaining 65 (51.18%) had CA-125 levels &lt;500 IU/ml. </p>

<p>Relationship between programmed cell death 5 expression 
and clinical parameters of epithelial ovarian cancer </p>

<p>To determine the clinical significance of reduced PDCD5 
expression in carcinoma, we examined relationships between </p>

<p>Table 1: PDCD5 mRNA and protein expression in 
normal human ovaries and ovarian tumors </p>

<p>Tissues 
n Relative mRNA 
expression* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>n 
Relative protein 
expression </p>

<p> † ‡ </p>

<p>Normal 
5 
1.00 ± 0.00 
33 
0.36 ± 0.03 
Benign 
8 
0.72 ± 0.19 </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>48 
0.31 ± 0.03 </p>

<p>|| </p>

<p>Epithelial cancer 11 
0.49 ± 0.21 </p>

<p>|| </p>

<p>127 
0.28 ± 0.04 </p>

<p>|| </p>

<p>*Measured by RT-PCR, 
 † Mean ± SD; </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Measured by signal density 
after immunostaining; 
 § P&lt;0.05; 
|| P&lt;0.001. PDCD5: Programmed cell 
death 5; RT-PCR: Reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction; 
SD: Standard deviation. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>



<p>PDCD5 expression and various clinical parameters of 
epithelial ovarian cancer. PDCD5 expression significantly 
differed by FIGO stage, pathological grade, whether tumor 
cytoreduction surgery was satisfactory or unsatisfactory, 
metastasis, ascites, and CA-125 level (P &lt; 0.05; Table 2). 
PDCD5 expression was significantly reduced in different 
ovarian cancer subtypes, and was lower in patients with 
FIGO Stage III-IV tumors (0.2745 ± 0.0342, n = 94) than 
in those with Stage I-II tumors (0.3092 ± 0.0257, n = 33). 
PDCD5 expression was inversely related to pathological 
grade and significantly lower in grade three tumors than in 
Grade 1 tumors (P &lt; 0.0001). </p>

<p>Risk factor analysis and patient prognosis </p>

<p>We next examined the association between PDCD5 
expression and patient survival. We collected survival 
data from 72 of the 94 Stage III-IV ovarian cancer 
patients at follow-up [Table 3], and divided the patients 
into low PDCD5 expression (&lt;median value) and high 
PDCD5 expression (&gt;median value) groups, according 
to their immunohistochemical analyses. Median overall 
survival was 19.5 months (95% CI: 13.63-25.37 months) 
for the low-PDCD5 group versus 63.5 months 
(95% CI: 61.15-65.85 months) for the high-PDCD5 
group (P &lt; 0.001). Multivariate Cox regression analysis </p>

<p>Figure 1: Expression of programmed cell death 5 (PDCD5) in human ovarian epithelial cell lines and cancer cell lines. (a) Real-time reverse 
transcription polymerase chain reaction shows PDCD5 mRNA expression in different cell lines, standardized to GAPDH mRNA; (b) Western 
blotting shows PDCD5 protein levels in different cell lines; (c) Flow cytometry shows analysis of cells labeled with anti-PDCD5 antibody; lower 
right: Relative PDCD5 protein data. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>

<p>
showed PDCD5 levels to significantly correlate with 
survival time (HR: 0.00, 95% CI: 0.00-0.00; P &lt; 0.001; 
Table 3). High PDCD5 protein expression was associated 
with significantly longer survival than for low PDCD5 
expression (P &lt; 0.001; Figure 4a). Patients with lower 
PDCD5 levels had significantly shorter disease-specific 
survival than those with higher expression. Spearman's 
analysis strongly associated PDCD5 expression with patient 
survival time (P &lt; 0.0001, R = 0.7139; Figure 4b). </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>Programmed cell death 5 is a human gene identified via 
the cDNA-representative differences analysis technique 
described by Liu et al. 
[2] at Peking University Human 
Genomic Center. The 6-Kb PDCD5 gene, located on 
chromosome 19q12-q13.1, contains 6 exons and 5 introns. 
It encodes a 125-amino acid protein that localizes to both 
the nucleus and cytoplasm. PDCD5 is expressed in more 
than 50 human tissues; high expression levels have been </p>

<p>Figure 3: Effects of various treatments on apoptosis in SKOV3 cells. SKOV3 cells were treated with programmed cell death 5 (PDCD5), either 
alone or combined with taxol or doxorubicin. Apoptotic cells were measured by Annexin V-FITC/propidium iodide staining and flow cytometry. 
Representative flow cytometry results are shown for each treatment. Lower panel: Data from 3 independent experiments. P20: 20 μg/ml human 
recombinant PDCD5 protein; T01: 0.1 μg/ml taxol; A0.5: 0.5 μg/ml doxorubicin. </p>

<p>Figure 2: Programmed cell death 5 (PDCD5) protein expression in normal 
ovaries and ovarian tumors, as detected by immunohistochemistry. 
(a) and (b) Epithelial ovarian cancer tissues; (c) Benign ovarian neoplasm 
tissue; (d) Normal ovarian epithelial tissues. Red: PDCD5 
+ cells; 
magnification: ×200. </p>

<p>d 
c </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>



<p>reported in the adult heart, testis, kidney, adrenal glands, 
and placenta. Expression is significantly lower in embryos. 
Functional analyses have shown that PDCD5 stimulates 
tumor cell apoptosis induced by various stimuli. 
[3-6] When 
cells undergo apoptosis, PDCD5 mRNA and protein </p>

<p>expression are elevated, and PDCD5 protein translocates 
to the nucleus. </p>

<p>[7]   Abnormal PDCD5 expression is associated with many 
diseases. Importantly, PDCD5 expression is significantly 
lower in tumor cells than in normal cells and correlates with 
tumor stage, malignancy, and prognosis. 
[4-9] Low PDCD5 
expression correlates highly with poor prognosis for gastric 
cancer, clear cell kidney cancer, and chondrosarcoma. 
[4] These 
studies indicate that PDCD5 protects against tumorigenesis 
and tumor progression. </p>

<p>Reportedly, PDCD5 protein modulates both apoptotic and 
paraptotic cell death in humans and is proposed to positively 
regulateTip60 histone acetyltransferase and p53 transcription 
factor to promote apoptosis. 
[10-12] PDCD5 can also interact 
with other molecules such as nuclear factor-κB p65 to 
regulate apoptosis via small heterodimer partner protein </p>

<p>[13]   and another protein, cytosolic chaperonin containing tailless 
complex polypeptide one, partly by inhibiting β-tubulin 
folding. </p>

<p>[14]   Recently, Xiao et al. 
[15] revealed that PDCD5 suppresses 
autoimmunity by modulating the forkhead box 
P3 (FOXP3)-regulatory T cell (Treg) axis. PDCD5 may 
thus serve as a guardian of immunological function, and the </p>

<p>Table 2: Relationship between PDCD5 protein expression 
and clinical prognostic factors in patients with epithelial 
ovarian cancer </p>

<p>Patient characteristic* </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>n PDCD5 expression </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Median age in years (range) 
52 (20-78) 
-
Pathology types 
Serous 
84 
0.2780 ± 0.0365 
-
Mucinous 
13 
0.3110 ± 0.0256 
-
Endometrioid 
14 
0.2937 ± 0.0259 
-
Clear cell 
9 
0.2861 ± 0.0364 
-
Others 
7 
0.2747 ± 0.0348 
-
FIGO stage 
Stage I-II 
33 
0.3092 ± 0.0257 
&lt;0.0001 
Stage III-IV 
94 
0.2745 ± 0.0342 
Grades 
1 
16 
0.3247 ± 0.0252 
&lt;0.0001 
2 
45 
0.2870 ± 0.0304 
3 
66 
0.2711 ± 0.0332 
Tumor cytoreduction surgery 
Satisfactory 
74 
0.2910 ± 0.0355 
0.0045 
Unsatisfactory 
53 
0.2730 ± 0.0332 
Lymph node invasion 
Yes 
58 
0.2713 ± 0.0354 
0.0003 
No 
69 
0.2938 ± 0.0326 
Omentum invasion 
Yes 
76 
0.2731 ± 0.0351 
&lt;0.0001 
No 
51 
0.2990 ± 0.0306 
Ascites 
Yes 
92 
0.2770 ± 0.0345 
0.0007 
No 
35 
0.3006 ± 0.0331 
CA-125 (U/ml) 
≤500 
65 
0.2942 ± 0.0347 
0.0004 
&gt;500 
62 
0.2723 ± 0.0333 
*Total n = 127, 
 † Mean ± SD. SD: Standard deviation; 
PDCD5: Programmed cell death 5; FIGO: Federation of Gynecology 
and Obstetrics; CA-125: Cancer antigen-125. </p>

<p>Table 3: Multivariate Cox regression of factors that 
affect survival time of patients with ovarian cancer </p>

<p>Variables 
Wald χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>HR 
P 
95% CI for 
Exp (B) </p>

<p>PDCD5 
30.1692 0.0000 &lt;0.001 
0.00-0.00 
Histology 
0.1612 0.6880 
1.0664 
0.78-1.46 
Stage 
3.7919 0.0515 
2.9112 
0.99-8.54 
Grade 
0.0872 0.7678 
0.9291 
0.57-1.51 
Age 
0.4495 0.5026 
1.0096 
0.98-1.04 
CA-125 levels 
3.8002 0.0512 
1.7799 
1.00-3.18 
Lymph nodes metastasis 
1.0278 0.3107 
1.3231 
0.77-2.27 
Omentum 
2.7299 0.0985 
1.9286 
0.89-4.20 
Ascites 
1.4765 0.2243 
0.6033 
0.27-1.36 
Cytoreductive surgery 
0.4231 0.5154 
0.9086 
0.68-1.21 
PDCD5: Programmed cell death 5; CI: Confidence interval; HR: Hazard 
ratio; CA-125: Cancer antigen-125. </p>

<p>Figure 4: (a) Kaplan-Meier plots of survival times (for all-cause mortality) in patients with ovarian cancer by programmed cell death 5 (PDCD5) 
protein expression. Loss or reduction of PDCD5 expression is associated with poor prognosis in patients with epithelial ovarian cancer. Patients 
with low PDCD5 expression have significantly shorter disease-specific survival than do those with high PDCD5 expression; (b) Spearman's 
analysis of average optical density of PDCD5 protein expression and patients' survival time indicates that PDCD5 expression is highly associated 
with patient survival time (P &lt; 0.0001, R = 0.7139). </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ April 20, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 8 </p>

<p>
PDCD5-FOXP3-Treg axis may be a therapeutic target for 
autoimmunity. These studies indicate the diverse biological 
activities of PDCD5. </p>

<p>Programmed cell death 5 can enhance apoptotic 
response to certain stimuli. Recombinant human PDCD5 
protein (rhPDCD5) has potent antitumor effects against 
chronic myelogenous leukemia K562 cells and may be a 
novel and promising agent for treating chronic myelogenous 
leukemia. 
[16] It was also shown to sensitize chondrosarcoma 
cells to cisplatin-based chemotherapy, by inhibiting cell 
growth and apoptosis both in vitro and in vivo. As rhPDCD5 
apparently induces cleavage of caspase-9, caspase-3, and 
poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase, its co-administration with 
cisplatin is a plausible treatment for chondrosarcoma. </p>

<p>[17]   In a human breast cancer xenograft model, intraperitoneal 
rhPDCD5 administration dramatically improved the 
antitumor effects of paclitaxel, which implies that it could 
be used therapeutically to enhance sensitivity to paclitaxel 
in breast cancer cells. 
[18] PDCD5 is downregulated in 
chondrosarcoma and might be an independent prognostic 
factor for overall survival in chondrosarcoma patients. </p>

<p>[19]   In this study, we examined PDCD5 expression in normal 
ovarian tissue, benign tumors, and ovarian cancers, and the 
relationship between PDCD5 expression and clinical features 
and prognosis. We found PDCD5 was most highly expressed 
in normal ovarian tissue; less expressed in benign tumors and 
had the lowest expression in ovarian cancer tissue. PDCD5 
expression was also inversely correlated with FIGO scores. 
Higher PDCD5 expression was associated with longer 
survival times for ovarian cancer patients, which accords 
with the results of Zhang et al. </p>

<p>[9]   In conclusion, programmed cell death 5 expression is 
reduced in ovarian cancer and correlates negatively with 
survival time. Our data indicate that low PDCD5 expression 
decreases apoptosis in ovarian cancer, thus promoting a poor 
prognosis. These results imply that PDCD5 could both offer 
a means of monitoring patient prognosis and be developed 
on the basis of an anticancer therapy. </p>

<p>AcknowledgMents </p>

<p>The authors are very grateful to Zhi-Jun Du for her kind linguistic 
advice during the preparation of this manuscript. We would also 
like to thank Professors Ying-Yu Chen and Da-Long Ma of Peking 
University Health Science Center for providing the anti-PDCD5 
antibody. </p>

<p>references </p>



<p>Received: 16-01-2015 Edited by: Li-Min Chen 
How to cite this article: Gao L, Ye X, Ma RQ, Cheng HY, Han HJ, 
Cui H, Wei LH, Chang XH. Low Programmed Cell Death 5 Expression 
is a Prognostic Factor in Ovarian Cancer. Chin Med J 2015;128:1084-90. </p>

<p>Source of Support: This work was supported by a grant from 
the "863" National High Technology and Development Program 
(No. 2012AA02A507). Conflict of Interest: None declared. </p>

</text></tei>