<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4388951" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) which is outlined as the most 
common cause of polyarthritis has increasingly affected people 
through the last decade [1]. Despite of a remarkable increase 
in prevalence of this disease in the United States [2], the 
growing incidence rate of RA in the other developing countries 
such as Iran has been noticeable as one of the major challenges 
for public health [3]. 
Cardiovascular diseases and dislipidemia are considered as 
the leading causes involved in the mortality of RA [4,5]. There 
are several lines of evidence imply an atherogenic lipid profile 
in patients with rheumatoid arthritis [4,6,7]. In accordance of 
their findings, high levels of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol </p>

<p>(LDL-C), total cholesterol and low level of high-density lipoprotein 
cholesterol (HDL-C) are correlated with the disease activity [4]. 
It is supposed that increased levels of pro-inflammatory 
mediators like TNFα and CRP may possibly account for this 
atherogenic lipid profile [4]. Thus, trying to relieve inflammation 
in inflammatory disorders such as RA might lead to a great 
improvement of lipid profile. 
Among dietary factors, vitamin K has been recently considered 
to have an important role in controlling inflammation and 
consequently in cardiovascular risk factors [1]. Previous studies 
investigating the effect of vitamin K on inflammation found it 
as a new immunomodulating factor [8,9]. 
Furthermore, vitamin K is thought to have a possible direct 
function in cardioprotection [10]. This putative effect of vitamin </p>

<p> § Corresponding Author: Neda Ghamarzad Shishavan, Tel. 98-41-1336-2117, Fax. 98-41-1334-0634, Email. Ghamarzad.n@gmail.com </p>

<p>Received: April 9, 2014, Revised: June 2, 2014, Accepted: June 3, 2014 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Sousan Kolahi et al. </p>



<p>K in atherosclerosis is explained through a few pathways. 
Calcification of soft tissues and consequently vessel rupture also 
inhibition of fat deposition in marrow cells are blocked in 
presence of sufficient amount of vitamin K [10,11]. 
Former studies reported a favorable effect of vitamin K on 
plasma total cholesterol, lipid peroxidation and ester-cholesterol 
deposition in the aorta of hypercholesterolemic rabbits [12]. 
These results were in keeping with those obtained in other 
investigations in rats and patients on continuous ambulatory 
peritoneal dialysis which confirmed a lipid lowering effect of 
vitamin K [11,13]. However, Kristensen et al. [14] have not found 
similar results in postmenopausal women and surprisingly 
reported undesirable effects of vitamin K on blood lipids. 
We hypothesized that vitamin K supplementation might have 
lipid lowering effects in patients with RA. Therefore, regarding 
this discrepancy in previous findings and high prevalence of 
mortality from rheumatoid arthritis due to cardiovascular risk factors, 
we aimed to examine the effects of vitamin K1 on lipid profile 
after 8 weeks intervention in women with rheumatoid arthritis. </p>

<p>SUBJECTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study population 
This randomized, double blind, placebo controlled trial was 
conducted on sixty four eligible women with RA accepting to 
participate. Patients were recruited from the outpatient rheuma-
tology clinic of Imam Reza Hospital, Tabriz, Iran, July to 
December 2012. 
Study eligibility criteria included being 20-50 years, docume-
ntation of (RA) regarding to the American College of Rheuma-
tology (ACR, 2010) classification for RA [15] which is diagnosed 
by rheumatology specialist, absence of chronic diseases, i.e., 
diabetes, liver or kidney disorders, malabsorption and cardiova-
scular disease, thyroid disorders, coagulation abnormality, patients 
with prothrombin time &lt; 10s, hyperprolactinemia, Cushing' 
syndrome, super obesity (Body Mass Index &gt; 40), cancer, high 
blood pressure, not taking hormonal therapy, contraceptive 
pills, antibiotics, antiepileptic drugs or other dietary supplements 
during the past 3 months. Being pregnant, lactate, postme-
nopause, being in severe stage of rheumatoid arthritis (Disease 
Activity Score-28 &gt; 5.1), smoking, lifestyle change and drug 
compliance less than 75% were the study exclusion criteria. </p>

<p>Study protocol 
List of patients with rheumatoid arthritis who referred to 
rheumatology clinic of Imam Reza Hospital, Tabriz, Iran, enabled 
us to have a preliminary screening by telephone and following 
it an orientation meeting was held for the volunteers. The 
meeting provided a comprehensive description about the 
purpose and protocol of study. Then, the written consent form 
was filled out by the participants. The demographic charac-
teristics and anthropometric measurements were also obtained. </p>

<p>Anthropometric measurements 
Weight (to the nearest 0.1 kg) and height (to the nearest 0.5 
cm) were measured in a standard position using a scale (Seca, 
Germany) and a wall-meter respectively. Finally, body mass 
index (BMI) was calculated for each patient with the usual </p>

<p>formula: weight (kg) / height 
2 (m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). </p>

<p>Assessment of anxiety level 
Given an important role of anxiety in exacerbation of symptoms 
in RA, the participants᾽ anxiety status was measured by the 
State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI-Y) scale before intervention. 
This standard scale has two 20-question sections. The first part 
is designed to assay the state anxiety which evaluates the 
current state of anxiety and their feeling at the moment and 
the second part focuses on the trait anxiety which includes 
general and stable states of anxiety. All of these data were 
collected by face to face interview. Finally patients were 
classified as having no or minimum, low, intermediate or severe 
state and trait anxiety regarding their scores from STAI-Y 
questionnaires [16]. </p>

<p>Assessment of physical activity level 
Short International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) was 
used to evaluate participants᾽ physical activity level (low, moderate 
and high). This questionnaire includes 7 questions and its 
validity and reliability has been investigated in previous studies 
[17,18]. Physical activity of each subject was measured considering 
the energy requirements defined in METS (metabolic equivalent). 
These following values are used for the analysis of IPAQ data: 
walking = 3.3 METs, moderate physical activity = 4.0 METs and 
vigorous physical activity = 8.0 METs. After calculation Met-
minutes/week (= MET level × minutes of activity/day × days per 
week), participants were classified in three groups (low, 
moderate and high physical Activity). High intensity activity was 
considered for vigorous activity on at least 3 days of a week, 
with at least 1500 MET-minutes/week or at least five days of 
combination of walking, moderate or vigorous intensity activities 
with at least 3000 MET-minutes/week. Moderate intensity 
activity was considered for five or more days of any combi-
nation of walking, moderate-intensity and vigorous intensity 
activities achieving of at least 600 MET-minutes/week and if no 
activity was reported or it wasn't enough to consider in two 
mentioned classes, it was classified as low physical activity [19]. </p>

<p>Assessment of disease activity score 
Disease Activity Score (DAS-28) is a quantitative measure to 
describe patient status in rheumatic diseases was evaluated by 
rheumatology specialist through the formula with 3 variables 
[DAS = 0.56 (tender joint count) 
2 + 0.28 (swollen joint count) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ 0.36 × Ln (CRP + 1) × 1.10 + 1.15]. DAS-28 scores represent 
remission (&lt; 2.6), mild (&lt; 3.2), moderate (&lt; 5.1) and severe (&gt; 
5.1) disease activity [20]. </p>

<p>Assessment of nutritional status 
Participants' nutritional status was assayed by a three-day 
food records. Subjects were advised to record all foods and 
beverages consumed throughout the day for two days of the 
week and one day of the weekend. According to the guideline 
of food portion size [21], amount of each dietary item they 
consumed was expressed in gram. Then these data were analyzed 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Nutritionist</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">IV</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">First Databank</rs>, San Bruno, CA, 
USA) modified for Iranian foods and daily intakes of energy and 
some nutrients were obtained. </p>



<p>Effects of phylloquinone in rheumatoid arthritis </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Flow chart of the study </p>

<p>Sample size and intervention 
To determine the sample size considering a percent change 
of 15% in primary outcome of total cholesterol and based on 
information obtained from a pilot study of size 5 and utilizing 
the Pocock formula it was estimated to be 24 per group to 
achieve 95% confidence interval and a power of 80%. Given 
dropout rate of 30% the sample size increased to 32 in each group. 
Participants were randomly assigned to one of the two 
groups using four-factor Randomized Block Design (RBD in 
sequentially numbered containers) with allocation ratio 1:1. In 
each block controls were matched to cases on available data, 
i.e., age, the place of residence (city or rural) and severity of 
the disease (according to DAS-28: remission, mild and moderate). 
Vitamin K1 or placebo pills were given to each subject. 
Experimental group received a daily chewable pill of 10 mg 
phylloquinone (manufactured by Minoo Company, Iran) for 8 
weeks. The dosage of vitamin K was used in other clinical trials 
was in various ranges (from microgram to milligram) and it 
seems there is not enough evidence for optimum doses of 
vitamin K. Even 45 mg/day of vitamin K2 was recently used in 
rheumatoid arthritis patients focusing its anti-inflammatory 
effects [22]. In addition to using different high doses in past 
researches [22-24] and safety of high doses of vitamin K [25], 
given the only available dosage in Iran, we considered to use 
10 mg/day pills of vitamin K1. 
Control group received similar amounts of mannitol as the 
placebo which was specially designed for this study (prepared 
in Faculty of Pharmacy, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, 
Iran). Both of the two supplements had similar taste and 
appearance and were provided to the volunteers in similar 
boxes. Participants, caregivers and those assessing the outcomes 
were blinded to group. Patients in each group were instructed 
to consume one pill daily after lunch. All participants were asked 
to return the boxes to the research team at the end of 
intervention, to calculate compliance of drug for each subject. 
The participants received a weekly phone call for monitoring 
the supplements consumption according to the protocol and 
being aware of probable side effects of the pills. </p>

<p>Biochemical measurements 
Blood samples (7 ml) were collected at baseline and at the 
end of trial after an overnight fasting. Then, the samples were 
centrifuged at 3,000 rpm for 15 min (Beckman Avanti J-25; 
Beckman Coulter, Brea, CA) at room temperature. Then, the 
serums were frozen in -70°C until further analysis. However, 
prothrombin time test (PT test) was immediately conducted on 
the day of sampling. </p>

<p>Assessment of prothrombin time and lipid profile 
In order to screening patients with coagulation abnormalities, 
prothrombin time was measured for all the participants before 
the trial. 2-3 cc of blood samples in citrated tubes were 
centrifuged (at 3,000 rpm for 20 min). Then reagent containing 
phospholipids (thromboplastin) and CaCl2 (0.025M) added to 
the plasma tubes. The time required for clot formation is 
measured by stopwatch (manual method). Time was reported 
in seconds (prothrombin time). Laboratory reference range 
value was considered 10-13.5 seconds. Patients who had normal </p>

<p>PT or a higher value participated in the study. 
Serum levels of total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoprotein 
(HDL) and triglyceride (TG) were assayed by enzymatic method 
(Pars azmoon Kit, Iran). Serum level of low-density lipoprotein 
(LDL) was determined by Friedewald formula: LDL = TC-HDL-
TG/5.0 (mg/dL) [26]. 
Medical Ethical Committee of Tabriz University of Medical 
Science approved this study and the registration number of this 
trial in Iranian Registry of Clinical Trials (IRCT) was www.irct.ir/ 
IRCT201205203140N4. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All analyses were performed based on Intention To Treat 
principle. The Statistical <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> software program (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 11.5</rs>; 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL) was used for all the statistical analyses. 
The data were checked for normality using Kolmogorov-
Smirnov test. Presentation of data was as mean (standard 
deviation), median (percentile 25, percentile 75) and frequency 
(percentage). Baseline indices were compared in vitamin K 
group versus placebo group to examine if the randomization 
was appropriate. Independent sample-t test, Mann-Whitney U 
test and Fisher exact test were used to compare baseline values 
between two groups. In order to determination the effects of 
treatment at the end of intervention, relevant confounders .i.e; 
duration of RA, energy intake, weight, prothrombin time and 
baseline values were adjusted (ANCOVA test). 
Moreover, in order to assay differences between before and 
after intervention within groups, Paired sample-t test, Wilcoxon 
Signed Ranks and Sign test were used [27-29]. Statistical 
significance was set at P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Baseline characteristics 
Of sixty four participants assigned to the trial, fifty eight 
patients completed the eight-week follow up (n = 30 in 
phylloquinone group and n = 28 in placebo group). No 
significant side effect in the two study groups was detected. </p>

<p>Sousan Kolahi et al. </p>



<p>Variables 
Intervention group 
(n = 30) </p>

<p>Placebo group 
(n = 28) 
P-value </p>

<p>Energy (kcal) </p>

<p>Baseline 
2,062.7 ± 476.65 
2,135.36 ± 556.92 
0.595 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
2,056.9 ± 609.71 
2,086.92 ± 569.92 
0.848 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Total fat (g) </p>

<p>Baseline 
77.8 ± 27.14 
86.1 ± 31.85 
0.289 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
73.12 ± 36.81 
85.56 ± 32.34 
0.35 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Cholesterol (mg) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Baseline 
180.35 (103.28,256.38) 168.35 (104.6,276.02) 0.95 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
164.8 (102.6,262.75) 163.65 (100.54,273.18) 0.663 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Saturated fatty acids (g) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Baseline 
15.91 (10.98,22.12) 
14.84 (13.28,20.67) 
0.84 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
14 (10.92,20.26) 
17.29 (12.84,24.61) 
0.585 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Monounsaturated fatty acids (g) </p>

<p>Baseline 
20. 40 ± 12.8 
29.94 ± 11.79 
0.074 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
22.38 ± 10.85 
30.75 ± 14.47 
0.568 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Polyunsaturated fatty acids (g) </p>

<p>Baseline 
20.67 ± 7.42 
23.92 ± 9.79 
0.158 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
18.9 ± 6.11 
24.59 ± 10.87 
0.759 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Vitamin K (μg) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Baseline 
48.14 (32.77,64.15) 
57.73 (43.45,89.9) 
0.106 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
34.39 (21.84,52.26) 
50.46 (23.05,75.76) 
0.086 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean ± SD for normally distributed variables, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>median 
(percentile 25, percentile 75) for non normally distributed variables. 
1) Compare baseline characteristics between two groups (Mann-Whitney U test for 
non normally distributed variables and Independent-sample t-test for normally 
distributed variables). 
2) Final comparison after intervention period; adjusted for confounders .i.e; duration 
of RA, energy intake, weight, PT and baseline values (ANCOVA). </p>

<p>Table 2. Daily dietary intakes in women with RA at baseline and after 8 weeks 
in both groups </p>

<p>Variables 
Intervention group 
(n = 30) </p>

<p>Placebo group 
(n = 28) 
P-value </p>

<p>Total cholesterol (mg/dl) </p>

<p>Baseline 
170.27 ± 35.66 
167.96 ± 30.94 
0.799 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
179.53 ± 34.55 
169 ± 32.22 
0.174 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>Triglyceride (mg/dl) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Baseline 
88 (64,116) 
86 (67.25,121.5) 
0.6 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
105 (82,124) 
89 (76.25,116.25) 
0.897 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>HDL (mg/dl) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Baseline 
49.5 (45,56.25) 
56.25 (44.62,64.5) 
0.192 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
51 (42.75,60) 
49.5 (42,60) 
0.622 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>LDL (mg/dl) </p>

<p>Baseline 
98.3 ± 35.21 
85.06 ± 34.81 
0.167 </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>After 8 weeks 
106.49 ± 32.58 
91.78 ± 27.58 
0.135 </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>LDL-C, Low Density Lipoprotein; HDL-C, High Density Lipoprotein. 
Data are presented as mean ± SD for normally distributed variables, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>median 
(percentile 25, percentile 75) for non normally distributed variables. 
1) Baseline vitamin K group vs. baseline placebo group (Independent-sample t-test 
for normally distributed variables and Mann-Whitney U for non normally distributed 
variables). 
2) Final comparison after treatment with vitamin K or placebo; adjusted for 
confounders .i.e; duration of RA, energy intake, weight, PT and baseline values 
(ANCOVA). </p>

<p>Table 3. Lipid profile and Lipid ratios in women with RA at baseline and after 
8 weeks in both groups </p>

<p>Variables 
Intervention group 
(n = 30) </p>

<p>Placebo group 
(n = 28) 
P-value </p>

<p>1) </p>

<p>Age (yrs) 
37.97 ± 8.22 
39.46 ± 8.22 
0.491 </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
71.63 ± 13.79 
70.39 ± 13.58 
0.731 </p>

<p>Height (cm) 
156.05 ± 7.163 
155.64 ± 7.09 
0.829 </p>

<p>BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>2) </p>

<p>29.44 ± 5.27 
29.26 ± 6.24 
0.91 </p>

<p>Disease duration (yrs) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>3 (1.5,8.5) 
7 (4,10.57) 
0.006 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Conventional therapy </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Prednisolone 
30 (100%) 
27 (96.4%) 
0.483 </p>

<p>Methotrexate 
26 (86.7%) 
27 (96.4%) 
0.354 </p>

<p>Chloroquine 
23 (76.7%) 
19 (67.9%) 
0.561 </p>

<p>Physical activity </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.604 </p>

<p>Low 
22 (73.3%) 
22 (78.6%) </p>

<p>Moderate 
7 (23.3%) 
6 (21.4%) </p>

<p>High 
1 (3.3%) 
0 (0%) </p>

<p>State anxiety </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.992 </p>

<p>Not at all 
14 (46.7%) 
14 (50.0%) </p>

<p>Low 
13 (43.3%) 
11 (39.3%) </p>

<p>Intermediate 
2 (6.7%) 
2 (7.1%) </p>

<p>Very much 
1 (3.3%) 
1 (3.6%) </p>

<p>Trait anxiety </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.877 </p>

<p>Not at all 
8 (26.7%) 
9 (32.1%) </p>

<p>Low 
12 (40.0%) 
9 (32.1%) </p>

<p>Intermediate 
8 (26.7%) 
7 (25%) </p>

<p>Very much 
2 (6.6%) 
3 (10.8%) </p>

<p>Prothrombin time (second) 
12.76 ± 0.67 
12.89 ± 0.94 
0.56 </p>

<p>DAS-28 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>1.74 (1.15,2.59) 
2.26 (1.46,2.87) 
0.194 
Data are presented as mean ± SD for normally distributed variables, 
 † frequency 
(percent) for categorical variables and 
 ‡ median (percentile 25, percentile 75) for 
non normally distributed variables. 
1) Compare baseline characteristics between two groups (Independent-sample t-test 
for normally distributed variables, Fisher exact tests for categorical variables and 
Mann-Whitney U test for non normally distributed variables). 
2) BMI, body mass index; DAS-28, Disease Activity Score 28. 
* Significant difference between groups (P &lt; 0.05) </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of RA patients at baseline in both groups </p>

<p>Only one patient who had experienced a slight heartburn at 
the beginning of intervention was excluded from the study. The 
diagram of study has been presented in Fig. 1. 
Baseline characteristics in vitamin K and placebo groups are 
shown in Table 1. No significant differences were observed in 
baseline characteristics between two groups with regards to 
age, BMI, DAS-28, prothrombin time, physical activity and stress 
level (P &gt; 0.05). The patients᾽ medications were routine drugs 
in RA treatment maintained as the same drug and dosage 
throughout the clinical trial period. No one consumed lipid 
lowering drugs during the study period. Compliance to the 
supplements provided to participants in this study was 
calculated through dividing the number of consumed pills by 
the total number of supplied pills to each subject. The 
compliance estimated was on average 92% in vitamin K group 
and 87% in placebo group which wasn't significantly different 
between two groups (P = 0.206). </p>

<p>Dietary intakes before and after intervention period 
Regarding Table 2 daily dietary intakes showed no significant 
differences between two groups before and after intervention 
(P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Lipid profile before and after intervention period 
Serum levels of lipid related markers such as total cholesterol 
(TC), high-density lipoprotein (HDL), low-density lipoprotein </p>



<p>Effects of phylloquinone in rheumatoid arthritis </p>

<p>(LDL) and triglyceride (TG) in both groups before and after 
intervention are presented in Table 3. Neither at beginning nor 
at the end of intervention the lipid related markers had 
significant differences between two groups. Even after adjusting 
for some confounders such as duration of RA, energy intake, 
weight, prothrombin time and baseline values, results of 
analysis of covariance did not show any significant differences 
in the levels of these markers between two groups at the end 
of the study (P &gt; 0.05). Although, given the differences (with 
95% confidence interval), surprisingly we noticed a worse serum 
lipid profile at the end of intervention in both groups that 
wasn't significantly different between before and after interve-
ntion values within groups (P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The present study showed that phylloquinone supplementa-
tion at dose of 10 mg per day for 8 weeks did not lead to any 
significant changes in lipids profile in women with rheumatoid 
arthritis. A few studies investigating the effects of vitamin K 
on lipid related markers to date reported conflicting results. 
The study conducted by Kawashima et al. [12] in hyperchole-
sterolemic rabbits showed that vitamin K2 significantly decreased 
plasma total cholesterol, lipid peroxidation and ester-cholesterol 
deposition in the aortas of rabbits. Another experimental study 
in rats indicated a significant reduction in serum triglyceride 
levels following vitamin K1 and K2 rich diets (600 mg/kg/day). 
In their study the reduction in triglycerides level in phyllo-
quinone group was 48% versus 29% in menaquinone group 
compared with the control. These data support a presumptive 
favorable effect of vitamin K1 on lipid profile [11]. Human 
investigations in the literature in this field are scanty. One study 
which conducted in dialysis patients who had osteoporosis due 
to secondary hyperparathyroidism, found a similar results to the 
previous experimental researches. Their study showed that 
administration of daily 45 mg MK-4, reduced serum total cholesterol 
significantly, without influencing triglyceride and low-density 
lipoprotein serum levels [13]. In contrast to aforementioned 
findings, we observed no significant lipid lowering effect of 
phylloquinone. Surprisingly, we found a little non significant 
increase in the levels of blood lipids after intervention period 
in both groups. In support of our findings, a study by Kristensen 
et al. [14] has reported that six weeks phylloquinone supple-
mentation in postmenopausal women not only didn't reach an 
improvement in lipid profile but also it induced an unfavorable 
effect on lipid profile. Inefficiency of food frequency question-
naire in exact determination of phylloquinone intake, not 
considering the baseline serum levels of lipid related markers 
and remarkable dropouts through the study were declared as 
explanations of these surprising findings [14]. However, a 
growing body of documents supports a pivotal role of vitamin 
K in improvement of lipid profile and coronary heart disease, 
little information is available about the mechanisms of this 
function. Understanding the mechanisms might explain these 
discrepant data. In this regard, several cell pathways which 
vitamin K influences to alter serum lipid related markers are 
proposed. Some certain proteins which are necessary for 
vascular tissue health are activated via vitamin K-dependant </p>

<p>gamma-carboxylation process. Among these proteins, carboxy-
lated form of matrix Gla-protein (MGP) prevents the infiltration 
of calcium into the vascular tissues. Thus, calcification of soft 
tissues may not happen in presence of vitamin K [10]. 
Likewise, in the study by Takeuchi et al. [30] it's been found 
that inhibition of adipocytes formation and fat deposition were 
induced only by vitamin K2 (MK-4) administration in mouse 
bone marrow cell cultures. Whereas, Sogabe et al. [11] 
demonstrated significant reductions in weights of total fat and 
visceral fat in both groups of rats fed by vitamin K1 and K2 
rich diets. It has been thought that there are some functional 
differences between phylloquinone and menaquinones, in 
results of their structural differences including redox properties 
or functions of their side chains and also differences in the 
tissue-specific utilization of the various forms of vitamin K that 
cause inconsistent results [14]. 
One possible explanation is that the optimum dose of vitamin 
K for its beneficial effect on lipid profile has not been defined 
yet. Thus, the dosage chosen in our trial may not be proper 
and it could influence phylloquinone᾽s function. A number of 
investigators suggest that various dosage of vitamin K1 may 
change its important and useful action in controlling inflammation 
[31] and consequently in improvement of blood lipids. 
In addition, the intervention period may have been insufficient 
to reach any significant change in lipid profile. Furthermore, 
consumption of routine drugs in controlling RA results in 
remission in our study subjects (according to DAS-28 in two 
groups) which may justify these findings. 
There are several strengths and limitations in our study. One 
of the strengths of present study was the design of study as 
randomized, double-blinded placebo-controlled trial. Moreover, 
ideal randomization was conducted in the study and two 
groups were matched in plenty of variables at the beginning 
of the intervention such as disease severity, physical activity, 
anxiety level, etc. This study as a first study assessed dietary 
intakes, anxiety level and physical activity to control their 
probable effects on blood lipids through the intervention 
period. Besides, all the participants had high compliance of drug 
and given to exclusion criteria subjects with low adherence in 
each group were excluded from the study. 
The limitation of this intervention was confining the trail to 
a special group of patients with rheumatoid arthritis, and it 
would be better to repeat this study in a big target population 
such as involving postmenopausal women with RA, patients in 
severe stage of the disease (DAS28 &gt; 5.1), and patients with 
vitamin K deficiency. On the other hand, as aforementioned 
the probable role of vitamin K might appear obviously at various 
dosages or after long-term intervention or in larger sample size. 
In conclusion, phylloquinone supplementation (10 mg/day) 
did not alter serum lipid profile in women with RA after eight 
weeks. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>We wish to thank Nutrition Research Center of Tabriz 
University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran which supported 
present research grant; and also we are thankful to women who 
participated in the study. This article was written based on the </p>

<p>Sousan Kolahi et al. </p>



<p>data from MS thesis of nutrition registered in Tabriz University 
of Medical Science under A/138 number. </p>



</text></tei>