<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4654549" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: The molecular mechanisms underlying stress-induced depression have not been 
fully outlined. Hence, the current study aimed at testing the link between behavioral changes 
in chronic mild stress (CMS) model and changes in hippocampal energy metabolism and the 
role of paroxetine (PAROX) in ameliorating these changes. Male Wistar rats were divided into 
three groups: vehicle control, CMS-exposed rats, and CMS-exposed rats receiving PAROX 
(10 mg/kg/day intraperitoneally). Sucrose preference, open-field, and forced swimming tests 
were carried out. Corticosterone (CORT) was measured in serum, while adenosine triphosphate 
and its metabolites, cytosolic cytochrome-c (Cyt-c), caspase-3 (Casp-3), as well as nitric oxide 
metabolites (NOx) were measured in hippocampal tissue homogenates. CMS-exposed rats 
showed a decrease in sucrose preference as well as body weight compared to control, which 
was reversed by PAROX. The latter further ameliorated the CMS-induced elevation of CORT 
in serum (91.71±1.77 ng/mL vs 124.5±4.44 ng/mL, P0.001) as well as the changes in adenos-
ine triphosphate/adenosine diphosphate (3.76±0.02 nmol/mg protein vs 1.07±0.01 nmol/mg 
protein, P0.001). Furthermore, PAROX reduced the expression of Cyt-c and Casp-3, as well as 
restoring NOx levels. This study highlights the role of PAROX in reversing depressive behavior 
associated with stress-induced apoptosis and changes in hippocampal energy metabolism in 
the CMS model of depression. 
Depression is the leading cause of disability worldwide. 
1 Stressful life events are 
pivotal players in the incidence of depression, especially in individuals with a genetic 
predisposition. 
2,3 In support of the role of stress in the incidence of depression, it has 
been reported that, in 70%-80% of the cases, the onset of the first episode of depres-
sion is preceded by a severe life event. 
4 It is proposed that stress induces structural 
remodeling in the hippocampal formation, including atrophy, neuronal loss, and 
decreased neurogenesis as well as apoptosis, 
5-7 which constitutes a newly emerging 
concept perceiving major depressive disorder (MDD) as a complex illness, associated 
with progressive morphological brain changes rather than change in the neurotrans-
mitter balance per se. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>In an elegant approach to simulate some of the environmental stressors culminating 
in the induction of MDD, Willner et al 
9,10 adopted a modification of the experimental 
stress models of depression, namely the chronic mild stress (CMS) battery. In this 
battery, rats were exposed to a variety of mild and unpredictable stressors for a period </p>

<p>correspondence: ahmed M abdel-tawab 
Department of Pharmacology, Faculty 
of Medicine, ain shams University, 
abbassia 11566, cairo, egypt 
email amtawab@med.asu.edu.eg </p>

<p>Noha N Nassar 
Department of Pharmacology, 
Faculty of Pharmacy, cairo University, 
cairo, egypt 
email nnagah@yahoo.com </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 
13 November 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2888 </p>

<p>Khedr et al </p>

<p>of weeks. 
11 A major token of this model is anhedonia, the 
decreased responsiveness to pleasurable stimuli, thus simu-
lating that seen in MDD in humans. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Notably, the hippocampus, a highly plastic stress-sensitive 
region, is not only a crucial player in learning and memory 
but also pivotal for the regulation of the hypothalamic-
pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis. Noteworthy, reduced volume 
of this brain region has been reported in numerous clinical 
and preclinical studies of hippocampal volume changes in 
depression, 
7,12 which lends further evidence of the central 
involvement of the hippocampus in regulating the central 
response to stress and eventually depression. In response to 
stress, the brain mounts a neuroendocrine stress response 
through the HPA axis, triggering behavioral, endocrine, and 
metabolic cascades. 
13,14 Noteworthy, elevated glucocorticoid 
(GC) has been reported to underlie such hippocampal changes. 
Indeed, impaired glucocorticoid receptors (GRs) function has 
been suggested to be associated with HPA axis hyperactivity 
in depression. 
15,16 Strenuous stress may induce apoptosis via 
genomic and non-genomic actions of the elevated GC 
17 as 
well as affecting mitochondrial functions. 
17,18 In addition to 
their critical role in energy production, 
19 mitochondria are 
pivotal in apoptosis signaling. 
20 Ample evidence associates 
neuroendocrine alterations and changes in mitochondrial sig-
naling to the vicious cascades of immune cell activation and 
reactive oxygen species formation in depressive disorders. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Certainly, increased cytokine levels have been linked to signs 
of marked depressive illness. 
21 Furthermore, increasing evi-
dence suggests that GC-induced apoptosis plays a key role in 
the induction of hippocampal neuronal damage. 
22-24 In contrast 
to the effects of stress, chronic use of several classes of antide-
pressants including selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors had 
shown its ability to protect against stress-induced apoptosis </p>

<p>25,26 </p>

<p>and to increase neurogenesis. </p>

<p>27-29 </p>

<p>Although the pathophysiology of depression is still 
scantily understood, some studies have demonstrated that 
deficiencies in energy metabolism may be involved. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Hence, the current investigation aimed at characterizing the 
mechanism(s) underpinning the relation between depres-
sion and changes in hippocampal energy metabolism and 
the utility of paroxetine (PAROX), a clinically effective 
antidepressant drug, in rectifying such changes. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
animals </p>

<p>Twenty-nine male Wistar rats (National Research Center 
Laboratory, Cairo, Egypt), weighing 200±50 g, were used 
for the experimental procedures. Rats were allowed at least 
2 weeks to acclimatize. Animals were housed individually and </p>

<p>received standard pellet rat chow (Meladco Feed Company, 
El Obour, Egypt) and tap water ad libitum for the duration 
of the experiments, unless otherwise recommended by the 
study protocol. Temperature was maintained at 22°C±2°C, 
and the light/dark cycle was held at 12 hours:12 hours with 
lights on at 5 am. All handling procedures were performed by 
the same investigator throughout the study. Animal handling 
and experimental protocols were approved by the Research 
Ethical Committee of the Faculty of Pharmacy, Cairo Uni-
versity (Cairo, Egypt), and comply with the Guide for the 
Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>experimental design </p>

<p>Training for sucrose solution intake and groups 
distribution </p>

<p>After 2 weeks of initial habituation to the laboratory conditions, 
animals were trained for 48 hours to drink 2% (w/v) sucrose 
(Fluka Chemical Co., Buchs, Switzerland) solution before 
introducing the CMS battery. Bottles were regularly checked to 
ensure non-leakage. Subsequently, animals received a series of 
four sucrose preference tests (SPTs). Following the last train-
ing session, three baseline SPTs were performed, separated by 
at least 3 days, and the results were averaged, to determine the 
basal sucrose intake before the start of the CMS battery. 
Following initial measurement of sucrose preference, 
animals (n=30) were divided into two sets with similar aver-
age sucrose preference. The first set (n=20; during the course 
of the experiment, there was one incidence of mortality in 
the CMS group, which reduced the number of animals in 
this group to nine) was exposed to CMS battery (Table 1), 
while the second set (n=10) served as vehicle control. After 
7 weeks of CMS exposure, the first set (CMS-exposed rats) 
was randomly allocated into another two subsets, namely 
(i) CMS group (n=9) receiving daily intraperitoneal (ip) 
vehicle injection (two saline:three dimethylsulfoxide) and 
(ii) PAROX group (n=10; Eva Pharmaceuticals, Cairo, 
Egypt) receiving ip 10 mg/kg PAROX daily (Figure 1). </p>

<p>32-34 </p>

<p>application of the cMs battery </p>

<p>Rats were exposed to two to five mild stressors per day 
for 11 weeks, given that no more than three mild stresses 
were applied at a time (Table 1). Stressors were presented 
in a semi-random sequence over the course of a week and 
repeated in successive weeks, with slight shifting between 
the days. </p>

<p>Measurements </p>

<p>All the 29 animals were used for both behavioral and bio-
chemical testing. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2889 </p>

<p>Paroxetine and hippocampal energy changes in cMs </p>

<p>Behavioral testing </p>

<p>All behavioral tests were done at least 24 hours after the 
last stressor at the end of experimental period. SPT was 
done weekly. The sequence of applying behavioral tests was 
open-field test (OFT), and then forced swimming test (FST) 
preceded by FST training on the previous day. Animals were </p>

<p>sacrificed the next day in the morning, namely 48 hours after 
the application of the last stressor. </p>

<p>sucrose preference test 
Sucrose preference was measured in all the 29 animals, by 
calculating the reduction in the consumption of sucrose </p>

<p>Table 1 schedule of stressors application during a period of 1 week </p>

<p>Day 
Light cycle 
Dark cycle </p>

<p>Duration 
Stressor 
Duration 
Stressor </p>

<p>saturday 
9 am-5 pm 
stroboscopic light 
5 pm-9 am 
cage tilting 
Foreign body 
sunday 
9 am-5 pm 
Pairing 
5 pm-9 am 
soiling the cage 
Noise 
cold restraint (30 minutes) 
Monday 
5 am-5 pm 
Food-water deprivation 
5 pm-9 am 
Water deprivation 
soiling of the cage 
Tuesday 
9 am-5 pm 
stroboscopic light 
5 pm-9 am 
cage tilting 
Foreign body 
Foreign body 
9 am-11 am 
empty bottles 
Wednesday 
9 am-5 pm 
Pairing 
5 pm-9 am 
Food-water 
deprivation 
Noise 
cold restraint (30 minutes) 
Thursday 
9 am-5 pm 
stroboscopic light 
5 pm-9 am 
reversed light/ 
dark cycle 
Foreign body 
9 am-11 am 
restricted food 
Friday 
continuous illumination </p>

<p>Notes: The above sequence was adopted from weeks 1-3. starting from week 3, slight variation in the stressors application was adopted to avoid habituation. saturday and 
sunday light cycle stressors were shifted every other week. Tuesday and Wednesday light cycle stressors were also shifted every other week except for the empty bottle 
stressor which was always on Tuesday. restraint stress was applied by placing the animals in a 25 cm ×7 cm plastic bottle, and fixing it with plaster tape on the outside so that 
the animal was unable to move; there was a 1 cm hole at one far end for breathing (ely et al). </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>• 
• </p>

<p>Figure 1 Timeline utilized in the current study showing order of stress induction and treatment administration. 
Notes: i, acclimatization; ii, application of stress; iii, continuing application of stress in addition to one of the groups administered the ParOX drug (dose 10 mg/kg/day). 
Weeks shown in squares indicate certain events were monitored at those weeks: week 0, start of the study, after the acclimatization; week 7, the week when the first 
determinations for glucocorticoids were determined to ascertain the induction of stress; week 12, the end of the study experiments. 
Abbreviations: cMs, chronic mild stress; DMsO, dimethylsulfoxide; FsT, forced swimming test; ParOX, paroxetine; sPT, sucrose preference test. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2890 </p>

<p>Khedr et al </p>

<p>solution or preference as an indicator of anhedonia. SPT was 
scheduled at the beginning of the dark cycle. 
35 After a 16-hour 
period of food and water deprivation, animals were presented 
simultaneously with two pre-weighed bottles, one bottle 
containing sucrose (2%) and the other containing water, 
for a period of 30 minutes. The position of the two bottles 
(right/left) was varied randomly from trial to trial, during 
the training period, and also on the weekly test. Bottles were 
weighed again after the test to calculate amount consumed 
from each solution. Sucrose preference was calculated from 
the following formula: </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>Sucrose 
preference </p>

<p>Sucrose intake (g) 
Sucrose intake (g) Wat 
= 
+ 
e er intake (g) 
×100 </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>Forced swimming test 
After 11 weeks of stress, FST was measured in all the 
29 animals according to Porsolt et al. 
37 Animal behavior 
was recorded by a video camera, and immobility time was 
measured with a stopwatch. The FST involves immersion 
of animals in a cylinder full of water (22.5 cm ×60 cm) 
containing 35 cm of water maintained at 25°C. On the first 
day, the rats were trained to swim for 15 minutes. Water 
was changed after testing of each animal. Twenty-four hours 
later, rats were reexposed to the forced swimming for 5 min-
utes. Animal behavior was recorded by a video camera, and 
immobility time was measured with a stopwatch. The dura-
tion of immobility was calculated by summing the total time 
spent immobile (ie, the time not spent actively exploring 
the cylinder or trying to escape from it). Included within the 
time spent immobile are the short periods of slight activity 
where the animals just make those movements necessary 
to maintain their heads above water. 
38 A stress-free period 
precedes the test with at least 12 hours, and the test was 
performed at least 3 days before decapitation. </p>

<p>Open-field test 
The OFT was performed in all the 29 animals as described 
by Blokland et al 
39 with modifications, in order to assess the 
general locomotor activity. 
40 The apparatus consists of a 
large black arena (90 cm ×90 cm ×60 cm), divided by strips 
into 25 equal small squares illuminated by white light. The 
automated <rs type="software">Open Control</rs> software 
41 was modified to detect 
the number and time spent in the central zones, with the aid 
of a USB camera used to record the whole sessions. Other 
parameters of OFT like rearing and grooming activity were 
recorded manually during each session. </p>

<p>Body weight gain </p>

<p>The percentage change in body weight gain in comparison to 
the baseline was calculated weekly as well as the final body 
weight gain, which was calculated as the difference between 
the final and baseline body weight. </p>

<p>Biochemical testing </p>

<p>Tissue and blood sampling 
Rats were euthanized using ip urethane (1.2 g/kg). Hippocampi 
were dissected under strict cooling conditions. One side of 
hippocampus was used for the assessment of either adenine 
nucleotides or nitric oxide metabolites (NOx). The other side 
of hippocampus was divided into two halves for the assess-
ment of cytochrome-c (Cyt-c) and caspase-3 (Casp-3). All 
hippocampi samples were stored at -70°C until assayed. The 
protein concentration was determined with the Bio-Rad pro-
tein assay reagent (BIO-RAD Laboratories, Richmond, CA, 
USA) according to the kit instruction manual using bovine 
serum albumin as a standard. Blood samples were taken from 
the animals between 3 pm and 5 pm, and sera were separated 
and stored at -20°C. </p>

<p>hPlc assay of serum steroids 
Samples (20 µL) were submitted to isocratic high-performance 
liquid chromatography (HPLC) using a reversed-phase octa-
decyl silane (C18) partition column at a temperature of 40°C 
and flow rate of 1 mL/min. The internal standard utilized was 
6-alpha methyl prednisolone. Mobile phase was prepared by 
adding distilled water to methanol and acetonitrile in a ratio of 
54:43:3, and filtered by 0.45 µm membrane filters. The mobile 
phase was degassed by sonication for 20 minutes before 
mounting into the HPLC pump. The corticosterone (CORT) 
peaks were analyzed spectrophotometrically (λ=254 nm) and 
identified by the comparison with the retention time of the 
corresponding standard solutions. 
42,43 The concentration of 
CORT was expressed in ng/mL. Method validation (retention 
times, linearity, several samples in the same day or several 
samples in several days, and recoveries) was carried out. </p>

<p>hPlc assay of high-energy phosphates and their 
metabolites 
Frozen samples were homogenized in 1,200 µL of ice-cold 
0.76 M perchloric acid (to which was added another 800 µL 
of 0.5 M perchloric acid containing 160 µM inosine-3-
monophosphate disodium salt as an internal standard) using 
an ice-chilled glass homogenizer; the homogenate was then 
allowed to extract for 30 minutes in ice-cold temperature, 
followed by centrifugation (6,000 rpm for 30 minutes at </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2891 </p>

<p>Paroxetine and hippocampal energy changes in cMs </p>

<p>4°C). The supernatant was removed and neutralized by the 
addition of approximately 200 µL of 6 N KOH, controlling 
the pH with pH indicator strip. Any further precipitate 
appearing after neutralization was removed by centrifugation 
(6,000 rpm for 30 minutes at 4°C). The collected supernatant 
was further filtrated using a 0.45 µm filter and used for direct 
analysis of energy metabolites. Samples (20 µL) after suit-
able pretreatment were submitted to isocratic HPLC using 
a reversed-phase octadecyl silane (C18) partition column 
(Alltech; 150 mm long ×4.6 mm internal diameter, 5.0 µm 
particle size, preceded by a short [40 mm ×4 mm] guard 
column of same material) at 37°C. Flow rate was adjusted 
at 1 mL/min. Inosine-3-monophosphate disodium salt served 
as an internal standard. Mobile phase comprised 20 mM 
potassium phosphate buffer (pH 6). The nucleotide (adenos-
ine triphosphate [ATP], adenosine diphosphate (ADP), and 
adenosine monophosphate [AMP]) peaks were analyzed 
spectrophotometrically (λ=254 nm) and identified by the 
comparison with the retention time of the corresponding 
standard solutions. 
44,45 Method validation was carried out. </p>

<p>estimation of NOx in hippocampal homogenate 
The method described by Miranda et al 
46 was used for the 
determination of total nitrate/nitrite as an index of nitric 
oxide (NO) production in hippocampal homogenate, with 
a modification for protein precipitation using zinc sulfate. </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>Briefly, hippocampal homogenates (20% homogenate in ice-
cold saline) were deproteinated using zinc sulfate followed 
by centrifugation at 12,000 rpm for 15 minutes at 4°C. To 
an aliquot of the supernatant, vanadium trichloride (0.8% in 
1 M HCl) was added for the reduction of nitrate to nitrite, 
followed by the rapid addition of Griess reagent consisting of 
N-(1-naphthyl)ethylenediamine dihydrochloride (0.1%) and 
sulfanilamide (2% in 5% HCl), and incubated for 30 minutes 
at 37°C. Mixtures were cooled, and the absorbance was 
measured spectrophotometrically at 540 nm. </p>

<p>estimation of casp-3 activity 
The procedure of the supplied kit (Biovision, Milpitas, CA, 
USA) was performed according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. Briefly, the levels of the chromophore p-nitroanilide 
released by Casp-3 activity in the tissue lysates were quanti-
fied spectrophotometrically at 405 nm. </p>

<p>cyt-c release in the cytosolic fraction of the rat brain 
hippocampus 
The procedure of the supplied kit (Biovision) was per-
formed according to the manufacturer's instructions, and </p>

<p>then proceeded with standard Western blot procedure. 
Briefly, sample protein of the cytosolic fraction was quan-
tified with the Bio-Rad protein assay reagent (Bio-Rad). 
Protein extracts (10 µg per lane) were run on a 12% sodium 
dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis 
(reagents for Laemmli sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacryl-
amide gel electrophoresis Bio-Rad) and electroblotted to 
nitrocellulose membranes using Mini Trans-Blot Electro-
phoretic transfer cell (Bio-Rad). Blots were then incubated 
overnight at 4°C with primary antibody anti-Cyt-c mouse 
monoclonal antibody (supplied in the kit at a dilution of 
1:1,500). After washing three times with tris buffered 
solution (TBS)/Tween (T) (1× TBS, 0.1% T-2), the blots 
were incubated for 60 minutes at room temperature with 
horse radish peroxidase-conjugated anti-mouse IgG (KPL, 
Gaithersburg, MD, USA) for 1 hour at room temperature, 
followed by washing three times with 15 mL of TBS/T. 
The blots were detected by the addition of the chromogenic 
substrate (4CN peroxidase substrate), which upon reacting 
with the peroxidase-labeled primary antibody developed 
a dark purple precipitate on the membrane. </p>

<p>Results 
Behavior experiments </p>

<p>effects of cMs and treatment with ParOX on 
sucrose preference as a measure of anhedonia </p>

<p>The CMS-exposed rats showed a decrease in sucrose pref-
erence over time. Moreover, the final sucrose preference 
was significantly less in stressed rats compared to the 
control and baseline values. Repeated one-way analysis 
of variance (ANOVA) revealed a significant difference 
in sucrose preference at week 5 compared to the baseline 
of both stressed groups prior to PAROX treatment (CMS 
group: F (2,8) =30.43, P0.0001; PAROX group: F (2,9) =14.87, 
P=0.0002). At week 5, the CMS-exposed rats showed a 
significant reduction in sucrose preference in comparison to 
their baseline (71.14±1.95 vs 87.34±1.55, P0.001). Addi-
tionally, PAROX group, prior to the initiation of PAROX 
treatment, had also showed a significant reduction in sucrose 
preference in comparison to their baseline (69.68±4.26 vs 
89.11±2.09, P0.001). At week 11, the PAROX-treated 
rats showed a significant increase in the sucrose prefer-
ence in comparison to week 5 (87.01±2.27 vs 69.68±4.26, 
P0.001), which was nonsignificant from the original 
baseline at week 0. At week 11, the CMS group showed a 
significant decrease in the sucrose preference in compari-
son to week 5 (79.98±1.72 vs 71.14±1.95, P0.01), which 
was also significantly different from the baseline at week 0 </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2892 </p>

<p>Khedr et al </p>

<p>(79.98±1.72 vs 87.34±1.55, P0.01). Furthermore, a sepa-
rate one-way ANOVA (F (2,26) =6.077, P=0.0068) revealed 
that the sucrose preference was significantly lower in both 
stressed groups prior to PAROX treatment in comparison to 
their control at week 5 (P0.05). Following treatment with 
PAROX at week 11, the sucrose preference of the treated 
group was normalized to near control values (F (2,26) =3.395, 
P=0.049) (Figure 2). </p>

<p>effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment 
on FsT </p>

<p>Exposure to CMS significantly increased the desperate 
behavior measured as the immobility time scored in the FST 
(F (2,22) =20.57, P0.0001). This was demonstrated by the 
significant increase in the immobility time scored by CMS 
rats in comparison to control rats (121.4±9.33 seconds vs 
57.43±7.27 seconds, P0.001). This increase in the des-
perate behavior was corrected by PAROX treatment, which 
demonstrated a significant reduction in the immobility time 
scored by the treated rats in comparison to CMS-exposed 
rats (53.6±8.37 seconds vs 121.4±9.33 seconds, P0.001) 
(Figure 3). </p>

<p>effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment 
on OFT </p>

<p>Exposure to CMS increased the activity and exploration of 
the rats when tested in the open field. There was a significant 
increase in the mean counts of both the ambulation fre-
quency (total zones count/horizontal activity) (F (2,26) =13.84, </p>

<p>P0.0001) and the central zones count (F (2,26) =5.375, 
P=0.0111) scored by the CMS group in comparison to the 
mean counts scored by the control group (99.8±17.25 vs 
19.2±6.3, P0.001 and 9±3.6 vs 1.3±0.75, P0.05). More-
over, the CMS exposure had also caused a significant increase 
in the rearing frequency (vertical movement) (F (2,26) =14.75, 
P0.0001) and the grooming frequency (F (2,26) =7.963, 
P=0.0020) in comparison to the mean counts scored by the 
control group (11±2.23 vs 1±0.3, P0.001 and 6±1.18 vs 
0.6±0.27, P0.05). 
This increase in the ambulation, central zones, and rearing 
frequency mean counts induced by the CMS was success-
fully ameliorated by PAROX treatment, which had shown a 
significant reduction in both mean counts in comparison to 
the CMS group (53.5±6.7 vs 99.8±17.25, P0.05; 0.5±0.34 
vs 9±3.6, P0.05; and 4.1±0.86 vs 11±2.23, P0.01). Yet 
the PAROX showed no effect on the grooming frequency, 
where the grooming frequency of the treated group showed 
a significant increase from the control group (7.8±1.97 vs 
0.6±0.27, P0.01) (Figure 4). </p>

<p>effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX 
treatment on the body weight gain </p>

<p>The body weight gain was significantly affected by CMS and 
PAROX treatment (F (2,26) =104.6, P0.0001) which showed a 
significant difference between the means. Post hoc analysis 
revealed that CMS showed a decrease in the body weight 
gain in comparison to control (11.22±3.77 g vs 97.7±5.92 g, 
P0.001). Paradoxically, PAROX induced greater reductions </p>

<p>Figure 2 effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment on the sucrose preference weekly changes from week 0 to week 11. 
Notes: Data are presented as mean ± seM (n=9-10). For comparisons among groups, repeated one-way aNOVa followed by Bonferroni's multiple comparison test was 
used, while for comparisons between groups, separate one-way aNOVa followed by "Bonferroni's multiple comparison test" was used. ***P0.001 significant compared 
to week 0. 
 † P0.05 compared to control at week 5. </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>Significant in comparison to week 5 at P0.001. </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>Significant in comparison to week 5 at P0.01. **Significant in 
comparison to week 0 at P0.01. 
Abbreviations: aNOVa, analysis of variance; cMs, chronic mild stress; ParOX, paroxetine; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2893 </p>

<p>Paroxetine and hippocampal energy changes in cMs </p>

<p>in body weight gain when compared to the control group 
(-18.9±7.37 vs 97.7±5.92, P0.001) (Figure 5A). 
Regarding the weekly changes in body weight gain, 
CMS-exposed rats in comparison to control at the same 
week showed a significant reduction in body weight gain 
at two time intervals -week 3 (F (2,26) =44.79, P0.0001) 
and week 7 (F (2,26) =117.9, P0.0001) (Figure 5B): first at 
week 3 (-5.1±1.95 g vs 14.31±1.37 g, P0.001), and the 
second time was at week 7 (-2.01±2.11 vs 31.75±1.99, 
P0.001). However, PAROX treatment did not show any 
improvement in body weight gain by the end of this study; 
it had even caused a much more significant reduction in the 
CMS-exposed rats in comparison to control (F (2,26) =150.8, 
P0.0001), as observed at week 11 (-7.54±2.96 g vs 
47.75±2.26 g, P0.001). This observed decrease was even 
significantly different from the decrease observed in the body 
weight gain of CMS group at the same week (-7.45±2.96 vs 
4.4±1.68, P0.01) (Figure 5B). </p>

<p>Figure 3 effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment on the immobility time 
in the FsT. 
Notes: Bar graph illustrating changes in FsT over the period of treatment. Data 
are presented as mean ± seM (n=9-10). For comparisons between groups, 
one-way aNOVa followed by Bonferroni's multiple comparison test was 
used. ***P0.001 significant in comparison to control. 
### P0.01 significant in 
comparison to cMs. 
Abbreviations: aNOVa, analysis of variance; cMs, chronic mild stress; FsT, 
forced swimming test; ParOX, paroxetine; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Figure 4 effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment on the mean counts of ambulation, central zones, rearing frequency, and grooming frequency scored in the open-
field test. 
Notes: (A) ambulation. (B) central zone. (C) rearing. (D) grooming. Data are presented as mean ± seM (n=9-10). For comparisons between groups, one-way aNOVa 
followed by Bonferroni's multiple comparison test was used. *P0.05 compared to control values. **P0.01 in comparison with control. ***P0.001 significant in comparison 
to control. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>Significant in comparison with the CMS group. </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>P0.01 significant in comparison to CMS. 
Abbreviations: aNOVa, analysis of variance; cMs, chronic mild stress; ParOX, paroxetine; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2894 </p>

<p>Khedr et al </p>

<p>Biochemical analysis </p>

<p>effect of 7 weeks of the cMs paradigm on serum 
steroids </p>

<p>Rats exposed to the CMS protocol for 7 weeks have dem-
onstrated a dramatic change in the serum steroids level in 
comparison to the control. This finding further consolidated 
the validity of the method. The serum CORT level of the 
CMS group had shown a significant increase in concentration 
by 4.8-fold in comparison to the control group at (P0.001) 
(Table 2). </p>

<p>effects of 11 weeks of the cMs paradigm and 
ParOX treatment on serum cOrT </p>

<p>Rats exposed to the CMS protocol for 11 weeks continued 
to express a significant change in the serum CORT level 
in comparison to control (F (2,18) =39.16, P0.0001). CORT 
concentration in the CMS group showed a significant increase 
by 37.72% in comparison to control. Treatment with PAROX 
significantly ameliorated the CMS-induced increase in serum 
CORT in comparison to the CMS group (91.71±1.77 ng/mL 
vs 124.5±4.44 ng/mL, P0.001) (Table 3). </p>

<p>effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment 
on the level of high-energy phosphates in the 
rat brain hippocampus </p>

<p>CMS-exposed rats showed a significant increase in the 
concentrations of ATP by 3.64-fold, ADP by 13.16-fold, 
AMP by 4.29-fold, and total adenine nucleotides (TAN) by 
5.52-fold, as well as a significant decrease in the ATP/ADP 
ratio by 3.56-fold and the adenylate energy charge (AEC) 
by 1.18-fold in comparison to the control group (P0.001) 
(Figure 6). 
Treatment with PAROX significantly ameliorated the 
CMS-induced increase in ATP, ADP, AMP, and TAN in 
comparison to the CMS group (1.8±0.19 nmol/mg protein 
vs 3.49±0.53 nmol/mg protein, P0.01; 0.12±0.01 nmol/mg 
protein vs 0.3±0.04 nmol/mg protein, P0.001; 
0.47±0.05 nmol/mg protein vs 3.29±0.52 nmol/mg protein, 
P0.01; 2.39±0.24 nmol/mg protein vs 7.07±1.1 nmol/mg 
protein, P0.001, respectively). Moreover, it ameliorated 
the CMS-induced decrease in the ATP/ADP ratio and AEC 
(3.76±0.02 vs 1.07±0.01, P0.001 and 0.84±0.007 vs 
0.72±0.007, P0.001, respectively) (Figure 6). </p>

<p>Table 2 effects of 7 weeks of cMs exposure compared to vehicle control on serum corticosteroids </p>

<p>Groups 
Corticosterone (ng/mL) 
Cortisol (ng/mL) 
11-deoxycortisol (ng/mL) 
Hydrocortisone (ng/mL) </p>

<p>Vehicle control (n=7) 
29.93±1.38 
40.81±1.43 
19.57±1.18 
15.84±1.91 
cMs (n=7) 
144.3±4.54*** 
165.2±4.51*** 
62.2±3.79*** 
52.19±4.36*** </p>

<p>Notes: Data are presented as mean ± seM (n=7). ***P0.001 significant in comparison to control. For comparisons among groups, unpaired Student's t-test was used. 
Abbreviations: cMs, chronic mild stress; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Figure 5 effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment on the body weight gain. 
Notes: (A) Final weight gain. (B) Weekly percentage change in body weight gain over the period of weeks (0-11). Data are presented as mean ± seM (n=9-10). For 
comparisons between groups, one-way aNOVa followed by Bonferroni's multiple comparison test was used. ***P0.001 significant in comparison to control. </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>P0.01 
significant in comparison to CMS. Data are presented as mean ± seM (n=9-10). 
Abbreviations: aNOVa, analysis of variance; cMs, chronic mild stress; ParOX, paroxetine; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2895 </p>

<p>Paroxetine and hippocampal energy changes in cMs </p>

<p>Table 3 effects of 11 weeks of cMs exposure and paroxetine treatment on serum corticosteroids </p>

<p>Groups 
Corticosterone (ng/mL) 
Cortisol (ng/mL) 
11-deoxycortisol (ng/mL) 
Hydrocortisol (ng/mL) </p>

<p>Vehicle control (n=7) 
90.4±2.41 
98.9±2.17 
18.89±0.3 
19.13±0.36 
cMs (n=7) 
124.5±4.44*** 
140.5±3.05*** 
41.33±3.86*** 
35.43±3.02*** 
Paroxetine (n=7) 
91.71±1.77 </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>113.9±1.64 </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>21.06±0.88 </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>18.91±0.32 </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>Notes: Data are presented as mean ± seM (n=7). ***P0.001 significant in comparison to control. </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>P0.001 significant in comparison to CMS. For comparisons among 
groups, one-way aNOVa followed by Bonferroni's multiple comparison test was used. 
Abbreviations: cMs, chronic mild stress; seM, standard error of the mean; aNOVa, analysis of variance. </p>

<p>Figure 6 effects of cMs paradigm and paroxetine treatment on the level of high-energy phosphates in the hippocampal homogenate. 
Notes: Bar graph illustrating changes in (A) aTP/aDP ratio, (B) aec, and (C) aTP, aDP, aMP, and TaN among treatment groups. Data are presented as mean ± seM (n=6). 
***P0.001 significant in comparison to control. </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>P0.001 significant in comparison to CMS. </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>P0.01 in comparison to cMs. For comparisons among groups, one-way 
aNOVa followed by Bonferroni's multiple comparison test was used. aec = (aTP +0.5 aDP)/TaN and TaN = aTP + aDP + aMP. 
Abbreviations: aDP, adenosine diphosphate; aec, adenylate energy charge; aMP, adenosine monophosphate; aNOVa, analysis of variance; aTP, adenosine triphosphate; 
cMs, chronic mild stress; ParOX, paroxetine; seM, standard error of the mean; TaN, total adenine nucleotides. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2896 </p>

<p>Khedr et al </p>

<p>effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment 
on the level of NOx </p>

<p>CMS had induced a robust reduction in the NOx (F (2,14) =311.9, 
P0.0001) by 42.42% in comparison to the control. PAROX 
treatment had significantly improved this reduction, showing 
6.63-fold increase in their mean concentration in comparison 
to the CMS, as well as 3.82-fold increase in comparison to 
the control group (Figure 7). </p>

<p>effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment 
on the casp-3 activity </p>

<p>CMS induced enhancement in the Casp-3 activity 
(F (2,21) =9.906, P=0.0009) which in comparison to the control 
group had shown a significant increase by 1.2-fold (P0.05). 
This increase was successfully ameliorated by PAROX treat-
ment that showed a 33.3% decrease in the Casp-3 activity in 
comparison to the CMS group (P0.001) (Figure 8). </p>

<p>effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment 
on cyt-c expression in the cytosolic fraction 
of the hippocampal homogenate </p>

<p>Cyt-c immunoreactivity was evident as a single band of 
molecular mass of 15 kDa (Figure 9) in the cytosolic frac-
tion of the rat hippocampus. A significant band was detected 
in the CMS group after exposure to the CMS battery for 
11 weeks. This expression was normalized near the normal 
by PAROX treatment. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study implicates the role of PAROX in reversing stress-
induced depressive-like behaviors associated with alterations </p>

<p>in hippocampal stress-induced hippocampal energy metabo-
lism and apoptosis in a CMS model of depression. 
In the current investigation, animals exposed to CMS 
showed anhedonia, indicated by reduced sucrose 
preference, 
11 as well as a significant decrease in body weight 
gain. This finding is in-line with other studies. </p>

<p>9,32,35,48-51 </p>

<p>Noteworthy, the reduction in body weight gain, a further </p>

<p>Figure 9 representive immunoblots of cyt-c protein illustrating the effect of cMs 
paradigm and ParOX treatment on the cyt-c expression in the cytosolic fraction 
of the hippocampal homogenate. 
Notes: The release of mitochondrial cyt-c was estimated by detecting the increase 
in the expression of the cyt-c in the cytosolic fraction of cMs-exposed rats in 
comparison to the ParOX-treated animals as well as the control; visualized as a 
dark purple precipitate developed when the 4cN peroxidase substrate reacts with 
the peroxidase-labeled secondary antibody. 
Abbreviations: cMs, chronic mild stress; cyt-c, cytochrome-c; ParOX, 
paroxetine; P, paroxetine; V, vehicle. </p>

<p>Figure 7 effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment on the level of NOx in 
the hippocampal homogenate. 
Notes: Data are presented as mean ± SEM. *Significant from vehicle at P0.01. 
***Significant in comparison to control at P0.001. </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>Significant in comparison to 
cMs at P0.001. For comparisons among groups, one-way aNOVa followed by 
Bonferroni's multiple comparison test was used. 
Abbreviations: aNOVa, analysis of variance; cMs, chronic mild stress; NOx, 
nitric oxide metabolites; ParOX, paroxetine; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Figure 8 effects of cMs paradigm and ParOX treatment on the casp-3 activity in 
the hippocampal homogenate. 
Notes: Bars represent mean ± SEM. *Significant in comparison to control at P0.01. </p>

<p>### </p>

<p>Significant in comparison to CMS at P0.001. For comparisons among groups, 
one-way aNOVa followed by Bonferroni's multiple comparison test was used. 
Abbreviations: aNOVa, analysis of variance; casp-3, caspase-3; cMs, chronic 
mild stress; ParOX, paroxetine; seM, standard error of the mean. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2897 </p>

<p>Paroxetine and hippocampal energy changes in cMs </p>

<p>indicator for the face validity of the adopted CMS para-
digm, presents a supplementary physiological index of 
stress. 
49,52 Although PAROX induced further weight loss in 
comparison to CMS and control animals, a finding similar 
to that previously reported by other authors, 
32 it amended 
CMS-induced reduction in sucrose preference, hence 
conferring a selective protection against CMS-induced 
anhedonia. Casarotto and Andreatini 
32 suggested that this 
might indicate a dissociation between the mechanisms 
underlying body weight changes and those underlying 
anhedonia. 
In the present study, CMS-exposed rats showed an 
increased immobility time in FST, suggestive of increased 
desperate behavior, 
53 a finding in-line with previous 
reports 
52,54,55 documenting increased immobility in the FST 
as a consequence of CMS anhedonia. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Although Walsh and Cummins 
56 and Katz et al 
57 reported 
an association of low activity in the OFT with depressive 
behavior, paradoxically, in the current investigation, rats 
showed a higher locomotor activity both vertically and 
horizontally, compared to control. This paradoxic finding is 
consistent with some previous reports. 
58,59 This may indicate a 
possible non-concordance of SPT with some other behavioral 
responses, including an anomalous decreased anxiety. 
60 To 
further validate the induction of stress, the study showed a 
significant increase in serum CORT following 7 weeks of 
CMS exposure in comparison to control. Such a finding is 
in-line with previous reports. 
49,52 At the end of the 11-week 
period, CORT concentrations showed a robust upsurge in 
response to CMS, compared to control. This finding confirms 
previously reported results. 
15,61,62 This dysregulation may be 
attributed to the reduced GR expression and function. </p>

<p>15,16,63-65 </p>

<p>The deficit might be related to the hypoactivity of the sero-
toninergic system associated with depression, as the GR 
expression is dependent on the central 5-hydroxytryptamine 
tone. 
66,67 This explanation is further verified by the ability 
of PAROX to reverse the elevation of the CMS-induced 
CORT. This finding supports other researches implicating 
antidepressants in amelioration of HPA axis hyperactivity, 
probably by modulating GR, via restoring its regulation by 
the serotoninergic tone. 
The increased CORT was associated with an eleva-
tion of apoptotic markers in CMS-exposed rats. Such an 
observation is in harmony with recent findings implicating 
a causal relationship between apoptosis and CMS-induced 
hippocampal neurodegenration. 
26,68 Indeed, PAROX ame-
liorated the CMS-enhanced expression of cytosolic Cyt-c 
as well as the increased Casp-3 activity. This finding points </p>

<p>toward the value of PAROX in reversing stress-induced 
apoptosis. Noteworthy, the anti-apoptotic effects of various 
classes of antidepressants had favorably received consider-
able attention. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Notably, postmortem brains of depressed patients showed 
DNA fragmentation and neuronal apoptosis, suggesting an 
enhanced neuronal vulnerability in MDD. 
5,6 Moreover, pro-
longed or excessive exposure to GCs is known to decrease 
neurogenesis and may promote apoptosis, 
22,69 particularly 
in the hippocampus, 
24 one of the most vulnerable brain 
regions to various neurobiological insults due to its high 
GRs content. 
70,71 Both genomic and non-genomic actions of 
CORT have been linked to stress-induced changes in mito-
chondrial membrane potential (MMP) leading to the release 
of Cyt-c from inner mitochondrial membrane to cytosol. 
17 In 
fact, the current study demonstrated enhanced expression of 
cytosolic Cyt-c, as well as its downstream player Casp-3 in 
CMS animals, suggestive of mitochondrial damage. 
Several reports advocate an important role of changes in 
brain energy metabolism in predisposing to depression. </p>

<p>30,72 </p>

<p>Moreover, rats subjected to chronic stress models showed 
a decrease in mitochondrial functions. 
73-75 In the present 
study, CMS-exposed rats showed a significant increase in 
hippocampal ATP, ADP, AMP, and TAN associated with a 
decrease in AEC as well as ATP/ADP. Notably, AEC ratio 
represents the amount of the metabolically available energy 
which is stored in the TAN pool and provides a quantita-
tive assessment of the cellular energy status. 
76 Hence, the 
observed reduction in AEC seen may indicate high metabolic 
stress. Noteworthy, an AEC 0.5 is indicative of cell death, 
while values ranging from 0.55 to 0.75 indicate consumption 
of energy for defense mechanisms, against stress. 
77 Conse-
quently, it is expected that in the presence of any metabolic 
stress, cells will react with a depletion of ATP and a simulta-
neous increase in the AMP levels and a significant decrease 
in AEC. 
78 Notably, in the current investigation, hippocampal 
cells showed a decline in the energy status, manifested as a 
decrease in AEC and the ATP/ADP ratio, paralleled with an 
increase in the ADP and AMP level in the CMS rats. 
Despite the decrease in the AEC observed in the CMS-
exposed rats, paradoxically, the ATP level increased. 
A plausible explanation might reside in the low MMP gradi-
ent that hampers adequate mitochondrial energy production. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Alternatively, the observed increase in ATP may be attributed 
to the increased glycolysis, compensating, at least in part, 
the disturbed mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation ATP 
supply. Nonetheless, the ATP generated by glycolysis would 
not meet the high energy demand of such a metabolically </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2898 </p>

<p>Khedr et al </p>

<p>active tissue like the brain, 
79 hence creating a mismatch 
between the rates of ATP consumption and production, lend-
ing a reasonable explanation for the observed decrease of 
AEC. However, another plausible explanation might be due 
to mitochondrial apoptosis-induced channel formation that 
enhances the release of Cyt-c, in the absence of mitochondrial 
depolarization and without loss of outer membrane integrity. 
These observations indicate that, instead of rupturing, a more 
selective mechanism of permeabilization is operating, like the 
formation of a pore in the outer membrane, a phenomenon 
unrelated to (1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine)-
induced changes in the membrane potential, which further 
implicates that the mitochondria may be still capable of 
creating some energy. </p>

<p>80,81 </p>

<p>Interestingly, the observed increase in ATP seen in this 
study offers verification for the incidence of CMS-induced 
apoptosis. Notably, ATP depletion is associated with necro-
sis, while its availability is required for the development of 
apoptosis. </p>

<p>76,82-84 </p>

<p>This study reported the successful amelioration of the 
CMS-induced increase in Casp-3 activity and Cyt-c expres-
sion in the cytosol by PAROX, hence implicating a suggested 
role of PAROX in alleviating the depressive symptoms 
through the modulation of the programmed cell death-medi-
ated neuronal loss. A recent study reported a role of PAROX 
(10 mg/kg/day) in partially ameliorating some parameters 
related to mitochondrial dysfunction and apoptosis in rats 
exposed to modified stress-restress. 
85 Several reports have 
implicated the increase in glutamate and induction of exci-
totoxicity to the increased cytosolic calcium transients, and 
further activation of the calcium-dependent neuronal NO syn-
thase (nNOS) inducing hippocampal neuronal degeneration. 
In fact, increased extracellular glutamate levels have been 
demonstrated in the rat hippocampus by several acute and 
chronic stress paradigms. 
86,87 This explanation was further 
supported by pervious findings from our laboratory 
88 report-
ing an increase in hippocampal glutamate level accompanied 
by a reduction in gamma amino butyric acid due to decrease 
in glutamic acid decarboxylase activity in CMS paradigm. 
Contrary to this view, the present study reported a decrease 
in NO concentrations suggesting a decrease in NO synthase 
(NOS) activity. The presented result supports previous find-
ings by Palumbo et al 
89,90 where they observed a significant 
reduction in nNOS activity and NOx production in the hip-
pocampus of CMS-exposed mice. The latter might be due 
to CORT inhibition of nNOS and mitochondrial NOS tran-
scription in the rat brain. 
91 Moreover, it has been previously 
reported in clinical studies that depressed patients had shown </p>

<p>a decreased activity in the calcium-dependent constitutive 
NOS in the prefrontal cortex of depressed patients 
92 as well 
as a reduction in NOS-containing neurons in the hypothala-
mus. 
92 The latter might be due to CORT-inhibiting nNOS and 
mitochondrial NOS transcription in the rat brain. 
91 Indeed, 
PAROX administration had successfully ameliorated this 
decrease in NO production as well as the dramatic increase 
in the serum CORT level suggestive of the protective role 
of NO in preventing apoptosis. </p>

<p>93-96 </p>

<p>Accordingly, the present investigation highlights a role 
of energy changes (suggestive of mitochondrial changes) in 
the etiology of depression, associated with a chronic stress 
paradigm. This is further confirmed by the ability of PAROX 
to reverse CMS-induced energy changes, as well as apop-
tosis, which associated with ameliorating the CMS-related 
behavior as seen in the OFT and FST, as well as reversal of 
anhedonic behavior. </p>

<p>Future indication </p>

<p>Findings from the present investigation prompt further 
studies to assess metabolic changes associated with depres-
sion in multiple organs. Notably, Harvey 
30 stated that 
mood disorders are often comorbid with cardiovascular, 
liver, kidney, and endocrine disorders, while increasing 
evidence concurs that depression involves inflammatory 
and neurodegenerative processes. This would suggest that 
metabolic disturbances resembling encephalopathy may 
underscore the basic neuropathology of depression at a far 
deeper level than currently realized. Viewing depression 
as a form of encephalopathy, and exploiting knowledge 
gleaned from our understanding of the neurochemistry and 
treatment of metabolic encephalopathy, may assist not only 
in our understanding of the neurobiology of depression 
but also in realizing new ideas in the pharmacotherapy of 
mood disorders. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors greatly appreciate the efforts of Dr Hanan El 
Mohammady, Section Head, Serology, Disease Surveillance 
and Research Lab, US Naval Medical Research Unit 
Number 3, for providing training and facilitating the use of 
gel electrophoresis and Western blot in her lab. The authors 
would also like to acknowledge engineer Ahmed Gala 
El-Din, Faulty of Engineering, Ain Shams University, and 
Mr Mohamed El Tabbal, sixth-year medical student, Faculty 
of Medicine, Ain Shams University, for developing the OFT 
analysis software and allowing the authors the opportunity 
for a free trial version. </p>

<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>2899 </p>

<p>Paroxetine and hippocampal energy changes in cMs </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment 2015:11 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Khedr et al </p>



</text></tei>