<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4736865" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Myasthenia gravis (MG) is an autoimmune neuromuscular 
disorder caused by anti-acetylcholine receptor 
antibodies (AChR-Abs) or other etiologies. Ocular symptoms 
were the first presentations in 40-50% of MG patients. 
Ptosis and diplopia were the most common symptoms of 
ocular MG (OMG). Limited studies demonstrated that 
patients presented with initial symptoms of only ptosis in 
47%, only diplopia in 14% and both ptosis and diplopia 
in 39% of OMG. [1] Variations of diplopia or ptosis did not 
significantly affect the physical or mental status of OMG. 
Initial presentation of concurrent ptosis and diplopia was 
significantly associated with insensitivity to pyridostigmine 
for OMG patients. However, the differences of clinical 
features including age of disease onset, gender, thymoma, 
as well as other autoimmune disease between various 
phenotypes of OMG remain unidentified. </p>

<p>OMG developed to generalized MG (GMG) in about 
50-80% patients within the first 1 or 2 years after disease 
onset and 38% of the MG patients experienced remission 
during 30 years of observation. [2,3] Early thymectomy and 
administration of prednisolone can decrease relapse and 
secondary generalization of OMG. Late age of onset, 
anti-AChR-Ab, and thymoma increased the risk of secondary 
generalization. Anti-Kv1.4 antibody and thymus hyperplasia 
increased MG relapse. Time of diagnosis from onset and 
age at onset (≤40 years) predicted MG remission. Gender 
does not seem to predict the course of MG. However, less 
attention was paid on the effect of initial OMG symptoms 
of disease onset such as ptosis and diplopia concurrence or 
alone, ptosis on one or both eyes on both MG relapse and 
OMG second generalization. Our study aimed to explore the 
clinical characteristics and prognosis of OMG with different 
phenotypes. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Eighty-three MG patients recruited in this study were 
examined in the Neurology Department of Beijing Shijitan 
Hospital between January 2002 and October 2014. Among 
83 MG patients, 59 patients presented with only ocular 
signs and symptoms at disease onset. The diagnosis of 
MG was based on the combination of clinical features and 
one of the laboratory criteria including favorable effect 
of cholinesterase inhibitors, positive results of repetitive 
nerve stimulation or single fiber electromyography and 
anti-AChR-Abs highly specific for MG. [4] The study was 
approved by the hospital ethics committee on clinical 
research and written informed consent was obtained from 
all of the patients in this study. </p>

<p>There were no well-accepted criteria for the diagnosis of 
OMG relapse. In this study, OMG relapse was diagnosed 
with the reappearance of any symptoms and signs of 
extra-ocular muscles weakness. The reappeared symptoms 
and signs should last more than 24 h. And the duration 
between the OMG relapse and last remission should be more 
than 30 days. Also, a minimal period of 2 years without 
generalization is required to classify a patient with initial 
ocular manifestations as having a pure ocular form. </p>

<p>The computed tomography scan explores the presence of 
a thymoma or thymic hyperplasia. Autoimmune thyroid </p>

<p>Clinical Features and Prognosis of Ocular Myasthenia Gravis 
Patients with Different Phenotypes </p>

<p>Li-Li Wang, Yun Zhang, Mao-Lin He </p>

<p>Department of Neurology, Beijing Shijitan Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 100038, China </p>

<p>Key words: Clinical Features; Diplopia; Ocular Myasthenia Gravis; Prognosis; Ptosis </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.166032 </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Dr. Li-Li Wang, 
Department of Neurology, Beijing Shijitan Hospital, Capital Medical 
University, Beijing 100038, China 
E-Mail: bitljq2012@163.com </p>

<p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, 
tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited 
and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. </p>

<p>For reprints contact: reprints@medknow.com </p>

<p>© 2015 Chinese Medical Journal ¦ Produced by Wolters Kluwer -Medknow </p>

<p>Received: 04-04-2015 Edited by: Li-Shao Guo 
How to cite this article: Wang LL, Zhang Y, He ML. Clinical Features 
and Prognosis of Ocular Myasthenia Gravis Patients with Different 
Phenotypes. Chin Med J 2015;128:2682-4. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ October 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 19 </p>



<p>diseases such as Graves' disease and antibody positive 
thyroid disease were diagnosed on the basis of clinical 
features, thyroid ultrasonography, and serum thyroxin and 
related autoantibody levels. The diagnosis of rheumatoid 
arthritis was based on the guideline of The American College 
of Rheumatology. </p>

<p>Age, gender, thymus abnormality, and associated 
autoimmune diseases, as well as prognosis including OMG 
relapse and second generalization were compared between 
different OMG groups. In addition, disequilibrium caused 
by treatment between the groups was precluded in order to 
assure the accuracy of this current analysis. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">22</rs> 
software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., USA). Categorical variables were 
analyzed using the Chi-square and Fisher exact test. 
Continuous variables were analyzed with t-test. P &lt; 0.05 
was considered as statistically significant. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Clinical features of ocular myasthenia gravis patients 
with different phenotypes </p>

<p>There were 33 female and 26 male OMG patients in this 
study, with a median age of 46.1 ± 18.5 years (range: 
4.0-72.0 years). This study demonstrated that patients 
presented with the initial symptom of only ptosis were in 
62.7% of OMG patients, only diplopia were in 10.2% and 
both ptosis and diplopia were in 27.1% of OMG patients. 
These patients were divided into two groups: single ptosis or 
diplopia group (n = 43) and concurrence diplopia and ptosis 
group (n = 16) based on the initial symptoms of disease onset. 
Results showed that age of onset, gender, thymus histology, 
and other autoimmune disease had no significant difference 
between the two groups. </p>

<p>Also, OMG with ptosis were further divided into unilateral 
group (n = 14) and bilateral group (n = 23) based on ptosis 
on one or both eyes. Other autoimmune diseases such as 
Graves' disease and rheumatoid arthritis were observed 
significantly more frequently in bilateral group than those 
in unilateral group (P = 0.006). </p>

<p>Prognosis of ocular myasthenia gravis patients with 
different phenotypes </p>

<p>OMG relapse and second generalization were investigated 
between bilateral ptosis and unilateral ptosis groups. MG 
relapse in the first 2 years after disease onset was observed 
more frequently in bilateral group (58.3%) than that in 
unilateral group (30.4%). However, the frequency and the 
time of MG relapse did not show statistically significant 
difference between the two groups. Also, there was no 
difference of OMG second generalization occurrence 
between the two groups (87.5% vs. 90.0%). Also, the time 
and the first symptom of OMG generalization between the 
two groups also had no statistical significance. </p>

<p>Prognosis features were also compared between the group 
with single ptosis or diplopia and the group with the </p>

<p>concurrence of diplopia and ptosis. OMG relapse occurred 
more frequently in single ptosis or diplopia group (41.5% 
vs. 28.6%) than in the group with concurrence of diplopia 
and ptosis. But the frequency and the time of MG relapse 
showed no statistical significance between the two groups. 
In addition, the ratio of OMG second generalization in 
the first 2 years after disease onset was found without 
differences in the two groups (82.1% vs. 91.7%). OMG 
progressed more rapidly in single ptosis or diplopia 
group. Time of OMG generalization showed statistically 
significant differences between the two groups (P = 0.019, 
Fisher exact test). However, the first symptoms of OMG 
generalization between these two groups did not show 
statistical difference. </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to investigate clinical features 
and prognosis of OMG with different phenotypes. This 
analysis showed that concurrent autoimmune disease was 
observed more commonly in bilateral ptosis patients (64.3%) 
than that in unilateral ptosis patients (17.4%). Patients with 
initial bilateral ptosis can predict the presence of concurrent 
autoimmune disease. OMG developed to GMG more 
rapidly in single ptosis or diplopia group compared to that 
in both ptosis and diplopia group. Initial single symptom 
ptosis or diplopia could serve as potential indicators for the 
generalization of OMG in the first 6 months. </p>

<p>Previously no studies have addressed the relationship of 
ptosis, diplopia with the occurrence of thymus abnormality 
and with the concurrence of other autoimmune diseases. 
This study demonstrated that thymus abnormality occurred 
more frequently in both ptosis and diplopia group although 
the difference was not statistical significant. Associated 
autoimmune diseases occurred significantly more frequently 
in bilateral ptosis group. This study also demonstrated that 
age of disease onset and gender had no relationship with the 
different presentations of OMG. </p>

<p>In the present study, 62.7% of OMG patients presented with 
ptosis, 10.2% with diplopia and 27.1% with the concurrence 
of ptosis and diplopia. The ratio of ptosis was higher in our 
study compared with that in a previous study that reported 
that ptosis, diplopia, ptosis, and diplopia were present in 
47%, 14%, and 39% of OMG patients, respectively. [1] This 
discrepancy may be related to the different race and heritage 
background between the two studies. </p>

<p>Until now, little attention was paid on the relationship 
of ptosis, as well as diplopia with OMG relapse and 
second generalization. This study demonstrated that OMG 
patients with single presentation of ptosis or diplopia 
developed early generalization in the first 6 months. To 
the best of our knowledge, there was no other related 
study reported. </p>

<p>The mechanisms underlying why different presentations 
of ptosis and diplopia have different clinical features and 
prognosis remain unclear. The previous study implied that </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ October 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 19 </p>

<p>
Th17 cell was the key factor in the development of both 
MG and associated Gravis' disease. Also, Concurrent 
autoimmune diseases such as Hashimoto's thyroiditis 
and rheumatoid arthritis were found in muscle-specific 
kinase (MuSK) antibody positive patients (9.6%) and 
Graves' disease was found in AChR-Ab positive patients. 
Therefore, Th17 cell and MuSK antibody, as well as 
AChR-Ab might contribute to OMG with the concurrence 
of other autoimmune diseases. </p>

<p>Treg percentage was significantly lower in the relapse stage 
than in the remission stage of childhood OMG. [5] Th17 and 
Treg contributed to immunologic disorders in MG patients. 
Therefore, we speculated that Th17 and Treg might be 
related to the prognosis of OMG. Also, genetic risk factors 
have been shown to have relevance to MG development. 
Further studies should be conducted to address these issues 
in the future. </p>

<p>In summary, our study demonstrated that patients with 
initial bilateral ptosis can predict the presence of concurrent 
autoimmune disease. Initial single symptom ptosis 
or diplopia could serve as potential indicators for the 
generalization of OMG in the first 6 months. </p>

<p>Financial support and sponsorship </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant from Beijing 
Shijitan Hospital, Capital Medical University of 
China (No. 2013-QB04). </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>references </p>



</text></tei>