<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4819553" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract MammaPrint is an FDA-cleared microarray-
based test that uses expression levels of the 70 Mam-
maPrint genes to assess distant recurrence risk in early-
stage breast cancer. The prospective RASTER study 
proved that MammaPrint Low Risk patients can safely 
forgo chemotherapy, which is further subject of the 
prospective randomized MINDACT trial. While Mam-
maPrint diagnostic results are obtained from mini-arrays, 
clinical trials may be performed on whole-genome arrays. 
Here we demonstrate the equivalence and reproducibility 
of the MammaPrint test. MammaPrint indices were col-
lected for breast cancer samples: (i) on both customized 
certified array types (n = 1,897 sample pairs), (ii) with </p>

<p>matched fresh and FFPE tissues (n = 552 sample pairs), 
iii) for control samples replicated over a period of 10 years 
(n = 11,333), and iv) repeated measurements (n = 280). 
The array type indicated a near perfect Pearson correlation 
of 0.99 (95 % CI: 0.989-0.991). Paired fresh and FFPE 
samples showed an excellent Pearson correlation of 0.93 
(95 % CI 0.92-0.94), in spite of the variability introduced 
by intratumoral tissue heterogeneity. Control samples 
showed high consistency over 10 year's time (overall 
reproducibility of 97.4 %). Precision and repeatability are 
overall 98.2 and 98.3 %, respectively. Results confirm that 
the combination of the near perfect correlation between 
array types, excellent equivalence between tissue types, 
and a very high stability, precision, and repeatability 
demonstrate that results from clinical trials (such as 
MINDACT and I-SPY 2) are equivalent to current </p>

<p>Electronic supplementary material The online version of this 
article (The use of multigene diagnostic testing to guide cancer 
treatment has increased dramatically, since the clinical 
introduction of the first US Food and Drug Administration 
(FDA)-cleared multigene diagnostic signature Mam-
maPrint [1]. These types of genomic tests interrogate gene 
expression levels in tissues to give information about the 
disease state and/or prognosis, and have led to new diag-
nostic approaches that are recognized by international 
clinical guidelines [2, 3]. MammaPrint determines the 
expression of 70 signature genes and helps guide physi-
cians to make adjuvant treatment decisions for early-stage 
breast cancer patients [4, 5]. The test is suitable for both 
fresh or fresh frozen (fresh) tissues and formalin-fixed 
paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tissues [4, 6, 7]. MammaPrint is 
part of Agendia's In Vitro Diagnostic (IVD) Test Suite that 
also includes BluePrint, which reveals breast cancer sub-
type [8]. 
MammaPrint was developed and validated based on 
fresh frozen tissues and cleared by the FDA [1, 4, 9, 10]. 
However, for diagnostic purposes, shipment of frozen tis-
sue is not always easily implemented in community hos-
pitals. Therefore, RNAretain (for room temperature sample 
stabilization during shipment) was validated, FDA-cleared 
and implemented [11, 12] and subsequently, MammaPrint 
was validated and cleared for use of FFPE tissues [6, 13]. 
To date, MammaPrint is one of the two (MammaPrint and 
Prosigna [14]) FDA-cleared [15] clinically implemented 
breast cancer multigene expression tests with 6 clearances, 
and obtained the EU IVD CE mark, for both fresh and 
FFPE tissues [1, 11, 13, 16-18]. Claims on current diag-
nostic clinical utility include its well-established prognostic 
value for metastasis risk assessment for early-stage breast 
cancer patients [5, 9, 10, 19-22]. </p>

<p>Since 2004, MammaPrint has been used for over 90,000 
patients to determine the patient's distant recurrence risk. 
The activity of the 70 signature genes is compiled in an 
index that is used to establish the qualitative MammaPrint 
results: Low Risk or High Risk for distant recurrence. 
Designated clinically low risk patients with positive hor-
monal receptor status could well be treated by hormonal 
therapy in the adjuvant setting [3], while clinically high 
risk patients are more suited to receive a combination of 
chemotherapy and hormonal therapy in an (neo-) adjuvant 
setting [3]. Clinical studies have shown MammaPrint's 
clinical prognostic value in lymph-node negative [10, 22] 
and lymph-node positive [19] breast cancer, for women 
diagnosed at all ages [21], and irrespective of pathological 
grade [9], estrogen receptor status or HER2 expression 
[20]. The RASTER study [12] provided the first prospec-
tive evidence of clinical utility for MammaPrint. It showed 
a 98.9 % 5-year metastasis-free survival for patients that 
were clinically high risk, based on standard clinical 
parameters, but who chose not to receive adjuvant 
chemotherapy based on their MammaPrint Low Risk status 
[5]. These study results indicated that these patients could 
safely forgo chemotherapy [23]. Confirmation of Mam-
maPrint's prognostic value is expected in 2016, when 
results are projected for the large European Organization 
for Treatment and Cancer (EORTC) prospective random-
ized clinical MINDACT trial (EORTC 10041; BIG 3-04) 
[24-26]. 
MammaPrint results can be obtained from both cus-
tomized mini-arrays and from customized whole-genome 
arrays. Both array types contain multiple replicates of the 
70 signature probes complemented with an identical large 
set of replicated normalization and control probes. Diag-
nostic MammaPrint results are generally obtained using 
customized mini-arrays (also referred to as 8-pack arrays), 
accommodating 8 individual samples per array [4]. In large 
clinical trials like MINDACT [26] and I-SPY 2 [27], 
MammaPrint expression analysis was performed on whole-
genome arrays containing over 32,000 unique probes per 
array. This array type is currently used in the I-SPY 2 trial 
with a MammaPrint FDA Investigational Device Exempt 
(IDE) status. For MammaPrint diagnostic use in Europe, 
both the customized mini-array and the customized whole-
genome array hold an IVD EU directive CE mark. The use 
of whole-genome arrays allows providing MammaPrint 
results to clinical trial participants alongside enabling full-
genome analysis for the early development of new gene 
expression signatures. For the MINDACT trial, this resul-
ted in an unprecedented dataset representing almost 6700 
early-stage breast cancer patients. 
The aim of the current study is to evaluate the equiva-
lence and robustness of the MammaPrint test in different 
settings. Microarray types [28, 29] as well as tissue </p>

<p> 
Breast Cancer Res Treat (2016) 156:279-287 </p>



<p>preservation techniques [30] have been known to poten-
tially influence array expression profiles in general. We, 
therefore, evaluated the agreement of MammaPrint indices 
between the customized mini-arrays and whole-genome 
arrays for 1897 array sample pairs and between fresh and 
FFPE tissues in 552 tissue sample pairs, and assessed 
reproducibility of [11,000 control samples over the last 10 
years as well as the precision and repeatability of the test. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Samples </p>

<p>Patient samples </p>

<p>MammaPrint indices as reported were collected for all 
patient tumor samples processed for which the sample was 
hybridized to both a customized mini-array and a customized 
whole-genome array (n = 1897 sample pairs, totaling 3,794 
sample hybridizations, 2005-2015), or for which samples 
with both fresh (fresh frozen or RNAretain) and FFPE tissues 
were hybridized to individual arrays (n = 552 totaling 1104 
sample hybridizations (2011-2015)). Data for the fresh 
versus FFPE comparison include the RASTER series [12] 
and a data series described previously by Sapino et al. [6]. 
Clinicopathological data and clinical outcome data were 
available for those 345 of the RASTER patients with mat-
ched samples of fresh and FFPE tissues [5, 12]. Additionally, 
for assessing the analytical performance of MammaPrint, 
indices were collected for fresh and FFPE samples repre-
senting MammaPrint High Risk and Low Risk samples. A 
total of 7 samples were measured for 20 days in duplicate, 
totaling to 280 measurements. 
For this study, only data and not samples were collected. 
All data and analyses used or performed for this study 
comply with the current ethical laws of the Netherlands. 
All patient sample data were anonymized in accordance 
with national ethical guidelines (''Code for Proper Sec-
ondary Use of Human Tissues,'' Dutch Federation of 
Medical Scientific Societies), study samples belonging to 
the used data had Institutional Review Board approvals. 
For this type of study, formal consent is not required. </p>

<p>Control samples </p>

<p>High Risk and Low Risk MammaPrint control samples are 
standardly used as technical and experimental controls 
within each batch run of samples. Data from MammaPrint 
control samples, each composed of a pool of clinically 
representative breast cancer tumors, are continuously 
monitored in the clinical diagnostic setting, and were 
available for stability assessment of MammaPrint test </p>

<p>indices in this study [4, 6, 31]. All control samples were 
processed at one of Agendia's core laboratory facilities in 
Amsterdam (The Netherlands) or Huntington Beach/Irvine 
(California, US) from August 2005 until March 2015, 
totaling n = 11,333 data points for analyses. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Analyses and visualization of data were performed in R (ver-
sion 3.1.1) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">RStudio</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 0.98.994</rs>). All samples had 
passed standard diagnostic quality control criteria [4, 6, 31]. 
Equivalence of MammaPrint indices was determined by 
the Pearson correlation for assessment of the degree of 
linear correlation, and a Passing-Bablok regression analysis 
to obtain the regression equation. Bland-Altman plots were 
used to visually examine the existence of any constant bias 
in the difference of measurements between paired samples. 
The Bland-Altman analysis allows visual identification of 
any proportional error (if data points show an angled linear 
association), systemic error (if the horizontal mean differ-
ence line of the data points is shifted parallel away from 
zero), or dependence of a method on the magnitude of 
measurements (if data points show an association that 
widens or narrows from left to right). 
Clinicopathological data and clinical outcome data of 
the 345 patient samples were analyzed using the statistical 
package <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">22.0</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>, Chicago, US). 
Survival analyses were performed to compare clinical 
performance of fresh and FFPE tissues. Kaplan-Meier 
analyses were used to compare the survival distributions of 
MammaPrint for fresh and FFPE for distant metastasis as 
first event (DMF) and distant recurrence-free interval 
(DRFI). DMF was defined as the time from surgery until 
the diagnosis of a distant metastasis as first event. For 
DMF, patients who present with a local recurrence, 
regional recurrence, or second primary tumor before the 
diagnosis of a distant metastasis were censored at such 
event, at death or at the end of follow-up. DRFI was 
defined as the time from surgery until the diagnosis of a 
first distant metastasis or breast cancer-related death. 
Reproducibility of the MammaPrint test was tested by 
evaluating diagnostic controls over a period of 10 years to 
assess nearly all sources of variation in n = 11,333 sam-
ples. Reproducibility was measured in terms of the relative 
stability, calculated as 100 minus the relative standard 
deviation, where the standard deviation was measured as a 
percentile of the total MammaPrint range [31]. To enable 
assessment of MammaPrint stability of repeated control 
sample measurements over time and independent of control 
sample, MammaPrint indices were centered on their indi-
vidual sample mean per RNA reference type. 
The analytical performance of the current MammaPrint 
fresh and FFPPE versions was assessed in a precision </p>

<p>Breast Cancer Res Treat (2016) 156:279-287 </p>

<p>
evaluation experiment according to the EP2-A5 docu-
mentation [32], as described by Delahaye et al. [31]. This 
analysis included precision and repeatability assessment of 
MammaPrint High Risk and Low Risk samples. Precision 
was determined by calculating the relative precision for 
repeated measurements of High Risk and Low Risk breast 
cancer samples over a period of 20 days. Repeatability was 
determined by calculating the relative stability between 
duplicate runs of the repeated measurements performed 
each day. Both the relative stability and the relative pre-
cision are calculated as 100 minus the relative standard 
deviation. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Equivalence of MammaPrint indices for mini-arrays 
versus whole-genome arrays </p>

<p>In large clinical trials, whole-genome gene expression 
arrays are used at times to enable discovery of expression 
signatures associated with a clinical endpoint of interest, 
alongside certified clinical diagnostic tests such as Mam-
maPrint. To demonstrate the equivalence of FDA-cleared, 
EU IVD-certified MammaPrint between customized mini-
array and customized whole-genome array types, we 
assessed the agreement between MammaPrint index values 
of breast cancer tissues hybridized to both array types 
(Fig. 1). Equivalence was measured using a set of 1897 
samples with matching mini-and whole-genome arrays, 
spanning the MammaPrint index range generally seen in 
diagnostics. MammaPrint indices generated using the 
customized whole-genome array showed an almost perfect 
correlation with the matching indices for the diagnostic 
arrays (r = 0.99, 95 % CI 0.989-0.991). Figure 1 shows 
the scatterplot of the indices showing a tight clustering 
around the 45°line of perfect correlation. This was con-
firmed by the Passing and Bablok regression analysis 
(y = 0.002 ? 1.00x) and a Bland and Altman analysis 
showing no bias in the association of MammaPrint indices 
between mini-array and whole-genome array types (Online 
Resource 1). 
In conclusion, comparison of 1897 mini-array versus 
whole-genome array sample pairs showed equivalence and 
robustness of MammaPrint results between the different 
arrays types both containing the 70 diagnostic Mam-
maPrint probes. </p>

<p>Equivalence of MammaPrint indices from fresh 
versus formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded tissues </p>

<p>The MammaPrint test, originally developed on fresh tis-
sues, was translated to FFPE to facilitate diagnostics and </p>

<p>subsequently cleared by the FDA in 2015 [6, 13]. Tissue 
preservation techniques have been known to generally 
influence array expression profiles [30]. Here, we extend 
our comparison study to examine the compatibility 
between MammaPrint indices results on fresh versus FFPE 
samples in a dataset of 552 sample pairs (Fig. 2). The 
Pearson correlation of the MammaPrint indices calculated 
for the fresh and FFPE tissues was 0.93 (95 % CI 
0.92-0.94). This is an excellent correlation given the data 
are naturally influenced by the heterogeneity within the 
tumor tissue and potential difference in tissue preservation 
techniques. This was confirmed by the Passing and Bablok 
regression analysis (y = -0.076 ? 1.05x) and a Bland and 
Altman analysis showing no relevant bias in the association 
of MammaPrint indices between fresh and FFPE tissue 
types (Online Resource 1). These results confirm the very 
high correlation between fresh and FFPE, which is in line 
with the MammaPrint FFPE FDA clearance [15]. 
In summary, comparison of 552 fresh versus FFPE 
sample pairs showed very high comparability of Mam-
maPrint indices between the tissue preservation techniques. </p>

<p>Impact of tissue preservation technique 
on MammaPrint patient survival prediction </p>

<p>Highly correlated continuous values may result in a lower 
concordance when these continuous variables are presented 
as binary categories. In particular, samples with a result 
close to a classification threshold that have a very small 
difference between two measurements may still result in a 
switch in binary outcome. Therefore, samples in diagnos-
tics with an index close to the MammaPrint classification 
threshold (area predefined) are tested multiple times to </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Equivalence of MammaPrint between customized mini-and 
whole-genome array types. Scatterplot showing equivalence of 
MammaPrint indices between customized mini-microarray used in 
diagnostics (x-axis) and customized whole-genome array (y-axis) 
hybridizations. Each dot represents a single female breast cancer 
sample for which labeled RNA was hybridized to both array types 
(n = 1897 sample pairs) </p>

<p> 
Breast Cancer Res Treat (2016) 156:279-287 </p>



<p>increase measurement precision. We assessed and com-
pared the clinical performance of MammaPrint in a retro-
spective setting to investigate the overall clinical effect of 
samples that have MammaPrint results generated from both 
fresh and FFPE tissues. 
Survival analysis for DMF and DRFI was performed for 
MammaPrint High Risk and Low Risk in a dataset of 345 
early-stage breast cancer patients for which matching fresh 
and FFPE tissues were available (Fig. 3). The Kaplan-
Meier curves (Fig. 3) for DMF and DRFI are similar 
between fresh and FFPE results. Moreover, 5-year survival 
rates for both the Low Risk and High Risk patients groups 
were comparable between fresh and FFPE as shown in 
Table 1. 
Summarizing, we showed clinical equivalence for 
MammaPrint results from fresh and FFPE tissues. </p>

<p>MammaPrint stability over time </p>

<p>To assess the stability of the MammaPrint test over time, 
we investigated the reproducibility of MammaPrint results 
in a large pool of control samples spanning a 10-year 
period, and investigated the precision and repeatability of 
MammaPrint High Risk and Low Risk samples. 
Control samples are used standardly as technical and 
experimental controls within each batch run of samples to 
monitor the quality. A minimum of two control samples are 
processed with each batch run, covering both binary results 
of the MammaPrint test. Stability of MammaPrint indices 
was assessed over a 10-year time period using the control 
samples of Agendia's MammaPrint quality control </p>

<p>monitoring system (n = 11,333). Three different fresh Low 
Risk controls, five different fresh High Risk controls, one 
FFPE Low Risk control and two different FFPE High Risk 
controls were used during this period of 10 years. Once a 
control sample is near depletion, a new control sample is 
created to replace it. Subsequently, both controls are used 
simultaneously for at least 20 measurements to assure the 
quality of the new control sample. Because each control 
sample has a different expected MammaPrint index, indices 
were centered on their individual sample mean to enable 
stability assessment over time independent of control sam-
ple. A data series of Low Risk and High Risk control sample 
measurements for both fresh and FFPE specimen types was 
available for stability assessment: n = 2494 fresh Low Risk, 
n = 4072 fresh High Risk controls (Fig. 4a), and n = 1639 
FFPE Low Risk, n = 3128 FFPE High Risk controls 
(Fig. 4b). MammaPrint indices of these control samples 
were plotted over time (10 years) in a run-sequence plot 
(Fig. 4), demonstrating high stability and reproducibility as 
the same result is generated regardless of scanner used, 
operator, lot, or day. The mean difference of the Mam-
maPrint indices from the sample mean was 0.0295 (95 % CI 
0.0289-0.0301) and 0.0477 (95 % CI 0.0466-0.0488) for 
fresh and FFPE controls, respectively. The standard devia-
tion was 0.0415 for fresh and 0.0619 for FFPE. Repro-
ducibility is given as 100 minus the relative standard 
deviation, 97.9 % for fresh and 96.9 % FFPE, resulting in 
overall reproducibility of 97.4 %, which is very close to the 
original reported value [6, 31]. 
While the reproducibility of the MammaPrint test was 
assessed in control samples consisting of pooled RNA of 
breast cancer samples, the analytical performance of the 
MammaPrint test was determined using (non-pooled) 
individual samples. The analytical performance of Mam-
maPrint fresh and FFPE in this study was assessed by 
determining the precision and repeatability in samples 
representing MammaPrint High Risk and Low Risk results 
that were measured twice per day for 20 days, totaling 280 
measurements. The overall precision was 98.2 % (99.0 % 
for fresh and 97.3 % for FFPE), while repeatability overall 
was 98.3 % (99.0 % for fresh and 97.6 % for FFPE). 
In summary, data on diagnostic control samples of 
Agendia's quality control monitoring system, covering 
10 years, and repeated measurements of samples show that 
the MammaPrint test for both fresh and FFPE is constant 
over time. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The study results show that MammaPrint is a robust and 
stable test, regardless of whether the used array type is a 
customized mini-array or customized whole-genome array, </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Equivalence of MammaPrint between matched fresh and 
FFPE tissue samples. Equivalence was assessed on tumor samples for 
which both the FFPE and fresh tumor samples were analyzed. The 
data are naturally influenced by intrinsic tissue heterogeneity, over 
5 % difference in MammaPrint results can be attributed to hetero-
geneity within the tumor [6, 31]. Each dot represents a single female 
breast cancer sample for which RNA derived from fresh and FFPE 
tissues was hybridized twice to either a customized mini or 
customized whole-genome microarray (n = 552 hybridization pairs) </p>

<p>Breast Cancer Res Treat (2016) 156:279-287 
283 </p>



<p>or the specimen type is fresh or FFPE. The excellent 
reproducibility of MammaPrint indices of control samples 
over the last 10 years and the excellent precision and 
repeatability of MammaPrint High Risk and Low Risk 
samples is further testament to the quality and robustness 
of the MammaPrint test. 
A major strength of our current study lies in the large 
sample size. Almost 2000 sample pairs demonstrated a 
near perfect agreement in MammaPrint index values </p>

<p>between mini and whole-genome array types. Addition-
ally, 552 sample pairs (with clinical data available for 345 
sample pairs) contributed to the comparison between fresh 
and FFPE MammaPrint results, with the results indicating 
excellent agreement. Assessment of the [11,000 control 
samples exemplifies the high stability of the MammaPrint 
results over time. Finally, robustness was shown in the 
280 measurements part of the precision and repeatability 
series. </p>

<p>DMF </p>

<p>DRFI </p>

<p>MammaPrint fresh 
MammaPrint FFPE </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>CumulaƟve Survival </p>

<p>0 
10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0 
10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>Time since surgery (months) </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0 
10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0 
10 20 30 40 50 60 </p>

<p>Time since surgery (months) </p>

<p>CumulaƟve Survival </p>

<p>p=0.001 
p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>p=0.004 
p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Time since surgery (months) 
Time since surgery (months) </p>

<p>CumulaƟve Survival </p>

<p>CumulaƟve Survival </p>

<p>MP Low Risk 
MP High Risk </p>

<p>Legend </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Equivalence in Survival 
data for DMF and DRFI in 345 
patients with matched fresh and 
FFPE samples. Kaplan-Meier 
curves were plotted for DRFI 
and DMF to assess the clinical 
equivalence of MammaPrint 
Low Risk (green lines) and 
High Risk (red lines) between 
matched fresh and FFPE in a 
series of 345 early-stage breast 
cancer patients. The majority of 
the patients that were classified 
as High Risk were treated in an 
adjuvant setting. The majority 
of patients classified as Low 
Risk were untreated. Log Rank 
(Mantel-Cox) p values are 
indicated per analysis </p>

<p>Table 1 Equivalence in 
Survival percentages for DMF 
and DRFI in 345 patients with 
matched fresh and FFPE 
samples </p>

<p>MammaPrint (Fresh tissues) 
MammaPrint (FFPE tissues) </p>

<p>% 
95 % CI 
% 
95 % CI </p>

<p>DMF </p>

<p>Low risk 
97.6 
95.2-100 
98.7 
96.9-100 </p>

<p>High risk 
90.7 
86.0-95.4 
89.9 
85.2-94.6 </p>

<p>DRFI </p>

<p>Low risk 
97.6 
95.2-100 
98.7 
96.9-100 </p>

<p>High risk 
89.1 
84.0-94.2 
88.3 
83.2-93.4 </p>

<p>Survival percentages, at 5 years after surgery, for DMF and DRFI for MammaPrint fresh and FFPE results. 
Survival percentages and their 95 % confidence interval are given for the Low Risk and High Risk groups, 
separately </p>

<p>DMF distant metastasis as first event; DRFI distant recurrence-free interval; FFPE formalin-fixed paraffin-
embedded; %, survival percentage at 5 years since surgery; 95 % CI, ninety-five percent confidence 
interval </p>

<p> 
Breast Cancer Res Treat (2016) 156:279-287 </p>



<p>Other IVD multigene assays are currently available for 
early breast cancer patients, including the Prosigna Breast 
Cancer Prognostic Gene Signature Assay (ProSigna, Seat-
tle, WA, USA [14]), OncotypeDx Breast Cancer Assay 
(Genomic Health, Redwood City, CA, USA [33]), Breast 
Cancer Index (BioTheranostics, San Diego, CA, USA 
[34]), and EndoPredict test (Sividon Diagnostics GmbH, 
Koln, Germany [35]). These assays are dedicated to FFPE 
breast cancer tissues and based on either microarray or 
(RT)-(q)PCR technology. IVD tests, like MammaPrint, 
need to be accurate, reliable, and clinically meaningful. 
Regulation under Clinical Laboratory Improvement 
Amendments (CLIA) is the first crucial step for quality 
control related to laboratories and personnel. To ensure full 
patient safety and quality control of IVD tests, including 
the group of laboratory developed test (LDTs), adhering to 
FDA regulation is essential [36]. For diagnostic tests per-
formed in the EU the equivalent regulatory oversight is the 
EU IVD CE mark and laboratory ISO-certification, 
requirements for which MammaPrint obtained regulatory 
certification as well. MammaPrint was the first of only two 
(MammaPrint and Prosigna Breast Cancer Prognostic Gene 
Signature Assay) of the above described multigene </p>

<p>signatures to obtain IVD CE mark and FDA clearance, for 
which it was required to demonstrate both analytical 
validity and clinical validity [36]. Moreover, MammaPrint 
is the first multigene classifier to publicly demonstrate such 
robust stability over time. Of note is that MammaPrint is 
independent of clinical factors, whereas the Prosigna gene 
signature assay is a combination of gene expression 
assessment (PAM50) and clinical factors (tumor size and 
proliferation score). MammaPrint diagnostic testing, 
including array types, is performed per FDA IVD 510 K 
clearance, or FDA Investigational Device Exempt status 
(IDE) for tests in the US, and EU IVD CE mark, whichever 
is required based on the quality regulatory oversight in 
respective countries. 
Large clinical studies featuring IVDs based on 
microarray technology often use whole-genome arrays to 
enable whole-genome analyses in relation to clinical end-
points of interest alongside the IVD results. This is a major 
advantage of the utility of microarrays for IVDs over RT-
PCR. When diagnostics is generally performed on dedi-
cated microarrays, it is of critical importance to demon-
strate equivalence between the different array types. For 
MammaPrint, we demonstrated that based on the near </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Stability of MammaPrint indices of diagnostic control sam-
ples over time. Stability of MammaPrint indices of MammaPrint High 
Risk and MammaPrint Low Risk control samples measured over a 
period of 10 years (2005-2015) for fresh (a) and 5 years (2011-2015) </p>

<p>for FFPE (b) separately. To enable comparison of the different control 
samples for Low Risk and High Risk, MammaPrint indices were 
centered on their individual sample means (see ''Methods'' section) </p>

<p>Breast Cancer Res Treat (2016) 156:279-287 
285 </p>



<p>perfect agreement (r = 0.99) between different array types, 
study results based on whole-genome arrays similarly 
apply to the current diagnostic setting. 
Previously, special arrangements were made by physi-
cians to obtain a fresh tissue specimen during surgery for 
MammaPrint. To broaden utility, we translated Mam-
maPrint to FFPE, thereby enabling the use of FFPE tissues 
and facilitating the decision of applying a MammaPrint test 
even after surgery of the primary tumor. A comparison 
between fresh and FFPE tissues of the same sample is 
naturally influenced by intrinsic intratumoral heterogeneity 
and differences in tissue preservation techniques [30] that 
are together fully accounting for the observed deviations. A 
difference of 5 % in MammaPrint binary result can be 
attributed to these phenomena [6, 31]. Despite this influ-
ence, comparison between fresh and FFPE demonstrated 
very high agreement (r = 0.93) in both MammaPrint Index 
values [6] and visualized clinical outcome prognosis, 
affirming previously described results [13]. Taken together, 
study results of large clinical studies featuring the 70-gene 
profile MammaPrint, in particular, the MINDACT trial 
whose level 1a evidence results will be available in 2016, 
can be interpreted and transposed to the current diagnostic 
setting based on FFPE tissues without any reservations. 
In summary, study results confirm that MammaPrint 
indices generated from customized mini-arrays show near 
perfect agreement to MammaPrint indices obtained from 
customized whole-genome arrays. Additionally, Mam-
maPrint for fresh and FFPE tissues are robust, equivalent, 
and stable tests (also at the clinical level) in spite of 
influences by tissue heterogeneity and tissue preservation 
techniques. Finally, stability assessment confirmed a very 
high reproducibility, precision, and repeatability of the 
MammaPrint test over time. This combination of high 
equivalence between different array types, between tissue 
types, and high stability over time demonstrates that results 
from clinical trials like MINDACT and I-SPY 2 are similar 
to the current MammaPrint FFPE and fresh diagnostics and 
can be used interchangeably. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments Bas Koster, Tina Treece, and Lisa Blumencranz 
for critically reading the manuscript and helpful discussions. </p>

<p>Ethics For this study, only data and not samples were collected. All 
data and analyses used or performed for this study comply with the 
current ethical laws of the Netherlands. All patient sample data were 
anonymized in accordance with national ethical guidelines (''Code for 
Proper Secondary Use of Human Tissues,'' Dutch Federation of 
Medical Scientific Societies), study samples belonging to the used 
data had Institutional Review Board approvals. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest Authors (except SL) are employed by Agendia 
(RB and LVV part-time) and CD is a consultant for Agendia, the 
commercial entity that markets the 70-gene signature as MammaPrint. 
LVV and RB report being shareholder of Agendia and are named 
inventors on the patent for the 70-gene signature used in this study. </p>

<p>No writing assistance was utilized in the production of this 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which per-
mits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original 
author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons 
license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p> 
Breast Cancer Res Treat (2016) 156:279-287 </p>







</text></tei>