<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4176174" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Mitochondrial RNA polymerases (MtRNAPs) are 
members of the single-subunit RNAP family, the most 
well-characterized member being the RNAP from T7 
bacteriophage. MtRNAPs are, however, functionally 
distinct in that they depend on one or more tran-
scription factors to recognize and open the promoter 
and initiate transcription, while the phage RNAPs are 
capable of performing these tasks alone. Since the 
transcriptional mechanisms that are conserved in 
phage and mitochondrial RNAPs have been so effec-
tively characterized in the phage enzymes, outstand-
ing structure-mechanism questions concern those 
aspects that are distinct in the MtRNAPs, particu-
larly the role of the mitochondrial transcription fac-
tor(s). To address these questions we have used both 
negative staining and cryo-EM to generate three-
dimensional reconstructions of yeast MtRNAP ini-
tiation complexes with and without the mitochon-
drial transcription factor (MTF1), and of the elon-
gation complex. Together with biochemical experi-
ments, these data indicate that MTF1 uses multiple 
mechanisms to drive promoter opening, and that its 
interactions with the MtRNAP regulate the conforma-
tional changes undergone by the latter enzyme as it 
traverses the template strand. </p>

<p>The single subunit RNA polymerases (RNAPs) form a 
widespread family of enzymes that represents a subset of 
the even larger pol A superfamily of nucleic acid poly-</p>

<p>merases (1-3). The first recognized member of this super-
family was DNA Pol I from Escherichia coli, and the best 
characterized member of the single-subunit RNAPs is that 
from bacteriophage T7. In addition to forming part of 
the genomes of many phages, single-subunit RNAP ho-
mologues are encoded in all eukaryotic nuclear genomes 
and are functionally expressed in chloroplasts and mito-
chondria, where they transcribe these organelles' messenger 
and ribosomal RNAs, and also prime replication of their 
genomes (1,2,4,5). 
Comparison of the primary and tertiary structures of the 
single-subunit RNAPs reveals that they all display an ar-
chitecture common to the broader pol A superfamily (3). 
All of these enzymes conserve a polymerase domain that 
contains the catalytic site and the template binding cleft, 
which is shaped like a cupped right hand with thumb, palm 
and fingers subdomains. Different members of this fam-
ily also exhibit structurally distinct domains, N-terminal to 
the polymerase domain, which are responsible for distinct 
functions of different family members. DNAP I, e.g. con-
tains an N-terminal exonucleoytic proofreading domain (6), 
while T7 RNAP displays an N-terminal domain (NTD) that 
participates in sequence-specific promoter interaction and 
binding of the nascent RNA (7,8). The recently described 
structure of the human mitochondrial RNAP (MtRNAP) 
repeats this pattern, as it resembles a T7 RNAP molecule 
to which is appended, at its N-terminus, a ∼370-residue N-
terminal extension domain that is structurally unrelated to 
any elements that have been described in the phage enzymes 
(9). 
The eukaryotic organellar RNAPs are properly described 
as single-subunit enzymes, since all catalytic activities re-
side in a single polypeptide which carries out processive, 
template-directed RNA chain extension without the need 
for any accessory proteins. However, the mitochondrial </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +34 915 854 690; Fax: +34 915 854 506; Email: jmv@cnb.csic.es 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Rui Sousa. Tel: +1 210 567 8782; Fax: +1 210 567 8778; Email: sousa@biochem.uthscsa.edu </p>

<p>Present Address: Srdja Drakulic, Department for Molecular Microbiology and Infection Biology, Centro de Investigaciones Biológicas (CIB-CSIC), Madrid 28040, 
Spain. </p>

<p>C The Author(s) 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 17 11247 </p>

<p>RNAPs are functionally distinct from the phage enzymes 
in that they require one or more transcription factors to 
open the promoter and initiate transcription, though these 
factors are dispensable during transcript elongation (10,11). 
Because fundamental structure-mechanism relationships in 
the phage RNAPs have been so effectively characterized, 
the most important questions for the MtRNAPs concern 
those aspects of structure and mechanism that are dis-
tinct from the phage polymerases. In particular, how does 
the initiation factor(s) function in the transcription cy-
cle? To address this we have used both negative stain-
ing and cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) to gener-
ate three-dimensional (3D) reconstructions of yeast MtR-
NAP:promoter complexes (quasi-ICs); initiation complexes 
(ICs) comprised of promoter, MtRNAP and the yeast mi-
tochondrial transcription factor (MTF1), and elongation 
complexes comprised of MtRNAP, RNA and DNA. To-
gether with biochemical data these 3D reconstructions re-
veal that the transcription factor drives promoter melting 
through multiple mechanisms and that, while the MtRNAP 
goes through a conformational cycle during transcription 
that bears similarity to that seen in the phage RNAPs and 
other pol A enzymes, the MtRNAP conformational cycle is 
distinct in that it is regulated by interactions with the tran-
scription factor. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Enzyme and template preparations </p>

<p>MTF1 and MtRNAP mutants were constructed with the 
Stratagene polymerase chain reaction site directed muta-
genesis kit following manufacturer's instructions. Expres-
sion and purification of mutant polymerases and MTF1 
transcription factor were carried out as described (10), 
except that proteins were expressed by growing cells to 
OD of 0.4 at 37 
• C, following which cultures were trans-
ferred to 16  • C for 30 min, at which point isopropyl ␤-D-1-
thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) was added to induce expres-
sion and the cultures were incubated for a further 24-48 h 
at 16 
• C. Purified proteins were stored at −20 
• C in buffer 
containing 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 0.5 M NaCl, 1 mM 
ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), 5 mM dithiothre-
itol (DTT) and 50% glycerol. DNAs or RNAs were synthe-
sized by Integrated DNA Technologies, dissolved at 1 mM 
concentration in 20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM 
EDTA, and subsequently annealed by mixing with equimo-
lar amounts of complementary oligonucleotides in the same 
buffer, heating to 95 
• C for 5 min, and slow cooling for 2 h 
at room temperature before being stored at −20 
• C. Com-
plexes for EM analysis were prepared by mixing equimolar 
amounts of yeast MtRNAP and annealed templates (with 
or without equimolar MTF1) followed by dialysis for 12-16 
h at 4 
• C into 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM 
EDTA, 2 mM DTT and 50% glycerol with final concentra-
tion of complexes of 10 M. Streptavidin labeled complexes 
were prepared by subsequently adding streptavidin (Sigma-
Aldrich) at 3-fold molar excess (to limit binding of multi-
ple complexes to the tetrameric streptavidin) to complexes 
which had been assembled from DNAs synthesized with bi-
otin at the 5 -ends. To assess complex homogeneity, as well </p>

<p>as to compare complex stability on different promoter tem-
plates in competition experiments, native polyacrylamide 
gel electrophoresis (PAGE) was used. Four microlitre of the 
assembled complexes were electrophoresed on 8-25% poly-
acrylamide gels with native buffer strips on a Pharmacia 
PhastSystem electrophoresis apparatus. Complexes were vi-
sualized by staining with coomassie blue or with a Molecu-
lar Dynamics Storm Imager with complexes assembled with 
DNAs labeled at their 5 -ends with fluorescein. </p>

<p>Transcription assays </p>

<p>In vitro transcription reactions were carried out at room 
temperature for 30 min in 10 l in transcription buffer (50 
mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 10 mM NaCl, 20 mM MgCl 2 , 10 
mM DTT) and nucleoside triphosphates (NTPs) at concen-
trations indicated in individual figure legends and 0.2 M 
template. RNA synthesis was initiated by addition of 0.4 
M yMtRNAP and 0.8 M MTF1. Transcripts were la-
beled by inclusion of 1% (v/v) 3000 ci/mM 10 mCi/ml [␣-
33 P] adenosine triphosphate (ATP) from ICN. Reaction 
samples taken at the time points specified in individual fig-
ure legends were quenched by addition of an equal volume 
of stop buffer (95% formamide, 20 mM EDTA, 0.01% xy-
lene cyanol). Transcription products were resolved by elec-
trophoresis in 20% (w/v) polyacrylamide gels (19% acry-
lamide, 1% bis-acrylamide, 7 M urea) in Tris/Borate/EDTA 
(TBE) buffer and analyzed with a Molecular Dynamics 
Phosphorimager. </p>

<p>Carboxypeptidase Y sensitivity </p>

<p>The sensitivity of MTF1 to carboxypeptidase digestion was 
assessed in experiments with 10 M MTF1 with or with-
out promoter DNA or MtRNAP in transcription buffer 
(minus DTT) with 0.01 /ml of carboxypeptidase Y. Reac-
tion aliquots at different times were taken and stopped by 
adding 1% v/v of a 100 mM PMSF solution in isopropanol. 
Digests were analyzed by denaturing (sodium dodecyl sul-
phate) PAGE on 10% polyacrylamide/bis-acrylamide gels. 
The band corresponding to MTF1 was excised and ana-
lyzed by mass spectrometry. </p>

<p>DNA cleavage with Fe-BABE conjugated proteins </p>

<p>For Iron (S)-1-p-bromoacetamidobenzyl EDTA (Fe-
BABE) cleavage experiments the 5 -end of the template 
(T) or non-template (NT) strands of the DNAs were 
labeled with [␥ -32P]ATP (4000 Ci/mmol; ICN) with T4 
polynucleotide kinase (Invitrogen) as described (12). Fe-
BABE (Dojindo Laboratories) was conjugated to cysteine 
substituted MTF1 or MtRNAPs as described (13). ICs 
halted at +0, +3 or +7, were formed at room temperature 
in transcription buffer containing labeled bubble or duplex 
yeast 14 s rRNA promoter template at 0.01 M, MtR-
NAP at 0.03 M and MTF1 at 0.06 M. After a 10 min 
incubation with varying NTP mixes to form complexes 
halted at different positions, cleavage was initiated by 
addition of sodium ascorbate and H 2 O 2 as described (14). 
Cleavage reactions were quenched after 5 s by addition 
of one reaction volume of stop buffer (95% formamide, </p>



<p>20 mM EDTA, 0.1% xylene cyanol). Cleavage products 
were analyzed by electrophoresis in denaturing 15% poly-
acrylamide gels (14.2% acrylamide, 0.8% bisacrylamide 
and 7 M urea) and visualized on a Molecular Dynamics 
Pphosphorimager. Cleavage positions were mapped by 
reference to Maxam-Gilbert G + A ladder prepared as 
described (15). </p>

<p>Electron microscopy and image processing </p>

<p>Aliquots of the different transcription complexes (quasi-IC, 
upstream labeled quasi-IC, IC, upstream and downstream-
labeled IC, EC, upstream and downstream labeled EC, 
spRNAPIV elongation complex (EC) and downstream 
labeled spRNAPIV EC) were applied onto previously 
glow-discharged carbon-coated copper/rhodium grids and 
stained with 2% uranyl acetate. Images were recorded under 
minimal-dose conditions on Kodak SO-163 film, in a JEOL 
JEM1200EXII microscope operated at 100 kV and 60 000 
magnification. Micrographs were digitized using a ZEISS 
scanner with the step size of 14 m, resulting in a pixel size 
of 2.33Å. 
For cryoEM, aliquots of IC and EC were applied onto 
glow-discharged, holey carbon grids (carbon-coated Quan-
tifoil R 1.2/ R1.3 300 mesh grids) containing an additional 
continuous thin layer of carbon, and plunged into liquid 
ethane. Images were acquired under minimal dose condi-
tions with a Tecnai F20 transmission electron microscope 
at 200 kV. The images were taken at magnification of ∼110 
000 using a 16 megapixel (Mpx) FEI Eagle CCD camera 
with a step size of 15 m, thus the original pixel size of 
the acquired images was 1.37Å. Cryo-EM micrographs 
were downsampled by a factor of 2 or 3 (EC and IC, re-
spectively). The contrast transfer function of the each ac-
quired image was estimated using <rs id="software-6" type="software">CTFFIND</rs><rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">3</rs> program 
(16) and corrected at the micrograph level. Individual par-
ticles were selected manually and extracted using XMIPP 
software (17) (Supplementary Figure S2A). Two types 
of free-pattern maximum-likelihood multi-reference refine-
ment approaches ('<rs type="software">Maximum Likelihood 2D' (ML2D</rs>) (18) 
(Supplementary Figure S2B) and '<rs type="software">Clustering 2D' (CL2D</rs>) 
(19)) were carried out with normalized particles. Homoge-
neous populations were obtained and averaged for a final 
two-dimensional (2D) characterization. 
Several starting reference models and initial 3D recon-
struction steps based on iterative angular refinement were 
performed using the <rs type="software">EMAN</rs> software package (20). In gen-
eral the initial volumes were created upon the class aver-
ages generated in the previous step, using a common lines 
approach or by using artificial noisy models and Gaussian 
blobs with the rough dimensions of the protein complexes. 
In the case of the streptavidin labeled complexes and those 
complexes analyzed by cryo-EM, the previously obtained 
EM maps of non-labeled or negatively-stained complexes 
were filtered to 70Å, and used as the initial models. The dif-
ferent strategies converged to similar solutions, and one of 
the models was selected to complete the refinement (Supple-
mentary Figure S2C). However, in the case of heterogeneity 
(EC cryo-EM; streptavidin-biotin labeled ICs) the most sta-
ble model was subjected to maximum likelihood 3D classifi-
cation (<rs type="software">ML3D</rs>) (18) to address this problem. The separated </p>

<p>particles were processed using <rs type="software">EMAN</rs> and the whole 3D re-
construction cycle was repeated de novo. The resolution of 
the reconstructions was determined by the FSC 0.5 criterion 
(Supplementary Figure S3), and these values were used to 
low-pass filter the final volumes. The visualization of den-
sity maps and atomic structures was performed using <rs type="software">UCSF Chimera</rs> (21). The dockings were firstly performed manu-
ally and then rendered by <rs type="software">Chimera</rs>, using a real time cor-
relation criterion between the reference model (final model) 
and the surface created from the atomic structure/model. 
The final validation of the obtained models was performed 
by comparison of the final 3D map projections and the gen-
erated class averages (<rs type="software">EMAN</rs>) with the results of 2D classi-
fications (Supplementary Figure S2B). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Structural characterization of yeast MtRNAP IC without 
MTF1 ('quasi IC') </p>

<p>Formation of the yeast mitochondrial initiation complex 
(IC) requires yeast MtRNAP (1324 residues) and MTF1 
(341 residues) which, together, form a stable complex with 
a duplex mitochondrial promoter DNA (11,22). A stable 
complex can also be assembled between the MtRNAP alone 
and a 'pre-melted' promoter (Supplementary Figures S1A-
C; bubble promoter or 'IC DNA') bearing sequence changes 
in the NT strand to create a mismatched +2 to −4 region 
(10). Because we wanted to identify MTF1 and MtRNAP 
in the 3D reconstruction of the IC, we sought to image 
ICs formed without MTF1 (quasi-ICs) as well as true ICs 
formed with both proteins. It is, however, possible that com-
plexes formed on the pre-melted promoters do not gen-
uinely recapitulate the structures of complexes formed on 
fully duplex promoters. We therefore used chemical nucle-
ases tethered to cysteines introduced into MTF1 or MtR-
NAP to compare the structure of ICs formed on duplex ver-
sus pre-melted promoters. We observed that these nucleases 
cut the promoter DNA at nearly identical locations on both 
types of promoters, and that, upon addition of NTPs that 
allowed extension of the RNA to different lengths, these 
cleavage sites shifted identically on both the fully duplex and 
pre-melted promoters (Supplementary Figures S1D and E). 
The ICs formed on the pre-melted and duplex promoters 
are therefore structurally and functionally similar. 
A total of 12848 images of negatively stained particles 
formed with the MtRNAP and a 29 bp promoter DNA 
in which the −2 to +4 region was heteroduplex were used 
to generate a 3D reconstruction of a quasi-IC (Figure 1A 
and B; see also Supplementary Figures S2 and S3A), re-
vealing a compact structure. The pol A class polymerases 
display a polymerase domain with the shape of a cupped 
right hand that forms a cleft in which the DNA binds. This 
central cleft is apparent in the 3D reconstruction of the 
quasi-IC, but is narrower than typically seen in other pol-A 
class polymerases (Figure 1C). The narrowness of this cleft 
in the quasi-IC seems to correspond to the 'clenched' con-
formation with a constricted central binding cleft observed 
in human MtRNAP (23) (Figure 1A), and this notion is 
strengthened by a better docking correlation value with this 
atomic structure (PDB ID: 3SPA; 0.85) than with that of </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 17 11249 </p>

<p>Figure 1. A yeast MtRNAP quasi-IC assumes a clenched conformation while the IC assumes an open state. (A) The 19Å resolution yeast MtRNAP 
quasi-IC structure reconstructed from 12848 negatively stained particles assembled from MtRNAP and a 29 bp pre-melted promoter DNA. Docked into 
the 3D reconstruction is the atomic structure of DNA-free human MtRNAP (PDB ID: 3SPA (23)) with residues 218-383 (N-terminal extension domain) 
in green, residues 384-672 (the N-terminal domain or NTD) in orange and residues 673-1230 (C-terminal, polymerase, catalytic domain) in purple. (B) As 
in (A), but with the atomic structure of human MtRNAP EC (PDB ID: 4BOC (24)) docked in; the DNA is not shown) (C) The quasi-IC 3D reconstruction 
rotated as indicated and cut at the plane indicated by the red line. (D) The IC reconstruction rotated as indicated and cut at the plane indicated by the 
red line (E) Difference map (gray volumes) generated by subtracting the IC from the quasi-IC with the atomic structure of MTF1 (PDB ID: 1I4W; blue) 
placed on the large density difference. </p>

<p>mtRNAP EC (PDB ID: 4BOC; 0.84) (Figure 1B), but spe-
cially by a 3D reconstruction of quasi-IC with DNA labeled 
with streptavidin at its upstream end ('upstream strepta-
vidin quasi-IC'), generated from 16514 particles (Supple-
mentary Figure S3B; 18Å resolution) in which the strep-
tavidin molecule (and therefore the 5 -end of the NT-strand 
DNA) is located closer to the polymerase domain. These 
results point to the yeast MtRNAP in quasi-IC having a 
clenched conformation </p>

<p>Yeast MtRNAP IC with MTF1 assumes an open conforma-
tion </p>

<p>To compare the quasi-IC conformation to that of a true 
IC, we carried out a 3D reconstruction of the IC at 22 
A resolution (Figures 1D, 2A and Supplementary Figure 
S3D) using 15917 negatively stained particles formed with 
yeast MtRNAP, MTF1 and the 29 bp pre-melted promoter 
DNA (Supplementary Figure S1B). Both our native gels 
and inspection of EM fields of negatively-stained quasi-
ICs and ICs indicated that the quasi-IC had a tendency 
to oligomerize that was suppressed in the IC. The excep-</p>



<p>Figure 2. Positioning MTF1 in the IC. (A) Two orthogonal views of the 3D reconstruction of yeast MtRNAP IC with MTF1 (blue) and the atomic 
structure of yeast MtRNAP (modeled on the human MtRNAP structure) fit into the reconstruction. The yeast MtRNAP N-terminal extension (residues 
240-383), NTD (residues (384-672) and the polymerase domain (residues 673-1233; 1317-1351) are in green, orange and purple, respectively, while the 
atomic structure of MTF1 is in blue. (B) The same two views of the 3D reconstruction of yeast MtRNAP IC with MTF1 generated from unstained, frozen 
particles. Docking as in (A). </p>

<p>tional homogeneity of the IC particles and their relatively 
large size (∼210 kDa) prompted us to attempt an EM re-
construction of the IC by cryo-EM. A total of 10 893 par-
ticles were used to generate a 15Å resolution 3D recon-
struction of the IC (Figure 2B and Supplementary Figure 
S3C). Comparison of the IC reconstructions obtained by 
negative staining and cryo-EM show them to be very similar 
(compare Figure 2A and B; see also Supplementary Figure 
S3C and D). We therefore aligned these two reconstructions 
and both docked well with the atomic structure of human 
MtRNAPEC (the correlation coefficient values were 0.84 
and 0.81 for the docking into the EM structures originating 
from frozen and negatively stained samples, respectively). In 
human MtRNAP, the transition from the clenched, DNA-
free to the open, elongation state involves the rotation of the 
palm and fingers domains by 10 
• and 15 
• , respectively. The 
resulting conformation of human MtRNAP in EC resem-
bles to that of the intermediate IC of T7 RNAP, the state 
with a 7 nts long RNA (24). Thus, we suggest that the con-
formation of MtRNAP in the IC is closer to the EC than to 
the clenched form found in the quasi-IC. Indeed, the IC as 
a whole, and the central, template-binding cleft, were found 
to be wider than in the quasi-IC (compare the cavities in the 
structures shown in Figure 1C and D). </p>

<p>Localization of MTF1 in the IC </p>

<p>The shape of the largest density element in the difference 
map obtained by subtraction of the IC from the quasi-IC 
is similar to the atomic structure of MTF1 (Figure 1E). 
MTF1 is a dumbbell-shaped molecule comprised of a larger 
mixed helical/sheet NTD and a smaller, helical C-terminal 
domain (25). Overall, the molecule has concave and convex 
sides that, together with the differences in the sizes of the 
two lobes of the dumbbell, allow us to orient the MTF1 with 
the C-terminal domain at the narrower end of the differ-
ence density and with the concave side facing the MtRNAP 
(Figures 1E and 2). This positions MTF1 in the IC with its 
concave and more electropositive side facing the electropos-
itive surface of the MtRNAP which forms the DNA and 
RNA binding sites of the polymerase (Figures 2 and 3; see </p>

<p>also Supplementary Figures S3C and D). The two 3D re-
constructions therefore indicate that MTF1 binds the IC so 
as to sandwich the DNA between the electropositive sur-
faces of the polymerase and the transcription factor. </p>

<p>Localization of DNA in the IC </p>

<p>To better reveal how the DNA binds in these complexes 
we carried out 3D reconstructions of negatively stained ICs 
formed with DNAs in which either the upstream (5 -NT 
strand end) or downstream (5 -T strand end) segments were 
labeled with biotin and then reacted with streptavidin. The 
3D reconstruction of the IC with streptavidin labeling the 
upstream end of DNA ('upstream streptavidin IC') reveals 
an extra density, appropriate for accommodating the strep-
tavidin molecule, connected to the NTD of the MtRNAP 
by a tube of density (Supplementary Figure S3F). Interest-
ingly, the position of the streptavidin matches the position 
of the upstream DNA termini of the aligned 3E2E atomic 
structure, the structure of T7RNAP IC with a 7 nts long 
RNA (Figure 4B). Furthermore, this part of the DNA is lo-
cated near the positively charged cleft and at the end of the 
C-terminal domain (C-terminal tail) of MTF1, the MtR-
NAP's C-terminal domain, the AT-rich recognition loop 
and intercalating ␤ hairpin, which as seen in the T7RNAP 
IC, inserts between the T and NT strands at the upstream 
edge of the transcription bubble (26,27). To identify the 
downstream segment of the DNA we generated a 3D re-
construction of an IC in which the downstream DNA end 
was labeled with streptavidin bound to biotin linked to the 
5 -end of the T strand ('downstream streptavidin IC'), re-
vealing an extra density that is not occupied by the atomic 
model of the IC (Supplementary Figure S3E). This density 
is appropriate in size and shape to accommodate the 50 kDa 
streptavidin tetramer, and sits adjacent to the N-terminal 
extension (Figure 4A). The position of the downstream end 
of DNA in 3E2E clashes with the NTD of MTF1, which 
suggests its placement deeper in the extended binding cleft 
formed by the MtRNAP and MTF1, also indicating it to be 
less accessible to streptavidin binding. Thus, the positions 
of upstream and downstream termini of DNA in the yeast </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 17 11251 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Localization of Fe-BABE cleavage sites on MTF1:IC-DNA models. Each panel shows the MTF1 structure (25) in surface representation with 
−, + and uncharged regions in red, blue and white, respectively. The DNA is in stick representation with the T-strand in cyan and the NT-strand in green. 
The DNA is placed on MTF1 as proposed in our IC model based on steric considerations, EM data, the positions of the intercalating hairpin (stacked 
on the −4 bp) and active site aspartates (nearest the T-strand +2 ribose), and the positions of the sites cut by Fe-BABE conjugated to different sites on 
MTF1. In each panel the position of the residue(s) to which Fe-BABE was conjugated is labeled and highlighted in yellow, and the centers of the sites of 
cleavage by those conjugates are indicated by showing the corresponding DNA nucleotides in space-filling representation. For the conjugates to residues 
332 and 340 , which correspond to residues on the disordered C-terminal tail of MTF1, the magenta arrow shows the possible position of the C-terminal 
tail based on the observation that conjugates to either of these residues cut within the unwound region of the promoter. </p>



<p>Figure 4. Localization of DNA in the IC. (A) Difference map (light blue volumes) generated by subtracting the IC from the downstream streptavidin IC 
with the atomic structure of streptavidin (PDB ID : 1N43: gray) placed on the large density difference. The atomic structure of T7RNAP in the 7 nts RNA 
long IC state (PDB ID : 3E2E) has been aligned with the previously fitted atomic structure of human MtRNAPEC. The 3E2E DNA molecule (NT strand 
dyed in yellow and T strand in cyan) is shown, with downstream and upstream ends emphasized by blue and yellow spheres. (B) Two views of the difference 
map (yellow volume) generated by subtracting the IC from upstream streptavidin IC. The position of the upstream 3E2E DNA's end is located within the 
reach of the streptavidin molecule (C) Two views of the difference map (gray volume) generated by subtracting the upstream streptavidin quasi-IC from 
quasi-IC. The docked atomic structure of human MtRNAP (PDB ID: 3SPA) is shown together with the DNA of aligned atomic structure of T7RNAP at 
3 nts long RNA IC state (PDB ID: 1QLN). The DNA length has been adjusted according to (D). NT and T strands are colored as in (A) and (B), yellow 
and cyan respectively. (D) Schematic representation of DNA sequence of 3E2E, top and of one used in this study, bottom, to form quasi-IC and IC. The 
boxed ATA sequence of NT-strand is not visible in the 3E2E atomic structure. The upstream edges of transcription bubbles are taken as a reference point 
for the alignment, allowing the adjustment of 3E2E DNA's length according to the length of the DNA used in this study. (E) Docked atomic structure of 
PDB ID: 3SPA shown with the original aligned 3E2E DNA (left) and adjusted DNA (right). </p>

<p>IC are close to their position in the T7RNAP IC with a 7 
nts long RNA (the late IC). This, together with the struc-
tural resemblance of these polymerases strongly suggests 
that yeast MtRNAP in complex with MTF1 acquires a con-
formation similar to the T7RNAP late IC. 
This raises a question of how the quasi-IC, with its nar-
rower cleft, binds DNA. When the 3D reconstructions of 
quasi-IC and IC, both with DNA labeled with streptavidin 
at their upstream end are compared (Supplementary Figure 
S3B and F, respectively), it can be observed that the strep-
tavidin in the quasi-IC is located closer to the polymerase 
domain than in IC (compare Figure 4B and C). Thus, bind-
ing of MTF1 is associated with an increased bending of the 
DNA in the complex and binding of the upstream segment 
of the promoter toward regions on the MtRNAP NTD(s), 
consistent with previously reported differential bending of 
promoter DNA by yeast MtRNAP alone versus the yeast 
MtRNAP:MTF1 complex (28). A similar change in DNA 
bending is observed in T7RNAP in the initiation steps 
of transcription--upon the incorporation of the 7th nu-</p>

<p>cleotide to the nascent RNA molecule, the N-terminal part 
of the enzyme (residues 72-152 and 191-267) and the speci-
ficity loop are rotated ∼45 
• (29). This rigid body rotation 
does not affect the contacts with the promoter, causing its 
additional bending. We have aligned the atomic structure of 
the T7RNAP IC with a 3 nts RNA (PDB ID: 1QLN (30) 
with the docked atomic structure of human MtRNAP. If 
the upstream edges of transcription bubbles are taken as a 
reference point (since the intercalating ␤ hairpins which in-
sert at the upstream edge of the transcription bubble play 
similar roles in T7RNAP and yeast MtRNAP transcrip-
tion initiation (27)), then the upstream end of the IC DNA 
used in this study can be modeled on the DNA of 1QLN 
(Figure 4D and E). The modeled position is in the range 
of the upstream streptavidin molecule that represents the 
experimentally defined position of the upstream DNA ter-
minus (compare Figure 4C and E). The conformation of 
T7RNAP without the DNA and with the DNA and 3 nts 
long RNA, is similar. However, the specificity loop and ␤-
intercalating hairpin become structured upon DNA bind-</p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 17 11253   ing. The same can be observed for these elements when the 
DNA-free and DNA-bound structures of human MtRNAP 
are compared. This, together with the position of the up-
stream end of the DNA in the quasi-IC, which matches that 
in the T7RNAP IC with 3 nts RNA, suggest that, in the 
absence of MTF1, DNA-free and DNA-bound MtRNAP 
assume a similar conformation. </p>

<p>Chemical nucleases tethered to MTF1 inform IC modeling </p>

<p>To test and refine our structural model of IC generated 
from the EM images of the quasi-IC and IC, and of the 
streptavidin-labeled complexes, we used the chemical nucle-
ase p-bromoacetamidobenzyl ethylenediaminetetraacetate 
(Fe-BABE (31)) conjugated to MTF1 cysteines. Upon re-
action with peroxide, Fe-BABE generates a local burst of 
diffusible hydroxyl radicals that cut nearby DNA strands, 
with the intensity of cutting determined by distance and ac-
cessibility. MTF1 conjugated with Fe-BABE cut both T and 
NT DNA strands in an IC (Supplementary Figure S4B). 
To determine which of the various MTF1 cysteines was 
conjugated with the Fe-BABE that was generating these 
cuts, we individually mutated each of the two surface ex-
posed cysteines on the DNA-binding face of MTF1 (C69 
and C192) to serines (mutation of buried cysteine residues 
caused MTF1 to aggregate during expression. There are two 
other surface exposed cysteines in MTF1: C220 and C320. 
C220 is on the side the opposite to that which is identified 
as binding DNA, while C320 is within the C-terminal tail of 
MTF1 that is disordered in the crystal structure of MTF1 
alone). Mutation of C69 did not affect cleavage patterns 
(not shown), but the C192S mutation almost completely 
eliminated the cleavage observed with the wild-type protein 
(Supplementary Figure S4A and B), indicating that cutting 
was due to Fe-BABE conjugated to C192 (a C192F muta-
tion has been reported to compromise MTF1 function but 
we found that a C192S mutant had WT activity (Supple-
mentary Figure S4I-M), suggesting that the isosteric ser-
ine substitution is less disruptive of MTF1 activity than the 
phenylalanine substitution). 
We then generated nine other individual cysteine substi-
tutions in the C69S/C192S mutant MTF1 background, ex-
pressed and purified these mutants, and conjugated them 
with Fe-BABE. All of the mutants were in surface exposed 
residues and were found to be similar in activity to the 
WT protein (Supplementary Figure S4I). ICs were formed 
with these Fe-BABE conjugated MTF1 mutants on a 63 bp 
DNA containing the active 14 s mitochondrial promoter 
with base changes introduced into the −4 to +2 region of 
the NT strand to create a heteroduplex region to enhance 
IC stability (cutting patterns on fully duplex promoters were 
modestly weaker but otherwise similar to those on the bub-
ble promoter; Supplementary Figures S1B and S4A-H). 
The DNA in the ICs was labeled at the 5 -end of either the T 
or NT strand with 33P and cutting was activated by adding 
peroxide to open complexes (no NTPs), or complexes in 
which NTPs allowing RNA extension to three or seven nu-
cleotides were present. The data set of all these cutting pat-
terns is presented in Supplementary Figures S4A-H, and is 
summarized in Figure 3. </p>

<p>The cleavage patterns of the conjugated MTF1 proteins 
were consistent with the model suggested by the EM 3D 
reconstructions, MTF1 was placed in the IC so that the du-
plex down-and upstream segments of the DNA were near 
the positively charged surface of the NTD and the positively 
charged region at the border of the N-and C-terminal do-
mains, respectively (Figure 3). The most N-terminal con-
jugate was at residue 78 and cleaved DNA only at posi-
tions downstream of the transcription bubble (Supplemen-
tary Figure S4A), while the most C-terminal conjugates 
within the C-terminal domain (at position 296 and 300) 
only cut DNA upstream of the unwound region (Supple-
mentary Figure S4F). Conjugates at intermediate positions 
(192/230/240) cut both up-and downstream DNA (Sup-
plementary Figures S4B, D and E), consistent with the 
DNA being sharply bent in the IC so that both up-and 
downstream DNA segments were accessible to hydroxyl 
radicals generated at these residues. The finer scale features 
of these cutting patterns also helped to refine the approx-
imate location of MTF1 and DNA in the IC: cutting by 
conjugates at position 192 was nearest to the apex of the 
DNA bend (at positions −7/−3/+9/+10, while cutting by 
the conjugate at 230 was furthest from the unwound re-
gion (−17/−11/−8/+12/+18/+21) and the conjugate at 
240 cut at intermediate positions (−11/−8/+9/+11). These 
cutting sites therefore indicated that MTF1 and the DNA 
should be modeled so that residues 192, 240 and 230 de-
fine an axis approximately centered on the apex of the bent 
DNA and extending parallel to the up-and downstream du-
plexes, with residue 192 closest to the apex and residue 230 
most distant (Figure 3). This placement of MTF1 is consis-
tent with the conclusion that the transcription factor inter-
acts with the unwound NT-strand to favor promoter melt-
ing, and with our observations that MTF1 binds quasi-ICs 
formed with promoters that contain a melted NT-strand 
more strongly than promoters that are missing the melted 
NT-strand (Supplementary Figure S4J-M). 
Cutting by conjugates attached to residues in the MTF1 
C-terminal tail was also informative. The last 16 residues of 
the MTF1 C-terminal tail, starting from the residue 325, are 
disordered in the crystal structure of the protein alone (25). 
Conjugates at residues 332 or 340 within this C-terminal 
tail cut the NT strand in the IC between −2 and +7, and 
the T strand between −5 and −2 (Figure 3 and Supple-
mentary Figure S4H). These cuts are either within or im-
mediately up-or downstream of the unwound DNA in the 
IC and suggest that, upon binding DNA, the C-terminal 
tail becomes ordered and inserts between the melted DNA 
strands where it may contribute to promoter opening. Con-
sistent with this, we observed that MTF1 binding to the IC 
protected its C-terminus from digestion by carboxypetidase 
(Supplementary Figure S5A). </p>

<p>The MTF1 C-terminal tail contributes to promoter opening </p>

<p>The functional role of the C-terminal tail of MTF1 was 
then tested by comparing the transcriptional activity and 
stability of ICs formed with full-length MTF1 or MTF1 
with the 17 most C-terminal residues deleted (residues 325-
341; corresponding to the disordered region in the MTF1 
crystal structure; MTF Cterm). We observed that on du-</p>



<p>plex promoters, the transcriptional activity in reactions with 
MTF Cterm was as high (or higher) than that obtained 
with full-length MTF1 when the concentration of the ini-
tiating NTP (ATP) was high. However, at low initiating 
NTP concentrations the activity in the MTF Cterm re-
actions was markedly reduced compared to those carried 
out with full-length protein. A similar difference in activity 
at high versus low ATP concentrations with MTF Cterm 
versus full-length MTF1 was not observed on pre-melted 
promoters (Supplementary Figure S5B and C). Other mea-
surements, including the sensitivity of ICs to varying salt 
levels and the rates of dinucleotide synthesis as a function 
of varying ATP concentrations, similarly indicated a spe-
cific deficiency in the activity of MTF Cterm ICs on du-
plex, but not pre-melted, promoters (Supplementary Fig-
ures S5D and E). Fitting of these data showed apparent 
K ATP to be 4-8-fold greater with MTF Cterm versus full-
length MTF1 on duplex promoters, but identical within ex-
perimental error on pre-melted promoters (Table 1). </p>

<p>The structure of the yeast MtRNAP elongation complex 
(EC) </p>

<p>We undertook a similar set of EM studies of the yeast MtR-
NAP EC. A synthetic transcription bubble was formed by 
hybridizing a 10 base RNA to the 5 -segment of a 21 base 
T-strand annealed to a 21 base NT-strand which was non-
complementary to the 10 bases at the 5 -end of the T-strand 
(Supplementary Figure S1C; 'EC DNA'). Native gel anal-
ysis showed that MtRNAP formed a stable complex with 
this nucleic acid scaffold and extension assays revealed that 
the RNA was quantitatively extended in a T-strand directed 
manner by the MtRNAP upon addition of NTPs (Sup-
plementary Figure S1F), confirming that the complexes 
formed with this scaffold were functional. Both gel analy-
sis and inspection of EM fields revealed that the ECs were 
highly homogeneous, so we carried out reconstructions of 
the EC by both cryoEM of unstained, frozen-hydrated par-
ticles (9538 particles, 19Å resolution) and negative stain-
ing (20 873 particles, 19Å resolution). Both 3D reconstruc-
tions were very similar (Figure 5A and B; see also Supple-
mentary Figure S6A and B). We also carried out a 3D re-
construction with negatively-stained particles of an EC as-
sembled with an MtRNAP from which residues 1-243 had 
been deleted, corresponding to a putative nuclear version 
of the polymerase that has been dubbed spRNAPIV (32). 
The 3D reconstruction of the spRNAPIV EC was very sim-
ilar to the negatively stained or cryoEM reconstructions of 
the full-length MtRNAP ECs (Figure 5C; see also Supple-
mentary Figure S6E), with no additional density apparent 
in the full-length reconstructions that could be clearly as-
signed to the element deleted in the spRNAPIV EC (Figure 
5A-C). The difference maps obtained by subtracting MtR-
NAP EC from spRNAPIV EC also failed to show any ob-
vious density that could be assigned to the region deleted 
in spRNAPIV. Therefore, it is probably that the N-terminal 
region deleted in spRNAPIV is either wholly or partially 
disordered and does not contribute to the density in the av-
eraged 3D reconstructions of the full-length MtRNAP. This 
would be consistent with what is observed with both hu-
man MtRNAP structures (PDB IDs: 4BOC (24) and 3SPA </p>

<p>(9)), in which residues 1-105 were deleted to enhance crys-
tallization, and in which residues 106-217 are disordered 
and invisible in the electron density map (23). The atomic 
structure of human MtRNAPEC (24) fits well into all of the 
three 3D reconstructions of EC shown here (Figure 5A-C; 
see also Supplementary Figure S6A,B and E). </p>

<p>Localization of DNA in the EC </p>

<p>The length and sequences of EC DNA scaffolds used in this 
study and in the atomic structure of human MtRNAPEC 
(24) are not identical. However, the downstream edge of 
two transcription bubbles can be used as reference point for 
alignment, which allows modeling of the position of the EC 
DNA termini (Figure 5D and E). To confirm this, we car-
ried out 3D reconstructions of negatively stained ECs as-
sembled with nucleic acid scaffolds in which either the up-
stream or downstream DNA ends were labeled with strep-
tavidin (Supplementary Figure S6C and D and Figure 5F 
and H). The difference in the positions of both the upstream 
and downstream DNA termini as modeled from the hu-
man MtRNAP EC structure and as experimentally deter-
mined by positions of the streptavidin molecules is ∼15Å 
(in the case of upstream DNA termini this discrepancy is 
even smaller as the 5 NT end of DNA used in this study is 
in the single stranded form, comparing to the correspond-
ing nucleotide at position −10 of DNA in 4BOC). Since 
the resolution of our structures is in the 15-25Å range, 
this represents excellent quantitative agreement between the 
human MtRNAP EC crystal structure and our EM recon-
structions. 
Using the positions of the streptavidin molecules to com-
pare the positions of the DNA IC and EC reveals a clear 
displacement of its upstream end during the transition from 
the IC to EC (Figure 6A and B). To test this further we 
conjugated Fe-BABE to cysteines introduced into the MtR-
NAP C-terminal domain on the thumb (at residue 780) and 
fingers subdomains (at residues 1025, 1074 and 1078), and 
on the NTD (at residue 493). The conjugates on the thumb 
and fingers subdomains cut DNA either within or immedi-
ately downstream of the transcription bubble in both the IC 
and EC, and generally tracked the downstream movement 
of the RNAP as the RNA was extended (Figure 6C; the con-
jugate on the thumb also showed discontinuous changes in 
cutting during initial transcription, as is also seen in similar 
experiments with T7RNAP (13)). However, the conjugate 
on the NTD exhibited cutting in ICs, but not the EC, con-
sistent with the observed displacement of the upstream end 
of DNA 
The N-terminal extension domain appears to be involved 
in formation of the downstream edge of the transcrip-
tion bubble (33), which led us to ask ourselves if the N-
terminal deletion in spRNAPIV might affect DNA bind-
ing to EC. To address this, we generated a 3D reconstruc-
tion of spRNAPIV and DNA labeled with streptavidin at its 
downstream end (see Supplementary Figures S6E and F). 
In the 3D reconstruction of the spRNAPIV EC the strep-
tavidin molecule is located at a similar position as in the 
downstream labeled version of the full length MtRNAP EC 
(compare Figure 5F and G), indicating that the deletion 
does not grossly alter the position of the downstream DNA. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 17 11255 </p>

<p>Figure 5. 3D reconstruction of the EC. (A) 3D reconstruction of the yeast MtRNAP EC generated from unstained, frozen particles. The atomic structure 
of human EC (PDB ID: 4BOC (24)) is fitted into the 3D reconstruction (correlation coefficient 0.74). (B) As in (A), but for a 3D reconstruction generated 
from negatively stained particles. The atomic structure of human EC (PDB ID: 4BOC (24)) is fitted into the 3D reconstruction (correlation coefficient 
0.84). (C) As in (B), but for ECs prepared with an MtRNAP from which the first N-terminal 243 residues were deleted (spRNAPIV EC). The atomic 
structure of human EC (PDB ID: 4BOC (24)) is fitted into the 3D reconstruction (correlation coefficient 0.92). (D) Left: schematic representation of EC 
DNA scaffold used in (24). Template and non-template strands are dyed in cyan and yellow, respectively. Cyan: 28 nts long non-template strand with 
nucleotides not visible in X-ray structure indicated by dashed squares; Orange-yellow: 28 nts long template strand with nucleotide not visible in X-ray 
structure indicated by dashed square; Red: 14nts long RNA. Underlined nucleotides are ones that form a transcription bubble. Right: docking of the 
human MtRNAPEC (PDB ID: 4BOC) in the cryo-EM map of yeast MtRNAPEC, obtained in this study. Template and non-template strands are dyed in 
cyan and yellow, respectively. Upstream (5 NT) and downstream (5 T) DNA termini are emphasized with spheres colored in yellow and cyan respectively. 
(E) Left: schematic representation of EC DNA scaffold used in this study, aligned with the DNA presented in (A), using the upstream edge of transcription 
bubble as a reference, alignment point. 21 nts long template and non-template strands are dyed in orange (yellow) and cyan, respectively, while 10 nts long 
RNA in red. Underlined nucleotides are ones that form a transcription bubble. Right: docking of the human MtRNAPEC (PDB ID: 4BOC) in the cryo-EM 
map, obtained in this study. Template and non-template strands are dyed in cyan and yellow, respectively. Positions of the upstream (5 NT) and downstream 
(5 T) DNA termini, shown with spheres colored in yellow and cyan respectively, are adjusted according to the alignment. (F) Difference map in which the 
3D reconstruction of negatively stained EC was subtracted from the 3D reconstruction obtained from EC particles in which the downstream DNA end 
was labeled with streptavidin ('downstream streptavidin EC'). The scale bar indicates a difference in positions of expected, theoretical (blue spheres) and 
experimental (streptavidin) downstream end of DNA (5 terminus of NT strand) (G) Difference map in which the 3D reconstruction of negatively stained 
spRNAPIV EC was subtracted from the 3D reconstruction obtained from spRNAPIV EC particles in which the downstream DNA end was labeled with 
streptavidin ('downstream streptavidin spRNAPIV EC') (H) As in (F), but this time the subtraction is performed between the 3D reconstruction of EC 
and a 3D reconstruction of EC in which the upstream end of the DNA is streptavidin-labeled ('upstream streptavidin EC'). </p>



<p>Figure 6. Displacement of the upstream end of DNA during the IC-EC transition. (A) Difference map (gray volume) generated by subtracting the IC 
from the upstream streptavidin IC with the atomic structure of streptavidin (gray) placed on the large density difference. The docked atomic structure of 
human MtRNAPEC (PDB ID: 4BOC, DNA not shown) and the DNA of aligned T7RNAPIC (3E2E) are shown and labeled as in Figure 5. (B) As in 
(A) but the subtraction is between EC and 'upstream streptavidin EC'. (C) Cleavage patterns of Fe-BABE molecules conjugated to the mtRNAP suggest 
conformational differences between the N-terminal domains of the IC and EC. Each panel shows the cleavages on either the NT-or T-strands, as indicated, 
in reactions with mtRNAP conjugated with Fe-BABE at the indicated residue positions. 'G/A' = markers used to map the cleavage sites with respect to 
the +1 transcription start site; '−' and '+' refer, respectively, to absence or addition of ascrobate/peroxide to activate cleavage (low levels of cutting are seen 
even in the absence of ascorbate/peroxide). NTPs allowing RNA extension to 0-13 nt, as indicated, were added to the reactions. Each panel also shows 
the MtRNAP structure in surface representation with −, + and uncharged regions in red, blue, and white, respectively. The DNA is in stick representation 
with the T-strand in green and the NT-strand in cyan. The position of the residue(s) to which Fe-BABE was conjugated is labeled and highlighted in yellow, 
and the centers of the sites of cleavage by those conjugates are indicated by showing the corresponding DNA nucleotides in space-filling representation 
(T-strand cleavage by conjugates at residues 780, 1025, 1074 and 1078 is not shown as it was very low, likely reflecting the fact that the proximal part of the 
T-strand is buried in the template binding cleft and inaccessible). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 17 11257 </p>

<p>Table 1. Apparent K ATP values for initiation from 14 s bubble or duplex promoter templates (values in M and +/− S.E. for n = 4-5) and in either the 
absence of MTF1 (bubble templates only) or in the presence of WT MTF1 or MTF Cterm </p>

<p>Bubble NoMTF1 
Bubble + MTF1 </p>

<p>Bubble + 
MTF1 Cterm 
Duplex + MTF1 </p>

<p>Duplex + 
MTF1 Cterm </p>

<p>110 ± 8.0 
167 ± 19 
197 ± 43 
66 ± 8.9 
579 ± 70 
Dinucleotide 
24 ± 4.0 
78 ± 17 
107 ± 27 
52 ± 15 
420 ± 70 
Total 
29 ± 4.0 
44 ± 7.1 
31 ± 11 
43 ± 8.7 
151 ± 17 
Runoff </p>

<p>Values were determined by measuring the rate of dinucleotide synthesis in reactions with ATP only, or the rates of incorporation of NTPs into all transcripts 
('Total') or only runoff transcript in reactions with all four NTPs (three NTPs at constant concentration and ATP varied). Deletion of the MTF1 C-terminus 
is seen to markedly increase K ATP for initiation on duplex, but not bubble, templates. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Pol A class polymerases are characterized by conforma-
tional changes during their reaction cycles that involve 
opening and closing of the central template binding cleft 
around which these enzymes are organized. Rotation of the 
fingers subdomain toward the cleft accompanies binding 
of NTP or dNTP, while rotation of the fingers away from 
the cleft, causing it to become more open, occurs upon 
pyrophosphate release at the end of the nucleotide addi-
tion cycle (6-8,34-36). In addition to this transition, which 
is common to all pol A class enzymes, individual mem-
bers of this family display distinct conformational changes, 
often involving distinct domains N-terminal to the com-
mon polymerase domain. In T7 RNAP, e.g. rotation of the 
NTD away from the polymerase domain progressively en-
larges the template binding cleft to accommodate the grow-
ing RNA:DNA hybrid as the RNA is extended during ini-
tial transcription (37). A subsequent, large-scale conforma-
tional change in the NTD occurs upon transition to elon-
gation, and ruptures promoter:RNAP interactions to allow 
promoter release and movement down the template DNA 
(7,34,36). 
Human MtRNAP, in the absence of DNA or transcrip-
tion factors, crystallized in a 'clenched' conformation that is 
more closed than any of the conformational states observed 
in the homologous T7 RNAP enzyme (23). Given the con-
formational malleability of these proteins, it is important 
to validate the physiological significance of the conforma-
tions observed in crystal structures because these conforma-
tions can be influenced by packing interactions or extreme 
crystallization solution conditions. Our EM data indicate 
that, under near-physiological solution environments, yeast 
MtRNAP assumes a tightly closed conformation similar 
to the clenched human MtRNAP state. The clenched con-
formation therefore appears to be a physiologically rele-
vant state. Interestingly, the upstream ends of the DNAs 
seem to be similarly positioned in the characterized yeast 
quasi-IC and T7RNAP IC with 0 or 3 nts long RNA. This 
could mean that upon binding to MtRNAP, bubble or even 
duplex promoter DNAs assume a topology similar to the 
DNAs in the T7RNAP early ICs with 3-nt long RNAs. 
However, as revealed by streptavidin labeling, the up-
stream end of the promoter in the quasi-IC is positioned 
far from the AT-rich recognition loop in the NTD of the 
mtRNAP, and is therefore less bent than the DNA in the 
IC. The latter interactions may be required to induce the 
sharp bending required for promoter opening. This could 
also explain why yeast MtRNAP alone is capable of start-</p>

<p>ing transcription from bubble promoters, but not from du-
plex ones. Additionally, yeast MtRNAP alone binds rela-
tively weakly to DNA and with relatively poor sequence 
specificity. MTF1 increases the stability and sequence speci-
ficity of the initiation complex (27,28). It is possible that, in 
the absence of MTF1, MtRNAP assumes a clenched con-
formation that associates weakly and non-specifically with 
DNA so that it can efficiently scan DNA for promoter se-
quences (Figure 7, quasi-IC). Encounter with a promoter 
could transiently slow this scanning to allow MTF1 bind-
ing, inducing the isomerization to the open state coupled 
with an increase of the DNA bending in the complex, as re-
vealed by the different positions of streptavidin in this study, 
and consistent with previously reported differential bending 
of promoter DNA by yeast MtRNAP alone versus the yeast 
MtRNAP:MTF1 complex (28). Our EM data reveal how 
the MtRNAP and the MTF1 engage to form a functional 
IC, indicating that the upstream end of the DNA is brought 
into close proximity with the AT rich recognition loop of 
the NTD, which, together with MTF1, form a specific bind-
ing site for the upstream (−4 to −9 bp) promoter sequence 
(Figure 7, IC). As is also seen in T7RNAP, sequence spe-
cific binding of the promoter would therefore involve the 
NTD(s) and the promoter recognition loop (12,26), but 
would also involve MTF1, which generates promoter speci-
ficity through the conformational changes it induces in the 
polymerase and possibly also by making direct, sequence-
specific interactions with the promoter. The sharp bending 
of the promoter in the IC complex would bring the DNA 
closer to the AT rich recognition loop, which would have 
a stabilizing effect on the MtRNAP:MTF1:DNA complex 
and would help drive promoter melting (28), as would inter-
actions between MTF1 and the unwound NT strand (38), 
and between the MTF1 C-terminal tail and the melted re-
gions of the promoter (39). 
Published data do not clearly define the interaction be-
tween MtRNAP and MTF1. Deletions of the N-terminal 
and the C-terminal regions of MTF1 resulted in the ab-
sence or decreased yield of IC (40), suggesting the involve-
ment of multiple regions in the MtRNAP:MTF1 inter-
action. Genetic screening has led to the identification of 
point mutations that cause loss or drastic decrease in mi-
tochondrial transcription. These mutants are distributed in 
three clusters: region 1 (Y42C, H44P and L53H), region 2 
(V135A, L154T and K157E) and region 3 (S218R, I221K 
and D225G). Mapping of these regions on the X-ray struc-
ture of MTF1 has revealed that they are not only facing 
different surfaces, but also that several of them are located 
in the interior of the protein (Supplementary Figure S7A-</p>



<p>Figure 7. Modeling the transition from quasi IC to EC. The C-terminal-catalytic domain, the NTD, AT-rich recognition loop (residues 450-470) and the 
N-terminal extension and are represented by contours in purple (magenta), orange, black and green, respectively. The template and non-template DNA 
strands are colored yellow and cyan, respectively. The quasi-IC is characterized by a narrow template binding cleft and DNA binding that is not highly 
sequence specific. Binding of MTF1 to the quasi-IC (not shown in the cartoon) induces opening of the template binding cleft by rotation of the fingers and 
palm domains. The isomerization to the open state is coupled with additional bending of the upstream end of DNA, which is brought close to the NTD and 
the AT-rich recognition loop, which together with MTF1, form a sequence-specific binding site for the upstream regions of the promoter. Upon transition 
to elongation and dissociation of MTF1, the template binding cleft remains open with N-terminal regions not undergoing an extensive remodeling, as seen 
in T7RNAP, while the upstream end of DNA moves away from the NTD and the AT-rich recognition loop. </p>

<p>C), implying that they affect the structural integrity of the 
MTF1 rather than binding to MtRNAP (25). One of the 
proposed models (39) takes into account only those muta-
tions that are in surface exposed residues: H44P of region 1, 
K157E of region 2 and all the amino acids of region 3, thus 
defining the interface where these residues are positioned 
as MTF1 s surface involved in interaction with MtRNAP. 
However, mutations R178A/K179A and H187A/R189A, 
which are located in the basic cleft at the interface of NH2 
and COOH terminal subdomains, were previously shown to 
inactivate transcription on linear but not supercoiled DNA 
promoters (41), but are not accommodated in this model. 
A low-resolution structure of the human mtRNAP IC gen-
erated by EM and image processing has been recently re-
ported (42) which reveals a completely different position for 
the transcription factors than that observed in this work for 
MTF1. However, we believe that the mentioned work suf-
fers from certain problems, among others the low number 
of particles used in the study and the absence of any ex-
perimental evidence regarding the location of the individ-
ual components which could have led to an incorrect or-
ganization of the IC (Supplementary Figure S7D and E). 
Our structural study provides a more precise and in-depth 
insight into the organization of IC state, complementing 
and allowing the evaluation of information gathered by bio-
chemical and biophysical approaches (25,39,43,44). Thus, 
our EM study shows for the first time how these two pro-
teins interact and, furthermore, excludes these hypothetical 
models, as the region 3 and the remaining superficially ex-
posed amino acids of region 1 and 2 are placed at the oppo-
site, outer face of MTF1. Additionally, our data places the 
positively charged cleft of MTF1 toward the MtRNAP and 
the DNA (Supplementary Figure S7B and C). </p>

<p>Transcription initiation requires the formation of stable 
and specific interactions between the RNAP and the pro-
moter, which lead to its bending and tension accumulation. 
This tension is released through the promoter melting and 
formation of the upstream edge of transcription bubble, 
generally in the AT rich regions of the promoters. In T7 
RNAP three structural elements-(1) the AT rich recogni-
tion loop (residues 93-101); (2) the specificity loop (residues 
739-770); and (3) the intercalating ␤-hairpin including 
Val237 (residues 230-245) are responsible for the promoter 
recognition, binding and melting. RNAPs remains bound 
to their promoters as the RNA is extended to a length that 
triggers promoter release and transition to elongation. The 
T7RNAP IC to EC transition involves large structural rear-
rangement of the entire NTD and specificity loop, resulting 
in the loss of all contacts with the promoter and the forma-
tion of the RNA exit channel (34). The C-terminal, catalytic 
domain undergoes fewer conformational changes. Our EM 
reconstructions of MtRNAP IC and EC reveal that, con-
sistent with what has been previously observed (9,24), that 
the N-terminal part of protein, unlike in T7RNAP, does not 
change conformation during the IC-EC transition (Figure 
7, EC). Unlike what is seen with T7RNAP, promoter re-
lease and transition to elongation do not depend on confor-
mational changes in the promoter binding elements of the 
mtRNAP. Instead, MtRNAPs recruit dissociable transcrip-
tion factor(s) which, in the initiation phase of transcription 
drive a transition from a clenched to an open conforma-
tion in the mtRNAP, and allow for promoter recognition, 
melting and stabilization of the IC. Subsequently, these fac-
tors become displaced and allow promoter release once the 
RNA reaches a length sufficient for formation of a stable 
MtRNAP:DNA:RNA complex. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2014, Vol. 42, No. 17 11259 </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACCESSION NUMBERS </p>

<p>PDB IDs: 3SPA, 4BOC, 1I4W, 1N43, 3E2E and 1QLN. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation [BFU2010-
15703, BFU2013-44202 to J.M.V.]; National Institutes of 
Health [GM0502522 to R.S.]. La Caixa foundation fel-
lowship [to S.D.].Funding for open access charge: Spanish 
Ministry of Science and Innovation [BFU2013-44202] [ to 
J.M.V.]. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







</text></tei>