<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4686099" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The aim of the present study was to investigate the 
protective effects of melatonin (MLT) on hypertension-induced 
renal injury and identify its mechanism of action. Twenty-four 
healthy male Wistar rats were divided into a sham control group 
(n=8), which was subjected to sham operation and received 
vehicle treatment (physiological saline intraperitoneally at 
0.1 ml/100 g), a vehicle group (n=8), which was subjected to 
occlusion of the left renal artery and vehicle treatment, and 
the MLT group (n=8), which was subjected to occlusion of 
the left renal artery and treated with MLT (10 mg/kg/day). 
Pathological features of the renal tissues were determined 
using hematoxylin and eosin staining and Masson staining. 
Urine protein, serum creatinine (Scr), superoxide dismutase 
(SOD) and malondialdehyde (MDA) were determined. 
Immunohistochemical analysis was performed to determine the 
expression of heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1), intercellular adhesion 
molecule-1 (ICAM-1), inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) 
and endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS). Furthermore, 
reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction was conducted 
to determine the mRNA expression of HO-1, ICAM-1, eNOS 
and iNOS. A marked decrease in blood pressure was noticed 
in the MLT group at week 4 compared with that of the vehicle 
group (P&lt;0.01). Furthermore, MLT treatment attenuated the 
infiltration of inflammatory cells and oedema/atrophy of renal 
tubules. MLT attenuated hypertension-induced increases in 
urine protein excretion, serum creatinine and MDA as well 
as decreases in SOD activity in renal tissues. Furthermore, 
MLT attenuated hypertension-induced increases in iNOS and 
ICAM-1 as well as decreases in eNOS and HO-1 expression 
at the mRNA and protein level. In conclusion, the results of 
the present study indicated that MLT had protective roles in </p>

<p>hypertension-induced renal injury. Its mechanism of action is, 
at least in part, associated with the inhibition of oxidative stress. </p>

<p>In animals with hypertension-induced renal injury, excessive 
accumulation of oxygen free radicals was observed together 
with down-regulation of antioxidase, indicating that oxidative 
stress has a crucial role in hypertension-induced renal injury (1). 
Reactive oxygen species (ROS), including superoxide radicals, 
hydrogen peroxide and hydroxyl radicals, have been reported 
to be closely associated with the pathogenesis of hypertension 
and renal damage (2,3). The underlying mechanisms may be 
as follows: i) ROS affects vascular resistance via inactivating 
nitric oxide, resulting in arteriolar vasoconstriction and eleva-
tion of peripheral hemodynamic resistance; and ii) ROS may 
cause lesions in renal tissues (4). 
Increasing evidence has revealed that hypertension is 
an independent risk factor for end-stage renal disease (5,6). 
However, the exact mechanism has remained to be sufficiently 
defined. It has been indicated that oxygen free radicals are able 
to trigger the elevation of blood pressure by inactivating nitric 
oxide, which finally raises the systemic vascular resistance (7). 
Reactive oxygen species also induce cellular injury and 
contribute to fibrosis and formation of atherogenic oxidized 
lipoproteins (8). Based on these facts, the present study 
hypothesized that the hypertension-induced renal injury is, at 
least in part, due to elevated generation of oxygen free radicals. 
Melatonin (MLT) has been reported to ameliorate renal 
ischemic re-perfusion injury through its radical-scavenging 
activity (9,10). However, only few studies have been conducted 
to investigate its roles in hypertension-induced renal injury (11). 
The present study aimed to investigate the roles of MLT in 
hypertensive rats with renal damage. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Animals. Healthy male Wistar rats (weighing 180-220 g) 
were purchased from the Laboratory Animal Center of 
Shanxi Medical University (Taiyuan, China). The rats were 
housed with a 12 h light/dark cycle, at 37˚C, in an atmosphere </p>

<p>Melatonin attenuates hypertension-induced renal injury 
partially through inhibiting oxidative stress in rats </p>

<p>YU-FENG QIAO 
1,2 , WEN-JUAN GUO 
1 , LU LI </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>, SHAN SHAO </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, XI QIAO 
1 , </p>

<p>JIN-JIN SHAO 
1 , QIONG ZHANG 
4 , RONG-SHAN LI 
4 and LI-HUA WANG </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Department of Nephrology, Second Hospital of Shanxi Medical University; 
2 School of Medicine, Second Clinical College Affiliated to Shanxi Medical University, Taiyuan, Shanxi 030001; 
3 Department of Nephrology, Baoding No. 1 Hospital, Baoding, Hebei 071000; 
4 Department of Nephrology, </p>

<p>Shanxi People's Hospital, Taiyuan, Shanxi 030001, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received October 7, 2014; Accepted June 25, 2015 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/mmr.2015.4495 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Professor Li-Hua Wang, Department of </p>

<p>Nephrology, Second Hospital of Shanxi Medical University, 
382 Wuyi Road, Xinghualing, Taiyuan, Shanxi 030001, P.R. China 
E-mail: lhwang017@126.com </p>

<p>Key words: melatonin, hypertension, oxidative stress, renal injury </p>

<p>QIAO et al: ROLES OF MLT IN HYPERTENSION-INDUCED RENAL INJURY </p>



<p>containing 75% humidity. All animal were provided with 
ad libitum access to food and water. All the experiments were 
performed according to the Principles of Laboratory Animal 
Care (NIH Publication no. 86-23, revised 1985) and the 
regulation of the Committee on the Use and Care of Animals 
of Fudan University (Shanghai, China), and approved by the 
Ethics Committee of the Shanxi Medical University (Taiyuan, 
China). </p>

<p>Preparation of hypertensive rats. The animals were subjected 
to occlusion of the left renal artery as previously described (12). 
In brief, the rats were anesthetized using 10% chloral hydrate. 
The renal artery of the left kidney was exposed and clipped 
with an artery clamp. In the sham control group, a sham 
procedure, which included the entire surgery expect the artery 
clipping, was applied. </p>

<p>Experimental design. Rats were divided into a sham control 
group (n=8), which was subjected to sham operation and 
received vehicle treatment (physiological saline intraperi-
toneally at 0.1 ml/100 g), a vehicle group (n=8), which was 
subjected to occlusion of the left renal artery and vehicle 
treatment, and the MLT group (n=8), which was subjected to 
occlusion of the left renal artery and injected intraperitone-
ally with MLT (10 mg/kg/day; Cayman Chemical Company, 
Ann Arbor, MI, USA). The animals were sacrificed with 10% 
chloral hydrate (Huayueyang Biotech Co. Ltd., Beijing, China) 
at week 12 after treatment. </p>

<p>Creatinine assay. Determination of serum creatinine was 
performed by Jaffe's reaction (13). In brief, aortic blood 
samples were obtained and centrifuged to separate the serum. 
Serum creatinine was determined with an automated system 
(Express 550 Analyzer; Ciba Corning Diagnostic Corp, East 
Walpole, MA, USA). </p>

<p>Determination of urine protein. Urine samples were collected 
24 h prior to scarification of the animals with sterilized devices 
(Metrical GRID Trade Co., Ltd, Kunshan, China). The urine 
protein concentration was determined using the Coomassie 
Brilliant Blue G-250 (product code B-0770; Sigma-Aldrich, 
St. Louis, MO, USA) method as previously described (14). </p>

<p>Malondialdehyde (MDA) assay and superoxide dismutase 
(SOD) assay. MDA in the renal tissues was determined using a 
kit purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, UK; cat. no. ab118970) 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. The activity of 
SOD was determined using the SOD assay kit (cat. no. KT-034; 
Kamiya Biomedical Company, Seattle, WA, USA) using the 
V-5100H spectrophotometer (Shanghai Metash Instruments 
Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China). </p>

<p>Pathological analysis. For the pathological analysis, the renal 
tissues were treated using conventional procedures, including 
formalin fixation, dehydration and embedding. Subsequently, 
the sections (3 µm) were stained using hematoxylin and eosin 
(H&amp;E; Alfa Aesar, Shanghai, China) and Masson's trichrome 
(Sigma-Aldrich), respectively. The pathological results were 
evaluated by two members of staff blinded to the study. The 
degree of injury was evaluated according to the damaged 
area of renal tubules using the following scoring system: 0, 
no injury; 1, injury in &lt;10%; 2, injury in 11-25%; 3, injury 
in 26-45%; 4, injury in 46-75%; and 5, injury in &gt;75% of the 
observed area. The evaluation was performed in 10 randomly 
selected fields in each slice, and was observed under a magni-
fication of 200x. </p>

<p>Reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) 
analysis. In the present study, the mRNA expression of 
heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1), intercellular adhesion molecule-1 
(ICAM-1), inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) and endothe-
lial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS) was determined using RT-PCR 
amplification. Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent 
TRIzol (Invitrogen Life Technologies, Shanghai, China). 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. The first-strand 
cDNA was synthesized with a random primer (Sangon Biotech 
Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China) using the SuperScript III reverse 
transcriptase (Invitrogen Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, 
USA). PCR amplification was performed using the primers 
and amplification conditions listed in Table I. GAPDH was 
amplified under the same reaction conditions, accordingly, to 
serve as the internal standard. Finally, the PCR products were 
electrophoresed on 1.5% agarose gels and analyzed using a 
Gel Documentation E-Gel 
® Imager system (Invitrogen Life 
Technologies). </p>

<p>Table I. Primer sequences and amplification conditions of reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>Gene 
Primer sequence (5'-3') 
Amplification conditions </p>

<p>iNOS 
F, CAGGTGCTATTCCCAGCCCAACA 
94˚C for 3 min; 30 cycles of 94˚C for 30 sec, 
R, CATTCTGTGCAGTCCCAGTGAGGAA 
61˚C for 30 sec and 72˚C for 60 sec; 72˚C for 5 min </p>

<p>eNOS 
F, TTCTGGCAAGACCGATTACACGACAT 
94˚C for 3 min; 30 cycles of 94˚C for 30 sec, 
R, AAAGGCGGAGAGGACTTGTCCAAA 
55˚C for 30 sec and 72˚C for 60 sec; 72˚C for 5 min </p>

<p>HO-1 
F, GGGAAGGCCTGGCTTTTTT 
94˚C for 3 min; 30 cycles of 94˚C for 30 sec, 
R, CACGATAGAGCTGTTTGAACTTGGT 
56˚C for 30 sec and 72˚C for 60 sec; 72˚C for 5 min </p>

<p>ICAM-1 
F, GTGAGCGTCCATATTTAGGCATGG 
94˚C for 3 min; 30 cycles of 94˚C for 30 sec, 59.6˚C 
R, ACAGACACTAGAGGAGTGAGCAGG 
for 30 sec and 72˚C for 60 sec; 72˚C for 5 min </p>

<p>GAPDH 
F, AACGACCCCTTCATTGAC 
94˚C for 3 min; 30 cycles of 94˚C for 30 sec, 57.8˚C 
R, TCCACGACATACTCAGCAC 
for 30 sec and 72˚C for 60 sec; 72˚C for 5 min </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 13: 21-26, 2016 </p>



<p>Immunohistochemical analysis. Immunohistochemical 
analysis based on the Streptavidin-Biotin Complex was 
performed according to a previously published method (15). 
The primary antibodies were HO-1 (1:300; cat. no. sc-136960; 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., Dallas, TX, USA), ICAM-1 
(1:150; cat. no. sc-1511; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), 
iNOS (1:100; cat. no. sc-650; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, 
Inc.) and eNOS (1:200; ab195944; Abcam). β-Actin (1:200; 
cat. no. sc-130301; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) served 
as the loading control. Horseradish peroxidase-conjugated 
secondary antibodies were purchased from the Gene Tex Inc. 
(Irvine, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. The data are presented as the mean ± stan-
dard deviation. Student's t-test and χ 
2 test were performed 
to carry out inter-group comparisons. Data analysis was 
performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS, Inc.</rs>., Chicago, 
IL, USA). P&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate a statistically 
significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>MLT attenuates hypertension-associated increases in blood 
pressure. The blood pressure in each group was monitored at 
weeks 0, 4, 6, 8 and 12 of MLT treatment. Compared with 
the sham control group, a significant increase in blood pres-
sure was observed in the vehicle group at weeks 4, 6, 8 and 
12 (P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 1). In the MLT group, a significant increase 
in blood pressure was observed at weeks 4, 6 and 8 (P&lt;0.05). 
However, MLT treatment significant attenuated the hyperten-
sion-induced increase in blood pressure at week 12 compared 
with that in the vehicle group (P&lt;0.01). </p>

<p>MLT attenuates hypertension-induced increases in urine 
protein excretion and serum creatinine. The excretion of </p>

<p>urine protein and the concentration of serum creatinine were 
markedly elevated in the vehicle group compared with those in 
the sham control group (P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 2A and B). In the group 
treated with MLT, the increases in urine protein and serum 
creatinine were attenuated compared with those in the vehicle 
group (P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 2A and B). </p>

<p>MLT attenuates hypertension-induced decreases of SOD and 
increases of MDA in renal tissues. The SOD activity in renal 
tissues showed marked decrease in the vehicle group compared 
with that in the sham control group (P&lt;0.01) (Fig. 2C). In the 
vehicle group, the expression of MDA was markedly increased 
compared with that in the sham control group (P&lt;0.01) 
(Fig. 2D). Of note, the activity of SOD was rescued and the 
expression of MDA was attenuated by treatment with MLT 
(P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>MLT reduces the infiltration of inflammatory cells and 
oedema/atrophy of renal tubules after hypertension-induced 
renal injury. H&amp;E staining and Masson's staining was performed 
to determine the pathological features of the renal tissues. In 
the sham control group, the renal tissues were clearly presented, 
and the renal tubular epithelial cells were intact and aligned in 
order. In the vehicle group, vacuolar degeneration and granular 
degeneration was revealed in the renal tubular epithelial cells. 
Infiltration of inflammatory cells, oedema and atrophy of renal 
tubules were also observed. Of note, these pathological changes 
were attenuated in the group treated with MLT (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>MLT modulates the expression of iNOS, eNOS, HO-1 and 
ICAM-1. Immunohistochemical analysis showed that iNOS, 
eNOS, HO-1 and ICAM-1 were mainly expressed in the cyto-
plasm of the renal tubular epithelial cells (Fig. 4). A minority 
of iNOS protein was detected in the nuclei as well. In addi-
tion, ICAM-1 was also detected in renal parenchyma. In the </p>

<p>Figure 1. MLT decreases the blood pressure in rats with renal injury. Prior to sacrification of the animals, the blood pressure was monitored at weeks 0, 4, 6, 
8 and 12. No statistical difference was observed in the blood pressure at the baseline levels between the different groups. The blood pressure was markedly 
increased in the vehicle group compared with that in the sham control. After treatment with MLT, a significant decrease in the blood pressure was observed 
at week 12 compared with that in the vehicle group. The data are presented as the mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01, compared with sham control group; 
# P&lt;0.01, compared with vehicle group. MLT, melatonin. </p>

<p>QIAO et al: ROLES OF MLT IN HYPERTENSION-INDUCED RENAL INJURY </p>



<p>sham control group, the expression of ICAM-1 and iNOS was 
weakly positive; however, their expression was enhanced in 
the hypertensive rats. Compared with the vehicle group, the 
expression of iNOS and ICAM-1 was significantly attenuated 
in the MLT group. The expression of HO-1 and eNOS was 
significantly decreased in the vehicle group compared with 
that in the sham control group. However, in the rats treated 
with MLT, the expression of HO-1 and eNOS was significantly 
increased compared with that in the vehicle group. In parallel </p>

<p>with the protein expression of iNOS, eNOS, HO-1 and ICAM-1, 
RT-PCR showed the same effects of hypertension and MLT 
treatment on the associated mRNA expression levels (Fig. 5): 
iNOS and ICAM-1 mRNA was elevated in the hypertensive 
rats compared with that in the animals of the sham control 
group, while these increases were attenuated by treatment 
with MLT. With regard to the mRNA expression of HO-1 and 
eNOS, a significant decrease was observed in the hypertensive 
rats, which was rescued by MLT treatment (P&lt;0.01). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Expression of urine protein, serum creatinine, SOD and MDA at week 12 in different groups. (A) MLT was able to reduce the expression of urine protein 
in rats with renal injury induced by hypertension. (B) MLT modulated the expression of serum creatinine in rats with renal injury induced by hypertension. 
(C) MLT increased the SOD activity in rats with renal injury induced by hypertension. (D) The expression of MDA was reduced in the animals with administra-
tion of MLT. The data are presented as the mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01, compared with sham control group; 
# P&lt;0.01, compared with vehicle group. SOD, 
superoxide dismutase; MDA, malondialdehyde; MLT, melatonin. </p>

<p>Figure 3. HE staining and Masson staining of the renal tissues (magnification, x200). MLT, melatonin; HE, hematoxylin and eosin. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 13: 21-26, 2016 </p>



<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Oxidative stress has been considered to have important roles 
in the genesis and development of hypertension-induced renal 
injury (16). The present study aimed to investigate the protec-
tive effects of MLT, an effective anti-oxidant, in hypertensive 
rats. The results indicated that MLT attenuated in creases in 
blood pressure as well as renal injury in hypertensive rats. 
Proteinuria has been reported to be clearly associated with 
an increased risk of mortality in patients with chronic kidney 
disease (17). To date, urine protein and serum creatinine have 
been recognized as effective screening tools for the substan-
tial risks associated with proteinuria (18,19). In the present 
study, the excretion of urine protein and serum creatinine was 
elevated in the vehicle group at week 12, indicating reduced 
renal function. Pathological analysis at week 12 indicated 
severe injury of the right renal tubule, which was characterized </p>

<p>by an aberrant structure, vacuolar degeneration and granular 
degeneration of renal tubular epithelial cells, infiltration of 
inflammatory cells, as well as oedema and atrophy of the renal 
tubules. Of note, in the group treated with MLT, the excretion 
of urine protein and the concentration of serum creatinine was 
markedly reduced compared with that in the vehicle group. In 
addition, the pathological changes were attenuated, including 
alleviation of vacuolar degeneration, granular degeneration of 
renal tubular epithelial cells and oedema of renal tubules. All 
of these results demonstrated that MLT exerted a protective 
effect against renal injury in hypertensive rats. 
In a previous study, abnormalities in the lipid peroxidation 
were observed in patients with renal disorders (20). MDA is a 
product of lipid peroxidation induced by oxidants and oxida-
tive stress (21), and has been speculated to have important roles 
in the pathogenesis of renal diseases. In the present study, the 
generation of MDA in renal tissues was elevated in the vehicle </p>

<p>Figure 4. Immunohistochemical analysis of iNOS, eNOS, HO-1 and ICAM-1. Magnification, x400. Arrows indicate positive staining. MLT, melatonin; HO-1, 
heme oxygenase-1; iNOS, inducible nitric oxide synthase; eNOS, endothelial nitric oxide synthase; ICAM-1, intercellular adhesion molecule-1. </p>

<p>Figure 5. MLT modulates the mRNA expression of iNOS, eNOS, HO-1 and ICAM-1 genes. Lanes: M, marker; 1, sham control group; 2, vehicle group; 3, MLT 
group. GAPDH served as the internal standard. MLT, melatonin. </p>

<p>QIAO et al: ROLES OF MLT IN HYPERTENSION-INDUCED RENAL INJURY </p>



<p>group, indicating that oxidative stress generated in the kidneys 
also contributed to the elevation of blood pressure. However, 
the increases of MDA were attenuated in the group treated 
with MLT. SOD constitutes the first line of defence against 
reactive oxygen species (22). In the present study, the activity 
of SOD was markedly increased in the MLT group compared 
with that in the vehicle group. All of these results indicated 
that MLT reduced oxidative stress in renal tissues. 
In normal renal tissues, the expression of iNOS is compara-
tively low; however, in renal tissues with pathologic disorders, 
its expression is significantly upregulated, and is considered 
the main source for the generation of nitric oxide, which is a 
major effector molecule of hypertension (23). Under normal 
pathological conditions, eNOS is the major source of nitric 
oxide; however, in renal tissues with pathological lesions, a 
de-coupling process of eNOS was induced, which resulted 
in the generation of O 2-(24). Finally, massive apoptosis and 
necrosis were reported in renal tubular epithelial cells following 
hypertension (24). In the present study, the expression of iNOS 
was markedly upregulated in the hypertensive vehicle group, 
which was attenuated in the group treated with MLT. With 
regard to eNOS, the expression in the vehicle group was mark-
edly downregulated, which was attenuated in the group treated 
with MLT. Based on these results, it was speculated that the 
mechanism of action of MLT may involve the elevated genera-
tion of nitric oxide in renal tubular epithelial cells through 
downregulating the generation of iNOS and upregulation of 
eNOS in renal tissues, finally resulting in a decrease in blood 
pressure and attenuation of renal tubular injury. 
The expression of ICAM-1 reflects the infiltration of 
inflammatory cells (25). In the vehicle group, the expression 
of ICAM-1 was markedly increased, which was attenuated in 
the group treated with MLT. HO-1 has been reported to have 
protective effects in renal tissues, serving as the rate-limiting 
enzyme of catalyzing hemocrystallin into biliverdin and 
carbon monoxide (26). In the present study, the expression of 
HO-1 was markedly reduced in the vehicle group compared 
with that in the sham control. However, treatment with MLT 
rescued HO-1 levels following hypertension. It is therefore 
speculated that MLT has protective effects against renal injury 
through inhibiting the infiltration of inflammatory cells and 
enhancing the expression of HO-1. 
In conclusion, MLT was able to alleviate hypertension and 
associated renal injury in rats. This protective effect may be 
associated with the reduction of oxidative stress, inhibition 
of infiltration of inflammatory cells and the enhancement of 
anti-oxidant molecules by MLT. </p>



</text></tei>