<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4823393" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives: Prehospital hypothermia is defined as a </p>

<p>core temperature &lt;36.0°C and has been shown to be 
an independent risk factor for early death in patients 
with trauma. In a retrospective study, a possible 
correlation between the body temperature at the time 
of admission to the emergency room and subsequent 
in-hospital transfusion requirements and the in-hospital 
mortality rate was explored. </p>

<p>Setting: This is a retrospective single-centre study at a </p>

<p>primary care hospital in Germany. </p>

<p>Participants: 15 895 patients were included in this </p>

<p>study. Patients were classified by admission 
temperature and transfusion rate. Excluded were 
ambulant patients and patients with missing data. </p>

<p>Primary and secondary outcome measures: The </p>

<p>primary outcome values were length of stay (LOS) in 
days, in-hospital mortality, the transferred amount of 
packed red blood cells (PRBCs), and admission to an 
intensive care unit. Secondary influencing variables 
were the patient's age and the Glasgow Coma Scale. </p>

<p>critical health condition. Hypothermia in 
combination with acidosis and coagulopathy 
is known as the lethal triad of death. 3 
Hypothermia alters enzymatic reactions of 
the coagulation cascade during the initiation 
phase and decreases platelet function, 3 4 pos-
sibly leading to severe bleeding and consecu-
tively required blood transfusion. It has been 
shown that the amount of applied fluids and 
transfused packed red blood cell (PRBC) is 
directly linked to hypothermia, is associated 
with a worse clinical outcome, 5 6 and 
increases the risk of postoperative mortality. 7 
Acute complications after PRBC transfusion 
can comprise hypothermia, hypocalcaemia, 
hypomagnesiaemia, citrate toxicity, lactic 
acidosis and air embolism. 8 Additionally, </p>

<p>Strengths and limitations of this study </p>

<p>▪ Using a retrospective design, we investigated the 
effects of prehospital hypothermia on patient 
in-hospital mortality, length of hospital stay, 
intensive care unit (ICU) admission and transfu-
sion requirements in the university hospital 
setting. 
▪ The hospital database captured a total of 54 732 
participants admitted to the emergency depart-
ment of the University Hospital of Bonn between 
1 January 2012 and 31 December 2013. 
▪ In total, 15 895 participants with inpatient status 
recorded admission temperature, hospital admis-
sion and discharge dates, demographics, 
Glasgow Coma Scale, ICU admission, mode of 
transportation and information about the 
in-hospital mortality were eligible for full set data 
analyses. 
▪ The retrospective approach does not allow for 
causal relationships between prehospital hypo-
thermia and any of the designated outcome 
measures. 
▪ The potential influence of patients' diagnoses on 
temperature regulation, medication regimes and 
haemoglobin levels of transfused patients was 
not accounted for and may therefore confound 
observed effects. </p>

<p>Klauke N, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009913. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009913 </p>



<p>Open Access 
Research </p>

<p>non-infectious serious hazards of transfusion (NISHOT) 
ranging from common complications, for example, aller-
gic or febrile haemolytic reactions, 9 to rare, life-
threatening entities such as the transfusion-related acute 
lung injury (TRALI) 10 or the transfusion-associated 
graft-versus-host disease (TA-GVHD) 11 can still pose a 
serious threat to patients. The patients' outcome might 
also be negatively affected by non-antibody antigen-
dependent reactions known as transfusion-related 
immune modulation 9 that are suspected to increase the 
rate of infection and tumour recurrence after transfu-
sion. 12 The aim of this study was to evaluate the effects 
of prehospital hypothermia on transfusion rate and mor-
tality. This retrospective single-centre database analysis 
was executed in the framework of a Germany-wide multi-
centre initiative for patient blood management (PBM-
Study: ClinicalTrials.gov, NCT01820949, post-results), 
which aims at reducing the amount of blood transfusion 
whenever feasible and beneficial for the patient. </p>

<p>MATERIAL AND METHODS 
This study reviewed the University Hospital Bonn 
(UHB) Emergency Department (ED) database from 1 
January 2012 until 31 December 2013 that contained 
anonymised data of 54 732 patients. Included in this 
study were patients with recorded admission tempera-
ture, documented admission and discharge date, age, 
Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS), intensive care unit (ICU) 
admission, mode of transportation and information 
about the in-hospital mortality. 
As a standard operating procedure, each patient's clin-
ical health status is evaluated by a nurse in the frame-
work of an emergency triage system when admitted to 
the ED. The triage includes the tympanal measurement 
of the patient's temperature. This method is easy and 
fast, shows accurate results and can be recommended 
for this purpose. 13 The length of stay (LOS) was calcu-
lated electronically. The GCS was evaluated by the emer-
gency physician arriving at the scene. 
The amount of transfused red blood cells was evalu-
ated by matching our database with the University 
Hospital Bonn Institute of Transfusion Medicine's data-
base and is presented as the raw number of received 
packages (PRBC). The transfusion criteria are given in 
the German guideline: cross-sectional guidelines for 
therapy with blood components and plasma derivatives 
(2014). 14 
According to the German guideline: S3 prevention of 
perioperative hypothermia (2014), a patient was defined 
as hypothermic when presenting with a temperature 
below 36.0°C, normothermic when presenting with a 
temperature from 36.1°C to 38.0°C, and hyperthermic 
when the temperature was &gt;38.1°C on arrival at the ED. 
The primary outcome values were LOS in days, 
in-hospital mortality, the transferred amount of PRBCs 
and ICU admission. 
Secondary influencing variables such as age and GCS 
were considered further grouping variables to compare </p>

<p>the hypothermic patients with the normothermic and 
hyperthermic patients. 
For quantitative data evaluation, the median test and 
Mann-Whitney U-test were used. To objectify if transfu-
sion and mortality were independent of the patient's 
temperature, age and GCS contingency tables were 
created and analysed with a χ 2 test. To compare means, 
Student's t test was used. The Kaplan-Meier analysis was 
applied to identify whether hypothermic and transfused 
patients had a higher risk of mortality than the other 
patients in the study. Binary logistic regression was used 
to determine risk factors for mortality. The univariate 
predictors were the body temperature and transfusion. 
The results are given in adjusted OR (AOR) and 
reached statistical significance with p&lt;0.001. Other 
results are presented as mean (SD) for ordinal data, and 
as median for data which had expected peaks and 
descriptive data as raw percentages. Statistical analysis 
was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS Statistics Amos</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V.22.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, USA). 
The present study was purely retrospective and 
approval by the ethics committee was not necessary as 
the General Medical Council explicitly excluded retro-
spective studies from approval in their code of medical 
ethics ( §15/1). 15 
All collected clinical data evaluated in this study were 
fully anonymised before analysis. Therefore, according 
to prior agreement with the local ethics committee and 
the data protection officer appointed by the University 
Hospital, verbal or written informed consent was not 
obtained. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
During the 2-year study period, 15 895 of the 54 732 
patients who arrived at the ED were included in the 
study. In total, 36 418 ambulant patients (admitted and 
discharged within 24 h) and patients lacking the 
required data were excluded. Also excluded were 1675 
patients who required interdisciplinary consultation or 
were admitted as case conferences from other hospitals. 
Of the included patients, 22.6% were hypothermic 
according to the German guideline, 71.8% normother-
mic and 5.4% hyperthermic. 
The mean LOS for all study patients was 8.6 days 
(median 4.9 days, SD 12.3). After arrival at the ED, 
14.0% of the patients were transferred to the ICU. In 
this group, 15.6% were hyperthermic, 14.3% normother-
mic and 12.7% hypothermic ( p=0.3) (for demographic 
data, table 1). </p>

<p>Effects of hypothermia 
Hypothermic patients died earlier than normothermic 
and hyperthermic patients ( p&lt;0.001) as depicted in the 
Kaplan-Meier analysis (figure 1). 
Additionally, the analysis revealed that patients who 
died during the study period had an already decreased 
core temperature when admitted to the ED. Those 
patients had a significantly lower mean body temperature </p>



<p>Klauke N, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009913. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009913 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>of 36.3°C (SD 1.1) than patients who were discharged 
alive (36.6°C, SD 0.8; p&lt;0.001). 
Hypothermic patients had a mean LOS of 8.7 days 
(median 4.7 days, SD 12.4), normothermic patients a 
mean LOS of 8.4 days (median 4.8 days, SD 11.6), and 
hyperthermic patients a mean LOS of 10.1 days (median 
6.2 days, SD 13.3). The LOS of the patient groups dif-
fered significantly ( p&lt;0.001) (figure 2). </p>

<p>Effects of blood transfusion 
Of the study patients, 1295 (8.1%) received PRBC 
during their stay with a median of four PRBC. Overall, 
1-3 PRBC were transfused to 45.2% of the patients, 4-6 
PRBC to 26.6%, 7-9 PRBC to 9.9%, and 18.3% received 
a massive transfusion, defined as 10 PRBC or more. The 
more PRBC a patient received, the longer was the LOS 
at the hospital ( p&lt;0.001). 
The in-hospital mortality rate of 5.1% for all study-
included patients increased with the number of adminis-
tered PRBC. It reached 9.9% for patients with 1-3 
PRBC; 14.0% for those with 4-6 PRBC, 19.0% for those 
with 7-9 PRBC, and 32.5% for those with ≥10 PRBC </p>

<p>( p&lt;0.001). Patients who died during their clinical stay 
received a mean amount of 13.3 (SD 16.4) PRBC. 
Patients who were admitted to the ICU had a fivefold 
increased risk of death (AOR 5.6; 95% CI 2.0 to 15.8; 
p=0.001). 
Referring to the Kaplan-Meier function, transfused 
patients died at a significantly higher rate and earlier 
than patients without transfusion ( p&lt;0.001), (figure 3). 
Referring to the used regression model, a univariate 
analysis for systolic blood pressure (SBP) 90/&gt;90 mm Hg 
and age ≥65/&lt;65 years showed that patients with 
SBP&gt;90 mm Hg had an increased risk of death by factor 
0.1 (OR 0.109; CI 95% 0.087 to 0.138; p&lt;0.001) and that 
patients ≥65 years had a threefold risk of death com-
pared with patients &lt;65 years (OR 3.140; 2.688 to 3.669; 
p&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>Influence of hypothermia on transfusion 
Hypothermic patients received significantly more PRBC 
(9.7%) during their hospital stay than normothermic 
(7.2%) and hyperthermic patients (9.4%), ( p&lt;0.001). 
The binary logistic regression model revealed that both </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographic data of the study population </p>

<p>Variable 
Total (n=15 895) </p>

<p>Hypothermic 
patients (n=3348) </p>

<p>Normothermic 
patients (n=10 517) </p>

<p>Hyperthermic 
patients (n=786) p Value </p>

<p>Age, mean (SD); [median] 
57.8 (21.1); [61] 60.3 (20.5); [64] 
57.2 (21.1); [60] 
56.3 (20.3); [60] &lt;0.001 
Sex, male (%) 
57.3 
59.9 
55.5 
62.1 
&lt;0.001 
Temperature, mean (SD); [median] 36.5 (0.8); [36.5] 35.6 (0.5); [35.8] 
36.7 (0.4); [36.6] 
38.8 (0.6); [38.6] &lt;0.001 
Transfused (%) 
8.2 
9.7 
7.2 
9.4 
&lt;0.001 
PRBC total, mean amount 
0.6 
0.7 (4.3) 
0.5 (3.0) 
0.6 (4.1) 
&lt;0.001 
PRBC during the first 24 h, 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>0.8 (2.8) 
1.1 (3.2) 
0.5 (1.8) 
0.2 (0.9) 
0.001 </p>

<p>PRBC day 2, mean (SD) 
1.5 (3.6) 
1.8 (4.1) 
1.1 (2.6) 
0.8 (1.6) 
0.042 
PRBC day 3, mean (SD) 
2.2 (4.3) 
2.5 (4.8) 
1.7 (3.3) 
1.2 (1.8) 
0.05 
Systolic BP (mm Hg) 
140 
139 
141 
135 
&lt;0.001 
GCS, mean (SD); [median] 
12.8 (4.3); [15] 
12.3 (4.5); [15] 
13.2 (3.9); [15] 
12.7 (4.1); [15] 
0.001 
ICU admission (%) 
14 
12.7 
14.3 
15.6 
0.292 
LOS (days), mean (SD); [median] 
8.6 (12.3); [4.9] 
8.7 (12.4); [4.7] 
8.4 (11.7); [4.8] 
10.1 (13.3); [6.2] &lt;0.001 
Mortality (%) 
5.1 
7.4 
3.4 
4.1 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>BP, blood pressure; GCS, Glasgow Coma Scale; ICU, intensive care unit; LOS, length of stay; PRBC, packed red blood cell. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Kaplan-Meier analysis: hypothermic patients had 
the highest mortality rate. LOS (d), length of stay in days. </p>

<p>Figure 2 LOS in days±SEM for each temperature category. 
LOS, length of stay. </p>

<p>Klauke N, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009913. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009913 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>body temperature and transfusion rate are risk factors 
for mortality. Prehospital hypothermia (≤36.0°C) 
increased the risk of death up to almost 50% (AOR 1.5; 
95% CI 0.7 to 3.0; p&lt;0.001) in contrast to normother-
mia. Transfusion of 1-3 PRBC increased the risk of 
death by 20% (AOR 0.2; 95% CI 0.1 to 0.3), similar to 
receiving 4-6 PRBC (AOR 0.3; 95% CI 0.2 to 0.4), and 
7-9 PRBC (AOR 0.5; 95% CI 0.3 to 0.8; p&lt;0.001). The 
administration of ≥10 PRBC increased the risk of death 
by factor 5 compared with patients with only 1-3 PRBC 
(AOR 5.7; 95% CI 1.3 to 2.2; p&lt;0.001). 
To evaluate the influence of prehospital hypothermia 
on the transfusion rate, further subgroups were created 
((A) ≤34.5°C; (B) 34.6-34.9°C; (C) 35.0-35.4°C and 
(D) 35.5-36.0°C). This subgroup analysis showed that a 
further decreased body core temperature was associated 
with a rising amount of PRBCs. The analysis revealed 
that the amount of administered PRBCs rose from 
group D (9.0%) to group A (16.1%). In comparison 
with the hypothermic patients, only 7.2% in the nor-
mothermic group (36.1-38.0°C) and 9.4% in the hyper-
thermic group (&gt;38.1) received a transfusion ( p&lt;0.001). 
In a logistic regression model, an admission tempera-
ture ≤34.5°C was associated with an eightfold risk of 
death (AOR 8.5; 95% CI 2.5 to 28.5; p=0.001) and with 
an approximately twofold risk of transfusion (AOR 1.8; 
95% CI 1.0 to 3.1; p=0.46). However, we calculated the 
relative risk for receiving PRBC in the group of patients 
admitted with a body temperature ≤34.5°C, and the ana-
lysis showed that these patients had a doubled relative 
risk (OR 2.0; CI 95% 1.3 to 3.1) of transfusion com-
pared with normothermic patients ( p=0.002). 
Referring to the regression model, other univariate 
predictors were again SBP ≤90/&gt;90 mm Hg and age 
≥65/&lt;65 years. This analysis showed that patients with 
an SBP&gt;90 mm Hg had an increased risk of transfusion 
by factor 0.4 (OR 0.389; 0.301 to 0.503; p&lt;0.001) and 
that patients ≥65 years showed a doubled risk of receiv-
ing transfusion compared with younger patients (OR 
1.935; 1.722 to 2.175; p&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>The contingency table displayed that 25% of the 
patients with a GCS≤8 received blood products, whereas 
only 7% of patients with a GCS&gt;9 received PRBC during 
their stay ( p&lt;0.001). The mean GCS in transfused 
patients was significantly lower (GCS 10) than that in 
non-transfused patients (GCS 13), ( p&lt;0.001). A GCS≤8 
(AOR 12.2; 95% CI 7.8 to 19.2; p=0.001) and transfusion 
of PRBC were connected with an increased risk of death 
(AOR 3.8; 95% CI 2.1 to 7.1; p=0.001). The Student's t 
test revealed that hypothermic patients had a significantly 
lower GCS (median 12.3, SD 4.5) than normothermic 
patients (median 13.2, SD 3.9; p&lt;0.001), but there was no 
significant difference in the GCS of hypothermic to 
hyperthermic patients (median 12.7, SD 4.1; p=0.47). 
In our analysis, we found that 26.8% of patients 
accompanied by an emergency physician were hypother-
mic and only 19.2% of patients accompanied by parame-
dics were hypothermic ( p&lt;0.001). 
To investigate the influence of the patient's age on 
LOS and received PRBCs, three different groups were 
created ((1) &lt;45 years, (2) 46-60 years and (3) 
&gt;61 years). Most patients were older than 61 years 
(50.6%). There were 28.1% of patients aged &lt;45 years 
and 21.4% between 46-60 years. Considering the 
median LOS, it appeared that patients belonging to 
group 3 stayed significantly longer at the hospital 
(median LOS 6.1 days) than younger patients ( p&lt;0.001). 
Patients belonging to group 2 stayed 4.8 days and 
patients who were aged 45 years and younger had a 
median LOS of 3.3 days. 
Considering that the transfused blood products 
patients in group 2 received the largest amount of PRBC 
(mean value 10.0 PRBC, median 4 PRBC, SD 15.0), 
whereas patients in group 3 received a mean amount of 
6.6 PRBC (median 4, SD 8.8), the patients in group 1 
received 5.9 PRBC (median 3, SD 9.7). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The overall aim of this study was to investigate the impact 
of hypothermia on transfusion rates and mortality at the 
UHB. Our findings indicate that patients presenting with 
hypothermia on admission to the ED have adverse out-
comes compared with normothermic and hyperthermic 
patients. The same is applicable to hypothermic patients 
who received transfusions of PRBC during their hospital 
stay. Although it seems to be obvious that hypothermia 
might be a negative outcome factor during the rescue 
and recovery process, the incidence of hypothermia in 
EDs remains a commonly observed phenomenon. Heat 
loss that may be caused by the prolonged rescue time and 
severe injuries is prolonged throughout the transporta-
tion to the next ER due to a non-existing standardised 
prehospital warming management. 
The study results show that almost one-third of the 
patients arrived hypothermic at the ED. We orientated 
ourselves on the current German guideline defining 
hypothermia as a core body temperature &lt;36.0°C. 16 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Kaplan-Meier analysis: mortality of transfused 
patients compared with not transfused patients. LOS (d), 
length of stay in days; PRBC, packed red blood cell. </p>



<p>Klauke N, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009913. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009913 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Other studies on this subject defined hypothermia 
as a core body temperature &lt;36.5°C, &lt;35.0°C and 
&lt;34.5°C. 6 17 18 Setting our temperature limit at 36.0°C 
led to the fact that our hypothermic patients group is 
not as large as in, for example, the study by Bukur et al. 6 
In our study, hypothermic patients did not have an 
increased LOS. Similar results are shown by Trentzsch 
et al, 5 whereas another paper found that patients with a 
body temperature &lt;35.0°C and major trauma stayed 
longer at the hospital. 19 Compatible results in a retro-
spective paper by Martin et al 17 showed a significantly 
increased LOS and ICU admission rate for hypothermic 
patients with major trauma (&lt;35.0°C) compared with 
normothermic patients ( p&lt;0.001). The differences in 
our findings compared with the studies by Ireland et al 
and Martin et al may be caused either by their collective 
of patients or by the fact that the Kaplan-Meier analysis 
in our study revealed that hypothermic patients had an 
increased mortality rate and died earlier than patients 
with normal or febrile temperatures. Martin et al and 
Ireland et al mainly used results of patients with major 
trauma in their studies, whereas we included every 
patient admitted to the ED despite the injury severity 
score (ISS). Our results revealed that hyperthermic 
patients had the longest LOS and were more often 
admitted to the ICU. We suggest that those patients 
were septic or in another febrile critical health condi-
tion that needed intensive treatment. 
Hypothermic patients showed an increased consump-
tion of PRBC and an increased risk of death. 
Responsible for these findings might be the partial 
impairment of the coagulation by hypothermia already 
outlined in the introduction. 3 4 20 Other factors that 
additionally affected the coagulation of the patients 
included in this study cannot be retraced due to the 
retrospective study design. 
The in-hospital death rate for patients with &gt;10 PRBC 
units rose to 37.8%, whereas patients with 1-3 PRBC 
units had a death rate of 9.9%.The multicentred patient 
blood management initiative, in which this study is inte-
grated, aims at an increase in patient safety and reduc-
tion of liberal admission of 1-3 PRBC because it was 
shown that already a small amount of allogeneic blood 
transfusion is associated with septic, pulmonary and 
embolic complications. 21 Other possible reasons for the 
increased mortality rate are predisposition to nosocomial 
and postoperative infections, cancer recurrence and 
microchimerism through the infusion of PRBC. 22 Our 
results prove that patients with 1-3 PRBC had a signifi-
cantly increased LOS compared with patients who 
received no transfusion ( p&lt;0.001). They additionally 
had an enhanced risk of death (AOR 0.174; p&lt;0.001). 
Our analysis demonstrated that patients with massive 
transfusion died earlier than other patients. One-third of 
the total amount of PRBC for each massively transfused 
patient in the ED was administered within the first 72 h. 
Among this group are most likely patients with severe 
injuries and major trauma who are in urgent need of </p>

<p>resuscitation fluids, for example, red blood cells as subsi-
dised by a large retrospective study by Barbosa et al. 23 
There was also a significant association between the 
GCS and PRBC. One fourth of the patients with a GCS 
of ≤8 were in need of PRBC, which seems reasonable 
since the GCS classifies the consciousness in patients 
with severe injuries. 
In addition, there was a difference in the occurrence 
of hypothermia depending on the mode of transporta-
tion. The incidence of hypothermia was significantly 
higher on an ambulance with an emergency physician 
present compared with ambulances operated by parame-
dics. These results indicate that patients accompanied by 
an emergency physician were either hypothermic due to 
their injuries and cold resuscitation fluids, or their body 
temperature was lowered protectively. 
Patients aged 61 years and older had the longest LOS. 
Despite this result, patients in the middle-aged group 
(46-60 years) received the most PRBC during their stay 
at the hospital. The study by Barbosa et al 23 displayed 
that age was independently associated with a higher risk 
of mortality in an observed 30-day period among trans-
fused patients after trauma. According to this, our study 
showed that patients who died during the stay at the hos-
pital had a mean age of 71.34 (SD 14.34), whereas 
patients who were discharged alive had a mean age of 
57.12 (SD 21.16; p&lt;0.001). </p>

<p>Limitations 
Owing to the retrospective study design, it was not pos-
sible to create a causal connection between the admission 
temperature and the distribution of PRBC as it would be 
in a prospective clinical trial. This study did not include 
the patients' diagnoses that might have influenced the 
temperature regulation. Additionally, medications such 
as anticoagulants could not have been retraced. We were 
not able to retrace the exact haemoglobin level of the 
transfused patients and to differentiate between patients 
with accidental and induced hypothermia retrospectively. 
It has to be taken into account that ambulances are able 
to cool patients, and that this is a standard procedure in 
patients with heart attacks, cardiac arrest and patients 
with possible brain damage as these patients benefit from 
a lower core body temperature. 24 25 
It has to be taken into consideration that our review 
did not analyse the connection of the ISS of each 
patient with the body temperature and the transfusion 
requirement. This is due to the fact that it was not pos-
sible to reproduce the ISS in retrospect. A prospective 
controlled clinical trial on a connection between tem-
perature, transfusion requirement and ISS could prove 
the importance of this subject. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION 
Despite the aforementioned limitations, this large retro-
spective study was able to show that prehospital hypo-
thermia is associated with an increased transfusion </p>

<p>Klauke N, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009913. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009913 </p>



<p>Open Access </p>

<p>requirement and a worse outcome compared with nor-
mothermic and not transfused patients. 
This study should create further awareness of the 
importance of the patient's body temperature and a 
more restrictive transfusion regime for patients who are 
not in life-threatening need of resuscitation fluids. 
Patients with low prehospital body core temperatures, 
owing to the injury severity or a prolonged rescue, 
should be protected from further heat loss with trauma 
warming blankets. An effective warming management 
installed on all ambulances and in the EDs could help 
prevent hypothermic patients from a worse outcome as 
induced through the primary injury. It should be noted 
that this is a hypothesis suggested by the findings of this 
study, a prospective randomised controlled trial should 
be conducted to investigate, if a prehospital worming is 
beneficial for the patients. </p>

<p>Contributors NK contributed to the data analysis, literature research and 
writing of the manuscript. IG and PM were involved in the planning of the 
trial. AF was responsible for the data analysis. OB and VG took part in the 
writing of the manuscript. GB took part in the planning of the trial and writing 
of the manuscript. MW participated in the planning of the trial, data analysis, 
literature research and writing of the manuscript. </p>

<p>Funding This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in 
the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. </p>

<p>Competing interests None declared. </p>

<p>Ethics approval Approval for the patient blood management study was given 
by the Ethics Committee of the Medical Faculty of the University of Bonn 
chaired by Professor K Racké (number 082/13 from the 7 May 2013). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Data sharing statement No additional data are available. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with 
the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, 
which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-
commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided 
the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/ </p>





<p>Klauke N, et al. BMJ Open 2016;6:e009913. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009913 </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

</text></tei>