<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4622454" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Changes in sleep characteristics in individuals with chronic stroke are not well 
described, particularly compared with healthy individuals. Therefore, the aim of this pilot study 
was to explore the sleep characteristics in individuals with chronic stroke compared to age-and 
sex-matched controls. Sixteen individuals with chronic stroke and ten age-and sex-matched 
controls underwent two nights of polysomnographic recording. The sleep characteristics of 
interest included total sleep time, sleep efficiency, and percent time, as well as time in minutes 
spent in stages N1, N2, and N3 and stage R sleep. The individuals with chronic stroke spent 
less percent time in stage N3 compared with controls (P=0.048). No significant differences in 
the other sleep characteristics were found between the stroke and control groups. Individuals 
with chronic stroke present with altered stage N3 sleep compared with healthy controls. These 
alterations in stage N3 sleep might be a sign of neuronal dysfunction and may impact recovery 
following stroke. A larger scale study is needed to confirm these findings. 
Individuals after stroke often experience sleep disturbances and changes in sleep 
patterns. Up to 40% of individuals with chronic stroke (defined as .6 months follow-
ing stroke) and 70% of those with acute stroke have sleep-wake disorders, including 
excessive daytime sleepiness, insomnia, hypersomnia, and fatigue. 
1 Sleep-related 
breathing disturbances are also common, affecting up to 70% of individuals with 
stroke, 
2 with obstructive sleep apnea being the most common form. 
2 Sleep-related 
movement disorders like restless leg syndrome and periodic limb movements, as 
well as stage R (formally referred to as rapid eye movement [REM]) sleep behavior 
disorder are also common in individuals with stroke. 
3 Sleep disturbances following 
stroke can lead to short-term and long-term negative patient outcomes 
4 and increase 
the risk of a recurrent stroke. 
5 Medication use, sleep-disordered breathing, depres-
sion, pain, impaired mobility, and other complications from the stroke are factors 
that contribute to compromised sleep in people following stroke. 
6 Furthermore, the 
area of the brain affected by the stroke can play an important role in determining the 
spectrum of sleep disturbances that occur. 
6 In addition, untreated sleep disturbances 
after stroke, like sleep apnea and excessive daytime sleepiness, increase the risk of 
developing another stroke. </p>

<p>7   Sleep has been shown to enhance learning motor skills and memory consolidation 
in individuals with chronic stroke. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Nature and Science of Sleep 
21 October 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Nature and Science of Sleep 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>al-Dughmi et al </p>

<p>Sleep is classified into two main stages: 
9 non-REM 
sleep (stage N) or REM (stage R) sleep. Stage N sleep is 
divided into three substages corresponding to increasing 
depth of sleep as shown using electroencephalograms 
(EEGs): N1 involves the transition from wakefulness to 
sleep and is characterized by sinusoidal alpha wave activ-
ity, N2 is characterized by sleep spindles and K complexes 
(clusters of low-and high-amplitude waves, respectively), 
and N3 or slow-wave sleep is characterized by slow delta 
waves. Stage R sleep is characterized by REMs and muscle 
atonia. 
Evidence suggests that sleep spindles and possibly 
stage R sleep are associated with consolidation of simple 
motor tasks during sleep in healthy individuals. 
10 Therefore, 
understanding the sleep characteristics in individuals with 
stroke could enable clinicians to capitalize on sleep to pro-
mote learning and hasten recovery. Furthermore, it would 
enable clinicians to treat sleep issues that may limit the 
individual's ability to benefit from sleep to enhance motor 
learning and recovery. 
While sleep disturbances and disorders in individuals 
with stroke can lead to an additional stroke and may impact 
the ability to learn new motor skills, 
7 sleep issues also nega-
tively impact functional outcomes and overall quality of life 
in individuals with stroke. 
11 Furthermore, there is evidence 
that poor sleep quality and sleep disruptions compromise 
the immune system, 
12 alter the tissue healing process, </p>

<p>13   increase pain sensitivity, 
14 contribute to depression and anxi-
ety, 
15 and reduce quality of life and functional well-being. </p>

<p>16   All of these comorbid conditions are commonly experienced 
by people following stroke, although the contribution of sleep 
to these comorbid conditions has not been fully examined 
in people with stroke. Therefore, exploring the sleep char-
acteristics in individuals with stroke could lead to a better 
understanding of the contribution of sleep to the development 
of comorbid conditions in people with stroke. 
Previous studies 
11,17-27 that used polysomnography (PSG) 
to examine sleep characteristics in individuals with stroke 
showed sleep alterations as following: decreased sleep effi-
ciency (SE), reduced total sleep time (TST), increased time 
spent in stage N1 sleep, and decreased percentage of time 
spent in stage N3 or slow-wave sleep. 
12,18-24,26-29 There is 
also evidence that sleep spindles increase in activity in the 
chronic stage of stroke, 
21,28 as well as increased time spent in 
stage N2 in the chronic phase. 
30 However, these studies have 
several limitations in their design. First, only four of the 12 
PSG studies included healthy participants as their control 
group; 
19,22,23 the remaining used hospitalized patients 
17,18,25 or </p>

<p>other patients with neurologic disease. 
20,21,27 Neurologically 
intact, sex-and aged-matched controls would be an ideal 
comparison to reduce the impact of medications or comor-
bidities that might impact sleep characteristics, thus making 
conclusions difficult. In addition, most of the PSG studies 
focus on individuals with acute stroke 
11,20,21,25 or included 
individuals with a diverse range of chronicity ranging from 
acute, subacute, to chronic stages. 
18,22 Therefore, evidence 
of sleep characteristics in individuals with chronic stroke of 
greater than 6 months is lacking. Understanding the sleep 
characteristics of individuals with chronic stroke is especially 
critical because approximately 6.8 million Americans are 
living with chronic stroke, 
29 and up to 50% of those with 
chronic stroke report having sleep disturbances. 
31 Another 
difficulty in interpreting the findings of prior studies is the 
majority were conducted on a single night. 
18-20,22-24,26-28,32 Two 
nights of PSG recording is recommended, where the first 
night is referred to as the "adaptation" or "acclimation" night 
and is disregarded from analysis and considered not repre-
sentative of the usual sleeping patterns. 
33 Only two studies 
conducted PSG on two to three consecutive nights, but their 
target population was individuals with acute stroke. 
19,27 To 
our knowledge, there are no studies that have assessed the 
sleep characteristics of individuals with chronic stroke using 
a healthy sex-and age-matched control group for comparison 
and using an acclimation night. 
Therefore, the purpose of this pilot study was to analyze 
the sleep characteristics of individuals with chronic stroke 
(defined as more than 6 months poststroke) compared with 
healthy age-and sex-matched controls using PSG con-
ducted on two nights (first night was used for acclimation). 
A secondary purpose was to make an exploratory analysis 
to compare the sleep characteristics of those with right-sided 
with those with left-sided middle cerebral artery (MCA) 
lesions. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The study was conducted according to the regulations and 
with approval from the Institutional Review Board at the 
University of Kansas Medical Center (KUMC). Informed 
consent was received from all participants. Participants 
were recruited from 1) the Stroke Registry at KUMC, 2) 
the American Stroke Foundation, 3) area stroke support 
groups, and 4) personal referral from consented subjects, 
area physicians, or study personnel. The inclusion criteria 
for all participants were as follows: 1) 40-75 years old, 2) 
no untreated sleep disorders including sleep apnea or nar-
colepsy, 3) must maintain a regular sleep schedule (defined </p>

<p>Nature and Science of Sleep 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Sleep characteristics in patients with stroke </p>

<p>for the purpose of this study as an average of 6-9 hours of 
sleep per night), and 4) score at least 26 on the Mini-Mental 
State Exam to insure no evidence of dementia. The inclusion 
criteria for participants with stroke were 1) unilateral stroke 
in the MCA distribution, and 2) current clinical status being 
at least 6 months poststroke. The exclusion criteria for all 
participants were as follows: 1) acute medical problems, 2) 
uncorrected vision loss, 3) previous history of psychiatric 
admission, 4) history of multiple strokes, transient ischemic 
attacks, or extensive white matter disease, 5) unable to give 
consent, 6) smoker, and 7) uncontrolled depression. 
Twenty-six individuals with stroke were enrolled in the 
study. Six individuals were excluded from the study after the 
night of PSG due to having undiagnosed sleep apnea. Ten age-
and sex-matched controls were included. Control participants 
were matched to two stroke participants for 1:2 ratio. Three 
individuals with stroke were identified as extreme outliers 
on box-plot test for normality of the sleep measures and 
were excluded from data analysis. One stroke participant 
was excluded because magnetic resonance imaging revealed 
a brainstem lesion. Therefore, 16 individuals with chronic 
stroke (mean age =57±10.34 years; eleven females and 
five males; Table 1) and ten sex-and age-matched control 
participants (mean age =60.8±11.68 years; six females and 
four males; Table 1) were included in data analysis. 
Participants underwent a night of acclimation sleep in the 
Sleep Medicine Clinic sleep laboratory at the University of 
Kansas Medical Center to acclimate individuals to the sleep 
laboratory and to exclude participants with a sleep disorder. 
The acclimation night was followed by a night for sleep data 
recording. Only the second night of recording was included 
in data analysis. The participants underwent a third night of 
PSG to examine the sleep parameters associated with sleep-
dependent off-line motor skill learning, and those data are 
not presented here. 
Participants were prepared for polysomnographic sleep 
monitoring using standardized techniques 
34 including six 
EEG sensors to measure brain wave activity placed accord-
ing to the international system for electrode placement, </p>

<p>35   two eye sensors to record horizontal eye movement (electro-</p>

<p>oculogram), and chin and tibialis anterior electromyogram 
sensors to assess muscle activity. Physiological signals were 
recorded using Nihon Kohden equipment (Foothill Ranch, 
CA, USA). Other instruments included a nasal airflow sensor, 
comfortable belts around the thorax and abdomen to monitor 
respiratory effort, a finger probe to assess pulse oximetry, 
and a microphone to monitor snoring. Each study session 
was digitally video recorded. The sleep records were scored 
according to standardized scoring criteria. 
36 The outcome 
measures of interest are as follows: TST, SE, time spent in 
stage N1, stage N2, stage N3, and stage R, and percent sleep 
period time spent in stage N1, stage N2, stage N3, and stage 
R. For data analysis, <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">20.0</rs> was used to perform 
all statistical analysis, and alpha was set at 0.05. Descriptive 
statistics were calculated. The data were analyzed for normal-
ity using the Shapiro-Wilk test and Skewness and Kurtosis 
test, as well as Box plots and normal Q-Q plots. Independent 
t-tests were used to compare the sleep parameters of the 
individuals with stroke with the control participants when 
the assumption of normality was satisfied. Effect sizes were 
calculated as Cohen's d values. Because this is a pilot study, 
data are presented without correction for multiplicity. Due to 
the sex difference in the stroke sample, linear regression was 
used to study if sex predicts the outcome measure of interest 
after controlling for age which can be a confounding factor 
for change in sleep parameters. An exploratory analysis was 
performed using independent t-tests to compare the sleep 
characteristics and descriptive characteristics of individuals 
with left-sided MCA lesions (n=7) to those with right-sided 
MCA lesions (n=9). Alpha was set at 0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>There was no significant difference in age (P=0.504), Mini-
Mental State Exam (P=0.924), Pittsburgh Sleep Quality 
Index (P=0.455), Geriatric Depression Scale (P=0.840), or 
average sleep for the week prior to testing (P=0.062) between 
the stroke participants and the healthy controls (Table 1). 
The participants with stroke showed higher TST than the 
control participants (414.75 minutes vs 388.3 minutes), 
but this was not statistically different (P=0.058; Table 2). </p>

<p>Table 1 Demographics of the participants </p>

<p>Group 
Sex 
Age (years) 
MMSE 
PSQI 
GDS 
AVG sleep 
UEFM 
OPS </p>

<p>Stroke 
11 females 5 males 
57 (10.34) 
29.43 (0.73) 
4.5 (3.85) 
5.36 (4.70) 
6.56 (2.52) 
56.88 (14.23) 
1.85 (0.41) 
control 
6 females 4 males 
60.8 (11.68) 
30 (0) 
4 (2.31) 
3.2 (4.23) 
7.467 (0.657) 
N/a 
N/a 
P-value 
0.504 
0.924 
0.455 
0.840 
0.062 </p>

<p>Note: Data are reported as mean (standard deviation). 
Abbreviations: MMSe, Mini-Mental State exam; PSQi, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality index; gDS, geriatric Depression Scale; aVg sleep, average hours of sleep over 1 week; 
UeFM, upper extremity portion of the Fugl-Meyer assessment of Motor recovery after Stroke; OPS, Orpington Prognostic Score. </p>

<p>Nature and Science of Sleep 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>142 </p>

<p>al-Dughmi et al </p>

<p>The individuals with stroke had higher SE than the control 
participants, but this difference was not significant (88.64% 
vs 83.5%, P=0.109; Table 2). The stroke group also spent 
less time than controls in the following stages of sleep: 
stage N1 (33.56 minutes vs 41.2 minutes, P=0.201), stage 
N3 (43.06 minutes vs 46.8 minutes, P=0.216), and stage R 
(81.69 minutes vs 88.9 minutes, P=0.660) but more time 
in stage N2 compared with controls (256.44 minutes vs 
215.4 minutes, P=0.270; Table 2), although not statistically 
significant. When comparing the percentage of time spent 
in each stage, the individuals with stroke had a significant 
lower percent time spent in stage N3 compared with controls 
(P=0.048), but there was no statistically significant difference 
between the other percent times. The analysis was repeated 
again for the percent of time spent in stage N3 variable, but 
this time with all the 19 stroke individuals without taking 
out the outliers. The analysis showed that there is a near 
significant difference in the percentage of time spent in stage 
N3 between the stroke participants and controls (P=0.082). 
To show that the percentage of time spent in stage N3 was 
not influenced by the presence of more females than males 
in our 16 stroke samples, linear regression was used with 
stage N3 as the dependent variable and sex as a predictor 
variable. The overall linear regression model to assess the 
impact of sex on the percentage of time spent in stage N3 </p>

<p>while controlling for age was not significant (P=0.97) with 
an R 
2 of 0.005. In addition, age was not significantly different 
between the female stroke participants compared with the 
male participants (P=0.308). 
Descriptive characteristics for the participants with 
right-sided (n=9) and left-sided (n=7) stroke are shown in 
Table 3. Those with right-sided lesions spent significantly 
less minutes in stage N3 (P=0.029) and significantly less 
percent time spent in stage N3 (P=0.019) compared with 
those with left-sided lesions. Those with right-sided lesions 
scored significantly higher on the Orpington Prognostic 
Score (P=0.038) compared with those with left-sided lesions, 
indicating individuals with right-sided lesions had higher 
stroke severity, although both groups would be considered 
to have mild strokes. 
37 There was no significant difference in 
other sleep variables between individuals with right-versus 
left-sided lesions. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first study that compared 
sleep parameters of individuals with chronic MCA stroke 
to age-and sex-matched healthy controls using PSG. 
Overall, the participants with chronic MCA stroke spent 
significantly less percent time in stage N3 compared 
with healthy controls. Also, individuals with chronic </p>

<p>Table 2 Descriptive mean statistics of sleep parameters in the stroke and control participants </p>

<p>Variable 
Stroke 
Control 
Shapiro-Wilk 
test (P-values) </p>

<p>Cohen's d 
t-test unless noted 
as U test (P-values) </p>

<p>TrT (min) 
469.06 (24.71) 
465.50 (22.97) 
0.930 (0.242) 
0.149 
0.367 (0.901) 
TST (min) 
414.75 (33.69) 
388.30 (57.55) 
0.967 (0.790) 
0.560 
1.485 (0.058) 
Stage N1 (min) 
33.56 (12.57) 
41.20 (15.52) 
0.834 (0.008) 
-0.540 
U=55.5 (0.201) 
Stage N2 (min) 
256.44 (38.92) 
215.40 (57.98) 
0.923 (0.190) 
0.831 
2.167 (0.270) 
Stage N3 (min) 
43.06 (26.84) 
46.80 (33.87) 
0.949 (0.476) 
-0.122 
-0.312 (0.216) 
Stage r (min) 
81.69 (27.04) 
88.9 (30.16) 
0.837 (0.009) 
-0.252 
U=71.5 (0.660) 
Stage N1 (%) 
8.32 (3.09) 
9.5 (4.37) 
0.857 (0.018) 
-0.312 
U=61 (0.336) 
Stage N2 (%) 
61.74 (8.27) 
54.8 (8.62) 
0.958 (0.622) 
0.823 
2.05 (0.805) 
Stage N3 (%) 
9.86 (5.94) 
12.6 (10.41) 
0.933 (0.271) 
-0.323 
-0.860 (0.048) 
Stage r (%) 
19.3 (6.15) 
20.3 (9.08) 
0.799 (0.003) 
-0.129 
U=76 (0.856) 
Sleep efficiency (%) 
88.64 (6.79) 
83.5 (11.46) 
0.856 (0.017) 
0.546 
U=49.5 (0.109) </p>

<p>Notes: Data are reported as mean (standard deviation), Shapiro-Wilk test statistic (P-values), values of cohen's d, and t-test statistic or Mann-Whitney U test (P-values). 
Abbreviations: TrT, total recording time; TST, total sleep time; min, minutes. </p>

<p>Table 3 Descriptive statistics of the right-(n=9) and left-(n=7) side stroke participants </p>

<p>Group 
Age (years) 
PSQI 
GDS 
AVG sleep 
UEFM 
OPS </p>

<p>right 
53.8 (10.76) 
5.11 (5.01) 
4.67 (5.7) 
7.81 (1.06) 
56.3 (15.39) 
1.9 (0.52) 
left 
61.1 (8.8) 
3.71 (1.49) 
3.86 (3.63) 
7.33 (0.69) 
57.6 (15.76) 
1.71 (0.19) 
P-values 
0.507 
0.103 
0.674 
0.661 
0.892 
0.038 </p>

<p>Note: Data are reported as mean (standard deviation). 
Abbreviations: PSQi, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality index; gDS, geriatric Depression Scale; aVg sleep, average hours of sleep over 1 week; UeFM, Upper extremity portion 
of the Fugl-Meyer assessment of Motor recovery after Stroke; OPS, Orpington Prognostic Score. </p>

<p>Nature and Science of Sleep 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>143 </p>

<p>Sleep characteristics in patients with stroke </p>

<p>MCA stroke spent less time in stage N1 and stage R, 
while spending more time in stage N2 compared with the 
control participants, although these differences were not 
statistically different. 
While this is the first study that has examined the sleep 
characteristics of individuals with chronic stroke, the results 
of this study mirror the results of the study of individuals 
with acute stroke, in which it was found that individuals 
with acute stroke spend less time in stage N3 sleep. </p>

<p>20,24,38   A recent study 
39 that investigated changes in the topographic 
sleep of EEG in acute and chronic (defined as 3 months 
for their study) stroke participants suggests that higher 
slow-wave activity during sleep reflects cortical plasticity 
and could be used as a predictive measure of recovery of 
patients with stroke. Furthermore, it has been found that 
higher slow-wave activity during sleep is associated with 
improved performance on a motor learning task in healthy 
individuals. 
40 Huber et al 
41 also suggest that a decrease in 
slow-wave activity during sleep might be due to inactivity 
of the extremity and the resultant lack of input to the con-
tralateral cortex. The latter might explain in part the low 
percentage of time spent in stage N3 in the stroke sample 
of the current study. 
Based on evidence from the literature, 
39,40 the decrease 
in N3 of chronic stroke participants in the current study 
may represent neuronal dysfunction. This finding is clini-
cally important as altered changes in neuroplasticity and 
in normal sleep homeostasis may negatively affect func-
tional recovery and motor learning of individuals with 
chronic stroke. To explore the association between N3 and 
functional abilities, a post hoc analysis was done using 
Pearson's correlations. However, no significant relation-
ship was found between time spent in stage N3 and the 
Upper Extremity Fugl-Meyer (r=0.001, P=0.998) or the 
Orpington Prognostic Score (r=0.143, P=0.599). The low 
sample size of the current study might explain the lack of 
association between function and stage N3 in the stroke 
participants. In addition, the Cohen's d value showed a 
small effect size of percent of time in stage N3 (-0.3), 
which might be influenced by the low sample size as 
well. Future studies should investigate these findings and 
explore more thoroughly if the reduction in time spent in 
stage N3 has negative functional outcomes in individuals 
with chronic stroke. 
The exploratory data analysis showed participants with a 
right-side MCA lesion spent significantly less time in stage 
N3 reported in minutes and less percentage compared with 
those with a lesion on the left-side MCA. In addition, those </p>

<p>with right-sided lesions had significantly higher stroke 
severity than those with left-sided lesions. Evidence from 
previous research 
39 found a decrease in slow-wave sleep in 
individuals with stroke correlated with higher stroke sever-
ity. However, it should be noted that the individuals in the 
current study would be considered to have mild strokes, </p>

<p>37   so it would be unlikely that the decrease in time spent in 
N3 would be due to stroke severity. Furthermore, because 
exact lesion location is unknown (ie, cortical vs subcorti-
cal), it is difficult to interpret this finding. If other studies 
confirm these results that the difference in stage N3 sleep 
is due to the location of a lesion, this information could 
guide clinicians and sleep specialists to more accurately 
predict the possible sleep quality disturbances in relation 
to lesion side in individuals with stroke. Future studies 
should further investigate this finding in individuals with 
chronic stroke and examine anatomical lesion location in 
more detail. 
When the data from this study were compared with 
published norms, 
42 the stroke participants had a similar SE 
(88.64%) compared with published norms for similar mean 
age (87%), whereas the control participants had a lower SE 
(83.5%). Furthermore, the percentage of time spent stage N1 
sleep for stroke (8.3%) and control participants (9.5%) was 
well below the normative values (around 20%). 
42 The high SE 
for the participants in this study and the low percent time spent 
in stage N1 sleep suggest that the participants in this study 
overall experience quality sleep. This is further supported 
by the average Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index for both the 
stroke and control participants having a global score below 
5, which indicates good sleep quality. 
43 Because individuals 
were excluded if an untreated sleep disorder was identified 
during the acclimation night and if they have uncontrolled 
depression, the individuals in this study likely have better 
sleep quality than the general stroke population, which does 
limit the generalizability of the findings of this study. 
When comparing the percentage of time spent in stage N2 
sleep, the control group spent 54.8% in stage N2, while the 
stroke participants spent 61.7% in stage N2, which is 10% 
more than published normative values (around 51%). 
42 This 
is particularly interesting because stage N2 sleep is linked 
to consolidation of simple motor tasks. 
11 If spending more 
time in stage N2 contributes to off-line motor skill learning 
in individuals with chronic stroke, perhaps using sleep as a 
treatment method could improve functional recovery and 
prognosis. 
There are several limitations in this pilot study. One 
limitation is exact location of the lesion is not known, so it </p>

<p>Nature and Science of Sleep 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>144 </p>

<p>al-Dughmi et al </p>

<p>was not possible to consider the location of the lesion in the 
interpretation of the data. Another limitation is the hetero-
geneity in age among the study participants in both groups, 
which limits data interpretation but improves generalizability. 
Furthermore, there is no consensus for reporting the time 
spent in the different sleep stages in percent time or in 
minutes. In this study, both were reported, but this lack of con-
sensus need to be addressed to improve comparison between 
studies. Medication use, particularly sleep-related medica-
tions, could be a confounding factor affecting interpretation 
and should be considered in future studies. In addition, the 
conclusions should be interpreted with caution due to the 
low sample size and lack of correcting for multiplicity due 
to this being a pilot study. A larger scale study is needed to 
verify the findings of this pilot study. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In conclusion, the findings of this pilot study suggest that 
individuals with chronic MCA stroke have altered sleep 
compared with healthy controls. It appears that alterations 
in the sleep parameters remain even more than 6 months 
following a stroke, particularly changes to stage N3 sleep. 
However, further large-scale studies are needed to verify if 
less time spent in stage N3 is associated with poor motor 
function or if more time spent in stage N2 is associated with 
improved motor function and recovery in individuals with 
chronic stroke. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We acknowledge the sleep technicians who worked on this 
study. We also thank the individuals who participated in this 
study. This study was supported by an American Heart 
Association Scientist Development Grant (09SDG2060618) 
awarded to CS. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/nature-and-science-of-sleep-journal </p>

<p>Nature and Science of Sleep is an international, peer-reviewed, open 
access journal covering all aspects of sleep science and sleep medicine, 
including the neurophysiology and functions of sleep, the genetics of 
sleep, sleep and society, biological rhythms, dreaming, sleep disorders and 
therapy, and strategies to optimize healthy sleep. The journal welcomes </p>

<p>original research, clinical &amp; epidemiological studies, reviews &amp; evalu-
ations, case reports and extended reports. The manuscript management 
system is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-
review system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Nature and Science of Sleep 2015:7 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>