<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4354499" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Gene targeting refers to the precise modification of a genetic locus using homologous recombination. The generation of novel cell lines and 
transgenic mouse models using this method necessitates the construction of a 'targeting' vector, which contains homologous DNA sequences to 
the target gene, and has for many years been a limiting step in the process. Vector construction can be performed in vivo in Escherichia coli cells 
using homologous recombination mediated by phage recombinases using a technique termed recombineering. Recombineering is the preferred 
technique to subclone the long homology sequences (&gt;4kb) and various targeting elements including selection markers that are required to 
mediate efficient allelic exchange between a targeting vector and its cognate genomic locus. Typical recombineering protocols follow an iterative 
scheme of step-wise integration of the targeting elements and require intermediate purification and transformation steps. Here, we present a 
novel recombineering methodology of vector assembly using a multiplex approach. Plasmid gap repair is performed by the simultaneous capture 
of genomic sequence from mouse Bacterial Artificial Chromosome libraries and the insertion of dual bacterial and mammalian selection markers. 
This subcloning plus insertion method is highly efficient and yields a majority of correct recombinants. We present data for the construction 
of different types of conditional gene knockout, or knock-in, vectors and BAC reporter vectors that have been constructed using this method. 
SPI vector construction greatly extends the repertoire of the recombineering toolbox and provides a simple, rapid and cost-effective method of 
constructing these highly complex vectors. </p>

<p>Video Link </p>

<p>The video component of this article can be found at The development of gene targeting technologies has enabled the construction of cell lines and mouse models to investigate different 
biological systems </p>

<p>1-3 </p>

<p>. A key first stage in the modification of a genomic sequence is the design and construction of a gene targeting vector </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>. 
Targeting vectors are plasmid constructs that carry the allele of interest containing the desired modifications(s) flanked by a selection marker 
(e.g., neomycin), and long genomic regions required for efficient homologous recombination in mammalian cells </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>. Precise gene modification 
is achieved by the introduction of the targeting vector into embryonic stem (ES) cells 
6 or somatic cells </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>, whereby homologous recombination 
between identical stretches of DNA sequence on the targeting vector and the genomic locus results in the transfer of the intended modification to 
the genome by gene conversion </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>. Such modified ES cells can be injected into mouse blastocysts to produce offspring (chimaeras) that can then 
transmit these modified alleles via the germline </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>. An alternate route to produce transgenic mice involves the microinjection of a gene expression 
vector into single celled mouse zygotes, which leads to the random integration of the vector in the mouse genome </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>. Traditional methods of 
vector construction have relied on conventional 'cut and paste' cloning using restriction enzymes and DNA ligases to clone the different selection 
marker and genomic fragments into a vector backbone. However, an inherent limiting factor of traditional cloning is the positioning and choice of 
restriction sites, especially with longer DNA sequences. This often necessitates multiple subcloning steps and also introduces extraneous DNA 
sequences into the vector, which often leads to a lower efficiency of gene targeting. </p>

<p>Recombineering (recombinogenic engineering) is a DNA engineering technology that overcomes these limitations by using homologous 
recombination (HR) mediated by phage recombination proteins in E. coli cells </p>

<p>11,12 </p>

<p>. Since any region of a homologous sequence can serve as a 
substrate of recombineering, the constraints of availability of restriction sites are removed. Large DNA sequences can be seamlessly modified 
directly in vivo, thus also preserving their structural integrity </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>. Recombineering is very efficient with short homologies (50 bp) 
14 and therefore </p>

<p>homology arms (HA) can be conveniently incorporated into synthetic oligo sequences. In a typical recombineering experiment, an oligo or 
a double stranded DNA (dsDNA) fragment containing HA is electroporated into recombineering competent E. coli cells containing the target 
located either on the chromosome or on a plasmid </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. The recombination potential is conferred by inducible expression of the Red recombination 
proteins of the phage 
16,17 or the RecET proteins of the rac prophage </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>. The Red/RecE exonuclease converts linear dsDNA to a single-stranded </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 2 of 13 </p>

<p>DNA (ssDNA) intermediate, which is then bound by its partner, Red/RecT, a single-stranded annealing protein (SSAP) </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>. The annealing of a long 
ssDNA or a short oligo to its complementary target sequence occurs on the lagging strand of the replication fork and leads to the incorporation of 
the sequence at the target site. Lagging strand ssDNA recombination is the basis of the high efficiency of recombineering and can be described 
by the 'beta' recombination model </p>

<p>20,21 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>A typical recombineering workflow to build a gene targeting vector involves either of the two following routes. One route involves subcloning the 
desired genomic region from a mouse BAC clone into a plasmid followed by the sequential insertion of LoxP recombination sites, a selection 
marker 
22 etc., or the alternative route involves targeting the BAC genomic locus with the different targeting vector elements by multiple rounds </p>

<p>of recombineering 
10,23 and then subcloning the modified locus into a plasmid by gap repair cloning </p>

<p>24,25 </p>

<p>. Variations on this theme have been 
used in different high-throughput recombineering pipelines as part of large mouse production programs </p>

<p>26,27 </p>

<p>. However, these procedures 
involve complicated and lengthy stages, require the use of specialized vectors and E. coli strains (e.g., Cre expressing cells) and utilize one or 
more intermediate steps of vector DNA purification and re-transformation (Table 1). Subcloning plus insertion (SPI) is a novel recombineering 
technique that combines beta recombination and gap repair cloning into a single process (Figure 1). SPI vector assembly is simple, quick and 
flexible and offers significant improvement on standard recombineering approaches (Table 1). Here, we demonstrate the ease and utility of using 
SPI for different vector construction applications with a particular emphasis on constructing non-standard and challenging vector designs. Test 
cases included the construction of a fluorescent reporter knockin vector, a dual tagged protein expression knockin vector, a BAC fluorescent 
reporter vector and a conditional knockout vector. These examined variously the requirement to localize a cell surface receptor, purify a nuclear 
protein complex or conditionally ablate the expression of a gene. </p>

<p>Protocol </p>

<p>1. Gene Targeting Design </p>

<p>1. Order an appropriate BAC clone covering the genomic region of interest. Ensure that this is isogenic to the type of ES cells to be modified 
e.g., RPCI-23 and RPCI-24 BAC clones for gene targeting with C57BL/6 ES cells. 
2. Apply conventional gene targeting criteria when designing the targeting vector. Key parameters include whether the modification is required 
to be constitutive or conditional, defining critical exons (CE) for deletion in a gene knockout strategy and spacing and placement of intronic 
cassettes. 
NOTE: Each of these has been discussed in detail elsewhere </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>. 
3. Choose genomic regions each of 5-6 kb flanking the target modification site. 
NOTE: The size of the subcloned insert is therefore typically 10-12 kb, although the upper limit can be as high as 80 kb with a low copy 
subcloning plasmid like p15A, pBR322 etc. and up to 200 kb with a BAC vector. </p>

<p>2. Multiplex Recombineering Oligos </p>

<p>1. Design oligos for the plasmid backbone (subcloning plasmid) and the selectable marker (insertion cassette). Design each oligo such that 
it contains 180 bp HA flanking the genomic target site and 20 bp of specific priming sequence of the insertion cassette or the subcloning 
plasmid (Figure 2). 
NOTE: Homology arms should not contain any repetitive elements, presence of repetitive elements will result in incorrect targeting and 
subcloning. Repetitive elements can be detected by using web based tools such as the ''Repeat Masker''. 
2. Include a unique restriction enzyme (RE) site on one of the vector oligos to linearize the gene targeting vector for ES cell targeting (Figure 2). 
3. Check oligo parameters using an <rs type="software">oligo analyzer</rs> program. Take care to avoid secondary structures in the priming regions. 
4. Shorter HA (50 bp) of the insertion cassette is tolerated and yields lower number of recombinants but ensure that the subcloning plasmid HA 
is always longer (180 bp). 
5. Determine the orientation of the genomic DNA insert of the particular BAC clone using web based tools like ''<rs type="software">cloneDB</rs>''. Establish the direction 
of replication from OriS by checking the map of the BAC plasmid backbone used in the BAC library construction. 
NOTE: OriS is usually opposite to the transcriptional direction of the Chloramphenicol (Chl) marker for all commonly used BAC plasmids. 
6. Add two terminal phosphorothioate (PTO) bonds to the 5' end of the oligo that is opposite to the direction of replication on the BAC clone. Add 
a 5' phosphate modification to the reverse oligo (Figure 2). 
NOTE: The asymmetric phosphorothioated PCR cassette upon Red digestion generates an ssDNA intermediate that can prime the lagging 
strand of the replication fork. 
NOTE: Maximal multiplex recombination frequency is observed with the lagging strand protected cassettes. Leading strand protected or dual 
protected cassettes may not produce equivalent recombination efficiencies at some loci. 
7. Order oligos with PAGE or HPLC purification. </p>

<p>3. BAC Clone Transformation with pSC101 BADgbaA Recombineering Plasmid. </p>

<p>1. To make the E. coli strain bearing the BAC recombineering proficient, transform it with the pSC101 BADgbaA plasmid containing the Red 
genes </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>. 
NOTE: The pSC101 BADgbaA plasmid contains the Red and RecA genes under the control of the Arabinose inducible araC-P BAD promoter, a 
tetracycline selection marker and the temperature sensitive pSC101 replicon. 
1. Stab a sterile pipette tip in the BAC agar culture and inoculate 5.0 ml of lysogeny broth (LB) pH 8.0 containing 12.5 μg ml 
-1 Chl. Grow at </p>

<p>37 °C for 5 hr shaking at 200 rpm. 
2. Chill 10% ( 
v / v ) glycerol solution, microcentrifuge tubes and electroporation cuvettes on ice. Cool a refrigerated large centrifuge and </p>

<p>microcentrifuge to 4 °C . 
3. Determine the optical density (OD) of the culture using a spectrophotometer and measure absorbance at 600 nm. Prepare 
electrocompetent cells (as described below) when an OD 600 reading of 0.3 to 0.8 is reached. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 3 of 13 </p>

<p>4. Spin down cells in a 50 ml centrifuge tube in a large centrifuge at 1,216 x g for 5 min at 4 °C . 
5. Wash cells with 1 ml of chilled 10% glycerol and spin down cells at 17,949 x g for 20 sec at 4 °C . Perform the wash step a total of 3 
times. 
6. Resuspend the cells in a total volume of 50 μl of 10% glycerol and add 10-200 ng of the pSC101 BADgbaA recombineering plasmid. 
Obtain a single cell suspension by pipetting up and down several times and then transfer the cells to a pre-chilled 1 mm gap 
electroporation cuvette. 
7. Electroporate the cells with a setting of 1.8 kv, 25 μF and 200 Ω. 
NOTE: Check the correct settings for each brand of electroporator. A time constant of electroporation less than 4 indicates the 
presence of salt and other impurities. 
8. Immediately recover the cells in 1 ml of LB and transfer the cells to a 50 ml centrifuge tube. 
9. Grow the BAC gbaA culture at 30 °C for 2 hr shaking at 200 rpm. 
NOTE: The pSC101 BADgbaA plasmid is lost when cells are grown at 37 °C due to inactivation of the temperature sensitive RepE 
replication factor. Grow gbaA cells at 30 °C to maintain the recombineering functions. 
10. Add 9 ml of LB containing 12.5 μg ml 
-1 Chl and 4 μg ml 
-1 Tetracycline (Tet) to the recovered BAC gbaA culture. Grow the BAC gbaA </p>

<p>culture O/N at 30 °C shaking at 200 rpm. 
NOTE: The transformation efficiency of electroporating the supercoiled gbaA plasmid is sufficiently high to permit saturation growth O/ 
N in liquid media. </p>

<p>4. Preparation of Insertion Cassettes and Subcloning Plasmids </p>

<p>1. To incorporate HA into the insertion cassette(s) and the subcloning plasmid, perform polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using the long 
modified oligos as described below. 
1. Optional: to prevent plasmid carryover into the recombineering reaction, use an R6K origin or similar narrow host range plasmid 
template to amplify the insertion cassette. 
2. Alternatively, linearize the plasmid template using an RE digest (Table 2). Choose a RE that cuts outside the PCR amplification region 
and is heat inactivated. Heat inactivate the RE as recommended by the manufacturer. 
3. Set up polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using a high-fidelity hotstart DNA polymerase system. Prepare a PCR master mix as detailed 
(Table 3). Perform thermal cycling as shown (Table 3). </p>

<p>2. Analyze PCR products by agarose gel electrophoresis. Load 1-5 μl of each PCR onto a 1% (w/v) agarose gel containing 0.5 mg ml 
-1 Ethidium </p>

<p>Bromide (EtBR). 
NOTE: The presence of non-specific amplification products does not interfere in the recombineering reaction. In some cases however, 
primer-dimers may decrease recombineering efficiency. 
3. Purify PCR products using a PCR purification kit. 
1. Optional: remove the plasmid template from PCRs by treatment with DpnI followed by PCR clean-up. Elute DNA in a minimal volume of 
sterile deionized water (as recommended by the manufacturer). 
NOTE: Addition of DpnI to unpurified PCR reactions results in reduced efficiency of cleavage of the methylated plasmid DNA template. </p>

<p>4. Quantify PCR amplified DNA by agarose gel analysis against a known set of DNA standards e.g., λ HindIII digest or by using a nanodrop 
spectrophotometer. </p>

<p>5. Subcloning Plus Insertion </p>

<p>1. Dilute the O/N BAC gbaA culture 50 fold by adding 200 μl in 10 ml LB+Chl+Tet. Grow at 30 °C shaking at 200 rpm for 1 hr 50 min. Include an 
sample to be used as negative control. 
2. Chill all recombineering materials and equipment to 4 °C as described in step 3.1.2. 
3. Pour LB agar pH 8 plates containing the correct concentration of the appropriate selective antibiotic(s) that will allow selection of the DNA 
fragment that is inserted as well as for the selection of the subcloning vector (Table 4). 
NOTE: Some antibiotics are pH sensitive. Use LB agar pH 8 as a rule. 
4. Prepare a 10% (w/v) solution of L-Arabinose. Filter sterilize through a 0.2 μm syringe filter. 
NOTE: Arabinose induces the expression of the recombineering proteins from the gbaA plasmid. 
5. Check the OD of the BAC gbaA culture using a spectrophotometer. Once an OD 600 of 0.25-0.3 is reached, induce the recombineering 
proteins as described in the following step. 
6. Add 200 μl of the 10% Arabinose solution to 10 ml of the BAC culture to achieve a final concentration of Arabinose of 0.2%. Include an 
uninduced culture (without Arabinose) to be used as negative control. 
7. Transfer the BAC culture to a 37 °C shaking incubator and induce Red expression for 45 min shaking at 230 rpm. 
NOTE: Expression of Red proteins is inefficient at 30 °C . 
8. Spin down cells and wash with 10% glycerol 3 times as described in step 3.1.5. 
9. Add 600-1,000 ng each of the subcloning plasmid and the insertion cassette(s) to the recombineering reaction. Include a vector only and 
vector plus single insert controls to check the recombination proficiency and integrity of the vector and the cassettes. 
10. Obtain a single cell suspension by pipetting up and down. Perform electroporation as described in step 3.1.7 and subsequent recovery in 1 ml 
LB at 37 °C for 1 hr for multi-copy plasmids or in 10 ml of LB at 37 °C for 3 hr for BAC vectors. 
11. Plate different dilutions of the recovered culture e.g., 90%, 10%, 1% on the dual selection agar plates and grow at 37 °C for 16 hr. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 4 of 13 </p>

<p>6. Analysis of Recombinants </p>

<p>1. Optional: Pick 6 to 12 colonies and perform colony PCR using a HA flanking primer and an insert specific primer. Include the subcloning 
plasmid and the insertion cassette plasmid as well as the parent BAC clone as negative controls. 
1. Perform agarose gel analysis of the colony PCRs. Identify positive clones by the presence of a bright band at the expected size. 
NOTE: The high efficiency of the SPI cloning process generates mostly correct recombinants. </p>

<p>2. Pick colonies into 5 ml LB pH 8 containing the selective antibiotic and grow O/N at 37 °C . 
3. Prepare DNA minipreps using a column purification kit as per the manufacturer's instructions. 
4. Prepare BAC miniprep DNA using standard phenol-chloroform isolation or a similar protocol. 
5. Perform RE digests on the miniprep DNA. Separate DNA by agarose gel electrophoresis. Analyze RE patterns to identify the clones 
containing the expected fragments sizes of the correct targeting vector. Choose an RE that clearly discriminates between the vector lacking 
insert(s) and the vector containing the insert(s). 
6. Optional: to obtain cells that are devoid of the BAC, which is still present in the E. coli after recombineering, use the miniprep plasmid DNA to 
transform DH5alpha or DH10B E. coli cells. 
7. Perform DNA sequencing across the HA and insertion cassette to check oligo synthesis errors. </p>

<p>Representative Results </p>

<p>Knockin Vectors </p>

<p>Knockin targeting vectors reflect the need to introduce a novel sequence feature in the genome including single base pair substitution in 
a protein coding region, the fusion of a fluorescent marker or an affinity tag to a protein or the integration of a gene expression cassette. 
To test the application of SPI in knockin vector construction strategies, two different test cases were examined. Dnttip1 encodes the 
deoxynucleotidyltransferase, terminal, interacting protein 1A (TDIF1) that together with class I histone deacetylase (HDAC) form a mitotic 
deacetylase complex (MiDAC) </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>. To investigate the role of Dnttip1 in cell division, a tandem-affinity tagging approach was taken to isolate the 
TDIF1 interacting proteins. Previous attempts to subclone a portion of the Dnttip1 gene using a p15A vector containing long homology regions 
resulted in low gap repair efficiency and frequent aberrant recombination products (data not shown). Thus, the construction of a knockin vector 
at the Dnttip1 locus provided a challenging recombineering exercise. A SPI strategy was designed to subclone a 12 kb section of the Dnttip1 
gene spanning the last exon (exon 13) into a low copy p15A vector and to simultaneously insert a dual affinity tag selection cassette into exon 
13, replacing the stop codon (Figure 3A). The 2X FLAG-calmodulin binding protein (CBP) linked FRT-PGK-em7-Neomycin (Neo)-BGhpA-FRT 
cassette (2.0 kb) was amplified from an RE linearized plasmid using dual PTO modified oligos that contained 120 bp HA flanking the Dnttip1 
stop codon. A p15A zeoDnttip1 subcloning vector (1.7 kb) was constructed that contained 200 bp regions homologous to the ends of the Dnttip1 
sequence to be subcloned. The Dnttip1 subcloning plasmid was RE linearized and PCR amplified using 20 bp modified oligos that generated 
a leading strand protected vector. The PCR products were DpnI treated, purified and co-electroporated into recombineering competent Dnttip1 
BAC E. coli cells as well as uninduced control cells. The SPI reactions were plated on Zeocin (Zeo) and Kanamycin (Kan) containing agar plates 
(Figure 3B). SPI produced the correctly modified Dnttip1 knockin vector in all of the 12 recombinants analysed (Figure 3C). DNA sequencing 
verified the absence of any errors resulting from oligo synthesis or PCR amplification. </p>

<p>Another example of SPI involved the in-frame insertion of an enhanced yellow fluorescent protein (eYFP) linked selection cassette at the P2rx1 
gene. The P2rx1 gene encodes a G-protein-coupled receptor that functions as an ATP-gated ion channel </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>. Linkage to YFP fluorescence permits 
the tracking of the P2x1 receptor on the cell surface in various functional assays. P2rx1 is another difficult locus that has presented significant 
problems with conventional recombineering methodologies (data not shown). Using SPI, a 12 kb segment of the P2rx1 gene encompassing the 
terminal exon (exon 12) was subcloned into a p15A zeo vector and modified with the concerted insertion of an eYFP-LoxP flanked Neo cassette 
replacing the stop codon in exon 12 to construct the P2rx1-eYFP knockin vector (Figure 3D). In this example, the lagging strand protected p15A 
vector (1.7 kb) contained 230 bp HA and the eYFP cassette contained 50 bp HA and was also left unmodified. The eYFP insertion cassette (2.7 
kb) was assembled by splicing overlap PCR of the eYFP gene, PCR amplified from pEYFP-C1, and the LoxP-PGK-em7-Neo-BGhpA-LoxP 
cassette, PCR amplified from pL452 (NCI, Frederick). The SPI reaction produced hundreds of colonies (data not shown). RE analysis of DNA 
minipreps prepared from 11 clones showed the majority contained the correctly assembled P2rx1-eYFP knockin vector (Figure 3E). Additional 
validation by DNA sequencing showed error free insertion of the eYFP cassette. However, some of the clones showed profiles of the untagged 
gap repaired and the tagged gap repaired plasmids in the same cell (lanes 6-9). A few samples also contained incorrectly gap repaired (lane 
2) or mistargeted plasmids (lanes 4 and 5). The failure of concurrent subcloning and targeting in some SPI recombinants highlights the limits 
of efficient SPI cloning when using large cassettes (&gt; 3 kb), which arise from the constraints on Red processivity of long DNA fragments </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>, or if 
using short HA. Indeed, increasing the HA of the eYFP cassette to 200 bp increased SPI efficiency and the correct targeting of the cassette (data 
not shown). Gene targeting with the P2rx1-eYFP knockin vector in JM8.N4 mouse ES cells (C57BL/6 strain) generated 6 positive clones out of 
96, which contained the correctly targeted P2rx1-eYFP sequence (Figure 3F). </p>

<p>BAC Reporter Vectors </p>

<p>A BAC clone of the target gene often contains all the requisite upstream and downstream regulatory elements e.g., enhancers, UTRs etc. as well 
the endogenous promoter to drive gene expression at natural levels </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>. A BAC reporter vector is therefore the preferred vehicle to recapitulate the 
endogenous expression pattern of a gene </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>. However, the large size of a BAC plasmid (up to 200 kb) presents significant practical problems with 
transfecting an intact BAC into cells </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>. Reducing the size of the BAC genomic insert through BAC trimming </p>

<p>34,35 </p>

<p>, while retaining the necessary 
regulatory elements of a gene, enables easier handling of the BAC and results in a more efficient transfection. Current BAC engineering 
technology involves multiple rounds of recombineering to achieve this goal 
35 . To demonstrate the utility of SPI in BAC trimming, a pBeloBAC11 </p>

<p>BAC vector was used to subclone a 30 kb genomic sequence including the full length P2rx1 gene from the 168 kb P2rx1 BAC together with 
the simultaneous insertion of an eYFP cassette in the P2rx1 gene (Figure 4A). The pBeloBAC11 zeo vector backbone (6.5 kb) containing 180 
bp HA was PCR amplified with modified oligos that generated a lagging strand protected vector. The same eYFP Neo cassette (3 kb), used in 
the previous P2rx1 knockin vector construction, was PCR amplified using lagging strand protected oligos containing 180 bp HA and targeted </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 5 of 13 </p>

<p>the P2rx1 exon 12 replacing the stop codon. Following combined electroporation of the eYFP cassette and the pBeloBAC11 zeo vector into 
P2rx1 BAC cells expressing the gbaA recombineering proteins, the culture was recovered in 10 ml LB pH 8 for 3 hr at 37C to segregate the BAC 
plasmids. Pure recombinants were selected on Zeo and Kan agar plates and were observed at a frequency of 2 x 10 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>. Colony PCR genotyping 
analysis revealed successful BAC trimming in the 3 out of 6 clones that were analysed (Figure 4B). Long range PCR amplification across the 
eYFP insertion site confirmed the correct cassette incorporation in the three positive clones (Figure 4B). The three clones lacking the eYFP 
insert were also incorrectly gap repaired at the 5' end, though the cause of mistargeting of the eYFP cassette in these clones may be separate 
to the correct closure of the 5' BAC end. The three eYFP positive BAC clones were further analysed with RE digests and showed the expected 
pattern of the correctly trimmed eYFP recombinant BAC (Figure 4C). Sequence analysis revealed absence of errors in the eYFP cassette in only 
1 clone out of the 3 positives. </p>

<p>Conditional Knockout (cko) Vectors </p>

<p>Conditional ablation of gene expression is an important tool to investigate developmental processes or to study biological systems at a particular 
time point. A conditional gene knockout strategy typically involves the placement of LoxP recombination sites surrounding a critical exon (CE). 
The deletion of a CE upon Cre expression or activation produces a frameshift and a premature stop codon, resulting in degradation of the mRNA 
due to nonsense mediated decay (NMD). The construction of a conditional gene targeting vector is a complex task and involves several steps 
of subcloning, targeting and transformation </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>. SPI offers a convenient route to simplify this process. As a test case, a conditional allele of the 
Zrsr2 gene was constructed using the SPI methodology (Figure 5A). The Zrsr2 gene encodes a splicing factor and a single copy is located on 
the X chromosome. The conditional status of gene deletion is particularly important in this instance to control for the possibility of cells adapting 
to the lack of Zrsr2 during ES cell selection in a constitutive gene deletion targeting strategy. SPI was performed to subclone a 10 kb portion 
of the ZrSr2 gene with concurrent insertion of two different LoxP flanked selection cassettes. The FRT-PGK-em7-Neo-FRT-LoxP cassette (2 
kb) was PCR amplified from RE digested pL451 using lagging strand protected oligos that contained 180 bp HA targeting the ZrSr2 intron 2. 
A second cassette containing Rox-PGK-em7-Blasticidin (Bsd)-Rox-LoxP (2 kb) was PCR amplified from an R6K plasmid with lagging strand 
protected oligos containing 180 bp HA identical to a downstream region in intron 3. The two LoxP sites flanked exon 3, the CE whose deletion 
upon conditional Cre activation results in a frameshift and introduces a premature stop codon. The Zrsr2 subcloning plasmid (1.6 kb) was PCR 
amplified from an RE linearised p15A zeo plasmid using lagging strand protected oligos containing 180 bp HA matching the ends of the 10 kb 
Zrsr2 sequence. SPI reactions were performed as described before and plated on Zeo+Neo+Bsd plates. The ZrSr2 conditional targeting vector 
was successfully assembled in most of the 12 recombinants examined (Figure 5B). Further DNA sequencing analysis showed correct insertion 
of both the selection markers in the ZrSr2 cko vector. </p>

<p>Figure 1. SPI cloning. Overview of the SPI cloning process combining cassette insertion and subcloning in a single step. (A) The BAC clone 
is transformed with the pSC101 BADgbaA plasmid and grown at 30C. (B) Following arabinose induction to express the Red proteins, the 
asymmetric modified insertion cassette and subcloning plasmid are introduced into the BAC clone and selected with both the insertion and 
subcloning markers to generate the final vector. Please click here to view a larger version of this figure. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 6 of 13 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Schematic illustrating the design of SPI recombineering oligos. The subcloning plasmid and insertion cassette are both generated 
by PCR using a combination of terminal PTO and phosphate modified oligos. The PCR fragment upon Red digestion in vivo, produces an 
ssDNA intermediate, which anneals to the lagging strand of the replication fork. Gene specific HA of 50-180 bp is incorporated into each oligo 
as shown. The arrow indicates the direction of DNA replication across a candidate gene. Dashed line represents subcloning plasmid sequence 
not incorporated into the PCR product. RE site, restriction enzyme site of linearization of final vector; F, forward sequence (20 bp) specific to the 
subcloning plasmid or insertion cassette; R, reverse complement sequence (20 bp) of the plasmid or cassette; sm, selection marker. Please click 
here to view a larger version of this figure. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 7 of 13 </p>

<p>Figure 3. SPI enables construction of difficult knockin vectors. (A) Schematic of the SPI strategy used in the construction of the Dnttip1 
dual tagged vector. Arrow indicates the direction of replication on the BAC clone. (B) Plating results of the uninduced and induced samples of 
the Dnttip1 SPI experiment. (C) EcoRI digest of Dnttip1 SPI clones. M, 1 kb ladder (NEB); C, p15A Dnttip1 gap repaired plasmid lacking the 
dual tag cassette. Fragment sizes are: tagged, 9.2+4.4+2.2 kb; control; 9.2+4.6 kb. (D) SPI based P2rx1-eYFP knockin vector construction. (E) 
EcoRI digest of P2rx1-eYFP SPI clones. M, 1 kb+ ladder (Invitrogen); C, p15A P2rx1 gap repaired plasmid lacking the eYFP cassette. Fragment 
sizes are: tagged, 8.3+4.4+3.1+0.03 kb; control; 8.3+3.1+1.8+0.03 kb. (F) Southern blot analysis of P2rx1-eYFP gene targeting in JM8.N4 ES 
cell cells. Top panel, Southern blot with the 3' end probe using PshAI digest. Shown is the screening result of 5 clones. Bottom panel, Southern 
blot using the 5' end probe and SpeI digest of the positives identified from the 3' end screening. PshAI RE site; S, SpeI RE site. Dashed line 
represents the end of the vector HA. Black box denotes southern probe. Expected restriction fragments are, PshAI: WT, 8.9 kb; eYFP-neo, 11.5 
kb; SpeI: WT, 6.9 kb; eYFP-neo, 7.6 kb. Please click here to view a larger version of this figure. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 8 of 13 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Simplified BAC trimming using SPI. (A) Schematic illustrating the concept of BAC trimming using SPI. Key to symbols is described 
in Figure 1. (B) PCR amplification across the 5' and 3' ends of the subcloned insert and across the P2rx1-eYFP insertion site. The screening 
strategy is shown for each type of PCR. M (top panel), Hyperladder 25 bp, (bottom panels), 1kb+; P, P2rx1 BAC; S, pBeloBAC11 zeo subcloning 
plasmid. (C) HindIII digest of the three eYFP positive SPI BAC clones from (B); E, expected HindIII restriction pattern of the trimmed eYFP BAC. 
Please click here to view a larger version of this figure. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 9 of 13 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Conditional knockout vector generation using SPI cloning. (A) Schematic of the simultaneous insertion of two different LoxP 
flanked selection cassettes during subcloning of the Zrsr2 allele. Key to symbols is described in Figure 1. (B) EcoRI digests of Zrsr2 SPI clones. 
L, 1 kb ladder (NEB); C1, p15A ZrSr2 gap repaired plasmid, C2, p15A ZrSr2 gap repaired plasmid containing the neo insert; C3, p15A ZrSr2 gap 
repaired plasmid containing the bsd insert. Fragment sizes are: cko, 7.7+2.9+2.6+1.6 kb; C1, 7.7+4.0 kb; C2, 7.7+4.3+1.6 kb; C3, 7.7+2.9+2.3 
kb. Please click here to view a larger version of this figure. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 10 of 13 </p>

<p>No of steps 
Conventional recombineering pipeline </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Multiplex recombineering </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Step 1 
Transformation of recombineering plasmid into 
BAC host </p>

<p>Transformation of recombineering plasmid 
into BAC host. Preparation of the targeting 
cassettes and subcloning vectors. </p>

<p>Step 2 
Insertion of R1/R2 Gateway cassette 
Multiplex gap repair cloning </p>

<p>Step 3 
Insertion of floxed Kan cassette 
O/N culture from single colonies </p>

<p>Step 4 
Gap repair into R3/R4 plasmid 
Plasmid preparation and verification </p>

<p>Step 5 
Transformation into Cre+ E. coli </p>

<p>Step 6 
Plasmid preparation and verification </p>

<p>Step 7 
O/N three-way Gateway reaction </p>

<p>Step 8 
Transformation of the three-way Gateway 
reaction into DH10B E. coli cells </p>

<p>Step 9 
Overnight culture from single colonies </p>

<p>Step 10 
Plasmid preparation and sequence verification </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Knockout mouse program (KOMP) high throughput vector construction pipeline. Average time of 3 weeks to verified clone </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Average time of 4 days to verified clone </p>

<p>Table 1: Comparison of conventional recombineering with SPI in the construction of conditional knockout vectors. </p>

<p>RE buffer 
5 μl </p>

<p>DNA 
1 μg plasmid or purified PCR products </p>

<p>RE 
1 μl (5 units or more) </p>

<p>TE 
up to 50 μl </p>

<p>Incubate at 37 °C for at least 1 hr. Heat inacitvate according to the manufacturers instructions </p>

<p>Table 2: RE digest. </p>

<p>PCR materials 
Final concentration </p>

<p>PCR buffer 
1x </p>

<p>dNTP 
200 nM </p>

<p>MgSO 4 
1.5 mM </p>

<p>Betaine 
1.3 M </p>

<p>DMSO 
1% </p>

<p>Forward primer 
200 nM </p>

<p>Reverse primer 
200 nM </p>

<p>DNA polymerase 
1 U </p>

<p>Template 
10 ng of multicopy plasmids or 2.5 μl of miniprep DNA for genotyping 
PCRs </p>

<p>Water 
up to 50 μl </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>For a standard 50 μl PCR reaction with multicopy plasmids. Long range genotyping PCRs were set up in 25 μl PCR reactions. </p>

<p>PCR conditions </p>

<p>95°C 
2 min </p>

<p>92°C 
10 sec </p>

<p>55°C 
30 sec </p>

<p>72°C 
30 sec </p>

<p>30 cycles </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Cycle no may be extended to 35 for BAC PCR genotyping </p>

<p>Table 3: PCR Set-up and Conditions. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 11 of 13 </p>

<p>Antibiotics 
Concentration 
a (μg ml </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Ampicllin 
50 </p>

<p>Blasticidin </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Chloramphenicol 
12.5 </p>

<p>Gentamicin 
2 </p>

<p>Hygromycin </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Kanamycin </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Tetracycline 
4 </p>

<p>Trimethoprim </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Zeocin 
5 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Recommended for use with BACs and multicopy plasmids when used in combinations in multiplex recombineering </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Blasticidin (35 μg ml </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) and Kanamycin (6 μg ml </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) when used together in combination </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Hygromycin and Trimethoprim are not recommended for selection with single copy BACs. </p>

<p>Table 4. Recommended antibiotic concentrations for use in SPI experiments. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Construction of ES cell lines and mouse models has historically involved gene targeting using plasmid constructs that contained the modified 
allele </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>. However, the construction of these complex gene targeting vectors has proved to be a significant bottleneck in the timely production of 
such models. The development of recombineering based vector construction strategies has allowed improved vector designs and more efficient 
vector assembly. Nonetheless, current recombineering protocols still involve multiple steps, require intermediate plasmid purification and use 
different bacterial strains. Subcloning plus insertion offers a novel approach to vector construction that can be performed in one electroporation 
event in the resident BAC host strain. The utility of SPI in gene targeting was tested here in a variety of vector construction applications. In 
all instances examined here, SPI proved to be efficient and the correct recombinant plasmid was produced. In the majority of the cases, the 
multiple different cassettes were correctly inserted in the targeting vector. Large DNA cassettes and vectors were easily accommodated in the 
SPI protocol and demonstrated the flexibility of this system. </p>

<p>SPI relies on the use of long homology sequences and phosphorothioate (PTO) protection of the linear DNA cassettes. PTO modification confers 
protection against exonucleases to the linear DNA 
20,21 and the long HA increases recombination efficiency to permit multiplexing. However, </p>

<p>synthesis of longer oligo sequences increases the chances of accumulating errors especially deletions. Mutations in the oligo can be particularly 
detrimental if they cover protein coding regions. DNA sequencing across the HA and covering the full-length of the inserted cassette is highly 
recommended to eliminate clones with any sequence alterations. Use of a high-fidelity DNA polymerase system is also suggested to avoid 
introduction of any PCR errors. The length and composition of the HA of the subcloning plasmid is more critical relative to that of the insertion 
cassette (data not shown). For particularly sensitive applications like construction of knockin vectors, where any mutations in exon regions 
are not tolerated, the HA of the insertion cassette can be shortened (50-120 bp) to avoid problems associated with long oligos. The insertion 
cassette can also be left unmodified or dual phosphorothioated (where knowledge of the direction of replication is not available). But multiplexing 
in these cases still requires long protected HA subcloning plasmids. A caveat of this particular strategy is the lowering of multiplexing efficiency 
that can potentially impact SPI cloning at different loci. </p>

<p>The length of the insertion cassette and the subcloning plasmid is another important parameter in SPI cloning. Larger DNA molecules 
electroporate less efficiently and the effect is cumulative, given the requirement to introduce all the cassettes in the same cell (data not shown). 
Multiplexing is most efficient with smaller insertion cassettes. DNA fragments larger than 3 kb also place a limit on Red mediated ssDNA 
processing, which is most efficient up to 3 kb </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>. Insertion cassettes exceeding 3 kb are dual resected and recombine less efficiently via a beta 
independent pathway </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>. Therefore, screening of sufficient colonies to identify the correct clone becomes important in these cases. A longer 
duration of recombination post electroporation also increases the chances of recovery of the correct clone in difficult SPI exercises. Up to 
four small cassettes (&lt; 1.5 kb) can be inserted simultaneously with the SPI process, though the multiplexing efficiency decreases with each 
additional cassette (data not shown). However, this reflects the outcome of an optimal SPI experiment and it is advisable to consider the limits of 
multiplexing when using many large cassettes. </p>

<p>The development of genome editing tools like clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPR)-cas9 endonuclease system 
has enabled the creation of novel genome modifications and has led to more efficient genome engineering </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>. However, these newer technologies 
have complemented gene targeting vectors rather than supplanted them. It is envisaged that the CRISPR-cas system could replace antibiotic 
selection and further refine the multiplex recombineering protocol. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>T.R.R is the inventor of a British patent application on multiplex recombineering technology. </p>

<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 12 of 13 </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>T.R.R conceived the project, designed and performed experiments and prepared the manuscript. E.J.K and S.E.M performed experiments. All 
authors contributed intellectually to the final manuscript. This work was funded by a University of Leicester Innovation Fellowship to SEM and 
by a UK Medical Research Council (MRC) Senior Research Fellowship to S.M.C (MR/J009202/1). DNA sequencing was performed by Protein 
and Nucleic Acid Laboratories (PNACL), Centre for Core Biotechnology Services, University of Leicester. We wish to thank A. Francis Stewart for 
providing the Rox and Dre plasmids. pL451 and pL452 plasmids were obtained from National Cancer Institute (NCI), Frederick, USA. </p>



<p>Journal of Visualized Experiments </p>

<p>www.jove.com </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015 Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License 
January 2015 | 95 | e52155 | Page 13 of 13 </p>



</text></tei>