<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4257079" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: The hemodialysis procedure involves contact 
between peripheral blood and the surface of dialyzer mem-
branes, which may lead to alterations in the pathways of 
innate and adaptive immunity. We aimed to study the 
effect of blood-membrane interaction on human peripheral 
basophils and neutrophils in hemodialysis with high-and 
low-permeability polysulfone dialyzers. The surface expres-
sion of CD203c (basophil selection marker) and CD63 (acti-
vation marker) after activation by the bacterial peptide 
formyl-methionyl-leucyl-phenylalanine (fMLP) or anti-Fcε 
receptor I (FcεRI) antibody and the absolute number of 
basophils was investigated before and after hemodialysis 
with each of the dialyzers. Moreover, the expression on 
neutrophils of CD11b, the CD11b active epitope, and CD88 
was analyzed in the same groups of individuals. The expres-
sion of CD63 in basophils following activation by fMLP was 
significantly higher in the patient group compared with that </p>

<p>in healthy controls, but no differences were observed after 
activation by anti-FcεRI. During the hemodialysis proce-
dure, the low-flux membrane induced up-regulation of 
CD63 expression on basophils, while passage through the 
high-flux membrane did not significantly alter the respon-
siveness. In addition, the absolute number of basophils 
was unchanged after hemodialysis with either of the 
dialyzers and compared with healthy controls. We found no 
significant differences in the expression of the neutrophil 
activation markers (CD11b, the active epitope of CD11b, 
and CD88) comparing the two different dialyzers before 
and after dialysis and healthy controls. Together, these 
findings suggest that alterations in basophil activity may 
be a useful marker of membrane bioincompatibility in 
hemodialysis. cellulose membranes were used in the early era of 
hemodialysis but have long since been substituted by 
membranes based on modified cellulose (cellulose 
diacetate and hemophan) and subsequently by 
membranes manufactured from synthetic polymers 
(polyacrylonitrile [AN69] or polysulfone). The modi-
fied and synthetic materials were introduced to 
improve the biocompatibility of dialyzers. In previ-
ous studies, it has been shown that neutrophils from 
patients dialyzed with polysulfone membranes have 
higher functionality compared with cells collected 
from patients treated with unmodified or modified 
cellulose membranes (5). The hemodialysis proce-
dure induces complement activation, as evidenced by 
the increased production of complement factors. 
These factors contribute to dialysis-associated micro-
inflammation through the release of interleukins 
(ILs) by monocytes, which exert chemotactic activity 
on neutrophils and monocytes (10). The intensity of 
complement generation is closely dependent on the 
type of dialysis membrane (11). In addition, the per-
meability of the membrane contributes to the overall 
biocompatibility properties. High-flux dialyzers (with 
large pore size and higher ultrafiltration coefficients) 
have better clearance of large molecules, such as 
β2-microglobulin and toxins with enzymatic and 
metabolic inhibitory effect, compared with low-flux 
dialyzers (with smaller pore size and lower ultra-
filtration coefficients), but the clinical consequences 
in terms of morbidity and mortality of long-term use 
are still debated (12-14). 
Basophils constitute a subtype of granulocytes and 
represent &lt;1% of total circulating leukocytes (15). 
Involvement of basophils in autoimmune kidney dis-
eases, such as lupus nephritis, has previously been 
observed. Formation of immune complexes may 
trigger basophils to secrete IL-4 and initiate T helper 
type 2 (Th2) differentiation, B-cell proliferation, 
plasma cell differentiation, and immunoglobulin 
production, responsible for the ongoing humoral 
immune response in affected tissues (16,17). It has 
also been proposed that hemodialysis patients 
display IgE-mediated anaphylactic reactions and that 
basophils from patients with autoimmune kidney 
disease up-regulate the cell surface expression of 
markers such as CD203c and CD63 upon activation 
(18,19). Studies have previously shown that neutro-
phil activity can be used to reflect the biocompatibil-
ity properties of different dialyzers. For example, 
CD11b expression on neutrophils was increased after 
hemodialysis with unsubstituted and substituted cel-
lulosic membranes, while it was similar to that in 
healthy controls after hemodialysis with synthetic 
polysulfone membranes (7). </p>

<p>Given the potential impact of the dialysis proce-
dure on granulocyte function, we aimed to investi-
gate the differences in activation of basophils (CD63 
expression) and neutrophils (expression of CD11b 
and the active epitope of CD11b) and in CD88 
expression in CKD patients undergoing hemodialysis 
with high-flux or low-flux polysulfone membranes, 
compared with that observed in healthy controls. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Study population 
The hemodialysis patients were recruited from 
the Department of Nephrology at the Karolinska 
University Hospital in Stockholm, Sweden. The pa-
tients had an estimated glomerular filtration rate 
(eGFR) of &lt;20 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 with a residual GFR 
of 6-11 mL/min/1.73 m 
2 (median 7). Patients were 
undergoing hemodialysis with high-flux polysulfone 
dialyzers three times per week for 4-4.5 h per dialysis 
before the study (n = 10). The dialysis vintage in this 
group was 4-84 months with median duration of 24 
months, and dialysis was done via an arteriovenous 
fistula (n = 8) or a central dialysis catheter (n = 2). 
Patients with cancer, an ongoing infection, or chronic 
inflammatory disease and those taking immunosup-
pressive drugs were excluded. Healthy controls were 
recruited among healthy blood donors (n = 10), all 
sex-and age-matched (±5 years) with the hemodi-
alysis patients. Demographic characteristics of all 
participants are shown in Table 1. The patients were 
treated with diuretics, beta-blockers, angiotensin-
converting enzyme inhibitors, angiotensin receptor 
blockers, calcium channel blockers, or a combination 
of these drugs (Table 1). Participants filled out a 
questionnaire regarding their health status, current 
comorbidities, medication, and vaccination status 
against hepatitis and influenza virus prior to the 
study. Written informed consent was obtained from 
all participants. </p>

<p>Dialysis procedure 
Before the study, the patients were routinely 
undergoing hemodialysis with a high-flux polysulfone 
capillary hemodiafilter with an effective surface area 
of 2.3 m 
2 (K0A urea: 1421 mL/min; ultrafiltration 
coefficient: 76 mL/h/mm Hg; sterilization method: 
inline steam; FX corDiax 1000, Fresenius AG, Bad 
Homburg, Germany). In one session of treatment, 
the dialyzer was shifted to a low-flux polysulfone cap-
illary dialyzer with an effective surface area of 1.8 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(K0A urea: 976 mL/min; ultrafiltration coefficient: 
14 mL/h/mm Hg; sterilization method: inline steam; </p>

<p>Z. ALJADI ET AL. 
946 </p>

<p>Artif Organs, Vol. 38, No. 11, 2014 </p>

<p>FX 10, Fresenius AG). The dialyzers were not 
reused, and interdialytic weight gain was less than 
5%, indicating similar ultrafiltration volumes. The 
purity of the dialysate fluid was tested at recom-
mended intervals according to the European best 
practice guidelines (20) and was found to be pure at 
all occasions. 
Peripheral blood samples were drawn before and 
after hemodialysis in each session (one session with 
high flux and one session with low flux). </p>

<p>Determination of CD203c and CD63 expression 
in basophils 
Initially, samples from eight study subjects were 
analyzed: four samples from healthy controls and 
four pre-high-flux hemodialysis samples. Whole 
blood was drawn into heparin tubes (Vacutainer, 
Becton Dickinson, Oxford, UK) and then incubated 
with different concentrations of stimulators (formyl-
methionyl-leucyl-phenylalanine [fMLP] and anti-Fcε 
receptor I [FcεRI] antibody) to achieve the optimal 
concentration for a maximum basophil activation 
response (21). fMLP was diluted in RPMI 1640 
medium (Sigma Aldrich, Taufkirchen, Germany) and 
concentrations of 10 
−6 to 5 × 10 
−5 M were prepared. 
Anti-FcεRI antibody (3 μg/mL) (Bühlmann Labora-
tories, Schönenbuch, Switzerland) was diluted (1:3) in 
stimulation buffer (Bühlmann Laboratories) and con-
centrations of 0.11 μg/mL to 3 μg/mL were prepared 
accordingly. Whole blood (100 μL) was distributed 
among polystyrene tubes (Falcon, Becton Dickinson, 
Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA) and incubated with the 
relevant concentrations of fMLP and anti-FcεRI anti-
body at 37°C for 25 min to initiate the degranulation 
of basophils and histamine release. Subsequently the </p>

<p>cells were stained with 18 μL of anti-CD203c-PE and 
CD63-FITC antibodies (Beckman Coulter, Paris, 
France) and incubated for 25 min at 4°C. Following 
lysis of red blood cells (RBCs) with 2 mL cold isotonic 
solution (154 mM NH4Cl, 10 mM KHCO3 supple-
mented with 0.1 mM EDTA, pH 7.2), samples were 
centrifuged for 5 min at 300 × g at 4°C; cells were then 
washed once with phosphate buffered saline (PBS) 
before being resuspended in 300 μL of cold PBS and 
subsequently analyzed. The surface expression of 
CD203c and CD63 on basophils was analyzed by 
flow cytometry (Navios, Beckman Coulter, Hialeah, 
FL, USA). Basophils were gated according to their 
granularity on side scatter and expression of CD203c 
(Fig. 1a). The percentage of CD63-positive cells 
within the total basophil population was calculated as 
shown in Fig. 1b. Data were analyzed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Kaluza analysis software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Beckman Coulter</rs>). 
After the optimal concentrations of fMLP and 
anti-FcεRI antibody were found, the same procedure 
was applied on the rest of the samples after incuba-
tion of 100 μL of whole blood with RPMI medium (as 
negative control), RPMI medium containing fMLP at 
a concentration of 5 × 10 
−5 M, and anti-FcεRI anti-
body at a concentration of 3 μg/mL in separate tubes. </p>

<p>Estimation of absolute number of basophils 
The absolute number of basophils was estimated in 
100 μL of whole blood by using the ImmunoPrep 
reagent system (Beckman Coulter) according to 
manufacturer's instructions. Subsequently, 100 μL of 
pretreated whole blood was mixed with 100 μL 
flow-count beads (Beckman Coulter) before flow 
cytometric analysis. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Demographic characteristics of participants </p>

<p>Category 
Healthy controls 
Hemodialysis </p>

<p>Sex 
Male (n) 
5 
5 
Female (n) 
5 
5 
Age (years), range (median) 
33-81 (64.5) 
37-76 (62.5) 
Comorbidities (n) 
Diabetes 
0 
2 
History of heart disease 
0 
4 
Hypertension 
0 
9 
Family history of kidney disease (n) 
0 
3 
Treatment (n) 
ACE inhibitors/ARB 
0 
5 
ESA 
0 
9 
Intravenous iron 
0 
8 
Vitamin D 
0 
9 
Smoking (n) 
0 
0 
Swedish snuff (n) 
0 
2 </p>

<p>ACE, angiotensin-converting enzyme; ARB, angiotensin receptor blockers; ESA, 
erythropoiesis-stimulating agent. </p>

<p>BASOPHIL ACTIVATION IN HEMODIALYSIS 
947 </p>

<p>Artif Organs, Vol. 38, No. 11, 2014 </p>

<p>Flow cytometric analysis of surface CD11b, active 
CD11b, and CD88 expression on neutrophils 
Whole blood was drawn into EDTA tubes 
(Vacutainer, Becton Dickinson) before and after the 
hemodialysis procedure with high-and low-flux 
dialyzers, respectively. Blood (150 μL) was distrib-
uted in polystyrene tubes and mixed with 2 mL cold 
isotonic solution to lyse the erythrocytes. After 
5 min, the tubes were centrifuged for 5 min at 300 × g 
at 4°C, the supernatant was discarded, and the cells 
were washed with PBS. The tubes were divided into 
three groups: the unstimulated cells, the cells stimu-
lated with increased temperature (+37°C), and the 
cells stimulated with IL-8 (CXCL8) (Research &amp; 
Diagnostics Systems, Abingdon, UK). RPMI 1640 
medium (200 μL) mixed with 10% fetal calf serum 
was added to all the tubes. IL-8-stimulated cells were 
stimulated with a final concentration of 100 ng/mL 
IL-8 (22). The unstimulated cells were incubated on 
ice, while the stimulated cells were incubated at 37°C 
for 30 min. The tubes were washed with PBS, 
and cells were resuspended in 100 μL of cold PBS. 
Antibodies were added to the relevant tubes-anti-
CD11b-FITC (Beckman Coulter; 20 μL) and anti-
CD11b-PE (activated form, clone CBRM1/5, 
BioLegend Inc., San Diego, CA, USA; 20 μL), as 
well as corresponding isotype controls (IgG1). The 
tubes were incubated for 30 min at 4°C. The cells 
were washed with PBS, resuspended in 350 μL of 
cold PBS, and subsequently analyzed. Data acquisi-
tion was conducted by flow cytometer, and data were 
analyzed using the <rs type="software">Kaluza analysis software</rs>. 
Neutrophils were gated according to their size and 
granularity on forward and side scatter as shown in 
Fig. 1c. The mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) of 
CD11b 
+ cells and percentage of active-CD11b 
+ cells 
were measured within region G, according to the 
gates set by the respective isotype controls. For 
detection of CD88 expression, 150 μL of blood was 
added to polystyrene tubes, RBCs were lysed, and 
cells were washed with PBS, resuspended in 100 μL 
of PBS, and incubated with 20 μL anti-CD88 anti-</p>

<p>body (Becton Dickinson) for 30 min, then washed 
once and, after addition of PBS, analyzed with flow 
cytometry. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
Scatter plots were prepared using <rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad Prism 5</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA, USA</rs>), 
representing the range with whiskers and the median 
as a middle line. Statistical analysis was done in 
<rs type="software">GraphPad Prism 5</rs>. As the study population was 
not normally distributed, comparison between the 
groups was performed by the nonparametric 
Kruskal-Wallis test. Significant differences between 
groups were analyzed using the post hoc Wilcoxon 
matched-pairs signed-rank test. A P value of &lt;0.05 
was considered significant. </p>

<p>Ethics statement 
The study was approved by the local ethical 
committee at the Karolinska University Hospital, 
Stockholm, Sweden (2012/1027/32). 
Written informed consent was obtained from all 
participants. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Laboratory findings 
The laboratory data for the study participants are 
shown in Table 2. There were no significant differ-
ences between the groups with regard to total leuko-
cyte and platelet counts. The erythrocyte count was 
significantly higher in healthy controls compared 
with patients, but no differences were seen when 
comparing pre-and postdialysis samples with either 
of the dialyzers. Serum albumin was significantly 
lower in hemodialysis patients before the procedure 
compared with healthy controls. </p>

<p>Absolute number of basophils following dialysis 
with high-flux and low-flux dialyzers compared with 
healthy controls 
The absolute number of basophils was calculated 
by flow cytometry to investigate the effect of dialyzer </p>

<p>a 
b 
c </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Flow-cytometric analysis of CD203c 
and CD63 expression on basophils and 
CD11b expression on neutrophils. Basophils 
were gated according to their granularity on 
side scatter and expression of CD203c (a). 
The number of CD63-positive cells within 
the total basophil population was measured 
(b). Granulocytes were gated according to 
their size and granularity on forward and 
side scatter (c). </p>

<p>Z. ALJADI ET AL. 
948 </p>

<p>Artif Organs, Vol. 38, No. 11, 2014 </p>

<p>membrane on the number of cells. There were no 
significant differences in the absolute number of 
basophils following hemodialysis with high-flux or 
low-flux dialyzers. In addition, the absolute number 
was similar to that of healthy controls (Table 3). </p>

<p>Optimization of basophil activation response to 
different concentrations of fMLP and anti-FcεRI 
antibody (dose-response curve) 
Basophils were stimulated by various concentra-
tions of fMLP (bacterial peptide) and anti-FcεRI 
antibody, and the activation response (CD63 expres-
sion) to stimulators was analyzed as shown in Fig. 2. 
Basophil activation response to fMLP at various con-
centrations reached a plateau, and therefore the con-
centration of 5 × 10 
−5 M was chosen as the optimal 
concentration (Fig. 2a). </p>

<p>Anti-FcεRI antibodies act by cross-linking the 
receptors on the surface of basophils and are a stron-
ger stimulator for degranulation. The maximum 
response of basophils was to anti-FcεRI antibody was 
observed at the concentration of 3 μg/mL, and the 
lowest observed stimulation was seen at a concentra-
tion of 0.11 μg/mL (Fig. 2b). </p>

<p>Basophil activation response to fMLP and 
anti-FcεRI antibody comparing hemodialysis 
patients with healthy controls 
The expression of CD63 in basophils was analyzed 
following fMLP and anti-FcεRI antibody stimula-
tion. Samples from patients on hemodialysis, 
obtained before each session of dialysis with high-
flux or low-flux dialyzers, were compared with those 
from healthy controls (n = 10 in each group). The </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Laboratory data for blood parameters (n = 14) </p>

<p>Leukocyte count 
(×10 
9 /L) </p>

<p>Erythrocyte count 
(×10 
12 /L) </p>

<p>Platelet count 
(×10 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>/L) </p>

<p>Creatinine 
(μmol/L) </p>

<p>Albumin 
(g/L) </p>

<p>CRP 
(mg/L) </p>

<p>Healthy 
5.3 (4.6-7.3) 
4.8 (4.4-5.0) 
246 (218-291) 
81 (65-83) 
39 (36.5-41) 
1 (1-3) 
Pre-HFD 
7.0 (6.6-9.0) 
3.7 (3.5-3.8) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>215 (165-254) 
707 (500-876) </p>

<p>e,f </p>

<p>33 (29.5-37) </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>4 (4-7) 
Post-HFD 
6.9 (5.5-7.8) 
3.9 (3.6-4.3) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>192 (164-239) 
184 (146-315) 
33.5 (31-38) 
6 (4-8) 
Pre-LFD 
6.7 (5.7-7.8) 
3.7 (3.5-3.7) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>211 (171-271) 
651 (516-835) </p>

<p>g,h </p>

<p>33 (30-36) </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>5 (3-7) 
Post-LFD 
6.2 (5.4-8.1) 
3.9 (3.6-4.1) </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>212 (178-246) 
240 (141-322) 
33 (31-38) 
5 (3-7) </p>

<p>Values are given as median and interquartile range (25-75%). 
a P = 0.0006 compared with healthy controls; 
b P = 0.04 compared with healthy controls; 
c P = 0.0005 compared with healthy controls; 
d P = 0.026 compared with healthy controls; 
e P = 0.02 compared with post-HFD; 
f P = 0.00001 compared with healthy controls; 
g P = 0.04 
compared with post-LFD; 
h P = 0.00001 compared with healthy controls; 
i P = 0.03 compared with healthy controls; 
j P = 0.04 compared with 
healthy controls. 
CRP, C-reactive protein; HFD, high-flux dialysis; LFD, low-flux dialysis. </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Absolute number of basophils (cell/μL) in peripheral whole blood </p>

<p>Pre-HFD 
Post-HFD 
Pre-LFD 
Post-LFD 
Healthy </p>

<p>Number of basophils/μL blood 
16 (12-32) 
23 (12-31) 
25 (16-36) 
28(17-51) 
27 (15-39) </p>

<p>The absolute number of basophils (cells/μL) was calculated in peripheral blood before and after dialysis with high-flux and low-flux 
membranes. Values are given as median and interquartile range (25-75%). 
HFD, high-flux dialysis; LFD, low-flux dialysis. </p>

<p>CD63 expression in basophils stimulated 
by different concentrations of fMLP </p>

<p>R 
P M </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>5 
× 
1 0 </p>

<p>-5 M </p>

<p>5 
× 
1 0 </p>

<p>-6 M 
1 0 </p>

<p>-5 M 
1 0 </p>

<p>-6 M </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>CD63 (%) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>CD63 expression in basophils stimulated by 
different concentrations of anti-FceRI </p>

<p>R 
P M </p>

<p>I 
3 
µ g 
1 
µ g </p>

<p>0 . 3 3 </p>

<p>µ g </p>

<p>0 . 1 1 </p>

<p>µ g </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>CD63 (%) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Basophil activation responses to 
different concentrations of fMLP and 
anti-FcεRI antibody (dose-response curve). 
Scatter plots represent the range with whis-
kers and the median as the middle line. (a) 
The level of CD63 expression in basophils 
following activation by fMLP reached a 
plateau involving four different concentra-
tions. (b) The maximum expression of CD63 
in basophils following activation by anti-
FcεRI antibody was observed at a concen-
tration of 3 μg/mL and gradually decreased 
at lower concentrations of stimulator. </p>

<p>BASOPHIL ACTIVATION IN HEMODIALYSIS 
949 </p>

<p>Artif Organs, Vol. 38, No. 11, 2014 </p>

<p>CD63 expression in fMLP-activated basophils from 
patients was significantly higher compared with that 
in healthy controls (Fig. 3a). However, basophil acti-
vation following stimulation by anti-FcεRI antibody 
was not significantly different between the groups 
(Fig. 3b). </p>

<p>Difference in basophil activation response 
following hemodialysis with high-flux and low-flux 
dialyzer membranes 
The CD63 expression in fMLP-and anti-FcεRI 
antibody-activated basophils was analyzed before 
and after hemodialysis with each type of dialyzer 
membrane. 
Following stimulation with fMLP, we observed no 
significant differences in CD63 expression comparing 
predialysis samples with postdialysis samples in any 
type of dialyzer; however, there was increased cell 
surface expression of CD63 on basophils after dialy-
sis with the low-flux dialyzer compared with the high-
flux dialyzer (P = 0.01) (Fig. 4a). 
The results demonstrated that anti-FcεRI 
antibody-activated basophils expressed significantly 
higher levels of CD63 following hemodialysis with </p>

<p>the low-flux membrane (compared with before 
dialysis) (P = 0.002). This finding was in contrast 
with that of cells subjected to interaction during 
high-flux hemodialysis. Moreover, basophil activa-
tion response to anti-FcεRI antibody in low-flux 
membrane-treated cells was significantly higher than 
in high-flux membrane-treated cells (P = 0.002) as 
shown in Fig. 4b. </p>

<p>Flow cytometric analysis of surface expression of 
CD11b, active CD11b, and CD88 on neutrophils 
No significant differences were observed in terms 
of CD11b expression (MFI) on neutrophils before 
stimulation (baseline) when comparing dialysis 
patients with healthy controls and comparing high-
flux dialyzer with low-flux dialyzer (Fig. 5a). In order 
to evaluate whether the cells had been differently 
primed, cells were stimulated with IL-8, a major 
factor regulating the expression of CD11b (22). The 
surface expression of CD11b (MFI) was increased 
after stimulation with IL-8, but the expression was 
similar when comparing cells subjected to high flux 
with those subjected to low flux and cells from 
healthy controls (Fig. 5b). </p>

<p>CD63 expression in fMLP-
stimulated basophils </p>

<p>P r e -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P r e -L F D 
H 
e a l t h y </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>CD63 (%) </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>P r e -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P r e -L F D 
H 
e a l t h y </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>CD63 expression in anti-FcεRI-
stimulated basophils </p>

<p>CD63 (%) </p>

<p>P = 0.04 
P = 0.04 </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Basophil activation response to 
fMLP and anti-FcεRI antibody comparing 
patients with healthy controls. Scatter plots 
represent the range with whiskers and the 
median as the middle line. A P value &lt;0.05 
was considered significant. (a) CD63 
expression in fMLP-activated basophils 
was significantly different comparing the 
samples from patients before dialysis 
with high-flux dialyzer (HFD) with those of 
healthy controls. Basophils from patients 
before dialysis with low-flux dialyzer (LFD) 
also expressed different levels of CD63 
compared with healthy controls. (b) The acti-
vation of basophils by anti-FcεRI was not 
significantly different between the groups. </p>

<p>a 
b 
CD63 expression in fMLP-
stimulated basophils </p>

<p>CD63 expression in anti-FceRI-
stimulated basophils </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>CD63 (%) </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>CD63 (%) </p>

<p>P r e -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P o s t -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P r e -L F D 
P o s t -L F D 
P r e -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P o s t -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P r e -L F D 
P o s t -L F D </p>

<p>P = 0.01 </p>

<p>P = 0.002 </p>

<p>P = 0.002 </p>

<p>FIG. 4. CD63 expression in activated 
basophils following dialysis with low-flux 
and high-flux dialyzers. Scatter plots 
represent the range with whiskers and 
the median as the middle line. A P value 
&lt;0.05 was considered significant. (a) The 
basophil activation response following 
stimulation with fMLP was significantly dif-
ferent when comparing samples obtained 
after dialysis with the low-flux dialyzer 
(LFD) to those after dialysis with the high-
flux dialyzer (HFD). (b) Anti-FcεRI antibody-
activated basophils expressed higher 
levels of CD63 after dialysis with the LFD 
membrane compared with before dialysis 
and also compared with those that under-
went dialysis with the HFD. </p>

<p>Z. ALJADI ET AL. 
950 </p>

<p>Artif Organs, Vol. 38, No. 11, 2014 </p>

<p>There were no significant differences in active 
CD11b expression (percentage) on neutrophils 
before stimulation (baseline) comparing hemodi-
alysis patients with healthy controls or comparing the 
effects of high-flux and low-flux dialyzers (Fig. 6a). 
Furthermore, no significant differences were ob-
served in active CD11b expression (percentage) on 
neutrophils after stimulation with IL-8 comparing 
dialysis patients with healthy controls and comparing 
high-flux and low-flux dialyzers (Fig. 6b). 
There were no significant differences in the expres-
sion of CD88 on neutrophils after hemodialysis compar-
ing high-flux and low-flux dialyzers (data not shown). 
The data were similar to those in healthy controls. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the present study, we demonstrate for the first 
time that blood interaction with dialysis membranes 
impacts the responsiveness of basophils in patients 
on maintenance hemodialysis. Moreover, respon-
siveness of basophils differs according to whether 
low-or high-flux polysulfone membranes are used. 
Interestingly, no concomitant changes in neutrophil 
activation were noticed. 
Our data demonstrate that the basophil response 
to fMLP was higher in the dialysis patient group com-
pared with healthy individuals. However, anti-FcεRI 
stimulation response did not differ between the 
patients and healthy subjects. It is not known 
whether this difference in fMLP response is a conse-</p>

<p>quence of altered expression of fMLP receptors or a 
consequence of primed intracellular pathways. fMLP 
binds to receptors expressed on basophils, the formyl 
peptide receptor (FPR) and formyl peptide receptor-
like 1 (FPRL1), which activates intracellular signal-
ing pathways such as the MEK-ERK pathway and 
leads to chemotaxis and release of mediators such as 
leukotriene C4 and histamine (23,24). However, 
better understanding of the mechanisms involved in 
fMLP activation of basophils in dialysis patients will 
require further investigations. 
We also report a difference in FcεRI-mediated 
activation when basophils pass through a dialyzer. 
The basophil response was increased after pas-
sage through the low-flux polysulfone dialyzer but 
unchanged following passage through the high-flux 
membrane. Cross-linking of Fcε receptors on the 
basophil surface results in a stronger response than 
activation by fMLP. It has been shown that patients 
undergoing hemodialysis may develop anaphylactic 
or anaphylactoid reactions. The underlying mecha-
nism involved in hemodialysis-associated anaphylac-
tic reactions may be related to activation of basophils 
through cross-linking of FcεRI on the surface of 
basophils and rapid release of histamine and heparin 
and a delayed release of IL-4 (18). IL-4 is regarded as 
a key mediator in the tuning of the T-cell differentia-
tion, favoring a Th2 response (25,26). The question 
we addressed in the present study was whether the 
differences in pore size and ultrafiltration coefficient </p>

<p>50 
150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 
30 
20 
10 
0 </p>

<p>MFI </p>

<p>P r e -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P o s t -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P r e -L F D 
P o s t -L F D </p>

<p>H 
e a l t h y 
P r e -H 
F D P o s t -H 
F D </p>

<p>P r e -L F D P o s t -L F D 
H 
e a l t h y </p>

<p>Total CD11b expression 
in unstimulated granulocytes </p>

<p>Total CD11b expression 
in IL-8-stimulated granulocytes 
a 
b 
FIG. 5. Total CD11b expression on the 
surface of neutrophils before (baseline) and 
after stimulation with IL-8. Scatter plots rep-
resent the range with whiskers and the 
median as the middle line. P &lt; 0.05 was 
considered significant. (a) Total CD11b 
expression on neutrophils before stimula-
tion with IL-8. (b) Total CD11b expression on 
neutrophils after stimulation with IL-8. There 
were no significant differences between the 
groups. </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 
80 
60 
40 
20 
0 </p>

<p>P r e -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P o s t -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P r e -L F D 
P o s t -L F D </p>

<p>H 
e a l t h y 
P r e -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P o s t -H </p>

<p>F D </p>

<p>P r e -L F D 
P o s t -L F D </p>

<p>H 
e a l t h y </p>

<p>Active CD11b expression 
in unstimulated granulocytes </p>

<p>Active CD11b expression 
in IL-8-stimulated granulocytes 
a 
b 
FIG. 6. CD11b active epitope expression 
on the surface of neutrophils before (base-
line) and after stimulation with IL-8. Scatter 
plots represent the range with whiskers 
and the median as the middle line. A P 
value &lt;0.05 was considered significant. (a) 
Active CD11b expression in neutrophils 
before stimulation with IL-8. (b) Active 
CD11b expression in neutrophils after stimu-
lation with IL-8. There were no significant 
differences between the groups. </p>

<p>BASOPHIL ACTIVATION IN HEMODIALYSIS 
951 </p>

<p>Artif Organs, Vol. 38, No. 11, 2014 </p>

<p>in high-and low-flux polysulfone membranes have an 
impact on cell activation, as the clinical use of high-
flux dialyzers has been suggested to reduce cardiovas-
cular mortality and improve survival (13,14), even 
though there is an ongoing debate regarding the supe-
riority of high-flux dialyzers over low-flux ones (27). 
As high-flux dialyzers are more efficient in removing 
immune modulators generated during the dialysis 
procedure, this is in line with our finding of increased 
basophil activation after low-flux hemodialysis. 
Previous studies have demonstrated that the 
hemodialysis procedure may lead to neutropenia, 
monocytopenia, and thrombocytopenia (28-30). 
Therefore, we analyzed the absolute number of 
basophils and did not detect any significant effects on 
cell number following passage through the different 
dialyzers. This implies that the variation in the 
basophil response was due to functional changes and 
not a consequence of entrapment of low-responding 
cells in the dialyzer. 
The state of neutrophil activation has previously 
been shown to be a sensitive marker of biocompatibil-
ity in hemodialysis. For example, during neutrophil 
adhesion and transendothelial migration, there is 
a rapid translocation of CD11b (a member of the 
integrin family) from an intracellular pool to the 
cell surface, followed by receptor aggregation and 
conformational change in the active epitope (31). It is 
well established that different dialyzer surfaces 
impact the function of neutrophils. It has been 
reported that CD11b expression on neutrophils 
increases at the beginning of hemodialysis with 
several types of dialyzers but declines to basal level at 
the end of the procedure with biocompatible dialyzers 
such as polysulfone membranes, while it remains high 
after dialysis with bioincompatible membranes 
(32,33). In the present study, we investigated both the 
surface expression of CD11b and the expression of the 
active epitope on neutrophils but found no significant 
differences in the expression of either marker after 
one session of hemodialysis between the low-flux 
membrane and the high-flux polysulfone membrane. 
It has been shown that the hemodialysis procedure 
activates several hemostatic pathways such as gen-
eration of C3a and C5a (anaphylatoxins) (34), but it 
has also been reported that neither C5a levels in 
plasma nor C5a levels in the dialysate compartment 
increase after dialysis with high-flux and/or low-flux 
polysulfone dialyzers (35). As the molecular weight 
of C5a is similar to that of β2-microglobulin, this 
anaphylatoxin can be cleared by high-flux mem-
branes due to a different kinetic gradient. We there-
fore investigated the expression of C5a receptor type 
1 (CD88) on neutrophils as a cellular marker for </p>

<p>complement activation. Following interaction with 
the ligand C5a, the receptors internalize within 
minutes to induce responses such as chemotaxis of 
neutrophils with up-regulation of CD11b, granule 
enzyme release, superoxide anion production, and 
platelet-neutrophil microaggregation (36). In a pre-
vious study, a high-flux dialysis membrane induced a 
decrease in C5a receptor expression on neutrophils 
in three out of four patients, but internalized C5aR 
expression showed a nonsignificant change (37). We 
did not find any significant differences in CD88 
expression on neutrophils from patients undergoing 
high-flux hemodialysis compared with low-flux dialy-
sis, which could be due to the difference in number of 
study subjects or insensitivity of this molecule for 
assessment of bioincompatibility. 
The hemodialysis procedure induces secretion of 
several inflammatory mediators besides anaphyla-
toxins that can impact basophil function, such as IL-1β 
and tumor necrosis factor α, from activated mono-
cytes. Of interest is that earlier studies reported a 
correlation between the cytokine IL-1 and the induc-
tion of histamine release from basophils (38). 
Bradykinin generation has been reported to be 
increased during hemodialysis with polysulfone 
membranes, which can be explained by the fact that 
the membrane surface carries negatively charged 
groups, which may activate the Hageman factor 
(coagulation factor XII), known to convert prekal-
likrein to kallikrein, which will generate bradykinin 
from high-molecular-weight kininogen (39,40). The 
bradykinin can trigger the IgE-independent activa-
tion of basophils to induce an anaphylactoid reaction 
during hemodialysis (18). Interestingly, we have also 
recently shown that the level of eotaxin, a potent 
chemoattractant to basophils (acting through CCR3 
receptors), was increased in patients with CKD (41). </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>This study demonstrates that the responsiveness of 
basophils to anti-FcεRI stimulation is affected when 
the cells pass through a dialyzer. These changes differ 
between high-flux and low-flux polysulfone dialyzers 
in patients with chronic kidney disease. Moreover, 
we also report an increased responsiveness to fMLP 
in patients on hemodialysis compared with healthy 
controls. Together, these data demonstrate that 
basophil activation may be a new and more sensitive 
marker for evaluating biocompatibility properties of 
dialyzers. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: This study was supported 
by grants from Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, </p>

<p>Z. ALJADI ET AL. 
952 </p>

<p>Artif Organs, Vol. 38, No. 11, 2014 </p>

<p>Sweden; Hesselman Foundation; and Amgen. We 
would like to thank Anette Bygdén-Nylander and 
Sofia Geschwind for excellent technical assistance. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: None. </p>



<p>BASOPHIL ACTIVATION IN HEMODIALYSIS </p>

<p>
Artif Organs, Vol. 38, No. 11, 2014 </p>

</text></tei>