<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4958110" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>a b s t r a c t </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to determine whether the use of a periarticular injection using liposomal 
bupivacaine could decrease pain and improve outcomes after total knee arthroplasty. Fifty consecutive 
patients received no periarticular injections (group A). Another 50 consecutive patients received a per-
iarticular injection of liposomal bupivacaine (group B). There were no differences in the groups with 
respect to gender, age, body mass index (BMI), or comorbidities. There was a significant reduction in the 
amount of narcotics used in the liposomal bupivacaine group (60.97-mg oral morphine equivalent vs 
89.74 mg, P ¼ 0.009). Patients in group B with a BMI &lt;40 and a Charlson comorbidity index of 0-3 had 
decreased length of stay (2.64 vs 3.06 days, P ¼ .004), narcotic use over 24-48 hours (110.66 vs 182.47 mg, 
P ¼ .013), and narcotic use over 48-72 hours (49.61 vs. 112.65 mg, P ¼ .004). In patients with a BMI &lt;40 
and comorbidity index of 3, periarticular injection using liposomal bupivacaine leads to earlier 
discharge along with decreased use of narcotics. 
Arthroplasty Today </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / w w w . a r t h r o p l a s t y t o d a y . o r g / </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.artd.2015.09.001 
2352-3441/Copyright © 2015 Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of American Association of Hip and Knee Surgeons. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND 
license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Arthroplasty Today 1 (2015) 117e120 </p>

<p>Material and methods </p>

<p>Fifty consecutive patients who underwent primary TKA and 
received an intraoperative PAI using liposomal bupivacaine be-
tween April 2013 and August 2013 were retrospectively reviewed. 
A separate cohort of fifty consecutive patients who underwent 
primary TKA without PAI between June 2012 and August 2012 were 
retrospectively included as a control group. All procedures were 
performed by a single surgeon. This study was approved by our 
institutional review board and was Health Insurance Portability 
and Accountability Act compliant. 
All patients received a single-shot femoral and sciatic nerve 
block performed by the anesthesia staff, and all patients received 
intravenous sedation unless general anesthesia was required for 
better airway control. A subvastus approach was the primary mode 
of exposure in both groups unless there was a contraindication. All 
cases were performed using a Stryker Triathlon TKA implant 
(Stryker, Mahwah, NJ). In the study group, the intraoperative PAI 
was performed after all components were implanted; the wound 
was irrigated with a dilute Betadine (Purdue Products LT, Stanford, 
CT 06901) irrigation and was then washed with normal saline from 
a pulse irrigator. The PAI was administered according to the lipo-
somal bupivacaine manufacturer's instructions. The PAI consisted 
of 20 mL of 1.3% liposomal bupivacaine (1 vial; 266 mg) diluted 
with 40-mL normal saline to create a total injection volume of 60 
mL. The control group did not receive any type of intraoperative 
PAI. 
The postoperative pain control regimen was the same for both 
groups and included the use of oral acetaminophen, celecoxib, 
tramadol, patient-controlled analgesia, and oral narcotics. Patient-
controlled analgesia was administered using morphine, unless 
contraindicated, at which point hydromorphone was substituted. 
All postoperative pain medications administered were tabulated 
and converted to a total oral morphine equivalent (mg) for use in 
the comparison of the two groups (Table 1) [7]. </p>

<p>A standardized physical therapy protocol was initiated for each 
group on postoperative day 1. The physical therapy regimen con-
sisted of 2 hours of continuous passive motion machine twice daily, 
assisted standing, and assisted walking. All patients were dis-
charged when deemed medically stable, their pain was under 
control, and the physical therapy goals were met. 
Standard statistical Student's t tests were used to evaluate the 
mean outcome of continuous variables between groups, and chi-
square tests were used to evaluate categorical variables. Dedi-
cated statistical software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">22</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL) was used 
to perform the data analysis. The two groups were compared on the 
basis of length of hospital stay; amount of narcotic pain medication 
used over the first 24, 48, and 72 hours; and the distance walked on 
postoperative days 1, 2, and 3. Statistically significant difference 
was considered at P .05 between groups. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Fifty consecutive patients were identified in the study group, 
consisting of 34 female and 16 male patients, with an average age 
of 64 (range: 46-88) years and an average BMI of 35 (range: 21-58). 
This was compared to the control group of 50 consecutive patients, 
consisting of 32 female and 18 male patients, with an average age 
of 64 (range: 38-85) years and an average BMI of 35 (range: 20-63). 
The average Charlson comorbidity index (CCI) for the study group 
was 3.34 (range: 2-6), and for the control group, it was 3.58 
(range: 0-8). There were no statistically significant differences 
between the groups with respect to gender, age, BMI, comorbid-
ities, or surgical approach. The cohort characteristics are outlined 
in Table 2. 
There was a statistically significant reduction in the amount of 
narcotics used over the 48-72-hour postoperative period in the 
liposomal bupivacaine group (60.97-mg oral morphine equivalent 
vs 89.74 mg, P ¼ .009). There was no statistical difference between 
the two groups with respect to length of hospital stay, amount of 
narcotics used from 0-24 hours and 24-48 hours, or the post-
operative walking distance (Table 3). </p>

<p>Table 1 
Equianalgesic conversion. </p>

<p>Drug 
Administration Dose 
(mg) </p>

<p>Conversion 
factor </p>

<p>PO morphine 
equivalent dose 
(mg) </p>

<p>Morphine 
PO 
10 
1 
10 
IV 
10 
3 
30 
Hydromorphone PO 
10 
4 
40 
IV 
10 
20 
200 
Hydrocodone 
PO 
10 
1 
10 
Oxycodone 
PO 
10 
1.5 
15 
Tramadol 
PO 
10 
0.25 
2.5 </p>

<p>PO, oral; IV, intravenous. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Cohort characteristics. </p>

<p>Demographics 
Liposomal 
bupivacaine PAI </p>

<p>No PAI 
Chi square 
df 
P value </p>

<p>Male 
16 
18 
0.18 
1 
0.67 
Female 
34 
32 
P value </p>

<p>Age 
64 (46-88) 
64 (38-85) 
0.837 
BMI 
35 (21-58) 
35 (20-63) 
0.93 
CCI 
3.34 (2-6) 
3.58 (0-8) 
0.366 
Chi square 
df 
P value </p>

<p>Subvastus 
33 
39 
1.79 
1 
0.18 
Parapatellar 
17 
11 </p>

<p>df, degrees of freedom; PAI, periarticular injection. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Outcomes in all patients. </p>

<p>Outcome &amp; Narcotic Usage 
Liposomal 
bupivacaine PAI </p>

<p>No PAI 
P value </p>

<p>Length of stay (d) 
2.94 
3.26 
0.092 
Narcotic use 0-24 h (mg) 
119.04 
111.58 
0.608 
Narcotic use 24-48 h (mg) 
114.74 
132.18 
0.217 
Narcotic use 48-72 h (mg) 
60.97 
89.74 
0.009 
Walking distance POD 1 (ft) 
61.32 
44.5 
0.067 
Walking distance POD 2 (ft) 
97.15 
81.42 
0.229 
Walking distance POD 3 (ft) 
101.93 
123.07 
0.246 </p>

<p>POD, postoperative day; PAI, periarticular injection. </p>

<p>Table 4 
Outcomes in patients with BMI &lt;40, CCI 0-3. </p>

<p>Outcome &amp; narcotic usage 
Liposomal 
bupivacaine PAI </p>

<p>No PAI 
P value </p>

<p>Length of stay (d) 
2.64 
3.06 
0.004 
Narcotic use 0-24 h (mg) 
117.61 
145.53 
0.298 
Narcotic use 24-48 h (mg) 
110.66 
182.47 
0.013 
Narcotic use 48-72 h (mg) 
49.61 
112.65 
0.004 
Walking distance POD 1 (ft) 
73.29 
59.07 
0.456 
Walking distance POD 2 (ft) 
114.77 
84.82 
0.193 
Walking distance POD 3 (ft) 
137.27 
119.38 
0.545 </p>

<p>POD, postoperative day; PAI, periarticular injection; BMI, body mass index; CCI, 
Charlson comorbidity index. </p>

<p>B.T. Webb et al. / Arthroplasty Today 1 (2015) 117e120 </p>

<p>
When a subset analysis was performed, the patients from the 
study group with a BMI &lt;40 and a CCI of 0-3 were found to have a 
statistically significant difference with respect to length of stay 
(2.64 vs 3.06 days, P ¼ .004), narcotic use over 24-48 hours (110.66 
vs 182.47 mg, P ¼ .013), and narcotic use over 48-72 hours (49.61 vs 
112.65 mg, P ¼ .004). There was a trend toward increased walking 
distance on postoperative day 2 (114.77 vs 84.82 ft, P ¼ .193), but 
this was not statistically significant with the numbers available for 
study (Table 4). All other subsets reviewed did not show any sta-
tistically significant differences between the two groups with the 
numbers available for review (Tables 5-7). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Periarticular injections after TKA have been widely used to 
alleviate postoperative pain to improve patient satisfaction and 
outcomes [8,9]. Many groups have used these injections as part of 
their multimodal pain control management plan after TKA. The use 
of liposomal bupivacaine as a PAI is a novel technique that can 
provide long-acting postoperative pain relief [10,11]. 
This retrospective study was undertaken to determine whether 
the addition of a PAI using liposomal bupivacaine compared to no 
PAI would enhance the postoperative pain relief of patients un-
dergoing TKA. Based on our study, the use of a liposomal bupiva-
caine PAI led to a decrease in narcotic use in the immediate 
postoperative period in patients undergoing primary TKA. Patients 
receiving liposomal bupivacaine were able to be discharged from 
the hospital sooner and had a trend toward increased walking 
distance earlier in their postoperative course. The greatest benefit 
was seen for the healthier (CCI, 3) and nonmorbidly obese pa-
tients (BMI, &lt;40). No statistically significant difference in length of 
stay, narcotic use, or walking distance was noted when comparing 
morbidly obese (BMI, &gt;40) patients and those with multiple 
comorbidities (CCI, &gt;3). Patients most likely to benefit from the 
addition of a PAI using liposomal bupivacaine in this study were 
those with a BMI &lt;40 and a CCI 3. 
There are limitations to this study, but despite being a retro-
spective review, this study was performed at a single institution </p>

<p>using consecutive patients, without variation in surgical technique, 
anesthesia, or the postoperative protocol. The study cohort and 
control groups both consisted of a consecutive series of patients 
that underwent primary TKA during a similar time period of the 
year to best eliminate selection bias. There are several questions 
that arise from the results of this study, which need further 
exploration. There is an added cost to each case using liposomal 
bupivacaine as a PAI. In a study by Bagsby et al [12], they 
concluded that liposomal bupivacaine PAIs provided inferior pain 
control compared to the less-expensive traditional PAI using short-
acting bupivacaine. However, this was also a retrospective study 
with two different surgeons, and the authors acknowledge that the 
results may be technique dependent. It is also important to note 
that this study compared PAI using liposomal bupivacaine versus 
short-acting bupivacaine, in comparison to our study, which 
compared liposomal bupivacaine to no PAI in the control group. A 
prospective, randomized study by Schroer et al [13] that 
comparing liposomal bupivacaine to standard bupivacaine did not 
show any significant benefit between the two periarticular in-
jections in patients undergoing primary TKA. Long-acting pain 
relief with the use of PAIs appears to be an important part of a 
multimodal pain regimen that allows for earlier discharge and 
improved outcomes. There is increasing evidence that short-stay 
and outpatient TKA is feasible in the near future [14]. Long-
acting pain relief through the use of PAI may allow for this to 
become a possibility. We demonstrated that healthier patients and 
those with a BMI &lt;40 had a shorter hospital stay and used fewer 
narcotics with the use of liposomal bupivacaine. Patients who are 
morbidly obese and with multiple medical problems may have 
difficulty in earlier return to function because of their inherent 
comorbid conditions despite the use of PAIs. In addition, it is not 
clear whether there are any differences in absorption and release 
of these PAIs in the morbidly obese patients because of the excess 
adipose tissue. Additional studies are required to demonstrate the 
true benefits of liposomal bupivacaine with respect to cost effec-
tiveness compared to a hospital pharmacyeprepared PAI, actual 
duration of pain relief, and its role in outpatient or short-stay 
hospitalization after TKA. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Periarticular TKA injection using liposomal bupivacaine in pa-
tients with a BMI of less than 40 kg/m2 and a comorbidity index of 
less than or equal to 3 leads to earlier hospital discharge and 
decreased narcotic usage. </p>



<p>Table 5 
Outcomes in patients with BMI &lt;40, CCI &gt;3. </p>

<p>Outcome &amp; narcotic usage 
Liposomal 
bupivacaine PAI </p>

<p>No PAI 
P value </p>

<p>Length of stay (d) 
3.07 
3.55 
0.252 
Narcotic use 0-24 h (mg) 
109.8 
87.5 
0.283 
Narcotic use 24-48 h (mg) 
108.93 
92.23 
0.228 
Narcotic use 48-72 h (mg) 
75.38 
68.57 
0.716 
Walking distance POD 1 (ft) 
61.43 
40.95 
0.08 
Walking distance POD 2 (ft) 
81.64 
78.23 
0.828 
Walking distance POD 3 (ft) 
82 
122.1 
0.176 </p>

<p>POD, postoperative day; PAI, periarticular injection; BMI, body mass index; CCI, 
Charlson comorbidity index. </p>

<p>Table 6 
Outcomes in patients with BMI &gt;40, CCI 0-3. </p>

<p>Outcome &amp; narcotic usage 
Liposomal 
bupivacaine PAI </p>

<p>No PAI 
P value </p>

<p>Length of stay (d) 
3 
3 
1 
Narcotic use 0-24 h (mg) 
156.5 
99.63 
0.106 
Narcotic use 24-48 h (mg) 
155.39 
126.75 
0.38 
Narcotic use 48-72 h (mg) 
80 
83.43 
0.867 
Walking distance POD 1 (ft) 
45.56 
31.43 
0.482 
Walking distance POD 2 (ft) 
94.38 
109.38 
0.738 
Walking distance POD 3 (ft) 
96.67 
156.67 
0.214 </p>

<p>POD, postoperative day; PAI, periarticular injection; BMI, body mass index; CCI, 
Charlson comorbidity index. </p>

<p>Table 7 
Outcomes in patients with BMI &gt;40, CCI &gt; 3. </p>

<p>Outcome &amp; narcotic usage 
Liposomal 
bupivacaine PAI </p>

<p>No PAI 
P value </p>

<p>Length of stay (d) 
4 
3 
0.391 
Narcotic use 0-24 h (mg) 
77.25 
119.67 
0.618 
Narcotic use 24-48 h (mg) 
67.5 
154.67 
0.254 
Narcotic use 48-72 h (mg) 
30 
125 
0.237 
Walking distance POD 1 (ft) 
24.33 
3 
0.472 
Walking distance POD 2 (ft) 
47.67 
11 
0.28 </p>

<p>POD, postoperative day; PAI, periarticular injection; BMI, body mass index; 
CCI, Charlson comorbidity index. </p>

<p>B.T. Webb et al. / Arthroplasty Today 1 (2015) 117e120 </p>



<p>
B.T. Webb et al. / Arthroplasty Today 1 (2015) 117e120 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>