<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4853038" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The placental syncytiotrophoblast, which is formed by the fusion of cytotrophoblast cells, is 
indispensable for the establishment and maintenance of normal pregnancy. The human 
endogenous retrovirus envelope glycoprotein syncytin-2 is the most important player in mediating 
trophoblast cell-cell fusion as a fusogen. We constructed expression plasmids of wild-type and 21 
single-amino-acid substitution mutants of syncytin-2, including 10 N-glycosylation sites individually 
silenced by mutagenizing N to Q, 1 naturally occurring single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) 
N118S that introduced an N-glycosylation site, and another 10 non-synonymous SNPs located 
within important functional domains. We observed that syncytin-2 was highly fusogenic and that 
the mutants had different capacities in merging 293T cells. Of the 21 mutants, N133Q, N312Q, 
N443Q, C46R (in the CXXC motif) and R417H (in the heptad repeat region and immunosuppressive 
domain) lost their fusogenicity, whereas N332Q, N118S, T367M (in the fusion peptide), V483I (in the 
transmembrane domain) and T522M (in the cytoplasmic domain) enhanced the fusogenic activity. 
We also proved that N133, and N443 were all 
glycosylated in 293T cells. A co-immunoprecipitation assay showed compromised interaction 
between mutants N443Q, C46R, T367M, R417H and the receptor MFSD2A, whereas N118S was 
associated with more receptors. We also sequenced the coding sequence of syncytin-2 in 125 
severe pre-eclamptic patients and 272 normal pregnant Chinese women. Surprisingly, only 1 non-
synonymous SNP T522M was found and the frequencies of heterozygous carriers were not 
significantly different. Taken together, our results suggest that N-glycans at residues 133, 312, 332 
and 443 of syncytin-2 are required for optimal fusion induction, and that SNPs C46R, N118S, T367M, 
R417H, V483I and T522M can alter the fusogenic function of syncytin-2. </p>

<p>The human placenta is a transient organ of embryonic 
origin whose main function involves the exchange of 
metabolic and gaseous products between the fetal and 
maternal circulation. It also acts as an important endo-
crine secretion organ for normal pregnancy and a barrier 
between the fetus and its mother for immune tolerance, 
ensuring the preservation of the fetus. The major constit-
uent of human placental tissue is the trophoblast, which 
stems from the trophectoderm of the blastocyst and </p>

<p>develops before any embryonic tissue arises. Villous 
cytotrophoblast cells (CTBs) have 2 distinct ways of dif-
ferentiation: to form highly invasive extravillous tropho-
blast cells or to fuse and form a multinucleated 
syncytiotrophoblast (STB) layer, a process designated 
syncytialization. The STB comes into direct contact with 
maternal blood, secreting important hormones to main-
tain pregnancy and mediating gas, nutrient and waste 
exchange. Inadequate syncytialization is correlated with </p>

<p>CONTACT Hongmei Wang 
wanghm@ioz.ac.cn; Hai-Yan Lin 
linhy@ioz.ac.cn 
Color versions of one or more of the figures in this article can be found online at www.tandfonline.com/kcam. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>These authors contributed equally to this work. 
Supplemental data for this article can be accessed on the publisher's website. 
© 2016 Lina Cui, Huiying Wang, Xiaoyin Lu, Rui Wang, Ru Zheng, Yue Li, Xiaokui Yang, Wen-Tong Jia, Yangyu Zhao, Yongqing Wang, Haibin Wang, Yan-Ling 
Wang, Cheng Zhu, Hai-Yan Lin, and Hongmei Wang. Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The moral 
rights of the named author(s) have been asserted. </p>

<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION 
2016, VOL. 10, NOS. 1-2, 39-55 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/19336918.2015.1093720 </p>

<p>severe pregnancy disorders such as pre-eclampsia (PE), 
which is a leading cause of maternal and fetal mortality. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Our understanding of the mechanisms underlying 
syncytialization in the placenta came from the identifica-
tion of the human endogenous retrovirus (HERV) enve-
lope proteins, syncytins, which are fusogens specifically 
expressed in the placenta. 
2-6 HERVs are remnants of 
infections of former exogenous retroviruses, occupying 
at least 8% of the human genome at various stages of 
"fossilization." 
7 The 2 bona fide envelope glycoproteins, 
syncytin-1 and syncytin-2, are encoded by HERV-W 
(the official name is ERVW-1) and HERV-FRD (official 
name ERVFRD-1), and the retroviruses carrying them 
entered the primate lineage 25 and 40 million years ago, 
respectively. 
4,8,9 Indeed, these 2 HERV envelope genes 
have undergone purifying selection during primate evo-
lution to play important functions in placental physiol-
ogy. 
10,11 The existence of 2 murine endogenous 
retroviral envelope genes (syncytin-A and -B), homolo-
gous but not orthologous to the human syncytin genes 
and also critical for trophoblast cell fusion, have been 
reported. 
12 The syncytin-A-deficient mouse placenta 
shows specific disruption of the architecture of the syn-
cytiotrophoblast layer I (ST-I). 
13 The syncytin-B null pla-
centa 
exhibits 
impaired 
formation 
of 
the 
syncytiotrophoblast layer II (ST-II). 
14 Furthermore, syn-
cytin genes with fusogenic activity and placenta-specific 
expression have been identified successively in the lepor-
idae, carnivora, ruminant, tenrecidae, rodentia squirrel-
related clade and marsupial opossum, namely syncytin-
Ory1, 
15 syncytin-Car1, 
16 syncytin-Rum1, 
17 syncytin-
Ten1, 
18 syncytin-Mar1 
19 and syncytin-Opo1, 
20 respec-
tively. This indicates that different syncytins have been 
acquired by different genomes and facilitate trophoblast 
cell-cell fusion in various animals. 
Syncytin-1 has been visualized in almost all types of 
trophoblastic cells, including villous and extravillous tro-
phoblast. 
3,5,6,21-24 Syncytin-1-induced cell-cell fusion is 
dependent on both ASCT1 and ASCT2 (alanine/serine/ 
cysteine/threonine transporter type 1 and 2), also called 
SLC1A4 and SLC1A5, respectively, which are Na 
C -
dependent transporters for polar neutral amino acids 
and a common cell surface receptor for retroviruses. </p>

<p>6,25-</p>

<p>27 Systematic ASC activity is present in basal but not in 
apical membranes of the STB, 
28,29 and ASCT2 appears to 
be ubiquitously expressed in most human placental tis-
sues, including the CTBs and STB. 
28,30-32 By contrast, the 
expression of syncytin-2 is restricted to some of the 
CTBs throughout pregnancy, and more often at the 
interface between the CTBs and STB. 
33 The receptor for 
syncytin-2, major facilitator superfamily domain con-
taining 2A (MFSD2A), is a carbohydrate transporter 
with 10-12 transmembrane domains and is specifically </p>

<p>expressed in the STB layer. 
34 The highly specific localiza-
tion of syncytin-2 and its receptor MFSD2A might argue 
for a major role of syncytin-2 in synergy with syncytin-1 
during the fusion of the mononucleated CTBs into the 
multinucleated STB in vivo, therefore favoring the 
growth and renewal of the STB and precluding the fusion 
of CTBs between themselves. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>The 1,617 bp sequence of the syncytin-2 envelope 
(env) gene mapped at 6p24.1 is within the HERV-FRD 
locus and encodes a~73 kDa glycosylated precursor pro-
tein. 
4,33,35,36 Similar to a retroviral envelope protein, syn-
cytin-2 is formed as a homotrimer connected by an 
intersubunit disulfide bond after posttranslational cleav-
age into the surface (SU) and transmembrane (TM) sub-
units by proteolytic furin, with the SU interacting with 
its receptor on the cell surface and the TM carrying the 
fusion activity and serving to mediate membrane 
fusion. 
36,37 The proper association of SU and TM subu-
nits is necessary for the functional integrity of syncytin-1 
and -2 because the chimeras of syncytin-1 and -2 swap-
ping their subunits lose their fusogenicities. 
36 As shown 
in Fig. 1A, the syncytin-2 precursor polypeptide contains 
the following important regions: (a) a signal peptide (SP) 
in the amino-terminal end (1-15 aa); (b) a disulfide bond 
isomerase motif (43-46 aa), Cys-X-X-Cys (CXXC); (c) a 
furin cleavage site (347-350 aa), RVRR, which separates 
the surface (SU) (16-350 aa) and transmembrane (TM) 
subunits (351-538 aa); (d) a conserved hydrophobic 
domain as a putative fusion peptide (FP) (354-374 aa) 
mediating the fusion of cell membranes; (e) a highly con-
served putative immunosuppressive domain (ISD) (414-
430 aa); (f) a CX6CC motif (431-439 aa), in which the 
first 2 cysteines can form an intersubunit disulfide bond 
and the third cysteine can form a intrasubunit disulfide 
bridge with the CXXC motif; (g) 2 heptad repeat regions 
(HR1 and HR2) (384-422 aa and 447-456 aa); (h) a 
transmembrane domain (TMD) (479-499 aa); and (i) a 
39-amino-acid cytoplasmic domain (CTM) (500-538 
aa). 
36,38-40 Functional domain integrality and proper 
maturation conformation are required for the fusogenic 
activity of syncytin-2. 
In the field of cell-cell fusion, interest in syncytins is 
emerging. Besides syncytins, only one another unrelated 
family of fusogens has been discovered, the F proteins in 
Caenorhabditis elegans. 
41 To date, critical functional char-
acterization of single-amino-acid mutations of syncytins 
and their relevance to diseases are still lacking. In the pres-
ent study, we investigated whether disruption of potential 
N-glycosylation sites and naturally occurring non-synony-
mous single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) (http:// 
www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/snp) in functional domains affected 
the fusogenicity of syncytin-2, and whether naturally occur-
ring SNPs that affected the fusogenic function of syncytin-2 </p>

<p> 
L. CUI ET AL. </p>

<p>were associated with pregnancy-related complications such 
as PE. We approached these issues by generating 21 site-
specific mutants, including 10 potential N-glycosylation site 
mutants and 11 naturally occurring SNPs, and assessed 
their fusogenic activities in 293T and HeLa cells, which do </p>

<p>not express syncytin-2 and serve as models for the cell-cell 
fusion assay. To define the receptor and other molecules 
interacting with syncytin-2, co-immunoprecipitation and 
protein mass spectrum analysis were utilized. Our results 
indicate that N-glycan and naturally occurring individual </p>

<p>Figure 1. Schematic of the syncytin-2 gene structure indicating the location of candidate N-glycosylation sites and non-synonymous sin-
gle-nucleotide polymorphic (SNP) sites and the establishment of the fusion assay for functional evaluation of syncytin-2 and its mutants. 
(A) Upper panel: structure of a human endogenous retrovirus (HERV)-FRD gene locus and its encoded envelope protein syncytin-2. </p>

<p>4,9 </p>

<p>HERV is typically composed of 5 
0 and 3 
0 LTRs (long terminal repeats), gag (group-specific antigen gene), pol (polymerase), and env (enve-
lope). Syncytin-2 encoded by the env gene is composed of SU and TM subunits. Lower panel: schematic diagram of syncytin-2 indicating 
the positions of 10 potential N-glycosylation sites (numbered 1-10) and 10 naturally occurring SNPs from SNP databases (http://www. 
ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/snp) in predicted functional domains (numbered 11-21). The positions of amino acids of different domains/motifs are 
indicated. SU, surface protein; TM, transmembrane protein; SP, signal peptide; FP, fusion peptide; HR, heptad repeat region; ISD, immu-
nosuppressive domain; TMD, transmembrane domain. CTM, cytoplasmic domain. (B) Establishment of 293T and HeLa cell lines that sta-
bly express EmGFP. (C) Cell-cell fusion mediated by exogenous syncytin-2. The 293T-EmGFP cells were transfected with phCMV empty 
vector or phCMV-syncytin-2 for 36 h. HeLa-EmGFP cells were co-transfected with phCMV-syncytin-2 and pcDNA3.1-MFSD2A-FLAG for 
36 h. Single-plasmid transfection with either phCMV-syncytin-2 or pcDNA3.1-MFSD2A-FLAG did not cause cell-cell fusion. All experi-
ments were repeated 3 times. Bars = 100 mm. </p>

<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION </p>

<p>
SNPs have different implications in regulating syncytin-2 
function and provide a better understanding of the struc-
ture-function relationship of syncytin-2. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Searching for single mutation sites that might affect 
the fusogenicity of syncytin-2 and the establishment 
of a syncytin-2-mediated fusion assay in 293T and 
HeLa cells </p>

<p>We first analyzed the putative N-glycosylation sites of 
syncytin-2 using the tool provided by the UniProt data-
base. In total, there are 10 potential N-glycosylation sites, 
with the first 8 located in the SU and the last 2 located in 
the TM (Fig. 1A, numbered as 1-10). We also searched 
the SNP database and found that 162 naturally occurring 
non-synonymous SNPs in the open reading frame 
(ORF) of syncytin-2 had been recorded. We selected 10 
sites that were located within important functional 
domains or motifs. Of these, N118S probably introduced 
a new N-glycosylation site, C46R was located in the 
CXXC domain, A359T and T367M were located in the 
FP, R417H was located in the HR1 and ISD domains, 
L432V was located in the CX6CC motif, V483I was 
located in the TMD, and L503F, I518V, T522M and 
S536L were located in the CTM (Fig. 1A, numbered as 
11-21). To characterize the effects of these N-glycosyla-
tion sites and non-synonymous SNPs on the fusogenic 
function of syncytin-2, we established a fusion assay 
using 293T-EmGFP and HeLa-EmGFP cell lines that sta-
bly overexpress green fluorescent protein (Fig. 1B) to 
monitor cell-cell fusion. The syncytin-2 receptor, </p>

<p>MFSD2A, is expressed in 293T cells. 
4 Therefore, syncy-
tin-2-mediated cell-cell fusion could be observed 24 h 
after transfection with a syncytin-2 expression plasmid. 
As fusion proceeded, patches of green fluorescence were 
seen as the formation of multinucleated syncytia 
(Fig. 1C). Moreover, as HeLa cells do not express 
MFSD2A, 
34 syncytin-2 mediated cell-cell fusion only 
occurred when co-transfecting syncytin-2 and MFSD2A 
overexpression plasmids, but not either plasmid alone 
(Fig. 1C). </p>

<p>Production and analysis of the effects of 21 single-
amino-acid-substitution mutants that either disrupt 
N-glycosylation sites or are encoded by naturally 
occurring non-synonymous SNPs on the fusogenicity 
of syncytin-2 </p>

<p>We first explored the requirement of each N-glycosyla-
tion site for the fusogenic function of recombinant syn-
cytin-2 by N to Q substitution at N133, N146, N177, 
N220, N241, N247, N312, N332, N443 and N523 
(Table 1). Meanwhile, the naturally occurring N118S, 
which probably introduces an N-glycosylation site, was 
also investigated. Of these mutants, N146Q, N177Q, 
N220Q, N241Q and N247Q in the SU subunit main-
tained their original fusion efficiency compared to wild-
type (WT) syncytin-2, whereas N133Q, N312Q and 
N443Q lost their fusogenicity and N118S and N332Q 
acquired enhanced fusogenic activity (Fig. S1). Impor-
tantly, as shown in Fig. 2, when the cell samples were 
subjected to Western blot analysis, all N to Q substitu-
tions except for N523Q revealed bands with lower </p>

<p>Table 1. Nucleotide and amino acid changes introduced to generate syncytin-2 mutants by site-directed mutagenesis. </p>

<p>Mutant site 
Residue number 
Forward Primer (5 
0 -3 
0 ) 
Allele change 
Fusion </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1 
133 
GTGTTATGGCCAAAAGGAAACAGGGAACAAATGTAGGCACTC 
aat!cag N!Q 
¡ 
2 
146 
CTCTTCCAAGTACAGTCTGTCAGGTTACTTTCACTGTAGATTC 
aat!cag N!Q 
C 
3 
177 
CAAGATTCCCCAAACCTCCACAGATTACTTTTCCTCAGGGAAC 
aat!cag N!Q 
C 
4 
220 
CCAATGTCTGCAAATTTCCCAGCTCAGCTCTACAGCGGAATGG 
aac!cag N!Q 
C 
5 
241 
CGAAATTCTCTTTTTTGGGAACAGAAAACCAAGGGAGCTAACCAG 
aat!cag N!Q 
C 
6 
247 
GGAAAATAAAACCAAGGGAGCTCAACAGAGCCAAACACCCTGCGTCC 
aac!caa N!Q 
C 
7 
312 
CACCAATGCCTCCCCAGTCAATGGACTGGAACTTGTACC 
aac!caa N!Q 
¡ 
8 
332 
CTTCATAGCCCCTGGCCAGCTCTCTCTTCCAATAC 
aat!cag N!Q 
CC 
9 
443 
GAAAAATGTTGCTTTTGGGTACAGCAATCAGGAAAAGTACAAGAC 
aat!cag N!Q 
¡ 
10 
523 
GGCCATAAAGCTCCAGACGCAACTCAGTGCAGGACGCCATC 
aat!caa N!Q 
C 
11 
46 
CCACCAATTGCTGGTTACGTACTAGCTCTTCCAC 
tgt!cgt N!Q 
¡ 
12 
118 
CCATCTTTACTAATATCAGCCTAATGGGAATAGCCCC 
aac!agc N!Q 
CC 
13 
359 
CATTTCATTCCCCTTCTCACGGGACTCGGCATTCTAG 
gcg!acg N!Q 
C 
14 
367 
CGGCATTCTAGCTGGTATGGGAACCGGAATTGCTG 
acg!atg N!Q 
CC 
15 
417 
CAGCCGTAGTCCTTCAAAATCATCGAGGACTAGACATGTTAAC 
cgt!cat N!Q 
¡ 
16 
432 
GCACAGGGAGGAATTTGTGTGGCCTTAGATGAAAAATG 
ttg!gtg N!Q 
C 
17 
483 
GGAAATGGTTCTCTTGGATTCTTCCCCTTACAGGC 
gtt!att N!Q 
CC 
18 
503 
GCTCCTTTTTGGTCCATGTTTCCTAAATCTAATAACCC 
ctc!ttc N!Q 
C 
19 
518 
GTCTCCTCTCGCCTTCAGGCCGTAAAGCTCCAGACGAATCTCA 
ata!gta N!Q 
C 
20 
522 
GGCCATAAAGCTCCAGATGAATCTCAGTGCAGGAC 
acg!atg N!Q 
CC 
21 
536 
CCTCGCAATATTCAAGAGTTACCCTTCTAGTGACTGCAG 
tca!tta N!Q 
C </p>

<p>a Cell fusion was monitored 36 h after transfection. ¡, no fusion; C, moderate fusion; CC, excessive fusion. </p>

<p> 
L. CUI ET AL. </p>

<p>molecular weight (arrowhead) than WT syncytin-2, indi-
cating that N-glycosylation of syncytin-2 was widely dis-
tributed at these sites. Moreover, the naturally occurring 
N118S caused a higher molecular weight (arrow), indi-
cating that the introduction of an extra N-glycosylation 
site occurred. Furthermore, the expression levels of the 
WT and mutant syncytins were consistent, showing that 
the transfection efficiency of the different plasmids and 
the exogenous expression of syncytin-2 were at a same 
level. Although the N118S immunostaining was reduced, 
it still significantly elevated the fusion efficiency. As a 
control, when all the N-glycans were removed by treat-
ment with PNGase F N-glycanase, only a »55 kDa band 
was seen, whereas the precursor of syncytin-2 protein 
appeared to be »73 kDa, in accordance with previous 
results. </p>

<p>33,35, 36 </p>

<p>We also investigated the effects of the 10 selected non-
synonymous SNPs located within important functional 
domains/motifs on the fusogenic function of syncytin-2. 
Of these, A359T, L432V, L503F, I518V and S536L had 
no impact on the fusion efficiency mediated by syncytin-
2 (Fig. S1). Notably, C46R and R417H inhibited normal 
cell-cell fusion, whereas T367M, V483I and T522M 
enhanced fusogenic activity compared with the WT 
(Fig. S1). Again, the expression levels of these mutants 
were consistent with that of WT (Fig. S2). </p>

<p>Identification of dysfunctional syncytin-2 mutants 
that stimulate or inhibit syncytin-2-mediated fusion </p>

<p>We next wanted to further characterize the above 
dysfunctional mutants together with WT syncytin-2, 
and the effects of the different stimulatory mutants </p>

<p>(including N118S, N332Q, T367M, V483I and 
T522M) and inhibitory mutants (including N133Q, 
N312Q, N443Q, C46R and R417H) were confirmed 
(Fig. 3A). N118 and N133 are close to each other 
and within the N-terminal half of the SU subunit. 
Gaining an extra N-glycosylation site at N118 and 
removal of the N-glycan at N133 stimulated and 
inhibited the fusion efficiency, respectively. However, 
although both N312 and N332 are located in the C-
terminal region of the SU subunit, disruption of 
both sites individually caused contradictory effects. 
Furthermore, C46R within the CXXC motif, T367M 
within the FP, R417H within the HR1 and ISD, 
V483I within the TMD and T522M within the CTM 
all caused significantly altered fusogenic activity, 
indicating that these functional domains were sensi-
tive to single-amino-acid substitution and that these 
sites were required for optimal fusion induction 
(Fig. 3A). Importantly, Western blot (Fig. 3B) and 
quantitative real-time PCR (Fig. 3C) analysis were 
used to ensure that all the WT and mutant syncytins 
were expressed at similar levels both at the mRNA 
and protein levels. Again, N118S stimulated the 
fusogenic activity of syncytin-2, despite the reduced 
immune-reactivity (Fig. 3B). Because its mRNA was 
expressed normally, one explanation for this could 
be the loss of an epitope due to the amino acid 
substitution. 
We then tested whether the 5 inhibitory mutants 
(N133Q, N312Q, N443Q, C46R and R417H) blocked 
syncytin-2-mediated fusion in 293T-EmGFP cells. We 
found that 293T-EmGFP cells in 6-well plates transfected 
with 1.5 mg WT syncytin-2 expression vector for 36 h </p>

<p>Figure 2. Western blot analysis of the expression of syncytin-2 and its single N-glycosylation site mutants in 293T-EmGFP cells after 36 h 
of transfection. All N-glycans of wild-type (WT) syncytin-2 were removed by treatment with PNGase F N-glycanase. phCMV empty vector 
(empty) was used as a control. The arrow and arrowhead represent bands with higher and lower molecular weight than for WT syncytin-
2, respectively. </p>

<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION </p>

<p>
formed obvious green multinucleated syncytia. The 
induction of cell-cell fusion upon syncytin-2 overexpres-
sion was dose-dependent, and higher doses of expression 
plasmids triggered cell-cell fusion to a larger extent 
(Fig. 4A and 4B). We then co-transfected the cells with </p>

<p>1.5 mg phCMV-syncytin-2 WT and 1.5 mg inhibitory 
mutant plasmids. As a control, the plasmids expressing 
the mutants were replaced with phCMV empty vector. 
As shown in Fig. 4C, the C46R and R417H mutants 
almost completely blocked the fusogenicity of WT </p>

<p>Figure 3. Expression of WT and mutant syncytin-2 in 293T-EmGFP cells and effects on cell-cell fusion. (A) Cell-cell fusion assay mediated 
by wild-type (WT) or mutant syncytin-2. 293T-EmGFP cells in 35 mm plates were transfected with 1.5 mg phCMV-syncytin-2 WT or 
mutant expression plasmids for 36 h. Patches of green fluorescence were monitored as the formation of multinucleated syncytia. Com-
pared with WT syncytin-2, more obvious syncytia were observed by transfection with syncytin-2 mutants N118S, N332Q, T367M, V483I 
and T522M. No syncytia were visible after overexpression of syncytin-2 mutants C46R, N133Q, N312Q, N443Q and R417H followed by 
microscopic examination at £40 and £100 magnification. Bars = 100 mm. (B) Western blot analysis of the expression of syncytin-2 and 
its mutants in 293T-EmGFP cells after 36 h of transfection. The cells shown in A were harvested for immunoblotting using syncytin-2 
and GAPDH antibodies, respectively. (C) The transcription levels of syncytin-2 were simultaneously quantified by real-time PCR using 
GAPDH as an internal control. Mean values and SDs are obtained from 3 independent experiments. Empty, phCMV empty vector. </p>

<p> 
L. CUI ET AL. </p>

<p>syncytin-2. Mutants N133Q, N312Q and N443Q signifi-
cantly suppressed the fusogenic properties of the native 
syncytin-2 protein. These results suggest that these 
mutants cause significant repressive effects on the fuso-
genic activity of syncytin-2 and therefore may serve as 
competitive inhibitors in WT syncytin-2-mediated cell-
cell fusion. </p>

<p>The abnormal interaction between syncytin-2 
mutant and its receptor MFSD2A during cell-cell 
fusion </p>

<p>To verify the interaction between syncytin-2 and its 
receptor MFSD2A, they were co-overexpressed in 
HeLa cells that express neither protein and analyzed 
by co-immunoprecipitation. We firstly detected the 
expression of FLAG-tagged MFSD2A in HeLa cells </p>

<p>by Western blotting using an anti-FLAG antibody. 
No immunoreactive bands were detected in control 
mock-transfected cells and pEF6-MFSD2A-trans-
fected cells (Fig. 5A). Monoclonal anti-FLAG anti-
body was then used for the co-immunoprecipitation 
of syncytin-2 in HeLa cells. As shown in Fig. 5B, the 
lysed cell samples precipitated by the anti-FLAG 
antibody contained significant amounts of syncytin-2 
protein, indicating that full-length MFSD2A associ-
ates with syncytin-2. Syncytin-2 was not detected 
either in the co-transfection of pcDNA3.1-MFSD2A-
FLAG and phCMV empty vector or of pcDNA3.1-
GFP-FLAG and phCMV-syncytin-2, indicating the 
adequate protein expression in this system and that 
the antibodies in this expression system are largely 
devoid of nonspecific protein binding. To infer the 
sensitivity and specificity of syncytin-2 with its </p>

<p>Figure 4. The 5 mutants N133Q, N312Q, N443Q, C46R and R417H exerted inhibitory effects on syncytin-2-mediated cell-cell fusion. (A) 
Dose-dependent promotion of cell-cell fusion after overexpression of syncytin-2. The 293T-EmGFP cells in 35 mm plates were trans-
fected with 0.25 mg, 0.5 mg, 1 mg, 1.5 mg, 2 mg and 3 mg phCMV-syncytin-2 WT for 36 h. Cell-cell fusion was monitored by microscopy 
at £40 magnification. (B) The cells shown in A were harvested for Western blotting analysis with syncytin-2 antibody. (C) The N133Q, 
N312Q, N443Q, C46R and R417H mutants of syncytin-2 interfere with the fusogenic capacity of WT syncytin-2 proteins. The 293T-EmGFP 
cells in 35 mm plates were transfected with 1.5 mg WT syncytin-2 and 1.5 mg mutant expression plasmids, followed by microscopic 
examination at £40 and £100 magnification. As a control, the cells were transfected with 1.5 mg WT syncytin-2 expression vector and 
1.5 mg phCMV empty vector. All experiments were repeated 3 times. WT, wild-type. Bars = 100 mm. </p>

<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION </p>

<p>
receptor MFSD2A, we further examined the interac-
tion between different syncytin-2 mutants and 
FLAG-tagged MFSD2A. The expression levels of WT 
syncytin-2 and syncytin-2 mutants were adjusted to 
similar levels. MFSD2A-FLAG strongly co-immuno-
precipitated with WT syncytin-2 and mutants 
N133Q, N312Q, N332Q, V483I and T522M, whereas 
minimal amounts were detected in N443Q, C46R, 
T367M and R417H immunoprecipitated complexes. 
N118S was associated with more receptors than the 
WT (Fig. 5C). We also employed preliminary mass 
spectrometry studies to find syncytin-2 interacting 
proteins during membrane merging (see Supplemen-
tary data and Fig. S3). </p>

<p>Identification of the T522M SNP in the coding region 
of syncytin-2 by genomic DNA sequencing in sPE 
patients and normal pregnant women </p>

<p>We further set out to identify non-synonymous SNPs in 
the coding region of syncytin-2 in 125 sPE patients and 
272 normal pregnant women by genomic DNA sequenc-
ing. Surprisingly, only 1 missense mutation 
(rs138651238; c.1565C&gt;T and p.T522M) was discovered 
(Fig. 6). In total, 18 heterozygous carriers of T522M out 
of 272 normal pregnant women were found. However, 
only 4 heterozygous carriers out of 125 sPE patients were 
identified. The frequency of T522M heterozygous </p>

<p>carriers was 0.0618 in the control group versus 0.0320 in 
sPE patients. A chi-square test was used to analyze the 
difference, revealing a chi-square of 0.167 and a P value 
of 0.124. The heterozygosity and MAF of T522M 
recorded by the 1000 Genomes Project are 0.009 and 
0.0044, respectively. Therefore, the frequency of this 
SNP appeared to be higher in the Chinese population. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We identified 10 single-amino-acid-substitution human 
syncytin-2 mutants with abnormalities in fusogenic 
function, including N133Q, N312Q, N332Q and N443Q, 
which silenced the N-glycosylation sites individually, 
and the naturally occurring SNPs C46R, N118S, T367M, 
R417H, V483I and T522M. N118S introduced a new N-
glycosylation site. Of these 10 mutants, N133Q (in the 
N-terminal half of the SU), N312Q (in the C-terminal 
region of the SU), N443Q (in the TM, close to the CX6C 
motif and HR2 domain), C46R (in the CXXC motif) and 
R417H (in the HR1 and ISD domain) exerted inhibitory 
effects on the fusogenic activity of syncytin-2, whereas 
N118S (in the N-terminal half of the SU), N332Q (in the 
C-terminal region of the SU), T367M (in the FP), V483I 
(in the TMD) and T522M (in the CTM) were 
stimulatory. 
Several lines of evidence suggest that the sequence 
polymorphisms of HERV family genes provide </p>

<p>Figure 5. Interaction between syncytin-2/mutants and the MFSD2A receptor. (A) HeLa cells were transiently transfected with expression 
plasmids encoding either FLAG-tagged MFSD2A (pcDNA3.1-MFSD2A-FLAG) or MFSD2A without a FLAG tag (pEF6-MFSD2A) and sub-
jected to Western blotting assay using an anti-FLAG antibody. The pcDNA3.1 empty vector was used as a control. (B) pcDNA3.1-
MFSD2A-FLAG and phCMV-syncytin-2 were co-transfected into HeLa cells to test the sensitivity and specificity of the interaction 
between syncytin-2 and MFSD2A. Cell lysates were immunoprecipitated with an anti-FLAG antibody and immunoblotted with an anti-
syncytin-2 antibody. phCMV empty vector and pcDNA3.1-GFP-FLAG were used as a control. (C) Cells expressing either syncytin-2 WT or 
the mutants were lysed, immunoprecipitated with the anti-FLAG antibody and immunoblotted with the anti-syncytin-2 antibody. 
phCMV empty vector and pcDNA3.1-GFP-FLAG were used as a control. WT, wild-type. Empty, phCMV empty vector. </p>

<p> 
L. CUI ET AL. </p>

<p>susceptibility to human diseases. 
42,43 For example, 
ERVW-1 3 
0 -long-terminal repeat (LTR) SNPs (142 T&gt;C 
and 277 A&gt;G) are associated with syncytin-1 overex-
pression and may be an indicator of the risk of urothelial 
cell carcinoma of the bladder. 
43 However, there is also a 
report suggesting the conservation of the ERVW-1 locus, 
including the LTR transcriptional elements and the 
splice sites involved in env mRNA maturation in 155 
individuals. 
11 The authors also sequenced the envelope 
ORF that encodes syncytin-1 in 24 individuals and found 
4 non-synonymous mutations that occurred at a fre-
quency of 25%, 4%, 2%, and 2%, respectively. However, 
these polymorphic variants are functionally preserved 
and do not affect the fusogenic function of WT syncytin-
1 in a heterotypic cell-cell fusion assay. 
11 To our knowl-
edge, this is the only published study related to the func-
tional analysis of the non-synonymous SNPs in the 
coding region of syncytins. Despite the availability of 
public SNP databases in which 162 non-synonymous 
SNPs of syncytin-2 have been recorded, their functional 
study and relevance to diseases remain surprisingly 
elusive. 
As one of the most common post-translational pro-
tein modifications, N-glycosylation is crucial for many 
elementary biological and pathological processes. Syncy-
tins belong to the class I fusion proteins that include the 
envelope proteins of many viruses, such as the human 
immunodeficiency virus (HIV). Typically, class I fusion 
proteins are synthesized as glycosylated precursors in the 
endoplasmic reticulum and then modified by N-glycosyl-
ation and disulfide bond formation. 
40 As such, syncytin-
2 is also glycosylated. 
33,36 In the case of the HIV envelope </p>

<p>protein, N-glycosylation is critical for viral infectivity, 
immunogenicity, cytopathicity and transmission. 
44-46 In 
an extensive study, 23 N-glycosylation sites in the gp120 
subunit of the simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) 
envelope protein are individually silenced, and the muta-
tions result in different effects on viral infectivity, repli-
cation and recovery. 
47 Therefore, we set out to screen all 
the N-glycosylation sites in syncytin-2 and to investigate 
whether they are necessary for the fusogenic function. 
Using individual deglycosylation studies, we verified 
that except for N523, the other 9 predicted N-glycosyla-
tion sites, including N133, N146, N177, N220, N241, 
N247, N312, N332 and N443, were indeed glycosylated 
in 293T cells. Moreover, the naturally occurring N118S 
introduced an extra N-glycosylation site and produced a 
protein with a higher molecular weight. Of these 10 gly-
cosylated sites, the first 9 were all located within the SU 
subunit. Interestingly, only the mutations of the first 2 
and the last 2 sites (N118S, N133Q, N312Q and N332Q), 
but not of the middle 5 sites (N146Q, N177Q, N220Q, 
N241Q and N247Q) altered the fusogenicity of syncytin-
2. The binding of the SU to the receptor is the prerequi-
site for the FP at the N-terminus of the TM to drive 
membrane fusion. 
37,40 Therefore, our results indicate 
that the N-glycans located at the N-terminal half and C-
terminal arm of the SU subunit are important for syncy-
tin-2-mediated cell-cell fusion probably by affecting the 
interaction between the SU and the receptor. The non-
functional sites from N146 to N247 indicate that this 
region is flexible in conformation and tolerates losing the 
glycosylation. In the case of syncytin-1, the N-terminal 
124 amino acids of the SU are the minimal receptor-</p>

<p>Figure 6. Identification of heterozygous carriers of syncytin-2 T522M (rs138651238) in normal pregnant women and severe pre-eclamp-
tic (sPE) patients. (A) Frequency of T522M in normal pregnant women (n D 272) and sPE patients (n D 125). (B) Sequencing of syncytin-
2 coding region revealed a C &gt; T single-nucleotide polymorphism with amino acid substitution at 522 (T522M). MAF, minor allele 
frequency. </p>

<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION </p>

<p>
binding domain containing a conserved 18-residue motif 
essential for syncytin-1-ASCT2 interaction. 
48 Moreover, 
N443Q, which is in proximity to the CX6CC motif and 
HR2 domain in the central region of the ectodomain 
TM, also significantly suppressed the fusogenic property 
of the native syncytin-2 protein. As reported, the 2 hep-
tad repeat regions HR1 and HR2 specifically form intra-
molecular interaction between each other and are 
necessary for syncytin-mediated cell-cell fusion. 
38 Our 
results add new evidence that the N443Q might destabi-
lize the hairpin conformation of HR1 and HR2, or hin-
der the formation of the disulfide bond, and discourage 
cell-cell fusion. Taken together, our results indicate that 
syncytin-2 has 9 N-linked glycosylation sites, among 
which glycans at residues 133, 312, 443 and 332 are 
required for optimal fusion induction, and that appropri-
ate sugar chain density over the specific region is pre-
served for functional integrity. 
We also generated another 10 mutants carrying the 
naturally occurring SNPs C46R, A359T, T367M, L432V, 
R417H, V483I, L503F, I518V, T522M and S536L, which 
are located in important functional domains or motifs. 
Of these, 2 defective mutants (C46R and R417H) and 3 
stimulatory mutants (T367M, V483I and T522M) were 
identified. C46R is located in the CXXC motif of the SU 
subunit, which is highly conserved among retroviral 
envelope proteins and participate in the formation of a 
labile intersubunit disulfide bond with the CX6CC motif 
of the TM subunit for isomerization. 
36,49 Therefore, the 
silencing effect of C46R on the fusogenic activity con-
firmed the significance of the CXXC motif for fusogene-
sis and the necessity of the cysteine for the formation of 
an intersubunit disulfide bridge. This agrees well with 
the effect of C46A from a previous extensive study, 
which shows mutations in the CXXC motif not only 
inhibit fusion but also can function as dominant-nega-
tive mutants. 
36 However, the naturally occurring SNP 
L432V located in the CX6CC motif in the TM subunit 
did not alter the fusion efficiency, indicating the flexibil-
ity of the 6 amino acids between the 3 cysteines. R417H 
is located in 2 domains, the HR1 domain discussed above 
and the 17-amino-acid ISD present in several retroviral 
envelope proteins that is highly immunosuppressive for 
inhibiting immune function. 
50,51 R417H led to a com-
plete loss of its fusogenic activity, implying the signifi-
cance of both domains for syncytin-2 fusion ability. 
Of the 3 stimulatory mutants that can enhance the 
fusogenic activity of syncytin-2, the T367M is located 
within the FP. FP is a conserved hydrophobic domain 
located at the N-terminus of the TM subunit mediating 
cell membrane fusion. 
38 The SNP V483I is located at the </p>

<p>hydrophobic stretch TMD domain. This suggests that 
the conformation of the hydrophobic transmembrane 
region might be sensitive to single-amino-acid substitu-
tion, although both valine and isoleucine are nonpolar 
amino acids. The CTM of syncytin-1 and syncytin-2 is 
essential for their fusogenic activities. The comparison of 
human ERVW-1 elements and the orthologous loci in 
simians reveals an syncytin-1-specific signature in the 
intracytoplasmic tail is crucial for the envelope fusogenic 
activity. 
10 A systematic study involves a series of C-ter-
minal truncated mutants of syncytin-1 shows that cyto-
plasmic sequences immediately adjacent to the 
transmembrane region are necessary for inducing opti-
mal cell-cell fusion, whereas the extreme C-terminus 
partially inhibits its fusogenic function. 
39 Similarly, dif-
ferent C-terminally truncated syncytin-2 mutants led to 
a decrease in the size and number of syncytia at different 
levels. 
36 Of the 4 SNPs (L503F, I518V, T522M and 
S536L) in the CTM tested, only T522M changed the 
fusogenic activity compared with the WT. This is also 
consistent with previous findings that some regions in 
the CTM of syncytin-1 are flexible in the conformation. </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>Altogether, we have characterized 5 SNPs (C46R, 
T367M, R417H, V483I and T522M) in conserved 
domains as strong candidates that can alter the fusogenic 
function of syncytin-2. 
To further define the functional properties of the 5 
defective mutants, WT and mutant syncytin-2 expres-
sion plasmids were co-transfected. We found that the 
C46R and R417H mutants almost completely blocked 
syncytin-2-mediated cell-cell fusion, and N133Q, N312Q 
and N443Q mutants significantly suppressed the fuso-
genic properties of the native syncytin-2 protein. The 
molecular mechanism of inhibition is unclear, but it is 
likely that the mutants with single-amino-acid substitu-
tions in important functional domains can efficiently 
compete with native syncytin-2 to bind the receptor or 
to trigger signaling pathways for merging membranes. 
We therefore employed co-immunoprecipitation experi-
ments to study the sensitivity and specificity of the inter-
action between syncytin-2 and its receptor MFSD2A. Of 
the 5 defective mutants, N133Q and N312Q could be 
pulled down normally by MFSD2A, whereas N443Q, 
C46R and R417H showed compromised interaction with 
the receptor. The results with R417H and N443Q are 
quite unexpected because they are located within the TM 
subunit. This finding probably provides insight into the 
significance of the TM subunit serving as an indispens-
able component of the SU-TM homotrimer during the 
interaction between the SU and the receptor. Notably, 
the significantly induced fusion with the N118S mutant </p>

<p> 
L. CUI ET AL. </p>

<p>correlated well with its higher ability to bind with the 
receptor. However, whether the T367M mutant that 
showed reduced interaction with the receptor while pro-
moting fusion is related to the activation of other signal-
ing pathways remains to be studied. 
PE is a common, multi-system and serious complica-
tion of human pregnancy affecting 3-5% of all women. 
Characterized by new-onset hypertension and protein-
uria after 20 weeks of gestation, PE is a major contributor 
to maternal morbidity and mortality worldwide, and 
unbalanced syncytialization has been implicated in its 
pathology. 
52 Expression of both syncytin-1 and syncytin-
2 are significantly decreased in sPE placentas vs. normal 
control. 
23,36,53-61 In our attempts to identify polymorphic 
sites within the coding sequence of syncytin-2 in 125 sPE 
patients and 272 normal pregnant women, only 1 mis-
sense mutation [rs138651238 (T522M)] was found. This 
mutation enhanced syncytin-2-mediated cell-cell fusion 
in vitro and occurred at a frequency of 0.0320 in sPE 
patients and 0.0618 in the control group. However, the 
statistical analysis revealed no significant difference. 
Considering the large number of non-synonymous SNPs 
in the coding region of syncytin-2 in the SNP database, 
further studies in a larger sample size are warranted. 
Taken together, we provided novel in vitro experi-
mental evidence for the structure-function relationship 
of syncytin-2 through investigating 21 single-amino-acid 
mutants. We proved that N133, N146, N177, N220, 
N241, N247, N312, N332 and N443 were glycosylation 
sites and that N133, N312, N332 and N443 played 
important roles in the fusogenic function of syncytin-2. 
The naturally occurring polymorphisms C46R, R417H, 
N118S, T367M, V483I and T522M led to abnormal fuso-
genicity. The binding between syncytin-2 and its recep-
tor MFSD2A was compromised by the N443Q, C46R, 
T367M and R417H mutations, whereas N118S was asso-
ciated with more receptors. We sequenced the syncytin-
2 coding sequences in sPE patients and normal pregnant 
women and found 1 missense mutation T522M. The 
above results suggest some key residues in determining 
the fusogenic function of syncytin-2, and investigation of 
the mechanisms will help to better understand how this 
molecule merges the membranes of CTBs. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Blood and DNA samples </p>

<p>A total of 397 blood samples were collected from 272 
normal pregnant Han Chinese women and 125 sPE 
patients undergoing legal procedures in Beijing Obstet-
rics and Gynecology Hospital and Peking University 
Third Hospital. A woman was determined to have sPE </p>

<p>when either severe hypertension (a systolic blood pres-
sure 160 mmHg or a diastolic blood pressure 110 
mmHg), severe proteinuria (more than 5 g of protein 
was collected in a 24 h urine specimen), or both, were 
present after 20 weeks of gestation. 
62 None of the sPE 
patients involved in this study had other maternal com-
plications. All the sPE patients were aged 23-35 and 
delivered at 25 to 40 weeks. In all cases, blood samples 
were anonymized after routine analysis was completed. 
Ethical approval and utilization of samples under stan-
dard experimental protocols was granted by the Ethics 
Committee of Beijing Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospi-
tal, Peking University Third Hospital and the Institute of 
Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences. Genomic DNA 
from blood lymphocytes was extracted using a genomic 
DNA extraction kit (DN0113, Biomed Biotechnology 
Corp., Beijing, China). </p>

<p>Plasmid construction and site-directed mutagenesis </p>

<p>The human syncytin-1 expression construct phCMV-
syncytin-1 
11 is a kind gift from Dr. Francois Mallet, Lab-
oratoire Commun de Recherche Hospices Civils de 
Lyon-bioM erieux, Cancer Biomarkers Research Group, 
Ecole Normale Sup erieure, Lyon, France. The phCMV 
empty vector was generated by removing the syncytin-1 
cDNA. The syncytin-2 cDNA fragment was amplified 
from pTM1-syncytin-2 
36 (a kind gift from Dr. Hungwen 
Chen, Institute of Biological Chemistry, Academia Sin-
ica, Taipei, Taiwan) and cloned into phCMV. A full-
length cDNA encoding the human MFSD2A with FLAG 
was amplified from pEF6-MFSD2A 
63 (a kind gift from 
Dr. Tommaso Dragani and Dr. Francesca Colombo, 
Department of Predictive and for Prevention Medicine, 
Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale Tumori, Milan, 
Italy) and cloned into an XhoI/XbaI-digested pcDNA3.1 
to generate pcDNA3.1-MFSD2A-FLAG. The full-length 
EmGFP coding sequence was amplified from the 
pcDNA6.2-EmGFP vector (V355-20, Invitrogen) and 
cloned into the pQCXIP vector using the restriction 
enzymes NotI/BamHI to generate pQCXIP-EmGFP. The 
primers used for amplifying the above cDNAs are sum-
marized in Table 2. 
The 21 human syncytin-2 mutants, including 10 
mutants (N133Q, N146Q, N177Q, N220Q, N241Q, 
N247Q, N312Q, N332Q, N443Q and N523Q) removing 
potential N-glycosylation sites, 1 naturally occurring 
SNP (N118S) introducing a new potential N-glycosyla-
tion site, and another 10 naturally occurring SNPs 
(C46R, A359T, T367M, R417H, L432V, V483I, L503F, 
I518V, T522M and S536L) located in predicted impor-
tant functional domains were generated on the WT 
phCMV-syncytin-2 expression vector template using the </p>

<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION </p>

<p>
QuikChange II XL site-directed mutagenesis kit (200514, 
Stratagene) following the manufacturer's instructions 
and verified by sequencing. The forward and reverse pri-
mers used for mutagenesis are summarized in Table 2. 
All constructs were sequenced to confirm that only the 
targeted mutations had occurred. The putative N-glyco-
sylation sites in human syncytin-2 proteins were 
obtained from the UniProt database. </p>

<p>Cell lines </p>

<p>293T and HeLa cells were purchased from the American 
Type Culture Collection. Cells were cultured in Dulbec-
co's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) supplemented 
with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Life Technologies), 
100 mg/ml streptomycin and 100 U/ml penicillin, and 
maintained in 95% air and 5% carbon dioxide at 37 
C. </p>

<p>Establishment of stable GFP-expressing 293T and 
HeLa cell lines </p>

<p>293T and HeLa cells were transfected with pQCXIP-
EmGFP using Lipofectamine 2000 (15338-100, Invitro-
gen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
Transfected cells were subjected to puromycin (P8833; 
Sigma Chemical Co.) selection (1.5 mg/ml for 293 T cells 
and 0.125 mg/ml for HeLa cells), and the antibiotics-
resistant clones were pooled for studies. The expression 
of EmGFP was confirmed under a fluorescence 
microscope. </p>

<p>Fusion assay of syncytin-2 </p>

<p>Cell-cell fusion mediated by syncytin-2 and its mutants 
was monitored 36 h after expression plasmid transfection </p>

<p>by tracing EmGFP-expressing 293T or HeLa cells. Fusion 
events were traced by fluorescence microscopy as the for-
mation of green multinucleated syncytia in transfected 
cells. 
38 For the negative control, cells were transfected 
with phCMV empty vector. </p>

<p>Real-time quantitative-PCR </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted and purified from cultured cells 
using TRIzol reagent (15596-018, Invitrogen) according 
to the manufacturer's instructions. RNA concentration 
was determined with a NanoDrop 2000 UV-Vis spectro-
photometer (Thermo Scientific). Two micrograms of 
total RNA were reverse transcribed into single-stranded 
cDNA using Superscript II reverse transcriptase 
(18064022, Invitrogen). Real-time quantitative PCR was 
performed using SYBR Premix Ex Taq kit (DRR081A, 
Takara) with the Real-time PCR System (ABI PRISM 
7500 Real-time PCR System, Applied Biosystems). Spe-
cific primers are indicated in Table 2. Data were analyzed 
using DCt method and normalized to GAPDH expres-
sion. All data were based on experiments performed at 
least in triplicates. </p>

<p>Western blotting and co-immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>The cells were homogenized in whole cell lysis buffer 
(50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 0.5% 
Triton X-100). A total of 30 mg/well of proteins were 
resolved by SDS-PAGE and transferred electrophoreti-
cally onto nitrocellulose membranes (Pall Corporation). 
After incubation with blocking buffer (5% fat-free milk 
in phosphate-buffered saline containing 0.5% Tween 20), 
membranes were incubated overnight at 4 
C with spe-
cific primary antibodies against syncytin-2 (P60508, </p>

<p>Table 2. Primers used for plasmid construction, real-time quantitative PCR and genomic DNA sequencing. </p>

<p>Gene 
Forward Primer (5 
0 -3 
0 ) 
Reverse primer (5 
0 -3 
0 ) </p>

<p>Plasmid construction 
Syncytin-2 cDNA 
5 
0 -CGCACTCGAGCACGCCACCATGG 
GCCTGCTCCTGCTGGTTCTCATTCTC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 
0 -ATTCTGCAGTCACTAGAAGGGTGACTCTTGAATATTGCGAGG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>MFSD2A-FLAG cDNA 
5 
0 -CTAGCTAGCCTCGAGGCCACCATGGCC 
AAAGGAGAAG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 
0 -GCTCTAGACTACTTGTCATCGTCATCCTTGTAGTCGATGTCATGA 
TCTTTATAATCACCGTCATGGTCTTTGTAGTCATTAAGTTTGTGC 
CCCAG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>EmGFP cDNA 
5 
0 -GAGCGGCCGCAGCCACCATGGTGAGC 
AAGGGCGAGGA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 
0 -GCGGGGATCCTCTATTACTTGTACAGCTCGTCCA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Real-time quantitative PCR 
Syncytin-2 
5 
0 -CCAAAGGAACCTGAAAATCC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 
0 -TTAGGGATTCTTAGTCAGCC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>GAPDH 
5 
0 -AAGGTGAAGGTCGGAGTCAAC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 
0 -GGGGTCATTGATGGCAACAATA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Genomic DNA sequencing 
HERV-FRD 
LF: 5 
0 -AACTTAGGCACATTAGCATT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>LR: 5 
0 -AACTTAGGCACATTAGCATT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>syncytin-2 ORF 
SF: 5 
0 -TGTACACCACCAGGAGTTCC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>SR: 5 
0 -TGGGTCTTGGCCTCTTGCTA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>syncytin-2-S1 
-
5 
0 -GCTGTAGAGCTGAGGTTGGA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>syncytin-2-S2 
5 
0 -CAGACTTACCAAACATACACCC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-
syncytin-2-S3 
5 
0 -ACCCCAGACATCTTCATAGC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p> 
L. CUI ET AL. </p>

<p>Abgent) and GAPDH (ab37187, Abcam), followed by 
incubation with appropriate secondary antibody. The 
blot was developed using the enhanced chemilumines-
cence (Pierce Chemical Co.). PNGase F N-glycanase 
(P0704S, Sigma Chemical Co.) was used to remove N-
glycans in the protein samples following the manufac-
turer's instructions. 
For the co-immunoprecipitation assay, HeLa cells 
were co-transfected with 4 mg WT or mutant human 
syncytin-2 constructs and 4 mg pcDNA3.1-MFSD2A-
FLAG in 60 mm culture dishes. Control experiments 
were performed by transfecting cells with appropriate 
empty vectors, phCMV empty vector or pcDNA3.1-
GFP-FLAG. After transfection for 48 h, the cells were 
lysed by suspension in ice-cold lysis buffer (50 mM Tris 
pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol and 0.5% Triton X-
100) supplemented with protease inhibitor cocktail 
(1mM phenylmethylsulfonylfluoride, 10 mg/ml aprotinin 
and 1mM sodium orthovanadate) (04693132001, Roche 
Diagnostics) for 1 h. After centrifugation at 12,000 g for 
20 min, the cell lysates containing FLAG-tagged 
MFSD2A proteins were immunoprecipitated with anti-
FLAG M2 agarose beads (F2426, Sigma Chemical Co.) at 
4 
C overnight. After centrifuging and washing for 
3 times, samples were subjected to Western blotting 
analysis with an anti-syncytin-2 antibody. </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry analysis </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation of the concentrated proteins was 
carried out with protein A sepharose beads (10-1141, 
Invitrogen) essentially as described by the manufacturer. 
293T cells were transfected with phCMV empty vector, 
phCMV-syncyntin-2 WT, phCMV-syncytin-2 N312Q 
and phCMV-syncytin-2 T522M plasmids, respectively. 
After transfection for 48 h, the cells were lysed by sus-
pension in ice-cold lysis buffer for 1 h. Lysates were col-
lected after centrifugation at 12,000 g for 20 min and 
immunoprecipitated with 3 mg anti-syncytin-2 antibody. 
Following an overnight incubation, samples were added 
to 30 ml of protein A bead slurry and rotated for 4 hours 
at 4 
C. After centrifuging and washing 3 times, samples 
were separated on an SDS-PAGE resolving gel and sub-
jected to direct mass spectrometry (MS) analysis. Using 
the LTQ-orbitrap XL mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher 
Scientific), 4 samples were run and analyzed by <rs id="software-6" type="software">Scaffold</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Proteome software</rs>). The peptide identities were 
accepted when the Peptide Prophet algorithm specified 
probabilities were at &gt;95.0%. Argot2 (Annotation 
Retrieval of Gene Ontology Terms; http://www.med-
comp.medicina.unipd.it/Argot2) was used to identify the 
functional classifications of the total and specific 
expressed proteins. DAVID (DAVID Bioinformatics </p>

<p>Resources 6.7; http://david.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/tools.jsp) was 
used to perform functional classification of the differen-
tially expressed proteins (the fold change was greater 
than or equal to 1.5 and the spectrum count number was 
not less than 4). Cytoscape was used to draw programs. </p>

<p>Genomic DNA sequencing of the human syncytin-2 
coding region </p>

<p>All PCR amplification reactions (50 ml) were performed 
using the TaKaRa LA Taq standard conditions. The 
9.5 kb ERV-FRD locus including flanking non-retroviral 
sequences in chromosome 6, LTRs, gag, pol and env ORF 
was amplified by long-distance PCR according to the 
reported method 
11 using sense primer LF and antisense 
primer LR. Each reaction tube contained a maximum of 
50 ng of DNA, 250 nM of each primer, 1.2 mM MgCl 2 , 
500 mM dNTPs, and 5 units of TaKaRa LA Taq DNA 
polymerase in 50 ml of PCR buffer. Cycling conditions 
were 3 min at 94 
C, followed by 30 cycles of PCR. Each 
cycle consisted of 30 sec at 94 
C, 40 sec at 58 
C, and a 
10 min elongation step at 68 
C. The 30th cycle included 
an additional 10 min elongation step at 68 
C. 
For template, 0.5 ml of the 9.5 kb long-distance ampli-
fication product was used to amplify the full-length syn-
cytin-2 env gene using sense primer SF and antisense 
primer SR. The amplification fragment was sequenced 
using antisense primer S1, sense primer S2 and sense 
primer S3, which are located at 655-674 bp, 466-487 bp 
and 967-986 bp in the coding region of syncytin-2, 
respectively. At least 2 independent readings on each 
strand were performed. The primers used for amplifying 
and sequencing the full-length syncytin-2 ORF are indi-
cated in Table 2. 
A chi-square test was used to analyze the difference of 
the frequency of T522M between normal pregnant 
women and sPE patients. The analysis was conducted 
using Statistical Package for Social Science software 
(SPSS for Windows version 10.0; SPSS Inc.), and P &lt; 
0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>ASCT 
alanine/serine/cysteine/threonine transporter 
CTBs 
cytotrophoblast cells 
CTM 
cytoplasmic domain 
DMEM 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium 
env 
envelope 
FBS 
fetal bovine serum 
FP 
fusion peptide 
gag 
group-specific antigen gene 
HERV 
human endogenous retrovirus 
HR 
heptad repeat region 
ISD 
immunosuppressive domain </p>

<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION </p>

<p>
LTR </p>

<p>long terminal repeat 
MAF 
minor allele frequency 
MFSD2A major facilitator superfamily domain con-
taining 2 
ORF 
open reading frame 
PE 
pre-eclampsia 
pol 
polymerase 
SNP 
single-nucleotide polymorphism 
SP 
signal peptide 
STB 
syncytiotrophoblast 
ST-I 
syncytiotrophoblast layer I 
ST-II 
syncytiotrophoblast layer II 
SU 
surface protein 
TM 
transmembrane protein 
TMD 
transmembrane domain 
WT 
wide-type </p>

<p>Disclosure of potential conflicts of interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Dr. Hungwen Chen for providing the pTM1-syncy-
tin-2 plasmid, Dr. Francois Mallet for providing the phCMV-
syncytin-1 plasmid, and Drs. Tommaso Dragani and Francesca 
Colombo for providing the pEF6-MFSD2A 830 plasmid. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Key Basic Research 
Program of China (2011CB944400), the Major Program of 
National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) 
(81490741) and a grant from NSFC (31271603). H. Y. Lin is a 
recipient of National Excellent Young Scientist supported by 
NSFC (81322008). </p>



<p> 
L. CUI ET AL. </p>



<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION </p>



<p>
 
L. CUI ET AL. </p>



<p>CELL ADHESION &amp; MIGRATION </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>