<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4554393" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: Maxillary sinus floor augmentation has been shown to be the most predictable 
surgical technique for enhancing the bone volume in the posterior area of the maxilla. The pur-
pose of this study was to analyze the serial slice image segmentation of newly formed bone and 
bone substitutes after sinus floor elevation using synchrotron radiation X-ray micro-computed 
tomography (SR-µCT). 
Materials and methods: Bone biopsy specimens were collected after 6 months of sinus 
floor augmentation. From the six bone biopsy specimens, the cross-sectional images at every 
8 µm along the apical direction from the inferior border using serial segmentation from three-
dimensional reconstructed X-ray images were analyzed. The amount of new bone and bone 
substitutes were measured at each slicing image (300-430 images per specimen). 
Results: The bone dynamics between the new bone and bone substitutes along the inferior-
superior direction in humans after maxillary sinus floor elevation (MSFE) were analyzed using 
the whole sample region. Although these observations suggest that the specimens are structur-
ally inhomogeneous, sinus floor elevation was confirmed to be a reliable surgical procedure 
for increasing the amount of bone. 
Conclusion: SR-µCT is highly effective for obtaining high-resolution images. An analysis of 
biological specimens using SR-µCT is quite reliable and this technique will be an important 
tool in the wide field of tissue engineering. 
Sinus floor elevation for dental implant placement in the posterior maxilla with 
deficient bone height is a well-known procedure for bone grafting. 
1-5 Previous stud-
ies have reported successful outcomes with bone substitutes (BSs) in sinus floor 
elevation procedures. 
2,6 Of the various BSs available, xenogeneic BSs (Bio-Oss </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>) are 
used widely and consist of the mineral phase of bovine bone, inorganic and a natural 
hydroxyapatite-containing ultrastructure. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>The quantitative determination of new bone (NB) is one of the key factors for 
judging the efficacy of various bone grafting materials for maxillary sinus floor 
elevation in humans. To observe and estimate the amount of NB after a surgical treat-
ment, hematoxylin-eosin (H&amp;E) photomicrography is one of the most widely used 
techniques in histology, because the conventional dye-stained photomicrographs are 
exceptionally good for highlighting biological structures, including bulk tissues and </p>

<p>correspondence: Yong-gun Kim 
Department of Periodontology, School 
of Dentistry, Kyungpook National 
University, 2177 Dalgubeol-daero, 
Jung-gu, Daegu 700-412, 
republic of Korea 
Tel +82 53 600 7524 
Fax +82 53 427 3263 
email periokyg@knu.ac.kr </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of Nanomedicine 
25 August 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 (Special Issue on diverse applications in Nano-Theranostics) </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>Seo et al </p>

<p>bones. In general, histologic techniques based on cutting 
and grinding are used to assess the ability of NB formation 
using BSs. Conventional histomorphometry using H&amp;E pho-
tomicrography, which uses samples obtained by a trephine 
bur, provides the information for bone dynamics along the 
coronal-apical direction from the longitudinal sectional view 
along the direction of the sagittal plane. On the other hand, a 
very limited number of sections are analyzed in conventional 
histomorphometry due to the complex physical process of 
slicing the bone samples and the time consuming and high 
cost of sample preparation. 
To avoid those demerits of conventional histomorphom-
etry, nondestructive micro-CT (µCT) has been used in bone 
analysis in various areas, such as growth and development, 
and animal models. µCT provides a multiple-angled attenu-
ated X-ray projection to reconstruct a three-dimensional (3D) 
representation of a specimen, which characterizes the spatial 
distribution of the material density with a spatial resolution 
of approximately 1.6 µm. 
8 In addition, it enables the calcula-
tion of 3D measures without the need to assume a geometric 
model, which ultimately defines the stereology. 
8 This means 
that µCT would provide the ability for stereological-based 
histomorphometry with a precise bone quantity. Although 
µCT provides many of the above-mentioned merits, it has 
some limitations for achieving high-resolution images using 
a desktop X-ray lab source due to polychromatic radiation 
and the low X-ray flux of X-ray sources. In addition, the wide 
use of µCT has been limited by the difficulty of volumetric 
analysis, serial segmentation, and handling of giga-byte data 
for post-processing. For those reasons, previous research 
focused on comparing µCT with conventional methods 
regarding the bone mineral density of iliac crest, vertebrae, 
femur, 
9-11 and trabecular pattern in an animal model. 
In this study, a synchrotron radiation source was used to 
provide monochromatic radiation of an extremely high flux, 
which enables X-ray images to be obtained with high speed 
and high resolution. To provide the accurate fraction from 
complex and volumetric samples without limited sampling 
issues, this study used serial slice image segmentation of a 
bone biopsy specimen at every 8 µm from the cross-sectional 
images of 3D reconstructions along the longitudinal direc-
tion after MSFE using synchrotron radiation X-ray micro-
computed tomography (SR-µCT). The quantitative degree 
of bone regeneration was analyzed based on the 300-430 
virtual slices from the 3D reconstruction images of the 
six samples. Although conventional desktop µ-CT cannot 
distinguish the complex shaped tissues with similar densi-
ties, such as regenerated bone, SR-µCT visualizes the bone 
regeneration pattern and spatial organization of the hard </p>

<p>tissue structures and is an excellent tool for examining the 
3D microarchitecture. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Patient selection </p>

<p>Partially edentulous patients with at least one posterior 
upper tooth missing were selected with a residual bone 
height between 1.5 and 4.5 mm. The exclusion criteria were 
all systemic and local factors interfering with bone or soft 
tissue healing. Patients with metabolic disorders, such as 
osteoporosis or diabetes, or any history of sinus diseases, 
were also excluded. Informed consent was obtained from 
all patients. </p>

<p>Sinus floor augmentation for implant 
placement and biopsy </p>

<p>All patients were treated by the same surgeon using the 
lateral approach. After flap elevation, an osteotomy on the 
lateral wall of the maxilla was performed to create a window. 
The space created between the maxillary alveolar process 
and the elevated Schneiderian membrane was filled using 
deproteinized bovine bone (Bio-Oss </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Geistlich Pharma AG, 
Wolhusen, Switzerland). To avoid infections, the patients 
received Augmentin 
® 625 mg, Etodin 
® 200 mg, and Stilen </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>1 T daily over a 7-day period. 
After 6 months of uneventful healing, the implant sites 
were prepared with trephine burs (3.0 mm outer diameter, 
2.0 mm inner diameter) to obtain bone cores from the 
implant sites (vertical biopsies). In each patient, one biopsy 
was harvested at one of the sites, where a dental implant 
was to be placed (Table 1). The bone specimens were fixed 
in 4% neutral-buffered paraformaldehyde and used for the 
conventional histological, histomorphometric, and SR-µCT 
investigations. The specimen contained both a grafted area 
and a residual alveolar process. The residual native bone 
was included in the histological examination, but not in the 
histomorphometric and SR-µCT analyses. In the analysis, 
the interested volume and area were approximately 3 mm 
(height) ×2 mm (diameter) for SR-µCT and approximately 
3 mm (height) ×2 mm (width) for histomorphometric analysis 
in the grafted area at each of the six samples. The upper part 
of Figure 2 presents a schematic diagram of the experimental 
procedure. </p>

<p>Synchrotron X-ray micro-computed 
tomography </p>

<p>SR-µCT was performed at the Bio-Medical Imaging Beam-
line 6C of the Pohang Light Source-II in Pohang, Korea. This 
beamline provides a monochromatic beam of a relatively </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 (Special Issue on diverse applications in Nano-Theranostics) </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>Bone dynamics in the upward direction </p>

<p>large spectral bandwidth (∆E/E) of approximately 1% using 
multilayer mirrors. The mirrors were coated with 26 (±0.5) Å 
thick bilayers of tungsten and boron carbide (Incoatec GmbH, 
Geesthacht, Germany). The mirror manipulator system, oth-
erwise called the double multilayer monochromator, is capa-
ble of tuning the X-ray photon energy between 10 and 55 keV 
(Vactron Inc., Daegu, Korea). In all, 23 keV was chosen 
for this experiment and was illuminated on the sample that 
had been mounted on a stack of precision rotation (ABRS; </p>

<p>Aerotech, PA, USA) and linear stages (LYS-9013, Vactron 
Inc.). The transmitting beam was recorded using a detector 
system (MICRX030; Optique Peter, Lentilly, France) opti-
cally coupling a scintillator screen of 50 µm thick YAG:Ce 
(Crytur, Turnov, Czech Republic) to a scientific CMOS cam-
era Zyla (Andor, Belfast, UK, 3,900×2,400 pixels). The field 
of view was 4.0 mm × 3.4 mm, with an effective pixel size 
of 1.6 µm. The sample-to-detector distance was set to 20 cm. 
For the tomographic scan, 360 projection images were taken 
at each 0.5° sample rotation from 0° to 180°. The exposure 
time per projection was 0.2 second. Figure 1 presents the 
treatment site and schematic layout of the setup. </p>

<p>Image processing and segmentation 
analysis </p>

<p>The quantitative degree of bone regeneration was analyzed 
based on the virtual slices taken from the serial slice image 
segmentation every 8 µm from the cross-sectional images 
of the 3D reconstructions along the longitudinal direction. </p>

<p>Figure 1 The procedure of Maxillary sinus floor elevation. 
Notes: The x-ray image of the treatment site (A) before and (B) after 6 months of maxillary sinus floor elevation, human biopsy specimens were obtained from bone cores 
of the implant sites. The red and yellow arrows indicate treatment sites. (C) Flow diagram summarizing the study design. 
Abbreviations: 3D, three-dimensional; PBS, phosphate-buffered saline; Sr-µcT, synchrotron radiation X-ray micro-computed tomography. </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary of sample information </p>

<p>Specimen 
Graft site 
(tooth number) </p>

<p>Sex 
(age) </p>

<p>After OP 
(month) </p>

<p>S1 
#24 
F (59) 
6 
S2 
#25 
F (59) 
6 
S3 
#26 
F (59) 
6 
S4 
#17 
M (33) 
6 
S5 
#16 
M (54) 
6 
S6 
#17 
M (54) 
6 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: F, female; M, male; OP, operation. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 (Special Issue on diverse applications in Nano-Theranostics) </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>132 </p>

<p>Seo et al </p>

<p>As a result, 300-430 virtual slices were analyzed. The 
number of slices depends on the length of the bone samples. 
The CT slice images were produced using commercial soft-
ware <rs id="software-0" type="software">Octopus</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">Version 8.4</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">inCT Co.</rs>., Aalst, Belgium) which 
implements an ordinary filtered back projection algorithm. 
The resulting images are a map of the local X-ray attenua-
tion coefficient plus the enhanced boundaries made by the 
interference of transmitting coherent X-rays. In the images, 
the newly formed bone fragments were clearly distinguished 
from the Bio-Oss 
® in the gray level. Image analysis software 
(<rs id="software-1" type="software">Amira</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 5.5</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">FEI Co.</rs>., Hillsboro, OR, USA) was used 
for 3D visualization. The slice images were noise filtered and 
then smoothed using the edge-preserving-smoothing func-
tion of the software. Segmentation was carried out based on 
the difference in the gray level between the Bio-Oss 
® and 
the newly formed bone and the volume was calculated by 
counting the number of voxels belonging to each material. At 
each slice, the measurements were performed to calculate the 
percentage (ie, area fraction) of mineralized bone, residual 
graft material, and soft tissue components. 
This study was approved by the Ethics committee of the 
Kyungpook National University Hospital. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>For all patients, perforation of the Schneiderian membrane, 
which is a frequent complication that often results in </p>

<p>incomplete bone regeneration, did not occur. No postopera-
tive complications were encountered after sinus elevation. 
Normal wound healing was observed after the surgical 
procedures. The SR-µCT method provides the ratio of the 
BS and newly generated bone every 8 µm along the longitu-
dinal direction from the serial slice images of the specimens. 
The pseudo-volume contents were observed from the area 
contents with a sufficient number of virtual slices of the 
individual specimens. 
From the 3D image sets of SR-µCT, the cross sections 
that showed close similarity to the photomicrographs could be 
identified easily. Figure 3A and B shows a 3D visualization 
image of a bone biopsy specimen acquired by SR-µCT. This 
was a whole bone specimen containing NB and BSs (Bio-
Oss </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>), newly formed bones were presented with red color, 
and BSs were present with pink color. The 3D visualization 
software that can make a cross-sectional view in the arbitrary 
direction is indispensable, as shown in Figure 3C. 
Figure 4 presents slice images of the six bone biopsy 
specimens harvested before implant placement in the graft 
area. As shown in Figure 4, the BS fractions appear lighter, 
the NB denser, and the soft tissues are invisible (black 
region). The slicing images produced differentiated the three 
major constituents of the grafted volume quite well: NB, BS 
material of Bio-Oss </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, and soft tissues. Field of the Material 
Statistics module was used to determine the grafted volume </p>

<p>Figure 2 Schematic diagrams of the Sr-µcT experiment performed at the 6c BMI beamline at PlS-II. 
Notes: a 23 keV monochromatic beam was attenuated by a graphite attenuator and the beam propagated 15 cm from sample to a Yag:ce 50 µm. The images stored in 
a ccD camera were transferred to a Pc for further data processing. Morphometric analysis by Sr-µcT was performed using a reconstruction of the 2D cross sections of 
the sample or 3D image visualization of the sample. 
Abbreviations: BMI, biomedical imaging; ccD, charge-coupled device; cT, computed tomography; 2D, two-dimensional; 3D, three-dimensional; gPU, graphics processing 
unit; PlS-II, pohang light source II; Sr-µcT, synchrotron radiation X-ray micro-computed tomography; Pc, personal computer. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 (Special Issue on diverse applications in Nano-Theranostics) </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>Bone dynamics in the upward direction </p>

<p>Figure 3 The 3D visualization image of bone biopsy specimen acquired by Sr-µcT. 
Notes: Whole bone specimen containing bone substitutes (Bio-Oss 
® ), newly formed bone (red), bone substitutes (Bio-Oss 
® , pink). (A) Side view, (B) top view, and 
(C) cross section. 
Abbreviations: Sr-µcT, synchrotron radiation X-ray micro-computed tomography; 3D, three-dimensional. </p>

<p>Figure 4 cross-sectional images of the six specimens (S1-S6). 
Notes: The major components, new bone (dark-colored region), Bio-Oss 
® (light-colored region), and soft tissue (black region), were presented. </p>

<p>statistics for each sample. Once a structure is segmented, the 
function easily measures its volume and area. This module 
takes a uniform or stacked label field as well as an optional 
scalar field as the input and computes some of the statistical 
quantities for the regions defined in the label field: </p>

<p>Area percentage </p>

<p>per slice (%) 
N 
= 
× 
⋅ 
⋅ 
Pixel (width height) 
1 
πr </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>100 
⋅ 
(%) </p>

<p>N (NB): number of pixels inside the NB area in a slice; 
N (BS): number of pixels inside the BS area in a slice; 
r: radius of the sample cross section. </p>

<p>In the mode of volume or area per slice, the slices were 
stored as results (N) in the spreadsheet. The results were 
labeled by the materials and the volume of these materials 
in each slice. The same output was produced by the area 
per slice mode. In both cases, the voxel size was used to 
calculate the value. Therefore, the area corresponds to the 
volume when multiplied by the voxel size. 
As shown in Figure 5, the ratio and distribution of NB 
and BSs were measured every 8 µm from six specimens. 
The 3D reconstructed images of each specimen are shown 
in the background of the graph, which was correlated with 
each sliced position. As a result, the bone dynamics between </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 (Special Issue on diverse applications in Nano-Theranostics) </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>134 </p>

<p>Seo et al </p>

<p>Figure 5 regenerated bone area versus slice number. each slice was sampled at every 8 µm. 
Notes: The background images show the 3D reconstructed images of six specimens (S1-S6) and the positions are correlated with the slice numbers. Whole bone specimen 
containing bone substitutes (Bio-Oss 
® ), newly formed bone (red), and bone substitutes (Bio-Oss 
® , white). 
Abbreviation: 3D, three-dimensional. </p>

<p>NB and BSs along the inferior-superior direction in human 
after MSFE can be analyzed using the whole sample region. 
One advantage of using SR-µCT is that the information it 
provides is the full sample region without physical proce-
dures to obtain an H&amp;E photomicrograph. The specimen 
was analyzed in the cross-sectional position, and the analysis 
readily extends to the entire volume. This suggests that the 
specimen is structurally inhomogeneous. The positional 
variation of the NB and BS fractions clearly indicates that 
the entire graft is not as homogeneous. Previous CT studies 
also revealed differences but they were not as large as in the 
present study. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study was a pilot study to analyze the bone dynamics 
in the sinus upward direction after MSFE. Most previous 
studies 
12-16 reported the total evaluation of the bone dynamics 
with a limited number of conventional histology with vari-
ous BSs and biomaterials, and the quantitative observation 
of bone dynamics within the whole volume of specimen is 
quite limited. 
The conventional histology using the H&amp;E photo-
graph is the standard method for examining the interface 
between the NB and BSs in the field of conductivity and 
osteoinductivity. 
17,18 The conventional method provides </p>

<p>cellular details and other information on the bone dynamics. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>On the other hand, the results analyzed based on the limited 
number of two-dimensional sections can be incomplete and 
misleading due the 3D aspects of the actual tissue sample. 
Recently, 3D observations of the tissue sample can be pos-
sible using µCT. </p>

<p>19-21 </p>

<p>This paper presented an approach to evaluate human bone 
biopsy specimens by high-flux SR-µCT. Using SR-µCT, the 
bone dynamics of human bone were observed directly along 
the inferior-superior direction after 6 months of MSFE and 
6 months after the sinus floor elevation, it was confirmed that 
bone augmentation in maxillary sinus had been performed suc-
cessfully. Each specimen had different amounts of Bio-Oss </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>remaining and different NB:BS ratios after 6 months of MSFE. 
The entire graft was not as homogeneous, even in the indi-
vidual specimens. On the other hand, the ratio of NB was much 
higher in the positions where the BSs had been applied than 
one in the untreated regions. This suggests that the region with 
BSs can be changed to the NB region, even though the speed 
of the transition differs according to the position and status 
of the patients. From this observation, the MSFE technique is 
quite reliable for the placement of dental implants in deficient 
bone areas of the posterior region of the maxilla. 
Different bone dynamics between the specimen of the 
upper and lower parts of sinus floor are expected due to </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 (Special Issue on diverse applications in Nano-Theranostics) </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>135 </p>

<p>Bone dynamics in the upward direction </p>

<p>the different environment near the BSs. In other words, 
the upper part should have less effect from the cell, which 
builds a bone structure including osteoblasts, than the 
lower parts. On the other hand, no significant difference 
was observed between the two parts in terms of the bone 
dynamics. 
These results can have two explanations. First, the 
observation region was limited to 3 mm along the upper 
direction, which is not a sufficient length scale to observe 
the difference between the upper and lower parts. This can 
be overcome by extending the observation region to 15 mm 
in the next experimental design. Second, the maturation 
period, 6 months recovery time, was too long to observe the 
early behavior of the BSs. To exclude this situation, different 
maturation periods can be applied to observe the early stages 
of bone regeneration. In addition, compaction of bone dur-
ing the process using a trephine bur can occur easily due to 
differences in the bone density between the sponge bone and 
the compact bone. This would make it difficult to observe 
the difference between the upper and lower parts. Therefore, 
more study will be needed to determine the correlation with 
the position along the upper direction. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Using synchrotron radiation, quantitative analysis of the 
bone dynamics of the whole volume of six specimens in 
human bones was performed 6 months after MSFE. The 
continuous bone regeneration pattern including the ratio 
and distribution of NB and BSs were measured every 8 µm 
from each specimen. In this study, the maxillary sinus floor 
elevation was confirmed to be a reliable surgical procedure 
that aims to increase the amount of bone. The use of SR-µCT 
is quite effective for obtaining high-resolution images due 
to the phase-contrast effect of synchrotron radiation. High-
throughput analysis of maxillary sinus floor elevation can be 
performed with high accuracy without the 3-week complex 
sample preparation procedure. An analysis of biological 
specimens using SR-µCT is quite reliable, and this technique 
would be a very important tool in the wide field of tissue 
engineering. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This research was supported by Kyungpook National Uni-
versity Research Fund, 2013 (2014). This research was 
supported by Basic Science Research Program through 
the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded 
by the Ministry of Science, ICT and Future Planning 
(No 2013005417). This work was supported by the National </p>

<p>Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) grant funded by the 
Korea government (MSIP, 2008-0062282). </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-nanomedicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of Nanomedicine is an international, peer-
reviewed journal focusing on the application of nanotechnology 
in diagnostics, therapeutics, and drug delivery systems throughout 
the biomedical field. This journal is indexed on PubMed Central, 
MedLine, CAS, SciSearch®, Current Contents®/Clinical Medicine, </p>

<p>Journal Citation Reports/Science Edition, EMBase, Scopus and the 
Elsevier Bibliographic databases. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system, which is all easy to use. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of Nanomedicine 2015:10 (Special Issue on diverse applications in Nano-Theranostics) </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>