<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4468621" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Pain, a common phenomenon in multiple sclerosis (MS) patients, is associated with many symptoms 
and problems. 
Aim: To investigation severity and distribution of musculoskeletal pain in MS patients. </p>

<p>Methods: In this cross-sectional study, 115 members of the Mazandaran MS Association with confirmed MS were 
randomly selected to participate in the study. The patients were asked to fill out Numerical Rating Score and Nodric 
questionnaires, respectively. The data was analyzed by SPSS ver. 16 software. </p>

<p>Results: The mean age of the participants was 30.43±5.86 years and 88 cases (76.5%) were female. The mean 
disease duration was 26.34±24.32 months and 87.8% of the cases were experiencing pain at the time of study. The 
mean pain severity was 3.75±2.25 and worst pain experienced was 5.73±2.12. The most common pain sites were: the 
knees (55.7%), wrist (43.5%), and neck (41.7%). Women experience higher prevalence of shoulder, upper back, and 
ankle pain (P&lt;0.05). In 62 cases (53.91%) MS interfered with daily functioning at least for a time. The prevalence of 
upper back and neck pain was higher in cases with a shorter disease duration (P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Conclusions: Pain was very common in patients with MS and not relevant to sex or age. In the majority of the cases 
more than 1 limb was involved and the prevalence of pain in the lower limbs was higher, especially in the knees. In 
females, the prevalence of pain in the shoulders, upper back, and ankle was higher compared to males. Also, neck and 
upper-back pain were found in the early stages of the disease. </p>

<p>Key words: Multiple sclerosis, Musculoskeletal pain, Pain measurement </p>

<p>SEVERITY AND DISTRIBUTION OF MUSCULOSKELETAL PAIN IN MULTIPLE 
SCLEROSIS PATIENTS </p>

<p>THE ARCHIVES OF BONE AND JOINT SURGERY. ABJS.MUMS.AC.IR 
VOLUME 3. NUMBER 2. APRIL 2015 </p>

<p>)115( </p>

<p>Pain conditions associated with MS are classified into 
4 major groups: continuous central neuropathic pain, 
intermittent central neuropathic pain, musculoskeletal 
pain, and mixed neuropathic and non-neuropathic 
pain, which have not been investigated thoroughly (8). 
Thus, this study aimed to investigate the severity and 
prevalence of musculoskeletal pain in MS patients in 
the Mazandaran Province (north of Iran) in 2013. </p>

<p>Methods 
Study design and population 
This cross sectional study's sample size requirement 
was based on Michalski et al.'s study and a considered 
of 5% error and 80% power was calculated for 
115 patients (11). Members of the Mazandaran MS 
Association, who had an established diagnosis of MS, 
were randomly entered into this study. This study 
was a questionnaire based cross sectional study and 
patients participated with full awareness. However, 
we respected the privacy of the patients and assured 
them that their information would be held under legal 
obligations of confidentiality. Also, this research was 
approved by the ethical committee of the Mazandaran 
University of Medical Science. </p>

<p>Data collection 
Data was collected by interviews and questionnaires. 
The Numeric Rating Scale questionnaire was used 
to measure pain severity (from 0 to 100). Thereby, 0 
represents no pain and 100 the worst painful sensation. 
This questionnaire consists of 3 questions to explore 
the cases´ current pain severity, highest rate of pain 
severity, and the average pain severity on the seventh </p>

<p>day preceding the interview. 
The Nordic musculoskeletal questionnaire (NMQ-E) 
was used to investigate the cases of musculoskeletal 
pain. This questionnaire consisted of questions about 
the existence and duration of limb pain including neck, 
shoulders, elbow, wrist, upper back, back, hip, thigh, 
and knee (12). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The difference in percentages (qualitative variables) 
was analyzed using the X2 test. Student´s t-test was 
used to estimate standard deviation and the data was 
analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 16</rs> software. A P value of 
˂0.05 was considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
Among the 115 participants with a mean age of 
30.43±5.86 years (range: 18-52) 27 cases (23.5%) 
were male. In this study, the percentage of females 
to males was 3.25. The disease duration of 75 cases 
(65.2%) was less than 2 years and in 40 cases (34.8%) 
it was more than 2 years. The mean disease duration 
was 26.34±24.32 months (range: 7.5-200 months). 
The frequency of musculoskeletal pain is shown in 
Table 1. According to these results, the most common 
limb pains were observed in the knee (55.7%), wrist 
(43.5%), and neck (41.7%). In the 12 months preceding 
the interview, 70 cases (60.9%) were suffering from 
chronic upper limb pain, 74 (64.3%) from lower limbs 
pain, and 53 (46.1%) from backache. In 62 cases 
(53.91%) musculoskeletal pain interfered with daily 
functioning at least for a time. 
In terms of pain in the neck, wrist, back, hip, and 
knee, there was no significant difference between men 
and women (P˃0.05). But 23.1% of men experienced </p>

<p>Table 1. Frequency (frequency percentage) of limb pain </p>

<p>Affected limbs 
12 months preceding interview 
7 days preceding interview 
Interfering with daily functioning </p>

<p>Neck pain 
48 (41.7%) 
33 (28.7%) 
18 (15.7%) </p>

<p>Shoulder pain 
40 (34.8%) 
29 (25.25) 
19 (16.5%) </p>

<p>Elbow pain 
31 (27%) 
26 (22.6%) 
21 (18.3%) </p>

<p>Wrist pain 
50 (43.5%) 
37 (32.2%) 
27 (23.5%) </p>

<p>Upper back pain 
38 (33%) 
29 (25.2%) 
19 (16.5%) </p>

<p>Backache 
44 (38.3%) 
35 (30.4%) 
26 (22.6%) </p>

<p>Hip pain 
43 (37.4%) 
33 (28.7%) 
25 (21.7%) </p>

<p>Knee pain 
64 (55.7%) 
51 (44.3%) 
34 (29.6%) </p>

<p>Ankle pain 
43 (37.4%) 
40 (34.7%) 
22 (19.1%) </p>

<p>Table 2. Mean pain severity based on MS duration </p>

<p>Pain severity 
Less than 2 
years </p>

<p>More than 2 
years 
P value </p>

<p>At the time of study 
3.66±2.22 
4.07±2.34 
0.11 </p>

<p>Mean pain severity for 
disease duration 
3.48±1.71 
4.55±1.29 
0.002 </p>

<p>Mean of the worst pain 
5.26±2.12 
6.60±1.85 
0.002 </p>

<p>Table 3. Mean pain severity based on the sex of MS patients </p>

<p>Pain severity score 
Males 
Females 
P value </p>

<p>At the time of study 
3.33±1.75 
3.63±2.50 
0.55 </p>

<p>Average pain severity 
3.48±1.31 
3.96±1.73 
0.18 </p>

<p>Mean of the worst pain 
5.37±1.64 
5.84±2.24 
0.31 </p>

<p>SEVERITY AND DISTRIBUTION OF MUSCULOSKELETAL PAIN IN MULTIPLE 
SCLEROSIS PATIENTS </p>

<p>THE ARCHIVES OF BONE AND JOINT SURGERY. ABJS.MUMS.AC.IR 
VOLUME 3. NUMBER 2. APRIL 2015 </p>

<p>)116( </p>

<p>shoulder pain; 66.6% in the right shoulder, 16.7% in 
the left shoulder, and 16.7% in both shoulders. Also, 
38.6% of women experienced shoulder pain; 17.64% 
in the right shoulder, 47.05% in the left shoulder, 
and 35.29% in both shoulders. Thus, a significant 
difference was observed between men and women in 
regards to shoulder pain (P=0.043). Upper back pain 
was experienced in 40.2% of women and 11.5% of men. 
Women had more back pain and the chance of upper 
back pain for women was 5.16 times more than men 
(OR: 5.16, &amp; 95%, CI: 1.43-18.50, P=0.007). In addition, 
the prevalence of ankle pain was 45.5% in women and 
22.2% in men. In women, the prevalence of ankle pain 
was significantly higher compared with men, and ankle 
pain in women was 2.19 times more than men (OR: 
2.19, 95%, CI:1.07-7.92, P=0.031). 
The results showed that the mean disease duration 
for cases experiencing neck pain on the seventh 
day preceding the interview was significantly lower 
compared with others (17.69±9.1 vs. 31.98±29.82 
months) (P=0.035). Also, the mean disease duration for 
patients with upper back pain was significantly lower 
compared with others (17.24±9.17 vs. 31.45±29.62 
months) (P=0.039). But the mean disease duration 
for patients whose knee pain interfered with their 
daily functioning was significantly higher compared 
with others (44.00±39.17 vs. 20.78±14.79 months) 
(P=0.001). No statistically significant difference was 
observed between the mean disease duration and 
other limb pains (P˃0.05). 
According to the results of the Numeric Rating Scale 
questionnaire, the point of prevalence of pain in patients 
was 87.8% (101 patients). Also, mean pain severity was 
3.75±2.25 at the time of this study; 3.33±1.75 for males 
and 3.63±2.50 for females (P=0.55). Mean pain severity 
was 3.66±2.22 for cases whose onset of MS was more 
than 2 years and 4.07±2.34 for those less than 2 years 
(r: 0.13, P=0.11). The average pain score was 3.85±1.65; 
3.96±1.73 for females and 3.48±1.31 for males. For 
those whose onset of MS was under 2 years the average 
pain score was 3.48±1.71 and for those over 2 years 
it was 4.55±1.29. There was a significant correlation 
between mean pain severity and disease duration 
(P=0.002, r: 0.25). In fact, there was no statistically 
significant difference between females and males in 
the average pain score (P=0.18). Also, the patients were 
asked to rank their worst pain from 0 to 100. The mean 
of the worst pain was 5.73±2.12; 5.37±1.64 for males 
and 5.84±2.24 for females (P=0.31) (Table 2 and 3). The 
mean of the worst pain was 5.26±2.12 for the patients 
whose onset of MS was less than 2 years and 6.60±1.85 
for those more than 2 years. A significant correlation 
was observed between disease duration and patients' 
worst pain (r: 0.25, P=0.002). </p>

<p>Discussion 
Multiple sclerosis is a chronic demyelinating and 
progressive disease of the central nervous system. Its 
incidence rate is reported not needed 2.5 per 100,000 
and its prevalence rate is 2.5 million cases worldwide 
(13-16). Approximately half of MS patients are affected </p>

<p>with pain and nearly three-quarters of patients report 
having had pain within the preceding month (8). 
According to this study, the prevalence of pain was 
87.8% and the prevalence of pain reported by Michalski 
et al. and Svendsen et al. was 81.6% and 79.4%, 
respectively, which is in concordance with our results 
(11, 6). According to several other studies the prevalence 
of pain in MS ranges from 29 to 86 (8). It is reported 
that the difference between points of prevalence in 
the studies is due to differences in definitions of pain, 
type of pain, sample size, survey technique, and tools 
of data collection (17-21). According to the literature, 
pain interferes with MS patients´ daily functioning and 
dramatically affects patients´ quality of life (22, 23). 
The risk factors reported to be associated with MS 
are age, disease duration, course of the disease, and 
physical disability of patients (21). In this study only 
disease duration significantly correlated with pain 
severity, but no significant correlation was observed 
between pain severity and age or sex. Similar to our 
study, some studies reported that only certain risk 
factors correlated with pain severity in MS patients, 
but others reported discrepant results (5, 22, 24-26). 
Solaro et al. conducted a study on pain severity of a 
large sample size of MS patients and reported that there 
was a significant correlation between pain severity 
and disease duration and age (5). They reported that 
females experienced more pain compared with males 
(24). This result was not in concordance with our 
study, but several studies similar to our study showed 
that males and females experienced almost the same 
pain severity (5, 25, 27-29). 
Similar to several other studies, we applied the 
Numeric rating score questionnaire to evaluate 
patients´ pain severity. In two studies, patients reported 
pain severity as mild (mean: 2.8), but 4 of them rated 
pain severity from 4.8 to 5.8, which was close to our 
results (6, 22, 27-30). 
In MS patients, limb pains were classified as continuous 
central neuropathic and back pain as neuromuscular 
pain (31). Similar to our study, Svendsen et al. reported 
that several patients experienced more than one limb 
pain simultaneously. Also, they observed that the most 
commonly affected limbs were lower limbs (96%), back 
(70%), and upper limbs (52%) (23). Osterberg et al. 
reported that among the patients suffering from central 
pain, the point of prevalence of lower limb pain was 
87% and upper limb pain was 31% (26). In this study 
the point of prevalence of lower limb pain and back pain 
was lower compared to the study of Osterberg et al., 
but still the point of prevalence of the lower limbs was 
higher compared with other limbs (26). In addition, the 
point of prevalence of pain in the shoulder, upper back, 
and ankle was higher in females compared with males. 
A significant result of this study was that the point of 
prevalence of neck and upper back pain was higher in 
MS patients with shorter disease duration. Neck pain 
of MS patients is represented according to Lhermitte´s 
sign, which is defined as feeling a transmit short lasing 
pain in the back of the neck and lower back associated 
with neck movements. It is reported that the point </p>

<p>SEVERITY AND DISTRIBUTION OF MUSCULOSKELETAL PAIN IN MULTIPLE 
SCLEROSIS PATIENTS </p>

<p>THE ARCHIVES OF BONE AND JOINT SURGERY. ABJS.MUMS.AC.IR 
VOLUME 3. NUMBER 2. APRIL 2015 </p>

<p>)117( </p>



<p>Masoud ShayestehAzar MD 
Mohammad Hossein Kariminasab MD 
Majid Sajjadi Saravi MD 
Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Imam Khomeini 
Hospital, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, 
Sari, Iran </p>

<p>Mahmoud Abedini MD 
Department of Neurology, Bu Ali Teaching Hospital, 
Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, Iran </p>

<p>Mehran Fazli MD 
Imam Khomeini Hospital of Esfarayen, Esfarayen Faculty 
of Medical Sciences, Esfarayen, Iran </p>

<p>Seyyed Abbas Hashemi MD 
Pedram Abdizadeh MD 
Faculty of Medicine, Student Research Committee, 
Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, Iran </p>

<p>of prevalence of neck pain can be up to 40%. In most 
patients, the symptoms resolve over 4-6 weeks, but in 
some it may recur during MS exacerbations (8). 
The results show that pain is a very common 
phenomenon in MS patients living in the Mazandaran 
province. Pain prevalence is not correlated with sex and 
age, but there is a significant correlation between pain 
incidence and disease duration. In most patients, more 
than one limb are affected with pain simultaneously. 
Also, the point of prevalence of lower limb pain is higher, 
especially knee pain. The prevalence of shoulder, upper 
back and ankle pain was higher in females compared 
with males. Moreover, the prevalence of upper back 
pain and neck pain was higher in MS patients with a 
shorter disease duration. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements 
We are grateful for being allowed to access the 
official archives of the members of the Mazandaran MS 
Association and for their help in collecting the data. </p>

<p>SEVERITY AND DISTRIBUTION OF MUSCULOSKELETAL PAIN IN MULTIPLE 
SCLEROSIS PATIENTS </p>

<p>THE ARCHIVES OF BONE AND JOINT SURGERY. ABJS.MUMS.AC.IR 
VOLUME 3. NUMBER 2. APRIL 2015 </p>

<p>)118( </p>



</text></tei>