<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4274470" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Asthma is a common chronic disease, affecting at least 300 
million people worldwide. 
1 It can develop at any age and is 
known to be associated with genetic, environmental, nutrition-
al, and socioeconomic factors. 
2,3 Some known risk factors for 
adult-onset asthma are female sex, atopy, nasal allergy, family 
history, and high-risk occupations. 
4,5 The population-attribut-
able risk for adult asthma due to occupational exposure is 
thought to be 10%-25%. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Work-related asthma (WRA) refers to the exacerbation of pre-
existing or concurrent asthma in the workplace, as well as to 
new-onset asthma induced by sensitizers or irritants present in 
the workplace. 
6 It is the most common work-related respiratory 
disease in industrialized countries, 
7,8 and the second most 
common in Korea after pneumoconiosis. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>The first case of WRA in Korea was identified in a sea squirt 
processing factory in 1976. 
10 Many more cases and causal agents </p>

<p>Work-Related Asthma in Korea -Findings from the Korea Work-
Related Asthma Surveillance (KOWAS) program, 2004-2009 </p>

<p>Soon-Chan Kwon, 
1 Jaechul Song, </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>* Yong-kyu Kim, 
2 Geoffrey M. Calvert </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, Hanyang University, Seoul, Korea </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Center for Occupational and Environmental medicine, Daejeon Sun Hospital, Daejeon, Korea 
3 National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health, Cincinnati, Ohio, USA </p>

<p>have been reported since, with isocyanates and reactive dyes 
being the most common agents. 
11-13 Before the Korea Work-Re-
lated Asthma Surveillance (KOWAS) program began in 2004, 
apart from a temporary WRA surveillance program conducted 
for 1 year in 1998, the only method to systematically estimate 
the number of WRA cases in Korea was by extracting data from 
workers' compensation schemes. 
14 This report provides find-
ings from the first 6 years of the KOWAS program (2004-2009). 
We used KOWAS data to estimate the incidence of WRA by ex-
amining various demographic factors and to identify the distri-
bution of causal agents over the study period. </p>

<p>Purpose: To determine the incidence and epidemiological characteristics of work-related asthma in Korea. Methods: During 2004-2009, the Korea 
Work-Related Asthma Surveillance (KOWAS) program collected data on new cases of work-related asthma from occupational physicians, allergy 
and chest physicians, regional surveillance systems, and workers' compensation schemes. The incidence was calculated on the basis of industry, 
occupation, sex, age, and region. In addition, the distribution of causal agents was determined. Results: During the study period, 236 cases of work-
related asthma were reported, with 77 cases from more than 1 source. A total of 22.0% (n = 52) were reported by occupational physicians, 52.5% 
(n = 124) by allergy and chest physicians, 24.2% (n = 57) by regional surveillance systems, and 43.2% (n = 102) by workers' compensation schemes. 
The overall average annual incidence was 3.31 cases/million workers, with a rate of 3.78/million among men and 2.58/million among women. The 
highest incidence was observed in the 50-59-year age group (7.74/million), in the Gyeonggi/Incheon suburb of Seoul (8.50/million), in the furniture 
and other instrument manufacturing industries (67.62/million), and among craft and related trades workers (17.75/million). The most common caus-
al agents were isocyanates (46.6%), flour/grain (8.5%), metal (5.9%), reactive dyes (5.1%), and solvents (4.2%). Conclusions: The incidence of 
work-related asthma in Korea was relatively low, and varied according to industry, occupation, gender, age, and region. Data provided by workers' 
compensation schemes and physician reports have been useful for determining the incidence and causes of work-related asthma. </p>

<p>Key Words: Work-related asthma; incidence; surveillance; industry; occupation </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits 
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Jaechul Song, MD, PhD, Department of Occupational 
and Environmental Medicine, Hanyang University College of Medicine, 
222 Wangsimni-ro, Seongdong-gu, Seoul 133-791, Korea. 
Tel: +82-2-2220-0663; Fax: +82-2-2220-4663; E-mail: jsong@hanyang.ac.kr 
Received: April 7, 2014; Revised: June 23, 2014; Accepted: July 7, 2014 </p>

<p>•There are no financial or other issues that might lead to conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2015 January;7(1):51-59. 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4168/aair.2015.7.1.51 
pISSN 2092-7355 • eISSN 2092-7363 </p>

<p>Kwon et al. </p>

<p>Volume 7, Number 1, January 2015 </p>

<p>52 http://e-aair.org </p>

<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2015 January;7(1):51-59. http://dx.doi.org/10.4168/aair.2015.7.1.51 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The establishment of KOWAS 
KOWAS is a scheme designed to collect information on WRA 
cases from multiple reporting sources. It was set up in 2004 by 
the Occupational Safety and Health Research Institute of the 
Korea Occupational Safety and Health Agency (OSHRI-KO-
SHA). The Department of Occupational and Environmental 
Medicine of Hanyang University was selected as the KOWAS 
program's headquarters. 
The scheme's reporting sources include the Korea Workers' 
Compensation and Welfare Service, occupational physicians, 
allergy and chest physicians, and regional work-related disease 
surveillance systems (i.e. regional surveillance systems that are 
housed in universities and funded by the KOSHA </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>). At the start 
of the program, there were 42 participating allergy and chest 
physicians, most of whom were affiliated with university hospi-
tals. There were also 30 participating occupational health physi-
cians or institutions, which included members of the Korean As-
sociation of Occupational and Environmental Clinics (KOEC). 
Regional surveillance systems located in the cities of Gumi, 
Incheon, Busan, and Changwon participated in the scheme in 
2004, but from 2005 to 2007, only the systems in Incheon and 
Busan continued their participation. None of the regional sur-
veillance systems participated after 2007. </p>

<p>Reporting individual cases 
Individual patients were written up as case reports and sent to 
the KOWAS program headquarters. Each case report included 
the patient's sex, age, geographic location, occupation type, and 
exposure duration. In addition, the suspected causal agent, 
dates of asthma onset and diagnosis, whether it was new-onset 
versus exacerbation of preexisting asthma, and whether objec-
tive diagnostic tests had been conducted were also reported. </p>

<p>Definitions 
There are 2 sub-types of WRA: (1) work-exacerbated asthma 
(WEA) and (2) new-onset occupational asthma (OA). New-on-
set OA is further divided into sensitizer-induced OA and irri-
tant-induced OA, including reactive airways dysfunction syn-
drome (RADS). 
16 The definition of WRA proposed by the Na-
tional Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH) 
was used in our study. 
17 Thus, all WRA cases satisfied criteria (A) 
and (B) listed below. In addition, all cases satisfied 1 or more of 
the following criteria: (A) Diagnosis of asthma by a physician, 
(B) An association between the symptoms of asthma and work, 
(1) Workplace exposure to an agent or process previously asso-
ciated with WRA, (2) Significant work-related changes in forced 
expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) or peak expiratory flow 
rate (PEFR), (3) Significant work-related changes in airways re-
sponsiveness measured by a nonspecific inhalation challenge 
test, (4) A positive response to an inhalation challenge test with </p>

<p>a specific agent to which the individual is exposed at work. 
The work-relatedness of WRA was classified as "definite" (sat-
isfied the following elements of the case definition: A, B, 1, plus 
≥2 of criteria 2-4), "probable" (A, B, 1, plus 1 of criteria 2-4), 
"possible" (A, B, did not satisfy 1 but satisfied ≥1 of criteria 2-4), 
and "suspicious" (A and B only) by the reporting source. </p>

<p>13,18 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The average annual incidence of WRA with regard to sex, age, 
region, industry, and occupation was based on the size of the 
working population as estimated in 2006 by the Korean Minis-
try of Employment and Labor, 
19,20 and 95% confidence intervals 
(CIs) were based on Poisson distribution. Industries and occu-
pations were classified using the eighth Korean Standard In-
dustrial Classification (KSIC), 
21 and the fifth Korean Standard 
Classification of Occupations (KSCO), 
22 respectively. 
Capture-recapture analysis was used to obtain a nearly unbi-
ased estimator (NUE) of the total number of WRA cases. 
23 To do 
this, the 4 reporting sources were stratified into 2 categories as 
follows: (1) the workers' compensation scheme (i.e. the Korea 
Workers' Compensation and Welfare Service), and (2) the other 
3 reporting sources (i.e. physicians' reports). Capture-recapture 
analysis was performed on specific industries and occupations 
when the number of overlapping reports was ≥7. Overlapping 
reports, i.e. duplicate cases, were defined as individuals who 
had identical names, dates of birth, resident registration num-
bers, and employers found in both reporting categories. 
The distribution of WRA cases based on sex, causal agent, 
WRA subtype, and reporting source were described over the 
study period, and annual trends were tested using the Cochran-
Armitage test for trend. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>., Cary, NC, 
USA) was used to perform all statistical analyses. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>From 2004 to 2009, a total of 239 cases of WRA were reported 
to the KOWAS, but 3 cases were excluded from analyses be-
cause the workplaces associated with these cases were not in-
cluded in the working population in this study. A total of 236 
cases were reported by 4 reporting sources: 52 (22.0%) by occu-
pational physicians, 124 (52.5%) by allergy and chest physicians, 
102 (43.2%) by workers' compensation schemes, and 57 (24.2%) 
by regional surveillance systems. Although some cases were re-
ported multiple times by different sources and in different years, 
each individual was counted only once. A total of 164 (69.5%) 
cases were men, and 72 (30.5%) were women. The overall mean 
age was 44.1 (±11.0) years, and the mean age for men (43.4± 
11.5 years) and women (45.6±9.5 years) were not significantly 
different. The highest frequencies of WRA were found among 
the 40-49 and 50-59-year-olds (31.4% and 26.3%, respectively). 
WRA was determined as "definite" in 58.1% of all cases (n=137), 
"probable" in 36.4% (n=86), "possible" in 4.2% (n=10), and </p>

<p>Work-Related Asthma in Korea 
AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>



<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2015 January;7(1):51-59. http://dx.doi.org/10.4168/aair.2015.7.1.51 </p>

<p>"suspicious" in 1.3% (n=3). According to the WRA sub-types, 
new-onset asthma was most frequent (92.4%, n=218) with sen-
sitizer-induced OA responsible for the vast majority at 86.9% of 
the total number of cases (n=205), followed by irritant-induced 
OA at 5.5% (n=13). WEA was responsible for 3.8% (n=9) of 
WRA cases. KOWAS had information regarding the specific ob-
jective tests that met the work-relatedness criteria for only 81 
cases. Among these cases, 13 (16.0%) had work-related serial 
changes of PEFR or FEV1, 3 (3.7%) had work-related serial 
changes of nonspecific challenge tests, and 72 (88.9%) had a 
positive response to specific challenge tests. Objective tests 
were performed on the other 152 cases which were classified as </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of work-related asthma cases -Korea, 2004-2009 </p>

<p>Cases n (%) 
Age, 
Mean±SD </p>

<p>Study population 
236 (100.0) 
44.1±11.0 
Sex 
Male 
164 (69.5) 
43.4±11.5 
Female 
72 (30.5) 
45.6±9.5 
Age (years) 
20-29 
30 (12.7) 
30-39 
52 (22.0) 
40-49 
74 (31.4) 
50-59 
62 (26.3) 
≥60 
18 (7.6) 
Reporting source* 
Compensation scheme 
102 (43.2) 
Allergy/chest physician 
124 (52.5) 
Regional surveillance 
57 (24.2) 
Occupational physician 
52 (22.0) 
Work-relatedness 
Definite 
137 (58.1) 
Probable 
86 (36.4) 
Possible 
10 (4.2) 
Suspicious 
3 (1.3) 
WRA sub-types 
Sensitizer-induced asthma 
205 (86.9) 
Irritant-induced asthma 
13 (5.5) 
Work exacerbated asthma 
9 (3.8) 
Unknown 
9 (3.8) 
Objective test 
Nonspecific challenge test 
110 (46.6) 
Work-related change in PEFR or 
FEV1 </p>

<p>13 (5.5) </p>

<p>Work-related change in nonspecific 
challenge test </p>

<p>3 (1.3) </p>

<p>Specific challenge test 
72 (30.5) </p>

<p>*Total percentages may exceed 100 because of multiple reporting. 
WRA, work-related asthma; PEFR, peak expiratory flow rate; FEV1, forced expi-
ratory volume in one second. </p>

<p>Table 2. Distribution of physician reported and work-related asthma cases by 
institution -Korea, 2004-2009 </p>

<p>Number of 
reporting 
physicians </p>

<p>Cases 
Percent 
of cases </p>

<p>cumulative 
percent of 
cases </p>

<p>Allergy/chest clinic </p>

<p>28* 
124 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Inha University hospital </p>

<p>1 
32 
25.4 
25.4 </p>

<p>Ajou University hospital </p>

<p>8 
27 
21.4 
46.8 </p>

<p>Soonchunhyang Buceon 
hospital </p>

<p>1 
23 
18.3 
65.1 </p>

<p>Chonnam University hospital </p>

<p>2 
11 
8.7 
73.8 </p>

<p>Sevrance hospital </p>

<p>2 
9 
7.1 
81.0 </p>

<p>Seoul National University 
hospital </p>

<p>7 
7 
5.6 
86.5 </p>

<p>Wonju Sevrance Christian 
hospital </p>

<p>2 
5 
4.0 
90.5 </p>

<p>Dankook University hospital </p>

<p>1 
4 
3.2 
93.7 </p>

<p>Kangdong Sacred Heart 
hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.8 
94.4 </p>

<p>Korea University Guro hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.8 
95.2 </p>

<p>Hanyang University hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.8 
96.0 </p>

<p>Eulji hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.8 
96.8 </p>

<p>Eulji University hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.8 
97.6 </p>

<p>Bundang Jesaeng hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.8 
98.4 </p>

<p>Seoul National University 
Bundang hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.8 
99.2 </p>

<p>Ulsan University hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
0.8 
100.0 </p>

<p>Occupational clinic </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>52 </p>

<p>Hallym University Sacred 
Heart hospital </p>

<p>1 
12 
23.1 
23.1 </p>

<p>Inha University hospital </p>

<p>5 
8 
15.4 
38.5 </p>

<p>Dankook University hospital </p>

<p>1 
5 
9.6 
48.1 </p>

<p>Busan University hospital </p>

<p>1 
4 
7.7 
55.8 </p>

<p>Donga University hospital </p>

<p>2 
3 
5.8 
61.5 </p>

<p>Kosin University Gospel hospital </p>

<p>1 
3 
5.8 
67.3 </p>

<p>Eulji University hospital </p>

<p>2 
3 
5.8 
73.1 </p>

<p>Chonnam National University 
hospital </p>

<p>1 
3 
5.8 
78.8 </p>

<p>Yeouido St. Mary's hospital </p>

<p>2 
2 
3.8 
82.7 </p>

<p>Hanyang University hospital </p>

<p>2 
2 
3.8 
86.5 </p>

<p>Samsung Changwon hospital </p>

<p>1 
2 
3.8 
90.4 </p>

<p>Occupational Lung Disease 
Institute </p>

<p>1 
2 
3.8 
94.2 </p>

<p>Ulsan University hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
1.9 
96.2 </p>

<p>Gumi Cha hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
1.9 
98.1 </p>

<p>Soonchunhyang Gumi hospital </p>

<p>1 
1 
1.9 
100.0 </p>

<p>Regional surveillance system </p>

<p>13 
57 </p>

<p>Incheon: Inha University ('04-'07) </p>

<p>5 
43 
75.4 
75.4 </p>

<p>Busan: Busan University ('04-'07) </p>

<p>4 
10 
17.5 
93.0 </p>

<p>Gumi: Cha University ('04) </p>

<p>2 
2 
3.5 
96.5 </p>

<p>Changwon: Sungkyunkwan 
University ('04) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3.5 
100.0 </p>

<p>*The sum of physicians exceeds 28 because 4 physicians were employed by 
more than one hospital during the study period; </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>The sum of cases exceeds 124 
because 2 cases was reported by more than one hospital; </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>The sum of reported 
physicians exceeds 22 because one physician was employed by more than one 
hospital during the study period. </p>

<p>Kwon et al. </p>

<p>Volume 7, Number 1, January 2015 </p>



<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2015 January;7(1):51-59. http://dx.doi.org/10.4168/aair.2015.7.1.51 </p>

<p>significantly different between men and women for the 7 most 
frequently reported agents (Table 5). 
During the study period, isocyanate-related asthma followed 
a decreasing trend (P=0.002). In terms of asthma sub-types, the 
frequency of sensitizer-induced OA also followed a decreasing 
trend (P=0.008), while that of WEA appeared to be increasing 
(P=0.006), but was based on data from a very small number of 
cases. While the number of cases reported by occupational phy-
sicians and regional surveillance systems steadily decreased, 
those reported by allergy and chest physicians remained rela-
tively steady (Table 6). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The average WRA incidence of 3.31/million reported in our 
study was lower than those reported by surveillance systems in 
other countries, which ranged from 5-174/million workers. </p>

<p>7,8,24-29 </p>

<p>This difference suggests a lower prevalence of asthma in Korea 
than in other industrialized countries, 
1,3,30 and a lower propor-
tion of WRA among adult asthmatics. 
12 However, most of the 
available estimates from other industrialized countries are 
based on data from the 1990s. Since WRA surveillance in Korea 
began later than in other countries, direct comparison of rates 
should be performed with caution. In some countries (e.g. the 
UK and France), the number of WRA cases decreased during 
the 1990-2000s; possible reasons for the decrease being due to </p>

<p>Table 3. Crude and estimated average annual incidence of work-related asthma per million workers by age, sex, and region -Korea, 2004-2009 </p>

<p>Total cases 
n (%) </p>

<p>Workers' 
compensation 
reports </p>

<p>Physician 
reports* </p>

<p>Estimated 
cases </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Number of 
employees </p>

<p>Crude average 
annual incidence rate 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Estimated average 
annual incidence rate </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Study population 
236 (100.0) 
102 
173 
447 (353-541) 
11,869,493 
3.31 (2.90 -3.76) 
6.28 (4.96-7.60) 
Sex 
Male 
164 (69.5) 
70 
119 
327 (240-414) 
7,222,741 
3.78 (3.23-4.41) 
7.54 (5.53-9.55) 
Female 
72 (30.5) 
32 
54 
120 (83-157) 
4,646,752 
2.58 (2.02-3.25) 
4.30 (2.96-5.64) 
Age (years) 
20-29 
30 (12.7) 
3,115,400 
1.60 (1.08-2.29) 
30-39 
52 (22.0) 
4,054,890 
2.14 (1.60-2.80) 
40-49 
74 (31.4) 
2,860,694 
4.31 (3.39-5.41) 
50-59 
62 (26.3) 
1,334,595 
7.74 (6.16-10.21) </p>

<p>≥60 
18 (7.6) 
438,825 
6.84 (4.05-10.81) 
Region 
Seoul, Kangwon 
22 (9.3) 
3,979,140 
0.92 (0.58-1.39) 
Busan, Ulsan, Gyeongnam 
29 (12.3) 
1,959,444 
2.47 (1.65-3.54) 
Daegu, Gyeonbuk 
7 (3.0) 
1,118,725 
1.04 (0.42-2.15) 
Gyeonggi, Incheon 
133 (56.4) 
2,606,896 
8.50 (7.12-10.08) 
Gwangju, Jeonla, Jeju 
22 (9.3) 
1,121,051 
3.27 (2.05-4.95) 
Daejeon, Chungcheong 
23 (9.7) 
1,084,237 
3.54 ( 2.24-5.30) </p>

<p>*Physician reports include reports from occupational physicians, allergy and chest physicians, and regional work-related disease surveillance systems; </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Estimated cas-
es were calculated by the capture-recapture analyses by two reporting sources; </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Estimated average annual incidence rates were calculated with estimated cases. </p>

<p>nonsuspicious, but details of this testing were not provided by 
the reporting source (Table 1). 
The number of allergy and chest clinics that reported at least 1 
case was 16, and 8 of these clinics accounted for the vast majori-
ty of reports (118 [93.7%] of 126 cases). The number of occupa-
tional clinics that reported at least 1 case was 15, and 8 occupa-
tional clinics reported 41 of these cases (78.8% of 52) (Table 2). 
The average annual incidence during the 6-year period was 
3.31 per million workers. When stratified by sex, the average an-
nual incidences were 3.78/million male workers and 2.58/mil-
lion female workers. The incidence was highest in the 50-59 year 
age group at 7.74/million workers. By region, the incidence was 
highest in Gyeonggi/Incheon at 8.50/million workers, and low-
est in Seoul and Gangwon at 0.92/million workers. The number 
of cases estimated by the capture-recapture method was 447 
(95% CI: 353-541), and the corresponding average annual inci-
dence of WRA was 6.28 (95% CI: 4.96-7.60) cases/million work-
ers, approximately double the crude incidence (Table 3). By in-
dustry, the incidence was highest in the furniture and other in-
strument manufacturing industries at 67.62/million workers. By 
occupation, the incidence rate was highest in the craft and relat-
ed trades at 17.75/million workers (Table 4). 
Among the suspected causative agents of OA or triggering fac-
tors of WEA, isocyanates were the most frequent at 46.6%, fol-
lowed by flour/grain (8.5%), metals (5.9%), reactive dyes (5.1%), 
and solvents (4.2%). The distribution of causal agents was not </p>

<p>Work-Related Asthma in Korea 
AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>



<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2015 January;7(1):51-59. http://dx.doi.org/10.4168/aair.2015.7.1.51 </p>

<p>reporting fatigue, changes in industrial structure, and substitu-
tion of hazardous materials from the workplace. 
31,32 Other possi-
ble reasons for the underestimation include the workers' unwill-
ingness to report illness because of concerns about job loss, </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>lack of workers' compensation coverage among some workers 
who may be at high risk of developing WRA (e.g. self-employed 
and temporary workers are not covered, and may carry a high 
risk of developing WRA), 
33 physicians' failure to ask about work-
relatedness, and physicians' unwillingness to report to surveil-
lance schemes even when work-relatedness is suspected. 
34 Fur-
thermore, the observed differences in WRA rates between coun-
tries arise not only from differences in reporting but also from 
differences in the distribution of industries and occupations. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>The WRA incidence estimated by capture-recapture analysis 
was 6.28/million. Capture-recapture models allow the estima-
tion of the true number of cases and the assessment of the 
completeness of the surveillance data. This methodology has </p>

<p>Table 4. Crude and estimated average annual incidence of work-related asthma per million workers by industry and occupation -Korea, 2004-2009 </p>

<p>Total 
cases 
n (%) </p>

<p>Workers' 
compensation 
report </p>

<p>Physician 
report* </p>

<p>Estimated 
cases </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>(95% CI) </p>

<p>Number of 
employees </p>

<p>Crude average 
annual incidence 
rate (95% CI) </p>

<p>Estimated average 
annual incidence 
rate 
 ‡ (95% CI) </p>

<p>Study population 
236 (100.0) 
102 
173 
447 (353-541) 11,869,493 3.31 (2.90 -3.76) 
6.28 (4.96-7.60) 
Industry </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Manufacture of food &amp; beverage (15) 
21 (8.9) 
5 
16 
224,403 15.60 (9.66-23.84) 
Manufacture of wood and pulp products 
(20-21) </p>

<p>8 (3.4) 
3 
7 
97,925 13.62 (5.87-26.82) </p>

<p>Manufacture of chemicals, rubber and 
plastics (24-25) </p>

<p>43 (18.2) 
17 
30 
378,449 18.94 (13.71-25.51) </p>

<p>Metal, ceramic, and machinery (22, 26-33) 
25 (10.6) 
13 
16 
1,667,334 2.50 (1.62-3.69) 
Vehicles and transport equipment (34-35) 
42 (17.8) 
20 
32 
60 (42-77) 
389,054 17.99 (12.97-24.32) 25.49 (17.91-33.07) 
Furniture and other instruments (36) 
45 (19.1) 
23 
34 
64 (45-82) 
110,908 67.62 (49.32-90.48) 95.60 (68.30-122.90) 
Construction (45-46) 
12 (5.1) 
3 
10 
809,992 2.47 (1.28-4.31) 
Services and trades (40, 50-93) 
26 (9.7) 
11 
18 
4,836,076 0.90 (0.59-1.04) 
Occupation </p>

<p>ll </p>

<p>0. Legislators, senior officials and managers 
1 (0.4) 
0 
1 
533,857 0.31 (0.01-1.74) 
1. Professionals 
7 (3.0) 
2 
5 
1,253,016 0.93 (0.37-1.92) 
2. Technicians and associated professionals 
4 (1.7) 
1 
3 
1,736,782 0.38 (0.10-0.98) 
3. Clerks 
3 (1.3) 
1 
2 
3,309,201 0.15 (0.03-0.44) 
4. Service workers 
5 (2.1) 
0 
5 
414,545 2.01 (0.65-4.69) 
5. Sales workers 
1 (0.4) 
1 
1 
264,436 0.63 (0.02-3.51) 
6. Skilled agricultural, forestry and fishery 
workers </p>

<p>1 (0.4) 
1 
0 
17,844 9.34 (0.28-52.02) </p>

<p>7. Craft and related trades workers 
110 (46.6) 
44 
86 
185 (136-235) 1,032,887 17.75 (14.59-21.39) 29.92 (21.92-37.92) 
8. Plant workers, machine operators and 
assemblers </p>

<p>81 (34.3) 
46 
53 
133 (96-169) 
2,147,733 5.58 (4.43-6.94) 
9.14 (6.63-11.65) </p>

<p>9. Elementary occupations 
15 (6.4) 
6 
9 
533,857 4.68 (2.90-3.76) </p>

<p>*Physician reports include reports from occupational physicians, allergy and chest physicians, and regional work-related disease surveillance systems; </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Estimated 
cases were calculated by the capture-recapture analyses by two reporting sources; </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Estimated average annual incidence rates were calculated with estimated cas-
es; </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>Industries classified according to the 8th Korean Standard Industrial Classification; </p>

<p>ll </p>

<p>Occupations classified according to the 5th Korean Standard Classification of 
Occupations. </p>

<p>been used in a variety of public health areas. 
23,35 The NIOSH in 
the United States used capture-recapture methods and esti-
mated that the "true" number of WRA cases was approximately 
6-to 7-fold higher than the number reported using surveillance 
data.26 In our study, the estimated "true" number of cases was 
approximately double the reported number. 
Approximately 80.1% (n=189) of all reported WRA cases were 
found in the manufacturing sector, including furniture manu-
facturing, chemical manufacturing, vehicle manufacturing, and 
food and beverage manufacturing. The rates in these manufac-
turing industries were higher than those in almost all other in-
dustries. The WRA incidence was highest in the furniture man-
ufacturing industry (67.62/million), likely due to the high rate 
of isocyanate use, which is the leading cause in the develop-
ment of WRA. 
Workers aged ≥50 years of age had higher rates of WRA com-
pared to younger workers. This pattern has also been observed </p>

<p>Kwon et al. </p>

<p>Volume 7, Number 1, January 2015 </p>



<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2015 January;7(1):51-59. http://dx.doi.org/10.4168/aair.2015.7.1.51 </p>

<p>in previous studies 
8,24,29,36 and could be due to a combination of 
reasons. For example, older workers are more likely to have a 
longer duration of exposure to hazardous substances, and they 
may have a greater susceptibility to developing asthma. In ad-
dition, younger workers may find it easier to change jobs to 
avoid exposures, and older workers may delay reporting their 
asthma symptoms. </p>

<p>24,26,37 </p>

<p>The rates of WRA in Korea differ substantially across regions 
within the country, ranging from 0.92-8.50/million workers. Re-
gional differences were also found in France. 
24 These findings 
may be due to regional differences in reporting, and in industri-
al composition. 
As in other countries, 
7,8,25,27,38-40 the most common cause of 
WRA in Korea was exposure to isocyanates, but the proportion 
of WRA cases attributed to isocyanates in Korea (46.6%) was 
much higher than that in other countries (13.6%-23.1%). Possi-</p>

<p>Table 5. Causal agents* of work-related asthma by sex, Korea, 2004-2009 </p>

<p>Agent 
Total 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Isocyanates 
110 (46.6) 
79 (48.2) 
31 (43.1) 
Flour/grain 
20 (8.5) 
12 (7.3) 
8 (11.1) 
Metals 
14 (5.9) 
9 (5.5) 
5 (6.9) 
Reactive dyes 
12 (5.1) 
11 (6.7) 
1 (1.4) 
Solvents 
10 (4.2) 
7 (4.3) 
3 (4.2) 
Pharmaceuticals 
8 (3.4) 
3 (1.8) 
5 (6.9) 
Wood dusts 
8 (3.4) 
5 (3.0) 
3 (4.2) 
Smoke, fumes 
6 (2.5) 
5 (3.0) 
1 (1.4) 
Cyanoacrylate 
3 (1.3) 
0 (0.0) 
3 (4.2) 
Synthetic glues 
3 (1.3) 
2 (1.2) 
1 (1.4) 
Persulphate 
3 (1.3) 
0 (0.0) 
3 (4.2) 
Paints 
3 (1.3) 
2 (1.2) 
1 (1.4) 
Irritant gases 
3 (1.3) 
3 (1.8) 
0 (0.0) 
Other dusts 
3 (1.3) 
3 (1.8) 
0 (0.0) 
Chemical compounds 
3 (1.3) 
2 (1.2) 
1 (1.4) 
Animal antigens 
2 (0.8) 
2 (1.2) 
0 (0.0) 
Plant antigens 
1 (0.4) 
1 (0.6) 
0 (0.0) 
Molds 
2 (0.8) 
2 (1.2) 
0 (0.0) 
Azodicarbonamide 
2 (0.8) 
2 (1.2) 
0 (0.0) 
Bleach 
2 (0.8) 
0 (0.0) 
2 (2.8) 
Metal-working fluids 
2 (0.8) 
2 (1.2) 
0 (0.0) 
Synthetic resins 
1 (0.4) 
1 (0.6) 
0 (0.0) 
Bisulfite salts 
1 (0.4) 
1 (0.6) 
0 (0.0) 
Phthalic anhydride 
1 (0.4) 
1 (0.6) 
0 (0.0) 
Colophony 
1 (0.4) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (1.4) 
Chocolate powder 
1 (0.4) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (1.4) 
Cold air 
1 (0.4) 
0 (0.6) 
0 (0.0) 
Unidentified 
10 (4.2) 
8 (4.9) 
2 (2.8) 
Total 
236 (100.0) 164 (100.0) 
72 (100.0) </p>

<p>*Cold air was not a causal agent, but an aggravating factor for one case with 
pre-existing asthma. </p>

<p>ble reasons were that claims for compensation are generally 
approved whenever isocyanate is present at the workplace re-
gardless of the actual WRA cause and reporting physicians are 
familiar with the processes leading to isocyanate exposure. The 
second most common cause of WRA in our study was grain 
dust, which was possibly due to a large number of WRA cases 
identified during an epidemiological investigation at a bakery. </p>

<p>41 </p>

<p>Approximately 5%-10% of bakery workers are thought to have 
WRA. 
42 Moreover, the actual number of cases of WRA caused 
by grain dust may have been much higher, considering that ag-
riculture workers in small companies (&lt;5 workers) and the 
self-employed are not eligible for workers' compensation in Ko-
rea. 
33 Some new and emerging causes of WRA were also identi-
fied by the KOWAS. Examples include azodicarbonamide </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>(used as a plastic foaming agent) and cyanoacrylate 
44 (used as 
an instant glue), both of which had not previously been ob-
served to cause WRA in Korea. 
The pattern of isocyanate exposure being the dominant cause 
of WRA in Korea tended to diminish over time. Factors respon-
sible for this decrease may include recent increased awareness 
and recognition of other causes of WRA, and a true reduction 
in the incidence of isocyanate-induced WRA, a sensitizer-in-
duced OA. Reductions in the incidence of isocyanate-induced 
WRA were also observed in France. 
32 Few cases of irritant-in-
duced OA were identified by the KOWAS. This may be because 
an understanding of the role of respiratory irritants in the etiol-
ogy of OA is too recent a phenomenon to be captured by the 
KOWAS data. </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>This analysis has several limitations. Although isocyanates 
were the most common cause of WRA, in some instances of 
isocyanate-caused WRA, an agent other than isocyanates may 
have caused the asthma. Second, the reported rates are likely to 
be underestimates. Many cases of WRA are never ascertained 
or reported. This is because many workers are not covered by 
workers' compensation, or because many physicians fail either 
to diagnose WRA or to report WRA to the KOWAS. Third, de-
tailed information on the specific objective diagnostic tests that 
were used to assess the work-relatedness criteria were often not 
available to the KOWAS. In these instances, the KOWAS relied 
on the work-relatedness assessment made by the reporting 
source. Fourth, the specific causal agent of WRA could not be 
identified because objective tests on the specific agents were ei-
ther not conducted or the test results were not available to the 
KOWAS. A similar lack of specificity is present in WRA reports 
from other countries. </p>

<p>7,8,24,25,27-29 </p>

<p>The effectiveness of the KOWAS could be improved if it was 
supported by active and ongoing work-related disease surveil-
lance schemes and occasional company-wide health evalua-
tions. The latter, prompted by findings made during the course 
of our surveillance study, helped to identify many additional 
WRA cases in a bakery. After a sentinel case of baker's asthma 
from an industrial bakery was reported to the KOWAS in Octo-</p>

<p>Work-Related Asthma in Korea 
AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>



<p>Allergy Asthma Immunol Res. 2015 January;7(1):51-59. http://dx.doi.org/10.4168/aair.2015.7.1.51 </p>

<p>ber 2005, a thorough epidemiological investigation was per-
formed by the KOSHA in 2006-2007. 
41 As a result, 12 additional 
workers were diagnosed with baker's asthma and reported to 
the KOWAS. In other cases where the causal agents could not 
be identified, or their work-relatedness could not be estab-
lished, the KOWAS findings prompted additional epidemiolog-
ical investigations. </p>

<p>46,47 </p>

<p>Before the KOWAS was established, the only method to esti-
mate rates of WRA in Korea was by analyzing data from work-
ers' compensation reports. However, many WRA patients do 
not apply for workers' compensation. The KOWAS scheme was 
designed to overcome this limitation. From 1997-2003, the 
number of cases of WRA from workers compensation ranged 
from 4-29. During the study period (2004-2009), the total num-
ber of WRA cases identified by the KOWAS was more than dou-
ble the number of cases identified by the worker's compensa-
tion scheme alone. As a public health surveillance system, the 
objective of the KOWAS is not only to estimate the magnitude 
of WRA, but to also analyze WRA trends in Korea, to detect 
emerging causes of WRA, and to guide policy changes and 
workplace interventions in order to prevent WRA and promote 
worker health. 
In conclusion, the incidence of WRA estimated from surveil-
lance data was lower in Korea than in other countries, and the 
incidence varied according to industry, occupation, sex, and </p>

<p>Table 6. Distribution of work-related asthma (WRA) cases by sex, causal agent, WRA sub-type, and reporting source -Korea, 2004-2009 </p>

<p>2004 
2005 
2006 
2007 
2008 
2009 
P-value* </p>

<p>Total 
40 (100.0) 
52 (100.0) 
35 (100.0) 
58 (100.0) 
25 (100.0) 
26 (100.0) 
Female 
11 (27.5) 
14 (26.9) 
12 (34.3) 
19 (32.8) 
5 (20.0) 
11 (42.3) 
0.568 
Causal agent 
Isocyanates 
26 (65.0) 
24 (46.2) 
20 (57.1) 
23 (39.7) 
10 (40.0) 
7 (26.9) 
0.002 
Flour/grain 
0 (0.0) 
1 (1.9) 
2 (5.7) 
15 (25.9) 
0 (0.0) 
2 (7.7) 
0.023 
Metals 
1 (2.5) 
2 (3.8) 
3 (8.6) 
3 (5.2) 
3 (12.0) 
2 (7.7) 
0.175 
Reactive dyes 
4 (10.0) 
5 (9.6) 
3 (8.6) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
0.003 
Solvents 
0 (0.0) 
2 (3.8) 
2 (5.7) 
6 (10.3) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
0.727 
Pharmaceuticals 
0 (0.0) 
1 (1.9) 
0 (0.0) 
3 (5.2) 
2 (8.0) 
2 (7.7) 
0.021 
Wood dust 
3 (7.5) 
1 (1.9) 
3 (8.6) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
1 (3.8) 
0.185 
WRA sub-type 
Sensitizer-induced OA 
37 (92.5) 
46 (88.5) 
33 (94.3) 
52 (89.7) 
18 (72.0) 
19 (73.1) 
0.008 
Irritant-induced OA 
1 (2.5) 
4 (7.7) 
2 (5.7) 
1 (1.7) 
3 (12.0) 
2 (7.7) 
0.468 
WEA 
1 (2.5) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
3 (5.2) 
1 (4.0) 
4 (15.4) 
0.006 
Reporting source </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Compensation scheme 
22 (55.0) 
24 (46.2) 
16 (45.7) 
19 (32.8) 
11 (44.0) 
10 (38.5) 
0.091 
Allergy/chest physician 
19 (47.5) 
33 (63.5) 
16 (45.7) 
25 (43.1) 
15 (60.0) 
16 (61.5) 
0.765 
Regional surveillance </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>23 (57.5) 
15 (28.8) 
12 (34.3) 
7 (12.1) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
Occupational physician 
14 (35.0) 
9 (17.3) 
8 (22.9) 
17 (29.3) 
3 (12.0) 
1 (3.8) 
0.023 </p>

<p>WRA, work-related asthma; OA, occupational asthma; WEA, work-exacerbated asthma. 
*P-value by Cochran-Armitage trend test; </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Total percentages may exceed 100 because of multiple reporting; </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>P-value could not be calculated because reporting from 
the regional surveillance systems ceased after 2007. </p>

<p>region. Data provided jointly by workers' compensation 
schemes and physician reports are useful for determining the 
rates and causes of WRA in Korea. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was commissioned by the OSHRI-KOSHA. We 
would like to thank the Korean Society of Occupational and En-
vironmental Medicine, the Korean Society of Occupational 
Asthma and Lung Diseases, the Korean Association of Occupa-
tional and Environmental Clinics, the regional surveillance sys-
tems, and the Korea Workers' Compensation and Welfare Ser-
vice for case reports. </p>



<p>Kwon et al. </p>

<p>Volume 7, Number 1, January 2015 </p>





<p>Work-Related Asthma in Korea 
AAIR </p>

<p>http://e-aair.org </p>





</text></tei>