<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4506345" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Age-related macular degeneration (AMD) is 
characterised by a spectrum of degenerative 
changes at the macula, which include drusen 
and/or hyper-/hypopigmentary changes (known 
as early AMD), atrophic changes (geographic 
atrophy, GA, a form of advanced AMD), and 
choroidal neovascularisation (neovascular or 'wet 
AMD', another form of advanced AMD). 1 
Macular pigment (MP) is a yellow pigment 
located in the macular region of the human 
retina, and is composed of lutein (L), zeaxanthin 
(Z), and meso-zeaxanthin (MZ). 2 MP filters short-
wavelength blue light (and therefore limits 
photooxidative damage passively) and its 
constituent carotenoids act as antioxidants by 
neutralizing free radicals. 3,4 
In the current study, known as the Meso-
zeaxanthin Ocular Supplementation Trial 
(MOST) AMD study, we compared the effect 
of sustained supplementation with some or all 
of MP's constituent carotenoids on visual 
function, and evaluated the impact of such 
supplementation on vision and disease 
progression. Observations that MZ, the 
dominant carotenoid in the epicentre of the MP's 
spatial profile, may offer advantages in terms of 
MP augmentation across its spatial profile 5 and </p>

<p>1 Macular Pigment 
Research Group, 
Department of Chemical 
and Life Sciences, 
Waterford Institute of 
Technology, Waterford, 
Ireland </p>

<p>2 Howard Foundation, 
Cambridge, UK </p>

<p>3 Department of 
Ophthalmology and Visual 
Sciences, University of 
Wisconsin, Madison, WI, 
USA </p>

<p>4 Northern Ireland, Centre 
for Food and Health 
(NICHE), University of 
Ulster, Coleraine, UK </p>

<p>Correspondence: 
KO Akuffo, Macular 
Pigment Research Group, 
Vision Research Centre, 
Waterford Institute of 
Technology, West Campus, 
Carriganore, Waterford, 
Ireland 
Tel: +353 (0)51 306261. 
E-mail: kakuffo@wit.ie </p>

<p>Received: 26 November 
2014 
Accepted in revised form: 
26 March 2015 
Published online: 
15 May 2015 </p>

<p>CLINICAL STUDY </p>

<p>Eye (2015) 29, 902-912 
© 2015 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 0950-222X/15 </p>

<p>www.nature.com/eye </p>

<p>in terms of enhancement of visual function 6 prompted 
this investigation. The 8-week 7 and 12-month 8 reports 
of the MOST AMD study have been published. In the 
current study, we present new data on a 3-year follow-up 
of subjects in the MOST AMD study. Of note, this is the 
first study to monitor MP, visual function, and AMD </p>

<p>status in response to supplementation with all three 
macular carotenoids in patients with early AMD, over a 
36-month period. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>The design and methodology of the MOST AMD study 
has been reported previously. 8 In brief, MOST AMD is 
a single-blind, randomised controlled clinical trial. 
Clinical assessments were carried out at the Institute of 
Eye Surgery (http://www.ioes.ie/), Waterford, Ireland. 
Before study enrolment, an eligibility screening visit was 
conducted by an ophthalmologist with a special interest 
in retinal disease (SB). The eligibility criteria included 
early AMD (one to eight on AREDS 11-step severity scale 9 
in at least one eye (the study eye), confirmed by the 
Ocular Epidemilogy Reading Center at the University of 
Wisconsin, Madison, WI, USA); best-corrected visual 
acuity (BCVA) ≥ 6/12 in the study eye; and no other 
ocular pathology. 
Subjects were randomly assigned to one of three 
parallel groups: Group 1-20 mg L, 0.86 mg Z (Ultra 
Lutein supplied by Natural Organics, Inc., Melville, NY, 
USA); Group 2-10 mg MZ, 10 mg L, 2 mg Z (Macushield 
(Macuvision Europe Limited, Solihull, UK)/Macuhealth 
LMZ3 (MacuHealth LLC, Birmingham, MI, USA)); Group 
3-17 mg MZ, 3 mg L, 2 mg Z (supplied by Industrial 
Organica, Monterrey, Mexico (not commercially 
available)). The above treatment groups (formulations) 
were selected to be comparable total concentrations of 
macular carotenoids (ie 22 mg). Of note, however, 
discrepancies between label claim and measured values of 
the supplements used in this trial have been reported 
previously, and in particular, the finding that the Group 1 
supplement contained small amounts of MZ 
(0.30 mg). 10,11 This has implications for the findings 
presented below. 
The supplements were prepared in a soft gel capsule. 
Subjects were instructed to take one capsule daily with 
a meal. All study supplements were indistinguishable in 
terms of external appearance, and were packaged in 
identical containers. Study visits were conducted 
at baseline, 12 months, 24 months, and 36 months. </p>

<p>Ethics </p>

<p>Ethics approval was granted by the Waterford Regional 
Hospital Ethics Committee. Written and informed consent </p>

<p>was obtained from each subject before study enrolment. 
The tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki were adhered to 
in all study procedures. </p>

<p>Outcome measures </p>

<p>The primary outcome measure was change in MP as 
measured by customized heterochromatic flicker 
photometry (cHFP) at 36 months. Secondary outcome 
measures included BCVA, letter contrast sensitivity (CS), 
serum concentrations of macular carotenoids, and grade 
of AMD. </p>

<p>Study procedures </p>

<p>MP measurement MP was measured using the Macular 
Densitometer (Macular Metrics, Corp., Providence, RI, 
USA) at 0.25°, 0.5°, 1.0°, and 1.75° retinal eccentricity, 
with a reference point at 7°. 12 </p>

<p>Serum L, Z, and MZ analysis Serum L, Z, and MZ were 
quantified by high-performance liquid chromatography 
using methodology described previously. 7,13 </p>

<p>Visual acuity BCVA was measured using the Early 
Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) 
logarithm of the minimum angle of resolution (LogMAR) 
chart (<rs id="software-2" type="software">Test Chart</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">2000 PRO</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Thomson Software Solutions</rs>, 
Hatfield, Hertfordshire, UK) viewed at 4 m. </p>

<p>Letter CS Letter CS was assessed using the LogMAR 
ETDRS (<rs id="software-1" type="software">Test Chart</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">2000 PRO</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Thomson Software Solutions</rs>) chart at five different spatial frequencies (1.2, 2.4, 
6.0, 9.6, and 15.15 c.p.d., respectively) viewed at 4 m. </p>

<p>Retinal photography and AMD grading </p>

<p>Following prior pupillary dilation (0.5% proxymetacaine 
hydrochloride, 2.5% phenylephrine hydrochloride, and 
1% tropicamide), 45° stereoscopic color fundus 
photographs were taken in three retinal photographic 
fields (optic disc, macula, temporal to macula) using a </p>

<p>Zeiss Visucam 200 (Carl Zeiss Meditec AG, Jena, 
Germany). Photographs were transferred to the Ocular 
Epidemiology Reading Center at the University of 
Wisconsin via an encrypted system. Photographs were 
graded in a masked manner using a modified version 
of the Wisconsin Age-Related Maculopathy Grading 
System 14,15 and adhered to the AREDS 11-step severity 
scale. 9 </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>

<p>903 </p>

<p>Eye </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>One eye (the study eye) of each subject comprised the unit 
of analysis. Statistical analysis was performed using IBM 
SPSS Statistics for Windows, version 21.0 (IBM, Armonk, 
NY, USA). To compare the effects of the three 
supplements (on each outcome measure, over time), 
we used repeated-measures analysis of variance, and 
contingency table analysis, as appropriate. Cognisant that 
this exploratory study would likely have insufficient 
power for such analyses, however, we did some 
additional analyses. In fact, and beyond the previously 
reported 12-month data, 8 we decided upon two strands of 
analysis: (a) between supplement group analysis over 
time: despite the small sample sizes, supplement groups 
were compared with each other, for changes in each 
outcome variable over the 3 years of the study. For 
interval outcome variables (MP, serum carotenoids, 
BCVA, CS), the method of analysis was repeated-
measures analysis of variance, with time as a within-
subjects factor and supplement as a between-subjects 
factor; we used the Greenhouse-Geisser correction for 
lack of sphericity. Post hoc analysis, with Bonferroni 
adjustment for multiple testing, was used where 
appropriate. For categorical outcome variables (AMD 
grade), we used contingency table analysis to compare 
supplements; (b) within-supplement group changes in 
each outcome variable, over the 3 years of the study. 
We used paired t-tests analysis here. 
Tests of significance, for all t-test analyses, were two-
tailed, and the 5% level of significance was used 
throughout. With the exception of post hoc analyses for the 
repeated-measures analysis of variance, we did not 
correct for multiple tests. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Sixty-seven subjects were enrolled at baseline, with 47 
subjects completing the final study visit at 36 months. 
Only those subjects who completed each study visit were 
included in analysis. Therefore, if a subject attended 
his/her 12-or 24-month visit, but did not complete the 
36-month visit, he/she was not included in the analysis. 
Where a subject did complete a study visit, but where 
a variable was not measured or recorded, that subject was 
also excluded from all analyses relating to that variable. 
Exclusions occurred only in the MP and CS analysis 
because data were not available at all study visits (MP 
analysis: 5 subjects; CS analysis: 6 subjects). We have also 
included the sample size in all tables for clarity. 
Baseline characteristics (eg age, gender, smoking 
status, education) of participants in intervention groups 
have been described previously, and the intervention </p>

<p>groups were statistically comparable in terms of these 
variables. 8 </p>

<p>MP and its constituent carotenoids in serum </p>

<p>Macular pigment 
(a) Comparing supplement groups In the repeated-
measures analysis of change in MP (at 0.25°, 0.5°, 1.0°, 
and 1.75°), the within-subjects Time × Supplement 
interaction effect was not significant (P = 0.759, 0.726, 
0.703, 0.110, respectively, using the Greenhouse-Geisser 
adjustment for lack of sphericity). Thus, the effect (on MP 
levels) over time, at any eccentricity, does not differ 
significantly between supplement groups. The boxplots in 
Figure 1 graphically illustrate these findings. 
(b) Within-supplement group analyses of MP are given 
in Table 1. </p>

<p>Serum concentrations of lutein 
(a) Comparing supplement groups In the repeated-
measures analysis of change in serum L, the within-
subjects Time × Supplement interaction effect was 
significant (P = 0.029, using the Greenhouse-Geisser 
adjustment for lack of sphericity). Thus, the effect (on 
serum L levels) over time differs significantly between the 
supplements used. Post hoc analysis indicates that 
increases in serum L over time in groups 1 and 2 are 
comparable (P = 1, after Bonferroni adjustment for 
multiple testing), and each of these groups exhibit 
significantly greater increases than group 3 (P = 0.029 and 
P = 0.004, respectively, after Bonferroni adjustment for 
multiple testing). The boxplots in Figure 2a graphically 
illustrate these findings. 
(b) Within-supplement group analyses of serum L are 
given in Table 2. </p>

<p>Serum concentrations of MZ 
(a) Comparing supplement groups In the repeated-
measures analysis of change in serum MZ, the within-
subjects Time × Supplement interaction effect was 
significant (P = 0.011, using the Greenhouse-Geisser 
adjustment for lack of sphericity). Thus, the effect over 
time (on serum levels of MZ) differs significantly between 
the supplement groups. Post hoc analysis indicates that 
increases in MZ over time in Groups 2 and 3 are 
comparable (P = 1, after Bonferroni adjustment for 
multiple testing), and each of these groups exhibits 
significantly greater increases than Group 1 (P = 0.001 for 
both, after Bonferroni adjustment for multiple testing). 
The boxplots in Figure 2b graphically illustrate these 
findings. </p>

<p>(b) Within-supplement group analyses of serum MZ are 
given in Table 2. </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>

<p>904 </p>

<p>Eye </p>

<p>Serum concentrations of zeaxanthin 
(a) Comparing supplement groups In the repeated-
measures analysis of change in serum Z, the within-
subjects Time × Supplement interaction effect was not 
significant (P = 0.081, using the Greenhouse-Geisser 
adjustment for lack of sphericity). Thus, the effect over 
time does not differ significantly between the 
supplements. The boxplots in Figure 2c graphically 
illustrate these findings. 
(b) Within-supplement group analyses of serum Z are 
given in Table 2. </p>

<p>Changes in visual function 
(a) Comparing supplement groups There were no 
significant Time × Supplement interaction effects for any 
vision-related outcome measures (BCVA, letter CS at any </p>

<p>spatial frequency), indicating that the observed effects 
over time in terms of these variables (see below) did not 
differ between intervention groups. </p>

<p>Best-corrected visual acuity 
Within-supplement group analysis There were no 
significant within-supplement changes in BCVA (P40.05, 
for all), with the exception of a statistically significant 
improvement in Group 3 between 12 and 24 months. </p>

<p>Contrast sensitivity 
Within-supplement group analysis of CS are given in 
Table 3. At 36 months, compared with baseline, the 
following significant improvements (Po0.05) in CS were 
observed: Group 2-1.2, 6, and 9.6 c.p.d.; Group 
1-15.15 c.p.d.; Group 3-6, 9.6, and 15.15 c.p.d. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Macular pigment response at different retinal eccentricities over the course of the MOST AMD study. Boxplots representing 
macular pigment optical density at four time points (baseline, 12 months, 24 months, and 36 months) for each intervention group: Group 
1-20 mg L and 0.86 mg Z; Group 2-10 mg MZ, 10 mg L, and 2 mg Z; Group 3-17 mg MZ, 3 mg L, and 2 mg Z Macular pigment was 
measured at 0.25° (a), 0.5° (b), 1.0° (c), and 1.75° (d) eccentricity using cHFP. 0-G1, Baseline Group 1; 12-G1, 12 months Group 1; 24-G1, 
24 months Group 1; 36-G1, 36 months Group 1; 0-G2, Baseline Group 2; 12-G2, 12 months Group 2; 24-G2, 24 months Group 2; 36-G2, 
36 months Group 2; 0-G3, Baseline Group 3; 12-G3, 12 months Group 3; 24-G3, 24 months Group 3; 36-G3, 36 months Group 3. MPOD, 
macular pigment optical density. </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>



<p>Eye </p>

<p>Table 1 
Within-supplement group analysis of macular pigment by intervention groups </p>

<p>Intervention N </p>

<p>Baseline, </p>

<p>mean 
± SD 
36 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>%Δ Sig. </p>

<p>Baseline, </p>

<p>mean 
± SD 
12 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>%Δ Sig. </p>

<p>12 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>24 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>%Δ Sig. </p>

<p>24 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>36 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>% 
Δ Sig. </p>

<p>MP at 0.25 
Group 1 13 0.51 </p>

<p>± 0.29 </p>

<p>0.72 
± 0.24 
41 0.004 0.51 </p>

<p>± 0.29 </p>

<p>0.61 
± 0.30 </p>

<p>20 0.039 </p>

<p>0.61 
± 0.30 </p>

<p>0.61 
± 0.25 </p>

<p>0 0.896 </p>

<p>0.61 
± 0.25 </p>

<p>0.72 
± 0.24 </p>

<p>18 0.134 </p>

<p>Group 2 16 0.50 </p>

<p>± 0.24 </p>

<p>0.76 
± 0.23 
52 0.001 0.50 </p>

<p>± 0.24 </p>

<p>0.63 
± 0.21 </p>

<p>26 0.001 </p>

<p>0.63 
± 0.21 </p>

<p>0.64 
± 0.17 </p>

<p>2 0.802 </p>

<p>0.64 
± 0.17 </p>

<p>0.76 
± 0.23 </p>

<p>19 0.095 </p>

<p>Group 3 12 0.51 </p>

<p>± 0.20 </p>

<p>0.85 
± 0.25 
67 0.000 0.51 </p>

<p>± 0.20 </p>

<p>0.62 
± 0.19 </p>

<p>22 0.021 </p>

<p>0.62 
± 0.19 </p>

<p>0.62 
± 0.19 </p>

<p>0 0.924 </p>

<p>0.62 
± 0.19 </p>

<p>0.85 
± 0.25 </p>

<p>37 0.003 </p>

<p>MP at 0.5 
Group 1 13 0.41 </p>

<p>± 0.28 </p>

<p>0.62 
± 0.26 
51 0.000 0.41 </p>

<p>± 0.28 </p>

<p>0.47 
± 0.27 </p>

<p>15 0.194 </p>

<p>0.47 
± 0.26 </p>

<p>0.53 
± 0.21 </p>

<p>13 0.092 </p>

<p>0.53 
± 0.21 </p>

<p>0.62 
± 0.26 </p>

<p>16 0.087 </p>

<p>Group 2 16 0.45 </p>

<p>± 0.21 </p>

<p>0.64 
± 0.20 
42 0.000 0.45 </p>

<p>± 0.21 </p>

<p>0.54 
± 0.18 </p>

<p>20 0.011 </p>

<p>0.54 
± 0.18 </p>

<p>0.55 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>2 0.343 </p>

<p>0.55 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>0.64 
± 0.20 </p>

<p>16 0.034 </p>

<p>Group 3 12 0.39 </p>

<p>± 0.19 </p>

<p>0.68 
± 0.20 
74 0.000 0.39 </p>

<p>± 0.19 </p>

<p>0.50 
± 0.20 </p>

<p>22 0.016 </p>

<p>0.50 
± 0.20 </p>

<p>0.50 
± 0.20 </p>

<p>0 0.879 </p>

<p>0.50 
± 0.20 </p>

<p>0.68 
± 0.20 </p>

<p>36 0.011 </p>

<p>MP at 1.0 
Group 1 13 0.30 </p>

<p>± 0.19 </p>

<p>0.45 
± 0.19 
50 0.006 0.30 </p>

<p>± 0.19 </p>

<p>0.38 
± 0.15 </p>

<p>27 0.053 </p>

<p>0.38 
± 0.15 </p>

<p>0.40 
± 0.14 </p>

<p>5 0.339 </p>

<p>0.40 
± 0.14 </p>

<p>0.45 
± 0.18 </p>

<p>13 0.298 </p>

<p>Group 2 16 0.29 </p>

<p>± 0.13 </p>

<p>0.46 
± 0.15 
59 0.000 0.29 </p>

<p>± 0.13 </p>

<p>0.37 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>28 0.010 </p>

<p>0.37 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>0.38 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>3 0.730 </p>

<p>0.38 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>0.46 
± 0.15 </p>

<p>21 0.071 </p>

<p>Group 3 12 0.26 </p>

<p>± 0.17 </p>

<p>0.52 
± 0.16 
100 0.000 0.26 </p>

<p>± 0.17 </p>

<p>0.37 
± 0.14 </p>

<p>42 0.010 </p>

<p>0.37 
± 0.14 </p>

<p>0.35 
± 0.13 </p>

<p>− 6 0.473 </p>

<p>0.35 
± 0.13 </p>

<p>0.52 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>49 0.011 </p>

<p>MP at 1.75 
Group 1 13 0.17 </p>

<p>± 0.11 </p>

<p>0.23 
± 0.19 
35 0.160 0.17 </p>

<p>± 0.11 </p>

<p>0.22 
± 0.09 </p>

<p>29 0.055 </p>

<p>0.22 
± 0.09 </p>

<p>0.24 
± 0.08 </p>

<p>9 0.256 </p>

<p>0.24 
± 0.08 </p>

<p>0.23 
± 0.19 </p>

<p>− 4 0.870 </p>

<p>Group 2 16 0.15 </p>

<p>± 0.12 </p>

<p>0.28 
± 0.11 
87 0.000 0.15 </p>

<p>± 0.12 </p>

<p>0.24 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>60 0.007 </p>

<p>0.24 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>0.24 
± 0.13 </p>

<p>0 0.793 </p>

<p>0.24 
± 0.13 </p>

<p>0.28 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>17 0.383 </p>

<p>Group 3 12 0.12 </p>

<p>± 0.13 </p>

<p>0.34 
± 0.14 
183 0.000 0.12 </p>

<p>± 0.13 </p>

<p>0.21 
± 0.09 </p>

<p>75 0.006 </p>

<p>0.21 
± 0.09 </p>

<p>0.21 
± 0.07 </p>

<p>0 0.899 </p>

<p>0.21 
± 0.07 </p>

<p>0.34 
± 0.14 </p>

<p>62 0.003 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: MP, macular pigment; N, number of subjects; SD, standard deviation; Sig., significance; %Δ, percentage change. </p>

<p>Macular pigment was measured at 0.25°, 0.5°, 1.0°, and 1.75° eccentricity using customized heterochromatic </p>

<p>flicker photometry. Statistical significance was tested using paired t-test. </p>

<p>Level of significance set at P </p>

<p>o0.05. The calculated percentage change from baseline to 36 months, calculated as the 36-month value minus baseline value divided by baseline value, multiplied by 100 (− , negative change; +, positive change); </p>

<p>the calculated percentage change from baseline to 12 months, calculated as the 12-month value minus baseline value divided by baseline value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change); the </p>

<p>calculated percentage change from 12 to 24 months, calculated as the 24-month value minus the 12-month value divided by the 12-month value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change); the </p>

<p>calculated percentage change from 24 to 36 months, calculated as the 36-month value minus the 24-month value divided by the 24-month value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change). </p>

<p>Group 1, 20 mg lutein and 0.86 mg zeaxanthin; Group 2, 10 mg meso-zeaxanthin, </p>

<p>10 mg lutein, and 2 mg zeaxanthin; Group 3, 17 mg meso-zeaxanthin, </p>

<p>3 mg lutein, and 2 mg zeaxanthin. </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>

<p>906 </p>

<p>Eye </p>

<p>Changes in grade of AMD </p>

<p>Because of the limited number of subjects in this study, 
we collapsed adjacent grades of AMD, as follows: AREDS 
grades 1-3 (representing eyes at low risk of progression to 
advanced AMD), and AREDS grades 4-8 (representing 
eyes at high risk of progression to advanced AMD). 
In terms of this collapsed and simplified classification, 
intervention groups were statistically similar in terms of 
baseline findings (P = 0.44, χ 2 test). Using this simplified 
and modified system, no study eye in any intervention 
group progressed from low risk to high risk of 
progression to advanced AMD over the course of the 
study period, and no study eye regressed from high risk 
to low risk of progression to advanced AMD in any </p>

<p>intervention group, and finally, no subject progressed to 
advanced AMD (AREDS grades 9-11) over the study 
period. Given that findings were identical for all three 
intervention groups, there was no need for statistical 
investigation of differences between intervention groups 
in terms of changes in risk for progression to 
advanced AMD. 
We also investigated clinically meaningful change in 
AMD grade along the AREDS 11-step scale, defined as 
a change of at least two steps along this scale. Thus, an 
increase of two steps between baseline and final visit at 
36 months was considered clinically meaningful disease 
progression and a decrease of two steps was considered 
a clinically meaningful disease regression. On this basis, 
there was no clinically meaningful change in AMD grade </p>

<p>Figure 2 Serum response of L, MZ, and Z over the course of the MOST AMD study. Boxplots representing serum concentrations of L 
(a), MZ (b), and zeaxanthin (c) at four time points (baseline, 12 months, 24 months, and 36 months) for each intervention group: Group 1 
-20 mg L and 0.86 mg Z; Group 2-10 mg MZ, 10 mg L, and 2 mg Z; Group 3-17 mg MZ, 3 mg L, and 2 mg Z. Serum macular 
carotenoids were analysed by HPLC and expressed as μmol/L; 0-G1, Baseline Group 1; 12-G1, 12 months Group 1; 24-G1, 24 months 
Group 1; 36-G1, 36 months Group 1; 0-G2, Baseline Group 2; 12-G2, 12 months Group 2; 24-G2, 24 months Group 2; 36-G2, 36 months 
Group 2; 0-G3, Baseline Group 3; 12-G3, 12 months Group 3; 24-G3, 24 months Group 3; 36-G3, 36 months Group 3. </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>



<p>Table 2 
Within-supplement group analysis of serum macular carotenoids by intervention groups </p>

<p>Intervention </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>Baseline, </p>

<p>mean 
± SD 
36 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>%Δ Sig. </p>

<p>Baseline, </p>

<p>mean 
± SD 
12 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>%Δ Sig. </p>

<p>12 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>24 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>%Δ Sig. </p>

<p>24 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>36 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>% 
Δ Sig. </p>

<p>Lutein 
Group 1 14 0.39 </p>

<p>±0.31 </p>

<p>0.81 
± 0.44 
108 0.006 0.39 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>0.81 
± 0.58 </p>

<p>108 0.014 </p>

<p>0.81 
± 0.58 </p>

<p>0.90 
± 0.57 </p>

<p>11 0.616 </p>

<p>0.90 
± 0.57 </p>

<p>0.81 
± 0.44 </p>

<p>−10 0.412 </p>

<p>Group 2 15 0.24 </p>

<p>± 0.11 </p>

<p>1.14 
± 0.83 
375 0.001 0.24 </p>

<p>± 0.11 </p>

<p>1.11 
± 0.67 </p>

<p>363 0.000 </p>

<p>1.11 
± 0.67 </p>

<p>0.85 
± 1.05 
− 23 0.336 </p>

<p>0.85 
± 1.05 </p>

<p>1.14 
± 0.83 </p>

<p>34 0.250 </p>

<p>Group 3 13 0.20 </p>

<p>± 0.08 </p>

<p>0.36 
± 0.13 
80 0.001 0.20 </p>

<p>± 0.08 </p>

<p>0.31 
± 0.17 </p>

<p>55 0.021 </p>

<p>0.31 
± 0.17 </p>

<p>0.39 
± 0.36 </p>

<p>26 0.367 </p>

<p>0.39 
± 0.36 </p>

<p>0.36 
± 0.13 </p>

<p>−8 0.694 </p>

<p>Zeaxanthin 
Group 1 14 0.09 </p>

<p>± 0.09 </p>

<p>0.13 
± 0.06 
44 0.124 0.09 </p>

<p>± 0.09 </p>

<p>0.12 
± 0.09 </p>

<p>33 0.314 </p>

<p>0.12 
± 0.09 </p>

<p>0.15 
± 0.09 </p>

<p>25 0.251 </p>

<p>0.15 
± 0.09 </p>

<p>0.13 
± 0.06 </p>

<p>−13 0.202 </p>

<p>Group 2 15 0.04 </p>

<p>± 0.03 </p>

<p>0.16 
± 0.12 
300 0.001 0.04 </p>

<p>± 0.03 </p>

<p>0.22 
± 0.24 </p>

<p>450 0.012 </p>

<p>0.22 
± 0.24 </p>

<p>0.13 
± 0.14 
− 41 0.221 </p>

<p>0.13 
± 0.14 </p>

<p>0.16 
± 0.12 </p>

<p>23 0.298 </p>

<p>Group 3 13 0.06 </p>

<p>± 0.05 </p>

<p>0.11 
± 0.04 
83 0.005 0.06 </p>

<p>± 0.05 </p>

<p>0.09 
± 0.06 </p>

<p>50 0.031 </p>

<p>0.09 
± 0.06 </p>

<p>0.10 
± 0.07 </p>

<p>11 0.653 </p>

<p>0.10 
± 0.07 </p>

<p>0.11 
± 0.04 </p>

<p>10 0.799 </p>

<p>Meso-zeaxanthin </p>

<p>Group 1 14 0.00 </p>

<p>± 0.00 </p>

<p>0.02 
± 0.02 </p>

<p>0.010 0.00 </p>

<p>± 0.00 </p>

<p>0.01 
± 0.01 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.01 
± 0.01 </p>

<p>0.01 
± 0.02 </p>

<p>0 0.393 </p>

<p>0.01 
± 0.02 </p>

<p>0.02 
± 0.02 </p>

<p>100 0.371 </p>

<p>Group 2 15 0.00 </p>

<p>± 0.00 </p>

<p>0.11 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>0.001 0.00 </p>

<p>± 0.00 </p>

<p>0.22 
± 0.27 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.22 
± 0.27 </p>

<p>0.09 
± 0.11 
− 59 0.083 </p>

<p>0.09 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>0.11 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>22 0.314 </p>

<p>Group 3 13 0.00 </p>

<p>± 0.00 </p>

<p>0.14 
± 0.10 </p>

<p>0.000 0.00 </p>

<p>± 0.00 </p>

<p>0.16 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.16 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>0.15 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>− 6 0.911 </p>

<p>0.15 
± 0.11 </p>

<p>0.14 
± 0.10 </p>

<p>−7 0.743 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: N, number of subjects; SD, standard deviation; Sig., significance; %Δ, percentage change. </p>

<p>Serum Lutein, Zeaxanthin and Meso-zeaxanthin were analysed by HPLC and expressed as </p>

<p>μmol/L. Statistical significance tested using paired t-test. </p>

<p>Level of significance set at Po0.05. </p>

<p>The calculated percentage </p>

<p>change from baseline to 36 months, calculated as the 36-month value minus baseline value divided by baseline value, multiplied by 100 (− , negative change; +, positive change); the calculated percentage change 
from baseline to 12 months, calculated as the 12-month value minus baseline value divided by baseline value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change); the calculated percentage change from 12 </p>

<p>to 24 months, calculated as the 24-month value minus the 12-month value divided by the 12-month value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change); the calculated percentage change from 24 to </p>

<p>36 months, calculated as the 36-month value minus the 24-month value divided by the 24-month value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change). </p>

<p>Group 1, 20 mg lutein and 0.86 mg zeaxanthin; Group 2, 10 mg meso-zeaxanthin, </p>

<p>10 mg lutein, and 2 mg zeaxanthin; Group 3, 17 mg meso-zeaxanthin, </p>

<p>3 mg lutein, and 2 mg zeaxanthin. </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>

<p>908 </p>

<p>Eye </p>

<p>Table 3 
Within-supplement group analysis of letter contrast sensitivity by intervention groups </p>

<p>Intervention </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>Baseline, </p>

<p>mean 
± SD 
36 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>% 
Δ Sig. </p>

<p>Baseline, </p>

<p>mean 
± SD 
12 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>% 
Δ Sig. </p>

<p>12 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>24 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>%Δ Sig. </p>

<p>24 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>36 Months, 
mean 
± SD </p>

<p>% 
Δ Sig. </p>

<p>Letter CS 1.2cpd 
Group 1 12 1.87 </p>

<p>±0.25 </p>

<p>1.89 
± 0.16 
1 0.817 1.87 </p>

<p>± 0.25 </p>

<p>1.96 
± 0.23 </p>

<p>5 0.222 </p>

<p>1.96 
± 0.23 </p>

<p>1.76 
± 0.22 
− 10 0.000 1.76 </p>

<p>± 0.22 </p>

<p>1.89 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>7 0.059 </p>

<p>Group 2 15 1.71 </p>

<p>± 0.24 </p>

<p>1.86 
± 0.18 
9 0.012 1.71 </p>

<p>± 0.24 </p>

<p>1.93 
± 0.29 </p>

<p>13 0.004 </p>

<p>1.93 
± 0.29 </p>

<p>1.85 
± 0.25 
− 4 0.207 1.85 </p>

<p>± 0.25 </p>

<p>1.86 
± 0.18 </p>

<p>1 0.861 </p>

<p>Group 3 13 1.75 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.82 
± 0.20 
4 0.432 1.75 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.89 
± 0.27 </p>

<p>8 0.069 </p>

<p>1.89 
± 0.27 </p>

<p>1.86 
± 0.24 
− 2 0.602 1.86 </p>

<p>± 0.24 </p>

<p>1.82 
± 0.20 </p>

<p>−2 0.494 </p>

<p>Letter CS 2.4cpd 
Group 1 12 1.76 </p>

<p>± 0.30 </p>

<p>1.87 
± 0.17 
6 0.227 1.76 </p>

<p>± 0.30 </p>

<p>1.89 
± 0.33 </p>

<p>7 0.077 </p>

<p>1.89 
± 0.33 </p>

<p>1.70 
± 0.25 
− 10 0.011 1.70 </p>

<p>± 0.25 </p>

<p>1.87 
± 0.17 </p>

<p>10 0.065 </p>

<p>Group 2 15 1.68 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.81 
± 0.21 
8 0.087 1.68 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.86 
± 0.31 </p>

<p>11 0.000 </p>

<p>1.86 
± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.78 
± 0.26 
− 4 0.221 1.78 </p>

<p>± 0.26 </p>

<p>1.81 
± 0.21 </p>

<p>2 0.657 </p>

<p>Group 3 13 1.63 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.78 
± 0.21 
9 0.083 1.63 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.85 
± 0.29 </p>

<p>13 0.005 </p>

<p>1.85 
± 0.29 </p>

<p>1.77 
± 0.22 
− 4 0.225 1.77 </p>

<p>± 0.22 </p>

<p>1.78 
± 0.21 </p>

<p>1 0.947 </p>

<p>Letter CS 6cpd 
Group 1 12 1.42 </p>

<p>± 0.30 </p>

<p>1.60 
± 0.15 
13 0.112 1.42 </p>

<p>± 0.30 </p>

<p>1.49 
± 0.41 </p>

<p>5 0.224 </p>

<p>1.49 
± 0.41 </p>

<p>1.39 
± 0.26 
− 7 0.200 1.39 </p>

<p>± 0.26 </p>

<p>1.60 
± 0.15 </p>

<p>15 0.037 </p>

<p>Group 2 15 1.37 </p>

<p>± 0.24 </p>

<p>1.52 
± 0.25 
11 0.040 1.37 </p>

<p>± 0.24 </p>

<p>1.44 
± 0.30 </p>

<p>5 0.079 </p>

<p>1.44 
± 0.30 </p>

<p>1.39 
± 0.34 
− 3 0.357 1.39 </p>

<p>± 0.34 </p>

<p>1.52 
± 0.25 </p>

<p>9 0.164 </p>

<p>Group 3 13 1.23 </p>

<p>± 0.44 </p>

<p>1.52 
± 0.27 
24 0.034 1.23 </p>

<p>± 0.44 </p>

<p>1.55 
± 0.29 </p>

<p>26 0.005 </p>

<p>1.55 
± 0.29 </p>

<p>1.48 
± 0.20 
− 5 0.357 1.48 </p>

<p>± 0.20 </p>

<p>1.52 
± 0.27 </p>

<p>3 0.547 </p>

<p>Letter CS 9.6cpd 
Group 1 12 1.14 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.35 
± 0.16 
18 0.043 1.14 </p>

<p>± 0.31 </p>

<p>1.14 
± 0.32 </p>

<p>0 0.959 </p>

<p>1.14 
± 0.32 </p>

<p>1.14 
± 0.28 
0 1.000 1.14 </p>

<p>± 0.28 </p>

<p>1.35 
± 0.16 </p>

<p>18 0.031 </p>

<p>Group 2 15 1.06 </p>

<p>± 0.27 </p>

<p>1.27 
± 0.34 
20 0.024 1.06 </p>

<p>± 0.27 </p>

<p>1.17 
± 0.39 </p>

<p>10 0.072 </p>

<p>1.17 
± 0.39 </p>

<p>1.06 
± 0.37 
− 9 0.115 1.06 </p>

<p>± 0.37 </p>

<p>1.27 
± 0.34 </p>

<p>20 0.025 </p>

<p>Group 3 13 0.94 </p>

<p>± 0.48 </p>

<p>1.30 
± 0.22 
38 0.020 0.94 </p>

<p>± 0.48 </p>

<p>1.17 
± 0.44 </p>

<p>24 0.031 </p>

<p>1.17 
± 0.44 </p>

<p>1.23 
± 0.27 
5 0.503 1.23 </p>

<p>± 0.27 </p>

<p>1.30 
± 0.22 </p>

<p>6 0.201 </p>

<p>Letter CS 15.15cpd 
Group 1 12 0.75 </p>

<p>± 0.32 </p>

<p>1.02 
± 0.23 
36 0.033 0.75 </p>

<p>± 0.32 </p>

<p>0.83 
± 0.31 </p>

<p>11 0.055 </p>

<p>0.83 
± 0.31 </p>

<p>0.79 
± 0.29 
− 5 0.509 0.79 </p>

<p>± 0.29 </p>

<p>1.02 
± 0.23 </p>

<p>29 0.011 </p>

<p>Group 2 15 0.70 </p>

<p>± 0.37 </p>

<p>0.91 
± 0.38 
30 0.083 0.70 </p>

<p>± 0.37 </p>

<p>0.78 
± 0.44 </p>

<p>11 0.278 </p>

<p>0.78 
± 0.44 </p>

<p>0.60 
± 0.47 
− 23 0.013 0.60 </p>

<p>± 0.47 </p>

<p>0.91 
± 0.38 </p>

<p>52 0.029 </p>

<p>Group 3 13 0.61 </p>

<p>± 0.48 </p>

<p>0.97 
± 0.25 
59 0.019 0.61 </p>

<p>± 0.48 </p>

<p>0.81 
± 0.38 </p>

<p>33 0.028 </p>

<p>0.81 
± 0.38 </p>

<p>0.93 
± 0.35 
15 0.169 0.93 </p>

<p>± 0.35 </p>

<p>0.97 
± 0.25 </p>

<p>4 0.555 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CS, contrast sensitivity; cpd, cycles per degree; N, number of subjects; SD, standard deviation; Sig., level of significance set at Po0.05; </p>

<p>%Δ, percentage change. </p>

<p>Letter contrast sensitivity was assessed using Thompson Test Chart PRO and recorded in the logarithm of contrast sensitivity (Log CS) units. Statistical significance was tested using paired t-test. </p>

<p>The calculated </p>

<p>percentage change from baseline to 36 months, calculated as the 36-month value minus baseline value divided by baseline value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change); the calculated </p>

<p>percentage change from baseline to 12 months, calculated as the 12-month value minus baseline value divided by baseline value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change); the </p>

<p>calculated percentage change from 12 to 24 months, calculated as the 24-month value minus the 12-month value divided by the 12-month value, multiplied by 100 ( </p>

<p>− , negative change; +, positive change); the </p>

<p>calculated percentage change from 24 to 36 months, calculated as the 36-month value minus the 24-month value divided by the 24-month value, multiplied by 100 (− , negative change; +, positive 
change). 
Group 1: 20 mg lutein and 0.86 mg zeaxanthin; Group 2: 10 mg meso-zeaxanthin, </p>

<p>10 mg lutein, and 2 mg zeaxanthin; Group 3: 17 mg meso-zeaxanthin, </p>

<p>3 mg lutein, and 2 mg zeaxanthin. </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>

<p>909 </p>

<p>Eye </p>

<p>in 43 (93%) study eyes, whereas 3 (7%) study eyes (one 
subject in Group 1 and two subjects in Group 3) exhibited 
a clinically meaningful progression along the AREDS 
11-step scale, and these observed changes were not 
statistically different between intervention groups 
(P = 0.29, Fisher's exact test). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study reports on the impact of sustained 
supplementation with different carotenoid formulations 
on serum concentrations of MP's constituent carotenoids, 
MP, visual function (BCVA and letter CS), and disease 
progression in subjects with early AMD. 
The strengths of this study include: (1) it is a 
randomized clinical trial comparing three different 
formulations containing some or all of MP's constituent 
carotenoids, with a follow-up of 3 years; (2) MP was 
measured using a validated technique at regular intervals 
throughout the study period; (3) assessment of visual 
function was not restricted to BCVA, and included CS; 
(4) assessment of AMD morphology was performed by an 
accredited reading centre in a masked manner. 
Serum response to supplementation reflected the 
carotenoid content of the supplement used. For example, 
serum L exhibited an increase in all three 
supplementation groups, but to a greater extent in Groups 
1 and 2, where intake of L was at least three times the 
typical dietary intake of this carotenoid. 16,17 Similarly, 
a significant rise in serum Z was noted following 
supplementation, but that was comparable across 
supplement groups, reflecting similar concentrations of 
this carotenoid in each of the three formulations tested. 
Finally, serum MZ response is noteworthy for several 
reasons. First, MZ was detected in the serum of patients 
supplemented with a formulation with no declared MZ 
content. However, we have shown that MZ is indeed 
present in commercially available formulations 
containing L, including Ultra Lutein, the Group 1 
supplement used in this study. 10 Finally, it is also worth 
noting that serum L and serum Z responses were 
unaffected by the presence of substantial concentrations 
of MZ (10 mg or more) in the formulation used, thereby 
allaying previously expressed concerns that the inclusion 
of MZ in a supplement may adversely impact upon the 
circulating bioavailability of the other two macular 
carotenoids. 
MP increased significantly in all groups at each 
eccentricity (with the exception of Group 1 at 1.75°) at 
3 years. It is surprising to see that MP did not increase 
at 1.75° in Group 1, given that L is the dominant 
carotenoid at this locus, and this seemingly 
counterintuitive observation might be because subjects in 
Group 1 were bioconverting L to MZ at the macula. 18,19 </p>

<p>Consistent with this hypothesis, only groups that received 
supplemental MZ exhibited significant augmentation of 
MP across the spatial profile of this pigment. 
In terms of MP increase over the course of the study, 
it was observed that MP continues to increase further and 
significantly in the third year of supplementation 
(but only in groups supplemented with meaningful 
concentrations of MZ) following a relative plateau in the 
second year of supplementation. Indeed, MP did not 
increase significantly between 12 and 24 months in any 
intervention group, at any eccentricity. Although the 
exact mechanism of macular carotenoid uptake has not 
been fully elucidated, it is plausible that there are several 
mediators (eg binding proteins, enzymes) that influence 
the capture, accumulation, and stabilisation of these 
carotenoids at the macula, 20 but further research is 
needed to understand these mechanisms. 
There was no significant change in BCVA over the 
course of the present study, other than a transient 
improvement between 12 and 24 months in Group 3. 
Murray et al 21 reported the impact of supplemental L on 
MP and visual acuity in patients with early AMD in 
a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, 
multicentre 12-month trial. At the end of their study, there 
was no change in BCVA in the L group, whereas BCVA 
in the placebo group had deteriorated significantly. 21 
In the present study, there was a nonsignificant increase 
in BCVA in all intervention groups, consistent with the 
view that BCVA stabilised over the 3-year period of the 
study in this cohort of patients with early AMD. The 
CARMA trial, a randomised controlled trial of L, Z, and 
coantioxidants vs placebo, reported no significant change 
in BCVA at 1 year, although there was a demonstrable 
benefit in terms of differential BCVA between 
intervention and placebo groups at 3 years. 22,23 Of note, 
visual acuity, which is a measure of the spatial resolving 
power of the visual system and remains the most 
commonly used measure of vision in clinical practice, 24 
is probably not sensitive enough to detect subtle but 
important changes in visual function experienced when 
monitoring subjects with early AMD. 25 
CS measures the threshold between visible and 
invisible at a given spatial frequency, and could be loosely 
described as 'faintness appreciation' 26 and is a better tool 
than BCVA for assessing visual function in early AMD. 25 
In Group 2 (a supplement with a formulation containing 
all three of MP's constituent carotenoids), there was a 
statistically significant improvement in CS at the lowest 
spatial frequency (2.4 c.p.d.), whereas this was not 
observed for Groups 1 and 3. At the highest spatial 
frequency (15.15 c.p.d.), letter CS improved in Groups 1 
and 3 at 36 months, but not in Group 2. At intermediate 
spatial frequencies (6 and 9.6 c.p.d.), however, only 
supplementation with formulations containing </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>



<p>Eye </p>

<p>appreciable amounts of MZ (Groups 2 and 3) resulted in a 
significant improvement in letter CS. Although some, but 
not all, previous studies have reported improvements in 
CS following supplementation with macular carotenoids 
in subjects with early AMD, our results suggest that those 
studies that failed to report an improvement in CS may 
be explained, at least in part, by a lack of MZ in the 
supplement formulation used. 23,27 Finally, an important 
and novel finding of the current study rests on the 
observation that further and significant improvements 
in CS are experienced beyond 24 months of 
supplementation with MP's constituent carotenoids, 
suggesting that sustained supplementation is indeed 
necessary to exert a beneficial effect on visual function. 
With respect to AMD, only three study eyes exhibited 
clinically meaningful disease progression (1 subject from 
Group 1 and 2 subjects from Group 3), and no study eye 
progressed to advanced AMD over the 3-year study 
period. This study is not adequately powered or designed 
to make meaningful comment on AMD progression. 
The current study compared the impact of 
supplementation with different carotenoid formulations 
on visual function, and our findings suggest that a 
formulation containing MZ yields benefits in terms of MP 
augmentation and in terms of CS enhancement. Further, 
sustained supplementation appears necessary, for at least 
3 years, if MP is to be augmented maximally and CS is to 
be optimised over that period of time. Of note, modest 
visual benefits were observed in the current study. Future 
clinical trials should examine the impact of 
supplementation with formulations containing MZ and 
Z at similar doses. The Central Retinal Enrichment 
Supplementation Trial (CREST), currently underway, will 
also add to our understanding of the role of the macular 
carotenoids, including MZ, on vision in healthy and 
diseased eyes. 28 
Limitations of the MOST AMD study include its small 
numbers and the fact that it is a single blind clinical trial 
with no placebo arm. With respect to the use of placebo in 
the current study, we believe that the findings arising 
from the secondary analysis of the AREDS2 may render 
the use of placebo in patients with early (including 
intermediate) AMD ethically questionable. 29,30 Of note, 
the term early AMD in this study includes patients with 
intermediate AMD (as defined by AREDS). However, the 
absence of placebo may render it difficult to demonstrate 
clinical efficacy of the different carotenoid formulations 
used in this study and our results should be interpreted 
with full appreciation of this limitation. We used the 
single-blind design because the current study was the first 
clinical trial to compare the impact of supplementation 
with three different carotenoid formulations (including 
MZ) on visual function in subjects with early AMD and 
therefore we wanted to monitor more closely the effects of </p>

<p>the three carotenoid formulations in terms of response 
among these subjects. Statistically, this exploratory study 
was underpowered for a direct comparison of the three 
supplements. Differences in effects between supplements 
were, in general, likely to be small, meaning that 
impractically large numbers of subjects would have been 
required to obtain statistically significant results. 
In conclusion, we report that the inclusion of MZ in 
a supplement formulation seems to confer benefits in 
terms of MP augmentation and in terms of enhanced CS 
in subjects with early AMD. An important and novel 
finding rests on the observation that sustained </p>

<p>supplementation with the macular carotenoids seems 
necessary to maximally augment MP and to optimise 
CS over a 3-year period in patients with early AMD. </p>

<p>Summary </p>

<p>What was known before 
K MP augmentation can be achieved with a variety of 
supplements. 
K The inclusion of MZ in a formulation appears to confer 
greater benefits in terms of visual function and 
augmentation of MP in subjects with early AMD at 
12 months. </p>

<p>What this study adds 
K Sustained supplementation in subjects with early AMD 
results in further augmentation of MP following 2 years of 
continuous supplementation, and confers visual benefit in 
these patients in terms of CS. 
K The inclusion of MZ in a formulation appears to be 
important if increases in MP, and consequential 
improvements in vision, are to be maximised in subjects 
with early AMD receiving supplements. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>JMN and SB do consultancy work for nutraceutrical 
companies in a personal capacity and as directors of 
Nutrasight Consultancy Limited. ANH is a 'honorary 
director' of Howard Foundation Holdings Limited and 
Nutriproducts Limited, which licence and supply 
nutraceutical ingredients. DIT is a consultant of Howard 
Foundation Holdings Limited. All other authors declare 
no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This study was funded by a grant from the Howard 
Foundation, Cambridge, UK. KOA and JMN (the 
principal investigator) are currently funded by the 
European Research Council (ERC), grant reference 
number: 281096. We would like to thank Industrial 
Orgánica and Macuvision Europe for providing the study 
supplements. </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>

<p>911 </p>

<p>Eye </p>



<p>This work is licensed under a Creative 
Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other 
third party material in this article are included in the 
article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not 
included under the Creative Commons license, users 
will need to obtain permission from the license holder to 
reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit 
http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>Macular carotenoid supplements in early AMD 
KO Akuffo et al </p>



<p>Eye </p>

</text></tei>