<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4615379" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Exposure to oxygen and light generates photooxidative stress by the bacteriochlorophyll a mediated formation of 
singlet oxygen ( 1 O 2 ) in the facultative photosynthetic bacterium Rhodobacter sphaeroides. We have identified SorY as an 
sRNA, which is induced under several stress conditions and confers increased resistance against 1 O 2 . SorY by direct 
interaction affects the takP mRNA, encoding a TRAP-T transporter. We present a model in which SorY reduces the 
metabolite flux into the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA cycle) by reducing malate import through TakP. It was previously 
shown that oxidative stress in bacteria leads to switch from glycolysis to the pentose phosphate pathway and to 
reduced activity of the TCA cycle. As a consequence the production of the prooxidant NADH is reduced and production 
of the protective NADPH is enhanced. In R. sphaeroides enzymes for glycolysis, pentose phosphate pathway, Entner-
Doudoroff pathway and gluconeogenesis are induced in response to 1 O 2 by the alternative sigma factor RpoHII. The 
same is true for the sRNA SorY. By limiting malate import SorY thus contributes to the balance of the metabolic fluxes 
under photooxidative stress conditions. This assigns a so far unknown function to an sRNA in oxidative stress response. </p>

<p>Microorganisms have to cope with oxidative stress in almost 
all environments and have therefore evolved sophisticated defense 
systems. A special type of oxidative stress is the so-called photoox-
idative stress, which occurs in the presence of light, oxygen and a 
photosensitizer. In photosynthetic organisms (bacterio-) chloro-
phylls act as photosensitizers, which transfer energy to ground 
state triplet oxygen generating highly reactive 1 O 2 . The response 
to photooxidative stress has been intensively investigated in the 
facultative photosynthetic alpa-proteobacterium Rhodobacter 
sphaeroides (reviewed in 1,2 ). Rhodobacter uses oxygen for aerobic 
respiration but induces the formation of photosynthetic com-
plexes when oxygen concentration decreases. The presence of 
blue light counteracts the formation of photosynthetic complexes 
at intermediate oxygen concentrations most likely in order to 
prevent the formation of 1 O 2 . 3-5 1 O 2 triggers a complex response 
at transcriptional and post-transcriptional level. 6-9 A main regula-
tor of this response is the alternative sigma factor RpoE, which 
directly activates a small subset of genes including the rpoHII 
gene. The RpoHII sigma factor subsequently induces a large </p>

<p>subset of genes, many of them with known functions in the oxi-
dative stress response. 6,10 Under non-stress conditions RpoE is 
inactivated by the anti-sigma factor ChrR, 11 which is proteolyti-
cally degraded upon 1 O 2 stress. 12,13 Many genes which are tar-
geted by RpoHII are also targeted by RpoHI, which is 
independent of RpoE and has a main role in the heat shock 
response. 14,15 1 O 2 does not only induce transcription of protein 
coding RNAs in R. sphaeroides but also of small non-coding 
RNAs (sRNAs). 9,16-18 sRNAs have been identified as compo-
nents of many bacterial regulatory networks and have important 
roles in the fine-tuning of adaptation processes. Trans-acting 
sRNAs target mRNAs which are transcribed from other regions 
of their genome and affect their translation and/or stability. 19 
The RNA chaperon Hfq is often required for the interaction of 
trans-acting sRNAs and their target mRNAs. 20-22 
The sRNA RSs1543 of R. sphaeroides is induced in response to 
photooxidative stress. 9 Here we show that RSs1543 responds to a 
variety of stresses and influences photooxidative stress resistance of 
R. sphaeroides. Therefore RSs1543 was renamed SorY for 1 O 2 resis-
tance RNA Y. We identified the takP mRNA, that encodes the 
extracytoplasmic receptor subunit of a TRAP-T transporter, as direct </p>

<p>© Fazal Adnan, Lennart Weber, and Gabriele Klug 
*Correspondence to: Gabriele Klug; Email: Gabriele.Klug@mikro.bio.uni-giessen.de 
Submitted: 01/05/2015; Revised: 03/09/2015; Accepted: 03/13/2015 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/15476286.2015.1031948 </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The 
moral rights of the named author(s) have been asserted. </p>

<p>www.tandfonline.com 
569 
RNA Biology </p>

<p>RNA Biology 12:5, 569--577; May 2015; Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC </p>

<p>RESEARCH PAPER </p>

<p>target of SorY and provide a model for the role of this sRNA in the 
photooxidative stress response. According to the model SorY regu-
lates TakP synthesis negatively during photooxidative stress to 
decrease harmful malate influx at high rates into the cell to favor the 
pathway shunt from the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA cycle) to the 
pentose phosphate pathway and Entner-Doudoroff pathway. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>SorY is induced by different stress factors 
SorY was originally identified as an sRNA induced by 1 O 2 in 
Rhodobacter sphaeroides. 9 The sorY gene is preceded by an 
RpoHI/RpoHII promoter consensus motif and a transcriptional 
terminator structure is localized at the 3end. 15 Both sigma factors 
can activate sorY transcription but at least one of them is required 
for 1 O 2 -dependent induction. Rhodobacter genes under control 
of RpoHI/RpoHII promoters often respond to multiple 
stresses. 15,23 We therefore tested the expression of SorY under 
several conditions in the wild type strain. Indeed SorY is also 
induced by the organic hydroperoxide tert-butyl hydroperoxide 
(tBOOH), hydrogen peroxide, the super oxide generating para-
quat, by heat, by diamide, by NaCl, by CdCl 2 and by SDS/ 
EDTA (Fig. 1A, B). There was no effect of ethanol or poly-
myxin-B, which alters membrane structures. Thus, SorY is 
indeed induced by various stresses, but strongest induction was 
observed in response to singlet oxygen. 
To learn more about the function of SorY we constructed a 
strain lacking this sRNA (DSorY) and strains overexpressing the 
sRNA from its own promoter (2.4.1pBBRSorYi) or from the 
strong, constitutive 16S rRNA promoter (2.4.1pBBRSorY). The 
northern blot shown in Figure 1C verifies the lack of SorY in the 
deletion mutant and its strong overexpression in the other strains, 
which depends on 1 O 2 , when the native promoter is present 
(2.4.1pBBRSorYi) but is very high even in absence of any stress 
in 2.4.1pBBRSorY. </p>

<p>Prediction and validation of targets for SorY 
Many sRNAs act on gene expression by base pairing to target 
mRNAs and influencing either the stability of these targets or the 
rate of translation or both. To get a hint on possible targets of 
SorY we compared the transcriptomes of a control strain har-
bouring an empty vector (2.4.1pBBR) and of the overexpressing 
strain (2.4.1pBBRSorYi) after 10 min of 1 O 2 stress by microar-
ray analysis (Fig. S1). From 3976 genes with a reliable A-value 
17 protein coding genes showed a log 2 fold change of &gt; 0.6 or &lt; 
¡0.6 between the 2 strains (Table 1). Putative interaction of the 
mRNAs transcribed from these genes and SorY were predicted 
by the <rs type="software">IntaRNA</rs> tool. 24 Table 1 shows the predicted parameters 
of genes with expression changes for which an energy value of 
less than ¡10 kcal/mol was calculated for a putative interaction. 
The effect of SorY on mRNA levels was confirmed by real time 
RT-PCR for RSP_2400, RSP_0097, sufC, and adhI (Fig. 2A). 
The microarray data for flgF could not be confirmed and 
RSP_0432 was not tested, since no function for this gene is pre-
dicted. Real time RT-PCR also demonstrated that deletion of 
SorY had an opposite effect on the transcript levels of these 
mRNAs than overexpression of SorY (Fig. 2A). 
To test whether the mRNAs are direct targets of SorY we 
applied an in vivo reporter system suitable for a-proteobacteria. 4 
Sequences predicted to bind SorY were cloned behind a constitu-
tive 16S promoter and translationally fused to the lacZ gene. 
This reporter construct was conjugated into cells either contain-
ing a vector control, or having SorY expressed from the 16S 
rRNA promoter. For reporter fusions harbouring sequences of 
RSP_2400, sufC, adhI and flgF the differences in b-galactosidase 
activity to the control strain were not significant, indicating no 
direct interaction of SorY with these mRNAs (Fig. S2). For 
RSP_0097, however, a 2-fold decrease of b-galactosidase activity 
was observed when SorY was overexpressed, indicating a direct 
interaction of the 2 RNAs (Fig. 3B). RSP_0097 encodes TakP 
(previously named SmoM), an extracytoplasmic solute receptor 
of a TRAP transporter suggested to transport a-keto acids. 25 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Induction of the small RNA SorY under various stress conditions shown by northern blot analysis of total RNA isolated from R. sphaeroides. SorY 
fold changes (FC) are normalized to the 5S rRNA. The quantification was done with <rs id="software-11" type="software">Quantity One</rs> Software (<rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">Bio-Rad</rs>). (A) The following reagents (and 
their final concentrations) were added to aerobically grown cultures at OD 600 of 0.4 and samples were taken immediately before (time 0) or 10 min after 
addition: 0.2 mM methylene blue in the presence of 800 Wm ¡2 white light, 300 mM tBOOH, 1 mM H 2 O 2 and 250 mM paraquat were added to aerobically 
grown cultures at OD 0.4 and samples were taken before and 10 min after the addition. (B) Semiaerobic cultures were shifted to 42 C at time 0 or the fol-
lowing reagents were added: 500 mM diamide, 500 mM NaCl, 10 mM CdCl 2 , 2.5 % ethanol, 1 mg/mL polymyxin-B or 0.005 % SDS along with 1 mM EDTA. 
(C) Altered SorY transcript levels in the overexpression strains and the knockout mutant (2.4.1DSorY) before and after 1 O 2 stress in comparison to the 
wild-type strain harboring the empty vector (2.4.1pBBR). SorY transcription in plasmid born overexpression strains is either constitutive due to the use of 
a 16S rRNA promoter (2.4.1pBBRSorY) or inducible due to the RpoHI/II dependent promoter of SorY (2.4.1pBBRSorYi). </p>

<p> 
Volume 12 Issue 5 
RNA Biology </p>

<p>SorY affects the stability of the takP mRNA 
Trans-acting sRNAs can have a direct effect on translation of 
an mRNA or its stability. However in most cases mRNA stability 
and consequently the mRNA level is also affected if the rate of 
translation is altered by an sRNA. Therefore the half-life of the 
takP mRNA was determined in a control strain (2.4.1pBBR) and 
in strain 2.4.1pBBRSorY, which constitutively overexpressed the 
sRNA. A clear difference in the decay rates was observed for the 
2 strains (Fig. 2B). When only taking into account the initial 
phase of decay, which followed a logarithmic kinetic, the half-life 
was about 1.6 min for the control strain but only about 1 min 
for the strain overexpressing 
SorY. This effect of SorY on 
takP mRNA half-life hints at 
a direct interaction of the 2 
RNAs, which leads to desta-
bilization of the target 
mRNA. </p>

<p>Single point mutations 
in SorY partially release its 
effect on takP 
The reporter gene study 
and the effect of SorY on 
takP stability indicated a 
direct interaction between 
SorY and takP. This assump-
tion was supported by an in 
vitro interaction study. Addi-
tion of SorY to a radio-
labeled takP mRNA segment 
resulted in retardation in a 
native gel. Addition of the 
unrelated sRNA PcrZ 4 or a 
segment 
of 
RSP_2591 </p>

<p>mRNA did not cause a retardation of takP (Fig. 2C). To further 
prove a direct interaction between SorY and takP mRNA in vivo 
we exchanged single nucleotides in the SorY sequence and tested 
the effect of the mutations on takP expression in the reporter sys-
tem. SorY sequences with point mutations at positions C39, 
C49 or C52 had a significantly smaller effect on takP expression 
than the wild type sequence (Fig. 3B). While overexpression of 
wild type SorY decreased expression levels of the takP reporter to 
about 50%, expression in the single mutants was only reduced to 
75-85 %. When compensatory mutations complementary to 
G49T or C52G are inserted into takP at positions ¡20 or -17, </p>

<p>Table 1. Expression level of genes passing the selection criteria of microarray analysis, which is a reliable A-value 12 and a log2 fold change of &gt; 0.6 or &lt; 
¡0.6 between the 2 strains 2.4.1pBBRSorYi and 2.4.1pBBR. We used the <rs type="software">IntaRNA</rs> tool to predict a putative interaction of the mRNAs transcribed from these 
genes and SorY. Predicted energy values and locations of the interaction sites are listed for genes deceeding a predicted energy value of ¡10 kcal/mol </p>

<p>RSP no. 
Gene 
Description 
Ratio [log2 FC] 
Energy [kcal/mol] 
Position SorY 
Position mRNA </p>

<p>RSP_2400 
ABC putrescine transporter, ATPase subunit 
¡0.76 
¡11.39 
35 -51 
¡13 -2 
RSP_0097 
takP 
TRAP-T family transporter, DctP subunit bind prot 
¡0.65 
¡17.61 
39 -75 
¡44 -¡7 
RSP_2401 
putative 6-aminohexanoate-cyclic-dimer hydrolase 
¡0.65 
RSP_0437 
sufC 
Suf C, ATPase 
¡0.65 
¡12.66 
42 -52 
558 -568 
RSP_0843 
Conserved protein containing sulfotransfer domain 
¡0.62 
RSP_0432 
hypothetical protein 
¡0.61 
¡12.43 
3 -35 
¡10 -28 
RSP_0433 
hypothetical protein 
¡0.61 
RSP_3881 
flgF 
possible flagellar basal-body ROD protein FLGF 
0.62 
¡17.50 
38 -55 
100 -116 
RSP_2579 
cycB 
cytochrome c553i 
0.65 
RSP_7367 
AbrB protein (AidB regulator) 
0.67 
RSP_3945 
Carbohydrate kinase, PfkB 
0.67 
RSP_3449 
Putative allophanate hydrolase subunit 2 
0.74 
RSP_2632 
argI 
Arginase 
0.82 
RSP_2580 
xoxJ 
putative methanol oxidation protein 
0.83 
RSP_2577 
cycI 
isocytochrome c2 
1.04 
RSP_2578 
xoxF 
putative pqq dehydrogenase protein(EC:1.1.99.8) 
1.11 
¡12.56 
3 -50 
128 -165 
RSP_2576 
adhI 
Alcohol dehydrogenase class III(EC:1.2.1.1) 
1.15 
¡10.01 
37 -50 
¡16 -¡2 </p>

<p>Figure 2. (A) Validation of microarray results by real-time RT-PCR and expression changes in a SorY deletion strain 
for putative SorY target genes. Relative expression of strain 2.4.1pBBRSorY is shown in relation to expression in the 
control strain 2.4.1pBBR, whereas the relative expression of the SorY deletion strain is shown in relation to the 
parental wild-type strain. Real-time RT-PCR data represents the mean of 3 independent experiments. Error bars 
indicate the standard deviation. (B) Effect of SorY overexpression on takP mRNA stability. The half-life of the takP 
mRNA in the control strain pBBR and strain pBBRSorY was calculated based on real-time RT-PCR with total RNA iso-
lated from cultures at several time points after the addition of rifampicin. Values are normalized to the 16S rRNA. 
The data represents the mean of 3 independent experiments. (C) Binding of takP and SorY in vitro. Band shift exper-
iment with 150 fmol 32 P-labeled takP (15 nM) fragment of 92 nucleotides length incubated with increasing concen-
trations of unlabeled SorY at 32 C for 20 min. Unlabeled sRNA SorY was added in a equimolar concentration 
(15 nM) to the labeled takP fragment or in 10 fold (150 nM) or 100 fold (1.5 mM) molar excess. As control 150 fmol 
of 32 P-labeled takP fragment were incubated with water, the sRNA PcrZ (1.5 mM) or with an mRNA fragment of 
RSP_2591 (1.5 mM) in 100 fold excess. </p>

<p>www.tandfonline.com 
571 
RNA Biology </p>

<p>respectively, binding to the corresponding mutated SorY coun-
terparts could not be restored as we did not observe any signifi-
cant decrease in b-galactosidase activity. The lack of restoration 
is most likely due to altered secondary structure of the sRNA after 
single nucleotide exchanges, which in all cases leads to an 
extended stem-loop in the sRNAs seed region (Fig. S3). More-
over, predicted energy values for the interaction of mutated SorY 
with corresponding compensatory mutated takP do not reach the 
value predicted for the original sequence (Table S1). We also 
tested the effect of the wild type SorY on the takP reporter with 
point mutations at position ¡20 or ¡17. Both point mutations 
led to a significantly smaller effect of SorY on reporter expression 
in comparison to the reporter plasmid with the original takP 
sequence.To further confirm the interaction of SorY with takP, 
the takP::lacZ reporter plasmid was used to measure b-galactosi-
dase activity in a SorY and hfq deletion strain in relation to their 
isogenic wild type strain. In both strains expression levels of the 
takP reporter increased about 50% (Fig. 3C). In total these </p>

<p>results support the view that SorY reduces takP mRNA levels in 
an Hfq-dependent manner. SorY was previously shown to inter-
act with Hfq. 26 </p>

<p>Effect of SorY and takP on resistance to 1 O 2 
We performed zone of inhibition assays, to further character-
ize the role of SorY in the photooxidative stress response. Consti-
tutive overexpression of SorY conferred increased resistance, 
while deletion of SorY resulted in higher sensitivity against 1 O 2 
(Fig. 4A). However, SorY overexpression had no effect on resis-
tance in strains lacking Hfq. These data indicate an important 
role of SorY in the stress response which is dependent on Hfq. 
If the increased stress resistance of a strain overexpressing SorY 
was due to the negative regulation of the sRNA on the expression 
of takP, a mutant lacking the takP gene should show a similar 
phenotype. Indeed a takP deletion strain also showed increased 
resistance to 1 O 2 in comparison to its isogenic wild type 
(Fig. 4A). Although the mutant was derived from a 2.4.1 strain, 
we used the original parental strain from which the mutant was 
generated as a control, since originally identical strains often 
show some genetic diversification when maintained in different 
laboratories. We designate the parental strain to the takP mutant 
2.4.1*. Interestingly, overexpression of SorY in strain 
2.4.1*DtakP did not affect resistance at all in comparison to the 
same strain harbouring the empty vector (Fig. 4A). In summary 
these results suggest that SorY supports the 1 O 2 defense primarily 
through takP under these experimental conditions. </p>

<p>The SorY phenotype depends on growth on malate 
Two homologues of TakP in R. capsulatus were previously 
characterized. DctP2 (RCAP_rcc02417; 81% sequence identity) 
was shown to bind a-keto acids in vitro 27 whereas DctP3 
(RCAP_rcc03024; 45% sequence identity) was needed for the </p>

<p>Figure 3. (A) SorY-takP seed region as predicted by <rs type="software">IntaRNA</rs>. Single 
nucleotide exchanges of SorY and takP are indicated by arrows. Position 
C1 of the mRNA refers to the translational start site. (B) Relative b-galac-
tosidase activity of the lacZ-based in vivo reporter system. Activity in the 
control strains containing the takP::lacZ, takP-17::lacZ or takP-20::lacZ 
reporter fusions and plasmid pBBR is set to 100% (open bar). Activities 
for all other combinations are calculated in relation to their respective 
control. Activity in the strain containing the reporter fusion and plasmid 
pBBRSorY is indicated by a solid bar. Gray bars represent strains overex-
pressing SorY with a single mutation at 3 different locations and the 
compensatory mutations of takP in the reporter plasmid. (C) Relative 
b-galactosidase activity of the in vivo reporter takP::lacZ in wild type R. 
sphaeroides compared to DSorY and Dhfq knockout strains. Activity in 
the control strain containing the reporter fusion is set to 100 % (open 
bar). For each strain, 3 independent biological experiments with techni-
cal duplicates were performed. Error bars indicate standard deviations. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effect of SorY expression levels on resistance against 1 O 2 stress 
visualized by inhibition zones. Comparison of strains with different SorY 
levels, in wild type, DtakP-or Dhfq-background. Zones of inhibition for 
the different strains are shown in relation to the zones determined for 
their respective control strain set to 100% (open bar). Assays were per-
formed on media with malate (A) or lactate (B) as main carbon source. 
The asterisk highlights the parental wild type to the DtakP mutant. Error 
bars indicate the standard deviation of biological triplicates. </p>

<p> 
Volume 12 Issue 5 
RNA Biology </p>

<p>uptake of the C4-dicarboxylates malate, succinate, and fumarate 
in vivo. 28,29 In this study malate was used as main carbon source. 
To confirm that resistance to 1 O 2 conferred by an overexpression 
of SorY or a deletion of takP (Fig. 4A), is due to altered malate 
import, we performed zone of inhibition assays with lactate as 
main carbon source (Fig. 4B). Smaller zones of inhibition were 
observed on media containing lactate compared to malate media 
(data not shown). Therefore the methylene blue concentration 
was increased for further assays on lactate media to achieve evalu-
able inhibition zones. On lactate there was no difference in size 
of inhibition zones, when SorY overexpression, SorY deletion or 
takP deletion were compared to their respective control strains 
(Fig. 4B), strongly suggesting that TakP is involved in malate 
uptake. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>RSs1543, now designated SorY, was originally identified as an 
sRNA, which is induced in R. sphaeroides by 1 O 2 . Transcription 
from an RpoHI/RpoHII dependent promoter 26 suggested the 
influence of several stress factors on SorY accumulation which 
was confirmed in this study. Agents leading to membrane stress 
like ethanol and polymyxin B had no effect on SorY expression. 
Addition of ROS or reagents leading to ROS formation resulted 
in SorY induction, which was also observed in response to heat, 
salt or CdCl 2 . Non-redox-reactive heavy metals like cadmium 
can bind thiol groups causing glutathione depletion and oxida-
tion of sulfhydryl groups in proteins and consequently leading to 
oxidative stress. RpoHI/RpoHII of R. sphaeroides were previously 
shown to be activated by photooxidative stress caused by strong 
blue light, 30 the presence of methylene blue and light, 9,15,26 or 
by heat shock. 10 
The focus of this study is on the role of SorY in the photooxi-
dative stress response. To understand how SorY can affect this 
response, we searched for putative interaction partners and con-
firmed the takP mRNA as a direct target of SorY. The functional 
interaction of SorY and takP was confirmed by i) a decreased 
half-life of the takP mRNA when SorY is overexpressed, ii) the 
effect of SorY on takP expression in a reporter gene system in 
vivo, iii) a dose dependent shift caused by direct binding in elec-
trophoretic mobility shift assays in vitro, iv) a similar phenotype 
of SorY overexpression and a takP deletion strain and v) failure 
of SorY to influence stress resistance in a takP deletion mutant. 
Whether a decreased takP half-life in the presence of SorY over-
expression is due to a recruitment and cleavage of RNases or due 
to fewer protective ribosomes present on the mRNA, was not fur-
ther investigated. The results achieved with reporter assays sug-
gest that SorY decreases takP stability/translation in an Hfq 
dependent manner, since the reporter activity is strongly 
decreased by SorY overexpression but strongly increased in SorY 
or Hfq deletion strains. Single nucleotide exchanges in SorY, pre-
dicted to weaken the interaction between the 2 RNAs, indeed 
diminished the effect of SorY on takP expression in those assays, 
further supporting the view that both RNAs interact directly. It 
was however not possible to reverse the effect of the mutations by </p>

<p>introducing compensatory mutations, which is most likely due to 
an extended stem-loop in the sRNA seed regions after each single 
nucleotide exchange and lower predicted energy values for the 
interaction of mutated SorY with corresponding compensatory 
mutated takP. SorY overexpression led to an increased resistance, 
whereas deletion of SorY resulted in higher sensitivity against 
1 O 2 . This effect was clearly dependent on presence of Hfq and 
TakP. Thus SorY confers resistance to 1 O 2 stress by a negative 
regulation of takP expression in an Hfq-dependent manner. 
Since overexpression of SorY in the takP deletion strain did not 
affect resistance at all, we conclude that takP is the primary target 
of SorY promoting resistance under these experimental 
conditions. 
Our results raised the question how SorY influences stress 
resistance by affecting takP expression. In a wild type strain 
expression of takP is about 2-fold down-regulated upon exposure 
to 1 O 2 . 17 Studies on R. sphaeroides TakP were initiated due to 
the higher selenite resistance of a TakP mutant strain. Binding of 
a-keto acids to this protein was confirmed in vitro and the struc-
ture of TakP binding pyruvate was solved. 25 The natural ligand 
of TakP is still unknown 25 and lack of pyruvate in our growth 
medium excluded the possibility that the phenotype of the takP 
mutant was due to altered pyruvate import. Therefore we consid-
ered malate to be the possible ligand for takP, which was the 
main carbon source in our medium. One of the TakP homo-
logues in Rhodobacter capsulatus, DctP3 (RCAP_rcc03024), was 
shown in vivo to be needed for the uptake of the C4-dicarboxy-
lates malate, succinate, and fumarate. 28,29 To confirm that resis-
tance to 1 O 2 conferred by an overexpression of SorY or a 
deletion of takP, is due to altered malate import, we performed 
zone of inhibition assays with growth media containing an equi-
molar concentration of lactate as main carbon source. Lactate 
medium led to slower cell growth and higher resistance towards 
1 O 2 in comparison to malate medium. Using lactate as main car-
bon source abolished the effects of takP deletion, SorY overex-
pression or SorY deletion on resistance against 1 O 2 . We conclude 
that resistance to 1 O 2 is conferred by down-regulation of TakP 
levels by SorY and consequently decreased malate import. 
Malate is an intermediate of the TCA cycle. A tight regulation 
of its uptake might be necessary, since very high amounts of 
malate could be dispensable or even harmful during oxidative 
stress. Several studies reported during the last years that oxidative 
stress redirects the metabolic flux from the glycolytic pathway to 
the oxidative pentose phosphate pathway (PPP) and Entner-
Doudoroff pathway (ED), while the fluxes associated with the 
TCA cycle are decreased. This metabolic shift leads to decreased 
production of NADH which can increase oxidative stress by 
transferring electrons to oxygen and increased production of 
NADPH in the PPP and ED, an important component in the 
oxidative stress defense. 31-35 Also up-regulation of some glyco-
lytic enzymes, i.e. fructose-bisphosphate aldolase and glucose-6-
P-isomerase was observed in E. coli during oxidative stress, which 
then leads to a glyoxylate shunt and subsequent decrease of 
NADH production. 32,36,37 
During menadione-induced ROS generation accumulation of 
pyruvate and malate, intermediates of the TCA cycle, was </p>

<p>www.tandfonline.com 
 
RNA Biology </p>

<p>observed. 38 We reanalyzed a previous transcriptome study in R. 
sphaeroides (Table S2) with respect to changes in the central car-
bon metabolism in response to 1 O 2 , which has not been reported 
for this organism so far. Our data revealed 1 O 2 to reduce expres-
sion of genes for some components of the TCA cycle, like genes 
for succinyl-CoA synthetase (sucC, sucD) and fumarate hydratase 
(fumC). At the same time genes for the pentose phosphate path-
way and Entner-Doudoroff pathway like glucose-6-P-dehydro-
genase (zwf), 6-phosphogluconolactonase (pgl), 2-keto-3-deoxy-
phosphogluconate aldolase (eda) are induced (Table S2). Addi-
tional expression of glucose-6-phosphate isomerase (pgi), fruc-
tose-1,6-bisphosphatase (glpX) and fructose-bisphosphate 
aldolase (fbaB) is induced to 
produce glucose-6-phosphate 
in gluconeogenesis, which 
then can be metabolized in 
ED and PPP to produce 
NADPH. 8,17,39 Interestingly, 
it was also shown that all the 
induced genes of ED, PPP 
and gluconeogenesis except 
glpX are part of the RpoHII 
regulon as is SorY. 10,40 
Moreover downregulation of 
sucC and sucD is also reliant 
on RpoHII. 10 
In Figure 5 we present a 
model for the effect of SorY 
on the metabolic flux and 
consequently on stress resis-
tance in R. sphaeroides. To 
combat oxidative stress the 
alternative sigma factor RpoE 
and subsequently RpoHII are 
activated. RpoHII induces 
the genes zwf, pgl, eda to 
switch from glycolysis to PPP 
and ED to reduce production 
of NADH and increase 
NADPH levels. In addition 
RpoHII triggers pgi and fbaB 
expression to strengthen glu-
coneogenesis. At the same 
time flux through the TCA 
cycle, which generates exces-
sive amounts of the prooxi-
dant NADH, is decreased by 
an RpoHII dependent down-
regulation of the genes sucC 
and sucD. In addition Rpo-
HII also induces expression 
of the sRNA SorY, which 
regulates TakP synthesis neg-
atively to decrease high but 
harmful malate influx into 
the cell and the TCA cycle </p>

<p>respectively. This represents a novel mechanism by which an 
sRNA confers resistance to 1 O 2 . Other sRNA were reported to 
contribute in the oxidative stress response by mechanisms differ-
ing from that of SorY function. In R. sphaeroides PcrZ counter-
acts the strong increase of photosynthetic gene expression upon a 
drop in oxygen tension 4 and therefore also bacteriochlorophyl a 
mediated generation of 1 O 2 . In Enterobacteria the sRNA OxyS 
is induced upon exposure to H 2 O 2 and negatively influences 
translation of the transcription factor FhlA and of the stationary 
phase specific alternative sigma factor RpoS for the benefit of the 
oxidative stress response. 41,42 Furthermore, a tight regulation of 
iron availability in E. coli by the sRNA RyhB 43 and its </p>

<p>Figure 5. To combat 1 O 2 stress the alternative sigma factor RpoE and subsequently RpoHII are activated in Rhodo-
bacter sphaeroides. RpoHII induces expression of the depicted enzymes for pentose phosphate pathway (PPP), Ent-
ner-Doudoroff pathway (ED) and gluconeogenesis to generate the antioxidant NADPH and indirectly represses 
enzymes for the TCA cycle, which generates the prooxidant NADH. To favor this pathway shunt RpoHII also induces 
the sRNA SorY. SorY regulates TakP synthesis negatively to limit intermediate availability for the TCA cycle by 
decreasing malate influx into the cell. This assigns a so far unknown function to a sRNA in oxidative stress response. 
Abbreviations: G6P -Glucose 6-phosphate, F6P -Fructose 6-phosphate, F1,6P -Fructose1,6-bisphosphate, G3P -
Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate, 6PGL -Phosphoglucono-d-lactone, 6PG -6-Phosphogluconate, KDPG -2-Keto-3-
deoxy-6-phosphogluconate, Ru5P -Ribulose 5-P, SUC-CoA -Succinyl CoA, SUC -Succinate, RC -reaction center, 
LH -light harvesting complex, a RpoHII regulon described by Nuss et al. (2009) or b Dufour et al. (2012), c RpoHII 
independent down-or d upregulation due to 1 O 2 . 8,17 </p>

<p> 
Volume 12 Issue 5 
RNA Biology </p>

<p>homologues, e.g. in Pseudomonas aeruginosa 44 and Erwinia chrys-
anthemi 45 contributes to the defense against ROS, which are gen-
erated in the Fenton reaction. 46,47 In Enterobacteria sRNAs like 
MicF, MicC and CyaR are involved in changing the outer mem-
brane composition in response to oxidative stress. 36,48,49 How-
ever, SorY is the first example of an sRNA providing resistance 
during photooxidative stress by decreasing import of a carbon 
source to limit metabolic flux through the TCA cycle. </p>

<p>Material and Methods </p>

<p>Bacterial strains and growth conditions 
Bacterial strains used in this study are listed in Table S3. 
Details on their construction are given in Supplementary Mate-
rial and Methods. For cultivation of R. sphaeroides strains at 
32 C, malate minimal-salt medium was used 50 or malate was 
substituted by an equimolar amount of lactate. To grow the cells 
aerobically, cultures were either gassed with air in Meplat bottles 
to attain a concentration of 160 to 180 mM of dissolved oxygen 
or by continuous shaking of Erlenmeyer flasks containing 20% 
culture by volume at 140 rpm. For semiaerobic growth condi-
tions, having a dissolved oxygen concentration of about 25 mM, 
Erlenmeyer flasks containing 80% culture by volume were 
shaken at 140 rpm. When necessary kanamycin (25 mg ml ¡1 ), 
tetracycline (1.5 mg ml ¡1 ) or spectinomycin (10 mg ml ¡1 ) was 
added to liquid and solid growth media (1.6% agar). Photooxi-
dative stress conditions were generated as described earlier, 51 
except the final concentration of methylene blue (0.2 mM) 
(Sigma-Aldrich; M9140). Other stress conditions were generated 
by a final concentration of 500 mM diamide (Sigma-Aldrich; 
D3648), 500 mM NaCl, 10 mM CdCl 2 , 2,5% Ethanol (Carl 
Roth; 5054.3), 1 mg/ml polymyxin-B (Sigma-Aldrich; P4932) or 
0.005 % SDS along with 1 mM EDTA. Use of antibiotics was 
avoided in cultures and agar plates used for inhibition zone 
assays. To culture Escherichia coli strains, cells were continuously 
shaken at 180 rpm in Luria-Bertani medium at 37 C or grown 
on solid growth media containing 1.6% (w/v) agar. When neces-
sary kanamycin (25 mg ml ¡1 ) or tetracycline (20 mg ml ¡1 ) was 
added to the media. </p>

<p>Microarray analysis 
Microarray analysis was performed as described before (Mank 
et al., 2012). Total RNA, obtained from aerobically grown cul-
tures of strains 2.4.1pBBRSorYi and 2.4.1pBBR after 10 min of 
photooxidative stress, was chemically labeled with Cy3 and Cy5 
(Kreatech; EA-022/EA-023), respectively. Multiarray analysis 
was performed with the Bio-conductor package <rs type="software">Limma</rs> for R. 
On the basis of calculated MA plots, genes were considered reli-
able if the average signal intensity [A-value: 1/2 log2 
(Cy3£Cy5)] was 12. To filter out potentially insignificant 
changes among genes that passed the reliability criterion, a cutoff 
value was applied; i.e., those genes were retained whose average 
expression value of 2.4.1pBBRSorYi (a) compared with the aver-
age value of the control treatment 2.4.1pBBR (b) was either a 
log2 Fold Change of 0.6 or a ¡0.6. Microarray data are </p>

<p>deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus (http://www.ncbi. 
nlm.nih.gov/geo/; accession no. GSE63328). </p>

<p>b-galactosidase activity assay 
To confirm the predicted mRNA:sRNA interaction in vivo, 
b-galactosidase activity was measured in all conjugants obtained 
after transferring the respective reporter plasmids via di-parental 
conjugation. Three independent liquid cultures, inoculated with 
equal numbers of colonies, were grown semiaerobically and 
diluted to OD 660 0.2, before reaching stationary phase. Three 
samples of 0.5 ml were collected in early exponential growth 
phase (OD 660 0.4). Measurements of b-galactosidase activity 
were carried out as described previously. 12 </p>

<p>Sensitivity to ROS generating chemicals 
To measure the sensitivity of Rhodobacter sphaeroides to 1 O 2 
zone of inhibition assays were performed as described before. 12 
50 ml of semiaerobically grown culture (OD 660 0.5) were added 
to 5 ml of top agar (minimal salt medium containing 0.8% aga-
rose) and poured on top of an agar plate (1.6% agarose in mini-
mal salt medium). Filter paper disks soaked with 5 ml of 10 or 
50 mM methylene blue (Sigma-Aldrich; M9140) were placed on 
top of the plates. The diameter of the inhibition zones was mea-
sured after incubation for 48 h at 32 C in the dark or with illu-
mination by a fluorescent tube in case of methylene blue. </p>

<p>Isolation of total RNA 
Total RNA used for both RNA gel blot and real time RT-
PCR was isolated by the hot phenol method. 52 To remove 
remaining traces of DNA, samples were treated with 6 U of 
DNaseI (Invitrogen; #18047019) per 1 mg of RNA. Absence of 
DNA contamination was confirmed by PCR with primers target-
ing gloB (RSP_0799) (Table S4). </p>

<p>Half-life determination of the mRNA 
RNA samples were prepared as described earlier. 9 Half-lifes 
were calculated based on Real time RT-PCR with 20 ng of total 
RNA for the target gene while 0.2 ng of the total RNA was used 
for the standard gene 16S rRNA. </p>

<p>Real Time RT-PCR 
Real Time RT-PCR was performed as described earlier 50 
Measurements were done in a Bio-Rad CFX96 Real Time Sys-
tem and the corresponding program <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Bio-Rad</rs> <rs id="software-3" type="software">CFX Manager</rs> was 
used for data analysis. After normalization relatively to the rpoZ 
gene, 53 which encodes the v-subunit of the RNA polymerase, 
relative mRNA levels were calculated according to. 54 Primers 
and corresponding efficiencies are listed in Table S4 and 
Table S5 respectively. </p>

<p>Northern blot analysis 
Northern blots were performed as described earlier. 9 Oligo-
deoxynucleotides used for end-labeling with [g-32 P]-ATP (Hart-
mann Analytic; SRP-301) by T4 polynucleotide kinase 
(Fermentas; #EK0031) are listed in Table S4. A low stringency 
Church buffer was used for hybridization. 55 Membranes were </p>

<p>www.tandfonline.com 
 
RNA Biology </p>

<p>washed in 5£ SCC buffer C 0.1 % SDS. After exposure on 
phosphoimaging screens (Bio-Rad), images were analyzed by the 
<rs id="software-10" type="software">1D-Quantity One</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Bio-Rad</rs>). </p>

<p>Electrophoretic mobility shift assay 
Templates for in vitro transcription by T7 RNA polymerase 
(New England Biolabs; #M0251) of SorY (86nt), PcrZ (136nt), 
the takP mRNA (92nt) and the RSP_2591 (177nt) mRNA 
(both fragments containing 5 0 UTR and the beginning of the 
coding sequence) were generated from corresponding primer 
pairs listed in Table S4. [a-32 P]-UTP (Hartmann Analytic; FP-
210) was used to label takP transcripts internally. In vitro tran-
scripts were treated with DNaseI (Promega; M6101) prior to gel 
purification. RNA band shift experiments were performed in 1£ 
structure buffer (Ambion) in a total reaction mixture volume of 
10 ml as follows. Transcripts were heated (90 C; 10 min), cooled 
down to 4 C and renatured at 32 C separately. 150 fmol of 
labeled takP RNA was incubated at 32 C for 20 min with unla-
beled SorY (ratios 1:1, 1:10, 1:100) or as controls with water, 
unspecific sRNA (PcrZ) and mRNA (RSP_2591) in 100 fold 
molar excess. Binding reactions were mixed with 3 ml of native 
loading dye (50% glycerol, 0.5£ TBE, 0.1% bromophenol blue) </p>

<p>and ran on native 6% polyacrylamide gels in 0.25£ TBE buffer 
at 150 V for 2 h. </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>No potential conflicts of interest were disclosed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank David Pignol for providing us with the takP dele-
tion strain, Fabian Billenkamp for the control substrate 
RSP2591 and student assistant Marcel Volk for support during 
the revision. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by Deutsche Forschungsgemein-
schaft (Kl563/20-2 and International Research Training Group 
GRK1384) and Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst. </p>

<p>Supplemental Material </p>

<p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed on the 
publisher's website. </p>



<p> 
Volume 12 Issue 5 
RNA Biology </p>



<p>www.tandfonline.com 
 
RNA Biology </p>

</text></tei>