<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4985394" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Bisphenol A (BPA) is an environmental endocrine disruptor </p>

<p>that has been associated with cardiovascular outcomes in previous 
observational studies. We aimed to examine the relationships of urinary 
BPA levels with hypertension and early macrovascular diseases. 
This is a cross-sectional study. From June through August 2009, 
3246 participants ages 40 years or older were enrolled from Baoshan 
District, Shanghai, China. Logistic regression modes were used to 
estimate the odds ratios (ORs) for prevalent risk of hypertension, 
elevated carotid intima-media thickness (CIMT), arterial stiffness, 
and peripheral artery disease (PAD) with multivariable adjustment. 
We also performed stratification analysis by age and sex. 
The median (interquartile range) for BPA was 0.81 (0.48, 1.45) ng/ 
mL, which is notably lower than previously reported in the United States 
and other Western countries. Urinary BPA concentrations were nega-
tively associated with hypertension (multivariable-adjusted OR for the 
highest versus lowest BPA quartile ¼ 0.61; 95% confidence interval 
[CI]: 0.46, 0.80), elevated CIMT (OR ¼ 0.64; 95% CI: 0.47, 0.87), and </p>

<p>arterial stiffness (OR ¼ 0.62; 95% CI: 0.44, 0.87). The corresponding 
OR for PAD (60 cases total) was not significant (OR ¼ 0.89; 95% CI: 
0.28, 2.80). The negative associations of BPA with hypertension, 
elevated CIMT, and arterial stiffness were consistent by age and sex 
stratifications, and were stronger among participants !60 versus &lt;60 
years of age, and among women than men. 
In contrast with previous investigations, our study suggests negative 
associations of BPA exposure with hypertension and early macrovas-
cular diseases among middle-aged and elderly Chinese. Future inves-
tigations are needed to draw more definite conclusions and generalize to 
other populations. </p>

<p>(Medicine 94(43):e1814) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ABI = Ankle-Brachial Index, ba-PWV = brachial-
ankle pulse wave velocity, BPA = bisphenol A, CI = confidence 
intervals, CIMT = carotid intima-media thickness, DBP = diastolic 
blood pressure, HDL-C = high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, IQR 
= interquartile range, LDL-C = low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, 
OR = odds ratio, PAD = peripheral artery disease, SBP = systolic 
blood pressure, SD = standard deviation. </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>isphenol A (BPA) is one of the world's most widely 
manufactured chemicals, with more than 2.2 million tons 
produced each year. 
1,2 Human population is widely and con-
tinuously exposed to BPA through food, drinking water, der-
mal exposures and inhalation of dusts. Detectable urinary 
BPA levels have been found to be present in 93% to 95% of 
children and adults in national surveys conducted in United 
States. 
3,4 BPA is considered as an environmental endocrine 
disruptor. 
5-7 Experimental and epidemiological studies have 
suggested that BPA exposure may be related to diabetes, </p>

<p>7-9 </p>

<p>cardiovascular disease, 
8 thyroid disease, 
10,11 obesity, and insu-
lin resistance. </p>

<p>5,6,12,13 </p>

<p>Hypertension is a major public health problem worldwide 
and is a core risk factor for cardiovascular disease. Macrovascular 
complications are major target organ damages in hypertension. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>The markers of the deterioration of macrovascular structure and 
function, such as carotid intima-media thickness (CIMT), bra-
chial-ankle pulse wave velocity (ba-PWV), and Ankle-Brachial 
Index (ABI), are predictors for cardiovascular disease. </p>

<p>15-17 </p>

<p>Recent epidemiological studies have reported that higher levels 
of urinary BPA were associated with hypertension, 
18,19 cardio-
vascular disease, 
8 coronary, and peripheral artery disease 
(PAD). 
20,21 Urinary BPA levels in Chinese adults are notably 
lower than those reported in the United States. 
4,9,22 Until recently, 
no previous study to our knowledge has examined the relation-
ships of urinary BPA levels with hypertension and early </p>

<p>Editor: Ahmet Aykan. 
Received: May 13, 2015; revised: September 18, 2015; accepted: 
September 22, 2015. 
From the State Key Laboratory of Medical Genomics, Key Laboratory for 
Endocrine and Metabolic Diseases of Ministry of Health, the National 
Clinical Research Center for Metabolic Diseases, and Shanghai Clinical 
Center for Endocrine and Metabolic Diseases, Rui Jin Hospital, Shanghai 
Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, Shanghai, China (TW, MX, YX, 
JL, ML, YC, WW, YB, GN) and Department of Pathology, Johns Hopkins 
University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA (SL). 
Correspondence: Yufang Bi, Key Laboratory for Endocrine and Metabolic 
Diseases of Ministry of Health, Department of Endocrine and Metabolic 
Diseases, Rui Jin Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of 
Medicine, 197 Rui-Jin 2nd Road, Shanghai 200025, China (e-mail: 
byf10784@rjh.com.cn). Shenghan Lai, Department of Pathology, Johns 
Hopkins University School of Medicine, 600N Wolfe Street, Pathology 
301, Baltimore, MD 21287, USA (e-mail: slai@jhmi.edu). 
TW and MX contributed equally to this article. 
This work was supported by the grants 2013BAI09B13 from the National 
Clinical Research Center for Metabolic Diseases, 81321001, 81390350, 
81222008, 81471059, 81130016, and 81500610 from the National 
Natural Science Foundation of China, the Shanghai Municipal of Science 
and Technology (13495810200), Shu Guang Project of Shanghai 
Municipal Education Commission and Shanghai Education Develop-
ment Foundation (12SG21), SMC-Chen Xing Young Scholars Program 
of Shanghai Jiao Tong University (2012), the 'Yang Fan Project for 
Young Scientist' of Shanghai Science and Technology Committee 
(15YF1410100), and the Youth Scientific Research Project of Shanghai 
Municipal Health and Family Planning Commission (20144Y0109). 
The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0, where it is 
permissible to download, share and reproduce the work in any medium, 
provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or 
used commercially. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000001814 </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OBSERVATIONAL STUDY </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>macrovascular diseases in Chinese population. The objective of 
this study was to examine the relationship between urinary BPA 
levels, a marker of BPA exposure, and hypertension and early 
macrovascular diseases in Chinese adults. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Study Design and Sample </p>

<p>Study participants were enrolled from Songnan Com-
munity in Baoshan District, Shanghai, China, as reported 
previously. 
9,11,23 During June and July 2008, 10,185 residents 
ages 40 years or older participated in a health examination, and 
were classified into 1 of 3 groups (normal glucose regulation, 
impaired glucose regulation, and diabetes) according to fasting 
glucose levels. 
9 From June to August 2009, we randomly 
selected 4012 participants from each group, and among these 
participants, 3455 participants with blood and urine samples 
available were included in this study. We excluded participants 
with missing data for urinary BPA concentration (n ¼ 32), 
hypertension (n ¼ 51), elevated CIMT (n ¼ 14), or arterial 
stiffness (n ¼ 112), and finally 3246 participants (1295 men 
and 1951 women) were included in final analysis. All study 
participants have provided written informed consent. The study 
protocol has been approved by the Committee on Human 
Research at Rui Jin Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University 
School of Medicine. </p>

<p>Clinical and Biochemical Measurements </p>

<p>Interviews about the sociodemographic characteristics, life-
style factors, medical history, and family history were conducted 
by trained personnel. We collected the information on hyperten-
sion medication by asking whether the participants have taken 
any hypertension medications (yes or no). Clinical examinations, 
including measurements of weight, height, waist circumference, 
and blood pressure were performed by experienced nurses 
according to a standard protocol. Body mass index was calculated 
as weight/height 
2 in kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Systolic blood pressure (SBP) and 
diastolic blood pressure (DBP) were measured using an electronic 
BP monitor (OMRON Model HEM-752 FUZZY; Omron Com-
pany, Dalian, China), on the nondominant arm in a seated position 
after resting for 10 min. We used the average value of 3 measure-
ments (taken at 5-min intervals) for analysis. 
Consistent with our previously published studies, 
11 all 
participants underwent a 75-g oral glucose tolerance test after 
an overnight fast, and blood samples were collected using BD 
Vacutainer 
1 vacuum blood-collection tubes (BD Company, 
Shanghai, China) at 0 and 2 hr during the test. Biochemical 
measurements were performed at the central laboratory in 
Shanghai Institute of Endocrine and Metabolic Diseases, which 
is certified by the College of American Pathologists. Blood 
glucose was measured on an autoanalyzer (ADVIA-1650 
Chemistry System, Bayer, Germany) using the glucose oxidase 
method. Serum lipids (total cholesterol, high-density lipopro-
tein cholesterol [HDL-C], low-density lipoprotein cholesterol 
[LDL-C], and triglycerides) and urinary creatinine were 
measured by an autoanalyzer (ADVIA-1650 Chemistry Sys-
tem). Diabetes was defined as fasting plasma glucose 
!7.0 mmol/L, or 2-hr oral glucose tolerance test plasma glucose 
!11.1 mmol/L, or self-reported physician diagnosis of diabetes 
or current use of antidiabetic medications. Impaired glucose 
regulation was defined as fasting plasma glucose !6.1 and 
&lt;7.0 mmol/L, or a 2-hr oral glucose tolerance test plasma 
glucose !7.8 and &lt;11.1 mmol/L, without a history of diabetes. </p>

<p>Morning spot urine samples were collected to measure 
urinary BPA concentration, using Eppendorf 10 mL centrifuge 
tubes (Eppendorf Company, Shanghai, China) which are made 
of polypropylene and free of BPA, delivered at 48C immediately 
and frozen at À808C within 4 hours of collection at the central 
laboratory. 
9,11 In order to prevent contaminations, sample pro-
cessing strictly adhered to the standard operating procedure at 
the central laboratory in Shanghai Institute of Endocrine and 
Metabolic Diseases. Urine samples were immediately stored 
and maintained at À808C during shipping to the Shanghai 
Institute of Materia Medica, Chinese Academy of Sciences 
for BPA measurement. None of the urine samples were thawed, 
refreezed, or aliquoted before measurement. Total (free and 
conjugated) urinary BPA concentration was measured by liquid 
chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry. 
9,11 The lower limit 
of detection for BPA was 0.30 ng/mL. The detection rate was 
88%, and for analysis purpose, we assigned a value of 0.15 ng/ 
mL for undetectable BPA concentration (N ¼ 386). </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Measurements of Early Macrovascular Diseases </p>

<p>The measurement of CIMT was performed by 1 trained 
sonographer, using a high-resolution B-mode tomographic 
ultrasound system (Esaote Biomedica SpA, Genoa, Italy), with 
a linear 7.5-MHz transducer. 
24 CIMT was measured on the far 
wall of the right and left common carotid arteries with 1.5 cm 
proximal to the bifurcation, and online at the end of diastole as 
the distance from the leading edge of the first to the second 
echogenic line, which represent the lumen-intimal interface and 
the collagen-contained upper layer of tunic adventitia, respect-
ively. We used the greater value of the right and left common 
CIMT for analysis. 
Participants were asked to have a rest of 10 to 15 min 
before ba-PWV examination. The ba-PWV was determined by 
Colin VP-1000 (Model BP203RPE II, form PWV/ABI) as 
reported previously. 
25 We used the greater value of the right 
and left common ba-PWV for analysis. 
For participants with at least 1 arm and weighting &lt;180 kg, 
supine SBP was measured using Colin VP-1000 (Model 
BP203RPE II, form PWV/ABI) after participants resting for 
10 to 15 min. 
25 For participants with conditions precluding the 
measurement of the right arm, left brachial artery SBP was 
measured. Left and right ABI values were calculated as the ratio 
of left and right ankle SBP to arm SBP, respectively. The 
smallest of the left and right ABI values were used in the 
analysis. It has been demonstrated that patients with ABIs great 
equal 1.5 are expected to have severe arterial rigidity, 
26 and in 
the present study, all participants had ABIs &lt;1.5. </p>

<p>Definitions </p>

<p>Hypertension was defined as SBP !140 mm Hg and/or 
DBP !90 mm Hg and/or taking regular antihypertensive medi-
cine. Participants in the highest 10% of CIMT (!0.8 mm) were 
defined as elevated CIMT. Upper quartile of ba-PWV 
(!1690 cm/sec) was regarded as arterial stiffness. PAD was 
defined as ABI &lt; 0.9. </p>

<p>27,28 </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC), and P values &lt;0.05 (2-sided) indicated 
statistical significance. We log 10 transformed variables with a 
skewed distribution to achieve a normal distribution. Basic 
characteristics were presented as mean AE standard deviation 
(SD) or median with interquartile range (IQR) for continuous </p>

<p>Wang et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>variables depending on normality, or proportions for categorical 
variables. To test for trend of characteristics across BPA quar-
tiles, BPA was modeled as an ordinal variable coding with 
regard to its quartiles as 1, 2, 3, and 4. We used linear regression 
model and logistic regression model to test P values for trend for 
continuous variables and dichotomous variables, respectively. 
To examine the association of BPA levels with hyperten-
sion and early macrovascular diseases, the participants were 
first categorized into quartiles of urinary BPA concentration, 
and multivariable logistic regression analyses were then per-
formed to calculate the odds ratios (ORs) and corresponding 
95% confidence intervals (CIs) of hypertension and early 
macrovascular diseases for each quartile of BPA with the lowest 
quartile as the reference group. Potential confounding factors 
were controlled for in multivariable logistic regression analyses, 
including age, sex, and urinary creatinine, which are closely 
related to the exposure levels and metabolism of BPA; and body 
mass index, waist circumference, smoking and alcohol drinking 
(never, former, or current), and education attainment ( 6, 6.1-
8.9, or !9 years), which are known risk factors for the out-
comes. A sensitivity analysis was performed with further 
adjusting for potential intermediates or consequences of the 
outcome, including total cholesterol, LDL-C, HDL-C, trigly-
cerides, and diabetes status (normal glucose regulation, 
impaired glucose regulation, or diabetes) and hypertension 
treatment (yes or no). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the basic characteristics of study partici-
pants according to BPA quartiles. Overall, median age was 58 
years (IQR, 52-68 years), and 40% were men. The median 
urinary BPA level was 0.81 ng/mL (IQR, 0.48-1.45 ng/mL) 
(data not shown). Compared with other participants, those in the 
highest BPA quartile were the youngest (on average) and had 
the highest proportions of men, current smokers, and current 
alcohol drinkers, and had the highest proportion with high 
education attainment (!9 years). Compared with participants 
in the lowest BPA quartile, those in higher quartiles had higher 
levels of body mass index and waist circumference, lower 
proportion of hypertension medication, and lower levels of 
SBP, ba-PWV, CIMT, HDL-C, and urinary creatinine. 
As shown in Figure 1, the prevalence of hypertension, 
elevated CIMT, and arterial stiffness gradually decreased from 
the first quartile to the third, but was similar between the third 
and fourth quartiles. The prevalence of PAD was highest among 
participants in the second BPA quartile, and no clear linear 
association was observed for BPA quartiles and PAD. After 
controlling for potential confounding factors, compared with 
participants in the lowest quartile, those in the highest quartile 
had a significantly lower prevalence of hypertension 
(OR ¼ 0.61; 95% CI: 0.46, 0.80), elevated CIMT (OR ¼ 0.64; 
95% CI: 0.47, 0.87), and arterial stiffness (OR ¼ 0.62; 95% CI: 
0.44, 0.87) (Table 2). BPA also was negatively associated with </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Characteristics of Study Participants </p>

<p>BPA Quartiles, ng/mL </p>

<p>P Value 
for Trend 
Characteristics </p>

<p>Quartile 1 
( 0.47) </p>

<p>Quartile 2 
(0.48-0.81) </p>

<p>Quartile 3 
(0.82-1.45) </p>

<p>Quartile 4 
(&gt;1.45) </p>

<p>Number 
819 
806 
818 
803 
-
Age, yr 
62.7 AE 10.2 
60.7 AE 9.9 
59.0 AE 9.6 
58.3 AE 9.6 
&lt;0.001 
Male sex, n (%) 
255 (31.1) 
327 (40.6) 
342 (41.8) 
371 (46.2) 
&lt;0.001 
High education attainment, n (%) 
201 (24.9) 
215 (26.8) 
239 (29.7) 
240 (30.3) 
&lt;0.001 
Current smoker, n (%) 
110 (13.4) 
170 (21.1) 
176 (21.5) 
219 (27.3) 
&lt;0.001 
Current alcohol consumer, n (%) 
86 (10.5) 
135 (16.8) 
122 (14.9) 
165 (20.6) 
&lt;0.001 
Body mass index, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>25.3 AE 3.9 
25.6 AE 4.1 
25.5 AE 3.7 
25.5 AE 3.6 
0.03 
Waist circumference, cm 
86.4 AE 9.8 
87.6 AE 9.9 
87.2 AE 9.8 
87.8 AE 9.7 
0.02 
Hypertension medication, n (%) 
57 (7.9) 
49 (7.0) 
53 (7.4) 
31 (4.5) 
0.02 
Systolic blood pressure, mm Hg 
141.8 AE 23.5 
139.4 AE 22.4 
137.8 AE 21.5 
136.1 AE 20.3 
&lt;0.001 
Diastolic blood pressure, mm Hg 
78.0 AE 10.8 
78.2 AE 10.2 
78.9 AE 9.9 
78.6 AE 10.0 
0.15 
Brachial-ankle pulse wave velocity, cm/sec 
1602 AE 443 
1527 AE 385 
1461 AE 343 
1453 AE 334 
&lt;0.001 
Ankle-Brachial Index 
1.12 AE 0.09 
1.12 AE 0.10 
1.12 AE 0.11 
1.12 AE 0.09 
0.72 
Carotid intima-media thickness, cm 
0.65 AE 0.15 
0.64 AE 0.14 
0.62 AE 0.13 
0.62 AE 0.14 
&lt;0.001 
Total cholesterol, mmol/L 
5.19 AE 1.04 
5.19 AE 0.99 
5.13 AE 0.99 
5.11 AE 0.94 
0.05 
Low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, mmol/L 
2.41 AE 0.71 
2.38 AE 0.69 
2.37 AE 0.70 
2.40 AE 0.64 
0.67 
High-density lipoprotein cholesterol, mmol/L 
1.39 AE 0.33 
1.36 AE 0.32 
1.34 AE 0.29 
1.32 AE 0.29 
&lt;0.001 
Triglycerides, mmol/L 
1.42 (1.00, 2.07) 1.44 (0.99, 2.10) 1.47 (1.02, 2.12) 1.46 (1.00, 2.10) 
0.27 
Urinary creatinine, mmol/L 
77.5 AE 3.7 
77.1 AE 3.9 
77.1 AE 3.6 
76.7 AE 3.8 
&lt;0.001 
Diabetes status, n (%) 
Normal glucose regulation 
371 (45.3) 
376 (46.7) 
406 (49.6) 
359 (44.7) 
0.23 
Impaired glucose regulation 
205 (25.0) 
160 (19.9) 
176 (21.5) 
170 (21.2) 
Diabetes 
243 (29.7) 
270 (33.5) 
236 (28.9) 
274 (34.1) </p>

<p>Data are mean AE SD or median (interquartile range) for continuous variables or number (proportion) for categorical variables. To test P values for 
trend of characteristics across BPA quartiles, BPA was modeled as an ordinal variable coding with regard to its quartiles as 1, 2, 3, and 4. Continuous 
variables were examined using univariable linear regression model, and univariable logistic regression model was used for dichotomous 
characteristics, such as sex, high education attainment (!9 years), current smoker, and current alcohol consumer. BPA ¼ bisphenol A, SD ¼ 
standard deviation. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 
Bisphenol A and Early Macrovascular Diseases </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>PAD, but there were relatively few cases (60 total) and esti-
mates were imprecise (for the fourth vs first quartile, 
OR ¼ 0.89; 95% CI: 0.28, 2.80). The associations between 
BPA and hypertension and macrovascular diseases were in 
dose-response manner (all P for trend &lt;0.05), except for the 
relationship with PAD. In the sensitivity analysis, we further 
adjusted potential intermediate variables, including total cho-
lesterol, LDL-C, HDL-C, log 10 (triglycerides), diabetes status, 
and hypertension medication, and the associations were not 
substantially changed (Table 2). 
Considering that urinary BPA concentration varied 
between men and women (median value of urinary BPA 
concentration: men, 0.90 [IQR, 0.56, 1.61] vs women, 0.76 
[0.43, 1.34], P &lt; 0.0001) and according to age (median value of 
urinary BPA concentration: age &lt;60 years, 0.90 [IQR, 0.55, 
1.57] vs age !60 years, 0.71 [IQR, 0.41, 1.26], P &lt; 0.0001), we 
further investigated the associations between BPA and hyper-
tension and early macrovascular diseases by age and sex 
stratifications. Associations of each 1-SD increase in urinary 
BPA with hypertension and early macrovascular diseases, 
stratified by age and sex are presented in Table 3. The negative 
association of BPA with hypertension and elevated CIMT was 
stronger in magnitude for older (hypertension: OR ¼ 0.61; 95% 
CI: 0.43, 0.86; elevated CIMT: OR ¼ 0.53; 95% CI: 0.39, 0.72) 
versus younger (hypertension: OR ¼ 0.73; 95% CI: 0.53, 1.00; 
elevated CIMT: OR ¼ 0.85; 95% CI: 0.50, 1.46), and with 
elevated CIMT and arterial stiffness were stronger in women </p>

<p>(elevated CIMT: OR ¼ 0.58; 95% CI: 0.39, 0.87; arterial stiff-
ness: OR ¼ 0.56; 95% CI: 0.38, 0.82) versus men (elevated 
CIMT: OR ¼ 0.71; 95% CI: 0.49, 1.02; arterial stiffness: 
OR ¼ 0.62; 95% CI: 0.39, 1.00), but the differences between 
stratum-specific estimates were not statistically significant (all 
P for interactions !0.05). There were relatively few cases (60 
total) of PAD, and the differences between sex or age strata 
were not statistically significant. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the present study, we found that urinary BPA levels 
were negatively associated with the prevalence of hypertension 
and early macrovascular diseases in 3246 middle-aged and 
elderly Chinese. The associations remained even after adjusting 
for potential confounding factors, intermediates, and potential 
consequences of the outcome. 
Previous studies have reported that urinary BPA concen-
trations were positively associated with self-reported heart 
disease in National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey 
(NHANES) 2003 to 2004 and NHANES 2005 to 2006, after 
adjusting for traditional risk factors. 
8,20 Recently, several epi-
demiological studies have suggested positive associations 
between urinary BPA levels and hypertension, 
18,19 cardiovas-
cular disease, 
8 coronary arterial disease, and PAD. 
20,21 Most of 
studies above-mentioned were conducted in western popu-
lations, except for 1 Korean study. 
18 Bae et al reported a positive </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Prevalence (95% confidence interval) of hypertension and early macrovascular diseases across urinary bisphenol A quartiles. 
(A) Hypertension, P for trend &lt; 0.0001; (B) elevated carotid intima-media thickness (CIMT), P for trend &lt; 0.0001; (C) arterial stiffness, P 
for trend &lt; 0.0001; and (D) peripheral artery disease (PAD), P for trend ¼ 0.26. Logistic regression model was used to test P values for 
trend of outcomes across BPA quartiles, and BPA was modeled as an ordinal variable coding with regard to its quartiles as 1, 2, 3, and 4. BPA 
¼ bisphenol A. </p>

<p>Wang et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>nonlinear dose-response association between urinary BPA and 
hypertension in 258 participants !60 years of age who did not 
report previous history of hypertension. The concentrations of 
urinary BPA (median value, 0.81 ng/mL; IQR, 0.48-1.45 ng/ 
mL) in the present study were low relative to concentrations in 
the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutri-
tion (EPIC)-Norfolk cohort study (median value, 1.3 ng/mL), </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>which reported a positive association between BPA and cor-
onary artery disease in a dose-response manner in a longitudi-
nal analysis. Urinary BPA concentrations in our study 
population also were lower than concentrations reported for 
other recent study populations (available median values range 
from 1.20 to 2.30 ng/mL, available mean values range from 1.79 
to 6.93 ng/mL). 
8,18-21,29 Different from the Korean study, in the 
present study, the associations between BPA and hypertension, 
elevated CIMT and arterial stiffness were negative and in dose-
response relationship. The most current study by Bae and Hong 
reported that consuming canned beverage and consequent 
increase of BPA exposure increased blood pressure acutely 
in 60 participants (56 women and 4 men) ages 60 years or older. 
It is an interesting study revealing a relationship between short-
term BPA exposure and acute effect on blood pressure. 
30 The 
association of chronic BPA exposure with cardiovascular risk is 
still to be evaluated in further longitudinal study. 
BPA is suspected to have a variety of effects in humans, 
and its estrogenic action is considered to be 1 of the major 
mechanisms. 
31 Estrogen has several important effects on the 
cardiovascular system. 
32 Estrogen alters the expression or </p>

<p>activity of ion channels, contractile proteins, and reactive 
oxygen species production and all of which may contribute 
to cardiovascular health. 
32-34 It is well-documented that estro-
gen improves vascular function and reduces atherosclerosis. </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>Experimental studies of mice have indicated that the athero-
protection is mediated by estrogen receptor-a and b, 
35,36 which 
have important roles in repairing blood vessels and controlling 
blood pressure. 
31,36 Estrogen is also important for maintaining 
and repairing the endothelium. This process appears to involve 
an estrogen mediated increase in endothelial nitric oxide 
synthase and cyclooxygenase. 
34 In humans, the incidence of 
cardiovascular disease differs widely among men and women, 
partly because of the variations in hormones. 
37 Studies have 
found that the incidence of cardiovascular disease is usually low 
in premenopausal women and tends to increase in postmeno-
pausal women, however, in postmenopausal women who 
receive estrogen therapy, the incidence can be reduced to 
premenopausal levels. 
37-39 Thus it is biologically possible that 
exogenous estrogen may have protective effects on hyperten-
sion and early macrovascular diseases. 
The exact mechanisms by which BPA exposure may affect 
the cardiovascular system are not fully understood. Experimen-
tal studies of rats and in vitro reported that BPA affects 
cardiovascular system mainly through inducing liver and oxi-
dative cellular damage, 
40 disrupting pancreatic b-cell function, </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>and promoting obesity and insulin resistance. 
6 Although hyper-
tension and early macrovascular diseases are risk factors for 
cardiovascular disease, experimental evidence of mice and in </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Associations of Urinary BPA With Hypertension and Early Macrovascular Diseases </p>

<p>BPA Quartiles, ng/mL </p>

<p>Quartile 1 
( 0.47) </p>

<p>Quartile 2 
(0.48-0.81) </p>

<p>Quartile 3 
(0.82-1.45) </p>

<p>Quartile 4 
(&gt;1.45) </p>

<p>P for 
Trend </p>

<p>Hypertension 
Case, % 
530 (64.7) 
467 (57.9) 
436 (53.3) 
432 (53.8) 
Age, sex, and urinary creatinine-adjusted 
1.00 
0.85 (0.69, 1.06) 
0.77 (0.62, 0.96) 
0.86 (0.69, 1.07) 
0.12 
Multivariable-adjusted </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>1.00 
0.71 (0.54, 0.93) 
0.66 (0.50, 0.86) 
0.61 (0.46, 0.80) 
&lt;0.001 
Elevated carotid intima-media thickness 
Case, % 
148 (18.1) 
128 (15.9) 
96 (11.7) 
92 (11.5) 
Age, sex, and urinary creatinine-adjusted 
1.00 
0.89 (0.67, 1.18) 
0.69 (0.51, 0.93) 
0.69 (0.51, 0.94) 
0.005 
Multivariable-adjusted </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>1.00 
0.89 (0.67, 1.18) 
0.67 (0.50, 0.91) 
0.64 (0.47, 0.87) 
0.001 
Arterial stiffness 
Case, % 
279 (34.1) 
209 (25.9) 
162 (19.8) 
161 (20.1) 
Age, sex, and urinary creatinine-adjusted 
1.00 
0.82 (0.65, 1.05) 
0.65 (0.50, 0.83) 
0.74 (0.57, 0.95) 
0.004 
Multivariable-adjusted </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>1.00 
0.74 (0.54, 0.99) 
0.55 (0.40, 0.77) 
0.62 (0.44, 0.87) 
0.001 
Peripheral artery disease 
Case, % 
15 (1.8) 
20 (2.5) 
15 (1.8) 
10 (1.3) 
Age, sex, and urinary creatinine-adjusted 
1.00 
1.71 (0.86, 3.40) 
1.50 (0.72, 3.14) 
1.10 (0.48, 2.49) 
0.78 
Multivariable-adjusted </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>1.00 
1.83 (0.74, 4.53) 
1.67 (0.65, 4.29) 
0.89 (0.28, 2.80) 
0.94 
Sensitivity analysis </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>Hypertension 
1.00 
0.72 (0.53, 0.98) 
0.61 (0.45, 0.83) 
0.60 (0.44, 0.82) 
&lt;0.001 
Elevated carotid intima-media thickness 
1.00 
0.80 (0.59, 1.08) 
0.70 (0.51, 0.97) 
0.64 (0.46, 0.89) 
0.009 
Arterial stiffness 
1.00 
0.78 (0.56, 1.08) 
0.51 (0.35, 0.73) 
0.59 (0.41, 0.85) 
0.001 
Peripheral artery disease 
1.00 
1.43 (0.66, 3.11) 
1.34 (0.58, 3.10) 
0.75 (0.28, 1.99) 
0.72 </p>

<p>BPA ¼ bisphenol A. 
Ã Multivariable-adjusted model was adjusted for age, sex, urinary creatinine, body mass index, waist circumference, smoking, alcohol drinking, and </p>

<p>education attainment. 
y Sensitivity analysis was further controlled for total cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, log 10 
(triglycerides), diabetes status, and hypertension medication, based on multivariable-adjusted model. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 
Bisphenol A and Early Macrovascular Diseases </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>

<p>vitro suggested that BPA also acts on cardiovascular system 
through a series of other ways, including inducing obesity, 
diabetes, and hormone and lipids dysfunctions. 
5,6,10 Further-
more, it has been suggested that the actions of estrogen and its 
receptors in the cardiovascular system differ by sex and age. </p>

<p>37,41 </p>

<p>In the present study, we observed that negative association of 
BPA with elevated CIMT were stronger in magnitude among 
those !60 versus &lt;60 years of age. Although it is plausible to 
speculate that as an exogenous estrogen, BPA may affect the 
cardiovascular system by mimicking estrogen, future research is 
needed to give a more clear demonstration on behavior of BPA 
in humans. 
The strength of the present study included the large sample 
size, and the understudied population. The present study has 
several limitations. Firstly, due to the cross-sectional nature of 
the study, we cannot establish that BPA exposure precedes 
hypertension and early macrovascular diseases. Longitudinal 
studies are needed to clarify the chronic effect of BPA exposure 
on health outcomes. Secondly, we did not collect data on diet 
behavior, and the specific hypertension medication categories </p>

<p>or dose. Thus, confounding by diet or medication cannot be 
ruled out. Thirdly, the BPA measures are from single spot urine 
samples, repeated measurements over weeks, months, or even 
years would improve the evaluation of a long-term exposure. 
Mahalingaiah et al 
42 measured urinary BPA concentrations in 
217 samples collected over weeks to months from 82 partici-
pants attending a fertility clinic in the United States. The authors 
reported that 63% of participants classified into the highest 
tertile of the geometric mean concentration of all samples would 
have been correctly classified based on a single urine sample. 
Fourthly, due to a generally lower level of BPA exposure in this 
population, it might be less likely to detect any possibly positive 
association between BPA and cardiovascular risk than in a 
population with a wider range of possible exposure levels. 
Fifthly, our study participants were restricted to middle-aged 
and elderly Chinese population. Therefore, age, race, and the 
BPA exposure levels should be considered when generalizing 
the findings to other populations. Further studies in prospective 
cohorts are warranted to verify our findings in other demo-
graphic or ethnic populations. 
In contrast with previously published studies, our study 
suggested negative relationships between BPA exposure and 
hypertension, elevated CIMT, and arterial stiffness in middle-
aged and elderly Chinese adults. Much about the actions of BPA 
on cardiovascular functions in humans remain unknown, and 
well-designed longitudinal studies including a wide range of 
BPA exposure levels, ages, and genders are imperative for 
confirming associations and understanding the mechanisms. </p>



<p>TABLE 3. Associations of Each 1-SD Increase in Urinary 
Bisphenol A With Hypertension and Early Macrovascular Dis-
eases, by Age and Sex Stratifications </p>

<p>Outcome and Group </p>

<p>Sample Size 
(Cases) </p>

<p>Multivariable 
OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>Hypertension 
Age, yr 
&lt;60 
1746 (763) 
0.73 (0.53, 1.00) 
!60 
1500 (1102) 
0.61 (0.43, 0.86) 
Sex 
Men 
1295 (771) 
0.62 (0.43, 0.88) 
Women 
1951 (1094) 
0.60 (0.45, 0.80) 
Elevated carotid 
intima-media thickness 
Age, yr 
&lt;60 
1746 (104) 
0.85 (0.50, 1.46) 
!60 
1500 (360) 
0.53 (0.39, 0.72) 
Sex 
Men 
1295 (279) 
0.71 (0.49, 1.02) 
Women 
1951 (185) 
0.58 (0.39, 0.87) 
Arterial stiffness 
Age, yr 
&lt;60 
1746 (167) 
0.50 (0.27, 0.94) 
!60 
1500 (644) 
0.53 (0.38, 0.74) 
Sex 
Men 
1295 (311) 
0.62 (0.39, 1.00) 
Women 
1951 (500) 
0.56 (0.38, 0.82) 
Peripheral artery disease 
Age, yr 
&lt;60 
1746 (12) 
0.31 (0.05, 1.71) 
!60 
1500 (48) 
1.16 (0.45, 3.04) 
Sex 
Men 
1295 (22) 
1.34 (0.31, 5.70) 
Women 
1951 (38) 
0.78 (0.27, 2.28) </p>

<p>CI ¼ confidence interval, OR ¼ odds ratio, SD ¼ standard deviation. 
Each 1-SD of log 10 -transformed urinary bisphenol A (ng/mL) was 0.41. 
Ã Multivariable-adjusted model was adjusted for age, sex, urinary </p>

<p>creatinine, body mass index, waist circumference, smoking, alcohol 
drinking, and education attainment. </p>

<p>Wang et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 43, October 2015 
Bisphenol A and Early Macrovascular Diseases </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 7 </p>

</text></tei>