<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4919585" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>BACKGROUND AND PURPOSE </p>

<p>The aims of the present study were to characterize the role of PAR1 in rat bladder under inflammatory conditions and determine 
whether a selective PAR1 antagonist, F16357, can prevent the pathophysiological symptoms of cyclophosphamide-induced 
interstitial cystitis (IC). </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL APPROACH </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry, contractile activity in isolated bladder and urodynamics were determined before and after 
cyclophosphamide treatment. F16357 was administered intravesically during the acute phase of inflammation, and effects on 
PAR1 and PAR1-related bladder contraction evaluated 24 h after cyclophosphamide injection. Urodynamics and associated 
voided volumes were recorded 7 and 24 h after cyclophosphamide. </p>

<p>KEY RESULTS </p>

<p>In control conditions, PAR1 was present only in some umbrella cells. Cyclophosphamide disrupted the urothelium and expression 
of PAR1 by all remaining urothelial cells. After F16357 treatment, urothelial damage was absent and PAR1 immunoreactivity 
similar to control tissues. Thrombin and TFLLR-NH 2 induced bladder contractions. These were increased in inflammatory 
conditions and antagonized by F16357 in a concentration-dependent manner. In telemetric experiments, furosemide increased 
urine production and voiding frequency for 60 min, 7 h after cyclophosphamide injection. Intravesical administration of F16357 
blocked these changes with a return to a physiological profile; 24 h after cyclophosphamide, the volume of micturition was still 
lower with no increase in number of micturitions. F16357 30 μM reduced the number of micturitions and improved bladder 
capacity, but did not affect diuresis. Under similar experimental conditions, lidocaine 2% induced comparable effects. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS AND IMPLICATIONS </p>

<p>PAR1 is expressed in rat bladder, overactivated in inflammatory conditions and involved in bladder function and sensation. 
F16357 could represent an interesting candidate for IC treatment. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>A, amplitude of micturition; BP, basal pressure; BPS, bladder pain The main roles of the urinary bladder are storage of urine and 
voiding at socially convenient moments. Several pathologi-
cal situations such as interstitial cystitis (IC) and bladder pain 
syndrome (BPS) are characterized by pelvic pain, inflamma-
tion and detrusor dysfunction. The symptoms of IC and BPS 
constitute a number of idiopathic heterogeneous disorders 
with unknown cause that are manifest as increased urinary 
frequency and urgency (Hanno et al., 2015). Unfortunately, 
at the present time, there is no effective treatment for these 
diseases. 
Cyclophosphamide (CYP)-induced cystitis is a well-
established experimental model of bladder inflammation 
and dysfunction due to the accumulation of its metabolite 
acrolein and damage to the urothelium in the bladder 
(Cox, 1979). In rats, an acute i.p. injection of CYP induces 
signs of pelvic pain (Saitoh et al., 2010), inflammation 
(Lecci et al., 2000; Auge et al., 2013) and alterations in 
urodynamic parameters (Hu et al., 2005; Dornelles et al., 
2014). Importantly, this acute model demonstrates many 
features of IC in humans. We have recently described a tele-
metric approach to evaluate, in the same conscious animal, 
urodynamic parameters in control conditions and after CYP 
injection (Monjotin et al., 2016). We now use this approach 
to evaluate drugs acting on lower urinary tract dysfunctions 
induced by CYP. 
Protease-activated receptors (PAR1, PAR2, PAR3 and 
PAR4) are a unique class of receptors that carry their own li-
gands tethered to the receptor complex. The protease cleaves 
the N-terminal part and allows receptor self-activation. 
Among these, the PAR1, a GPCR, is activated by proteolytic 
cleavage of the N-terminus by thrombin and trypsin 
(Dery et al., 1998). Some studies have shown that CYP 
induces an increased expression and function of the PARs in 
bladder (Dattilio and Vizzard, 2005; Moffatt, 2007). 
Proteases released during bladder inflammation play a key 
role in the urinary system and hyperalgesia in rodents, and a 
deficiency of PAR1 expression reduced bladder inflammation 
(D'Andrea et al., 2003; Saban et al., 2007). The intravesical 
administration of PAR-activating peptides results in a local 
inflammatory reaction (Saban et al., 2007), and thrombin 
stimulates the release of macrophage migration inhibitory 
factor (MIF), a pro-inflammatory cytokine, by urothelial cells 
(Vera et al., 2010). </p>

<p>Consequently, PARs seem to be involved in bladder dys-
functions. The involvement of PAR2 has been extensively 
studied (Moffatt, 2007). However, a definitive role for PAR1 
in IC physiopathology and associated bladder dysfunctions 
has yet to be established in functional models of lower 
urinary tract syndromes. 
The aims of the present study were to characterize the 
roles of PAR1 in rat bladder under inflammatory conditions 
and determine whether a selective PAR1 antagonist, namely, 
F16357, can prevent the pathophysiological alterations in 
CYP-induced IC. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Compliance with requirements for experimental 
design, statistical analysis and requirements for 
studies using animals </p>

<p>Seventy-six adult female rats (Sprague Dawley or Wistar Han, 
200-250 g; Charles River, l'Arbresle, France) were kept, at 
least two per cage (polysulfone type 1291H with shaving 
litter), at a constant temperature (22 ± 2°C), with controlled 
humidity (40-70%), controlled ventilation (more than 10 
changes h À1 ) and a regular light/dark cycle (12 h/12 h, 07 h 
to 19 h), with food and tap water provided ad libitum. 
Animals were acclimatized to their conventional environment 
for at least 5 days after their arrival. Music was broadcasted in 
all animal facilities and enrichment such as toys or cotton was 
given when compatible with the experiments. 
All animal care and experimental procedures were in ac-
cordance with the 2010/63/EU Directive on the protection 
of animals used for scientific purposes and French legislation 
decree n° 2013-118 and were approved by the internal Ethic 
committee (CEA-CEPC-110 approved on March 16, 2013). 
The experimental procedures used in the work described in 
this article were as humane as possible. Animal studies 
are reported in compliance with the ARRIVE guidelines 
(Kilkenny et al., 2010; McGrath &amp; Lilley, 2015). 
CYP-induced IC is a well-described model, and most of 
the bibliography on this model is on mouse and rats. Bladder 
telemetry has already been studied in rats and justifies the se-
lection of rats for these studies. Moreover, this work and espe-
cially the in vivo experiments rely on previously described 
experiments on bladder pressure evaluation by telemetry in </p>

<p>Tables of Links </p>

<p>TARGETS </p>

<p>GPCRs </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Enzymes </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>PAR1 
COX1 </p>

<p>PAR2 
Neutrophil elastase </p>

<p>PAR3 
Neuronal NOS </p>

<p>PAR4 </p>

<p>LIGANDS </p>

<p>Acrolein 
Lidocaine </p>

<p>Cyclophosphamide 
TFLLR-NH 2 </p>

<p>Furosemide 
Thrombin </p>

<p>GTPγS </p>

<p>These Tables list key protein targets and ligands in this article which are hyperlinked to corresponding entries in http://www.guidetopharmacology.org, 
the common portal for data from the IUPHAR/BPS Guide to PHARMACOLOGY (Southan et al., 2016) and are permanently archived in the Concise Guide 
to PHARMACOLOGY 2015/16 ( 
a,b Alexander et al., 2015a,b). </p>

<p>F16357 for the management of interstitial cystitis BJP </p>

<p>British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 2225 </p>

<p>rats. In all these experiments, no analgesia was given to 
the animals after CYP injection because evaluation of the 
effects of compounds was essentially based on bladder func-
tion related to sensation/pain. Nevertheless, a behavioural 
evaluation of the pain was performed regularly (presence 
of ptose, chromodacryorrhoea, hunched back, abdominal 
licking and/or piloerection) to ensure that internal critical 
end points were not exceeded and in compliance with 
ethical procedures. Moreover, animals were placed under a 
heating lamp for at least 4.5 h after CYP injection to avoid 
CYP-induced hypothermia. No animals had to be killed 
due to ethical issues. 
The rationale for the chosen group size, to obtain a repre-
sentative evaluation of pharmacological effect of tested 
compounds, was evaluated by a statistician and approved by 
the internal ethical committee. For preliminary in vitro 
experiments related to immunohistochemistry, in which no 
statistical analysis was performed, only three animals per 
condition were used, with a total of n = 9 animals. For other 
experimental conditions, the number of animals used is pre-
sented in figure legends. In organ bath chamber experiments, 
at least one strip was treated with vehicle on each day of the 
experiment to ensure the reproducibility of the test, thus 
explaining the difference in group size between F16357-
treated strips and vehicle-treated strips in both physiological 
and inflammatory conditions. The difference in group size 
observed between physiological and inflammatory condi-
tions in organ bath chamber experiments was related to the 
anticipation of a major impact of CYP on animal welfare 
below the end points at which the animals would need to 
be killed. However, no animals reached these end points, 
and the supplementary strips were included in the results. 
In the telemetric experiments, the difference in group size was 
due to a loss of bladder pressure signal. Randomization of 
animals was performed on body weight for in vitro experiments. 
No randomization was performed for telemetric experiments 
because the animals were reused for different groups. 
Data were not recorded blindly, but analyses were. Exper-
iments and audit were carried out in a quality environment 
assessed by regular audits conducted by the quality assurance 
unit and in respect of internal standard operating procedures. </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>In vitro evaluation of F16357 in 
PAR1-overexpressed conditions </p>

<p>Determination of ligand efficacy by [ 35 S]-GTPγS binding assay in 
COS-7 cells transiently expressing human PAR1. Receptor-
linked G protein activation of PAR1 was determined by 
measuring the stimulation of [ 35 S]-GTPγS (1000 Ci·mmol À1 ) 
incorporation, essentially as previously described (Wurch 
et al., 1999). Briefly, COS-7 cells were transiently transfected 
with pRK5-PAR1 plasmid, coding for the human PAR1, by 
electroporation. Membranes of COS-7 cells expressing 
human PAR1 were pre-incubated 30 min with F16357 alone 
or in the presence of TFLLR-NH 2 (3 μM) in a buffer 
containing 20 mM HEPES (pH 7.4), 0.1 μM GDP, 3 mM 
MgCl 2 and 100 mM NaCl. The reaction was started with 
0.4 nM [ 35 S]-GTPγS in a final volume of 500 μL in 96-well </p>

<p>plates, and incubation was performed for an additional 
30 min. Experiments were terminated by rapid filtration, 
and counting was performed using a Topcount microplate 
scintillation counter (Perkin-Elmer). Basal binding is defined 
as 0%. Efficacy is expressed relative to [ 35 S]-GTPγS binding 
stimulated by 10 μM TFLLR-NH 2 (=100%), and antagonist 
potency was determined against TFLLR-NH 2 (3 μM)-induced 
[ 35 S]-GTPγS binding. </p>

<p>Serum Response Element (SRE)-dependent luciferase activity in 
COS-7 cells expressing human PAR1. COS-7 cells were co-
transfected with plasmid expressing human PAR1 (1 μg) and 
the SRE-luciferase reporter gene (5 μg), seeded in 96-well 
plates, and luciferase activities were measured 48 h post-
transfection in serum-deprived cells as previously described 
(De Vries et al., 2006). F16357 was added 15 min before the 5 h 
agonist treatments. Luminescence was detected in a Topcount 
luminometer (Perkin-Elmer) and expressed as a percentage of 
TFLLR-NH 2 (1 μM)-induced SRE-luciferase response. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry experiments </p>

<p>CYP, 150 mg·kg À1 , or its vehicle (saline) was injected bilater-
ally i.p. in a final volume of 5 mL·kg À1 to induce bladder in-
flammation (T = 0). At T + 2.5 h, animals were anaesthetized </p>

<p>by isoflurane 1.5% (0.5 L·min À1 per animal), and the bladder 
was emptied. A catheter (PE-10) was inserted in the bladder 
through the urethra, and the intravesical administration of 
saline was performed. The urinary meatus was clamped, and 
the catheter was removed. After 60 min of exposure, the 
clamp was removed, the bladder was emptied and the ani-
mals were returned to their home cage to recover. Animals 
were placed under a heating lamp after the CYP injection 
for up to 4.5 h in order to avoid CYP-induced hypothermia; 
24 h after CYP injection, the animals were anaesthetized with 
pentobarbital (60 mg·kg À1 , 1 mL·kg À1 ) and killed by cervical 
dislocation and the bladders excised and fixed for 2 h in 4% 
paraformaldehyde in PBS. The bladders were then washed in 
PBS and transferred to solutions with progressively higher 
sucrose concentrations (10, 20 and 30%) to act as a cryo-
preservant. The tissues were subsequently 'snap-frozen' using 
isopentane. Tissue sections (7-8 μm) were cut at À25°C, 
placed on polylysine-coated slides and air-dried. Sections 
were washed in Tris-buffered saline (TBS), TBS Tween (TBS-T) 
and subjected to a TBS wash cycle for 5 min at each stage. 
Primary antibodies were diluted with PBS with 1% triton-X. 
Combinations of primary antibodies were then placed on 
each slide and incubated overnight at 4°C. Primary poly-
clonal antibodies included were against PAR1 (1:100; Santa 
Cruz, Cat No. sc-8202), vimentin (1:5000; BioGenex, Cat. 
No MU074-uc), COX1 (1:100; Santa Cruz, Cat No. sc-1752) 
and neuronal NOS (1:500; Santa Cruz, Cat No. 648) were 
used. These antibodies were chosen because they have been 
characterized at the molecular level for the specific epitope 
(see manufacturers data sheets). After overnight incubation, 
sections were washed in TBS, TBS-T and TBS and incubated 
with appropriate secondary fluorescent antibodies: mouse, 
goat and rabbit primary antibodies were visualized using 
donkey anti-mouse/goat/rabbit IgG antibody conjugate 
(Molecular Probes) Alexa Fluor 488 or 594 for 1 h at room 
temperature. Slides were then washed, a drop of 
Vectashied/DAPI was added, and covered with a cover slip. </p>

<p>BJP </p>

<p>N Monjotin et al. </p>

<p>2226 British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 </p>

<p>Sections were viewed using an Olympus BX61 fluores-
cence microscope with ×10, ×20 and ×60 objectives. Images 
were captured using an Olympus XM10 monochrome camera 
in 16-bit digital format and examined using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Image J</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>). </p>

<p>Isolated bladders contractility </p>

<p>At T0, CYP or its vehicle was administered as previously de-
scribed; 24 h after CYP injection, animals were anaesthetized 
with pentobarbital (60 mg·kg À1 , 1 mL·kg À1 ) and killed by cer-
vical dislocation. The urinary bladder was promptly removed 
and placed in oxygenated modified Krebs-Henseleit solution 
of the following composition (mM): NaCl 114, KCl 4.7, CaCl 2 
2.5, MgSO 4 1.2, KH 2 PO 4 1.2, NaHCO 3 25 and glucose 11.7 
(pH 7.4, oxygenated with 95% O 2 and 5% CO 2 ). The bladder 
was cleaned of connective tissue, the distal and proximal por-
tions were removed and the bladder was cut longitudinally in 
two equal strips. The strips were immersed in glass organ 
baths containing the oxygenated Krebs-Henseleit solution 
maintained at 37°C. 
After an initial stabilization period of at least 90 min at a 
basal resting tension of 1.0 g, strips were exposed to KCl 
50 mM to verify viability. After further stabilization and 
washing, one concentration of F16357 or vehicle (DMSO 
0.3%) was added to the bath for 30 min. Then, a cumulative 
concentration-response curve or the response to a single ad-
ministration of TFLLR-NH 2 (a selective PAR1-activating peptide) 
and/or thrombin (a native PAR1 protease) was performed. </p>

<p>In vivo experiments </p>

<p>Telemetric devices. The transmitters used for these 
experiments were PhysioTel HD-S10 (Data Science 
International), allowing pressure (accuracy ±3 mmHg) and 
activity measurements to be obtained in small animals 
(4.4 g and 3.1 cc). The pressure of each transmitter was 
calibrated at 3 points by the manufacturer. Calibration 
values were checked at three points (0, 30 and 100 mmHg) 
by a sphygmomanometer just before implantation and after 
the animal had been killed to ensure the validity of the data 
obtained. </p>

<p>Surgical procedure. Pre-operative analgesic (buprenorphine 
and ketofen) and antibiotic (enrofloxacin) treatments were 
given to all animals before anaesthesia (isoflurane 2-4%). In 
aseptic conditions, a small laparotomy was performed. The 
transmitter was placed on the right side of the abdominal 
cavity and sutured on the abdominal wall (silk 4/0) in order 
to avoid contact with the bladder. The pressure transducer 
was inserted in the dome of the urinary bladder and secured 
with a purse string (silk 6/0). After checking the pressure 
values, the incisions were closed with resorbable sutures 
(Vicryl 3/0 for abdominal wall and Vicryl 4/0 for skin). 
Animals received post-operative care (analgesic and 
antibiotic) for 2 days following the surgery. All animals were 
given a further recovery period of at least 1 month before 
being used for the experiments. 
Before cystometric analyses, all instrumented rats were ac-
climatized to the experimental environment and basal 
urodynamic parameters established for all telemetered rats 
using a furosemide challenge as described previously 
(Monjotin et al., 2016). </p>

<p>Measurement of urodynamic parameters by telemetry. Naïve 
instrumented rats received an injection of furosemide 
(Lasilix ® 10 mg·kg À1 , 2 mL·kg À1 , s.c.) to stimulate diuresis 
and were immediately placed in customized metabolic 
cages. Bladder pressure and voided volumes were 
continuously recorded for 60 min following the furosemide 
pulse. Cystometric evaluation was performed on conscious 
freely moving rats, and parameters recorded were 
micturition pressure (MP), basal pressure (BP), amplitude of 
micturition (A = MP-BP), inter-contraction interval (ICI) and 
voided volume per micturition (V). 
After a washout period, another set of experiments was 
performed on the same animals. At T0, CYP 150 mg·kg À1 or 
its vehicle (saline) was administered. At T + 2.5 h, animals 
were anaesthetized using isoflurane 1.5% (0.5 L·min À1 per 
animal), and the bladder was emptied by gentle pressure on 
the abdominal wall. A catheter (PE-10) was inserted in the 
bladder through the urethra, and the intravesical administra-
tion of saline, F16357 30 μM or lidocaine 2% was performed. 
The urinary meatus was lightly clamped, and the catheter was 
removed. After 60 min, the clamp was removed, the bladder 
was emptied and the animals were returned to their home 
cage. The furosemide protocol was performed 7 and 24 h after 
CYP injection, and bladder pressure and voided volumes were 
continuously recorded as previously described. After the 
second furosemide evaluation, animals were anaesthetized 
with pentobarbital (60 mg·kg À1 , 1 mL·kg À1 ) and killed by 
cervical dislocation. Then, each transmitter was removed 
and the pressure calibration checked. </p>

<p>Data and statistical analysis </p>

<p>Results are expressed as mean ± SEM, with n indicating the 
number of animals, strips or independent in vitro experiments 
used for a particular set of experiments. For in vitro experi-
ments in recombinant models, isotherms were analysed by a 
nonlinear regression (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad</rs>) to yield IC 50 values. 
K b values of antagonists for inhibition of agonist action 
were calculated according to Lazareno and Birdsall calculation: 
K b = IC 50 /{1 + [(agonist)/EC 50 ]} (Lazareno and Birdsall, 1993), 
where [agonist] is the concentration of TFLLR-NH 2 in the test 
(Lazareno and Birdsall, 1993). Values given are from at least 
five independent experiments performed at least in duplicate </p>

<p>for [ 35 S]-GTPγS experiments and quadruplicate for 
SRE-luciferase experiments. 
Statistical analysis of data was carried out using <rs id="software-4" type="software">SigmaStat</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">3.5</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Systat</rs>). For isolated bladder experiments, a 
two-way ANOVA followed by a multiple comparison versus 
vehicle with the Holm-Sidak method was performed only if 
F achieved P &lt; 0.05, and there was no significant variance 
in homogeneity. For telemetric experiments, Student's paired 
t-test and Mann-Whitney rank sum test were used. Values of 
P &lt; 0.05 were considered to show significant differences 
between means. The data and statistical analysis comply with 
the recommendations on experimental design and analysis 
in pharmacology (Curtis et al., 2015). </p>

<p>Equipment </p>

<p>Isolated 
bladder 
contractions. For 
isolated 
bladder 
experiments, tissues were placed in organ bath chambers 
(EMKA Technologies). Isometric tension transducers (IT50, 
EMKA Technologies) were connected to amplifiers, (EMKA </p>

<p>F16357 for the management of interstitial cystitis BJP </p>

<p>British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 2227 </p>

<p>Technologies) and contractile responses were recorded using 
IOX2 software (EMKA Technologies). </p>

<p>In vivo experiments. Telemetry equipment (Data Science 
International) was interfaced with easyMATRIX and <rs id="software-3" type="software">IOX2</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">EMKA Technologies</rs>). HD-S10 telemetry transmitters were 
used in conjunction with RPC-1 receivers. For volume 
measurements, customized IT50 isometric transducers 
(EMKA Technologies) were used. Weighing signals were 
converted through an analogue-to-digital IT50 converter 
(EMKA Technologies). For telemetric, cystometric and 
voided volume recording, animals were freely moving in 
customized metabolic cages (Technilab). </p>

<p>Drugs </p>

<p>CYP, lidocaine, thrombin, TFLLR-NH 2 and all reagents for 
buffer preparation were obtained from Sigma Aldrich. 
[ 35 S]-GTPγS was obtained from Perkin-Elmer Life Science 
and furosemide (Lasilix ® ) from local pharmacy. 
F16357 (3-(2-chlorophenyl)-1-[4-(4-fluorobenzyl)-piperazin-
1-yl]-propenone) was synthesized in a medicinal chemistry 
department at Pierre Fabre Research Institute. 
Materials used for surgical procedures were obtained from 
Centravet. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>In vitro evaluation of F16357 in 
PAR1-overexpressed conditions </p>

<p>In a [ 35 S]-GTPγS binding assay at human PAR-1 thrombin re-
ceptors, F16357 had no agonist activity when tested alone 
(data not shown), but antagonized 3 μM TFLLR-NH 2 -induced 
[ 35 S]-GTPγS binding with pKb values of 6.04 (5.61-6.82) 
(Figure 1A). In a standard SRE-luciferase reporter gene assay 
in PAR-1 transfected in COS-7 cells, F16357 antagonized 
1 μM TFLLR-NH 2 -induced luminescence with a pKb value of 
5.49 (5.45-5.65) (Figure 1B). 
Collectively, these results demonstrated that F16357 ex-
erts an antagonism against PAR1 in various models with a 
pharmacological potency between 5.49 and 6.04 depending 
on the level of receptor expression. All these results are in 
accordance with those previously reported in the publication 
of Perez et al. (2009), in which compound #39 represents the 
F16357. </p>

<p>PAR1 immunoreactivity (IR) in the lateral wall 
of the bladder </p>

<p>Sections of the lateral wall of the bladder were examined for 
PAR1 IR after treatment with either vehicle (Figure 2A, control) 
or CYP (Figure 2B). In control rats, the urothelium, stained 
with an antibody to NOS [green appears as a multilayered 
structure, arrows: (+)]. PAR1-IR can be seen (red), but this is 
localized to the umbrella cells. Not all umbrella cells were 
PAR1-IR with large areas showing no PAR1-IR. No PAR1-IR 
was detected in cells of the lamina propria or muscle layer; 
24 h after CYP treatment, there was a clear disruption and 
damage to the urothelium (Figure 2B). Cells of the urothelium 
have been lost, and the barrier is absent or reduced to a single-
cell layer. Such changes are often associated with an expansion </p>

<p>of the lamina propria, but there appears to be little damage to 
the sub-urothelial interstitial cells. All of the urothelial cells 
remaining after CYP were strongly PAR1-IR. The 'punctate' 
distribution was lost. Qualitatively, these observations 
suggested an increased expression of PAR1 in the basal 
urothelial cells after CYP exposure. Intravesical administration 
of F16357 (30 μM) 2.5 h after CYP treatment appeared to 
induce less damage (Figure 2C). PAR1-IR was again restricted 
to a small population of umbrella cells. Note that, however, 
in the section illustrated, the lamina propria was still expanded 
(Figure 2C). Therefore, the local administration of F16357 
appeared to prevent the sequence of events underpinning 
urothelial damage possibly by preventing the overexpression 
and activation of PAR1. </p>

<p>Effect of PAR1 activation in the bladder </p>

<p>Typical traces, demonstrating a concentration-dependent in-
crease in the amplitude of micro-contractions evoked by the 
PAR1-selective activating peptide TFLLR-NH 2 , are shown in 
Figure 3A, B. In physiological conditions, the amplitude of 
these contractions was &lt;0.1 g and increased up to 0.7 g 24 h 
after CYP treatment. In both physiological and inflammatory 
conditions, pretreatment with F16357 30 μM suppressed the 
maximal contraction elicited by TFLLR-NH 2 (Figure 3C, D) 
and reduced the rhythmic instability. A specific analysis 
based on an evaluation of the AUC of micro-contractions 
showed that these micro-contractions were reduced by 48% 
after F16357 (30 μM) treatment (Figure 3D). </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Concentration-dependent effect of F16357: on TFLLR-NH 2 -induced 
G-protein activation (n = 5 independent experiments) (A) or on 
TFLLR-NH 2 -induced SRE-luciferase activity (n = 5 independent 
experiments) (B); both in the membrane of COS-7 cells. </p>

<p>BJP </p>

<p>N Monjotin et al. </p>

<p>2228 British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 </p>

<p>Under control conditions, TFLLR-NH 2 induced 
concentration-dependent contractions from 1 μM (thresh-
old) up to 100 μM, and the maximal amplitude was about 
0.6 g (corresponding to 14% of KCl 50 mM contraction). 
F16357 decreased the TFLLR-NH 2 -induced bladder contrac-
tion in a concentration-dependent manner with a total </p>

<p>blockade at 10 and 30 μM (P &lt; 0.05 for both) (Figure 4A). 
These results demonstrate that the PAR1 was involved in 
the generation or modulation of micro-contractions in the 
isolated bladder; 24 h after CYP treatment, TFLLR-NH 2 
induced concentration-dependent contractions of bladder 
strips from 1 μM (threshold) up to 100 μM. The maximal </p>

<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>Location of IR to PAR1 in control (A), CYP-treated (B) and CYP + F16357-treated bladders. (A) Sections of the lateral wall of the bladder from a 
control rat illustrating the regionalized localization of IR to PAR1 (red) to primarily the umbrella cells of the urothelium (*). The lumen (lum), 
urothelium (uro) and lamina propria are identified. Regions of the urothelium devoid of PAR1-IR are also apparent (+). The section is counter-
stained with an antibody to NOS (green) and the nuclear marker DAPI (blue). Calibration bars (A), (B) and (C) 30 mm. (B) Sections of lateral wall 
from a rat injected with CYP. Note (a) the disruption and loss of the urothelium down to a single cell layer and (b) the appearance of PAR1-IR in 
all epithelial cells. No PAR1-IR was found in the lamina propria interstitial cells. These sections are also stained with an antibody to vimentin 
(Vim: green) to identify interstitial cells. Calibration bars (B) 40 and 15 mm in (a) and (b). (C) Images from bladders from CYP-treated animals that 
also had intravesical F16357 (30 μM). The section is counterstained with an antibody to NOS (green) and the nuclear marker DAPI (blue). Note the 
absence of urothelial damage and the regional distribution of PAR1-IR to the umbrella cells. Also, a region of the bladder wall where the 
lamina propria has expanded (★). Calibration bars (C) 100 mm, (a) 20 and (b) 15 mm. </p>

<p>F16357 for the management of interstitial cystitis BJP </p>

<p>British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 2229 </p>

<p>amplitude was about 1.1 g (corresponding to 27% of KCl 
contraction) and was twofold higher in inflamed tissues 
compared with control conditions. Pretreatment with 
F16357 decreased the TFLLR-NH 2 -induced bladder contrac-
tion in a concentration-dependent manner from 10 μM up </p>

<p>to a total blockade at 30 μM (P &lt; 0.05 for both) (Figure 4B). 
The pIC 50 values of F16357 were 5.32 and 5.07 in control 
and inflammatory conditions respectively. These results 
suggest that PAR1 is more involved in this pathological 
condition and that the potency of F16357 was not modified. </p>

<p>Figure 3 </p>

<p>Representative traces of in vitro bladder contraction recording. Effect of cumulative concentration-response curve with TFLLR-NH 2 (1x10 
À7 up to </p>

<p>1x10 
À4 M in semi-logarithmic increment, each arrow represents one concentration) in physiological conditions (A) and 24 h after CYP injection </p>

<p>(B). Effect of F16357 (30 μM) on the cumulative concentration-response curve to TFLLR-NH 2 in physiological conditions (C) and 24 h after CYP 
injection (D). </p>

<p>Figure 4 </p>

<p>Upper panel: concentration-response curves for TFLLR-NH 2 -induced contractions of bladder strips in vitro. Effect of pretreatment with F16357 or 
vehicle (DMSO 0.3%). Physiological conditions, n = 5 for all concentrations of F16357 and n = 7 for vehicle group (A). Pathological conditions, 
24 h after CYP injection, n = 6 for all concentrations of F16357 and n = 10 for vehicle group (B). Lower panel: effect of pretreatment with F16357 or 
vehicle (DMSO 0.3%) on thrombin 3 U·mL 
À1 incubation followed by TFLLR-NH 2 100 μM-induced contraction of bladder strips in vitro. Physiological </p>

<p>conditions, n = 5 for all groups (C). Pathological conditions, 24 h after CYP injection, n = 6 for vehicle group and n = 5 for F16357 group (D). </p>

<p>BJP </p>

<p>N Monjotin et al. </p>

<p>2230 British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 </p>

<p>In a separate set of experiments, thrombin (a PAR1 
selective protease, 3 U·mL À1 ) and TFLLR-NH 2 (100 μM) in-
duced first a phasic bladder contraction followed by a tonic 
change with an increase in rhythmic contractions in both 
physiological and CYP conditions. In physiological conditions 
(Figure 4C), bladder contractions were around 0.3 g with 
thrombin and 0.6 g with TFLLR-NH 2 . F16357 30 μM 
antagonized both means of stimulation [protease (P = 0.06) 
and agonist peptide (P &lt; 0.05)]. 24 h after CYP (Figure 4D), 
thrombin and TFLLR-NH 2 contracted the bladder to a larger 
extent, and the associated micro-contractions during the tonic 
phases were also increased (not shown). In inflammatory condi-
tions, F16357 30 μM abolished both thrombin-and TFLLR-NH 2 -
induced bladder contraction (P &lt; 0.05 for both activators). 
These data demonstrate that the bladder PAR1 signalling 
pathway can be activated by two distinct mechanisms. F16357 
suppressed both thrombin-and TFLLR-NH 2 -induced bladder 
contractions (P &lt; 0.05) and blocked each agonist-induced 
increase in micro-contractions in physiological and 
inflammatory conditions. </p>

<p>Effect of PAR1 blockade on cystometric 
parameters </p>

<p>Typical traces recorded in control and after CYP injection 
(150 mg·kg À1 , i.p.) are shown in Figure 5A. In both records, 
the upper trace shows bladder pressure and the lower voided 
volume. Furosemide injection induced an increase in the di-
uresis, which resulted in the rapid production of urine, blad-
der filling and the triggering of a series of several voids. A 
perfect time match between individual voided volumes and 
maximal pressures corresponding to micturitions was obtained 
in all records. The amplitude of the micturition was almost 
stable throughout the 60 min recording. The pattern of voiding 
was such that the ICI increased following the furosemide 
injection and, in the last 30 min, its diuretic effects waned. 
Interestingly, individual voided volumes were constant 
(Figure 5A) despite the progressive increase in ICI. 
Seven hours after CYP injection, a furosemide pulse 
induced an increase in the number of micturitions and a 
decrease in ICI without any modification of the amplitude 
of bladder contraction (Figure 5B, upper panel) as compared 
with control. CYP also decreased the mean volume of individ-
ual micturitions, as well as the total voided volume within 
1 h. F16357 (30 μM) restored the physiological urodynamic 
profile and mean voided volumes (P &lt; 0.05) (Figure 5C). </p>

<p>Effect of F16357 on urodynamic parameters in 
rats </p>

<p>In the absence of CYP-induced inflammation, no notable 
modification of the cystometry parameters was obtained 
after a single intravesical injection of F16357 30 μM, 
regardless of the time of furosemide pulse 7 or 24 h (data 
not shown). 
In rats treated with CYP followed by an intravesical injec-
tion of vehicle, a furosemide challenge at 7 h resulted in 
18 ± 5 micturitions of 0.7 ± 0.2 mL (mean volume of 
individual micturitions). The intravesical administration of 
F16357 30 μM reduced the micturition frequency and in-
creased the individual voided volumes to restore the so-called 
basal urodynamic parameters (P &lt; 0.05 for both); however, </p>

<p>the micturition amplitude and the total voided volume 
were not significantly affected by the F16357 treatment 
(Figure 6A-D). When the furosemide challenge was repeated 
at 24 h, the total voided volume was reduced by about 60% 
when compared with the 7 h time point, thus affecting the 
number of micturitions (only 4 ± 1). This reduction in total 
voided volume, despite a reduced voiding frequency, was in 
accordance with data previously obtained, and corresponded 
to a significant fall in the rate of urine production as previ-
ously reported (Monjotin et al., 2016). The intravesical 
administration of F16357 30 μM significantly reduced the 
micturition frequency and increased the individual voided 
volumes in a comparable magnitude as those at 7 h 
(P &lt; 0.05). Again, the amplitude of micturition and the total 
voided volume were not affected by this pharmacological 
treatment (Figure 6E-H). These data demonstrate that the 
local treatment of F16357 (30 μM) for 1 h in the bladder 
lumen was able to reduce the number of micturitions, an 
effect lasting for up to 22 h post-infusion. </p>

<p>Effect of lidocaine on urodynamic parameters in 
CYP-treated rats </p>

<p>After the 7 h furosemide pulse, lidocaine 2% reduced the num-
ber of micturitions and increased the mean individual voided 
volumes when compared with vehicle (P &lt; 0.05), without </p>

<p>Figure 5 </p>

<p>Representative traces of telemetric recording after a pulse of furose-
mide (10 mg·kg 
À1 , 2 mL·kg 
À1 ) in physiological conditions (A), after </p>

<p>CYP-induced inflammation (B) and after intravesical administration 
of F16357 30 μM 2.5 h after CYP injection (C). </p>

<p>F16357 for the management of interstitial cystitis BJP </p>

<p>British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 2231 </p>

<p>affecting the other urodynamic parameters (Figure 7A-D). 
When the furosemide challenge was retested at 24 h, a 
reduction in the micturition frequency was also observed, and 
the other parameters measured were not affected significantly 
by the lidocaine 2% treatment (Figure 7E-H). These data 
support the idea that reducing sensation could be a key compo-
nent for alleviating the urodynamic disturbances mediated by a 
powerful inflammatory agent in this rat IC model. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study suggests that PAR1 may be a novel thera-
peutic in the management of IC. Furthermore, pharmacolog-
ical actions of a selective PAR1 antagonist, F16357 (Perez 
et al., 2009; Ramachandran et al., 2012), may be particularly 
useful in the alleviation of IC symptoms. Firstly, the data 
demonstrate that PAR1 expression increases in inflammatory </p>

<p>Figure 6 </p>

<p>Effect of intravesical administration of vehicle (n = 7) or F16357 30 μM (n = 6) (0.6 mL for 1 h) 7 h (A-D) and 24 h (E-H) on the number of 
micturitions (A and E), the amplitude of micturition (B and F), the mean voided volume per micturition (C and G) and the total voided volume 
in 1 h after furosemide pulse (D and H). Dotted line represents the mean values obtained with intravesical infusion of vehicle in physiological 
conditions (n = 4). </p>

<p>BJP </p>

<p>N Monjotin et al. </p>

<p>2232 British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 </p>

<p>conditions in the rat urothelium, in the well-established 
model of haemorrhagic cystitis induced by CYP. Secondly, 
functional studies demonstrate a physiological response 
involving PAR1 both in isolated bladders and in conscious 
freely moving rats. Interestingly, the compound F16357 
exhibited a concentration-dependent antagonism of PAR1 
and demonstrated a clear improvement of the symptoms of 
bladder sensation induced by CYP. 
Proteases like tryptase (Boucher et al., 1995; Okragly et al., 
1999) or neutrophil elastase (Kuromitsu et al., 2008) are re-
leased during inflammation, and their levels are found to be 
increased in urine from IC patients. Thrombin, another ser-
ine protease with a high affinity for PAR1, plays an important 
role in the induction of inflammation and pain (Vergnolle, 
2009). In rat bladder, the distribution of PARs is well 
established for PAR2, PAR3 and PAR4, but PAR1 has yet to be 
further characterized (D'Andrea et al., 2003; Moffatt, 2007; Vera </p>

<p>et al., 2010). Nevertheless, the presence of PAR1 was confirmed 
in rat bladder by Vera in 2010 and has recently been shown to 
be involved in bladder pain by Kouzoukas in 2015, but its role 
in bladder function has yet to be established (Vera et al., 2010; 
Kouzoukas et al., 2015). In human bladder cells (Urotsa), all four 
subtypes of PAR have been well characterized (Vera et al., 2010). 
The first goal of this work was to study the modulation of 
PAR1 expression in the rat bladder wall in both physiological 
and inflammatory conditions. The present findings demon-
strate that PAR1 is only present in some urothelial cells under 
control, non-inflammatory conditions. However, 24 h after 
CYP injection, the urothelium is damaged, and the remain-
ing urothelial cells were also found to express PAR1. No 
PAR1 was found in lamina propria despite expansion of the 
interstitial space associated with the inflammation. These 
results in rat bladders are different from those in mouse in 
which inflammation decreased the PAR1 expression </p>

<p>Figure 7 </p>

<p>Effect of intravesical administration of vehicle (n = 6) or lidocaine 2% (n = 7) (0.3 mL for 1 h) 7 h (A-D) and 24 h (E-H) on the number of micturitions 
(A and E), the amplitude of micturition (B and F), the mean voided volume per micturition (C and G) and the total voided volume in 1 h after furosemide 
pulse (D and H). Dotted line represents the mean values obtained with intravesical infusion of vehicle in physiological conditions (n = 9). </p>

<p>F16357 for the management of interstitial cystitis BJP </p>

<p>British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 2233 </p>

<p>(D'Andrea et al., 2003). The observations obtained here 
demonstrate that local administration of a PAR1 antagonist 
(F16357) during the acute phase of the inflammation (i.e. 2.5 h 
after CYP injection) (Lanteri-Minet et al., 1995) limits the 
urothelial damage and eliminates the increased expression of 
PAR1-IR. However, it does not appear to moderate the 
expansion of the lamina propria. 
Moreover, PAR1 is involved in bladder pain in animal 
models (Kouzoukas et al., 2015). These findings associated 
with the immunostaining results demonstrate the potential 
of a PAR1 antagonist, namely, F16357, in the pathophysiol-
ogy and treatment of IC. 
The second set of experiments demonstrates a functional 
role for PAR1 in bladder contractions after stimulation by ei-
ther an endogenous protease (i.e. thrombin) or an agonist 
peptide (i.e. TFLLR-NH 2 ) (Vergnolle, 2009).The increased ac-
tivity of PAR1 was demonstrated in bladder inflammation, 
in line with the increased expression of the target. To the best 
of our knowledge, the functional implication of PAR1 has 
never been reported in rat bladder contractility, and PAR1 ef-
fects are selectively and concentration-dependently antago-
nized by F16357. In the present experimental conditions, a 
smaller bladder contraction was obtained with thrombin 
than with TFLLR-NH 2 , which could be explained either by 
the presence of natural anti-protease or by an off-target effect 
(Benezra et al., 1993; Lafleur et al., 2001; Tran and Stewart, 
2003). At the concentrations tested, a difference in efficacy 
between the two agonists is not related to an insufficient con-
centration of thrombin because 3 UI·mL À1 was supramaximal 
(data not shown). Another explanation could also be related 
to a difference in the mechanism of PAR1-induced activation 
because TFLLR-NH 2 does not display any enzymatic activity. 
Moreover, rhythmic contractions were reported by Nakahara 
in 2004 after trypsin-induced bladder contractions in CYP-
treated rats (Nakahara et al., 2004). In the present work, 
thrombin and TFLLR-NH 2 also induced rhythmic detrusor 
contractions that were reduced by F16357. All these data con-
firm the role of PARs and especially PAR1 in rhythmic con-</p>

<p>tractions. In these conditions, the concentration-dependent 
antagonism induced by F16357 on detrusor contractility 
demonstrates that PAR1 is a very interesting target for the 
management of bladder overactivity and the exacerbation 
of the bladder sensitivity described in IC patients (Grover 
et al., 2011). Nevertheless, in order to evaluate the involve-
ment of bladder sensitivity in the bladder contractility, the 
relationship between PAR1 expression in the urothelium 
and detrusor function warrants further investigations. 
In the next part of this study, the effects of F16357 were ex-
amined in an integrative animal model of IC induced by CYP. 
As described previously (Monjotin et al., 2016), radiotelemetry 
enables continuous recording of urodynamic parameters in 
fully unrestrained conditions in conscious animals. The bladder 
is not filled artificially with saline but urine following as part of 
an endogenous diuresis. Consequently, bladder filling and emp-
tying operate in a more physiological condition (Buyuknacar 
et al., 2008; Andersson et al., 2011). As a result, the timing of a 
void is determined by the animal, a conscious decision, and 
not only by activation of reflexes when the bladder is full. The 
decision of the animal to void therefore involves the integration 
of multiple inputs: painful sensation and volume sensations 
(Eastham and Gillespie, 2013). </p>

<p>Bladder function was recorded at the critical time periods 
after CYP injection (Dornelles et al., 2014). In acute inflam-
matory conditions (i.e. 7 h after CYP injection), furosemide, 
a loop diuretic with a short half-life (update ANSM November 
2010), greatly increased the number of micturitions and de-
creased the voided volume per micturition compared with 
the physiological state. This change in the voiding pattern 
is consistent with the idea that the introduction of painful 
bladder sensations, as a result of the CYP-induced cystitis, 
contributes to the decision to void (Cox, 1979; Saitoh et al., 
2010; Pessina et al., 2015). F16357 was tested in this stringent 
rat model of IC, in order to evaluate the effect of a PAR1 an-
tagonist. These telemetric data demonstrate a very clear ben-
eficial effect of a short and local administration of F16357 on 
voiding pattern and urodynamic parameters, thus supporting 
an hypothesis for the involvement of a PAR component 
(Dattilio and Vizzard, 2005; Vergnolle, 2009), especially 
PAR1 in the bladder pain sensation (Kouzoukas et al., 2015). 
These beneficial effects are maintained during the chronic 
phase of inflammation up to 24 h (Jezernik et al., 2003). 
Interestingly, furosemide induced a different effect on 
urine production at the two different times of recording; 
24 h after CYP injection, the number of voids was reduced 
markedly in all groups. We have previously reported the same 
results after water loading instead of the furosemide pulse 
(Monjotin et al., 2016), thus eliminating a possible interac-
tion between furosemide and CYP or its metabolites, or a loss 
of the pharmacological efficacy of furosemide during the 
second pulse. These observations could probably be induced 
by a major effect of CYP on kidney function (Kim et al., 2011). 
Local administration of lidocaine, a therapeutic option 
for IC management (Henry et al., 2015), was evaluated, and 
comparable results with F16357 in amplitude and duration 
were obtained. In humans, intravesical instillations of lido-
caine 2% may interrupt the self-perpetuating neuro-
inflammatory cycle presented in IC (Henry et al., 2015). In 
the current experimental model, the comparable effects ob-
tained with lidocaine and F16357 confirm the involvement 
of pain sensation in the modification of the voiding pattern. 
Collectively, these results show that PAR1 antagonism plays 
a key role in the control of bladder pain either by a direct ef-
fect on receptor or by an indirect mechanism with inhibition 
of some inflammatory cytokines such as MIF (Kouzoukas 
et al., 2015). 
Finally, the urodynamic and immunohistochemistry 
results suggest an effect of F16357 on the urothelial recon-
struction, but further explorations (especially on the kinetic 
effect of F16357) are required. Several hypotheses can be 
proposed, such as the role of PAR1 antagonism in the 
acceleration of the urothelial repair, the prevention of 
urothelium damage or a combination of both. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>This work has demonstrated the presence of PAR1 in the rat 
bladder and its involvement in bladder function and sensa-
tion. The local administration of the novel selective PAR1 an-
tagonist F16357 elicits robust and durable effects on bladder 
contractility, urodynamics and bladder pain sensation. 
Hence, F16357 could represent an interesting candidate for </p>

<p>BJP </p>

<p>N Monjotin et al. </p>

<p>2234 British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 </p>

<p>IC/PBS treatment because it improves most of the pathologi-
cal features, namely, pelvic pain, inflammation and detrusor 
dysfunction. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to Mr. Laurent Bardin for his scien-
tific input, to Mr. Albert Volant for expert animal care and 
surgery assistance and to Ms. Cecile Vue, Ms. Brigitte Gutkin 
and Ms. Valérie Berthet for technical assistance. Nathalie 
Vergnolle is supported by the European Research Council 
(ERC-2012-StG-20111109). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>N.M. performed the research, designed the research study, 
analysed the data, supervised the study and wrote the paper. 
J.G. designed the research study, analysed the data, provided 
critical discussions and approved the version to be published. 
M.F. performed the research and analysed the data. B.L.G. 
provided critical discussions and approved the version to be 
published. D.J. analysed the data, provided critical discus-
sions and approved the version to be published. N.V. super-
vised the study, provided critical discussions and approved 
the version to be published. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest </p>

<p>N.M., M.F., B.L.G. and D.J. are employees of Institut de 
Recherche Pierre Fabre. J.G. is a scientific consultant for the 
Institut de Recherche Pierre Fabre. </p>

<p>Declaration of transparency and 
scientific rigour </p>

<p>This Declaration acknowledges that this paper adheres to the 
principles for transparent reporting and scientific rigour of 
preclinical research recommended by funding agencies, 
publishers and other organisations engaged with supporting 
research. </p>



<p>BJP </p>

<p>N Monjotin et al. </p>

<p>2236 British Journal of Pharmacology (2016) 173 2224-2236 </p>

</text></tei>