<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4622569" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Preserving the chemical and structural integrity of therapeutic antibodies during manufacturing and storage is a 
major challenge during pharmaceutical development. Oxidation of Fc methionines Met252 and Met428 is frequently 
observed, which leads to reduced affinity to FcRn and faster plasma clearance if present at high levels. Because 
oxidation occurs in both positions simultaneously, their individual contribution to the concomitant changes in 
pharmacokinetic properties has not been clearly established. A novel pH-gradient FcRn affinity chromatography 
method was applied to isolate three antibody oxidation variants from an oxidized IgG1 preparation based on their FcRn 
binding properties. Physico-chemical characterization revealed that the three oxidation variants differed predominantly 
in the number of oxMet252 per IgG (0, 1, or 2), but not significantly in the content of oxMet428. Corresponding to the 
increase in oxMet252 content, stepwise reduction of FcRn affinity in vitro, as well as faster clearance and shorter 
terminal half-life, in huFcRn-transgenic mice were observed. A single Met252 oxidation per antibody had no significant 
effect on pharmacokinetics (PK) compared with unmodified IgG. Importantly, only molecules with both heavy chains 
oxidized at Met252 exhibited significantly faster clearance. In contrast, Met428 oxidation had no apparent negative 
effect on PK and even led to somewhat improved FcRn binding and slower clearance. This minor effect, however, 
seemed to be abrogated by the dominant effect of Met252 oxidation. The novel approach of functional 
chromatographic separation of IgG oxidation variants followed by physico-chemical and biological characterization has 
yielded the first experimentally-backed explanation for the unaltered PK properties of antibody preparations containing 
relatively high Met252 and Met428 oxidation levels. </p>

<p>The more than 30 approved therapeutic antibodies in clinical 
use and »350 in clinical development demonstrate the impor-
tance of monoclonal antibodies as therapeutic entities in numer-
ous disease indications, such as oncology, inflammation, </p>

<p>transplantation, infection and ophthalmology. 
1,2 Immunoglobu-
lin G (IgG) is the class and format most widely adopted for thera-
peutic antibodies. 
3 The two variable antigen-binding fragments 
(Fab) of IgG mediate its specificity for the target antigen, while 
the crystallizable fragment (Fc) is responsible for its effector func-
tions via interaction with the Fcg receptor (FcgR) family, and </p>

<p>© Jan Stracke, Thomas Emrich, Petra Rueger, Tilman Schlothauer, Lothar Kling, Alexander Knaupp, Hubert Hertenberger, Andreas Wolfert, Christian Spick, Wilma 
Lau, Georg Drabner, Ulrike Reiff, Hans Koll, and Apollon Papadimitriou 
*Correspondence to: Jan Olaf Stracke; Email: Jan_olaf.stracke@roche.com 
Submitted: 05/07/2014; Revised: 06/14/2014; Accepted: 06/16/2014 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4161/mabs.29601 </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-Commercial License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/3.0/), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The 
moral rights of the named author(s) have been asserted. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com 
1229 
mAbs </p>

<p>mAbs 6:5, 1229--1242; September/October 2014; Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC </p>

<p>REPORT </p>

<p>for its long serum half-life via interaction with the neonatal Fc 
receptor (FcRn). </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>Maintaining the chemical and structural integrity of antibody 
therapeutics during manufacturing and shelf-life is a major chal-
lenge during pharmaceutical development. 
6 In particular, the 
effect of chemical modifications in the Fc of therapeutic IgGs on 
FcRn-mediated pharmacokinetic (PK) properties has become the 
subject of increasing interest for pharmaceutical companies and 
scrutiny by health authorities. One of the most widely observed 
and discussed chemical degradation events in IgGs is the oxida-
tion of methionine (Met) to methionine sulfoxide in two posi-
tions in the Fc, and understanding its effect on FcRn interaction 
and PK is crucial to antibody therapeutics development. 
7-9 In 
contrast to other chemical degradation pathways, the activation 
energy of methionine oxidation is rather low, which explains the 
focus on its role as one of the main potential causes of protein 
degradation during refrigerated storage. </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>When investigating the potential effect of chemical modifica-
tions on PK properties in vitro, analysis of the FcRn/IgG interac-
tion is of vital importance. FcRn is a heterodimeric receptor 
consisting of two polypeptides, a 48-52 kDa class I major histo-
compatibility complex-like protein (a-FcRn) and a 14 kDa b2-
microglobulin (b2 min). The FcRn/IgG interaction occurs in a 
strictly pH-dependent manner in the endosomes of vascular 
endothelial cells and bone marrow-derived cells and functions to 
salvage IgG from lysosomal degradation. 
5 FcRn binds to the 
CH2-CH3 portion of the Fc domain of IgG with high affinity at 
acidic endosomal pH. 
12,13 The receptor then facilitates the recy-
cling of IgGs to the cell surface and the subsequent release into 
the blood stream upon exposure of the FcRn/IgG complex to the 
neutral extracellular pH environment. 
14 Crystal structure data 
and in vitro binding experiments indicate that the receptor-anti-
body interaction can occur in 2:1 stoichiometry, with two FcRn 
molecules binding to the two heavy chains (HC) of an IgG. </p>

<p>12,15 </p>

<p>However, this hypothesis remains to be confirmed in vivo. 
The FcRn binding region in the CH2-CH3 interface of the Fc 
contains two methionine residues located at positions 252 in the 
CH2 domain and 428 in the CH3 domain (Eu numbering 
16 ), 
which are highly conserved among IgG isotypes. 
17 Both residues 
are surface exposed, structurally close to the FcRn-binding inter-
face and susceptible to oxidation, with the oxidation rate of 
Met252 being approximately twice that of Met428. 
7,9 A third 
Met residue at position 358 has been described in some IgG1 
alleles and is present in all other IgG subclasses. 
17 Its buried loca-
tion in the CH3 domain at the CH3/CH3 interface between the 
two antibody HCs and its significant distance to the FcRn bind-
ing site renders the oxidation of Met358, and an effect on FcRn 
binding, unlikely. Most probably due to its structural position, 
Met358 is found to oxidize at a much slower rate compared with 
Met252 and Met428 if present. </p>

<p>7,18 </p>

<p>It has been described that Met252 and Met428 oxidation is 
accompanied by conformational changes in the backbone 
between residues 242-252 (Eu numbering 
16 ) of the FcRn bind-
ing region. 
19-21 Analysis of a truncated antibody Fc demonstrated 
that the main structural changes upon oxidation occur in the 
CH2 domain whereas the CH3 is less compromised. 
22 Oxidation </p>

<p>of Met252 and Met428 was shown to impair affinity to FcRn 
and PK properties of monoclonal antibodies. 
7-9 However, only 
IgG preparations with high oxidation levels (»80% oxMet252) 
exhibited significantly faster clearance compared with non-
degraded batches. 
8 As a consequence, it has been hypothesized 
that only molecules with both HCs oxidized at least in one posi-
tion have markedly altered FcRn affinity and faster clearance 
in vivo. </p>

<p>8,23 </p>

<p>During processing and storage of antibody preparations, oxi-
dation of Met252 and Met428 occurs in parallel at both posi-
tions, albeit with different reaction rates. 
9,11,24 Even under 
tailored oxidation stress conditions, it has not been possible to 
generate antibody samples selectively oxidized at one position 
only. 
7-9,22,25 With the two methionines present in each HC, four 
oxidation sites exist in the IgG Fc, giving rise to a total of 10 Fc 
oxidation variants containing 0 to 4 Met oxidations per molecule 
(Fig. 1). 
8 This heterogeneity is the main reason for the current 
lack of understanding of the contribution of Met252 vs. Met428 
oxidation to structural changes, FcRn binding affinity and in 
vivo clearance. Improved understanding of the FcRn affinities 
and PK properties of these 10 Fc methionine oxidation variants 
would be of considerable value for the development of antibody 
therapeutics. The prerequisite for this, however, is the ability to 
resolve and separate the oxidation variants in a preparative man-
ner for in vitro and in vivo characterization. So far, attempts 
using common chromatographic purification techniques have 
not delivered samples enriched in certain IgG oxidation variants, 
but rather provided mixtures of antibody species oxidized at both 
positions, Met252 and Met428. 
8,9 Furthermore, site-specific 
mutations of these two residues can have varying effect on FcRn 
binding, depending on the nature and size of the introduced 
amino acid. Mutation of Met252 can significantly increase or 
decrease the affinity to FcRn, whereas changing Met428 to 
another amino acid led to stronger affinity to the receptor and 
prolonged serum half-life in vivo. 
26 Thus, mutant IgG models to 
study the consequences of Fc methionine oxidation need to be 
considered carefully. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Schematic illustration of all 10 IgG Fc methionine oxidation 
variants. The black diamond represents oxMet252 and the gray triangle 
indicates oxMet428. The variable domains of HC and LC are shaded in gray. </p>

<p> 
Volume 6 Issue 5 
mAbs </p>

<p>In the study presented here, we applied a novel pH-gradient 
FcRn affinity chromatography method that closely mimics the 
physiological conditions of interaction between FcRn and IgG to 
isolate three functionally distinct antibody oxidation variants 
from a hydrogen peroxide-treated IgG1 batch based on their dif-
ferent FcRn-binding properties. 
27 The structure-function rela-
tionship of Fc methionine oxidation could be established, and 
the individual contribution of oxMet252 vs. oxMet428 to FcRn 
affinity loss and PK impairments could be clarified. 
Our results provide the first experimentally-backed explana-
tion for the observation that even antibody preparations with rel-
atively high total Fc methionine oxidation levels (e.g., 40% 
oxMet252 and 25% oxMet428) do not show markedly impaired 
PK profiles. The effect of Fc methionine oxidation on antibody 
PK and functionality may be re-assessed for future pharmaceuti-
cal development on the basis of this study. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>FcRn affinity chromatography of H 2 O 2 -treated mAb1 and 
isolation of 3 main oxidation variants 
We recently developed an analytical pH gradient FcRn affin-
ity liquid chromatography method with conditions closely resem-
bling the physiological mechanism of interaction between IgGs 
and FcRn. 
27 In the current study, using a refined pH-gradient, 
FcRn chromatography analysis of monoclonal IgG1 and IgG4 
preparations reproducibly yielded one single peak as shown for 
the representative IgG1 mAb1 (Fig. 2, black curve). After hydro-
gen peroxide treatment, the chromatogram of the antibody, now 
termed mAb1_Ox, exhibited three distinct peaks, whereby the 
retention time of the last eluting peak corresponds to the main 
peak in the untreated mAb1 sample (Fig. 2, gray curves). Two 
additional peaks, named prepeaks I and II, eluted earlier and at </p>

<p>lower pH in the gradient than the main peak. Thus, the FcRn 
column resolved a total of 3 distinct antibody oxidation variants 
in the hydrogen peroxide-treated sample mAb1_Ox that differed 
in their affinity to FcRn, with the latest eluting variant (main 
peak) exhibiting the highest and the earliest eluting variant (pre-
peak II) the lowest FcRn binding properties. 
In order to characterize and compare the 3 resolved oxidation 
variants with regard to their physico-chemical, functional and 
PK properties, a preparative version of the FcRn affinity column 
was established. Approx. 200 mg of mAb1, that exhibit only a 
single main peak eluting at »82 min, were treated with 0.01% 
(v/v) hydrogen peroxide for 18 h (Fig. 3A and B). This oxidized 
material mAb1_Ox, exhibiting 3 peaks, was applied to the pre-
parative FcRn affinity column and 10 mg of each peak were iso-
lated for further in vitro and in vivo characterization (Fig. 3C). 
Because the three peaks were not base-line resolved, the peak val-
leys were not included in the fraction pools in order to obtain the 
individual variants as pure as possible (Fig. 3C). The 3 fraction 
pools, original mAb1 and mAb1_Ox were dialyzed in formula-
tion buffer containing 5 mM L-methionine to suppress further 
oxidation. The protein concentration was adjusted to 1 mg/ml in 
all samples and aliquots were stored frozen below -60 
C to avoid 
any further degradation and modification. 
After the described separation and preparation, five samples 
were obtained for characterization: (1) the untreated antibody 
mAb1; (2) a portion of the same antibody batch that was treated 
with hydrogen peroxide, mAb1_Ox; (3) the 3 peaks isolated 
from mAb1_Ox using the FcRn column, mAb1_Ox_main peak; 
(4) mAb1_Ox_prepeak I; and (5) mAb1_Ox_prepeak II (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Characterization of isolated mAb1 oxidation variants 
To verify the successful isolation of the three antibody oxi-
dation variants from mAb1_Ox, the samples were subjected to 
analytical FcRn chromatography and compared with the start-
ing material (mAb1) and the H 2 O 2 -treated, non-fractionated 
batch (mAb1_Ox) (Fig. 4). The results demonstrated that the 
three peaks were purified without detectable contaminations 
of the respective neighboring species. Subsequently, all five 
samples were extensively characterized with regard to their 
quality, assessing the following analytical parameters: Color, 
turbidity, aggregation and fragmentation (SE-HPLC, CE-SDS 
red./non-red.), charge heterogeneity (CE-IEF, cIEX), oligosac-
charide pattern (RP-UPLC of 2AB-labeled glycans), endotoxin 
content (LAL gel clotting assay), target binding (SPR target 
binding assay; Biacore), and functionality (molecule-specific 
qualified cell-based assay). The results generated using these 
analytical methods unanimously demonstrated that all five 
samples were of high product quality and not significantly dif-
ferent with regard to purity, integrity and functionality (data 
not shown). 
To determine potential differences in the nature and quantity 
of chemical modifications, all samples were subjected to tryptic 
LC-MS peptide mapping. The four samples that encountered 
hydrogen peroxide treatment (mAb1_Ox_. . .) exhibited low lev-
els of methionine and tryptophan oxidation in the complemen-
tarity-determining regions that, however, did not affect target </p>

<p>Figure 2. Analytical FcRn affinity chromatography of mAb1 (black curve) 
and H 2 O 2 -treated mAb1_Ox (0.01 and 0.02% v/v, dark gray and light 
gray curves, respectively). The dotted line indicates the pH gradient. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>
binding and in vitro functionality (data not shown). Due to their 
distance from the FcRn binding region, and since no effect was 
observed on target binding, these oxidations were not considered 
relevant for FcRn-dependent functionality. The only significant 
differences that could be detected among the five samples were 
considerable variations in the overall content and ratio of oxi-
dized Fc methionines, oxMet252 and oxMet428. 
As expected, untreated antibody mAb1 exhibited base-line 
oxidation levels, with 5% oxMet252 and 2% oxMet428. In con-
trast, the unfractionated hydrogen peroxide-treated mAb1_Ox 
contained considerably higher oxidation levels, with 41% of 
Met252 and 28% of Met428 residues affected (Table 1). Sur-
prisingly, a very strong and stepwise increase of oxMet252 from 
3 to 50 to 90% was detected in mAb1_Ox_main peak, 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak I and mAb1_Ox_prepeak II, respectively. 
These increasing oxMet252 levels clearly correlate with the step-
wise decrease in retention time and affinity on the FcRn column 
(Fig. 4; Table 1). In contrast, oxidation levels at position 
Met428 showed no strict correlation with retention time and 
affinity on the column. They differed insignificantly between 
mAb1_Ox_main peak (20% oxMet428) and mAb1_Ox_pre-
peak I (23% oxMet428) and were only increased to 42% in 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak II. These results strongly suggest that oxida-
tion of Met252, but not of Met428, has a dominant negative 
effect on FcRn affinity. 
The theoretical FcRn:IgG binding stoichiometry is 2:1, with 
one FcRn molecule binding to each of the two IgG HCs. 
15,28 In </p>

<p>Figure 3. (A) Schematic illustration of sample preparation of five mAb1-derived samples for further characterization. (B) FcRn chromatogram of 
untreated mAb1. (C) FcRn chromatogram of mAb1_Ox; the three separated peaks were individually collected and pooled as indicated by the gray 
rectangles. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Overlay of the analytical FcRn chromatograms of the five 
mAb1-derived samples in comparison to placebo buffer. (0) Placebo, (1) 
mAb1, (2) mAb1_Ox, (3) mAb1_Ox_main peak, (4) mAb1_Ox_prepeak I, 
(5) mAb1_Ox_prepeak II. </p>

<p> 
Volume 6 Issue 5 
mAbs </p>

<p>addition, in an IgG batch, three molecule variants differing in 
their Met252 oxidation content can exist, Met252/Met252, 
oxMet252/Met252, and oxMet252/oxMet252. Here, the 
observed steep and stepwise FcRn affinity reduction of the three 
isolated species from mAb1_Ox is accompanied by the equally 
stepwise increase in oxMet252 content (Fig. 4; Table 1). This 
strongly suggests that the three peaks isolated from mAb1_Ox 
indeed correspond to the 3 Met252 oxidation variants. Accord-
ingly, both HCs of mAb1_Ox_main peak are basically unaf-
fected (3% oxMet252), whereas mAb1_Ox_prepeak I (50% 
oxMet252) and mAb1_Ox_prepeak II (90% oxMet252) repre-
sent antibody species oxMet252/Met252 (one HC oxidized at 
Met252) and oxMet252/oxMet252 (both HCs oxidized at 
Met252), respectively. 
To verify that the number of oxMet252 per IgG is the main 
determinant for the distinct pH-dependent FcRn binding prop-
erties of the three isolated variants on the column, a plasmin 
digest followed by LC-ESI-mass spectrometry analysis of all five 
samples was performed (Fig. 5). Since plasmin cleaves the HCs 
specifically between lysine and threonine N-terminal of the hinge 
double-disulfide bonds (S[219]-C-D-K-T-H-T-C-P-P-C-P-A-P-
E-L-L-G-G-P(238)), this treatment generates Fc with intact 
covalent linkage between the two Fc HC fragments. After degly-
cosylation, the resulting Fc of all five samples were analyzed. In 
contrast to the full-length antibodies, the Fc can be analyzed for 
oxidation events with greatly improved resolution using mass 
spectrometry due to their lower molecular mass of »50 kDa. </p>

<p>Since hydrogen peroxide treatment induced oxidation in the Fc 
only at positions Met252 and Met428 (methionine sulfoxide, 
C16 Da) as confirmed by peptide map analysis, the Fc can 
exhibit a minimum of 0 (neither Met252 nor Met428 oxidized 
in both HCs) and a maximum of 4 (both HCs oxidized at 
Met252 and Met428) methionine oxidations in total. 
As indicated by a relatively homogeneous signal in the mass 
spectrum, mAb1 Fc contains predominantly 0 methionine oxida-
tion (0 oxMet) with low levels of single-oxidized Fc (1 oxMet) 
(Fig. 5). In contrast, the mAb1_Ox Fc exhibits the most hetero-
geneous mass spectrum of all five samples with a mixture of all 
oxidation variants from 0 to 4 oxMet. The Fc of mAb1_Ox_-
main peak and mAb1_Ox_prepeak II contain predominantly 0 
to 2 and 2 to 4 oxMet, respectively, whereas the intermediate 
fraction mAb1_Ox_prepeak I exhibits 1 to 3 oxMet in its Fc. In 
agreement with the peptide map data and the FcRn affinity col-
umn elution profile, these results complete the picture of the 
oxMet252 vs. oxMet428 distribution in the 3 isolated mAb1_Ox 
oxidation variants (Fig. 6; Table 1). 
In summary, mAb1_Ox_main peak contains antibody var-
iants that are predominantly oxidized at position Met428, but 
not at Met252. The plasmin digest indicates that the 20% 
oxMet428 found in this fraction are most probably distributed 
statistically. Apart from the dominant 0 oxMet signal, a signifi-
cant 1 oxMet and a smaller 2 oxMet signal can be detected in the 
mass spectrum (Fig. 5). In analogy, mAb1_Ox_prepeak II con-
tains predominantly antibody variants that carry oxMet252 in 
both HCs (90% oxMet252 in total). This is confirmed by the 
detection of a minimum of 2 oxMet in the corresponding mass 
spectrum of the plasmin digested sample. The 42% of Met428 
in this sample are most probably also distributed statistically due 
to the presence of a significant 3 oxMet signal and a less promi-
nent 4 oxMet signal in the mass spectrum of the Fc. The interme-
diate fraction, mAb1_Ox_prepeak I Fc (50% oxMet252) exhibits 
a minimum of one oxidation (1 oxMet) in addition to a signifi-
cant quantity of 2 oxMet and lower levels of 3 oxMet. The com-
plete absence of 0 and 4 oxMet in this fraction, which would 
have been present if both, oxMet252 and oxMet428, were dis-
tributed statistically, demonstrate that all antibody variants in 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak I carry at least one oxMet252. Hence, the 
hypothesis that the affinity of mAb1 oxidation variants to FcRn 
in the pH-gradient of the FcRn chromatography predominantly 
depends on the total number of Met252 oxidations per antibody 
molecule-0, 1, or 2 oxMet252-but not on the oxidation status 
at position Met428, has been verified by the accumulated analyti-
cal data. The results of these analyses are summarized in Table 1 
and Figure 6 with the 10 IgG oxidation variants assigned to the 
corresponding peaks in the FcRn chromatogram. 
To complement these data that strongly suggest that Met252 oxi-
dation is the dominant negative factor for FcRn/IgG interactions, a 
second in vitro FcRn-binding assay on SPR basis and an in vivo eval-
uation in a relevant PK model was performed with the five samples. </p>

<p>FcRn binding analysis 
Surface plasmon resonance (SPR) analysis was performed to 
characterize the properties of the five samples with regard to FcRn </p>

<p>Figure 5. ESI-MS analysis results of plasmin-digested samples: (1) mAb1, 
(2) mAb1_Ox, (3) mAb1_Ox_main peak, (4) mAb1_Ox_prepeak I, (5) 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak II. Signals in the mass spectra represent number of 
methionine oxidations (indicated by dotted lines and italic numbers; 
C16 Da for each oxidation) in the intact Fc (minimum 0, maximum 4 
oxMet per Fc). The sketch shows the resulting fragment after plasmin 
digest: Disulfide-linked, intact Fc with 4 potential oxMets. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>
binding. For this, the nature of the on-rate, the total binding levels 
(RU max.) and the characteristics of the dissociation were assessed 
(Fig. 7A and B). MAb1_Ox exhibited a significant decrease of 
21% in total binding levels compared with mAb1. After fraction-
ation, mAb1_Ox_main peak showed the highest overall binding 
and slowest off-rate of all five samples with the 6% improvement in 
total binding compared with mAb1 being significant. The binding 
properties of this variant are noteworthy considering the 20% 
oxMet428 (and 3% oxMet252) content of mAb1_Ox_main peak </p>

<p>compared with baseline oxidation levels in mAb1 (Table 1). These 
data suggest that oxMet428 does not impair the FcRn/IgG interac-
tions and may even hint toward a positive effect on FcRn affinity. 
In comparison to mAb1 and mAb1_Ox_main peak, mAb1_Ox_-
prepeaks I and II show a significant and stepwise loss of binding lev-
els and increased off-rates. The RU max. values of mAb1_Ox_pre 
peak I and mAb1_Ox_prepeak II are reduced by 33% and 67%, 
respectively, compared with mAb1. In summary, data from SPR-
based FcRn binding analysis nicely correlated with the binding 
properties of the five samples observed on the FcRn affinity column 
(Figs. 4 and 7). </p>

<p>PK in human FcRn-transgenic mice 
The stepwise reduction of FcRn affinity of the three isolated 
mAb1 oxidation variants demonstrated by FcRn chromatography 
and SPR analysis suggested an impact on in vivo clearance due to 
impairment of the FcRn-mediated IgG recycling mechanism. To 
explore the effect of Met252 and Met428 oxidation on antibody 
clearance and terminal half-life, a PK study was performed in a 
human FcRn-transgenic mouse model. HuFcRn-transgenic mice 
were chosen to provide for the well-known species-specificity of 
the FcRn/IgG interaction. 
29 Importantly, mAb1 does not bind 
to the murine target. HuFcRn transgenic mice were injected 
intravenously with a single dose of the five samples at a dose level 
of 10 mg/kg. The corresponding serum concentrations were ana-
lyzed over a time period of 28 d. Serum concentrations vs. time 
profiles of all samples exhibited a biphasic profile with an initial 
rapid decrease in antibody serum concentration within the first 
24 h followed by a log-linear decline over time as shown in 
Figure 8A. PK parameters calculated from these curves revealed 
that only mAb1_Ox_prepeak II had a significantly higher sys-
temic clearance rate of 0.083  § 0.008 mL/min/kg compared 
with untreated mAb1 (0.044  § 0.002 mL/min/kg; P &lt; 0.0001). 
MAb1_Ox and mAb1_Ox_prepeak I, showed apparent faster 
systemic clearance rates of 0.048  § 0.003 and 0.049  § 
0.002 mL/min/kg, respectively (Fig. 8B). However, these values 
are not significantly different compared with the ones obtained 
for mAb1 (P values 0.059). 
Interestingly, mAb1_Ox_main peak is cleared significantly 
slower compared with the non-oxidized mAb1 control sample 
(0.038  § 0.002 mL/min/kg; P D 0.022). Although this differ-
ence is rather small and at the limit of significance, it is in agree-
ment with the FcRn SPR analysis data obtained for this sample </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of sample characterization results </p>

<p>Sample 
Peptide Map 
Plasmin digest/ ESI-MS </p>

<p>oxMet252 [%] 
oxMet428 [%] 
No. oxMet per Fc </p>

<p>1: mAb1 
5 
2 
0, 1 
2: mAb1_Ox 
41 
28 
0, 1, 2, 3, 4 
3: mAb1_Ox_main peak 
3 
20 
0, 1, 2 
4: mAb1_Ox_prepeak I 
50 
23 
1, 2, 3 
5: mAb1_Ox_prepeak II 
90 
42 
2, 3, 4 </p>

<p>Note: Left column: Sample names. Middle column: Total oxMet252 and ox Met428 levels from tryptic LC-MS peptide map analysis. Right column: 
Numbers of oxMet per Fc (minimum 0, maximum 4 oxMet) from LC-ESI-MS analysis of plasmin-digested samples. </p>

<p>Figure 6. FcRn chromatogram of mAb1_Ox with the relative peak areas 
of the 3 separated peaks. Arrows indicate the mAb1 oxidation variants in 
the 3 peaks according to the results of LC-MS peptide map and plasmin 
digest/ESI-MS analysis. </p>

<p> 
Volume 6 Issue 5 
mAbs </p>

<p>Figure 7. SPR analysis of FcRn/IgG interaction. (A) Binding level (on-rate). (B) Off-rates (normalized RU max. values). Samples: (1) mAb1, (2) mAb1_Ox, (3) 
mAb1_Ox_main peak, (4) mAb1_Ox_prepeak I, (5) mAb1_Ox_prepeak II. Evaluation of SPR-data was performed by comparison of the biological response 
signal height at 180 s after injection. All signals were normalized to mAb1 (100%). </p>

<p>Figure 8. Pharmacokinetic analysis in huFcRn-transgenic mice. (A) Serum concentration over time after single bolus injection. Samples: (1) mAb1, (2) 
mAb1_Ox, (3) mAb1_Ox_main peak, (4) mAb1_Ox_prepeak I, (5) mAb1_Ox_prepeak II. (B) Bar diagram of plasma clearance. Corresponding clearance 
and terminal half-life values for all 5 indicated samples are given in the table above the graph. </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>
and suggests that the 20% oxMet428 content may result in 
improved FcRn affinity and PK properties. 
Direct comparison of the PK parameters of the three isolated 
mAb1_Ox fractions mAb1_Ox_mainpeak, mAb1_Ox_prepeak I 
and mAb1_Ox_prepeak II revealed a stepwise increase in clear-
ance that is in accordance with the sequential FcRn chromatogra-
phy elution profile and the stepwise decrease of total binding 
levels in SPR analysis. Using a Pearson correlation test, it was 
demonstrated that the systemic clearances of the three antibody 
oxidation variants were significantly different from each other 
(P values &lt; 0.0001). 
Serum terminal half-life values were 2.3-fold lower for 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak II (t 1/2 D 13.4  § 2.2 h) compared with its 
untreated control mAb1 (t 1/2 D 30.2  § 8.6 h) (Fig. 8B). Termi-
nal half-lives of the three purified variants decreased stepwise 
from 38.8  § 1.2 h (mAb1_Ox_main peak) to 28.0  § 3.0 h 
(mAb1_Ox_prepeak I) to 13.4  § 2.2 h (mAb1_Ox_pre peak 
II), and therefore are inversely correlated with increasing levels of 
Met252 oxidation. mAb1_Ox_ main peak, despite carrying 20% 
oxMet428, showed the longest terminal half-lives (t 1/2 D 38.8  § 
1.2 h) among all compounds tested (P 0.0216) and compared 
with untreated mAb1. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Structure-function relationship-current situation 
The detailed understanding of the structure-function relation-
ship of Fc methionine oxidation is of great importance for the 
development of therapeutic antibodies. The limited knowledge 
of how exactly Met252 and Met428 oxidation influence the PK 
of therapeutic IgGs necessitates considerable efforts to monitor 
these modifications upon release and storage of drug substance 
and drug product batches. Fc methionine oxidation is generally 
regarded as a potential critical quality attribute (pCQA) and 
changes in the Met oxidation levels during manufacturing or 
storage raise justified questions concerning the effect on shelf-life 
and in vivo clearance. 
In previous studies, oxidized antibody batches were evaluated 
that differed in their total Met oxidation levels, but always con-
tained both oxMet252 and oxMet428, with the former being 
more prominent. 
8,9,22 As the four methionine residues in an IgG 
Fc give rise to a total of 10 oxidation variants (Fig. 1) with poten-
tially distinct FcRn affinities and PK profiles, it is not feasible 
using such mixtures to investigate which variants are altered in 
their properties and which are not. 
8 This is complicated by the 
fact that an antibody can theoretically be bound by two FcRn 
molecules, one per HC. 
35 Therefore, methionine oxidation in 
only one HC of an IgG, even at both positions, may not result in 
faster clearance since the other HC is still able to fully interact 
with FcRn. This clearly highlights the demand for a different 
approach to investigate the effect of Fc methionine oxidation on 
FcRn binding and PK in more detail. 
Available chromatographic methods, such as Protein A affinity 
chromatography, are valuable analytical tools to resolve and assess 
overall Fc methionine oxidation levels in degraded antibody </p>

<p>samples, but they are not capable of separating functionally dis-
tinct oxidation variants with sufficient resolution. </p>

<p>8,9,21,32 </p>

<p>Attempts to oxidize one methionine position selectively while 
leaving the second position intact have all failed, since both posi-
tions are similarly prone to oxidation. The rate of oxidation of 
Met252 is approximately twice that of Met428, leading to a 
higher oxMet252 than oxMet428 content after forced oxidation 
or real-time storage. 
7-9,22,25 The use of point mutations to mimic 
or block oxidation either at Met252 or Met428 leads to consider-
able changes in the affinity to FcRn, likely due to structural dis-
tortions in the Fc. 
26,33 Exchange of Met252 and Met428 has 
been shown to compromise or increase FcRn interactions. </p>

<p>26,34 </p>

<p>Such mutational approaches are of value, but cannot simulate the 
situation of methionine oxidation exactly. They need to be 
designed with great care in order to enable conclusions relevant 
for the wild-type situation. Due to these reasons, a highly 
resolved structure-function relationship of the individual effect of 
oxMet252 and oxMet428 has not been established yet. </p>

<p>Relevance of pH gradient FcRn chromatography 
The pH gradient FcRn affinity chromatography method used 
in this study was recently introduced as a new analytical tool for 
monitoring the interactions of monoclonal antibodies and FcRn 
in vitro under physiological conditions. 
27 In contrast to other 
analytical methods commonly applied to study FcRn/IgG inter-
actions in vitro (e.g., SPR), FcRn affinity chromatography condi-
tions reflect the pH-dependency of the interaction in an 
unprecedented manner. 
13 While SPR analysis only yields overall 
kinetic or binding values and is unable to resolve and quantify 
antibody species differing in their affinity to the receptor, FcRn 
affinity chromatography allows direct identification and quantifi-
cation of individual IgG species with altered binding functionali-
ties. Adjustment of the pH gradient allows optimal separation 
and characterization of antibody variants detected in a sample of 
interest. In comparison to common chromatographic methods 
(e.g., size exclusion or ion-exchange chromatography) that utilize 
artificial matrices and binding groups for separation, FcRn chro-
matography resolves molecule species based on their affinity to 
an immobilized physiological interaction partner. 
21,30,31 Similar 
to these methods, FcRn chromatography can be scaled up to 
facilitate preparative isolation of variants. This enables secondary 
characterization strategies for the separated variants, such as phys-
ico-chemical analysis and PK assessment, and facilitates the estab-
lishment of structure-function relationships. </p>

<p>Effect of methionine oxidation on FcRn binding 
The monoclonal therapeutic antibody mAb1 used for this 
investigation is a representative IgG1 kappa. MAb1 and numer-
ous other therapeutic antibodies, IgG1 and IgG4, have all exhib-
ited the same peak pattern on the FcRn affinity column after 
hydrogen peroxide treatment or storage under accelerated condi-
tions. Therefore, mAb1 is considered a representative model to 
study the structure-function relationship and the consequences of 
Fc methionine oxidation on FcRn-dependent PK of therapeutic 
antibodies in general. </p>

<p> 
Volume 6 Issue 5 
mAbs </p>

<p>After chromatographic isolation of the three peaks from 
mAb1_Ox, extended physico-chemical characterization of the 
fractionated peaks and two control samples revealed no signifi-
cant differences in purity, integrity and target binding. Indeed, 
the only significant modifications that differed strongly among 
the five samples were the quantity and distribution of Met252 
and Met428 oxidations in the Fc. 
The stepwise increase of oxMet252 levels in the three isolated 
peaks correlated well with a decrease in retention time on the 
FcRn column and faster off-rates in the SPR analysis, whereas 
oxMet428 levels did not show a similar correlation. The 
oxMet252 increase in the three peaks corresponds to the number 
of oxMet252 per IgG: 0, 1, or 2. 
Our results strongly suggest that oxidation of Met252, but 
not, or to a significantly lesser extent, of Met428, results in 
functional alterations of the FcRn binding properties of anti-
bodies. Wang et al. 
21 have previously indicated that oxidation 
of Met252 (CH2 domain) and Met428 (CH3 domain) is 
accompanied by subtle conformational changes in the FcRn 
binding region. Studies using a truncated antibody Fc demon-
strated that the main structural changes upon oxidation occur 
in the CH2 domain, whereas the CH3 is less compromised. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>The melting temperature (T m ) of the CH2 domain is 
markedly decreased upon oxidation while the T m of the CH3 
only changes slightly. In support of these findings, the rates of 
deamidation of two CH2 asparagine residues were significantly 
increased upon oxidation, while those of other residues were 
not affected. These results are in excellent agreement with our 
melting temperature data of an oxidized full-length IgG1 
(data not shown). The regions undergoing significant struc-
tural changes by oxidation of Met252 and Met428 were 
mapped to CH2 residues 243-247 using hydrogen/deuterium 
exchange LC-MS peptide mapping. 
20 In the same report, a 
detailed molecular mechanism for the affinity reduction 
between FcRn and IgG induced by Met252 oxidation has 
been suggested. Impaired hydrophobic interactions between 
oxMet252 and Pro134 of FcRn and repulsion between 
oxMet252 and Glu135 seem to be responsible for the decrease 
in affinity. While Met252 oxidation directly affected FcRn/ 
IgG binding, Met428 oxidation is hypothesized to destabilize 
the CH2-CH3 hinge region, probably by disrupting the 
hydrophobic core formed between CH2 and CH3. 
20 How-
ever, our results and the data reported by Hinton et al. 
26 on 
Met428 oxidation and site-specific mutants, respectively, may 
suggest that molecular changes at this position may also lead 
to improved FcRn binding. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic characterization-effect of oxMet252 
vs. oxMet428 
The relevance of the FcRn chromatography and SPR results 
was corroborated by the results of the PK experiments in mice 
transgenic for human FcRn. This model is extremely valuable, 
and the only non-primate surrogate system available to study 
FcRn-mediated PK properties of therapeutic antibodies and anti-
body variants in vivo. Its predictive value for the primate situa-
tion has been demonstrated previously by analyzing PK </p>

<p>properties of IgG Fc variants in monkeys. 
27,36,37 These reports 
suggest that the observed consequences of methionine oxidation 
should be translatable to the monkey and human system. 
The PK data of the five samples compellingly demonstrated 
for the first time for a wild-type IgG1 that oxidation of Met252, 
but not, or to a much lesser extent, of Met428, has a negative 
impact on FcRn-mediated PK properties. The significant differ-
ences in plasma clearance rates between the three isolated FcRn 
chromatography peaks strongly support the hypothesis that FcRn 
can interact with antibodies in vivo in a 2:1 stoichiometry. 
Importantly, compared with the untreated mAb1 sample, 
only the oxMet252/oxMet252 species (mAb1_Ox_pre-peak II), 
but neither Met252/oxMet252 (mAb1_Ox_pre-peak I) nor 
Met252/Met252 (mAb1_Ox_main peak) species, were cleared 
significantly faster. 
The similar PK profile of mAb1_Ox_prepeak I (Met252/ 
oxMet252) and mAb1 (Met252/Met252) strongly suggests that 
the interaction of a single functional HC with FcRn is enough to 
convey the typical antibody PK. According to these findings, a 
1:1 stoichiometry for the FcRn/IgG1 interaction is sufficient in 
vivo. However, the »20% difference in the Met428 oxidation 
content between these two samples also has to be considered. 
Interestingly, antibody species with only increased Met428 oxi-
dation levels (mAb1_Ox_main peak: 20% oxMet428), but base-
line oxMet252 content (3%), exhibited increased affinity to 
FcRn in SPR analysis and significantly slower plasma clearance 
compared with mAb1 control. These surprising results, which 
may suggest a positive effect of Met428 oxidation on FcRn bind-
ing and PK, are in agreement with previous studies in which 
Met428Leu mutants were evaluated in rhesus monkeys. 
26 This 
mutant showed an 11-fold increase in binding to human FcRn at 
pH 6.0 compared with the wild-type counterpart in a competi-
tive FcRn binding assay. PK analysis in rhesus monkeys demon-
strated an »2.3-fold lower mean clearance for a T250Q/M428L 
double mutant compared with wild-type IgG. 
26 While the domi-
nant negative impact of Met252 oxidation on FcRn/IgG interac-
tions and in vivo clearance is apparent from our results, the 
potential positive effect of Met428 oxidation is less evident, but 
should at least be considered for data interpretation. 
The substantial levels of Met252 (41%) and Met428 (28%) 
oxidation make it difficult to comprehend why mAb1_Ox 
showed a similar PK profile as mAb1. However, coinciding 
observations have been reported previously by Wang et al. 
8 and 
may be explained by interpretation of our data. MAb1_Ox is 
comprised of a mixture of three main mAb1 oxidation variants 
with each showing a distinctive PK profile in our study. The inte-
gration of the relative peak areas in the analytical FcRn chro-
matogram of mAb1_Ox yielded: 30% mAb1_Ox main peak 
with the slowest clearance of all five samples (even slower than 
mAb1), 20% mAb1_Ox_prepeak II with the fastest clearance 
(approx. twice the rate of mAb1), and 50% mAb1_Ox_prepeak I 
with a clearance that is slightly, but not significantly, faster than 
that of mAb1 (Figs. 6 and 8B). This composition may help to 
explain the relatively indistinguishable PK profile of mAb1_Ox 
compared with mAb1. The fast clearance of 20% of the antibod-
ies (mAb1_Ox_prepeak II) in the mixture seems to be partially </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>
compensated by 30% of molecules that exhibit a small, but sig-
nificantly slower clearance (mAb1_Ox_main peak). From the rel-
ative quantities of the three variants in mAb1_Ox, obtained from 
the integrated peak areas, and from the clearance values of the 
three isolated variants, a theoretical clearance for mAb1_Ox can 
be calculated that corresponds accurately to the plasma clearance 
experimentally determined in the PK study (data not shown). 
Thus, the experimental data indeed support the hypothesis that 
oxidation at Met428 alone may lead to somewhat improved 
FcRn binding. 
If Met428 oxidation actually has this effect, it is surprising 
that 42% oxMet428 in the mAb1_Ox_prepeak II sample were 
not able to compensate some of the effect of the 90% 
oxMet252. On the contrary, the clearance of this sample is 
markedly faster than expected from the clearance slope between 
mAb1_Ox_main peak and prepeak I. It appears that Met428 
oxidation can amplify the reduction in FcRn affinity and 
increase in clearance if it occurs in parallel to Met252 oxidation. 
Possibly, Met428 oxidation has an additional negative effect on 
FcRn binding only if co-located on the same HC with 
oxMet252. In this case, the higher oxMet428 levels in 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak II compared with the other two peaks may 
be the result of the fractionation procedure. In this sample, the 
early eluting flank of the peak was included, while it was omit-
ted during fractionation of the two other peaks (Fig. 3C). For 
example, for mAb1_Ox_main peak, only the late eluting 2/3 of 
the peak were collected. In case there would be a gradient of oxi-
dation sub-species within the three peaks, the variants </p>

<p>containing both oxMet252 and oxMet428 on the same HCs 
would most probably exhibit the lowest affinity to the FcRn col-
umn, and thus elute in the front flank of the respective peaks. 
This hypothesis can be supported by the asymmetrical shape of 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak II that exhibits a small shoulder at lower 
retention times (Fig. 3C). Further studies of the distribution of 
oxMet428 and oxMet252 within the individual three peaks are 
required to investigate this. 
Another potential reason for the higher oxMet428 levels in 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak II is that preceding Met252 oxidation indu-
ces structural changes that in turn lead to higher solvent exposure 
of Met428, and thereby an increased oxidation rate. 
In summary, it appears that Met428 oxidation has no signifi-
cant negative consequence and may even lead to somewhat 
increased FcRn affinity if not accompanied by Met252 oxidation. 
On the other hand, it seems to amplify the loss of FcRn affinity 
and impairment of PK properties when it occurs in parallel (on 
the same HC) to the faster and functionally dominant Met252 
oxidation. </p>

<p>Relevance for the analytical control strategy and the 
in vivo situation 
Although the FcRn chromatography method is a valuable ana-
lytical tool that allows the separation and quantification of the 3 
Met252 oxidation variants based on their FcRn affinity, it is not 
yet established as a standard release or characterization method 
for monoclonal antibodies. Overall methionine oxidation is gen-
erally quantified using LC-MS peptide map analysis. 
Assuming that methionine 
oxidation occurs under first-
order kinetics and that the rate 
of Met252 oxidation is approx. 
twice that of Met428 oxidation, 
it is actually possible to simulate 
the relative quantities of all 10 
oxidation species for a certain 
IgG lot with known total 
oxMet252 and oxMet428 levels 
using a model described previ-
ously. 
8,23 This model could not 
be verified experimentally up to 
now because a method to sepa-
rate the 10 oxidation variants 
for quantification and analytical 
characterization did not exist. 
Using FcRn affinity chromatog-
raphy, we could now determine 
the distribution of the three 
main Met252 oxidation variants 
in 
mAb1_Ox 
(Met252/ 
Met252, oxMet252/Met252, 
and 
oxMet252/oxMet252) 
experimentally. Although the 
column was not capable of fully 
resolving the additional Met428 
oxidation heterogeneity within </p>

<p>Scheme 1. Relative distribution of all 10 mAb1 methionine oxidation variants in mAb1_Ox. Due to the homodi-
meric structure of IgG, the oxidation hotspots are present in duplicate. Relative values from the theoretical sim-
ulation are compared with experimentally derived values. Clearance for the 3 Met252 oxidation variants is 
compared with mAb1 control. 
1 Relative peak areas in mAb1_Ox FcRn chromatogram (Fig. 6.) 
2 According to 
peptide map and plasmin digest/ESI-MS analysis (Table 1, Figure 6.) 
3 Simulation for 41% oxMet252 (acc. to Ion-
escu et al. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>); reaction rates k oxMet252 D 0.19 h 
¡1 and k oxMet428 D 0.09 h 
¡1 (acc. to Pan et al. 
9 ). 
4 Assuming bino-
mial distribution of oxMet428 vs Met428 within the 3 isolated peaks, the variant distribution in mAb1_Ox can 
be calculated from the total oxMet428 content (peptide map) and the rel. peak areas (Table 1 and Figure 6). 
For example, for variant mAb1_Ox_main peak_oxMet428/Met428 (in bold): 2 (HC isomers, one oxMet428 on 
left or on right HC) x 0.2 (oxMet428 content in mAb1_Ox_main peak) x 0.8 (Met428 content in mAb1_Ox_main 
peak) x 0.3 (rel. peak area of mAb1_Ox_main peak in FcRn chromatogram) x 100 D »10%. </p>

<p> 
Volume 6 Issue 5 
mAbs </p>

<p>these three peaks, the Met428/oxMet428 distribution can be eas-
ily calculated from the peptide map data assuming a binomial 
distribution (Scheme 1). Indeed, when comparing the relative 
quantities of the 10 oxidation variants of mAb1_Ox derived 
from our experimental data set with the simulation performed 
according to Ionescu et al., 
23 a good agreement of the results is 
observed. The reaction rates for the oxidation used for this simu-
lation were 0.19 h 
¡1 and 0.09 h 
¡1 for Met252 and Met428 oxi-
dation, respectively. 
9 Notable discrepancies between the 
experimental and simulated values were observed mainly for the 
three highly oxidized species containing three or four oxidized 
methionines. Discrepancies may be due to the negligence of 
structural changes induced by oxidation at one position that lead 
to altered reaction rates for the remaining three methionines in 
the simulation model. 
It is noteworthy that only the clearance of the oxMet252/ 
oxMet252 antibody variants (equivalent to mAb1_Ox_prepeak 
II) was significantly faster with a factor of »2 compared with 
untreated mAb1 in this study. The half-lives of the other variants 
that contain no or only one oxMet252 per IgG were not signifi-
cantly decreased. This means that the exposure of the oxMet252/ 
oxMet252 species was still »50% of that obtained for mAb1 
control. In comparison, the exposure of the other variants was at 
least 100% compared with mAb1. According to these observa-
tions, it should be sufficient to consider the relative content of 
the oxMet252/oxMet252 species, determined either by FcRn 
chromatography or by calculation from peptide map data assum-
ing a binomial distribution of oxMet252 and Met252, in order 
to estimate the PK properties of an antibody batch, e.g., after 
extended storage. 
In mAb1_Ox, the relative content of the oxMet252/ 
oxMet252 variant was determined to be 20% using FcRn chro-
matography, whereas 80% of molecules were oxMet252/Met252 
and Met252/Met252 variants (both exhibiting 100% exposure). 
Since the 20% oxMet252/oxMet252 variant still conveyed half 
of the exposure of unmodified IgG, it is comprehendible why the 
exposure of mAb1_Ox was not significantly lower than that of 
mAb1 in our study despite of the high overall Met252 and 
Met428 oxidation levels. 
Thus, IgG batches with a total oxMet252 level of »40% (e.g., 
mAb1_Ox) contain »80% molecules that have at least one HC 
intact and are able to bind to FcRn. 
These considerations are in agreement with previous PK 
studies conducted in huFcRn-transgenic mice, where such 
oxidized antibody preparations exhibited similar PK proper-
ties as the unmodified control sample. 
8 A markedly deterio-
rated PK profile was only observed after the oxMet252 
content was increased to 80% by extended incubation with 
hydrogen peroxide. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Considering that the levels of Fc methionine oxidation 
after hydrogen peroxide treatment as applied in our study 
and in the literature (e.g., Wang et al. 
8 ) are far higher than 
those typically observed during normal refrigerated shelf-life, 
it appears unlikely that overall PK properties of therapeutic 
antibody preparations will be negatively affected by oxidation 
events. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Three main antibody oxidation variants were isolated from a 
hydrogen peroxide-treated IgG batch based on their different 
FcRn binding properties utilizing the novel pH gradient FcRn 
affinity chromatography as a preparative tool. By this approach 
we were able to isolate and characterize antibody oxidation var-
iants differing in the content of oxMet252 and, to a lesser extent, 
oxMet428 for the first time. FcRn/IgG interaction characteristics 
in the FcRn chromatography were confirmed by SPR analysis 
and have been shown to be predictive of FcRn-mediated PK 
properties in vivo. Met252 oxidation was the dominant contribu-
tor to PK impairment observed in mice transgenic for the human 
FcRn receptor. Importantly, increased plasma clearance was only 
observed if both IgG HCs were oxidized at Met252. The effect 
of Met428 oxidation on FcRn binding is most probably subordi-
nate to the dominant chemical/structural changes due to Met252 
oxidation, but may amplify this negative effect if co-localized. 
Overall, the results presented here suggest that the relevance of 
methionine oxidation for the FcRn-dependent PK properties of 
therapeutic antibodies may have been overestimated, and that a 
very high oxidation threshold has to be exceeded (»&gt;50% 
oxMet252) before markedly faster plasma clearance is observed 
in vivo. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Sample preparation 
Approximately 200 mg of a representative humanized mono-
clonal IgG1 (G1m1,17 allotype) from the Roche development 
portfolio were treated with 0.01% (v/v) hydrogen peroxide for 
18 h according to published protocols to induce methionine oxi-
dation in the Fc. 
7 The oxidation reaction was quenched by addi-
tion of 50 mM L-methionine solution. The original untreated 
antibody batch was termed mAb1, whereas the H 2 O 2 -treated 
portion of the batch was named mAb1_Ox. 
The FcRn affinity chromatography method was described pre-
viously. 
27 For preparative purposes, 60 mg FcRn/b2-microglo-
bulin were expressed, purified and biotinylated as described. For 
coupling, 10 g streptavidin sepharose (GE Healthcare) were 
added to the prepared receptor and incubated for two hours at 
room temperature under mild shaking. The resulting FcRn-
sepharose matrix was filled in a XK 16 column housing (W 
1.6 cm £ L 6 cm, GE Healthcare) and incorporated in an 
€ 
AKTA Avant chromatography system (GE Healthcare). The col-
umn was equilibrated with 20 mM 2-(N-morpholine)-ethanesul-
fonic acid (MES) buffer containing 150 mM NaCl, pH 5.5 
(eluent A) at a flow rate of 2 ml/min. 
The oxidized antibody sample mAb1_Ox containing »20 mg 
of IgG was adjusted to pH 5.5 by dilution with eluent A and 
applied to the FcRn column at room temperature. The column 
was washed with 5 column volumes of eluent A followed by elu-
tion of the bound antibody in a linear gradient from 0-100% 
20 mM Tris/HCl, 150 mM NaCl, pH 8.5 (eluent B) in 40 col-
umn volumes. The elution profile was obtained by continuous </p>

<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>

<p>
measurement of the absorbance at 280 nm. The eluate was col-
lected in 4 ml fractions that were pooled as depicted in Fig-
ure 3C, resulting in three samples: mAb1_Ox_prepeak II, 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak I and mAb1_Ox_main peak (in sequence of 
elution). In order to obtain sufficient quantities of all three sepa-
rated antibody oxidation variants for the intended characteriza-
tion, fractions of eight separation runs were collected, pooled and 
concentrated to »1 mg/ml using 15 ml Amicon Ultra centrifu-
gal filters (10 kD, Millipore). All five resulting samples (mAb1, 
mAb1_Ox, mAb1_Ox_main peak, mAb1_Ox_prepeak I and 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak II) were subsequently dialyzed against the 
formulation buffer for mAb1: 20 mM sodium citrate, 190 mM 
sucrose, 20 mM L-arginine, 0.02% polysorbate 20, pH 5.5, sup-
plemented with 5 mM L-methionine. Protein concentration was 
adjusted to 1 mg/ml in all samples and aliquots were stored at 
-70 
C until use. </p>

<p>Analytical FcRn chromatography 
Separation and sample homogeneity after the preparative 
FcRn chromatography runs were confirmed for all five samples 
by analytical scale FcRn affinity chromatography. For this, 
FcRn-sepharose matrix was filled in a MonoQ column housing 
(inner diameter 5 mm £ length 50 mm, GE Healthcare) and 
incorporated in a HPLC system with UV detector. The column 
was equilibrated with 20 mM 2-(N-morpholine)-ethanesulfonic 
acid (MES) buffer containing 150 mM NaCl, pH 5.5 (eluent A) 
at 0.3 ml/min. Thirty mg of each sample were diluted at a vol-
ume ratio of 1:1 with eluent A and applied to the FcRn column 
at room temperature. The column was washed with 5 column 
volumes of eluent A followed by elution in a linear gradient from 
0-100% 20 mM Tris/HCl, 150 mM NaCl, pH 8.5 (eluent B) 
in 36 column volumes. The elution profile was obtained by con-
tinuous measurement of the absorbance at 280 nm. 
The five samples (mAb1, mAb1_Ox, mAb1_Ox_main peak, 
mAb1_Ox_prepeak I and mAb1_Ox_prepeak II) intended for 
PK evaluation were subjected to a full physico-chemical and 
functional characterization in vitro. </p>

<p>Physico-chemical and functional characterization 
For determination of protein concentration, dilutions of the 
generated samples were performed with placebo buffer on an 
analytical balance at room temperature. Weights of used sample 
aliquots and diluted samples were recorded with four decimal 
places. For each sample, three independent dilutions were per-
formed and analyzed in a qualified UV spectrophotometer at 
280 nm and 320 nm. After subtracting the absorbance of 
320 nm, from the 280 nm absorbance, the protein concentration 
was calculated according to Lambert-Beer law using the dilution 
factors and averaging the concentrations obtained from the three 
independent dilutions per sample. Concentrations were reported 
with two decimals. Furthermore, the following analytical meth-
ods were applied: Size-exclusion chromatography, non-gel siev-
ing denaturing capillary electrophoresis (CE-SDS; non-reduced 
and reduced), capillary isoelectric focusing (CE-IEF), reverse-
phase UPLC of released and labeled oligosaccharides, mAb1-
specific SPR target binding assay and mAb1-specific qualified </p>

<p>cell-based functional assay (the latter two assays were developed 
in-house). 
38-44 The five samples were comparable with regard to 
quality and physico-chemical properties by using the above men-
tioned analytical methods, e.g., very low aggregate content, unal-
tered charge distribution, identical oligosaccharide profiles, in 
vitro target binding and functionality (data not shown). </p>

<p>Tryptic peptide mapping by RP-HPLC-MS/MS 
An aliquot of 190 mL 8M guanidine hydrochloride/0.4 M tris 
(hydroxymethyl)aminomethane hydrochloride (TRIS-HCl), pH 
8.0 was added to 50 mg protein in 50 mL formulation buffer and 
incubated for 1 h at 37 
C with 20 mL 0.24 M dithiothreitol 
(DTT). Subsequently the mixture was incubated with 20 mL 
0.6 M iodoacetic acid for 0.25 h at room temperature in the dark. 
Reaction was quenched by addition of 30 mL 0.24 M DTT. The 
sample was transferred into 482 mL 50 mM TRIS-HCl by buffer 
exchange on a Sephadex G25 column. For tryptic digests, 13.4 mL 
trypsin (Promega, sequencing grade) (0.25 mg/mL trypsin in 
50 mM TRIS-HCl) were added. The addition of trypsin was 
repeated after 2.5 h, the total incubation time was 5 h at 37 
C 
and the final mAb1/trypsin ratio »36:1 (w/w). For quenching, 
20 mL 10% formic acid were added. The sample was centrifuged at 
9,000 g for 5 min. An ACQUITY nanoUPLC (Waters) running 
in "high flow mode" followed by a Triversa Nanomate nanoESI-
source (Advion) and coupled with a LTQ-Orbitrap (Thermo) was 
used for sample analysis. Four ml of sample were loaded onto a 
ACQUITY UPLC column (BEH300 C18, 1.0 £ 150 mm, 
1.7 mm) using a flow rate of 60 ml/min, a column temperature of 
50 
C and a gradient of 1 to 40% eluent B (0.1% formic acid/ace-
tonitrile) in 130 min (eluent A: 0.1% formic acid). Data analysis 
was performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">XCalibur</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Thermo.</rs>). The extent 
of oxidation of a peptide was estimated in a relative manner to the 
unmodified peptide using this software. </p>

<p>Electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (ESI-MS) 
after plasmin digest 
For mass spectrometry analysis of the Fc, a plasmin digest was 
performed. For the digest, 100 mg of all five samples were dia-
lyzed using slide-a-lyzers into 50 mM Tris(hydroxymethyl)ami-
nomethane, pH 8.0, at 4 
C overnight. Subsequently, 0.1 units 
plasmin (1.05 U plasmin/mg Protein, Roche Diagnostics) were 
added to each sample and incubated at 25 
C for 72 h. After the 
digest, plasmin-treated samples (50 mg) were deglycosylated by 
adding 0.5 mL N-glycanase plus (Roche Diagnostics) and 
sodium phosphate buffer (0.1 M, pH 7.1) to obtain a final sam-
ple volume of 115 mL. The mixture was incubated at 37 
C for 
18 h. For denaturing, 100 mL of 6 M Gua¢HCl (Pierce) were 
added. The mixture was incubated at 37 
C for 30 min. Samples 
were desalted by SEC (Sepharose G-25, isocratic, 40% acetoni-
trile with 2% formic acid). ESI mass spectra (Cve) were recorded 
on a Q-TOF instrument (maXis, Bruker) equipped with a nano 
ESI source (TriVersa NanoMate, Advion). MS parameter set-
tings were as follows: Transfer: Funnel RF, 400 Vpp; ISCID 
Energy, 0 eV; Multipole RF, 400 Vpp; Quadrupole: Ion Energy, 
4.0 eV; Low Mass, 600 m/z; Source: Dry Gas, 8 L/min; Dry 
Gas Temperature, 160 
C; Collision Cell: Collision Energy, </p>

<p> 
Volume 6 Issue 5 
mAbs </p>

<p>10 eV; Collision RF: 2000 Vpp; Ion Cooler: Ion Cooler RF, 300 
Vpp; Transfer Time: 120 ms; Pre Puls Storage, 10 ms; scan range 
m/z 600 to 2000. Software (<rs type="software">MassAnalyzer</rs>) developed in-house 
was used for data evaluation. </p>

<p>Surface plasmon resonance analysis -FcRn binding 
The FcRn binding properties of mAb1 starting material were 
compared with that of the other four samples by SPR technology 
using a BiaCore T100 instrument (BiaCore AB). FcRn receptor 
was immobilized on a Biacore CM5-biosensor chip (GE Health-
care Bioscience) via amine coupling to a level of 400 response 
units (RU). The assay was performed at room temperature with 
PBS, 0.05% polysorbate 20, pH 6.0 (GE Healthcare Bioscience) 
as running and dilution buffer. A total of 200 nM of each 
antibody sample were injected at a flow rate of 50 mL/min at 
room temperature. Association time was 180 s, dissociation 
phase was 360 s. Regeneration of the chip surface was accom-
plished by a short injection of HBS-P, pH 8.0. Evaluation of 
SPR-data was performed by comparing the response signal 
height at 180 s after injection and the dissociation behavior 
by overlay. The corresponding parameters are the RU max 
level (180 s after injection) and a sensorgram alignment. The 
RU max values were calculated in relative difference values to 
the reference mAb1 material. </p>

<p>Pharmacokinetic study in human FcRn-transgenic mice 
Female C57BL/6J mice deficient in mouse FcRn a chain gene, 
but hemizygous transgenic for a human FcRn a-chain gene 
(mFcRn¡/¡ huFcRn tg C/¡, line 276; Jackson Laboratories, 
Bar Harbor, USA) were used throughout the PK studies. 
45,46 Pro-
cedures were performed in accordance with the guidelines of the 
Association for Assessment and Accreditation of Laboratory Ani-
mal Care (http://www.aaalac.org). All studies were authorized by 
the Regional Council of Oberbayern, Germany. 
The five antibody samples were given as a single intravenous 
bolus injection via the tail vein. Due to limited blood volume of 
mice, three groups of six animals each were required to cover 
nine sampling time points, i.e., three sampling time points per 
animal. Blood samples were taken in group 1 at 5 min, 24 and 
336 h, in group 2 at 2, 168 and 504 h, and in group 3 at 8, 48, 
and 672 h after administration. Blood samples of about 100 mL 
were obtained by retrobulbar puncture and stored at room tem-
perature for 60 min to allow clotting. Serum samples of at least 
40 mL were obtained by centrifugation at 9300 x g at 4 
C for 
3 min and immediately frozen and stored at -20 
C until 
analyzed. </p>

<p>Serum levels of the five antibody samples were determined by 
a mAb1-antigen-captured electrochemiluminescence immunoas-
say using the ELECSYS e411 immunoanalyzer (Roche Diagnos-
tics). Briefly, serum samples, undiluted or pre-diluted with assay 
buffer, were incubated with capture and detection molecules for 
9 min at 37 
C. Biotinylated recombinant mAb1 antigen was 
used as capture molecule and a ruthenium(II) tris (bipyridyl) 3 </p>

<p>2C </p>

<p>(Ru[bpy] 3 
2C ) labeled anti-Ab1-idiotype mouse monoclonal anti-
body was used for detection. Streptavidin-coated magnetic 
microparticles were added and incubated for additional 9 min at 
37 
C to allow complex formation due to biotin-streptavidin 
interactions. Complexes are magnetically captured on an 
electrode and a chemiluminescent signal generated using the 
co-reactant tripropylamine (TPA) was measured by a photomul-
tiplier detector. All serum samples and positive or negative con-
trol samples were analyzed in replicates and calibrated against 
reference standard. 
PK parameters were calculated by non-compartmental analysis, 
using the PK evaluation program <rs id="software-2" type="software">WinNonlin</rs> 
TM (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Pharsight</rs>), <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">ver-sion 5.2.1</rs>. Briefly, the area under the concentration/time curve 
AUC (0-672 h) was calculated by linear trapezoidal rule (with lin-
ear interpolation) from time 0 to infinity. The apparent terminal 
half-life (t 1/2 ) was derived from the equation: t 1/2 D ln2 / lz. 
Total body clearance (CL) was calculated as Dose/AUC. Statisti-
cally significant differences in the PK parameters between different 
mAb1 preparations were determined by ANOVA analysis. </p>

<p>Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest </p>

<p>All authors are current or former employees of Roche Diag-
nostics GmbH. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Isabel Hermann, Andreas Petzold, Adrian Zwick 
and Simone Lutz for contributing to the sample characterization. 
Hans Auer and Stefan Seeber have kindly provided the FcRn. All 
above colleagues are or were part of Roche Research and Early 
Development (pRED), Roche Innovation Center Penzberg, Ger-
many. Ulla Grauschopf (Pharmaceutical Development and Sup-
plies, Roche, Basel, Switzerland) kindly supported the study with 
thermal stability data of an oxidized full-length antibody. </p>

<p>Supplemental Material </p>

<p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed on the 
publisher's website. </p>



<p>www.landesbioscience.com </p>



<p>
 
Volume 6 Issue 5 
mAbs </p>

</text></tei>