<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4926940" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: The purpose of this study was to examine the relationship among academic self-efficacy, socially-prescribed perfectionism, 
and academic burnout in medical school students and to determine whether academic self-efficacy had a mediating role in the 
relationship between perfectionism and academic burnout. 
Methods: A total of 244 first-year and second-year premed medical students and first-to fourth-year medical students were enrolled 
in this study. As study tools, socially-prescribed perfectionism, academic self-efficacy, and academic burnout scales were utilized. 
For data analysis, correlation analysis, multiple regression analysis, and hierarchical multiple regression analyses were conducted. 
Results: Academic burnout had correlation with socially-prescribed perfectionism. It had negative correlation with academic self-efficacy. 
Socially-prescribed perfectionism and academic self-efficacy had 54% explanatory power for academic burnout. When socially-prescribed 
perfectionism and academic self-efficacy were simultaneously used as input, academic self-efficacy partially mediated the relationship 
between socially-prescribed perfectionism and academic burnout. 
Conclusion: Socially-prescribed perfectionism had a negative effect on academic self-efficacy, ultimately triggering academic 
burnout. This suggests that it is important to have educational and counseling interventions to improve academic self-efficacy by 
relieving academic burnout of medical school students. </p>

<p>Many students who were at the top of their class at </p>

<p>high school have experienced disappointment over their </p>

<p>academic scores in medical school. They often have </p>

<p>extreme stress caused by overloaded studies and anxiety </p>

<p>over worries of failing courses, subsequently leading to </p>

<p>their loss of self-confidence or feeling inferior. This </p>

<p>seems to be especially true for those students who have </p>

<p>advanced to medical school because of excellent high </p>

<p>school grades or expectations and persuasion by parents </p>

<p>or close friends. They usually lack self-motivation for </p>

<p>medical school studies, thus experiencing academic </p>

<p>difficulties [1]. Active investigations into Korean acade-</p>

<p>mic burnout of medical students began after 2012. A few </p>

<p>studies have attempted to determine the relationship </p>

<p>between perfectionism and academic burnout or between </p>

<p>self-efficacy and academic burnout [2,3], hence elucida-</p>

<p>ting causative variables of academic burnout in medical </p>

<p>Ji Hye Yu, et al : The relationship among self-efficacy, perfectionism and academic burnout </p>



<p>students. </p>

<p>In this study, we focused on maladaptive variables that </p>

<p>might have threatened the psychological well-being of </p>

<p>medical students to search for psychological variables </p>

<p>that may decrease academic burnout through studying </p>

<p>the relationship between socially-prescribed perfec-</p>

<p>tionism and academic burnout. As one of the dimensions </p>

<p>of perfectionism, socially-prescribed perfectionism is </p>

<p>characterized by acknowledgement of unreal and </p>

<p>impractical assignment of academic goals not by the </p>

<p>student themselves, but by others or by the fear of </p>

<p>negative judgment by others [4]. Academic burnout </p>

<p>consists of physical, emotional, and psychological deple-</p>

<p>tion due to fatigue, frustration, distance from studies, </p>

<p>stress, helplessness, and cynical attitude as a result of </p>

<p>academic overload [2]. In a prior study [5], it was </p>

<p>observed that academic burnout was a major causative </p>

<p>variable for school maladjustment. In addition, academic </p>

<p>burnout was found to be closely related to perfectionism </p>

<p>[5]. Numerous investigations have revealed that perfec-</p>

<p>tionism tendencies and academic burnout are signifi-</p>

<p>cantly static correlated [6]. It is representative variable </p>

<p>that can aggravates negative results caused by stress and </p>

<p>a variable that may enhance academic burnout [7]. </p>

<p>Perfectionism and academic self-efficacy have been </p>

<p>confirmed as main variables that can affect academic </p>

<p>burnout [1]. That is, academic self-efficacy can in-</p>

<p>fluence the performance of students. It is also an indi-</p>

<p>vidual variable that can significantly predict academic </p>

<p>achievement. In this context, academic self-efficacy is </p>

<p>explained as an overall judgment, including self-ability </p>

<p>to manipulate and effectuate required series of acade-</p>

<p>mically related tasks [8]. In other words, individuals </p>

<p>with high academic self-efficacy will select challenging </p>

<p>task and put in further effort in order to successfully </p>

<p>complete the task. When confronted with difficult </p>

<p>obstacles, they will persevere to accomplish the tasks in </p>

<p>spite of barriers. In addition, high degrees of academic </p>

<p>self-efficacy can lead to lower levels of anxiety and </p>

<p>hence excellent self-control abilities. It can be surmised </p>

<p>that academic self-efficacy may decrease academic </p>

<p>burnout as a consequence of socially-prescribed perfec-</p>

<p>tionism. Therefore, the objectives of this study were (1) </p>

<p>to determine whether medical students' socially-</p>

<p>prescribed perfectionism could affect academic burnout, </p>

<p>and (2) to understand whether academic self-efficacy </p>

<p>could mediate the relationship between socially-</p>

<p>prescribed perfectionism and academic burnout. </p>

<p>Subjects and methods </p>

<p>1. Subject </p>

<p>A total of 227 first-year and second-year premed </p>

<p>medical students and first-to fourth-year medical </p>

<p>students who replied to questionnaire were enrolled in </p>

<p>this study. Three were excluded from this study due to </p>

<p>errors in replying. Therefore, a total of 224 replies were </p>

<p>used for this study. The questionnaire used in this study </p>

<p>was conducted between October 28 and September 9, </p>

<p>2015. Each questionnaire needed approximately 15 </p>

<p>minutes to complete. The distribution of class year and </p>

<p>gender of participants are shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>2. Measures </p>

<p>1) Socially-prescribed perfectionism </p>

<p>In order to measure socially-prescribed perfectionism, </p>

<p>multidimensional perfectionism scale developed by </p>

<p>Hewitt &amp; Flett [9] and adapted by Lee [10] was em-</p>

<p>ployed. This scale comprised of three subscales: self-</p>

<p>oriented perfectionism, socially-prescribed perfec-</p>

<p>tionism, and other-oriented perfectionism. Each sub-</p>

<p>scale comprised of 15 items. Therefore, it had a total of </p>

<p>Ji Hye Yu, et al : The relationship among self-efficacy, perfectionism and academic burnout </p>



<p>Table 1. Distribution of Class Year and Age of Medical Students </p>

<p>Year 
Gender 
Total 
Male 
Female 
Premedical students 1 
27 (18.00) 
5 (6.58) 
32 (14.29) 
Premedical students 2 
13 (8.78) 
10 (13.16) 
23 (10.27) 
Medical students 1 
28 (18.92) 
19 (25.00) 
47 (20.98) 
Medical students 2 
26 (17.57) 
14 (18.42) 
40 (17.86) 
Medical students 3 
25 (16.89) 
14 (18.42) 
39 (17.41) 
Medical students 4 
29 (19.59) 
14 (18.42) 
43 (19.20) 
Total 
148 (100.00) 
76 (100.00) 
224 (100.00) </p>

<p>Data are presented as number (%). </p>

<p>45 questionnaire items (e.g., "My family expects me to be </p>

<p>perfect"). Five-point Likert Scale was used to score for </p>

<p>each item, ranging from "strongly disagree" (1 point) to </p>

<p>"strongly agree" (5 points). Higher points indicated </p>

<p>higher degrees of perfectionism inclination. In this </p>

<p>study, we only used 15 items directly related to </p>

<p>"socially-prescribed perfectionism." Its Cronbach α </p>

<p>value was 0.794. </p>

<p>2) Academic self-efficacy </p>

<p>Academic self-efficacy was assessed using the scale </p>

<p>developed by Kim &amp; Park [8]. This scale consisted of a </p>

<p>total of 28 items in the following three subscales: </p>

<p>self-confidence (e.g., "I feel anxious when I speak in </p>

<p>front of the class"), self-regulatory efficacy (e.g., "I </p>

<p>usually make a plan for studying and adhere to the </p>

<p>plan"), and task difficulty preference (e.g., "I enjoy </p>

<p>challenging complex problems"). The 5-point Likert </p>

<p>Scale system was used. Higher scores indicated higher </p>

<p>academic self-efficacy. The academic self-efficacy </p>

<p>Cronbach α value was 0.901. The Cronbach α values for </p>

<p>subscales of self-confidence, self-regulatory efficacy, </p>

<p>and task difficulty preference were 0.717, 0.740, and </p>

<p>0.759, respectively. </p>

<p>3) Academic burnout </p>

<p>Academic burnout was measured using the Maslach </p>

<p>Burnout Inventory-Student Survey (MBI-SS) academic </p>

<p>burnout scale developed by Lee &amp; Lee [11]. This scaling </p>

<p>system had a total of 14 items, including five items of </p>

<p>emotional exhaustion (e.g., "I feel stressed and exhausted </p>

<p>from studying"), five items of inefficacy (e.g., "I know </p>

<p>how to effectively relieve stress from studying"), and </p>

<p>four items of cynicism (e.g., "I am not sure if what I am </p>

<p>studying now is necessary"). Each item was scored using </p>

<p>the 5-point Likert scaling system. Higher points were </p>

<p>interpreted as having a higher likelihood of academic </p>

<p>burnout. The Cronbach α value of academic burnout was </p>

<p>0.873. For subscales, the Cronbach α values for </p>

<p>emotional exhaustion, inefficacy, and cynicism were </p>

<p>0.887, 0.762, and 0.782, respectively. </p>

<p>3. Analysis </p>

<p>First, correlation analysis was conducted to identify </p>

<p>subscales. To determine whether academic self-efficacy </p>

<p>could mediate the relationship between socially-</p>

<p>prescribed perfectionism and academic burnout, three </p>

<p>steps of procedure suggested by Baron &amp; Kenny [12] was </p>

<p>utilized. Obtained data were subjected to statistical </p>

<p>analysis using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 12.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, </p>

<p>USA). </p>

<p>Ji Hye Yu, et al : The relationship among self-efficacy, perfectionism and academic burnout </p>



<p>Table 2. Descriptive Statistics and Correlations for the Measures </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 
1 
2 
-0.374** 
1 
3 
-0.447** 
0.763** 
1 
4 
-0.444** 
0.760** 
0.836** 
1 
5 
-0.453** 
0.909** 
0.935** 
0.935** 
1 
6 
0.353** -0.490** 
-0.566** 
-0.619** 
-0.602** 
1 
7 
0.288** -0.663** 
-0.650** 
-0.680** 
-0.719** 
0.419** 
1 
8 
0.349** -0.339** 
-0.413** 
-0.475** 
-0.440** 
0.511** 
0.346** 
1 
9 
0.428** -0.609** 
-0.675** 
-0.737** 
-0.727** 
0.856** 
0.686** 
0.803** 
1 
Mean 
2.737 
3.244 
3.167 
3.245 
3.221 
2.874 
2.790 
2.888 
2.854 
SD 
0.426 
0.518 
0.509 
0.519 
0.478 
0.889 
0.589 
0.786 
0.599 </p>

<p>1: Socially-prescribed perfectionism, 2: Self-confidence, 3: Self-regulatory efficacy, 4: Task difficulty preference, 5: Academic self-efficacy, 
6: Emotional exhaustion, 7: Inefficacy, 8: Cynicism, 9: Academic burnout, SD: Standard deviation. 
**p&lt;0.01. </p>

<p>Table 3. Multiple Regression Analysis of Socially-Prescribed Perfectionism and Academic Self-Efficacy on Academic Burnout </p>

<p>Independent variable 
Unstandardized coefficients 
Standardized coefficients 
t 
B 
SE </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>Socially-prescribed perfectionism 
0.173 
0.073 
0.123 
2.386* 
Academic self-efficacy 
-0.841 
0.064 
-0.674 
-13.044*** </p>

<p>R 
2 =0.544, adj. R 
2 =0.540, F=128.354*** </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05, ***p&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>1. Correlations among socially-prescribed </p>

<p>perfectionism, academic burnout, and </p>

<p>academic self-efficacy </p>

<p>The relationships among variables are summarized in </p>

<p>Table 2. Socially-prescribed perfectionism was positi-</p>

<p>vely correlated (r=0.428, p&lt;0.01) with academic burnout </p>

<p>while academic self-efficacy was negatively correlated </p>

<p>(r=-0.727, p&lt;0.01) with academic burnout. All subscales </p>

<p>of academic self-efficacy showed negative correlations </p>

<p>with academic burnout, including self-confidence (r= </p>

<p>-0.609, p&lt;0.01), self-regulatory efficacy (r=-0.675, p&lt; </p>

<p>0.01), and task difficulty preference (r=-0.737, p&lt;0.01). </p>

<p>In addition, there was a negative correlation (r=-0.453, </p>

<p>p&lt;0.01) between socially-prescribed perfectionism and </p>

<p>academic self-efficacy. </p>

<p>2. Effect of socially-prescribed perfectionism </p>

<p>and academic self-efficacy on academic </p>

<p>burnout </p>

<p>Multiple regression analysis was performed to evaluate </p>

<p>the effect of socially-prescribed perfectionism and </p>

<p>academic self-efficacy on academic burnout. The results </p>

<p>are shown in Table 3. Socially-prescribed perfectionism </p>

<p>and academic self-efficacy could explain 54% (F= </p>

<p>128.354, p&lt;0.001) for academic burnout. Both socially-</p>

<p>prescribed perfectionism (β=0.123, p&lt;0.05) and acade-</p>

<p>mic self-efficacy (β=-0.674, p&lt;0.001) could signifi-</p>

<p>cantly predict academic burnout. </p>

<p>Ji Hye Yu, et al : The relationship among self-efficacy, perfectionism and academic burnout </p>



<p>Table 4. Hierarchical Multiple Analysis for Examining the Mediating Effect of Academic Self-Efficacy </p>

<p>Dependent 
variable </p>

<p>Independent 
variable </p>

<p>Unstandardized 
coefficients </p>

<p>Standardized 
coefficients 
t 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(Adj. R 
2 ) 
∆ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>F 
B 
SE </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>Academic 
self-efficacy </p>

<p>Socially-prescribed 
perfectionism </p>

<p>-0.510 
0.068 
-0.453 
-7.487*** 
0.205 
(0.202) </p>

<p>56.057*** </p>

<p>Academic 
burnout </p>

<p>Socially-prescribed 
perfectionism </p>

<p>0.602 
0.086 
0.428 
6.968*** 
0.184 
(0.180) </p>

<p>48.551*** </p>

<p>Socially-prescribed 
perfectionism </p>

<p>0.173 
0.073 
0.123 
2.386* 
0.544 
(0.540) </p>

<p>0.360 128.354*** </p>

<p>Academic 
self-efficacy </p>

<p>-0.841 
0.064 
-0.674 
-13.044*** </p>

<p>*p&lt;0.05, ***p&lt;0.001. </p>

<p>3. Mediating effect of academic self-efficacy </p>

<p>on the relationship between socially-</p>

<p>prescribed perfectionism and academic </p>

<p>burnout </p>

<p>Hierarchical multiple analysis results are shown in </p>

<p>Table 4. The socially-prescribed perfectionism could </p>

<p>significantly (β=0.428, p&lt;0.001) explain academic </p>

<p>burnout. When both socially-prescribed perfectionism </p>

<p>and academic self-efficacy were used as input simul-</p>

<p>taneously, the β-value of socially-prescribed perfec-</p>

<p>tionism on academic burnout was significantly (p&lt;0.05) </p>

<p>decreased from 0.428 to 0.123. These results revealed </p>

<p>that academic self-efficacy could partially mediate the </p>

<p>relationship between socially-prescribed perfectionism </p>

<p>and academic burnout. Sobel test revealed that academic </p>

<p>self-efficacy could significantly (Z=6.810, p&lt;0.001) </p>

<p>mediate the relationship between socially-prescribed </p>

<p>perfectionism and academic burnout. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>A typical representative example of a person who is </p>

<p>expected to be perfect not only by himself or herself, but </p>

<p>also by parents, teachers, and the community is medical </p>

<p>student. These individuals socially experience strong </p>

<p>achievement motivation for perfectionism. They receive </p>

<p>frequent praises and messages from the society that </p>

<p>perfectionism is good [13]. According to previous </p>

<p>studies, such perfectionism tendencies can predict posi-</p>

<p>tive or negative adaptation to school life according to </p>

<p>whether the tendency is expressed positively or nega-</p>

<p>tively. It has been found that perfectionism is closely </p>

<p>related to academic self-efficacy which can determine </p>

<p>self-ability and self-confidence [3,14]. Therefore, it is </p>

<p>of great interest to clarify the relationships among </p>

<p>perfectionism tendency, academic burnout, and academic </p>

<p>self-efficacy to find variables that can reduce academic </p>

<p>burnout. </p>

<p>In the present study, we investigated the relationship </p>

<p>between socially-prescribed perfectionism and academic </p>

<p>burnout in medical students. We also determined </p>

<p>whether academic self-efficacy might mediate the </p>

<p>relationship between socially-prescribed perfectionism </p>

<p>and academic burnout. Our results are summarized in the </p>

<p>following. </p>

<p>First, there was a significant correlation (r=0.428) </p>

<p>between academic burnout and socially-prescribed per-</p>

<p>fectionism. There was also a significant negative </p>

<p>Ji Hye Yu, et al : The relationship among self-efficacy, perfectionism and academic burnout </p>



<p>correlation (r=-0.727) between academic burnout and </p>

<p>academic self-efficacy, demonstrating a close relation-</p>

<p>ship between socially-prescribed perfectionism and </p>

<p>academic burnout or academic self-efficacy in medical </p>

<p>students. That is, when socially-prescribed perfec-</p>

<p>tionism inclination is high but academic self-efficacy is </p>

<p>low, there is an increased risk of academic burnout. Our </p>

<p>results are in agreement with a previous report [1] about </p>

<p>a negative correlation (r=-0.59) between academic burn-</p>

<p>out and academic self-efficacy. The observation that </p>

<p>academic self-efficacy is more related to academic </p>

<p>burnout than socially-prescribed perfectionism suggests </p>

<p>that academic self-efficacy is an effective predictor for </p>

<p>academic performance. Therefore, it is of critical impor-</p>

<p>tance to have education or counseling programs to </p>

<p>enhance academic self-efficacy in medical students who </p>

<p>experience academic burnout. </p>

<p>Second, multiple regression analysis was performed to </p>

<p>determine the effect of socially-prescribed perfec-</p>

<p>tionism and academic self-efficacy on academic burnout. </p>

<p>Our results showed that academic burnout could be </p>

<p>predicted by both socially-prescribed perfectionism (β= </p>

<p>0.123, p&lt;0.05) and academic self-efficacy (β=-0.674, </p>

<p>p&lt;0.001), with academic self-efficacy having greater </p>

<p>significance, suggesting that academic self-efficacy </p>

<p>might play a greater role than socially-prescribed per-</p>

<p>fectionism in academic burnout of medical students. </p>

<p>Third, hierarchical multiple analysis was conducted in </p>

<p>this study to determine whether academic self-efficacy </p>

<p>could mediate the relationship between socially-</p>

<p>prescribed perfectionism and academic burnout. The </p>

<p>results showed that academic self-efficacy could indeed </p>

<p>mediate the relationship between socially-prescribed </p>

<p>perfectionism and academic burnout. Academic self-</p>

<p>efficacy psychologically lowered socially-prescribed </p>

<p>perfectionism and academic self-efficacy, consequently </p>

<p>leading to academic burnout. In other words, medical </p>

<p>students with higher maladaptive academic perfec-</p>

<p>tionism are at increased risk of having academic burnout. </p>

<p>Academic self-efficacy acting as a psychological re-</p>

<p>source may decrease the chances of academic burnout. </p>

<p>Other prior reports have also shown that socially-</p>

<p>prescribed perfectionism can negatively affect academic </p>

<p>self-efficacy [15,16]. These studies have also suggested </p>

<p>that medical students' socially-prescribed perfectionism </p>

<p>inclinations itself not only can elicit academic burnout, </p>

<p>but also can have negatively affect academic self-</p>

<p>efficacy, thus promoting academic burnout. Hence, </p>

<p>methods that can help medical students overcome </p>

<p>socially-prescribed perfectionism while enhancing </p>

<p>academic self-efficacy are needed. </p>

<p>In this study, we focused on variables such as socially-</p>

<p>prescribed perfectionism and academic self-efficacy that </p>

<p>could influence medical students. We also attempted to </p>

<p>describe the significance of academic self-efficacy in </p>

<p>mediating the relationship between socially-prescribed </p>

<p>perfectionism and academic burnout in order to find </p>

<p>solutions to prevent academic burnout. We confirmed </p>

<p>that academic self-efficacy was a significant variable </p>

<p>that could influence individual psychological variables </p>

<p>associated with study abilities. </p>

<p>One of the limitations of this study is that only a </p>

<p>specific group of students in a single educational </p>

<p>institution was included in the present study. Another </p>

<p>limitation is that a higher number of variables that may </p>

<p>affect academic burnout should have been included and </p>

<p>analyzed in this study to improve the statistical power. </p>

<p>An ideal study design should encompass a diverse range </p>

<p>of individual internal and external variables that might </p>

<p>affect academic burnout so that structural relationships </p>

<p>can be demonstrated. Nonetheless, this study provides </p>

<p>basic information for medical students to avoid academic </p>

<p>burnout. </p>

<p>Ji Hye Yu, et al : The relationship among self-efficacy, perfectionism and academic burnout </p>



<p>Acknowledgements: None. </p>

<p>Funding: None. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest: None. </p>



</text></tei>