<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4004741" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Motivated by a need to provide research opportunities 
to a growing number of STEM majors, we have developed 
a metagenomics research module, coupled with next gen-
eration sequencing (NGS), that allows students to address 
novel questions centered on urban microbial community 
diversity. Studies have shown that providing students with 
opportunities to investigate genuine research questions, as 
opposed to "cookbook" exercises, can result in improved 
learning outcomes and changes in students' appreciation of 
science and research (1-8). We have successfully used the 
urban metagenomics module in an introductory microbiol-
ogy lab at a large urban university to engage many more 
students in research projects than was previously possible 
using a traditional apprenticeship model. While we have 
focused on bacterial diversity and community dynamics 
in the urban environment, the module can be adapted for 
studying microbial communities in almost any environment 
and can be modified to target microorganisms other than 
bacteria as well as adapted to include whole genome shot-
gun sequencing and transcriptome analysis. The chance to 
participate in an innovative research project focusing on the 
urban environment resonates with our students because the 
urban environment is where they live, work, and study. We 
believe that using current techniques to investigate research 
questions that are relevant to our students leads to improve-
ments in their attitudes toward science and improves their 
performance in the lab. </p>

<p>PROCEDURE </p>

<p>The metagenomics module is well suited for under-
graduates working in small groups of three to six students. 
The protocol uses commercially available kits to reduce the 
preparation time for the lab and to maximize consistency. 
Working with the instructor, the students choose the site(s) </p>

<p>to be investigated. The outline for the metagenomics module 
is as follows: </p>

<p>1. Identify sites and collect environmental samples 
by swabbing 
2. Isolate and purify genomic DNA 
3. Amplify16S rRNA gene region using universal PCR 
primers 
4. Analyze and quantify 16S rRNA amplicon 
5. Roche/454 or Illumina sequencing of 16S rRNA 
amplicons 
6. DNA sequence analysis </p>

<p>In this article, we cover the novel aspects of the proto-
col. A more detailed description of the protocol is provided 
in the supplemental materials. The detailed protocol, as 
well as a list of materials and reagents, are available at the 
CUNY Undergraduate Research Site (http://www.cuny.edu/ 
research/sr/undergrad-research/for-faculty/AREM.html). </p>

<p>Sample collection </p>

<p>Collecting sufficient sample material from the urban 
environment can be a challenge because surfaces in the 
city often have fewer microorganisms than samples from 
soil, water, or humans, and the urban samples often contain 
contaminants that can inhibit PCR. Samples are collected 
using a swabbing technique. Students are instructed to swab 
an area roughly the size of their palm (~10 x 10 cm) and 
have successfully collected material from streets, sidewalks, 
subway platforms, playground equipment, and other com-
mon urban environments. Students swab three to six sites 
within a square meter and combine the material from the 
swabs into a single sample. Once the sample is collected on 
the swab, we use a modified version of the Mo Bio Power 
Soil kit protocol to extract the DNA from the sample. 
Steps 2 to 5 are routine and described in detail in Ap-
pendix 1: Detailed protocol. </p>

<p>DNA sequence data analysis </p>

<p>The sequence data is run through filtering and analysis 
pipelines, such as <rs id="software-0" type="software">QIIME</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">qiime.org</rs>), in order to define op-
erational taxonomic units and is compared to bacterial 16S </p>

<p>Undergraduate Urban Metagenomics Research Module  † </p>

<p>Theodore R. Muth* and Catherine M. McEntee 
Department of Biology, City University of New York (CUNY) Brooklyn College, Brooklyn, NY 11210 </p>

<p>Journal of Microbiology &amp; Biology Education </p>

<p>MUTH and MCENTEE: URBAN METAGENOMICS </p>



<p>Volume 15, Number 1 </p>

<p>rRNA databases (such as Green Genes, http://greengenes. 
lbl.gov/cgi-bin/nph-index.cgi) to determine the bacterial 
diversity of the sample. Depending on the goals of the 
course and the experience of the instructor, the filtering 
and taxonomic assignments can be done with the students. 
Alternatively, these steps can be performed by the instruc-
tor outside of the class and the taxonomic classification and 
relative abundance data can be used in class. Many of the 
academic and commercial sequencing facilities will perform 
filtering and basic analysis of the raw sequence data. Classes 
that do not have a wet lab component can analyze data 
collected by students in other courses or data collected by 
other investigators. </p>

<p>Safety </p>

<p>The metagenomics module can be run safely in any 
lab that is designed to conduct routine molecular and 
microbiological techniques. At the sample collection 
step, a small fraction of the sample can be plated on 
media that support microbial growth. This allows for an 
excellent demonstration of the power of metagenom-
ics because students see how little bacterial diversity 
they can identify by colony morphology on the plate 
compared to how many species they are able to identify 
using metagenomics. Because there is a risk of culturing 
pathogens collected in the environment, students should 
seal the plates with Parafilm after inoculating them and 
simply observe what they see growing on the sealed plate 
before autoclaving them. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>We have used the metagenomics research module 
in the introductory microbiology lab sections over three 
semesters, reaching almost 400 students. Students have 
collected and analyzed data from a number of previously 
uncharacterized urban sites around New York City and 
we have begun to accumulate data over a number of 
time points that will allow students to determine how 
stable these bacterial communities are. Our preliminary 
outcomes assessment shows that the microbiology lab 
sections using the urban metagenomics module have 
lower rates of Ds, Fs, and withdraws relative to control 
sections (see Table 1). This may be the result of a greater 
engagement of students in the lab, due to the relevance 
and excitement of studying samples they have collected 
from within their community, which may carry over 
to keep students motivated to study and perform well 
throughout the course. In support of this, we have used 
post-course, anonymous, evaluation surveys to show that 
students in the lab sections using the urban metagenomics 
module tend to have more positive responses regarding 
the lab as a whole when compared to the responses from 
students in the traditionally formatted lab. For example, 
students in the sections using the metagenomics module </p>

<p>report a greater confidence in interpreting scientific 
data and a greater appreciation for research (see Fig. 1). 
Importantly, Figure 2 shows that students who partici-
pated in the urban metagenomics lab are more likely to 
remain involved in science, as measured by the number 
of students who continue on into masters, graduate, or 
professional programs in the biological and biomedical 
sciences. In summary, the urban metagenomics research 
module is an easily transferable, affordable unit that can 
be incorporated into a number of undergraduate STEM 
courses and used to improve student outcomes. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIALS </p>

<p>Appendix 1: Detailed protocol </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was funded by an NSF-CCLI type I grant 
awarded to the authors. Preliminary data from this work 
has been presented at the ASMCUE 2012 meeting (see JMBE 
Vol. 13, No. 1 for ASMCUE 2012 abstracts; http://jmbe.asm. 
org/index.php/jmbe/article/view/412). The authors declare 
that there are no conflicts of interest. </p>



<p>TABLE 1. 
Percentage grade distribution of students enrolled in traditional 
microbiology lab sections and in lab sections using the urban 
metagenomics research module. The percentage of students 
earning Ds, Fs, or withdrawing from the course (W) is lower in 
the sections using the urban metagenomics lab. </p>

<p>Grade Distribution (%) </p>

<p>Grade 
Traditional 
Urban Metagenomics </p>

<p>A 
39 
40 
B 
36 
38 
C 
13 
16 </p>

<p>D 
3 
1 
F 
1 
0 </p>

<p>W 
8 
5 </p>

<p>Journal of Microbiology &amp; Biology Education </p>

<p>MUTH and MCENTEE: URBAN METAGENOMICS </p>

<p>Volume 15, Number 1 </p>



<p>5. Shaffer, C. D., et al. 2010 The genomics education 
partnership: successful integration of research into laboratory 
classes at a diverse group of undergraduate institutions. CBE 
Life Sci. Educ. 9:55-69. 
6. Udovic, D., D. Morris, A. Dickman, J. Postlethwait, and 
P. Wetherwax. 2002. Workshop biology: demonstrating 
the effectiveness of active learning in an introductory biology 
course. Bioscience 52:272-281. 
7. Wei, C. A., and T. Woodin. 2011. Undergraduate research 
experiences in biology: alternatives to the apprenticeship 
model. CBE Life Sci. Educ. 10:123-131. 
8. Woodin, T., C. V. Carter, and L. Fletcher. 2010. Vision 
and change in biology undergraduate education, a call for 
action-initial responses. CBE Life Sci. Educ. 9:71-73. </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. (A) Student responses to a survey question regarding 
their appreciation for scientific research. Responses from students 
in lab sections using the urban metagenomics module (the module 
is the key component of the Authentic Research Experience in 
Microbiology; AREM) are shown in blue and those from students 
in traditional lab sections are shown in gray (control). The per-
centage of students agreeing or agreeing strongly is shown on the 
y-axis. In the second and third set of columns the students have 
been grouped by gender, indicated in parentheses. (B) Student 
responses to a survey question regarding their comfort in evalu-
ating and interpreting data. In the case of both survey questions, 
the students using the urban metagenomics module (blue bars) 
responded more positively. The survey was optional, anonymous, 
and hosted by the <rs type="software">Survey Monkey</rs> site. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Percentage of students who responded to the survey who 
were enrolled in a masters or graduate program in the biological 
sciences or enrolled in a professional program in the biomedical or 
health sciences. Responses from students using the urban metage-
nomics lab sections are shown in blue and those from students in 
the traditional lab sections are shown in gray. </p>

</text></tei>