<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4150201" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Packaging system is one of the important factors post-
harvest for maintenance of fresh appearance, delay of 
deterioration process, and enhancement of shelf-life during 
storage of raw meat (Jayasingh et al., 2001; Lagerstedt et al., 
2011). Meat packaging technology has been consistently 
advanced with improvement of consumer's practical sense 
for meat quality. Now, vacuum packaging (VACP), 
modified atmosphere packaging (MAP), and vacuum skin 
packaging (VSP) have been utilized in the meat industry. 
The VACP, the most popular packaging system for 
aging of fresh meat, with little oxygen environment inside 
the pack, has a beneficial effect on prevention of oxidation, 
flavor preservation, and inhibition of microbial growth but </p>

<p>gives rise to unacceptable color due to development of 
deoxymyoglobin and deformation of shape (Borch et al., 
1996; Santos et al., 2005; Troy and Kerry, 2010; Avilés et 
al., 2014). The VSP improves the appearance together with 
color stability and slows the growth rate of microorganisms 
compared to VACP (Barros-Velázquez et al., 2003; Vázquez 
et al., 2004). The MAP has the advantages of better color 
stability and microorganism control owing to filling with 
oxygen (O 2 ) and carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) inside the pack 
(Lopez-Lorenzo et al., 1980; Gill and Harrison, 1989). In 
retail fresh meat, high oxygen-MAP (70% to 80% O 2 /20% 
to 30% CO 2 ; HOMAP) is the most effective in stabilizing 
color but entails the oxidative deterioration (Jakobsen and 
Bertelsen, 2000; Lund et al., 2007b). Recently, the more 
advanced type of HOMAP combined with VSP has been 
industrially developed for the purpose of extending shelf-
life of fresh meat as compared to HOMAP alone. 
The oxidation stability of components, such as fat, 
protein and myoglobin, in the meat, plays a major part in </p>

<p>Open Access </p>

<p>Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. </p>

<p>Vol. 27, No. 9 : 1336-1344 September 2014 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.5713/ajas.2014.14136 </p>

<p>www.ajas.info </p>

<p>pISSN 1011-2367 eISSN 1976-5517 </p>

<p>Evaluation of Various Packaging Systems on the Activity of 
Antioxidant Enzyme, and Oxidation and Color Stabilities in 
Sliced Hanwoo (Korean Cattle) Beef Loin during Chill Storage </p>

<p>Sun Moon Kang, Geunho Kang, Pil-Nam Seong, Beomyoung Park, and Soohyun Cho* 
Animal Products Research and Development Division, National Institute of Animal Science, 
Rural Development Administration, Suwon 441-706, Korea </p>

<p>ABSTRACT: The effects of various packaging systems, vacuum packaging (VACP), medium oxygen-modified atmosphere packaging </p>

<p>(50% O 2 /20% CO 2 /30% N 2 , MOMAP), MOMAP combined with vacuum skin packaging (VSP-MOMAP), high oxygen-MAP (80% 
O 2 /20% CO 2 /0% N 2 , HOMAP), and HOMAP combined with VSP (VSP-HOMAP), on the activity of antioxidant enzyme, and oxidation 
and color stabilities in sliced Hanwoo (Korean cattle) beef loin were investigated at 4°C for 14 d. Higher (p&lt;0.05) superoxide dismutase 
activity and total reducing ability were maintained in VSP-MOMAP beef than in HOMAP beef. Lipid oxidation (2-thiobarbituric acid 
reactive substances, TBARS) was significantly (p&lt;0.05) retarded in MOMAP, VSP-MOMAP, and VSP-HOMAP beef compared with 
HOMAP beef. Production of nonheme iron content was lower (p&lt;0.05) in VSP-MOMAP beef than in HOMAP beef. Red color (a*) was 
kept higher (p&lt;0.05) in VSP-MOMAP beef compared with MOMAP, HOMAP, and VSP-HOMAP beef. However, VACP beef was 
found to have the most positive effects on the antioxidant activity, oxidation and red color stabilities among the various packaged beef. 
These findings suggested that VSP-MOMAP was second to VACP in improving oxidation and color stabilities in sliced beef loin during 
chill storage. (Key Words: Packaging, Antioxidant, Oxidation Stability, Color, Beef Loin, Hanwoo) </p>

<p>Copyright © 2014 by Asian-Australasian Journal of Animal Sciences </p>

<p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author: Soohyun Cho. Tel: +82-31-290-1703, 
Fax: +82-31-290-1697, E-mail: shc0915@korea.kr </p>

<p>Submitted Feb. 24, 2014; Revised Apr. 13, 2014; Accepted Jun. 9, 2014 </p>

<p>Kang et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1336-1344 </p>



<p>preserving the meat quality. During storage of meat, lipid 
oxidation, which is originated by contact with oxygen, 
creates free radicals contributing to the oxidation of 
myoglobin and protein (Xiong, 2000; Faustman et al., 2010). 
This oxidation process negatively affects the quality of meat. 
The accumulation of metmyoglobin on the surface of meat 
causes the consumer's refusal to purchase and economic 
loss of retail (Smith et al., 2000). The oxidation of meat 
protein 
incurs 
the 
development 
of 
carbonyls, 
hydroperoxides, and sulfoxides, deterioration of texture, 
and decline in water-holding capacity (Davies and Dean, 
2003; Morzel et al., 2006). Thus, to keep the quality of the 
raw meat, a decrease in oxidation stability should be 
prevented as much as possible. 
Not only in the tissues of living animals but also in 
muscles post-slaughter, enzymatic and non-enzymatic 
antioxidant systems subsist to defend against attacks of free 
radicals (Chan and Decker, 1994). Several studies have 
reported the inhibitory effect of the enzymatic antioxidant 
system, such as catalase, superoxide dismutase (SOD), and 
glutathione peroxidase (GPx), on the lipid oxidation of meat 
(Mei et al., 1994; Lee et al., 1996). The endogenous 
antioxidant enzymes in the meat are affected by various 
factors, such as feed, pre-slaughter stress, packaging and 
processing, etc. (Mercier et al., 2004; Chen et al., 2010; 
Gheisari and Motamedi, 2010; Kang et al., 2012). 
Particularly, in a previous study on the beef packaged with 
modified atmosphere, Kang et al. (2012) found that 
increasing O 2 concentration accelerated the lipid oxidation 
and browning of color due to a decrease in the activity of 
some antioxidant enzyme. However, there have been few 
researches reported on the comparison of antioxidant 
enzymes, lipid and protein oxidation, and color among 
VACP, O 2 -MAP alone, and O 2 -MAP combined with VSP 
during storage. This research was, therefore, conducted to 
estimate the activities of antioxidant enzymes, and 
oxidation and color stabilities in sliced Hanwoo (Korean 
cattle) beef loin in various packaging systems during chill 
storage. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Reagents and chemicals 
Experimental deionized water (DW) was made using a 
Milli-Q Water Purifier (Millipore SAS, Molsheim, Alsace, 
France). Ethyl alcohol, ethyl acetate, and chloroform were 
purchased from J. T. Baker (Phillipsburg, NJ, USA). 
Thiobarbituric acid (TBA) was obtained from Alfa Aesar 
(Ward Hill, MA, USA). The 2,4-dinitrophenylhydrazine 
(DNPH), ammonium sulfamate, β-nicotinamide adenine 
dinucleotide phosphate reduced (β-NADPH), cacodylic 
acid, 
diethylenetriaminepentaacetic 
acid 
(DTPA), 
ethylenediaminetetraacetate (EDTA), glutathione reductase </p>

<p>from Baker's yeast (GSH-R), guanidine-HCl, L-glutathione 
reduced (GSH), lead acetate, neocuproine, 3-(2-pyridyl)-
5,6-diphenyl-1,2,4-triazine-p,disulfonic acid (ferrozine), 
pipes, potassium ferricyanide, pyrogallol, bovine serum 
albumin (BSA), trichloroacetic acid (TCA), and trizma base 
were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Co. LLC. (St. Louis, 
MO, USA). </p>

<p>Sample preparation and experimental design 
Hanwoo (Korean cattle; steer) beef loins (carcass 
quality grade of 1) at d 2 post-slaughter were purchased 
from a local market and then aged under VACP at 2°C for 7 
d before trimming to conform with the commercial 
distribution condition. The sliced lean meat (about 1 cm 
thickness) were randomly assigned to five different types of 
packaging treatments; i) vacuum packaging (VACP), ii) 
medium oxygen-modified atmosphere packaging (50% 
O 2 /20% CO 2 /30% N 2 ; MOMAP) alone, iii) MOMAP 
combined with vacuum skin packaging (VSP-MOMAP), iv) 
HOMAP (80% O 2 /20% CO 2 /0% N 2 ) alone, or v) HOMAP 
combined with VSP (VSP-HOMAP). The beef of VACP 
treatment was placed into a seven-layered film 
(nylon/tie/linear low density polyethylene (LLDPE)/tie 
/nylon/tie/LLDPE; FoodSaver pouch, Rollpack Co., Ltd., 
Pyeongtaek, Gyeonggi, Korea) and packaged using a VACP 
machine (CD-120, Webomatic Maschinenfabrik GmbH, 
Bochum, North Rhine-Westphalia, Germany). Using a MAP 
machine (MAP-RT1, HyperPac Co., Hwaseong, Korea) 
equipped with a gas mixer (MAP Mix 9001 ME, PBI 
Dansensor A/S, Ringsted, Sjae lland, Denmark), the packs of 
MOMAP and HOMAP treatments were applied to vacuum, 
filled with mixed gases, and then sealed with an oxygen 
barrier film (max. O 2 transmission rate: 0.002 cc/cm 2 ·24 h 
at 4.4°C, relative humidity (RH) 100%, max. moisture 
vapor transmission rate: 0.39 mg/cm 2 ·24 h at 4.4°C, RH 
100%; Lid 1050, Cryovac Sealed Air Corp., Duncan, SC, 
USA) following the placement of beef onto a polystyrene 
barrier foam tray (max. oxygen transmission rate: 0.1 
cc/cm 2 ·24 h at 23°C, RH 0%, max. moisture vapor 
transmission rate: 7.87 mg/cm 2 ·24 h at 38°C, RH 100%; 
SCB00-096, Cryovac Sealed Air Corp., USA). The beef of 
VSP-MOMAP and VSP-HOMAP treatments were placed 
into a tray and covered with a permeable intact film 
(100247492, Cryovac Sealed Air Corp., USA) by a VSP 
machine (VSP-S100, Samhwa Co., Hwaseong, Korea) 
before accomplishment of MAP. Packaged samples were 
then stored in a refrigerator (DS-95P, Dasol Scientific Co., 
Ltd., Hwaseong, Korea) at 4°C for 14 d and measurements 
were made on d 1, 3, 7, 10, and 14. </p>

<p>Determination of gas concentration 
The concentrations (%) of O 2 and CO 2 in MAP were 
confirmed by a portable gas analyzer (OxyBaby M+X </p>

<p>Kang et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1336-1344 </p>

<p>
O 2 /CO 2 , Witt-Gasetechnik GmbH &amp; Co., KG, Witten, North 
Rhine-Westphalia, Germany). The relative percentage of 
nitrogen was calculated as 100-(O 2 [%]+CO 2 [%]). </p>

<p>Antioxidant enzyme activity measurement 
Five grams of beef were homogenized with 20 mL of 
ice-cold 0.05 M phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) using an Ultra-
Turrax (T25 Digital, Ika Werke GmbH &amp; Co., KG, Staufen, 
Baden-Wüttenberg, Germany) at 13,500 rpm for 30 s, 
centrifuged at 2°C/1,000 g (Renerre et al., 1996; Avanti J-E 
Centrifuge, Beckman Coulter, Inc., Palo Alto, CA, USA) 
for 15 min and then filtered with a Whatman filter paper No. 
1. Catalase (hydrogen peroxide: hydrogen peroxide 
oxidoreductase; E.C. 1.11.1.6) activity was analyzed with 
the method developed by Aebi (1983). The decomposition 
rate of H 2 O 2 was measured at 240 nm at 25°C 
(ProteomeLab DU-800, Beckman Coulter, Inc., USA) for 
30 s immediately after mixing 100 μL of beef extracts with 
29 mM H 2 O 2 (in phosphate buffer, pH 7.0). The GPx 
(glutathione: hydrogen peroxide oxidoreductase; E.C. 
1.11.1.9) activity was analyzed with the enzymatic 
procedure reported by Flohé and Günzler (1984). The 
oxidation rate of NADPH was measured at 340 nm at 25°C 
for 180 s following mixing 100 μL of extracts with enzyme 
medium (1 mM EDTA-1 mM NaN 3 -0.5 units/mL GSH-R-1 
mM GSH-0.15 mM β-NADPH-0.15 mM H 2 O 2 in phosphate 
buffer, pH 7.0). The SOD (superoxide: superoxide 
oxidoreductase; E.C. 1.15.1.1) activity was analyzed as 
described by Marklund (1986). The inhibition rate of 
pyrogallol (0.2 mM in tris-cacodylate-DTPA buffer, pH 8.2) 
autooxidation by 50 μL of extracts was measured at 420 nm 
at 25°C for 120 s. The activities of three antioxidant 
enzymes were computed with change in rates of absorbance 
values per min as unit enzyme/g meat. </p>

<p>Measurement of total reducing ability 
Total reducing ability (TRA) was performed as 
described by Lee et al. (1981). Briefly, 2 g of samples were 
homogenized with 10 mL of ice-cold 25 mM pipes buffer 
(pH 5.8) by a Polytron (PT-MR 2100, Kinematica AG, 
Littau, Luzern, Switzerland) at 13,500 rpm for 15 s. Five 
milliliters of homogenates were mixed with 100 μL of 0.04 
M ammonium sulfamate, 200 μL of 0.5 M lead acetate, and 
2.5 mL of 20% (w/v) TCA and then made up to total 
volume of 10 mL with DW following incubation with 2 mL 
of 5 mM potassium ferricyanide in an ice under the dark for 
60 min. Before filtration with a Whatman filter paper No. 
42, final mixtures were centrifuged at 2°C/3,000 g (Avanti 
J-20XP Centrifuge, Beckman Coulter, Inc., USA) for 10 
min and then measured at 420 nm. The TRA was expressed 
as absorbance value of sample against absorbance value of 
1 mM potassium ferricyanide (blank). </p>

<p>2-Thiobarbituric acid reactive substances content 
analysis 
The 2-thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS) 
content was measured with the process previously reported 
by Sinnhuber and Yu (1977). The beef samples (0.5 g) were 
mixed with about 0.1 g of antioxidant mixture (54% [w/w] 
propylene glycol-40% [w/w] Tween 20-3% [w/w] butylated 
hydroxytoluene-3% [w/w] butylated hydroxyanisole, 3 mL 
of 1% (w/v) TBA-0.3% (w/v) NaOH, and 17 mL of 2.5% 
(w/v) TCA-36 mM HCl, boiled at 100°C for 30 min and 
ice-cooled for 10 min. Then, 5 mL of upper solutions were 
transferred to a conical tube and 3 mL of chloroform was 
added before centrifugation at 4°C/3,000 g (Avanti J-E 
Centrifuge, Beckman Coulter, Inc., USA) for 30 min. 
Absorbance values of supernatants were measured at 532 
nm and converted into mg malonaldehyde (MA)/kg meat. </p>

<p>Carbonyl content analysis 
Carbonyl content was analyzed according to the 
procedure described by Mercier et al. (1998). Two grams of 
samples were mixed with 20 mL of ice-cold 0.15 M KCl 
and filtered with a Whatman filter paper No. 1. One 
hundred microliters of extracts were incubated either with 
0.5 mL of 0.2% (w/v) DNPH (in 2 N HCl; for carbonyl 
content) or 2 N HCl (for protein content) for 60 min under 
the dark, combined with 0.6 mL of 20% (w/v) TCA and 
placed on ice for 10 min. Following centrifugation at 
2°C/3,000 g (Microfuge 22R Centrifuge, Beckman Coulter 
GmbH, Krefeld, North Rhine-Westphalia, Germany) for 5 
min, the sediments were rinsed with ethyl acetate-ethyl 
alcohol (1:1) at three times, dried in a hood and then 
dissolved in 1 mL of guanidine-HCl (6 M in 20 mM 
potassium phosphate buffer, pH 6.5). Absorbance values of 
mixtures measuring at 370 (DNPH-incubated) and 280 
(HCl-incubated) nm were converted into nmol carbonyl/mg 
protein with standard curve of BSA and millimolar 
extinction coefficient (22.0 mM -1 cm -1 ; Reznick and Packer, 
1994) of protein hydrazones. </p>

<p>Nonheme iron content measurement 
Nonheme iron content was quantified based on the 
ferrozine method developed by Carter (1971). One and half 
grams of samples were homogenized with 4.5 mL of ice-
cold 0.1 M citrate-phosphate buffer (pH 5.5) and 
centrifuged at 2°C/1,800 g for 10 min. One milliliter of 
supernatants was mixed with 0.5 mL of 2% (w/v) ascorbic 
acid, incubated at 20°C to 22°C under the dark for 10 min, 
and then combined with 0.5 mL of ice-cold 11.3% (w/v) 
TCA before centrifugation at 2°C/10,000 g for 10 min. 
Final supernatants were reacted with 10% (w/v) ammonium 
acetate and ferroin color reagent for 10 min and 
spectrophotometrically measured at 562 nm. The results 
were calculated with absorbance values of samples against </p>

<p>Kang et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1336-1344 </p>



<p>blank and molar extinction coefficient (28,000 M -1 cm -1 ) of 
iron-ferrozine complex as μg Fe/g meat. </p>

<p>Determination of instrumental meat color 
The determination of Commission Internationale de 
l'Eclairage (CIE) a* value was performed on the surface of 
samples by a chroma meter (CR-400, Konica Minolta 
Sensing, Inc., Tokyo, Honshu, Japan) calibrated with a 
white plate (illuminant C; L* = 97.70, a* = -0.05, and b* = 
1.94). The beef stored under VACP was determined after 
blooming for 30 min while the beef stored under other 
packaging systems was determined immediately after 
removal of film. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
All data collected for the activities of catalase, GPx, and 
SOD, TRA, the contents of TBARS, carbonyl, and 
nonheme iron, and CIE a* value were analyzed by two-way 
analysis of variance using the general linear model 
procedure of <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2011</rs>) program. As fixed factors, the 
effects of packaging system (VACP, MOMAP, VSP-
MOMAP, HOMAP, and VSP-HOMAP), storage time (d 1, 
7, and 14 or d 1, 3, 7, 10, and 14), and their interaction 
(packaging system×storage time) on all variables were 
evaluated in our study. Duncan's multiple range test was 
carried out to compare significant (p&lt;0.05) differences 
among mean values of variables in packaging systems 
within each storage time or in storage times within each 
packaging system, when significances of two main factors 
were presented. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Antioxidant enzyme activity 
Packaging system (p&lt;0.001), storage time (p&lt;0.001), 
and their interaction (p&lt;0.05) had significant effects on the 
catalase activity in the sliced Hanwoo beef loin (Table 1). </p>

<p>During 14 d of storage, a decrease (p&lt;0.05) in catalase 
activity was observed in the sliced beef stored under VACP, 
MOMAP, and VSP-MOMAP (Figure 1). The sliced beef 
stored under VACP had higher (p&lt;0.05) catalase activity </p>

<p>Table 1. Effects of packaging system, storage time, and their 
interaction on the variables </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Significance 
Packaging 
system 
Storage time 
Interaction </p>

<p>Catalase 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
0.041 
GPx 
0.044 
&lt;0.001 
NS 
SOD 
0.001 
&lt;0.001 
NS 
TRA 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
TBARS 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
Carbonyl 
0.004 
&lt;0.001 
0.025 
CIE a* 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
Nonheme iron 
0.008 
&lt;0.001 
0.023 </p>

<p>GPx, glutathione peroxidase; NS, not significant; SOD, superoxide 
dismutase; TRA, total reducing ability; TBARS, 2-thiobarbituric acid 
reactive substances; CIE, Commission Internationale de l'Eclairage. </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>1 
7 
14 </p>

<p>Catalase </p>

<p>(Unit </p>

<p>g 
-1 meat) </p>

<p>Storage time (d) </p>

<p>VACP 
MOMAP 
VSP-MOMAP 
HOMAP 
VSP-HOMAP </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>1 
7 
14 </p>

<p>GPx </p>

<p>(Unit </p>

<p>g 
-1 meat) </p>

<p>Storage time (d) </p>

<p>VACP 
MOMAP 
VSP-MOMAP 
HOMAP 
VSP-HOMAP </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>1 
7 
14 </p>

<p>SOD </p>

<p>(Unit </p>

<p>g 
-1 meat) </p>

<p>Storage time (d) </p>

<p>VACP 
MOMAP 
VSP-MOMAP 
HOMAP 
VSP-HOMAP </p>

<p>Figure 1. Antioxidant enzyme activity in sliced Hanwoo (Korean 
cattle) beef loin in various packaging systems for 14 d at 4°C. 
Data are presented as means±SD. GPx, glutathione peroxidase; 
SOD, superoxide dismutase; VACP, vacuum packaging; MOMAP, 
medium oxygen-modified atmosphere packaging (50% O 2 /20% 
CO 2 /30% N 2 ) alone; VSP-MOMAP, MOMAP combined with 
vacuum skin packaging; HOMAP, high oxygen-MAP (80% 
O 2 /20% CO 2 /0% N 2 ) alone; VSP-HOMAP, HOMAP combined 
with VSP; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Kang et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1336-1344 </p>

<p>
compared with the beef stored under MOMAP, VSP-
MOMAP, HOMAP, and VSP-MAP for 14 d of storage. 
However, there were not significant differences for catalase 
activity by both O 2 concentration in MAP and combination 
with VSP. Whereas, the activities of GPx and SOD in the 
stored-sliced beef were influenced by both packaging 
system (p&lt;0.05 and p = 0.001) and storage time (p&lt;0.001), 
there were no significant (p&gt;0.05) effects due to their 
interaction (Table 1). The activity of GPx decreased 
(p&lt;0.05) in the sliced beef stored under MOMAP, VSP-
MOMAP, and HOMAP during storage (Figure 1). At d 14, 
the sliced beef stored under VACP had higher (p&lt;0.05) GPx 
activity than the beef stored under HOMAP. A decrease 
(p&lt;0.05) in SOD activity was indicated in the sliced beef 
stored under all packaging systems (Figure 1). Compared 
with the other packaging systems, the sliced beef stored 
under VACP had higher (p&lt;0.05) SOD activity at d 14. At 
the same storage time, the sliced beef stored under both 
MOMAP and VSP-MOMAP had higher (p&lt;0.05) SOD 
activity compared with the beef stored under both HOMAP 
and VSP-HOMAP. But combination with VSP did not 
influence GPx and SOD activities in the sliced beef at d 14 
of storage. These results imply that higher O 2 atmosphere in 
a packaging system decreased the activities of antioxidant 
enzymes in the stored-sliced beef. Previously, Kang et al. 
(2012) reported a similar finding which the activity of some 
antioxidant enzyme in the chopped beef was decreased by 
an increase in O 2 concentration in MAP for 8 d. This 
phenomenon may be partially due to decomposed or 
denatured antioxidant enzymes by oxidation promoted by </p>

<p>exposure to higher O 2 atmosphere. </p>

<p>Total reducing ability 
There were significant effects of packaging system 
(p&lt;0.001), storage time (p&lt;0.001), and their interaction 
(p&lt;0.001) on the TRA in the sliced beef loin (Table 1). A 
decrease (p&lt;0.05) in TRA was found in the sliced beef 
stored under all packaging systems during storage (Figure 
2). The sliced beef stored under VACP had higher (p&lt;0.05) 
TRA than the beef stored under the other packaging systems 
for 14 d of storage. Combination with O 2 -MAP and VSP 
gave a tendency to maintain higher TRA in the stored-sliced 
beef than O 2 -MAP alone. However, the sliced beef stored 
under VSP-MOMAP had higher (p&lt;0.05) TRA than the 
beef stored under HOMAP from 7 d and indicated higher 
(p&lt;0.05) TRA than the beef stored under VSP-HOMAP at d 
14. Liu et al. (2014) reported similar results where the beef 
steak stored under VACP or carbon monoxide-MAP had 
higher TRA compared with the steak stored under HOMAP 
for 14 d. The decreased TRA in the higher O 2 packaging 
system may be due to consumption of reducing components 
for oxymyoglobin stabilization (Seyfert et al., 2007) or 
destruction of endogenous antioxidants, such as vitamins, 
thiols, polyamines, and peptides, by oxidation process 
(Decker et al., 2000; Clausen et al., 2009). </p>

<p>2-Thiobarbituric acid reactive substances content 
In the sliced beef loin, packaging system (p&lt;0.001), 
storage time (p&lt;0.001), and their interaction (p&lt;0.001) had 
significant effects on TBARS content (Table 1). During </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>1 
7 
14 </p>

<p>TRA 
(ΔA 420 </p>

<p>nm) </p>

<p>Storage time (d) </p>

<p>VACP 
MOMAP 
VSP-MOMAP 
HOMAP 
VSP-HOMAP </p>

<p>Figure 2. Total reducing ability (TRA) in sliced Hanwoo (Korean 
cattle) beef loin in packaging systems for 14 d at 4°C. Data are 
presented as means±SD. VACP, vacuum packaging; MOMAP, 
medium oxygen-modified atmosphere packaging (50% O 2 /20% 
CO 2 /30% N 2 ) alone; VSP-MOMAP, MOMAP combined with 
vacuum skin packaging; HOMAP, high oxygen-MAP (80% 
O 2 /20% CO 2 /0% N 2 ) alone; VSP-HOMAP: HOMAP combined 
with VSP; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 
3 
7 
10 
14 </p>

<p>TBARS </p>

<p>(mg </p>

<p>MA </p>

<p>kg 
-1 meat) </p>

<p>Storage time (d) </p>

<p>VACP 
MOMAP 
VSP-MOMAP 
HOMAP 
VSP-HOMAP </p>

<p>Figure 3. TBARS content in sliced Hanwoo (Korean cattle) beef 
loin in packaging systems for 14 d at 4°C. Data are presented as 
means±SD. TBARS, 2-thiobarbituric acid reactive substances; 
VACP, vacuum packaging; MOMAP, medium oxygen-modified 
atmosphere packaging (50% O 2 /20% CO 2 /30% N 2 ) alone; VSP-
MOMAP, MOMAP combined with vacuum skin packaging; 
HOMAP, high oxygen-MAP (80% O 2 /20% CO 2 /0% N 2 ) alone; 
VSP-HOMAP, HOMAP combined with VSP; SD, standard 
deviation. </p>

<p>Kang et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1336-1344 </p>



<p>storage, a sharp increase (p&lt;0.05) in TBARS content was 
observed in the sliced beef stored under all packaging 
systems (Figure 3). The sliced beef stored under VACP 
maintained lower (p&lt;0.05) TBARS content for 14 d of 
storage compared with the beef stored under the other 
packaging systems. From 7 d, the sliced beef stored under 
MOMAP, VSP-MOMAP, and VSP-HOMAP had lower 
(p&lt;0.05) TBARS content than the beef stored under 
HOMAP. This result is in agreement with a report of 
O'Grady et al. (2000) who found that a higher O 2 packaging 
system increased the TBARS content in the minced beef for 
10 d. In addition, Franco et al. (2012) also reported that the 
beef steak stored under VACP had lower TBARS content 
for 10 d compared with the steak stored under HOMAP. In 
the present study, packaging together with VSP delayed the 
development of TBARS in the sliced beef stored under O 2 
atmosphere packaging. This could be attributed to the fact 
that VSP blocked the direct exposure of beef to O 2 
atmosphere. </p>

<p>Carbonyl content 
Packaging system (p&lt;0.01), storage time (p&lt;0.001), and 
their interaction (p&lt;0.05) had significant effects on the 
carbonyl content, measured as an index of protein oxidation, 
in the sliced beef loin (Table 1). Carbonyl content increased 
(p&lt;0.05) in the sliced beef stored under all packaging 
systems during storage (Figure 4). In our results, the sliced 
beef stored under VACP, MOMAP, and VSP-MOMAP 
showed a tendency to have lower carbonyl content 
compared with the beef stored under HOMAP for 14 d. 
However, at only d 7 of storage, there were significant </p>

<p>(p&lt;0.05) differences in carbonyl content among the storage 
systems. The generation of protein carbonyls in the meat 
products is initiated and accelerated by lipid oxidation 
(Butterfield and Stadtman, 1997; Xiong, 2000). To explain 
in more detail, following the creation of radicals from 
protein or amino acids (arginine, cysteine, histidine, lysine, 
methionine, proline, serine, tryptophan, and valine) by 
attack of hydroxyl radicals (·OH) produced during the 
oxidation process of unsaturated fatty acids, a peroxy 
radical product is created by reaction with former radicals 
and oxygen and then finally develops carbonyls through 
further oxidative processes with reactive oxygen species or 
metal ions. Thus, a rapid increase in lipid oxidation by 
higher O 2 packaging may promote the generation of 
carbonyls and this increase in carbonyl content with lipid 
oxidation appeared at d 7 of storage in our study. This is 
supported by a previous study of Lund et al. (2007a) who 
reported that beef patties stored under HOMAP had higher 
carbonyl and TBARS contents at 6 d compared with the 
patties stored under 100% N 2 -MAP. Furthermore, our result 
at d 14 of storage is similar with another finding of Lund et 
al. (2007b) who reported that the carbonyl content was not 
different between sliced meat stored under either HOMAP 
and VSP at d 14. They explained that this phenomenon is 
because of the advanced reaction of carbonyls. According to 
Xiong and Decker (1995), carbonyls cause the cross-linking 
of proteins, resulting in aggregation, polymerization, and 
insolubilization, via formation of Schiff base with free 
amino acids. Our result may be due to their proven 
mechanism and is also supported by a study of Lund et al. 
(2007b) who observed higher protein cross-linkage in 
HOMAP compared with VSP. </p>

<p>Instrumental meat color 
Red color, determined with CIE a* value, in the sliced 
beef loin was influenced by packaging system (p&lt;0.001), 
storage time (p&lt;0.001), and their interaction (p&lt;0.001) 
(Table 1). During storage, the a* value rapidly decreased 
(p&lt;0.05) in the sliced beef stored under Ox-MAP, but little 
changed in the beef stored under VACP (Figure 5). 
Compared with the sliced beef stored under the other 
packaging systems, the beef stored under VACP had lower 
(p&lt;0.05) a* value up to 3 d of storage and further storage to 
14 d resulted in higher (p&lt;0.05) a* value. From 7 d of 
storage, the sliced beef stored under VSP-MOMAP 
presented a higher a* value than the beef stored under both 
HOMAP, and VSP-HOMAP. Moreover, it had higher 
(p&lt;0.05) a* value than the beef stored under MOMAP 
from10 d of storage. The sliced beef stored under VSP-
HOMAP indicated a tendency to have higher a* value than 
the beef stored under HOMAP during storage. Lindahl 
(2011) also observed the deterioration of red color in the 
beef steak stored under HOMAP. In a previous study by Li </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>1 
7 
14 </p>

<p>Carbonyl </p>

<p>(nmol </p>

<p>mg 
-1 protein) </p>

<p>Storage time (d) </p>

<p>VACP 
MOMAP 
VSP-MOMAP 
HOMAP 
VSP-HOMAP </p>

<p>Figure 4. Carbonyl content in sliced Hanwoo (Korean cattle) beef 
loin in packaging systems for 14 d at 4°C. Data are presented as 
means±SD. VACP, vacuum packaging; MOMAP, medium 
oxygen-modified atmosphere packaging (50% O 2 /20% CO 2 /30% 
N 2 ) alone; VSP-MOMAP, MOMAP combined with vacuum skin 
packaging; HOMAP, high oxygen-MAP (80% O 2 /20% CO 2 /0% 
N 2 ) alone; VSP-HOMAP, HOMAP combined with VSP; SD, 
standard deviation. </p>

<p>Kang et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1336-1344 </p>

<p>
et al. (2012), a similar finding of maintenance of red color 
in the sliced beef stored under VSP has been reported. In the 
stored fresh meat, the decrease of red color is caused by 
oxidation of oxymyoglobin to metmyoglobin and is 
elevated by lipid oxidation (Faustman et al., 2010). In the 
present study, higher O 2 packaging accelerated the 
deterioration of red color in the sliced beef but VSP retarded 
the decrease of red color by O 2 atmosphere. Thus, this result 
may be related with different developments of TBARS by 
packaging systems. </p>

<p>Nonheme iron content 
Significant effects of packaging system (p&lt;0.01), 
storage time (p&lt;0.001), and their interaction (p&lt;0.05) on the 
nonheme iron content were found in the sliced beef loin 
(Table 1). Nonheme iron content increased (p&lt;0.05) in the 
sliced beef stored under all packaging systems at d 14 of 
storage (Figure 6). At the same storage time, the sliced beef 
stored under VACP had lower (p&lt;0.05) nonheme iron 
content compared with the beef stored under the other 
packaging systems. Moreover, the beef stored under VSP-
MOMAP had lower (p&lt;0.05) nonheme iron content than the 
beef stored under HOMAP. Nonheme iron, i.e. free ion, is 
created by reaction of metmyoglobin with lipid 
hydroperoxides or H 2 O 2 and has a direct relationship with 
lipid oxidation because of initiation and propagation by 
production of free radicals through Penton's reaction (Harel 
and Kanner, 1985; Reeder and Wilson, 1998; Min and Ahn, 
2005; Muhlisin et al., 2013). Thus, based on our results with </p>

<p>this mechanism, the nonheme iron content in the stored-
sliced beef may be highly correlated with activities of 
antioxidant enzymes, TRA, meat redness and degree of 
lipid oxidation as affected by packaging systems. 
In conclusion, we confirmed the activity of antioxidant 
enzyme, and lipid and protein oxidation, and color 
stabilities in sliced Hanwoo beef loin in various packaging 
systems during chill storage. The VACP had the most 
positive effects on the stored-sliced beef loin among the 
packaging systems. However, VSP-MOMAP maintained 
higher oxidation and red color stabilities by supporting 
higher activity of some endogenous antioxidant enzyme and 
higher reducing ability compared with MOMAP, HOMAP, 
and VSP-HOMAP. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by 2014 year Postdoctoral 
Fellowship Program (Project No. PJ010170012014) of 
National Institute of Animal Science, Rural Development 
Administration, Republic of Korea. </p>

<p>REFERENCES </p>

<p>Aebi, H. E. 1983. Catalase. In: Methods of Enzymatic Analysis. 
(Eds. H. U. Bergmeyer, J. Bergmeyer, and M. Graβl). Verlag 
Chemie GmbH, Weinheim, Germany. pp. 273-286. 
Avilés, C., M. Juárez, I. L. Larsen, A. Rodas-González, and J. L. 
Aalhus. 2014. Effect of multiple vacuum packs on colour 
development and stability in beef steaks. Meat Sci. 96:124. 
Barros-Velázquez, J., L. Carreira, C. Franco, B. I. Vázquez, C. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>1 
3 
7 
10 
14 </p>

<p>CIE </p>

<p>a* </p>

<p>Storage time (d) </p>

<p>VACP 
MOMAP 
VSP-MOMAP 
HOMAP 
VSP-HOMAP </p>

<p>Figure 5. CIE a* value in sliced Hanwoo (Korean cattle) beef loin 
in packaging systems for 14 d at 4°C. Data are presented as 
means±SD. CIE, Commission Internationale de l'Eclairage; 
VACP, vacuum packaging; MOMAP, medium oxygen-modified 
atmosphere packaging (50% O 2 /20% CO 2 /30% N 2 ) alone; VSP-
MOMAP, MOMAP combined with vacuum skin packaging; 
HOMAP, high oxygen-MAP (80% O 2 /20% CO 2 /0% N 2 ) alone; 
VSP-HOMAP, HOMAP combined with VSP; SD, standard 
deviation. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1 
7 
14 </p>

<p>Nonheme </p>

<p>iron 
(μg g 
-1 meat) </p>

<p>Storage time (d) </p>

<p>VACP 
MOMAP 
VSP-MOMAP 
HOMAP 
VSP-HOMAP </p>

<p>Figure 6. Nonheme iron content in sliced Hanwoo (Korean cattle) 
beef loin in packaging systems for 14 d at 4°C. Data are presented 
as means±SD. VACP, vacuum packaging; MOMAP, medium 
oxygen-modified atmosphere packaging (50% O 2 /20% CO 2 /30% 
N 2 ) alone; VSP-MOMAP, MOMAP combined with vacuum skin 
packaging; HOMAP, high oxygen-MAP (80% O 2 /20% CO 2 /0% 
N 2 ) alone; VSP-HOMAP, HOMAP combined with VSP; SD, 
standard deviation. </p>

<p>Kang et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1336-1344 </p>





<p>Kang et al. (2014) Asian Australas. J. Anim. Sci. 27:1336-1344 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>