<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4499650" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Fura-2 analogs are ratiometric fluoroprobes that are widely used for the quantitative measurement 
of [Ca 
2+ ]. However, the dye usage is intrinsically limited, as the dyes require ultraviolet (UV) excitation, 
which can also generate great interference, mainly from nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) 
autofluorescence. Specifically, this limitation causes serious problems for the quantitative measurement 
of mitochondrial [Ca 
2+ ], as no available ratiometric dyes are excited in the visible range. Thus, NADH 
interference cannot be avoided during quantitative measurement of [Ca 
2+ ] because the majority of NADH 
is located in the mitochondria. The emission intensity ratio of two different excitation wavelengths 
must be constant when the fluorescent dye concentration is the same. In accordance with this principle, 
we developed a novel online method that corrected NADH and Fura-2-FF interference. We simultaneously 
measured multiple parameters, including NADH, [Ca 
2+ ], and pH/mitochondrial membrane potential; 
Fura-2-FF for mitochondrial [Ca 
2+ ] and TMRE for Ψ m or carboxy-SNARF-1 for pH were used. W ith 
this novel method, we found that the resting mitochondrial [Ca 
2+ ] concentration was 1.03 μ M. This 
1 μ M cytosolic Ca 
2+ could theoretically increase to more than 100 mM in mitochondria. However, the 
mitochondrial [Ca 
2+ ] increase was limited to ∼30 μM in the presence of 1 μM cytosolic Ca 
2+ . Our method 
solved the problem of NADH signal contamination during the use of Fura-2 analogs, and therefore the 
method may be useful when NADH interference is expected. </p>

<p>Ca 
2+ is an essential element involved in initiating and 
controlling the excitation-contraction coupling process in car-
diac myocytes. The predominant Ca 
2+ source is trans-sarco-
lemmal Ca 
2+ influx and SR Ca 
2+ release [1-3]. For many years, 
mitochondria were simply regarded as an ATP-generating 
factory. However, several recent reports showed that mito-
chondria participate in many other important processes, such 
as apoptosis, ischemic-reperfusion injury, aging, and other dis-
eases [4-8]. All of those phenomena are related to Ca 
2+ [4-8]. 
Several mechanisms of mitochondrial Ca 
2+ regulation in car-
diac myocytes were reported, including involvement of the 
mCU [4,6,7,9], RaM [10,11], the RyR [12,13], the mNCX 
[14-17], and the CPX [18,19]. To date, their dynamics and </p>

<p>quantitative roles in cardiac myocyte mitochondrial Ca 
2+ reg-
ulation were unclear. Further, their exact working mecha-
nism, molecular identity, and regulatory factors were un-
known. The role of mitochondria in cytosolic Ca 
2+ regulation 
in cardiac myocytes was controversial as well [4,6,7,9,20]. 
In order to study these issues, quantitative and real-time mea-
surements of [Ca </p>

<p>2+   ]m were required. 
The [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m range was reportedly 0.08 to 20 μM [21-24]. 
The most frequently used fluoroprobe to determine this range 
was rhod-2. Rhod-2-AM has a positive charge, and therefore 
it may preferentially load into mitochondria because of the 
large negative potential of the mitochondrial matrix. However, 
rhod-2 has limitations regarding quantitative mitochondrial 
Ca 
2+ measurement because it is not a ratiometric dye. In 
addition, rhod-2 can measure only up to several μM of Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>



<p>JH Lee, et al </p>

<p>Fig. 1. A microfluorometry system for multiparameric measurement. 
The diagram shows the instrumentation used to measure NADH 
(emission, 450 nm; excitation, 361 nm), Fura-2-FF (emission, 500 nm; 
excitation, 353 and 400 nm), and TMRE (emission, 590 nm; excitation, 
530 nm) or carboxy-SNARF-1 (emission, 590 and 640nm; excitation, 
539 nm). The light from a Xenon arc lamp excited the fluoroprobes 
in a myocyte, and then the emission passed through a dichroic mirror 
and band-pass filters to measure the intensity using photon-counting 
devices. Near infrared from a microscope was used as a light source 
to visualize the myocytes during experiments using a CCD camera 
and monitor. </p>

<p>because its dissociation constant (Kd) ranged from 0.57 to 
0.80 μM [12,25,26]. 
Fura-2 analogs are widely used for quantitative measure-
ments of [Ca </p>

<p>2+   ]. The Kd value of Fura-2-FF was reportedly 
18∼35 μM in calibrating buffers [27-31] and 6∼13 μM 
in cells [27,32]. However, this dye has potential usage prob-
lems due to NADH contamination and dye loading into mi-
tochondria. Specifically, NADH contamination is a serious 
problem because most NADH is located in the mitochondria 
and because [NADH] change is related to mitochondrial mem-
brane potential (Ψm), in turn, [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m change [33-36]. These 
problems have been ignored and no methods exist to avoid 
or overcome them. 
In this report, we developed a novel online NADH correction 
method to measure [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m quantitatively, as well as a meth-
od to simultaneously measure multiple parameters, includ-
ing NADH, [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m, and pH/Ψm. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Cell preparation </p>

<p>Sprague-Dawley (SD) rats (8∼10 weeks old) were anes-
thetized with a mixture of ketamine hydrochloride (90 mg/kg) 
and Rompun 
Ⓡ (10 mg/kg). We injected the anesthetics in-</p>

<p>traperitoneally. The rat chest cavity was opened, and the 
heart was excised and mounted on a Langendorff-type ap-
paratus. The heart was sufficiently perfused with Tyrode's 
solution (mmol/L: NaCl, 133.5; KCl, 5.4; HEPES, 5; taurine, 
20; MgCl2, 3; CaCl2, 0.75; and glucose, 5.5; pH adjusted to 
7.4 with NaOH) to remove all residual blood in the heart. 
Subsequently, the heart was perfused with Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-free Tyrode's 
solution (mmol/L: NaCl, 133.5; KCl, 5.4; HEPES, 5; taurine, 
20; MgCl2 3; EGTA 0.5; glucose, 5.5; pH adjusted to 7.4 
with NaOH), and then with collagenase (Worthington Bio-
chemical Co., NJ, USA) containing Tyrode's solution (mmol/L: 
NaCl, 133.5; KCl, 5.4; HEPES, 5; taurine, 20; MgCl2, 3; CaCl2, 
0.15; and glucose, 5.5; collagenase, 0.8 mg/mL; pronase, 0.04 
mg/mL; pH adjusted to 7.4 with NaOH) for 15 minutes. Single 
cardiac myocytes were dispersed by gentle agitation of the 
digested heart in a high K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-low Cl 
-solution and stored in 
cell culture medium (Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium; 
Sigma, St. Louis, USA) at room temperature (24∼26 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C) for 
later use. The high K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-low Cl 
-solution was comprised of the 
following, in mmol/L: KCl, 25; K-glutamate, 70; KH2PO4, 10; 
taurine, 10; glucose, 11; EGTA, 0.5; and HEPES, 10; pH ad-
justed to 7.2 with KOH. All experimental protocols were 
approved by our institutional animal care and use committee. </p>

<p>Solutions and reagents </p>

<p>Fura-2-FF was purchased from TEFLabs (TX, USA). The 
TMRE and carboxy-SNARF-1-AM were obtained from Invi-
trogen (Seoul, Korea). </p>

<p>Fluoroprobe loading procedure </p>

<p>Ventricular myocytes were incubated in Fura-2-FF-AM 
(8 μM) solution for 60 min at 4 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C, and then at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C for 
30 min. Next, ventricular myocytes were incubated for 60 
min at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C with a dye-free solution to sufficiently hydro-
lyze the AM ester dye. Finally, the ventricular myocytes 
were transferred into and incubated in fresh medium. If 
carboxy-SNARF-1 was needed for the study, the dye (2 μM) </p>

<p>was added into the second incubation step. To remove cyto-
solic compartments and to visualize the mitochondrial fluo-
rescence, single isolated cardiomyocytes were perfused with 
saponin (0.1 mg/mL) for 60 s in the perfusing bath which 
is mounted on the inverted microscope (Fig. 1). All experi-
ments were performed at 37 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>C. </p>

<p>Spectrofluorometric measurements with a multipara-
metric measurement system </p>

<p>A fast monochromator (Polychrome II; Till Photonics, 
Inc., Germany) was used as an excitation light source. A fused 
quartz light guide was used to divert the excitation light 
to an inverted microscope (TE-300; Nikon, Tokyo, Japan). 
An oil immersion lens (40x, NA 1.3) was used. A near infra-
red filter (Chroma Technology Corp., Bellows Falls, VT, USA) 
was used between the microscope illuminator and specimen 
to monitor the object field with a charge-coupled device 
(CCD) camera (FTM1800NH/HGI; Philips, Salt Lake, USA). 
The image was captured with a BT878-based TV capture 
board, and the object field or cell area, as a pixel unit, was 
measured with custom-made software. The object field area 
was set with a field diaphragm (Nikon, Tokyo, Japan). Four 
photomultiplier tubes (PMTs) were used to detect emission 
wavelengths, and each had band-pass filters (450, 500, 590, 
and 640 nm). Dichroic mirrors and band-pass filters were 
purchased from Chroma (Brattleboro VT, USA). A photon 
counting method was applied with the combination of a pho-
tomultiplier tube (R2949; Hamamatsu, Hamamatsu Japan), pho-
ton counter unit (C3866; Hamamatsu, Hamamatsu, Japan), 
and high-speed counter (NI 6602; National Instruments, 
Austin, USA). Custom-made driving software was used to 
control and sample data. A diagram of the whole system 
is shown in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Correction of NADH and Fura-2-FF Interference </p>



<p>Fig. 3. NADH and Fura-2 excitation and emission spectra. (A) The 
NADH excitation spectrum was obtained at 465-nm emission and 
the emission spectrum was obtained at 365-nm excitation. (B) The 
Fura-2 excitation spectrum was obtained at 500-nm emission and 
the emission spectrum was obtained at 340-nm excitation. The 
emission spectrum was shifted to the left by an increase in Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>. 
Ex is excitation. Em is emission. </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Identification of isosbestic points. (A) The isosbestic point 
at 450-nm emission (red arrow). Ca 
2+ in the non-bound state (--) 
and Ca 
2+ in the bound state (−) (B) The isosbestic point at 500-nm 
emission for Ca 
2+ in the non-bound state (--) and Ca 
2+ in the bound 
state (−) (C) The graph shows subtracted data. Ca 
2+ in the non-bound 
state was subtracted from that in the bound state at 450 nm. (D) 
The graph shows subtracted data. Ca 
2+ in the non-bound state was 
subtracted from that in the bound state at 500 nm. (E) Standard 
deviation data from graph C. (F) Standard deviation data from 
graph D. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The excitation spectrum of NADH-Fura-2-FF. The spectrum 
shows the interference between NADH and Fura-2-FF at each 
emission (450 and 500 nm). (A) The NADH excitation spectrum at 
450-nm emission. (B) The NADH excitation spectrum at 500-nm emi-
ssion. (C) The Fura-2-FF excitation spectrum at 450-nm emission 
under Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-free and 1 mM Ca 
2+ conditions. (D) The Fura-2-FF ex-
citation spectrum at 500-nm emission under Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-free and 1 mM 
Ca 
2+ conditions. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Development of a NADH correction method 
NADH-Fura-2 signal interference: Simultaneous measure-
ment of Fura-2-FF and NADH was technically difficult be-
cause each fluoroprobe produced signal interference. Fig. 2 
shows this interference. Emission wavelengths of 450 and 
500 nm were selected for NADH and Fura-2-FF, respectively. 
The excitation spectrums of both fluoroprobes overlapped. 
In addition, each fluoroprobe could generate emission at 
both 450 and 500 nm. The light intensity at each emission, 
therefore, contained signals from both fluoroprobes. This in-
terference had to be corrected to obtain an exact measure-
ment of the emission signal, specifically the quantitative 
measurement of Ca 
2+ with Fura-2-FF. 
Correction principles: The excitation wavelength and the 
concentration of NADH can affect the emission intensity but 
not the emission spectral curve. Changes in [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] did not 
affect the emission and excitation spectrums of NADH (data 
not shown). Thus, the 450 and 500 nm ratio of NADH was 
constant at any excitation wavelength. The same principle 
can be applied to Fura-2-FF if NADH or [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] does not affect 
the emission and excitation spectrums of Fura-2-FF. However, 
the Fura-2-FF emission spectrum was shifted to the left by 
Ca 
2+ (Fig. 3B). Therefore, only isosbestic excitation could gen-
erate a Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-independent emission spectrum. The isosbestic 
point was different for each emission wavelength (i.e., 450 
and 500 nm). To minimize NADH contamination during iso-
sbestic point acquisition, 10 μM FCCP and 10 μM ADP 
were added in the absence of mitochondrial substrates. The 
residual emission intensity was measured, and the relation-
ship between the intensity and the cell area was obtained 
for correction of subsequent experiments. After myocytes 
were loaded with Fura-2-FF, the cell area was measured 
in each cardiac myocyte to correct the residual signals. The 
excitation spectrums at 450 and 500 nm emission were ob-
tained by changing [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] from 0 to 10 mM under FCCP-free </p>

<p>and mitochondrial substrate-free conditions (Fig. 4A and B). 
The excitation spectrum of the Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-bound state was sub-
tracted from the excitation spectrum of Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-free conditions. 
Those subtracted curves are shown in Fig. 4C and D. To 
obtain an isosbestic point, we chose the wavelength show-
ing the minimum standard deviation value (Fig. 4E and F). 
The isosbestic points were 361 at 450-nm emissions and </p>



<p>JH Lee, et al </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Cellular area-dependent autofluorescent background. • 
(F361,450) was used for NADH signal correction. ○ (F353,500) and ▼ 
(F400,500) were used for Fura-2-FF signal correction, respectively. △ 
(F530,590) was used for TMRE signal correction. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Measurement of RN factors. (A) The NADH signal in 
Fura-2-FF-free myocytes at 361-nm excitation and 450-nm emission 
was measured in the presence of various mitochondrial substrates. 
(B) F400,500 (•) and F353,500 (−) were measured simultaneously to 
monitor the NADH contribution to the Fura-2-FF signal. (C) The 
graph shows the relationships between F361,450,NADH and F353,500,NADH 
(•) and between F361,450,NADH and F400,500,NADH (○). Linear relation-
ships are evident in the graph. </p>

<p>353 at 500-nm emissions, respectively. Using isosbestic ex-
citation, the following equations were valid: </p>

<p>F361,450=F361,450,NADH+F361,450,fura 
(1) 
F353,500=F353,500,NADH+F353,500,fura 
(2) 
F400,500=F400,500,NADH+F400,500,fura 
(3) </p>

<p>where Fx,y is the measured emission intensity at y nm by 
x nm excitation, Fx,y,NADH represents the pure NADH-de-
pendent emission intensity, and Fx,y,fura represents the pure 
Fura-2-FF dependent emission intensity. In addition, the 
Rf, RN1, and RN2 values must be constant because of the 
consistent shape of the emission spectrum: </p>

<p>Rf=F361,450,fura/F353,500,fura 
(4) 
RN1=F400,500,NADH/F361,450,NADH 
(5) 
RN2=F353,500,NADH/F361,450,NADH 
(6) </p>

<p>With these constants, equations (1), (2), and (3) can be 
changed as follows: </p>

<p>F361,450=F361,450,NADH+Rf*F353,500,fura 
(7) 
F353,500=RN2*F361,450,NADH+F353,500,fura 
(8) 
F400,500=RN1*F361,450,NADH+F400,500,fura 
(9) </p>

<p>If the constants, Rf, RN1, and RN2, were known, the pure 
NADH and Fura-2-FF signals could be obtained by solving 
the above equations. The Rf was calculated with the fluo-
rescence intensity observed in Fig. 4A and B. RN1 and RN2 
were obtained in myocytes that were not loaded with 
Fura-2-FF. The NADH signal was changed according to the 
supply of mitochondrial substrates: malate, pyruvate, or 
malate plus pyruvate (Fig. 5A and B). The linear relation-
ships of F400,500,NADH vs. F361,450,NADH and F353,500,NADH vs. 
F361,450,NADH are shown in Fig. 5C, and each slope indicates 
RN1 and RN2. The equations of each pure signal values are 
as follows: </p>

<p>F361,450,NADH=(A-Rf*B)/(1-Rf*RN2) 
( 1 0 ) </p>

<p>F353,500,fura /F400,500,fura=Rfura・= </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>         
        </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>              
      </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(11) </p>

<p>Rfura is the ratio value of Fura-2-FF that was used to calcu-
late the free calcium concentration. 
Background subtraction: The excitation light intensity 
used to induce fluorescence was much stronger than the fluo-
rescence emission. Although the selected excitation wave-
length was far different from the emission wavelength and 
was blocked using a band-pass filter, the stray light from 
excitation was still present. The stray light was reflected 
at the boundary between the solution and the cover slip 
and diffracted in the cells due to cellular components. Cells 
may also produce unwanted autofluorescence. Those signal 
artifacts were comparable to the real fluorescence emission 
from the dye; thus, correction was necessary. First, the re-
flected signal at the cover slip boundary was measured. 
Then, the background signal due to cellular autofluorescence 
was measured in the presence of FCCP and in the absence 
of mitochondrial substrates. The cell-dependent background 
signal was linearly related to the cell area; these relation-
ships are shown in Fig. 6. Later, the dye-loaded cellular 
area was measured, and the autofluorescence calculated 
from the cellular area was corrected. Further, the cell-free 
window background was also measured and subtracted. The 
background correction was performed before the experi-
ments began. We determined the relationship between the 
cellular area and cellular autofluorescence on each ex-
perimental day. </p>

<p>Calibration equation </p>

<p>The Ca 
2+ concentration could be calculated from the ratio </p>

<p>value calculated from equation (11) using Grykiewicz's equa-
tion [37]. To convert the ratio into a concentration, the equa-
tion required four parameters: Kd, dissociation constant; Rmin, 
minimum ratio; Rmax, maximum ratio; and F380,max/F380,min, the </p>

<p>Correction of NADH and Fura-2-FF Interference </p>



<p>Table 1. The dissociation constant (Kd) of Fura-2-FF at different 
pH values </p>

<p>Conditions 
pH 
Kd±S.E. (μM) </p>

<p>Without cell 
6.0 
10.1622±0.4461 (n=12) 
6.5 
6.7459±0.2751 (n=23) 
7.0 
5.5703±0.1392 (n=36) 
7.5 
6.4291±0.2219 (n=27) 
8.0 
6.5048±0.0364 (n=3) 
With cell 
6.0 
10.8589±0.6653 (n=12) 
6.5 
4.2521±0.2319 (n=12) 
7.0 
3.9020±0.2702 (n=10) 
7.5 
5.2825±0.4023 (n=10) </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Simultaneous measurement of NADH, [Ca 
2+ ]m, and pH. 
Using carboxy-SNARF-and Fura-2-FF-loaded myocytes, NADH, 
[Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m, and pH was measured simultaneously. The mitochondrial 
pH changes were investigated following Ca 
2+ changes. The increase 
in [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m did not affect mitochondrial pH. Mitochondrial pH was 
7.504±0.047 (mean±S.E., n=13). </p>

<p>ratio of maximum and minimum at 380 nm excitation. How-
ever, applying the equation was not easy because both Rmax 
and F380,max/F380,min require Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-saturated conditions with-
out dye-loss. Replicating that condition in real cells was a 
difficult and erroneous procedure. In mitochondria, dye-satu-
rated conditions for Fura-2-FF without dye-loss were vir-
tually impossible. We found that the Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-bound form of 
Fura-2-FF was practically non-fluorescent at 400-nm exci-
tation. The new equation using this property was developed 
and is as follows: </p>

<p>[Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] =Kdㆍ(F400,500,max/F353,500,max)ㆍ(R-Rmin) 
( 1 2 ) </p>

<p>The F400,500,max and F353,500,max are maximum values of the 
emitted signals at 500 nm with the excitation at 400 and 
353 nm. Since F353,500,max was an isosbestic emission value 
and was constant, the above equation could be simplified 
further as follows: </p>

<p>[Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]=Kdㆍ(1/Rmin)ㆍ(R-Rmin) 
(13) </p>

<p>The details of the derivation of the above equations are 
shown in the Appendix. </p>

<p>The Kd of Fura-2-FF </p>

<p>To apply the calibration equation, the Kd value had to 
be determined. If we knew the free [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] and the other 
parameters in the calibration equation, we could calculate 
Kd. To calculate the free Ca 
2+ concentration, <rs id="software-2" type="software">WINMAXC32</rs> 
version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">2.50</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Chris Patton</rs>, Stanford University) was used. 
EGTA purity was double-checked using the pH and oxalate 
method [38-42]. We obtained pH-dependent changes of Kd 
values in a cell-free solution. To simulate the experimental 
conditions, we measured pH-dependent Kd values with a 
dye-free cell in the window. A summary of the measured 
Kd values is shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>M itochondrial pH changes by the change in [Ca 
2+ ]m </p>

<p>Using carboxy-SNARF loaded myocytes, mitochondrial 
pH changes were determined following Ca 
2+ changes (Fig. 7). 
The increase in [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m did not affect mitochondrial pH. The 
mitochondrial pH was 7.504±0.047 (mean±standard error 
[S.E.], n=13). The Kd value of Fura-2-FF at pH 7.5 was 5.28 
μM; this value was used for later Ca 
2+ calculations. </p>

<p>M itochondrial Ca 
2+ changes due to correction </p>

<p>Fig. 8 shows the differences in Ca 
2+ concentrations before 
and after the correction. The results clearly showed the impor-
tance of correction for NADH and Fura-2-FF interference. The 
mitochondrial resting calcium concentration was 1.03±0.13 
μM (mean±S.E., n=32) and the maximum [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m at 1 μM 
cytosolic Ca 
2+ ([Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]c) was 29.6±1.61 μM (mean±S.E., n=33) 
(Fig. 9). </p>

<p>Simultaneous measurement of NADH, [Ca </p>

<p>2+ ]m, and Ψm </p>

<p>TMRE has a positive charge and is distributed in a mem-
brane potential-dependent manner. If the concentration in 
each compartment is known, the membrane potential can 
be calculated using Nernst's equation. TMRE was perfused 
at 2 nM to record the changes in the TMRE signal in mito-
chondria. The resting Ψm was assumed to be −150 mV. 
Based on this, Ψm was calculated. NADH was decreased 
by the application of Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, but the Ψm remained similar 
(Fig. 10). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Interest in the ubiquitous role of Ca 
2+ in cells and cellular 
organelles is increasing. To study Ca 
2+ dynamics, the use of 
Ca 
2+ indicators has steadily increased. Mitochondria have </p>

<p>378 </p>

<p>JH Lee, et al </p>

<p>Fig. 9. Resting and maximal [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m at l μM cytosolic Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>. The 
resting [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m was 1.03±0.13 μM (mean±S.E., n=32) and the maximal 
[Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m was 29.6±1.61 μM (mean±S.E., n=33). </p>

<p>Fig. 10. Simultaneous measurement of NADH, [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m, and Ψm. Using 
Fura-2-FF-loaded myocytes, NADH, [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m, and Ψm were measured 
simultaneously. The resting Ψm was assumed to be −150 mV. </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Results of NADH and Fura-2-FF interference correction. 
The left panels show the signals prior to correction and the right 
panels show the signals after correction. NADH and the ratio of 
Fura-2-FF signals were changed following correction. The calculated 
[Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m was substantially decreased. (A) NADH signals at 450-nm 
emission. (B) Fura-2-FF signals at 500-nm emission. The figure 
shows F400,500 (--), F353,500 (----), and the ratio of Fura-2-FF (-). 
(C) The mitochondrial calcium concentration calculated from the 
Fura-2-FF ratio. </p>

<p>now become a focus because of their role in many cellular proc-
esses, such as energy generation, apoptosis, ischemic-reper-
fusion injury in the heart, aging, etc. Ca 
2+ has a central 
role in these processes. However, quantitative and dynamic 
mitochondrial Ca 
2+ data are not yet available. For quantita-
tive measurement of mitochondrial Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, a ratiometric ap-
proach is essential. Ratiometric fluoroprobes are advanta-
geous for quantitative measurement of [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] because dye 
loss due to leakage or photobleaching does not affect the 
calculation of [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]. These problems cannot be avoided </p>

<p>when single excitation and single emission dyes are used 
to determine [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]. 
Fura-2 was first introduced in 1985 as a ratiometric fluo-
rescent dye [37]; several analogs were subsequently devel-
oped. However, Fura-2 has several disadvantages when used 
to measure mitochondrial Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>. First, targeted dye loading 
into the mitochondria is not easy. Therefore, Fura-2 would 
likely be nonspecifically loaded into all organelles of the 
cell. One major Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-related organelle is the SR. However, 
the total SR and mitochondria percent volumes are about 
3.5% and 34∼36%, respectively, in rat ventricular my-
ocytes [43,44]. Therefore, even though Ca 
2+ in SR may affect 
the results, the effect would be negligible. Second, cellular 
autofluorescence from NADH could contaminate the Fura-2 
signal. More than 90% of cellular NADH is present in the 
mitochondria (data not shown). Excitation and emission 
spectrums of NADH and Fura-2 widely overlap. Importantly, 
Ca 
2+ changes in mitochondria could affect NADH, which, 
in turn, affects Fura-2 signals. Therefore, this complicated 
interference must be solved to quantitatively measure [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m. 
This problem, however, has not been systematically inves-
tigated since Fura-2 was introduced. We were able to suc-
cessfully correct for the interference between NADH and 
Fura-2 using the spectral characteristics of NADH and 
Fura-2. Fig. 8 shows the effect of NADH and Fura-2-FF 
interference. The NADH signal was considerably decreased 
after the correction (Fig. 8). The corrected Fura-2-FF signal 
resulted in lower [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m. This interference implied that da-
ta from previous reports using Fura-2 analogs could be 
wrong, as the NADH signal could be different based on the 
correction or lack thereof. We would like to further inves-</p>

<p>Correction of NADH and Fura-2-FF Interference </p>



<p>tigate this possibility in the future. 
Our calibration equation (Equation 12) has many advan-
tages over Grynkiewicz's equation. First, it only required 
three calibration parameters: Kd, F340,max/F400,max, and Rmin. 
Second, the ratio value was directly linear to the Ca 
2+ con-
centration at a constant pH. Therefore, the rate of ratio change 
could be directly converted to the rate of Ca 
2+ change. Third, 
obtaining the calibration parameters, particularly F340,max/ 
F400,max, is relatively error-free. In Grynkiewicz's equation, 
F380,max/F380,min is prone to error because it divides the larg-
est number by the smallest number. In addition, to obtain 
F380,max/F380,min, we had to accomplish real free-and satu-
rated-[Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] conditions because F380 must reach the real max-
imum and minimum values, respectively. If not, F380,max/F380,min 
can easily be faulty. However, in our new equation, the 
F340,max/F400,max measurement error is much smaller because 
it is the ratio of the largest numbers at each excitation. 
Fourth, as shown in Equation 13, when the isosbestic ex-
citation value was chosen instead of 340 nm in the new 
equation, only Rmin is required to convert the ratio into the 
Ca 
2+ concentration if the pH was unchanged and the Kd 
value at that pH is known. Finally, the calibration proce-
dure is much simpler, as Rmin is the only parameter needed. 
However, there are limitations associated with use of the 
equation. The new equation was generated based on the 
assumption that the emission of Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-saturated Fura-2-FF was 
zero at 400-nm excitation. However, Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-saturated Fura-2-FF 
actually produces a small emission. This causes deflection 
from the linearity between the ratio and Ca 
2+ concentration 
at very high Ca 
2+ concentrations. We that found our equa-
tion could be reasonably applied to [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m concentrations 
up to 50-fold that of the Kd. This range is reasonably accept-
able under experimental conditions. The new equation still 
does not solve the problems of incomplete hydrolysis of the 
AM form of the dye, dye compartmentalization, autofluo-
rescence, etc. Dye loading problems are inevitable, but care-
ful loading and washing may minimize these kinds of errors 
(see Ref. [45]). In the case of compartmentalization, mi-
tochondria had the largest volume; therefore, this type of 
error could be ignored. We used a very careful loading pro-
cedure to minimize incomplete hydrolysis of the AM form; 
therefore, we believe that this error was also minimized. 
The Kd value of Fura-2-FF is pH dependent; therefore, 
if the procedure could cause changes in pH, we need to con-
sider the pH effect when calculating [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m. Cytosolic Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>application increased [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m, but the mitochondrial pH did 
not change. Therefore, the constant Kd at pH 7.5 was used 
to calculate [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m. 
Our microfluorometry system could measure NADH, [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m, 
and pHm simultaneously. In addition, the Ψm could be meas-
ured using TMRE because the excitation and the emission 
spectrum of TMRE overlapped with those of carboxy-SNARF-1. 
Therefore, we were able to successfully measure Ψm using 
TMRE (Fig. 10). 
The resting [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m was approximately 1.03 μM. A pre-
vious report showed that [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m ranged from 0.08 to 0.17 
μM [23,24]. Our study revealed a higher value than that 
of previous reports (see Refs. [23,24]). The change in [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m 
plays a central role in the exercise-dependent increase in 
ATP by activating three mitochondrial matrix Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-sensi-
tive enzymes (pyruvate dehydrogenase, α-ketoglutarate 
dehydrogenase, and NAD-dependent isocitrate dehydrogen-
ase) [46-51]. Pyruvate and α-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase 
were almost fully activated at 1 μM because of the low 
Kd values, 0.77 and 0.28 μM, respectively [51]. The Kd val-</p>

<p>ue of NAD-dependent isocitrate dehydrogenase was 5.4 μM 
[51]. Therefore, the [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m-dependent increase in ATP may 
be due to the activation of NAD-dependent isocitrate dehyd-
rogenase. 
The maximal attainable [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m seemed to be limited. 
Our data showed that the maximal [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m was about 30 
μM at 1 μM cytosolic Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>. Even when we applied more 
than 1 μM, the maximal [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m was not increased further 
(data not shown). The 30 μM concentration is far below 
the electrochemical equilibrium because the Ψm is about 
−150 mV and the concentration of the electrochemical 
equilibrium must be up to 10 
5 times the cytosolic [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]. 
This limitation implied the strong possibility that other 
mechanisms exist to limit Ca 
2+ increase in mitochondria. 
This may be a Ca 
2+ efflux mechanism, an inhibitory regu-
lator of Ca 
2+ influx, or the increase in Ca 
2+ buffer by a vol-
ume increase or an actual buffer increase. Until now, two 
mechanisms were suggested for mitochondrial Ca 
2+ efflux, 
mNCX and CPX. Ca 
2+ was applied under 0 mM Na 
+ con-
ditions; therefore, mNCX could not be the efflux mechanism 
involved in limiting the increase in [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m. CPX may 
change mitochondrial pH because it causes influx of H 
+ into 
mitochondria. However, mitochondrial pH was not changed 
during [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m increase. The MCU, a major Ca 
2+ influx 
pathway, did not show inactivation [52]. The electrochemical 
gradient for Ca 
2+ influx was huge, and thus it would likely 
be difficult for CPX to counteract the Ca 
2+ influx to limit 
the [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m increase. Another possibility is the opening of 
the MPTP. It was reported that [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m overload could open 
the MPTP [53-55]. However, MPTP is permeable to 1.5-kDa 
molecules [54-56]; if the MPTP was opened, Fura-2-FF or 
NADH would be decreased. Further, if the MPTP was 
opened, the Ψm would be substantially depolarized. However, 
we did not observe these phenomena. Mitochondria are known 
to be a Ca 
2+ sink because of their relatively larger Ca 
2+ buf-
fering capacity [57-60]. If the limitation was caused by the 
buffer, [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m must continuously increase, even though the 
speed was slower; however, this was not observed. Ca 
2+ and 
Pi could form a precipitate [61], and free [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m may not 
increase because of continuous precipitate formation. Another 
possibility is mitochondrial swelling. Ca 
2+ overload caused 
mitochondrial swelling, an indication of MPTP opening [53-55]. 
However, actual swelling may occur without MPTP opening. 
Mitochondria reportedly had a Pi-containing particle [61]. 
Mitochondrial swelling and dissolution of those particles 
may increase mitochondrial buffering capacity to limit [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>]m 
increase. The Pi effect on mitochondrial Ca 
2+ dynamics re-
quires further study. 
In conclusion, we successfully developed a method to solve 
NADH and Fura-2-FF interference. This method enables 
more accurate Ca 
2+ measurements. In particular, quantita-
tive measurement of mitochondrial Ca 
2+ dynamics is now 
possible and many uncertainties surrounding mitochon-
drial Ca 
2+ dynamics can be answered in the future using 
our new method. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This research was partly supported by the National 
Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry 
of Education, Science and Technology (No. 2011-0010965) 
and (No. 2012-0009829). </p>



<p>JH Lee, et al </p>





<p>JH Lee, et al </p>

<p>Appendix: Derivation of the new calibration equations. </p>

<p>If the fluorescent dye is only bound to Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, the following equation is valid: </p>

<p> 
        </p>

<p>  </p>

<p>(1a) </p>

<p>Total dye concentration: DT 
Free-form dye concentration: Df 
Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-bound-form dye concentration: Db 
Dissociation constant: Kd. </p>

<p>If each form of the dye generates fluorescence emission at k by the excitation wavelengths x and y, the fluorescence intensity 
of the mixture of the free-and bound-form dye is as follows: </p>

<p>Fx,k=aㆍDf+bㆍDb 
(2a) 
Fy,k=cㆍDf+dㆍDb 
(3a) </p>

<p>where Fx,k is the emitted intensity at k by the x excitation, and Fy,k is the emitted intensity at k by the y excitation. 
Since the Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-bound form of Fura-2-FF does not generate fluorescence at the 400 nm emission, we can describe this by 
setting d to zero. When the florescence ratio R is the ratio Fx,k/Fy,k, </p>

<p>   ㆍ  
ㆍ   ㆍ  </p>

<p>(4a) </p>

<p>   
     
ㆍ      </p>

<p> ㆍ      </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>(5a) </p>

<p>if all dye is the free form and [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] is zero, R is the minimum value (Rmin) and equal to a/c. In addition, Fy,k is the 
maximum value (Fy,k,max) and is c·DT. If all dye is the Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-bound form in Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>-saturated conditions, Fx,k is the maximum 
value (Fx,k,max) and is bㆍDT. Therefore, [Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>] can be calculated with the following equation: </p>

<p> 
     ㆍ    
  ㆍ       </p>

<p>(6a) </p>

<p>If x is the isosbestic excitation, (2a) and (5a) can be converted as follows: </p>

<p>Fx,k=a'ㆍDT=a'ㆍ(Df+Db) 
(7a) </p>

<p>   
    ′ 
ㆍ  ′   ′ </p>

<p> ㆍ      </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>  </p>

<p>Since a'/c equals Rmin, the following equation can be derived: </p>

<p> 
     ㆍ    
 ㆍ      </p>

<p>The English in this document has been checked by at least two professional editors, both native speakers of English. For 
a certificate, please see: </p>

<p>http://www.textcheck.com/certificate/iNNy9q </p>

</text></tei>