<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4963800" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Magnetic resonance venography (MRV) has diagnostic 
accuracy equivalent or superior to venous ultrasonography 
for acute deep vein thrombosis (DVT). 1-5 MRV allows for 
more accurate determination of thrombus volume and is not 
limited by edema or depth of venous segments. MRV with 
direct thrombus imaging has the additional advantages of 
more precise differentiation of acute versus chronic DVT 6 
and more accurate detection of changes in thrombus vol-
ume over time. 7 In acute DVT trials comparing anticoagu-
lation regimens, the extent of thrombus volume reduction 
over time has not been evaluated using MRV. 
We conducted this multicenter randomized controlled 
trial to evaluate the feasibility of MRV as a thrombus </p>

<p>Magnetic resonance venography to 
assess thrombus resolution with 
edoxaban monotherapy versus parenteral 
anticoagulation/warfarin for symptomatic deep 
vein thrombosis: A multicenter feasibility study </p>

<p>Gregory Piazza 1 , Venkatesh Mani 2 , Samuel Z Goldhaber 1 , Michael A Grosso 3 , 
Michele Mercuri 3 , Hans J Lanz 3 , Steven Schussler 3 , Ching Hsu 3 , Amy Chinigo 3 , 
Bruce Ritchie 4 , Venkatesh Nadar 5 , Kevin Cannon 6 , John Pullman 7 , 
Mauricio Concha 8 , Marlin Schul 9 and Zahi A Fayad 2 ; for the edoxaban 
Thrombus Reduction Imaging Study (eTRIS) Investigators </p>

<p>Abstract 
The feasibility of magnetic resonance venography (MRV) for measuring change in thrombus volume with a novel 
anticoagulation regimen versus standard anticoagulation in patients with symptomatic deep vein thrombosis (DVT) 
has not been assessed. Our aim was to study the feasibility of MRV to measure change in thrombus volume in patients 
with acute symptomatic objectively confirmed proximal DVT in an open-label multicenter trial (edoxaban Thrombus 
Reduction Imaging Study, eTRIS). We randomized patients in a 2:1 allocation ratio to edoxaban 90 mg/day for 10 days 
followed by 60 mg/day versus parenteral anticoagulation bridging to warfarin for 3 months. The primary efficacy outcome 
was a surrogate end point of the relative change in MRV-quantified thrombus volume from baseline to Day 14-21. 
A total of 85 eligible patients from 26 study sites were randomized to edoxaban monotherapy (n=56) versus parenteral 
anticoagulation as a 'bridge' to warfarin (n=29). The mean relative change in MRV-quantified thrombus volume from 
baseline to Day 14-21 was similar in patients treated with edoxaban and parenteral anticoagulation as a 'bridge' to 
warfarin (−50.1% vs −58.9%; 95% confidence interval of treatment difference, −12.7%, 30.2%). However, thrombus 
extension was observed in eight patients in the edoxaban monotherapy group and in none in the warfarin group. 
Rates of recurrent venous thromboembolism (3.6% vs 3.6%, p=0.45) and clinically relevant non-major bleeding (5.4% 
vs 7.1%, p=0.34) were also similar. No major bleeds occurred in either on-treatment group during the study period. 
In conclusion, MRV can assess change in thrombus volume in patients with acute DVT randomized to two different 
anticoagulant regimens. </p>

<p>ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT01662908 
Investigational New Drug (IND) Application: Edoxaban IND # 63266 </p>

<p>Keywords 
anticoagulation, deep vein thrombosis, edoxaban, magnetic resonance, MRV, venous thromboembolism eTRIS </p>

<p>1 Cardiovascular Division, Department of Medicine, Brigham and 
Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA 
2 Translational and Molecular Imaging Institute, Icahn School of Medicine 
at Mount Sinai, New York, NY, USA 
3 Daiichi Sankyo Pharma Development, Edison, NJ, USA 
4 Division of Hematology, Department of Medicine, University of 
Alberta, Edmonton, AB, Canada 
5 Lewin and Nadar Cardiology Associates, Camp Hill, PA, USA 
6 Wilmington Health, Wilmington, NC, USA 
7 St James Healthcare, Butte, MT, USA 
8 Intercoastal Medical Group, Sarasota, FL, USA 
9 Lafayette Regional Vein and Laser Center, Lafayette, IN, USA </p>

<p>Corresponding author: 
Gregory Piazza, Cardiovascular Division, Brigham and Women's 
Hospital, 75 Francis St, Boston, MA 02115, USA. 
Email: gpiazza@partners.org </p>

<p>645853V MJ0010.1177/1358863X16645853Vascular MedicinePiazza et al. </p>

<p>research-article2016 </p>

<p>Original Article </p>



<p>Vascular Medicine 21(4) </p>

<p>imaging tool and to assess the relative change in thrombus 
volume with MRV in patients with acute DVT treated with 
either oral monotherapy with edoxaban versus parenteral 
heparin as a 'bridge' to oral anticoagulation with warfarin. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>The study was a randomized, open-label, parallel-group, 
active-control, multicenter trial. From September 2012 to 
January 2014, we screened 94 patients with acute DVT 
(Figure 1). Study patients were enrolled at 26 sites across 
the USA, including urban, non-urban, teaching, and non-
teaching hospitals. Institutional Review Board approval 
was obtained at all sites. All index DVT and all recurrent 
DVT, bleeding, major adverse cardiac events, death, and 
hepatic events were evaluated via a centralized, blinded 
adjudication process. </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>Eligible patients were required to have acute, sympto-
matic DVT involving the popliteal, femoral, or iliac vein 
(Supplementary material). Symptom onset could be no 
longer than 1 week prior to randomization. Diagnosis of 
DVT required one of the following: a non-compressible 
vein on ultrasonography, an intraluminal filling defect on 
contrast venography, or an intraluminal filling defect on 
contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT). Patients 
diagnosed with concomitant pulmonary embolism (PE) at 
the time of randomization were excluded (Supplementary 
material). 
Up to 48 hours of LMWH or unfractionated heparin and/ 
or a single dose of warfarin were permitted prior to randomi-
zation. Patients with greater than 48 hours of anticoagulation 
prior to potential randomization were excluded. Patients 
were randomized with a web-based system in a 2:1 allocation </p>

<p>ratio to either edoxaban monotherapy or a parenteral antico-
agulant 'bridge' of LMWH or unfractionated heparin to war-
farin. Written informed consent was obtained from each 
study patient. 
Enrollment was planned to continue until 90 patients 
were randomized across both treatment groups. Owing to 
slow enrollment, the study was discontinued by the sponsor 
after 85 patients had been randomized. </p>

<p>Anticoagulation </p>

<p>Subjects randomized to the edoxaban monotherapy arm 
received edoxaban 90 mg once daily for 10 days (± 2 days) 
followed by 60 mg once daily for approximately 90 days. 
After randomization, patients assigned to edoxaban mono-
therapy were stratified by need for dose reduction (body 
weight ⩽ 60 kg or creatinine clearance (CrCL) between 
⩾ 30 ml/min and ⩽ 50 ml/min). Patients stratified to the 
dose reduction arm received 45 mg once daily for 10 days 
followed by 30 mg once daily for a total of approximately 
90 days. The study protocol allowed for concomitant aspi-
rin use up to 100 mg daily. 
For patients randomized to parenteral anticoagulation as 
a 'bridge' to oral anticoagulation with warfarin, parenteral 
anticoagulation with open-label subcutaneous enoxaparin 
(1 mg/kg twice daily or 1.5 mg/kg once daily) or intrave-
nous unfractionated heparin was administered as soon as 
possible after randomization for at least 5 days. Open-label 
warfarin was started approximately at the same time as 
enoxaparin or unfractionated heparin. As soon as an inter-
national normalized ratio (INR) ⩾ 2 was achieved on two 
consecutive days or a single INR &gt; 3 was achieved, paren-
teral anticoagulation was stopped, and warfarin was contin-
ued to maintain the INR target range of 2.0-3.0. </p>

<p>Magnetic resonance venography </p>

<p>The study mandated two MRV examinations. The first 
study was performed within 36 hours after randomization, </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flow of patients through each stage of the trial. (DVT, deep vein thrombosis; LMWH, low-molecular weight heparin; mITT, 
modified intention-to-treat.). </p>

<p>Piazza et al. </p>



<p>and the second was performed between days 14 and 21 
after randomization. All images were analyzed by a Core 
Imaging Laboratory (Translational and Molecular Imaging 
Institute, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New 
York, NY, USA). 
For each imaging time point, bilateral lower extremity 
and lower pelvis MRV with contrast was performed in a 
single examination of approximately 60 minutes. 8 For sub-
jects with normal renal function (creatinine clearance &gt; 60 
ml/min), a dose of 0.03 mmol/kg (0.12 ml/kg) Ablavar ® 
(gadofosveset trisodium; Lantheus Medical Imaging, North 
Billerica, MA, USA) was injected at a rate of 2 ml/second. 9 
Ablavar is a blood pool contrast agent with favorable prop-
erties for venous imaging. 
After acquiring scout and time-of-flight images to iden-
tify the arterial vasculature, three dimensional (3D) 
T1-weighted gradient echo images (GRE; VIBE, LAVA) 
were acquired before and after the injection of Ablavar to 
estimate thrombus volume. Thrombus volume was assessed 
utilizing contrast-enhanced MRV images after the contrast 
agent circulated for 5 minutes to ensure a steady state in the 
blood pool. To determine locations and extent of thrombus, 
pre-and post-contrast 3D gradient echo sequences were 
acquired from: (1) the mid-calf to above the knee, (2) above 
the knee to the thigh and lower pelvis, and (3) thigh and 
lower pelvis to abdomen. 
Image analysis (Supplementary material) was performed 
on a dedicated workstation (Apple Mac Pro ® with <rs type="software">OsiriX 
MD</rs>) by two treatment-blinded experienced image analysts. 
Baseline and follow-up MRV images were compared for 
each subject for the following venous segments: external 
iliac, common femoral, superficial femoral, deep femoral, 
popliteal, anterior tibial, posterior tibial, gastrocnemius, 
and peroneal veins. 
For MRV images, analysts traced 3D curved multiplanar 
reconstructions, using contours following the centerline of 
each venous segment, and produced 1 mm axial slices per-
pendicular to the curved path. Analysts then manually seg-
mented regions of interest corresponding to the thrombus. 
Thrombus volume was calculated by multiplying the area 
of interest (thrombus) by the slice thickness (1 mm) using a 
custom <rs id="software-1" type="software">MATLAB</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Mathworks Inc.</rs>., Natick, MA, USA) 
script. Total thrombus volume in each subject was calcu-
lated by adding the thrombus volumes in each vessel. 
The eTRIS-DVT total score was calculated as the sum 
of the individual modified Oral Direct Factor Xa Inhibitor 
Deep Vein Thrombosis (ODIXa-DVT) vessel score for ves-
sels in which thrombus was present. The ODIXa-DVT 
score is a validated method for calculating thrombus bur-
den based on the finding of non-compressibility on venous 
ultrasonography in prespecified venous segments. 10 The 
eTRIS volumetric DVT total score was calculated as the 
product of the thrombus volume in the vessel and the modi-
fied ODIXa-DVT score for that vessel. </p>

<p>Clinical follow-up </p>

<p>Clinical follow-up visits were performed on post-randomi-
zation Day 10 ± 2, Day 14-21, Day 45 ± 4, Day 90 ± 7, and </p>

<p>Day 120 ± 7 (30 days post-study drug completion). All sub-
jects who permanently stopped taking the study drug were 
expected to have a follow-up visit 30 days later. Overall, 82 
of the 85 patients randomized (96.5%) completed the 
30-day follow-up visit. Study subjects were evaluated for 
recurrent DVT, PE, bleeding, myocardial infarction (MI), 
stroke, systemic embolic events, hepatic events, and death, 
as well as any other adverse event. </p>

<p>Outcomes </p>

<p>The primary efficacy outcome was a surrogate end point 
of the relative change in thrombus volume assessed by 
MRV from baseline to Day 14-21. Secondary efficacy 
outcomes included recurrence of venous thromboembo-
lism (VTE), defined as a composite of adjudicated recur-
rent DVT, PE, or VTE-related death (Supplementary 
material), and change from baseline to Day 14-21 in the 
presence or absence of thrombus by venous segment as 
detected by MRV. A reduction in thrombotic burden was 
defined as any decrease in thrombus volume on MRV and 
no adjudicated recurrent VTE. 
The primary safety outcome was clinically relevant 
bleeding (International Society on Thrombosis and 
Haemostasis major or clinically relevant non-major bleed-
ing) (Supplementary material). 11 All other overt bleeding 
not meeting criteria for major or clinically relevant non-
major bleeding was classified as nuisance bleeding. All 
bleeding events were adjudicated by a Clinical Endpoints 
Committee blinded to treatment allocation. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>The total intended sample size of approximately 90 sub-
jects (60 in the edoxaban group, 30 in the parenteral antico-
agulant 'bridge' to warfarin group) was chosen based on 
study feasibility, rather than on statistical considerations. 
To collect more information of relative thrombus volume 
change by MRV in the edoxaban treatment group, a 2:1 ran-
domization allocation ratio was used. 
Results for continuous variables were compared to base-
line using a paired t-test or Wilcoxon signed rank test. For 
two-group comparisons, a two-sample t-test or Wilcoxon 
rank sum was used for continuous data, and Fisher's exact 
test was used for binary data. All p-values were two-sided, 
and a p-value of &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. 
The primary efficacy analysis was based on the modi-
fied intention-to-treat (mITT) analysis set: all randomized 
subjects who received at least one dose of randomized 
study drug. The primary safety analysis (on-treatment) was 
performed using the safety analysis set: all randomized 
subjects who received at least one dose of randomized 
study drug according to the treatment actually received. 
Data analyses were performed using software <rs id="software-2" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">Version 8.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC, USA). 
The relative change of thrombus volume from baseline 
was calculated as the difference between Day 14-21 
and baseline measurements divided by the baseline </p>



<p>Vascular Medicine 21(4) </p>

<p>measurement, then multiplied by 100. The relative change 
from baseline was summarized within each group and 
compared by providing the treatment difference and a 
95% confidence interval (CI) of the difference. The rela-
tive change from baseline (MRV measurement) at Day 
14-21 was also analyzed using an analysis of covariance 
(ANCOVA) model with treatment group and stratum as 
factors and baseline measurement as a covariate. The 
composite of recurrent DVT, PE, or VTE-related death 
was summarized by treatment, and a 95% CI was gener-
ated for the difference between the two groups for the 
mITT analysis set. 
Of a total trial population of 85 patients, 56 were ran-
domized to edoxaban monotherapy and 29 to a parenteral 
anticoagulant 'bridge' (with unfractionated heparin or 
LMWH) to warfarin (Figure 1). One patient randomized 
to parenteral anticoagulation as a 'bridge' to warfarin did 
not receive the assigned therapy due to withdrawal of 
consent. 
Seven individuals in the edoxaban monotherapy group 
and two in the warfarin group did not have a Day 14-21 
MRV assessment (resulting in 49 in the edoxaban group 
and 26 in the parenteral anticoagulant 'bridge' to warfarin 
group). Three patients (one in the edoxaban monotherapy 
group and two in the parenteral anticoagulant 'bridge' to 
warfarin group) no longer had visible thrombus at the 
time of the baseline MRV, despite having DVT visualized 
on compression venous ultrasound at the time of diagno-
sis (all index DVTs were adjudicated by a blinded 
reviewer). Therefore, the primary MRV variable was 
reported for 72 subjects in total (48 in the edoxaban mon-
otherapy group and 24 in the parenteral anticoagulant 
'bridge' to warfarin group) for the mITT and per protocol 
analyses. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Baseline demographics and clinical 
characteristics </p>

<p>Mean age was 55.6 years in the edoxaban monotherapy 
group and 53.1 years in the parenteral anticoagulant 
'bridge' to warfarin group (Table 1). Among patients 
randomized to edoxaban monotherapy, two patients 
(3.6%) met criteria for the prespecified dose reduction. 
Two additional patients (3.6%) in the edoxaban monother-
apy group required post-randomization dose reduction 
because of concomitant P-glycoprotein (P-gp) inhibitor 
administration. 
DVT was unprovoked (idiopathic) in 52% of patients 
randomized to edoxaban monotherapy and in 64% of 
those assigned to LMWH or unfractionated heparin as a 
'bridge' to warfarin (Table 2). The mean time from symp-
tom onset to randomization was similar in the two groups 
(4.7 days vs 4.8 days). Anticoagulation was started within 
48 hours of randomization in nearly 90% of patients in 
both groups. 
Mean and median times within the therapeutic range for 
the INR in patients assigned to LMWH or unfractionated 
heparin as a 'bridge' to oral anticoagulation with warfarin 
were 60.9% and 64.5%, respectively. </p>

<p>MRV-determined change in thrombus 
volume </p>

<p>Baseline mean total thrombus volume measured by MRV 
was smaller in the edoxaban monotherapy group compared 
with the parenteral anticoagulant 'bridge' to warfarin group 
(6994 cm 3 vs 12,683 cm 3 ). The least squares mean change 
in thrombus volume from baseline to Day 14-21 was </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and baseline characteristics. </p>

<p>Variable 
Edoxaban n = 56 
LMWH or unfractionated 
heparin/warfarin n = 28 </p>

<p>Mean age ± SD, years 
55.6 ± 14.1 
53.1 ± 12 
Male, n (%) 
41 (73.2) 
21 (75) 
Race, n (%) 
Caucasian 
43 (76.8) 
21 (92.9) 
Black 
11 (19.6) 
2 (7.1) 
Other 
2 (3.6) 
0 (0) 
Met criteria for dose reduction at randomization, n (%) 
2 (3.6) 
2 (7.1) 
Weight ⩽ 60 kg 
1 (1.8) 
1 (3.6) 
CrCl ⩾ 30 to ⩽ 50 ml/min 
1 (1.8) 
1 (3.6) 
Pulmonary disease, n (%) 
16 (28.6) 
7 (25) 
Recent bone fracture, n (%) 
14 (25) 
6 (21.4) 
Active tobacco use, n (%) 
12 (21.4) 
5 (17.9) 
History of cancer, n (%) 
10 (17.9) 
3 (10.7) 
Cardiovascular disease, n (%) 
9 (16.1) 
4 (14.3) 
Concomitant antiplatelet therapy, n (%) 
9 (16.1) 
1 (3.6) 
Liver disease, n (%) 
7 (12.5) 
4 (14.3) 
Renal disease, n (%) 
6 (10.7) 
1 (3.6) 
P-gp inhibitors requiring edoxaban dose reduction, n 
(%) </p>

<p>2 (3.6) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>LMWH, low-molecular weight heparin; SD, standard deviation; CrCl, creatinine clearance; P-gp, P-glycoprotein. </p>

<p>Piazza et al. </p>



<p>-50.1% for the edoxaban monotherapy group and -58.9% 
for the warfarin group, with a difference in means of 8.8% 
(95% confidence interval (CI), -12.7, 30.2) in the mITT 
analysis (Table 3). An example of MRV-assessed thrombus 
volume reduction of 60% from baseline to follow-up in a 
patient with acute DVT treated with edoxaban monother-
apy is shown in Figure 2. There was no difference in the 
change in thrombus volume between the mITT and the per 
protocol analyses. In the mITT analysis, thrombus volume 
decreased from baseline to Day 14-21 in 81.6% of patients 
in the edoxaban monotherapy group and in 92.3% in the 
warfarin group (Table 4). Thrombus extension was observed 
in eight patients in the edoxaban monotherapy group and in 
none in the warfarin group. Of note, in six of these eight 
patients, the initial DVTs were very small at baseline 
(&lt; 0.05 cm 3 ) with relatively small changes in absolute vol-
ume at Day 14-21. 
We performed a reproducibility analysis limited to the 
three highest-enrolling centers and found no difference in 
the primary efficacy end point. </p>

<p>Secondary efficacy outcomes </p>

<p>Decreased thrombotic burden, defined as any decrease in 
thrombus volume on MRV and no adjudicated recurrent 
VTE, was observed in 81.6% of patients in the edoxaban 
monotherapy group and 88.5% of patients in the warfarin 
group (Table 4). Three patients (6.3%) in the edoxaban 
monotherapy group and two (8.3%) in the warfarin group 
had resolution of the entire thrombus volume. The mean 
change in the eTRIS-DVT total score from baseline to Day 
14-21 was identical in both treatment groups (-0.8). The 
mean percent change in the eTRIS volumetric DVT total 
score from baseline to Day 14-21 was -42.1% in the 
edoxaban monotherapy group and -40.3% in the warfarin 
group. </p>

<p>In the mITT analysis, adjudicated recurrent VTE 
occurred in two patients in the edoxaban monotherapy 
group (3.6%) and in one patient in the warfarin group 
(3.6%). In the edoxaban monotherapy group, one patient 
suffered a non-fatal PE, and one developed a new DVT. 
One patient in the warfarin group suffered a non-fatal PE. </p>

<p>Safety outcomes </p>

<p>Adjudicated bleeding events during the on-treatment period 
occurred in 17.9% of patients in the edoxaban monotherapy 
group and 17.9% in the warfarin group (Table 5). Major or 
clinically relevant non-major bleeding occurred in 5.4% of 
patients in the edoxaban monotherapy group and 7.1% in 
the warfarin group. No serious adverse events were attrib-
uted to edoxaban. However, one warfarin patient suffered a 
fatal subdural hematoma on Day 76. Adjudicated clinically 
relevant non-major or nuisance bleeding events in the ini-
tial 10 days of treatment were more common for patients 
in the edoxaban monotherapy group (n = 7) than for those 
in the parenteral anticoagulant 'bridge' to warfarin group 
(n = 2) (12.5% vs 7.1%). 
One patient in the edoxaban monotherapy group suffered 
non-fatal MI, and another suffered a non-fatal stroke. The 
non-fatal MI occurred in an 82-year-old man with known 
coronary artery disease, obesity, hypertension, hypercholes-
terolemia, diabetes, peripheral artery disease, aortic steno-
sis, renal artery stenosis, chronic iron deficiency anemia, 
and heart failure on Day 4 of edoxaban therapy. The acute 
ischemic stroke occurred in a 63-year-old man with widely 
metastatic pancreatic cancer on Day 22 of edoxaban ther-
apy, and was not in the setting of atrial fibrillation. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Our aim was to evaluate the feasibility of MRV for compar-
ing change in thrombus volume between an oral regimen of </p>

<p>Table 2. Clinical characteristics of deep vein thrombosis (DVT). </p>

<p>Variable 
Edoxaban n = 56 
LMWH or unfractionated 
heparin/warfarin n = 28 </p>

<p>Provoked DVT, n (%) 
27 (48.2) 
10 (35.7) 
Unprovoked DVT, n (%) 
29 (51.8) 
18 (64.3) 
Mean days between onset of symptoms and randomization ± SD 
4.7 ± 1.9 
4.8 ± 1.8 
Anticoagulation started within 48 hours of randomization, n (%) 
51 (91.1) 
25 (89.3) </p>

<p>LMWH, low-molecular weight heparin; SD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 3. Change in thrombus volume as measured by magnetic resonance venography (MRV) based on modified intention-to-treat 
analysis. </p>

<p>Edoxaban (n = 48) 
LMWH or unfractionated heparin/warfarin (n = 24) </p>

<p>Baseline 
Day 14-21 
% change 
Baseline 
Day 14-21 
% change </p>

<p>Mean total thrombus 
volume ± SD, mm 3 </p>

<p>6994.0 ± 9053.6 4055.5 ± 6796.8 −46.6 ± 45.53 
12,683.1 ± 13,572.1 7952.9 ± 11,413.4 −51.4 ± 33.0 </p>

<p>Least squares (geometric) 
mean change (95% CI) </p>

<p>−50.1 (−76.0, −24.3) 
−58.9 (−87.1, −30.8) </p>

<p>Difference between the 
means (95% CI) </p>

<p>8.8 (−12.7, 30.2) </p>

<p>LMWH, low-molecular weight heparin; SD, standard deviation; CI, confidence interval. </p>



<p>Vascular Medicine 21(4) </p>

<p>once daily edoxaban 90 mg for 10 days followed by 60 mg 
versus conventional anticoagulation with a parenteral 
anticoagulant as a 'bridge' to warfarin. Overall thrombus 
volume regression was similar in both groups. However, a 
subset of patients in the edoxaban monotherapy group </p>

<p>(16.7%) experienced an increase in thrombus volume on 
follow-up MRV. This observation suggests that initial par-
enteral anticoagulation may be important for treatment with 
edoxaban. In the HOKUSAI-VTE trial, parenteral antico-
agulation followed by oral edoxaban 12 was shown to have </p>

<p>Table 4. Thrombotic burden as measured by magnetic resonance venography (MRV) in the modified intention-to-treat analysis. </p>

<p>Edoxaban (n = 56) 
LMWH or unfractionated heparin/warfarin (n = 28) </p>

<p>Freedom from adjudicated recurrent VTE, n (%) 
54 (96.4) 
27 (96.4) 
Improvement in thrombus volume a , n (%) 
40 (81.6) 
24 (92.3) 
Improved thrombotic burden b , n (%) 
40 (81.6) 
23 (88.5) 
Thrombus extension c , n (%) 
8 (16.7) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>LMWH, low-molecular weight heparin; VTE, venous thromboembolism; MRV, magnetic resonance venography. 
a Improvement in thrombus volume and thrombotic burden is based on number of subjects with MRV assessment at baseline and Day 14-21; n = 48 
for the edoxaban monotherapy group and n = 24 for the parenteral anticoagulant 'bridge' to warfarin group. 
b Improved thrombotic burden = any improvement in thrombus volume as measured by MRV and no adjudicated recurrent VTE (deep vein thrombo-
sis, non-fatal pulmonary embolism, or VTE-related death). Based on number of subjects with MRV assessment at baseline and Day 14-21, n = 48 for 
the edoxaban monotherapy group and n = 24 for the parenteral anticoagulant 'bridge' to warfarin group. 
c Based on number of subjects with MRV assessment at baseline and Day 14-21, n = 48 for the edoxaban monotherapy group and n = 24 for the 
parenteral anticoagulant 'bridge' to warfarin group. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Thrombus volume reduction of 60% from baseline to follow-up as measured by magnetic resonance venography (MRV) in 
a patient with acute deep vein thrombosis (arrows) randomized to treatment with edoxaban. </p>

<p>Piazza et al. </p>



<p>similar efficacy and improved safety compared with paren-
teral anticoagulant as a 'bridge' to warfarin for the treat-
ment of acute DVT. 
MRV is a reproducible and quantitative tool for assess-
ment of changes in lower extremity venous thrombus 
volume. 7 We believe this is the first study to evaluate 
change in thrombus volume with MRV in this patient popu-
lation. Compared with venous ultrasound, MRV provides a 
more comprehensive and contiguous assessment of the 
presence of thrombus as well as volumetric analysis. Unlike 
conventional venography, MRV is non-invasive. Compared 
with CT venography, MRV avoids ionizing radiation and 
iodinated contrast. Thus, MRV shows promise as a research 
tool. Advanced non-contrast and non-gadolinium-based 
MRI techniques hold promise as research tools for throm-
bus imaging and clinical diagnosis of DVT. 13,14 </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>Our study had limitations. Fifteen percent of patients did 
not have a complete set of MRV examinations performed 
within the Day 14-21 interval. This incomplete follow-up 
may compromise the primary efficacy outcome analysis 
and interpretation. Our study stopped short of the planned 
90-patient enrollment due to slow patient accrual. Lack of 
statistical power may have impacted our ability to detect a 
difference, in either direction, in thrombus volume as 
assessed by MRV as well as clinical outcomes. Despite ran-
domization, the two study groups demonstrated important 
differences, most notably in baseline thrombus volume. 
The difference in initial thrombus burden may have biased 
our analysis of the change in thrombus volume. </p>

<p>Strengths </p>

<p>Our study had certain strengths. We utilized quantitative 
MRV as a clinical research tool among many different 
types of study sites. We evaluated a novel oral monother-
apy dosing regimen for edoxaban in a rigorous randomized 
controlled trial setting for the treatment of acute sympto-
matic DVT. Finally, we obtained clinical follow-up in 
96.5% of study patients. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>MRV can assess change in thrombus volume in patients 
randomized to two different anticoagulant regimens. The </p>

<p>subset of patients in the edoxaban monotherapy group that 
experienced an increase in thrombus volume on follow-up 
MRV suggests that initial parenteral anticoagulation may 
be important for treatment with edoxaban. </p>

<p>Declaration of conflicting interests </p>

<p>Dr Piazza receives research grant support from Daiichi Sankyo, 
EKOS, a BTG International Group company, Bristol Myers 
Squibb, and Janssen. Dr Mani receives consulting fees from 
Tursiop Inc. and research grant support from Novartis AG and 
Daiichi Sankyo. Dr Goldhaber receives research grant support 
from Daiichi Sankyo, EKOS, a BTG International Group com-
pany, Bristol Myers Squibb, and Janssen. Drs Grosso, Mercuri, 
Lanz, Hsu, and Chinigo and Mr Schussler receive salary from 
Daiichi Sankyo. Drs Ritchie, Nadar, Cannon, Pullman, Concha, 
Schul, and Fayad receive research grant support from Daiichi 
Sankyo. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support 
for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: 
research grant from Daiichi Sankyo. </p>

<p>Role of sponsor </p>

<p>The sponsor of the study had no role in the data interpretation. 
GP, VM, SZG, and ZAF had full access to the data and had the 
final responsibility for the decision to submit for publication. </p>

<p>Supplementary material </p>

<p>The supplementary material is available at http://vmj.sagepub.com </p>



<p>Table 5. Adjudicated bleeding events in the safety analysis during the on-treatment period. a </p>

<p>Edoxaban (n = 56) 
LMWH or unfractionated heparin/warfarin (n = 28) </p>

<p>Adjudicated confirmed bleeding events, n (%) 
10 (17.9) 
5 (17.9) 
Major or clinically relevant non-major bleeding, n (%) 
3 (5.4) 
2 (7.1) 
Major bleeding, n (%) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Fatal bleeding, n (%) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Intracranial hemorrhage, n (%) 
0 (0) 
0 (0) 
Clinically relevant non-major bleeding, n (%) 
3 (5.4) 
2 (7.1) 
Nuisance bleeding, n (%) 
9 (16.1) 
3 (10.7) </p>

<p>LMWH, low-molecular weight heparin. 
a The median duration of treatment was 91 days and 88.5 days in the edoxaban monotherapy and the parenteral anticoagulant 'bridge' to warfarin 
groups, respectively. The median duration of study drug exposure was 90.5 days and 86 days in the edoxaban monotherapy and the parenteral 
anticoagulant 'bridge' to warfarin groups, respectively. </p>



<p>Vascular Medicine 21(4) </p>



</text></tei>