<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4478301" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background: We have previously shown that recurrent arterial ischaemic stroke (AIS) in chil-</p>

<p>dren with cerebral arteriopathy is associated with increased circulating endothelial cells and 
endothelial microparticles, consistent with ongoing endothelial injury. To date, however, little 
is known about endothelial repair responses in childhood AIS. We examined the relationship 
between the number and function of circulating endothelial progenitor cells (EPC), the levels 
of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) and AIS recurrence. Methods: Flow cytometry 
was used to identify peripheral blood mononuclear cells positive for CD34/kinase insert do-
main-containing receptor (KDR). In a subgroup of patients (5 in each group selected at ran-
dom), monocytic EPC function was assessed by colony-forming unit (EPC-CFU) capacity and 
incorporation into endothelial cell networks in Matrigel. BDNF was measured using ELISA. 
Results: Thirty-five children, aged 12 years (range: 5-16.5; 9 males), with AIS and cerebral ar-</p>

<p>teriopathy were studied; 10 had recurrent AIS. CD34+/KDR+ cells were significantly higher in 
recurrent AIS compared to non-recurrent AIS patients (p = 0.005) and controls (p = 0.0002). 
EPC-CFU and EPC incorporation into endothelial cell networks were significantly reduced in 
recurrent compared to non-recurrent AIS patients (p = 0.04 and p = 0.01, respectively). Levels 
of BDNF were significantly higher in recurrent compared to non-recurrent AIS patients (p = 
0.0008) and controls (p = 0.0002). Conclusions: Children with recurrent AIS and cerebral ar-
teriopathy had increased circulating CD34+/KDR+ cells and BDNF consistent with an endo-
thelial repair response. However, EPC function was impaired. Future studies are needed to 
examine whether suboptimal endothelial repair contributes to childhood AIS recurrence. </p>

<p>Abnormalities or arteriopathies of the cervical or intracranial circulation are implicated 
in the aetiology and recurrence of childhood arterial ischaemic stroke (AIS) [1] . We have 
previously shown that in children with AIS associated with arteriopathy, indices of endo-
thelial injury (circulating endothelial cells and endothelial microparticles) are higher in those 
with a recurrent compared with a monophasic disease course suggesting that persistent 
endothelial injury could contribute to recurrent AIS [2] . Similar to other vascular disorders, 
it is likely that a series of endothelial repair responses are mobilized in response to this 
ongoing vascular injury to re-establish endothelial integrity [3] . For instance, circulating 
CD34+/kinase insert domain-containing receptor (KDR)+ cells are considered to play a key 
role as endothelial progenitor cells (EPC) in vascular maintenance and repair, and a reduced 
number has been proposed to result in endothelial dysfunction [4] . Monocyte-derived EPC 
are likely to have an additional role since a reduced function of these cells negatively influ-
ences their restorative capacities [3, 4] . Notably, previous studies have suggested that EPC 
release brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), and they have implicated this in neuronal 
protection and neurogenesis following ischaemic stroke [5] . 
We hypothesized that, in addition to persistent endothelial injury, recurrence of childhood 
AIS associated with cerebral arteriopathy is also characterized by impaired vascular repair 
responses that influence neurotrophic support to the ischaemic brain. The aim of this study 
was therefore to compare the number of circulating CD34+/KDR+ cells, the functional prop-
erties of monocyte-derived EPC, and the levels of BDNF in children with AIS associated with 
cerebral arteriopathy with and without recurrence. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods </p>

<p>A cross-sectional study was conducted of children aged &gt;28 days with AIS (acute focal 
neurological deficit attributable to cerebral infarction in a corresponding arterial distri-
bution) and imaging evidence of cerebral/cervical arteriopathy presenting to the Great 
Ormond Street Hospital NHS Foundation Trust from October 2007 to January 2012. The study 
had Institutional Ethics Committee approval. Informed consent/assent was obtained from 
the study participants/parents. Cerebral/cervical arteriopathy was defined as focal or 
segmental stenosis or occlusion, with regular or irregular abnormalities of the arterial wall 
and categorized according to published consensus definitions [6, 7] . Magnetic resonance 
imaging (MRI) and magnetic resonance angiography (MRA) were performed on a 1.5-tesla 
magnetic resonance scanner using a standard imaging protocol, including T2-weighted turbo 
spin-echo imaging in the axial plane, fluid-attenuated inversion recovery (FLAIR) sequence 
in the coronal plane, T1-weighted spin-echo imaging in the sagittal plane, and three-dimen-
sional short-echo time-of-flight MRA of the circle of Willis. In the &lt;2-year age group, the axial 
T2-weighted imaging was replaced by a double-echo short tau inversion recovery imaging 
sequence, and the coronal FLAIR sequence was not acquired. Catheter cerebral arterio-
graphy was performed at the clinician's discretion. Blood was taken prior to cerebral arterio-
graphy to avoid catheter-induced endothelial injury. All children underwent standardized 
investigations for AIS risk factors (online suppl. material; for all online material, see www. 
karger.com/doi/10.1159/000381963). The patients were categorized into 2 groups 
according to AIS recurrence (&gt;1 week after the initial clinical event). We recruited 25 healthy 
controls aged 11.5 years (range: 2-16; 7 males) undergoing minor surgical procedures (pre-
operative blood samples obtained) with no identifiable chronic illnesses. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2015;5:68-74 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000381963 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Eleftheriou et al.: Endothelial Repair in Childhood Arterial Ischaemic Stroke with 
Cerebral Arteriopathy </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2015 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>Flow Cytometric Identification of CD34+/KDR+ Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells </p>

<p>CD34+/KDR+ peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) were identified using flow 
cytometry as previously described [2] . Briefly, PBMC were isolated by density centrifugation 
(Lymphoprep TM , Axis Shield, Dundee, UK). After purification with 3 washing steps, the cells 
were resuspended at a concentration of 2 × 10 
6 cells/ml and 50 μl of Fc receptor blocking 
agent added per millilitre before incubating with KDR (clone KDR2, conjugated with biotin 
followed by streptavidin FITC; Sigma-Aldrich) and CD34 (clone 8G12, PerCP-conjugated; 
Becton Dickinson) antibodies. While assessing EPC numbers, we adjusted for their low event 
rate in flow cytometry by using IgG isotype controls for all fluorochromes (BD Biosciences). 
After washing, we counted the cells with FACSCalibur (BD Biosciences) and gated the mono-
nuclear cells identifying CD34+/KDR+ cells. </p>

<p>Colony-Forming Unit Counts </p>

<p>EPC colony-forming units (CFUs) were assessed as previously described [3, 8] . Briefly, 
PBMC were isolated by density centrifugation (Lymphoprep). After purification with 3 
washing steps, 2 × 10 6 PBMC were plated on fibronectin-coated 24-well plates. The cells were </p>

<p>Table 1. Study population characteristics </p>

<p>Demographics 
AIS recurrence (n = 10) 
AIS no recurrence (n = 25) 
p value </p>

<p>Sex (M:F) 
6:4 
16:9 
1 
Median age, years 
8.2 (0.9 -15.4) 
9.4 (2.7 -17.4) 
0.681 
Median time from event to 
evaluation, months 
7 (6 -13) 
11 (6 -24) 
0.1 
Clinical features 
Focal neurological deficit 
10 (100) 
25 (100) 
1.0000 
Diffuse neurological deficits 
7 (70) 
2 (8) 
0.0005 
Sebire et al. [6] classification of 
cerebral arteriopathy </p>

<p>n = 3 arterial dissection (30) 
n = 16 TCA/FCA (64) 
n/a 
n = 1 PACNS (10) 
n = 4 arterial dissection (16) 
n = 1 PVA (10) 
n = 3 PVA (12) 
n = 1 moyamoya (10) 
n = 2 moyamoya (8) 
n = 4 unclassified (40) 
Median ESR, mm/h 
(normal range: 0 -10) 
5.4 (1 -12) 
6.6 (1 -28) 
0.561 
Median CRP, mg/l 
(normal range: &lt;10) 
5 (3 -16) 
5 (3 -6) 
0.873 
MRI 
Multifocal and bilateral lesions 
9 (90) 
5 (20) 
0.0002 
MRA 
Multifocal and bilateral lesions 
9 (90) 
5 (20) 
0.0002 
Anterior and posterior circulation 7 (70) 
2 (8) 
0.0005 
Collaterals 
4 (40) 
2 (8) 
0.0400 
Treatment 
Aspirin 
10 (100) 
25 (100) 
1 
Anticoagulation 
(heparin/warfarin) 
3 (30) 
5 (20) 
0.6614 
Corticosteroids 
4 (40) 
0 (0) 
0.0040 
Cyclophosphamide 
2 (20) 
0 (0) 
0.0756 
Surgical revascularization 
2 (20) 
4 (16) 
1 </p>

<p>Figures in parentheses are percentages or ranges. Focal neurological deficits included hemiparesis, facial 
weakness and hemisensory loss. Diffuse neurological deficits included neurocognitive dysfunction, personality 
changes and concentration difficulties. M = Male; F = female; TCA = transient cerebral arteriopathy; FCA = focal 
cerebral arteriopathy; PACNS = primary angiitis of the central nervous system; ESR = erythrocyte sedimentation 
rate; CRP = C-reactive protein; MTHFR = methylene-tetrahydrofolate reductase; PVA = post-varicella arteriopathy; 
n/a = not applicable. p values were calculated using Fisher's exact test for categorical data and the Mann-Whitney 
U test for continuous variables. p values &lt;0.05 (two-sided) were regarded as significant. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2015;5:68-74 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000381963 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Eleftheriou et al.: Endothelial Repair in Childhood Arterial Ischaemic Stroke with 
Cerebral Arteriopathy </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2015 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>cultured and maintained in EGM-2 culture medium supplemented with growth factors as per 
the manufacturer's recommendations (PromoCell), plus 20% foetal calf serum and 40 ng/ml 
of vascular endothelial growth factor. After 4 days of culture, the non-adherent cells were 
removed by washing with phosphate-buffered saline. The culture medium was changed to 
maintain the cells in culture until day 7. CFUs were defined as a central core of rounded cells 
surrounded by elongating and spindle-shaped cells and were counted after 7 days in culture. 
Colonies were counted manually in a minimum of 2 wells of each 24-well plate by 2 inde-
pendent observers who were unaware of clinical profiles, and the results were expressed as 
average numbers of CFUs per well (online suppl. fig. 1). In selected samples, the endothelial 
phenotype was confirmed using endothelial-specific indicators, i.e., uptake of DiI-LDL, 
staining for UEA-1 lectin as previously reported [3, 8] . </p>

<p>Matrigel Plate Assay </p>

<p>In 5 subjects per group, Matrigel assays were employed to examine the ability of putative 
EPC to incorporate into endothelial capillary networks. Growth factor-reduced Matrigel 
Matrix (Becton Dickinson Labware) was thawed and placed in 96-well plates at 37 ° C for 30 
min to allow solidification. Putative EPC were labelled with 2 μg/ml of DiI-LDL to distinguish 
them from human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVEC) and were then coplated (3,000 
cells/well) with HUVEC (10,000 cells/well) on top of a solidified Matrigel layer and cultured 
at 37 ° C for 18-20 h with EGM-2 medium. Incorporation of EPC into capillary networks of 
HUVEC on Matrigel was examined with fluorescence microscopy. Five independent fields 
were assessed for each well and the mean numbers of EPC incorporated into the HUVEC 
capillary networks was determined (online suppl. fig. 2). </p>

<p>Brain-Derived Neurotrophic Factor </p>

<p>Blood was collected into 3.2% trisodium citrate and centrifuged twice at 5,000 g for 
5 min each to obtain platelet-poor plasma. BDNF levels were measured by sandwich ELISA 
using a commercially available kit from RayBio Systems Europe. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Numeric results were summarized as median and range. The Kruskal-Wallis test followed 
by the Mann-Whitney U test was applied to compare experimental laboratory markers and 
Fisher's exact test for categorical data. Binary logistic regression examined the relationship 
between numbers of CD34+/KDR+ cells and recurrence. p values &lt;0.05 (two-sided) were 
regarded as significant. Statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">17</rs>. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Patient Characteristics </p>

<p>We studied 35 children aged 12 years (range: 5-16.5; 9 males). These were a subgroup 
of the 46 previously described patients from a linked study [1] , where sufficient blood was 
available to undertake the aforementioned assays. The median body mass index was 15 
(range: 14-18). None of the children had hyperlipidaemia, arterial hypertension or received 
statins. Clinical characteristics of the study populations are summarized in table 1 . Ten 
children had AIS recurrence and 25 had a single event. Evaluation took place at a median of 
7 months (range: 6-13) following recent AIS for those children with AIS recurrence compared 
to 11 months (range: 6-24) for those without recurrence (p = 0.1000). All those with recur-
rence had progression of previously identified arteriopathy; they more commonly had diffuse 
neurological deficits (p = 0.0005) and multifocal, bilateral lesions on MRI (p = 0.0002). </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2015;5:68-74 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000381963 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Eleftheriou et al.: Endothelial Repair in Childhood Arterial Ischaemic Stroke with 
Cerebral Arteriopathy </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2015 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>Circulating CD34+/KDR+ Cells Are Increased but EPC Function Is Impaired in Recurrent AIS </p>

<p>CD34+/KDR+ cell counts were significantly higher in patients with AIS recurrence (0.1% 
of gated PBMC, range: 0.02-0.3) compared to those with no recurrence (0.03% of gated PBMC, 
range: 0.01-0.09, p = 0.005; controls: 0.01% of gated PBMC, range: 0-0.05, p = 0.0002; fig. 1 a). 
In binary logistic regression analysis, after correction for age/gender/time to sampling from 
recent AIS, higher numbers of circulating CD34+/KDR+ cells were significantly related to 
recurrence (odds ratio: 1.88; 95% confidence interval: 1.1-2.1, p = 0.03). In contrast, EPC-CFUs 
were reduced in children with AIS recurrence (2 CFUs/well, range: 1-2) compared to children 
with no recurrence (6 CFUs/well, range: 3-9, p = 0.04; controls: 14 CFUs/well, range: 4-17, 
p = 0.03; fig. 1 b). Furthermore, incorporation of EPC into HUVEC vascular networks in Matrigel 
was decreased in children with recurrent AIS (193 cells/mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, range: 0-210) compared to 
those with non-recurrent AIS (396 cells/mm 2 , range: 202-596, p = 0.01; controls: 3,636 cells/ 
mm 
2 , range: 1,478-4,478, p = 0.007; fig. 1 c). </p>

<p>Levels of BDNF Are Higher in Children with Recurrent AIS </p>

<p>Levels of BDNF were increased in children with recurrence (24 ng/ml, range: 15-41) 
compared to those with a single event (14.50 ng/ml, range: 2.4-22, p = 0.0008; controls: 5 
ng/ml, range: 1.8-8.1, p = 0.0002; fig. 1 d). </p>

<p>0.44 
0.39 
0.34 
0.29 
0.24 
0.19 
0.14 
0.09 
0.04 </p>

<p>AIS 
recurrence 
PBMCs expressing 
CD34/KDR (%) </p>

<p>AIS no 
recurrence </p>

<p>Healthy 
controls </p>

<p>** 
*** </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
AIS 
recurrence </p>

<p>EPC-CFU count </p>

<p>AIS no 
recurrence </p>

<p>Healthy 
controls </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4,000 </p>

<p>3,000 </p>

<p>2,000 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>0 
AIS 
recurrence 
EPC incorporation (per mm 2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>AIS no 
recurrence </p>

<p>Healthy 
controls </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
AIS 
recurrence </p>

<p>BDNF (ng/ml) </p>

<p>AIS no 
recurrence </p>

<p>Healthy 
controls </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Circulating EPC and BDNF in children with AIS. a CD34+/KDR+ cell counts were significantly higher 
in patients with AIS recurrence compared to those with no recurrence (p = 0.005) and controls (p = 0.0002). 
b EPC-CFUs were reduced in children with AIS recurrence compared to children with no recurrence (p = 
0.04) and controls (p = 0.03). c Incorporation of EPC into HUVEC vascular networks in Matrigel was de-
creased in recurrent AIS compared to non-recurrent AIS (p = 0.01) and controls (p = 0.007). d Levels of BDNF 
were increased in children with recurrence compared to those with a single event (p = 0.0008) and controls 
(p = 0.0002). * p &lt; 0.05; * * p &lt; 0.005; * * * p &lt; 0.0005, with Mann-Whitney U test. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2015;5:68-74 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000381963 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Eleftheriou et al.: Endothelial Repair in Childhood Arterial Ischaemic Stroke with 
Cerebral Arteriopathy </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2015 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We have demonstrated important differences in endothelial repair mechanisms between 
children with recurrence of AIS associated with cerebral arteriopathy. While CD34+/KDR+ 
cells were increased in the recurrence group, the angiogenic function of monocytic EPC was 
impaired. These novel exploratory observations could provide an important insight into the 
pathogenesis of childhood AIS. 
Mobilization of CD34+/KDR+ cells in response to ongoing tissue ischaemia could be an 
attempt to mediate vascular repair, and hence higher levels of these cells may reflect the 
extent of ischaemic brain injury. In conditions of acute vascular ischaemia, an increase in the 
number of circulating CD34+/KDR+ cells has been observed in association with a concom-
itant increase in levels of EPC-mobilizing factors, such as vascular endothelial growth factor 
and stromal cell-derived factor-1, suggesting a direct causal relationship [4] . In addition, 
recent studies proposed that CD34+/KDR+ cells are generated from CD34+ cells at platelet-
rich sites of vascular injury, thus reflecting the plasticity of CD34+ cells and their capacity to 
respond to and be taken up into ischaemic lesional tissue [9, 10] . These responses to isch-
aemic insult may still be relevant to patients with recurrent AIS sometime after the initial 
insult, as we have detected ongoing endothelial injury many months after an acute clinical 
event [1] . 
Our preliminary observations are in keeping with similar studies in systemic vasculitis 
that suggest that attempts at endothelial repair may be thwarted (for reasons as yet uniden-
tified) in children with the most severe vasculitis [11] . The same may also be true of children 
with recurrent AIS. As BDNF mobilizes haematopoietic progenitor cells and promotes revas-
cularization in ischaemic injury [5, 12] , the increased levels we noted may represent a 
continuous effort to support endothelial repair and neuronal survival in children with 
recurrent AIS. It is uncertain which factors might result in the decreased circulatory EPC 
angiogenic function we observed. Possibilities include: increased uptake from the circulation 
of the most angiogenic active EPC into areas of cerebral ischaemia, inherently impaired angio-
genic potential in children prone to AIS recurrence, or another as yet undefined neuro-immu-
nological pathway secondary to brain injury adversely influencing angiogenic responses. 
Larger longitudinal studies of CD34+/KDR+ cells and EPC function over time and in response 
to therapy (aspirin, anticoagulation and/or immunosuppression) are now urgently needed. 
We regard our findings as exploratory since the cross-sectional nature of this small study 
precludes any causal effect to be determined. In addition, although treatments were within 
recommended clinical guidelines, there remained some therapeutic heterogeneity. The 
timing of sampling from the index AIS was not standardized in our study. We did, however, 
perform binary logistic regression analysis after correction for this potentially important 
confounder and found that higher numbers of circulating CD34+/KDR+ cells were still signif-
icantly related to AIS recurrence. The effect of immunosuppression on endothelial repair 
responses was not formally assessed in our study; future longitudinal studies of EPC changes 
with time after the initial cerebrovascular event and in response to therapy would be of 
considerable interest in paediatric AIS and could enhance our understanding of the effect of 
immunosuppression on EPC biology. We were underpowered to perform formal subgroup 
analyses of the various arteriopathies studied herein; larger multicentre prospective studies 
to establish the specificity of these vascular repair responses across different vascular pathol-
ogies leading to AIS are now warranted. 
In summary, children with recurrent AIS associated with cerebral arteriopathy had 
increased numbers of circulating CD34+/KDR+ cells but impaired EPC angiogenic function. 
Whether this contributes to the vascular dysfunction associated with AIS recurrence now 
requires further investigation. </p>



<p>Cerebrovasc Dis Extra 2015;5:68-74 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1159/000381963 </p>

<p>E X T R A </p>

<p>Eleftheriou et al.: Endothelial Repair in Childhood Arterial Ischaemic Stroke with 
Cerebral Arteriopathy </p>

<p>www.karger.com/cee </p>

<p>© 2015 S. Karger AG, Basel </p>



<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>Dr. Eleftheriou received funding from the Action Medical Research (clinical research 
fellowship). </p>

<p>Disclosure Statement </p>

<p>The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

</text></tei>