<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4138420" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Background: Nitric oxide plays a major role in increasing uterine blood flow during 
the luteal phase and early pregnancy. This study was done to compare uterine artery 
and sub-endometrial blood flow indices during the luteal phase between patients 
with unexplained recurrent abortion and fertile women and also to evaluate the ef-
fects of nitric oxide donors on blood flow indices in the abortion group. 
Methods: The study included a control group of 30 primiparae who had normal vag-
inal delivery and no history of abortion and an abortion group of 30 nulliparous 
women with history of two or more unexplained recurrent abortions. Transvaginal 
three-dimensional pulsed color Doppler ultrasound was done on days 21-23 of the 
cycle to measure uterine artery resistance and pulsation indices and the subendome-
trial vascular, flow and vascular-flow indices. Isosorbide mononitrate 20 mg tablet 
was administered vaginally in the abortion group and blood flow indices were meas-
ured again after two hours. The Student t-test and the paired t-test were used for 
analysis of results and a p-value of ≤0.05 was considered significant. 
Results: Patients with unexplained recurrent abortion had significantly higher uter-
ine artery resistance and pulsation indices and lower sub-endometrial vascular, flow 
and vascular-flow index (p&lt;0.01-0.0001). Isosorbide mononitrite significantly de-
creased uterine artery and increased sub-endometrial blood flow indices (p&lt;0.001). 
Conclusion: Uterine artery and sub-endometrial blood flow decreased during the lu-
teal phase in patients with unexplained recurrent abortion. Nitric oxide donors in-
creased blood flow and may be of a therapeutic value. </p>

<p>of women (5) and the rest remain unexplained. 
Scientists (6) showed that during the luteal phase 
of normal menstrual cycle, uterine artery imped-
ance to blood flow decreases and there is an in-
crease in uterine and sub-endometrial blood flow 
which reaches its maximum level during the peri-
od of implantation. Other studies (7) showed that 
uterine artery perfusion regulates uterine receptiv-
ity, influences the success of implantation, main-
tains early pregnancy and that impaired uterine 
perfusion plays a central role in the pathogenesis </p>

<p>* Corresponding Author: 
Mohamed Abdel-Razik, 
Department of Obstetrics 
and Gynecology, Benha 
Faculty of Medicine, 
Egypt 
E-mail: 
mohamedabdelrazik@ 
hotmail.com </p>

<p>Received: Dec. 27, 2013 
Accepted: Jun. 24, 2014 </p>

<p>J Reprod Infertil, Vol 15, No 3, Jul-Sept 2014 </p>



<p>Abdel-Razik M, et al. JRI </p>

<p>of unexplained recurrent abortion (URA) (8). Past 
studies (9, 10) provide evidences that nitric oxide 
(NO) generated in vivo from the essential amino 
acid L-arginine by the vascular endothelium plays 
a major role in vascular smooth muscle relaxation. 
Subsequently, it results in a decrease in vascular 
resistance which leads to an increase in uterine 
artery blood flow observable in early pregnancy. 
Impaired L-arginine-nitric oxide pathway has 
been suggested to be a subtle cause of URA and 
treatment with nitric oxide donors is reported as a 
significant success in some studies (11-13). Based 
on these observations, an attempt was made to 
study uterine arteries and sub-endometrial blood 
flow during the luteal phase in normal fertile 
women and in patients with URA. Moreover, in 
this study, an investigation was carried out to find 
the effects of vaginal administration of isosorbide 
mononitrate (IMN) as a source of nitric oxide and 
a perfusion enhancer on uterine arteries and sub-
endometrial blood flow indices in patients with 
URA. </p>

<p>Methods 
The study was done during the period from Jan-
uary to November 2013 at Benha University Hos-
pital after approval of the ethical committee (Aus-
tralian New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry reg-
istration number: ACTRN 12614000069651) and 
informed consent was taken from every partici-
pant in two groups. The control group consisted of 
30 primiparae who had normal vaginal delivery 
and no history of abortion. The abortion group 
consisted of 30 nulliparae with history of two or 
more successive (2) URA which entails (1) pres-
ence of a normal uterine cavity by hysterography, 
no luteal phase defect (progesterone level &gt;10 ng/ 
ml), normal thyroid function tests (TSH, T3 and 
T4), normal levels of lupus anticoagulant meas-
ured by the activated partial thromboplastin time 
(32-43 seconds), normal levels of anticardiolipin 
IgG (&lt;20 GPL) and IgM (&lt;15 MPL) measured by 
ELISA and normal karyotyping (done for 10 cases 
with more than three successive abortions). Wom-
en using hormonal contraception or intrauterine 
device or treated with vasodilators were excluded. 
Vaginal ultrasound (Voluson, PRO V, GE Health 
Care USA.) was done on cycle days 21-23 using 
7.5 M. Hz probe; Transvaginal three-dimensional 
pulsed color Doppler ultrasound identified the 
uterine artery and three similar consecutive wave-
forms were displayed and the resistance index 
(RI) and the pulsation index (PI) were measured. </p>

<p>An area within 5 mm of the echogenic endometrial 
border was identified and the histogram and the 
virtual organ computer aided analysis (VOCAL) 
were used to measure the sub-endometrial vascu-
lar index (VI), the flow index (FI) and the vascu-
lar-flow index (VFI). Isosorbide mononitrate 
(IMN) 20 mg tablet (Effox, Mina Pharma Co, 
Egypt; under license of Schwartz Pharma, Ger-
many) was administered vaginally in the study 
group and blood flow indices were measured 
again after two hours. 
Statistical design: Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 16</rs>. The mean, standard deviation 
and the Student t test were used to compare blood 
flow indices in the control and abortion groups 
and the paired t-test was used for comparison of 
blood flow before and after administration of IMN 
in the abortion group. The p≤0.05 was considered 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>Results 
There was no significant difference between 
both groups regarding the mean age and the mean 
body mass index (p&gt;0.05). However, there was a 
significantly higher uterine artery RI and PI and 
significantly lower sub-endometrial VI, FI and 
VFI in the abortion group as compared to the con-
trol group (p&lt;0.01-0.0001). The results are shown 
in table 1. 
After administration of IMN in the abortion 
group, there was a significant decrease of uterine 
artery RI and PI and a significant increase in sub-
endometrial VI, FI and VFI (p&lt;0.001) as shown in 
table 2. </p>

<p>Table 1. Comparison between bio data, uterine artery and sub-endometrial 
blood flow indices in the control and the abortion groups </p>

<p>Variables 
Control (n=30) 
Mean±SD </p>

<p>Abortion (n=30) 
Mean±SD </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>25.88±3.33 
26.11±3.22 
0.3 </p>

<p>Body mass index </p>

<p>24.70±3.44 
23.52±1.21 
1.8 </p>

<p>Resistance index </p>

<p>0.69±0.22 
0.91±0.11 
4.9 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>Pulsation index </p>

<p>2.44±0.11 
2.88±0.66 
3.6 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>Vascular index </p>

<p>1.05±0.32 
0.56±0.22 
6.9 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>Flow index </p>

<p>12.33±4.90 
9.11±2.08 
3.3 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Vascular-flow index </p>

<p>0.21±0.01 
0.17±0.03 
6.9 </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p> *  p&lt;0.01,  *  *  p&lt;0.001 </p>



<p>J Reprod Infertil, Vol 15, No 3, Jul-Sept 2014 </p>

<p>Effects of NO Donors on URA </p>

<p>JRI </p>

<p>Discussion 
Decreased uterine and sub-endometrial artery 
blood flow is considered a causative factor in re-
current abortion (14). In the present study, the RI 
and PI of the uterine arteries were significantly 
higher during the luteal phase in patients with 
URA as compared to normal fertile women (p&lt; 
0.001). This result agreed with previous studies 
(15) which referred to the elevated uterine artery 
RI in women with unexplained recurrent pregnan-
cy loss in the mid luteal phase of a non pregnant 
cycle. In another study (16), women with unex-
plained recurrent pregnancy loss had significantly 
higher uterine artery PI in the second half of the 
menstrual cycle than those in a control group. In 
the present study, patients with URA had signifi-
cantly lower sub-endometrial VI, FI and VFI than 
the ones in the control group. Vaquero et al. (17) 
reported significant decrease of sub-endometrial 
blood flow indices with an increase in resistance 
to uterine artery blood flow in patients with unex-
plained recurrent miscarriage. Other studies (18) 
found that in IVF pregnancies with live birth, 
there was significantly higher sub-endometrial 
blood flow than those with miscarriage and that 
failure of implantation was associated with ab-
sence (19) or decrease (20) of sub-endometrial 
blood flow. El-mashad et al. (21) evaluated uter-
ine PI and plasma adrenomedullin (AM) levels in 
women with unexplained recurrent pregnancy loss 
(RPL) compared to controls and found that uterine 
artery PI and AM levels were significantly higher 
in RPL group. However, Yildiz et al. (22) report-
ed no statistically significant difference regarding 
uterine artery PI and RI values measured between 
the 18th and 23rd days of the menstrual cycle in 
patients with recurrent pregnancy loss and the 
control group. In the present study, IMN applied 
vaginally during the luteal phase in patients with 
history of URA caused significant decrease in </p>

<p>uterine artery RI and PI and significant increase in 
sub-endometrial VI, FI and VFI. In a study by El 
Far et al., (11) intravaginal sildenafil citrate-a se-
lective phosphodiesterase-5 (PDE-5) inhibitor that 
augments the action of nitric oxide by inhibiting 
cAmp degradation by the enzyme (PDE-5) suc-
cessfully treated four patients with unexplained 
recurrent spontaneous miscarriage. Other authors 
(23) investigated the effect of sildenafil on uterine 
volumetric blood flow (UVF) and vascular im-
pedance in nonpregnant, nulliparous women in the 
luteal phase and demonstrated a significant in-
crease in UVF in response to sildenafil. In another 
study, Amin et al. (12) evaluated the effect of 
treatment with N-acetyl cysteine as a NO donor 
plus folic acid in patients with unexplained recur-
rent pregnancy loss and found a significant in-
crease in the take-home baby rate as compared to 
treatment with folic acid alone. Amite et al. (13) 
studied the effect of NO donors on uterine blood 
flow velocity waveforms during the first trimester 
of pregnancy by administration of 5 mg IMN sub-
lingual and found a fall in the RI of the uterine 
artery and concluded that NO donors may be of 
therapeutic value in cases where uterine circula-
tion is impaired. The results of the present study 
supported Amite et al.'s conclusion. Nitric oxide 
has important physiological functions and its use 
in the luteal phase and during pregnancy is prom-
ising for treatment of URA. Nitric oxide increases 
uterine and sub-endometrial blood flow, increases 
utero-placental circulation (24), causes peripheral 
vasodilatation and lowers systemic blood pressure 
(25). Also, it has anti-thrombotic and anti-inflam-
matory effects by inhibiting platelet aggregation 
and adhesions of neutrophils to the vessel wall 
(26). Moreover, it regulates apoptosis (27) and 
causes relaxation of the myometrium (28). </p>

<p>Conclusion 
Patients with URA had a decrease in uterine ar-
teries and sub-endometrial blood flow during the 
luteal phase of the menstrual cycle. Nitric oxide 
donors act as perfusion enhancer drugs that in-
crease blood flow and may be of value in improv-
ing endometrial receptivity and pregnancy out-
come. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest 
The authors declare no conflict of interest. </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison between uterine artery and sub-endometrial 
blood flow indices before and after isosorbide mononitrite (IMN) 
administration in the abortion group </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Before IMN 
(n=30) 
Mean±SD </p>

<p>After IMN 
(n=30) 
Mean±SD </p>

<p>paired t </p>

<p>Resistance index </p>

<p>0.91±0.11 
0.72±0.44 
4.51 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Pulsation index </p>

<p>2.88±0.66 
1.98±0.77 
7.12 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Vascular index </p>

<p>0.56±0.22 
0.82±0.61 
9.46 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Flow index </p>

<p>9.11±2.08 
10.22±2.11 
6.73 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Vascular-flow index </p>

<p>0.17±0.03 
0.28±0.16 
4.62 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p> *  p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>J Reprod Infertil, Vol 15, No 3, Jul-Sept 2014 </p>



<p>Abdel-Razik M, et al. JRI </p>





<p>J Reprod Infertil, Vol 15, No 3, Jul-Sept 2014 </p>

<p>Effects of NO Donors on URA </p>

<p>JRI </p>



</text></tei>