<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4160583" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Increased triglycerides (TGs) and decreased high density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C) levels are established as 
diabetic risks for nondiabetic subjects. The aim of this study was to investigate the relationship among TG, HDL-C, TG/HDL-C 
ratio, and early-phase insulin secretion in normoglycemic and prediabetic subjects. 
Methods: We evaluated 663 Japanese subjects who underwent the 75-g oral glucose tolerance test. On the basis of these results, 
the subjects were divided into four groups: those with normal glucose tolerance (NGT; n=341), isolated impaired fasting glucose 
(i-IFG; n=211), isolated impaired glucose tolerance (i-IGT; n=71), and combined IFG and IGT (IFG+IGT; n=40). Insulin se-
cretion was estimated by the insulinogenic index (IGI) (Δinsulin/Δglucose [30 to 0 minutes]) and disposition index (DI) (IGI/ 
homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance). 
Results: In prediabetic subjects (i-IFG, i-IGT, and IFG+IGT), linear regression analyses revealed that IGI and DI were positively 
correlated with HDL-C levels. Moreover, in subjects with i-IGT and (IFG+IGT), but not with i-IFG, the indices of insulin secre-
tion were negatively correlated with the log-transformed TG and TG/HDL-C ratio. In both the subjects with i-IGT, multivariate 
linear regression analyses revealed that DI was positively correlated with HDL-C and negatively with log-transformed TG and 
TG/HDL-C ratio. On the other hand, in subjects with NGT, there was no association between insulin secretion and lipid profiles. 
Conclusion: These results revealed that serum TG and HDL-C levels have different impacts on early-phase insulin secretion on 
the basis of their glucose tolerance status. </p>

<p>Impaired insulin secretion and insulin resistance are consid-
ered as the primary pathophysiological factors in the develop-
ment of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) [1]. T2DM is preced-
ed by a long prediabetic state, which is defined by an oral glu-
cose tolerance test (OGTT) including isolated impaired fasting 
glucose (i-IFG), isolated impaired glucose tolerance (i-IGT), 
or their combination (IFG+IGT) [2]. In these high-risk indi-</p>

<p>viduals, abnormalities of β-cell function are present at early 
stages prior to the development of T2DM. 
A specific non-low density lipoprotein (non-LDL) dyslipid-
emia known as atherogenic dyslipidemia, which is character-
ized by increased triglyceride (TG) along with decreased high 
density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C), is present in subjects 
with diabetes and prediabetes, as well as those with normal 
glucose tolerance (NGT). This abnormal lipid profile has been 
recently hypothesized to play a primary role in the develop-</p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Obesity and metabolic syndrome </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.4093/dmj.2014.38.4.294 
pISSN 2233-6079 · eISSN 2233-6087 </p>



<p>Lipids and insulin secretion </p>

<p>Diabetes Metab J 2014;38:294-301 
http://e-dmj.org </p>

<p>ment of T2DM, and dysfunction of β-cells caused by dyslipid-
emia precedes the manifestation of disease [3,4]. 
The plasma TG/HDL-C concentration ratio is significantly 
related to a direct measure of insulin-mediated glucose dis-
posal [5]. In nondiabetic Korean subjects, the TG/HDL-C ra-
tio was independently associated with later development of 
T2DM [6]. Hermans et al. [7,8] revealed that the TG/HDL-C 
ratio was related to decreased insulin secretion, β-cell function 
loss, and poorer glycemic control in both sexes among sub-
jects with T2DM. Another study reported that HDL-C levels 
were associated with β-cell function in prediabetic subjects 
[9]. On the other hand, the association between TG and TG/ 
HDL-C ratio, and insulin secretion in prediabetic and NGT 
subjects remain to be clarified. 
The aim of the present study was to investigate the associa-
tion between serum TG and HDL-C levels, and TG/HDL-C 
ratio and early-phase insulin secretion in normoglycemic and 
prediabetic subjects. One of the empirical indices that mea-
sures β-cell function, the insulinogenic index (IGI), is a surro-
gate measure of early-phase insulin secretion [1]; it calculates 
the difference between the postprandial insulin peak (mea-
sured at 30 minutes) and basal insulin in relation to the differ-
ence in glucose levels (IGI=ΔInsulin0-30/ΔGlucose0-30). The 
homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-
IR) is used to estimate insulin sensitivity. Because the amount 
of insulin secreted by β-cells is strongly dependent on the pre-
vailing degree of insulin sensitivity, accounting for differences 
in insulin sensitivity is a critical point when evaluating β-cell 
function. Therefore, in the present study, the disposition index 
(DI), which is the ratio of IGI relative to HOMA-IR (IGI/HOMA-
R), was determined as this gives an adjusted measure of β-cell 
function that accounts for variations in insulin sensitivity [10]. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects 
Between January 2005 and December 2008, 746 subjects aged 
35 years or older who had no known history of diabetes un-
derwent a 75-g OGTT as part of a routine health examination 
at Iida Municipal Hospital. The 75-g OGTT was conducted af-
ter an overnight fast (&gt;12 hours). Blood samples were collect-
ed at 0 minute (fasting plasma glucose; FPG), 30 minutes, 1 
hour, and 2 hours postchallenge plasma glucose (2 hr-PG) fol-
lowing the OGTT. The glucose tolerance status of each subject 
was classified based on the criteria of the American Diabetes </p>

<p>Association (2011), as follows: NGT (FPG &lt;100 mg/dL and 2 
hr-PG levels &lt;140 mg/dL), i-IFG (FPG of 100 to 125 mg/dL 
and 2 hr-PG levels &lt;140 mg/dL), i-IGT (FPG ≤125 mg/dL 
and 2 hr-PG levels of 140 to 199 mg/dL), and (IFG+IGT; FPG 
of 100 to 125 mg/dL and 2 hr-PG levels of 140 to 199 mg/dL) 
[11]. 
Subjects who were newly diagnosed with diabetes (according 
to the following definition: hemoglobin A1c ≥6.5%, FPG ≥126 
mg/dL, or 2 hr-PG ≥200 mg/dL) were excluded [11]. Subjects 
who were on steroids or were taking drugs interfering with 
lipid metabolism, and those with IGI values of ≤0 were also 
excluded [12]. On the basis of the OGTT results, subjects with 
NGT (n=341), i-IFG (n=211), i-IGT (n=71), and IFG+IGT 
(n=40) were selected for the present study. Informed consent 
was obtained from all participants. </p>

<p>Biochemical measurements 
Plasma glucose levels, serum total cholesterol (TC), TG, HDL-
C, LDL-cholesterol (LDL-C), and serum uric acid (UA) were 
determined using standard methods (Hitachi 47 automatic 
analyzer; Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan). Serum insulin level was mea-
sured by chemiluminescent enzyme immunoassay (Chemilu-
mi Insulin; Kyowa Medics, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Familial history and lifestyle questionnaires 
A questionnaire was used to obtain information about familial 
medical history and the subjects' lifestyle, such as smoking 
habits and alcohol ingestion. Familial history of diabetes was 
defined as having one or more relatives (parent or sibling) with 
diabetes. Individuals who had smoked &lt;100 cigarettes during 
their lifetime were considered nonsmokers, those who had 
smoked ≥100 cigarettes and were currently not smoking were 
considered former smokers, and those who had smoked ≥100 
cigarettes and were currently smoking were considered current 
smokers. The following criteria were defined for alcohol con-
sumption groups: drinking never or rarely (0 to 5 times/year), 
occasionally (1 to 5 times/month), and regularly (1 to 7 times/ 
week). </p>

<p>Calculations 
Insulin sensitivity was determined by the HOMA-IR, which 
was calculated as FPG (mg/dL)×fasting insulin (μIU/mL)/405 
[13]. The IGI, which determines the early insulin response 
during the OGTT, was calculated as the ratio of the change in 
insulin to the change in glucose from 0 to 30 minutes (ΔInsulin0-30/ </p>



<p>Shimodaira M, et al. </p>

<p>Diabetes Metab J 2014;38:294-301 
http://e-dmj.org </p>

<p>ΔGlucose0-30). The DI, which is an adjusted measure of β-cell 
function that accounts for variations in insulin sensitivity, was 
calculated as the ratio of the IGI relative to the HOMA-IR 
(IGI/HOMA-R) [10]. </p>

<p>Statistical methods 
Statistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 21.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Co.</rs>., Armonk, NY, USA). One-way analysis of vari-
ance was used to compare the clinical characteristics among 
the four groups followed by the Bonferroni post hoc test for 
continuous variables. The chi-square test was used to compare 
the categorical parameters. Normal distribution of variables 
was checked by Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. 
Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated to evaluate 
the relationships between indices of insulin secretion and sev-
eral clinical variables (body mass index [BMI], systolic blood 
pressure [SBP], diastolic blood pressure, UA, TC, TG, HDL-C, 
TG/HDL-C ratio, LDL-C, FPG, and fasting insulin level). The 
distributions of TG and TG/HDL-C ratio were skewed; hence, 
we conducted Pearson linear correlation using log-transformed 
values instead of the raw data. To assess independent relation-
ships between β-cell function and the clinical variables, a mul-
tiple linear regression analysis was performed. Standardized 
coefficients (β) were determined after adjusting for age, BMI, 
SBP, UA, smoking status, and alcohol ingestion. Data were ex-
pressed as mean±standard deviation. A P values of &lt;0.05 was 
considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The clinical and metabolic characteristics of the study popula-
tion are summarized in Table 1. In brief, subjects affected by 
prediabetes had significantly higher age, BMI, blood pressure, 
and levels of fasting insulin, TC, TG, LDL-C, and HOMA-IR 
but lower HDL-C levels than NGT subjects, which was expect-
ed. Glucose levels were higher in subjects with i-IFG, i-IGT, 
and IFG+IGT than in NGT subjects. We found a significant 
difference in insulin secretion (HOMA-β, IGI, and DI) among 
the four groups. 
Spearman correlation analyses of subjects with i-IFG, i-IGT, 
and IFG+IGT demonstrated that IGI and DI were positively 
correlated with serum HDL-C levels. In addition, in subjects 
with i-IGT and IFG+IGT, but not with i-IFG, IGI, and DI were 
negatively correlated with log-transformed TG and the log-
transformed TG/HDL-C ratio. On the other hand, in NGT sub-</p>

<p>jects, neither HDL-C and log-transformed TG, nor log-trans-
formed TG/HDL-C ratio were associated with insulin secre-
tion. Moreover, there were no significant correlations between 
insulin secretion and TC, and LDL-C levels among all subjects 
(Table 2). 
As presented in Table 3, multivariate linear regression anal-
yses revealed that DI was positively correlated with HDL-C in 
the subjects with i-IFG, i-IGT, and IFG+IGT even after adjust-
ing for potential confounding factors. Moreover, in those with 
i-IGT, DI was inversely correlated with log-transformed TG 
and the log-transformed TG/HDL-C ratio. However, DI was 
not significantly associated with the TG or TG/HDL-C ratio 
in the subjects with i-IFG and IFG+IGT. 
Because the relationship between lipid profiles and insulin 
secretion may be explained by the disproportional distribu-
tion of men and women, we examined insulin secretion by 
gender. In i-IGT subjects, decreased HDL-C and increased TG 
and TG/HDL-C ratio were significantly correlated with de-
creased DI in both men and women shown in Tables 4 and 5, 
respectively. However, the association between HDL-C and DI 
in subjects with i-IFG and IFG+IGT was not found in the 
analysis performed separately in men and women. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Elevated TG and decreased HDL-C levels are known to be as-
sociated with the development of T2DM. These atherogenic 
lipid abnormalities often precede T2DM by several years, indi-
cating that altered lipoprotein metabolism is an early event in 
the development of β-cell dysfunction. In fact, among subjects 
with prediabetes, hypertriglyceridemia is demonstrated as a 
predictor of T2DM progression [14]. Elevated TG levels induce 
β-cell apoptosis by increasing the levels of ceramide and nitric 
oxide [15,16]. On the other hand, HDL-C stimulates insulin 
secretion by interacting with ABCA1, the ATP-binding cas-
sette transporter G1, or the scavenger receptor B1, and it also 
inhibits β-cells apoptosis [4]. Therefore, subjects with Tangier 
disease, which is caused by an ABCA1 mutation, exhibit im-
paired insulin secretion [17]. 
In the present study, indices of early-phase insulin secretion, 
IGI and DI, were correlated with HDL-C levels in prediabetic 
subjects but not in NGT subjects. Although the specific reason 
for this inconsistency is unknown, it is hypothesized that HDL-
C may play an important role in protecting β-cells in subjects 
in the relatively late stages of hyperglycemia, particularly in </p>



<p>Lipids and insulin secretion </p>

<p>Diabetes Metab J 2014;38:294-301 
http://e-dmj.org </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and metabolic characteristics of study participants according to glucose tolerance status </p>

<p>Characteristic 
NGT 
Prediabetes 
P value 
Isolated IFG 
Isolated IGT 
IFG+IGT </p>

<p>No. of patients 
341 
211 
71 
40 </p>

<p>Men, % 
55.4 
69.2 
76.1 
77.5 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Age, yr 
50.3±8.2 
52.0±8.0 
52.6±9.5 
53.7±9.9 
0.008 </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>22.6±2.8 
23.8±3.1 
24.0±3.6 
25.6±3.9 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>SBP, mm Hg 
119.7±18.3 
122.9±17.2 
121.5±16.5 
131.6±17.5 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>DBP, mm Hg 
74.1±12.0 
77.7±12.2 
74.6±12.2 
81.7±12.6 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>eGFR, mL/min/1.73 m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>75.1±12.7 
75.4±11.7 
73.9±9.0 
75.0±13.3 
0.937 </p>

<p>UA, mg/dL 
5.2±1.3 
5.6±1.4 
6.0±1.1 
6.2±1.3 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Lipids, mg/dL </p>

<p>TC 
202.5±34.4 
209.6±32.9 
213.6±34.2 
206.9±30.8 
0.052 </p>

<p>TG 
103.1±64.9 
143.6±111.7 
169.5±105.6 
160.0±93.8 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>HDL-C 
65.9±17.3 
62.1±17.3 
62.3±16.4 
59.2±15.4 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>LDL-C 
116.8±29.7 
115.9±27.5 
123.8±33.7 
121.7±27.4 
0.606 </p>

<p>Glucose levels, mg/dL </p>

<p>Fasting 
92.2±4.8 
105.9±5.5 
95.0±3.4 
109.2±7.0 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>0.5 hr-PG 
132.4±26.8 
153.2±26.9 
167.4±24.1 
173.0±28.3 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>1 hr-PG 
121.6±33.7 
145.5±37.8 
178.4±45.2 
190.8±46.8 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>2 hr-PG 
102.6±18.0 
110.3±17.7 
157.6±13.8 
161.3±17.2 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Insulin levels, µIU/mL </p>

<p>Fasting 
5.3±2.8 
7.6±3.9 
8.5±5.7 
9.0±6.0 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>0.5 hr-PG 
46.1±31.3 
49.1±34.1 
57.4±36.0 
47.3±35.9 
0.282 </p>

<p>HOMA-IR 
1.2±0.7 
1.9±1.0 
2.0±1.4 
2.5±1.7 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>HOMA-β 
65.7±36.7 
63.7±34.4 
75.0±34.6 
70.3±47.2 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>IGI 
1.4±1.0 
1.3±0.7 
0.7±0.5 
0.6±0.5 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>DI 
10.8±5.9 
8.0±3.6 
4.8±0.5 
2.9±0.2 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>HbA1c, % 
5.0±0.3 
5.1±0.3 
5.3±0.4 
5.3±0.3 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Familial history of diabetes, % 
12.90 
18.01 
22.54 
25.00 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Smoking status, % 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Current 
9.1 
19.4 
23.9 
25.0 </p>

<p>Former 
20.8 
32.7 
23.9 
50.0 </p>

<p>Never 
70.1 
47.9 
52.1 
25.0 </p>

<p>Alcohol ingestion, % 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Regularly 
19.9 
26.5 
22.5 
25.0 </p>

<p>Occasionally 
36.4 
33.2 
31.0 
35.0 </p>

<p>Never or rarely 
43.7 
40.3 
46.5 
40.0 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean±standard deviation. Statistical analysis was performed using the analysis of variance and chi-square tests. P value 
showed differences among four groups. 
NGT, normal glucose tolerance; IFG, impaired fasting glucose; IGT, impaired glucose tolerance; BMI, body mass index; SBP, systolic blood 
pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; eGFR, epidermal growth factor receptor; UA, uric acid; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglyceride; HDL-C, 
high density lipoprotein cholesterol; LDL-C, low density lipoprotein cholesterol; PG, postchallenge plasma glucose; HOMA-IR, homeostasis 
model assessment of insulin resistance; IGI, insulinogenic index; DI, disposition index; HbA1c, hemoglobin A1c. </p>



<p>Shimodaira M, et al. </p>

<p>Diabetes Metab J 2014;38:294-301 
http://e-dmj.org </p>

<p>those with prediabetes, whereas its protective effects are less 
apparent in those with NGT. Moreover, these indices of insulin 
secretion did not correlate with TG or the TG/HDL-C ratio in 
NGT subjects. Thus, our present study provides new insights 
into the pathophysiological differences in lipid levels and insu-
lin secretion among normoglycemic and prediabetic subjects. 
The evidence now suggests that subjects with i-IFG and i-
IGT may represent different populations, with more or less 
overlapping subclinical characteristics and pathophysiology. 
Isolated IGT is associated with an increase in cardiovascular-
related mortality and all-cause mortality [18]. On the other </p>

<p>hand, i-IFG is a risk category for diabetes, but its relationship 
with atherosclerosis is less clear [19]. The present study re-
vealed that insulin secretion correlated with TG, HDL-C, and 
the TG/HDL-C ratio in both men and women subjects with i-
IGT. However, such correlations were not identified in i-IFG 
subjects, even though the sample size was the largest in this 
group among the three prediabetes subjects. Similar to the re-
sults reported by Lorenzo et al. [20], in our study, TG levels 
were higher in i-IGT subjects compared with i-IFG subjects. 
Van der Zijl et al. [21] showed that lipid accumulation in the 
pancreas was positively associated with TG levels and nega-</p>

<p>Table 3. Associations of TG, HDL-C, and TG/HDL-C ratio with disposition index in total subjects </p>

<p>Isolated IFG 
Isolated IGT 
IFG+IGT </p>

<p>β 
P value 
β 
P value 
β 
P value </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-0.036 
0.873 
-0.249 
0.004 
-0.168 
0.087 </p>

<p>HDL-C 
0.526 
0.038 
0.149 
0.009 
0.174 
0.021 </p>

<p>TG/HDL </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-0.166 
0.483 
-0.252 
0.005 
-0.103 
0.051 </p>

<p>Standardized coefficients (β) were shown after adjusting for age, body mass index, systolic blood pressure, uric acid, smoking status, and alco-
hol ingestion. 
IFG, impaired fasting glucose; IGT, impaired glucose tolerance; TG, triglyceride; HDL-C, high density lipoprotein cholesterol. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Log-transformed. </p>

<p>Table 2. Peason correlation coefficients between indices of insulin secretion and demographic and metabolic variables </p>

<p>NGT 
Prediabetes </p>

<p>Isolated IFG 
Isolated IGT 
IFG+IGT </p>

<p>IGI r 
DI r 
IGI r 
DI r 
IGI r 
DI r 
IGI r 
DI r </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.112 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-0.069 
0.277 
0.277 
0.078 
-0.075 
0.049 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.044 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>SBP, mm Hg 
0.024 
0.027 
0.165 
-0.125 
0.014 
-0.005 
-0.052 
-0.039 </p>

<p>DBP, mm Hg 
0.079 
0.009 
0.15 
-0.249 
0.031 
0.017 
0.066 
0.093 </p>

<p>UA, mg/dL 
-0.081 
-0.088 
0.279 
-0.042 
-0.111 
-0.089 
0.277 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.180 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>TC, mg/dL 
0.071 
-0.078 
0.023 
-0.075 
0.066 
0.010 
-0.071 
-0.152 </p>

<p>TG, mg/dL </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.066 
0.078 
0.138 
-0.130 
-0.233 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-0.133 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-0.315 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-0.224 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>HDL-C, mg/dL 
-0.076 
0.019 
0.489 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.309 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.137 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.144 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.498 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.349 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>TG/HDL-C </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.072 
-0.059 
0.264 
-0.063 
-0.231 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-0.143 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-0.385 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-0.309 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>LDL-C, mg/dL 
0.111 
0.062 
0.081 
-0.088 
-0.098 
0.135 
0.365 
0.310 </p>

<p>FPG, mg/dL 
0.009 
-0.127 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.117 
-0.245 
-0.116 
-0.070 
-0.177 
-0.222 </p>

<p>Fasting insulin, µIU/mL 
0.335 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.128 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.364 
0.361 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.299 
-0.059 
0.545 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.554 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>IGI 
-
0.831 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-
0.626 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-
0.764 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-
0.648 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>DI 
0.831 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-
0.626 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-
0.764 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-
0.648 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Coefficients (r) and P values were calculated using the Pearson's correlation model. 
NGT, normal glucose tolerance; IFG, impaired fasting glucose; IGT, impaired glucose tolerance; DI, disposition index; BMI, body mass index; 
SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; UA, uric acid; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglyceride; HDL-C, high density lipopro-
tein cholesterol; LDL-C, low density lipoprotein cholesterol; FPG, fasting plasma glucose; IGI, insulinogenic index. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05, </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Log-transformed, </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01. </p>



<p>Lipids and insulin secretion </p>

<p>Diabetes Metab J 2014;38:294-301 
http://e-dmj.org </p>

<p>tively with HDL-C levels. Moreover, they reported that pan-
creatic fat content gradually increased with deterioration of 
glucose metabolism (NGT, 7.6%; IFG, 12.1%; and IGT, 22.4%), 
and an inverse relationship between pancreatic fat content and 
DI was observed [21]. In the present investigation, different 
association between lipid profiles and DI in i-IFG and i-IGT 
could be the result of differences in pancreatic fat content be-
tween the two groups. 
He et al. [22] found that TG and the TG/HDL-C ratio were 
independent risk factors for T2DM, and that TG/HDL-C was 
a stronger risk factor of the two. Moreover, Giannini et al. [23] 
reported that the TG/HDL-C ratio is associated with insulin 
resistance and may be used along with other factors to identify 
subjects at increased risk of insulin resistance-driven morbidi-
ty. In the present study, we investigated DI, which can be con-
sidered an index of pancreatic functionality and can predict 
the normal β-cell response adequate for any degree of insulin 
resistance [24]. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first 
report to reveal that this index is correlated with the TG/HDL-
C ratio in both men and women with i-IGT even after adjust-
ing for the associated variables. Our results add further sup-
port to the notion that the TG/HDL-C ratio may be a clinically 
simple and useful indicator of insulin secretion independent </p>

<p>of insulin sensitivity among subjects with i-IGT. 
The current study had some limitations. First, the 75-g 
OGTT was performed as part of a health check-up rather than 
for any specified research purpose, and there were no prede-
termined criteria for undergoing the test. Second, the current 
study had a small sample size and a high prevalence of men es-
pecially in subjects with IFG+IGT. Our sample size and dis-
proportional distribution of gender may be insufficient to 
clearly confirm the association between lipid profile and insu-
lin secretion in subjects with IFG+IGT. Third, and finally, we 
did not measure subclinical inflammatory markers (such as C-
reactive protein, interleukin-6, or tumor necrosis factor-α), 
which may affect insulin secretion. However, the strength and 
consistency of the association observed using routine bio-
chemical measures may have beneficial implications for clini-
cal practice. 
In conclusion, in a sample of prediabetic subjects, consistent 
associations were found between lower HDL-C and lower ear-
ly-phase insulin secretion levels. Moreover, in both men and 
women with i-IGT, insulin secretion was negatively correlated 
with TG and the TG/HDL-C ratio. These results suggest that 
early-phase insulin secretion is affected by HDL-C and TG in 
prediabetic subjects. </p>

<p>Table 4. Associations of TG, HDL-C, and TG/HDL-C ratio with disposition index in men subjects </p>

<p>Isolated IFG 
Isolated IGT 
IFG+IGT </p>

<p>β 
P value 
β 
P value 
β 
P value </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-0.041 
0.871 
-0.325 
&lt;0.001 
-0.008 
0.096 </p>

<p>HDL-C 
0.515 
0.056 
0.167 
0.008 
0.059 
0.070 </p>

<p>TG/HDL </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-0.176 
0.494 
-0.308 
0.002 
-0.025 
0.088 </p>

<p>Standardized coefficients (β) were shown after adjusting for age, body mass index, systolic blood pressure, uric acid, smoking status, and alco-
hol ingestion. 
IFG, impaired fasting glucose; IGT, impaired glucose tolerance; TG, triglyceride; HDL-C, high density lipoprotein cholesterol. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Log-transformed. </p>

<p>Table 5. Associations of TG, HDL-C, and TG/HDL-C ratio with disposition index in women subjects </p>

<p>Isolated IFG 
Isolated IGT 
IFG+IGT </p>

<p>β 
P value 
β 
P value 
β 
P value </p>

<p>TG </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.082 
0.417 
-0.148 
0.0338 
0.244 
0.813 </p>

<p>HDL-C 
0.892 
0.377 
0.112 
0.0312 
-0.397 
0.278 </p>

<p>TG/HDL </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.147 
0.351 
-0.100 
0.0348 
0.271 
0.550 </p>

<p>Standardized coefficients (β) were shown after adjusting for age, body mass index, systolic blood pressure, uric acid, smoking status, and alco-
hol ingestion. 
IFG, impaired fasting glucose; IGT, impaired glucose tolerance; TG, triglyceride; HDL-C, high density lipoprotein cholesterol. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Log-transformed. </p>



<p>Shimodaira M, et al. </p>



<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The authors thank Nobuo Shimosawa for preparing an elec-
tronic database of the patients' medical records. </p>





<p>Lipids and insulin secretion </p>



</text></tei>