<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4225645" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>homeostasis model of assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR), a surrogate 
marker of insulin resistance (IR), and metabolic risk score at both baseline and 
follow-up. 
Conclusion: In young Korean males, higher D6D activity predicts the future 
development of IR and associated metabolic disorders including dyslipidemia. </p>

<p>Obesity has become increasingly prevalent among 
children and adolescents in many countries. Childhood 
obesity increases the risk of developing health problems 
including insulin resistance (IR) and metabolic syndrome 
[1,2], and also adult obesity and cardiovascular disease 
[3,4]. Therefore, early detection of childhood obesity and 
metabolic disorders is required to efficiently prevent 
development of problems in adulthood. Studies on child 
populations may clarify the mechanisms underlying the 
development of obesity and metabolic disorders, because 
problems in children are not confounded by the conse-
quences of advanced metabolic disorders. 
The levels of specific serum fatty acids and fatty acid 
desaturases have been suggested to serve as useful 
biomarkers predicting the development of IR and 
metabolic disorders [5e11]. Higher levels of saturated 
fatty acids, palmitoleic acid, linoleic acid, and dihomo-
gamma linolenic acid (DGLA), have been reported to be 
associated with obesity and metabolic syndrome. In 
addition, both animal and human studies have suggested 
that fatty acid desaturases play roles in various meta-
bolic disturbances, including dyslipidemia and IR [12]. 
The data have been derived principally from cross-
sectional studies, which cannot predict the future 
development of obesity and metabolic disorders. Lon-
gitudinal studies can yield integrated information on the 
development of metabolic disorders over time, and can 
identify the optimal points of intervention [13]. There-
fore, in the present study, we explored the longitudinal 
relations of plasma phospholipid (PL) fatty acid 
composition and desaturase activities to IR and meta-
bolic risk factors in Korean boys. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Study participants and anthropometric 
parameters </p>

<p>This study is part of the Korean Children and 
Adolescent Cohort Study, which follows a student 
cohort from the time of entry into elementary school (at 
7 years of age) to graduation (at age 19 years) in Seoul 
and Kyunggi provinces, Korea. The overall objective of 
the cohort study is to identify early risk factors for 
obesity and associated metabolic disease. The study was 
approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Korea 
Center for Disease Control and Prevention and the </p>

<p>Ethics Committee of Seoul-Paik Hospital, Inje Univer-
sity, Seoul, Korea. Informed parental consent was ob-
tained for each individual prior to enrolment. Body 
weight and body fat percentage were measured using a 
body composition analyzer (BC418; Tanita, Tokyo, 
Japan) and height was measured using an automatic 
stadiometer (DS-102; Jenix, Seoul, Korea). Obese chil-
dren were defined as those with a body mass index 
(BMI) greater than the 85 th percentile for age and 
gender, based on Korean child growth standards [14]. A 
total of 131 boys aged 9e11 years in 2008e2009 were 
included. After 2 years, health data were obtained once 
more. </p>

<p>2.2. Biochemical analysis </p>

<p>Each blood sample was collected from an antecubital 
vein into a vacutainer tube between 9:00 AM and 
11:00 AM after a 12-hour overnight fast. Within 30 mi-
nutes, plasma and serum were separated and stored at 
À80 C prior to further analysis. The levels of triglyc-
eride (TG), total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein-
cholesterol (HDL-C), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), 
aspartate aminotransferase (AST), and glucose were 
measured using an autoanalyzer (model 7600II; Hitachi, 
Tokyo, Japan). The fasting serum insulin level was 
measured using a Roche E170 instrument (Roche Di-
agnostics, Mannheim, Germany). The IR index was 
calculated using the homeostasis model assessment of 
insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) [15]. A metabolic risk 
score was constructed by summing the z-score of five 
metabolic risk factors, which are BMI, systolic blood 
pressure (SBP), TG, HDL-C, and HOMA-IR [16]. </p>

<p>2.3. Fatty acid analysis </p>

<p>Plasma lipids were extracted using a modification of 
the method of Folch et al [17]. The PL fraction was iso-
lated by thin-layer chromatography and the fatty acids 
were converted into methyl esters using the method of 
Lepage and Roy [18]. The composition of the methylated 
fatty acid mix was determined by gas chromatography 
(HP 7890A; Hewlett-Packard, Palo Alto, CA, USA). In-
dividual fatty acids were identified by comparing reten-
tion times to those of standards and quantified based on 
the peak area relative to the total methylated fatty acid 
peak area (set at 100%). Desaturase levels were estimated 
by calculating the product:precursor ratios of individual 
fatty acids (using the proportions calculated above) as 
follows: delta-6D (D6D) Z [20:3n-6/18:2n-6]; delta-6D 
(D5D) Z [20:4n-6/20:3n-6]; stearyl-CoAD-16 (SCD-</p>

<p>252 
Y.S. Choi, et al </p>

<p>16) Z [16:1n-7/16:0]; and stearyl-CoAD-18 (SCD-
18) Z [18:1n-9/18:0] [18]. </p>

<p>2.4. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed with the aid of 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.1</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA</rs>). All data are expressed as mean AE standard de-
viation (SD). The normality of data distribution was 
checked. Variables with skewed distributions were log-
transformed prior to analysis. The significance of 
observed between-group differences was assessed using 
the unpaired Student t test and the significance of 
among-group differences was analyzed using one-way 
analysis of variance (ANOVA). If a statistically signif-
icant effect was noted, Duncan's post-hoc test was 
applied to identify a between-group difference with a 
significance level of p &lt; 0.05. Pearson correlation co-
efficients were calculated to measure the extent of cor-
relation between pairs of variables. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Participant characteristics </p>

<p>Anthropometric and biological characteristics of all 
individuals at baseline are shown in Table 1. At 
commencement of the study, 75 of 131 boys were obese, </p>

<p>and all had a significantly greater body weight, BMI, 
BMI z-score, and waist circumference than did the 
others. HOMA-IR values and levels of serum ALT, TG, 
and insulin were significantly higher and HDL-C was 
significantly lower in obese individuals (Table 1). Two 
years later, the children were examined once more. Of 
the 56 individuals who were not obese at baseline, 
categorized as "lean", 40 boys had BMI values below 
the 60 th percentile at follow-up. Of the 75 initially obese 
boys, 57 remained obese at follow-up. At this time, 14 
boys who were not obese at baseline and 20 boys who 
were obese at that time had BMI values in the 60e85% 
percentile, and were categorized as "intermediate" in 
terms of obesity. 
The baseline and follow-up data of lean and obese 
individuals were compared. Not surprisingly, the mean 
values of height, weight, BMI, and waist circumference 
of both groups increased significantly over the 2 years, 
as did blood glucose and insulin levels, and HOMA-IR 
values. The mean values of BMI z-score, AST, and ALT 
levels were lower in lean boys at follow-up than at 
baseline, but this was not true of obese individuals. The 
mean SBP, diastolic blood pressure (DBP), and lipid 
levels (total cholesterol, HDL-C, and TG) did not differ 
between baseline and follow-up in either group. 
At follow-up, obese boys had a significantly greater 
BMI z-score, and waist circumference than lean or </p>

<p>Table 1. Anthropometric and biochemical characteristics of the study participants. a </p>

<p>Baseline 
Follow-up </p>

<p>Lean (n Z 56) Obese (n Z 75) 
p 0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Lean (n Z 40) </p>

<p>Intermediate 
(n Z 34) Obese (n Z 57) 
p 1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Age (y) 
10.5 AE 0.6*** 
10.4 AE 0.6 yyy 
0.161 
12.5 AE 0.7 
12.2 AE 0.6 
12.3 AE 0.7 
0.274 
Height (cm) 
142.7 AE 5.3*** 144.6 AE 6.6 yyy 
0.073 156.9 AE 7.3 
156.5 AE 7.9 
157.0 AE 8.1 
0.923 
Body weight (kg) 
37.1 AE 3.5*** 
50.0 AE 8.3 yyy &lt;0.0001 46.5 AE 5.1 
53.3 AE 6.8 
65.1 AE 12.1 &lt;0.0001 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
18.2 AE 0.5*** 
23.8 AE 2.3 yyy &lt;0.0001 18.8 AE 0.8 
21.7 AE 1.0 
26.2 AE 3.0 
&lt;0.0001 
BMI z-score 
À0.02 AE 0.14*** 1.49 AE 0.40 yyy &lt;0.0001 À0.21 AE 0.26 
0.68 AE 0.24 
1.60 AE 0.46 &lt;0.0001 
Waist circumference 
(cm) </p>

<p>62.4 AE 3.7*** 
77.6 AE 6.2 yyy &lt;0.0001 66.4 AE 5.1 
74.9 AE 5.8 
85.5 AE 8.1 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>SBP (mmHg) 
108.0 AE 8.6 
111.5 AE 13.1 
0.064 107.8 AE 10.5 109.7 AE 11.7 115.1 AE 10.4 
0.001 
DBP (mmHg) 
71.1 AE 7.5 
71.2 AE 8.8 
0.930 
68.2 AE 10.3 
69.1 AE 9.0 
70.9 AE 8.3 
0.152 
AST (U/L) 
23.3 AE 2.8** 
26.3 AE 9.1 
0.008 
21.7 AE 3.1 
23.0 AE 4.0 
28.3 AE 14.8 
0.001 
ALT (U/L) b 
13.8 AE 3.9* 
26.7 AE 23.2 
&lt;0.0001 12.1 AE 3.6 
16.0 AE 8.6 
34.5 AE 37.1 &lt;0.0001 
Total cholesterol 
(mg/dL) </p>

<p>167.1 AE 24.5 
173.8 AE 27.9 
0.159 161.0 AE 18.6 161.4 AE 33.4 173.3 AE 31.2 
0.030 </p>

<p>HDL-C (mg/dL) 
60.1 AE 12.0 
52.0 AE 10.8 
&lt;0.0001 61.0 AE 10.9 
55.9 AE 12.3 
49.4 AE 9.4 
&lt;0.0001 
TG (mg/dL) a,b 
61.5 AE 34.1 
104.5 AE 63.8 
&lt;0.0001 57.1 AE 28.0 
89.8 AE 41.5 117.4 AE 60.5 &lt;0.0001 
Glucose (mg/dL) 
86.3 AE 6.4** 
85.8 AE 8.0 yy 
0.714 
90.8 AE 8.0 
90.8 AE 6.4 
90.7 AE 9.1 
0.951 
Insulin (mIU/mL) a,b 
6.1 AE 4.2*** 
12.0 AE 11.0 yyy &lt;0.0001 
8.8 AE 3.5 
11.9 AE 8.2 
21.6 AE 19.9 &lt;0.0001 
HOMA-IR a,b 
1.3 AE 0.9*** 
2.5 AE 2.4 yyy &lt;0.0001 
2.0 AE 0.8 
2.72 AE 2.1 
5.0 AE 4.9 
&lt;0.0001 
Metabolic risk 
score </p>

<p>À1.59 AE 1.25*** 1.19 AE 2.23 yyy &lt;0.0001 À1.87 AE 1.37 À0.58 AE 1.57 
1.64 AE 2.51 &lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>MetS (%) 
d 
17.3 
d 
d 
2.9 
22.8 
d </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Tested by unpaired Student t test (p0, *, y) or one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA; p1 Z p value for linear trends); b Data are log transformed prior to 
analysis. All values are presented as mean AE standard deviation (SD). * Baseline vs. follow-up in control; *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001. y Baseline 
vs. follow-up in obese; y p &lt; 0.05; yy p &lt; 0.01; yyy p &lt; 0.001. ALT Z alanine aminotransferase; AST Z aspartate aminotransferase; BMI Z body mass index; 
DBP Z diastolic blood pressure; HDL-C Z high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; HOMA-IR Z homeostasis model of assessment of insulin resistance; 
IU Z international unit; SBP Z systolic blood pressure; TG Z triglyceride; U Z unit. </p>

<p>Desaturase Activity and Insulin Resistance in Boys </p>

<p>
intermediate individuals. In addition, obese individuals 
had significantly higher concentrations of ALT, TG, and 
insulin and a higher mean HOMA-IR value than the 
other groups. </p>

<p>3.2. Plasma PL fatty acid composition and 
desaturase levels </p>

<p>Table 2 shows the relative proportions of 25 indi-
vidual fatty acids of plasma PLs. At baseline, over 63% 
of total fatty acids were saturated (SFAs), and no sig-
nificant difference in the level of total SFA, palmitate, 
or stearate was evident between obese and lean in-
dividuals. Monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) 
constituted 11% of total fatty acids in either group. 
However, the palmitoleic acid (16:1n-7) level was </p>

<p>higher in obese individuals. Although no difference in 
total n-6 polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) or 20:4n-6 
level was observed, the DGLA (20:3n-6) level was 
higher in obese individuals as were the SCD-16 and 
D6D indices. 
Baseline and follow-up data on lean and obese in-
dividuals were separately compared. The levels of only 
four fatty acids (22:0, 20:1, 22:5n-3, and 20:4n-6) 
differed between baseline and follow-up. The mean 
22:5n-3 level increased in both groups at follow-up and 
the mean 20:4 level fell in lean boys at follow-up. Obese 
individuals had a higher palmitoleic acid and DGLA 
level than lean boys at follow-up. Also, trends toward 
increases in the SCD-16 and D6D indices were evident 
in boys of heavier weight. </p>

<p>Table 2. Plasma PL fatty acid composition and estimated desaturase activity of the study participants. a,b </p>

<p>Baseline 
Follow-up </p>

<p>Control 
(n Z 56) </p>

<p>Obese 
(n Z 75) 
p 0 </p>

<p>Control 
(n Z 33) </p>

<p>Intermediate 
(n Z 25) </p>

<p>Obese 
(n Z 46) 
p 1 
Total SFA 
63.5 AE 5.8 
63.4 AE 7.5 yy 
0.776 
63.5 AE 9.7 
60.6 AE 10.3 
61.8 AE 9.2 
0.515 
c12:0 
0.14 AE 0.08 
0.13 AE 0.06 
0.443 
0.12 AE 0.06 
0.14 AE 0.06 
0.11 AE 0.05 
0.666 
c14:0 
0.54 AE 0.14 
0.51 AE 0.11 
0.385 
0.54 AE 0.22 
0.52 AE 0.08 
0.50 AE 0.14 
0.435 
c16:0 
38.9 AE 3.7 
38.1 AE 4.8 
0.213 
39.2 AE 6.4 
36.9 AE 6.5 
37.3 AE 6.2 
0.217 
c18:0 
21.2 AE 2.3 
21.7 AE 2.8 
0.341 
20.7 AE 3.3 
20.2 AE 3.6 
20.9 AE 2.9 
0.620 
c20:0 
0.51 AE 0.16 
0.53 AE 0.15 
0.321 
0.55 AE 0.10 
0.52 AE 0.12 
0.55 AE 0.11 
0.941 
c22:0 
1.17 AE 0.49* 
1.28 AE 0.45 
0.163 
1.26 AE 0.24 
1.23 AE 0.23 
1.33 AE 0.31 
0.238 
c24:0 
1.05 AE 0.41 
1.10 AE 0.38 
0.371 
1.12 AE 0.27 
1.05 AE 0.24 
1.07 AE 0.27 
0.413 
Total MUFA 
11.0 AE 1.6 
11.0 AE 1.6 y 
0.889 
11.3 AE 1.0 
11.1 AE 1.2 
11.1 AE 1.1 
0.545 
c16:1n-7 
0.43 AE 0.18 
0.51 AE 0.20 
0.018 
0.36 AE 0.15 
0.44 AE 0.18 
0.44 AE 0.15 
0.027 
c18:1n-9 
6.89 AE 1.46 
6.79 AE 1.55 
0.589 
6.23 AE 1.68 
6.68 AE 2.06 
6.62 AE 1.48 
0.278 
c18:1n-7 
1.25 AE 0.23 
1.16 AE 0.21 
0.039 
1.20 AE 0.28 
1.12 AE 0.20 
1.13 AE 0.26 
0.283 
c20:1n-9 
0.32 AE 0.26* 
0.32 AE 0.32 
0.446 
0.62 AE 0.62 
0.50 AE 0.59 
0.43 AE 0.45 
0.197 
c22:1n-9 
0.71 AE 0.42 
0.69 AE 0.49 
0.306 
1.31 AE 1.08 
0.89 AE 0.99 
0.92 AE 0.84 
0.271 
c24:1n-9 
1.40 AE 0.57 
1.50 AE 0.57 
0.248 
1.52 AE 0.46 
1.47 AE 0.38 
1.57 AE 0.43 
0.522 
Total n-6 FA 
21.7 AE 4.3*** 
21.8 AE 5.7 yyy 
0.752 
21.2 AE 8.0 
24.1 AE 8.1 
22.7 AE 7.5 
0.428 
c18:2n-6 
14.2 AE 2.9 
13.7 AE 3.2 
0.285 
14.0 AE 4.9 
15.4 AE 4.8 
14.4 AE 4.1 
0.690 
c18:3n-6 
0.40 AE 0.13 
0.39 AE 0.14 
0.497 
0.45 AE 0.18 
0.37 AE 0.11 
0.39 AE 0.11 
0.153 
c20:2n-6 
0.29 AE 0.18 
0.28 AE 0.12 
0.993 
0.29 AE 0.13 
0.30 AE 0.14 
0.29 AE 0.12 
0.864 
c20:3n-6 
2.08 AE 0.48 
2.38 AE 0.61 
0.008 
2.00 AE 0.53 
2.28 AE 0.71 
2.39 AE 0.55 
0.007 
c20:4n-6 
4.44 AE 1.74* 
4.74 AE 2.30 
0.891 
3.96 AE 3.11 
5.22 AE 3.21 
4.84 AE 3.24 
0.255 
c22:4n-6 
0.18 AE 0.09 
0.21 AE 0.09 
0.108 
0.24 AE 0.27 
0.24 AE 0.11 
0.21 AE 0.12 
0.894 </p>

<p>Total n-3 FA 
3.72 AE 1.27 
3.82 AE 1.19 yyy 
0.632 
3.72 AE 1.30 
3.80 AE 1.15 
3.80 AE 1.23 
0.367 
c18:3n-3 
0.11 AE 0.07 
0.13 AE 0.07 
0.109 
0.13 AE 0.09 
0.14 AE 0.08 
0.14 AE 0.11 
0.955 
c20:3n-3 
1.15 AE 0.70 
0.96 AE 0.63 
0.319 
1.26 AE 0.66 
0.92 AE 0.64 
1.17 AE 0.70 
0.569 
c20:5n-3 
0.37 AE 0.33 
0.42 AE 0.30 
0.340 
0.42 AE 0.45 
0.53 AE 0.37 
0.45 AE 0.35 
0.663 
c22:5n-3 
0.58 AE 0.34* 
0.59 AE 0.30 yyy 
0.709 
0.76 AE 0.37 
0.72 AE 0.28 
0.77 AE 0.29 
0.532 
c22:6n-3 
1.51 AE 1.03 
1.71 AE 1.14 
0.453 
1.54 AE 1.46 
1.95 AE 1.42 
1.89 AE 1.70 
0.591 
Desaturase activity 
D6D 
0.15 AE 0.04 
0.18 AE 0.04 
&lt;0.0001 
0.15 AE 0.04 
0.16 AE 0.04 
0.18 AE 0.05 
0.029 
D5D 
2.15 AE 0.78 
1.95 AE 0.80 
0.075 
1.85 AE 1.38 
2.10 AE 1.13 
1.94 AE 1.26 
0.590 
SCD-16 
0.011 AE 0.005 
0.013 AE 0.006 
0.016 
0.009 AE 0.004 0.012 AE 0.006 0.012 AE 0.004 0.031 
SCD-18 
0.334 AE 0.100 
0.323 AE 0.099 
0.462 
0.319 AE 0.126 0.354 AE 0.154 0.328 AE 0.103 0.572 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data are log transformed prior to analysis; b Tested by unpaired Student t test (p 0 , *, y) or one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA; p 1 Z p value for linear 
trends). All values are presented as mean AE standard deviation (SD). * Baseline vs. follow-up in control; *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001. y Baseline vs. 
follow-up in obese; y p &lt; 0.05; yy p &lt; 0.01; yyy p &lt; 0.001. D5D Z delta-5D; D6D Z delta-6D; FA Z fatty acid; MUFA Z monounsaturated fatty acid; 
PL Z phospholipid; SCD Z stearyl-CoAD; SFA Z saturated fatty acid. </p>

<p>254 
Y.S. Choi, et al </p>

<p>3.3. Correlation between fatty acid and 
desaturase levels and the risks of adiposity 
and IR </p>

<p>The baseline level of palmitoleic acid (as a percent-
age of all fatty acids) was closely associated with WC 
and metabolic risk score (r Z 0.217, p &lt; 0.05; 
r Z 0.221, p &lt; 0.05, respectively). DGLA level was 
also highly associated with WC, HDL-C, TG, and 
metabolic risk score (r Z 0.205, p &lt; 0.05; r Z À0.176, 
p &lt; 0.05; r Z 0.371, p &lt; 0.001; r Z 0.260, p &lt; 0.01, 
respectively). The SCD-16 level was closely associated 
with WC and metabolic risk score (r Z 0.209, p &lt; 0.05; 
r Z 0.200, p &lt; 0.05, respectively) but not with the 
HOMA-IR value (Table 3). The D6D level was highly 
associated with most of the metabolic risk factors such 
as WC, TG, and HDL-C. The D6D level was thus 
positively associated with the HOMA-IR value and the 
metabolic risk score (r Z 0.267, p &lt; 0.01; r Z 0.394, 
p &lt; 0.001). The baseline D6D level showed significant 
positive association with the follow-up WC, HOMA-IR, </p>

<p>and metabolic risk score (r Z 0.480, r Z 0.364, and 
r Z 0.436, respectively). The baseline D5D level 
exhibited a negative association with them (Table 3). 
A stepwise multiple regression analysis with the 
baseline levels of age, BMI z-score, WC, TG, HDL-C, 
and four estimated desaturase indices was performed 
to investigate potential factors associated with the 
follow-up HOMA-IR. Significant associations with the 
follow-up HOMA-IR were found for baseline WC and 
D6D (Table 4). Similarly, strong associations with the 
follow-up metabolic risk score were found for baseline 
WC and D6D level. Based on the regression analysis, 
the baseline D6D level could be a major predictive 
marker for future metabolic risks. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>We investigated the relationships between individual 
plasma PL fatty acids and desaturase activities and </p>

<p>Table 3. Correlation coefficient between estimated desaturase activity and risks for metabolic syndrome. a </p>

<p>D6D 
D5D 
SCD-16 
SCD-18 
Baseline 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
0.414*** 
À0.203* 
0.193* 
À0.093 
BMI z-score 
0.410*** 
À0.209* 
0.199* 
À0.097 
Waist circumference (cm) 
0.414*** 
À0.254** 
0.209* 
À0.137 
SBP (mmHg) 
0.151 
À0.137 
0.153 
0.068 
DBP (mmHg) 
0.181* 
À0.160 
À0.031 
À0.039 
AST 
0.279** 
À0.124 
0.153 
À0.013 
ALT 
0.370*** 
À0.164 
0.155 
À0.070 
Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
0.214* 
À0.030 
0.073 
0.110 
HDL-C (mg/dL) 
À0.292*** 
0.082 
À0.090 
0.055 
TG (mg/dL) 
0.482*** 
À0.144 
0.166 
0.015 
Glucose (mg/dL) 
À0.138 
0.219* 
0.119 
0.126 
Insulin (mIU/mL) 
0.290** 
À0.195* 
0.036 
À0.072 
HOMA-IR 
0.267** 
À0.161 
0.050 
À0.054 
Metabolic risk score 
0.394*** 
À0.258** 
0.200* 
À0.006 
Follow-up 
BMI (kg/m 2 ) 
0.445*** 
À0.279** 
0.155 
À0.100 
BMI z-score 
0.456*** 
À0.297*** 
0.156 
À0.103 
Waist circumference (cm) 
0.480*** 
À0.300*** 
0.153 
À0.087 
SBP (mmHg) 
0.340*** 
À0.305*** 
À0.017 
À0.181* 
DBP (mmHg) 
0.203* 
À0.155 
À0.092 
À0.061 
AST 
0.131 
À0.145 
0.012 
À0.092 
ALT 
0.306*** 
À0.258** 
0.089 
À0.116 
Total cholesterol (mg/dL) 
0.197* 
À0.092 
0.091 
0.123 
HDL-C (mg/dL) 
À0.289*** 
0.147 
0.000 
0.135 
TG (mg/dL) 
0.356*** 
À0.233** 
0.090 
À0.105 
Glucose (mg/dL) 
0.004 
À0.219* 
À0.228** 
À0.208* 
Insulin (mIU/mL) 
0.377*** 
À0.261** 
0.046 
À0.066 
HOMA-IR 
0.364*** 
À0.278** 
0.014 
À0.089 
Metabolic risk score 
0.436*** 
À0.340*** 
0.112 
À0.107 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Tested by age-adjusted partial correlation analysis; data are log transformed prior to analysis. *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001. ALT Z alanine 
aminotransferase; AST Z aspartate aminotransferase; BMI Z body mass index; D5D Z delta-5D; D6D Z delta-6D; DBP Z diastolic blood pressure; 
HDL-C Z high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; HOMA-IR Z homeostasis model of assessment of insulin resistance; IU Z international unit; 
SBP Z systolic blood pressure; SCD Z stearyl-CoAD; TG Z triglyceride. </p>

<p>Desaturase Activity and Insulin Resistance in Boys </p>

<p>
metabolic risk factors in Korean children. Furthermore, 
we explored the longitudinal relations of estimates of 
desaturase activity to body fatness, IR, and metabolic 
risk score. Obese boys had significantly higher pro-
portions of palmitoleic acid and DGLA at baseline than 
did lean children, in agreement with data on Japanese 
children [9]. Increased DGLA levels are positively 
associated with the development of metabolic disorders 
in both adults and children [19e21]. A previous cross-
sectional study found that obese children have higher 
proportions of DGLA in plasma lipids than do those of 
normal weight [21]. Our data are in agreement with 
these earlier reports. The present study, a longitudinal 
study, also shows that obese boys had persistently high 
proportions of DGLA and palmitoleic acid at follow-up. 
Assessment of plasma DGLA level and/or palmitoleic 
acid level would give useful information on obesity 
status in children. Additionally, the present study shows 
that the baseline plasma DGLA content was positively 
associated with both present and future adiposity index 
values and metabolic risk score in Korean children. 
Plasma fatty acid composition could be regulated by 
many factors such as dietary, hormonal, and environ-
mental factors [12,22]. To assess the effect of dietary 
fatty acids on the serum PL fatty acid composition of the 
study participant, a reliable database for fatty acid 
composition of Korean food is needed, but was not 
available at this time. Linoleic acid (18:2n-6) is directly 
converted into 18:3n-6 by D6D and rapidly elongated to 
20:3n-6 (DGLA) [22]. DGLA is converted into arach-
idonic acid by D5D [22]. The DGLA level, regulated by 
D6D activity, is increased by insulin [12]. Hyper-
insulinemia induced by obesity might change the 
expression level of D6D. We observed D6D had a 
positive association with HOMA-IR, a surrogate marker 
of IR for epidemiology study. The observed increases in </p>

<p>DGLA concentration and D6D activity, accompanied by 
a fall in D5D expression, in obese individuals suggest 
that impaired fatty acid metabolism, possibly caused by 
the development of IR, may trigger the accumulation of 
DGLA. Although DGLA plays multiple roles in pro-
tecting against inflammation and cell proliferation [22], 
increases in DGLA and D6D levels in association with 
IR could nonetheless aggravate metabolic disorders. A 
recent cross-sectional study with Korean adults sug-
gested D6D as a major factor for determining plasma 
level of C-reactive protein, a surrogate marker for 
inflammation [23]. 
Not only was the baseline D6D activity significantly 
higher in obese than in lean children at baseline, but it 
was also positively associated with adiposity indices at 
follow-up. Baseline D6D activity also exhibited positive 
associations with the follow-up values of surrogate 
markers of IR and metabolic disorders, including the TG 
level, HOMA-IR value, and metabolic risk score. 
Accumulating evidence suggests that D6D plays a 
crucial role in the development of obesity and metabolic 
syndrome. High levels of D6D activity have been esti-
mated in adults with obesity, diabetes, and metabolic 
syndrome [18,24,25]. Warensjo et al [25] found that a 
higher estimated D6D activity increased the risk of 
metabolic syndrome over 20 years in middle-aged men. 
To the best of our knowledge, only one prior study [26] 
explored the associations between longitudinal changes 
in fatty acid composition and body fatness in children. 
In that study, increased D6D activity was significantly 
associated with an elevated waist-to-hip ratio in both 
boys and girls. The authors suggested that D6D activity 
was positively associated with an increased HOMA-IR 
value only in girls [26]. However, their small sample 
size may have limited the observations that could be 
made. In the present study, the D6D levels did not vary 
greatly over the 2 years, whereas the HOMA-IR level 
increased. Thus, no positive association between 
changes in D6D and changes in the HOMA-IR value 
were noted. However, baseline D6D activity was posi-
tively associated with both baseline and follow-up 
HOMA-IR values, and also follow-up metabolic risk 
score. Results from the present multiple regression 
analysis suggested that WC and D6D were the major 
determinants of HOMA-IR and metabolic risk score, a 
suggested tool for an early-life determination of meta-
bolic risk. Thus early detection of elevated D6D activity 
in Korean boys may predict the future development of 
IR and associated metabolic disorders including dysli-
pidemia. Adequate regulation of D6D level at an early 
age may help prevent the development of metabolic 
disorders. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>All authors declare no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Table 4. Stepwise multiple regression analysis for pre-
dicting follow-up HOMA-IR levels and meta-
bolic risk score. a,b </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Adjusted 
p 
r 2 
b Coefficient </p>

<p>Follow up HOMA-IR c 
Waist circumference 
0.026 
&lt; 0.0001 0.206 
D6D 
0.619 
0.007 
0.250 
Follow up metabolic risk score d 
Waist circumference 
0.135 
&lt;0.0001 0.356 
D6D 
2.338 
0.002 
0.402 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data are log transformed prior to analysis; b For multiple stepwise 
regression analysis, only the two independent variables incorporated into 
the model are listed, and the r 2 values displayed are cumulative; c In-
dependent variables include: baseline age, BMI z-score, waist circum-
ference, TG, HDL-C, and desaturase; d Independent variables include: 
baseline age, waist circumference, and desaturase. BMI Z body mass 
index; HDL-C Z high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; HOMA-
IR Z homeostasis model of assessment of insulin resistance; 
TG Z triglyceride. </p>

<p>256 
Y.S. Choi, et al </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank all the participating schools, children, and 
parents, as well as current and past investigators and 
staff. This work was supported by intramural grants 
from the Korea National Institute of Health, Korea 
Center for Disease Control (4845-302-210-13, 2012-
NG64001-00). </p>



<p>Desaturase Activity and Insulin Resistance in Boys </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>