<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4870320" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Injuries to the glenoid labrum can occur anywhere around 
the labrum. They may involve only the anterior or antero-
inferior portion, as seen in a Bankart and anterior labral 
periosteal sleeve avulsion (ALPSA) lesions, the posteroin-
ferior area (Kim's lesion), or the superior labrum from an-</p>

<p>terior to posterior (SLAP) lesions. SLAP lesions were first 
classified by Snyder et al. 1) into 4 subtypes. However, more 
extensive labral tears do occur, some of which may be pro-
gression of pre-existing SLAP lesions, or its combination 
with a Bankart lesion (SLAP type V). 2,3) 
A Bankart lesion is the primary pathology in post-
traumatic anterior shoulder instability 4) and is present in 
over 90% of traumatic anterior shoulder dislocation. 5,6) A 
concomitant SLAP lesion occurs in up to 22% of anterior 
instabilities, 1,7) the presence of which greatly increases 
shoulder instability. 8-10) As such, it has been suggested that 
more extensive lesions are a result of an increased number </p>

<p>and superior labrum from anterior to posterior (SLAP) lesions, and to analyze the effect of concomitant SLAP repair on surgical out-</p>

<p>comes. 
Methods: We retrospectively reviewed patients who underwent arthroscopic stabilization for anterior shoulder instability between </p>

<p>January 2004 and March 2013. A total of 120 patients were available for at least 1-year follow-up. Forty-four patients with repa-</p>

<p>rable concomitant detached SLAP lesions (group I) underwent combined SLAP and anterior stabilization, and 76 patients without </p>

<p>SLAP lesions (group II) underwent anterior stabilization alone. Patient characteristics, preoperative and postoperative pain scores, </p>

<p>Rowe scores, and shoulder ranges of motion were compared between the 2 groups. 
Results: Patients in group I had higher incidences of high-energy trauma (p = 0.03), worse preoperative pain visual analogue scale </p>

<p>(VAS) (p = 0.02), and Rowe scores (p = 0.04). The postoperative pain VAS and Rowe scores improved equally in both groups without </p>

<p>significant differences. Limitation in postoperative range of motion was similar between the groups (all p-value &gt; 0.05). 
Conclusions: Anterior instability with SLAP lesion may not be related to frequent episodes of dislocation but rather to a high-</p>

<p>energy trauma. SLAP fixation with anterior stabilization procedures did not lead to poor functional outcomes if appropriate surgical </p>

<p>techniques were followed. 
Keywords: Anterior instability, Superior labrum anterior posterior lesion, Bankart repair, Anterior instability outcomes, Shoulder </p>

<p>dislocation </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery 2016;8:168-174 • http://dx.doi.org/10.4055/cios.2016.8.2.168 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016 by The Korean Orthopaedic Association </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0) 
which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • pISSN 2005-291X eISSN 2005-4408 </p>

<p>Received July 26, 2015; Accepted December 16, 2015 
Correspondence to: Joo Han Oh, MD 
Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Seoul National University Bundang 
Hospital, 82 Gumi-ro 173beon-gil, Bundang-gu, Seongnam 13620, Korea 
Tel: +82-31-787-7197, Fax: +82-31-787-4056 
E-mail: ohjh1@snu.ac.kr </p>



<p>Durban et al. Anterior Shoulder Instability with or without a SLAP Lesion </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 8, No. 2, 2016 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>of dislocations and treatment of both lesions is imperative 
to restore joint stability. 3-5,11) 
However, this is not always true since extensive 
lesions have been noted with a low number of disloca-
tions in the presence of a high-energy trauma. 12,13) As 
such, other authors believe that reattachment of the con-
comitant SLAP lesion depends on the age and functional 
demands of the patient, noting that biceps tenodesis or 
tenotomy had varied results. Most studies claim that there 
is no significant difference in the range of motion (ROM), 
functional scores, and recurrence rates when compared to 
patients who underwent Bankart repair alone; 8,14-16) how-
ever, a number of authors have noted several limitations 
of ROM, especially in external rotation, among those who 
underwent the combined procedure. 8,17) 
To investigate these problems further, the authors 
compared the clinical characteristics of patients who had 
anterior shoulder instability with and without SLAP lesion. 
In addition, we analyzed the effect of concomitant SLAP 
repair on surgical outcome after arthroscopic stabiliza-
tion of anterior instability. We hypothesized that anterior 
shoulder instability with SLAP lesion would be related to 
high-energy trauma or more episodes of dislocation com-
pared to shoulder instability without SLAP lesion, and that 
shoulder ROM will decrease after combined arthroscopic 
anterior capsulolabral reconstruction and SLAP repair, re-
sulting in poorer clinical outcomes. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Inclusion and Exclusion Criteria 
The study was approved by the hospital's Institutional Re-
view Board (IRB number: B-1407/258-108) and we retro-
spectively reviewed the prospectively collected data of pa-
tients who underwent arthroscopic anterior capsulolabral 
reconstruction in the senior author's institution between 
January 2004 and March 2013 and included those who 
met the following criteria: (1) had posttraumatic anterior 
instability and (2) were available for follow-up for at least 
1 year after surgery. We excluded patients with previous 
stabilization procedures performed by another surgeon, 
multiple surgeries due to recurrent dislocations, biceps te-
notomy or tenodesis, and detached SLAP lesions that were 
not repaired because the lesions were asymptomatic, or 
had no physical findings regarding SLAP lesions. Patients 
with humeral avulsion of glenohumeral ligament or bony 
Bankart lesions exceeding 20% of the glenoid were also 
excluded. 
A total of 198 patients underwent arthroscopic sta-
bilization for anterior shoulder instability during the in-</p>

<p>dexed period and 120 (61%) were available for functional 
assessment at least 1 year after surgery. We divided the 
patients into 2 groups according to the presence of SLAP 
lesion. All SLAP lesions were type II (63.6% of type V) by 
Snyder's classification. 1) There were 44 patients (36.7%) 
with reparable concomitant detached SLAP lesions (group 
I) and 76 patients (63.3%) without (group II); patients in 
group II served as the control population. Hand domi-
nance, level of sports activity, and presence of a high-en-
ergy trauma were evaluated together with the population 
demographics. Injuries sustained through sports or falls 
from a height, thus causing forceful abduction and exter-
nal rotation, traction, forceful hyperextension, or result-
ing in direct blows to the shoulder were considered high-
energy trauma. </p>

<p>Range of Motion Evaluation and Functional Outcome 
Assessment 
Range of external rotation in 0° and in 90° of abduction 
was measured using a goniometer. Internal rotation at 
the back was assessed with the patients sitting upright 
and their hands placed at their backs as high as possible. 
Anatomic reference points were the inferior border of 
the scapula for the seventh thoracic vertebra (T7) and the 
highest point of the iliac crest for the fourth lumbar verte-
bra (L4). For ease of statistical analysis, the vertebral levels 
were converted into numeric values as follows: T1-12 to 
1-12, L1-5 to 13-17, and sacrum to 18. 
Functional outcomes were evaluated using the Rowe 
score, wherein lesser scores denote worse shoulder condi-
tion. The visual analogue scale (VAS) for pain was used 
to grade the pain suffered by the patient, with 0 being no 
pain and 10 being the worst pain experienced. Patient sat-
isfaction with regard to the surgical outcome and improve-
ment was also rated using the VAS, with 10 being the best 
score. 
The ROM and functional outcome measurements 
were evaluated during preoperative admission, 6 months 
and 1 year postoperatively, and annually thereafter. The 
scores and ranges of motion at the final follow-up visit 
were used for the statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Surgical Procedure 
All patients underwent arthroscopic surgery performed 
by the senior surgeon. Anterior shoulder stabilization con-
sisted of a Bankart or ALPSA lesion fixation with capsular 
plication, with or without a rotator interval (RI) closure. 
Additional RI closure using additional suture anchor was 
confined to patients who demonstrated definite sulcus 
sign with shoulder in the external rotation position. A </p>



<p>Durban et al. Anterior Shoulder Instability with or without a SLAP Lesion </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 8, No. 2, 2016 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>concurrent SLAP lesion was repaired between the 10-to 
12-o' clock positions on a right shoulder, to avoid anterior 
labral and capsular plication at the 12-to 2-o' clock posi-
tions. 
We used the lateral decubitus position for the shoul-
der arthroscopy with the operated arm pulled by a trac-
tion device (ACUFEX; Smith &amp; Nephew, Andover, MA, 
USA) with approximately 4 kg of weight (10 lb). During 
anterior capsulolabral reconstruction, an additional lateral 
traction device was applied for lateral pulling of the arm to 
obtain easy access to the anterior compartment of the gle-
nohumeral joint. Diagnostic arthroscopy was performed 
throughout the standard posterior portal as the viewing 
portal, and an anteroinferior portal as the primary work-
ing portal. After overall examination of the glenohumeral 
joint, the additional anterosuperior portal was used as the 
secondary working portal for procedures on the anterior 
labrum or capsule. 
For Bankart repair or anterior capsular shift, the 
abnormally attached labrum or anteroinferior glenohu-
meral ligament was mobilized from the glenoid neck, then 
2-to 3-mm wide subchondral bone was exposed using a 
motorized burr for the recipient bed. The capsule together 
with the anterior labrum, when present, were sutured and 
tacked down using 3 or 4 evenly spaced suture anchors 
(BIOKNOTLESS; Depuy Mitek Inc., Raynham, MA, USA) 
between the 2-to 6-o' clock positions, on the right shoul-
der. 
For repair of a SLAP lesion, we used the trans-rota-
tor cuff portal, as described by O'Brien et al. 18) and Oh et 
al. 19) to achieve the appropriate angle for anchor insertion. 
After preparation of the subchondral bone of the superior 
glenoid rim, 1 to 2 anchors (BIOKNOTLESS) were used 
for repair of the superior labrum in most cases. To prevent 
postoperative external rotation limitation, we did not fix 
the anterosuperior labrum (1-to 2-o' clock position), and 
released the superior and posterosuperior capsule after 
fixation of SLAP lesion. </p>

<p>Postoperative Rehabilitation 
A standardized rehabilitation protocol was applied to all 
patients. Immobilization neutral rotation with an abduc-
tion pillow was maintained for 6 weeks. ROM exercises 
were initiated at 6 weeks after surgery and the brace was 
discontinued. Muscle-strengthening exercises commenced 
3 months after surgery, and were continued until at least 6 
months postoperatively. Return to sports was permitted 6 
months after surgery. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
All statistical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">IBM SPSS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 20</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Co., Armonk, NY, USA</rs>) with a 95% confi-
dence level. We used the independent t-test to compare 
data from the groups and a p-value of less than 0.05 was 
considered to indicate significance. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Demographics 
A total of 120 patients were included in the study (Table 1). 
The mean age of the patients was 24 years (range, 15 to 69 
years), with a mean follow-up of 32.3 months (range, 12 to 
92 months). There were 104 males and 16 females. 
In group I, there were 41 males and 3 females, with 
an average age of 24.6 years (range, 17 to 49 years). The 
dominant shoulder was involved in 28 patients (63.6%). 
The mean symptom duration was 49.5 months before 
surgery, with a mean pain VAS of 5.6. A history of high-
energy trauma to the affected shoulder was noted in 40 pa-
tients (90.9%), and there was an average of 8.3 dislocations 
per shoulder. Twenty-seven patients engaged in overhead 
sports and 21 were involved in competition-level sports. 
In group II, there were 63 males and 13 females, 
with an average age of 23.6 years (range, 15 to 69 years). </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic Data of Patients </p>

<p>Demographic data 
Group I 
(SLAP+) 
Group II 
(SLAP-) 
p-value </p>

<p>No. of patients 
44 
76 </p>

<p>Age at surgery (yr), mean (range) 24.6 (17-49) 23.6 (15-69) 
0.54 </p>

<p>Follow-up (mo), mean (range) 
34.9 (12-92) 30.9 (12-75) 
0.31 </p>

<p>Sex (male:female) 
41:3 
63:13 
0.11 </p>

<p>Dominant arm involvement 
28 (63.6) 
52 (68.4) 
0.60 </p>

<p>Symptom duration (mo) 
49.5 ± 47.3 
65.2 ± 75.7 
0.22 </p>

<p>Age at first dislocation (yr) 
20.4 ± 5.3 
17.9 ± 10.1 
0.12 </p>

<p>No. of dislocation episodes 
8.3 ± 15.4 
13.6 ± 20.7 
0.15 </p>

<p>History of high-energy trauma 
40 (90.9) 
57 (75.0) 
0.03* </p>

<p>Pain visual analogue scale 
5.6 ± 3.0 
4.3 ± 3.0 
0.02* </p>

<p>Degree of sports (competition/ 
recreation) 
21 (47.7) 
35 (46.1) 
0.33 </p>

<p>Overhead sports 
27 (61.2) 
40 (52.6) 
0.36 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation or number (%). 
SLAP: superior labrum from anterior to posterior. 
*Statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05). </p>



<p>Durban et al. Anterior Shoulder Instability with or without a SLAP Lesion </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 8, No. 2, 2016 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>The dominant shoulder was involved in 52 patients 
(68.4%). The mean symptom duration was 65.2 months 
before surgery, with a mean pain VAS of 4.3. A history of 
high-energy trauma to the affected shoulder was noted in 
57 patients (75.0%), and there was an average of 13.6 dis-
locations per shoulder. Forty patients engaged in overhead 
sports and 35 were involved in competition-level sports. 
Patients with anterior instability and detached SLAP 
lesion (group I) had a significantly higher incidence of 
high-energy trauma (p = 0.03), and patients in group II 
had a younger mean age of dislocation, longer symptom 
duration and more episodes of dislocation; however, these 
were not significantly different from group I (p = 0.12, p = 
0.22, and p = 0.15, respectively). 
A Bankart, ALPSA, or bony Bankart lesion was en-
countered marginally, more frequently in patients with de-
tached SLAP lesion, while there were a greater number of 
patients with RI incompetency in SLAP-negative patients, 
but the difference was not significant (p = 0.49) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Evaluation of Clinical Outcomes 
Preoperative shoulder external rotation in 90° abduction 
and internal rotation were better in group I than in group 
II, though the differences were not significant (p = 0.28 
and p = 0.84, respectively). Generally, there was noted 
limitation in all ROMs in group I postoperatively, but 
the changes in ROM were not significantly different than 
those observed in group II (Table 3). 
Group I patients had higher pain VAS (p = 0.02) and 
lower Rowe (p = 0.04) scores preoperatively, as compared 
to those in group II (Table 4). The pain VAS and func-
tion scores of both groups improved postoperatively. Both 
groups were equally satisfied with their condition (p = 0.91) 
and the redislocation rate was similar (p = 0.27). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In the current study, patients with anterior instability and 
detached SLAP lesion had a significantly higher incidence 
of high-energy trauma (p = 0.03). However, the mean age 
at the first dislocation, symptom duration before surgery, 
and the number of dislocations were not significantly </p>

<p>Table 2. Radiologic Characteristics </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Group I (SLAP+) 
(n = 44) 
Group II (SLAP-) 
(n = 76) 
p-value </p>

<p>Bankart or ALPSA lesion 
42 (95.5) 
64 (84.2) 
0.07 </p>

<p>Hill-Sachs lesion 
35 (79.6) 
55 (72.4) 
0.34 </p>

<p>Rotator interval 
incompetency* 
8 (18.2) 
18 (23.7) 
0.49 </p>

<p>Bony Bankart lesion 
16 (36.4) 
16 (21.1) 
0.07 </p>

<p>Values are presented as number (%). 
SLAP: superior labrum from anterior to posterior, ALPSA: anterior labral 
periosteal sleeve avulsion. 
*Rotator interval incompetency: tear or redundancy. </p>

<p>Table 3. Preoperative and Postoperative Range of Motion </p>

<p>Variable 
Group I 
(SLAP+) 
Group II 
(SLAP-) 
p-value </p>

<p>ER arm at side </p>

<p>Preoperative 
79.0 ± 17.8 
81.3 ± 15.1 
0.42 </p>

<p>Postoperative 
77.7 ± 16.3 
76.6 ± 19.2 
0.74 </p>

<p>Change in ROM 
-1.3 ± 20.2 
-4.6 ± 18.7 
0.32 </p>

<p>ER at 90° abduction </p>

<p>Preoperative 
100.8 ± 22.8 
96.5 ± 18.8 
0.28 </p>

<p>Postoperative 
99.6 ± 16.4 
99.5 ± 17.0 
0.98 </p>

<p>Change in ROM 
-1.3 ± 27.3 
2.79 ± 22.1 
0.37 </p>

<p>IR (spine level) </p>

<p>Preoperative 
5.8 ± 2.7 
6.0 ± 2.5 
0.84 </p>

<p>Postoperative 
6.7 ± 1.5 
7.1 ± 1.8 
0.19 </p>

<p>Change in ROM 
-0.8 ± 2.7 
-0.91 ± 2.5 
0.69 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation. 
SLAP: superior labrum from anterior to posterior, ER: external rotation, ROM: 
range of motion, IR: internal rotation. </p>

<p>Table 4. Functional Outcome Scores and Redislocation Rates </p>

<p>Variable 
Group I (SLAP+) 
(n = 44) 
Group II (SLAP-) 
(n = 76) 
p-value </p>

<p>Pain VAS </p>

<p>Preoperative 
5.62 ± 3.0 
4.3 ± 3.1 
0.02* </p>

<p>Postoperative 
1.1 ± 2.0 
0.9 ± 1.8 
0.53 </p>

<p>Rowe score </p>

<p>Preoperative 
56.1 ± 12.9 
62.0 ± 14.4 
0.04* </p>

<p>Postoperative 
87.6 ± 15.3 
89.2 ± 14.3 
0.57 </p>

<p>Satisfaction VAS 
8.4 ± 1.6 
8.40 ± 2.2 
0.91 </p>

<p>Redislocation 
3 (6.8) 
2 (2.6) 
0.27 </p>

<p>Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation or number (%). 
SLAP: superior labrum from anterior to posterior, VAS: visual analogue scale. 
*Statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05). </p>



<p>Durban et al. Anterior Shoulder Instability with or without a SLAP Lesion </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 8, No. 2, 2016 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>different between the 2 groups. Involvement of the domi-
nant arm was similar in both groups, as were the degree 
of sports and participation in overhead sports. On the 
whole, patients in group I suffered more pain, had more 
difficulties in performing daily activities, perceived a more 
unstable shoulder, and were more dissatisfied with their 
shoulder condition, as evidenced by higher pain VAS (p = 
0.02) and lower Rowe (p = 0.04) scores preoperatively. 
Patients in group II had a younger mean age at dis-
location, longer symptom duration and more episodes of 
dislocation; however, these were not significantly different 
from group I (p = 0.12, p = 0.22, and p = 0.15, respec-
tively). Bony and soft tissue injuries were more severe in 
patients with SLAP lesion, group I, which suggests that 
instability with SLAP lesion may be related not to the 
chronicity or frequency of shoulder dislocation but to the 
presence of high-energy trauma. 
Several studies have noted that patient age at the 
time of first dislocation greatly influences the subsequent 
number of dislocations and have suggested that an in-
creased number of dislocations creates more-severe labral 
tears. 15,20) Younger age and longer time from initial injury 
to surgery contribute to the propagation of the injuries, 
which in turn worsens the present instability. 4,5) However, 
recent investigations have reported that a history of high-
energy trauma to the involved shoulder may also account 
for extensive lesions and severe instability even after a 
single dislocation. Kim et al. 13) reported that 68.7% of pa-
tients with fewer than five dislocations had extensive cir-
cumferential labral lesions. Likewise, radiologic evaluation 
of shoulder dislocation patients showed superior labral 
involvement in 39% of patients with a single episode. 12) 
In the current study, we observed that patients with a com-
bined anterior instability and detached SLAP lesion had sig-
nificantly higher incidence of high-energy trauma (p = 0.03) 
and fewer episodes of dislocation (p = 0.15). This suggests 
that the severity of the lesions may not be secondary to 
progression of a simple injury; rather, it was a result of the 
initial trauma. As such, this supports our hypothesis that 
anterior shoulder instability with SLAP lesion is related to 
high-energy trauma. 
Preoperative pain VAS and Rowe scores were signif-
icantly worse in patients with SLAP lesions, despite having 
fewer dislocation episodes. The current findings are in 
accordance with those of Kim et al. 13) who reported that 
patients with more severe labral lesions had worse pre-
operative pain VAS and functional scores and consulted 
sooner than those with only a Bankart or ALPSA lesion, 
most likely because of the more severe pain and limitation 
of activity of daily living. Postoperatively, their patients </p>

<p>had similarly improved ROM and shoulder scores, despite 
the degree of injury and extent of repair. These are consis-
tent with previous reports that the functional outcomes of 
patients with combined lesions are not dependent on con-
comitant SLAP repair. 15) Therefore, we ascertain that SLAP 
repair combined with an anterior stabilization procedure 
does not lead to poor functional outcomes if appropriate 
surgical procedures and methodical postoperative reha-
bilitation are performed. 
The objective of surgical management is to provide 
adequate joint stability, pain relief, and shoulder ROM 
comparable to the preinjury level so that the patient may 
return to his or her preinjury status. The basic tenet in the 
treatment of anterior shoulder instability is to recognize 
that surrounding structures, aside from the Bankart lesion, 
contribute to the pathology. Fixation of both the Bankart 
lesion and symptomatic SLAP lesion has been advocated 
by some authors, since fixation of only one would still 
result in residual instability in some cases. 3,11,21) A biome-
chanical study of SLAP repair showed that, when all other 
structures in the joint are intact, a SLAP repair alone helps 
to normalize the glenohumeral translation. However, 
when there was an additional pathology, the repair was 
rendered ineffective. 22) Another cadaveric study by Mihata 
et al. 10) investigated the effect of combined type II SLAP 
lesions with anterior capsular laxity, as would be seen in 
throwing athletes. They noted increased external rotation 
and anterior glenohumeral translation after simulation 
of anterior capsular laxity and type II SLAP lesion. After 
arthroscopic repair of the SLAP lesion alone, there was a 
significant decrease in the external rotation; however, this 
did not fully restore anterior glenohumeral translation. 10) 
As such, most authors would recommend fixation of both 
lesions to restore primary shoulder stability, which is es-
sential to allow postoperative rehabilitation, while pre-
venting residual laxity. Furthermore, repair of the SLAP 
lesion, especially in younger and more active patients, 
promoted return to overhead sports, and good outcomes 
can be achieved with appropriate treatment. 16,23) However, 
concerns regarding limitation of shoulder motion second-
ary to over-tightening of the capsulolabral complex or 
over-treatment have been raised. Postoperative decrease in 
shoulder ROM may be expected in most procedures and a 
decrease specifically in external rotation has been noted to 
occur, especially after combined anterior shoulder stabili-
zation and SLAP repair. 14,18) 
Although recovery of shoulder ROM may be slower 
in this subset of patients, no difference was noted in the 
final ROM after 1 year. In the current study, the surgical 
technique for anterior capsulolabral reconstruction was </p>



<p>Durban et al. Anterior Shoulder Instability with or without a SLAP Lesion </p>

<p>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery • Vol. 8, No. 2, 2016 • www.ecios.org </p>

<p>identical in both groups. For the concurrent SLAP repair, 
we repaired between the 10-to 12-o' clock positions on a 
right shoulder and avoided anterior labral and capsular 
plication at the 12-to 2-o' clock positions. This fixation was 
firm and stable, and at the same time, provided some slack 
to the biceps anchor to maintain some external rotation. 
After fixation of SLAP lesions, authors always also release 
the superior and posterosuperior capsule. As such, we did 
not observe a significant decrease in external rotation in 
our patients with combined labral lesions. While there was 
indeed a decrease in the ROM at final follow-up, this was 
not different from the final ROM of the patients without 
SLAP lesions. Therefore, care should be taken during the 
surgery to preserve postoperative external rotation. 
There are some limitations to be mentioned in the 
present study. First, the natural history of untreated as-
ymptomatic SLAP lesions and their possible effect on 
the patient outcomes is unclear. Patients with anterior 
shoulder instability with asymptomatic detached SLAP 
lesions and those who underwent biceps tenodesis with 
anterior stabilization procedures instead of SLAP fixation 
should also be evaluated. Second, high-energy trauma is a 
somewhat vague and subjective experience. However, we 
confined high-energy trauma if shoulders were dislocated </p>

<p>after a forceful traumatic event, such as vehicle accident, 
fall with outstretched hand and so on. Third, the number 
of subjects was limited and the length of follow-up in this 
retrospective study was relatively short. Also, the high rate 
of patients lost to follow up could pose a risk of type I er-
ror. A prospective study with mid-term follow-up would 
facilitate determination of differences in patient perfor-
mance and return to sports between the 2 groups. 
In conclusion, the extent of labral lesion was not 
dependent on the number of preoperative dislocations, 
but related to the amount of energy exerted during the 
initial dislocation. Our findings show that combined ar-
throscopic anterior capsulolabral reconstruction and ad-
ditional fixation of SLAP lesion can yield good to excellent 
functional outcomes, if appropriate surgical procedures 
are conducted, such as saving anterosuperior labral fixa-
tion and superior and posterosuperior capsular release 
after SLAP fixation. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was 
reported. </p>







</text></tei>