<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4078681" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Background Rapid increases in marketing of 
e-cigarettes coincide with growth in e-cigarette use in 
recent years; however, little is known about how 
e-cigarettes are marketed on social media platforms. 
Methods Keywords were used to collect tweets related 
to e-cigarettes from the Twitter Firehose between 1 May 
2012 and 30 June 2012. Tweets were coded for 
smoking cessation mentions, as well as health and 
safety mentions, and were classified as commercial or 
non-commercial ('organic') tweets using a combination 
of Naïve Bayes machine learning methods, keyword 
algorithms and human coding. Metadata associated with 
each tweet were used to examine the characteristics of 
accounts tweeting about e-cigarettes. 
Results 73 672 tweets related to e-cigarettes were 
captured in the study period, 90% of which were 
classified as commercial tweets. Accounts tweeting 
commercial e-cigarette content were associated with 
lower Klout scores, a measure of influence. Commercial 
tweeting was largely driven by a small group of highly 
active accounts, and 94% of commercial tweets included 
links to websites, many of which sell or promote 
e-cigarettes. Approximately 10% of commercial and 
organic tweets mentioned smoking cessation, and 34% 
of commercial tweets included mentions of prices or 
discounts for e-cigarettes. 
Conclusions Twitter appears to be an important 
marketing platform for e-cigarettes. Tweets related to 
e-cigarettes were overwhelmingly commercial, and a 
substantial proportion mentioned smoking cessation. 
E-cigarette marketing on Twitter may have public health 
implications. Continued surveillance of e-cigarette 
marketing on social media platforms is needed. </p>

<p>Awareness and use of Electronic Nicotine Delivery 
Systems (commonly known as electronic cigarettes 
or e-cigarettes) have increased rapidly among adults 
and youth in the past few years. Two recent studies 
found that ever use of e-cigarettes doubled among 
adults between 2010 and 2011 (from 3.3% to 
6.2%), 
1 and among youth between 2011 and 2012 
(from 3.3% to 6.8%). 
2 Coinciding with this 
increase is the rapid expansion of e-cigarette mar-
keting on a variety of media channels, including the 
internet and traditional platforms ( print, radio, 
event sponsorship and TV) some of which have 
long prohibited tobacco advertising. 
Because e-cigarettes are not currently subject to 
the same marketing restrictions as traditional cigar-
ettes, researchers and the public health community 
have expressed concern about potential impact of 
the rapid expansion of e-cigarette marketing on 
e-cigarette initiation and transition to regular use of </p>

<p>electronic and combustible cigarettes, especially 
given limited scientific evidence related to these 
products' long-term health impact, efficacy in 
smoking substitution or cessation, 
3 and potential 
role in combustible tobacco uptake. Therefore 
understanding the scope and content of e-cigarette 
marketing across various media platforms becomes 
critically important. Social media could be used to 
promote e-cigarettes' role in smoking cessation 
despite limited scientific evidence supporting such 
claims, and there is evidence that such claims are 
found on social media. 
4 Better understanding of 
e-cigarette marketing on social media can provide 
valuable insights towards characterising forces that 
propelled the exponential growth of e-cigarettes 
from 2010 to 2012. Isolating and analysing the 
impact of e-cigarette marketing on the microblog-
ging platform Twitter is important because Twitter 
use is widespread and growing rapidly, particularly 
among young adults and minority populations. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Examining e-cigarette marketing on social media 
platforms is also important from a US policy per-
spective. Due to recent court rulings, the US Food 
and Drug Administration (FDA) cannot regulate 
e-cigarettes as drugs or medical devices unless they 
are marketed for therapeutic purposes. 
6 While 
FDA can regulate e-cigarettes as tobacco products 
as a result of the 2009 Family Smoking Prevention 
and Tobacco Control Act, the agency has yet to 
announce its specific plan for e-cigarette regulation 
in the USA. Ample evidence indicates that internet 
messaging has been employed to bypass marketing 
restrictions on combustible tobacco. 
7 8 Discovering 
how e-cigarettes are marketed online and on social 
media has important and direct relevance to poten-
tial FDA regulations for these products. 
Our study fills these research gaps by examining 
a snapshot of e-cigarette marketing on Twitter over 
a 2-month period (May-June 2012). Twitter is a 
microblogging website that forms a valuable reposi-
tory of public information on consumer attitudes 
and behaviours. Twitter's popularity has increased 
rapidly since its founding in 2006; over 200 
million active monthly users worldwide now 
produce more than 500 million tweets and 2.1 
billion Twitter search engine queries daily. 
9 Users of 
Twitter tend to be young (30% of internet users on 
Twitter were aged 18-29 years in 2013) and 
members of minority groups (27% of internet users 
on Twitter were African American and 28% Latino 
in 2013, compared with 14% White). 
5 Data gener-
ated through Twitter is not limited to the content 
of tweets themselves, but also includes metadata 
attached to each tweet, such as time posted and 
user-level information including geo-identifiers 
(when user-enabled) and number of accounts a user </p>

<p>Open Access 
Scan to access more 
free content </p>

<p> 
Huang J, et al. Tob Control 2014;23:iii26-iii30. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2014-051551 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>is followed by and follows, and user's Klout score (a measure of 
a user's influence on social media platforms). 
10 Tweet content 
and associated metadata can be leveraged to track communica-
tions by consumers and companies. 
In this paper, we use a novel methodology to capture and 
analyse e-cigarette related tweets and metadata through the 
Twitter Firehose (Twitter's certified complete data stream), 
measuring the volume of Twitter communications related to 
e-cigarettes and quantifying the extent to which tweets about 
e-cigarettes include mentions of smoking cessation, safety and 
price promotions. In addition, we quantify the proportion of 
e-cigarette tweets tied to commercial interests and those reflect-
ing putatively 'organic' points of view and experiences. We also 
estimate the influence of commercial and organic e-cigarette 
tweets by using user-level metadata including Klout score and 
number of followers. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Data collection </p>

<p>Through a licensed Twitter data provider (Gnip; http://www. 
gnip.com), we obtained access (for an institutionally negotiated 
fee) to the Twitter Firehose. In contrast to the publicly available 
Twitter data stream (Twitter API), which provides approximately 
1% of all real-time tweets, the Firehose provides real-time 
search access to 100% of all tweets, as well as metadata asso-
ciated with each tweet. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Tweets related to e-cigarettes were identified and collected 
from the Firehose if they contained one or more keywords of 
interest, identified via expert consensus ('e-cigarette,' 'ecigar-
ette,' 'e-cig,' or 'ecig'). By 'expert consensus' we refer to review 
by our interdisciplinary team of collaborators representing sub-
stantial expertise in health behaviour and public health policy 
research. Tweets that included additional relevant keywords 
('electronic,' 'blu,' 'njoy') along with the word 'cig' or 'cigarette' 
anywhere in the tweet text also were included. Blu and Njoy 
were selected as the top-selling e-cigarette brands in the USA 
according to Nielsen. 
12 It should also be noted that variations 
of the keyword 'vape' were not included in our search terms; 
we focused on search terms with extremely high precision at the 
expense of recalling the corpus of e-cigarette related tweets. 
Twitter is a global platform on which a tweet from any loca-
tion can be viewed by users from any location and where geolo-
cation often cannot be reliably determined; however, our data 
collection sought to gather only English-language tweets to 
focus the analyses. 
A random sample of 500 collected tweets was reviewed to 
assess whether tweets were relevant to e-cigarettes (over 99%) 
and whether they were in English (99%). </p>

<p>Content coding </p>

<p>An iterative process combining human coding and machine learn-
ing was used to classify all collected tweets as either organic or 
commercial. <rs type="software">DiscoverText</rs>, a cloud-based text analytics software, 
was used to collect, archive and machine-classify tweets. 
<rs type="software">DiscoverText</rs> requires no text preprocessing prior to coding. This 
is the first study to apply this novel methodology to analysing 
content related to e-cigarettes. Organic tweets were those 
deemed non-sponsored; they reflected individual opinions or 
experiences or linked to non-promotional content. Commercial 
tweets were defined by presence of any of the following: branded 
promotional messages; URLs linking to commercial websites; 
usernames indicating affiliations with commercial sites; or user's 
Twitter page consisting only of promotional tweets (ie, spammer 
accounts). For the purposes of this study, a tweet containing a </p>

<p>commercial link was coded as 'commercial' regardless of whether 
it was posted by an ostensibly individual account. Thus our defin-
ition of 'commercial' would include many tweets posted by 
'affiliate marketers.' Commercial websites included those that dir-
ectly sold e-cigarette related products as well as 'landing' or 
'affiliate' websites for sales </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>; these sites did not themselves sell 
e-cigarette related products but promoted or reviewed these pro-
ducts and linked to retailer sites. 
Two human coders coded a random sample of 2000 collected 
tweets, using tweet content as well as the associated metadata to 
determine whether tweets were commercial or organic. The two 
coders achieved notably high agreement (κ=0.93) on an add-
itional overlap sample of 500 tweets. The coded set of tweets 
was used to train a machine classifier using a Naïve Bayes algo-
rithm; the machine classifier was applied to the full set of col-
lected tweets. When we tested agreement between machine 
classification and a human coder in an additional sample of 500 
tweets, we found that the machine classifier identified tweets as 
'commercial' with high levels of accuracy but was less accurate 
in identifying 'organic' tweets; the machine algorithm misclassi-
fied commercial tweets as organic more often than the reverse. 
Rather than reviewing all classified tweets, we systematically 
reviewed and recoded select tweets based on relevant features. 
Since our definition of 'commercial' tweets includes those 
linking to commercial sites, we reviewed the most common 
URLs in the data set and, for websites deemed commercial, we 
recoded all tweets containing these URLs as 'commercial.' We 
also reviewed and recoded tweets where the text exactly 
matched other tweets coded as 'commercial' or included some 
common commercial keywords (eg, coupon, discount, free trial, 
starter kit). Finally, we searched account name fields to identify 
those with explicit e-cigarette sales affiliations (eg, VaporGod 
LLC), recoding all tweets posted by such accounts as commer-
cial. Approximately 1500 tweets were recoded. Our final coding 
algorithm was highly consistent with human coders when tested 
on an additional random sample of 500 tweets (κ=0.88). 
A similar combination of human coding and machine classifi-
cation was applied to distinguish tweets that mentioned 
smoking cessation from those that did not. Smoking cessation 
mentions included any references to the use of e-cigarettes in 
quitting or stopping smoking either in the tweet text, the URL 
or the username fields. For example, the following tweets were 
coded as cessation mentions: "Stop smoking with the electronic 
cigarette starter kit..." "Need to quit smoking #ecig," and 
"Give up smoking with electronic cigarettes?" The machine clas-
sifier was trained using a set of 3500 tweets coded by two 
human coders with a high level of agreement (κ=0.90). After 
applying the machine classifier to the full set of collected tweets, 
we compared results with a human coder in an additional 
sample of 500 tweets, finding the machine classifier misclassified 
'no cessation' tweets as 'cessation' more often than the reverse. 
To improve the coding algorithm, we systematically reviewed 
and recoded a subset of tweets based on presence or absence of 
common keywords related to cessation (variations of 'quit*' and 
'stop sm*' in the tweet text, account name or full URL fields). 
We manually reviewed approximately 5000 tweets where 
machine classifier and keyword algorithms disagreed, recoding 
approximately 3500. Our final coding process was consistent 
with human coders (κ=0.87). 
Among commercial tweets, various keywords were used to 
identify those with mentions of health effects (using letter string 
'health') or safety (using the string 'safe') as well as mentions of 
pricing or discounts (using the strings: money, deal, %, $, save, 
promo, dollars, discount, coupon, code, price, cost). </p>

<p>Huang J, et al. Tob Control 2014;23:iii26-iii30. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2014-051551 
iii27 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>Analysis of account information </p>

<p>To measure the potential reach of collected e-cigarette tweets, 
user-level information was analysed, focusing on (A) number of 
followers and (B) Klout score, a proprietary measure of influ-
ence calculated using data from Twitter and other social net-
works (Klout scores range from 1 to 100; higher scores indicate 
greater influence). 
16 Klout was not available for 1889 users 
(8%) and follower data became available from Gnip only as of 
28 May 2012; thus the total times tweets were posted (sum of 
followers for all tweets) is calculated as of June 2012. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Between 1 May and 30 June 2012, our keywords identified a 
total of 73 672 tweets from the Twitter Firehose, almost all of 
which (99%) were relevant to e-cigarettes. These tweets were 
posted by 23 700 separate Twitter users. Average number of total 
e-cigarette tweets per day was 1208 (SD=325). Average number 
of e-cigarette tweets per user over the study period was 3 
(SD=90.7). 
For 14 319 accounts where follower count was available, the 
average number of followers was 845, with the median being 
53. The follower count varied greatly (SD=7230), with 13.4% 
of accounts having fewer than 10 followers and 11.1% of 
accounts having more than 1000 followers. 
Table 1 shows the characteristics of e-cigarette related tweets 
collected, presented in total and separately for organic versus 
commercial. Among collected tweets, 66 102(89.6%) were clas-
sified as commercial. Compared with organic tweets, commer-
cial tweets were more likely to include URLs (94% vs 11%, 
p&lt;0.001) and to be retweets (19% vs 17%, p&lt;0.001). 
There were 17 936 Twitter users who posted commercial 
tweets and 6254 users who posted organic tweets; 490 users 
posted tweets that fell into both categories. The average number 
of e-cigarette tweets by those who posted commercial tweets 
was 3.7, three times higher than among those who posted 
organic tweets (1.2, p=0.002). Although those posting organic 
tweets, on average, had more followers than those posting com-
mercial tweets (867 vs 841), this difference was not statistically 
significant ( p=0.86). Average Klout scores among those posting 
organic e-cigarette tweets was twice as high as among those 
posting commercial e-cigarette tweets (30.6 vs 15.4, p&lt;0.001). 
Of all collected e-cigarette tweets, 63 254 (86%) included 
URLs. Of these tweets, 62 406 (98.7%) were coded as commer-
cial. URLs were predominantly for .com addresses (85.2%), fol-
lowed by .org (4.8%) and .net (4.6%) addresses. The 
most-mentioned website was vaporgod.com (13 244 mentions), </p>

<p>followed by purecigs.com (4546) and bestcelebrex.blogspot.com 
(3232). 
The total times these e-cigarette tweets were posted on 
Twitter feeds (the sum of all followers of all tweets) was nearly 
4 million for organic tweets and 173 million for commercial 
tweets in June 2012, implying that commercial e-cigarette 
tweets were posted on followers' Twitter feeds 45 times as often 
as organic tweets. 
Overall, approximately 11% of e-cigarette tweets were found 
to contain references related to smoking cessation. Cessation 
mentions were more frequent among commercial (11%) than 
among organic tweets (9%, p&lt;0.001). 
Tweet activity was highly concentrated among the most active 
users, with the top three users producing 25% of e-cigarette 
tweets and the top 100 users producing 48% of e-cigarette 
tweets over the study period. Figure 1 depicts the distribution 
of tweets across users, where each dot represents the number of 
users who posted a given number of e-cigarette tweets. The 
figure shows that while approximately 10 000 users tweeted 
about e-cigarettes once, only one user tweeted about e-cigarettes 
over 10 000 times. Out of the top 10 most active users, eight 
had smoking or e-cigarette related usernames; over 99% of 
e-cigarette tweets by these 10 users were coded as commercial 
and 99.6% included URLs. The top 10 most active Twitter 
accounts had a higher-than-average number of followers (5601 
vs 845, 0.7 SD from the mean). The same accounts had an 
average Klout score that was 0.6 SD higher than the mean (26.7 
vs 19.3). 
Of the 23 700 Twitter users who posted about e-cigarettes, 
589 (2% of users) had username fields containing the keywords 
or letter strings 'vape,' 'vapor,' 'cig,' 'smok' or 'elec.' These 589 
users produced 30 046 tweets over the study period, or 40.7% 
of total tweets. Of these tweets, 29 898 (99.5%) were coded as 
commercial. 
The extent of mentions related to e-cigarette health and 
safety, as well as price or discounts, is shown in table 2. Among 
commercial e-cigarette tweets, 2% contained descriptions or 
mentions related to health, and mentions of safety were present 
among approximately 1%. About a third of all commercial 
e-cigarette tweets contained price or discount mentions. </p>

<p>SUMMARY AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Whereas prior studies of tobacco-related content on social net-
works have noted the presence of e-cigarette promotion, 
4 14 our 
study is the first to quantify overall presence of e-cigarette rele-
vant content on Twitter. Unlike previous studies, 
4 15 we analysed </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of organic and commercial tweets </p>

<p>Tweet type </p>

<p>Total 
e-cig 
tweets </p>

<p>Total 
users </p>

<p>Average e-cig 
tweets per user </p>

<p>Average Klout 
per user </p>

<p>Average followers 
per user </p>

<p>Total times 
posted in June* 
(sum of 
followers of all 
tweets) </p>

<p>Includes 
URL 
Retweets </p>

<p>Cessation 
Mention </p>

<p>Commercial 
66 102 
17 936 3.7 (SD=104.3) 
15.4 (SD=10.1) 
848.4 (SD=7004.3) 
173 133 016 
62 406 (94%) 12 520 (19%) 7140 (11%) 
Organic 
7570 
6254 1.2 (SD=1.0) 
30.6 (SD=12.0) 
866.9 (SD=7881.4) 
3 834 216 
848 (11%) 
1270 (17%) 
677 (9%) 
Total 
73 672 
23 700 3.1 (SD=90.7) 
19.3 (SD=12.5) 
844.7 (SD=7229.8) 
176 967 232 
63 254 (86%) 13 790 (19%) 7817 (11%) 
Difference 
between 
commercial and 
organic: p value </p>

<p>0.002 
&lt;0.001 
0.856 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>*Total times posted represents the number of times tweets appeared on feeds, and was calculated by summing the total number of followers for each collected tweet. This calculation 
represents activity for June only, reflecting the availability of follower counts from our data supplier. </p>

<p> 
Huang J, et al. Tob Control 2014;23:iii26-iii30. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2014-051551 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>metadata associated with each tweet to better understand poten-
tial reach of e-cigarette-related tweets across the platform. Our 
analyses revealed that advertising and promotion represents the 
overwhelming majority of Twitter content related to e-cigarettes. 
Over a 2-month period in 2012, we found that 90% of nearly 
74 000 tweets related to e-cigarettes contained commercial 
content-either promotional messages or URLs linked to com-
mercial websites promoting e-cigarette use. Commercial tweeting 
about e-cigarettes was largely driven by a small number of highly 
active users. The fact that 25% of all tweets examined were gen-
erated by just three users suggests an automated process-these 
users may be 'bots' set by commercial bodies to tweet on a bulk 
level. The vast majority of commercial e-cigarette tweets con-
tained links to websites and a third included price or discount 
appeals; more than 1 in 10 commercial tweets mentioned 
smoking cessation. The finding that e-cigarettes are extensively 
marketed on Twitter is consistent with the increasing levels of 
e-cigarette web searches and sales. 
12 16 Our findings are consist-
ent with those of Prochaska et al 
4 who found that many Twitter 
accounts dedicated to smoking cessation included links to com-
mercial e-cigarette sites. While only 11% of the e-cigarette tweets 
collected in this study mentioned smoking cessation, the high 
absolute number of such mentions is noteworthy. 
The rapid growth in the popularity of e-cigarettes may in part 
reflect marketing and networking efforts through Twitter, the 
extent of which has been demonstrated by our findings in this 
study. Some researchers have hypothesised that, due to lack of </p>

<p>regulatory standards, social media may play an increased role in 
the diffusion of tobacco products and pro-smoking messages. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Prior to emergence of e-cigarette TV ads in late 2012, e-cigarettes 
were primarily marketed online 
17 ; however, the extent and strat-
egies of online marketing were not well-understood. 
Our study offers strong evidence of the presence of e-cigarettes 
marketing on Twitter, a non-trivial portion of which contains 
mentions related to smoking cessation and price promotions. 
Price promotion and discounting significantly influence product 
uptake and consumption, an association strongly demonstrated 
for regular cigarettes. 
18 E-cigarette marketing on Twitter may 
have contributed to the rapid rise in e-cigarette popularity. 
Results of our analysis of Twitter data have implications for the 
marketing of e-cigarettes on other social media platforms due to 
high levels of cross-platform interaction. Given the substantial 
youth presence on social media, 
5 the marketing of e-cigarettes on 
those platforms may entice non-smokers-youth in particular-
to experiment with and initiate e-cigarette use. 
These results have direct and important implications for 
future FDA regulations on e-cigarettes and related products, par-
ticularly with respect to marketing restrictions on social media. 
To the extent that e-cigarette safety and efficacy have not yet 
been fully studied, extensive marketing of the products on social 
media may carry public health risks. The recent court case deci-
sion 
6 was predicated on the company's assertion that 
e-cigarettes were not marketed as cessation devices, a claim con-
tradicted by our findings. Learning the extent to which 
e-cigarette marketing appeals to new users who had not previ-
ously used tobacco-especially children and adolescents-and 
affects initiation is a stated FDA research priority. 
19 Given the 
pervasiveness of e-cigarette marketing on Twitter (and likely 
other social media platforms) and the substantial youth presence 
on those platforms, it is imperative for the FDA to closely 
monitor content and reach of such strategies and adopt appro-
priate social media marketing regulations for tobacco products, 
including e-cigarettes, that are consistent with the Family 
Smoking Prevention and Tobacco Control Act. 
Our study has several limitations and raises questions for 
future research. First, our study is cross-sectional in nature, 
examining e-cigarette-related tweets for a short 2-month 
window, and does not examine trends over time. Future studies 
can use our analyses as a starting point to examine trends in 
volume of e-cigarette-related content on Twitter. Second, the 
time frame during which our data were collected was just prior 
to the launch of major e-cigarette TV marketing. Thus we were 
unable to examine the relationships between televised e-cigarette 
ads and Twitter conversation. Future research should seek to 
clarify these relationships. Third, we may have overlooked 
important keywords including emerging brands and variations 
of slang terms 'vape.' Pilot testing indicated that slang terms 
involving variations of 'vape' were less precise than the key-
words we selected (eg, 'vapes' may refer to marijuana vapori-
sers). We focused on precision rather than recall since including 
less relevant keywords would require extensive data preproces-
sing to eliminate irrelevant tweets in order to draw valid conclu-
sions from the content analysis. For future studies we will 
develop efficient methods for conducting such preprocessing. 
While our keywords demonstrated high precision, our analyses 
likely underestimate the total amount of e-cigarette-related 
tweets. Fourth, our data do not allow us to map the interrela-
tionships between Twitter users who post e-cigarette-related 
content. Future research might measure types of interactions 
between e-cigarette marketers and potential customers, includ-
ing whether commercial and organic accounts are likely to </p>

<p>Figure 1 Distribution of activity across Twitter accounts who posted 
about e-cigarettes, May/June 2012. </p>

<p>Table 2 Health, safety, cessation and price mentions in 
commercial tweets </p>

<p>Mentions </p>

<p>Tweets 
(N) </p>

<p>Fraction of 
commercial 
tweets (%) </p>

<p>Total times posted 
(summed followers)* </p>

<p>Health 
1290 
2.0 
1 210 961 
Safety 
754 
1.1 
514 550 
Cessation 
7140 
10.8 
7 410 062 
Any (health or safety or 
cessation) </p>

<p>8985 
13.6 
8 734 272 </p>

<p>Price or discount 
22 675 
34.3 
144 918 562 </p>

<p>*Total times posted represents the number of times tweets appeared on feeds, and 
was calculated by summing the total number of followers for each collected tweet. 
Follower counts were available for tweets posted for June 2012 only, and therefore 
underestimate the total postings during the study period. </p>

<p>Huang J, et al. Tob Control 2014;23:iii26-iii30. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2014-051551 
iii29 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>follow, retweet, or mention one another. We also cannot reliably 
distinguish whether an organic user tweeting commercial 
content was paid or encouraged to do so by a commercial 
entity. Our estimates do not take into account content viewed 
by actively searching for e-cigarette-related keywords using the 
Twitter search interface. By 2010 Twitter was the world's fastest 
growing search engine. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Finally, more research is needed to better understand how 
social media marketing affects smokers' and non-smokers' 
beliefs and attitudes about e-cigarettes, and ultimately whether 
it influences product use. Future studies could examine the 
content of organic tweets about e-cigarettes to better understand 
tweeters' assessments of products' appeal, safety and smoking 
cessation application. 
Given the absence of demographic or smoking status informa-
tion about individual users, external validity of inferences 
drawn from Twitter data partly depends upon available informa-
tion about user characteristics at the population level. Internet 
users on Twitter are described as primarily young (30% aged 
18-29 years), African American (27%) or Latino (28%). 
5 While 
Klout score is not universally acknowledged as the top measure 
of online influence, the measure is useful to characterise poten-
tial reach and impact of Twitter messaging. It is generated using 
an undisclosed algorithm to capture influence, defined as 'ability 
to drive people to action'-thus retweets and replies are likely 
weighted most heavily. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Despite the limitations, this study contributes to the literature 
by beginning to characterise the presence and nature of 
e-cigarette marketing on social media and identifying potential 
directions for future research. This paper extends the line of 
research on tobacco-related information using 'big data' by 
adopting a standard statistical algorithm-based machine learning 
method which, until recently, 
14 has received little attention from 
tobacco control researchers. Research using Twitter data is rela-
tively new and standardised methodologies for classifying and 
analysing those data are needed. The study described here con-
tributes to the testing and standardisation of novel methods for 
conducting such analyses. </p>

<p>What the paper adds </p>

<p>▸ While the marketing and use of e-cigarettes have increased, 
little is known about how e-cigarettes are marketed and 
promoted on social media platforms. 
▸ This study reveals that Twitter appears to be an important 
marketing platform for e-cigarettes. E-cigarette marketing on 
Twitter may carry major public health risks. Continued 
surveillance of e-cigarette marketing on social media 
platforms is needed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank Lisa Vera, Steve Binns and Huayi Li for 
their excellent research assistance. </p>

<p>Contributors SLE, GS, JH and RK together designed the study; GS and RK 
collected data; JH and RK conducted data analysis; SLE, GS, JH and RK contributed 
to data interpretation; RK and JH wrote the first draft; SLE, JH and RK revised the 
draft; the final version of the paper has been reviewed and approved by all four 
coauthors. </p>

<p>Funding This project is funded by a National Cancer Institute-funded grant (Grant 
No. 1U01CA154254), titled "Tobacco Control in a Rapidly Changing Media 
Environment" (Principal investigator: SLE). The National Cancer Institute did not play 
any role in study design; in the collection, analysis and interpretation of data; in the 
writing of the report; and in the decision to submit the article for publication. The 
opinions expressed here are those of the authors, and do not necessarily reflect 
those of the sponsors. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Patient consent Not applicable. </p>

<p>Ethics approval This study is cleared for ethics by Research Ethics Boards 
or International Review Boards at the University of Illinois at Chicago (USA). </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>

<p>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the 
Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 3.0) license, which 
permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, 
and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is 
properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/3.0/ </p>



<p> 
Huang J, et al. Tob Control 2014;23:iii26-iii30. doi:10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2014-051551 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

</text></tei>