<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4399784" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: This study was conducted to identify predictors of self-reported academic per-
formance in undergraduate medical students at Hawassa University. 
Methods: An analytical cross-sectional study involving 592 undergraduate medical students was 
conducted in November 2012. The academic performance of the study subjects was measured 
by self-reported cumulative grade point average (GPA) using a self-administered questionnaire. 
Data were entered and analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 16</rs> 
software. Pearson's bivariate correlations, multiple linear regression, and multiple logistic 
regression were used to identify predictors of academic performance. 
Results: The self-reported academic performance of students had been decreasing as the 
academic years progressed, with the highest and lowest performance being in the premedicine 
(mean GPA 3.47) and clinical I (mean GPA 2.71) years, respectively. One hundred and fifty-eight 
(26.7%) of the participants had ever been delayed, 37 (6.2%) had ever re-sat for examination, 
and two (0.3%) had ever been warned due to academic failure. The overall variation in self-
reported academic performance of the students was 32.8%. Participant age alone explained 
21.9% of the variation. On the other hand, university entrance examination results, substance use 
at university, and medicine as first choice by students were identified as predictors of variation 
in self-reported academic performance, accounting for 6.9%, 2.7%, and ,1% of the variation, 
respectively. Students who had never used tobacco, alcohol, or khat after starting university 
were twice as likely to score a self-reported cumulative GPA above 3.0 (adjusted odds ratio 1.95, 
95% confidence interval 1.25-3.02) and less likely to be delayed, have to re-sit an examination, 
or be warned (adjusted odds ratio 0.47, 95% confidence interval 0.29-0.77). 
Conclusion: Only 32.8% of the variation in self-reported academic performance was explained 
by the studied variables. Hence, efficacious mechanisms should be designed to combat the 
intervenable determinants of self-reported academic performance, like substance use and a low 
medical school entrance examination result. Further studies should also be undertaken to gain a 
better understanding of other unstudied determinants, like personality, learning style, cognitive 
ability, and the system used for academic evaluation. 
Academic performance is a key component of medical education that is used by govern-
ing bodies like ministries of education and health and universities to assess whether a 
medical graduate is sufficiently competent and fit to practice medicine. 
1,2 It is also used 
to identify students who are displaying the appropriate level of competence, to enable 
students to ascertain their own academic progress, and to predict the future performance 
of students. 
1,3 The purpose of medical education is to ensure that students meet the </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Advances in Medical Education and Practice 
9 April 2015 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>306 </p>

<p>gedefaw et al </p>

<p>ethical, clinical, technical, and scientific standards expected 
of a good physician. 
4 Therefore, academic performance of 
medical students should be evaluated continuously. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>In developed countries, various studies have revealed 
that a number of factors affect the academic performance 
of undergraduate medical students. Prior academic achieve-
ment, such as medical school entrance examination result, </p>

<p>6,7 </p>

<p>cognitive ability, 
8,9 personality, 
10,11 learning style, 
12 and 
stress at medical school 
8 were among the identified factors. 
There is a scarcity of scientific evidence on determinants 
of academic performance among medical students in 
developing countries like Ethiopia. However, studies done 
on substance use among university students found that use 
of substances like khat and cigarettes negatively affected 
academic performance. </p>

<p>13,14 </p>

<p>Khat is a stimulant drug derived from a shrub (Catha 
edulis) found in Eastern Africa and Southern Arabia. Leaves 
of the khat shrub are held in the cheek or chewed as gum, 
and release their stimulants cathinone and cathine. These 
chemicals are structurally similar to amphetamine and have 
a similar stimulant effect on the brain and body. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Ethiopia, one of the developing countries in Eastern 
Africa, suffers from a shortage of health professionals, par-
ticularly physicians. According to the 2011/2012 report of 
the Federal Ministry of Health, the physician to population 
ratio was 1:28,847. 
16 This figure is far below the interna-
tional standard recommendation of 1:10,000. 
17 Recently, 
the Ministry of Education, as well as the Ministry of Health, 
in Ethiopia aimed to increase the number of physicians by 
opening new medical schools to increase the number of 
medical students. 
18,19 Despite the increased intake of medical 
students each year, the number of students graduating from 
these schools is still not as high as needed, largely due to a 
high attrition rate. Attrition is of concern, because it is a waste 
not only of the students' time, effort, and money, but also for 
medical academic institutions and the government. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>As it is normal for some students in an educational 
institution to perform well while others do poorly, even after 
receiving the same services, researchers are curious to know 
what makes some students perform poorly. The findings 
of the current study would help in assisting policy-makers 
and implementers to come up with policies and strategies 
that can be employed to improve academic performance, 
in addition to generating evidence about predictors of 
self-reported academic performance among medical stu-
dents in Ethiopia. Hence, this study aimed at identifying 
the predictors of academic performance in undergraduate 
medical students. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>This study was conducted among undergraduate medical 
students of Hawassa University (HU, a public university 
established in 1999) in Hawassa City, the capital city of 
the Southern Nations Nationalities and People's Region 
of Ethiopia. The university has a total of five campuses. 
It is one of the 32 public universities in Ethiopia, and is 
engaged in the provision of all-round education, research, 
and training. 
Formal training of medical professionals at HU began 
in 2003 with the opening of the College of Medicine and 
Health Sciences (CMHS) and its tertiary teaching hospital, 
ie, Hawassa University Referral Hospital. At the time of 
the study, the college had an annual acceptance of 150-200 
medical students. Medical students are admitted to the 
school as per the national criteria set by the Federal Ministry 
of Education, which are mainly based on students' perfor-
mance in the Ethiopian National Higher Education Entrance 
Examinations. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>New medical students joining the CMHS at HU initially 
attend general courses for 6 months in the premedical train-
ing program before embarking on the preclinical academic 
years, ie, preclinical I (year 1) and preclinical II (year 2). All 
medical students completing preclinical and clinical training, 
ie, clinical I (year 3) and clinical II (year 4), are required to 
successfully pass through a 1-year internship program in 
order to graduate. In general, the duration of undergraduate 
medical training has a curriculum of 5.5 years. Until the end 
of 2013, the medical school has graduated more than 340 
general medical practitioners. 
The curriculum of the medical school during the study 
period includes the basic medical courses in the preclinical 
years (years 1 and 2) while the clinical courses are usu-
ally covered in the subsequent three years (clinical I, II, 
and internship). The student evaluation system includes 
written examinations, oral examinations, individual and 
group assignments, practical examinations, and progressive 
assessment. Students are expected to score at least 60% to 
pass each course. Students who fail to achieve 60% in the 
basic and clinical courses need to repeat the course or re-sit 
an examination based on individual academic records. 
The grading system of the school is based on the fixed 
scale system of HU with 85%-100% (A), 80%-84.9% 
(B+), 70%-79.9% (B), 65%-69.9% (C+), 60%-64.9% (C), 
55%-59.9% (D+), 50%-54.9% (D), and less than 50% (F). 
According to the system, A has a score of 4.0 whereas B+, B, 
C+, C, D, and F have scores of 3.5, 3.0, 2.5, 2.0, 1.0, and 0, 
respectively. Accordingly, the maximum and the minimum </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>307 </p>

<p>Predictors of self-reported academic performance in medical students </p>

<p>cumulative grade point average (GPA) a medical student can 
achieve will be 4.0 and 0, respectively. </p>

<p>study design and participants </p>

<p>This analytical cross-sectional study, which used a quantita-
tive data collection method, involved all medical students who 
had at least one semester GPA (year 1 to internship program) 
at the CMHS. Medical students who did not have at least one 
semester GPA were excluded. </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>The dependent variable (academic performance) was mea-
sured by students' self-reported cumulative GPA for the 
current academic year. 
22 The independent variables were: 
prior academic performance (university entrance examination 
result and type of high school), sociodemographic character-
istics (age, sex, maternal educational level, paternal educa-
tional level, original background, and allowance per month), 
personal characteristics (choice of medicine as first interest, 
substance use before and after joining university, history of 
academic withdrawal, duration of study at university, usual 
number of sleeping hours per day, estimated length of time 
spent on extracurricular activities, and missing academic 
activities). </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Academic performance was dichotomized into good and 
low based on the mean cumulative GPA and/or presence of 
academic delays, experience of re-sitting examinations, and 
academic warnings. </p>

<p>24,25 </p>

<p>Substance use in this study represented the use of at least 
one of chewing khat, smoking cigarettes, or alcohol use in 
the 30 days preceding the study period. </p>

<p>Data collection and analysis </p>

<p>A self-administered, pretested, structured questionnaire 
prepared in English was used for data collection, since 
English is the medium of instruction in all higher educa-
tion institutions in Ethiopia. Most of the questions were 
close-ended with precoded responses, and mainly grouped 
into sociodemographic characteristics, earlier school per-
formance and characteristics, behavioral characteristics, and 
academic performance and GPA in each academic year. The 
questionnaire was developed by the authors after reviewing 
the relevant literature on the subject. Based on their training 
background, students were divided into two main categories: 
preclinical (years 1 and 2) and clinical (years 3 and 4 and 
internship). To minimize the non-response rate, data were 
collected for each batch of students immediately after they 
finished written examinations or after bedside teaching; the </p>

<p>data collection was conducted in lecture halls. Data collectors 
as well as the supervisors were trained assistant lecturers from 
other campuses at HU. Instructions on how to complete the 
questionnaire correctly, particularly on how to follow skip 
patterns, was given to the study subjects before embarking on 
completing the questionnaire. After the questionnaires were 
collected back from the students, the supervisors checked all 
questionnaires for completeness. 
Data were entered, cleaned, and analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical 
Package for the Social Sciences</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 16</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Descriptive statistics were used to 
summarize and present the data. To determine the relation-
ship between self-reported academic performance and the 
different independent variables, bivariate Pearson's correla-
tion analysis was done three times (for total participants, and 
for preclinical, and clinical student subcategories). Multiple 
linear regression was used to estimate the cumulative and 
individual effects of each independent variable as well as to 
control confounding effects. 
To explain the variability of the outcome variable accord-
ing to the explanatory variables and identify the effects of 
confounding, three multiple linear regression analyses were 
constructed for total participants, clinical, and preclinical 
students. Out of the 20 explanatory variables, we used a back-
ward selection procedure to test several combinations of these 
variables and used a model that gives us the largest adjusted 
R 
2 and the smallest standard error. Regression diagnostics 
were done for the fitness of model. The correlation between 
each of the explanatory variables was less than 0.7, and the 
variance inflation factor was #5. Moreover, linearity and 
other assumptions were guided under the umbrella of central 
limit theory because the sample size was very large. 
For the logistic regression models, a P-value ,0.2 was 
taken as a cut-off point for selecting variables to enter into 
the multiple logistic regression model. A probability value 
of ,0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. </p>

<p>Ethical considerations </p>

<p>Ethical approval was obtained from the institutional review 
board at CMHS. Further, permission letters were presented 
to all responsible units in the CMHS to seek permission to 
engage in data collection. Participation of the students was 
on a voluntary basis. Written informed consent was obtained 
after the purpose of the study was explained to the students 
in their specific subcategories. Identifiers of the study partici-
pants were not recorded anywhere on the questionnaire, and 
appropriate measures (adequate spacing between individuals 
during completion of the questionnaires, recruiting data col-</p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>308 </p>

<p>gedefaw et al </p>

<p>lectors, and supervisors from other campuses) were taken to 
ensure confidentiality of information. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>During the study period, a total of 770 undergraduate medi-
cal students were registered in the medical school. However, 
150 students were in their premedical study period so were 
excluded from the study as they did not have any GPA. Of 
the 620 students invited, 610 participated in the study, giving 
a response rate of 98.4%. Questionnaires from only 592 stu-
dents were used for the study; questionnaires for 18 students 
were discarded because of incomplete responses. 
Of the total number of respondents, 36.3% were in the 
preclinical years, and the remaining 63.7% were in the clini-
cal years. More than three-quarters (79.9%) of the partici-
pants were male, and the mean age of the participants was 
22.16±1.85 years. Participants reported an average monthly 
allowance of 19.8±14.7 USD; males reported a smaller allow-
ance than females (17.5 USD versus 29 USD, respectively, 
P,0.0001, Table 1). 
With regards to preuniversity history, more than three 
quarters (77.9%) of participants completed their high 
school education at a government school and the average 
self-reported university entrance examination result was 
72%±3.97%. There was a statistically significant difference 
between the mean entrance examination results of male 
and female students (72.4% versus 71.2%, respectively, 
P=0.009). Of the total number of participants, only 33 (5.6%) 
had ever used any substance before starting university, 
while about a quarter (24.2%) used any substances during 
the data collection period. Khat was the most commonly 
used substance, followed by alcohol and cigarette smoking. 
When substance use was disaggregated by academic year, 
the proportion of substance users increased with increment 
in academic year. The students' mean lengths of time usually 
spent studying, sleeping, and on extracurricular activities 
in 24 hours were 7.9±2.8, 6.96±1.22, and 3.2±1.74, respec-
tively, Table 2). 
Forty-seven participants (7.9%) had been in medical 
school for more than 6 years. Self-reported academic perfor-
mance had been decreasing as the academic years progressed, 
with the highest and lowest performance being in premedi-
cine (mean GPA 3.47) and clinical I medicine (mean GPA 
2.71), respectively. The mean current self-reported cumula-
tive GPA of the participants was 3.08±0.38; more than half 
(61.7%) of the students had a cumulative GPA $3.0, and 
there was no difference in cumulative GPA between female 
and male students (3.08 and 3.09, P=0.804). However, there </p>

<p>was a statistically significant difference in cumulative GPA 
between clinical and preclinical students (2.95 and 3.31, 
P=0.000, Table 3). 
More than a quarter of the participants (26.7%) had 
ever been delayed (needed to repeat a course) in their time 
as medical students, but few (6.2%) had needed to re-sit 
an examination. Self-reported academic performance was 
good for 61.7% of the students (cumulative GPA $3.0). </p>

<p>Table 1 sociodemographic characteristics of undergraduate 
medical students at college of Medicine and health sciences, 
hawassa University, november 2012 </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Frequency (n) 
Percentage </p>

<p>sex 
Male 
473 
79.9 
Female 
119 
20.1 
Age, years 
22.16 (mean) 
1.848 (sD) 
15-19 
53 
9.0 
20-24 
485 
81.9 
$25 
54 
9.1 
religion 
Orthodox christian 
356 
60.1 
Protestant christian 
123 
20.8 
Muslim 
79 
13.3 
Other* 
34 
5.7 
Ethnicity 
Amhara 
236 
39.9 
Oromo 
168 
28.4 
Tigre 
44 
7.4 
gurage 
37 
6.2 
Other** 
107 
18.1 
Original background 
Urban 
362 
61.1 
rural 
230 
38.9 
Medical education status 
Preclinical i 
115 
19.4 
Preclinical ii 
101 
17.1 
clinical i 
144 
24.3 
clinical ii 
149 
25.2 
internship 
83 
14.0 
Maternal educational level 
no formal education 
237 
40.0 
Primary school (1-8) 
140 
23.6 
secondary school (9-12) 
79 
13.3 
college and above 
136 
23.0 
Paternal educational level 
no formal education 
157 
26.5 
Primary school (1-8) 
144 
24.3 
secondary school (9-12) 
74 
12.5 
college and above 
217 
36.7 
Monthly allowance, UsD 
19.8 (mean) 
14.7 (sD) 
,10 
167 
28.2 
10-25 
329 
55.6 
25-50 
76 
12.8 
.50 
20 
3.4 </p>

<p>Notes: *catholic; **sidama. 
Abbreviation: sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>309 </p>

<p>Predictors of self-reported academic performance in medical students </p>

<p>Low academic performance (delay, re-sit, and/or warning) 
was reported by 29.7% of the students (Table 3). 
According to the bivariate Pearson's correlation analy-
sis, seven of the independent variables had a significant 
correlation with self-reported academic performance. Age 
(r=-0.469, P=0.000), university entrance examination results 
(r=0.356, P=0.000), substance use at university (r=-0.219, 
P=0.000), and missing of bedside/round sessions (r=-0.398, 
P=0.000) were moderately correlated, and history of with-
drawal from academic activity (r=0.094, P=0.022), missing 
lectures (r=0.111, P=0.007), and missing seminars/tutorials 
(r=0.147, P=0.000) were weakly correlated. </p>

<p>Table 2 Former high school background and behavioral cha-
racteristics of undergraduate medical students at college of Med-
icine and health sciences, hawassa University, november 2012 </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Frequency (n) 
Percentage </p>

<p>completed high school in 
government school 
461 
77.9 
Private school 
131 
22.1 
University entrance examination 
result (%) </p>

<p>72.0 (mean) 
3.97 (sD) </p>

<p>60-69.9 
163 
27.5 
70-79.9 
419 
70.8 
$80 
10 
1.7 </p>

<p>Was medicine their first choice? 
Yes 
537 
90.7 
no 
55 
9.3 
Ever use of substances before 
university 
Yes 
33 
5.6 
no 
559 
94.4 
Type of substance ever use 
before university (n=33) 
Khat alone 
18 
3.0 
Alcohol and khat 
11 
1.9 
cigarettes, alcohol, and khat 
4 
0.68 </p>

<p>current substance use (n=592) 
Yes 
143 
24.2 
no 
449 
75.8 
Type of currently used substances 
(n=143) 
Khat alone 
110 
18.6 
Alcohol and khat 
97 
16.4 
cigarettes, alcohol, and khat 
33 
5.5 
substance use by academic year 
Preclinical i 
10 
8.7 
Preclinical ii 
26 
25.7 
clinical i 
42 
29.2 
clinical ii 
34 
22.8 
internship 
31 
37.3 
Average daily duration of study, 
hours </p>

<p>7.9 (mean) 
2.8 (sD) </p>

<p>,5 
53 
9.0 </p>

<p>5-10 
458 
77.4 
.10 
81 
13.7 </p>

<p>Average daily duration of sleep, 
hours </p>

<p>6.96 (mean) 
1.22 (sD) </p>

<p>,5 
13 
2.2 </p>

<p>5-10 
578 
97.6 
.10 
1 
0.2 </p>

<p>Average daily duration of 
extracurricular activities, hours </p>

<p>3.2 (mean) 
1.74 (sD) </p>

<p>,1 
2 
0.3 </p>

<p>1-3 
373 
63.0 
.3 
217 
36.7 </p>

<p>Type of missed academic activities 
lecture 
326 
55.1 
seminar/tutorial 
115 
19.4 
Bedside/round 
33 
5.5 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Table 3 Patterns of academic performance among undergraduate 
medical students at college of Medicine and health sciences, 
hawassa University, november 2012 </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Frequency (n) 
Percentage </p>

<p>Withdrawal history with any cause 
Yes 
26 
4.4 
no 
566 
95.6 
University attendance, years 
#6 
545 
92.1 </p>

<p>.6 
47 
7.9 
gPA 
Mean 
sD 
Premedicine 
3.47 
0.29 
Preclinical i 
2.99 
0.42 
Preclinical ii 
2.88 
0.40 
clinical i 
2.71 
0.38 
clinical ii 
2.73 
0.40 
current cumulative 
3.08 
0.38 
have you ever been delayed 
(repeated courses) 
Yes 
158 
26.7 
no 
434 
73.3 
Academic year of delay (n=158) 
Preclinical 
90 
56.9 
clinical 
68 
43.1 
have you ever had to re-sit an 
examination 
Yes 
37 
6.2 
no 
555 
93.8 
Academic years of re-sit 
examination, n=37 
Preclinical 
34 
91.2 
clinical 
3 
8.8 
Academic performance, cumulative 
gPA 
good ($3.0) 
365 
61.7 </p>

<p>low (,3.0) 
227 
38.3 
Academic performance 
good (never delayed, had to 
re-sit, been warned) </p>

<p>416 
70.3 </p>

<p>low (delayed, had to re-sit, 
been warned) </p>

<p>176 
29.7 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: gPA, grade point average; sD, standard deviation. </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>310 </p>

<p>gedefaw et al </p>

<p>Similar correlation analyses were done for subgroups 
(clinical and preclinical years): age (r=-0.540, P=0.00), 
university entrance examination results (r=0.390, P=0.00), 
substance use at university (r=0.261, P=0.000), missing 
lectures (r=0.168, P=0.001) and missing seminars/tutorials 
(r=-0.091, P=0.020) had a statistically significant correlation 
with academic performance among the preclinical students. 
Only three variables, ie, history of withdrawal from academic 
activity (r=0.18, P=0.036), university entrance examination 
results (r=0.240, P=0.000), and medicine as first choice (r=-
0.139, P=0.035) had a statistically significant correlation with 
academic performance in the clinical years. 
The identified independent variables explained 32.8% of 
the variation in academic performance (R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>=0.328, P=0.000). 
Four variables (participant age, substance use at university, 
university entrance examination results, and medicine as first 
choice), accounted for the statistically significant variation in 
self-reported academic performance. Multiple linear regres-
sion analyses for subgroups revealed that the aforementioned 
independent variables explained 30.1% and 14.7% of the 
variation in self-reported academic performance for preclini-
cal and clinical year students, respectively (Table 4). 
Stepwise multiple linear regression analysis was also done 
for all the participants. Participant age alone explained 21.9% 
of the variation in self-reported academic performance. </p>

<p>University entrance examination results, substance use at 
university, and medicine as first choice explained 6.9%, 2.7%, 
and ,1% of variation in academic performance, respectively. 
Considering type of substance used versus academic perfor-
mance, the mean cumulative GPA of substance users was 
found to be less than that of non-users (alcohol, 2.96 versus 
3.12, P=0.000; khat, 2.91 versus 3.12, P=0.000; cigarettes, 
2.90 versus 3.12, P=0.007). 
To express the strength of relationship in a more inter-
pretable way, bivariate and multivariate logistic regressions 
were done. Students who have never used any substances at 
university were twice as likely to have scored a self-reported 
cumulative GPA of 3.0 and above (adjusted odds ratio [AOR] 
1.95, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.25-3.02) and less likely 
to have been delayed, to have had to re-sit, and/or be warned 
(AOR 0.47, 95% CI 0.29-0.77) than their counterparts. Those 
students whose university entrance examination result was 
66%-70% (AOR 3.05, 95% CI 1.25-7.47) and 71%-75% 
(AOR 3.81, 95% CI 1.91-4.29) were more likely to have 
scored a self-reported cumulative GPA of 3.0 and above 
than students whose entrance examination result was #65% 
(Table 6). When the predictive validity of university entrance 
examination results as a predictor of self-reported academic 
performance was tested using a receiver operating character-
istic curve, the point of the curve that was closer to the left </p>

<p>Table 4 Bivariate correlation between independent variables and academic performance among undergraduate medical students at 
college of Medicine and health sciences, hawassa University, november 2012 </p>

<p>Variables 
Performance 
Performance 
Performance </p>

<p>All students 
Preclinical years 
Clinical years </p>

<p>r 
P-value 
r 
P-value 
r 
P-value </p>

<p>sex 
-0.010 
0.804 
-0.076 
0.148 
0.010 
0.877 
Age 
-0.469 
0.000 
-0.540 
0.000 
-0.023 
0.72 
religion 
-0.094 
0.051 
-0.026 
0.618 
-0.135 
0.052 
Ethnicity 
-0.013 
0.753 
0.010 
0.843 
-0.055 
0.401 
Original background 
-0.018 
0.667 
0.006 
0.914 
0.040 
0.545 
Paternal educational level 
0.038 
0.354 
0.013 
0.805 
0.019 
0.773 
Maternal educational level 
0.041 
0.325 
0.014 
0.791 
-0.018 
0.790 
Monthly allowance 
0.006 
0.877 
-0.047 
0.369 
0.031 
0.639 
Type of preparatory school 
0.003 
0.941 
-0.037 
0.485 
-0.007 
0.918 
Withdrawal history by any cause 
0.094 
0.022 
0.064 
0.227 
0.138 
0.036 
University entrance examination result 
0.356 
0.000 
0.390 
0.000 
0.240 
0.000 
Was medicine their first choice 
-0.075 
0.067 
-0.040 
0.452 
-0.139 
0.035 
substance use before university 
0.035 
0.389 
0.005 
0.922 
-0.005 
0.941 
current substance use 
-0.219 
0.000 
-0.261 
0.000 
-0.118 
0.072 
Daily duration of study 
0.053 
0.202 
0.094 
0.075 
-0.100 
0.129 
Daily amount of sleep 
-0.044 
0.280 
-0.077 
0.145 
0.094 
0.154 
Daily time spent on extracurricular activities 
0.006 
0.888 
-0.020 
0.706 
0.060 
0.365 
Missing lectures 
0.111 
0.007 
0.168 
0.001 
0.038 
0.561 
Missing bedside/rounds 
-0.398 
0.000 
-0.091 
0.186 
0.079 
0.128 
Missing seminars/tutorials 
0.147 
0.000 
0.158 
0.020 
0.093 
0.071 </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>311 </p>

<p>Predictors of self-reported academic performance in medical students </p>

<p>Table 5 results of multiple linear regression analysis of academic performance among undergraduate medical students at college of 
Medicine and health sciences, hawassa University, november 2012 </p>

<p>Performance 
Performance 
Performance </p>

<p>All students* 
Preclinical students** 
Clinical students*** </p>

<p>Stand B 
t static 
P-value 
Stand B 
t static 
P-value 
Stand B 
t static 
P-value </p>

<p>constant 
7.88 
0.000 
3.51 
0.001 
4.713 
0.000 
sex 
-0.080 
-2.112 
0.055 
-0.083 
-1.359 
0.76 
-0.070 
-1.250 
0.212 
Age 
-0.389 
-10.488 
0.000 
-0.347 
-5.510 
0.000 
-0.148 
-2.741 
0.006 
Original background 
0.045 
1.209 
0.227 
-0.036 
-0.057 
0.571 
0.055 
0.996 
0.320 
Monthly allowance 
0.057 
1.436 
0.152 
0.111 
1.571 
0.118 
0.107 
1.862 
0.063 
University entrance 
examination result </p>

<p>0.271 
7.665 
0.000 
0.283 
4.792 
0.000 
0.268 
5.331 
0.000 </p>

<p>Medicine as first choice 
0.077 
2.264 
0.024 
0.055 
0.949 
0.344 
0.116 
2.383 
0.018 
substance use before 
university </p>

<p>-0.070 
-1.954 
0.051 
-0.122 
-1.904 
0.058 
-0.063 
-1.236 
0.217 </p>

<p>current substance use 
-0.204 
-5.332 
0.000 
-0.330 
-4.625 
0.000 
-0.194 
-3.631 
0.000 
religion 
-0.067 
-1.924 
0.055 
-0.163 
-2.731 
0.057 
-0.043 
-0.871 
0.384 
Missing seminars/tutorials 
0.044 
1.262 
0.207 
0.039 
0.623 
0.534 
0.041 
0.829 
0.408 </p>

<p>Notes: *Adjusted R 
2 =0.328, P=0.000; **adjusted R 
2 =0.301, P=0.000; ***adjusted R 
2 =0.147, P=0.000. </p>

<p>upper quadrant of the x-y axis yielded a sensitivity of 0.61 
and 1 -specificity of 0.33. The threshold point that minimizes 
the trade-off between the sensitivity and specificity of the 
university entrance examination result was at 72.25%. The 
area under the receiver operating characteristic curve was 
found to be 0.68 (95% CI 0.64-0.73). Although the university 
entrance examination result was associated with the student's 
self-reported academic performance, an area of 0.68 under 
the receiver operating characteristic curve implies that the 
university entrance examination result was poor in setting the 
threshold for a dependent variable, in this case self-reported 
academic performance. We also noted an association between 
participant age and academic performance, with the odds of 
having a self-reported cumulative GPA $3.0 being 70% less 
for students aged older than 22 years (AOR 0.30, 95% CI 
0.20-0.44) when compared with their younger counterparts 
(Table 5). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the present study, we evaluated the correlation of dif-
ferent independent variables with self-reported academic 
performance. Self-reporting may affect the quality of study 
data, even though appropriate measures are taken during 
data collection to assess actual performance. To minimize 
this problem, an appropriate explanation was given to the 
participants on the importance of reporting their actual 
academic performance, and the data collection tool was 
pretested on paramedical students. More than three quarters 
of the participants were male (79.9%) which is consistent 
with the male predominance found in other studies done </p>

<p>in higher institutions in Ethiopia. 
13,26-28 This indicates that 
female involvement in higher institutions is still low, despite 
continuing recruitment efforts. 
In the current study, self-reported academic performance 
was higher among premedicine students. This is consistent 
with the findings of a study of freshmen at Jimma Univer-
sity where medical students had the lowest dismissal rate. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>Although the definition of low academic performance in 
medical students varies in the literature, two studies done in 
the USA of 1st-year medical students found low academic 
performance rates of 11.4% and 14%, 
24,25 which are by far 
lower than the low academic performance level found in the 
current study. 
The identified explanatory variables accounted for only 
32.8% of the variation in self-reported academic performance 
for the total study population, indicating that approximately 
70% of the variation in academic performance had to 
be explained by determinants not assessed in this study. 
Subgroup analysis showed that these variables explained only 
30.1% and 14.7% of the variation in academic performance 
for preclinical and clinical year students, respectively. This 
finding suggests that the variables chosen are poorer predic-
tors of self-reported academic performance for students in 
the clinical years than for students in the preclinical years. 
This could be due to a difference in the teaching-learning and 
evaluation system between the two categories of students. 
Participant age was one of the predictors of self-reported 
academic performance in this study. Student age alone 
accounted for 21.9% of the variation in academic per-
formance, with academic performance decreasing as age </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>312 </p>

<p>gedefaw et al </p>

<p>increased. After controlling for other variables, for every 
1-year increment in age, the cumulative GPA decreased by 
0.389. However, the effect of student age on performance 
at medical school is a controversial issue. Older students 
in several studies did less well in scientific reasoning and 
tended to be graded with lower scores at the beginning of 
their courses, basically in the 1st year of their medical stud-
ies. 
30-32 However, recent studies show that older and more 
mature medical students performed better than their younger 
counterparts. </p>

<p>33,34 </p>

<p>Student age warrants very careful attention when inter-
preting the findings of the current study, given that this was 
at the point of data collection not the age of entry to medical 
school. It is very difficult to conclude that older students 
are performing less well than their younger counterparts, 
because being older could be due to academic delay, a longer 
time spent at medical school, or a difference in the nature of 
the academic years rather than age alone. 
In the current study, as university entrance examination 
result of participants increased by one mark, their cumulative </p>

<p>Table 6 Binary and multiple logistic regression analysis of academic performance based on cgPA average as a dichotomous variable, 
college of Medicine and health sciences, hawassa University, november 2012 </p>

<p>Variables 
Academic performance, 
CGPA </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) </p>

<p>Good ($3.0) 
Low (,3.0) 
Crude OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value 
Adjusted OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Age (years) 
0.000 
0.000 
#20 
107 
10 
1 
1 </p>

<p>21-25 
252 
213 
9.044 (4.613-17.733) 
0.275 (0.058-1.297) </p>

<p>.25 
6 
4 
7.133 (1.722-29.556) 
1.924 (0.484-7.652) 
religion 
0.105 
0.923 
Orthodox 
231 
125 
1 </p>

<p>Muslim 
50 
29 
0.685 (0.337-1.396) </p>

<p>Protestant 
65 
58 
0.735 (0.325-1.663) </p>

<p>Other 
19 
15 
1.130 (0.527-2.426) 
Ethnicity 
0.083 
0.574 
Amhara 
158 
78 
1 </p>

<p>Oromo 
92 
76 
0.680 (0.425-1.088) </p>

<p>Tigre 
31 
13 
1.138 (0.698-1.857) </p>

<p>gurage 
22 
15 
0.578 (0.272-1.227) </p>

<p>Other 
62 
45 
0.939 (0.439-2.009) 
Maternal education 
0.075 
0.515 
no formal education 
156 
81 
1 </p>

<p>Primary school 
77 
63 
0.983 (0.631-1.532) </p>

<p>high school 
43 
36 
1.549 (0.953-2.518) </p>

<p>college and above 
89 
47 
1.585 (0.900-2.794) 
Withdrawal history 
0.043 
0.513 
Yes 
11 
15 
1 </p>

<p>no 
354 
212 
2.277 (1.027-5.050) 
Medicine as first choice 
0.046 
0.05 
Yes 
338 
199 
1 </p>

<p>no 
27 
28 
1.761 (1.009-3.074) 
current substance use 
0.000 
0.003 
Yes 
69 
74 
1 
1 </p>

<p>no 
296 
153 
2.075 (1.417-3.039) 
1.945 (1.253-3.019) 
Missing seminars/tutorials 
0.003 
0.055 
Yes 
57 
58 
1 </p>

<p>no 
307 
169 
1.848 (1.226-2.788) 
University entrance result, % 
0.000 
0.000 
60-65 
11 
14 
1 
1 </p>

<p>66-70 
64 
92 
3.494 (1.490-8.193) 
3.053 (1.248-7.47) </p>

<p>71-75 
150 
70 
3.946 (2.51-6.203) 
3.809 (1.908-4.293) </p>

<p>.75 
140 
51 
1.281 (0.835-1.966) 
1.443 (0.908-2.293) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: CGPA, cumulative grade point average; CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio. </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>313 </p>

<p>Predictors of self-reported academic performance in medical students </p>

<p>GPA increased by 0.271. Other researchers have demonstrated 
a similar predictive validity of academic performance prior to 
entry into medical school. 
7,35 A study done on school leaving 
examination results in New Zealand showed that these were 
predictive of GPA at medical school, especially in the preclini-
cal years; however, only 16% of the variance in GPA at medical 
school was explained by previous academic performance. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>Studies done in the USA and the UK also found that previous 
academic achievement is a stronger predictor of preclinical 
academic performance than clinical academic performance, 
and that its predictive value decreased as students progressed 
through the academic years. 
37,38 This is because prior academic 
achievement demonstrates that the student has a minimum 
level of competence and the basic knowledge on which to 
build and integrate new knowledge. </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>In the current study, khat, a central nervous system stimu-
lant, 
40,41 was the most commonly used substance at university. 
Similar rates of khat use have been found in other studies 
in Ethiopian high schools (18.4%), 
27 universities (19.6%), </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>and medical schools (14%-33.1%). </p>

<p>13,24 </p>

<p>There was a significant difference in mean self-reported 
cumulative GPA between substance users and non-users. 
Substance use alone explained 2.7% of the variation in self-
reported academic performance, and students who were not 
substance users were twice as likely to self-report a cumula-
tive GPA $3.0 and less likely to be delayed, have to re-sit, or 
be warned than their counterparts. This finding is consistent 
with the findings of a study conducted among medical and 
health officer students at Jimma University. 
13 Similar studies 
in Ethiopia 
14 and Saudi Arabia 
42 found that chewing khat is 
a risk factor for frequent absenteeism from class and poor 
academic performance in students. A recent study done in 
the same study area also found that absenteeism was higher 
among substance users, 
43 indicating that substance use has 
a negative influence on academic performance, perhaps as a 
result of the waste of valuable time and energy spent chew-
ing khat, absenteeism from class, and lack of concentration 
during class due to insomnia. 
This study has several limitations. It used self-administered 
questionnaires and instruments, so the reliability of the data 
could be questioned since bias might have been introduced, 
resulting in underreporting or overreporting. Further, there 
could have been some recall bias in students' self-reported 
GPAs. We recommend future studies designed with appropriate 
ethical considerations taken into account in order to be able 
to use students' academic records to assess their academic 
performance. The cross-sectional design of our study is also a 
limitation, because the presented associations lack cause-effect </p>

<p>relationship. However, we included a representative sample of 
all undergraduate medical students from year 1 to internship, 
with a large sample size and a high response rate. Thus, it is 
possible to generalize the results internally for all medical 
students at HU. However, generalizability to medical students 
attending other medical schools might be limited. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The factors investigated in this study explained only 32.8% 
of variation in academic performance. Other factors known 
to influence academic performance, such as student moti-
vation, personality, evaluation system, and learning style, 
should be studied in the future. It would be important to pay 
extra attention to students with a lower entrance examination 
result, substance users, and older students, particularly dur-
ing the clinical years. More education to promote awareness 
of the harmful effects of substance use in medical schools 
is needed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We are grateful to the Hawassa University's College of 
Medicine and Health Sciences and the Johns Hopkins 
University Technical Support for the Ethiopian HIV/AIDS 
Initiative for their technical and financial support during this 
study. We would also like to thank all the medical students 
who participated in this study for their commitment. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>AG conceived the research idea; AG and AA wrote the pro-
posal; AG and AA were involved in data collection; and AG 
and BT analyzed the data and wrote the draft manuscript. AG, 
AA, and BT critically reviewed and edited the manuscript 
for intellectual content. All authors reviewed and approved 
the final manuscript. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/advances-in-medical-education-and-practice-journal </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice is an international, peer-
reviewed, open access journal that aims to present and publish research 
on Medical Education covering medical, dental, nursing and allied 
health care professional education. The journal covers undergraduate 
education, postgraduate training and continuing medical education </p>

<p>including emerging trends and innovative models linking education, 
research, and health care services. The manuscript management system 
is completely online and includes a very quick and fair peer-review 
system. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/testimonials.php to read real 
quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>Advances in Medical Education and Practice 2015:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>315 </p>

<p>Predictors of self-reported academic performance in medical students </p>

</text></tei>