<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4621721" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>‫لدى‬ ‫والقلق‬ ‫الزوجية‬ ‫العالقة‬ ‫نوعية‬ ‫بني‬ ‫العالقة‬ ‫لدراسة‬ ‫األهداف:‬ 
‫السعودية.‬ ‫العربية‬ ‫اململكة‬ ‫في‬ ‫الثدي‬ ‫بسرطان‬ ‫املصابات‬ ‫النساء‬ </p>

<p>‫امرأة‬ 49 ‫من‬ ‫متتالية‬ ‫عينة‬ ‫على‬ ‫الدراسة‬ ‫هذه‬ ‫أجريت‬ ‫الطريقة:‬ 
‫سرطان‬ ‫فى‬ ‫للتميز‬ ‫العمودي‬ ‫مركز‬ ‫في‬ ‫الثدى‬ ‫بسرطان‬ ‫مصابة‬ ‫متزوجة‬ 
‫في‬ ‫السعودية‬ ‫العربية‬ ‫اململكة‬ ‫جدة،‬ ‫العزيز،‬ ‫عبد‬ ‫امللك‬ ‫بجامعة‬ ‫الثدي‬ 
‫للقلق‬ ‫املستشفى‬ ‫مقياس‬ ‫تطبيق‬ ‫مت‬ ‫وقد‬ ‫3102م.‬ ‫عام‬ ‫من‬ ‫مبكر‬ ‫وقت‬ 
‫احلياه‬ ‫نوعية‬ ‫ومقياس‬ ‫الزوجية،‬ ‫احلياة‬ ‫إدراك‬ ‫ومقياس‬ ‫واالكتئاب،‬ 
‫على‬ ‫املشاركون‬ ‫أجاب‬ ‫وكذلك‬ ‫الدراسة‬ ‫في‬ ‫املشاركني‬ ‫على‬ ‫الزوجية‬ 
. ‫السرطان‬ ‫وخصائص‬ ‫الدميوغرافية‬ ‫البيانات‬ ‫تخص‬ ‫أسئلة‬ </p>

<p>‫القلق‬ ‫مرض‬ ‫وجود‬ ‫إلى‬ ‫تشير‬ ‫التي‬ ‫القلق‬ ‫أعراض‬ ‫أن‬ ‫تشير‬ ‫النتائج:‬ 
‫القلق‬ ‫مرض‬ ‫وجود‬ ‫إلى‬ ‫تشير‬ ‫والتي‬ 10.4% ‫فى‬ ‫وجدت‬ ‫املمكن‬ 
‫عالقة‬ ‫توجد‬ ‫وال‬ .)25% ‫(املجموع‬ 14.6% ‫في‬ ‫وجدت‬ ‫احملتمل‬ 
‫في‬ ‫القلق‬ ‫مرض‬ ‫وكان‬ ‫القلق.‬ ‫ومرض‬ ‫الزوجية‬ ‫العالقه‬ ‫نوعية‬ ‫بني‬ 
‫اإلجتماعي‬ ‫والوضع‬ ‫املنخفض،‬ ‫بالتعليم‬ ً ‫ومتأثرا‬ ً 
‫مرتبطا‬ ‫األول‬ ‫املقام‬ 
‫السن.‬ ‫املنخفض،وصغر‬ ‫واالقتصادي‬ </p>

<p>‫النساء‬ ‫بني‬ ‫منتشره‬ ‫القلق‬ ‫أعراض‬ ‫أن‬ ‫الدراسة‬ ‫أظهرت‬ ‫اخلامتة:‬ 
‫سرطان‬ ‫بعيادة‬ ‫يتابعن‬ ‫واآلتي‬ ‫الثدي‬ ‫بسرطان‬ ‫املصابات‬ ‫املتزوجات‬ 
‫حاجة‬ ‫هناك‬ ‫زال‬ ‫وما‬ ‫السعودية.‬ ‫العربية‬ ‫اململكة‬ ‫في‬ ‫باجلامعة‬ ‫الثدى‬ 
‫الثدىي‬ ‫سرطان‬ ‫تشخيص‬ ‫كان‬ ‫إذا‬ ‫ما‬ ‫لتحديد‬ ‫البحوث‬ ‫من‬ ‫مزيد‬ ‫إلى‬ 
‫لوجود‬ ‫السبب‬ ‫هو‬ ‫هذا‬ ‫كان‬ ‫وإذا‬ ‫الزوجية،‬ ‫العالقة‬ ‫على‬ ً 
‫سلبا‬ ‫يؤثر‬ 
‫النساء.‬ ‫هؤالء‬ ‫لدى‬ ‫القلق‬ </p>

<p>Objectives: To examine relationship between the 
quality of marital relationship and anxiety among 
women with breast cancer (BC) in the Kingdom of 
Saudi Arabia (KSA). </p>

<p>Methods: This cross-sectional study recruited a 
consecutive series of 49 married women with BC seen 
in the Al-Amoudi Breast Cancer Center of Excellence 
at King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah, KSA in early 
2013. Participants completed the Hospital Anxiety and 
Depression Scale, Spouse Perception Scale, and Quality </p>

<p>of Marriage Index forms, and answered questions on 
demographic and cancer characteristics. </p>

<p>Results: Anxiety symptoms indicating "possible" 
anxiety disorder were present in 10.4% and "probable" 
anxiety disorder in 14.6% (25% total). No significant 
relationship was found between the quality of marital 
relationship and anxiety symptoms (B=-0.04, standard 
error=0.05, t=-0.81, p=0.42). Anxiety was primarily 
driven by low education, poor socioeconomic status, 
and young age. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Anxiety symptoms are prevalent among 
married women with BC seen in a university-based 
clinic in the KSA. Further research is needed to 
determine whether a diagnosis of BC adversely affects 
marital relationship, and whether this is the cause for 
anxiety in these women. </p>

<p>Cancer &amp; anxiety ... Al-Zaben et al </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (10)   B </p>

<p>reast cancer (BC) is the most common cause 
of cancer death in women worldwide, 
1 and the 
Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (KSA) is no exception. </p>

<p>2   Breast cancer has become a particular problem in Arab 
countries due to its late stage at presentation and its 
increased occurrence among young women. 
3 Both 
during and after treatment, even if the cancer goes 
into remission, concerns regarding recurrence, effect 
on the marital relationship, and frequent medical visits 
for monitoring, often result in high levels of anxiety 
(including post-traumatic stress-like symptoms). </p>

<p>4-8   Anxiety and other mood symptoms are not benign in 
women with BC, as they are associated with increased 
mortality and cancer recurrence. </p>

<p>9,10   Studies in Western countries (United States, 
Canada, England, Australia, and Germany) indicate a 
prevalence of significant anxiety ranging from 4-45% 
in BC patients, depending on anxiety measure, cutoff 
score, geographical region, and time since diagnosis </p>

<p>11-14   (compared with 15-37% of cancer patients in general 
with anxiety during the first year after diagnosis). 
15 The 
most commonly used measure of anxiety symptoms in 
BC patients is the Hospital Anxiety and Depression 
Scale (HADS), which assesses for "possible" and 
"probable" anxiety disorder (with a sensitivity and 
specificity of approximately 80%). 
12,16,17 Using this 
measure, the prevalence of "probable" anxiety disorder in 
BC patients ranges from 2-23% and "possible" anxiety 
disorder is present in an additional 19-22% (21-45% 
combined). 
11,13,18 Although factors that increase risk 
of anxiety in women with BC are poorly understood, 
a few studies largely from Western countries report 
more symptoms in younger persons and Caucasians, 
immigrants, those with lower education, later disease 
stage, and lower social support. 
8,11,13,19 In one of the few 
studies from an Eastern country, 
20 anxiety levels among 
BC patients from Bangkok, Thailand, were significantly 
higher among those with poor problem solving skills, 
more pain and fatigue, and poorer family functioning. 
Although research is limited almost entirely to the 
US and other Western countries, studies indicate that 
support from a spouse (especially emotional support) 
improves the adjustment of women to BC, 
21-25 and 
may even impact survival. 
26 Not all studies, however, 
report that having a marital partner buffers against the 
stress of BC. 
27,28 The demands of caregiving, the effects 
of BC and its treatments on sexual relationship, and 
coping with psychological changes in a BC patient can 
all lead to lower well-being in a spouse, and decrease 
his ability to provide support. 
24 Our exhaustive review 
of the literature uncovered several studies that have 
examined the prevalence of emotional reactions to BC </p>

<p>in the Middle East, finding that 19-73% of women 
had significant anxiety symptoms. 
22,29-34 In those 
studies, anxiety was associated with poorer physical 
functioning, the presence of metastatic disease, 
higher education, lower social support, duration of 
marriage, and spouse's level of anxiety. With regard 
to KSA, there has been a significant increase in the 
incidence of BC, which occurs at a younger age than 
in Western countries. 
35 A recent review of research on 
coping with BC, however, revealed not a single study 
from KSA. 
36 Our review identified only 2 studies </p>

<p>37,38   that examined the prevalence or correlates of anxiety 
in Saudi cancer patients (none specifically in BC), 
and only one study 
39 that examined attitudes of Saudi 
males toward BC. The first study examined anxiety in 
30 hospitalized patients with cancer (9 with BC) at the 
King Khalid National Guard Hospital in Jeddah, KSA. </p>

<p>37   Researchers found that anxiety symptoms assessed by 
the Hamilton Anxiety Scale were significantly higher 
in cancer patients compared with 39 patients with 
a range of chronic illnesses; 3 patients with cancer 
(10%) had a clinical diagnosis of generalized anxiety 
disorder based on Diagnostic and Statistical Manual 
of Mental Disorders, 4th edition (DSM-IV) criteria. 
The second study examined non-pain symptoms in 124 
cancer patients (27% with BC) at King Faisal Specialist 
Hospital in Riyadh, KSA. 
38 The most frequently reported 
non-pain symptoms were fatigue (80%), loss of appetite 
(72%), dry mouth (69%), and anxiety (61%). Finally, 
researchers examined attitudes toward BC among males 
accompanying female patients to outpatient clinics at 
King Abdulaziz Hospital in Jeddah, KSA. When men 
were asked what they would do if their wives were 
diagnosed with BC, 9.4% said they would leave their 
wives. </p>

<p>39   Given the current knowledge gap on this subject 
in KSA, we decided to: 1) determine the prevalence 
of anxiety symptoms in married women seen in an 
urban-based university outpatient clinic in Jeddah; 2) 
identify the correlates of anxiety symptoms (especially 
marital quality [MQ]); and 3) determine whether the 
relationship between MQ and anxiety differed between 
Saudi nationals and immigrants. We hypothesized 
that anxiety symptoms would be prevalent, that 
higher MQ would be strongly and inversely related to 
anxiety symptoms, and that this relationship would be 
particularly strong in women who were Saudi nationals 
(where cultural factors might have the most influence). </p>

<p>Methods. Identification of prior research studies was 
performed using the search terms: anxiety; BC; marital 
relationship; spouse; MQ; Middle East; and KSA in </p>

<p>Cancer &amp; anxiety ... Al-Zaben et al </p>



<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (10) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>various combinations. These search words were entered 
into PubMed and <rs type="software">Google Scholar</rs> to locate all relevant 
studies. A convenience sample of women with BC 
(volunteers) was recruited between January 2013 and 
March 2013 from King Abdulaziz University's (KAU) 
Sheikh Mohammed Hussein Al-Amoudi Breast Cancer 
Center of Excellence in Jeddah, KSA. Consecutive 
women presenting to the outpatient clinic for initial 
assessment or follow-up were approached for inclusion 
in the study. The inclusion criteria were: age 18 to 65 
years; diagnosis of BC documented in the medical 
record; currently married; and attending the clinic 
on the day that the interviewers were present in the 
clinic. The exclusion criteria were women without BC, 
those outside the age range above, those who were not 
currently married, and all those being seen on days and 
times when interviewers were not present. The average 
length of time that participants were diagnosed with 
and/or experienced symptoms of BC were 38.4 months 
(range 2 weeks to 180 months). The questionnaire 
was translated into Arabic, and was self-completed 
by participants. Medical students (trained by KAU 
psychiatry faculty on how to approach patients, obtain 
consent, and administer the questionnaire) explained 
the study to the participants and obtained informed 
consent before proceeding. The institutional review 
board of KAU Hospital approved the study following 
the principles of the Helsinki Declaration. 
Questionnaire. Participants were asked regarding 
their age (27-65 years), nationality/citizenship (Saudi=1 
versus immigrant=0), education level (none=1, primary 
school only=2, high school only=3, university=4, post-
graduate=5), employment status (yes=1 versus no=0), 
and family income per month (&lt;3,000 Saudi Arabian 
Riyals (SAR)=1; 3,000 to 5,000=2; &gt;5,000=3). Also 
assessed were duration of illness in months (0.5-180) 
and type of treatment received (radiation therapy, 
chemotherapy, surgery). 
Anxiety. The HADS 
16 is a self-rated scale commonly 
used to measure anxiety and depressive symptoms in 
outpatient medical populations including those in the 
Middle East. 
30,31,32 Scores of 0-7 are considered normal, 
8-10 signify "possible" anxiety disorder, and 11-21 
indicate "probable" anxiety disorder (range 0-21). The 
Cronbach's alpha for anxiety subscale (HADS-A) is 
reported to be high (0.85). 
40 The reliability and validity 
of HADS in Arabic has been previously established. 
41 In 
the current study, HADS-A subscale's alpha was 0.78 
(standardized), which is above the recommended 
threshold of 0.70. </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>Marital relations. Two standard scales were used to 
measure marital adjustment. The Spousal Perception </p>

<p>Scale (SPS) is a self-rated 12-item measure of emotional 
support and emotional strain in the relationship with 
a spouse. 
43 In the present study, we administered the 
6-item emotional support subscale where each item is 
rated from one (not at all) to 4 (a lot), with a score 
range from 6-24 (higher scores indicating greater 
perceived spousal support). The average score in the 
original validation study was approximately 20. 
43 The 
Cronbach's alpha of the scale is reported to be 0.91. 
44 In 
the present study, the internal reliability was similarly 
high (alpha=0.85). The second scale administered was 
the Quality of Marriage Index (QMI). 
45 The QMI is 
a 6-item self-rated scale that assesses the "essential 
goodness of a relationship." Each item is rated on a scale 
from one (very strong disagreement) to 7 (very strong 
agreement) with a theoretical score range of 7-42 (higher 
scores indicating a more positive marital relationship). 
Average scores have been reported to range from 28-37, 
with higher scores in men. 
46-48 Internal reliability of the 
QMI ranges from 0.91-0.97. 
44 The alpha in the present 
sample was 0.89. For inclusion in multivariate analyses, 
the SPS and QMI were combined to form a 12-item 
scale that ranged from 6-66 (alpha=0.91). Although the 
psychometric properties of the Arabic versions of the 
above 2 scales have not been established, we chose these 
measures based on their "content" validity; as noted 
above, both scales' reliability in the present sample was 
acceptable. 
Statistical analyses. The characteristics of the 
sample were described by means + standard deviations 
(SD) or percentages (Table 1). A correlation matrix 
(Pearson r) was constructed for all study variables (Table 2). 
In multivariate analyses, income was dichotomized 
into low (&lt;3,000=0) versus high (&gt;3,000=1), and 
education was dichotomized into low (0=no education 
or only primary school) versus high (one=high school or 
beyond). Blocks of independent variables were entered 
in a stepwise fashion into 3 general linear models 
predicting the dependent variable (anxiety symptoms): 
model one included only the sample demographics 
(age, nationality, education, employment, income); 
model 2 included demographics and cancer-related 
factors; and model 3 included demographics, cancer-
related factors, and overall MQ (Table 3). Given the 
sample size, only independent variables significant at 
p&lt;0.10 were carried forward into later models. Since 
these analyses were largely exploratory, the significance 
level was set at p=0.05, and analyses were not adjusted 
for multiple comparisons. All analyses were performed 
using the <rs id="software-2" type="software">Statistical Analysis System</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">9.3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc</rs>., Cary, North Carolina, USA). </p>

<p>Cancer &amp; anxiety ... Al-Zaben et al </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (10) </p>

<p>Results. Of the 50 women approached to participate 
in the study, all (100%) agreed to complete the 
questionnaire. One participant, however, completed 
only part of the questionnaire, leaving a final sample 
of 49. The average age of participants was 48.9 
(SD=7.1) years, with a range from 35-65 (Table 1). 
Most participants were Saudi citizens (58.3%).Three-
quarters (73.5%) had graduated from high school or 
attended college, although only one-third (31.9%) were 
employed. The average yearly family income was 
48,000 SAR (approximately $12,000 per year). The 
average duration of illness since diagnosis of BC was 
3 years (38.4 months). The most common type of 
cancer treatment was surgery (89.8%), followed by 
chemotherapy (83.7%) and radiation therapy (57.1%). 
Marital adjustment, on average, was low to moderate. </p>

<p>Perception of spouse support SPS averaged 16.7 
(SD=3.9) on a theoretical range of 6-24, indicating low 
to moderate support compared with an average of 20 in 
Western samples. 
43 The QMI averaged 31.0 (SD=5.7), 
indicating moderate MQ compared with scores in 
Western samples that have ranged from 28-37. 
46-48 The 
overall quality of the marital relationship (summing 
the SPS and QMI) averaged 47.6 (SD=8.7) with a 
theoretical score ranging from 12-66. The average 
number of anxiety symptoms was 5.6 (SD=3.8), ranging 
from 0-15 (where the theoretical score range was 0-21). 
The prevalence of 'possible' anxiety disorder (HADS-A 
score 8-10) was 10.4% and 'probable' anxiety disorder 
(HADS-A score 11-21) was 14.6%. The most common 
anxiety symptom was feeling frightened something 
awful would happen, while the least common symptom </p>

<p>Table 1 -Characteristics of the participants included in a study on anxiety in Jeddah, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia 
(n=49). </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Mean ± SD (range) 
n (%) 
Demographics 
Nationality, Saudi 
28 (58.3) 
Age, years 
48.9 ± 7.1 
(35-65) 
Education, high school or beyond 
36 (73.5) 
Employment status, employed 
15 (31.9) 
Family income per year (SAR) 
&lt;36,000 
6 (12.2) 
36,000-60,000 
30 (61.2) 
&gt;6,000 
13 (26.5) </p>

<p>Cancer characteristics 
Duration of illness, months 
38.4 ± 48.9 (0.5-180) 
Treatment 
Radiation therapy 
28 (57.1) 
Chemotherapy 
41 (83.7) 
Surgery 
44 (89.8) </p>

<p>Anxiety 
Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale-A (HADS-A) (total) 
5.6 ± 3.8 
(0-15) 
1) Feels tense or wound up 
0.8 ± 0.7 
(0-3) 
2) Feels frightened: something awful will happen 
1.2 ± 1.0 
(0-3) 
3) Experiences worrying thoughts 
0.9 ± 0.8 
(0-3) 
4) Feels at ease and relaxed (reverse) 
0.8 ± 0.9 
(0-3) 
5) Feels frightened like butterflies in stomach 
0.8 ± 0.9 
(0-3) 
6) Feels restless and need to be on the move 
0.7 ± 0.8 
(0-3) 
7) Has sudden feeling of panic 
0.5 ± 0.7 
(0-2) 
HADS-A score 0-7 (no significant anxiety) 
36 (75.0) 
HADS-A score 8-10 (possible anxiety) 
5 (10.4) 
HADS-A score 11-21 (probable significant anxiety) 
7 (14.6) </p>

<p>Marital Quality 
Spousal Perception Scale (SPS) (total) 
16.7 ± 3.9 
(6-23) 
Quality of Marriage Index (QMI) (total) 
31.0 ± 5.7 
(9-40) 
Total Marital Quality (SPS + QMI) 
47.6 ± 8.7 
(15-62) 
 *  N varies by less than 5%, SAR -Saudi Arabian Riyal=(0.27 US dollars) </p>

<p>Cancer &amp; anxiety ... Al-Zaben et al </p>



<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (10) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>was having a sudden feeling of panic. Bivariate correlates 
of anxiety symptoms were lower education (r=-0.48, 
p=0.0005), lower income (r=-0.38, p=0.007), and not 
receiving radiation therapy (r=-0.32, p=0.03) (Table 2). 
There were weak, non-significant inverse relationships 
between symptoms of anxiety and the perception that 
the spouse cares and understands (r=-.21, p=0.15), 
perceived MQ (r=-0.08, p=0.58), and overall quality 
of the relationship (r=-0.15, p=0.32) (Figure 1), where 
average anxiety scores are plotted again MQ in decile 
(tenths). Multivariate analyses indicated that only 
age (B=-0.12, standard error [SE]=0.05, p=0.01) 
and education (B=-4.75, SE=1.07, p&lt;0.0001) were </p>

<p>independently associated with anxiety symptoms (Table 
3) Model 3. As in bivariate analyses, no significant 
relationship was found between the overall quality 
of the marital relationship and anxiety symptoms 
(B=-0.04, SE=0.05, t=-0.81, p=0.42). Nationality did 
not moderate this relationship (interaction B=0.07, 
SE=12.7, t=0.59, p=0.56). In other words, the inverse 
relationship between marital relationship quality and 
anxiety was not stronger in women who were Saudi 
citizens compared with those who were immigrants. </p>

<p>Discussion. Approximately one in 7 women 
(14.6%) had anxiety symptoms that were frequent </p>

<p>Table 2 -Bivariate correlations between all study variables as found in a study on anxiety in Jeddah, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. </p>

<p>Variables 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 
13 
Age 
0.12 -0.13 -0.02 
0.16 
0.27* 0.30* 0.10 
0.17 -0.18 
-0.16 
-0.10 
-0.15 
Nationality 
-
0.36* 0.42* 0.48* 0.16 
0.19 
-0.04 
0.13 -0.20 
-0.13 
-0.09 
-0.13 
Education 
-
-
0.63* 0.66* 0.22 
0.18 
-0.04 -0.08 -0.48* 
0.27* 
0.30* 
0.31* 
Employment 
-
-
-
0.31* 0.06 
0.13 
-0.05 
0.09 -0.20 
0.29* 
0.15 
0.26* 
Income 
-
-
-
-
0.38* 0.27* -0.08 -0.03 -0.38* 
0.00 
0.09 
0.04 
Duration 
-
-
-
-
-
0.59* 
0.33* 0.22 -0.11 
0.11 
0.19 
0.16 
Radiation therapy 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.51* 0.25 -0.32* -0.05 
-0.01 
-0.04 
Chemotherapy 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-0.15 -0.12 
0.01 
-0.05 
-0.01 
Surgery 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.02 
-0.21 
-0.09 
-0.18 
HADS-A 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-0.08 
-0.21 
-0.15 
QMI 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.65* 
0.94* 
SPS 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.87* 
MQ-total 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
SPS -Spousal Perception Scale, QMI -Quality of Marriage Index, MQ -marital quality, MQ-total -SPS + QMI, 
HADS-A -Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale-Anxiety, *p&lt;0.10, </p>

<p>Table 3 -Multivariate model examining relationship between anxiety (HADS-A) and overall 
marital quality (MQ-total) of the study sample. </p>

<p>Demographics 
Model 1 
Model 2 
Model 3 
B (SE) 
Age 
-0.12 (0.05) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-0.10 (0.05) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>-0.12 (0.05) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Nationality 
-0.97 (1.07) 
---
---
Education 
-4.33 (1.51) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-4.60 (1.08) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>-4.75 (1.07) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Employment 
-0.02 (1.12) 
---
---
Income 
-2.61 (1.79) 
---
---</p>

<p>Illness characteristics 
Duration of illness 
---
0.01 (0.01) 
---
Rx (radiation versus other) 
---
-1.91 (1.19) 
---</p>

<p>Marital quality 
MQ-total 
---
---
-0.04 (0.05) 
Model R-square (n) 
0.43 (46) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.38 (48) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.35 (48) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>HADS-A -Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale-Anxiety, MQ-total-SPS + QMI, 
SPS -Spousal Perception Scale, QMI -Quality of Marriage Index, Rx -treatment, 
B (SE)=unstandardized beta (standard error), </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>p&lt;0.05, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p≤0.01, </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>p≤0.001 </p>

<p>Cancer &amp; anxiety ... Al-Zaben et al </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (10)   enough to qualify them for a "probable" anxiety 
disorder, and an additional 10.4% had symptoms on 
the HADS that indicated a "possible" anxiety disorder, 
resulting in a total of 25% with significant anxiety 
symptoms. This prevalence rate of anxiety symptoms is 
similar to that reported in Western countries using the 
HADS (2-23% for probable anxiety disorder; 19-22% 
for possible disorder, 21-45% combined), although is 
on the low side. 
11,13,18 Contrary to our predictions, the 
quality of the marital relationship was not significantly 
related to anxiety symptoms, and nationality (Saudi 
versus immigrant) did not moderate this relationship. 
More important as a risk factor for anxiety were age 
and education. Younger women were more likely to 
experience anxiety symptoms, as were women with 
lower education, lower income, and lack of employment 
(which education probably acted as a proxy for 
in multivariate analyses). No other characteristic 
(including time since diagnosis) was related to anxiety 
symptoms. 
Our failure to find a relationship between anxiety 
symptoms and perceived support from the spouse, or 
quality of the marriage may be due to several factors. 
First, religious and cultural traditions in this patriarchal 
society may have led women to accept and successfully 
cope with lack of spousal support, and therefore 
adapt to their cancer in other ways -perhaps through 
support from other family members, or their religious 
beliefs. A second possibility was our sample size, which 
reduced the power of this study to detect significant 
relationships. However, the very weak relationship 
between overall marital adjustment and anxiety 
symptoms (B=-0.04, SE=0.05) reduces the likelihood </p>

<p>that statistically or clinically significant relationships 
would be found even in a much larger sample. Third, 
women who participated in this study had been living 
with a diagnosis of BC for an average of 3 years and 
were still married. Not included were women whose 
diagnosis of BC led to marital discord and divorce. 
Such a selection effect would reduce the variability in 
anxiety symptoms and marital discord in our sample 
of married women whose marriages had endured and 
stabilized over time. The net effect of all these factors 
would be to lower our ability to detect an adverse effect 
of the BC diagnosis on anxiety symptoms and MQ. 
The inverse relationship between age and anxiety 
found here has been reported by other researchers in 
Western countries, including studies in the United 
States, 
8 Germany, 
13 and Australia. 
11 However, this 
is the first time that an inverse association has been 
reported in the Middle East and Far East since the 
published studies from Iran 
31 and Thailand 
20 did not 
find an association between anxiety and age. There are 
several reasons why younger women with BC are likely 
to have higher levels of anxiety. First, the diagnosis of 
BC at a young age is not "on time" as it might be in 
later life when cancer is more common and expected. 
Having one's life cut short by cancer can interfere 
with future dreams and hopes for family and work. 
Second, having BC diagnosed at a young age during 
the reproductive years can interfere with body image 
(following mastectomy), female identity, and sexual 
intimacy, and convey a sense of loss of control that may 
increase anxiety levels. Younger women may also be less 
likely to agree to, and comply with hormonal therapies 
that interfere with their sexual activity, 
49 and may cause 
premature menopause, 
50 increasing anxiety toward the 
course of the cancer and premature mortality. Finally, 
the strongest risk factor we identified for anxiety was 
lower education. Again, this finding is consistent with 
reports from Western countries, such as Germany 
13 and 
Australia, 
11 although is inconsistent with one of the only 
studies on anxiety in BC patients in the Middle East, 
where higher levels of education were associated with 
more anxiety (Iran). 
31 Women with lower education 
may not be aware of the surgical, chemotherapeutic, 
and radiation therapies available that successfully cure 
BC or improve its prognosis, or in some instances, may 
not be able to afford such treatments. Imagining a death 
sentence with BC, or a poor prognosis when nothing 
can be done could certainly increase anxiety. 
Limitations. We acknowledge several limitations 
of the present study. First, the sample was a relatively 
small convenience sample and acquired from only one 
university-based urban BC clinic, which limits our ability </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Relationship between quality of the marital 
relationship and anxiety symptoms, with 
standard errors. HADS-A -Hospital Anxiety and 
Depression Scale -Anxiety subscale. </p>

<p>Cancer &amp; anxiety ... Al-Zaben et al </p>



<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (10) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>to generalize the study findings to women with BC in 
rural areas, or those seeking care in other government-
supported and private settings. Second, the cross-
sectional nature of these analyses precludes speculation 
regarding the direction of effects in the relationships 
detected (namely, a hereditary predisposition to anxiety 
could just as well impair women's ability to complete 
their education, as lack of education could lead to 
greater anxiety). Third, detailed information on cancer 
stage, severity of disability, or interference with mobility, 
and the presence of other medical co-morbidities were 
not assessed, limiting our ability to control for these 
factors in multivariate analyses. Finally, the way in 
which anxiety was measured (by a count of symptoms 
and their severity) did not allow for an assessment of 
interference with social, occupational, or recreational 
functioning, precluding our ability to determine the 
true prevalence of anxiety disorder. Nevertheless, this 
study also has a number of strengths. First, we used 
standard psychometrically valid measures to assess 
anxiety symptoms and MQ, and carefully analyzed 
the data using stepwise multivariate statistics. Second, 
the use of the HADS-A to assess anxiety symptoms 
allows for comparison of our results with past studies, 
and those to be conducted in the future. Third, to our 
knowledge, this is the first report from KSA on the 
prevalence or correlates of anxiety symptoms and the 
relationship between MQ and anxiety symptoms in 
married women with BC. Given the important role 
that religion, cultural, and social forces play in this part 
of the world, 
51 these initial preliminary findings should 
help to stimulate future research on anxiety in women 
with BC in this country and throughout the Middle 
East. 
In conclusion, anxiety symptoms are present in a 
significant number of married women with BC being 
followed up in a university-based BC clinic in Jeddah, 
KSA, especially those who are younger and with lower 
education. Although weak trends were found in the 
expected direction, no significant relationship was found 
between perceptions of spousal support or quality of the 
marital relationship and anxiety symptoms. Cultural 
factors, low power due to sample size, high quality 
of care, and a selection effect may at least partially 
explain these findings. Given that between 15% and 
25% of women with BC experience significant anxiety 
symptoms, these findings should stimulate clinicians 
to screen women with BC for anxiety and other mood 
symptoms, and then treat significant symptoms with 
psychotherapy and/or appropriate doses of a serotonin 
re-uptake inhibitor. </p>



<p>Cancer &amp; anxiety ... Al-Zaben et al </p>





</text></tei>