<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4922354" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Summary </p>

<p>Background: The purpose of the present study was to 
report and discuss the hematological and biochemical 
behavior of elite soccer players, in order to get more insight 
in the physiological characteristics of these sportsmen and 
to provide trainers and sports doctors with useful indicators. 
Methods: Nineteen male soccer players volunteered to par-
ticipate in this study. We followed the young elite soccer 
players during a competitive half season. Venous blood 
samples were collected between 9:00 and 10:00 a.m. 
after an overnight fast (10 h) at baseline, after 45 and 90 
days and hematological and biochemical parameters were 
measured. 
Results: Hemoglobin and hematocrit levels were signifi-
cantly reduced over the observational period (p&lt;0.05), but 
erythrocyte count and iron levels remained unchanged. 
Bilirubin and ferritin levels significantly increased in 
response to regular soccer training (p&lt;0.05). We observed 
a significant decrease in muscle enzyme plasma activity 
during the 90 days study period. ANOVA analysis revealed 
a significant increase in the leukocyte and neutrophil 
counts (p&lt;0.05), in parallel with a significant decrease in 
the lymphocyte count (p&lt;0.05) after the observational 
period of 90 days. 
Conclusions: Elite soccer players are characterized by sig-
nificant changes in biochemical and hematological param-</p>

<p>Kratak sadr`aj </p>

<p>Uvod: Cilj ove studije je bio da se odrede i analiziraju 
hematolo{ki i biohemijski parametri kod elitnih fudbalera, 
kako bi se dobio bolji uvid u fiziolo{ke karakteristike ovih 
sportista i pru`ile korisne informacije trenerima i doktorima 
sportske medicine. 
Metode: Devetnaest fudbalera je dobrovoljno u~estvovalo u 
ovoj studiji. Mlade elitne fudbalere smo pratili tokom druge 
polovine sezone. Uzorci venske krvi su sakupljeni nata{te, 
izme|u 9.00 i 10.00 ~asova, na po~etku studije i nakon 45 
i 90 dana redovnih treninga, i odre|eni su osnovni bio-
hemijski i hematolo{ki parametri. 
Rezultati: Nivo hemoglobina i hematokrit se zna~ajno 
smanjuju u toku posmatranog perioda (p&lt;0,05), dok su 
broj eritrocita i koncentracija serumskog gvo`|a ostali 
nepromenjeni. Nivo bilirubina i feritina se zna~ajno pove -
}ava kao posledica redovnih treninga (p&lt;0,05). Zapazili 
smo zna~ajno smanjenje nivoa mi{i}nih enzima u serumu 
tokom 90 dana. ANOVA je otkrila zna~ajno pove}anje 
broja leukocita i neutrofila (p&lt;0,05), kao i zna~ajno sma -
njenje broja limfocita (p&lt;0,05) posle 90 dana redovnih 
treninga. 
Zaklju~ak: Elitni mladi fudbaleri pokazuju zna~ajne 
promene u vrednostima biohemijskih i hematolo{kih para-
metara tokom druge polovine sezone, koje su posledica 
treninga, ali i adaptacije na fizi~ku aktivnost. Iako su vred-</p>

<p>J Med Biochem 2015; 34 (4) </p>



<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Soccer is a multiple-sprint sport that requires 
high-intensity, intermittent activity to be undertaken 
over an extended period of time. In addition to inten-
sive daily training sessions, players are involved in 
additional commitments such as national cups and 
other matches. These competitive demands may 
impose strains to various physiological systems, 
including the musculoskeletal, nervous, immune and 
metabolic, which might be reflected in changes in the 
biochemical and hematological parameters (1). 
Despite its diffu sion and popularity, very few studies 
have been performed concerning the biochemistry 
and hematology of soccer players. Surprisingly, hema-
tological parameters and biochemical characteristics 
which can be crucial for predicting optimal physical 
performance have been scarcely examined in elite 
soccer players, who are involved in very demanding 
competitive seasons. We followed the young elite soc-
cer players during a competitive half season. In the 
present study, we report and discuss the hematologi-
cal and biochemical behavior of the athletes, in order 
to get more insight in the physiological characteristics 
of these sportsmen and to provide trainers and sports 
doctors with useful indicators. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Subjects </p>

<p>Nineteen male soccer players, members of the 
young selection of the soccer club »Partizan«, Bel -
grade, Serbia, volunteered to participate in this study. 
One month prior to entering the study and during the 
study, the participants were instructed to abstain from 
vitamin and mineral supplementation, ergogenic aid 
or any medications in general. Subjects were also 
advised not to make any drastic changes in their diet 
during the study period. The physicians of the outpa-
tient clinic »Vita Maxima«, Belgrade, Serbia evaluated 
the physical performance of all participants, and sport 
injury rates and incidence were recorded. </p>

<p>The study was undertaken in compliance with 
the Helsinki Declaration and approved by the Ethical 
Committee of the Sports Medicine Association of 
Serbia. The soccer players and parents gave written 
informed consent after having been explained the 
procedures, benefits and possible risks of participa-
tion in the study. </p>

<p>Baseline measurements and screening for 
aerobic capacity </p>

<p>Subjects reported to the laboratory and their 
height, weight and total body fat were measured 
using a portable stadiometer and body composition 
analyzer (BC-418, Tanita, Japan), respectively. Then 
the subjects completed a maximal oxygen consump-
tion test (VO 2 max). VO 2 max was measured on a 
motor-driven treadmill (Run race, Techno gym, Italy), 
using an indirect calorimetry system (Quark b2, 
Cosmed, Italy) with an incremental exercise test to 
volitional fatigue. To estimate average energy and 
nutritional intake, soccer players recorded their 
dietary intake during 4 consecutive days. The energy, 
macronutrient and micronutrient intakes were calcu-
lated using <rs id="software-0" type="software">CRON-O-Meter</rs> v<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">0.9.6</rs>. software. </p>

<p>Study design </p>

<p>We followed the young elite soccer players dur-
ing a competitive half season, over a three-month 
period (March, April and May). During the study, the 
soccer players were engaged in a controlled training 
programme, that consisted of 7-8 training sessions 
per week (∼720 min), comprised of exercise on the 
soccer field (5-6 times a week, ∼600 min) and weight 
training (2 times a week, 120 min) sessions, in addi-
tion to a weekly match. Over this period, the training 
and preparatory programme took place at the sport 
centre »Partizan-Teleoptik« in Belgrade. Venous blood 
samples were collected between 9:00 and 10:00 
a.m. after an overnight fast (10 h) at baseline, after 
45 and 90 days. </p>

<p>Blood collection and analysis </p>

<p>All blood samples were collected into heparin 
vacutainer tubes, K-EDTA treated vacutainer tubes 
and nonadditive serum vacutainer tubes (Greiner Bio-
one, Kremsmünster, Austria). Plasma and serum were 
separated by centrifugation and multiple aliquots of 
each sample were stored at -80 °C until analysis. </p>

<p>The hematological parameters [leukocytes 
(WBC), erythrocytes (RBC), hemoglobin (Hb), hema-
tocrit (Ht), platelets (PLT), mean corpuscular volume 
(MCV), mean cell hemoglobin (MCH), mean cell 
hemoglobin corpuscular (MCHC), lymphocytes, neu-</p>

<p>eters over the half season, which are linked to training 
workload, as well as adaptation induced by the soccer train-
ing. Although the values of the measured parameters fell 
within the reference range, regular monitoring of the bio-
chemical and hematological parameters is fundamental for 
the identification of a healthy status and related optimal 
performances by sport doctors and trainers and selection of 
a correct workload by trainers. </p>

<p>Keywords: soccer, hematology, biochemistry </p>

<p>nosti ovih parametara bile u granicama referentnih vred -
nosti, pra}enje biohemijskih i hematolo{kih parametara je 
osnova za procenu zdravstvenog statusa sportista i optimal-
nih sportskih performansi, ali i korisno sredstvo za odre -
|ivanje optimalnog intenziteta i u~estalosti treninga. </p>

<p>Klju~ne re~i: fudbal, hematologija, biohemija </p>



<p>trophils, basophiles, eosinophils, monocytes] were 
obtained from CellDyn 3700 (Abbott, Chicago, IL, 
USA). Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspar-
tate aminotransferase (AST), creatine kinase (CK), 
lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), uric acid, creatinine 
(Cre), billirubin, glucose, total proteins, urea, hs-CRP, 
along with iron, ferritin and transferrin were mea -
sured using an ILab 300 Plus autoanalyser employing 
reagents purchased from Biosystems S.A. (Barcelona, 
Spain) and Bioanalytica (Belgrade, Serbia). Percen -
tage changes in plasma volume during the study peri-
od were assesed by the method described by Dill and  Costill (2). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were inspected for normal distribution 
using the Kolmogrov-Smirnov test. Results are 
expressed as mean ± SEM for normally distributed 
variables. When the distribution differed from normal, 
geometric means and 95% confidence intervals were 
given. Hematological and biochemical parameters 
were analyzed using the ANOVA repeated-measures 
general linear model. Non-normally distributed data 
were transformed logarithmically, before statistical 
comparisons were made. Spearman's non-parametric 
correlation analysis was used to assess univariate 
associations between studied variables. P values ≤ 
0.05 were considered statistically significant. Stati -
stical analyses were performed using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">PASW Statistics</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">18.0</rs> and <rs id="software-2" type="software">MedCalc</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">11.4</rs> 
Software, Belgium) software. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Table I presents the anthropometric characteris-
tics of the athletes and the data obtained in the ma x -
imal oxygen consumption test. </p>

<p>The mean daily energy intakes, as well as the 
mean daily intake of protein, fat, carbohydrates, vita-
mins and minerals, are presented in Table II. </p>

<p>Markers of iron metabolism are shown in Table 
III. Hemoglobin, hematocrit levels, MCV and transfer-
rin were significantly reduced over the observational 
period (p=0.045, p=0.040, p=0.036, p=0.025, 
respectively). RBC count, platelet counts, MCH, 
MCHC and iron levels remained unchanged, while 
ferritin levels significantly increased throughout the 
study (p=0.048). All the values of measured param-
eters fell within the reference range. Plasma volume 
increased by 9% after 45 days of regular training and 
then decreased by 1.5% by the end of the observa-
tional period. </p>

<p>We observed significant decrease in AST, CK 
and LDH plasma activity during the 90 days study 
period (p=0.038, p=0.049 and p=0.003 respec-
tively), in parallel with the decrease in uric acid, Cre </p>

<p>and total proteins levels (p=0.009, p=0.024 and 
p=0.012, respectively). Bilirubin levels significantly 
increased in response to regular soccer training 
(p=0.028). We observed an increase in hs-CRP after 
the 90 days of regular soccer training, although mar-
ginally significant (p=0.08). No significant changes 
were found regarding ALT, glucose and urea levels 
over the study period. CK, LDH and Cre levels were 
above normal values during the entire observational 
period, while the other biochemical parameters were 
within the reference range. </p>

<p>Table I Anthropometric characteristics of the soccer players. </p>

<p>Age (years) 
17.62±0.14 </p>

<p>Weight (kg) 
72.3±1.8 </p>

<p>Height (cm) 
180.2±1.4 </p>

<p>Body mass index (kg/m 2 ) 
22.24±0.41 </p>

<p>Fat (%) 
9.72±0.81 </p>

<p>VO 2max (mL/min/kg) 
52.9±0.7 </p>

<p>Training experience (years) 
9.88±0.21 </p>

<p>Table II Estimated daily energy and nutrient intake of the 
soccer players. </p>

<p>Energy (kcal) 
2932±147 </p>

<p>Protein (g) 
125±6.3 </p>

<p>Carbohydrates (g) 
366±23 </p>

<p>Monosaccharides (g) 
123±18 </p>

<p>Fiber (g) 
12.6±1.5 </p>

<p>Fat (g) 
101±7 </p>

<p>Saturated fat (g) 
29.9±3.2 </p>

<p>Cholesterol (mg) 
344±38 </p>

<p>Vitamin A (IU) 
2120±389 </p>

<p>Vitamin C (mg) 
135±30 </p>

<p>Vitamin E (mg) 
6.1±1.5 </p>

<p>Copper (mg) 
1.92±0.5 </p>

<p>Iron (mg) 
15.1±1.6 </p>

<p>Manganese (mg) 
4.0±0.9 </p>

<p>Selenium (mg) 
164±8 </p>

<p>Zinc (mg) 
13.5±1.8 </p>

<p>Values are expressed as mean ± SEM. </p>

<p>Values are expressed as mean ± SEM. </p>

<p>J Med Biochem 2015; 34 (4) </p>



<p>Table III Mean values of the hematological parameters and plasma volume changes in elite soccer players at baseline, after 45 
and after 90 days of regular soccer training over the competitive half season. </p>

<p>Table IV Biochemical profile of the soccer players at baseline, after 45 and after 90 days of regular soccer training over the com-
petitive half season. </p>

<p>Table V Total blood leukocyte count, lymphocyte, neutrophil, basophil, eosinophil and monocyte counts in soccer players at base-
line, after 45 and after 90 days of regular soccer training. </p>

<p>Parameter 
Baseline 
After 45 days 
After 90 days </p>

<p>Hb (g/L) 
157±3.9 
151±2.0* 
152±2.1 </p>

<p>Hct (L/L) 
0.482±0.010 
0.457±0.006** 
0.462±0.005 </p>

<p>RBC (×10 12 /L) 
5.4±0.10 
5.2±0.07 
5.3±0.05 </p>

<p>MCV (fL) 
88.64±0.89 
87.58±0.40 
86.81±0.73* </p>

<p>MCH (pg) 
28.9±0.31 
28.9±0.33 
28.5±0.31 </p>

<p>MCHC (g/L) 
326±2.3 
330±3.0 
329±2.4 </p>

<p>PLT (×10 9 /L) 
253±12.7 
247±10.6 
249±9.5 </p>

<p>Iron (mmol/L) 
10.8±0.70 
9.6±0.92 
10.3±0.84 </p>

<p>Ferritin (mg/L) '' 
49(32.1-77.8) 
63(49.6-80.7) 
69(51.7-91.8)* </p>

<p>Transferrin (g/L) 
2.87±0.09 
2.66±0.08* 
2.72±0.08 </p>

<p>Plasma volume changes (%) 
+9% 
-1.5% </p>

<p>'Mean±SEM: ''Geometric mean values (95 th confidence interval). 
The difference in relation to baseline was significant at p&lt;0.05 (*) and p&lt;0.01(**). </p>

<p>Values are expressed as mean ± SEM. 
The difference in relation to baseline was significant at p&lt;0.05 (*). The difference in relation to day 45 was significant at p&lt;0.05 (#). </p>

<p>Parameter 
Baseline 
After 45 days 
After 90 days </p>

<p>ALT (U/L)" 
20(18.6-22.5) 
18(16.7-20.1) 
19(16.1-22.6) </p>

<p>AST (U/L)" 
41(35.7-47.0) 
32.2(28.6-36.4)* 
28.7(24.5-33.6)* </p>

<p>CK (U/L)" 
421(204-870) 
477(348-654) 
342(215-544)# </p>

<p>LDH (U/L) 
441±17.5 
395±10.5 
359±15.8**# </p>

<p>Uric acid (mmol/L) 
355±16.6 
368±23.5 
314±13.7* # </p>

<p>Creatinine (mmol/L) 
133±3 
135±3 
131±3# </p>

<p>Bilirubin (mmol/L) 
12.6±1.80 
16.8±1.89* 
19.6±2.18* </p>

<p>Glucose (mmol/L) 
6.1±0.17 
6.0±1.9 
5.8±0.13 </p>

<p>Total proteins (g/L) 
77±0.9 
75±1.6 
73±1.2*# </p>

<p>Urea (mmol/L) 
6.6±0.36 
6.5±0.38 
7.0±0.41 </p>

<p>hs-CRP (mg/L)" 
1.26(0.89-1.78) 
1.58(0.81-2.3) 
1.98(1.24-3.17) </p>

<p>Parameter 
Baseline 
After 45 days 
After 90 days </p>

<p>WBC ( x10 9 /L) 
6.0±0.2 
5.7±0.2 
6.7±0.4# </p>

<p>Lymphocytes (%) 
39.7±2.1 
38.3±1.8 
33.9±2.5* </p>

<p>Neutrophils (%) 
49.0±2.2 
50.1±1.9 
55.1±2.1* </p>

<p>Basophils (%) 
1.2±0.2 
1.1±0.1 
1.0±0.15 </p>

<p>Eosinophils (%) 
2.1±0.2 
2.1±0.3 
1.9±0.3 </p>

<p>Monocytes (%) 
8.0±0.6 
8.4±0.5 
8.1±0.5 </p>

<p>'Mean±SE: ''Geometric mean values (95 th confidence interval). 
The difference in relation to baseline was significant at p&lt;0.05 (*) and p&lt;0.01(**). The difference in relation to day 45 was sig-
nificant at p&lt;0.05 (#). </p>

<p>ANOVA analysis revealed a significant increase 
in the WBC (p=0.05) count in parallel with a signifi-
cant decrease in the lymphocyte count (p=0.027) 
and increase in the neutrophil count after 90 days of 
observation compared to baseline values (p=0.045). 
There were no significant changes in the basophil, 
neutrophil or monocyte counts. Total and differential 
blood leukocyte counts were in the reference range. </p>

<p>BMI was positively correlated with Cre levels at 
the beginning of the study (r=0.460, p&lt;0.01). We 
found positive correlation between bilirubin and fer-
ritin levels at baseline and after 90 days of regular 
soccer training (r=0.531, p&lt;0.05; r=0.571, p&lt;0.05, 
respectively). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The physiologic stress induced by prolonged 
and intensive physical activity is reflected in transient 
yet significant changes in biochemical and hemato-
logical parameters. Regular monitoring of these 
parameters in elite athletes during a competitive sea-
son might be useful for detecting possible iron defi-
ciency, anemia or other health problems, in addition 
to exercise planning and training programming. </p>

<p>The stability of hematologic status indices is one 
of the key determinants of optimal exercise perform-
ance, particularly in endurance sports such as soccer. 
Several investigators suggested that the value of 
hematologic indices and iron status measures in elite 
athletes varies during the season as a consequence of 
different training regimes (3-5). It was shown that 
hematological parameters were higher at the begin-
ning of the competition season and then declined in 
well-trained athletes (6). Although low values of 
hematological variables have been observed in ath-
letes during intensive training periods compared with 
clinical norms (7), other investigations have verified 
normal concentrations of hematological indices 
throughout training programmes (5, 8). We observed 
that hemoglobin, hematocrit, MCV and transferrin 
diminished significantly in the soccer players during 
the first 45 days of regular training. The decrease in 
Hb and Ht during a competitive season might be an 
indicator of heavy effort, as showed in aerobic heavy 
sports such as cycling and triathlon (9, 10), 
endurance and ultra endurance events (11), but also 
in football (6). However, despite the decrease in Hb 
and Hct, we did not detect any decrease in the red 
blood cell count. Accordingly, other studies showed a 
decrease in Hb and Hct and no changes in RBC or 
total red blood cell volume (12, 13). Generally, train-
ing induces hemodilution due to plasma volume 
expansion, which is a compensatory mechanism that 
increases cardiac output and reduces blood viscosity, 
thereby optimizing microcirculation and improving 
oxygen delivery to the working muscle (14). In fact, 
we observed a plasma volume expansion from base-</p>

<p>line to day 45 (Table III), which reinforces the pre mise 
that the decrement in Hb and Hct during competitive 
half season occurs because of the plasma volume 
expansion. </p>

<p>Bilirubin is the end-product of hemoglobin 
catabolism; therefore, its increased concentration in 
serum probably indicates a certain degree of hemoly-
sis, owing to mechanical trauma, but also oxidative 
injuries of the erythrocytes (15, 16). In the present 
study, bilirubin levels in soccer players increased sig-
nificantly over the 3 months of regular training. 
However, we did not detect any impairment at the 
level of the circulating erythrocyte pool. In addition, 
we could observe neither an increase in serum iron 
levels potentially reflecting hemolysis, nor an increase 
in transferrin levels possibly showing accelerated ery-
thropoiesis secondary to hemolysis. On the other 
hand, it may be that increased myoglobin levels, due 
to muscle damage, and subsequent myoglobin 
degradation, also contribute to the increased bilirubin 
production. </p>

<p>Ferritin values presented a trend different from 
that observed in a wide sample of elite football play-
ers, in which the parameter peaked at the middle of 
the season (6). Other studies showed decrease in fer-
ritin during the season in runners and swimmers (17), 
as well as in subjects performing a 12-week period of 
heavy training (18). The results of the present study 
are similar to those reported in the study of Banfi et  al. (5), with a significant increase in ferritin levels at 
the end of the observational period. In addition, we 
observed a positive correlation between ferritin and 
bilirubin levels in soccer players. Increased levels of 
bilirubin detected in the present study could suggest 
hemolysis and release of free iron in the blood. Iron is 
essential for normal cell growth and proliferation. 
However, excess iron might be potentially harmful, as 
it can catalyze the formation of toxic reactive oxygen 
species via Fenton chemistry. Therefore, the in -
creased levels of serum ferritin might be an adaptive 
response to increased oxidative stress mediated by 
iron, because ferritin sequester iron in blood or in 
cells and attenuate its pro-oxidant activity. The results 
of our study are in accordance with several results 
supporting a role of ferritin in the protection against 
oxygen free radical-mediated damage (19, 20). </p>

<p>The kind of sport and the related different 
anthro pometric characteristics of athletes might affect 
Cre levels. Previous studies reported lower serum Cre 
in cyclists, Nordic skiers and swimmers (21, 22) and 
higher serum Cre levels in soccer and rugby players 
than those observed in controls (23). Values of serum 
Cre in young soccer players exceeded the reference 
intervals for the general population (62-115 mmol/L) 
over the entire observational period. This difference 
may be linked to the generally higher muscle mass in 
athletes, because total muscle mass is the most 
important determinant of the creatine pool size and </p>

<p>464 Barali} et al.: Hematology and biochemistry in soccer </p>

<p>J Med Biochem 2015; 34 (4) </p>



<p>creatinine production (24). As previously demonstrat-
ed, we found significant correlation between the Cre 
concentration and BMI (21, 25). Serum Cre levels in 
soccer players decreased significantly throughout the 
study, which might be associated with the increase in 
training and competition workloads during competi-
tive season. Similar results were obtained in other 
sport disciplines, such as alpine skiing and rugby (25). </p>

<p>During high intensity exercise, the purine 
nucleotide system is extremely active and the elimina-
tion of adenosine monophosphate (AMP) causes a 
buildup of hypoxanthine, which is converted to UA 
(26). The involvement of purine nucleotide metabo-
lism in soccer has been reported, demonstrating a 
marked ATP reduction and increased blood UA fol-
lowing soccer activity (27). Regular soccer training 
induced decrease in plasma UA in soccer players, 
which might be related to lower release of hypoxan-
thine from the muscle. Enhanced capacity of muscles 
to regenerate ATP might be one of the reasons for 
this (28). Therefore, diminished accumulation of UA 
might be a part of the adaptive response induced by 
the soccer training programme. </p>

<p>Soccer is aerobic-anaerobic sport and involves 
eccentric muscle contractions resulting in muscle cell 
breakdown and leakage of cell content (29, 30). We 
observed increased plasma muscle enzymes in soccer 
players above normal values during the entire com-
petitive season, which might indicate extensive cell 
damage and an impaired functional status of the 
muscle tissue. Exercise-induced trauma to the muscu-
lature has been shown to lead to an inflammatory 
response and migration of phagocytic cells into the 
affected area. We noticed increased neutrophil counts 
over the observational period, which was accompa-
nied with increase in hs-CRP levels. Such changes 
implicate that regular soccer training might be associ-
ated with minor inflammatory events. Increase in CRP, 
if observed chronically, is associated with increased 
risk of coronary vascular disease (31). On the other 
hand, repair of muscle injury is dependent on inflam-
matory mediators and it is not clear whether this 
inflammatory response needs to be curbed for better 
recovery and improved function. Despite the ob -
ser ved increase in neutrophil count and hsCRP levels, 
the magnitude of muscle damage in soccer players </p>

<p>was reduced significantly over the observational peri-
od, as a result of adaptation and conditioning of the 
muscle through regular training and was not compro-
mised by proinflammatory changes (32). </p>

<p>It is widely accepted that acute and chronic 
exercise alters the number and function of circulating 
cells of the innate and acquired immune system (33). 
In the present study, we detected certain changes: an 
increase in leukocytes and neutrophil number, hs-
CRP, along with decrease in lymphocytes number. We 
did not find pathological trends in the studied athletes 
and the fluctuations of the number of total leukocytes 
and subpopulations seemed to be physiological. </p>

<p>Our study showed that elite soccer players are 
characterized by physiological values of the bioche m -
ical, hematological parameters and the parameters of 
iron metabolism over the half season. In spite of sig-
nificant decrease in Hb and Hct levels in soccer play-
ers over the competitive half season, erythrocyte pool 
was found to be well preserved. In addition, the 
results of our study do not imply significant hemolysis 
in soccer players. It is therefore proposed that the 
exercise induced decrease in Hb and Hct is entirely 
due to plasma volume expansion, without any contri-
bution of red blood cell loss. Also, the observed 
inflammation might contribute to plasma volume 
expansion (13). The variability of the parameters dur-
ing the half season is linked to training and competi-
tion workload, as well as the adaptation induced by 
soccer training. The follow up of the athletes by 
means of biochemical and hematological parameters 
is fundamental for sport doctors and trainers to iden-
tify a healthy status and the related optimal perform-
ances and for trainers to select a correct workload. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement. This work was financially 
supported by grants from the Ministry of Education, 
Science and Technological Development, Republic of 
Serbia (Project number III41027, III46001 and OI 
175035). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement </p>

<p>The authors stated that they have no conflicts of 
interest regarding the publication of this article. </p>



<p>Received: January 26, 2014 
Accepted: May 14, 2014 </p>

<p>466 Barali} et al.: Hematology and biochemistry in soccer </p>

</text></tei>