<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4449848" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Vancomycin-resistant enterococci (VRE) are important nosocomial pathogens and food chain has been considered as an 
assumed source for dissemination of VRE to human. </p>

<p>Objectives: The presence of VRE isolates from food samples and typing of these isolates with Phene plate, a biochemical fingerprinting 
method, were investigated. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods: Thirty samples of meat, chicken and cheese were analyzed for VRE during 2010. Antibiotic susceptibility tests 
and minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) were also examined. VRE isolates were typed with the Phene plate system (PhPlate), a 
biochemical fingerprinting method. </p>

<p>Results: A total of 70 VRE isolates were obtained and identified as Enterococcus faecium by species-specific PCR. All the isolates carried vanA, 
while none of them harbored vanB. The VRE isolates included 35, 27, and 8 isolates from meat, chicken and cheese, respectively. Typing 
with the PhPlate revealed a diversity index of 0.78 for E. faecium, containing 10 common and four single types. The results of antibiotic 
susceptibility and MIC tests showed an increased resistance to ciprofloxacin, erythromycin, ampicillin and gentamicin, to which, 100%, 
100%, 100%, and 95% of VRE isolates were resistant, respectively. Only 5% of the isolates were resistant to chloramphenicol and the MIC of 
the isolates for vancomycin and teicoplanin was ≥ 256 µg/mL and for gentamicin-resistant isolates it was 1024 µg/mL. Conventional and 
molecular identification tests exhibited that all the isolates were E. faecium carrying vanA. None of the isolates harbored vanB. </p>

<p>Conclusions: The results showed that enterococci are common contaminants in food. Indeed, this study indicates a high prevalence of 
multidrug-resistant enterococci in food of animal origin in Iran. Isolating some persisting enterococcal isolates revealed that continuous 
surveillance of antimicrobial resistance in enterococci from food is essential. </p>

<p>Keywords: Fingerprinting; Food; Minimum Inhibitory Concentration; Multidrug Resistance; Vancomycin-Resistant Enterococci </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribu-
tion-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncom-
mercial usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Enterococci are pervasive and predominant inhabitants 
of the gastrointestinal tract of humans and animals, found 
in soil, water and food (1). For many years, they were consid-
ered as normal flora and unharmful to man (2). However, 
over the last years, enterococci have emerged as major nos-
ocomial pathogens, representing an increasingly impor-
tant problem for public health (3). Indeed, these bacteria 
have a great ability to acquire resistance to some antimicro-
bial agents such as glycopeptides, in particular vancomy-
cin, which are important for human therapy (4). Although 
enterococci are normally of relatively low virulence, they 
can transfer their antimicrobial resistance genes and viru-
lence factors to other intestinal microflora and/or virulent 
bacteria, resulting in an increased pathogenicity (5). 
The climbing incidence of antibiotic resistant Entero-</p>

<p>coccus spp. is the result of increased use of antibiotics in 
human health care system and animal growth promot-</p>

<p>ers (6). The presence of large numbers of enterococci, in 
particular multidrug resistant ones, occurs commonly in 
vegetables, dairy and animal products (7). This dilemma, 
in part, is because of extensive usage of antimicrobial 
agents in modern farm industry (8). Due to limited thera-
peutic options for treating vancomycin-resistant entero-
cocci (VRE), they are considered as a major cause of con-
cern. VRE has been isolated from hospital sources, food 
animals, environment, and waste water. Previously, we in-
vestigated more about VRE from clinical samples, surface 
water and sewage treatment plants in Iran. The results of 
our prior studies showed isolation of a high number of 
VRE isolates from water and sewage (9, 10). </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>In view of the lack of information about VRE isolates in 
food samples, we studied the occurrence of VRE in meat, 
chicken and cheese which were sold in local markets. </p>

<p>Talebi M et al. </p>

<p>Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2015;8(4):e15815 
2 </p>

<p>3. Materials and Methods </p>

<p>3.1. Sample Collection and Processing </p>

<p>Thirty food samples, each 10 from chicken, meat and 
cheese were collected from Tehran local markets from 
April to September 2010. The samples were sealed in a 
plastic bag, labeled immediately and transported to a mi-
crobiology laboratory in a cold cycle. Ten grams of each 
sample were suspended in 90 mL of saline and then heav-
ily vortexed. The mixture was filtered using 0.45 µ filter 
membrane (Millipore, Sparks, MD, USA). The filters were 
then transferred to m-Enterococcus agar (Becton Dickin-
son and Co., Sparks, MD, USA) supplemented with 4 µg/ 
mL vancomycin and incubated for 48 hours at 37°C. </p>

<p>3.2. Identification of Isolates </p>

<p>Colonies suspected to be Enterococcus were subjected 
to identification tests using the following characteris-
tics: growth and hydrolysis of bile-esculin agar, growth 
in the presence of 6.5% NaCl, absence of catalase, pres-
ence of pyrrolidonyle arylamidase, 0.04% tellurite re-
duction, arabinose utilization, arginine dehydrolase 
activity, methyl-a-d-glucopyranoside acidification, and 
motility and pigmentation. Species identifications were 
confirmed by PCR using specific primers (11). </p>

<p>3.3. Antibiotic Susceptibility Tests </p>

<p>Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) for vancomy-
cin, teicoplanin and gentamicin were determined using 
the E test (Biodisk AB, Solna, Sweden). Susceptibility tests 
to ampicillin (10 µg), ciprofloxacin (5 µg), gentamicin 
(120 µg), erythromycin (15 µg), tetracycline (30 µg), chlor-
amphenicol (30 µg), linezolid (30 µg), and quinupristin/ 
dalfopristin (Q-D) (15 µg), (Mast Diagnostics Ltd., Bootle, 
Merseyside, UK) were performed by disc diffusion meth-
od according to the Clinical Laboratory Standard Insti-
tute (CLSI) guidelines (12). Enterococcus faecalis ATCC29212 
was used as control. </p>

<p>3.4. DNA Extraction and Polymerase Chain Reaction </p>

<p>All the VRE isolates were investigated for vancomy-
cin resistance genes. For DNA extraction, one isolated 
colony from each plate was transferred into 200 μL 
distilled water and boiled at 100°C for 15 minutes. The 
mixture was centrifuged and 10 μL of the supernatant 
was used as the DNA template in the PCR mix. Identi-
fication of van genotypes (vanA, vanB) for each isolate 
of VRE was performed by a separate PCR with specific 
primers as follows: vanA, 5'-CATGAATAGAATAAAAGTT-
GCAATA-3', 5'-CCCCTTTAACGCTAATACGATCAA-3'; vanB, 
5'-GTGACAAACCGGAGGCGAGGA-3', 5'-CCGCCATCCTCCT-
GCAAAAAA-3'. The PCR assay was performed in a total 
volume of 25 μL containing 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH = 8.3), 
1.5 mM MgCl 2 , 0.2 mM each dNTPs, 0.5 U TaqDNA poly-</p>

<p>merase (HT Biotechnology, Cambridge, UK), and each 
primer (40 pmol). The PCR cycle was as follows; initial 
denaturation at 94°C for five minutes, 30 cycles of dena-
turation at 94°C for one minute, annealing at 54°C for 
one minute and extension at 72°C for one minute, with 
a final extension at 72°C for 10 minutes (13). The PCR was 
performed with an Eppendorf Mastercycler (Eppendorf, 
Hauppauge, NY). </p>

<p>3.5. Typing of Vancomycin-Resistant Enterococci 
Isolates </p>

<p>All the isolated VRE were typed using a high-resolu-
tion biochemical fingerprinting method, Phene plate 
(PhPlate) system, which is specifically developed for typ-
ing of enterococci strains (The PhPlate AB, Stockholm, 
Sweden). Microplates with 11 carbohydrate substrates 
were specifically chosen to differentiate between strains 
of enterococci. Preparation and inoculation of the plates 
were according to the manufacturer instruction. Briefly, 
a loopful of a fresh bacterial culture was inoculated in 
PhPlate growth media containing 0.2% (w/v) protease 
peptone, 0.05% (w/v) yeast extract, 0.5% (w/v) NaCl and 
0.011% (w/v) bromothymol blue. The plates were then in-
cubated at 37°C and images of the plates were scanned 
after 16, 24 and 48 hours using an HP Scanjet 4890 scan-
ner. After the final scan, the PhPlate software (<rs id="software-0" type="software">PhPWin</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.2</rs>) was used to create the absorbance data (biochemi-
cal fingerprint) from the scanned images. The correla-
tion coefficient using a pair-wise comparison of the 
biochemical fingerprints and clustered was determined 
according to the unweighted pair group method (UP-
GMA) with arithmetic averages. The mean similarity 
between the compared isolated minus 2SD was taken as 
the ID-level of the system. Isolates showing similarity to 
each other above this level were considered as identical 
(Common Biochemical Phenotypes: C-BPT) (13). </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1. Vancomycin resistant Enterococci Detection 
and Identification </p>

<p>According to the biochemical tests, a total of 102 iso-
lates belonged to enterococci, 48, 40 and 14 of which 
were from meat, chicken and cheese, respectively. Anti-
biotic susceptibility test revealed that 35, 27 and 8 iso-
lates obtained from meat, chicken and cheese, respec-
tively, were vancomycin-resistant. Conventional and 
molecular identification tests exhibited that all the iso-
lates were E. faecium carrying vanA. None of the isolates 
harbored vanB. </p>

<p>4.2. Antibiotic Resistance </p>

<p>Using the method of CLSI, all the isolates were tested 
for their resistance against antimicrobial agents. All the </p>

<p>Talebi M et al. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2015;8(4):e15815 </p>

<p>VRE isolates were susceptible to linezolid, quinupristin-
dalfopristin and tetracycline. However, they showed dif-
ferent degrees of resistance to other antibiotics. All the 
VRE isolates were also resistant to ciprofloxacin, eryth-
romycin and ampicillin (100%). Almost the same antibi-
otic resistance was observed for gentamicin (95%), but 
only 5% of the isolates were resistant to chlorampheni-
col. The MIC of the isolates for vancomycin and teico-
planin was ≥ 256 µg/mL and for gentamicin-resistant 
isolates it was 1024 µg/mL. </p>

<p>4.3. Typing </p>

<p>The results of typing with PhPlate system showed a di-
versity of Di = 0.78 for the E. faecium population. A total 
of 14 types with 10 common types (C-BPT) constituting 
66 isolates and four single types (S-BPT) were seen (Fig-
ure 1). Each common type comprised 2 -31 strains. The 
VRE from the meat samples showed 11 types comprising 
35 isolates, while the chicken isolates contained only 
four types. Some of the isolates collected from differ-
ent food samples on different sampling occasions were 
found to have the same C-BPT (Table 1). </p>

<p>Table 1. Number of Vancomycin resistant Enterococci Strains 
in Each Phene Plate Type and Their Sample Types and Number of 
Sampling a </p>

<p>BPT 
Number of 
VRE Isolates 
Number of 
Sampling 
Sample Type </p>

<p>CT1 
3 
1,2 
Meat </p>

<p>CT2 
2 
1,2 
Meat </p>

<p>CT3 
4 
3,5 
Meat </p>

<p>CT4 
2 
4,6 
Meat, chicken </p>

<p>CT5 
3 
1,3 
Meat </p>

<p>CT6 
4 
1,6 
Meat </p>

<p>CT7 
2 
2,4 
Meat </p>

<p>CT8 
2 
1,7 
Meat , chicken </p>

<p>CT9 
31 
1,2,3,4,6,7,8,9,10 
Meat, chicken, 
cheese </p>

<p>CT10 
13 
2,3,4,6,7,8 
Chicken, cheese </p>

<p>ST1 
1 
3 
Meat </p>

<p>ST2 
1 
4 
Meat </p>

<p>ST3 
1 
10 
Cheese </p>

<p>ST4 
1 
7 
Cheese </p>

<p>a Abbreviations: BPT, biochemical phenotype; CT: common type; and </p>

<p>ST: single type. </p>

<p>Figure 1. A Unweighted Pair Group Method Dendrogram Showing 70 En-
terococcus faecium Strains Isolated From Different Samples </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>A high rate of vanA containing Enterococcus isolates 
was detected in food samples of chicken (9/10) and meat 
(10/10) in this study. Isolation of vanA-containing entero-
cocci strains in poultry and fresh slaughtered chicken 
samples has been reported in Germany (14). Further-
more, high-level glycopeptide-resistant VanA-type strains </p>

<p>Talebi M et al. </p>

<p>Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2015;8(4):e15815 
4 </p>

<p>from supermarket-purchased chicken were detected in 
England (15). On the other hand, absence of VRE from 
meats was reported in studies performed in the US (16, 
17) which reflected the absence of VRE isolation in animal 
food product. Elimination of VRE, in part, may have been 
resulted during the food processing. On the contrary, in 
European countries, VRE have been frequently isolated 
from meat products, which might be due to the usage of 
glycopeptides avoparcin antibiotic in food animal pro-
duction environments before banning this antibiotic 
(18, 19). In this study, we obtained similar results to the 
European countries which may indicate the presence of 
similar diets in Iran. 
Our results showed the presence of enterococci strains 
in 50% of cheese samples. In contrast, in a study by Giraffa 
and Sisto, there was no evidence of VRE in dairy products 
(20). However, some years later, Giraffa and colleagues 
in Italy found that 50% of the cheeses examined were 
contaminated by VRE (7). E. faecium was the only species 
isolated in all the samples in our study, while in most of 
the studies E. faecium and E. faecalis were simultaneously 
isolated from food samples. Klein et al. reported a total of 
34 VRE strains isolated from raw minced beef and pork 
and 38% of VRE isolates were identified as E. faecium, 35% 
were E. faecalis, and the remaining isolates were from the </p>

<p>E. faecium group (21). Moreover, similar results were de-
tected in the UK in fresh and frozen chicken, 58% and 40% 
of which were E. faecium and E. faecalis, respectively (15). 
Antibiotic susceptibility tests showed that in the pres-
ent study, the VRE isolates were resistant to at least four 
antibiotics including gentamicin, ciprofloxacin, erythro-
mycin and ampicillin. This has been confirmed by other 
studies which have found the prevalence of antibiotic-re-
sistant enterococci in farm animals and their meat to be 
higher than 60% (22, 23). These studies showed that exten-
sive agricultural use of glycopeptides or other antibiot-
ics has created animal reservoir of resistant enterococcal 
species to antibiotics which has complicated the control 
of infections caused by enterococci. Here we determined 
that resistance to gentamicin was very high among the 
animal products (95%). Using the synergism between 
aminoglycosides and B-lactams or glycopeptides elimi-
nated owing to high-level aminoglycoside resistance, 
which is of vast clinical importance (24). Peters and col-
leagues have reported a very low gentamicin resistance 
in food from animal origin in Germany (25). The differ-
ence in the reported antibiotic resistance among animal 
products could be due to geographical differences and 
the policy as well as production practices performed in 
these countries. 
All of our isolates were susceptible to tetracycline, in 
comparison with the results from Peters and colleagues 
who found a high rate of tetracycline resistance in their 
strains (25). The reason for the absence of resistance to 
tetracycline in this study may be due to the fact that tetra-
cycline is not used as a therapeutic antimicrobial in veter-
inary medicine in Iran. In consistent with another study, </p>

<p>here we reported that the prevalence of chloramphenicol 
resistance was very low among E. faecium strains (26).We 
found no resistant isolate to oxazolidinone, linezolid and 
Q-D in this study (25). Although surveillance of entero-
cocci from food sources for resistance to linezolid has not 
been reported extensively (26), there are some resistance 
reports to Q-D in the USA, given the use of the analogue 
virginiamycin since 1974 (27, 28). 
In PhPlate analysis, we found that some of the C-BPT 
were found on different sampling occasions and food 
samples (i.e. C8, C9), indicating a high prevalence of cer-
tain E. faecium C-BPT in the food. In addition, in another 
study, typing with PhPlate exhibited a high diversity in 
a large number of enterococci isolated from different 
sources including food samples (29). On the other hand, 
genotyping with Pulse-Field Gel Electrophoresis profile 
(PFGE) and Random Amplification of Polymorphic DNA 
(RAPD) PCR revealed a marked heterogeneity in food iso-
lates (30, 31). These results also showed that isolates with 
identical BPT pattern were found in different sampling 
occasions in the same food sample (i.e. isolates in C10), 
suggesting that some of the strains persisted for a period 
of time. 
In conclusion, the high prevalence of multidrug resis-
tance among enterococci isolated from food is a serious 
threat to public health. To the best of our knowledge, 
there is no use of antibiotic other than human use, in ani-
mal feeding in Iran. The data presented here, on the other 
hand, suggested the presence of antibiotic pressure in 
food animals. The level of antibiotics in animal product, 
in turn, may be due to treatment regimens used for infec-
tions in animals. Controlled use of antibiotics in animal 
husbandry is highly suggestive in Iran. </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions </p>

<p>Study concept and design: Fateh Rahimi, Mohammad 
Reza Pourshafie. Acquisition of data: Malihe Talebi, Javad 
Sadeghi, Fateh Rahimi. Analysis and interpretation of 
data: Malihe Talebi, Fateh Rahimi. Drafting of the manu-
script: Malihe Talebi, Javad Sadeghi. Critical revision of 
the manuscript for important intellectual content: Mo-
hammad Reza Pourshafie. Administrative, technical, and 
material support: Fateh Rahimi, Mohammad Reza Pour-
shafie. Study supervision: Mohammad Reza Pourshafie. </p>



</text></tei>