<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4758284" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Increasing evidence has demonstrated that the 
tumor suppressor gene Hath1 is implicated in the devel-
opment and progression of tumors and is verified to be 
downregulated in several types of tumor. However, the roles 
and precise molecular mechanisms of Hath1 in cutaneous 
squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) remain to be elucidated. In 
the present study, two approaches were used to investigate the 
tumor-suppressing effect of Hath1 in cutaneous SCC. Firstly, 
the effect of inhibiting Hath1 expression with short hairpin 
RNA (shRNA) on tumor growth and apoptosis was investi-
gated. KUMA5 cells were stably transfected with a plasmid 
expressing Hath1 shRNA (pGenesil-1-Hath1). Secondly, the 
anti-tumor effect of Hath1 was investigated in KUMA5 cells 
following transfection with pcDNA3.1-Hath1. The mRNA and 
protein expression of Hath1 was detected by reverse transcrip-
tion quantitative polymerase chain reaction and western blot 
analysis, respectively. Cell proliferation in vitro was assessed 
using an MTT assay. Flow cytometry was used to detect cell 
apoptosis. The results demonstrated that compared with the 
control groups, the expression of Hath1 was significantly 
reduced in the KUMA5/pGenesil-1-Hath1 cells and mark-
edly increased in the KUMA5/pcDNA3.1-Hath1 cells. Cell 
proliferation was markedly increased in the KUMA5/pGen-
esil-1-Hath1 cells in a time-dependent manner; however, it 
was markedly inhibited in the KUMA5/pcDNA3.1-Hath1 
cells. Flow cytometry revealed that apoptosis decreased 
in KUMA5/pGenesil-1-Hath1 cells and increased in 
KUMA5/pcDNA3.1-Hath1 cells. Downregulation of Hath1 
expression promoted the proliferation and reduced the 
apoptosis of KUMA5 cells. By contrast, overexpression of 
Hath1 inhibited proliferation and induced the apoptosis of </p>

<p>KUMA5 cells. These findings provide possible new strate-
gies and therapeutic targets for the treatment and diagnosis 
of cutaneous SCC. </p>

<p>Non-melanoma skin carcinoma is one of the most frequent 
types of tumor worldwide and includes two histological 
types: Basal cell carcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma 
(SCC) (1-3). Cutaneous SCC is the second most common 
cutaneous carcinoma and accounts for 20% of all types of 
cutaneous tumor (4-6). Previous studies have made significant 
progress in understanding the mechanisms underlying the 
tumorigenesis and development of cutaneous SCC (7-12). 
However, the incidence rates of patients with cutaneous SCC 
have been increasing rapidly each year, due to the lack of 
molecular targeted therapies and reliable molecular markers 
in early diagnosis. Therefore, novel molecular biomarkers and 
targeted therapeutic approaches for the diagnosis and treat-
ment of patients with cutaneous SCC are urgently required. 
Hath1, also termed Math1, Atoh1 and Cath1 in 
mouse, drosophila and chicken, respectively, is a basic 
helix-loop-helix (bHLH) transcription factor (13). Hath1 
was initially identified as a tumor suppressor gene in colon 
cancer (14). However, increasing evidence has revealed that 
Hath1 is not only a tumor suppressor in colon cancer (14-24), 
but is also downregulated and involved in the tumorigenesis 
of various other types of human cancer, including medul-
loblastoma (25,26), gastric carcinoma (27,28), intestinal 
neuroendocrine tumors (29), lung cancer (30,31) and Merkel 
cell carcinoma (32). Inherited or acquired defective mutants 
of Atoh were initially identified in patients with Merkel cell 
carcinoma by Leonard in 2002 (32). Deletion of Hath1 using 
retrovirus vectors led to the disruption of Sonic hedgehog 
signaling in the developing cerebellum and finally resulted 
in medulloblastoma formation (26). Bossuyt et al confirmed 
that the incidence of colonic polyps in mice lacking the 
Hath1 gene was 100% compared with that in wild type 
mice (16). Zhu et al found that Hath1 expression is down-
regulated in non-mucinous adenocarcinomas (19-21) and 
that Hath1 inhibits the proliferation of colon cancer cells 
possibly through upregulating the expression of Muc2 and 
p27 and downregulating the expression of cyclin D1 (24). 
Collectively, these studies highlight the important role of </p>

<p>Effect of Hath1 on the proliferation and apoptosis 
of cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma in vitro </p>

<p>ZUOLIN YING </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>, XIAOJIE LI 
1 , HONG DANG 
1 , FENG WANG 
2 and XIAOYAN XU </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Dermatology; 
2 Experimental Research Center, </p>

<p>Shanghai First People's Hospital Affiliated to Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, Shanghai 200080, P.R. China </p>

<p>Received August 19, 2014; Accepted April 22, 2015 </p>

<p>DOI: 10.3892/mmr.2015.4463 </p>

<p>Correspondence to: Dr Zuolin Ying, Department of Dermatology, </p>

<p>Shanghai First People's Hospital Affiliated to Shanghai Jiao Tong 
University School of Medicine, 100 Haining Road, Shanghai 200080, 
P.R. China 
E-mail: yingzuolin501@sina.com </p>

<p>Key words: Hath1, shRNA, overexpression, KUMA5 cell, </p>

<p>proliferation, apoptosis </p>

<p>YING et al: ANTI-TUMOR EFFECTS OF HATH1 IN CUTANEOUS SQUAMOUS CELL CARCINOMA </p>



<p>Hath1 as a tumor suppressor gene in these types of tumor and 
further investigation of the functions of Hath1 may provide 
potential molecular targets for the treatment of these tumors. 
However, to the best of our knowledge, no studies on the 
biological role of Hath1 in cutaneous SCC have been reported 
to date. Therefore, the current study predominantly focused on 
the biological function of the Hath1 gene. In order to examine 
the effects of the Hath1 gene on the growth, proliferation and 
apoptosis of cutaneous SCC, Hath1 was alternately silenced 
with short hairpin RNA (shRNA), or overexpressed using a 
recombinant eukaryotic expression vector carrying the Hath1 
gene. KUMA5 human cutaneous squamous carcinoma cells 
were infected with pcDNA3.1-Hath1 or pGenesil-1-Hath1. 
Subsequently, cell proliferation and apoptosis were examined 
by MTT assay and flow cytometry to provide further insight 
into the potential use of Hath1 for the targeted therapy of 
cutaneous SCC. Collectively, these data suggest that Hath1 
may be a novel molecular target for the treatment of cuta-
neous SCC. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Construction of the pcDNA3.1-Hath1 vector. The present 
study was approved by an ethical review committee of the 
Shanghai First People's Hospital (Shanghai, China), and 
written informed consent was obtained from all participants 
at the Shanghai First People's Hospital Affiliated to Shanghai 
Jiao Tong University School of Medicine (Shanghai, China). 
Total RNA was extracted from normal human cutaneous 
tissue using 1 ml of TRIzol reagent (cat. no. 15596-018; 
Invitrogen Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according 
to the manufacturer's instructions. cDNA was then synthe-
sized using an ABI TaqMan one-step RT-PCR Master 
Mix Reagents kit (cat. no. 4309109; Applied Biosystems, 
Foster City, CA, USA). Based on the GenBank sequence 
(NC_000004.12), upstream and downstream primers were 
synthesized for Hath1 gene amplification. The restriction 
enzyme sites for BamHI and HindIII were added to the 5' end 
of each primer. Subsequently, the full-length Hath1 gene was 
amplified by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) 
from the cDNA template with the primers containing the 
BamHI and HindIII restriction sites. The PCR product was 
then ligated into the pMD18-T vector (cat. no. 6011; Takara 
Bio., Inc., Dalian, China), transformed and screened for 
positive clones. Following sequence verification, the correct 
sequence was cloned into the pcDNA3.1 expression vector 
(cat. no. V790-20; Invitrogen Life Technologies) to construct 
the pcDNA3.1-Hath1 recombinant expression vector. The 
Hath1 primer was synthesized by Sangon Biotech (Shanghai) 
Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). </p>

<p>shRNA design and expression plasmid vector construction. 
The following sequence was used to design the shRNA: 
Hath1, AAACGACAAGAAGCTGTCCAAATAGTGAA 
GCCACAGATGTATTTGGACAGCTTCTTGTCGTTG. The 
DNA sequence targeting the Hath1 gene was cloned into the 
pGenesil-1 (cat. no. VRG0358; Wuhan Genesil Biotechnology 
Co., Ltd., Wuhan, China), a vector expressing shRNA and 
enhanced green fluorescent protein in mammalian cells. 
Recombinant plasmid pGenesil-1-Hath1 and pGenesil-1 </p>

<p>scramble control were constructed and verified by Wuhan 
Genesil Biotechnology Co., Ltd. </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection. The KUMA5 human cuta-
neous squamous carcinoma cell line was purchased from the 
Cell Bank of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, 
China) and cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium 
(DMEM)/F12 medium (Gibco-BRL, Carlsbad, CA, USA: 
nutrient mixture F12; cat. no. 11039-021) supplemented with 
10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco-BRL; cat. no. 12483-020) in 
a humidified incubator containing 5% CO 2 at 37˚C. When 
cultured to exponential phase, KUMA5 cells were replated at 
5x10 
4 cells/well in six-well plates. Transient transfection was 
performed using Lipofectamine 2000 transfection reagent (cat. 
no. 11668-019; Invitrogen Life Technologies) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. Screening of stably transfected 
cells was performed as follows: The cells were transfected with 
either the pcDNA3.1-Hath1 or pGenesil-1-Hath1 eukaryotic 
expression vectors and then cultured in DMEM/F12 containing 
800 µg/ml G418 (cat. no. sc-29065; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, 
Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA) for 2 weeks. Positive clones were 
screened and verified by reverse transcription (RT)-qPCR and 
western blot analysis. </p>

<p>RNA isolation, RT-qPCR and western blot analysis. mRNA 
transcript expression was quantified via RT-qPCR and 
normalized to the expression of β-actin. Total RNA from 
the KUMA5 cells that had been transfected with either the 
pcDNA3.1-Hath1, pGenesil-1-Hath1, pGenesil-1 scramble 
control or blank control was isolated using TRIzol reagent 
according to the manufacturer's instructions and the quality 
of the RNA was confirmed (i.e., A 260 /A 280 &gt;1.8). qPCR 
was performed using an ABI 7900HT Fast Real-Time 
PCR System (cat. no. 4329003; Applied Biosystems). 
Detailed sequences of the primers are as follows: β-actin, 
forward 5'-ATGATATCGCCGCGCTCGTCGTC-3' and 
reverse 5'-CGCTCGGCCGTGGTGGTGAA-3'; Hath1, 
forward 5'-CGCCGCCCAGTATTTGCTA-3' and reverse 
5'-ATTCACCTGTTTGCTGGAAGG-3'. Total protein 
from cell lines was extracted using the ReadyPrep Protein 
Extraction kit (cat. no. 163-2087; Bio-Rad Laboratories, 
Hercules, CA, USA). The protein concentration was deter-
mined using a BCA Protein Assay kit (cat. no. 23227; Pierce 
Biotechnology, Inc., Rockford, IL, USA). Protein lysates 
were loaded onto a 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacryl-
amide gel. Separated protein bands were electrotransferred 
onto polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membranes. The PVDF 
membranes were then blocked in Tris-buffered saline (TBS; 
10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5 and 150 mM NaCl) containing 5% 
non-fat dry milk at room temperature for 1 h and incubated at 
4˚C overnight with anti-Hath1 monoclonal antibody (1:400; 
cat. no. sc-136173; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) and 
anti-β-actin monoclonal antibody (1:1,000; cat. no. sc-47778; 
Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.). Following primary anti-
body incubation, the membranes were washed in TBS with 
Tween 20 (10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl and 
0.05% Tween-20) and a rabbit anti-mouse IgG-horseradish 
peroxidase antibody (1:2,000; cat. no. sc-358920; Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) was added. The membrane was 
then incubated at 37˚C for 2 h. ECL Plus Western Blotting </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 12: 7845-7850, 2015 </p>



<p>Substrate (cat. no. 32132; Pierce Biotechnology, Inc.) was 
used to visualize the immunoreactive bands. Relative protein 
level was normalized to β-actin concentration. Three separate 
experiments were performed in duplicate for each treatment. </p>

<p>Examination of cell viability. Cell viability was determined 
using an MTT assay (cat. no. M2128; Sigma-Aldrich, 
St. Louis, MO, USA). Cells were cultured in 24-well plates 
at a concentration of 5x10 
4 and allowed to adhere. Following 
treatment for different time intervals, 100 µl MTT (0.5 mg/ml) 
was added into the cells and the mixture was incubated for 
4 h at 37˚C. Subsequently, the supernatant was removed and 
dimethyl sulfoxide (cat. no. D2650; Sigma-Aldrich) was used 
to dissolve the resultant formazan crystals. The absorbance 
was read at 570 nm (EL309 Automated Microplate Reader; 
Bio-Tek Instruments, lnc., Winooski, VT, USA). Six wells were 
measured for each group and the experiment was repeated 
three times. </p>

<p>Flow cytometric analysis of cell apoptosis. To detect cell 
apoptosis, the proliferating phase KUMA5 cells (5x10 
4 clones) 
were trypsinized, washed with cold phosphate-buffered 
saline and resuspended in binding buffer according to the 
manufacturer's instructions of the Annexin V-fluorescein 
isothiocyanate (FITC)/propidium iodide (PI) Apoptosis 
Detection kit (cat. no. KGA106; Nanjing KeyGen Biotech Co., 
Ltd., Nanjing, China). FITC-Annexin V and PI were added to 
the fixed cells for 20 min in darkness at room temperature. 
Subsequently, Annexin V binding buffer was added to the 
mixture prior to measuring fluorescence using a FACSort flow 
cytometer (BD Biosciences, Mountain View, CA, USA). Cell 
apoptosis was analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Cell Quest</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Becton Dickinson</rs>, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) 
was used for data analysis. All experiments were repeated 
three times and data are presented as the mean ± standard 
deviation. Differences between groups were analyzed using 
one-way analysis of variance. P&lt;0.05 was considered to indi-
cate a statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Expression of Hath1 in KUMA5 cells. Total cellular RNA 
and protein were extracted from KUMA5 cells that had been 
transfected with the pcDNA3.1-Hath1, pGenesil-1-Hath1, 
pGenesil-1 scramble control or a blank control. RT-qPCR 
and western blot analysis were performed to determine the 
mRNA and protein expression of Hath1, respectively. The 
results demonstrated that the expression of Hath1 in KUMA5 
cells transfected with pcDNA3.1-Hath1 was nearly four times 
higher than in the control groups (Fig. 1). The efficiency of 
gene silencing through pGenesil-1-Hath1 transfection was 
78% (Fig. 1). 
The protein expression of Hath1 was high in the 
pcDNA3.1-Hath1-transfected group, low in the control group, 
and barely detectable in the pGenesil-1-Hath1-transfected 
group (Fig. 2). Therefore, it was concluded that KUMA5 
strains with stable overexpression or depletion of the Hath1 
gene had been successfully created. </p>

<p>Effect of Hath1 on KUMA5 cell proliferation. It was hypoth-
esized that cell proliferation may be affected by the level of 
Hath1 in cutaneous SCC cells. To examine the effect of Hath1 
on cell proliferation, an equal number of KUMA5 cells trans-
fected with either the pcDNA3.1-Hath1, pGenesil-1-Hath1, 
pGenesil-1 scramble control or a blank control were seeded 
and analyzed using an MTT assay. The present study found 
that Hath1 overexpression attenuated the proliferation of 
KUMA5 cells and Hath1 gene RNA interference enhanced the 
proliferation of KUMA5 cells (Fig. 3). Taken together, Hath1 
clearly inhibited the proliferation and growth of SCC cells, 
indicating that Hath1 may act as a potential tumor suppressor 
in cutaneous SCC and that Hath1 may represent a novel target 
for the treatment of SCC. </p>

<p>Effect of Hath1 on the apoptosis of KUMA5 cells. To further 
confirm the inhibitory effect of Hath1 on KUMA5 cells, the 
rate of apoptosis was examined by Annexin V and PI staining 
of KUMA5 cells transfected with the pcDNA3.1-Hath1, 
pGenesil-1-Hath1, pGenesil-1 scramble control or a blank 
control. FITC-Annexin V and PI were added to the fixed cells 
for 20 min in darkness at room temperature. Subsequently, 
Annexin V binding buffer was added to the mixture prior to 
measuring the fluorescence using a FACSort flow cytometer 
(BD Biosciences). Cell apoptosis was analyzed using Cell </p>

<p>Figure 1. Relative mRNA expression of Hath1 in KUMA5 cells. Control, 
blank control group (Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium/F12); GFP, pGen-
esil-1 scramble control group; Hath1, pcDNA3.1-Hath1-transfected group; 
shRNA, pGenesil-1-Hath1-transfected group. GFP, green fluorescent protein; 
shRNA, short hairpin RNA. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Relative protein expression of Hath1 in KUMA5 cells. Control, 
blank control group (Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium/F12); GFP, pGen-
esil-1 scramble control group; Hath1, pcDNA3.1-Hath1-transfected group; 
shRNA, pGenesil-1-Hath1-transfected group. GFP, green fluorescent protein; 
shRNA, short hairpin RNA. </p>

<p>YING et al: ANTI-TUMOR EFFECTS OF HATH1 IN CUTANEOUS SQUAMOUS CELL CARCINOMA </p>



<p>Quest 3.0 software (Becton Dickinson). The results demon-
strated that a significantly higher rate of apoptosis was present 
in the KUMA5 cells overexpressing Hath1 compared with </p>

<p>that of the control groups (Fig. 4). In addition, a significantly 
lower rate of apoptosis was observed in the KUMA5 cells 
transfected with pGenesil-1-Hath1 compared with that of the 
control groups (Fig. 4). Therefore, these results suggest that 
overexpression of Hath1 may promote apoptosis in KUMA5 
cells. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Hath1, located on the chromosomal region 4q22, is the 
mammalian homologue of Drosophila atonal, a bHLH 
transcription factor. It is known to be important in the 
differentiation of various cells, including cerebellar granule 
cells (33), inner hair cells in the auditory system (34), 
epidermal Merkel cells (32), intestinal secretory cells (35,36) 
and hindbrain neurons (37). Previous studies have demon-
strated that Hath1 acts as a tumor suppressor gene in various 
types of cancer, including colon cancer (14-24), medul-
loblastoma (25,26), gastric carcinoma (27,28), intestinal 
neuroendocrine tumors (29), lung cancer (30,31) and Merkel 
cell carcinoma (32). 
However, to date, no studies on the biological role of Hath1 
in cutaneous SCC have been reported. The present study 
demonstrated for the first time, to the best of our knowledge, 
the anti-proliferative and pro-apoptotic activity of Hath1 
in cutaneous SCC, using a variety of techniques, including 
overexpression of Hath1 and shRNA-mediated Hath1 
silencing. As shown in Figs. 1 and 2, Hath1 was successfully 
silenced or overexpressed. The expression level of Hath1 
in pGenesil-1-Hath1-transfected cells was significantly 
decreased to 22% of the normal levels (P&lt;0.05). Cells trans-
fected with pcDNA3.1-Hath1 had significantly higher levels of 
Hath1 expression, which was ~3.9 times higher than the control 
groups (P&lt;0.05). MTT assays demonstrated that the prolif-
eration of KUMA5/pGenesil-1-Hath1-transfected cells was 
promoted in a time-dependent manner, however, proliferation 
was inhibited in KUMA5/pcDNA3.1-Hath1-infected cells. 
Furthermore, the apoptotic rate of the pGenesil-1-Hath1-trans-
fected group significantly decreased. By contrast, the 
apoptotic rate of the KUMA5/pcDNA3.1-Hath1-infected 
group significantly increased. These experimental results 
demonstrated that overexpression of Hath1 could repress 
the proliferation of KUMA5 cells and promote apoptosis. 
However, shRNA-mediated Hath1 silencing enhanced the 
growth of KUMA5 cells and inhibited the apoptosis of 
KUMA5 cells. 
The expression level of the Hath1 gene was frequently 
found to significantly affect cell proliferation and apop-
tosis (14,16,20-22,24). Zhu et al (20,21,24) and Leow et al (14) 
identified that overexpression of Hath1 inhibits proliferation of 
HT29 colon cancer cells through downregulation of cyclin D1 
and upregulation of p27 and MUC2, a goblet cell differ-
entiation marker. In a previous study, knockout of Hath1 
was demonstrated to promote tumorigenesis in colorectal 
mouse models with intestine-specific deletion of Hath1 (18). 
The anti-tumor effects of Hath1, including the inhibition of 
colon cancer cell proliferation and enhancement of apoptosis 
in vitro and in vivo, may be achieved by activation of the 
Jun N-terminal kinase signaling pathway (16). According to 
Zhao et al (22), Hath1 can effectively inhibit the proliferation </p>

<p>Figure 4. Effect of Hath1 on the apoptosis of KUMA5 cells. Control, blank 
control group (Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium/F12); GFP, pGenesil-1 
scramble control group; Hath1, pcDNA3.1-Hath1-transfected group; shRNA, 
pGenesil-1-Hath1-transfected group. GFP, green fluorescent protein; FITC, 
fluorescein isothiocyanate; shRNA, short hairpin RNA. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effect of Hath1 on KUMA5 cell growth. Control, blank control 
group (Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium/F12); GFP, pGenesil-1 scramble 
control group; Hath1, pcDNA3.1-Hath1-transfected group; shRNA, pGen-
esil-1-Hath1-transfected group. GFP, green fluorescent protein; shRNA, short 
hairpin RNA. </p>

<p>MOLECULAR MEDICINE REPORTS 12: 7845-7850, 2015 </p>



<p>of four colon cancer cell lines, namely HT-29, LS17T, SW480 
and SW620 with weak or absent expression of Hath1. In addi-
tion, the inhibition of cell proliferation by Hath1 was inversely 
proportional to the expression of Hath1 in these four colon 
cancer cell lines. However, instead of inducing apoptosis, an 
increase in tumor cell sensitivity to the chemotherapeutic 
drug 5-fluorouracil was observed in one of the four colon 
cancer cell lines. By contrast, shRNA-mediated Hath1 gene 
silencing using retroviral vectors could significantly accel-
erate the growth rate of the normal rat intestinal epithelial 
cell line IEC6 with suppressed growth by high expression of 
the Hath1 gene, which also confirmed the tumor suppressor 
activity of Hath1 (22). A previous study (38) demonstrated that 
retroviral-mediated Hath1 expression can significantly reduce 
human esophageal keratinocyte cell proliferation and induce 
marked expression of Barrett's esophagus markers Mucin-2 
and Keratin-20. The results of the present study, which build on 
earlier studies (14,16,20-22,24), confirm the anti-proliferative 
and pro-apoptotic activities of Hath1. 
In conclusion, the present results verify the anti-tumor 
effects of Hath1 on the proliferation and apoptosis of cuta-
neous SCC. Hath1 may be a potential therapeutic target for the 
inhibition of growth and progression of cutaneous SCC. These 
studies provide insights into the tumorigenesis and develop-
ment of cutaneous SCC and provide new strategies and targets 
for the treatment of cutaneous SCC. However, further studies 
are required to clarify the associated molecular mechanisms 
and signal transduction of Hath1. </p>



<p>YING et al: ANTI-TUMOR EFFECTS OF HATH1 IN CUTANEOUS SQUAMOUS CELL CARCINOMA </p>





</text></tei>