<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4505995" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: The survival rates of preterm infants has increased over the last years, but oral feeding difficulties are the most common 
problems encountered by them 
Objectives: This study aimed at comparing the effects of non-nutritive sucking (NNS) and pre-feeding oral stimulation on feeding 
skills, length of hospital stay and weight gain of 26-32 weeks gestational age preterm infants in NICU, to determine the more effective 
intervention. 
Patients and Methods: Thirty-two preterm infants were assigned randomly into three groups. One intervention group received pre-
feeding oral stimulation program and the other received non-nutritive sucking stimulation, while the control group received a sham 
intervention. Gestational age of infants was calculated during 1, 4 and 8 oral feeding and discharge time from NICU. The infants' weights 
were measured weekly from birth and at discharge time. 
Results: Mean gestational age on 8 time oral feeding per day, in 3 groups was not significant (P = 0.282). Although NNS and pre-feeding 
oral stimulation groups has fulfilled this criterion 7.55 and 6.07 days sooner than the control group, respectively (a result which is of great 
clinical and economic importance), but the difference did not reach statistical significance. Weight gaining at discharge time in NNS 
group was significantly higher than control and pre-feeding oral stimulation groups (P &lt; 0.05). 
Conclusions: This study revealed that pre-feeding oral stimulation and NNS programs both were effective on oral feeding skills and 
weight gaining of the immature newborns. Yet, it seems that NNS program was more effective than pre-feeding oral stimulation on weight 
gaining. </p>

<p>Keywords: Infant, Premature; Length of Stay; Weights </p>

<p>Copyright © 2015, Growth &amp; Development Research Center. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-
Commercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial 
usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>The survival rates of preterm infants has increased over 
the last years (1-5), but oral feeding difficulties are the most 
common problems encountered by them (4, 6). These dif-
ficulties may negatively affect attainment of indepen-
dent oral feeding and lead to prolonged hospital stay, 
family stress, long-term health problems and financial 
costs (7, 8). Caregivers and speech language pathologists 
that work in the NICUs may use various oral stimulation 
techniques to facilitate oral feeding of preterm infants (9). 
NNS and pre-feeding oral stimulation are among the most 
common stimulation techniques in use. These interven-
tions have been proved to be beneficial for oral feeding 
skills, attainment of full oral feeding, weight gaining and 
reducing the length of hospital stay (10, 11). Due to a lack of 
empirical evidence, caregivers in NICU, while aware of the 
feeding difficulties of these infants, are confused about 
the kind of intervention which is more effective. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>The aim of this study was to compare the effects of NNS 
and pre-feeding oral stimulation program on feeding 
performance, length of hospital stays, weight gaining. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>According formula, Thirty-two preterm infants (16 
males and 16 females) from NICU at Kamali Hospital 
(Karaj, IR Iran) participated in the study. In this interven-
tional research with convenience sampling, a random as-
signment was performed using a simple randomization 
method. The following inclusion criteria were consid-
ered: preterm infants from 26 to 32 weeks of gestational 
age that fed through a tube and their birth weight were 
1000 to 2000 grams. Gestational age is the common term 
used from the first day of the woman's last menstrual cy-
cle to the current date. Infants were excluded if they had 
congenital anomalies, chronic medical complications, </p>

<p>Asadollahpour F et al. </p>

<p>Iran J Pediatr. 2015;25(3):e809 </p>

<p>
asphyxia, third or fourth degree intracranial hemorrhag-
es, necrotizing enterocolitis, metabolic disorders, genet-
ic syndromes, oral-motor defects, neurological disorders, 
umbilical catheter, medication (aminophylin, analgesic), 
intra uterine growth pattern documented by a neona-
tologist. The study was performed between January and 
June 2012. The study was approved by the Institutional 
Review Board for Human Subjects Research of University 
of Social Welfare and Rehabilitation Sciences. Informed 
consent was obtained from parents before their infants 
entered into the study. </p>

<p>3.1. Procedure </p>

<p>The infants were randomly using a simple randomiza-
tion assigned into NNS (n = 11), pre-feeding oral stimu-
lation (n = 10) and control (n = 11) group. The NNS pro-
gram consisted of thrice daily stroking of the palate for 
5 minutes to elicit a suck. This intervention delivered 
by one speech therapist who was blinding to research 
and was performed through introduction of the little 
finger in infant's oral cavity to gently stroke the palate 
to elicit a suck. NNS stimuli were started during initial 
5 minutes of tube feeding and were administered for 10 
consecutive days. Details of the program can be found 
in Harding et al. study (12). Pre-feeding oral stimulation 
was performed by the same speech therapist. The oral 
stimulation program consisted of once daily stroking of 
cheeks, gums and tongue and followed by 3 minutes of 
non-nutritive sucking for 15 minutes. The exact stimu-
lation program can be found in Fucile et al. study (13). 
The control group received sham intervention. For this 
group, the same speech therapist placing her hands in 
the incubator without touching the infant for 15 min-
utes and 10 consecutive days. Therefore, all infants re-
ceived the same duration for each intervention and all 
interventions were delivered by one person. </p>

<p>3.2. Outcomes </p>

<p>The primary outcome of study was the time needed to 
attainment of independent oral feeding. Independent 
oral feeding was defined as introduction to 8 successful 
oral feeding per day for 48 hours. Furthermore, gestation-
al age of infants was calculated during 1, 4 and 8 oral feed-</p>

<p>ing per day (Feeding parameters of infants). The second-
ary outcome was length of hospital stay that was defined 
as date that infant born to date of discharge from the 
hospital. Weight gaining was another outcome that was 
measured by recording the weight every day by a nurse in 
NICU by using a digital balance at 8 am (A digital scale sen-
sitive to 1 g (seca 334, Mobile digital baby scale, CE 0123). 
Introduction of oral feeding occurred according unit's 
routine when the preterm infants were clinically stable. </p>

<p>3.3. Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs><rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">16.0</rs> 
statistical software. Kolmogorov-Smirnov test revealed 
continuous variables to be normal, so parametric tests 
were used. An ANOVA was performed followed by Schef-
fé's method to compare 3 groups (NNS, pre-feeding oral 
stimulation and control group) for the gestational age 
at different stage of oral feeding. Repeated measures 
ANOVA were performed to analyze intra-group changes. 
A MANOVA was performed to compare the weight gains 
from birth through weeks between three groups. Statisti-
cal significance was considered at α = 0.05. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>There was no significant difference in regard to gesta-
tional age, birth weight, gender distribution and Apgar 
score between 3 groups (Table 1) in pre-test stage. While 
the gestational age of independent oral feeding in both 
intervention groups was lower than control group (Fig-
ure 1), the analyzes revealed no significant difference in 
the gestational age between three groups (P &gt; 0.05). Also 
weight of the groups obtained through time (Figure 2). 
The average days of life for independent oral feeding in 
NNS and pre-feeding oral stimulation were 16.72 ± 8.94 
and 18.20 ± 9.18 day respectively, while the control group 
was 24.27 ± 9.42 day. Although the NNS and pre-feeding 
stimulation groups reached 7.55 and 6.07 days sooner 
to independent oral feeding than in the control group, 
but the difference did not reach statistical significance. 
Preterm infants in the intervention (NNS and pre-feeding 
oral stimulation) and control groups did not differ statis-
tically in regard to attainment of 1, 4, and 8 oral feeding 
per day (P &gt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic Features of Preterm Infants a </p>

<p>NNS 
Pre-Feeding Oral Stimulation 
Control 
P Value </p>

<p>Gestational age at birth, week 
30.18 ± 1.77 
30.01 ± 1.76 
30.29 ± 1.95 
0.844 </p>

<p>Birth weight, gr 
1406.36 
1343.01 
1393.63 
0.58 </p>

<p>Gender distribution 
0.913 </p>

<p>Male 
6 
5 
5 </p>

<p>Female 
5 
5 
6 </p>

<p>Apgar score 5 min 
7.85 ± 2.17 
7.55 ± 1.997 
7.78 ± 2.24 
0.58 </p>

<p>a Abbreviation: NNS, non-nutritive sucking. </p>

<p>Asadollahpour F et al. </p>



<p>Iran J Pediatr. 2015;25(3):e809 </p>

<p>35 
34 
33 
32 
31 
30 
29 
28 
27 </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Prefeeding oral 
sttimulation </p>

<p>NNS </p>

<p>b i r t h </p>

<p>1 o r a l f e e d i n g 
2 o r a l f e e d i n g 
3 o r a l f e e d i n g 
4 
o r a l f e e d i n g 
6 
o r a l f e e d i n g 
8 o r a l f e e d i n g </p>

<p>d i s c h a g e </p>

<p>Figure 1. Gestational Age of the Groups Regarding Feeding Performance </p>

<p>Control </p>

<p>Prefeeding oral 
sttimulation </p>

<p>NNS </p>

<p>1800 
1600 
1400 
1200 
1000 
800 
600 
400 
200 
0 </p>

<p>w 
e i g h t a t b i r t h 
w 
e i g h t a t 1 s t w </p>

<p>e e k </p>

<p>w 
e i g h t a t 2 s t w </p>

<p>e e k </p>

<p>w 
e i g h t a t 3 s t w </p>

<p>e e k </p>

<p>w 
e i g h t a t 4 s t w </p>

<p>e e k </p>

<p>w 
e i g h t a t d i s c h a r g e </p>

<p>Figure 2. Weight Gaining of the Groups Through Time </p>

<p>Also no significance difference were found in the length 
of hospital stay between the three groups (P &gt; 0.05), but 
the average length of hospital stay in the control group 
was higher than in the intervention groups ( 26.54 ± 12.48 
days for NNS group; 27.60 ± 12.57 days for pre-feeding 
oral stimulation group; and 33.45 ± 13.46 days for control 
group). In relation to the weight at discharge, ANOVA 
revealed a significant difference between three groups 
(F = 5.956, df = 29, P = 0.007) (Table 2). Scheffes method 
showed that the difference was related to means of NNS 
and control group. 
Using a repeated measures ANOVA with a Greenhouse-
Geisser correction, the mean scores for weight changes 
in NNS group were statistically significantly different (F 
(1.984, 7.934) = 28.086, P &lt; 0.0005). The results of the Bon-
ferroni post hoc test revealed that the difference between 
the times 1 and 6 (1182 ± 50.73 gr. Vs 1556 ± 24.00 gr.), 2 and 
3 (1162 ± 50.23 gr. Vs 1261 ± 52.78 gr.), 2 and 4 (1162 ± 50.23 gr. 
Vs 1334 ± 46.00 gr.), 2 and 5 (1162 ± 50.23 gr. Vs 1424 ± 37.36 
gr.), 2 and 6 (1162 ± 50.23 gr. Vs 1556 ± 24.00 gr.) were sig-
nificantly different (P &lt; 0.05) (Figure 3). For pre-feeding 
oral stimulation group a repeated measures ANOVA with 
a Greenhouse-Geisser correction, revealed that the mean 
scores for weight changes were statistically significantly </p>

<p>Estimated Marginal Means of Weight </p>

<p>Time </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
Estimated Marginal Means </p>

<p>1.600 </p>

<p>1.500 </p>

<p>1.400 </p>

<p>1.300 </p>

<p>1.200 </p>

<p>1.100 </p>

<p>Figure 3. The Weight Changes Over Time for NNS Group </p>

<p>Estimated Marginal Means of Weight </p>

<p>Time 
Estimated Marginal Means </p>

<p>1.600 </p>

<p>1.500 </p>

<p>1.400 </p>

<p>1.300 </p>

<p>1.200 </p>

<p>1.100 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>Figure 4. The Weight Changes Over Time for Pre-Feeding Oral Stimulation Group </p>

<p>different (F (1.321, 6.604) = 22.568, P &lt; 0.001). The results of 
the Bonferroni post hoc test revealed that the difference 
between the times 2 and 3 (1153 ± 34.22 gr. Vs 1233 ± 37.47 
gr.), 2 and 4 (1153 ± 34.22 gr. Vs 1312 ± 45.12 gr.), 2 and 5 (1153 
± 34.22 gr. Vs 1415 ± 50.38 gr.), 2 and 6 (1153 ± 34.22 gr. Vs 
1503 ± 45.94 gr.), 3 and 5 (1233 ± 37.47 gr. Vs 1415 ± 50.38 gr.), 
3 and 6 (1233 ± 37.47 gr. Vs1503 ± 45.94 gr.), 4 and 6 (1312 ± 
45.12 gr. Vs1503 ± 45.94 gr.) were significantly different (P 
&lt; 0.05) (Figure 4). 
A repeated measures ANOVA with a Greenhouse-Geiss-
er correction, showed that the mean scores for weight 
changes in control group were statistically significantly 
different (F (2.488, 14.927) = 26.021, P &lt; 0.0005). The re-
sults of the Bonferroni post hoc test revealed that the dif-
ference between the times 1 and 6 (1193 ± 45.55 gr. Vs 1453 
± 28.59 gr.), 2 and 5 (1054 ± 23.38 gr. Vs 1240 ± 39.03 gr.), 2 
and 6 (1054 ± 23.38 gr. Vs 1453 ± 28.59 gr.), 3 and 6 (1117 ± 
25.51 gr. Vs 1453 ± 28.59 gr.), 4 and 5 (1153 ± 29.09 gr. Vs 1240 
± 39.03 gr.), 4 and 6 (1153 ± 29.09 gr.Vs1453 ± 28.59 gr.) were 
significantly different (P &lt; 0.05) (Figure 5). 
The MANOVA test revealed no significant difference 
in weekly weight gain between three groups (F (12, 20) 
= 0.904, P &gt; 0.05; Wilk's lambda = 0.420, partial Eta 
squared = 0.325). </p>

<p>Asadollahpour F et al. </p>

<p>Iran J Pediatr. 2015;25(3):e809 </p>

<p>
Table 2. ANOVA results Between Groups for Weight Discharge a </p>

<p>NNS 
Pre-Feeding Oral Stimulation 
Control 
P Value </p>

<p>Body Weight at discharge, gr 
1654.54 ± 133.29 
1553.01 ± 140. 55 
1472.72 ± 94.34 
0.007* </p>

<p>a Abbreviation: NNS, non-nutritive sucking. </p>

<p>Estimated Marginal Means of Weight </p>

<p>Time 
Estimated Marginal Means </p>

<p>1.500 </p>

<p>1.400 </p>

<p>1.300 </p>

<p>1.200 </p>

<p>1.100 </p>

<p>1.000 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Estimated Marginal Means of Weight </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>NNS and pre-feeding oral stimulation strategies are 
widely used to accelerate the independent oral feeding of 
preterm infants. However, which the intervention is most 
effective, is not yet understood. This study continued to 
confirm the benefits of oral stimuli techniques applied to 
preterm infants and to determine which of them is most 
effective. The results of our study indicated that the NNS 
and pre-feeding oral stimulation program had a benefi-
cial effect on the time needed to attainment to different 
stage of oral feeding and independent oral feeding. The 
preterm infants in NNS and pre-feeding oral stimulation 
groups reached 7.55 and 6.07 days sooner than control 
group to these criteria. Therefore in term of performance 
in oral feeding, NNS program seemed to be more benefi-
cial than pre-feeding oral stimulation and pre-feeding 
oral stimulation was more fruitful than shame interven-
tion. Although statistically not significant, our results 
were similar to Lessen et al. (14), Fucile et al. (13), Rocha et  al. (15), who confirmed the beneficial effects of two inter-
ventions in attainment to oral feeding (a result which is 
of great clinical and economic importance). Also several 
studies did not find any improvement in independent 
oral feeding (10, 16). These differences may result from dif-
ferent administrations of stimulation protocol or small 
sample size that affected the achievement of statistical 
significance. Our finding suggested that NNS program 
compared to pre-feeding oral stimulation program im-
proved weight gaining at discharge time. These results 
was in contrast to the study from Lyu et al. (17) and in line 
with those of Bernbaum et al. (18). This difference may be </p>

<p>explained by the different method used by these studies. 
In general newborns in NNS and pre-feeding oral stimu-
lation groups discharged sooner than control group. This 
findings (although not statistically significant) agree 
with Fucile et al. (19) and is in contrast to previous studies, 
which reported that oral stimulation decreased length of 
hospital stay (15, 20). Our study had several power and 
weakness. For example, medical events and lack of exact 
protocol for discharge may lead prolonged the length of 
hospital stay. The implementation of specific protocol for 
discharge may have allowed for better discrimination be-
tween groups and reduce these weakness. 
Furthermore, another weakness of our study was small 
sample size. For future studies, we propose to recruit 
a larger sample size to increase the possibility of an 
achievement of statistical significance. 
In conclusion, although our finding not showed sig-
nificant differences between groups in independent oral 
feeding (may be for small sample size) but results empha-
sized the importance of NNS for improvement of weight 
gain in preterm infants. Also, we have demonstrated that 
both NNS and pre-feeding oral stimulation may contrib-
ute to the improvement of independent oral feeding. 
Since these interventions have beneficial effects on pre-
term infants weight gaining and independent oral feed-
ing, we offer the use of both interventions in NICU. Fur-
thermore, NNS is more effective on weight gain. We may 
further propose that caregivers and speech language 
pathologist in NICU primarily use NNS because of its sim-
plicity and safety for using by parents and NICU staff. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Authors wish to thank the parents of the newborns and 
nursing staff of NICU for their intimate cooperation. </p>

<p>Authors' Contributions </p>

<p>Faezeh Asadollahpour and Fariba Yadegari helped in de-
veloping the original idea and edited the manuscript. All 
authors equally help to write this manuscript. </p>



<p>Asadollahpour F et al. </p>





</text></tei>