<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4666316" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Demographic aging of the world population contributes to an increase in the number of persons 
diagnosed with dementia (PWD), with corresponding increases in health care expenditures. In 
addition, fewer family members are available to care for these individuals. Most care for PWD 
occurs in the home, and family members caring for PWD frequently suffer negative outcomes 
related to the stress and burden of observing their loved one's progressive memory and functional 
decline. Decreases in cognition and self-care also necessitate that the caregiver takes on new roles 
and responsibilities in care provision. Smart technologies are being developed to support family 
caregivers of PWD in a variety of ways, including provision of information and support resources 
online, wayfinding technology to support independent mobility of the PWD, monitoring systems 
to alert caregivers to changes in the PWD and their environment, navigation devices to track PWD 
experiencing wandering, and telemedicine and e-health services linking caregivers and PWD with 
health care providers. This paper will review current uses of these advancing technologies to 
support care of PWD. Challenges unique to widespread acceptance of technology will be 
addressed and future directions explored. </p>

<p>Keywords </p>

<p>technology; dementia care; caregiver support </p>

<p>This work is published by Dove Medical Press Limited, and licensed under Creative Commons Attribution -Non Commercial 
(unported, v3.0) License. The full terms of the License are available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/.Non-
commercial uses of the work are Demographic trends associated with older adults experiencing cognitive </p>

<p>decline </p>

<p>As life expectancies increase, Americans are living longer with more chronic conditions 
than ever before. The number of adults aged 65 years and older is expected to double from 
40.2 million in 2010 to 88.5 million in 2050. 1 According to the United States Department of 
Health and Human Services, 2 older adults are living with chronic conditions such as arthritis 
(50%), heart disease (30%), cancer (24%), diabetes (20%), and hypertension (72%). 
Cognitive impairments are also prevalent in this aging population, ranging from age-specific 
memory loss to clinically diagnosed dementia. Population-based studies have found that 
28% of community-dwelling older adults have mild cognitive changes such as memory loss; 
this includes 19% of adults aged over 65 years and 29% of those aged over 85 years. 3 
Currently, 11% of older adults are living with Alzheimer's disease (AD) and other types of 
dementia. </p>

<p>Older adults with cognitive impairments, even mild, are at a higher risk of developing AD, 
with an annual conversion rate from mild cognitive impairment to AD of 3%-13%, which is 
significantly higher than the rate in those without cognitive impairment (1% per year). 4 A 
new case of AD is diagnosed every minute, and the annual incidence of AD and other 
dementias is projected to double by 2050. 5 Thus, the number of persons with AD (PWD) 
will nearly triple from 5.2 million in 2014 to a projected 13.8 million in 2050. 6 </p>

<p>These demographic trends simultaneously affect caregiving populations. Currently, there are 
65.7 million informal caregivers in the US. 7,8 Over 90% of older adults with chronic 
disabilities receive some care support, and about two-thirds receive only informal unpaid 
care. 2 Specifically, 43.5 million family members accept responsibility for providing 
informal, unpaid care for older adults, and 15.5 million are caring for PWD. 6,8 </p>

<p>Most older adults, including PWD, desire to remain in their homes as they age. 9 Declining 
physical and mental capabilities create significant challenges to manage increasing care 
needed to remain living at home. Since the 1980s, technology has been investigated as a 
possible support for aging in place. 10 Technology-based interventions currently employed to 
support caregivers of PWD range from internet-based information and support groups to 
robotic companions and use of smartphones to report symptoms. 11-13 As technology 
advances, so will new opportunities to reduce both the burden of caregiving and the need for 
premature nursing home placement due to caregivers no longer being able to meet care 
demands. This paper focuses on telemedicine and smart technologies as potential supports 
for the growing population of PWD and their family caregivers. </p>

<p>While this paper is not a systematic review, the authors conducted a similar search. Search 
terms for technology, telehealth/telemedicine, and sensor, monitoring, and tracking 
technology were combined with moderating terms like rural health and dementia caregiving 
to find articles with comprehensive reviews, exemplars of uses, and experimental or unique 
reports of applications. No criteria were developed for inclusion or exclusion of articles. </p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 2 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Costs and negative outcomes of caregiving </p>

<p>Cognitive impairment, including memory loss and related neurodegenerative diseases, is 
placing increasing demands on US health care and family systems. In 2014, the medical cost 
of caring for PWD is estimated at $214 billion; the expected medical cost in 2050 is 
projected to be $1.2 trillion. 6 The annual overall Medicare and Medicaid expenditure for 
dementia care is $150 billion for acute, long-term, and hospice care. 6 Uncompensated 
contributions of family caregivers were estimated at $202.6 billion in 2010 considering an 
hourly wage of $11.93 per hour. 6,7 PWD have more than triple the number of 
hospitalizations and nursing home admissions compared with older adults with other 
conditions. AD and other types of dementia are the sixth leading cause of death. 6   Family caregivers experience high levels of stress, burden, and role captivity that lead to 
negative physical, psychological, social, and spiritual outcomes. 14-16 Caregivers of PWD 
must cope with their loved one's progressive memory loss, self-care impairment, and 
communication breakdown. Additional caregiver challenges include learning new skills to 
manage disruptive behaviors; altered manifestations of behavioral and psychological 
symptoms that are common, progressive, and change in dementia; and complex conditions 
such as delirium that require guidance from health care professionals. 17-19 Caregiving 
stress, strain, and burden contribute to negative physical and mental health outcomes that 
include depression, insomnia, and psychotropic medication use, with notable increases in 
caregiver morbidity and mortality. 20,21   Different types of caregivers face unique challenges. Spousal caregivers may experience 
grieving due to changes in their relationship with their life partner. They may struggle to 
physically manage care or suffer cognitive changes themselves. Children and younger 
spousal caregivers may have occupational stress and career changes and may still be caring 
for their children while balancing care for parents or a spouse with AD. Caregivers separated 
by distance face unique challenges as they manage caregiving from afar. They may worry 
about their family member's safety and security, medication schedules, wandering, and need 
for information and socialization. The distant caregiver may be totally unaware of the needs 
of their family member, placing further burden on the onsite caregiver(s). 6 </p>

<p>Telemedicine and e-health </p>

<p>Telemedicine and e-health services are now widely used and well integrated into the daily 
lives of middle-aged and older adults. Over 50% of those aged over 65 years use computers 
and related devices daily to access the internet to seek medical information and social 
support. 22 Surveys of family caregivers report that 80%-95% request mobile systems and 
find that interactive features assist in caregiving. Two-thirds of family caregivers in the US 
have a mobile wireless device, and 69% of these report that it assists them in caregiving. 
Mobile technology features such as mobile text messaging, personal medical recording, and 
visual communication with health care providers meet specific user needs. 22-24   Telemedicine and e-health services are now available to support care for older adults and 
family caregivers. Virtual care in the community delivered via technology-based approaches 
is able to overcome the limitations of face-to-face delivery; namely, time constraints, </p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 3 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>geographic limitations, and transportation issues. 25 For those dealing with early-stage AD, 
key considerations are 1) identifying the needs of cognitively impaired adults and their 
family caregivers, 2) developing technological applications suitable for constrained 
environments and user abilities, 3) establishing training strategies for cognitively impaired 
adults to use the technologies, and 4) providing appropriate technical support for cognitively 
impaired adults and caregivers. 26 </p>

<p>PWD use of technology </p>

<p>Online or internet-based technology can support PWD themselves, especially in early stages. 
There have been several studies testing online resources for PWD focused on maintaining 
cognitive skills, learning new things, maintaining social interactions, and finding 
information. 27 Examples include electronic applications providing reminders (eg, 
medication management prompting devices), social contact (eg, cellphones, online chat 
groups), safety (eg, alarm systems and action triggered lighting), and daily activities (eg, 
music players). Cognitive stimulation activities are also often web or computer based. 
Cognitive stimulation has been shown to have positive effects in PWD in early and mid 
stages. 28 </p>

<p>Caregiver support through technology </p>

<p>Although technology can target the PWD themselves, the vast majority of telemedicine and 
smart technologies are designed to support family caregivers. Two separate systematic 
reviews highlight the benefits of web-based caregiver support programs. 29 Web-based 
training and educational programs to support caregivers are readily available. The Internet-
Based Savvy Caregiver, based on the validated Savvy Caregiver program, 30 is an example. 
It provides an interactive, iterative curriculum that improves knowledge about, and 
competence for, caregiving. 25   A customized computer-telephone integration system, <rs type="software">e-care</rs>, provides a psychoeducational 
intervention that identifies resources and strategies to enhance safety, communication, self-
care, social support, and management of problem behaviors in the community. 31 The system 
features screen phones with hierarchal menus (text and voice) that enables users to 1) place 
and receive calls, 2) send and retrieve messages, 3) access a range of information and 
services, and 4) conference with several people simultaneously. This system was effective in 
decreasing caregiver burden and depression significantly in depression scores in caregivers 
with high depression scores at baseline. 31   Another type of in-home caregiver support links caregivers with expert guidance for 
managing challenging care situations using video monitoring. Caregivers are trained to 
capture behaviors that are a problem via computer video recording, which is then wirelessly 
uploaded for a team of experts to review and provide feedback. In a pilot study, this system 
demonstrated improved behavior management and caregiver communication and was 
reported as easy to use. 32 Support for caregivers can also be provided via web-based video 
conferencing and/or text-based chat forums. 33   There is growing use and acceptance of video conferencing in both the diagnosis and 
monitoring in geriatric medical 34 and geriatric psychiatry care. 35-37 Though further large-</p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 4 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>scale studies are needed, research has established the reliability and validity for 
neurocognitive testing and neurological examinations via video telemedicine. 35,37,38 Video 
conferencing can also link local primary care professionals to specialists for assessments, 
enhancing the administration of standardized assessments and examinations. 35,36 Telehealth 
diagnosis and monitoring have been welcomed in remote and rural areas and with Spanish-
speaking and Native American populations, as access to specialized services is limited in 
these underserved areas. 39,40   Monitoring systems </p>

<p>It is widely recognized that caregiving is burdensome and leads to excessive levels of stress; 
thus, technology must be adapted to address the causes of caregiver stressors. For example, 
caregivers are concerned about the safety and security of their PWD. It is stressful if the 
caregiver needs to leave the PWD at home alone for any length of time or while they work, 
due to possible wandering, accidents, or other negative events that may harm the PWD. 
Technology that monitors whether or not the PWD leaves the home, falls, or enacts other 
behaviors and potentially dangerous environmental conditions (eg, heat, water on the floor, 
fire) may alleviate some of these concerns. Many new systems provide these types of 
monitoring and tracking systems. Three main aims of monitoring are detection of activities 
of daily living (ADLs), occurrence of significant events (ie, falls), and changes in health 
status, or a combination of these. 41   Monitoring systems are designed to detect changes in one or more ADLs or physical 
parameters. Detection of subtle changes can trigger interventions to avert negative outcomes 
such as hospitalizations. In a systematic review, Peetoom et al 41 categorized existing 
monitoring technologies into five categories: 1) in-home passive infrared motion sensors, 2) 
body-worn sensors, 3) video monitoring, 4) pressure sensors, and 5) sound recognition 
integrated with multicomponent systems and "smart homes". An example of simple 
monitoring is a motion detector that turns on a bathroom light or a wireless home security 
system that is triggered by exiting or entering, activating an alarm. This technology gathers 
information through activity sequence awareness, location awareness, presence awareness, 
and context awareness capabilities. 42 Initially, data are captured to identify patterns for the 
individual over time. Systems are developed to code behavior using computer-derived 
algorithms to identify patterns that deviate from normal and trigger warnings. 43 Requisite to 
this system is a person capable of receiving and responding to the alarm to alleviate or 
intervene on the alarm upon notification. </p>

<p>Other sensor technologies monitor the progression of AD over time. Changes in ADLs and 
instrumental ADL performance provide objective data about disease progression. 44 Through 
sensor technology, health care providers are able to detect cognitive decline reflected in 
behaviors such as getting out of bed at odd hours or going to bed earlier and earlier from day 
to day. 44 Yefimova and Woods 45 also describe use of sensor technologies 1) to identify 
patterns of baseline norms of activities through multimodal awareness monitoring and then 
2) to detect the onset or escalation of disruptive behaviors. Repetitive motions might be 
"normal" in the bathroom when one is brushing teeth, though might indicate increased 
agitation if it occurs when sitting down. 45 </p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 5 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>A commercially available example is the QuietCare system, which monitors ADLs. 43 The 
QuietCare system requires a response to the alarms, activated through emails to caregivers, 
and in urgent situations to a 24/7 regional emergency center. In a Dutch study on 
psychogeriatric patients living at home alone, there was a significant decrease in burden for 
formal or informal caregivers at a distance. 43 </p>

<p>Ambient assistive living with smart technologies </p>

<p>Ambient assistive living (AAL) integrates telecommunications, electronics, and computing 
to support people in carrying out their everyday life activities to support continued 
independent living at home or in an apartment. AAL results from a new comprehensive 
technologic paradigm called "ambient intelligence". 46 The technology is focused on 
empowering human-machine interactions by using sensitive, adaptive, and responsive 
strategies to human needs in digital environments. 46 AAL is characterized by "sensors and 
devices interconnected through a network … which senses features of the users and their 
environment, then reasons about the accumulated data, and finally selects actions to take that 
will benefit the users in the environment" 10 (p. 278). Complex AAL systems can include 
multiple sensor devices located within an environment, such as Bluetooth Low Energy, 
radiofrequency identification, microchip implant, sensor technology, software agents (a 
software program that has some capacities of artificial intelligence), affective computing, 
and biometrics (some include nanotechnology). </p>

<p>"Smart homes" are one example of complex AAL and use remote network monitoring and 
exchange of data at a distance. AAL technologies can 1) monitor ambient temperatures, 
gases, and motion; 2) notify problematic changes to remote users; and 3) enable family and 
health care providers to predict and intervene on impending incidents. 47,48 For example, a 
stove temperature sensor can collect real-time temperature data. If the stove has been left on 
for too long, data points indicating the temperature are detected, compared, and then 
analyzed in order to generate an alert for distance caregivers. 47   At Tiger Place, an assisted living facility in Columbia, MI, USA, an aging in place initiative 
uses this type of complex monitoring system. A wide variety of data are collected using 1) 
infrared sensors detecting motion on kitchen cabinets while preparing meals and 2) bed 
pneumatic sensors assessing levels of pulse, respiration, and restlessness. 48 Algorithms are 
developed to analyze these data to identify functional decline and potential illnesses. Then, 
health care providers such as nurse practitioners provide timely and effective care to 
improve and maintain health and functional independence. 48 While this system is 
scientifically verified, it is not used in home settings yet because it requires expensive 
advanced technologies and intensive training for health care providers. </p>

<p>Wayfinding and tracking </p>

<p>Wayfinding technologies can assist PWD in living safely by providing prompts for 
independent mobility within a home and community. 49 Wayfinding systems typically use 
global positioning systems (GPS) that allow PWD in earlier stages to increase freedom, 
autonomy, and confidence in being able to go outdoors independently without fear of 
becoming lost. Orientation assistance can be given through three modalities, visual, audio, </p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 6 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>and tactile signals, or a combination, and have been tested indoors and outdoors. 50 An 
example of a tactile-based system uses four small vibrating motors attached to a wearable 
belt with an integrated GPS, a three-axis compass, an inertial sensor, power management, a 
battery, and an algorithmic executive processor that provides the PWD with direction-
relevant cues on which way to go. 51 The effectiveness of this system is limited to PWD in 
mild stages, because of cognitive demands for perceiving and interpreting the sensations. </p>

<p>Another navigation system using scenario-based video clips embedded with Bluetooth 
sensor technology was developed and tested with some success on cognitively intact 
individuals. 49 Lancioni et al 52,53 have done studies on navigational systems using either 
light or auditory cues, finding consistently that visual cues are more effective wayfinding 
cues for PWD. </p>

<p>In contrast, tracking devices use similar technology but focus on providing caregivers with a 
way to know the location of the PWD and to prevent and intervene in unsafe situations. A 
pilot study evaluated the feasibility and acceptability of a GPS device with expanded 
features for 1) tracking location and tracing path through satellite, 2) programming 
telephone connection between the PWD and the family caregivers, and 3) activating a 
loudspeaker function to communicate with the PWD in case they cannot use the phone. 54  This study of dyads (N=33) found that the GPS intervention increases the ability of PWD to 
go outside independently, results in more freedom of PWD away from caregivers, and 
decreases levels of stress of both PWD and caregivers. 54   Another example using complex tracking programs is prevention of nighttime falls in PWD. 
This tracking program, HBTec-TS system, incorporates a nightlight path device that is 
installed near the bed and is triggered to light up automatically when the person steps out of 
bed. The lighting guides the PWD to the bathroom at night. In addition, this system can be 
integrated with a wrist band similar to LifeLine ® , a remote intercom, and a connection to a 
hotline for emergency personnel. 55 A recent study using the HBTec-TS system reported a 
significant decrease in nighttime falls in the intervention group (N=49) compared with the 
control group (N=47) of community-dwelling PWD (odds ratio =0.37, 95% confidence 
interval =0.15-0.88, P=0.02). This system reduced the relative risk of falls by 48.8% in 
PWD at high risk for frequent falls. 55 </p>

<p>Perspectives of users </p>

<p>Several qualitative studies 54,57,58 describe the responses of caregivers and PWD to 
technology. Caregiver views did vary and they expressed both positive feelings and 
concerns. For example, caregivers felt that GPS technology has the opportunity to promote 
autonomy, mobility, and safety of the PWD while providing family member caregivers with 
peace of mind. However, these tracking devices are not helpful for every PWD and may lead 
to diminished privacy and dependency. 56 In general, technology that allows people to 
remain more independent and reside at home safely is rated positively. 54,57,58 Span et al 59  found that involving the PWD in the process of developing technological applications 
enhanced usability and acceptability and contributed to a sense of empowerment. </p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 7 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Specific to sensor networks, Steel et al 57 identified six major themes related to the use of 
technology that potentially affect users' acceptance. These include valuing independence 
and related perceptions of nursing homes, the perceived impact on quality of life and 
potential changes in lifestyle, and concerns about cost, social implications, adherence, 
health, confidentiality, anxiety, and system reliability. In addition, user preferences related 
to technology self-efficacy and willingness to be trained, design preferences such as type of 
technology (wearable, ambient monitoring, or embedded sensors), and external factors 
involving support availability were related issues. 57 In another study, older users saw 
technology as a support to aging in place, citing increased feelings of safety and security, 
thus postponing institutionalization. 58 Studies indicated that systems should be not only 
unobtrusive and acceptably installed but easy to use. </p>

<p>Challenges to adoption </p>

<p>There are various barriers that limit the use of technology by PWD and their caregivers, 
including 1) ethical considerations; 2) user perspectives; 3) access to, and reimbursement 
for, technology; and 4) privacy. Privacy is a major concern, specifically when technological 
devices utilize recorded video and audio of PWD and caregivers with a risk of exposing 
sensitive, personally identifiable data. The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability 
Act of 1996 must be adhered to regarding all data that are obtained through the 
technological devices in the home. 46 Obtaining informed consent of the PWD and their 
caregivers is extremely important before the implementation of technology devices in the 
home. All collected data should be encrypted and secure, in order to maintain and ensure 
confidentiality. </p>

<p>The use of technology in the home has the potential to reduce autonomy of PWD. 
Technology can become too controlling and violate privacy. Restrictions and automations 
are intended to support independent living; however, unnecessary and too frequent use of 
technologies easily diminishes independence of choice and action of the PWD living in their 
home. Instead of being helpful, extremely advanced technology beyond the user's capacity 
can become frustrating and dehumanizing to the PWD. 58,60 Significant time must be spent 
on educating and ensuring understanding of each type of technological device that will be 
used in the home. 58   There may also be stigma associated with the technology. Families may be apprehensive 
about the presence of technology in the home, with the belief that such devices are used only 
for dependent and frail older adults. 60 There are concerns that technology that is obtrusive 
and visible may cause potential embarrassment and anxiety. Devices should be designed to 
minimize attracting attention; for example, using a smartphone for a technological 
application is discreet and can help avoid stigmatization. 46 In addition, alarms should not be 
too loud. Features should be designed to alert the caregiver but prevent agitation and avoid 
frightening the PWD. 61   A critical factor in acceptance of technology is ease of use. 62 This is especially pertinent for 
PWD whose caregivers are themselves aging and may have limited experience and different 
attitudes toward technology. Spousal caregivers may also be of advanced age with </p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 8 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>corresponding physical and cognitive changes such as reduced processing speed, less 
manual dexterity, and low visual acuity. There is a risk that older adults may feel frustrated 
if they frequently fail in using devices, and they may find technology use as another 
burdensome caregiving task. </p>

<p>There is also concern that technology use may result in loss of human contact. Technology 
devices enable PWD to increase their independence. Thus, PWD may need less frequent 
contact with formal or informal caregivers. This increased independence could result in 
social isolation and loneliness of the PWD. 60 It is important to guarantee that the technology 
devices in the home do not replace human care and contact. 46   Socioeconomic barriers exist. For example, internet access is a necessary requirement of 
many advanced technologies. However, families of PWD living in rural areas or with low 
incomes may have limited internet access. Dial-up services used in some areas by some 
older adults may not meet capacity for data transfer. Indeed, the number of persons aged 65 
years and older with high-speed internet connections has increased to 39% from 19% in 
2008, but it still has far to go to achieve universal access. 63 Modest incomes of older adults 
may be to blame in part, and older adults may not see the value of high-speed internet 
access. </p>

<p>Insurance coverage for new technology to support dementia care is also lagging. Consumers 
must be able to afford these services, as many emerging technologies are not covered by 
personal health insurance, Medicare, or Medicaid. Who will handle the finances associated 
with installing and utilizing the technology is a major concern of PWD and their 
caregivers. 60 If technology requires an out-of-pocket expense, they are less likely to use 
technology, even though they know that it could be beneficial for care. </p>

<p>Future directions </p>

<p>Technological devices must be designed with end user ease in mind in order to be functional 
and accepted. It is important to select the most appropriate devices based on the user's need 
and their technological competence. For example, devices must be power efficient to avoid 
unexpected powering off. 61 Devices should require minimal configuration such as repeated 
need to log on and enter passwords. 46 User manuals should be available for reference 
featuring a large font and diagrams of limited complexity. </p>

<p>Sufficient training for PWD and their family caregivers is critical when technological 
devices are introduced and implemented in the home. These technologies must be simple 
and limited in focus and should not require fine motor skills or excessive cognitive 
processing. Consideration of adults' learning styles is also essential in training older adults 
to use advancing technologies. A hands-on approach (experiential learning style) is essential 
to developing competency in technology use by older adults. PWD and their caregivers 
should be involved in developing and testing these technologies. 64 Ongoing tech support 
and resources for troubleshooting that are readily accessible will also be needed. </p>

<p>Health care providers must also be prepared to screen, analyze, and interpret data and 
respond 60 and may need technical support and training. Providing care through e-health and </p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 9 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>other technologies may require the acquisition and practice of new skills for health care 
professionals. For example, clinicians using technology in working with older adults need to 
be aware of potential isolation effects. Research is needed to determine appropriate levels of 
in-person contact that technology can supplement. Special skills and strategies for providing 
care with technology need to be identified through research and incorporated into 
educational programs for health professionals. </p>

<p>Proactive policy support is needed to make consumers aware of available technologies to 
support care for PWD. The leading factor driving acceptance and use of technology is 
perceived value (usefulness) or meeting a need. 62 Marketing available technologies to make 
consumers aware of these supports will play a crucial role. 64 In addition, access to internet 
infrastructure is critical to use of technology to support dementia care in the home. The 
Federal Communication Commission developed a National Broadband Plan in 2010 and 
identified how high-speed internet access is essential for older adults for next-generation 
internet technologies that include telehealth and smart homes, supporting needs of older 
adults, including personal fulfillment, health preservation, social connectedness, caregiver 
support, and functional capability and activity. 63   Ethical principles should be applied to protect PWD users from potential negative aspects of 
technology. Mahoney et al 65 developed a list of ethical principles for gerotechnology 
research and development targeting persons with AD and their caregivers. Their guidelines 
state how to maintain respect, autonomy, beneficence, justice and distributional fairness, 
nonabandonment, and privacy and confidentiality. 65 Stringent regulation should be applied 
for data collection, de-identification, data storage, distribution of study findings, as well as 
secondary data use. All data collected by technology should have a clear purpose that will 
benefit the user. </p>

<p>Future research is needed to demonstrate cost-effectiveness to support changes in 
reimbursement policies. Expansion of telehealth under the Affordable Care Act is projected 
to increase telehealth services 500% by 2017. 66 Support by official agencies such as the 
Administration on Aging or endorsement by the Alzheimer's Association may also increase 
consumer use. </p>

<p>Even though the US is considered an early adopter of technology, it actually lags behind 
other countries in adoption of health care technologies by up to 12 years. 67,68 The US lacks 
an integrated network of connectivity, a key that has enabled smaller countries to implement 
technology-driven health solutions. 68 A review of selected technology innovations 
completed by Chan et al 69 found that many systems were designed in Europe. In Japan, the 
Ministry of International Trade and Industry built 13 "welfare techno houses" that were 
equipped with fully automated biomedical devices. 70 The Japanese also developed electrical 
appliances fitted with sensors (eg, rice cooker, air conditioning, refrigerator, TV set) to 
monitor activities such as having or preparing a meal or bathing. Raw data are translated 
using mathematical models into usable behavioral data. 71 </p>

<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 10 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Cutting-edge technologies </p>

<p>Wearable, implantable (microcapsule devices that are swallowed), and microsystems are 
being developed and are available on a limited basis. Devices that are worn by the user or 
embedded in the home are connected by wired or wireless networks to a service center that 
has monitoring and diagnostic capabilities. These devices capture data from sounds, images, 
body motion, and ambient parameters (light, temperature, humidity), vital signs (blood 
pressure, respiration, body temperature, heart/pulse rate, bodyweight/fat, blood oxygenation, 
electrocardiogram), sleep patterns and other health parameters, daily activities, and social 
interactions. Algorithms compare data with an established profile of the user's physical and 
physiological patterns and can provide alerts and assistance for emergency situations. 
Wearable (machine washable) garments with sensors are being designed in the US and other 
countries. These units measure a variety of physiologic parameters and can also be 
embedded with tracking technology. 72   Robot technology has been more fully developed to assist in supporting basic activities 
(getting dressed, bathing, toileting, eating) and mobility, providing household maintenance, 
monitoring those who need continuous care, and maintaining safety. Robots have been 
designed with consideration of social, aesthetic, and emotional factors to support the quality 
of life of older adults. 10 </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>As the population with dementia expands and increases the burden on family caregivers, 
telemedicine and smart technologies have potential to support aging in place for PWD while 
reducing caregiver burden and its negative outcomes, improving quality of life for families 
experiencing dementia and reducing health care costs. Finally, the potential for technology 
to support dementia care at home may reduce health care expenditures secondary to formal 
care needs and premature institutional care. However, realizing the potential for technology 
to meet dementia care needs depends on a number of factors, including raising awareness of 
available technologies and their utility, promoting accessibility and affordability, and 
overcoming challenges to acceptance and use. Future research and continuous development 
are required to use advanced technology integrated with current dementia care. </p>



<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 11 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 12 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 13 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 14 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Bossen et al. 
Page 15 </p>

<p>Smart Homecare Technol Telehealth. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 December 01. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

</text></tei>