<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4586752" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The differentiation propensities of human pluripotent stem 
cell (hPSC) lines vary from one line to another (Osafune et al.,  2008; Bock et al., 2011; Chetty et al., 2013; Gage et al., 2013). 
Some cell lines fail to yield terminally differentiated cells at 
subsequent stages of differentiation (Tabar and Studer, 2014). 
These limitations in the ability to systematically differentiate 
hPSC lines into desired lineages substantially restrict their util-
ity for cell replacement therapy and disease modeling, as mov-
ing stem cell-based therapies to patients will require the ability 
to differentiate all cell lines. 
Here, we show that PP1, a Src tyrosine kinase inhibi-
tor, regulates the retinoblastoma protein (Rb) and cell cycle 
of hPSCs, enriches cells in the early G1 phase, and improves 
their multilineage differentiation potential. Importantly, the PP1 
treatment yields high differentiation efficiencies even in cell 
lines that have low differentiation propensities under control 
conditions. We demonstrate these effects in both human em-
bryonic and induced pluripotent stem cell (iPSC) lines. Further-
more, we show that Src plays an important regulatory role in 
this process, as genetic suppression of Src regulates Rb activity 
and enhances the differentiation potential of hPSCs. 
Our focus on PP1 and Src was motivated by the find-
ing that the embryonic cell cycle lengthens to incorporate gap 
phases as it transitions from a proliferative stage to a stage 
governed by cell fate decisions (Trelstad et al., 1967; Hartwell  and Weinert, 1989; Murray and Kirschner, 1989; Frederick  and Andrews, 1994; Edgar and Lehner, 1996). One mecha-
nism that plays a critical role in maintaining cell proliferation </p>

<p>at the early developmental stages is Src tyrosine kinase sig-
naling (Frame, 2002; Segawa et al., 2006; Kim et al., 2009). 
High protein tyrosine kinase activity is required for the early 
developmental events that occur before cell fate specification 
(Imamoto and Soriano, 1993; Livingston et al., 1998). Analo-
gous to early development, Src activity is elevated in prolifer-
ating PSCs (Annerén et al., 2004), potentially preventing the 
lengthening of the cell cycle for differentiation and cell fate 
specification. We therefore hypothesized that inhibiting Src 
activity might regulate the cell cycle and improve the differen-
tiation propensity of hPSCs. 
In previous work, we showed that treatment of hPSCs 
with DMSO improves differentiation propensity after directed 
differentiation (Chetty et al., 2013). The present study provides 
a new tool to improve differentiation and strengthens the case 
that manipulating the cell cycle is critical for improving directed 
differentiation. The mechanistic results presented here indicate 
that Src plays an important regulatory role in controlling cell 
fate decisions of hPSCs. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>PP1 treatment improves the differentiation 
capacity of hPSCs in a dose-dependent manner </p>

<p>Src-tyrosine kinase signaling regulates cell growth and prolif-
eration of various cell types, including PSCs (Annerén et al.,  2004), cancer cells (Frame, 2002), and normal somatic cells </p>

<p>Driving human pluripotent stem cells (hPSCs) into specific lineages is an inefficient and challenging process. We show 
that a potent Src inhibitor, PP1, regulates expression of genes involved in the G1 to S phase transition of the cell cycle, 
activates proteins in the retinoblastoma family, and subsequently increases the differentiation propensities of hPSCs into 
all three germ layers. We further demonstrate that genetic suppression of Src regulates the activity of the retinoblastoma 
protein and enhances the differentiation potential of hPSCs across all germ layers. These positive effects extend beyond 
the initial germ layer specification and enable efficient differentiation at subsequent stages of differentiation. </p>

<p>A Src inhibitor regulates the cell cycle of human 
pluripotent stem cells and improves directed 
differentiation </p>

<p>Sundari Chetty, 1 Elise N. Engquist, 1 Elie Mehanna, 1 Kathy O. Lui, 1 Alexander M. Tsankov, 1,2 and Douglas A. Melton 1,3 </p>

<p>1 Department of Stem Cell and Regenerative Biology, Harvard Stem Cell Institute, Cambridge, MA 02138 
2 Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, Cambridge, MA 02142 
3 Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138 </p>

<p>© 2015 Chetty et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the pub-
lication date (see http://www.rupress.org/terms). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>Correspondence to Sundari Chetty: schetty@mcb.harvard.edu; or Douglas 
A. Melton: dmelton@harvard.edu </p>

<p>Abbreviations used in this paper: hPSC, human pluripotent stem cell; iPSC, in-
duced pluripotent stem cell; qPCR, quantitative PCR; Rb, retinoblastoma protein. </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
(Playford and Schaller, 2004). In most cell types, Src is neg-
atively regulated (held in an inactive state), but in PSCs and 
cancer cells, Src activity is elevated (Frame, 2002; Annerén  et al., 2004). PP1 (Fig. 1 A) has been shown to effectively 
block Src activity and the proliferation of many types of tu-
morigenic cells (Hanke et al., 1996; Bain et al., 2007). We 
tested whether inhibition of Src signaling by PP1 treatment 
affects the differentiation capacity of hPSCs. We focused on 
the hPSC line HUES6, a cell line with a 24-h doubling time 
that does not exhibit bias toward any particular lineage and 
is representative of cell lines with relatively low efficiencies 
of differentiation (Cowan et al., 2004; Osafune et al., 2008;  Bock et al., 2011). To enhance therapeutic utility, differenti-</p>

<p>ations were performed under low-serum conditions. After a 
24-h treatment with PP1 at different doses, HUES6 cells were 
cultured in differentiation media with Wnt3a and Activin A for 
24 h, then assessed for the percentage of cells that differenti-
ated into Brachyury (Brachy)+ cells, a marker for mesendo-
derm and an early marker for differentiation (Fig. 1 B). 
A 24-h treatment with PP1 increased the percentage 
as well as the total number of cells that differentiated com-
pared with untreated control cells in a dose-dependent man-
ner (Fig. 1, C-F). At dosages of 25-50 µM, the percentage 
of cells differentiating into Brachy+ cells reached nearly 
50%, an ∼300-fold enhancement relative to control cells. 
In all conditions, cells that did not differentiate retained the </p>

<p>Figure 1. PP1 treatment improves the differentiation capacity of hPSCs in a dose-dependent manner. (A) Chemical structure of 4-amino-5-(4-methylphenyl)-
7-(t-butyl)pyrazolo-d-3,4-pyrimidine (PP1). (B) Schematic of directed differentiation of hPSCs into Brachy+ cells after no treatment (control) or a 24-h PP1 
treatment at varying doses. (C-E) Percentages (C) and absolute numbers (D) of control and PP1-treated HUES6 hPSCs differentiating into Brachy+ cells in 
relation to the total cell numbers (E) in control and PP1-treated cultures. (F) Immunostaining for Oct4, Brachy, and DAPI in control and PP1-treated cultures 
after directed differentiation. Error bars indicate SEM of three replicates. Bars, 200 µM. </p>

<p>Src regulates stem cell differentiation • Chetty et al. </p>



<p>pluripotency marker Oct4 (Fig. 1 F). Because a 25-µM PP1 
treatment maximizes the percentage and total number of dif-
ferentiated cells, we used this as an optimal dosage in subse-
quent analyses. Improvements in differentiation capacity were 
also observed in other human embryonic and iPSC lines after 
a 24-h PP1 (25 µM) treatment (Fig. 2). These improvements 
were driven by an enhanced competency for differentiation; 
across all cell lines, the rate of cell death did not differ sig-</p>

<p>nificantly between the two groups (Fig. S1; P = 0.3 Annexin+/ 
PI−; P = 0.1 Annexin+/PI+). 
The change in intercellular morphology with exposure to 
PP1 is consistent with the effects of Src activity on cell-cell 
adhesion (Frame, 2002; Playford and Schaller, 2004). While el-
evated Src activity disrupts cell-cell adhesion, inhibition of its 
activity is associated with improved multicellular interactions 
(Segawa et al., 2006). Cells treated with higher dosages of PP1 </p>

<p>Figure 2. PP1 treatment improves differentiation capacity 
across hPSC lines. (A) Schematic of directed differentiation 
of hPSCs into Brachy+ cells after no treatment (control) or 
a 24-h 25 µM PP1 treatment. (B-I) Percentages and abso-
lute numbers of control and PP1-treated hPSCs differentiat-
ing into Brachy+ cells in the HUES8 (B and C), HUES49 
(D and E), H9 (F and G), and iPSC 11b (H and I) hPSC 
lines. Error bars indicate SEM of two replicates (HUES49, 
H9, iPSC11b) or four replicates (HUES8). *, P ≤ 0.05; **, 
P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
aggregate into tight, dense clusters distinct from the spread-out, 
planar arrangement of control cells and cells treated with low 
doses of PP1 (Fig. 1 F). 
In addition to dosage, the duration of the PP1 treatment can 
also regulate the differentiation capacity of hPSCs. Treatment 
durations that were shorter than the cell line's doubling time 
induced only a 2-5% differentiation rate (unpublished data). 
Among the inhibitors tested, PP1 proved to be the most 
effective in enhancing differentiation potential. Consistent 
with prior reports, treatment of hPSCs with other inhibitors to 
perturb various cell cycle-related kinase signaling pathways 
had a minimal or moderate effect on improving differentia-
tion potential (Smith, 2001; Orford and Scadden, 2008; Li and  Kirschner, 2014). Treatment with a Cdk2 inhibitor at 5-10 µM 
induced ∼20% of the cells to differentiate into Brachy+ cells 
but was associated with a substantial degree of cell loss at 
higher doses (Fig. S2, A-I). </p>

<p>PP1 treatment regulates the cell cycle and 
activity of Rb in hPSCs </p>

<p>Given that the PP1 treatment effectively enhances differentia-
tion potential at the 24 h time point, we treated hPSCs with 
25 µM PP1 for 24 h and investigated the effects on the cell cycle. 
Cell cycle analysis by flow cytometry showed that the PP1 treat-
ment changes the distribution of hPSCs in the G1, S, and G2/M 
phases of the cell cycle, increasing the proportion of cells in G1 
and decreasing the number of cells in the S and G2/M phases. 
These effects were consistently observed in several human em-
bryonic and iPSC lines (Figs. 3, 4 A, and S3). Further inves-
tigation of the HUES6 cell line showed that a 24-h treatment 
with 25 µM PP1 nearly doubles the percentage of cells in G1 
phase (∼70%) compared with controls (∼35%; Fig. 4 B). The 
proportion of cells in the S and G2/M phases is concomitantly 
reduced by at least twofold after the PP1 treatment (Fig. 4 B). 
A significant shift toward G1 was observed across all cell lines 
(Fig. 3 and Fig. S3; P &lt; 0.002). 
Rb predominantly remains in an inactive hyperphos-
phorylated state throughout the cell cycle of human and mouse 
PSCs. While phosphorylated Rb promotes cell division, the 
accumulation of hypophosphorylated Rb (active Rb) is asso-
ciated with an enrichment of cells in the early G1 phase of the 
cell cycle and an improved capacity for differentiation (Buc- hkovich et al., 1989; Chen et al., 1989; Orford and Scadden,  2008). We assessed the phosphorylation status of Rb in control 
and 25 µM PP1-treated hPSCs. After a 24-h PP1 treatment, 
the percentage of hPSCs expressing hypophosphorylated Rb 
increased by &gt;60-fold from 0.3% to 20% (Fig. 4, C and D). 
Phosphorylation of Rb occurs at 16 distinct sites (Harbour and  Dean, 2000). Assessment of the inactive phosphorylated status 
of Rb at one of these sites (serine 780) showed that PP1 treat-
ment leads to a twofold reduction in the percentage of cells 
expressing pRb780 (Fig. 4, C and E). The phosphorylation of 
Rb at serine 780 was also differentially regulated by other cell 
cycle inhibitors (Fig. S2 J). 
In its hypophosphorylated state, Rb plays a critical role 
in growth suppression. In coordination with Rb, the retino-
blastoma-associated protein 46/48 (RbAP46/48; a histone 
chaperone protein) regulates the cell cycle by aiding in the 
transcriptional repression of Rb-related target genes, particu-
larly genes involved in the G1 to S phase transition (Harbour  and Dean, 2000; Taylor-Harding et al., 2004). We assessed 
the fraction of cells expressing the cofactor RbAP46/48 in </p>

<p>control and PP1-treated hPSCs. Flow cytometry analysis 
showed that the percentage of hPSCs expressing RbAP46/48 
nearly doubles between control and PP1-treated cells (Fig. 4, 
F and G). Furthermore, treatment with 25 µM PP1 for 24 h 
also regulated the expression of many genes associated with 
cell cycle control. The expression of genes promoting cell 
division, including Cyclin A1, Cdk2, and Cdc6, were signifi-
cantly reduced in PP1-treated hPSCs relative to control cells 
(Fig. 4 H). Expression of p27, a cell cycle inhibitor that pro-
motes growth arrest in G1 (Toyoshima and Hunter, 1994), was 
significantly increased in PP1-treated hPSCs compared with 
control cells (Fig. 4 H). No significant difference in expres-
sion levels was observed for Cyclin A2, Cyclin D1, Cyclin 
E1, E2f1, and p21 between control and PP1-treated hPSCs 
(Fig. 4 H). Together, these results show that PP1 treatment 
of hPSCs promotes growth inhibition and an accumulation of </p>

<p>Figure 3. PP1 treatment enriches cells in G1 across hPSC lines. Distri-
bution of hPSCs in the G1, S, and G2/M phases of the cell cycle after 
no treatment (control) or a 24-h 25 µM PP1 treatment in the HUES8 (A), 
HUES49 (B), H9 (C), and iPSC 11b (D) hPSC lines. (E) Mean percentage of 
hPSCs across all cell lines in the G1, S, and G2/M phases of the cell cycle 
after no treatment (control) or a 24-h 25 µM PP1 treatment. </p>

<p>Src regulates stem cell differentiation • Chetty et al. </p>



<p>cells in the G1 phase by regulating genes involved in the G1 to 
S phase transition. The enhanced hypophosphorylated state of 
Rb increases the proportion of cells in the early G1 phase and 
more generally indicates an increased presence of early G1 in 
the hPSC cycle after PP1 treatment. </p>

<p>Genetic suppression of Src regulates Rb 
activity and improves the differentiation 
capacity of hPSCs across all germ layers </p>

<p>Given that PP1 is a potent Src inhibitor (Hanke et al., 1996;  Bain et al., 2007), we assessed whether treatment of hPSCs with </p>

<p>Figure 4. PP1 treatment regulates the cell cycle and enhances the activity of Rb in hPSCs. (A and B) Distribution (A) and percentage (B) of HUES6 hPSCs in 
the G1, S, and G2/M phases of the cell cycle after no treatment (Control) or a 24-h 25 µM PP1 treatment. (C) Immunostaining for the active hypophosphor-
ylated Rb (red) and inactive phosphorylated pRb780 (green) in control and PP1-treated hPSCs. Bar, 200 µM. (D and E) Percentage of hPSCs expressing 
hypophosphorylated Rb (D) and hyperphosphorylated Rb (E; pRb780) after no treatment (Control) or a 24-h 25 µM PP1 treatment. (F and G) Flow cytometry 
analysis of the percentage of hPSCs expressing the retinoblastoma-associated protein 46/48 (RbAP46/48) after no treatment (Control) or a 24-h 25 µM 
PP1 treatment. (H) Relative expression levels of cell cycle-regulated genes in PP1-treated hPSCs compared with untreated controls. Error bars indicate SEM 
of 2-3 replicates. *, P ≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
PP1 reduced protein levels of Src. Western blot analysis using 
two different Src specific antibodies showed that PP1 treat-
ment does indeed suppress Src levels (Fig. 5 A). To investigate 
whether suppression of Src mimics the effects of PP1 on hPSCs, 
we next genetically suppressed Src in hPSCs using siRNA. siR-
NA-mediated knockdown of Src suppressed both the gene ex-
pression (Fig. 5 B) and protein (Fig. 5 C) levels of Src in hPSCs. 
Similar to PP1, Src knockdown also enhanced the activity of 
Rb by substantially reducing the levels of the phosphorylated 
and hyperphosphorylated forms of the Rb protein (ppRb) and 
increasing levels of the hypo-or underphosphorylated forms of 
Rb (Fig. 5 C). Together with PP1, these results provide further 
support that inhibition of Src increases the proportion of hPSCs 
in the early G1 phase of the cell cycle. 
Prior literature has shown that cells have an enhanced ca-
pacity to respond to extracellular signals in the G1 phase (Scott  et al., 1982). To investigate whether these effects regulate the 
differentiation propensity of hPSCs, we next assessed whether 
genetic suppression of Src improves the differentiation poten-
tial of hPSCs across all germ layers. After Src knockdown of 
hPSCs with siRNA, we subsequently induced differentiation 
into each of the germ layers using three different directed dif-
ferentiation protocols (Chetty et al., 2013; Fig. 5 D). The per-
centage of cells becoming Sox1+, Brachy+, and Sox17+ cells 
was quantified to assess multilineage differentiation potential 
into the ectodermal, mesodermal, and endodermal germ layers, 
respectively (Fig. 5 D). Transfection of hPSCs with Src siRNA 
before directed differentiation significantly increased the num-
ber and percentage of differentiated cells across all three germ 
layers (Fig. 5, E and F). After Src knockdown, the percentage 
of hPSCs that differentiated into each germ layer was enhanced 
by ∼2-10-fold (Fig. 5 F). At the time points assessed, differen-
tiation rates of ∼50% were observed across all the germ layers 
after Src knockdown (Fig. 5 F). While Src knockdown promoted 
aggregation of cells initially, the cells spread out more rapidly 
after differentiation compared with the PP1 treatment. The sup-
pression of the protein expression of Src was also reduced to a 
greater degree in PP1-treated cultures compared with genetic 
suppression of Src, potentially due to variations in potency and/ 
or technical limitations of using siRNA (Fig. 5, A and C). </p>

<p>PP1 treatment improves the differentiation 
capacity of hPSCs across all germ layers </p>

<p>Similar to Src knockdown, we next tested whether the PP1 
treatment improves the differentiation potential of hPSCs 
across germ layers. We treated HUES6 hPSCs with 25 µM PP1 
for 24 h and subsequently induced differentiation into each of 
the germ layers (Fig. S4 A). The percentage of cells becom-
ing Pax6+, Brachy+, and Sox17+ cells was quantified to assess 
multilineage differentiation potential into the ectodermal, meso-
dermal, and endodermal germ layers, respectively (Fig. S4 A). 
Treatment of hPSCs with 25 µM PP1 for 24 h before directed 
differentiation significantly increased the number and percent-
age of differentiated cells across all three germ layers (Fig. 
S4, B and C). No significant differences in total cell number 
were observed for differentiations toward the ectodermal and 
endodermal germ layers. A 1-d differentiation toward the me-
sodermal germ layer resulted in a reduction in total cell number 
after the PP1 treatment. After PP1 treatment, the percentage of 
hPSCs that differentiated into each germ layer was enhanced by 
∼10-fold for ectodermal differentiation, 60-fold for mesoder-
mal differentiation, and 2.5-fold for endodermal differentiation </p>

<p>(Fig. S4 C). At the time points assessed, differentiation rates 
of 40-75% were observed across all the germ layers after the 
PP1 treatment, roughly comparable to the differentiation rates 
observed for genetic suppression of Src (Fig. 5). Differences in 
these rates between the PP1 treatment and genetic suppression 
of Src could be due to variations in the potency of the treatments. 
To further evaluate how well stem cells differentiate into 
the three germ layers after the PP1 treatment, we used the 
highly quantitative PCR (qPCR)-based Scorecard assay as an 
assessment of lineage specification (Bock et al., 2011). Three 
published directed differentiation protocols were used to differ-
entiate hPSCs into representative populations of the ectodermal 
(dEC), mesodermal (dME), and endodermal (dEN) germ layers 
(Gifford et al., 2013; Fig. 6 A). The expression levels of a panel 
of genes specific to pluripotent stem cells and the three germ 
layers were measured in control and PP1-treated hPSCs and 
differentiated cultures. For most germ layer markers, higher ex-
pression levels were observed in PP1-treated differentiated cells 
compared with controls (Fig. 6 B). The mean expression across 
all ectodermal, mesodermal, and endodermal markers on the 
panel was also significantly higher in PP1-treated differentiated 
cells relative to controls (Fig. 6 B, right bars). These differences 
were generally not present in PP1-treated and control hPSCs 
before directed differentiation (Fig. S4 D). In comparison to a 
reference set of 14 other pluripotent stem cell lines, the PP1-
treated differentiated cells had a higher germ layer differentia-
tion potential than control samples (Fig. S4, E and F) and often 
had higher potential than other cell lines in the reference set. 
These results show that the PP1 treatment improves lin-
eage specification after directed differentiation by enhancing 
the expression of genes relevant for a given lineage. Together, 
these analyses show that the PP1 treatment improves the ca-
pacity for differentiation using six different induction protocols. 
Improvements in lineage specification would predict that 
the PP1 effects should persist to improve differentiation at sub-
sequent stages of differentiation. To evaluate the long-term ef-
fects of PP1, hPSCs were differentiated through a 15-d directed 
differentiation protocol into Pdx1+ pancreatic progenitor cells 
after the initial 24-h 25 µM PP1 treatment (Fig. 6 C). The PP1 
treatment of hPSCs increased the number of Pdx1+ cells by 
threefold, inducing a 70% differentiation rate (Fig. 6, D and E). 
The PP1-treated cells also continued to expand throughout the 
stages of the directed differentiation protocol (Fig. 6 F). Further 
differentiation of the PP1-treated hPSCs toward terminally dif-
ferentiated cells of the pancreatic lineage (Fig. S5 A) promoted 
differentiation into Nkx6.1+ and Ngn3+ endocrine cells as well 
as hormone-expressing C-peptide+ cells (Fig. S5 B). Thus, 
the increased differentiation efficiency after PP1 treatment is 
sustained throughout subsequent stages of differentiation and 
shows that the PP1 treatment is capable of driving hPSCs past 
the initial germ layers toward later stages of development. 
In prior work, we showed that pretreatment with DMSO 
at a concentration of 1-2% could significantly improve the dif-
ferentiation propensities of hPSCs (Chetty et al., 2013). We 
tested whether combining PP1 and DMSO could have benefi-
cial effects on hPSC differentiation. While combining the two 
treatments (25 µM PP1 with 2% DMSO) simultaneously com-
promised cell survival (unpublished data), sequential treatment 
with a lower concentration of DMSO (0.5%) had positive effects. 
After a 24-h treatment with 25 µM PP1, hPSCs were treated 
with 0.5% DMSO for 24 h and then cultured in differentiation 
media with Wnt3a and Activin A for 24 h (Fig. S5 C). This com-</p>

<p>Src regulates stem cell differentiation • Chetty et al. </p>



<p>Figure 5. Genetic suppression of Src regulates the activity of Rb and improves the differentiation capacity of hPSCs across all germ layers. (A) Western blot 
with Src-specific antibodies shows the levels of the Src protein after PP1 treatment of hPSCs. (B) Relative expression level of the Src gene in hPSCs transfected 
with Src siRNA compared with hPSCs transfected with nontargeting control siRNA. (C) Western blot with Src-specific antibodies shows the levels of the Src 
protein in hPSCs transfected with Src siRNA; phospho-specific antibodies show the levels of the indicated phosphorylated forms of Rb after transfection with 
Src siRNA. ppRb, hyperphosphorylated Rb. (D) Schematic of directed differentiation of hPSCs into Sox1+ ectodermal, Brachy+ mesodermal, or Sox17+ 
endodermal cells after transfection of hPSCs with control siRNA or Src siRNA. (E) Immunostaining for the indicated differentiation markers after directed 
differentiation in control and Src siRNA-transfected cultures. Bar, 200 µM. (F) Percentages of cells expressing the indicated differentiation markers in control 
and Src siRNA-transfected cultures. Error bars indicate SEM of 2-3 replicates. **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
bined treatment increased the percentage and absolute number 
of Brachy+ cells relative to cultures treated with PP1 alone in 
the HUES 6 line (Fig. 1 and Fig. S5, D-F). The combined treat-</p>

<p>ment increased the absolute yield of differentiated cells in other 
cell lines as well (Fig. S5 G). These findings indicate that op-
timizing the concentrations and timing of the DMSO and PP1 </p>

<p>Figure 6. PP1 treatment improves the specificity of differentiation of hPSCs. (A) Schematic of directed differentiation of HUES6 hPSCs into ectoderm (dEC, 
blue), mesoderm (dME, green), and endoderm (dEN, yellow) populations. (B) Difference in mean expression between PP1-treated and control samples, 
−∂CT = −(CT PP1 − CT C ONTROL ), for selected ectoderm (left), mesoderm (center), and endoderm (right) marker genes after directed differentiation into the three 
germ layers. All markers with −∂CT ≥ 1.9 or ≤ −1.9 are displayed, where −∂CT = 2 represents a fourfold increase in expression for PP1-treated versus 
control samples. The mean difference in expression for all ectoderm, mesoderm, and endoderm markers on the Scorecard panel (Life Technologies) is 
displayed as the rightmost bar. Error bars indicate standard deviation in difference in expression of two replicates. (C) Schematic of stepwise differentiation 
into pancreatic progenitor (PP1; Pdx1+) cells following a 15-d directed differentiation protocol after no treatment (control) or a 24-h 25 µM PP1 treatment. 
(D) Immunostaining for Pdx1 in control and PP1-treated cultures after directed differentiation. Bar, 200 µM. (E) Percentage of cells differentiating into Pdx1+ 
pancreatic progenitor cells in control and PP1-treated cultures. (F) Total cell numbers in control and PP1-treated cultures through the three stages of directed 
differentiation. Error bars indicate SEM of 4-6 replicates. ***, P ≤ 0.001. </p>

<p>Src regulates stem cell differentiation • Chetty et al. </p>



<p>treatments could provide further benefits for directed differen-
tiation. Using different doses of these two treatments at various 
stages of directed differentiation could also improve long-term 
differentiation potential and should be further explored. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In summary, the results show that a potent Src inhibitor, PP1, 
regulates the cell cycle and differentiation capacity of both 
human embryonic and iPSCs. A 24-h treatment with PP1 mod-
ulates the expression of genes involved in the G1 to S phase 
transition, enhances Rb activity, and increases the percent of 
cells in the early G1 phase of the cell cycle. After these effects, 
hPSCs respond more efficiently and effectively to various di-
rected differentiation protocols, leading to improvements in 
differentiation potentials across all germ layers. Genetic sup-
pression of Src in hPSCs similarly activates Rb and improves 
differentiation capacity, suggesting an important role for Src 
in controlling proliferation and differentiation. These early 
manipulations of the starting state of hPSCs increase the out-
put and specificity of differentiated cells at subsequent stages. 
The PP1 treatment enhances the yield of differentiated cells to 
80% even in cell lines that would otherwise have low differ-
entiation propensities. In cases where efficiencies are already 
high under control conditions, PP1 has no adverse effects. 
Thus, the effects are durable in that they extend beyond the 
initial germ layer specification. 
Our findings on the importance of the cell cycle mirror 
results in the literature on embryogenesis. In early develop-
ment as well as in pluripotent stem cells, a truncated cell cycle 
initially supports the amplification of cells (Smith, 2001; Or- ford and Scadden, 2008). However, the cell cycle then length-
ens as development progresses to incorporate gap phases and 
give cells the opportunity to become more specialized (Trel- stad et al., 1967; Hartwell and Weinert, 1989; Murray and  Kirschner, 1989; Frederick and Andrews, 1994; Edgar and  Lehner, 1996). Similarly, lengthening the truncated cell cycle 
of pluripotent stem cells through suppression of Src or small 
molecules such as PP1 may help direct their differentiation 
into specialized cell types. 
Few factors have been identified to date that effectively 
regulate the pluripotent cell cycle and directed differentiation 
(Smith, 2001; Orford and Scadden, 2008; Zhu et al., 2009;  Chetty et al., 2013; Li and Kirschner, 2014). PP1 has proven to 
be a potent tool to regulate the pluripotent G1 phase, as it en-
hances the hypophosphorylated state of Rb and enriches cells in 
the early G1 phase before directed differentiation. Our findings 
also support recent work suggesting that the G1 phase of the cell 
cycle may play an important role in enhancing the differentiation 
of hPSCs (Sela et al., 2012; Pauklin and Vallier, 2013; Singh et  al., 2013). Given its role in regulating Rb and the cell cycle, PP1 
could also be a useful tool in controlling the tumorigenicity of 
pluripotent stem cells and their differentiated progeny to enhance 
their therapeutic utility (Ben-David and Benvenisty, 2011). 
The robust impacts of the PP1 treatment and genetic sup-
pression of Src on hPSCs are consistent with prior work showing 
the importance of Src tyrosine kinase activity in regulating cell 
proliferation in early development (Trelstad et al., 1967; Freder- ick and Andrews, 1994). In addition, with the evolution of mul-
ticellular organisms, a negative regulation of Src was acquired 
that proved to be critical for interactions and communications </p>

<p>between cells (Segawa et al., 2006). Src inhibition may simi-
larly play an important regulatory role as a single cell undergoes 
cell division into a multicellular organism in early development. 
More broadly, this study shows that the PP1 treatment 
alters the "starting state" of hPSCs to be more amenable to di-
rected differentiation. Manipulating this starting state, whether 
through PP1, direct inhibition of Src, or other tools, increases 
the utility of pluripotent stem cells. Studying how this state re-
lates to the recently established primitive "reset" state of hPSCs 
(Takashima et al., 2014) could provide further mechanistic in-
sights into how various pluripotent states control cell fate deci-
sions and the developmental potential of pluripotent stem cells. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>hPSC maintenance conditions </p>

<p>All hPSC cultures were maintained at 37°C, 5% CO 2 and grown on a 
monolayer of irradiated CF1 mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs; Glo-
balStem) in hPSC medium consisting of KO-DMEM (Invitrogen), 10% 
KOSR (Invitrogen), 1% GlutaMAX, nonessential amino acids, peni-
cillin/streptomycin, and 0.1% β-mercaptoethanol supplemented with 
10 ng/ml bFGF (Invitrogen). Medium was changed every 24 h, and 
lines were passaged using TrypLE (Invitrogen). Before differentiation 
experiments, cells were expanded for at least two passages on Matrigel 
(BD) in mTeSR (STE MCELL Technologies) with 10 µM of ROCK 
inhibitor Y-27632 (Abcam). 
The HUES cell lines (HUES6, HUES8, HUES49, and H9;  Cowan et al., 2004; Osafune et al., 2008) and the iPSC line (iPSC11b; 
Boulting et al., 2011) were used in this study. 
siRNA transfection. Src siRNA (s13414, Life Technologies; Chr. 
20: 35973088-36033821) and nontargeting control siRNA (4390843; 
Life Technologies) were transfected into hPSCs plated onto Matri-
gel-coated plates at 70% confluence. Cells were transfected with either 
control siRNA (50 pmol) or Src siRNA (50 pmol) using Lipofectamine 
RNAimax transfection reagent (Invitrogen), according to the manufac-
turer's instructions. Cells were subsequently either differentiated or 
collected for analysis 24 h after transfection. </p>

<p>Differentiation protocols </p>

<p>For all differentiation studies, hPSCs were plated onto wells coated with 
growth factor-reduced Matrigel (BD) in mTeSR with 10 µM ROCK 
inhibitor Y-27632. Cells were plated at a density of 1-2 million per 
well of a six-well plate or 100,000-200,000 per well of a 96-well plate. 
24 h before the onset of differentiation, cells were cultured in mTeSR 
with inhibitor treatment. Inhibitor medium was removed after 24 h and 
replaced with differentiation-inducing media at the start of each differ-
entiation, with replacement of medium every day in all protocols. 
Treatments in this study include PP1 (Thermo Fisher Scien-
tific), PP2 (Tocris Bioscience), 1-Naphthyl PP1 (Tocris Bioscience), 
Saracatinib (Thermo Fisher Scientific), Bosutinib (Sigma-Aldrich), 
K252a (Sigma-Aldrich), N-[(2R)-2,3-Dihydroxypropoxy]-3,4-diflu-
oro-2-[(2-fluoro-4-iodophenyl)amino]-benzamide (Stemgent), Ros-
covitine (Sigma-Aldrich), CDK2 inhibitor (EMD Millipore), and 
Palbociclib HCl (Selleck Chemicals) at dosages of 1 µM, 5 µM, 10 µM, 
25 µM, 40 µM, and 50 µM for 24 h. 
To induce differentiation into the ectodermal, mesodermal, and 
endodermal germ layers and pancreatic endocrine lineage, cells were 
directly differentiated as follows. 
Ectoderm. Cells were cultured in KO-DMEM (Invitrogen) 
medium containing 10% knockout serum replacement (Invitrogen) 
and supplemented with Noggin (500 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems) and </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>

<p>
4-[4-(1,3-benzodioxol-5-yl)-5-(2-pyridinyl)-1H-imidazol-2-yl]ben-
zamide (10 µM; Tocris) for 3-4 d. 
Mesoderm. Cells were cultured in Advanced RPMI 1640 (re-
duced serum; Invitrogen) or RPMI 1640 medium (Invitrogen) supple-
mented with human recombinant AA (100 ng/ml) + Wnt3a (20 ng/ml; 
R&amp;D Systems) for 1 d. 
Endoderm. Cells were cultured in MCDB-131 medium (Invitro-
gen) supplemented with NaHCO 3 (2.5 g/liter), 1% GlutaMAX, glucose 
(5.5 mM), 0.1% FAF-BSA (Proliant/Lampire), and ITS:X (1:50,000; 
Invitrogen), and treated with Wnt3a (20 ng/ml) + AA (100 ng/ml) for 1 
d and then AA (100 ng/ml) for 3 d. 
Pancreatic endocrine differentiation. Cells were cultured in 
MCDB-131 medium supplemented with NaHCO 3 (2.5 g/liter), 1% 
GlutaMAX, glucose (5.5 mM), 0.1% FAF-BSA, and ITS:X (1:50,000), 
and were treated with Wnt3a (20 ng/ml) + AA (100 ng/ml) for 1 d, 
AA (100 ng/ml) for 3 d, and FGF7 (50 ng/ml; PeproTech) for 2 d. For 
further endocrine differentiation, cells were cultured in MCDB-131 
medium supplemented with NaHCO 3 (2.5 g/liter), 1% GlutaMAX, 
glucose (8 mM), 2% FAF-BSA, and ITS:X (1:200), and treated for 4 
d with FGF7 (50 ng/ml) + noggin (100 ng/ml) + retinoic acid (2 µM; 
Sigma-Aldrich) + SANT-1 (0.25 µM; Sigma-Aldrich) + AA (20 ng/ 
ml); for 3 d with SANT-1 (0.25 µM) + PdBu (200 nM; EMD) + noggin 
(100 ng/ml); and for 4-6 d with noggin (100 ng/ml) + Alk5 inhibitor 
(1 µM; Axxora). 
Directed differentiations for the scorecard analyses were performed 
using the following previously published protocols (Gifford et al., 2013). 
Ectoderm. Ectoderm differentiation was induced using A83-01 
(2 µm; Tocris Bioscience), PNU 74654 (2 µm; Tocris Bioscience), Dor-
somorphin (2 µm; Tocris Bioscience), and DMEM/F12 (Life Technolo-
gies) containing 15% knockout serum replacement (Life Technologies) 
for 4 d. 
Mesoderm. Mesoderm differentiation was induced in DMEM/ 
F12 (Life Technologies) and 0.5% FBS (HyClone; GE Healthcare), 
with Activin A (100 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems) for 1 d, and subsequently 
induced with BMP4 (100 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems), VEGF (100 ng/ml; 
R&amp;D Systems), and FGF2 (20 ng/ml; Millipore) for 3 d. 
Endoderm. Endoderm differentiation was induced in Advanced 
RPMI (Invitrogen) and 0.5% FBS (HyClone), with Activin A (100 ng/ 
ml; R&amp;D Systems) and LiCl (2 µg/ml; R&amp;D Systems) for 4 d. </p>

<p>Immunocytochemistry and quantification </p>

<p>Cells were rinsed in PBS and fixed in 4% PFA (Sigma-Aldrich) for 30 
min. After the rinses, cells were blocked for 1 h at room temperature 
in 5% donkey serum (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Inc.) 
and 0.3% Triton X-100 in PBS. All primary antibody incubations were 
done overnight at 4°C in blocking solution at a 1:500 dilution unless 
otherwise noted. Primary antibodies used in this study were: Oct4 
(mouse; R&amp;D Systems), Sox1 (goat; R&amp;D Systems), Pax6 (rabbit; Co-
vance), Brachyury (goat; R&amp;D Systems), Sox17 (goat; R&amp;D Systems), 
Pdx1 (goat; R&amp;D Systems), Nkx6.1 (mouse; University of Iowa, De-
velopmental Hybridoma Bank), Ngn3 (sheep; R&amp;D Systems), C-pep-
tide (rat; Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank), pRb 780 (1:350; 
Rb phosphorylation at Ser780; rabbit; Cell Signaling Technology), and 
underphosphorylated Rb (1:100; mouse; BD). Cells were rinsed the 
next day, followed by secondary antibody incubation for 1 h at room 
temperature at a 1:500 dilution. Secondary antibodies (Invitrogen) con-
jugated to Alexa Fluor 488 or 594 were used to visualize primary an-
tibodies. After PBS rinses, all nuclei were visualized by staining with 
Hoechst 33342 (1:1,000; Invitrogen). 
Image acquisition and quantification. Immunofluorescent im-
ages were taken using a microscope (Observer.D1; Carl Zeiss) using 
an LD A-Plan 10×/0.25 NA Ph1 M27 objective lens with the DAPI, </p>

<p>GFP, or Texas red fluorochromes. Cells were imaged in PBS at room 
temperature, and images were acquired using the microscopy camera 
Axiom 503 mono(D) with the acquisition software <rs id="software-1" type="software">AxioVision Rel</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.7</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Carl Zeiss</rs>). For quantification analyses, 30 10× fields per well were 
acquired and quantified using a high-content screening system (Array-
Scan VTI; Cellomics Technology). Cells labeled by antibody staining 
and total cell number (based on DAPI nuclei staining) were quantified 
to obtain percentages of target cell types. </p>

<p>Flow cytometry </p>

<p>For intracellular antibody staining, cells were fixed in 4% PFA for 20 
min at 4°C followed by two PBS washes. Cells were resuspended in 
blocking solution consisting of 5% donkey serum and 0.3% Triton 
X-100 in PBS. Cells were then incubated for 30 min at 4°C with pri-
mary antibody RbAP46/48 (1:500; rabbit; Active Motif North Amer-
ica) or Ki67 (1:500; rabbit; Abcam) and washed twice in PBS. Last, 
cells were incubated with secondary antibody donkey anti-rabbit Alexa 
Fluor 594 (1:500; Invitrogen) for 30 min at 4°C and washed twice be-
fore assessment on a flow cytometer (LSR II FACS; BD) and analysis 
using the FlowJo software. </p>

<p>Annexin V-propidium iodide staining </p>

<p>Cells were harvested with TrypLE Express (Invitrogen), washed with 
cold PBS, and resuspended with annexin-binding buffer (50 mM Hepes, 
700 mM NaCl, and 12.5 mM CaCl 2 , pH 7.4) to a final concentration of 
10 6 cells/ml. 5 µl of Annexin V Alexa Fluor 488 conjugate (Molecular 
Probes) and 1 µl of 100 µg/ml propidium iodide (Molecular Probes) 
were added per 100 µl of cell suspension. After 15 min of incubation 
at room temperature, 400 µl of annexin-binding buffer was added per 
100 µl of cell suspension. Samples were mixed gently and left on ice 
until analysis. Cells were assessed with a flow cytometer (LSR II FACS; 
BD) and analyzed using FlowJo software. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>Cells were lysed using the RIPA lysis buffer (Santa Cruz Biotech-
nology, Inc.). Proteins were separated by 7.5% SDS-PAGE (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories) and transferred to nitrocellulose membranes (Bio-Rad 
Laboratories). The membranes were blocked in 3% BSA in 0.1% 
Tween 20 TBS for 1 h at room temperature and then incubated with the 
following primary antibodies overnight at 4°C: Src (47405; 1:1,000; 
rabbit; Abcam), Src (16885; 1:1,000; mouse; Abcam), ppRb (G3-245; 
1:1,000; mouse; BD), underphosphorylated Rb (G99-549; 1:1,000; 
mouse; BD), or GAP DH (MAB374; 1:1,000; mouse; Millipore) as the 
loading control. After washing, the membranes were incubated with 
secondary antibodies for 1 h at room temperature: anti-mouse HRP 
(1:3,000; Cell Signaling Technology) or anti-rabbit HRP (1:5,000; Cell 
Signaling Technology), and then incubated in chemiluminescent HRP 
substrate (Millipore) for signal detection and development. </p>

<p>RNA isolation and gene expression analyses by real-time PCR </p>

<p>Total RNAs were isolated from purified cells of untreated and PP1-
treated hPSCs using the RNeasy mini kit (QIA GEN) and reverse 
transcribed using Superscript III RT (Invitrogen), according to the man-
ufacturer's instructions. Real-time qPCR reactions were analyzed with 
a Mastercycler realplex 4 Sequence Detector (Eppendorf) via SYBR 
green (QuantitectTM SYBR Green PCR kit; QIA GEN). The relative 
gene expression level of each sample was expressed as a relative quan-
titation (RQ) value determined by the 2 − ddCT method that represents 
the fold change in gene expression normalized to the housekeeping 
gene, GAP DH. The relative gene expression level of each sample was 
also compared with an internal control, i.e., untreated hPSCs. Comple-
mentary DNA PCR primer sequences are shown in Table S1. </p>

<p>Src regulates stem cell differentiation • Chetty et al. </p>



<p>qPCR and Scorecard analysis </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted from frozen cell pellets using Ambion Pure 
Link RNA Mini kit (Life Technologies). Eight cDNA reactions were 
set up from 1 µg of total RNA per sample using a High-Capacity cDNA 
RT kit (Life Technologies). qPCR was performed on 384-well TaqMan 
hPSC Scorecard plates using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Viia7 RUO</rs> software and a ViiA7 instru-
ment (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Applied Biosystems</rs>). Data were normalized to the mean expres-
sion level of five control genes that are highly invariant in expression 
during directed differentiation. Differentiation potential was calculated 
(Bock et al., 2011) for four gene classes (EC, ectoderm; ME, meso-
derm; EN, endoderm; PP, pluripotent). </p>

<p>Cell cycle analysis </p>

<p>Cells were trypsinized and fixed in 4% PFA for 20 min on ice and 
stained with Hoechst 33342 (5 µg/ml; Invitrogen) in PBS for 30 min. 
Equal numbers of cells were assessed for each cell line on a flow cy-
tometer (LSR II FACS; BD) and analyzed using FlowJo software. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>For statistical comparisons, mean values of two or more independent 
experiments were subjected to unpaired two-tailed Student's t tests. 
P-values ≤0.05 were considered significant. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material </p>

<p>Fig. S1 shows cell viability after the PP1 treatment. Fig. S2 shows how 
various cell cycle inhibitors regulate the differentiation potential of 
hPSCs. Fig. S3 shows the cell cycle profiles of several cell lines after 
the PP1 treatment. Fig. S4 shows how PP1 enhances the differentiation 
potential across all germ layers using various directed differentiation 
protocols. Fig. S5 shows that the initial PP1 treatment has positive im-
pacts on terminal differentiation and provides benefits on differentiation 
capacity when combined with a DMSO treatment. Table S1 includes 
primer sequences used in the study. Online supplemental material is 
available at http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.201502035/DC1. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Lydia Gold, Veronika Akopian, and Ameen Chaudry for 
their excellent technical support, and Barak Blum, Jose Rivera-Feli-
ciano, and Kristin Narayan for their helpful feedback on the manu-
script. We also thank the Flow Cytometry Core facilities for 
their assistance. </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from the Harvard Stem Cell Insti-
tute, the US National Institutes of Health (1R24DK092758 and 
1U01HL10040804), and the Leona M. and Harry B. Helmsley 
Charitable Trust. </p>

<p>The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 9 February 2015 
Accepted: 20 August 2015 </p>



<p>JCB • VOLUME 210 • NUMBER 7 • 2015 </p>



<p>
</p></text></tei>