<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4408226" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Skin permeability is widely considered to be mechanistically implicated in chemically-induced 
skin sensitization. Although many chemicals have been identified as skin sensitizers, there have 
been very few reports analyzing the relationships between molecular structure and skin 
permeability of sensitizers and non-sensitizers. The goals of this study were to: (i) compile, curate, 
and integrate the largest publicly available dataset of chemicals studied for their skin permeability; 
(ii) develop and rigorously validate QSAR models to predict skin permeability; and (iii) explore 
the complex relationships between skin sensitization and skin permeability. Based on the largest 
publicly available dataset compiled in this study, we found no overall correlation between skin 
permeability and skin sensitization. In addition, cross-species correlation coefficient between 
human and rodent permeability data was found to be as low as R 2 =0.44. Human skin permeability 
models based on the random forest method have been developed and validated using OECD-
compliant QSAR modeling workflow. Their external accuracy was high (Q 2 ext = 0.73 for 63% of 
external compounds inside the applicability domain). The extended analysis using both 
experimentally-measured and QSAR-imputed data still confirmed the absence of any overall </p>

<p>concordance between skin permeability and skin sensitization. This observation suggests that 
chemical modifications that affect skin permeability should not be presumed a priori to modulate 
the sensitization potential of chemicals. The models reported herein as well as those developed in 
the companion paper on skin sensitization suggest that it may be possible to rationally design 
compounds with the desired high skin permeability but low sensitization potential. </p>

<p>Skin sensitization is a complex adverse toxicological endpoint that is influenced by several 
biological parameters, such as protein binding, dendritic cell activation, individual variation, 
and time-dose exposure (Jaworska et al., 2011; Johansen et al., 2011). Skin permeability is 
also often considered as a potential parameter affecting chemicals' sensitization potential 
(MacKay et al., 2013). It relates to the ability of a molecule to pass through the skin, a 
characteristic which is primarily influenced by the physicochemical properties of the 
chemical as well as the physicochemical and biological properties of the membrane (Xia, 
2011). </p>

<p>Despite the high importance of skin permeability for consumer product efficacy and its 
supposed influence on potential toxicities such as skin sensitization, the amount of 
experimental data available in the public domain is surprisingly limited. In the early 90's, a 
compilation of data points for skin permeability gathered from several sources was 
published (Flynn, 1990). Subsequent studies added some complementary data allowing 
researchers to develop Quantitative Structure-Activity Relationship (QSAR) models for 
predicting skin permeability. However, as shown in Table S1, most of the published studies 
reporting on skin permeability modeling (Abraham et al., 1999; Barratt, 1995; Berge, 2009; 
Chen et al., 2010, 2007; Cronin et al., 1999; Hostýnek and Magee, 1997; Lien and Gao, 
1995; Magnusson et al., 2004; Moss and Cronin, 2002; Moss et al., 2011; Patel et al., 2002; 
Potts and Guy, 1995, 1992) have not included certain critical elements of QSAR model 
development and validation protocol, such as the definition of the applicability domain (AD) 
or proof of passing the Y-randomization test, which constitute best practices of QSAR 
modeling (OECD, 2004; Tropsha, 2010). Recently, several QSAR studies were 
benchmarked on a series of 11 compounds and all of them failed to predict skin permeation 
quantitatively; they were only able to rank permeants (Brown et al., 2012). Another recent 
study showed that most of the available QSAR models underestimate the skin permeability 
of hydrophilic solutes (Chen et al., 2013). Recent studies (Chauhan and Shakya, 2010) 
attempted to overcome the related problems with complex chemical mixtures and built a 
QSAR model based on several mixtures of 36 chemicals with porcine skin data. The latter 
model followed the best practices of QSAR modeling (Tropsha, 2010); however, we have 
identified 21 duplicative structures in that dataset (see Table S3) indicating a potential bias 
of the model and a likely over-estimation of its true performance. </p>

<p>Alves et al. 
Page 2 </p>

<p>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Despite the underlying importance of skin permeability and its identification as a necessary 
step in the OECD Adverse Outcome Pathway (AOP) for skin sensitization (Karlberg et al., 
2008; OECD, 2012), we could not find any study among those compiled in Tables S1 and 
S2, where both endpoints were analyzed concurrently and in the context of their possible 
inter-dependency. The prevalence of dermal exposure to diverse chemicals in consumer 
products and in the environment, the importance of permeability for skin sensitization, and 
the lack of reliable models to predict these endpoints for new chemicals have motivated us 
to initiate a tandem study on collecting and analyzing both skin permeability and skin 
sensitization data. In the companion paper (Alves et al., 2014), we have reported on new 
QSAR models of skin sensitization. In this study, we have compiled, curated, and integrated 
skin permeability coefficient (Kp) data extracted from various literature sources. Using this 
unique data collection, we have developed and rigorously validated QSAR models for skin 
permeability, and explored the relationships between the skin sensitization potential and the 
chemical permeability coefficient. The QSAR models developed in this and the 
accompanying study (Alves et al., 2014) are publicly available and can be used for 
evaluating chemically induced skin effects in silico as part of both research and development 
projects as well as in support of regulatory decisions on consumer products. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Datasets </p>

<p>Skin sensitization datasets (datasets A and B)-In the Part I of this study (Alves et 
al., 2014) we described two skin sensitization datasets. Briefly, one of them (dataset A) was 
retrieved from the ICCVAM (Interagency Coordinating Committee on the Validation of 
Alternative Methods) report on the murine reduced local lymph node assay (ICCVAM 
2009). The modeling set (Dataset A) consisted of 254 compounds (127 sensitizers and 127 
non-sensitizers) and the external validation set (dataset B) consisted of 133 sensitizers from 
the ICCVAM report (ICCVAM 2009) and 18 additional compounds taken from the study of 
Jaworska et al. (2011). This collection of data was used to explore the intrinsic relationship 
between skin sensitization and skin permeability (human data from dataset D; see below) for 
a subset of 20 compounds from the same dataset for which both skin sensitization and skin 
permeability data were known. </p>

<p>Human skin permeability dataset (dataset D)-In vitro human skin permeability 
coefficients were retrieved from the literature (Chauhan and Shakya, 2010) including 211 
records expressed in logKp (cm.h −1 ); this dataset contained the well-known and frequently 
studied Flynn dataset (Flynn, 1990). 17 duplicates and two sets of triplicates were identified 
and curated leaving unique compounds only. Three additional compounds and water were 
also removed for the following reasons: both styrene (logKp = −0.19) and ethyl benzene 
(logKp = 0.08) were identified as activity outliers (i.e., their logKp values were far outside 
the activity range of the other compounds in the dataset between −5.52 and −0.69) whereas 
digitoxin (natural product) was a structural outlier. The remaining 186 compounds (dataset 
D) were retained for modeling. </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Rodent dataset (dataset E)-The set of in vitro rodent skin permeability data consisting 
of 103 chemical compounds was retrieved from the literature (Moss et al., 2011). After 
curation, 96 compounds (dataset E) were kept for modeling. The following five activity 
outliers were removed from the dataset E: bisphenol A diglycidyl ether (−5.26), 
decabromodiphenyl oxide (−5.15), 4-N butylamine (−0.64), bufexamac (−0.57), and 
triclosan (0.13). The overall range of logKp for the final dataset varied from −4.85 to −0.94. </p>

<p>Data curation </p>

<p>Chemical structures were retrieved either from PubChem (https:// 
pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/, accessed in March 2012) or ChemSpider (http:// 
www.chemspider.com/, accessed in March 2012) databases using chemical names. 
Chemicals were removed if their structures could not be found. Each dataset was carefully 
curated according to previously established guidelines (Fourches et al., 2010). Briefly, 
counterions were removed, whereas specific chemotypes such as aromatic and nitro groups 
were normalized using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">ChemAxon Standardizer</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">v.5.3</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">ChemAxon Budapest, Hungary</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://www.chemaxon.com</rs>). The presence of duplicates, i.e., identical compounds reported 
more than once in the same dataset, is known to lead to over-optimistic estimations of the 
predictivity for developed QSAR models. However, the analysis of such records also gives 
an estimate of the dataset quality: if activity data for the same compound are consistent, the 
overall data quality is high; if there is a large deviation in experimental values between 
different records of the same compound, the quality is, obviously, low. Thus, after the 
structural standardization, the duplicates were identified using <rs type="software">ISIDA Duplicates</rs> (Varnek et 
al., 2008) and <rs type="software">HiT QSAR</rs> (Kuz'min et al., 2008) software and carefully analyzed. If the 
experimental properties associated with two duplicative structures were identical, or highly 
similar, then one compound was chosen at random and deleted. However, if their 
experimental properties were significantly different, we deleted both records from the 
dataset. During the curation of human skin permeability dataset, we found 17 pairs of 
duplicate structures and two sets of triplicates as shown in Table S3. The permeability 
values for duplicative records were almost identical (logKp variation ~ 0.01 LU) except 
those for butanoic acid that had a variation higher than ca. 0.4 LU. Thus, the LogKp value 
for all 17 compounds was averaged and the duplicative records were removed so that only 
one permeability coefficient was used for a chemical compound. </p>

<p>Cheminformatics Approaches </p>

<p>Hierarchical Cluster Analysis-The clustering of a chemical dataset consists of 
merging compounds into distinct clusters of chemically similar molecules [see (Downs and 
Barnard, 2003; Mercier, 2003) for a review of the most popular clustering approaches used 
in computational chemistry]. In this study, we have employed the Sequential Agglomerative 
Hierarchical Non-overlapping (SAHN) method implemented in the <rs id="software-3" type="software">ISIDA/Cluster</rs> program 
(<rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://infochim.u-strasbg.fr.</rs>) (Varnek et al., 2007). Briefly, each compound represents one 
cluster at the start. Then, the m compounds are merged iteratively into clusters using their 
pairwise Euclidean distances stored in a squared (m * m) symmetric distance matrix. The 
two closest objects (molecules or clusters) are iteratively identified and merged to form a 
new cluster, the distance matrix being updated with the re-computed distances separating the 
newly formed cluster and the others, according to the user-specified type of linkage </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>(complete linkage in this study). The process is repeated until one cluster remains. The 
parent-child relationships between clusters result in a hierarchical data representation, or 
dendrogram. In particular, we used <rs type="software">ISIDA/Cluster</rs> to obtain the heat map (see Results 
section) of the proximity matrix. </p>

<p>Dragon Descriptors-The following types of descriptors were generated using <rs id="software-5" type="software">Dragon 
software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">v.5.5.</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Talete SRL, Milan, Italy</rs>): 0D constitutional (atom and group counts), 1D 
functional groups, 1D atom-centered fragments, 2D topological descriptors, 2D walk and 
path counts, 2D autocorrelations, 2D connectivity indices, 2D information indices, 2D 
topological charge indices, 2D eigenvalue-based indices, 2D topological descriptors, 2D 
edge-adjacency indices, 2D Burden eigenvalues, 2D binary fingerprints, 2D frequency 
fingerprints, and molecular properties. The detailed discussion for these descriptors can be 
found elsewhere (Todeschini and Consonni, 2000). </p>

<p>SiRMS Descriptors-2D Simplex Representation of Molecular Structure (SiRMS) 
descriptors (Muratov et al., 2010) (representing numbers of unique tetratomic fragments 
with fixed composition and topological structure) were generated by the <rs type="software">HiT QSAR</rs> 
software (Kuz'min et al., 2008). At the 2D level, the connectivity of atoms in a simplex, 
atom type, and bond nature (single, double, triple, or aromatic) have been considered. 
SiRMS descriptors account not only for the atom type, but also for other atomic 
characteristics that may impact biological activity of molecules, e.g., partial charge, 
lipophilicity, refraction, and an atom ability for being a donor/acceptor in hydrogen-bond 
formation (H-bond). For atom characteristics with continuous values (charge, lipophilicity, 
and refraction) the division of the entire value range into definite discrete groups has been 
carried out. The atoms have been divided into four groups corresponding to their (i) partial 
charge A≤−0.05&lt;B≤0&lt;C≤0.05&lt;D, (ii) lipophilicity A≤−0.5&lt;B≤0&lt;C≤0.5&lt;D, and (iii) 
refraction A≤1.5&lt;B≤3&lt;C≤8&lt;D. For H-bond characteristic, the atoms have been divided into 
three groups: A (acceptor of hydrogen in H-bond), D (donor of hydrogen in H-bond), and I 
(indifferent atom). The usage of sundry variants of differentiation of simplex vertexes 
(atoms) represents the principal feature of the SiRMS approach (Kuz'min et al., 2007). 
Detailed description of <rs type="software">HiT QSAR</rs> and SiRMS can be found elsewhere (Kuz'min et al., 
2008; Muratov et al., 2010). </p>

<p>QSAR modeling-The QSAR modeling workflow used in this study includes three major 
steps (Tropsha and Golbraikh, 2007; Tropsha, 2010): (i) data curation/preparation/analysis 
(selection of compounds and descriptors), (ii) model building, and (iii) model validation/ 
selection. Here we followed a 5-fold external cross-validation procedure: the full set of 
compounds with known experimental activity is randomly divided into five subsets of equal 
size; then one of these subsets (20% of all compounds) is set aside as an external validation 
set and the remaining four sets together form the modeling set (80% of the full set). This 
procedure is repeated five times allowing each of the five subsets to be used as external 
validation set. Models are built using the modeling set only, and it is important to emphasize 
that the compounds in corresponding external set (fold) are never employed either to build 
and/or select the models. Each modeling set is divided into many internal training and test 
sets; then models are built using compounds of each training set and applied to test set </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>compounds to assess their properties. The statistical metrics used to assess different aspects 
of model performance are available in the Supplementary Materials. </p>

<p>Best models were identified and selected according to acceptable threshold values (&gt; 0.6) of </p>

<p>for the internal test sets (called out-of-bag set in Random Forest, vide infra). Then, 
selected models were applied to the external set compounds to predict their skin 
sensitization potential. This procedure was repeated five times to ensure that every 
compound was present once and only once in the corresponding external test set. Since the 
accuracy of each model is estimated only based on external set compounds, which are never 
used to derive, bias, or select models, this protocol ensures an objective estimation of the 
true external predictivity of the models. In addition, 1,000 rounds of Y-randomization were 
performed for each dataset to assure that the high accuracy of the models built with real data 
was not due to chance correlations. </p>

<p>Random Forest-Random Forest models were constructed according to the original RF 
algorithm (Breiman, 2001) using the <rs id="software-8" type="software">CF software</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">version 2.12</rs> (Polishchuk et al., 2009). RF 
is an ensemble of single decision trees. Outputs of all trees are aggregated to obtain one final 
prediction. Each tree is grown as follows: (i) a bootstrap sample is produced from the whole 
set of N compounds to form a training set for the current tree. Compounds that are not in the 
training set of the current tree are placed in the out-of-bag (OOB) set (size of ~ N/3); (ii) the 
best split by CART algorithm (Breiman et al., 1984) among the m randomly selected 
descriptors from the entire pool in each node is chosen; (iii) each tree is then grown to the 
largest possible extent; there is no pruning. The predicted classification values are defined 
by majority voting for one of the classes. Thus, each tree predicts values for only those 
compounds that are not included in the training set of that tree (for OOB set only). Since RF 
possesses its own reliable statistical characteristics (based on OOB set prediction) which 
could be used for validation and model selection, no cross-validation was performed 
(Breiman, 2001). Thus, the final model is chosen by the lowest error for prediction of the 
OOB set. The local (tree) applicability domain approach (Artemenko et al., 2011) was used 
for all RF models developed in this study. </p>

<p>DERMWIN-The <rs id="software-9" type="software">Dermal Permeability Coefficient Program (DERMWIN</rs>) is a module 
available in the EPI Suite package developed by the <rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">EPA’s Office of Pollution Prevention Toxics and Syracuse Research Corporation.</rs> and available at <rs corresp="#software-9" type="url">http://www.epa.gov/oppt/ exposure/pubs/episuitedl.htm.</rs>. The <rs id="software-10" type="software">DERMWIN</rs> <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-number">v.2.02</rs> estimates chemicals' dermal 
permeability coefficient using the following equation 1 (USEPA, 2004): </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>where K o/w is the octanol/water partition coefficient and MW is the molecular weight of the 
chemical. Human skin permeability dataset (dataset D) was imported to <rs type="software">DERMWIN</rs> as 
SMILES strings, and logKp was calculated and compared to the predictions of our models. </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Relationship between human and rodent skin permeability coefficients </p>

<p>First, we searched for the subset of chemicals that had both human and rodent skin 
permeability data available to verify whether we could increase the dataset size by merging 
these data. We found 34 compounds that have both human and rodent experimental data. As 
is obvious from Figure 1, the correlation between human and rodent data was not high 
enough to merge these datasets. </p>

<p>A linear regression of the logKp values yielded R 2 =0.44 only. Therefore, we decided that 
the data for humans and rodents were definitely not compatible and built species-specific 
QSAR models. Human-based and rodent-based QSAR models for skin permeability were 
developed using the same protocol used for skin sensitization as described in the companion 
paper (Alves et al., 2014). The results (Table 1) suggest that continuous models for both 
datasets afforded high predictive accuracy as estimated by Q 2 ext values. However, the 
quality and coverage of human-based models 12 and 14 were higher than the same 
characteristics of the best rodent-based model 21. Thus, models 12 and 14 were retained for 
in silico screening of chemical libraries of concern to identify potential human skin 
sensitizers. Additional statistical characteristics of the models are present in Supplementary 
Materials (Table S2). </p>

<p>Relationship between skin sensitization and permeability </p>

<p>We have explored whether there are intrinsic relationships between skin sensitization and 
skin permeability of chemicals. Since rodent data did not correlate well with human data, 
only human skin permeability data were employed for this analysis. We identified a subset 
of 20 compounds for which both skin sensitization and skin permeability data were known. 
These experimental data were compiled from several studies (Chauhan and Shakya, 2010; 
ICCVAM, 2009; Jaworska et al., 2011). As shown in Table 2, there is no direct relationship 
between the two endpoints. The ranges of logKp values for sensitizers (logKp = −3.62 -
−1.28) vs. non-sensitizers (logKp = −3.05 -−1.6) confirm this finding. For instance, five 
non-sensitizers have low permeability coefficient while logKp values for two other non-
sensitizers are high. There is a common understanding that a chemical should penetrate the 
skin to cause sensitization (penetration is generally regarded as the first step in the skin 
sensitization AOP (Karlberg et al., 2008; OECD, 2012)). However, we found examples 
when a relatively weak penetrant can still be a strong sensitizer (e.g., p-Phenylenediamine, 
logKp = −3.62), whereas a strong penetrant, can be a non-sensitizer (e.g., octanoic acid, 
logKp = −1.60). This observation suggests that skin permeability and skin sensitization are 
generally decoupled processes and therefore it may be possible to modify chemicals such as 
to affect permeability without affecting sensitization, and vice versa. </p>

<p>Cluster analysis of human skin permeability dataset </p>

<p>We have performed a cluster analysis of the human skin permeability set (dataset D) 
following the same method used for the skin sensitization dataset A (part I in (Alves et al., 
2014)). Due to the poor concordance between human and rodent data, and a heightened 
interest in human skin permeability data, this analysis was only conducted using dataset D. </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>As illustrated in Figure 2, the dendrogram for the dataset D is not as extensive as for skin 
sensitization dataset A (Alves et al., 2014), i.e., compounds in the skin penetration dataset D 
are more structurally similar than those in the skin sensitization dataset A. Short-chain 
alcohols have similar logKp values (ca. −3.0) except for ethylene glycol (logKp = −4.07). 
For glycol ethers with short carbon chains (cluster b in Figure 2), the decrease of 
permeability is likely related to the chain length (2-(2-methoxyethoxy)ethanol (logKp= 
−3.69) &lt; 2-(2-ethoxyethoxy)ethanol (logKp= −3.88) &lt; 2-(2-butoxyethoxy)ethanol) (logKp= 
−4.45). To confirm this tendency, we have calculated permeability for two additional glycol 
ethers. We found that 2-(2-propoxyethoxy)ethanol (logKp pred = −4.05), which had an 
logKppred intermediary between 2-(2-ethoxyethoxy)ethanol and 2-(2-butoxyethoxy)ethanol, 
followed the trend but our predictions indicated a slight increase in permeability for 2-(2-
(pentyloxy)ethoxy)ethanol (logKp pred = −3.95). Then, with further increase of the chain 
length, this effect reached saturation resulting in a highly similar permeability for the next 
three compounds: 2-(2-(hexyloxy)ethoxy)ethanol (logKp pred = −3.88), 2-(2-
(heptyloxy)ethoxy)ethanol (logKp pred = −3.87), and 2-(2-(octyloxy)ethoxy)ethanol 
(logKp pred −3.89). Two compounds, 2-(2-(nonyloxy)ethoxy)ethanol and 2-(2-
(decyloxy)ethoxy)ethanol were outside of the AD for the consensus model 5. </p>

<p>As a result of cluster analysis, we found three compounds that had different activity 
annotations from the rest of the cluster members and were therefore suspicious. These 
compounds included a barbiturate (amylobarbital) and two steroid derivatives of 
hydrocortisone (hydrocortisone methylsuccinate, and hydrocortisone succinamate). Our 
procedure for evaluating suspicious compounds was based on the permeability prediction for 
these compounds using developed models and a search for additional experimental data to 
verify their human skin permeability coefficients. Unfortunately, we were unable to find any 
confirmatory data in the literature to prove or refute the values of permeability coefficients 
for these substances. According to our consensus model 5, amylobarbital had a predicted 
logKp = −3.56 (experimental logKp= −2.64) similar to other barbitals: barbital (logKp = 
−3.95), phenobarbital (logKp = −3.34), and butobarbital (logKp = −3.71), which made us 
less confident in the accuracy of the reported permeability of this compound. Within steroids 
(cluster c in Figure 2), progesterone was the strongest penetrant (logKp = −1.89), whereas 
the addition of one hydroxyl group in position 17 of the steroid scaffold significantly 
decreased the permeability (hydroxyprogesterone logKp = −3.22). The hydroxyl group in 
position 17 appears to be bad for steroid permeability, since testosterone (logKp = −3.40) 
contains the hydroxyl group but lacks the ethoxy group. We removed both hydroxyl and 
ethoxy group from position 17, and the resulting compound, 3-oxo-delta4-steroid, had a 
predicted logKp pred = −2.28; adding a methyl group to the same position resulted in a 
logKp pred = −2.28, which was higher than the permeability of hydroxyprogesterone and 
testosterone, but lower than that of progesterone. </p>

<p>The presence of other substituents and positions of double bonds seemed to be less 
important. The effects of the substituent in position 21 on compound permeability seem to 
depend on its size: it decreases when a methyl substituent (methylsuccinate; logKp = −3.68) 
is replaced by a larger group (succinamate substituent; logKp = −4.59) but dramatically 
increases as shown in the four hydrocortisone derivatives (hydrocortisone hexanoate, </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>hydrocortisone octanoate, hydrocortisone methylpimelate, and hydrocortisone 
hemipimelate) that have a long chain in this position (see Table S4). In the beginning of the 
homological series of compounds, the permeability of carboxylic acids (cluster a in Figure 
2) increased proportionally to the length of the hydrocarbon chain, i.e., acetic acid (logKp = 
−3.21) &lt; propionic acid (logKp = −2.74) &lt; butanoic acid (logKp = −2.90) &lt; pentanoic acid 
(logKp = −2.70) &lt; hexanoic acid (logKp = −1.85) &lt; heptanoic acid (logKp = −1.70) &lt; 
octanoic acid (logKp = −1.60). Then, similarly to glycol ethers from cluster b, the effect 
reached saturation and predicted logKp values for five next carboxylic acids became very 
similar: nonanoic acid (logKp pred = −1.68), decanoic acid (logKp pred = −1.68), undecanoic 
acid (logKp pred = −1.71), dodecanoic acid (logKp pred = −1.82), and tridecanoic acid 
(logKp pred = −1.84). </p>

<p>QSAR modeling of skin permeability </p>

<p>We have employed a dataset (Chauhan and Shakya, 2010) comprising 211 compounds 
(dataset D). Several structural duplicates were identified during the curation process. The 
complete list of 17 duplicate pairs and two sets of triplicates is shown in Table S3. Skin 
permeability values for all pairs of duplicates were the same or almost the same. This 
observation also means that the statistical performance of the models developed in an earlier 
study (Chauhan and Shakya, 2010) may have been over-optimistic because, as shown 
previously (Fourches et al., 2010), the presence of duplicates with identical activity 
annotations in both training and test sets generally leads to an overestimation of the model's 
predictivity. Here, we built species-specific QSAR models of skin permeability using the 
same protocol used for the skin sensitization study (Alves et al., 2014). The results shown in 
Table 1 suggest that continuous models with high accuracy for both datasets have been 
generated; however, the quality and coverage of human-based models 12 and 14 were higher 
than the same characteristics of rodent-based model 21. The former models have been 
retained for in silico screening of chemical libraries. </p>

<p>Comparison of developed QSAR models vs. DERMWIN permeability predictions </p>

<p>The <rs id="software-12" type="software">DERMWIN</rs> module available as part of the <rs corresp="#software-12" type="creator">EPI suite software</rs> has been employed in 
several recent studies (Fong and Tong, 2012; Fong et al., 2014; Zhang et al., 2013) for 
evaluating skin permeability. For this reason, we decided to compare our models with that 
implemented in this software. <rs type="software">DERMWIN</rs> uses a linear equation that relates the 
permeability coefficient with the chemical's octanol/water partition coefficient and 
molecular weight. However, statistical characteristics of this model suggested that this 
correlation was not adequate to predict human permeability. Although our consensus model 
12 had a lower coverage of chemical space than <rs type="software">DERMWIN</rs> (77% vs. 100%), it 
significantly outperformed DERMWIN in predictivity (Q 2 ext = 72% vs. 43%, respectively) 
(see Table 1). When the AD restriction was removed and the predictive accuracy of the 
models was evaluated using the same set of compounds (143 compounds), the comparison 
was in favor of our model (Q 2 ext = 71% vs. 66%, respectively) (see Table 3). </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Can rodent skin permeability data be used to predict human permeability? </p>

<p>As presented in the Results section, we found 34 compounds that had experimental 
permeability coefficient data for both human and rodents. Although the overall correlation 
between skin permeability measured in these two species was not high, we wished to 
determine whether the model obtained on rodent dataset E could be used to predict skin 
permeability in humans. Virtual screening of the human dataset D using the model 
developed with the rodent data resulted in a reasonably high predictivity (Q 2 ext = 0.77, 
RMSE = 1.27) but only for a very small fraction (19%) of compounds. Based on these 
results, one can assume that the rodent model could be used for predicting human skin 
permeability for at least some compounds within the conservative AD, but this observation 
should be considered with caution since it does not hold true for a larger data set. Additional 
experimental results for greater number of compounds are needed for more definitive 
conclusions. </p>

<p>Relationships between skin sensitization potential and skin permeability based on 
computed data </p>

<p>Given the small number of compounds with known experimental values of both skin 
sensitization and permeability, we decided to apply our selected QSAR models to cross-
predict these properties. The use of QSAR-imputed permeability and sensitization data 
allowed us to examine the possible relationships between the two endpoints for a much 
larger set of compounds. Skin sensitization model 5 (see the companion paper (Alves et al., 
2014)) was used for predicting skin sensitization for 186 compounds in the human skin 
permeability dataset (D), whereas skin permeability model 5 (Table 1) was used for 
calculating permeability coefficients for 387 compounds in the skin sensitization dataset 
retrieved from ICCVAM (254 compounds from dataset A + 133 sensitizers from dataset B) 
(see (Alves et al., 2014)). Then, we combined all predictions for compounds with 
unavailable experimental data (see Table S5). Compounds outside of AD either for model 5 
or 12 were removed from the analysis. In the end, 283 compounds that had information 
(experimental or predicted) for both endpoints were considered for the analysis. As one can 
see in Figure S1, all but one of the weakest penetrants (logKp &lt; −5) were non-sensitizers. 
The only exception was 1-dodecyl glycidyl ether, which could have been mispredicted by 
model 5. It was hypothesized recently that compound accumulation in the skin is 
contributing more significantly to skin sensitization than its actual permeability through the 
skin layer (Jaworska et al., 2013). Our results (see Figure S1) show that easily-penetrating 
compounds may be both sensitizers and non-sensitizers. For compounds with low 
permeability we made the same observation. These findings re-confirm the absence of the 
global correlation between skin permeability and sensitization. </p>

<p>Aforementioned results contradict a common view of skin permeation as the first step in the 
adverse outcome pathway leading to skin sensitization (OECD, 2012). To investigate 
whether the concordance between skin sensitization and permeability could be confined to 
certain chemical classes, we have performed a cluster analysis for the entire dataset of 283 
compounds with imputed data. Careful analysis of the relationships between the two </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>endpoints within clusters of structurally similar compounds showed that the observation 
linking the high permeability and skin sensitization potential could be made only for one 
cluster out of 34. This specific Cluster 1 is formed by 11 compounds represented by four 
barbitals (barbital, amylobarbital, butobarbital, and phenobarbital) and seven other drugs 
(scopolamine, ibuprofen, atropine, griseofulvin, cyclamen aldehyde, p-tert-butyl-alpha-
ethyl-hydrocinnamal, and sodium-3,3,5-trimethyl-benzenesulfonate). The comparison 
between permeability and sensitization for compounds in this cluster is shown in Figure S2 
and Table S6. The analysis revealed that seven compounds are associated with logKp &lt; −2.5 
and are non-sensitizers, whereas the four other compounds with logKp &gt; −2.5 are 
sensitizers. </p>

<p>No distinct trend could be observed for the remaining clusters. Although, as noticed above, 
skin permeability is widely considered to be mechanistically implicated in skin sensitization, 
we have found no evidence that high permeability implies high skin sensitization potency 
and vice versa. Some other authors reached the same conclusions. For instance, the analysis 
of mechanism-based QSARs demonstrates no role for skin permeability in determining 
potency (Roberts and Aptula, 2008). Similarly, in another recent study (Jaworska et al., 
2013) the authors hypothesizes that the accumulation of a chemical in the epidermis layer of 
the skin is much more related to the skin sensitization than the actual penetration properties. 
In another study (Roberts and Patlewicz, 2010), it was hypothesized that skin sensitizers 
reach the viable epidermis by-passing skin permeability route via shunt pathways, since bad 
penetrants have shown to be sensitizers when applied by intradermal injection. </p>

<p>Another important benefit of this cheminformatics analysis is the use of structural rules 
established from the interpretation of developed QSAR models, SAR and cluster analysis, in 
order to design new compounds with improved permeability and sensitization 
characteristics. We illustrated this approach using an example of putative stepwise structural 
optimization for permeability of pentanoic acid, considering experimental data and 
predictions using developed models (Figure 3). Starting from this compound with a 
relatively low permeability (logKp = −2.7), several transformation steps can increase its 
permeability more than 10-fold and convert it to n-heptanol (logKp = −1.50). n-heptanol is 
predicted as a sensitizer (which is confirmed by its Material Safety Data Sheet (OXEA, 
2013) but it can be transformed to octanoic acid that has a similar permeability (logKp = 
−1.60) as n-heptanol but lacks its sensitization potential. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>We have compiled, curated, and integrated the largest publicly available datasets of skin 
permeability for diverse chemicals. The analysis of the experimental data for compounds 
containing both skin sensitization and permeability data indicated that, with a few 
exceptions, there is no overall concordance between these two endpoints, i.e., weak 
penetrants could be strong sensitizers and vice versa. Although sensitizers have to penetrate 
the skin layer, the permeability coefficient is not a determinant of the skin sensitization 
potential. Cluster analysis also helped us to highlight the high consistency of experimental 
Kp data reported in the literature. </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>We have built statistically significant and externally predictive QSAR models of skin 
permeability that can be used to predict the permeability of untested compounds through the 
skin. Comparison of the developed consensus model with <rs type="software">DERMWIN</rs> software showed that 
our model significantly outperformed DERMWIN in predictivity (Q 2 ext = 72% and 43%, 
respectively) but at the expense of some lost in coverage (77% vs. 100%); when applied to 
the same set of compounds as used for DERMWIN (ignoring the AD for our models) the 
performance of our model is still higher (Q 2 ext = 71% vs. 66%). The compiled datasets and 
all the models developed in this study have been made publicly available at the Chembench 
Web Portal (http://chembench.mml.unc.edu). </p>

<p>The use of skin permeability and sensitization values imputed by our QSAR models allowed 
us to examine the relationships between these two endpoints utilizing a significantly 
expanded set consisting of 283 compounds. The results indicated that there is still no overall 
concordance between these endpoints. This phenomenon could be explained by attributing 
higher impact to compound accumulation in the skin on sensitization potential, rather than 
permeability through the skin layer. Further investigation into this observation would be 
facilitated via building predictive models of compound accumulation in the skin, and 
incorporating considerations of protein binding and reactivity. </p>

<p>In conclusion, the skin permeability models developed in this study could be useful for risk 
assessment purposes in addition to the assessment of skin sensitization; for instance, the 
knowledge how much of an applied dose will penetrate the skin may be helpful to estimate 
systemic exposure to topically applied chemicals. Moreover, the lack of correlation between 
skin permeability and skin sensitization established in this study suggests a possibility of 
rational design of compounds with the desired high permeability but low skin sensitization 
potential that may be of value to the cosmetics industry. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Refer to Web version on PubMed Central for supplementary material. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported in part by NIH (grants GM66940 and GM096967), EPA (grant RD 83499901), and 
FAPEG (grant 201310267001095). A.T. acknowledges partial support from Russian Scientific Foundation (project 
14-43-00024). E.M. acknowledges partial support from STCU (Grant P407) E.M, V.A., and C.H.A acknowledge 
partial support from CNPq (PVE, Grant 400760/2014-2). V.A. thanks CNPq and Science without Borders program 
for the financial support of his visit to the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. N.K. and J.S. are supported 
by the NIEHS contract N01-ES 35504 and the Intramural Research Program of the NIEHS. This article may be the 
work product of an employee or group of employees of the NIEHS, NIH, or other organizations; however, the 
statements, opinions, or conclusions contained therein do not necessarily represent the statements, opinions, or 
conclusions of NIEHS, NIH, the United States government, or other organizations. The use of commercial product 
names is for comparative purposes only and does not constitute endorsement by any of the authors, organizations, 
or agencies. </p>

<p>ABBREVIATIONS </p>

<p>AD 
Applicability domain </p>

<p>AOP 
Adverse outcome pathway </p>

<p>Alves et al. 
Page 12 </p>

<p>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>ICCVAM </p>

<p>Interagency Coordinating Committee on the Validation of Alternative 
Methods </p>

<p>Kp 
Permeability coefficient </p>

<p>LLNA 
Local lymph node assay </p>

<p>LU 
Logarithmic unit </p>

<p>MAE 
Mean absolute error </p>

<p>OECD 
Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development </p>

<p>(Q)SAR 
(Quantitative) structure-activity relationship </p>

<p>RMSE 
Root mean squared error </p>



<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Highlights </p>

<p>• We compiled the largest publicly-available skin permeability dataset. </p>

<p>• Predictive QSAR models were developed for skin permeability. </p>

<p>• No concordance between skin sensitization and skin permeability has been 
found. </p>

<p>• Structural rules for optimizing sensitization and penetration were established. </p>

<p>Alves et al. 
Page 16 </p>

<p>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 1. </p>

<p>Human vs. rodent skin permeability correlation (R 2 = 0.44, logKp Human = 0.72*logKp Rodent 
− 1.17). </p>

<p>Alves et al. 
Page 17 </p>

<p>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 2. </p>

<p>Cluster analysis of the human skin permeability dataset D: dendrogram and heat map of the 
distance matrix ordered based on structural similarity (blue/violet = similar; yellow/red = 
dissimilar). The following clusters are noted: (a) carboxylic acids, (b) glycol ethers, and (c) 
steroids. </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 3. </p>

<p>Example of a structural transformation of sensitizer n-octanol with low permeability to non-
sensitizer octanoic acid with improved permeability. Desired change of property is 
highlighted by green, undesired -by red; Δ = logKp parent − logKp child . </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Alves et al. </p>

<p>
Table 1 </p>

<p>Statistical characteristics of QSAR models for skin permeability assessed by 5-fold external cross-validation. </p>

<p>Models </p>

<p>Q 2 </p>

<p>ext </p>

<p>RMSE MAE Coverage </p>

<p>HUMAN 
Model 1 -SiRMS </p>

<p>0.69 </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>Model 2 -SiRMS no AD * </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.73 </p>

<p>0.53 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Model 3 -Dragon </p>

<p>0.73 </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p>Model 4 -Dragon no AD * </p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p>0.70 </p>

<p>0.49 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Model 5 -Consensus </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>0.49 </p>

<p>0.38 </p>

<p>0.77 </p>

<p>Model 6 -Consensus no AD * </p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p>0.69 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Model 7 -Consensus Rigor </p>

<p>0.73 </p>

<p>0.45 </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>0.63 </p>

<p>DERMWIN </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>0.78 </p>

<p>0.49 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>RODENT 
Model 8 -SiRMS </p>

<p>0.57 </p>

<p>0.67 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.71 </p>

<p>Model 9 -SiRMS no AD * </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.82 </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Model 10 -Dragon </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>0.69 </p>

<p>Model 11 -Dragon no AD * </p>

<p>0.32 </p>

<p>0.84 </p>

<p>0.63 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Model 12 -Consensus </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>0.77 </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>0.86 </p>

<p>Model 13 -Consensus no AD * </p>

<p>0.38 </p>

<p>0.80 </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>Model 14 -Consensus Rigor </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>0.53 </p>

<p>Notes: Models 1 to 7: Human-based skin permeability models. Models 8 to 13: Rodent-based skin permeability models. RSME: root mean square error; MAE: mean absolute error </p>

<p>* 
Applicability Domain was not considered in these models. </p>

<p>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Alves et al. 
Page 22 </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Comparison of the performance of consensus QSAR model with that of DERMWIN on the set of 143 
compounds. </p>

<p>Models 
Q 2 </p>

<p>ext </p>

<p>RMSE MAE </p>

<p>Model 5 -Consensus 0.72 
0.49 
0.38 </p>

<p>DERMWIN 
0.66 
0.53 
0.37 </p>

<p>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2016 April 15. </p>

</text></tei>