<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4870544" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: A considerable number of patients infected with HIV also have mental health problems. Individual psychotherapy is 
an effective way to treat these issues. Lack of social acceptance is a barrier to patients receiving proper medication and emotional/ 
psychological support. 
Objectives: The purpose of this study was to examine the individual factors of social acceptance in patients infected with human 
immunodeficiency virus. 
Patients and Methods: Fifty HIV-infected patients who were registered in the Behavioral Consultation Center entered the study. Each 
of them filled out a questionnaire based on the Crown-Marlow social acceptance scale. Their answers were evaluated according to the 
questionnaire key. 
Results: Forty-five patients (90%) were male and five (10%) were female. Their ages ranged between 28 and 52 years old. Other variables 
researched in this study include patients' age, sex, education, occupation, place of living, marital status, family history of HIV, and family 
history of psychological disorders. Employed patients experienced more social acceptance than housewives and people who were 
unemployed or retired. 
Conclusions: This study showed that HIV-infected patients with jobs enjoy a great deal of acceptance from the people around them and 
a higher quality of life in general. It also led to suggestions for further study with the purpose of finding more effective solutions for 
HIV prevention and better strategies for dealing with psychological disorders. Such research could also help in providing an enhanced 
understanding of the potential psychological impact that AIDS has on patients in Iran. </p>

<p>Keywords: HIV, Social Support, Social Values, Social Distance </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non-
Commercial 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial 
usages, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Regardless of having symptoms or opportunistic in-
fections, individuals who are HIV-positive and who have 
CD4 lymphocyte counts fewer than 350 cells/micro liters 
have been defined as patients with acquired immunode-
ficiency syndrome (AIDS). Biologically, HIV belongs to the 
retrovirus family and the Lenti virus subfamily (1). 
The social risk of a health condition involves the pos-
sibility that a person will suffer socially if it is disclosed 
that he or she has a severe health problem (2). The psy-
chosocial complications of declining health consist of 
psychological stress related to the poor quality of life 
that HIV-infected patients and their families suffer from, 
including the economic and psychosocial effects on fam-
ily functioning that illness and death have (3). The major 
psychiatric problems in HIV-infected patients involve low </p>

<p>self-confidence issues; consequently, they are more prone 
than most people to suicide ideation and attempts (4). In 
recent years, studies indicate that a considerable num-
ber of patients infected with HIV also have mental health 
problems (3, 5). 
Social acceptance of HIV disease involves help and sup-
port from the patient's social network (6) which is often 
associated with a better prognosis for the patient (7). 
This network includes family, friends, neighbors, and 
co-workers; an example of a lack of social acceptance is 
if any of these people do not accept the responsibility of 
giving medication and care to the patients (8). 
In 1987, the first case of HIV/AIDS reported in Iran was a 
6-year-old boy with hemophilia. An important factor that 
limits the extent of HIV in Iran is the social and cultural </p>

<p>Bidaki R et al. </p>

<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2016;5(1):e22243 </p>

<p>
beliefs and behaviors in that part of the world (9). Since 
there are many different potential factors involved in 
the social acceptance of HIV-infected patients in the psy-
chotherapy process, we conducted a research to evalu-
ate the social acceptance of patients in faceted with HIV 
who in 2012 received help from behavioral consultation 
centers in Yazd, a central province in Iran. To the best of 
our knowledge, the current study was one of the first re-
search projects involving the assessment of the social ac-
ceptance of HIV-infected patients in Iran. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to examine the individual 
factors of social acceptance in patients infected with hu-
man immunodeficiency virus and also seeks to evaluate 
the scores of social acceptance of the patients at the be-
havioral consultation center in the Yazd Province. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>This was a cross-sectional study that was conducted in 
2012 concerning behavioral disorders in HIV-infected pa-
tients at the consultation center in the city of Yazd, the 
capital of Yazd Province in Iran. </p>

<p>3.1. The Study Population </p>

<p>The patients chosen for the current study are the HIV-
infected individuals who had records at the behavioral 
consultation center in Yazd. </p>

<p>3.2. Sampling Method </p>

<p>Out of the 70 patients needed, only 50 were willing to 
fill in the guide-scale social acceptance Crowne-Marlowe 
questionnaire, a Persian translation of the Crowne-Mar-
low questions that were used in the study. It comprised 
33 yes-no questions (10). Subjects' responses were com-
pared to a scale key in order to determine each individ-
ual's score. Scores of 0-8 represent the people who were 
most likely excluded from society yet who were not look-
ing for answers to their lack of social acceptance. The 
score range 9 -19 indicates that there was an average so-
cial acceptance of the patients' behavior, a result that is 
consistent with the social behavior in general. A score in 
between 20 and 33 demonstrates a high level of social ac-
ceptance, implying that the patients' actual behavior was 
very compatible with the rule sand norms of the society 
around them. The variables in this research include each 
patient's age, residential area, job, and gender. </p>

<p>3.3. Data analysis </p>

<p>The questionnaires were completed under the supervi-
sion of physicians and psychologists who were working at 
the Yazd behavioral consultation center. After the HIV pa-
tients completed the questionnaires, the physicians and 
psychologists evaluated there social acceptance scores of </p>

<p>the patients; these scores were calculated out of a total of 
20. The specific data of patients were analyzed by statisti-
cal package for the social sciences (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs>) <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 14</rs>. In this 
study, t-test and chi-squared test were used and the P-val-
ues that are less than 0.05 are considered significant. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>The current study included 50 patients infected with 
HIV. The mean was 34.86 years old with arrange between 
28 and 52 years old. Forty-five patients were male and five 
patients were female. Forty-five patients were living in ur-
ban areas with an average social acceptance score of 16.73, 
and five patients were rural inhabitants with an average 
score of 15. The difference between two groups, however, 
is not significant (P-Value = 0.403) (Table 1). 
These results show that social acceptance scores are not 
correlated with patients' inhabitance status. 
Twenty-six patients (52%) that were between 28 and 34 
years old had a mean social acceptance score of 16.23. 
twenty-four patients (48%) between the ages of 35 and 52 
had a mean social acceptance score of 16.91. The differenc-
es between these two groups are not significant either (P 
= 0.583). The results indicate that patients' social accep-
tance scores have no significant correlation with their 
age (Table 1). The mean social acceptance score of male 
patients' was 16.84 out of 20, and for females, it was 14 out 
of 20. These results reveal that there is no relationship 
between the social acceptance of AIDS patients and their 
gender (P = 0.168) (Table 1). 
The next factor to consider in this study is the patients' 
level of education. For the two patients who were illiter-
ate, their mean social acceptance score was 14.50. Eleven 
patients with a primary education had a mean score of 
16.36. A total of 22 people who were educated up until 
secondary school had an average score of 16.63. Fifteen 
people had a higher education in the university and also 
diploma, with an average score of 16.56. None of the pa-
tients in the study had acquired post-diploma education. 
The data analysis indicates that the social acceptance 
of these patients is not associated with education level, 
since the difference among the patients with varying 
education levels is not statistically significant (P = 0.913). 
In regard to the employment factor, seven patients who 
were laborers had a score of 17.42, while five patients who 
were housewives had a mean score of 14. Twenty-two pa-
tients were working in non-governmental organizations 
and had a score of 18.22, while the 16 unemployed and re-
tired patients had a mean score of 14.68 (P = 0.036) (Table 
1). Unlike in the studies of the other factors, these results 
are statistically significant. The Post-Hoc test showed sig-
nificant differences between the social acceptance of pa-
tients working in non-governmental organizations and 
that of patients who are housewives (P = 0.043) or are un-
employed or retired (P = 0.012), respectively. 
Thus, the overall social acceptance of employed patients 
was more than that of unemployed or retired patients. </p>

<p>Bidaki R et al. </p>



<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2016;5(1):e22243 </p>

<p>Table 1. The Social Acceptance Scores of Patients Infected With HIV in the Yazd Behavioral Consultation Center in 2012 </p>

<p>Variables 
Samples (N) 
Average Score 
P Value </p>

<p>Residential area 
0.403 </p>

<p>Urban 
45 
16.73 ± 4.46 </p>

<p>Rural 
5 
15 ± 2.91 </p>

<p>Total 
50 
16.56 ± 4.34 </p>

<p>Age 
0.583 </p>

<p>28 -34 
26 
16.23 ± 5.16 </p>

<p>35 -52 
24 
16.91 ± 3.32 </p>

<p>Total 
50 
16.56 ± 4.34 </p>

<p>Gender 
0.168 </p>

<p>Male 
45 
16.84 ± 4.43 </p>

<p>Female 
5 
14 ± 2.44 </p>

<p>Total 
50 
16.56 ± 4.34 </p>

<p>Job 
0.036 </p>

<p>Labor 
7 
17.42 ± 3.55 </p>

<p>Housewife 
5 
14 ± 2.44 </p>

<p>Non-governmental organizations 
22 
18.22 ± 4.17 </p>

<p>Unemployed -retired 
16 
14.68 ± 4.51 </p>

<p>Total 
50 
16.56 ± 4.34 </p>

<p>Moreover, in the current study, 17 patients were unmar-
ried and had a mean score of 16.94. Thirty-one patients 
were married and had a score of 16.64. Two patients were 
divorced and had a score of 12. The low test scores of these 
people are most likely due to the low number of divorced 
individuals studied in this research; consequently, de-
spite the outward appearance of these results, the social 
acceptance of these patients is actually not significantly 
associated with marital status (P = 0.316). 
During the study, patients were also asked about their 
family history of HIV infection. For 46 patients who did 
not have any family history of HIV, the average score of 
social acceptance was 16.65. In the four people who did 
have a family history of HIV, the mean score was 15.50. 
However, the difference between having and not having 
a familial history of HIV is not statistically significant ei-
ther (P = 0.616). 
Thirty-five persons in the population did not have a 
family history of psychiatric disorders, achieving 16.57 
as their average score of social acceptance. The 15 people 
who did have a family history of psychological disorders 
had an average score of 16.53. This test confirms that this 
difference is statistically significant (P = 0.978). 
Concerning another factor in this research-the measure-
ment of CD4 lymphocyte levels in patients-the person 
correlation coefficient which is a measure of the strength 
of the linear relationship between two variables showed 
no significant relationship between social acceptance and 
the rate of CD4 lymphocytes in patients (r = 0.016 and P 
= 0.912). Nevertheless, there was a significant correlation 
between the number of CD4 lymphocytes/micro liters and </p>

<p>the duration of the HIV affliction; as a result, the number 
of CD4 lymphocytes decreased during the infection. </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>In the current study, social acceptance was recorded 
with scores of 15 and 16.73 in rural and urban areas, but 
the difference was not statistically significant (Table 1). In 
comparison, a study in Thailand discovered that the so-
cial acceptance of HIV-positive patients in rural areas was 
lower than that of patients in urban areas (11). In another 
study, urban women claimed that there were more ob-
stacles to caring for HIV-positive patients in urban areas 
than in rural areas, possibly due to the high amount of 
HIV stigma existing in urban places (12). 
In terms of the educational level of the patients, none of 
the patients had post-diploma education. The data analy-
sis indicated that the social acceptance level of these pa-
tients is not associated with their education level, since 
the differences among the groups of patients with differ-
ent education levels is not significant (P = 0.913). This fact 
may be due to the lack of post-graduate education in the 
patients involved in this study; otherwise, we would have 
expected a significant difference in the social acceptance 
of patients based on each one's level of education. 
In regards to the measurement of CD4 lymphocyte lev-
els, the analysis of data showed no significant relation-
ship between social acceptance and the measurement of 
CD4 lymphocytes in patients (r = 0.016 and P = 0.912). This 
is similar to the findings of another research project that 
also revealed that patients' CD4 lymphocyte counts are 
not significantly associated with their quality of life (13). </p>

<p>Bidaki R et al. </p>

<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2016;5(1):e22243 </p>

<p>
Nevertheless, there was significant correlation between 
the numbers of CD4 lymphocytes/micro liters and the 
duration of the patients' HIV affliction; consequently, the 
number of CD4 in patients decreased during their period 
of infection, a result that seems to be an expected conse-
quence of this phenomenon. 
In our study, the factors involving patients' age, gender, 
level of education, family history of HIV infection and 
psychological disorders, time of HIV infection diagnosis, 
inhabitance, and marriage status did not have any signif-
icant correlation with the level of social acceptance they 
received (Table 1). Nevertheless, another study that was 
conducted in Kenya, Namibia, and Tanzania demonstrat-
ed that greater levels of depressive symptoms in HIV-pos-
itive patients were related to the factors of younger age 
and being female (14). These results may be consequenc-
es of low social support received by young people and 
female in those countries in general. However, another 
study indicated that gender was not a factor in determin-
ing any differences in identified psychiatric outcomes (6). 
Unfortunately, at the moment, there are no explanations 
for the conflicting results obtained from these additional 
studies. Further investigations need to be conducted in 
order to answer the question of why some factors have 
not achieved clear statistical significance in our research. 
That being said, it is also important to note that our study 
suffered from a major drawback: A very low number of 
patients participating in the study consequently, this dis-
advantage may very well have affected our findings and, 
in turn, the interpretation of the number of variables. 
Moreover, since the current study was one of the first to 
evaluate the different factors affecting social acceptance 
of HIV-positive patients in Iran, we faced a very limited 
availability of information at the time of this study, hin-
dering our ability to accurately interpret the results we 
obtained. Needless to say, then, a great deal of work still 
remains to be done on researching this issue, which re-
mains controversial. 
In the current research, based on our data, significant 
differences were reported between social acceptance of 
patients working in non-governmental organizations 
and social acceptance of patients who were housewives 
(P = 0.043) or unemployed or retired (P = 0.012) (Table 1). 
Consequently, the findings of the present study suggest 
that the social acceptance of patients working in non-
governmental organizations is more than that of unem-
ployed and retired patients. These results are consistent 
with an earlier study in China, which was conducted 
on individuals with AIDS in order to document unem-
ployment as a risk factor for suicidal ideation in these 
patients (7). Also, a study in Ethiopia confirmed the vi-
tal role employment play sin improving AIDS patients' 
quality of life, and consequently, in increasing social ac-
ceptance of them as well (15). This evidence shows that 
having a job provides patients with not only as source 
of income, but also a social community, which in turn 
increases their opportunity to enjoy greater social ac-</p>

<p>ceptance. Various other sources of research on this topic 
also confirm that stigmatization of patients infected 
with HIV/AIDS is strongly related to the amount of fear 
of HIV and awareness about it that exist at the commu-
nity level. Since people's attitudes are partly formed 
through social influence and social knowledge, rel-
evant public-health interventions must be considered 
for reducing HIV/AIDS stigma in society. Thus, attention 
should be drawn to the role of social influences as HIV/ 
AIDS stigma intervention (16). In addition, clinical in-
terventions such as complementary therapies and be-
havioral-medicine interventions should be established 
for people living with HIV/AIDS, since these treatments 
have reportedly improved patients' quality of life (14). 
Our study results did not include any score range of 
20 -33. This fact means that the actual behavior of the 
infected individuals was not ideally compatible with the 
cultural believes and community norms. At present, it 
appears that additional educational programs need to be 
established for people living with HIV/AIDS as a pathway 
toward achieving community norms. In comparison, re-
sults of a research project conducted in the United States 
indicate mild levels of depression and anxiety manifesta-
tions, as well as a moderate mean score of social accep-
tance, in the HIV-infected patients. The patients adapted 
to their difficult health condition by using positive recon-
stitution, coping methods, and social acceptance (17). The 
increasing trend to establish care and treatment services 
throughout the country will give more medical person-
nel the opportunity to provide holistic mental and psy-
chosocial health care for people living with HIV. </p>

<p>5.1. Conclusion </p>

<p>This study showed that HIV-infected patients with jobs 
enjoy a great deal of acceptance from the people around 
them and a higher quality of life in general. It also led to 
suggestions for further study with the purpose of finding 
more effective solutions for HIV prevention and better 
strategies for dealing with psychological disorders. Such 
research could also help in providing an enhanced un-
derstanding of the potential psychological impact that 
AIDS has on patients in Iran. In order to help improve 
the attitude that members of society have towards HIV 
patients, sanitation authorities need to provide better 
policies and strategies for combating psychological dis-
orders in the country. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We appreciate all the staff at the behavioral consulta-
tion center in Yazd city for their cooperation. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution:All of the authors have the 
same contribution to this manuscript. 
Financial Disclosure:There was no financial support 
for the current research. </p>

<p>Bidaki R et al. </p>



<p>Int J High Risk Behav Addict. 2016;5(1):e22243 </p>



</text></tei>