<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4131081" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Prostate-specific antigen (PSA) is the most widely used 
marker for the early detection of prostate cancer (PC) [1]. 
Patients who have elevated PSA levels or abnormal find-
ings on a digital rectal examination (DRE) but whose biop-
sy results are negative pose a problem in PC screening. </p>

<p>When the result of a DRE is normal and PSA is lower than 
10 ng/mL, prostate biopsies fail to detect PC in 80% of men 
[2]. However, PSA is not a cancer-specific marker, and vari-
ous benign processes also affect PSA concentrations [3,4]. 
Elevated PSA due to benign conditions (benign prostatic 
hyperplasia [BPH] and prostatitis) most directly under-
scores the difficulty in making a decision about repeat </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:527-532 </p>



<p>Stimac et al </p>

<p>biopsy. The question remains as to the nature of the rela-
tionship between PSA and subclinical prostatic inflamma-
tion. Histological inflammation is a frequent finding in 
prostate biopsies that are performed on men without PC 
[5]. Several studies have investigated the relationship be-
tween PSA levels and the morphology of prostatic in-
flammation [6-9]. The results are controversial. Although 
it is known that acute prostatitis can contribute to lack of 
total PSA (tPSA) specificity, major disagreement remains 
over the effect of asymptomatic inflammation on free PSA 
(fPSA) and percentage of free PSA (f/tPSA) values [10-13]. 
It is essential to understand how factors other than PC, 
such as inflammation of the prostate, influence changes in 
PSA values. We therefore investigated the correlation be-
tween the morphological parameters of inflammation in 
prostate biopsies and tPSA, fPSA, and f/tPSA values in pa-
tients in the so-called "gray zone" (tPSA＜10 ng/mL) and 
without clinically detectable PC. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>This study, which was performed from November 2008 to 
December 2012, included a series of 106 men with tPSA 
＜10 ng/mL and/or f/tPSA＜18% and who had undergone 
prostate biopsy that was negative for PC and showed no 
signs of prostatitis. Institutional Review Board approval 
was obtained before the initiation of the study. Serum PSA 
measurement (Immulite-DPC assay, Siemens, Erlangen, 
Germany), DRE, and transrectal ultrasound (Sonoline SI 
400 U/S, Siemens) were performed on each patient. A bipla-
nar transrectal probe was used with a frequency 5/7.5 MHz. 
Transrectal ultrasonography was used to determine the 
prostate volume [Vp=/6× (D1×D2×D3)] and to guide the 
biopsies. Each patient underwent eight-core biopsy with 
an 18-gauge needle fitted to a Bard Magnum gun. Patients 
diagnosed with PC or premalignant lesions on biopsy were 
excluded from the study. Patients were also excluded from 
the study if they had a documented history or clinical signs 
of prostatitis, had PSA greater than l0 ng/mL, had prostate 
volume measured by transrectal ultrasound (TRUS) great-
er than 40 cm 3 
, had previously undergone prostate surgery, 
had received 5-alpha-reductase inhibitors, or had an in-
dwelling catheter or evidence of urinary tract infection 
(UTI). 
Hematoxylin-eosin-stained slides taken from archival 
sections of biopsied prostatic tissue were analyzed by one 
pathologist. Each core of prostatic tissue (eight cores sam-
pled from each patient) was scored for the type of in-
flammation and was graded by using a 4-point scale as fol-
lows: 0, no inflammatory cells (Fig. 1A); 1, mononuclear cell 
infiltrate (chronic inflammation; Fig. 1B); 2, mononuclear 
and polymorphonuclear cell infiltrate (chronic active in-
flammation; Fig. 1C); 3, polymorphonuclear cell infiltrate 
(acute inflammation; Fig. 1D). The effects of these morpho-
logic aspects of inflammation were then correlated with se-
rum tPSA, fPSA, and f/tPSA values. 
In almost every set of biopsies, different types of histo-</p>

<p>logical inflammation were found. Thus, we used regression 
factor analysis to create a reduced classification for in-
flammation type. Factor analysis was applied according to 
the criteria of dimensionality reduction based on the num-
ber of derived variables. Input variables were the eight var-
iables describing type of inflammation in individual biopsy 
cores of the prostate by use of the previously described 
4-point scale. The criterion was to obtain a derived varia-
ble, that is, one factor on which each respondent was as-
signed a specific factor score. Instead of using four grades 
of inflammation for each biopsy core, we created two groups 
for statistical analysis. By use of regression analysis, each 
patient was given a unique inflammation type factor score 
(ITFS). The median of the factor scores was then calculated 
(ITFS median, 0.053). Patients with factor scores lower 
than or equal to the median (ITFS≤0.053) were included 
in the "more chronic inflammation" group. Similarly, those 
with factor scores higher than the median (ITFS＞0.053) 
were included in the "more acute inflammation" group. 
Descriptive statistics were used to characterize the age 
of patients, Vp, tPSA, fPSA, and f/tPSA. Comparisons of 
tPSA, fPSA, and f/tPSA values between groups were done 
by using Mann-Whitney U tests, and p＜0.05 was consid-
ered statistically significant. Correlations among age, Vp, 
tPSA, fPSA, f/tPSA, and ITFS were determined by using 
Spearman's rank correlation analysis. For correlation 
analysis, p＜0.01 was considered statistically significant. 
Data were analyzed by using <rs id="software-0" type="software">R ver. 2.10.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">(Development Core Team. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria, 2009</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Data for 106 patients who met the inclusion criteria were 
analyzed. The median (range) age of the patients was 65 
years (47 to 83 years) and the patients' median (range) pros-
tate volume (Vp) was 31.5 cm 3 (16 to 40 cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>). The median 
(range) levels of tPSA, fPSA, and f/tPSA were 6.6 ng/mL 
(3.4 to 10 ng/mL), 0.9 ng/ml (0.14 to 3.1 ng/mL), and 13.45% 
(2.5% to 35%). All patients had a Vp of less than 40 cm 3 to 
minimize the effect of adenoma on PSA values. 
After initial histological coding of each biopsy core (eight 
cores per prostate biopsy) for inflammatory type, different 
types of histological inflammation were found in almost ev-
ery set of prostate biopsies. Therefore, instead of having 4 
grades of inflammation type for each biopsy core and for 
simplification purposes, we used regression analysis to cre-
ate a reduced classification for inflammation type with two 
groups of patients for comparison: patients with more 
chronic inflammation (n=61, 57.5%) and patients with 
more acute inflammation (n=45, 42.5%). 
The clinical characteristics and differences between the 
two groups according to grade of inflammation are shown 
in Table 1. The median (range) levels of tPSA, fPSA, and 
f/tPSA were 6.4 ng/mL (3.4 to 10 ng/mL), 1.09 ng/mL (0.28 
to 3.1 ng/mL), and 15% (5.5% to 35%) for the chronic in-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:527-532 </p>

<p>Subclinical Inflammation and PSA </p>



<p>FIG. 1. Grading of inflammation type observed in prostate biopsies. (A) Normal prostate epithelial tissue without inflammatory cell 
infiltrate (inflammation type grade 0) (H&amp;E, ×200). (B) Stromal and periglandular mononuclear cell infiltrate (inflammation type 
grade 1) (H&amp;E, ×400). (C) Mononuclear and polymorphonuclear cell infiltrate in stroma and partially in epithelium of glands and 
ducts (inflammation type grade 2) (H&amp;E, ×200). (D) Aggressive polymorphonuclear cell infiltrate with extensive destruction of 
prostate epithelium and formation of microabscess in lumina of glands or ducts (inflammation type grade 3) (H&amp;E, ×400). </p>

<p>TABLE 1. The clinical characteristics and differences between 
two groups of patients according to inflammation grading </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Inflammation type groups </p>

<p>p-value a 
More chronic 
(n=61) </p>

<p>More acute 
(n=45) </p>

<p>Age (y) 
Vp (cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>) 
tPSA (ng/mL) 
fPSA (ng/mL) 
f/tPSA (%) </p>

<p>64 (47-81) 
38 (19-40) 
6.4 (3.4-10) 
1.09 (0.28-3.1) 
15 (5.5-35) </p>

<p>67 (54-83) 
29 (16-40) 
7.3 (4.1-10) 
0.79 (0.14-2.9) 
12 (2.5-29.6) </p>

<p>0.310 
＜0.001 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.200 
0.003 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>＜0.001 * </p>

<p>Values are presented as median (range). 
Vp, prostate volume; PSA, prostate-specific antigen; tPSA, total 
PSA; fPSA, free PSA; f/tPSA, percentage of free PSA. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>:Mann-Whitney U tests. </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Statistically significant, p＜0.05. </p>

<p>flammation group, and 7.3 ng/mL (4.1 to 10 ng/mL), 0.79 
ng/mL (0.14 to 2.9 ng/mL), and 12% (2.5% to 29.6%) for the 
acute inflammation group. A significant difference was 
found in fPSA (p=0.003) and f/tPSA (p＜0.001) levels be-
tween groups, whereas the difference in tPSA levels was 
not significant (p=0.200). However, patients with more 
acute inflammation seemed to have slightly increased 
tPSA values. A positive correlation existed but was not sig-
nificant (r=0.12, p=0.210). The fPSA and f/tPSA values 
were significantly decreased in the group of patients with 
more acute inflammation than in the patients with more 
chronic inflammation in the biopsy specimens. 
When we looked at the distribution of inflammation 
groups related to tPSA and f/tPSA values, patients with 
more acute inflammation tended to group below the hori-
zontal line that represented the 18% f/tPSA cutoff for better 
discrimination between PC and benign conditions (Fig. 2). 
More acute histological inflammation decreased the per-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:527-532 </p>



<p>Stimac et al </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Scattergram of percentage of free prostate-specific 
antigen (f/tPSA) versus total PSA (tPSA) values in two groups of 
patients according to inflammation type. The horizontal line 
represents the 18% cutoff limit for more efficient discrimination 
between prostate cancer and benign conditions. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Spearman's rank correlation matrix showing relationships between studied characteristics (significance: p＜0.01) </p>

<p>Variable 
Age 
tPSA 
fPSA 
f/tPSA 
Vp 
ITFS </p>

<p>Age 
r 
p-value 
tPSA 
r 
p-value 
fPSA 
r 
p-value 
f/tPSA 
r 
p-value 
Vp 
r 
p-value 
ITFS </p>

<p>1 
0.06 
0.540 
1 </p>

<p>0.15 
0.130 </p>

<p>0.40 
＜0.001 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.15 
0.130 </p>

<p>-0.13 
0.170 </p>

<p>0.82 
＜0.001 ** 
1 </p>

<p>0.29 
0.003 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.12 
0.220 </p>

<p>0.32 
0.001 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.31 
0.001 ** 
1 </p>

<p>0.03 
0.780 </p>

<p>0.12 
0.210 </p>

<p>-0.31 
0.001 ** </p>

<p>-0.43 
＜0.001 ** </p>

<p>-0.48 
＜0.001 ** 
1 </p>

<p>PSA, prostate-specific antigen; tPSA, total PSA; fPSA, free PSA; f/tPSA, percentage of free PSA; Vp, prostate volume; ITFS, in-
flammation type factor score. 
** Statistically significant, p＜0.01. </p>

<p>centage of free PSA, a tendency similar to that in PC. 
With the use of Spearman's analysis (Table 2), there was 
a significant negative correlation between type of in-
flammation and fPSA (r=-0.31, p=0.001) and f/tPSA 
(r=0.43, p＜0.001) PSA values, in that a decrease in fPSA 
and f/tPSA values was found in patients with more acute 
inflammation. Total PSA values correlated significantly 
with fPSA (r=0.4, p＜0.001) but not with type of in-
flammation (r=0.12, p＞0.01). As expected, no correlation 
emerged between Vp and tPSA values (r=0.12, p=0.22), be-
cause only patients with small prostates (＜40 cm 3 ) were 
included in the study. On the other hand, Vp correlated 
with age (r=0.29, p=0.003), fPSA (r=0.32, p=0.001), and </p>

<p>f/tPSA (r=0.31, p=0.001). Also, there was a significant neg-
ative correlation between Vp and inflammation type (r=-
0.48, p＜0.001). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We are often confronted with the association of abnormal 
PSA levels and biopsies that reveal no PC but only 
inflammation. Should the abnormal PSA levels be in-
terpreted as a sign of missed PC, or can an inflammation 
explain the elevation of PSA? Although the determination 
of PSA is the best tool for the early detection of PC, the diag-
nostic accuracy of PSA is limited because of limited sensi-
tivity and specificity, particularly in men with tPSA levels 
up to 10 ng/mL. The ratio of free-to-total PSA, calculated 
as percentage of fPSA, has been suggested as a useful tool 
for differentiating between PC and BPH, because the ratio 
is lower in PC than in BPH [14]. It is known that prostatitis 
can contribute to a rise in PSA, but disagreement exists 
about the effect of histological inflammation on PSA and 
its fractions. Recent results suggest that a decreased 
f/tPSA is not only characteristic of PC [15-17]. It is sug-
gested that subclinical inflammation could affect both 
tPSA and fPSA values. 
The best predictor of the serum PSA in patients with 
BPH but without PC is the size of the prostate [18]. Meyer 
at al. [13] reported that the serum PSA increased only in 
patients with benign prostates larger than 40 g. To mini-
mize the effect of prostatic adenoma on PSA values, we in-
cluded only patients with Vp up to 40 g. As expected, no cor-
relation emerged between Vp and tPSA values (r=0.12, 
p=0.220). By contrast, we found a positive correlation be-
tween Vp and fPSA values (r=0.32, p=0.001). Similar re-
sults were reported by Scattoni et al. [19]. </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:527-532 </p>

<p>Subclinical Inflammation and PSA </p>



<p>While some authors did not find any correlation between 
tPSA levels and subclinical inflammation, others found the 
correlation to be significant [9,20]. Okada et al. [17] re-
viewed cases of negative prostate biopsy results. In that 
study, the presence of inflammation correlated sig-
nificantly with tPSA levels. Brawer et al. [6] found elevated 
tPSA levels only in patients with clinically acute 
prostatitis. Pansadoro et al. [7] found elevated tPSA values 
in 71% of patients with acute prostatitis, 15% of patients 
with chronic prostatitis, and 6% of patients with non-
bacterial prostatitis. The results from our study agree with 
those of Nickel et al. [9] and Kwak et al. [8], who found no 
correlation between tPSA levels and type or extent of 
inflammation. 
The present study was performed to draw attention to 
the effect of subclinical inflammation on fPSA and f/tPSA 
values. Our results confirm our hypothesis and those of oth-
ers that more acute histological inflammation of the pros-
tate induces a significant decrease of fPSA and f/tPSA val-
ues, compared with more chronic inflammation, although 
the scattergram of f/tPSA related to tPSA values showed 
overlap among all data (Fig. 2) [12,13]. Patients with more 
acute inflammation tended to group below the horizontal 
line that represented the 18% f/tPSA cutoff for more effi-
cient discrimination between PC and benign conditions. 
That cutoff was previously shown to be the limit with the 
highest efficiency to differentiate between BPH and PC 
[21]. These data emphasize that all benign prostatic dis-
eases do not differ from PC in regard to f/tPSA. 
Only a few studies have evaluated fPSA in patients with 
asymptomatic inflammation. Many studies confirm that it 
can cause a rise of tPSA, but there are major discrepancies 
in findings when we look at fPSA values. Morote et al. [11] 
studied patients without evidence of PC in TRUS-guided 
biopsies. In that study, the size of the prostate was the only 
significant contributor to the PSA concentration. In a study 
performed by Minardi et al. [22], inflammation associated 
with BPH compared with BPH only led to false-positive 
tPSA and f/tPSA levels, because 60% of these patients had 
an f/tPSA ratio below l6%. Our results comply with those 
of Jung et al. [12] and Meyer et al. [13], who reported re-
duced f/tPSA values in patients with PC and inflammation 
compared with controls or BPH patients. On the other 
hand, our results differ from those of Ornstein et al. [10], 
who showed that f/tPSA levels do not appear to be altered 
by inflammation. However, those results must be consid-
ered preliminary because Ornstein et al. [10] did not strat-
ify the patients by the type of inflammation present. 
Opposite to our results, Scattoni et al. [19] reported that 
histologically more acute inflammation induces an in-
crease in the f/tPSA ratio, whereas chronic inflammation 
seems to induce lower f/tPSA ratios in patients without PC. 
Because our results confirm that histological inflamma-
tion (especially more acute) is characterized by slightly ele-
vated tPSA (and decreased fPSA values), f/tPSA fails to dif-
ferentiate between cancerous and noncancerous prostatic 
disease. </p>

<p>It is assumed that inflammation increases PSA concen-
trations by causing leakage of PSA from acini. However, in-
creased PSA concentrations have only been found when 
glandular epithelium was disrupted [23]. Recent studies 
have demonstrated that acute, clinical inflammation pro-
duces a more intense or different process of PSA release 
than does subclinical inflammation of the prostate [24,25]. 
All our patients had different patterns of inflammation but 
had no signs of clinical prostatitis. Changes in tPSA values 
between groups were minimal and were not statistically 
significant (the acute inflammation group had slightly 
higher tPSA values), but patients with more acute histo-
logical inflammation had significantly decreased fPSA and 
f/tPSA values. The molecular reasons for these inflamma-
tion-related changes in the PSA forms are still not defined. 
PSA exists in different forms [26]. It is predominantly 
bound to l-antichymotrypsin with approximately 70% to 
90% of tPSA in serum. The approximately 10% to 30% of 
tPSA that is not bound to proteins represents fPSA. Thus, 
changes in f/tPSA reflect changes in fPSA or PSA 1-an-
tichymotripsin. As in PC, the changed f/tPSA in subclinical 
prostatitis similarly proves that PSA 1-antichymotripsin 
is elevated compared with fPSA. Bjork et al. [26] showed 
that 1-antichymotripsin is also synthesized in PC cells 
but not in BPH cells. In that way, more PSA is complexed 
in PC than in BPH, leading to the changes observed in 
serum. Similar changes can occur in prostatic inflamma-
tion, because increased 1-antichymotripsin production is 
a typical reaction to inflammation. Another explanation 
was proposed by Zackrisson et al. [27], who studied the evo-
lution of tPSA and fPSA and their ratios during 1-year fol-
low-up after febrile UTI [27]. Most men in their study had 
a rise in fPSA and tPSA during the acute phase of the UTI. 
After 1 month, fPSA rapidly decreased to the levels that 
were maintained during the rest of the follow-up period, 
but elevations of tPSA were sustained for up to 6 months 
after the acute phase of UTI. These changes in tPSA and 
fPSA levels during the chronic phase of UTI could falsely 
be interpreted as a sign of PC. It was previously shown that 
the fPSA molecule has a much shorter mean half-life than 
does tPSA [26]. 
Our results imply that the decreased level of serum fPSA 
and f/tPSA is not typical of PC alone, because these values 
are similarly affected by subclinical inflammation. Despite 
the significant effect of subclinical inflammation on fPSA 
and f/tPSA levels, we cannot deduce if the f/tPSA is a reli-
able discriminator between PC and prostatitis. Neither 
clinical examination nor PSA permits reliable discrim-
ination of PC and prostatitis, especially in patients with 
PSA levels up to 10 ng/mL. These patients should undergo 
prostate biopsy. On the other hand, when we find consid-
erable inflammation in our biopsy report, but no evidence 
of PC, long-term antibiotic or anti-inflammatory therapy 
seems like a reasonable option. Bozeman et al. [28] showed 
that the use of antibiotics for 4 weeks normalized tPSA and 
fPSA levels in 30% of studied patients. In this way, un-
necessary biopsies could be avoided in a considerable num-</p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2014;55:527-532 </p>



<p>Stimac et al </p>

<p>ber of patients. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Inflammation has an important prevalence in cancer-free 
prostate biopsy specimens. Subclinical inflammation 
seems to have a significant influence on fPSA and f/tPSA 
values in patients with tPSA levels up to 10 ng/mL but with-
out detectable PC. Subclinical inflammation is not charac-
terized by elevated tPSA concentrations alone but also by 
a decreased percentage of fPSA, a tendency similar to that 
in PC. In the assessment of biopsy results negative for PC, 
it might be helpful to evaluate the degree and extension of 
histological inflammation, especially in terms of the neces-
sity for subsequent repeated biopsies. </p>

<p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST 
The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>



</text></tei>