<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4837866" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>2+ </p>

<p>-binding chaperone mainly resident in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) lumen. Recently, it has 
been shown that non-ER CRT regulates a wide array of cellular responses. We previously found that CRT was up-regulated during hypoxia/ 
reoxygenation (H/R) and this study was aimed to investigate whether CRT nuclear translocation aggravates ER stress (ERS)-associated 
apoptosis during H/R injury in neonatal rat cardiomyocytes. 
Methods: Apoptosis rate and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) leakage in culture medium were measured as indices of cell injury. 
Immunofluorescence staining showed the morphological changes of ER and intracellular translocation of CRT. Western blotting or reverse 
transcription polymerase chain reaction was used to detect the expression of target molecules. 
Results: Compared with control, H/R increased apoptosis rate and LDH activity. The ER became condensed and bubbled, and CRT 
translocated to the nucleus. Western blotting showed up-regulation of CRT, Nrf2, activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4), CHOP and 
caspase-12 expression after H/R. Exogenous CRT overexpression induced by plasmid transfection before H/R increased cell apoptosis, 
LDH leakage, ER disorder, CRT nuclear translocation and the expression of ERS-associated molecules. However, administration of the 
ERS inhibitor, taurine, or CRT siRNA alleviated cell injury, ER disorder, and inhibited ERS-associated apoptosis. 
Conclusions: Our results indicated that during H/R stress, CRT translocation increases cell apoptosis and LDH leakage, aggravates ER 
disorder, up-regulates expression of nuclear transcription factors, Nrf2 and ATF4, and activates ERS-associated apoptosis. </p>

<p>Key words: Apoptosis; Calreticulin; CCAAT/Enhancer-binding Protein Homologous Protein; Endoplasmic Reticulum; 
Hypoxia/Reoxygenation </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Prof. Xiu-Hua Liu, 
Department of Pathophysiology, Chinese People's Liberation Army 
General Hospital, 28 Fuxing Road, Beijing 100853, China 
E-Mail: xiuhualiu98@163.com </p>

<p>Original Article </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.150103 </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 3 </p>

<p>
translocation from the ER to the cytosol, CRT is the only 
known mammalian protein that is translocated from the ER 
without being degraded. 
[6] Over the past decade, the effects 
of non-ER CRT located in other parts of the cell, plasma 
membrane, and extracellular matrix in many physiological 
processes have been well described, such as cell adhesion, 
phagocytosis, apoptosis and tumor recognition. 
[2,6] The exact 
mechanism underlying the pro-apoptotic effect of non-ER 
CRT has not been clarified. </p>

<p>We hypothesized that during H/R, CRT is translocated to the 
nucleus, promoting expression of ER stress (ERS)-associated 
transcription factors such as Nrf2 and activating transcription 
factor 4 (ATF4), causing ER damage and subsequent 
apoptosis. To test this hypothesis, CRT was overexpressed 
by either plasmid transfection or knockdown by siRNA 
interference in cardiomyocytes. Results showed that CRT 
overexpression aggravated its' nuclear translocation and 
ERS-associated apoptosis induced by H/R. ERS inhibitor, 
taurine, and CRT siRNA alleviated its' translocation and 
cell injury. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Cell culture and experimental protocol </p>

<p>All procedures were performed in accordance with the guide 
for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals published by 
the US National Institutes of Health (Publication No. 85-23,  revised 1996), and approved by the animal care and use 
committee of Chinese People's Liberation Army General 
Hospital. Primary cultures of cardiac myocytes from neonatal 
Sprague-Dawley rats (born within 24 hours) were prepared 
as previously described. 
[7] Briefly, ventricular tissue was 
enzymatically dissociated, and the resulting cell suspension 
was enriched. The dispersed cells were preplated for 
1.5 hours to minimize fibroblast contamination. Cells were 
plated at 2.5-3.0 × 10 
5 cells/ml onto poly-D-lysine-coated 
coverslips, well plates or dishes and cultured in Dulbecco's 
modified Eagle's medium (Gibco-Invitrogen, Carlsbad, 
CA, USA) supplemented with 10% neonatal bovine 
serum (PAA, Linz, Austria), 3.7 g/ml sodium bicarbonate 
and 100 mg/ml ampicillin. Cardiomyocytes were randomly 
divided into the following groups for treatment: (1) 
normal control (C); (2) hypoxia (95% N 2 -5% CO 2 ) 
for 8 hours and reoxygenation (95% air-5% CO 2 ) for 
16 hours (H/R); (3) overexpression by transfection with 
pcDNA3.1-CRT for 24 hours prior to H/R (CRT); (4) 
vector control transfection with pcDNA3.1 for 24 hours 
prior to H/R (pcDB); (5) stealth RNAi transfection for 
24 hours prior to H/R (siCRT); (6) negative control siRNA 
transfection for 24 prior to H/R (si-neg). 40 mmol/L taurine 
was administrated just before hypoxia to inhibit ERS. The 
treatments of the experiment were shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>Plasmid construction </p>

<p>The open reading frame of rattus norvegicus CRT (rCRT) 
gene deposited in GenBank database (accession number 
NM_022399) was cloned from a cDNA library of rat </p>

<p>spleen by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) with the 
primers 5'-CCTCGGCCCACCATGCTCC-3' and 5'-GT 
GGCCTCTACAGCT CATCC-3'. rCRT full-length gene was 
linked using pGEM-T Easy (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) 
and subcloned into pcDNA3.1/Myc-His(-) B (Invitrogen). </p>

<p>Stealth RNAi™ siRNA construction </p>

<p>Calreticulin Stealth RNAi™ siRNA duplexes were 
designed and synthesized by Invitrogen Co., CA, USA. 
The sequences were designed to target the rattus norvegicus 
CRT (rCRT) gene (NM_022399). Sense primer: 5'-UUG 
GCUUGUCUGCAACCCUUUAUCC-3'. Antisense primer: 
5'-GGAUAAAGGGUUGCAGACAAGCCA A-3'). </p>

<p>Cardiomyocyte viability, lactate dehydrogenase leakage, 
and apoptosis </p>

<p>Cell viability was measured using a Trypan Blue Exclusion 
test as previously described. 
[8] Lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) 
activity in the culture medium was measured by the LDH 
assay kit (Sigma) according to the kit protocol. The cell 
apoptosis rate was analyzed by the annexin V-propidium 
iodide (PI) apoptosis detection kit (KeyGen) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions, using quantitative fluorescence 
activated cell sorter (BD FACSCalibur, America). </p>

<p>Immunocytofluorescence staining </p>

<p>Cardiomyocytes were grown on coverslips at a 
density of 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>/cm 
2 and immunofluorescence was performed 
as previously described. 
[9] Briefly, the cells were fixed 
in prechilled methanol at −20°C for 5 minutes and 4% 
paraformaldehyde at room temperature for another 
15 minutes, the slides were then blocked by the addition 
of 10% donkey serum in phosphate-buffered saline 
containing 0.1% triton X-100 for 30 minutes. We identified 
cells by indirect immunofluorescent staining with an 
anti-CRT rabbit polyclonal antibody (1:50, Stressgen), and 
anticoncanavalin A 
[10] goat polyclonal antibody (1:100, 
vector laboratories) overnight at 4°C. Then they were stained 
with TexasRed-conjugated donkey antirabbit (Santa Cruz 
Biotechnology) and fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated </p>

<p>Table 1: Experiment Treatments </p>

<p>Experiment 
groups </p>

<p>Plasmid/siRNA 
transfection </p>

<p>Taurine 
Hypoxia/ 
reoxygenation </p>

<p>C 
-
-
-
H/R 
-
-
√ 
CRT 
√ 
-
√ 
pcDB 
√ 
-
√ 
siCRT 
√ 
-
√ 
si-neg 
√ 
-
√ 
CRT+tau 
√ 
√ 
√ 
pcDB+tau 
√ 
√ 
√ 
C: Normal control; H/R: Hypoxia/reoxygenation; CRT: CRT 
overexpression+H/R; pcDB: pcDB plasmid transfection+H/R; 
siCRT: CRT siRNA interference+H/R; si-neg: Negative control 
siRNA+H/R; CRT+tau: CRT overexpression+40 mM taurine+H/R; 
pcDB+tau: pcDB plasmid transfection+40 mM taurine+H/R. √: The 
treatment was taken; CRT: Calreticulin. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 3 </p>



<p>donkey antigoat IgG (Santa Cruz Biotechnology). The 
coverslips were mounted on glass slides with mounting 
medium and DAPI (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, 
USA). Images were obtained under a confocal scanning 
microscope (Zeiss LSM-510 Meta, Jena, Germany). A ×60 
oil immersion objective with a numerical aperture of 1.4 
was used. </p>

<p>Isolation of total RNA and reverse transcription 
polymerase chain reaction (PCR) </p>

<p>The total RNA isolation and reverse transcription PCR 
involved the use of the EasyScript First-strand cDNA 
Synthesis Super-Mix Kit (TransGen, Beijing, China) 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. Primers for 
glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) and 
CRT were in Table 2. The PCR products were separated on 
1.5% agarose gel and photographed for analysis. </p>

<p>Separation of cytoplasmic and nuclear extracts </p>

<p>The NE-PER nuclear and cytoplasmic extraction 
reagents (Thermo Scientific. Cat No. 78833) were 
used to separate cytoplasmic and nuclear extracts 
from cardiomyocytes, according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. 
[11] The antibody for Histone H3 (a nucleus 
control protein, Cell Signaling, Cat No. 9715) and 
the antibody for Rho guanine nucleotide dissociation 
inhibitor-α (GDI-α) (H-43) (a cytoplasmic control protein, 
Santa Cruz, Cat No. sc-292544) were used to verify the 
effectiveness of separation. The relative level of analyzed 
nuclear proteins was normalized to that of Histone H3, and 
the relative level of cytoplasmic proteins was normalized 
to that of GDI. </p>

<p>Western blotting analyses </p>

<p>Cardiomyocytes were lysed, and protein extraction was 
performed as previously described. 
[12] The soluble supernatant 
of the extracts was determined by the Bradford method, and 
16 samples of 50 mg protein were prepared and separated 
on 10% acrylamide gels. The separated proteins were 
electrophoretically transferred to nitrocellulose membranes, 
blocked with 5% bovine serum albumin in tris-buffered 
saline Tween 20, containing 20 mmol/l tris-HCl (pH 7.6), 
137 mmol/l NaCl and 0.1% Tween 20. The membranes 
were incubated with the antibodies against CRT (1:1000, 
Stressgen), Nrf2 (1:1000, Santa Cruz), ATF4 (1:1000, Santa 
Cruz), glucose-regulated protein 78 (GRP78) (1:1000, Santa 
Cruz), CHOP (1:200, Santa Cruz), caspase-12 (1:1000, Santa </p>

<p>Cruz), caspase-3 (1:1000, Santa Cruz), Bax (1:200, Santa 
Cruz), Bcl-2 (1:200, Santa Cruz) and GAPDH (1:500, Santa 
Cruz), respectively overnight at 4°C. After incubation for 
2 hours with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary 
antibodies, the reaction was visualized using an enhanced 
chemiluminescence kit (Santa Cruz Biotechnology). The 
integrated optical density (mean intensity × area) of proteins 
was quantified using <rs type="software">Image-Pro Plus</rs>. The relative level 
of analyzed protein expression was normalized to that of 
GAPDH. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Each experiment was performed at least in triplicate and 
cardiomyocytes were pooled from three to four different rat 
litters. Our data from three to four experiments was pooled 
and analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">13.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, 
IL, USA); data are presented as mean ± standard deviation. 
Differences observed between the two groups were analyzed 
by two-sample t-tests for independent samples and among 
groups by one-way analysis of variance with Newman-Keuls 
posttest analysis. A P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>Cardiomyocyte injury represented by cell viability, 
lactate dehydrogenase leakage, and apoptosis rate </p>

<p>We examined H/R-induced cell injury and the effects of 
either CRT overexpression or RNA interference. Cell 
viability was measured using the Trypan Blue Exclusion 
test, and LDH activity in the culture medium was used 
to reflect cellular membrane permeability. The cellular 
apoptosis rate was identified using annexin V-PI double 
staining and quantified using a BD Biosciences FACSCalibur 
flow cytometer [Figure 1a]. Compared with control, the cell 
apoptosis rate and LDH activity in a medium increased in 
the H/R group [Figure 1c] (P &lt; 0.05), while cell survival rate 
decreased [Figure 1d]. The CRT over-expression exaggerated 
H/R injury, and compared with H/R group, apoptosis rate 
and LDH activity increased [Figure 1b and 1c] (P &lt; 0.05), 
while cell survival rate decreased [Figure 1d] (P &lt; 0.05). 
Either siRNA interference or taurine protected H/R injury. 
Compared with H/R group, apoptosis rate and LDH activity 
both decreased [Figure 1b and 1c] (P &lt; 0.05), while cell 
survival rate increased [Figure 1d] (P &lt; 0.05). Either the 
pcDNA3.1 plasmid (vector) or negative control siRNA 
transfection showed no significant differences compared 
with H/R (P &gt; 0.05). To conclude, H/R induced cell apoptosis 
and LDH leakage, CRT overexpression exaggerated H/R 
injury, while CRT siRNA and taurine protected H/R injury. </p>

<p>mRNA and protein expression of CRT </p>

<p>Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction and Western 
blot were used to detect the mRNA and protein expression of 
CRT [Figure 1e and 1f]. H/R upregulated CRT mRNA and 
protein expression compared with control (P &lt; 0.05). There 
was successful overexpression of CRT induced by plasmid 
transfection compared with vector transfection (P &lt; 0.05). </p>

<p>Table 2: Primer Sequences for RT-PCR </p>

<p>Sequences (forward and reverse) 
Product length (bp) </p>

<p>CRT 
P1:5'-CAAGGATATCCG GTG TAA GGA-3' 
P2: 5'-CAT AGA TAT TCG CAT CGG GG-3' </p>

<p>445 </p>

<p>GAPDH 
P1:5'-TGC TGA GTA TGT CGT GGA G-3' 
P2: 5'-GTC TTC TGA GTG GCA GTG AT-3 </p>

<p>288 </p>

<p>CRT: 
Calreticulin; 
GAPDH: 
Glyceraldehydes-3-phosphate 
dehydrogenase; RT-PCR: Real time-polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 3 </p>

<p>
Stealth siRNA transfection both down-regulated CRT 
expression at mRNA and protein level compared with 
negative control siRNA transfection (P &lt; 0.05). It indicated 
that CRT overexpression and knockdown were successful. </p>

<p>Immunocytofluorescence staining </p>

<p>Concanavalin A is a nonspecific ER stain, which could 
stain the nuclear envelope, the rough ER, and the matrix 
of some multivesicular bodies. However, it has been used 
as an accepted marker to visualize the structure of ER. </p>

<p>[13]   Figure 2 showed the results of co-immunocytoflurescene 
of concanavalin A (green) and CRT (red). During the 
resting state, the ER displayed as homogeneous faint </p>

<p>green fluorescence, distributed around the nuclei. The red 
fluorescence representing CRT was mainly co-localized 
with concanavalin A, showing weak intensity in the 
nuclear area. After H/R, the green fluorescence of ER 
became condensed, grainy and bubbled. The fluorescence 
intensity of CRT increased, no longer overlapping with 
concanavalin A, and the low fluorescence area of the nuclei 
disappeared, suggesting that CRT translocated from ER 
to nuclei. CRT overexpression aggravated the structural 
disorder of ER, and the CRT nuclear translocation 
became obvious. RNA interference knockdown the total 
expression of CRT and the phenomena of ER bubbling 
and CRT nuclear translocation eventually decreased. </p>

<p>Figure 1: The cell injuries induced by hypoxia/reoxygenation (H/R) and the effects of calreticulin (CRT) over-expression and siRNA interference 
and taurine administration. Cardiomyocytes were transfected by either pcDNA3.1-CRT or pcDNA3.1 or either stealth siRNA or negative control 
siRNA for 24 hours, then hypoxia for 8 hours and reoxygenation for 16 hours. 40 mmol/L taurine was administrated prior to hypoxia to inhibit 
endoplasmic reticulum stress. (a) Images of flow cytometry. (b) The statistical analysis graph of apoptosis rate analyzed by flow cytometry. (c) 
Lactate dehydrogenase activity of culture medium. (d) cardiomyocyte survival rate. (e) The mRNA expression and the statistical analysis graph of 
CRT and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH). (f) The protein expression and the statistical analysis graph of CRT and GAPDH 
(P &lt; 0.05 vs. control, </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. H/R). Each experiment had been repeated for 3 times. </p>

<p>d 
c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 3 </p>



<p>Protein expression of transcription factors and markers 
of endoplasmic reticulum -stress and apoptosis </p>

<p>Cytoplasmic and nuclear extracts were separated 
by NE-PER nuclear and cytoplasmic extraction 
reagents (Thermo Scientific. Cat No. 78833). Following 
H/R, the protein expression of CRT in the nuclear 
extracts increased compared with the control and 
hypoxic preconditioning (HPC) groups (P &lt; 0.05). 
Hypoxic preconditioning also induced CRT nuclear 
translocation, but the extent was much lower than 
the H/R group (P &lt; 0.05) [Figure 3a and 3b]. Along 
with the translocation of CRT from ER to nucleus, the 
expression of transcription factors such as Nrf2 and ATF4 
in nuclear extracts increased [Figure 3a and 3b compared 
with control] (P &lt; 0.05). H/R notably up-regulated 
the specific ERS markers, such as GRP78, CHOP and 
caspase-12 [Figure 4] (P &lt; 0.05). It suggested that H/R 
induces ERS. Among these markers, GRP78 is a protective 
molecule and CRT overexpression, siRNA interference 
and taurine had no obvious effects on the up-regulation 
of GRP78 induced by H/R [Figure 4b] (P &gt; 0.05). With 
regard to the pro-apoptotic molecules such as CHOP 
and caspase-12, CRT over-expression increased their 
expressions to a higher degree [Figure 4b] (P &lt; 0.05); 
however, taurine administration and CRT siRNA 
interference decreased the expression of CHOP and 
caspase-12 [Figure 4b] (P &lt; 0.05). CRT overexpression 
aggravated the apoptosis-promoting effect of H/R 
associated with ERS, while taurine and CRT siRNA 
alleviated ERS-associated apoptosis. In regard to 
general apoptosis-associated markers [Figure 5a], H/R 
up-regulated the pro-apoptotic molecules caspase-3 and 
Bax, while down-regulated the antiapoptotic molecule 
Bcl-2 [Figure 5b] (P &lt; 0.05). CRT over-expression 
exacerbated the H/R effect, and the expression of 
caspase-3 and Bax increased while Bcl-2 expression 
decreased [Figure 5b] (P &lt; 0.05). Taurine and CRT siRNA 
inhibited the up-regulation of caspase-3 and Bax, and the 
down-regulation of Bcl-2 [Figure 5b] (P &lt; 0.05), indicating 
that these treatments relieved apoptosis induced by H/R. </p>

<p>dIscussIon </p>

<p>Myocardial ischemia-reperfusion injury is a serious concern 
to human health. Thrombolytic therapy is widely used to 
rescue ischemic myocardium, but its beneficial effect is often 
limited by cardiomyocyte oxidative stress induced by either 
I/R or H/R. Such injury threatens cardiomyocyte integrity 
and survival, and it is associated with ER dysfunction. </p>

<p>[14]   The ER is an important sub-cellular organelle for protein 
folding, lipid synthesis, and calcium storage. Disturbance of 
ER homeostasis results in ERS, acting as a mediator between 
survival and apoptosis. This study demonstrates that CRT, a 
major ER Ca 
2+ binding chaperone with multiple functions, 
translocates from the ER to the other parts of the cell during 
cardiomyocyte H/R, promotes ER dysfunction, and induces 
ERS-associated apoptosis. </p>

<p>Figure 2: Co-immunocytoflurescene of concanavalin A (green) and 
calreticulin (CRT) (Red). During the resting state, the endoplasmic 
reticulum displayed a homogeneous faint green fluorescence, distributed 
around the nuclei. The red fluorescence representing CRT was mainly 
co-localized with concanavalin A, showing weak intensity in the nuclear 
area. After hypoxia/reoxygenation (H/R), the green fluorescence of the 
endoplasmic reticulum (ER) became condensed, grainy and bubbled. 
The fluorescence intensity of CRT increased, no longer overlapped 
with concanavalin A, and the low fluorescence area of the nuclei 
disappeared, suggesting that CRT translocated from ER to the nuclei. 
CRT overexpression aggravated the structural disorder of ER, and the 
CRT nuclear translocation became obvious. RNA interference knocked-
down the total expression of CRT and the phenomena of ER bubbling 
and CRT nuclear translocation eventually decreased. The control plasmid 
(pCDB) or negative control siRNA (si-neg) transfection had no effect 
on ER disorder and CRT re-distribution induced by H/R. CRT + H/R 
represented transfection with CRT plasmid 24 hours before H/R. pcDB 
+ H/R represented transfection with control plasmid 24 hours before 
H/R. siCRT + H/R represented transfection with CRT siRNA 24 hours 
before H/R. si-neg + H/R represented transfection with siRNA control 
24 hours before H/R. The cell density for immunocytofluorescence 
analysis was 1 × 10 
4 cell/cm 
2 and the transfection efficiency of our 
experiment was about 65%. Each experiment was repeated in triplicate. </p>

<p>While the control plasmid (pCDB) or negative control 
siRNA (si-neg) transfection had no effect on ER disorder 
and CRT re-distribution induced by H/R. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 3 </p>

<p>
Calreticulin has long been known as an ER luminal protein, 
and previous reports mainly focused on its function as 
a calcium binding chaperone, regulating intracellular 
Ca 
2+ homeostasis and protein folding. However, it is difficult 
to explain the controversial effects of CRT during apoptosis 
induced by ischemia, hypoxia or oxidative stress in different 
cell types. In recent years, it has been found that CRT has 
multiple functions in the other intracellular compartments, 
cell surface, and extracellular matrix. 
[2,6] Agents that directly 
lower ER Ca 
2+ levels can induce the rapid translocation of 
presynthesized CRT from the ER. 
[6] Once CRT translocates 
to the cytosol, it can be posttranslationally modified by 
arginyl transferase, which attaches an arginine residue to the 
N-terminal aspartic acid residue of the protein and localizes 
CRT to cytoplasmic stress granules. 
[15] It has also been 
reported that CRT can bind to the KxGFFKR sequence of 
many nuclear transcription factors, such as glucocorticoid 
receptor, regulating gene transcription. </p>

<p>[16]   Cardiomyocytes over-expressing CRT exhibit increased 
intracellular calcium as well as either an expression or 
activity of pro-apoptotic factors such as Bax, p53, caspase-8 
and caspase-3, together with reduced antiapoptotic factor 
Bcl-2. 
[17] The direct inhibition of CRT overexpression induced 
by either I/R or H/R injury through the endogenous protective 
phenomena such as IPC or hypoxic preconditioning (HPC), 
alleviates cardiomyocyte apoptosis, 
[5] inhibits caspase-12 
activation in vitro, limits myocardial infarct size, improves 
heart function in vivo, and is consistent with its effect in 
rat skeletal muscle cells. 
[18] Recently, we found that CRT 
inhibition by antisense oligonucleotides weakened hypoxic 
postconditioning protection, and at the same time, attenuated 
H/R injury. 
[5] Based on previous studies, this work focused 
on the changes of CRT subcellular localization induced 
by H/R and its effect on ERS-associated apoptosis. We 
further hypothesized that H/R injury may up-regulate CRT 
expression and affect its subcellular localization. Other than </p>

<p>Figure 3: Cytoplasmic and nuclear extracts were separated using NE-PER nuclear and cytoplasmic extraction reagents. The relative amounts of 
protein expression levels of calreticulin (CRT), Nrf2, activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4). (a) Results of Western blotting of CRT, Nrf2, ATF4, 
Rho guanine nucleotide dissociation inhibitor-α (GDI-α) and Histone H3. Rho GDI was used as the endogenous loading control for cytoplasmic 
protein, and Histone H3 was used as the endogenous loading control of nuclear protein. (b) Statistical analysis of relative expression levels of 
nuclear and cytoplasmic proteins. The relative level of analyzed nucleus proteins was normalized to that of histone H3, and the relative level 
of cytoplasmic proteins was normalized to that of GDI. After hypoxia/reoxygenation (H/R), the protein expression of CRT in nuclear extracts 
increased compared with the control group and hypoxic preconditioning (HPC) group (P &lt; 0.05). Hypoxic preconditioning also induced CRT 
nuclear translocation, but the extent was much lower than H/R group (P &lt; 0.05) [Figure 4a and 4b]. Each experiment was repeated in triplicate 
( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 vs. control, 
 † P&lt;0.05 vs. H/R). </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Figure 4: The relative amounts of protein expression levels of molecular markers associated with ER stress, such as glucose-regulated protein 78 
(GRP78), CHOP and caspase-12. (a) Results from Western blotting of GRP78, CHOP, caspase-12 and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase 
(GAPDH). (b) The statistical analysis graph of relative expression levels of these markers normalized to that of GAPDH. Hypoxia for 8 hours 
and reoxygenation for 16 hours (hypoxia/reoxygenation [H/R]) up-regulated the expressions of GRP78, CHOP and caspase-12. Among them, 
GRP78 was a protective molecule and calreticulin (CRT) over-expression, siRNA interference and taurine administration had no obvious effects 
on up-regulation of GRP78 induced by H/R. With regard to the pro-apoptotic molecules such as CHOP and caspase-12, CRT over-expression 
increased, while siRNA interference and taurine administration decreased their expression. Each experiment was repeated in triplicate. 
* P &lt; 0.05 
vs. control ( 
 † P&lt;0.05 vs. H/R). </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 3 </p>



<p>its functions of re-establishing ER Ca 
2+ homeostasis and 
restoring proper protein folding in the ER lumen, CRT may 
have other effects on ERS -associated apoptosis. Either brief 
ischemic or hypoxic stress lead to the induction of CRT as 
an ER chaperone, and further succeeds in re-establishing 
ER homeostasis, while prolonged ischemia or hypoxia may 
induce CRT overexpression and translocation from the ER 
to the cytosol and disturb the anti-and pro-apoptotic balance 
of unfolded protein response, leading to an apoptotic fate. </p>

<p>This study showed that hypoxia re-oxygenation increased 
cell apoptosis and the permeability of the cell membrane, 
the appearance of ER condensation, and the bubbling 
phenomena. Along with the nuclear translocation of CRT, 
the expression of transcription factors such as Nrf2 
[19] and 
ATF4 in nuclear extracts also increased. The expression 
of ER-associated apoptosis markers, such as CHOP and 
caspase-12 increased, and the expression ratio of Bcl-2 to 
Bax decreased. Exogenous CRT overexpression aggravated 
cardiomyocyte H/R injury, causing cell apoptosis, and an 
increase in necrosis rate and cell membrane permeability. 
Additionally, the activity of LDH in the culture medium 
was increased, and ER morphology injury was aggravated. 
The nuclear translocation of CRT and the activation of 
ERS-associated apoptosis pathway further increased. There 
was a positive correlation between the over-expression of 
CRT induced by H/R and the up-regulation of pro-apoptotic 
molecules such as CHOP and caspase-12 associated 
with ERS. Taurine is a conditionally essential amino 
acid, which is high in the myocardium (10-40 mmol/L), 
playing cytoprotective role, including calcium modulation, 
membrane stabilization, osmoregulation, antioxidation, 
protein phosphorylation, and ion flux. Our previous work has 
confirmed that taurine inhibits ERS in the myocardium, </p>

<p>[20]   and in our in vitro experiment we used 40 mmol/L of 
taurine as an ERS inhibitor according to the dose reported 
in the literature. 
[21] This work showed that taurine and CRT 
siRNA interference both attenuated injuries induced by 
H/R, showing reversed damages to ER structure, decreased </p>

<p>CRT distribution in ER and nucleus, and the expression 
of pro-apoptotic molecules. When ERS is overactive, as a 
multifunctional protein, CRT may retro-translocate to the 
other parts of the cell and no longer play a protective role, 
promoting ER dysfunction and participating in the activation 
of the ERS-associated apoptosis cascade. H/R induced 
CRT over-expression and translocation, aggravating ER 
dysfunction and activating the ERS-associated apoptosis 
pathway to enhance cardiomyocyte damage. </p>

<p>It has been reported that during ERS-associated apoptosis, 
the expression of CRT, Nrf2 and ATF4 were up-regulated, </p>

<p>[22]   but the exact relationship between these factors has not been 
clarified. We found that along with CRT nuclear translocation, 
the expression of Nrf2 and ATF4 in nuclear extraction 
increased, suggesting that CRT nuclear translocation 
induced by H/R might participate in regulating nuclear 
transcription factor expression and gene transcription. 
CHOP, also named growth arrest and DNA damage inducible 
gene 153 (GADD153), can directly regulate nuclear target 
genes to increase the tendency of cell apoptosis. CHOP 
up-regulation increased cell sensitivity to apoptosis induced 
by ERS. 
[23] CHOP over-expressing cells displayed cell cycle 
arrest, Bcl-2 down-regulation and Bax translocation from the 
cytoplasm to the mitochondria and eventually to apoptosis. 
Furthermore, CHOP-induced apoptosis may be blocked by 
either Bcl-2 overexpression or the knockout of Bax. In our 
study, CRT over-expression up-regulated CHOP and Bax, 
and down-regulated Bcl-2, while taurine administration and 
the siRNA interference had opposite effects, indicating that 
CRT overexpression may be involved in the CHOP-related 
apoptotic pathway during cardiomyocyte H/R injury. </p>

<p>Casapse-12 is localized to the ER and activated by ERS, 
including the disruption of ER calcium homeostasis and 
the accumulation of excess proteins in the ER, but not 
by either membrane-or mitochondrial-targeted apoptotic 
signals. Mice that are deficient in casapse-12 are resistant to 
ERS-induced apoptosis, but their cells undergo apoptosis in </p>

<p>Figure 5: The relative amounts of protein expression levels of molecular markers associated with apoptosis, such as caspase-3, Bcl-2 and Bax. 
(a) Results of Western blotting of caspase-3, Bcl-2, Bax and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH). (b) The statistical analysis 
graph of relative expression levels of these markers normalized to that of GAPDH. Hypoxia for 8 hours and reoxygenation for 16 hours (hypoxia/ 
reoxygenation [H/R]) up-regulated the expressions of caspase-3 and Bax, and down-regulated Bcl-2 expression. calreticulin overexpression induced 
by plasmid transfection 24 h before H/R further aggravated the changes induced by H/R, while siRNA interference and taurine administration had 
the opposite effects. Each experiment was repeated in triplicate ( </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 vs. control. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 vs. H/R). </p>

<p>b 
a </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ February 5, 2015 ¦ Volume 128 ¦ Issue 3 </p>

<p>
response to other death stimuli. Thus, casapse-12 mediates 
an ER specific apoptosis pathway. 
[24] In our study, CRT 
overexpression up-regulated expression of caspase-12 
and caspase-3, while taurine administration and siRNA 
interference had opposite effects, indicating that CRT 
overexpression may be involved in the ER-specific apoptosis 
pathway during cardiomyocyte H/R injury. </p>

<p>Collectively, CRT is a major calcium-binding chaperone that 
is primarily located within the ER. Over the past decade, 
CRT has also been implicated into a variety of processes 
that occur outside of the ER lumen. From the results of the 
study, we speculated that CRT nuclear translocation might 
regulate the transcriptional activities of nuclear transcription 
factors such as Nrf2 and ATF4, affecting the transcription 
and translation of ERS-associated proteins and causing ER 
damage and subsequent apoptosis. </p>

<p>references </p>



<p>Received: 05-09-2014 Edited by: Xiu-Yuan Hao </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Xu FF, Liu XH. Calreticulin Translocation 
Aggravates Endoplasmic Reticulum Stress-associated Apoptosis during 
Cardiomyocyte Hypoxia/Reoxygenation. Chin Med J 2015;128:353-60. </p>

<p>Source of Support: This study was supported by the National Natural 
Science Foundation of China (No. 81170140 and No. 31471094). 
Conflict of Interest: None declared. </p>

</text></tei>