<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4790474" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Lignin poses a major challenge in the processing of plant 
biomass for agro-industrial applications. For bioengineering 
purposes, there is a pressing interest in identifying and char-
acterizing the enzymes responsible for the biosynthesis 
of lignin. Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:shikimate hydroxycinna-
moyl transferase (HCT; EC 2.3.1.133) is a key metabolic 
entry point for the synthesis of the most important lignin 
monomers: coniferyl and sinapyl alcohols. In this study, we 
investigated the substrate promiscuity of HCT from a bryo-
phyte (Physcomitrella) and from five representatives of 
vascular plants (Arabidopsis, poplar, switchgrass, pine and 
Selaginella) using a yeast expression system. We demonstrate 
for these HCTs a conserved capacity to acylate with p-
coumaroyl-CoA several phenolic compounds in addition to 
the canonical acceptor shikimate normally used during 
lignin biosynthesis. Using either recombinant HCT from 
switchgrass (PvHCT2a) or an Arabidopsis stem protein 
extract, we show evidence of the inhibitory effect of 
these phenolics on the synthesis of p-coumaroyl shikimate 
in vitro, which presumably occurs via a mechanism of com-
petitive inhibition. A structural study of PvHCT2a confirmed 
the binding of a non-canonical acceptor in a similar manner 
to shikimate in the active site of the enzyme. Finally, we 
exploited in Arabidopsis the substrate flexibility of HCT to 
reduce lignin content and improve biomass saccharification 
by engineering transgenic lines that overproduce one of the 
HCT non-canonical acceptors. Our results demonstrate con-
servation of HCT substrate promiscuity and provide support 
for a new strategy for lignin reduction in the effort to im-
prove the quality of plant biomass for forage and cellulosic 
biofuels. </p>

<p>Plant biomass is routinely utilized in diverse agro-industrial sec-
tors such as pulp and paper, forage, bio-manufacturing and 
bioenergy. Among several sustainable energy strategies, the 
conversion of plant cell walls into fermentable sugars offers 
the possibility for microbial production of bio-based products 
including materials (e.g. biopolymers), commodity chemicals, 
fine and specialty chemicals, and liquid fuels (Vickers et al. 2012, 
George et al. 2015). Lignin is a hydrophobic polymer that per-
meates plant cell walls and impedes the biochemical processes 
used for plant biomass conversion into fermentable sugars 
(Zeng et al. 2014). Lignin from ferns and gymnosperms contains 
p-hydroxyphenyl (H) and guaiacyl (G) units derived from p-
coumaroyl alcohol and coniferyl alcohol, respectively; and 
lignin from certain lycophytes and angiosperms additionally 
contains syringyl (S) units (Boerjan et al. 2003, Weng et al. 
2010). These lignin monomers (or monolignols) are synthesized 
from phenylalanine in the cytosol and exported to the cell wall 
for oxidative polymerization (Boerjan et al. 2003). 
In the lignin pathway, the metabolic entry point responsible 
for the production of both coniferyl and sinapyl alcohols involves 
hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:shikimate hydroxycinnamoyl transfer-
ase (HCT), which catalyzes the coupling of p-coumaroyl-CoA 
with shikimate to produce p-coumaroyl shikimate (Fig. 1) 
(Hoffman et al. 2003, Hoffman et al. 2004). Following this step, 
the hydroxycinnamoyl moiety of p-coumaroyl shikimate is 
hydroxylated by p-coumaroyl shikimate 3 
0 -hydroxylase (C3 
0 H) 
to produce caffeoyl shikimate which is then transesterified by 
HCT to release caffeoyl-CoA, or, as recently described in 
Arabidopsis, cleaved by caffeoyl shikimate esterase (CSE) to re-
lease caffeate (Fig. 1) (Franke et al. 2002, Vanholme et al. 2013a). 
Reduction of HCT activity limits the synthesis of coniferyl and 
sinapyl alcohols and causes a backlog of upstream metabolites, </p>

<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 57(3): 568-579 (2016) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcw016, Advance Access publication on 8 February 2016, 
available online at www.pcp.oxfordjournals.org 
! The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Japanese Society of Plant Physiologists. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For 
commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Regular Paper </p>

<p>which leads to a redirection of part of the metabolic flux of p-
coumaroyl-CoA into p-coumaryl alcohol. Therefore, the lignin 
from plants exhibiting strong HCT down-regulation is enriched 
in H units and its content is heavily reduced due to the poor 
capacity of p-coumaroyl alcohol to incorporate the polymer 
(Hoffman et al. 2004, Vanholme et al. 2013b). Considering its 
central role in lignin biosynthesis, HCT has been a target in 
genetic engineering strategies for improving the commercial util-
ity of plant biomass. For example, down-regulation of HCT ex-
pression reduces lignin content and improves forage digestibility 
and saccharification efficiency in alfalfa (Chen and Dixon 2007, 
Shadle et al. 2007). 
HCT belongs to the BAHD family of acyl-CoA-dependent 
transferases, which includes several enzymes that use hydroxy-
cinnamoyl-CoAs as a donor for the transfer reaction (D'Auria 
2006). These transferases are capable of acylating a wide variety 
of acceptors, and some of them exhibit broad substrate flexi-
bility (Landmann et al. 2011, Molina and Kosma 2014). For 
example, it is well known that some HCTs can use quinate as 
a substrate in addition to shikimate (Hoffman et al. 2003, 
Lallemand et al. 2012, Walker et al. 2013, Escamilla-Treviño 
et al. 2014). Moreover, HCT from globe artichoke (CcHCT) 
was shown to accept 3-hydroxyanthranilate as a substrate 
(Moglia et al. 2010), and similar substrate promiscuity was 
described for HCT from Coleus blumei, which can also use 
3-amino-and 3-hydroxybenzoates as acceptor substrates, form-
ing both p-coumarate ester and amide conjugates (Sander and 
Petersen 2011). Although HCT is a well-conserved enzyme 
among land plants (Xu et al. 2009, Tohge et al. 2013), charac-
terization of its substrate flexibility remains poorly described. 
Furthermore, until now, it had yet to be tested whether the 
substrate promiscuity of HCT could be exploited for lignin en-
gineering and improving plant biomass. </p>

<p>In this study, using a yeast expression system, we investi-
gated the substrate promiscuity of HCT from a bryophyte 
(Physcomitrella patens), a lycophyte (Selaginella moellendorffii), 
a coniferous gymnosperm (Pinus radiata), a monocot angio-
sperm (Panicum virgatum) and two dicot angiosperms (Populus 
trichocarpa and Arabidopsis thaliana) toward a series of ben-
zene and benzoate derivatives. Recombinant yeast strains that 
individually co-express these phylogenetically related HCTs 
with 4-coumarate-CoA ligase were capable of producing p-
coumaroyl conjugates when fed with p-coumarate and shiki-
mate, 3-hydroxybenzoate, 2,5-dihydroxybenzoate (gentisate), 2,3-
dihydroxybenzoate, 3,4-dihydroxybenzoate (protocatechuate), 
3-aminobenzoate, 3-hydroxyanthranilate, 5-hydroxyanthranilate, 
ortho-hydroxyphenol (catechol) and para-hydroxyphenol (hydro-
quinone). Purified recombinant HCT from switchgrass showed 
activity towards these new 'non-canonical' substrates, which con-
firmed their capacity to bind the active site of the enzyme. 
Moreover, we demonstrate that in vitro formation of p-coumar-
oyl shikimate by either a switchgrass recombinant HCT 
(PvHCT2a) or an Arabidopsis stem protein extract is partially 
inhibited in the presence of the non-canonical acceptors, presum-
ably via a mechanism of competitive inhibition. Finally, we ex-
tended this characterization to in vivo inhibition assays by 
engineering Arabidopsis lines to overproduce one of these 
HCT-competitive inhibitors (protocatechuate) in lignifying tis-
sues, and showed an approximately 30% reduction of lignin con-
tent, providing a significant improvement of biomass 
saccharification efficiency. Our results demonstrate the potential 
of inhibiting HCT in various bioenergy crops by overproducing 
unusual HCT acceptors in planta. The substrate promiscuity of 
HCT was observed in all the plant taxa we tested, and it appears 
to have been conserved since plants first appeared on land about 
450 Ma ago. This novel approach could be particularly valuable to 
reduce lignin in crops for which genomic information is still 
unavailable. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Selection and identification of HCT sequences </p>

<p>For this study, we selected HCT from Arabidopsis (AtHCT) 
since it has been shown to be genetically implicated in lignin 
biosynthesis (Hoffman et al. 2004). A HCT from the woody 
dicot poplar was also selected. In particular, out of seven 
HCT genes found in the poplar genome, PtHCT1 and PtHCT6 
have been associated with lignin biosynthesis because of their 
xylem-specific expression profile (Shi et al. 2010). PtHCT6 was 
selected for this study since it has higher catalytic efficiency 
towards coumaroyl-CoA (Wang et al. 2014). In the monocot 
switchgrass, two enzymes (PvHCT1a and PvHCT2a) have 
proven HCT activity (Escamilla-Treviño et al. 2014). PvHCT2a 
was selected for this study based on its predicted involvement 
in lignin biosynthesis according to gene expression profiling 
experiments (Shen et al. 2013). For gymnosperms, we selected 
a HCT from pine (PrHCT) for which the silencing in cell cultures 
results in reduction of lignin content (Wagner et al. 2007). 
Moreover, we conducted a phylogenetic analysis using </p>

<p>phenylalanine </p>

<p>p-coumaroyl-CoA </p>

<p>p-coumaroyl shikimate </p>

<p>feruloyl-CoA </p>

<p>p-coumaryl alcohol </p>

<p>coniferyl alcohol </p>

<p>sinapyl alcohol </p>

<p>H-unit </p>

<p>G-unit </p>

<p>HCT </p>

<p>shikimate </p>

<p>coniferaldehyde </p>

<p>sinapaldehyde 
S-unit </p>

<p>p-coumaraldehyde </p>

<p>C3'H </p>

<p>CSE </p>

<p>caffeoyl shikimate </p>

<p>caffeate </p>

<p>caffeoyl-CoA </p>

<p>HCT </p>

<p>shikimate </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Simplified representation of the lignin biosynthetic pathway. 
Abbreviations: HCT, hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:shikimate hydroxycinna-
moyl transferase; C3 
0 H, p-coumaroyl shikimate 3 
0 -hydroxylase; CSE, 
caffeoyl shikimate esterase. Dashed arrows represent the CSE-
mediated esterification of caffeoyl shikimate as described in 
Arabidopsis (Vanholme et al. 2013a). </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 57(3): 568-579 (2016) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcw016 </p>

<p>biochemically characterized hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA-depend-
ent BAHD transferases (Supplementary Table S1) and con-
firmed that AtHCT, PtHCT6, PvHCT2a and PrHCT belong to 
the same clade along with other characterized HCTs 
(Supplementary Fig. S1). In order to include a HCT from a 
lycophyte, we searched the S. moellendorffii genome for the 
presence of putative HCT homologs using AtHCT as bait. Five 
sequences were retrieved by selecting proteins whose sequence 
share at least 35% identity with that of AtHCT, and two of 
which, SmHCT1a and SmHCT1b (60% and 61% identical 
to AtHCT, respectively), fall into the 'HCT clade' 
(Supplementary Table S1; Supplementary Fig. S1). These 
two proteins (98% identical) are products of allelic variants of 
the same gene, and SmHCT1a was selected for further charac-
terization. Similarly, the genome of the bryophyte P. patens was 
analyzed for the identification of putative HCT homologs using 
AtHCT as bait. Out of the seven sequences retrieved (using a 
protein sequence identity cut-off of 30%), one protein 
(PpHCT1) falls into the 'HCT clade' and was selected for this 
study (Supplementary Table S1; Supplementary Fig. S1). </p>

<p>Screening of HCT substrate promiscuity using a 
yeast heterologous expression system </p>

<p>AtHCT, PtHCT6, PvHCT2a and PrHCT, as well as putative HCTs 
from S. moellendorffii (SmHCT1a) and P. patens (PpHCT1), were 
individually co-expressed with Arabidopsis 4-coumarate-CoA 
ligase 5 (4CL5) in yeast to investigate their substrate affinity 
toward various acceptors. In these in vivo assays, the different 
recombinant yeast strains were fed individually with p-couma-
rate in combination with shikimate (as a positive control) 
or one of the potential phenolic acceptors listed in 
Supplementary Fig. S2. These acceptors were chosen based 
on previous reports that assign this type of alternative sub-
strates for HCT (Moglia et al. 2010, Sander and Petersen, 
2011). 4CL5 converts p-coumarate into p-coumaroyl-CoA, 
which is in turn coupled to shikimate or other potential ac-
ceptors by HCT. Subsequently, we performed liquid chroma-
tography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) analysis of 
the yeast culture medium for the detection of p-coumaroyl 
conjugates produced by the different HCTs. Out of 20 phenolics 
tested, the analysis indicated that all six HCTs produced p-
coumaroyl conjugates in the presence of shikimate, 3-hydroxy-
benzoate, gentisate, 2,3-dihydroxybenzoate, protocatechuate, 
3-aminobenzoate, 3-hydroxyanthranilate, 5-hydroxyanthrani-
late, catechol and hydroquinone (Fig. 2; Supplementary 
Table S2; Supplementary Fig. S3). None of these products 
was found in the culture medium of a control yeast strain ex-
pressing 4CL5 alone and fed with p-coumarate and the corres-
ponding acceptors. For these yeast-feeding assays, the limited 
control of enzyme expression, substrate penetrability and se-
cretion of products does not allow direct comparisons of activ-
ities between the different HCTs and the various acceptors 
tested. </p>

<p>Activity and inhibition of recombinant HCT </p>

<p>PvHCT2a was expressed in Escherichia coli and purified to con-
firm its activity towards shikimate and the nine new acceptors </p>

<p>identified with the yeast screen. PvHCT2a was selected for bio-
chemical assays since its expression in E. coli yielded pure and 
high amounts of recombinant enzyme (Supplementary Fig. 
S4), as opposed to the yield obtained using AtHCT which 
was expressed almost entirely as insoluble inclusion bodies. 
Conclusively, incubations of recombinant PvHCT2a with p-
coumaroyl-CoA and shikimate, gentisate, 3-hydroxyanthranilate, 
2,3-dihydroxybenzoate, catechol, protocatechuate, 5-hydro-
xyanthranilate, 3-hydroxybenzoate, 3-aminobenzoate and 
hydroquinone resulted in the formation of the corresponding 
p-coumaroyl conjugates (Supplementary Fig. S5). The chro-
matographic peaks of these PvHCT2a products showed reten-
tion times similar to those of the p-coumaroyl conjugates 
previously characterized in the yeast feedings. In contrast, in-
cubations of PvHCT2a with only p-coumaroyl-CoA, or just the 
different acceptors, did not produce any of these reaction prod-
ucts (data not shown). Assuming similar LC-MS/MS response 
factors for the different p-coumaroyl conjugates, comparison of 
their peak intensities obtained from PvHCT2a in vitro assays 
showed that shikimate is the best substrate, followed by 3-
hydroxyanthranilate (Supplementary Fig. S6). Substrate satur-
ation curves using shikimate or the non-canonical acceptors 
were attempted to determine the affinity of PvHCT2a for 
these different substrates. Apparent substrate saturation of 
the enzyme could be achieved only in the case of shikimate, 
3-hydroxyanthranilate and protocatechuate; double reciprocal 
plots indicated K m values of 699 mM, 830 mM and 1.48 mM, 
respectively, for these three acceptors (Supplementary Fig. S7). 
For the other acceptors, the lack of enzyme saturation at high 
concentrations indicates higher K m values and much lower af-
finity of PvHCT2a for these substrates compared with shikimate 
(Supplementary Fig. S7). 
Because HCT acylates non-canonical acceptors in the pres-
ence of p-coumaroyl-CoA, we tested the influence of these 
potential competitive inhibitors on the formation of p-coumar-
oyl shikimate catalyzed by PvHCT2a in vitro. We observed that 
p-coumaroyl shikimate synthesis was reduced in reactions con-
taining p-coumaroyl-CoA and an equimolar amount of shiki-
mate and the non-canonical acceptors, in comparison with 
control reactions containing only p-coumaroyl-CoA and shiki-
mate. In particular, inhibitions of p-coumaroyl shikimate syn-
thesis ranged from 11% to 48%, depending on the acceptors 
present, and were stronger at higher concentrations (Fig. 3). In 
these reactions, the presence of p-coumaroyl conjugates 
formed from the coupling of p-coumaroyl-CoA with the non-
canonical acceptors was also detected in addition to p-coumar-
oyl shikimate (data not shown). </p>

<p>PvHCT2a substrate-binding site </p>

<p>The structure of the related HCT from Sorghum bicolor 
(SbHCT) has been described previously (Walker et al. 2013). 
As expected, the PvHCT2a structure consists of two domains, 
with the p-coumaryl-CoA-and shikimate-binding sites located 
between them. Domain I consists of N-terminal residues 1-199 
and C-terminal residues 387-409. Domain II consists exclusively 
of C-terminal residues 200-386 and 410-446 (Fig. 4A). The 
structure of PvHCT2a in complex with p-coumaroyl-CoA and </p>



<p>A. Eudes et al. | Substrate promiscuity of HCT and lignin reduction </p>

<p>shikimate reveals that the two molecules reacted during the 
soaking of the compounds into the crystal. Therefore, the prod-
uct state was observed in the electron density map, given the 
ternary complex of PvHCT2a, free CoA and p-coumaroyl shiki-
mate (Fig. 4B). A similar product state formation of p-coumar-
oyl shikimate was described for the related structure SbHCT 
(Walker et al. 2013). In contrast, our crystal structure of 
PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-protocatechuate is in a substrate 
state, i.e. the ternary complex consists of PvHCT2a, p-coumar-
oyl-CoA and protocatechuate (Fig. 4C). Data collection, </p>

<p>refinement and model statistics for both PvHCT2a-p-coumar-
oyl-CoA-shikimate and PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-protoca-
techuate structures are summarized in Supplementary 
Table S3. 
The p-coumaroyl-shikimate contacts the PvHCT2a via the 
phenolic group and carbonyl group of the p-coumaroyl portion. 
The shikimate portion contacts PvHCT2a through both the 
carboxyl and hydroxyl groups. The carbonyl group of the p-
coumaroyl moiety directly contacts Trp384 and the phenolic 
moiety interacts via water-mediated hydrogen bonds with </p>

<p>319.0820 [M-H] -</p>

<p>320.0831 
321.0925 </p>

<p>Time (min) 
1 
2 3 
4 
5 6 
7 8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>7.50 min </p>

<p>Time (min) 
1 
2 3 
4 
5 6 
7 8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>10.12 min </p>

<p>299.0562 [M-H] -</p>

<p>300.0588 </p>

<p>Time (min) 
1 
2 3 
4 
5 6 
7 8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>11.10 min </p>

<p>298.0724 [M-H] -</p>

<p>299.0744 
300.0759 </p>

<p>Time (min) 
1 
2 3 
4 
5 6 
7 8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>10.27 min </p>

<p>299.0562 [M-H] -</p>

<p>300.0595 
301.0634 </p>

<p>Time (min) 
1 
2 3 
4 
5 6 
7 8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>10.80 min </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E 
F </p>

<p>G 
H </p>

<p>I 
J </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>255.0660 [M-H] -</p>

<p>256.0688 
257.0835 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 4 
5 6 
7 
8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>13.34 min </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>299.0562 [M-H] -</p>

<p>301.2309 
300.0601 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>12.02 min </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>298.0721 [M-H] -</p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>12.54 min </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>283.0606 [M-H] -</p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>10.69 min </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>283.2627 
282.0760 [M-H] -</p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 </p>

<p>12.71 min </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>255.0654 [M-H] -</p>

<p>256.0677 </p>

<p>x10 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>x10 4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>x10 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>x10 3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>x10 4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>x10 3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>x10 3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>x10 3 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>x10 3 
2.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x10 4 </p>

<p>Intensity (counts) 
Intensity (counts) </p>

<p>Intensity (counts) 
Intensity (counts) </p>

<p>Intensity (counts) 
Intensity (counts) </p>

<p>Intensity (counts) 
Intensity (counts) </p>

<p>Intensity (counts) 
Intensity (counts) </p>

<p>Fig. 2 p-Coumaroyl conjugates produced by PvHCT2a in vivo activity assays. Representative LC-MS chromatograms of p-coumaroyl conjugates 
produced by PvHCT2a after feeding the recombinant yeast strains co-expressing At4CL5 and PvHCT2a with p-coumarate and (A) shikimate, 
(B) gentisate, (C) 3-hydroxyanthranilate, (D) 2,3-dihydroxybenzoate, (E) catechol, (F) protocatechuate, (G) 5-hydroxyanthranilate, (H) 3-hydro-
xybenzoate, (I) 3-aminobenzoate and (J) hydroquinone. Structures of p-coumaroyl hydroxybenzoates (B, D, F) are arbitrarily shown with an ester 
linkage involving the hydroxyl group on the C3 position on the carbon ring. The structure of p-coumaroyl 3-hydroxyanthranilate (C) is 
represented as determined in Moglia et al. (2010). See also Table S2. </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 57(3): 568-579 (2016) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcw016 </p>

<p>Ser38 and Tyr40. The carboxyl group of the shikimate moiety 
makes a salt bridge interaction with Arg369. While the C5 
hydroxyl group contacts the catalytic residue His163, the C3 
hydroxyl group contacts Thr382 (Fig. 4B). 
We then analyzed the structure of the protocatechuate 
ternary complex to better understand the mechanism of 
PvHCT2a. The protocatechuate binds in a very similar 
manner to shikimate, with the carboxyl group making a tight 
salt bridge with Arg369, and the C3 (equivalent to C5 in the 
shikimate moiety) hydroxyl group interacting with the nitrogen 
NE2 of His163. However, we see that the C5 (equivalent to C3 in 
the shikimate moiety) hydroxyl interaction with Thr382 is lost, 
since this hydroxyl group is absent in protocatechuate (Fig. 4C). </p>

<p>Characterization of Arabidopsis lines producing a 
competitive inhibitor of HCT in lignifying tissues </p>

<p>As a preliminary experiment, we determined the influence of 
the alternative HCT acceptors on the formation of p-coumaroyl 
shikimate catalyzed by a total protein extract from Arabidopsis 
stems. Compared with control reactions containing only p-
coumaroyl-CoA and shikimate, and except for catechol and 
5-hydroxyanthranilate, we observed reductions of p-coumaroyl 
shikimate synthesis ranging from 6.0% to 63.5% in reactions 
containing equimolar amount of the different non-canonical 
substrates, and the strongest inhibition was observed with pro-
tocatechuate (Supplementary Fig. S8). 
Since the synthesis of p-coumaroyl shikimate by protein 
extracts from Arabidopsis stems is strongly inhibited by proto-
catechuate in vitro, we attempted to generate Arabidopsis 
transgenic lines that overproduce protocatechuate from </p>

<p>chorismate to reduce lignin content. A two-gene strategy was 
employed to convert some of the endogenous chorismate pool 
into p-hydroxybenzoate-and eventually protocatechuate by 
co-expressing chorismate pyruvate-lyase from E. coli (ubiC) </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Structural study of PvHCT2a. (A) Cartoon representation of the 
monomeric PvHCT2a structure. The overall structure of PvHCT2a 
consists of two domains with the p-coumaroyl-CoA-and shikimate-
binding site located between the domains. Each of the domains con-
tains a core b-sheet surrounded by a-helices. (B) Substrate-binding 
site of the PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-shikimate ternary complex. 
The residues Arg369, Thr382, His163 and Trp384 interact directly with 
p-coumaroyl shikimate. The residues Ser38 and Tyr40 interact via 
water-(W32) mediated hydrogen bonds with p-coumaroyl shikimate. 
The His163 residue was observed in two alternative conformations 
represented in magenta and pink. (C) Substrate-binding site of the 
PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-protocatechuate ternary complex. The 
major difference between protocatechuate and shikimate binding is 
the loss of the C5 hydroxyl interaction with Thr382. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Coumaroyl shikimate (% of control) </p>

<p>400 µM 
800 µM 
1.6 mM </p>

<p>* 
* * 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* * </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Inhibition of HCT activity in vitro. Production of p-coumaroyl 
shikimate by recombinant PvHCT2a using p-coumaroyl-CoA and shi-
kimate as substrates (400 mM each) was measured in the absence 
(control) or presence of various concentrations of 3-aminobenzoate, 
protocatechuate, 3-hydroxyanthranilate, 2,3-dihydroxybenzoate, 3-
hydroxybenzoate, gentisate, hydroquinone, catechol or 5-hydroxyan-
thranilate. Asterisks indicate significant differences from the control 
using the unpaired Student's t-test (**P &lt; 0.005, *P &lt; 0.05). </p>



<p>A. Eudes et al. | Substrate promiscuity of HCT and lignin reduction </p>

<p>and p-hydroxybenzoate 3-monooxygenase from Pseudomonas 
aeruginosa (pobA) (Fig. 5A). In Arabidopsis lignifying tissues, 
the promoter of the secondary cell wall cellulose synthase gene 
AtCesa4 was used to drive the expression of ubiC, while the 
promoter of the cinnamate 4-hydroxylase gene AtC4H, involved 
in the lignin biosynthetic pathway, was used to drive the ex-
pression of pobA. Two different promoters were used to min-
imize gene silencing effects that could potentially arise from the 
expression of identical 5 
0 -untranslated region (UTR) sequences. 
Moreover, using an N-terminal fusion with a sequence encod-
ing a plastid-targeting signal peptide, both ubiC and pobA were </p>

<p>targeted to the plastids in which chorismate is produced. Two 
lines harboring a T-DNA carrying either ubiC alone (ubiC-1 and 
ubiC-2) or pobA alone (pobA-1 and pobA-2), and three lines 
harboring a T-DNA carrying both genes (ubiC-pobA-1, -2 and -
3) were selected for characterization. Reverse transcription-
PCR (RT-PCR) showed the expression of only ubiC or pobA 
in the ubiC-1, -2 lines and pobA-1, -2 lines, respectively, and 
expression of both genes in the three ubiC-pobA lines (Fig. 
5B). Methanol-soluble metabolites were extracted from stems 
of the transgenic lines, and both p-hydroxybenzoate and pro-
tocatechuate were quantified using LC-MS/MS. The metabolite 
analysis showed a higher amount of p-hydroxybenzoate in the 
ubiC-1 and -2 lines compared with the wild type (7.5-and 6.8-
fold higher, respectively), while the levels observed in the ubiC-
pobA lines were similar to those of the wild type. In contrast, 
the protocatechuate content was 24-to 26-fold higher in the 
ubiC-pobA lines compared with the wild-type and the ubiC lines 
(Fig. 5C). These results confirmed the production of p-hydro-
xybenzoate from chorismate by ubiC activity and its efficient 
conversion to protocatechuate by pobA in the ubiC-pobA 
transgenic lines. In addition, measurement of phenylalanine-
an amino acid derived from chorismate and precursor of mono-
lignols-and salicylic acid contents revealed no significant dif-
ference between the wild type and transgenic lines 
(Supplementary Table S4). </p>

<p>Protocatechuate overproducer lines show 
reduction of lignin and improved biomass 
saccharification </p>

<p>Lignin content was measured from the stem biomass of 
senesced mature wild-type, ubiC, pobA and ubiC-pobA plants 
using the Klason method. In comparison with the wild type, 
lignin reductions of 31-37% were measured in the ubiC-pobA 
lines, whereas no decrease of lignin content was observed in the 
ubiC and pobA single lines (Fig. 5D). In addition, a reduction in 
stem height at maturity was noticeable for all three ubiC-pobA 
lines at late development stages compared with the single 
transgenic lines and wild-type plants (Supplementary Fig. 
S9). Lastly, using pyrolysis-gas chromatography (GC)/MS, we 
determined that the monomeric composition of lignin was 
altered in the pobA-ubiC lines, showing an increased S:G ratio 
as a result of higher and lower relative amount of S and G units, 
respectively (Table 1; Supplementary Table S5). </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>COOH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>ubiC 
pobA </p>

<p>chorismate 
p-hydroxybenzoate protocatechuate </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>800 
Protocatechuate 
p-Hydroxybenzoate </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>nmol.g -1 
fresh weight </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>tub8 </p>

<p>pobA </p>

<p>ubiC 
989 bp 
483 bp 
1040 bp </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>Lignin content (% cell wall) </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Characterization of transgenic Arabidopsis lines accumulating 
protocatechuate. (A) Strategy used for the conversion of chorismate 
into protocatechuate via p-hydroxybenzoate. (B) Detection by RT-
PCR of ubiC and pobA transcripts using stem mRNA from 5-week-old 
wild-type (WT), pobA, ubiC and ubiC-pobA transgenic lines. Tub8-
specific primers were used to assess cDNA quality for each sample. 
(C) p-Hydroxybenzoate and protocatechuate contents in stems from 
5-week-old WT, pobA, ubiC and ubiC-pobA transgenic lines. Bars rep-
resent the SE from four biological replicates (n = 4). Asterisks indicate 
significant differences from the wild type using the unpaired Student's 
t-test (*P &lt; 0.005). (D) Lignin content in senesced mature stems from 
WT, pobA, ubiC and ubiC-pobA transgenic lines. Values in parentheses 
are the SE from biological replicates (n = 13 for the WT, n = 4 for ubiC-
pobA-1 and -2, n = 3 for ubiC-1 and -2, pobA-1 and -2, and ubiC-pobA-
3). Asterisks indicate significant differences from the WT using the 
unpaired Student's t-test (*P &lt; 0.001). </p>

<p>Table 1 Lignin composition in senesced mature stems from wild-
type (WT) and ubiC-pobA plants </p>

<p>%H 
%G 
%S 
S/G </p>

<p>WT 
4.4 (0.2) 
60.4 (0.8) 
35.2 (0.6) 
0.58 </p>

<p>ubiC-pobA-1 
5.1 (0.0) 
41.6 (0.3)* 
53.3 (0.3)* 
1.28* </p>

<p>ubiC-pobA-2 
5.0 (0.4) 
42.6 (0.2)* 
52.3 (0.5)* 
1.23* </p>

<p>ubiC-pobA-3 
4.8 (0.4) 
46.7 (0.1)* 
48.4 (0.3)* 
1.04* </p>

<p>Values in parenthests are the SE from biological replicates (n = 7 for the WT, 
n = 4 for ubiC-pobA-1 and -2, n = 3 for ubiC-pobA-3). 
Asterisks indicate significant differences from the WT using the unpaired 
Student's t-test (*P &lt; 0.001). 
See also Supplementary Table S2. </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 57(3): 568-579 (2016) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcw016 </p>

<p>Saccharification assays on stem material were conducted to 
evaluate the potential of our approach to reduce overall bio-
mass recalcitrance and engineer forage and bioenergy crops. As 
shown in Fig. 6, higher amounts of sugars were released from 
the biomass of the three ubiC-pobA lines, which exhibited sac-
charification improvements of 24-26% compared with the wild 
type during a 96 h enzymatic hydrolysis. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The substrate promiscuity of HCT was demonstrated by its 
capacity to form p-coumaroyl conjugates using various ac-
ceptors other than shikimate. This substrate flexibility appears 
conserved between HCTs from different representatives of land 
plants, occurring at least in one bryophyte and one lycophyte, 
as well as in euphyllophytes including one gymnosperm, one 
monocot angiosperm and two dicot angiosperms. Although 
P. patens contains orthologs of all the genes required for the 
synthesis of p-coumaryl and coniferyl alcohols (Xu et al. 2009), 
the presence of lignified tissues has never been demonstrated in 
this plant. We show here that P. patens possesses a bona fide 
HCT, but its physiological role remains unclear. Although 
PpHCT1 falls into the clade of known HCTs in the phylogenetic 
tree of hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA-dependent BAHD transferases 
(Supplementary Fig. S1), it may instead be involved in the 
synthesis of alternative phenylpropanoid conjugates such as 
chlorogenic acid (3-O-caffeoylquinic acid) which has been iden-
tified in P. patens (Erxleben et al. 2012). Moreover, this is, to our 
knowledge, the first demonstration of HCT activity for an 
enzyme from Selaginella. However, its involvement in lignifica-
tion remains questionable due to the presence in this plant of a 
dual meta-hydroxylase (SmF5H), which can by-pass the enzym-
atic steps catalyzed by C3 
0 H and HCT (Weng et al. 2010). More 
generally, BAHD acyltransferases from Selaginella could have a 
role in the synthesis of phenolic esters other than p-coumaroyl 
shikimate (Weng and Noel 2013). 
Although the formation of p-coumaroyl shikimate occurs 
via an ester linkage between p-coumaroyl-CoA and shikimate, </p>

<p>these HCTs can also catalyze the formation of p-coumaroyl 
conjugates via an amide bond, as exemplified with the use of 
3-aminobenzoate as acceptor. Both ester and amide linkages 
are possible for the formation of p-coumaroyl 3-hydroxyanthra-
nilate and p-coumaroyl 5-hydroxyanthranilate, but only one 
product was observed in our assays when these acceptors 
were tested. For these two cases, an amide bond can be antici-
pated, as previously determined for the p-coumarate conjugate 
formed by CcHCT using 3-hydroxyanthranilate (Moglia et al. 
2010). In this work, the apparent K m value observed for 
PvHCT2a towards shikimate ($700 mM) is comparable with 
the values observed for tobacco HCT (750 mM), which has 
been genetically implicated in lignin biosynthesis (Hoffmann 
et al. 2003), and for poplar HCT (895 mM; Kim et al. 2011), 
but higher than the values reported for HCT from coffee (75 
mM; Lallemand et al. 2012), sorghum (153 mM; Walker et al. 
2013) and Coleus blumei (332 mM; Sander and Petersen 2011). 
The slightly different structure of the new HCT acceptors 
described in this study could influence their binding to the 
active site of the enzyme and explain the higher apparent K m 
values of HCT for these substrates compared with shikimate. 
The catalytic mechanism of HCT has been elegantly 
described previously by Walker et al. (2013). In their mutagen-
esis experiments using shikimate as a substrate, the mutant 
T384A-SbHCT (equivalent to Thr382 in PvHCT2a) showed 
only 9% of the enzyme activity compared with wild-type 
SbHCT (Walker et al. 2013). We therefore propose that the 
loss of the C5 hydroxyl interaction with Thr382 in the 
PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-protocatechuate complex af-
fected the effective binding of protocatechuate, thus engender-
ing a similar effect to the T384A mutation in SbHCT on the 
turnover rate of the substrate. This is most probably the reason 
why it was possible to capture crystallographically the substrate 
PvHCT2a-p-coumaryl-CoA-protocatechuate ternary complex, 
compared with the product state when shikimate was used in 
soaking experiments. 
Our goal was to use the substrate promiscuity of HCT to 
reduce lignin. In this attempt, we generated Arabidopsis lines 
that overproduce protocatechuate, a non-canonical acceptor 
and competitive inhibitor of HCT in vitro. The engineered 
plants accumulate approximatey 25-fold more protocatechu-
ate than wild-type plants, and showed significant lignin re-
ductions (31-37%) in biomass. Interestingly, transgenic lines 
expressing the pobA gene alone accumulated approximately 
1.8-fold more protocatechuate than wild-type plants presum-
ably from the conversion of the endogenous pool of p-hydro-
xybenzoate but showed no reduction of lignin content, 
suggesting that a threshold amount of protocatechuate is 
necessary to inhibit significantly HCT activity in vivo. Since 
lignin is reduced in the protocatechuate-overproducing 
plants, either the amount of p-coumaroyl protocatechuate 
produced by HCT is too low to sustain lignin biosynthesis, 
or p-coumaroyl protocatechuate is not metabolized further 
in the lignin biosynthetic pathway. In particular, it is not 
known whether C3 
0 H can hydroxylate p-coumaroyl protoca-
techuate, and whether CSE would cleave the putative result-
ing p-caffeoyl protocatechuate. Neither p-coumaroyl </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
90 
100 </p>

<p>WT 
ubiC-pobA-1 
ubiC-pobA-2 
ubiC-pobA-3 </p>

<p>Time (hours) </p>

<p>Sugars (µg mg -1 </p>

<p>biomass) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Saccharification of biomass from mature senesced stems of the 
wild type (WT) and ubiC-pobA transgenic lines. A 96 h time course of 
sugars released from pre-treated biomass digested with cellulase is 
shown. Values are means ± SE of six biological replicates (n = 6). 
Asterisks indicate significant differences from the WT using the un-
paired Student's t-test (P &lt; 0.005). </p>



<p>A. Eudes et al. | Substrate promiscuity of HCT and lignin reduction </p>

<p>protocatechuate nor putative p-caffeoyl protocatechuate 
were detected in the metabolite extracts from ubiC-pobA 
transgenic plants, possibly because of their conjugation to 
other metabolites such as sugars, as was recently shown for 
other lignin oligomers (Dima et al. 2015). 
Our dual transgene strategy consists of a two-step conver-
sion of chorismate into protocatechuate. Steady-state levels of 
phenylalanine and salicylate, two metabolites derived from 
chorismate, are not significantly changed in the ubiC, pobA 
and ubiC-pobA transgenics compared with the wild type, sug-
gesting that chorismate is not limiting in these lines, as previ-
ously hypothesized in the case of tobacco plants that express 
ubiC and show normal growth characteristics (Siebert et al. 
1996, Viitanen et al. 2004). Therefore, the reduction of lignin 
observed only in the ubiC-pobA lines (and not in the ubiC single 
lines) is unlikely to be the consequence of phenylalanine deple-
tion, although our data cannot rule out a possible slowing 
down of the metabolic flux. In addition, the height reduction 
observed in the ubiC-pobA lines at the mature stage is probably 
a consequence of lignin reduction rather than drastic changes 
in levels of salicylic acid, a metabolite whose overaccumulation 
in some transgenic plants often results in dwarf phenotypes 
(Rivas-San Vicente and Plasencia 2011). 
In contrast to previous studies of plants in which HCT ac-
tivity was down-regulated, the lignin composition of our trans-
genic lines does not show any enrichment in H units, possibly 
due to a lower degree of inhibition of activity and the consump-
tion of p-coumaroyl-CoA by HCT for the formation of both 
p-coumaroyl protocatechuate and p-coumaroyl shikimate. 
Nevertheless, the increase of the S:G ratio in our transgenics, 
which results from the decrease of G units in favor of an in-
crease in S units, is a lignin feature predicted by metabolic flux 
analysis in the case of HCT down-regulation, and was previously 
observed in plants affected in HCT activity (Chen and Dixon 
2007, Ziebell et al. 2010, Vanholme et al, 2013b, Wang et al. 
2014, Eudes et al. 2015). In addition, analysis of HCT transcript 
levels in the ubiC-pobA transgenic lines showed no major dif-
ference compared with the wild type (Supplementary Fig. 
S10), which is consistent with the hypothesis that protocatech-
uate affects the activity of HCT rather than its expression in the 
ubiC-pobA lines. 
Engineering strategies for the overproduction of HCT non-
canonical acceptors other than protocatechuate could be 
developed as alternative approaches to reduce lignin. For ex-
ample, plant lines could be engineered to express anthranilate 
3-hydroxylase, 2,3-dihydroxybenzoate synthase/dehydrogen-
ase, salicylate 5-hydroxylases, 3-aminobenzoate synthase or 3-
hydroxybenzoate synthase for the accumulation of 3-hydro-
xyanthranilate, 2,3-dihydroxybenzoate, 2,5-dihydroxybenzoate, 
3-aminobenzoate or 3-hydroxybenzoate respectively, using the 
metabolites anthranilate, isochorismate, salicylate, 3-dehy-
droshikimate and chorismate as substrates (Gehring et al. 
1997, Liu et al. 2010, Andexer et al. 2011, Hirayama et al. 
2013, Zhang et al. 2013, Fang and Zhou 2014). It is interesting 
to note that very low amounts of 2,3-and 2,5-dihydroxybenzo-
ates could be detected in our metabolite extracts from wild-
type plants ($10 nmol g 
-1 FW), whereas hydroxyanthranilates, </p>

<p>3-hydroxybenzoate and 3-aminobenzoate were below the de-
tection limit, and, to our knowledge, have never been measured 
in plant extracts. With the exception of the occurrence of 
the phytoalexin p-coumaroyl 5-hydroxyanthranilate in oats 
(Collins 1989), p-coumaroyl conjugates of such phenolics 
have never been reported. Lastly, although catechol and 
hydroquinone are found in plants (Mageroy et al. 2012, 
Rychlińska and Nowak 2012), no corresponding p-coumaroyl 
esters have been described, maybe as a consequence of 
poor HCT activity towards these diphenols (Supplementary 
Fig. S6). 
HCT seems to have appeared at the same time that plants 
began colonizing land. It is unclear why such promiscuity has 
been retained, and this question will require further study. 
However, a strategy of exploiting this substrate promiscuity 
of HCT offers a novel way to reduce lignin in plants. Because 
this enzymatic activity appears to be conserved among land 
plants, this strategy can be valuable to affect HCT activity in 
bioenergy crops for which no HCT gene has been cloned or for 
which multiple, functionally redundant copies are present. In 
this respect, particular attention should be paid to the spatio-
temporal activity of the transgene promoters employed for the 
overproduction of HCT alternative substrates to limit possible 
growth defects associated with lignin reduction as observed in 
this study using Arabidopsis. Lastly, as we show here in the case 
of protocatechuate overproduction, such an approach has the 
potential to add value to plant biomass by increasing the 
amount of valuable metabolites utilized in the bio-based chem-
ical industry (Linger et al. 2014). </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Cloning of HCTs and activity assays using yeast </p>

<p>For the cloning of AtHCT and PpHCT1, total RNA (1 mg) from A. thaliana 
seedlings and total RNA (5 mg) from P. patens protonemal tissue were extracted 
using the Plant RNeasy extraction kit (Qiagen) and reverse-transcribed using 
the Transcriptor First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Roche Applied Science). The 
cDNA preparations obtained were used to amplify AtHCT (GenBank accession 
No. NP_199704.1/At5g48930) and PpHCT1 (http://www.cosmoss.org, acces-
sion No. Pp3c2_29140V1.1; GenBank accession No. KU513965) using the oligo-
nucleotides AtHCT-B1/AtHCT-B2 and PpHCT-B1/PpHCT-B2 (Supplementary 
Table S6), respectively, for cloning into the Gateway pDONR221 entry vector 
by BP recombination (Life Technologies). Gene sequences encoding for PtHCT6 
(NCBI reference sequence XP_006368492.1), PvHCT2a (GenBank accession No. 
AGM90558.1), PrHCT (GenBank accession No. ABO52899.1) and SmHCT (NCBI 
reference sequence: XP_002991534.1), flanked with the attB1 (5 
0 end) and attB2 
(3 
0 end) Gateway recombination sites, were synthesized for expression in yeast 
(GenScript) and cloned into the Gateway pDONR221 entry vector by BP re-
combination (Life Technologies). All six entry clones were LR recombined with 
the pDRf1-4CL5-GW vector (Eudes et al. 2011) to generate the constructs 
pDRf1-4CL5-AtHCT, pDRf1-4CL5-PtHCT6, pDRf1-4CL5-PvHCT2a, pDRf1-4CL5-
PrHCT, pDRf1-4CL5-SmHCT, and pDRf1-4CL5-PpHCT1. 
For HCT activity assays, the pDRf1-4CL5-HCT constructs and the control 
pDRf1-4CL5 vector (Eudes et al. 2011) were transformed into the 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae pad1 knockout (MATa his3D1 leu2D0 met15D0 
ura3D0 Ápad1, ATCC 4005833) using the Frozen-EZ Yeast Transformation II 
Kit </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>(Zymo Research Corporation) and selected on solid medium containing 
1 Â yeast nitrogen base (YNB) without amino acids (Difco 291940) supple-
mented with 3% glucose and 1 Â dropout-uracil (CSM-ura; Sunrise Science 
Products). Overnight cultures from single colonies were grown in 2 Â YNB </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 57(3): 568-579 (2016) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcw016 </p>

<p>medium without amino acids (Difco) supplemented with 6% glucose and 
2 Â CSM-ura (Sunrise Science Products). Overnight cultures were used to in-
oculate 4 ml of fresh medium at an OD 600 = 0.15. Substrates were added to the 
medium 4 h later at a final concentration of 1 mM, and the cultures were grown 
for 24 h; p-coumarate was used as the donor, and the various acceptors tested 
(Sigma-Aldrich) are listed in Supplementary Fig. S1. For the detection of the p-
coumaroyl conjugate products, an aliquot of the culture medium was collected, 
cleared by centrifugation (20,000 Â g for 5 min at 4 
C), mixed with an equal 
volume of 50% (v/v) methanol-water and filtered using Amicon Ultra centri-
fugal filters (3,000 Da MW cut-off regenerated cellulose membrane; EMD 
Millipore) prior to HPLC-electrospray ionization-time-of-flight MS (HPLC-ESI-
TOF MS) analysis. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analysis </p>

<p>Multiple alignments on the full-length protein sequences were performed by 
ClustalW. A phylogenetic tree was generated with MEGA6 (Tamura et al. 2013) 
using the maximum likelihood method and default parameters. </p>

<p>Heterologous expression, purification and activity 
of PvHCT2a </p>

<p>The pDONR221-PvHCT2a entry vector was LR recombined with the pDEST17 
bacterial expression vector, which introduces an N-terminal 6 Â His tag (Life 
Technologies). The construct was transferred into Rosetta 2 (DE3) chemically 
competent E. coli (EMD Milipore), according to the manufacturer's instructions. 
A single bacterial colony, grown on Luria-Bertani agar containing 100 mg ml </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>carbenicillin and 30 mg ml 
-1 chloramphenicol was used to inoculate a 5 ml 
liquid culture supplemented with the same antibiotic concentrations and 
grown overnight at 37 
C. The overnight culture was used to inoculate a 0.5 
liter Luria-Bertani culture at an OD 600 = 0.05 containing the same antibiotic 
concentrations and grown at 37 
C until it reached an OD 600 = 0.8-1.0. 
Expression was induced by the addition of 0.5 mM isopropyl-b-D-thiogalacto-
pyranoside (IPTG), and the culture was transferred at 18 
C and grown for 24 h. 
The recombinant protein was affinity purified using a HIS-Select HF Nickel 
Affinity Gel (Sigma-Aldrich) according to the manufacturer's instructions and 
buffer-exchanged with 40 mM Tris buffer pH 7.5 using Amicon Ultra centrifugal 
filters (30,000 Da MW cut-off regenerated cellulose membrane; EMD Millipore). 
Purity and integrity were verified by SDS-PAGE, and the recombinant protein 
was stored atÀ20 
C in 40 mM Tris buffer pH 7.5, containing 10% (v/v) glycerol. </p>

<p>In vitro transferase assays were performed at 30 
C for 15 min in 40 ml 
reactions containing 50 mM Tris buffer pH 7.5, 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 
400 mM p-coumaroyl-CoA (MicroCombiChem e.K.), 120 ng of recombinant 
PvHCT2a protein and 1 mM of various acyl acceptors. Similar conditions 
were used to obtain substrate saturation curves except that the incubation 
time was reduced to 2 min and the concentration of the acyl acceptors varied 
from 0 to 6.4 or 12.8 mM. For the competitive inhibition experiment, assays 
were performed at 30 
C for 15 min in 40 ml reactions containing 50 mM Tris 
buffer pH 7.5, 400 mM p-coumaroyl-CoA, 400 mM shikimate and 120 ng of 
recombinant PvHCT2a protein without (control) or with 0.4-1.6 mM of various 
acyl acceptors. All reactions were terminated by adding 40 ml of 50% (v/v) cold 
methanol-water and kept at -20 
C until HPLC-ESI-TOF MS analysis. </p>

<p>For structural study, a PvHCT2a sequence was synthesized for expression in 
E. coli (GenScript), amplified using the oligonucleotides PvHCT2a-infus-fw/ 
PvHCT2a-infus-rv (Supplementary Table S6) and cloned into a BamHI/ 
NdeI-digested pSKB3 vector using the In-Fusion HD cloning kit (Clontech). 
The construct was transferred into BL21 (DE3) chemically competent E. coli 
(EMD Milipore), according to the manufacturer's instructions. A single bacterial 
colony, grown on Luria-Bertani agar containing 50 mg ml 
-1 kanamycin was used 
to inoculate a 50 ml liquid culture supplemented with the same antibiotic 
concentrations and grown overnight at 37 
C. The overnight culture was used 
to inoculate a 3 liter Luria-Bertani culture containing the same antibiotic con-
centration and grown at 37 
C until it reached an OD 600 = 0.8. Expression was 
induced by the addition of 0.5 mM IPTG, and the culture was transferred at 18 
C 
and grown for 24 h. Cell paste was lysed in 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl 
and 30 mM imidazole, and loaded onto a 5 ml Histrap column on an AKTA FPLC. 
The column was washed to baseline prior to elution with a gradient of 0-100% 
buffer 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl and 500 mM imidazole in 20 </p>

<p>column volumes. The cleanest elution fractions were pooled and dialyzed back 
into the lysis buffer with the addition of TEV protease to remove the 6His-tag. The 
cleaved material was applied again through a 5 ml Histrap column on the AKTA 
FPLC to separate the cleaved PvHCT2a from other components. The purified 
PvHCT2a was then dialyzed into 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0 and 20 mM NaCl prior 
to concentration for crystallographic studies. </p>

<p>Crystallization of PvHCT2a in complex with ligands </p>

<p>The final concentration of PvHCT2a used for crystallization trials was 
12 mg ml </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>. The PvHCT2a apoenzyme sample was screened using the sparse 
matrix method (Jancarik and Kim 1991) with a Phoenix Robot (Art Robbins 
Instruments) and the following crystallization screens: Crystal Screen, SaltRx, 
PEG/Ion, Index and PEGRx (Hampton Research) and Berkeley Screen 
[Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL)]. Crystals of PvHCT2a apoen-
zyme were found in 0.2 M lithium sulfate, 0.1 M Tris-HCl pH 8.5 and 25% (w/v) 
polyethylene glycol 3,350. Crystals of PvHCT2a in complex with p-coumaroyl-
CoA-shikimate and p-coumaroyl-CoA-protocatechuate were obtain by soaking 
PvHCT2a apoenzyme crystals using 5 mM p-coumaroyl-CoA and 5 mM shiki-
mate or protocatechuate solutions for 3 h. Crystals of PvHCT2a apoenzyme were 
obtained after 1 d by the sitting-drop vapor diffusion method, with the drops 
consisting of a mixture of 0.5 ml of protein solution and 0.5 ml of reservoir solution. </p>

<p>X-ray data collection and structure determination </p>

<p>The crystals of PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-shikimate and PvHCT2a-p-cou-
maroyl-CoA-protocatechuate were placed in a reservoir solution containing 
20% (v/v) glycerol, then flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen. The X-ray data sets for 
PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-shikimate and PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-
protocatechuate were collected at the Berkeley Center for Structural 
Biology beamlines 8.2.1 and 8.2.2 of the Advanced Light Source at LBNL. 
The diffraction data were recorded using an ADSC-Q315r detector. The 
data sets were processed using the program <rs id="software-5" type="software">HKL-2000</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Otwinowski and Minor</rs> 1997). 
The PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-shikimate structure was determined 
by the molecular-replacement method with the program <rs id="software-6" type="software">PHASER</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">McCoy et. al</rs>. 2007) using the SbHCT structure (PDB ID 4KE4) (Walker et al. 2013) as a 
search model. The PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-shikimate structure was 
used as a search model to solve the PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-protoca-
techuate structure. Structure refinement was performed using the phenix.re-
fine program (Afonine et al. 2012). Manual rebuilding using <rs id="software-8" type="software">COOT</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">Emsley and Cowtan</rs> 2004) and the addition of water molecules allowed construction 
of the final model. Five percent of the data were randomly selected for cross-
validation. The final model of PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-shikimate and 
PvHCT2a-p-coumaroyl-CoA-protocatechuate have R and R free factors of 
15.9%/18.6% and 17.9%/20.5%, respectively. Root-mean-square deviation dif-
ferences from ideal geometry for bond lengths, angles and dihedrals were 
calculated with <rs id="software-9" type="software">Phenix</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="creator">Adams et al.</rs>. 2010). The overall stereochemical qual-
ity of the final models was assessed using the program <rs id="software-10" type="software">MolProbity</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Davis et al.</rs>. 2007). </p>

<p>Plant material and growth conditions </p>

<p>Seeds of wild-type and transgenic A. thaliana (ecotype Columbia, Col-0) lines 
were germinated directly on soil. Growing conditions were 150 mmol m 
-2 s </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>, 
22 
C, 60% humidity and 14 h of light per day. Selection of T 2 transgenic plants 
and identification of homozygous lines, for which the T 3 progeny were not 
segregating on antibiotic, was made on Murashige and Skoog vitamin medium 
(PhytoTechnology Laboratories), supplemented with 1% sucrose, 0.8% agar and 
50 mg ml 
-1 kanamycin. </p>

<p>HCT activity assays in Arabidopsis </p>

<p>Total proteins were extracted from Arabidopsis stems as previously described 
(Vanholme et al. 2013b). Briefly, stems of 5-week-old wild-type plants were frozen 
in liquid nitrogen and ground into a fine powder. Total proteins from approxi-
mately 500 mg of stem powder were extracted at 4 
C with 1 ml of extraction 
buffer consisting of 20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5 containing 10 mM DTT, 15% glycerol, 
1% insoluble polyvinylpolypyrrolidone (PVPP) and 1 Â protease inhibitor cocktail 
(Roche). Total proteins were quantified using the Bradford method (Bradford </p>



<p>A. Eudes et al. | Substrate promiscuity of HCT and lignin reduction </p>

<p>1976). HCT activity assays were performed at 30 
C for 30 min in 40 ml reactions 
containing 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 400 mM p-coumaroyl-CoA, 400 mM shikimate 
and 12 mg of total proteins without (control) or with 400 mM of various acyl 
acceptors. All reactions were terminated by adding 40 ml of 50% (v/v) cold 
methanol-water and kept at -20 
C until HPLC-ESI-TOF MS analysis. </p>

<p>Construction of binary vectors </p>

<p>Generation of the pTKan-pCesa4::GWR1R2 destination vector was previously 
described (Eudes et al. 2012). To generate the pTKan-pCesa4::schl-ubiC con-
struct, a gene sequence encoding ubiC from E. coli (GenBank accession No. 
CAA47181.1) containing the encoding sequence of a plastid targeting signal 
(SCHL; Lebrun et al. 1992) and flanked with the Gateway attB1 (5 
0 end) and 
attB4 (3 
0 end) recombination sites was synthesized for expression in 
Arabidopsis (Supplementary Data S1) (GenScript). The sequence was ampli-
fied by PCR to replace the Gateway attB4 (3 
0 end) by the attB2 recombin-
ation site and cloned into the Gateway pDONR221-P1P2 entry vector by BP 
recombination (Life Technologies). A sequence-verified entry clone was LR 
recombined with the pTKan-pCesa4::GWR1R2 vector to generate the pTKan-
pCesa4::schl-ubiC construct. 
Generation of the pTKan-pC4H::schl-GWR3R2 destination vector was pre-
viously described (Eudes et al. 2015). To generate the pTKan-pC4H::schl-pobA 
construct, a gene sequence encoding pobA from P. aeruginosa (GenBank ac-
cession No. AAG03636.1) flanked with the Gateway attB3 (5 
0 end) and attB2 (3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>end) recombination sites was synthesized for expression in Arabidopsis 
(Supplementary Data S1) (GenScript) and cloned into the Gateway 
pDONR221-P3P2 entry vector by BP recombination (Life Technologies). An 
entry clone was LR recombined with the pTKan-pC4H::schl-GWR3R2 vector 
to generate the pTKan-pC4H::schl-pobA construct. 
A multisite LR recombination (Life Technologies) using the pDONR221-P1-
schl::ubiC-P4, pDONR221-L4R-tg7-pC4H::schl-L3R (Eudes et al. 2015) and 
pDONR221-P3-pobA-P2 entry vectors and the pTKan-pCesa4::GWR1R2 destin-
ation vector was performed to generate the pTKan-pCesa4::schl-ubiC-
pC4H::schl-pobA construct. 
All constructs were introduced into wild-type (Col-0) Arabidopsis plants via 
Agrobacterium-mediated transformation (Bechtold and Pelletier 1998). </p>

<p>RNA extraction and RT-PCR </p>

<p>Total RNA (1 mg) were extracted from stems of 5-week-old wild-type and T 3 
homozygous transgenic lines using the Plant RNeasy extraction kit (Qiagen) 
and reverse-transcribed using the Transcriptor First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit 
(Roche Applied Science). The cDNA preparations obtained were quality-
controlled using tub8-specific oligonucleotides, and the pobA, ubiC and AtHCT 
transcripts were detected using specific oligonucleotides listed in Supplementary 
Table S6. For the PCR, OneTaq (New England Biolabs) was used according to the 
manufacturer's instructions, with 1 min of elongation time and 60 
C for the 
annealing temperature. Thirty (for pobA and ubiC expression) or 25 (for AtHCT 
expression) PCR cycles were used to amplify the DNA fragments. </p>

<p>Plant metabolite extraction </p>

<p>Arabidopsis stems of 6-week-old wild-type and T 3 homozygous transgenic lines 
were collected in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80 
C until further utilization. 
Prior to metabolite extraction, collected stems were pulverized in liquid nitro-
gen. For extraction of methanol-soluble metabolites, 200-300 mg of frozen 
stem powder was mixed with 1 ml of 80% (v/v) methanol-water and shaken 
at 1,400 r.p.m. for 15 min at 70 
C. The mixture was cleared by centrifugation for 
5 min at 20,000 Â g. This step was repeated four times. Extracts were pooled 
and cleared once more by centrifugation (5 min, 20,000 Â g), mixed with 2 ml of 
analytical grade water and filtered using Amicon Ultra centrifugal filters 
(10,000 Da MW cut-off regenerated cellulose membrane; EMD Millipore). 
Phenylalanine was quantified in the filtered extracts using HPLC-ESI-TOF MS 
analysis. For measurement of 4-hydroxybenzoate, protocatechuate and salicylic 
acid, an aliquot of the filtered extracts was dried under vacuum, resuspended 
with 1 N HCl and incubated at 95 
C for 3 h. The mixture was subjected to three 
ethyl acetate partitioning steps. Ethyl acetate fractions were pooled, dried 
in vacuo and resuspended in 50% (v/v) methanol-water prior to HPLC-ESI-
TOF MS analysis. </p>

<p>Metabolite analyses </p>

<p>Metabolites were analyzed using HPLC-ESI-TOF MS as previously described 
(Eudes et al. 2013, Eudes et al. 2015). Protocatechuate, 4-hydroxybenzoate, 
phenylalanine, and salicylic acid were quantified via 10-point calibration 
curves of authentic standard compounds for which the R 
2 coefficients 
were ! 0.99. For the identification of the p-coumaroyl conjugates, the mea-
sured masses agreed with the expected theoretical masses within &lt; 5 p.p.m. 
mass error. </p>

<p>Lignin content and composition </p>

<p>The biomass from senesced mature stems of wild-type plants and T 3 homozy-
gous transgenic lines was used to determine lignin content and composition. 
Soluble extracts from stem biomass samples were extracted sequentially by 
sonication (20 min) with 80% ethanol (three times), acetone (once), chloro-
form-methanol (1 : 1, v/v, once) and acetone (once). The standard NREL bio-
mass protocol was used to measure the lignin content (Sluiter et al. 2008). The 
chemical composition of lignin was analyzed by pyrolysis-GC/MS as previously 
described (Del Rio et al. 2012, Eudes et al. 2015). </p>

<p>Cell wall pretreatments and saccharification </p>

<p>Ball-milled senesced mature stems (10 mg) were mixed with 340 ml of NaOH 
(0.25%, w/v), shaken at 1,400 r.p.m. (30 
C, 30 min) and autoclaved at 120 
C for 
1 h for dilute alkali pre-treatment. Saccharification was initiated by adding 650 
ml of 100 mM sodium citrate buffer pH 5.0 containing 80 mg ml 
-1 tetracycline 
and 1% (w/w) Cellic CTec2 cellulase (Novozymes). At t = 0 and after 24, 48, 72 
and 96 h of incubation at 50 
C with shaking (800 r.p.m.), samples were cen-
trifuged (20,000 Â g, 2 min) and 10 ml of the supernatant was collected for 
measurement of reducing sugars using the 3,5-dinitrosalicylic acid assay and 
glucose solutions as standards (Miller 1959). </p>

<p>Data deposition </p>

<p>The atomic co-ordinates and structure factors of PvHCT2a-p-coumaryl-CoA-
shikimate and PvHCT2a-p-coumaryl-CoA-protocatechuate complexes have 
been deposited in the Protein Data Bank, with PDB ID codes 5FAL and 
5FAN, respectively. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at PCP online. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was part of the DOE Joint BioEnergy Institute (http:// 
www.jbei.org) supported by the U. S. Department of Energy, 
Office of Science, Office of Biological and Environmental 
Research, through contract DE-AC02-05CH11231 between 
Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory and the U.S. 
Department of Energy. The Berkeley Center for Structural 
Biology is supported in part by the National Institutes of 
Health, National Institute of General Medical Sciences. The 
Advanced Light Source is supported by the Director, Office of 
Science, Office of Basic Energy Sciences, of the U.S. Department 
of Energy under Contract No. DE-AC02-05CH11231. The 
United States Government retains and the publisher, by accept-
ing the article for publication, acknowledges that the United 
States Government retains a non-exclusive, paid-up, irrevoc-
able, world-wide license to publish or reproduce the published 
form of this manuscript, or allow others to do so, for United 
States Government purposes. </p>



<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 57(3): 568-579 (2016) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcw016 </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank Noppadon Sathitsuksanoh for assistance 
with the pyrolysis-GC/MS, Tess Scavuzzo-Duggan for providing 
P. patens protonemal tissue, Dr. Nigel W. Moriarty for helpful 
analysis of the ligand geometry and restraints, Novozymes for 
providing Cellic CTec2, and Sabin Russell for editing this manu-
script. We are also grateful to the staff of the Berkeley Center for 
Structural Biology at the Advanced Light Source of Lawrence 
Berkeley National Laboratory. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>J.D.K. has financial conflicts of interest in Amyris, LS9, and Lygos. 
D.L. has financial conflicts of interest in Afingen. All other au-
thors have no conflicts of interest to declare. </p>





<p>A. Eudes et al. | Substrate promiscuity of HCT and lignin reduction </p>





<p>Plant Cell Physiol. 57(3): 568-579 (2016) doi:10.1093/pcp/pcw016 </p>

</text></tei>