<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4259556" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Network meta-analysis (NMA) has emerged as a useful analytical tool allowing 
comparison of multiple treatments based on direct and indirect evidence. Commonly, a hier-
archical Bayesian NMA model is used, which allows rank probabilities (the probability that 
each treatment is best, second best, and so on) to be calculated for decision making. However, 
the statistical properties of rank probabilities are not well understood. This study investigates 
how rank probabilities are affected by various factors such as unequal number of studies per 
comparison in the network, the sample size of individual studies, the network configuration, 
and effect sizes between treatments. In order to explore these factors, a simulation study of four 
treatments (three equally effective treatments and one less effective reference) was conducted. 
The simulation illustrated that estimates of rank probabilities are highly sensitive to both the 
number of studies per comparison and the overall network configuration. An unequal number 
of studies per comparison resulted in biased estimates of treatment rank probabilities for every 
network considered. The rank probability for the treatment that was included in the fewest 
number of studies was biased upward. Conversely, the rank of the treatment included in the 
most number of studies was consistently underestimated. When the simulation was altered to 
include three equally effective treatments and one superior treatment, the hierarchical Bayesian 
NMA model correctly identified the most effective treatment, regardless of all factors varied. 
The results of this study offer important insight into the ability of NMA models to rank treat-
ments accurately under several scenarios. The authors recommend that health researchers use 
rank probabilities cautiously in making important decisions. 
Meta-analysis is a statistical procedure that can be used to synthesize evidence from 
multiple studies to determine the common effect when effect sizes are consistent, 
or to identify reasons for variation between studies when effects are inconsistent. </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>The traditional meta-analysis method allows comparison of two interventions. In 
practice, there are often multiple therapies for a particular disease. 
3 Sound decision 
making requires comparisons of all available, relevant competing interventions. 
4,5 The 
comparative effectiveness of a range of interventions requires statistical methodology 
beyond classical meta-analysis methods. 
Network meta-analysis (NMA), also called multiple treatments meta-analysis or 
mixed treatment comparison, is an extension of the traditional pairwise meta-analysis 
that enables comparisons between multiple interventions simultaneously, 
6 respecting 
the randomization in the evidence. 
7 In practice, direct evidence may not be available for </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
Clinical Epidemiology 
3 December 2014 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>hyster </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1gen </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>2gen </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Mirena </p>

<p>Figure 1 network configuration. 
Note: Copyright © 2010. BMJ. Adapted from Middleton LJ, Champaneria R, 
Daniels JP, et al. hysterectomy, endometrial destruction, and levonorgestrel 
releasing intrauterine system (Mirena) for heavy menstrual bleeding: systematic 
review and meta-analysis of data from individual patients. 2010;341:c3929. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: 1gen, first-generation hysteroscopic endometrial destruction 
technique; 2gen, second-generation nonhysteroscopic endometrial destruction 
technique; hyster, hysterectomy. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>452 </p>

<p>Kibret et al </p>

<p>every pair of treatments. NMA enables researchers to obtain the 
relative efficacy of a particular intervention versus any compet-
ing intervention even when direct evidence is not present, via a 
common comparator. 
8 NMA yields more precise estimates by 
combining direct and indirect evidence versus direct evidence 
alone. 
4,6,7,9,10 In addition to relative effects, when conducted in 
a Bayesian framework, NMA generates the probability that 
each treatment is ranked first, second, and so on. 
11,12 It has been 
applied in clinical research areas such as diabetes, 
13 cardiovas-
cular safety, 
14 cancer, 
15 anatomy, 
16-20 and drug development, </p>

<p>21   and is gaining considerable favor among clinicians, guideline 
decision makers, and health technology agencies. </p>

<p>22-24   Considerable research focused on methodological issues 
of NMA has been published in recent years; however, a limited 
number of simulation studies have been conducted. In particu-
lar, few simulations have explored the operating characteristics 
of rank probabilities obtained from an NMA. Some concern 
has been raised about the use of rank probabilities in decision 
making. Researchers argue that rank probability is sensitive 
to various factors and it is biased when there is a paucity of 
direct comparisons. Because of this fragility, researchers 
claim that decisions based on rank probabilities should not 
be trusted unless accompanied with effect sizes of pairwise 
comparisons, such as means and their credible intervals, as 
in some cases individual treatments may be disqualified on 
the basis of cost or clinical contraindication. 
11,24-26 If there 
are few trials per comparison, as in the study by Haas et al </p>

<p>27   for neonatal mortality outcome, it may lead to the problem 
of overestimating rates, suggesting extra caution should be 
exercised when interpreting the treatment rankings. This study 
aims to investigate how rank probabilities obtained from a 
Bayesian NMA are affected by characteristics of the network, 
including network configuration, number of studies per com-
parison, individual study sample sizes, and effect sizes. The 
simulation was conducted for a binary outcome. </p>

<p>Motivating example </p>

<p>A recently published article shared the results from pair-wise 
comparisons of four treatments in the reduction of heavy 
menstrual bleeding, 
28 including analysis of individual patient 
data. The authors conducted a wide-range search for studies 
that compared hysterectomy (hyster), endometrial destruc-
tion (both first-generation hysteroscopic [1gen] and second-
generation nonhysteroscopic [2gen] techniques), and the 
levonorgestrel releasing intrauterine system (Mirena) from 
the Cochrane Library, MEDLINE, Embase, and CINAHL 
databases and reference lists. The authors found that the 
level of satisfaction with treatment was the most commonly 
measured outcome across all identified studies, with 21 out of </p>

<p>30 using this measure, and used it as their primary outcome 
measure. Direct and indirect comparisons among the four 
treatments were made without an NMA approach. The binary 
outcome data from 20 of these two-arm studies were avail-
able, and the resulting network is shown in Figure 1. 
The network plot reveals an unequal number of studies 
per comparison and the absence of direct evidence between 
some of the pairs of treatments (eg, hyster and Mirena). An 
NMA synthesizing all evidence simultaneously was not 
conducted and rank probabilities were not estimated. 
Using the available raw data (from the identified studies), 
a Bayesian NMA was performed for the purpose of yield-
ing probabilistic conclusions. It was possible to determine 
estimates for both relative effect sizes and rank probabilities 
through Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulation 
sampling using an R package called <rs type="software">gemtc</rs>. The pairwise 
estimates are available in Table 1. Based on this table, 
hysterectomy is the treatment yielding the greatest reduc-
tion of patients' dissatisfaction regarding heavy menstrual 
bleeding, with the remaining three treatments relatively 
indistinguishable. These estimates are very similar to their 
findings despite the methods applied. 
The rank probabilities of the four treatments are pro-
vided in Table 2. This ranking supports the conclusion that 
hysterectomy is the most effective treatment. However, when 
working with real data, there is no way to know if any bias is 
present in the findings. This paper will consider what factors </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>453 </p>

<p>A Bayesian NMA simulation study </p>

<p>might influence these rank probabilities. The focus will be 
on the first rank probability (ie, the first column of Table 2). 
Using comprehensive simulations, possible sources of bias in 
networks similar to this one (eg, the effect of unequal studies 
per comparison) will be assessed. 
The rest of this article is organized as follows. First, 
a brief description of the NMA method is provided. Next, 
the simulation approach is described, results are presented, 
and a discussion and limitations of the simulation are given. 
Finally, a conclusion is provided. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The NMA method relies on the fundamental assumptions 
of homogeneity, similarity, and consistency. 
29 Homogeneity 
requires the effect of treatments to be similar across trials, </p>

<p>30   similarity (or transitivity) requires that relative treatment 
effects are assumed to be exchangeable, and consistency 
(or coherence) requires that evidence from both direct and 
indirect comparisons is in agreement. 
4,29,31,32 Assumptions 
can prove difficult to verify. </p>

<p>33   In NMA, a network's geometry uses nodes to represent inter-
ventions and edges to represent the direct comparisons between </p>

<p>interventions. The amount of available information is often 
represented in network plots by varying the sizes of nodes and 
thickness of edges. The visual depiction of a network can reveal 
that some treatments are included in significantly more studies 
than others. This disparity may come from comparator prefer-
ence bias, sponsorship bias, selective reporting bias, and time lag 
bias. 
4 Network geometries range from simple (a network with 
only three treatments) to very complex (a network with multiple 
treatments). 
34 In this simulation study, graphical networks that 
often result from systematic reviews were considered: star, </p>

<p>35,36   loop, one closed loop, 
25,36,37 and ladder (linear) 
25,36,37 (Figure 2). 
All of the four network patterns also exist together in the paper 
published by Lu and Ades. 
23 Each network comprises four nodes 
representing four interventions (treatments one to four labeled 
T 1 , T 2 , T 3 , and T 4 ). Except for the star pattern, each configuration 
has both direct and indirect evidence. </p>

<p>statistical details </p>

<p>In NMA, input data are summary statistics gathered from 
published literature. The aggregate input data might be 
available in two formats: arm-level summaries (eg, odds, 
absolute risk, hazard, mean) or contrast-level summaries 
(eg, odds ratio, risk ratio, hazard ratio, mean difference). 
Arm-level data, which is modeled with the exact likeli-
hood rather than its normal approximation, 
6 were adopted 
in this simulation study. Both frequentist and Bayesian 
frameworks can suitably fit models for either of the two 
data formats. </p>

<p>38   Although inference based on NMA can be made in both 
frequentist and Bayesian frameworks, Bayesian NMA is 
more common and provides two advantages. First, it allows 
researchers to incorporate prior knowledge for parameters of 
interest and a rich and flexible family of models can be fitted. 
Second, treatment rank probabilities can be calculated easily. 
Employing a Bayesian framework requires the calculation of 
posterior distributions using MCMC methods. Procedures are 
described in detail by Salanti et al. 
11 Furthermore, Bayesian 
inferences are exact for finite samples when appropriate 
priors are used (unlike frequentist inference, which relies 
on a normality assumption) and, hence, are more appealing, 
especially with small samples. 
The calculation of rank probabilities is also straightfor-
ward in the Bayesian framework. For every MCMC run, 
each treatment in the study is ranked based on the relative 
effect estimates. The proportion of MCMC cycles in which 
the treatment ranks first gives the probability that it is the 
best among all competing treatments in the study. Similarly, 
rank probabilities of being second best, third best, and so on 
are computed for every treatment. </p>

<p>Table 2 The treatment rank probabilities </p>

<p>Rank probability </p>

<p>1st 
2nd 
3rd 
4th </p>

<p>1gen 
0.00020 
0.12555 
0.31260 
0.56165 
2gen 
0.00355 
0.35570 
0.50455 
0.13620 
Mirena 
0.04245 
0.47750 
0.17830 
0.30175 
hyster 
0.95380 
0.04125 
0.00455 
0.00040 </p>

<p>Note: Copyright © 2010. BMJ. Adapted from Middleton LJ, Champaneria R, 
Daniels JP, et al. hysterectomy, endometrial destruction, and levonorgestrel 
releasing intrauterine system (Mirena) for heavy menstrual bleeding: systematic 
review and meta-analysis of data from individual patients. 2010;341:c3929. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: 1gen, first-generation hysteroscopic endometrial destruction 
technique; 2gen, second-generation nonhysteroscopic endometrial destruction 
technique; hyster, hysterectomy. </p>

<p>Table 1 Relative treatment effects of all possible comparisons </p>

<p>1gen 
2gen 
Mirena 
hyster </p>

<p>1gen 
-
1.14 
(0.78-1.61) </p>

<p>1.16 
(0.54-2.50) </p>

<p>2.72* 
(1.51-5.05) 
2gen 
0.88 
(0.62-1.28) </p>

<p>-
1.02 
(0.50-2.09) </p>

<p>2.38 
(1.23-4.95) 
Mirena 
0.86 
(0.40-1.84) </p>

<p>0.98 
(0.48-2.01) </p>

<p>-
2.34 
(0.89-6.17) 
hyster 
0.37 
(0.20-0.66) </p>

<p>0.42 
(0.20-0.82) </p>

<p>0.43 
(0.16-1.12) </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Notes: *The figures in the table show estimated odds ratios along with 95% credible 
interval (CrI) for the treatment shown in the row relative to the treatment in the 
corresponding column. For example, we can see that more women were dissatisfied 
at 12 months after first generation endometrial destruction than after hysterectomy: 
odds ratio (95% CrI) 2.72 (1.51 to 5.05). 
Abbreviations: 1gen, first-generation hysteroscopic endometrial destruction tech-
nique; 2gen, second-generation nonhysteroscopic endometrial destruction technique; 
hyster, hysterectomy. </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>454 </p>

<p>Kibret et al </p>

<p>The general linear model for NMA has been proposed 
by several researchers. 
32,39 The model can be fitted for dif-
ferent types of data, including normal, binomial, Poisson, 
and multinomial. The following sections will review how 
the Bayesian NMA model can be fitted for arm-level study 
summaries of binary outcomes. </p>

<p>Fixed effects models in NMA </p>

<p>This section describes both fixed and random effects NMA 
models confined to binary outcomes. Suppose that there are 
N randomized controlled trials that compare K treatments. 
Let r ik be the number of events of the ith clinical trial in the 
arm representing treatment k. Let n ik represent the number 
of observations and p ik denote the corresponding success 
probability for treatment k in study i. Then the distribution 
of the number of events is given by: </p>

<p>r 
Bin p n 
i 
N k 
K </p>

<p>ik 
ik 
ik </p>

<p>( , ), 
, , ; 
, , 
= 
= 
1 
12 
… 
… 
(1) </p>

<p>where p ik represents the corresponding probability of a suc-
cessful outcome for treatment k and is modeled on the logit 
scale as: </p>

<p>log ( ) log 
, , , ; 
, , 
it 
p 
p 
i 
N b k 
K </p>

<p>ib </p>

<p>ib </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>p ib = 
-
= 
= 
= = 
1 
1 2 
1 
µ 
… 
… </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>log ( ) log 
log ( 
) </p>

<p>, 
, </p>

<p>it p 
p 
p 
d 
p 
it 
d </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>i 
i k 
i k 
k </p>

<p>= 
-
= + 
⇔ 
= 
+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 
1 
11 </p>

<p>µ 
µ </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>with i =1, 2, …, N; k =2, …, k; b  k where µ i are the trial 
specific baselines representing the log odds of an event occur-
ring in the referent treatment group (k = b). Then, d i,1k are the </p>

<p>fixed trial-specific log odds of event occurrence in group k 
compared with the referent treatment. The logit link function 
maps the probabilities onto the real number line. </p>

<p>Random effects models in NMA </p>

<p>In a random effects model, each study i provides an esti-
mate of the study-specific log odds, δ i,1k which are assumed 
to be independent of the order in which they were carried 
out (exchangeable). Then, the random effects model is 
obtained by replacing d i,1k in the above fixed effects model 
by δ i,1k , ie, </p>

<p>log ( ) log 
, </p>

<p>, , 
; 
, , ; 
. </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>it p 
p 
p </p>

<p>i 
N k 
k b k </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>i 
i k </p>

<p>= 
-
= + </p>

<p>= 
= 
&lt; </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 2 
2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>µ δ </p>

<p>… 
… 
(4) </p>

<p>It is typically assumed that δ 
σ </p>

<p>i bk 
b k 
k 
b </p>

<p>N d 
d 
d </p>

<p>,~( </p>

<p>, ) 
= 
-</p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>2 . </p>

<p>The notation k  b indicates that k is after b and d 11 =0. Prior 
distributions for basic parameters (d 12 , d 13 , d 14 , …) need to 
be assumed in the Bayesian framework while the remaining 
contrasts, called functional parameters, are defined in terms 
of those treatments compared with the baseline treatment 
directly assuming consistency. The functional parameters 
are written as: </p>

<p>d d d b 
K s 
K </p>

<p>t 
K s t </p>

<p>st 
bt 
bs </p>

<p>= -
= 
= </p>

<p>= 
&lt; </p>

<p>, 
, , , ; 
, , , ; </p>

<p>, , , ; 
. </p>

<p>1 2 
2 3 </p>

<p>3 4 </p>

<p>… 
… </p>

<p>… 
(5) </p>

<p>With regard to choice of priors for hyperparameters, it 
is common to set weakly informative priors that let the data 
speak, usually µ 
β </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>d 
N </p>

<p>bk </p>

<p>, , 
( , 
) 
∼ 0 10 
4 . 
4,32,39 For the likelihood of 
binomial outcomes with logit link models, a uniform flat prior </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>T 1 </p>

<p>T 1 </p>

<p>T 1 </p>

<p>T 2 </p>

<p>T 2 
T 2 </p>

<p>T 2 </p>

<p>T 1 </p>

<p>T 3 </p>

<p>T 3 </p>

<p>T 3 
T 3 </p>

<p>T 4 </p>

<p>T 4 </p>

<p>T 4 </p>

<p>T 4 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Type of network geometry considered in our simulation. 
Notes: (A) Star geometry. (B) Loop geometry. (C) One closed loop geometry. (D) Ladder or linear geometry. T 1 denotes a reference treatment and T 2 to T 4 are treatments 
that are compared relative to the reference. </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>455 </p>

<p>A Bayesian NMA simulation study </p>

<p>for the standard deviation (ie, σ ∼ Uniform ( , ) 
0 5 ) 
40 is usually 
used. A flat γ prior on the precision (ie, 1/σ 
γ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 001 0 001 
∼ ( . , . )) 
is another alternative. It assigns small weights to a large stan-
dard deviation. This feature may be useful particularly when 
data are sparse to improve numerical stability and speed 
convergence of MCMC sampling. 
The dramatic increase of interest in the Bayesian analysis 
is primarily because of the emergence of MCMC methods. 
While the MCMC method provides a convenient way to 
draw inference from complicated statistical models, there 
are some problems associated with this method. One of 
these problems is that convergence in MCMC sampler is a 
complex issue. It usually needs a large number of iterations 
to reach convergence. In addition, early MCMC iterations 
are highly sensitive to starting values of parameters and do 
not provide good information about the target distribution 
and, hence, are required to be thinned. The basic idea is 
that although the chains look divergent at early iterations 
due to different starting points, when the MCMC algorithm 
is converged, the chains should mix together and become 
indistinguishable from each other as they converge to the 
same posterior distribution. In this study, the package gemtc 
(http://cran.r-proct.org/web/packages/gemtc/index.html) 
from the R library, was used to implement the Bayesian 
NMA through MCMC simulation nicely, and is compat-
ible with other packages that can conduct convergence 
diagnostics. </p>

<p>Simulation studies </p>

<p>In this section, the simulation design and results are provided. 
As outlined in the Background section, this simulation study 
addresses how an unequal number of studies per comparison 
affects the ranking of treatments and the influence of network 
configuration. </p>

<p>simulation design </p>

<p>In this study, four treatments were considered and two-
arm level binary data were simulated. The treatments were 
denoted T 1 (placebo), T 2 , T 3 , and T 4 . The parameters varied 
during simulation are given in Table 3. Three scenarios were 
considered. The first two scenarios used the success prob-
ability conditions (0.1, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5) for (T 1 , T 2 , T 3 , T 4 ). In 
both scenarios, three equivalent treatments were compared 
with a reference treatment, T 1 . The difference between 
the two scenarios was the position of the reference treat-
ment within the network configuration, ie, T 1 and T 3 were 
interchanged. The third scenario with success probabilities 
(0.2, 0.2, 0.2, 0.8) for (T 1 , T 2 , T 3 , T 4 ) compared a superior </p>

<p>treatment with the remaining equally inferior treatments. 
Under each of the three scenarios, four different network 
patterns, seven different numbers of studies per comparison, 
and three different study-level sample sizes were used to 
simulate arm-level data. 
For the ladder and star geometries, the unequal number 
of studies (1, 5, 15) denoted the number of studies for the 
comparisons between treatments (T 1 and T 2 , T 2 and T 3 , T 3 
and T 4 ) and (T 1 and T 2 , T 1 and T 3 , T 1 and T 4 ), respectively. 
Likewise, the unequal number of studies (1, 3, 5, 15) for loop 
and one closed loop geometries denoted the number of studies 
comparing the pairs of treatments (T 1 and T 2 , T 2 and T 3 , T 3 
and T 4 , T 1 and T 4 ), respectively. Lastly, for the completely 
connected loop geometry, the number of studies between (T 1 
and T 2 , T 1 and T 3 , T 1 and T 4 , T 2 and T 3 , T 2 and T 4 , T 3 and T 4 ) 
were set at (1, 2, 3, 5, 10, 15), respectively. 
Using the parameters described above, binary data 
were generated from an appropriate binomial distribution. 
Then, the hierarchical Bayesian NMA model was fitted to 
perform statistical inference. In each MCMC simulation, 
the first 5,000 iterations were discarded as a burn-in to 
minimize the effect of initial values on the posterior 
distribution. Moreover, to minimize poor mixing (or slow 
convergence), chains were thinned by keeping every 
tenth simulated draw from each MCMC sequence. After 
burn-in and thinning, 2,000 iterations were used to estimate 
posterior distributions and make inferences about rank 
probabilities. For each simulation setting, this process was 
repeated 1,000 times. Convergence was assessed using 
the Brooks-Rubin diagnostic test where a potential scale 
reduction factor of 1.05 or lower was considered sufficient 
for convergence. </p>

<p>41   The first rank probability estimates yielded from the 
MCMC process were averaged over the 1,000 simulations 
for each setting to create mean first rank probabilities. Two 
measures of performance, the bias for estimates of first rank 
probabilities and the standard deviation of the estimates over 
1,000 samples, were calculated. </p>

<p>Table 3 Parameters varied during simulations </p>

<p>Parameters 
Values </p>

<p>Probability of success 
for T 1 , T 2 , T 3 , T 4 </p>

<p>(0.1, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5), (0.5, 0.5, 
0.1, 0.5), (0.2, 0.2, 0.2, 0.8) 
study sample size 
50, 100, 200 
network pattern 
star, ladder, loop, one closed loop 
Number of studies per comparison </p>

<p>network 
star, ladder 
loop, one closed loop </p>

<p>Equal: 
(1, 2, 3, 5, 10, 15) 
(1, 2, 3, 5, 10, 15) </p>

<p>Unequal: 
(1, 5, 15) 
(1, 3, 5, 15) </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>456 </p>

<p>Kibret et al </p>

<p>simulation results </p>

<p>In this section, estimates of the mean, bias, and standard 
deviation of first rank probabilities for each simulation set-
ting are given. For the first two sets of success probabilities, 
no difference between the average first rank probabilities of 
T 2 , T 3 , and T 4 were expected. Table 4 shows results for a star 
geometry. For an equal number of studies per comparison, 
the star geometry identified treatments as expected with 
minimal bias. However, with an unequal number of studies 
per comparison, the star geometry showed large bias and 
large standard deviation. 
The upward bias of the first rank probability corresponds 
to the treatment with the smallest number of studies in the 
network. All possible permutations of the unbalanced number 
of studies were checked and showed that the overestimation 
of the first rank probability always aligns with the treatment 
used in the fewest number of studies. 
Table 5 shows results for the loop geometry. Here, T 3 was 
consistently underestimated, albeit slightly, though it was 
expected to be equivalent in efficacy with T 2 and T 4 . 
In order to determine the impact of direct evidence, 
an additional simulation was conducted using a complete 
network. When direct evidence was available for all treat-
ment comparisons, the model correctly estimated the ranks 
of treatments. These results are provided in Table 6. 
The results from the one closed loop geometry are pro-
vided in Table 7. As with the loop geometry, the rank prob-
ability of T 3 was underestimated while those of T 2 and T 4 
were overestimated. The underestimation by the one closed 
loop configuration was more extreme than with the loop 
configuration. This appears to be related to the additional 
direct evidence in the one closed loop configuration; T 3 was </p>

<p>compared with T 1 , T 2 , and T 4 as opposed to only T 2 and T 4 
in loop geometry. 
Table 8 displays the results of when the position of the 
reference treatment for the one closed loop network geometry 
was changed. This result shows that T 4 , the treatment that was 
compared only with the placebo, was favored as compared to 
the other two equivalent treatments, which were compared 
to one another. 
Table 9 shows results for the ladder geometry. The first 
rank probability for T 3 was underestimated as with the loop 
geometry, with even stronger bias. 
Table 10 shows results for the final scenario, when T 4 is 
superior in efficacy compared to three equally less effective 
treatments. Here, as expected, T 4 was identified by the model 
under each simulation setting as the most effective treatment 
with highest rank probability, regardless of the network 
geometry or placement of the superior treatment within it. 
The impact of the number of studies on the rank probability 
was negligible. In this scenario, bias and standard deviations 
were generally very small in all cases. The results were 
presented with a sample size of 50 for the star network pat-
tern since the results were not markedly different for other 
network configurations or sample sizes, regardless of the 
position of the superior treatment. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>NMA offers a set of methods to model, visualize, analyze, and 
interpret a comprehensive picture of the evidence involving 
multiple treatments and to understand the relative merits of 
each intervention. In NMA, the Bayesian approach is becom-
ing more popular than the frequentist approach. It provides 
a simple process for calculating the rank probabilities of </p>

<p>Table 4 Star network pattern with success probabilities (0.1, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5) and n=200 </p>

<p>Number of 
studies </p>

<p>Rank probability 
Bias 
Standard deviation </p>

<p>T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 </p>

<p>(1, 1, 1) 
0.00 
0.33 
0.33 
0.34 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.10 
0.10 
0.10 
(2, 2, 2) 
0.00 
0.34 
0.32 
0.34 
0.00 
0.00 
-0.01 
0.00 
0.00 
0.19 
0.20 
0.20 
(3, 3, 3) 
0.00 
0.34 
0.32 
0.33 
0.00 
0.01 
-0.01 
0.00 
0.00 
0.23 
0.22 
0.23 
(5, 5, 5) 
0.00 
0.33 
0.34 
0.33 
0.00 
0.00 
0.01 
0.00 
0.00 
0.23 
0.24 
0.24 
(10, 10, 10) 
0.00 
0.35 
0.33 
0.33 
0.00 
0.01 
-0.01 
-0.01 
0.00 
0.25 
0.24 
0.24 
(15, 15, 15) 
0.00 
0.34 
0.32 
0.34 
0.00 
0.01 
-0.01 
0.01 
0.00 
0.25 
0.24 
0.25 
(1, 5, 15) 
0.00 
0.43 
0.31 
0.26 
0.00 
0.09 
-0.02 
-0.07 
0.00 
0.27 
0.23 
0.21 
(15, 5, 1) 
0.00 
0.26 
0.30 
0.44 
0.00 
-0.07 
-0.03 
0.10 
0.00 
0.22 
0.23 
0.27 
(15, 1, 5) 
0.00 
0.27 
0.43 
0.31 
0.00 
-0.07 
0.09 
-0.02 
0.00 
0.21 
0.27 
0.24 
(1, 15, 5) 
0.00 
0.43 
0.26 
0.31 
0.00 
0.10 
-0.07 
-0.02 
0.00 
0.27 
0.21 
0.24 
(5, 15, 1) 
0.00 
0.30 
0.26 
0.44 
0.00 
-0.03 
-0.08 
0.11 
0.00 
0.23 
0.21 
0.27 
(5, 1, 15) 
0.00 
0.30 
0.44 
0.25 
0.00 
-0.03 
0.11 
-0.08 
0.00 
0.23 
0.27 
0.21 </p>

<p>Note: T 1 is reference treatment and T 2 to T 4 are treatments in comparison relative to this reference. </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>457 </p>

<p>A Bayesian NMA simulation study </p>

<p>Table 6 Loop (complete) network pattern with success probabilities (0.1, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5) and n=200 </p>

<p>Number of studies 
Rank probability 
Bias 
Standard deviation </p>

<p>T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 </p>

<p>(1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1) 
0.00 
0.33 
0.33 
0.34 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.19 
0.19 
0.19 
(2, 2, 2, 2, 2, 2) 
0.00 
0.32 
0.33 
0.35 
0.00 
-0.01 
0.00 
0.01 
0.00 
0.23 
0.23 
0.23 </p>

<p>(3, 3, 3, 3, 3, 3) 
0.00 
0.33 
0.33 
0.34 
0.00 
0.00 
-0.01 
0.00 
0.00 
0.23 
0.23 
0.24 </p>

<p>(5, 5, 5, 5, 5, 5) 
0.00 
0.35 
0.32 
0.32 
0.00 
0.02 
-0.01 
-0.01 
0.00 
0.25 
0.24 
0.24 </p>

<p>(10, 10, 10, 10, 10, 10) 
0.00 
0.32 
0.33 
0.35 
0.00 
-0.01 
0.00 
0.01 
0.00 
0.24 
0.25 
0.25 </p>

<p>(15, 15, 15, 15, 15, 15) 
0.00 
0.34 
0.33 
0.33 
0.00 
0.01 
-0.01 
0.00 
0.00 
0.26 
0.25 
0.25 </p>

<p>(1, 2, 3, 5, 10, 15) 
0.00 
0.37 
0.33 
0.29 
0.00 
0.04 
0.00 
-0.04 
0.00 
0.26 
0.25 
0.23 </p>

<p>(15, 10, 5, 3, 2, 1) 
0.00 
0.29 
0.34 
0.38 
0.00 
-0.05 
0.00 
0.04 
0.00 
0.23 
0.25 
0.26 </p>

<p>Note: T 1 is reference treatment and T 2 to T 4 are treatments in comparison relative to this reference. </p>

<p>Table 7 One closed loop network pattern with success probabilities (0.1, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5) and n=200 </p>

<p>Number 
of studies </p>

<p>Rank probability 
Bias 
Standard deviation </p>

<p>T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 </p>

<p>(1, 1, 1, 1) 
0.00 
0.36 
0.24 
0.39 
0.00 
0.03 
-0.09 
0.06 
0.00 
0.14 
0.10 
0.14 </p>

<p>(2, 2, 2, 2) 
0.00 
0.35 
0.26 
0.38 
0.00 
0.02 
-0.07 
0.05 
0.00 
0.22 
0.19 
0.22 </p>

<p>(3, 3, 3, 3) 
0.00 
0.35 
0.26 
0.39 
0.00 
0.02 
-0.08 
0.06 
0.00 
0.23 
0.19 
0.24 </p>

<p>(5, 5, 5, 5) 
0.00 
0.37 
0.25 
0.37 
0.00 
0.04 
-0.08 
0.04 
0.00 
0.25 
0.20 
0.25 </p>

<p>(10, 10, 10, 10) 
0.00 
0.36 
0.25 
0.39 
0.00 
0.03 
-0.09 
0.06 
0.00 
0.26 
0.21 
0.27 </p>

<p>(15, 15, 15, 15) 
0.00 
0.36 
0.24 
0.40 
0.00 
0.03 
-0.09 
0.07 
0.00 
0.26 
0.21 
0.27 </p>

<p>(1, 3, 5, 15) 
0.00 
0.42 
0.25 
0.33 
0.00 
0.08 
-0.08 
0.00 
0.00 
0.27 
0.21 
0.24 </p>

<p>(15, 3, 5, 1) 
0.00 
0.31 
0.25 
0.44 
0.00 
-0.02 
-0.08 
0.11 
0.00 
0.23 
0.20 
0.26 </p>

<p>Note: T 1 is reference treatment and T 2 to T 4 are treatments in comparison relative to this reference. </p>

<p>Table 5 Loop network pattern with success probabilities (0.1, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5) and n=200 </p>

<p>Number of 
studies </p>

<p>Rank probability 
Bias 
Standard deviation </p>

<p>T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 </p>

<p>(1, 1, 1, 1) 
0.00 
0.35 
0.29 
0.35 
0.00 
0.02 
-0.04 
0.02 
0.00 
0.13 
0.12 
0.13 </p>

<p>(2, 2, 2, 2) 
0.00 
0.34 
0.31 
0.35 
0.00 
0.01 
-0.03 
0.02 
0.00 
0.22 
0.20 
0.21 </p>

<p>(3, 3, 3, 3) 
0.00 
0.36 
0.29 
0.35 
0.00 
0.03 
-0.05 
0.02 
0.00 
0.24 
0.21 
0.24 </p>

<p>(5, 5, 5, 5) 
0.00 
0.36 
0.28 
0.36 
0.00 
0.02 
-0.05 
0.03 
0.00 
0.25 
0.22 
0.25 </p>

<p>(10, 10, 10, 10) 
0.00 
0.36 
0.28 
0.36 
0.00 
0.02 
-0.06 
0.03 
0.00 
0.27 
0.23 
0.26 </p>

<p>(15, 15, 15, 15) 
0.00 
0.35 
0.30 
0.36 
0.00 
0.02 
-0.04 
0.02 
0.00 
0.25 
0.23 
0.25 </p>

<p>(1, 3, 5, 15) 
0.00 
0.38 
0.27 
0.35 
0.00 
0.04 
-0.06 
0.02 
0.00 
0.25 
0.21 
0.25 </p>

<p>(15, 3, 5, 1) 
0.00 
0.37 
0.28 
0.35 
0.00 
0.04 
-0.05 
0.02 
0.00 
0.25 
0.21 
0.24 </p>

<p>Note: T 1 is reference treatment and T 2 to T 4 are treatments in comparison relative to this reference. </p>

<p>Table 8 One closed loop network pattern with success probabilites (0.1, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5) and n=200 </p>

<p>Number 
of studies </p>

<p>Rank probability 
Bias 
Standard deviation </p>

<p>T 3 
T 2 
T 1 
T 4 
T 3 
T 2 
T 1 
T 4 
T 3 
T 2 
T 1 
T 4 </p>

<p>(1, 1, 1, 1) 
0.30 
0.29 
0.00 
0.41 
-0.04 
-0.04 
0.00 
0.08 
0.12 
0.12 
0.00 
0.15 </p>

<p>(2, 2, 2, 2) 
0.28 
0.28 
0.00 
0.44 
-0.06 
-0.05 
0.00 
0.10 
0.20 
0.20 
0.00 
0.24 </p>

<p>(3, 3, 3, 3) 
0.29 
0.29 
0.00 
0.42 
-0.04 
-0.05 
0.00 
0.09 
0.22 
0.22 
0.00 
0.26 </p>

<p>(5, 5, 5, 5) 
0.30 
0.29 
0.00 
0.41 
-0.03 
-0.05 
0.00 
0.08 
0.23 
0.22 
0.00 
0.27 </p>

<p>(10, 10, 10, 10) 
0.29 
0.30 
0.00 
0.41 
-0.05 
-0.03 
0.00 
0.08 
0.22 
0.23 
0.00 
0.27 </p>

<p>(15, 15, 15, 15) 
0.28 
0.30 
0.00 
0.42 
-0.06 
-0.03 
0.00 
0.09 
0.22 
0.24 
0.00 
0.28 </p>

<p>(1, 3, 5, 15) 
0.35 
0.33 
0.00 
0.32 
0.02 
-0.00 
0.00 
-0.01 
0.25 
0.24 
0.00 
0.24 </p>

<p>(15, 3, 5, 1) 
0.25 
0.26 
0.00 
0.49 
-0.08 
-0.08 
0.00 
0.16 
0.21 
0.22 
0.00 
0.28 </p>

<p>Note: T 1 is reference treatment and T 2 to T 4 are treatments in comparison relative to this reference. </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



<p>Kibret et al </p>

<p>interventions, incorporates prior knowledge, and fits more 
flexible models. 
The primary purpose of this article was to examine 
the effect of various factors on rank probabilities of treat-
ments in NMA through simulation. For the treatments 
compared in loop, one closed loop, and ladder network 
structures with an equal number of studies per comparison, 
the model-estimated rank probabilities exhibited bias. The 
model favored the treatment that was directly compared 
with the fewest number of treatments in the network 
patterns. The rank probability of the treatment that was 
compared with the largest number of treatments was always 
underestimated. 
The simulations also showed that when two equally 
effective treatments in the same network are included in 
the same number of direct comparisons, the effectiveness 
of the treatments to which they are compared will affect 
the rankings. Treatments that are compared directly with 
inferior treatments yield ranks that are overestimated, 
while treatments that are exclusively compared with equal 
or superior treatments yield ranks that are underestimated. 
When there is an unequal number of studies per comparison 
for a given network structure, the model overestimated 
the rank probability of the treatment associated with 
smaller number of studies. The first rank probability's </p>

<p>overestimation when it is the least-studied treatment is an 
artifact of a larger estimated variance for that treatment. The 
rank probabilities obtained from Bayesian NMA for loop, 
one closed loop, and ladder geometry can be reliable only 
when there is direct evidence for every treatment involved 
in the analysis or when there is an obvious superiority in 
efficacy. In other words, rank estimates for treatments that 
have never been directly compared should not be trusted. 
The position of the reference treatment in the network may 
affect conclusions from rank probabilities. Increasing the 
sample size of individual studies did not help to adjust the 
over/underestimation of the rank probabilities. These find-
ings validate the concerns of Mills et al 
24 about using rank 
probabilities for decision making. 
There are some limitations of this simulation that must 
be noted. Although the Bayesian NMA model can be used 
broadly, only a binary outcome was considered in this 
simulation study. This study was also confined to only 
two-arm studies. In practice, multi-arm studies in NMA 
are often encountered where correlation is induced among 
contrasts that involve a common comparator and must be 
modeled. 
38,42 Furthermore, this study only focused on the 
rank probabilities that each treatment is best, but the authors 
might be interested in investigating all of the ranks of avail-
able treatments. </p>

<p>Table 9 Ladder network pattern success probabilities (0.1, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5) and n=200 </p>

<p>Number 
of studies </p>

<p>Rank probability 
Bias 
Standard deviation </p>

<p>T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 </p>

<p>(1, 1, 1) 
0.02 
0.36 
0.24 
0.37 
0.02 
0.03 
-0.09 
0.04 
0.00 
0.09 
0.07 
0.09 
(2, 2, 2) 
0.00 
0.37 
0.25 
0.38 
0.00 
0.04 
-0.09 
0.05 
0.00 
0.20 
0.16 
0.20 
(3, 3, 3) 
0.00 
0.38 
0.25 
0.38 
0.00 
0.04 
-0.09 
0.05 
0.00 
0.23 
0.18 
0.23 
(5, 5, 5) 
0.00 
0.37 
0.25 
0.38 
0.00 
0.04 
-0.08 
0.04 
0.00 
0.24 
0.20 
0.24 
(10, 10, 10) 
0.00 
0.39 
0.24 
0.37 
0.00 
0.05 
-0.09 
0.04 
0.00 
0.26 
0.21 
0.26 
(15, 15, 15) 
0.00 
0.37 
0.25 
0.38 
0.00 
0.04 
-0.09 
0.05 
0.00 
0.26 
0.21 
0.26 
(1, 5, 15) 
0.00 
0.41 
0.25 
0.34 
0.00 
0.08 
-0.08 
0.00 
0.00 
0.26 
0.21 
0.25 
(15, 5, 1) 
0.00 
0.32 
0.25 
0.43 
0.00 
-0.01 
-0.09 
0.09 
0.00 
0.22 
0.19 
0.25 </p>

<p>Note: T 1 is reference treatment and T 2 to T 4 are treatments in comparison relative to this reference. </p>

<p>Table 10 Star network pattern success probabilities (0.2, 0.2, 0.2, 0.8) and n=200 </p>

<p>Number 
of studies </p>

<p>Rank probability 
Bias 
Standard deviation </p>

<p>T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 
T 1 
T 2 
T 3 
T 4 </p>

<p>(1, 1, 1) 
0.01 
0.08 
0.08 
0.83 
0.01 
0.08 
0.08 
-0.17 
0.00 
0.04 
0.04 
0.04 
(2, 2, 2) 
0.00 
0.01 
0.01 
0.98 
0.00 
0.01 
0.01 
-0.02 
0.00 
0.01 
0.01 
0.02 
(3, 3, 3)  0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
1.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
(5, 5, 5)  0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
1.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
(10, 10, 10)  0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
1.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
(15, 15, 15)  0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
1.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
(1, 5, 15)  0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
1.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.01 
0.00 
0.01 
(15, 5, 1)  0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
1.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>459 </p>

<p>A Bayesian NMA simulation study </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>This simulation study revealed several occasions of bias 
of rank probabilities obtained from a Bayesian NMA. For 
example, for an unequal number of studies per comparison, 
the rank probability of the treatment with more studies was 
underestimated. In addition, the rank probability of the treat-
ment that was directly compared with the placebo and an 
equivalent treatment simultaneously (eg, T 2 and T 4 in loop, 
ladder, and one closed loop geometries) gained spurious rank 
probabilities, whereas the rank probability of a treatment that 
was compared with two equivalent treatments (eg, T 3 in loop, 
ladder, and one closed loop) was underestimated. In summary, 
decisions should not be made based on rank probabilities espe-
cially when treatments are not directly compared (ie, ladder, 
one closed loop, star) as they may be ill-informed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>JB would like to acknowledge Discovery Grant funding from 
the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of 
Canada (NSERC) (grant number 293295-2009) and Canadian 
Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) (grant number 84392). 
JB holds the John D. Cameron Endowed Chair in the Genetic 
Determinants of Chronic Diseases, Department of Clinical 
Epidemiology and Biostatistics, McMaster University. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>Clinical Epidemiology </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/clinical-epidemiology-journal </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology is an international, peer-reviewed, open access, 
online journal focusing on disease and drug epidemiology, identifica-
tion of risk factors and screening procedures to develop optimal pre-
ventative initiatives and programs. Specific topics include: diagnosis, 
prognosis, treatment, screening, prevention, risk factor modification, </p>

<p>systematic reviews, risk &amp; safety of medical interventions, epidemiol-
ogy &amp; biostatistical methods, and evaluation of guidelines, translational 
medicine, health policies &amp; economic evaluations. The manuscript 
management system is completely online and includes a very quick 
and fair peer-review system, which is all easy to use. </p>

<p>Clinical Epidemiology 2014:6 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>