<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4360915" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Statherin is an important salivary protein for maintaining oral health. The purpose of the current 
study was to determine if differences in statherin levels exist between diabetic and healthy subjects. 
Methods: A total of 48 diabetic and healthy controls were randomly selected from a community-based database. Di-
abetic subjects (n = 24) had fasting glucose levels N 180 mg/dL, while controls (n = 24) had levels b 110 mg/dL. Pa-
rotid saliva (PS) and sublingual/submandibular saliva (SS) were collected and salivary flow rates determined. 
Salivary statherin levels were determined by densitometry of Western blots. Blood hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) and 
total protein in saliva were also obtained. 
Results: SS, but not PS, salivary flow rate and total protein in diabetics were significantly less than those in healthy 
controls (p = 0.021 &amp; p b 0.001 respectively). Correlation analysis revealed the existence of a negative correlation 
between PS statherin levels and HbA1c (p = 0.012) and fasting glucose (p = 0.021) levels, while no such correlation 
was found for SS statherin levels. When statherin levels were normalized to total salivary protein, the proportion of 
PS statherin, but not SS statherin, in diabetics was significantly less than that in controls (p = 0.032). In contrast, the 
amount of statherin secretion in SS, but not PS, was significantly decreased in diabetics compared to controls (p = 
0.016). 
Conclusions and general significance: The results show that synthesis and secretion of statherin is reduced in diabetics 
and this reduction is salivary gland specific. As compromised salivary statherin secretion leads to increased oral 
health risk, this study indicates that routine oral health assessment of these patients is warranted. 
Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Diabetes mellitus is a growing global epidemic with more than 
439 million projected to be affected by 2030 [3]. Oral diseases, such as 
periodontitis, dental caries, fungal infection, xerostomia, and salivary 
gland dysfunction, are all major complications associated with diabetes 
[6,17]. Saliva contains a number of components, such as electrolytes, </p>

<p>multiple buffering systems, digestive enzymes, lubricant glycoproteins, 
and antimicrobial proteins, to maintain oral homeostasis and preserve 
the health of the teeth and oral mucosa and prevent infection. There-
fore, salivary dysfunction may account for a number of the oral diseases 
associated with diabetes and may be a risk factor for these patients. In-
deed, decreased salivary flow rates have been documented in clinical 
cohort studies and animal models of diabetes [17,23,31]. Further, a lim-
ited number of studies have reported changes in saliva composition, 
such as amylase, total protein and antimicrobial proteins, in diabetic pa-
tients [6,14,23,27]. 
Human salivary statherin is a low molecular weight phosphoprotein, 
containing 43 amino acids, that functions to inhibit spontaneous pre-
cipitation of calcium and phosphate salts (primary precipitation) from sa-
liva and the growth of hydroxyapatite crystals (secondary precipitation) 
on the surface of the teeth [18,20]. In addition, statherin is a major compo-
nent of the "acquired" dental pellicle and functions to regulate mineraliza-
tion at the surface through binding of its hydrophilic N-terminal domain 
to hydroxyapatite and selection of oral microorganisms that bind to the </p>

<p>BBA Clinical 3 (2015) 135-140 </p>

<p>⁎ Corresponding author at: Geriatric Research Education and Clinical Center (GRECC), 
South Texas Veterans Healthcare System, 7400 Merton Minter Boulevard, San Antonio, 
TX 78229-4404, USA. Tel.: +1 210 617 5197; fax: +1 210 617 5312. 
E-mail addresses: izumim@dpc.agu.ac.jp (M. Izumi), zhangb2@uthscsa.edu 
(B.-X. Zhang), deand@uthscsa.edu (D.D. Dean), lina@uthscsa.edu (A.L. Lin), 
saunders@uthscsa.edu (M.J. Saunders), hazuda@uthscsa.edu (H.P. Hazuda), 
yeh@uthscsa.edu (C.-K. Yeh). 
1 Equal contributions as first author. 
2 Current address: Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Radiology, Aichi-Gakuin </p>

<p>University School of Dentistry, 2-11 Suemori-Dori, Chikusa-Ku, Nagoya 464-8651, Japan. 
Tel./fax: +81 52 759 2165. </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbacli.2015.01.002 
2214-6474/Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). </p>

<p>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect </p>

<p>BBA Clinical </p>

<p>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : h t t p : / / w w w . j o u r n a l s . e l s e v i e r . c o m / b b a -c l i n i c a l / </p>

<p>pellicle through its C-terminal domain [7,18,20]. Further, the level of 
statherin in whole saliva has been reported to be higher in caries-free pa-
tients than in caries-susceptible patients and those with elevated 
decayed, missing, and filled teeth (DMFT) indices [29]. Based on these 
observations, it is generally believed that statherin plays a critical role in 
protecting oral tissues from a number of common dental disorders 
(e.g., periodontal diseases, dental caries and oral mucosa infections) [11, 
25]. 
Previous studies have shown that oral health in patients with type 2 
diabetes is compromised and that many of the problems these patients 
have are attributable to reduced salivary production or secretion and al-
terations in the composition of their saliva [17,23,31]. In other studies, 
statherin expression in labial, submandibular, and parotid gland tissue, 
obtained from control and diabetic (type 2) patients undergoing head 
and neck tumor resection, was examined using immunogold labeling 
and transmission electron microscopy (TEM). Statherin immunoreac-
tivity was detected in small vesicles, diffusely localized throughout the 
cytoplasm of labial serous cells, and in secretory granules of serous 
acinar cells in both submandibular and parotid glands [11-13]. Detailed 
statistical analyses revealed that the number of stained particles was 
significantly lower in tissues of diabetic subjects than non-diabetic 
controls. Recent proteome and peptidome analyses of saliva from chil-
dren with type 1 diabetes also suggest a relatively lower production of 
statherin than those in controls [1]. 
Since the earlier studies, mentioned above, demonstrated decreased 
production of statherin in salivary gland tissue (type 2 diabetics) and sa-
liva (type 1 diabetics), the current study aimed to determine whether 
there are measurable differences in salivary statherin from sublingual/ 
submandibular and parotid glands from normal (n = 24) and type 2 
diabetic (n = 24) middle aged subjects. Changes in statherin production 
were also evaluated for correlation with fasting blood glucose and 
HbA1c levels and DMFT indices. The overall goal was to evaluate wheth-
er salivary statherin had potential as a marker of salivary dysfunction, 
oral health, and overall disease activity in type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>2.1. Subjects </p>

<p>A total of 48 subjects, 24 diabetic and 24 healthy age-and gender-
matched controls, were randomly selected from 1322 subjects in the 
Oral Health: San Antonio Longitudinal Study of Aging (OH: SALSA) data-
base [6] which included both Mexican American and European 
American ethnic groups. The number of subjects to be included in the 
study was estimated using a power analysis (effect size = 0.85,αerror = 
0.05, power = 0.80) and based on a preliminary study of PS. The study 
protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Univer-
sity of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio and informed consent 
was obtained from each participant. Diabetic subjects were identified 
based on fasting plasma glucose levels N 180 mg/dL. Control subjects 
(non-diabetic), with comparable age and gender to the diabetic cohort, 
were identified by having no major health problems and fasting plasma 
glucose levels b 110 mg/dL. Some of the control subjects, however, were 
taking anti-cholesterolemic or anti-hypertensive medications. Body 
mass index (BMI), HbA1c, and oral health status were also obtained 
for both groups, but not used as selection criteria. </p>

<p>2.2. Saliva collection </p>

<p>Parotid saliva (PS) and sublingual/submandibular saliva (SS) pro-
duction were stimulated and collected as previously described [6]. In 
brief, PS was collected using a modified Carlson-Crittenden cup, while 
SS was collected using a micropipette connected to a mini-vacuum 
pump. Stimulation of saliva production was achieved by swabbing the 
lateral surfaces of the tongue with 0.1 M (≈2%, w/v) citric acid every 
30 s. PS was collected for 5 min and SS for 3 min. Salivary flow rate </p>

<p>was calculated by dividing the total volume of saliva obtained by the 
length of time taken to collect it and expressing the result as mL/min. 
Saliva samples were divided into 100 μL aliquots and stored at −80°C 
until analyzed. </p>

<p>2.3. Immunoblot analysis </p>

<p>Salivary statherin levels were determined using a previously 
described method with some modification [6,30]. Saliva (PS and SS) 
samples were thawed and ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA) 
was added to a final concentration of 0.5 mM to minimize aggregate 
formation. Following a series of pilot experiments, the volume of saliva 
required to obtain an optimal statherin signal in the immunoblot analy-
sis was found to be 0.125 μL for both control and diabetic samples. Total 
protein content of the saliva was determined by measuring absorbance 
at 215 nm using a DU® spectrophotometer (Beckman Coulter, CA, USA) 
[26]. Bovine serum albumin was used as a standard. 
Saliva samples were separated on precast 4-20% SDS-PAGE gels 
(Mini-PROTEAN® TGX™, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Inc., CA, USA) and then 
transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride membranes (Millipore Corp, 
Bedford, MA). The membranes were immunoblotted with a primary 
antibody against human statherin (1:2000 dilution; STATH Polyclonal 
Antibody [catalog #19724-1-AP], Proteintech, IL, USA) at 4°C overnight, 
followed by incubation with horseradish peroxidase-labeled secondary 
antibody (1:10,000) (GE Healthcare Life Sciences, PA, USA). The 
statherin immunoreactive band was visualized using an ECL detection 
kit (ECL Advance™ Western Blotting Detection Kit, GE Healthcare, Buck-
inghamshire, UK) and band images were acquired and analyzed with an 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">AutoChemi</rs> system (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">UVP, Inc.</rs>., CA, USA). Gray-scale values for statherin-
positive bands were quantified using <rs type="software">Scion Image</rs> software (Scion Cor-
poration, MD, USA). </p>

<p>2.4. Quantification of statherin </p>

<p>To compensate for variations in immunoblotting, one PS sample was 
selected from the normal controls that produced an average level of 
band intensity after SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting. The integrated 
gray value of this standard (0.125 μL saliva) was assigned an arbitrary 
value of 100. Statherin levels in all samples were calculated relative to 
this PS standard and are reported as the percent (%) statherin level for 
a particular PS or SS sample. 
To normalize the data, the % statherin level (calculated above) was 
divided by the protein content in the saliva sample (% statherin level 
divided by μg protein/μL saliva). To obtain an estimate of the rate of 
statherin secretion in PS and SS, the % statherin level was multiplied 
by the measured salivary flow rate (mL/min). </p>

<p>2.5. Statistical analysis </p>

<p>A power analysis was performed using the statistical software, 
<rs id="software-4" type="software">G*Power</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">version 3.1.9.2</rs>) [8,9] to determine the appropriate number 
of subjects to include in the study. The Mann-Whitney U-test was 
used for comparing data from control and diabetic subjects. Spearman's 
rank correlation coefficient was used for the test of correlation between 
statherin level and HbA1c and blood glucose levels. These statistical 
analyses were carried out using PASW Statistics 17.0 software (SPSS, 
Inc., IL, USA). A p-value less than 0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>The demographics of the control and diabetic subjects are shown in 
Table 1. The average age of the subjects in both groups was nearly 
identical and the male/female ratio was identical in each. In diabetic 
subjects, median body mass index (BMI) and HbA1c level were statisti-
cally higher when compared with controls (p = 0.049 and p b 0.001, </p>

<p> 
M. Izumi et al. / BBA Clinical 3 (2015) 135-140 </p>

<p>respectively). Salivary flow rates of diabetic subjects were less than con-
trols for the SS (p = 0.021) with no apparent changes in the PS (p = 
0.428). Interestingly, the total protein concentration in SS was also 
significantly decreased (p b 0.001) in diabetics but was unchanged in 
PS (p = 0.404). 
Statherin was easily detected in minute amounts of saliva, using im-
munoblot analysis (Fig. 1A). The level of statherin in PS was significantly 
decreased in diabetics as compared with controls (~45% reduction; p = 
0.031; Fig. 1B); in contrast, the statherin level in SS from diabetics was 
also lower, but this difference was not statistically significant (p = 
0.109; Fig. 1B). Correlation analysis revealed a negative correlation 
between PS statherin levels and serum HbA1c (p = 0.012; Fig. 2A). 
Similarly, a correlation was also demonstrated between PS statherin 
levels and fasting glucose (p = 0.021; Fig. 2C). In contrast, there was 
no significant correlation between statherin levels and HbA1c or fasting 
glucose in SS (Fig. 2B and D). </p>

<p>When statherin levels were normalized to total protein in the saliva, 
the proportion of statherin in PS total protein was significantly lower in 
diabetics than in healthy controls (p = 0.032; Table 2). In contrast, 
the ratio of statherin to total protein in SS was not significantly different 
between diabetics and controls. On the other hand, the amount of 
statherin secretion per unit time in SS was significantly decreased in di-
abetics compared to controls (p = 0.016), but this difference was not 
observed for statherin secretion in PS (Table 2). 
We also evaluated the DMFT index for the control and diabetic 
subjects in this study. Both DMFT for the crown (DMFT-c) and root 
(DMFT-r) are higher in diabetic patients than controls (Fig. 3). The 
correlation studies showed that DMFT-r is negatively correlated 
with SS salivary flow rates (p = 0.026). No other correlation be-
tween DMFT-r, DMFT-c, and statherin levels was observed. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>We have previously shown that salivary flow rates and several anti-
microbial proteins are altered in non-insulin-dependent (type 2) diabet-
ic patients [6]. In the current study, we determined the level of salivary 
statherin in poorly controlled type 2 diabetic patients (based on HbA1c 
and fasting glucose values) compared to healthy age-and gender-
matched controls. The results show that statherin levels in diabetic pa-
tients are significantly decreased in PS and that a negative correlation 
exists between PS statherin levels and HbA1c and fasting glucose levels. 
We have also shown that SS salivary flow rates are reduced in diabetic 
patients and diabetic patients have higher DMFT scores. 
Patients with diabetes (both types 1 and 2) are known to have al-
tered salivary gland function such as decreased flow rates and altered 
composition [2,6,14,23,27]. In the present study, we observed that stim-
ulated SS flow rates were significantly decreased in diabetic subjects. 
We did not detect any significant decrease in stimulated PS flow rates 
in diabetes as indicated by some previously published studies [2]. The 
reason for these discrepancies in measures of salivary function with 
diabetes may be due to cohort effects, large individual variations, and 
sample sizes. To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first to </p>

<p>Table 1 
Demographics of the study subjects. </p>

<p>Control (n = 24) 
Diabetics (n = 24) 
p value </p>

<p>Age (years) 
67 (58.8-70.0) 
67.5 (58.3-70.8) 
-
Gender (male/female) 
11/13 
11/13 
-
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
26.5 (25.0-29.3) 
29 (26.3-35.8) 
0.049 
Fasting glucose (mg/dL) 
94.5 (89.0-98.3) 
199.5 (193.0-265.5) 
-
HbA1c (%) 
5.5 (5.1-5.9) 
9.0 (8.0-12.7) 
b0.001 
Salivary flow rate (mL/min) 
PS 
0.29 (0.11-0.43) 
0.31 (0.19-0.53) 
0.428 (NS) 
SS 
0.42 (0.30-0.51) 
0.24 (0.18-0.45) 
0.021 
Total protein (μg/μL) 
PS 
1.99 (1.51-2.98) 
1.88 (1.58-2.23) 
0.404 (NS) 
SS 
1.97 (1.60-2.56) 
1.52 (1.13-1.79) 
b0.001 </p>

<p>The data shown are the median value for each parameter; the 25th and 75th percentile 
values are shown in parentheses. 
Abbreviations: PS: stimulated parotid saliva, SS: stimulated submandibular/sublingual 
saliva. 
p value determined using the non-parametric Mann-Whitney U-test. 
-: not statistically evaluated for differences. 
NS: not significant. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Statherin levels in the saliva of patients with diabetes and healthy age-and gender-matched controls as measured by immunoblot analysis. Stimulated parotid saliva (PS) and sublingual/ 
submandibular saliva (SS) were collected as described in Materials and methods section and then subjected to 4-20% gradient SDS-PAGE, followed by Western blotting for statherin, and 
quantification using <rs type="software">Scion Image</rs> software. Panel A: a representative gel of salivary statherin in 0.125 μL saliva (PS and SS) collected from diabetic patients and controls. ST: prescreened PS sample 
used for quantitation (see Materials and methods section). Panel B: statherin levels in saliva were determined by converting the stained region of the immunoblot (for each sample) into a 
density value. The relative statherin level was expressed as the ratio of statherin band density for an individual subject to the standard PS sample run on each gel. The box plots show the 
1st and 3rd quartiles, median (horizontal line between the 1st and 3rd quartiles) and outliers (open circles) [more than 1.5× (3rd-1st quartiles)]. </p>

<p> 
M. Izumi et al. / BBA Clinical 3 (2015) 135-140 </p>

<p>document decreased statherin levels in glandular saliva of type 2 dia-
betics. Previously, a quantitative peptidomic study of whole saliva sug-
gested a decrease in salivary statherin levels of type 1 diabetic patients 
[1]. A lower immunoreactive statherin level in parotid, submandibular 
and labial glands from diabetic patients has also been reported using 
an immunogold transmission electron microscopy approach [11,12]. 
The effect of diabetes on statherin secretion appears to be more pro-
nounced on PS than SS as statistically significant differences were only 
observed in PS (see Table 2, % statherin levels and % statherin levels nor-
malized to protein). Since no differences in PS flow rate and total pro-
tein concentrations were found between healthy controls and 
diabetics (Table 1), statherin levels in PS appear to be directly influ-
enced by the hyperglycemia of diabetes mellitus. This conclusion is fur-
ther supported by our results showing a negative correlation between </p>

<p>PS statherin levels and HbA1c and fasting glucose levels (see Fig. 2). 
However, prior studies have reported that immunoreactive statherin 
is only present in serous acinar cells. The less pronounced effect of dia-
betes on statherin levels in SS may be due to differences in the acini of 
these two glands. In addition, in the present study, the effect of diabetes 
on statherin production by individual submandibular and sublingual 
glands could not be evaluated as we did not collect separate saliva sam-
ples from these two glands [28]. 
Our results further demonstrate that SS flow rate and total protein 
concentrations are significantly lower in diabetic patients. Prior studies 
have shown that statherin concentrations increase with salivary flow 
rates [16]. The decrease in median statherin levels in SS of diabetic pa-
tients, although not significant, may relate to the significantly reduced 
salivary flow rates found in diabetes (see Fig. 1). Currently, the cellular </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Correlation between salivary statherin levels and fasting blood glucose and HbA1c levels in patients with diabetes and healthy age-and gender-matched controls. Normalized 
statherin levels in stimulated parotid saliva (PS, panels A and C) and stimulated submandibular/sublingual saliva (SS, panels B and D) were plotted against HbA1c (panels A and B) or 
fasting blood glucose (panels C and D) levels. A significant negative correlation was found between PS statherin and HbA1c (panel A) and fasting blood glucose (panel C). </p>

<p>Table 2 
Salivary statherin in diabetic and control subjects. </p>

<p>Statherin level 
(% statherin) </p>

<p>Statherin level normalized to protein 
(% statherin / μg protein/μL saliva) </p>

<p>Total statherin secretion 
(% statherin / μg protein/μL saliva) × (mL/min) </p>

<p>PS 
Control subjects 
97.0 
(59.5-127.0) </p>

<p>43.19 
(29.67-63.12) </p>

<p>22.97 
(15.38-33.28) 
Diabetic subjects 
53.0⁎ 
(26.5-119.0) </p>

<p>26.26⁎ 
(13.51-53.17) </p>

<p>15.37 
(6.93-27.50) 
SS 
Control subjects 
25.5 
(13.8-57.5) </p>

<p>14.06 
(6.34-25.46) </p>

<p>11.41 
(5.21-21.88) 
Diabetic subjects 
13.0 
(4.0-44.0) </p>

<p>8.55 
(4.00-31.66) </p>

<p>3.38⁎ 
(1.25-12.69) </p>

<p>The data shown are the median value for each parameter; the 25th and 75th percentile values are shown in parentheses. 
The % statherin level in a 0.125 μL aliquot of saliva was calculated in relation to the amount measured in a pre-screened PS sample of equal volume as described in Materials and methods 
section. These data were then normalized to the total protein content in a μL saliva (=% statherin level/total protein). Total statherin secretion was calculated by multiplying the % statherin 
level/total protein in a μL saliva by salivary flow rate (mL/min). 
Abbreviations: PS: stimulated parotid saliva, SS: stimulated submandibular/sublingual saliva. 
⁎ p b 0.05 vs. control subjects. </p>

<p> 
M. Izumi et al. / BBA Clinical 3 (2015) 135-140 </p>

<p>and molecular mechanisms, responsible for inducing salivary gland dys-
function in diabetes, are unclear. Morphological, immunolabeling and 
functional studies of salivary glands, using experimental animal models 
and clinical samples, indicate that diabetes leads to changes in the auto-
nomic nervous system [22,31], lower expression of cyclic AMP receptors 
and secretory proteins (e.g., amylase, proline-rich proteins, and mucins) 
[21,24], and structural changes in cellular organelles (e.g., increased 
acinar and secretory granule area, reduced mitochrondria size, and 
increased membrane folding) [19,31] as compared to normal salivary 
gland cells. Whether these alterations contribute to, or are associated 
with, differences in salivary statherin levels between diabetes and 
healthy controls require further study. Nevertheless, statherin, an abun-
dant salivary protein as our results demonstrate, can serve as a marker 
for studying the effect of diabetes on salivary function. 
Statherin is a major salivary protein with multiple physiological 
functions. Reduced statherin levels in PS and total statherin secretion 
in SS can put diabetic patients at risk for a number of oral diseases. 
Indeed, statherin levels have been associated with elevated decayed, 
missing, and filled teeth/surfaces (DMFT/DMFS) indices [29]. While a di-
rect correlation between statherin levels and DMFTs were not found in 
the current study, the DMFT index for crown and roots were both higher 
in diabetic patients compared to the healthy non-diabetic controls and 
confirmed previous studies demonstrating an association between dia-
betes and DMFT [15,17]. Thus far, the association of dental caries and di-
abetes has not been well documented [17]. In contrast, diabetic patients 
are known to be at a higher risk for more severe periodontal diseases 
[17]. The lower salivary flow rates and periodontal diseases among dia-
betic patients may partially explain the higher DMFT-c and DMFT-r in 
diabetic patients [10,17]. In our cohort, the differences in DMFTs may 
derive from missing teeth since the diabetic group has significantly 
more missing teeth (data not shown). Whether the missing teeth are 
due to periodontal disease or caries is currently unclear. Regardless, 
the lower statherin concentration and secretions in this study suggest 
a potential major risk for oral diseases in diabetic patients. 
In prior studies, salivary statherin levels have been quantified with 
chromatography, ELISA and immunodiffusion assays using investigator 
prepared statherin or its antibodies [4,16,18]. In this study, we devel-
oped a highly sensitive method for specifically quantifying statherin in </p>

<p>saliva using gel electrophoresis and immunoblotting with commercially 
available antibodies. The immunoblot analysis allowed the relative 
quantification of statherin with b0.5 μg total salivary protein 
(~0.125 μL saliva). The primary antibody used in this study does 
not cross-react with rodent saliva or salivary gland tissue as predict-
ed by phylogenetic studies [5]. The commercially available antibod-
ies open the way for developing highly sensitive antibody-based 
assays for measuring statherin and exploring the role of statherin 
in the pathogenesis of oral diseases. 
In conclusion, we have shown that statherin levels in PS and the 
statherin secretion rate in SS are decreased in poorly controlled diabetic 
patients compared to non-diabetic controls. In addition, statherin levels 
in PS were negatively correlated with blood glucose and HbA1c levels. 
We have further demonstrated that diabetic patients have a higher 
DMFT index and lower salivary flow rates. Alterations in statherin 
level and secretion, in combination with compromised salivary flow 
rates, may account for the higher incidence of oral complications in di-
abetic patients. Oral diseases, especially periodontal diseases have 
been linked to diabetic control, further emphasizing that oral health 
maintenance should be an integral part of diabetic management [17]. </p>

<p>Transparency document </p>

<p>The Transparency document associated with this article can be found, 
in the online version. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>NIH (DE021084 [CKY]; DE10756 [MJS]) and VA Merit Review 
1I01BX001103 [CKY] partially support this work. 
The authors confirm they have no conflicts. </p>



<p> 
M. Izumi et al. / BBA Clinical 3 (2015) 135-140 </p>



<p> 
M. Izumi et al. / BBA Clinical 3 (2015) 135-140 </p>

</text></tei>