<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4634381" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Stargardt disease (STGD1) due to mutations in the large ABCA4 gene is the most common inherited macular degeneration in humans. 
We have shown that dual adeno-associated viral (AAV) vectors effectively transfer ABCA4 to the retina of Abca4−/− mice. However, 
they express both lower levels of transgene compared with a single AAV and truncated proteins. To increase productive dual AAV 
concatemerization, which would overcome these limitations, we have explored the use of either various regions of homology or 
heterologous inverted terminal repeats (ITR). In addition, we tested the ability of various degradation signals to decrease the 
expression of truncated proteins. We found the highest levels of transgene expression using regions of homology based on either 
alkaline phosphatase or the F1 phage (AK). The use of heterologous ITR does not decrease the levels of truncated proteins relative to 
full-length ABCA4 and impairs AAV vector production. Conversely, the inclusion of the CL1 degradation signal results in the selective 
degradation of truncated proteins from the 5′-half without affecting full-length protein production. Therefore, we developed dual AAV 
hybrid ABCA4 vectors including homologous ITR2, the photoreceptor-specific G protein-coupled receptor kinase 1 promoter, the AK 
region of homology and the CL1 degradation signal. We show that upon subretinal administration these vectors are both safe in pigs 
and effective in Abca4−/− mice. Our data support the use of improved dual AAV vectors for gene therapy of STGD1. </p>

<p>Stargardt disease (STGD1; MIM#248200), the most common form 
of inherited macular degeneration in humans, is caused by 
mutations in ABCA4 [coding sequence (CDS): 6822 bp], which </p>

<p>encodes the photoreceptor (PR)-specific all-trans-retinal trans-
porter (1,2). In the absence of a functional ABCA4 protein, vita-
min A aldehyde forms bisretinoid adducts that are deposited 
in retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cells during the process of </p>

<p>Received: July 14, 2015. Revised and Accepted: September 14, 2015 </p>

<p>© The Author 2015. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. 
For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2015, Vol. 24, No. 23 
6811-6825 </p>

<p>doi: 10.1093/hmg/ddv386 
Advance Access Publication Date: 29 September 2015 
Original Article </p>



<p>disc shedding and phagocytosis. Consequently, abnormally 
high levels of lipofuscin pigments, such as A2E and all-trans-
retinal dimer-phosphatidylethanolamine, accumulate in the 
RPE, triggering RPE-cell death and causing secondary PR degener-
ation (2). Abca4−/− mice (3), the only STGD1 animal model, recap-
itulate some of the features of the human retinal disease 
including abnormal lipofuscin accumulation in the RPE. 
Sight-restoring therapy for many inherited retinal degenera-
tions (IRDs) including STGD1, is still a major unmet medical 
need. Gene therapy with adeno-associated viral (AAV) vectors re-
presents, to date, the most promising approach for treatment of 
many IRDs (4-9). However, one of the main obstacles for the use 
of AAV is their packaging capacity limited to ∼5 kb. This has be-
come a limiting factor for the development of gene replacement 
therapy for common IRDs due to mutations in genes with a CDS 
larger than 5 kb, which include, among others, STGD1. Dual AAV 
vectors, based on the ability of AAV genomes to concatamerize 
via intermolecular recombination, have been successfully 
exploited to overcome this limitation (10-12). Others and we 
have recently shown the potential of dual AAV vectors in the 
retina (10,13-15). In particular we have reported that dual AAV 
hybrid AK vectors which rely on both ITR-mediated concatemer-
ization and homologous recombination mediated by the AK se-
quence of the F1 phage for the reconstitution of the full-length 
expression cassette, transduce efficiently mouse and pig PR and 
rescue the Abca4−/− mouse retinal phenotype (10,15). However, 
critical issues need to be addressed before considering further 
clinical translation of this strategy. First, the levels of PR trans-
duction achieved with dual AAV vectors are lower than those 
achieved with single normal size AAV vectors (10,15). A second 
major issue associated with the use of dual AAV vectors is the 
production of truncated proteins from the 5′-half vector that con-
tains the promoter sequence and/or from the 3′-half vector due to 
the low promoter activity of the inverted terminal repeats (ITR) 
(10,13,16,17). Both increased transduction efficiency and reduc-
tion of truncated protein production may be achieved by boosting 
the directional formation of productive tail-to-head concate-
mers, which reduces the number of non-concatemerized single 
AAV vector halves from which the truncated protein products de-
rive. Since directional reconstitution of dual AAV hybrid vectors 
relies on recombination mediated by regions of homology in-
cluded in the two vectors, we sought to evaluate side-by-side 
the various recombinogenic regions used in the context of dual 
AAV hybrid vectors which include those derived from either the 
human placental alkaline phosphatase cDNA (12,18) or the AK 
sequence from the F1 phage (10). 
Another option we have explored to increase the generation of 
productive tail-to-head AAV genome concatemers is the use of 
vectors with heterologous ITR (i.e. vectors with ITR from different 
AAV serotypes at the opposite ends of the viral genome). Indeed, 
vectors with heterologous ITR from serotypes 2 and 5 (ITR2 and 
ITR5, respectively), which are highly divergent [58% of homology 
(19)], show both reduced ability to form circular monomers 
and increased directional tail-to-head concatamerization than 
vectors with homologous ITR (20), and reconstitute transgene ex-
pression more efficiently than dual AAV vectors with homolo-
gous ITR (20,21). 
Although highly recombinogenic sequences and/or heterol-
ogous ITR can be explored to achieve higher rates of productive 
dual AAV concatemer formation, the production of truncated 
protein products might still remain an issue. MicroRNA (miR) tar-
get sequences, artificial stop codons or protein ubiquitination 
signals can be exploited to mediate the degradation of truncated 
protein products. Among the miR expressed in the retina, miR-</p>

<p>let7b or -26a are expressed at high levels (22-25) while miR-124 
and -204 have been shown to restrict AAV-mediated transgene 
expression to either RPE or PR, respectively (26). Signals that me-
diate the degradation of proteins include: (i) the short degron CL1, 
a C-terminal destabilizing peptide that shares structural similar-
ities with misfolded proteins and is thus recognized by the ubi-
quitination system (27-29), (ii) ubiquitin, whose fusion at the N-
terminal of a donor protein mediates both direct protein degrad-
ation or degradation via the N-end rule pathway (30,31) and (iii) 
the N-terminal PB29 degron which is a 9 aminoacid-long peptide 
which, similarly to the CL1 degron, is predicted to fold in struc-
tures that are recognized by enzymes of the ubiquitination path-
way (32). Additionally, artificial stop codons can be inserted to 
cause the early termination of an mRNA. We evaluated the ability 
of these strategies to silence the expression of truncated proteins 
from dual AAV vectors. Finally, in view of a possible clinical trans-
lation of dual AAV vectors for retinal gene therapy, we evaluated 
the efficacy and the safety of dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors in-
cluding these optimized features in Abca4−/− mice and in wild-
type mice and pigs, respectively. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors which include the AK 
or AP1 recombinogenic regions show efficient mouse 
photoreceptor transduction </p>

<p>We evaluated in parallel the transduction efficacy of dual AAV 
hybrid ABCA4 vectors with different regions of homology. The 
most used derive from either the head or tail (18) of the middle 
one-third of the human placental alkaline phosphatase cDNA 
(12). We have previously shown that dual AAV hybrid vectors in-
cluding the AK sequence from the F1 phage outperform those in-
cluding the sense placental alkaline phosphatase head region 
sequence [AP (10), Supplementary Material, Fig. S1], which we 
generated based on the description provided in Ghosh et al. (18). 
Recently, the exact sequence of the head and tail placental alka-
line phosphatase sequences (AP1 and AP2) have been published 
by Lostal et al. (16). These correspond to the reverse complemen-
tary (antisense) sequences in the middle one-third of the AP 
cDNA (Supplementary Material, Fig. S1). Thus, we compared 
the efficacy of these AP1 and AP2 sequences to that of both the 
AK sequence and of the AP sequence we have previously tested 
in Trapani et al. (10). For this purpose we generated dual AAV2/2 
hybrid vectors that include the ABCA4-3×flag CDS, under the con-
trol of the ubiquitous CMV promoter, and either the AK (10), AP 
(10), AP1 or AP2 (16) regions of homology (Fig. 1 and Supplemen-
tary Material, Fig. S1). We used these vectors to infect HEK293 
cells [multiplicity of infection, m.o.i.: 5 × 10 
4 genome copies </p>

<p>(GC)/cell of each vector]. Cell lysates were analysed by Western 
blot with anti-3×flag antibodies to detect ABCA4-3×flag 
(Fig. 2A). Each of the dual AAV hybrid vectors sets resulted in ex-
pression of full-length proteins of the expected size that were not 
detected in the lanes loaded with negative controls (Fig. 2A). 
Quantification of ABCA4 expression (Fig. 2B) showed that infec-
tion with dual AAV hybrid AP1 and AP2 vectors resulted in slight-
ly higher levels of transgene expression than with dual AAV 
hybrid AK vectors and all significantly outperformed dual AAV 
hybrid AP vectors. We have previously found that the efficiency 
of dual AAV vectors which rely on homologous recombination 
is lower in terminally-differentiated cells as PR than in cell cul-
ture (10). We therefore evaluated PR-specific transduction levels 
in C57BL/6 mice following subretinal administration of dual 
AAV2/8 AK, AP1 and AP2 vectors which include the PR-specific </p>



<p>human G protein-coupled receptor kinase 1 (GRK1) promoter 
(dose of each vector/eye: 1.9 × 10 
9 GC; Fig. 2C). One month after </p>

<p>vector administration we detected efficient ABCA4 protein ex-
pression more frequently in retinas treated with dual AAV hybrid 
AK than AP1 or AP2 vectors (Fig. 2C). However, the average ABCA4 
expression levels from all treated eyes were not significantly </p>

<p>different between eyes injected with dual AAV hybrid AK, AP1 
and AP2 vectors [mean ABCA4 levels: AK: 3.7 ± 0.9 arbitrary 
units (a.u.); AP1: 3.7 ± 0.9 a.u.; AP2: 2.5 ± 0.5 a.u. No significant dif-
ferences were found using one-way ANOVA. More details on the 
quantification and specific statistical values can be found in the 
Material and Methods section]. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Schematic representation of the dual AAV vectors tested. ITR: inverted terminal repeats from AAV2 or AAV5; Prom: promoter; CDS: coding sequence; SD: splicing 
donor signal; HR: homology region, AK or from human placental alkaline phosphatase (AP1, AP2 and AP); Deg Sig: degradation signal (see Table 2); SA: splicing acceptor </p>

<p>signal; pA: polyadenylation signal. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Efficient ABCA4 protein expression using the AK, AP1 and AP2 regions of homology. Representative Western blot analysis of (A) HEK293 cells (50 micrograms/ 
lane) infected with dual AAV2/2 hybrid CMV-ABCA4 vectors or (C) C57BL/6 retinas (whole retinal lysates) 1-month post-injection with dual AAV2/8 hybrid GRK1-ABCA4 </p>

<p>vectors (dose of each vector/eye: 1.9 × 10 
9 GC). The upper arrow indicates full-length proteins, the lower arrow indicates truncated proteins from the 3′-half vector. Since no </p>

<p>truncated proteins can be detected in the mouse retina (10), the lower arrow in (C) points to the level of truncated proteins present in a lysate of infected cells which has </p>

<p>been loaded on the same gel as positive control. The molecular weight ladder is depicted on the left. (B) Quantification of ABCA4 protein bands from Western blot analysis 
in (A). The intensity of the ABCA4 bands in (A) was divided by the intensity of the Filamin A bands. The histograms show the expression of proteins as a percentage relative </p>

<p>to dual AAV hybrid AK vectors, the mean value is depicted above the corresponding bar. Values are represented as: mean ± s.e.m. *pANOVA ≤ 0.05, the asterisk indicates </p>

<p>significant differences with AK. **pANOVA &lt; 0.001, the asterisks indicate significant differences with AK, AP1 and AP2. More details on the statistical analysis including </p>

<p>specific statistical values can be found in the Statistical analysis paragraph of the Materials and Methods section. The Western blot images are representative of: (A) n = 3 
independent experiments; (B) n = 8 eyes injected with dual AAV hybrid AK, n = 8 eyes injected with dual AAV hybrid AP1, n = 8 eyes injected with dual AAV hybrid AP2, n = 8 </p>

<p>eyes injected with negative control vectors. The quantifications (B) are from n = 3 independent experiments. (A-C) AK: cells infected or eyes injected with dual AAV hybrid </p>

<p>AK vectors; AP1: cells infected or eyes injected with dual AAV hybrid AP1 vectors; AP2: cells infected or eyes injected with dual AAV hybrid AP2 vectors; AP: cells infected </p>

<p>with dual AAV hybrid AP vectors; neg: negative controls, in (A) cells infected with either the 3′-half vectors (3′) or EGFP-expressing vectors (EGFP), in (B) eyes injected with 
the 3′-half vectors; α-3×flag: Western blot with anti-3×flag antibodies; α-Filamin A, Western blot with anti-Filamin A antibodies, used as loading control; α-Dysferlin, </p>

<p>Western blot with anti-Dysferlin antibodies, used as loading control. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2015, Vol. 24, No. 23 | 6813 </p>

<p>Inclusion of heterologous ITR in dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 
vectors affects their production yields and does not 
reduce levels of truncated proteins </p>

<p>To test if the use of heterologous ITR improves the productive dir-
ectional concatemerization of dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors, 
we generated dual AAV2/2 hybrid ABCA4 vectors that included 
the ABCA4-3×flag CDS with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 in either 
the 5:2 (left ITR from AAV5 and right ITR from AAV2) or the 2:5 (left 
ITR from AAV2 and right ITR from AAV5) configuration. The pro-
duction of dual AAV vectors bearing heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 
requires the simultaneous expression of the Rep proteins from 
AAV serotypes 2 and 5 which cannot cross-complement virus 
replication (19). Indeed, it has been shown that Rep2 and Rep5 
can bind interchangeably to ITR2 or ITR5, although less efficient-
ly than to homologous ITR, however they cannot cleave the ter-
minal resolution sites of the ITR from the other serotype (33). 
Therefore, before generating dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors 
with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5, we assessed the potential com-
petition of (i) Rep5 with Rep2 in the production of AAV2/2-CMV-
EGFP vectors (i.e. vectors with homologous ITR2) and (ii) Rep2 
with Rep5 in the production of AAV5/2-CMV-EGFP vectors (i.e. 
vectors with homologous ITR5), using the same amount of the 
Rep5Cap2 and Rep2Cap2 packaging constructs (ratio1:1). Indeed, 
when the Rep5Cap2 packaging construct is provided in addition 
to Rep2Cap2, the total yields of AAV2/2-CMV-EGFP vectors are re-
duced to 42% of those of control preparations obtained when only 
Rep2Cap2 is provided as packaging construct (average of four 
independent preps of each type, p Student's t-test: 0.014). Con-
versely, no significant differences were found in the total yields 
of AAV5/2-CMV-EGFP preps obtained when Rep2Cap2 was 
added to Rep5Cap2, which were 83% of those obtained when 
Rep5Cap2 was the only packaging construct transfected (average 
of four independent preps of each type, no significant differences 
were found using Student's t-test). Given the competition of Rep5 
with Rep2 in the production of vectors with ITR2, we tested three 
different ratios between Rep5 and the Rep2Cap2 packaging </p>

<p>constructs in the production of dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors 
with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 (Protocol A with 1:1, Protocol B 
with 1:3 and Protocol C with 1:10 Rep5:Rep2Cap2 ratio). As 
shown in Supplementary Material, Table S1, viral titres deter-
mined by PCR quantification using a probe annealing to ITR2 pro-
gressively increased when the amount of Rep5 was decreased, 
with the best titre obtained with Protocol C. These results con-
firmed the competition of Rep5 with Rep2 during the production 
of vectors with ITR2 and led us to follow Protocol C for the produc-
tion of AAV vectors with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5. However, 
several AAV preparations obtained with this strategy revealed: 
(i) up to 6-fold lower titres determined on ITR2 than titres deter-
mined on a transgenic sequence in between the ITR (Table 1) 
which could suggest that the integrity of ITR2 is compromised 
and (ii) a mean reduction of about 6-fold in the total yields of 
AAV vectors with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 compared with 
those containing homologous ITR2 ( p Student's t-test: 0.04; </p>

<p>Table 1. Low yields and differences between ITR2 and transgene titres 
of AAV2 with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 </p>

<p>ID 
ITR 
configuration </p>

<p>ITR2 titre 
(GC/ml) </p>

<p>Transgene 
titre (GC/ml) </p>

<p>Yields 
(GC/ml×3.5 ml) </p>

<p>2101 
5:2 
2.0E+12 
2.5E+12 
7.9E+12 
2136 
5:2 
2.4E+11 
6.0E+11 
1.5E+12 
2137 
5:2 
4.4E+11 
2.5E+12 
5.1E+12 
2140 
5:2 
5.2E+10 
1.5E+11 
3.5E+11 
2102 
2:5 
4.6E+11 
1.2E+12 
2.9E+12 
2135 
2:5 
1.5E+12 
2.5E+12 
7.0E+12 
2138 
2:5 
6.8E+11 
1.2E+12 
3.3E+12 
2139 
2:5 
4.8E+11 
2.5E+12 
5.2E+12 
AAV2/2 
(n = 8) </p>

<p>2:2 
(8.5 ± 3.7) 
E+12 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(5.9 ± 2) 
E+12 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(2.5 ± 0.9)E+13 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>ID: identification number of AAV vectors; GC: genome copies. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Values represent mean ± s.e.m. </p>

<p>Table 2. Degradation signals tested in this study </p>

<p>Degradation signal 
Nucleotide sequence 
Size (bp) 
References </p>

<p>5′-half vectors 
CL1 
gcctgcaagaactggttcagcagcctgagccacttcgtgatccacctg 
48 
(27-29) 
3×204 + 3×124 
aggcataggatgacaaagggaacgataggcataggatgacaaagggaa 
aagcttaggcataggatgacaaagggaaggtaccagatct 
ggcattcaccgcgtgccttacgat 
ggcattcaccgcgtgccttaaagcttggcattcaccgcgtgcctta </p>

<p>158 
(22) </p>

<p>4×let7b 
aaccacacaacctactacctcacgataaccacacaacctactacctca 
aagcttaaccacacaacctactacctcatcacaaccacacaacctactacctca </p>

<p>102 
(22-24) </p>

<p>4×26a 
agcctatcctggattacttgaacgat 
agcctatcctggattacttgaaaagcttagcctatcctggattacttgaatcac 
agcctatcctggattacttgaa </p>

<p>102 
(24,25) </p>

<p>3′-half vectors 
3×STOP 
Tga-a-tga-a-tga 
11 
PB29 
atgcacagctggaacttcaagctgtacgtcatgggcagcggc 
42 
(32) 
3×PB29 
atgcacagctggaacttcaagctgtacgtcatgggcagcggcggggtaccatgcac 
agctggaacttcaagctgtacgtcatgggcagcggcggatgcac 
agctggaacttcaagctgtacgtcatgggcagcggc </p>

<p>136 </p>

<p>ubiquitin 
atgcagatcttcgtgaagactctgactggtaagaccatcaccctcgaggtggag 
cccagtgacaccatcgagaatgtcaaggcaaagatccaagataa 
ggaaggcattcctcctgatcagcagaggttgatctttgccggaaaacagc 
tggaagatggtcgtaccctgtctgactacaacatccagaaagagtccaccttgc 
acctggtactccgtctcagaggtggg </p>

<p>228 
(30,31) </p>

<p>The sequences underlined correspond to the degradation signals while those not underlined have been included for cloning purposes. </p>



<p>Table 1). However, Southern blot analysis of AAV preparations 
with heterologous ITR revealed no evident alterations of genome 
integrity (Fig. 3A). To test if the inclusion of heterologous ITR in 
dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors enhanced the formation of tail-
to-head productive concatemers and full-length protein trans-
duction while reducing the production of truncated proteins, 
we infected HEK293 cells with dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors 
with either heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 (in the 5:2/2:5 configur-
ation) or homologous ITR2 (Fig. 3B). Given the difference between 
the ITR2 and transgene titres for vectors with heterologous but 
not homologous ITR (Table 1), we infected cells with 10 
4 GC/cell </p>

<p>of each vector based on either ITR2 or transgene titres. Western 
blot analysis of HEK293 cells infected with dual AAV vectors 
based on ITR2 titres showed that the inclusion of heterologous 
ITR2 and ITR5 resulted in higher levels of both full-length and 
truncated protein than the inclusion of homologous ITR2 
(Fig. 3B and C). However this was not observed when HEK293 
cells were infected with the same dual AAV vector preps based 
on the transgene titre (Fig. 3B and D). In conclusion, the ratio </p>

<p>between full-length and truncated protein expression was simi-
lar regardless of the ITR included in the vectors and of the vector 
titre used to dose cells (Fig. 3C and D). </p>

<p>Inclusion of the CL1 degron in the 5′-half vector decreases 
the production of truncated proteins </p>

<p>To selectively reduce the levels of truncated ABCA4 proteins pro-
duced by each 5′-and 3′-half of dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors 
(10), we placed putative degradation sequences in the 5′-half vec-
tor after the splicing donor signal between AK and the right ITR, 
and in the 3′-half vector between AK and the splicing acceptor 
signal (Fig. 1). Thus, the degradation signal will be included in 
the truncated but not in the full-length protein which results 
from a spliced mRNA. As degradation signals in the 5′-half vec-
tors we have included: (i) the CL1 degron (CL1), (ii) four copies 
of the miR-let7b target site (4×let7b), (iii) four copies of the miR-
26a target site (4×26a) or (iv) the combination of three copies 
each of miR-204 and miR-124 target sites (3×204 + 3×124) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Genome and transduction efficiency of vectors with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5. (A) Alkaline Southern blot analysis of DNA extracted from 3 × 10 
10 GC of both </p>

<p>5′-and 3′-ABCA4-half vectors with either homologous (2:2) or heterologous (5:2 or 2:5) ITR, and of a control AAV preparation with homologous ITR2 (CTRL). The expected </p>

<p>size of each genome is depicted below each lane. The molecular weight marker (kb) is depicted on the left 5′: 5′-half vector; 3′: 3′-half vector. (B-D) Representative Western 
blot analysis and quantification of HEK293 cells infected with dual AAV2/2 hybrid ABCA4 vectors with either heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 or homologous ITR2 at m.o.i. </p>

<p>based on either the ITR2 (B and C) or the transgene (B and D) titre. The Western blot images (B) are representative of n = 3 independent experiments; the </p>

<p>quantifications (C and D) are from n = 3 independent experiments. (B) The upper arrow indicates full-length ABCA4 protein, the lower arrow indicates truncated </p>

<p>proteins; the molecular weight ladder is depicted on the left. The micrograms of proteins loaded are depicted below the image. α-3×flag: Western blot with anti-3×flag 
antibodies; α-Filamin A: Western blot with anti-Filamin A antibodies, used as loading control. (C and D) Quantification of full-length and truncated ABCA4 protein </p>

<p>bands from Western blot analysis of cells infected with a dose of vector based on either the ITR2 (C) or the transgene (D) titre. The histograms show either the </p>

<p>intensity of the full-length and truncated protein bands divided by that of the Filamin A bands or the intensity of the full-length protein bands divided by that of the </p>

<p>truncated protein bands in the corresponding lane. The mean value is depicted above the corresponding bar. Values are represented as: mean ± s.e.m. *p Student's t-
test ≤ 0.05. More details on the statistical analysis including specific statistical values can be found in the Statistical analysis paragraph of the Materials and Methods </p>

<p>section. 2:2 2:2: cells infected with dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors with homologous ITR from AAV2; 5:2 2:5: cells infected with dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors with </p>

<p>heterologous ITR from AAV2 and AAV5; neg: cells infected with EGFP-expressing vectors, as negative controls. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2015, Vol. 24, No. 23 | 6815 </p>

<p>As degradation signals in the 3′-half vectors we have included: (i) 
three stop codons (STOP), (ii) PB29 either in a single (PB29) or in 
three tandem copies (3×PB29) or (iii) ubiquitin (Table 2). We gen-
erated dual AAV2/2 hybrid ABCA4 vectors including the various 
degradation signals and evaluated their efficacy after infection 
of HEK293 cells [m.o.i.: 5 × 10 
4 GC/cell of each vector]. Since </p>

<p>miR-let7b, miR-26a, miR-204 and miR-124 are poorly expressed 
or completely absent in HEK293 cells [Ambion miRNA Research 
Guide and (34)], to test silencing of the constructs which contain 
their corresponding target sites, we transfected cells with miR 
mimics [i.e. small, chemically modified double-stranded RNAs 
that mimic endogenous miR (35)], prior to infection with the 
AAV2/2 vectors containing the corresponding target sites. To de-
fine the concentration of miR mimics required to achieve silen-
cing of a gene containing the corresponding miR target sites, </p>

<p>we used a plasmid encoding for the reporter EGFP protein and 
containing the miR target sites before the polyadenylation signal 
(data not shown). The same experimental settings were used for 
further evaluation of the miR target sites in the context of dual 
AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors. We found that inclusion of miR-
204 + 124 and 26a target sequences in the 5′-half of dual AAV hy-
brid ABCA4 vectors reduced albeit did not abolish the expression 
of the truncated protein products (Fig. 4A and Supplementary 
Material, Table S2). 
Notably, as shown in Figure 4B, we found that the inclusion of 
the CL1 degradation signal in the 5′-half vector reduced truncated 
protein expression to undetectable levels. Since differences in 
the tissue-specific expression of enzymes of the ubiquitination 
pathway that mediate CL1 degradation (27) may account for 
changes in CL1 efficacy, we further evaluated the efficacy of the </p>

<p>Figure 4. Inclusion of the CL1 degradation signal but not of miR target sites in the 5′-half vectors results in significant reduction of truncated proteins. (A) Representative </p>

<p>Western blot analysis of HEK293 cells infected with dual AAV2/2 hybrid vectors encoding for ABCA4, containing miR target sites for either miR-let7b (4×, left panel), miR-</p>

<p>204 + 124 (3×, central panel) or miR-26a (4×, right panel). 5′ + 3′: cells co-infected with 5′-half vectors without miR target sites and 3′-half vectors; 5′mir + 3′: cells co-infected </p>

<p>with 5′-half vectors containing miR target sites and 3′-half vectors; neg: control cells infected with the 3′-half vectors; +scramble: cells infected in the presence of scramble 
miR mimics; +mimic let7b: cells infected in the presence of miR-let7b mimics; +mimic 204+124: cells infected in the presence of miR-204 and -124 mimics; +mimic 26a: </p>

<p>cells infected in the presence of miR-26a mimics. (B and C) Representative Western blot analysis of either HEK293 cells infected with dual AAV2/2 hybrid vectors (B) or pig </p>

<p>eyes (c; RPE+retina) 1-month post-injection of dual AAV2/8 hybrid vectors encoding for ABCA4 and containing or not the CL1 degradation signal. 5′ + 3′: cells co-infected or </p>

<p>eyes co-injected with 5′-half vectors without CL1 and 3′-half vectors; 5′-CL1 + 3′: cells co-infected or eyes co-injected with 5′-half vectors containing CL1 and 3′-half 
vectors; 5′: cells infected with 5′-half vectors without CL1; 5′-CL1: cells infected with 5′-half vectors containing CL1; neg: control cells infected or control eyes injected </p>

<p>with either the 3′-half vectors or EGFP-expressing vectors, as negative controls. (A-C) The upper arrows indicate full-length ABCA4 proteins, the lower arrows indicate </p>

<p>truncated proteins; the molecular weight ladder is depicted on the left. The micrograms of proteins loaded are depicted below the image. α-3×flag: Western blot with </p>

<p>anti-3×flag antibodies; α-Filamin A: Western blot with anti-Filamin A antibodies, used as loading control; α-Dysferlin: Western blot with anti-Dysferlin antibodies, 
used as loading control. (A and B) The Western blot images are representative of n = 3 independent experiments. (C) The Western blot image is representative of n = 5 </p>

<p>eyes injected with 5′ + 3′ vectors, n = 2 eyes injected with 5′-CL1 + 3′ vectors and n = 5 of eyes injected with either the 3′-half vectors or EGFP-expressing vectors as </p>

<p>negative controls. </p>



<p>CL1 degron in the pig retina, which has a size and structure simi-
lar to human (15,26,36,37) and is therefore an excellent pre-clin-
ical large animal model to evaluate vector safety and efficiency. 
To this aim, we injected subretinally in Large White pigs AAV2/ 
8 dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors (of which the 5′-half vector in-
cluded or not the CL1 sequence, dose of each vector/eye: 1 × 10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>GC). Notably, we found that the inclusion of the CL1 degradation 
signal in the 5′-half vector resulted in reduction of truncated pro-
tein expression to levels that are below the detection limit of the 
Western blot analysis (Fig. 4C). Among the degradation signals 
tested in the 3′-half vector we identified three (PB29, 3×PB29 
and ubiquitin) that reduced both the levels of truncated protein 
products and of full-length proteins (Supplementary Material, 
Fig. S2 and Table S3). </p>

<p>Subretinal administration of improved dual AAV vectors 
reduces lipofuscin accumulation in the Abca4−/− retina </p>

<p>Based on our findings, improved dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors 
should include homologous ITR2, the AK region of homology and 
CL1. As ABCA4 is expressed in both rod and cone photoreceptors 
in humans (38), we identified a suitable promoter for ABCA4 
delivery by comparing the PR transduction properties of single 
AAV2/8 vectors encoding EGFP from either the human GRK1 or 
IRBP (interphotoreceptor retinoid binding protein) promoters, 
which have been both described to drive high levels of combined 
rod and cone PR transduction in various species (39-41). Taking 
advantage of the pig retinal architecture which includes a 
streak-like region with a cone:rod = 1:3 (42) similar to the 
human macula, we injected subretinally 1 × 10 
11 GC/eye of either </p>

<p>AAV2/8-GRK1-or IRBP-EGFP vectors in 3 month-old Large White 
pigs. Four weeks after the injection, we analysed the correspond-
ing retinal cryosections under a fluorescence microscope. EGFP 
fluorescence quantification in the PR cell layer (Supplementary 
Material, Fig. S3a and b) showed that both promoters give com-
parable levels of PR transduction ( predominantly rods in this re-
gion). However, when we counted the number of cones labelled 
with an antibody raised against cone arrestin (CAR) (43) that 
were also EGFP-positive, we found higher although not statistic-
ally significant levels of cone PR transduction with the GRK1 pro-
moter (Supplementary Material, Fig. S3C and D). Based on this, 
we included the GRK1 promoter in our improved dual AAV hybrid 
ABCA4 vectors, and investigated their ability to both express 
ABCA4 and decrease the abnormal content of autofluorescent li-
pofuscin material in the RPE of Abca4−/− mice. We initially in-
jected subretinally 1 month-old C57/BL6 mice with improved 
dual AAV vectors (dose of each vector/eye: 2 × 10 
9 GC) and </p>

<p>found that 12 out of 24 (50%) injected eyes had detectable albeit 
variable levels of full-length ABCA4 protein by Western blot [Fig-
ure 5A; ABCA4 protein levels in the ABCA4-positive eyes: 2.8 ± 0.7 
a.u. (mean ± standard error of the mean)]. This is similar to our 
previous finding that a different version of the dual AAV platform 
resulted in 50% ABCA4-expressing eyes (10). We then injected 5.5 
month-old pigmented Abca4−/− mice subretinally in the tem-
poral region of the eye with the improved dual AAV vectors 
(dose of each vector/eye: 1.8 × 10 
9 GC). Three months later we har-</p>

<p>vested the eyes and measured the levels of lipofuscin fluores-
cence (excitation: 560 ± 40 nm; emission: 645 ± 75) on retinal 
cryosections [in either the RPE alone or in RPE + outer segments 
(OS)] in the temporal region of the eye (Fig. 5B and C and Supple-
mentary Material, Fig. S4). We found that lipofuscin fluorescence 
intensity in this region of the eye was significantly higher in un-
treated Abca4−/− than in both Abca4+/− and −/− mice injected 
with the therapeutic dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors (Fig. 5B </p>

<p>and C and Supplementary Material, Fig. S4). Then, using trans-
mission electron microscopy we counted the number of RPE lipo-
fuscin granules. These were increased in 5.5-to 6-month old 
albino Abca4−/− mice injected with PBS compared with age-
matched Abca4+/+ controls (Fig. 5D), at levels similar to those 
we have independently measured in Abca4−/− mice either unin-
jected or injected with a control AAV vector (data not shown). The 
number of lipofuscin granules in Abca4−/− RPE was normalized 3 
months post subretinal injection of improved dual AAV hybrid 
ABCA4 vectors (dose of each vector/eye: 1 × 10 
9 GC, Fig. 5D). </p>

<p>Improved dual AAV vectors are safe upon subretinal 
administration to the mouse and pig retina </p>

<p>To investigate the safety of improved dual AAV2/8 hybrid ABCA4 
vectors, we injected them subretinally in both wild-type C57BL/6 
mice and Large White pigs (dose of each vector/eye: 3 × 10 
9 and </p>

<p>1 × 10 
11 GC, respectively). One month post-injection we measured </p>

<p>retinal electrical activity by Ganzfeld electroretinogram (ERG) and 
found that both the a-and b-wave amplitudes were not signifi-
cantly different between mouse eyes that were injected with 
dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors and eyes injected with either 
negative control AAV vectors or PBS (Fig. 6A and Supplementary 
Material, Fig. S5A). Similarly, the b-wave amplitude in both sco-
topic, photopic, maximum response and flicker ERG tests was 
comparable in pig eyes that were injected with dual AAV hybrid 
ABCA4 vectors to those of control eyes injected with PBS (Fig. 6B 
and Supplementary Material, Fig. S5B). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>AAV restricted packaging capacity represents one of the main ob-
stacles to the widespread application of AAV for gene therapy of 
IRDs including STGD1. However, recently, several groups, includ-
ing ours, have independently reported effective delivery of large 
genes to both the mouse and pig retina by dual AAV vectors 
(10,13,15,44), thus expanding their applicability to diseases like 
STGD1 due to mutations in genes with a CDS which exceeds 
the canonical AAV cargo capacity. Here we set-up to overcome 
some limitations associated with the use of dual AAV vectors, 
namely their relatively low efficiency when compared with a sin-
gle vector, and the production of truncated proteins which may 
raise safety concerns. Strategies aiming at increasing dual AAV 
genome tail-to-head concatemerization should in theory in-
crease the levels of full-length and reduce those of truncated pro-
teins from free single half-vectors. We set to improve tail-to-head 
dual AAV hybrid genome concatemerization by including either 
optimal regions of homology or heterologous ITR. In a side-by-
side evaluation of previously described regions of homology, 
we have found that the AP1 and AP2 sequences recently pub-
lished by Lostal et al. (16) and the AK sequence from the F1 
phage (10) drive overall similar levels of protein expression in 
vitro, with dual AAV hybrid AK vectors driving efficient ABCA4 ex-
pression in the mouse retina more frequently than those with 
AP1 and AP2 sequences. Independently, the availability of differ-
ent regions of homology will still be useful to direct proper conca-
temerization of triple AAV vectors which are being exploited to 
further expand AAV cargo capacity (16,45). Heterologous ITR2 
and ITR5 have been successfully included in dual (20,21) and tri-
ple (45) AAV vectors. We found that, although the genome of AAV 
vectors with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 is homogeneous in size, 
the yields of AAV vectors with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 are 
lower than those of vectors with homologous ITR2. We also de-
tected less vector genomes with heterologous ITR when we </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2015, Vol. 24, No. 23 | 6817 </p>

<p>probe their ITR2 than when we probe a different region of their 
genome. As we show that Rep5 interferes with production of vec-
tors with ITR2, this suggests anomalies at the level of ITR2 
included in AAV vectors with heterologous ITR, which are pro-
duced in the presence of Rep5, but not in AAV vectors with hom-
ologous ITR2, which are produced only in the presence of Rep2 
and that showed similar titres whether we probed ITR2 or a dif-
ferent region of the genome. In addition, regardless of the titre 
used to perform the infections, inclusion of heterologous ITR2 
and ITR5 in dual AAV hybrid vectors did not result in significant 
increase in the rates of full-length to truncated protein produc-
tion. These results partly differ from those previously reported 
where dual AAV vectors with heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 had 
higher transduction efficiency than vectors with homologous 
ITRs and apparently no production issues (20,21). Besides the dif-
ferent packaging constructs and production protocols, in this </p>

<p>study we used dual AAV hybrid vectors which included regions 
of homology between the two half-vectors as opposed to the 
trans-splicing (TS) system used in the previous reports which 
simply relies on the ITR for concatemerization (20,21). As in 
dual AAV hybrid vectors the reconstitution of the full-length 
gene is mainly mediated by the region of homology included in 
the vectors (12) which directs concatemer formation, this may ac-
count for the lack in the increase in transgene expression we ob-
served with vectors with heterologous ITR compared with the 
previous studies that used TS vectors (20,21). 
The production of truncated protein products from single 
half-vectors of dual AAV might raise safety concerns and we 
aimed at overcoming this by including various degradation sig-
nals in our dual AAV vectors. The inclusion of miR target sites 
in the transcript of a gene has been shown to be an effective strat-
egy to knock-down and restrict transgene expression in various </p>

<p>Figure 5. Subretinal delivery of improved dual AAV vectors results in ABCA4 expression in mouse photoreceptors and significant reduction of lipofuscin accumulation in </p>

<p>the Abca4−/− mouse retina. (A) Representative Western blot analysis of C57BL/6 retinas (whole retinal lysates) either injected with dual AAV2/8 hybrid ABCA4 vectors </p>

<p>(5′ + 3′) or with negative controls (neg). The arrow indicates full-length proteins, the molecular weight ladder is depicted on the left. α-3×flag: Western blot with anti-</p>

<p>3×flag antibodies; α-Dysferlin: Western blot with anti-Dysferlin antibodies, used as loading control. (B and C) Representative pictures (B) and quantification (C) of 
lipofuscin autofluorescence (red signal) in the retinas (RPE or RPE + OS) of either pigmented Abca4+/− mice not injected or injected with AAV as control (Abca4+/−) or </p>

<p>pigmented Abca4−/− mice either not injected (Abca4−/−) or injected with dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors (Abca4−/− AAV5′+3′). (B) The scale bar (75 μm) is depicted in </p>

<p>the picture. RPE: retinal pigment epithelium; ONL: outer nuclear layer; INL: inner nuclear layer; GCL: ganglion cell layer. The arrows indicate lipofuscin signal. </p>

<p>(C) Mean lipofuscin autofluorescence in the temporal side of three sections for each sample. Mean autofluorescence in each section was normalized for the length of 
the underlying RPE. The mean value is depicted above the corresponding bar. Values are represented as mean ± s.e.m. ***p ANOVA &lt; 0.0001. n = 4 eyes for each group. </p>

<p>(D) Mean number of RPE lipofuscin granules counted in at least 40 fields (25 µm 
2 )/retina of albino Abca4+/+ mice either not injected (Abca4+/+ not inj) or injected with </p>

<p>PBS (Abca4+/+ PBS), and albino Abca4−/− mice injected with either PBS (Abca4−/− PBS) or dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors (Abca4−/− AAV5′+3′). The mean value is </p>

<p>depicted above the corresponding bar. Values are represented as mean ± s.e.m. *pANOVA ≤ 0.05; **pANOVA ≤0.01. n = 4 eyes from Abca4+/+ not inj; n = 4 eyes from Abca4 
+/+ PBS; n = 3 eyes from Abca4−/− PBS; n = 3 eyes from Abca4−/− AAV5′ + 3′. More details on the statistical analysis including specific statistical values can be found in the </p>

<p>Statistical analysis paragraph of the Materials and Methods section. </p>



<p>tissues, including the retina (26). However, we achieved only a 
partial reduction of truncated protein production with miR target 
sites. Although we cannot rule out that miR target sites lead to a 
more effective silencing in the mouse retina than in vitro, our in 
vitro experiments suggest that features of the mRNA external to 
the miR target sites rather than miRNA levels might affect the 
efficiency of the silencing. Indeed, while miR mimics provide 
robust silencing of a canonical EGFP expression cassette contain-
ing the miR target sites, this silencing was less robust when we 
tested the same mimics with dual AAV ABCA4 vectors (Fig. 4A). 
Along this line, since the truncated protein products that derive 
from the 5′-half are produced from a vector that is not endowed 
with a canonical polyadenilation signal, it may be possible that 
the resulting mRNA cannot undergo an efficient miR-mediated 
silencing (46,47). 
Importantly, we achieved complete degradation of the trun-
cated protein product from the 5′-half vector by inclusion of the 
CL1 degron. We showed that this signal is effective both in vitro 
and in the pig retina, indicating that the enzymes of the degrada-
tive pathway required for CL1 activity are expressed in various 
cell types. On the other hand, we found that none of the degrad-
ation signals tested in the 3′-half vectors significantly reduced 
truncated protein expression without affecting full-length </p>

<p>protein expression. In addition, we found a negative correlation 
between the length of the degradation signal included in the 
3′-half vector and the levels of protein expression, possibly indi-
cating that increasing the size of the sequences between the ITR 
and the splicing acceptor signal interferes with mRNA process-
ing. However, we could never abolish truncated protein forma-
tion from the 3′-half vectors even using different lengths of 
degradation sequences. Since 3′-half vectors do not have a ca-
nonical promoter with a defined transcription start site, it is pos-
sible that start codons downstream of the region of the vector 
where we included the degradation signals are recognized more 
efficiently than the ATG of the degradation signals. This would 
result in exclusion of the degradation signal from the truncated 
proteins. As the truncated protein product from the 3′-half vector 
is less abundant than that produced by the 5′-half vector (Fig. 4A 
and Supplementary Material, Fig. S2), its presence should raise 
less safety concerns. Indeed, although further formal toxicity 
studies are required to finally address this issue, data presented 
here in the mouse and pig retina support the safety of improved 
dual AAV vectors. 
Notably, we found that subretinal administration of improved 
dual AAV vectors, under the control of the GRK1 promoter, which 
provides high levels of combined rod and cone transduction, </p>

<p>Figure 6. Similar electrical activity between either negative control or improved dual AAV-treated eyes of mice and pigs. (A) Mean a-(left panel) and b-(right panel) wave </p>

<p>amplitudes of C57BL/6 mice 1-month post-injection of either dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors (AAV5′ + 3′) or negative controls (i.e. negative control AAV vectors or PBS; neg). 
Data are presented as mean ± s.e.m.; n indicates the number of eyes analysed. More details on the statistical analysis can be found in the Statistical analysis paragraph of </p>

<p>the Materials and Methods section. (B) Mean b-wave amplitudes (μV) in scotopic, maximal response, photopic and flicker ERG tests in pigs 1-month post-injection of either </p>

<p>dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors (AAV5′ + 3′) or PBS. n = 5 eyes injected with dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors; n = 4 injected with PBS; *: n = 2. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2015, Vol. 24, No. 23 | 6819 </p>

<p>results in effective ABCA4 delivery in mice, although at variable 
levels. This could be due to both the inherent variability of the 
subretinal injection in the small murine eye and the overall 
lower efficacy of the dual AAV system compared with a single 
AAV vector (10). Despite this variability, we found that dual AAV 
mediated ABCA4 delivery results in significant lipofuscin reduc-
tion in the Abca4−/− retina suggesting that a wide range of trans-
gene expression levels can similarly contribute to therapeutic 
efficacy. This was observed using two independent techniques, 
however, more pronounced improvement of the phenotype was 
observed when we dissected and analysed the AAV transduced 
area of the retina that indeed showed normalization of the num-
ber of lipofuscin granules. HPLC measurement of A2E, the major 
lipofuscin granules component, has been used to assess the effi-
cacy of therapies in Abca4−/− mice (48-50). However, we found 
these measurements to be inconsistent in our hands, even be-
tween affected and normal retinas (data not shown), thus we 
were not able to use this technique in our rescue experiments. 
In conclusion, our study characterized dual AAV vectors with 
improved features in view of their potential future clinical appli-
cation to the therapy of STGD1. In addition, our findings can be 
used to improve dual AAV vectors for gene therapy of other con-
ditions due to mutations in genes with a CDS which exceeds AAV 
cargo capacity. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Generation of plasmids </p>

<p>The plasmids used for AAV vector production were all derived 
from dual AAV hybrid AK vector plasmids encoding for the 
human ABCA4 gene containing the ITR of AAV serotype 2 (10). 
For cloning purposes, the 77 bp-long AK sequence (10) was fol-
lowed by a 32 bp-long region (sequence: attaacgtttataatttcaggtgg-
catctttc) in each of the dual AAV hybrid AK vectors. The 77-bp AK 
recombinogenic sequence and the following 32-bp-long region 
were replaced with three different recombinogenic sequences 
derived from the human placental alkaline phosphatase gene: 
AP [NM_001632_4, bp 927-1204, (10)]; AP1 [NM_001632_4, 
bp 1802-1516 (16)]; AP2 [NM_001632_4, bp 1224-938 (16)]. 
Dual AAV vector plasmids bearing heterologous ITR from AAV 
serotype 2 (ITR2) and ITR from AAV serotype 5 (ITR5) in the 5:2-2:5 
configuration were generated by replacing the left ITR2 in the 5′-
half vector plasmid and the right ITR2 in the 3′-half vector plas-
mids, respectively, with ITR5 (NC_006152.1, bp 1-175). Dual AAV 
vector plasmids bearing heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 in the 2:5-
5:2 configurations were generated by replacing either the right 
or the left ITR2 with the ITR5, respectively. The pAAV5/2 pack-
aging plasmid containing the Rep5 and AAV2 Cap genes (Rep5-
Cap2), was obtained from the pAAV2/2 packaging plasmid, 
containing the Rep and Cap genes from AAV2 (Rep2Cap2), by re-
placing Rep2 with the Rep5 open reading frame from AAV5 
(NC_006152.1, bp 171-2206). 
The pZac5:5-CMV-EGFP plasmid containing the EGFP expres-
sion cassette with ITR5 was generated from the pAAV2.1-CMV-
EGFP plasmid, containing the ITR2 flanking the EGFP expression 
cassette (51). 
Degradation signals were cloned in dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 
vectors as follows: in the 5′-half vector plasmids between the 
AK sequence and the right ITR2; in the 3′-half vector plasmids be-
tween the AK sequence and the splice acceptor signal. Details on 
degradation signal sequences can be found in Table 2. 
The ABCA4 protein expressed from dual AAV vectors is tagged 
with 3×flag at both N-(amino acidic position 590) and C-termini </p>

<p>for the experiments shown in Figures 3 and 4 and Supplementary 
Material, Figure S2, and at the C-terminus alone for the experi-
ments in Figures 2 and 5a. 
Dual AAV hybrid ABCA4 vectors included either the ubiqui-
tous CMV (52) or the GRK1 (41) promoters. Single AAV vectors en-
coding EGFP included either the GRK1 or the IRBP (39) promoters. </p>

<p>AAV vector production and characterization </p>

<p>AAV2/2 and AAV2/8 vector large preparations were produced 
by the TIGEM AAV Vector Core by triple transfection of HEK293 
cells followed by two rounds of CsCl2 purification. AAV vectors 
bearing homologous ITR2 were obtained as previously 
described (54). 
To obtain AAV vectors bearing heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 a 
suspension of 1.1 × 10 
9 low-passage HEK293 cells was quadru-</p>

<p>ple-transfected by calcium phosphate with 500 µg of pDeltaF6 
helper plasmid which contains the Ad helper genes (55), 260 µg 
of pAAV cis-plasmid and different amounts of Rep2Cap2 and 
Rep5 packaging constructs. The amount of Rep2Cap2 and Rep5 
packaging constructs was as follows: </p>

<p>(i) PROTOCOL A: 130 µg of each Rep5 and Rep2Cap2 (ratio 1:1) 
(ii) PROTOCOL B: 90 µg of Rep5 and 260 µg of Rep2Cap2 (ratio 
1:3) 
(iii) PROTOCOL C: 26 µg of Rep5 and 260 µg of Rep2Cap2 (ratio 
1:10) </p>

<p>Each AAV preparation was then purified according to the pub-
lished protocol (54). 
The protocols described below were used for the Rep compe-
tition experiments: </p>

<p>1. to assess Rep5 competition with Rep2 for production of AAV 
vectors with ITR2, HEK293 cells were either quadruple-trans-
fected by calcium phosphate with pDeltaF6, pAAV2.1-CMV-
EGFP cis, the Rep2Cap2 and Rep5Cap2 constructs at a weight 
ratio of 2:1:1.5:1.5 or, as a control, quadruple-transfected 
with the pDeltaF6, pAAV2.1-CMV-EGFP, the Rep2Cap2 pack-
aging construct and a control irrelevant plasmid at a weight 
ratio of 2:1:1.5:1.5; 
2. to assess Rep2 competition with Rep5 for production of AAV 
vectors with ITR5, HEK293 cells were either quadruple-trans-
fected by calcium phosphate with pDeltaF6, pZac5:5-CMV-
EGFP, the Rep5Cap2 and Rep2Cap2 constructs at a weight 
ratio of 2:1:1.5:1.5 or, as a control, quadruple-transfected 
with pDeltaF6, pZac5:5-CMV-EGFP, the Rep5 construct and a 
control irrelevant plasmid at a weight ratio of 2:1:1.5:1.5. </p>

<p>For the large-scale AAV vector preparations physical titres [(GC)/ 
mL] were determined by averaging the titre achieved by PCR 
quantification using TaqMan (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, 
CA, USA) (54) with a probe annealing on ITR2 and that obtained 
by dot-blot analysis (56) with a probe annealing within 1 kb 
from ITR2. For the large-scale AAV5:2 vector preparations pro-
duced with different Rep5:Rep2Cap2 weight ratio using the 5′-
half plasmid of dual AAV vector, physical titres were determined 
by PCR quantification using TaqMan with a probe annealing on 
ITR2. For the AAV vector preparations used in the competition ex-
periments physical titres were determined by PCR quantification 
using TaqMan with a probe annealing on the bovine growth hor-
mone (BGH) polyadenilation signal, included in the EGFP-expres-
sing cassette packaged in the AAV vectors. </p>



<p>AAV infection of HEK293 cells </p>

<p>AAV infection of HEK293 cells was performed as previously de-
scribed (10). AAV2 vectors bearing heterologous ITR2 and ITR5 
and produced according to Protocol C were used to infect 
HEK293 cells with a multiplicity of infection (m.o.i) of 1 × 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>GC/cell of each vector (i.e. 2 × 10 
4 total GC/cell when we used </p>

<p>dual AAV vectors at a 1:1 ratio) calculated considering either 
the ITR2 or the transgene titre. Infections with AAV2/2 bearing re-
combinogenic regions and degradation signals were carried out 
with a m.o.i of 5 × 10 
4 GC/cell of each vector (i.e. 1 × 10 
5 total GC/ </p>

<p>cell in the case of dual AAV vectors at 1:1 ratio) calculated consid-
ering the average titre between TaqMan and dot-blot. 
For the experiments using 5′-half vectors containing miR 
target sites, cells were transfected with the corresponding miR 
mimics (50 nM; miRIDIAN microRNA mimic hsa-let-7b-5p, hsa-
miR-204-5p, hsa-miR-124-3p and hsa-miR-26a-5p; Dharmacon, 
Lafayette, CO, USA) using calcium phosphate 4 h prior to 
infection. </p>

<p>Subretinal injection of AAV vectors in mice and pigs </p>

<p>Mice were housed at the Institute of Genetics and Biophysics ani-
mal house (Naples, Italy), maintained under a 12-h light/dark 
cycle (10-50 lux exposure during the light phase). C57BL/6 mice 
were purchased from Harlan Italy SRL (Udine, Italy). Pigmented 
Abca4−/− mice were generated through four successive crosses 
of albino Abca4−/− mice (10) with Sv129 mice and then main-
tained inbred; breeding was performed crossing Abca4+/− with 
−/− mice. Albino Abca4−/− mice were generated through succes-
sive crosses and backcrossed with BALB/c mice (homozygous for 
Rpe65 Leu450) and maintained inbred; breeding was performed 
crossing Abca4+/− mice with −/− mice. C57BL/6 (5 week-old), pig-
mented Abca4−/− (5.5 month-old) and albino Abca4−/− (2.5-to 3-
month old) mice were anaesthetized as previously described (57), 
then 1 µl of either PBS or AAV2/8 vectors was delivered subretin-
ally to the temporal side of the retina via a trans-scleral trans-
choroidal approach as described by Liang et al. (58). AAV2/5-
VMD2-human Tyrosinase (59) (dose: 2×10e8 GC/eye) was added 
to the AAV2/8 vector solution that was subretinally delivered to 
albino Abca4−/− mice (Fig. 5D). This allowed us to mark the RPE 
within the transduced part of the eyecup, which was subsequent-
ly dissected and analyzed. 
The Large White Female pigs used in this study were regis-
tered as purebred in the LW Herd Book of the Italian National 
Pig Breeders' Association. Pigs were housed at the Cardarelli hos-
pital animal house (Naples, Italy) and maintained under 12-h 
light/dark cycle (10-50 lux exposure during the light phase). 
This study was carried out in accordance with the Association 
for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology Statement for the 
Use of Animals in Ophthalmic and Vision Research and with 
the Italian Ministry of Health regulation for animal procedures. 
All procedures were submitted to the Italian Ministry of Health; 
Department of Public Health, Animal Health, Nutrition and 
Food Safety. Surgery was performed under anaesthesia and all ef-
forts were made to minimize suffering. Animals were sacrificed 
as previously described (36). Subretinal delivery of AAV vectors 
to 3 month-old pigs was performed as previously described 
(36). All eyes were treated with 100 µl of either PBS or AAV2/8 vec-
tor solution. The AAV2/8 dose was 1 × 10 
11 GC of each vector/eye </p>

<p>therefore co-injection of dual AAV vectors at a 1:1 ratio resulted in 
a total dose of 2 × 10 
11 GC/eye. </p>

<p>For the animal studies included in Figures 2C, 4C, 5 and 6 and 
Supplementary Material, Figures S3-S5, right and left eyes were </p>

<p>assigned randomly to the various experimental groups and the 
researchers conducting and quantifying the experiments were 
blind to the treatment received by the animals. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis </p>

<p>HEK293 cells, mouse and pig retinas were lysed in RIPA buffer 
(50 m Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 150 m NaCl, 1% NP40, 0.5% Na-Deoxy-
cholate, 1 m EDTA pH 8.0, 0.1% SDS). Lysis buffers were supple-
mented with protease inhibitors (Complete Protease inhibitor 
cocktail tablets; Roche, Milan, Italy) and 1 m phenylmethylsul-
fonyl. After lysis, samples of cells containing ABCA4 were 
denatured at 37°C for 15 min in 1× Laemli sample buffer supple-
mented with 4 M urea. Lysates were separated by 6% or 8% (the 
latter used for the WB in Fig. 4C) SDS-polyacrylamide gel electro-
phoresis. The antibodies used for immuno-blotting are as fol-
lows: anti-3×flag (1:1000, A8592; Sigma-Aldrich); anti-Filamin A 
(1:1000, catalogue #4762; Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, 
MA, USA); anti-Dysferlin (1:500, Dysferlin, clone Ham1/7B6, 
MONX10795; Tebu-bio, Le Perray-en-Yveline, France). Filamin A 
and Dysferlin were used as loading controls for the in vitro and 
in vivo experiments, respectively. 
The quantification of ABCA4 bands detected by Western blot 
was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> software (free download available at 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij</rs>/). Quantification of the Western blot ex-
periments has been performed as follows: </p>

<p>-Figure 2A and B: the intensity of the ABCA4 band was nor-
malized to that of Filamin A band in the corresponding 
lane. Normalized ABCA4 expression was then expressed 
as percentage relative to dual AAV hybrid AK vectors; 
-Figure 2C: the intensity of the ABCA4 band (a.u.) was cal-
culated as fold of increase relative to the mean intensity 
measured at the same level in the negative control lanes 
of each gel (the measurement of the negative control sam-
ple in lane 7 of the lower left panel was excluded from the 
analysis given the exceptionally high background signal). 
Values for each group are represented as mean ± standard 
error of the mean (s.e.m.); 
-Figure 3B-D: the full-length ABCA4 and truncated protein 
band intensities were divided by those of the Filamin A 
bands or the intensity of the full-length ABCA4 protein 
bands was divided by that of the truncated protein 
bands in the corresponding lane. Values are represented 
as: mean ± s.e.m; 
-Supplementary Material, Table S2: full-length ABCA4 and 
truncated protein band intensities were measured in cells 
co-infected with 5′-and 3′-half vectors. The ratio between 
the intensity of full-length ABCA4 and truncated protein 
bands in the presence of either the corresponding mimic 
or a scramble mimic was calculated. Values represent 
mean ± s.e.m. of the ratios from three independent 
experiments; 
-Supplementary Material, Table S3: full-length ABCA4 and 
truncated protein band intensities were measured in cells 
co-infected with 5′-and 3′-half vectors. The ratio between 
the intensity of the full-length ABCA4 and truncated 
bands from vectors either with or without the degradation 
signals was calculated. Values represent mean ± s.e.m. of 
the ratios from three independent experiments. 
-Figure 5A: the intensity of the ABCA4 band (a.u.) was calcu-
lated as fold of increase relative to the mean background in-
tensity measured in the negative control lanes of the 
corresponding gel. Values are expressed as mean ± s.e.m. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2015, Vol. 24, No. 23 | 6821 </p>

<p>Southern blot analysis </p>

<p>Three ×10 
10 GC of viral DNA were extracted from AAV particles. To </p>

<p>digest unpackaged genomes, the vector solution was resus-
pended in 240 µl of PBS pH 7.4 19 (GIBCO; Invitrogen S.R.L., 
Milan, Italy) and then incubated with 1 U/µl of DNase I (Roche) 
in a total volume of 300 µl containing 40 m TRIS-HCl, 10 m 
NaCl, 6 m MgCl 2 , 1 m CaCl 2 pH 7.9 for 2 h at 37°C. The DNase 
I was then inactivated with 50 m EDTA, followed by incubation 
with proteinase K and 2.5% N-lauroyl-sarcosil solution at 50°C for 
45 min to lyse the capsids. The DNA was extracted twice with 
phenol-chloroform and precipitated with two volumes of ethanol 
100 and 10% sodium acetate (3 M, pH 7). Alkaline agarose gel elec-
trophoresis and blotting were performed as previously described 
(60). Ten microlitres of the 1 kb DNA ladder (N3232L; New England 
Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA) were loaded as molecular weight 
marker. Two different double strand DNA fragments were la-
belled with digoxigenin-dUTP using the DIG high prime DNA la-
belling and detection starter kit (Roche), and used as probes. The 
5′ probe (768 bp) was generated by double digestion of the 
pZac2.1-CMV-ABCA4_5′ plasmid with SpeI and NotI; the 3′ 
probe (974 bp) was generated by double digestion of the 
pZac2.1-ABCA4_3′_3×flag_SV40 plasmid with ClaI and MfeI. Pre-
hybridization and hybridization were performed at 65°C in 
Church buffer (60) for 1 h and overnight, respectively. Then, the 
membrane (Whatman Nytran N, charged nylon membrane; 
Sigma-Aldrich, Milan, Italy) was first washed for 30 min in SSC 
29-0.1% SDS, then for 30 min in SSC 0.59-0.1% SDS at 65°C and 
then for 30 min in SSC 0.19-0.1% SDS at 37°C. The membrane 
was then analyzed by chemiluminescence detection by enzyme 
immunoassay using the DIG DNA Labelling and Detection Kit 
(Roche). </p>

<p>Histological analysis </p>

<p>Mice were euthanized, and their eyeballs were then harvested 
and fixed overnight by immersion in 4% paraformaldehyde 
(PFA). Before harvesting the eyeballs, the temporal aspect of the 
sclerae was marked by cauterization, in order to orient the eyes 
with respect to the injection site at the moment of the inclusion. 
The eyeballs were cut so that the lens and vitreous could be re-
moved while leaving the eyecup intact. Mice eyecups were infil-
trated with 30% sucrose for cryopreservation and embedded in 
tissue-freezing medium (O.C.T. matrix; Kaltek, Padua, Italy). For 
each eye, 150-200 serial sections (10 µm thick) were cut along 
the horizontal plane and the sections were progressively distrib-
uted on 10 slides so that each slide contained 15-20 sections, 
each representative of the entire eye at different levels. The sec-
tions were stained with 4′,6′-diamidino-2-phenylindole (Vecta-
shield; Vector Lab, Peterborough, UK) and were monitored with 
a Zeiss Axiocam (Carl Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) at different 
magnifications. 
Pigs were sacrificed, and their eyeballs were harvested and 
fixed overnight by immersion in 4% PFA. The eyeballs were cut 
so that the lens and vitreous could be removed, leaving the eye-
cups in place. The eyecups were gradually dehydrated by progres-
sively infiltrating them with 10, 20 and 30% sucrose. Tissue-
freezing medium (O.C.T. matrix; Kaltek) embedding was per-
formed. Before embedding, the swine eyecups were analyzed 
with a fluorescence stereomicroscope (Leica Microsystems 
GmbH, Wetzlar, Germany) in order to localize the transduced re-
gion whenever an EGFP-encoding vector was administered. For 
each eye, 200-300 serial sections (12 µm thick) were cut along 
the horizontal meridian and the sections were progressively </p>

<p>distributed on glass slides so that each slide contained 6-10 sec-
tions. Section staining and image acquisition were performed as 
described for mice. </p>

<p>Cone immunofluorescence staining </p>

<p>Frozen retinal sections were washed once with PBS and then per-
meabilized for 1 h in PBS containing 0.1% Triton X-100. A blocking 
solution containing 10% normal goat serum (Sigma-Aldrich) was 
applied for 1 h. A primary antibody [anti-human CAR (61,62), 
which also recognizes the porcine CAR ('Luminaire founders'-
hCAR, 1:10.000; kindly provided by Dr Cheryl M. Craft, Doheny 
Eye Institute, Los Angeles, CA, USA)] was diluted in PBS and incu-
bated overnight at 4°C. The secondary antibody (Alexa Fluor 594, 
anti-rabbit, 1:1000; Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, 
USA) was incubated for 45 min. Sections stained with the anti-
CAR antibodies were analyzed at 63× magnification using a 
Leica Laser Confocal Microscope System (Leica Microsystems 
GmbH), as previously described (63). Briefly, for each eye six dif-
ferent z-stacks from six different transduced regions were 
taken. For each z-stack, images from single plans were used to 
count CAR+/EGFP + cells. In doing this, we carefully moved 
along the Z-axis to distinguish one cell from another and thus 
to avoid to count twice the same cell. For each retina we counted 
the CAR-positive (CAR+)/EGFP-positive (EGFP+) cells on total CAR 
+ cells. We then calculated the average number of CAR+/EGFP + 
cells of the three eyes of each experimental group. </p>

<p>EGFP quantification </p>

<p>Fluorescence intensity in PR was rigorously and reproducibly 
quantified in an unbiased manner as previously described (63). 
Individual colour channel images were taken using a Leica micro-
scope (Leica Microsystems GmbH). TIFF images were gray-scaled 
with image analysis software (<rs id="software-1" type="software">LAS AF lite</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Leica Microsystems GmbH</rs>). Six images of each eye were analyzed at 20× magnifica-
tion by a masked observer. The PR (outer nuclear layer + OS) 
were selectively outlined in every image, and the total fluores-
cence for the enclosed area was calculated in an unbiased man-
ner using the image analysis software. The fluorescence in PR 
was then averaged from six images collected from separate ret-
inal sections from each eye. We then calculated the average fluor-
escence of the three eyes of each experimental group. </p>

<p>Quantification of lipofuscin autofluorescence </p>

<p>For lipofuscin fluorescence analysis, eyes were harvested from 
pigmented Abca4+/− and Abca4−/− mice at 3 months after AAV 
injection. Mice were dark-adapted over-night and sacrificed 
under dim red-light. For each eye, four overlapping pictures 
from the temporal side of three sections at different levels of 
the eye were taken using a Leica DM5000B microscope equipped 
with a TX2 filter (excitation: 560 ± 40 nm; emission: 645 ± 75) (64-
68) and under a 20× objective. The four images for each section 
were then combined in a single montage used for further fluores-
cence analysis. Intensity of lipofuscin fluorescence (red signal) in 
each section was automatically calculated using the <rs type="software">ImageJ</rs> soft-
ware and was then normalized for the length of the RPE under-
lying the area of fluorescence. </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy </p>

<p>For electron microscopy analyses eyes were harvested from al-
bino Abca4−/− and Abca4+/+ mice at 3 months after AAV injec-
tion. Eyes were fixed in 0.2% glutaraldehyde-2% PFA in 0.1 M </p>



<p>PHEM buffer pH 6.9 (240 m PIPES, 100 m HEPES, 8 m MgCl2, 
40 m EGTA) overnight and then rinsed in 0.1 M PHEM buffer. 
Eyes were then dissected under light microscope to select the 
tyrosinase-positive portions of the eyecups. The transduced por-
tion of the eyecups were subsequently embedded in 12% gelatin, 
infused with 2.3 M sucrose and frozen in liquid nitrogen. Cryosec-
tions (50 nm) were cut using a Leica Ultramicrotome EM FC7 
(Leica Microsystems) and extreme care was taken to align PR con-
necting cilia longitudinally. To avoid bias in the attribution of 
morphological data to the various experimental groups, counts 
of lipofuscin granules were performed by a masked operator 
(Dr Roman Polishchuk) using the <rs id="software-4" type="software">iTEM</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Olympus SYS</rs>, 
Hamburg, Germany). The 'Touch count' module of the <rs type="software">iTEM</rs> soft-
ware was used to count the number of lipofuscin granules in 
25 µm 
2 areas (at least 40) distributed randomly across the RPE </p>

<p>layer. The granule density was expressed as number of granules 
per 25 µm 
2 . </p>

<p>Electroretinogram recordings </p>

<p>Electrophysiological recordings in mice and pigs were performed 
as detailed in (69) and in (70), respectively. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>p-values ≤0.05 were considered statistically significant. One-way 
ANOVA with post-hoc Multiple Comparison Procedure was used 
to compare data depicted in Figure 2B (pANOVA = 1.2 × 10 
−6 ), </p>

<p>Figure 2C (pANOVA = 0.326), Figure 5C (pANOVA = 1.5 × 10 
−10 ), </p>

<p>Figure 5D (pANOVA = 0.034) and Figure 6A (pANOVA a-wave: 0.5; 
pANOVA b-wave: 0.8) and Supplementary Material, Table S3 
( pANOVA = 0.0135). As the counts of lipofuscin granules (Fig. 5D) 
are expressed as discrete numbers, these were analyzed by devi-
ance from a Negative Binomial generalized linear models (71). 
The statistically significant differences between groups deter-
mined with the post-hoc Multiple Comparison Procedure are 
the following: Figure 2B: AP versus AK: 1.08 × 10 
−5 ; AP1 versus </p>

<p>AK: 0.05; AP2 versus AK: 0.17; AP1 versus AP: 1.8 × 10 </p>

<p>−6 </p>

<p>; AP2 versus 
AP: 2.8 × 10 
−6 ; AP2 versus AP1: 0.82. Figure 5C: Abca4+/− versus </p>

<p>Abca4−/−: 0.00; Abca4−/− versus Abca4−/− AAV5′+3′: 9.3 × 10 
−5 ; </p>

<p>Abca4+/− versus Abca4−/− AAV5′ + 3′: 4 × 10 
−6 . Figure 5D: Abca4 </p>

<p>−/− PBS versus Abca4−/− AAV5′ + 3′: 0.01; Abca4+/+ PBS versus 
Abca4−/− AAV5′ + 3′: 0.37; Abca4+/+ not inj versus Abca4−/− 
AAV5′ + 3′: 0.53; Abca4+/+ PBS versus Abca4−/− PBS: 0.05; Abca4 
+/+ not inj versus Abca4−/− PBS: 0.03; Abca4+/+ not inj versus 
Abca4+/+ PBS: 0.76. Supplementary Material, Table S3: 3×STOP 
versus no degradation signal: 0.97; 3×STOP versus PB29: 1.0; 
3×STOP versus 3×PB29: 0.15; 3×STOP versus ubiquitin: 0.10; PB29 
versus no degradation signal: 1.0; PB29 versus 3×PB29: 0.1; PB29 
versus ubiquitin: 0.07; 3×PB29 versus no degradation signal: 
0.06; 3×PB29 versus ubiquitin: 1.0; ubiquitin versus no degrad-
ation signal: 0.04. 
The Student's t-test was used to compare data depicted in 
Table 1, Figures 3C, D and 6B and in Supplementary Material, 
Figure S3B-D and Table S2. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Supplementary Material is available at HMG online. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Annamaria Carissimo (Bioinformatics Core, TIGEM, 
Naples, Italy) for the statistical analyses; Monica Doria, Antonella </p>

<p>Ferrara and Viola Alba (AAV Vector Core, TIGEM, Naples, Italy) for 
AAV vector production; Mary D Allen (Laboratory for Vision Re-
search) and Dr Cheryl MCraft (University of Southern California, 
Los Angeles, CA) for providing the anti-human CAR antibody; 
Graciana Diez-Roux (Scientific Office, TIGEM, Naples, Italy) for 
the critical reading of this manuscript. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest statement. Ivana Trapani, Pasqualina Colella and 
Alberto Auricchio are co-inventors on patent applications on the 
dual AAV vector platform. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The following funding support is gratefully acknowledged: the 
European Research Council/ERC Grant agreement number: 282085 
'RetGeneTx'; the Italian Telethon Foundation (grant TGM11MT1) 
and a grant from Shire. Funding to pay the Open Access publication 
charges for this article was provided by FONDAZIONE TELETHON. </p>



<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2015, Vol. 24, No. 23 | 6823 </p>







<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2015, Vol. 24, No. 23 | 6825 </p>

</text></tei>