<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4922208" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Breast cancer is the most common cancer in Iranian women as is worldwide. Mammography screening has been 
introduced as a beneficial method for reducing mortality and morbidity of this disease. </p>

<p>Objectives: We developed an analytical model to assess the cost effectiveness of an organized mammography screening program 
in Iran for early detection of the breast cancer. </p>

<p>Patients and Methods: This study is an economic evaluation of mammography screening program among Iranian woman aged 
40 -70 years. A decision tree and Markov model were applied to estimate total quality adjusted life years (QALY) and lifetime costs. </p>

<p>Results: The results revealed that the incremental cost effectiveness ratio (ICER) of mammography screening in Iranian women in 
the first round was Int. $ 37,350 per QALY gained. The model showed that the ICER in the second and third rounds of screening 
program were Int. $ 141,641 and Int. $ 389,148 respectively. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Study results identified that mammography screening program was cost-effective in 53% of the cases, but incremental 
cost per QALY in the second and third rounds of screening are much higher than the accepted payment threshold of Iranian health 
system. Thus, evaluation of other screening strategies would be useful to identify more cost-effective program. Future studies with 
new national data can improve the accuracy of our finding and provide better information for health policy makers for decision 
making. </p>

<p>Keywords: Cost Effectiveness, Screening, Mammography, Iran, QALY </p>

<p>1. Background </p>

<p>Cancer with about 20% mortality rate is the second 
cause of mortality worldwide and (1) breast cancer is the 
most common cancer occurred among women. Based 
on the report published by the Iranian cancer registry, in 
2009, there were a total number of 7,582 women diagnosed 
with breast cancer and the age standardized incidence rate 
(ASR) was 28.25 per 100,000 (2). Regardless of the underes-
timated report, it is estimated that about 10,000 women 
are annually diagnosed and treated with breast cancer. 
Iran has a relatively young population causing a lower age 
distribution of breast cancer compared to its counterparts 
(3). About 51% of diagnosed breast cancer cases are less 
than 50 years old (2). According to Harirchi et al. (2011), the 
frequency of patients diagnosed with the advanced stages 
of disease was higher in Iran compared to the developed 
nations (4). 
In spite of the huge burden of the breast cancer on </p>

<p>Iranian women, their family and the health system, there 
have not been developed any early diagnosis or screening 
program, strategy in this country so far. It is expected that 
a screening policy for breast cancer, can downstage the dis-
ease distribution and decrease the mortality rates and dis-
abilities associated with breast cancer (1). Early detection 
of breast cancer through population based screening pro-
gram may decrease the amount of resources spent on the 
treatment of patients. Otherwise, it imposes extra burden 
on the society in terms of resources spent on the screening 
process consisting initial investments needed for screen-
ing and the further operational costs required for clarifica-
tion of the abnormal cases (1). </p>

<p>As mentioned before, Iran has a young population in 
which the lower mammographic sensitivity and higher 
rate of false positive report are more evident (5). Warner  (2011) showed that the benefit-to-risk ratio is too low to al-
low a routine screening program for women less than 50 </p>

<p>Copyright © 2016, Iranian Journal of Cancer Prevention. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 
International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits copy and redistribute the material just in noncommercial usages, provided the 
original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Haghighat S et al. </p>

<p>years of old (6). Findings of Barfar and colleagues do not 
support the implementation of national mammography 
screening programs in Iranian women aged less than 50 
years (7). The question is that whether decreases in the 
cost of treatment and the rate of mortality and disability 
would be big enough to compensate for the cost of screen-
ing and the operational costs of abnormal findings. In 
other words, would a prospective population based mam-
mography screening program be a cost effective strategy 
in order to reduce the burden of breast cancer in Iran. </p>

<p>2. Objectives </p>

<p>Therefore, we developed an analytical model to assess 
the incremental cost effectiveness of an organized screen-
ing program in Iran. </p>

<p>3. Patients and Methods </p>

<p>This study is an economic evaluation of mammogra-
phy screening strategy among Iranian woman aged 40 -70 
years compared to no-screening. The study was conducted 
from the viewpoint of Iranian health system. Model out-
comes were quality adjusted life years (QALY) and lifetime 
costs calculated over 50-year time horizon. Comparative 
performance of two strategies was measured by using the 
incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER). Future health 
effects and costs were discounted at an annual rate of 3% 
and 5% respectively. </p>

<p>3.1. Data Sources </p>

<p>The result of the three unpublished mammography 
screening programs conducted on small populations (8- 10) were used in this study. Annual transition probabilities 
between health states were derived from previous studies, 
national reports, and expert panels if needed. information 
about age distribution (11) and prevalence of breast cancer 
among Iranian women (12) was adopted from national re-
ports and summarized in Table 1. </p>

<p>3.2. Modeling </p>

<p>The costs and consequences of the mammography 
screening were compared with non-screening program. 
We used a decision tree to detect patients with breast can-
cer. Then a Markov model was used to calculate additional 
life years saved due to early detection of breast cancer 
through screening program. 
Women over 40 were included in the model. Accord-
ing to the report released by Iran statistics center in 2012, 
the population of 40 -69 year old women was estimated 
to be about 9, 102, 292. It was assumed that almost 80% </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic Characteristics of Iranian Women </p>

<p>Parameter 
Best Estimate of Parameter, % </p>

<p>Frequency of female Population in Iran 
by age groups </p>

<p>&lt; 40 
71.59 </p>

<p>40 -44 
6.53 </p>

<p>45 -49 
5.36 </p>

<p>50 -54 
4.69 </p>

<p>55 -59 
3.57 </p>

<p>60 -64 
2.48 </p>

<p>65 -69 
1.79 </p>

<p>≥ 70 </p>

<p>3.99 </p>

<p>Frequency of Breast cancer in Iranian 
women by age groups </p>

<p>&lt; 40 
19.4 </p>

<p>40 -44 
14.6 </p>

<p>45 -49 
16.5 </p>

<p>50 -54 
15.0 </p>

<p>55 -59 
11.6 </p>

<p>60 -64 
8.9 </p>

<p>65 -69 
5.3 </p>

<p>≥ 70 </p>

<p>8.6 </p>

<p>Breast cancer Cumulative mortality 
rate in Iranian women in time horizon 
after diagnosis, Y </p>

<p>1 
0.05 </p>

<p>2 
0.12 </p>

<p>3 
0.18 </p>

<p>4 
0.24 </p>

<p>5 
0.29 </p>

<p>6 
0.32 </p>

<p>7 
0.44 </p>

<p>8 
0.47 </p>

<p>9 
0.49 </p>

<p>10 
0.52 </p>

<p>11 
0.54 </p>

<p>12 
0.57 </p>

<p>13 
0.59 </p>

<p>14 
0.61 </p>

<p>15 
0.63 </p>

<p>of the target population (7,300,000 women) would par-
ticipate in the screening program. According to the ex-
perts, abnormal findings would be detected in 60% of at-</p>

<p> 
Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(1):e5443. </p>

<p>Haghighat S et al. </p>

<p>tendances in which almost 7% (3% -10%) require more as-
sessment (13, 14). The probability of using invasive or non-
invasive assessments procedures were assumed to be 20% 
and 80% respectively. Akbari et al. (2012) showed that the 
sensitivity and specificity of mammography are about 69% 
and 48% in women less than 50 years old and 82% and 67% 
in 50 years and above respectively (5). In two screening 
projects conducted by BCRC, similar finding have been dis-
covered (9, 10). Thus, according to expert opinions, over-
all sensitivity and specificity of mammography were con-
sidered 75% and 55% respectively. Women with positive re-
sult were considered as breast cancer patients and entered 
the Markov model. According to the previous studies con-
ducted in Iran, the breast cancer detection rate was esti-
mated to be 1/1000 in screened women (8-10, 15). The proba-
bility of developing breast cancer in the intervals between 
routine screenings (interval cancers) was assumed 0.0001 
(0.000072 -0.00024 (14, 15). </p>

<p>Five states were incorporated into the Markov model: 
healthy individuals, development of breast cancer while 
remaining alive, development of metastasis, death due to 
breast cancer, and death from other causes. Age distribu-
tion in non-screen group was based on the official reports 
of Iran (4, 16, 17). Probability of different treatment pro-
cedures were derived from some published studies (18, 19)  and expert panels. Due to lack of data about stage distri-
bution of breast cancer in screening program in Iran evi-
dences form other similar countries (in terms of similarity 
in population characteristics and cancer incidence) such 
as China (20) and Turkey were used (1) stage distributions 
in two strategies are shown in Table 1. Based on SEER data at 
2002, the probability of occurrence of metastasis in stages 
I, II and III were predicted to be 0.01, 0.08 and 0.21, respec-
tively (20). </p>

<p>3.3. Effect </p>

<p>The background and disease specific mortality rate for 
patients with breast cancer were estimated using Iran life 
tablulation 2009, Iran death registry data (21), and two lon-
gitudinal studies conducted by Haghighat and Movahedi 
(16, 22). Both disease specific and background mortality 
rates were only considered for the first 15 years of diag-
nosed patients with stage IV or metastasis state and there-
after only background mortality were included in our cal-
culations (Table 1). </p>

<p>We used a value of 0.95 for quality of life of healthy 
(breast cancer-free) women, and values of 0.9, 0.8, 0.7, and 
0.3 were assigned to patients in stage I, stage II, stage III, 
and stage IV of disease, respectively (20). </p>

<p>3.4. Cost </p>

<p>The cost of screening as well as the cost of assessment 
of the patients with abnormal findings were identified. Ac-
cording to the study conducted on vulnerable household 
women in Iran (8, 15), personnel expenditures had been es-
timated 0.21 of total screening costs which was added to 
initial costs of screening. 
Cost of treatment included workup costs to determine 
the stage of disease; direct treatment costs and the cost 
of diagnosis and management of metastatic patients. We 
used combination of public and private sector national tar-
iffs in 2012 (23), to estimate the mean cost of medical care. 
For the sake of comparison, the costs were converted from 
Iranian currency (Rials-IRR) into international dollars (Int. 
$). </p>

<p>3.5. Sensitivity Analysis </p>

<p>One-way Sensitivity analyses were performed by vary-
ing the following parameters: discount rate of cost and 
QALY, cost of mammography screening, cost of cancer 
treatment, recall rate, abnormal mammograms, and fi-
nally detection rate of cancer in 2 strategies. We assigned 
beta-distributions for quality of life, triangular distribu-
tion for costs and recall rate and normal and uniform dis-
tributions for other parameters and probabilities. 
All the components of a breast cancer screening pro-
gram were transferred to simulation software and <rs type="software">Excel</rs> to 
calculate the cost effectiveness ratio. A Monte Carlo simu-
lation was done with 1000 iteration and 95% confidence 
interval of cancer costs and effects in screened and non-
screened strategies. 
Regarding world health organization guidelines and 
per capita GDP in Iran, the $39300 considered as cost ef-
fectiveness threshold. Medical interventions with a cost of 
less than three times GDP per capita per QALY are generally 
considered to be cost-effective (24, 25). According to cen-
tral intelligence agency report in 2012 (26), GDP per Capita 
of Iran is Int. $ 13,100, so the ceiling rate of government for 
health intervention was estimated about Int.$ 39,300. </p>

<p>3.6. Repeated Screening </p>

<p>Since the effect of screening program in finding inci-
dental cases would be established after three rounds (27), 
we estimated the costs of three rounds of screening pro-
gram. Annual inflation rate of 17% (28) was applied to 
costs. ICER was calculated for the second and third round 
of screening. Cancer detection rate in non-screen group 
was assumed constant during the second and third screen-
ing rounds. The incidence rates in screened women were 
considered 0.001, 0.0007 and 0.0005 in the first, second 
and third round of screenings respectively (14, 29). Recall </p>

<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(1):e5443. 
3 </p>

<p>Haghighat S et al. </p>

<p>rate in the first, second and third round of screening was 
assumed 7% (3% -10%), 3.6% (3% -7%) and 3.7% (3% -7%) re-
spectively (8-10, 13). Interval cancer rate was assumed con-
stant during three rounds of screenings. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>This study examined the effect and cost of screening 
program in 9, 102, 292 Iranian women aged 40 -69 years, 
of which 7,300,000 women (80%) participated in the pro-
gram. About 10,000 patients with breast cancer are diag-
nosed annually in this target population. Advanced can-
cers were frequent in 44% of patients while about 14% of 
them were in stage I of the disease. Table 2 demonstrates 
the changes in stage distribution of breast cancer before 
and after screening. It has been shown that due to screen-
ing program the proportion of patients in stage I, increases 
from 14% to 33% and stage III decreases from 32% to 11%. </p>

<p>Table 2. Breast cancer Stage Distribution in Screened and Non-Screened Patients (n 
= 10.000) </p>

<p>Disease Staging 
Frequency, No. (%) </p>

<p>Non-Screening 
Screening </p>

<p>I 
1400 (0.14) 
3300 (0.33) </p>

<p>II 
4200 (0.42) 
4300 (0.43) </p>

<p>III 
3200 (0.32) 
1100 (0.11) </p>

<p>IV 
1200 (0.12) 
1300 (0.13) </p>

<p>The effect of screening on the target population was 
demonstrated by a decision tree model (Figure 1). Con-
sidering model assumptions, it was noticed that screen-
ing could find 5110 cases more than non-screening strat-
egy. To show the changes of QALY due to screening strate-
gies, Markov model was applied (Figure 2). Results showed 
that screening could provide 13.400 QALY more than non-
screening strategy which is 1.34 QALY per each participant. 
Table 3 demonstrates the mean, minimum, and maxi-
mum costs of screening, treatment and diagnostic work-
ups per woman participated in the program. It was es-
timated that cost of mammography screening and eval-
uation of the abnormal findings in 7,300,000 recruited 
women was int. $ 3,186,403,941. It means that the cost of 
finding each cases due to screening policy would be Int. $ 
623.562. 
Study findings showed that the mean costs of treat-
ment in a breast cancer were Int. $ 16,434 and Int. $ 17,504 
in screening and non-screening strategies respectively. The 
cost of treatment increased in upper stages of diagnosis 
compared to lower ones. </p>

<p>Table 3. Costs of Screening, Diagnosis, and Treatment Modalities in Each Screened 
Women </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Parameter 
Cost, Int. $ </p>

<p>Initial screening 
199 (179 -219) </p>

<p>Assessment of abnormal findings of screening 
237 (213 -300) </p>

<p>Disease staging work up 
570 (513 -629) </p>

<p>Treatment of stage I 
12,280 (11,052 -16,938) </p>

<p>Treatment of stage II 
17,436 (15,693 -23,080) </p>

<p>Treatment of stage III 
18,941 (17,047 -24,960) </p>

<p>Treatment of stage IV 
20,000 (18,000 -26,746) </p>

<p>Diagnosis and treatment of metastasis 
18,073 (16,265 -22,785) </p>

<p>a Values are expressed as Mean (Range). </p>

<p>Incremental cost and effect of triennially mammogra-
phy screening in 40 -70 years old women have been pre-
sented in Table 4. Results showed that the cost of every 
QALY saved through mammography screening program 
would be Int. $ 37,350. Given that there are 7,300,000 
women eligible for screening, the total cost of screening 
program will be about Int. $ 272,655,000,000. The incre-
mental costs per QALY were Int. $ 141,350 and Int. $ 389,148 
in the second and third rounds of screening. 
We demonstrated the sensitivity of the outcome vari-
able changing certain model parameters using tornado di-
agram in Figure 3. The results showed that the cost effec-
tiveness of screening was very sensitive to recall rate of ab-
normal findings. Variation of recall rate between 3% and 
10% changes the ICER from Int. $ 26280 to Int. $ 85847 re-
spectively. 
Model robustness was tested in a probabilistic sensi-
tivity analysis (PSA).The result showed that screening pro-
gram would be cost effective in 53% of the cases regarding 
the threshold of 39300 $. 
In the second round of screening, the ICER was totally 
higher than what Iranian health system was willing to pay. 
In the third round of screening the cost of an additional 
health day was about Int.US $1500 and in 0.004 of cases, 
screening was inferior strategy. </p>

<p>5. Discussion </p>

<p>This is the first study conducted about the cost effec-
tiveness of mammography screening program in Iran. Re-
sults indicate that the cost of mammography screening in 
Iranian women is Int. $ 37,350 per quality-adjusted life-
year (QALY), with a probability of 53% being cost-effective 
at a threshold of Int. $ 39.300. ICER varies according to 
the changes in age groups, interval of screening and basic </p>

<p>4  Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(1):e5443. </p>

<p>Haghighat S et al. </p>

<p>Invited Population </p>

<p>Mammography Screening </p>

<p>Abnormal </p>

<p>No Recall </p>

<p>No Cancer </p>

<p>Recall </p>

<p>Cancer </p>

<p>No Cancer </p>

<p>Cancer </p>

<p>No Cancer </p>

<p>Cancer 
Normal </p>

<p>Normal </p>

<p>Cancer 
No Screening </p>

<p>Figure 1. Decision Tree Model </p>

<p>Breast Cancer Cases </p>

<p>Screeing </p>

<p>No Screeing </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 2 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 3 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage I </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 3 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 2 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage I </p>

<p>Survive 
Stay Stage 1 </p>

<p>Dead 
Stay Stage 2 </p>

<p>Dead 
Stay Stage 3 </p>

<p>Dead 
Stay Stage 4 </p>

<p>Dead 
Stay Stage 2 </p>

<p>Dead 
Stay Stage 3 </p>

<p>Dead 
Stay Stage 4 </p>

<p>Dead </p>

<p>Dead </p>

<p>Stay Stage 1 </p>

<p>Die From Cancer </p>

<p>Die From Cancer </p>

<p>Go Stage 4 (metastasis) </p>

<p>Go Stage 4 (metastasis) </p>

<p>Go Stage 4 (metastasis) </p>

<p>Go Stage 4 (metastasis) </p>

<p>Go Stage 4 (metastasis) </p>

<p>Go Stage 4 (metastasis) 
Breast Canccer Stage I </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 2 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 3 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage I </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 2 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 3 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Breast Canccer Stage 4 </p>

<p>Death from Breast Cancer </p>

<p>Death From Breast Cancer </p>

<p>Survive </p>

<p>Survive </p>

<p>Survive </p>

<p>Survive </p>

<p>Survive </p>

<p>Survive </p>

<p>Survive </p>

<p>Die From Background 
Mortality </p>

<p>Die From Background 
Mortality </p>

<p>Die From Background 
Mortality </p>

<p>Die From Background 
Mortality </p>

<p>Die From Background 
Mortality </p>

<p>Die From Background 
Mortality </p>

<p>Die From Background 
Mortality </p>

<p>Die From Background 
Mortality </p>

<p>Dead </p>

<p>Dead From Breast Cancer </p>

<p>Dead </p>

<p>Dead From Breast Cancer </p>

<p>Figure 2. Markov Model </p>

<p>probability assumptions of involved parameters in screen-
ing. </p>

<p>In this study, we developed a model for comparing 
mammography screening versus non screening strategy </p>

<p>in 40 -70 year Iranian women. We estimated 7,300,000 el-
igible women who would participate in program. Because 
of an insufficiency of the resources required for screen-
ing program, such as health staffs and mammography </p>

<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(1):e5443. 
5 </p>

<p>Haghighat S et al. </p>

<p>Table 4. Cost and Effect of Screening VS. Non Screening in Three Rounds of Interventions </p>

<p>Screening Rounds 
Cost, Int. $ 
Effect, QALY 
ICER (Int.$/QALY) </p>

<p>Screen 
Non-Screen 
Increment 
Screen 
Non-Screen 
Increment </p>

<p>First 
265 
15 
249 
0.959 
0.952 
0.007 
37,350 </p>

<p>Second 
380 
25 
355 
0.955 
0.952 
0.003 
141,641 </p>

<p>Third 
592 
39 
551 
0.953 
0.952 
0.001 
389,148 </p>

<p>8.7 </p>

<p>-2.3 </p>

<p>129.4 </p>

<p>23.2 </p>

<p>8.5 </p>

<p>-2.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>49.7 </p>

<p>-3.4 </p>

<p>13.5 </p>

<p>-30.7 </p>

<p>-7.2 </p>

<p>2.4 </p>

<p>-28.7 </p>

<p>-14.6 </p>

<p>-4.7 </p>

<p>3.1 </p>

<p>-0.4 </p>

<p>-16.6 </p>

<p>2.6 </p>

<p>-5.2 </p>

<p>36.3 </p>

<p>-40.0 
-20.0 
0.0 
20.0 
40.0 
60.0 
80.0 
100.0 
120.0 
140.0 </p>

<p>Incidence Rate Screen [(-10%) -(+10%)] </p>

<p>Incidence rate NonScreen [(-10%) -(+10%)] </p>

<p>Recall Rate [3% -10%] </p>

<p>Abnormality Rate [(-20%) -(+20%)] </p>

<p>Interval Rate [0.000072 -0.00024] </p>

<p>Cancer Cost_Screen [(-10%) -Private] </p>

<p>Cancer Cost_NonScreen [(-10%) -Private] </p>

<p>Cancer QALY_Screen [6.51 -10.20] </p>

<p>Cancer QALY_NonScreen [5.81 -8.84] </p>

<p>Discount Rate Cost [0 -0.1] </p>

<p>Discount Rate QALY [0 -0.06] 
High Value 
Low Value </p>

<p>Figure 3. Results of One-Way Sensitivity Analysis (Tornado Diagram) </p>

<p>equipment etc., the triennially interval of screening were 
adopted. Warner et al. (2011) believe that biennially screen-
ing increases the probability of recall rate by 40% and 
chance of unnecessary biopsy by 3% (6). Similar to Fielder 
study (30), we considered the variation of interval cancer 
frequency in a range of 24% to 80% of breast cancer inci-
dence. Variation of interval cancer showed only 13% change 
of ICER in sensitivity analysis, which is a very low range 
compared to some parameters like recall rate. So it seems 
that triennially screening costs and effects are not affected 
very much by interval cancer rates. Comparing these esti-
mations in annually and biannually screening may lead to 
more accurate conclusion, which can be studied in the fu-
ture. </p>

<p>The age distribution of breast cancer in Iran is about 
one decade lower than developed countries (3, 31); there-
fore, we considered start age of screening from 40. Im-
plementing mammography screening for breast cancer 
in young population has been criticized by some stud-</p>

<p>ies. Salzmann and colleagues (1997) showed that ICER of 
screening mammography in 40 to 49 year old women is 
almost five times more than that of the older (32). Screen-
ing mammography for women in their 40s can be effective, 
but its benefit is tiny and expensive (33). In Iran, nearly 12% 
of women are in 40 -49 age group, and about 16% are 50 
years and more. It stresses the need for precise economic 
evaluation to establish screening program in this young 
population. </p>

<p>Incidence rate of breast cancer in Iran is about 30 
per 100,000 women population (2, 12). Based on our as-
sumption, to detect a breast cancer case, 1000 women 
should be screened. Sensitivity analysis showed that a 10% 
change in the incidence of breast cancer, the ICER would 
change by 15.8%. The effect of lower incidence rate on 
cost-effectiveness of a mammography screening program 
has been shown in studies conducted in Turkey (1), China 
(20) and India (34) with an incidence rate of 39/100,000, 
46/100,000 and 19.1/100,000, respectively. </p>

<p>6 
Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(1):e5443. </p>

<p>Haghighat S et al. </p>

<p>The total cost of biannually mammography screening 
in Turkish women over 40 for 10 years was estimated about 
US $ 6,836,877,672 (1). Astim has defined no threshold for 
payment in Turkey and has insisted just the most cost-
effective method between ten strategies. Although there is 
no consensus on what constitutes an acceptable ICER, the 
U.K. National institute for health and clinical excellence 
(NICE) typically have accepted technologies as cost effec-
tive if the ICERs are below US $ 36,000 to US $ 54,000 (US 
$ 15, £ 0.55) per QALY (35). Besides, the case detection rate 
of screening in Turkey has been considered 7/1000 com-
pared to 1/1000 in Iran. Figure 3 indicates that increasing 
10% in screening incidence rate leads to 7% reduction of 
costs/QALY. It may be one of the most important reasons 
of different estimates of ICER in Iran compared to Turkey. 
Wong et al. have estimated the cost of biennial mam-
mography for Chinese women ages 40 to 69 years, US $ 
61,600 per QALY (nearly 90.000 Int. $/QALY). They have sug-
gested the necessity of more studies for the rest of Greater 
China and East Asia, with lower breast cancer incidence 
and more overriding health care priorities (20). Underesti-
mation of cost in Iran may be due to Wong's assumptions 
derived from SEER and doing biennially screening in Hong 
Kong. 
The cost of screening of Indian women aged 40 to 60 
with biennial CBE and mammography were estimated Int. 
$ 1341 and Int. $ 3468 per life year gained respectively. 
Okonkwo et al. have presented CBE screening as a benefi-
cial method and believe that introduction of screening in 
India depends largely on the health system's willingness to 
pay and other health priorities (34). 
This study indicated that the first round of triennially 
mammography screening is cost-effective in 53% of cases, 
while in the second and third rounds the chance of be-
ing cost-effective is very small. These low effects have been 
reported in some recently published articles. Prasad and 
colleagues insist on harm of screening and argue that re-
ductions in overall mortality of breast cancer screening 
should be the benchmark and call for higher standards of 
evidence (36). Currently published Cochrane review which 
shows that trials with adequate randomization do not find 
an effect of screening on total cancer mortality, including 
breast cancer, (RR 1.02, 95% CI 0.95 to 1.10) after 10 years (37). 
Definitely, the smaller the effect, the less cost-effectiveness 
would be expected. The availability of sufficient health 
equipment, high quality workforce, and the time spent on 
the detection of new cases are other factors affecting the 
results. 
Because of insufficient national data, the frequency of 
different stages of breast cancer in Iran was considered 
based on some limited studies. In spite of applying 10% 
variation in each stage frequency, its effect on study results </p>

<p>cannot be ignored. 
Despite these limitations, we consider the developed 
models as holistic ones for demonstrating the breast can-
cer states in annual intervals in Iran. Establishing some lo-
cal screening programs and applying their results to this 
model, may facilitate evaluating different strategies for 
disease control. 
In this study we calculated only direct costs of screen-
ing. According to Lidgren et al. study, indirect costs were 
constituted 70% of the total cost (38). Definitely implying 
both expenditures will provide more accurate estimation 
of breast cancer burden on the health system. Develop-
ment of new diagnosis and treatment modalities in breast 
cancer can decrease the side effects and promotes the qual-
ity of life in them. Thus, it seems that the estimated cost for 
screening is the least threshold and many other facilities 
should be considered by health policy makers to improve 
the women and community health. </p>

<p>5.1. Conclusion </p>

<p>The mammography screening program, in the first 
round, was cost-effective in 53% of the cases in Iran. In-
cremental cost per QALY in the second and third rounds 
of screening are much higher than the accepted payment 
threshold by Iranian health system. Thus, evaluation of 
other screening strategies would be useful to identify more 
cost-effective program. Future studies with new national 
data can improve the accuracy of our finding and provide 
better information for health policy makers for decision 
making. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Authors thank the researchers of breast cancer re-
search center (BCRC) and death office of Iran ministry of 
health for providing data for this research. </p>

<p>Footnotes </p>

<p>Authors' Contribution: All of the authors have been con-
tributed in designing, analysis, preparing of manuscript 
and reviewing the research process. </p>

<p>Financial Disclosure: There was no financial support for 
this research. </p>

<p>Funding/Support: There was no financial support. </p>



<p>Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(1):e5443. </p>

<p>
Haghighat S et al. </p>



<p> 
Iran J Cancer Prev. 2016; 9(1):e5443. </p>

</text></tei>