<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4182997" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Maturação somática e composição corporal em adolescentes eutróficos do sexo feminino com ou sem 
adequação de gordura corporal </p>

<p>Maturación somática y composición corporal en adolescentes eutróficos del sexo femenino con o sin 
adecuación de grasa corporal </p>

<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: To evaluate the relationship between the 
stages of somatic maturation and body composition in eutro-
phic female adolescents with or without excessive body fat. 
Methods: Cross-sectional study of 118 female adoles-
cents, from 14 to 19 years-old, in Viçosa, Minas Gerais, 
Southeast Brazil. The adolescents were divided in two 
groups: Group 1 (G1), eutrophic with adequate body fat 
percentage, and Group 2 (G2), eutrophic with high body 
fat percentage. The somatic maturation was assessed by the 
formula for estimating the Peak Height Velocity (PHV). 
Results: The PHV had higher average score in G1 adoles-
cents compared to G2 (0.26 versus 0.05; p=0.032). There was 
an association between G1, G2 and the somatic maturation 
(p=0.049). The female adolescents before and during PHV 
presented higher values of fat body BMI (p=0.034) and per-
centage of central fat (p=0.039) compared to the adolescents 
after PHV. There was a correspondence between before PHV 
stage and the excess of body fat (α=0.751). 
Conclusions: There was an association between somatic 
maturation and body composition in eutrophic female 
adolescents. Length, BMI and fat percentage were differ-
ent among the somatic maturation stages. It is relevant to 
evaluate the somatic maturation and the changes occurring </p>

<p>in the body composition during adolescence in order to 
better evaluate and manage the nutritional status and the 
body fat excess. </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2014;32(1):78-84. </p>

<p>Valter Paulo N. Miranda et al </p>

<p>central (p=0,039) do que as adolescentes pós-PVC. Houve 
correspondência entre o estágio pré-PVC e o excesso de 
gordura corporal com poder discriminatório satisfatório 
(α=0,751). 
Conclusões: Os resultados mostraram associação entre a 
maturação somática e a composição corporal de adolescentes 
eutróficas do sexo feminino. Variáveis como estatura, IMC 
e percentual de gordura foram diferentes entre os estágios 
de classificação da maturação somática. Assim, é relevante 
analisar a maturação somática e as alterações que ocorrem 
com a composição corporal durante a adolescência, visando 
avaliar e controlar o estado nutricional e o acúmulo de gor-
dura corporal. </p>

<p>Palavras-chave: adolescente/crescimento &amp; desenvolvimento; 
composição corporal; gordura corporal. </p>

<p>RESUMEN </p>

<p>Objetivo: Evaluar la relación entre las etapas de matura-
ción somática y de composición corporal en adolescentes del 
sexo femenino eutróficas, con o sin exceso de grasa. 
Métodos: Estudio transversal con 118 adolescentes del 
sexo femenino, de 14 a 19 años, en Viçosa, Minas Gerais 
(Brasil), divididas en dos grupos: Grupo 1 (G1) -eutróficas 
con porcentaje elevado de grasa corporal -y Grupo 2 (G2) -
eutrófica con porcentaje adecuado de grasa. Se evaluó la 
maturación somática por la fórmula de estimativa del Pico 
de Velocidad de Crecimiento (PVC). 
Resultados: El PVC tuvo mayor escore mediano en las 
adolescentes del G1 en comparación al G2 (0,26 versus 0,05; 
p=0,032). Hubo asociación entre G1, G2 y las etapas de ma-
turación somática (p=0,049). Las adolescentes en las etapas 
pre y durante PVC presentaron valores mayores de IMC, 
de grasa (p=0,034) y porcentaje de grasa central (p=0,039) 
que las adolescentes post-PVC. Hubo correspondencia entre 
la etapa pre-PVC y el exceso de grasa corporal con poder 
discriminatorio satisfactorio (α=0,751). 
Conclusiones: Los resultados mostraron asociación entre 
la maturación somática y la composición corporal de adoles-
centes eutróficas del sexo femenino. Variables como estatura, 
IMC y porcentaje de grasa fueron distintos entre las etapas 
de clasificación de la maturación somática. Así, es relevante 
evaluar la maturación somática y las alteraciones que tienen 
lugar con la composición corporal durante la adolescencia, 
visando a evaluar y a controlar mejor el estado nutricional y 
la acumulación de grasa corporal. </p>

<p>According to the World Health Organization 
(1) , ado-
lescence is defined as the period of life ranging from ten 
to 19 years, being a phase of transition from childhood to 
adulthood. Puberty comprises the physical and biological 
changes; however, adolescence encompasses puberty and 
psychosocial transitions 
(1) . Puberty starts 1 year earlier in 
girls, but their peak height velocity (PHV) occurs two years 
earlier, compared to boys 
(1) . 
During adolescence, there is an increase of approximately 
50% in weight and of 15-25% in the individuals' adult 
height 
(2) . The girls begin the growth spurt at 9.5 years, 1 or 
2 years earlier than boys 
(3) . The changes in body composi-
tion include changes in the relative proportions of water, 
lean mass, fat mass and skeletal, as well as characteristics 
of pubertal maturation, resulting in phenotypic differences 
between the sexes </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>. The relative amount of fat in females 
gradually increases during adolescence </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>. Growth is rapid 
in early childhood and pre-adolescence, increasing sharply 
during the adolescence growth spurt, reducing and, even-
tually ending, as adult dimensions are achieved </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>. Physical 
growth is particularly sensitive to environmental conditions, 
among which stand out: immigration, emerging diseases, 
low levels of physical activity, the various types of urbani-
zation, differences in socioeconomic terms and basic health 
care, in addition to different dietary habits, and pollution 
(7) . 
Somatic maturation is used to evaluate the biologi-
cal development, using, for this, the analysis of PHV in 
height </p>

<p>(8,9) </p>

<p>, which can be obtained by the formula of Mirwald 
et al </p>

<p>(10) </p>

<p>, which has anthropometric measures of height, height, 
and cephalic length. 
All changes in body composition that occur during 
adolescence are associated with the biological maturation 
state 
(9) . Changes in the nutritional status of adolescents may 
vary between individuals, according to genetic, hormonal, 
and environmental processes 
(1,11) . In the study by Pinto 
et al </p>

<p>(12) </p>

<p>, the prevalences of overweight and abdominal obesity 
showed an increase in the final stages of sexual maturation 
for both sexes, when indicators of body mass index (BMI) 
and waist circumference were evaluated. Girls with early 
sexual maturation had a higher prevalence of overweight 
and abdominal obesity than adolescents in which the sexual 
maturation was delayed </p>

<p>(12) </p>

<p>. </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2014;32(1):78-84. </p>

<p>Somatic maturation and body composition in female healthy adolescents with or without adjustment for body fat </p>

<p>Given the above, the aim of this study was to evaluate 
the relationship between the stages of somatic maturation 
and body composition in eutrophic adolescent females or 
without excess body fat. </p>

<p>Method </p>

<p>Cross-sectional study, with 118 female adolescents from 14 
to 19 years, students of public schools in the municipality of 
Viçosa, state of Minas Gerais, with the following inclusion cri-
teria: presence of menarche for at least 1 year; to be eutrophic 
by the BMI with adequate or excess body fat percentage; do 
not make use of medications; do not present chronic illnesses 
and not having been pregnant, or to be pregnant. 
The adolescent were grouped into: Group 1 (G1), eutro-
phic by BMI for age and sex (IMC/A) 
(13) and with adequate 
body fat percentage (&gt;20% and &lt;25%) 
(14) ; Group 2 (G2), 
eutrophic by BMI/A 
(13) , but with a high percentage of body 
fat (≥30%) 
(14) . The percentage body fat (%BF) was estima-
ted by bipolar bioelectrical impedance (Tanita </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>) and by the 
biceps, triceps, subscapular, and suprailiac skinfold thickness 
measured by a Lange Skinfold Caliper (Beta Technology Inc), 
according to techniques proposed by Cameron </p>

<p>(15) </p>

<p>. We classi-
fied %BF as proposed by Lohman 
(14) . To be included in the 
study, the adolescent's %BF should match the classification 
range by the two methods. 
To calculate the sample size, we used the software <rs id="software-0" type="software">Epi-Info</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">6.04</rs>. We considered the population of 3,608 adolescents 
in the age range and sex for the study 
(16) , the prevalence of 
excess body fat of 25% 
(17) , an acceptable variability of 11% 
and a confidence level of 95%, with minimum sample of 59 
adolescents in each group (G1 and G2), totaling a sample 
of 118 adolescents. 
For the sample selection, we chose randomly four public 
schools by convenience, located in the urban area of the muni-
cipality. Screening was performed with measurement of weight, 
height, and %BF in 560 adolescents. Of these, all students who 
met the inclusion criteria participated in the random selection 
draw. The selected adolescents from both groups underwent 
anthropometric and body composition assessments. 
According to the techniques proposed by Jellife </p>

<p>(18) </p>

<p>, weight 
was measured using an electronic digital scale with a ma-
ximum capacity of 150kg and 100g sensitivity, and height 
was measured with a portable stadiometer with 2.0m-lenght 
and 0.1cm-resolution. We classified the nutritional status by 
BMI and height by age and sex, as proposed by the World 
Health Organization </p>

<p>(13) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>For the location of the peripheral and central body fat, we 
used the sum of the biceps and triceps skinfolds and the subs-
capular and suprailiac skinfolds. Body fat in kilograms (Fat 
kg) was calculated from the %BF estimated by the bioimpe-
dance analyzer and the adolescent's weight. The fat-free mass 
in kilograms (FFM kg) was obtained subtracting the Fat kg 
from the total weight. 
The waist circumference (WC) and the hip circumferen-
ce (HC) were measured with a flexible and inelastic tape 
measure, with extension of 2m, divided into centimeters 
and subdivided into millimeters, care being taken not to 
compress the soft parts. The measure f the WC was ob-
tained at the midpoint between the last rib and the iliac 
crest, and the HC as the largest circumference of the hip-
-buttocks region. We calculated the waist-to-hip ratio 
(WHR) and the waist-to-height ratio (WHtR). The WC, 
the RCQ, and the RCE were classified as: adequate (&lt;90th 
percentile) and inadequate (≥90th percentile). The 90th 
percentile is the cutoff used for the studied population 
(19) . 
We calculated the somatic maturation with the for-
mula to estimate the PHV for adolescents, developed by 
Mirwald et al 
(10) . The formula of somatic maturation for 
girls, according to Mirwald et al </p>

<p>(10) </p>

<p>, is: -9,376 + [0.0001882 
x (leg length and sitting height interaction)] + 0.0022 x 
(age and leg length interaction) + 0.005841 x (age and 
sitting height interaction) -0.002658 x (age and weight 
interaction) + 0,07693 x (weight by height ration). From 
the resulting value, adolescents were classified into three 
stages: pre-PHV (PHV&lt;-1), during PHV (PHV≥-1 or 
PHV≤+1) and post-PHV (PHV&gt;+1). 
For data analysis we used the software Epi-Info 6.04 and 
the <rs type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS</rs>), ver-
sion 17.0. We performed the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test to 
verify the normality of data. We used the Mann-Whitney; 
Kruskall-Wallis, and the Bonferroni's post hoc test (for the 
latter, we considered p&lt;0.025). Pearson's chi-square test for 
linear association was used to verify the relationship between 
somatic maturation and nutritional status of adolescents. 
We also used the multiple correspondence analysis, as a 
method of multivariate exploratory analysis, to observe the 
association between groups of adolescents regarding body 
fat, stages of somatic maturation, and the classification of 
WC, WHR and the WHtR. 
The project was approved by the Research Ethics 
Committee of Universidade Federal de Viçosa (UFV). 
Participants older than 18 or parents signed the informed 
consent form. </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2014;32(1):78-84. </p>

<p>Valter Paulo N. Miranda et al </p>

<p>Variables 
PHV -Median (Minimum-Maximum) 
p-value* 
Pre-PHV 
During-PHV 
Post-PHV 
Weight 
51.1 (38.0-58.0) 
51.1 (38.8-66.6) 
50.6 (43.6-68.8) 
0.983 
Height 
1.6 (1.5-1.63) 
1.6 (1.47-1.74) 
1.6 (1.5-1.7) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.015 
BMI 
21.4 (17.2-23.0) 
19.6 (16.6-24.5) 
19.2 (17.3-24.74) 
0.278 
FBMI 
7.6 (4.2-8.93) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4.9 (3.4-9.9) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4.6 (3.71-9.9) 
0.034 
FFBM 
13.9 (12.96-14.9) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>14.3 (12.9-16.1) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>14.6 (13.3-15.3) 
0.264 
%BF 
32.5 (25.0-34.0) 
25.0 (21.5-37.8) 
25.0 (20.5-34.8) 
0.039 
%BF4S 
54.1 (41.7-60.9) 
51.4 (38.2-65.6) 
49.2 (43.8-58-5) 
0.148 
WC 
68.5 (57.0-74.0) 
66.0 (57.0-80.0) 
65.5 (60.0-78.0) 
0.607 
HC 
93.5 (82.0-100.0) 
91.8 (81.0-103.0) 
90.0 (58.0-105.0) 
0.741 
WHR 
0.73 (0.68-0.80) 
0.72 (0.61-0.85) 
0.73 (0.64-0.8) 
0.859 
WHtR 
0.44 (0.38-0.49) 
0.40 (0.34-0.5) 
0.40 (0.37-0.48) 
0.076 
FFM 
34.7 (28.7-38.9) 
37.1 (30.46-44.5) 
37.8 (33.3-41.34) 
0.068 
FKg 
18.0 (9.3-21.0) 
13.0 (8.34-27.31) 
12.2 (9.5-27.5) 
0.215 </p>

<p>Table 1 -Stages of somatic maturation and evaluation of anthropometric and body composition variables in eutrophic adolescents 
from 14 to 19 years, with adequate or high body fat percentage. Viçosa (2005) </p>

<p>PHV: peak height velocity; WC: waist circumference; HC: Hip circumference; BMI: body mass index; BFMI: body fat mass index; FFBM: fat-free 
body mass; %CBF: central fat percentage; %CF4S: central fat percentage 4 skinfolds; WHR: waist-to-hip ratio; WHtR: waist-to-height ratio; 
FFM: fat-free mass (kg); Fkg; total fat in kg. *significant value by the Kruskall Wallis test with Bonferroni's post hoc test. 
a post-puberty classification 
greater index of height, verified by the post hoc de Bonferroni's post hoc (p&lt;0.025). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>classification pre-PHV and during PHV with greater indexes 
of BFMI. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>classification pre-PHV and during PHV with greater indexes of central fat percentage. </p>

<p>Table 2 -Classification of stages of somatic maturation and evaluation of anthropometric and body composition variables of eu-
trophic adolescents from 14 to 19 years, according to study groups. Viçosa, 2009 </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>PVC -Median (Min-Max) </p>

<p>p-value* </p>

<p>PVC -Median (Min-Max) </p>

<p>p-value* </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 </p>

<p>Pre -PHV 
During PHV 
Post-PVC 
Pre -PHV 
During PHV 
Post-PVC </p>

<p>Weight </p>

<p>47 (38-55) 
48 (38-57) 
49 (44-52) 
0.888 
52 (47-58) 
56 (46-66) 
58 (50-69) 
0.080 </p>

<p>Height </p>

<p>1.5 (1.4-1.6) 
1.6 (1.4-1.7) 
1.6 (1.5-1.7) 
0.288 
1.5 (1.5-1.6) 
1.6 (1.5-1.7) 
1.6 (1.5-1.7) 
0.049 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>BMI </p>

<p>19 (17-22) 
19 (16-21) 
18 (17-20) 
0.976 
22 (20-23) 
22 (20-24) 
22 (20-25) 
0.666 </p>

<p>FBMI </p>

<p>5.5 (4.2-6.8) 
4.3 (3.5-4.9) 
4.4 (3.7-4.5) 
0.624 
7.7 (6.3-8.7) 
7.0 (6.2-9.2) 
7.0 (6.2-9.7) 
0.650 </p>

<p>FFBMI 13.9 (12.9-14.8) 14.2 (12.9-16.0) 14.0 (13.0-15.3) 0.983 13.9 (13.1-14.5) 14.9 (14.0-15.0) 14.9 (14.2-15.1) 0.078 </p>

<p>%CF </p>

<p>29 (25-33) 
24 (21-25) 
23 (21-25) 
0.080 
33 (33-34) 
33 (31-34) 
33 (31-35) 
0.080 </p>

<p>%CF4S </p>

<p>53 (50-55) 
50 (38-62) 
49 (43-58.5) 
0.736 
54 (42-61) 
49 (44-54) 
49 (45-54) 
0.254 </p>

<p>WC </p>

<p>65 (57-63) 
64 (57-69) 
63 (60-66) 
0.996 
69 (63-74) 
73 (67-78) 
73 (67-78) 
0.391 </p>

<p>HC </p>

<p>89 (82-96) 
89 (81-97) 
88 (85-93) 
0.996 
94 (88-100) 
97 (92-105) 
98 (92-105) 
0.309 </p>

<p>WHR </p>

<p>0.7 (0.7-0.8) 
0.7 (0.6-0.8) 
0.7 (0.6-0.8) 
0.862 
0.7 (0.7-0.8) 
0.7 (0.6-0.8) 
0.8 (0.6-0.9) 
0.828 </p>

<p>WHtR </p>

<p>0.4 (0.4-0.5) 
0.4 (0.3-0.4) 
0.4 (0.4-0.4) 
0.683 
0.4 (0.4-0.5) 
0.4 (0.3-0.5) 
0.5 (0.4-0.5) 
0.594 </p>

<p>FFM </p>

<p>33 (29-38) 
37 (30-45) 
38 (33-41) 
0.649 
34 (30-38) 
38 (32-44) 
39 (35-41) 
0.012 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>FKg </p>

<p>13 (9-17) 
11 (8-13) 
12 (10-12) 
0.926 
18 (15-21) 
19 (10-27) 
18 (15-28) 
0.841 </p>

<p>PHV: peak height velocity; Max: maximum value; WC: wait circumference; HC: hip circumference Min: minimum value; BMI: body mass 
index; BFMI: body fat mass index; FFBMI: fat-free body mass index; %CF: percentage of central fat; %CF4S: percentage of central fat 
4 skinfolds; WHR: waist-to-hip ratio; WHtR: waist-to-height ratio; FFM: fat-free mass; Fkg: total fat in kg. *significant value (p&lt;0.05) by 
Kruskall Wallis test. </p>

<p>a In Group 2 post-PHV adolescents with higher height than pre-PHV verified by Bonferroni's test (p&lt;0.05); 
b In Group 2 the post-PHV adolescents 
with higher rates of fat-free mass than those in the pre-PHV, verified by Bonferroni's post hoc test (p&lt;0.025). </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2014;32(1):78-84. </p>

<p>Somatic maturation and body composition in female healthy adolescents with or without adjustment for body fat </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The study included 118 adolescents with a mean age of 
16.4±1.4 years. Adolescents from G2 presented higher va-
lues for weight, BMI, BMI of fat, WC, HC, WHR, WHtR, 
and percentage of central and peripheral fat (p&lt;0.001). 
Regarding the classification of somatic maturation, 10 
(8.5%) were classified as in the pre-PHV, 92 (78.0%) in the 
PHV, and 16 (13.5%) in the post-PHV stage. 
PHV in height had higher scores in adolescents from G1 
in comparison to G2 (0.26 versus 0.05 points; p=0.032). 
An association was found between groups and stages of soma-
tic maturation (p=0.049). There was a greater proportion of 
G1 adolescents (96.2%) in the stages during and post-spurt 
in comparison to G2 adolescents (86.42%). Girls in the 
pre-PHV and during PHV presented higher BMI values of 
fat (p=0.034) and percentage of central fat (p=0.039), when 
compared to those in post-PHV (Table 1). 
By analyzing the somatic maturation separately in each 
group, no difference was found between the PHV stage 
and anthropometric measures in G1. On the other hand, 
adolescents from G2 who were in the period of spurt and 
post-spurt presented higher values of height and fat-free 
mass (Table 2). 
In multiple correspondence analyses (Figure 1), the 
main plain (dimension 1=50.1% and dimension 2=22.3%) 
explained 72.4% of data variability. The first dimension 
presented Cronbach's alpha equal to 0.751, with satisfactory 
discriminatory power. This dimension is characterized by the 
extremes -adolescents in the pre-spurt stage, with excess 
body fat (G2) and with inadequate values of WC, WHR, 
and WtHR were correspondent. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The results showed an association between somatic matu-
ration and body composition in eutrophic female adolescents. 
Variables such as height, BMI of fat and %BF were different 
between the stages of somatic maturation. We observed that 
measures of body fat were associated with the pre-PHV 
and during-PHV stages. Similarly, studies showed that the 
stages of sexual maturation influence the anthropometric 
and body composition parameters, allowing the systematic 
construction and use of references considering pubertal 
development 
(4,20,21) . 
According to Siervogel et al </p>

<p>(11) </p>

<p>, during puberty, there are 
changes in lean body mass and in body fat distribution, </p>

<p>with accelerated growth rate (growth spurt) and the fusion 
of the bone epiphysis until adult height is achieved. The 
distribution of body fat that occurs during the process of 
maturation may explain the frequency of adolescents with 
adequate %BF, classified in the stages during PHV and 
post-PHV of somatic maturation. 
PHV was higher in eutrophic adolescents with appropria-
te percentage of body fat compared to those with excess body 
fat (p=0.032). Adolescents with adequate %BF were more 
frequently classified as during and post-PHV; while those 
with excess adiposity were more frequently classified in the 
pre-PHV stage (Figure 1). Physiologically, this finding can 
be explained, as a certain amount of body fat is necessary 
for the growth spurt in both sexes, and in females body fat 
is accumulated especially in the central region 
(11) . </p>

<p>Figure 1 -Multiple correspondence analysis between the groups 
of classification of somatic maturation, indexes of waist circumfe-
rence and waist-to-height ratio with the groups of adolescents 
with adequate fat percentage (G1) and excess fat (G2) </p>

<p>Adeq WC 
Adeq WHtR </p>

<p>Adeq WHR </p>

<p>Inadeq WHtR </p>

<p>Inadeq WHR </p>

<p>Inadeq WC 
Post-PHV </p>

<p>During-PHV </p>

<p>Adequate fat </p>

<p>Excess Fat </p>

<p>Pré-PVC </p>

<p>Dimension 2 -22.3% / α=0.129 </p>

<p>Dimension 1 -50.1% / α=0.751 </p>

<p>Class. Cint 
Class. RCE 
Class. RCQ 
Grupo 
PVC. class </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-2 
-4 
-3 
-2 
-1 
0 
1 </p>

<p>*Cronbach's α with satisfactory discriminatory value </p>

<p>Class.Waist: classification of waist circumference; Class.WHtR: 
classification of the waist-to-height ratio; Class.WHR: classifica-
ção of the waist-to-hip ratio; PHV.class: classification of somatic 
maturation; PHV: peak height velocity; Excess Fat: Group 2; WC: 
waist circumference; WHR: waist/height ratio; WHR: waist/hip 
ratio; Adequate Fat: Group1; Adeq: adequate; Inadeq: inadequate </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2014;32(1):78-84. </p>

<p>Valter Paulo N. Miranda et al </p>

<p>The results of this study showed that variables such as 
height, BMI of fat, and percentage of central fat varied in 
different classification stages of somatic maturation. As ob-
served, the rates of height were higher in stages during and 
after PHV. The BMI of fat and the percentage of central fat 
had higher rates of somatic maturation in pre-PHV stage. 
According to Barbosa et al 
(21) , the increase in body mass ob-
served in females coincides with increases in fat accumulation 
and the period of greatest increase in height. 
While observing the variation of anthropometric indexes 
in the stages of somatic maturation in G1 and G2, we found 
that G1 adolescents with adequate %BF showed no difference 
in anthropometric indexes of body composition between the 
groups of somatic maturation. On the other hand, the partici-
pants of G2, with excess fat, varied among the three groups of 
somatic maturation regarding height and fat-free mass in the 
stages during and post-PHV. This result is consistent with the 
maturation process, since height and muscle mass are directly 
proportional to the PHV also in females </p>

<p>(6,11) </p>

<p>. 
It is noteworthy that all the girls evaluated had already 
passed menarche; nevertheless, it was found that almost 18% 
of the total sample was still in the stage of pre-spurt, and 
these adolescents presented a higher body fat accumulation. 
To Duarte </p>

<p>(20) </p>

<p>, the weight tends to increase after menarche, 
due to the overall growth and development of the body and 
especially the increase in fat deposits, due to the greater role 
of estrogen and progesterone. In the first period, about 95% of 
adult height has already been reached and linear growth enters 
a deceleration process, ceasing around 2.5-3.0 years later </p>

<p>(20) </p>

<p>. 
According to the literature, the accumulation of fat in 
the central region in girls who have not reached the PHV 
is necessary to provide the physiological changes that 
occur during puberty 
(4,11) . In the present study, there was 
correspondence between the group of girls who presented 
excess fat and inadequate WC, WHR, and WHtR with 
the pre-PHV classification of somatic maturation. The ado-
lescents who were in the PHV stage and in the post-PHV 
stage had correspondence with the adequate values of 
these variables. These results show that the WHR, the 
WHtR, and the WC were related to the stages of somatic 
maturation, and it is important to emphasize that these 
variables are good indicators of metabolic syndrome and of 
the occurrence of cardiovascular disease in adolescence 
(22,23) . 
Ibanez et al 
(24) showed that, regardless of BMI, both the 
measures that reflect total adiposity (body fat in kg and 
%BF) and those that reflect the body fat distribution (waist 
circumference, WHR, and abdominal fat) were higher, in </p>

<p>all pubertal stages, in girls with early sexual maturation. 
This association cannot be made in this study, as 8.5% of 
adolescents, although in the pre-PHV stage, were classified 
as pubescent for having already passed the menarche. 
Barbosa et al 
(21) also found that the assessment of nutri-
tional status, and the anthropometric and body compo-
sition changes during adolescence are strongly related to 
the growth spurt. Siervogel et al 
(11) and the World Health 
Organization 
(25) highlight the importance of considering 
biological markers for the beginning and the end of the 
pubertal growth spurt. Corroborating the cited researches, 
the present study showed that, in addition to biological mar-
kers, anthropometric body composition variables, especially 
those related to body fat, have varied in the pre-PHV stage. 
The increase in body fat observed in virtually all countries 
of the world in recent decades, makes the use of anthropo-
metric measures in population surveys to define reference 
values even more critical </p>

<p>(25) </p>

<p>. According to Gomes et al 
(26) , it 
is essential to include information on sexual maturation to 
assess the nutritional status of adolescents </p>

<p>(26) </p>

<p>. This, in turn, is 
marked by the human biological variability, which originates 
from the interaction between genetic and environmental 
factors that occur during the growth spurt. Changes in body 
composition of adolescents are markers of metabolic changes 
that occur during pubertal development 
(21,27) . 
Metabolic changes, in turn, predict the risk of occur-
rence in adult life, of non-communicable chronic diseases, 
especially cardiovascular disease, diabetes, osteoporosis, and 
obesity 
(6,7,27,28) . Thus, we emphasize that the knowledge of 
the association between pubertal development and body 
composition enables the planning and practice of interven-
tion measures to prevent this outcome 
(11) . Several factors 
may influence the development of obesity in adolescence, 
namely, inadequate dietary intake, physical inactivity, sexual 
maturity, socioeconomic status and parental influence 
(29) . 
According to Duarte 
(20) , the interrelationships between 
growth, physical development, and maturation are still 
poorly known in Brazilian children and adolescents. 
Given the above, it is considered that the pubertal stage 
determines striking changes in anthropometric and body 
composition parameters in adolescents. There are numerous 
intrinsic and environmental factors that may influence the 
onset of puberty, with no optimal hormonal marker 
(21,30) . 
The main methodological implications related to studies 
of pubertal development include determining the initiation 
and progression, and form of assessment; this also applies to 
the process of somatic maturation. </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2014;32(1):78-84. </p>

<p>Somatic maturation and body composition in female healthy adolescents with or without adjustment for body fat </p>



<p>Regarding limitations of this study, we may consider the fact 
that teenagers aged from 10 years were not selected, which pro-
bably increased the number of girls in the group classified as pre-
-PHV. Another limitation is related to the use of a cross-sectional 
design, which does not allow the assessment of cause and effect. 
Even so, there was a relationship between somatic maturation 
and body composition variables in adolescents. 
We may conclude that there is variation of anthropome-
tric and body composition values among the three stages 
of PHV of somatic maturation, especially those related to 
body fat. The study indicates the importance of following 
these anthropometric and body composition variables from 
the beginning of pubertal growth spurt in females, in order 
to control the accumulation of adipose tissue, as well as its </p>

<p>future consequences on the health of adolescents. Therefore, 
we realize the importance of working with somatic matura-
tion in assessing body composition of adolescents. 
It is noteworthy that, during puberty, not only chrono-
logical age, sex, and stage of sexual maturation should be 
considered in the assessment of nutritional status, but also 
the adolescent's stage of somatic maturation, i.e., the eva-
luation of puberty has to consider the multitude of factors 
that surround it. Future studies with adolescents in the 
initial period of adolescence (10 to 14 years) may show the 
relationship between body composition, and stages of soma-
tic and sexual maturation in both sexes. Therefore, health 
professionals may use somatic maturation as an additional 
tool to evaluate a healthier body development of adolescents. </p>

</text></tei>