<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4295086" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Global warming due to human-induced increments in atmospheric concentrations of greenhouse gases 
(GHG) is one of the most debated topics among environmentalists and politicians worldwide. In this paper 
we assess a novel source of GHG emissions emerged following a controversial policy decision. After the 
outbreak of bovine spongiform encephalopathy in Europe, the sanitary regulation required that livestock 
carcasses were collected from farms and transformed or destroyed in authorised plants, contradicting not 
only the obligations of member states to conserve scavenger species but also generating unprecedented GHG 
emission. However, how much of this emission could be prevented in the return to traditional and natural 
scenario in which scavengers freely remove livestock carcasses is largely unknown. Here we show that, in 
Spain (home of 95% of European vultures), supplanting the natural removal of dead extensive livestock by 
scavengers with carcass collection and transport to intermediate and processing plants meant the emission 
of 77,344 metric tons of CO 2 eq. to the atmosphere per year, in addition to annual payments of ca. $50 
million to insurance companies. Thus, replacing the ecosystem services provided by scavengers has not only 
conservation costs, but also important and unnecessary environmental and economic costs. </p>

<p>Moreover, as vultures (specialized or obligate scavengers) in Europe 
have traditionally relied on domestic livestock carcasses for feed-
ing </p>

<p>12,13   , the implementation of the European sanitary legislation -
with the associated reduction in food supply and/or the change in its 
temporal and spatial availability, has had negative impacts on vulture 
behaviour, ecology and conservation at both the individual and guild 
levels 
14-17 . 
Although new and encouraging legislation was approved in March 
2011 (Regulation EC 142/2011), allowing farmers to abandon extens-
ive livestock carcasses in certain ''free areas'' in the field and at feed-
ing stations 
18 , it is far from implementation and an important 
portion of livestock carcasses is still removed from the field by 
authorised companies as mandated by the previous regulation. 
Moreover, some regions lack the specific legislation required to apply 
the European guidelines at the local scale, and future reversion to 
more restrictive rules due to new sanitary pressures cannot be ruled 
out. Thus, modelling the current scenario of GHG emissions linked 
to the artificial removal of livestock carcasses may help to broaden 
our understanding of the dimensions of supplanting this ecosystem 
service provided by scavengers. Mapping ecosystem services, or the 
consequences of their suppression, has been suggested as an essential 
step to minimize the anthropogenic footprint through the imple-
mentation and improvement of ''win-win'' strategies -those benefit-
ing both biodiversity conservation and human welfare, as well as the 
reconciliation of conflicting policies 
19,20 . Until now, however, how 
vertebrate animals might be allied in the fight against climate change, 
hence benefiting humanity through preventing the release of carbon 
and nitrogen stored in terrestrial ecosystems to the atmosphere is 
largely unknown 
21 , and never has been spatially assessed. 
Here, we spatially quantify the GHG emissions associated with 
one aspect of the application of the European sanitary regulation 
1774/2002, namely the transport of carcasses from extensive farms 
to processing plants (Fig. 1). Briefly, this regulation mandates that 
livestock carcasses be collected from farms within 24 (cattle) or 48 h 
(other livestock) after death and moved to processing plants, where 
they are subjected to different treatments depending on their risk to 
public and animal health (i.e., if they are ruminant or non-ruminant 
carcasses). However, due to the long distance at which these plants </p>

<p>are located, most livestock collected is first stored, unprocessed, at 
intermediate plants. At the end, carcasses can be used for industrial 
purposes (e.g. to produce organic fertilizers) or be transported to 
incineration plants or approved landfills 
22 . Fossil fuel combustion 
associated with the transport sector is one of the main sources of 
GHG emissions worldwide 
23 , and thus our goal is to demonstrate 
how much of this emission could be prevented in the return to 
traditional and natural systems in which scavengers freely remove 
livestock carcasses, or conversely, how much GHG is generated by 
supplanting this ecological service. We recreated the process of car-
cass collection and transport and the associated generation of GHG 
in peninsular Spain, where the majority of European vulture popula-
tions is located (ca. 95%) </p>

<p>7,9   . 
To spatially estimate GHG emission, we divided the entire area 
into 10 3 10 km grids and, for each, estimated the biomass of car-
casses generated per year using the total number of extensive live-
stock (i.e., cattle, sheep, goat and pig), their weight and annual 
mortality rates. We calculated the distance covered in the transport 
of carcasses to intermediate and/or processing plants by twice simu-
lating the displacement (using the main national road network) of a 
truck from the nearest plant to the centre of each grid (empty and full 
truck; Fig. 1). We calculated GHG emissions associated with carcass 
transport according to IPCC 
24 . GHG emissions are quantified as 
metric tons of CO 2 equivalents. As an indicator of the capacity of 
the environment to provide the supplanted ecosystem service, we 
used information from the National Biodiversity Inventory to cross 
the estimated GHG emissions with the distance of each grid centre to 
the nearest breeding site, and with the richness per grid of obligate 
scavengers (griffon Gyps fulvus, cinereous Aegypius monachus, 
Egyptian Neophron percnopterus and bearded vultures Gypaetus 
barbatus). </p>

<p>Results 
Supplanting the removal of dead livestock by scavengers through 
carcass collection and transport to intermediate and processing 
plants represented trips by 49,808,685 km and the consequent emis-
sion of 77,344 metric tons of CO 2 eq. to the atmosphere per year. Our 
estimates of CO 2 eq. should be considered as a minimum, as GHG </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Schematic representation of the application of the European sanitary regulation 1774/2002 and the natural system of extensive livestock </p>

<p>carcass removal. Following this regulation, carcasses are collected from extensive livestock farms and moved to the nearest processing plant within 24-
48 h after death. However, as some regions are too far from these processing plants and trucks would thus cover long distances without a full load, some 
intermediate plants have been established as storage points. From there, carcasses are then moved to processing plants using larger trucks. Carcasses may 
then be transported to incineration plants. The route done by full and empty trucks is shown by orange and black arrows, respectively. In the traditional, 
natural scenario, vultures and other scavengers efficiently remove carcasses in situ, normally in ,24 h </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>. The activities modelled in this article are included 
in the blue box. Photographs were taken by José A. Donázar (goat) and José A. Sánchez-Zapata (vultures). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7811 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07811 </p>

<p>
emitted during carcass processing and incineration has not been 
included. This calculation is a challenge, as collected carcasses might 
follow very different industrial processes subjected to different 
sources of energy consumption and GHG emissions. </p>

<p>Mountainous and remote areas such as the Pyrenees or western 
Spain showed the highest levels of GHG emissions (Fig. 2), mainly 
due to their higher numbers of livestock but also to their location far 
from intermediate and/or processing plants. Paradoxically, those </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Estimated CO 2 emissions (in metric tons of CO 2 eq. per 10 3 10 km grid per year) associated with the transport of extensive livestock </p>

<p>carcasses from farms to processing plants in continental Spain. The location of intermediate (circles) and processing (triangles) plants is shown in (a), 
and vulture breeding sites are shown in (b). Legend values represent the number of breeding pairs. Maps were generated with <rs id="software-2" type="software">ArcGIS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">10.1</rs>. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7811 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07811 </p>

<p>
areas are also among the best conserved regions in Europe, showing 
the highest densities of vultures. Indeed, we found a strong asso-
ciation between CO 2 emissions and the distribution and richness 
of obligate scavengers (Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Discussion 
After the implementation of the European sanitary legislation 
approved in 2002, many contradictions between biodiversity conser-
vation and sanitary policies arose. The removal of livestock carcasses 
from the field and their disposal at only a few authorised feeding 
points proved to have more negative than positive effects for the 
long-term viability of vulture and other scavenger populations 
8,25 . 
Our findings suggest an additional argument in favour of traditional, 
more natural systems of livestock carcass removal. In Spain, emis-
sions from the transport sector increased by 43.7% between 1990 and 
2012, and currently account for 23.7% of total GHG emissions. 
According to our results, the emissions associated with the transport 
of extensive livestock carcasses represented 0.1% of the total national 
transport emissions in 2012 
26 . For comparison, our estimate signifies </p>

<p>25, 15, 8 and 4% of total national emissions arising from rice cultiva-
tion, burning of agricultural residuals in the field, the chemical indus-
try and sewage treatment, respectively </p>

<p>27   . It is worth to remark that 
this estimate corresponds only to one part of livestock carcass treat-
ment, such that emissions would increase with the inclusion of the 
transformation and incineration of carcasses. Thus, further research 
is needed to complete the estimation of the total GHG emission 
linked to whole application of the actual sanitary regulation. 
Given that Spain is one of European countries that has to pay more 
to comply with the Kyoto protocol 
28 , this is an unnecessary incre-
ment in GHG emission that should be considered, mainly when 
scavengers -and vultures in particular-are highly efficient in remov-
ing carcasses from the field 
29,30 . Indeed, the removal rate of livestock 
carcasses by scavengers in Spain (median: 166 min for predictable 
and 182 min for unpredictable carcasses) 
15 is faster than figures 
depicted in the legislation. Strikingly, regions with the largest 
amounts of CO 2 emissions are also those supporting the largest 
vulture populations, suggesting that, in the absence of sanitary con-
straints, vultures would have removed most of the extensive livestock 
carcasses from the field without unnecessary environmental costs. In 
addition, this EC regulation also entails economic costs other than 
those previously mentioned (i.e., derived from the excess of CO 2 ). 
The annual payment made by farmers and regional and national 
administrations to Spanish insurance companies for the artificial 
removal and processing of extensive livestock carcasses was ca. $50 
million in 2012 
31 . Environmental and economic savings associated to 
natural carcass removal have also been identified in other European 
countries hosting vultures, such as France, in which livestock carcass 
management strategies differ. However, due to the restricted geo-
graphic distribution of the main scavenger species, the griffon vulture 
(720 breeding pairs at one reintroduction site in the Grands Causses 
region, Massif Central, France), figures are substantially lower than 
those calculated in Spain (8.42-33.11 tons of CO 2 per year, depend-
ing on the simulated scenario) 
21 . 
In 2013, no cases of BSE were reported in Spain, and European 
statistics show that the number of reported cases in farmed cattle is 
anecdotal 
32 , so the sanitary risk associated with the natural removal 
of carcasses could be considered negligible. Therefore, the return to 
the traditional system in which vultures and other scavengers freely 
exploit the carcasses of extensive livestock is highly recommended 
from multiple points of view. Humans and scavengers have coexisted 
for millennia, and vultures have traditionally provided important 
ecosystem services such as disease and pest control, nutrient cycling, 
cultural inspiration and recreational activities </p>

<p>11   . Replacing some of 
these services, as shown here, not only has conservation costs but also 
unnecessary environmental and economic costs, which can be saved 
if we simply let nature do its job. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Livestock and carcass availability. We obtained the number of head of livestock per 
municipality in 2012 from the Spanish Ministry of Agriculture, Food and 
Environment 
33 . We included the most important extensive livestock species: cattle, 
sheep, goat and pig. From the same source, we obtained the average weight of each 
livestock age class. Numbers, weight, and the annual mortality rate of each type of 
livestock per age class (Decree 17/2013 of the region of Castilla y León 
34 ; 
Supplementary Table 1) were used to calculate the biomass of carcasses generated per 
year. We generated one map with the biomass of carcasses per municipality per day, 
as carcass collection should occur within 24-48 h after livestock death. This map was 
then divided into 10 3 10 km grids using the Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM) 
system. </p>

<p>Carcass transport. We simulated the movement of carcasses from farms to 
processing plants directly or indirectly, through intermediate plants, following the 
scheme shown in the Fig. 1. We estimated the distance travelled by carcasses using the 
main national paved road network and the network analysis extension in <rs id="software-0" type="software">ArcGIS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">10.1</rs>. As the location of each farm was not available, we considered the center of each 
10 3 10 km grid to be the point of origin (i.e., the farm) from which carcasses were 
moved. From these points, we calculated the distance travelled by trucks to the nearest 
plant. If this plant was a processing plant, then carcass movement was considered 
complete. If this plant was an intermediate plant, another truck was used to complete </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Relationships between CO 2 emissions and vulture distribution </p>

<p>and richness in continental Spain. Metric tons of CO 2 eq. per grid per year 
were (a) negatively associated with distance to the nearest vulture nest/ 
colony (estimate: 2.80E-07, SE: 1.60E-08; x 
2 5 482.71, p , 0.0001) and (b) 
higher in areas with higher richness of vulture species (Kruskal-Wallis test, 
x </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 5 187.8, p , 0.001). </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7811 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07811 </p>

<p>
the transport of the carcasses to processing plants. In our analysis, movements from 
farms (i.e., grid centers) to intermediate or processing plants were performed daily, 
using 7.5 t rigid trucks of 230 hp, while movements from intermediate to processing 
plants occurred weekly and used 24 t articulated trucks of 340 hp. Vehicle types were 
determined by direct information from companies and regional regulations. We 
assumed that daily trucks collected all the carcasses generated within a grid cell until 
they reached their full load (7.5 t). Trucks moving carcasses from intermediate to 
processing plants were also completely loaded. Typically, more than one truck per 
week moved from an intermediate plant to a processing plant. All trips were 
calculated twice, as trucks must make the same trip in both directions. Intermediate 
and processing plants were geographically located using information provided by the 
Spanish Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Environment and the Autonomous 
Communities 
35 . Distance calculations were made using the shortest road between 
origin and destination points (i.e., farms to intermediate or processing plants, and 
intermediate plants to processing plants), and prioritizing road type from highest to 
lowest speed (i.e., highways, national roads, autonomic roads, streets, and unpaved 
roads) </p>

<p>36   . </p>

<p>GHG emissions. During the combustion process, most carbon is immediately 
emitted as CO 2 , although other GHG such as N 2 O and CH 4 are also produced. Thus, 
we calculated the emissions of these three gases separately as E(i) 5 AD * EF(i), where 
i is the gas type (CO 2 , CH 4 or N 2 O), AD is activity data and EF is the emission factor, 
73.7 t/TJ for CO 2  37 and 0.0039 t/TJ for CH 4 and N 2 O 
24 . Activity data (AD) was 
calculated as FC * FD * LHV, where FC is fuel consumption, FD is fuel density and 
LHV is lower heat value. FD (0.845 kg/l) and LHV (0.0424 TJ/t) were obtained from 
the Spanish Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Environment 
33 . FC was calculated by 
multiplying the distance covered by each truck by the expected average fuel 
consumption per km expected by each type of truck </p>

<p>24   . We considered that all trucks of 
the same type consumed the same quantity of fuel per km regardless of their load 
(0.21 l/km for trucks used to move carcasses from farms to the nearest plant and 
0.26 l/km for trucks used to move carcasses from intermediate plants to processing 
plants) 
38 . We assumed that all trucks used oil/diesel fuel and were 11 yrs old, such that 
motors are thermally stabilized and do not have catalysts. These assumptions are 
based on the fact that in 2011, ca. 90% of trucks and vans in Spain were diesels, and 
their average age was 11 yrs old 
39 . As fuel combustion is not perfect and a small 
portion may lead to residuals (ash and soot), we included an ''oxidation factor'' which 
expresses the ratio of CO 2 emitted per fuel unit (0.99) 
37 . Results are presented as CO 2 
equivalents (CO 2 eq.), a quantity that describes, for a given mixture and amount of 
GHG, the amount of CO 2 that would have the same global warming potential (GWP) 
when measured over a specified timescale (100 years) 
24 . GWP values for CH 4 and 
N 2 O were 34 and 298, respectively, with climate-carbon feedback values and lifetimes 
taken from 
40 . CO 2 eq. is expressed as parts per million by volume and referred to the 
10 3 10 km grid cell where carcasses originated. </p>

<p>Scavenger distribution. We used data available from the Spanish National 
Biodiversity Inventory 
33 to map the distribution of obligate scavengers (i.e., griffon 
Gyps fulvus, cinereous Aegypius monachus, Egyptian Neophron percnopterus and 
bearded vultures Gypaetus barbatus) across Spain. We focused on the breeding 
population, which represents approximately two-thirds of the total vulture 
population. We calculated the distance of each 10 3 10 km grid center to the nearest 
breeding site (i.e., nest or colony) of any obligate scavenger. Because of the high daily 
mobility of these species (griffon vultures: up to 70 km from breeding sites; cinereous 
vultures: up to 86 km from breeding sites; bearded vultures: up to 45 km from 
breeding sites; Egyptian vultures: up to 70 km from breeding sites) </p>

<p>12,41   , we also 
calculated their richness (i.e., number of species) in a 100 km buffer around each 10 3 
10 km grid cell. We used Generalized Linear Models (1/mu 
2 link function and inverse 
Gaussian error distribution) to explore the relationship between metric tons of CO 2 
eq. per grid and distance to the nearest obligate scavenger breeding site. Metric tons of 
CO 2 eq. in a 100 km buffer around grids with different species richness (from 0 to 4) 
were compared using a Kruskal-Wallis test. All analyses were performed in R 
42 . We 
used <rs id="software-1" type="software">ArcGIS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">10.1</rs> to generate maps. </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was funded by the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness through 
the project CGL2012-40013-C02-01/02. Z.M.-R. was supported by FPU12/00823, M.C. by </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7811 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07811 </p>



<p>
Author contributions </p>

<p>Z.M.-R., F.B. and J.A.S.-Z. conceived the idea. Z.M.-R., J.M.P.-G., F.B., C.L., R.M.-O. and 
J.A.S.-Z. collected and analysed the data. Z.M.-R., M.M., M.C. and J.A.S.-Z. wrote the paper. 
Z.M.-R., J.M.P.-G., M.M., F.B., M.C., C.L., R.M.-O., A.M., J.A.D. and J.A.S.-Z. discussed the 
results and commented on the manuscript. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Morales-Reyes, Z. et al. Supplanting ecosystem services provided by 
scavengers raises greenhouse gas emissions. Sci. Rep. 5, 7811; DOI:10.1038/srep07811 (2015). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in 
this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative 
Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder 
in order to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7811 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07811 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>