<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4153526" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Deep brain stimulation (DBS) of the globus pallidus internus (GPi) is recommended as a promis-
ing technique for the management of the primary generalized dystonia (PGD) with DYT1 gene mutation. We 
present the first report of DBS results in Iranian patients with DYT1 positive PGD. 
Methods: Nine patients who suffered from severely disabling DYT1 positive PGD consecutively were recruit-
ed for the study between 2008 and 2010. The patients underwent bilateral deep brain stimulation of the GPi in a 
single procedure. The mean follow up duration was 8.8 ± 2.2 months. The efficacy of the intervention was eval-
uated by comparing pre-and post operative scores of patients with Burke-Fahn-Marsden's dystonia Scale 
(BFMDS). Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 11.0 software. 
Results: Of 9 patients six were female with the mean age of 15.2 ± 5.5 years old (range: 8-25 years old). The 
mean for Burke-Fahn-Marsden's Dystonia Rating Scale (BFMDRS) score was 47.22 ± 14.1 before surgery and 
12.3 ± 8.2 after follow up, which significantly improved (P=0.0001).The mean stimulation parameters at the last 
visit were at a frequency of 152.2 ± 32.4 Hz (range 130-230 Hz), a voltage of 2.6 ± 0.7 V (range 1.1-4), and a 
pulse width of 60 μsec. No complication was observed during follow up. 
Conclusion: Bilateral DBS of the GPi has an encouraging result for the management of DYT1 positive PGD 
and is recommended as a safe technique for the treatment of these patients. Shorter pulse width in stimulation 
parameters is suggested for DYT1 dystonia patients. </p>

<p>Keywords: Deep brain stimulation, Globus pallidus internus, DYT1 dystonia. </p>

<p>Cite this article as: Miri Sh, Ghoreyshi E, Shahidi Gh. A, Parvaresh M, Rohani M, Saffari M. Deep brain stimulation of globus pallidus </p>

<p>internus for DYT1 positive primary generalized dystonia. Med J Islam Repub Iran 2014 (1 Mar). Vol. 28:18. </p>

<p>Introduction 
Primary generalized dystonia (PGD) is a 
progressive neurological disorder charac-
terized by involuntary, prolonged muscle 
contractions and abnormal twisting pos-
tures in young adults (1). The most frequent 
cause of early onset primary dystonia is an 
autosomal dominant disease due to muta-
tion in DYT1 gene locus on chromosome 
9q34, which encodes for an abnormal torsin 
A protein (2,3).Since pharmacotherapy </p>

<p>usually has a limited efficacy in suppress-
ing the disease progression, surgical ap-
proaches have been considered for the 
treatment of severe forms of PGD (4). Pal-
lidotomy improves the symptoms, but it has 
severe side effects (5). Unilateral pallidot-
omy cannot adequately resolve generalized 
symptoms, and bilateral pallidotomy may 
cause serious complications such as cogni-
tive impairment, dysarthria, dysphagia, and 
limb weakness (5,6). Other surgical tech-</p>

<p>Deep brain stimulation for DYT1 dystonia </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 28.18. 1 Mar 2014 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>nique is a bilateral deep brain stimulation 
(DBS) by implanting electrodes in the Glo-
bus Pallidus Internus (GPi) which is particu-
larly recommended for patients with DYT1-
positive dystonia (4,7). 
The intervention showed encouraging re-
sults in different reports from various coun-
tries (4,8). However, no study in Iran has 
demonstrated the outcome of DBS in pri-
mary generalized dystonia with DYT1 mu-
tation. The present study aimed to evaluate 
the efficacy and safety of the bilateral DBS of 
GPi for the management of 9 Iranian patients 
with advanced DYT1 positive dystonia. </p>

<p>Methods 
Between January 2008 and December 
2010, nine consecutive patients (six fe-
males) who suffered from DYT1 positive 
dystonia underwent bilateral globus palli-
dus internus DBS at the department of Neu-
rosurgery of Rasool-Akram teaching hospi-
tal, Iran University of Medical Sciences, 
Tehran, Iran. The study was approved by the 
ethics committee of the university. All pa-
tients and their families provided written in-
formed consent for the surgical procedure 
and follow up examinations. 
The diagnosis of dystonia was based on 
the Fahn's criteria for PGD by two expert 
neurologists 9). All patients harbored ge-
netically proven DYT1 mutation and their 
neurological examination was normal ex-
cept for dystonia. Brain MRIs were normal 
with no focal lesion and secondary causes 
of dystonia were excluded. Psychiatric dis-
orders and cerebral atrophy were other ex-
clusion criteria. 
The mean for age at surgery was 15.2 ± 
5.5years (range: 8-25 years) and for dura-
tion of the disease 7.3± 5.1 years (range: 1-
17 years). The patients had a disabling form 
of PGD which was refractory to medical 
treatment with anticholinergic medications, 
banzodiazepines, neuroleptics, or baclofen. </p>

<p>Neurological evaluations 
The patients were assessed preoperatively 
and "on" stimulation 6 to 9 months after 
surgery with the Burke-Fahn-Marsden's </p>

<p>dystonia rating scale (BFMDS) by two neu-
rologists expert in movement disorders 
field (6). Higher scores representative of 
higher level of disability. The mean dura-
tion of follow up after surgery was 8.8 ± 
2.2 months (range: 6-12 months). The 
mean for the BFMDS scores were com-
pared preoperatively and postoperatively. 
All evaluations were performed by the 
same neurologist. </p>

<p>Surgical intervention and electrical setting 
All 9 patients underwent implantation for 
bilateral GPi electrodes and implantable 
pulse generator (IPG) in a single session 
under general anesthesia. The stereotactic 
system was Leksell/Lerch in all procedures. 
Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) was 
done for visualization of target location (the 
posteroventral part of the GPi) before sur-
gery and confirmation of the electrode posi-
tion postoperatively. Then the electrodes 
were connected to subcutaneous IPG within 
the chest or abdomen. Surgeries had been 
performed by the same neurosurgical group. 
The IPGs were programmed 2 weeks af-
ter surgery in monopolar mode. The initial 
electrical variables were as follow: fre-
quency 130 Hz; pulse width 60μs; and am-
plitude 2 V. In each GPi the dippest elec-
trode was turned on. In order to optimize 
the settings, variables were gradually 
changed according to clinical response at 
the follow up visits. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
The mean and standard deviation of pa-
tient's age, disease and follow up duration, 
in addition to pre-and post-operative 
BFMDS scores were calculated. According 
to the normal distribution of data, the 
paired t-test was used to compare changes 
of the BFMDS before and after surgery. 
We correlated post-operative BFMDRS 
with patients' age, disease duration, age at 
the time of surgery and pre-operative 
BFMDRS.A probability value less than 0.05 
was considered to be significant. The <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
software <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 11.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">(SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA)</rs>) was used for the statistical analysis. </p>

<p>S. Miri, et al. </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 28.18. 1 Mar 2014 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>Results 
Demographic characteristics of the pa-
tients are shown in Table 1. 
Severe disabilities were observed in all 
patients before surgery. However, the pa-
tient's posture, dystonic movements, and 
motor function considerably improved after 
DBS -GPi. The BFMDRS movement score 
significantly improved from 42.2±14.1 
(range 20 to 70) before surgery to 12.3 ± 
8.2 (range 3 to 28) after surgery (mean fol-
low up: 8.8 ± 2.2 months) (p=0.0001). The 
patients showed a considerable reduction of 
74.4% ± 13.5% (range 56 to 92%) in their 
BFMDRS score. 
The percentage of BFMDRS score im-
provement was not significantly correlated 
with the age of the disease onset, the dura-
tion of symptoms (between onset and sur-
gery), age at the time of surgery, and pre-
operative BFMDRS scores (p&gt;0.05). 
The mean stimulation parameters at the 
last visit were at frequency of 152.2 ± 32.4 
Hz (range 130-230 Hz), a voltage of 2.6 ± 
0.7 V (range 1.1-4), and a pulse width of 
60μsec which all adjusted to the patient's 
clinical response. The most common used 
electrodes (contacts) in the patients were 
0/1 (left) and 4/5 (right). 
No complication was observed in the pa-
tients. Neurological deficits, infection, or sys-
tem malfunctions did not occur in patients. </p>

<p>Discussion 
Medically refractory dystonia patients, 
who suffer from severe disabilities, are 
considered for surgical treatment. The DBS 
of basal ganglia is an appropriate surgical 
technique for treatment of these patients 
(10). Efficacy of DBS with globus pallidus 
internus targeting in primary dystonic pa-
tients was shown first in 1999 (11). Stimu-
lation of GPi showed favorable results, es-
pecially in patients with DYT1 mutation 
(10). 
In a recent study, Markun et al. reported 
the rate of improvement in BFMDRS 
movement scores as much as 61.5% at 1 
year after surgery, 64.4% two years, and 
70.3% at the mean follow up of 32 months 
12).These results were similar to other 
study by Isaias et al. in 32 patients with 
PGD 13). In the study of Borggrafe et al. 
movement score of BFMDRS in PGD pa-
tients was 56.9 ± 22.7 before bilateral DBS 
-GPi and it improved to 23.7 ± 23.2 over a 
mean period of 13 months after surgery 
(14). It has been mentioned that among the 
studied patients, those with DYT1 mutation 
had higher rate of improvement (77% vs. 
44%, respectively) (14). Another study by 
Cif et al. represented marked improvement 
in motor score of BFMDRS postoperatively 
up to 10 years after surgery (57.5 ± 23.9 vs. 
23.3 ± 19.2). However, presence of new 
signs and recurrence of previous signs were </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographics and clinical characteristics of the patients. </p>

<p>Patient's 
Number 
Sex 
FH 
Age at 
onset 
(years) </p>

<p>Onset 
location 
Disease 
duration 
(years) </p>

<p>Drug 
hx 
Age at 
surgery 
(years) </p>

<p>F/u 
(mo 
) </p>

<p>BFMDS 
score 
before </p>

<p>BFMDS 
score 
after 
Case 1 
F 
-
7 
Lt up ex 
4 
A.ch 
11 
12 
41 
3 
Case 2 
F 
-
9 
Rt Lo ex 
7 
A.ch+ 
Bz 
16 
9 
50 
8 </p>

<p>Case 3 
M 
+ 
8 
Rt up ex 
7 
A.ch+ 
Bz 
25 
6 
70 
13 </p>

<p>Case 4 
F 
-
7 
Lt up ex 
4 
A.ch+ 
A.ep 
11 
6 
44 
5 </p>

<p>Case 5 
M 
-
7 
Trunk 
1 
A.ch+ 
A.ep 
8 
6 
64 
28 </p>

<p>Case 6 
F 
-
7 
Rt lo ex 
7 
-
14 
11 
44 
14 
Case 7 
M 
-
9 
Rt up ex 
3 
A.ch 
12 
8 
46 
20 
Case 8 
F 
+ 
8 
Rt up ex 
11 
A.ch 
19 
11 
20 
4 
Case 9 
f 
+ 
9 
Rt up ex 
12 
A.ch 
21 
11 
46 
16 
F, female; M, male; FH, family history; Mo, months; F/U, follow up; Rt up ex, right upper extremity; Lt up ex, left up-
per extremity; Rt Lo ex, Right lower extremity; Lt Lo ex, Left lower extremity; Drug hx, Drug history; A.ch, anticholin-
ergics; Bz, benzodiazepines; A.ep, anti epileptics; BFMDS, Burke-Fahn-Marsden's dystonia Scale. </p>

<p>Deep brain stimulation for DYT1 dystonia </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 28.18. 1 Mar 2014 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>also reported in the study (15). Additional-
ly, in Alcindor et al. report for a patient with 
DYT1 positive PGD who underwent DBS -
GPi, after a 10-year follow up was fully in-
dependent and had an active life style (2). 
In accordance with findings of previous 
studies, our study indicates promising re-
sults of bilateral DBS -GPi in symptoms 
improvement of DYT1 positive patients 
with primary generalized dystonia during a 
period of 6 to 12 months after surgery. Our 
patients showed 75% reduction in their 
BFMDRS score. 
We did not include DYT1 negative pa-
tients with primary generalized dystonia in 
the present study. Thus we could not judge 
about the superiority of DBS-GPi in DYT1 
positive patients compare to other PGD pa-
tients. Nevertheless, findings of the men-
tioned studies propose that evaluating PGD 
patients for DYT1 mutation can help pre-
dicting outcome of DBS at consultation be-
fore surgery. There are few studies that re-
ject this assumption. For example, accord-
ing to Coubes and his colleagues, DYT1 
positive and negative patients have no sig-
nificant differences in functional and clini-
cal improvement after DBS procedure (4). 
Despite the finding of the later study, ge-
netic assessment of PGD patients for DYT1 
mutation still seems a valuable diagnostic 
criteria. 
Markun et al. suggested that shorter dura-
tion of the disease is another predictor of 
long-term BFMDRS scores improvement 
after DBS procedure (12). Furthermore, 
minor motor impairment before surgery is 
introduced as a predictor for better im-
provement after surgery (14). However, our 
results did not establish any of these corre-
lations which could be due to limitation in 
number of subjects. 
Although DBS is a very effective treat-
ment for DYT1 positive dystonia patients, 
response of cases to the intervention is var-
iable 12). Accordingly, we observed a wide 
range of responses. Improvement in BFM 
scores was between 50% and 92%. This 
diversity also was observed in the previous 
studies (2,16,17).This difference could be </p>

<p>due to patient's genetic diversity and heter-
ogeneity or various motor anomalies in pa-
tients 16). 
According to the results of the Moro's 
study, higher frequency of stimulation leads 
to better clinical improvement in pallidal 
stimulation for dystonia (18). A frequency 
of 130 Hz is associated with the best clini-
cal improvement in the patients. Higher 
voltage is also related to significant im-
provement of clinical symptoms (18). 
However, due to the risk of delivering ex-
cessive charge to the brain and decreasing 
battery life, voltage may have gradual de-
cline (19). Most of recent studies used 
stimulation frequencies of 100 to 185 Hz 
(5,15,19). In our study, frequency and am-
plitude setting was similar to other studies. 
Although it has been reported that in-
creasing pulse width had no significant ef-
fect on clinical improvement (18), most of 
studies implanted long pulse duration (120 
to 450 μsec) (10,19). Among stimulation 
parameters, the pulse width setting in our 
patients was unique and considerably 
shorter than similar studies. The pulse 
width equal to 60 μsec besides a high fre-
quency (150 Hz) had a reasonable clinical 
response in the patients. This setting has at 
least two prominent advantages for the pa-
tients: shorter pulse width could extend bat-
tery life and it may decrease the side ef-
fects. Regarding the tolerability of the set-
ting and good clinical response in the pa-
tients, it is advisable to use pulse width of 
60 μsec in DYT1 positive dytonia patients. 
Similar to other studies, we used deepest 
electrodes more commonly in our patients 
(15,18,19). 
Adverse events may occur after the DBS 
procedure. The rate of complications is dif-
ferent in various studies. In Borggrafe's 
study, adverse events occurred in 50% of 
patients and 13% of them underwent anoth-
er surgery (14). Cubes reported one case of 
delayed unilateral infection of IPG after 
DBS which leaded to system removal (4). 
Hardware malfunction, including extension 
of cable disconnection and early IPG dys-
function, in addition to hardware infection </p>

<p>S. Miri, et al. </p>



<p>MJIRI, Vol. 28.18. 1 Mar 2014 </p>

<p>http://mjiri.iums.ac.ir </p>

<p>were also observed in another study (15). 
Nonetheless, increasing rigidity, more 
cramping and development of diaphoresis 
were reported 4 years after DBS which led 
to revision of surgery to resolve symptoms 
(2). Despite these findings, we observed no 
complication among our study subjects. 
One probable cause of this difference could 
be our short term follow up of patients. 
This was a limitation in the present study 
which also made the durability of response 
to DBS in our DYT1 patients unclear. 
However, initial therapeutic response was 
favorable. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
DBS -GPi for DYT1 positive dystonia is 
a highly effective treatment with rapid re-
sponse and infrequent complications. Using 
shorter pulse width in stimulation setting 
may suggested for DYT1 dystonia patients. 
Further studies on factors relating to better 
response and higher improvement rate 
among these patients is needed. </p>



</text></tei>