<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4153088" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Several individual components of the Mediterranean diet have been shown to offer protection against prostate cancer. The present study is the first to 
investigate the association between adherence to the Mediterranean diet and the relative risk of prostate cancer. We also explored the usefulness of the 
Mediterranean Diet Score (MDS) in a non-Mediterranean population. FFQ data were obtained from 1482 incident prostate cancer patients and 1108 popu-
lation-based controls in the Cancer of the Prostate in Sweden (CAPS) study. We defined five MDS variants with different components or using either 
study-specific intakes or intakes in a Greek reference population as cut-off values between low and high intake of each component. Unconditional logistic 
regression was used to estimate the relative risk of prostate cancer for high and medium v. low MDS, as well as potential associations with the individual 
score components. No statistically significant association was found between adherence to the Mediterranean diet based on any of the MDS variants and 
prostate cancer risk (OR range: 0·96-1·19 for total prostate cancer, comparing high with low adherence). Overall, we found little support for an association 
between the Mediterranean diet and prostate cancer in this Northern European study population. Despite potential limitations inherent in the study or in 
the build-up of a dietary score, we suggest that the original MDS with study-specific median intakes as cut-off values between low and high intake is useful 
in assessing the adherence to the Mediterranean diet in non-Mediterranean populations. </p>

<p>Crete and other parts of Greece, southern Italy and Spain, in 
the period before the 1960s. The general features of this diet 
are high intake of vegetables, fruits, nuts, beans, cereals and 
lean fish, together with high consumption of olive oil, moderate 
consumption of alcohol (especially wine with meals) and low 
amounts of milk and red meat. Several of these individual 
food items, or the nutrients they contain, have been associated 
with a reduced risk of prostate cancer </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>. Based on previous 
knowledge about the effect of Mediterranean dietary com-
ponents, Trichopoulou et al. 
(5) estimated that shifting to a tra-
ditional Mediterranean diet could prevent up to 10 % of the 
prostate cancer cases in Western high-income countries. 
Several dietary scores have been developed to assess adher-
ence to the Mediterranean diet </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>. In 1995, Trichopoulou 
et al. 
(7) developed the Mediterranean Diet Score (MDS) based 
on eight dietary components: the intake of vegetables, fruits 
and nuts, legumes, cereals, meat, dairy products and alcohol, 
as well as the ratio of MUFA to SFA. Fish was added as a 
ninth component in 2003 </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>. The MDS and several modified ver-
sions have been used in epidemiological studies of various health 
outcomes, both in Mediterranean and non-Mediterranean popu-
lations </p>

<p>(6,9,10) </p>

<p>. An important component of the traditional 
Mediterranean diet is olive oil, resulting in a high ratio of 
MUFA to SFA. Outside the Mediterranean region olive oil is 
consumed less frequently, and the intake of MUFA is not only 
considerably lower, but mainly originates from a higher meat 
intake rather than from vegetable oils. In an attempt to adapt 
the MDS for use in non-Mediterranean populations, the fat 
ratio component has been modified so as to include both 
MUFA and PUFA in the numerator </p>

<p>(11,12) </p>

<p>. Moreover, the cut-off 
value between high and low intake for each MDS component is 
the median intake in the population under study. However, using 
the median intake in a non-Mediterranean study population may 
be questionable, as the intake of certain components may be 
much lower or higher than that in a typical Mediterranean popu-
lation. Thus the score may be less able to discriminate between 
intake levels that are beneficial or non-beneficial to health. 
In the present study, we investigated the association between 
the Mediterranean diet and the relative risk of prostate cancer 
in a Swedish population. In order to examine the potential 
effect of using study-specific median intakes in a 
non-Mediterranean population as cut-off values in the MDS, 
we developed several variants of the score using both intakes 
in the Swedish study population and in a Greek reference 
population 
(8) as cut-off values. We also created an alternative 
score that more closely reflects the traditional Mediterranean 
diet, directed towards its most beneficial components. 
Furthermore, we explored the potential effect measure modi-
fication by selected covariates. To the best of our knowledge, 
this is the first study specifically investigating prostate cancer 
risk and the Mediterranean diet using a dietary score. </p>

<p>Experimental methods </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>The Cancer of the Prostate in Sweden (CAPS) study is a 
population-based case-control study on prostate cancer and </p>

<p>has been described in detail previously </p>

<p>(13-15) </p>

<p>. Briefly, incident 
and histologically confirmed prostate cancer cases were ident-
ified from four of the six regional cancer registries in Sweden 
and were invited to take part in the study. Cases were 35-79 
years old at enrolment, from January 2001 to September 
2002, and lived in the central and northern parts of Sweden. 
For 95 % of the cases, clinical data were obtained from the 
National Prostate Cancer Registry. Advanced cases were 
defined as those meeting at least one of the following criteria: 
tumour, nodes, metastasis stage T3/T4 or N1 or M1; Gleason 
score 8-10; or serum prostate-specific antigen level at diagno-
sis ≥100 ng/ml. Localised cases were defined as those with 
T1/T2, N0, M0, Gleason score 2-6 and prostate-specific anti-
gen &lt;20 ng/ml. Cases with Gleason score 7 who did not meet 
the criteria for advanced disease were included in neither 
advanced nor localised cases due to the difference in aggres-
siveness seen for Gleason 3 + 4 compared with Gleason 
4 + 3 </p>

<p>(16) </p>

<p>. Controls were selected randomly from the Swedish 
Population Registry every 6 months, being frequency-matched 
to cases by age in 5-year categories and region of residence. 
Invitations to participate were sent out to eligible controls 
about once a month, except July and August, to reflect the 
continuous enrolment of cases. 
All study participants were asked to complete a baseline 
questionnaire. The number of cases filling in the questionnaire 
was 1499 (79 %) out of 1895 invited and the corresponding 
number for controls was 1130 (67 %) out of 1684 invited. 
The average time between diagnosis and sending out the ques-
tionnaire was 5 months. The study was performed according 
to the guidelines laid down in the Declaration of Helsinki 
and was approved by the ethics committees at Karolinska 
Institutet and Umeå University in Sweden. Written informed 
consent was obtained from all participants. </p>

<p>Exposure assessment </p>

<p>Usual dietary intake over the past year was assessed using a 
semi-quantitative FFQ with 106 items, including foods, bev-
erages and alcohol, and with three additional questions on 
dietary fat, including a question on regular use of olive oil 
for cooking and/or in dressings (yes/no) </p>

<p>(13,14,17,18) </p>

<p>. The intake 
of several food items assessed with a shorter version of the 
FFQ has been validated against four 7 d weighed food records 
in 111 randomly sampled Swedish women, giving Spearman 
correlation coefficients in the range 0·16-0·82 (e.g. 0·30-
0·37 for vegetables/tomatoes, 0·38-0·49 for fruit/fruit juice, 
0·16-0·61 for refined grains/whole grains/cereals, 0·44 for 
fish, 0·44 for dairy products, 0·37-0·60 for meat/poultry 
and 0·56-0·82 for alcoholic beverages) </p>

<p>(19) </p>

<p>. Although the vali-
dation was performed in women, the results are likely to be 
similar in men </p>

<p>(20,21) </p>

<p>. The intake of nutrients has been validated 
against fourteen repeated 24-h recall interviews in 248 ran-
domly sampled Swedish men, showing Spearman correlation 
coefficients in the range 0·25-0·81 (e.g. 0·75 for SFA, 0·66 
for MUFA, 0·49 for PUFA and 0·81 for ethanol) 
(22) . The 
energy intake assessed by the FFQ was within 8 % of the esti-
mated intake from the 24 h recalls in the same validation 
study. To calculate nutrient and energy intakes, we created </p>



<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>aggregated codes corresponding to 253 food and beverage 
items, and linked the dietary data from the questionnaire to 
the Swedish National Food Administration database </p>

<p>(23) </p>

<p>, com-
prising about 1500 food products. 
The questionnaire also contained questions regarding known 
and potential lifestyle risk factors for prostate cancer, such as 
physical activity, tobacco use, height, weight, education, occu-
pation, marital status, history of diabetes and family history 
of cancer (prostate or other). The questions on physical activity 
included occupational activity, walking/bicycling, exercise and 
household/leisure-time activity at age 15, 30, 50 and 65 
years. They have been validated against two 7 d activity diaries 
in 111 men (Spearman correlation r 0·56) </p>

<p>(24) </p>

<p>. Physical activity 
level was calculated as metabolic equivalent by multiplying 
the reported time in h/d for each activity by the assigned meta-
bolic equivalent value, given in appendix 1 of the publication by 
Norman et al. </p>

<p>(24) </p>

<p>. Only activities of moderate or vigorous inten-
sity (metabolic equivalent ≥3) were used </p>

<p>(25) </p>

<p>. We calculated the 
lifetime physical activity by taking the mean value over all ages. </p>

<p>The Mediterranean Diet Score </p>

<p>We created five variants of the MDS originally developed by 
Trichopoulou et al. </p>

<p>(7,8) </p>

<p>, as listed in Table 1. The main score, 
denoted as MDS-gram, is based on nine components: a high 
ratio of MUFA and PUFA to SFA (MP:S); high vegetable 
intake (including tomato juice, ketchup and root vegetables, 
except potatoes); high intake of fruit, nuts and seeds; high 
legume intake; high cereal intake; high fish and seafood intake; 
low intake of dairy products; low intake of meat and meat pro-
ducts (including poultry); and moderate alcohol intake. 
Frequencies of intake from the questionnaire were translated 
into intakes in g/d using standard portion sizes </p>

<p>(26) </p>

<p>. All intakes 
were energy-adjusted by dividing the actual food intake by the 
individual's total energy intake and multiplying by 10 460 kJ 
(equivalent to 2500 kcal) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>. A score of zero or one was 
assigned to each component using the median intake among 
the controls in g/d as cut-off between low and high intake. 
For beneficial components (the first six listed previously), 
one point was given for intakes at or above the median and 
zero points otherwise. For the milk and meat components, 
one point was given for intakes below the median and zero 
points otherwise. For alcohol (ethanol), one point was given 
for intakes above zero and below the median intake, and zero 
points otherwise. A total score ranging from zero to nine points 
was calculated by summing up the scores of the individual com-
ponents. The total score was then categorised into low (zero to 
three points), medium (four to five points) or high (six to nine 
points) adherence to the Mediterranean diet based on the 
approximate tertile distribution among the controls. 
A total of three score variants were created based on the 
same components as MDS-gram, but with different cut-off 
values between low and high intake of each component. In 
MDS-serv, we used the study-specific median intakes 
(among the controls) expressed as servings/week instead of 
g/d as cut-off values, assuming that one serving of a food 
item has the same impact no matter the serving size. In 
MDS-cent, the study-specific twenty-fifth or seventy-fifth </p>

<p>Table 1. 
Description of the Mediterranean Diet Score (MDS) variants </p>

<p>Score </p>

<p>Unit </p>

<p>Cut-off values </p>

<p>MP:S ratio </p>

<p>Vegetables* </p>

<p>Fruits 
Nuts Legumes </p>

<p>Cereals </p>

<p>Fish † </p>

<p>Dairy 
products </p>

<p>Meat/meat 
products ‡ </p>

<p>Ethanol </p>

<p>Total 
score </p>

<p>MDS-gram </p>

<p>g/d 
Median in CAPS </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>+Nuts/seeds </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>&gt;0, &lt;median </p>

<p>0-9 </p>

<p>MDS-serv </p>

<p>serv/ 
w 
Median in CAPS </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>+Nuts/seeds </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>&gt;0, &lt;median </p>

<p>0-9 </p>

<p>MDS-cent </p>

<p>g/d </p>

<p>Twenty-fifth/ 
seventy-fifth </p>

<p>centile in CAPS § </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>+Nuts/seeds </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x 
&gt;0, &lt;seventy-fifth 
centile </p>

<p>0-9 </p>

<p>MDS-greek </p>

<p>g/d 
Median in Greek 
population </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>+Nuts/seeds </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>10 to &lt;50 g/d </p>

<p>0-9 </p>

<p>MDS-alt </p>

<p>g/d 
Median in CAPS </p>

<p>Olive oil use </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x ¶ </p>

<p>x 
Whole grains </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Red/processed </p>

<p>meat </p>

<p>Red wine: &gt;0, 
&lt;median ¶ </p>

<p>0-10 </p>

<p>MP:S ratio, ratio of MUFA and PUFA to SFA; CAPS, Cancer of the Prostate in Sweden study; serv/w, servings per week; alt, alternative. </p>

<p>* Includes vegetables, tomato juice, ketchup and root vegetables, except potatoes. Potatoes were not included among either vegetables or cereals, as consistent with the original score. However, including them in either of these groups did not 
change the results significantly. </p>

<p> † Includes caviar and seafood. 
 ‡ Includes poultry. 
 § The twenty-fifth centile was used for the intake of legumes, cereals, fish, milk and meat, and the seventy-fifth centile for the MP:S ratio and the intake of vegetables, fruits/nuts and ethanol. 
║Trichopoulou et al. </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p> ¶ The seventy-fifth centile was used as the cut-off value since the median intake was zero. </p>



<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>centiles of the intake (in g/d) were used as cut-off values instead 
of the median intake; the centile level for each component was 
chosen so as to achieve cut-off values that were close to the 
median intakes in the Greek reference population, while main-
taining a sufficient number of participants in the extreme 
groups. In MDS-greek, the median intakes (in g/d) in the afore-
mentioned Greek reference population were used as cut-off 
values; however, for vegetable and fruit/nut intake we used 
the ninetieth centile of the intake in the CAPS population 
since very few participants reached the Greek median intake 
levels. MDS-serv and MDS-cent were categorised using the 
same adherence cut-off values as MDS-gram, whereas MDS-
greek was categorised as low (zero to two points), medium 
(three to four points), or high (five to nine points) adherence. 
Lastly, we created an alternative score, denoted as MDS-alt, 
with a focus on the most 'traditional' components of the 
Mediterranean diet. This score was based on ten components, 
basically the same as in the other score variants except that the 
fat ratio was replaced by olive oil use, cereals by whole grains, 
meat by red/processed meat, ethanol by red wine and fruits 
and nuts/seeds were separated into two components. Similar 
variants of the MDS have been used in other studies 
(27-30) . 
Olive oil use was added as a separate component since it 
was not included in the nutrient calculations for fat, due to 
the design of the questionnaire in the CAPS study (yes/no, 
no frequency reported). The study-specific median intake in 
g/d was used as the cut-off between low and high intake of 
each component. The total MDS-alt ranging from zero to 
ten points was categorised into low (zero to three points), 
medium (four to five points) or high (six to ten points) adher-
ence to the Mediterranean diet. </p>

<p>Statistical methods </p>

<p>We excluded men with incomplete dietary data (n 67) or unrea-
sonably high or low energy intakes (&lt;3300 kJ/d or &gt;21 000 
kJ/d) (n 27). In total, 2590 participants (1482 cases and 
1108 controls) were included in the final analyses. Baseline 
characteristics of cases and controls were compared using 
the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney test for continuous variables 
and the χ 
2 test for categorical variables. Correlations between 
the continuous MDS variants and their components were eval-
uated by estimating Spearman correlation coefficients. 
Unconditional logistic regression was used to generate OR 
with 95 % CI, as estimates of the relative risk of prostate can-
cer according to adherence to the Mediterranean diet. 
Adherence to each MDS variant was analysed using indicator 
variables for low, medium and high score, with low as the 
reference group. Additionally, the scores were modelled as 
continuous variables, firstly by assessing the linear effect of a 
one-point increment in the score on prostate cancer risk and 
secondly by fitting restricted cubic splines to relax the linear 
assumption and to create smoothed functions of adherence 
to the scores. Moreover, we evaluated the individual effects 
of each MDS component. All analyses were performed for 
total prostate cancer, for advanced (n 588) and localised 
(n 512) disease, as well as for Gleason score 7 disease subtype 
(n 218). </p>

<p>Simple regression models included the matching factors: age 
and region of residence. Multivariate regression models 
additionally included education, smoking, BMI, energy intake, 
physical activity, history of diabetes and family history of 
prostate cancer. Potential confounders were selected based 
on subject matter knowledge as well as on indications pro-
vided by purely statistical procedures, such as a change in 
β-coefficients (&gt;10 %). Other covariates that were considered 
as potential confounders but not included in the final model 
were height, employment status, marital status, snuff use, 
use of dietary supplements, use of olive oil and intake of cof-
fee, phyto-oestrogens, potatoes, sweet foods and non-alcoholic 
beverages. The potential effect measure modification by 
selected covariates (age, family history of prostate cancer, his-
tory of diabetes and BMI) was evaluated in two ways: formal 
interaction tests by including multiplicative interaction terms in 
logistic regression models, and by the use of interaction indi-
cator variables to obtain a stratified effect. 
Wald and likelihood ratio tests were used to assess the stat-
istical significance of observed associations (P &lt; 0·05, two-
sided tests). The fit of the models was evaluated by the 
Hosmer-Lemeshow and the Pearson χ 
2 goodness-of-fit 
tests. All analyses were performed using the statistical software 
systems <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute Inc.</rs>.) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 12</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">StataCorp LP</rs>). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The study population is described in Table 2. The cases were 
somewhat younger than the controls and were more likely to 
reside in the northern part of Sweden, to be employed, 
to take dietary supplements and to have a family history of 
prostate cancer. Cases and controls also differed with regard 
to their intake of total energy, alcohol, non-alcoholic bev-
erages, tomatoes and sweet foods, but there were no major 
differences concerning BMI, level of education, marital status, 
smoking status, physical activity, coffee intake or potato intake. 
The differences observed for the matching factors age and 
region of residence may be explained by the lower participation 
rate among controls than among cases, and was apparent already 
before exclusion of participants (n 94) (results not shown). 
The mean total score of each of the five MDS variants, as 
well as the distribution between the three adherence groups, is 
given in Table 3. The results were in general similar for cases 
and controls, except for a slightly higher mean of MDS-serv, 
MDS-cent and MDS-alt among the cases. The mean total 
score of MDS-gram was 4·4 (SD 1·7) among both cases and 
controls: 31 % of cases and 33 % of controls had low adher-
ence, 42 % of cases and 40 % of controls had medium adher-
ence and 27 % of both cases and controls had high adherence. 
Table 4 presents the intake levels of the MDS components 
and of the total energy, macronutrients and selected food 
items, in the CAPS population as well as in the Greek refer-
ence population. The intake of vegetables and fruits was con-
siderably lower in the Swedish population, whereas the intake 
of legumes, cereals, fish and dairy products was higher than 
that in the Greek population. The intake of meat was similar 
in both populations. As expected, the MP:S ratio in the </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>Table 2. Characteristics of the cases and controls in the Cancer of the Prostate in Sweden (CAPS) study </p>

<p>Cases (n 1482) 
Controls (n 1108) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
n 
% † 
n 
% † 
P* </p>

<p>Age (years) 
&lt;0·01 
Mean 
66·8 
6 7 ·7 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>7·3 
7 ·5 
Region of residence 
&lt;0·01 
Northern Sweden 
455 
31 
197 
18 
Central Sweden 
1027 
69 
911 
82 
Education level 
0·15 
0-9 years 
675 
46 
506 
46 
10-12 years 
595 
40 
468 
42 
≥13 years 
207 
14 
127 
11 
Marital status 
0·25 
Married/partner 
1200 
81 
867 
78 
Divorced/unmarried 
204 
14 
165 
15 
Widower 
77 
5 
71 
6 
History of diabetes 
0·62 
Yes 
171 
12 
134 
12 
No 
1292 
87 
953 
86 
Family history of prostate cancer 
&lt;0·01 
Yes 
273 
18 
103 
9 
No 
1209 
82 
1005 
91 
Smoking 
0·44 
Never smoker 
575 
39 
424 
38 
Former smoker 
734 
49 
535 
48 
Current smoker 
156 
11 
134 
12 
Dietary supplement use 
&lt;0·01 
Yes 
702 
47 
437 
39 
No 
737 
50 
623 
56 
BMI at inclusion (kg/m 
2 ) 
0·44 
&lt;25 
574 
39 
400 
36 
25 to &lt;30 
686 
46 
526 
47 
≥30 
177 
12 
141 
13 
Physical activity (MET-h/d) ‡ 
0·94 
Mean 
12·7 
1 2 ·8 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>8·9 
9 ·1 
Total energy intake (kJ/d) 
&lt;0·01 
Mean 
9583·5 
9303·9 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>2670·2 
2721·1 
Alcohol intake (g/d) 
&lt;0·01 
Mean 
8·2 
8 ·0 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>16·8 
1 9 ·9 
Non-alcoholic beverage intake (servings/d) 
&lt;0·01 
Mean 
1·0 
0 ·9 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>1·2 
1 ·2 
Coffee intake (cups/d) 
0·67 
Mean 
3·1 
3 ·1 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>1·9 
2 ·0 
Tomato intake (servings/d) 
&lt;0·01 
Mean 
0·4 
0 ·4 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>0·3 
0 ·3 
Potato intake (servings/d) 
0·19 
Mean 
0·5 
0 ·5 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>0·3 
0 ·3 
Sweet foods intake (servings/d) § 
&lt;0·01 
Mean 
0·8 
0 ·8 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>0·5 
0 ·5 
Disease characteristics among cases (% of all cases) 
-
Advanced 
588 
40 
-
-
Localised ¶ 
512 
34 
-
-
Gleason score 7 
218 
15 
-
-
Unknown 
87 
6 
-
-
Other 
77 
5 
-
-
Gleason score 
-
Mean 
6·5 
-</p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>1·2 
-</p>

<p>Continued </p>



<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>Swedish population was lower than the MUFA:SFA ratio in 
the Greek population. The intake of SFA was similar in 
both populations, whereas the intake of MUFA and PUFA, 
as well as the total energy, was lower in the Swedish popu-
lation. The Swedish population ate more potatoes and sweet </p>

<p>foods but drank less non-alcoholic beverages than the Greek 
population. The correlation between individual components 
and the main score, MDS-gram, was low to moderate, ranging 
from r s 0·07 for ethanol to r s 0·58 for vegetables. Similarly, the 
individual components of the alternative score, MDS-alt, were 
weakly or moderately correlated with the total score (range r s 
0·05-0·46). Inter-correlation between the individual com-
ponents was in the range r s 0·02-0·40 (results not shown). 
The correlation coefficients between the MDS variants ranged 
from 0·43 between MDS-serv and MDS-greek, to 0·79 
between MDS-gram and MDS-serv and between MDS-gram 
and MDS-alt, respectively (results not shown). 
As shown in Fig. 1, no statistically significant association 
was found between any of the MDS variants and prostate can-
cer. However, high MDS-cent, MDS-greek and MDS-alt 
scores seemed to be associated with a 20-35 % increased rela-
tive risk of advanced prostate cancer, compared with low 
scores, and a somewhat weaker increased risk of total prostate 
cancer. However, the estimates were not statistically significant 
and the CI were wide. For cases with Gleason score 7, a non-
statistically significant inverse association was seen for high v. 
low MDS-gram and MDS-serv (multivariate OR were 0·84, 
95 % CI 0·59, 1·19; and 0·77, 95 % CI 0·55, 1·09, respectively; 
results not shown). No association was seen between Gleason 
score 7 disease subtype and any of the other MDS-variants. 
There was no evidence of an association between the continu-
ous scores and prostate cancer, in neither logistic regression 
models nor restricted cubic spline regression models, except 
for a non-significant positive association between the total 
prostate cancer and MDS-cent (results not shown). 
Among the individual score components, a high vegetable 
intake was associated with an increased risk of prostate cancer, 
with multivariate OR 1·25 (95 % CI 1·05, 1·50; P trend = 0·01) 
for total prostate cancer, 1·37 (95 % CI 1·09, 1·72; P trend = 
0·006) for advanced disease and 1·25 (95 % CI 0·98, 1·60; 
P trend = 0·07) for localised disease (results not shown). In sup-
plementary analyses, the positive association remained but was 
weakened when tomatoes were excluded from vegetable 
intake, and a high intake of tomato products was found to 
be positively associated with localised disease (multivariate 
OR 1·25; 95 % CI 0·99, 1·59; P trend = 0·07) compared with 
low intake. A high ethanol intake was associated with an 
increased risk of advanced prostate cancer (multivariate OR 
1·25; 95 % CI 0·99, 1·58; P trend = 0·06). Simple models </p>

<p>Table 2. Continued </p>

<p>Cases (n 1482) 
Controls (n 1108) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
n 
% † 
n 
% † 
P* </p>

<p>PSA level (ng/ml) 
-
Mean 
88·4 
-</p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>360·4 
-</p>

<p>MET, metabolic equivalent; PSA, prostate-specific antigen. 
* Two-sided P values estimated using the χ 
2 test for categorical variables and the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney test for continuous variables. 
 † Percentage of all cases and of all controls, respectively. Column percentages do not always add up to 100 due to missing data. 
 ‡ Activity of at least moderate intensity (MET ≥ 3). 
 § Includes confectionery, sweet bakery products and ice cream. 
║ Meeting at least one of the following criteria: tumour stage T3/T4 or N1 or M1; or Gleason score 8-10; or PSA ≥ 100 ng/ml. 
 ¶ Meeting all of the following criteria: tumour stage T1/T2, N0, M0, Gleason score 2-6 and PSA &lt; 20 ng/ml. </p>

<p>Table 3. Adherence to the Mediterranean Diet Score (MDS) variants in 
cases and controls in the Cancer of the Prostate in Sweden (CAPS) study* 
(Mean values and standard deviations; number of participants and 
percentages) </p>

<p>Cases 
(n 1482) </p>

<p>Controls 
(n 1108) </p>

<p>Characteristics 
n 
% † 
n 
% † </p>

<p>MDS-gram (points) 
Mean 
4·4 
4 ·4 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>1·7 
1 ·7 
MDS-serv (points) 
Mean 
4·4 
4 ·3 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>1·7 
1 ·7 
MDS-cent (points) 
Mean 
4·2 
4 ·1 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>1·5 
1 ·5 
MDS-greek (points) 
Mean 
3·3 
3 ·3 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>1·2 
1 ·1 
MDS-alt (points) 
Mean 
4·6 
4 ·5 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>1·9 
1 ·9 
Adherence to MDS-gram 
Low (0-3 points) 
460 
31 
360 
33 
Medium (4-5 points) 
621 
42 
445 
40 
High (6-9 points) 
401 
27 
303 
27 
Adherence to MDS-serv 
Low (0-3 points) 
482 
33 
359 
32 
Medium (4-5 points) 
600 
40 
456 
41 
High (6-9 points) 
400 
27 
293 
27 
Adherence to MDS-cent 
Low (0-3 points) 
493 
33 
387 
35 
Medium (4-5 points) 
723 
49 
517 
47 
High (6-9 points) 
266 
18 
204 
18 
Adherence to MDS-greek 
Low (0-2 points) 
339 
23 
262 
24 
Medium (3-4 points) 
939 
63 
703 
63 
High (5-9 points) 
204 
14 
143 
13 
Adherence to MDS-alt 
Low (0-3 points) 
449 
30 
367 
33 
Medium (4-5 points) 
524 
36 
405 
37 
High (6-10 points) 
509 
34 
336 
30 </p>

<p>* For details of the MDS variants, see Table 1. 
 † Percentage of all cases and of all controls, respectively. </p>



<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>Table 4. 
Summary statistics of the intake of the components of the Mediterranean Diet Score (MDS) variants, of the intake of energy, macronutrients and selected food items, and their correlation with the total score, </p>

<p>for the controls of the Cancer of the Prostate in Sweden (CAPS) study and for the male study population in the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC) in Greece 
(Twenty-fifth centiles; median values; mean values and standard deviations; seventy-fifth centiles; Spearman correlation coefficients) </p>

<p>CAPS* (n 1108 controls) </p>

<p>EPIC 
-Greece † (n 8895 men) </p>

<p>Twenty-fifth centile </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>Seventy-fifth centile </p>

<p>Spearman </p>

<p>r 
s  ‡ </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>Components in MDS-gram, MDS-serv, MDS-cent and MDS-greek </p>

<p>Components of the original MDS † </p>

<p>Ratio of MUFA and PUFA to SFA </p>

<p>1·0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>·3 </p>

<p>1 
·4 </p>

<p>0 
·5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>·7 </p>

<p>0 
·49 
Ratio of MUFA to SFA </p>

<p>1·7 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>·8 </p>

<p>0 
·5 </p>

<p>Vegetables (g/d) </p>

<p>80·3 </p>

<p>118·2 </p>

<p>137·8 </p>

<p>8 3 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>176·6 </p>

<p>0 
·58 </p>

<p>Vegetables (g/d) </p>

<p>549·9 </p>

<p>583·6 </p>

<p>233·9 </p>

<p>Fruits, nuts and seeds (g/d) </p>

<p>70·1 </p>

<p>116·0 </p>

<p>131·7 </p>

<p>8 3 </p>

<p>·8 </p>

<p>176·7 </p>

<p>0 
·50 
Fruits and nuts (g/d) </p>

<p>362·5 </p>

<p>393·0 </p>

<p>214·6 </p>

<p>Legumes (g/d) </p>

<p>15·8 </p>

<p>2 6 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>3 2 </p>

<p>·8 </p>

<p>2 7 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>4 1 </p>

<p>·4 </p>

<p>0 
·46 </p>

<p>Legumes (g/d) </p>

<p>9·1 </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>·4 </p>

<p>7 
·4 </p>

<p>Cereals (g/d) </p>

<p>219·0 </p>

<p>278·8 </p>

<p>304·5 </p>

<p>125·7 </p>

<p>377·2 </p>

<p>0 
·35 </p>

<p>Cereals (g/d) </p>

<p>266·4 </p>

<p>191·0 </p>

<p>8 0 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>Fish (g/d) </p>

<p>25·6 </p>

<p>3 6 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>4 1 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>2 4 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>5 1 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>0 
·52 </p>

<p>Fish (g/d) </p>

<p>23·7 </p>

<p>2 6 </p>

<p>·4 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>·3 </p>

<p>Dairy products (g/d) </p>

<p>344·8 </p>

<p>551·8 </p>

<p>612·1 </p>

<p>366·1 </p>

<p>820·4 </p>

<p>−0·34 
Dairy products (g/d) </p>

<p>196·7 </p>

<p>222·6 </p>

<p>147·6 </p>

<p>Meat/meat products (g/d) </p>

<p>90·2 </p>

<p>120·1 </p>

<p>127·0 </p>

<p>5 2 </p>

<p>·8 </p>

<p>156·3 </p>

<p>0 
·09 
Meat/meat products (g/d) </p>

<p>120·8 </p>

<p>129·3 </p>

<p>6 0 </p>

<p>·4 </p>

<p>Ethanol (g/d) </p>

<p>1·4 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>·1 </p>

<p>8 
·2 </p>

<p>1 5 </p>

<p>·1 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>·6 </p>

<p>0 
·07 </p>

<p>Ethanol § </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Additional components in MDS-alt 
Olive oil use (yes/no) </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0·48∥ </p>

<p>Olive oil (g/d) ¶ </p>

<p>45·5 </p>

<p>4 6 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>2 1 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>Fruits (g/d) </p>

<p>68·8 </p>

<p>115·2 </p>

<p>130·4 </p>

<p>8 3 </p>

<p>·3 </p>

<p>175·0 </p>

<p>0 
·46∥ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Nuts and seeds (g/d) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1·3 </p>

<p>2 
·4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>·8 </p>

<p>0 
·46∥ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Whole grains (g/d) </p>

<p>74·5 </p>

<p>121·7 </p>

<p>145·4 </p>

<p>100·5 </p>

<p>190·0 </p>

<p>0 
·26∥ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Red/processed meat (g/d) </p>

<p>78·5 </p>

<p>107·5 </p>

<p>113·5 </p>

<p>4 9 </p>

<p>·6 </p>

<p>141·4 </p>

<p>−0·05∥ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Red wine (g/d) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>28·9 </p>

<p>4 6 </p>

<p>·3 </p>

<p>4 1 </p>

<p>·8 </p>

<p>0 
·33∥ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Intake of energy, macronutrients, and selected food items not included in the MDS variants </p>

<p>Intake of components not included in the original MDS </p>

<p>Total energy (kJ/d) </p>

<p>7300·1 </p>

<p>8930·7 </p>

<p>9303·9 </p>

<p>2721·1 </p>

<p>10925·6 </p>

<p>−0·33 
Total energy (kJ/d) </p>

<p>9851·4 
10 202·6 </p>

<p>2949·3 </p>

<p>Total fat (g/d) </p>

<p>60·7 </p>

<p>7 6 </p>

<p>·0 </p>

<p>8 1 </p>

<p>·3 </p>

<p>2 9 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>9 7 </p>

<p>·4 </p>

<p>−0·35 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Saturated fat (g/d) </p>

<p>25·7 </p>

<p>3 3 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>3 6 </p>

<p>·0 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>·4 </p>

<p>4 3 </p>

<p>·9 </p>

<p>−0·43 </p>

<p>Saturated fat (g/d) </p>

<p>33·1 </p>

<p>3 4 </p>

<p>·6 </p>

<p>1 3 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>Monounsaturated fat (g/d) </p>

<p>21·0 </p>

<p>2 6 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>2 8 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>·2 </p>

<p>3 3 </p>

<p>·3 </p>

<p>−0·31 </p>

<p>Monounsaturated fat (g/d) </p>

<p>55·9 </p>

<p>5 8 </p>

<p>·4 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>·0 </p>

<p>Polyunsaturated fat (g/d) </p>

<p>8·0 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>·9 </p>

<p>1 0 </p>

<p>·7 </p>

<p>4 
·2 </p>

<p>1 2 </p>

<p>·7 </p>

<p>−0·08 </p>

<p>Polyunsaturated fat (g/d) </p>

<p>15·0 </p>

<p>1 7 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>9 
·2 </p>

<p>Carbohydrates (g/d) </p>

<p>214·8 </p>

<p>263·4 </p>

<p>270·8 </p>

<p>8 1 </p>

<p>·7 </p>

<p>315·4 </p>

<p>−0·24 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Protein (g/d) </p>

<p>68·6 </p>

<p>8 3 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>8 6 </p>

<p>·0 </p>

<p>2 4 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>9 8 </p>

<p>·9 </p>

<p>−0·25 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Potatoes (g/d) </p>

<p>62·5 </p>

<p>108·2 </p>

<p>106·3 </p>

<p>6 2 </p>

<p>·1 </p>

<p>146·9 </p>

<p>0 
·03 </p>

<p>Potatoes (g/d) </p>

<p>88·7 </p>

<p>9 8 </p>

<p>·9 </p>

<p>6 3 </p>

<p>·3 </p>

<p>Sweet foods (g/d)** </p>

<p>21·8 </p>

<p>3 7 </p>

<p>·8 </p>

<p>4 3 </p>

<p>·5 </p>

<p>2 9 </p>

<p>·7 </p>

<p>5 9 </p>

<p>·4 </p>

<p>0 
·05 </p>

<p>Sweets (g/d) </p>

<p>22·8 </p>

<p>2 6 </p>

<p>·8 </p>

<p>1 9 </p>

<p>·7 </p>

<p>Non-alcoholic beverages (g/d) † † </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>133·9 </p>

<p>207·4 </p>

<p>263·0 </p>

<p>294·8 </p>

<p>−0·07 
Non-alcoholic beverages (g/d) </p>

<p>337·5 </p>

<p>387·1 </p>

<p>244·0 </p>

<p>* All intakes in the CAPS study except energy intake are adjusted to a daily total energy intake of 10 460 kJ (equivalent to 2500 kcal). For details of the MDS variants, see Table 1. 
 † Trichopoulou </p>

<p>et al. </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p> ‡ Correlation with the total score (MDS-gram), except where marked </p>

<p>║, whose definition is given later. </p>

<p> § Categorisation of ethanol (&lt;10 g/d; 10 to &lt;30 g/d; 
≥30 g/d) was independent of the median intake in the study population. </p>

<p>║ Correlation with total score (MDS-alt). 
 ¶ Not included as a component of the MDS in the EPIC study. 
** Includes confectionery, sweet bakery products and ice cream. 
 † † Includes juices and soft drinks. </p>



<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>showed an inverse association for a high MP:S ratio, but the 
association disappeared after adjusting for potential confoun-
ders. A high meat intake was associated with a 10-15 % 
reduction in prostate cancer risk in multivariate models, 
although this was not statistically significant. No association 
was found between the intake of fruits and nuts, legumes, cer-
eals, fish or dairy products and prostate cancer. The results for 
Gleason score 7 disease subtype were in the same direction as 
for total prostate cancer (results not shown). As illustrated in 
Fig. 2, smoothed functions of intake showed weak positive 
associations between total prostate cancer and the MP:S ratio, 
vegetable intake and fruit/nut intake, although the CI included 
the value of 1. A dose-response trend was suggested for the 
association with the MP:S ratio. A high intake of legumes, 
fish and meat was possibly associated with a non-significant 
reduced risk of prostate cancer, whereas no association was 
observed for cereals, dairy products or alcohol. 
Analysis of components specific to the MDS-alt showed an 
inverse association between a high intake of red/processed 
meat and total prostate cancer (multivariate OR 0·83; 95 % 
CI 0·70, 0·99; P trend = 0·04). The results were similar but non-
statistically significant in the case of advanced and localised 
disease. We observed an increased risk of advanced disease 
for a high intake of red wine (multivariate OR 1·39; 95 % 
CI 1·06, 1·82; P trend = 0·02). No statistically significant associ-
ations were seen for olive oil use, whole grains, fruit or nuts. </p>

<p>Tests for potential interactions between the Mediterranean 
diet (MDS-gram) and selected covariates showed no statistically 
significant interactions (results not shown). However, when data 
were stratified using interaction indicator variables, men with a 
family history of prostate cancer had a non-significant increased 
risk of total prostate cancer (OR 1·67; 95 % CI 0·87; 3·22; 
P interaction = 0·29) comparing high with low MDS-gram, which 
was not seen in men without a family history of the disease; 
this possible interaction was even more pronounced for advanced 
disease (OR 2·42; 95 % CI 1·10, 5·34; P interaction = 0·10). 
Furthermore, stratified analyses showed a positive association 
between the Mediterranean diet and prostate cancer among 
obese men (BMI ≥ 30 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>), with multivariate OR 2·06 (95 % 
CI 1·11, 3·81; P interaction = 0·09) for total malignancy, 2·17 (95 % 
CI 0·99, 4·76; P interaction = 0·24) for advanced disease and 1·94 
(95 % CI 0·84, 4·49; P interaction = 0·48) for localised disease, but 
not among men with BMI &lt; 30 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Age at inclusion and 
diabetes did not act as effect modifiers in the present study. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Overall, we found no association between the Mediterranean 
diet and relative risk of prostate cancer. Among individual 
score components, a high intake of vegetables and alcohol 
was associated with an increased risk of prostate cancer, and 
a high intake of red/processed meat with a decreased risk of </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Relative risk of total (n 2336), advanced (n 1494) and localised (n 1441) prostate cancer (PC) according to adherence to the Mediterranean Diet Score (MDS) 
variants: (a) MDS-gram, (b) MDS-serv, (c) MDS-cent, (d) MDS-greek and (e) MDS-alt. For details of the MDS variants, see Table 1. Estimates reflect OR (95 % CI) 
derived from unconditional logistic regression models. All models are adjusted for age (in 5-year intervals), region of residence (north/central), education (0-9 years; 
10-12 years; ≥13 years), smoking status (never/former/current), BMI (quartile distribution of controls), energy intake (quartile distribution of controls), physical activity 
(quartile distribution of controls), history of diabetes (yes/no) and family history of prostate cancer (yes/no). Adherence groups were categorised as follows: (a-c) low 
adherence, 0-3 points (reference); medium adherence, 4-5 points; high adherence, 6-9 points; (d) low adherence, 0-2 points (reference); medium adherence, 3-4 
points; high adherence, 5-9 points; (e) low adherence, 0-3 points (reference); medium adherence, 4-5 points; high adherence, 6-10 points. </p>



<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>the disease. The association between MDS and prostate cancer 
was indicated as positive in obese men and in men with a 
family history of the disease. 
To the best of our knowledge, no other studies have so far 
been carried out on the association between the Mediterranean 
dietary pattern and prostate cancer using a dietary score. A few 
studies looking at empirically derived dietary patterns have 
shown an increased risk of prostate cancer with 'Western' diet-
ary patterns rich in meat and processed foods </p>

<p>(31-33) </p>

<p>, i.e. foods 
consumed at low amounts in the traditional Mediterranean 
diet. Interestingly, Greek migrants in Australia have a lower 
risk of prostate cancer than men born in Australia, and they 
have also retained the dietary habits of their native country, 
as opposed to many other migrant populations </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>. Studies on 
the Mediterranean diet and overall cancer risk have shown 
inconsistent results </p>

<p>(2,3) </p>

<p>. A meta-analysis of data from seven 
cohort studies provided a pooled relative risk of cancer of 
0·94 (95 % CI 0·92, 0·96) for a two-point increase in the 
MDS 
(9) . In a recent review, the Mediterranean diet was con-
sidered as 'probably' protective against overall cancer, albeit 
there is variation with regard to different cancer sites 
(3) . </p>

<p>Although the Mediterranean diet as a whole has not pre-
viously been studied in relation to prostate cancer, its individ-
ual components have. Recent reviews suggest that a high 
intake of vegetables, marine fatty acids, legumes and foods 
containing vitamin E (such as vegetable oils, nuts and seeds) 
may offer protection against the disease </p>

<p>(4,34-37) </p>

<p>, and a favour-
able effect may also be seen with a low intake of meat and 
foods rich in Ca such as dairy products 
(4,35-38) . In theory, 
the combined effect of these components may be beneficial 
in prostate cancer prevention. 
In the present study, the observed positive association 
between a high vegetable intake and prostate cancer is unex-
pected, considering earlier indications of an inverse associ-
ation </p>

<p>(34,36) </p>

<p>. The main contributors to the vegetable intake 
were tomatoes, carrots and mixed vegetables, each contribut-
ing on average 14-16 %. A high intake of tomatoes, notably 
tomato sauce, has been shown in several studies to reduce 
the risk of prostate cancer </p>

<p>(34,37,39) </p>

<p>. The indicated positive 
association between tomato intake and localised disease in 
our study may be explained by localised cases potentially 
being more health conscious and more likely to eat healthier. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Dose-response relationship between components of the Mediterranean Diet Score (MDS-gram; see Table 1 for details) and relative risk of total prostate 
cancer (n 2336): (a) MUFA and PUFA to SFA (MP:S) ratio, (b) vegetables, (c) fruits and nuts, (d) legumes, (e) cereals, (f) fish, (g) meat and meat products, (h) 
dairy products and (i) alcohol. Results from restricted cubic regression splines with five knots. (---), OR; (----), 95 % CI. The CI cross at the reference point, equiv-
alent to the tenth centile of the intake in the study population. Regression models include age (in 5-year intervals), region of residence (north/central), education (0-9 
years; 10-12 years; ≥13 years), smoking status (never/former/current), BMI (quartile distribution of controls), energy intake (quartile distribution of controls), physical 
activity (quartile distribution of controls), history of diabetes (yes/no) and family history of prostate cancer (yes/no). </p>



<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>The increased risk for the total vegetable intake was strongest 
for advanced disease and remained, although weakened, when 
tomatoes were excluded from the vegetable intake. Also, the 
vegetable intake was much lower in the study population 
than in the Greek reference population, and thus a true detri-
mental effect is unlikely. We also observed positive associ-
ations between advanced disease and intakes of total alcohol 
and red wine, although there is limited evidence for an associ-
ation between alcohol and prostate cancer </p>

<p>(36,37,40) </p>

<p>. Moreover, 
our findings of an inverse association with red/processed 
meat and no association with dairy products are in contrast 
with previous findings of an increased risk of prostate cancer 
for high intakes of meat and Ca, although the evidence is 
inconsistent 
(36,37,41,42) . The deviating results in our study 
may be explained by residual confounding or recall bias, or 
may be due to chance, considering that we tested multiple 
hypotheses. Another component of the MDS that deserves 
attention is the fish intake. Previous studies on the intake of 
fatty fish rich in n-3 fatty acids have shown inverse associations 
with prostate cancer </p>

<p>(43,44) </p>

<p>, whereas a recent meta-analysis of 
the total fish intake showed no association 
(45) . The MDS 
does not distinguish between fatty and non-fatty fish, which 
may explain the lack of association in our study. 
Olive oil is the main source of fat in the Mediterranean 
region and was included as a component of the alternative 
score, MDS-alt. It has been shown to protect against several 
types of cancer 
(46,47) , but no consistent association has been 
found with prostate cancer 
(48) . We observed no association 
between olive oil use and prostate cancer. Due to the generally 
low intake of olive oil in the Swedish population at the time of 
data collection, this component probably has little overall 
influence on the present results. 
The construction of a dietary score as a measure of a healthy 
diet is complex, and the MDS is no exception. An inappropriate 
scoring method may be unable to detect a true association or 
may lead to misclassification of exposure. For instance, the 
score may be too blunt to detect a weak association with cancer 
since it does not capture all dietary aspects or factors unrelated 
to diet, or because the beneficial and non-beneficial com-
ponents of the score may counter-balance each other's potential 
effects, leading to a null result. This is a possible explanation for 
the overall lack of association seen in the present study. Also, 
strong correlations between the score and its components 
may influence the discriminatory power of each individual com-
ponent. In the present study, the estimated inter-correlation 
between all components and their correlation with the total 
score was low to moderate, which means that each component 
contributes equally to the score. An exception was the vegetable 
component with a relatively high correlation with the total score 
(r s 0·58); hence, it may be the dominant factor determining the 
score. Milà-Villarroel et al. 
(49) recently evaluated the reliability of 
several indexes assessing adherence to the Mediterranean diet, 
and the MDS showed high performance. 
Using study-specific intakes, as opposed to externally 
defined values, as cut-off between low and high intake 
increases the statistical power in each intake group, but it 
does not necessarily mean that the score is able to discriminate 
between beneficial and non-beneficial health effects. This may </p>

<p>be problematic especially in non-Mediterranean populations 
where intake levels may be very different from those of a typi-
cal Mediterranean population. The main differences between 
our Swedish study population and the Greek reference popu-
lation were the considerably lower intake of fruit and veg-
etables and higher dairy product intake in the former. 
However, the two populations differ not only in nationality 
but also in age, the CAPS population being older, and in the 
type of exposure data, the Greek data being longitudinal and 
prospective whereas the Swedish data were collected only 
once and retrospectively. Nevertheless, the observed differ-
ences in intake could indicate a limited discriminatory power 
of the MDS in the study population of the present study. 
To explore the influence of using study-specific intakes as 
cut-off values, we compared variants of the MDS with differ-
ent cut-off values, including one score based on the median 
intake in a Greek reference population. Overall, we did not 
find any statistically significant association with prostate cancer 
for any of the score variants. The non-significant increased risk 
of disease found with MDS-cent and MDS-greek was unex-
pected, as we had rather anticipated inverse associations. 
These results are probably driven by a high vegetable intake, 
as the vegetable component had the highest correlation with 
the total score and was positively associated with prostate can-
cer risk, especially advanced disease. Since overall we observed 
no major differences between the score variants, we suggest 
that the use of study-specific intakes as cut-off values in the 
MDS is appropriate also in non-Mediterranean populations. 
The usefulness of the MDS in non-Mediterranean populations 
is further supported by an Australian study where the MDS was 
found to be appropriate for the prediction of survival in both a 
population of Mediterranean descent (Greek-Australians) and 
a non-Mediterranean population (Anglo-Celts) </p>

<p>(50) </p>

<p>. Also, in a 
European multi-centre cohort study, a two-point increment in 
the MDS yielded risk estimates for overall cancer that were simi-
lar in men in Northern and Southern European countries </p>

<p>(51) </p>

<p>. 
We also created an alternative score variant, MDS-alt, to 
investigate the effect of a more specific score that better reflects 
the 'original' Mediterranean diet. Replacing the fat ratio with 
olive oil use, cereals with whole grains, meat with red/processed 
meat and ethanol with red wine, as well as separating fruits from 
nuts, ideally captures the most health-beneficial components of 
the Mediterranean diet. Comparing MDS-gram and MDS-alt, 
which both used study-specific median intakes as cut-off values, 
we found no statistically significant associations for either of 
them, the two scores being highly correlated. The non-
statistically significantly increased relative risk of advanced pros-
tate cancer seen with MDS-alt is surprising, and may be driven 
by the vegetable component as previously discussed, or may be 
due to residual confounding. 
The influence of diet on risk of developing prostate cancer 
may differ between men who are diagnosed in young or old 
age, or between men with and without a family history of 
the disease, since the type of prostate cancer and disease mech-
anisms may differ between the groups. We also hypothesised 
that diabetic men, as well as overweight or obese men, may 
have different metabolic responses to a Mediterranean diet 
compared with non-diabetic or normal-weight men. Formal </p>



<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

<p>interaction tests showed no statistically significant interactions 
for any of these factors. However, in stratified analyses we 
observed positive associations between adherence to the 
Mediterranean diet and prostate cancer among men with a 
family history of prostate cancer and among obese men, but 
not among men without a family history of the disease or 
who were non-obese. These results should be interpreted 
with caution, especially since the control groups were relatively 
small (n 89 for those with a family history of prostate cancer 
and n 129 for BMI ≥30 kg/m 
2 ). 
The strengths of our study include the large sample size, 
high response-rate, the use of population-based random con-
trols, complete and rapid ascertainment of prostate cancer 
cases and clinical information on prostate cancer subtypes. 
The proportion of prostate-specific antigen-detected cases 
was low (29 % of 1499) due to the low frequency of prostate-
specific antigen testing at the time of enrolment </p>

<p>(14) </p>

<p>, ensuring a 
high proportion of cases with clinically relevant prostate can-
cer. The risk of confounding by population stratification was 
minimised by the ethnic homogeneity of the study population. 
Also, the extensive questionnaire provided detailed infor-
mation on both exposure and potential confounding factors. 
Some limitations with the case-control design need to be 
considered in the interpretation of the present results. 
Selection bias is possible since cases are generally more 
prone to participate than controls, and selection of health-
conscious controls may occur. The retrospective collection 
of exposure information may produce recall bias. However, 
a previous study comparing original and repeated dietary recall 
interviews showed very little or no overall difference in per-
formance between prostate cancer cases and non-cases 
(52) . 
Another drawback is the fact that the FFQ assesses dietary 
intake 1 year prior to diagnosis, which may differ from dietary 
habits earlier in life, before tumour initiation. Furthermore, 
reverse causation bias cannot be ruled out, although men 
&gt;60 years generally tend to maintain their dietary habits 
even after a cancer diagnosis </p>

<p>(53-55) </p>

<p>. 
Due to limitations in the method for exposure assessment, 
measurement error is likely to occur. FFQ generally underes-
timate total energy intake as a result of their inability to capture 
the whole diet. The mean and median energy intakes in the 
CAPS study population were considerably lower than 10 
600 kJ, the recommended daily energy intake for sedentary 
men 61-74 years of age </p>

<p>(56) </p>

<p>, which could indicate an underes-
timation of total food intake. Since energy intake was signifi-
cantly different between cases and controls, differential 
misclassification of exposure is possible. FFQ may also over-
estimate the usual intake of those food items actually asked 
for, leading to distorted estimates of intake </p>

<p>(57) </p>

<p>, and social 
desirability may lead to over-reporting of healthy foods and 
under-reporting of unhealthy foods. The validation study of 
an FFQ almost identical to the one used in the CAPS study 
showed low to moderate correlation for several food 
items </p>

<p>(19) </p>

<p>; however, high correlation coefficients between 
FFQ and food records are rarely achieved </p>

<p>(58) </p>

<p>. Another study 
validating a modified MDS version assessed by an FFQ 
against 24-h recalls showed a Pearson's correlation coefficient 
of 0·48, and the average FFQ-based score was 102 % of the </p>

<p>recall-based score </p>

<p>(59) </p>

<p>. In the present study, the use of 
energy-adjusted dietary intake reduces the potential influence 
of bias due to measurement error. Besides, such errors have 
less influence on the ranking of individuals, which is our main 
objective, compared with assessment of absolute intake </p>

<p>(57) </p>

<p>. 
The potential effect of any remaining measurement error on 
our relative risk estimates is attenuation, which would reduce 
the likelihood of detecting a potentially weak diet-disease 
relationship </p>

<p>(57) </p>

<p>; thus it may in part explain the lack of an associ-
ation seen between the Mediterranean diet and prostate cancer. 
In conclusion, we found no support for any association 
between the Mediterranean dietary pattern and prostate cancer 
in the Swedish CAPS study. We have compared several MDS 
variants with different compositions and cut-off values, and 
observed no significant associations with any of the scores. 
We suggest that using study-specific median intakes as cut-off 
values as in the original MDS is an appropriate way of assessing 
adherence to the Mediterranean diet also in non-Mediterranean 
populations. However, the present results, including the unex-
pected associations seen for certain components of the MDS, 
need to be cautiously interpreted in light of potential limitations 
in the case-control design, the exposure assessment or the dis-
criminatory power of the MDS in our study population. 
Further studies are needed to clarify the relationship between 
the Mediterranean diet and prostate cancer risk. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The present study was funded by the Swedish Cancer Society 
(grant no. 08 0470). The work of R. B. was partially supported 
by the Italian Ministry of Education and Research (MIUR, 
PRIN 2009 X8YCBN). The work of C. G. and C. L. V. was 
supported by the Italian Association for Research on Cancer 
(AIRC, grant no. 10068). The authors declare no conflicts of 
interest. We would like to acknowledge Vassiliki Benetou for 
valuable feedback regarding the MDS, and all those involved 
in the CAPS study, notably the participants, the urologists 
and data collectors, and the Regional Cancer Registries. The 
authors' contributions were as follows: E. M. and 
K. B. planned the study; E. M. analysed the data and wrote 
the manuscript; C. G., R. B., T. M. A., C. L. V. and 
L. A. M. participated in the planning of the study and the analy-
sis and interpretation of the data; O. A., H. G., H.-O. A. and 
K. B. were involved in designing and conducting the CAPS 
study; and K. B. obtained the funding of and supervised the 
present study. All authors have taken part in critical revision 
of the manuscript and have approved the final version. This 
material was presented in part at the Eighth International 
Conference on Diet and Activity Methods, 14-17 May 2012, 
Rome, Italy; the Eleventh European Nutrition Conference, 
26-29 October 2011, Madrid, Spain; and was published (in 
part) in: the Eleventh European Nutrition Conference 
(FENS). Ann Nutr Metab (2011) 58, Suppl. 3, 273-274. </p>





<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>





<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>





<p>journals.cambridge.org/jns </p>

</text></tei>