<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4989431" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Periprosthetic joint infection (PJI) is the main cause of failure following total joint arthroplasty. Until now, the diagnosis 
of PJI is still confronted with technical limitations, and the question of whether synovial fluid biomarker, C-reactive protein (CRP), can 
provide high value in the diagnosis of PJI remains unanswered and, therefore, was the aim of the study. 
Methods: First, we conducted a systematic review on CRP in the diagnosis of PJI by searching online databases using keywords 
such as "periprosthetic joint infection", "synovial fluid", and "C-reactive protein". Eligible studies providing sufficient data to 
construct 2 × 2 contingency tables were then selected based on the list of criteria and the quality of included studies was assessed 
subsequently. Finally, the reported sensitivity, specificity, diagnostic odds ratio (DOR), summary receiver operating characteristic (SROC) 
curve, and the area under the SROC (AUSROC) were pooled together and used to evaluate overall diagnostic performance. 
Results: Seven studies were included in our review, six of which comprising a total of 456 participants were further investigated in our 
meta-analysis. The pooled sensitivity, specificity, and DOR were 0.92 (95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.86-0.96), 0.90 (95% CI: 0.87-0.93), 
and 101.40 (95% CI: 48.07-213.93), respectively. The AUSROC was 0.9663 (standard error, 0.0113). 
Conclusions: Synovial fluid CRP is a good biomarker for the diagnosis of PJI with high sensitivity and specificity. </p>

<p>Key words: C-reactive Protein; Periprosthetic Joint Infection; Synovial Fluid </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Meta Analysis </p>

<p>Access this article online </p>

<p>Quick Response Code: 
Website: 
www.cmj.org </p>

<p>DOI: 
10.4103/0366-6999.187857 </p>

<p>Address for correspondence: Dr. Cheng-Bin Wang, 
Department of Clinical Laboratory, Chinese People's Liberation Army 
General Hospital, Beijing 100853, China 
E-Mail: wangcb301301@163.com </p>

<p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, 
tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited 
and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms. </p>

<p>For reprints contact: reprints@medknow.com </p>

<p>© 2016 Chinese Medical Journal ¦ Produced by Wolters Kluwer -Medknow </p>

<p>Received: 25-04-2016 Edited by: Qiang Shi 
How to cite this article: Wang C, Wang Q, Li R, Duan JY, 
Wang CB. Synovial Fluid C-reactive Protein as a Diagnostic Marker for 
Periprosthetic Joint Infection: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. 
Chin Med J 2016;129:1987-93. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 20, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 16 </p>

<p>
clinical history and symptoms; thus, a more specific and 
sensitive routine for PJI diagnosis is required. [7] To address 
the inconsistency of different tests, the American Academy 
of Orthopedic Surgeons (AAOS) published their first 
guideline in 2010 as a reference for the diagnosis of PJI, [8] 
in which ESR and CRP were used as screening tests and 
joint aspiration should be performed when the level of these 
markers are elevated. Then, in 2012, the Musculoskeletal 
Infection Society (MSIS) renewed with a consensus 
statement providing a concise definition of a PJI. [9] Although 
the MSIS definition provides a standard for definitive 
retrospective diagnosis and research, its complexity makes 
it difficult to use in daily clinical practice. The ideal method 
of PJI diagnosis would be a single test or panel that is highly 
sensitive, specific, and simple to interpret. [10] </p>

<p>In recent years, researches on PJI diagnosis have started to 
focus on synovial fluid instead of serum, since synovial fluid 
is the site of primary infection, and the diagnosis should 
be more sensitive than that of serum theoretically. Studies 
have revealed that number of antimicrobial peptides and 
inflammatory cytokines including CRP, interleukin (IL)-1, 
IL-6, IL-17A, interferon-γ, tumor necrosis factor-α, defensin, 
cathelicidin LL-37, and so on in synovial fluid could be used 
as biomarkers for diagnosis. [11] </p>

<p>CRP is a protein that has long been measured in the serum 
as an indicator of infection, and it has already become a 
well-known protein in the orthopedic community. [12] Until 
now, several studies have suggested that the CRP levels in 
synovial fluid may serve as a simple and cost-effective means 
for improving the diagnosis of PJI as the local CRP is thought 
to enhance complement activation and phagocytosis. [13] 
However, there are also studies concluded that CRP from 
synovial fluid does not offer a diagnostic advantage in the 
detection of PJIs after comparing the value of synovial fluid 
CRP with serum CRP. </p>

<p>To address this controversy, we believe that establishing a 
prompt, precise, and convenient diagnostic guideline based 
on current evidence, consensus, expert opinions, and reviews 
is necessary. Therefore, in this study, we aim to conduct 
a meta-analysis to investigate the diagnostic accuracy of 
synovial fluid CRP for diagnosing PJI. Ultimately, this will 
improve the management of patients with PJI as an effective 
treatment of PJI requires an accurate and quick diagnosis. To 
the best of our knowledge, our study is the first meta-analysis 
that evaluates the clinical utility of synovial fluid CRP in the 
diagnosis of PJI. In our study, we compared the diagnostic 
performance of synovial fluid CRP with the consensus-based 
guidelines. </p>

<p>MeThods </p>

<p>Search strategy </p>

<p>The methodological approach to evidence searching and 
synthesis described in this protocol was based on the 
Cochrane collaboration's diagnostic test accuracy methods. [14] 
In our study, we performed a literature search, screened </p>

<p>the studies identified, and selected the studies that meet 
the eligibility criteria. We then extracted the data from the 
selected studies and assessed the eligible studies by means 
of the revised Quality Assessment of Diagnostic Accuracy 
Studies (QUADAS-2) criteria. [15] Statistical analysis, 
evidence synthesis, and report compilation were carried 
out as the steps below. We strictly adhered to standards of 
the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and 
Meta-Analyses in reporting the findings of this review. [16] </p>

<p>We searched the electronic databases including PubMed, 
EMBASE, Web of Science, the Cochrane Library, and 
Science Direct for entries recorded from the time of 
database inception to December 2015. Vocabulary and 
syntax were adjusted according to different databases. We 
used keywords including "periprosthetic joint infection" 
or "prosthesis-related infections" to represent the disease, 
"synovial fluid" or "fluid, synovial" to represent the source 
of our target biomarker, and "C-reactive protein" or "protein, 
C-reactive" as our target index. </p>

<p>Studies that were related with patients suffering from the 
hip, knee, and shoulder joint arthroplasties or investigated 
our target biomarker were included. Therefore, animal-only 
studies and studies that do not report data on the diagnostic 
performance of our target index were excluded. </p>

<p>Study selection </p>

<p>Screening was performed in a two-step process: title/abstract 
screening and full-text screening. Two researchers 
independently reviewed the title and abstract of each assay 
to select those that were likely for further screening. In the 
initial stage of the screening, 10-15 articles should be used to 
reach acceptable levels of agreement among the researchers. 
When confronted with disagreements, two researchers had to 
come to a consensus about the screening methods. Following 
full-text screening, a list of excluded studies with reasons 
for exclusion was presented. </p>

<p>Inclusion criteria were as follows: patients who have 
undergone knee, hip, or shoulder joint replacements; 
sufficient synovial fluid had to be aspirated for study method 
and CRP of synovial fluid was detected; the diagnosis of PJI 
was confirmed by MSIS or AAOS; sufficient data can be 
extracted for the construction of a 2 × 2 contingency table. 
Exclusion criteria were as follows: unrelated biomarkers, 
CRP of the serum, not synovial fluid; insufficient data 
to calculate sensitivity and specificity; case reports, 
commentaries, expert opinion, and narrative reviews; 
duplicates. </p>

<p>Quality assessment </p>

<p>The methodological quality of the included studies was 
appraised by an adapted version of the QUADAS-2, 
which consisted of four key domains that discussed patient 
selection, index test, reference standard, and flow and timing. 
Risk of bias assessment of the four domains and clinical 
applicability of the first three domains were assessed with 
signaling questions. Questions were answered as "yes" for </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 20, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 16 </p>



<p>low risk of bias/concerns, "no" for high risk of bias/concerns, 
or "unclear". </p>

<p>Data extraction </p>

<p>The following information was extracted: (1) study 
characteristics including author, year of publication, 
country, design, sample size, and number analyzed for each 
study; (2) population characteristics including patients' mean 
age, sex; (3) intervention characteristics including method 
of sampling, method of measuring, and threshold; (4) gold 
standard including MSIS or AAOS; (5) outcomes including 
false/true positive, false/true negative from 2 × 2 table 
for diagnostic studies, sensitivity and specificity, positive 
likelihood ratio (PLR), and negative likelihood ratio (NLR). 
Data were extracted by a single reviewer with all outcomes 
and then verified by the other reviewers. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis and heterogeneity assessment </p>

<p>For all the studies from which we constructed the 2 × 2 table, 
pooled sensitivity, specificity, PLR, NLR, and the diagnostic 
odds ratio (DOR) were calculated using the bivariate model. [17] 
The summarized receiver operating characteristic (SROC) 
curve was constructed. In diagnostic test, heterogeneity was 
commonly caused by threshold effect. When threshold effect 
existed, there was a negative correlation between sensitivity and 
specificity. Heterogeneity caused by the threshold effect was 
evaluated by Spearman's correlation coefficient. If there were 
more than one threshold in an article, the threshold with the 
largest Youden index was chosen. The percentage of the total 
variation across studies was described by the I 2 statistic, which 
indicated the existence of significant heterogeneity when the 
value exceeded 50%. The value of I 2 ranges from 0 to 100%, 
with 0 implying no observed heterogeneity, and larger values 
indicating increasing heterogeneity. [18] The random effects 
model was chosen due to the expected clinical and statistical 
heterogeneity among the studies. [17] For all effect estimates, 
P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. All analyses 
were conducted using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Meta-Disc</rs> software (version 14.0, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Unit of Clinical Biostatistics team</rs>, Madrid, Spain). </p>

<p>resulTs </p>

<p>Of the identified 237 articles, 186 of which were excluded 
with the reasons of duplicates. Among the left 51 articles, 
40 were excluded after reading the title and abstract, 
reasons including the unqualified source of CRP detected 
and inappropriate article type (reviews, comments, or 
letters). After reading the whole 11 articles included, 4 were 
unqualified due to insufficient data, and 7 of which were 
considered suitable for systematic review. [19-25] Among 
these articles, one used improper cutoff value and was 
excluded, leaving 6 further analyzed for meta-analysis. [19-24] 
The study selection process is illustrated in Figure 1. 
Graphical summary of the methodological assessment 
based on QUADAS-2 quality assessment for the 6 studies 
of meta-analysis is shown in Figure 2. </p>

<p>A total of 456 samples from patients who had undergone 
hip or knee joint replacement were included in the </p>

<p>meta-analysis. All studies were conducted prospectively, 
and five of the studies took the synovial fluid samples 
before any clinical treatment while one did not mention. 
However, the cutoff value of synovial fluid CRP varied in 
each study: 2.8, 3.65, 6.6, 9.5, and 12.2 mg/L, respectively. 
In addition, to determine synovial fluid CRP, enzyme-linked 
immunosorbent assay (ELISA) was used in two studies while 
turbid metric immunoassay or kinetic infrared immunoassay 
was used in the other four. As for the standard diagnosis, 
MSIS and AAOS were both included since the details had an 
overlap with each other. Detailed characteristics of individual 
study are summarized in Table 1, and detailed number of 
patients involved in each study and their diagnosis results 
are illustrated in Table 2. </p>

<p>For the included studies, the overall pooled sensitivity 
was 0.92 (95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.86-0.96), 
and the pooled specificity was 0.90 [95% CI: 0.87-0.93, 
Figure 3a and 3b]. The pooled PLR and NLR were 
9.00 (95% CI: 6.15-13.16) and 0.10 [95% CI: 0.06-0.18, 
Figure 4a and 4b], respectively. The area under the 
SROC (AUSROC) was 0.9663 [standard error 0.0113, 
Figure 5] and the DOR was 101.40 (95% CI: 48.07-213.93). 
The results are summarized in Table 3. Spearman's 
correlation coefficient (−0.40) and the P value (0.60), which 
represent threshold effect were tested for the between-study 
variability (heterogeneity). We could also come to the same 
conclusion since there was no shoulder-like ROC plane 
curve. The heterogeneity for sensitivity and specificity was 
tested through I 2 range (0 and 26.8%, respectively). </p>

<p>discussion </p>

<p>PJI is currently one of the most common complications 
associated with TJA and difficult to diagnose. [26] The major 
reasons for this difficulty are the absence of specific clinical 
signs and symptoms, the relative lack of accurate laboratory </p>

<p>Figure 1: Flowchart of the selection process for eligible studies. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 20, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 16 </p>

<p>
tests, and low culture rate in isolation of pathogens due to 
prior therapy and formation of biofilms. [27,28] The accurate 
definition of what constitutes PJI is still controversial; [29] 
therefore, several orthopedic associations have established 
clinical guidelines for diagnosing PJI. [30] The MSIS recently 
responded to this diagnostic difficulty by developing a 
definition for PJI. [31] According to the MSIS, the diagnosis 
of PJI definition requires positive result in either one of two 
major criteria (sinus tract communication with a prosthesis 
or pathogen isolated by culture from two separate fluid 
samples) or four of six minor criteria (elevated ESR, 
elevated CRP, elevated WBC count, elevated percentage 
of polymorphonuclear neutrophils (PMN), presence of 
purulence, and greater than five neutrophils per high-power 
field on frozen section). [32] By comparison, AAOS 
guideline is similar to MSIS, including the following four 
thresholds: ESR &gt;30 mm/h, serum CRP value &gt;10 mg/L, 
synovial WBC count &gt;1760 cells/µl for chronic infection 
or 10,700 cells/µl for acute infection, and synovial PMN 
differential percentage &gt;73% for chronic infection or greater 
than 89% for acute infection. [8] PJI should be diagnosed if 3 
out of 4 thresholds were abnormal. </p>

<p>Although clinically useful, these definitions are complex and 
time-consuming, with the subjective interpretation of the 
frozen section histology and the delay in diagnosis of several 
independent culture results. On the contrary, synovial fluid 
aspirated from patients with joint replacement may provide </p>

<p>researchers with a perfect source of PJI diagnosis since 
host proteins with direct antimicrobial activity may play 
an important role in response to pathogen elimination. [33,34] 
The promise of synovial fluid biomarkers to diagnose PJI 
has been reported during the past few years; however, the 
reference standard in some of these studies is not based 
on MSIS or AAOS, which makes the comprehensive 
analysis of these studies more challenging. According to 
our search results, none of the articles so far have carried 
out a systematic review or meta-analysis about synovial 
fluid biomarkers in the diagnosis of PJI and we consider it 
necessary to fill this gap. </p>

<p>At the initial stage of our systematic study, we used the 
keywords such as "biological biomarkers", "inflammatory 
cytokines", and "antimicrobial peptides" in the research 
strategy to obtain as many highly correlated articles as 
possible. After reviewing searched studies, only two out of </p>

<p>Table 1: Characteristics of studies included for meta-analysis </p>

<p>Author, year Country Participants, n 
(male/female) </p>

<p>Age, median 
(range), (years) </p>

<p>Diagnosis 
standard </p>

<p>Study 
design </p>

<p>Detection 
method </p>

<p>Assay 
platform </p>

<p>Cutoff value 
(mg/L) </p>

<p>Sampling 
time </p>

<p>Deirmengian 
et al., 2014 [19] 
USA 
44/51 
67 (41-86) 
MSIS 
P 
ELISA 
Commercial 
ELISA kit 
12.2 
Before 
treatment 
Vanderstappen 
et al., 2013 [20] 
Belgium 
UA (44) 
UA 
MSIS 
P 
Turbidimetric 
immunoassay 
CRPL3 Roche 
Diagnostics 
2.8 
Before 
treatment 
Buttaro 
et al., 2015 [21] 
Argentina 
43/33 
67 (31-90) 
MSIS 
P 
Kinetic 
immunoassay 
LX20-Beckman 
Coulter 
9.5 
Before 
treatment 
Tetreault 
et al., 2014 [22] 
USA 
57/62 
60 (32-82) 
MSIS 
P 
Turbidimetric 
immunoassay 
Architect TM 
Integrated 
System </p>

<p>6.6 
Before 
treatment </p>

<p>Parvizi 
et al., 2012 [23] 
USA 
UA (63) 
68.2 (42-94) 
AAOS 
P 
Turbidimetric 
immunoassay 
Synchron LX 
System 
9.5 
UA </p>

<p>Parvizi 
et al., 2012 [24] 
USA 
UA (66) 
UA 
AAOS 
P 
ELISA 
RBM assay 
3.65 
Before 
treatment 
UA: Unavailable; P: Prospective study; ELISA: Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; RBM: Rules-based medicine's human inflammation multi-
analyte profiling; MSIS: Musculoskeletal Infection Society; AAOS: Academy of Orthopedic Surgeon's; CRP: C-reactive protein. </p>

<p>Table 2: Data extracted for the construction of 2 × 2 
table </p>

<p>Author, year 
TP 
FP 
FN 
TN </p>

<p>Parvizi et al., 2012 [23] 
18 
2 
2 
41 
Parvizi et al., 2012 [24] 
21 
4 
1 
33 
Vanderstappen et al., 2013 [20] 
9 
2 
1 
32 
Tetreault et al., 2014 [22] 
28 
13 
4 
74 
Deirmengian et al., 2014 [19] 
28 
7 
1 
59 
Buttaro et al., 2015 [21] 
21 
3 
2 
50 
TP: True positive; FP: False positive; FN: False negative; TN: True negative. </p>

<p>Figure 2: Quality assessment of included studies using QUADAS-2 
tool criteria. QUADAS-2: The revised Quality Assessment of Diagnostic 
Accuracy Studies. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 20, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 16 </p>



<p>five qualified studies used synovial fluid IL-6 as a biomarker 
for diagnosis of PJI; hence, the meta-analysis would not be 
accurate due to the limited numbers. As for α-defensin, all 
qualified five studies came to the same conclusion that it 
was a biomarker with high sensitivity and specificity for 
the diagnosis of PJI. Based on the studies we have searched, 
opinion toward the diagnostic value of synovial fluid CRP 
is still in debate; thus, we focused on this biomarker. CRP 
release is induced by the recognition of pathogenic patterns, </p>

<p>playing several mechanistic roles in the innate immune 
response [35] and is currently assayed in the serum as a 
common and inexpensive test to screen for the presence 
of PJI in MSIS. [36,37] However, elevated concentration of 
serum CRP is nonspecific for the diagnosis of localized 
infection since CRP is an acute-phase reactant in numerous 
noninfectious diseases. [38] After quality assessment, six 
articles were highly qualified for our meta-analysis, four of 
which used MSIS as the reference standard and the rest used 
AAOS as the reference standard. </p>

<p>In our meta-analysis, we found that synovial fluid CRP 
showed high sensitivity and specificity for the diagnosis 
of PJI. Pooled estimates of sensitivity and specificity were 
0.92 and 0.90, respectively. Based on the low I 2 (0 and 
26.8%, respectively), Spearman's correlation coefficient 
with P &gt; 0.05, and inexistence of shoulder-like curve, we 
believe that the heterogeneity among studies is low. As for 
the diagnostic performance estimated by the summary ROC, 
synovial fluid CRP had a high (area under the curve [AUC] 
&gt;0.9) diagnostic ability to identify PJI patients based on the 
suggested guidelines for the interpretation for the AUSROC. 
The DOR of our pooled analysis is 101.40, indicating a high 
diagnostic value of synovial fluid CRP in PJI diagnosis. </p>

<p>Of seven articles screened for systematic review, the one 
carried out by Deirmengian et al. [25] was not included in 
meta-analysis due to the use of an improper cutoff value. In 
the article, he conducted the study combining synovial fluid 
α-defensin and CRP together. However, CRP was used solely </p>

<p>Figure 3: Pooled sensitivity and specificity of CRP in the diagnosis of PJI. CRP: C-reactive protein; PJI: Periprosthetic joint infection. </p>

<p>Figure 4: Positive LR and negative LR of CRP in the diagnosis of PJI. 
LR: Likelihood ratio; CRP: C-reactive protein; PJI: Periprosthetic joint 
infection. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 20, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 16 </p>

<p>
as a complementary biomarker and evaluated through ROC 
analysis with the purpose of improving the specificity of 
α-defensin assays used. As part of the combined algorithm, 
this CRP threshold was applied only to α-defensin-positive 
samples. After the detection of both α-defensin and CRP, 
the false positive α-defensin results could be reversed to true 
negative, which meant this CRP cutoff value was decided 
only for the false positive samples. Therefore, the CRP cutoff 
value used was relatively low and the generated 2 × 2 table 
was not suitable for the meta-analysis in this study. </p>

<p>Two studies conducted by Parvizi et al. [23,24] came to 
the conclusion that future investigations are needed to 
confirm their findings in a larger cohort. We performed this 
meta-analysis with the primary aim of enlarging the number 
of samples, which is in accordance with the studies of Parvizi 
et al. [23] and Vanderstappen et al., [20] who found that intra-
articular CRP level could also reflect the severity of PJI in 
their studies. Buttaro et al. [21] admitted that synovial fluid CRP 
was easier to obtain, less expensive, and less dependent on 
the technique of obtaining and interpreting the frozen section. 
Tetreault et al. [22] found that measurement of CRP in synovial 
fluid rather than serum using readily available assays does not 
offer a diagnostic advantage in the detection of PJIs. However, 
based on our meta-analysis, the diagnostic value of synovial 
fluid CRP is higher than that of serum CRP. [39] The pooled 
estimates for sensitivity, specificity, and the AUC for the serum 
CRP of the 25 included studies were 0.82 (95% CI: 0.80-0.84), 
0.77 (95% CI: 0.76-0.78), and 0.877 ± 0.016, respectively. </p>

<p>There are two major limitations in our study. First, despite 
an in-depth search of several electronic databases, there </p>

<p>were only six articles qualified for our meta-analysis and 
it was impossible to further analyze and divide the studies 
into subgroups to explore other potential factors that may 
affect the heterogeneity and perform meta-regression 
analysis. Therefore, characteristics of patients included in 
each study including age, basic condition before surgery, 
and the existence of systematic diseases could not be fully 
analyzed in the meta-analysis. Second, the ideal cutoff value 
for the synovial fluid CRP test could not be determined since 
the raw data were not provided in the published articles. It 
is hard to come to a consistent cutoff value since different 
laboratories used different methods to detect synovial fluid 
CRP, for example, ELISA and turbidimetric immunoassay, 
both of which performed antibody response with the target 
protein (CRP). As a matter of fact, there is still no standard 
cutoff value for the diagnosis worldwide currently even for 
the same method. Thus, our meta-analysis also indicates that 
large-scale, prospective, randomized trials with standardized 
reference and detecting method, strict included, and excluded 
criteria are in urgent requirement to generate a more precise 
cutoff value for clinicians. </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, our study is the first 
meta-analysis that evaluates the clinical utility of synovial 
fluid CRP in the diagnosis of PJI. Although the number 
of studies included in our meta-analysis is limited, all 
the included studies are highly qualified and illustrate the 
high sensitivity and specificity of synovial fluid CRP in 
discriminating PJI patients from those who had undergone 
joint replacement and showed similar symptoms. This 
systematic review has constituted a primary foundation 
for evidence-based guides on the diagnostic performance 
of synovial fluid, which can provide recommendations to 
clinicians for diagnosing PJI accurately and efficiently. 
Meanwhile, prospective studies are in urgent need to further 
validate our findings, and more synovial fluid biomarkers 
of high sensitivity and specificity are required in clinical 
practice for the diagnosis of PJI. </p>

<p>Financial support and sponsorship </p>

<p>Nil. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>references </p>

<p>1. Bozic KJ, Kurtz SM, Lau E, Ong K, Chiu V, Vail TP, et al. The 
epidemiology of revision total knee arthroplasty in the United 
States. Clin Orthop Relat Res 2010;468:45-51. doi: 10.1007/ 
s11999-009-0945-0. 
2. Shearer DW, Youm J, Bozic KJ. Short-term complications have more 
effect on cost-effectiveness of THA than implant longevity. Clin 
Orthop Relat Res 2015;473:1702-8. doi: 10.1007/s11999-014-4110-z. </p>

<p>Figure 5: Summary of SROC of CRP in the diagnosis of PJI. 
SROC: Summarized receiver operating characteristics curve; 
CRP: C-reactive protein; PJI: Periprosthetic joint infection; SE: Standard 
error. </p>

<p>Table 3: Summary results of bivariate model analysis </p>

<p>Sen (95% CI) 
I 2 </p>

<p>Sen </p>

<p>Spe (95% CI) 
I 2 </p>

<p>Spe </p>

<p>PLR (95% CI) 
NLR (95% CI) 
DOR (95% CI) 
SROC (SE) </p>

<p>0.92 (0.86-0.96) 
0 
0.90 (0.87-0.93) 
13.9% 
9.00 (6.15-13.16) 
0.10 (0.06-0.18) 
101.40 (48.07-213.93) 
0.9663 (0.0113) 
Sen: Sensitivity; CI: Confidence interval; Spe: Specificity; PLR: Positive likelihood ratio; NLR: Negative likelihood ratio; DOR: Diagnostic odds ratio; 
SROC: Summarized receiver-operating curve; SE: Standard error. </p>

<p>Chinese Medical Journal ¦ August 20, 2016 ¦ Volume 129 ¦ Issue 16 </p>





</text></tei>