<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4183043" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: To assess vitamin E levels in the breast milk, 
analyzing the prematurity and the birth weight influence 
in α-tocopherol concentration of colostrum milk. 
Methods: Cross-sectional study, in which the colostrum 
was collected from 93 nursing mothers in a public maternity of 
Natal, Rio Grande do Norte, Northeast Brazil. The newborns 
were classified based on gestational age and birth weight. The 
analysis of α-tocopherol in the milk was carried out by high 
performance liquid chromatography. 
Results: The α-tocopherol concentration in the colostrum 
of lactating women whose children were born at term was 
1,093.6±532.4µg/dL; for preterm infants, the concentration 
was 1,321.6±708.5µg/dL (p=0.109). In the preterm group, the 
α-tocopherol concentration in the colostrum of lactating women 
whose children were born with low and normal birth weight was 
1,316.0±790.7 and 1,327.2±655.0µg/dL, respectively (p=0.971). 
In the term group, the α-tocopherol levels were higher in mothers 
of children with birth weight &gt;4000g, being 1,821.0±575.4µg/ 
dL, compared to 869.5±532.1µg/dL and 1,039.6±477.5µg/dL 
with low and adequate birth weight, respectively (p&gt;0.05). 
Conclusions: Prematurity did not influence α-tocopherol 
levels in the colostrum milk. Mothers who had macrossomic 
term neonates presented increased α-tocopherol levels. These re-
sults indicate that birth weight can influence α-tocopherol leves 
in the colostrum milk. </p>

<p>(4):473-9. </p>

<p>Influence of prematurity and birth weight on the concentration of α-tocopherol in colostrum milk </p>

<p>RESUMEN </p>

<p>Objetivo: Evaluar los niveles de vitamina E en la leche 
materna, una vez que los lactantes son considerados grupo 
de riesgo para la deficiencia de esa vitamina, analizando la 
influencia de la prematuridad y del peso al nacer en la con-
centración de α-tocoferol en la leche calostro. 
Métodos: Estudio transversal, con colecta de leche ca-
lostro de 93 mujeres atendidas en una maternidad pública 
de Rio Grande do Norte (Brasil). Los recién nacidos fueron 
clasificados con base en la edad gestacional y en el peso al 
nacer. El α-tocoferol fue determinado por cromatografía 
líquida de alta eficiencia. 
Resultados: La concentración de α-tocoferol en el ca-
lostro de lactantes cuyos hijos nacieron a término fue de 
1.093,6±532,4µg/dL; en el caso de recién nacidos pretérmino, la 
concentración fue de 1.321,6±708,5µg/dL (p=0,109). En el gru-
po pretérmino, las mujeres con neonatos de bajo peso y de peso 
adecuado presentaron valores de α-tocoferol de 1.316,0±790,7 y 
1.327,2±655,0µg/dL (p=0,971), respectivamente. En el grupo a 
término, hubo valores superiores de α-tocoferol en mujeres con 
niños de peso al nacer &gt;4.000g, siendo 1.821,0±575,4µg/dL 
en comparación a 869,5±532,1µg/dL y 1.039,6±477,5µg/dL 
con bajo peso y peso adecuado, respectivamente (p&gt;0,05). 
Conclusiones: A pesar de presentar tendencia de aumento 
respecto al grupo a término, la prematuridad no influenció 
el α-tocoferol en el calostro. Sin embargo, lactantes que tu-
vieron recién nacidos a término con macrosomía presentaron 
niveles aumentados de α-tocoferol. Esos resultados indican 
que el peso al nacer puede influenciar el α-tocoferol de la 
leche, sugiriendo que neonatos con bajo peso pueden ingerir 
menos vitamina E cuando amamantados. </p>

<p>Vitamin E is a generic term used to designate eight dif-
ferent molecules: α-, β-, γ-and δ-tocopherol and α-, β-, 
γ-and δ-tocotrienol 
(1) . Of these, α-tocopherol is the only 
isomer related to the vitamin E nutritional requirement. 
The naturally occurring form of the vitamin is RRR-α-
tocopherol 
(1,2) . Vitamin E is considered one of the best 
biological antioxidants because of the protection it offers to 
plasmatic membranes and low density lipoproteins against 
oxidation and lipid peroxidation reactions 
(3) . </p>

<p>Oxidative stress can cause excessive production of reac-
tive oxygen species and/or lead to deficiencies in antioxidant 
protection systems. This situation is considered to be a con-
tributing factor to the pathophysiologic condition of many 
disorders. Free radicals are produced by normal metabolic 
processes and it is believed that their concentrations increase 
during periods of accentuated metabolic activity, such as 
pregnancy and birth </p>

<p>(4)   . 
Towards the end of pregnancy, the vitamin E concentra-
tion in fetal tissues increases as adipose tissues are built 
up, since they store around 90% of the vitamin. Newborn 
infants born preterm have scant adipose tissue and so they 
have limited vitamin E reserves, making them more sus-
ceptible to deficiencies of this micronutrient compared with 
full term newborns 
(5) . According to Debier et al </p>

<p>(6)   , newborn 
infants are more susceptible to oxidative damage than adults. 
Breastmilk plays an important role in protecting against 
oxidative stress, because it contains antioxidant molecules, 
including the tocopherols, and it is especially important for 
preterms since it can prevent retinopathy 
(7,8) . 
A study conducted in Spain 
(9) found that very low weight 
neonates had higher hydroperoxide levels than a control 
group. This observation is linked to the increased degree 
of oxidative damage suffered by these babies, since hydro-
peroxides indicate the degree of oxidative stress suffered by 
erythrocytes. Furthermore, Baydas et al 
(10) demonstrated that 
premature newborn infants and full-term low birth weight 
infants had lower serum α-tocopherol than a control group. 
Breastmilk is the only source of vitamin E that newborns 
on exclusive breastfeeding have. Research has concluded 
that the concentration of this micronutrient in breastmilk 
may be influenced by several different variables, including 
stage of lactation and gestational age 
(11,12) . Studies that have 
compared the concentration of α-tocopherol in colostrum 
from mothers of full term and premature neonates have 
reported conflicting results. Some found that mothers 
recently-delivered of full term infants had significantly 
higher α-tocopherol levels in colostrum </p>

<p>(12)   , but others found 
no association between gestational age and these levels 
(13,14) . 
A previous study conducted at our center found no signifi-
cant relationship between α-tocopherol in colostrum and 
birth weight 
(15) . 
There is evidence that preterm and/or very low weight 
neonates suffer increased oxidative stress and have lower 
levels of antioxidants such as vitamin E 
(9,16,17) . In view of 
this, the relationships between gestational age and birth 
weight and colostrum α-tocopherol concentration needs to </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2013;31(4):473-9. </p>

<p>Evellyn Câmara Grilo et al </p>

<p>be investigated, in order to verify whether there are certain 
characteristics that can be identified as being linked with 
risk of vitamin E deficiency in newborn infants. This study 
investigated the influence of neonates' gestational age and 
birth weight on the concentration α-tocopherol in their 
mothers' colostrum milk. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>This was a cross-sectional study that collected samples 
of colostrum milk from 93 women seen at the Januário 
Cicco teaching maternity hospital in Natal, Rio Grande do 
Norte, Brazil, after prior approval by the Research Ethics 
Committee at the Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do 
Norte. Newborn infants were classified by gestational age 
and birth weight. Their mothers were enrolled while still in 
the maternity ward if they did not meet any of the following 
exclusion criteria: maternal complications (diabetes, hyper-
tension, cancer, liver disease, infectious diseases, gastroin-
testinal tract diseases, heart disease, syphilis, HIV infection, 
among others); fetal malformation; multiple births; vitamin 
supplementation during pregnancy or postpartum vitamin 
A "megadose" supplementation, because this comprises 
200,000UI of retinyl palmitate combined with 49.4mg of 
all-rac-α-tocopherol. 
Sample size was calculated using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statcalc</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Epi-Info</rs>, ver-
sion <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3.5.3</rs>). According to public health statistics for Natal, 
the city has a 7.9% rate of premature live births </p>

<p>(18)   . Since 
the maternity hospital at which the study was conducted 
hosts an average of 200 births per month, a sample of 90 
recently-delivered mothers was needed to ensure a 95% 
confidence level. Samples were collected between January 
and September of 2010. 
The study sample comprised 93 recently-delivered moth-
ers who volunteered after explanation of the study objectives, 
signing free and informed consent forms. 
Data on infant characteristics were taken from medi-
cal records. The sample of newborn infants was classified 
by gestational age, with those born at less than 37 weeks 
defined as preterm and those born at 37 to 42 weeks as full 
term </p>

<p>(19)   . Newborn infants were also classified by birth weight 
as follows: low birth weight (LBW): &lt;2500g; normal birth 
weight: ≥2500g and ≤4000g; and macrosomia: &gt;4000g 
(20) . 
On the first and second days after delivery, 2mL of colos-
trum was taken in the morning after an overnight fast of 8 to 
12 hours. The samples were extracted by manual expression 
of just one breast at the start and end of a feed. </p>

<p>The colostrum samples were pooled to avoid major 
variations in vitamin levels. The samples were stored at 
-20°C in a nitrogen atmosphere until lipid extraction and 
α-tocopherol analysis. 
The α-tocopherol extraction technique was adapted from 
a method described by Ortega et al </p>

<p>(21)   . For one 500μL aliquot 
of colostrum, 500μL of 95% ethanol (Merck 
® , Rahway, 
NJ, USA), was used to precipitate proteins and then 2mL 
of hexane (Merck 
® ) was used to extract lipids. Next the 
samples were mixed for 1 minute and then centrifuged for 
10 minutes, after which the hexane extract was transferred 
to a new tube. This process was conducted twice, making 
4mL of extract, from which a 2mL aliquot was drawn and 
evaporated in a nitrogen atmosphere in a 37°C water bath. 
For analysis, the dry extract was dissolved in 250μL of HPLC 
grade absolute ethanol (Merck 
® , Rahway, NJ, USA) and 
20μL taken for analysis in the High Performance Liquid 
Chromatograph. 
The concentration of α-tocopherol in samples was then 
determined using a chromatograph (Shimadzu Corporation </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, 
Kyoto, Japan). The system comprises an LC-20 AT Shimadzu 
pump connected to a SPD-20A Shimadzu UV-VIS Detector, 
with a Shim-pack CLC-ODS (M) 4.6mm x 15cm column 
and a computer running the LC solution program (Shimadzu 
Corporation </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, Kyoto, Japan) to process the data. The mobile 
phase used for α-tocopherol analysis was methanol (chro-
matography grade) and water MiliQ 
® (97:3), in an isocratic 
system with a 1.5mL/min flow rate. The wavelength chosen 
to monitor absorption was 292nm, and retention time of 8.2 
minutes was obtained. 
Alpha-tocopherol was identified and quantified in samples 
by comparing the area of the chromatographic profile with 
the area for standard α-tocopherol (Sigma </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>, St. Louis, MO, 
USA). The concentration of the standard was confirmed 
against the specific extinction coefficient in absolute ethanol 
for α-tocopherol (ε 1%, 1cm=75.8 to 292nm) 
(22) . 
Statistical analysis was performed using the open 
source <rs id="software-0" type="software">statistical software R</rs>, version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">2.15</rs>. The results for 
α-tocopherol concentrations in colostrum were expressed as 
means with standard deviations. Numerical variables were 
shown not to be normal, by the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, 
characterizing the samples as parametric. 
The preterm and full term subsets were compared for the 
response variable α-tocopherol concentration in colostrum 
using analysis of variance (ANOVA), with Tukey's post hoc 
test. This statistical treatment evaluated both the main ef-
fects of gestational age and birth weight on α-tocopherol </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2013;31(4):473-9. </p>

<p>Influence of prematurity and birth weight on the concentration of α-tocopherol in colostrum milk </p>

<p>concentration in colostrum and the interaction between 
the two variables. Differences were considered significant 
when p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Twenty-two neonates were defined as preterm and 71 were 
defined as full term. Half (50%) of the preterm neonates also 
had low birth weight and none of them had macrosomia. 
Just 7.0% of the full term neonates had low birth weight 
and 8.5% had macrosomia (Table 1). Overall, 16 of the 93 
newborn infants had low birth weight, 71 had normal birth 
weights and six were abnormally heavy. Mean birth weight 
for the preterm subset was 2560±710g and mean full term 
birth weight was 3260±500g (p&lt;0.001). 
Mean α-tocopherol concentration in colostrum for the 
whole sample (n=93) was 1,147.6±582.9µg/dL. Mean concen-
tration of α-tocopherol in colostrum from breastfeeding moth-
ers whose children were born full term was 1,093.6±532.4µg/ </p>

<p>dL; and the mean for mothers of preterm newborn infants was 
1,321.6±708.5µg/dL (p&gt;0.05) (Figure 1). 
When α-tocopherol concentration was further broken 
down by birth weight, it was found that mean α-tocopherol 
concentration in the colostrum of breastfeeding mothers 
whose children were born preterm and with low weight was 
1,316.0±790.7µg/dL; and that mothers whose children were 
preterm but born with normal weight had a mean concentra-
tion of 1327.2±655.0µg/dL, with no significant difference 
between them (p&gt;0.05) (Figure 2). The colostrum of women 
whose children were in the full term group and were born 
with macrosomia had a mean α-tocopherol concentration 
of 1,821.0±575.4µg/dL, which was higher than for women 
with full term children born at low weight, with a concen-
tration of 869.5±532.1µg/dL (p&lt;0.05), and higher than for 
mothers of full term children born at normal weight, whose 
concentration was 1,039.6±477.5 (p&lt;0.05) (Figure 2). 
Thus, ANOVA indicated a main effect from the variable 
birth weight (F=5.81; p&lt;0.05). However, gestational age did </p>

<p>2,250 
2,000 
1,750 
1,500 
1,250 
1,000 
750 
500 
250 
0 
α-tocopherol [µg/dL] </p>

<p>Full term 
(n=71) </p>

<p>Preterm 
(n=22) </p>

<p>Figure 1 -α-tocopherol concentration in colostrum of </p>

<p>breastfeeding mothers, by gestational age of infants. There was </p>

<p>no statistically significant difference between the full term and </p>

<p>preterm groups according to Student's t test (p&gt;0.05) </p>

<p>2,500 </p>

<p>2,250 </p>

<p>2,000 </p>

<p>1,750 </p>

<p>1,500 </p>

<p>1,250 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>750 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>α-tocopherol [µg/dL] </p>

<p>Full term 
(n=71) </p>

<p>Preterm 
(n=22) </p>

<p>Low birth weight 
Normal birth weight 
Macrosomia </p>

<p>*Statistically significant difference between subset with macrosomia 
and other full term subsets (low birth weight and normal birth weight) 
according to ANOVA with Tukey's post hoc test p&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>Figure 2 -α-tocopherol concentration in colostrum of </p>

<p>breastfeeding mothers, by birth weight and gestational age </p>

<p>Table 1 -Characteristics of the sample of newborn infants from 
the Januário Cicco teaching maternity hospital, by birth weight 
and gestational age, 2010 </p>

<p>Birth weight </p>

<p>Gestational age 
Preterm </p>

<p>(n=22) </p>

<p>Full term </p>

<p>(n=71) 
n 
% 
n 
% 
Low weight (n=16) 
11 
50.0 
5 
7.0 
Normal weight (n=71) 
11 
50.0 
60 
84.5 
Macrosomia (n=6) 
00 
-
6 
8.5 </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2013;31(4):473-9. </p>

<p>Evellyn Câmara Grilo et al </p>

<p>not exhibit a main effect (F=2.87; p&gt;0.05), and there was 
no statistically significant interaction between gestational 
age and birth weight (F=0.21; p&gt;0.05). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Some studies have found that macrosomic, premature 
and/or low weight newborn infants have lower vitamin E 
concentrations in plasma or the umbilical cord </p>

<p>(17,23-25)   . It is 
therefore essential that infants in these groups that could be 
at risk of deficiency receive their intake of this micronutrient 
in breastmilk in order to protect them from oxygen toxicity 
and to stimulate immune system development 
(26) . 
The mechanisms by which α-tocopherol is transported 
to the mammary gland are not well understood, but there 
is consensus that the colostrum-secretion cells increase 
α-tocopherol uptake at the end of pregnancy, during 
labor and at the start of lactation. Schweigert 
(27) studied 
transport of liposoluble vitamins and lipids in cows and 
suggested that cholesterol and vitamin E may be transferred 
to colostrum by a secretory cell transport system that is 
specific to LDL. 
Considering that colostrum is an exclusively breastfed 
infant's sole source of nutrients, it is important to deter-
mine the concentration of vitamin E in breastmilk. The 
mean α-tocopherol concentration in the colostrum of the 
breastfeeding mothers studied here was in line with the 
results of studies of similar populations, such as a study by 
Dimenstein et al 
(28) who reported a figure of 1,155±811µg/dL 
and a study by Garcia et al 
(29) who reported an α-tocopherol 
concentration of 1,206±859µg/dL. 
When results were broken down by gestational age, it was 
found that the α-tocopherol concentration in the colostrum 
of recently-delivered mothers whose babies were born prema-
turely was similar to the results of similar studies undertaken 
in Germany(1,450µg/dL) 
(13) and Spain (from 1,292.1 to 
1,722.8µg/dL) </p>

<p>(12)   . However, our result is higher than the mean 
concentration observed in a study in China (777.84µg/dL) </p>

<p>(14)   . 
The mean α-tocopherol concentration in colostrum from 
mothers of full term infants observed here was similar to 
the result from a German population (1,140µg/dL) 
(13) , 
higher than the concentration found in a Chinese population 
(741.67µg/dL) 
(14) and lower than the concentration observed 
in colostrum from a Spanish population (from 2,153.5 to 
2,584.2µg/dL) 
(12) . 
When α-tocopherol concentration in colostrum from 
mothers of full term infants was compared with the </p>

<p>concentration in colostrum from mothers of preterms 
there was no statistical difference. Similar results have 
been published by Haug et al 
(13) and Zheng et al 
(14) . 
Only the Spanish study found a significant difference 
between their full term and preterm groups, with higher 
α-tocopherol concentrations in colostrum from mothers 
whose children were born full term(2,154 to 2,584µg/dL) 
compared with mothers of preterm infants(1,292 to 
1,723µg/dL). It should be pointed out, however, that only 
30 women were enrolled on the Spanish study, 15 with 
full term and 15 with preterm infants 
(12) . 
It has been shown that the plasma lipoprotein pro-
file changes during colostrum formation, with the 
observation that the LDL fraction transports around 
20% of lipids 4 weeks before birth but just 4% at the 
time of birth 
(27) . On the basis of this evidence, it has 
been hypothesized that the imminence of birth causes 
biochemical changes to lipoproteins irrespective of the 
duration of gestation. 
It is therefore assumed that recently-delivered mothers 
whose gestations lasted less than 37 weeks and/or who 
gave birth to low weight infants have a similar biochemi-
cal pattern of α-tocopherol transport to the mammary 
glands to that of mothers whose children were born full-
term and/or with normal birth weight, which may be 
explained by an accelerated physiological adaptation, in 
response to the imminence of birth. This would explain 
the absence of significant differences in α-tocopherol 
concentrations between subsets divided by gestational 
age and also after further subdivision by birth weight 
and gestational age (into low birth weight and normal 
birth weight subsets). 
However, α-tocopherol concentration was significantly 
higher in the colostrum of breastfeeding mothers whose 
children were born full-term and macrosomic than in the 
normal and low birth weight subsets of the full-term group 
(Figure 2), which contrasts with the results of a study con-
ducted in the same city as this one (Natal), in which birth 
weight had no influence on vitamin levels 
(15) . 
Studies of the kinetics and metabolism of RRR-α-
tocopherol have found that 99% of the average quantity of 
this compound that is estimated to exist in the human body 
is contained in adipose tissues. High rates of α-tocopherol 
transfer between adipose tissue and plasma lipoproteins were 
also observed 
(30) . On this basis, it is supposed that when the 
body's α-tocopherol stocks are high there will be a higher 
concentrations of vitamins in lipoproteins, which in turn </p>



<p>Rev Paul Pediatr 2013;31(4):473-9. </p>

<p>Influence of prematurity and birth weight on the concentration of α-tocopherol in colostrum milk </p>

<p>may be related to increased transfer of α-tocopherol to the 
mammary glands, mediated by lipoproteins. 
The fact that both this metabolic condition and excess 
weight gain either before or during pregnancy are linked 
with macrosomia </p>

<p>(31)   , suggests that the increased α-tocopherol 
concentrations in the colostrum of recently-delivered mothers 
whose children were born macrosomic is the result of their 
greater accumulation of adipose tissue which in turn leads to 
increased maternal stocks of the vitamin and, as a consequence, 
to greater availability to the mammary glands. Further studies 
should be conducted to test for an association between gesta-
tional body mass index and the concentrations of α-tocopherol 
in colostrum and breastmilk and for a relationship between 
gestational weight gain and vitamin E concentrations. 
In view of the findings of this study, it is believed that 
the colostrum received by these newborn infants may be 
more beneficial in terms of nutritional vitamin E intake. 
This micronutrient is essential for macrosomic newborns 
who may be more susceptible to deficiency of the vitamin 
because of lower plasma α-tocopherol concentrations and 
impaired antioxidant capacity, considering the enzymatic 
mechanisms involved </p>

<p>(22,32)   . The authors of a study of newborn </p>

<p>infants with macrosomia that was conducted in Algeria 
concluded that excess weight is potentially a factor that 
increases oxidative stress 
(32) . 
The vitamin E content of human milk can affect the 
biochemical status of this vitamin in breastfed babies 
(33) . 
Newborn infants with macrosomia therefore benefit more 
in terms of vitamin E transfer when fed on their own moth-
ers' milk, since they are potentially at risk of increased 
oxidative stress 
(32) . 
Certain elements of this study could be considered limita-
tions, including the lack of an assessment of maternal nu-
tritional status, by means of serum α-tocopherol assay, and 
the lack of a dietary assessment of the breastfeeding mothers 
enrolled on the study. 
Studies such as this one that investigate the influence 
of neonatal characteristics on α-tocopherol in colostrum 
are important to delineate subsets at risk of vitamin E 
deficiency, considering the vitamin supply provided to 
newborn infants in breastmilk, and to widen understand-
ing of the influence that factors such as gestational age 
have on the adaptive capacity of mechanisms that transfer 
α-tocopherol to the mammary glands. </p>







</text></tei>