<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4286759" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We analyzed the correlation between survival and antitumor effect evaluated by RECIST in advanced 
NSCLC patients with chemotherapy plus target therapy or not as first-line treatment, to examine the 
applicability of RECIST in this population. The patients were screened from 4 clinical trials (12621, 12006, 
FASTACT-I, and FASTACT-II), and those who received chemotherapy plus target therapy or 
chemotherapy alone were eligible. Among the 59 enrolled patients, 29 received combination therapy, while 
the other 30 received chemotherapy only. In the combination therapy group, patients with PR or SD had 
longer overall survival (OS) than those with PD (P , 0.001 and P 5 0.002, respectively). However, in the 
chemotherapy alone group, compared with PD patients, either PR or SD group had no significant overall 
survival benefit (P 5 0.690 and P 5 0.528, respectively). In summary, for advanced NSCLC patients 
receiving chemotherapy plus target therapy as first-line treatment and evaluated by RECIST criteria, SD has 
the same overall survival benefit as PR, suggesting that antitumor effective evaluation by RECIST criteria 
cannot be translated to overall survival benefit especially for this kind of patients. Therefore, developing a 
more comprehensive evaluation method to perfect RECIST criteria is thus warranted for patients received 
target therapy in NSCLC. </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>ung cancer is the leading cause of cancer death in the world, about 85% cases of which are non-small cell lung 
cancer (NSCLC). Appropriately 25% of NSCLC patients possess local advanced disease, and 40% have 
metastatic disease at initial diagnosis; systemic chemotherapy has been the main therapeutic method for 
these patients 
1 . However, the standard cytotoxic chemotherapy of platinum-based doublet has reached the 
therapeutic bottleneck, with an OS of about 10 months and one-year survival rate at 35% 
2 . Recent successful 
development of targeted therapy has greatly improved the survival of NSCLC patient population and changed the 
therapeutic situation to a large extent. These agents include angiogenesis inhibitors, tumor cell apoptosis indu-
cers, and epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR)-tyrosine kinase inhibitors (EGFR-TKIs) 
3,4 , which have been 
widely used in advanced NSCLC. 
In recent years, the combination therapy of cytotoxic drugs with target agents, especially the small-molecular 
tyrosine kinase inhibitors, has been studied as the first-line treatment. A phase III study (INTACT 2) confirmed 
the safety of Gefitinib plus paclitaxel and carboplatin in chemotherapy-naive patients with advanced NSCLC 
5 . 
Besides, a phase II trial of sequential combination of erlotinib and chemotherapy as first-line treatment for 
advanced NSCLC showed a significant improvement in PFS 
6 , which was further confirmed by the FASTACT-
II study 
7 . Now this model of combination therapy has become a promising option for the management of 
advanced cancers. 
In clinical trials and practice using chemotherapy, RECIST has been widely used to identify and quantify the 
antitumor activity of new agents, providing a relatively quick assessment of efficacy. The treatment effect was 
usually evaluated as PR ($30% decrease in the sum of diameter of target lesions), PD ($20% increase in the sum 
of diameter of target lesion), SD (,20% increase in the sum of diameter of target lesion or ,30% decrease in 
them). However, many anticancer drugs especially the target agents show their main antitumor effect as slowing 
down or inhibiting the growth of tumor volume rather than decreasing it; Therefore, it is uncommon to observe </p>

<p>OPEN </p>

<p>SUBJECT AREAS: </p>

<p>NON-SMALL-CELL LUNG 
CANCER </p>

<p>OUTCOMES RESEARCH </p>

<p>marked shrinkage of tumor on the imaging. It has been found that 
the objective response rate of target agents has not always been 
corresponding with the clinical benefit. For example, in a phase II 
clinical trials assessing the efficacy of bevacizumab for metastatic 
renal cell carcinoma, the response was only 10-13% 
8 , but the sub-
sequent phase III clinical trial demonstrated that the PFS in bevaci-
zumab group was significant longer than that in placebo (4.8 months 
vs. 2.5 months, HR 5 0.39, P , 0.001) 
9 . Moreover, our previous 
study indicated that although SD patients showed no significant 
difference from PR group (P 5 0.528), the PFS (5.56 months vs. 
2.03 days, P , 0.001) and OS (12.2 months vs. 7.1 months, P , 
0.001) of SD1 patients were significantly shorter than those of 
SD-/0 patients 
10 . Hence, many specialists recommended the disease 
control rate (DCR), rather than response rate for clinical evaluation 
of target agent in research. However, there is still lack of special study 
on the assessment of combination of target therapy and 
chemotherapy. 
Therefore, the present study aimed to analyze the correlation of 
objective response evaluated by RECIST with patient survival in 
advanced NSCLC patients who received combination of target ther-
apies and chemotherapy or chemotherapy alone from 4 independent 
clinical trials, in order to ultimately provide a better management for 
advanced cancer patients. </p>

<p>Results 
Of the 59 patients evaluated, 29 received combination of target ther-
apy and chemotherapy, while the other 30 received only chemother-
apy. As shown in Table 1, 31 patients were evaluated as PR (52.5%); 
22 had a best evaluation of SD (37.3%), and 6 were evaluated as PD 
(10.2%). The median PFS for this series of 59 patients was 6.9 months 
(95% confidence interval [CI], 5.13-8.73), and the median OS was 
22.8 months (95% CI, 19.13-26.41). 
In the 29 patients who received both target therapy and chemo-
therapy (9 patients from 12006: GP 1 Sorafenib; 8 patients from 
12621: TC 1 Sorafenib; 5 patients from FASTACT-I: GP/GC 1 
Tarceva; and 7 patients from FASTACT-II: GP/GC 1 Tarceva), 16 
with best evaluation of PR; 9 with best response of SD, and the rest 4 
patients had a response of PD. Among these 29 patients, there was no 
significant difference between the PR and SD groups with respect to 
PFS (P 5 0.111) and OS (P 5 0.440). However, in comparison with 
the PD group, significant differences were found between the PR and 
PD groups in PFS (P , 0.001) and OS (P , 0.001). The patients with 
SD also exhibited a longer PFS (P 5 0.002) and OS (P 5 0.028) 
compared with PD patients (Table 2 and Figure 1). Moreover, 
patients with disease control (PR 1 SD) achieved significant longer 
PFS and OS compared to those with PD (P , 0.001 and P , 0.001, 
respectively). 
Among the other 30 patients treated with chemotherapy alone (9 
from GP group in 12006, 5 from TC group in 12621, 4 from GP/GC 
group in FASTACT-I, and 6 from GP/GC group in FASTACT-II), 15 
had tumor regression more than 30%, 13 had tumor regression less 
than 30%, and the rest patients had tumor enlargement more than 
20%. Comparing with SD group, the patients with PR had no obvious 
survival benefit (P 5 0.588); however, the PFS of the latter was 
significantly longer than that of the PD (P 5 0.010) and SD (P , 
0.001) patients. Nevertheless, neither PR group nor SD group 
showed longer OS compared with PD group, which was different 
from the results of combined target therapy and chemotherapy 
(Table 3 and Figure 2). 
The correlation between the response to therapy and the survival 
was examined using univariate analysis. The median survival time of 
PR, SD, and PD groups was 27.8, 24.1, and 10.6 months, respectively, 
while the corresponding median PFS was 7.4, 6.9, and 1.5 months, 
respectively. Of the 59 evaluated patients, comparing with PD 
patients, the ones with disease control (PR 1 SD) showed obvious 
survival benefit (P 5 0.001) (Table 4). In further comparison, the PFS 
of both PR and SD groups were significantly longer than that of the 
PD group (both P , 0.001). The PR and SD groups also showed a 
longer survival time compared with PD group (P 5 0.002 and P 5 
0.018, respectively. There were no significant difference in OS (P 5 
0.847) and PFS (P 5 0.747) observed between PR and SD groups 
(Figure 3). 
The results of the univariate analysis of the correlation between 
clinical characteristics and prognosis of the 59 patients revealed that </p>

<p>Table 1 | Characteristics of all patients </p>

<p>Characteristics 
Cases (n 5 59) 
Percentage(%) </p>

<p>Age(years) 
Median 
57(27-78) 
Gender 
Male 
38 
64.4 
Female 
21 
35.6 
Smoking status 
Never-smoker 
29 
48.3 
Smoker 
31 
51.7 
Histological feature of tumor 
Adenocarcinoma 
49 
83.1 
Nonadenocarcinoma 
10 
16.9 
Disease stage 
IIIB 
5 
8.5 
IV 
54 
91.5 
ECOG PS 
0 
17 
28.8 
1 
42 
71.2 
Response 
PR 
31 
52.5 
SD 
22 
37.3 
PD 
6 
10.2 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ECOG, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group; PS, performance status; CR, 
complete response; PR, partial response; SD, stable disease; PD, progressive disease. </p>

<p>Table 2 | Correlation between different response and the PFS in patients treated with target therapy and chemotherapy (n 5 29) </p>

<p>Items 
PFS (months) (95% CI) 
Univariate analysis P* 
Median survival (months) (95% CI) 
Univariate analysis P* </p>

<p>1. PR 
13.1(0.0-27.3) 
0.111 
-
0.440 
SD 
6.9(1.2-12.5) 
24.1(0.0-48.8) 
2. PR 1 SD 
12.9(4.4-21.4) 
,0.001 
-
,0.001 
PD 
1.5(0.9-2.2) 
5.7(0.0-11.8) 
3. SD 
6.9(1.2-12.5) 
0.002 
24.1(0.0-48.8) 
0.028 
PD 
1.5(0.9-2.2) 
5.7(0.0-11.8) 
4. PR 
13.1(0.0-27.3) 
,0.001 
-
,0.001 
PD 
1.5(0.9-2.2) 
5.7(0.0-11.8) </p>

<p>Note:*Log-Rank test. 
Abbreviations: CI, Confidence interval; OS, overall survival; PFS, progression free survival; CR, complete response; PR, partial response; SD, stable disease; PD, progressive disease. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7683 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07683 </p>

<p>
there were no statistically significant correlation between the pro-
gnosis and the smoking history (P 5 0.421), age (P 5 0.482), and 
pathological type (P 5 0.209). </p>

<p>Discussion 
We have retrospectively analyzed the correlation of therapeutic efficacy 
evaluated by RECIST with the patient survival in 4 clinical trials with 
target agents. Among the total 59 patients evaluated, PR and SD 
groups had similar PFS and OS, which was consistent with the popu-
lation receiving combination therapy. Based on this, our research 
firstly analyzed the correlation between objective response and survival 
after combination treatment of chemotherapy with target therapy. 
Target therapy aims to inhibit the growth of tumor, which is 
different from the killing-effect of cytotoxic drugs. The molecular-
targeted therapies available for lung cancer are more likely to result in 
SD than to produce tumor regression. Our previous study 
10 reported 
EGFR-TKI for advanced NSCLC, with survival benefit observed in 
patients with tumor stabilization. Kurata et al. 
11 demonstrated that 
1% increase in DCR would prolong the survival time by 0.0375 
months in advanced NSCLC patients receiving EGFR-TKI as sec-
ond-line therapy. About 67% phase II and phase III clinical trials for 
target therapy take DCR (CR 1 PR 1 SD), other than objective 
response rate, as primary objective 
12 . We also found the same results 
in the chemo and target therapy queue, SD patients had no difference 
with PR patients in OS (P 5 0.440) and PFS (P 5 0.111). However, 
both PR and SD patients had better survival benefit than PD patients 
(P , 0.001 and P 5 0.028, respectively), indicating that the SD </p>

<p>patients also obtained survival benefit from the combination of 
chemo and target therapy or target therapy only. This information 
suggested that DCR may be a better endpoint than response rate in 
this kind of clinical study, to avoid missing a good antitumor drug. 
Moreover, better criteria should be explored in the evaluation of 
combination of target and chemotherapy. 
In the chemotherapy queue, overwhelming superiority of SD and 
PR patients over PD patients was observed in PFS (P , 0.001 and P 5 
0.010, respectively); however, there was no difference in OS between 
(PR 1 SD) group and PD group (P 5 0.564), which was different 
from the present study 
13 . The possible reasons for this may include 
the small sample size, which had no enough power to distinguish the 
difference in survival between patients with disease control and PD. 
Besides, the subsequent therapies are confounding factors of OS, 
which may counteract the difference of OS between groups. 
In our study, the median survival of target combined with chemo-
therapy group was 15.9 months, which was much longer than 2 phase 
II trials of first-line EGFR-TKI in unselected patients with advanced 
NSCLC </p>

<p>14,15   . All patients in this group had received chemotherapy, 
which enhanced the killing effect on tumor cells to certain extent. In 
terms of the killing-effect of chemotherapy, in the 22 patients eval-
uated with SD, only 1 patient had slight tumor enlargement, while the 
other 21 had tumor regression, which is different from the result of 
our previous report that 13 out of the 40 patients in SD group had 
slight tumor enlargement 
10 . The median survival of chemotherapy 
group was 14.1 months, much longer than the result of other studies, 
possibly due to a subsequent treatment. </p>

<p>Figure 1 | PFS and OS curves for patients received both target therapy and chemotherapy with different response: (A) Comparison of PFS among patients </p>

<p>with PR, SD, and PD. (B) Comparison of OS among patients with PR, SD, and PD. </p>

<p>Table 3 | Correlation between different response and the PFS in patients treated with chemotherapy (n 5 30) </p>

<p>Items 
PFS (months) (95% CI) 
Univariate analysis P* 
Median survival (months) (95% CI) 
Univariate analysis P* </p>

<p>1. PR 
5.0(3.0-6.9) 
0.136 
27.8(-) 
0.588 
SD 
6.9(6.3-7.5) 
22.1(8.5-35.8) 
2.PR 1 SD 
6.8(4.3-9.3) 
,0.001 
22.1(8.5-35.8) 
0.564 
PD 
0.8(-) 
13.3(-) 
3.SD 
6.9(4.7-9.2) 
,0.001 
22.1(8.5-35.8) 
0.528 
PD 
0.8(-) 
13.3(-) 
4.PR 
5.0(3.4-6.9) 
0.010 
27.8(-) 
0.690 
PD 
0.8(-) 
13.3(-) </p>

<p>Note:*Log-Rank test. 
Abbreviations: CI, Confidence interval; OS, overall survival; PFS, progression free survival; CR, complete response; PR, partial response; SD, stable disease; PD, progressive disease. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7683 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07683 </p>

<p>
At present, OS is considered to be the most important indicator of 
clinical efficacy endpoints for therapy regimen, but it requires pro-
longed follow-up and is often affected significantly by other factors, 
such as subsequent treatment. Therefore, OS may lead to either a 
waste of the medical resources or a loss of the benefit from main-
tained therapy. Therefore, a more effective parameter is needed to 
guide the choice of treatment during the course of disease. In onco-
logy, change in tumor size is linked to survival in some solid tumors. 
Bruno et al. suggested that change in tumor size can be used as a 
primary endpoint in the design and evaluation of phase II studies and 
in supporting go/no-go decisions and phase III study design 
16 . Kris 
also indicated that any increase or decrease of tumor size should be 
taken as a surrogate endpoint for efficacy 
17 . Many analyses showed 
that the change of tumor size was an independent prognostic factor. 
We also found that SD patients with tumor regression had significant 
survival benefit. He et al. suggested that initial PR and SD patients 
with advanced NSCLC enjoy similar PFS and OS 
18 . These results 
suggest that response rate may be not a suitable indicator to define 
the evaluation of antitumor treatment. 
The World Health Organization (WHO) criteria, evaluating the 
effect of treatment by comparing the sum of the products of bidi-
mensional lesion measurement, were a reliable norm in assessing the 
effectiveness of chemotherapy for patients with advanced NSCLC. 
However, after 20 years of practice, we found that the criteria 
remained to be improved. The measurable, evaluable lesions were 
not defined, and estimating the tumor size by the product of the 
longest diameter and its vertical length caused inaccuracy of the 
result. Thus the EORTC, NCI, and NCIC put forward the RECIST, </p>

<p>which was also based on the morphological features of tumor, but 
used the unidimensional lesion measurement, defining both the 
measurable lesions and the number of target lesions, making a great 
progress when compared to the WHO criteria </p>

<p>19,20   . Therefore, in both 
clinical trials and practice, the RECIST became a standard for evalu-
ation of efficacy. However, limitations remained in RECIST criteria, 
which is especially true when dealing with the targeted therapy. Ours 
and several other studies have verified that patients with SD have 
been also benefited from the continuation of the original treatment 
17 . 
Several limitations need to be considered. The sample size of the 
present study is small, and this is a retrospective study; all the patients 
with advanced NSCLC were from 4 clinical trials enrolled in one 
center. Moreover, in the field of combinatorial chemotherapy and 
target therapy, a limited number of the clinical trials are available, so 
we were unable to enroll more patients into this study. However, 
these patients were initially enrolled under strict inclusion criteria 
and received treatment in a standard way with a long follow-up, and 
the imaging evaluation was performed by a systematical radiologic 
review committee. Therefore, the results of the present study could 
still provide important information. 
Our study showed that in patients with chemotherapy plus target 
agents as first-line treatment, under evaluation with RECIST criteria, 
SD patients had the same overall survival benefit as PR patients. 
Moreover, when compared with PD group, patients with disease 
control (PR 1 SD) had longer survival. However, in the chemother-
apy alone group, there was no significant difference between disease 
control group and PD group. These findings indicated that RECIST 
criteria may not reflect the change of tumor cell viability timely to </p>

<p>Figure 2 | PFS and OS curves for patients received chemotherapy only with different response: (A) Comparison of PFS among patients with PR, SD, and </p>

<p>PD.(B) Comparison of OS among patients with PR, SD, and PD. </p>

<p>Table 4 | Correlation between different response and the PFS in whole series of NSCLC patients (n 5 59) </p>

<p>Items 
PFS (months) (95% CI) 
Univariate analysis P* 
Median survival (months) (95% CI) 
Univariate analysis P* </p>

<p>1. PR 
7.4(3.7-11.0) 
0.847 
27.8(15.7-39.9) 
0.747 
SD 
6.9(6.4-7.4) 
24.1(13.2-35.1) 
2. PR 1 SD 
7.3(6.1-8.4) 
,0.001 
27.8(20.0-35.6) 
0.001 
PD 
1.5(0.6-2.5) 
10.6(0.3-21.0) 
3. SD 
6.9(6.4-7.4) 
,0.001 
24.1(13.1-35.2) 
0.018 
PD 
1.5(0.6-2.5) 
10.6(0.3-21.0) 
4. PR 
7.4(3.7-11.0) 
,0.001 
27.8(15.7-39.9) 
0.002 
PD 
1.5(0.6-2.5) 
10.6( 0.3-21.0) </p>

<p>Note:*Log-Rank test. 
Abbreviations: CI, Confidence interval; OS, overall survival; PFS, progression free survival; CR, complete response; PR, partial response; SD, stable disease; PD, progressive disease. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7683 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07683 </p>

<p>
fully reliably predict patient's prognosis, especially for advanced 
NSCLC patients receiving chemotherapy plus target therapy as 
first-line treatment. Therefore, a more comprehensive evaluation 
method is thus needed to evaluate therapeutic efficacy in this popu-
lation. Prospective randomized studies with advanced NSCLC 
patients are required to further validate the present results. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Patients. Patients with stage IIIB or IV NSCLC were enrolled in 4 clinical trials 
(FASTACT-I study, FASTACT-II study, 12621 study, and 12006 study); among them 
the ones who received targeted therapy (Tarceva or Sorafenib) combining with 
chemotherapy or chemotherapy alone as first-line treatment in Sun Yat-Sen 
University Cancer Center from September, 2006 to August, 2011, were 
retrospectively analyzed. The criteria for eligibility were as follows: 1) histologically-
or cytologically-confirmed stage IIIB or IV NSCLC, 2) an age of at least 18 years, 3) an 
Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1, 4) having 
at least one measurable lesion, 5) possessing adequate hematologic, hepatic, and renal 
function, and 6) having a life expectancy of at least 3 months. Prior radiation therapy 
was permitted, if the indicator sites (the sites that were followed to determine whether 
there was a response) had not been irradiated, and the radiation therapy had been 
completed at least 4 weeks before the enrollment. Patients who had received systemic 
treatment, including target therapy, chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks of 
study were excluded; patients with brain metastases were ineligible for the studies. All 
patients provided written informed consent. This study was approved by the Ethics 
Committee of Sun Yat-Sen University Cancer Center. All the methods were carried 
out in accordance with the approved guidelines from Sun Yat-Sen University Cancer 
Center. 
Of the 64 patients enrolled, 4 patients in the 12006 study even had not completed a 
cycle treatment, and 1 patient dropped out after 1 cycle treatment due to AE in the 
12621 study. A total of 59 patients were finally evaluated, with 21 females and 38 
males. The median age was 57 years (range, 27-78 years). The clinical characteristics 
of the patients in the 4 clinical trials were similar (Table 1). </p>

<p>Treatment. In the 12621 study, patients received 175 mg of paclitaxel per square 
meter of body-surface area and carboplatin at a dose calculated to produce an AUC 
(area under the concentration-time curve) of 5 mg per milliliter per minute on day 1, 
and 400 mg Sorafenib/placebo on day 1-21. The cycle was repeated every 3 weeks. In 
the 12006 study, patients treated with gemcitabine, at a dose of 1250 mg per square 
meter of body-surface area (administered on day 1 and 8), 75 mg of cisplatin per 
square meter of body-surface area (administered on day 1), and Sorafenib/placebo 
400 mg twice per day, for a cycle of 3 weeks. In both studies patients continued to 
receive Sorafenib or placebo until progression or unacceptable toxicity or death after 3 
cycles of treatment. Patients were administered 6 cycles of gemcitabine at a dose of 
1250 mg per square meter of body-surface area on days 1 and 8, followed by cisplatin 
at a dose of 75 mg per square meter of body-surface area or carboplatin 53 AUC on 
day 1, and with intercalated Tarceva/placebo 150 mg/day on days 15-28 every 4 
weeks both in the FASTACT-I/II study. In the same way, patients continued to 
receive Tarceva or placebo until progression or unacceptable toxicity or death, and all 
patients in the placebo group were offered second-line Tarceva at the time of 
progression. We analyzed all the evaluable patients in these 4 trials. Among the 13 </p>

<p>patients from 12621 study, 8 received GP and Sorafenib, while others received GP and 
placebo. Of the 24 patients from 12006 study, 9 were treated with GP and Sorafenib, 
and the remaining ones received GP and placebo. Among the 9 patients from 
FASTACT-I study, 5 received GP/GC and Tarceva, and 4 received GP/GC and 
placebo. The rest 13 patients were from FASTACT-II study; 7 of them received GP/ 
GC and Tarceva, and the other 6 received GP/GC and placebo. </p>

<p>Tumor response evaluation. The target lesion was assessed with computed 
tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at baseline within 4 weeks 
before randomization. RECIST (version 1.0) evaluation of therapeutic effect was 
based on tumor assessment with follow-up, including chest and upper-abdominal CT 
scan every 2 cycles of treatment or every 6 weeks until disease progression or death. 
Besides, the method of assessment was exactly the same as that in the corresponding 
clinical trials, and the imaging evaluation was performed by an independent 
radiologic review committee. The designations of CR, PR, SD, and PD were on the 
basis of the standardized response definitions established by the RECIST. CR was 
defined as the disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes 
(whether target or non-target) must have reduction in short axis to ,10 mm. PR was 
defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of diameter of target lesions, taking the 
baseline sum diameters as reference. SD referred to a change of lesion size ranging 
from an increase of ,20% to a decrease of ,30% and with no new lesion. PD was 
defined as at least a 20% increase in the sum of diameter of target lesions, taking the 
smallest sum on study as reference. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. We calculated 95% CI for PFS and OS outcomes to assess the 
treatment efficacy. Kaplan-Meier method was used to describe PFS and OS. All 
reported time-to-event comparisons were conducted using the log-rank test analysis 
respectively. A P value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">17.0</rs> software was used for all statistical analysis (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs>, Armonk, NY). </p>

<p>Follow-up. The 59 patients received CT scan every 6 weeks until disease progression 
or death according to the criteria of these 4 clinical trials. They were also asked to 
answer questionnaire like quality of life (QoL) every 6 weeks at the clinic or on the 
phone. We compared the difference of patients' survival by means of PFS and OS. PFS 
was calculated from the date of randomization to disease progression (local or 
metastatic) or death for any reason. OS was defined as the time elapsed from the date 
of randomization to the time of death for any cause. Patients who had not progressed 
or died at the time of statistical analysis were censored at the time of last follow-up. </p>



<p>Figure 3 | PFS and OS curves for the 59 patients with different response after therapy: (A) Comparison of PFS among patients with PR, SD, and PD. (B) </p>

<p>Comparison of OS among patients with PR, SD, and PD. </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7683 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07683 </p>



<p>
Acknowledgments </p>

<p>This study was supported by provincial science and technology fund in 2009 
(303040791002). </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Z.T. wrote manuscript and analyzed data; Z.L. performed research and analyzed data; 
Z.H.Y. and Z.L. designed research and performed research; H.Z.H. and F.W.F. analyzed 
data; G.J.Y., Z.Y.Y. and Z.Y. performed research. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Zhou, T. et al. The Effectiveness of RECIST on Survival in Patients 
with NSCLC Receiving Chemotherapy with or without Target Agents as First-Line 
Treatment. Sci. Rep. 5, 7683; DOI:10.1038/srep07683 (2015). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in 
this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated 
otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative 
Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder 
in order to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>www.nature.com/scientificreports </p>

<p>SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | 5 : 7683 | DOI: 10.1038/srep07683 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>