<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4846046" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Introduction: Currently, there is no single consensual definition of sarcopenia in the literature. 
This creates a challenge for the evaluation of its prevalence and its direct or indirect impact 
on the quality of life of elderly populations of different races and ethnicities. Furthermore, no 
studies as yet have analyzed these variables in populations of elderly subjects of the "quilom-
bola" ethnic group. 
Objective: We aimed to verify the association between sarcopenia and quality of life in qui-
lombola elderly using the Baumgartner and the European Working Group on Sarcopenia in 
Older People (EWGSOP) criteria. 
Methods: This was a cross-sectional study of 70 male and female participants (mean age: 
65.58±6.67 years). Quality of life was evaluated using the multidimensional 36-item Short-Form 
Health Survey (SF-36) of the Medical Outcomes Study. Sarcopenia was diagnosed according 
to the Baumgartner cutoff for appendicular skeletal muscle mass and the criteria recommended 
by the EWGSOP. Muscle mass and fat mass percentages were analyzed by dual-energy X-ray 
absorptiometry, while handgrip strength (HGS) was evaluated using a hand-held dynamometer. 
Physical performance was assessed through a gait speed test. 
Results: The prevalence of sarcopenia was 15% according to the Baumgartner cutoff and 10% 
according to EWGSOP criteria. Quilombola elderly classified as physically active or very active 
were at least six times less likely to develop sarcopenia than those classified as irregularly active 
or sedentary. HGS was negatively associated with a diagnosis of sarcopenia according to both 
sets of criteria. Subjects with sarcopenia reported lower scores than those without the condition 
on the physical role functioning and bodily pain domains of the SF-36. 
Conclusion: In this sample of quilombola elderly, quality of life was negatively associated with 
sarcopenia, regardless of the classification criteria used. Additionally, the results showed that 
diagnostic criteria for sarcopenia should include reductions in lean mass in addition to measures of 
functioning and physical performance because some subjects showed the former symptom without 
any alteration of the latter two variables. The cutoff value suggested by Baumgartner criteria were 
less accurate than that specified by the EWGSOP criteria because they do not consider function-
ing and physical performance. However, Baumgartner criteria were more sensitive in detecting 
sarcopenia because reductions in lean mass predict alterations in strength and walking speed. 
The term sarcopenia comes from the Greek words "sarco", meaning muscle, and 
"penia", meaning loss, and was first used by Irwin Rosenberg. 
1 This condition was origi-
nally described by Evans and Campbell  2 and was defined by Evans 
3 as an age-related 
reduction in muscle mass. This phenomenon has been increasingly investigated in </p>

<p>This article was published in the following Dove Press journal: 
International Journal of General Medicine 
19 April 2016 
Number of times this article has been viewed </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>silva neto et al </p>

<p>the literature, and there is now a growing body of research 
into sarcopenia. 
Sarcopenia leads to a reduction in fat-free mass and muscle 
strength, as well as impaired physical performance. 
4,5 This con-
dition is also associated with other illnesses such as osteopo-
rosis, osteopenia, obesity, diabetes mellitus type II, and breast 
cancer, as well as cardiovascular and respiratory diseases, bone 
fragility, falls, impaired mobility, alterations in glycemic and 
metabolic control, reduced basal metabolism, and reduced 
functional capacity. 
6-8 These conditions may cause functional 
dependence and increase the likelihood of hospitalization and 
institutionalization, as well as causing significant health care 
costs and taking a heavy toll on quality of life. </p>

<p>9   According to the literature, there is significant difficulty 
in estimating the prevalence of sarcopenia 
10 due to the vari-
ous techniques used to assess muscle mass, muscle strength, 
and physical performance, as well as the different diagnostic 
cutoffs and the variability in the anthropometric and socio-
economic diversity of the populations studied. Therefore, to 
improve the management of this condition, diagnostic criteria 
for sarcopenia in different elderly populations should also 
consider variables such as race and ethnicity. 
The association between low levels of lean mass, reduced 
muscle strength, and poor health-related quality of life 
(HRQOL) is not exclusive to Caucasian populations. One study 
demonstrated an association between low lean body mass, 
reduced mobility and low quality of life in African Americans. </p>

<p>11   Additional research has also analyzed changes in muscle mass 
and strength in elderly individuals of different races and ethnici-
ties. 
12 These studies found that men lost twice as much muscle 
strength than women, and Blacks lost 28% more strength than 
Whites. Leg muscle strength decreased by 3.4% annually in 
Caucasian males, 4.1% in Black males, 2.6% in Caucasian 
females, and 3.0% in Black females. 
The "quilombola" population is formed by ethnic/racial 
groups with a particular historical background, specific ter-
ritorial relations, and self-declared ancestry from Blacks 
who resisted slavery. 
13 In addition to their shared genetics, 
the quilombola people have a strong ethnic group identity, 
follow a particular form of social organization, and live in 
predominantly rural areas. </p>

<p>14   According to the Palmares Foundation, a federal agency 
responsible for the registration of quilombola communities, 
a total of 1,500 such groups are officially recognized in 
Brazil. 
15 However, the actual number of quilombola com-
munities is estimated to be ∼5,000. As per the global trend, 
the elderly population of quilombola communities has also 
increased. 
14 Although the health of minority populations is </p>

<p>a widely recognized priority, few studies have focused on 
elderly quilombola populations. Investigations of the relation-
ship between health and quality of life in these subjects are 
especially scarce, and the few existing studies on the topic 
usually involve stratified samples. </p>

<p>15   Although the literature suggests that sarcopenia may 
have a negative impact on health and HRQOL, little is 
known regarding the repercussions of this condition on 
elderly Blacks, especially those who live in quilombola 
communities. 
10 As such, the aim of this study was to evalu-
ate the association between sarcopenia and quality of life in 
elderly individuals from quilombola communities using the 
Baumgartner and European Working Group on Sarcopenia 
in Older People (EWGSOP) criteria. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>The sample included adults of both sexes of at least 60 years 
of age, recruited from the quilombola communities of 
Malhadinha and Córrego Fundo, located in the rural outskirts 
of Brejinho do Nazaré, 100 km from Palmas, the state capital 
of Tocantins. Data were collected over the course of 12 trips 
to these locations, incurring significant costs in terms of 
transportation, food, and expendable supplies. All subjects 
provided written consent for participation. This study was 
approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the Federal 
University of Tocantins under protocol number 045/2014. 
All experimental procedures were performed in accordance 
with Federal Resolution 466/12. </p>

<p>Procedure </p>

<p>The inclusion criteria for the study were age 60 years or older, 
residence in the Malhadinha or Córrego Fundo communities 
(Brejinho de Nazaré, Tocantins), and scores of at least 17 on the 
Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE). Exclusion criteria 
consisted of the following: inability to move without assis-
tance, presence of metallic prostheses, self-reported cardiac or 
respiratory disorders, self-reported acute pain in the upper or 
lower limbs, physical disability, as well as a history of stroke, 
cancerous cachexia, untreated chronic disease or mental illness, 
severe arthritis, inflammatory diseases, and/or medication-
induced anorexia. All interviewers were trained to administer 
the assessment instruments involved in this study. </p>

<p>Instruments </p>

<p>socioeconomic questionnaire </p>

<p>This instrument was used to collect data on the socio-
economic status, as well as information on participant age, 
sex, and education level. </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>sarcopenia and quality of life in quilombola elderly in Brazil </p>

<p>sample characteristics </p>

<p>Cognitive impairment was investigated using the MMSE. 
Scores were analyzed as recommended by Brucki et al. </p>

<p>16   Physical activity levels were evaluated using the short ver-
sion of the International Physical Activity Questionnaire 
(IPAQ), which has already been validated for use in Brazilian 
populations. This instrument was administered in individual 
interviews, as recommended for developing countries, and it 
allowed for the classification of participants as very active, 
active, infrequently active, or sedentary, according to their 
scores. </p>

<p>17   anthropometric measurements </p>

<p>Body mass was measured using a digital scale accurate to 
0.1 kg (Filizola, São Paulo, Brazil). Height was measured 
using a wall-mounted stadiometer accurate to 0.1 cm 
(Cardiomed, Curitiba, Paraná, Brazil). These values were 
then used to calculate the body mass index (BMI) of each 
participant. Waist and hip circumference were then mea-
sured 
18 to allow for a calculation of the waist-to-hip ratio 
(WHR) of each subject. 
Appendicular skeletal muscle mass (ASMM) and fat mass 
percentages were analyzed using a Lunar DPX dual-energy 
X-ray absorptiometer and the Encore 2013 software. Low 
ASMM was defined according to the cutoffs described by 
Baumgartner et al 
19 (5.45 kg/m 
2 for women and 7.26 kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>for men). Relative ASMM was calculated by dividing dual-
energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA)-determined ASMM 
by the square of participant height. </p>

<p>Physical performance </p>

<p>All participants performed a 3 m walking speed test, in which 
gait speed was measured in meters per second. 
20 Performance 
on this task was analyzed according to the cutoffs recom-
mended by the EWGSOP. 
4 Speeds of #0.8 m/s were consid-
ered indicative of impaired physical performance. Handgrip 
strength (HGS) was measured using a standard dynamometer 
(Saehan, Masan, South Korea). 
21 HGS values ,30 kg in 
men and ,20 kg in women were considered indicative of 
mobility limitations. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Definition of sarcopenia </p>

<p>This study used the definition of sarcopenia provided by the 
EWGSOP, 
4 which describes the disorder based on three main 
factors, which consist of muscle mass, muscle strength, and 
physical performance. Sarcopenia can be diagnosed based on 
the presence of reduced walking speed and/or HGS in addi-
tion to low ASMM. The criteria proposed by Baumgartner </p>

<p>et al, 
19 however, can be used to diagnose sarcopenia based 
solely on the presence of reduced ASMM. </p>

<p>Quality of life </p>

<p>Quality of life was investigated using the 36-item Short-
Form Health Survey (SF-36) of the Medical Outcomes 
Study. This instrument has been translated and validated for 
use in Brazilian populations. 
22 The SF-36 is a multidimen-
sional questionnaire composed of 36 items, each of which 
is scored on a rating scale containing two to six response 
options. The items are distributed into eight domains, which 
can be grouped into two main categories: physical (physical 
functioning, bodily pain, general health perceptions, and 
physical role functioning) and mental (mental health, vital-
ity, social role functioning, and emotional role functioning) 
health. Each item is scored on a scale ranging from one to 
six. The questionnaire yields a total score of zero to 100, in 
which zero corresponds to the "worst" and 100 to the "best" 
possible health status. </p>

<p>statistical analysis </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs>, version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, 
NY, USA). Categorical variables were first summarized as 
absolute and relative frequencies, while continuous variables 
were described as mean values and standard deviations 
(n=70). The association between exposure and outcome 
variables (a diagnosis of sarcopenia according to EWGSOP 
and Baumgartner criteria) was evaluated using chi-square or 
Fisher's exact test. Odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals 
were also calculated. Exposure variables were categorized at 
the median, in the case of height and weight, or as described 
in the previous section. 
The distribution of quality-of-life scores was analyzed 
using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov method. Nonparametric 
Friedman tests were then used to investigate the associa-
tion between quality of life and a diagnosis of sarcopenia 
according to Baumgartner and EWGSOP criteria. Once the 
normality of each variable had been tested, Mann-Whitney 
U-tests were used to analyze nonparametric variables, while 
Student's t-tests for independent samples were used to com-
pare the mean value of parametric variables between subjects 
with and without sarcopenia. Results were considered sig-
nificant at P#0.05. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The sample consisted of 70 elderly quilombola subjects 
aged between 60 years and 85 years, with a mean age of </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>silva neto et al </p>

<p>65.58±6.67 years. Twenty-six participants lived in the 
Malhadinha community, while 44 lived in the Córrego Fundo 
community. The prevalence of sarcopenia in the sample was 
10.0% (n=7) according to EWGSOP criteria and 15.7% 
(n=11) according to the Baumgartner cutoffs. 
Prevalence rates per sex are shown in Table 1. Elderly 
quilombola females were four times more likely than males to 
receive a diagnosis of sarcopenia according to Baumgartner, 
but not EWGSOP, criteria. Participants were then divided 
by their median age into two groups. The prevalence of 
sarcopenia did not differ between younger and older subjects. 
Most patients with the disorder were illiterate, although the 
association between sarcopenia and education level was not 
found to be significant. 
MMSE scores showed that all participants had sufficient 
intellectual ability to complete the tasks involved in this 
study. The analysis of physical activity levels showed that 
most subjects were active to very active, and all sedentary 
subjects were diagnosed as having sarcopenia according to 
both sets of criteria. Participants who were active to very 
active were at least six times less likely to develop sarcopenia 
than those who were irregularly active or sedentary. These 
findings suggest that physical activity may be protective 
against this condition. 
When sarcopenia was diagnosed solely on the basis of 
ASMM levels, subjects with the condition were found to have 
lower body weight than the remainder of the sample, although 
the two groups did not differ in height. BMI values suggested 
that subjects who met both diagnostic criteria for sarcopenia 
were either normal (EWGSOP: n=5; and Baumgartner: n=6) 
or underweight (EWGSOP: n=2; and Baumgartner: n=5). 
Body composition data demonstrated that individuals with 
sarcopenia had normal waist circumference and fat mass 
percentage, as well as low-to-moderate cardiovascular risk 
(CVR). Interestingly, fat mass percentages were found to 
be elevated in 67.17% (n=47) of the sample. According to 
Baumgartner criteria, subjects with low-to-moderate CVR 
were eight times more likely to develop sarcopenia than those 
with high CVR. Patients with sarcopenia showed low HGS 
and ASMM values but had normal gait speed. 
The analysis of quality-of-life assessments showed that 
subjects with sarcopenia obtained lower scores on the pain 
and physical aspects domain of the SF-36 than those without 
the condition, as described in Table 2. Additionally, the social 
and emotional domains of the SF-36 were influenced by 
lean mass percentage. A negative correlation was identified 
between a diagnosis of sarcopenia according to both clas-
sification criteria and the following domains of the SF-36: </p>

<p>physical role functioning (Baumgartner: P=0.014; and 
EWGSOP: P=0.012), bodily pain (Baumgartner: P=0.001; 
and EWGSOP: P=0.001), social role functioning (Baum-
gartner: P=0.036; and EWGSOP: P=0.042), and emotional 
role functioning (Baumgartner: P=0.001; and EWGSOP: 
P=0.002). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Age-associated changes in body composition have been 
investigated by several studies. 
23 However, the repercussions 
of these alterations and their impact on the quality of life of 
elderly subjects have not been entirely elucidated, 
24 especially 
in quilombola populations. 
Although several methods are available for the assess-
ment of body composition in elderly populations, DEXA is 
among the most reliable tools for this purpose and is consid-
ered the ideal method to diagnose sarcopenia in multiracial 
patients. 
25 Unfortunately, its routine use in clinical practice 
is impractical, especially in small cities or rural areas such 
as the quilombola communities near Brejinho do Nazaré, in 
the state of Tocantins. 
The results of this study showed that quilombola elderly 
experienced significant alterations in their body mass, with 
more than half the sample showing elevated fat mass percent-
ages and 30% being overweight or obese. The sample also 
showed an elevated prevalence of sarcopenia, although this 
value was higher when estimated using Baumgartner (15%) 
than EWGSOP (10%) criteria. The findings described herein 
corroborate those of previous studies 
11,26 on the prevalence of 
sarcopenia in elderly Black populations. However, no studies 
of this nature had ever been performed in a quilombola 
community in Brazil. The discrepancies between various 
diagnostic methods for sarcopenia have been investigated by 
several studies. 
27,28 In this investigation, the cutoff value sug-
gested by Baumgartner was less accurate than that specified 
by the EWGSOP because it does not consider functioning 
and physical performance, both of which have been found to 
predict fragility, mortality, mobility incidents, disability, and 
the risk of institutionalization and hospitalization in elderly 
populations. 
10 However, the Baumgartner criteria were more 
sensitive in detecting sarcopenia because reductions in lean 
mass predict alterations in strength and walking speed. </p>

<p>11   Therefore, additional studies comparing the use of different 
criteria and cutoff points in this population are required, as is 
the adaptation of the said criteria and cutoffs to other racial/ 
ethnic groups. 
27,28 There is an urgent need for a consensus on 
the best method to diagnose sarcopenia in racial and ethnic 
groups such as the quilombola population. </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>sarcopenia and quality of life in quilombola elderly in Brazil </p>

<p>Table 1 association and odds ratios for sarcopenia according to eWGsOP and Baumgartner criteria and sociodemographic and 
clinical features of quilombola elderly (n=70) </p>

<p>EWGSOP 
Baumgartner </p>

<p>Sarcopenia, 
n (%) </p>

<p>No sarcopenia, 
n (%) </p>

<p>P-value OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Sarcopenia, 
n (%) </p>

<p>No sarcopenia, 
n (%) </p>

<p>P-value OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Sociodemographic variables </p>

<p>Sex 
0.228 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.051 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Male 
5 (16.1) 
26 (83.9) 
3.558 
(0.614-9.765) </p>

<p>8 (25.8) 
23 (74.2%) 
4.174 
(1.003-17.378) </p>

<p>Female 
2 (5.1) 
37 (94.9) 
1 
3 (7.7) 
36 (92.3%) 
1 </p>

<p>Age (years) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.692 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.932 </p>

<p>#64 
3 (7.7) 
36 (92.3) 
0.563 
(0.116-2.725) </p>

<p>6 (15.4) 
33 (84.6) 
0.945 
(0.259-3.446) </p>

<p>$65 
4 (12.9) 
27 (87.1) 
1 
5 (16.1) 
26 (83.9) 
1.000 </p>

<p>Education (years) 
0.694 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.506 </p>

<p>Illiterate 
5 (11.9) 
37 (88.1) 
1.757 
(0.316-9.760) </p>

<p>8 (19.0) 
34 (81.0) 
1.961 
(0.472-8.143) </p>

<p>literate 
2 (7.1) 
26 (92.9) 
1 
3 (10.7) 
25 (89.3) 
1.000 </p>

<p>Cognitive function and physical activity level </p>

<p>MMSE </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.438 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.768 </p>

<p>#19 
4 (13.8) 
25 (86.2) 
2.027 
(0.418-9.837) </p>

<p>5 (17.2) 
24 (82.8) 
1.215 
(0.333-4.439) </p>

<p>$20 
3 (7.3) 
38 (92.7) 
1 
6 (14.6) 
35 (85.4) 
1 </p>

<p>IPAQ score 
0.041 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Infrequently active + 
sedentary </p>

<p>3 (33.3) 
6 (66.7) 
7.125 
(1.280-9.675) </p>

<p>4 (44.4) 
5 (55.6) 
6.171 
(1.333-28.572) </p>

<p>Very active + active 
4 (6.6) 
57 (93.4) 
1 
7 (11.5) 
54 (88.5) 
1 </p>

<p>Sample characteristics, multivariate adjustments, and odds ratios </p>

<p>Anthropometric measures and body composition </p>

<p>Weight (kg) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.428 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.045 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>#64.5 
5 (14.3) 
30 (87.5) 
2.750 
(0.496-5.246) </p>

<p>9 (25.7) 
26 (74.3) 
5.712 
(1.135-28.748) </p>

<p>$64.6 
2 (5.7) 
33 (84.3) 
1 
2 (5.7) 
33 (94.3) 
1 </p>

<p>Height (m) 
1.000 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.743 </p>

<p>#1.55 
4 (11.4) 
31 (88.6) 
1.376 
(0.285-6.658) </p>

<p>5 (14.3) 
30 (85.7) 
0.806 
(0.221-2.932) </p>

<p>$1.56 
3 (8.6) 
32 (91.4) 
1 
6 (17.1) 
29 (82.9) 
1 </p>

<p>BMI (kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
0.094 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>#27 
7 (14.3) 
42 (85.7) 
na 
11 (22.4) 
38 (77.6) 
na </p>

<p>.27 
0 (0.0) 
21 (100.0) 
0 (0.0) 
21 (100) </p>

<p>WC (cm) 
0.331 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.105 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>normal 
7 (12.5) 
49 (87.5) 
na 
11 (19.6) 
45 (80.4) 
na </p>

<p>Increased 
0 (0.0) 
14 (100) 
0 (0.0) 
14 (100) </p>

<p>WHR (cm) 
0.130 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>low + moderate risk 5 (16.7) 
25 (83.3) 
3.800 
(0.683-21.131) </p>

<p>9 (30.0) 
21 (70.0) 
8.143 
(1.608-41.238) </p>

<p>high risk 
2 (5.0) 
38 (95.0) 
1 
2 (5.0) 
38 (95.0) 
1 </p>

<p>%FM 
0.350 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>normal 
5 (21.7) 
18 (78.3) 
6.250 
(1.110-35.202) </p>

<p>8 (34.8) 
15 (65.2) 
7.822 
(1.84-33.365) </p>

<p>Increased 
2 (4.3) 
45 (95.7) 
1 
3 (6.4) 
44 (93.6) 
1 </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>Table 2 Quality of life of quilombola elderly with and without sarcopenia according to eWGsOP and Baumgartner criteria (n=70) </p>

<p>EWGSOP 
Baumgartner </p>

<p>Variables 
Sarcopenia, 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>No sarcopenia, 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>P-value 
Sarcopenia, 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>No sarcopenia, 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>PF </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>72.14 (13.18) 
72.61 (15.42) 
0.938 
65.00 (19.36) 
73.98 (13.95) 
0.070 
PrF </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>61.79 (24.69) 
82.36 (18.81) 
0.028* 
65.46 (24.31) 
83.07 (18.33) 
0.015* 
BP </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>62.86 (25.63) 
80.66 (20.16) 
0.067 
56.06 (23.98) 
83.14 (17.90) 
0.001* 
GhP </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>72.86 (13.09) 
70.86 (16.65) 
0.760 
63.54 (21.73) 
72.46 (14.85) 
0.095 
VIT </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>70.71 (14.56) 
72.59 (14.68) 
0.750 
65.45 (12.23) 
73.69 (13.59) 
0.085 
srF </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>65.36 (21.04) 
74.36 (19.67) 
0.220 
62.46 (20.17) 
75.51 (19.26) 
0.037* 
erF </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>70.48 (28.70) 
84.44 (18.14) 
0.127 
61.82 (27.01) 
87.01 (15.20) 
0.002* 
Mh </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>77.71 (14.94) 
75.78 (18.91) 
0.795 
67.82 (23.57) 
77.49 (17.18) 
0.111 </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Parametric variable: student's t-test for independent samples; 
b nonparametric variable: Mann-Whitney U-test. *P=0.05. 
Abbreviations: BP, bodily pain; erF, emotional role functioning; eWGsOP, european Working Group on sarcopenia in Older People; GhP, general health perceptions; 
Mh, mental health; PF, physical functioning; PrF, physical role functioning; srF, social role functioning; VIT, vitality. </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>silva neto et al </p>

<p>The increased likelihood of loss of lean mass in males 
according to the criteria specified by Baumgartner et al 
19 may 
be partly attributed to the reduction in testosterone and growth 
hormone levels observed with advancing age. 
29,30 Interest-
ingly, when sarcopenia was diagnosed based on functional 
capacity in addition to lean mass loss, no significant sex 
differences in its prevalence were observed. These findings 
suggest that, although elderly subjects with sarcopenia do 
show reductions in lean mass, their HGS may be preserved, 
regardless of their sex. 
Unlike most other studies in the literature, 
27,31 this investi-
gation identified no association between age and a diagnosis 
of sarcopenia according to either set of criteria. This may be 
partly explained by the relatively young age of the sample, 
as well as the fact that all participants were at least 60 years 
of age. In a recent systematic review, Cruz-Jentoft et al </p>

<p>32   found that age was not consistently reported in studies of </p>

<p>sarcopenia: while some investigations report mean values for 
whole samples, others report age ranges or break this variable 
down into categories, preventing a comprehensive analysis 
of the relationship between age and sarcopenia. 
The high level of physical activity reported by the qui-
lombola population proved to be a protective factor against 
the development of sarcopenia. This result corroborates the 
findings of several previous studies 
9,33,34 on the association 
between sarcopenia and lifestyle factors in elderly popula-
tions, which found that subjects who report little to no physi-
cal activity are at higher risk of developing both sarcopenia 
and disability than those with high activity levels. As such, 
interventions which aim to promote or maintain high levels of 
physical activity, such as resistance training, may be a useful 
tool for the prevention and treatment of sarcopenia. 
35 These 
interventions have been found to have a beneficial effect on 
muscle mass, strength, and physical function. 
7 Although there </p>

<p>Table 1 (Continued) </p>

<p>EWGSOP 
Baumgartner </p>

<p>Sarcopenia, 
n (%) </p>

<p>No sarcopenia, 
n (%) </p>

<p>P-value OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Sarcopenia, 
n (%) </p>

<p>No sarcopenia, 
n (%) </p>

<p>P-value OR 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>Relative ASMM 
,0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>,0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>normal 
0 (0.0) 
59 (100) 
na 
0 (0.0) 
59 (100) 
na </p>

<p>Increased 
7 (100) 
4 (36.4) 
11 (100) 
0 (0.0) </p>

<p>Physical performance </p>

<p>HGS 
,0.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>normal 
0 (0.0) 
46 (100) 
na 
3 (6.5) 
43 (93.5) 
0.140 
(0.33-0.592) 
Decreased 
7 (29.2) 
17 (70.8) 
8 (33.3) 
16 (66.7) 
1 
GS (m/s) 
normal 
7 (10.0) 
63 (90.0) 
na 
11 (15.7) 
59 (84.3) 
na 
reduced 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) 
0 (0.0) </p>

<p>Notes: relative asMM is the appendicular skeletal muscle mass divided by the square of participant height. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>results obtained using Fisher's exact test. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Variables separated 
by median values. 
Abbreviations: %FM, fat mass percentage; ASMM, appendicular skeletal muscle mass; BMI, body mass index; CI, confidence interval; EWGSOP, European Working Group 
on sarcopenia in Older People; Gs, gait speed; hGs, handgrip strength; IPaQ, International Physical activity Questionnaire; MMse, Mini -Mental state examination; Or, odds 
ratio; na, not available; Wc, waist circumference; Whr, waist-to-hip ratio. </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>sarcopenia and quality of life in quilombola elderly in Brazil </p>

<p>is some disagreement in the literature as to the ideal exercise 
program for subjects with sarcopenia, resistance training has 
yielded positive results in these populations due to its effects 
on skeletal muscle hypertrophy. </p>

<p>36   All subjects who met both diagnostic criteria for sarcope-
nia were either normal (EWGSOP: n=5; and Baumgartner: 
n=6) or underweight (EWGSOP: n=2; and Baumgartner: 
n=5). This result corroborates the results of previous studies, 
which reported a negative association between BMI and 
sarcopenia, whereby subjects with low BMI were more 
likely to develop the disorder, even in rural elderly popula-
tions. 
37 In the Brazilian population, Da Silva et al 
38 obtained 
a similar finding in both men and women and found that 
social conditions such as low income, low educational levels, 
loneliness, and lifestyle factors may also be associated with 
sarcopenia. 
HGS was associated with sarcopenia according to both 
classification criteria, suggesting that the maintenance of 
HGS may be important for adequate functioning and may 
have a protective effect against sarcopenia. Studies show 
that muscle strength decreases more rapidly than muscle 
mass, suggesting that aging may compromise the quality 
of muscle tissue. 
35 Researchers have also found that muscle 
mass maintenance or gain may not prevent the age-related 
decline in muscle strength. 
39 Low HGS value is also a prog-
nostic factor for falls, cognitive impairment, hospitaliza-
tion, cardiovascular disease, and mortality. 
39 These findings 
underscore the importance of prevention and rehabilitation 
interventions directed at HGS. 
Functional independence is crucial for healthy aging 
and has been found to be associated with both functional 
capacity and quality of life in elderly populations. 
40,41 The 
physical role functioning and bodily pain scores of subjects 
with sarcopenia (diagnosed according to either classifica-
tion criteria) were lower than those reported by individuals 
without the condition. Both domains are part of the physical 
component of HRQOL. These findings suggest that sar-
copenia may have a greater effect on physical health than 
on mental health. According to the literature, low muscle 
strength and low muscle mass may both be associated with 
poor quality of life. 
42,43 In a study performed by Sayer et al, </p>

<p>44   the relationship between HGS and HRQOL was evaluated in 
2,987 men and women aged between 59 years and 73 years. 
HRQOL was evaluated using the SF-36, while a hand-held 
dynamometer was used to measure HGS. The study found 
that low HGS was associated with lower scores on the physi-
cal functioning, physical role functioning, general health 
perceptions, vitality, and bodily pain scales of the SF-36 </p>

<p>and was therefore related to both sarcopenia and general-
ized frailty. A comparative study of HRQOL in subjects 
with "sarco-osteopenia" and healthy adults found that the 
former obtained lower scores on the physical functioning, 
vitality, physical role functioning, and emotional role func-
tioning domains than the latter, which is consistent with the 
impact of sarcopenia on HRQOL. 
45 Sarcopenia had a nega-
tive impact on the quality of life of quilombola subjects, as 
shown by the correlational analysis performed in this study. 
As such, future studies may wish to develop a measure of 
HRQOL specific to sarcopenia. 
This study had some limitations, such as the absence 
of a validated diagnostic protocol for sarcopenia in Brazil-
ian elderly. Additionally, the cross-sectional nature of this 
investigation precludes the assignment of cause and effect 
relationships to the variables studied. Nevertheless, our study 
was able to provide prevalence estimates of sarcopenia in a 
population that has only been scarcely studied. The advan-
tages of this study include its well-characterized sample of 
both men and women and its clear geographical focus, as 
well as the fact that it is the first investigation of sarcopenia 
in quilombola elderly. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The high prevalence of sarcopenia in quilombola elderly is a 
public health emergency, not least due to the impact of this 
condition on quality of life, as shown in this study. Although 
there does not appear to be a single consensual definition of 
sarcopenia in the literature, our study showed that, regardless 
of the diagnostic criteria used, this condition was significantly 
associated with quality of life. 
We also found that diagnostic criteria for sarcopenia 
should include reductions in lean mass in addition to mea-
sures of functioning and physical performance, because some 
subjects showed the former symptom without any alteration 
of the latter two. Additionally, all subjects showed adequate 
physical fitness, reinforcing the need for prophylactic inter-
ventions to promote high physical activity levels, because 
reductions in lean mass and muscle strength are prognostic 
of impaired physical performance. 
In this study, both the EWGSOP and Baumgartner 
criteria were applied to an elderly quilombola population. 
Although both were effective in diagnosing sarcopenia, we 
under score the need for consensus diagnostic criteria that 
consider patients' ethnic and/or racial backgrounds. 
This study may serve as a basis for future investigations 
of the body composition of elderly quilombola subjects, for 
the development of prevention and rehabilitation strategies </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>silva neto et al </p>

<p>for sarcopenia, as well as the elaboration of assessment 
instruments to measure HRQOL in quilombola elderly with 
this condition. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>The authors thank the Mature University Program (Program 
University of Maturidade-UMA) of the Federal University 
of Tocantins, the Graduate Program in Health Sciences and 
Technology of the University of Brasilia, and the Arai Kamin-
ish and Costa Laboratory, Tocantins, Brazil. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>Luiz Sinésio Silva Neto contributed to project development, 
researcher training, data collection, as well as manuscript 
drafting and revision. Margô GO Karnikowski contributed to 
data analysis, the description of study results, and manuscript 
drafting. Neila B Osório was involved in data collection 
and manuscript drafting. Leonardo C Pereira took part in 
manuscript drafting. Marcilio B Mendes was involved in data 
collection. Dayani Galato contributed to data analysis. Liana 
B Gomide Matheus contributed to manuscript revision. João 
Paulo C Matheus took part in project design, in the critical 
reading of the manuscript, and approved the final version 
of this article. He is also responsible for the accuracy and 
integrity of this work. All authors contributed toward data 
analysis, drafting and critically revising the paper and agree 
to be accountable for all aspects of the work. </p>

<p>Disclosure </p>

<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </p>



<p>International Journal of General Medicine </p>

<p>Publish your work in this journal </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript here: http://www.dovepress.com/international-journal-of-general-medicine-journal </p>

<p>The International Journal of General Medicine is an international, 
peer-reviewed open-access journal that focuses on general and internal 
medicine, pathogenesis, epidemiology, diagnosis, monitoring and treat-
ment protocols. The journal is characterized by the rapid reporting of 
reviews, original research and clinical studies across all disease areas. </p>

<p>A key focus is the elucidation of disease processes and management 
protocols resulting in improved outcomes for the patient. The manu-
script management system is completely online and includes a very 
quick and fair peer-review system. Visit http://www.dovepress.com/ 
testimonials.php to read real quotes from published authors. </p>

<p>International Journal of General Medicine 2016:9 </p>

<p>submit your manuscript | www.dovepress.com </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>

<p>Dovepress </p>



</text></tei>