<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4555593" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background: Youth sports programs are extremely popular throughout the United States, with children starting formal sports 
participation as young as 4 years. This places children at greater risk for concussions and other trauma. </p>

<p>Purpose: To describe the epidemiology of concussions sustained during participation in 9 organized sports prior to participation in 
high school athletics. </p>

<p>Methods: Over an 11-year span from January 2002 to December 2012, the authors reviewed the concussions sustained by ath-
letes aged 4 to 13 years while playing basketball, baseball, football, gymnastics, hockey, lacrosse, soccer, softball, and wrestling, 
as evaluated in emergency departments (EDs) in the United States and captured by the National Electronic Injury Surveillance Sys-
tem (NEISS) database of the US Consumer Product Safety Commission. </p>

<p>Study Design: Descriptive epidemiology study. </p>

<p>Results: There were 4864 (national estimate [NE] ¼ 117,845) youth athletes evaluated in NEISS EDs as sustaining concussions 
from 2002 to 2012. Except for the year 2007, concussion frequencies trended upward throughout the 11-year time frame as well as 
with increasing age. Loss of consciousness (LOC) occurred in 499 cases (NE, 12,129; 10%). Football had the highest frequency of 
concussions, with 2013 (NE, 51,220; 41%), followed by basketball, with 977 (NE, 22,099; 20%), and soccer, with 801 (NE, 18,916; 
17%). The majority of concussions were treated in the outpatient setting, with 4444 (91.4%) patients being treated and released; 
412 (9%) patients required admission and were found to have increased frequencies of LOC (n ¼ 17; 18.0%) compared with LOC in 
the total group (n ¼ 499, 10%). The total number of player-to-player injury mechanisms mirrored the total number of concussions 
by year, which increased throughout the 11-year span, except for the year 2007. Subgroup analysis of athletes aged 4 to 7 years 
demonstrated a difference in the mechanism of injury distribution, with a ball-to-head mechanism increase of 5% from 15% to 20% 
and a player-to-other object mechanism of injury increase by more than double to 13% compared with the entire cohort over the 
11-year time frame. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Within the 4-to 13-year age range, there were a significant number of young athletes who presented to EDs with con-
cussion as a result of playing organized sports. The 4-to 7-year age group had a disproportionately higher player-to-other object 
mechanism of injury. </p>

<p>Clinical Relevance: Younger children are more susceptible to long-term sequelae from head injuries, and therefore, improved sys-
tems of monitoring for these athletes are required to monitor the patterns of injury, identify risk factors, and develop evidence-
based prevention programs. </p>

<p>Keywords: concussion; epidemiology; NEISS; pediatrics; head injuries </p>

<p>Concussions are mild traumatic brain injuries that are 
generally self-limiting and are defined as a traumatically 
induced transient disturbance of brain function. 
3,8 It is 
believed that blows to the head that impart a linear and/ 
or rotational force produce concussions. 
3,8 Experiments 
in rat models reveal that the brain has an increased sus-
ceptibility to a second injury until normal cellular homeo-
stasis has returned. 
3,14,18 Furthermore, studies in animal 
models and humans reveal that second hits result in pro-
gressively more significant metabolic and cognitive </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to David Buzas, MD, Department of 
Orthopaedic Surgery, Wayne State University, 10000 Telegraph Road, 
Taylor, MI 48180, USA (e-mail: dbuzas@med.wayne.edu). </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Wayne State University, Taylor, 
Michigan, USA. 
The authors declared that they have no conflicts of interest in the 
authorship and publication of this contribution. </p>

<p>The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine, 2(4), 2325967114528460 
DOI: 10.1177/2325967114528460 </p>

<p>ª The Author(s) 2014 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>This open-access article is published and distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution -NonCommercial -No Derivatives License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/), which permits the noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction of the article in any medium, provided the original author and source are 
credited. You may not alter, transform, or build upon this article without the permission of the Author(s). For reprints and permission queries, please visit SAGE's Web site 
at http://www.sagepub.com/journalsPermissions.nav. </p>

<p>dysfunction. 
3,14,15,18-21 In young rat models selected for 
interspecies age equivalence, it was found that during the 
recovery period, the brain functions at a reduced capacity 
and is less responsive to stimulation. 
14,18 Also, in these 
young rat models, metabolic and cognitive dysfunction can 
be potentiated, resulting in an extended recovery time if the 
brain is challenged with cognitive or physical exertion. </p>

<p>14,18 </p>

<p>Data from these studies are extrapolated to the immature 
brain of the developing human child, and it is surmised that 
youth athletes are more susceptible to functional and meta-
bolic perturbations than are their adult counterparts. In 
these same youth rat models it was also found that recovery 
takes longer because of synaptic pathways being less devel-
oped, which when extrapolated to the developing human 
child would put the child at an increased risk for repeat/sec-
ondary injuries. 
3,14,18 Historically, very few investigations 
and monitoring of concussions have focused on competitive 
athletes prior to participation in high school sports. There-
fore, valid comparisons with concussions in more mature 
athletes may not exist. 
Concussions can occur in any sport but are more com-
monly seen in contact or collision sports such as football, 
hockey, rugby, soccer, and basketball. 
8,9 Calculated esti-
mates of sports-related concussions range from 1.6 to 3.8 
million per year, 
9 with the majority of concussions occur-
ring in football players 
7,13 and as many as 50% going unre-
ported. 
8 Football, basketball, and soccer were the sports 
with the greatest number of traumatic brain injuries 
(which includes but is not specific to concussions) for chil-
dren between the ages of 5 and 18 years in the time span 
from 2001 to 2005, based on a study analyzing emergency 
room visits. 
4 During this period, it was estimated that there 
were 2.4 million sports-and recreation-related injuries 
evaluated in hospital emergency departments (EDs). </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Monitoring for head injuries has increased significantly 
at the professional and collegiate levels but to a lesser 
extent at the high school level. 
5,6,8,10,13,17 Forty-two states 
and the District of Columbia have passed guidelines for 
the diagnosis and treatment of concussion in sports. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>These guidelines range from coaches receiving additional 
training in the recognition of concussions to mandatory 
evaluation and clearance by a trained medical profes-
sional before the athlete can return to play after a concus-
sion has been alleged. </p>

<p>6,8,11 </p>

<p>The objective of this study was to describe the epidemiol-
ogy of youth concussions (aged 4-13 years) for 9 sports (bas-
ketball, baseball, football, gymnastics, hockey, lacrosse, 
soccer, softball, and wrestling) that presented to US EDs 
over an 11-year period from January 2002 to December 
2012 using a nationally representative database. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>National Electronic Injury Surveillance System </p>

<p>Data were collected from the National Electronic Injury 
Surveillance System (NEISS), a database maintained by 
the US Consumer Product Safety Commission (CPSC) 
that collects information on injuries that present to US </p>

<p>EDs at a network of 100 hospitals. NEISS hospitals are a 
stratified probability sample of hospitals in the United 
States and its territories. The participating hospitals have 
at least 6 beds and a 24-hour ED where trained coders 
review all ED records daily and enter demographic, injury, 
and treatment information into the NEISS database. Each 
case is assigned 1 or 2 CPSC-specific product codes that 
designate what products or activities were involved at the 
time of injury. 
16 National estimates can then be calculated 
by summing the number of cases that present to each 
NEISS ED after using a multiplier based on the size of the 
hospital and the number of hospitals similarly sized across 
the United States. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Utilization of NEISS </p>

<p>We selected the 9 sports that we believed had the greatest 
contact/risk for concussion during play. Then, one author 
(D.B.) queried the NEISS database for all basketball-, 
baseball-, football-, gymnastics-, hockey-, lacrosse-, soccer-, 
softball-, and wrestling-related head injuries (product codes 
1205, 5041, 1211, 1272, 3272, 1215, 1267, 5034, and 1270, 
respectively, and body part location code 75, with a diagnosis 
of concussion) spanning from January 2002 to December 
2012. The NEISS data set provides patient demographic 
information (age, race, and sex) on the injury sustained, 
diagnosis, disposition, location of injury occurrence (school, 
place of recreation, home, public property, street, or high-
way), and a brief narrative describing how the injury 
occurred. Narratives are a relatively new feature that was 
added to the NEISS database on January 1, 2002, but are 
highly variable as to their content and length. However, the 
narrative description of the activity being performed when 
the injury occurred was of particular interest. This included 
information on injury mechanisms (player-to-player, ball-to-
head, player-to-ground, or player-to-other object), loss of 
consciousness (LOC), and concurrently sustained fractures. </p>

<p>Exclusion Criteria </p>

<p>Each case also had a locale for where the injury occurred 
(eg, home, ranch/farm, street or highway, other public 
property, mobile home, industrial place, school, place of 
recreation or sport, and not recorded). With the goal of tar-
geting concussions that occurred during organized sports 
participation, we excluded from our data set any case that 
did not occur at school or a place of recreation/sport, or did 
not have a location of injury recorded. The narratives pro-
vided were also reviewed for each case and sport. All cases 
in which the narrative described situations other than 
organized competitive sports participation at the time of 
injury were excluded. Some examples of narrative phrases 
that resulted in exclusion were ''play with [a sibling/family 
member],'' ''play at home,'' ''struck with bat at batting 
cage,'' ''playing catch,'' ''ran into coach,'' ''hit head on metal 
sewer grate,'' ''pool basketball,'' ''injured at daycare,'' 
''playing with ball during gymnastics,'' ''hanging on soccer 
goal,'' ''goalpost fell onto player,'' and ''climbing soccer 
net.'' Those cases in which the narratives described 
bystanders who were injured in the stands or individuals </p>

<p> 
The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine </p>

<p>who were injured while helping at practice were excluded. 
Cases where the injury occurred from another event and 
the individual was only identified as an athlete involved 
in a given sport were excluded. The total number of cases 
excluded was 748 (13% of all cases), the majority of which 
were due to play at a locale other than one associated with 
organized play. </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>Descriptive statistical analysis was performed using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft Corp</rs>, Redmond, Washington, 
USA) and <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> statistics <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">v22</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corp</rs>, Armonk, New 
York, USA). Subset analysis was performed on the ath-
letes who sustained a fracture, those who required hospi-
tal admittance, and those whose ages ranged from 4 to 7 
years. National estimates of youth concussions relating 
to 9 sports (basketball, baseball, football, gymnastics, 
hockey, lacrosse, soccer, softball, and wrestling), LOC, 
and in the 4-to 7-year age group were also calculated 
utilizing NEISS hospitals as a stratified national sam-
pling. 
16 The Pearson correlation coefficient was obtained 
to quantify the correlation between individual sports and 
the overall frequencies of concussions with each succes-
sive year. An alpha of .05 and an r &gt; 0.602 indicated sta-
tistical significance. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The total number of cases was 4864 (national estimate 
[NE], 117,845). The distribution of male-to-female athletes 
over the 11-year span is provided in Table 1. 
The prevalence of male concussions was the overwhelm-
ing majority over the entire 11-year time frame (Figure 1). 
Concussion frequencies trended up throughout the 
11-year time frame with increasing age of the players (Fig-
ure 2). The number of concussions is broken down by race 
in Table 2. 
Racial distributions were consistent throughout the 
study period. ''Other'' was defined as American Indian/ 
Alaskan Indian, Native Hawaiian/Pacific Islander, or any 
other race than the previously mentioned ones. The large 
majority (91%) of patients were treated as outpatients. Con-
cussion breakdown by disposition is provided in Table 3. 
The majority (60%) of concussions occurred at a place of 
recreation or sports. Concussion breakdown by location of 
injury is found in Table 4. 
In total, there were 499 concussions (NE, 12,128; 10%), in 
the entire cohort. The frequencies of players experiencing 
LOC had an overall upward trend (Figure 3). </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Entire Cohort by Sex (N ¼ 4864) </p>

<p>National Estimate 
No. of Concussions 
% of Cohort 
Mean Age, y 
Median Age, y 
Pearson r </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Youth athletes 
117,845 
4864 
100 
11.1 
12.0 
-
Male 
92,932 
3905 
80 
11.1 
12.0 
1.00 
Female 
24,913 
959 
20 
11.4 
12.0 
0.99 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Pearson correlation coefficient of the subgroup compared with the entire cohort. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>900 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012 
Number of concussions </p>

<p>Year </p>

<p>Sex DistribuƟon by Year </p>

<p>Female 
Male </p>

<p>Figure 1. The number of concussion cases, per year, by sex, 
in youth athletes presenting to NEISS emergency depart-
ments over an 11-year time frame. </p>

<p>4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 
13 
2012 
6 
7 
20 
21 
49 
104 120 186 220 337 
2011 
1 
8 
13 
31 
40 
57 
101 160 187 260 
2010 
1 
7 
9 
11 
32 
39 
77 
121 145 170 
2009 
2 
1 
12 
13 
24 
35 
65 
83 
123 159 
2008 
1 
4 
7 
11 
8 
25 
50 
44 
73 
100 
2007 
1 
5 
4 
9 
15 
17 
26 
51 
43 
84 
2006 
0 
3 
4 
4 
19 
21 
34 
53 
69 
75 
2005 
0 
3 
3 
6 
10 
15 
40 
51 
56 
76 
2004 
3 
7 
3 
10 
12 
17 
24 
38 
44 
75 
2003 
1 
4 
1 
6 
14 
17 
29 
41 
45 
71 
2002 
2 
4 
4 
4 
9 
22 
29 
34 
46 
71 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1400 </p>

<p>1600 </p>

<p>Number of Concussions </p>

<p>Years of Age </p>

<p>Concussions by Age </p>

<p>Figure 2. The number of concussions per year, and by age. </p>

<p>The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine 
Concussions in Youth Sports Over 11 Years 3 </p>

<p>The mechanism of injury with the greatest number of 
concussions was player-to-player, with a total of 1943 
(40%) concussions (Table 5, Figure 4). </p>

<p>The entire cohort contained a total of 34 fractures. 
The distribution of fractures by type is broken down 
in Table 6. Subgroup analysis of the players who sustained 
a concussion with a concurrent fracture demonstrated 4 
severe injuries, defined as ''no permanent functional dis-
ability but severe injury'' by the National Catastrophic 
Injury project at the University of North Carolina, 
12 con-
sisting of 2 skull fractures and 2 thoracic spine compres-
sion fractures. There was also a case associated with a 
subdural hematoma without a fracture. 
A subgroup for inpatient (admitted or transferred) ath-
letes was created and then analyzed (Table 7). The mechan-
ism of injury causing the greatest number of concussions 
was player-to-player (45%). Also, 83% of concussed youths 
in the inpatient subgroup were male (Table 8). 
All concussion cases with associated fractures were then 
grouped together, and fracture frequency was grouped by 
mechanism of injury (Table 9). 
The number of concussions by sport is broken down in 
Table 10. The frequency of concussions had an overall 
upward trend for each sport over the 11-year time span. </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Entire Cohort by Race (N ¼ 4864) </p>

<p>Race </p>

<p>No. of 
Concussions </p>

<p>% of All 
Concussions </p>

<p>Pearson 
r </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>White 
2339 
48 
1.00 
Black/African 
American </p>

<p>630 
13 
1.00 </p>

<p>Other 
351 
7 
0.99 
Not stated 
1544 
32 
1.00 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Pearson correlation coefficient of the subgroup compared with 
the entire cohort. </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Concussions by Treatment Disposition (N ¼ 4864) </p>

<p>Treatment </p>

<p>No. of 
Concussions </p>

<p>% of All 
Concussions </p>

<p>Outpatient treatment 
4444 
91 
Admitted or transferred 
412 
9 
Left against medical 
advice </p>

<p>4 
&lt;0.1 </p>

<p>No recorded disposition 
4 
&lt;0.1 </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
Concussions by Place of Occurrence (N ¼ 4864) </p>

<p>Occurrence </p>

<p>No. of 
Concussions </p>

<p>% of All 
Concussions </p>

<p>Pearson 
r </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Place of recreation or 
sports </p>

<p>2893 
60 
0.98 </p>

<p>School 
1185 
24 
0.85 
Not recorded 
786 
16 
0.90 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Pearson correlation coefficient of the subgroup compared with 
the entire cohort. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012 </p>

<p>LOC cases </p>

<p>Year </p>

<p>Loss of Conciousness by Year </p>

<p>Figure 3. Concussion cases associated with a loss of con-
sciousness (LOC) by year. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012 </p>

<p>Number of Concussions </p>

<p>Concussions by Mechanism of Injury </p>

<p>Concussions </p>

<p>Player-to-player </p>

<p>Ball-to-head </p>

<p>Player-to-ground </p>

<p>Player-to-other-object </p>

<p>Not specified </p>

<p>Figure 4. Number of concussions trended over the 11-year 
time frame by mechanism of injury. </p>

<p>TABLE 5 
Concussions by Mechanism of Injury (N ¼ 4864) </p>

<p>Mechanism of 
Injury </p>

<p>No. of 
Concussions </p>

<p>% of All 
Concussions </p>

<p>Mean 
Age, y </p>

<p>Median 
Age, y </p>

<p>Player-to-
player </p>

<p>1944 
40 
11.4 
12 </p>

<p>Player-to-
ground </p>

<p>856 
18 
11 
11 </p>

<p>Ball-to-head 
720 
15 
10.8 
11 
Player-to-
other object </p>

<p>271 
5 
10.6 
11 </p>

<p>Not specified 
1073 
22 
11.2 
12 </p>

<p>4 Buzas et al 
The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine </p>

<p>The frequency of concussions per sport, trended over the 
11-year time frame, is illustrated in Figure 5. 
A similar study published by Bakhos et al 
2 had an age 
cutoff of 8 years; however, we analyzed a subgroup of indi-
viduals from ages 4 to 7 years, which, to our knowledge, has 
never been reported on in the literature. The number of 
concussions in the 4-to 7-year-old subgroup was 277 (NE, 
6769; 6%). In this same subgroup, 19 (7%) required inpati-
ent treatment (Table 11). This subgroup was added so that 
any differences between younger and older youth athletes 
could be addressed in the development of future studies 
that focus more on this younger population. 
The player-to-player mechanism of injury was also the 
highest in this subgroup (n ¼ 71, 26%). The number of con-
cussions by mechanism of injury in this subgroup is given 
in Table 12. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our data report that football, basketball, and soccer are 
associated with the greatest number of concussions in 
decreasing order. Our data are consistent with previous 
studies that identify football as the sport associated with 
the greatest number of concussions. 
2,5,10 However, our data 
indicate basketball and soccer as the second and third high-
est sports associated with the greatest number of concus-
sions, which is in contrast to the study by Lincoln et al, </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>which found that lacrosse is second to football and soccer 
comes in third when males and females are grouped 
together. Lincoln et al 
10 conducted an epidemiologic study 
analyzing concussion frequencies in high school sports. 
They prospectively gathered data for 25 schools in a large 
public school system and reported 2651 concussions over 
an 11-year period. One factor that may contribute to the dif-
ference between that study and the present one is a poten-
tial difference in the popularity of sports between age 
groups. Another potential explanation for this difference 
between our study and that by Lincoln et al 
10 is the differ-
ences in the popularity of specific sports by geographic loca-
tion. 
1 The sequence of concussion prevalence by sports in 
our study matches that published by the Centers for Dis-
ease Control and Prevention 
4 in decreasing order: football, 
basketball, and soccer. 
All sports were found to have a high correlation of con-
cussion frequencies when compared with the entire group 
over the 11-year time span. The sports with the highest cor-
relation to the total number of concussions included football 
(r ¼ 1.00), basketball (r ¼ 1.00), and soccer (r ¼ 1.00). The 
sport with the lowest correlation was wrestling (r ¼ 0.95). 
Lacrosse had a 30-fold increase in the number of concussion 
cases. This may be attributed to an increasing popularity of 
the sport, as there was only 1 concussion associated with 
the sport in 2002, and/or to an increased awareness of con-
cussions associated with the sport. 
The increase in concussion frequencies by age may be 
because of an increasing number of participants as well as 
a more aggressive play by maturing athletes (see Figure 2). 
The number of concussions increased throughout the entire 
11-year time frame except from 2006 to 2007, in which there </p>

<p>TABLE 6 
Fractures by Type </p>

<p>Type of Fracture 
No. of Fractures 
% of All Fractures </p>

<p>Facial bones 
22 
65 
Clavicle 
3 
9 
Skull 
2 
6 
Distal radius 
2 
6 
Thoracic spine 
2 
6 
Forearm 
1 
3 
Toe 
1 
3 
Tibia/fibula 
1 
3 
Total 
34 
100 </p>

<p>TABLE 7 
Concussions Grouped by Mechanism of Injury 
in the Inpatient Subgroup (n ¼ 412) </p>

<p>Mechanism 
of Injury </p>

<p>No. of 
Concussions </p>

<p>% of Inpatient 
Subgroup </p>

<p>Mean 
Age, y </p>

<p>Median 
Age, y </p>

<p>Player-to-
player </p>

<p>185 
45 
11.7 
12 </p>

<p>Player-to-
ground </p>

<p>82 
20 
11.1 
12 </p>

<p>Ball-to-head 
49 
12 
10.8 
11 
Player-to-
other object </p>

<p>22 
5 
11.1 
12 </p>

<p>Not specified 
74 
18 
11.3 
12 </p>

<p>TABLE 8 
Patient Sex and Loss of Consciousness Distribution 
in the Inpatient Subgroup (n ¼ 412) </p>

<p>No. of 
Concussions </p>

<p>% of Inpatient 
Subgroup </p>

<p>Mean 
Age, y </p>

<p>Median 
Age, y </p>

<p>Loss of 
consciousness </p>

<p>74 
18 
11.4 
12 </p>

<p>Male 
61 
83 
11.4 
12 
Female 
13 
17 
11.2 
12 </p>

<p>TABLE 9 
Mechanism of Injury Distribution 
in the Fracture Subgroup </p>

<p>Fracture 
Subgroup </p>

<p>No. of 
Fractures </p>

<p>% of 
Fractures </p>

<p>Mean 
Age, y </p>

<p>Median 
Age, y </p>

<p>Total fractures 
34 
100 
11.5 
12 
Player-to-player 
16 
47 
11.4 
12 
Player-to-
ground </p>

<p>1 
3 
-
-</p>

<p>Ball-to-head 
8 
24 
11.6 
12 
Player-to-other 
object </p>

<p>4 
12 
10.3 
10 </p>

<p>Not specified 
5 
15 
12.4 
12 </p>

<p>The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine 
Concussions in Youth Sports Over 11 Years 5 </p>

<p>was a drop from 282 to 255 (see Figure 1). This decrease in 
concussions for the year 2007 is most likely due to a real drop 
in concussions for the year, as it is unlikely that awareness 
about concussions would decrease for that specific year. 
Furthermore, the proportion of males to females appeared 
to stay consistent (see Figure 1), and we do not believe that 
differences in sex played a significant role in the observed 
trends. The increasing trend in the number of concussions </p>

<p>for each age group with successive years may be because of 
an increased awareness by the involved parties (parents/ath-
letes/coaches) and therefore may explain the increasing 
trend with the progression in time. 
The frequency of LOC associated with concussion 
increased each year throughout the 11-year time frame 
except for 2011, which dropped to 8% from 11% in 2010 (see 
Figure 3). As the sample size for LOC is small, a possible 
explanation for the observed difference may be random 
chance. The frequency of LOC was strongly correlated 
(r ¼ 0.98) with the frequency of concussions over the same 
period. However, the frequency of LOC increased by 68% 
from 2008 to 2009 and by 29% from 2011 to 2012. This 
trend was reflected in the frequency of total number of 
concussions, which increased by 60% from 2008 to 2009 
and by 25% from 2011 to 2012. The increase in the preva-
lence of LOC closely correlated with the increase in the 
number of concussions, and therefore, a plausible explana-
tion may be an increased awareness and therefore report-
ing of concussion cases. An increased awareness is a better 
explanation for the increased LOC than a more aggressive 
style of play, as one would expect a disproportionate 
increase in the prevalence of LOC when compared with 
the prevalence of concussions if a more aggressive style 
of play was the case. 
We found that fractures occurred in older children 
(mean age, 11.5 years) and closely coincided with our </p>

<p>TABLE 10 
Concussions by Sport </p>

<p>Sport 
National Estimate 
No. of Concussions 
% of All Concussions 
Pearson r </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Increase </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Football 
51,220 
2013 
41 
1.00 
6.1Â 
Basketball 
22,099 
977 
20 
1.00 
3.6Â 
Soccer 
18,916 
801 
17 
1.00 
5.6Â 
Baseball 
12,610 
525 
11 
0.99 
2.8Â 
Softball 
4005 
146 
3 
0.98 
2.8Â 
Wrestling 
2824 
117 
2 
0.95 
4.2Â 
Lacrosse 
1600 
99 
2 
0.99 
30Â 
Hockey 
1550 
76 
2 
0.97 
5.5Â 
Gymnastics 
1550 
76 
2 
0.98 
6.0Â </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Pearson correlation coefficient comparing specified sport with the entire cohort. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Comparison in the number of concussions between years 2012 and 2002. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012 
Number of Concussions </p>

<p>Year </p>

<p>Concussions by year per sport </p>

<p>Soccer </p>

<p>GymnasƟcs 
Hockey </p>

<p>Lacrosse 
Basketball </p>

<p>Baseball </p>

<p>SoŌball 
Wrestling 
Football 
Total </p>

<p>Figure 5. Eleven-year trend on the number of concussions by 
sport. </p>

<p>TABLE 12 
Mechanism of Injury in the 4-to 7-Year Subgroup </p>

<p>Mechanism 
of Injury </p>

<p>No. of 
Concussions </p>

<p>% of Concussions 
in Subgroup </p>

<p>Mean 
Age, y </p>

<p>Median 
Age, y </p>

<p>Player-to-
player </p>

<p>71 
26 
6.4 
7 </p>

<p>Player-to-
ground </p>

<p>62 
22 
6.1 
6 </p>

<p>Ball-to-head 
55 
20 
6.1 
6 
Player-to-
other 
object </p>

<p>36 
13 
5.7 
6 </p>

<p>Not specified 
53 
19 
6.1 
7 </p>

<p>TABLE 11 
Patient Sex and Inpatient Distribution 
in the 4-to 7-Year Age Group (n ¼ 277) </p>

<p>No. of 
Concussions </p>

<p>% Concussions 
in Subgroup </p>

<p>Mean 
Age, y </p>

<p>Median 
Age, y </p>

<p>Male 
228 
82 
6.2 
6 
Female 
49 
18 
5.8 
6 
Inpatient 
treatment </p>

<p>19 
7 
6.2 
7 </p>

<p>6 Buzas et al 
The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine </p>

<p>overall data set mean age of 11.1 years. Within the frac-
ture subgroup, LOC occurred in 29% of patients, which 
is almost triple that of the overall frequency of 10% in the 
overall cohort. The majority (71%) of these fractures 
involved the head, demonstrating additional injuries to 
the head other than concussion. These data suggest that 
older children may be at greater risk for sustaining a frac-
ture because of more aggressive play by the maturing ath-
lete as well as increased forces associated with increasing 
body weight of the involved athletes. 
We found that fewer hospital admissions (7%) were 
observed in the 4-to 7-year-old subgroup versus the overall 
group (9%). The proportion of males (82%) versus females 
(18%) in this subgroup is equivocal to the entire group of 
(80% male, 20% female). The decreased frequency of frac-
tures with decreasing age may be explained by the fact that 
younger bones have greater plasticity and therefore may be 
less likely to fracture. Furthermore, this group consisted of 
lighter subjects, and it is hypothesized that there was 
reduced force transmission during collisions. The younger 
group may also be associated with an overall less aggres-
sive style of play. 
The ball-to-head mechanism of injury increased from 
15% in the overall cohort to 20% in the 4-to 7-year-old sub-
group. The player-to-other object mechanism of injury 
more than doubled from 6% in the overall cohort to 13% 
in the younger subgroup, suggesting that the origins of con-
cussions in this subgroup are drastically different from the 
older children. Consequently, this population would most 
likely require a different approach to interventions tar-
geted at reducing the number of concussions. The mechan-
ism-of-injury data suggests that interventions focusing on 
altering the environment, with the goal of removing objects 
or obstacles from or around the field of play, would have an 
increasing disproportionate benefit to this subgroup. The 
addition of protective head gear may also be of greater ben-
efit for the 4-to 7-year-old subgroup, which would target 
the ball-to-head mechanism of injury. 
Out of the entire cohort, 9% required hospital admis-
sion or transfer after presentation to the ED, suggesting 
a more serious injury. Of the concussions in the admitted 
subgroup, 18% were associated with LOC, which is 
almost double the overall group frequency of LOC 
(10%), further implying a more serious injury. Other-
wise, the other mechanisms of injury in this subgroup 
remained similar to the overall data. 
The NEISS data set provides valuable epidemiological 
information on concussion frequencies in youth athletics 
over a variety of sports. However, the heterogeneity of the 
narrative descriptions of the mechanism/situation around 
which the injury occurred leaves noteworthy gaps in the 
data set and therefore may be a source of information bias. 
This potential bias is an inherent weakness of the database 
and is out of our control. The creation of a national data-
base, with standardized narrative input, focused on head 
injuries associated with all levels of organized sports from 
youth leagues to the professional levels would be an invalu-
able tool in identifying risk factors associated with specific 
sports by age groups. A standardized national database 
may also provide a method for monitoring the effects of the </p>

<p>implementation of new safety measures, such as innovative 
protective equipment (eg, helmets, braces, mouth guards, 
pads, flooring, etc), rule changes, and education programs 
focusing on proper technique and injury prevention. 
Another potential source of bias would be an uneven geo-
graphic sampling of emergency rooms throughout the 
nation. The ED sampling is supposedly a national represen-
tation of all EDs in the country. As such, one assumption of 
this study is that clustering of departments in the sample is 
controlled. Another potential source of bias may occur in 
the method used to exclude cases. Excluding some of the 
accidental injuries outside the exact sport (eg, ''goalpost fell 
onto player'') may have introduced a measurement bias. 
The highly variable narrative is illustrated in the example 
above, such that the reviewer cannot know the circum-
stances involving the injury (eg, whether it was related to 
horseplay, during competitive play, or as an incidental 
occurrence in a nonathlete). We did not assume that these 
ambiguous cases were associated with competitive play, 
and therefore, our results may be an underestimate. How-
ever, these cases were within a small minority, and bias 
is believed to be minimal. 
Another potential source of bias in this study stems 
from the nature of reporting of concussions using the 
NEISS database. This study only takes into account the 
athletes with concussions who presented to the ED. It 
might be the case that these athletes are a minority of the 
total number of youth athletes suffering from concussion. 
Furthermore, the same group of athletes who presented to 
the ED may have experienced more severe concussions 
(eg, higher incidence of fractures, LOC, spine injury, etc). 
These biases may provide an underestimate and a greater 
severity of concussions than is actually the case. Future 
studies may be able to address this if a national database 
is used in which all concussion cases are reported at the 
time and location of occurrence (eg, on the playing field) 
such that the level of severity (eg, vomiting, LOC, and 
deteriorating symptoms) may be recorded and subse-
quently analyzed. 
Despite these limitations, the NEISS data set is the 
only nationally representative stratified probability sam-
ple of concussions occurring in youth athletics in the 
United States. It is the only system that allows querying 
of concussions occurring in athletes prior to participation 
in high school sports. Additionally, the stability of the 
NEISS database allows monitoring for changes over time 
by overall concussion prevalence or by specific sport. 
This study provides valuable information about risk of 
injury among youth athletes participating in pre-high 
school athletics. </p>



<p>The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine 
Concussions in Youth Sports Over 11 Years 7 </p>



<p>8 Buzas et al 
The Orthopaedic Journal of Sports Medicine </p>

</text></tei>