<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4310406" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background--Pulmonary artery pressure (PAP) is an important marker in cardiovascular disorders, being closely associated with 
morbidity and mortality. Noninvasive assessment by Doppler echocardiography is recommended by current guidelines. So far, the 
reliability of this method has been assessed only in small studies with contradictory results. Therefore, the aim of this study was to 
analyze the reliability of noninvasive PAP assessment by Doppler echocardiography compared to invasive measurements in a large 
patient population. </p>

<p>Methods and Results--We retrospectively analyzed data from a large tertiary cardiology department over 6 years in order to 
compare invasively measured PAP to estimated PAP from echocardiography examinations. N=15 516 patients fulfilled inclusion 
criteria and n=1695 patients with timely matched examinations (within 5 days) were analyzed. In n=1221 (72%) patients, 
pulmonary hypertension (PH) was diagnosed invasively (postcapillary PH: n=1122 [66%]; precapillary PH: n=99 [6%]). Systolic 
pulmonary artery pressure (sPAP) was 45.3AE15.5 mm Hg by Doppler echocardiography and 47.4AE16.4 mm Hg by right heart 
catheterization. Pearson's correlation coefficient was r=0.87 (P&lt;0.0001). Mean right atrial pressure (RAP) was 12.0AE5.7 mm Hg 
by right heart catheterization and was estimated to be 12.1AE6.6 mm Hg by echocardiography (r=0.82, P&lt;0.0001). Bland-Altman 
analysis showed a bias of À2.0 mm Hg for sPAP (95% limits of agreement À18.1 to +14.1 mm Hg) and +1.0 mm Hg for RAP (95% 
limits of agreement +0.1 to +1.9 mm Hg). Noninvasive diagnosis of pulmonary hypertension with Doppler echocardiography had a 
good sensitivity (87%) and specificity (79%), positive and negative predictive values (91% and 70%), as well as accuracy (85%) for a 
sPAP cut-off value of 36 mm Hg (AUC 0.91, P&lt;0.001, CI 0.90 to 0.93). </p>

<p>Conclusions--In this study, Doppler echocardiography proved to be a reliable method for the assessment of sPAP, being well 
suited to establish the noninvasive diagnosis of pulmonary hypertension in patients with cardiac diseases. ( J Am Heart Assoc. 
2014;3:e001103 doi: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103) </p>

<p>Key Words: Doppler echocardiography • pulmonary artery pressure • pulmonary hypertension • right heart catheterization </p>

<p>N umerous cardiac and pulmonary pathologies are </p>

<p>associated with an increase in pulmonary artery 
pressures (PAP), and multiple studies evidenced the prog-
nostic relevance of pulmonary hypertension (PH). This 
condition is characterized by an increase in mean pulmo-
nary arterial pressure and pulmonary vascular resistance, </p>

<p>leading to right heart failure and death if left untreated. 1-5 
Furthermore, even slightly elevated PAP may have adverse 
prognostic implications in the general population. 6 There-
fore, the measurement of PAP has gained wide acceptance 
in the assessment and follow-up of patients with cardiac or 
pulmonary disorders. 
Direct pressure measurement with right heart catheteriza-
tion is the reference method and "gold standard" for 
quantification of PAP; however, a noninvasive assessment of 
pulmonary artery systolic pressure (sPAP) by Doppler echo-
cardiography is feasible, and represents a keystone examina-
tion in suspected PH according to current guidelines. 7 
Furthermore, echocardiography may represent an important 
step in the diagnosis work-up in diseases in which prognosis 
may be largely affected by PH and may even differentiate 
the causes of PH. 8,9 However, a reliable noninvasive quanti-
fication by Doppler echocardiography is an important </p>

<p>prerequisite. </p>

<p>From the Department of Cardiology, Angiology, and Pneumology, University of 
Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany. 
Correspondence to: Sebastian Greiner, MD, Department of Cardiology, 
Angiology and Pneumology, University of Heidelberg, Im Neuenheimer Feld 
410, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany. E-mail: sebastian.greiner@med.uni-heidel-
berg.de </p>

<p>Received May 14, 2014; accepted July 18, 2014. 
ª 2014 The Authors. Published on behalf of the American Heart Association, </p>

<p>Inc., by Wiley Blackwell. This is an open access article under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License, which permits use, 
distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Assessment of sPAP by continuous-wave Doppler was first 
reported by Yock and Popp 30 years ago. 10 Right ventricular 
systolic pressure (RVSP) is calculated from the maximal flow 
velocity of the tricuspid valve regurgitation using the modified 
Bernoulli equation DP=49Vmax 2 , and adding an estimated 
RAP. 10 First publications of noninvasive sPAP measurements 
by Doppler echocardiography were very encouraging. 10-13 
Although assessment of RAP was simplified, a study by Chan 
et al 14 in 1987 suggested that this method of noninvasive 
PAP assessment is superior compared to other noninvasive 
approaches. 14 For many years, noninvasive PAP measurement 
by addition of RVSP and estimated RAP is advised and used in 
standard echocardiography routinely. 7,9,15 However, until now 
only studies with small and selected patient populations were 
conducted to assess correlation between sPAP measure-
ments by right heart catheterization and Doppler echocardi-
ography. Furthermore, some recent studies questioned the 
accuracy of noninvasively measured sPAP. 16-20 
Thus, in this study we aimed to analyze the diagnostic 
accuracy and reliability of noninvasive PAP assessment 
compared to invasive measurements in a large patient 
population of a high-turnover tertiary cardiac care center. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Study Protocol </p>

<p>The study was conducted retrospectively and is based on 
digitized data from right heart catheterizations and Doppler 
echocardiography examinations carried out at the Cardiology 
Department of the University Hospital of Heidelberg over 
6 years (Figure 1). This analysis was carried out fulfilling 
the standards of the Ethics Committee of the University of 
Heidelberg and in concordance with the Declaration of 
Helsinki. 
All patients included in the study had appropriate clinical 
indications for echocardiography. Indications for right heart 
catheterization are listed in Table 1. We identified 15 516 
consecutive patients with right heart catheterization and 
echocardiography examinations from July 1, 2007 through 
June 30, 2013 (Figure 1). In 3920 patients, a cardiac 
ultrasound examination was performed within 5 days before 
or after invasive examination. A number of the 2543 
echocardiographic examinations had to be excluded because 
PAP measurements were not explicitly documented (eg, 
tricuspid regurgitation was absent, transesophageal and 
stress echocardiography, as well as selective examinations 
to rule out pericardial effusion or intracardiac thrombi). There 
were no further reasons for exclusion from the statistical 
analysis (eg, atrial fibrillation or severe tricuspid insuffi-
ciency). Thus, 1695 timely matched examinations were 
included in the statistical analysis. </p>

<p>Echocardiography </p>

<p>Echocardiographic examinations were performed on commer-
cially available ultrasound systems (Vivid S5, Vivid i, Vivid 7, 
and Vivid E9 GE Healthcare Vingmed, Trondheim, Norway and 
ie33, Philips, Eindhoven, the Netherlands) according to the 
guidelines of the American Society of Echocardiography. 21 
Images were obtained in left lateral decubitus for parasternal 
and apical views and supine position for subxyphoidal views 
using 1.5 to 4.0 MHz phased-array transducers. The compre-
hensive examination included standard 2D echocardiography 
for anatomic imaging and Doppler echocardiography for 
assessment of velocities. Doppler measurements were carried 
out over 3 heart cycles during passive expiration. All 
examinations were digitally stored in a Picture Archiving and 
Communication System (PACS) with accessibility for offline 
analysis on workstations (Centricity, GE Healthcare Vingmed, 
Trondheim, Norway). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Flow chart depicting study protocol for analysis of </p>

<p>systolic pulmonary artery pressures measurements by right heart 
catheterization and Doppler echocardiography over 6 years. 
*Noncomprehensive examinations (eg, transoesophageal echo-</p>

<p>cardiography to rule out intracardiac thrombus prior to cardio-
version of atrial fibrillation, examination to rule out pericardial 
effusion, focused examination to rule out left ventricular throm-
bus, and stress echocardiography). </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Reliability of Noninvasive Assessment of sPAP 
Greiner et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Noninvasive assessment of pulmonary artery systolic 
pressures (sPAP) was achieved by measurement of right 
ventricular systolic pressure (RVSP) and adding RAP. RVSP 
was derived from the peak systolic velocity of the tricuspid 
regurgitation obtained with continuous-wave (CW) Doppler 
using the modified Bernoulli equation: DP=49Vmax 2 . RAP 
was estimated by the diameter of the inferior vena cava and 
its variability during inspiration as described before. 9,21,22 
Offline reassessment of CW Doppler spectral envelopes, as 
well as inferior vena cava diameter and respiratory behavior, 
was conducted in n=258 examination for clarification of 
misdiagnosis of PH by 2 independent, experienced examiners 
blinded to invasive data. </p>

<p>Right Heart Catheterization </p>

<p>A femoral or jugular venous approach was used for right 
heart catheterization. Cardiac output and cardiac index were </p>

<p>calculated by saturation measurement according to Fick's 
method. PAP, pulmonary capillary wedge pressure, and right 
ventricular and right atrial pressures were measured during 
breath hold in baseline over at least 3 heart cycles. Mean 
pulmonary artery pressure was calculated by integration of 
the pressure curve by <rs id="software-0" type="software">Metek</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Metek GmbH</rs>, 
Roetgen, Germany). Pulmonary vascular resistance was 
derived from pulmonary vascular resistance = (mean pulmo-
nary artery pressure À pulmonary capillary wedge pressure)/ 
cardiac output. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed by <rs id="software-1" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 18.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">IBM Corporation</rs>, Armonk, NY) and <rs id="software-2" type="software">GraphPad Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">v5.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">GraphPad Software Inc.</rs>., La Jolla, CA) was used for plotting. 
Normal distribution was assessed by the Kolmogorov-Smir-
nov test. Results are expressed as meanAESD. A P&lt;0.05 was 
considered statistically significant. For comparison of invasive 
and noninvasive measurements of sPAP and RAP, linear 
regression analyses were conducted and Pearson's correla-
tion coefficient was calculated. Bland-Altman analyses were 
carried for sPAP and RAP measurements to show systematic 
deviations. For discrimination of sPAP threshold, receiver 
operating characteristics analysis was conducted. Sensitivity, 
specificity, positive and negative predictive values, as well as 
accuracy were analyzed for different cut-off values. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Clinical characteristics of the study population and indications 
for heart catheterization are presented in Table 1. A group of 
1695 individuals who had time-matched (AE5 days) echocar-
diography examinations and right heart catheterization was 
included for analysis (Figure 1). A preponderance of male 
individuals could be found in this unselected patient popula-
tion (67%). The majority of patients were found to be in New 
York Heart Association functional classification II (27%) and III 
(51%) at the time of examinations. 
Findings during invasive examination and Doppler echocar-
diography are shown in Table 2. sPAP was 47.4AE16.4 mm Hg 
by right heart catheterization and 45.3AE15.5 mm Hg by 
Doppler echocardiography. Linear regression analysis showed 
a very good association, with a Pearson's correlation coeffi-
cient r of 0.87 (P&lt;0.0001, SEE=8.1 mm Hg, Figure 2). Bland-
Altman analysis showed a bias of À2.0 mm Hg (95% limits of 
agreement: À18.1 to +14.1 mm Hg, Table 3). Mean RAP was 
12.0AE5.7 mm Hg by right heart catheterization and 
12.1AE6.6 mm Hg by Doppler echocardiography. Pearson's 
correlation coefficient r was 0.82 (P&lt;0.0001) and correspond-
ing Bland-Altman analysis showed a bias of +1.0 (limits of </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of the Study Population </p>

<p>Characteristics </p>

<p>N 
1695 </p>

<p>Age, y 
63AE15 </p>

<p>Gender, % males 
67 </p>

<p>Height, cm 
172AE9 </p>

<p>Weight, kg 
78AE16 </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m² 
26AE5 </p>

<p>BSA, m² 
1.9AE0.2 </p>

<p>SBP, mm Hg 
128AE19 </p>

<p>DBP, mm Hg 
68AE13 </p>

<p>Functional classification, n (%) </p>

<p>NYHA I 
85 (5) </p>

<p>NYHA II 
458 (27) </p>

<p>NYHA III 
864 (51) </p>

<p>NYHA IV 
288 (17) </p>

<p>Indications for heart catheterization, n (%) </p>

<p>Known or suspected CMP 
542 (32) </p>

<p>Evaluation valve disease </p>

<p>Aortic valve disease 
322 (19) </p>

<p>Mitral valve disease 
104 (6) </p>

<p>Tricuspid valve disease 
34 (2) </p>

<p>Known or suspected ICM 
459 (27) </p>

<p>Known or suspected PH 
99 (6) </p>

<p>Other miscellaneous indications 
135 (8) </p>

<p>Values are given as meanAESD or numbers (percentage) as required. BMI indicates body 
mass index; BSA, body surface area; CMP, cardiomyopathy; DBP, diastolic blood; ICM, 
ischemic cardiomyopathy; NYHA, New York Heart Association; PH, pulmonary artery 
hypertension; SBP, systolic blood pressure. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Reliability of Noninvasive Assessment of sPAP 
Greiner et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>agreement +0.1 to +1.9 mm Hg, Table 3). None of the 
patients presented a right ventricular outflow obstruction or 
a pulmonary valve stenosis at invasive examination. Details of 
the subgroup of patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension 
(n=99) are given in the supplemental analysis (Table 4). </p>

<p>Analyses in regard to time latency were conducted on 
examinations that were carried out within 24 hours (n=932, 
55%) and between 2 and 5 days (n=763, 45%), respectively. 
Near-simultaneous examinations within 24 hours showed a 
closer correlation (r=0.89, P&lt;0.0001), but an unchanged 
systematic underestimation of À2.3 mm Hg by Doppler 
echocardiography in the Bland-Altman analysis. Examinations 
with time latency of more than 24 hours show slightly lower 
correlation (r=0.81, P&lt;0.0001) and a systematic underestima-
tion of À2.4 mm Hg by Doppler echocardiography as well. 
Examinations that were carried out before right heart cathe-
terization (n=1084, 64%) correlated better (r=0.89, P&lt;0.0001) 
than examinations after right heart catheterization (n=611, 
36%; r=0.84, P&lt;0.0001) with systematic underestimation 
by Doppler echocardiography of À2.8 and À1.4 mm Hg, 
respectively. 
The diagnosis of pulmonary hypertension, as defined by 
invasively measured mean pulmonary artery pressure 
≥25 mm Hg, was feasible by noninvasive sPAP assessment </p>

<p>with an AUC of 0.91 in the receiver operating characteristics 
analysis (P&lt;0.001, 95% CI=0.90 to 0.93, Figure 3). A cut-off 
value of 36 mm Hg showed good sensitivity (87%) and 
specificity (79%), good positive predictive value (91%), nega-
tive predictive value (70%), and best accuracy (85%) (Table 5). 
A lower cut-off value of 31 mm Hg with an accuracy of 84% 
missed only 66 of 1221 patients with PH, but yielded 199 
false-positive reports. 
Systolic PAP overestimation and underestimation leading 
to significant overdiagnosis or underdiagnosis of pulmonary 
hypertension are listed in Table 5. An incomplete CW 
Doppler spectral envelope was the predominant cause for 
underestimation, whereas overestimation was due to differ-
ent causes. In one third of the cases, overestimation was 
due to false interpretation of the spectral envelope maximal 
velocity boundary in the presence of vertical linear Doppler 
artifacts ("fringes"), followed by incomplete spectral-wave 
envelope and too-soft signal due to low spectral Doppler 
gain setting. Severe tricuspid regurgitation by echocardio-
graphic definition was present in n=79 of all patients (5%) 
and a sPAP was documented in the echo report in spite of 
the restrictions of the measurement in this setting. </p>

<p>Table 2. Findings During Invasive Examination and Doppler 
Echocardiography </p>

<p>Parameters </p>

<p>Right heart catheterization </p>

<p>CO, mL/min 
4.3AE1.4 </p>

<p>CI, mL/min per m² 
2.3AE0.7 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin, g/dL 
12.3AE2.0 </p>

<p>PVR, dyn/(s•cm À5 ) 
208AE171 </p>

<p>sPAP, mm Hg 
47.4AE16.4 </p>

<p>dPAP, mm Hg 
21.6AE8.2 </p>

<p>mPAP, mm Hg 
31.6AE10.9 </p>

<p>PCWP, mm Hg 
21.4AE8.2 </p>

<p>mRAP, mm Hg 
12.0AE5.7 </p>

<p>PH prevalence </p>

<p>No PH, n (%) 
474 (28) </p>

<p>PH, n (%) 
1221 (72) </p>

<p>Doppler echocardiography </p>

<p>sPAP, mm Hg 
45.3AE15.5 </p>

<p>RAP, mm Hg 
12.1AE6.6 </p>

<p>Values are given as meanAESD. CO indicates cardiac output; CI, cardiac index; dPAP, 
diastolic pulmonary artery pressure; mPAP, mean pulmonary artery pressure; mRAP, 
mean right atrial pressure; PCWP, pulmonary capillary wedge pressure; PH, pulmonary 
hypertension (no PH: mPAP&lt;25 mm Hg; PH: mPAP≥25 mm Hg); PVR, pulmonary 
vascular resistance; RAP, right atrial pressure; sPAP, systolic pulmonary artery pressure. </p>

<p>Table 3. Correlation and Bland-Altman Analysis of 
Pulmonary Artery Systolic Pressures and Right Atrial 
Pressures (Catheterization vs. Echocardiography) </p>

<p>N 
R 
Bias 
SD 
95% LOA </p>

<p>sPAP 
1695 
0.87 
À2.0 
8.2 
À18.1 
+14.1 </p>

<p>RAP 
1595 
0.82 
+1.0 
1.0 
+0.1 
+1.9 </p>

<p>LOA, limits of agreement; RAP, right atrial pressure; sPAP, systolic pulmonary artery 
pressure. </p>

<p>sPAP 
echo , mm Hg </p>

<p>sPAP invas 
, mm Hg </p>

<p>n = 1,695 
r = 0.87 
SEE = 8.1 mm Hg 
p &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Linear regression analysis plot of invasive and nonin-</p>

<p>vasive values of pulmonary artery systolic pressure. echo indicates 
noninvasive measurement by echocardiography; invas, invasive 
measurement by right heart catheterization; r, correlation coeffi-
cient (Pearson); sPAP, systolic pulmonary artery pressure. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Reliability of Noninvasive Assessment of sPAP 
Greiner et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>However, severe tricuspid regurgitation accounted for only 
11 cases (7%) of underestimation and missed diagnosis of 
PH. Misinterpretation of the diameter and respiration 
dynamics of the inferior vena cava was also involved in 
both underestimation and overestimation, but in a lesser 
manner. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study that 
analyzes accuracy of noninvasive assessment of sPAP by 
Doppler echocardiography in comparison to invasive pressure 
measurement in a large, unselected patient population. In our 
study, Doppler echocardiography has proven to be a 
reliable noninvasive method for the assessment of sPAP. </p>

<p>Table 4. Supplemental Analysis of PAH Subgroup </p>

<p>Characteristics of patients with PAH </p>

<p>N 
9 9 </p>

<p>Age, y 
69AE14 </p>

<p>Gender, % males 
61 </p>

<p>Height, cm 
171AE10 </p>

<p>Weight, kg 
77AE15 </p>

<p>BMI, kg/m² 
26AE4 </p>

<p>BSA, m² 
1.9AE0.2 </p>

<p>SBP, mm Hg 
117AE27 </p>

<p>DBP, mm Hg 
65AE13 </p>

<p>Right heart catheterization </p>

<p>CO, mL/min 
4.4AE1.3 </p>

<p>CI, mL/min per m² 
2.3AE0.6 </p>

<p>Hemoglobin, g/dL 
12.7AE2.0 </p>

<p>PVR, dyn/(s•cm À5 ) 
400AE234 </p>

<p>sPAP, mm Hg 
53.1AE16.0 </p>

<p>dPAP, mm Hg 
21.4AE7.7 </p>

<p>mPAP, mm Hg 
34.0AE9.8 </p>

<p>PCWP, mm Hg 
12.8AE2.3 </p>

<p>mRAP, mm Hg 
9.2AE3.9 </p>

<p>Doppler echocardiography </p>

<p>sPAP, mm Hg 
50.9AE16.0 </p>

<p>RAP, mm Hg 
10.1AE5.0 </p>

<p>Linear regression analysis (sPAP) </p>

<p>r (Pearson) 
0.89 </p>

<p>SEE, mm Hg 
7.5 </p>

<p>P value 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Bland-Altman analysis (sPAP) </p>

<p>Bias, mm Hg 
À2.2 </p>

<p>SD, mm Hg 
7.6 </p>

<p>95% LOA, mm Hg 
À12.8 to 17.1 </p>

<p>Linear regression analysis (RAP) </p>

<p>r (Pearson) 
0.73 </p>

<p>SEE, mm Hg 
3.5 </p>

<p>P value 
&lt;0.0001 </p>

<p>Bland-Altman analysis (RAP) </p>

<p>Bias, mm Hg 
+0.5 </p>

<p>SD, mm Hg 
3.5 </p>

<p>95% LOA, mm Hg 
À7.4 to 6.5 </p>

<p>Values are given as meanAESD or numbers (percentage) as required. BMI indicates body 
mass index; BSA, body surface area; CI, cardiac index; CO, cardiac output; DBP, diastolic 
blood; dPAP, diastolic pulmonary artery pressure; LOA, limits of agreement; mPAP, mean 
pulmonary artery pressure; mRAP, mean right atrial pressure; PAH, pulmonary arterial 
hypertension; PCWP, pulmonary capillary wedge pressure; PVR, pulmonary vascular 
resistance; RAP, right atrial pressure; SBP, systolic blood pressure; sPAP, systolic 
pulmonary artery pressure. </p>

<p>Table 5. Sensitivity, Specificity, and Diagnostic Accuracy 
of Noninvasive Assessment of Pulmonary Hypertension by 
Doppler Echocardiography at Various Cut-Off Levels </p>

<p>Cut-off 
sPAP, 
mm Hg </p>

<p>Sensitivity, 
% </p>

<p>Specificity, 
% </p>

<p>PPV, 
% </p>

<p>NPV, 
% </p>

<p>ACC, 
% </p>

<p>≥26 
98.5 
28.7 
78.1 
88.3 
79.0 </p>

<p>≥31 
94.6 
58.0 
85.3 
80.6 
84.4 </p>

<p>≥36 
87.0 
79.1 
91.5 
70.2 
84.8 </p>

<p>≥41 
73.1 
91.4 
95.6 
56.8 
78.2 </p>

<p>≥46 
59.5 
97.0 
98.1 
48.2 
70.0 </p>

<p>ACC indicates accuracy; NPV, negative predictive value; PPV, positive predictive value; 
sPAP, systolic pulmonary arterial pressure. </p>

<p>AUC 
p value 
95% CI 
Cut-off 
Sensitivity 
Specificity </p>

<p>sPAP 
0.91 
&lt;0.001 
0.90 -0.93 
36 mm Hg 
87 % 
79 % </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>1 -Specificity </p>

<p>Figure 3. Receiver operating characteristics (ROC) analysis for </p>

<p>noninvasive diagnosis of pulmonary hypertension as defined 
invasively (mean pulmonary artery pressure ≥25 mm Hg). AUC 
indicates area under the curve; sPAP, systolic pulmonary artery 
pressure. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Reliability of Noninvasive Assessment of sPAP 
Greiner et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Furthermore, pulmonary hypertension could be detected with 
high sensitivity and specificity. 
Our findings confirm previous reports. Thirty years ago, a 
first publication by Yock and Popp 10 found a high correlation </p>

<p>between noninvasive and invasive data in 54 patients (r=0.93, 
SEE=8 mm Hg). 10 Berger et al 11 found an even higher 
correlation in a study population of 41, when invasive and 
noninvasive examinations were conducted simultaneously in 
almost all patients (r=0.97, SEE=4.9 mm Hg). 11 Currie et al 12 
assessed accuracy of noninvasively measured RVSP simulta-
neously with right heart catheterization in 127 patients and 
described very good correlations (r=0.96, SEE=7 mm Hg). 12 
Vazquez de Prada et al 13 conducted a similar study including 
34 patients with adequate CW Doppler tracings, with a time 
interval of 24 to 48 hours between examinations; nonethe-
less, they showed high correlations as well (r=0.96). 13 
Although recommended in many guidelines 7,9,15 and used 
routinely, noninvasive quantification of sPAP has never been 
tested sufficiently in unselected large patient populations 
undergoing routine echocardiography examination. This lack 
of information has sparked the discussion about reliability of 
this method. Few publications had mentioned doubts about is 
reliability. Arcasoy et al 16 found in a cohort study of 374 
patients with advanced lung disease that in 52% of the cases, 
pressure estimations were inaccurate, and that 48% of 
patients were false positive for pulmonary hypertension as 
determined by echocardiography. Noninvasive estimation of 
sPAP was not possible in 57% of the patients. The authors 
suggested that factors related to chronic pulmonary disease 
may have influenced the results, limiting accurate visualiza-
tion and measurement of the tricuspid regurgitation jet. 16 
In our study, only 424 patients had to be excluded due to 
the absence of tricuspid regurgitation (20%). This ratio is 
much lower than described by Arcasoy et al. 16 In 227 of these 
424 patients, pulmonary hypertension with mean pulmonary 
artery pressure ≥25 mm Hg was documented invasively, 
confirming that absence of a measurable tricuspid regurgita-
tion does not exclude PH. 
Some years later, 3 smaller studies-Fisher et al 17 (n=65), 
Rich et al 18 (n=183), and D'Alto et al 19 (n=152) -as well as 
the analysis of the REVEAL registry 20 stated that Doppler 
echocardiography may frequently be inaccurate, causing 
frequent overestimation and underestimation of PAP in 
patients being evaluated for pulmonary hypertension. They 
suggested that this method should not be relied on to make 
individual diagnoses of pulmonary hypertension. 
Three recent meta-analyses by Zhan et al, 23 Janda et al 24 , 
and Taleb et al 25 assessed this issue on the basis of n=736 
(6 studies), n=1485 (29 studies), and n=522 (9 studies), 
respectively. The mean time interval between echocardiogra-
phy and right heart catheterization of the included studies 
ranged from 2 hours to 90 days. The reported results are not </p>

<p>completely consistent. Whereas accuracy calculated with the 
random effects model by Taleb et al 25 was low (73%), 
sensitivity for diagnosis was similarly high in all 3 meta-
analyses (82%, 83%, and 88%, respectively). Specificity was 
found to show a higher variation (68%, 72%, and 56%, 
respectively). 23-25 In our study, the receiver operating char-
acteristics analysis demonstrates a high diagnostic accuracy 
for a sPAP cut-off value of 36 mm Hg (AUC=0.91, sensitiv-
ity=87%, specificity=79%, accuracy=85%, Figure 3 and 
Table 5). Higher cut-off levels show better specificity for 
diagnosis of PH, but on the basis of increasing numbers of 
patients with missed diagnoses. Even lower cut-off levels may 
be appropriate in younger persons as sPAP values are age 
dependent as described in a comprehensive echocardiogra-
phy study by Lam et al. 6 
Potential sources of error for the sPAP assessment with 
Doppler echocardiography were already discussed by Yock 
and Popp, 10 and commented on in the subsequent stud-
ies. 11,12,17-20 In our study, we could document a series of 
sources of error in an offline analysis of all cases, with 
significant overestimation or underestimation (Table 6). </p>

<p>Table 6. Sources of sPAP Overestimation or Underestimation 
Leading Correspondingly to Overdiagnosis or Underdiagnosis 
of Pulmonary Hypertension </p>

<p>Overestimation 
n=99 </p>

<p>Underestimation 
n=159 </p>

<p>CW Doppler, n (%) </p>

<p>Incomplete spectral wave 
envelope </p>

<p>16 (16.2) 
110 (69.6) </p>

<p>Maximal velocity boundary 
artifacts ("fringes") </p>

<p>33 (33.3) 
2 (1.3) </p>

<p>Spectral gain set too soft 
12 (12.1) 
1 (0.6) </p>

<p>Velocity range set too high 
7 (7.1) 
1 (0.6) </p>

<p>Sweep velocity set to slow 
3 (3.0) 
1 (0.6) </p>

<p>Valve closure artifacts 
("snaps") </p>

<p>2 (2.0) 
2 (1.3) </p>

<p>Atrial fibrillation 
7 (7.1) 
3 (1.9) </p>

<p>Severe tricuspid 
regurgitation </p>

<p>1 (1.0) 
11 (7.0) </p>

<p>Inferior vena cava, n (%) </p>

<p>Respiration dynamics 
misinterpreted </p>

<p>9 (9.1) 
20 (12.6) </p>

<p>Could not be depicted 
8 (8.1) 
7 (4.4) </p>

<p>Aorta mistaken as inferior 
vena cava </p>

<p>1 (1.0) 
0 (0) </p>

<p>Overestimation was defined when sPAP assessed with Doppler echocardiography was 
&gt;35 mm Hg and mPAP measured invasively was &lt;25 mm Hg, whereas underestimation </p>

<p>was defined when sPAP assessed with Doppler echocardiography was ≤35 mm Hg and 
mPAP measured invasively was ≥25 mm Hg. CW indicates continuous-wave Doppler; 
mPAP, pulmonary artery mean pressure; sPAP, systolic pulmonary artery pressure. </p>

<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Reliability of Noninvasive Assessment of sPAP 
Greiner et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

<p>Contrary to former assertions, characteristics of the inferior 
vena cava were not the main reason for inaccuracy, but rather 
were due to the many pitfalls inherent to the Doppler method. 
Thus, optimal settings when assessing tricuspid regurgitation 
velocities should be taken into account. Further pitfalls should 
be kept in mind. Stenosis of the right ventricular outflow tract, 
pulmonary valve, or the pulmonary trunk may lead to 
systematic overestimation of right ventricular systolic pres-
sure. Severe tricuspid insufficiency may lead to underestima-
tion as pressure gradients decrease with increasing effective 
regurgitant orifice area. Furthermore, since the absence of 
tricuspid regurgitation does not rule out PH, the presence of 
indirect signs must be observed. 
Based on our experience, the following aspects should be 
considered for best results: (1) since angle between ultrasound 
beam and direction of flow must be kept to a minimum, 
tricuspid regurgitation should first be detected with color 
Doppler from the best ultrasound view and multiple transducer 
positions may be necessary; (2) settings should be corrected, a 
colored spectral wave should be chosen, gain for optimal signal-
to-noise ratio, velocity range allowing waves to fill at least two 
thirds of spectral depiction, and sweep velocity set to 100 to 
200 mm/s should be attempted; (3) only signals extended for 
at least half of the systole should be measured, and incomplete 
or absent tricuspid regurgitation may be avoided by increasing 
blood pool volume with a strategy as simple as drinking a cup 
of water before examination; (4) maximal velocities in the 
presence of atrial fibrillation should be averaged; and (5) 
maximal velocities should be measured at the best spectral-
wave boundary, avoiding including Doppler artifacts ("fringes"). </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>The interpretation of the study results is limited by its 
retrospective manner, as well as due to the fact that this 
analysis represents the data collected in only 1 cardiology 
center. 
This study addressed all patients with right heart cathe-
terization and PAP measurement by Doppler echocardiogra-
phy within 5 days. The majority of patients with elevated PAP 
had postcapillary PH. Only a minority of n=99 patients had 
pulmonary arterial hypertension. 
Doppler echocardiography and right heart catheterization 
were carried out nonsimultaneously, with time latency of 2 to 
5 days for 45% of the study population. Fifty-five percent of 
the examinations were carried out within 24 hours. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Our study validates the noninvasive quantification of sPAP by 
Doppler echocardiography in a large, unselected patient </p>

<p>population. Values obtained noninvasively show reliable 
results and good correlation to invasive measurements. PH 
can be detected with high sensitivity and specificity. However, 
several pitfalls should be taken into account to achieve best 
results. </p>

<p>Disclosures </p>

<p>The authors had full access to the data and take responsibility 
for its integrity. All authors read and agreed to the article as 
written. All authors declare that they have no conflict of 
interest. </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Reliability of Noninvasive Assessment of sPAP 
Greiner et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>



<p>DOI: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001103 
Journal of the American Heart Association </p>



<p>Reliability of Noninvasive Assessment of sPAP 
Greiner et al </p>

<p>ORIGINAL RESEARCH </p>

</text></tei>