<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4357732" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Although the RNase H-dependent mechanism of inhi-
bition of gene expression by chemically modified an-
tisense oligonucleotides (ASOs) has been well char-
acterized, little is known about the interactions be-
tween ASOs and intracellular proteins that may alter 
cellular localization and/or potency of ASOs. Here, 
we report the identification of 56 intracellular ASO-
binding proteins using multi-step affinity selection 
approaches. Many of the tested proteins had no 
significant effect on ASO activity; however, some 
proteins, including La/SSB, NPM1, ANXA2, VARS 
and PC4, appeared to enhance ASO activities, likely 
through mechanisms related to subcellular distribu-
tion. VARS and ANXA2 co-localized with ASOs in 
endocytic organelles, and reduction in the level of 
VARS altered lysosome/ASO localization patterns, 
implying that these proteins may facilitate ASO re-
lease from the endocytic pathway. Depletion of La 
and NPM1 reduced nuclear ASO levels, suggesting 
potential roles in ASO nuclear accumulation. On the 
other hand, Ku70 and Ku80 proteins inhibited ASO 
activity, most likely by competition with RNase H1 for 
ASO/RNA duplex binding. Our results demonstrate 
that phosphorothioate-modified ASOs bind a set of 
cellular proteins that affect ASO activity via different 
mechanisms. </p>

<p>RNase H1 is a conserved endonuclease that selectively de-
grades the RNA strand within a DNA/RNA duplex (1). 
Synthetic antisense oligonucleotides (ASOs) that harness 
this property to direct sequence-specific cleavage of the 
RNAs are used for both biological research and biomedi-
cal purposes (2,3). The mechanism of ASO-directed RNase 
H1 cleavage of target RNAs has been well characterized, 
and the crystal structure of RNase H1 has been solved (1,4). </p>

<p>Evidence clearly shows that ASOs introduced into mouse 
or human cells trigger substrate RNA degradation through 
RNase H1, but not RNase H2 (5). Recently we showed that 
the mitochondrial protein P32 associates with RNase H1 
to increase RNase H1 activity, most likely by increasing the 
turnover rate of the enzyme (6). It also appears that the level 
of RNase H1 protein is a limiting factor in terms of ASO po-
tency, as reducing RNase H1 decreased and over-expressing 
RNase H1 increased ASO-directed RNA cleavage (5). 
The chemical composition of one class of ASOs currently 
used as therapeutic agents has 10 deoxyribonucleotides 
flanked on either side by five 2 -O-methoxyethyl (MOE) 
modified nucleotides with nucleotides linked via phospho-
rothioate (PS) backbones; this configuration is often re-
ferred to as a 'gapmer'. This chemical composition ensures 
efficient cellular uptake and stability against nuclease di-
gestion (7). Internalization of ASOs has been shown to be 
largely through endocytosis (8,9). At low concentrations 
(&lt;1 M), ASOs may enter cells predominately through 
receptor-mediated endocytosis, whereas at high concentra-
tions, fluid phase endocytosis plays a major role (10). It has 
been proposed that two pathways may exist for ASO up-
take and accumulation in cells--a non-productive pathway 
in which internalized ASOs are not functionally active and 
a productive pathway through which ASOs can hybridize 
with RNAs and trigger RNase H1 cleavage (9,11,12). 
When ASOs are incubated with cells in culture in the 
absence of transfection reagents (free uptake), internalized 
ASOs predominantly accumulate in lysosomes; and GW/P-
body localization of PS-ASOs in Huh-7 cells was also re-
ported previously (13). Lysosome-localized ASOs are con-
sidered to be inactive (8,9,14). However, ASOs can escape 
from the membrane-enclosed endocytosis particles to the 
cytosol during intracellular trafficking (11,12), and the re-
leased ASOs thus have the potential to reach the target 
RNAs. The productive pathway of ASO uptake may in-
volve AP2M1, since reduction of AP2M1, but not clathrin 
or caveolin, reduces ASO activity upon free uptake (9). Al-
though the molecular mechanism of the productive path-
way has not been defined, previous studies showed that nu-
clear localization of ASOs positively correlates with the an-</p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 760 603 3816; Fax: +1 760 603 2600; Email: Lliang@isisph.com </p>

<p>C The Author(s) 2015. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which 
permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact 
journals.permissions@oup.com </p>



<p>tisense activity (15). This is evidenced by the observations 
that upon transfection, ASOs accumulate in the nucleus, 
and ASO activity is significantly increased as compared 
with ASO free uptake, by which ASOs are barely detectable 
in the nucleus (15). However, upon free uptake, ASOs can 
still be active even without significant nuclear accumulation 
(9,13). In addition, ASOs were shown to shuttle between the 
cytoplasm and nucleus, and nuclear import is most likely 
mediated by an active transport pathway (16,17). These re-
sults suggest that in the case of free uptake, the portion 
of ASOs in the productive pathway is small relative to the 
ASOs accumulated in endosomes and lysosomes, whereas 
upon transfection, the fraction of ASOs entering the pro-
ductive pathway, or ASOs released to the cytosol, is in-
creased. 
In addition to the many properties of the targeted RNAs, 
such as RNA structure, sequence, and RNA-binding pro-
teins that can affect ASO accessibility to the target RNA 
(18), the binding of intracellular proteins to ASOs may also 
influence antisense activity at many steps, e.g. release of 
ASOs from endocytosis pathways, proper subcellular lo-
calization, interaction of ASOs with RNA substrates and 
recruitment of RNase H1 to the ASO/RNA duplex. Pre-
vious studies have demonstrated that PS-ASOs bind more 
proteins, including NCL1, hnRNP A1 and albumin, than 
ASOs containing phosphodiester (PO) backbone (19-22). 
Some proteins may compete with RNase H1 for binding to 
the mRNA-ASO duplex. Indeed, it was shown very recently 
that hspA8 and hnRNP F could bind to an ASO/RNA du-
plex and compete with RNase H1, leading to inhibition of 
RNase H1 cleavage (23). In addition, we recently demon-
strated that the chaperone protein TCP1 complex interacts 
with PS-ASOs and can increase ASO activity (22). The beta 
subunit of the TCP1 complex co-localizes with ASOs in nu-
clear PS bodies upon transfection. Several TCP1 proteins 
also co-localize with ASOs in cytoplasmic endosomes and 
lysosomes in the case of free uptake, suggesting a potential 
role of TCP1 proteins in ASO release from the endocyto-
sis pathway and/or in nuclear retention (22). Additionally, 
we also found that paraspeckle proteins, including P54nrb, 
PSF and PSPC1, bind to ASOs and inhibit ASO activ-
ity (24). These paraspeckle proteins co-localize with ASOs 
in different nuclear structures, such as nuclear paraspeck-
les, ASO-induced nuclear filaments and perinucleolar cap 
structures (24). The chemical modification at the 2 moiety 
also affects protein binding. For example, ASOs with more 
hydrophobic 2 modifications (e.g. constrained ethyl) tend 
to bind more proteins and more avidly than those with more 
hydrophilic 2 modifications (e.g. 2 -MOE) [(22,24) and our 
unpublished data]. In addition, some proteins bind primar-
ily to single-stranded ASOs (ssASOs), whereas others, such 
as P54nrb and PSF proteins, bind the ASO/RNA duplex 
(24). These results suggest that a number of cellular pro-
teins interact with ASOs and affect the antisense activity 
positively or negatively. However, information about intra-
cellular ASO-binding proteins and their effects on ASO ac-
tivity and localization is still limited. 
To better understand the interactions between intracel-
lular proteins and ASOs, we sought to identify the major 
ASO-binding proteins using multiple-step affinity selection 
approaches. Here we report the identification of 56 intracel-</p>

<p>lular ASO-binding proteins. To our knowledge, this is the 
first systematic study investigating the binding of ASOs to 
intracellular proteins and the effects of ASO-binding pro-
teins on ASO activity and/or localization. Although PS-
ASOs interact with a number of proteins, a relatively small 
subset of intracellular proteins appears to be the major 
binders of PS-ASOs as determined using our competition-
mediated approach. Certain proteins, including La, NPM1, 
valyl-tRNA synthetase (VARS), PC4 and ANXA2, moder-
ately increased ASO activity, likely through different mech-
anisms, such as by altering ASO subcellular distribution. 
ANXA2 and VARS were found to co-localize with ASOs 
in the cytoplasm, similar to previously reported results with 
TCP1 proteins. On the other hand, Ku70/Ku80 complex 
proteins were found to inhibit ASO activity, most likely due 
to competition with RNase H1 for binding to ASO/RNA 
duplex. Thus, intracellular proteins can bind to and affect 
ASO activity and/or subcellular localization. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Antibodies, siRNAs, ASOs and quantitative real time PCR 
(qRT-PCR) primer probe sets are listed in Supplementary 
data. </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection of plasmids, siRNAs and ASOs </p>

<p>HEK293 cells stably over-expressing Flag-tagged human 
RNase H1 were grown as described previously (6). HeLa 
cells were grown as described elsewhere. One day before 
transfection, cells were re-seeded at ∼50-70% confluency. 
Transfection of plasmids was performed using Effectene 
(Qiagen) based on manufacturer's instructions. At 36 h 
after plasmid transfection, cells were collected for west-
ern analysis or were reseeded at ∼50% confluency, grown 
overnight, and transfected with ASOs. Transfection of siR-
NAs and ASOs was performed as described previously (25). 
Briefly, HeLa cells grown to ∼70% confluency in complete 
Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium without antibiotics 
were transfected with 3-5-nM siRNA using Lipofectamine 
RNAiMax (Life Technologies). Eight or 24 h post siRNA 
transfection, cells were reseeded in 6-well or 96-well plates 
at 50% confluency and incubated for overnight. Cells were 
then transfected with indicated concentration of ASOs us-
ing Lipofectamine 2000 (Life Technologies), and, after 4 h, 
RNA or protein was prepared. For ASO activity assay upon 
free uptake, HEK293 cells treated with siRNAs for 24 h 
were washed and reseed at ∼40% confluency. ASOs were 
added 8 h later directly to the medium without transfection 
reagent. After 16 h of ASO incubation, RNA was prepared 
from cells and mRNA levels were determined by qRT-PCR. </p>

<p>Affinity selection of ASO or ASO/RNA duplex-binding pro-
teins </p>

<p>Affinity selection of ASO-binding proteins was performed 
as described recently (22,24). Briefly, 100-l Neutravidin 
beads (Thermo Scientific) were incubated with 100 l of 
200-M biotinylated ASO ISIS386652 at 4 
• C for 2-3 h in 
W-100 buffer [50-mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 100-mM KCl, 
5-mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), 0.1% NP-
40 and 0.05% sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS)]. The beads </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2929 </p>

<p>were then blocked for 30 min at 4 
• C in 300-l block-
ing buffer [1-mg/ml bovine serum albumin (BSA), 0.2-
mg/ml glycogen and 0.2-mg/ml yeast tRNA in W-100]. 
After three washes with W-100, ASO-coated beads were 
incubated for 2-4 h at 4 
• C with 3-mg HeLa cell extract 
prepared in buffer A [25-mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 5-mM 
MgCl 2 , 150-mM KCl, 10% glycerol, 0.5-mM PMSF, 5-mM 
␤-mercaptoethanol and one tablet of Protease Inhibitor 
Cocktail/50 ml (Roche)]. After three washes with 500-l 
W-200 buffer [50-mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 200-mM KCl, 5-
mM EDTA, 0.05% SDS, 0.1% NP-40], the beads were trans-
ferred to a 1-ml column and washed seven times with W-
200, 1 ml each time. Bound proteins were eluted with 200 
l of 50-M ASO116847 in W-100 by incubation at room 
temperature for 30 min with gentle rotation. The eluted 
ASO-protein complexes were precipitated and analyzed by 
SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE). Alterna-
tively, to identify binding proteins that can bind ASO/RNA 
duplex, the eluted ASO-protein complexes were diluted 
with 200-l W-100 supplemented with 100 units of RNase-
OUT (Life Technologies) and further incubated at 4 
• C for 
2 h with 40-l Neutravidin beads pre-incubated with 40 
l of 200-M biotinylated oligonucleotides complementary 
(XL180) or non-complementary (XL181) to ASO116847. 
After washing seven times with W-200 supplemented with 
20-unit/ml RNaseOUT, the beads were treated with 100-l 
Tris-EDTA buffer containing 5-units/l RNase I at 30 
• C 
for 30 min, and the eluted proteins were precipitated and 
separated on 4-12% SDS-PAGE. Sliver staining was car-
ried out using ProteoSilver Plus Silver Stain Kit (Sigma) 
based on manufacturer's instructions. The interesting pro-
tein bands were excised and identified by mass spectrom-
etry by Alphalyse Inc. Briefly, the samples were reduced 
and alkylated with iodoacetamide, followed by trypsin di-
gestion. The digested peptides were concentrated and ana-
lyzed on a Bruker Autoflex Speed MALDI TOF/TOF in-
strument. MALDI MS/MS was conducted on 15 peptides 
for peptide fragmentation analysis. The MS and MS/MS 
spectra were combined and used to search database with the 
<rs type="software">Mascot</rs> software. Alternatively, the isolated proteins were 
analyzed by western blot. </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation of RNase H1-associated proteins </p>

<p>Whole cell lysates were prepared from HEK293 cells ex-
pressing Flag-tagged RNase H1 (6) using IP buffer (Pierce) 
supplemented with proteinase inhibitor and 5-mM EDTA. 
Aliquots of cell lysate (∼2-mg protein) were incubated at 
4 
• C for 1 h with 100 l of 200-M ASO116847, or with 
100 l of 200 M of pre-annealed ASO116847/XL279 du-
plex, or without ASO. Next, 50-l anti-FLAG beads were 
added, and immunoprecipitation was performed at 4 
• C for 
2 h. After seven washes with wash buffer (50-mM Tris-HCl 
(pH 7.5), 150-mM NaCl, 5-mM EDTA, 0.1% NP-40, 0.05% 
SDS), co-precipitated proteins were eluted by competition 
using 100 l of 1-mg/ml 3×FLAG peptide in wash buffer. 
The eluted proteins were precipitated and analyzed by west-
ern blot. </p>

<p>RNA preparation and qRT-PCR </p>

<p>Total RNA was prepared from HeLa cells using the RNeasy 
mini kit (Qiagen) or Tri-Reagent (Sigma). Northern hy-
bridization and qRT-PCR using TaqMan primer probe sets 
were conducted as described previously (25). qRT-PCR 
reactions were performed in triplicate, and average val-
ues were calculated and normalized to the amount of to-
tal RNA measured using the Ribogreen approach. The P-
values were calculated based on unpaired t-test (n = 3), 
with P &lt; 0.05 considered to be significant. The sequences 
of primer probe sets for different RNAs are listed in Sup-
plementary data. </p>

<p>Subcellular fractionation </p>

<p>Untreated HeLa cells or cells treated with PS-ASOs for 
indicated times were harvested, washed with phosphate 
buffered saline (PBS) and pelleted. Cytoplasmic and nu-
clear fractions were prepared using Qproteome Nuclear 
Protein kit (Qiagen) based on the manufacturer's instruc-
tions. Cytoplasmic and nuclear proteins were separated on 
4-12% SDS-PAGE and analyzed by western blot. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence staining </p>

<p>Cells were grown in glass-bottomed culture dishes (MatTek) 
for 16 h and were transfected or not transfected with 50-nM 
fluorescent-labeled ASOs for 4-8 h. For free uptake, cells 
were incubated with 2-M fluorescent-labeled ASOs for 16-
24 h. Immunofluorescence staining was performed as de-
scribed (22), with minor revisions. Briefly, cells were fixed 
with 4% paraformaldehyde for 30 min at room temperature 
and were permeabilized for 5 min using 0.1% Triton X-100 
in PBS. Following three washes with PBS, cells were treated 
with blocking buffer (1-mg/ml BSA in PBS) at room tem-
perature for 30 min and were incubated with primary an-
tibodies (1:100-1:200) in blocking buffer at room tempera-
ture for 2-4 h, or at 4 
• C overnight. After three 5-min washes 
with wash buffer (0.1% NP-40 in PBS), cells were incu-
bated with secondary antibodies (1:200) in blocking buffer 
at room temperature for 1-2 h and washed three times (5 
min each) with wash buffer. For double staining, two an-
tibodies were used together. Anti-fade reagent containing 
DAPI (Life Technologies) was added, and slides were cov-
ered with cover slips. Images were taken using a confocal mi-
croscope (Olympus, FV-1000) and were analyzed with Flu-
oview Ver. 2.0b Viewer (Olympus). </p>

<p>Western analysis </p>

<p>Equal portions of ASO-binding proteins isolated by affin-
ity selection or an equal amount of proteins from whole 
cell extracts (∼20 g) were separated on 4-12% SDS-PAGE 
and transferred to a membrane. Blocking, antibody incuba-
tion and detection of proteins with enhanced chemilumines-
cence were performed as described previously (26). </p>



<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Identification of ASO-binding and ASO/RNA duplex-
binding proteins </p>

<p>Intracellular ASO-binding proteins were isolated from 
HeLa cell extracts using a biotinylated 5-10-5 PS/MOE 
gapmer ASO ISIS386652. To reduce non-specific protein 
binding, the bound proteins were eluted from the beads 
by competition using ASO ISIS116847, an ASO with the 
same sequence and chemical composition as ISIS386652 
but lacking biotin (Figure 1A). The isolated ASO-protein 
pool was either separated by SDS-PAGE for silver stain-
ing (Figure 1B, lane 1) or was used as starting material 
to isolate proteins that bind the ASO/RNA duplex. The 
ASO/RNA duplex-binding proteins are particularly inter-
esting since these proteins might be expected to affect the 
activity of RNase H1, which recognizes the ASO/RNA du-
plex and cleaves the target RNA. This was done using a bi-
otinylated oligonucleotide (XL180) complementary to the 
elution ASO ISIS116847, or using a biotinylated oligonu-
cleotide (XL181) that does not base-pair with the ASO and 
served as a negative control. Both XL180 and XL181 con-
tain 20 nucleotides modified with 2 -O-methyl and an un-
modified linker sequence. We have shown that 2 -O-methyl-
modified oligonucleotides are more stable to nucleases in-
cluding RNase H1 than unmodified RNA and create du-
plexes that behave similarly to RNA-ASO duplexes with 
regard to binding of proteins including RNase H1 [(27,28)  and our unpublished data]. The duplex-binding proteins 
were released from the beads using RNase I digestion, sep-
arated by SDS-PAGE, and visualized using silver staining 
(Figure 1B, lanes 2). 
As exemplified in Figure 1B, multiple proteins were iso-
lated with the duplex and the proteins of interest were ex-
cised and identified by mass spectrometry. The affinity se-
lection was performed multiple times and the interesting 
proteins were selected mainly based on whether they were 
consistently observed to bind to ASO or ASO/RNA-like 
duplex, or whether the proteins exhibited different bind-
ing preference to PS-ASOs with different 2 -modifications, 
which can affect protein binding [(22,24) and our unpub-
lished data]. Collectively, 56 proteins were identified (Ta-
ble 1) that bind to either the ssASO or the ASO/RNA-
like duplex (Figure 1B and data not shown). Our system 
enabled identification of reasonably abundant proteins that 
bind ASOs or ASO-RNA duplexes with moderate to high 
affinity. The identified proteins included 30 DNA-or RNA-
binding proteins and 11 proteins of the chaperone fam-
ily. The RNA-binding class of proteins included hnRNP 
proteins and the nuclear paraspeckle proteins P54nrb, PSF 
and PSPC1, which we showed recently to co-localize with 
ASOs and inhibit ASO activity (24). Consistent with pre-
vious findings (20), the ASO-binding protein NCL1 was 
co-selected with ASOs in our study. Some abundant chap-
erone proteins were also isolated. It is unlikely that these 
proteins were identified due to contamination, since we pre-
viously showed that TCP1 proteins co-localize with ASOs 
in nuclear PS bodies and in cytoplasmic endocytosis par-
ticles and enhance ASO activity (22). It was also previ-
ously reported that heat shock protein hspA8 binds to an </p>

<p>ASO/RNA duplex and inhibits RNase H1-mediated cleav-
age (23). 
To confirm that the proteins identified by mass spec-
trometry are able to bind ssASO or the ASO/RNA-like 
duplex, isolated proteins were subjected to western anal-
yses (Figure 1C). Consistent with silver staining results, 
the binding of Ku80, Ku70, PC4/Sub1 and P54nrb with 
either the ssASO or the ASO/RNA-like duplex was con-
firmed. Several of these proteins were previously shown to 
bind double-stranded DNA (29-31). Certain proteins, such 
as PSF, ATAD3A, VARS and TCP1␤, were also found 
to be able to bind the ASO/RNA-like duplex, to differ-
ent extents. However, some proteins, including La, NPM1, 
PSPC1, NCL1, ANXA2 and KCTD12, appeared to bind 
primarily to ssASO. That the binding of these proteins is rel-
evant was supported by our finding that competition with 
PO oligonucleotides carrying 2 -O-methyl modification did 
not significantly elute Ku70, TCP1 and P54nrb proteins 
from the captured PS-ASO [(22,24) and data not shown]. 
Together, these results confirmed the binding of these pro-
teins to PS-ASOs and indicate that these proteins can have 
different affinities to ssASO or ASO/RNA-like duplex. </p>

<p>La or NPM1 enhances ASO activity </p>

<p>Protein binding to ASOs may impact the ability of the 
ASO to inhibit gene expression. We recently showed that 
reduction in the levels of three different subunits of the 
TCP1 complex reduced antisense activity, whereas reduc-
tion of paraspeckle proteins P54nrb, PSF and PSPC1 in-
creased ASO activity (22,24). Using similar approaches, 
we analyzed the effects of reducing the levels of La and 
NPM1 on ASO activity. La and NPM1 are abundant nu-
clear RNA-binding proteins that function in maturation of 
polymerase III transcripts and ribosome biogenesis, respec-
tively (32,33). HeLa cells were treated for 24 h with siRNAs 
specific to La or NPM1. As controls, cells were treated with 
an siRNA targeting the mRNA encoding another ASO-
binding protein NCL1, which was previously shown to have 
no effect on RNaseH-mediated ASO activity (22), or with 
an inactive siRNA with sequence complementary to U16 
snoRNA (34). As expected, the levels of the targeted mR-
NAs and proteins were dramatically and specifically re-
duced by the corresponding siRNAs as determined by qRT-
PCR (Figure 2A) and western analyses (Figure 2B), respec-
tively. To ascertain the effects of protein reduction on ASO 
activity, control and siRNA-treated cells were transfected 
for 4 h with ASOs specific to four different RNAs, and lev-
els of the ASO-targeted RNAs were analyzed by qRT-PCR 
(Figure 2C-E). In cells depleted of La or NPM1, the anti-
sense activity of an ASO targeting PTEN mRNA was re-
duced, as evidenced by less reduction of the PTEN mRNA 
especially at lower doses (&lt;10 nM) of ASO (Figure 2C) 
when compared with mock-transfected control cells (UTC). 
Consistent with our previous studies (22), treatment with 
NCL1-or U16-targeted siRNAs had no significant effect 
on the activity of the PTEN ASO. Similar observations were 
made for an ASO targeting drosha mRNA (Figure 2D): re-
duced ASO activity was observed in cells depleted of La 
or NPM1 but not in NCL1-or U16-siRNA-treated cells. 
Although the protein effects on ASO activity were mod-</p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2931 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Identification of ASO-binding proteins by affinity selection. (A) Schematic of the affinity selection approaches. The ASO-binding proteins are 
indicated using colored circles. The biotin tag is indicated by the red dots at the ends of the gapmer ASOs. (B) A representative silver-stained 4-12% 
SDS-PAGE gel used to resolve affinity-selected proteins. Certain protein bands identified by mass spectrometry are numbered and indicated. Proteins were 
isolated by competition with ASO (lane 1), ASO/RNA-like duplex (lane 2) or a non-complementary RNA-like 2 -O-methyl oligonucleotide (lane 3). The 
marker was pre-stained protein Benchmark (Life Technologies). (C) Western analyses of proteins isolated with either ssASO or ASO/RNA-like duplex. 
Isolated proteins were separated on a 4-12% SDS-PAGE, transferred to a membrane, and probed for indicated proteins by immunoblotting. </p>

<p>est, the difference was statistically significant. Decreased ac-
tivity was also found in cells treated with La-and NPM1-
siRNAs for ASOs targeting NCL1 mRNA (Figure 2E) and 
U16 snoRNA (Figure 2F), suggesting that La and NPM1 
proteins enhance ASO activity independently of ASO se-
quence or targeted RNA. 
Since reductions in levels of La and NPM1 had only 
modest effects on ASO activity, the experiments were re-
peated multiple times. Similar results were observed in each 
replicate [data not shown and (22)], suggesting that the ex-
perimental system is reliable. Although siRNA treatment 
can cause unexpected effects (35), the reduced ASO ac-
tivity in La-and NPM1-siRNA-treated cells appears to 
be specific, since treatments with NCL1-siRNA and U16-
siRNA did not have significant effects on ASO-directed tar-
get reduction (Figure 2C and D). We performed similar 
siRNA-mediated reduction experiments for an additional 
18 proteins identified in the ASO-binding assay and found 
no significant effect on ASO activity (Table 2). For exam-
ple, siRNA-mediated reduction of ASO-binding proteins 
ACLY, eIF4H, KCTD12, ATAD3A and GRSF1 did not al-
ter the activity of ASOs targeting different RNAs (Supple-
mentary Figures S1-S4). 
To further confirm that decreased ASO activity was 
caused by reductions in levels of La or NPM1 proteins 
and not experimental artifacts, La protein was reduced in 
HeLa cells either by treatment with an siRNA or with a </p>

<p>La-specific ASO with a sequence different from the siRNA 
(Figure 3A). The siRNA and the ASO cause mRNA degra-
dation through different pathways (i.e. RISC and RNase 
H1 pathways, respectively). The activity of the PTEN ASO 
was reduced in cells depleted of La protein, regardless of 
the methods used (Figure 3B). Similarly, reduction in lev-
els of NPM1 using either siRNA or ASO treatment de-
creased the PTEN ASO activity (Figure 3C and D). Fi-
nally, we transfected HeLa cells with plasmids designed to 
over-express La or NPM1 proteins (Figure 3E) and found 
that over-expression of either protein led to moderately in-
creased ASO activity, as compared with control cells trans-
fected with an empty vector (Figure 3F and G). Together, 
these results confirm that La and NPM1 enhance ASO an-
tisense activity. 
The effects of depleting La and NPM1 proteins on ASO 
activity do not appear to be due to alterations in the nor-
mal functions of these proteins. La is required for the matu-
ration of polymerase III-transcribed RNAs (32); however, 
under the experimental conditions we used for depletion 
of La, the steady-state levels of polymerase III-transcribed 
tRNA 
tyr and 7SL RNA were not affected (Supplementary 
Figure S5A). NPM1 is involved in ribosome biogenesis and 
nuclear transport of RPL5 protein (36,37), and steady-state 
rRNA levels and the nuclear/cytoplasmic distribution of 
RPL5 protein were not affected by NPM1 depletion under 
our experiment conditions (Supplementary Figure S5B and </p>



<p>Table 1. List of the identified ASO-binding proteins </p>

<p>Table 2. Effects of proteins on ASO activity </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2933 </p>

<p>Figure 2. La and NPM1 enhance ASO activity. (A) Levels of mRNAs encoding La and NPM1 were reduced by siRNA treatment for 48 h, as determined by 
qRT-PCR analyses. Cells treated with NCL1 siRNA or a functionally inactive U16 siRNA were used as controls, and mRNA levels were determined by qRT-
PCR. (B) Reduction of La and NPM1 protein levels was confirmed by western analysis. Whole cell lysates from mock-transfected (UTC) or siRNA-treated 
cells were subjected to western immunoblotting. ␥ -tubulin served as a loading control. (C-F) Depletion of La or NPM1 protein reduced the activity of ASOs 
targeting PTEN, drosha, NCL1 and U16 RNAs, respectively. Control cells or cells treated with siRNAs were transfected with indicated concentrations of 
ASOs for 4 h, and RNA was prepared and subjected to qRT-PCR analyses using primer probe sets specific to each ASO-targeted RNA. Where shown, 
error bars are standard deviations of three independent experiments. P-values were calculated based on unpaired t-test (n = 3), and the significance is 
indicated above the bars. 'NS': not significant. '*': 0.01&lt;P&lt;0.05; '**': 0.001&lt;P&lt;0.01; '***': 0.0001&lt;P&lt;0.001; and '****': 0.00001&lt;P&lt;0.0001. </p>



<p>Figure 3. The effects on ASO activity were specific to depletion of La or NPM1. (A) Western analysis for La protein in cells treated with either siRNA or 
an ASO targeting La mRNA. ␥ -tubulin served as a loading control. UTC indicates mock-transfected cells. (B) Reduction of La levels by either siRNA 
or ASO caused similar effects on the activity of an ASO targeting PTEN mRNA. ASO treatment and qRT-PCR analysis were performed as described 
in Figure 2. (C) NPM1 protein was reduced by either an siRNA or an ASO targeting NPM1 mRNA as determined by western. ␥ -tubulin was used as a 
loading control. (D) Reduction of NPM1 protein by either siRNA or ASO decreased the activity of an ASO targeting PTEN mRNA. (E) La or NPM1 was 
transiently over-expressed in HeLa cells. After 48 h, protein levels were detected by western. (F, G) Over-expression of La or NPM1 protein increased the 
activity of ASOs targeting PTEN or NCL1 mRNAs, respectively. Where shown, the error bars are standard deviations of three independent experiments. 
P-values were calculated based on unpaired t-test (n = 3), and the significance is indicated above the bars. 'NS': not significant. '*': 0.01&lt;P&lt;0.05; '**': 
0.001&lt;P&lt;0.01; '***': 0.0001&lt;P&lt;0.001; and '****': 0.00001&lt;P&lt;0.0001. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2935 </p>

<p>C). Altogether, our results indicate that our experimental 
system is capable to identify the moderate changes in ASO 
activities induced by intracellular proteins and that La and 
NPM1 can enhance ASO activity. </p>

<p>Identification of additional proteins that can enhance ASO 
activity </p>

<p>Using the experimental systems described above and previ-
ously (22), we examined the effects of other ASO-binding 
proteins on ASO activity, as summarized in Table 2. The 
effects of reducing each of these proteins on ASO activ-
ity were repeated multiple times to confirm the observed 
phenotypes [data not shown and (22)]. Representative re-
sults are shown throughout this study. Collectively, 32 pro-
teins have been characterized thus far. Eighteen of the tested 
ASO-binding proteins do not appear to impact ASO activ-
ity, as described above. However, eight proteins enhanced 
ASO activity. In addition to La and NPM1, and the three 
TCP1 subunits that we reported recently (22), ANXA2, 
VARS and PC4/Sub1 were also found to enhance ASO ac-
tivity. ANXA2 is a phospholipid binding protein implicated 
in multiple cellular processes including exocytosis, endocy-
tosis, membrane reorganization, vesicular trafficking and 
regulation of gene expression (38). Depletion of ANXA2 
by siRNA treatment reduced the activities of tested ASOs 
targeting PTEN, NCL1 and U16 RNAs (Figure 4A-D). 
As a control, reduction of LRPPRC by siRNA treatment 
had no effect on ASO activity, as we reported previously 
(22,24). Similarly, reduction of VARS by two different siR-
NAs caused similar reduction of ASO activities (Figure 4E-
H), suggesting that VARS can also enhance ASO activity 
in cells. Although VARS functions in protein synthesis, the 
observed effects on ASO activity do not appear to be due 
to impaired translation, since reduction of the asparaginyl-
tRNA synthetase NARS, another ASO-binding protein, by 
two different siRNAs had no significant effect (Supplemen-
tary Figure S6). In addition, depletion of the transcrip-
tion co-factor PC4/Sub1, which binds both ssASO and the 
ASO/RNA duplex (Figure 1C), also moderately reduced 
ASO activity (Supplementary Figure S7). Currently it is not 
clear how PC4/Sub1 protein enhances ASO activity, as no 
co-localization of this protein with ASOs was observed and 
reduction of PC4 did not significantly affect ASO subcel-
lular distribution (data not shown). However, this protein 
may affect ASO activity in ways other than affecting ASO 
distribution. </p>

<p>Ku70/Ku80 proteins inhibit ASO activity </p>

<p>In addition to the proteins that enhance ASO activity, some 
proteins may inhibit ASO activity, as we reported recently 
for the paraspeckle proteins P54nrb and PSF (24). Indeed, 
we found in the current study that Ku70 and Ku80 proteins, 
which bind ssASOs and ASO/RNA duplexes as was the 
case for P54nrb and PSF (Figure 1C), also inhibited ASO 
activity. Ku70 and Ku80 proteins interact with each other to 
form a heterodimer that binds dsDNA break ends and is in-
volved in DNA repair (29). Levels of Ku70 or Ku80 protein 
were reduced using specific siRNAs; depletion of either pro-
tein led to a reduction in levels of the other (Figure 5A), con-</p>

<p>sistent with previous findings (39). Compared with mock-
transfected control cells, depletion of Ku70/Ku80 caused 
moderately greater reduction of PTEN (Figure 5B) and 
NCL1 mRNAs (Figure 5C) targeted by specific ASOs. As 
a negative control, siRNA-mediated reduction of LRPPRC 
had no effect on ASO activity. 
Since the effect of reducing Ku70/Ku80 on ASO activ-
ity was modest, we confirmed this observation by analyz-
ing effects of inhibiting expression of three different pro-
teins in the same experiment to minimize experimental vari-
ation. These proteins included Ku70, LRPPRC and TCP1␤. 
Treatment with siRNAs resulted in specific reductions in 
mRNA levels (Figure 5D). Consistent with our previous 
observations (22), reduction of TCP1␤ moderately reduced 
ASO activity, whereas depletion of Ku70 caused the oppo-
site effect (Figure 5E). As expected, reduction of LRPPRC 
had no significant effect on ASO activity. Together, our re-
sults indicate that Ku70/Ku80 complex proteins negatively 
affect ASO activity. </p>

<p>The effects of proteins on ASO activity are not unique to 
HeLa cells </p>

<p>As the identification and characterization of the ASO-
binding proteins described above were performed using 
HeLa cells, next, we determined if these proteins could also 
affect ASO activity in other cell types. To this end, La, 
Ku70 and ANXA2 were reduced by siRNA treatment in 
HEK293 cells (Supplementary Figure S8A), and the effect 
on ASO activity was analyzed using the NCL1 ASO (Sup-
plementary Figure S8B-D), as described above. The qRT-
PCR results indicate that reduction of La or ANXA2 de-
creased, whereas reduction of Ku70 increased, ASO activ-
ity, as compared with the effects in control cells treated with 
a luciferase siRNA. These results suggest that the identified 
ASO-binding proteins can also affect ASO activity in other 
cell types. 
Since ASO uptake and intracellular trafficking may uti-
lize different pathways between transfection and free up-
take, we then investigated if these proteins affect ASO ac-
tivity upon free uptake. For this purpose, La, Ku70 or 
ANXA2-reduced HEK293 cells were washed, reseeded and 
incubated for 16 h with the NCL1 ASO at different con-
centrations without transfection reagent, as described in the 
Materials and Methods section. Total RNA was prepared 
from cells and the levels of NCL1 mRNA were measured by 
qRT-PCR. The results showed that, similar to transfection, 
the ASO activity was reduced in La-or ANXA2-depleted 
cells, but increased in Ku70-reduced cells (Supplementary 
Figure S8E). Together, these results indicate that the ob-
served protein effects on ASO activity are not unique to a 
single cell type, and not unique to transfection delivery of 
ASOs. </p>

<p>The effects of proteins on ASO activity do not appear to be 
due to direct interactions with RNase H1 </p>

<p>Since ASO-mediated RNA reduction results from cleavage 
by RNase H1 (5), it is possible that the proteins identified 
or the treatments with different siRNAs or ASOs may affect 
the level of RNase H1. This was not the case, as RNase H1 </p>



<p>Figure 4. ANXA2 and VARS enhance ASO activity. (A) HeLa cells were either mock transfected (UTC) or treated with ANXA2 siRNA or a control 
LRPPRC siRNA for 32 h, and total RNA was prepared from an aliquot of cells and subjected to qRT-PCR analysis for ANXA2 or LRPPRC mRNA (left 
panel). Whole cell lysates prepared from an aliquot of cells were subjected to western analysis for ANXA2 (right panel). RPL5 served as a loading control. 
(B-D) Reduction of ANXA2, but not LRPPRC, decreased the activity of ASOs targeting (B) PTEN, (C) NCL1 or (D) U16 RNAs. Control or siRNA-
treated cells were transfected with ASOs targeting indicated mRNAs, and the antisense activity was determined by qRT-PCR. (E) VARS expression in HeLa 
cells was reduced by treatment with two different siRNAs. VARS mRNA (left) and protein (right) levels were detected by qRT-PCR or western analysis, 
respectively. GAPDH protein served as a loading control. (F-H) Reduction of VARS protein decreased the antisense activity of ASOs targeting (F) drosha, 
(G) NCL1 and (H) U16 RNAs, as determined by qRT-PCR analyses. Where shown, error bars are standard deviations of three independent experiments. 
P-values were calculated based on unpaired t-test (n = 3), and the significance is indicated above the bars. 'NS': not significant. '*': 0.01&lt;P&lt;0.05; '**': 
0.001&lt;P&lt;0.01; '***': 0.0001&lt;P&lt;0.001; and '****': 0.00001&lt;P&lt;0.0001. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2937 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Ku70 and Ku80 inhibit ASO activity. (A) siRNA mediated reduction of Ku70 or Ku80 proteins. siRNA targeting LRPPRC was used as a negative 
control. Whole cell lysates from control cells or cells treated with siRNAs for 36 h were subjected to western analyses for Ku70 or Ku80 protein. ␥ -tubulin 
served as a loading control. (B, C) Reduction of Ku70 or Ku80 protein, but not LRPPRC, increased the activity of ASOs targeting (B) PTEN and (C) 
NCL1 mRNAs as detected by qRT-PCR. (D) Reduction of Ku70, TCP1β or LRPPRC mRNAs by siRNA treatment was demonstrated by qRT-PCR. 
(E) qRT-PCR analysis for ASO-directed PTEN mRNA reduction in different test cells. Where shown, the error bars are standard deviations of three 
independent experiments. P-values were calculated based on unpaired t-test (n = 3), and the significance is indicated above the bars. 'NS': not significant. 
'*': 0.01&lt;P&lt;0.05; '**': 0.001&lt;P&lt;0.01; '***': 0.0001&lt;P&lt;0.001; and '****': 0.00001&lt;P&lt;0.0001. </p>

<p>protein levels were comparable in cells treated with various 
siRNAs (Supplementary Figure S9A). In addition, the lev-
els of RNase H1 and levels of ASO-binding proteins were 
not affected by transfection of cells with ASOs (Supplemen-
tary Figure S9B). 
Next, we analyzed whether any of the proteins that im-
pact ASO activity interact with RNase H1, directly or 
bridged by ASOs or the duplex. For this purpose, cell 
lysates were prepared from HEK293 cells over-expressing 
Flag-tagged RNase H1 and were incubated with an ASO 
or ASO/RNA-like duplex. RNase H1 and associated pro-
teins were co-immunoprecipitated using anti-Flag beads. 
The co-isolated proteins were eluted by competition using 
Flag peptides, precipitated and analyzed by western (Sup-</p>

<p>plementary Figure S9C). The Flag-tagged RNase H1 was 
efficiently isolated with or without ASOs. However, none 
of the tested ASO-binding proteins, including La, NPM1, 
PC4, ANXA2, VARS, Ku70 or Ku80, was co-selected with 
RNase H1 in the presence or absence of ASOs or the 
ASO/RNA-like duplex. Thus, the tested proteins do not 
have stable physical interactions with RNase H1, either di-
rectly or mediated by ASOs or ASO/RNA-like duplexes, 
although we cannot exclude the possibility that some pro-
teins may transiently interact with RNase H1 in cells, but 
not detected in our experiments. </p>



<p>Ku80 and P54nrb compete with RNase H1 for ASO/RNA 
duplex binding </p>

<p>Since no physical interaction was observed between the 
ASO-binding proteins and RNase H1, these proteins may 
affect ASO activity through other indirect mechanisms. For 
example, proteins like Ku70/Ku80 and P54nrb that inhibit 
antisense activity may bind to the ASO/RNA duplex to 
reduce the accessibility of RNase H1to the substrate. To 
evaluate this possibility, levels of P54nrb and Ku80 were 
reduced in HeLa cells by siRNA treatment, and affinity 
selection was performed using an ASO/RNA-like duplex 
formed with ISIS386652 and XL279. The co-isolated pro-
teins were determined by western analysis (Figure 6A). 
As expected, moderately less P54nrb and Ku80 were co-
isolated with the duplex from cell lysates depleted of the cor-
responding proteins as compared with amounts from con-
trol cells. However, the level of co-isolated RNase H1 was 
moderately increased upon depletion of P54nrb or Ku80, 
suggesting that P54nrb and Ku80 compete with RNase H1 
for binding to the duplex. This view is further supported by 
the observation that simultaneous depletion of P54nrb and 
Ku80 further increased the binding of RNase H1 to the du-
plex (Figure 6B and C). 
Next, we determined whether over-expression of RNase 
H1 reduced the binding of P54nrb or Ku80 proteins to the 
RNA/ASO duplex. Cell lysates were prepared from con-
trol HEK293 cells and HEK293 cells over-expressing Flag-
RNase H1. The over-expression of RNase H1 was con-
firmed by western analysis, and no significant changes in 
the levels of Ku80 or P54nrb were detected (Figure 6D). 
The endogenous RNase H1 was not detected due to its 
low abundance. Next, affinity selection was performed us-
ing the duplex, and co-isolated proteins were analyzed by 
western blot. The level of co-isolated RNase H1 was dra-
matically increased in cells that over-expressed RNase H1 
as compared with that in control cells (Figure 6E). More-
over, reduced binding of P54nrb (∼55% reduction) and 
Ku80 (∼38% reduction) to the duplex was observed upon 
RNase H1 over-expression. Together, these results indicate 
that P54nrb and Ku80 compete with RNase H1 for bind-
ing to the ASO/RNA duplex and suggest that competition 
with RNase H1 may contribute to the inhibitory effects of 
P54nrb and Ku80/Ku70 proteins on ASO activity. Thus, the 
data on these proteins and the data on the hspA8 and hn-
RNP F proteins described earlier identify a general mech-
anism affecting RNase H1-mediated ASO activity and the 
type of proteins likely to be involved. </p>

<p>La and NPM1 affect ASO nuclear accumulation </p>

<p>Next, we analyzed the potential mechanisms by which some 
ASO-binding proteins enhance ASO activity. Previous stud-
ies have shown that ASO activity positively correlates with 
ASO nuclear localization upon transfection (15). We thus 
examined the effects of reduction of certain identified pro-
teins on ASO subcellular distribution using confocal mi-
croscopy. Control cells or cells depleted of different ASO-
binding proteins were transfected with Cy3-labeled ASOs 
for 4 h, and ASO localization was determined in live cells 
by confocal imaging. No significant difference in the nu-
clear levels of ASOs was detected in cells individually de-</p>

<p>Figure 6. Ku80 and P54nrb compete with RNase H1 for binding to 
ASO/RNA duplex. (A) Reduction of P54nrb or Ku80 protein levels 
by siRNA treatment increased the binding of RNase H1 protein to 
the ASO/RNA-like duplex, as determined by affinity selection using an 
ASO/RNA-like duplex, followed by western analyses. (B) Simultaneous 
treatment with siRNAs targeting P54nrb and Ku80 reduced levels of both 
proteins, as shown by western analysis. (C) Simultaneous reduction of 
P54nrb and Ku80 led to a significant increase in the binding of RNase H1 
to the ASO/RNA-like duplex. Silver staining of an aliquot of the affinity 
selected proteins analyzed on a separate SDS-PAGE is shown as a loading 
control. (D) The protein levels of RNase H1, Ku80 and P54nrb in control 
cells (UTC) or cells over-expressing RNase H1 were evaluated by western 
blot. (E) Over-expression of RNase H1 led to reduced binding of P54nrb 
and Ku80 proteins to the ASO/RNA-like duplex, as determined by affin-
ity selection followed by western analyses. The numbers below the lanes 
indicate the estimated protein level relative to control. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2939 </p>

<p>pleted of Ku70, Ku80, PC4, VARS or ANXA2 as compared 
with control cells (data not shown). However, upon deple-
tion of NPM1, reduced nuclear ASO accumulation was ob-
served in many cells, as compared with that in control cells, 
in which ASOs strongly accumulated in nuclei (Figure 7A). 
Note that the reduced nuclear ASO accumulation was not 
due to the presence of siRNAs, as siRNA-mediated deple-
tion of NCL1 in the same way did not reduce ASO nuclear 
accumulation. 
To rule out the possibility that the difference in nu-
clear ASO levels in control and NPM1-depleted cells re-
sulted from variation in ASO transfection, control cells and 
NPM1-depleted cells were mixed and reseeded in the same 
dish, followed by transfection of Cy-3 labeled ASOs. Cells 
were fixed and stained for NPM1 protein. More intense 
ASO nuclear signal was observed in cells that exhibited 
strong NPM1 staining than in cells showing weaker NPM1 
staining (Figure 7B). These results indicate that reduction 
of NPM1 protein decreased ASO nuclear accumulation. 
Similarly, reduction of La protein also caused a significant 
reduction of ASO nuclear accumulation (Figure 7C). To-
gether, these results suggest that La and NPM1 proteins 
may enhance ASO activity by facilitating nuclear accumu-
lation of ASOs. </p>

<p>VARS is recruited to Lamp1-containing organelles in the 
presence of ASOs </p>

<p>In similar co-staining experiments, no significant co-
localization with ASOs transfected into cells was detected 
for La, NPM1, Ku70, Ku80 or PC4 proteins; ASOs and 
these proteins were evenly distributed in the nucleoplasm 
(data not shown). Similarly, no significant co-localization 
of transfected ASOs with VARS was detected in either cy-
toplasm or nucleus (data not shown). However, upon ASO 
free uptake, VARS appeared to be enriched in some cyto-
plasmic structures that co-localized with ASOs (Figure 8A, 
right panels). In cells without ASO, VARS was evenly dis-
tributed in the cytoplasm (Figure 8A, upper left panel). To 
determine whether these VARS-enriched structures were re-
lated to endocytosis organelles, ASO-incubated cells were 
co-stained for VARS and Lamp1, a lysosomal marker that 
is also present in some late endosomes (40). Consistently, 
in cells incubated with ASOs in the absence of transfection 
reagent, we observed aggregation of VARS in cytoplasmic 
structures that co-localized with Lamp1 (Figure 8B). By 
examining ∼300 cells, we found that 86.4% VARS-stained 
structures co-localized with Lamp1 and ASO. These results 
suggest that in the presence of ASOs VARS can localize to 
lysosomes/late endosomes. 
We next determined whether VARS depletion affected 
ASO subcellular localization. HeLa cells treated with an 
siRNA targeting VARS or control cells were incubated with 
2-M Cy3-labeled ASO for 24 h, fixed and stained for 
Lamp1. Consistent with previous studies, ASOs localized in 
perinuclear structures that co-localized with Lamp1 in the 
cytoplasm of control cells (Figure 8C, upper panel), sug-
gesting a dominant localization of ASOs in lysosomes/late 
endosomes upon free uptake. However, in VARS-depleted 
cells, ASOs localized in smaller, but condensed perinuclear 
structures (Figure 8C, lower panel; Supplementary Figure </p>

<p>S10A). Similarly, Lamp1 also appeared to be present in con-
densed perinuclear regions that co-localized with ASOs in 
VARS-depleted cells, but in control cells much of the Lamp1 
appeared in dot-like structures scattered throughout the cy-
toplasm. By analyzing about 200 cells in different images, 
we found that the condensed lysosome structure was ob-
served in 42.7 ± 6.6% of VARS reduced cells, and only in 
∼17.6 ± 7.9% of control cells. The condensed Lamp1 stain-
ing pattern in VARS-depleted cells was not driven by the 
uptake of ASOs, since a similar pattern of Lamp1 staining 
was observed in cells depleted of VARS using two different 
siRNAs but not incubated with ASOs (Supplementary Fig-
ure S10B). This effect seems to be specific to VARS reduc-
tion, since depletion of NARS did not alter the Lamp1 pat-
tern (data not shown). Together, these results suggest that 
VARS may affect lysosome structure or localization and 
also affects ASO localization into lysosomes/endosomes 
upon ASO free uptake. </p>

<p>ANXA2 co-localizes with ASOs in late endosomes </p>

<p>In cells transfected with ASOs, ANXA2 co-localized with 
ASOs in distinct cytoplasmic structures containing Lamp1 
(Supplementary Figure S10C). Since ANXA2 is required 
for endocytosis and for the biogenesis of late endosomes 
(38), this protein may be involved in ASO trafficking 
through the endocytosis pathway. To better understand this 
possibility, HeLa cells were incubated with ASOs by free 
uptake; under these conditions, ASOs mainly enter cells 
through endocytosis pathways (12). Interestingly, ANXA2 
protein was observed in distinct cytoplasmic loci in the pres-
ence of ASO, whereas in cells not treated with ASO an even 
staining pattern was observed (Figure 9A), suggesting that 
ASO treatment enriched ANXA2 in these cytoplasmic loci. 
Indeed, ANXA2-stained loci were not obvious 2 h after 
ASO treatment, although at this time significant amount 
of ASOs was already detected in cells (Supplementary Fig-
ure S10D). However, 4 h after ASO incubation, ANXA2 
was observed to co-localize with ASOs in distinct struc-
tures. These cytoplasmic ANXA2-containing structures co-
localized with ASOs and also with Lamp1 (Figure 9B), 
indicating lysosomal and/or late endosomal localization. 
However, fewer ANXA2-stained loci were observed than 
Lamp1-stained structures, suggesting ANXA2 was only en-
riched in a subset of Lamp1-containing organelles. To de-
termine whether the ANXA2-stained structures were late 
endosomes, we co-stained for Rab7, a marker of late endo-
somes. Indeed, upon ASO incubation, majority of ANXA2-
stained structures co-localized with Rab7 (Figure 9C). Sta-
tistical analyses showed that 74.7 ± 5.3% ANXA2-stained 
structures co-localized with RAB7, whereas 98 ± 1.8% 
ANXA2-stained structures co-localized with LAMP1, in-
dicating that some ANXA2 co-localized with ASOs in lyso-
somes. Early endosome enrichment of ANXA2 was not de-
tected upon ASO incubation as shown by co-staining for the 
early endosome marker EEA1 (Supplementary Figure S11). 
Together, these results indicate that ASO and ANXA2 are 
localized to late endosomes and lysosomes, implying that 
ANXA2 functions in ASO intracellular trafficking. </p>



<p>Figure 7. Reduction of NPM1 or La can moderately reduce nuclear ASO levels. (A) Control cells or cells depleted of NPM1 or NCL1 were transfected 
with 50-nM cy3-labeled ASOs (red) for 5 h, and images of live cells were taken. In many NPM1-siRNA-treated cells nuclear ASO levels were reduced as 
compared with control cells or NCL1-siRNA-treated cells. (B) NPM1-siRNA-treated cells and control cells were mixed, reseeded and transfected with 50-
nM cy3-labeled ASO. After 5 h, cells were fixed and stained for NPM1 protein. The arrows indicate cells in which NPM1 levels are reduced. (C) Reduction 
of La protein (green) by treatment with La-siRNA moderately reduced the nuclear ASO level, as compared with the levels in control cells. Scale bars: 10 
m. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2941 </p>

<p>Figure 8. VARS can co-localize with ASOs in Lamp1-stained structures upon free uptake and can affect lysosome pattern. (A) VARS staining (cyan) in 
control cells [(-)ASO] or cells incubated with 2-M cy3-labeled ASOs (red) for 24 h. Upon ASO incubation, VARS appears in aggregated dot structures 
that co-localize with ASOs (exemplified by arrows). Scale bars: 20 m. (B) VARS/ASO-containing structures co-localized with Lamp1, as indicated by 
arrows. HeLa cells incubated with 2-M Cy3-labeled ASOs for 24 h were fixed and co-stained for VARS and Lamp1. Scale bars: 10 m. (C) Reduction of 
VARS led to more condensed ASO/lysosome localization in perinuclear structures, as indicated by arrows. Control cells or cells treated with VARS-siRNA 
for 24 h were incubated with 2-M ASO for an additional 24 h, then fixed and stained for Lamp1. Scale bars: 20 m. </p>



<p>Figure 9. ANXA2 can co-localize with ASOs in late endosomes/lysosomes upon free uptake. (A) ANXA2 staining in control cells (left panel) or cells 
incubated with 2-M FITC-labeled ASOs for 24 h (right panels). ANXA2-stained structures that co-localize with ASOs are exemplified by arrows. Scale 
bars: 5 m. (B) Co-staining of ANXA2 and Lamp1 in cells incubated with 2-M Cy3-labeled ASOs for 24 h. Arrows indicate the co-localization of ASO, 
ANXA2 and Lamp1. Scale bars: 10 m. (C) Co-staining of ANXA2 and Rab7 in cells incubated with 2-M Cy3-labeled ASOs for 24 h. Co-localization 
of ASO/ANXA2/Rab7 is exemplified by arrows; whereas some ANXA2/ASO containing structures that do not co-localize with Rab7 are indicated by 
circles. Scale bars: 5 m. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2943 </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>PS ASOs bind proteins with higher affinity than do PO 
ASOs (20). To reduce non-specific binding and to enhance 
the probability of identification of proteins that are likely 
to impact ASO activity or localization, we developed a 
multi-step affinity selection assay to isolate PS ASO-binding 
proteins and proteins that bind ASO/RNA duplex. Using 
these approaches, we identified 56 intracellular proteins that 
bound to PS-ASOs. As our goal and the approach were to 
identify intracellular ASO-binding proteins, the set of pro-
teins we identified does not include many membrane pro-
teins, which may also play roles in ASO uptake and traf-
ficking. Thirty-two proteins were characterized for effects 
on ASO activity and localization. Among these proteins, 14 
exhibited effects on ASO activity. That most characterized 
ASO-binding proteins had no significant impact on ASO 
activity was not unexpected, since ASOs can bind many dif-
ferent proteins and the effects of reducing levels of a par-
ticular protein might be compensated by other proteins. In 
addition, we cannot exclude the possibility that some iso-
lated proteins may not bind ASOs in cells as there are many 
differences between live cells and cell homogenates. 
Effects of the characterized proteins on ASO activity 
were modest, with approximately doubling or halving of 
potencies in most cases. These changes were specific as evi-
denced by the following observations: (i) similar results were 
observed using different approaches (siRNA or RNase H-
dependent ASOs for inhibition of protein expression) and 
using different siRNAs to target the same mRNAs, ruling 
out potential off-target effects; (ii) reduction of 18 ASO-
binding proteins did not cause significant change in ASO 
activity, indicating the experimental system we used for the 
ASO activity assay is suitable for detecting these moderate 
changes; and (iii) over-expression of La or NPM1 led to op-
posite effects on ASO activity compared to protein deple-
tion, confirming these observed phenotypes are specific to 
the tested proteins. In addition, the effects on ASO activ-
ity appeared not to be due to secondary effects related to 
depletion of the proteins. The ASO activity assay was per-
formed at relatively early time points after protein deple-
tion to reduce the potential secondary effects due to inhi-
bition of the endogenous activities of the depleted proteins. 
For example, under the experimental conditions we used, 
reduction of La protein, which is required for the matura-
tion of polymerase III-transcribed RNAs (e.g. tRNAs and 
7SL RNA), did not cause detectable changes in the level of 
evaluated polymerase III transcripts. In addition, reduction 
of NPM1, which is involved in nucleocytoplasmic shuttling 
of RPL5 protein, did not change the subcellular distribu-
tion of RPL5 under our experimental conditions. Further-
more, the effects of reducing VARS on ASO activity were 
not due to impaired translation related to a deficiency in the 
charged tRNA, as reduction of NARS, another tRNA syn-
thetase, had no detectable effect on ASO activity. It is very 
unlikely that the effects of proteins on ASO activity were 
derived from altered stability of PS-ASOs with 2 -MOE or 
other 2 -modifications by reduction of these proteins, since 
these chemically modified ASOs are very stable, with a half-
life of 2-4 weeks in vivo (41). These results all argue that the 
influence of these proteins on ASO activity is specific, al-</p>

<p>though indirect effects for certain protein cannot be com-
pletely excluded. 
The moderate effect of each protein on ASO activity was 
not unexpected. ASOs can bind a variety of proteins, and 
each protein may associate with a small portion of cellular 
ASOs. In addition, due to the relatively high capacity of nu-
merous ASO-binding proteins, reduction of one particular 
protein may lead to binding of ASOs by other cellular pro-
teins. Thus, the effect of reduction of an individual protein 
could be partially compensated by many other proteins, re-
sulting in moderate phenotypes. 
One mechanism through which cellular proteins reduce 
ASO activity is by competition with RNase H1 for bind-
ing sites on the ASO-RNA duplex. Such competition has 
been observed for hnRNP F and hspA8, which were pre-
viously shown to inhibit ASO-directed RNase H cleavage 
(23). A similar mechanism was also observed in this study. 
We showed that P54nrb and Ku80 directly compete with 
RNase H1. We consider this as an important observation 
and already have reported that such mechanisms may com-
plicate interpretation of results from ASO experiments (23). 
Equally importantly, our results emphasize the complex-
ity of ASO-RNA-protein interactions and show that, once 
again, due to the low cellular concentration of RNase H1 
(2), abundant proteins may have a competitive advantage. 
That RNase H1 clearly has an affinity for the RNA/ASO 
duplex that is similar to Ku70/Ku80 is demonstrated by the 
fact that over-expression of RNase H1 overcame the effect 
of Ku70/Ku80 for binding and on antisense activity. The 
screening process to identify optimal sites for ASO activity 
in specific RNAs would be facilitated if preferred binding 
sequences for proteins that compete with RNase H1 were 
bettered elucidated. 
Proteins may enhance ASO activity through multiple 
mechanisms. Previously we showed that TCP1 complex pro-
teins enhance ASO activity (22). These proteins can be 
recruited to cytoplasmic structures related to endocyto-
sis, raising the possibility that these proteins may facilitate 
escape of ASOs from endosomes or lysosomes. Here, we 
showed that VARS, which enhanced ASO activity, was en-
riched in lysosome/endosome-related structures upon ASO 
incubation, suggesting that it may be involved in the re-
lease of ASOs from endocytosis structures into the cytosol. 
VARS is required for aminoacyl-tRNA synthesis (42), and a 
role in cellular uptake has not been documented. It is possi-
ble that this protein is recruited on the endosome/lysosomes 
when these structures are loaded with ASOs, which may 
cause some topological changes of the membrane struc-
tures. It is also possible that VARS may be directed by 
ASOs to localize in these organelles. Further investigation 
is needed to evaluate these possibilities. However, the ef-
fect of this protein on ASO activity appears to be specific 
as reduction of this protein using two different siRNAs 
caused similar effect on ASO activity, whereas reduction 
of another aminoacyl-tRNA synthase, NARS, had no de-
tectable effects. Moreover, reduction of VARS, but not re-
duction of NARS, led to strong perinuclear condensation 
of lysosomes, suggesting that this protein may be involved, 
directly or indirectly, in the distribution or localization of 
lysosomes. Thus, the increased ASO activity upon VARS </p>



<p>depletion may stem from altered ASO release from endo-
somes or lysosomes. 
In addition to VARS, we also found that ANXA2 was 
enriched in late endosomes and lysosomes upon ASO in-
cubation. This is not surprising, since ANXA2 is known 
to be involved in endocytosis and exocytosis (38). ANXA2 
is a phospholipid-binding protein that is required for the 
biogenesis of late endosomes from early endosomes (43). 
Given that this protein binds negatively charged phospho-
lipids of the membrane and that ASO release from lipo-
somes may occur through a flip-flop mechanism (44), bind-
ing of ANXA2 to the membrane of endosomes or lyso-
somes may change the local conformation of the lipid bi-
layer to facilitate ASO release and subsequently increased 
ASO activity. In addition, it is also likely that ANXA2 may 
be involved in ASO trafficking within the endocytosis path-
ways, such as from early endosome to late endosomes. 
Nuclear localization of ASOs is positively correlated with 
ASO activity after transfection (15). Thus, altering the ASO 
concentration in the nucleus may alter also activity. We 
tested the ASO localization upon free uptake in cells de-
pleted of various proteins, no significant nuclear localiza-
tion of ASOs was observed under this situation, since upon 
free uptake, the nuclear level of ASOs is too low to be con-
vincingly detected by confocal imaging. Thus, judging if the 
nuclear ASO level is affected by reduction of these different 
proteins awaits more sensitive detection approaches. How-
ever, upon transfection, alteration in the nuclear ASO levels 
appears to be the mechanism through which La and NPM1 
proteins enhance ASO activity. Reduction of La or NPM1 
decreased nuclear ASO levels, but did not completely pre-
vent nuclear localization of ASOs. A role of NPM1 in nu-
cleocytoplasmic shuttling has already been demonstrated 
for some ribosomal proteins. Thus it is possible that NPM1 
may also be involved in ASO trafficking, directly or indi-
rectly via other shuttling proteins. In addition, a role of La 
in nuclear export has also been reported (45); it is therefore 
likely that this protein may contribute to ASO shuttling. 
However, other possibilities also exist. For example, it has 
been reported that La has non-canonical helicase activity 
(46) and can accelerate duplex formation and enhance du-
plex dissociation (47). Thus, La may facilitate ASO binding 
to mRNA substrate or unwinding of the ASO/RNA duplex 
after RNase H1 cleavage. 
Further understanding how additional ASO-binding 
proteins impact ASO activity, especially the roles of these 
proteins on ASO intracellular trafficking/distribution, 
awaits further investigation. We are currently investigating 
the structure-activity relationships of ASO binding to vari-
ous types of proteins. This information should enable us to 
design more effective ASOs. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We wish to thank Walt Lima and Timothy Vickers for stim-
ulating discussions. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>ISIS Pharmaceuticals. Funding for open access charge: ISIS 
Pharmaceuticals. 
Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2015, Vol. 43, No. 5 2945 </p>



</text></tei>