<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4410849" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>Squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) of the lung is the second most common subtype of lung cancer. 
With limited treatment options, the 5-year survival rate of SCC is only 15%. Although genomic 
alterations in SCC have been characterized, identifying the alterations that drive SCC is critical for 
improving treatment strategies. Mouse models of SCC are currently limited. Using lentiviral 
delivery of Sox2 specifically to the mouse lung, we tested the ability of Sox2 to promote 
tumorigenesis in multiple tumor suppressor backgrounds. Expression of Sox2, frequently 
amplified in human SCC, specifically cooperates with loss of Lkb1 to promote squamous lung 
tumors. Mouse tumors exhibit characteristic histopathology and biomarker expression similar to 
human SCC. They also mimic human SCCs by activation of therapeutically relevant pathways 
including STAT and mTOR. This model may be utilized to test the contribution of additional 
driver alterations in SCC, as well as for preclinical drug discovery. </p>

<p>Lung cancer is a leading cause of cancer-related deaths in the United States and worldwide. 
Squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) is the second most common type of lung cancer, 
representing ~30% of cases and over 400,000 deaths worldwide each year (Cancer Genome 
Atlas Research Network, 2012; Jemal et al., 2011). Currently, the 5-year survival rate for 
SCC is approximately 15%. One of the major problems contributing to treatment failure is a </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/). </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Correspondence: trudy.oliver@hci.utah.edu. 
SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION 
Supplemental Information includes Supplemental Experimental Procedures and three figures and can be found with this article online 
at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2014.05.036. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS 
A.M. designed and performed the majority of experiments, acquired and analyzed data, and wrote the manuscript. K.B., U.K., P.C., 
and S.P. performed experiments. S.C provided human tissue. B.W. and S.C. analyzed histopathology and provided clinical expertise. 
T.O. conceived of the project, analyzed the data, and wrote the paper. </p>

<p>HHS Public Access </p>

<p>Author manuscript </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Published in final edited form as: 
Cell Rep. 2014 July 10; 8(1): 40-49. doi:10.1016/j.celrep.2014.05.036. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>lack of targeted therapies. Targeted therapies that are effective against adenocarcinoma, the 
other major subtype of non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC), are ineffective or 
contraindicated for SCC. The current standard of care for SCC involves surgery when 
operable, or combination chemotherapy, usually a platinum doublet, which has a poor 
response rate (Oliver et al., 2013). Identification of new therapeutic targets for SCC requires 
elucidation of the critical genes and pathways driving this disease. </p>

<p>Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network (2012) recently sequenced 178 human SCCs, 
identifying numerous genetic alterations that may serve as valuable therapeutic targets. 
However, SCC has one of the highest mutation rates of all tumor types, making it difficult to 
distinguish "driver" from "passenger" mutations. Some genetic alterations in SCC occur in 
proteins for which targeted therapies are available, such as fibroblast growth factor receptor 
(FGFR) and phosphatidyl inositol 3-kinase (PI3K)/ AKT. Other potential oncogenic drivers 
were discovered for which there are currently no available therapies, such as the 
transcription factors SOX2, P63, and NRF2 (Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, 
2012). </p>

<p>Mouse models of adenocarcinoma and small cell lung cancer (SCLC) have been utilized to 
understand mechanisms of tumor initiation, progression, and therapeutic response (Kwon 
and Berns, 2013). Genetic models of SCC have only recently been generated (Ji et al., 2007; 
Xiao et al., 2013). The combination of Kras G12D expression and Lkb1 loss in the mouse lung 
leads to lung tumors of multiple lineages (adenocarcinoma, mixed adenosquamous, 
squamous, and large cell) (Jackson et al., 2001; Ji et al., 2007). While KRAS is commonly 
mutated in human lung adenocarcinomas (~21%), it is rarely altered in SCC (~6%) (Perez-
Moreno et al., 2012). In the mouse lung, Kras G12D expression alone promotes the exclusive 
development of lung adenocarcinomas (Jackson et al., 2001). LKB1 (also known as serine/ 
threonine kinase 11; STK11), a tumor suppressor implicated in metabolism, cell polarity, and 
growth control, is lost or mutated in 5%-19% of human SCCs (Ji et al., 2007; Perez-Moreno 
et al., 2012; Shackelford and Shaw, 2009). This suggests that Lkb1 loss in the 
Kras G12D/+ Lkb1 fl/fl model contributes to the altered spectrum of lung tumor types, including 
squamous tumors. </p>

<p>Recently, a kinase-dead IKKα knockin mouse was reported to develop lung SCCs (Xiao et 
al., 2013). This discovery followed other mouse models with loss-of-function IKKα alleles 
that developed papillomas and skin SCC (Liu et al., 2012). The kinase-dead IKKα knockin 
mice develop spontaneous SCCs of the lung but also develop tumors in the skin, 
forestomach, and esophagus, contributing to early mortality (Xiao et al., 2013). When wild-
type IKKα expression is restored using a skin promoter, mice survive longer and develop 
lung SCCs but still have defects in the forestomach and esophagus. These phenotypes are 
consistent with the observation that IKKα is downregulated in human skin SCC and in head 
and neck SCC (Liu et al., 2012), but the role of IKKα in lung SCC is less clear. Copy 
number losses and genomic mutations in IKKα are rare in human lung SCCs, and other 
mechanisms of altering IKKα and its related pathways are not well defined (Cancer Genome 
Atlas Research Network, 2012). The broad spectrum of lung tumor types in 
Kras G12D/+ Lkb1 fl/fl mice and the extrapulmonary phenotypes in the kinase-dead IKKα mice </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. 
Page 2 </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>make the study of biomarkers, mechanisms of progression, and squamous-specific therapies 
difficult. </p>

<p>SOX2 is one of the most frequently altered genes in human SCC, amplified in ~21% and 
overexpressed in 60%-90% of tumors (Bass et al., 2009; Brcic et al., 2012; Cancer Genome 
Atlas Research Network, 2012; Hussenet et al., 2010). SOX2 is also frequently expressed in 
early-stage SCC, suggesting that SOX2 expression may be an initiating event in SCC 
development (Bass et al., 2009; Brcic et al., 2012; Hussenet et al., 2010). Gain-of-function 
and loss-of-function studies have previously underscored a critical role for Sox2 in lung 
development, specifically its importance in the proliferation and differentiation of basal and 
neuroendocrine cells (Gontan et al., 2008; Lu et al., 2010; Que et al., 2009). Consistent with 
this observation, SOX2 amplification is common in SCC and SCLC, lung tumors that are 
thought to originate from basal and neuroendocrine cells, respectively (Bass et al., 2009; 
Hussenet et al., 2010; Rudin et al., 2012). However, expression of Sox2 alone in the lung 
promotes hyperplasia and tumors of the adenocarcinoma lineage with aberrant basal cell 
marker expression (Lu et al., 2010). Although SOX2 is one of the most frequent genetic 
alterations associated with human SCC, it has not yet been shown to promote squamous lung 
tumors in vivo. Here, we sought to identify combinations of gene drivers that promote lung 
SCC. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Lentiviral Approach to Identify Combinatorial Drivers of Lung SCC </p>

<p>To identify genetic combinations that facilitate Sox2-driven SCC, we used a lentiviral 
approach to combine Sox2 expression with loss of distinct tumor suppressor genes. 
Bicistronic lentiviruses expressing Sox2 and Cre recombinase are delivered specifically to 
the mouse lung using intranasal inhalation, allowing constitutive expression of two genes 
driven by β-Actin and Pgk promoters, respectively. Lentiviruses are administered to mice 
harboring conditional LoxP-flanked ("floxed") tumor suppressor alleles to simultaneously 
create two genetic "hits": expression of Sox2 via the lentivirus and deletion of a tumor 
suppressor gene using the Cre/LoxP system (Figure S1A). Control cDNA (GFP) or murine 
Sox2 were cloned into bicistronic lentiviral vectors under control of the β-Actin promoter 
(referred to as Lenti-GFP-Cre or Lenti-Sox2-Cre, respectively). Sox2 expression was 
validated by immunoblot analysis and Cre expression was verified using a human 
embryonic kidney 293T (HEK293T) reporter system that was used to calculate viral titer 
(Figures S1B and S1C). </p>

<p>Mice harboring conditional LoxP-flanked tumor suppressor alleles (Lkb1 fl/fl , p53 fl/fl , or 
p53 fl/fl Rb fl/fl ) were infected with Lenti-GFP-Cre or Lenti-Sox2-Cre. LKB1 is lost or mutated 
in 5%-19% of human SCCs, but loss of Lkb1 alone in the mouse lung does not lead to tumor 
formation (Ji et al., 2007). TP53 is one of the most common genetic alterations in SCC 
(mutated in ~81% of tumors), but loss of p53 alone in the mouse lung leads to rare 
adenocarcinomas after long latencies (Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, 2012; 
Jackson et al., 2005; Meuwissen et al., 2003). Both TP53 and RB1 alterations are common in 
human SCLC (in which SOX2 is genomically amplified in ~27% of cases), and loss of 
p53/Rb in the mouse lung leads to SCLC after long latencies, as well as rare </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. 
Page 3 </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>adenocarcinomas (Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, 2012; Meuwissen et al., 2003; 
Rudin et al., 2012). We reasoned that these tumor suppressor genes may cooperate with 
Sox2 expression to promote lung tumor development. Beginning at 3 months postinfection, 
mice were monitored for tumor formation every month by low-dose microcomputed 
tomography (microCT) imaging for 7.5-12 months or until tumors were detected. The Sox2-
Lkb1 combination had the greatest reduction in tumor-free survival compared to other 
genetic combinations tested (Figure S1D). Individual tumors were observed by microCT in 
all three conditional genetic backgrounds and analyzed by histopathology (Figures 1A and 
1B; Table 1). It is striking that most of the tumors in the Lenti-Sox2-Cre Lkb1 fl/fl 
combination (n = 7 of 9 tumors in 17 mice) were classified as squamous tumors, as 
determined by analysis of hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E)-stained sections by two 
independent pathologists (Figure 1B; Table 1). Sox2-Lkb1 squamous tumors exhibited 
characteristic SCC features, including keratin pearls and desmoplastic stroma (Brcic et al., 
2012) (Figure 1B). Lkb1 fl/fl mice receiving Lenti-GFP-Cre did not develop tumors (n = 0 of 
14 mice) as expected (Table 1). Sox2 expression in the context of p53 loss or loss of p53/Rb 
did not lead to squamous lung tumors, but it did lead to a few adenocarcinomas at latencies 
of 5-12 months (Table 1). The Sox2-Lkb1 combination exhibited significantly increased 
tumor incidence (Fisher's exact test, two sided, p = 0.009) and a significant enrichment in 
squamous tumors (89% versus 0%, Fisher's exact test, two sided, p = 0.001), compared to 
all other genetic combinations combined (Table 1). Together, these findings suggest that 
Sox2 expression and Lkb1 loss specifically cooperate to promote squamous tumorigenesis. </p>

<p>Lenti-Sox2-Cre Lkb1 fl/fl Tumors Express Biomarkers of Human SCC </p>

<p>Expression of basal cell markers such as cytokeratin-5 (K5), -14 (K14), and P63 distinguish 
human SCC from adenocarcinoma (Reis-Filho et al., 2003; Terry et al., 2010). We analyzed 
tumors from each genetic combination, as well as 12 human SCCs for squamous biomarker 
expression. Sox2-Lkb1 squamous tumors consistently expressed all of the basal cell markers 
examined (K5, K14, and p63) and were similar to human SCC, whereas adenocarcinomas in 
mice from other genetic combinations including Kras G12D did not (Figures 1C and 1D; 
Figure S2; Table 1). Most human lung tumors express TTF1 (also known as Nkx2.1), but 
mean expression of TTF1 is significantly reduced in SCCs compared to adenocarcinomas 
and is reportedly expressed in only ~10% of SCCs (Perner et al., 2009). Compared to 
Kras G12D -driven mouse adenocarcinomas that were uniformly TTF1 positive, TTF1 levels 
were significantly reduced in Sox2-Lkb1 tumors (Student's unpaired t test, p = 0.02) (Figures 
1C and 1D). Sox2-Lkb1 tumors exhibited a broad spectrum of TTF1 expression, ranging 
from no TTF1 expression (similar to human SCCs) to higher levels of expression. Sox2-
Lkb1 tumors expressed significantly less TTF1 than mouse adenocarcinomas but 
significantly more TTF1 than human SCCs (Student's unpaired t test, p = 0.04) (Figures 1C 
and 1D). Taken together, these results demonstrate that Sox2-Lkb1 tumors highly resemble 
human SCC at the level of histopathology and squamous biomarker expression. </p>

<p>Next, we sought to validate Sox2 expression and Lkb1 loss in mouse squamous tumors. All 
Sox2-Lkb1 tumors were strongly positive for nuclear Sox2 expression, similar to 75% of 
human SCCs (n = 9 of 12) (Figures 2A and 2B). Kras G12D -driven adenocarcinomas and 
adenocarcinomas arising from other genetic combinations (p53 or p53/Rb loss) were </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>negative for Sox2 (Figures 2A and 2B; Figure S2). Given that the same lentiviruses were 
used in all experiments, this suggests that there may be a selective advantage for high Sox2 
expression in the context of Lkb1 loss. It is interesting that Kras G12D/+ Lkb1 fl/fl squamous 
tumors had little or no Sox2 expression, suggesting that there may be Sox2-independent 
mechanisms of squamous tumorigenesis (Figures 2A and 2B). Recombination of the Lkb1 
allele was determined by PCR analysis on DNA from macrodissected Sox2-Lkb1 tumors. All 
tumors examined (n = 5 of 5) demonstrated the presence of the recombined Lkb1 floxed 
allele as well as Sox2 expression (Figure 2C; Table 1). Two of nine Sox2-Lkb1 tumors 
appeared as adenocarcinomas by H&amp;E, and both tumors exhibited Sox2 expression and 
Lkb1 recombination; one tumor expressed basal cell markers and, as such, was reclassified 
by pathologists as squamous, whereas the other tumor did not express K5 or p63 (Table 1). 
This suggests that Sox2 expression and Lkb1 loss may not be sufficient for squamous 
tumorigenesis in all contexts and/or that this adenocarcinoma represents an intermediate 
state that has the potential to trans-differentiate to a squamous tumor under certain 
conditions (Han et al., 2014). </p>

<p>LKB1 phosphorylates and activates adenosine monophosphate-activated protein kinase 
(AMPK), which negatively regulates the mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) pathway. 
Immunohistochemical (IHC) analysis of Sox2-Lkb1 tumors demonstrated an absence of 
phosphorylated AMPK (pAMPK) and enhanced expression of phosphorylated eukaryotic 
translation initiation factor 4E-binding protein 1 (p4EBP1), an mTOR substrate (Hay and 
Sonenberg, 2004; Perner et al., 2009), con-firming activation of the mTOR pathway 
(Figures 2A and 2B). The mTOR pathway is frequently activated in human lung SCCs and 
represents a potential therapeutic target (Mantripragada and Khurshid, 2013). Indeed, we 
observed that, of the human SCCs with strong SOX2 expression (9 of 12), five demonstrated 
evidence of mTOR pathway activation as well (55% of Sox2+ SCCs) (Figure 2D). 
Altogether, these data reveal that SOX2 expression and mTOR activity frequently co-occur 
in human SCC and that Sox2-Lkb1 tumors strongly resemble human SCCs at the level of 
pathway activation. </p>

<p>Sox2-Driven SCCs Exhibit Expression or Activation of Potential Therapeutic Targets </p>

<p>To identify pathways dysregulated in Sox2-driven SCC, we performed IHC analysis for 
therapeutically relevant pathways in Sox2-Lkb1 tumors, Kras G12D Lkb1 fl/fl squamous tumors 
identified by K5 staining, and human SCCs. FGFR family members are frequently amplified 
and/or harbor activating point mutations in human SCC, and FGFR inhibitors are currently 
in clinical trials (Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, 2012; Dutt et al., 2011; Liao et 
al., 2013). Notably, SOX2 and FGFR2 expression are highly correlated in human SCC, and 
SOX2 can bind the FGFR2 promoter (Bass et al., 2009; Boyer et al., 2005; Fang et al., 
2011), suggesting that FGFR2 may be a direct target of SOX2 in lung cancer. We examined 
expression of FGFR2 in each tumor group and found that Fgfr2 expression tended to be 
higher in Sox2-Lkb1 tumors compared to Kras G12D Lkb1 fl/fl squamous tumors, but these data 
did not reach statistical significance (Figures 3A and 3B). FGFR2 was highly induced by 
SOX2 expression in human A549 lung cancer cells harboring LKB1 mutations (Figure S3) 
but not in two other cell lines with LKB1 mutations (H23 and H157) (Mahoney et al., 2009; </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure S3). We were not able to detect phospho-Frs or pFGFR2 in the Sox2-Lkb1 tumors, so 
it remains to be determined whether pathways downstream of FGFR2 are activated. </p>

<p>The nuclear factor κB (NF-κB) pathway is activated and implicated in various cancers, 
including lung adenocarcinoma (Meylan et al., 2009; Xue et al., 2011) and lung SCC (Xiao 
et al., 2013). Sox2-Lkb1 tumors demonstrated evidence of NF-κB pathway activity as 
indicated by nuclear p65, similar to Kras-driven adenocarcinomas (Figure S3). Although, 
the role of NF-κB signaling in SCC development remains to be determined, activation of 
this pathway in multiple mouse models of SCC warrants further study of NF-κB as a 
potential therapeutic target. Inducible SOX2 expression alone was not sufficient to increase 
nuclear p65 in human cell lines regardless of LKB1 status, suggesting that other factors are 
likely driving NF-κB signaling in these cells (Figure 3C). </p>

<p>The RAS/MAPK/PI3K pathways are frequently activated in human squamous tumors via 
different mechanisms (Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network, 2012). To examine the 
status of these pathways, we stained tumors for pErk and pAkt. Notably, pErk was 
significantly reduced in Sox2-Lkb1 tumors compared to Kras G12D Lkb1 fl/fl squamous tumors 
and human SCCs (Figures 3A and 3B). We speculate that Kras activation in 
Kras G12D Lkb1 fl/fl squamous tumors maintains pErk signaling, which is absent in Sox2-
driven tumors. We observed variable levels of pAkt in Sox2-Lkb1 tumors, ranging from little 
or no pAkt to high levels similar to those in Kras G12D Lkb1 fl/fl tumors (Figures 3A and 3B). 
Together, Sox2-Lkb1 tumors had reduced MAPK pathway activity compared to 
Kras G12D Lkb1 fl/fl squamous tumors, suggesting that Sox2-Lkb1 tumors may rely more 
heavily on other growth factor signaling pathways for proliferation, including mTOR. A 
recent study published while this article was under consideration demonstrated that Pten loss 
cooperates with Lkb1 loss to promote SCC (Xu et al., 2014). Notably, Pten/Lkb1-null tumors 
also exhibited low MAPK pathway activation. </p>

<p>Stat3 has been shown to cooperate with Sox2 to promote tumor progression in esophageal 
and forestomach tumors, cancers in which SOX2 is genomically amplified (Liu et al., 2013). 
Preclinical studies have identified STAT3 inhibitors, and STAT3 decoys are now being 
tested in patients with head and neck SCC (Sen et al., 2012). Compared to Kras G12D 
adenocarcinomas and Kras G12D Lkb1 fl/fl squamous tumors, the Jak-Stat pathway was 
significantly activated in Sox2-Lkb1 tumors (indicated by phospho-Stat3) with clear nuclear 
pStat3 in some cells within the squamous tumors (Figures 3A and 3B). Human SCCs had 
variable levels of pStat3 similar to those in Sox2-Lkb1 tumors (Figures 3A and 3B). It is 
striking that, in multiple human lung cancer cell lines of adenocarcinoma and squamous 
lineage, inducible expression of SOX2 consistently promoted nuclear pStat3 accumulation 
(Figure 3C). Altogether, these data suggest that Sox2 contributes to Stat signaling in vivo 
and thus represents a therapeutic target warranting further investigation for SCC treatment. </p>

<p>To summarize, we have used a lentiviral-based approach to generate a mouse model of SCC 
based on Sox2 expression and Lkb1 loss, highlighting their cooperation in lung SCC 
development. Both SOX2 expression and mTOR pathway activity frequently co-occur in 
human SCC, making this model particularly relevant to the human disease. Mouse tumors 
recapitulate the human disease at the level of histopathology, biomarker expression, and </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>activation of potential therapeutic targets that have been largely unexplored in SCC 
treatment. It is important to note that Stat signaling was induced by SOX2 in vitro and 
enriched in Sox2-driven squamous tumors. This model thus serves as a preclinical tool to 
test whether STAT inhibition is therapeutically effective against Sox2-driven SCCs. </p>

<p>The low penetrance of tumor formation in this model may be due to low lentiviral titer 
and/or the underlying cell of origin. Although we recognize that tumor numbers in this study 
are low, the paucity of other squamous lung tumor models suggests that this particular 
genetic combination is highly relevant. While this article was under consideration, Xu et al. 
demonstrated that Pten/Lkb1 loss promotes squamous lung tumors exclusively, in contrast to 
Kras/Lkb1 mice, which develop multiple tumor types (Ji et al., 2007; Xu et al., 2014). It 
remains unknown why PI3K activation, as opposed to MAPK, would lead exclusively to 
squamous tumors in the context of Lkb1 loss, especially since PI3K pathway alterations also 
occur in adenocarcinoma (Ding et al., 2008). We speculate that, since Pten/Lkb1-null tumors 
express Sox2, Sox2 may be a critical target of the PI3K pathway in these tumors. </p>

<p>In both Pten/Lkb1 and Sox2/Lkb1 mouse models, inflammatory microenvironment and 
activation of immune signaling pathways appear to distinguish SCC from adenocarcinoma 
(Xu et al., 2014). A notable difference between the two models is that adenoviruses used in 
Pten/Lkb1 and Kras/Lkb1 models are thought to enhance inflammation compared to 
lentiviruses used here. These models will serve as preclinical tools for further investigation 
of immunotherapy efficacy and function. </p>

<p>It is unclear whether SCCs arise from basal cells or whether the transforming events 
promote basal cell differentiation. The identity of the cell of origin for SCC remains an 
important unanswered question. One model suggests that basal cells serve as the cells of 
origin because SCCs express basal cell markers and Sox2 is expressed in basal cells (Que et 
al., 2009; Sutherland and Berns, 2010). However, other studies suggest that Sox2 promotes 
basal cell fate (Han et al., 2014; Lu et al., 2010). Recent studies in Kras G12D/+ Lkb1 fl/fl mice 
suggest that type II pneumocyte-derived lung adenocarcinomas can transdifferentiate into 
SCCs (Han et al., 2014). Given that lentiviruses in our model may target multiple cell types 
in the mouse lung, it is possible that Sox2 expression and Lkb1 loss are capable of altering 
cell fate to a squamous-like identity. Given that we also detected one tumor that appeared as 
an adenocarcinoma expressing basal cell markers, we speculate that transdifferentiation may 
also occur in this model. The lentiviral approach used here could be adapted to investigate 
the cell of origin for Sox2-driven SCCs. </p>

<p>Bicistronic lentiviruses may also be used to test other candidate SCC drivers, such as P63 
and NRF2, as well as to identify cooperating genetic events that promote SCC. We expect 
that murine squamous tumors will have fewer "passenger" genetic alterations than human 
SCC due to lack of carcinogen exposure, thereby providing a biological filter to identify 
"driver" genetic changes in SCC. Beyond lung cancer, findings from this model may have 
important clinical implications for other squamous or SOX2-driven malignancies such as 
SCLC and brain, esophageal, and oral cancers. </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Mouse Breeding and Lentiviral Infections </p>

<p>Mice were housed in an environmentally controlled room according to the Committee of 
Animal Care. Lkb1 fl/fl mice were purchased from The Jackson Laboratory. LSL-Kras G12D/+ 
and p53 fl/fl animals were kindly provided by Tyler Jacks. p53 fl/fl Rb fl/fl mice were generated 
by Anton Berns (Meuwissen et al., 2003) and obtained from T. Jacks. Lung tumor tissue 
from Kras G12D/+ Lkb1 fl/fl mice was kindly provided by Reuben Shaw. At 6-8 weeks of age, 
anesthetized mice were infected with ~10 7 infectious units/ml of Lenti-Sox2-Cre or GFP-
Cre lentiviruses or 6.47 ~10 7 plaque-forming units of AdCre (University of Iowa) by nasal 
instillation as described elsewhere (Jackson et al., 2001). Viruses were administered in a 
Biosafety Level 2+ room according to Institutional Biosafety Committee guidelines. </p>

<p>Lentivirus Production </p>

<p>GFP and murine Sox2 cDNAs were cloned into bicistronic lentiviral vectors expressing Cre 
to generate Lenti-Sox2-Cre and Lenti-GFP-Cre plasmids and confirmed by direct 
sequencing. 293T cells were transfected with a three-plasmid transfection system including 
the lentiviral vector, pCMV-delta-8.2 (Addgene) and pCMV-VSV-G (Addgene). Virus was 
harvested posttransfection, concentrated by ultracentrifugation (24,000 × g), and titered 
using HEK293T reporter cells stably expressing a Lox-DsRed2(Stop)-Lox-GFP cassette. 
Number of cells expressing green fluorescent protein was measured by flow cytometry and 
used to calculate titer (infectious U/ml). </p>

<p>MicroCT Imaging </p>

<p>At indicated time points, mice were scanned for 30 s to 2 min under isoflurane anesthesia 
using a small animal Quantum FX microCT (PerkinElmer) at 45 υm resolution, 90 kV, with 
160 υA current. Images were acquired using <rs type="software">PerkinElmer Quantum FX</rs> software and 
processed with <rs id="software-1" type="software">Analyze</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">11.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">AnalyzeDirect</rs>). </p>

<p>Human Tissue </p>

<p>Excess deidentified fresh tissue was obtained with prior patient consent under approved 
protocol by the institutional review board (#10924). Institutional guidelines regarding 
specimen use were followed. </p>

<p>Supplementary Material </p>

<p>Refer to Web version on PubMed Central for supplementary material. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Drs. W. Akerley, S. Slomowitz, and A.J. Bhutkar for valuable advice and Dr. K. Jones for critical reading 
of the manuscript. We are especially grateful to Dr. R. Shaw for providing Kras/Lkb1 tissue. Thanks to members of 
the T.G.O. Lab for technical support, especially M. Terry, R. Arya, and J. Clegg. We thank Y. Derose, B. 
Anderson, and K. Gligorich for histological services; M. DuPage, K. Lane, and the T. Jacks laboratory for lentiviral 
constructs; and M. Van Brocklin for HEK293T reporter cells. T.G.O. was supported in part by a Department of 
Defense Lung Concept Award (DoD USAMRAA W81XWH-12-1-0211) and a V Scholar award from The V 
Foundation for Cancer Research. T.G.O. is a Damon Runyon-Rachleff Innovation Awardee supported in part by the 
Damon Runyon Cancer Research Foundation (DRR-26-13). </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. 
Page 8 </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>



<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 1. Lenti-Sox2;Lkb1 fl/fl Tumors Express Biomarkers of Human SCC </p>

<p>(A) Left panels: two representative microCT images with tumor outlined in dashed blue 
lines and heart outlined in solid red lines in axial view. Middle panels: three-dimensional 
microCT reconstructions (3D recon) with lung tumors in blue. Right panels: gross 
morphology of dissected lungs with tumors indicated by blue arrows. Mouse IDs (JC156 
and JC163) correspond to tumors in Table 1. 
(B) Lenti-Sox2;Lkb1 fl/fl tumors and human SCC stained with H&amp;E. Top scale bars represent 
100 μM; bottom scale bars represent, 50 μM. 
(C) Representative Kras G12D/+ mouse lung adenocarcinomas, Lenti-Sox2;Lkb1 fl/fl tumors, or 
human lung SCCs stained with K5, K14, p63, or TTF1. Scale bar represents 50 μM. </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. 
Page 11 </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>(D) Average IHC score based on 0-5 scoring system where 5 indicates &gt;90% positive; 4 
indicates &gt;75%; 3 indicates &gt;50%; 2 indicates &gt;25%; 1 indicates &gt;10%; and 0 indicates 
negative. Human SCCs (n = 12), tumors from Table 1, and Kras G12D/+ adenocarcinomas 
were compared for K5, p63, and TTF1 IHC. Number of tumors analyzed is indicated in the 
color key. Error bars represent mean ± SEM. Student's unpaired t test, *p = 0.02 for Sox2/ 
Lkb1 versus Kras, and p = 0.04 for Sox2/Lkb1 versus human SCC. 
See also Figure S1. </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 2. Lenti-Sox2;Lkb1 fl/fl Tumors Express Sox2 and Exhibit Activation of the mTOR 
Pathway Similar to Human SCCs </p>

<p>(A) Representative IHC of Sox2, p4EBP1, and pAMPK in Kras G12D/+ mouse lung 
adenocarcinomas, Lenti-Sox2;Lkb1 fl/fl tumors, human lung SCCs, and Kras G12D/+ Lkb1 fl/fl 
squamous tumors. Brown/red staining is positive. Scale bar represents 50 μm. 
(B) Average IHC scores for Sox2 and p4EBP1 from individual tumors indicated in Table 1 
based on 0-5 scoring system where 5 indicates &gt;90% positive; 4 indicates &gt;75%; 3 indicates 
&gt;50%; 2 indicates &gt;25%; 1 indicates &gt;10%; and 0 indicates negative. Number of tumors 
analyzed is indicated in color key at right. Error bars represent mean ± SEM. Student's 
unpaired t test, ****p &lt; 0.001. 
(C) PCR validation of Lkb1 recombination in tumor samples from mice indicated in Table 1. 
Wild-type (WT), floxed (flox), and recombined (del) Lkb1 alleles indicated. Actin serves as 
input control. Mixed 1:1 Lkb1 WT and floxed DNA, Lkb1 +/+ , and Lkb1 fl/fl normal lung 
DNA serve as controls. 
(D) Left panels: representative images of Sox2− and p4EBP1-positive and -negative IHC. 
Right panels: contingency table of human SCCs (n = 12) stained with antibodies to SOX2 
and p4EBP1. 
See also Figure S2. </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. 
Page 13 </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Figure 3. Murine SCCs Exhibit Expression of Potential Therapeutic Targets </p>

<p>(A) Representative IHC of Kras G12D/+ mouse lung adenocarcinomas, mouse Lenti-
Sox2;Lkb1 fl/fl tumors, human lung SCCs, and Kras G12D/+ Lkb1 fl/fl squamous tumors stained 
with indicated antibodies. Brown/red staining is positive. Scale bar represents 50 μm. 
(B) Average IHC score of FGFR2, pErk, pAkt, and pStat3 stains in individual tumors from 
Table 1, human SCCs, and Kras G12D/+ Lkb1 fl/fl squamous tumors. Number of tumors 
analyzed is indicated in color key at right. IHC scoring system is based on scoring system 
where 5 indicates &gt;75% positive; 4 indicates &gt;50%; 3 indicates &gt;25%; 2 indicates &gt;10%; 1 
indicates &gt;2.5%; and 0 indicates negative. Error bars represent mean ± SEM. For Student's 
unpaired t test, *** indicates p &lt; 0.0002 and *p &lt; 0.01. 
(C) Immunoblot of cytoplasmic (c) and nuclear (n) protein extracts for SOX2, pStat3, and 
NF-κB p65 from human lung cancer cell lines under control (−) or 48 hr SOX2 induction 
(+) in stable Tet-On cells. Nemo and Parp serve as loading controls for cytoplasmic and 
nuclear fractions, respectively. 
See also Figure S3. </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. 
Page 14 </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Table 1 </p>

<p>Lenti-Sox2;Lkb1 fl/fl 
Mice Develop Squamous Lung Tumors </p>

<p>Genotype 
Virus delivered </p>

<p>No. of mice 
with 
tumors/ 
total mice </p>

<p>p value 
for 
tumor 
incidence </p>

<p>Sox2 
versus 
GFP </p>

<p>Mouse </p>

<p>ID 
with 
tumor 
Pathological review based on H&amp;E (subtype </p>

<p>after biomarker staining) </p>

<p>Biomarker staining </p>

<p>No. of 
squamous 
tumors/ 
total 
tumors 
(based on 
biomarker 
staining) </p>

<p>Lkb1 
recombination </p>

<p>by PCR </p>

<p>Latency </p>

<p>Lkb1 fl/fl </p>

<p>GFP </p>

<p>0/14 (0%) </p>

<p>0/0 (0%) </p>

<p>6-10 months </p>

<p>Sox2 </p>

<p>7/17 (41%) </p>

<p>p = 0.009 </p>

<p>8/9 (89%) </p>

<p>6-10 months </p>

<p>JC156 </p>

<p>squamous </p>

<p>K5+, K14+, p63+, 
Sox2+, TTF1 low </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>6 months, 5 
days </p>

<p>JC156b squamous </p>

<p>n/a </p>

<p>n/a </p>

<p>6 months, 5 
days </p>

<p>JC163 </p>

<p>squamous </p>

<p>K5+, K14+, p63+, 
Sox2+, TTF1+ </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>7 months, 15 
days </p>

<p>JC163b squamous </p>

<p>K5+, K14+, p63+, 
Sox2+, TTF1+ </p>

<p>n/a </p>

<p>7 months, 15 
days </p>

<p>JC191 </p>

<p>squamous </p>

<p>K5+, p63+, Sox2+, 
TTF1− </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>7 months, 9 
days </p>

<p>JC205 
well-differentiated adenocarcinoma (squamous) </p>

<p>K5+, p63+, Sox2+ </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>7 months, 5 
days </p>

<p>JC215 
well-differentiated adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>K5−, p63−, Sox2+ </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>9 months, 8 
days </p>

<p>JC217b squamous </p>

<p>K5−, p63+, Sox2+, 
TTF1− </p>

<p>n/a </p>

<p>9 months, 12 
days </p>

<p>JC229 </p>

<p>squamous </p>

<p>K5+, p63+, Sox2+, 
TTF1− </p>

<p>n/a </p>

<p>9 months, 18 
days </p>

<p>p53 fl/fl </p>

<p>GFP </p>

<p>0/10 (0%) </p>

<p>0/0 (0%) </p>

<p>5.5-7.5 months </p>

<p>Sox2 
1/8 (11.1%) p = 0.44 </p>

<p>0/1 (0%) </p>

<p>5.5-7.5 months </p>

<p>JC147 
well-differentiated adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>K5−, p63−, Sox2−, 
TTF1+ </p>

<p>5 months, 19 
days </p>

<p>Rb fl/fl 
p53 fl/fl </p>

<p>GFP </p>

<p>2/28 (7%) </p>

<p>0/2(0%) </p>

<p>6-12 months </p>

<p>JC118 
well-differentiated adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>n/a </p>

<p>6 months, 6 
days </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Author Manuscript </p>

<p>Mukhopadhyay et al. </p>

<p>
Genotype 
Virus delivered </p>

<p>No. of mice 
with 
tumors/ 
total mice </p>

<p>p value 
for 
tumor 
incidence </p>

<p>Sox2 
versus 
GFP </p>

<p>Mouse </p>

<p>ID 
with 
tumor 
Pathological review based on H&amp;E (subtype </p>

<p>after biomarker staining) </p>

<p>Biomarker staining </p>

<p>No. of 
squamous 
tumors/ 
total 
tumors 
(based on 
biomarker 
staining) </p>

<p>Lkb1 
recombination </p>

<p>by PCR </p>

<p>Latency </p>

<p>JC204 
poorly differentiated NSCLC (Adeno) </p>

<p>K5−, p63−, Sox2−, 
TTF1+ </p>

<p>8 months, 12 
days </p>

<p>Sox2 </p>

<p>2/14 (14%) </p>

<p>p = 0.59 </p>

<p>0/3 (0%) </p>

<p>6-12 months </p>

<p>JC189 
well-differentiated adenocarcinoma </p>

<p>K5−, p63−, Sox2−, 
TTF1+ </p>

<p>10 months, 27 
days </p>

<p>JC216 
poorly differentiated NSCLC (Adeno) </p>

<p>K5−, p63−, Sox2−, 
TTF1+ </p>

<p>12 months </p>

<p>JC216b poorly differentiated NSCLC (Adeno) </p>

<p>n/a </p>

<p>12 months </p>

<p>Detailed histopathology, biomarker staining, Lkb1 recombination results, and latency of tumors are identified in mice receiving GFP or Sox2 lentiviruses in indicated conditional genetic backgrounds. n/a 
indicates insufficient tissue available for analysis. See also Figure S1. </p>

<p>Cell Rep. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2015 April 27. </p>

</text></tei>