<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4707405" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>Healthcare provider knowledge on ASD children ... Murshid </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (12) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>A utism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a lifelong </p>

<p>neurodevelopmental disability that affects children 
at a young age. Children with ASD usually show multiple, 
complicated deficiencies in their social, emotional, and 
communicative skills. 1 Because of the multiple signs 
and symptoms of ASD, a multidisciplinary team is 
required to diagnose and offer comprehensive medical 
care for affected children. These teams usually include 
different specialists and subspecialists, such as general 
practitioners for primary diagnoses, and lead to referrals 
to relevant professionals or pediatricians who are able 
to confirm, or refute the ASD diagnosis. Clinical 
psychologists, psychiatrists, and psychotherapists (who 
are able to confirm the diagnosis of autism and introduce 
a customized individual behavior management plan), 
dieticians (who can provide advice and information 
concerning nutrition and diet), special educators (who 
can assess children's educational needs), social workers 
(who can assess the care needs of children with ASD and 
their families), speech and language therapists (who can 
assess speech, language, and communication abilities), 
audiologists (who can evaluate possible hearing 
impairments), opticians (who can assess any visual 
difficulties that the children might have), in addition 
to specialists in oral health (OH [such as, pediatric 
dentist, who can perform early check-ups and introduce 
both primary and comprehensive preventive and 
therapeutic oral care]). 2 From a medical point of view, 
the recognition and diagnosis of ASD in its early stages 
is significant. Early intervention and treatment can 
control, and in many cases improve, the symptoms. 3,4 
From a dental point of view, early examinations for 
intervention and prevention among children in general 
(and those with special needs specifically) are strongly 
recommended by major dental academies. 2,5 However, 
because children with ASD have multiple medical 
issues, their dental issues might not receive equal 
consideration from healthcare providers (HCPs) trying 
to provide the best comprehensive care. In addition, 
several well-documented national and international 
studies have observed a lack of dental knowledge among 
primary HCPs, 6-15 and educators 16-20 who work with 
children. Most published studies have reported data 
collected from HCPs who work with healthy children, 
or those with disabilities, such as cerebral palsy, or Down 
syndrome, however, no studies have been conducted to </p>

<p>assess the dental knowledge of educators and HCPs that 
interact with children diagnosed with ASD. Therefore, 
because of the unique characteristics of children with 
ASD, this study evaluated the dental knowledge of, and 
attitudes toward oral healthcare among different HCPs 
and educators interacting with children with ASD in 
Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (KSA). </p>

<p>Methods. This study is a cross-sectional survey 
undertaken at special-needs centers within Riyadh 
between September and November 2014. The study 
took place in the College of Dentistry, King Saud 
University, Riyadh, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. This 
period was selected as it is the beginning of the school 
year, thus, the researchers would have ample time to 
review the results of this study, to plan and conduct 
a special oral health educational workshop with a 
volunteer group of students, for HCPs involved in the 
participating centers. Ethical approval was obtained 
from the Research Center of the College of Dentistry, 
King Saud University, Riyadh, KSA. Seven special-
needs centers from different socio-economic areas of 
the city were approached through their administrative 
offices to distribute and collect questionnaires to, and 
from all their staff members. A total of 305 copies were 
distributed to 7 centers based on the number of special-
needs care providers working at each center who agreed 
to participate in the study, and only the completely 
answered copies were included. The questionnaires were 
formulated in simple Arabic language and designed 
specifically for the study. Each copy of the questionnaire 
had a cover letter, which served as an invitation and 
explained the purpose of the study, as well as provided 
a short biography of the investigator. The survey was 
voluntary, and did not collect identifiable participant 
information. The target group included educators 
and special-needs care providers who worked with 
children diagnosed with ASD. A self-administered, 
15-item questionnaire included demographic questions 
concerning gender, age, educational level, employment 
status (permanent or volunteer job), and type of 
specialty. Additional questions asked for specific details 
regarding the special-needs care providers' knowledge 
and experiences with advice regarding: toothbrush 
use; pediatric dentist referrals; oral, dental, or both 
types of examinations provided; appropriate age for 
a first dental visit; the frequency of tooth brushing; 
tools used during brushing; suitable people to help 
the child during brushing; their own sources of dental 
knowledge; and causes of dental concerns. The validity 
of the questionnaires was based on previous similar 
questionnaires designed and used by the author in </p>

<p>Disclosure. Author has no conflict of interests, and the 
work was not supported or funded by any drug company. </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (12) </p>

<p>Healthcare provider knowledge on ASD children ... Murshid </p>

<p>previous studies. 21 For data reliability it was found that 
the data was reliable (alpha was 0.715) according to 
Cronbach's alpha standard cut-off for reliability is 0.7. 
A pilot study of a group of educators and special-needs 
care providers (n=25) working at one of the special-
needs centers was conducted to evaluate the content 
validity of the questionnaires. The questionnaires 
were revised, and corrected according to participants' 
comments before the final draft was distributed. 
Data analysis. Data were entered and analyzed 
using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for Social Sciences</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 21</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA</rs>). Descriptive 
statistics such as, frequency tables and percentages 
were conducted to explore the general features of 
the data. The outcome variable (dependent) was the 
dental knowledge and attitude of HCPs who advised 
preventive dental measures. Preventive dental measures 
consisted of counseling parents regarding oral hygiene, 
recommending that parents seek dental checkups, visual 
examinations of the oral cavity and teeth to explore for 
causes of dental decay, age of first dental visit, number of 
tooth brushing per day, tolls of toothbrushing, persons 
responsible regarding the child's oral hygiene, sources 
of dental knowledge, and the main cause of dental 
decay. The independent (determinant) variables were 
age, gender, education level, type of job, and specialties. 
Chi-square test and logistic regression were used to 
determine significance of variation, or the association 
at a 95% confidence level (p&lt;0.05). A cross tabulation 
analysis was conducted to analyze different categorical 
variables (responses of the participants). </p>

<p>Results. Of the 305 questionnaires distributed 
to 7 centers, 217 were collected with a response 
rate of 71.1% (37 [17.1%] males and 180 [82.9%] 
females). More than half (66.8%) of the participants 
were between the age of 20 and 35 years (mean=31.5 
years and median=30.5 years). In addition, 69.1% of 
the participants had bachelor's degrees 40.6% were 
special educators, 12.9% were speech therapists, and 
13.8% were play or training therapists. Participants' 
work in the centers was their primary job for more 
than 3 quarters of the sample (76.5%). The remaining 
23.5% of participants were either trainees (14.7%) or 
volunteers (2.3%) as shown in Table 1. In response to the 
questions regarding dental knowledge, the data revealed 
that approximately 49.8% of the participants did not 
offer any advice regarding toothbrushing to parents of 
children with ASD. Almost 3 quarters (73.3%) of the 
participants never recommended that any of the parents 
seek dental checkups, and 75.6% never performed 
dental examinations of children with ASD under their </p>

<p>Table 1 -Distribution of participants working at selected special-needs 
centers according to socio-demographic data. </p>

<p>Socio-demographics 
n (%) 
Gender 
Males 
37 (17.1) 
Females 
180 (82.9) 
Age, years 
&lt;20-25 
78 (35.9) 
26-35 
67 (30.9) 
36-45 
59 (27.2) 
46-55 
12 (5.5) 
56+ 
1 (0.5) 
Education 
High school degree or diploma 
43 (19.8) 
Bachelor's degree 
150 (69.1) 
Master's degree 
18 (8.3) 
Doctor of Philosophy or others 
6 (2.8) 
Specialty 
Speech therapist 
28 (12.9) 
Training/play therapist 
30 (13.8) 
Special-needs educators 
88 (40.6) 
Teachers in merging classes 
11 (5.1) 
Sociologist 
10 (4.6) 
Nutritionist 
3 (1.4) 
Psychologists 
10 (4.6) 
Trainee or students 
32 (14.7) 
Others (such as, volunteers) 
5 (2.3) 
Type of job 
Temporary job 
51 (23.5) 
Primary job 
166 (76.5) 
Total 
217 (100) </p>

<p>care. Approximately, 43.9% of participants believed 
that children should have their first dental visit between 
the ages of one and 3 years old, 35.9% thought that 
children should visit dentist between the ages of 3 and 
6 years old, and only 10.1% thought that they should 
seek dental care after 6 years of age. Fortunately, only 
11% of participants thought that children should visit 
a dental clinic only when experiencing pain. Almost 
all participants agreed that children should practice 
good oral hygiene either once (18.9%), or twice per 
day (60.4%), and 16.6% even supported the notion of 
brushing one's teeth 3 times per day, or more. In general, 
the participants choose toothbrushes and toothpaste as 
the major tools to be used while performing good oral 
hygiene practices. Only a few (3.2%) participants chose 
traditional Siwak sticks as a tool for brushing one's teeth 
(Table 2). Approximately, equal numbers of responses 
were provided with regard to the person in charge of 
helping children with ASD with their oral hygiene. One </p>



<p>Healthcare provider knowledge on ASD children ... Murshid </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (12) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>Table 2 -The distribution of participants working at special-needs centers based on their responses to the dental knowledge questions (n=217). </p>

<p>Questions 
n (%) 
Chi-squared 
P-value 
1. Have you ever advised the parents of a child with ASD to brush their child's 
teeth? 
Yes 
No 
109 (50.2) 
108 (49.8) </p>

<p>0.687 
0.407 </p>

<p>2. Have you ever referred a child with ASD to a dental clinic? 
Yes 
No 
58 (26.7) 
159 (73.3) </p>

<p>4.846 
0.028 </p>

<p>3. Have you ever examined the teeth of a child with ASD? 
Yes 
No 
53 (24.4) 
164 (75.6) </p>

<p>0.511 
0.474 </p>

<p>4. At what age do you believe that children with ASD should have their first 
dental visit? 
Between 1 and 3 years 
Between 3 and 6 years 
6 years and up 
Only in the event of pain </p>

<p>93 (42.9) 
78 (35.9) 
22 (10.1) 
24 (11.1) </p>

<p>1.974 
0.578 </p>

<p>5. In your opinion, how many times should children with ASD practice good 
OH per day? 
Never 
Irregular cleaning 
Once per day 
Twice per day 
3 or more per day </p>

<p>1 (0.5) 
8 (3.7) 
41 (18.9) 
131 (60.4) 
36 (16.6) </p>

<p>5.229 
0.156 </p>

<p>6. In your opinion, what tools should be used to clean the teeth of children with 
ASD? 
Toothbrush and toothpaste 
Siwak 
Mouth rinse 
A combination of tools 
Other </p>

<p>187 (86.2) 
7 (3.2) 
7 (3.2) 
11 (5.0) 
5 (2.3) </p>

<p>3.367 
0.338 </p>

<p>7. In your opinion, if the child is unable to practice OH, who should help him 
or her? 
The mother or father 
Any of the siblings 
Any family member 
A nanny or house helper 
A teacher or trainer 
Do not know 
Anyone can help </p>

<p>76 (35.0) 
2 (0.9) 
74 (34.1) 
5 (2.3) 
1 (0.5) 
5 (2.3) 
54 (24.9) </p>

<p>5.387 
0.495 </p>

<p>8. Have you ever received instructions for OH practice? 
Yes 
No 
62 (28.6) 
155 (71.4) </p>

<p>4.616 
0.032 </p>

<p>9. If so, from which source? 
Dentist 
Media (such as, TV, radio, newspapers or magazines) 
Professional brochures and leaflets 
Friends or relatives 
Other sources </p>

<p>24 (11.1) 
6 (2.7) 
14 (6.5) 
4 (1.8) 
14 (6.5) </p>

<p>0.547 
0.969 </p>

<p>10. In your opinion, what is the cause of dental cavities? 
Bacteria 
Hereditary factors 
Irregular OH practices 
Do not know 
Combination of factors </p>

<p>31 (14.3) 
9 (4.1) 
112 (51.6) 
22 (10.1) 
43 (19.8) </p>

<p>2.658 
0.617 </p>

<p>ASD -autism spectrum disorder, OH -oral hygiene. p&lt;0.05 was considered significant </p>

<p>third (35%) of participants believed that parents should 
be responsible, 34.1% believed that any family member 
should be able to help, and 24.9% thought that anyone 
who interacts with them should be able to help. Only 
a few participants mentioned teachers, therapist, and </p>

<p>nannies. Most participants (71.4%) did not receive any 
dental instruction or information from professionals, 
only 11.1% received information from a dentist, and 
6.5% received information from official brochures and 
leaflets. The remaining participants received information </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (12) </p>

<p>Healthcare provider knowledge on ASD children ... Murshid </p>

<p>from different sources. Regarding more specific dental 
knowledge, only 14.3% of participants believed 
bacteria to be the cause of dental cavities, whereas 4.1% 
thought that cavities are hereditary. Most participants 
(51.6%) thought that dental cavities are caused by 
irregular oral hygiene practices. Furthermore, 19.8% 
thought that cavities have multiple causes. Finally, 
10% did not know their causes (Table 2). Females 
comprised most of the participants, and more women 
(55%) than men (27%) advised parents regarding 
oral hygiene (Pearson's chi-square=9.606). However, 
with regard to children's referrals, men referred more 
children to dental care (43.2%) than females (23.3%, 
Pearson's chi-square=6.212), and an equal percentage 
(24.4%) were divided between men and women with 
regard to performing dental examinations (Pearson's 
chi-square=0.000, Table 3). 
Approximately half (42.4%) of the men and 
women agreed that the appropriate time for the first 
dental visit is at one to 3 years of age (Pearson's chi-
square=4.688, p=0.196). With regard to frequency 
of tooth brushing, women were more in favor of 
brushing twice (63.9%), or 3 times (18.9%) per day 
compared with men. In addition, 45.9% of the men 
chose brushing once per day, whereas 13.9% of the 
women did so (Pearson's chi-square=20.593, p=0.000). 
An approximate 81% agreement was found between 
the men and women regarding the use of toothbrush 
and toothpaste as the main tools used during oral 
hygiene (Pearson's chi-square=4.322, p=0.229). Similar 
agreements were observed with regard to the person 
responsible for addressing oral hygiene among the 
children. The participants chose family members for this 
responsibility (Pearson's chi-square 3.470, p=0.748). </p>

<p>More men (32.4%) received dental information than 
women (27.8%; Pearson's chi-square=326, p=0.568). 
In addition, more men (66.7%) received dental 
information from dentists than did women (38.0%; 
Pearson's chi-square=4.399, p=0.355). More men 
(16.2%) than women (13.9%) thought that bacteria 
caused dental decay, and more women (52.2%) than 
men (48.6%) thought that irregular brushing was the 
primary cause (Pearson's chi-square=0.936, p=0.919). 
Age groups and dental knowledge. The younger 
participant age group (20 and 25 years old) was 
repeatedly less likely to attend to children's OH 
compared with the other age groups. Approximately 
64.1% of this group did not advise parents regarding oral 
hygiene (Pearson's chi-square=16.334), 79.5% had not 
referred any children for a dental examination (Pearson's 
chi-square=10.459), and 83.3% had not examined any 
children's teeth (Pearson's chi-square= 4.782, Table 4). 
Approximately equal percentages of participants (29%) 
from all age groups agreed that children should have 
their first dental visit between the ages of one and three 
years old (chi-square=11.766, p=0.465), and up to 45% 
of 20-35-year-old participants thought that children 
should practice good oral hygiene at least twice a day 
(chi-square=17.765, p=0.123). Most of the age groups 
chose a toothbrush and toothpaste as the major tools of 
oral hygiene (chi-square=9.812, p=0.632). In addition, 
all of the participants agreed that mothers or family 
members should be responsible for helping with the 
oral hygiene of children with ASD (chi-square=57.941, 
p=0.000). Participants between 36 and 45 years old 
received dental information more often (37.3%) than the 
other groups (chi-square=9.033, p=0.060), and dentists 
were the source of their knowledge (chi-square=18.964, </p>

<p>Table 3 -The distribution of participants working at special-needs centers based on gender and their responses to the dental 
knowledge questions (n=217). </p>

<p>Questions 
Gender 
Total 
Chi-square 
P-value 
Male 
Female 
Have you ever advised the parents of a child 
with ASD to brush their child's teeth? 
9.606 
0.002 </p>

<p>Yes 
10 (27.0) 
99 (55.0) 
109 (50.2) 
No 
27 (73.0) 
81 (45.0) 
108 (49.8) </p>

<p>Have you ever referred a child with ASD to a 
dental clinic? 
6.212 
0.013 </p>

<p>Yes 
16 (43.2) 
42 (23.3) 
58 (26.7) 
No 
21 (56.8) 
138 (76.7) 
159 (73.3) 
Have you ever examined the teeth of a child 
with ASD? 
0.00 
0.988 </p>

<p>Yes 
9 (24.3) 
44 (24.4) 
53 (24.4) 
No 
28 (75.7) 
136 (75.6) 
164 (75.6) </p>

<p>ASD -autism spectrum disorders. p&lt;0.05 was considered significant </p>



<p>Healthcare provider knowledge on ASD children ... Murshid </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (12) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>p=0.089). However, approximately equal percentages of 
all the age groups chose irregular brushing as the major 
cause of dental decay (chi-square=23.618, p=0.098). 
Educational level, specialties, and dental knowledge. 
Approximately 70% of the participants hold a 
bachelor's degree. With regard to participant specialties, 
special educators comprised more than 40% of the 
participants, and 56% of them advised parents about 
oral hygiene (Pearson's chi-square=29.233). However, 
a large percentage (45.9%) of participants did not 
recommend that any children to seek dental care, and 
40.2% never attempted to examine the children's teeth </p>

<p>(Pearson's chi-square=12.602). Approximately half 
(45.6%) of the special educators also considered 3 and 
6 years old as the appropriate age range for the first 
dental visit (Pearson's chi-square=29.962). Moreover, 
62.2% of participants believed that teeth should be 
cleaned 3 or more times per day using a toothbrush 
and toothpaste (Pearson's chi-square=49.152). None 
of the special educators believed that they should play 
a role in the oral hygiene of the children, however, 
48.4% had received dental information. Approximately 
60% of their dental information began with dentists, 
whereas 50.1% came from the media (Pearson's chi-</p>

<p>Table 4 -The distribution of participants working in special-needs centers based on age and their responses to the dental knowledge questions (n=217). </p>

<p>Questions and participant 
response </p>

<p>Age group, years 
Total </p>

<p>Chi-square 
2-sided 
p-value 
20-25 
26-35 
36-45 
46-55 
56+ </p>

<p>n (%) 
Have you ever advised the parents 
of a child with ASD to brush 
their child's teeth? </p>

<p>16.334 
0.003 </p>

<p>Yes 
28 (35.9) 
33 (49.3) 
39 (66.1) 
9 (75.0) 
0 (0.0) 
109 (50.2) 
No 
50 (64.1) 
34 (50.7) 
20 (33.9) 
3 (25.0) 
1 (100.0) 
108 (49.8) 
Have you ever referred a child 
with ASD to a dental clinic? 
10.459 
0.033 </p>

<p>Yes 
16 (20.5) 
14 (20.9) 
25 (42.4) 
3 (25.0) 
0 (0.0) 
58 (26.7) 
No 
62 (79.5) 
53 (79.1) 
34 (57.6) 
9 (75.0) 
1 (100.0) 
159 (73.3) 
Have you ever examined the teeth 
of a child with ASD? 
4.782 
0.310 </p>

<p>Yes 
13 (16.7) 
18 (26.9) 
18 (30.5) 
4 (33.3) 
0 (0.0) 
53 (24.4) 
No 
65 (83.3) 
49 (73.1) 
41 (69.5) 
8 (66.7) 
1 (100.0) 
164 (75.6) 
Total 
78 (100.0) 
67 (100.0) 
59 (100.0) 
12 (100.0) 
1 (100.0) 
217 (100.0) 
p&lt;0.05 was considered significant. ASD -autism spectrum disorders </p>

<p>Table 5 -Multinomial logistic regression analysis, gender, age, educational level, type of job, and specialty as explanatory variables versus dental knowledge 
and attitude (outcome variables). </p>

<p>Dependent, outcome variables </p>

<p>Independent, determinant variables 
Overall 
p-value 
Gender 
Age 
Educational 
level 
Type of 
job 
Specialty </p>

<p>1. Have you ever advised the parents of a child with 
ASD to brush their child's teeth 
0.025 
0.34 
0.62 
0.21 
0.23 
0.011 </p>

<p>2. Have you ever referred a child with ASD to a dental clinic? 
0.000 
0.001 
0.027 
0.22 
0.44 
0.027 
3. Have you ever examined the teeth of a child with ASD? 
0.001 
0.11 
0.04 
0.12 
0.030 
0.030 
4. At what age do you believe that children with ASD should have 
their first dental visit? 
0.64 
0.058 
0.75 
0.21 
0.89 
0.66 </p>

<p>5. In your opinion, how many times should children with ASD 
practice good OH per day? 
0.17 
0.000 
0.71 
0.41 
0.53 
0.89 </p>

<p>6. In your opinion, what tools should be used to clean the teeth of 
children with ASD 
1.00 
0.56 
0.97 
0.92 
0.63 </p>

<p>7. In your opinion, if the child is unable to practice OH, who 
should help him or her? 
1.00 
0.32 
0.00 
0.95 
0.98 
0.89 </p>

<p>8. Have you ever received instructions for OH practice? 
0.060 
0.68 
0.11 
0.48 
0.60 
0.19 
9. If so, from which source? 
0.009 
0.65 
0.002 
0.06 
0.12 
0.041 
10. In your opinion, what is the cause of dental cavities 
NA 
0.26 
0.000 
NA 
0.95 
NA 
p&lt;0.05 was considered significant. ASD -autism spectrum disorders, OH -oral health </p>



<p>www.smj.org.sa Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (12) </p>

<p>Healthcare provider knowledge on ASD children ... Murshid </p>

<p>square=21.146). Most educators (43.8%) believed 
that irregular brushing was the primary cause of dental 
decay (Pearson's chi-square=47.939). Approximately 
77% of participants were working at the centers as 
their primary job, and 51.8% of these workers advised 
parents regarding oral hygiene. However approximately 
70% of these employees had not referred any children 
to dental clinics or examined their teeth. Approximately 
40% of them thought that children should seek their 
first dental visit between one and 3 years old, and 64% 
thought that children should brush twice per day using 
a toothbrush and toothpaste (87.8%). In addition, 58% 
thought that family members should be responsible for 
their oral hygiene. Almost 68% of participants had 
not received any dental information; only 43.4% had 
received information from dentists, and 52% thought 
that irregular brushing causes dental decay. 
Multinomial logistic regression analysis. Table 5 
showed the multinomial logistic regression analysis 
using gender, age, educational level, specialty, and 
dealing with ASD children as determinant (independent 
variables) versus outcome variables (dependent) of 
dental knowledge and attitude; the results show wide 
variations in the significance of the different variables 
at p&lt;0.05. </p>

<p>Discussion. One of the most significant 
issues that major health academies agree on is the 
recommendation for early dental checkups among 
children. In the case of children with special needs, 
the importance of early dental checkups becomes even 
more significant. 5 Children diagnosed with ASD, due 
to the nature of their syndrome are generally exposed 
to a myriad of HCPs before they have the chance to 
visit a dental clinic. Primary medical care providers have 
opportunities to play significant roles in referring, or 
advising children and their families to seek dental care. 
Taking into consideration previously published reports 
of the paucity of dental knowledge among HCPs, 6-11,13,15 
and educators 16,18,19 working with children, the urgency 
to assess the dental knowledge of professional personal 
working with children with ASD greatly increased. 
Data from this study reveals that participants 
primarily focused on the medical and educational aspects 
of care and abandoned dental aspects. Disappointingly, 
nearly half of the participants neglected to emphasize 
the importance of oral hygiene, and fail to advise 
parents with regard to brushing for their children. 
Furthermore, they did not make made clear efforts to 
refer the children to their dental colleagues. Although 
they cannot be expected to have more than basic 
dental background knowledge, one appropriate course </p>

<p>of action would be to refer them to someone who 
actually does. Advising parents to seek early dental 
checkup is associated with increase in dental visits 
and improvements in dental prevention among young 
children. 22-26 Obviously, the OH of these children was 
not one of the participants' concerns, even though the 
children were under their care every day. Ignorance 
of the necessity of oral examination and reluctance to 
perform it is predictable, given the results of previous 
studies, 8,27 however, the large number of respondents 
who ignored these issues was unexpected. In addition, 
most of the HCPs believed that the parents or other 
family members should be responsible for the children's 
oral hygiene practices, no one believed that teachers 
should be involved with tooth brushing in the event 
that the children were unable to do so, even though the 
children spend half of their day in special-needs centers 
under their care. Participants' responses with regard 
to the cause of dental cavities revealed the paucity of 
their dental knowledge because only 14% thought that 
bacteria was the main cause of dental decay. Similar 
findings were reported among parents of children 
with ASD, wherein approximately 11% believed that 
bacteria were the main cause of dental decay. 28 This 
result comes as an unfortunate surprise as HCPs should 
be better informed and more knowledgeable than the 
parents. Lewis et al 27 and dela Cruz et al 8 reported 
similar findings regarding lack of dental care knowledge 
among HCPs. However, the general dental knowledge 
of these participants was generally considered as 
satisfactory, especially with regard to the frequencies of 
tooth brushing, the tools used for oral hygiene care, and 
the appropriate age for dental visits. The findings of this 
study agreed with previously published data reporting 
the dental knowledge of special-needs care providers 
and educators working with children. 6,17,20,27,28 
Due to the complexity of ASD and the disabilities 
that these children often display, multiple serious 
medical and behavioral issues can overshadow OH 
issues. Dental personnel must be held accountable 
for not disseminating appropriate and specific dental 
knowledge tailored to children with ASD among their 
peers. This result is clear given the large number of 
participants who did not receive dental instructions 
from dental personal; this finding was similar to a figure 
reported by previous studies. 27-29 Dental knowledge may 
be disseminated by publishing pamphlets and brochures, 
and making them accessible to their colleagues in centers 
for special-needs children. Ideally, these brochures would 
consist of sets of detailed instructions regarding on how 
to address the large variety of neuro-atypical patients 
who they might encounter, especially as no universal </p>



<p>Healthcare provider knowledge on ASD children ... Murshid </p>

<p>Saudi Med J 2015; Vol. 36 (12) www.smj.org.sa </p>

<p>and unified set of instructions exist specifically geared 
toward their OH. These pamphlets and brochures 
might be useful for special-needs care providers, as well 
as the parents and guardians of the children. Increasing 
awareness of the importance of proper oral care among 
educators and different special-needs care providers 
by emphasizing dental issues across different medical 
educational facilities, and planning consecutive dental 
educational seminars might increase their confidence 
with regard to performing dental examinations, or at 
least encourage them to refer the children to receive 
appropriate dental care. The OH of children with ASD 
deserves more attention from all healthcare sectors in 
KSA and worldwide. More dental studies should focus 
on the different aspects of spreading dental awareness, 
prevention and treatment for this group of children. 
Although the number of studies regarding the various 
medical issues of children with ASD grows every day, 
studies with a focus on their OH and hygiene are scarce, 
especially in KSA. Only a limited number of studies 
have been published with regard to the dental condition 
of children with ASD. 30-34 
The support of HCPs referring children with ASD 
to the dentist at an early age will assist their families in 
understanding proper oral hygiene and initiate different 
dental preventive measures. Because of the complex 
behaviors of children with ASD, an early introduction 
to the dentist will prepare them to accept good oral 
hygiene because these children are better behaved in 
familiar places. Although multiple dental studies have 
reported that children with ASD have a low prevalence 
of cavities, 31,32,35,36 the same studies have highlighted 
other OH problems that cannot be overlooked. Many 
children with ASD have serious gingival and periodontal 
problems, 32,37 habits, such as gum picking, self-tooth 
extraction, or self-mutilation, or bruxism that can affect 
their OH, if not their general health. 32,36,38 
This study identified several issues that need 
consideration in future exploration and development 
of educators and special-needs care providers' roles in 
advising the children with ASD under their care. This 
study has some limitations that could affect the results, 
such as the data collection method, limited time of 
data collection, centers included, and characteristics 
of the participants. Future studies to include centers of 
children with special needs from different areas of the 
kingdom is highly recommended. 
In conclusion, given the limitations of this study, 
it can be concluded that a clear lack of knowledge 
regarding essential dental attitude exists, and its 
practical application among the participating group 
of HCPs working with children with ASD in Riyadh, </p>

<p>KSA is weak. We recommend that: medical education 
in OH must be restructured to include components 
that address self-efficacy in providing risk assessment, 
early detection, and referral services; more efforts from 
dental personnel sectors should be made to increase 
special-needs care providers' dental knowledge of the 
importance of early checkups and referrals to pediatric 
dentists to promote OH and prevent dental diseases, 
especially for children with special needs through 
continuing education workshops and seminars; and 
HCPs might benefit from the American Academy of 
Pediatric Dentistry online publication (www.aapd.org), 
which provides important information to physicians, 
educators and parents. </p>

<p>Acknowledgment. The author gratefully acknowledges the 
center's administration and staff members for their time and effort and 
cooperation, which made this study possible. In addition, gratitude is 
extended to Mr. Ibrahim Al-Hassan for his help with the data entry 
and analysis. </p>







</text></tei>