<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4835540" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Hydrogen, the simplest element in the universe, has a surprisingly complex phase diagram. 
Because of applications to planetary science, inertial confinement fusion and fundamental 
physics, its high-pressure properties have been the subject of intense study over the past two 
decades. While sophisticated static experiments have probed hydrogen's structure at ever 
higher pressures, studies examining the higher-temperature regime using dynamic 
compression have mostly been limited to optical measurement techniques. Here we present 
spectrally resolved x-ray scattering measurements from plasmons in dynamically compressed 
deuterium. Combined with Compton scattering, and velocity interferometry to determine 
shock pressure and mass density, this allows us to extract ionization state as a function of 
compression. The onset of ionization occurs close in pressure to where density functional 
theory-molecular dynamics (DFT-MD) simulations show molecular dissociation, suggesting 
hydrogen transitions from a molecular and insulating fluid to a conducting state without 
passing through an intermediate atomic phase. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he insulator-metal transition in hydrogen has been a 
central problem in physics since Wigner and Huntington's 
1935 prediction of a transformation of insulating molecular 
hydrogen to a monatomic conducting state at high pressure 1 . In 
recent decades, owing to fundamental questions about the structure 
of gas giants 2-6 , hydrogen's high-pressure properties have been the 
subject of intense study. Diamond anvil cell experiments have 
explored the low-temperature, high-pressure structure of hydrogen. 
It has been shown to remain in an insulating, molecular state at 
pressures in excess of 300 GPa (ref. 7) and recent work has focused 
on its phases near room temperature 8-13 . Sophisticated ab initio 
simulation techniques have advanced in tandem, resulting in a 
wide computational exploration of the hydrogen phase diagram, 
see McMahon and coauthors 14 . 
High-pressures produced by dynamic compression techniques 
generally result in higher-temperature conditions. Experiments 
using reverberating shock waves to produce conductive liquid 
hydrogen at 140 GPa and temperatures near 3,000 K (refs 15,16), 
reached densities very close to those predicted by Wigner and 
Huntington 17 . Recent experiments using the Sandia Z machine 
reached 300 GPa and 1,800 K, finding evidence for a liquid-liquid 
insulator-metal transition from optical reflectivity measure-
ments 18 . In single-shock experiments, the temperatures reached 
are still higher, and the transition to metallic behaviour is driven 
by the combined pressure and temperature reached in the shock 
front. These experiments produce thermodynamic states lying on 
the primary shock Hugoniot. Optical reflectivity measurements 
have been used to observe a transition to metallic behaviour in 
laser-driven samples near 50 GPa and 8,000 K (ref. 19). X-ray 
scattering makes it possible to directly observe electron properties 
in such an experimental configuration, but until now it has not 
progressed beyond proof-of-principle in shock-compressed 
cryogenic samples 20 . In this work, we use a single-shock laser 
compression scheme, employing x-ray scattering to directly 
measure the ionization of laser-shocked deuterium as a 
function of compression. 
Dynamic experiments along the principal Hugoniot result 
in target conditions far from the region where a first-order </p>

<p>liquid-liquid phase transition from molecular to conducting 
fluids has been predicted 21,22 . We illustrate this in the hydrogen 
phase diagram shown in Fig. 1, which shows that most parts of 
the interiors of brown dwarfs (Gliese-229b, shown in brown) and 
giant planets (Jupiter, shown in black) are also at off-Hugoniot 
states. However, the P -T range of our experiments covers one of 
the most interesting parts of the Jovian interior. The flattening of 
the isentrope at B25 GPa is due to the dissociation of the 
hydrogen molecules. As shown by French et al. 23 , this is 
accompanied by a drastic increase in the dc electrical 
conductivity which represents a continuous nonmetal-to-metal 
transition. This result is validated with the x-ray scattering 
measurements presented in this study, where we find that the 
average ionization becomes significant just at this point on the 
Hugoniot curve, and coincident with dissociation. This is of great 
importance for planetary physics when validating equation of 
state (EOS) data that are used for interior 2,23 and dynamo 
models 24 . 
Inelastic x-ray scattering has a long history as a powerful probe 
of material properties in static samples. Recently, x-ray scattering 
has been employed in high-energy density physics experiments 25 
using laser-produced x-ray sources to measure density and 
temperature in targets dynamically shocked to warm, dense 
conditions 26-29 . Experiments at the Omega laser have 
demonstrated the viability of backscattering techniques for 
density measurements in cryogenic deuterium 20 . Here we 
combine forward and backward x-ray scattering observations 
with a simultaneous measurement of shock velocity using the 
velocity interferometry system for any reflector (VISAR) 
technique to infer pressure and mass density from the velocity 
of the shock and EOS tables. With a delocalized electron density 
measured using x-ray scattering, we can then directly determine 
the ionization state of shocked deuterium as a function of 
compression. We compare the onset of ionization with the 
molecular dissociation fraction calculated from density functional 
theory-molecular dynamics (DFT-MD) simulations and find 
that both quantities increase sharply between compressions of 
2.5rr/r 0 r3.3. </p>

<p>5,000 </p>

<p>4,000 </p>

<p>3,000 </p>

<p>2,000 </p>

<p>50 % dissociated, DFT 
Tamblyn &amp; Bonev 2010 55 </p>

<p>Extrapolation of 
Tamblyn's data 55 </p>

<p>Coexistence line, DFT 
Lorenzen et al. 2010 21 </p>

<p>Melting line, Caillabet et al. 2011 53 
Jupiter adiabat 
Brown Dwarf Gliese-229b 
Principal Hugoniot curve, DFT </p>

<p>Coexistence line, DFT 
Morales et al. 2010 22 
Coexistence line, QMC 
Morales et al. 2010 22 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>Nonmetallic 
fluid </p>

<p>Metallic 
fluid </p>

<p>Solid </p>

<p>Onset of significant 
ionization in our 
experiment </p>

<p>0 
50 
100 
150 
200 
250 
300 </p>

<p>T (K) </p>

<p>P (GPa) </p>

<p>CP </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Phase diagram of hydrogen. Displayed are the melting line 53 (orange), the isentropes of Jupiter 2,23 (black) and the Brown Dwarf Gliese-229b 
(ref. 54) (brown), the principal Hugoniot curve (magenta) and results for the first-order liquid-liquid (plasma phase) transition (green 21 and blue 22 ) 
together with predictions at which P-T points the system is dissociated by 50% (ref. 55) (red). </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:11189 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>Results 
Experiment design and layout. X-ray scattering is sensitive 
to both the electron and ion structure in the target. The 
scattering cross section depends on the total dynamic structure 
factor of the material that, in the case of dense plasma conditions, 
is often expressed using a chemical picture approach 
due to Chihara 30,31 as S ee k; o 
ð 
Þ¼f k 
ð Þ þ q k 
ð Þ 
j 
j 2 S ii k; o 
ð 
Þ 
þ Z f S 0 
ee k; o 
ð 
ÞþZ b 
R 
do 0 ~ S ce k; o À o 0 
ð 
Þ S S k; o 0 
ð 
Þ. Here k is the 
wave-vector probed, f(k) is the ionic form factor, q(k) represents 
the electron screening cloud around the ion and Z f (Z b ) is the 
number of free (bound) electrons per atom. S ii and S ee 
0 represent 
the dynamic structure contributions of ions and free electrons; 
transitions of bound electrons into the continuum, S ce , are 
modulated by the motion of the ions, represented by S S . 
In the non-relativistic limit, the probe energy and 
experimental geometry define the k-vectors probed according to 
k¼ k 
j j¼4p E 0 
hc sin y=2 
ð Þ. Our experiments probe density fluctua-
tions at scale lengths of k ¼ 7.78 Â 10 9 m À 1 in the forward 
direction and 1.88 Â 10 10 m À 1 in the backward direction. The </p>

<p>scattering process can be defined with the parameter a ¼ 1/kl S , 
where l S represents the screening length in the plasma. For the 
strongly degenerate systems studied in this work, the screening 
length can be approximated with the Thomas-Fermi length, </p>

<p>and a¼ 1 </p>

<p>kl S </p>

<p>¼ 1 </p>

<p>kl TF </p>

<p>¼ 1 </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi </p>

<p>4m e e 2 
' 2 
3n e 
p </p>

<p>À Á 1=3 
q 
where n e is the free-electron 
density. Thus, for our conditions, the forward scattering vector 
extends beyond the screening length and provides collective 
scattering even at small ionization fractions 32 , while the backward 
scattering vector is sufficiently long to probe at a scale length 
smaller than the screening length of the plasma, observing the 
electron momentum distribution in the Compton limit 33 . 
A series of cryogenic experiments was performed at the Janus 
Laser Facility at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, a 
schematic of which is shown in Fig. 2. A drive laser was focused 
onto a cryogenic target, launching a shock wave into liquid 
deuterium at an initial density r 0 ¼ 0.17 ± 0.004 g cm À 3 . A 
second laser, incident on a Si 3 N 4 foil fixed to the target at an 
intensity of 1 Â 10 14 W cm À 2 and wavelength of 527 nm, created 
an intense x-ray source by pumping the 2 keV Ly-a line in Si </p>

<p>To HOPG </p>

<p>To HOPG </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Time (ns) </p>

<p>Position (μm) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
500 </p>

<p>Energy </p>

<p>Drive 
Probe </p>

<p>Probe laser </p>

<p>Pusher </p>

<p>Drive laser </p>

<p>Drive laser </p>

<p>X-ray collection 
window </p>

<p>X-ray window </p>

<p>CH+Aluminium </p>

<p>VISAR </p>

<p>Liquid D 2 </p>

<p>10-20 ns </p>

<p>2-6 ns 
2 ns </p>

<p>Si 3 N 4 foil </p>

<p>SiO 2 rear window </p>

<p>D 2 fill </p>

<p>Ni shield </p>

<p>Time </p>

<p>Ni shield </p>

<p>Cu target body </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Experimental set-up and timing. (a) The copper target is held at 19 K, liquefying the deuterium that is filled into the central cavity. A drive laser 
is incident on a 2-mm-diameter Al pusher, launching a shock wave along the axis. A probe laser irradiates a Si 3 N 4 foil, pumping the 2,005 eV Si Ly-a 
transition. X-rays scattered in the forward and backward directions are spectrally dispersed with highly oriented pyrolytic graphite (HOPG) crystals whose 
direct view of the laser-plasma is prevented by Ni shields. (b) Cross section of the target reservoir across the thickness of the target. The target is sealed 
with aluminium on the front surface and a transparent quartz rear window to allow the VISAR beam to probe shock evolution. (c) Schematic of laser beam 
timing showing the shock drive beam (red) of 2-6 ns preceding a 2-ns probe pulse. The probe is delayed by 10-20 ns, depending on drive intensity, to allow 
the shock front to advance into the x-ray spectrometer view. Shorter delay times yielded higher shock pressures. (d) <rs type="software">HYDRA</rs> simulations of mass density 
evolving as a function of space and time, with a lineout at the x-ray probe time of 20 ns. The compressed D 2 peak (r Shock ¼ 0.54 g cm À 3 ) has traversed into 
the spectrometer field of view at t ¼ 20 ns when we make the x-ray measurement. The high-density peak lagging the D 2 shock front is due to the aluminium 
pusher, but is shielded by the x-ray window. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:11189 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>(ref. 34; Supplementary Fig. 1 and Supplementary Methods). 
These photons were collimated through a 400-mm-diameter 
aperture in the target, timed to probe the shock as it reached the 
x-ray collection ports. The x-rays were scattered from the shock 
front and collected through 400 mm ports at 45° and 135° from 
the incident photons. The probe pulse was delayed 10-20 ns after 
the rise of the drive beam, allowing the shock to traverse a 
distance of 350 mm to reach the volume accessed by the x-ray 
diagnostic port. The fields of view of the spectrometers were 
shielded with Ni-coated cones (40° opening angle) from ambient 
x-ray emission and stray light from both laser beams. The 
radiation was collected and spectrally dispersed with highly 
ordered pyrolytic graphite crystal spectrometers 35 curved at a 
107-mm radius. 
The drive laser beam used a phase plate to produce a round 
600-mm-diameter spot on target. The forward scattering 
measurements were made on deuterium shock-driven by a 
frequency-doubled 2-ns-long laser pulse producing a wavelength 
of 527 nm at the target. The backscattering measurements were 
made operating the same laser at the 1,054 nm fundamental. 
These shots used 4 ns drive pulses at moderate compression 
and 6 ns at higher compression, all at nominal intensities of 
4 Â 10 13 W cm À 2 . 
The drive laser was incident on a CH-coated aluminium layer 
ranging from 12 to 40 mm in thickness, depending on intended 
shock pressure. The CH layer was ablated in the laser-target 
interaction, driving a shock wave into the Al pusher that released 
into the D 2 layer. The aluminium shielded the bulk D 2 from hot 
electrons and x-rays produced in the laser-solid interaction that 
could preheat the target before the shock arrived. </p>

<p>Shock velocity and inferred compression. Since deuterium 
becomes optically reflective under shock compression, the shock 
velocity can be directly measured using the VISAR technique 36,37 . 
For this purpose, we propagated a 532-nm VISAR probe beam 
anti-parallel to the drive beam along the axis of the shock through 
the rear window. The reflected signal from the D 2 shock front was 
collected and sent to two interferometers, coupled to optical 
streak cameras. These provided two 20-ns-long channels showing 
the evolution of shock velocity on each shot. Using two 
interferometers of differing sensitivities allowed the absolute 
velocity to be determined in spite of the discontinuity in phase 
caused by the shock. 
To determine the mass density-and hence compression 
r/r 0 -of the target using measured shock velocity, one of two 
approaches is necessary. Impedance matching techniques can be 
used to determine particle velocity in addition to shock velocity, 
closing the Rankine-Hugoniot relations 38-40 and directly 
constraining state variables in the target. Alternatively, existing 
theoretical models or measured EOS values can be used to 
calculate compression from the shock velocity measured with 
VISAR; that is the approach used in this study. While one of 
several modern EOS models could be effectively used, we have 
chosen the quotidian EOS (ref. 41) because of its computational 
efficiency and the fact that it represents a middle ground between 
popular EOS models in the pressure regime of interest. Because 
we rely on an EOS that is not perfectly known, this approach 
requires careful accounting for that uncertainty in our inferred 
compression. Hicks et al. 42 gave a comparison of both calculated 
and measured EOS values and their associated experimental 
uncertainties. For our experimental conditions, variations in EOS 
models are relatively small; near 15 GPa, where we observe the 
onset of ionization, models vary by about 10% in compression at 
a given pressure (Supplementary Fig. 2 and Supplementary 
Methods). This uncertainty is included in the error bar of quoted 
values of mass density. </p>

<p>Figure 3 shows a VISAR streak record along with the extracted 
shock velocities for high-power laser drive conditions. Also 
shown are simulation results from <rs type="software">HYDRA</rs>, a radiation-
hydrodynamics code widely used for modelling inertial confine-
ment fusion and laser-plasma experiments 43 . <rs type="software">HYDRA</rs> accurately 
reproduces the measured late-time shock velocities when 
scattering is performed. Stray light from the drive beam is 
visible for 2 ns early in the streak. Shock breakout from the Al 
pusher into D 2 occurs near the end of the drive beam where a 
discontinuous fringe shift is visible. As the shock decays, a drop in 
signal amplitude is visible in the raw data, since reflectivity falls 
as shock pressure and ionization decrease. The peak velocity 
immediately following shock breakout from the pusher is 
22 km s À 1 with pressures near 50 GPa, which decays to 
14 ± 1 km s À 1 and 15 þ 3.5/ À 4.5 GPa at 21 ns, the centre of 
the 2-ns-long x-ray probe. </p>

<p>X-ray scattering spectra. Figure 4 shows collective scattering data 
measured with the forward spectrometer for two shock condi-
tions. The upper spectrum is taken from the same shot as Fig. 3, 
with a compression of r/r 0 ¼ 3.2 þ 0.2/ À 0.3 at the time of x-ray 
probing, while the lower spectrum used a lower laser intensity 
drive to reach r/r 0 ¼ 2.8 þ 0.3/ À 0.4. At this lower drive condi-
tion, no inelastic feature is visible above the noise and spectral 
resolution of the detector, placing an upper bound on ionization 
state of Zr0.04. 
At the higher drive condition, a downshifted plasmon feature 
is visible centred at 1,998 eV below the probe energy of 
E 0 ¼ 2,005 eV. The plasmon resonance in this low-temperature 
regime experiences very little damping and is therefore quite 
narrow. The presented fit curves include broadening due 
to collisional effects calculated in the local-field-corrected 
Born-Mermin approximation, which goes beyond the random 
phase approximation to the dynamical structure factor by 
including electron-electron interactions and electron-ion colli-
sions in the Born approximation 27,44 . The spectrum is convolved </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Time 
VISAR </p>

<p>2 ns drive 
20 ns </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
8 
10 </p>

<p>HYDRA </p>

<p>X-ray probe 
window </p>

<p>VISAR 1 </p>

<p>VISAR 2 </p>

<p>12 
Time (ns) </p>

<p>Velocity (km s -1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>14 
16 
18 
20 
22 
24 </p>

<p>Figure 3 | VISAR shock velocity compares well with hydrodynamic 
simulations up to 20 ns when the x-ray probe begins. We linearly 
extrapolate the mean velocity to obtain the average conditions during the 
x-ray probe. Uncertainty in shock velocity is estimated to be ± 1 km s À 1 ; 
uncertainty in timing is ± 0.5 ns. Inset: raw VISAR streak for one of two 
streak cameras. The bright pulse early in time comes from the drive beam. 
Breakout of the shock from the aluminium pusher into the deuterium occurs 
near the end of the drive beam, and the decaying shock velocity in D 2 is 
extracted from the fringes shifting in time. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:11189 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>with the instrument function introduced by the highly ordered 
pyrolytic graphite crystal and detector. The broad low-energy tail 
may be explained by bound-free transitions, whose fit includes 
density-and temperature-dependent continuum lowering. A best 
fit to the data indicates a delocalized electron density of 
n e ¼ 2.5 ± 0.4 Â 10 22 cm À 3 due to the free-electron density-
sensitive plasmon shift at 7 eV. Combined with the mass 
density inferred from the VISAR trace, this corresponds to an 
average ionization state of Z ¼ 0.15 ± 0.04. The measured electron 
density corresponds to a Fermi temperature of T F ¼ 3.1 eV. For 
typical temperatures of a fraction of an electron volt, the electrons 
are therefore strongly degenerate, with y¼kT=e F $ 0:1, and a 
scattering parameter of a ¼ 1.5. </p>

<p>Figure 5 shows the 135° backscattered spectrum from another 
shot using a 4-ns laser drive, and a probe beam delay of 15 ns. 
<rs type="software">HYDRA</rs> calculations using an intensity profile matched to the 
velocity measurements shown above predict pressures of 16 GPa 
and compressions of 3.2 þ 0.2/ À 0.4, producing target conditions 
very close to those achieved in the plasmon scattering case. The 
ratio of elastic to inelastic scattering is strongly dependent on the 
ionization of the target; with increasing average ionization, 
the inelastic scattering contribution from free electrons grows 
relative to the remaining elastic signal. Fits are shown in 
Fig. 5a for ionizations Z ¼ 0.1-0.5 and a best fit is achieved for 
n e ¼ 2.4 Â 10 22 cm À 3 . This corresponds Z ¼ 0.15±0.08, in good 
agreement with the plasmon data. At these conditions, the 
scattering parameter is a ¼ 0.63. 
For non-collective scattering, the theoretical models used to 
describe the bound-free contribution can have a significant effect 
on the inelastic spectrum. In the present case where weakly bound 
electrons in the compressed deuterium occupy states near the 
continuum, continuum depression plays a particularly important 
role. To minimize any ambiguity introduced by this model 
dependence, we have compared our results, which use a Stewart-
Pyatt (SP) model 45 for ionization potential depression, with a set 
of calculations using the Eckert- (EK) 46 model. The resulting 
curves are shown in Fig. 5b, with the SP model in red and the EK 
model in blue. The contribution to the spectrum from bound-free 
scattering are shown separately as dashed curves, illustrating 
that the primary difference comes through the shift of the 
EK feature towards E 0 . We attribute this to a much higher 
value of continuum depression calculated by the EK model, 
DE EK ¼ 10.2 eV compared with DE SP ¼ 2.1 eV for SP. We note 
that in both cases a best fit is found for an ionization state 
of Z ¼ 0.15 (Supplementary Figs 3 and 4 and Supplementary 
Methods). We conclude that, for very similar experimental drive 
conditions, plasmon and Compton scattering provide nearly 
identical ionization states; this is significant because the sensitivity 
of plasmon spectra and Compton scattering spectra to bound-free 
models and structure factors is very different. This finding 
indicates that contributions from bound-free scattering and 
interband transitions are accounted for by our data analysis and 
that interband transitions play a minor role in the interpretation 
of the data. </p>

<p>Discussion 
Figure 6 summarizes measurements of ionization across several 
shock-drive and probe delay conditions producing compressions </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>Energy (eV) 
Energy (eV) </p>

<p>2,020 
2,020 
2,010 
2,010 
2,000 
2,000 
1,990 
1,990 
1,980 
1,980 
1,970 
1,970 
1,960 
1,960 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Measured backscattering spectrum with theoretical fits. Fits are shown for target conditions of T e ¼ 0.15 eV and r/r 0 ¼ 3.2. (a) Four ionization 
states corresponding to Z ¼ 0.1 (blue), 0.15 (red), 0.25 (green) and 0.5 (yellow) are shown, with a best fit found for n e ¼ 2.4 Â 10 22 cm À 3 and 
Z ¼ 0.15±0.08. (b) Theoretical fits for Z ¼ 0.15 using the SP (red) and EK (blue) models for ionization potential depression. Solid lines correspond to the 
total spectrum and dashed to the elastic and bound-free scattering contributions without free-free scattering. Both models result in best fit values for 
ionization of Z ¼ 0.15. </p>

<p>Intensity (a.u.) </p>

<p>Plasmon 
feature </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>ΔE pl =7 eV </p>

<p>1,980 
1,990 
2,000 
2,010 
2,020 </p>

<p>P=15 GPa </p>

<p>P=11 GPa </p>

<p>/ 0 =3.2 </p>

<p>/ 0 =2.8 </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Measured forward scattering spectra with theoretical fits. 
Pressure and compression are inferred from VISAR measurements. X-ray 
forward scattering spectrum from 3.2 Â shock-compressed D 2 showing 
elastic scatter at 2005 eV and downshifted plasmon with theoretical fits 
corresponding to T e ¼ 0.15 eV and n e ¼ 1.3 (blue), 2.5 (red) and 4.0 
(yellow) Â 10 22 cm À 3 . Below, a spectrum from 2.8 Â compressed D 2 
showing no evidence of free electrons as a visible inelastic scattering 
feature. </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:11189 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>



<p>between r/r 0 ¼ 2.8 and r/r 0 ¼ 4.05. Measured ionization states 
for both forward and backscattered configurations are shown as a 
function of compression, along with predicted ionizations from 
several models. The compression values for the backscattering 
data points and the lowest compression case, where velocity 
measurements are not possible below the onset of optical 
reflectivity, were determined using hydrodynamic calculations 
benchmarked to VISAR measurements. The error bars in 
compression for these points include a 20% uncertainty in drive 
intensity and uncertainty between EOS models at the relevant 
pressures. The data indicate a sharp onset of ionization between 3 
and 3.5 times compression. 
This onset is reproduced by average-atom simulations of a D 
ion system embedded in a plasma background 47 , but with lower 
absolute ionization values. The Thomas-Fermi model exhibits 
very little of the density dependence in the data at low 
compression. Similar results have been reported in x-ray 
scattering experiments on shock-compressed CH (ref. 48). We 
also show the deuterium dissociation curve calculated with the 
code FVT, a chemical picture model based on fluid variational 
theory 49 that predicts the onset of molecular dissociation at 
higher compressions than measured here. 
Theoretical models for dense matter can be divided into 
chemical and physical-picture models. In the chemical picture, 
ions, atoms and molecules are treated as elementary members of 
the ensemble, while in the physical picture, nuclei and electrons 
are treated as elementary particles and bound states are long-lived 
correlations between them. While ab initio physical picture 
theories represent the state-of-the-art in simulating hydrogen 
under extreme conditions, an explicit definition of ionization 
within a physical-picture model is difficult in pressure and 
temperature regimes where electron delocalization and finite 
temperatures blur the characteristics of free and bound electrons. 
To provide a comparison to our measurements we have 
calculated the dissociation of deuterium molecules along the 
Hugoniot using DFT-MD (ref. 50). DFT-MD couples a finite-
temperature treatment of electrons using density functional 
theory with a molecular dynamics treatment of ion motion. 
The dissociated fraction, shown in red in Fig. 6, is estimated by 
tracking neighbouring ions in the system as the simulation 
evolves in time (Supplementary Figs 5 and 6 and Supplementary </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Forward scatter 
Thomas fermi 
Average atom </p>

<p>FVT dissociated 
fraction </p>

<p>Backward scatter </p>

<p>DFT-MD dissociated 
fraction </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.01 
2 
2.5 
3 </p>

<p>11 GPa </p>

<p>15 GPa </p>

<p>16 GPa </p>

<p>15 GPa 
52 GPa </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>Compression </p>

<p>4 
4.5 </p>

<p>Ionization </p>

<p>Figure 6 | Average ionization of D 2 plotted as a function of compression 
along the single-shock Hugoniot. Values of ionization inferred from 
plasmon measurements are shown as red squares, measurements using 
Compton scattering are shown as blue circles, and pressures from quotidian 
EOS (QEOS) are indicated for each data point. Ionization degree calculated 
with Thomas-Fermi theory is shown as a dashed line, while average-atom 
calculations are shown between a lower bound of T e ¼ 0.1 eV and an upper 
bound of T e ¼ 0.5 eV as a shaded region. The dark red line shows the 
molecular dissociation fraction calculated from density functional molecular 
dynamics simulations along the principal Hugoniot and the dotted line 
shows a similar dissociation calculation with the chemical picture code FVT. 
Measurements indicate a sharp increase in ionization near 3 Â compression, 
consistent with the DFT-MD calculated dissociated fraction. </p>

<p>0.6 
0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 
Reflectivity </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 
0 
0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 
25 
50 
75 
100 </p>

<p>Pressure (GPa) 
Energy (eV) </p>

<p>Energy (eV) </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>(10 6 </p>

<p>S m -1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>(10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>S m </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 -1 </p>

<p>10 -2 </p>

<p>10 -3 </p>

<p>10 -4 </p>

<p>10 -5 </p>

<p>10 -6 </p>

<p>10 -7 
0 </p>

<p>Celliers et al. (2000) 19 , 808 nm 
DFT-MD (this study), 808 nm </p>

<p>DFT-MD (this study), 532 nm </p>

<p>Loubeyre et al. (2012) 51 , H 
Loubeyre et al. (2012) 51 , D </p>

<p>0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 </p>

<p>/ 0 =4.04, T=4,700K, P=26.5 GPa </p>

<p>/ 0 =3.22, T=3,600K, P=16.9 GPa </p>

<p>/ 0 =3.18, T=3,500K, P=15.9 GPa </p>

<p>/ 0 =3.12, T=3,300K, P=14.7 GPa </p>

<p>/ 0 =2.8, T=2,000K, P=9.3 GPa </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>Figure 7 | Reflectivity and conductivity calculated from DFT-MD simulations. (a) Reflectivities along the principal Hugoniot curve for 808 nm from the 
experiments of Celliers et al. (black diamonds) and DFT-MD calculations in this work (solid black line). Reflectivities for 532 nm from the experiments of 
Loubeyre et al. in hydrogen (red dots) and deuterium (red triangles) and DFT-MD calculations in this work (solid red line). (b) Dynamic electrical 
conductivity at the five experimental points for which the thermodynamic states along the principal Hugoniot curve are given in the legend. The dc limit 
(o-0) is displayed in the inset. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:11189 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>Methods). The fraction of dissociated molecules in the calcula-
tions matches the fraction of measured ions closely, suggesting 
that the processes of dissociation and ionization occur nearly 
simultaneously along the Hugoniot, see also refs 21-23. 
To facilitate further comparison between our simulations and 
experimental results, optical reflectivity and dynamic conductivity 
were calculated from the DFT-MD results. Figure 7a 
shows reflectivity calculated along the principal Hugoniot 
(Supplementary Fig. 7 and Supplementary Note 1). Comparisons 
are made at 808 nm with the results of Celliers et al. 19 and at 
532 nm with the recent measurements by Loubeyre et al. 51 . Good 
agreement is found between experiment and theory. Between 20 
and 50 GPa, DFT-MD is seen to produce somewhat higher 
reflectivities than the Loubeyre results, attributable to the fact that 
DFT-MD underestimates the bandgap systematically using 
exchange-correlation functionals like that of Perdew, Burke, and 
Ernzerhof (ref. 52), leading to early bandgap closure and an 
earlier onset of dissociation and, thereby, conduction. In Fig. 7b, 
the dynamic conductivity along the Hugoniot is plotted at a 
pressure range corresponding to our experimental conditions. 
The DC limit is plotted in the inset, showing that conductivity 
starts at very small values near 0.1 S m À 1 at 2.8 Â compression 
(black curve), rising orders of magnitude to a metallic 
conductivity of 10 5 S m À 1 near fourfold compression (yellow 
curve). This confirms the continuous transition from an 
insulating molecular fluid to a metallic degenerate electron 
liquid observed in the experiments. 
More broadly, this work demonstrates the viability of 
combining x-ray spectroscopic and optical velocity measurements 
to make detailed inferences into the electronic states of a variety 
of materials compressed to pressures relevant to planetary 
science. As fourth-generation light sources come online, we 
expect these results to lead to an unprecedented exploration of the 
high-pressure structure of hydrogen and other light elements and 
allow experimental determination of such properties as interior 
temperature profiles and core erosion in giant planets. </p>







<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors thank the Jupiter Laser Facility staff for facility support and W. Unites for 
target development and experimental support. This work performed under the auspices 
of the (US) Department of Energy (DOE) by Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory 
(LLNL) under Contract No. DE-AC52-07NA27344 and supported by Laboratory 
Directed Research and Development (LDRD) Grant 11-ER-050. P.D. was supported by 
the NNSA SSGF programme. A.B., B.H., P.S. and R.R. acknowledge support from the 
Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) within the SFB 652 and the BMBF via the FSP-
301. A.B. performed calculations within the grant mvp00008 at the North-German </p>

<p>Supercomputing Alliance (HLRN). This work was supported by DOE Office of Science, 
Fusion Energy Science under FWP 100182. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>P.D., T.D., J.R.R., A.P. and L.F. performed the experiments. P.D., J.R.R. and S.H.G. 
analysed the data. C.F., A.B., B.H., P.S. and R.R. performed simulations of ionization, 
dissociation, reflectivity and conductivity; L.D. performed hydrodynamic simulations. 
P.C., G.W.C., M.P.D., O.L.L., R.W.F., R.R. and S.H.G. provided additional support for 
experiment design, analysis and interpretation. P.D. and S.H.G. wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Davis, P. et al. X-ray scattering measurements of dissociation-
induced metallization of dynamically compressed deuterium. Nat. Commun. 7:11189 
doi: 10.1038/ncomms11189 (2016). </p>

<p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or 
other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons 
license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under 
the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license 
holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/ </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:11189 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms11189 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

</text></tei>