<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4345719" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:46+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Hyponatremia is a common and potentially serious complication of transsphenoidal surgery (TSS). 
Since September 2009, we have implemented moderate water intake restriction (&lt;2500 mL/day) after 
TSS in an attempt to prevent this complication. The aim of this study was to investigate the efficacy 
of a combination of moderate restriction of water intake plus antidiuretic hormone (arginine vasopressin 
[AVP]) replacement therapy in patients with diabetes insipidus (DI) for reducing the incidence of delayed 
hyponatremia after TSS. Patients treated from September 2005 to August 2009 were allowed to drink 
water freely after surgery (the control group), while patients treated from September 2009 to June 2012 
were restricted to less than 2500 mL water per day (the water restriction group). To reduce the occurrence 
of hypernatremia, AVP replacement therapy was provided immediately after the development of DI. We 
retrospectively analyzed the incidence of hyponatremia, DI, and hypernatremia in patients following TSS. 
Hyponatremia incidence was significantly lower in the water restriction group (P = 0.017); however, there 
were no significant differences in DI incidence and hypernatremia incidence between the 2 groups. Under 
DI control with AVP replacement therapy, the water restriction group showed no significant difference in 
the daily self-rated thirst level for the patients with and without DI. Moderate water intake restriction in 
addition to AVP replacement therapy significantly decreases the incidence of hyponatremia without patient 
discomfort (extreme thirst) and other complications. However, further studies are required to determine the 
most effective amount of water and the optimal duration of postoperative water restriction. </p>

<p>Transsphenoidal surgery (TSS) is the first-line treatment for sellar and parasellar lesions, with 
the exception of some specific anatomical and histopathological conditions. Pituitary adenoma is 
the most common lesion treated using this approach. This surgery is less invasive and seldom 
results in serious complications; however, it can be the cause of disturbance in water and electro-</p>

<p>Received: August 13, 2013; accepted: November 18, 2013 
Corresponding author: Kazuhito Takeuchi, MD 
Department of Neurosurgery, Nagoya University, Graduate School of Medicine, 
65 Tsurumai-cho, Showa-ku, Nagoya, Aichi 466-8550, Japan 
Phone number: +81-52-744-5134, Fax number: +81-52-744-2360, E-mail: mail@wajit.com </p>



<p>Kazuhito Takeuchi et al. </p>

<p>lyte metabolism. Diabetes insipidus (DI) occurs in 10% to 50% of patients after TSS 
4, 6, 11, 12, 14) , 
while delayed hyponatremia is reported to occur in 1.8% to 35% of patients around postoperative 
day 
7 9, 11, 13, 16, 19) . Hyponatremia may become symptomatic, and prolonged hyponatremia may be 
life threatening 
5, 9, 21) . It is imperative to minimize risk factors for delayed hyponatremia after 
transsphenoidal tumor resection, because recent advances in neuroendoscopic techniques are less 
traumatic to the nasal apparatus, resulting in shorter hospital stays. Hyponatremia following TSS 
may arise because of deficiency in the supply of adrenocortical hormone, syndrome of inap-
propriate secretion of antidiuretic hormone (SIADH), and/or inappropriate fluid consumption </p>

<p>8, 13, 17) </p>

<p>. 
Although the causes of delayed hyponatremia following TSS are still unclear, some authors 
attribute this to SIADH and others suggest frequent coincidence with DI </p>

<p>8, 15, 20) </p>

<p>. We promote a 
novel method for managing water and electrolyte balance after TSS. We have previously managed 
water balance after TSS with free fluid intake and aggressive fluid replacement. In the present 
study, we adopted moderate restriction of postoperative water intake and reduced fluid replacement 
while carefully monitoring DI and body weight. We also monitored subjective sensation of thirst, 
as excessive thirst may hinder treatment compliance. To this end, we created a self-rated thirst 
level scale and assessed the relationship between thirst and DI in relation to delayed hyponatremia 
after TSS. The aim of the present study was to investigate the feasibility of moderate restriction 
of water intake to reduce the occurrence of delayed hyponatremia after TSS. </p>

<p>PATIENTS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patient Population and Surgical Procedures 
In this retrospective study, we collected data from the charts of patients who had sellar and 
parasellar lesions and underwent purely endoscopic endonasal TSS from September 2005 to June 
2012. A single surgeon (TN) performed all surgeries. 
Surgeries were performed under general anesthesia, with visualization provided by a 4-mm 
diameter rigid-lens endoscope. We operated through a unilateral nostril (usually on the right 
side), using a midline paraseptal approach to access the sphenoid sinus. This approach leaves 
the contralateral nostril intact and results in reduced postoperative nasal obstruction and less 
severe postoperative thirst due to oral breathing. The ipsilateral mucosa on the nasal septum was 
dissected to the level of the anterior wall of the sphenoid sinus. The bony septum was removed 
to expose the mucosa on the contralateral side. Routine wide-open sphenoidotomy was performed 
for all patients. Sellar and suprasellar procedures began with internal debulking of the tumor, 
followed by identification of the tumor capsule. In most cases, capsulectomy with an angled 
endoscope was possible. After tumor excision, we packed the tumor cavity with abdominal fat 
to prevent postoperative cerebrospinal fluid leakage. Nasal packing was removed immediately 
after extubation. </p>

<p>Standard Protocol for Postoperative Management of Water and Electrolyte Balance 
In September 2009, we adopted a new protocol for managing water and electrolyte balance 
after TSS. The core concept of the present study is moderate restriction of water intake and 
adequate control of DI immediately after surgery. 
On the day of surgery and on postoperative day 1, the patients were intravenously admin-
istered 1000 mL sugar electrolyte maintenance transfusion solution containing 0.3% NaCl. On 
postoperative day 2, they were administered 500 mL sugar electrolyte maintenance transfusion 
solution. Postoperative patients were permitted to drink fluids 3 hours after returning to the ward. 
Patients without Cushing's disease were intravenously administered 100 mg hydrocortisone on the </p>



<p>FLUID MANAGEMENT AFTER PITUITARY SURGERY </p>

<p>day of surgery and on postoperative day 1. An additional 100 mg was administered during the 
surgery. Fifty milligrams of hydrocortisone was administered on postoperative day 2, and 20 mg 
hydrocortisone was administered orally on postoperative days 3 and 4. For patients with Cushing's 
disease, cortisol replacement therapy was initiated upon confirmation of adrenal insufficiency. 
We prepared a printed form that the patients could use to record their thirst level. We repre-
sented thirst on a scale of 0-10, with 0 indicating no thirst and 10 indicating unbearable thirst. 
The midpoint of the scale (5) represented ordinary thirst (Fig. 1). The patients were instructed 
to keep the form at their bedside and were required to circle a number on 1 scale for each day. 
As a general rule, the patients were permitted to drink no more than 2500 mL water per day 
from postoperative day 1 to postoperative day 10. Blood tests for serum levels of electrolytes 
and endocrine function were performed 2 days before surgery and on postoperative days 1, 
7, and 10. Hyponatremia was diagnosed if the serum sodium level was less than 135 mEq/L. 
Hypernatremia was diagnosed if the serum sodium level was greater than 148 mEq/L. </p>

<p>Management of DI 
Urine volume was monitored every 2 hours on the day of surgery and on postoperative day 1, 
and every 8 hours from postoperative day 2 to postoperative day 10. We only observed balanced 
intake and fluid output on the day of the surgery and on postoperative day 1, because most 
patients were administered a relatively large volume of fluid during anesthesia. DI was diagnosed 
if urine volume reached 1000 mL/4 h and urine specific gravity fell below 1.005 on or after 
postoperative day 2. From postoperative day 2, the patients received intravenous substitution </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Thirst Questionnaire. Patients were required to circle a number depicting their own thirst level on this 
questionnaire each day, from the day of surgery to postoperative day 10. </p>

<p>Day 10 </p>

<p>Day 2 </p>

<p>No 
Ordinary 
Unbearable 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>・・・ 
・・・ </p>

<p>No 
Ordinary 
Unbearable 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>Day 1 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Day 0 </p>

<p>No 
Ordinary 
Unbearable 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>No 
Ordinary 
Unbearable 
0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
10 
7 
8 
9 </p>



<p>Kazuhito Takeuchi et al. </p>

<p>therapy of vasopressin or were nasally administered deamino-8-D-arginine vasopressin (ddAVP) if 
they were diagnosed with DI. The target volume of urine output for this treatment was defined 
as less than 1000 mL/4 h and less than 2500 mL/day. If body weight increased after surgery, 
administration of antidiuretic hormone (ADH) was discontinued. </p>

<p>Study Design 
Patients in puerperium and those with a medical history of hyponatremia were excluded from 
the study. The remaining patients were categorized into the following 2 groups: control group, 
patients who were treated from September 2005 to August 2009 and were allowed to drink water 
freely after surgery; water restriction group, patients who were treated from September 2009 to 
June 2012 and were subjected to moderate water restriction. 
Demographics, tumor type and volume, incidence of hyponatremia, hypernatremia, and DI, 
operative time, intraoperative blood loss, intraoperative fluid balance, and average daily oral fluid 
intake between postoperative day 1 and postoperative day 7 or before the day of occurrence of 
hyponatremia were analyzed. 
Preoperative tumor volume was measured using a preoperative magnetic resonance imaging 
(MRI) scan and was calculated as follows: 
Volume (mm 
3 ) = Width (mm) × Height (mm) × Depth (mm) ÷ 2 </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
Statistical analyses were performed with the software package <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">19.0 J</rs> for Windows 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., IL, USA). Categorical variables were assessed with the Pearson chi-square test, 
and quantitative variables were compared with unpaired 2-tailed t tests. A P value ≤0.05 was 
considered statistically significant. Values are expressed as mean ± standard deviation. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 191 patients with sellar lesions were treated using purely endoscopic endonasal 
TSS during this period. Two patients in puerperium and 4 patients with a medical history of 
hyponatremia were excluded. The remaining 185 patients were enrolled in the study. </p>

<p>Clinical Characteristics 
Clinical characteristics (age, lesion type, and perioperative indices) for the 2 patient groups 
are summarized in Table 1. The water restriction group included 93 patients and the control 
group included 92 patients. The mean age was 48.99 ± 14.44 years in the water restriction group 
and 51.65 ± 15.91 years in the control group (P = 0.271). There were 52 women in the water 
restriction group and 44 women in the control group (P = 0.216). 
There were no statistically significant differences between these 2 groups with respect to 
clinical characteristics. </p>

<p>Water and Electrolyte Disturbances 
Hyponatremia was observed in 5 patients in the water restriction group and 15 patients in 
the control group; this was a statistically significant difference (P = 0.017, Table 2). Among 
these patients, symptomatic hyponatremia was observed in only 1 patient in the water restriction 
group, as opposed to 6 patients in the control group, showing no significant difference (P = 
0.052). There were 24 patients with DI and 3 patients with hypernatremia in the water restriction 
group and 27 patients with DI and 3 patients with hypernatremia in the control group; however, </p>



<p>FLUID MANAGEMENT AFTER PITUITARY SURGERY </p>

<p>there was no statistically significant difference (P = 0.480 and P = 0.989, respectively; Table 
2). There were 24 patients with DI in the water restriction group and 27 patients in the control 
group, with no significant difference (P = 0.480). Three patients in the water restriction group 
had hypernatremia, with maximum serum sodium levels of 150 mEq/L, 154 mEq/L, and 148 
mEq/L respectively, and 3 patients in the control group had maximum serum sodium levels of 
158 mEq/L, 148 mEq/L, and 151 mEq/L, respectively. 
Isolated hyponatremia, combined DI and hyponatremia, and isolated DI were observed in 
3, 2, and 22 patients, respectively, in the water restriction group, and 2, 13, and 14 patients, 
respectively, in the control group (Table 3). The incidence of both DI and hyponatremia in the 
same patient was significantly less in the water restriction group than in the control group (P 
= 0.003). 
Data on the average daily oral fluid intake of isolated hyponatremia patients, combined DI 
and hyponatremia patients, and isolated DI patients were available in 3 of 3, 2 of 2, and 19 
of 22 patients in the water restriction group, respectively, and 2 of 2, 6 of 13, and 11 of 14 </p>

<p>Table 1 Characteristics of patients treated with endoscopic endonasal TSS. NF, non-functioning pituitary 
adenoma; GH, growth hormone-secreting pituitary adenoma; PRL, prolactin secreting pituitary adenoma; 
ACTH, adrenocorticotropic hormone-secreting pituitary adenoma </p>

<p>Water Restriction 
Control 
P </p>

<p>n 
93 
92 </p>

<p>Sex 
0.271 </p>

<p>Female 
52 
44 </p>

<p>Male 
41 
48 </p>

<p>Age, y 
48.99±14.44 
51.65 ± 15.86 
0.216 </p>

<p>Tumor type 
0.544 </p>

<p>NF 
49 
55 </p>

<p>GH 
25 
25 </p>

<p>PRL 
9 
4 </p>

<p>ACTH 
4 
6 </p>

<p>Craniopharyngioma 
3 
1 </p>

<p>Rathke's cleft cyst 
2 
1 </p>

<p>meningioma 
1 
0 </p>

<p>Tumor volume (mm 
3 ) 
5426±6944 
5571±5427 
0.876 </p>

<p>Table 2 Incidence of hyponatremia (with or without symptoms), diabetes insipidus (DI), and hypernatremia. </p>

<p>Water Restriction 
Control 
P </p>

<p>Hyponatremia 
5 (5.4%) 
15 (16.3%) 
0.017 </p>

<p>Symptomatic 
1 (1.1%) 
6 (6.5%) 
0.052 </p>

<p>Asymptomatic 
4 (4.3%) 
9 (9.8%) 
0.145 </p>

<p>DI 
21 (25.8%) 
27 (29.3%) 
0.48 </p>

<p>Hypernatremia 
3 (3.2%) 
3 (3.3%) 
0.989 </p>



<p>Kazuhito Takeuchi et al. </p>

<p>patients in the control group, respectively. The average daily oral fluid intake was 1595.1 ± 
754.3 ml, 1817.2 ± 807.8 ml, and 2304.6 ± 640.3 ml in the water restriction group, respectively, 
and 2597.5 ± 1072.9 ml, 3034.9 ± 1378.1 ml, and 3258.2 ± 1946.1 ml in the control group, 
respectively (Table 3). Average daily oral fluid intake was greater than 2500 ml in 1 (50%) of 
2 isolated hyponatremia patients, 5 (83.3%) of 6 combined DI and hyponatremia patients, and 
6 (54.5%) of 11 isolated DI patients in the control group. There were no statistically significant 
differences between the 2 groups with respect to intraoperative data. </p>

<p>Assessment of Thirst Level 
Only 37 of the 93 patients in the water restriction group evaluated their thirst level because 
the questionnaire was formulated after the treatment protocol had been initiated. These 37 patients 
included 9 patients with DI and 28 without DI (Fig. 2). There were no statistically significant 
differences in the thirst levels of patients with and without DI from the day of surgery to 
postoperative day 10. </p>

<p>Illustrative Case in the Control Group 
A 47-year-old woman with a growth hormone-producing pituitary microadenoma detected on 
MRI underwent purely endoscopic endonasal TSS. Six hours after the surgery, she developed DI, 
and vasopressin was administered intravenously. On postoperative day 1, intravenous administra-
tion of vasopressin was switched to nasal administration of ddAVP, which was continued until 
postoperative day 4. She was allowed to drink freely and exhibited polyuria and polydipsia. 
The maximum urine output (9693 mL/day) was observed on postoperative day 4. A subsequent 
decrease in urine output led to discontinuation of ddAVP administration on postoperative day 5. 
Despite the alleviation of DI, the patient had been drinking 3000-6000 mL/day from postoperative 
day 1 to postoperative day 7. She experienced headaches and nausea on postoperative day 8, and 
blood examination revealed hyponatremia (119 mEq/L) on postoperative day 9. She was kept 
under water restriction after developing hyponatremia. Her symptoms and serum sodium level 
improved, and she was discharged from our department on postoperative day 18. </p>

<p>Table 3 Intraoperative and postoperative measurements of water and electrolyte disturbances. 
*Average daily oral fluid intake during postoperative day 1 to day 7 or the day before incidence of 
hyponatremia. </p>

<p>Water Restriction Group 
Control Group </p>

<p>Isolated 
Hyponatremia </p>

<p>Combined 
DI-Hyponatremia 
Isolated DI 
Isolated 
Hyponatremia 
DI-Hyponatremia 
Isolated DI </p>

<p>n 
3 (3.2%) 
2 (2.2%) 
22 (23.7%) 
2 (2.2%) 
13 (14.1%) 
14 (15.2%) </p>

<p>Sex </p>

<p>Female 
3 
2 
13 
2 
4 
7 </p>

<p>Male 
0 
0 
9 
0 
9 
7 </p>

<p>Age, y 
44.3 (26-70) 
32.0 (28-36) 
41.05 (24-62) 
53.5 (35-72) 
54.3 (19-75) 
48.1 (22-77) </p>

<p>Intraoperative data </p>

<p>Duration, min 
208.6±41.4 
319.0±190.9 
236.1±120.5 
122.0 ± 53.7 
163.6 ± 30.8 
208.5 ± 62.5 </p>

<p>Blood loss, mL 
30.0±43.6 
107.5±65.8 
208.7±281.1 
15.0 ± 21.2 
29.2 ± 24.7 
83.2 ± 94.1 </p>

<p>Fluid balance, mL 
966.7±255.4 
1458.0±100.41 
1453.7±930.6 
1770.0 ± 905.1 
1455.7 ± 659.2 
1701.2 ± 548.5 </p>

<p>Post-operative data </p>

<p>Oral fluid intake (ml)* 
1595.1±754.3 
1817.2±807.8 
2304.6±640.3 
2597.5±1072.9 
3034.9±1378.1 
3258.2±1946.1 </p>



<p>FLUID MANAGEMENT AFTER PITUITARY SURGERY </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Hyponatremia is a common electrolyte disturbance in the neurosurgical population. This 
complication is attributed to SIADH, cerebral salt wasting (CSW), and adrenal insufficiency </p>

<p>8, 15, </p>

<p>21) . Hyponatremia following TSS has been reported by several authors. The reported incidence 
of this complication is approximately 30%, and it occurs about 7 days after surgery 
3, 7, 11, 16) . 
Approximately 20% of patients become symptomatic </p>

<p>21) </p>

<p>. The symptoms of hyponatremia are vari-
able and include headache, nausea, vomiting, mental status disturbance, seizures, and coma 
2, 5, 21) . 
Therefore, if this complication occurs, patients may require additional treatment and longer 
hospital stay, even if there are no noticeable problems with the surgery itself. Insufficient or 
inappropriate treatment for this complication can induce other neurological disturbances, such as 
seizures, osmotic demyelination syndrome, coma, and even death </p>

<p>5, 15) </p>

<p>. 
The pathophysiology of delayed hyponatremia has been discussed extensively, and the main 
cause following TSS is believed to be the release of excessive antidiuretic hormone, presumably 
induced by surgical manipulation of the posterior pituitary gland and pituitary stalk </p>

<p>7, 18, 20) </p>

<p>. SIADH 
treatment is based on restriction of water intake. We evaluated this treatment by implementing 
moderate water restriction to prevent hyponatremia after TSS. To date, the method for preventing 
this complication has not been established. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study 
to test a possible method for preventing hyponatremia following TSS. </p>

<p>Occurrence of Hyponatremia 
We evaluated the usefulness of limiting oral fluid intake to 2500 mL/day from immediately </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Changes in the Thirst Level after Transsphenoidal Surgery. </p>



<p>Kazuhito Takeuchi et al. </p>

<p>after TSS to postoperative day 10. Previously identified risk factors for hyponatremia after TSS 
are older age, female sex, microadenomas, adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH)-producing tu-
mors, and the presence of transient DI </p>

<p>7, 10, 13, 16, 17, 21) </p>

<p>. Although there were no significant differences 
in patient demographics or tumor-type distribution between the water restriction group and the 
control group, moderate water restriction significantly decreased the occurrence of this potentially 
life-threatening complication. Although there was no significant difference in the occurrence of 
symptomatic hyponatremia between the 2 groups, the occurrence of symptomatic hyponatremia 
tended to be quite low, because only 1 patient on water restriction developed symptomatic 
hyponatremia (1.1%) compared with 6 control patients (6.5%). The incidence of combined DI 
and hyponatremia was significantly lower in the water restriction group than in the control 
group. Olson et al. reported that two-thirds of normonatremic patients had dysfunctional arginine 
vasopressin (AVP) secretion under the water load test at 7 days after TSS, and that 9 of 23 
patients actually developed hyponatremia after the water load test </p>

<p>13) </p>

<p>. Hence, even normonatremic 
patients can develop hyponatremia after this surgery </p>

<p>13) </p>

<p>. Thus, many patients may be susceptible to 
hyponatremia following TSS if exposed to excessive volitional fluid consumption. In this study, 
the average daily oral fluid intake was greater than 2500 mL in 83% of the combined DI and 
hyponatremia patients in the control group. On the other hand, patients restricted to 2500 mL/ 
day, especially those with DI, demonstrated a significantly reduced occurrence of hyponatremia. 
As revealed by the illustrative case discussed in the Results section, controlling water and 
osmotic balance is difficult when patients drink water freely. Patients occasionally drink water 
excessively after their urine output decreases, which can cause delayed hyponatremia after TSS 
in patients with DI. The reported incidence of combined DI and hyponatremia in this study is 
within the range of 4.5%-20% 
1, 3, 7, 11, 13, 16, 21) . We speculate that water restriction for patients with 
DI under antidiuretic hormone replacement therapy stabilizes net changes in body fluid content 
and facilitates the control of fluid and electrolyte balance. This moderate water restriction regimen 
has the potential to reduce the incidence of hyponatremia after surgery. </p>

<p>Endoscopic TSS for Sellar Lesions 
Sigounas et al. reported that the incidence of DI can be reduced by treating patients with 
endoscopic surgery instead of microscopic surgery 
18) . Given that the main cause of both 
hyponatremia and DI is abnormal ADH secretion, endoscopic surgery may decrease the rate of 
postoperative hyponatremia. In this study, all patients underwent purely endoscopic endonasal 
TSS. The incidence of hyponatremia was 5.4% in the water restriction group and 16.3% in 
the control group. Recent large studies on delayed hyponatremia reported that hyponatremia 
occurs in 36.7% of patients treated with microscopic surgery 
11) . In comparison, the incidence 
of hyponatremia observed in the present study was relatively low, even in the control group. 
Transsphenoidal endoscopic surgery may reduce the incidence of postoperative hyponatremia. </p>

<p>Complications of Moderate Water Restriction after TSS 
Dehydration is the most serious potential complication of water restriction, especially in pa-
tients with DI. There was no significant difference between the incidence of hypernatremia in the 
experimental and control groups. We implemented AVP replacement therapy to control the urine 
output immediately after approaching DI criteria to avoid dehydration. However, 3 patients in 
the experimental group developed DI. To reduce the incidence of hypernatremia among patients, 
water restriction therapy should be aborted until DI is brought under control. In our opinion, DI 
control is important for reducing not only the incidence of hypernatremia, but also the thirst level, 
which in turn reduces oral fluid intake. Some researchers have reported that ADH replacement 
therapy during the first 2 postoperative weeks can actually increase the risk for hyponatremia, and </p>



<p>FLUID MANAGEMENT AFTER PITUITARY SURGERY </p>

<p>thus, close monitoring of patient body weight and urine output is recommended, especially for 
patients undergoing ADH replacement therapy </p>

<p>7, 11, 12) </p>

<p>. ADH replacement therapy can be safe and 
can even decrease the incidence of hyponatremia if implemented together with water restriction 
therapy and can be withdrawn when the patient's body weight increases or when the patient's 
urine parameters no longer meet the criteria for DI. </p>

<p>Alleviation of Thirst 
Our department has implemented various methods to reduce patient thirst. Nasal obstruction 
after TSS should be avoided, as this tends to increase patient thirst due to oral breathing. As 
a general rule, a hemilateral nasal approach via the right nostril was chosen to keep the left 
nostril intact. Nasal packing was not employed after surgery if cerebrospinal fluid leakage was 
not predicted in the intraoperative period. This provided patients a natural nasal airway via their 
intact left nostril. If nasal packing was necessary to prevent postoperative cerebrospinal fluid 
leakage, a breathable space was preserved in the nostril. 
The patients appeared to tolerate moderate water restriction if they frequently drank small 
amounts of water, rather than infrequent large amounts. There was no statistically significant 
difference in postoperative thirst level between water-restricted patients with DI and those 
without DI. Unfortunately, thirst level data were not available for all patients, but these findings 
suggest that thirst was not intolerable under moderate water restriction if the patients' DI was 
sufficiently controlled. </p>

<p>Limitations 
This study revealed that the incidence of hyponatremia in patients treated with water restriction 
after pituitary surgery was significantly lower than that in patients who drank water freely. While 
body weight, sex ratio, and tumor type distribution did not differ between groups, these factors 
were not considered when deciding on the maximum allowable volume; thus, all patients in the 
water restriction group were limited to 2500 mL/day immediately after surgery. Additional studies 
are also required to determine the optimal start and stop points for this regimen. This was a 
retrospective study, and we did not perform systematic daily endocrinological tests or water load 
tests. Therefore, uptake and excretion of electrolytes and daily changes in endocrine functions 
were not evaluated. Hence, a multicenter, prospective study including these tests is needed. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to test a potential method for preventing hyponatremia 
following TSS. Although there might be other causes of hyponatremia other than postoperative 
water excess, for example, adrenal insufficiency, moderate water restriction after pituitary surgery 
is a potentially effective and safe method to reduce hyponatremia. Indeed, hyponatremia after 
TSS is a largely preventable complication. Patients should not drink water freely after TSS, even 
if they are normonatremic and develop DI. The optimal amount and duration of water restriction 
are still unclear and require larger-scale multicenter trials. </p>

<p>Funding: None </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: None </p>



<p>Kazuhito Takeuchi et al. </p>



</text></tei>