<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4049731" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) generated from somatic cells of patients can provide immense opportunities 
to model human diseases, which may lead to develop novel therapeutics. Huntington's disease (HD) is a devastating 
neurodegenerative genetic disease, with no available therapeutic options at the moment. We recently reported the char-
acteristics of a HD patient-derived iPSC carrying 72 CAG repeats (HD72-iPSC). In this study, we investigated the 
in vivo roles of HD72-iPSC in the YAC128 transgenic mice, a commonly used HD mouse model carrying 128 CAG 
repeats. To do this, we transplanted HD72-iPSC-derived neural precursors into the striatum of YAC128 mice bilaterally 
and observed a significant behavioral improvement in the grafted mice. Interestingly, the transplanted HD72-iPSC-de-
rived neural precursors formed GABAeric neurons efficiently, but no EM48-positive protein aggregates were detected 
at 12 weeks after transplantation. Taken together, these results indicate no HD pathology was developed from the 
grafted cells, or no transmission of HD pathology from the host to the graft occurred at 12 weeks post-transplantation. </p>

<p>Induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) generated by re-
programming of fully differentiated somatic cells from pa-
tients into self-renewing pluripotent stem cells has com-</p>

<p>pletely transformed our ability to study disease in human 
cells (1, 2). Using iPSC technology, it is possible to create 
both genetically inherited and sporadic diseases in vitro 
(3). Moreover, since iPSCs can be derived directly from pa-
tients with a given disease, they carry all of the genetic 
components associated with the disease, which make cer-
tain cell types more susceptible to a disease state, thereby 
serving as the most useful genetic model of the disease (4). 
Huntington's disease (HD) is a devastating neuro-
degenerative genetic disease, caused by abnormal ex-
pansion of CAG repeats in the huntingtin (HTT) gene (5). 
Clinical features of HD include progressive motor dys-
function, cognitive decline, and psychiatric disturbance, 
probably caused by both neuronal dysfunction and neuro-
nal cell death (6). Pathological hallmark of HD is the for-
mation of aggregated huntingtin inclusion in the cyto-
plasm and nucleus, characterized by the expression of 
EM48 (7, 8). Despite numerous efforts, there are no avail-</p>



<p>able therapeutic options for HD at the moment (9). 
We recently reported the characteristics of a HD pa-
tient-derived iPSC carrying 72 CAG repeats (HD72-iPSC) 
(10, 11). In this study, we investigated the in vivo roles 
of HD72-iPSC in the YAC128 transgenic mice, carrying 
the entire 170-kb genomic locus of human HTT gene plus 
25 kb of the 5' flanking sequence and about 120 kb of 3' 
flanking sequence, which is commonly used as a pre-
clinical model in HD (12). To do this, we transplanted 
HD72-iPSC-derived neural precursors into the striatum of 
YAC128 mice bilaterally and observed a significant behav-
ioral improvement in the grafted mice. Interestingly, the 
transplanted HD72-iPSC-derived neural precursors formed 
GABAeric neurons efficiently, but no EM48-positive pro-
tein aggregates were detected at 12 weeks after transpla-
ntation. Taken together, these results indicate no HD 
pathology was developed from the grafted cells, or no 
transmission of HD pathology from the host to the graft 
occurred at 12 weeks post-transplantation, which will pro-
vide useful insights on the in vivo function and patho-
genic effects of HD patient-derived iPSCs. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>Culture and neuronal differentiation of HD72-iPSC 
We cultured and maintained HD72-iPSC according to 
the method described previously (10). Neuronal differ-
entiation was induced by co-culturing HD72-iPSC with 
PA6 stromal cells (obtained from RIKEN Cell Bank, 
Ibaraki, Japan) (13). Using the 5-stage protocol, we ini-
tially induced neural rosette-like structures, detached 
them mechanically and formed neurospheres in suspen-
sion culture. To make neural precursor cells, we dis-
sociated neurospheres we dissociated neurospheres follow-
ing treatment with Accutase 
TM (Chemicon, Temecula, CA, </p>

<p>USA) and plated onto poly L-ornithine (PLO; 15 μg/ml, 
Sigma, Sigma, St.Louis, MO, USA)/fibronectin (FN; 1 μg/ml, 
Sigma)-coated 60 mm 
2 tissue culture dishes. Neural pre-</p>

<p>cursor cells were maintained in GMEM supplemented 
with 1% penicillin, 1% streptomycin, 1% nonessential 
amino acids, 0.1% β-mercaptoethanol, N2 supplements 
and 20 ng/ml bFGF (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </p>

<p>YAC128 transgenic mice and cell transplantation 
We performed animal experiments in accordance with 
the CHA University IACUC (Institutional Animal Care 
and Use Committee; IACUC090012). YAC128 mice 
(FVB-Tg(YAC128)53Hay/J) were originally purchased 
from the Jackson Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME, USA), and 
12 month-old mice were used in transplantation 
experiments. We stereotaxically injected a total of 15 mice </p>

<p>with 1μl of HD72 iPSC-derived neural precursor cells 
(100,000 cells/μl) into the striatum of both hemispheres 
using the following coordinates: AP +0.5 mm, ML ±1.75 
mm and DV −2.5 mm from the Bregma. In the sham 
group (n=15), 1μl of suspension medium (GMEM) were 
injected into both hemispheres in parallel. Uninjected 
YAC128 wild-type littermates were included as a control 
group (n=14). Both cell-transplanted and medium-in-
jected animals were received cyclosporine A intra-
peritoneally (5 mg/kg, Sigma) 24 h before transplantation 
and daily up to 12 weeks. </p>

<p>Behavioral test 
Rotarod test was performed, in which mice were placed 
on the rod with an accelerating rotating speed from 4 to 
40 rpm over a period of 3 minutes with a 15 minutes rest 
between trials (14). Mice were trained on three consec-
utive days for three trials per day before transplantation. 
Three trials were performed and the mean latencies to fall 
were used to analyze data. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
We performed statistical analyses on the rotarod scores 
using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Statistical Analysis System</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Enterprise 4.1</rs>; SAS 
Korea) on a CHA University mainframe computer. Perfor-
mance measures were analyzed using the PROC MIXED 
program, a linear mixed models procedure. A p value of 
＜0.05 was considered significant. </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry 
To investigate the pathological features of YAC128 
mice, we sacrificed the 12 month-old YAC128 mice and 
their wild-type littermates, perfused and fixed their brains 
with 4% paraformaldehyde. 30 μm frozen coronal sec-
tions were prepared using a cryostat (Microm, Walldorf, 
Germany). A conventional DAB (3,3'-diaminobenzidine) 
immunohistochemistry using antibodies for DARPP-32 
(1:100, Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA) 
and EM48 (1:50, Chemicon) was performed. To analyze 
the marker expression from the transplanted cells, we sac-
rificed the transplanted mice at 12 week-post trans-
plantation and performed fluorescence immunohist-
ochemical analyses using the following primary anti-
bodies: human-specific nuclei (hNu) (1:200, Chemicon), 
human-specific mitochondria (hMito) (1:200, Chemicon), 
human-specific Nestin (hNestin) (1:200, Chemicon), 
MAP2 (1:200, Chemicon), GAD6 (1:200, Developmental 
Studies Hybridoma Bank, Iowa City, IA, USA), 
Gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) (1:5000, Sigma), 
DARPP-32 (1:100, Cell Signaling), SVP38 (1:200, Sigma), 
EM48 (1:50, Chemicon). Secondary antibodies used were </p>

<p>Iksoo Jeon, et al: HD72-iPSC in YAC128 Mice 45 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Pathological features of YAC128 transgenic mice. Expression 
of DARPP-32 (A, B) and EM48 (C, D) in YAC128 mice (A, C) and 
their littermates (B, D). Scale bar: 50 μm. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Behavioral improvement following transplantation of 
HD72-iPSC-NPC into YAC mice. Significant improvement of rotar-
od activity was observed in the transplanted group at as early as 
three weeks after transplantation. *denotes p＜05 and **denotes 
p＜001. </p>

<p>goat anti-mouse IgG-conjugated Alexa-555 (1:200, Molecular 
Probes), goat anti-rabbit IgG-conjugated Alexa-488 (1:200, 
Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA) and goat anti-mouse 
IgM-conjugated Alexa-555 (1:200, Molecular Probes). We 
counter-stained the cells using DAPI, and photographed 
the staining patterns using a confocal laser-scanning mi-
croscope imaging system (LSM510, Carl Zeiss, Inc., 
Thornwood, NY, USA). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Pathological features of YAC128 transgenic mice 
We first examined the pathological characteristics of 12 
month-old YAC128 transgenic mice, by which full-spec-
trum of neuronal loss and behavioral deficits are known 
to become evident (12). As expected, we observed the ex-
pression of DARPP-32, a marker for medium spiny neu-
rons (MSNs) is significantly reduced, whereas the ex-
pression of EM48, a marker for aggregated mutant hun-
tingtin protein (mHtt) is significantly increased in the 
transgenic mice (Fig. 1B and D, respectively), compared 
with their wild-type littermates (Fig. 1A and C, re-
spectively). </p>

<p>Behavioral improvement following transplantation of 
HD72-iPSC-NP cells into YAC128 mice 
To address the in vivo roles of GABAergic neurons de-
rived from HD72-iPSCs (10), we transplanted 100,000 
HD72-iPSC-derived neural precursors, in a volume of 1μl, 
into the striatum of both hemispheres of each YAC128 
mice (n=15). In sham control mice (n=15) we only in-
jected suspension medium (GMEM) into both hemi-</p>

<p>spheres in parallel. Uninjected YAC128 wild-type litter-
mates were included as a control group (n=14). To eval-
uate functional effects of the grafts, we employed rotarod 
test, because it has been shown that rotarod performance 
is greatly reduced in the YAC128 mice. They exhibit ro-
tarod deficit initially at 4 months of age but become more 
prominent at 6 months of age (12). Poor performance on 
the rotarod represents motor learning deficits, indicating 
some aspects of cognitive functions are also affected in 
YAC128 mice. To our surprise, we observed a significant 
improvement of rotarod activity in the transplanted group 
at as early as three weeks after transplantation, compared 
with the sham controls (Fig. 2). Therefore, these results 
strongly suggest that HD72-iPSC-derived neural pre-
cursors played some beneficial roles after transplantation, 
although they carry genetic mutations. </p>

<p>Neuronal differentiation and pathology development 
from the transplanted HD72-iPSC-NPC 
After completion of behavior test at 12 weeks, we sacri-
ficed the mice and analyzed their brains histologically. To 
identify the transplanted human cells, we used antibodies 
against human-specific nuclear antigen (hNu) and human 
mitochondria (hMito). Using confocal microscopy and 
double immunostaining, we found that some of the trans-
planted HD-iPSC-derived cells were still Nestin-positive 
neural precursors (Fig. 3A). Importantly, a large number 
of the surviving human neurons were MAP2-positive (Fig. 
3B), and some neurons exhibited GABAergic and MSN 
features, i.e., they were immunoreactive for GAD6 (Fig. 
3C), GABA (Fig. 3D) and DARPP-32 (Fig. 3E). We also 
found that transplanted human cells expressed the syn-</p>



<p>Fig. 3. Immunohostochemical analyses showing neuronal differentiation and pathology development from the transplanted HD72-iPSC-NPC. 
(A∼F) Formation of markers specific for Nestin (A), MAP2 (B), GAD6 (C), GABA (D), DARPP-32 (E), and SVP38 (F). Arrowheads indicate 
the co-localized cells. (G, H) Areas showing transplanted human cells do not co-localize with EM48 (G), or the host tissues expressing 
EM48 but devoid of transplanted human cells (H). (I) Co-localization of EM48 in the DARPP-32-positive cells. Asterisks indicate the co-lo-
calized cells. Scale bar: 50 μm. </p>

<p>aptic vesicle protein synaptophysin (SVP38) (Fig. 3F), 
suggesting the possibility of synapse formation in the 
graft. 
Intranuclear inclusions of huntingtin are a pathological 
hallmark of HD, which can be readily detected using an 
antibody against aggregated huntingtin (EM48) (Ref 20, 
21). We examined whether HD72-iPSC-derived neurons 
develop huntingtin aggregates 12 weeks after transplantation. 
Interestingly, we found no EM48-positive aggregates were 
formed from the transplanted HD72-iPSC-derived neural 
precursors at this stage (Fig. 3G), while the host tissue in 
the YAC128 mice normally expresses EM48 (Fig. 3H). In 
this case, we also observed that DARPP-32-positive me-
dium spiny neurons were already affected by EM48-pos-
itive aggregates (Fig. 3I). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In this study, we investigated the in vivo roles of 
HD72-iPSC in the YAC128 transgenic mice, a commonly 
used preclinical mouse model of HD, carrying the entire 
170-kb genomic locus of human HTT gene (12). To do 
this, we transplanted HD72-iPSC-derived neural pre-
cursors into the striatum of YAC128 mice bilaterally and 
observed a significant improvement in the rotarod perfo-
rmance. Interestingly, although they carry genetic muta-
tions, the transplanted HD72-iPSC-derived neural pre-
cursors formed GABAeric and MSN-type neurons effi-
ciently, and led to no obvious neuropathological develop-
ment, judged by the absence of but EM48-positive protein 
aggregates at 12 weeks after transplantation. This ob-</p>

<p>Iksoo Jeon, et al: HD72-iPSC in YAC128 Mice 47 </p>

<p>servation was very similar to our recent report (10), in 
which the same type of cells were transplanted into the 
quinolinic acid-lesioned rodent model of HD. However, in 
the same report, we also showed that HD pathology can 
develop after ∼9 months in vivo (10), suggesting that cel-
lular age may be a key factor in identifying aggregates in 
human HD-iPSCs (4). Therefore, it will be likely that the 
transplanted HD72-iPSC-derived neural precursors will 
give rise to EM48-positive aggregates at later stages. 
Another important aspect of results is that no EM48-pos-
itive aggregates were detected in the transplanted cells at 
12 weeks post-transplantation, while the host tissue in the 
YAC128 mice normally expresses EM48. Moreover, 
DARPP-32-positive medium spiny neurons were already 
affected by EM48-positive aggregates. These results 
strongly indicate that no HD pathology was developed ei-
ther from the transplanted cells, or no transmission of HD 
pathology from the host to the graft took place at 12 weeks 
post-transplantation. It will be interesting to investigate 
whether "host-to-graft" or "graft-to-host" transmission of 
HD pathology can occur at later stages. At the same time, 
it will be important to address whether and how normal 
iPSC-derived GABAergic neurons can contribute to the 
functional recovery and neuronal regeneration. In order 
these HD-iPSCs to be used for the cell therapy, it will es-
sential to target the HTT mutation and correct it to a nor-
mal gene in the HD-iPSCS before transplantation (15). 
There are a wide range of HD-iPSC lines available 
through HD iPSC consortium (16), so it will be useful to 
uncover their pathogenic mechanisms in the future. Taken 
together, results from this study can provide useful in-
sights on the in vivo function and pathogenic effects of 
human HD-iPSCs, as well as on the development of HD 
therapeutics in the future. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments 
This study was supported by a grant of the Basic 
Science Research Program through the National Research 
Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of 
Education, Science and Technology (2012R1A1A2006827), 
Republic of Korea to J.S. </p>

<p>Potential conflict of interest 
The authors have no conflicting financial interest. </p>



</text></tei>