<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4255760" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Objective: Parenteral nutrition in infants with gastrointestinal disorders can 
be lifesaving, but it is also associated with parenteral nutrition-associated 
liver disease. We investigated the effects of incorporating v-3 fish oil in a 
parenteral nutrition mixture on signs of parenteral nutrition-associated liver 
disease and explored the mechanism involved in this process. 
Methods: Seven-day-old New Zealand rabbits were divided into 3 groups of 
8, and for 1 week they were infused via the right jugular vein with standard 
total parenteral nutrition with soybean oil (TPN-soy) or TPN with v-3 fish 
oil-based lipid emulsion (TPN-FO), or naturally nursed with rabbit milk 
(control). Serum and liver tissues were analyzed for serological indicators 
and pathology, respectively. Reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain 
reaction was used to evaluate the messenger RNA levels of the 
endoplasmic reticulum stress chaperone protein glucose-regulated protein 
94 (GRP94) in liver tissues and GRP94 protein levels were compared 
through immunohistochemistry and Western blot assays. 
Results: TPN-soy animals had significantly higher serum total bilirubin, 
direct bilirubin, and g-glutamyl transpeptidase and lower serum albumin 
than the controls (P &lt; 0.01, each) or the TPN-FO group, which were similar 
to the controls (P &lt; 0.01 cf. TPN). Damage to liver tissues of the TPN-FO 
group was much less than that of the TPN-soy group. GRP94 messenger 
RNA and protein levels in liver tissues of TPN-soy animals were 
significantly higher than that of the controls or TPN-FO rabbits, which 
were similar to the controls. </p>

<p>Conclusions: Incorporating v-3 fish oil in parenteral nutrition emulsion 
greatly prevented liver dysfunction and liver tissue damage in week-old 
rabbit kits, possibly by preventing endoplasmic reticulum stress. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Experimental Assignment and Establishment of 
TPN Model </p>

<p>The animal ethics committee of the Children's Hospital 
Affiliated to Soochow University granted approval for this study. 
Seven-day-old full-term New Zealand white rabbits (male and 
female, n ¼ 24, weighing 100-120 g) were obtained from Wuxi 
Huishan Jiangnan Experimental Animal Centre (animal license 
number SCXK [Su] 2009-0005), Jiangsu, China. All of the rabbits 
were nursed from their mother before arrival. During the experi-
mental period, the rabbits were maintained in an incubator at 
268C to 288C and 40% to 60% humidity, under a 12 hour/12 hour 
light/dark cycle. 
The rabbits were randomly and equally divided into 3 groups 
of 8, to be sustained for 1 week on total parenteral nutrition with 
soybean oil (TPN-soy) via infusion, TPN containing fish oil (TPN-
FO) via infusion, or naturally nursed with rabbit milk only (control). 
In the TPN groups, animals were infused with nutrient mix; 
the total daily volume of intravenous nutrient solution for each 
rabbit in the TPN groups was 240 mL/kg, infused within 24 hours. 
The TPN regimen was sustained for 7 days, as previously described 
(15) (the components in the mix were purchased from Sino-Swed 
Pharmaceutical, Beijing, China [Tables 1 and 2]. 
Anesthesia was implemented with intraperitoneal injection 
of chloral hydrate (0.3 g/kg body weight). The rabbit was then 
placed in a horizontal dorsal decubitus position on the surgical 
table, and its legs were fixed to the extremities of the table. Skin 
sterilization was performed with benzalkonium bromide solution. 
For injection, the jugular vein was located, and a 10-gauge angio-
catheter with a 1.2-mm silica gel tube was inserted approximately 
1.5 cm into the superior vena cava. The tail end of the silica gel tube 
led out through a 0.5-cm incision in the dorsal scapular area, which 
was used as a subcutaneous tunnel exit. To avoid detachment, the 
end of the silica gel tube was connected to a rotating device. </p>

<p>The components in 240 mL of the TPN given the TPN-soy 
group were 40 mL of a 20% medium-and long-chain fat emulsion 
(72 kcal, 34.3% of total calories), consisting of 2 g soybean oil, 2 g 
medium-chain triglyceride, and 0.24 g egg phospholipids; 80 mL 
of 11.4% pediatric compound amino acid injection-18AA-II 
(36.4 kcal, 17.3% of calories); 36 mL of 50% glucose (72 kcal, 
48.4% of calories); 74 mL of 10% glucose (29.6 kcal); 4 mL of 10% 
NaCl; 3 mL of 10% KCl; 3 mL of 10% calcium gluconate; a half-
piece of a water-soluble vitamin (0.3 mg vitamin B 1 , 0.36 mg 
vitamin B 2 , 4 mg nicotinamide, 0.4 mg vitamin B 6 , 1.5 mg 
pantothenic acid, 10 mg vitamin C, 6 mg biotin, 40 mg folic acid, 
and 0.5 mg vitamin B 12 ); a half-piece fat-soluble vitamin (25 mg 
[82.5 IU] vitamin A, 10.125 mg [5 IU] vitamin D, 0.2275 mg 
[0.25 IU] vitamin E, and 3.75 mg vitamin K 1 ); and a half-piece of 
trace elements (CaCl 2 Á2H 2 O, 39.25 mg; MgCl 2 Á6H 2 O, 15.21 mg; 
FeCl 3 Á6H 2 O, 0.675 mg; ZnCl 2 , 0.135 mg; MnCl 2 Á4H 2 O, 0.395 mg; 
CuCl 2 Á2H 2 O, 42.5 mg; NaF, 0.105 mg; KI, 8.5 mg; Table 2). The 
TPN-FO group received the same as the TPN-soy group, but 
substituting for the 20% medium-and long-chain fat emulsion 
was 40 mL of 10% v-3 fish oil-based lipid emulsion (containing 
1.92-2.88 g soybean oil, 1.92-2.88 g medium-chain triglycerides, 
1.6-2.4 g olive oil, 0.96-1.44 g fish oil, 4.32-6.48 mg DL-a-
tocopherol, 0.384-0.576 g egg phosphatide, 0.9-1.1 g glycerol, 
9.6-14.4 mg sodium oleate, and 0.72-0.88 mg sodium hydroxide). 
The ratio of v-6 to v-3 PUFAs in the v-3 fish oil-based lipid 
emulsion was 3.0 to 2.2 to 1. 
Each 240-mL portion of TPN comprised 210 kcal, and the 
ratio of sugar to lipid was 1.4:1. Fat in each TPN group was given 
for 40 mL Á kg 
À1 Á day </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>; components are listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>Serological Evaluation </p>

<p>To evaluate the relevant serological indicators, rabbits were 
anesthetized by intraperitoneal injection of 10% chloral hydrate. 
Two milliliters of blood were collected by cardiac puncture into </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Fat emulsions of the TPN-soy and TPN-FO groups </p>

<p>Wt/40 mL </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>TPN-soy 
20% medium-and 
long-chain fats </p>

<p>Soybean oil 
2 g </p>

<p>Medium-chain 
triglyceride </p>

<p>2 g </p>

<p>Egg phospholipids 
0.24 g 
TPN-FO 
10% v-3 fish oil-based 
lipid emulsion </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>Soybean oil 
1.92-2.88 g </p>

<p>Medium-chain 
triglyceride </p>

<p>1.92-2.88 g </p>

<p>Olive oil 
1.6-2.4 g 
Fish oil 
0.96-1.44 g </p>

<p>DL-a-Tocopherol </p>

<p>4.32-6.48 mg 
Egg phosphatide 
0.384-0.576 g 
Glycerol 
0.9-1.1 g 
Sodium oleate 
9.6-14.4 mg 
Sodium hydroxide 
0.72-0.88 mg </p>

<p>TPN ¼ total parenteral nutrition; TPN-FO ¼ TPN with v-3 fish oil; TPN-
soy ¼ TPN with soybean oil. 
Ã In each 240-mL portion of TPN, containing 40 mL fat and comprising </p>

<p>210 kcal. Ratio of sugar to lipid was 1.4:1. 
y The ratio of v-6 to v-3 PUFAs in the v-3 fish oil-based lipid emulsion 
was 3.0-2.2 to 1. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Vitamins and trace elements per 240 mL TPN in both groups </p>

<p>Vitamins 
Water-soluble 
B 1 
0.3 mg 
B 2 
0.36 mg 
Nicotinamide 
4 mg 
B 6 
0.4 mg 
Pantothenic acid 
1.5 mg 
C 
1 0 m g 
Biotin 
6 mg 
Folic acid 
40 mg 
B 12 
0.5 mg 
Fat-soluble 
A 
2 5 mg (82.5 IU) 
D 
10.125 mg (5 IU) 
E 
0.2275 mg (0.25 IU) 
K 1 
3.75 mg 
Trace elements 
CaCl 2 Á2H 2 O 
39.25 mg 
MgCl 2 Á6H 2 O 
15.21 mg 
FeCl3Á6H 2 O 
0.675 mg 
ZnCl 2 
0.135 mg 
MnCl 2 Á4H 2 O 
0.395 mg 
CuCl 2 Á2H 2 O 
42.5 mg 
NaF 
0.105 mg 
KI 
8.5 mg </p>

<p>TPN ¼ total parenteral nutrition. </p>

<p>JPGN Volume 59, Number 6, December 2014 
v-3 Fish Oil-Induced Liver Protection </p>

<p>www.jpgn.org </p>



<p>lithium heparin anticoagulant tubes. After centrifuging at 3500 rpm, 
the serum was carefully separated and stored at À208C until used. 
Before analysis, the serum samples were removed from the À208C 
refrigerator and incubated overnight at 48C. 
The total bilirubin, direct bilirubin, alanine aminotransferase, 
aspartate aminotransferase, total protein, albumin, g-glutamyl trans-
peptidase (g-GT), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), triglyceride, total 
cholesterol, and prealbumin levels were examined using a Hitachi 
7600 automated chemistry analyzer (Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan). </p>

<p>Pathological Examination </p>

<p>In addition to collecting blood samples (described above), 
liver tissues were collected after the animals were anesthetized. The 
abdomen was opened and the liver tissues were carefully removed. 
Some of the tissues were stored at À808C for analysis of GRP94 
messenger RNA (mRNA) and GRP94 protein (described below), 
whereas other portions were used for immunohistochemical (below) 
or histopathological analysis. 
After washing with normal saline tissue, samples were fixed 
in 10% paraformaldehyde, dehydrated through an alcohol series, 
cleared in xylene, and embedded in paraffin. Paraffin-embedded 
tissues were sectioned (5-mm thick) with a microtome. For histo-
pathological comparisons, sections were dried, deparaffinized, and 
stained with hematoxylin and eosin. A pathologist who is experi-
enced in liver disease reviewed the histology slides. </p>

<p>Reverse-Transcriptase Polymerase Chain 
Reaction </p>

<p>The mRNA levels of GRP94 were detected via reverse-tran-
scriptase polymerase chain reaction. Liver tissues were removed from 
the À808C refrigerator and crushed. Total RNA was extracted using 
Trizol reagent in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions 
(Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), and the amount and purification were 
evaluated with an ultraviolet spectrophotometer. 
A total of 1 mg RNA was used to synthesize complementary 
DNA using a Reverse Transcriptase Kit (Promega, Madison, WI). 
PCR primers were designed using Primer 5.0 software, compared 
with the GenBank database for identification, and synthesized by 
Sangon Biotech (Shanghai, China). PCR amplification was per-
formed on the GRP94 gene upstream primer (5 
0 -AGGAAACACTC 
TGGGACG-3 
0 ) and downstream primer (5 
0 -ATTCAGGTACTT 
AGGCATC-3 
0 ), producing an amplified fragment of 583 bp. 
Amplification of the glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase 
(GAPDH) gene upstream primer (5 
0 -GTTTGTGATGGGCGTG 
AA-3 
0 ) and downstream primer (5 
0 -CGAAGGTAGAGGAGTG 
GGTG-3 
0 ) produced an amplified fragment of 497 bp. The PCR 
reaction included 200 mmol/L dNTP, 2 U Taq DNA polymerase, 
0.2 mmol/L of each of the upstream and downstream primers, 5 mL 
template complementary DNA, and ddH 2 O to reach a total volume 
of 50 mL. Reaction conditions were predenaturation at 948C for 
10 minutes; denaturation at 948C for 45 seconds, annealing at 558C 
for 30 seconds, and extension at 728C for 30 seconds, for a total of 
35 cycles; and extension at 728C for 7 minutes. 
After electrophoresis in a 1.5% agarose gel, ethidium 
bromide-stained bands were visualized by ultraviolet transillumi-
nation, and the fluorescence intensity was semiquantified using a 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Bio2239</rs> gel analysis system (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Bio-Print</rs>, Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry </p>

<p>Some of the paraffin-embedded tissue sections (described 
above) were used for immunohistochemical analysis. The glass </p>

<p>slides used for immunohistochemistry were precoated with poly-L-
lysine (WuHanBoster Biological Technology, Wuhan, China). 
Immunostaining was carried out with a streptavidin-peroxidase 
kit obtained from Suzhou Enmaike Bio-Tech (Suzhou, China) in 
accordance with the manufacturer's instructions. Three nonoverlap-
ping fields were randomly selected under Â400 magnification. 
The cells positively stained with anti-GRP94 primary anti-
body appeared with brown-yellow granules in the cytoplasm of 
hepatocytes. The intensity of immunohistochemical staining was 
analyzed using <rs type="software">Image-Pro-Plus</rs> image analysis software. An aver-
age gray value supplied by the software was used to reference the 
intensity of GRP94 staining (ie, normalized to an internal control). </p>

<p>Western Blot </p>

<p>Total protein was extracted from cells using lysis buffer. 
Protein concentrations were measured and equal amounts of protein 
extracts were resolved using sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacryl-
amide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE), which were then trans-
ferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride membrane (Millipore, Temecula, 
CA). Membranes were blocked with blocking buffer for 2 hours, 
and then incubated with primary antibody against GRP94 or b-actin 
(1:1000 dilution) at 48C overnight. After washing, membranes were 
incubated with ALP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit secondary anti-
body (1:600 dilution) at room temperature. Immunobands were 
visualized using an ALP kit (WesternBreeze; Invitrogen). To 
quantify protein levels, the expression bands of target proteins 
were analyzed, and the densitometric values were used to conduct 
statistical analysis. The housekeeping protein b-actin was used as 
an internal control. </p>

<p>Statistical Analyses </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">17.0</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>, 
Chicago, IL) and are presented as mean AE standard deviation. 
Statistical significance was determined using 1-way analysis of 
variance. P &lt; 0.05 was recognized as significantly different. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Serological Indicators </p>

<p>No statistical significance was found in the levels of total 
protein, alanine aminotransferase, ALP, aspartate aminotransferase, 
triglyceride, total cholesterol, or prealbumin among the 3 groups 
(P &gt; 0.05, Table 3). Compared with control animals, TPN-soy 
animals had significantly higher serum total bilirubin, direct bilir-
ubin, and g-GT levels, but lower albumin (P &lt; 0.01). No statistical 
differences were detected in the levels of these indicators in 
TPN-FO animals compared with the controls (P &gt; 0.05, each). 
Compared with the TPN-soy group, serum total bilirubin, direct 
bilirubin, and g-GT were significantly lower in the TPN-FO group 
(F ¼ 1247.40, 1037.94, 971.09, respectively; P &lt; 0.01 each), and 
albumin was significantly higher (F ¼ 70.31, P &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>Liver Pathology </p>

<p>Histological examination of the liver tissues obtained from 
the 3 experimental groups revealed that those of the control rabbits 
appeared normal, with intact hepatocytes (Fig. 1A) and without any 
signs of hepatocyte degeneration, necrosis, inflammatory cell infil-
tration, cholangiectasis, bile duct epithelial hyperplasia, or choles-
tasis. In the liver tissues of the TPN-soy group, inflammatory cell 
infiltration, diffuse hepatic steatosis, and disrupted hepatic cord 
structure were, however, evident (Fig. 1B), but there was no 
cholestasis or liver fibrosis, and the hepatic lobule was still visible. </p>

<p>Zhu et al 
JPGN Volume 59, Number 6, December 2014 </p>



<p>www.jpgn.org </p>

<p>In the TPN-FO group, only mild hepatic steatosis and inflammatory 
cell infiltration were found (Fig. 1C); the morphology of hepato-
cytes was normal, and there was no cholangiectasis, bile duct 
epithelial hyperplasia, or cholestasis. </p>

<p>GRP94 mRNA Levels in Liver Tissues </p>

<p>Hematoxylin and eosin staining of liver tissues revealed that 
rabbits given TPN containing fish oil sustained only mild hepatic 
steatosis and inflammatory cell infiltration compared with the 
animals infused with TPN containing soybean oil. Considering that 
ER stress is associated with liver pathology and GRP94 participates 
in the regulation of ER stress, we then assessed the mRNA levels of 
GRP94 in the liver tissues of the different groups to investigate the 
molecular mechanism underlying the seeming hepatic protection of 
TPN-FO against TPN-soy-induced liver damage. 
We found that the GRP94 mRNA levels in liver tissues of the 
TPN-soy group (1.217 AE 0.113, referenced to the gray value stan-
dard) were significantly higher than these levels in the control 
(0.614 AE 0.034, P &lt; 0.01; Fig. 2) and also significantly higher than 
the GRP94 mRNA levels of the TPN-FO group (0.661 AE 0.117). 
The GRP94 mRNA levels of the TPN-FO and controls were similar. </p>

<p>GRP94 Protein Levels in Liver Tissues </p>

<p>To further our investigation of the mechanism underlying 
hepatic protection associated with TPN-FO, the protein levels of 
GRP94 in liver tissues were determined via immunohistochemistry 
and Western blot assays. </p>

<p>Immunostaining of these tissues showed that GRP94 protein 
levels in the liver tissues of the TPN-soy group (133.84 AE 13.66, 
referenced to the gray value standard) were significantly higher than 
those of the controls (78.14 AE 8.17, P &lt; 0.01; Fig. 3) and also 
significantly higher than the GRP94 protein levels of the TPN-
FO group (80.73 AE 9.36, P &lt; 0.01), whereas the GRP94 protein 
levels of the TPN-FO and controls were similar. 
The results obtained by Western blot were in accord with 
those of the immunostaining (Fig. 4). That is, there was no 
associated upregulation in the GRP94 protein levels in the TPN-
FO group (0.29 AE 0.03, relative optical density) as there was in the 
TPN-soy-treated animals (0.63 AE 0.04, P &lt; 0.05), and GRP94 
protein levels of the TPN-FO and controls (0.22 AE 0.01) did not 
differ significantly (P &gt; 0.05). These data suggest that TPN-FO 
may prevent liver damage induced by TPN-soy, possibly by sup-
pressing GRP94 upregulation and ER stress. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>PNALD is a serious complication of patients, especially 
infants, who require long-term parenteral nutrition therapy. Here, 
we sustained 7-day-old rabbit kits for 1 week with TPN containing 
either soybean oil or v-3 fish oil, to examine the role of v-3 fish oil 
in preventing parenteral nutrition-associated liver injury. The 
effects of both of these were compared with normally nursed 
controls with regard to signs of PNALD. We found that, compared 
with the control group, usual soybean oil parenteral nutrition was 
associated with significant liver dysfunction, as indicated by higher </p>

<p>TABLE 3. Serological indicator levels of the 3 experimental groups </p>

<p>TPN-FO 
TPN-soy 
Control 
F 
P </p>

<p>Total bilirubin, mmol/L 
3.28 AE 1.69 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>50.2 AE 3.06 </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>2.28 AE 1.04 
1247.40 
&lt;0.01 
Direct bilirubin, mmol/L 
1.76 AE 0.86 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>47.2 AE 3.91 </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>1.05 AE 0.57 
1037.94 
&lt;0.01 
Total protein, g/L 
25.6 AE 3.01 
23.0 AE 1.94 
24.2 AE 3.12 
1.48 
0.25 
Albumin, g/L 
26.3 AE 3.12 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>11.7 AE 1.05 </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>26.8 AE 2.83 
70.31 
&lt;0.01 
AST, IU/L 
77.1 AE 4.41 
78.8 AE 2.70 
72.7 AE 10.3 
1.47 
0.25 
ALT, IU/L 
24.9 AE 2.98 
26.8 AE 6.57 
21.9 AE 1.49 
2.79 
0.08 
g-GT, IU/L 
14.3 AE 5.46 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>130 AE 5.61 </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>11.2 AE 5.68 
971.09 
&lt;0.01 
ALP, IU/L 
74.0 AE 4.30 
72.3 AE 6.69 
72.3 AE 13.6 
0.08 
0.92 
Triglyceride, mmol/L 
2.18 AE 0.89 
2.86 AE 1.49 
1.74 AE 1.29 
0.14 
0.87 
Total cholesterol, mmol/L 
0.69 AE 0.53 
0.92 AE 0.62 
0.41 AE 0.21 
0.42 
0.66 
Prealbumin, mg/L 
88.8 AE 27.2 
86.5 AE 13.8 
80.8 AE 29.9 
0.64 
0.54 </p>

<p>ALP, alkaline phosphatase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase; g-GT, g-glutamyl transpeptidase; TPN ¼ total parenteral 
nutrition; TPN-FO ¼ TPN with v-3 fish oil; TPN-soy ¼ TPN with soybean oil. 
Ã P &lt; 0.01 compared with TPN-soy. 
y P &lt; 0.01 compared with the control. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Representative histologic images of liver tissues. A, Control; B, TPN-soy group; C, TPN-FO group. Original magnification Â400. 
TPN ¼ total parenteral nutrition; TPN-FO ¼ TPN with v-3 fish oil; TPN-soy ¼ TPN with soybean oil. </p>

<p>JPGN Volume 59, Number 6, December 2014 
v-3 Fish Oil-Induced Liver Protection </p>

<p>www.jpgn.org </p>



<p>serum total bilirubin, direct bilirubin, and g-GT levels and lower 
serum albumin. These effects were not observed in the TPN-FO 
group, which was similar to the control group. Moreover, histological 
examination of liver tissues revealed hepatic damage in the TPN-soy 
group not seen in the TPN-FO, including inflammatory cell infiltra-
tion, diffuse hepatic steatosis, and disrupted hepatic cord structure. 
These observations are consistent with previous reports (15). 
Rats given TPN were found to have higher levels of the ER 
stress marker protein CHOP (C/EBP homologous protein), and also 
higher levels of molecules that are proapoptotic under ER stress, 
c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase (JNK1/2), and p38 MAPK (16). This 
suggests that ER stress is induced by TPN therapy. GRP94 is also a 
marker for ER stress, and in the present study we detected higher 
levels of GRP94 mRNA and GRP94 protein in the liver tissues of 
the rabbits given TPN-soy. Therefore, ER stress may participate in 
TPN-mediated liver damage in both rats and rabbits. Furthermore, it 
was reported that in normal liver L02 cells cultured in vitro, ER 
stress contributed to the progression of PNALD (17). In that report, </p>

<p>ERS was induced with palmitate, which led to the upregulation of 
tribbles homolog 3 (TRB3), a pseudokinase that is known to be 
involved in the pathogenesis of PNALD. Therefore, the ER stress 
seems be an important contributing factor in the pathogenesis and 
progression of PNALD. 
Although the etiology of PNALD is poorly understood, the 
soybean or combined soybean and safflower oils that are included in 
TPN are accepted as contributing factors (18). Both of these oils are 
rich in v-6 fatty acids. It has been reported that v-6 PUFAs generate 
proinflammatory mediators, which may contribute to the onset of 
liver diseases, whereas mediators derived from v-3 PUFAs are 
largely anti-inflammatory (19). A randomized controlled trial con-
ducted by Puder et al (20) showed that fish oil-based intravenous 
lipid emulsion was safe for infants with PNALD, and could reduce 
mortality and organ transplantation rates in children with short 
bowel syndrome. Consistent with their observations, Diamond et al 
(21) reported that v-3 fatty acids may prevent PNALD by improv-
ing bile flow, inhibiting steatosis, and exerting immunomodulatory </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>CON group 
TPN-soy group 
TPN-FO group </p>

<p>GRP94 protein expression gray value </p>

<p>GRP94 </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Immunohistological analysis of GRP94 protein in liver tissues. Representative results of GRP94 staining in samples derived from (A) 
control, (B) TPN-soy group, and (C) TPN-FO group. Quantitative data (D). Original magnification Â400. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01, compared with control; 
Ã P &lt; 0.01, compared with TPN-soy. GRP94 ¼ glucose-regulated protein 94; TPN ¼ total parenteral nutrition; TPN-FO ¼ TPN with v-3 fish oil; TPN-</p>

<p>soy ¼ TPN with soybean oil. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>CON group TPN-soy group TPN-FO group </p>

<p>GRP94 m RNA expression grey value </p>

<p>GRP94 </p>

<p>GRP94 </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>MARK 
1 
2 
3 4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>100 bp </p>

<p>250 bp </p>

<p>500 bp </p>

<p>750 bp 
1000 bp </p>

<p>2000 bp </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. GRP94 mRNA levels in liver tissues determined by RT-PCR. A, Representative RT-PCR results. MARK, DNA marker; lanes 1, 2, control; lanes 
3, 4, TPN-soy; lanes 5, 6, TPN-FO. B, Quantitative data. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.01, compared with control; 
Ã P &lt; 0.01, compared with TPN-soy. Glyceraldehyde </p>

<p>3-phosphate dehydrogenase was used as internal control. GRP94 ¼ glucose-regulated protein 94; mRNA ¼ messenger RNA; RT-PCR ¼ reverse-
transcriptase polymerase chain reaction; TPN ¼ total parenteral nutrition; TPN-FO ¼ TPN with v-3 fish oil; TPN-soy ¼ TPN with soybean oil. </p>

<p>Zhu et al 
JPGN Volume 59, Number 6, December 2014 </p>



<p>www.jpgn.org </p>

<p>effects, although the molecular mechanism involved in this process 
remains unclear. In the present study, we found that substitution of 
v-3 fish oil for soybean fat emulsion was associated with prevention 
of liver dysfunction indicated by serology results, and liver tissue 
damage observed through histology. This implies that v-3 fish oil 
may protect against PNALD. Moreover, levels of GRP94 mRNA 
and GRP94 protein in the kits given TPN with v-3 fish oil were 
comparable with the control rabbits, and significantly lower than 
those given TPN with soybean fat emulsion. These data indicate 
that TPN-induced liver injury was reduced in those given v-3 fish 
oil, unlike those given soybean fat emulsion, and its mechanism 
may be associated with a reduction in ER stress by reducing the 
GRP94 expression associated with soybean fat emulsion. Our 
findings are consistent with a previous report that glycyrrhizin, 
an active component of licorice root that has been used to treat 
chronic hepatitis, represses TPN-associated acute liver injury in rats 
by suppressing ER stress (16). 
There was a difference in the amount of a-tocopherol between 
the 2 TPN solutions. a-Tocopherol is a well-known lipophilic anti-
oxidant that has the ability to scavenge peroxyl radicals (22). 
Nandivada et al (19) reported that the risk factors of cholestasis 
and hepatic injury observed in PNALD included elevated serum 
concentrations of phytosterols, an abundance of v-6 PUFAs, and a 
relative paucity of a-tocopherol. Moreover, previous research indi-
cated that a-tocopherol protected against CCl 4 -induced liver damage 
(22). Unfortunately, we did not investigate whether the a-tocopherols 
play a role in the prevention of PNALD in the TPN-FO group. 
In summary, our present study showed that substitution of v-3 
fish oil for soybean fat emulsion in TPN greatly prevented liver 
dysfunction and liver tissue damage in week-old rabbit kits, possibly 
by preventing ER stress. Our study may provide valuable evidence for 
the use of v-3 fish oil for preventing PNALD in infants. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments: The authors gratefully acknowledge all 
members of the laboratory for sharing reagents and advice and 
thank the pathologist for reviewing the histology slides. The authors 
also thank Medjaden Bioscience for assisting in the preparation of 
this manuscript. </p>



<p>0.0000 </p>

<p>0.2000 </p>

<p>0.4000 </p>

<p>0.6000 </p>

<p>0.8000 </p>

<p>1.0000 </p>

<p>GRP94/actin density ratio </p>

<p>CON group 
TPN-soy 
group </p>

<p>TPN-FO 
group </p>

<p># </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>GRP94 </p>

<p>Actin </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>2 
3 </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Western blot of the GRP94 protein in liver tissues. A, Representative Western blot results. Lane 1, control; lane 2, TPN-FO; lane 3, TPN-
soy. B, Quantitative data. 
# P &lt; 0.05, compared with control; 
Ã P &lt; 0.05, compared with TPN-soy. Actin was used as internal control. </p>

<p>GRP94 ¼ glucose-regulated protein 94; TPN ¼ total parenteral nutrition; TPN-FO ¼ TPN with v-3 fish oil; TPN-soy ¼ TPN with soybean oil. </p>

<p>JPGN Volume 59, Number 6, December 2014 
v-3 Fish Oil-Induced Liver Protection </p>

<p>www.jpgn.org </p>



</text></tei>