<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4380214" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>to contribute 28% of the 
gating charge, and R2, R3, R4, and K5 contribute 35, 26, 
28, and 15%, respectively (Aggarwal and MacKinnon,  1996; Seoh et al., 1996). That is, the first four positive 
residues contribute about the same amount of charge. 
The large magnitude of charge movement has been 
explained by the existence of aqueous cavities that 
sharply focus the electric field near the center of the 
voltage-sensing domain (VSD) (Islas and Sigworth, 2001;  Asamoah et al., 2003 ; Ahern and Horn, 2005) and 
across which the S4 charges move in sequence (Tao  et al., 2010). 
A wonderful breakthrough in our understanding of 
voltage gating came in the form of the x-ray structures 
of the Kv1.2 channel, a mammalian orthologue of Shaker 
(Long et al., 2005) and the paddle chimera between 
Kv1.2 and the S3b-S4 of Kv2.1 (Long et al., 2007). 
These structures most likely represent an active/relaxed 
(Villalba-Galea et al., 2008) conformation of both the 
VSD and the pore domain and are the basis for models 
of the hypothetical resting state of the channels. These </p>

<p>Much has been learned about the voltage sensors of ion channels since the x-ray structure of the mammalian 
voltage-gated potassium channel Kv1.2 was published in 2005. High resolution structural data of a Kv channel en-
abled the structural interpretation of numerous electrophysiological findings collected in various ion channels, 
most notably Shaker, and permitted the development of meticulous computational simulations of the activation 
mechanism. The fundamental premise for the structural interpretation of functional measurements from Shaker is 
that this channel and Kv1.2 have the same characteristics, such that correlation of data from both channels would 
be a trivial task. We tested these assumptions by measuring Kv1.2 voltage-dependent gating and charge per chan-
nel. We found that the Kv1.2 gating charge is near 10 elementary charges (e o ), 25% less than the well-established 
13-14 e o in Shaker. Next, we neutralized positive residues in the Kv1.2 S4 transmembrane segment to investigate the 
cause of the reduction of the gating charge and found that, whereas replacing R1 with glutamine decreased voltage 
sensitivity to 50% of the wild-type channel value, mutation of the subsequent arginines had a much smaller effect. 
These data are in marked contrast to the effects of charge neutralization in Shaker, where removal of the first four 
basic residues reduces the gating charge by roughly the same amount. In light of these differences, we propose that 
the voltage-sensing domains (VSDs) of Kv1.2 and Shaker might undergo the same physical movement, but the sep-
tum that separates the aqueous crevices in the VSD of Kv1.2 might be thicker than Shaker's, accounting for the 
smaller Kv1.2 gating charge. </p>



<p>Kv1.2 is less voltage dependent than Shaker </p>

<p>contained 130 KCl, 3 HEPES, and 1 EDTA, pH 7.4 (KOH). Gating 
currents were recorded in the absence of permeant ions using the 
following solutions: 130 NMDG-Asp, 10 HEPES, 5 NaCl, and 2.5 
CaCl 2 , pH 7.4 (NMDG), in the pipette solution, and 130 NMDG-Asp, 
10 HEPES, 5 NaCl, and 2.5 EDTA, pH 7.4 (NMDG), in the bath 
solution. Charge-per-channel experiments were made using sym-
metrical Cs 
+ solutions, which contained 120 CsCl, 10 HEPES, and 
1.5 EDTA, pH 7.4 (NMDG), in the bath, and 120 CsCl, 10 HEPES, 
and 1.5 CaCl 2 , pH 7.4 (NMDG), in the pipette. 
All recordings were performed at room temperature (22°C) using 
an Axopatch 200B amplifier (Molecular Devices) and acquired with 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Pulse and Patchmaster</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">HEKA</rs>). Patch pipettes were pulled 
from borosilicate glass, fire-polished to a resistance of 0.5-1 MΩ, and 
covered in dental wax to reduce linear capacitive currents. 
Macroscopic currents were low-pass filtered at 5 kHz and sam-
pled at 15 kHz. For macroscopic current recordings, the follow-
ing voltage protocol was used: patches were held at 90 mV, and 
voltage was stepped from 70 to 90 mV in 10-mV increments for 
100 ms before being changed back to 90 mV for 100 ms. All 
macroscopic current recordings are the average of 10 current 
traces to reduce noise. For leak subtraction, a P/5 protocol was 
applied from a leak holding potential of 120 mV. 
The first 100 µs of the tail current were averaged and divided by 
the largest tail current value in the set of traces to yield a normal-
ized current that is directly proportional to the open probability, 
P o . The voltage dependence of the normalized tail currents was 
fitted to a fourth-power Boltzmann function: </p>

<p>V </p>

<p>q 
V V k T </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>( ) 
exp </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>' </p>

<p>= 
+ </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p>− 
− </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>app </p>

<p>P o 
(1) </p>

<p>Here, q app is the apparent gating charge of one subunit in the tet-
ramer, and V is a value related to the V 1/2 of the P o (V) function by: </p>

<p>V 
V 
q 
k T </p>

<p>app </p>

<p>B 
1 2 </p>

<p>4 2 1 </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>' 
ln 
. 
= − 
− </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>T and k B have their usual meanings. The time constant of channel 
activation,  on , was estimated by fitting a single exponential to the 
late phase of ionic currents activated by depolarization, and the 
activation delay, d, was determined to be the point where the ex-
ponential fit intersects the time axis using the equation: </p>

<p>I t I 
e </p>

<p>t d </p>

<p>on </p>

<p>( ) 
. 
= 
− </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
  </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
  </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>− 
− </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
  
 </p>

<p> 
  </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>Channel closure kinetics were measured using a tail current 
protocol in which the voltage was held at 120 mV for 100 ms, 
and then stepped to 60 mV for 100 ms to activate all channels, and 
followed by pulses starting from 150 to 0 mV in 10-mV steps for 
100 ms. Tail currents were fit with a single-exponential function to 
obtain the time constant associated with the deactivation event. 
The voltage dependence of all time constants  i (V) was fit to the 
equation: </p>

<p>τ 
τ </p>

<p>i 
i 
i 
B </p>

<p>V 
q V k T </p>

<p>( ) = ( ) ( 
) </p>

<p>0 exp 
. 
(3) </p>

<p>Here,  i (0) is the value of the time constant at zero mV, and q i is 
the partial charge associated with the time constant. 
For nonstationary noise analysis, 50-300 depolarizing pulses to 
100 mV were delivered from a holding potential of 90 mV, then 
returned to 90 mV. The variance  
2 was calculated from these at 
each point in time, using the method of pairwise sweep subtraction </p>

<p>refined models of closed and open conformations have 
been used in molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of 
the voltage-driven conformational changes that activate 
the channel (Khalili-Araghi et al., 2010; Delemotte et al.,  2011; Jensen et al., 2012; Vargas et al., 2012). An impor-
tant caveat is that all of the functional data that has 
been used to construct and validate these model struc-
tures and the subsequent simulations have been derived 
from experiments performed in Shaker (Lainé et al.,  2004; Campos et al., 2007; Lin et al., 2011). 
Although the degree of homology between Shaker and 
Kv1.2 is high, especially in the VSD (66% identical), there 
is no a priori reason to think that these two channels 
should be functionally equal. After all, they have evolved 
to perform distinct functions at specific physiological con-
ditions in two very different kinds of organisms. 
The use of data derived from Shaker to validate struc-
tures obtained from Kv1.2 makes the assumption that 
basic biophysical properties between these two channels 
are the same and that mutagenesis of equivalent amino 
acid residues should produce the same structural per-
turbations and functional effects. These assumptions 
need to be experimentally tested. In this work, we set 
out to explore the basic voltage-dependent behavior of 
heterologously expressed homomeric Kv1.2 channels 
to contrast these characteristics with those of Shaker. 
Our results point to several important basic differences 
that need to be taken into account in further structure-
function comparisons between the two channels. </p>

<p>M A T E R I A L S A N D M E T H O D S </p>

<p>Molecular biology and heterologous expression 
The WT Kv1.2 and Shaker 29-4 (N-type inactivation removed) chan-
nels were provided by B. Roux (University of Chicago, Chicago, IL) 
and F. Sigworth (Yale University, New Haven, CT), respectively. 
Point mutations in Kv1.2 S4 were constructed in a single PCR 
reaction using mutagenic oligonucleotides, the KOD Hot Start 
DNA Polymerase (EMD Millipore), and the Kv1.2-pMAX plasmid 
as a template. Only mutants R294Q, R297Q, R300N, and R303Q 
produced detectable currents when expressed in Xenopus laevis 
oocytes. Shaker in the pGEMA plasmid and Kv1.2 constructs were 
linearized using NotI and PacI, respectively. The digested plas-
mids were transcribed with the T7 mMESSAGE mMACHINE kit 
(Ambion), and the resulting mRNAs were resuspended in nuclease-
free water at a concentration of 0.5-1 mg/ml. 
A piece of ovary was surgically removed from tricaine-anesthetized 
Xenopus females and mechanically ruptured into small sections. 
Ovary segments were treated with 1.2 mg/ml type I collagenase 
(Sigma-Aldrich) in OR2 solution for 30 min, and stage V-VI 
oocytes were selected and stored in ND96 solution hereafter. 
Healthy oocytes were injected with 50 ng mRNA 5-24 h after har-
vesting, and recordings were performed 1-3 d after injection. </p>

<p>Electrophysiology and data analysis 
The composition of all the solutions listed in this section is given 
in millimolar quantities. The pipette solution for ionic current 
recordings, unless otherwise stated, was composed of 130 KCl, 
3 HEPES, and 1.8 CaCl 2 , pH 7.4 (KOH), and the bath solution </p>

<p>Ishida et al. </p>



<p>G V 
A 
Q V k T </p>

<p>app 
B </p>

<p>( ) = </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>exp 
, 
(7) </p>

<p>was fitted to the 10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-10 
3 range of normalized conductance to 
yield a lower bound estimate of the voltage dependence. 
Data analysis and model fitting were performed using custom 
scripts written in <rs id="software-1" type="software">Igor Pro</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">6</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">WaveMetrics</rs>). </p>

<p>Sequence alignment and structural model building 
Shaker and Kv1.2 amino acid sequences were aligned using <rs id="software-2" type="software">AlignX</rs> 
in <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">the Vector NTI software package (Invitrogen</rs>). The structural 
model of Shaker was constructed using the <rs type="software">I-TASER</rs> protein structure 
prediction server, with the Kv1.2 open state model of Khalili-Araghi 
et al. (2010) as a template. </p>

<p>R E S U L T S </p>

<p>Macroscopic properties of Kv1.2 </p>

<p>All of our patch-clamp recordings of ionic and gating cur-
rents were performed in the cell-attached configuration 
to maximize patch stability and avoid voltage shifts that 
have been reported to be present in Kv1.2 channels when 
recorded in excised-patch configurations (Rezazadeh  et al., 2007; Schmidt et al., 2012). Nevertheless, we ob-
served some variability in channel behavior. Most cur-
rents behaved as those ionic potassium (K 
+ ) currents 
depicted in Fig. 1 A. Large amplitude currents could be 
routinely measured, with activation that speeded up 
with depolarizing voltages, as has been reported for 
other voltage-gated K 
+ ion channels and previously for 
Kv1.2 (Scholle et al., 2004). Occasionally, faster onset 
currents could be recorded, which also activated over a 
more negative voltage range (not depicted). These less 
common currents are related to the more typical ones 
shown in Fig. 1 by an approximate 15-mV voltage shift, 
both in kinetics and steady-state properties. This obser-
vation is similar to what has been shown to occur to 
Kv1.2 in mammalian cell expression systems (Rezazadeh  et al., 2007) and to the Kv1.2-Kv2.1 paddle chimera 
(Schmidt et al., 2012), where fast and slow populations 
of channels can be distinguished. In our recording con-
ditions (symmetric K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>), the I-V curve shows a negative 
slope region, indicative of voltage-dependent activation 
(Fig. 1 B). The voltage dependence of activation was 
estimated from the amplitude of tail currents at the end 
of a depolarizing pulse. The normalized magnitude of 
the tail current is shown in Fig. 1 C, along with a fit to 
a fourth-power Boltzmann function, with an apparent 
gating charge per subunit of 2.7 e o . 
Nonstationary noise analysis of macroscopic ionic cur-
rents revealed that the channels reached a maximum 
open probability of 0.8 and had a single-channel cur-
rent of 0.7 pA at 40 mV, almost the same as Shaker 
(Heginbotham and MacKinnon, 1993). 
Activation kinetics showed marked deviation from a 
single-exponential time course (Fig. 1 D). We character-
ized activation with two parameters: the time constant 
of an exponential fit to the second half of the time </p>

<p>to reduce the influence of any channel rundown (Heinemann and  Conti, 1992). To estimate the number of channels, N and the ampli-
tude of the single-channel current, i, variance was plotted against 
the mean current I  and fitted with the equation (Sigworth, 1980): </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>= 
− 
i I 
I 
N 
. 
(4) </p>

<p>For gating current recordings, patches were depolarized in 10-mV 
steps up to 40 mV from a 90-mV holding potential for 50 ms, 
and then returned to 90 mV. Currents were filtered at 10 kHz 
and sampled at 50 kHz, and a P/5 protocol from a holding 
potential of 140 mV was applied to subtract linear current com-
ponents. On-gating currents were integrated to obtain the charge 
moved at every voltage. 
Estimation of the apparent gating charge was done through the 
limiting slope method as implemented in Islas and Sigworth (1999). 
These experiments were performed using the same set of solutions 
as the macroscopic current recordings: low-pass filtered at 2 kHz 
and sampled at 10 kHz. The holding potential was set to 100 mV 
for 100 ms, and then the patch was depolarized for 700 ms in 5-or 
10-mV steps from the most positive potential at which individual 
channel openings could be clearly observed (usually 60 mV) 
down to 90 mV. The patch was stepped down to the holding po-
tential for 100 ms after each test pulse. Leak and capacitive currents 
were subtracted using an average of null sweeps. 100-1,000 current 
traces at each potential were idealized using the half-amplitude 
threshold crossing method (Colquhoun and Sigworth, 1995). 
These idealized records were then averaged to obtain the ensemble 
time course of the product of the number of channels times the 
open probability (NP o ). P o was obtained from these ensembles by 
dividing the steady-state value of NP o by the number of channels 
estimated from noise analysis. 
The apparent charge, Q app , was estimated from the slope of the 
P o (V) relationship according to: </p>

<p>Q 
k T 
d P 
dV </p>

<p>app 
B </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>= 
ln , 
(5) </p>

<p>or from a fit of P o plotted against voltage to the equation: </p>

<p>P V 
A 
Q V k T </p>

<p>o 
app 
B </p>

<p>( ) = </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>exp 
. 
(6) </p>

<p>In these equations, A is a scaling factor, and k B and T have their 
usual meanings. 
Charge per channel was determined as in Noceti et al. (1996). 
After removal of the vitelline membrane, oocytes were soaked in 
Cs </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-containing solution for 30 min to allow exchange of the inter-
nal solution. After this time period, the reversal potential of Cs 
+ cur-
rents was within ±3 mV of 0. A pulse to a voltage near 0 mV (the Cs </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>reversal potential in these experiments) was delivered to the patch 
to elicit a gating current trace free of ionic current from which the 
maximum charge was calculated. After the reversal potential pulse, 
voltage was stepped to 90 mV to elicit a Cs 
+ tail current. The vari-
ance of these Cs 
+ currents was calculated from 300 pulses and 
used to estimate the number of channels as described above, using 
a pairwise subtraction algorithm. The maximum charge displaced 
by the activation of a single channel was determined from the rela-
tionship between the on-charge and the number of channels from 
several patches. 
Voltage ramps were used to estimate the limiting slope and the 
apparent gating charge contribution of each charged residue in S4. 
Patches were depolarized with a 5-s ramp spanning the range 
of 100 to 50 mV. The resulting current was converted to con-
ductance according to G(V ) = I/(V  V rev ) and normalized to the 
steady-state value. An exponential function, </p>



<p>Kv1.2 is less voltage dependent than Shaker </p>

<p>oocytes with very high expression levels and were appar-
ent at voltages more negative than those that induce 
significant channel opening, as expected for a channel 
where charge movement is coupled to channel opening 
(Fig. 2 A). The charge obtained from integration of cur-
rents during depolarization (on-gating currents) was dis-
cernible at voltages as negative as 80 mV and became 
saturated at voltages positive to 10 mV. The Q(V) rela-
tionship could be fit by a sum of two Boltzmann equa-
tions (Fig. 2 B). The voltage dependence of charge 
movement is reminiscent of that in Shaker (Zagotta et al.,  1994b; Schoppa and Sigworth, 1998a). 
At negative voltages, on-gating currents are rapid, be-
come slower at intermediate voltages, and turn faster 
again at more depolarized potentials. We quantified gat-
ing current kinetics by fitting a single exponential to 
the decay phase of the transient current. The decay is 
exponentially dependent on voltage with an average as-
sociated charge q on = 0.54 e o (Fig. 2 C). Charge return 
during repolarization (off-gating currents) is initially also 
rapid but becomes significantly slowed down in the range 
of voltages where channels begin to open (Fig. 2 D). </p>

<p>course of current activation and a delay, which was mea-
sured by extrapolating the exponential fit to zero cur-
rent (Schoppa and Sigworth, 1998a). Both the time course 
of the exponential fit and the delay are voltage depen-
dent (partial charges of 0.25 and 0.45 e o , respectively). 
Deactivation kinetics, measured from inward tail cur-
rents, also behaved as in other Kv channels, and deacti-
vation could be accounted for by a single-exponential 
relaxation, whose time constant decreased exponentially 
with hyperpolarization (q deact = 0.72 e o ; Fig. 1 E). 
The sigmoidal time course suggests that Kv1.2 chan-
nels also transit through many closed states before reach-
ing the open state. A Cole-Moore-type experiment reveals 
that the delay is voltage dependent, becoming shorter 
as the prepulse voltage is made more positive (Fig. 1 F). 
This result confirms that the channel has to move through 
several closed states before opening. </p>

<p>Gating currents </p>

<p>We recorded voltage-dependent charge movement from 
cell-attached patches in the absence of permeant ions. 
Gating currents could be observed in patches from </p>

<p>Figure 1. Kinetic and steady-state properties of Kv1.2 potassium currents. (A) Family of representative K 
+ current traces activated by 
voltage steps from 70 to 30 mV in 10-mV increments from a holding potential of 90 mV. (B) I-V relationship of the data shown in A. 
(C) Voltage dependence of the channel activation. The magnitude of tail currents was normalized to the maximum value. Open prob-
ability obtained from noise analysis of macroscopic currents at 50 mV was 0.8. The red curve is the fit to a Boltzmann function to the 
fourth power (Eq. 1), with parameters V = 45 mV and q app = 2.7 e o . (D) Current activation time courses (black traces) showing marked 
sigmoidal activation. The red curves are fits to Eq. 2. The time-axis intersect is the delay. (E) Activation time constant,  on , from fits as in 
D (triangles), activation delay (rhombuses), and deactivation,  off , (inverted triangles). The red lines are exponential fits to Eq. 3. The 
partial charges associated with each time constant are: q act = 0.25 e o , q delay = 0.45 e o , and q deact = 0.72 e o . (F) Cole-Moore shift experiment 
showing the reduction of delay as the prepulse potential is made more positive. The inset shows the value of the delay determined as in 
D as a function of the prepulse potential. Error bars are the SEM. </p>

<p>Ishida et al. </p>



<p>measured previously in Shaker channels (Schoppa et al.,  1992; Aggarwal and MacKinnon, 1996; Noceti et al.,  1996; Seoh et al., 1996; Islas and Sigworth, 1999) and 
which is generally assumed to be the same for Kv1.2. 
When the P o (V) data are transformed according to Eq. 5, 
it can be seen that the apparent charge approaches a 
limiting value of 10 e o and that the data between P o values 
of 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>-10 
7 is very close to this limiting value (Fig. 3 C). 
Several explanations are possible for the apparent re-
duced voltage dependence of Kv1.2 channels. Limiting 
slope measurements are approximate and give the gat-
ing charge only if channel opening is strictly coupled to 
charge movement (Sigg and Bezanilla, 1997; Islas and  Sigworth, 1999). Although the gating current and mac-
roscopic ionic current behaviors of the channel are con-
sistent with a sequential mechanism and strict coupling 
of charge movement to channel opening, we decided to 
carry out a direct measurement of the gating charge per 
channel by comparing charge movement and channel 
number in the same patch. </p>

<p>Direct gating charge determination </p>

<p>We simultaneously measured gating and ionic tail cur-
rents in cell-attached patches in solutions where Cs 
+ is 
the only permeant ion (Noceti et al., 1996). Potassium 
channels generally have a single-channel conductance 
for Cs 
+ that is at least an order of magnitude smaller 
than that of K 
+ (Heginbotham and MacKinnon, 1993), 
and it seems that Kv1.2 is not an exception. The reduced </p>

<p>It is noteworthy that the kinetics of charge movement in 
Kv1.2 is about threefold slower than that of Shaker, and 
the voltage dependence is slightly higher (q onKv1.2 = 0.54 e o 
and q onShaker = 0.39-0.45 e o ; Zagotta et al., 1994b; Schoppa  and Sigworth, 1998a; Islas and Sigworth, 1999). </p>

<p>Limiting slope measurements of the voltage sensitivity </p>

<p>For a voltage-gated ion channel that is activated by de-
polarization, an estimate of the gating charge can be 
obtained from the logarithmic voltage sensitivity or lim-
iting slope of the open probability measured at hyper-
polarized voltages (Almers, 1978), although this only 
measures the charge coupled to opening. We performed 
the measurement of open probability to the lowest pos-
sible values in our experimental conditions, according 
to methods described previously (Hirschberg et al.,  1995; Islas and Sigworth, 1999; González-Pérez et al.,  2010). Fig. 3 A shows ensemble averages from idealized 
channel records at four negative voltages. It can be seen 
from these that channel opening is steeply voltage de-
pendent when the open probability is very low. Fig. 3 B 
shows the voltage dependence of the steady-state value 
of these ensembles normalized to the number of chan-
nels present in each patch for several experiments. 
We were surprised by these measurements of the lim-
iting slope of Kv1.2 channels, as they indicate that the 
voltage dependence of opening at values of P o between 
10 
4 and 10 
7 is consistent with a gating charge of 
9.6 ± 0.25 e o , a value well below the expected 13-14 e o </p>

<p>Figure 2. Gating currents and 
charge movement. (A) Gating 
current traces recorded from 
a cell-attached patch. Traces 
shown correspond to 80, 60, 
40, 20, 0, and 20 mV from a 
holding potential of 90 mV. 
(B) Voltage dependence of the 
normalized charge movement 
from five different patches. 
Charge was determined from the 
time integral of traces as in A. 
The red curve is a fit of a sum 
of two Boltzmann functions with 
charges q 1 = 0.3 e o , q 2 = 3 e o , and 
V </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1/2 = 70 mV, V </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1/2 = 37 mV. 
Error bars are the SEM. (C) Time 
constant of current decay  on de-
termined from an exponential fit 
to the gating current decay; n = 5 
patches. The red line is the aver-
age fit of Eq. 3 to all five patches; 
the partial charge is q on = 0.54 e o . 
(D) Time constant of the off-
gating current decay determined 
from an exponential fit. Note 
that the time constant becomes 
very slow and voltage indepen-
dent at voltages more positive 
than 40 mV, which corresponds 
to the range of channel opening. </p>



<p>Kv1.2 is less voltage dependent than Shaker </p>

<p>Fig. 4 shows the data from a representative patch. Gat-
ing and tail currents can be recorded in a single sweep 
and at the same gain (Fig. 4 A). The number of chan-
nels in the patch was estimated from variance analysis 
of the inward Cs 
+ tail current (Fig. 4 C). The single-chan-
nel Cs 
+ current at 90 mV was 0.02 pA, which can be 
compared with 1.8 pA measured in K 
+ solutions to 
give a permeability ratio P Cs /P K of 0.01. This value is 
the same as has been measured for Shaker and other po-
tassium channels (Heginbotham and MacKinnon, 1993;   magnitude of macroscopic Cs 
+ currents allows for pre-
cise determination of the reversal potential, at which the 
gating current is clearly resolved without ionic current 
contamination. Noise analysis of the tail current was used 
to determine the number of channels in the patch. The 
reversal potential of each patch was within ± 3 mV of 
0 mV, the expected reversal potential for Cs </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>. It should 
be noted that charge movement is already saturated at 
approximately 10 mV (Fig. 2 B), which means that at 
0 mV we measured all the charge available. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Limiting slope measurements of the apparent gating charge on Kv1.2. (A) Ensemble averages from a representative patch. 
Between 100 and 500 idealized sweeps were averaged to produce the ensembles at each voltage. (B) Measurements of the open prob-
ability of Kv1.2 channels were performed down to values between 10 
7 and 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>. Shown are the data from six patches where the maximal 
open probability and channel number were measured. The apparent charge was estimated from a fit to Eq. 6 to the data between 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>and 10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. The dotted lines are the P o for a Boltzmann function elevated to the fourth power with a total charge of 10 e o (red curve), and 
for Scheme 1 (blue curve). The prediction from the allosteric model (Scheme 2) is shown by the lime-colored line. Both schemes have 
a total charge of 10 e o . The inset shows the median (9.65 e o ) and the 25th and 75th percentiles (box) and the 90th and 10th percentiles 
(whiskers). The mean and SEM are 9.57 ± 0.24 e o . (C) The slope from the data in B is plotted as a function of P o according to Eq. 5. The 
data show that the limiting slope is approached at values &lt;10 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. The curves are model predictions as in A and have the same color coding. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Simultaneous measurements 
of the gating currents and channel 
number. (A) Representative experiment 
showing simultaneous measurement of 
outward gating current and inward 
Cs 
+ current. The reversal potential was 
near zero (+1.5 mV). (B) Gating cur-
rent (back trace) and its integral (red). 
(C) Noise analysis of the inward Cs </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>current. The variance versus mean re-
lationship was fit to Eq. 4 to obtain the 
number of channels and the amplitude 
of the single-channel current at 90 mV, 
which in this patch are 145,070 and 
0.023 pA, respectively. </p>

<p>Ishida et al. </p>



<p>developed to account for Shaker channel gating data 
can be applied to explain gating in Kv1.2. There are 
a handful of available successful models that vary in their 
degree of detail and experimental constraints (Zagotta  et al., 1994a; Schoppa and Sigworth, 1998b; Ledwell  and Aldrich, 1999). All of them share a basic architec-
ture. Upon depolarization, four VSDs undergo two to 
three independent transitions, which are mainly re-
sponsible for the observed charge movement. Once all 
of the VSDs reach an activated conformation, one or 
two more transitions, which move less charge and are 
produced by a concerted conformational change in all 
subunits, lead to the final pore opening. Our model is 
represented in Scheme 1 and is very similar to that pre-
sented by Ledwell and Aldrich (1999) to account for the 
behavior of WT Shaker and the ILT mutant, with a total 
of 16 closed states and a single open state. 
The rate constants k ij for a transition from state i to j, 
represented by an arrow, have the form: </p>

<p>k 
k 
q V kT </p>

<p>ij 
ij 
ij </p>

<p>= ( ) </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>0 exp 
, </p>

<p>where k ij (0) is the value of the rate constant at 0 mV, 
and q ij is the partial charge associated with the transi-
tion. The values of the parameters for each rate constant 
are listed in Table 1. 
Fig. 6 shows that the model accounts well for the mac-
roscopic time course of the open probability, the time 
course of on-and off-gating currents; the equilibrium be-
havior of charge movement, Q(V), and channel opening; 
P o (V); and the kinetics of on-gating currents. 
This result suggests that although the gating charge 
in Kv1.2 is 30% smaller than in Shaker, the gating mech-
anism in conserved; that is, both channels possess a VSD 
that undergoes conformational changes that are strictly 
coupled to pore opening. </p>

<p>Properties of S4-neutralized mutants </p>

<p>We have shown that the gating mechanism of Kv1.2 
potassium channels is very similar to Shaker channels. </p>

<p>Pérez-Cornejo and Begenisich, 1994). The circles in 
Fig. 5 show the correlation of charge and channel num-
ber for 10 patches obtained from several oocytes. The 
straight line is a linear fit with a slope of 9.96 e o /chan-
nel and is entirely in agreement with the limiting slope 
value. As a control for internal consistency in our ex-
periments, we repeated these measurements in Shaker 
under the same conditions. The linear fit to the Shaker 
data gives a slope of 13.3 e o /channel, which is in accord 
with previous estimates (Schoppa et al., 1992; Aggarwal  and MacKinnon, 1996; Noceti et al., 1996; Seoh et al.,  1996; Islas and Sigworth, 1999). The ratios of the charge 
to channel number (Q/N) are shown if Fig. 5 B, indicat-
ing that Kv1.2 has 30% less gating charge than Shaker. </p>

<p>Kinetic model of Kv1.2 gating </p>

<p>The data presented above indicate that macroscopic gat-
ing properties of Kv1.2 are similar to those of Shaker chan-
nels. We decided to explore if kinetic models previously </p>

<p>Figure 5. Estimation of the charge per channel in Kv1.2 and 
Shaker channels. (A) The relationship between channel number 
and charge movement for both channels is linear. Estimation 
of the gating charge per channel is obtained from a linear fit to 
the data for each channel type (red line). Shaker patches, 13.3 e o , 
n = 9, and correlation coefficient (r) = 0.990. Kv1.2 patches, 9.96 e o , 
n = 10, and (r) = 0.988. (B) Bar plot of the quotient of total charge 
and number of channels (Q/N) for Shaker and Kv1.2. Values are the 
mean, and error bars are the SEM for the same data in A. The as-
terisks indicate that the two datasets are different with a P &lt; 0.01 
level (Student's t test). </p>

<p>T A b L E 1 </p>

<p>Parameters of Scheme 1 </p>

<p>Rate constant 
(at 0 mV) </p>

<p>Value 
(at 0 mV) </p>

<p>Partial 
charge </p>

<p>Equilibrium 
constant </p>

<p>Value 
(at 0 mV) </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>e o </p>

<p>k 1 
520 
0.4 
K 1 
0.5 </p>

<p>k 1 
1,000 
0.6 </p>

<p>k 2 
1,900 
0.8 
K 2 
31.66 </p>

<p>k 2 
60 
0.7 </p>

<p>k a 
950 
0.2 
K A 
9.5 </p>

<p>k a 
100 
0.6 </p>

<p>k o 
1,000 
0.05 
K o 
2.85 
k c 
350 
0.2 </p>

<p>Rate constants used in the model of Scheme 1 derived from fits to data in 
Fig. 6. Equilibrium constants are calculated as: K i = k i /k -i . </p>



<p>Kv1.2 is less voltage dependent than Shaker </p>

<p>S4 charges could make very different individual contri-
butions to overall charge movement. 
We decided to explore the last possibility by neutral-
izing each residue in S4 and measuring the apparent 
gating charge of each mutant through the limiting slope 
method. R1, R2, and R4 were mutated to glutamine, 
whereas R3 was swapped with asparagine. Although we 
constructed several K5 and R6 mutants, we could not 
detect currents when expressing any of them. 
Charge-neutralized mutants R1Q (R294Q), R2Q 
(R297Q), R3N (R300N), and R4Q (R303Q) produced 
detectable voltage-activated currents, although their mag-
nitude is vastly reduced with respect to WT channels 
(Fig. 7). The R1Q and R2Q mutants have a phenotype 
that makes experiments difficult, as even in cell-attached 
patch experiments, the steady-state voltage dependence 
shifts to more negative voltages with a fast time course. 
This effect is very pronounced in R2Q, where the mag-
nitude of inward currents at negative voltages-which is 
proportional to the negative shift of the G(V) curve-
increases severalfold with a time constant of 4.4 min </p>

<p>However, there is a very important difference in that the 
gating charge is significantly reduced. Why is this im-
portant? As we will touch upon in the Discussion, the free 
energy associated with the conformational changes lead-
ing to channel opening is related to the magnitude of 
the gating charge. 
Also, the magnitude of the gating charge of Shaker has 
been used as a constraint in MD simulations that make use 
of models based on the structure of Kv1.2 (Khalili-Araghi  et al., 2010; Delemotte et al., 2011; Jensen et al., 2012). 
There are several scenarios that can explain the reduced 
gating charge in Kv1.2. The magnitude of the physical 
displacement of the S4 charges could be smaller, the dis-
tribution of the electric field across the VSD could be dif-
ferent between the two channels, and finally, individual </p>

<p>Scheme 1 </p>

<p>Figure 6. A kinetic model for Kv1.2 channels. (A) Current traces, I, from a representative patch were converted to P o according to: 
P o = I/iN. The number of channels, N, in the patch was estimated from noise analysis. Black traces are the experimental data and the red 
curves are the best estimate from Scheme 1. (B) The same parameters of the model were used to fit gating current traces from a separate 
experiment. The red curves superimposed on the black traces are the fit from the model. (C) The same parameters also describe the 
steady-state voltage dependence of charge movement and open probability and the kinetics of on-gating currents. (D) The parameters 
used are given in Table 1. </p>

<p>Ishida et al. </p>



<p>on the overall gating charge does not appear to be as 
large as in the R1Q channel, as this mutation causes the 
loss of 17% of the gating charge when compared with 
the WT value (Fig. 9 B). 
R3Q mutant channels express very poorly (Fig. 7 A), 
with macroscopic ionic currents being &lt;100 pA in am-
plitude at positive voltages. The charge estimated from 
the G(V) curves obtained from voltage ramps is 5.5 e o , 
which corresponds to a contribution to the gating charge 
of 18%. Limiting slope measurements could be performed 
for R3N only to a P o of 5 × 10 
5 , yielding a value of 
Q app = 7.35 ± 0.15 e o . 
Finally, mutant R4Q has a Q app = 5.61 ± 0.19 e o , also es-
timated from voltage ramps. The contribution of each 
charge to the total gating charge was calculated as a ratio 
of the Q app estimates of each mutant to the Q app from volt-
age ramps of WT channels (Fig. 9 C). These experiments 
indicate that positive charges in S4 contribute to the gat-
ing charge of Kv1.2 channels in a manner that is similar to 
experiments in Shaker (Aggarwal and MacKinnon, 1996;  Seoh et al., 1996), but with different relative contributions 
of each positive residue in S4, especially for R1. </p>

<p>(Fig. 8). For this reason, we could not reliably estimate 
the gating charge of Kv1.2-R2Q from careful limiting 
slope experiments as in WT Kv1.2, and we resorted to 
measuring the voltage-dependent conductance from 
currents elicited by slow (10-mV/s) voltage ramps. 
All four mutants have reduced voltage sensitivity, as 
judged from the apparent gating charge obtained by 
fitting Eq. 7 to the voltage-dependent conductance 
measured from voltage ramp experiments. It should 
be noted that this charge value is underestimated, be-
cause the apparent charge obtained for the WT channel 
under the same experimental conditions is only 6.7 e o 
(Fig. 9 B). The effect of the R1Q mutation is dramatic, 
with an apparent charge of only 3.4 e o (Fig. 9 B). This 
corresponds to a 50% reduction in the gating charge 
when compared with 6.7 e o for WT. For this mutant, we 
also measured the limiting slope in a few patches, and 
the gating charge from the slope is 5.6 e o , which gives a 
reduction of 46% when compared with the limiting 
slope charge of 9.6 e o for the WT. 
The R2Q apparent charge also measured from volt-
age ramps is 5.56 ± 0.14 e o . The effect of neutralizing R2 </p>

<p>Figure 7. Neutralization of positive charges in S4 alters the voltage dependence of mutant Kv1.2 channels. (A) Representative current 
families recorded from cell-attached patches from oocytes expressing mutants R1Q (R294Q; red), R2Q (R297Q; yellow), R3N (R300N; 
green), and R4Q (R303Q; blue). (B) Voltage dependence of the normalized amplitude of tail currents for all four mutants. Curves are 
fits to Eq. 1. Color coding is the same as in A. Error bars are the SEM. </p>



<p>Kv1.2 is less voltage dependent than Shaker </p>

<p>charge and is consistent with a concerted allosteric con-
formation change. The kinetics of opening are slightly 
slower than in Shaker. 
On the other hand, the gating charge of Kv1.2 is re-
duced and significantly different from the gating charge 
of Shaker. We have established this with two different 
lines of evidence. First, the limiting slope measured at 
very low open probabilities yields a charge of 9.6 ± 0.25 e o . 
Second, direct measurement of charge movement and 
the number of channels in the same patch also yields a 
charge near 10 e o . 
In retrospect, it can be argued that the reduced 
charge movement in Kv1.2 is entirely consistent with its 
physiological function. It is known (Adrian, 1975) that 
channels that shape the action potential waveform are 
more efficient at sustaining a high speed of propaga-
tion of action potentials if they have moderate amounts 
of gating charge, because their contribution to cell ca-
pacitance is smaller. Kv1.2 subunits are found in many 
neurons where they assemble as a homotetramer or as 
part of tetramers with Kv1.1 (Dodson et al., 2002), giv-
ing rise to sustained delayed-rectifier potassium currents 
that activate at relatively negative potentials. These cur-
rents play a role in action potential repolarization and 
also limit the depolarization produced by intense synap-
tic inputs (Dodson et al., 2003). 
The reduced gating charge as compared with Shaker 
channels has another important consequence. It has 
been shown that for a voltage-gated channel, the change 
in free energy G in going from the closed to the open 
state (including all closed states), can be obtained from 
the Q(V) relationship (Chowdhury and Chanda, 2012), 
according to G = Q max · V m , where Q max is the gating 
charge and V m is the median voltage, which is obtained 
from the Q(V) relationship and defined by: </p>

<p>Q V dV 
Q 
Q V dV </p>

<p>Vm </p>

<p>Vm </p>

<p>( ) = 
− ( ) </p>

<p>  
  </p>

<p>−∞ </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>∫ 
∫ max </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>From the Kv1.2 Q(V) measurements in Fig. 6, we calcu-
lated a V m value of 32.7 mV, which when combined with 
our measurement of the gating charge of Q max = 10 e o , 
gives a G of 7.5 Kcal/mol. The free energy change 
can also be computed from the equilibrium constants 
of the gating model, which in our case is given by: </p>

<p>∆G 
RT 
K K 
K K </p>

<p>A 
O </p>

<p>model = − 
⋅ 
  
  
⋅ </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>ln 
. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
2 </p>

<p>0 4 
0 
0 </p>

<p>The equilibrium constants of our model are given in 
Table 1. From these, the value of G model is 8.5 Kcal/mol, 
which is in close agreement with G. 
This value is interesting, as the G for Shaker calcu-
lated using the median voltage method or from a detailed 
gating model (Schoppa and Sigworth, 1998b) is almost 
twice as big (14 Kcal/mol) (Chowdhury and Chanda,  2012). This difference indicates that, mainly because of </p>

<p>D I S C U S S I O N </p>

<p>We have assessed, with a certain degree of detail, the 
voltage-dependent gating characteristics of Kv1.2 po-
tassium channels. In many aspects, these proteins are 
very similar to the better understood and amply stud-
ied Shaker channels. Gating charge movement precedes 
pore opening and is almost entirely distributed among 
a large number of closed states. The opening transition 
seems to be different and, like in Shaker, carries less </p>

<p>Figure 8. Nonstationary behavior of the R2Q mutant. (A) The 
voltage dependence of the tail current amplitude of R2Q shifts 
with time. Representative data from a cell-attached patch imme-
diately after seal formation (circles), after 1 min (squares), and 
after 25 min (triangles). The curves are fits to a simple Boltzmann 
function with steepness and V 1/2 : 2.95 e o , 36.1 mV (circles); 3.74 e o , 
42.4 mV (squares); 5.26 e o , 61.8 mV (triangles). (B) Ampli-
tude of the inward current at 50 mV increases as a function of 
time. Traces were taken at 5, 7, 10, 15, and 25 min after seal for-
mation. (C) The current value at the end of the pulse was plotted 
as a function of time. The fitting curve is an exponential with a 
time constant of 4.4 min. </p>

<p>Ishida et al. </p>



<p>scheme and an allosteric model, respectively. The two 
models have the same gating charge of 10 e o . It can be 
seen that if it exists, a reduction in the slope of the 
P o (V) curve consistent with voltage-independent open-
ings would be distinguishable only at much lower open 
probabilities than those reached here. 
What is the origin of the reduced gating charge in 
Kv1.2 channels? The first MD-derived calculation of 
the gating charge of an ion channel (Khalili-Araghi et al., 
2010) made use of atomic models of the closed and 
open conformations based on the Kv1.2/2.1 chimera 
structure. Strikingly, these calculations yielded a gating 
charge of 10 e o . The authors suggested that the origin 
of this "anomaly" could be traced to the position of the 
first arginine of S4 in the electric field, and that it should 
be deeper into the local electric field. Consequently, 
the position of R1 was fixed on steered MD simulations 
to force the calculation to yield a gating charge closer to 
the expected 13 e o . So, our data would suggest that argi-
nine 294 might actually be pointing out in the closed 
state, thus being subject to a smaller fraction of the elec-
tric field. 
Kv1.2 charge movement seems to occur through the 
same mechanisms as in Shaker, and a sequence align-
ment of Shaker and Kv1.2 indicates that the key charges, </p>

<p>the larger gating charge in Shaker channels, their open-
ing is accompanied by a larger stabilization of the open 
state at positive voltages. One could speculate that the 
reduced G in Kv1.2 implies that these channels are 
allosteric, in the sense that the energy difference be-
tween the open and closed state is smaller and perhaps 
there is a higher open probability of voltage-independent 
openings at negative voltages. However, we have mea-
sured the P o (V) curve down to P o values of 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>, and we 
do not find convincing evidence of a reduced apparent 
charge at low P o values as should be expected from 
allosteric models. In Fig. 3 C we compare the best pre-
diction from Schemes 1 and 2, a fully coupled gating </p>

<p>Scheme 2 </p>

<p>Figure 9. Limiting slope estimates of the contribution of S4 charges to the gating charge. Limiting slopes of WT Kv1.2 and the mutants 
R1Q, R1Q, R3N, and R4Q were measured from the normalized conductance obtained from slow voltage ramps. (A) Data for all four 
mutants. The color traces are the normalized conductance-voltage relationships of the mutants, and the black trace is the WT. The 
gray line is a fit to Eq. 7. (B) The average apparent charge obtained from data as in A, with the number of patches analyzed indicated 
in parentheses. Also included are data for limiting slope experiments for WT, R1Q, and R3N, for completeness. The error bars are the 
SEM. (C) The average fraction of WT charge for each neutralization, obtained from the voltage ramp data. The values are: 0.51, 0.83, 
0.82, and 0.86 for R1Q, R2Q, R3N, and R4Q, respectively. </p>



<p>Kv1.2 is less voltage dependent than Shaker </p>

<p>Specific role of S4 residues </p>

<p>The contribution of specific S4 charges to the total gat-
ing charge in Shaker has been examined previously 
using two different methods. Channels were counted by 
means of radiolabeled high affinity toxins (Aggarwal  and MacKinnon, 1996) or nonstationary noise analysis 
(Seoh et al., 1996). The first method counts channels 
that can bind the toxin but can underestimate the Q/N 
value if some channels bind toxin but do not contribute 
to the gating current, such as desensitized channels or 
channels that are down-regulated via phosphorylation 
or other mechanisms (O'Connell et al., 2010). Noise 
analysis can underestimate the number of channels if 
the data are sampled at low bandwidth. For heavily 
filtered data, the error can be as high as 10% (Alvarez  et al., 2002). Also, channel rundown can influence the 
channel number determination. In Shaker, both methods 
agreed on the size of the WT gating charge, although 
significant differences were found when studying S4 
charge neutralizations. 
Neutralization of the first arginine in the Shaker S4 
produced a reduction of the gating charge of 4 e o 
(Aggarwal and MacKinnon, 1996). Why does the neu-
tralization of R1 in Kv1.2 lead to a larger reduction of </p>

<p>both negative and positive, implicated in charge move-
ment and charge compensation within the membrane 
are conserved (Fig. 10), thus not providing a clue as to 
why Kv1.2 gating charge is reduced. Possible scenarios 
that could explain the difference include a smaller 
magnitude of the physical displacement of the Kv1.2 
voltage sensor. This would be consistent with the obser-
vation that Shaker channels have an 11-amino acid in-
sertion between S3b and S4 (Fig. 10), which modulates 
gating kinetics (Gonzalez et al., 2001) and possibly al-
lows a larger displacement in Shaker than in Kv1.2. We 
tested this hypothesis, but the Kv1.2 chimera with the 
Shaker linker did not produce functional channels. 
Another likely explanation is that the electric field 
across the Kv1.2 voltage sensor is less focused than in 
Shaker channels. In Shaker, estimates of the thickness of 
the septum or hydrophobic region across which the 
field is thought to be focused are in the order of 6-10 Å 
(Islas and Sigworth, 2001; Asamoah et al., 2003). In con-
trast, the MD simulations performed in Kv1.2/2.1 chi-
mera and the isolated VSD show that water can penetrate 
in outward-and inward-facing cavities, leaving a 15-17-Å 
hydrophobic region across which the field can be focused 
(Jogini and Roux, 2007; Ramsey et al., 2010). </p>

<p>Figure 10. Amino acid alignment of the S1, S2, and S4 regions of Kv1.2 and Shaker channels. The alignment shows the almost absolute 
conservation of positive (blue) and negative (red) charges shown to be involved in charge movement, salt-bridge formation, and charge-
to-charge interactions. The phenylalanine at position 274 (green), proposed to act as a charge transfer center, is also conserved and oc-
cupies the same position in both channels. The obvious difference between both channels is an eleven-amino acid insertion between the 
S3b and S4 in Shaker (orange). Nonconserved amino acids are highlighted in light purple. The inset shows a molecular model of Shaker 
(brown) superimposed on a model of Kv1.2 (yellow) based on the Kv1.2-2.1 chimera structure and showing the extra loop in Shaker. </p>

<p>Ishida et al. </p>





<p>charge, even beyond what would be maximally expected 
from the removal of four positive charges that cross the 
full membrane electric field? It seems inescapable that 
the mutation is also changing the structure of the initial 
closed and/or open state. It has been proposed that R1 
is close to the gating charge transfer center in the deac-
tivated state of the VSD (Tao et al., 2010; Lin et al.,  2011), which would suggest that its neutralization leads 
to destabilization of the initial closed state. Perhaps in 
our R1Q mutant, R2 moves up to occupy the original 
position of R1, leading to a smaller translation of S4 and 
thus further reducing the gating charge. 
Neutralization of the subsequent three charges of the 
VSD of Kv1.2 shows that they all have a similar contribu-
tion to the gating charge, as first described in Shaker 
channels. However, the fraction of the gating charge 
that is reduced by neutralization of R2, R3, and R4 is 
less than what is observed in Shaker mutants (Aggarwal  and MacKinnon, 1996), and markedly below the 4 e o 
that would be expected if the residues crossed the en-
tire membrane field. This observation is also consistent 
with a scenario where the hydrophobic septum of the 
VSD of Kv1.2 is thicker than in Shaker, as the same trans-
lational movement of the S4 helix in a less focused elec-
tric field would result in a reduction of the electrical 
distance traversed by each residue and, consequently, the 
gating charge. </p>

<p>We thank Tamara Rosenbaum for helpful discussions of this 
manuscript. 
This study was supported by PAPIIT grant IN212612-3 from 
Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico-Direccion General de 
Asuntos del Personal Academico-Programa de Apoyo a Proyectos 
de Investigacion e Inovacion Tecnologica (UNAM-DGAPA-PAPIIT) 
and CONACyT grant 151297 to L.D. Islas. I.G. Ishida was supported 
by an Undergraduate Fellowship from UNAM-DGAPA-PAPIIT. 
The authors declare no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Kenton J. Swartz served as editor. </p>

<p>Submitted: 10 October 2014 
Accepted: 17 February 2015 </p>







</text></tei>