<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4338086" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A canal wall down (CWD) tympanomastoidectomy is thought 
to be an effective procedure in treatment of chronic middle ear </p>

<p>disease, however, it has disadvantages regarding cavity problems 
such as continuous ear drainage (range, 20% to 60%) [1], accu-
mulation of keratin debris, frequent vertigo attacks following 
temperature or pressure change, and difficulty in fitting a hear-
ing aid. In addition, the final hearing gained after staged ossicu-
loplasies in patients who have undergone CWD is usually 5-10 
dB worse than the patients who have undergone canal wall up 
(CWU) tympanomastoidectomy due to its ineffective sound 
transmission [2,3]. 
Various techniques of mastoid obliteration or canal wall re-
construction have been reported to overcome cavity problems. 
Several kinds of muscular flap [4,5], fat [6], cortical bone pate 
[7], hydroxylappatite [8], β-tricalcium phosphate and polyphos-
phate [9], demineralized bone matrix [10,11] and silicone blocks 
[12] are used. However, all of these techniques have its advan-
tages and disadvantages. Bone pate is restricted by its insuffi-
cient amount in material and it is vulnerability to infection </p>

<p>• Received October 16, 2013 
Revised January 8, 2014 
Accepted February 3, 2014 </p>

<p>• Corresponding author: Hyong-Ho Cho 
Department Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Chonnam National 
University Hospital, Chonnam National University Medical School, 
42 Jebong-ro, Dong-gu, Gwangju 501-757, Korea 
Tel: +82-62-220-6770, Fax: +82-62-228-7743 
E-mail: victocho@hanmail.net </p>

<p>• Co-corresponding author: Yong Beom Cho 
Department Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Chonnam National 
University Hospital, Chonnam National University Medical School, 
42 Jebong-ro, Dong-gu, Gwangju 501-757, Korea 
Tel: +82-62-220-6770, Fax: +82-62-228-7743 
E-mail: choyb@chonnam.ac.kr </p>

<p>pISSN 1976-8710 eISSN 2005-0720 </p>

<p>Donor-Site Morbidity Following Minimally Invasive 
Costal Cartilage Harvest Technique </p>

<p>Hyung Chae Yang·Hyong-Ho Cho·Si Young Jo·Chul Ho Jang·Yong Beom Cho </p>

<p>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Chonnam National University Medical School, Gwangju, Korea </p>

<p>Objectives. Autologous costal cartilage is a promising alternative for mastoid obliteration. However, donor-site morbidities 
of the chest wall limit the use of this graft. To address this issue, we have developed a minimally-invasive technique of 
harvesting costal cartilage and report donor site morbidity associated with the procedure. </p>

<p>Methods. Donor site morbidities were evaluated for 151 patients who underwent costal cartilage harvest, canal wall down 
mastoidectomy, and mastoid obliteration. Pain and cosmetic concern were evaluated via visual analogue scale (VAS). 
Scars were evaluated via the modified Vancouver Scar Scale (VSS) and the Patient and Observer Scar Assessment 
Scale (POSAS). Postoperative complications were assessed during the follow-up period. </p>

<p>Results. The mean duration of noticeable pain was 5.3 days post operation. The mean VAS score for pain was 3.0 of 10 on 
the first day after the operation and gradually declined. At the 6 months post operation, the mean VAS cosmetic score 
at the costal cartilage harvest site was 0.6 of 10. The mean VSS score was 9.5 out of 10 total, and the mean POSAS 
score was 23.27 out of 110 total. </p>

<p>Conclusion. The minimally-invasive chopped costal cartilage harvest technique resulted in acceptable pain, cosmetic con-
cern, and postoperative complications for most patients. There were no major postoperative complications. Costal 
cartilage is an acceptable donor for mastoid obliteration in canal wall down mastoidectomy, especially in the context 
of the extremely low donor site morbidity of the minimally-invasive technique presented in the study. </p>

<p>Keywords. Pain, Postoperative; Pain Measurement; Otologic Surgical Procedures; Cartilage; Tissue and Organ Procurement </p>



<p>[13,14]. Fat and muscular flaps have unpredictable absorption 
rate over the time [6]. Synthetic materials are limited by the 
need for vascularized flap coverage, infection, incomplete osteo-
intergration, and late extrusion [15]. Black [13] reported that 
autologous cartilage is excellent material for canal reconstruc-
tion and mastoid obliteration. However, he reported that inade-
quate amount for filler work from the ear locality and complica-
tion risk from the costal supplies limited its appeal as filler [13]. 
Autologous costal cartilage has been widely used in otolaryn-
gologic surgery. It is an excellent source of grafting material for 
the rhinoplasty [16], auricular reconstruction [17], and laryngo-
tracheal reconstructions [18]. However, as Black [13] men-
tioned, conventional costal cartilage harvest techniques which 
were commonly used in those procedures can cause complica-
tions such as pneumothorax, chest wall deformity, seroma for-
mation, persistent pain, infection, and keloid formation [16,19]. 
In addition, donor-site morbidities after costal cartilage harvest 
make it an invasive procedure and limit its usage. 
To use the costal cartilage as a mastoid obliteration material, 
surgeons should overcome the morbidity of costal cartilage har-
vest procedure. So, we present a minimally invasive costal carti-
lage harvest technique to address the complications associated 
with costal cartilage harvest. A minimally invasive costal carti-
lage harvest procedure preserves the all perichondria and har-
vest only required amount for mastoid obliteration. In addition, 
there is remnant cartilage which can gives the structural stability 
to costal cartilage. </p>

<p>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the donor site morbid-
ity of newly developed costal cartilage harvest technique and to 
see whether the morbidity of this technique can be accepted by 
surgeon and the patient or not. It is an important first step 
whether costal cartilage can be used, as an alternative material 
for mastoid obliteration and reconstruction of posterior ear ca-
nal wall or not. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patients </p>

<p>A retrospective review of patient records was performed for a 
consecutive series of 151 patients who underwent CWD mas-
toidectomy and mastoid obliteration using costal cartilage in the 
treatment of chronic otitis media. The study was approved by 
the Institutional Review Board at Chonnam National University 
Hospital (No. CNUH-2013-120). </p>

<p>Surgical technique for costal cartilage harvest and mastoid 
obliteration </p>

<p>Autologous costal cartilage harvest procedure and tympanomas-
toidectomy were carried out simultaneously. Right costal carti-
lages were preferred to differentiate postoperative pains from 
potential angina symptoms. A 1.5-to 4-cm-sized incision was 
made over the seventh costal cartilage just inferior to the infra-
mammary crease (Fig. 1A). Subcutaneous and fascial layers </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Mastoid obliteration with chopped costal cartilage. (A) Costal cartilage was harvested from the 7th rib. Note that perichondrial layers of 
lower and inferior portions are preserved. (B) Newly devised instruments for costal cartilage harvest. (C) Immediate postoperative photograph 
of costal cartilage harvest site demonstrates a 1.5-cm incision upon closure. (D) Costal cartilage is prepared by a bone mill. (E) A mastoidec-
tomized cavity before mastoid obliteration. (F) An intraoperative photograph shows a mastoidectomized cavity obliterated with chopped cos-
tal cartilage. </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>D 
E 
F </p>

<p>Yang HC et al. Minimally Invasive Costal Cartilage Harvest 15 </p>

<p>were dissected down to the level of external oblique muscles. 
The muscle fibers were bluntly divided to identify the costal 
cartilage. The overlying perichondrium was incised longitudinal-
ly along the midline of costal cartilage axis. Using a newly de-
vised cartilage gouge (Fig. 1B), a portion of upper central costal 
cartilage was harvested. Cartilage and perichondrium of lateral 
and inferior locations was left intact. The competency of pleura 
was evaluated by the absence of air bubbles from a pool of nor-
mal saline in the donor site. Upon hemostasis, the donor site 
was closed by layers, including the perichondrial layer (Fig. 1C). 
The harvested cartilage was ground with a bone mill (Quentin 
Bone mill, Quentin Dental products, Leimen, Germany) (Fig. 
1D) and were set aside in physiologic saline solution. After 
CWD mastoidectomy (Fig. 1E), the disease-free mastoidecto-
mized cavity was obliterated with the prepared autologous cos-</p>

<p>tal cartilage (Fig. 1F) and fibrin-based adhesive (Greenplast, 
Green Cross, Seoul, Korea). The retroauricular wound was closed 
in the standard fashion. </p>

<p>Donor site morbidity evaluation </p>

<p>The overall perception and attitude to the costal cartilage har-
vest technique was evaluated first. Additionally, donor site mor-
bidity was checked in the framework of postoperative pain, pa-
tient-centric cosmetic concern, scar evaluation, and of other 
complications. The retroauricular skin incision sites were com-
pared with costal cartilage harvest incision sites. </p>

<p>Pain </p>

<p>Postoperative pain was assessed by a questionnaire, which in-
cluded a 10-cm visual analogue scale (VAS Pain) (Table 1). A </p>

<p>Table 2. The variables and scores of Modified Vancouver Scar Scale in the study population at the postoperative 6 months </p>

<p>Variable 
Score range 
Description 
No. of patients (n=51) 
Mean±SD 
Score 0 
Score 1 
Score 2 </p>

<p>Scar quality 
0-2 
0, poor; 1, satisfactory; 2, good 
3 
8 
40 
1.72±0.57 
Length of donor defect 
0-2 
0, poor; 1, satisfactory; 2, good 
1 
4 
46 
1.88±0.38 
Depth 
0-2 
0, poor; 1, satisfactory; 2, good 
0 
0 
51 
2.00±0.00 
Deformity 
0-1 
0, significant; 1, none 
2 
49 
-
0.96±0.20 
Contour change 
0-1 
0, significant; 1, none 
0 
51 
-
1.00±0.00 
Tender 
0-1 
0, significant; 1, none 
0 
51 
-
1.00±0.00 
Clicking 
0-1 
0, significant; 1, none 
0 
51 
-
1.00±0.00 </p>

<p>Table 1. Pain and scar assessment scales and scores used in the study </p>

<p>Scale 
Score range 
Description 
Chest score* Ear score </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>Visual analogue scale 
Pain 
0-10 
0, no pain; 10, worst pain 
0.80±1.25 
1.48±1.86 &lt;0.001 
Cosmetic 
0-10 
0, best; 10, worst 
0.62±1.22 
0.68±1.28 0.421 
Patient and observer scar assessment scale 
POSAS 
11-110 11 to 110, 'excellent' to 'poor' 
23.17±12.47 19.43±6.81 0.055 
PSAS 
6-60 
11.07±8.07 
8.23±4.20 0.017 
Pain 
1-10 
1, no complaints; 10, worst imaginable 
1.23±0.57 
1.20±0.55 0.655 
Itching 
1-10 
1, no complaints; 10, worst imaginable 
1.37±0.76 
1.40±0.72 0.794 
Color 
1-10 
1, as normal skin; 10, very different 
2.77±2.47 
1.50±1.16 0.003 
Stiffness 
1-10 
1, as normal skin; 10, very different 
1.90±2.06 
1.53±1.19 0.233 
Thickness 
1-10 
1, as normal skin; 10, very different 
2.20±2.46 
1.33±0.84 0.028 
Irregular 
1-10 
1, as normal skin; 10, very different 
1.60±1.19 
1.26±0.64 0.175 
OSAS 
5-50 
12.10±4.80 11.20±3.27 0.273 
Vascularization 
1-10 
1, normal skin; 10, worst scar imaginable 
3.23±1.07 
3.40±1.00 0.349 
Pigmentation 
1-10 
1, normal skin; 10, worst scar imaginable 
2.83±0.60 
2.90±1.03 0.819 
Thickness 
1-10 
2.36±1.96 
1.90±1.34 0.306 
Relief 
1-10 
1.77±1.50 
1.43±0.86 0.168 
Pliability 
1-10 
1.90±1.21 
1.57±0.90 0.210 
Mexameter 
Erythema 
0-999 A higher value representing more melanin or erythema 
421±99.2 
437±99.9 0.150 
Pigmentation 
0-999 A higher value representing more melanin or erythema 
178±54.0 
185±92.8 0.860 </p>

<p>Scores were estimated at the postoperative 6 months. Values are presented as mean±SD. POSAS, patient and observer scar assessment 
scale; PSAS, patient scar assessment scale; OSAS, observer scar assessment scale. 
*Chest score denotes mean score of costal cartilage harvest site. </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Ear score denote mean score of retroauricular skin incision site. </p>



<p>score of 10 indicated the worst pain conceivable, and a score 0 
indicated no pain. Out of the 151 patients, 52 male and 83 fe-
male patients (n=135) with ages ranging from 22 to 80 years 
answered the questionnaire. Patients evaluated pain on postop-
erative days 1, 2, 3, 7, 30, 60, and 180. In addition to VAS Pain 
score, the duration of physical suffering were also asked in the 
questionnaire. </p>

<p>Scar </p>

<p>Similarly to the pain assessment, cosmetic concerns were as-
sessed on 10-cm VAS within the same questionnaire (VAS cos-
metic). A score of 10 indicated the poorest cosmetic outcome 
conceivable, and a score 0 indicated no cosmetic problem. VAS 
Cosmetic score of costal cartilage harvest sites were compared 
to that of the retroauricular skin incision site. 
Additionally, the incisional scars were assessed according to 
the modified Vancouver Scar Scale (VSS) [20] and the Patient 
and Observer Scar Assessment Scale (POSAS) [21]. The VSS en-
capsulated multiple factors, including pain, clicking sound, scar 
length, depth, and scar consistency and provided a numerical 
reflection of donor-site quality (Table 2). A score of 10 indicated 
an excellent donor site, and a score of 0 indicated the worst pos-
sible scar. 
The POSAS were evaluated for 30 patients at 6 months post 
operation. It consists of two numeric scales: the Patients Scar As-
sessment Scale (patients scale, PSAS) which is to be completed 
by the patient, and the Observer Scar Assessment Scale (observ-
er scale, OSAS) which is to be completed by the physician (Table 
1) [21]. A score of 11 indicated a normal skin, and score 110 in-
dicated the worst scar imaginable. The POSAS scores were com-
pared between the costal cartilage harvest site and the retroau-
ricular skin incision site. 
In addition to VAS and POSAS assessments, a skin color meter 
(Mexameter MX18, CK electronic, Cologne, Germany) was used 
for objective scar evaluation. Erythema and pigmentation levels </p>

<p>were assessed for 30 patients 6 months post operation (Table 1). </p>

<p>Donor site complication </p>

<p>Surgical complications of costal cartilage harvest were evaluated 
during the follow-up period in terms of contour deformity, pneu-
mothorax, seroma formation, keloid formation and surgical site 
infection. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">PASW</rs> ver. <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">18.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA). Continuous variables were presented as 
mean±SD. The paired t-test was used to compare normally dis-
tributed data, and the Wilcoxon signed-rank test was used other-
wise. Two-sided P-values of less than 0.05 indicated statistical 
significance. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Of the 155 patients, 135 completed the questionnaire for pain 
and cosmetic concern (53 males and 83 females). The mean age 
was 48.6±13.7 years (range, 22 to 80 years) (Fig. 2). Additional-
ly, the number of patients who had been assessed with VSS, PO-
SAS, and Mexameter was 51, 30 and 30, respectively. </p>

<p>Overall perceptions and attitudes to the procedure </p>

<p>One hundred and ten patients (85.3%) responded that costal 
cartilage harvest procedure was an acceptable method, while 19 
patients (14.7%) considered the procedure as uncomfortable. 
One hundred and nine out of 133 patients (82.0%) answered to 
reuse the costal cartilage if they have to redo the ear surgery. 
One hundred and twenty-four out of 133 patients (93.2%) an-
swer to donate their cartilage to the child for homologous graft, 
if their child need CWD and mastoid obliteration. </p>

<p>20-29 30-39 40-49 50-59 60-69 70-79 ≥80 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Age group (year) </p>

<p>Number of patients </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Age-sex distribution of the study population. Four young 
women are included in this study. </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
7 
180 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Time (day) 
Pain VAS score out of 10 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Visual analogue scale (VAS) pain score of the study patients. 
The VAS pain score gradually decreased to 0.9 by 180 days after 
operation. A score of 10 indicates the worst pain imaginable, and a 
score of 0 indicates no pain. Solid line indicates mean VAS pain 
score. Error bar indicates standard deviation. </p>

<p>Yang HC et al. Minimally Invasive Costal Cartilage Harvest 17 </p>

<p>Pain </p>

<p>None of the patients in this study required patient-controlled an-
algesia (PCA) for postoperative pain management. VAS pain 
score for the costal cartilage harvest site was 3.0±2.5 on postop-
erative day 1 and dropped gradually during the follow-up period. 
At 6 months post operation, the mean VAS pain score for costal 
cartilage harvest site was 0.9±1.3 (Fig. 3). The pain at the costal 
cartilage harvest site using the minimally-invasive technique was 
significantly less than that at the retroauricular skin incision site 
at 6 months (Table 1). The mean duration of noticeable postoper-
ative pain was 5.3±9.46 days. At 1 month post operation, only 
three out of the 133 patients experienced physical suffering. At 2 
months, none of the patient reported physical suffering. </p>

<p>Scar </p>

<p>The length of incision was from 1.5 to 4 cm, and the mean scar 
length was 2.5 cm. This incision provided accesses adequate 
enough for 3 to 5 cm 
3 of costal cartilage harvest volume. The 
volume of costal cartilage needed to obliterate the mastoidecto-
mized cavity ranged from 1.2 to 4 cm </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>. 
On the questionnaire regarding cosmetic concern at 6 months 
post operation, the mean VAS cosmetic scores were 0.6 and 0.7 
for costal cartilage harvest site and retroauricular skin incision 
site, respectively. There were no statistically significant differenc-
es between these two sites (Table 1). Of the 100 patients who re-
sponded to this portion of the questionnaire, VAS cosmetic score 
greater than 3 for five patients, all of whom were female patients. 
The VSS score on postoperative day 1 was 8.3±1.2, and this 
gradually increased to 9.5±1.0 by 6 months post operation. All 
of the patients gave highest score for four out of the total 7 vari-
ables (depth, contour change, tenderness, clicking) (Table 2). Out 
of the 51 patients, 39 patients had scored 10 of 10, which repre-
sented the best result imaginable. There was no patient who 
scored 5 or less on this scale. 
The mean POSAS score was 23.17±12.47. The mean OSAS 
score was 12.10±4.80, with a mean PSAS score of 11.07±8.07 
at 6 months post operation. The POSAS (P=0.063) and OSAS 
(P =0.230) values were not significantly different between the 
two sites. However, the PSAS scores were significantly different 
between the two incision sites (P=0.035) (Table 1). 
The mean erythema values, as measured by mexameter, were 
422 and 437 for costal cartilage harvest site and retroauricular 
skin incision site, respectively (P =0.401). The mean pigmenta-
tion were 179 and 186 for costal cartilage harvest site and retro-
auricular skin incision site, respectively (P=0.683). The erythe-
ma and pigmentation levels were not significantly different be-
tween the donor and recipient sites (Table 1). </p>

<p>Donor site complication </p>

<p>Out of 151 patients, three patients experienced wound dehis-
cence, which was managed with wound dressing. None of the 
patients reported clicking sound or contour deformity on their </p>

<p>chest. There was no case of hematoma. One patient did develop 
keloid formation. Otherwise, there were no major complica-
tions, such as pneumothorax, atelectasis, chest wall deformity, 
or massive bleeding. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Overall perceptions and attitudes to the procedure </p>

<p>To see the overall perceptions and attitudes to the procedure, 
we had asked 3 simple questions. "What is your overall percep-
tion to costal cartilage harvest procedure? Is this relatively com-
fort as a procedure?" "If you have to redo the ear surgery, are 
you willing to use the rib cartilage for mastoid obliteration 
again?" "If your child needs CWD and mastoid obliteration sur-
gery are you willing to donate your rib cartilage for homologous 
graft?" Majorities of the patients satisfied with these procedures. 
However this study was done to Korean with chronic otitis me-
dia. Korean tends to sufficiently dressed than the Westerner due 
to their cultural characteristic, and most of the patients' ages 
tend to be above the marriageable age. The patients seemed to 
have relatively less cosmetic burden to the chest scar. </p>

<p>Pain </p>

<p>Pain is the most common complication after a costal cartilage 
harvest procedure [22,23]. The VAS is a simple and often used 
method for evaluating variations in pain intensity. It is superior 
to fixed interval scales, relative pain scales, and verbal reports of 
pain, and its usefulness in pain evaluation has been validated by 
several studies [24-26]. 
Postoperative pain has been reported to peak at 7 days after 
the conventional costal cartilage harvest technique [19]. In this 
study, most patients reported that postoperative pain slightly af-
fected their daily activity in the first two postoperative days, 
while none of the patients required PCA. Postoperative pain 
was most severe on day 1, at 2.9 out of the 10 VAS scale, and 
decreased rapidly after day 2 (Fig. 3). On postoperative day 7, 
most patients reported no significant pain which interfered with 
daily activities. This may be due to the preservation of pericho-
drial layer and the use of minimally-invasive technique. 
In the study of postoperative pain after conventional harvest 
method, notwithstanding the use of bupivacaine infusion, the 
mean VAS pain score was 3 in the immediate postoperative pe-
riod, which increased to 7 by day 7. Out of 39 patients in the 
study, six experienced persistent pain at the 3-month point [19]. 
The present study, the mean duration of noticeable pain was 
5.3 days, after which patients usually regarded the pain as mi-
nor or nonexistence. At the time 2 months post operation, no 
patients had reported noticeable pain. Compared to the pain 
studied after the conventional method [19], our technique 
causes less postoperative pain with shorter pain duration. </p>



<p>Scar </p>

<p>The mean incision length from this study was one-third that of 
conventional costal cartilage harvest method [19]. Contour de-
formity or depth changes were uncommon, considering the 
smaller incisions, minimal invasive maneuvers, and preservation 
of perichondrial layer. The mean VAS Cosmetic score was 0.6 
for the costal incision site, which was less than that for the retro-
auricular skin incision site. 
Adding to the VAS cosmetic score, the VSS and POSAS scales 
were used for scar assessment. Several versions of VSS exist and 
this study adopted the version which was modified by Uppal et 
al. [19]. The VSS encapsulates multiple factors, including length, 
depth, and consistency of the scar, to numerically reflect the 
quality of incisional scar at the donor site (Table 1). In this study, 
the VSS score was 8.3±1.2 on postoperative day 1 and gradual-
ly increased to 9.5±1.0 by 24 weeks post operation. As a score 
of 10 indicates an excellent donor site while a score of 0 indi-
cates the worst possible, the 24-week score represented ex-
tremely satisfactory donor site outcomes (Fig. 4). Although a di-
rect comparison is not possible, the VSS scores were reported to 
be 2 and 8.5 on days 1 and 90 post operation in the study on 
conventional costal cartilage harvest technique [19]. These find-
ings suggest that the minimally-invasive technique presented has 
resulted in more acceptable scars than that after the convention-
al harvest procedure. 
The POSAS was known to be a more useful subjective tool 
than VSS for linear scar evaluation [23]. In this study, the mean 
POSAS scores was 23.17 out of 110 total, with a mean OSAS 
score of 12.10 out of 50 total and a mean PSAS score of 11.07 
out of 60 total. As the smallest possible score of 11 indicates a 
normal skin and the maximum score 110 indicates the worst 
scar imaginable, the findings of our study represents high level 
of cosmetic satisfaction from patients who underwent the mini-
mally-invasive harvest technique. </p>

<p>The Mexameter is narrow-band spectrophotometry device 
and measures the extent of vascularization and pigmentation 
based on the differences in light absorption of red and green 
light by hemoglobin and melanin, respectively. In this study, the 
Mexameter was used for two purposes. First, for the sake of ob-
jectivity in scoring, the authors score the vascularity and pig-
mentation of OSAS according to Mexameter value. Second, the 
Mexameter values were compared between the costal cartilage 
harvest site and the retroauricular skin incision site, which re-
vealed no significant difference across the two surgical incisions. 
A direct comparison of morbidities between the minimally-in-
vasive and conventional costal cartilage harvest techniques 
would have been ideal. However, the authors of the study be-
lieve that to perform conventional costal cartilage harvest tech-
niques is perhaps unethical, considering the clinical experiences 
with the minimally invasive technique. To overcome this limita-
tion, we have adopted various kinds of scar evaluation scales, 
such as VAS, VSS, POSAS, and Mexameter assessments. In addi-
tion to various scar scales, we have compared the costal carti-
lage harvest site to the retroauricular skin incision site. 
VAS pain, VAS cosmetic, Mexameter assessments, POSAS 
and OSAS scores were not significantly different between the 
two sites. However, the PSAS score of costal cartilage harvest 
site was significantly lower than that of retroauricular skin inci-
sion site. We have wondered why some patients scored the cos-
tal cartilage harvest site lower, even though they had answered 
that the overall cosmetic burden of costal cartilage harvest site 
was less than that of retroauricular skin incision site. We specu-
late that this discrepancy arises from the difference in a patient's 
ability to make first-hand observations of the costal cartilage 
harvest site, where a close observation of the retroauricular site 
is difficult. Similar values which were evaluated by observer 
(OSAS) had no statistically significant difference. </p>

<p>Surgical complication </p>

<p>The postoperative complications after the minimally-invasive 
was less than that reported for conventional costal cartilage har-
vest. Additionally, there were no major complications to report, 
due to the minimal invasiveness of the operation. 
In conclusion, the minimally-invasive chopped costal cartilage 
harvest technique resulted in acceptable pain, cosmetic concern, 
and postoperative complications for most patients. We believe 
that costal cartilage is an acceptable donor for mastoid oblitera-
tion in CWD mastoidectomy, especially in the context of the 
extremely low donor site morbidity of the minimally-invasive 
technique presented in the study. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was re-
ported. </p>

<p>Time (day) </p>

<p>1 
7 
30 
120 
180 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
Modified Vancouver Scar Scale </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Modified Vancouver Scar Scale (VSS) score of the study pa-
tients. A VSS score of 10 indicates an excellent donor site, and a 
score of 0 indicates the worst donor site possible. The VSS score 
improved over the follow-up period and is relatively close to the 
highest (optimal) score by 180 days post operation. Solid line indi-
cates mean score. Error bar indicates standard deviation. </p>

<p>Yang HC et al. Minimally Invasive Costal Cartilage Harvest 19 </p>



</text></tei>