<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4513598" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Background and purpose -Supine computed tomography 
scanogram (CTS) is a commonly used alternative to weight bear-
ing long leg plain radiograph (LLR) in measuring knee align-
ment. No published studies have validated its use in the native 
knee and the post-unicompartmental replacement knee (UKR). 
We quantified the difference in measurements obtained from CTS 
and LLR for knee alignment. 
Patients and methods -Supine CT scanograms and weight 
bearing long leg plain anteroposterior radiographs were obtained 
for 40 knees (in 25 patients), 17 of which were native, and 23 of 
which were post-UKR. The mechanical and anatomical axes of 
the tibio-femoral joint were measured. Bland-Altman plots were 
used to calculate the 1.96 standard deviation limits of agreement 
between CTS and LLR. Intraclass correlation was used to assess 
intra-rater and inter-rater reliability (where values &gt; 0.81 indi-
cate very good reliability). 
Results -CTS and LLR were equally reliable in measurement 
of the mechanical and anatomical axes of the tibio-femoral joint 
(intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) &gt; 0.9 for all parameters). 
Statistically significant and clinically relevant differences were 
found between CTS and LLR in measurement of the mechanical 
axis (limits of agreement: UKR −3.2° to 6.3°; native −3.2° to 5.6°) 
and the anatomical axis (limits of agreement: UKR −3.7° to 8.7°; 
native −2.0° to 8.8°). 
Interpretation -Although it is a reliable tool, CTS is not neces-
sarily an accurate one for measurement of knee alignment when 
compared to LLR. We recommend that CTS should not be used 
as a substitute for LLR in measurement of the mechanical or ana-
tomical axes of the knee. </p>

<p> </p>

<p>Measurement of knee alignment is useful in planning of 
operative intervention including high tibial osteotomy (HTO), 
uncompartmental knee replacement (UKR), and total knee 
replacement (TKR), and in the assessment of postoperative 
outcomes (Hernigou and Deschamps 2004, Hardeman et 
al. 2012, Kyung et al. 2013, Pietsch et al. 2013, Chen et al. 
2014). The degree of accuracy required is thought to be ± 5° 
for native knees (Sharma et al. 2011), ± 3° after TKR (Bathis 
et al. 2004), and ± 2.5° after UKR (Gulati et al. 2009, Weale 
et al. 2000). 
The weight bearing long leg anteroposterior radiograph 
(LLR) shows loss of cartilage space and ligament laxity, and 
is therefore thought to be the best method for the measurement 
of coronal alignment of the knee (Babazadeh et al. 2013). 
However, some feel that the supine LLR is more suitable for 
planning in HTO (Ogata et al. 1991, Brouwer et al. 2003). 
Several recent papers have used the 2-D supine CT scano-
gram/scout film (CTS) to assess knee alignment (Moon et al. 
2012, Kyung et al. 2013, Bugbee et al. 2013). Clinicians are 
also using this modality in clinical practice. CTS is severely 
limited by being a non-weight bearing modality in addition 
to having the same limitations as LLR (i.e. influence of rota-
tional malalignment and flexion deformity). 
Brouwer et al. (2003) compared standing and supine LLR, 
but patients were excluded if they were unable to stand on one 
leg, if they had had previous surgery, or if they had a clinical 
malalignment. Gbejuade et al. (2014) compared CTS and LLR 
after TKR; however, weight bearing may not be as important a 
factor in measurement of alignment after TKR. 
The present study is the first to determine the differences in 
knee alignment measurement between CTS and LLR in native 
knees and after UKR. </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (4): 440-443 </p>



<p>methods </p>

<p>Ethics approval was obtained for the analysis of joint imaging 
in 25 patients who had undergone UKR in a previous com-
puter navigation study (Cobb et al. 2006, REC 03/0087). 
Each patient underwent conventional CTS of the limb 
(patient lying supine, patellae pointing toward the ceiling) 
and LLR (patient standing erect with patellae facing forward, 
X-ray beam centered on knee). Images were rejected for anal-
ysis if they appeared to be significantly rotated. This gave us 
a sample size of 40 knees in total, consisting of 23 UKRs and 
17 native knees. 
Axes were defined according to Paley (2002). Mechani-
cal knee alignment (MA) was measured by comparing the </p>

<p>mechanical axis of the femur (center of femoral head to mid-
point of femoral surgical epicondyles) with the mechanical 
axis of the tibia (center of tibial spines to center of talus). 
Anatomical knee alignment (AA) was measured by compar-
ing the anatomical axis of the femur (using a line connecting 
3 midpoints of the femoral shaft) with the anatomical axis of 
the tibia (the same as the mechanical axis). This is shown for 
LLR and CTS in Figure 1. </p>

<p>Statistics 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">MedCalc</rs> for Windows (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MedCalc Software</rs>, Ostend, Belgium) 
was used for statistical analysis. 
Reliability was assessed using 10 randomly selected paired 
scans, each measured in triplicate by 2 independent observ-
ers at different times. Intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) 
scores showed highly reliable intra-rater and inter-rater reli-
ability for all measurements using CTS and LLR (defined by 
ICC &gt; 0.81 according to guidance set out by Altman, 1990) 
(Table). 
The correlation between CTS and LLR was quantified using 
Pearson's correlation coefficient. Paired-samples t-tests were 
used to assess the statistical significance of the mean difference 
seen in measurements between CTS and LLR. The agreement 
between CTS and LLR was quantified using Bland-Altman 
plots, demonstrated by 1.96 standard deviation limits of agree-
ment (LOA). These plots are shown in Figures 2-5. </p>

<p>results </p>

<p>UKR mechanical axis (Figure 2) 
The mean measurement in this group was 2.9° varus (SD 5.3) 
for LLR and 4.4° varus (SD 3.8) for CTS. The mean differ-
ence was 1.5° (95% CI: 0.47-2.57; p = 0.007). 
The correlation coefficient r was 0.91 (95% CI: 0.80-0.96; p 
&lt; 0.001). 8 of 23 measurements were more than 2.5° different. </p>

<p>UKR anatomical axis (Figure 3) 
The mean measurement in this group was 3.4° valgus (SD 5.6) 
for LLR and 0.89° valgus (SD 5.1) for CTS. The mean differ-
ence was 2.5° (95% CI: 1.2-3.9; p &lt; 0.001). 
The correlation coefficient r was 0.83 (95% CI: 0.63-0.93; p 
&lt; 0.001). 15 of 23 measurements were more than 2.5° different. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Measurements of knee alignment: mechanical axis for LLR 
(a) and CTS (b); anatomical axis for LLR (c) and CTS (d). </p>

<p>Intraclass correlation coefficient reliability measurements (with 95% confidence intervals) </p>

<p>Mechanical knee alignment 
Anatomical knee alignment 
LLR 
CTS 
LLR 
CTS </p>

<p>Intra-rater 
0.97 (0.93-0.99) 
0.97 (0.92-0.99) 
0.98 (0.94-0.99) 
0.99 (0.98-1.00) 
Inter-rater 
0.97 (0.89-0.99) 
0.91 (0.57-0.98) 
0.98 (0.90-0.99) 
0.93 (0.75-0.98) </p>



<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (4): 440-443 </p>

<p>Native knee mechanical axis (Figure 4) 
The mean measurement in this group was 4.2° varus (SD 4.3) 
for LLR and 5.4° varus (SD 3.6) for CTS. The mean differ-
ence was 1.2° (95% CI: 0.08-2.4; p = 0.04). 
The correlation coefficient r was 0.85 (95% CI: 0.63-0.95; 
p &lt; 0.001). 1 of 17 measurements was more than 5° different. </p>

<p>Native knee anatomical axis (Figure 5) 
The mean measurement in this group was 2.3° valgus (SD 4.0) 
for LLR, and 1.4° varus (SD 4.3) for CTS. The mean difference 
was 3.4° (95% CI: 1.9-4.8; two-tailed probability p &lt; 0.001). 
The correlation coefficient r was 0.78 (95% CI: 0.49-0.92; 
p &lt; 0.001). 4 of 17 measurements were more than 5° different. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>We found that measurements of knee alignment using CTS 
and LLR were statistically significantly different (in the native 
and post-UKR knee). </p>

<p>Given that differences of ± 5° from neutral for native knees 
are thought to be important in terms of disease progression 
(Sharma et al. 2011), our results that 6-24% of measurements 
differed by more than 5° are potentially clinically significant. 
Given that differences of ± 2.5° for UKR are used to deter-
mine the accuracy of implant positioning in research (Gulati et 
al. 2009, Weale et al. 2000), our results that 39-65% of mea-
surements differed by more than 2.5° are potentially clinically 
significant. 
We found a mean difference of 1.2° to 3.4° more valgus in 
CTS than in LLR. Brouwer et al. (2003) evaluated supine LLR 
with weight bearing LLR in 20 patients, and found a mean of 
2° more varus in the weight bearing LLR than in the supine 
LLR. Patients were exluded from Brouwer's analysis if valgus 
alignment was identified on clinical examination, which may 
partly explain the difference in results. 
Gbejuade et al. (2014) compared weight bearing LLR with 
supine CTS in 24 patients after TKR, and found good overall 
agreement in measurement of the mechanical axis angle but a 
substantial under-detection of malalignment (&gt; 5°) in the CTS </p>

<p>Figure 2. Bland-Altman plot of the differences in measurement of 
mechanical knee alignment between CTS and LLR (UKR). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Bland-Altman plot of the differences in measurement of ana-
tomical knee alignment between CTS and LLR (UKR). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Bland-Altman plot of the differences in measurement of 
mechanical knee alignment between CTS and LLR (native knee). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Bland-Altman plot of the differences in measurement of ana-
tomical knee alignment between CTS and LLR (native knee). </p>

<p>CTs -llr (°) </p>

<p>mean of CTs and llr (°) </p>

<p>CTs -llr (°) </p>

<p>mean of CTs and llr (°) </p>

<p>mean of CTs and llr (°) </p>

<p>CTs -llr (°) </p>

<p>mean of CTs and llr (°) </p>

<p>CTs -llr (°) </p>

<p>Acta Orthopaedica 2015; 86 (4): 440-443 </p>



<p>group. They therefore advised caution in the use of CTS for 
measurement of knee alignment in patients after TKR. 
Emerging technologies such as the EOS 2D/3D imaging 
system have the potential to image the weight bearing limb 
with simultaneous AP and lateral images, low radiation doses, 
and 3D reconstruction. Currently, however, the National Insti-
tute for Health and Clinical Excellence does not recommend 
its routine use in the National Health Service (NHS) due to a 
lack of clinical evidence to quantify the extent of patient ben-
efits (NICE Diagnostics Guidance DG1, 2011). 
In summary, supine CT scanogram, when compared to the 
reference standard of weight bearing long leg radiographic 
measurement of knee alignment, had similar precision (repeat-
ability/interobserver error), but poor accuracy (closeness to 
the true value as measured by weight bearing long leg radio-
graph). We therefore recommend that it should not be used 
as a substitute for long leg weight bearing plain radiographs 
in measurement of the mechanical axis or anatomical axis of 
the knee. </p>



</text></tei>