<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4616535" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: To date, the role of invariant natural killer T (iNKT) cells in </p>

<p>chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection is not fully understood. In 
previous reports, iNKT cells were identified by indirect methods. 
However, discrepancies regarding the prevalence and function of iNKT 
cells during HBV infection were observed. 
In this study, we have devised a direct, highly specific CD1d 
tetramer-based methodology to test whether patients with HBV infec-
tion have associated iNKT-cell defects. In our study, a total of 93 
chronic HBV-infected patients and 30 healthy individuals (as control) 
were enrolled. The prevalence of iNKT cells, their cytokine producing 
capacity, and in vitro expansion were determined by flow cytometric 
analysis with CD1d tetramer staining. 
Our observation demonstrated that there was no significant differ-
ence in circulating CD1d-tetramer positive iNKT cell numbers between 
HBV-infected patients and healthy controls. The capacity of iNKT cells 
to produce IFN-g or IL-4 as well as their in vitro expansion was also 
comparable between these 2 groups. However, among chronic HBV-
infected patients, a decrease in iNKT cell-number was observed in 
chronic hepatitis B (CHB) and cirrhosis patients in comparison to that in 
immune tolerant (IT) patients. 
These results indicated that patients with chronic HBV infection 
may have normal prevalence and preserved function of circulating 
iNKT cells. And antiviral therapy with nucleot(s)ide analogue does 
not alter the frequency and function of circulating iNKT cells in chronic 
Hepatitis B patients. </p>

<p>(Medicine 94(24):e961) </p>

<p>Abbreviations: a-GalCer = alpha-galactosylceramide, ALT = 
alanine aminotransferase, APC = antigen presenting cells, CHB = </p>

<p>chronic hepatitis B, CTL = cytotoxic lymphocyte, DC = dendritic 
cell, HBeAg = hepatitis B e antigen, HBsAg = hepatitis B surface 
antigen, HBV = hepatitis B virus, HC = healthy control, 
IC = immune carrier, IL = interlukin, iNKT = invariant natural 
killer T, IR = immune reactive, IT = immune tolerant, PBMC = 
peripheral blood mononuclear cell. </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>espite the introduction of effective hepatitis B vaccine, 
more than 360 million people are chronically infected with 
hepatitis B virus (HBV) worldwide. 
1 Most adults can mount an 
effective immune response to eliminate HBV after infection. 
However, HBV infection tends to become chronic when infec-
tion takes place during childhood or infancy and can lead to 
liver cirrhosis and cancer. 
2-4 Generally the prognosis of HBV 
infection depends on the intensity of the host adaptive immu-
nity. An abundant HBV specific polyclonal cytotoxic lympho-
cyte (CTL) response can effectively control HBV infection, 
while a weak monoclonal CTL response results in chronicity. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>The effectiveness of CTL responses to HBV infection is some-
times dictated by the microenvironment in the liver which is 
largely regulated by the innate immune response. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Invariant natural killer T (iNKT) cells are a subset of T 
lymphocytes recognizing lipid-based antigens in context with 
the MHC-like molecule CD1d. 
6 Therefore, iNKT cells can link 
the innate and adaptive immune responses. 
7 The T cell receptors 
expressed by iNKT cells are highly conserved. These T cell 
receptors are composed of Va24-Ja18 segments paired with 
Vb11 in humans and nonhuman primates and Va14-Ja18 
segments paired with one of Vb8.2, Vb7, or Vb2 in mice. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Upon activation, iNKT cells initiate immune responses through 
their unique ability to activate antigen presenting cells (APC) 
(eg, dendritic cells [DCs]), natural killer cells, and CD8 
þ T cells 
through cytokines produced by activated iNKT cells or direct 
cell-to-cell contact. 
8,9 Therefore, the function of iNKT cells 
affects early immune responses to many diseases including viral 
infection. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Although iNKT cells are important for immune-responses 
against viral infections, 
11,12 their role in responses against HBV 
viral infection is controversial. In an HBV transgenic animal 
model, it has been found that iNKT cells control HBV replica-
tion through induction of hepatic IFN a/b/g and natural killer 
cell activation. 
13 And activation of iNKT cells by a-galacto-
sylceramide (a-GalCer) can enhance HBV-specific CTL 
responses following hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg)-
immunization. 
14 iNKT cells have been reported to decrease 
in hepatitis B e antigen (HBeAg) positive chronic hepatitis B 
(CHB) patients, and the decreased iNKT cell numbers were not 
associated with viral load. 
15,16 However, de Lalla et al 
17 showed 
that the numbers of iNKT cells in chronic HBV-infected 
patients with high viral load were comparable to those in </p>

<p>Editor: Wenyu Lin. 
Received: December 11, 2014; revised: May 5, 2015; accepted: May 12, 
2015. 
From the Department of Infectious Diseases, Huashan Hospital, Fudan 
University, Shanghai, China (HZ, YZ, HL, YZ, YK, RM, FY, JZ); 
Department of Melanoma Medical Oncology, The University of Texas MD 
Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, USA (DZ); and Key laboratory 
of Medical Molecular Virology of the Ministries of Education and Health 
(MOH&amp;MOE), Shanghai Medical College, Fudan University, Shanghai, 
China (JZ). 
Correspondence: Jiming Zhang, Department of Infectious Diseases, 
Huashan Hospital, Fudan University, 12 Middle Wulumuqi Road, 
Shanghai 200040, China (e-mail: jmzhang@fudan.edu.cn). 
This study was supported by National Science and Technology Major Project 
of China (No.2012ZX10002007-001-002, 2013ZX10002001), National 
Natural Science Foundation of China (81271833, 81471933), and Inter-
national cooperation of the Science &amp; Technology commission of 
Shanghai Municipality (No.08410708600). DZ is supported by US 
NIH grant AI079232. 
The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose. 
Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. 
This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons 
Attribution-NonCommercial License, where it is permissible to download, 
share and reproduce the work in any medium, provided it is properly cited. 
The work cannot be used commercially. 
ISSN: 0025-7974 
DOI: 10.1097/MD.0000000000000961 </p>

<p>Medicine </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>OBSERVATIONAL STUDY </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 1 </p>

<p>healthy controls (HCs). Therefore, the role of iNKT cells in the 
immunological pathogenesis of chronic HBV infection has not 
been clarified so far. 
Until now, staining with CD1d tetramer loaded with lipid 
antigen has been a sensitive and accurate method for the 
identification of iNKT cells. To investigate the role of iNKT 
cells in the development of chronic HBV infection, we analyzed 
iNKT cells and their function in chronic HBV infected patients 
with tetramer staining. The results revealed that the fraction of 
iNKT cells among peripheral blood mononuclear cells 
(PBMCs) in chronic HBV-infected patients was not statistically 
different from that in healthy donors. However, among chronic 
patients, a decrease in iNKT cell-number was observed in 
patients with CHB and cirrhosis in comparison to that in 
immune tolerant (IT) patients. Reduction of viral load by 
tenofovir (TDF) antiviral treatment did not rescue iNKT cell 
numbers. The functions of iNKT cells were comparable 
between HBV-infected patients and HCs. Our results indicate 
that iNKT cells are mainly influenced by the inflammatory 
circumstance caused by HBV infection rather than HBV itself. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Patient Populations </p>

<p>A total of 75 treatment naive patients with chronic HBV 
infection (in various infectious phases) and 18 cirrhosis patients 
participated in this study between 2010 and 2012. Thirty age 
and gender-matched healthy individuals were recruited as HCs. 
The ethics committee at Huashan Hospital, Fudan University 
granted approval for all aspects of this study. Blood samples 
were obtained with informed written consent from healthy 
individuals and HBV-infected patients. The inclusion criterion 
for chronic HBV infection was defined by the presence of 
detectable HBsAg for at least 6 months. Individuals with 
concurrent HCV, HDV, HIV, autoimmune liver disease, or 
alcoholic liver disease were excluded. 
Based on the European Association for the Study of the 
Liver clinical practice guidelines (2009), 
18 patients were classi-
fied into 4 groups according to the natural phases of chronic 
HBV infection as follows: The IT phase was defined by HBeAg 
positive, high viral load (usually &gt;10 
7 IU/mL), normal or low 
level of alanine aminotransferase (ALT), mild or no liver necro-
inflammation, and no or slow progression of fibrosis. The 
immune reactive (IR) phase was defined by: HBeAg positive, 
elevated viral load, increased or fluctuating levels of ALT, 
moderate or severe liver necro-inflammation, and more rapid </p>

<p>progression of fibrosis. The inactive carrier (IC) state was 
defined by HBeAg negative and anti-HBeAg antibody positive, 
very low or undetectable serum HBV DNA levels and normal 
ALT. The HBeAg-negative CHB (HBeAg-negative hepatitis) 
phase was defined by: HBeAg negative with fluctuating levels 
of serum HBV DNA and ALT. Cirrhosis was diagnosed by 
imaging, biochemical, and histological examination. In this 
study, both IR and HBeAg-negative hepatitis were classified 
into the CHB group and the cut-off value for normal ALT was 
50 U/L. Patient characteristics are summarized in Table 1. A 
flow chart for subject enrollment and study design is shown in 
Figure 1. </p>

<p>Isolation and In Vitro Stimulation of PBMCs </p>

<p>PBMCs were isolated from heparinized whole blood by 
Ficoll density gradient centrifugation on Lymphoprep (AXIS-
SHILD, Oslo, Norway). Cells were resuspended in RPMI 1640 
medium (GIBCO, Carlsbad, CA) with 10% fetal bovine serum 
and 1% penicillin-streptomycin at a concentration of 10 
6 cells/ 
mL. Then these cells were cultured with 50 ng/mL phorbol 
myristate acetate (PMA) (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) and 200 ng/mL 
ionomycin (Sigma) at 378C for 5 hours in the presence of 
0.7 mL/mL monensin during the last 1 hours. </p>

<p>Generation of a-GalCer Loaded Dendritic Cells 
for In Vitro iNKT Stimulation </p>

<p>a-GalCer loaded DCs were produced as described pre-
viously. 
19 Briefly, CD14 
þ monocytes were separated from 
PBMCs with anti-CD14 microbeads (Mitenyi, Bergisch Gladbach, 
Germany) and cultured in Iscove's Modified Dubecco's Medium 
(IMDM) (GIBCO, Carlsbad, CA) with 2% human serum. Gra-
nulocyte macrophage colony-stimulating factor (800 U/mL) 
(PeProtech, Rocky Hill, NJ) and interlukin (IL)-4 (1000 U/mL) 
(PeProtech) were added, and cells were incubated at 378C for 5 
days. At day 5, a-GalCer (100 ng/mL) was added. At day 6 of 
culture, tumor necrosis factor-a (10 ng/mL) (PeProtech) was added 
to trigger the maturation of DCs. DCs were harvested at day 8 of 
culture to be used for the stimulation of iNKT cells in vitro. </p>

<p>In Vitro Expansion of iNKT Cells </p>

<p>PBMCs from chronic HBV-infected patients were mixed 
with a-GalCer pulsed DCs at the ratio of 10:1, then co-cultured 
in AIM-V medium (GIBCO, Carlsbad, CA) with 10% human 
serum and IL-15 (10 ng/mL) (PeProtech). IL-2 (100 U/mL) 
(PeProtech) was added on the second day after co-culture. After 
14 days of co-culture, iNKT cells were restimulated by </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Clinical Characteristics of Subjects Enrolled in This Study </p>

<p>Characteristic 
HC 
IT 
CHB 
IC 
Cirrhosis </p>

<p>Number 
30 
18 
38 
19 
18 
Gender (M/F) 
18/12 
12/6 
23/15 
11/8 
13/5 
Age (y) 
27 (23-57) 
25 (13-33) 
33 (19-63) 
41 (20-57) 
54 (37-67) 
ALT (U/L) 
18 (8-30) 
30.5 (11-45) 
127.5 (33-847) 
27 (19-40) 
38 (21-123) 
HBV-DNA (log 10 copies/mL) 
ND 
7.89 (6.76-8.51) 
7.85 (4.11-10.26) 
&lt;3-3.66 
&lt;3-5.99 
HBsAg (log 10 IU/mL) 
ND 
4.63 (4.34-4.87) 
3.5 (2.07-5.28) 
3.16 (0.19-4.04) 
2.65 (0.87-3.63) 
HBeAg (þ/À) 
0/30 
18/0 
22/16 
0/19 
6/12 
HBeAb (þ/À) 
0/30 
0/18 
16/22 
19/0 
12/6 </p>

<p>Data were shown as median (range). CHB ¼ chronic hepatitis B, HC ¼ healthy control, IC ¼ inactive carrier, IT ¼ immune tolerant, ND ¼ not 
determined. </p>

<p>Zhu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>aGalCer-pulsed DCs. 
19 Expanded iNKT cells were quantified 
by staining with aGalCer-CD1d tetramer (kindly provided by 
the NIH Tetramer Facility), anti-CD3, and anti-CD4 antibodies 
(eBioscience, San Diego, CA). </p>

<p>Flow-Cytometric Analysis </p>

<p>PBMCs or expanded iNKT cells were harvested, washed 
with PBS, and stained with APC-PBS57-CD1d tetramer at 378C 
in the dark for 20 minutes. Cells were then incubated with near-
IR fluorescent reactive dye (Invitrogen, Darmstadt, Germany), 
PE-Cy7-anti-CD3 and PerCP-Cy5.5-anti-CD4 at 48C for 
20 minutes. After incubation, cells were extensively washed, 
fixed, and permeabilized using a BD Cytofix/Cytoperm kit (BD 
Pharmingen, San Diego, CA), according to the manufacturer's 
instructions. These cells were finally stained with either PE-
anti-IFN-g or PE-anti-IL-4 (eBioscience) and analyzed on a BD 
Canto II flow cytometry. </p>

<p>Isolation and In Vitro Stimulation of Hepatic and 
Splenic Lymphocytes From HBV-Tg Mice </p>

<p>The male full-HBV-Tg mice with BALB/c background 
were purchased from Infectious Disease Center, No. 458 </p>

<p>Hospital (China), which expresses high level of HBsAg and 
have detectable HBV DNA in the serum. 
20 The same weeks of 
BALB/c mice were purchased as control mice. The full-HBV-
Tg mice were fed in the laboratory in accordance with Bio-
logical Safe Level 2. Animals were treated humanely, and all 
procedures were carried out in compliance with the Guide for 
the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals published by the 
United States National Institutes of Health. Hepatic and splenic 
lymphocytes were prepared as previously described. 
21 The 
procedures of in vitro stimulation, staining and flow cytometry 
detection were same as mentioned before. iNKT cells were 
defined as CD3 and CD1d tetramer positive cells. For intra-
cellular cytokine detection, cells were stained with APC-
PBS57-CD1d tetramer and PerCP cy5.5-anti-CD3 and then 
fixed and permeabilized using BD Cytofix/Cytoperm kit. 
The fixed cells were then stained with PE-anti-IFN-g or 
PE-anti-IL-4 and analyzed on a BD Canto II flow cytometry. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>All statistical analyses were performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad 
Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5</rs> software. The numbers of total or cytokine-producing 
iNKT cells in different groups of patients were compared by a </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Recruitment of study subjects and flow chart of study design. Among 250 chronic HBV-infected patients, 93 were enrolled in 
our study. We conducted a cross-sectional and a longitudinal study on the peripheral iNKT cell number, their cytokine-producing function 
and in vitro expansion. HBV ¼ hepatitis B virus, PBMC ¼ peripheral blood mononuclear cells, IT ¼ immune tolerant, CHB ¼ chronic 
hepatitis B, IC ¼ inactive carrier. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 
Preserved Function of Circulating iNKT Cells </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 3 </p>

<p>Kruskal-Wallis test followed by a Dunns post-test. The multiple 
linear regression model was used to estimate multivariate 
factors which influence the iNKT cell numbers, including 
HBsAg levels, HBV-DNA values, HBeAg status, ALT, gender, 
and age. Comparisons between 2 groups were conducted using 
Mann-Whitney test. A Friedman test followed by a Dunns post-
test was used to compare iNKT cell frequency before and after 
antiviral therapy. A P value &lt; 0.05 was considered to be 
statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Circulating CD1d Tetramer-Positive iNKT Cell 
Counts Were Decreased in CHB and Cirrhosis 
Patients Compared to Those in Immune Tolerant 
Patients </p>

<p>To assess the impact of HBV on the frequency of peripheral 
iNKT cells, we compared the numbers of peripheral iNKT cells in 
93 patients in different stages of chronic HBV infection to those in 
30 HCs. Detection of iNKT cells, defined as CD1d-tetramer and 
CD3 double positive cells, was accomplished by flow cytometry 
(Figure 2A). As shown in Figure 2B, iNKT cell numbers in 
healthy subjects and chronic HBV infected patients were both 
considerably low and varied between individuals. The numbers of 
peripheral iNKT cells in HBV-infected patients were not signifi-
cantly different from those in the HC group (P ¼ 0.44). However, 
among the HBV-infected patients, the numbers of peripheral 
iNKT cells in IT patients (mean ¼ 0.21%) were higher than those 
in CHB patients (mean ¼ 0.14%, P &lt; 0.05) and cirrhosis patients 
(mean ¼ 0.10%, P &lt; 0.01) (Figure 2C). The numbers of CD4 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>iNKT and CD4 
À iNKT cells in IT patients were also higher than 
those in CHB and cirrhosis patients (P &lt; 0.05) (Figure 2D and E). </p>

<p>Peripheral iNKT Cells From CHB Patients Are 
Functionally Comparable to Those From Healthy 
Controls </p>

<p>To investigate the function of iNKT cells, we analyzed the 
cytokine production of iNKT cells in vitro following stimu-
lation with PMA/ionomycin for 5 hours (Figure 3A). iNKT cells 
can rapidly produce a broad spectrum of cytokines such as IFN-
g and IL-4 upon activation. In our study, the major fraction of 
peripheral iNKT cells produced IFN-g, irrespective of whether 
they were obtained from CHB patients or HCs, suggesting that 
IFN-g is the dominant cytokine made by iNKT cells. The levels 
of cytokine IFN-g and IL-4 production in iNKT cells from CHB 
patients were similar to that from HCs (Figure 3B and C). 
We further analyzed the proliferative responses of iNKT 
cells stimulated by aGalCer-loaded DCs. Twenty cases were 
randomly enrolled in this study (5 each from IT, CHB, IC, and 
HC groups). In all subjects, iNKT cell numbers significantly 
increased after 14 days of culture (Figure 4A). The proliferation 
of iNKT cells was detected following stimulation in all groups 
(Figure 4A). Although the increase in iNKT cell numbers varied 
among individuals (2-70-fold change), we did not detect 
differences in fold changes of total, CD4 
þ , CD4 
À iNKT cells 
between CHB patients and HC (P ¼ 0.77, 0.91, and 0.75, 
respectively) (Figure 4B-D). </p>

<p>iNKT Cell Numbers Are Not Associated With 
Either HBV Viral Road or HBsAg Titers </p>

<p>To investigate the role of iNKT cells in disease pro-
gression, we compared the numbers of peripheral iNKT cells </p>

<p>in patients of different ages, serum ALT levels, viral copies, 
HBeAg status, and HBsAg titers among all 93 patients using the 
multiple linear regression model. As shown in Table 2, the 
numbers of iNKT cells were negatively correlated with age 
(CI ¼ À0.0071, P ¼ 0.003), which was consistent with the 
results of a previous study. 
22 And yet the levels of iNKT cells 
were not associated with viral load, HBsAg, ALT, HBeAg, or 
gender (P ¼ 0.97, 0.81, 0.16, 0.86, and 0.22, respectively). </p>

<p>The Numbers of Peripheral iNKT Cells Do Not 
Change With Inflammation or Fibrosis </p>

<p>Twenty three patients including 5 IT, 14 CHB, and 4 IC 
patients without cirrhosis were pathologically diagnosed by 
liver biopsy. Based on necroinflammation grading and fibrosis 
staging, patients were divided into a no/mild necroinflammation 
and fibrosis (G0-1S0-1) group and a moderate to severe 
necroinflammation and fibrosis (G2-4/S2-3) group. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>Nine patients were enrolled in the G0-1S0-1 subgroup and 
the other 14 were enrolled in the G2-4/S2-3 subgroup. As shown 
in Figure 5A-C, total, CD4 
þ and CD4 
À peripheral iNKT cell 
numbers exhibited no significant difference between these sub-
groups (P ¼ 0.33, 0.14, and 0.41, respectively). The function of 
iNKT cells was analyzed by measuring cytokine production 
following stimulation with PMA and ionomycin in vitro. The 
induced production of IFN-g and IL-4 was similar between these 
groups (P ¼ 0.16 and 0.26, respectively) (Figure 5D and E). </p>

<p>Tenofovir Therapy Does Not Alter Either 
Peripheral iNKT Cell Numbers or Their Function </p>

<p>We followed up 13 CHB patients who received tenofovir 
(TDF) antiviral therapy for 72 weeks to longitudinally analyze 
the influence of antiviral therapy on peripheral iNKT cell 
numbers and their function. The clinical characterization of 
these 13 patients was shown in Supplementary Table 1, http:// 
links.lww.com/MD/A296. At the end of 72 weeks of treatment, 
HBV DNA was undetectable and ALT levels were normal in all 
of these patients, while no HBeAg seroconversion occurred in 
any patient. We compared the iNKT cell numbers and their 
function at baseline, 48 and 72 weeks after the initiation of 
antiviral therapy (Figure 6A). The numbers and function of 
peripheral iNKT cells were similar before and after treatment. 
As illustrated in Figure 6, no changes in either total, CD4 
þ or 
CD4 
À iNKT cell numbers were observed in the 13 CHB patients 
under antiviral therapy (P ¼ 0.74, 0.38, and 0.20, respectively) 
(Figure 6B-D). Likewise, IFN-g and IL-4 producing iNKT 
cells were not influenced by antiviral therapy or the efficacy of 
therapy (Figure 6E and F) (P ¼ 0.34 and 0.37, respectively). 
These results suggested that antiviral therapy with TDF had 
little influence on either iNKT cell numbers or their function. </p>

<p>The Frequency and Cytokine Producing Capacity 
of Hepatic iNKT Cells From HBV-Tg Mice are 
Comparable to Those From WT Mice </p>

<p>Flow cytometric analysis revealed that there were approxi-
mately 0.5% to 1.5% iNKT cells (CD1d tetramer 
þ CD3 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>) in the 
spleen and 5% to 25% iNKT cells in the liver of both HBV-Tg 
mice and wild type (WT) mice (Figure S1A, http://links.lww.-
com/MD/A296). The frequency of splenic and hepatic iNKT 
cells in HBV-Tg mice was comparable to that in WT mice 
(P ¼ 0.28 and 0.57, respectively) (Figure S1B and D, http:// 
links.lww.com/MD/A296), which was in accordance with 
previous study. 
24 Similarly, percentages of splenic or hepatic </p>

<p>Zhu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Numbers of peripheral iNKT cells in patients with different stages of hepatitis. (A) Representative analysis of peripheral iNKT cell 
numbers in patients in different stages of HBV infection compared to healthy controls. iNKT cells were identified as CD3 and CD1d 
tetramer double-positive cells and divided into CD4 
þ and CD4 
À subsets. (B) Comparison of iNKT cell numbers between chronic HBV-
infected patients and healthy controls. (C-E) Pooled numbers of total, CD4 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>, and CD4 
À iNKT cells in IT, CHB, IC, and cirrhosis subgroups. 
Horizontal bars represent the median with interquartile range for each group. 
Ã P &lt; 0.05, 
ÃÃ P &lt; 0.01, 
ÃÃÃ P &lt; 0.001 using the Kruskal-Wallis </p>

<p>nonparametric test followed by Dunn post-test. HBV ¼ hepatitis B virus, IT ¼ immune tolerant, CHB ¼ chronic hepatitis B, IC ¼ inactive 
carrier, HC ¼ healthy control. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 
Preserved Function of Circulating iNKT Cells </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 5 </p>

<p>IFN-g 
þ iNKT and IL-4 
þ iNKT cells were not different between 
these 2 groups (P &gt; 0.05) (Figure S1C and E, http://links.lww. 
com/MD/A296). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>iNKT cells are a subset of T cells which can jump start 
the immune activation in immune defenses and play an </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. iNKT cells from HBV-infected patients have the same capacity to secrete Th1 and Th2 cytokines as those from healthy controls. 
(A) Representative dot plots of interferon-g (IFN-g) and interleukin-4 (IL-4) releasing iNKT cells in CHB patients and healthy controls. (B, C) 
Pooled percentages of IFN-g and IL-4 producing iNKT cells in each group. Horizontal bars represent the median with interquartile range 
using the Kruskal-Wallis nonparametric test followed by Dunn post-test. IT ¼ immune tolerant, CHB ¼ chronic hepatitis B, IC ¼ inactive 
carrier, HC ¼ healthy control. </p>

<p>Zhu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 </p>

<p>6 | www.md-journal.com </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>important role in linking innate and adaptive immune responses. 
Despite their low frequency in the periphery, iNKT cells have 
been implicated in infectious diseases including chronic HBV 
infection. 
However, some contradictory results have been published 
as for the frequency and function of peripheral iNKT cells in 
HBV infection. Two study groups reported a significant drop in 
iNKT cell (6B11 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>CD3 
þ /Va24 
þ Vb11 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>) frequency, 
15,16 while 
another study reported significantly increased iNKT cell 
(CD3 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>CD56 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>) frequency in HBeAg positive CHB patients. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>And a research in Italy revealed that the percentage of iNKT 
cells (CD3 
þ Va24 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>Vb11 
þ ) in PBMCs of CHB patients was 
comparable with those in healthy donors. 
17 One of the reasons 
for the discrepancy between these studies may be the different 
identification of iNKT cells. It has been suggested that 
CD3 
þ CD56 
þ , Va24 
þ Vb11 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>, or 6B11 
þ CD3 
þ cells are not 
entirely iNKT cells. 
26 At present, a lipid antigen loaded 
CD1d-tetramer marker for the identification of iNKT cells is </p>

<p>sensitive and specific, which can accurately detect 1 iNKT cell 
in 1 million PBMCs (0.0001%). 
27 Additionally, despite its 
binding of some non-iNKT cells, 
28 CD1d-tetramer can detect 
the entire CD1d-restricted iNKT cell population, while other 
antibodies only detect a subset of this population. In this study, 
we detected iNKT cells using CD1d tetramer staining for the 
first time in HBV-infected patients to accurately and compre-
hensively understand the role of iNKT cells in HBV infection. 
Our results showed that circulating iNKT cell numbers 
were low and variable between all individuals, including 
healthy subjects (range ¼ 0.01%-0.28% in CD3 
þ T cells), 
which was similar to previous results. 
16 And we found no 
significant difference of the iNKT cell frequency between 
CHB patients and HCs. Despite of high viral load in IT patients, 
no difference were observed between this group and HCs. In 
addition, our study on the IT HBV-Tg mice model also revealed 
that the frequency of hepatic iNKT cells in HBV-Tg mice was 
comparable to that in WT mice. On the other hand, iNKT cell </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. iNKT cells from CHB patients have the same capacity of in vitro expansion as healthy controls. (A) Representative dot plots of 
iNKT cell numbers immediately following collection and after in vitro expansion. (B-D) Pooled total, CD4 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>, and CD4 
À iNKT cell expansion 
fold changes in IT, CHB, IC, and HC groups. Horizontal bars represent the median, minimum, and maximum values. Comparisons 
between these groups were performed by Kruskal-Wallis nonparametric test followed by Dunn post test. IT ¼ immune tolerant, 
CHB ¼ chronic hepatitis B, IC ¼ immune carrier, HC ¼ healthy control. </p>

<p>TABLE 2. Factors Independently Associated With iNKT Cell Numbers in Chronic HBV-Infected Patients by Multivariate Analysis </p>

<p>Variables 
Coefficient 
95% CI 
P Value </p>

<p>Age (y) 
À0.0071 
(À0.0118, À0.0025) 
0.003 
Gender (male) 
À0.0577 
(À0.1518, 0.0363) 
0.223 
ALT (U/L) 
À0.0002 
(À0.0005, 0.0001) 
0.157 
HBV-DNA (log 10 copies/mL) 
À0.0008 
(À0.0391, 0.0376) 
0.967 
HBsAg (log 10 IU/mL) 
0.0081 
(À0.0576, 0.0737) 
0.805 
HBeAg (positive) 
0.0115 
(À0.1167, 0.1396) 
0.858 </p>

<p>CI ¼ confidence interval. </p>

<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 
Preserved Function of Circulating iNKT Cells </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 7 </p>

<p>frequency was not associated with either HBV viral road or 
HBsAg titers. And an iNKT cell stimulator a-GalCer did not 
affect either HBV-DNA or ALT levels despite of a strong 
decrease of iNKT cells when used as monotherapy for CHB 
infection in a phase I/II trial. 
29 On the above rationale, we 
assumed that iNKT cell frequency was influenced by the 
inflammatory circumstance caused by HBV infection rather 
than HBV itself. 
However, discrepancy existed between subgroups of 
chronic HBV patients. iNKT cell numbers in CHB and cirrhosis 
patients were lower than those in patients in IT patients. It may 
be due to the migration of iNKT cells to the inflammation site in 
the hepatitis phase, which is consistent with a previous study </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>that the iNKT cells were significantly enriched in chronically 
inflamed livers when compared with noninflamed ones. How-
ever, only cirrhosis and HCC patients were enrolled in that 
study and the migration and differentiation of iNKT cells in the 
liver of other HBV infected patients still remain unknown. In </p>

<p>the future, in vivo imaging studies may be developed to study 
the migration of iNKT cells in vivo, such as using isotope-
labeled a-GalCer/CD1d tetramers. On the other hand, CHB and 
cirrhosis patients were older than IT patients and age was an 
independent risk factor for iNKT cell frequency by multivariate 
analysis. Therefore, age might be another factor that contributes 
to the discrepancy between subgroups. 
Upon activation, iNKT cells can produce large amount of 
cytokines including Th1 cytokine IFN-g and Th2 cytokine IL-4 
which may accelerate initial immune responses. Our results 
indicate that the production of cytokines by iNKT cells was 
unimpaired in all patients. Meanwhile, when stimulated by 
aGalCer-loaded DCs in vitro, iNKT cells from HBV-infected 
patients had the same proliferative responses as those from 
healthy subjects. Similar results were observed in the hepatic 
iNKT cells from full-HBV-Tg mice model. Above mentioned 
results indicated the preserved function of peripheral iNKT cells 
in chronic HBV infection. </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. iNKT cell frequency and IFN/IL-4 producing iNKT cells in G and S subgroups. (A-C) Pooled total, CD4 </p>

<p>þ </p>

<p>, and CD4 
À iNKT cell 
numbers in G0-1S0-1 and G2-4/S2-3 subgroups. (D, E) Pooled percentage of IFN-g and IL-4 producing iNKT cells in G0-1S0-1 and G2-4/ 
S2-3 subgroups. Horizontal bars represent the median and max values. Comparisons between these 2 subgroups were performed using 
Mann-Whitney test. </p>

<p>Zhu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>To observe the influence of antiviral therapy on iNKT cell 
frequency and function, we followed up on 13 TDF treated 
patients for 72 weeks in this study. Despite a decline in viral 
load and an improvement in liver inflammation, iNKT numbers 
and their cytokine producing capacity did not change after 72 
weeks of antiviral therapy. This result further supported our 
opinion that HBV itself do not influence either the iNKT cell 
frequency or its function. 
It should be noted that our study on iNKT cells in HBV 
infection mainly focused on the iNKT cells in human peripheral 
blood. In fact, iNKT cells are more abundant in the liver and 
other organs. 
30 The changes in iNKT cell frequency in periph-
eral blood may be a result of alterations in the recruitment of 
iNKTs. Further studies may be needed to investigate the dis-
ease-associated function of hepatic iNKT cells. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>In summary, using the direct and specific tetramer 
staining method for detecting iNKT cells, we demonstrated </p>

<p>the absence of CHB-associated defect in the frequency of 
peripheral iNKT cells or in their ability to secrete IFN-g 
and IL-4 upon primary stimulation. However, among chronic 
HBV-infected patients, a decrease in iNKT cell-number was 
observed in CHB and cirrhosis patients in comparison to that in 
IT patients. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
The authors acknowledge the NIH Tetramer Facility for 
their kind provision of APC-PBS57-CD1d tetramer and Dr 
Xiaoqin Wang (Fudan University) for her helpful suggestion 
in statistical analysis. </p>



<p>Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 
Preserved Function of Circulating iNKT Cells </p>

<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>www.md-journal.com | 9 </p>



<p>Zhu et al 
Medicine Volume 94, Number 24, June 2015 </p>



<p>Copyright # 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved. </p>

</text></tei>