<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4272508" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:52+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Goal: The aim of the study was to estimate the diagnostic accuracy of optical coherence tomography parameters in normal, preperimet-
ric, developed perimetric and terminal glaucoma. Methods: 180 eyes of 140 consecutive patients were evaluated in this retrospective 
cross sectional pilot study. Copernicus Spectral -domain optical coherence tomography with resolution of 3 mm obtained through the 
optic nerve head were included. All examined eyes were divided into four groups (healthy eyes, initial, preperimetric glaucoma, developed 
perimetric glaucoma and terminal glaucoma). Results: The highest value of the RIM is noticed in control group 1,44 (1,21-1,70).There 
is no significant difference in the size of the disc in the eyes with developed open angle glaucoma ( 1,80 ±0,66) compared to normal eyes 
(p= 0,663), to the eyes with initial glaucoma ( p=0,120), and terminal glaucomatous atrophy ( p=0,068). There is statistically importance of 
E/D parameter in healthy group 0,17 (0,04 -0,27), early glaucomatous group 0,44 (0,35-0,51), developed glaucoma 0,47 ( 0,39-0,61) respec-
tively p&lt;0,005 . The volume of cup was significantly greater in the eyes with terminal glaucomatous atrophy 1,05 (0,85 -1,4) compared to 
the healthy eyes 0,31 ( 0,06-0,51) ( p &lt; 0,005), significantly greater to initial glaucoma 0,84 ( 0,58-1,12) (p=0,007) and significantly higher 
compared to developed glaucoma 0,82 ( 0,62-1.07) (p=0,003). There is no significant difference in the cup between the eyes with early and 
developed glaucoma (p=0,912). The eyes with terminal glaucoma had significant lower value of the thickness of retinal nerve fiber layer 
56,50 (45,50-71,25) compared to developed glaucoma group 82,5 (72-95,75), initial glaucoma 110,50 (102-123) and healthy eyes 132 (119-
150) (p &lt;0,005). Conclusion: The SD-OCT scanning should be used to quantify optic nerve head anatomy in human eyes. The changes 
can be recognized and can indicate as important risk factor in considering glaucoma changes. It also should be considered as an exact 
model of glaucoma pathology. 
Key words: initial, perimetric and terminal glaucoma, optic nerve head, retinal nerve fiber layer, rim of the disc, the size of 
the disc, the volume of the cup. </p>

<p>Glaucoma is a leading cause of irreversible but prevent-
able blindness all around the world. Referring the epidemi-
ological studies at least half of glaucoma suffers are undiag-
nosed (1, 2). Early recognition and medical treatment could 
benefit in some suspected groups (3). Previous studies have 
shown that morphological changes to the optic nerve head 
(ONH) and thickness of the retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL) 
might precede visual field defects (1, 4, 5). 
Copernicus Spectral-domain optical coherence tomog-
raphy (SD-OCT) is well known, new and modern imaging 
tool using low-coherence interferometry to provide high 
resolution cross-sectional images of RNFL and ONH 
(6). It shows accurate and objective anatomic changes in </p>

<p>glaucoma eyes. This technique can discriminate between 
healthy eyes ant those with preperimetric (7-13) and de-
veloped glaucoma (7, 8). Using a confocal scanning laser 
ophthalmoscopy (9, 10) and a scanning laser polarime-
try (11, 12) can enchance the usefulness of the imaging 
modalities for early glaucoma detection. It is still unclear 
which of OCT parameters show promising results for ear-
ly detection of glaucoma and should be used as major sign 
for glaucoma detection (8, 14-18). </p>

<p>2. AIM OF THE STUDY </p>

<p>The aim is to identify which measurements allow for the 
best differentiation between normal, preperimetric, ini-
tial glaucoma and developed, perimetric glaucoma. </p>

<p>ORIGINAL ARTICLE </p>

<p>doi: 10.5455/medarh.2014.68.113-116 </p>

<p>Med Arh. 2014 Apr; 68(2): 113-116 </p>

<p>Received: January 18th 2014 | Accepted: April 04th 2014 
© AVICENA 2014 </p>

<p>Published online: 22/04/2014 
Published print: 
04/2014 </p>

<p>Correlation Between Retinal Nerve Fiber Layer and Disc Parameters in Glaucoma Suspected Eyes </p>



<p>Med Arh. 2014 Apr; 68(2): 113-116 </p>

<p>3. METHODS </p>

<p>180 eyes of 140 consecutive patients were evaluated in 
this retrospective cross sectional pilot study. Copernicus 
SD-OCT with resolution of 3 mm obtained through the 
ONH were included. All examined eyes were divided into 
four groups. The size of the disc, the volume of cup, cup/ 
disc ratio (E/D), size of the rim and the thickness of the 
RNFL were observed in 50 normal eyes ( control group 
without glaucoma), 50 eyes with the signs of initial open 
angle glaucoma, 50 eyes with developed simple glaucoma 
and 30 eyes with terminal glaucoma signs (final glauco-
matous atrophy). 
Mean anatomical values within diagnostic categories 
were compared using one way analysis of variance and 
multivariable analysis. Bivariate analysis was used to in-
vestigate relationships between evident variables and sig-
nificant ( p&lt;0,05) relationships. These results were incor-
porated in the final statistical conclusion. 
All variables were expressed for categorical data as the 
means±s.e.m. or medians and interquartile ranges for 
continuous data with or without a normal distribution, 
respectively. Normally distributed continuous variables 
were compared between groups using two-tailed-tests. 
Nonparametric data was compared between groups using 
the independent samples Mann-Whitney U-test. P-value 
&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. All statisti-
cal analyses were performed using the computer software 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 20.0</rs> 
(SPSS, Chicago, IL). </p>

<p>4. RESULTS </p>

<p>The highest value of RIM is noticed in control group 
1,44 (1,21-1,70) and was statistically significant higher 
than the values of RIM in early glaucoma study group 
1,04 (0,85-1,33) respectively (p&lt;0,005), developed, peri-
metric group 0,86 (0,64-1,26) respectively (p&lt;0,005) and 
terminal glaucoma group 0,39 (0,14-0,68) respectively 
(p&lt;0,005). Terminal glaucoma study group had significant 
lower values of RIM compared to early glaucoma group 
(p&lt;0,005) and developed glaucoma group (p&lt;0,005). The </p>

<p>patients with developed glaucoma had significantly lower 
value of RIM than incipient study group (p&lt;0,005). 
The largest disc was noticed in early glaucoma 
group1,94±0,62, and was statistically higher than control 
study group 1,75±0,66 respectively (p=0,047) and ter-
minal glaucoma group1,58±0,10 respectively (p=0,002). 
There is no significant difference between the size of disc 
in the developed perimetric glaucoma group1,80±0,66 
compared to control group (p=0,663), incipient glaucoma 
group (p=0,120) and terminal glaucoma group (p=0,068). 
The statistically significant difference was not noticed in 
the size of disc in terminal glaucoma group and the con-
trol group (p=0,140). </p>

<p>E/D parameter was extremely higher in terminal glau-
coma group 0,77 (0,57-0,85) and it was significantly high-
er compared to control group 0,17 (0,04-0,27) (p&lt;0,005), 
much higher than in early glaucoma group 0,44 (0,35-
0,51) respectively (p&lt;0,005), and developed glaucoma 
group 0,47 (0,39-0,61) respectively (p&lt;0,005). There is sig-</p>

<p>Figure 1. Comparison of the values of RIM of the disc in study 
groups. Legend: * comparing to control group, **comparing to ini-
tial glaucoma, ***comparing to developed glaucoma, p-probability, 
NS-not significant </p>

<p>Figure 2. Comparison of the size of DISC-parameters in different 
study groups. Legend: * comparing to control group, **comparing 
to initial glaucoma, ***comparing to developed glaucoma, p-proba-
bility, NS-not significant </p>

<p>Figure 3. Comparison of E/D parameters (excavation /size) in the 
study groups. Legend: * comparing to control group, **comparing 
to initial glaucoma, ***comparing to developed glaucoma, p-proba-
bility, NS-not significant </p>

<p>Correlation Between Retinal Nerve Fiber Layer and Disc Parameters in Glaucoma Suspected Eyes </p>



<p>Med Arh. 2014 Apr; 68(2): 113-116 </p>

<p>nificantly lower the value E/D in control group compared 
to early glaucoma group (p&lt;0,005) and developed glauco-
ma (p&lt;0,005). The statistically significant difference of the 
value of the parameter E/D was noticed in between early 
and developed glaucoma group (p=0,039). </p>

<p>The highest value of CUP is noticed in terminal glauco-
ma group 1,05 (0,85-1,40) and was statistically significant 
compared to control group 0,31 (0,06-0,51) respectively 
(p&lt;0,005), as well as statistically higher than incipient 
glaucoma group 0,84 (0,58-1,12) respectively(p=0,007), 
and statistically higher than developed glaucoma group 
0,82 (0,62-1,07) respectively (p=0,003). Comparing the 
values of the CUP parameters statistically higher values 
were noticed in early glaucoma group (p&lt;0,005) and the 
group with developed glaucoma (p&lt;0,005). There is no 
statistically significant difference in CUP values in be-
tween early and developed glaucoma group (p=0,912). 
The parameters of RNFL thickness is higher in control 
study group 132 (119-150) and was statistically signifi-</p>

<p>cant compared to early glaucoma group 110,50 (102-123) 
respectively (p&lt;0,005), developed glaucoma group 82,5 
(72-95,75) respectively (p&lt;0,005) and terminal glaucoma 
group 56,50 (45,50-71,25) respectively (p&lt;0,005). The ter-
minal glaucoma patients showed statistically significant 
lower values of RNFL parameter than early glaucoma 
eyes (p&lt;0,005), developed glaucoma patients (p&lt;0,005). 
The developed glaucoma group had statistically signifi-
cant lower values of RNFL parameter than early glaucoma 
group (p&lt;0,005). </p>

<p>5. DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The changes of ONH and RNFL defects might cause the 
development of visual field loss (19,20). Most of studies 
evaluated the usefulness of OCT parameters for detecting 
differences between normal and glaucomatous eyes (4). 
Our study was an attempt to evaluate the usefulness of 
OCT parameters and RNFL in detecting early structural 
damage in glaucoma suspected eyes. We wanted to em-
phasize the parameter best able to discriminate between 
each subgroup of glaucoma suspected eyes and healthy 
eyes . The aim of the study was to investigate whether the 
combination of single parameters could improve the diag-
nostic power of OCT in detecting glaucoma. 
Zangwill et al. (21) found statistically significant differ-
ence between ocular hypertensive and normal eyes for 
disc area, height in contour, rim area and rim volume. 
Anton et al. (9) observed that all ONH parameters ex-
cept for cup area differed statistically between ocular hy-
pertensive and normal eyes. 
Bowd et al. (22) measured RNFL thickness by OCT and 
observed that this parameter was 15 per cent thinner in 
ocular hypertensive eyes than normal eyes. 
Subbiah et al. (23) ocular hypertensive eyes had a thin-
ner mean RNFL thickness as well as nasal, inferior and 
temporal quadrants than normal eyes. 
Sugimoto et al. (24) reported that RNFL thickness mea-
surements could not distinguish ocular hypertensive eyes 
from normal eyes. They found that ONH parameters pre-
sented with poorer diagnostic precision than RNFL pa-
rameters. 
In a study by Caprioli et al. (25) who compared the pe-
rimetrically normal to glaucoma suspected eyes with uni-
lateral loss for normal eyes suggested that time domain 
OCT might detect evidence of glaucomatous damage ear-
lier than Heidelberg Retinal Tomograph II. 
Our results are in agreement with those of Naithani et 
al. (26 ) and Burgansky et al. (18). The average RNFL and 
C/D ratio as well as rim are almost be included as vari-
ables in formulas using the RNFL and ONH parameters. 
All these results would be beneficial to test our approach 
on separating glaucomatous ones of patients with hyper-
tension. </p>

<p>6. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Our study demonstrated the both ONH and RNFL pa-
rameters might reveal statistically significant differences 
between normal and glaucoma suspected eyes. The RNFL 
parameters were better at discriminating between nor-
mal and developed and terminal glaucoma. These ONH 
parameters offered better diagnostic precision in identi-</p>

<p>Figure 4. Comparison of the CUP of the disc in different study 
groups. Legend: * comparing to control group, **comparing to ini-
tial glaucoma, ***comparing to developed glaucoma, p-probability, 
NS-not significant </p>

<p>Figure 5. Comparison of the thickness of the RNFL in the study 
groups. Legend: * comparing to control group, **comparing to ini-
tial glaucoma, ***comparing to developed glaucoma, p-probability, 
NS-not significant </p>

<p>Correlation Between Retinal Nerve Fiber Layer and Disc Parameters in Glaucoma Suspected Eyes </p>



<p>Med Arh. 2014 Apr; 68(2): 113-116 </p>

<p>fication of glaucomatous eyes. The combination of RNFL 
parameters only or both ONH and RNFL parameters 
provided the best classification results. The changes in 
the values of OCT parameters can be recognized and can 
indicate as important risk factor in considering glaucoma 
changes. It also should be taken as an exact model of glau-
coma pathology. </p>

<p>CONFLICT OF INTEREST: NONE DECLARED </p>



</text></tei>