<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4575381" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
Summary The objectives of this study were to estimate per-
sistence with denosumab and put these results in context by 
conducting a review of persistence with oral bisphosphonates. 
Persistence with denosumab was found to be higher than with 
oral bisphosphonates. 
Purpose This study had two objectives: to analyse persistence 
in Swedish women initiating denosumab for treatment of post-
menopausal osteoporosis (PMO) and to put these findings in 
context by conducting a literature review and meta-analysis of 
persistence data for oral bisphosphonates. 
Methods The study used the Swedish Prescribed Drug Register 
and included women aged at least 50 years initiating 
denosumab between May 2010 and July 2012. One injection 
of denosumab was defined as 6-month persistence. Women 
were considered persistent for another 6 months if they filled 
their next prescription within 6 months+56 days and survival 
analysis applied to the data. A literature search was conducted 
in PubMed to identify retrospective studies of persistence with 
oral bisphosphonates and pooled persistence estimates were 
calculated using a random-effects model. </p>

<p>Results The study identified 2,315 women who were incident 
denosumab users. Mean age was 74 years and 61 % had been 
previously treated for PMO. At 12 and 24 months, persistence 
with denosumab was 83 % (95 % CI, 81-84 %) and 62 % 
(95 % CI, 60-65 %), respectively. The literature search iden-
tified 40 articles for inclusion in the meta-analysis. At 12 and 
24 months, persistence with oral bisphosphonates ranged from 
10 % to 78 % and from 16 % to 46 %, with pooled estimates of 
45 % and 30 %, respectively. 
Conclusion These data from the Swedish Prescribed Drug 
Register and literature review suggest that persistence was 
higher with denosumab than with oral bisphosphonates. </p>

<p>Osteoporosis is a disease characterized by excessive bone resorp-
tion leading to reduced bone strength and an increased risk of 
fracture. In women, reduced oestrogen levels during or after 
menopause can lead to postmenopausal osteoporosis (PMO) [1]. 
There are several treatments available for osteoporosis, which 
have the primary aim of reducing the risk of fracture [2, 3]. For 
optimal outcomes, patients need to take their treatment according 
to the dosing instructions and for the prescribed duration (i.e., 
they need to be both compliant and persistent with therapy) [4]. 
Studies in both the USA and Europe have shown that persistence 
with osteoporosis treatment is important for reducing the risk of 
fracture [5-7]. The data indicate that, compared with treatment 
lasting for less than 1-month, treatment must extend beyond 
1 year in order to significantly reduce 3-year fracture incidence 
[6]. Evidence suggests, however, that approximately 50 % of 
women do not follow their prescribed osteoporosis treatment </p>

<p>* L. Karlsson 
linda.karlsson@quantifyresearch.com </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Quantify Research, Hantverkargatan 8, SE-112 
21 Stockholm, Sweden </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Department of Learning, Informatics, Management and Ethics 
(LIME), Medical Management Centrum (MMC), Karolinska 
Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Department of Pharmacy, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Amgen (Europe) GmbH, Zug, Switzerland </p>

<p>Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 
DOI 10.1007/s00198-015-3253-4 </p>

<p>regimen and 50 % discontinue treatment within 1 year [8, 9]. 
Hence, persistence is an important consideration in the overall 
management of patients with osteoporosis. Moreover, modelling 
studies have shown that the incorporation of persistence in health 
economic evaluations can have a considerable impact on the 
estimated cost-effectiveness of an intervention [10, 11]. 
Oral bisphosphonates (BPs), including both alendronate and 
risedronate, are the current mainstay of anti-osteoporosis treat-
ment in Europe [12]. Oral BPs can be administered daily, week-
ly, or monthly. An alternative treatment option is denosumab, a 
fully human monoclonal antibody that inhibits the RANK li-
gand, which is administered as a 60-mg subcutaneous injection 
once every 6 months. Denosumab 60 mg is indicated for the 
treatment of osteoporosis in postmenopausal women and in 
men at increased risk of fracture, and for the treatment of bone 
loss associated with hormone ablation in men with prostate 
cancer at increased risk of fracture [13]. Denosumab 60 mg 
has also been shown to increase bone mass in women with bone 
loss associated with adjuvant aromatase inhibitor therapy [14]. 
In patients with osteoporosis, the long-interval subcutaneous 
dosing regimen of denosumab could enable higher persistence 
with therapy than that observed with other anti-osteoporosis 
treatments [7, 9]. Indeed, levels of 12-month persistence have 
been reported with denosumab that vastly exceed the 50 % rate 
cited above. In a randomized, cross-over trial comparing 
denosumab with alendronate, 91 % of patients were persistent 
with treatment over 12 months, whilst in two single-arm, pro-
spective, observational studies conducted in the USA, Canada, 
Austria, Belgium, Greece, and Germany, 12-month persistence 
rates varied from 82 to 94 % across countries [15-17]. To our 
knowledge, however, no study of real-world persistence with 
denosumab therapy in Sweden has yet been published. 
This study had two objectives. The first was to estimate 
persistence in Swedish women in whom denosumab treatment 
was initiated for PMO and to explore patient characteristics 
that might affect persistence. The second was to put the find-
ings regarding persistence with denosumab into context by 
conducting a literature review and meta-analysis of published, 
retrospective data on persistence with oral BPs. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Persistence with denosumab </p>

<p>Data source and patient selection </p>

<p>This study involved the analysis of data from the Swedish 
Prescribed Drug Register, which contains information on 
drugs dispensed on prescription since 2005 for the Swedish 
population (approximately 9.6 million individuals) [18]. Mor-
tality data were collected from the Swedish Causes of Death 
Register, which includes death dates for all people residing in </p>

<p>Sweden at the time of death. Swedish national registers have a 
high degree of accuracy. The loss of patient information from 
the Swedish Prescribed Drug Register is less than 0.6 % of all 
possible values and fewer than 0.5 % of all deaths are missing 
from the Causes of Death Register [19]. 
Women aged 50 years or older in whom denosumab treat-
ment was initiated between 1 May 2010 and 31 July 2012 
were identified in the Swedish Prescribed Drug Register. To 
capture relevant baseline characteristics, data needed to be 
available for at least the 18-month period before treatment 
initiation (the pre-index period). Similarly, to accumulate suf-
ficient follow-up time to study persistence, data needed to be 
available for at least the 8-month period immediately follow-
ing treatment initiation. The analysis focused on women with 
PMO and included only those receiving denosumab 60 mg. 
As denosumab is also used to increase bone mass in patients 
with bone loss associated with adjuvant aromatase inhibitor 
therapy, patients filling prescriptions for aromatase inhibitors 
in the pre-index period were excluded from the study. </p>

<p>Definition of persistence </p>

<p>Persistence was defined as the number of days from the date of 
treatment initiation to the end of the duration of the last filled 
prescription or the end of the study period (31 March 2013). 
One injection of denosumab equated to 6 months' persistence; 
hence, all women were defined as being persistent with ther-
apy for at least 6 months. Women were considered to be per-
sistent for an additional 6 months if they filled their next 
denosumab prescription within 6 months+56 days of admin-
istration of the previous injection (i.e., a gap of 56 days was 
permitted) [4]. Women failing to refill their prescription before 
the end of the permissible gap were defined as being non-
persistent 6 months after the last filled prescription. </p>

<p>Covariates </p>

<p>The covariates used in the analysis were: age; previous oste-
oporosis treatment in the pre-index period; glucocorticoid use, 
defined as filling a prescription for cortisone, hydrocortisone, 
methylprednisolone, prednisolone, prednisone, triamcinolone, 
betamethasone, or dexamethasone equivalent to at least 
450 mg of prednisolone in the pre-index period [20]; concur-
rent calcium and/or vitamin D supplementation, defined as 
filling prescriptions corresponding to at least 109,500 mg of 
calcium (1,200 mg/day for 3 months) and/or 73,000 IU of 
vitamin D (800 IU/day for 3 months) in the 6 months after 
treatment was initiated [21]; dependency, defined as living in a 
dependent/institutionalized setting (determined on the basis of 
the initial prescription being pre-dispensed); and receiving 
primary care (defined as the initial prescription being pre-
scribed in the primary care setting). </p>

<p> 
Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Persistence with therapy was estimated at 12, 18, and 
24 months using Kaplan-Meier survival curves, with non-
persistence as the failure event. Women were censored for 
death and end of data availability (31 March 2013). Covariates 
associated with non-persistence were investigated using a 
parametric proportional hazards model (Weibull distribution). 
The effects of alternative permissible gaps of 30, 90, and 
180 days were explored using sensitivity analyses. 
Denosumab has a biannual dosing regimen and women may 
refill their prescriptions several months earlier than the date on 
which the next injection is needed, which can result in long 
gaps between prescriptions. This possible accumulation of 
denosumab was accounted for in another sensitivity analysis, 
which used a 56-day permissible gap and permitted women to 
cover future gaps between filled prescriptions with previously 
dispensed medication. 
Subgroup analyses were conducted according to the calen-
dar year of the index denosumab injection. Further subgroup 
analyses compared persistence in treatment-naïve women 
with that in treatment-experienced women. The latter group 
was defined as those with a prescription for another anti-
osteoporosis drug (alendronate, risedronate, ibandronate, eti-
dronate, zoledronic acid, strontium ranelate, raloxifene, or 
parathyroid hormone analogue) in the pre-index period. 
Model distribution and covariate selection were based on 
maximizing the log-likelihood and minimizing the Akaike 
information criterion. The proportional hazards assumption 
was tested by graphical inspection and by exploring whether 
the included covariates significantly varied over time. The 
statistical analysis was executed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">12</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">StataCorp</rs> 
LP, College Station, TX, USA). </p>

<p>Persistence with oral bisphosphonates </p>

<p>Literature review </p>

<p>The literature review focused on persistence with oral BPs, 
which are the most commonly used treatments for osteopo-
rosis in Europe and the USA [1]. Retrospective studies that 
estimated treatment persistence with oral BPs at 12 and 
24 months were identified in the PubMed database. The 
search string used was Bosteoporo*[All fields] AND 
(persistence[All fields] OR adherence[All fields] OR 
compliance[All fields] OR discontin*[All fields]) AND 
(register*[All fields] OR claim*[All fields] OR record*[All 
fields] OR health plan*[All fields] OR pharmacy*[All 
fields] OR prescript*[All fields]) OR (osteoporosis[All 
fields] AND persistence[All fields])^. Searches also includ-
ed the MeSH terms Bpatient compliance^, Bcompliance^, 
Bpostmenopausal^, and Bosteoporosis^. The search </p>

<p>encompassed all articles published until 22 November 
2013 with an English-language abstract. 
In addition to the PubMed database search, seven review 
articles [22-28] were cited in the papers included after the 
literature search and full-text review. These review articles 
were manually searched to identify articles not found using 
the search string. To be included in this study, an article need-
ed to present at least one estimate of 12-and 24-month per-
sistence with oral BP treatment. No additional inclusion 
criteria were used. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Pooled estimates of persistence at 12 and 24 months were 
calculated using a random-effects model [29]. Subgroup anal-
yses of 12-month persistence were conducted according to 
frequency of administration (weekly and daily; only for those 
studies directly comparing these two frequencies) and region 
(Europe, North America, and other). </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Persistence with denosumab </p>

<p>Study population </p>

<p>The final cohort consisted of 2,315 incident users of 
denosumab (Fig. 1) who contributed a total of 2,747 person-
years. Baseline patient characteristics are presented in Table 1. 
Women were followed up for a mean (median) of 433 (387) 
days, until censoring or non-persistence with therapy. The 
majority (61 %) of women had received another anti-
osteoporosis treatment in the 18 months before starting 
denosumab treatment. Approximately two fifths of women 
were prescribed their initial prescription medication in a pri-
mary care setting, and approximately one fifth had received 
glucocorticoids before initiation of denosumab treatment. 
Even though the inclusion period continued to 31 July 2012, 
the majority (62 %) of women filled their index prescription in 
2010 or 2011. </p>

<p>Persistence </p>

<p>The estimated Kaplan-Meier curves for persistence with 
denosumab are presented in Fig. 2. Using a permissible gap 
of 56 days, persistence with denosumab treatment was 83 % 
(95 % CI, 81-84 %) at 12 months, 69 % (95 % CI, 67-71 %) 
at 18 months, and 62 % (95 % CI, 60-65 %) at 24 months. 
Increasing the permissible gap to 90 and 180 days, 12-month 
persistence was 84 % (95 % CI, 83-86 %) and 87 % (95 % CI, 
86-88 %), respectively. Decreasing the permissible gap to 
30 days, 12-month persistence was 78 % (95 % CI, 76-79 %). </p>

<p>Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>

<p>
The sensitivity analysis allowing patients to have overlap-
ping prescriptions showed results similar to the analysis with a 
permissible gap of 90 days (data not shown). 
At 24 months, women who had received previous anti-
osteoporosis treatment (during the pre-index period) were 
more likely to be persistent with therapy than those who had 
not (65 vs. 58 %, p&lt;0.001); no difference was observed at 
12 months (p=1.000). No difference in 12-month persistence </p>

<p>was found between women whose denosumab treatment was 
initiated in 2010 or 2011 and those first receiving denosumab 
in 2012 (p=1.000). </p>

<p>Determinants of non-persistence </p>

<p>A multivariate Weibull model was fitted to identify variables 
that were significantly associated with non-persistence 
(Table 2). For all included covariates, no significant evidence 
of non-proportional hazards was observed (data not shown). 
Previous anti-osteoporosis treatment (during the pre-index 
period) was associated with a higher rate of persistence 
compared with no previous treatment. Filling a prescription 
for calcium and vitamin D supplementation in the first 6 months 
after denosumab initiation was also found to be associated with 
a higher persistence rate. Glucocorticoid treatment during the 
pre-index period was associated with a lower denosumab </p>

<p>Table 1 Baseline characteristics of women with PMO initiating 
denosumab 60 mg </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Study population 
(N=2,315) </p>

<p>Follow-up, days </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>433.4±183.3 
Age, years </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>73.7±9.0 
Previous anti-osteoporosis treatment </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>1,406 (60.7) 
Glucocorticoid use </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>483 (20.9) 
Concurrent calcium/vitamin D supplementation </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>826 (35.7) </p>

<p>Dependency/institutionalized </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>98 (4.2) </p>

<p>Primary care </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>903 (39.0) </p>

<p>Filling first prescription in 2010 or 2011 
1,426 (61.6) </p>

<p>Filling first prescription in 2012 
889 (38.4) </p>

<p>Data are mean±standard deviation or n (%) 
a Time until censoring or non-persistence </p>

<p>b Age of patient at initiation of denosumab treatment </p>

<p>c Experience of any other anti-osteoporosis treatment in the 18 months 
before initiation of denosumab treatment 
d Filling prescriptions equivalent to at least 450 mg of prednisolone in the 
18 months before initiation of denosumab treatment 
e Filling prescription for calcium and vitamin D supplements in the 
6 months after initiation of denosumab treatment 
f Receiving initial denosumab prescription as pre-dispensed </p>

<p>g Initial denosumab prescription prescribed in the primary care setting </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Flow chart of the selection 
of women with PMO initiating 
denosumab 60 mg </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 5 </p>

<p>5 0 </p>

<p>7 5 </p>

<p>1 0 0 </p>

<p>Percent of patients on treatment </p>

<p>0 
6 
12 
24 
18 
30 </p>

<p>Months after denosumab initiation </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Kaplan-Meier estimates of persistence with denosumab therapy 
for permissible gaps of different lengths </p>

<p> 
Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>

<p>persistence rate. Age, pre-dispensing of the initial prescription, 
and receiving treatment in the primary care setting did not have 
significant effects on persistence levels. </p>

<p>Literature review and meta-analysis: persistence with oral 
bisphosphonates </p>

<p>Included articles </p>

<p>The search of the PubMed database identified 663 articles, 
most of which were excluded on the basis of their title or 
abstract (Fig. 3). The most frequent reasons for exclusion 
were: not reporting an estimate of 12-or 24-month persis-
tence; discussing only hormone replacement therapy, osteopo-
rotic fractures, or calcium/vitamin D supplementation; not 
using retrospective data; not having been written in English; 
and being a review. Review articles were manually searched 
for any articles that had not been identified by the search of 
PubMed [22, 28]. 
In total, 40 articles were included in the final review and 
meta-analysis (Table 3) [5, 6, 30-67]. These included studies 
from 12 different countries, with the largest number of studies 
being conducted in the USA (17 studies) [5, 35-38, 41, 42, 46,  49-51, 54, 56, 59, 63, 64, 66] and the next largest number 
being conducted in the Netherlands (four studies) [43, 44, 48,  61]. Two studies used the Swedish Prescribed Drug Register 
[6, 47]. In the majority of studies, a patient was defined as 
non-persistent with treatment if the time period between two </p>

<p>consecutive prescription fills exceeded the length of the per-
missible gap. The most commonly used permissible gap was 
30 days [5, 30, 32-40, 44, 49, 52, 55, 56, 58, 61, 65]; other 
commonly used permissible gaps were 60 and 90 days. In nine 
studies [6, 31, 40-42, 45, 47, 64, 66], patients were allowed to 
accumulate medicine (i.e., use supply from a previous pre-
scription) and in 16 studies [6, 30-32, 34, 39, 40, 44-46, 52,  54, 55, 57, 61, 63], they were allowed to switch between 
treatments during the study period (e.g., from alendronate to 
risedronate or from weekly to daily oral BPs). The studies 
varied in the type of data source used (e.g., claims, medical 
charts), type of patients included (e.g., women with PMO, 
treatment-naïve women), and type of oral BP prescribed 
(e.g., alendronate, risedronate). </p>

<p>Persistence at 12 and 24 months </p>

<p>Of the 40 included studies, 39 reported at least one estimate of 
12-month persistence with treatment (Fig. 4) [6, 30-67] and 
17 [5, 6, 31, 32, 37, 45, 46, 48, 50-52, 55, 58, 59, 61, 64, 65] 
reported at least one estimate of 24-month persistence 
(Table 3). Estimates of 12-month persistence varied widely, 
from 10 to 78 %, with the majority of estimates ranging from 
30 to 60 %, and there was a large amount of heterogeneity 
between studies in the methods used (Fig. 4). The pooled 
estimate of 12-month persistence with oral BP therapy was 
45 % (95 % CI, 41-49 %). Estimates of 24-month persistence 
ranged from 16 to 46 % (Table 3), and the pooled estimate was 
30 % (95 % CI, 25-35 %). In Sweden, 12-month persistence 
with oral BPs was reported to be 51 % [6], and 52 % (in 
patients starting treatment in 2009) or 67 % (in those starting 
treatment in 2006) [47], and 24-month persistence reported to 
be 25 % [6] (Table 3). 
Studies investigating the differences between daily and 
weekly oral BPs [30, 35-37, 50, 55] reported that daily ad-
ministration was associated with lower 12-month persistence 
compared with weekly administration (pooled estimates: 36 
vs. 48 %, respectively) (Fig. 4). North American studies had a 
slightly lower pooled estimate of 12-month persistence com-
pared with European studies (43 % based on 19 studies vs. 
46 % based on 16 studies) (Fig. 4). The pooled 12-month 
estimate of persistence in other regions (based on four studies) 
was higher than the European and North American estimates. 
The results of studies varying the permissible gap all indicated 
that wider permissible gaps were associated with higher per-
sistence with treatment [6, 31, 33, 41, 45, 49, 51, 63, 64, 66]. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>For optimal clinical outcomes, women with PMO need to 
persist with anti-osteoporosis medications for the prescribed 
treatment duration. To the best of our knowledge, this is the </p>

<p>Table 2 Determinants of non-persistence with denosumab treatment 
(Weibull hazards model) </p>

<p>Covariate 
Hazard 
ratio </p>

<p>95 % 
confidence 
interval </p>

<p>p 
value </p>

<p>Age 
1.00 
0.99-1.01 
0.48 </p>

<p>Previous anti-osteoporosis treatment </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.85 
0.73-0.98 
0.03 </p>

<p>Glucocorticoid use </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>1.28 
1.08-1.53 
0.01 </p>

<p>Concurrent calcium/vitamin D 
supplementation </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.80 
0.68-0.93 
0.01 </p>

<p>Dependency/institutionalized </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>0.97 
0.66-1.43 
0.88 </p>

<p>Primary care </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>1.09 
0.94-1.27 
0.25 </p>

<p>A hazard ratio &gt;1 indicates a higher probability of discontinuing treat-
ment relative to continuing treatment. Estimated model parameters: con-
stant=0.20 and p=1.49 
a Experience of any other anti-osteoporosis treatment in the 18 months 
before initiation of denosumab treatment 
b Filling prescriptions equivalent to at least 450 mg of prednisolone in the 
18 months before initiation of denosumab treatment 
c Filling prescriptions for calcium and/or vitamin D supplements in the 
6 months after initiation of denosumab treatment 
d Receiving initial denosumab prescription as pre-dispensed </p>

<p>e Initial denosumab prescription prescribed in the primary care setting </p>

<p>Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>

<p>
Identified articles ( </p>

<p>Remaining articles (n=158) </p>

<p>Remaining articles (n=79) </p>

<p>Excluded by title review (n=505) </p>

<p>Excluded by abstract review (n=79) </p>

<p>Excluded by full-text review (n=40) </p>

<p>Included cited publication (n=1) </p>

<p>Remaining articles ( </p>

<p>n=663) </p>

<p>n=40) </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Flow chart of the literature 
search </p>

<p>Table 3 Summary of data included in the literature review </p>

<p>Publication 
Country 
Number of 
women </p>

<p>Treatment for 
which persistence 
was assessed </p>

<p>Female (%) Permissible 
gap </p>

<p>12/24-month 
persistence (%) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Balasubramanian et al. 
(2013) [64] </p>

<p>USA 
92,839 
ALE-IBA-RIS-other 
100 
60 days 
42/30 </p>

<p>Brankin et al. (2006) [30] 
UK 
15,330 
ALE-RIS 
100 
30 days 
Weekly vs. daily 
GPRD: 52/-vs. 40/-
MEDIPLUS: 44/-vs. 33/-
DIN-LINK: 70/-vs. 56/-</p>

<p>Burden et al. (2012) [31] 
Canada 
451,113 
ALE-ETI-RIS 
84 
60 days 
63/46 </p>

<p>Cheen et al. (2012) [32] 
Singapore 
798 
ALE-RIS 
92 
30 days 
69/18 </p>

<p>Cheng et al. (2013) [58] 
Taiwan 
2,975 
ALE-other 
90 
30 days 
51/38 </p>

<p>Chiu et al. (2013) [65] 
Taiwan 
333 
ALE-other 
0 
30 days 
46/30 </p>

<p>Cotte et al. (2008) [34] 
France 
2,468 
ALE-ETI-RIS-other 
100 
30 days 
Previous fracture: 34/-
No previous fracture: 41/-</p>

<p>Cotte et al. (2010) [33] 
France 
2,990 
ALE-IBA-RIS 
100 
Monthly: 45 days 
Weekly: 30 days </p>

<p>Monthly: 48/-
Weekly: 30/-</p>

<p>Cramer et al. (2005) [35] 
USA 
2,741 
ALE-RIS 
100 
30 days 
Weekly: 44/-
Daily: 32/-</p>

<p>Cramer et al. (2006) [36] 
USA 
15,640 
ALE-RIS 
100 
30 days 
Weekly vs. daily 
USA: 44/-vs. 32/-
UK: 52/-vs. 40/-
France: 51/-vs. 44/-</p>

<p>Curtis et al. (2006) [59] 
USA 
1,158 
ALE/RIS 
77-80 
90 days 
ALE: 52/40 
RIS: 50/40 </p>

<p>Gallagher et al. (2008) [53] 
UK 
44,531 
ALE-RIS 
81 
90 days 
58/-</p>

<p>Gold et al. (2007) [37] 
USA 
4,769 
ALE 
100 
30 days 
Weekly: 36/24 
Daily: 26/16 </p>

<p>Gold et al. (2009) [54] 
USA 
263,383 
IBA/RIS 
93-94 
90 days 
IBA: 18/-
RIS: 40/-</p>

<p>Hadji et al. (2012) [55] 
Germany 
4,147 
ALE-ETI-IBA-RIS-other 100 
30 days 
28/13 </p>

<p>Hansen et al. (2013) [57] 
Denmark 
100,556 
Not specified 
85 
56 days 
61/-</p>

<p>Huybrechts et al. (2006) [38] USA 
38,120 
ALE-RIS-other 
100 
30 days 
78/-</p>

<p> 
Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>

<p>first retrospective register study of persistence among Swedish 
women in whom denosumab therapy was initiated for the 
treatment of PMO. Twelve-month persistence with 
denosumab treatment was 83 %. This result is similar to pre-
viously reported estimates of persistence with denosumab 
[15-17] and is higher than previously published estimates of 
persistence with oral BPs. Indeed, this study's pooled estimate </p>

<p>from 39 studies of oral BPs showed that only 45 % of patients 
were persistent with treatment after 12 months. </p>

<p>Persistence with denosumab </p>

<p>The women included in our database study were slightly older 
than those included in a study of treatment-naïve users of oral </p>

<p>Table 3 (continued) </p>

<p>Publication 
Country 
Number of 
women </p>

<p>Treatment for 
which persistence 
was assessed </p>

<p>Female (%) Permissible 
gap </p>

<p>12/24-month 
persistence (%) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Jones et al. (2008) [39] 
Canada 
62,897 
ALE/RIS 
100 
30 days 
ALE: 56/-
RIS: 54/-</p>

<p>Landfeldt et al. (2012) [6] 
Sweden 
56,586 
ALE-RIS-other 
86 
56 days 
51/25 </p>

<p>Li et al. (2012) [40] 
UK 
66,116 
ALE-ETI-IBA-RIS-other 100 
30 days 
32/-</p>

<p>Lo et al. (2006) [41] 
USA 
13,455 
ALE 
100 
60 days 
50/-</p>

<p>McCombs et al. (2004) [42] USA 
3,720 
ALE-ETI-RIS 
93 
14 days 
24/-</p>

<p>McGowan et al. (2013) [60] Ireland 
1,565 
Not specified 
Not reported 35 days 
Urban: 46/-
Rural: 50/-</p>

<p>Netelenbos et al. (2011) [43] Netherlands 8,626 
ALE-RIS-other 
80 
183 days 
43/-</p>

<p>Penning-van Beest et al. 
(2006) [44] </p>

<p>Netherlands 2,124 
ALE-ETI-RIS 
100 
30 days 
43/-</p>

<p>Rabenda et al. (2008) [45] 
Belgium 
54,807 
ALE 
100 
35 days 
40/25 </p>

<p>Sheehy et al. (2009) [67] 
Canada 
32,804 
ALE-RIS 
89-90 
45 days 
Previous fracture: 
Brand ALE/RIS: 61/-
Generic ALE: 45/-
No previous fracture: 
Brand ALE/RIS: 67/-
Generic ALE: 39/-</p>

<p>Siris et al. (2006) [5] 
USA 
35,537 
ALE-RIS 
100 
30 days 
-/20 </p>

<p>Solomon et al. (2005) [46] 
USA 
40,002 
ALE-RIS-other 
96 
120 days 
55/40 </p>

<p>Ström et al. (2012) [47] 
Sweden 
17,647 
ALE 
84-88 
56 days 
Started treatment in 2006: 67/-
Started treatment in 2009: 52/-</p>

<p>van Boven et al. (2013) [61] Netherlands 8,610 
ALE-ETI-IBA-RIS-other 76 
30 days 
59/46 </p>

<p>van den Boogaard et al. 
(2006) [48] </p>

<p>Netherlands 14,760 
ALE-ETI-RIS 
100 
7 days 
44/27 </p>

<p>Vanelli et al. (2009) [49] 
USA 
168,640 
Not specified 
91-94 
30 days 
Treatment-experienced: 45/-
Treatment-naïve: 20/-</p>

<p>Wade et al. (2012) [63] 
USA 
33,558 
ALE-IBA-RIS-other 
94 
90 days 
45/-</p>

<p>Weiss et al. (2007) [56] 
USA 
165,955 
ALE-RIS/IBA 
100 
30 days 
ALE-RIS: 12/-IBA: 10/-</p>

<p>Weycker et al. (2006) [50] 
USA 
12,538 
ALE-RIS-other 
100 
90 days 
Weekly: 57/39 
Daily: 50/33 </p>

<p>Xu et al. (2013) [66] 
USA 
41,461 
ALE-IBA-RIS-other 
92-95 
90 days 
Commercial: 42/-
MAPD: 41/-</p>

<p>Yeaw et al. (2009) [51] 
USA 
10,268 
ALE-ETI-IBA-RIS-other 94 
60 days 
41/23 </p>

<p>Yu et al. (2012) [52] 
Taiwan 
3,589 
ALE-other 
91 
30 days 
51/36 </p>

<p>Ziller et al. (2012) [62] 
Germany 
195,191 
ALE/ETI/IBA/RIS 
86-92 
183 days 
ALE 70 mg: 45/-
ETI: 43/-
IBA 150 mg: 51/ 
RIS 35 mg: 35/-</p>

<p>-, estimates are for all reported treatments; /, estimates are for separate treatments </p>

<p>ALE alendronate; DIN-LINK Doctors' Independent Network Database; ETI etidronate; GPRD General Practice Research Database; IBA oral 
ibandronate; MAPD Medicare Advantage Prescription Drug; MEDIPLUS IMS Disease Analyzer, not specified no reporting for specific oral 
bisphosphonates, other other anti-osteoporosis treatments (e.g., strontium ranelate, raloxifene, zoledronate, and hormone replacement therapy), RIS, 
risedronate </p>

<p>Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>

<p>
BPs which also used the same database [6, 47]. Additionally, 
the majority of women in our study had previously received 
other anti-osteoporosis therapies; this is not surprising given 
that most women are prescribed oral BPs as their first line of 
treatment and subsequently switch to another treatment if they 
do not respond or experience intolerable side effects or dosing 
inconvenience. We estimated 12-and 24-month persistence 
with denosumab therapy to be 83 and 62 %, respectively, 
using a permissible gap of 56 days (8 weeks). The length of 
this gap is somewhat arbitrary and was chosen to be consistent 
with that used in previous studies of persistence using the 
same database [6, 47]. Varying the permissible gap to 30, 
90, and 180 days resulted in estimated persistence rates of 
78, 84, and 87 %, respectively, at 12 months, indicating that 
the estimates were robust. 
Women who had received previous anti-osteoporosis ther-
apies were more likely to persist with denosumab than treat-
ment-naïve women. One possible explanation for this finding 
is that treatment-experienced women are more informed about </p>

<p>their disease and receive more information from their prescrib-
er. Filling a prescription for calcium and/or vitamin D supple-
mentation in the first 6 months after initiating denosumab was 
significantly associated with persistence, with those who filled 
prescriptions having a higher persistence rate than those who 
did not. Similar results were reported by Cotte et al. [33], 
who found that the rate of persistence was higher in women 
taking calcium and vitamin D supplementation than in those 
who did not take such supplements. While the reason for this 
is not clear, a possible explanation is that calcium and vitamin 
D supplementation is an indicator of high risk and, therefore, 
high disease awareness. Finally, women receiving gluco-
corticoids before initiating denosumab had lower rates 
of persistence than those who had no experience of 
glucocorticoids. Similar results have been reported else-
where for other anti-osteoporosis treatments [6, 44, 53], 
and further study is warranted to elucidate the reasons 
for the association between persistence and glucocorticoid 
use. </p>

<p>0 5 10 15 20 25 30 35 40 45 50 55 60 65 70 75 80 85 </p>

<p>Balasubramanian et al. 2013 
Cheng et al. 2013 
Chiu et al. 2013 
Hansen et al. 2013 
van Boven et al. 2013 
McGowan et al. 2013 
McGowan et al. 2013 
Xu et al. 2013 
Xu et al. 2013 
Burden et al. 2012 
Cheen et al. 2012 
Hadji et al. 2012 
Landfeldt et al. 2012 
Li et al. 2012 
Ström et al. 2012 
Ström et al. 2012 
Wade et al. 2012 
Yu et al. 2012 
Ziller et al. 2012 
Ziller et al. 2012 
Ziller et al. 2012 
Ziller et al. 2012 
Netelenbos et al. 2011 
CoƩe et al. 2010 
CoƩe et al. 2010 
Gold et al. 2009 
Gold et al. 2009 
Sheehy 2009 
Sheehy 2009 
Sheehy 2009 
Sheehy 2009 
Vanelli et al. 2009 
Vanelli et al. 2009 
Yeaw et al. 2009 
CoƩe et al. 2008 
CoƩe et al. 2008 
Gallagher et al. 2008 
Jones et al. 2008 
Jones et al. 2008 
Rabenda et al. 2008 
Gold et al. 2007 
Gold et al. 2007 
Weiss et al. 2007 
Weiss et al. 2007 
Brankin et al. 2006 
Brankin et al. 2006 
Brankin et al. 2006 
Brankin et al. 2006 
Brankin et al. 2006 
Brankin et al. 2006 
Cramer et al. 2006 
Cramer et al. 2006 
Cramer et al. 2006 
Cramer et al. 2006 
Cramer et al. 2006 
Cramer et al. 2006 
CurƟs et al. 2006 
CurƟs et al. 2006 
Huybrechts 2006 
Lo et al. 2006 
Penning-van Beest et al. 2006 
van den Boogaard et al. 2006 
Weycker et al. 2006 
Weycker et al. 2006 
Cramer et al. 2005 
Cramer et al. 2005 
Solomon et al. 2005 
McCombs et al. 2004 </p>

<p>Pooled-All 
Pooled-Weekly 
Pooled-Daily 
Pooled-Europe 
Pooled-North America 
Pooled-Other </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Estimates of 12-month 
persistence with oral 
bisphosphonate treatment black 
square individual study, black 
diamond pooled estimate. Data 
are given as percentage (95 % 
confidence interval. Citation 
numbers of the studies detailed in 
this figure are given in Table 3 </p>

<p> 
Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>

<p>Persistence with oral bisphosphonates </p>

<p>The literature review identified 40 retrospective studies 
reporting at least one estimate of 12-or 24-month persistence 
with oral BPs, using varying methodologies. While all studies 
were similar in terms of how persistence was defined, they 
varied in the size of the permissible gap, which is directly 
related to the probability of being defined as non-persistent. 
Other study design heterogeneities concerned the possibility 
of a patient accumulating prescriptions or switching between 
dosages, dosing intervals, types of BP, and differences in 
study population. Less obvious differences, which were not 
systematically captured in our review, related to data quality 
and completeness, under-reporting by family physicians, and 
administrative hurdles. As well as methodological heteroge-
neity, the results are likely to have been influenced by other 
factors, such as types of healthcare organization, approaches 
to patient monitoring, drug reimbursement levels, and popu-
lation disease awareness. 
The pooled estimate from our literature review showed that 
45 % of patients were persistent with oral BP therapy after 
12 months. This relatively low persistence can possibly be 
explained by the asymptomatic nature of osteoporosis [68]  and the complicated administration of oral BPs, whereby the 
tablet is taken under fasting conditions and with the patient 
remaining in an upright position for about an hour to avoid 
oesophageal reflux and oesophagitis, which, although infre-
quent, has been reported [69]. 
The two Swedish studies identified in the literature review 
were based on the Swedish Prescribed Drug Register. They 
estimated 12-month persistence with oral BPs to be 51 and 
67 %, and 24-month persistence to be 25 % [6, 47]. It is worth 
noting that the estimate of 67 % was derived before the intro-
duction of generic alendronate, which is likely to have caused 
a drop in persistence. These estimates for persistence with oral 
BP therapy are lower than the rates observed with denosumab 
using the same database. The permissible gap was identical to 
that in the present study (56 days); the only major difference 
was that patients were allowed to accumulate medicine in the 
studies of oral BPs. </p>

<p>Limitations </p>

<p>While retrospective register studies are based on historical 
prescription data and, hence, avoid the reporting bias that 
can arise in prospective studies, pharmaceuticals administered 
in hospitals are not captured by the Swedish Prescribed Drug 
Register and thus have not been included in our analysis. It is 
estimated that less than 10 % of sold denosumab doses have 
been administered in hospitals. By not including denosumab 
administered in hospitals, we may have not identified women 
who started treatment earlier than was recorded in the database 
and so we may have underestimated the true persistence rate; </p>

<p>however, these women may be atypical and, to a large extent, 
may have been given denosumab for reasons related to cancer 
diagnoses. A register of prescriptions does not provide any 
assurance that the dose was actually taken; therefore, persis-
tence with denosumab may have been overestimated in this 
study. Another limitation of retrospective data is that all vari-
ables of interest may not be available, and it was not possible 
in this database analysis to control for bone mineral density, 
concomitant medicine use, comorbidities, lifestyle factors, 
and socioeconomic variables, all of which may be important 
predictors of persistence [57]. 
The literature review included all identified retrospective 
studies on oral BPs that reported at least one estimate of either 
12-or 24-month persistence, with no other quality require-
ment for inclusion. Some persistence estimates may conse-
quently have been derived from data of insufficient quality 
for a robust analysis. In addition, there was heterogeneity be-
tween the studies. With this in mind, the pooled estimates and 
the comparisons between the studies need to be interpreted 
with some caution. Moreover, the analysis did not consider 
persistence with other anti-osteoporosis drugs such as zoledro-
nic acid and intravenous bisphosphonates. Persistence with 
these treatments, which are administered less frequently than 
oral BPs, has previously been shown to be higher than with 
oral BPs [62]. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Persistence with denosumab in women with PMO in Sweden 
was found to be approximately two-fold higher than pooled 
persistence rates from a meta-analysis of retrospective data on 
oral BPs. Our results from clinical practice are consistent with 
previous reports of persistence with denosumab, in both a 
clinical trial setting and studies of routine practice. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments Editing support was provided by Claire 
Desborough, Amgen (Europe) GmbH, and Oxford PharmaGenesis Ltd, 
Oxford, UK (funded by Amgen). The authors also thank Fereshte 
Ebrahim, National Board of Health and Welfare, Sweden, for sample 
extraction. The study was sponsored by Amgen Inc. </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest LK and OS have previously consulted for com-
panies marketing products for osteoporosis. JL, EP, and MI are employed 
by Amgen Inc. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits any noncommer-
cial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give 
appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to 
the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>

<p>Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>



<p>
 
Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>



<p>Osteoporos Int (2015) 26:2401-2411 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>