<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4157927" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>During pregnancy, diabetes mellitus exerts detrimental effects on the 
development of the fetus, especially the central nervous system. In the 
current study, we evaluated the effects of postnatal treadmill exercise 
on short-term memory in relation with cell proliferation and apoptosis in 
the hippocampus of rat pups born to streptozotocin (STZ)-induced dia-
betic maternal rats. Adult female rats were mated with male rats for 24 
h. Two weeks after mating, the pregnant female rats were divided into 
two groups: control group and STZ injection group. The pregnant rats in 
the STZ injection group were administered 40 mg/kg of STZ intraperito-
neally. After birth, the rat pups were divided into the following four groups: 
control group, control with postnatal exercise group, maternal STZ-in-
jection group, and maternal STZ-injection with postnatal exercise group. 
The rat pups in the postnatal exercise groups were made to run on a </p>

<p>treadmill for 30 min once a day, 5 times per week for 2 weeks beginning 
4 weeks after birth. The rat pups born to diabetic rats were shown to 
have short-term memory impairment with suppressed cell proliferation 
and increased apoptosis in the hippocampal dentate gyrus. Postnatal 
treadmill exercise alleviated short-term memory impairment by increased 
cell proliferation and suppressed apoptosis in the rat pups born to dia-
betic rats. These findings indicate that postnatal treadmill exercise may 
be used as a valuable strategy to ameliorate neurodevelopmental prob-
lems in children born to diabetics. </p>

<p>Kim YH, et al. • Postnatal treadmill exercise alleviates memory impairment in rat pups </p>

<p>in each group were left undisturbed together with their mothers 
for 28 days. The rat pups were then divided into the following 
four groups: control group; control with postnatal exercise group; 
maternal STZ-injection group; and maternal STZ-injection with 
postnatal exercise group (n=12 in each group). </p>

<p>Exercise protocols 
The rat pups in the postnatal exercise groups performed tread-
mill running for 2 weeks starting 4 weeks after birth. Treadmill 
exercising continued for 30 min once a day 5 times per week for 2 
weeks. The workload of the exercise consisted of running at a speed 
of 2 meters/min for the first 5 min, 5 meters/min for the next 5 
min, and then 8 meters/min for the last 20 min, with a zero de-
gree inclination. The rat pups in the non-exercise groups were left 
on the treadmill without running for 30 min for the same dura-
tion of time. All rat pups were injected with 50 mg/kg of 5-bro-
mo-2´-deoxyuridine (BrdU) intraperitoneally 1 h prior to the be-
ginning of each exercise session. </p>

<p>Determination of short-term memory 
Short-term memory was evaluated by assessing the latency of 
the step-down avoidance task, according to the previously describ-
ed method (Heo et al., 2014). The rat pups were trained in the 
step-down avoidance task. In brief, the rat pups were placed on a 
7×25 cm platform at a height of 2.5 cm, then allowed to rest for 
2 min. The platform faced a 42×25 cm grid of parallel 0.1-cm 
caliber stainless steel bars that were spaced 1 cm apart. During the 
training session on the 12 days after starting treadmill exercise 
(postnatal day 40), the animals received a 0.5 mA scramble foot 
shock for 2 sec immediately upon stepping down. The retention 
time was then determined 2 days after the training session (post-
natal day 42). The latency of the step-down avoidance task was 
defined as a rat pup stepping down and placing all four paws on 
the grid. Latencies&gt;300 sec were counted as 300 sec. </p>

<p>Tissue preparation 
Immediately after determination of the retention time, the rat 
pups were anesthetized using Zoletil 50 
® (10 mg/kg, ip; Vibac 
Laboratories, Carros, France), transcardially perfused with 50 mM 
of phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), and fixed with a freshly prepar-
ed solution consisting of 4% paraformaldehyde in 100 mM phos-
phate buffer (PB; pH 7.4). The brains were dissected and post-fixed 
in the same fixative overnight, and transferred to a 30% sucrose 
solution for cryoprotection. Coronal sections, 40-μm thick, were 
made with a freezing microtome (Leica, Nussloch, Germany). </p>

<p>BrdU immunohistochemistry 
In order to detect newly generated cells in the dentate gyrus, 
BrdU-specific immunohistochemistry was performed according 
to a previously described method (Kim et al., 2014). The sections 
were permeabilized by incubation in 0.5% Triton X-100 in PBS 
for 20 min, after which the sections were pre-treated with 50% 
formamide-2X standard saline citrate (SSC) at 65°C for 2 h, dena-
turated in 2 N HCl at 37°C for 30 min, then rinsed twice in 100 
mM sodium borate (pH 8.5). Next, the sections were incubated 
overnight at 4°C with BrdU-specific mouse monoclonal antibody 
(1:600; Roche, Mannheim, Germany). The sections were then wash-
ed 3 times with PBS and incubated for 1 h with a biotinylated 
secondary murine antibody (1:200; Vector Laboratories, Burlin-
game, CA, USA). The sections were then incubated for an addi-
tional h using the VECTASTAIN 
® Elite ABC Kit (1:100; Vector 
Laboratories) according to the manufacturer's instructions. For vi-
sualization, the sections were incubated in 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 
7.6) containing 0.02% 3,3´-diaminobenzidine (DAB), nickel chlo-
ride (40 mg/mL), and 0.03% hydrogen peroxide for 5 min. 
After BrdU-specific staining, counter-staining was performed 
on the same sections using mouse anti-neuronal nucleic (NeuN) 
antibody (1:300; Chemicon International, Temecula, CA, USA). 
The sections were washed 3 times with PBS and incubated for 1 h 
with a biotinylated secondary anti-mouse antibody. For staining, 
the sections were incubated in a reaction mixture consisting of 
0.02% DAB and 0.03% hydrogen peroxide for 5 min. The sec-
tions were finally mounted onto gelatin-coated slides. The slides 
were air-dried overnight at room temperature, and coverslips were 
mounted using Permount 
® (Fisher Scientific, Fair Lawn, NJ, USA). </p>

<p>Caspase-3 immunohistochemistry 
For the visualization of the caspase-3 expression, caspase-3 im-
munohistochemistry was performed as a previously described me-
thod (Choi et al., 2013). In brief, the sections were incubated over-
night with mouse anti-caspase-3 antibody (1:500; Santa Cruz Bio-
technology Inc., Santa Cruz, CA, USA), then for another h with 
the biotinylated secondary murine antibody. The bound secondary 
antibody was then amplified with a Vector Elite ABC kit </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. The 
antibody-biotin-avidin-peroxidase complex was visualized using 
0.02% DAB. The sections were finally mounted onto gelatin-coated 
slides. The slides were air-dried overnight at room temperature, 
and coverslips were mounted using Permount 
® (Fisher Scientific). </p>

<p>Bax immunohistochemistry 
Bax immunohistochemistry was performed according to a pre-</p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.12965/jer.140145 </p>

<p>Kim YH, et al. • Postnatal treadmill exercise alleviates memory impairment in rat pups </p>



<p>viously described method (Yang et al., 2010). The sections were 
drawn from each brain and incubated overnight with mouse an-
ti-Bax antibody (1:500; Santa Cruz Biotechnology Inc.). The sec-
tions were then washed 3 times with PBS and incubated for 1 h 
with a biotinylated secondary murine antibody (1:200; Vector 
Laboratories). The bound secondary antibody was then amplified 
with a Vector Elite ABC kit </p>

<p>® </p>

<p>. The antibody-biotin-avidin-peroxi-
dase complexes were visualized using 0.02% DAB and the sec-
tions were finally mounted onto gelatin-coated slides. The slides 
were air dried overnight at room temperature, and coverslips were 
mounted using Permount 
® (Fisher Scientific). </p>

<p>TUNEL staining 
The TUNEL assay was performed using an in situ Cell Death 
Detection Kit 
® (Roche) according to the manufacturer's protocol 
(Choi et al., 2013). The sections were fixed in ethanol-acetic acid 
(2:1) and rinsed. The sections were then incubated with 100 μg/ 
mL proteinase K, rinsed, incubated in 3% H2O2, permeabilized 
with 0.5% Triton X-100, rinsed again, and incubated in the TU-
NEL reaction mixture. The sections were rinsed and visualized 
using Converter-POD with 0.02% DAB. Mayer's hematoxylin 
(DAKO, Glostrup, Denmark) was used for counter-staining and 
the sections were finally mounted onto gelatin-coated slides. The 
slides were air-dried overnight at room temperature, and covers-
lips were mounted with Permount 
® (Fisher Scientific). </p>

<p>Data analysis 
The numbers of BrdU-positive, caspase-3-positive, Bax-posi-
tive, and TUNEL-positive cells in the hippocampal dentate gyrus 
were counted hemi-laterally using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Image-Pro 
® Plus</rs> computer-as-
sisted image analysis system (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">(Media Cyberbetics Inc.</rs>., Silver Spring, 
MD, USA) attached to a light microscope (Olympus, Tokyo, Ja-
pan). These data are expressed as the number of cells per square 
millimeter (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) of cross-sectional area in each of the selected hip-
pocampal dentate gyri. All values are expressed as the mean±stan-
dard error of the mean (SEM). For comparisons among the groups, 
one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Duncan's post-hoc test 
were performed with a P&lt;0.05 as an indication of statistical sig-
nificance. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Effect of postnatal treadmill exercise on memory in the 
step-down avoidance task </p>

<p>The latency of the step-down avoidance task was 126.25±12.31 </p>

<p>sec in the control group, 156.91±14.05 sec in the control with 
postnatal exercise group, 66.16±15.45 sec in the maternal STZ-in-
jection group, and 115.66±17.68 sec in the maternal STZ-injec-
tion with postnatal exercise group (Fig. 1). These findings indi-
cate that the rat pups born to the diabetic rats had significant me-
mory retardation, and the postnatal treadmill exercise ameliorated 
the memory impairment (P&lt;0.05). In the normal rat pups, the 
postnatal treadmill exercise also enhanced memory function (P&lt; 
0.05). </p>

<p>Effect of postnatal treadmill exercise on the number of 
BrdU-positive cells in the hippocampal dentate gyrus </p>

<p>The number of BrdU-positive cells in the hippocampal dentate 
gyrus was 1,214.09±75.11/mm 
2 in the control group, 1,418.52± 
84.8/mm 
2 in the control with postnatal exercise group, 862.87± 
81.39/mm 
2 in the maternal STZ-injection group, and 1,149.23± 
92.60/mm 
2 in the maternal STZ-injection with postnatal exercise 
group (Fig. 2). The results indicate that the rat pups born to the 
diabetic rats had a significant decrease in cell proliferation in the 
hippocampal dentate gyrus (P&lt;0.05), and the postnatal treadmill 
exercise increased cell proliferation (P&lt;0.05). In normal rat pups, 
postnatal treadmill exercise also enhanced cell proliferation (P&lt;0.05). </p>

<p>Effect of postnatal treadmill exercise on the number of 
caspase-3-positive cells in the hippocampal dentate gyrus </p>

<p>Photomicrographs of the caspase-3-positive cells in the hippo-</p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Latency (sec) </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Effect of postnatal treadmill exercise on latency in the step-down avoid-
ance task of the rat pups. (A) Control group, (B) control with postnatal exercise 
group, (C) maternal streptozotocin (STZ)-injection group, and (D) maternal STZ-in-
jection with postnatal exercise group. Values shown are the mean± SEM. *P&lt; 
0.05 when compared to the control group. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt; 0.05 when compared to the ma-
ternal STZ-injection group. </p>

<p>Kim YH, et al. • Postnatal treadmill exercise alleviates memory impairment in rat pups </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Effect of postnatal treadmill exercise on cell proliferation in the hippo-
campal dentate gyrus of the rat pups. Upper: Photomicrographs of 5-bromo-2'-
deoxyuridine (BrdU)-positive cells in the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus. 
The sections were stained with BrdU (black) to identify newly generated cells 
and with mouse anti-neuronal nuclei antibody to determine the presence of 
neuronal nuclei (NeuN; brown). The scale bar represents 250 μm. Lower: The 
number of BrdU-positive cells in the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus. (A) 
Control group, (B) control with postnatal exercise group, (C) maternal strepto-
zotocin (STZ)-injection group, and (D) maternal STZ-injection with postnatal ex-
ercise group. Values shown are the mean± SEM. *P&lt; 0.05 when compared to 
the control group. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt; 0.05 when compared to the maternal STZ-injection group. </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 
2,000 </p>

<p>1,500 </p>

<p>1,000 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>BrdU-positive cells in the dentate gyrus/mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Effect of postnatal treadmill exercise on caspase-3 expression in the 
hippocampal dentate gyrus of the rat pups. Upper: Photomicrographs showing 
immunostaining for caspase-3 in the dentate gyrus of the hippocampus. The 
scale bar represents 100 μm. Lower: The number of caspase-3-positive cells in 
each group. (A) Control group, (B) control with postnatal exercise group, (C) ma-
ternal streptozotocin (STZ)-injection group, and (D) maternal STZ-injection with 
postnatal exercise group. Values shown are the mean± SEM. *P&lt; 0.05 when 
compared to the control group. </p>

<p># </p>

<p>P&lt; 0.05 when compared to the maternal STZ-in-
jection group. </p>

<p>P &lt; 0.05 
140 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Caspase-3-positive cells in the dentate gyrus/mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>A 
B 
C 
D </p>

<p>* </p>

<p># </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>campal dentate gyrus are presented in Fig. 3. The number of cas-
pase-3-positive cells was 23.65±7.40/mm 
2 in the control group, 
16.91±4.80/mm 
2 in the control with postnatal exercise group, 
112.38±12.82/mm 
2 in the maternal STZ-injection group, and 
74.51±12.12/mm 
2 in the maternal STZ-injection with postnatal 
exercise group (Fig. 3). The results indicate that the rat pups born 
to the diabetic rats had a significant increase in caspase-3 expres-
sion in the hippocampal dentate gyrus (P&lt;0.05), and postnatal 
treadmill exercise inhibited caspase-3 expression (P&lt;0.05). In nor-</p>

<p>mal rat pups, postnatal treadmill exercise exerted no significant 
effect on caspase-3 expression. </p>

<p>Effect of postnatal treadmill exercise on the number of 
Bax-positive cells in the hippocampal dentate gyrus </p>

<p>Photomicrographs of Bax-positive cells in the hippocampal den-
tate gyrus are presented in Fig. 4. The number of Bax-positive 
cells was 22.87±4.22/mm 
2 in the control group, 30.61±6.54/ 
mm 
2 in the control with postnatal exercise group, 125.71±7.61/ 
mm 
2 in the maternal STZ-injection group, and 79.16±8.33/mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>http://dx.doi.org/10.12965/jer.140145 </p>

<p>Kim YH, et al. • Postnatal treadmill exercise alleviates memory impairment in rat pups </p>



<p>in the maternal STZ-injection with postnatal exercise group (Fig. 
4). The results indicate that rat pups born to diabetic rats had a 
significant increase in Bax expression in the hippocampal dentate 
gyrus (P&lt;0.05), and postnatal treadmill exercise inhibited Bax 
expression (P&lt;0.05). In normal rat pups, postnatal treadmill ex-
ercise exerted no significant effect on Bax expression. </p>

<p>Effect of postnatal treadmill exercise on the number of 
TUNEL-positive cells in the hippocampal dentate gyrus </p>

<p>This work was supported by the National Research Foundation 
of Korea Grant funded by the Korean Government (NRF-2009-
352-G00056). </p>



</text></tei>