<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC4497354" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Summary </p>

<p>Several exocrine drainage procedures have been successfully developed to perform 
pancreas transplantation (PT). Retroperitoneal graft placement allows exocrine 
drainage via direct duodenoduodenostomy (DD). This technique provides easy 
access for endoscopic surveillance and biopsy. A total of 241 PT procedures were 
performed in our centre between 2002 and 2012. DD was performed in 125 
patients, and duodenojejunostomy (DJ) in 116 patients. We retrospectively com-
pared our experience with these two types of enteric drainage, focusing on graft 
and patient survivals, as well as postoperative complications. With a mean follow-
up of 59 months, both groups demonstrated comparable patient and graft surviv-
als. 14 (11%) of 125 cases in the DD group and 21 (18%) of 116 cases in the DJ 
group had pancreatic graft loss (P = 0.142). Graft thrombosis [5 (4%) vs. 18 
(16%) P = 0.002], anastomotic insufficiency [2 (1.6%) vs. 8 (7%) P = 0.052] and 
relaparotomy [52 (41%) vs. 56 (48%) P = 0.29] occurred more frequently in the 
DJ group, whereas gastrointestinal bleeding [14 (11%) vs. 4 (3%) P = 0.026] 
occurred more often in the DD group. DD is a feasible and safe technique in PT, 
with no increase in enteric complications. It is equivalent to other established 
techniques and extends the feasibility of anastomotic sites, especially in recipients 
who have undergone a second transplantation. </p>

<p>Pancreas transplantation (PT) has undergone remarkable 
development since its first implementation in 1966. It has 
become an accepted therapeutic option for diabetes mell-
itus owing to improvements in the procedure, progress 
behind organ conservation and intensive care medicine, 
and the increase in the availability of improved immuno-
suppressants [1]. Regarding surgical techniques, the blad-
der drainage method favoured until the mid-1990s has </p>

<p>been increasingly replaced worldwide by enteric drainage 
[2]. Enteric drainage of the pancreas graft is considered 
the current standard method in PT; hence, in 2010, 
more than 90% of the patients with simultaneous pan-
creas-kidney (SPK) transplantation were treated with 
enteric drainage [2]. The most common method of 
enteric drainage is performing an anastomosis between 
the donor duodenum and the recipient jejunum, with 
the pancreas graft in an intraperitoneal position. This 
particular method has been modified in recent years. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>



<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and 
distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. </p>

<p>Transplant International ISSN 0934-0874 </p>

<p>Boggi et al. [3] achieved excellent results by means of a 
side-to-side duodenojejunostomy (DJ) with the Roux-en-
Y method, including pancreas graft placement in a retro-
peritoneal position. If the pancreas is placed in the right 
retrocolic space, a further option is direct side-to-side 
duodenoduodenostomy (DD) [4-8]. Gastric-exocrine 
drainage techniques were also reported [9,10]. 
The advantage of DD is that both the small bowel anas-
tomosis and the pancreatic head of the graft can be accessed 
endoscopically. This facilitates biopsy for diagnosis of rejec-
tion. In addition, in cases of intestinal bleeding at the anas-
tomotic site, an endoscopic intervention for haemostasis 
may follow. Possible disadvantages appear in cases of anas-
tomotic insufficiency or graft loss because subsequent leaks 
at the native duodenal site are more difficult to repair. 
Because of these potential complications, the safety of 
DD has been controversial [5,6,11,12]. However, the few 
published reports on this topic generally involve small case 
sample sizes. Hence, the aim of this study was to review our 
experience with 125 DD procedures performed after PT. 
We focused on the results and complications of DD in 
comparison with DJ performed in a group of patients who 
had undergone PT. 
In this study, we further aimed to describe DD as a surgi-
cal technique and its development over the years with 
respect to cases requiring treatment for duodenal leak after 
pancreas graft failure and removal. Here, we present data 
from 125 cases of DD in PT, the largest reported series of 
this technique to date. </p>

<p>Patients and methods </p>

<p>A total of 241 adult patients underwent PT at our centre 
between September 2002 and September 2012. SPK trans-
plantation was performed in 219 patients; pancreas after 
kidney (PAK) transplantation, in 16 patients; and PT 
alone (PTA), in six patients. All the patients had C-pep-
tide-negative type 1 diabetes. Between 2002 and 2005, DJ 
became the standard procedure in our centre. The first 
DD was then performed in 2005. Between 2005 and 
2007, DD and DJ were applied. Since 2007, DD has been 
the standard procedure in our centre. This produced two 
groups of patients in our cohort as follows: patients with 
enteric drainage by DJ (n = 116) and those with DD 
(n = 125), who were analysed, retrospectively compared 
and evaluated for postoperative results and surgical com-
plications. </p>

<p>Operative technique </p>

<p>Standard back-table preparation is performed before PT. 
The spleen is then removed, and the vessels are ligated, as 
well as the bile duct and gastroduodenal artery. The donor </p>

<p>duodenum is reduced to a length of 8-12 cm and closed 
proximally and distally with a linear stapler. In our 
approach, these staple lines are inverted with seromuscular 
interrupted stitches using absorbable sutures. The mesen-
teric root that was previously transected by staple lines is 
sewed over in a double-row continuous technique (4-0 
polypropylene). Arterial reconstruction of the pancreas 
graft, which includes the superior mesenteric and splenic 
artery, was performed using a donor iliac artery Y-graft. 
Venous extension graft of the portal vein was not necessary 
in any of the cases examined. 
All the PT procedures were performed through a median 
laparotomy for surgical access. In case of planned DJ, the 
pancreas graft is placed intraperitoneally in a head-up posi-
tion. The venous anastomosis is usually performed first and 
is placed to the proximal superior mesenteric vein, or alter-
natively to the inferior caval vein. The arterial graft is ori-
ented caudally through a window made in the ileocecal 
mesentery. The arterial anastomosis is created between the 
Y-graft and the recipient's right common iliac artery (CIA) 
with an end-to-side anastomosis using two half-running 
sutures of 5-0 or 6-0 polypropylene. The DJ is placed at the 
second jejunal loop level by a two-layer, hand-sewn, side-
to-side anastomosis with running sutures using 4-0 polydi-
oxanone. 
In case of a planned DD, the right colon is mobilized 
and a Kocher manoeuvre is performed. Exploration in 
the mesenteric root area of the superior mesenteric vein 
follows to assess the feasibility of anastomosis. In case of 
a small calibre mesenteric vein or distinct mesenteric 
root steatosis, venous anastomosis is created alternatively 
to the inferior caval vein. The pancreas is inserted verti-
cally with the head upright. The arterial anastomosis is 
then created end-to-side between the donor's Y-iliac 
graft and the recipient's right CIA. After sufficient mobi-
lization of the recipient duodenum, both duodena are 
approximated side-to-side, roughly at the level between 
the second and third portions of the recipient's duode-
num. The external suture line is then applied to the 
posterior wall using 4-0 polydioxanone in a running 
suture style. Subsequently, a 2.5-to 3-cm longitudinal 
incision of both duodena is made (Fig. 1a). The inner 
layer is performed with a full-thickness running suture 
using 4-0 nonabsorbable polypropylene in consequence 
of the highly vascularized duodenum. Finally, the second 
external running suture line of the anterior wall is 
applied, again using 4-0 polydioxanone (Fig. 1b). The 
mobilized right colon is returned to its native position, 
thus completely covering the pancreas and making it a 
retroperitoneal organ. We do not routinely perform 
appendectomy. After reperfusion of the pancreatic graft 
and completion of the enteric anastomosis in cases of 
combined pancreas-kidney transplantation, the kidney </p>



<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>

<p>Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation 
Walter et al. </p>

<p>transplantation is performed with arterial and venous 
anastomosis to the recipient's left-sided pelvic vessels. 
Finally, two Jackson-Pratt drains are inserted routinely. 
One drain is placed in a retroperitoneal position beside 
the pancreas graft, ending behind the DD. A second 
drainage is positioned on the kidney graft. 
In this study, all pancreas transplant operations were 
performed by a group of five surgeons. In the transition 
period between the two techniques (2005-2006), the 
leading surgeon selected which anastomosis to apply during 
the operating procedure. Since 2007, the target standard 
has been retroperitoneal placement of the pancreas graft 
with portal venous anastomosis and side-to-side DD. 
Exceptions were made in special situations (e.g. pro-
nounced retroperitoneal adhesions after previous opera-
tions or if the superior mesenteric vein is found unsuitable 
for anastomosis). A gastric tube is intraoperatively inserted 
and maintained for 3-5 postoperative days, depending on 
the clinical course. </p>

<p>Immunosuppression </p>

<p>All the patients underwent quadruple immunosuppres-
sion comprising induction and triple maintenance ther-
apy. Most patients received Thymoglobulin (Sanofi, 
Germany) antibody induction in doses of 1.5 mg/kg of 
body weight used as an intraoperative single-shot ther-
apy. Since 2009, patients receive additional doses of 
Thymoglobulin (1.5 mg/kg of body weight) during the 
course of induction therapy. Additional doses were 
administered on the first and second postoperative days 
in target of a cumulative dose of 4.5 mg/kg of body 
weight according to blood leucocyte/thrombocyte levels 
and clinical course. 
Twenty patients were given interleukin-2 receptor antag-
onists for induction [up until 2007, Daclizumab (Zenapax, 
Roche Pharma AG, Grenzach-Wyhlen, Germany); since 
2007, basiliximab (Simulect, Novartis Pharma AG, Basel, 
Switzerland)]. On the day of the operation, the patients 
were intravenously administered 500 mg of prednisolone 
(Solu-Decortin H, Merck Pharma GmbH, Darmstadt, 
Germany). Patients were administered an additional 
125 mg of intravenous prednisolone on postoperative day 
1. Prednisolone was orally administered as of postoperative 
day 2, starting with a 20-mg dose. The oral dose was 
tapered to a maintenance level of 5 mg daily by week 8. 
In most cases, maintenance immunosuppression com-
prised triple therapy with tacrolimus, mycophenolic acid 
and prednisolone. 
Tacrolimus (Prograf, Astellas Pharma, Munich, Germany) 
therapy was started on the first postoperative day, with a 
dose of 0.15 mg/kg of body weight twice a day. Target 
blood trough levels during the first 2 months were 10-15 
and 8-12 ng/ml subsequently. Mycophenolic acid therapy 
was also started on the first postoperative day, with either 
mycophenolate mofetil (CellCept, Roche Pharma AG) 2 g 
daily or mycophenolate sodium (Myfortic, Novartis 
Pharma AG) 720 mg twice daily. 
All the patients received cytomegalovirus (CMV) pro-
phylaxis with ganciclovir, followed later by valganciclovir 
for at least 3 months. In CMV high-risk constellations 
(D+/RÀ; D+/R+), CMV prophylaxis was performed for 
6 months. Pneumocystis jirovecii prophylaxis was per-
formed with trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole for 3 months 
in total. Perioperative antibiotic prophylaxis was performed 
with ceftriaxone/metronidazole and fluconazole. </p>

<p>Anticoagulant therapy </p>

<p>Before pancreas graft reperfusion, all the patients received 
an intraoperative 1.500-U dose of antithrombin III. Anti-
coagulation with intravenous unfractionated heparin 
(400-600 U/h) was started within 4-6 h after the opera-</p>

<p>Figure 1 Duodenoduodenostomy. Incision of both duodena (a); the 
external running suture line of the anterior wall is applied (b). A, anasto-
mosis; DD, donor duodenum; GB, gallbladder; L, liver; NP, native pan-
creas; P, pancreas graft; RD, recipient duodenum. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>



<p>Walter et al. 
Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation </p>

<p>tion, following patient stabilization. The leading surgeon 
determined the start time of heparin therapy according to 
the intraoperative course. After 12 postoperative hours, if 
the patients were stabilized, partial thromboplastin time 
(PTT)-adapted heparin therapy was performed with a tar-
get PTT between 50 and 60 s. In addition, antithrombin 
substitution targeting &gt;90% is performed. Anticoagulant 
therapy with unfractionated heparin was continued for 
7-10 days and thereafter switched to thrombosis prophy-
laxis with a low molecular weight heparin (enoxaparin or 
fraxiparin). Moreover, all the patients received a platelet 
aggregation inhibition with oral acetylsalicylic acid at 
100 mg starting from day 7. 
Patient medical records, data from electronic labora-
tory recording system and Eurotransplant's donor 
records were gathered to determine donor and recipient 
characteristics. Furthermore, operative details, including 
use of different perfusion solutions, cold ischaemic time 
and total operative time, were reviewed. The primary 
observation target was patient and graft survivals within 
both groups. Secondary observation targets included 
occurrence rates of early postoperative complications 
such as bleeding, anastomotic insufficiency, graft throm-
bosis and necessity of relaparotomies. Occurrence of his-
tologically confirmed rejection episodes was examined in 
both groups as well. </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>For statistical analysis, the chi-square test and Fisher's exact 
test were used to compare categorical variables, and the 
Mann-Whitney U-test was used to compare continuous 
variables. Patient and graft survivals were calculated using 
the Kaplan-Meier method with the log-rank test. A 
P &lt; 0.05 was considered as statistically significant. Analysis 
was performed using <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> (Chicago, IL, USA). 
The local ethics board of the Faculty of Medicine, Ruhr-
University of Bochum, approved the study. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Between September 2002 and September 2012, a total of 
241 PT procedures were performed (219, SPK transplanta-
tions; 16, PAK transplantations; and 6, PTA). 
Donor characteristics are detailed in Table 1. Median 
donor ages, body mass index, sex distribution and cause of 
death were similar in both groups. Regarding the used perfu-
sion solutions, the perfusion rate of the histidine-trypto-
phan-ketoglutarate solution (Custodiol HTK) to the 
pancreata was significantly higher in the DD group. This is 
owing largely to the fact that the HTK solution has been used 
exclusively in Germany since 2007 during visceral removal 
operations. In the DD group, only 8.8% of the removed pan-
creata were perfused with the University of Wisconsin solu-
tion. These organs were harvested outside Germany. 
The recipients' characteristics are detailed in Table 2. 
Recipient age was a little higher in the DD group, although 
this difference was not statistically significant (P = 0.084). 
Recipient body mass index and pretransplant dialysis dura-
tion were significantly higher in the DD group. There was 
no difference in sex distribution. Portal venous drainage 
was performed significantly more frequent in the DD group 
(DD, 64% vs. DJ, 12%; P &lt; 0.001). 
No significant differences were observed between the 
groups regarding cold ischaemic time, both the pancreas 
and kidney grafts, and human leucocyte antigen mismatch. 
The DD group had a significantly longer operative time 
than the DJ group (Table 2). </p>

<p>Patient and graft survivals </p>

<p>The mean follow-up duration was 59.31 AE 37.81 months. 
The length of patient follow-up was shorter in the DD 
group than in the DJ group (33.2 AE 21.1 months vs. 
87.4 AE 31.1 months). 
The total patient survival rates were 96.1%, 93.1% and 
91.2% after 1, 3 and 5 years, respectively. The total pan-</p>

<p>Table 1. Donor characteristics. </p>

<p>Donor characteristics </p>

<p>Duodenoduodenostomy 
(n = 125) </p>

<p>Duodenojejunostomy 
(n = 116) 
P-value </p>

<p>Gender male/female 
69/56 
52/64 
NS 
Age (years) 
35.5 AE 13.2 
35.5 AE 12.6 
NS 
BMI (kg/m²) 
23.5 AE 3.1 
23.4 AE 3.0 
NS 
Preservation solution 
UW 
12 (10) 
95 (82) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>HTK 
113 (90) 
21 (18) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Traumatic cause of death 
34 (27.2%) 
28 (24.1%) 
NS </p>

<p>BMI, body mass index; UW, University of Wisconsin solution; HTK, histidine-tryptophan-ketoglutarate. 
Values are given as mean AE SD or n (% of group). </p>



<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>

<p>Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation 
Walter et al. </p>

<p>creas graft survival rates were 79.7%, 77.4% and 73.2%, 
respectively. The total kidney graft survival rates were 
90.1%, 88.6% and 84.9%, respectively. The cumulative 
patient survival rates (estimated with the Kaplan-Meier 
method) were 95.8%, 94.8% and 91.6%, respectively, in 
the DD group and 96.5%, 92.1% and 90.3%, respec-
tively, in the DJ group, with no statistically significant 
difference (P = 0.624; log-rank test, Fig. 2a). The pan-
creas graft survival rates were 82%, 82% and 75.9%, 
respectively, in the patients with DD and 77.6%, 73.1% 
and 69.5% in the patients with DJ (P = 0.20; log-rank 
test, Fig. 2b). Accordingly, no statistically significant dif-
ference was observed in kidney graft survival after 1, 3 
and 5 years (P = 0.924). </p>

<p>Surgical complications </p>

<p>In total, two anastomotic insufficiencies occurred in the 
DD group; both patients required reoperation. One patient </p>

<p>underwent a new DD placement; the other patient merely 
underwent oversewing of a small leak. No further corrective 
surgery was necessary in these two patients. In total, eight 
anastomotic insufficiencies were observed in the DJ group, 
each requiring surgical treatment. 
Two patients in the DJ group developed a small bowel 
obstruction from an internal hernia in the area of the pan-
creatic graft that required surgical treatment. Complica-
tions of gastrointestinal bleeding occurred more frequently 
in the DD group than in the DJ group. In total, 14 DD 
patients developed bleeding complications in the area of 
the enteric anastomosis. Of these 14 patients, seven could 
be treated with endoscopic haemostasis. Four patients 
required surgical correction following inefficient endo-
scopic haemostasis. Conservative therapy was successful in 
three cases (blood transfusion, reduction in anticoagulant 
therapy and increase in PPI medication, respectively). 
Four patients in the DJ group developed anastomotic 
bleeding, two of which underwent corrective surgical pro-</p>

<p>Table 2. Recipient characteristics. </p>

<p>Recipient characteristics </p>

<p>Duodenoduodenostomy 
(n = 125) </p>

<p>Duodenojejunostomy 
(n = 116) 
P-value </p>

<p>Gender (male/female) 
83/42 
66/50 
NS 
Age (years) 
45.5 AE 7.7 
43.7 AE 8.4 
NS 
BMI (kg/m²) 
25.1 AE 3.8 
23.5 AE 2.9 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>CMV 
RÀ/D+ 
36 (28.8) 
34 (29.3) 
NS 
R+/D+ 
29 (23.2) 
26 (22.4) 
NS 
RÀ/DÀ 
31 (24.8) 
18 (15.5) 
NS 
R+/DÀ 
29 (23.2) 
38 (32.8) 
NS 
Duration of diabetes mellitus (years) 
31 AE 8.8 
29.9 AE 8.9 
NS 
Duration of dialysis (months) 
37.5 AE 24.1 
(n = 110) </p>

<p>32.1 AE 28.8 
(n = 91) </p>

<p>&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Venous drainage 
Systemic venous 
45 (36) 
102 (88) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Portal venous 
80 (64) 
14 (12) 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Cold ischaemic time (min) 
Pancreas 
683.2 AE 164.5 
688.3 AE 171.8 
NS 
Kidney 
784.9 AE 198.6 
748.5 AE 183.7 
NS 
HLA mismatch 
AB 
2.9 AE 0.9 
3.0 AE 0.9 
NS 
DR 
1.6 AE 0.6 
1.5 AE 0.6 
NS 
ATG 
113 (90.4) 
104 (89.7) 
NS 
IL-2 RA 
12 (9.6) 
8 (6.9) 
NS 
Tacrolimus 
122 (97.6) 
113 (97.4) 
NS 
Type of transplantation 
SPK 
115 (92.0) 
104 (89.7) 
NS 
PTA 
3 (2.4) 
3 (2.6) 
NS 
PAK 
7 (5.6) 
9 (7.7) 
NS 
Operative time (min) 
341.9 AE 81.4 
270.2 AE 76.6 
&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>BMI, body mass index; SPK, simultaneous pancreas-kidney transplantation; PAK, pancreas after kidney transplantation; PTA, pancreas transplantation 
alone; CMV, cytomegalovirus; R, recipient; D, donor; IL2-RA, interleukin 2-receptor antibody; ATG, antithymocyte globulin. 
Values are given as mean AE SD or n (% of group). </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>



<p>Walter et al. 
Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation </p>

<p>cedures. Pancreatic graft removal was necessary for 14 
cases (11.2%) in the DD group and 21 cases (18.1%) in 
the DJ group. This difference was not statistically signifi-
cant (P = 0.142). The main cause of early graft loss was 
graft thrombosis (23/241, 9.5%), with five cases in the 
DD group and 18 cases in the DJ group (P = 0.002). 
When comparing portal venous (pv) versus systemic </p>

<p>venous (sv) drainage within the DD group, no differences 
were found regarding pancreatic graft loss (pv 10% vs. sv 
13.3%; P = 0.568) and relaparotomy rate (pv 41.2% vs. 
sv 42.2%; P = 0.915). 
The hole in the recipient duodenum resulting from 
graft pancreatectomy was primarily treated in all the cases 
with a transverse, double-layer, interrupted suture using 
polydioxanone (3-0 or 4-0). Ten of the 14 patients had 
no complications during the postoperative course. Follow-
ing pancreatectomy and oversewing the duodenum, three 
patients developed insufficiencies of the duodenal suture 
with consecutive duodenal leak. One female patient was 
treated with a Roux-en-Y-constructed DJ, forming a side-
to-side anastomosis. In a second patient, the duodenal 
leak was treated with a side-to-side DJ. In a third patient, 
we were able to treat the duodenal leak conservatively 
while keeping the intra-abdominal drain in place for 
longer. 
Pancreatectomy was performed in another patient who 
developed abdominal sepsis and mycotic erosion bleeding 
in the area of the pancreas graft. The patient showed undis-
turbed healing of the duodenal oversewing. However, the 
patient developed a complication involving a perforated 
peptic postpyloric duodenal ulcer. This complication 
required a distal gastric resection, including end-to-side 
gastrojejunostomy with blind closure of the proximal duo-
denum. The patient developed septic multiple organ failure 
and died 61 days after SPK transplantation after duodenal 
stump insufficiency and abdominal sepsis with evidence of 
a mycotic infection caused by Candida glabrata. The differ-
ent complications caused by the two enteric drainage tech-
niques are shown in Table 3. 
Relaparotomy rates during the first three postoperative 
months (DD, 41.6% vs. DJ, 48.2%; P = 0.29) and inpa-
tient stay [DD, 42.1 days (range, 14-116 days) vs. DJ, 
42.3 days (range, 14-170 days); P = 0.784] were compa-
rable in both groups. In the first post-transplant year, 
142/241 (58.9%) inpatients were admitted again. No dif-
ferences arose between the DD and the DJ groups (DD: 
58.4% vs. DJ: 59.4%). The average number of inpatient 
admissions totalled 0.8 AE 1.02 in the DD group in the 
first year and 1.0 AE 1.09 in the DJ group, without a sta-
tistically significant difference. The most common three 
reasons for admission in both groups were urinary tract 
infections (DD: 29.6% vs. DJ: 21.5%), gastroenteritis 
(DD: 16% vs. DJ: 31.8%) and kidney transplant dysfunc-
tion (DD: 12% vs. DJ: 16.3%). During the first year, 5 
(4%) and, respectively, 7 (6%) pneumonias were observed 
in the DD and DJ groups. The CMV infection rate was 
comparable in both groups (DD: 8%; DJ: 11.2%, 
P = 0.511). 
After 1 year, the histologically confirmed overall rejec-
tion rate was 29.8%. These cases were mostly kidney biop-</p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Figure 2 Kaplan-Meier curves representing patient (a) and pancreas 
graft survival (b) by enteric drainage technique. There was no significant 
difference between the DD and DJ groups [log-rank test, P = 0.624 (a); 
P = 0.202 (b)]. DD, duodenoduodenostomy; DJ, duodenojejunostomy. </p>



<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>

<p>Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation 
Walter et al. </p>

<p>sies from the patients with combined pancreas-kidney 
transplantations (96%). Four patients in the DD group 
underwent trouble-free pancreatic graft endoscopic biop-
sies using a 21-gauge biopsy needle. The 1-year rejection 
rate was 28.8% in the DD group and 31% in the DJ group 
(P = 0.705). Of 36 cases in the DD group, 26 were consid-
ered borderline or Banff IA rejections. The 1-year rejection 
rate was 26.6% in patients with systemic venous drainage 
and 30.0% in patients with portal venous drainage within 
the DD group (P = 0.837). Of 36 rejections in the DJ 
group, 20 were borderline or Banff IA. 
Serum creatinine, HbA1c and fasting glucose levels were 
measured and compared after 1 month, 6 months, 1 year 
and 2 years. With regard to pancreatic and kidney graft 
functions, no difference was found between both groups. 
The functional parameters for both groups are shown in 
Table 4. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Safety management of exocrine pancreatic secretions has 
received the most attention in PT, as local release of acti-
vated pancreatic enzymes, similar to acute pancreatitis, can 
result in serious local tissue damage. The drainage of exo-
crine secretions into the urinary bladder dominated the 
1980s and 1990s. This technique allows immunological 
monitoring of the graft through the determination of pan-</p>

<p>creatic enzymes in the urine or via cystoscopic biopsy 
[13,14]. In most centres today, bladder drainage is no 
longer used because of significant urological problems, 
reflux pancreatitis and potentially considerable bicarbon-
ate loss. Bladder drainage has been increasingly replaced 
by enteric drainage; the proportion of patients undergo-
ing PT with enteric drainage currently accounts for 
approximately 91% in the SPK transplantation group, 
89% in the PAK transplantation group and 85% in the 
PTA group as per transplantation procedure [1]. Enteric 
drainage PT is usually performed as proximal DJ with or 
without Roux-en-Y limb [11]. Furthermore, exocrine 
drainage into the distal ileum [15] and gastric-exocrine 
drainage [9,10] were reported. DD emerges as another 
option for enteric drainage if the pancreas graft is placed 
in the right retroperitoneal space. DD in PT has already 
been described in single case reports and case series [4-
8], all of them having in common a small number of 
patients. 
The objective of this study was to describe our experi-
ence with 125 DD cases in PT to assess the comparative 
advantages or disadvantages between this technique and 
DJ. The study focused on cases in which pancreatic graft 
loss resulted in a duodenal leak that required treatment. 
This complication requires sophisticated surgical treatment 
and is the focal point of arguments from opponents of DD, 
thus spurring a controversy in the field. </p>

<p>Table 3. Complications by drainage technique. </p>

<p>Duodenoduodenostomy 
(n = 125) </p>

<p>Duodenojejunostomy 
(n = 116) 
P-value </p>

<p>Pancreas graft loss 
14 (11) 
21 (18) 
NS 
Pancreas graft thrombosis 
5 (4) 
18 (16) 
P = 0.002 </p>

<p>Anastomotic insufficiency 
2 (1.6) 
8 (7) 
P = 0.052 </p>

<p>GI anastomotic bleeding 
14 (11) 
4 (3) 
P = 0.026 </p>

<p>Blood transfusion 
84 (67) 
76 (66) 
NS 
Number of red cell 
concentrates/patient </p>

<p>4.28 AE 6.6 
4.0 AE 5.5 
NS </p>

<p>Obstruction 
0 (0) 
2 (1.7) 
NS 
Overall relaparotomy rate 
52 (41) 
56 (48) 
NS 
Due to bleeding, evacuation 
of haematoma </p>

<p>18 (14) 
11 (9) 
NS </p>

<p>Due to graft pancreatitis, 
peripancreatic fluid, intra-
abdominal abscess, 
necrosectomy </p>

<p>17 (13) 
13 (11) 
NS </p>

<p>Pancreas graft thrombosis 
5 (4) 
18 (16) 
P = 0.002 </p>

<p>Anastomotic insufficiency 
2 (1.6) 
8 (6.9) 
P = 0.052 </p>

<p>Graft pancreatectomy 
4 (3.2) 
1 (0.8) 
NS 
Graft nephrectomy 
2 (1.6) 
1 (0.8) 
NS 
Fascial wound dehiscence 
repair </p>

<p>4 (3.2) 
4 (3.4) 
NS </p>

<p>Values are given as mean AE SD or n (% of group). </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>



<p>Walter et al. 
Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation </p>

<p>Compared with the results from high-volume centres in 
the United States [16,17] and summarized data from the 
International Pancreas Transplant Registry [2], similarly 
good 1-and 5-year patient and graft survival rates could 
be achieved. In comparison with the US data, the compli-
cation rate (graft thrombosis, bleeding, rejection and rela-
parotomy rates) was slightly higher in this study. 
However, it must be noted that our recipient and donor 
groups had a significantly older age and that the donors 
exhibited a high proportion of death by cerebrovascular 
causes (&gt;70%). In our opinion, the main reason for the 
relatively high rejection rate is a result of including the 
borderline rejections. For the overall collective of the 
study, there are at least 24 cases; that means exactly one-
third of all reported rejections. If the borderline rejections 
are not included and rejection is defined as starting from 
stage BANFF I, as many authors do, there is a 1-year rejec-
tion rate of 18.4% (23/125) for the DD group and 21.5% 
(25/116) for the DJ group, respectively. Complications 
such as graft pancreatitis, intra-abdominal infections and 
required relaparotomies, which occurred more often in 
our patients, frequently necessitate a reduction in immu-
nosuppressive therapy. It is also conceivable that the 
increased rejection rate could be due to this fact. After 
having analysed our data in 2009, we already noticed the 
increased rejection rates. For this reason and based on our 
positive experience with a repeated thymoglobulin dose in 
kidney transplantation within the Eurotransplant Senior 
Program, we extended the induction therapy in SPK from 
a single-shot therapy with 1.5 mg/kg/BW to two further 
postoperative administrations. The hospital stay of our 
patients is relatively long in relation to international stan-
dards, especially in the US. In our institution, we still have 
the opportunity to implement part of the rehabilitation 
during patients' initial admission, which results in a 
longer hospitalization period. The inpatients' stay is 
reported as a mean of 42 days in both groups. However, 
this value is distinctly inflated by 'long-stay patients' with 
a complicated recovery period. The median inpatient stay 
is 33 days in the DD group and 34 days in the DJ group. 
This value of inpatient hospitalization following pancreas 
transplantation can be found in most of the German 
transplantation centres. 
Inspired by the results from Boggi et al. [3], applying 
retroperitoneal placement of pancreas grafts, the first DD 
cases in our centre were performed in patients with 
retransplantations or previous abdominal operations pre-
senting distinct interenteric adhesion. Owing to the close 
anatomical location of both duodena, placement of a DD 
was the easiest and safest solution. Increasing experience 
with this technique and comparative results with DJ have 
established this surgical method as standard practice in 
our centre since 2007. </p>

<p>Table 4. Graft function by drainage technique. </p>

<p>Pre-Transplant </p>

<p>P-value 
After 1 month </p>

<p>P-value 
After 6 months </p>

<p>P-value 
After 1 year </p>

<p>P-value 
After 2 years </p>

<p>P-value </p>

<p>DD </p>

<p>DJ </p>

<p>DD </p>

<p>DJ </p>

<p>DD </p>

<p>DJ </p>

<p>DD </p>

<p>DJ </p>

<p>DD </p>

<p>DJ </p>

<p>Serum 
creatinine </p>

<p>mg/dl </p>

<p>5.8 
AE 2.5 
(104) </p>

<p>5.2 
AE 2.4 
(67) </p>

<p>0.168 </p>

<p>1.8 
AE 1.1 
(111) </p>

<p>1.6 
AE 1.1 
(103) </p>

<p>0.366 </p>

<p>1.5 
AE 0.6 
(99) </p>

<p>1.5 
AE 0.9 
(97) </p>

<p>0.809 </p>

<p>1.4 
AE 0.5 
(71) </p>

<p>1.3 
AE 0.6 
(93) </p>

<p>0.333 </p>

<p>1.5 
AE 0.7 
(48) </p>

<p>1.5 
AE 1.0 
(91) </p>

<p>0.853 </p>

<p>HbA1c% </p>

<p>7.7 
AE 1.6 
(87) </p>

<p>7.6 
AE 1.3 
(36) </p>

<p>0.894 </p>

<p>6.4 
AE 0.9 
(95) </p>

<p>6.2 
AE 0.8 
(70) </p>

<p>0.870 </p>

<p>5.9 
AE 0.8 
(89) </p>

<p>5.8 
AE 1.1 
(83) </p>

<p>0.938 </p>

<p>5.9 
AE 0.9 
(75) </p>

<p>5.5 
AE 0.7 
(90) </p>

<p>0.109 </p>

<p>6.0 
AE 1.0 
(44) </p>

<p>5.6 
AE 1.0 
(82) </p>

<p>0.186 </p>

<p>Fasting 
glucose 
level mg/dl </p>

<p>n. a. </p>

<p>n. a. </p>

<p>n. a. </p>

<p>112.8 
AE 42.5 
(109) </p>

<p>112 
AE 45.5 
(101) </p>

<p>0.527 </p>

<p>107.7 
AE 42.1 
(88) </p>

<p>104.0 
AE 38 
(97) </p>

<p>0.848 </p>

<p>105.5 
AE 31.2 
(71) </p>

<p>102.6 
AE 32.1 
(92) </p>

<p>0.568 </p>

<p>104.6 
AE 32.2 
(45) </p>

<p>97.0 
AE 12.02 
(79) </p>

<p>0.965 </p>

<p>DD, duodenoduodenostomy; DJ, duodenojejunostomy. 
Values are given as mean 
AE SD (n, number of patients). </p>



<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>

<p>Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation 
Walter et al. </p>

<p>The 1 (DD, 82% vs. DJ, 78%)-and 5-year pancreas graft 
survival rates (DD, 82% vs. DJ, 73%) were slightly better in 
the DD group, although this difference was not statistically 
significant (log-rank test, P = 0.202). This is interesting 
because the patients in the DD group were on average 
older, showed longer diabetes and dialysis durations and 
had higher BMI compared with the DJ group. In addition, 
most of their organs were perfused with HTK Custodiol. 
All these factors are well known for their negative impact 
on the results of PT [18-23]. 
Removal of the pancreas graft was necessary in 14 
(11.2%) of the 125 cases in the DD group compared with 
21 of the 116 graft removals (18.1%) in the DJ group 
(P = 0.129). The main cause for early graft loss was graft 
thrombosis (23/241, 9.5%) with five cases (4%) in the DD 
group and 18 cases (15.5%) in the DJ group. Pancreas graft 
thrombosis occurred significantly less in the DD group 
(P = 0.002). As suggested by other authors, a potential 
advantage of the DD anastomosis is the avoidance of tor-
sion or twisting of the allograft vessels [5]. 
The location of the graft in the retroperitoneum and 
anastomosis to the relatively fixed recipient duodenum 
may reduce graft mobility, which in turn may play a role in 
minimizing torsion on vascular anastomoses. In this 
regard, other investigators have noted a decrease in vascular 
thrombosis rate after placement of the pancreas in an 
upright, right-sided retroperitoneal position [3]. The 
higher number of portal venous anastomoses in the DD 
group offers another potential explanation for the low 
thrombosis rate in the DD group. Due to the high-flow and 
low-pressure systems, some authors discuss the portal 
venous drainage to be advantageous in the prevention of 
graft thromboses [3]. 
Depending on the thickness of the retroperitoneal space, 
the intraperitoneal positioning of the pancreas graft often 
involves a longer arterial Y-graft, whereas the retroperito-
neal technique allows shortening the Y-graft to a minimum. 
Kinking or twisting of the graft vessels is thus greatly 
reduced. In this respect, our data confirm the previous 
results obtained by Boggi et al. [3]. 
As a rare complication, anastomotic insufficiency was 
identified in a total of 10 (4.1%) of 241 cases, occurring 
more frequently in the DJ group (n = 8). Anastomotic 
insufficiency occurred in only two cases in the DD 
group. Small bowel obstruction caused by internal hernia 
in the region of the pancreas graft and requiring surgery 
occurred only in the DJ group (n = 2). The DD group 
showed an increased incidence of gastrointestinal anasto-
motic bleeding. This trend was already noted by Gun-
asekaran et al. [5] who found that bleeding 
complications correlated with the application of circular 
staplers. In our approach, where all DD procedures were 
hand-sewn, the cause of this complication seems to have </p>

<p>likely been the abundant blood vessel supply to the duo-
denum. 
As mentioned earlier, cases of graft loss resulting in a 
duodenal leak requiring treatment is the most frequently 
discussed problem in DD. In our experience, severe sur-
gical problems resulting from this issue are rare. After 
the 14 pancreas graft losses in the DD group, all duode-
nal leaks were primarily closed transversely, in two rows. 
The Gambee technique is a well-established method that 
can be used for at least the inner suture line. Three of 
these 14 patients showed insufficiency of the duodenal 
suture. Two of these patients had to undergo reoperation. 
In one case, the placement of Roux-en-Y DJ was 
performed, and in the other case, a side-to-side DJ was 
placed. In one case, with only slight biliary secretion, 
conservative therapy with keeping an abdominal drain in 
use for longer proved to be successful. 
Therefore, we agree with other authors [5] that the longi-
tudinal duodenotomy should not be longer than 2.5-3 cm 
to allow for a tension-free, transverse duodenal closure in 
case of graft removal. Otherwise, anastomosis must not be 
created too tightly to prevent stasis of secretions, and food 
or blood coagulum in the duodenal segment of the pan-
creas graft. Anastomosis should always be placed widely to 
allow easy passage by a standard gastroscope. 
In recent years, histological examination of graft biopsies 
for rejection diagnostics has increasingly grown in impor-
tance. A biopsy is often indispensable, especially within the 
context of the increasing number of retransplantations in 
immunized patients, in PAK transplantation, or in isolated 
PT. However, isolated pancreas rejections not involving a 
kidney graft were also discussed in SPK transplantation 
[24]. These cases were most likely clinically inapparent 
rejections without any deterioration in renal function [25]. 
Although percutaneous ultrasound-or CT-guided pancre-</p>

<p>Figure 3 Endoscopic view of the anastomosis between both duodena. 
A, anastomosis; DD, donor duodenum; DP, donor papilla vateri; ND, 
native duodenum. </p>

<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>



<p>Walter et al. 
Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation </p>

<p>atic graft biopsies are now considered safer, there are still 
risks for bowel perforation, bleeding and pancreatic fistula 
formation. With the implementation of a retroperitoneal 
technique as described by Boggi et al. [3], these complica-
tions can be significantly prevented, as the pancreas graft is 
fixed and compartmentalized in the right retroperitoneal 
space. In our opinion, another essential advantage of 
the DD is the improved endoscopic accessibility of the 
pancreas graft for rejection diagnostics. In addition to the 
visual inspection of duodenal mucosa, there is opportu-
nity for mucosal biopsy and ultrasound-guided pancreas 
biopsy (Fig. 3). Occurrence of bleeding can be visually 
checked immediately. Potential pancreatic fistula formation 
generally occurs with little consequence as the fistula 
intraluminally drains on its own into the duodenum. Other 
research groups also report successful therapy of pancreatic 
duct leaks in the pancreas graft by endoscopic papillotomy 
and stent insertion [5]. 
Endoscopic protocols are not kept at our centre. Endoso-
nographically controlled biopsy of the pancreas graft with a 
21-G needle was performed in four patients. In all the cases, 
sufficient tissue for histological examination was attainable. 
No complications were observed in any of the four 
patients. 
According to our years of experience with more than 125 
DD procedures in PT, we consider DD placement to be a 
simple and safe technique. Gastrointestinal complication 
rates were generally low (with exception of anastomotic 
bleeding). Our patient population even exhibited fewer 
complications with DD than with DJ. We could not con-
firm a special risk to patients, particularly those with graft 
loss. In fact, this technique produced advantages such as 
easy endoscopic access to the graft. With the introduction 
of this technique, occurrence of graft thrombosis could be 
significantly prevented. Nevertheless, potential benefits of 
this technique must be interpreted restrictively at the 
moment, as the present pool of 'DD drainage procedures' 
is still small and other enteric drainage techniques demon-
strate similarly excellent results. 
For patients undergoing pancreatic retransplantation 
procedures or patients exhibiting pronounced intestinal 
adhesions after previous abdominal operations, the DD 
represents a safe, alternative option for anastomosis com-
pared with the already existing enteric exocrine drainage 
techniques. </p>

<p>Authorship </p>

<p>MW: collected and analysed the data and wrote the paper. 
MJ, SK, PK, SM, TK and AW: analysed the data and edited 
the paper. RV: analysed the results and edited the paper. 
PS: designed the study, collected and analysed data, and 
wrote the paper. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>The study was performed without any financial support. </p>





<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>

<p>Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation 
Walter et al. </p>



<p>© 2014 The Authors. Transplant International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Steunstichting ESOT 27 (2014) 805-815 </p>



<p>Walter et al. 
Duodenoduodenostomy in pancreas transplantation </p>

</text></tei>